<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2935446" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Motivation: Intrinsically disordered proteins play a crucial role 
in numerous regulatory processes. Their abundance and ubiquity 
combined with a relatively low quantity of their annotations motivate 
research toward the development of computational models that 
predict disordered regions from protein sequences. Although the 
prediction quality of these methods continues to rise, novel and 
improved predictors are urgently needed. 
Results: We propose a novel method, named MFDp (Multilayered 
Fusion-based Disorder predictor), that aims to improve over 
the current disorder predictors. MFDp is as an ensemble of 
3 Support Vector Machines specialized for the prediction of 
short, long and generic disordered regions. It combines three 
complementary disorder predictors, sequence, sequence profiles, 
predicted secondary structure, solvent accessibility, backbone 
dihedral torsion angles, residue flexibility and B-factors. Our method 
utilizes a custom-designed set of features that are based on raw 
predictions and aggregated raw values and recognizes various types 
of disorder. The MFDp is compared at the residue level on two 
datasets against eight recent disorder predictors and top-performing 
methods from the most recent CASP8 experiment. In spite of 
using training chains with ≤25% similarity to the test sequences, 
our method consistently and significantly outperforms the other 
methods based on the MCC index. The MFDp outperforms modern 
disorder predictors for the binary disorder assignment and provides 
competitive real-valued predictions. The MFDp's outputs are also 
shown to outperform the other methods in the identification of 
proteins with long disordered regions. 
The intrinsically disordered proteins (IDPs), also referred to 
as unstructured proteins, lack stable tertiary structure under 
physiological conditions in vitro. The IDPs play a crucial 
role in transcriptional regulation, translation and cellular signal 
transduction (Dunker et al., 2008). Their prevalence was also 
implicated in various human disorders including the neuro-
degenerative diseases such as Huntington, Parkinson's and 
Alzheimer's disease (Raychaudhuri et al., 2009). However, the 
functional role of IDPs is not as well understood when compared 
with the well-packed proteins. Importantly, the annotations of the 
disorder lag behind the rapidly accumulating number of known </p>

<p> *  To whom correspondence should be addressed. </p>

<p>protein chains. To compare, the curated DisProt database (Sickmeier  et al., 2007) includes little over 500 chains, the PDB database 
(Berman et al., 2000) that allows finding unstructured segments in 
the solved tertiary structures (which are assumed to be equivalent to 
disordered segments) includes ∼58 000 proteins, while the overall 
number of known protein chains is &gt;9 million. The disorder 
is frequently observed in regions with low-sequence complexity 
and with low content of hydrophobic amino acids, which would 
often form a core of a folded globular protein (Dyson and  Wright, 2005; Uversky et al., 2000). These and other sequence 
characteristics can be used to differentiate between disordered and 
ordered regions, which in turn implies that disorder is predictable 
from the sequence. The past decade observed development of a 
number of computational models for the prediction of the disordered 
regions. These methods allow for high-throughput annotations 
of protein chains which provide a viable solution to close the 
annotation gap. These predictors could be categorized into four 
groups: (i) methods based on relative propensity of amino acids 
to form disorder/ordered regions which include GlobPlot (Linding  et al., 2003), IUPred (Dosztányi et al., 2005), FoldIndex (Prilusky  et al., 2005) and Ucon (Schlessinger et al., 2007a); (ii) methods 
built utilizing machine-learning classifiers, such as DISpro (Hecker  et al., 2008), DISOPRED (Jones and Ward, 2003) DISOPRED2 
(Ward et al., 2004), PrDOS (Ishida and Kinoshita, 2007), POODLE-
S (Shimizu et al., 2007a), <rs id="software-33" type="software">POODLE-L</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-33" type="creator">Hirose et al</rs>., 2007), 
POODLE-W (Shimizu et al., 2007b), Spritz (Vullo et al., 2006), 
DisPSSMP (Su et al., 2006), DisPSSMP2 (Su et al., 2007), IUP 
(Yang and Yang, 2006), NORSnet (Schlessinger et al., 2007b) and 
OnD-CRFs (Wang and Sauer, 2008); (iii) methods based on a meta-
approach which combines predictions from multiple base predictors 
including recent MD (Schlessinger et al., 2009), metaPrDOS (Ishida  and Kinoshita, 2008), GS-metaDisorder (J.Bujnicki, unpublished 
data) and MULTICOM (Cheng et al., 2005); and (iv) methods 
based on analysis of predicted 3D structural models, such as 
<rs id="software-39" type="software">DISOclust</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-39" type="creator">McGuffin</rs>, 2008). Since 2002, the sequence-based 
disorder predictors are biannually assessed and compared during 
the critical assessment of structure prediction (CASP) experiments. 
Although the prediction quality continues to rise, as shown in the 
most recent CASP8 (Noivirt-Brik et al., 2009), improved prediction 
methods are still urgently needed (Schlessinger et al., 2009). 
We propose a novel architecture, named MFDp (Multilayered 
Fusion-based Disorder predictor), that aims to improve the overall 
quality of the prediction when compared with modern methods. We 
analyze and quantify improvements provided by MFDp for a generic 
prediction of all disordered segments and also for the prediction of 
long-disordered segments. The latter is motivated by recent results 
that show that long-disordered regions are useful for target selection 
for structure determination of integral membrane protein (Punta </p>

<p>© The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>M.J.Mizianty et al. </p>

<p>Table 1. List of input information sources used by disorder predictors based on machine learning classifiers (sorted by the year of publication) </p>

<p>Prediction method 
Input information 
Meta 
predictor </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>AA 
type </p>

<p>AA 
propensity </p>

<p>AA 
position </p>

<p>PSSM 
profile </p>

<p>SS 
prediction </p>

<p>Solvent accessi-
bility prediction </p>

<p>Terminus 
indicator </p>

<p>GS-metaDisorder 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
Unpublished data 
MD 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
Schlessinger et al. (2009) 
metaPrDOS 
X 
Ishida and Kinoshita (2008) 
DISpro 
X 
X 
X 
Hecker et al. (2008) 
OnD-CRF 
X 
X 
Wang and Sauer (2008) 
POODLE-S 
X 
X 
Shimizu et al. (2007a) 
POODLE-L 
X 
X 
Hirose et al. (2007) 
POODLE-W 
X 
X 
Shimizu et al. (2007b) 
DisPSSMP2 
X 
X 
Su et al. (2007) 
PrDOS 
X 
X 
Ishida and Kinoshita (2007) 
MULTICOM-CMFR 
X 
X 
X 
X 
Cheng et al. (2005) 
DISOPRED2 
X 
X 
Ward et al. (2004) </p>

<p>et al., 2009), they are implicated in protein-protein recognition 
(Tompa et al., 2009) and were found helpful in prediction of protein 
crystallization propensity (Slabinski et al., 2007). 
The MFDp is based on four novel ideas. First, motivated by 
the observation that combining orthogonal predictors is helpful 
(Oldfield et al., 2005; Schlessinger et al., 2009), we fuse four 
complementary disorder predictors. This is in contrast to earlier 
ensemble-based solutions that combined predictors selected in an ad 
hoc manner. When compared to the recently proposed orthogonal 
ensemble-based MD predictor (Schlessinger et al., 2009), we 
consider different aspects to judge dissimilarity. MD combines four 
predictors that tackle different 'types' of disorder, while we combine 
three methods that differ in their approach to perform predictions. 
We use a machine learning-based predictor <rs type="software">DISOPRED2</rs>, residue 
propensity-based <rs type="software">IUPred</rs> and a recent <rs type="software">DISOclust</rs> that is based on 
tertiary structure predictions (i.e. prediction based on the sequence-
derived tertiary structure). The usage of the 3D-based predictor is 
the novel aspect of our ensemble. We select <rs id="software-48" type="software">DISOPRED2</rs> since 
it was demonstrated to provide high-quality predictions and to be 
orthogonal to other machine learning-based methods (<rs corresp="#software-48" type="creator">Schlessinger</rs>  et al., 2009). The <rs type="software">IUPred</rs> provides two models that specialize 
in prediction of long-and short-disordered regions, respectively. 
The DISOclust utilizes a premise that ordered residues should be 
conserved in 3D space in multiple models, whereas residues that 
vary or are consistently missing are correlated with the disorder. It 
predicts per-residue error in multiple fold recognition models which 
is followed by an analysis of the conservation of the per-residue 
errors across all models (McGuffin, 2008). 
Second, we use the most comprehensive selection of the input 
information sources when compared with the recent methods 
(Table 1). Similar to MD, <rs type="software">DISpro</rs> and MULTICOM, we use the 
sequence profiles (the most widely used inputs; Table 1), predicted 
secondary structure (SS) [disordered regions are characterized by 
lack of SS (Radivojac et al., 2004, 2007; Vucetic et al., 2003)] 
and solvent accessibility [unstructured regions have a large solvent-
accessible area (Schlessinger et al., 2009)]. We also utilize sequence-
based predictions of backbone dihedral torsion angles, B-factor 
[which are associated with disordered regions (Zhang et al., 2009)]   and the sequence terminus indicator [similarly to PrDOS (Su et al.,  2007)]. The usage of the backbone angles is motivated by their 
usefulness in building-scoring function for fold recognition and 3D 
structure prediction (Wu and Zhang, 2008), and by the success of 
the 3D-based <rs type="software">DISOclust</rs> that ranked fourth in CASP8 (Noivirt-Brik  et al., 2009). We tried predictions of signal peptides, but we did not 
find them useful. 
Third, we aggregate the predictions, before feeding them into a 
classifier, using a sliding window to facilitate predictions of long-
disordered regions. The aggregation utilizes neighboring predictions 
to perform averaging, to find maximal and minimal prediction 
value/probability and to analyze local SS conformations, which 
helps the classifier to find longer stretches of disordered residues. 
Fourth, we use two-layered architecture where the first layer 
includes three predictors, one designed for all disordered residues, 
one for short (&lt;30 residues), and one for long segments. These 
predictors use different inputs encoded using numerical descriptors 
derived from the abovementioned sources. The second layer 
combines their outputs to generate our disorder predictions. 
MFDp is capable of recognizing various types of disorder, since 
it is trained using a dataset that includes residues from disordered 
regions of all sizes and that combines proteins from the DisProt 
database and X-ray structures from the PDB. </p>

<p>2 METHODS </p>

<p>2.1 Datasets </p>

<p>The proposed method was designed and tested on a dataset with 514 protein 
sequences. These sequences were harvested from the PDB and the DisProt 
databases. The PDB sequences were filtered using the culled PDB list (Wang  and Dunbrack, 1993) to extract a high-quality and low-sequence identity 
subset. We selected sequences that have structures with R-factor &lt;0.2 and 
resolution &lt;2.0 Å, and that are characterized by sequence identity &lt;5%. 
The above follows the selection process used by GS-metaDisorder, one 
of the leading methods in CASP8. Since most protein chains in PDB are 
completely ordered, we kept randomly selected 20% of the ordered proteins. 
We extracted the entire set of 1195 proteins from the current release 4.9 of 
the DisProt and we merged them with the PDB chains. The combined set was </p>

<p>i490 </p>

<p>MFDp -Multilayered fusion-based disorder predictor </p>

<p>filtered at 25% sequence identity as follows. For a given pair of sequences 
that share &gt;25% identity, we remove the chain that has fewer disordered 
residues. Next, we removed any of the remaining 522 sequences that share 
significant similarity with chains in the CASP8 dataset that is also used 
to validate our predictions; we removed each sequence that shares &gt;25% 
identity to any of the CASP8 targets. The resulting dataset, named mixed 
disorder (MxD) dataset, has 514 protein sequences, with 309 from DisProt 
and 205 from PDB. Our method is also compared against other solutions 
using the CASP8 dataset, which contains 122 proteins; details concerning 
this dataset are given in Noivirt-Brik et al. (2009). </p>

<p>2.2 Definition of disorder </p>

<p>Prior works show that the assignment of the disordered regions performed 
using different experimental methods is not always consistent (Vucetic et al.,  2003). The disorder predictors that were trained on regions identified by 
one experimental method could be less accurate for prediction of disordered 
regions that were characterized by other methods (Schlessinger et al., 2007a,  b). To date, there is no golden standard for the assignment of the disordered 
regions. In the past CASP experiments the disordered regions were defined as 
residues that lack coordinates in structures solved by X-ray crystallography 
and as residues that exhibit high variability within ensemble or are annotated 
as disordered in REMARK 465 by experimentalists for the structures solved 
by NMR (Bordoli et al., 2007; Noivirt-Brik et al., 2009). Consequently, 
the above definition is used to annotate disordered residues in the CASP8 
dataset. The MxD dataset utilizes two types of annotations to generalize the 
proposed predictive model. The chains extracted from PDB are annotated 
using the above definition, while the chains from DisProt use the curated 
annotations extracted from this database. </p>

<p>2.3 Evaluation criteria and test procedures </p>

<p>The assessment of the predictions uses the same criteria as in the CASP 
experiments (Bordoli et al., 2007; Noivirt-Brik et al., 2009). The evaluation 
was performed per-residue since per-protein predictions are more prone to 
overfitting (Schlessinger et al., 2009). The predictions are at two levels: (i) the 
binary value that defines whether a given residue is or is not disordered; 
and (ii) the real value that quantifies probability of disorder. The binary 
predictions were assessed using five measures: </p>

<p>MCC = 
TP * TN−FP * FN </p>

<p>(TP+FP) * (TP+FN) * (TN+FP) * (TN+FN) </p>

<p>Sensitivity = SENS = TP/(TP+FN) = TP/N disorder </p>

<p>Specificity = SPEC = TN/(TN + FP) = TN/N order </p>

<p>ACC = (SENS+SPEC)/2 </p>

<p>S w = (W disorder  * TP−W order  * FP+W order  * TN </p>

<p>−W disorder  * FN)/(W disorder  * N disorder +W order  * N order ) </p>

<p>where TP is the number of true positives (correctly predicted disordered 
residues), FP denotes false positives (ordered residues that were predicted as 
disordered), TN denotes true negatives (correctly predicted ordered residues), 
FN stands for false negatives (disordered residues that were predicted 
ordered), W disorder is the total percent of ordered residues, W order is the total 
percent of disordered residues and N order and N disorder are the total number of 
ordered and disordered residues, respectively. The S w and MCC values range 
between −1 and 1 and they are equal zero when all residues are predicted to 
be ordered or disordered. The higher the values of these measures the better 
the predictions. 
The receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve was used to examine 
the predicted probabilities. For each value of probability P achieved by a 
given method (between 0 and 1), all the residues with probability equal to or 
greater than P are set as disordered, and all other residues are set as ordered. 
Next, the TP-rate and the FP-rate are calculated and we use the area under 
the curve (AUC) to quantify the predictive quality. </p>

<p>We designed the proposed predictor (which includes selection of features 
that are used to encode the inputs, parameterization of the Support Vector 
Machine (SVM)-based classifiers and selection of the threshold for the 
predicted disorder probabilities to obtain binary predictions) using 5-fold 
cross validation on the MxD dataset. In this test, we divide the dataset into 
five equal-sized subsets of protein chains. We use four of these subsets to 
form a training dataset that is utilized to compute the model and the fifth 
subset constitutes the testing dataset that is used to perform the evaluation. 
This is repeated five times, each time choosing a different subset to be the 
test dataset. The test on the CASP 8 was performed using the model trained 
on the MxD dataset. </p>

<p>2.4 Architecture </p>

<p>Predictions are performed using an ensemble of three SVM classifiers that 
are designated to predict all disordered residues (SVM ALL ), and disordered 
residues in long (≥30 residues) (SVM LONG ) and short segments (&lt;30 
residues) (SVM SHORT ). Each classifier is designed individually, i.e. uses 
different parameters and different set of input features (see Sections 2.5 
and 2.6) computed from the <rs type="software">IUPred</rs>, <rs type="software">DISOclust</rs> and <rs type="software">DISOPRED2</rs> 
predictions, the sequence, the sequence profiles and the various relevant 
sequence-based predictions. The latter predictions are performed using 
methods chosen based on two criteria: (i) their quality is comparable 
to the leading relevant predictors; and (ii) they provide a stand-alone 
implementation that could be utilized to build an autonomous implementation 
of the proposed disorder predictor. We utilize PSIPRED (McGuffin et al.,  2000) for the SS prediction, Real-SPINE3 for the prediction of the relative 
solvent accessibility (RSA) and backbone dihedral torsion angles (Faraggi  et al., 2009), <rs id="software-57" type="software">PROFbval</rs> for the B-factor prediction and residue flexibility 
prediction (<rs corresp="#software-57" type="creator">Schlessinger</rs> et al., 2006) and RPSP for the signal peptide 
prediction (Plewczynski et al., 2008). We also use <rs type="software">IUPred</rs> to predict globular 
domains. The selection of the SVM as the classifiers was motivated by its 
prior extensive use in disorder prediction (Hirose et al., 2007; Ishida and  Kinoshita 2007, 2008; Peng et al., 2006; Shimizu et al., 2007a, b; Vullo,  et al. 2006). We use a linear-kernel-based SVM introduced in Fan et al. 
(2008). The real-valued prediction is computed as a maximum among the 
probabilities generated by SVM ALL , SVM SHORT and SVM LONG (we combine 
all predicted disordered residues) and the resulting value is binarized using 
the threshold that equals 0.37. The value of the threshold was found using the 
MxD dataset. We 'smooth out' our binary predictions by filtering out short 
segments (≤2 residues). On the first pass, we convert predicted ordered 
residues in segments ≤2 residues to disordered residues with probability of 
0.37. One the second pass, we reassign the short, ≤2 residues, segments of 
disordered residues as ordered with probability of 0.369. The MFDp predictor 
is shown in Figure 1. </p>

<p>2.5 Feature space representation </p>

<p>The MFDp utilizes four complementary disorder predictors, <rs type="software">IUPred LONG (IUPREDL</rs>), <rs type="software">IUPred SHORT (IUPREDS</rs>), <rs type="software">DISOPRED2</rs> and <rs type="software">DISOclust</rs>; 
the sequence, the PSSM profile (Altschul et al., 1997), the predicted SS, 
the predicted RSA, the predicted globular domains (IUPREDG), backbone 
dihedral torsion angles and signal peptides. The predictors were run with 
their default parameters. The PSSM profiles were generated using the non-
redundant (nr) database from NCBI (downloaded on November 19, 2009), 
which was filtered using PFILT (Jones and Swindells, 2002) to remove 
low-complexity regions, transmembrane regions and coiled-coil segments. 
We utilize a sliding window of size 15 centered over the predicted residue 
to extract the features. We use the raw numerical values for each of the 
15 positions, which include: the probability of the prediction of disordered 
residues from IUPREDL, IUPREDS, DISOPRED2 and DISOclust; the 
PSSM values; the probabilities of prediction of helix, coil and strand 
conformations from PSIPRED; the predicted B-factor values; the predicted 
solvent accessibility and backbone angles; and the binary values denoting 
whether a given position in the window is predicted as a signal peptide, </p>

<p>i491 </p>

<p>M.J.Mizianty et al. </p>

<p>IUPRED 
-long 
-short </p>

<p>ALL 
SHORT 
LONG </p>

<p>sequence </p>

<p>REAL Spine3 </p>

<p>PSIPRED </p>

<p>PSIBLAST 
DISOclust </p>

<p>DISOPRED 
PROFbval </p>

<p>16 features 
30 features 
17 features </p>

<p>SVM ALL 
SVM SHORT 
SVM LONG </p>

<p>outputs 
probability = max {SVM ALL , SVM SHORT , SVM LONG } 
binary prediction using threshold = 0.37 on probability </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Architecture of the MFDp method. </p>

<p>belongs to a globular domain, is part of a purification tag or is predicted 
as flexible by <rs type="software">PROFbval</rs>, to encode the features. We also aggregate the raw 
numerical values (except for the predicted backbone angles) by computing 
averages in the sliding widows of sizes between 3 and 41, and by taking 
maximal and minimal value in the sliding widows of sizes between 3 and 
15. The averages for the residue at the i-th position in the sequence are 
computed as follows: </p>

<p>X_avg avg m = </p>

<p>min( </p>

<p>avg m </p>

<p>2 ,seqLen) </p>

<p>wn=max </p>

<p>-avg m </p>

<p>2 ,0 </p>

<p>X_w{w n } 
m </p>

<p>where X ∈{PSSM_{AA j }, SS_{SS k }, RSA, IUPREDL, IUPREDS, 
DISOPRED, DISOCLUST} is the name of a given feature, AA j with 
j ∈{1,2,...,20} is the amino acid type, SS k with k ∈{H, E, C} is the type 
of the SS, avg m with m ∈{3,5,7,...39,41} is the size of the window, w n with 
n ∈{−20,−19,...,19,20} is the position in the window where 0 denotes the 
position of the predicted residue, and X_w{w n } is the value of feature X for 
the residue at position w n (the actual position in the sequence equals i+w n ). 
When aggregating, we ignore the positions in the window that are outside 
of the chain for the residues close to the sequence terminus, i.e. we sum 
only the values for the positions in the chain and this sum is dived by the 
total number of these positions. The features are divided into 17 categories 
based on the source information used including sequence, PSSM, amino-acid 
frequency, conservation, SS, RSA, torsion angles, <rs type="software">DISOPRED2</rs>, <rs type="software">DISOclust</rs>, 
<rs type="software">IUPREDL</rs>, IUPREDS, B-factor, signal peptides, purification tag, globular 
domains, strict flexibility and non-strict flexibility. Detailed description is 
provided in the appendix at http://biomine.ece.ualberta.ca/MFDp.html. </p>

<p>2.6 Feature selection and parameterization of SVMs </p>

<p>We designed three SVMs using different versions of the MxD dataset. The 
SVM ALL was designed using the entire MxD dataset, while SVM LONG 
and SVM SHORT were developed using the MxD dataset where the disorder 
residues from short (&lt;30 residues) and from long (≥30 residues) disorder 
segments were removed, respectively. For each of the three models we used 
the following procedure. In the 'first step' we remove all highly correlated 
features within each of the 17 feature categories. For each feature we compute 
its average biserial correlation (over five correlations computed from the five 
training subsets of the MxD dataset) with the outcomes, i.e. annotation of 
ordered and disorder residues. We sort the features in each category according 
to their average biserial correlations. The set of the selected features is 
initialized with the feature that has the highest biserial correlation. Next, </p>

<p>for each following features we calculate its average correlation (over the 
five training subsets) with any of the features which were already selected, 
and we add it to the set of selected features only if the correlation &lt;0.9. We 
discard the features that were not selected. In the 'second step' we quantify 
predictive quality of the features selected in the first step using the linear 
SVMs. We construct feature sets by selecting top t features, according to 
their average biserial correlations, from each category. We take all features 
in a given category if their number &lt; t. Next, we run 5-fold cross validation 
on the MxD dataset where we vary the value of t between 1 and 15, and for 
each t we parameterize the value of constant C of the linear SVM classifiers. 
We consider C in consecutive powers of 2 between 2 −8 and 2 5 . For each of the 
prediction models (ALL, LONG and SHORT) t = 1 provides the best values 
of AUC in the 5-fold cross validation on the MxD dataset. Next, starting 
from the least correlated feature from the selected 17 features, we removed a 
given feature if it increases AUC value for the 5-fold cross validation-based 
prediction on the MxD dataset; this lead to removal of the features related 
to the annotation of the signal peptides. For the remaining relevant feature 
categories, we attempt to add additional features which improve predictive 
quality. For each of the remaining categories, starting with the category with 
the most correlated feature, we keep adding features (starting with second-
best feature from the category) as long as the addition of a feature increased 
the AUC value for the 5-fold cross validation on the MxD dataset. For 
each removal/addition, we tuned the C parameter of the SVM. For the ALL 
model, we selected 16 features from 11 categories; for the SHORT model, 
we selected 30 features from 12 categories; and for the LONG model, we 
have 17 features from 12 categories. The selected features are shown in 
the Table 1 in the appendix at http://biomine.ece.ualberta.ca/MFDp.html. A 
significant fraction of the features (27 out of the entire set of 63) are based on 
the aggregated information, which suggests that our features provide better 
discriminatory power than the raw values. The selected features consider 
almost all sources, except for the signal peptides annotations. 
The entire process, including feature selection and SVM parameterization, 
was consistently carried using 5-fold cross validation on MxD dataset. </p>

<p>3 RESULTS </p>

<p>3.1 Comparison with existing predictors </p>

<p>We compare MFDp with relevant predictors on the MxD and CASP8 
datasets. For the MxD dataset, we use 5-fold cross validation to 
assess our predictions; we use 75% of each of the five training 
subsets to compute SVMs, the other 25% to find the threshold used 
for binarization of the probabilities, and the test subsets to evaluate 
predictions. In contrast, predictions from other method are generated 
on the entire dataset (without cross-validation) using either web-
servers or stand-alone implementations provided by the authors. 
For the test on the CASP8 dataset, the MFDp is trained, including 
computation of SVMs (using the same parameters as for the MxD 
dataset) and the selection of the threshold, using all fully disordered 
and PDB chains in the MxD dataset; these chains have similar 
disorder characteristics to the chains in the CASP8. The training 
chains from the MxD dataset share at most 25% identity to any 
chain the CASP8 set making it challenging to perform predictions. 
On the contrary, the methods we compare with use large training 
datasets that may share substantial similarity to the CASP8 targets 
(i.e only a handful of CASP8 target were consider as free-modeling), 
which could raise their predictive quality. 
The cross-validated predictions of MFDp are compared to its 
input predictors, including: <rs type="software">DISOPRED2</rs>; <rs type="software">IUPredL</rs> and <rs type="software">IUPredS</rs> 
(IUPred predictions for short and long segments); <rs type="software">DISOclust</rs>; and 
<rs type="software">PROFBval</rs>, and with selected other recent methods including the </p>

<p>i492 </p>

<p>MFDp -Multilayered fusion-based disorder predictor </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparison of predictive quality measured on the MxD and CASP8 datasets when considering all disordered regions </p>

<p>Dataset Predictor 
MCC 
S w 
ACC 
SENS 
SPEC 
AUC </p>

<p>Value SD 
Signif-Value SD 
Signif-Value SD 
Value SD 
Value SD 
Value SD 
Signif-
icance 
icance 
icance </p>

<p>MxD 
MFDp 
0.44 
±0.02 
0.51 
±0.01 
0.75 
±0.01 0.76 
±0.01 0.75 
±0.01 0.81 
±0.01 
MD 
0.43 
±0.02 
+ 
0.48 
±0.01 
+ 
0.74 
±0.01 0.68 
±0.01 0.80 
±0.01 0.81 
±0.01 
= 
DISOPRED2 0.40 
±0.02 
+ 
0.44 
±0.02 
+ 
0.72 
±0.01 0.66 
±0.01 0.78 
±0.01 0.78 
±0.01 
+ 
IUPredL 
0.39 
±0.02 
+ 
0.42 
±0.01 
+ 
0.71 
±0.01 0.60 
±0.01 0.82 
±0.01 0.78 
±0.01 
+ 
IUPredS 
0.37 
±0.01 
+ 
0.38 
±0.01 
+ 
0.69 
±0.01 0.53 
±0.01 0.85 
±0.01 0.78 
±0.01 
+ 
NORSnet 
0.34 
±0.02 
+ 
0.37 
±0.02 
+ 
0.68 
±0.01 0.55 
±0.02 0.81 
±0.01 0.74 
±0.01 
+ 
DISOclust 
0.33 
±0.01 
+ 
0.40 
±0.01 
+ 
0.70 
±0.01 0.78 
±0.01 0.62 
±0.01 0.77 
±0.01 
+ 
Ucon 
0.31 
±0.01 
+ 
0.34 
±0.01 
+ 
0.67 
±0.01 0.57 
±0.01 0.77 
±0.01 0.74 
±0.01 
+ 
PROFbval 
0.19 
±0.01 
+ 
0.22 
±0.01 
+ 
0.61 
±0.00 0.84 
±0.01 0.38 
±0.01 0.69 
±0.01 
+ </p>

<p>CASP8 MFDp 
0.61 
±0.06 
0.63 
±0.06 
0.82 
±0.03 0.68 
±0.06 0.95 
±0.00 0.89 
±0.02 
379 
0.59 
±0.06 
+ 
0.65 
±0.05 
-
0.82 
±0.03 0.71 
±0.05 0.94 
±0.00 0.91 
±0.02 
-
DISOPRED2 0.59 
±0.06 
+ 
0.61 
±0.06 
+ 
0.80 
±0.03 0.65 
±0.06 0.95 
±0.00 0.88 
±0.02 
+ 
297 
0.57 
±0.05 
+ 
0.66 
±0.05 
-
0.83 
±0.02 0.74 
±0.05 0.92 
±0.00 0.90 
±0.02 
-
97 
0.56 
±0.05 
+ 
0.65 
±0.05 
-
0.82 
±0.02 0.73 
±0.05 0.92 
±0.00 0.91 
±0.02 
-
153 
0.55 
±0.05 
+ 
0.67 
±0.05 
-
0.83 
±0.02 0.76 
±0.05 0.90 
±0.00 0.91 
±0.02 
-
IUPredS 
0.54 
±0.06 
+ 
0.52 
±0.06 
+ 
0.76 
±0.03 0.56 
±0.06 0.96 
±0.00 0.85 
±0.03 
+ 
IUPredL 
0.53 
±0.09 
+ 
0.45 
±0.09 
+ 
0.73 
±0.05 0.48 
±0.09 0.98 
±0.00 0.82 
±0.03 
+ 
69 
0.51 
±0.05 
+ 
0.66 
±0.04 
-
0.83 
±0.02 0.80 
±0.04 0.86 
±0.00 0.90 
±0.02 
-
NORSnet 
0.48 
±0.12 
+ 
0.37 
±0.11 
+ 
0.69 
±0.06 0.39 
±0.11 0.98 
±0.00 0.79 
±0.04 
+ 
DISOclust 
0.42 
±0.05 
+ 
0.59 
±0.04 
+ 
0.80 
±0.02 0.78 
±0.04 0.82 
±0.01 0.86 
±0.02 
+ 
MD 
0.42 
±0.06 
+ 
0.56 
±0.06 
+ 
0.78 
±0.03 0.71 
±0.06 0.85 
±0.01 0.85 
±0.03 
+ 
Ucon 
0.29 
±0.06 
+ 
0.34 
±0.07 
+ 
0.67 
±0.03 0.47 
±0.07 0.87 
±0.00 0.74 
±0.04 
+ 
PROFbval 
0.19 
±0.03 
+ 
0.31 
±0.03 
+ 
0.65 
±0.01 0.86 
±0.03 0.45 
±0.01 0.78 
±0.03 
+ </p>

<p>We report the averages and corresponding SDs for bootstrapping with 1000 repetitions of 80% of chains. Underlined methods are used as inputs for MFDp. The methods are sorted 
by the MCC values and the highest values are shown in bold. Results of tests of significance of the differences between MFDp and the other methods are given in the 'significance' 
columns. The tests compare average values from 1000 bootstrapping repetitions. The + and -mean that MFDp is statistically significantly better/worse with P &lt; 0.01, and = means 
that results are not significantly different. </p>

<p>consensus-based MD (Schlessinger et al., 2009), the propensity-
based <rs id="software-72" type="software">Ucon</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-72" type="creator">Schlessinger</rs> et al., 2007a) and the machine learning-
based <rs id="software-73" type="software">NORSnet</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-73" type="creator">Schlessinger</rs> et al., 2007b). Our results on the 
CASP8 dataset are also compared against five top-performing 
methods in the CASP8 experiments (Noivirt-Brik et al., 2009). 
These methods are identified by the group number in square 
brackets (as registered for the CASP8 meeting) and the group 
name. They include GS-MetaServer2 [153], <rs type="software">GeneSilicoMetaServer</rs> 
[297], MULTICOM-CMFR [69] (Cheng et al., 2005), <rs id="software-75" type="software">DISOclust</rs> 
[97] (<rs corresp="#software-75" type="creator">McGuffin</rs>, 2008) and McGuffin [379], which is a human-
based consensus that uses DISOclust. More detailed description 
of these predictors can be found in the CASP8 abstracts at 
http://predictioncenter.org/casp8/doc/CASP8_book.pdf. 
We compare predictive quality when considering all disordered 
regions and for the regions that are at least 30 residues long, 
respectively. The selection of the length threshold is consistent with 
values used in the recent investigation of protein-protein recognition 
mechanisms (Tompa et al. 2009) and in design of predictors for 
long segments (Han et al. 2009; Peng et al. 2006). The same as in 
the CASP8, we discard the disordered regions with three or fewer 
residues (Noivirt-Brik et al., 2009; private correspondence with 
authors), i.e. these residues are ignored when computing the quality 
measures. Similarly, for the results on the long segments we discard 
the shorter regions. Following the CASP8, predictions were assessed </p>

<p>using bootstrapping in which 80% of the targets were randomly 
selected 1000 times and we report the corresponding averages and 
standard deviations see Tables 2 and 3. We recomputed the results 
for the CASP8 submissions and we found them consistent with the 
original report (Noivirt-Brik et al., 2009). We also analyze statistical 
significance of the differences between MFDp and the other 
methods. We compared the 1000 paired average results for MCC, 
S w and AUC obtained from using the bootstrapping with 80% of the 
targets on both CASP8 and MxD datasets. Since the averages do not 
follow normal distribution, as tested using Shapiro-Wilk test at the 
0.05 significance, we use Wilcoxon rank sum test and we measure 
significance of the differences at 0.01 level. Tables 2 and 3 show 
that MFDp consistently outperforms all methods based on the MCC 
index. These improvements are statistically significant with P &lt; 0.01 
when compared with all considered competitors on both datasets and 
for both all and long-disordered segments, except for <rs type="software">NORSnet</rs> and 
<rs type="software">IUPREDL</rs> on the long regions and the CASP8 dataset. Results on the 
MxD dataset demonstrate that MFDp significantly outperforms its 
input methods as well as MD, <rs type="software">NORSnet</rs> and <rs type="software">Ucon</rs> when considering 
the S w and AUC values and for both all and long-disordered 
segments. Only MD method is shown to be comparable with 
respect to the AUC values. For the prediction of both all and long 
segments on the smaller CASP8 dataset, the MFDp significantly 
improves over its input predictors, MD, <rs type="software">NORSnet</rs> and Ucon for </p>

<p>i493 </p>

<p>M.J.Mizianty et al. </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparison of predictive quality measured on the MxD and CASP8 datasets when considering disordered regions that are ≥30-residues long </p>

<p>Dataset Predictor 
MCC 
S w 
ACC 
SENS 
SPEC 
AUC </p>

<p>Value SD 
Signif-Value SD 
Signif-Value SD 
Value SD 
Value SD 
Value SD 
Signif-
icance 
icance 
icance </p>

<p>MxD 
MFDp 
0.44 
±0.02 
0.52 
±0.02 
0.76 
±0.01 0.77 
±0.01 0.75 
±0.01 0.82 
±0.01 
MD 
0.44 
±0.02 
+ 
0.50 
±0.02 
+ 
0.75 
±0.01 0.70 
±0.01 0.80 
±0.01 0.82 
±0.01 
= 
IUPredL 
0.41 
±0.02 
+ 
0.45 
±0.01 
+ 
0.72 
±0.01 0.63 
±0.01 0.82 
±0.01 0.79 
±0.01 
+ 
DISOPRED2 0.40 
±0.02 
+ 
0.46 
±0.02 
+ 
0.73 
±0.01 0.67 
±0.02 0.78 
±0.01 0.78 
±0.01 
+ 
NORSnet 
0.37 
±0.02 
+ 
0.41 
±0.02 
+ 
0.70 
±0.01 0.59 
±0.02 0.81 
±0.01 0.76 
±0.01 
+ 
IUPredS 
0.37 
±0.01 
+ 
0.38 
±0.01 
+ 
0.69 
±0.01 0.53 
±0.01 0.85 
±0.01 0.78 
±0.01 
+ 
DISOclust 
0.33 
±0.01 
+ 
0.40 
±0.01 
+ 
0.70 
±0.01 0.79 
±0.01 0.62 
±0.01 0.77 
±0.01 
+ 
Ucon 
0.32 
±0.01 
+ 
0.37 
±0.01 
+ 
0.68 
±0.01 0.60 
±0.01 0.77 
±0.01 0.75 
±0.01 
+ 
PROFbval 
0.19 
±0.01 
+ 
0.22 
±0.01 
+ 
0.61 
±0.00 0.84 
±0.01 0.38 
±0.01 0.70 
±0.01 
+ </p>

<p>CASP8 MFDp 
0.60 
±0.10 
0.73 
±0.09 
0.86 
±0.04 0.78 
±0.09 0.95 
±0.00 0.90 
±0.04 
NORSnet 
0.59 
±0.16 
= 
0.57 
±0.16 
+ 
0.79 
±0.08 0.59 
±0.17 0.98 
±0.00 0.87 
±0.05 
+ 
IUPredL 
0.59 
±0.15 
= 
0.60 
±0.15 
+ 
0.80 
±0.07 0.62 
±0.15 0.98 
±0.00 0.85 
±0.06 
+ 
DISOPRED2 0.58 
±0.11 
+ 
0.68 
±0.10 
+ 
0.84 
±0.05 0.73 
±0.10 0.95 
±0.00 0.90 
±0.04 
= 
379 
0.56 
±0.10 
+ 
0.71 
±0.08 
+ 
0.86 
±0.04 0.77 
±0.08 0.94 
±0.00 0.93 
±0.03 
-
297 
0.54 
±0.09 
+ 
0.73 
±0.08 
+ 
0.87 
±0.04 0.81 
±0.08 0.92 
±0.00 0.91 
±0.04 
-
IUPredS 
0.53 
±0.11 
+ 
0.59 
±0.10 
+ 
0.79 
±0.05 0.63 
±0.10 0.96 
±0.00 0.86 
±0.05 
+ 
97 
0.52 
±0.09 
+ 
0.71 
±0.08 
+ 
0.85 
±0.04 0.79 
±0.08 0.92 
±0.00 0.93 
±0.03 
-
153 
0.50 
±0.09 
+ 
0.72 
±0.08 
+ 
0.86 
±0.04 0.81 
±0.08 0.90 
±0.00 0.92 
±0.03 
-
69 
0.44 
±0.08 
+ 
0.69 
±0.07 
+ 
0.85 
±0.03 0.83 
±0.07 0.86 
±0.00 0.91 
±0.03 
-
DISOclust 
0.37 
±0.07 
+ 
0.63 
±0.07 
+ 
0.81 
±0.04 0.81 
±0.07 0.82 
±0.01 0.88 
±0.04 
+ 
MD 
0.36 
±0.09 
+ 
0.58 
±0.11 
+ 
0.79 
±0.05 0.73 
±0.11 0.85 
±0.01 0.86 
±0.05 
+ 
Ucon 
0.28 
±0.09 
+ 
0.41 
±0.12 
+ 
0.71 
±0.06 0.54 
±0.12 0.87 
±0.00 0.77 
±0.06 
+ 
PROFbval 
0.16 
±0.04 
+ 
0.31 
±0.05 
+ 
0.66 
±0.03 0.87 
±0.05 0.45 
±0.01 0.81 
±0.06 
+ </p>

<p>We report the averages and corresponding SDs for bootstrapping with 1000 repetitions of 80% of chains. Underlined methods are used as inputs for MFDp. The methods are sorted 
by the MCC values and the highest values are shown in bold. Results of tests of significance of the differences between MFDp and the other methods are given in the 'significance' 
columns. The tests compare average values from 1000 bootstrapping repetitions. The + and − mean that MFDp is statistically significantly better/worse with P &lt; 0.01, and = means 
that results are not significantly different. </p>

<p>the binary prediction measured using MCC and S w . The fact that 
MFDp is successful in maintaining high-quality predictions for the 
long segments is important given that predictors designed for long 
disordered regions are usually less successful in predicting short 
regions (Obradovic et al., 2005; Peng et al., 2005). Our method 
is outperformed on the S w and AUC values for the prediction of 
all segments by the top five CASP8 methods, but we significantly 
improve over these methods based on the MCC index. We also 
significantly improve over their binary assignments, measured with 
MCC and S w , for the long-disordered segments. Our improvement 
are achieved in spite of the fact that our training chains share 
&lt;25% identity to CASP8 targets, while the top predictors in CASP8 
use training sequences that likely share more significant similarity. 
Moreover, the GS-MetaServer2 [153] and <rs type="software">GeneSilicoMetaServer</rs> 
[297] are unpublished and do not offer implementations/servers. 
The McGuffin [379] method is not automated and requires human 
expert and the <rs type="software">DISOclust</rs> [97] results submitted to CASP8 are better 
than the results generated by the stand-alone <rs type="software">DISOclust</rs> provided to 
us by the authors. The MFDp is available as an automated web 
server at http://biomine.ece.ualberta.ca/MFDp.html. The ROCs for 
the predictions on both datasets are shown in Figure 2. This figure 
focuses on the FP rates &lt; 0.5; the entire curve is given in the 
appendix at http://biomine.ece.ualberta.ca/MFDp.html. The curve 
reveals that MFDp provides favorable TP rates for the FP values </p>

<p>between 0 and 0.4 on the MxD dataset and between 0.1 and 
0.4 on the CASP8 dataset when compared with all predictors 
except the top-performing methods in the CASP8. Our method 
provides comparable TP rates for the FP rates &gt;0.2 when compared 
with the top performers from the CASP8 experiment. Overall, we 
conclude that MFDp outperforms modern existing predictors for 
binary disorder predictions and provides competitive real-valued 
predictions. </p>

<p>3.2 Predictions of proteins with long-disordered 
segments </p>

<p>We investigate the quality of our predictions applied to find proteins 
with long (≥30 residues)-disordered regions. This binary prediction 
is motivated by the fact that this information is useful for target 
selection (Punta et al., 2009; Slabinski et al., 2007) and protein-
protein recognition (Tompa et al., 2009). Similar evaluation was also 
performed for the MD (Schlessinger et al., 2009). Although ∼43% 
of disordered residues in CASP8 are in the long segments (allowing 
for a relatively robust per-residues evaluations), there are only 15 
such segments and thus we did not use this dataset. The results 
on the MD dataset obtained using 5-fold cross validation for the 
MFDp and the predictions from the servers for MD, <rs type="software">DISOPRED2</rs>, 
<rs type="software">IUPred</rs>, <rs type="software">NORSnet</rs>, <rs type="software">DISOclust</rs>, <rs type="software">Ucon</rs> and <rs type="software">PROFbval</rs> are summarized </p>

<p>i494 </p>

<p>MFDp -Multilayered fusion-based disorder predictor </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
0 . 1 
0 . 2 
0 . 3 
0 . 4 
0 . 5 </p>

<p>FP rate </p>

<p>TP rate </p>

<p>M FDp 
M D 
IUP REDL 
IUP REDS 
DISOP RED2 
DISOclust 
No rsnet 
Uco n 
PROFbval </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
0.1 
0.2 
0.3 
0.4 
0.5 </p>

<p>FP rate </p>

<p>TP rate </p>

<p>M FDp 
M D 
IUP REDL 
IUP REDS 
DISOP RED2 
DISOclust 
Norsnet 
Uco n 
PROFbval 
69 
97 
153 
297 
379 </p>

<p>Fig. 2. ROCs for the predictions on the (A) MxD and (B) CASP8 datasets. </p>

<p>Table 4. Comparison of predictions of proteins with long (≥30 residues) 
disordered segments on the MxD datasets </p>

<p>Predictor 
MCC 
ACC 
SENS 
SPEC 
AUC </p>

<p>MFDp 
0.53 
0.77 
0.82 
0.71 
0.86 
Ucon 
0.52 
0.73 
0.53 
0.95 
0.85 
DISOPRED2 
0.52 
0.76 
0.71 
0.81 
0.82 
IUPredS 
0.52 
0.75 
0.63 
0.87 
0.83 
IUPredL 
0.51 
0.74 
0.60 
0.89 
0.83 
MD 
0.49 
0.74 
0.67 
0.81 
0.80 
NORSnet 
0.48 
0.71 
0.51 
0.93 
0.80 
DISOclust 
0.47 
0.73 
0.84 
0.62 
0.82 
PROFbval 
0.39 
0.69 
0.73 
0.66 
0.76 </p>

<p>Underlined methods are used as inputs for MFDp. The methods are sorted by the MCC 
values and the highest values are shown in bold. </p>

<p>in Table 4. The corresponding ROC curves are shown in Figure 3 
(for 0-0.5-TP-rate range) and in the appendix (for the entire range). 
The results demonstrate that MFDp outperforms all considered 
predictors as measured using MCC, ACC and AUC values. This 
suggests that our method is a useful resource for annotation of 
proteins with long disordered regions. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
0.1 
0.2 
0.3 
0.4 
0.5 </p>

<p>FP rate </p>

<p>TP rate </p>

<p>M FDp 
M D 
IUP REDL 
IUP REDS 
DISOPRED2 
DISOclust 
No rsnet 
Uco n 
PROFbval </p>

<p>Fig. 3. ROCs for the predictions of proteins with long-disordered segments 
on the MxD dataset. </p>

<p>3.3 Case studies </p>

<p>We selected CASP8 target T0480 (PDBid 2K4X) which was solved 
with NMR, and CASP8 target T0404 (PDBid 2DFE) which was 
solved with X-ray crystallography, as our case studies. We compare 
side-by-side prediction of MFDp, its input predictors <rs type="software">DISOPRED2</rs>, 
<rs type="software">IUPred</rs>, <rs type="software">DISOclust</rs>, the recent ensemble-based MD, and two top-
performing on the CASP8 (with respect to MCC) McGuffin 
[379] and <rs type="software">GeneSilicoMetaServer</rs> [297] methods (Fig. 4). For the 
T0480, which is a small protein with ∼50% disordered residues 
located at sequence termini, MFDp finds both disordered segments, 
achieves below-average MCC of 0.59 and improves over predictions 
of its ensemble predictors. The MD over-predicts disorder and 
<rs type="software">GeneSilicoMetaServer</rs> generates predictions comparable to that of 
MFDp. The T0404 includes 25% disordered residues with one longer 
segment away from the termini. Most of the predictors find both 
disordered segments, and they also incorrectly annotate another 
disordered segment at the N-terminus, except IUPREDL which 
predicts only the middle segment. The <rs type="software">GeneSilicoMetaServer</rs> and 
MD slightly over-predict disorder, and the segment in the center 
of the chain is most accurately predicted by MFDp, <rs type="software">DISOPRED2</rs> 
and McGuffin. Although these predictions should not be assumed 
typical, they demonstrate that the MFDp can outperform all of its 
input predictors. </p>

<p>4 CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>The MFDp predicts disordered regions of all sizes and different 
types. On average, it improves over the predictions of current 
solutions for the binary disorder assignment and provides 
competitive real-value predictions, as evaluated on two datasets with 
low-sequence similarity. The MFDp's outputs are also shown to 
outperform other predictors for the identification of proteins with 
long-disordered regions. The main reasons for the improvements 
are the application of a comprehensive set of information sources 
including complementary disorder predictions, sequence profiles 
and other relevant sequence-based predictors of structural and 
functional protein characteristics, novel two-layer architecture 
and the usage of custom features that aggregate raw prediction 
inputs. </p>

<p>i495 </p>

<p>M.J.Mizianty et al. </p>

<p>4 
0 
4 
0 
T 
t 
e 
g 
r 
a 
t 
8 
P 
S 
A 
C 
0 
8 
4 
0 
T 
t 
e 
g 
r 
a 
t 
8 
P 
S 
A 
C 
true </p>

<p>DDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDD------------------------------DDDDDDD </p>

<p>true </p>

<p>---------------------------------------DDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDD--------------------------------------------DDDDDDDDD </p>

<p>MFDp DDDDDDD----------------------------------------DDDDDDDD MFDp DDDDD-----------------------------------DDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDD----------------------------------------------DDDDDDD 
DP2 </p>

<p>DD---------------------------------------------D--DDDDD </p>

<p>DP2 </p>

<p>DDDD------------------------------------DDDDDDDDDDDDDDD---------------------------------------------------DDDD </p>

<p>IUPL </p>

<p>-------------------------------------------------------</p>

<p>IUPL </p>

<p>---------------------------------------DDDDDDDDDDDDDD--DDDDDD-------------------------------------------------</p>

<p>IUPS </p>

<p>DDDDDD---------------------------------------------DDDD </p>

<p>IUPS </p>

<p>DDDDD-------------------------------------DDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDD------------------------------------------------D </p>

<p>DISOc DD-------------------------------------------DDDDDDDDDD DISOc DDDDDDDDDDD------------------------DDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDD----------------------------------------------D---DDDD 
MD </p>

<p>DDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDD </p>

<p>MD </p>

<p>DDDDDDD---DDDDDD-DDDDD-------------DDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDD--------DDDDD------------------------------DDDDDDDDD </p>

<p>379 </p>

<p>DD---------------------------------------------D-DDDDDD </p>

<p>379 </p>

<p>DDDD------------------------------------DDDDDDDDDDDDDDD-----------------------------------------------D--DDDDD </p>

<p>297 </p>

<p>DDDDDD---------------D-----------------------DDDDDDDDDD </p>

<p>297 </p>

<p>DDDDDDDDDD----------------DDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDD---------------------------------------------DDDD </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Comparison of predictions from MFDp, DISOPRED2 (DP2), IUPREDL (IUPL), IUPREDS (IUPS) and DISOclust (DISOc), MD; and two CASP8 
predictors with the highest MCC, McGuffin (379) and GeneSilicoMetaServer (297) for CASP8 targets T0480 (on the left) and T0404 (on the right). The '-' 
and 'D' denote the ordered and disordered residues, respectively. The actual disorder annotations are shown in the first line. </p>

<p>Funding: NSERC Canada (to L.K.); Icore/Alberta Ingenuity 
Scholarships (to W.S., K.C. and K.D.K.). </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: none declared. </p>



</text></tei>