<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2806324" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The cytokinetic apparatus of animal cells consists of a transient, 
dynamic array of actin filaments and myosin-2-the contractile 
ring-and proteins that link it to the plasma membrane. Con-
striction of the contractile ring must draw the cell surface 
between the poles of the mitotic apparatus, separating centro-
somes and sister chromosomes, to properly partition daughter 
cells. To ensure this, cytokinetic apparatus formation depends 
on spatial cues conferred upon the cortex by the mitotic apparatus. 
For over a century, biologists have speculated that "as-
tral rays" extending from the spindle poles might transmit 
the cytokinetic signal to the cell surface (Bütschli, 1876). 
With the proof that astral rays are based on microtubules 
(Harris, 1961), that microtubule destruction prevents cytoki-
nesis (Beams and Evans, 1940; Hiramoto, 1956; Hamaguchi, 
1975), and that opposing asters can direct cytokinesis with-
out an intervening spindle (Rappaport, 1961), the role of 
astral microtubules as cytokinetic signal transmitters became 
ensconced in essentially all models of animal cytokinesis 
(for review see Burgess and Chang, 2005). A variety of spe-
cific molecular hypotheses are based on this assumption: </p>

<p>delivery of signals from spindle to cortex via microtubule 
motors (Wright et al., 1993; Adams et al., 1998; Powers et al., 
1998; Minestrini et al., 2003), signaling at the cortex via plus 
end tracking proteins (Inoue et al., 2004; Strickland et al., 
2005a), and local sequestration of cytokinetic regulators at 
the cortex by microtubule binding (Mandato et al., 2000; 
Dechant and Glotzer, 2003; Birkenfeld et al., 2007). 
The assumption that microtubules transmit the cyto-
kinetic signal has also engendered long-running debates 
about the nature of the microtubule population responsible 
for signal delivery. These debates include whether astral 
microtubules deliver a positive or negative signal to the cortex 
(Wolpert, 1960; Schroeder, 1981; Rappaport, 1986), whether 
more microtubules contact the equatorial or the polar cortex 
after anaphase onset (Asnes and Schroeder, 1979; White and 
Borisy, 1983; Dechant and Glotzer, 2003; Motegi et al., 2006), 
whether more microtubule ends from opposing asters contact 
the equator or not (Devore et al., 1989; Harris and Gewalt, 
1989; Yoshigaki, 1999), and whether dynamic properties of 
microtubules reaching the cortex are determinants for signal </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>nimal cells decide where to build the cyto 
kinetic apparatus by sensing the position of the 
mitotic spindle. Reflecting a longstanding pre 
sumption that a furrowinducing stimulus travels from 
spindle to cortex via microtubules, debate continues 
about which microtubules, and in what geometry, are 
essential for accurate cytokinesis. We used live imaging 
in urchin and frog embryos to evaluate the relationship 
between microtubule organization and cytokinetic fur 
row position. In normal cells, the cytokinetic apparatus 
forms in a region of lower cortical microtubule density. </p>

<p>Remarkably, cells depleted of astral microtubules con 
duct accurate, complete cytokinesis. Conversely, in 
anucleate cells, asters alone can support furrow induction 
without a spindle, but only when sufficiently separated. 
Ablation of a single centrosome displaces furrows 
away from the remaining centrosome; ablation of both 
centrosomes causes broad, inefficient furrowing. We 
conclude that the asters confer accuracy and preci 
sion to a primary furrowinducing signal that can reach 
the cell surface from the spindle without transport 
on microtubules. </p>

<p>Action at a distance during cytokinesis </p>

<p>George von Dassow, 
1,2 Koen J.C. Verbrugghe, 
3 Ann L. Miller, 
3 Jenny R. Sider, 
1,5 and William M. Bement </p>

<p>1,3,4 </p>

<p>1 Center for Cell Dynamics, Friday Harbor Laboratories, University of Washington, Seattle, WA 98250 
2 Oregon Institute of Marine Biology, University of Oregon, Eugene, OR 97420 
3 Department of Zoology and 
4 Laboratory of Molecular Biology, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI 53706 
5 Amundsen High School, Chicago, IL 60625 </p>

<p>© 2009 von Dassow et al. This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution-
Noncommercial-Share Alike-No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publica-
tion date (see http://www.jcb.org/misc/terms.shtml). After six months it is available under a 
Creative Commons License (Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, 
as described at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). </p>

<p>T H E J O U R N A L O F C E L L B I O L O G Y </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 187 • NUMBER 6 • 2009 
832 </p>

<p>enabled high-contrast, high-resolution microtubule visualization 
throughout the cell cycle, from the eight-cell stage on in purple 
urchin or sand dollar embryos (Fig. 1 and Video 1) and X. laevis 
blastomeres (Fig. S1 D and Video 2), which revealed apparently 
single microtubules extending to the cortex, even in large cells. 
Rapid microtubule growth and shrinkage were clearly evident 
(Fig. 1 C and Fig. S1 E), with microtubule growth at 16.7 ± 
11 µm/min (n = 50) and shrinkage at 9.9 ± 2.6 µm/min (n = 50) 
in X. laevis embryos, which is consistent with studies of cell 
free extracts (e.g., Belmont et al., 1990). 
Immunostaining embryos expressing EMTB-3G showed 
that GFP overlapped nearly completely with tubulin (Fig. S2), 
the sole exception being the ends of spindle midzone micro-
tubules and the center of the midbody, which were underlabeled 
by EMTB-3G. The only drawback to EMTB-3G was that rapid 
expression in the earliest embryos caused cell cycle arrest 
(Fig. S1 A) or defective mitosis. However, injection of 0.05-
0.1 ng/nl EMTB-3G mRNA routinely produced embryos with 
robust microtubule labeling and normal cell cycle progres-
sion; such embryos cleaved with no sign of mitotic errors to late 
blastula, whereupon they began to swim, gastrulated normally, 
and became morphologically normal feeding pluteus larvae 
(Fig. S1, B and C). 
We assessed microtubule dynamics in surface and axial 
views of sand dollar and purple urchin embryos (Fig. 1 and 
Fig. 2, A-C) and in surface views of X. laevis embryos (Fig. 2 D, 
Video 2, and Fig. S1 D). In all three species, regardless of imag-
ing plane, three observations were remarkably consistent. 
First, microtubules arrived in every part of the cortex, includ-
ing the equator, before furrowing (Fig. 1 A, B [ii-iv], and C; 
Fig. 2, A-C; and Fig. S1 D). Second, after anaphase onset, 
most astral microtubules at the cortex were stable, regardless 
of orientation (Fig. 2, A-C; and Fig. S1 D). Third, astral 
microtubules reached the cortex in greater density outside the 
furrow region (Figs. 1 C, 2, and S1 D). The last point was 
confirmed by imaging both microtubules (with 3C-EMTB) 
and active Rho, the earliest known marker for cytokinetic 
apparatus specification (with GFP-rhotekin GTPase-binding 
domain [rGBD]; Benink and Bement, 2005) in X. laevis em-
bryos (Fig. 2 D), which showed that microtubules arrived at the 
cortex before Rho activation even in very large cells, and that 
the Rho zone occupied a microtubule-poor region of the cortex. </p>

<p>Nocodazole-insensitive microtubules </p>

<p>in living cells </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence analysis of fixed echinoderm zygotes (Foe 
and von Dassow, 2008) revealed a nocodazole-insensitive popu-
lation of astral microtubules that arises at anaphase onset and that 
has a clear equatorial bias before furrowing. However, EMTB-3G 
detects apparently stable microtubules throughout the cortex 
in later embryos (eight-cell and beyond). We tested whether 
these are nocodazole insensitive by perfusing eight-cell and older 
EMTB-3G-expressing embryos with nocodazole. Consistent 
with previous results, 10-20-µM nocodazole treatment during 
anaphase prompted rapid loss of most astral microtubules but left 
a substantial fraction extending from each spindle pole (Fig. 3 
and Video 3). However, in contrast to the results obtained with </p>

<p>delivery (Mandato et al., 2000; Canman et al., 2003; Shannon 
et al., 2005; Strickland et al., 2005b; Foe and von Dassow, 
2008; Odell and Foe, 2008; Vale et al., 2009). These cannot be 
dismissed as model system-dependent variation, as different 
studies in the same system have reached opposite conclusions 
(see Dechant and Glotzer, 2003 vs. Motegi et al., 2006 vs. 
Verbrugghe and White, 2007). 
Newer findings change the details but not the notion 
that microtubules deliver the cytokinetic signal. Specifically, 
recent work demonstrates at least two experimentally sepa-
rable cytokinetic signals: one from the spindle midzone and 
one from the asters (Bringmann and Hyman, 2005; Werner 
et al., 2007; Baruni et al., 2008; von Dassow, 2009). Also, it is 
now clear that activation of the small GTPase Rho at the cell 
equator is a conserved feature of animal cytokinesis (Bement 
et al., 2005), and this event is attributed to the centralspin-
dlin complex, which consists of the kinesin MKLP1 and 
MgcRacGAP, working with Ect2, a Rho GEF (Yüce et al., 
2005; Zhao and Fang, 2005; Kamijo et al., 2006; Nishimura 
and Yonemura, 2006). A popular scenario posits that MKLP 
transports centralspindlin along microtubules to the equato-
rial cortex, where it meets and activates Ect2, locally activat-
ing Rho (Saint and Somers, 2003; Somers and Saint, 2003; 
D'Avino et al., 2006). Delivery of a positive signal to the 
equator may be complemented by provision of a negative 
signal by dynamic microtubules that contact the cortex else-
where (Werner et al., 2007; Chen et al., 2008; Murthy and 
Wadsworth, 2008; Foe and von Dassow, 2008). 
Surprisingly, however, no direct proof has ever been 
offered that microtubules must contact the cortex for transmis-
sion of the cytokinetic signal. This is partly because it is hard 
to disrupt microtubules before anaphase onset without induc-
ing metaphase arrest. Also, in large cells where signal transport 
might be most important, the means to clearly image micro-
tubules extending to the cell surface have been lacking. 
Here, we demonstrate the means to image and manipu-
late microtubules in living embryos of echinoderms and 
amphibians. We find that a functional cytokinetic appara-
tus forms and closes in the proper position in the complete 
absence of contact or even approach of astral microtubules 
with the cortex in very large, round cells. We also find that 
pairs of asters without an intervening spindle can specify a 
functional cytokinetic apparatus only when they are separated 
sufficiently from each other. We show that the centrosomes 
or asters confine the signal or its effect. Based on these and 
other results, we propose that distinct subsets of the mitotic 
apparatus collaborate to make specification of the cytokinetic 
apparatus both accurate and precise. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Spatial organization and behavior of live </p>

<p>microtubules during embryonic cytokinesis </p>

<p>To image microtubules in living urchin or Xenopus laevis 
embryos, we used three tandem GFPs fused to the ensconsin 
microtubule-binding domain (EMTB-3G; Faire et al., 1999). 
This probe, unlike fluorophore-conjugated or GFP-tubulin, </p>

<p> 
Action at a distance • von Dassow et al. </p>

<p>In the course of these experiments, we noticed that noco-
dazole treatment failed to prevent cytokinesis even when it pre-
vented microtubules from approaching the cortex, either from 
the spindle midzone or the asters (Fig. 3 and Video 3). Every </p>

<p>zygotes, in these smaller cells, there was no obvious directional 
bias of nocodazole-insensitive microtubules toward the equator 
before furrowing (Fig. 3), which indicates that these stable micro-
tubules cannot solely explain cytokinetic pattern formation. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Microtubules in live urchin embryos. All panels show single confocal sections. (A and A) 16-cell purple urchin embryo; A shows a 2× enlarged 
view of the lower cell (indicated by white mark in A). Microtubules approach the cortex everywhere before anaphase onset (1 min, 30 s); during ana-
phase, just before furrowing, many astral microtubules penetrate both polar and equatorial cortex (arrowheads in A). (B) Vegetal view, 28-cell sand dollar 
embryo; i-vi are 2× enlarged views as indicated. Astral microtubules frequently cross spindle midplane before and during anaphase (i-iii), approach within 
1 µm of the equatorial surface before furrowing (ii-iv), and curve inward as the furrow ingresses (v and vi). Arrowheads point to exemplars. (C) Eight-cell 
sand dollar embryo; single microtubules grow as far as the cell surface in all directions (equatorially in the 01:56 frame, tropically in the 01:08 frame, 
and toward the pole in the 03:32 frame). Astral microtubules reach the polar cortex most densely in anaphase (08:48) but also reach the equator before 
furrowing (frame 10:48). (C) Enlargement of successive frames for microtubules indicated by arrowheads in C (intensities squared to enhance contrast). 
Video 1 corresponds to A-C. Time is indicated in minutes:seconds. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 187 • NUMBER 6 • 2009 </p>

<p>
Figure 2. The furrow forms in a microtubule-poor region. (A) Single superficial confocal sections of a 16-cell sand dollar embryo, slightly compressed 
(EMTB-3G). (02:00) All three cells in metaphase; few microtubule ends are visible. (07:00) Left cell begins cleavage, right cell is still in metaphase, and 
the top cell has likely entered anaphase. (13:00) Right cell begins to cleave; fewer microtubules approach the cell surface (bright dots) in the incipient 
furrow than outside it. (A) "Kymocubes" made by 3D rendering sequence in A; white lines denote frames in A. The whole of each of three cells is shown </p>

<p> 
Action at a distance • von Dassow et al. </p>

<p>the modestly separated chromosomes even when the closest 
detectable approach by a spindle microtubule to the cell sur-
face was &gt;10 µm (Fig. 4 C and Fig. S4 B). Only failure to enter 
anaphase prevented furrowing. In a minority of cells, the 
ingressing furrow initially failed to separate the chromosome 
sets. However, in many of these, the cell corrected this error 
as the constricting furrow approached the spindle, either by 
the spindle being moved back and forth until it matched the 
furrow position, or by shifting the furrow toward the spindle 
midzone (not depicted). 
These results, which were obtained by imaging a single 
medial optical plane, were confirmed by complete z series 
or surface views of live TSA-treated cells (not depicted). To 
complement live imaging, we treated embryos with TSA, 
then fixed and stained for tubulin and serine-19 phosphory-
lated myosin light chain (phospho-myosin; a marker for 
active myosin-2 and the cytokinetic apparatus). 3D recon-
structions of these embryos showed clearly that a func-
tional cytokinetic apparatus, replete with active myosin-2, 
forms at the equator of TSA-treated cells in the complete 
absence of approach of spindle microtubules to the cortex 
(Fig. 5), which eliminates the possibility that the apparent 
lack of astral microtubules seen by live cell imaging reflects 
either deficiencies in the EMTB-3G probe or the imaging 
regimen. Finally, the possibility that the cytokinetic pattern 
formed long before TSA took effect was ruled out by cases in 
which TSA was applied before metaphase; the cell depicted in 
Fig. S4 B, for example, never achieved long astral microtubules 
in this cell cycle. We find it impossible to escape the conclu-
sion that abolishing contact between astral microtubules and 
the cell cortex simply does not prevent the cell from assem-
bling a normally positioned, functional cytokinetic apparatus. </p>

<p>Astral microtubules focus the </p>

<p>cytokinetic pattern </p>

<p>Although TSA-treated cells established accurate cytokinetic 
furrows, those furrows were abnormally broad, as was the 
distribution of active myosin-2 (e.g., Fig. S4 B and Fig. 5). 
We therefore assessed cytokinetic pattern formation using 
GFP-rGBD, alone or in combination with 3C-EMTB. The 
Rho zone was harder to detect in TSA-treated cells, but was 
definitely present (Fig. 6, C and D), which confirmed that 
cells can confine Rho activation to the equator without help 
from asters. TSA-treated cells, like normal cells, exhibited 
ubiquitous low-level cortical Rho activity that declined after 
anaphase onset (Fig. 6 D). However, the Rho zone was much 
wider than normal in TSA-treated cells (Fig. 6 A). Measurement </p>

<p>cell that entered anaphase (as deduced from emergence of 
a dark gap between spindle halves), regardless of the extent 
of the surviving aster, established a well-placed furrow. This 
is epitomized by Fig. 3 B: cytokinesis occurred in one cell 
that entered anaphase just when nocodazole was added (and 
completely lacked long astral microtubules) but not in three 
metaphase-arrested cells. </p>

<p>Microtubule-independent delivery of the </p>

<p>cytokinetic signal </p>

<p>The nocodazole results imply that cytokinetic signals can 
reach the cortex without the help of microtubules extending 
from the spindle to the cortex. But because nocodazole must 
be applied after anaphase onset to avoid metaphase arrest, 
it might be that signaling occurred in the narrow window 
before nocodazole took effect. Also, although nocodazole 
greatly shortened microtubules extending from the spindle 
to the cell surface, perhaps stable microtubules were still 
close enough to mediate equatorial delivery. To inhibit astral 
microtubule growth without cell cycle arrest, we therefore 
treated embryos with trichostatin A (TSA), an inhibitor 
of HDAC6 (a tubulin deacetylase) that selectively disrupts 
dynamic microtubules in mammalian cells (Matsuyama et al., 
2002). Perfusion of urchin embryos with TSA in prophase or 
metaphase caused rapid collapse of the aster and usually a 
delay, but not an arrest, in metaphase (Fig. 4; Videos 4 and 5; 
and Figs. S3 and S4). 
In metaphase, TSA caused the entire aster to collapse 
within minutes (Figs. 4, S3 B, and S4 A); as with nocodazole, 
anaphase cells retained a subset of stable astral microtu-
bules (Fig. S3 B). The spindle itself often became much 
shorter in TSA-treated cells, and sometimes became deranged 
during a prolonged metaphase (e.g., Fig. S4 B). Even so, 
most TSA-treated cells underwent anaphase, as revealed by a 
widening gap in the midzone and emergence of nuclear vesi-
cles near spindle poles (Fig. 4, A and C), or by coexpressing 
EMTB-3G and mCherry-histone H2B (mC-H2B; Figs. 4 B 
and S3 B). Although short microtubules often regrew from 
centrosomes in anaphase, and isolated microtubules formed 
in the cytoplasm (e.g., Fig. 4 C), extension of microtubules 
from either the spindle midzone or the poles to the cortex was 
not detected. 
Astonishingly, the vast majority of TSA-treated cells 
completed cytokinesis, despite the near-total absence of 
astral microtubules (Fig. 4, Videos 4 and 5, and Figs. S3 B 
and S4). Moreover, cytokinesis occurred with unexpected 
fidelity; the furrow formed and closed equatorially between </p>

<p>in the kymocube. Bright dots (open arrowheads in A-C) indicate brief cortical visits by microtubule ends; these predominate in metaphase. Vertical streaks 
(closed arrowheads in A-C) indicate kinematically stable microtubule ends, which appear before furrowing, and are scarce in the equatorial zone. 
(B) Kymograph of 5-µm medial strip (indicated by box) 1 µm beneath the surface of a slightly flattened eight-cell sand dollar embryo. The arrow indicates 
furrow initiation time; vertical streaks above this point indicate stable microtubules at the cortex before furrowing. These are notably fewer in the equator. 
(C) Surface rendering of single medial sections of uncompressed sand dollar blastomeres, each covering anaphase through cytokinesis. Long streaks (stable 
microtubules at the cell surface) are evident well before furrowing. Broad smears appear during furrowing, notably in the area around the crotch; these 
reflect microtubules growing along the cortex (see also A and B). (D) Single superficial sections from a 6.5-h X. laevis embryo mosaically expressing GFP-
rGBD (red) and 3C-EMTB (cyan). Surface microtubules disappear in metaphase, then reappear (16:52) 90 s before active Rho appears in the equator 
(18:28). Microtubules are largely absent from a &gt;20-µm-wide band inhabited by the Rho zone; arrows indicate equatorial microtubules that disappear 
during furrowing. Time is indicated in minutes:seconds. </p>



<p>JCB • VOLUME 187 • NUMBER 6 • 2009 </p>

<p>
of Rho zone width by curve fitting (see Materials and methods) 
showed that Rho activity in TSA-treated cells covered a lati-
tude range along the cell surface on average twice as wide as 
in controls from the same batch of eggs (Fig. 6 B; 0.28 ± 0.14 
of the pole-to-pole cell diameter in TSA-treated cells [n = 23] </p>

<p>Figure 3. Nocodazole-insensitive microtubules exhibit no orientation bias in urchin blastomeres. (A-C) Single sections, all expressing EMTB-3G; 
(A-C) 2× enlarged views of cells indicated by the white marks in A-C. (A) Eight-cell purple urchin embryo; 20 µM nocodazole was added at time 00:00. 
Within 2 min, most astral microtubules disassembled; remaining microtubules are randomly oriented and most end well short of the cortex. Even so, fur-
rowing is accurate and timely. Arrowheads indicate surviving nonequatorial astral microtubules. (B) 16-cell purple urchin embryo; 10 µM nocodazole was 
added at time 00:00. The top left cell entered anaphase around time 0; none of the other cells in view left metaphase nor furrowed. This one cell cleaved 
despite nearly complete absence of astral microtubules, and the furrow crossed the spindle midzone. (C) 16-cell sand dollar embryo; 10 µM nocodazole 
was added at time 00:00, at which time three of four macromeres have entered anaphase; the east cell enters anaphase shortly thereafter (03:00). In all 
cells, numerous astral microtubules, pointing in all directions, persist &gt;5 min after nocodazole addition (arrowheads). Stable microtubules may approach 
the cortex in west and south cells (03:00), but none can be seen to do so in north and east cells; all commence furrowing at a normal time and complete 
cytokinesis. Note that in all cases, stable microtubules become brighter because EMTB-3G liberated by disassembly becomes available for binding. 
Video 3 includes A-C. Time is indicated in minutes:seconds. </p>

<p>vs. 0.14 ± 0.06 in controls [n = 29]; P &lt; 0.0002). Notably, the 
intensity above background integrated across the entire Rho 
zone was not significantly less than normal in TSA-treated 
cells; thus, Rho activity is diluted, not diminished, by the 
absence of asters. </p>

<p>837 
Action at a distance • von Dassow et al. </p>

<p>Video 6). In all cases, regardless of cytokinetic behavior, astral 
microtubules penetrated the cortex everywhere (as in normal 
cells) during anaphase and telophase, and in no case did we 
detect anything like a spindle between two centrosomes in an 
anucleate cytoplast. 
The observed behavioral spectrum might suggest that as-
ters alone can induce a furrow but that induction isn't robust 
under these conditions. However, we noticed that anucleate 
cytoplasts that manifest deeply ingressing furrows have a greater 
separation between adjacent asters (Fig. 7, A vs. B). This is 
apparent even within a single case: in Fig. 7 C, deeply in-
gressing furrows develop between well-separated asters, and 
only shallow furrows develop between closer pairs. This cor-
relation was quantified by comparing the distance between 
centrosomes versus the distance from the surface, versus the 
extent of furrowing (see Materials and methods). As shown 
in Fig. 7 E, if the distance between centrosomes exceeded </p>

<p>Asters alone can only induce a furrow if </p>

<p>they are far enough apart </p>

<p>The results of TSA treatment show that cells can accurately 
position the cytokinetic apparatus without the astral micro-
tubule array. Yet numerous classical results identified the 
juxtaposition of two asters as the sufficient condition for fur-
row induction (e.g., Rappaport 1961). To resolve this contra-
diction, we created EMTB-3G-expressing cell fragments that 
contain centrosomes but lack nuclei (see Materials and meth-
ods). These anucleate cytoplasts conduct a normal centro-
some cycle: duplication and separation, and cyclic alternation 
between a compact, dense, and dynamic aster (metaphase) 
and a loose aster of long, stable microtubules (interphase). 
Anucleate cytoplasts with two or more centrosomes exhibited 
a full spectrum of cytokinetic behaviors: some showed no sign 
of cleavage; some cleaved completely; and in some, furrows 
ingressed some distance before regressing (Fig. 7, A-C; and </p>

<p>Figure 4. Cleavage occurs despite diminution of the aster and cortical microtubules by TSA. All panels are single confocal sections. (A) 16-cell purple 
urchin embryo (EMTB-3G), treated with 20 µM TSA at time 00:00. A shows a 2× enlarged view of the indicated cell (white mark in A). Within minutes of 
TSA addition in metaphase, asters were reduced to nearly nothing (04:00). Despite reduction in spindle length, cells enter anaphase (07:20) and complete 
cytokinesis (11:20-16:10). No microtubules connecting the mitotic apparatus to the cortex are visible (see Video 4). (B) 16-cell purple urchin embryo 
(cyan, EMTB-3G; yellow, mC-H2B); 15 µM TSA was added at time 00:00. After a delay in metaphase, five of six cells in focus initiate cytokinesis. B shows 
a 2× enlarged view of the indicated cell (white mark in B). (C) One cell within a 16-cell sand dollar embryo (EMTB-3G), treated with 25 µM TSA 10 min 
before time 00:00. Although the aster regrows slightly, the cortex is 20 µm away from the nearest spindle microtubule ends; nevertheless, cytokinesis 
completes accurately (see Video 4). Arrowheads in A and C indicate metaphase plate before (04:00 and 04:48), and the gap after (07:20 and 10:48), 
anaphase onset. Time is indicated in minutes:seconds. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 187 • NUMBER 6 • 2009 </p>

<p>
Figure 5. Myosin occupies a wider-than-normal zone in asterless cells. Cyan, anti-tubulin; yellow, Hoechst; magenta, anti-phospho-myosin. (A and B) Un-
treated 16-cell sand dollar embryos. Projection of 24 0.5-µm sections, vegetal view (A); and 19 0.6-µm sections, side view (B). (C and D) 16-cell sand dollar 
embryos fixed 10 min after adding 25 µM TSA. (C) A projection of 18 0.5-µm sections through the middle portion of the macromeres. (D) A projection of 
28 0.5-µm sections through the middle portion of the mesomeres. A-D are from the same batch fixed at the same time. Normally, phospho-myosin is virtually 
absent outside of 10 µm furrow zone. In TSA-treated cells, phosphomyosin is not as thoroughly excluded from the poles but is still enriched equatorially, 
with definite zones around ingressing furrows (brackets in D), even though no spindle microtubules approach the cortex. A-D are 2× enlarged views of 
the cells indicated by the white marks in A-D. </p>

<p>the distance to the cell surface, furrows ingressed deeply. 
If the two distances were roughly equal, only shallow fur-
rows developed. If centrosomes were substantially closer </p>

<p>than the distance to the surface, no furrow developed. These 
differences were highly significant (in both comparisons, 
P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p> 
Action at a distance • von Dassow et al. </p>

<p>because something associated with centrosomes depletes or 
inactivates the signal in the cell interior. If the first hypothesis 
were correct, one would predict destruction of a single aster to 
broaden and strengthen the signal; if the second were correct, 
relatively little change in signal level is expected. Both hypoth-
eses predict that destroying a single aster should shift the signal 
away from the midzone, toward the ablated aster. A third 
hypothesis is that asters or centrosomes generate positive sig-
nals that are summed at the equator, with or without synergistic 
signals from the midzone; in this case, destruction of a single 
aster should shift the signal away from the ablated aster, and the 
signal should be weakened. 
We tested these predictions by destroying centrosomes 
in sand dollar blastomeres using a UV laser (see Materials 
and methods). Most singly ablated cells clearly underwent </p>

<p>Asters spatially confine the </p>

<p>cytokinetic signal </p>

<p>The behavior of anucleate cytoplasts confirms that asters, or the 
centrosomes they grow from, somehow provide enough posi-
tional information to direct furrowing. Meanwhile, nocodazole 
and TSA treatment show that the astral microtubules need not 
reach the cortex for the cell to accurately identify the appropri-
ate furrow site, although the cytokinetic apparatus is more 
broadly specified in the absence of asters. These results could 
be reconciled if the central spindle localizes a positive signal, 
and the astral microtubules or centrosomes suppress cortical 
contractility outside the equator, thereby sharpening this signal 
at the cortex. A second hypothesis is that a positive signal from 
the spindle midzone is spatially confined by the asters or centro-
somes, perhaps by interacting with astral microtubules or </p>

<p>Figure 6. Active Rho occupies a wider-than-normal zone in asterless cells. (A) GFP-rGBD at similar stages of furrowing in control (left) and TSA-treated 
(right) purple urchin embryos; single confocal sections. Rho zones are broader and fainter in TSA-treated cells compared with untreated siblings, but zones 
are centered equatorially and match furrows. Plots show representative fits between intensity data (red) and a fit curve (blue) that measures zone width 
along the cell outline (see Materials and methods). (B) Measured zone widths normalized by pole-to-pole cell length, plotted against integrated intensity, 
minus baseline, within the curve fit as shown in A, expressed as a fraction of baseline. (C) Normal Rho zones, eight-cell purple urchin embryo (red, GFP-
rGBD; cyan, 3C-EMTB). (D) Eight-cell purple urchin embryo (same probes as C) treated with 20 µM TSA at time 00:00. Uniform cortical Rho activity during 
metaphase (00:00) disappears as cells enter anaphase, as in normal cells (Bement et al., 2005). Rho zones (brackets) are barely detectable above back-
ground, yet furrows develop and complete with minor delay (compare times in C), which implies that cells normally express more equatorial Rho activity 
than they require. Time is indicated in minutes:seconds. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 187 • NUMBER 6 • 2009 </p>

<p>
often partitioning both chromosome sets into the daughter 
cell with an intact centrosome. In most singly ablated cells, 
furrowing completed without significant attempts by the cell 
to correct furrow position; this contrasts with the results of 
physical spindle displacement (Bement et al., 2005) or TSA 
treatment (this paper). 
We also conducted ablations in cells coexpressing 
GFP-rGBD with 3C-EMTB. Because of numerous experimental 
factors (see Materials and methods), double labeling was often 
faint. Even so, some crucial observations emerged: first, Rho 
zones appeared even in cells with extreme ablations; second, </p>

<p>anaphase (e.g., Fig. 8 A), as confirmed by conducting abla-
tions in cells coexpressing EMTB-3G and mC-H2B (Fig. S5 B 
and Video 8). Ablation of a single centrosome in metaphase 
consistently shifted furrows from the spindle midzone toward 
the ablated pole (Fig. 8, Video 7, and Fig. S5). If the aster 
regrew substantially, or if the ablation took place in anaphase, 
no displacement of the furrow resulted (see Fig. S5 C). Partial 
ablations, in which some microtubules regrew from the irra-
diated pole, led to modest displacement. Complete ablations 
caused cells to establish furrows that closed near (Fig. 8, A, 
B, and D) or beyond (Fig. S5, A and C) the ablated aster, </p>

<p>Figure 7. Asters alone induce furrows only if they are far enough apart. (A-C) Single-plane sequences of anucleate, centrosome-containing cytoplasts 
(sand dollars). (A) Anucleate cytoplast with four centrosomes, two in focus. In normal cells this size, furrowing would begin between 03:00 and 07:00, 
but no furrow occurs even 20 min later. Centrosomes are closer than the distance to the equator. (B) Anucleate cytoplast with two centrosomes, farther 
apart than the distance to the equator. A furrow initiates at the expected time and place, and proceeds to completion. (C) An anucleate cytoplast with four 
centrosomes variously spaced. A deeply ingressing furrow bisects the well-spaced centrosomes; shallow furrows form over closely spaced centrosomes. 
Time is indicated in minutes:seconds. (D) Long-term differential interference contrast sequence of two halves of a bisected sand dollar zygote. The film 
began shortly after the unbisected zygote would have divided; because each half has only one centrosome, neither divided at first mitosis. All subsequent 
divisions proceeded normally in the nucleated half (right), creating a perfect blastula. The anucleate half cleaved abortively in its first attempt. After that, 
four centrosomes (dots in the 1:51:40 frame) were variously spaced. The second attempt made deep furrows between the widely separated asters, but none 
between the closely spaced pair. Subsequent divisions were variously successful. Time is indicated in hours:minutes:seconds. (E) Aster separation strongly 
correlates to the furrow extent. See Materials and methods for measurement. Video 6 corresponds to A-C. </p>

<p> 
Action at a distance • von Dassow et al. </p>

<p>We also ablated both centrosomes, which was difficult 
given the narrow time window and the likelihood of missing 
one or both poles. In several instances, we accomplished this 
operation with minimal aster regrowth and without preventing 
anaphase (Fig. 8, C and D; and Fig. S5 B). In some doubly ab-
lated cells that executed anaphase, cleavage failed, and cells ex-
hibited only incoherent surface ruffling. Other doubly ablated 
cells initiated broad, shallow furrows, approximately over the 
midzone (Fig. 8 C). Many of these completed cytokinesis, often 
(not always) partitioning daughter chromosomes to daughter 
cells (compare two doubly ablated cells in Fig. S5 B). </p>

<p>these zones were not notably different (broader, brighter, or 
dimmer) than zones in normal cells (Fig. 8 B and Video 9); and 
third, rather than appearing asymmetrically (as one would ex-
pect if asters only inhibited Rho activation), zones were cen-
tered on the eventual furrow site. Importantly, we did not find 
more Rho activity than normal on the polar cortex near ablated 
centrosomes, which implies that asters or centrosomes shape 
the distribution of the cytokinetic signal rather than only inhib-
iting it; if the latter were true, we would expect Rho activation 
to take place in a normal spatial relation to the intact centro-
some instead of shifting distally, as we observed. </p>

<p>Figure 8. Centrosome ablation displaces furrows. (A-D) Single-plane recordings of sand dollar embryos expressing EMTB-3G alone (A) or GFP-rGBD (red) 
and 3C-EMTB (cyan; B-D); time is shown in minutes:seconds after last irradiation. Arrows, ablation sites; dotted lines, furrow plane. (A) Single-pole ablation 
in a moderately large cell. Few astral microtubules remain; furrowing occurs over the spindle end rather than the midzone (see Video 7). (B) Two single-pole 
ablations. Furrows form over and close upon the ablated end. In the top cell, chromosomes are partitioned by the furrow; in the bottom cell, they are not. 
Rho activity zones in ablated cells are similar to normal cells but shifted. (C) Double-pole ablation in a large cell. A broad furrow with barely detectable 
Rho activity forms above the spindle midplane and closes between spindle halves. (D) A normal cell (left), singly ablated cell (top), and doubly ablated cell 
(right). The furrow in the doubly ablated cell is broad, with dilute Rho activity, but closes accurately. The furrow in the singly ablated cell is shifted away 
from the midplane. (E) Distances (percentage of cell length) between spindle midplane and furrow plane in control, double-, and single-ablated cells (dots) 
superimposed upon normal curves computed from mean and standard deviation. Video 9 corresponds to B-D. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 187 • NUMBER 6 • 2009 </p>

<p>
myosin-2 network by displaced asters in Caenorhabditis 
elegans embryos (Werner et al., 2007). However, most of 
these studies, including ours, posit that this requires direct ac-
tion of microtubules at the cortex, a presumption challenged 
by our results. 
Asters could limit the cytokinetic cue either by inhibiting 
that signal locally-by providing an antagonist, by sequestra-
tion, or by degradation-or by spatially confining the signal to 
the equatorial region (e.g., through plus-end-directed transport 
of the signal or its generators away from the centrosomes). Sim-
ple inhibition would predict that the Rho zone would be broader 
and brighter after destruction of one or both asters, in contrast to 
what we observed. Instead, the Rho zone is diluted by reduction 
of the asters with TSA, and ablation of a single centrosome 
shifts the Rho zone away from the remaining aster without in-
creasing the intensity or breadth. This argues that asters spa-
tially confine the signal, thus enhancing it locally by preventing 
it from spreading away from the equator. 
Our third finding is that although paired asters without 
a midzone can direct cytokinetic apparatus induction as previ-
ously described (Rappaport, 1961), they can do so only under 
limited geometrical conditions. The use of a live microtubule 
label reveals unambiguously and for the first time that micro-
tubules from paired asters penetrate the cortex extensively, re-
gardless of whether a furrow forms, and paired asters induce 
furrows only if there is a microtubule-poor corridor between 
them. This further argues that the centrosomes or asters limit, 
rather than create, the cytokinetic signal, as otherwise, closely 
separated asters would be more potent furrow inducers than dis-
tant ones. Anucleate cytoplasts lack chromosomes or midzone 
but likely retain the molecular species that normally generate 
the cytokinetic signal. Therefore, if the asters spatially confine 
the signal rather than simply inhibiting or promoting it, then 
perhaps juxtaposed asters, in anucleate cytoplasts or toroidal 
cells, elicit furrowing by concentrating enough of the partici-
pants between them. 
If the cytokinetic signal can pattern the cortex without the 
aid of microtubules, how does it get there? Actin can support 
myosin-powered vectorial transport, but F-actin is dispensable 
for cytokinetic apparatus specification (Straight et al., 2003; 
Bement et al., 2005; Foe and von Dassow, 2008). Intermediate 
filaments and membrane systems permeate the cell but are in-
herently nonpolar, so it is hard to imagine how they could con-
duct signals from spindle to cortex. We are led to hypothesize 
that the primary signal for cytokinesis reaches the cell surface 
from the spindle by diffusion. 
Diffusion seems a poor means to accurately deliver a sig-
nal from an interior structure to the cell periphery across large 
distances, but a diffusible cue arising from the cell interior could 
be sharpened by at least three nonexclusive mechanisms. First, 
if the signal is inactivated or sequestered at centrosomes or by 
astral microtubules (even if they do not reach the cortex), lat-
eral spreading would be suppressed. Centrosomal inactivation 
could occur by microtubule-independent means as described 
previously for polarization in C. elegans embryos (Cowan and 
Hyman, 2004). Sequestration could result from microtubule 
binding by MKLP1 or other candidate signaling agents. </p>

<p>This is consistent with results from TSA treatment, col-
lectively implying that asters confer accuracy and precision 
to the cytokinetic signaling mechanism. To quantify this we 
scored all centrosome-ablated, EMTB-expressing cells that 
made credible attempts at cleavage into three categories: dou-
ble ablations, partial single-pole ablations, and total single-
pole ablations. In each, and in controls from the same films, 
we measured the concurrence of furrow plane and spindle 
midzone, normalized by cell diameter. The results, super-
imposed upon normal curves computed from mean and vari-
ance in each category (Fig. 8 E), show that doubly ablated cells 
are less precise than controls but accurate in aggregate, whereas 
singly ablated cells are precisely inaccurate. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Our most surprising finding is that astral microtubules are not 
needed to transmit the cytokinetic signal, even in large round 
cells where the nearest spindle microtubule is far from the cell 
surface. Although it could be argued that our experimental ap-
proaches account for this result, the EMTB probes reveal both 
dynamic and stable microtubules, and precisely colocalize with 
all astral and cortical microtubules revealed by anti-tubulin in 
fixed samples. The cortical distribution of microtubules seen in 
living cells with EMTB parallels that detected by careful EM 
analysis of urchin zygotes (Asnes and Schroeder, 1979). Thus, 
if there is some significant cortical microtubule population not 
detected by EMTB-based probes, it is also undetectable by any 
other means currently available. Moreover, the same results are 
obtained in fixed samples never microinjected with EMTB nor 
subjected to live imaging, and the TSA results are supported by 
those obtained with nocodazole. Collectively, these results com-
pel the conclusion that neither astral microtubules extending from 
centrosomes to regions outside the equator, astral microtubules 
extending from centrosomes to the equator, nor microtubules ex-
tending from the midzone to the equator are necessary for deliv-
ery of the cytokinetic signal from the spindle to the cortex. 
The second finding is that centrosomes, or the asters that 
grow from them, limit the spatial extent of the cytokinetic 
signal. This idea is not new, but the approach-centrosome 
ablation in urchin blastomeres-complements those used in 
other studies and affirms this principle in urchin embryos. 
The latter point is critical: it has been vigorously argued, 
based on micromanipulation studies of urchin zygotes, that 
asters provide a positive signal that is summed at the equator 
(for reviews see Rappaport, 1996; Burgess and Chang, 2005). 
If this were true, ablation of a single centrosome should shift cyto-
kinetic apparatus assembly away from the ablated centrosome. 
In fact, exactly the opposite happens: the cytokinetic appara-
tus is displaced toward the ablated centrosome, often so far 
that all chromosomes end up in one daughter cell. An inhibi-
tory signal from the asters is consistent with studies show-
ing that myosin-powered cortical flow is directed away from 
microtubule-organizing centers (Hird and White, 1993; Benink 
et al., 2000; Chen et al., 2008), formation of furrows away from 
asters during cytokinesis in monopolar cells (Canman et al., 
2003; Hu et al., 2008), and local symmetry breaking of a cortical </p>

<p> 
Action at a distance • von Dassow et al. </p>

<p>than the egg diameter. To prevent stripped eggs from sticking to glass, cul-
ture vessels were coated with 1% BSA in FSW before adding eggs. For in-
jection, stripped sand dollar eggs were arranged in a row in an uncoated 
coverslip-bottom dish that had been cleaned with 95% ethanol. Clean 
glass is sticky enough to enable microinjection but allow release of injected 
embryos with gentle swirling. 
Both species of urchin eggs were injected with 0.5-2% of the cell 
volume (a sand dollar egg is 1 nl; a purple urchin egg is 0.3 nl) using 
needles made from 1 mm OD filament-containing capillaries on a micro-
pipette puller (P-97; Sutter Instrument Co.). Injections were performed on an 
inverted microscope (TS100; Nikon) equipped with a cooling stage (Dagan 
Corporation) maintained at 12°C, using a hanging-joystick oil hydraulic 
micromanipulator (Narishige) and Picospritzer III (Parker Hannifin Corp.). 
Needle concentration of RNA was 1 ng/nl or less for GFP-rGBD or mC-H2B, 
and &lt;0.1 ng/nl for EMTB-3G and 3C-EMTB. We found that injection of 
higher levels of EMTB-based probes caused increasingly severe early defects, 
including mitotic spindle bifurcation, due apparently to a delay in metaphase 
during which duplicated centrosomes prematurely separate or, at the highest 
levels, complete cell cycle arrest (Fig. S1 A). Notably, for both purple urchins 
and sand dollars, normal embryos that develop from zygotes injected with 
0.05-0.1 ng/nl EMTB-3G mRNA are many times brighter by the 32-cell 
stage than are the usually defective four-and eight-cell embryos that result 
from injection of higher levels. We therefore surmise that either the earliest 
cell divisions are especially sensitive to the introduction of an exogenous 
microtubule-binding moiety or that rapid expression of this probe cannot be 
tolerated (perhaps because some slow posttranslational modification renders 
it less harmful). Therefore, all results reported here on purple urchins and 
sand dollars come from eight-cell embryos and beyond, injected with a dose 
of mRNA at which mitotic defects were rare. 
X. laevis embryos were obtained and injected as described previ-
ously (Bement et al., 2005). Each blastomere of the two-cell embryo was 
injected with 5 nl of either EMTB-3G mRNA alone (0.01-0.04 ng/nl) or 
5 nl of a mixture of 3C-EMTB and GFP-rGBD at final needle concentrations 
of 0.04 and 0.2 ng/nl, respectively. </p>

<p>Constructs and mRNA synthesis 
All constructs were assembled in pCS2 modified to contain three EGFP at 
the putative carboxy terminus, or one or three mCherry at the amino ter-
minus. mRNA was synthesized from linearized plasmids using the SP6 
mMessage mMachine kit (Applied Biosystems), according to the manu-
facturer's instructions. </p>

<p>Live imaging and drug perfusion 
Sand dollar or purple urchin embryos were placed on a clean glass slide in 
a 10-20 µl drop of FSW, between two ridges of high vacuum grease (Dow 
Corning) spaced 1 cm apart. A coverslip was applied, resting on the 
grease ridges, and then pressed down until eggs or embryos were trapped 
by slight-to-moderate compression. With some batches of eggs, we found it 
necessary to coat slides and coverslips by rinsing with 1% BSA in FSW to 
prevent cells from sticking too tightly to the glass and thus deforming them-
selves during cytokinesis. These chambers remained open on both ends, 
allowing perfusion of solutions by addition of large drop (40-50 µl) of FSW 
containing either nocodazole or TSA and up to 0.1% DMSO. 
Purple urchin and sand dollar embryos were imaged with a laser 
scanning confocal microscope (Radiance 2000; Bio-Rad Laboratories) 
mounted on a compound microscope (E800; Nikon) using a 40× 1.3 NA 
Plan-Fluor oil lens. Room temperature was maintained at 14-17°C, which 
is tolerated well by both species. Some experiments were conducted on a 
spinning disc confocal microscope (CARV; BD) consisting of an inverted 
microscope (TE2000; Nikon) with a 60× 1.4 NA Plan-Apochromat oil lens 
and a 60× 1.2 NA Plan-Apochromat water lens, the CARV spinning disc 
head, and a camera (ORCA-ER; Hamamatsu), controlled by <rs id="software-0" type="software">MetaMorph</rs> 
software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">MDS Analytical Technologies</rs>). X. laevis embryos were imaged 
on a laser scanning confocal microscope (1024; Bio-Rad Laboratories) 
mounted on an Axiovert microscope (Carl Zeiss, Inc.) using a 63× 1.4 NA 
Plan-Apochromat oil objective. </p>

<p>Fixation and antibody staining 
Embryos were fixed by transferring 200-300 devitellinized sand dollar 
embryos in 100 µl of seawater into 900 µl of fixative at a final concentra-
tion of 2% formaldehyde (from 20% EM-grade stock), 0.2% glutaralde-
hyde, 0.2% Triton X-100, 100 mM Hepes, pH 7.0, 50 mM EGTA, 10 mM 
MgSO 4 , and 400 mM dextrose. After 1 h in fixative, embryos were rinsed 
3× in PBT and once in PBS, treated for 2 h with 0.1% sodium borohydride 
in PBS (to reduce autofluorescence), washed once in PBS, then blocked in </p>

<p>Second, the microtubule-poor corridor between asters 
could represent a path from the central spindle to the cell sur-
face in which the putative diffusible signal is relatively mobile. 
Thus, an initial bias established by the spindle in the cell center 
would be maintained out to the cell surface. If the few micro-
tubules penetrating this region tended to trap potential signal 
generators (e.g., chromosomal passenger proteins or central-
spindlin), such an effect would be enhanced. 
Third, an initially broad signal could be sharpened at or 
near the cortex. A microtubule-independent mechanism is indi-
cated by the fact that Rho zones eventually focus even when 
microtubules don't reach the cortex, whereas a microtubule-
dependent mechanism is suggested because partial inhibition of 
astral microtubule outgrowth enhances myosin recruitment (Foe 
and von Dassow, 2008). Anillin, which binds F-actin, Rho, and 
MgcRacGAP, is a good candidate for the first type of amplifier 
(e.g., D'Avino et al., 2008); transport of centralspindlin or chro-
mosomal passenger proteins along stable microtubules to the 
equator (Canman et al., 2003; D'Avino et al., 2006; Odell and 
Foe, 2008), and inhibition of Rho activation by microtubules 
outside the equator (Werner et al., 2007; Odell and Foe, 2008; 
Murthy and Wadsworth, 2008), are good candidates for the sec-
ond kind of amplifier. 
The core proposition-that the primary cytokinetic sig-
nal is focused to the equator by the combined action of the 
spindle midzone and the centrosomes-requires that future 
attention be directed toward parameters that are not yet well 
established, such as realistic diffusion and transport rates for 
large macromolecular complexes (like centralspindlin) over 
long distances within the cytoplasm, and on distinctions that 
few studies of cytokinesis have made, i.e., to differentiate the 
role of the aster from the role of other centrosome-associated 
cellular constituents. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Eggs and microinjections 
Gametes of the purple urchin Strongylocentrotus purpuratus and the sand 
dollar Dendraster excentricus were obtained either by intracoelomic injec-
tion of 0.56 M KCl or, for purple urchins, by alternately bouncing then 
shaking a gravid individual in the palm of the hand. Sperm were collected 
dry from the aboral surface and kept chilled until use. Purple urchin eggs 
were shed into a large volume of coarse-filtered seawater (FSW), rinsed 
twice in FSW, and stored settled at sea-table temperature (11-14°C) until 
use. Sand dollar eggs were shed into a large volume of FSW and left un-
rinsed at sea-table temperature until use. All echinoderm embryo culture 
likewise took place at sea-table temperature. 
Purple urchin eggs were prepared for injection by dejellying with two 
rapid washes in calcium/magnesium-free artificial seawater, then returned 
to FSW in dishes rendered nonsticky by washing with 1% BSA in FSW. De-
jellied eggs were used within 2 h. For injections, coverslip-bottom dishes 
were coated by washing 30 s in 1% protamine sulfate, rinsing 3× in distilled 
water, and air drying. Dejellied purple urchin eggs were arranged in a row 
in an injection dish filled with FSW + 1 mM 3-aminotriazole, which prevents 
hardening of the vitelline envelope, then fertilized by addition of several 
drops of a 1:10,000 dilution of dry sperm. Good batches of gametes yield 
nearly 100% fertilization within 5 min. For imaging, purple urchin embryos 
were removed from their still-soft vitelline envelopes using a hand-pulled 
mouth pipet, and transferred either directly to a microscope slide or into to a 
plastic Petri dish coated with 1% BSA in FSW. 
Sand dollar eggs were fertilized within their jelly by the addition of 
1-2 ml of sperm diluted 1:10,000 in FSW. 10-15 min after insemina-
tion, fertilized eggs were deprived of their jelly and vitelline envelopes by 
one passage in and out of a hand-pulled mouth pipet cut to slightly larger </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 187 • NUMBER 6 • 2009 </p>

<p>
furrow. The latter was measured by drawing a line from the inflection 
point of the curved cell surface during midfurrow ingression to the inflec-
tion point on the opposite side, and measuring the intersection with a line 
drawn along the spindle axis. Data were plotted and tested for signifi-
cance in <rs type="software">Mathematica</rs>. </p>

<p>Image processing 
3D projection of confocal z series (brightest-point projection only; no volume 
rendering) and measurements from time-lapse confocal data were conducted 
using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs>. Images were adjusted for white and black point; no gamma 
adjustment or nonlinear filtering was applied except as noted in the figure 
legends. Kymographs were created from time-lapse sequences using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> 
(Fig. S1 D and Fig. 2 B) or the freeware volume rendering program <rs id="software-8" type="software">Voxx</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-8" type="url">http://www.nephrology.iupui.edu/imaging/voxx</rs>/; Fig. 2, A and C). 
Fig. 2 A was made using a brightest-point projection, and Fig. 2 C by using 
 blending such that only the surface is visible. Pseudocoloring and figure 
layout were performed in ImageJ or Photoshop CS3 (Adobe). </p>

<p>Online supplemental material 
Fig. S1 demonstrates the viability of urchin embryos expressing EMTB-3G 
and documents cortical microtubule dynamics in X. laevis embryos. Fig. S2 
displays colocalization between EMTB-3G and anti-tubulin in fixed sand 
dollar embryos. Fig. S3 contrasts microtubule configuration in normal 
and TSA-treated urchin embryos expressing both EMTB-3G and mC-H2B. 
Fig. S4 presents extreme cases of TSA treatment. Fig. S5 presents ad-
ditional cases of centrosome-ablated cells. Video 1 shows EMTB-3G in 
normal purple urchin and sand dollar embryos. Video 2 corresponds to 
Fig. S1 D: superficial view of EMTB-3G in normal X. laevis blastomere. 
Video 3 shows nocodazole-treated purple urchin and sand dollar embryos 
expressing EMTB-3G. Video 4 shows TSA-treated purple urchin and sand 
dollar embryos expressing EMTB-3G. Video 5 shows untreated and TSA-
treated purple urchin embryos expressing EMTB-3G and mC-H2B. Video 6 
shows anucleate sand dollar cytoplasts expressing EMTB-3G. Video 7 
shows sand dollar blastomeres expressing EMTB-3G, in which a single 
centrosome was ablated in metaphase. Video 8 shows sand dollar embryo 
expressing EMTB-3G and mC-H2B, in which two cells suffered ablation of 
both centrosomes in metaphase, and two cells experienced ablation of a 
single pole. Video 9 shows centrosome-ablated sand dollar blastomeres 
expressing GFP-rGBD and 3C-EMTB. Online supplemental material is avail-
able at http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200907090/DC1. </p>

<p>This paper was supported by National Institutes of Health grant GM066050 
to G.M. Odell and grant GM052932 to W.M. Bement, National Science 
Foundation grant MCB-0917887 to G. von Dassow, and a Michael Guyer 
Fellowship to K. J.C. Verbrugghe. </p>

<p>Submitted: 16 July 2009 
Accepted: 16 November 2009 </p>



<p>Analysis of Rho zone width 
As described previously (Bement et al., 2005), single frames from equivalent 
stages of furrow ingression were selected from sequences at medial planes 
within cells expressing GFP-rGBD alone or with 3C-EMTB. A freehand line 
selection was drawn along the cell edge and then straightened using 
<rs type="software">ImageJ</rs>. Intensities were plotted along a 7-pixel-wide band covering the cell 
edge, yielding data points (position and intensity) spanning the Rho zone in 
the furrow. Intensity data were imported into <rs id="software-2" type="software">Mathematica</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Wolfram Re-search, Inc.</rs>.) and fit with a Gaussian curve plus a quadratic equation with 
small coefficients. The Gaussian curve fits the Rho zone, whereas the quadr-
atic fits the background cortical signal level. The width of the Rho zone was 
taken as twice the standard deviation of the fit Gaussian curve, which is 
equivalent to slightly less than the peak width at half maximum height. Total 
intensity of the Rho zone was taken as the integral under the Gaussian curve 
from the center plus or minus two standard deviations, minus the integral in 
the baseline fit over the same region. Zone widths plotted in Fig. 6 B were 
normalized by the pole-to-pole distance in each measured cell. Significance 
was judged using the mean difference test in <rs type="software">Mathematica</rs>. </p>

<p>Creation and analysis of anucleate cytoplasts 
Sand dollar zygotes were bisected either freehand using a fine glass 
needle or using a needle mounted on a hanging-joystick oil hydraulic 
micromanipulator (Narishige Group). Bisection was conducted after pro-
nuclear fusion for uninjected eggs, or 45 min after fertilization (and after 
injection) for injected eggs. Bisection yields half zygotes, which by ran-
dom chance include some pairs in which one half contains the nucleus 
and a single centrosome and the other half contains only a centrosome. 
Such pairs were recognized by differential interference contrast micros-
copy or by staining live cells with Hoechst 33342. Anucleate, centrosome-
containing cytoplasts conduct orderly centrosome duplication and separa-
tion on a normal schedule; the nucleated half skips first cleavage, then 
develops normally as a tetraploid (Fig. 8 D). Among EMTB-3G-expressing 
anucleate cytoplasts, we scored all cases in which either no furrows or dis-
crete furrows formed (omitting cases in which the cytoplast strangled itself 
into the shape of a balloon animal, which we took to be a sign of poor 
health) as follows: for each centrosome pair in focus, we measured, at the 
time corresponding to anaphase, the distance between centrosomes and 
divided by the distance from the midpoint between them to the cell surface. 
We then scored cortical behavior into three categories: (1) no furrow or 
incoherent ruffling, (2) shallow furrow, or (3) deep or complete furrow. 
Significance was judged using the mean difference test in <rs type="software">Mathematica</rs>. </p>

<p>Centrosome ablation and analysis 
We used a highly focused pulsed UV laser (MicroPoint; Photonic Instru-
ments, Inc.) coupled to an inverted microscope (TE2000) with a CARV 
spinning disk unit. All ablations were performed on sand dollar embryos 
using 365-nm light and a 60× 1.25 NA Plan-Fluor oil lens; the suboptimal 
NA of this lens imposes a nearly twofold cost in image brightness, but the 
higher UV transmittance was found to be essential. Double labeling (as in 
Fig. 8, B-D) further required a double band GFP/dsRed filter set (Chroma 
Technology Corp.), which imposes a further twofold cost in brightness. 
To destroy a centrosome in metaphase, as judged by collapse of the aster 
around it, required rapid pulses (10-20 Hz) at full power over several 
seconds. This amount of irradiation bleached GFP-based probes by as 
much as twofold per successful centrosome destruction. Our frequent 
misses constituted a built-in control: cells subjected to this degree of cyto-
plasmic irradiation outside the spindle suffered no ill effects (beyond 
bleaching). We found it difficult, though not impossible, to perform simi-
lar ablations in purple urchin embryos, as they are substantially more 
opaque than sand dollar embryos. Ablated cells and controls from the 
same recordings were analyzed using ImageJ by making three measure-
ments: the pole-to-pole cell length, the midpoint between the spindle ends 
(not poles, as one or both were destroyed), and the position of the </p>

<p> 
Action at a distance • von Dassow et al. </p>



</text></tei>