<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2700377" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T14:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Efficient cancer cell migration through tissue barriers requires 
dynamic interactions between the ECM and the actin cytoskele-
ton as well as the capacity for matrix degradation (Wolf and  Friedl, 2006). A prominent feature of the cell migration machin-
ery is the generation of organized adhesive structures. The most 
extensively characterized of these structures, focal adhesions, 
contain clusters of integrin receptors tethered to ends of actin 
stress fibers (Schoenwaelder and Burridge, 1999; Carragher and  Frame, 2004). Highly invasive cancer cells also form special-
ized actin-rich ECM-degrading membrane protrusions known 
as invadopodia, which, in contrast to focal adhesions, are pri-
mary sites of rapid actin polymerization (Buccione et al., 2004,  2009; Yamaguchi et al., 2006; Linder, 2007). Significant prog-
ress has been made in characterizing the form and function of 
invadopodia, which are comprised of actin regulators such as 
Arp2/3, neural Wiscott-Aldrich syndrome protein, gelsolin, and 
cortactin (Yamaguchi et al., 2005; Clark et al., 2007) and are 
dependent on Src kinase activity (Spinardi et al., 2004). Invado-
podia also contain concentrated foci of matrix-degrading prote-
ases such as matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs; Linder and   Aepfelbacher, 2003). A stepwise model for invadopodia for-
mation has been proposed (Artym et al., 2006); however, the 
precise mechanisms that regulate invadopodia formation and 
dynamics are not well understood. 
FAK is a nonreceptor tyrosine kinase that plays a central role 
in cell migration (Mitra et al., 2005). FAK has been shown to co-
ordinate lamellipodial formation and focal adhesion turnover in 
fibroblasts (Webb et al., 2004; Tilghman et al., 2005). Increased 
expression of FAK has been detected in metastatic tumors of the 
breast, prostate, colon, and brain (Owens et al., 1995; Cance et al.,  2000; Gabarra-Niecko et al., 2003; Lark et al., 2005). Recent evi-
dence suggests that FAK may be involved in cancer progression, as 
FAK is required for ErbB2-mediated oncogenic transformation 
and invasion (Benlimame et al., 2005). Furthermore, mammary 
epithelial-specific disruption of FAK has been shown to block the 
transition to carcinoma formation in a mouse transgenic cancer 
model (Lahlou et al., 2007). In addition, stable expression of the 
FAK-related nonkinase, an alternative transcript of FAK, has 
been shown to block mammary carcinoma lung metastases (van  Nimwegen et al., 2005). </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>ocal adhesion kinase (FAK) is important for breast 
cancer progression and invasion and is necessary 
for the dynamic turnover of focal adhesions. How-
ever, it has not been determined whether FAK also regu-
lates the dynamics of invasive adhesions formed in cancer 
cells known as invadopodia. In this study, we report that 
endogenous FAK functions upstream of cellular Src (c-Src) 
as a negative regulator of invadopodia formation and 
dynamics in breast cancer cells. We show that depletion 
of FAK induces the formation of active invadopodia but </p>

<p>impairs invasive cell migration. FAK-deficient MTLn3 breast 
cancer cells display enhanced assembly and dynamics of 
invadopodia that are rescued by expression of wild-type 
FAK but not by FAK that cannot be phosphorylated at 
tyrosine 397. Moreover, our findings demonstrate that FAK 
depletion switches phosphotyrosine-containing proteins 
from focal adhesions to invadopodia through the tempo-
ral and spatial regulation of c-Src activity. Collectively, our 
findings provide novel insight into the interplay between 
FAK and Src to promote invasion. </p>

<p>FAK alters invadopodia and focal adhesion 
composition and dynamics to regulate breast 
cancer invasion </p>

<p>Keefe T. Chan, 
1,2,3 Christa L. Cortesio, 
2,3,4 and Anna Huttenlocher </p>

<p>2,3 </p>

<p>1 Department of Molecular and Cellular Pharmacology, </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Medical Microbiology and Immunology, 
3 Department of Pediatrics, and 
4 Department of Biomolecular 
Chemistry, University of Wisconsin, Madison, WI 53706 </p>

<p>© 2009 Chan et al. This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution-
Noncommercial-Share Alike-No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publica-
tion date (see http://www.jcb.org/misc/terms.shtml). After six months it is available under a 
Creative Commons License (Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, 
as described at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). </p>

<p>T H E J O U R N A L O F C E L L B I O L O G Y </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 185 • NUMBER 2 • 2009 
358 </p>

<p>To determine how FAK regulates invadopodia formation, 
we visualized the dynamics of the invadopodia marker GFP-
cortactin (Perrin et al., 2006; Cortesio et al., 2008) in control or 
FAK-deficient MTLn3 cells by time-lapse microscopy (Fig. 1 D  and Videos 1-3). FAK-deficient cells formed significantly 
greater numbers of GFP-cortactin-containing invadopodia than 
control cells. In this study, we analyzed the dynamics of short-
lived invadopodia precursor structures (Yamaguchi et al., 2005;  Cortesio et al., 2008). Live fluorescence imaging demonstrated 
that FAK-depleted cells formed invadopodia that were present for 
a shorter duration than those formed in control cells by 2 min 
(unpublished data). From plots of GFP-cortactin fluorescence 
intensities over time, we generated rate constants for net inva-
dopodia assembly and disassembly (Fig. 1 E). The rate of inva-
dopodia assembly was significantly enhanced by twofold in 
FAK-deficient cells as compared with control cells. We also 
found modest increases in the rate of disassembly of invado-
podia, indicating that invadopodia dynamics are enhanced in 
FAK-deficient breast cancer cells. Additionally, confocal micros-
copy revealed that invadopodia formed by FAK-deficient MTLn3 
cells were still able to project vertically from the ventral mem-
brane surface into a gelatin matrix (Fig. 1 F). Collectively, our 
results identify a novel role for endogenous FAK as a negative 
regulator of invadopodia formation and dynamics in breast can-
cer cells. These findings are especially intriguing in light of data 
demonstrating that depletion of FAK results in impaired focal 
adhesion dynamics (Webb et al., 2004). </p>

<p>Enhanced invadopodia formation in </p>

<p>FAK-deficient MTLn3 cells is not sufficient </p>

<p>for invasion </p>

<p>Because the matrix-degrading function of invadopodia has 
been attributed to the focalized activity of MMPs (Chen and  Wang, 1999; Artym et al., 2006), we examined whether the 
invadopodia formed in FAK-deficient MTLn3 cells retained their 
capacity to degrade the ECM. We cultured cells on fibronectin-
Alexa Fluor 568 gelatin substrates in the absence or presence 
of the pan-MMP inhibitor GM6001 (Fig. 2, A and B). FAK-
deficient MTLn3 cells displayed a threefold increase in the 
formation of active invadopodia associated with focal areas of 
matrix degradation as compared with control cells (Fig. 2 C). 
The regions of matrix degradation formed in both control and 
FAK-deficient cells required the activity of MMPs because 
GM6001 impaired matrix degradation without affecting the 
formation of cortactin-containing puncta. To determine whether 
formation of invadopodia correlates with the invasive capacity 
of MTLn3 cancer cells, we assayed the ability of serum-starved 
MTLn3 cells to invade toward serum through Matrigel-coated 
membranes (Fig. 2 D). Invasion of MTLn3 control and FAK-
deficient cells across Matrigel was impaired in the presence of 
GM6001, suggesting that the formation of functional invado-
podia is necessary for Matrigel invasion. However, FAK-deficient 
cells, despite forming more active invadopodia, displayed sub-
stantially impaired Matrigel invasion as compared with control 
cells, demonstrating that enhanced formation of invadopodia 
in FAK-deficient cells is not sufficient to mediate invasive 
cell migration. </p>

<p>FAK promotes cell migration by its ability to bridge sig-
nals between integrin and growth factor receptors (Sieg et al.,  2000). Downstream of integrin or growth factor stimulation, 
FAK is cis-or trans-phosphorylated at Tyr-397, which pro-
vides a critical binding site for Src family kinases (Schaller  et al., 1994), the p85 regulatory subunit of phosphatidylinosi-
tol 3-kinase (Chen and Guan, 1994), and phospholipase C 
(Zhang et al., 1999). In particular, Src binding to Tyr-397 is 
important for phosphorylation of Tyr-576/577, which is im-
portant for full FAK activation. Subsequently, an activated 
FAK-Src complex mediates the phosphorylation of multiple 
adhesion components involved in the dynamic regulation of 
cell motility, including p130Cas (Tachibana et al., 1997) and 
paxillin (Bellis et al., 1995). 
In this study, we sought to determine whether FAK is in-
volved in cell invasion through the regulation of invadopodia, 
which are thought to be responsible for the ability of cancer 
cells to degrade and invade through the matrix. Intriguingly, we 
find that depletion of FAK enhances the formation and dynam-
ics of matrix-degrading invadopodia, which is rescued upon ex-
pression of wild-type FAK but not by expression of FAK that 
cannot be phosphorylated at Tyr-397. We demonstrate that en-
hanced invadopodia formation in FAK-depleted cells is not suf-
ficient for cancer cell invasion. We also provide evidence that 
depletion of FAK expression regulates a switch from phospho-
tyrosine-containing proteins at focal adhesions to invadopodia 
via the spatial and temporal regulation of active Src. Together, 
our findings provide novel insight into the mechanism of FAK-
Src signaling in cancer cell invasion. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>FAK negatively regulates invadopodia </p>

<p>formation and dynamics </p>

<p>Previous studies have demonstrated a critical role for FAK in 
regulating the turnover of focal adhesions (Webb et al., 2004;  Schober et al., 2007); however, a role for FAK in regulating the 
dynamics of invadopodia in cancer cells has not been character-
ized. MTLn3 mammary adenocarcinoma cells form invado-
podia when plated on fibronectin or fibronectin-gelatin substrates, 
and the formation of these structures is thought to correlate with 
invasive capacity (Yamaguchi et al., 2005). To generate FAK-
deficient MTLn3 breast cancer cells, we used two independent 
siRNAs that depleted endogenous FAK by 80% (Fig. 1 A) with-
out affecting the expression of FAK-related proline-rich tyro-
sine kinase (Pyk2; Lim et al., 2008). Invadopodia structures 
were identified in cells cultured on fibronectin-coated cover-
slips stained for the invadopodia markers cortactin and actin 
(Fig. 1 B). We unexpectedly found that FAK-deficient MTLn3 
cells formed increased numbers of invadopodia on fibronectin, 
fibronectin-gelatin, and Matrigel surfaces (Fig. 1 C and unpub- lished data). We also observed increased invadopodia formation 
in FAK-deficient MDA-MB-231 human mammary adenocarci-
noma cells (Fig. S1) and SNB19 human glioblastoma cells (un-
published data), indicating that the ability of endogenous FAK 
to suppress invadopodia formation may be a general property of 
invasive cancer cells. </p>

<p> 
FAK IMPAIRS INVADOPODIA FORMATION • Chan et al. </p>

<p>GFP-FAK, GFP-FAK-Y397F, or GFP-FAK-K454R (Fig. S2 A). 
We tested the capacity of the cell lines cultured on fibronectin-
Alexa Fluor 568 gelatin substrates to form invadopodia and 
degrade the ECM (Fig. 3 A). Depletion of endogenous FAK 
in GFP-expressing cells resulted in significantly enhanced 
numbers of active invadopodia (Fig. 3 B). Expression of wild-
type FAK restored numbers of active invadopodia to those 
observed in control cells. However, GFP-FAK-Y397F expres-
sion failed to rescue invadopodia numbers. Expression of 
kinase-dead GFP-FAK also rescued invadopodia but not 
to the same extent as wild-type FAK. We next assayed the </p>

<p>Expression of wild-type FAK but not </p>

<p>Y397F-FAK rescues enhanced invadopodia </p>

<p>formation and impaired invasion upon FAK </p>

<p>depletion in MTLn3 cells </p>

<p>To begin to investigate how FAK regulates invadopodia for-
mation, we generated MTLn3 cell lines stably expressing 
GFP, wild-type GFP-FAK, the SH2 domain-binding mutant 
GFP-FAK-Y397F, and the kinase-inactive mutant GFP-FAK-
K454R. Treatment with FAK siRNA (which targets a sequence 
in the 5 untranslated region of FAK) effectively reduced en-
dogenous FAK expression without affecting the expression of </p>

<p>Figure 1. FAK negatively regulates invadopodia formation and dynamics. (A) Cell lysates from MTLn3 cells transiently transfected with control siRNA (Ctlsi) 
or FAK siRNA (FAKsi A and FAKsi B) were analyzed by Western blotting and probed for FAK or Pyk2. Actin was probed as a loading control. (B) MTLn3 
cells were plated on fibronectin-coated coverslips and stained with anticortactin antibody (green) and rhodamine-phalloidin (red). Boxed regions depict 
regions of invadopodia shown magnified in insets. (C) Quantification of cortactin-and actin-containing invadopodia is expressed as the mean number of 
invadopodia per cell. (D) GFP-cortactin was transiently cotransfected with control siRNA or FAK siRNA (FAK siRNA B is shown) into MTLn3 cells. Cells were 
plated on fibronectin-coated glass-bottomed dishes and analyzed by time-lapse fluorescence microscopy. Time-lapse montages demonstrate representative 
images of the dynamics of the invadopodia marker GFP-cortactin over a period of 10 min. (E) Rate constants for assembly and disassembly were calculated 
from plots of fluorescence intensities of GFP-cortactin as described in Materials and methods (Videos 1-3). (F) Representative x-z confocal images of 
invadopodia in MTLn3 cells show cortactin-containing invadopodia (red) projecting into the gelatin matrix (green). Arrows indicate representative invado-
podia. Data shown are means ± SEM of three independent experiments. *, P &lt; 0.05 by t test compared with control siRNA. Bars, 10 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 185 • NUMBER 2 • 2009 </p>

<p>
critical role in limiting invadopodia formation and is also 
required for efficient invasion. 
FAK has been shown to be important for the regulation of 
focal adhesion morphology and turnover in fibroblasts, which 
contribute to efficient migration (Sieg et al., 1999; Webb et al.,  2004). In accordance with these studies, FAK-deficient MTLn3 
cells displayed enlarged vinculin-containing focal adhesions at 
the cell periphery, which is consistent with impaired focal adhe-
sion disassembly in fibroblasts depleted of FAK (Fig. S2 B). 
This corresponded to a threefold reduction in transwell migra-
tion as compared with control cells expressing GFP (Fig. S2 C). 
Focal adhesion morphology and migration were restored in 
cells expressing GFP-FAK or GFP-FAK-K454R but not GFP-
FAK-Y397F. Collectively, these data are consistent with the 
hypothesis that FAK and its phosphorylation at Tyr-397 are 
critical in the differential regulation of focal adhesion and inva-
dopodia dynamics to modulate migration and invasion. 
Previous studies have suggested that FAK localizes to in-
vadopodia structures (Hauck et al., 2002; Hsia et al., 2003). To 
determine whether FAK localizes to invadopodia in MTLn3 
cells, we performed immunofluorescent cell staining in cells 
stably expressing GFP-FAK and visualized them by confocal 
microscopy (Fig. S2 D). We plated cells on fibronectin-gelatin 
coverslips and stained for vinculin, a known marker of focal 
adhesions, and Arp2/3, which is known to localize to invado-
podia (Yamaguchi et al., 2005). Z sectioning revealed that 
GFP-FAK and vinculin were localized to focal adhesions, and 
we did not detect the presence of vinculin or FAK in Arp2/3-
containing invadopodia. These data indicate that the invadopo-
dia formed by MTLn3 cells are morphologically distinct 
from podosomes, which contain vinculin-rich adhesive rings 
(Buccione et al., 2004; Oikawa et al., 2008). We were unable to 
stain for endogenous FAK, but we found that endogenous 
phosphorylated FAK at Tyr-397 localized with GFP-vinculin 
at focal adhesions but not cortactin-containing invadopodia 
(Fig. S2 E). Collectively, these data suggest that FAK does not 
localize to invadopodia in MTLn3 cells, which is consistent 
with experiments performed in MDA-MB-231 breast cancer 
cells (Bowden et al., 2006), but nevertheless, is able to modu-
late invadopodia formation. </p>

<p>FAK functions upstream of Src </p>

<p>kinase activity to negatively regulate </p>

<p>invadopodia formation </p>

<p>Because phosphorylation of FAK at Tyr-397 is known to mediate 
Src binding (Schaller et al., 1999; Sieg et al., 1999), we next 
wanted to determine whether FAK modulates invadopodia for-
mation through a Src-dependent pathway. Substantial evidence 
supports a critical role for Src tyrosine kinases in podosome and 
invadopodia formation (Linder and Aepfelbacher, 2003; Spinardi  et al., 2004). Thus, we assayed the ability of control or FAK-
deficient MTLn3 cells to form invadopodia on fibronectin-gelatin 
coverslips in the absence or presence of the Src kinase inhibitor 
PP2 (Fig. 4 A). Accordingly, we found that the enhanced inva-
dopodia formation observed in FAK-deficient cells required 
Src activity (Fig. 4 B). To determine whether FAK functions 
upstream or downstream of Src, we examined invadopodia </p>

<p>ability of the cell lines to invade through Matrigel-coated 
membranes (Fig. 3 C). Depletion of FAK in MTLn3 cells 
expressing GFP resulted in significantly impaired invasion. 
Invasion was restored in cells expressing wild-type and kinase-
dead GFP-FAK but not in cells expressing GFP-FAK-Y397F, 
suggesting that phosphorylation of FAK at Tyr-397 plays a </p>

<p>Figure 2. Enhanced invadopodia formation in FAK-deficient MTLn3 cells 
requires MMP activity but is not sufficient for invasion. (A) MTLn3 cells 
transiently transfected with control siRNA (Ctlsi) or FAK siRNA (FAKsi) were 
cultured on fibronectin-Alexa Fluor 568 gelatin coverslips in the presence 
of DMSO vehicle control (GM6001) and stained with anticortactin anti-
body (green). (B) MTLn3 cells transiently transfected with control siRNA or 
FAK siRNA were cultured on fibronectin-Alexa Fluor 568 gelatin-coated 
coverslips in the presence of 50 µM GM6001 (+GM6001) and stained 
with anticortactin antibody (green). Boxed regions in A and B depict re-
gions of invadopodia shown magnified in insets. (C) Quantification of ac-
tive invadopodia, defined as colocalizing areas of cortactin staining and 
matrix degradation, is expressed as the mean number of active invadopo-
dia per cell. (D) MTLn3 cells transiently transfected with control siRNA or 
FAK siRNA were cultured in the presence of vehicle control (GM6001) or 
50 µM GM6001 (+GM6001) and were assayed for their ability to invade 
through Matrigel-coated membranes. Relative invasion was determined by 
normalizing the number of cells invaded to those transfected with control 
siRNA (GM6001). Data shown are means ± SEM of three independent 
experiments. *, P &lt; 0.05 by one-way ANOVA compared with control 
siRNA (GM6001). Bars, 10 µm. </p>

<p>361 
FAK IMPAIRS INVADOPODIA FORMATION • Chan et al. </p>

<p>FAK depletion regulates a switch between </p>

<p>phosphotyrosine-containing proteins at </p>

<p>focal adhesions to invadopodia </p>

<p>The FAK-Src complex can bind to and phosphorylate diverse 
substrates to regulate adhesion dynamics and cell migration 
(Mitra et al., 2005). Also, tyrosine phosphorylation is a critical 
mechanism by which focal adhesion dynamics are regulated 
(Crowley and Horwitz, 1995; Zamir et al., 1999). Therefore, we 
reasoned that FAK may differentially regulate invadopodia and 
focal adhesions through its effects on localized tyrosine phosphory-
lation. We examined the distribution of tyrosine-phosphorylated 
proteins in control and FAK-deficient MTLn3 cells cultured on 
fibronectin-gelatin substrates (Fig. 5 A). Control cells displayed 
robust tyrosine phosphorylation at focal adhesions that con-
tained GFP-paxillin and GFP-vinculin (unpublished data) and 
at invadopodia positive for Arp2/3 staining. In contrast, FAK-
deficient MTLn3 cells exhibited dramatically reduced tyrosine 
phosphorylation at focal adhesions but displayed strong tyro-
sine phosphorylation at invadopodia. Additionally, we tested 
the localization of a phosphotyrosine reporter construct consist-
ing of two tandem Src SH2 phosphotyrosine-binding domains 
(YFP-dSH2), which specifically detects tyrosine phosphoryla-
tion at focal adhesions (Fig. 5 B; Kirchner et al., 2003). YFP-dSH2 
was strongly localized with phosphotyrosine at focal adhe-
sions, but not invadopodia, in control cells. However, upon FAK 
depletion, phosphotyrosine staining at focal adhesions and 
YFP-dSH2 localization were severely impaired. Accordingly, 
live fluorescence microscopy of YFP-dSH2 in control cells 
revealed its localization at dynamic focal adhesion structures 
(Videos 4 and 5). YFP-dSH2 localization at focal adhesions in 
FAK-deficient cells was decreased, and the YFP-dSH2 that was 
present at focal adhesions displayed impaired dynamics. Inter-
estingly, we did not detect any clear localization at invadopodia 
puncta, indicating the predominant specificity of the YFP-dSH2 
probe for tyrosine-phosphorylated substrates at focal adhesions. 
Together, these data support the hypothesis that FAK regulates 
a balance between phosphotyrosine-containing proteins at focal 
adhesions and invadopodia. 
To determine whether FAK modulates tyrosine phosphoryla-
tion at focal adhesions through a Src-dependent pathway, we inves-
tigated the effects of FAK depletion on phosphotyrosine localization 
in Src-transformed MTLn3 cells (Fig. 5 A). Similar to untrans-
formed cells, we observed strong phosphotyrosine staining at both 
focal adhesions that contained GFP-paxillin and at invadopodia 
positive for Arp2/3 in v-Src-transformed MTLn3 cells. In contrast, 
phosphotyrosine staining at focal adhesions in FAK-deficient 
v-Src-transformed cells remained robust, suggesting that FAK is 
not necessary for tyrosine phosphorylation at focal adhesions in 
Src-transformed cells. We also examined the invasive capacity of 
untransformed and v-Src-transformed MTLn3 cells (Fig. S3). We 
found that FAK-deficient cells were impaired 80% in their ability 
to invade through Matrigel-coated membranes. However, FAK-
deficient MTLn3 cells expressing v-Src were impaired only 40% 
in their invasive capacity despite similar knockdown efficiency. 
These results indicate that depletion of FAK likely modulates 
localized tyrosine phosphorylation at focal adhesions and invado-
podia upstream of Src to regulate invasion. </p>

<p>formation in MTLn3 cells stably expressing cellular Src (c-Src) 
or activated c-Src-527F (Fig. 4 C). Cells expressing c-Src or 
c-Src-527F formed dramatically enhanced numbers of cortactin-
containing invadopodia as compared with control cells. Depletion 
of FAK in cells that overexpress c-Src resulted in a significant 
increase in invadopodia (Fig. 4 D). However, in cells expressing 
c-Src-527F or constitutively active viral Src (v-Src; Fig. 4 E), 
we found that depletion of FAK did not enhance invadopodia 
formation, suggesting that c-Src-527F or v-Src functions inde-
pendently of endogenous FAK to modulate invadopodia forma-
tion. This is the first study to show that endogenous FAK 
functions as a negative regulator of invadopodia formation in 
cancer cells upstream of c-Src. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Expression of wild-type but not Y397F-FAK restores enhanced 
matrix-degrading invadopodia and impaired invasion in FAK-deficient 
MTLn3 cells. (A) MTLn3 cells stably expressing GFP, GFP-FAK (wild type), 
GFP-FAK-Y397F, and GFP-FAK-K454R were transiently transfected with con-
trol siRNA (Ctlsi) or FAK siRNA (FAKsi), cultured on fibronectin-Alexa Fluor 
568 gelatin coverslips, and stained with anticortactin antibody (blue). Bar, 
10 µm. (B) Quantification of active invadopodia, defined as colocalizing 
areas of cortactin staining and matrix degradation, is expressed as the 
mean number of active invadopodia per cell. (C) MTLn3 cells treated as 
in A were assayed for their ability to invade through Matrigel-coated mem-
branes. Relative invasion was determined by normalizing the number of 
cells invaded to those transfected with control siRNA. WT, wild type. Data 
shown are means ± SEM of three independent experiments. *, P &lt; 0.05 by 
t test compared with GFP-expressing cells transfected with control siRNA. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 185 • NUMBER 2 • 2009 </p>

<p>
phosphorylated paxillin, FAK-deficient cells displayed a dra-
matic reduction in the localization of phospho-p130Cas at focal 
adhesions. However, in MTLn3 cells depleted of FAK, we de-
tected an increase in phospho-p130Cas at dotlike structures, 
some of which contained cortactin. These results indicate that 
FAK is critical for the localized tyrosine phosphorylation of 
paxillin and p130Cas at focal adhesions. 
Recent evidence has also implicated the Tks5/FISH family 
of adaptor proteins in podosome formation (Seals et al., 2005;  Oikawa et al., 2008). In accordance with these studies, we ob-
served localization of Tks5 with cortactin-containing invado-
podia (Fig. 6 E) but not at vinculin-containing focal adhesions in 
control cells (Fig. 6 F). FAK-deficient cells displayed increased 
numbers of Tks5/cortactin-positive invadopodia. In addition, we 
detected an enhancement of invadopodia that contained phos-
phorylated cortactin in FAK-deficient MTLn3 cells (Fig. S4). 
Collectively, concomitant with a decrease in phosphorylated pax-
illin and p130Cas localization at focal adhesions was an increase 
in the localization of Tks5/FISH and phosphorylated cortactin at 
invadopodia, supporting a switch in localized tyrosine phosphory-
lation mediated by FAK depletion. </p>

<p>The FAK-Src complex has been demonstrated to mediate the 
phosphorylation of multiple adhesion components involved in cell 
migration, the best characterized of which are p130Cas (Tachibana  et al., 1997) and paxillin (Bellis et al., 1995). To distinguish the spe-
cific phosphoprotein components at focal adhesions and invado-
podia, we first examined the localization of tyrosine-phosphorylated 
paxillin and p130Cas in MTLn3 cells cultured on fibronectin-
gelatin coverslips. Phosphorylated paxillin at Tyr-31 was absent in 
cortactin-positive invadopodia in control cells (Fig. 6 A). FAK-
deficient cells displayed an increase in invadopodia that also lacked 
phosphopaxillin. In contrast, phosphopaxillin localized strongly 
with vinculin-positive focal adhesions in control cells (Fig. 6 B). 
Depletion of FAK impaired phosphopaxillin staining at focal adhe-
sions but did not result in its redistribution to other structures. 
Previous studies have shown that p130Cas is critical for podo-
some organization and Src transformation (Honda et al., 1998;  Brabek et al., 2005). We observed some localization of phospho-
p130Cas at cortactin-containing invadopodia (Fig. 6 C), although 
phospho-p130Cas was predominantly localized to focal adhesion-
like structures in control cells, which was confirmed by immuno-
staining with an antivinculin antibody (Fig. 6 D). Similar to </p>

<p>Figure 4. FAK functions upstream of Src kinase to regulate invadopodia formation. (A) MTLn3 cells transiently transfected with control siRNA (Ctlsi) or FAK 
siRNA (FAKsi-A and FAKsi-B) were cultured on fibronectin-gelatin coverslips in the presence of vehicle control (PP2) or 2 µM PP2 (+PP2). Cells were stained 
with anticortactin antibody (green) and rhodamine-phalloidin (red). (B) Quantification of cortactin-and actin-containing invadopodia is expressed as the 
mean number of invadopodia per cell. (C) MTLn3 cells expressing c-Src or c-Src-527F were transiently transfected with control siRNA or FAK siRNA, cultured 
on fibronectin-gelatin coverslips, and stained with anticortactin antibody. (D) Quantification of cortactin-containing invadopodia in c-Src-or c-Src-527F-
expressing cell lines is expressed as the mean number of invadopodia per cell. (E) MTLn3 cells expressing v-Src were transiently transfected with control 
siRNA or FAK siRNA and cultured on fibronectin-gelatin coverslips. Cells were stained with anticortactin antibody (green) and rhodamine-phalloidin (red). 
Data shown are means ± SEM of three independent experiments. *, P &lt; 0.05 by one-way ANOVA compared with control siRNA (PP2). Bars, 10 µm. </p>

<p> 
FAK IMPAIRS INVADOPODIA FORMATION • Chan et al. </p>

<p>mediates a switch in tyrosine phosphorylation of FAK-Src 
substrates at focal adhesions to invadopodia. </p>

<p>Depletion of FAK modulates the </p>

<p>redistribution of active Src from focal </p>

<p>adhesions to invadopodia </p>

<p>We observed that FAK was strongly present at focal adhesions 
but not at invadopodia (Fig. S2, D and E). It was intriguing 
that a focal adhesion protein could modulate the dynamics of 
distal invadopodia structures. A previous study suggested that </p>

<p>To confirm our hypothesis, we performed a phosphoprotein 
profile analysis of the focal adhesion and invadopodia components 
that we examined by immunolocalization (Fig. 7). In FAK-depleted 
cells, we observed a twofold reduction in global tyrosine phosphory-
lation of paxillin and p130Cas as compared with control cells. In 
addition, although we found enhanced numbers of invadopodia 
containing phosphorylated cortactin, we only detected a modest in-
crease in global cortactin phosphorylation. Intriguingly, we found 
a substantial increase in tyrosine phosphorylation of Tks5 in FAK-
deficient cells. Together, our data indicate that FAK depletion </p>

<p>Figure 5. FAK differentially regulates tyrosine phosphorylation at focal adhesions and invadopodia. (A) MTLn3 (parental) cells or v-Src-transformed 
MTLn3 cells transiently transfected with control siRNA (Ctlsi) or FAK siRNA (FAKsi) and cotransfected with GFP-paxillin were cultured on fibronectin-gelatin 
coverslips and stained with anti-p34Arc (Arp2/3 subunit) antibody and antiphosphotyrosine antibody. Two sets of overlays are depicted to illustrate local-
ization of GFP-paxillin or Arp2/3 (green) with phosphotyrosine (pY) staining (red). (B) MTLn3 cells transiently transfected with control siRNA or FAK siRNA 
and cotransfected with YFP-dSH2 were cultured on fibronectin-gelatin coverslips and stained with anti-p34Arc antibody (red) and antiphosphotyrosine 
antibody (blue). Regions outlined by boxes indicate images of invadopodia and focal adhesions. Arrows indicate representative invadopodia, and 
arrowheads indicate representative focal adhesions. Bars, 10 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 185 • NUMBER 2 • 2009 </p>

<p>
consistent with possible endosomes (Fig. 8 A). Although we 
found that global Src activity was decreased in MTLn3 cells 
depleted of FAK (Fig. 7), we observed a substantial increase 
in the number of invadopodia containing active Src. Ratio im-
ages of cortactin to phospho-Src did not reveal any clear dif-
ferences in the amount of active Src at invadopodia in control 
and FAK-deficient cells. In contrast, phospho-Src was almost 
completely absent at focal adhesion-like structures in FAK-
deficient cells. Staining with an antivinculin antibody in con-
trol cells verified that active Src was localized to focal 
adhesions (Fig. 8 B). Depletion of FAK resulted in reduced </p>

<p>the localization and activity of Src could be regulated by asso-
ciation with FAK (Schaller et al., 1999). Thus, we wanted to 
determine how FAK depletion impaired tyrosine phosphoryla-
tion of FAK-Src substrates at focal adhesions but enhanced 
tyrosine phosphorylation of substrates at invadopodia. To ad-
dress this, we examined the localization of activated c-Src by 
staining for Tyr-416 c-Src in control and FAK-deficient 
MTLn3 cells on fibronectin-gelatin substrates (Fig. 8). In con-
trol cells, we detected the robust presence of active Src at both 
cortactin-containing invadopodia and focal adhesion-like 
structures as well as within several cytoplasmic dots, which is </p>

<p>Figure 6. FAK modulates the localization of pY31-paxillin, pY410 p130Cas, and Tks5 in MTLn3 cells. (A-F) MTLn3 cells transiently transfected with control 
siRNA (Ctlsi) or FAK siRNA (FAKsi) were cultured on fibronectin-gelatin coverslips and stained with anti-pY31 paxillin (A and B), anti-pY410 p130Cas 
(C and D), or anti-Tks5/FISH antibody (E and F; red). Cells were costained with the invadopodia marker cortactin (A, C, and E; green) or the focal adhesion 
marker vinculin (B, D, and F; green). Regions outlined by boxes correspond to magnified images of pY31-paxillin, pY410 p130Cas, or Tks5 localization 
at focal adhesions and/or invadopodia shown in insets. Bars, 10 µm. </p>

<p> 
FAK IMPAIRS INVADOPODIA FORMATION • Chan et al. </p>

<p>dynamics (Fig. 9). FAK-deficient MTLn3 breast cancer cells 
display enhanced dynamics of invadopodia that are rescued by 
expression of wild-type FAK but not by expression of FAK that 
cannot be phosphorylated at Tyr-397. Furthermore, we show 
that depletion of endogenous FAK by siRNA induces the for-
mation of active invadopodia and mediates a switch from robust 
phosphotyrosine-containing proteins at focal adhesions to inva-
dopodia through the spatial and temporal regulation of Src 
activity. Our findings provide novel insight into the mechanism 
of FAK-Src signaling in cancer cell invasion. 
Significant progress has been made in understanding the 
molecular mechanisms by which adhesive structures assemble 
and disassemble during cell migration. It appears that many of the 
signaling pathways that govern focal adhesion formation and dis-
assembly also play roles in the regulation of invadopodia dynam-
ics. For example, Src kinases and calpain proteases are important 
for the disassembly of both focal adhesions and podosome-type 
adhesions, including podosomes (Calle et al., 2006) and invado-
podia (Cortesio et al., 2008). Nevertheless, the mechanisms that 
regulate the formation of invadopodia and focal adhesions can be 
distinct. For example, Src kinase activity is necessary for the for-
mation of podosome-type adhesions (Spinardi et al., 2004), but 
its role in focal adhesion formation is less clear. Indeed, expres-
sion of constitutively active Src in cells that normally form focal 
adhesions promotes a switch to the formation of podosome-type 
adhesions (Gavazzi et al., 1989) and has been associated with a 
more invasive phenotype. Many cancer cells form both focal ad-
hesions and invadopodia, but the molecular determinants that me-
diate the balance between formation of firm adhesive structures 
through focal adhesions and the generation of invasive matrix-
degrading adhesion structures remain poorly understood. 
Our findings suggest that FAK is poised to play a key role 
in regulating a dynamic interplay in signaling between focal ad-
hesions and invadopodia during invasive cell migration. In ac-
cordance with a recent publication (Vitale et al., 2008), our data 
indicate that FAK is not necessary for the formation of invado-
podia but instead can function to limit the formation of matrix-
degrading invadopodia in cancer cells. However, our study is the 
first to show that depletion of endogenous FAK provides a criti-
cal switch between focal adhesion and invadopodia dynamics. 
We find that FAK depletion induces the formation of functional 
invadopodia in several different cancer cell lines, including 
MTLn3 and MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cells (Fig. S1) and 
SNB19 glioblastoma cells (unpublished data). Furthermore, our 
study presents a novel separation between enhanced generation 
of invadopodia and the invasive capacity of cancer cells. FAK-
deficient MTLn3 cells showed impaired invasion across Matrigel-
coated filters despite showing enhanced invadopodia formation 
on many different matrices including fibronectin, fibronectin-
gelatin, and Matrigel (unpublished data). Although we found 
that MTLn3 invasion across Matrigel requires proteinase activ-
ity, enhanced matrix degradation alone is not sufficient for effi-
cient tumor cell invasion in FAK-deficient cells. These findings 
suggest that FAK plays a complicated role in cancer cell invasion. 
It is intriguing to speculate that mechanisms that limit matrix 
degradation, through FAK or related pathways, may be necessary 
to optimize the matrix environment for invasive cell motility. </p>

<p>localization of active Src at enlarged vinculin-positive focal 
adhesions. Additionally, we generated ratio images of vinculin 
to phospho-Src. The vinculin/phospho-Src ratio was greater in 
FAK-deficient cells than control cells, suggesting a decrease in 
active Src at focal adhesions in FAK-deficient cells. Collec-
tively, these data highlight a novel role for FAK in the differen-
tial modulation of focal adhesion and invadopodia composition 
and dynamics to regulate invasion through the spatial and tem-
poral regulation of Src activity. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>A hallmark of invasive tumor cells is the ability to degrade the 
ECM through the generation of invadopodia. Previous studies 
have suggested a critical role for FAK in breast cancer progres-
sion and metastatic disease; however, the role of FAK in invado-
podia formation has not been characterized (Owens et al., 1995;  Cance et al., 2000; Gabarra-Niecko et al., 2003; Lark et al.,  2005). In this study, we describe a novel function for endog-
enous FAK in the regulation of invadopodia formation and </p>

<p>Figure 7. FAK regulates a switch in tyrosine phosphorylation at focal 
adhesions and invadopodia. (A) Cell lysates from MTLn3 cells transiently 
transfected with control siRNA (Ctlsi) or FAK siRNA (FAKsi) were analyzed 
by immunoblotting (IB) or immunoprecipitation (IP)/immunoblotting and 
probed with phospho-specific antibodies anti-pY397 FAK, anti-pY416 
Src, anti-pY410 p130Cas, anti-pY31 paxillin, anti-pY421 cortactin, or 
antiphosphotyrosine and antibodies to total proteins anti-FAK, anti-Src, anti-
p130Cas, antipaxillin, anticortactin, or anti-Tks5/FISH. (B) Quantification 
of immunoblots or immunoprecipitation/immunoblots is expressed as fold 
change in phosphorylation to total protein. Fold change was determined 
by the ratio of normalized phosphorylation to total protein in FAK siRNA 
compared with control siRNA. Data shown are means ± SEM of three 
independent experiments. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 185 • NUMBER 2 • 2009 </p>

<p>
also contribute to the ability of FAK to suppress invadopodia 
formation. Collectively, our data demonstrate that phosphoryla-
tion of FAK at Tyr-397 is important for limiting invadopodia 
formation by FAK upstream of Src. 
Previous studies have demonstrated that tyrosine phos-
phorylation is a critical mechanism by which focal adhesion 
dynamics are regulated (Crowley and Horwitz, 1995; Zamir  et al., 1999). We found that tyrosine phosphorylation was 
decreased at focal adhesions but not at invadopodia in FAK-
deficient MTLn3 cells. Furthermore, depletion of FAK resulted 
in enlarged peripheral focal adhesions and impaired localization 
and dynamics of a specific phosphotyrosine reporter at focal 
adhesions, which is consistent with previous reports of impaired 
focal adhesion disassembly in fibroblasts (Sieg et al., 1999;  Webb et al., 2004). In contrast, FAK-deficient cells displayed 
enhanced formation and dynamics of matrix-degrading invado-
podia. Together, our data indicate that FAK is critical for tyrosine </p>

<p>This is an especially attractive hypothesis because FAK expres-
sion is associated with the invasive activity of human tumors 
and has been implicated in breast cancer progression and inva-
sion in mouse models (Owens et al., 1995; Cance et al., 2000;  Gabarra-Niecko et al., 2003; Lark et al., 2005; Mitra et al., 2006;  Lahlou et al., 2007). 
We have substantial evidence indicating that FAK func-
tions upstream of c-Src to suppress invadopodia formation. For 
example, we found that endogenous FAK suppresses invado-
podia formation in wild-type breast cancer cells and cells that 
overexpress wild-type c-Src. However, FAK siRNA had no 
effect on invadopodia formation in cells that express either active 
c-Src-527F or transforming v-Src. In addition, expression of 
wild type but not Y397F-FAK, which abrogates Src binding, 
suppressed invadopodia formation in FAK-deficient cells. Inter-
estingly, we observed partial effects in cells expressing kinase-
inactive FAK, suggesting that the kinase activity of FAK may </p>

<p>Figure 8. Recruitment of active Src to focal adhesions but not invadopodia requires FAK. (A and B) MTLn3 cells transiently transfected with control siRNA 
(Ctlsi) or FAK siRNA (FAKsi) were cultured on fibronectin-gelatin coverslips and stained with anti-pY416 Src antibody (red) and anticortactin antibody 
(A, green) or antivinculin antibody (B, green). (A) Ratiometric images are presented as a ratio of cortactin/pY416 Src. (B) Ratiometric images are presented 
as a ratio of vinculin/pY416 Src. Regions outlined by boxes correspond to magnified images of pY416 Src localization at focal adhesions and invadopodia 
shown in insets. The color bars indicate the ratio on a scale of black = 0 (high pY416 Src) to white = 10 (low pY416 Src). Bars, 10 µm. </p>

<p> 
FAK IMPAIRS INVADOPODIA FORMATION • Chan et al. </p>

<p>Our findings demonstrate a novel role for FAK as a nega-
tive regulator of invadopodia formation and provide mechanistic 
insight into the dynamic regulation of adhesive structures 
involved in cell invasion. It is especially intriguing that endogenous 
FAK and c-Src display opposing functions on invadopodia. Src 
is required for the generation of invadopodia, whereas FAK sup-
presses the formation and dynamics of invadopodia. A challenge 
for future investigation will be to elucidate the downstream 
mechanisms by which the FAK-Src complex differentially regu-
lates the balance between adhesive and degradative structures 
and to characterize their precise functions in vivo. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Reagents and antibodies 
Fibronectin was purified as described previously (Ruoslahti et al., 1982). 
The following reagents were used: -MEM, Opti-MEM I, Ham's F12 
medium, Oregon green 488 gelatin conjugate, rhodamine phalloidin, 
Alexa Fluor 568 protein labeling kit (Invitrogen), gelatin from porcine skin 
(Sigma-Aldrich), PP2 (in ethanol used at 2 µM; Axxora; Enxo Biochem, 
Inc.), and GM6001 (in DMSO used at 50 µM; EMD). The following mouse 
monoclonal antibodies were used: anticortactin (clone 4F11), anti-Src 
(clone GD11), antiphosphotyrosine (4G10; Millipore), antivinculin (clone 
h-VIN1), anti--actin (clone AC-15; Sigma-Aldrich), anti-Pyk2 (clone 11), 
antipaxillin (clone 349), anti-p130Cas (clone 21), and anti-FAK (clone 77; 
BD). The following rabbit polyclonal antibodies were used: anti-p34Arc, 
anti-pY421 cortactin (Millipore), anti-FAK (clone C-20), anti-Tks5/FISH 
(clone M-300; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.), anti-pY31 paxillin, anti-
pY397 FAK (Invitrogen), anti-pY410 p130Cas, and anti-pY416 Src (Cell 
Signaling Technology). Rabbit monoclonal antibody used for staining was 
anti-pY397 FAK (Invitrogen). The following secondary antibodies were used: 
Alexa Fluor 680 goat anti-mouse IgG (Invitrogen), IRDye 800CW goat 
anti-rabbit IgG (Rockland Immunochemicals, Inc.), FITC sheep anti-mouse 
IgG (whole molecule; Chroma Pure), FITC donkey anti-rabbit IgG, TRITC 
donkey anti-rabbit IgG (Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories), Rhodamine 
red-X goat anti-mouse IgG, and Marina blue goat anti-mouse IgG (Invitro-
gen). Immunoprecipitation control IgGs used were mouse IgG (whole mole-
cule; Chroma Pure) and rabbit IgG (Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories). </p>

<p>Cell lines and siRNA transfection 
The following cell lines were used: MTLn3 rat mammary adenocarcinoma 
(provided by J. Condeelis and J. Segall, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, 
New York, NY), MDA-MB-231 human mammary adenocarcinoma (provided 
by A. Rapraeger, University of Wisconsin, Madison, WI), and SNB19 
human glioblastoma (provided by M. Symons, The Feinstein Institute for Medi-
cal Research at North Shore-LIJ, Manhasset, NY). MTLn3 cells were cultured 
in -MEM supplemented with 5% FBS (HyClone) and antibiotics (Cellgro; 
Mediatech) as described previously (Segall et al., 1996). MDA-MB-231 and 
SNB19 cells were cultured in DME (Cellgro; Mediatech) supplemented with 
10% FBS, nonessential amino acids (Sigma-Aldrich), and antibiotics. RNAi </p>

<p>phosphorylation at focal adhesions and mediates a balance 
between tyrosine phosphorylation and dynamic turnover at 
invadopodia and focal adhesions. 
It is interesting that although we find that FAK does not 
localize to invadopodia in MTLn3 cells, it is still able to modu-
late their formation and dynamics, implicating a common sig-
naling mechanism that regulates focal adhesion and invadopodia 
dynamics. It has been proposed that FAK may be important for 
localized Src activity and phosphorylation of substrates that 
regulate cell migration (Schaller et al., 1999). In this context, 
our study is the first to demonstrate that depletion of FAK 
induces a redistribution of active Src from focal adhesions to inva-
dopodia. Although we found that global Src activity is decreased, 
we observed a substantial increase in the number of invadopodia 
containing active Src in FAK-deficient cells. These findings sug-
gest that FAK depletion induces a switch from focal adhesion 
initiation to invadopodia initiation through the spatial regulation 
of Src activity and localized tyrosine phosphorylation. Accord-
ingly, depletion of FAK results in decreased tyrosine phosphor-
ylation of p130Cas and paxillin at focal adhesions and enhanced 
tyrosine phosphorylation of cortactin and Tks5/FISH at invado-
podia. Our findings demonstrate that FAK is critical for local-
ization of active Src to focal adhesions, and it will be important 
to determine what localizes and activates Src at invadopodia. 
Interestingly, with the substrates we examined, we found 
that Tks5/FISH phosphorylation is substantially increased in 
FAK-deficient cells. In accordance with previous reports, we 
find that Tks5 is required for invadopodia/podosome formation 
in MTLn3 cells using RNAi (Seals et al., 2005; Oikawa et al.,  2008; unpublished data). It is intriguing to speculate that phos-
phorylation of Tks5 by Src may play a role in modulating the 
enhancement of invadopodia upon FAK depletion. Mapping 
the Src phosphorylation sites of Tks5 will be critical for 
addressing this hypothesis. However, it is unlikely that a single 
substrate will be sufficient to block the enhancement in invado-
podia upon FAK depletion because Src targets multiple sub-
strates involved in invadopodia and focal adhesion dynamics 
(Luo et al., 2008). Collectively, our experiments provide novel 
insight into how FAK differentially modulates focal adhesion 
and invadopodia dynamics through the spatial and temporal 
regulation of localized c-Src activity. </p>

<p>Figure 9. A model for FAK in invadopodia regulation. FAK and its phosphorylation at Tyr-397 recruit a pool of active Src to mediate localized tyrosine 
phosphorylation of substrates at focal adhesions. A balance between tyrosine phosphorylation at focal adhesions and invadopodia is required for proper 
dynamics and cell migration. Depletion of FAK releases active Src to mediate enhanced phosphorylation of substrates at invadopodia, which impairs focal 
adhesion dynamics but enhances the formation and dynamics of invadopodia; however, this is not sufficient for effective invasion. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 185 • NUMBER 2 • 2009 </p>

<p>
(Artym et al., 2006) and subsequently coating with 10 µg/ml fibronectin 
for 1 h at 37°C. Matrigel (BD) coverslips were prepared by coating a thin 
layer of a 1:10 dilution of Matrigel for 1 h at 37°C. Cells were cultured 
on coverslips for 16 h, fixed, and stained with antibodies. Coverslips 
were imaged using a 60×/1.40 oil objective on an inverted microscope 
(1X-70; Olympus) equipped with a cooled charge-coupled device (CCD) 
camera (CoolSNAP FX; Photometrics) or an inverted microscope (TE300; 
Nikon) equipped with a cooled CCD camera (Orca II; Hamamatsu Photo-
nics). Images were captured into MetaVue (version 6.2; MDS Analytical 
Technologies) or MetaMorph imaging software (version 7.1; MDS Analyti-
cal Technologies). At least 40 cells were counted in each of at least three 
separate experiments performed on separate days. Dotlike structures con-
taining cortactin and/or actin were scored as invadopodia. For ratio-
metric analysis, images were first subjected to high-pass filtration based on 
the water algorithm (Zamir et al., 1999) to remove diffuse background fluor-
escence. The images were thresholded based on the vinculin image be-
cause it had the largest signal to noise ratio, providing the clearest 
distinction between focal adhesions and background. The thresholded 
vinculin image was used to generate a binary image in which values at 
focal adhesions equal 1 and all other values equal 0. A ratio image of 
vinculin/pY416 Src was generated, and high frequency noise was 
removed with a low-pass filter. Ratio images were displayed with similar 
nucleocytoplasmic background as a control for possible differences in 
staining. Ratiometric images presented are representative of at least 50 
cells visualized by immunofluorescence. </p>

<p>Fluorescent gelatin degradation assay 
Alexa Fluor 568-conjugated gelatin was prepared using the Alexa Fluor 
568 protein labeling kit according to the manufacturer's instructions (Invit-
rogen). Oregon green 488-conjugated and Alexa Fluor 568 gelatin-
coated coverslips were prepared as described previously (Artym et al.,  2006). Fluorescent gelatin coverslips were subsequently coated with 10 µg/ml 
fibronectin for 1 h at 37°C. Cells were cultured on coverslips for 16 h, 
fixed, and stained with anticortactin antibody. Active invadopodia were 
identified as areas of cortactin-containing dots that localized with areas of 
matrix degradation. A total of 40-60 cells were counted in at least three 
independent experiments performed on separate days. All measurements 
shown are the mean ± SEM. </p>

<p>Time-lapse fluorescence microscopy and quantification 
of invadopodia dynamics 
Fluorescence imaging of YFP-dSH2 and EGFP-cortactin dynamics were per-
formed using a 60×/1.40 oil objective on an inverted microscope (1X-70; 
Olympus) in a 37°C closed system as previously described (Franco et al.,  2004; Webb et al., 2004; Cortesio et al., 2008). Glass-bottomed dishes 
(35 mm) were coated with 10 µg/ml fibronectin for 1 h at 37°C. Cells 
were plated in Ham's F12 containing 5% FBS and 20 mM Hepes, pH 7.2, 
and were allowed to adhere for 3 h. Fluorescent images were collected 
using a cooled CCD camera (CoolSNAP FX; Hamamatsu Photonics) and 
captured into MetaVue every 1 min for 1 h. Time-lapse sequences from live 
fluorescence imaging were first subjected to high-pass filtration based on 
the water algorithm (Zamir et al., 1999) to remove diffuse background fluor-
escence. For each rate constant, measurements were made on a total of 
40-60 invadopodia in five to six cells from at least three independent 
experiments performed on separate days. </p>

<p>Migration and invasion assays 
Transwell filters (Corning) with 8-µm pores were coated on the bottom sur-
face with 10 µg/ml fibronectin for 1 h at 37°C and were dried after coating. 
Cells were serum starved for 3 h in -MEM with 1% FBS. 10 
5 cells were 
plated in the top chamber and were allowed to migrate toward -MEM con-
taining 10% FBS for 16 h. Cell invasion experiments were performed using 
similar conditions with 8-µm porous chambers coated with Matrigel (BD). 
Cells were allowed to invade through the Matrigel membrane for 48 h. In 
GM6001 treatment experiments, DMSO vehicle or GM6001 were added 
to both upper and lower chambers. Cells on the bottom surface were fixed 
and stained using a Hema-3 stain kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Cells were 
counted from four to six representative 20× or 40× fields per condition in at 
least three independent experiments performed on different days. All data 
are shown normalized to control as mean ± SEM. </p>

<p>Confocal microscopy 
Confocal images were collected using a laser-scanning confocal micro-
scope (Fluoview FV-1000; Olympus) using a 60× Plan Apo/1.45 oil im-
mersion objective with a 3.0 zoom factor and were captured into Fluoview </p>

<p>transfections were performed with Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen) accord-
ing to the manufacturer's instructions. In brief, MTLn3 cells were plated at 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>in 6-well plates 24 h before transfection. MTLn3 cells were transfected with 
120 pmol siRNA and 4 µl Lipofectamine 2000 in 2 ml Opti-MEM I for 45 min 
to 1 h. Sense sequences for Stealth siRNA oligonucleotides (Invitrogen) used are 
as follows: control siRNA, 5-GAAUCUCAUCUAUUUCGUAACGGAC-3; 
FAK siRNA (target A), 5-UGACAGAUACCUAGCAUCUAGCAAA-3; 
and FAK siRNA (target B), 5-UCUCCAUGCCUGAUAAUACUGGCCC-3. 
FAK siRNA (target A) targets a sequence in the 5 untranslated region of FAK. 
All cells were cultured for 48 h before experimental analysis. </p>

<p>DNA constructs 
pMX-GFP-FAK was generated by subcloning murine GFP-FAK from pEGFP-
C1-FAK-HA (provided by D. Schlaepfer, University of California, San Diego, 
La Jolla, CA) into the pMX-IRES-GFP retroviral vector (provided by C. Svendsen, 
University of Wisconsin) from which the IRES-GFP sequence was excised. GFP-
FAK was amplified using the following primers: forward, 5-ACAGGATCCG-
CCACCATGGTGAGCAAGGGCGAG-3 and reverse, 5-ATATGTATTCTA-
GATGATCGTCTGTCGACTCAGTGTGGCCGTGTCTGCCCTAGC-3. 
pMX-GFP-FAK-Y397F and pMX-GFP-FAK-K454R were generated 
using the Quikchange site-directed mutagenesis kit (Agilent Technologies) 
with the following primers: Y397F (forward), 5-CTGTGTCAGAGACAGAT-
GACTTTGCAGAGATCATCGATGAGG-3 and (reverse) 5-CCTCATCGAT-
GATCTCTGCAAAGTCATCTGTCTCTGACACAG-3; and K454R (forward), 
5-GGCTGTTGCAATCAGAACATGTAAAAACTG-3 and (reverse) 5-CAG-
TTTTTACATGTTCTGATTGCAACAGCC-3. Retroviral transfection was per-
formed as described previously (Franco et al., 2004). Cells expressing 
GFP were sorted by FACS (University of Wisconsin Comprehensive Cancer 
Center Flow Cytometry Core Facility). c-Src was amplified from LCNX-c-Src 
(provided by P. Keely, University of Wisconsin), and c-Src-527F was 
amplified from pCDNA3.1(+)-c-Src-527F (Cortesio et al., 2008) using 
the following primers: forward, 5-ATTGTGGGATTCATGGGGAGCAG-
CAAGAGC-3 and reverse, 5-GCCAGGGAATTCCTATAGGTTCTCTC-
CAGGCTG-3. pMX-c-Src-IRES-GFP or pMX-c-Src-527F-IRES-GFP were 
generated by subcloning into the BamHI and EcoRI sites of the pMX-IRES-
GFP vector. Cells positive for c-Src or c-Src-527F were identified by GFP 
expression. FPGV v-Src was a provided by M. Frame (Edinburgh Cancer 
Research Centre, Edinburgh, Scotland, UK). v-Src transformation of MTLn3 
cells was performed as described previously (Cortesio et al., 2008). EGFP-
cortactin has been described previously (Perrin et al., 2006; Cortesio  et al., 2008). YFP-dSH2 was provided by T. Gomez (University of Wisconsin) 
and has been previously described (Kirchner et al., 2003). GFP-vinculin 
was provided by A. Bershadsky and B. Geiger (The Weizmann Institute 
of Science, Rehovot, Israel). GFP-paxillin has been previously described 
(Laukaitis et al., 2001). Transient transfections of YFP-dSH2, GFP-vinculin, 
or GFP-paxillin were performed using Lipofectamine 2000 with 2 µg DNA 
24 h after siRNA transfection. </p>

<p>Immunoblot analysis and immunoprecipitation 
Cells were scraped into lysis buffer (50 mM Tris, pH 7.6, 500 mM NaCl, 
0.1% SDS, 0.5% deoxycholate, 1% Triton X-100, 0.5 mM MgCl 2 , 0.2 mM 
PMSF, 1 µg ml 
1 pepstatin, 2 µg ml 
1 aprotinin, 1 µg ml 
1 leupeptin, and 
1 mM sodium orthovanadate) on ice and clarified by centrifugation. Protein 
concentrations were determined using a bicinchoninic acid protein assay kit 
(Thermo Fisher Scientific) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Immuno-
blotting of cell lysates was performed as previously described (Cortesio  et al., 2008), and blots were imaged with an Infrared Imaging System 
(Odyssey; LI-COR Biosciences). For immunoprecipitations, MTLn3 cells were 
plated 48 h after siRNA transfection on 15-cm dishes coated with 10 µg/ml 
fibronectin. Cells were incubated for 3 h at 37°C in 5% CO 2 , washed once 
with PBS, and lysed in ice-cold modified RIPA buffer (20 mM Tris, pH 8.0, 
150 mM NaCl, 1% Triton X-100, 1% sodium deoxycholate, 2 mM EDTA, 
0.2 mM PMSF, 1 µg ml 
1 pepstatin, 2 µg ml 
1 aprotinin, 1 µg ml 
1 leu-
peptin, and 1 mM sodium orthovanadate). 500 µg cleared lysates were in-
cubated overnight at 4°C with 5 µg antipaxillin (mouse monoclonal), 
anticortactin (mouse monoclonal), or anti-Tks5/FISH (rabbit polyclonal) anti-
bodies or with 5 µg mouse or rabbit IgG. Immune complexes were cap-
tured on GammaBind G-Sepharose beads (GE Healthcare), washed three 
times in RIPA, and analyzed by immunoblotting. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence 
Glass coverslips were acid washed, ethanol sterilized, and coated with 
ECM as previously described (Cortesio et al., 2008). Fibronectin cover-
slips were prepared by coating with 10 µg/ml fibronectin for 1 h at 37°C. 
Fibronectin-gelatin (10 µg/ml fibronectin and 0.2% gelatin) coverslips 
were prepared by coating gelatin coverslips as described previously </p>

<p> 
FAK IMPAIRS INVADOPODIA FORMATION • Chan et al. </p>

<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">Prism</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">4</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software, Inc</rs></p>

<p>We thank Dr. S.K. Yoo for helpful discussions and technical assistance. 
We would like to acknowledge funding by grants from the National 
Institutes of Health to A. Huttenlocher (R01 CA085862-08) and by the Depart-
ment of Defense predoctoral fellowship to C. Cortesio (BC073295). </p>

<p>Submitted: 16 September 2008 
Accepted: 23 March 2009 </p>



<p>JCB • VOLUME 185 • NUMBER 2 • 2009 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>