<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2996622" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>S St tu ud dy y D De es si ig gn n: : A new classification system for throacolumbar spine injury, Thoracolumbar Injury Classification and Severity </p>

<p>Score (TLICS) was evaluated retrospectively. </p>

<p>P Pu ur rp po os se e: : To evaluate intrarater and interrater reliability of newly proposed TLICS schemes and to estimate validity of </p>

<p>TLICS's final treatment recommendation. </p>

<p>O Ov ve er rv vi ie ew w o of f L Li it te er ra at tu ur re e: : Despite numerous literature about thoracolumbar spine injury classifications, there is no consensus </p>

<p>regarding the optimal system. </p>

<p>M Me et th ho od ds s: : Using plain radiographs, computed tomography scanning, magnetic resonance imaging, and medical records, 3 </p>

<p>clssifiers, consisting of 2 spine surgeons and 1 senior orthopaedic surgery resident, reviewed 114 clinical thoracolumbar spine </p>

<p>injury cases retrospectively to classify and calculate injury severity score according to TLICS. This process were repeated on </p>

<p>4 weeks intervals and the scores were then compared with type of treatment that patient ultimately received. </p>

<p>R Re es su ul lt ts s: : The intrarater reliability of TLICS was substantial agreement on total score and injury morphology, almost perfect </p>

<p>agreement on integrity of the posterior ligament complex (PLC) and neurologic status. The interrater reliability was sub-</p>

<p>stantial agreement on injury morphology and integrity of the PLC, moderate agreement on total score, almost perfect agree-</p>

<p>ment on neurologic status. The TLICS schems exhibited satisfactory overall validity in terms of clinical decision making. </p>

<p>C Co on nc cl lu us si io on ns s: : The TLICS was demonstrated acceptable intrarater and interrater reliability and satisfactory validity in terms </p>

<p>of treatment recommendation. </p>

<p>radiology and with the consequent widening knowledge of 
the anatomy as well the biomechanics of thoracolumbar 
injury, continuous efforts have been made to establish a 
more ideal classification system that is applicable to clinical 
practice, and as one of these efforts, Vaccaro et al. [12] in 
2005 suggested the Thoracolumbar Injury Classification 
and Severity Score (TLICS). 
Therefore, we evaluated the intraobserver and interob-
server reliability of the TLICS, and we assessed the validity 
of selecting the treatment based on this classification sys-
tem. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>1. Materials </p>

<p>From January 2004 to June 2009, among the 168 patients 
who received operative or conservative treatment for trau-
matic thoracolumbar injury, 114 cases were recruited as the 
subjects who had accessible medical records, computed 
tomography (CT) and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). 
In the process of selecting the patient group, to exclude 
osteoporotic compression fracture, the age of the patient 
group was arbitrary limited to younger than 56 years, and so 
the study group was composed of 74 male patients and 40 
female patients with a mean age of 40.3 years (range, 15 to 
56 years). As for the causative mechanism of injury, 58 
cases (51%) were falls, 48 cases (42%) were traffic acci-
dents and 8 cases (7%) were miscellaneous. Thirty two </p>

<p>cases (28%) were associated with musculoskeletal injury, 7 
cases (6%) were associated with neurologic injury and 6 
cases (5%) were associated with intraabdominal organ 
injury. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>The score of the patient group, according to the TLICS, 
was retrospectively examined 2 times by 3 classifiers who 
were orthopedic surgeons, by viewing the thoracolumbar 
simple radiographs, the CT, the MRI and the medical 
records at 4 week intervals. 
The TLICS consists of three variables: 1) the morphology 
of the fracture pattern as assessed by radiological tests, 2) 
whether injury in the posterior ligamentous complex (PLC) 
is involved or not, and 3) the neurologic status of the patient 
(Table 1). After scoring each variable, the treatment plans 
are determined according to the sum (Table 2). When scor-
ing the variables of the TLICS, the morphology of injury, 
based on the radiology of the thoracolumbar injury, was 
classified as 3 types: 1) the compression type, 2) the 
translocation/rotation type and 3) the distraction type, and 
they were each scored as 1, 3 and 4 points, respectively. 
Additionally, concerning the presence of a burst fracture 
with the compression injuries, 1 point was added and thus it 
was scored as 2 points. For cases with multiple injuries of 
an identical type, no more than one injury was added to be 
scored. For cases with the combination of multiple different </p>

<p>110 / ASJ: Vol. 4, No. 2, 2010 </p>

<p>Table 1. Summary of the revised scale, the TLICS </p>

<p>Component 
Qualifiers 
Score </p>

<p>Morphology type 
Compression 
1 
Burst 
1 
Translational/Rotational 
3 
Distraction 
4 
Neurological involvement 
Intact 
0 
Nerve root 
2 
Cord, conus medullaris 
Complete 
2 
Incomplete 
3 
Cauda equna 
3 
PLC 
Intact 
0 
Injury suspected/Indeterminate 
2 
Injured 
3 </p>

<p>TLICS: Thoracolumbar Injury Classification and Severity 
Score, PLC: Posterior ligamentous complex. </p>

<p>Table 2. Summary of scores associated with various fracture 
management points </p>

<p>Management 
Score </p>

<p>Nonoperative 
≤ 3 
Nonoperative or Operative 
4 
Operative 
≥ 5 </p>

<p>Table 3. Interpretation of Kappa statistics </p>

<p>k-value 
Agreement </p>

<p>&lt; 0 
&lt; Chance 
0.01-0.20 
Slight 
0.21-0.40 
Fair 
0.41-0.60 
Moderate 
0.61-0.80 
Substantial 
0.81-0.99 
Almost perfect </p>

<p>types of injuries, only one injury type with the highest 
points was scored. Regarding the score of the injury in the 
posterior ligamentous complex, the cases with no other 
injury were 0 points, the cases with unclear injury were 2 
points and the cases with apparent injury were scored as 3 
points. As for the score of the neurologic status, the cases 
without neurological symptoms on the neurologic examina-
tion were 0 points, the cases with injury at the nerve root 
were 2 points and the cases with complete or incomplete 
neurological injury in the spinal cord and the conus 
medullaris were 2 points and 3 points, respectively. The 
cases with injury in the cauda equine were scored as 3 </p>

<p>points (Figs. 1 and 2). 
Afterward, the intrarater reliability, as well as the inter-
rater reliability of the score for each variable and sum, were 
evaluated by Cohen's unweighted k-value and Spearman' s 
rank order correlation. For the statistical distinction of the 
Kappa values, the distinction according to the guideline of 
Viera and Garrett [13] was applied (Table 3). In addition, 
the sensitivity and specificity were evaluated by the percent 
of correct treatment protocols according to the sum of the 
TLICS and the treatment actually performed on the patients. 
The validity of selecting treatment protocols according to 
this classification was also assessed. <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 13.0</rs> (SPSS </p>

<p>Reliability and Validity of TLICS / 111 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. A neurologically intact patient (0 point) with compression fracture (1 point) and intact posterior ligamentous 
complex (0 point). Total score was 1, thus treatment recommendation is non-surgical treatment. </p>

<p>Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) was used for statistical analysis. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The intrarater reliability of each variable of the TLICS 
showed substantial agreement (k = 0.753) for determining 
the injury pattern, almost perfect agreement (k = 0.81) for </p>

<p>whether there was injury in the posterior ligamentous com-
plex, almost perfect agreement (k = 0.96) for the neurologi-
cal status assessment and substantial agreement (k = 0.724) 
for the sum of the total score (Table 4). In regard to the 
interrater reliability of each variable, determination of the 
injury pattern showed substantial agreement (k = 0.608), 
there was substantial agreement (k = 0.641) for whether </p>

<p>112 / ASJ: Vol. 4, No. 2, 2010 </p>

<p>Fig. 2. T12 flexion burst fracture in patient with incomplete spinal cord injury. Compression injury (1 point) with 
burst component (1 point), injury to posterior ligament complex (3 point) and incomplete spinal cord injury (3 point). 
Total score was 8, thus treatment recommendation is surgery. </p>

<p>there was injury in the posterior ligament complex, almost 
perfect agreement (k = 0.91) for the neurological status 
assessment and moderate agreement (k = 0.576) for the sum 
of the total score (Table 5). 
Regarding the validity of the selection of treatment proto-
cols according to the TLICS classification, of the total 684 
cases, 114 cases were double-measured by the 3 investiga-
tors. There were 362 cases for which the actual total TLICS 
score was higher than 5 points, and among them, surgery 
was performed for 355 cases. Among the 195 cases with the 
total score lower than 3 points, surgery was not performed 
for 176 cases. It was shown that the percent of correctly 
selecting treatment according to the TLICS was 95%, the 
sensitivity was 98%, and the specificity was 90% (Table 6). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The classification of traumatic thoracolumbar injury was 
first reported in 1929 by  [7], and afterwards, spinal 
fracture was classified to 5 types according to the mecha-
nism of injury. In 1949, Nicoll [14] revised the concept of 
instability, and Nicoll [14] claimed that the fracture gap 
caused by the comminution of the vertebral body as well as 
injury of the PLC could induce instability. In 1970, 
Holdsworth [15] explained thoracolumbar injury by intro-
ducing the concept of the two-column theory. Based on this, 
Louis [16] in 1977 was able to explain the structure of the 
vertebral body by the three-column concept. 
With the rapid development of radiology, Denis [17] in </p>

<p>1983 introduced the three-column concept based on the 
findings of thoracolumbar CT. According to the injury 
mechanism and the degree of injury, he classified spinal 
injury into 4 types of major spinal injury (compression frac-
ture, burst fracture, seat-belt injury and fracture-dislocation) 
and 4 types of minor spinal injury (articular process frac-
ture, transverse process fracture, spinous process fracture 
and isthmus fracture). With the widening knowledge of the 
mechanisms of spinal injury, McCormack et al. [18] in 
1994 suggested the loading-sharing classification for deter-
mining the necessity of reinforcing the anterior column dur-
ing surgical treatment for burst fracture. In addition, Magerl 
et al. [19] considered the major external forces placed on 
the vertebral body as compression, distraction and rotation 
and according to this, they reported the AO classification 
that divides thoracolumbar injury to a total of 53 fracture 
groups. 
In such a manner, numerous classification systems for 
thoracolumbar injury have been reported, and studies on 
their validity have been continuously conducted, yet none 
of them is currently accepted as an optimal classification. 
The prerequisite of an ideal classification method for thora-
columbar injury includes the following factors: it should be 
comprehensive and it can be readily applied, the reliability 
and reproducibility should also be ensured and it should be 
of help to determine the degree of injury and to decide the 
treatment strategy, and furthermore, it should be of help to 
evaluate the prognosis. In addition, it should be able to be 
used as a common language for effective and reliable com-</p>

<p>Reliability and Validity of TLICS / 113 </p>

<p>Table 4. Intrarater statistics </p>

<p>Value Standard error p-value </p>

<p>Injury morphology 
k-value 
0.753 
0.032 
0 
PLC 
k-value 
0.81 
0.027 
0 
Neurology change 
k-value 
0.96 
0 
0 
TLICS total 
k-value 
0.724 
0.027 
0 </p>

<p>PLC: Posterior ligamentous complex, TLICS: Thoracolumbar 
Injury Classification and Severity Score. </p>

<p>Table 6. Summary of validity data </p>

<p>% Correct 
Sensitivity 
Specificity 
PPV 
NPV </p>

<p>TLICS 
95 
0.98 
0.9 
0.95 
0.96 </p>

<p>PPV: Positive predictive value, NPV: Negative predictive value, TLICS: Thoracolumbar Injury Classification and Severity Score. </p>

<p>Table 5. Interrater statistics </p>

<p>Value Standard error p-value </p>

<p>Injury morphology 
k-value 
0.608 
0.026 
0 
PLC 
k-value 
0.641 
0.024 
0 
Neurology change 
k-value 
0.91 
0 
0 
TLICS total 
k-value 
0.576 
0.021 
0 </p>

<p>PLC: Posterior ligamentous complex, TLICS: Thoracolumbar 
Injury Classification and Severity Score. </p>

<p>munication among clinicians. For this, assessment of both 
the intraobserver and interobserver reliability is essential. 
The classification systems that have been recently applied 
for thoracolumbar injury most frequently in clinical practice 
include the Denis [17] classification and the AO classifica-
tion according to Margerl et al. [19]. Blauth et al. [20] have 
reported that the interobserver reliability of the basic type of 
AO classification (A, B and C type) was low (fair agree-
ment, k = 0.33), and in regard to the AO classification, 
when the basic type was subclassified into subgroups, the 
interobserver reliability decreased even more. Oner et al. [8] 
and Wood et al. [9] have reported in their study that the 
Denis classification system showed higher interobserver 
reliability than did the AO classification system (Oner, k = 
0.60, 0.35; Wood, k = 0.606, 0.475). Nonetheless, the two 
classification methods showed unsatisfactory interobserver 
reliability. The AO classification system includes the most 
abundant information on the classification of injury, and so 
it has the advantage that it could classify almost any types </p>

<p>of injury, yet it has many limitations to be applied to clini-
cal practice due to the unavoidable complexity and the con-
sequent low reproducibility. On the other hand, the Denis 
classification is too simple, and so it has the limitation that 
it does not contain important anatomical and pathophysio-
logic factors that play an important role in deciding the 
treatment protocols for injury in the PLC or for nerve 
injury. In 1986, Bucholz and Grill [21] pointed out that the 
limitation of the Denis [17] classification system results 
from the absence of considering the dynamic mechanism of 
spinal injury and the level of the associated nerve injury. 
Vaccaro et al. [22] in 2005 suggested a new classification 
method, the Thoracolumbar Injury Severity Score (TLISS) 
and this would compensate for the problems of the previous 
classification systems and satisfy the requirements of an 
ideal classification system. This classification scores three 
variables that are considered to be directly associated with 
the stability of the vertebral body and the prognosis. These 
variables are composed of the mechanism of injury as deter-</p>

<p>114 / ASJ: Vol. 4, No. 2, 2010 </p>

<p>Fig. 3. A neurologically intact patient (0 point) with compression injury of L2 vertebral body (1 point) with burst 
component (1 point) and intact posterior ligamentous complex (0 point). Total score was 2, thus treatment recom-
mendation is non-surgical treatment. But, about 40% canal compromise with kyphotic deformity was seen and we 
treated this patient with surgery. </p>

<p>mined by radiologic tests, the present of an injury in the 
PLC and the neurologic status, and all of these are scored to 
help decide on the treatment plans. Afterward, the TLISS 
was modified to the TLICS that includes the radiological 
injury pattern (the morphology and the fracture pattern), 
which could be classified objectively instead of subjectively 
for determining the mechanisms of injuries. Vaccaro et al. 
[12] later reported the high reliability and reproducibility of 
the TLICS. In addition, Whang et al. [23] reported the 
results of a study conducted on the reliability of the TLICS, 
and this revealed the satisfactory reliability of the TLICS by 
showing that determining the injury pattern showed moder-
ate agreement (k = 0.626), the presence of injury in the PLC 
showed moderate agreement (k = 0.447) and the total score 
showed moderate agreement (k = 0.455). 
As for our study, the interobserver reliability of the 
TLICS was higher than substantial agreement for all the 
categories, and the interobserver reliability showed higher 
than substantial agreement for all the categories, except that 
the total score showed moderate agreement (k = 0.576), and 
our results were found to be better than the results reported </p>

<p>by Whang et al. [23]. Until now, the k-value required for a 
clinically reliable classification system has been determined 
to be higher than 0.55 [24], and when considering the opin-
ion of Oner et al. [25] that the standard is too strict to apply 
to a classification system for traumatic vertebral fracture, 
our results could be considered to show excellent reliability. 
In addition, the results of our study was found to be excel-
lent as compared with the intraobserver and interobserver 
reliability of the Denis classification system and the AO 
classification system reported by Oner et al. [8] and Wood 
et al. [9], respectively. 
In other words, when establishing a treatment plan 
through the TLICS, as compared with the treatment method 
that was actually applied to patients, the validity of the deci-
sion-making for surgery was satisfactory for the percent 
correct, the sensitivity and the specificity. Nevertheless, the 
specificity was relatively low (90%), which might have 
resulted from the fact that the choice of treatment method 
varied depending on the preference of clinicians in some 
cases. Indeed, in our study we administered operative treat-
ments for the burst fracture with the invasion of a bony </p>

<p>Reliability and Validity of TLICS / 115 </p>

<p>Fig. 4. L1 burst fracture in patient without neurologic symptom (0 point). Compression injury (1 point) with burst 
component (1 point) and intact posterior ligamentous complex (0 point). Total score was 2, thus treatment recom-
mendation is non-surgical treatment. But, fracture of T12 spinous process was seen and our treatment choice was 
surgery. </p>

<p>fragment to the spinal canal reaching 50% that were without 
injury in the PLC and neurologic symptoms (TLICS total 
score = 2), and for the cases of burst fracture associated 
with fracture in the lamina or fracture in the adjacent spin-
ous process and these case were without neurologic symp-
toms and injury in the PLC (TLICS total score = 2) (Figs. 3 
and 4). In addition, for the cases that injury in the PLC is 
not apparent and it is only suspected, operative treatment 
may be preferred depending on the clinician' s opinion. Fur-
ther evaluation is required when considering that the previ-
ous classification systems were unrelated to the selection of 
treatment plans and the studies on the validity of selecting 
treatment plans were meager as compared with the studies 
conducted on the reliability of TLICS. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>The ideal classification system of thoracolumbar injury 
should be comprehensive, easy to apply, it ensures suffi-
cient reliability and reproducibility, and it should be of help 
to determine the degree of injury and for deciding the treat-
ment plan. Furthermore, the ideal classification system 
should be helpful for determining the prognosis. The TLICS 
showed excellent interobserver and intraobserver reliability 
as well as satisfactory validity for selecting a treatment 
plan. Therefore, it could be considered a superior classifica-
tion system that is applicable in clinical practice, as com-
pared with the previous classification systems. </p>



</text></tei>