<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2781407" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">


<p>TMP21 has been shown to be associated with the -secretase 
complex and can specifically regulate -cleavage without affect-
ing -mediated proteolysis. To explore the basis of this activity, 
TMP21 modulation of -secretase activity was investigated 
independent of -cleavage using an amyloid-precursor pro-
tein (APP) construct which lacks the amyloid intracellular 
domain domain. The APP construct behaves similarly to the 
full-length precursor protein with respect to -and -cleavages 
and is able to undergo normal -processing. Co-expression of 
APP and TMP21 resulted in the accumulation of membrane-
embedded higher molecular weight A-positive fragments, 
consistent with an inhibition of -secretase cleavage. The APP 
system was used to examine the functional domains of TMP21 
through the investigation of a series of TMP21-p24a chimera 
proteins. It was found that chimeras containing the transmem-
brane domain bound to the -secretase complex and could 
decrease -secretase proteolytic processing. This was con-
firmed though investigation of a synthetic peptide correspond-
ing to the TMP21 transmembrane helix. The isolated TMP21 
TM peptide but not the homologous p24a domain was able to 
reduce A production in a dose-dependent fashion. These 
observations suggest that the TMP21 transmembrane domain 
promotes its association with the presenilin complex that 
results in decreased -cleavage activity. </p>

<p>Alzheimer disease is a progressive neurodegenerative disor-
der and the most common cause of dementia worldwide. One </p>

<p>of the main histopathological hallmarks in Alzheimer disease is 
senile plaque, an extracellular protein deposit composed pri-
marily of the amyloid -peptide (A), 5 which is generated by 
sequential cleavages of the amyloid-precursor protein 
(APP) by -and -secretase activities (1). Cleavage by 
-secretase occurs within the APP transmembrane domain 
at several sequences, such as the -site, to produce A40/42, 
and the -site, which results in the release of the cytosolic 
amyloid intracellular domain (AICD) (2). AICD is targeted 
to the nucleus and regulates transcription of several genes 
including KAI1 (3, 4), glycogen synthase kinase 3 (4 -6), 
neprilysin (7, 8), p53 (9), epidermal growth factor receptor 
(10), LRP1 (11), Tip60, APP, or -site APP-cleaving enzyme 
(BACE) (4). 
Several lines of evidence have shown that /-secretase activ-
ity requires multimeric membrane protein complexes, the pre-
senilin complexes, which are composed of at least four compo-
nents: presenilin (PS1 or PS2), nicastrin (NCT), anterior 
pharynx-defective phenotype 1 (APH-1), and presenilin 
enhancer 2 (PEN-2) (12-16). All four components appear to be 
essential for /-secretase activity (17-19). NCT and APH-1 form 
an initial subcomplex to which full-length PS1 or PS2 and PEN-2 
are added (18, 20, 21). During maturation of the presenilin com-
plexes, nicastrin is glycosylated, and presenilins are cleaved into N-
and C-terminal fragments which remain associated as a het-
erodimer in the active high molecular weight complex (20, 22). In 
these complexes presenilins have been proposed to serve as the 
catalytic subunit (23), whereas the large ectodomain of NCT plays 
an essential role in substrate recognition (24, 25). 
It has been demonstrated that TMP21, a member of p24 
cargo protein with homology to p24a, binds the presenilin com-
plexes and acts as a modulator resulting in the selective sup-
pression of -but not -secretase cleavage (26). TMP21 small 
interfering RNA suppression enhances the production of A, 
whereas overexpression or the ablation of TMP21 does not </p>

<p>affect AICD production. In this context TMP21 has no effect on 
p53 or NEP, which are two target genes of AICD activation (27). 
In the current study, the effects of TMP21 on -secretase 
activity were investigated independent of -cleavage using an 
APP construct which lacks the AICD domain (terminates at 
A49). The APP fragment behaves similarly to the full-length 
precursor protein with respect to and cleavages and is able 
to undergo -processing, which is sensitive to inhibition by 
DFK167 (28). Co-expression of APP and TMP21 resulted in 
the accumulation of membrane-embedded higher molecular 
weight A-positive fragments, consistent with an inhibition of 
-secretase cleavage. This reporter system was used to deter-
mine the functional domain of TMP21 through the investiga-
tion of a series of TMP21-p24a chimera proteins. In addition, a 
synthetic peptide corresponding to the TMP21 transmem-
brane helix but not the p24a TM domain was able to reduce A 
secretion in a dose-dependent fashion. These observations 
indicate that the transmembrane domain of TMP21 is a pri-
mary site of action, and its physical association with the prese-
nilin complex can alter -cleavage. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>Mutagenesis and cDNA Constructs-TMP21 and p24a 
tagged at the C-terminal with the FLAG epitope were cloned in 
pcDNA4 as previously described (26). Chimera constructs 
between TMP21 and p24a cDNA were obtained following a 
three-step PCR protocol as previously described (36), and then 
all constructs were confirmed by DNA sequencing and cloned 
in pcDNA4 vector with the FLAG epitope at the C terminus. 
APP constructs containing a stop codon at the end of the 
transmembrane domain of human APP (isoforms correspond-
ing to 695 or 751) were cloned in pcDNA3 as previously 
described (28). The wild-type APP constructs (APP WT iso-
forms 695 or 751) were cloned into pcDNA3. 
Cell Culture, Transfection, and Treatment-Native HEK293 
cells or stably transfected HEK293 cells expressing the Swedish 
APP mutant (APPSwe) were maintained in Dulbecco's modi-
fied Eagle's medium (Invitrogen) supplemented with 10% fetal 
bovine serum. Transient transfections were performed in 
native HEK293 cells by using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen) 
or FuGENE 6 (Roche Applied Science) according to the manu-
facturer's instructions, and then cells were collected 24 -48 h 
after transfection. 
Membrane Fraction Preparation and Immunoprecipitation-
HEK293 cells were harvested and homogenized in buffer A (5 
mM HEPES, pH 7.4, 1 mM EDTA, 0.25 M sucrose, protease 
inhibitor mixture from Roche Applied Science). The homoge-
nate was clarified by centrifugation at 1000 g for 5 min at 4 °C, 
and the supernatant was centrifuged at 100,000 g for 1 h at 
4 °C. For immunoprecipitation of the intracellular A long spe-
cies, cell pellets or membrane pellets were homogenized in 
radioimmune precipitation assay buffer (50 mM Tris, pH 7.4, 
150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 1% Triton, 0.5% deoxycholate, 0.1% 
SDS, protease inhibitor mixture). Isolates of either total lysate 
(2.5 mg) or membrane fraction (800 g) were diluted in 1 ml of 
radioimmune precipitation assay buffer. For immunoprecipita-
tion of presenilin complexes, membrane pellets were homoge-
nized in buffer B (25 mM HEPES, pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 2 mM </p>

<p>EDTA, 1% CHAPSO, protease inhibitor mixture). Isolates of the 
membrane fraction (800 g) were diluted in 1 ml of buffer B to a 
final concentration of 0.5% CHAPSO. After preclearing with pro-
tein G-Sepharose 4 fast flow (GE Healthcare) for 1 h at 4 °C, lysates 
were subjected to immunoprecipitation with the appropriate anti-
body (a mouse monoclonal anti-A 6E10 (from Covance) or a 
mouse monoclonal anti-FLAG (from Sigma) antibodies). Immu-
noprecipitants were recovered by overnight incubation at 4 °C 
with protein G-Sepharose. Beads were washed 3 times with radio-
immune precipitation assay buffer or buffer B (0.5% CHAPSO) 
and once with phosphate-buffered saline. 
SDS/PAGE and Western Blot Analyses-Whole cell lysates 
(total protein 50 g), membrane lysates (protein 25-50 g), and 
immunoprecipitated proteins were dissolved in SDS sample 
buffer, separated on Tris-Tricine gels 16% or Tris-glycine gels 
4 -20% (Invitrogen), and transferred to nitrocellulose membranes. 
Target proteins were visualized by enhanced chemiluminescence 
(ECL Amersham Biosciences) with the following antibodies: 
mouse monoclonal anti-A 6E10 (Covance), anti-A 4G8 
(Covance), rabbit polyclonal anti-PS1-NTF, anti-NCT-Nt, anti-
FLAG (from Sigma), and anti-APP CTF antibodies. 
Peptide Synthesis and Assays-The TMP21 transmembrane 
domain sequence containing three N-and C-terminal lysine 
residues (KKK-VLYFSIFSMFCLIGLATWQVFYL-KKK) and 
the p24a transmembrane domain (KKK-VVLWSFFEALVL-
VAMTLGQIYYL-KKK) peptides were synthesized by standard 
Fmoc (N-(9-fluorenyl)methoxycarbonyl)-based solid phase 
methodology. The terminal lysines were added to increase pep-
tide solubility. Peptides were purified by reverse phase high 
pressure liquid chromatography using water/acetonitrile mix-
tures buffered with 0.1% trifluoroacetic acid on a POROS 20R2 
column. Stock solutions of both peptides were prepared in 
DMSO and added at the desired final concentrations (10 and 30 
g/ml) to the media of cultures of HEK293 cells stably express-
ing the Swedish variant of APP. Media was collected at different 
time points and A40 levels were determined by ELISA. 
A40 ELISA and Cell-free Assays-A40 levels were meas-
ured by ELISA assays using conditioned medium collected 
from HEK293 cells after a transient transfection or a treatment 
with synthetic peptide (TM-TMP21, TM-p24). The enzyme-
linked immunoabsorbent assay ELISA was performed according 
to the manufacturer's instructions (BIOSOURCE. Determination 
of -secretase activity by cell-free assay was as previously described 
(26). Briefly, membrane fractions were isolated from HEK293 cells 
and incubated with recombinant FLAG-tagged APP-C100. 
TMP21 and p24a synthetic peptides solubilized in DMSO were 
added to the reaction mixture at the desired concentrations and 
A40 generated by proteolysis was measured by ELISA. 
Statistical Analysis-Statistical analyses were performed 
with <rs id="software-0" type="software">PRISM</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Graph-Pad Software, San Diego. CA</rs>) by 
using the unpaired Student's t test for pairwise comparisons. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Effects of TMP21 on -Secretase Processing in an APP 
Reporter Assay-TMP21 is a type 1 transmembrane protein 
member of the p24 cargo-protein family that is involved in 
vesicular targeting and protein transport (29). In addition to its 
trafficking functions, TMP21 has been shown to specifically </p>

<p>TMP21 Functional Domain </p>

<p>OCTOBER 16, 2009 • VOLUME 284 • NUMBER 42 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 28635 </p>

<p>regulate proteolysis at the -secretase site, whereas no effects 
on -cleavage were observed (26, 27, 30). A C-terminal-trun-
cated APP construct terminating at the -site was employed to 
allow investigation of TMP21 activity independent of -medi-</p>

<p>ated cleavage (Fig. 1A). This APP protein is recognized by an 
A antibody targeting the N-terminal A residues 1-17 (6E10) 
(Fig. 1B) and undergoes normal processing by -, -, and 
-secretase to produce similar levels of A peptides and soluble 
APP (sAPP) fragment in the absence of AICD production 
(Fig. 1, C and D). Comparable findings have been previously 
reported which confirm that the APP variant is comparable 
with the wild-type protein but permits examination of -secre-
tase activities without any complicating factors associated with 
-related processing (28). 
Co-transfection of APP-WT or APP with C-terminal 
FLAG-tagged TMP21 resulted in a slight increase in expression 
levels of full-length proteins (Fig. 2A). A similar minor increase 
was observed for APP-CTF immunoreactivity in cells overex-
pressing APP-WT protein. This finding is consistent with pre-
vious investigations that demonstrated dual effects of TMP21 
on -secretase activity and APP trafficking (26, 27, 30). How-
ever, unique effects in -cleavage were observed in cells co-
expressing the APP construct with TMP21. Immunoprecipi-
tation and reprobing with an anti-A antibody (6E10 
N-terminal epitope) revealed the expected APP-CTF for the 
wild-type protein (Fig. 2B, short exposure, top panel). Upon 
longer exposure, two intracellular A-reactive bands were 
observed in cells expressing APP at higher molecular weights 
than are seen for the synthetic A40 peptide (Fig. 2B, long 
exposure, bottom panel). These A-reactive bands accumu-
lated in the cells co-expressing TMP21. These bands were only 
observed after immunoprecipitation followed by Western blot-
ting, suggesting that they are a small percentage of the total 
A-related species. 
The appearance of these bands suggests that after extracel-
lular cleavage (,, or cleavage) the -secretase is impaired 
by TMP21 expression, leading to unprocessed intracellular A 
species terminating at the -site (corresponds to A residue 
49). The molecular weights of these TMP21-induced bands are 
in the range of -to-A (residues 1-49; molecular mass, 5.3 
kDa) and possibly a -to-fragment (residues 11-49; molec-
ular mass, 4.1 kDa). These frag-
ments also contained the A N ter-
minus as shown by their reactivity 
to different antibodies. A-positive 
species were isolated by immuno-
precipitation from cells expressing 
APP and probed with antibodies 
recognizing A residues 1-17 
(6E10) and 17-24 (4G8). The higher 
molecular weight bands induced by 
TMP21 expression were detected 
by both antibodies and were not 
seen in control mock-transfected 
cells (Fig. 3, A and B). These data 
suggest that the bands are produced 
by normal cleavage at or near the 
-secretase site and their higher 
molecular weight as compared with 
A-(1-40) would be consistent 
with impaired -processing in the 
presence of TMP21. The molecular </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Characterization of the APP construct. A, schematic represen-
tation of the wild-type human amyloid-precursor protein (APPWT) and its 
cleavage sites by the indicated secretases. APP corresponds to the N-termi-
nal fragment of APP generated by -cleavage (APP). 6E10 antibody recog-
nizes the 1-17 sequence of A, 4G8 antibody recognizes the 17-24 sequence 
of A, and APP C-terminal antibody recognizes the cytoplasmic tail. B, HEK293 
cells were transiently transfected with APPWT or APP cDNA as described and 
analyzed by Western blot for detection of APP full-length (APP FL) or the APP 
C-terminal fragment (APP CTF) using different APP antibodies (6E10, APP Ct). 
The APP-CTF-directed antibody does not label APP, which lacks the C termi-
nus. C, medium of HEK293 cells transfected with APPWT or APP cDNA were 
analyzed by immunoblotting to detect the secreted extracellular fragment 
soluble APP using 6E10 antibody. D, level of secreted A40 peptide were 
analyzed by ELISA from medium of HEK293 cells transfected with APPWT or 
APP cDNA. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. TMP21-induced accumulation of intracellular A-positive fragments in cells expressing APP. 
A, HEK293 cells were transiently co-transfected with TMP21-FLAG and APPWT or APP cDNA, then analyzed by 
Western blot for detection of full-length APP (APP FL), the APP C-terminal fragment (APP CTF), or TMP21-FLAG 
protein. B, intracellular A species were immunoprecipitated using 6E10 antibody (IP WB) in HEK293 cells 
transiently co-transfected with TMP21-FLAG along with APP-WT or APP cDNA, then detected by Western blot 
using 6E10 antibody (short exposure, top panel). Note the high molecular weight intracellular A at 5 kDa 
recognized by 6E10 antibody in cells overexpressing APP and A-positive bands at 6.5 and 5 kDa protected 
by co-transfection with TMP21 (longer exposure, bottom panel). Synthetic A40 peptide was used as a molec-
ular weight marker and positive control. </p>

<p>TMP21 Functional Domain </p>



<p>VOLUME 284 • NUMBER 42 • OCTOBER 16, 2009 </p>

<p>weights of the bands are comparable with that of a synthetic A 
1-49 peptide, which indicates that the A-positive fragments 
would be consistent with an incompletely processed A-con-
taining APP fragments (Fig. 3C). Similar bands were also 
observed in cells expressing the APP isoform when treated 
with the -secretase inhibitor, Compound E, which supports 
the possibility that they are generated by impaired -processing 
(Fig. 3C). 
The fact that these fragments contain the hydrophobic ter-
minus of A was supported by fractionation studies. Mem-
brane and soluble cytosolic fractions from cells expressing 
APP with or without TMP21 were isolated, and the A-posi-
tive species were immunoprecipitated. It should be noted that 
APP is recovered in the membrane fraction, in agreement with 
the demonstration that APP behaved as a membrane-bound 
type 1 protein as does APP (28). Probing with anti-A (6E10) 
revealed the presence in the membrane fraction but not in the 
soluble fraction of the high molecular weight, presumably 
unprocessed fragments that were induced by TMP21 expres-
sion (Fig. 4). These findings support the fact that the fragments 
are membrane-embedded and, therefore, likely contain the 
APP transmembrane domain terminating at the -cleavage site 
(i.e. A49). 
Taken together, these findings indicate that in the absence of 
any rate-limiting -cleavage, TMP21 has a unique effect on </p>

<p>-secretase activity, resulting in the accumulation of intracel-
lular membrane-embedded A-related species. These results 
are reminiscent of recent reports describing an accumulation of 
intracellular longer A species when -secretase activity is 
inhibited at the site but not at the site (31-33). TMP21-
mediated -secretase inhibition was seen only with the APP 
construct, and no significant level of membrane-embedded 
A-reactive fragments was observed with the co-expression of 
APP-WT and TMP21. This suggest that one of the main targets 
for TMP21 may be the membrane-embedded A fragment 
(residues 1-49) that is generated after release of the AICD cyto-
plasmic tail. In addition, this finding provides a reporter assay 
to investigate which domains are responsible for its activity. 
Identification of TMP21 Functional Domains-The TMP21-
related and homologous cargo protein, p24a, was found to be 
inactive with respect to regulating -secretase activity (26). 
Therefore, p24a protein was used to create a series of chimera 
proteins to identify which domains of TMP21 modulate 
-secretase activity as seen in the APP reporter assay. Chime-
ras are all FLAG-tagged and included substitution of the trans-
membrane (TM) and C terminus of TMP21 into p24a (TMP21-
TMCt), replacement of the p24a N terminus with the 
corresponding extracellular domain of TMP21 (TMP21-Nt), 
replacement of p24a TM with TMP21 (TMP21-TM), and a 
final construct in which the TMP21 C terminus was inserted 
into full-length p24a (TMP21-Ct) (Fig. 5A). 
The chimeras as well as wild-type TMP21 and p24a were 
transiently expressed in HEK293 cells, and no effects were 
observed on the levels of -secretase components on the levels 
of nicastrin maturation or PS1 processing (Fig. 5B). The chime-
ras all expressed at reasonable levels, suggesting that they were 
not misfolded or rapidly degraded. Two of the constructs, 
TMP21-TMCt and TMP21-TM, were found at slightly higher 
levels as compared with wild-type TMP21 and may, therefore, 
be well tolerated by the cells. Co-immunoprecipitation studies 
were conducted for the FLAG-tagged proteins, which success-
fully pulled down all of the chimeras (Fig. 5C). FLAG-tagged 
wild-type TMP21 and p24a were used as controls, and as pre-
viously reported, TMP21 but not p24a interacts with mature </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Intracellular A-positive fragments are generated by impaired 
-processing and migrate at the level of A1-49 synthetic peptides. 
Intracellular A species were immunoprecipitated from membrane fractions 
using 6E10 antibody (6E10) in HEK293 cells transiently co-transfected with 
APP in the presence and absence of TMP21-FLAG, then detected by immu-
noblotting using 6E10 (A) or 4G8 (B) antibodies. C, HEK293 cells were trans-
fected with APP in the presence or absence of TMP21-TM, then treated or 
not with Compound E (100 nM). Intracellular A species were then immuno-
precipitated and detected using 6E10 antibody. Both TMP21-TM overexpres-
sion and Compound E treatment led to an accumulation of A-positive frag-
ment. Synthetic A standard peptides were used as molecular weight 
markers. </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. TMP21-induced A species are associated with the lipid 
bilayer. HEK293 cells were transiently transfected with the APP vector in the 
presence or absence of wild-type TMP21. Empty vector (pcDNA3) was used as 
a negative control. Membrane and cytosolic soluble fractions were prepared 
and probed with anti-FLAG antibodies for TMP21 detection or immunopre-
cipitated (IP) using anti-A 6E10 and analyzed for detection of intracellular A 
species. Both TMP21 and A positive fragments were embedded in the mem-
brane. No TMP21 or A-species were detected in the soluble fraction. </p>

<p>TMP21 Functional Domain </p>

<p>OCTOBER 16, 2009 • VOLUME 284 • NUMBER 42 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 28637 </p>

<p>NCT and the PS1-NTF (Fig. 5C). However, significant differ-
ences were observed between the chimeras. Association with 
mature NCT and the PS1-NTF were only found for con-</p>

<p>structs containing the TM domain 
of TMP21 (TMP21-TMCt and 
TMP21-TM; Fig. 5C). In contrast, 
no binding was observed for chi-
mera containing the N-or C-termi-
nal fragments of TMP21. These 
observations indicate that the trans-
membrane domain of TMP21 is 
essential for its physical interaction 
with the -secretase complex and 
may be the primary site of action. 
To investigate their functional 
aspects, TMP21 chimeras were co-
transfected with APP. Full-length 
APP was found to be expressed at 
higher levels for cells co-transfected 
with wild-type TMP21 or the chi-
meras TMP21-TMCt or TMP21-
TM, containing the transmembrane 
domain (Fig. 6A). This phenome-
non may be the result of the effect of 
TMP21 on APP trafficking as noted 
previous (30). Examination of the 
intracellular A-containing frag-
ments by immunoprecipitation fol-
lowed by Western blotting revealed 
that the two higher molecular 
weight species were only seen for 
the chimeras containing the TMP21 
transmembrane domain (TMP21, 
TMP21-TMCt, and TMP21-TM, 
Fig. 6B). This is consistent with the 
observed interactions of the chime-
ras with PS1 and NCT which were 
dependent upon the TMP21 TM 
domain. The relative intensity of 
A-positive fragments observed in 
cells expressing TMP21-TMCt and 
TMP21-TM chimeras was higher 
than for the wild-type TMP21. This 
could be because of slightly higher 
levels of the chimeras, as FLAG 
immunoreactivities were more pro-
nounced (Fig. 6A). Alternatively, 
this may reflect the fact that the chi-
meric proteins were more readily or 
efficiently incorporated into the 
-secretase complexes. Only a 
small proportion of the full-length 
TMP21 is incorporated into com-
plexes, and therefore, replacement, 
for example, of the ectodomain in 
the chimeras may result in a more 
accessible conformation for secre-
tase binding. 
Appearance of the A-positive fragments suggests that they 
may result from a decreased processing of the APP-CTF. It 
would, therefore, be predicted that a corresponding decrease in </p>

<p>FIGURE 5. TMP21 interacted with PS-complex through its transmembrane domain. A, schematic represen-
tation of TMP21-p24a chimera FLAG-tagged proteins indicating the domains (extracellular, TM, and C termi-
nus) of the p24a template, which were replaced with the corresponding TMP21 sequences. B, HEK293 cells 
were transiently transfected with TMP21, p24a, or chimera proteins. Membrane fractions were prepared and 
analyzed by Western blot for detection of NCT, PS1-NTF, and FLAG-tagged proteins. C, FLAG-tagged wild-type 
TMP21-p24a and chimeras were immunoprecipitated (IP) from membrane fractions and analyzed by immu-
noblotting for detection of NCT, PS1 N-terminal fragment (PS1-NTF), and the FLAG-tagged proteins. Note that 
only wild-type TMP21 and chimera FLAG proteins containing the transmembrane domain of TMP21 were 
associated with both NCT and PS1-NTF. </p>

<p>FIGURE 6. A production and effects of individual TMP21 domains. A, HEK293 cells were transiently co-trans-
fected with TMP21-FLAG and APP. Membrane fraction were prepared and analyzed by Western blot for detection 
of APP holoprotein (APP-FL) and TMP21-FLAG proteins. B, intracellular A species were immunoprecipitated using 
6E10 antibody in HEK293 cells transiently co-transfected with TMP21-FLAG and APP and subsequently probed 
with the 6E10 antibody. Only TMP21 and chimera FLAG proteins containing the transmembrane domain of TMP21 
resulted in the accumulation of the membrane-embedded higher molecular weight A-positive fragments. 
C, HEK293 cells were co-transfected with APP and TMP1-p24a chimeras, and A40 levels were determined by 
ELISA. No changes were observed for full-length TMP21 or p24 and chimeras containing the extracellular N terminus 
(TMP21-Nt) or intracellular C terminus (TMP21-Ct) of TMP21. Significant reduction was observed for cells expressing 
the chimera containing the TMP21 transmembrane domain (TMP21-TM). </p>

<p>TMP21 Functional Domain </p>



<p>VOLUME 284 • NUMBER 42 • OCTOBER 16, 2009 </p>

<p>A secretion would be seen under these conditions. However, a 
more complex response was associated with TMP21 and the 
chimera proteins with respect to A production. Overexpres-
sion of full-length wild-type TMP21 and APP did not result in 
any significant change in A production (Fig. 6C). Levels were 
comparable with controls as well as cell transfected with 
the p24a homolog. This is consistent with other studies in 
whole cells where high levels of TMP21 were also shown to not 
have an appreciable effect on A levels (26, 27). Therefore, the 
A-positive fragments must represent only a small percentage 
of the total A. This could be because of a limited incorporation 
of full-length TMP21 into mature complexes. Similar issues 
with incorporation into functional complexes are seen for 
NCT, which is also not readily assembled into active complexes 
and accumulates as the immature species. 
For the chimera proteins, expression of constructs contain-
ing the N-terminal ectodomain (TMP21-Nt) or the intracellu-
lar cytoplasmic tail (TMP21-Ct) did not result in any apprecia-
ble changes in A production (Fig. 6C). In contrast, expression 
of the chimera containing the TMP21 transmembrane domain 
(TMP21-TM) with APP reduced A levels by 65% (Fig. 6C). 
The double-chimera TMP21-TMCt also reduced A levels 
below that of the TMP21-Nt and TMP21-Ct constructs, con-
sistent with their binding to PS1 and NCT (data not shown). 
The ability of the TMP21-TM-containing chimera was a con-
sistent observation which suggests that the transmembrane 
domain has a more pronounced effect than full-length TMP21. </p>

<p>The reason for this is unclear, but it 
is possible that the other domains 
(N and C termini) regulate other 
functions such as trafficking or 
binding to the -secretase complex. 
Therefore, replacement of these 
domains may result in a more 
potent activity of the TMP21 trans-
membrane region. 
TM-containing chimeras binding 
to the -complex may represent one 
of their mechanisms of action. 
However, the chimeras also consis-
tently increased the levels of full-
length APP precursor. This could 
provide another explanation for the 
accumulation of the A-positive 
fragments and possibly changes in 
A levels. Based upon these obser-
vations, either of the two func-
tional aspects of TMP21, inhibi-
tion of -secretase cleavage or 
changes in APP metabolism, may 
be responsible for the alterations 
in A-related processing (26, 27, 
30). To try and dissect these two 
functions, direct interaction of the 
TMP21 transmembrane domain 
to the -secretase complex and its 
ability to alter cleavage were inves-
tigated using synthetic peptides in 
cell culture and cell-free assays. 
Effects of a Synthetic Transmembrane Domain on A 
Processing-The TM domains of TMP21 and p24a were syn-
thesized with three additional lysine residues attached at both 
the N and C termini to increase solubility. This approach has 
been used previously for investigations into the membrane 
insertion and structure of the APP transmembrane helix (34). 
The TMP21 TM peptide (KKK-VLYFSIFSMFCLIGLATWQV-
FYL-KKK) solubilized in DMSO was added at different concen-
trations to cells expressing the APP-Swedish variant, and A40 
secretion was measured in medium by ELISA analysis. After 
incubation for 8 h, cells exposed to 10 g/ml (final media con-
centration) of the TMP21 peptide reduced A40 by 17% (Fig. 
7A). A dose response was observed at 30 g/ml peptide which 
produced an 32% reduction in A secretion. The correspond-
ing p24a transmembrane peptide (KKK-VVLWSFFEALVL-
VAMTLGQIYYL-KKK) had no statistically significant effects 
at either 10 or 30 g/ml (Fig. 7A). The reduction of A levels 
was also not because of an inherently toxic effect of the TMP21 
peptide that may have led to loss of production because of cell 
death. Viability assays indicated that no cell toxicity was asso-
ciated with either the TMP21 or p24a peptides at the concen-
trations investigated (supplemental Fig. 1). The reduced A40 
trend for cells treated with the TMP21 peptide at longer condi-
tioning time (e.g. 16 h) remained the same with comparable 
dose-dependent decreases for treatments with 10 and 30 g/ml 
(data not shown). Treatment of cells expressing APP with the </p>

<p>FIGURE 7. Synthetic transmembrane domain of TMP21 reduced A40 secretion. A, HEK293 cells stably 
overexpressing APPsw were treated with the synthetic transmembrane domain of TMP21 or p24a (0, 10, 30 
g/ml), and levels of secreted A40 peptide were analyzed by ELISA after 8 h of incubation. The synthetic 
peptide corresponding to the TMP21 transmembrane domain decreased A40 processing and secretion in a 
dose-dependent manner. No significant effects were observed for the related p24a TM domain peptide. 
B, HEK293 cells were transfected with APP, and 8 h before harvesting cells were treated with TMP21 or p24a 
transmembrane peptides (30 g/ml) or a DMSO control. Intracellular A species were immunoprecipitated 
and detected using 6E10 antibody. Treatment with the TMP21-TM peptide only resulted in the accumulation of 
A-positive fragments. Synthetic A standard peptides were used as molecular weight markers confirmed that 
the fragments had molecular weights corresponding to A1-49 and related peptides. C, cell-free assays were 
conducted using membrane preparations from HEK293 cells with recombinant APP-C100 as the -secretase 
substrate. Synthetic peptides corresponding to transmembrane domains of TMP21 and p24a were added to 
final concentrations of 0, 10, 30, and 60 g/ml to the reaction mixture. </p>

<p>TMP21 Functional Domain </p>

<p>OCTOBER 16, 2009 • VOLUME 284 • NUMBER 42 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 28639 </p>

<p>TMP21-TM synthetic peptide demonstrated a similar increase 
in the antibody-positive fragments (Fig. 7B). These fragments 
were identical to those seen after transfection of the TMP21-TM 
construct or wild-type protein. No change in these antibody-pos-
itive fragments was observed after treatment with the comparable 
p24a-TM peptide or DMSO control (Fig. 7B). These observations 
suggest that, in addition to its effects on APP metabolism, TMP21 
can directly alter -secretase activity. Given the specific ability of 
the synthetic TMP21 transmembrane domain to decrease A40 
production, it is likely that the peptide associates with the -secre-
tase complex and reduces proteolysis. These observations are con-
sistent with the effects of recombinant TMP21 on A processing 
as shown previously (26). 
Cell-free -secretase assays were also conducted in an effort 
to support these findings and investigate the activity of the syn-
thetic TM peptides. Membrane fractions were prepared from 
HEK293 cells and incubated with the synthetic TM peptides at 
various concentrations. Recombinant C100 protein was added 
to the reaction mixture, and A production was assayed by 
ELISA. Incubation of membranes with the TMP21 or p24a 
transmembrane peptides at 10 g/ml did not have any detect-
able effect on A levels (Fig. 7C). The TMP21 peptide had a 
modest effect at 30 g/ml which resulted in approximately a 
10% reduction in A production (Fig. 7C). A more pronounced 
decrease in A was observed for membranes incubated with 60 
g/ml of the TMP21 TM peptide which resulted in an 50% 
reduction in A processing. This was specific for the TMP21 
peptide, as no significant difference was observed for the cor-
responding p24a TM peptide (Fig. 7C). 
Relatively higher concentrations of the TMP21 transmem-
brane peptide were required in the cell-free assay to produce 
the same decrease in A processing as compared with the live 
cell cultures. This may be because of the fact that the level of the 
C100 substrate is much higher in the cell-free assay. Therefore, 
if the TMP21 binds to the -secretase complex as proposed, 
then the higher amount of substrate could compete for binding 
sites in the -complex. As a result, increased amounts of the 
TMP21 transmembrane peptide would be required to displace 
and/or compete with the C100 substrate. 
Taken together, these observations have demonstrated that 
TMP21 expression has a unique effect on -secretase process-
ing when examined in the absence of a possibly competing 
-mediated proteolysis. This was evident by the effects seen 
with the truncated APP which led to the accumulation of 
A-containing membrane-embedded fragments. Because the 
AICD sequence, which is lacking in APP construct, contains 
the YENP motif, essential for APP internalization (35), it is pos-
sible to envisage that TMP21 acts on -secretase activity and 
upstream APP recycling and preferentially targets the mem-
brane-embedded A fragment released after the -cleavage. 
However, this remains speculative, and the exact site of the twin 
function of TMP21 in terms of -secretase modulation and 
APP metabolism has yet to be elucidated. The direct activity of 
TMP21 on -secretase appeared to be primarily mediated by its 
transmembrane domain. It is likely that specific residues are 
responsible for these effects, and further mutagenesis studies 
may shed more light on this issue. However, the ability of the 
TMP21 peptide to alter APP processing and A production </p>

<p>could represent a novel strategy for modulating amyloid pro-
duction and its subsequent pathology. </p>





<p>VOLUME 284 • NUMBER 42 • OCTOBER 16, 2009 </p>



<p>TMP21 Functional Domain </p>

<p>OCTOBER 16, 2009 • VOLUME 284 • NUMBER 42 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 28641 </p>

</text></tei>