<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2886355" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Terminal differentiation is usually coupled with permanent exit 
from the cell cycle and represents the most common cellular 
state in adult animals. How terminal differentiation controls the 
cell cycle machinery to maintain a stable postmitotic state re-
mains unclear. Evidence from several model organisms sug-
gests that inhibition of the E2F transcription factor and/or the 
G1-S cyclin, cyclin E (CycE), is a key event for coordinating 
cell cycle exit and differentiation (for reviews see Buttitta and 
Edgar, 2007; Miller et al., 2007; Onoyama and Nakayama, 2008; 
Pajalunga et al., 2008; van den Heuvel and Dyson, 2008). Yet, 
activation of E2F or CycE in many contexts is insufficient to 
abrogate exit (Akli et al., 1999; Pajalunga et al., 1999; Latella </p>

<p>et al., 2001; Camarda et al., 2004; Balsitis et al., 2006; Buttitta 
et al., 2007; Gibbs et al., 2008). 
E2F transcription factors play key roles in regulating the 
cell cycle as many genes required for S, G2, and M phases are 
targets of E2F (Ishida et al., 2001; Polager et al., 2002; Ren et al., 
2002; Dimova et al., 2003). Importantly, E2F complexes (made 
up of an E2F subunit and its dimerization partner [DP]) can act 
as both transcriptional activators and repressors of the same 
targets. Association with the retinoblastoma tumor suppressor 
proteins (RBs) can convert E2F-DP complexes to transcriptional 
repressors by recruiting repressive chromatin-modifying com-
plexes (Dyson, 1998), whereas the G1 cyclin-Cdk complexes, 
CycD-Cdk4 and CycE-Cdk2, promote E2F activity by phosphory-
lating and inhibiting the association of RBs with E2F-DP com-
plexes (Du and Pogoriler, 2006). CycE-Cdk2 activity is also 
directly essential for S-phase entry, as it regulates critical 
components to initiate S phase in both kinase-dependent </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>erminally differentiated cells in Drosophila melano-
gaster wings and eyes are largely resistant to prolif-
eration upon deregulation of either E2F or cyclin E 
(CycE), but exogenous expression of both factors together 
can bypass cell cycle exit. In this study, we show this is the 
result of cooperation of cell cycle control mechanisms that 
limit E2F-CycE positive feedback and prevent cycling after 
terminal differentiation. Aberrant CycE activity after dif-
ferentiation leads to the degradation of E2F activator com-
plexes, which increases the proportion of CycE-resistant 
E2F repressor complexes, resulting in stable E2F target gene </p>

<p>repression. If E2F-dependent repression is lost after differ-
entiation, high anaphase-promoting complex/cyclosome 
(APC/C) activity degrades key E2F targets to limit cell 
cycle reentry. Providing both CycE and E2F activities by-
passes exit by simultaneously inhibiting the APC/C and 
inducing a group of E2F target genes essential for cell 
cycle reentry after differentiation. These mechanisms are 
essential for proper development, as evading them leads 
to tissue outgrowths composed of dividing but terminally 
differentiated cells. </p>

<p>A robust cell cycle control mechanism limits 
E2F-induced proliferation of terminally differentiated 
cells in vivo </p>

<p>Laura A. Buttitta, 
1 Alexia J. Katzaroff, 
1,2 and Bruce A. Edgar </p>

<p>1,3 </p>

<p>1 Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle, WA 98109 
2 Molecular and Cellular Biology Graduate Program, University of Washington, Seattle, WA 98195 
3 Deutsches Krebsforschungszentrum-Zentrum für Molekulare Biologie der Universität Heidelberg Allianz, D-69120 Heidelberg, Germany </p>

<p>© 2010 Buttitta et al. This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution-
Noncommercial-Share Alike-No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the pub-
lication date (see http://www.rupress.org/terms). After six months it is available under a 
Creative Commons License (Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, 
as described at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). </p>

<p>T H E J O U R N A L O F C E L L B I O L O G Y </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 189 • NUMBER 6 • 2010 
982 </p>

<p>cell cycle on time (Frolov et al., 2001), and mitotic tissues of 
e2f1 </p>

<p>su89 </p>

<p>,e2f2 double mutant animals, thought to lack all E2F 
repressive function, exit the cell cycle normally (Weng et al., 
2003). Therefore, we sought to reveal a more subtle role for 
E2F2 in blocking CycE-E2F feedback specifically after cell 
cycle exit and influencing exit flexibility in the presence of high 
CycE-Cdk2 activity. 
Clones of cells overexpressing CycE and Cdk2 were gen-
erated in an e2f2 
76Q1/G5.1 -null background using the heat shock 
(hs)-FLP Gal4 method (Pignoni and Zipursky, 1997), where 
clones are negatively marked by the CD2 (cluster of differenti-
ation 2) antigen and CycE and Cdk2 are expressed under the 
control of a Gal4 responsive upstream activating sequence 
(UAS). E2F transcriptional activity was monitored in wings 
at stages after cell cycle exit, using a reporter containing an 
E2F-responsive proliferating cell nuclear antigen (PCNA) pro-
moter fused to GFP (Thacker et al., 2003). In the absence of 
e2f2, CycE-Cdk2 was able to activate the E2F reporter in 
clones within the wing after terminal differentiation at 36 h 
after puparium formation (APF; Fig. 1 A), an effect absent in 
wild-type (WT) wings. However, the CycE-Cdk2-induced E2F 
activity in e2f2 mutant wings was temporary, as CycE-Cdk2 
was unable to sustain E2F activity beyond 40 h APF in the 
absence of e2f2 (Fig. 1 B). 
We next examined whether the loss of e2f2 influenced the 
flexibility of cell cycle exit in the presence of high CycE-Cdk2 
activity. GFP-marked e2f2-null mutant clones expressing CycE-
Cdk2 were generated using the mosaic analysis with a repres-
sible cell marker (MARCM) system (Lee and Luo, 2001) and 
examined for ectopic mitoses after normal cell cycle exit in 
pupal eyes and wings by staining for phosphorylated Ser10 on 
histone H3 (PH3; Fig. 1, C-E). Ectopic mitoses were evident in 
e2f2 
/ cells expressing CycE-Cdk2 in eyes from 24-44 h APF 
(Fig. 1 C, 36 h APF shown), indicating a delay of cell cycle exit 
8 h beyond the effect of CycE-Cdk2 expression alone in the eye. 
However, mitoses were no longer observed in e2f2 
/ cells ex-
pressing CycE-Cdk2 after 44 h APF in eyes (Fig. 1 D) or in 
wings after 36 h APF (Fig. 1 E and Table I). This reveals a cell 
cycle exit function for e2f2 in temporarily limiting CycE activa-
tion of E2F but also demonstrates that an e2f2-independent 
mechanism prevents E2F transcriptional activation after pro-
longed exit in eyes and wings. </p>

<p>Ectopic CycE-Cdk2 activity in </p>

<p>terminally differentiated cells leads </p>

<p>to E2F1 degradation </p>

<p>Recent work has delineated a Dacapo-and Rbf-independent 
mechanism limiting E2F1 activity in embryos and proliferat-
ing cells. E2F1 is degraded each cell cycle during S phase in a 
PCNA interaction protein motif (PIP) box-dependent manner 
via a Cul4 ubiquitin ligase complex (Shibutani et al., 2007; 
2008). We considered whether ectopic CycE-Cdk2 activity 
could inhibit E2F activity after exit by promoting S-phase ini-
tiation and thereby E2F1 degradation. This idea was supported 
by our previous observation that CycE-Cdk2 expression cor-
related with low E2F1 protein levels in the wing (Buttitta 
et al., 2007). </p>

<p>and -independent manners (Lukas et al., 1997; Mailand and 
Diffley, 2005; Geng et al., 2007). 
Drosophila melanogaster has been a key organism for 
studies of cell cycle exit in part because its E2F/CycE network is 
simpler than mammals, consisting of only two RB family (Rbf) 
members (Rbf and Rbf2), a single Cip/Kip type cyclin-dependent 
kinase inhibitor, Dacapo (no INK homologues), two E2Fs (one 
activator, E2F1, and one repressor, E2F2), one DP, and one es-
sential G1-S cyclin, CycE (Duronio and O'Farrell, 1995; de Nooij 
et al., 1996; Lane et al., 1996; Sawado et al., 1998; Frolov et al., 
2001; Stevaux et al., 2002). 
Investigations into cell cycle exit in Drosophila have dem-
onstrated that RB/E2F repressive activity is not required for per-
manent exit in vivo (Weng et al., 2003; Frolov et al., 2005). We 
have suggested that this is caused by independent but parallel re-
pression of E2F and cyclin-Cdk activities, a mechanism we call 
double-assurance (Buttitta et al., 2007). The restraint of both 
E2F and CycE activities upon exit partially involve Rbf and 
Dacapo (Firth and Baker, 2005) but, based on genetic experi-
ments, must also include Rbf-and Dacapo-independent mecha-
nisms (Buttitta et al., 2007). 
The finding that E2F activity alone is insufficient to main-
tain cycling of differentiating cells is surprising because E2F activ-
ity itself up-regulates CycE and Cdk2 after exit to levels even 
higher than those in proliferating cells (Buttitta et al., 2007). 
High CycE-Cdk2 activity normally promotes increased E2F 
activity via phosphorylation of RBs and cooperates with E2F-
dependent induction of CycE and Cdk2 to establish a positive 
E2F-CycE feedback loop for cell cycle entry (Yung et al., 2007; 
Assoian and Yung, 2008), similar to that of Cln1 and -2 in yeast 
(Skotheim et al., 2008). However, we have found that E2F-CycE 
positive feedback appears to be limited after terminal differen-
tiation to prevent ectopic cycling (Buttitta et al., 2007). In this 
study, we examine why both ectopic E2F and CycE activities 
must be provided to bypass cell cycle exit in Drosophila and un-
cover specific cell cycle control mechanisms that cooperate to 
limit E2F-CycE positive feedback and maintain a stable post-
mitotic state. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>E2F2 complexes are partially responsible </p>

<p>for CycE-resistant E2F repression </p>

<p>after exit </p>

<p>CycE induces E2F activity in proliferating and reversibly quies-
cent cells by preventing the formation of Rbf-E2F repressive 
complexes. However, our previous results indicated that CycE 
activity could not prevent repression of E2F target genes after 
cell cycle exit in terminally differentiated eye and wing cells 
(Buttitta et al., 2007). Rbf-E2F2-mediated repression is some-
how resistant to G1 cyclin-Cdks despite G1 cyclin-Cdk phos-
phorylation of Rbf (Frolov et al., 2003). This makes E2F2 
complexes prime candidates as factors limiting CycE-dependent 
activation of E2F after cell cycle exit in differentiated cells. 
Genetic studies of E2F2 have failed to demonstrate a role for 
E2F2 in cell cycle exit upon differentiation in vivo (Frolov 
et al., 2001; Weng et al., 2003). e2f2 mutant cells exit from the </p>

<p> 
Mechanisms maintaining cell cycle exit • Buttitta et al. </p>

<p>wing and eye. Levels of GFP-E2F1 were determined by detection 
of the GFP tag using an anti-GFP antibody and compared be-
tween GFP-E2F1 
WT and GFP-E2F1 
PIP3A (Fig. 1, F-H). We found 
that levels of GFP-E2F1 
PIP3A in the presence of CycE-Cdk2 after </p>

<p>To test whether CycE-Cdk2 activity affected degradation 
of E2F1 after cell cycle exit in a PIP box-dependent manner, we 
generated clones coexpressing either WT GFP-E2F1 
WT or E2F 
with a mutated PIP box, GFP-E2F1 
PIP3A with CycE-Cdk2 in the </p>

<p>Figure 1. Degradation of E2F1 activator complexes and a switch to E2F2 repressor complexes contributes to the CycE-Cdk2-resistant repression of E2F ac-
tivity after exit. Clones overexpressing CycE-Cdk2 and negatively marked by CD2 (A and B) were generated using hs-FLP act&gt;Gal4/UAS in e2f2 </p>

<p>76Q1/G5.1 </p>

<p>mutant wings. E2F transcriptional activity was monitored at the indicated stages using the PCNA-GFP reporter (A and B). CycE-Cdk2 activity is temporarily 
able to activate the E2F reporter in the absence of e2f2 (A) but is unable to sustain E2F activity after 40 h APF (B). (C-E) GFP-marked e2f2-null mutant 
clones expressing CycE-Cdk2 were generated using the MARCM system and examined for ectopic mitoses by staining for PH3. Neurons are marked by 
expression of Elav. Ectopic mitoses in e2f2 
/ cells expressing CycE-Cdk2 are evident in Elav-negative cells in eyes from 24 to 40 h APF (36 h APF shown; 
C) but are no longer observed by 44 h APF (D). No ectopic mitoses are observed in e2f2 
/ cells expressing CycE-Cdk2 in wings after 36 h APF (E). 
(F-H) Clones expressing either GFP-E2F1 
WT or GFP-E2F1 
PIP3A with CycE-Cdk2 were generated using hs-FLP act&gt;Gal4/UAS in pupal wings (F-H) and eyes 
(H). Clones were negatively marked by CD2 (F and G), and levels of GFP-tagged E2F1 were compared at 44 h APF. All GFP measurements were acquired 
at the same gain and at roughly similar tissue sections. Several samples (n = 7) across three independent experiments were compared for GFP intensity 
using ImageJ (National Institutes of Health), and representative examples are shown. Bars in H indicate the mean GFP intensity across all samples measured, 
and error bars indicate the standard deviation. GFP-E2F1 
WT is destabilized in the presence of CycE-Cdk2 after exit in eyes and wings (F-H). Wings ex-
pressing either GFP-E2F1 
WT or GFP-E2F1 
PIP3A in the dorsal domain during pupal stages (under control of ap-Gal4/UAS, tub-Gal80 </p>

<p>TS </p>

<p>) were assayed for PH3. 
(I and J) No ectopic mitoses were evident in wings expressing either the stabilized or WT forms of E2F1 after 36 h APF (44 h APF shown). However, several 
ectopic ELAV 
+ neurons were found in the dorsal posterior margin of all GFP-E2F1 </p>

<p>PIP3A </p>

<p>-expressing wings (J, arrows). Bars, 50 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 189 • NUMBER 6 • 2010 </p>

<p>
cells, which are believed to lack all E2F-DP transcriptional 
function (Frolov et al., 2005). 
GFP-labeled Dp 
/ cells overexpressing CycE-Cdk2 did 
not bypass exit in wings or eyes after 36 h APF and arrested at 
the G1-S transition with high levels of CycE-Cdk2 activity, as 
evident by anti-MPM2 (mitotic phosphoprotein marker 2) anti-
body staining of CycE-Cdk2-phosphorylated targets at the his-
tone locus body (Fig. 2, A and B, arrows indicate examples; 
White et al., 2007). The arrest of CycE-Cdk2-expressing 
Dp mutant cells at the G1-S transition is indistinguishable 
from normal cells expressing CycE-Cdk2 at 36 h APF. (Buttitta 
et al., 2007). 
Because CycE-Cdk2 was insufficient to bypass exit in 
Dp mutant cells, we next examined whether other cell cycle 
regulators, particularly regulators of the G2-M transition, 
could bypass exit in Dp-null cells. Expression of the G2-M 
regulators, CycA, Rca1 (regulator of CycA), and the Cdc25c 
phosphatase, String (Stg), all failed to bypass exit in Dp-null 
cells (Fig. S1). However, some Dp 
/ cells coexpressing CycE 
and the G2-M regulator Stg continued cycling at 40-44 h APF, 
as indicated by PH3 and MPM2, with a mitotic index of 0.9% 
and 3% in the wing and eye, respectively (Fig. 2, C and D, 
PH3 shown). Importantly, rare ectopic mitoses were also evi-
dent in some control WT wings and eyes expressing CycE and 
Stg (mitotic index up to 0.3% and 1.0% in some wing and 
eyes, respectively; Fig. 2, G and H). This suggests that some 
very low level of cycling, undetected by our previous clonal 
assays (Buttitta et al., 2007), continues in a small number of 
cells expressing CycE + Stg. This cycling is moderately in-
creased threefold when all E2F-DP function is lost in Dp-null 
cells. Therefore, we questioned whether the loss of E2F2-DP 
repressive function was responsible for the increased cycling </p>

<p>exit were higher in both pupal eyes and wings than GFP-
E2F1 
WT (Fig. 1, F-H). This suggests that if CycE-Cdk2 is ab-
errantly activated after exit, it could induce S-phase initiation 
and PIP box-dependent E2F1 degradation to serve as a self-
correcting mechanism to limit CycE-E2F positive feedback 
after exit. 
To test whether stabilized E2F1 is sufficient to bypass 
exit, we expressed GFP-E2F1 
PIP3A in the dorsal domain of the 
wing (using Apterous [ap]-Gal4/UAS) during pupal stages and 
assayed for ectopic mitoses. No mitoses were evident in wings 
expressing either the stabilized or WT forms of E2F1 after 36 h 
APF (Fig. 1, I and J), suggesting that the stabilized E2F1 cannot 
delay cell cycle exit further than WT E2F1. However, stabilized 
E2F1 did cause a mild phenotype, as several ectopic neurons 
were found in the dorsal posterior margin of all GFP-E2F1 </p>

<p>PIP3A </p>

<p>-
expressing wings (Fig. 1 J, arrows). 
These results suggest that a switch to CycE-resistant E2F2 
repressive complexes together with the degradation of E2F1 
activator complexes underlie the resistance of terminally differ-
entiated cells to G1 cyclin-Cdk-induced proliferation. </p>

<p>Bypass of cell cycle exit is limited in the </p>

<p>absence of all E2F-DP function </p>

<p>Our results suggest that in the absence of e2f2, aberrant CycE-
Cdk2 activity leads to degradation of E2F1, and the subsequent 
loss of both E2F activator and repressor complexes results 
in cell cycle exit, even in the face of high cyclin-Cdk activity. 
However, because our experiments were performed in the pres-
ence of endogenous E2F1, we could not rule out the potential 
contribution of a novel CycE-resistant E2F1 repressive complex 
to cell cycle exit. To address this, we directly examined whether 
CycE-Cdk2 could bypass cell cycle exit in Dp-null mutant </p>

<p>Table I. Genetic manipulations of cell cycle regulators and their effects on cell cycle exit </p>

<p>Genetic backgrounds 
Delay exit 24-40 APF? 
Delay exit past 44 APF? (mitotic index) 
Figure or reference </p>

<p>e2f2 
/ + CycE + Cdk2 
Yes 
No 
Fig. 1 
GFP-E2F1 </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>Yes 
No 
Fig. 1 
GFP-E2F1 </p>

<p>PIP3A </p>

<p>Yes 
No 
Fig. 1 
GFP-E2F1 
WT + CycE + Cdk2 
Yes 
ND 
Fig. 1 
GFP-E2F1 
PIP3A + CycE + Cdk2 
Yes 
ND 
Fig. 1 
dp 
/ + CycE + Cdk2 
Yes 
No 
Fig. 2 
dp 
/ + CycE + Stg 
Yes 
Yes (≤3%) 
Fig. 2 
e2f2 
/ + CycE + Stg 
Yes 
Yes (≤1%) 
Fig. 2 
CycE + Stg 
Yes 
Yes (≤1%) 
Fig. 2 
rbf1 
/ + CycE-Cdk2 
Yes 
No, wing blade 
Yes, neurons </p>

<p>Buttitta et al., 2007 </p>

<p>rbf 
/ + CycE + Stg 
Yes 
Yes (15-20%) 
Fig. 3 
rbf 
/ + Stg 
Yes 
No 
Fig. 3 
CycA 
Yes 
No 
Buttitta et al., 2007 
Rca1 
Yes 
No 
Fig. 5 
E2F1-DP + Rca1 
Yes 
Yes 
Figs. 5 and 6 
E2F1-DP + Fzy </p>

<p>RNAi </p>

<p>Yes 
Yes 
Fig. 5 
E2F1-DP + Fzr </p>

<p>RNAi </p>

<p>Yes 
Yes 
Fig. 5 
E2F1-DP + Cortex </p>

<p>RNAi </p>

<p>Yes 
No 
Fig. 5 
E2F1-DP 
Yes 
No 
Fig. 6 
CycE + Cdk2 
Yes 
No 
Buttitta et al., 2007 
E2F + CycE-Cdk2 
Yes 
Yes 
Buttitta et al., 2007 
E2F + CycE + Stg 
Yes 
Yes 
Buttitta et al., 2007 </p>

<p> 
Mechanisms maintaining cell cycle exit • Buttitta et al. </p>

<p>Loss of rbf together with CycE and Stg 
prevents cell cycle exit and produces </p>

<p>tumor-like overproliferation of terminally </p>

<p>differentiated cells </p>

<p>We previously tested whether rbf mutant cells expressing 
CycE-Cdk2 could bypass exit and found continued cycling of 
differentiated neurons in late-stage pupae but no cycling and 
an S/G2-phase arrest in the epithelial wing blade (Table I; 
Buttitta et al., 2007). Based on the low level of mitoses seen in 
Dp mutant cells expressing both CycE and Stg, we reasoned </p>

<p>seen in Dp mutant cells expressing CycE + Stg. However, e2f2-
null mutant cells expressing CycE + Stg in wings and eyes 
were indistinguishable from control cells expressing CycE + Stg 
(Fig. 2, E and F). 
The failure of most Dp mutant cells to significantly by-
pass cell cycle exit, even in the presence of high CycE and Stg, 
suggests that E2F-DP activity is somehow required for ectopic 
proliferation of terminally differentiated cells, even though it 
is not required for proliferation earlier in development (Frolov 
et al., 2001, 2005). </p>

<p>Figure 2. Bypass of cell cycle exit is limited in the absence of E2F-DP function. (A-H) GFP-marked control or e2f2-or Dp-null mutant clones expressing the 
indicated cell cycle regulators were generated using the MARCM system and examined for ectopic mitoses by staining for PH3 (A and C-H) or ectopic 
CycE-Cdk2 activity indicated by MPM2 foci (B). Neurons are shown by staining for Elav (blue). Dp 
/ cells expressing CycE-Cdk2 do not bypass exit in 
wings (A) or eyes (B) after 36 h APF (40-44 h shown) and arrest with high levels of CycE-Cdk2 activity, as evident by MPM2-positive nuclear foci (eyes 
shown; arrows point to examples of foci in B). Some Dp 
/ cells expressing CycE and the G2-M regulator Stg continue cycling at 40 h APF, as indicated by 
PH3 (C and D) with a mitotic index of 0.9% and 3% in the wing and eye, respectively. A few mitoses are also observed in e2f2-null mutant cells expressing 
CycE and Stg at 40-44 h APF (E and F). However, similar levels of ectopic mitoses are evident in some control wings (G; mitotic index up to 0.3%) and 
eyes (H; up to 1.0%) expressing CycE and Stg (40-44 h APF shown). Bars: (A and C-H) 50 µm; (B) 20 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 189 • NUMBER 6 • 2010 </p>

<p>
index up to 20%) in wings and eyes of rbf 
/ cells expressing 
CycE + Stg at all time points examined, including the latest 
time point at which we could perform antibody staining, 60 h 
APF (Fig. 3, A, B, and E-G). Overproliferation continued at 
60 h APF when ommatidia differentiation, wing adult cuticle, 
and trichome differentiation were evident (Fig. 3, E and F). 
Proliferation of differentiated cells in the late wing generated </p>

<p>that expressing CycE and Stg in rbf 
/ cells might completely 
bypass exit by providing the necessary G2-M activity and E2F 
activator function. To test this, we generated GFP-marked rbf-
null mutant clones expressing CycE and Stg using the MARCM 
system and examined them for ectopic S phases (by BrdU in-
corporation) or mitoses (PH3). Ectopic cell cycles, including 
S phases and mitoses, were evident at very high levels (mitotic </p>

<p>Figure 3. Loss of rbf together with CycE and Stg prevents cell cycle exit and causes overproliferation of terminally differentiated cells. (A-G) GFP-marked 
rbf-null mutant clones expressing CycE and Stg were generated using the MARCM system and examined for ectopic S phases (BrdU; A) or mitoses (PH3; 
B, E, and F). Ectopic cell cycles are evident at high levels (mitotic index up to 20%) in wings (A, B, and F) and eyes (E; 15%) at all time points examined, 
including the latest time point, 60 h APF. Bulges and folding of adult cuticle are observed in regions of mutant clones in the thorax (C) and wing (D and 
inset). Eye (E) and wing (F) terminal differentiation structures such as lenses, bristles, and wing hairs are evident. A tangential section of a wing clone shows 
tissue folding caused by overproliferation (G). (H and I) GFP-marked rbf-null mutant clones expressing Stg were generated using the MARCM system and 
examined for ectopic mitoses at late stages up to 56 h APF (PH3; H and I; 48 h APF shown). At stages after 40 h APF, a few mitoses were evident in more 
proximal regions of some clones (H, arrowheads) but not in most clones in the wing (H, insets) or the eye (I, insets show a second example of a clone in 
the eye). (C, E, and F) Yellow outlines indicate clone boundaries. DIC, differential interference contrast. Bars: (A, B, E, F, H, and I) 50 µm; (C) 100 µm; 
(D) 0.5 mm; (G) 20 µm. </p>

<p> 
Mechanisms maintaining cell cycle exit • Buttitta et al. </p>

<p>clusters of small cells, resulting in folding of the epithelium, 
reminiscent of tumor-like overgrowth (Fig. 3 G). We also ob-
served outgrowths on adult nota and folding of the adult wing 
indicative of overproliferation with relatively normal terminal 
differentiation (Fig. 3, C and D). Importantly, the dramatic by-
pass of exit observed in rbf 
/ CycE/Stg-expressing cells was 
not recapitulated in rbf-null mutant clones expressing only Stg. 
Cells mutant for rbf expressing Stg exhibited few mitoses re-
stricted to the proximal regions of some clones in the wing at 
48 h APF, and no mitoses were observed in eyes after 48 h APF 
(Fig. 3, H and I). 
Our results indicate that the E2F activity provided by the 
loss of rbf 
/ plays an essential role in bypassing exit. We con-
firmed that rbf 
/ cells ectopically activate the E2F-responsive 
PCNA-GFP reporter after exit, demonstrating aberrantly high 
E2F1 transcriptional activity (Fig. S2 G). Yet despite the E2F 
activity, the threshold for both CycE and Stg activities somehow </p>

<p>remains high in rbf 
/ cells, and independent activation of both 
is required to bypass cell cycle exit. </p>

<p>Gene expression changes caused by E2F </p>

<p>transcriptional activation and DP loss are </p>

<p>highly similar after cell cycle exit </p>

<p>Our results with rbf 
/ cells indicate that some level of E2F 
activator, not simply E2F derepression, is required to bypass cell 
cycle exit upon terminal differentiation. This requirement is 
specific to the forced proliferation of terminally differentiating 
cells, as cells lacking all E2F-DP activity can proliferate during 
normal development (Frolov et al., 2001, 2003, 2005). This sug-
gests that certain critical E2F targets may require the activator 
function of E2F for expression in differentiating cells. There-
fore, we chose to compare gene expression changes caused by 
high E2F activity to those caused by the loss of all E2F-DP func-
tion in terminally differentiating cells. </p>

<p>Figure 4. E2F transcriptional activation and 
Dp loss are highly similar, except for specific 
genes that require E2F activity for expression 
after exit. Using microarrays, we compared 
gene expression in E2F1-DP-expressing wings 
(ap-Gal4/UAS-E2F1, UAS-DP, tub-Gal80 
TS ) 
with controls (ap-Gal4/UAS, tub-Gal80 
TS ) 
and Dp mutant wings (w;Dp 
a1/a2 ) with con-
trols (w) at three time points. (A) Heat map 
of transcript changes (color range indicates 
the log 2 ratio of expression compared with 
controls). All transcripts with a fold change 
of 1.5 or more (&gt;log 2 ± 0.6) at one or more 
time points are shown. Gray bars indicate 
transcripts that were removed from analysis 
because of high variability among indepen-
dently replicated experiments (n = 4 for E2F; 
n = 3 for Dp 
/ ). Transcripts were clustered 
using <rs type="software">Genesis</rs> software for hierarchical clus-
tering. Representative genes from each major 
cluster are listed on the right. Typical group 
transcripts are up-regulated in E2F-expressing 
and Dp 
/ wings at 24 and 36 h APF, 
whereas other transcripts are repressed or in-
versely regulated. Arrays for E2F and Dp </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>at 24 and 36 h were highly similar with a 
correlation coefficient of 0.74. (B) A group 
of 162 genes was up-regulated &gt;1.75-fold 
(&gt;log 2 0.82) by E2F activity at one or both 
time points APF but was not significantly 
increased in Dp </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>(change &lt;1.3-fold; 
&lt;log 2 0.4). Asterisks indicate examples of genes 
that regulate cyclin-Cdk activity or mitosis. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 189 • NUMBER 6 • 2010 </p>

<p>
Figure 5. APC/C activity limits E2F-induced bypass of exit. (A) Several APC/C components (APC1, -4, -5, -6, -7, -8, and -10) and regulators (cdc20, 
cdc20-like, and Cks30A) are transcriptionally increased (1.5-40-fold) when E2F activity is high or de-repressed in Dp mutant wings. (B-I) GFP-marked 
clones expressing the indicated cell cycle regulators were generated using hs-FLP tub&gt;Gal4/UAS, tub-Gal80 
TS and examined for PH3 (B-I) or MPM2 (F). 
Nuclei were stained with Hoechst (blue; G-I). PH3 is seen in clones expressing the APC/C inhibitor Rca1 at 24-36 h APF in the eye and wing (wing 
shown; B) but not the late wing and was only observed once in the eye at 40-44 h APF (C, arrow). When E2F1-DP and Rca1 are coexpressed, bypass 
of exit is observed as late as 60 h APF (D) without disrupting terminal differentiation of ommatidia or bristles (E). Yellow outline indicates clone boundary. 
Coexpression of E2F1-DP with Fzy RNAi or Fzr RNAi also led to ectopic mitoses in eyes (F and H) and wings (G and I) at 48 h APF, as shown by PH3 </p>

<p> 
Mechanisms maintaining cell cycle exit • Buttitta et al. </p>

<p>These include transcripts increased by E2F expression but de-
creased in Dp mutants, and vice versa. Genes up-regulated by high 
E2F but decreased in Dp mutants could be genes that require 
E2F1-DP complexes for basal expression as well as activation, 
and therefore, expression is lost in the absence of Dp. In con-
trast, genes decreased by E2F but increased in Dp mutants could 
be genes somehow actively repressed by E2F1-DP complexes, 
repression which is lost upon the loss of Dp. Neither subgroup of 
conversely regulated transcripts exhibited any statistically signifi-
cant enrichment in GO terms, although several of these genes are 
known to be important in developmental signaling, differentia-
tion, and proliferation (i.e., HLHm5, scribbled, Toll-9, and glass). </p>

<p>Specific cell cycle genes require E2F </p>

<p>activity for expression after exit </p>

<p>A group of 162 genes was up-regulated &gt;1.75-fold (&gt;log 2 0.82) 
by increased E2F activity at one or both time points after exit but 
was not significantly increased in Dp mutants at any time point 
(change &lt;1.3-fold; &lt;log 2 0.4; Fig. 4 B). This group includes genes 
that may become limiting for bypass of exit in Dp mutants, which 
is consistent with the finding that this group is significantly en-
riched for genes regulating the cell cycle and mitosis (P &lt; 8.07 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>) 
but is also enriched for genes involved in RNA processing 
(P &lt; 7.15 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>) and chromatin regulation (P &lt; 3.4 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>). We noted that 
cycE and stg were among this group, as well as the cyclin-Cdk-
activating kinase component, cdk7, which is important for maxi-
mal CycB-Cdk1 activity (Larochelle et al., 1998), and the Cdk 
target of Stg phosphatase activity, Cdk1 (cdc2). Asterisks in Fig. 4 B 
indicate several examples of genes in this group that regulate 
cyclin-Cdk activity or mitosis. 
Based on our array analysis, E2F activation and Dp loss re-
sult in highly similar changes in gene expression upon terminal 
differentiation. This is because a major role for DP after cell cycle 
exit is in forming repressive E2F-DP complexes, and therefore, 
loss of DP after exit more closely resembles E2F derepression. 
However, we found a set of genes important for mitosis, cell cycle 
progression, and chromatin regulation that specifically require E2F 
activator function for expression in terminally differentiating cells. 
We propose that it is the E2F-dependent transcriptional activation 
of these genes, together with high CycE and Stg activity, that is re-
quired to abrogate cell cycle exit upon terminal differentiation. </p>

<p>Anaphase-promoting complex/cyclosome </p>

<p>(APC/C) activity limits E2F-induced </p>

<p>bypass of exit </p>

<p>Although E2F activity induces robust expression of many cell 
cycle genes after exit, including cycE and stg, the threshold of 
CycE and Stg activity required to bypass exit is increased in ter-
minally differentiating cells. The increased threshold for CycE 
is not simply a result of an up-regulation of Dacapo because cell 
cycle exit still occurs in wings and certain cell types in the eye </p>

<p>We took advantage of the relatively synchronous cell 
cycle exit in the wing to examine gene expression by microarray 
in E2F-DP-expressing wings, which temporarily delay exit 
because of E2F activity, and Dp mutant wings, which lack 
E2F-DP function but exit on time. We directly compared 
E2F1-DP-expressing wings (ap-Gal4/UAS-E2F1, UAS-DP, 
tub-Gal80 
TS ) with controls (ap-Gal4/UAS, tub-Gal80 
TS ) and 
Dp mutants (w;Dp </p>

<p>a1/a2 </p>

<p>) with controls (w) during proliferation (third 
larval instar [L3]), at normal exit (24 h APF), and after pro-
longed exit when E2F no longer promotes cycling (36 h APF). 
Fig. 4 shows the hierarchically clustered heat maps of transcript 
changes (log 2 ratio of expression compared with controls) for 
all transcripts with a fold change of 1.5 or more (&gt;log 2 ± 0.6) at 
one or more time points. Gray bars indicate transcripts that were 
removed from the analysis because of high variability among 
replicates (Fig. 4 A). The complete dataset is available as tab-
delimited text in the online supplemental material as a txt file, 
additional array data descriptions can be found in Materials and 
methods, and complete clusters can be viewed in high resolu-
tion on the <rs type="software">JCB DataViewer</rs>. 
Overall, transcript changes caused by E2F1-DP (E2F) 
overexpression and Dp loss were strikingly similar in terminally 
differentiating cells. When arrays were compared, a correlation 
coefficient of 0.74 was found for E2F and Dp 
/ arrays at 24 and 
36 h APF. Representative genes from each major cluster are listed 
in Fig. 4. The largest cluster consists of what we call typical tran-
scripts, which represent many known E2F target genes, that are 
up-regulated in both E2F-expressing and Dp 
/ wings at 24 and 
36 h APF. This group contains most of the 157 genes identified as 
Drosophila E2F targets in proliferating S2 cells by Dimova et al. 
(2003). This even includes genes in groups B and C from that 
study, which were unaffected by Dp loss in S2 cells (Dimova 
et al., 2003) but we find to be affected by Dp loss in wings in vivo. 
We also identified many additional E2F targets corroborated by 
other model system studies (for review see Bracken et al., 2004). 
Typical group transcripts were enriched for Gene Ontology (GO) 
terms involved in cell cycle (P &lt; 6.84 
9 ), DNA replication and 
repair (P &lt; 2.56 
8 ), microtubule cytoskeleton organization 
(P &lt; 2.14 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>), and DNA packaging (P &lt; 2.84 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>). 
The second largest cluster of coregulated genes in E2F-
overexpressing and Dp mutant wings consisted of genes re-
pressed in differentiating cells. Because E2F1-DP is thought to 
act as a transcriptional activator, this group of repressed genes is 
somewhat unexpected. These genes are not repressed indirectly 
by a delay in cell cycle exit, as they are similarly repressed in 
Dp mutants, which exit normally. We also don't believe this group 
is caused by E2F1-DP repressive complexes blocking transcrip-
tion, as such targets would be expected to increase rather than 
decrease in Dp mutants. 
The third group of transcripts altered by E2F expression 
and Dp loss are inversely regulated between the two genotypes. </p>

<p>staining (F-I) and MPM2 cytoplasmic mitotic staining (F; white in F inset; arrowhead indicates cytoplasmic MPM2 staining). G1-S progression was also 
observed in clones expressing E2F1-DP with Fzy RNAi in eyes at 48 h APF, as indicated by MPM2 nuclear foci (F; white in F inset; arrows point to foci). 
Sparse clones overexpressing E2F + RNAis for the three APC/C activators were induced at 0 h white prepupae, and cells per clone for at least 50 clones/ 
genotype were quantified at 54-56 h APF. The distributions of clonal cell counts and mean cells/clone are indicated in J. (J, right) Examples of large clones 
and overlying wing cuticle and hairs at 56 h APF. DIC, differential interference contrast. Bars, 50 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 189 • NUMBER 6 • 2010 </p>

<p>
a germline cdc20-like protein which is up-regulated by E2F 
after exit in wings (Fig. 5 A) but had no effect on cycling or E2F 
delay of cell cycle exit in eyes or wings. When clones express-
ing E2F + Cortex 
RNAi were induced by a limited heat shock at 0 h 
APF, very few clones containing more than four cells were ob-
served at 48-56 h APF. However, we observed an increase in the 
mean cells/clone when Fzy or Fzr RNAis were coexpressed 
with E2F, as well as an increase in the number of clones con-
taining six or more cells (Fig. 5 J). Some of the E2F + Fzy </p>

<p>RNAi </p>

<p>and E2F + Fzr 
RNAi clones contained as many as 10-16 cells/ 
clone (Fig. 5 J, right), indicating that multiple rounds of com-
plete extra cell cycles occurred with normal adult wing cuticle 
differentiation. This finding was consistent with our observation 
that E2F + Rca1 expression also increased the frequency of larger 
clones in the wing (Fig. S2 D). 
We hypothesized that high APC/C activity after exit could 
limit E2F-induced bypass of cell cycle exit by degrading key 
E2F targets. This is consistent with our finding that E2F1-DP-
overexpressing cells do not accumulate the known APC/C targets 
CycA, Geminin (Gem; Zielke et al., 2008), CycB, or Stg (based 
on a Stg-GFP fusion protein) after prolonged exit in wings or 
eyes (40-44 h APF; Fig. 6, A, C, E, and G; and Fig. S3), despite 
expressing high levels of cycA, gem, stg, and cycB transcripts by 
microarray (see supplemental dataset and <rs type="software">JCB DataViewer</rs>). 
In contrast, cells expressing E2F + Rca1 together accumulated 
CycA in wings (Fig. 6 B), Stg-GFP in eyes (Fig. 6 D), Gem in 
eyes (Fig. 6 H), and very low levels of CycB in wings and eyes 
(Fig. 6 F and Fig. S3). 
In contrast to other cyclins, E2F activity is able to induce 
CycE protein accumulation after prolonged exit (Buttitta et al., 
2007) because CycE is not a target for degradation by the APC/C. 
CycE activity is thought to inhibit the APC/C (Sigrist and 
Lehner, 1997; Reber et al., 2006). Therefore, an increase in 
APC/C levels could raise the CycE threshold after exit by re-
quiring increased CycE for complete APC/C inhibition. Consis-
tent with this, we found that cells overexpressing high levels 
of CycE-Cdk2 accumulated APC/C targets such as Gem and 
CycA after exit (Fig. 6, I and J). 
We suggest that high APC/C activity after exit raises the 
threshold of CycE and Stg required for cell cycle reentry of dif-
ferentiated cells. This appears to be increased even further by 
aberrant E2F activity in differentiated cells by increasing the ex-
pression of several core components as well as inducing expres-
sion of the activator fzy. This could explain why the increased 
CycE expression provided by high E2F activity alone is insuffi-
cient to bypass cell cycle exit after terminal differentiation. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Studies of terminal differentiation and cell cycle exit have 
largely focused on events initiating the inhibition of CycE and 
E2F activity (for reviews see Myster and Duronio, 2000; Buttitta 
and Edgar, 2007; Miller et al., 2007; Pajalunga et al., 2008). 
Several genes have been identified that can temporarily delay 
exit either by increasing cyclin-Cdk activity or by preventing 
E2F inhibition in Drosophila. Relatively little attention, though, 
has focused on the mechanisms that ultimately act to establish </p>

<p>in dacapo-null mutant cells overexpressing E2F1-DP (Buttitta 
et al., 2007). In our array analysis, we noted that E2F activity 
(or Dp loss) induced expression of several components of the 
APC/C and certain APC/C activators (Fig. 5 A). Therefore, 
we wondered whether high APC/C activity could limit E2F-
induced cell cycle reentry after differentiation. 
The fly orthologues of at least one APC/C activator (Cdh1 or 
Fizzy [Fzy]-related [Fzr] in flies) and one core APC/C component 
(APC1 or Shattered in flies) normally increase after cell cycle 
exit in eyes (Pimentel and Venkatesh, 2005; Tanaka-Matakatsu 
et al., 2007; Zielke, 2007). We have confirmed that both Fzr 
transcript and protein also increase in wings after normal exit 
(Fig. S2 C). We speculated that an increase in APC/C activity after 
exit could limit E2F-induced bypass of exit by degrading the 
G2-M cyclin-Cdks and Stg, which are known APC/C targets. This 
could also raise the threshold for CycE after exit by requiring in-
creased CycE-Cdk2 activity to inhibit the high levels of APC/C 
(Sigrist et al., 1995; Sigrist and Lehner, 1997; Reber et al., 2006). 
This idea is consistent with the finding that the loss of fzr or shat-
tered delays cell cycle exit by one cycle in the embryo and larval 
eye (Sigrist and Lehner, 1997; Pimentel and Venkatesh, 2005; 
Tanaka-Matakatsu et al., 2007). Therefore, we examined whether 
APC/C activity contributes to cell cycle exit in both the pupal 
eye and wing and to what extent inhibition of the APC/C could 
delay exit. 
To inhibit the APC/C upon cell cycle exit without disturb-
ing mitotic cycles, we overexpressed Rca1, an S and G2 inhibitor 
of the APC/C which leads to accumulation of CycA but does 
not disrupt mitosis when overexpressed (Grosskortenhaus and 
Sprenger, 2002). Clones of cells expressing Rca1 temporarily 
delayed cell cycle exit (Fig. 5 B) but did not continue significant 
cycling after 40 h APF in the eye or wing (Fig. 5 C, eye shown 
exhibiting the sole mitosis observed). However, when E2F and 
Rca1 were coexpressed, continued mitoses were observed very 
late in the eye and wing, including the latest time point tested, 60 h 
APF, without disrupting terminal differentiation of ommatidia 
(Fig. 5, D and E; and Fig. S2 A). 
Rca1 increases CycA by inhibition of the APC/C. How-
ever, the effect of Rca1 + E2F on cell cycle exit was not simply 
caused by an increase in CycA levels, as coexpression of CycA 
with E2F1-DP could not continue to bypass exit after 40-44 h 
APF in wings or eyes (Fig. S2 B). APC/C activity is dependent 
on sufficient levels of core components and the presence of 
the activators Cdc20 (Fzy in Drosophila) and Fzr. To directly 
reduce APC/C activity in cells overexpressing E2F, we co-
expressed E2F with RNAis to core APC/C components (APC2 
and -8) or the activators Fzy or Fzr in clones and examined late 
pupal eyes and wings after 48 h APF for ectopic cycling. We 
observed frequent mitoses, as assessed by both PH3 and MPM2 
cytoplasmic staining in pupal eyes and wings at 56 h APF, when 
E2F was coexpressed with each RNAi (Fig. 5, F-I; and Fig. S2, 
E and F). We also observed MPM2 nuclear foci indicative of 
G1-S progression in cells expressing E2F + Fzy 
RNAi (Fig. 5 F, 
inset), suggesting complete additional cell cycles occur. 
To confirm that additional cell cycles occurred, we per-
formed a clonal analysis on cells coexpressing E2F with Fzy or 
Fzr RNAi, as well as cells expressing E2F and an RNAi to Cortex, </p>

<p> 
Mechanisms maintaining cell cycle exit • Buttitta et al. </p>

<p>CycE ubiquitin ligase Fbw7 (Archipelago in Drosophila), Hippo 
signaling, and cycE transcriptional down-regulation (Li and 
Vaessin, 2000; Moberg et al., 2001; Firth and Baker, 2005; Choksi 
et al., 2006; Sukhanova et al., 2007; Nicolay and Frolov, 2008). 
This leads to hypophosphorylation of Rbf, resulting in E2F-DP 
target gene repression and stable cell cycle arrest. Yet, cell cycle 
exit still occurs in mutants lacking these CycE inhibitors and in the 
presence of high CycE-Cdk2 activity, demonstrating that addi-
tional mechanisms can trigger exit (Buttitta et al., 2007). </p>

<p>and maintain robust cell cycle exit in these situations. The data 
we present in this study suggest a model for robust maintenance 
of cell cycle exit in terminally differentiated cells, even in the 
face of aberrant CycE or E2F activity. </p>

<p>Robust cell cycle exit mechanisms </p>

<p>Previous studies in Drosophila have suggested that cell cycle exit 
is normally triggered by a decrease in CycE-Cdk2 activity, through 
the cooperation of multiple CycE inhibitors such as Dacapo, the </p>

<p>Figure 6. APC/C activity limits accumulation of E2F-induced cell cycle regulators. GFP-marked clones expressing the indicated cell cycle regulators were 
generated using hs-FLP tub&gt;Gal4/UAS, tub-Gal80 
TS and examined for CycA, CycB, or Gem (A, B, and E-J). Clones negatively marked by CD2, expressing 
the indicated regulators (C and D) were generated using hs-FLP act&gt;Gal4/UAS and examined for Stg-GFP fusion protein. Cells expressing E2F1-DP in the 
wing and eye fail to accumulate CycA (A), Stg-GFP (C), Gem (E), and CycB (G) at 40-48 h APF. Cells coexpressing E2F1-DP + Rca1 accumulate CycA (B) 
and low levels of CycB in the wing (F), as well as Stg-GFP and Gem in the eye (D and H). Cells expressing CycE-Cdk2 accumulate Gem in the eye (I) and 
CycA in wing (J). (F, I, and J) Yellow outlines indicate clone boundaries. (D) Arrows indicate examples of clones with increased Stg-GFP expression. Bars, 
50 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 189 • NUMBER 6 • 2010 </p>

<p>
effect on the cell cycle after terminal differentiation? During 
proliferative stages, overexpression of CycE-Cdk2 does not 
arrest cells, and E2F1 is able to reaccumulate after S phase. In 
contrast, cells with high CycE-Cdk2 after differentiation fail to 
complete their final G1-S transition or arrest in S phase with 
low E2F1 protein levels (Buttitta et al., 2007), suggesting that 
the E2F1 degradation machinery remains active. This arrest 
may be partially caused by the depletion of E2F target genes 
critical for S-phase completion. But the arrest of rbf 
/ cells 
overexpressing CycE in the wing blade, which have high levels 
of E2F target gene expression from previous cell cycles, sug-
gests that there may also be an activation of a checkpoint or 
inhibition of a key activity for S-phase completion independent 
of E2F transcriptional regulation after terminal differentiation. 
Although we do not know the specific mechanism for this ar-
rest, the addition of Stg is able to restore cycling in rbf 
/ cells 
overexpressing CycE (Fig. 3 and Table I). This demonstrates 
that Stg or a target of Cdk1 activity is able to bypass the arrest 
of cells with high CycE-Cdk2 after terminal differentiation to 
allow E2F1 reaccumulation. 
Importantly, the cell cycle control mechanisms we describe 
in this study do not act alone at exit. They likely cooperate with 
other cell cycle inhibitors known to promote exit such as Dacapo, 
Fbw7, and Hippo signaling. These cell cycle controls together 
limit cell cycle reentry to ensure robust cell cycle exit upon 
terminal differentiation. </p>

<p>APC/C functions in terminally </p>

<p>differentiated cells </p>

<p>The data presented in this study demonstrate an important role 
for the APC/C in maintaining cell cycle exit in the face of aber-
rant E2F activity in terminally differentiated postmitotic tissues 
(Fig. 5). Interestingly, work in mammalian neurons has shown 
additional postmitotic functions for the APC/C in mature cells 
(Puram et al., 2010). Both the APC/C 
Fzr/Cdh1 and APC/C </p>

<p>Cdc20 </p>

<p>complexes carry out important nonmitotic functions in the con-
trol of axon and dendrite growth and patterning, synapse devel-
opment, and neuron survival (Konishi et al., 2004; Li et al., 
2008; Huynh et al., 2009; Kim et al., 2009; Yang et al., 2009). 
This suggests that the APC/C complexes in many terminally 
differentiated cells carry out previously unappreciated dual 
roles in promoting postmitotic cell maturation and protecting 
against aberrant cell cycle reentry. This is supported by the re-
cent finding that Cdh1 is a haplo-insufficient tumor suppressor 
in mice (García-Higuera et al., 2008), although further studies 
will be required to determine whether the tumors in Cdh1 </p>

<p>APC/C 
Fzr activity normally increases at G1 arrest, degrad-
ing G2 and mitotic cell cycle targets such as CycA, CycB, and 
Stg (Fig. S2; Sigrist and Lehner, 1997; Pimentel and Venkatesh, 
2005; Tanaka-Matakatsu et al., 2007; Zielke, 2007). This func-
tion of the APC/C is essential for timely exit, as loss of the APC/C 
is sufficient to cause an additional cell cycle, likely via un-
restrained CycA activity (Table I; Sigrist and Lehner, 1997; Jacobs 
et al., 2001; Buttitta et al., 2007; Tanaka-Matakatsu et al., 2007). 
The mammalian APC/C 
Fzr/Cdh1 has been shown to interact with 
RB to promote cell cycle exit via degradation of Skp2 and sub-
sequent stabilization of p27 
Kip1 (Binné et al., 2007). A similar 
mechanism may also act to promote exit in Drosophila via 
APC/C </p>

<p>Fzr </p>

<p>, Rbf, and Dacapo, but functions for a Drosophila Skp2 
homologue in cell cycle control have not yet been examined. 
When E2F is aberrantly activated in differentiating cells, 
expression of several APC/C 
Fzy components increases and may 
cooperate with high APC/C 
Fzr to limit the accumulation of mi-
totic cyclins and other essential E2F transcriptional targets for 
cycling such as Stg (Figs. 5 and 6). CycE-Cdk2 activity has been 
shown to inhibit APC/C (Sigrist and Lehner, 1997; Reber et al., 
2006), and thus, the increased APC/C activity present in differ-
entiating cells may raise the threshold levels of CycE required 
for APC/C suppression. Our data suggest that this may explain, 
at least in part, why supraphysiological levels of ectopic CycE 
are required to bypass cell cycle exit in differentiating wings and 
eyes (Fig. 7). 
If CycE-Cdk2 is aberrantly activated in differentiating 
cells, cell cycle exit is temporarily delayed with cells arresting at 
the G1-S transition or in early S phase with phosphorylated his-
tone locus bodies and some partially replicated DNA (Buttitta 
et al., 2007). In such cells, the S phase-dependent degradation of 
E2F1 protein by the Cul4 ubiquitin E3 ligase appears to remain 
on, leading to an increased ratio of repressive E2F2 to E2F1. This 
ultimately results in stable CycE-Cdk2-resistant repression of 
E2F target genes and cell cycle exit (Fig. 1). If E2F2 is absent, 
aberrant CycE-Cdk2 leads to S-phase initiation and PIP box-
dependent Cul4-mediated destruction of E2F1, resulting in loss 
of both E2Fs and thereby loss of all E2F-DP function. This situa-
tion is similar to that in Dp mutants, which lack all E2F-dependent 
transcriptional function. In these mutants, critical cell cycle genes, 
including Stg and other cyclin-Cdk regulators, are protected from 
derepression (Fig. 4 B), and their expression remains low, ensur-
ing a noncycling state. 
The S phase-dependent degradation of E2F1 occurs nor-
mally during proliferation (Shibutani et al., 2008), so how does 
the normally transient degradation of E2F1 have such a profound </p>

<p>Figure 7. A robust cell cycle control mecha-
nism limits E2F-induced proliferation after cell 
cycle exit. (A) E2F-dependent transcriptional 
repression (dotted lines) of targets, including 
many APC/C components, is established at exit. 
(B) If aberrant E2F activity occurs, transcrip-
tional activation (dotted arrows) of APC/C 
components and activators limits the accumu-
lation of key cell cycle targets such as Stg. 
(C) The resulting high APC/C activity in differ-
entiating cells requires increased CycE to by-
pass exit, thereby raising the CycE threshold. </p>

<p> 
Mechanisms maintaining cell cycle exit • Buttitta et al. </p>

<p>and w;Dp </p>

<p>a2 </p>

<p>/Cyo-GFP (Royzman et al., 1997); w; de2f2 
c03344 FRT40A 
(from M. Frolov, University of Illinois, Chicago, IL; Ambrus et al., 2007); 
de2f2 
G5.1 and de2f2 
76Q1 (both from Frolov et al. [2001]); and w; Stg-GFP 
Yale Trap insertions YD0685 and YD0246 were also used. w; UAS-Fzr </p>

<p>RNAi </p>

<p>, 
w; UAS-Fzy </p>

<p>RNAi </p>

<p>, w; UAS-Cortex </p>

<p>RNAi </p>

<p>, w; UAS-APC2 </p>

<p>RNAi </p>

<p>, and w; UAS-APC8 </p>

<p>RNAi </p>

<p>are all from the Vienna Drosophila RNAi Center (#25550, #44834, 
#41472, #2993, and #52279, respectively). </p>

<p>Antibodies 
Antibodies used were rabbit -phospho-Ser10-histone H3 (PH3; 1:4,000; 
Millipore), mouse -phospho-Ser10-histone H3 (PH3; 1:1,000; Milli-
pore), mouse -MPM2 (1:500; Millipore), mouse -BrdU (1:100; BD), rat 
-ELAV (embryonic lethal abnormal vision; 1:200; Developmental Studies 
Hybridoma Bank), rabbit -GFP (1:1,000; Invitrogen), mouse -rat CD2 
(1:800; AbD Serotec), mouse -CycA (1:100; Developmental Studies 
Hybridoma Bank), mouse -CycB (1:50; Developmental Studies Hybrid-
oma Bank), rabbit -Gem (1:100; provided by B. Calvi, Indiana Univer-
sity, Bloomington, IN), and rabbit -Fzr (1:3,000; provided by C. Lehner, 
University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland). Appropriate secondary antibodies 
were Alexa Fluor 488, 568, or 633 conjugated (Invitrogen) and used 
at 1:4,000. </p>

<p>Histology 
Pupae, staged from white prepupae (0 h) at 25°C, were dissected and 
fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde in 1× PBS for 30 min at room tempera-
ture. Pupal cuticle was removed from wings after fixation. Tissues 24-36 h 
APF were blocked in PBS + 0.1% Triton X-100 + 1% BSA for 1 h. Tissues 
36-44 h APF were blocked in PBS + 0.3% Triton X-100 + 1% BSA (PAT) 
overnight. For stages after 44 h APF, we incorporated a methanol dehydra-
tion series after fixation (25, 50, 75, and 100% methanol/1× PBS, 10 min 
each) that allowed improved antibody penetration, increased sensitivity, 
and BrdU detection for tissues 44-60 h APF. After step-wise rehydration, 
tissues were blocked in PAT overnight, and antibody staining or BrdU incor-
poration was performed as described previously (Buttitta et al., 2007; 
Zielke et al., 2008) using Alexa Fluor 488-, Alexa Fluor 568-or Alexa 
Fluor 633-conjugated secondary antibodies and Vectashield mounting 
medium (Vector Laboratories). Wing hinge and notum as well as head 
capsule and antenna were excluded from our analyses. 1 µg/ml Hoechst 
33258 (Invitrogen) was used to label nuclei. Confocal sections and differ-
ential interference contrast images were collected on a microscope (LSM 
510; Carl Zeiss, Inc.) using a 25× objective. Single representative sections 
(2.2 µm) are shown, except for Fig. 3 (E and F), which are projections of 
eight sections at a 1-µm interval. Images were cropped using <rs id="software-9" type="software">Photoshop</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-9" type="creator">Adobe</rs>). Mitotic index was calculated as the mean number of PH3-positive 
cells/100 GFP-positive cells among multiple clones in several samples, 
counted blind, from at least two independent experiments. </p>

<p>Clonal overexpression 
We used the hs-Flp/FRT tub&gt;CD2&gt;Gal4 method for clonal overexpression, 
with tub temperature-sensitive Gal80 (Gal80 </p>

<p>TS </p>

<p>; McGuire et al., 2004). 
Gal80 
TS was inactivated at 29°C. Hours APF are presented as equivalent 
time at 25°C for simplicity. All incubation times were adjusted appropri-
ately as described previously (Buttitta et al., 2007). Loss of function clones 
(or appropriate controls) were generated using MARCM (Lee and Luo, 
2001). Larvae were heat shocked for 45 min at 37°C at 60-72 h after egg 
deposition, collected for staging at 0 h APF, aged at 25°C, and dissected 
at the indicated times. </p>

<p>Clonal cell counts 
Nonoverlapping clones labeled with membrane-bound GFP, expressing the 
indicated regulators, were induced at 0 h APF (white prepupae) and fixed 
54-56 h later, nuclei were labeled with 1 µg/ml Hoechst 33258, and 
cells/clone were counted. We excluded wings with &gt;50 clones/wing 
(to reduce the possibility of independent clones merging). We also excluded 
clones in the wing margin, hinge, notum area, and hemocytes in the veins. No 
apoptosis inhibitor was used in the clonal cell count experiments. </p>

<p>Microarray 
For microarray experiments, 10 pupal wings from animals expressing 
E2F1 and DP (ap-Gal4/UAS-E2F1, UAS-DP, tub-Gal80 </p>

<p>TS </p>

<p>) and controls 
(ap-Gal4/UAS, tub-Gal80 </p>

<p>TS </p>

<p>) or Dp mutants (w;Dp </p>

<p>a1/a2 </p>

<p>) and controls (w) were 
dissected at the appropriate time points. For E2F1-DP samples, tempera-
ture shifts limited the overexpression to pupal stages. For L3 discs, E2F1-DP 
was expressed for the equivalent of 24 h before dissection of wandering 
larvae. RNA was isolated using standard techniques (TRIZOL), and cDNA 
synthesis was performed with one subsequent round of T7-dependent linear </p>

<p>heterozygotes arise from defects in cell cycle exit, cell cycle 
reentry, or genetic instability in proliferating cells. </p>

<p>Cell cycle exit, terminal differentiation, </p>

<p>and cancer </p>

<p>It is becoming increasingly clear that certain highly differentiated 
cells retain the ability to enter the cell cycle. In some cases, this 
serves a beneficial regenerative function, as recently shown for 
terminally differentiated cardiomyocytes in the zebrafish heart 
(Jopling et al., 2010; Kikuchi et al., 2010). But in other cases, this 
ability seems to be a part of the normal tissue development, as 
shown for differentiated horizontal cells that reenter the cell cycle 
for their final division in the zebrafish retina before full matura-
tion (Godinho et al., 2007). Proliferation of terminally differenti-
ated mammalian cells has also been observed in monocytes and 
macrophages lacking the c-Maf and MafB transcription factors 
(Aziz et al., 2009). Strikingly, Maf double knockout macrophages 
appear to fully retain their differentiation-associated functions 
in vivo despite exhibiting continued cycling for months, demon-
strating a clear independence of differentiation and cell cycle exit 
in these cells (Aziz et al., 2009). 
We have shown that cell cycle exit is not essential for ter-
minal differentiation in Drosophila eyes and wings. Evasion of 
the robust cell cycle exit mechanism by loss of the tumor sup-
pressor rbf together with deregulation of CycE and Stg can lead 
to tumor-like overproliferation of differentiated tissues (Fig. 3). 
Our results may be relevant to specific cancers such as retino-
blastoma, where aberrantly dividing differentiated cells have 
been proposed to be the cancer cell of origin (Chen et al., 2004; 
Ajioka et al., 2007; Xu et al., 2009). Aberrant division of differ-
entiated cells could lead to genetic instability and acquisition of 
secondary mutations, leading to dedifferentiation and ultimately 
to metastatic cancer. Our data show that the robust exit mecha-
nism is essential for proper tissue development and suggest that 
even terminally differentiated cells should not be excluded as a 
potential source of cancer. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Fly strains 
The following fly strains were used: w 
1118 ; y w hsflp </p>

<p>122 </p>

<p>;UAS-CycE (Neufeld 
et al., 1998); y w hsflp 
122 ;+;UAS-CycE,UAS-Stg (Neufeld et al., 1998); 
y w hsflp </p>

<p>122 </p>

<p>;+;UAS-CycE,UAS-Cdk2 (Meyer et al., 2000); y w hsflp 
122 ;UAS-
E2F,UAS-DP/Cyo-GFP (UAS-DP from N. Dyson, Massachusetts General 
Hospital, Boston, MA; Neufeld et al., 1998); y w hsflp </p>

<p>122 </p>

<p>;UASp-GFP-
E2F1 </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>;UAS-CycE,UAS-Cdk2 and y w hsflp 
122 ;UASp-GFP-E2F1 </p>

<p>PIP3A </p>

<p>; 
UAS-CycE,UAS-Cdk2 (UASp-GFP-E2F1 from Shibutani et al. [2008]); w; 
UAS T -GFP-E2F1 
WT and w;UAS T -GFP-E2F1 
WT PIP3A (provided by J. Davidson 
and R. Duronio, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, NC); y w 
hsflp </p>

<p>122 </p>

<p>;UAS-CycA;+ (Jacobs et al., 2001); w;act&gt;CD2&gt;Gal4,UAS-GFP 
(Pignoni and Zipursky, 1997); w;tub&gt;CD2&gt;Gal4,UAS-GFP;tub-Gal80 </p>

<p>TS </p>

<p>(tub&gt;CD2&gt;Gal4 from F. Pignoni, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA; 
Gal80 
TS described in McGuire et al. [2004]); w;tub&gt;CD2&gt;Gal4,UAS-
GFP;tub-Gal80 </p>

<p>TS </p>

<p>,UAS-Diap (UAS-Diap from Lohmann et al. [2002]); w;ap-
Gal4,UAS-GFP/CyO;tub-Gal80 
TS (ap-Gal4 described in Calleja et al. 
[1996]); FRT19A,w,rbf 
14 /FM7 (from W. Du, University of Chicago, Chi-
cago, IL; Du and Dyson, 1999); y w hsflp122;+;UAS-Rca1 (from F. 
Sprenger, University of Regensburg, Regensburg, Germany; Zielke et al., 
2008); and FRT19A,w,rbf 
14 /FM7;+; UAS-CycE,UAS-Stg. 
FRT19A,ywhsflp 
122 , tub-Gal80; tub-Gal4,UAS-GFP/MKRS (Lee and 
Luo, 2001); y w hsflp </p>

<p>122 </p>

<p>,tub-Gal4,UAS-GFP;FRT42D tub-Gal80 (Jiang et al., 
2009); w;+; act&gt;CD2&gt;Gal4, PCNA-GFP (PCNA-GFP from Thacker et al. 
[2003]); FRT42D,Dp </p>

<p>a3 </p>

<p>/CyO-GFP;+ (from Frolov et al. [2005]); w;Dp </p>

<p>a1 </p>

<p>/CyO-GFP </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 189 • NUMBER 6 • 2010 </p>

<p>
with statistical analysis. Thanks also to E. Payandeh for help with mitotic index 
quantifications. We thank Drs. B. Calvi, W. Du, R. Duronio, C. Lehner, 
F. Sprenger, M. Frolov, and N. Dyson and the Bloomington and Vienna Stock 
Centers, The Yale Flytrap collection, and the Developmental Studies Hybrid-
oma Bank for flies and/or antibodies. 
L.A. Buttitta was supported by a Leukemia and Lymphoma Society Spe-
cial Fellowship (LLS#3370-09) and National Institutes of Health (NIH) grant 
(K99 GM086517). A Developmental Biology training grant (T32 HD07183) 
supported A.J. Katzaroff. This work was also supported by an NIH grant 
(GM070887) to B.A. Edgar. </p>

<p>Submitted: 1 October 2009 
Accepted: 12 May 2010 </p>

<p><rs id="software-2" type="software">Genesis</rs><rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-date">2002</rs><rs id="software-3" type="software">GOrilla</rs><rs corresp="#software-3" type="url">http://cbl-gorilla.cs.technion.ac.il</rs><rs id="software-4" type="software">FatiGO</rs><rs corresp="#software-4" type="url">http://www.babelomics.org</rs> 
Additional description of microarray data. In addition to the analysis 
provided in the results section, we also examined the other clusters of tran-
scripts affected by E2F activity in the wing. The second largest cluster of 
coregulated genes in E2F-overexpressing and Dp mutant wings was re-
pressed in differentiating cells. Because E2F1-DP is thought to act as a 
transcriptional activator, this group of repressed genes is somewhat un-
expected. These genes are not repressed indirectly by a delay in cell cycle 
exit, as they are similarly repressed in Dp mutants, which exit normally. We 
also do not believe that this group is caused by E2F1-DP repressive com-
plexes blocking transcription, as such targets would be expected to in-
crease rather than decrease in Dp mutants. One possibility suggested by 
Bracken et al. (2004) is that the extensive transcriptional up-regulation 
caused by E2F (or in Dp mutants) could cause some spurious antisense reg-
ulation of genes. Although we have not investigated this possibility, &gt;0% of 
the transcriptional changes we observed in both genotypes are indeed in-
creases in transcript levels. Overall, this group of repressed transcripts 
is significantly enriched for genes involved in monooxygenase activity 
(caused by six cytochromeP450 genes; P &lt; 8.08 
4 ) and genes with cat-
alytic activity (P &lt; 5.85 
4 ), suggesting some functional significance for 
this group. 
We were surprised to find that most transcripts were not affected by 
E2F overexpression or Dp loss at the proliferative L3 time point. This may be 
because E2F target gene expression is already high in controls during prolif-
eration, as evident by the high activity of the E2F reporter construct (PCNA-
GFP) and high levels of E2F target gene expression at this stage (Thacker 
et al., 2003). This is also supported by our finding that the few transcripts 
up-regulated by E2F and/or Dp loss at L3 are normally at low abundance in 
wings and were significantly (P &lt; 0.009) enriched for genes with expression 
one standard deviation lower than the mean gene expression. These tran-
scripts were also enriched for genes identified as group D or E germline/ 
differentiation genes specifically regulated by E2F2 in Dimova et al. (2003), 
which we find to be ectopically induced in nongermline tissues by E2F over-
expression and Dp loss (examples include spn-E, nanos, BthD, CG6790, 
CG8316, and CG7628). Thus, the transcriptional activation of E2F targets 
at proliferative stages seems to be masked by the high levels of E2F activity 
already present in the controls. Interestingly, this also suggests that normal 
levels of E2F targets are somehow maintained in an E2F-DP-independent 
manner in proliferating Dp mutant cells. </p>

<p>Western blotting 
Western blots were performed as described previously (Prober and Edgar, 
2000) with the following modifications. Protein was isolated from 20 pupal 
or larval wings (with notum removed) by boiling for 5 min in 40 µl of 1× SDS 
sample buffer containing -mercaptoethanol. 20 µl of sample was then 
used for SDS-PAGE. Rabbit anti-Fzr (provided by C. Lehner) was used at 
1:3,000 with the appropriate HRP-conjugated secondary antibody. </p>

<p>Online supplemental material 
Fig. S1 shows that bypass of cell cycle exit is limited, even in the ab-
sence of all E2F-DP function. Fig. S2 shows GFP-labeled clones expressing 
the indicated cell cycle regulators generated using hs-FLP tub&gt;Gal4/ 
UAS, tub-Gal80 
TS . Fig. S3 shows GFP-marked clones expressing the 
indicated cell cycle regulators generated using hs-FLP tub&gt;Gal4/UAS, 
tub-Gal80 
TS and examined for CycB or Gem. The complete E2F and Dp </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>array dataset (provided as tab-delimited text) is included as a txt file. 
Complete microarray clusters are also available for viewing on the <rs type="software">JCB 
DataViewer</rs>. Online supplemental material is available at http://www.jcb 
.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200910006/DC1. </p>

<p>We thank members of the Edgar and Schubiger Laboratories, especially 
J. Bandura and N. Zielke for helpful discussions, the Fred Hutchinson Cancer 
Research Center Imaging and Array Facilities for help with data acquisition 
and array hybridizations, and S. Thomas, J. Davison, and M. Morgan for help </p>

<p> 
Mechanisms maintaining cell cycle exit • Buttitta et al. </p>



<p>JCB • VOLUME 189 • NUMBER 6 • 2010 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>