<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2652046" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>To date, the most prevalent model for transport of pre-proteins to plant mitochondria is based on the activity of an 
N-terminal extension serving as a targeting peptide. Whether the efficient delivery of proteins to mitochondria is 
based exclusively on the action of the N-terminal extension or also on that of other protein determinants has yet to 
be defined. A novel mechanism is reported here for the targeting of a plant protein, named MITS1, to mitochondria. It 
was found that MITS1 contains an N-terminal extension that is responsible for mitochondrial targeting. Functional 
dissection of this extension shows the existence of a cryptic signal for protein targeting to the secretory pathway. 
The first 11 amino acids of the N-terminal extension are necessary to overcome the activity of this signal sequence 
and target the protein to the mitochondria. These data suggest that co-operation of multiple determinants within the 
N-terminal extension of mitochondrial proteins may be necessary for efficient mitochondrial targeting. It was also 
established that the presence of a tryptophan residue toward the C-terminus of the protein is crucial for 
mitochondrial targeting, as mutation of this residue results in a redistribution of MITS1 to the endoplasmic reticulum 
and Golgi apparatus. These data suggest a novel targeting model whereby protein traffic to plant mitochondria is 
influenced by domains in the full-length protein as well as the N-terminal extension. </p>

<p>In eukaryotic cells, the presence of several distinct organelles 
generates the need for efficient protein targeting mechanisms 
of newly synthesized proteins. Targeting of most proteins 
destined to the secretory pathway is initiated by the binding 
of the signal recognition particle (SRP) to a signal sequence 
in a nascent polypeptide chain emerging from a cytosolic 
ribosome. The nascent polypeptide is then co-translationally 
inserted in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) upon recognition 
of the SRP by an ER-membrane anchored SRP receptor 
(Nagai et al., 2003). The synthesis of proteins destined to 
other organelles, such as plastids and mitochondria, generally 
occurs on free ribosomes and the targeting is post-trans-
lational (reviewed in Alder and Johnson, 2004). Protein 
targeting to mitochondria relies on an N-terminal extension </p>

<p>on the protein precursor, the so-called pre-sequence, which 
directs the protein to the organelles. Pre-sequences do not 
have a common primary sequence but are generally com-
posed of an N-terminal leader sequence of 20-35 amino 
acids, enriched in basic, hydrophobic, and hydroxylated 
residues (Neupert, 1997; Schatz and Dobberstein, 1996). The 
pre-sequence appears to fold into a defined secondary 
structure. This folding is essential for the correct distribution 
of charged and apolar residues and is necessary for efficient 
protein import (Matouschek et al., 1997; Gaume et al., 1998). 
The N-terminal part of the pre-sequence forms a positively 
charged amphiphilic a-helix or b-sheet, whereas the C-
terminal region probably serves as a recognition site for 
matrix proteases (Gavel and von Heijne, 1990; Neupert, </p>

<p>* These authors contributed equally to the work. 
y To whom correspondence should be addressed: E-mail: brandizz@msu.edu 
ª 2008 The Author(s). </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-
nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>1997). Pre-sequences are generally cleaved off from precur-
sors as they pass through the mitochondrial double mem-
brane via the outer and inner membrane translocases (TOM 
and TIM complexes, respectively), or once inside the mito-
chondria by specific peptidases (for reviews see Neupert, 
1997; Glaser et al., 1998). 
Although it is generally assumed that import mechanisms 
are conserved in different organisms, import mechanisms 
into plant mitochondria appear to rely on several peculiar-
ities that include proteins involved in the TIM and TOM 
complexes and the primary and secondary structures of the 
pre-sequences (for a review see Millar et al., 2006). Much 
information on mitochondrial protein targeting mechanisms 
has been gathered from the functional dissection of the N-
terminal pre-sequences (Logan and Leaver, 2000; Chabregas 
et al., 2001; Duby et al., 2001). There is, however, little 
information on whether pre-sequences are the exclusive de-
terminants for mitochondrial targeting or if other protein 
domains influence the efficiency of the process. 
The question of whether the functional role of a mito-
chondrial pre-sequence may be influenced by distal amino 
acid residues within the full-length protein is addressed 
here. A novel nuclear-encoded Arabidopsis thaliana protein 
has been identified, called MITS1 (MItochondrial-Targeting 
Signal 1), which appears to be targeted to mitochondria. 
Live cell imaging analyses of the N-terminal extension of 
MITS1 and a series of MITS1-deletions fused to the yellow 
fluorescent protein (YFP) indicated that the N-terminal pre-
sequence is responsible for the intracellular targeting of the 
protein. However, in contrast to the full-length peptide, a 
leaderless pre-sequence (lacking the first 11 amino acids) di-
rected YFP protein fusions to the ER. Furthermore, muta-
tion of a tryptophan residue at position 361 (W361A) 
resulted in the redistribution of MITS1 to the ER and 
Golgi apparatus, suggesting that mitochondrial targeting pro-
cesses in plant cells may rely not only on the composition of 
the pre-sequence but also on that of other domains within 
the protein sequence. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Plant material and transient expression systems </p>

<p>Four-week-old Nicotiana tabacum (cv. Petit Havana) green-
house plants grown at 25°C were used for Agrobacterium 
tumefaciens (strain GV3101)-mediated transient expression 
(Batoko et al., 2000). The bacterial optical density (OD 600 ) 
used for plant leaf transformation was 0.05 for MITS1:YFP 
and its mutants and for b-ATPase:GFP, and 0.2 for 
ERD2:GFP. </p>

<p>Molecular cloning </p>

<p>Standard molecular techniques were used for subcloning 
(Sambrook et al., 1989). The fluorescent proteins used in 
this study were based on fusions with either mGFP5 
(Haseloff et al., 1997) or EYFP (Clontech Inc., Palo Alto, 
CA, USA). The spectral properties of mGFP5 allow </p>

<p>efficient spectral separation from YFP (Brandizzi et al., 
2002). The ER/Golgi marker used in this study was the H/ 
KDEL receptor ERD2 fused to GFP (Boevink et al., 1998). 
The mitochondrial marker b-ATPase:GFP was a generous 
gift of Dr DC Logan, University of St Andrews, UK 
(Logan and Leaver, 2000). The cDNA of MITS1 
(At1g52080, Ref. NM_104089) was amplified by PCR from 
an ABRC clone. Point mutations and deletion mutants were 
created using site-directed mutagenesis. The binary vector 
pVKH18En6 (Batoko et al., 2000) was used for all the 
constructions in this study. All the prepared inserts were 
spliced upstream of YFP, using the unique XbaI and SalI 
sites of the vector (daSilva et al., 2004). A methionine 
residue was added to the N-terminus of the 12-39 deletion 
mutant to allow translation. </p>

<p>Bio-informatic, sampling, imaging, and quantification </p>

<p>The bio-informatic tools for the prediction of MITS1 
targeting to mitochondria were <rs id="software-1" type="software">Predotar</rs> (Small et al., 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">2004</rs>), <rs type="software">iPSORT</rs> and <rs type="software">PSORTII</rs> (Bannai et al., 2002), 
<rs type="software">MitoPred</rs> (Guda et al., 2004), and <rs type="software">SignalP</rs> (Nielsen et al., 
1997). The simulation of the Helical Wheel Projection of the 
MITS1 N-terminal was from http://rzlab.ucr.edu/scripts/ 
wheel/wheel.cgi (D Armstrong and R Zidovetzki). 
Imaging was performed using an upright Zeiss Laser 
Scanning Confocal Microscope LSM510 META (Zeiss, 
Jena, Germany) with a 363 water immersion objective. 
Transformed leaves were analysed 48 h after infection of the 
lower epidermis. For imaging expression of YFP constructs, 
GFP constructs or both, the imaging settings as described 
by Brandizzi et al. (2002) were used. Appropriate controls 
were used to exclude the possibility of energy transfer be-
tween fluorochromes and cross-talk. Images were acquired 
using non-saturating settings and the same imaging param-
eters were used. Post-acquisition image processing was 
carried out using <rs type="software">CorelDraw12</rs> software. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>MITS1 is efficiently targeted to plant mitochondria </p>

<p>MITS1 (AGI: At1g52080) is a putative actin-binding pro-
tein of 573 amino acid residues with a predicted molecular 
mass of 66 kDa. The N-terminal region of this protein (39 
amino acids) contains a hydrophobic stretch of 20 residues 
(predicted with <rs type="software">TMHMM</rs> and <rs type="software">TMPred</rs> (Hofmann and 
Stoffel, 1993; Krogh et al., 2001) and flanking regions en-
riched with positively-charged amino acids (Fig. 1A). 
Because of the predicted secondary structure of this 
sequence, various publicly available bio-informatics tools 
suggest targeting of MITS1 to mitochondria (see Materials 
and methods). To confirm this prediction experimentally, 
full-length MITS1 was fused to the N-terminus of the 
yellow fluorescent protein (YFP; Fig. 1A), and the resulting 
construct was expressed in tobacco leaf epidermal cells for 
live cell confocal microscopy analyses. For simplicity, this 
construct was named MITS1. MITS1 appeared in </p>



<p>numerous structures of heterogeneous size and shape (Fig. 
1B), resembling the previously described appearance of 
plant mitochondria (Logan and Leaver, 2000). Co-localiza-
tion analyses of MITS1 with b-ATPase:GFP, a known 
mitochondrial marker (Logan and Leaver, 2000), confirmed 
that MITS1 localizes to mitochondria (Fig. 1B), thus 
providing experimental support for our prediction. These 
observations prompted us to carry out a functional dissec-
tion of the NH 2 -terminal extension of MITS1 to identify the 
targeting determinants within this region. </p>

<p>The N-terminal extension of MITS1 contains three 
regions that co-ordinate the mitochondrial targeting 
signal </p>

<p>To explore the role of the N-terminal extension of MITS1, 
several defined segments of the pre-sequence were fused to 
YFP for confocal microscopy analyses (see Fig. 2A for a 
schematic representation). It was found that the YFP fusion 
to the predicted pre-sequence of MITS1 (MITS1 </p>

<p>1-39 </p>

<p>) was 
localized to mitochondria, as confirmed by co-expression 
analyses with b-ATPase:GFP (Fig. 2B). A Helical Wheel 
Projection analysis of residues 1-39 (see Materials and 
methods) confirmed the presence of clusters of positive 
charges on one side of the helix (Fig. 2C), consistent with 
the known properties of pre-sequences in forming cationic 
amphipathic helices (Duby et al., 2001). The necessity of this 
pre-sequence for MITS1 mitochondrial targeting was further 
reinforced by the evidence that a YFP fusion to MITS1 
amino acids 40-573 lacking the entire pre-sequence was 
cytosolic (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>Having established that the pre-sequence of MITS1 is 
sufficient to redistribute a fluorescent protein to mitochon-
dria, the next aim was to establish the functional role of 
different domains within this pre-sequence. When a YFP 
fusion to the first 11 amino acids preceding the central 
hydrophobic region of the pre-sequence, MITS1 
1-11 (Fig. 
2A) was expressed, it was found that the protein was 
distributed in the cytosol rather than to mitochondria (Fig. 
2B). This suggests that this region is insufficient to target 
YFP to organelles efficiently. 
A fusion of the first 31 amino acids of the MITS1 to YFP, 
which lacked the positively charged region at the C-terminus 
of the pre-sequence, MITS1 
1-31 (Fig. 2A), was also found in 
the cytosol (Fig. 2B). This is consistent with the required 
presence of the positively charged region in functional 
mitochondrial pre-sequences (Duby et al., 2001). Interest-
ingly, however, the MITS1 
12-39 peptide fusion (Fig. 2A), 
which was made by adding a methionine residue upfront to 
allow translation, and contained the hydrophobic core region 
and the positively-charged flanking region, was localized to 
the ER as well as the mitochondria (Figs 2B, 4). This 
suggests that the 12-39 amino acid region of MITS1 can 
function as a promiscuous targeting signal for microsomal 
and mitochondrial membranes. 
Taken together, these data indicate that the first 39 amino 
acids of MITS1 constitute a pre-sequence for efficient mito-
chondrial targeting. They also suggest that the first 11 
amino acids of the pre-sequence alone appear to be nec-
essary for directing the protein to mitochondria rather than 
to the ER, despite being insufficient for targeting a YFP 
fusion to mitochondria. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. MITS1 harbours an N-terminal targeting signal and is localized to mitochondria. (A) Schematic representation of MITS1 and of its 
N-terminal region. Positively-charged residues follow a 20 residue hydrophobic region, characteristic of a mitochondrial targeting 
sequence. (B) In epidermal cells of tobacco leaves, MITS1:YFP labels punctate structures of various sizes that colocalize with the 
mitochondrial marker b-ATPase:GFP (arrows). Insets: magnified section of main panels. Scale bars¼5 lm. </p>

<p>Co-operation of mitochondrial targeting determinants in plants | 743 </p>

<p>The data presented above mirrored the Helical Wheel 
Projection analyses of each peptide that showed that pep-
tide 12-39 has the most cationic charges on the side of the 
helix after peptide 1-39, followed by peptides 1-31 and 1-11 
(Fig. 2C). Consistent with these Helical Wheel projections, 
peptides 1-39 and 12-39 were capable of targeting YFP to 
the mitochondria, although a subcellular pool of the 12-39 
YFP fusion was also directed to the ER. On the other hand, 
the remaining peptides (1-11 and 1-31) were not sufficient 
for directing YFP to any organelle, most likely due to the 
absence of a defined cationic side on the helical structure. </p>

<p>Mutation of tryptophan 361 redistributes MITS1 to the 
ER and Golgi apparatus </p>

<p>Having demonstrated that the N-terminal extension of 
MITS1 functions alone as an efficient targeting signal to 
mitochondria, the next aim was to determine whether 
other domains of the full-length protein could influence the 
activity of this pre-sequence. Within the MITS1 sequence 
two tryptophan residues (W361 and W416) were found. 
Tryptophan is a rare amino acid that is known to be 
involved in the targeting and stability of some proteins 
(Garcia et al., 1992; Kleinberger-Doron and Kanner, 1994; </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Exploration of the N-terminal 39 residues of MITS1 reveals that a co-ordination of three regions is required for efficient 
mitochondria targeting. (A) Schematic representation of the N-terminal consecutive domains fused to YFP and their subsequent 
intracellular localizations. (B) Region 1-39 efficiently targets a YFP to mitochondria (arrow) and the YFP punctate structures fully co-
localize with b-ATPase:GFP (arrows). 1-11:YFP (missing the central hydrophobic core and the positively-charged region) and 1-31:YFP 
(missing the positively-charged region) were localized to the cytosol (empty arrowheads). (C) The Helical Wheel Projection of MITS1 N-
terminal pre-sequence shows a cationic cluster in 1-39 and 12-39 sequences (but not in the other pre-sequence truncations) consistent 
with their localization to mitochondria (blue dots are hydrophobic residues, + indicates positive charge). Insets: magnified section of main 
panels. Scale bars¼5 lm. </p>



<p>Hoffman et al., 2006). Therefore it was decided to test 
whether mutation of either of these residues in the full-
length MITS1 would affect the mitochondrial targeting of 
MITS1. Each of the two tryptophan residues was changed 
to alanine (W361A and W416A, see Fig. 5A for a sche-
matic representation) and the constructs were expressed as 
YFP-fusions in plants. Confocal microscopy analyses 
revealed that the mutant MITS1 
W361A (Fig. 5B) was 
localized at the ER and the Golgi apparatus, as demon-
strated by co-expression of the mutant with the known ER 
and Golgi marker, ERD2:GFP (Boevink et al., 1998); Fig. 
5B). Colocalization analyses with b-ATPase:GFP further 
excluded the possibility that the punctate structures 
labelled by MITS1 
W361A were mitochondria (Fig. 5B). On 
the other hand, a MITS1 bearing mutation of the 
tryptophan residue at position 416 (MITS1 
W416A ) was 
localized at mitochondria labelled with b-ATPase:GFP 
(Fig. 5B) in the same manner as wild-type MITS1 (Fig. 
1B). These data suggest that the integrity of specific amino 
acids that are distal from the N-terminal domain of a 
mitochondrial protein affect the function of a pre-sequence 
in a dominant fashion. 
Finally, since it was shown that the pre-sequence lacking 
the first 11 amino acids (peptide 12-39) is capable of </p>

<p>directing a YFP fusion to the ER and mitochondria (Fig. 
2B), we wanted to explore the possibility of whether the 
W361A mutation, which affects the activity of the pre-
sequence (Fig. 5), would also interfere with the targeting 
properties of peptide 12-39. To investigate this, a YFP fu-
sion was constructed of the MITS1 
W361A mutant lacking the 
first 11 residues of full-length MITS1 (MITS1 
12-W361A-573 ; 
Fig. 6A). Differently from the ER/mitochondria targeting 
of MITS1 
12-573 (Fig. 6B; see Supplementary Fig. S1 at JXB 
online), the resulting chimera was found in the cytosol (Fig. 
6B). As incorporation of the alanine residue in position 361 
must occur after the synthesis of the N-terminal 12-39 
sequence which is responsible for ER and mitochondria 
targeting, these data further strengthen our hypothesis that 
distal protein residues may influence targeting properties of 
an N-terminal sequence. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The pre-sequence amphipathicity influences the 
targeting of MITS1 </p>

<p>At present, the biological function of MITS1 remains un-
known, but publicly available databases (NCBI and TAIR) </p>

<p>Fig. 4. MITS1 
12-39 does not localize at Golgi bodies. To exclude the possibility that the punctate structures labelled by MITS1 </p>

<p>12-39 </p>

<p>peptide fusion were Golgi bodies, cells were cotransformed with the ER/Golgi marker, ERD2:GFP (Boevink et al., 1998) and MITS1 </p>

<p>12-39 </p>

<p>. 
As shown in this figure, MITS1 
12-39 labelled the ER (empty arrow), and dots (full arrow), which did not colocalize with the Golgi </p>

<p>(arrowhead). These dots corresponded to mitochondria as shown in Fig. 2. Insets: magnified section of main panels. Scale bars¼5 lm. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Residues 1-39 of the N-terminal extension are required for MITS1 to reach mitochondria. (A) A schematic representation of 
MITS1 lacking the first 39 amino acids. (B) In the absence of the N-terminal pre-sequence, MITS1 was found in the cytosol (empty 
arrowhead), which in plant cells assumes a diffuse yet reticulated appearance. No co-localization was noticed with the mitochondrial 
marker, b-ATPase:GFP (arrow). Insets: magnified section of main panels. Scale bars¼5 lm. </p>

<p>Co-operation of mitochondrial targeting determinants in plants | 745 </p>

<p>indicate MITS1 as a putative actin-binding protein, with an 
'actinin-type actin-binding domain signature 1' that is 
similar to a region involved in the actin-binding activity of 
the chloroplastic actin-binding protein, CHUP1 (Oikawa 
et al., 2003). In addition, several different types of protein 
domain prediction software revealed that MITS1 contains 
an AAA-ATPase motif (55-360; SMART, Schultz et al., 
1998; Letunic et al., 2006), and two leucine zipper patterns 
(279-300 and 324-345; <rs type="software">ScanProsite</rs>, (Hulo et al., 2008). In 
contrast with CHUP1, MITS1 is localized to mitochondria. 
Helical Wheel analysis strongly suggests that the pre-
sequence of MITS1 attains a secondary structure with 
a clustered cationic side that is a known property of 
mitochondria targeting sequences (Duby et al., 2001). The 
N-terminal part of the mitochondrial pre-sequence is be-
lieved to fold into an amphiphilic a-helix both in a phospho-
lipid environment and in vivo (Roise et al., 1988; Lemire 
et al., 1989). Consistent with these observations, the MITS1 
mutants with a less defined polar cluster on the side of the </p>

<p>helical wheel, compared with the 1-39 peptide, showed a 
reduced ability to target YFP to mitochondria. Although 
stability of the a-helix is important for maintenance of 
mitochondrial import (Hammen et al., 1996; Heard and 
Weiner, 1998), in vivo mutagenesis analysis of a plant pre-
sequence from the b-subunit of the F 1 -ATPsynthase from 
Nicotiana plumbaginifolia showed that the N-terminal 
helical structure of the pre-sequence is necessary but not 
sufficient for efficient mitochondrial import, and that its 
hydrophobic residues play an essential role in in vivo 
mitochondrial targeting (Duby et al., 2001). These findings 
may explain how peptide 12-39, which maintained a similar 
cluster of cationic amino acids on the side of the helix in 
comparison to the full-length pre-sequence, showed target-
ing to the mitochondria and also to other organelles. It is 
possible that the distribution of the hydrophobic residues of 
peptide 12-39 may be altered, resulting in a less efficient 
targeting signal in comparison to the full-length pre-
sequence. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Tryptophan 361 influences the activity of the MITS1 N-terminal pre-sequence. (A) Schematics of the mutations within MITS1 
fusions to YFP. (B) Confocal images of tobacco leaf epidermal cells coexpressing a MITS1:YFP mutant and either ERD2:GFP or b-
ATPase:GFP. MITS1 </p>

<p>W361A </p>

<p>:YFP was found in the ER (empty arrow) and Golgi apparatus (arrowhead) as confirmed by the ER/Golgi 
apparatus marker ERD2:GFP (ER, empty arrow; Golgi apparatus, arrowhead). The mutation of tryptophan 416 to alanine did not affect 
the distribution of MITS1 to mitochondria (arrow). Insets: magnified section of main panels. Scale bars¼5 lm. </p>



<p>The MITS1 pre-sequence contains promiscuous 
targeting signals </p>

<p>The evidence that peptide 12-39 is distributed to the ER in 
addition to mitochondria, suggests that the first 11 amino 
acids of the N-terminal extension are necessary to overcome 
protein mistargeting to the ER. Whether the putative signal 
sequence masked by the first 11 amino acids is functional 
for MITS1 in planta is unknown, but the presence of 
multiple targeting signals in the same protein sequence has 
been reported for certain post-translationally targeted pro-
teins containing either a nuclear localization signal 
(AtLIG1; Sunderland et al., 2006) or peroxisomal signal 
(FPS protein; Martin et al., 2007). In these cases, the 
function of the mitochondrial pre-sequence resulted in a 
dominant effect over the other sequences. It has also been 
demonstrated that chimeric signals may be functional in 
directing proteins to different organelles in the same cell. 
This is the case for chloroplast and plant mitochondrial 
proteins (Brink et al., 1994; Pujol et al., 2007), which, to 
some extent, have similar targeting sequences. Interestingly, 
it has been demonstrated that some chimeric signal se-
quences may retain the ability for ER and mitochondria 
targeting. For example, for the biogenesis of the hepatic 
P4501A1 isoenzyme a microsomal signal sequence may be 
cleaved to activate a mitochondrial targeting signal (Addya 
et al., 1997). In this experimental system, we did not observe 
ER localization of either a pre-sequence-YFP fusion or full-
length MITS1-YFP fusion but it will be interesting to </p>

<p>determine whether the activation of the microsomal signal 
sequence in MITS1 may occur in planta (i.e. the activation 
may be development or stress-regulated), as this may 
represent a novel protein targeting mechanism. </p>

<p>Targeting activity of the MITS1 pre-sequence is 
influenced by a distal amino acid residue </p>

<p>Our results indicate that the integrity of an amino acid 
residue placed distally from the N-terminal extension is a 
factor that influences the activity of the mitochondrial pre-
sequence. This phenomenon was specific to tryptophan in 
position 361 as the tryptophan in position 416 did not 
appear to affect MITS1 targeting to mitochondria. These 
data support the suggestion that, in plant cells, the nature of 
the mature protein can also affect the targeting properties of 
the pre-sequence (Lee and Whelan, 2004). As mitochondrial 
targeting is a process that occurs post-translationally and 
involves interaction of the newly synthesized proteins with 
cytosolic chaperones (Young et al., 2003; Yano et al., 2004), 
it is possible that the integrity of distal domains of pre-
proteins is important for a productive surface interaction 
with these chaperones for efficient targeting. 
A similar explanation, however, is not sufficient to 
explain the cytosolic distribution of the MITS1 mutant that 
lacks the first 11 amino acids of the N-terminal extension 
and bears a mutation of the tryptophan in position 361 
(MITS1 
12-W361A-573 ). This is because peptide 12-39 and 
MITS1 
12-573 were found to be sufficient to target YFP to </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Tryptophan 361 mutation influences the behaviour of a truncated MITS1. (A) Schematic representation of the MITS1 </p>

<p>12-573 </p>

<p>constructs. (B) Confocal images of tobacco leaf epidermal cells show distribution of MITS1 </p>

<p>12-W361A-573 </p>

<p>:YFP in the cytosol (empty 
arrowhead) but no colocalization with b-ATPase:GFP. MITS1 
12-573 was found in the ER (empty arrows) and dots. Most of these </p>

<p>colocalized with mitochondria (full arrows) but not with the Golgi (see Supplementary Fig. S1 at JXB online). Insets: magnified section of 
main panels. Scale bars¼5 lm. </p>

<p>Co-operation of mitochondrial targeting determinants in plants | 747 </p>

<p>the ER. As the synthesis of the distal portion of MITS1 
containing tryptophan 361 should occur after import of the 
N-terminal region into the ER during co-translational 
translocation, the tryptophan 361 mutation should not 
interfere with the distribution of the mutant to the ER. 
One possibility is that the 12-39 peptide associates with the 
cytosolic face of the ER, rather than facilitating trans-
location through the ER membrane. 
In conclusion, a novel aspect of mitochondrial protein 
targeting in plants has been demonstrated that encompasses 
functional co-ordination of the pre-sequence and the in-
tegrity of a distal amino acid residue. Further studies in an 
endogenous context are required to gain an understanding of 
whether the signal sequence that appears in the N-terminal 
extension of MITS1 depends on mechanisms that are known 
to affect targeting of a protein to different organelles [i.e. 
alternative splicing and/or differential initiation of trans-
lation (Ma and Taylor, 2008; Christensen et al., 2005)]. </p>

<p>Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplemental material can be found at JXB online. 
Supplementary Fig. S1. MITS1 
12-573 does not localize to 
Golgi bodies. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work was supported by grants awarded to FB from the 
Department of Energy at Michigan State University, the 
Canada Foundation for Innovation (CFI), the Canada 
Research Chair fund, and the Natural Science and Engi-
neering Research Council of Canada (NSERC). LAM was 
supported by an NSERC post-doctoral fellowship. ASJ was 
supported by an NSERC undergraduate summer research 
award. We thank Dr DC Logan (University of St Andrews, 
UK) for providing b-ATPase:GFP DNA. </p>



<p>Co-operation of mitochondrial targeting determinants in plants | 749 </p>

</text></tei>