<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2826650" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:39+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Glutathione (GSH) and ascorbate (ASC) are important antioxidants that are involved in stress defence and cell 
proliferation of meristematic root cells. In principle, synthesis of ASC and GSH in the roots as well as ASC and GSH 
transport from the shoot to the roots by phloem mass flow is possible. However, it is not yet known whether the ASC 
and/or the GSH level in roots depends on the supply from the shoot. This was analysed by feeding mature leaves 
with [ 
14 C]ASC or [ </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>S]GSH and subsequent detection of the radiolabel in different root fractions. Quantitative 
dependency of root ASC and GSH on shoot-derived ASC and GSH was investigated with poplar (Populus 
tremula3P. alba) trees interrupted in phloem transport. [ </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>S]GSH is transported from mature leaves to the root tips, 
but is withdrawn from the phloem along the entire transport path. When phloem transport was interrupted, the GSH 
content in root tips halved within 3 d. [ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]ASC is also transported from mature leaves to the root tips but, in 
contrast to GSH, ASC is not removed from the phloem along the transport path. Accordingly, ASC accumulates in 
root tips. Interruption of phloem transport disturbed the level and the ASC redox state within the entire root system. 
Diminished total ASC levels were attributed mainly to a decline of dehydroascorbate (DHA). As the redox state of 
ASC is of particular significance for root growth and development, it is concluded that phloem transport of ASC may 
constitute a shoot to root signal to coordinate growth and development at the whole plant level. </p>

<p>Ascorbate (ASC) and glutathione (GSH) are important 
antioxidants that exhibit numerous functions in stress 
defence, regulation of plant metabolism, as well as growth 
and development (May et al., 1998; Meyer and Hell, 2005; 
Mullineaux and Rausch, 2005; Halliwell, 2006; Noctor, 
2006; Meyer, 2008; Foyer and Noctor, 2009). Both 
ASC and GSH are involved in root development due to 
their function in redox regulation. However, this function 
is executed in an independent way because one 
cannot compensate for the absence of the other (Sánchez-
Fernández et al., 1997; Potters et al., 2002, 2004; Jiang and 
Feldman, 2005). Maintenance of the root quiescent centre 
(QC) is accompanied by low total ASC content and high 
ascorbate oxidase activity (Kerk and Feldman, 1995; Liso </p>

<p>et al., 2004); as a result the total ASC pool is dominated by 
dehydroascorbate (DHA) (Jiang et al., 2003). ASC is 
necessary for the transition from G 1 to S in the cell cycle 
(Liso et al., 1988). 
As a consequence, any changes in ASC content affect cell 
cycle activity. Hence, the G 1 state is extended when the ASC 
content of the cells in the QC is low, as reviewed in Potters 
et al. (2002). Application of ASC induced cell division in 
Allium cepa roots (Liso et al., 1988). In the tobacco cultivar 
Bright Yellow 2 (BY-2), ASC stimulated cell division while 
DHA decreased the mitotic index (de Pinto et al., 1999) and 
slowed down cell cycle progression (Potters et al., 2004). 
The latter, however, was only observed when DHA was 
added in the G 1 phase (Potters et al., 2004). ASC treatment </p>

<p>ª 2009 The Author(s). </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-
nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>of Arabidopsis roots resulted in a complete loss of a QC 
marker. Lee et al. (2007) concluded that ASC treatment 
might change the maintenance of cell type identities in 
roots, and affected cell type-specific gene expression. When 
auxin transport was inhibited by a specific inhibitor, DHA 
in the QC declined to approximately one-third compared to 
the controls, whereas ASC increased; these reactions were 
accompanied by an activation of the distal region in the QC 
(Jiang et al., 2003). These examples clearly demonstrate the 
importance of the ASC to DHA ratio and its adjustment for 
root growth and development. 
GSH, though less intensively studied, is also important 
for root growth and development (Potters et al., 2002). 
GSH enhanced the number of meristematic cells undergoing 
mitosis, while depletion of GSH had the opposite effect 
(Sánchez-Fernández et al., 1997). Inhibition of GSH 
synthesis by the specific inhibitor buthionine sulphoximine 
(BSO) resulted in reduced root formation (Cobbett et al., 
1998). In accordance with this, a mutant from Arabidopsis 
(rml1) deficient in c-glutamylcysteine synthetase (c-ECS) is 
unable to establish roots (Vernoux et al., 2000). c-ECS 
catalyses the first step of glutathione synthesis. Thus this 
mutant revealed a markedly diminished GSH content. 
Root hair development depends on formation of reactive 
oxygen species (ROS) by NADPH oxidase (Foreman et al., 
2003). As ASC and GSH are involved in ROS detoxification 
(Noctor and Foyer 1998), the amounts of ASC and/or GSH 
as well as the maintenance of its redox state seem to be 
important for root hair growth. Indeed, in Arabidopsis 
roots, the GSH level is linked to root hair tip growth, and 
redox-dependent modulation is thought to be a crucial 
element in adjusting growth and development to the 
environment conditions (Sánchez-Fernández et al., 1997). 
In addition to the influences of ASC on cell division within 
the QC, it may also be involved in lateral root development, 
since a very low ASC content Arabidopsis mutant (vtc2) 
exhibited altered root growth with the number and length of 
lateral roots being increased (Olmos et al., 2006). As ASC 
removes ROS (Foyer and Halliwell, 1976; Noctor and 
Foyer, 1998), the low ASC in roots of the vtc2 mutant can 
improve lateral root development (Foreman et al., 2003; 
Olmos et al., 2006) probably by retaining ROS. Therefore, 
low ASC contents mediated by ROS scavenging under 
stress conditions may improve growth, as discussed by 
Olmos et al. (2006). From these observations it can be 
hypothesized that ASC and/or GSH transported from the 
shoot to the roots may affect the levels of these antioxidants 
in the roots and thereby function as a shoot to root signal 
for growth and development. A prerequisite for such 
a function is that the ASC and GSH level in the root tip 
depends on its long-distance transport from the shoot. 
The highest level of ASC synthesis takes place in the 
leaves, but ASC synthesis seems to be apparent in all plant 
cells (see Hancock et al., 2003). Feeding of L-galactono-
1,4-lactone, the precursor of ascorbate (Smirnoff et al., 
2001), results in increased ASC contents mainly in mature 
leaves of Medicago sativa (Franceschi and Tarlyn, 2002) but 
also in Cucurbita maxima roots (Liso et al., 2004). ASC is </p>

<p>a widespread constituent of phloem sap, and isolated 
phloem strands are competent for ASC biosynthesis 
(Hancock et al., 2003). Transport of ASC from leaves to 
sink tissues such as root tips and floral tissues has been 
demonstrated for three herbaceous plant species (Franceschi 
and Tarlyn, 2002). Since sulphate assimilation is a light-
dependent process (Brunold, 1990) and because cysteine 
formation limits GSH synthesis (Strohm et al., 1995) it is 
assumed that GSH is mainly synthesized in the leaves. This 
is supported by the finding that GSH synthesis can be 
stimulated with increasing light intensity (Ogawa et al., 
2004). However, glutathione production has also been 
found in other plant organs including the roots (Vauclare 
et al., 2002). Like ASC, GSH is a regular constituent of 
phloem sap (Rennenberg et al., 1979; Bonas et al., 1982; 
Lappartient and Touraine, 1996; Bourgis et al., 1999; 
Hartmann et al., 2000; Kuzuhara et al., 2000; Schulte et al., 
2002) and is transported from mature leaves to the roots 
(Rennenberg et al., 1979; Bonas et al., 1982; Hartmann 
et al., 2000). However, it has not been established whether 
ASC and/or GSH levels in the roots and, hence, root 
growth and development depend on in situ synthesis of 
these antioxidants or its long-distance transport from the 
shoot in the phloem. The aim of the present study was to 
address these questions by two different approaches. Radio-
labelled ASC or GSH was fed to a mature poplar leaf and 
the distribution of radioactivity in different root fractions 
was determined. In girdling experiments, where phloem 
transport to the root was interrupted at the transition 
between stem and root, the dependency of the ASC and 
GSH levels in different root fractions on shoot-derived ASC 
and GSH was determined. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Plant material and growth conditions 
Seedlings of the poplar hybrid Populus tremula3P. alba clone 717 
1B4 (Institute National de la Recherche Agronomique, INRA) 
were micropropagated as described by Strohm et al. (1995) and 
Noctor et al. (1996). After 4 weeks, cuttings were transferred onto 
quartz sand (0.7-2 mm, Gö tz and Moritz, Freiburg, Germany) 
and were grown in a greenhouse (2665°C) under long day (16 h 
light) conditions and a light intensity that varied from 60 lmol m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>s 
À1 to 600 lmol m 
2 s 
À1 depending on the weather conditions. At 
full sunlight the greenhouse was shaded automatically. Seedlings 
were watered with 1/4 modified Hoagland solution combined with 
Long-Ashton medium (Strohm et al., 1995) consisting of 1.25 mM 
KNO 3 , 2.5 mM Ca(NO 3 ) 2 , 0.5 mM MgSO 4 , 4.5 mM MgCl 2 , 
0.25 mM KH 2 PO 4 , 2.3 lM MnCl 2 , 10 lM H 3 BO 3 , 0.08 lM 
CuCl 2 , 0.2 lM ZnCl 2 , 0.2 lM Na 2 MoO 4 , 0.04 lM CoCl 2 , 
22.5 lM FeCl 2 , and 22.5 lM Na 2 EDTA. Plants were harvested 
after 8 weeks of growth. Since the bark of deciduous trees includes 
the phloem, interruption of phloem transport can be achieved by 
peeling off the bark (Mason and Maskell, 1928). In girdling 
experiments, 2 cm of the bark was peeled off at the stem-root 
transition around the entire plant. </p>

<p>Feeding of [ 
35 S]GSH and L-[ 
14 C]ASC to the leaves </p>

<p>[ </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>S]GSH was fed to leaves using the flap feeding technique of 
Biddulph (1956). A flap was cut into a mature leaf so that the </p>



<p>connection to the main vein was maintained in the direction of the 
petiole. For this purpose, the first two cuts of ; 1 mm were made 
lateral to the main leaf vein. The third cut was made to release the 
leaf vein from the leaf lamina. The flap that contained part of the 
main vein remained connected in the direction of the petiole. In 
this way GSH and ASC were fed directly into the phloem, and 
phloem transport out off the fed leaf was facilitated. During 
cutting of the flap, the leaf was submerged in potassium phosphate 
buffer (50 lM K 2 HPO 4 /KH 2 PO 4 buffer, pH 6.2). After cutting, 
the flap was dipped immediately into a test tube containing the 
feeding solution, i.e. 15.6 ll of [ 
35 S]GSH {30 lCi [ 
35 S]GSH 
(Hartmann Analytic GmbH, Braunschweig, Germany) prepared 
from an aqueous solution containing 1075 Ci mmol 
À1 GSH and 
10 mM dithiothreitol (DTT)} or 15 ll of [ 
14 C]ascorbic acid 
{30 lCi of L-[1-
14 C]ASC (American Radiolabeled Chemicals, Inc., 
St. Louis, MO, USA) prepared from solid ASC with 8.5 mCi 
mmol 
À1 in 50 lM K 2 HPO 4 /KH 2 PO 4 buffer pH 6.2}. The feeding 
solutions were taken up completely within 3065 min. 
After a total incubation time of 2, 3, or 5 h in the case of 
[ 
35 S]GSH feeding, or after 5 h in the case of [ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]ASC feeding at 
room temperature (2563°C) and 600630 lE m 
À2 s 
À1 PAR 
(Osram, HPS L 65W/150 ultra white and Osram, L Fluora 35W/ 
77R, Osram, Munich, Germany) at plant height, incubation was 
terminated by cutting off the fed leaf. Subsequently, poplar trees 
were dissected into the apex, and the first, second, third, seventh, 
and 11th leaves counted from the apex. The trunk section basal to 
the fed leaf was divided into sections of 2 cm in length that were 
separated into bark and wood. The root system was separated into 
six root fractions of different developmental stages (Fig. 1). 
Fraction 6 (R6) was the main root that appears green. Smaller 
roots that showed secondary growth and appeared red were 
combined in fraction 5 (R5). Roots with secondary growth that 
appeared white constituted fraction 4 (R4). Fraction 3 (R3) 
contained roots with a diameter of ; 0.5-1 mm and small side 
roots. Long white roots without side roots that were ; 1 mm in </p>

<p>diameter were combined in fraction 2 (R2). Root tips were 
sampled whenever possible and were combined in fraction 1 (R1). 
All samples were immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored 
at -24°C until analysis. </p>

<p>35 S and 
14 C analyses 
35 S and 
14 C radioactivity was determined in 20-100 mg of 
powdered (under liquid nitrogen) plant tissue as described by 
Herschbach and Rennenberg (1996). After solubilization with 
a tissue solubilizer (1 ml of Soluene 350, Packard Instruments, 
Frankfurt, Germany), samples were bleached with 200 ll of H 2 O 2 
(30%) overnight. After adding 5 ml of scintillation fluid (HiSafe 3, 
Packard Instruments, Frankfurt, Germany), radioactivity was 
determined using a liquid scintillation counter (Wallac System 
1409, Wallac, Turku, Finland). Data were corrected for quenching. </p>

<p>Analyses of thiols and 
35 S-labelled metabolites </p>

<p>Thiols, i.e. cysteine, c-EC, and GSH, were extracted, derivatized, 
and quantified as described by Strohm et al. (1995) and Hersch-
bach et al. (2000). A 30 mg aliquot of leaf material powdered 
under liquid nitrogen or 100 mg of root and bark powder was 
homogenized in 750 ll of 0.1 M HCl containing 50 mg of 
insoluble polyvinylpolypyrrolidone (PVPP). Samples were centri-
fuged (14 000 g, 15 min) and 120 ll of the clear supernatant was 
added to 180 ll of 200 mM CHES buffer (pH 9.3). Reduction of 
reduced disulphides was performed with 30 ll of 15 mM DTT for 
1 h at room temperature. Thiols were derivatized with 20 ll of 
30 mM monobromobimane and stabilized by adding 240 ll 
of 10% (v/v) acetic acid after 15 min of derivatization. Aliquots of 
150 ll were taken to separate bimane conjugates by HPLC 
analysis (SUPERCOSILTM LC-18, 25 cm34.6 mm, 5 lm, 
Sigma-Aldrich) as described by Schupp and Rennenberg (1988) 
using 10% (v/v) methanol, 0.25% (v/v) acetic acid (pH 3.9) as 
solvent A and 90% (v/v) methanol, 0.25% (v/v) acetic acid (pH 3.9) 
as solvent B. Bimane derivatives were detected by fluorescence 
detection at 480 nm after excitation at 380 nm (Schupp and 
Rennenberg, 1988) and quantified by the use of external standards. 
During this analysis [ 
35 S]sulphate eluted prior to cysteine. To 
determine the amount of 
35 S in thiols, 1 ml fractions of the 
HPLC eluate were collected. After addition of 4 ml of scintilla-
tion fluid (HiSafe 3, Packard Instruments, Frankfurt, Germany), 
radioactivity was determined by liquid scintillation counting and 
classified by comparison with the fluorescent detector output. </p>

<p>Analyses of 
14 C-labelled metabolites </p>

<p>For 
14 C-labelled metabolite analysis in plants fed [ 
14 C]ASC 
a combination of HPLC analysis and liquid scintillation counting 
was applied. For this purpose, ASC was determined as described 
by Polle et al. (1990). ASC and DHA were extracted from 100 mg 
of root or wood tissue or from 50 mg of leaf tissue in 500 ll of 
meta-phosphoric acid (5%, v/v) plus 50 mg of PVPP at 4°C. Total 
ASC was determined after enzymatic oxidation of ASC to DHA 
by ascorbate oxidase. Aliquots of 50 ll of tissue extracts were 
diluted with 100 ll of sodium acetate (200 mM, pH 6.2). After 
addition of 15 ll of ascorbate oxidase (1 mg ml 
À1 in 200 mM 
sodium acetate pH 6.2) the mixture was incubated for 15 min at 
37°C. Thereafter, 100 ll of 3.7 mM sodium acetate were added 
and the mixture was kept further for 30 min at room temperature. 
Thereafter, DHA was derivatized after addition of 50 ll of o-PDA 
(o-phenyldiamine, 1 mg ml 
À1 ethanol) during 30 min at room 
temperature in the dark. The final volume was adjusted to 655 ll. 
A 150 ll aliquot was taken to separate the DHA derivative by 
isocratic HPLC analysis with a solvent consisting of 80 mM 
K 2 HPO 4 and 20% (v/v) methanol (pH 7.8 adjusted with ortho-
phosphoric acid) on a reversed phase column (ODS 1534.6 mm, 
5 lm Ultrasphereä, Beckman Lincoln, Krefeld, Germany). 
Fluorescence of the DHA derivate was measured at 450 nm after </p>

<p>Fig. 1. The root system of an 8-week-old poplar plant grown in 
sand culture. The root system was dissected into six fractions of 
different developmental stages. Fraction 6 (R6) was the main root 
that appears green. Smaller roots that revealed secondary growth 
and appeared red were indicated as fraction 5 (R5). Roots with 
secondary growth which appeared white constituted fraction 
4 (R4). Fraction 3 (R3) contained the roots with a diameter of 
; 0.5-1 mm and developed small side roots. The long white 
roots without side roots that were ; 1 mm in diameter comprised 
fraction 2 (R2). The root tips were sampled whenever possible 
and were combined in fraction 1 (R1). The bar indicates 5 mm. </p>

<p>Redox states of glutathione and ascorbate depend on phloem transport | 1067 </p>

<p>excitation at 350 nm. DHA was quantified using external stand-
ards. Radioactivity within the eluate was determined with a liquid 
scintillation counter in 1 min fractions after adding 4 ml of 
scintillation fluid (HiSafe 3, Packard Instruments, Frankfurt, 
Germany). </p>

<p>ASC assay 
ASC in non-radioactive samples was determined photometrically 
using the method of Okamura (1980) as described by Haberer 
et al. (2007). ASC and DHA were extracted from 20-25 mg of 
plant tissue, which was frozen and powdered under liquid 
nitrogen, with 500 ll of meta-phosphoric acid (5%; w/v) at 4°C 
on ice. The mixture was stirred and centrifuged (14 000 g, 30 min, 
4°C). The supernatant (100 ll) was neutralized with triethanol-
amine (20 ll, 1.5 mM) and mixed with sodium phosphate buffer 
(100 ll, 150 mM, pH 7.4). The ASC in the assay was measured 
directly, while total ASC was measured after complete reduction 
by DTT (50 ll, 10 mM, 30 min). Excess DTT was removed with 
N-ethylmaleimide (50 ll of NEM, 0.5%). Samples for ASC 
analysis were treated in the same way as described by Haberer 
et al. (2007). ASC reduces ferric ions to ferrous ions which coupled 
with 2,2#-dipyridyl to form a complex with a characteristic 
absorption at 525 nm, allowing quantification (Okamura, 1980). 
DHA was then calculated by subtraction of readings for ASC from 
readings for total ASC. </p>

<p>Data analysis 
Significant differences in ASC, DHA, and GSH contents between 
treatments (n¼3) and between root sections (n¼3) of girdled trees 
were analysed with the statistics program <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">16.0 for windows</rs> 
(Chicago, IL, USA). Prior to the test of significance with the 
Turkey test, the normality and homogeneity of the data were 
tested. Normality of the data was tested with the Kolmogorov-
Smirnov test that includes correction of significance after Lilliefors 
and Shapiro-Wilk. Homogeneity of variance was tested with the 
Levene test. If homogeneity was not given, values were transferred 
using the natural logarithm. If homogeneity was still not given, the 
Games-Howell test was applied. Significant differences at P &lt;0.05 
are indicated. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Translocation of 
35 S after [ 
35 S]GSH feeding to a leaf </p>

<p>One leaf of poplar plants (one of the ninth to 14th leaf 
counted from the apex) was fed with [ 
35 S]GSH by flap 
feeding (Biddulph, 1956) and the subsequent 
35 S transport 
out of the fed leaf was terminated after 2, 3, and 5 h. Along 
the transport path, the highest labelling in bark and wood 
was detected just below the fed leaf, and labelling decreased 
with increasing distance from the fed leaf (data not shown). 
After 2 h of incubation, only low levels of 
35 S were detected 
in the root tips or any other root fraction (Fig. 2A). 
35 S 
reached the root tips 3 h after starting [ 
35 S]GSH feeding. A 
slight enrichment of 
35 S in the root tips compared to the 
roots of fraction 2 was observed after 5 h of incubation. As 
the root tips only amounted to 4.2-8.7% of total root mass 
(Fig. 2B), the distribution of 
35 S within the root system was 
calculated (Fig. 2C). From this calculation, it appears that 
within the root system, 
35 S is preferentially found in the 
roots of fraction R3 and in the main root (fraction R6). 
This distribution correlates well with the biomass of </p>

<p>different root fractions that was highest in roots of fraction 
R3 followed by the main root (R6) (Fig. 2B). 
Along the transport path from the fed leaf to the roots, 
the [ 
35 S]GSH to [ 
35 S]sulphate ratio decreased. This indicates 
that with increasing distance from the fed leaf, the amount 
of labelled GSH declined in comparison with the amount of 
labelled sulphate. Whereas the [ 
35 S]GSH to [ 
35 S]sulphate 
ratio in the fed leaf ranged from 1.0 to 1.5, it amounted 
to 0.2 in the bark, 0.4 in the wood, and ranged from 0.17 
to 0.33 in the roots. </p>

<p>GSH contents in roots after stem girdling </p>

<p>Poplar plants were girdled at the transition of the stem to 
the roots to disrupt glutathione transport in the phloem. 
Glutathione contents in roots of different fractions were 
analysed 6 h, 24 h, 3 d, and 5 d after girdling (Fig. 3). 
Roots from control poplar plants without a bark girdle 
were harvested twice; first at time zero and secondly after 
120 h, i.e. 5 d after starting the experiment. The GSH 
content without girdling was similar in roots of fraction 
R4, R5, and R6, but only half as high in roots of fraction 
R3 and R2 (Fig. 3). GSH contents in the root tip (R1) were 
; 30% higher compared to the main root (R6). Disruption 
of phloem transport did not affect the glutathione content 
of the roots of fraction R2, R3, R4, R5, or R6, but GSH in 
the root tips (fraction R1) declined with increasing time of 
disrupted phloem transport. After 3 d of disruption of 
phloem transport, the GSH content of the root tips was 
diminished to about half the level determined prior to 
girdling. Compared with control roots which were harvested 
on day 0 and day 5, the GSH content in root tips after 5 d 
of phloem transport interruption was diminished to 
40% and 60%, respectively. GSSG contents in roots were 
not affected by girdling in any root fraction either 6 h or 5 
d of girdling (data not shown). </p>

<p>Translocation of 
14 C after [ 
14 C]ASC feeding to a leaf </p>

<p>After 5 h incubation, the </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C from [ 
14 C]ASC fed to a mature 
leaf (16th or 18th counted from the apex) was detected 
mainly in the root tips (Fig. 4A). Preferential translocation 
of 
14 C label to the root tip was also obvious when the 
absolute distribution of 
14 C within the root system was 
calculated. Although the contribution of root tips to total 
root fresh weight was only 2.560.5% (Fig. 4B), the 
proportion of 
14 C within the root tip fraction amounted to 
56.5625.0% (Fig. 4C). This means that root tips are the 
preferential sink for the 
14 C transported from the fed leaf to 
the root system. 
14 C was also detected in the apex (46648 
dpm mg 
À1 fw) and in young developing leaves (76681 dpm 
mg 
À1 fw); however, at amounts comparable with those 
found in the main root fraction (R6) (53639 dpm mg 
À1 fw). 
In both the apex and the main root, the ASC determined by 
HPLC analysis correlated with the 
14 C in the corresponding 
fraction of the HPLC eluate (data not shown). Apparently, 
[ 
14 C]ASC is transported in both the acropetal and basipetal 
direction. These results indicate that [ 
14 C]ASC is </p>



<p>transported from the fed leaf to the roots by phloem 
transport, but, in contrast to [ 
35 S]GSH, ASC was not taken 
up from the phloem along the transport path and was 
preferentially transported to the root tips. </p>

<p>ASC contents in roots after stem girdling </p>

<p>ASC and DHA were analysed in the root system after 
disruption of phloem transport by girdling (Fig. 5). Total 
ASC levels in roots reached only 10-40% of the levels in 
leaves (; 6-8 lmol ASC g 
À1 leaf fw). The lowest amounts 
of total ASC were found in roots of fractions R2 and R3, 
while total ASC levels were higher in roots of fractions R6, 
R5, R4, and R1 (Fig. 5). Girdling resulted in a significant 
decline in total ASC in root tips (R1) and in roots from 
fraction R3 and R6. In these fractions, total ASC was 
diminished to ; 40% of that in controls after 5 d of 
girdling. The contribution of oxidized to total ASC was 30-
60% prior to girdling and 6 h after phloem disruption 
by girdling. This was also true for the root tips, where 40% 
and 50% of the ASC was found to be oxidized, respectively 
(Fig. 5). After 24 h of girdling the contribution of DHA to 
total ASC declined significantly. After 120 h of phloem 
disruption by girdling, the pool of DHA was significantly 
diminished in all root fractions. This was clearly an effect of 
girdling, as non-girdled control poplar plants did not show 
such an effect. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In poplar plants ASC is transported from mature leaves to 
the roots. As previously observed for herbaceous plants 
(Franceschi and Tarlyn, 2002) leaf fed [ 
14 C]ASC accumu-
lated in poplar root tips. In contrast to the two herbaceous 
species Medicago sativa and Arabidopsis where young 
leaves, flower buds, and siliques are strong sinks for the 
applied [ 
14 C]ASC, this was not observed with poplar. 
Although [ 
14 C]ASC labelling was found in the poplar apex 
(46648 dpm mg 
À1 fw) and in young developing leaves 
(76681 dpm mg 
À1 fw) 5 h after feeding, this labelling was 
negligible compared to the labelling of root tips (R1) 
(22196849 dpm mg 
À1 fw). Whether flowers or seeds of 
poplar are sinks for ASC from mature leaves could not be 
answered in the present study, because poplar trees switch 
from juvenile growth to reproductive growth after only 
7-10 years (Hsu et al., 2006). Thus, it cannot be excluded 
that during flowering and seed development phloem </p>

<p>Fig. 2. 
35 S in root fractions (A), relative root fresh weight of each </p>

<p>fraction (B), and relative 
35 S distribution between root fractions </p>

<p>(C). (A) 
35 S radioactivity in the six root fractions (see Fig. 1) 2, 3, </p>

<p>and 5 h after feeding [ 
35 S]GSH to a mature leaf. (B) Contribution of </p>

<p>the six different root fractions to total root fresh weight. Total root 
fresh weight of the individual poplar plants was set to 100% and </p>

<p>the percentage of each fraction was calculated. (C) The contribu-
tion of 
35 S detected in each of the six root fractions to total root 
35 S radioactivity per root system of poplar plants fed with [ 
35 S]GSH </p>

<p>to a mature leaf. Total 
35 S determined in the whole root system </p>

<p>was set to 100%. The contribution of each root fraction was 
calculated. Data given are mean values from three poplar plants 
investigated per time point. Different indices indicate significant 
differences between root fractions at P &lt;0.05. </p>

<p>Redox states of glutathione and ascorbate depend on phloem transport | 1069 </p>

<p>transport into apical sink tissues also takes place in poplar, 
as found for herbaceous plants. 
During ASC transport to the roots ASC was not 
withdrawn from the phloem and was thus not stored in 
bark or wood tissues, or in any other root fraction. This 
was indicated by a lack of [ 
14 C]ASC accumulation in these 
tissues (data not shown). Thus it can be concluded that root 
tips of poplar trees are a preferential sink of shoot-derived 
ASC. Contrasting results were found for GSH. Along the 
transport path, 
35 S from the 
35 S fed as GSH to a mature 
leaf decreased continuously up to the main root and 
accumulated in the bark and wood of the trunk (data not 
shown). Simultaneously, the proportion of radiolabelled 
sulphate compared to GSH increased. Previous experiments 
also showed that radiolabelled GSH in the phloem declined 
during its transport from source to sink, whereas sulphate 
remained more or less constant (Hartmann et al., 2000). 
Nevertheless, GSH is a regular sulphur constituent of 
phloem exudates from poplar (Herschbach et al., 1998) and 
thus it is transported from the shoot to the roots (present 
study). Thus, although GSH was transported up to fine 
roots, specific accumulation of [ 
35 S]GSH in root tips was 
not found 5 h after [ 
35 S]GSH was fed to a mature leaf. In 
conclusion, root tips of poplar trees are a preferential sink 
of shoot-derived ASC, but not for shoot-derived GSH or 
sulphate. 
Beside transport to the roots it must be considered that 
ASC could be synthesized in roots. When Cucurbita maxima 
roots were fed with the ASC precursor L-galactono-1, </p>

<p>Fig. 3. GSH contents in the six different root fractions of 8-week-
old poplar plants girdled for different periods of time at the 
transition between stem and root. c_120 indicates an additional 
control harvested at day 5 after starting the experiment. Data given 
are mean values 6SD from three plants at the time indicated. 
(a) Indices indicate significant differences between the six root 
fractions during one harvest time at P &lt;0.05; (A) indicates 
significant differences between sampling dates along one root 
fraction at P &lt;0.05. The absence of indices indicated that 
significant differences were not found. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Distribution of 
14 C within the root system 5 h after </p>

<p>[ 
14 C]ASC was fed to a mature leaf. Data given in A are mean </p>

<p>values of dpm mg 
À1 fresh weight from the three trees analysed. </p>

<p>Data given in B are mean values 6SD of the percentage of each 
root fraction from total root fresh weight. Data given in C represent 
the amount of 
14 C from each root fraction relative to total 
14 C </p>

<p>determined in the whole root system that was set to 100%. 
Different indices indicate significant differences between root 
fractions at P &lt;0.05. </p>



<p>4-lactone, the ASC level increased (Liso et al., 2004); and 
the enzyme catalysing the final step of ascorbate synthesis 
(L-galactono-1,4-lactone dehydrogenase) was detected both 
in leaves and in roots (Groten et al., 2005; Matamoros 
et al., 2006). ASC levels in roots are usually low compared 
to leaves (Franceschi and Tarlyn, 2002; Matamoros et al., 
2006) as also found in the present study (7.061.1 lmol ASC 
g 
À1 fw in leaves versus 2.360.3 lmol ASC g 
À1 fw in 
fine roots). The girdling experiments with poplar indicate 
that -despite ASC synthesis in roots (Liso et al., 2004; 
Groten et al., 2005; Matamoros et al., 2006) -even these 
low root ASC levels are largely maintained by phloem 
transport of ASC. Approximately half of the ASC was lost 
in root fractions R1, R3, R5, and R6 24 h after disruption 
of phloem transport. This decline is consistent with the ASC 
turnover rate of 2.5% h 
À1 previously reported in Arabidop-
sis leaves (Conklin et al., 1997). In germinating pea 
seedlings an even faster turnover of ASC of 13% h 
À1 has 
been reported (Pallanca and Smirnoff, 2000). Phloem trans-
port interruption simultaneously induced a decline in DHA 
content of poplar roots. Apparently, phloem transport of 
ASC plays a decisive role in ASC homeostasis in poplar 
roots. 
Kerk and Feldmann (1995) established a direct correla-
tion between the ASC redox state and cell proliferation 
rates. High DHA contents blocked the transition from G 1 
to S in the QC of Zea mays roots that correlated with low 
ASC contents in the QC and prevented cell proliferation, 
while higher ASC levels induced cell division in surrounding 
meristematic initials. In tobacco cell cultures (BY-2), peak 
values of ascorbate, but not GSH, coincided with a peak in 
the mitotic index (de Pinto et al., 1999). Similar to 
decreasing DHA during the G 1 phase that may shorten the 
cell cycle in tobacco cell cultures (Kato and Esada, 1999), 
the reduction of DHA in roots as found in the present study 
after girdling could trigger cell division and thus may 
change root growth and development. This was supported 
by an ASC-deficient mutant (vtc2) that revealed changes in 
the root system (Olmos et al., 2006). The most noticeable 
root phenotype is the aberrant gravitropic response of the 
primary root and lateral roots of the vtc2 mutant. Thus, 
phloem-transported ASC may be considered as a signal 
controlling root growth and development. Still, a phloem-
transported signal that controls root ASC synthesis cannot 
be excluded from the present experiments. However, ASC 
re-synthesis in the roots from ASC degradation products 
synthesized in the fed leaf is unlikely because specific 
labelling of 
14 C coincides with the HPLC ASC peak (data 
not shown). </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Total ascorbate (complete bar), ASC (grey parts), and DHA 
(striped pattern) in different root fractions of 8-week-old poplar 
plants girdled for different periods of time at the transition between 
stem and root. Total ascorbate and ASC were determined 
photometrically as described by Haberer et al. (2007). DHA 
contents were calculated as the difference between these two </p>

<p>parameters. c_120 indicates an additional control harvested at day 
5 after starting the experiment. Data given are means 6SD from 
three individual plants. (a) Indices indicate significant differences of 
total ASC within one root fraction between treatments at P &lt;0.05 
and (A) indicates significant differences of DHA of a given root 
fraction between treatments at P &lt;0.05. Absence of indices 
indicates that significant differences were not found. </p>

<p>Redox states of glutathione and ascorbate depend on phloem transport | 1071 </p>

<p>The low shoot-derived GSH supply to root tips may be 
the result of significant sulphate assimilation so that the 
roots are largely independed of reduced sulphur from the 
shoot. Tips of maize roots showed the highest levels of 
adenosine 5#-phosphosulphate reductase activity (Kopriva 
et al., 2001), the enzyme that catalyses the regulatory step 
for sulphate reduction (Kopriva and Koprivova, 2004; 
Martin et al., 2005). GSH synthesis from sulphate has been 
demonstrated in excised root of Arabidopsis (Vauclare et al., 
2002) and poplar roots (Scheerer et al., 2009). Therefore, 
it seems possible that roots are self-sufficient in sulphate 
reduction and thus in GSH synthesis. Another explanation 
for the lack of preferential translocation of shoot-derived 
GSH to the root tip may be GSH degradation in the fed 
leaf and GSH re-synthesis in the roots. As cysteine is not 
the main transport form of reduced sulphur in the phloem 
of poplar (Herschbach et al., 1998, 2000) and radiolabelling 
of the cysteine pool was not observed in phloem exudates 
from poplar (Hartmann et al., 2000), it seems improbable 
that cysteine is the transport form of reduced sulphur from 
mature leaves to roots. Hence GSH re-synthesis from shoot-
derived cysteine within the roots seems unlikely, but GSH 
synthesis from shoot-derived glutamate and/or glycine 
cannot be excluded. Nevertheless the GSH content in root 
tips declined after 3 d of phloem transport interruption, 
indicating that part of the GSH in root tips originates from 
the shoot. The observed decline suggests a contribution of 
long-distance transport to the compensation of GSH 
turnover in the root tips of ; 0.5% h 
À1 . Apparently, this 
low rate of delivery by phloem transport is required to 
maintain the GSH level in the root tips that do not seem 
from these experiments to be completely self-sufficient in 
GSH synthesis. As an alternative explanation, a shoot 
signal delivered by phloem transport may be necessary for 
full capacity of GSH biosynthesis in root tips. 
It seems from the present experiments that poplar root 
tips are dependent on GSH and ascorbate from the shoot. 
However, the rates are different (around 10% losses of 
GSH, but even 50% loss of total ASC after 24 h phloem 
interruption). As the ASC content in roots was one order of 
magnitude higher than that of GSH it may be speculated 
that the effect of ASC on redox-dependent root growth is 
more relevant. Maintenance of the cellular redox state does 
not only depend on the concentration of an antioxidant, but 
-among other factors -also on the rate constant of its 
conversion in disturbing reactions. As the rate constant for 
superoxide radical scavenging is higher for GSH than for 
ASC (Rennenberg and Polle, 1994), ASC may be a less 
potent chemical antioxidant than GSH at similar concen-
trations. This may be overcome by higher ASC concen-
trations, as frequently observed in plant tissues including 
roots (Rennenberg and Polle, 1994; Noctor, 2006; Rennen-
berg et al., 2007), thereby supporting the relevance of ASC 
for redox-dependent root growth under these conditions. 
This is supported by an Arabidopsis mutant (vtc) low in 
ASC. This mutant showed changes in hormone levels and 
primary root development, and also changed stress sensitiv-
ity. It can therefore be assumed that the ASC level is one </p>

<p>possible internal signal allowing plants to respond to 
environmental stimuli by adjusting growth and develop-
ment (Kotchoni et al., 2009). 
Since both GSH and ASC are subject to compartmenta-
tion, the subcellular distribution of GSH and ASC seems to 
be essential for its functions in plant growth and de-
velopment. This point is even more important when it is 
considered that both antioxidants affect root growth and 
development in different ways. Whereas ASC/DHA seems 
more effective in cell proliferation, GSH affects cell size 
determination in tobacco cell cultures (de Pinto et al., 1999) 
and root hair formation that could not be mimicked by 
ASC in Arabidopsis roots (Sánchez-Fernández et al., 1997). 
The latter corresponds to high GSH contents in the root 
epidermis and in rapidly dividing cells (Fricker et al., 2000). 
Nevertheless, GSH depletion blocks cell proliferation in 
BY-2 tobacco cell cultures (Vernoux et al., 2000). Potters 
et al. (2002) concluded that a sufficient GSH concentration 
is necessary for regular cell division. This view is supported 
by results from studies with Arabidopsis mutants. Whereas 
root development was not found in the rml1 mutant that 
exhibited only 3% of the GSH detected in control roots 
(Vernoux et al., 2000), cell division in roots, i.e. normal root 
development, was observed in the cad2-1 mutant which 
exhibits 30% of the GSH compared to the control (Howden 
et al., 1995). 
From these studies it can be concluded that not only the 
redox state but also the absolute amounts of GSH and ASC 
are important for the development of plants in a changing 
environment. The present study shows that shoot to root 
transport in the phloem is required to maintain the GSH 
and ASC levels in the roots. Thus, phloem transport of 
these antioxidants may constitute an important signal for 
the adjustment of root growth and development to chang-
ing environmental conditions. Further experiments under 
distinct environmental growth conditions that include trans-
genic plants modified in phloem transport of ASC or GSH 
and in root ASC or GSH biosynthesis are required to test 
these assumptions. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>Financial support by the University of Freiburg within the 
programme 'Support of evaluated research projects' is 
gratefully acknowledged. </p>







<p>Redox states of glutathione and ascorbate depend on phloem transport | 1073 </p>





</text></tei>