<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2911847" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:45+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs type="software">Significance Analysis of 
Microarray (SAM</rs><rs type="software">SAM</rs><rs type="software">SAM</rs><rs type="software">Muscle</rs><rs type="software">Jalview</rs>the consensus binding site for ArcA, which likely activates 
the ED operon in aerobic conditions (45). </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The unique combination of experimental data, computa-
tional predictions, curated genome annotations and visual-
ization tools in SKB provides a unique opportunity for 
researches to discover new biological regularities not only 
related to Shewanella species, but also to all bacterial or-
ganisms. The presented case study demonstrates only some 
of the available opportunities and capabilities. Although 
the biological role of IG transcription suggested in the 
study is only a hypothesis and will require further experi-
mental validation, the discovery of the potential role was 
significantly facilitated by the collected information and 
the tools provided in SKB. </p>

<p>We thank members of the Shewanella Federation for their 
contribution in developing the resource and in data 
submission. We are especially grateful to Jim Fredrickson, </p>

<p>Anna Obraztsova, Miriam Land, Timothy Gardner, 
Alexander Beliaev, Mary Lipton, Grigoriy Pinchuk, Lee 
Ann McCue and Dmitry Rodionov. We also want to thank 
anonymous reviewers of the manuscript for thoughtful 
suggestions and comments on the study. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>Shewanella Federation consortium; Genomic Science 
Program of the Office of Biological and Environmental 
Research; US Department of Energy (DOE). Funding 
for open access charge: Office of Biological and 
Environmental Research, U.S. Department of Energy (DOE). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest. None declared. </p>



<p>Figure 5. The alignment of a conserved regulatory locus in the Shewanella genomes in the intergenic region between hexR and 
zwf genes. The locus is located from À56 to À103 nc upstream of zwf and has three adjacent binding sites for ArcA, HexR and 
Crp, respectively. The Crp binding site (TAAAAATAGATGCATTTAACAAATTC) was extracted from ShewRegDB. It was predicted by 
TractorDB (24). The HexR binding site is identified by similarity to HexR binding site consensus in Pseudomonas species (60, 61). 
The HexR binding site in Shewanella perfectly matches the Pseudomonas aeruginosa binding site (TGTTGTttaattACtACA) with 
the same location (À71 nt 5 0 of the transcriptional start site of zwf (59). Binding of HexR to this binding site in P. aeruginosa 
was experimentally confirmed by gel shift assays. The HexR binding site in Shewanella has a perfect consensus 
TGTTGTTATATTACAACA across the species. The alignment also indicates that in Shewanella spp. the HexR binding site overlaps 
the Crp binding site. Thus, in some growth conditions, the ED pathway may be activated by Crp, but HexR binding to the site can 
prevent the pathway activation. In the Crp(À) mutant, hexR is downregulated and releases the ED operon for activation by other 
transcription factors, like ArcA, for example. One of the binding sites for the two-component response regulator ArcA is 
demonstrated with the consensus (5 0 -GTTAgctagAATGTTA-3 0 ). </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>Page 11 of 13 </p>

<p>Database, Vol. 2010, Article ID baq012, doi:10.1093/database/baq012 </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>



<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>Page 13 of 13 </p>

<p>Database, Vol. 2010, Article ID baq012, doi:10.1093/database/baq012 </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

</text></tei>