<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2553567" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>This study evaluated methylation patterns of long 
interspersed nuclear element-1 (LINE-1) sequences 
from 17 loci in several cell types, including squa-
mous cell cancer cell lines, normal oral epithelium 
(NOE), white blood cells and head and neck squa-
mous cell cancers (HNSCC). Although sequences of 
each LINE-1 are homologous, LINE-1 methylation 
levels at each locus are different. Moreover, some 
loci demonstrate the different methylation levels 
between normal tissue types. Interestingly, in 
some chromosomal regions, wider ranges of 
LINE-1 methylation levels were observed. In cancer-
ous cells, the methylation levels of most LINE-1 loci 
demonstrated a positive correlation with each other 
and with the genome-wide levels. Therefore, the 
loss of genome-wide methylation in cancerous 
cells occurs as a generalized process. However, 
different LINE-1 loci showed different incidences 
of HNSCC hypomethylation, which is a lower methy-
lation level than NOE. Additionally, we report a 
closer direct association between two LINE-1s in 
different EPHA3 introns. Finally, hypermethylation 
of some LINE-1s can be found sporadically in 
cancer. In conclusion, even though the global hypo-
methylation process that occurs in cancerous cells 
can generally deplete LINE-1 methylation levels, 
LINE-1 methylation can be influenced differentially 
depending on where the particular sequences are 
located in the genome. </p>

<p>Long interspersed nuclear element-1 (LINE-1 or L1) 
sequences are highly repeated and widely interspersed </p>

<p>human retrotransposon sequences (1). LINE-1s constitute 
about 17% of the human genome with up to 600 000 
copies present (2). Approximately 3000-4000 copies 
remain in a full-length form and some may be retrotrans-
positionally active (3). By measuring the quantity of 
LINE-1 methylation, we found that LINE-1 methylation 
levels are varied. Whereas cancerous cells revealed a lower 
percentage of methylation, their normal tissue counter-
parts, normal tissues from different organs, showed 
tissue-specific levels of methylated LINE-1s (4). The 
levels of LINE-1 methylation were significantly different 
among different tissue types. Moreover, while the range of 
LINE-1 methylation levels in some tissues was narrow, 
some other tissues, such as the esophagus or thyroid, con-
tained widely distributed LINE-1 methylation levels (4). 
The variation of methylation levels of LINE-1s in normal 
tissues and the hypomethylation observed in cancerous 
cells has been confirmed by several studies (5-18). These 
data indicate that the epigenetic event may be important 
for cellular functions, not only in cancer, but also in 
normal cells (4). Moreover, these findings led us to a ques-
tion of whether methylation patterns of each LINE-1 are 
distinct despite the sequences being homologous. 
In cancer, DNA methylation of the whole genome is 
generally depleted and this event is called 'global hypo-
methylation' (19-21). The causal mechanism of global 
hypomethylation is not known (22). Global hypomethyla-
tion may have several consequences on the multistep pro-
cess of carcinogenesis. The most commonly recognized 
effects are to facilitate chromosomal instability (23-25) 
and to control gene expression (26). Interestingly, both 
consequences have been proposed to occur 'in cis', on 
nearby genomic sites of the hypomethylation (26-28). 
Therefore, if each LINE-1 locus possesses distinct methy-
lation levels, LINE-1s may play different roles in cellular 
biology and cancer development, depending on their loca-
tions. This study evaluated the methylation status of 
different LINE-1s in normal cells and cancerous tissues. </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +662 256 4532; Fax: +662 254 1931; Email: mapiwat@chula.ac.th </p>

<p>ß 2008 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>The finding may provide more information on the roles of 
the epigenetic modifications of repetitive sequences. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Cells and tissue preparation </p>

<p>Eleven head and neck squamous cell cancer (HNSCC) cell 
lines (WSU-HN) (29), including WSU-HN 4, 6, 8, 12, 13, 
17, 19, 22, 26, 30 and 31, were provided by Dr Silvio 
Gutkind (NIH, USA). HeLa (cervical cancer) and KB 
(oral cancer cell line, but with a HeLa contaminant) 
lines (ATCC, Manassas, VA, USA) were included. Cells 
were cultured in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium 
(Gibco BRL, Life Technologies, Pairly, UK), supplemen-
ted with 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum 
(Sigma, St Louis, MO, USA). Cells were incubated at 
378C in 5% CO 2 . 
Normal oral epithelium (NOE) samples from 12 
individuals were collected. Briefly, each subject used 
20 ml of sterile 0.9% NaCl solution to rinse and gargle 
for 15 s then spit the solution into a sterile 50-ml closed 
container, which was kept at 48C until the samples were 
processed for DNA collection (within 24 h of collection). 
Cells from the oral rinses were collected by centrifugation 
at 2500g for 15 min at 48C. The supernatant was discarded 
and the pellets were washed with sterile PBS. Several sam-
ples of white blood cells (WBCs) from normal, healthy 
individuals were also collected. Several archival paraffin-
embedded tissues, derived from HNSCCs, were obtained 
and prepared in 5 mm thickness sections on slides for 
microdissection as previously described (4). </p>

<p>COBRA PCR </p>

<p>Combined bisulfite restriction analysis (COBRA) (30) for 
genome-wide LINE-1s (COBRALINE1) and COBRA 
for unique L1 sequences (CU-L1) were both performed 
as previously described, with some modifications (4). 
LINE-1s were selected by blat using L1.2 sequence to 
http://genome.ucsc.edu and full-length intronic LINE-1s 
with the representative COBRALINE-1 CpG dinucleo-
tides were selected. All selected LINE-1s are listed in 
Supplementary Table S1. After extraction, all DNA sam-
ples were treated with sodium bisulfite as previously 
described (4,31). Briefly, genomic DNA was denatured 
in 0.22 M NaOH for 10 min at 378C. Thirty microliters 
of 10 mM hydroquinone and 520 ml of 3 M sodium bisul-
fite were both added for 16-20 h at 508C. The DNA was 
purified and incubated in 0.33 M NaOH for 5 min at 258C, 
ethanol-precipitated, then washed with 70% ethanol and 
resuspended in 20 ml of TE buffer. Two microliters of 
bisulfited DNA were subjected to 35 cycles of PCR with 
two primers, as listed in Supplementary Table S2, at an 
annealing temperature of 538C. The amplicons were 
digested in 30 ml reaction volumes with 2 U of TaqI or 
8 U of TasI in 1 Â TaqI buffer (MBI Fermentas) overnight 
at 658C and then electrophoresed on 8% non-denaturing 
polyacrylamide gels. The intensities of DNA fragments 
were measured on a PhosphoImager, using the 
<rs type="software">ImageQuant</rs> software (Molecular Dynamics, GE Health-
care, Slough, UK). The TaqI positive methylated </p>

<p>amplicons yielded 80-bp DNA fragments, whereas the 
TasI positive unmethylated amplicons resulted in 98-bp 
fragments (previously reported as 97 bp). The LINE-1 
methylation level was calculated as a percentage (the 
intensity of the TaqI-digested methylated LINE-1 frag-
ment divided by the sum of the TasI-digested unmethy-
lated LINE-1 and TaqI-positive amplicons). For CU-L1, 
several other methylated and unmethylated digested 
amplicons, as listed in Supplementary Table S2, were 
also measured. The methylation levels among several 
CpG dinucleotides were compared. All COBRA assays 
were performed in duplicate. The same set of DNAs was 
applied as positive controls in each set of the COBRA 
experiments. The PCR products of some of the CU-L1 
were cloned into the pGEM-T easy vector (Promega, 
Santhan, UK) and sequenced. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Statistical significance was determined by applying an 
independent sample t-test and Pearson's correlation coef-
ficient to the data, as specified. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>COBRA for unique to LINE-1 sequence (CU-L1) </p>

<p>Previously, we investigated the methylation of genome-
wide LINE-1s by investigating the methylation status of 
two CpG dinucleotides at the 5 0 -end of LINE-1s (4). This 
study compares the methylation status of LINE-1s across 
different loci. Because there are variations in both lengths 
and sequences of LINE-1s, we compared methylation 
levels of LINE-1s between locations by comparing methy-
lation levels of the same representative CpG dinucleotides: 
TaqI positive 80-bp methylated DNA fragments and TasI 
positive 98-bp unmethylated DNA fragments (Figure 1A). 
We selected a set of 17 full-length LINE-1s located within 
introns. All LINE-1s possessed both representative 
CpG dinucleotides. Selected LINE-1s (Supplementary 
Table S1), a schematic representation of the assay 
(Figure 1A) and typical examples of PCR results 
(Figure 1B) are shown. We modified the COBRA protocol 
(30) to devise a PCR protocol to evaluate LINE-1 methy-
lation status in the entire genome (COBRALINE-1) and 
at a specific locus (CU-L1) by replacing the LINE-1 for-
ward primer with an oligonucleotide locating on unique 
sequence 5 0 to LINE-1. Briefly, DNA is treated with bisul-
fite to distinguish between methylated and unmethylated 
sequences before PCR (32). Treatment with bisulfite con-
verts unmethylated cytosines, but not methylated cyto-
sines, to uracils and then thymines after PCR. This 
generates detectable methylation-dependent changes in 
the restriction pattern of PCR-amplified LINE-1 
sequences (Figure 1A). The modified DNA was amplified 
by 5 0 -UTR LINE-1 bisulfited sequence primers and then 
digested with TaqI and TasI restriction enzymes, which 
recognize methylated and unmethylated sequences, respec-
tively. The level of LINE-1 methylation in each sample 
was calculated by dividing the measured intensity of 
TaqI digestible amplicons by the sum of the TasI and 
TaqI products (4) (Figure 1A). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 17 5705 </p>

<p>We designed the CU-L1 PCR to constitute several 
digested fragments, including methylated, unmethylated 
and control, which are without candidate CpG restriction 
sequences, so that we could check for multiple CpG dinu-
cleotides containing TaqI sites and an unmethylated CpG 
containing TasI site. Therefore, the intensities of each 
methylated and unmethylated band could be measured 
to compare the methylation status among several CpG 
nucleotides. Figure 2A and B provides examples of the 
positive linear correlation between methylated fragments 
from the CU-L1 locations. Direct correlations between </p>

<p>unmethylated fragments were also demonstrated 
(Figure 2C and D). Therefore, the methylation levels of 
the representative COBRALINE-1 TaqI and TasI sites 
represent methylation levels of each LINE-1 in a positive 
correlated fashion. 
To evaluate the relationship among all of the 5 0 LINE-1 
CpGs, CU-L1 amplicons were cloned and sequenced. 
Figure 3 demonstrates examples of CU-L1 sequences. 
Direct correlation of methylation levels between CU-L1 
and bisulfite sequencing can be observed. Both CU-L1 
and bisulfite sequences demonstrated low L1-LRP2 
methylation levels in WSU-HN 6 and 22 cells and high 
methylation levels in WSU-HN 26 cells, compared with a 
sample of NOE. Therefore, CU-L1 methylation levels 
were applied to compare methylation levels between 
each DNA sample. The bisulfite sequences (Figure 3) 
demonstrated that even though they were directly corre-
lated, the methylation statuses of the CpG dinucleotides 
from 5 0 LINE-1 are not equally distributed. We found that 
the CpGs around TaqI and TasI COBRALINE-1 digested 
sites might be more prone to be demethylation than others 
(Figure 3). 
Interestingly, even though a universal characteristic of 
cancer development is clonal in origin and selective clonal 
expansion, bisulfite sequencing indicated that LINE-1 
methylation patterns of each DNA strand from the same 
locus are not identical (Figure 3). This indicates that 
LINE-1 methylation may be dynamic. Moreover, there 
are mixtures of CU-L1 alleles with distinguishably differ-
ent methylation statuses. For example, the methylation 
status of L1-LRP2 can divide the chromosomes of the 
cancer cell lines, WSU-HN 6 and 22, into two groups. 
The DNA from one group was almost completely 
unmethylated and that from the others was partially 
methylated (Figure 3). This result may suggest that 
LINE-1 hypomethylation in cancer may also be a dynamic 
process and either different chromosomes or cells may be 
unequally influenced by the global hypomethylation 
process. 
A general concern with the COBRA method is the mis-
interpretation of cases of a mutation or polymorphism at 
a restriction site. For COBRALINE-1, this type of error is 
irrelevant because of the vast number of targeted LINE-1 
sequences in the genome (4). For CU-L1, we were able to 
check for the possibility of a mutation error. If there is a 
mutation at the TaqI restriction site, for example TCGA 
to TTGA, then the homozygous or heterozygous poly-
morphic sample will result in a false positive as completely 
unmethylated for two or one alleles, respectively. 
Therefore, CU-L1 methylation levels should dramatically 
deviate from the linear correlation of the linked CpGs. 
However, striking deviation was rare when methylation 
levels between CpGs were compared (Figure 2A). 
Nevertheless, because CU-L1 contains several methylated 
and unmethylated fragments, alternative sites could be 
selected if the density of the representative sites deviated 
strikingly from the group (Figure 2A). Moreover, in 
normal cells, particularly WBCs, CU-L1s of most loci 
usually demonstrated methylation levels in a limited 
range without a striking deviation (Figure 4A). In conclu-
sion, mutations or polymorphisms of these CU-L1 </p>

<p>Figure 1. COBRA for unique L1 sequence (CU-L1) and COBRA for 
genome-wide LINE-1s (COBRALINE1). COBRA was performed as 
previously described (30), with some modifications (4). (A) Schematic 
representation of CU-L1 and COBRALINE-1, showing LINE-1 
sequence in relation to the 5 0 unique sequence. AACCG and CCGA 
are LINE-1 sequences, following bisulfite treatment and PCR, 
unmethylated AACCG sequences are converted to AATTG (TasI 
site) and methylated sequences are converted from CCGA to TCGA 
(TaqI site). The amplicon sizes of CU-L1 are between 300 and 500 bp 
and for COBRALINE-1 are 160 bp. After digestion, COBRALINE-1 
yielded two TasI-digested unmethylated L1 sequence fragments of 62 
and 98 bp and one 80 bp TaqI-digested methylated L1 sequence. The 
LINE-1 methylation level was calculated as a percentage (the intensity 
of methylated LINE-1 divided by the sum of the unmethylated LINE-1 
and the TaqI-positive amplicons). CU-L1 usually has additional TaqI 
site(s) and AATT sequences; therefore, there are additional methylated, 
unmethylated and control bands. Met and unmet are methylated and 
unmethylated sequences, respectively. Control bands are digested DNA 
fragments without candidate CpG restriction sequences. (B) A typical 
example of results from COBRALINE-1 and CU-L1. The ranges of 
intensity between methylated and unmethylated bands of CU-L1 were 
wider than COBRALINE-1. The unmet, met and control arrows indi-
cate unmethylated, methylated and control LINE1 sequences, respec-
tively. M is a standard size marker. The -ve is dH 2 O. Several samples 
from WSU-HN cells are shown. </p>



<p>restriction sites are rare and several informative amplicons 
help prevent interpretation errors. </p>

<p>LINE-1 methylation levels vary among locations and cell types </p>

<p>Our previous study showed that genome-wide LINE-1 
methylation levels can be significantly different among 
normal tissue types (4). Moreover, some tissues, such as 
the thyroid and esophagus, demonstrated wider ranges 
in the methylation level. Here, we compared LINE-1 
methylation levels of the 17 loci between NOE and </p>

<p>WBC (Figure 4A). Means of the LINE-1 methylation 
levels varied from highly methylated, which was the case 
for the L1-PKP4, L1-EPHA3-IVS5, L1-EPHA3-IVS15, 
L1-ANTXR2 and L1-COL24A1 fragments, to 24-41%, 
which was the case for the L1-PPP2R2B and L1-PKG1 
fragments. To support the premise that LINE-1 is com-
pletely methylated, the partial methylation levels of 
genome-wide LINE-1s would have to not only be reported 
by COBRALINE-1 (4), but also by several other techni-
ques (9,18,33). The lower methylation levels of some of the </p>

<p>Figure 2. Correlation between the bands of CU-L1. Pixel counts of CU-L1 fluorescent intensities from 19 cell lines, 12 WBCs and 12 NOEs are 
shown. Examples of two LINE-1 loci are shown. (A and B) Comparison between methylated bands. (C and D) Comparison between unmethylated 
bands. (A and C) The L1-EPHA3-IVS5 locus. (B and D) The L1-MGC4217 locus. Each band was named according to the restriction enzymes and 
sizes of the digested fragment. Most samples demonstrate a linear correlation. The arrow indicates a striking deviation of the 151-bp TaqI band from 
the same sample. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 17 5707 </p>

<p>CU-L1s proved that not all LINE-1s are completely 
methylated in normal cells. 
LINE-1 methylation patterns are distinguishable 
between NOE and normal WBCs. Even though there 
was limited range, when COBRALINE-1s were compared 
between NOE and WBCs, they were significantly different, 
P &lt; 0.01. Similarly, methylation levels between WBCs and 
NOE of some CU-L1 loci were also different, such 
as in the case of the L1-PPP2R2B (P &lt; 10 À9 ) and 
L1-CNTNAP5 (P &lt; 10 À10 ) fragments. Interestingly, in 
normal cells, most loci possessed limited ranges, within 
4-6% of CU-L1s, while some loci, such as L1-SPOCK3, 
demonstrated a wider range of up to 45.46%. The wider 
ranges could most frequently be found in NOE rather 
than WBCs, such as at the L1-FAM49A, L1-LOC286094 
and L1-LRP2 loci. This result is similar to our previous 
COBRALINE-1 finding that the ranges of genome-wide 
LINE-1 methylation levels differ across tissues (4). </p>

<p>Characteristics of LINE-1 hypomethylation in cancer </p>

<p>Genome wide LINE-1 methylation levels in cancerous 
tissue are lower in variable degrees than in the representa-
tive normal cells (4). To evaluate the cancer-specific epi-
genetic process in detail, we reported CU-L1s from 17 
loci in 11 WSU-HN, HeLa and KB cell lines and com-
pared our findings with those from a number of NOE 
(Figure 4B). LINE-1 hypomethylation, which is a methy-
lation level lower than that in NOE, can be observed in all 
loci. However, each locus had a different number of sam-
ples with hypomethylation. Three to six samples out of 13 
were found to have hypomethylation at the L1-PKP4, 
L1-SPOCK3 and L1-MGC42174 loci. On the contrary, 
the L1-FAM49A, L1-LOC286094, L1-LRP2, L1-CDH8 
and L1-PRKG1 loci demonstrated hypomethylation in 
12-13 samples out of 13 samples. Moreover, the level of 
hypomethylation varied when comparisons were made 
between loci. For example, WSU-HN19 cells had comple-
tely unmethylated L1-COL24A1 and L1-ADAMTS20 
loci, but were barely hypomethylated at the L1-EPHA3-
IVS5 and L1-EPHA3-IVS15 loci (Figure 4B). Different 
CU-L1 levels were observed even if the cells were from 
the same origin. WSU-HN30 and WSU-HN31 were two 
cell lines derived from the same patient, but from different 
tissue origins. While most CU-L1 levels were similar, 
different levels were found at some loci, such as at 
L1-EPHA3-IVS15 (Figure 4B). Similar findings were 
found in HeLa and KB cells, which also had a HeLa 
contaminant. The hypomethylation level at the 
L1-ANTXR2 locus was higher in KB cells than it was in 
HeLa. On the contrary, the L1-COL24A1 locus in HeLa 
was more hypomethylated than in KB cells (Figure 4B). 
The differences in the CU-L1 methylation pattern between 
cell lines were similar to a previous report where a distinc-
tive pattern of LINE-1 methylation was reported in differ-
ent cell lines (6). This result may suggest that the global 
hypomethylation pattern of cancer cells can be variable. 
It is important to note that hypermethylation of CU-L1 
could be observed sporadically, for example, the methyla-
tion level in WSU-HN8 at the L1-CNTNAP5 locus 
(Figure 4B). Therefore, each LINE-1 locus may have </p>

<p>Figure 3. CU-L1s bisulfite sequences. CU-L1s bisulfite sequenced 
methylated CpG dinucleotides and non-methylated CpGs of each 
clone are illustrated with closed and open circles, respectively. The 
80-bp (methylated) and 98-bp (unmethylated) TasI-digested fragments 
are the 20th and 19th CpGs, respectively. Sample names and CU-L1 
methylation levels are shown on the left. </p>

<p>5708 Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 17 </p>

<p>different potential for developing carcinogenic-related 
hypomethylation. This may indicate that LINE-1 hypo-
methylation is dynamic and influenced in cis by factors 
located on the same chromosome. 
Similar patterns of LINE-1 methylation can be 
observed in vivo. Figure 4C shows the CU-L1 results 
from 17 microdissected HNSCC paraffin-embedded sec-
tions. Because the quality of DNA derived from these 
sample types was poor, not all CU-L1s yield positive 
amplicons. Nevertheless, these samples demonstrated 
LINE-1 methylation patterns that were similar to those 
in the HNSCC cell lines. The specific characteristics 
included a variable degree of frequent LINE-1 hypo-
methylation and sporadic events of L1-CNTNAP5 hyper-
methylation (Figure 4C). 
We evaluated the directions of relationships between 
methylation levels of two that were between genome-wide </p>

<p>and a specific locus or between two loci. Correlations are 
reported as Pearson correlation coefficients (r). The 
r-values between À0.5 and 0.5 were considered not 
significant. The multiple white spots in Figure 5 represent 
r-values between the COBRAs, listed on the x-axis, and 
the other r-values. We observed positive correlations 
between LINE-1 methylation levels between genome-
wide and a specific locus or between two loci more fre-
quently in WSU-HN than in NOE cells. This is demon-
strated by the fact that most r-values between the LINE-1s 
of WSU-HN cells, but not of NOE cells, are frequently 
closer to one (Figure 5A and B). Hence, methylation 
levels of LINE-1s in cancer cells may result from a gen-
eralized process of global demethylation. However, 
methylation of certain loci, such as L1-SPOCK3 
and L1-PKP4, did not have a positive correlation 
with their cancer genome or other loci (Figure 5A). </p>

<p>Figure 4. CU-L1 methylation levels. (A) NOE and WBC, (B) NOE and epithelial cell lines, (C) NOE and HNSCC. Each dot represents means AE SD 
each CU-L1 methylation level. Dashed and solid lines connect the measurements from the same samples. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 17 5709 </p>

<p>Interestingly, both of the loci had less hypomethylation in 
many samples (Figure 4B). Therefore, they may be less 
influenced by the global hypomethylation process. The 
highest correlation value observed in cancerous cells, 
was between the two LINE-1s inserted in the same gene, 
L1-EPHA3-IVS5 and L1-EPHA3-IVS15 (P &lt; 10 À16 ; 
Pearson r = 0.913) (Figure 5A). These characteristics of 
CU-L1 methylation levels suggest that loss of LINE-1 
methylation in cancers, in addition to being a result of 
genome-wide hypomethylation, may also be influenced 
by locus-specific pressure. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Methylation patterns of LINE-1s in different normal 
tissue types and hypomethylation characteristics in many 
types of epithelial cancers have been previously reported 
(4-18). To our knowledge, this is the first report to demon-
strate methylation patterns of LINE-1s at different geno-
mic locations. It is surprising that even though LINE-1s 
are repetitive sequences, methylation levels of LINE-1s 
among different loci can be different. In normal cells, 
some loci possess high methylation levels, whereas many 
loci are only partially methylated. This suggests that 
cis-elements, or factors on the same chromosome near 
each LINE-1, may influence the epigenetic modification. 
LINE-1 methylation levels of some loci represent a tissue-
specific pattern, as shown by the different levels between 
NOE and WBC. Interestingly, Eller and colleagues (34) 
demonstrated that LINE-1 elements are frequently 
excluded from housekeeping regions. Moreover, hyper-
methylation of LINE-1s has been reported during abnor-
mal overgrowth and differentiation of human placenta 
(11). It is therefore possible that LINE-1 methylation is 
associated with tissue-specific phenotypes of the cells in 
relation to the genome function in cis. Finally, in some 
regions (e.g. L1-SPOCK3), this epigenetic control may be </p>

<p>a dynamic process. Wider ranges of methylation levels 
could be observed with a greater number of LINE-1 loci 
in NOE than in WBC. Interestingly, we previously found 
intermediate ranges of genome-wide LINE-1 methylation 
levels in head and neck squamous cells and wider ranges in 
esophageal and thyroid tissues (4). 
LINE-1 hypomethylation is a common epigenetic pro-
cess in cancer that may progressively evolve during the 
multistage carcinogenesis process (4,5,7,12). The underly-
ing mechanism of this process is not known. Because the 
methylation levels of most LINE-1 loci in cancerous cells 
are positively correlated with each other and on a genome-
wide level, we concluded that the mechanism leading to 
global hypomethylation is a generalized process that 
simultaneously influences dispersed loci. Our experiments, 
however, have demonstrated that the locus-specific epige-
netic modifications of some loci may also be related to 
carcinogenesis. Evidence that supports this hypothesis 
includes the data that show different hypomethylation 
incidences from different LINE-1 loci, the direct associa-
tion between the two LINE-1s in EPHA3 introns and 
hypermethylation of some loci, such as L1-CNTNAP5, 
in some HNSCCs. In conclusion, even though global 
hypomethylation processes can generally and progres-
sively deplete LINE-1 methylation levels, locus-specific 
methylation of LINE-1s can differentially be influenced 
by carcinogenic processes depending on where the parti-
cular LINE-1s are located in the genome. 
The level of LINE-1 hypomethylation is positively asso-
ciated with how the tumor progresses (4,5,7,12). 
Consequently, the potential roles of a PCR-based LINE-
1 methylation analysis for cancer diagnosis has been eval-
uated by several studies (8-10,12,13). Differential methy-
lation levels of normal tissues, however, limit the utility 
of COBRALINE-1. For example, the application of 
COBRALINE-1 to analyze circulating free cell DNA 
should be limited because serum DNA contains a mixture </p>

<p>Figure 5. COBRALINE-1 and CU-Ls correlation. Pearson correlation coefficient values between LINE-1 and genome-wide loci of (A) WSU-HN 
cells and (B) NOE cells. Arrows indicate an association between loci L1-EPHA3-IVS5 and L1-EPHA3-IVS15. </p>



<p>of DNA released from normal and cancerous cells (35). 
The cancer-induced global hypomethylation differentially 
influences each LINE-1 locus depending on their loca-
tions. Moreover, variations of methylation levels in 
normal cells occur specifically at some loci. Consequently, 
since there are a vast number of LINE-1s, researchers can 
test and select for LINE-1 loci that yield specific informa-
tion related to cancer development. The CU-L1 methyla-
tion levels may therefore be an important tool for cancer 
diagnosis in the future. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Dr J. Silvio Gutkind at the NIH, USA for 
kindly providing the WSU-HN cell lines. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Thailand Research Fund (TRF); the National Center for 
Genetic Engineering and Biotechnology (BIOTEC); 
NASTDA (Thailand); Chulalongkorn University; Royal 
Golden Jubilee PhD grant (to C.P., S.K.). Funding for 
open access charge: Chulalongkorn University. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>5712 Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 17 </p>

</text></tei>