<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2846736" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Asthma is a prevalent inflammatory airway disease character-
ized by bronchial hyperresponsiveness (BHR) and atopy, affect-
ing more than 300 million people worldwide. The disease phe-
notypes are triggered by CD4+ T lymphocytes generating the 
Th2-associated cytokines IL-4 and IL-5 in response to allergens. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Atopy is associated with the increased generation of Immuno-
globulin E (IgE) and determined as a hypersensitivity (allergy) 
to common environmental allergens. 
2 IgE or specific IgE also 
serve as a significant risk factor to the development of asthma. 
T cells recognize antigen presenting cells by the presence of 
antigens bound to MHC class II molecules. The receptor-ligand 
complexes B7-1 (CD80) and B7-2 (CD86) then form a ligand with 
CD28 and the cytotoxic T lymphocyte-associated 4 (CTLA4) re-</p>

<p>Association Between Serum IgE Levels and the CTLA4 +49A/G and 
FCER1B -654C/T Polymorphisms in Korean Children With Asthma </p>

<p>Kyu-Young Oh, 
1 Mi-Jin Kang, 
2 Won-Ah Choi, 
2 Ji-Won Kwon, 
3 Byoung-Ju Kim, 
3 Jinho Yu, 
3 Soo-Jong Hong </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Korean Minjok Leadership Academy, Korea </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Asan Institute for Life Sciences, University of Ulsan College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of Pediatrics, Childhood Asthma Atopy Center, Asan Medical Center, University of Ulsan College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea </p>

<p>ceptors, which trigger co-stimulation. This formation facilitates 
the activation of T cells. 
3 Previous data suggest that this co-stim-
ulatory pathway plays a central role in regulating the develop-
ment of Th2 cells, and ultimately the magnitude of the immune 
response. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>In murine models, the infiltration of eosinophils into broncho-
alveolar lavage fluid and airway hyperresponsiveness are com-
pletely inhibited in mice treated with CTLA4-Ig. 
5 The upregula-</p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2010 April;2(2):127-133. 
doi: 10.4168/aair.2010.2.2.127 
pISSN 2092-7355 • eISSN 2092-7363 </p>

<p>Purpose: T cells play a central role in cell-mediated immunity, atopic disease, and asthma. The balance of CD28/cytotoxic T-lymphocyte antigen 4 
(CTLA4)-derived signal transduction plays an important role in the activation of T cells and an increased immunoglobulin E (IgE) response. The aim of 
the current study was to investigate the association between polymorphisms in the genes encoding both CTLA4 and the high-affinity IgE receptor 1B 
(FCER1B) and serum IgE levels in Korean children with asthma. </p>

<p>Methods: We enrolled 238 controls and 742 children with asthma. The CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B -654C/T polymorphisms were genotyped by 
PCR-restriction fragment length polymorphism analysis. </p>

<p>Results: We observed no difference in the distribution of CTLA4 +49A/G among controls, children with asthma, and those with atopic asthma. In 
contrast, the GA genotype of CTLA4 +49A/G in children with atopic asthma was significantly higher compared to that in those with non-atopic asth-
ma. Moreover, significantly higher log Dp/Df-specific IgE levels were found in children with asthma and those with atopic asthma carrying one or two 
copies of the CTLA4 +49A versus those homozygous for +49G. Gene-gene interactions between CTLA4 and FCER1B with the heterozygote and homozy-
gote of variant genotypes were associated with the log Dp/Df-specific IgE levels, but not asthma development. In addition, children with Dp/Df (+) 
asthma carried an elevated combined genotype of risk allele compared to those with Dp/Df (-) asthma. </p>

<p>Conclusions: The CTLA4 +49A/G polymorphism may contribute to the production of IgE in Korean children with asthma, especially in Dp/Df-specific 
IgE levels, but not in the direct development of asthma. In addition, Dp/Df-specific IgE levels with a FCER1B -654C/T polymorphism may involve addi-
tive effects. </p>

<p>Key Words: Asthma; CTLA4; FCER1B; polymorphism; Dermatophagoides pteronyssinus; Dermatophagoides farinae; immunoglobulin E </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits 
unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Soo-Jong Hong, MD, PhD, Department of Pediatrics, 
Asan Medical Center, College of Medicine, Ulsan University, 388-1 Poongnap-
dong Songpa-gu, Seoul 138-736, Korea. 
Tel: +82-2-3010-3379; Fax: +82-2-473-3725; E-mail: sjhong@amc.seoul.kr 
Received: November 27, 2009; Accepted: February 9, 2010 </p>

<p>•There are no financial or other issues that might lead to conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2010 April;2(2):127-133. doi: 10.4168/aair.2010.2.2.127 </p>

<p>Oh et al. 
Volume 2, Number 2, April 2010 </p>



<p>tion of ovalbumin-specific serum IgE levels are also reduced. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>The genetic makeup significantly influences the onset of pheno-
types such as IgE levels. The genes encoding the CTLA4 and 
CD28 map to the human chromosome 3q13-q23, which is linked 
to asthma in Hispanics, 
6 Dutch, 
7 and numerous other popula-
tions. CTLA4 affects the upregulation of serum IgE levels, a phe-
notype of asthma. 
8 In genetic studies, the CTLA4 promoter 
(-318C/T) polymorphism was found to be associated with asth-
ma severity while exon 1 (+49 A/G) was associated both BHR </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>and total serum levels of IgE. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>The high-affinity IgE receptor 1 (FCER1) is involved in the in-
duction of immune responses in atopic disease by facilitating 
IgE-dependent activation of mast cells and basophils. 
11 The gene 
encoding FCER1B influences the total serum levels of IgE and 
interacts synergistically with the functional polymorphism (4G/ 
5G) at the plasminogen activator inhibitor-1 (PAI-1) promoter 
region to alter asthma susceptibility. 
12 The -109C/T polymor-
phism of the FCER1B gene is also associated with increased to-
tal serum IgE levels in patients with asthma. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>We began this study based on the hypothesis that the total se-
rum IgE levels are largely determined by genetic factors. Each 
polymorphism of multiple genes has a relatively small effect on 
IgE levels, finally setting the IgE level through influencing nu-
merous genes. Since both the CTLA4 and FCER1B genes can 
determine the total serum levels of IgE (an intermediate pheno-
type of asthma), we investigated whether increased serum IgE 
and susceptibility in Korean children with asthma are associat-
ed with CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B -654C/T polymorphisms. 
In addition, we investigated if the phenotype produced by the 
two polymorphisms is synergistic in Korean children with asth-
ma. Such an effect of the CTLA4 and FCER1B genes has been 
previously demonstrated to influence the total serum IgE levels 
in the Japanese population, but we intended to expand the 
study to Korean children with asthma. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Subjects 
The study subjects consisted of 238 control and 742 Korean 
children with asthma who visited the Asthma and Allergy Clin-
ics of the Asan Medical Center. All subjects were classed into 
three specific groups: 238 non-atopic controls without asthma, 
599 with atopic asthma, and 143 with non-atopic asthma. Asth-
ma phenotypes and BHR were determined by a physician fol-
lowing the guidelines from the American Thoracic Society. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Asthma was determined by a history of patient dyspnea and 
wheezing during the previous 12 months, a greater than 12% 
reversibility of FEV1 after b2-agonist inhalation, and/or a meth-
acholine provocation test result with a PC20 value of less than 
16 mg/mL. Atopy was confirmed by a positive skin prick test 
(wheal diameter ≥3 mm) to at least one of 27 common aeroal-
lergens in Korea 
15 or by an elevated allergen-specific IgE level. </p>

<p>Non-atopics were defined by negative specific IgE in response 
to Dermatophagoides farinae (Df) and Dermatophagoides pter-
onyssinus (Dp), and negative skin prick test results to 27 com-
mon aeroallergens including grass pollen, animal dander, and 
mold. The non-atopic non-asthmatic control subjects had no 
previous history of asthma or any other allergic diseases, nor-
mal total IgE levels (≤100 IU/mL), normal results for the lung 
function tests, no airway hyperresponsiveness (PC20 &gt;16 mg/ 
mL), and showed negative results for the skin prick tests. Writ-
ten informed consent was obtained from the parents of all sub-
jects, and the study was approved by the ethics committee of 
the Asian Medical Center Institutional Review Board. </p>

<p>Serum IgE measurement, skin prick test, and the methacholine 
challenge test 
Serum IgE levels were measured using a fluorescent enzyme 
immunoassay (AutoCAP System; Pharmacia Diagnostics AB, 
Uppsala, Sweden). Specific IgE concentrations were considered 
positive when ≥0.35 KIU/L, and subsequent results were divid-
ed into classes 1 to 6 according to their values. The skin prick 
test was performed using 27 common aeroallergens in Korea. A 
maximum wheal diameter of ≥3 mm was considered positive. 
In the methacholine challenge test, a dosimeter with a con-
centration range of 0.625-25 mg/mL was used. In addition, we 
used a spirometer (Microspiro HI298; Chest Corporation, To-
kyo, Japan) to measure FEV1 after each inhalation. Airway re-
sponsiveness was expressed as the concentration of methacho-
line that provoked a 20% fall in FEV1 (PC20). Subjects were con-
sidered hyperresponsive when the PC20 levels were less than 
16 mg/mL. </p>

<p>Genotyping of the CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B -654C/T 
polymorphisms 
DNA was isolated from blood samples using a G-DEX II kit 
(iNtRon, Seoul, Korea). The CTLA4 +49A/G (rs231775) was gen-
otyped by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) followed by restric-
tion fragment length polymorphism analysis (RFLP). Experi-
mental settings were confirmed by comparing cases with the 
results of DNA sequencing. PCR products were formed in a re-
action volume of 15 μL that contained 30 ng of template DNA, 
0.5 units of AmpliTaq Gold Taq polymerase (Applied Biosystems, 
Foster City, CA), 1.5 μL of MgCl2-free 10× buffer (Applied Bio-
systems), 0.9 μL of 25 mmol/L MgCl2, 0.5 μL of each specific 
primer 5'-AAGGCTCAGCTGAACCTGGTT-3' and 5'-CTGCT-
GAAACAAATGAAACCC-3' for CTLA4 +49A/G and 0.75 μL of 
deoxyribonucleoside triphosphates (2.5 mmol/L of each de-
oxyribonucleoside triphosphate). The cycling conditions were 
as follows: 95°C for 12 minutes, 35 cycles at 95°C for 30 seconds, 
annealing for 1 minute at 54°C for CTLA4 +49A/G and exten-
sion at 72°C for 40 seconds, followed by a final extension step at 
72°C for 10 minutes. The CTLA4 +49A allele was digested into 
135 and 18 base pair (bp) fragments using BstE II (New England </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2010 April;2(2):127-133. doi: 10.4168/aair.2010.2.2.127 </p>

<p>CTLA4 Polymorphism and IgE Levels 
AAIR </p>



<p>http://e-aair.org </p>

<p>BioLabs, Beverly, MA) at 60°C for 2 hours, and products verified 
on a 3.5% agarose gel (FMC BioProducts, Rockland, ME). The 
FCER1B -654C/T (rs574700) was genotyped using the TaqMan 
SNP Genotyping Assay. Primer Express (Applied Biosystems) 
was used to design the MGB TaqMan probes. One allelic probe 
was labeled with the fluorescent FAM dye and the other with 
the VIC dye. PCRs were run in a TaqMan universal master mix 
without UNG (Applied Biosystems) using PCR primer concen-
trations of 900 nM and TaqMan MGB-probe concentrations of 
200 nM. Reactions were performed in a 384-well format in a to-
tal reaction volume of 5 μL using 20 ng of genomic DNA. The 
plates then were placed in a thermal cycler (PE 9700; Applied 
Biosystems) and heated at 50°C for 2 minutes and 95°C for 10 
minutes followed by 40 cycles at 95°C for 15 seconds and 60°C 
for 1 minutes, with a final soak at 25°C. The TaqMan assay plates 
were transferred to the Prism 7900HT instruments (Applied Bio-
systems), where the fluorescence intensity in each well of the 
plate was read. Fluorescence data files from each plate were an-
alyzed by automated allele-calling software (<rs id="software-0" type="software">SDS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">2.1</rs>). </p>

<p>Statistical analyses 
The clinical parameters (total IgE, PC20, total eosinophil count, 
FEV1 (%)) were analyzed according to the Kruskal-Wallis test 
among the four groups as shown in Table 1. To analyze the as-
sociation between the genotypes and asthma, we adopted a dom-
inant model since relatively few individuals were homozygous 
for the risk alleles. Since the age and sex displayed differences 
between controls and patients with asthma, a logistic regression 
analysis adjusted for age and sex was used to calculate the odds 
ratios (ORs) and the 95% confidence intervals (CIs). The rela-
tionship between clinical phenotypes and genotypes was test-
ed using the independent t-test; the analysis of increasing trend 
of aOR and log IgE was followed by a logistic and linear regres-
sion, respectively. All statistical analyses were performed using 
the <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">14.0</rs> for Windows (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL), and a P val-
ue of ≤0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Frequency of the CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B -654C/T 
polymorphisms 
We sought to study the association of the CTLA4 +49A/G and 
FCER1B -654C/T polymorphisms with asthma susceptibility, 
and determined the occurrence of these genotypes in asthma, 
atopic asthma, non-atopic asthma, and control groups using 
subjects homozygous for a common allele as a reference group. 
When the allele frequencies of the CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B 
-654C/T polymorphisms were compared, no significant associ-
ation between the carriers of the risk allele of the CTLA4 and 
FCER1B polymorphisms and the susceptibility of asthma were 
evident (Table 2). In addition, the controls did not display a cor-
relation with those having asthma or atopic asthma, although 
for the CTLA4 +49A/G polymorphism, the GA genotype of chil-
dren with non-atopic asthma was shown to be significantly low-
er when compared to control samples (OR=0.60, 95% CI=0.38-
0.95; Table 2). For the FCER1B -654C/T polymorphism, differ-
ent genotype frequencies did not vary among the four groups. </p>

<p>The association between IgE levels and the CTLA4 +49A/G and 
FCER1B -654C/T polymorphisms 
We next investigated the association between the levels of to-
tal IgE and specific IgE, and the CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B 
-654C/T polymorphisms. For the CTLA4 +49A/G polymor-
phism, the risk allele was shown to be associated with log Dp/ 
Df-specific IgE in those with asthma, as the GA+AA genotype 
displayed elevated levels of log Dp/Df-specific IgE compared to 
the GG genotype (Dp-IgE, GG, 0.80±1.10 IU/mL, GA+AA, 0.97± 
1.04 IU/mL, P=0.044; Df-IgE, GG, 0.89±1.10 IU/mL, GA+AA, 
1.08±1.02 IU/mL, P=0.024; Table 3). In addition, in those with 
atopic asthma, the log Df-specific IgE was elevated in GA+AA 
genotypes (Df-IgE, GG, 1.14±0.93 IU/mL, GA+AA, 1.31±0.82 
IU/mL, P=0.035; Table 3), although the risk allele was not asso-
ciated with log total IgE levels. In addition for the FCER1B gene, </p>

<p>Table 1. Clinical characteristics of study subjects </p>

<p>Clinical parameter* 
Control 
Asthma 
Atopic asthma 
Non-atopic asthma </p>

<p>Sex (M/F) 
128/110 
484/258 
400/199 
84/59 
Age (yr) 
9.97±2.89 
9.03±2.73 
9.19±2.68 
8.35±2.82 
Log TEC (/µL) 
2.17±0.32 
2.58±0.37 
2.64±0.35 
2.34±0.36 
Eosinophils (%) 
2.47±1.53 
6.48±4.41 
7.11±4.44 
3.85±3.14 
Log IgE (IU/mL) 
1.53±0.51 
2.33±0.59 
2.48±0.48 
1.67±0.53 
Log PC20 (mg/mL) 
1.38±0.10 
0.40±0.51 
0.35±0.51 
0.57±0.48 
Max.% fall in FEV1 (%) 
9.10±8.55 
24.65±16.97 
25.55±17.22 
18.72±13.98 
FEV1 (%) 
89.37±13.66 
85.67±13.97 
84.85±13.60 
89.17±14.97 
FEF25-75% (%) 
96.38±22.80 
79.62±24.61 
78.28±24.35 
85.45±25.01 </p>

<p>*Mean±S.D. 
P&lt;0.05 for differences among the 4 groups according to the Kruskal-Wallis test. </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2010 April;2(2):127-133. doi: 10.4168/aair.2010.2.2.127 </p>

<p>Oh et al. 
Volume 2, Number 2, April 2010 </p>



<p>Table 2. Allele frequencies of the CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B -654C/T polymorphisms in asthmatic, atopic asthmatics, non-atopic asthmatics and controls </p>

<p>Genotype 
Control 
Total asthma 
Atopic asthma 
Non-atopic asthma </p>

<p>N 
% 
N 
% 
aOR 95% CI 
N 
% 
aOR 95% CI 
N 
% 
aOR 95% CI </p>

<p>CTLA4 +49A/G </p>

<p>GG 
GA 
AA </p>

<p>115 
107 
16 </p>

<p>48.32 
44.96 
6.72 </p>

<p>369 
312 
61 </p>

<p>49.73 
42.05 
8.22 </p>

<p>1.00 
0.88 
1.10 </p>

<p>0.65-1.20 
0.60-1.99 </p>

<p>287 
265 
47 </p>

<p>47.91 
44.24 
7.85 </p>

<p>1.00 
0.94 
1.12 </p>

<p>0.68-1.29 
0.61-2.07 </p>

<p>82 
47 
14 </p>

<p>57.34 
32.87 
9.79 </p>

<p>1.00 
0.60 
1.06 </p>

<p>0.38-0.95 
0.47-2.36 </p>

<p>GG 
GA/AA 
Freq. (A) </p>

<p>115 
123 
0.29 </p>

<p>48.32 
51.68 </p>

<p>369 
373 
0.29 </p>

<p>49.73 
50.27 </p>

<p>1.00 
0.91 0.67-1.22 </p>

<p>287 
312 
0.30 </p>

<p>47.91 
52.09 </p>

<p>1.00 
0.96 0.71-1.31 </p>

<p>82 
61 
0.26 </p>

<p>57.34 
42.66 </p>

<p>1.00 
0.66 0.43-1.02 </p>

<p>FCER1B -654C/T </p>

<p>CC 
CT 
TT </p>

<p>181 
55 
2 </p>

<p>76.05 
23.11 
0.84 </p>

<p>550 
184 
8 </p>

<p>74.12 
24.80 
1.08 </p>

<p>1.10 
1.32 </p>

<p>0.78-1.55 
0.28-6.26 </p>

<p>439 
152 
8 </p>

<p>73.29 
25.38 
1.34 </p>

<p>1.14 
1.65 </p>

<p>0.80-1.62 
0.35-7.84 </p>

<p>111 
32 
0 </p>

<p>77.62 
22.38 
0.00 </p>

<p>0.95 0.58-1.56 </p>

<p>CC 
CT/TT 
Freq. (T) </p>

<p>181 
57 
0.12 </p>

<p>76.05 
23.95 </p>

<p>550 
192 
0.13 </p>

<p>74.12 
25.88 
1.11 0.79-1.56 </p>

<p>439 
160 
0.14 </p>

<p>73.29 
26.71 
1.16 0.82-1.64 </p>

<p>111 
32 
0.11 </p>

<p>77.62 
22.38 
0.92 0.56-1.50 </p>

<p>Adjusted odds ratio (aOR) by age and sex. Logistic regression analysis was performed. </p>

<p>Table 3. Association between the CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B -654C/T polymorphisms and log IgE (total, Dp, Df ) in Korean children with asthma </p>

<p>Asthma 
Atopic asthma </p>

<p>CTLA4 +49A/G 
GG 
GA+AA 
P-value 
GG 
GA+AA 
P-value </p>

<p>Log total IgE 
Log Dp specific IgE 
Log Df specific IgE </p>

<p>2.29±0.60 
0.80±1.10 
0.89±1.10 </p>

<p>2.37±0.57 
0.97±1.04 
1.08±1.02 </p>

<p>0.088 
0.044 
0.024 </p>

<p>2.47±0.48 
1.04±0.95 
1.14±0.93 </p>

<p>2.49±0.49 
1.18±0.88 
1.31±0.82 </p>

<p>0.610 
0.083 
0.035 </p>

<p>FCER1B -654C/T 
CC 
CT+TT 
P-value 
CC 
CT+TT 
P-value </p>

<p>Log total IgE 
Log Dp specific IgE 
Log Df specific IgE </p>

<p>2.33±0.60 
0.87±1.09 
0.97±1.08 </p>

<p>2.33±0.57 
0.94±1.03 
1.03±1.00 </p>

<p>0.951 
0.439 
0.533 </p>

<p>2.50±0.49 
1.11±0.93 
1.22±0.90 </p>

<p>2.45±0.48 
1.13±0.91 
1.23±0.84 </p>

<p>0.363 
0.770 
0.922 </p>

<p>Data present means±SEM. 
The independent t-test was performed. </p>

<p>the risk allele did not show any association with the log total IgE 
and Dp/Df-specific IgE levels. </p>

<p>The combined effect of the CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B -654C/ 
T polymorphisms 
Thus far, our findings have shown that the Dp/Df-specific IgE 
differed according to the CTLA4 genotype. Since the FCER1B 
gene is known to code a receptor for IgE, we analyzed the com-
bination of both the CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B -654C/T poly-
morphisms to determine if a synergetic influence on asthma 
susceptibility and intermediate phenotypes exist. When the sub-
jects were divided into four combination groups and tested for 
the frequency of asthma or atopic asthma, the combined allele 
frequencies did not differ between the children with asthma 
and those without (Table 4). However, when the combined al-
lele frequencies of children with Dp/Df (-) and Dp/Df (+) asth-
ma were tested, those with Dp/Df (+) asthma carried an in-</p>

<p>creased combined genotype of risk allele compared to those 
with Dp/Df (-) asthma (Table 5). We then investigated the asso-
ciation between the total serum IgE, Dp/Df-IgE levels, and the 
combination groups of the CTLA4 and FCER1B genes. The log 
Dp-IgE showed an increasing trend in children with asthma by 
linear regression from the low-risk group 1 (CTLA4 GG and 
FCER1B CC) to high-risk group 4 (CTLA4 GA+AA and FCER1B 
CT+TT) (P=0.031), while the log Df-IgE showed an increased 
trend in both the children with asthma and those with atopic 
asthma (P=0.020, P=0.049, respectively). The log total IgE did 
not show an increased trend among the four groups (Table 6). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The present study indicates that the CTLA4 +49A/G polymor-
phism may influence the Dp/Df-specific IgE levels, but not the 
development of asthma. Our data also suggest an additive effect </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2010 April;2(2):127-133. doi: 10.4168/aair.2010.2.2.127 </p>

<p>CTLA4 Polymorphism and IgE Levels 
AAIR </p>



<p>http://e-aair.org </p>

<p>Table 4. Combined allele frequencies of combination between the CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B -654C/T polymorphisms in asthmatic children and non-asthmatic 
controls </p>

<p>Group 
Control 
Asthma 
Atopic asthma </p>

<p>N 
% 
N 
% 
aOR 
95% CI 
N 
% 
aOR 
95% CI </p>

<p>I 
91 
38.24 
273 
36.79 
1.00 
210 
35.06 
1.00 
II 
24 
10.08 
96 
12.94 
1.33 
0.80-2.21 
77 
12.85 
1.39 
0.83-2.34 
III 
90 
37.82 
277 
37.33 
1.03 
0.74-1.44 
229 
38.23 
1.10 
0.78-1.56 
IV 
33 
13.87 
96 
12.94 
0.97 
0.61-1.54 
83 
13.86 
1.09 
0.68-1.75 </p>

<p>Adjusted odds ratio (aOR) by age and sex. Logistic regression analysis was performed. 
Group I had CTLA4 GG and FCER1B CC. 
Group II had CTLA4 GG and FCER1B CT+TT. 
Group III had CTLA4 GA+AA and FCER1B CC. 
Group IV had CTLA4 GA+AA and FCER1B CT+TT. </p>

<p>between the CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B -654C/T polymor-
phisms, which contributes to the upregulation of the Dp/Df-
specific IgE level. 
CTLA4 serves as an important function in the immune sys-
tem by forming the receptor-ligand complexes that trigger the 
co-stimulatory pathway. 
3 This pathway regulates the develop-
ment of Th2 cells and ultimately determines the magnitude of </p>

<p>the systemic immune response. 
4 The gene encoding the CTLA4 
is also known to influence the phenotypes of asthma such as 
the IgE levels. 
8 Despite this, previous studies have thus far sug-
gested that no link exists between the CD28/CTLA4 region and 
asthma. 
16 In agreement with these findings, the frequency of 
the CTLA4 +49A/G polymorphisms in this study did not vary 
significantly in those with asthma, and as such, this polymor-</p>

<p>Table 5. Combined allele frequencies of combination between the CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B -654C/T polymorphisms in Dp/Df (-) asthmatic and Dp/Df (+) asth-
matic children </p>

<p>Group 
Dp/Df (-) asthma 
Dp/Df (+) asthma </p>

<p>N 
% 
N 
% 
aOR 
95% CI </p>

<p>I 
84 
42.64 
185 
34.45 
1.00 
II 
25 
12.69 
70 
13.04 
1.32 
0.78-2.24 
III 
68 
34.52 
206 
38.36 
1.35 
0.93-1.98 
IV 
20 
10.15 
76 
14.15 
1.72 
0.99-3.02 </p>

<p>Adjusted odds ratio (aOR) by age and sex. Logistic regression analysis was performed. 
P=0.034 is a trend of increasing frequency in Dp/Df (+) asthmatics from group I to group IV compare to Dp/Df (-) asthmatics. 
Group I had CTLA4 GG and FCER1B CC. 
Group II had CTLA4 GG and FCER1B CT+TT. 
Group III had CTLA4 GA+AA and FCER1B CC. 
Group IV had CTLA4 GA+AA and FCER1B CT+TT. </p>

<p>Table 6. Combination effect of the CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B -654C/T polymorphisms on log IgE (total, Dp, Df ) in children with asthma </p>

<p>Group 
Log total IgE 
Log Dp specific IgE 
Log Df specific IgE </p>

<p>Asthma (N) 
Atopic asthma (N) 
Asthma (N) 
Atopic asthma (N) 
Asthma (N) 
Atopic asthma (N) </p>

<p>I 
2.29±0.61 (271) 
2.47±0.49 (209) 
0.78±1.12 (210) 
1.03±0.98 (183) 
0.87±1.12 (213) 
1.12±0.97 (185) 
II 
2.31±0.58 (94) 
2.47±0.45 (75) 
0.83±1.03 (80) 
1.07±0.89 (69) 
0.93±1.03 (82) 
1.19±0.85 (71) 
III 
2.37±0.58 (273) 
2.52±0.48 (226) 
0.94±1.05 (219) 
1.18±0.87 (194) 
1.07±1.04 (221) 
1.32±0.81 (196) 
IV 
2.35±0.55 (95) 
2.44±0.50 (83) 
1.05±1.02 (80) 
1.19±0.92 (74) 
1.12±0.96 (80) 
1.27±0.83 (74) </p>

<p>Data present means±SEM. 
P=0.031 and P=0.088 are in log Dp IgE which are increasing trends in asthma and atopic asthma by linear regression, respectively. 
P=0.020 and P=0.049 are in log Df IgE which are increasing trends in asthma and atopic asthma by linear regression, respectively. 
Group I had CTLA4 GG and FCER1B CC. 
Group II had CTLA4 GG and FCER1B CT+TT. 
Group III had CTLA4 GA+AA and FCER1B CC. 
Group IV had CTLA4 GA+AA and FCER1B CT+TT. </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2010 April;2(2):127-133. doi: 10.4168/aair.2010.2.2.127 </p>

<p>Oh et al. 
Volume 2, Number 2, April 2010 </p>



<p>phism was not associated with the susceptibility of asthma in 
Korean children. We found that the log Dp/Df-specific IgE was 
shown to be associated with the CTLA4 +49A/G polymorphism 
since both children with asthma and those with atopic asthma 
having the GA+AA genotype displayed higher Dp/Df-specific 
IgE levels. These results suggest that the CTLA4 +49A/G poly-
morphism appears to affect the production of excessive IgE, 
particularly the Dp/Df-specific IgE. The sensitization of a spe-
cific allergen is extremely important to the development of ato-
py and as such is an independent risk factor for the develop-
ment of asthma in children. In particular the Dp/Df-allergen is 
the main sensitized allergen in Korean children. 
The gene encoding FCER1B facilitates IgE-dependent activa-
tion of mast cells and basophils and thus activates the immune 
system. 
11 FCER1B has also been demonstrated to influence to-
tal serum IgE levels. 
12 Based on this, the current study aimed to 
combine the effects of the CTLA4 and FCER1B genes to investi-
gate whether they displayed a synergistic influence upon asth-
ma susceptibility and the intermediate phenotypes of asthma 
such as IgE or specific IgE. The alleles of the two genes were com-
bined and classified from groups 1-4 according to the increased 
number of the risk alleles. We found that the genetic frequency 
of combined groups did not differ between the children with 
asthma or atopic asthma and controls, and also that the total 
serum IgE levels showed no increase from groups 1-4. Thus, the 
combination of genes was shown to be associated neither with 
asthma susceptibility nor with the upregulation of the total se-
rum IgE levels. However, when tested for a Dp/Df-specific IgE, 
the combination of both the CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B -654C/ 
T polymorphisms displayed a marked difference in frequency 
between children with Dp/Df (-) asthma and those with Dp/Df 
(+) asthma and an increasing trend of Dp-specific IgE levels in 
those with asthma and Df-specific IgE levels in both those with 
asthma and children with atopic asthma. Similarly, we observed 
that the combination of the CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B E237G 
polymorphisms was associated with the increase in total IgE 
and Dp/Df-specific IgE levels, since the -654C/T and E237G poly-
morphisms of the FCER1B gene were in strong linkage disequi-
librium (data not shown). These results suggest an additive in-
fluence of the two genes on the increased levels of Dp/Df-spe-
cific IgE. 
While previous studies 
10 have demonstrated the synergistic 
influence of the CTLA4 and FCER1B genes on the total serum 
IgE levels, their effect on asthma susceptibility remains unin-
vestigated. While previous data demonstrated a CTLA4 -318C/ 
T polymorphism that was found to influence the total serum 
IgE levels, in this study, we detected a meaningful association 
only between the CTLA4 +49A/G polymorphism and the Dp/ 
Df-specific IgE levels, but no association with total serum levels. 
We also found that a combination of the CTLA4 and FCER1B 
polymorphisms upregulated the Dp/Df-specific IgE levels in 
contrast to previous work in the Japanese population, which </p>

<p>displayed a co-stimulatory effect on total IgE levels. The dis-
crepancies may be explained by variances in the study popula-
tion, number of subjects, or differences in the target single nu-
cleotide polymorphism (SNP). In particular, the observed dif-
ferences may have been due to genetic variations between the 
Japanese and Korean populations. 
The current study is not without its limitations. First, the study 
was performed only on a selected group of people with asthma 
(Korean children) and thus is not a full representation of the 
general Korean population. Second, despite many SNPs in the 
CTLA4 and FCER1B genes, only a single SNP in each gene was 
selected. We chose the CTLA4 +49A/G polymorphism since it 
has been more stringently investigated than the -318C/T poly-
morphism, and the combinations of the IL-13 +2044A/G and 
CTLA4 +49A/G were associated with log IgE levels (unpublished 
data). We considered three SNPs (-109C/T, -654C/T, and E237G) 
in the FCER1B gene, assuming that the -654C/T and -109C/T 
polymorphisms were in strong linkage disequilibrium in the 
Japanese population. 
12 We investigated the two polymorphisms 
(-654C/T and E237G), which displayed a strong linkage disequi-
librium (LD=0.971) meaning that the -654C/T polymorphism 
was present as a representative SNP of the FCER1B gene. Third, 
the genetic results obtained in this study are yet to be verified in 
vivo and as such, the expression genetics may vary in terms of 
being representative of the general population. However, as the 
current study only included subjects who were diagnosed by a 
physician with consistent inclusion criteria and a defined dis-
tinctive phenotype (including IgE and bronchial responsive-
ness), the findings may be more reliable than in previous stud-
ies in the Japanese population that used only adults possessing 
a confounding factor (e.g., smoking). 
In conclusion, the CTLA4 +49A/G and FCER1B -654C/T poly-
morphisms are not associated with development of asthma in 
Korean children. However, the +49A allele of CTLA4 may act to 
increase the Dp/Df-specific IgE levels and display an additive 
effect with the -654T allele of the FCER1B. Since Dp/Df appears 
to be an important factor facilitating the production of IgE, both 
the +49A and -654T alleles of the CTLA4 and FCER1B genes may 
regulate the production and signaling of Dp/Df-IgE, particular-
ly in Korean children with asthma. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant of the Korea Healthcare 
technology R&amp;D Project, Ministry for Health, Welfare and Fam-
ily Affairs, Republic of Korea (A084144). </p>



<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2010 April;2(2):127-133. doi: 10.4168/aair.2010.2.2.127 </p>

<p>CTLA4 Polymorphism and IgE Levels 
AAIR </p>





</text></tei>