<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2677872" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Mutational analysis of the histone H3 N-terminal 
region has shown it to play an important role both 
in chromatin function in vivo and nucleosome 
dynamics in vitro. Here we use a library of mutations 
in the H3 N-terminal region to investigate the 
contribution of this region to the action of the 
ATP-dependent remodelling enzymes Chd1, RSC 
and SWI/SNF. All of the enzymes were affected dif-
ferently by the mutations with Chd1 being affected 
the least and RSC being most sensitive. In addition 
to affecting the rate of remodelling by RSC, some 
mutations prevented RSC from moving nucleo-
somes to locations in which DNA was unravelled. 
These observations illustrate that the mechanisms 
by which different ATP-dependent remodelling 
enzymes act are sensitive to different features of 
nucleosome structure. They also show how altera-
tions to histones can affect the products generated 
as a result of ATP-dependent remodelling reactions. </p>

<p>Chromatin presents an obvious impediment to nuclear 
processes that require access to DNA. To counter this 
obstruction the eukaryotic cell has evolved mechanisms 
that alter chromatin structure and/or dynamics. An 
assortment of enzymes have been found to participate in 
gene regulation that act to post-translationally modify 
histone proteins (1). Several of these modifications, includ-
ing phosphorylation, acetylation and methylation have 
been shown at least in some cases to create epitopes that 
are specifically recognized by chromatin-binding proteins 
(2). However, it is also possible that a subset of chromatin 
modifications act to directly alter the biophysical pro-
perties of chromatin (3-5). A second class of enzyme 
acting to manipulate chromatin structure during gene 
regulation non-covalently reconfigures chromatin in </p>

<p>energy-consuming reactions (6). These ATP-dependent 
remodelling enzymes share homology with the superfamily 
2 group of helicase related proteins (7) and have been 
referred to as Snf2 family proteins as they share additional 
homology within the catalytic subunit of the SWI/SNF 
complex (8,9). There is likely to be interplay between 
these two classes of enzyme as many ATP-dependent 
remodelling enzymes are associated with protein motifs 
capable of recognizing histone modifications. 
To investigate this interplay we previously investigated 
the effects of histone truncation on ATP-dependent remo-
delling (10). This pointed to an important role for the 
histone H3 tail in nucleosome dynamics. A peptide liga-
tion approach was used to show that H3 K14 acetylation 
acted to direct recruitment of RSC complexes to chroma-
tin (11). Consistent with this H3 K14 acetylation is impor-
tant for RSC function (12). In addition to this specific 
effect on recruitment of RSC, point mutations in histone 
H3 were found to have a range of distinct effects on the 
dynamic properties of nuclesomes (10). In particular, it 
was found that mutation of the histone H3 aN helix 
could alter different aspects of the dynamic properties of 
nucleosomes such as inherent mobility, site exposure and 
histone dimer stability (10). 
Here we take advantage of this designer library of 
mutant nucleosomes to investigate how the dynamic 
properties of nucleosomes influence the action of ATP-
dependent remodelling enzymes. We find that modifica-
tions affecting different aspects of the nucleosome have 
specific effects on different remodelling enzymes, and 
that these can act to alter either the rate of remodelling 
or the products generated. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Chromatin assembly </p>

<p>Xenopus laevis histones were bacterially expressed, purified 
and assembled into tetramers and octamers, as 
appropriate, as described (13). Site-directed mutagenesis 
was performed using the Stratagene QuikChange Kit. </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: 01382 385796; Fax: 01382 388072; Email: t.a.owenhughes@dundee.ac.uk </p>

<p>ß 2009 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Nucleosomes were assembled by salt dialysis using an 
equilmolar ratio of octamer and purified PCR-amplified 
DNA fragments (14). The nomenclature used to define 
DNA fragments is aBc, with a and c are numbers that 
describe the upstream and downstream bp extensions, 
respectively. B is the nucleosome positioning sequence 
source, with A representing the MMTV nucleosome A 
(15). Fluorescently labelled oligos were from Eurogentec 
(Belgium) and unlabelled oligos from the Oligonucleotide 
Synthesis Laboratory (University of Dundee, UK). The 
oligo sequences to amplify the 54A18 fragment are 5 
0 TA 
TGTAAATGCTTATGTAAACCA and 5 
0 TACATCTA 
GAAAAAGGAGC; for the 54A0 fragment 5 
0 TATGTA 
AATGCTTATGTAAACCA and 5 
0 ATCAAAACTGTG 
CCGCAG. The PCR was purified by ion exchange 
chromatography using a 1.8-ml SOURCE 15Q (GE 
Healthcare) column. </p>

<p>Purification of chromatin-remodelling enzymes </p>

<p>Yeast strains TAP tagged for RSC (16) and SWI/SNF (17) 
were purified as described previously (11). 
A pGEX-6p plasmid containing the Saccharomyces 
cerevisiae CHD1 gene made by Daniel Ryan was trans-
formed into Rosette 2 cells (Novagen). 6 l of cells were 
grown in 2YT media (1.6% bactotryptone, 1.0% yeast 
extract, 0.5% NaCl, pH 7.5) to an A 600 of $0.6, induced 
with 0.4 mM IPTG and expressed at 258C overnight. All 
subsequent steps were performed at 48C. The cells were 
pelleted in a Beckman JS 4.2 rotor at 4000 r.p.m. for 
25 min, washed with 1 X PBS and re-suspended in 
120 ml of lysis buffer [20 mM Tris pH 7.5, 350 mM 
NaCl, 0.1% (v/v) Tween, 0.05% (v/v) 2-mercaptoethanol, 
2 mM E-64, 1 mM AEBSF, 1 mM pepstatin, 2.6 mM apro-
tinin], before freezing at -808C. The thawed cells were 
homogenized with a 30-cm 
3 dounce, followed by sonica-
tion with a Branson S450 digital sonicator at 30% inten-
sity using a 10-min cycle of 20 s ON, 30 s OFF and 
centrifugation in a Beckman JA-25.50 rotor at 31 000 g 
for 15 min. The supernatant was added to 300 ml 
TALON metal affinity resin (Clontech Laboratories 
Incorporated), followed by rotation for 2 h, before centi-
fugation in a Heraeus Megafuge 1.0 centrifuge (Thermos 
Fischer Scientific) at 300 g for 1 min. The beads were re-
suspended in lysis buffer and added to a 10-ml Poly-Prep 
column (BioRad). The column was washed with 20 ml of 
lysis buffer, followed by elution in 4 ml of lysis buffer with 
250 mM imidazole. The eluate was added to 600 ml of glu-
tathione Sepharose 4B beads (GE Healthcare) in a 10-ml 
Poly-Prep chromatography column and washed with 
10 ml of glutathione elution buffer [20 mM Tris pH 7.5, 
350 mM NaCl, 0.1% (v/v) Tween, 0.5 mM EDTA, 1 mM 
DTT]. The beads were rotated overnight with 2 ml glu-
tathione elution buffer containing 5 mg of precision pro-
tease. The eluate collected and the column washed with a 
further ml of glutathione elution buffer. The eluate was 
concentrated with a YM-50 Microcon spin concentrator 
(Millipore) at 14 000 g in a Eppendorf benchtop centrifuge 
to a 100 ml volume. The sample was dialysed for 2 h 
against storage buffer [20 mM Tris pH 7.5, 350 mM 
NaCl, 1 mM DTT, 0.1% (v/v) Tween, 10% (v/v) glycerol] </p>

<p>in a microdialysis apparatus (15) using 12 000-14 000-Da 
MWCO membrane (SpectraPor 2.1). The dialysed sample 
was aliquoted in 10 ml volumes and stored at -808C. </p>

<p>Nucleosome repositioning assays </p>

<p>Nucleosomes were assembled on 54A18 DNA fragments 
for RSC and SWI/SNF repositioning and 54A0 DNA 
fragments for Chd1 repositioning. Each 10 ml reaction 
contained 1 pmol of wild-type and mutant nucleosomes 
assembled on cy3 and cy5 labelled DNA, respectively, 
50 mM NaCl, 50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 3 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM 
ATP and the quantity of remodeller specified in figures. 
Samples were incubated in 0.2-ml thin walled PCR tubes 
(ABgene, UK) in an Eppendorf mastercycle with heated 
lid at 308C for the times specified in figures, before reac-
tion termination by transferal to ice and addition of 500 ng 
of HindIII-digested bacteriophage lambda competitor 
DNA (Promega, USA) and 5% (w/v) sucrose. Samples 
were resolved on a native polyacrylamide gel [5% acryla-
mide:bis acrylamide (49:1 ratio), 0.2 Â TBE buffer 
(0.5 mM EDTA, 22.3 mM Tris-borate, pH 8.3), 0.1% 
APS and 0.1% TEMED]. Gels were cast horizontally 
between 20 by 20-cm glass plates using 1.5-mm Teflon 
spacers, before mounting vertically in the gel apparatus 
(Thermo Fischer Scientific, USA) and pre-running at 
300 V for 3 h with continuous pump recirculation of 0.2 
Â TBE buffer between the upper and lower compartments 
at 48C. Gels were run at 300 V for 3.5 h and imaged using 
a Phosphoimager FLA-5100 (Fujifilm, Japan). Gel band 
intensities were quantitated using <rs id="software-0" type="software">AIDA</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Raytest</rs>, Germany). The proportion of nucleosomes repo-
sitioned was calculated as the intensity of the sum of all 
detectable products over the sum of the major initial posi-
tion plus products. In many assembly reactions a propor-
tion of nucleosomes are assembled at a minor assembly 
location marked as the P position (e.g. 
Ã in Figure 2A) (18). 
Including this band in the calculations was found not to 
significantly affect the determination of initial rates. 
In some histone mutants the proportion of nucleosomes 
assembled at the P position was altered, and some 
additional less abundant sites of deposition were also 
observed. However, again inclusion nucleosomes 
assembled at these locations was not found to significantly 
affect the comparison of initial rates. As a result, in the 
analysis presented here nucleosomes deposited at locations 
other than the major NucA locations are not in included 
in quantitation. For some mutations a small proportion of 
nucleosomes were observed to undergo thermal reposi-
tioning in control reactions lacking remodelling enzyme. 
However, this was generally detected after long incuba-
tions and the proportion of nucleosomes repositioned at 
early time points was low enough not to affect the calcu-
lation of initial rates. The reproducibility of the assay 
when carried out in this manner was found to be high 
(Supplementry Figure 1). 
In this way the proportion of nucleosomes repositioned 
is calculated independently of the total signal detectable in 
each lane. The initial rate was calculated as previously 
described (11). Each initial rate was repeated at least </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 8 2505 </p>

<p>three times using chromatin prepared in separate assembly 
reactions. </p>

<p>High-resolution nucleosome mapping </p>

<p>Nucleosomes for high-resolution site-directed mapping 
(H3 C110A, H4 S47C) were prepared as previously 
described (18). Each 10 ml reaction contained 4 pmol map-
ping nucleosome, 50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 50 mM KCl, 1 mM 
MgCl 2 and the RSC quantities specified in Figure 5. 
The samples were incubated at 308C for 2 h, before ter-
mination by the addition of 500 ng of HindIII-digested 
bacteriophage lambda competitor DNA (Promega) and 
incubation on ice. One microlitre of 33 nM and 333-nM 
ammonium ferrous sulphate was added to the no RSC 
control and RSC repositioned samples, respectively and 
incubated on ice for 10 min. One microlitre of the reaction 
was removed and resolved on a 5% native polyacrylamide 
gel. To the remaining sample, 5 ml of 19.2-mM ascorbic acid 
and 0.05% (v/v) hydrogen peroxide was added to each 
sample, followed by incubation on ice for 90 min. The reac-
tions were terminated by phenol:chloroform:isoamyl 
alcohol (25:24:1) extraction and ethanol precipitation. 
Each sample was re-suspended in 5 ml of mapping loading 
buffer (5 mM EDTA, 0.1% bromophenol blue in forma-
mide), heated at 908C for 3 min and loaded onto a sequenc-
ing gel [8% acrylamide:bis acrylamide (49:1 ratio), 8 M 
urea, 1 Â TBE, 0.1% APS and 0.1% TEMED]. The gels 
were pre-run using 1 L of boiling 1 Â TBE buffer until the 
temperature probe reached 508C. The gel was loaded 
immediately and run at 508C temperature, for 1.5-2 h. 
Fluorescent DNA markers for the 54A18 DNA fragment 
were created using a CycleReader Auto DNA Sequencing 
kit (Fermentas, Canada). The dideoxyribonucleotide 
sequencing products migrate 1 bp slower relative to the 
mapping cleavage products, as determined by examining 
the previously characterised +70 cleavage site for nucleo-
somes assembled on the 54A18 DNA fragments (19). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Histone H3 mutations have specific effects on nucleosome 
repositioning by Chd1 and RSC </p>

<p>A competitive repositioning assay was used to compare 
the initial rates at which mutated and wild-type nucleo-
somes are moved by RSC and Chd1 (10,11). This involves 
mixing equimolar amounts of wild-type and mutated 
nucleosomes assembled on cy3 and cy5 labelled DNA 
fragments, ATP and the appropriate amount of remodel-
ling enzyme at 308C, before reactions were stopped by the 
addition of excess competitor DNA. The reaction pro-
ducts were analysed on native polyacrylamide gels and 
the extent to which the wild-type and mutant nucleosomes 
are repositioned established through the use of selective 
filters. As Chd1 repositions mononucleosomes most effi-
ciently from positions close to DNA ends to more cen-
trally located positions (18), we used a DNA fragment 
that positions nucleosomes such that 54 bp is located on 
one side and none on the other (54A0). Native gel electro-
phoresis can be used to track the loss of nucleosomes 
form their initial location and accumulation at </p>

<p>destinations (Figure 1A). Quantitation enables the propor-
tion of nucleosomes moved to be tracked over a time 
course (Figure 1B). Approximately three-quarters of the 
histone mutations tested caused relatively minor changes 
of 25% or less to the initial rate (Figure 1C). The H3 H39A 
mutation caused the greatest effect on Chd1 repositioning 
with a 1.9-fold AE 0.1 (mean AE standard error of the mean) 
increase to the initial rate relative to wild-type controls 
(Figure 1A and B). These results suggest that Chd1 is 
not greatly affected by mutations in this region of H3. 
To determine whether the above effects were a property 
shared among all chromatin-remodelling enzymes we 
tested the ability of the RSC complex to reposition the 
H3 mutated nucleosomes. RSC and related SWI/SNF </p>

<p>Time (mins) 
Chd1 repositioned 
nucleosomes (%) </p>

<p>WT 
H3 H39A 
WT data 
H3 H39A data </p>

<p>Initial rate 1.9 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>4 
8 
1 6 
0 
1 2 
0 </p>

<p>Cy3 WT </p>

<p>Mins 
0 0 
1 2 
8 </p>

<p>Cy5 H3 H39A </p>

<p>4 
1 6 1 6 1 6 
0 </p>

<p>ATP </p>

<p>Chd1 
-
+ </p>

<p>+ 
-</p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
-</p>

<p>-
+ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>H3 mutations </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>Mean initial rate of Chd1 </p>

<p>repositioning </p>

<p>K56A 
R42A 
R40A 
R53A 
R52A 
R49A 
S57A 
P38A 
P43A 
T45A 
G44A 
V46A 
H39A 
Y41A 
Y54A 
L48A 
E50A 
I51A 
Q55A </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>Final </p>

<p>Initial </p>

<p>Final </p>

<p>Initial </p>

<p>Figure 1. Competitive repositioning of histone H3 mutations by Chd1. 
(A) A native polyacrylamide gel for a repositioning assay using wild-
type and H3 H39A nucleosomes assembled on 54A0 fragments, 6.9 
fmol Chd1 and incubation at 308C for the indicated times. (B) Chd1 
repositioned H3 H39A nucleosomes 1.9-fold AE 0.1 (mean AE standard 
error of the mean) faster than wild-type nucleosomes. The raw data 
from the repositioning assays are plotted as points, the average hyper-
bolic fit of the data is shown as a line. (C) The initial rate of Chd1 
repositioning is plotted for the histone H3 mutations. The dashed line 
marks an initial rate of 1. The error bars represent the standard error 
of the mean. WT, wild-type. </p>



<p>complexes reposition nucleosomes from central locations 
towards and up to 50 bp beyond the end of an MMTV 
nucA DNA fragment (19) and similar behaviour has been 
observed on other DNA fragments (20,21). For this 
reason, RSC repositioning was performed using nucleo-
somes assembled on 54A18 DNA fragments. The H3 
R42A and R49A mutations were observed to have the 
greatest effects with $2-fold increases in the initial rate 
of RSC repositioning relative to wild-type nucleosomes 
(Figure 2A and B). Comparison of the effects of mutations 
on the initial rates of RSC and Chd1 repositioning 
revealed many differences (Table 1). For example, the 
H3 P43A mutation caused a 1.6-fold reduction to the ini-
tial rate of Chd1 repositioning, whereas RSC repositioned 
this same nucleosome equivalently to wild-type controls. 
In contrast, the H3 I51A and Q55A mutations caused </p>

<p>1.7-and 1.4-fold decreases to the initial rate of RSC repo-
sitioning, but had far smaller effects on Chd1 action. 
Collectively, these results show that single alanine muta-
tions within the histone H3 N-terminal region cause 
different effects on the repositioning capabilities of the 
Chd1-and RSC-remodelling enzymes. </p>

<p>Histone mutations alter the products generated following 
remodelling with RSC </p>

<p>Typically, RSC repositions nucleosomes assembled on 
54A18 DNA fragments to three faster migrating bands 
on native PAGE gels (11), denoted as 1, 2 and 3 in 
order of increasing mobility (Figure 3). For wild-type 
nucleosomes the majority of nucleosomes accumulate 
with the intensity in band 2 &gt; band 1 &gt; band 3 
(Figure 3). Marked differences to this banding pattern 
were observed following repositioning of H3 mutated 
nucelosomes. For example, H3 G44A or T45A mutated 
nucleosomes are largely repositioned to band 1, with min-
imal nucleosomes present in either band 2 or band 3, 
whereas other H3 mutations such as H3 Y41A or K56A 
showed a pattern more similar to wild-type controls 
(Figure 3). 
In principle, these differences to the products observed 
could reflect either a slower rate of remodelling and the 
accumulation of intermediates or a genuine difference in 
the products generated. To investigate this further, reac-
tions were performed with higher concentrations of RSC 
over extended time courses. We observed that wild-type 
nucleosomes were initially converted to band 2, but 
at completion equivalent amounts of band 2 and band 
3 accumulated (Figure 4). Importantly, histone mutants 
showed distinct effects following prolonged remodelling. 
These effects were assigned into four main categories. 
Class 1 mutations, generated a similar distribution </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Time (mins) 
RSC repositioned 
nucleosomes (%) </p>

<p>WT 
H3 R49A 
WT data 
H3 R49A data </p>

<p>Initial rate 2.1 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Cy3 WT </p>

<p>0 0 
4 8 
3 2 </p>

<p>Cy5 H3 R49A </p>

<p>16 
64 64 64 
0 </p>

<p>ATP </p>

<p>RSC 
-
+ </p>

<p>+ 
-</p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
-</p>

<p>-
+ </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>H3 mutations </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>Mean initial rate of RSC 
repositioning </p>

<p>K56A 
R42A 
R40A 
R53A 
R52A 
R49A 
S57A 
P38A 
P43A 
T45A 
G44A 
V46A 
H39A 
Y41A 
Y54A 
L48A 
E50A 
I51A 
Q55A </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Mins </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Initial </p>

<p>Final </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Initial </p>

<p>Final </p>

<p>Figure 2. Histone H3 mutations differentially affect RSC repositioning. 
(A) Native polyacrylamide gel displaying repositioning of wild-type and 
H3 R49A nucleosomes assembled on 54A18 fragments by 0.44 fmol 
RSC at 308C for the indicated times. Asterisk denotes P position. 
(B) RSC repositioned H3 R49A nucleosomes 2.1-fold AE 0.1 faster 
than wild-type nucleosomes. The raw data of the repositioning assays 
are shown as points, the curved line represents the average hyperbolic 
equation fit. (C) The initial rates of RSC repositioning for the histone 
H3 mutations. The dashed line indicates an initial rate of 1. Error bars 
represent the standard error of the mean. WT, wild-type. </p>

<p>Table 1. Effects of histone mutations on repositioning by RSC and 
Chd1 </p>

<p>Mutation 
Initial rate of 
Rsc respositioning </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Initial rate of Chd1 
respositioning </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>H3 P38A 
1.3 AE 0.1 
1.0 AE 0.05 
H3 H39A 
1.4 AE 0.05 
1.9 AE 0.1 
H3 R40A 
1.3 AE 0.1 
1.1 AE 0.02 
H3 Y41A 
1.5 AE 0.2 
0.8 AE 0.05 
H3 R42A 
2.2 AE 0.3 
1.4 AE 0.1 
H3 P43A 
1.1 AE 0.05 
0.6 AE 0.05 
H3 G44A 
1.7 AE 0.1 
0.9 AE 0.01 
H3 T45A 
1.6 AE 0.1 
1.2 AE 0.1 
H3 V46A 
0.9 AE 0.05 
0.9 AE 0.05 
H3 L48A 
1.1 AE 0.05 
0.8 AE 0.05 
H3 R49A 
2.1 AE 0.1 
1.2 AE 0.05 
H3 E50A 
1.2 AE 0.1 
0.9 AE 0.05 
H3 I51A 
0.6 AE 0.1 
0.8 AE 0.05 
H3 R52A 
1.2 AE 0.1 
0.9 AE 0.1 
H3 R53A 
1.1 AE 0.1 
0.8 AE 0.1 
H3 Y54A 
1.3 AE 0.2 
0.9 AE 0.05 
H3 Q55A 
0.7 AE 0.1 
1.1 AE 0.05 
H3 K56A 
1.2 AE 0.1 
0.9 AE 0.05 
H3 S57A 
1.4 AE 0.2 
0.8 AE 0.05 
H3 K56Q 
1.3 AE 0.1 
ND </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Each value represents the mean AE SEM. ND, not determined. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 8 2507 </p>

<p>to wild-type. Class 2 mutations, such as H3 K56A, dis-
played increased accumulation of band 1. Class 3 muta-
tions, such as H3 R40A, were under-represented for band 
2 and class 4 mutations, such as H3 I51A, showed the most 
marked differences to wild-type controls with the majority 
of nucleosomes only converted to band 1 (Figure 4). </p>

<p>H3 I51A prevents RSC from unravelling nucleosomes </p>

<p>In order to characterize the products generated following 
remodelling of the different histone mutations, we 
employed site-directed hydroxyl radical mapping (22). 
Briefly, this involves the incorporation of cysteaminyl 
EDTA at H4 S47C, a residue that is close to the DNA 
at the nucleosome dyad axis. Ferrous ions, ascorbic acid 
and hydrogen peroxide are added to produce a localized 
Fenton reaction at the EDTA derivative. The resulting 
hydroxyl radicals cleave strongly at a single proximal 
DNA site and more weakly at 7 and 8 bp away on each 
DNA strand. This characteristic cleavage pattern can be 
used to determine the position of the nucleosomal dyad 
axis at base-pair resolution (22). </p>

<p>Site-directed mapping showed increasing amounts 
of RSC progressively remove control nucleosomes 
(H4 S47C) away from the +70 position. Nucleosomes 
appear at new locations up to 111 bp along the longer 
arm (Figure 5, lanes 3, 7-9). This involves moving the 
nucleosome to locations in which DNA is removed from 
one side of the histone octamer as has been described 
previously (19-21). These results suggest that for wild-type 
nucleosomes the faster migrating products on native 
PAGE gels correspond to nucleosomes being repositioned 
by RSC to a series of locations on what was originally the 
longer linker DNA arm (Figure 5). 
In contrast, repositioning of H3 I51A nucleosomes 
(a Class 4 mutation), resulted in accumulation at only 
a subset of the locations observed for wild-type nucleo-
somes. The major positions observed are at +27, +26 
and +22, which correspond to the edge of the nucleosome 
being positioned at 11, 10 and 6 bp from the end of the 
DNA fragment (Figure 5 lanes 5, 11-13). Although wild-
type nucleosomes were moved to a series of positions 
beyond this in which from 2 to 57 bp of DNA are removed 
from the edge of the nucleosome, these locations are all </p>

<p>Cy5 H3 G44A </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>Cy5 H3 T45A </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>Cy5 H3 K56A </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>Cy5 H3 Y41A </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>Cy3 WT </p>

<p>Cy3 WT </p>

<p>Cy3 WT </p>

<p>Cy3 WT </p>

<p>Figure 3. Histone H3 mutations alter banding patterns following remodelling with RSC. When nucleosomes that have been remodelled by RSC 
(0.44 fmol) are separated on a native polyacrylamide gel three faster migrating species can be detected. These are labelled 1, 2 and 3. Nucleosomes H3 
G44A and T45A were predominantly relocated to band 1 after a 64-min incubation at 308C, in contrast wild-type nucleosomes were relocated 
equally to bands 1 and 2. Repositioning of mutations H3 K56A and Y41A produced a similar banding pattern relative to wild-type. Note band 3 
represents a doublet in some gels. WT, wild-type. </p>



<p>under-represented for I51A nucleosomes. The single pre-
dominant band on native PAGE gels observed following 
remodelling of H3 I51A nucleosomes corresponds to the 
co-migration of nucleosomes at a subset of locations in 
which DNA remains fully wrapped. </p>

<p>Comparison of remodelling by RSC and SWI/SNF </p>

<p>The SWI/SNF complex has a similar subunit composition 
to RSC. The catalytic subunits Snf2 and Sth1 share several 
sequence motifs as do other members of the complexes 
(23). Biochemical characterization of the activities of 
these complexes has also suggested they function similarly 
(19,24,25). In order to investigate whether interactions 
with histone H3 affect the action of these enzymes simi-
larly, the products of remodelling reactions driven by 
SWI/SNF were resolved by native PAGE and assigned 
to one of four classes as described for RSC. 
Interestingly, the extent to which each of the mutations 
affects the two remodelling complexes differs. For 
instance, a marked difference is observed between the pro-
ducts generated following remodelling of H3 I51A nucleo-
somes by RSC and SWI/SNF. While RSC generates 
predominantly band 1 (Figure 6A), SWI/SNF remodelling 
results in more of band 3. A difference between RSC and </p>

<p>SWI/SNF repositioning is also observed for the H3 Q55A 
mutant nucleosomes (Figure 6A). Despite the qualitative 
difference in the products generated by these enzymes, the 
rates at which SWI/SNF and RSC remodel I51A nucleo-
somes are comparable (Figure 6B and C) with the initial 
rates of remodelling being reduced by 0.6-fold in compar-
ison to wild-type nucleosomes in both cases (data 
not shown). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The ability to manipulate the coding sequence of histone 
genes together with the expression and assembly of these 
proteins in vitro provides an opportunity to monitor the 
direct effects of these mutations on chromatin dynamics. 
We have identified differences in the sensitivities of chro-
matin-remodelling enzymes to mutations affecting differ-
ent aspects of nucleosome structure. This indicates there 
are differences in the underlying mechanisms by which 
even closely related enzymes act. 
We observed that remodelling by the enzyme Chd1, 
was affected very little in terms of either the products 
generated or the rates at which nucleosomes were reposi-
tioned (Figure 7B; Table 1). Although the initial rate of </p>

<p>1 
3 
0 </p>

<p>Intensity </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>Class 1 
3.52 
1.18 
0.44 </p>

<p>RSC (fmole) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>* 
0 </p>

<p>Intensity </p>

<p>RSC 
-
-</p>

<p>H3 K56A </p>

<p>Class 2 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>* 
0 </p>

<p>H3 R40A </p>

<p>Class 3 </p>

<p>Band </p>

<p>Intensity </p>

<p>H3 I51A </p>

<p>Class 4 </p>

<p>Bands 1 and 2 
predominate at lower 
RSC concentrations </p>

<p>Reduced accumulation 
of band 2 </p>

<p>Majority of nucleosomes 
only converted to band 1 </p>

<p>Band </p>

<p>Intensity </p>

<p>1 
0 
3 
2 
* </p>

<p>Band 
1 
0 
3 
2 
* </p>

<p>Band 
1 
0 
3 
2 
* </p>

<p>1 
3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>* 
0 </p>

<p>Figure 4. The effect of H3 mutations on the end products of RSC directed remodelling. To drive remodelling reactions towards completion, reactions 
were performed for 2 h at 308C with increasing concentrations of RSC as indicated. The products were separated into one of four classes dependent 
on the distribution pattern of the repositioned products (bands 1, 2 and 3). Wild-type nucleosomes represent class 1, H3 K56A nucleosomes class 2, 
H3 R40A nucleosomes class 3 and H3 I51A nucleosomes class 4. The band intensities of the RSC remodelled nucleosomes are plotted in the graph to 
the right of each respective native polyacrylamide gel. Band 0, main initial nucleosome position. Asterisk denotes P position. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 8 2509 </p>

<p>remodelling by RSC was affected to a greater extent than 
Chd1 the magnitude of the effects remained low, with the 
maximum effect being 2.2-fold (Figure 7E). This indicates 
that both enzymes were able to engage and reposition 
nucleosomes efficiently. Consistent with this the binding 
of RSC to nucleosomes bearing the H3 E50A, I51A and 
Q55A mutations was equivalent to wild-type nucleosomes 
(Supplementary Figure 2). The limited effects of these 
mutations on the rate of nucleosome sliding by RSC and 
Chd1 contrasts with the more substantial effects these 
mutations were observed to have on spontaneous thermal 
nucleosome repositioning (compare Figure 7B, E and F). 
This lack of correlation is likely to reflect significant </p>

<p>differences in the mechanisms for thermal and ATP-
dependent nucleosome repositioning. 
In contrast to the limited effects on the initial rates of 
remodelling, the outcome of RSC remodelling reactions 
was affected dramatically with many mutations altering 
the spectrum of products generated (Figure 7C). A related 
but less dramatic effect was observed with the SWI/SNF 
complex (Figure 7D). While RSC repositions wild-type 
nucleosomes to a series of locations in which the nucleo-
some dyad is so close to the edge of the DNA fragment 
that up to 57 bp of DNA are removed from one edge of 
the nucleosome, these locations were under-represented 
when H3 I51A mutant nucleosomes were used as a </p>

<p>41 
31 </p>

<p>54 
18 </p>

<p>+26 
+27 </p>

<p>+70 </p>

<p>+47 </p>

<p>+22 </p>

<p>+14 
+16 </p>

<p>+7 </p>

<p>-24 </p>

<p>-41 </p>

<p>+0 </p>

<p>+42 </p>

<p>46 
26 </p>

<p>62/61 
10/11 </p>

<p>66 
6 </p>

<p>74/72 
-2/0 </p>

<p>81 
-9 </p>

<p>88 
-16 </p>

<p>112 
-40 </p>

<p>129 
-57 </p>

<p>0 128 
128 
0 </p>

<p>+ 
-
-+ 
-
-
128 
0 
128 
0 </p>

<p>0 128 
128 
0 </p>

<p>RSC 
+ 
-
-+ 
-
-
128 
0 
128 
0 
Mins </p>

<p>RSC 
Mins </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 
Lane^M 
6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 
5 </p>

<p>WT H3 I51A 
WT 
H3 I51A </p>

<p>Figure 5. RSC redistributes H3 I51A nucleosomes to a subset of locations. The base-pair locations of RSC repositioned nucleosomes on the 54A18 
fragment were determined by site-directed hydroxyl radical mapping. At top, sequencing gels. M, guanine marker of the 54A18 fragment, lane 1. No 
RSC controls, lanes 2, 4, 6 and 10. Repositioning of nucleosomes at 308C for 128 min using 10 fmol RSC, lanes 7, 11; 83 fmol RSC, lanes 8, 12; and 
660 fmol RSC, lanes 3, 5, 9 and 13. The cleavage products and an illustration of nucleosome locations (black ovals initial locations, clear ovals RSC 
redistributed locations) on the 54A18 DNA fragment are shown alongside the sequencing gels. At bottom, the corresponding native polyacrylamide 
gel.^(caret sign), non-specific bands. WT, wild-type mapping nucleosomes. </p>



<p>substrate (Figure 5). This means that the mechanics of 
moving nucleosomes to locations in which DNA is unra-
velled differ from those involved in repositioning within 
the confines of a DNA fragment. 
It is notable that there is a good correlation between 
residues that have strong effects on thermally driven 
nucleosome positioning and the inability of RSC to 
move nucleosomes into positions where DNA is unra-
velled (compare Figure 7C and F). At first this appears 
to be counterintuitive as nucleosomes that are inherently 
more mobile cannot be repositioned so effectively by RSC. 
However, it is also true that the H3 E50A, I51A and Q55A 
mutations reduce the stability of histone octamers (10; 
data not shown). One model for RSC action involves 
the RSC complex drawing DNA over the surface of 
nucleosomes while remaining bound to the histone octa-
mer in a fixed orientation (26). The reduction to octamer 
stability resulting from the H3 E50A, I51A and Q55A 
mutations might result in the octamer rather than the </p>

<p>DNA being distorted as a result of ATP hydrolysis. 
Furthermore, as RSC starts to move nucleosomes to loca-
tions in which DNA is unravelled from their surface, the 
overall loss of histone contacts will require the ATPase 
motor within the RSC complex to exert greater forces. 
Indeed, it has been estimated that a force of 3 pN will 
be required to dissociate each helical contact (27). The 
increased forces that are applied during DNA unravelling 
might drive a reconfiguration of the histone octamer that 
prevents any further repositioning. This could explain why 
RSC is able to move nucleosomes to positions where his-
tone DNA contacts are retained, but not to locations 
where DNA is unravelled. In this case the reason why 
Chd1 is not affected in the same way could be simply that 
the repositioning of nucleosomes to more central locations 
does not involve unravelling DNA to the same extent. 
Having observed that mutations to the H3 aN region of 
the nucleosome can affect the outcome of remodelling 
reactions, it will be of interest to investigate whether his-
tone modifications exert similar effects. Our own prelimi-
nary observations made using mutations designed to 
mimic a selection of modifications known to occur in 
this region of the nucleosome revealed only subtle effects 
on the action of ATP-dependent remodelling enzymes 
(data not shown). It is possible that the use of amnio 
acid substitutions is not a sufficiently accurate mimic for 
post-translational modifications and hopefully the devel-
opment of new technologies will allow the effect of histone 
modifications within the globular core of nucleosomes 
to be tested directly (28). Nonetheless, our observations 
illustrate a principle by which alterations to the structure 
of nucleosomes can selectively affect the outcome of remo-
delling reactions. It is of special note that the unravelling 
of DNA is affected as this might be anticipated to affect 
the ability of enzymes to catalyse octamer removal by 
collision (26). As a result these observations expand the 
repertoire of different means by which post-translational 
modification of histones can potentially exert effects on 
chromatin dynamics (3). </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We would like to thank Helder Ferreira, Andrew Flaus, 
Daniel Ryan and other members of the TOH lab for 
useful discussion. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>The Todd Foundation Awards for Excellence, William 
Georgetti Scholarship, ORSAS, Fellow of New Zealand 
federation of graduate women (to J.S.); and a Wellcome 
Trust senior research fellowship (064414 to T.O.H.). 
Funding for open access charge: Wellcome Trust award 
to the University of Dundee. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>

<p>Mins 
0 </p>

<p>RSC </p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>H3 I51A </p>

<p>H3 Q55A </p>

<p>1 
3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 
3 </p>

<p>0 
1 
3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>128 
0 </p>

<p>SWI/SNF </p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>128 </p>

<p>Mins 
0 0 
4 8 
32 
16 
64 64 64 
0 </p>

<p>ATP (1 mM) </p>

<p>RSC (0.44 fmole) </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>Cy3 WT </p>

<p>Cy5 H3 I51A </p>

<p>Mins 
0 0 
8 16 
64 
32 
128 128 128 
0 </p>

<p>ATP (1 mM) </p>

<p>Swi/Snf (30 fmole) </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Cy3 WT </p>

<p>Cy5 H3 I51A </p>

<p>1 
3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Initial </p>

<p>Final </p>

<p>Initial </p>

<p>Final </p>

<p>Figure 6. Differences observed between RSC and SWI/SNF end pro-
ducts. (A) Repositioning of 1 pmol of H3 I51A and Q55A mutant 
nucleosomes by 0.44, 1.18 or 3.52 fmol RSC showed a preferential 
accumulation in band 1 on native polyacrylamide gels. In contrast, 
repositioning of 0.5 pmol of mutant nucleosomes with 10, 20 or 
60 fmol of SWI/SNF showed repositioning to band 3. Band 0, main 
initial position. (B) RSC and (C) SWI/SNF repositioning of H3 I51A 
nucleosomes. Asterisk denotes P position, not present in either muta-
tion. WT, wild-type. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 8 2511 </p>



<p>H2A C-terminal 
extension </p>

<p>DNA entry gyre </p>

<p>H4 α1 helix </p>

<p>DNA central gyre </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>1.3 
nd 
1.9 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>5.4 
9.2 </p>

<p>1.7 </p>

<p>1.2 
2.5 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>4.0 
2.0 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>3.6 </p>

<p>1.1 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>2.7 
1.7 </p>

<p>Thermal initial rate </p>

<p>1.3 
nd 
1.4 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.7 
0.6 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.1 
2.1 </p>

<p>1.1 </p>

<p>1.2 
0.9 </p>

<p>1.1 </p>

<p>1.7 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.3 </p>

<p>2.2 
1.6 </p>

<p>RSC initial rate </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>T 
R </p>

<p>R 
R </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>P 
V </p>

<p>G 
A </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>Q </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>44 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>52 </p>

<p>53 
46 </p>

<p>47 </p>

<p>48 </p>

<p>49 </p>

<p>54 </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>56 </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>H3 αN helical map </p>

<p>RSC products generated </p>

<p>2 
nd 
2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 
4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 
2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 
3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 
3 </p>

<p>Swi/Snf products generated </p>

<p>2 
nd 
2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 
3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 
2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 
3 </p>

<p>Chd1 initial rate </p>

<p>0.9 
nd 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1.1 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>0.8 
1.2 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 
0.9 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.1 </p>

<p>1.4 
1.2 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>Figure 7. Remodelling enzymes are distinctly affected by histone H3 mutations. (A) The histone H3 aN helical map, introduced in ref. 10. This map 
allows the impact of each interaction surface to be compared among the different remodellers. (B) The initial rate of Chd1 repositioning. (C) The 
distribution of the end products after RSC repositioning, class 1-4 (see Figure 4 for description of classes). (D) The distribution of end products after 
SWI/SNF, classes 1-4. (E) The initial rate of RSC repositioning. (F) The initial rate of thermal repositioning, values from ref. 10, except for H3 
E50A where remeasurement detected a difference from the previously published value. </p>





<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 8 2513 </p>

</text></tei>