<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2815316" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>A diet habit, which is developed in childhood, lasts for a life time. In this sense, nutrition education and early exposure to healthy menus in 
childhood is important. Children these days have easy access to the internet. Thus, a web-based nutrition education program for children is an 
effective tool for nutrition education of children. This site provides the material of the nutrition education for children with characters which are 
personified nutrients. The 151 menus are stored in the site together with video script of the cooking process. The menus are classified by the 
criteria based on age, menu type and the ethnic origin of the menu. The site provides a search function. There are three kinds of search conditions 
which are key words, menu type and "between" expression of nutrients such as calorie and other nutrients. The site is developed with the operating 
system Windows 2003 Server, the web server ZEUS 5, development language JSP, and database management system Oracle 10 g. </p>

<p>Childhood is a critical time of human development. The most 
common nutrition-related problems among children include 
under-nutrition, iron-deficiency anemia, dental caries, high blood 
lipid profile, overweight and obesity (Boyle, 2003). In 2003, the 
Korea president announced the First Year of Children's Safety. 
Since then, the government has promoted various polices in order 
to enhance children's health. However, they appear to lack a 
comprehensive vision or systematic development of action plans. 
The eating habits which developed in childhood greatly affect 
one's lifelong habits and health. Besides, the education to provide 
information on food safety and nutrition has not been adequate. 
Improper dietary habits and unhealthy life styles may have 
resulted in a radical increase in producing number of overweight 
and obese children and teenagers. The Korea National Health 
&amp; Nutrition Survey 2005 revealed that over the past seven years, 
there has been a significant 1.5-fold increase in the number of 
overweight boys and girls under 18 years of age. And dietary 
intakes of children were deficient in calcium and potassium. In 
contrast, the intakes of protein and sodium were becoming </p>

<p>excessive (Department of Health and Welfare &amp; Korea Health 
Industry Development Institute, 2006). 
Nutrition education for children is valuable in changing dietary 
behaviors and promoting health, considering that good eating 
behavior formed in childhood would continue to later life. Some 
off-line programs on menu planning and nutrition analysis have 
been developed and used (Han, 1997; Hong, 1989; Hong, 1996; 
Joni, 1983; Kang et al., 1999; Kolasa &amp; Miller, 1996). The use 
of internet has become popular in Korea. Those who use internet 
reached 75% in 2006; of those aged 6-19 years, 98.5% used 
the internet (National Internet Development Agency of Korea 
&amp; Ministry of Information Communication Republic of Korea, 
2007). So, needs for web-based contents have been rapidly 
increasing in educational fields. "Diet and meal management" 
of lecture contents and software system for web-based nutritional 
assessment and counseling (Youn, 2001) were researched. The 
Korean Society of Community Nutrition, Nutrition Education 
Center of Ulsan University, The Korean Food &amp; Nutrition 
Society and KFDA are running internet-based nutrition education 
programs. Some web-based programs for nutrition were deve-
loped (Han, 2000; Han &amp; Jeong, 2004; Her &amp; Lee, 2002; Her </p>

<p>* This study was supported by Research Funds of Korea Food and Drug Administration. 
 § Corresponding Author: Soon-Myung Hong, Tel. 82-52-259-2374, Fax. 82-52-259-1496, Email. smhong@ulsan.ac.kr </p>

<p>Soon-Myung Hong et al. </p>



<p>Table 1. Web server system </p>

<p>Operating system 
Windows 2003 server </p>

<p>Web server 
Zeus </p>

<p>Language 
JSP, JavaScript </p>

<p>Database 
Oracle 10g </p>

<p>Table 2. Healthy menu DB classification </p>

<p>Healthy menu </p>

<p>Classification 
Infant 
Child 
Adolescent 
Total </p>

<p>Main dish 
28 
29 
28 
85 </p>

<p>Side dish 
15 
14 
15 
44 </p>

<p>Dessert 
7 
8 
7 
22 </p>

<p>Total 
50 
51 
50 
151 </p>

<p>Menu type 
Infant 
Child 
Adolescent 
Total </p>

<p>Korean food 
21 
18 
17 
56 </p>

<p>Western food 
22 
22 
22 
66 </p>

<p>Chinese food 
5 
6 
4 
15 </p>

<p>Japanese food 
1 
3 
4 </p>

<p>Asian food 
1 
2 
7 
10 </p>

<p>Total 
50 
51 
50 
151 </p>

<p>&amp; Lee, 2003a; Her &amp; Lee, 2003b; Hong &amp; Kim, 2005; Kim 
&amp; Yoon, 1999; Lee et al., 2002) and also a food exchange 
program (Hong et al., 2004). But it is limited to adults and not 
easy for an inexperienced person. Those of the program have 
to be developed for wider groups of people. Needs for nutrition 
education of children are increasing and related resources are 
essential (Park et al., 2006; Shin et al., 2006). Internet could 
be a useful route for children to provide nutrition information 
and educational messages. Many kinds of topics or methods 
might be effectively applied, in designing and planning nutrition 
web-sites or planning education programs, for example cooking 
or selecting snacks, flash animation with nutrition messages. 
Nutrition web-sites for children should be constructed in a way 
that children find the sites easily and search the contents for 
fun (Ahn et al., 2007; Ahn &amp; Kim, 2007). So, we tried to make 
kid-friendly web-based nutrition education searching system for 
healthy menu recipe and easily learned nutrition information with 
a lot of searching methods. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>The implementation of the system </p>

<p>This system is on the operating system the Windows 2003 
Server, which is Zeus. The languages for the development of 
this site are Java Server Page and Java Script. It does not make 
use of <rs type="software">ActiveX</rs> and only uses HTML because the site with 
<rs type="software">ActiveX</rs> functions can be in operation with a particular browser. 
The meal plan and nutrition evaluation go through complicated 
procedures and calculation processes. This is why the deve-
lopment procedures are important. The site is based on MVC 
Model2 (Model View Controller Pattern). The DBMS is Oracle 
10 g. The content is shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>Construction of web contents </p>

<p>The web contents contain introductions of a home-page, the 
menu of three age groups (infants, children and adolescents) and 
menu search. The contents are menu pictures, cooking methods, 
macro nutrients and sodium levels, video scripts of cooking 
courses, close-up of menu pictures, exchange of weight and 
printing. </p>

<p>The DB structure </p>

<p>The DB (Database) of the system consists of 4 segments. They 
are healthy menu DB, food nutrient DB, nutrition intake guideline </p>

<p>DB and nutrient guideline DB. Healthy menu DB is developed 
in the sub-project of this research. It is shown in Table 2. Food 
nutrient DB is based on the 7th food table of 2006 of National 
Rural Living Science Institute. Nutrition intake guideline DB is 
based on the data of The Korean Nutrition Society 2005. Nutrient 
Daily Value guideline DB is based on the data of KFDA 2007. </p>

<p>Menu searching method </p>

<p>Users can search by the title of a menu, ingredients, menu 
types (main dish, dessert), ethnic food and each nutrient. With 
those searching conditions, the screen can show recipe, video 
script, food data of menu and nutrients. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Contents and search function </p>

<p>The site of the department of nutritional evaluation in Korea 
Food and Drug Administration (http://nutrition.kfda.go.kr) is Fig. 
1, which is involved in a banner for children's healthy menus. 
The contents of this children's healthy menus site are classified 
into four groups. The first is introduction of this home page. 
It explains the overall introduction of this site. The second page 
contains the information of menus for infants, children and 
adolescents (Fig. 2). This part contains all information which 
users want to get by a search function. The third part provides 
a search function so that users can find the information which 
they need. The users specify search conditions. Types of the 
conditions are menu name, raw material of a menu, types of 
menus such as main dish, side dish and dessert, many kinds of 
ethnic menu such as Korean food, Chinese food, Japanese food, 
Western style food, Southeast Asian food, nineteen nutrients and 
calories and so on. The fourth part, <rs type="software">NutriEval</rs>, is like this site. 
The <rs type="software">NutriEval</rs> is another web-based program for meal plan 
drafting and nutrition evaluation. It is an independent program 
itself. It will be discussed in another chance. </p>



<p>Web-based nutrition education and healthy menu for children </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Home page of the department of nutritional evaluation, Korea Food and 
Drug Administration (http://nutrition.kfda.go.kr) </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Page containing the information of menus for infants, children and 
adolescents </p>

<p>Fig. 3. The introduction of home page </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Cali and Friends page </p>

<p>Introduction of home page </p>

<p>This introduction page summarizes the whole site. Fig. 3 is 
the technical introduction of the home page. This is the page 
which has links to the contents classified into eight groups. They 
are "Cali and Friends", "Food Pyramid", "Nutrition Safari", 
"Guideline of Diet Plan", "Guideline of Nutrition Intake", 
"Guideline of Nutrition Ingredient", "Nutrition Manifest" and 
"NutriEval". </p>

<p>Cali and friends as nutrient nicknames </p>

<p>"Cali" means Calorie. Because this site is focused on children, 
the terminology had better be familiar and easy to use and 
pronounce for children. For this reason, some of the nutrients 
are given an alias, gender and character. Children learn the 
nutrients by playing with the alias. The aliases are "Cali", 
"Carbo", "Pro", "Lipi", "Mine" and "Vita". They are associated 
with "Calorie and Energy", "Carbohydrate", "Protein", "Lipid, </p>

<p>Fats and Oil", "Mineral" and "Vitamin", correspondingly. Fig. 
4 is the "Cali and Friends" page. </p>

<p>Nutrition safari </p>

<p>In this page, children learn the importance of nutrients by a 
"safari tour". The contents consist of two parts. One is "nutrition 
café" and the other is "nutrition villages". Fig. 5 is the page 
of the "nutrition safari". 
Nutrition café: Children learn what nutrients do in their bodies. 
In addition to the functions of nutrients, the children learn the 
reason why they have to eat well-balanced foods and how to 
eat healthy foods. Fig. 6 is the page of "Nutrition café". 
Nutrition villages: There are eight villages. They are "Carbo-
hydrate", "Protein", "Lipid", "Mineral", "Vitamin", "Fiber", 
'Water" and "Calorie". Children learn what nutrients do in their 
bodies by visiting the villages. They also learn the food in which 
the nutrients are abundant. Fig. 7 is the page of "Carbohydrate" 
village, one of the eight villages. </p>

<p>Soon-Myung Hong et al. </p>



<p>Fig. 5. Nutrition safari page </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Nutrition café page </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Nutrition café page of "Protein village" </p>

<p>Fig. 8. Food tower page </p>

<p>Food tower </p>

<p>This page provides the amount and types of foods which are 
consumed in a daily meal (Fig. 8). Each layer of the food guide 
tower shows in turn to the upper step that nutrients should be 
taken in lesser amounts. There are four layers. The function of 
each layer's food type is explained. The symptom is also 
explained when each layer's nutrition is over-eaten or is deficient 
in a body. </p>

<p>Guideline of diet plan </p>

<p>This page gives the guidelines of diet plan for the age groups, 
infants, children and adolescents (Fig. 9). For each age group, 
there are seven recommendations by their age and critical 
nutrition education and the characters which are the alias of 
important nutrients. </p>

<p>Guideline of dietary reference intakes (DRIs) for Koreans </p>

<p>On this page, users will learn why guidelines of a diet plan </p>

<p>are so important (Fig. 10). There are four criteria in the guideline, 
which are average, recommended, sufficient and upper limit 
amount (DRIs, Korean Nutrition Society 2005). In the nutrition 
intake table, users can find the most appropriate criteria of the 
four criteria for them because those kinds of criteria are different 
by the age, gender and nutrient needs. </p>

<p>Guideline of nutrients daily value (DV) </p>

<p>The guideline of nutrients is the representative value for each 
ingredient. The value is applied to the all kinds of foods except 
the group under the age of four, pregnant women and breast 
feeding women. It is guideline of labeling of nutrient of processed 
foods in terms of the percentile expression (Fig. 11) and it's 
getting important for nutrition assessment and health care to 
prevent an epidemiologic obesity trend. </p>

<p>Guideline of nutrition labeling </p>

<p>This page contains the information on the nutrition label (Fig. 
12). The users learn why nutrition labeling is important, how </p>

<p>118 </p>

<p>Web-based nutrition education and healthy menu for children </p>

<p>Fig. 9. Guideline page of diet plan </p>

<p>Fig. 10. Guideline page of dietary reference intakes (DRIs) </p>

<p>Fig. 11. Guideline of nutrients daily value (DV) </p>

<p>Fig. 12. Guideline of nutrition labeling </p>

<p>nutrition labeling with each food is interpreted and how the 
nutrition amount is used for their health. </p>

<p>Menu search classification and recipe contents </p>

<p>This site contains menus for the infants, children and ado-
lescents. The menus are classified into groups by the criteria of 
age, menu type, and ethnic origin of menu. The items of menu 
type are main dish, side dish, dessert, etc. The items of ethnic 
menus are Korean food, Chinese food, Japanese food, Western 
style food, Southeast Asian food, etc. This information also is 
searched by the search function. Fig. 13 is the page showing 
the main dish for infants. There are screen scripts showing the 
cooking process of a menu (Fig. 14). There is also a trans-
formation program which modifies the weights of raw materials 
of a menu according to the change of weight of a certain raw 
material of the menu. Fig. 15 shows a cooking course with video 
script. </p>

<p>Search function </p>

<p>This site provides the search function which finds a menu under 
a certain condition. It comes from 151 menus developed by the 
sub-project in association with this research. The search 
conditions are classified into three categories based on the 
contents of the sub-expression. 
The first one is the key word expression. The search content 
expressions of the combination of the name of menu, name of 
food materials, age group, menu type, menu style and nutrients. 
The site accommodates the both the Korean and English names. 
Fig. 16 is the menu search page whose search condition is 
pumpkin. The second one is the "between" expression of the 
lower bound and the upper bound of a certain nutrition ingredient 
such as calorie and other nutrients. The absence of either of the 
bound expressions means the value higher than the lower bound 
value or the value lower than the upper bound. Fig. 17 is the 
result of menu search. If we chose pumpkin as the title of menu, 
we can the result of pumpkin menu and then, we can click wider 
picture, recipe, video script, raw material of menu, nutrient and 
specific capture. </p>

<p>Soon-Myung Hong et al. </p>



<p>Fig. 13. Page showing main dish list for infants </p>

<p>Fig. 14. Menu recipe sample </p>

<p>Fig. 15. Menu recipe with Video script </p>

<p>Fig. 16. Menu search page whose search condition is a pumpkin </p>

<p>Fig. 17. Result of search of pumpkin </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This research aims to develop healthy menus during childhood 
and making it available to the public. For this goal, the web-based 
program is the most familiar and friendly interface to school 
children. Some web-based programs for nutrition were developed 
(Han &amp; Jeong, 2004; Her &amp; Lee, 2002; Hong &amp; Kim, 2005; 
Lee et al., 2002), but web-based nutrition education programs 
for children are very limited. Nutrition web-sites for children 
should be constructed in a way which children find the sites 
easily and search the contents while having fun (Ahn et al., 2007; 
Ahn &amp; Kim, 2007). 
We developed and composed this website to implement a 
database program to store contents and search function. This 
study has been focusing on a standardization of nutrient infor-
mation. To date, in the domestic environment, it is difficult to </p>

<p>find any research, organization or homepage that provides the 
standards of nutrient expression. Therefore, we anticipate that 
the constructed nutrient database system will make a contribution 
to save nutrition information and to design criteria for sharing </p>



<p>Web-based nutrition education and healthy menu for children </p>

<p>its information. In the introduction of this site, contents of DRIs 
and Daily Value (DV) were added. Recently, restaurant nutrition 
labeling was researched and it would become set in a legal term 
(Hong &amp; Jeong, 2007) to prevent global tendency of high calorie 
diet and out-going food. 
The home page explains the site as a whole. This page has 
links to the contents classified into eight nutrient groups. These 
contents were considered for needs of nutrition education (Park 
et al., 2006; Shin et al., 2006). Previous web-based nutrition 
programs did not include them. So these kinds of trials will be 
good education tools (Han &amp; Jeong, 2004; Her &amp; Lee, 2002; 
Hong &amp; Kim, 2005). 
This site contains menus for infants, children and adolescents. 
The menus can be searched by many categories and have screen 
scripts of the cooking process. There is also a transforming 
program that modifies the weights of raw materials of menus 
according to the change of weight of a certain raw material of 
the menu. This site provides the search function for 151 healthy 
menus for children in association with this research. 
We tried to make the program from the children's viewpoints, 
but some did not work properly. And the menu for the kids is 
very limited. So we have to provide easier and a variety of menus 
having more nutritious ingredients for the kids. This kind of effort 
was organized for kid's easy access and attribute motive to learn 
about food and nutrition. It will give better motive for education 
needs of kids (Park et al., 2006; Shin et al., 2006). These kinds 
of trials can be helpful for a future disease preventing program 
and it could give knowledgeable information to the kids. We 
hope that these kinds of web-based systems could be widely used 
for nutrition education for kids and adults. </p>

<p>Literature cited </p>

<p>Ahn Y, Kim HM, Seo JS, Yoon EY, Bea HJ &amp; Kim KW (2007). 
Needs assessment for developing a nutrition information site for 
elementary school children among elementary school dietitians. 
Korean Journal of Community Nutrition 12:405-416. 
Ahn Y &amp; Kim KW (2007). Study on utilization status of internet 
and needs assessment for developing nutrition education programs 
among elementary school children. Nutrition Research and Prac-
tice 1:341-348. 
Boyle MA (2003). Community nutrition in action (3rd Eds), p.309-
311. Tomson wadsworth, USA 
Department of Health and Welfare &amp; Korean Health Industry 
Development Institute (2006). The Third Korea National Health &amp; 
Nutrition Examination Survey (KNHANES III), 2005-Nutrition 
Survey(1). Department of Health and Welfare, Seoul. Republic of 
Korea 
Han JS (1997). A computerized system for diagnosis and nutritional 
assessment of dietary intakes : Recommended dietary allowances 
for Koreans, 6 
th revision. Journal of the Korean Society of Food 
science and Nutrition 26:726-732. 
Han JS (2000). A system for nutritional assessment and diagnosis of </p>

<p>dietary intakes through internet. Journal of the Korean Society of 
Food science and Nutrition 29:1177-1184. 
Han JS &amp; Jeong JH (2004). A web-based internet program for 
nutrition counseling and diet management of patient with diabetes 
mellitus. Journal of the Korean Society of Food science and 
Nutrition 33:114-122. 
Her ES &amp; Lee KH (2003a). Utilization status of internet and dietary 
information of school children in Gyeongnam and Jeonbuk areas. 
Korean Journal of Community Nutrition 8:15-25. 
Her ES &amp; Lee KH (2003b). Effect-evaluation of nutritional education 
program using internet for school children. The Korean Journal 
of Nutrition 36:500-507. 
Her ES &amp; Lee KH (2002). Development of computer-aided nutri-
tional education program for the school children. The Korean 
Journal of Nutrition 35:791-799. 
Hong SM (1989). Development of computer programs for nutrition 
counseling. The Korean Journal of Nutrition 22:275-289. 
Hong SM (1996). Development status and application of software in 
nutrition. The Korean Journal of Nutrition 29:1170-1174. 
Hong SM &amp; Kim G (2005). System for nutrition counseling and 
screening. Korean Journal of Community Nutrition 7:220-229. 
Hong SM, Cho HS &amp; Kim G (2003). A basic study of food exchange 
database construction and search system (ENECC/E-Food Exch-
ange) based on internet Journal of the Korean Dietetic Association 
9:159-171. 
Hong SM &amp; Jeong HJ (2007). Model development of nutrition labe-
ling on restaurant and fast-food, p.124-181. Korean Food &amp; Drug 
Association report, Seoul. Republic of Korea 
Joni Youngwirth (1983). The evolution of computers in dietetics: A 
review, J Am Die Assoc 32:62-67. 
Kang HJ, Kim KJ &amp; Kim I (1999). A study on the computerized 
nutrition counseling program by food intake and exercise amount 
checking. The Korean Jounal of Nutrition 32:598-607. 
Kim YJ &amp; Yoon EY (1999). Development and evaluation of nutrition 
education program through internet. Korean Journal of Community 
Nutrition 4:546-553. 
Kolasa KM &amp; Miller MG (1996). New developments in nutrition 
education using computer technology. J Nutr Educ 28:7-14. 
Lee JW, Seo JS, Kim KE &amp; Ly SY (2002). A needs assessment to 
develop website contents on nutritional information and counseling 
for teenagers. Korean Journal of Community Nutrition 7:664-674. 
National Internet Development Agency of Korea &amp; Ministry of 
Information Communication Republic of Korea (2007). 2006 
Survey on the computer and internet usage. http://isis.nida.or.kr/ 
index_unssl. jsp. Accessed on 8/1/07. 
Park YH, Kim HH, Shin KH, Shin EK, Bae IS &amp; Lee YK (2006). 
A survey on practice of nutrition education and perception for 
implementing nutrition education by nutrition teachers in ele-
mentary schools. The Korean Journal of Nutrition 39:403-416. 
Shin EK, Shin KH, Kim HH, Park YH, Bae IS &amp; Lee YK (2006). 
A survey on the needs educators, learners and parents for imple-
menting nutrition education by nutrition teachers in elementary 
schools. Journal of the Korean Dietetic Association 12:89-101. 
The Korean Nutrition Society (2005). Dietary Reference Intakes 
(DRIs) for Koreans. Seoul. Republic of Korea 
Youn SJ (2001). Implementation of WEB site for nutrition assessment 
and management. Ministry of Health Welfare and Family Affairs 
[Abstract]. </p>

</text></tei>