<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2686520" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:48+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>We present a database DOOR (Database for 
prOkaryotic OpeRons) containing computationally 
predicted operons of all the sequenced prokaryotic 
genomes. All the operons in DOOR are predicted 
using our own prediction program, which was 
ranked to be the best among 14 operon prediction 
programs by a recent independent review. Cur-
rently, the DOOR database contains operons for 
675 prokaryotic genomes, and supports a number 
of search capabilities to facilitate easy access and 
utilization of the information stored in it. </p>

<p>(1) Querying the database: the database provides a 
search capability for a user to find desired 
operons and associated information through 
multiple querying methods. 
(2) Searching for similar operons: the database 
provides a search capability for a user to find 
operons that have similar composition and 
structure to a query operon. 
(3) Prediction of cis-regulatory motifs: the data-
base provides a capability for motif identifica-
tion in the promoter regions of a user-specified 
group of possibly coregulated operons, using 
motif-finding tools. 
(4) Operons for RNA genes: the database includes 
operons for RNA genes. 
(5) OperonWiki: the database provides a wiki page 
(OperonWiki) to facilitate interactions between 
users and the developer of the database. </p>

<p>We believe that DOOR provides a useful resource to 
many biologists working on bacteria and archaea, 
which can be accessed at http://csbl1.bmb.uga. 
edu/OperonDB. </p>

<p>In prokaryotic organisms, a substantial fraction of func-
tionally related genes are organized into operons, each of 
which is a group of genes arranged in tandem on the same </p>

<p>strand of a genome sharing a common promoter and ter-
minator. Genes in the same operon are transcribed 
together as one messenger RNA. Having the knowledge 
of operons represents the next key step in deciphering the 
information encoded in a genome after its genes are iden-
tified. It represents the basis for elucidating higher level 
genomic structures, such as regulons and modulons as well 
as the cellular machineries, such as metabolic pathways 
and regulatory networks. In addition, operons, as the 
basic units of transcription and cellular functions, provide 
the essential information for experimental designs for 
studying cellular systems. 
A number of operon databases are currently available 
on the Internet. These databases contain information with 
varying levels of reliability and having different emphases. 
For example, OperonDB contains predicted operons for 
550 genomes with documented prediction sensitivity 
at 30-50% on Escherichia coli (1). MicrobesOnline is a 
database with operons for 620 genomes with prediction 
accuracy at 85% and 83% for E. coli K12 and Bacillus 
subtilis, respectively (2). ODB contains both predicted and 
experimentally validated operons for 203 genomes (3). 
RegulonDB contains experimentally validated operons 
and associated transcriptional regulators but for E. coli 
only (4), collected from the published literature. And 
DBTBS is a database with similar content to that of 
RegulonDB but for B. subtilis (5). 
Among these databases, RegulonDB and DBTBS have 
highly reliable data but they each are only for a specific 
organism, while the others cover more organisms with less 
reliable operon data. None of these databases provide the 
basic operon-centric tools in support of comparative 
genome analyses. We believe that the biological commu-
nity could benefit from having a new operon database 
with high-quality predicted operons as well as high cover-
age along with strong querying capabilities. Our DOOR 
(Database for prOkaryotic OpeRons) database is designed 
to fulfill this goal. </p>

<p>DATA </p>

<p>We have recently published a computer program for 
operon prediction (6), with prediction accuracy at 90.2% </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 706 542 9779; Fax: +1 706 542 9751; Email: xyn@bmb.uga.edu </p>

<p>ß 2008 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>and 93.7% on B. subtilis and E. coli genomes, respec-
tively, measured on experimentally validated operons. 
Our prediction program employs two classifiers, one for 
genomes with substantial numbers of experimentally vali-
dated operons and one for genomes with only limited or 
no such data. For the first case, our program was trained 
on a subset of the known operons, using a nonlinear (deci-
sion tree-based) classifier utilizing both general features of 
genomes and genome-specific features, while for the 
second case, our program was trained based only on 
general features of genomes, using a linear (logistic func-
tion-based) classifier. The advantage of this strategy, i.e. 
combining genome-independent and genome-specific 
information when available, is clear as the program was 
recently ranked as the most accurate operon prediction 
program in the public domain by an independent assess-
ment of 14 operon prediction programs, across all three 
performance measurements: prediction sensitivity, speci-
ficity and overall accuracy (7). 
Using this prediction program, we have made operon 
predictions for all complete prokaryotic genomes (NCBI 
release of 2 May 2008), and organized the data into a rela-
tional database, DOOR. Currently, DOOR contains pre-
dicted operons for 675 organisms with 736 chromosomes 
and 489 plasmids, consisting of a total of 450 986 operons. 
The RNA genes and protein-encoding genes in NCBI 
release are treated the same by our operon prediction pro-
gram, so DOOR also contains operons for RNA genes. 
For each gene and operon in DOOR, we provide the 
following information collected from public databases. 
For each gene, we include its location in the genome, the 
name of the genome, its gene name, its GI number, its locus 
tag, its COG number(s), its molecular function described 
using a few keywords, a label for it being a protein-or 
RNA-encoding gene and its genomic sequence. To facil-
itate operon comparisons, DOOR also contains precalcu-
lated BLAST E-values and alignment bit-scores between 
each pair of potentially homologous genes across all 
genomes (with E-values lower than a preselected threshold) 
(see Tools supported by DOOR section for details). 
For each operon, the DOOR database contains its com-
ponent genes, its precalculated promoter sequence (up to 
200 bp, our default value), its precalculated similar oper-
ons, a link to the relevant literature in the ODB database 
(3) and a link to its corresponding operon page at 
MicrobesOnline. 
The whole DOOR system is implemented on a Fedora 
Core 8 Linux computer using <rs type="software">MySQL</rs> as the database 
management system. DOOR employs Apache for its 
web server, and php to implement the dynamic web 
pages. In addition, the Wiki of the DOOR system is imple-
mented using <rs id="software-10" type="software">MediaWiki</rs> <rs corresp="#software-10" type="version-number">1.13.0</rs>. </p>

<p>TOOLS SUPPORTED BY DOOR </p>

<p>Currently, the DOOR system supports the following 
search capabilities to facilitate access to and utilization 
of the information stored in the database by its user. We 
expect that the list of tools will continue to expand in 
DOOR as the needs arise. </p>

<p>Basic querying capabilities </p>

<p>Searching for operons. A user can search for interested 
operons in DOOR by multiple ways. 
(1) Find an operon by its genes. A user can first find a gene 
in DOOR by searching for it using various gene attributes, 
such as the gene name, locus tag, GI number, COG num-
ber(s), protein product description in conjunction with the 
organism's name. Multiple attributes can be combined 
using AND or OR operations, and thus complex queries 
can be conducted against the DOOR database. After a 
target gene is identified, the system returns a link to the 
operon that contains the gene (if such an operon exists). 
(2) Find an operon by operon attributes. One can find an 
operon by operon attributes, such as Operon ID, operon 
size and the number of component genes in conjunction 
with the organism's name. 
(3) Find operons by its similar operon. A user can find 
similar operons to a query operon in DOOR. Figure 1 
shows an example of using a query operon to search for 
its similar operons with low homology between the corre-
sponding genes. </p>

<p>Selecting operons. A user can browse all operons in selected 
genomes, and copy the operons to a working environment, 
where the user can carry out operations on the selected 
operons, such as predicting their cis-regulatory motifs. </p>

<p>Retrieving literature information of selected operons. The 
DOOR database allows a user to output related literature 
for a selected operon. Figure 2 shows an example of such 
an application. </p>

<p>Calculating general statistics. The DOOR system pro-
vides a number of procedures for calculating various 
operon-related statistics for a specified genome, including 
(i) the distribution of the number of genes across all oper-
ons in the genome; (ii) the distributions of inter-genic dis-
tances between operons and between genes, respectively; 
(iii) the percentage of genes in operons (with at least two 
genes); (iv) the distribution of the operon lengths in term 
of the genomic sequence lengths covered by each operon; 
and (5) the correlation between operon size and its gene 
length. For each of these distributions, we also calculate 
the average, the median and the standard deviation. We 
expect that this list will grow as the needs arise. </p>

<p>Crosslinking to other operon databases. The DOOR 
system also provides links to other databases, currently 
two databases ODB and MicrobesOnline for each of its 
operons. The reason for linking to these databases is that 
ODB provides the most comprehensive literature informa-
tion for operons and MicrobesOnline is the second largest 
operon database on the Internet. We expect that the cross-
links to other databases will grow as the needs arise and as 
new-related databases emerge. </p>

<p>Generating easy-to-read text files for specified operons and 
associated information. The DOOR system can generate 
a file containing user-specified operons and associated 
information in a plain text format and output it to the 
users' local computer to facilitate large-scale applications 
by users. </p>



<p>Identification of similar operons </p>

<p>We now present a quantitative method for measuring the 
similarity between two operons, which generalizes the idea 
of 'conserved gene pairs' (1). </p>

<p>Given two operons O 1 and O 2 , with O 1 having m genes 
and O 2 having n genes. For each pair of genes between O 1 
and O 2 , we call them homologous genes if their sequence 
similarity, measured by BLAST, is above a preselected 
cutoff. We then create a bipartite graph G, in which 
genes in O 1 and O 2 are represented as vertices and for 
each pair of homologous genes defined above, we create 
an edge between the two genes and use their sequence 
similarity as their weight in the graph G. The weight 
of the maximum weighted bipartite matching (8) for 
graph G is defined as the similarity score between 
operons O 1 and O 2 . In the current implementation, 
DOOR uses the Àlogarithm of BLAST E-values or align-
ment bit-scores to measure the level of similarity between 
two operons. Please find a detailed explanation in the 
Supplementary Material. 
In DOOR, two operons with at least two pairs of 
matched genes in their maximum weighted bipartite 
matching are considered as similar operons. Figure 3 
shows an example of two similar operons with six genes, 
in which pair-wise sequence similarity is not very signifi-
cant, with E-values 10 
À8.2 , 10 </p>

<p>À4.0 </p>

<p>, 10 
À6.1 , 10 </p>

<p>À21.5 </p>

<p>, 10 </p>

<p>À3.0 </p>

<p>and 10 
À2.7 . These two sets of six homologous genes 
arranged in tandem strongly suggest that these two sets 
of genes are involved in the same biological pathways in </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Figure 1. Find similar operons with operon 4015 by using the criterion '(3 Unweighted Score 20) AND (À30 Weighted Score 0) AND (0 Bit 
Score 225)'. (A) Is a query form. (B) Is the hit operons. Among the nine hit operons, five have not been annotated by COG. </p>

<p>Figure 2. An operon with reference information (highlighted), whose 
genes make the pyruvate dehydrogenase complex in E. coli. The first 
reference is a case study in 1976, and the second and third references 
reported two experimental studies on this complex. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, Database issue D461 </p>

<p>their own organisms, indicating that these homologous 
gene pairs are orthologous. 
We expect that as the prediction accuracy of operons 
continues to improve, we will soon see many operon-based 
comparative genome analyses. Hence a capability like the 
above should prove to be a useful tool in support of such 
operon-based analyses. </p>

<p>Motif finding </p>

<p>The DOOR system allows a user to predict cis-regulatory 
motifs for a given set of similar operons. For a set of 
operons identified to be similar, the system can retrieve 
the corresponding promoter sequence of each operon, 
and then it applies either MEME (9) or CUBIC (10), 
selected by the user, to find conserved sequence motifs 
across the promoter sequences and predict them to be 
cis-regulatory motifs. </p>

<p>OperonWiki </p>

<p>The DOOR system supports a wiki page (OperonWiki) to 
facilitate interactions between the user and the developers 
of the database. Our goal is to have a comprehensive set of 
operons for all sequenced prokaryotic genomes, which will 
require substantial manual curations in order to keep our 
operon data as accurate as possible. Our plan is that we 
will rely not only on our development team but also on the 
user community of the database to do this. We have devel-
oped a Wiki for the DOOR system to collect users' feed-
backs about our operon data and make necessary changes 
on the database when such suggestions are made by users 
after our validation. </p>

<p>Using the DOOR system: an example </p>

<p>We now give an example to illustrate how to use the 
search capabilities supported by DOOR. The ssuEADCB 
operon in E. coli has five genes, and these genes are 
involved in the alkanesulfonate metabolism. Our goal 
here is to predict the cis-regulatory motifs of this operon 
in E. coli through searching the DOOR database. </p>

<p>A user can go to the main page of DOOR, click on 
'Operon Search' and then specify the query criterion 
'Operon ID = 4015' to find this operon if the user 
knows its ID. Otherwise, the user can find this operon 
by using other information. For example, he/she can 
search for the operon by finding its component genes 
through the 'Gene Search' page by using the query criteria 
'(Gene Include ssu) AND (Species Name Include 
MG1655)'. On the query result page, click the link con-
taining operon ID ('4015') to get to the detailed target 
operon page. The user can see that this operon has 1476 
similar operons. By clicking on the link '1476' on the 
'Similar Operon' row, the user can see the list of all its 
similar operons. In order to apply the prediction tool for 
cis-regulatory motifs, the user needs to select a number of 
similar operons to the query operon by checking the 
checkbox on relevant operon rows, and then click the 
button 'Add Selected Operons', which adds all the selected 
operons to the working environment. To see which oper-
ons have been added to the working environment, the user 
can click the button 'Selected Operons' on the main menu. 
Then check the checkboxes for the interested operons and 
click the button 'Show Upstream Regions' to get and 
show the promoter regions of the selected operons. The 
user can now proceed to predict cis-regulatory motifs by 
either clicking on 'Do MEME' (or 'Do CUBIC'), which 
invokes the MEME with the selected promoter sequences. 
In this case, the program returns the following table 
(Table 1) for operon ID = 4015. 
For this particular example, we have checked which 
transcription factors can bind to the promoter sequences 
in the RegulonDB database. We found that six transcrip-
tional factors can bind to the promoter region of the 
ssuEABCD operon, and the binding sites for four of 
them have been identified experimentally. Two of them 
are identified here by running MEME. We believe that 
the reason for failing to identify the other two motifs is 
due to the small number of promoter sequences that we 
used in this example. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>National Science Foundation (NSF/DBI-0354771, 
NSF/ITR-IIS-0407204, NSF/CCF-0621700, NSF/DBI-
0542119, partial); BioEnergy Science Center grant from 
the Office of Biological and Environmental Research in </p>

<p>Table 1. Identified cis-regulatory binding motifs for the ssuEDACB operon (Operon ID is 4015) by MEME </p>

<p>Transcriptional factor 
Binding site sequence 
MEME Motif </p>

<p>Cbl 
aaagccctttCTTTAGTTTATTTTCAGAAA 
AAGATACACAAAATTTATATttggaatttt </p>

<p>Found in identified motif 2. </p>

<p>IHF3 
actgaacgagTAATTCATTGATTcaacatctaa 
Found in identified motif 3. 
IHF4 
gacaaatcttTAATTTATAGATTtcatgaatat 
Not found. 
IHF5 
aacaaa aaaaGAACAAT TGGTTAtaaggagaga 
Partially found in motif 1. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Two similar operons in Beijerinckia indica subsp. indica 
ATCC 9039 and Methanosphaera stadtmanae DSM 3091, each of 
which is represented as a sequence of green segments. Each red line 
connecting two genes represents a homology relationship. </p>



<p>the DOE Office of Science. Funding for open access 
charge: National Science Foundation (NSF/DBI-
0542119). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, Database issue D463 </p>

</text></tei>