<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2830412" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Our study focused on the antioxidant activities of Mosidae leaf ethanol extract (MLE) and included measurements of reducing power, total phenolic 
compounds, DPPH radical scavenging activity, and hydroxyl radical scavenging activity. In order to determine whether or not MLE evidences any 
chemopreventive activities, experimental lung metastasis was induced via the i.v. inoculation of colon26-M3.1 carcinoma cells into BALB/c mice. 
Additionally, we attempted to characterize any possible cytotoxic effects in murine normal splenocytes and tumor cells (B16-BL6 and colon26-M3.1). 
The total phenolic content and reducing capacity were measured at 39 mg/100 mL and 1.24, respectively, whereas the DPPH and hydroxyl radical 
scavenging activities of MLE were measured to be 88.89% and 22.10%, respectively. Prophylactic i.v. treatment with MLE resulted in a dose-dependent 
and significant inhibition of lung metastasis. Specifically, a MLE dose of 200 ug per mouse resulted in an 88.90% inhibition of lung metastasis. 
For the cytotoxicity assay, MLE doses up to 100 ug/mL were not shown to affect the growth of normal murine splenocytes. Additionally, the 
survival of normal cells was not affected at MLE doses below 500 ug/mL. However, MLE doses up to 500 ug/mL reduced the percentage of 
tumor cell growth for B16BL6 (67% alive) and colon26-M3.1 (62% alive) cells. </p>

<p>Plants generate a board variety of biologically active 
substances, some of which are associated with special flavors 
or tastes, and others that evidence antioxidant and/or antimi-
crobial activities. Antioxidants reduce damage to cells and 
biomolecules attributable to reactive oxygen/nitrogen species 
(ROS/RNS) [1]. In the past, both ROS and RNS have been 
implicated in the oxidative destruction of food products as well 
as in the pathogenesis of several human diseases including 
atherosclerosis, diabetes mellitus, chronic inflammation, 
neurodegenerative disorders including Alzheimer's disease, and 
certain types of cancer [2,3]. Among the dietary antioxidants, 
phenolic compounds and secondary metabolites from plants are 
the most abundant [1]. 
A variety of natural products with biological properties that 
enhance the host defense system have been previously applied </p>

<p>as cancer immunotherapies [4-7], where they are becoming 
increasingly viewed as alternatives to cytotoxic drugs [8]. This 
is relevant, considering that innate immune system activation may 
perform a critical role in defense against foreign antigens 
including tumors [9]. 
Mosidae (Adenophora remotiflora) is a perennial, wild plant 
of the Campanulaceae family, which inhabits the Korean 
peninsula. Mosidae has been traditionally utilized in Korea as 
a Complementary and Alternative Medicine (CAM) for the 
treatment of certain diseases including expectoration, chills, 
fever, poisoning, and phlegm discharge [10]. The principal 
constituents of Mosidae leaves (ML) are the organic acids, 
saponin and inulin, and unlike individual constituent crude drugs 
its efficacy and quality can be altered. Additionally Mosidae has 
also been reported to exert antioxidant effects [11] in a few in 
vitro and in vivo studies [12]. However, the anti-metastatic effects 
of Mosidae have yet to be clearly elucidated. </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant from the Agricultural R &amp; D Promotion Center (108065-03-1-HD120). 
 § Corresponding Author: Ae-Jung Kim, Tel. 82-41-630-5249, Fax. 82-41-630-5175, Email. aj5249@naver.com 
Received: October 9, 2009, Revised: February 1, 2010, Accepted: February 5, 2010 
ⓒ2010 The Korean Nutrition Society and the Korean Society of Community Nutrition 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Ae-Jung Kim et al. </p>



<p>(a) 
(b) </p>

<p>Fig. 1. The Mosidae (Adenophora remotiflora) leaves. Two-month-old fresh (a) </p>

<p>and vacuum freeze dried (b) of Mosidae leaves were donated by Eco-Sprout Co, </p>

<p>Ltd. (Gyeonggido, Korea) and identified by Dr Kang, Department of Oriental medicine 
Resources, Joongbu University (Keumsan, Korea). </p>

<p>In this study, we evaluated the antioxidant activity of Mosidae 
leaves ethanol extract (MLE) which was extracted with 70% 
ethanol solution in water bath at 30℃ for 1 hour, by assessing 
its reducing power, total phenolic compounds, DPPH radical 
scavenging activity, and hydroxyl radical scavenging activity. We 
also evaluated the anti-metastatic activity of MLE through the 
prophylactic inhibition of lung metastasis of colon26-M3.1 
carcinoma cells. The cytotoxic effects of MLE were evaluated 
using an experimental metastasis model featuring murine 
splenocyte and tumor cells (B16BL6 and colon26-M3.1). </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>Two-month-old fresh (a) and vacuum freeze-dried (b) Mosidae 
(Adenophora remotiflora) leaves were donated by Eco-Sprout 
Co, Ltd. (Gyeonggido, Korea), an environmentally-friendly 
agricultural company (Fig. 1). The material was filtered through 
a 0.2 um micro filter and stored at 4℃ until use. 
The proximal compositions of fresh Mosidae leaves (ML), 
moisture, protein, fat and ash (%), were determined by following 
AOAC [13] procedures. </p>

<p>Antioxidant activities </p>

<p>Total phenolic compound content 
Total phenolic content of the MLE was measured using 
Folin-Ciocalteau reagent [14,15]. Folin-Ciocalteau reagent was 
diluted by 2 times using deionized water. The 2.0 mL of MLE 
solution (25 mg/mL) was mixed with diluted reagent (0.4 mL) 
and 2.0 mL of 2% sodium carbonate solution. Then mixed 
solution was held at room temperature for 30 min. After the 
absorbance of the solution was determined at 750 nm by an 
UV/visible spectrophotometer (UV-1601, Shimadzu, Tokyo, 
Japan). Standard curve was drawn using a tannic acid and 
calculated from it. </p>

<p>DPPH free radical scavenging activity 
The free radical scavenging activities of MLE were evaluated 
according to the method described by Huang et al. [16], albeit 
with slight modification. Briefly, 0.2 mL of MLE was mixed 
with 1.0 mL of 0.2 mM DPPH ethanol solution. After 30 min 
at room temperature, absorbance values were measured by a 
UV-visible spectrophotometer set at 517 nm. The percent 
inhibition of DPPH radical by the sample extract was calculated 
by the following formula: DPPH free radical scavenging activity 
(%) = (1-As/Ab)×100, where Ab is the blank absorbance and 
As is the absorbance of the extract sample [16]. α-Tocopherol 
and BHT were used as positive standards. </p>

<p>Reducing power 
The reducing power was determined according to the method 
of Oyaizu [14]. The 1.0 mL of sample solution was mixed with 
0.5 mL of 50 mM sodium phosphate buffer (pH 6.5) and 0.7 
mL of 1% potassium ferricyanide. The mixture was incubated 
at 50℃ for 20 min. After 1.0 mL of 10% trichloroacetic acid 
and 1.0 mL of distilled were added, the mixture was centrifuged 
at 3,000 rpm for 10 min. The 1.0 mL of upper layer was mixed 
with 0.1 mL of 0.1% of ferric chloride, and the absorbance was 
measured at 700 nm. The assays were carried out in triplicate 
and the results were expressed as mean values standard 
deviations. BHT and α-tocopherol were used as standards. </p>

<p>Hydroxyl radical scavenging effect 
The effect of hydroxyl radical was assayed by using the 
2-deoxyribose oxidation method [17]. The reaction mixture 
contained 1.0 mL of 0.1 M sodium phosphate buffer (pH 7.4), 
0.20 mL of 10 mM 2-deoxyribose, 0.20 mL of 10 mM 
FeSO4-EDTA, 0.20 mL of 10 mM hydrogen peroxide and 0.20 
mL of extract solution in a tube. After incubation at 37℃ for 
1 hour, the reaction was stopped by adding 1.0 mL of 1.0% 
trichloroacetic acid and 1.0 mL of 1.0% of thiobarbituric acid. 
The mixture was boiled for 10 min, cooled in ice and then 
measured at 532 nm. Hydroxyl radical-scavenging effect was 
evaluated as the inhibition rate of 2-deoxyribose oxidation by 
hydroxyl radical. </p>

<p>Mice and cell cultures </p>

<p>Specific pathogen-free female BALB/c mice (6 weeks old) 
were purchased from NARA Biotech. (Seoul, Korea) and housed 
in a specific pathogen free environment. All experiments were 
conducted in accordance with the guidelines established by the 
Animal Care and Use Committee of Yuhan University 
(2009E-001). Water and dietary pellets were supplied ad libitum. 
Highly lung metastatic sublines of colon 26 carcinoma (colon26-
M3.1) and murine B16-BL6 melanoma cells were maintained as 
monolayer cultures in Eagle's minimal essential medium 
(EMEM) supplemented with 7.5% fetal bovine serum (FBS), 
sodium pyruvate, nonessential amino acids and L-glutamine, all </p>



<p>Mosidae (Adenophora remotiflora) leaves </p>

<p>Table 1. The chemical composition of fresh Mosidae leaves (ML) 
(%) </p>

<p>Sample 
Moisture 
Protein 
Fat 
Ash </p>

<p>Mosidae leaf 
91.92 ± 12.33 </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>1.63 ± 0.22 0.04 ± 0.01 0.60 ± 0.05 </p>

<p>1) Mean ± SD </p>

<p>Table 2. Antioxidant Activities of Mosidae leaves ethanol extract (MLE) </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>Total phenolic 
compounds 
(μg/100 mL) </p>

<p>Reducing 
power </p>

<p>DPPH free 
radical 
scavenging 
effect (%) </p>

<p>Hydroxyl 
radical 
scavenging 
effect (%) </p>

<p>MLE </p>

<p>3) </p>

<p>39.00 ± 0.05 1.24 ± 0.22 
ab1)2) 88.89 ± 0.60 
b 29.37 ± 6.71 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>BHT </p>

<p>3) </p>

<p>-
2 . 0 9 ± 0 . 0 6 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>99.06 ± 0.41 
a 22.10 ± 1.50 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>α-Tocopherol </p>

<p>3) </p>

<p>-
1.72 ± 0.22 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>95.45 ± 0.39 
ab 27.71 ± 3.56 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>1) Data are shown as mean ± SD. 
2) Values with different superscripts within the column are significantly different at </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 by Duncan's multiple range test. </p>

<p>3) 1 g of samples (MLE, BHT and α-Tocopherol) were extracted with 70% ethanol 
solution in water bath at 30℃ for 1 hour, respectively. </p>

<p>Table 3. Prophylactic effects of MLE on lung metastasis </p>

<p>Samples 
Conc. 
(μg/mice) </p>

<p>No. of lung metastasis </p>

<p>Mean ± SD 
Range 
Inhibition (%) </p>

<p>Control (Challenge only) 64.7 ± 8.1 </p>

<p>1)a2) </p>

<p>59 -80 
-</p>

<p>MLE </p>

<p>1 
61.4 ± 4.8 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>57 -68 
-</p>

<p>20 
27.0 ± 9.1 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>21 -41 
58.3 </p>

<p>200 
7.2 ± 5.2 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>4 -15 
88.9 
1) Data are shown as mean ± SD. 
2) Values with different superscripts within the column are significantly different at </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 by Duncan's multiple range test. </p>

<p>of which were purchased from Gibco BRL (Gibco: Carlsbad, 
CA, USA). Splenocytes from normal mice were cultured in 
RPMI-1640 (Gibco: Carlsbad, CA, USA) supplemented with 
7.5% fetal bovine serum and glutamine [18]. </p>

<p>Experimental lung metastasis </p>

<p>Experimental lung metastasis was induced via i.v. inoculation 
of colon26-M3.1 carcinoma cells (3×10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>) into BALB/c mice [19]. 
To assess the anti-metastatic activity of MLE, groups of five 
mice each were i.v. treated with MLE (50 ug-10 mg/kg mice) 
2 days prior to tumor cell inoculation. The mice were sacrificed 
14 days later and their lungs were fixed in Bouin's solution. Lung 
tumor cell colonies were counted under a microscope [18]. </p>

<p>Cytotoxicity assay </p>

<p>For the cytotoxcity assay, various doses of MLE (0.1-500 
ug/mL) in culture medium were added to each well of a 96-well 
plate containing either murine tumor cells (B16-BL6 cell and 
colon26-M3.1) (1×10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>/well) or splenocytes (2×10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>/well) from 
normal mice. After incubation for 72 hours, cytotoxcity was 
assayed by WST-1 based colorimetric assay (Wako Pure 
Chemicals Industrials, Ltd., Osaka, Japan) [19]. The absorbance 
of each well was monitored at 450 nm using a micro-plate reader 
(Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The data were expressed as mean ± SD values using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, NC, USA). Each experimental set was compared 
by one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Duncan's 
multiple-range test (P &lt; 0.05) using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">SAS program</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, NC, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Proximate compositions </p>

<p>The proximate compositions of fresh ML are shown in Table 
1. The fresh ML consisted of moisture (91.92%), protein (1.63%), 
fat (0.04%) and ash (0.6%). </p>

<p>Antioxidant activities </p>

<p>In this study, the antioxidant activity of MLE was evaluated 
by measuring reducing power, total phenolic compounds, DPPH 
radical scavenging, and hydroxyl radical scavenging. As shown 
in Table 2, the concentration of total phenolic compounds in 
MLE was 39 mg/100 mL. MLE evidenced a high reducing 
capacity (1.24), similar to that of α-Tocopherol (1.72). The DPPH 
scavenging activity of MLE was 88.89%, a value much lower </p>

<p>than that of BHT (99.06%) and α-Tocopherol (95.45%). 
Nonetheless, we noted no significant differences between MLE 
and α-Tocopherol. The hydroxyl radical scavenging activity of 
MLE (22.10%) was significantly lower than that of BHT 
(29.37%), but did not differ significantly from that of α 
-Tocopherol (27.71%). </p>

<p>Inhibitory effect of MLE on lung metastasis </p>

<p>In order to determine whether MLE has any inhibitory effect 
on lung tumor metastasis, we assessed the effects of MLE on 
the experimental lung tumor metastasis of colon26-M3.1 cells. 
As shown in Table 3, prophylactic i.v. MLE treatment signifi-
cantly inhibited lung metastasis in a dose-dependent manner. 
Specifically, a dose of 200 ug MLE per mouse strongly inhibited 
lung metastasis by 88.90%. Thus, MLE treatment within a certain 
range exerted no apparent side effects, such as a reduction in 
body weight (data not shown). </p>

<p>Cytotoxicity assay </p>

<p>The cytotoxic effects of MLE on murine splenocyte and tumor 
cells (B16BL6 and colon26-M3.1) were examined in vitro as 
shown in Fig 2. MLE doses up to 100 ug/mL had no effect 
on the growth of normal murine splenocytes. Additionally, the </p>

<p>Ae-Jung Kim et al. </p>



<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>(c) </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Cytotoxicity assays of Mosidae leaves ethanol extract (MLE) on murine 
normal splenocyte and tumor cells. (a): normal murine splenocyte cell line, (b): 
B16BL6 tumor cell line, (c): colon26-M3.1 tumor cell line. </p>

<p>survival of normal murine splenocytes was not shown to be 
influenced at MLE doses below 500 ug/mL. However, MLE 
doses up to 500 ug/mL resulted in decreased tumor cell growth 
in the B16BL6 (67% alive) and colon26-M3.1 (62% alive) cells. 
These results demonstrate that MLE had no effect on normal 
murine splenocytes, but demonstrated its cytotoxic effects against 
tumor cells. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Mosidae (Adenophora remotiflora) has been traditionally used 
as an alternative medicine in Korea. However, there are currently 
no reports concerning its biological activity on the basis of the 
scientific evidence. Our study focused on the antioxidant 
activities of Mosidae leaf ethanol extract (MLE) by measuring 
reducing power, total phenolic compounds, DPPH radical 
scavenging, and hydroxyl radical scavenging. We also evaluated 
the anti-metastatic activity of MLE with regard specifically to 
its prophylactic lung metastasis inhibitory activity in colon26-
M3.1 carcinoma cells. The cytotoxic effects of MLE were 
examined in an experimental metastasis model of murine 
splenocyte and tumor cells (B16BL6 and colon26-M3.1). 
The proximate compositions of fresh ML are provided in Table 
1. The moisture content of the fresh ML was 91.92%, the protein 
content of fresh ML was 1.63%, the fat content was 0.04%, and 
the ash content of fresh ML was 0.6%. An increasing amount 
of evidence suggests that the production of reactive oxygen 
species underlies a variety of disorders, and is also responsible 
for cellular damage [20]. The reducing capacity of cellular 
damage may be a significant indicator of any potential 
antioxidant activity [21]. Accordingly, MLE might contain a 
sizable amount of reductant, which may react with free radicals 
to stabilize and terminate free radical chain reactions. In this 
study, the reducing capacity of MLE was similar to that of 
vitamin E, but less profound than that of BHT. Phenolic 
compounds are thought to perform important functions as dietary 
antioxidants for the prevention of oxidative damage in living 
systems. Cho [22] reported that tannins extracted from fresh ML 
harbored high levels of total phenolic compounds as compared 
with spinach and aster, and moreover exhibited high DPPH 
radical scavenging activities. In this study, the total phenolic 
content of MLE was 39 mg/100 mL. The DPPH assay is known 
to provide reliable information concerning the antioxidant 
potential of a particular compound [23]. The results in Table 
3 show that the DPPH radical scavenging activity of MLE is 
similar compared with α-Tocopherol and BHT. Kim et al. [10] 
did report the DPPH radical scavenging activity of fresh MLE 
(55.63%), which was lower than the value we reported (88.89%). 
However, such a difference could have been caused by the 
different cultivation conditions in our experiments. For instance, 
the samples utilized in this study were cultivated by the 
environmentally-friendly agricultural company, Eco-Sprout Co, 
Ltd. 
The hydroxyl radical is considered a quick initiator of lipid 
peroxidation through the abstraction of hydrogen atoms from 
unsaturated fatty acids. Hence, the hydroxyl radical scavenging 
activity of MLE was evaluated and the results are shown in Table 
2. In this study, the hydroxyl radical scavenging activity of MLE 
was 29.37%, a level similar to that of BHT and α-Tocopherol. 
Therefore, MLE appears likely to be an effective radical 
scavenger. Furthermore, the results of this study show that MLE </p>



<p>Mosidae (Adenophora remotiflora) leaves </p>

<p>is a good scavenger of DPPH and hydroxyl radical. 
In an experimental tumor metastasis model, natural products 
commonly used in Oriental medicine were deemed useful in 
suppressing tumor growth and inhibiting tumor metastasis [18]. 
Unlike conventional chemotherapeutic agents, natural products 
have been shown to be relatively nontoxic to normal cells and 
to enhance host defense by stimulating immune-related cells [24]. 
In fact, many previous reports have demonstrated that some 
Oriental medicines inhibit the proliferation of macrophages, as 
well as metastasis in experimental tumor models [7,18,25]. In 
this study, prophylactic i.v. treatment with MLE inhibited the 
lung metastasis of colon26-M3.1 carcinoma cells in a dose-
dependent manner. Specifically, a 200 ug dose of MLE per mouse 
strongly inhibited lung metastasis by 88.90%. Therefore, MLE 
treatment in this range exerted no apparent side effects, such 
as reduction in body weight or piloerection (data not shown). 
Since the inception of the National Center for CAM, there has 
been an enormous increase in the number of basic science studies 
and therapy-based clinical trials designed to explore Comp-
lementary and Alternative Medicine (CAM). This subspecialty 
of immunology represents a particularly productive area with a 
large number of therapies shown to affect the immune system. 
Some recent studies have uncovered a biochemical mechanism 
that may potentially be involved in the immune modulatory 
pathways exploited by a variety of herbs [5,7,8]. Clinically, 
hundreds of trials have examined the effects of CAM on asthma, 
allergic rhinitis, and atopic dermatitis [26-28]. In our cytotoxicity 
assay, MLE did not affect the growth or survival of normal 
murine splenocytes. However, MLE doses up to 500 ug/mL 
reduced the percentage of tumor cell growth in B16BL6 (67% 
alive) and colon26-M3.1 (62% alive) cells. These results 
demonstrate that MLE has no effect on normal cell, but does 
demonstrate its cytotoxic effects against tumor cells. 
Pine pollen extract showed strong antioxidant and anti-
inflammatory activity [29], and the results of this study also 
demonstrated that MLE has strong antioxidant activity by 
measuring reducing power, DPPH radical scavenging, and 
hydroxyl radical scavenging. MLE may prove to be useful in 
preventing lung tumor metastasis, because it appears to exert no 
additional side effects. Therefore, MLE may be useful in the 
development of new plant materials as CAMs against diseases 
whose principal pathology is oxidative stress. </p>



<p>Ae-Jung Kim et al. </p>





</text></tei>