<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2867195" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: The purpose of our study is to evaluate the clinical results of arthroscopic suture bridge repair for patients with </p>

<p>rotator cuff tears. 
Methods: Between January 2007 and July 2007, fifty-one shoulders underwent arthroscopic suture bridge repair for full thickness </p>

<p>rotator cuff tears. The average age at the time of surgery was 57.1 years old, and the mean follow-up period was 15.4 months. 
Results: At the last follow-up, the pain at rest improved from 2.2 preoperatively to 0.23 postoperatively and the pain during </p>

<p>motion improved from 6.3 preoperatively to 1.8 postoperatively (p &lt; 0.001 and p &lt; 0.001, respectively). The range of active forward 
flexion improved from 138.4° to 154.6°, and the muscle power improved from 4.9 kg to 6.0 kg (p = 0.04 and 0.019, respectively). </p>

<p>The clinical results showed no significant difference according to the preoperative tear size and the extent of fatty degeneration, </p>

<p>but imaging study showed a statistical relation between retear and fatty degeneration. The average Constant score improved from </p>

<p>73.2 to 83.79, and the average University of California at Los Angeles score changed from 18.2 to 29.6 with 7 excellent, 41 good </p>

<p>and 3 poor results (p &lt; 0.001 and p = 0.003, respectively). 
Conclusions: The arthroscopic suture bridge repair technique for rotator cuff tears may be an operative method for which a </p>

<p>patient can expect to achieve clinical improvement regardless of the preoperative tear size and the extent of fatty degeneration. 
Keywords: Shoulder, Arthroscopy, Rotator cuff, Suture bridge repair technique </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery 2010;2:105-111 • doi:10.4055/cios.2010.2.2.105 </p>

<p>Received December 1, 2008; Accepted May 12, 2009 
Correspondence to: Yong Girl Rhee, MD 
Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Kyung Hee University School of 
Medicine, Hoegi-dong, Dongdaemun-gu, Seoul 130-701, Korea 
Tel: +82-2-958-8370, Fax: +82-2-964-3865 
E-mail: shoulderrhee@hanmail.net </p>

<p>Surgical rotator cuff repair is aimed at anatomic restoration 
of the rotator cuff and the head of humerus to reduce pain 
and restore the joint function. While open rotator cuff 
repair was commonly done in the past, arthroscopic repair 
is currently being widely performed. Arthroscopic rotator 
cuff repair provides benefits that cannot be obtained 
with open surgery. Unfortunately, it is also known for 
its technical difficulty and the inevitable employment of 
special equipment such as suture anchors. 1-3) Accordingly, 
arthroscopic repair had to be replaced by open surgery 
in some cases and mini-open surgery was the treatment </p>

<p>of choice in other cases. However, due to the advanced 
development of surgical instruments and the increased 
experience with arthroscopic rotator cuff repair, most 
rotator cuff tears can now be treated arthroscopically. 
Furthermore, the focus of the treatment has been trans-
ferred from just treating rotator cuff tears to raising 
the healing rates and inventing more efficient surgical 
techniques. As a result, the double-row suture anchor 
technique was introduced, which maximizes the contact 
area between the tendon and the tuberosity insertion 
footprint, and the suture bridge technique has become 
a recommended treatment method. 4-7) Particularly, the 
latter technique has been described in biomechanical 
studies as being more effective in increasing the contact 
area and the contact pressure at the tendon-bone interface 
and achieving high initial fixation strength compared to 
the former technique. 4-7) Even so, there are few reported </p>



<p>Yi et al. Arthroscopic Suture Bridge Repair Technique for Full Thickness Rotator Cuff Tear </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery • Vol. 2, No. 2, 2010 • www.ecios.org </p>

<p>maximum internal rotation strength were measured with 
the arm in the neutral position. Regarding the range of 
motion, forward elevation, external rotation with the arm 
in a neutral position, external and internal rotation with 
the arm at 90° abduction and posterior internal rotation 
and abduction were all measured before surgery and at 
the last follow-up. For clinical assessments, the Constant 
score 9) and the University of California at Los Angeles 
(UCLA) score were measured and the patients' satisfaction 
was also evaluated. </p>

<p>Operative Technique 
All of the operations were performed by the same surgeon 
with the patients in the beach-chair position. Passive 
range of motion and the levels of anterior, posterior 
and inferior translation were examined with the patient 
under anesthesia. After preoperative skin preparation, 
a posterior portal was established 2 cm inferior and 1 
cm medial to the posterolateral corner of the acromion 
and a diagnostic arthroscopy was performed through 
this portal. When the presence of rotator cuff tear was 
iden tified and a lesion of the long biceps tendon was 
also observed, the arthroscope was inserted through the 
posterior portal to the subacromial space, and a lateral 
portal was additionally created. Through this portal, the 
pattern of the rotator cuff tear in the subacromial space 
was observed. If severe fibrillation was observed inferior 
to the acromion, except when the acromion was seen as 
being flat on the preoperative radiographs, the pa tient 
was young or the rotator cuff tear was caused by a def-
inite trauma, then acromioplasty was performed based 
on the plain radiographs and arthroscopic findings. After 
acromioplasty, a posterolateral portal was created as a 
viewing portal in the middle of the imaginary line con-
necting the posterior portal and the lateral portal. 10) A 
shaver was used to debride the torn edges of the rotator 
cuff and the greater tuberosity, and a high speed burr was 
used to expose the cancellous bone. The torn rotator cuff 
was pulled with a grasper and a proper suture site was 
determined. A spinal needle was inserted from the lateral 
edge of the acromion to determine the proper position 
and angle (immediately lateral to the joint cartilage) for 
insertion of a bone punch. Through a 5 mm incision, 
a Bio-Cork screw suture anchor (Arthrex, Naples, FL, 
USA) was inserted into the planned site. The number of 
the anchors used was 1 or 2 depending on the tear size. 
Then, through the 3 sister portals 10) or a modified Neviaser 
portal, a suture was passed through the rotator cuff as 
proximally as possible using a suture hook (Linvatec, 
Largo, FL, USA) or a Banana SutureLasso (Arthrex) and </p>

<p>studies on the clinical results of the suture bridge tech-
nique. 
The purpose of this study was to report the clinical 
outcomes of the arthroscopic suture bridge technique in 
patients with full thickness rotator cuff tear and to assess 
the impact of the preoperative tear size and the extent of 
fatty degeneration on the final outcome. We postulated 
that the preoperative tear size would have no impact 
on the final outcome due to the excellent initial fixation 
strength provided by the arthroscopic suture bridge 
technique, and even in cases of large tears. In contrast, we 
expected that the extent of fatty degeneration would affect 
the final outcome. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Materials 
This retrospective review included 49 patients (51 cases) 
who had undergone arthroscopic suture bridge repair for 
a full thickness rotator cuff tear between January 2007 
and July 2007. The patients with the following conditions 
were excluded: partial thickness rotator cuff tear, the 
patients who required tenotomy or tenodesis for treating 
the long biceps tendon, superior glenoid labrum injury 
that required fixation, acromioclavicular arthritis that 
required excision of the distal end of the clavicle, advanced 
glenohumeral arthritis, anterior instability of the shoulder, 
nerve injury and previous shoulder joint surgery. There 
were 25 males (27 cases) and 24 females (24 cases) with 
an average age of 57.1 years (range, 36 to 75 years). Thirty-
nine cases involved the dominant shoulder and 12 cases 
involved the non-dominant shoulder. The mean follow-up 
period was 15.4 months (range, 12 to 18.3 months). 
The size of the tear was measured along the longest 
axis by using probes during surgery and the tear sizes were 
categorized into small (&lt; 1 cm), medium (1 cm to 3 cm), 
large (3 cm to 5 cm) and massive (&gt; 5 cm) tears according 
to the classification of DeOrio and Cofield. 8) </p>

<p>Assessment 
All of the physical examinations were performed the 
day before surgery and during the follow-up period. The 
measurements obtained at the last follow-up were used 
for analysis. Subjective pain was measured using the 
visual analogue scale (VAS). Muscle strength tests were 
performed using a Nottingham Mecmesin Myometer 
(Mecmesin Co., Nottingham, UK) and the values were 
recorded in kilograms (kg). Maximum elevation strength 
was measured with the arm elevated to 90° in the scapular 
plane and maximum external rotation strength and </p>



<p>Yi et al. Arthroscopic Suture Bridge Repair Technique for Full Thickness Rotator Cuff Tear </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery • Vol. 2, No. 2, 2010 • www.ecios.org </p>

<p>the suture limb that was loaded onto the inserted suture 
anchor was passed using the shuttle-relay. The suture limbs 
were spaced the same distance apart and Revo knots, one 
of the non-sliding knots, were tied in a horizontal mattress 
suture pattern. Suture bridge repair was then carried 
out by fixating one limb from each anchor to the lateral 
aspect of the greater tuberosity using a PushLock anchor 
(Arthrex). Postoperatively, a self-controlled analgesia de-
vice was used for all patients at their request. </p>

<p>Postoperative Rehabilitation 
Pendulum exercises and passive forward flexion were 
started immediately after surgery and passive exercise 
was performed until the 6th postoperative week to restore 
the normal range of motion. Active joint exercise and 
muscle strength exercise were performed from the 6th 
postoperative week. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis 
The pre-and postoperative clinical outcomes were com-
pared using paired t-tests and Wilcoxon signed rank tests. 
The Mann-Whitney test was used to assess differences re-
gard ing gender, age, range of motion and muscle strength 
in the groups, as divided according to the tear size, and the 
as sociation between the preoperative Global fatty de gen-
eration index (GFDI) and the final outcome. Correlation 
between the preoperative tear size and the retear rate was 
assessed using Pearson's chi-square test. Statistical analyses 
were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver.12.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, 
IL, USA) with a 95% confidence interval. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Pain and the Range of Motion 
The mean VAS score at rest decreased from 2.2 (0 to 7) 
preoperatively to 0.23 (0 to 2.5) postoperatively (p &lt; 0.001). 
The mean VAS score during motion improved from 6.3 (2 
to 9) preoperatively to 1.8 (0 to 7.5) postoperatively (p &lt; 
0.001). The mean range of active forward flexion increased 
from 138.4° preoperatively to 154.6° postoperatively and 
the mean range of passive forward flexion improved from 
143.4° to 161.9° (p = 0.04, 0.009). The mean external 
rotation in the neutral position was 50.4° preoperatively 
and 42.5° postoperatively (p = 0.052). The mean external 
rotation at 90° abduction was 70.7° preoperatively and 
78.3° post operatively and the mean internal rotation at 
90° ab duction was 63.4° preoperatively and 47.5° post-
operatively (p = 0.06, &lt; 0.001). The mean internal ro-
tation behind the back was T12 preoperatively and T10 
postoperatively (p = 0.021) (Table 1). </p>

<p>Muscle Strength 
The mean muscle strength during forward flexion in-
creased from 4.9 kg preoperatively to 6.0 kg post opera-
tively, during external rotation in the neutral position from 
6.5 kg to 6.9 kg (p = 0.038, 0.383), and during internal 
rotation in the neutral position from 7.8 kg to 8.6 kg (p = 
0.265). The improvement of the muscle strength during 
forward flexion was statistically significant. </p>

<p>Clinical Assessment 
The mean Constant score 9) improved from 73.2 (range, 
44 to 88) preoperatively to 83.7 (range, 20 to 99) post-
operatively (p = 0.001). The mean UCLA score increased 
from 18.2 preoperatively to 29.7 at the last follow-up (p &lt; 
0.001) and there were 7 (13.7%) excellent, 41 (80.4%) good, 
and 3 (5.9%) poor cases. The mean patient satisfaction 
score at the last follow-up was 92.1 out of the total 100 
points. </p>

<p>Postoperative Results Analyzed according to the Tear 
Size 
Eight (16%) small, 17 (33%) medium, 9 (18%) large and 
17 (33%) massive tears that were classified according to 
the classification of DeOrio and Cofield 8) were observed 
during arthroscopy. The small and medium tears were 
combined into one group and the large and massive 
tears were combined into another group, and the clinical 
outcomes at the last follow-up were compared between 
the 2 groups. The differences between the two groups 
regarding the preoperative age, gender, the level of pain at 
rest and during motion, and the muscle strength and range 
of motion during forward flexion did not show statistical 
significance (p = 0.124, 0.203, 0.673, 0.574, 0.056, and 
0.903, respectively). No significant difference was found 
between the groups regarding the postoperative retear 
rate (p = 0.109). Muscle strength during forward flexion 
at the last follow-up was more satisfactory in the small 
to medium tear group than that in the large to massive 
tear group (p = 0.029), but no significant differences were </p>

<p>Table 1. The Preoperative and Postoperative Range of Motion </p>

<p>FF (active) ERs 
ERa 
IRa 
IRp </p>

<p>Preoperative 
138.4° 
50.4° 
70.7° 
63.7° 
T12 </p>

<p>Postoperative 154.6° 
42.5° 
78.3° 
47.5° 
T10 </p>

<p>p-value 
0.04 
0.052 
0.06 
0.001 
0.021 </p>

<p>FF: Forward flexion, ERs: External rotation at the side, ERa: External rotation 
at abduction, IRa: Internal rotation at abduction, IRp: Internal rotation to the 
posterior. </p>



<p>Yi et al. Arthroscopic Suture Bridge Repair Technique for Full Thickness Rotator Cuff Tear </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery • Vol. 2, No. 2, 2010 • www.ecios.org </p>

<p>found with regard to the other parameters (Table 2). </p>

<p>Postoperative Results Analyzed according to 
Preoperative Fatty Degeneration 
According to the GFDI that was evaluated preoperatively 
using magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), 11) the patients 
were subdivided into those with ≤ 1 GFDI (21 cases) and 
those with &gt; 1 GFDI (30 cases). The postoperative pain at 
rest and during movement remarkably decreased in both 
groups (p &lt; 0.001). No significant difference was found 
between the groups regarding the preoperative VAS score 
for pain at rest and during movement (VAS) (p = 0.143, 
0.097, respectively). Postoperatively, the VAS score for 
pain at rest was notably low in the group with ≤ 1 GFDI 
(p = 0.043) (Table 3). With regard to the range of motion, 
active and passive forward flexion and external rotation 
in the neutral position were greater preoperatively in the 
group with ≤ 1 GFDI than that in the other group (p = 
0.003, 0.003, and 0.013, respectively), but no statistically 
significant difference was found between the groups 
postoperatively (p = 0.075, 0.396, and 0.799, respectively). 
The muscle strength, the clinical test results and the 
postoperative patient satisfaction were better on average 
in the group with ≤ 1 GFDI both preoperatively and 
postoperatively, but the difference was not statistically 
significant (p = 0.251, 0.198, and 0.348, respectively) </p>

<p>Postoperative Retear 
MRI scanning was performed in 46 of the 51 cases at an 
average of 7.2 months (range, 6 to 9 months) after surgery 
and retear was observed in 17 (36.9%) of them: 2 (28.6%) 
in the 7 patients with small tears, 4 (26.7%) in the 15 
patients with medium tears, 3 (33.3%) in the 9 patients </p>

<p>with large tears and 8 (53.3%) in the 15 patients with 
massive tears. The patients were divided into an anatomic 
restoration group and a retear group for comparisons. 
The Constant score 9) at the last follow-up was 84.8 and 
82.3 respectively and the UCLA score was 29.9 and 28.7 
respectively, showing no statistically significant difference 
between the groups (p = 0.189, 0.273). However, a signifi-
cant difference was found between the groups regarding 
the preoperative fatty degeneration, which was severe in 
the retear group (p = 0.048). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Advances have been made in performing surgical ro ta-
tor cuff repair and there are many recent studies showing 
excellent clinical outcomes. 12-15) Particularly, arthroscopy, 
which is associated with a good cosmetic appearance 
and rapid rehabilitation due to the minimal damages 
to adjacent structures, is employed in various medical 
fields. It is widely recommended for the treatment of the 
shoulder because there is no need to detach the deltoid 
muscle when performing arthroscopy. 13) 
The factors that appear to be determinants for re-
tear after repair and postoperative recovery include the 
suture strength, 4) the contact area and contact pressure at 
the tendon-bone interface, 16) the tendon-bone inter face 
motion, 17) fatty degeneration of the rotator cuff muscles, 18) 
the tear size, the bone quality of the humerus, the design 
and effect of the suture materials and the rehabilitation 
program's propriety. In open repairs, suture techniques 
with superior holding power such as the Mason-Allen 
technique 19) and transfixion suture are employed without 
difficulty. However, they are not easy to perform in 
arthroscopic rotator cuff repair and other materials such 
as suture anchors should be used instead. Unfortunately, 
biomechanical studies have shown that the arthroscopic 
single-row suture anchor technique allows weaker </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparison of the Clinical Outcomes between the Small-</p>

<p>Medium and Large-Massive Sized Tear Groups </p>

<p>Postoperative 
Small to 
medium 
Large to 
massive 
p-value </p>

<p>Cases 
25 
26 </p>

<p>VAS 
1.7 
2.0 
0.541 </p>

<p>FF (active) 
159° 
150.4° 
0.287 </p>

<p>Muscle strength (FF) 
6.8 kg 
5.3 kg 
0.029 </p>

<p>Constant score 
86.6 
80.7 
0.13 </p>

<p>UCLA score 
30.6 
28.7 
0.12 </p>

<p>VAS: Visual analogue scale, FF: Forward flexion, UCLA: University of California 
at Los Angeles. </p>

<p>Table 3. Differences of the Pain VAS according to the GFDI </p>

<p>Pain VAS 
p-value 
GFDI ≤ 1 GFDI &gt; 1 </p>

<p>Preoperative 
Rest 
1.67 
2.57 
0.143 </p>

<p>Motion 
5.71 
6.7 
0.097 </p>

<p>Postoperative 
Rest 
0.048 
0.35 
0.043 </p>

<p>Motion 
1.67 
1.91 
0.420 </p>

<p>VAS: Visual analogue scale, GFDI: Global fatty degeneration index. </p>



<p>Yi et al. Arthroscopic Suture Bridge Repair Technique for Full Thickness Rotator Cuff Tear </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery • Vol. 2, No. 2, 2010 • www.ecios.org </p>

<p>fixation than the established transfixion suture does. 17,20) 
The concept of footprint reconstruction was recently 
introduced and Apreleva et al. 21) evaluated the 3-dimen-
sional structures of the rotator cuff insertion sites after 
repairs using various techniques and they described that 
the larger the interface was, the better was the potential 
for tendon-bone healing and the strength of the repaired 
tendon. Thereafter, several arthroscopic repair techniques 
that provide greater holding power, interface area and 
contact pressure have been developed and the arthroscopic 
suture bridge technique is one of them. 22-24) While the 
arthroscopic suture bridge technique has been described 
in many biomechanical reports as being more effective 
for obtaining high initial fixation strength and greater 
interface area and pressure than the other suture methods, 
studies analyzing the clinical results of such repairs are 
rare. 6,7,25) 
Regarding the factors influencing the clinical out-
come of rotator cuff repair, Kim et al. 1) reported that the 
final outcome was more dependent on the preoperative 
tear size rather than the surgical technique. With regard to 
the rotator cuff integrity and the shoulder function, some 
authors have documented that they could not find a clear 
correlation between them, 22,26,27) while others suggested 
that great rotator cuff integrity would result in satisfying 
shoulder function. 23,24,28,29) Gazielly et al. 23) associated the 
anatomical integrity of the rotator cuff and the clinical 
out come: the larger the early tear size was the worse the 
clinical outcome was. In this current study, arthroscopic 
suture bridge repairs for various sizes of rotator cuff tears 
re sulted in improvement in pain, range of motion and 
muscle strength, and the differences in the clinical im-
prove ment, except for muscle strength during forward 
flexion, were not statistically significant between the small 
and medium size tear group and the large and massive 
size tear group. In addition, postoperative MRI showed no 
differences between the groups regarding the recurrence 
rate (p = 0.109). We attribute this to the anatomical integ-
rity of the rotator cuff, which could be obtained with the 
ar throscopic suture bridge technique regardless of the pre-
operative tear size. Therefore, we believe that this clinical 
study confirmed the advantages of the arthroscopic suture 
bridge technique, and this technique has been previously 
established by many biomechanical studies: the firm, early </p>

<p>fixation and high tendon-bone contact pressure provided 
by the repair method contributes to the repaired cuff 's 
integrity even in the cases of large size tears. 5-7,25) 
Preoperative fatty degeneration is known as an im-
portant factor for the anatomical integrity of the repaired 
rotator cuff. According to Goutallier et al., 11) severe fatty 
degeneration was correlated with an unsatisfactory surgical 
outcome and a high retear rate. Similarly, radiological 
retears were identified in the patients who had severer fatty 
de generation in our study. However, the retear rate and 
preoperative fatty degeneration were not correlated with 
each other at a statistically significant level for the clinical 
tests, which is contrary to the study of Goutallier et al. 11) 
In our opinion, this is because the suture bridge technique 
was not as much affected by the level of preoperative fatty 
degeneration as the other methods. 
In this study, we analyzed the final clinical results of 
the arthroscopic suture bridge technique for rotator cuff 
repair and we confirmed clinical improvements in the 
repaired shoulders regardless of the preoperative tear size 
and the level of fatty degeneration. However, we think that 
studies involving a larger population, long-term follow-
up and comparisons with other suture techniques should 
be conducted in the future to determine the magnitude 
of the contribution of the technique to the integrity of the 
shoulder and the clinical improvement. 
The arthroscopic suture bridge technique for rota-
tor cuff repair resulted in clinical improvement in pain, 
the range of motion and muscle strength regardless of the 
pre operative tear size and fatty degeneration, al though 
radiologically detected retears were found in the patients 
with severer preoperative fatty degeneration. This tech-
nique can be applied when a large tear has to be treated 
or when the established methods such as the single-row 
suture technique will not achieve satisfying results due 
to advanced fatty degeneration. In addition, the clinical 
improvement that can be obtained with this method is ex-
pected to be less affected by the tear size and fatty degen-
eration. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was 
reported. </p>









<p>Yi et al. Arthroscopic Suture Bridge Repair Technique for Full Thickness Rotator Cuff Tear </p>



</text></tei>