<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2453617" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVE-Many prevalent diseases of advanced societies, 
such as obesity-induced type 2 diabetes, are linked to indolent 
mononuclear cell-dependent inflammation. We previously pro-
posed that blockade of ␣4 integrin signaling can inhibit inflam-
mation while limiting mechanism-based toxicities of loss of ␣4 
function. Thus, we hypothesized that mice bearing an ␣4(Y991A) 
mutation, which blocks signaling, would be protected from 
development of high-fat diet-induced insulin resistance. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS-Six-to eight-week-
old wild-type and ␣4(Y991A) C57Bl/6 male mice were placed on 
either a high-fat diet that derived 60% calories from lipids or a 
chow diet. Metabolic testing was performed after 16 -22 weeks of 
diet. </p>

<p>RESULTS-␣4(Y991A) mice were protected from development 
of high-fat diet-induced insulin resistance. This protection was 
conferred on wild-type mice by ␣4(Y991A) bone marrow trans-
plantation. In the reverse experiment, wild-type bone marrow 
renders high-fat diet-fed ␣4(Y991A) acceptor animals insulin 
resistant. Furthermore, fat-fed ␣4(Y991A) mice showed a dra-
matic reduction of monocyte/macrophages in adipose tissue. 
This reduction was due to reduced monocyte/macrophage migra-
tion rather than reduced monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 
production. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS-␣4 integrins contribute to the development of 
HFD-induced insulin resistance by mediating the trafficking of 
monocytes into adipose tissue; hence, blockade of ␣4 integrin 
signaling can prevent the development of obesity-induced insulin 
resistance. Diabetes 57:1842-1851, 2008 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>besity leads to insulin resistance that results in 
type 2 diabetes (1) and that contributes to 
hypertension and cardiovascular disease (2). 
Mononuclear cell-mediated inflammation in 
obese adipose tissue plays a pathogenetic role in insulin 
resistance (3,4). Thus, there is great interest in the possi-
bility of using anti-inflammatory strategies to ameliorate 
obesity-induced insulin resistance. 
Blockade of leukocyte adhesion is a proven therapeutic 
strategy for a wide variety of inflammatory diseases (5). In </p>

<p>particular, inhibiting ␣4 integrins or their counter-
receptors (vascular cell adhesion molecule-1 [VCAM-1] 
and mucosal adressin cell adhesion molecule-1 [MadCAM-
1]) blocks inflammatory responses mediated by mononu-
clear leukocytes (6). ␣4 integrin antagonists are of proven 
benefit in several human inflammatory diseases (7,8). 
These antagonists, such as the monoclonal antibody na-
talizumab, block ligand binding function, thus producing a 
complete loss of ␣4 integrin function. Lack of ␣4 integrins 
is embryonic lethal and results in defective placentation, 
heart development, and hematopoiesis (9 -11). Further-
more, natalizumab therapy has been associated with fatal 
progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy in humans, 
possibly because of defective T-cell trafficking to the brain 
(12,13). Thus, currently available ␣4 integrin antagonists 
are of proven value in mononuclear cell-mediated dis-
eases; however, complete loss of ␣4 integrin function is 
associated with developmental defects and abnormal 
hematopoiesis. 
As noted above, whereas ␣4 integrin antagonists show 
promise for several autoimmune and inflammatory dis-
eases, mechanism-based toxicities may limit their use, 
particularly in low-grade chronic inflammatory conditions, 
such as obesity-induced insulin resistance. We recently 
proposed an alternative strategy-blockade of ␣4 integrin 
signaling-to perturb functions involved in inflammation, 
while limiting mechanism-based adverse effects (14). ␣4 
integrin signaling involves the binding of paxillin to the ␣4 
integrin tail, and a point mutation (␣4Y991A) that selec-
tively blocks this interaction reduces ␣4-mediated leuko-
cyte migration (15) and adhesion strengthening in flowing 
blood (16) while sparing ␣4-mediated static cell adhesion 
(17). Furthermore, mice bearing an ␣4(Y991A) mutation 
are viable and fertile and have intact lympho-hematopoie-
sis and humoral immune responses; however, they exhibit 
defective recruitment of mononuclear leukocytes in exper-
imental inflammation (18). Here, we report that the 
␣4(Y991A) mutation reduces mononuclear leukocyte infil-
tration of white adipose tissue (WAT) in high-fat diet-
induced obese mice and hence reduce high-fat diet-
induced insulin resistance. Thus, we establish that 
blocking ␣4 integrin signaling can ameliorate the meta-
bolic consequences of high-fat diet-induced obesity. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>Animals and animal care. The ␣4(Y991A) mice were previously described 
and have been backcrossed nine times onto the C57BL/6 background (18). We 
fed male mice (aged 6 -8 weeks) either on high-fat diet, containing 60% fat by 
weight (D12492; Research Diets) or on chow diet (10% fat; D12450B; Research 
Diets) for 16 -22 weeks. All experiments were approved by the University of 
California San Diego Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee. 
Glucose and insulin tolerance tests. We carried out glucose tolerance tests 
(GTTs) and insulin tolerance tests (ITTs) as described previously (19) (see </p>

<p>From the 
supplemental methods in the online appendix available at http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.2337/db07-1751). 
Whole-blood and plasma measurements. Total white blood cell number 
and differential counts were assessed by standard techniques (ACP Diagnostic 
Lab, University of California, San Diego). We measured plasma insulin by 
radioimmunoassay (Linco Research) and determined free fatty acids by 
colorimetric assay (Wako). Plasma cytokines were measured by the core 
laboratories of the Diabetes and Endocrinology Research Consortium (Uni-
versity of California, Los Angeles; LINCOplex assay for Mouse Cytokines, 
http://www.derc.med.ucla.edu/core.htm). Plasma cholesterol and triglyceride 
levels were measured by enzymatic methods using an automated bichromatic 
analyzer (Abbot Diagnostics). All of these measurements were performed on 
11 wild-type and 9 ␣4(Y991A) mice for high-fat diet and 6 wild-type and 5 
␣4(Y991A) mice for chow diet (Table 1). 
Histochemistry. Adipose tissue was fixed overnight in 10% formaldehyde, 
dehydrated in ethanol bath, and paraffin-embedded. Sections were stained 
with hematoxylin-eosin (H-E) for observation of adipose tissue structure. 
Pancreas isolation and determination of islet area. Pancreata were 
isolated and fixed in 4% formalin overnight. Paraffin sections were generated 
and stained with H-E. Pictures were taken of H-E-stained pancreas sections, 
and the area of Langerhans islets and the total area of the pancreas were 
measured using <rs id="software-0" type="software">ImageJ</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">NIH</rs> freeware). Islet area was depicted as 
percentage of total pancreas area. Sections of four to seven mice per group 
and at least six different pancreas areas per mouse were analyzed for 
statistical significance using unpaired two-tailed Student's t test. P values 
Ͻ0.05 were considered significant. 
Bone marrow transplantation. We injected bone marrow obtained from 
wild-type and ␣4(Y991A) mice (4 ϫ 10 
6 cells) through the tail vein into male 
C57BL/6 (4 months) and ␣4(Y991A) (4 -6 months) mice that had been 
irradiated (10 Gy) 4 h before. Mice were allowed 4 weeks for reconstitution of 
donor marrow, which we verified by PCR (18). 
Isolation of stromal vascular cells. Epidydimal fat pads were minced in 
PBS and digested with collagenase (Roche) and DNase I (Sigma) for 1 h at 37°C. 
Suspensions were then filtered through a 100-m nylon cell strainer and 
then spun at 1,000g for 10 min. The preadipocyte/adipocyte-enriched fraction 
was removed. Isolated stromal vascular cells were resuspended in red blood 
cell lysis buffer (10 mmol/l KHCO 3 , 150 mmol/l NH 4 Cl, and 0.1 mmol/l EDTA, 
pH 8) for 5 min at room temperature. Cell suspension was centrifuged for 5 
min at 500g, and stromal vascular cells were resuspended in PBS at 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>cells/100 l. 
Flow cytometry. Cells were harvested from WAT, peripheral blood, and bone 
marrow and incubated in Fc blocker (rat anti-mouse CD16/32) for 20 min at 
room temperature. The cells were then incubated with fluorescein isothiocya-
nate (FITC)-Ly-6G (1/200) and phycoerythrin (PE)-7/4 (1/50) (BD Biosciences/ 
PharMingen, San Diego, CA). Negative control staining was performed with 
FITC-rat IgG2a/k and PE-rat IgG2a. Cell staining was analyzed with FACScan 
flow cytometer using <rs id="software-1" type="software">CellQuest</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">BD Biosciences Systems</rs>). 
Cell migration assay. Cell migration was assayed in a modified Boyden 
chamber system using a 24-well transwell plate (8-m pore size; Corning) 
coated with 5 g/ml VCAM-1 (R&amp;D Systems). Monocyte chemoattractant 
protein-1 (MCP-1) (R&amp;D Systems) was added in the lower chamber at 1 
nmol/l. Cells harvested from wild-type or ␣4(Y991A) bone marrow were 
grown for 5-7 days in the presence of granulocyte macrophage-colony-
stimulating factor (5 l of 0.1 mg/ml stock solution). Bone marrow-derived 
macrophages (2 ϫ 10 
4 ) were kept in suspension in 1% serum containing 
medium for 1 h at room temperature. Cells were then added to the top </p>

<p>chamber and incubated overnight at 37°C. Filters were fixed and stained with 
crystal violet, and migrated cells in the lower chamber were enumerated. 
RNA isolation and RT-PCR. Total RNA was isolated from WAT using 
RNeasy Lipid Tissue kit (Qiagen). RT-PCRs were carried out as described in 
the online appendix (20). 
Statistical analysis. Means and SEs were calculated for all dependent 
measures. Data were analyzed for statistical significance using the one-or 
two-tailed Student's t test. Significance was set at P Յ 0.05. For Fig. 1B, change 
scores for the chow diet and high-fat diet data were determined using the total 
area under the curve (AUC) (21). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>␣4(Y991A) mutation is protective against the development 
of high-fat diet-induced glucose intolerance and insulin 
resistance. To investigate the role(s) of integrin ␣4 inter-
action with paxillin in ␣4-mediated functions in vivo, we 
previously generated and analyzed mice bearing a point 
mutation in the ␣4 integrin tail (Y991A) that inhibits 
paxillin binding with little detectable effect on the binding 
of other proteins (18). To examine the potential effect of 
this mutation on a model of human type 2 diabetes, these 
␣4(Y991A) mice and wild-type controls were placed on a 
60% fat diet for 16 -22 weeks. On this diet, wild-type 
animals developed impaired glucose tolerance (Fig. 1A). In 
contrast, mice bearing the ␣4(Y991A) mutation were par-
tially protected against high-fat diet-induced glucose in-
tolerance (Fig. 1A; Supplemental Fig. 1A). The increased 
glucose tolerance in the high-fat diet-fed ␣4(Y991A) ani-
mals was not due to greater insulin release because these 
mice released significantly less insulin than high-fat diet-
fed wild-type animals (P ϭ 0.036) (Fig. 1B.). The wild-type 
mice showed a greater increase in pancreatic ␤-cells than 
those bearing the ␣4(Y991A) mutation (Fig. 1C) in re-
sponse to the high-fat diet. Because increased ␤-cells is an 
early manifestation of insulin resistance (22), these find-
ings strongly suggested that the ␣4(Y991A) mutation 
helped preserve sensitivity to insulin in fat-fed animals. 
This idea was confirmed by the finding that the high-fat 
diet-fed mutant mice showed a much greater insulin-
induced drop in blood glucose than the high-fat diet-fed 
wild-type mice (Fig. 1D). Thirty minutes after administra-
tion of 0.85 units/kg insulin, plasma glucose decreased by 
43% in the mutant fat-fed animals compared with a 28% 
decline in wild-type animals. In contrast, the chow-fed 
animals of both genotypes exhibited a 37% decline at 30 
min (0.75 units/kg insulin injected). At later time points, 
there was a statistically insignificant trend of greater 
insulin-induced drop in chow-fed ␣4(Y991A) animals ver-</p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Plasma measurements of lipids and adipokines in wild-type and ␣4(Y991A) mice </p>

<p>Normal chow diet 
High-fat diet 
Genotype 
Wild type 
Y991A 
Wild type 
Y991A </p>

<p>n 
6 
5 
10 
9 
Plasma free fatty acids (mol ⅐ l 
Ϫ1 ⅐ ml 
Ϫ1 ) 
0.71 Ϯ 0.23 
0.44 Ϯ 0.07 
0.89 Ϯ 0.15 
0.61 Ϯ 0.09 
Total cholesterol (mg/dl) 
132.2 Ϯ 5.9 
130.0 Ϯ 2.7 
238.7 Ϯ 10.5* 
203.0 Ϯ 27.9* 
Plasma triglycerides (mg/dl) 
41.2 Ϯ 2.5 
42.7 Ϯ 2.4 
42.4 Ϯ 2.6 
46.6 Ϯ 4.6 
MCP-1 (pg/ml) 
22.0 Ϯ 3.5 
25.67 Ϯ 6.1 
43.25 Ϯ 16.6 
47.0 Ϯ 20.5 
Adiponectin (g ⅐ ml 
Ϫ1 ⅐ g 
Ϫ1 ) 
1.13 Ϯ 0.22 
1.37 Ϯ 0.04 
0.63 Ϯ 0.05* 
0.68 Ϯ 0.03* 
Leptin (pg/ml) 
3,699 Ϯ 465 
4,129 Ϯ 723 
14,038 Ϯ 1,219* 
10,222 Ϯ 1,878* 
IL-6 (pg/ml) 
0.63 Ϯ 0.01 
0.89 Ϯ 0.09 
1.51 Ϯ 0.68 
1.62 Ϯ 0.44 
Resistin (pg/ml) 
900.3 Ϯ 60.6 
1,104.3 Ϯ 67.4 
1,446.4 Ϯ 108.6 
1,270.8 Ϯ 68.6 
TNF-␣ (pg/ml) 
2.61 Ϯ 0.28 
2.41 Ϯ 0.31 
3.16 Ϯ 0.27 
3.28 Ϯ 0.49 </p>

<p>Data are means Ϯ SE. n values per group are indicated. *Significant difference between diet within genotype. None of these parameters were 
statistically different between genotypes. </p>

<p>C.C. FÉ RAL AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, JULY 2008 </p>

<p>
0 </p>

<p>20 
40 
60 
80 
100 
120 
140 </p>

<p>Glucose (mg/dl) </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>WT 
YA </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
80 
100 
120 
140 </p>

<p>Glucose (mg/dL) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>175 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>225 </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
80 
100 
120 
140 </p>

<p>Glucose (mg/dL) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>WT HFD 
YA HFD 
WT Chow 
YA Chow </p>

<p>n=10 </p>

<p>n=5 </p>

<p>n=6 </p>

<p>n=8 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>HFD 
Chow </p>

<p>WT HFD 
YA HFD </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>** 
* 
* </p>

<p>n=11 </p>

<p>n=5 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>n=6 </p>

<p>n=6 </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>ns 
ns </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>ns 
ns </p>

<p>ns 
ns 
ns </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>Chow YA 
Chow wt 
HFD wt HFD YA </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>p=0.036 </p>

<p>Insulin Area under the curve </p>

<p>(ng/ml/90min) </p>

<p>Time following insulin injection (min) 
Time following insulin injection (min) </p>

<p>WT 
YA </p>

<p>Chow 
YA </p>

<p>Chow 
wt </p>

<p>HFD 
wt </p>

<p>HFD 
YA </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>p=0.012 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Islet area (in %) </p>

<p>FIG. 1. ␣4(Y991A) mutation protects mice against the development of high-fat diet-induced glucose intolerance and insulin resistance. A: In vivo 
glucose homeostasis was assessed by GTT in wild-type (ⅷ) and ␣4(Y991A) mice (□) on high-fat diet (plain symbols) and normal chow (dotted 
symbols). The results shown are means ؎ SE for each time point. B: Plasma insulin concentrations during GTT were collected. They are 
represented as total AUC, which was calculated using the trapezoidal method (see RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS for details). C: Size of pancreatic 
␤-cell islets (right) in wild-type (closed) and ␣4(Y991A) (open) mice was measured. Representative H-E staining of wild-type and ␣4(Y991A) 
pancreas is also shown (left). Arrowheads indicate pancreatic islets. D: ITT was performed in wild-type (ⅷ) and ␣4(Y991A) mice (□) on high-fat 
diet (HFD; left) and normal chow (Chow; right). Plasma glucose was significantly higher in wild-type mice fed high-fat diet than in all other groups 
during both the GTTs and ITTs. No significant differences in plasma insulin during the GTT were found between the wild-type and ␣4(Y991A) mice 
on chow diet. Plasma insulin and percentage of pancreatic ␤-cell islets were significantly higher in the wild-type mice after high-fat diet. n values 
per group are indicated. *P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; ns, not significant. </p>

<p>PREVENTING OBESITY-INDUCED INSULIN RESISTANCE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, JULY 2008 </p>

<p>sus wild type. Thus, the ␣4(Y991A) mutation protects 
against high-fat diet-induced insulin resistance. 
The ␣4(Y991A) mutation did not affect caloric intake 
or weight gain. Both wild-type and ␣4(Y991A) mice 
exhibited the same caloric intake on high-fat diet (Fig. 2A, 
left), which was about 1.5-fold higher than on chow diet 
(Fig. 2A, right). Consistent with similar caloric intake, no 
differences in weight gain were observed between wild-
type and ␣4(Y991A) mice (Fig. 2B, left and right). Animals 
were weight matched before starting the 16 weeks of diet 
[average starting weight for high-fat diet, 27.8 Ϯ 0.6 and 
27.3 Ϯ 1.0 g for wild type and ␣4(Y991A), respectively; for 
chow diet, 27.8 Ϯ 1.3 and 28.8 Ϯ 1.6 g for wild type and 
␣4(Y991A), respectively]). Gross histological analysis of 
WAT isolated from high-fat diet-fed wild-type and 
␣4(Y991A) mice showed no statistical difference in adipo-
cyte size or number (Fig. 2C; Supplemental Fig. 1B). 
Plasma levels of free fatty acids and triglycerides were 
similar between wild-type and ␣4(Y991A) mice on both 
diets (Table 1). Wild-type mice exhibited increased plasma 
cholesterol on high-fat diet (238.7 Ϯ 10.5 mg/dl) in com-
parison with those on chow diet (132.2 Ϯ 5.9 mg/dl). The 
␣4(Y991A) mice on high-fat diet exhibited a statistically 
insignificant trend to a lesser rise in cholesterol (203.0 Ϯ 
27.9 vs. 130.0 Ϯ 2.7 mg/dl, high-fat diet vs. chow diet), 
which may reflect a decrease in LDL levels. Plasma 
adiponectin concentrations decreased to similar levels in 
both high-fat-fed wild-type and ␣4(Y991A) mice. Plasma 
leptin and resistin levels increased after high-fat diet, but 
no differences were found between genotypes (Table 1). 
High-fat diet-fed ␣4(Y991A) mice exhibited similar plasma 
expression of proinflammatory cytokines, such as interleu-
kin-6 (IL-6), tumor necrosis factor-␣ (TNF-␣), and MCP-1, 
compared with wild-type mice (Table 1). 
Bone marrow-derived cells are responsible for pro-
tection from high-fat diet-induced insulin resistance. 
Even though ␣4 integrin is not present at the surface of 
adipocytes (data not shown), it is widely expressed (23,24) 
and is particularly prominent in the functioning of mono-
nuclear leukocytes. Moreover, bone marrow-derived 
mononuclear cells contribute to insulin resistance (3,4,25). 
To determine whether the protection against high-fat 
diet-induced insulin resistance in the ␣4(Y991A) mice is 
mediated through bone marrow-derived cells, we per-
formed bone marrow transplantation (BMT) experiments. 
Six-to eight-week-old lethally irradiated (10 Gy) wild-type 
male mice received bone marrow cells from either wild-
type or ␣4(Y991A) donor mice via tail vein injection. 
Recipient mice were allowed 4 weeks for recovery and 
reconstitution of the transplanted bone marrow and were 
then placed on high-fat diet for 16 -22 weeks before 
metabolic experiments. Posttransplant chimerism was 
evaluated by PCR on both groups. No wild-type ␣4 was 
detected in blood collected from mice receiving bone 
marrow from ␣4(Y991A) mice [␣4(Y991A)-BMT]. Mice 
transplanted with wild-type and ␣4 mutant [␣4(Y991A)-
BMT] bone marrow gained equal amounts of weight on 
high-fat diet compared with normal chow (data not 
shown). Levels of plasma fatty acids, cholesterol, triglyc-
erides, adiponectin, and leptin were similar between ge-
notypes (data not shown). 
Wild-type mice that received ␣4(Y991A) bone marrow 
were partially protected against high-fat diet-induced glu-
cose intolerance (Fig. 3A) and insulin resistance (Fig. 3B) 
compared with wild-type animals that received wild-type 
bone marrow. When animals were fed a normal diet, </p>

<p>glucose tolerance was similar in mutant and wild-type 
transplanted mice (Fig. 3A), but there was a statistically 
insignificant trend toward increased insulin sensitivity in 
chow-fed ␣4(Y991A) compared with wild-type marrow 
recipients (Fig. 3C). In reverse BMT experiments, i.e., 
transplantation of wild-type bone marrow into lethally 
irradiated ␣4(Y991A) mice, no mutant allele was detected 
in ␣4(Y991A) animals receiving wild-type bone marrow, 
confirming complete reconstitution of wild-type bone mar-
row in these animals. Wild-type marrow made ␣4(Y991A) 
acceptor mice susceptible to glucose intolerance (Supple-
mental Fig. 2). Thus, bone marrow-derived cells are 
responsible for the observed protection of ␣4(Y991A) mice 
from high-fat diet-induced insulin resistance. 
The ␣4(Y991A) mutation leads to a decrease in adi-
pose tissue monocyte/macrophages in high-fat diet-
fed mice. The foregoing experiments showed that the 
effect of the ␣4(Y991A) mutation was manifest through 
bone marrow-derived cells. Among bone marrow-derived 
cells, ␣4 integrin is highly expressed on most mononuclear 
leukocytes (26). Monocyte/macrophages are bone marrow-
derived mononuclear cells that mediate the inflammatory 
response to high-fat diet, and macrophages contribute to 
the pathogenesis of obesity-induced insulin resistance 
(25,27). We therefore used flow cytometry to quantify the 
presence of monocyte subpopulations, defined by the level 
of expression of surface markers 7/4 and Ly6-G (28) in the 
stromal vascular fraction (SVF) of WAT isolated from 
wild-type and ␣4(Y991A) mice on chow or high-fat diet. 
We used a combination of Ly-6G and 7/4 markers, de-
scribed by Tsou et al. (28), which define a cell population 
uniformly positive for F4/80, CD11b, and CC chemokine 
receptor 2 for CCL2/MCP-1 (CCR2) and phenotypically 
identical to the inflammatory monocytes previously de-
scribed (29 -32). 
The accumulation of macrophages, associated with obe-
sity-induced insulin resistance, occurs predominantly in 
epididymal WAT (25,33); hence we studied WAT from this 
site. High-fat diet-fed ␣4(Y991A) mice exhibited a marked 
reduction in the number of monocytes (7/4 
hi Ly-6G </p>

<p>neg </p>

<p>) 
compared with high-fat diet-fed wild-type mice (0.8 Ϯ 0.13 
vs. 2.88 Ϯ 0.49%) (Fig. 4A, top left panel) in WAT SVF. This 
phenomenon was also observed (Fig. 4A, bottom left 
panel) with 7/4 </p>

<p>dim </p>

<p>Ly-6G 
neg cells (mixed monocyte/lympho-
cytes) (Y991A 3.77 Ϯ 1.43% vs. wild type 7.6 Ϯ 1.11%). In 
contrast, when fed a normal diet, wild-type and ␣4(Y991A) 
mice had similar percentages of both 7/4 
hi Ly-6G 
neg and 
7/4 
dim Ly-6G 
neg cells in their WAT SVF (Fig. 4A, right 
panels). These results were confirmed by the reduction in 
mRNA for F4/80, a macrophage marker, in WAT from 
fat-fed ␣4(Y991A) mice compared with wild-type mice 
(Supplemental Fig. 1C). Thus, the ␣4(Y991A) mutation 
leads to a reduction in monocyte/macrophage accumula-
tion in the WAT SVF in response to high-fat diet. 
WAT monocyte/macrophages derive in part from periph-
eral blood monocytes, which in turn are derived from 
the bone marrow. To investigate the cause of the 
reduced monocyte/macrophage accumulation in WAT of 
␣4(Y991A) mice, we quantified monocyte subpopula-
tions in the peripheral blood and in the bone marrow of 
wild-type and ␣4(Y991A) mice. In the high-fat diet-fed 
mice, there was a reduction in the percentage (1.4 Ϯ 
0.28 vs. 2.9 Ϯ 0.38% for Y991A and wild type, respec-
tively) and absolute number of monocytes in the periph-
eral blood of ␣4(Y991A) mice (Fig. 4A and B). In 
contrast, there was no significant difference in the </p>

<p>C.C. FÉ RAL AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, JULY 2008 </p>

<p>
B </p>

<p>Time on diet (weeks) </p>

<p>2 
4 
6 
8 
1 0 
1 2 
1 4 
1 6 </p>

<p>Body growth rate (% of BW week 0) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>YA 
WT </p>

<p>2 
4 
6 
8 
1 0 
1 2 
1 4 
1 6 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>YA 
WT </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Weeks on Diet </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
6 
8 
1 0 
1 2 
1 4 
1 6 
1 8 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>WT 
YA </p>

<p>Weeks on Diet </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
6 
8 
10 
12 
14 
16 
18 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>WT 
YA </p>

<p>HFD 
Chow </p>

<p>HFD 
Chow </p>

<p>WT 
YA </p>

<p>HFD </p>

<p>n=9 </p>

<p>n=10 </p>

<p>n=10 </p>

<p>n=4 </p>

<p>n=10 
n=4 </p>

<p>n=9 </p>

<p>n=10 </p>

<p>Body growth rate (% of BW week 0) </p>

<p>Time on diet (weeks) </p>

<p>Calorie intake (in kcal) </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Normal caloric intake, weight gain, and adipocyte size in ␣4(Y991A) mice compared with wild-type mice after high-fat diet. Calorie intake 
(A) and weight gain (B) were measured in wild type (ࠗ) and ␣4(Y991A) (f) mice on high-fat diet (HFD; left) and normal chow (chow; right). 
C: H-E staining of WAT isolated from wild type (WT) and ␣4(Y991A) (YA) mice was performed. No significant difference was observed between 
genotypes within diet. n values are indicated. </p>

<p>PREVENTING OBESITY-INDUCED INSULIN RESISTANCE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, JULY 2008 </p>

<p>percentage of pure or mixed monocyte populations in 
the bone marrow of high-fat diet-fed wild-type and 
␣4(Y991A) mice (Fig. 4A). Similarly, a slight monocyto-
penia was observed in the peripheral blood of normal 
chow-fed ␣4(Y991A) mice (1.71 Ϯ 0.13 vs. 2.39 Ϯ 0.12% 
for Y991A and wild type, respectively), and there was no 
significant difference in abundance of 7/4 
hi Ly-6G 
neg and 
7/4 
dim Ly-6G 
neg cells in the bone marrow (Fig. 4). Taken 
together, these data suggest that the ␣4(Y991A) muta-
tion does not impair monocyte development. Rather, 
they suggest that the mutation reduces mobilization of 
these cells. These data do not define the relative contri-
butions of reduced egress from the bone marrow and 
entry into the adipose tissue in high-fat diet-fed mice in 
the observed reduced macrophage accumulation in 
␣4(Y991A) WAT. 
␣4(Y991A) monocyte/macrophages exhibit reduced 
chemotaxis toward MCP-1. MCP-1 is an important 
monocyte chemoattractant and is particularly implicated 
in the mobilization of monocytes from the bone marrow 
and the infiltration of adipose tissue with monocyte/ 
macrophages (34,35). Thus, we hypothesized that the 
decreased 7/4 
hi Ly-6G 
neg and 7/4 
dim Ly-6G 
neg cells in WAT of 
high-fat diet-fed ␣4(Y991A) mice could be due to impaired 
migration in response to this chemokine. ␣4(Y991A) bone 
marrow-derived macrophages showed reduced ␣4 inte-
grin-dependent MCP-1-driven migration relative to wild-
type cells (Fig. 5A). Thus, impaired ␣4 integrin-dependent 
monocyte/macrophage migration can account for the de-
creased number of monocyte/macrophages detected in 
WAT of fat-fed ␣4(Y991A) mice. 
Chemokines, such as MCP-1, are produced by macro-
phages, endothelial cells, and adipocytes (4,36,37). De-
ficiency in MCP-1 production and/or secretion could 
also contribute to an impairment of monocyte/macro-
phages migration into adipose tissue (4). Circulating 
MCP-1 was increased approximately twofold after high-
fat diet, but no significant difference was observed 
between genotypes (Table 1). The relative expression of 
MCP-1 was also evaluated in the WAT of ␣4(Y991A) and 
wild-type mice by RT-PCR (Fig. 5B). As expected from 
the circulating level of MCP-1, no difference was ob-
served in MCP-1 mRNA expression in epididymal WAT 
between genotype in high-fat diet-fed mice (Fig. 5B). 
Thus, we ascribe the reduction in monocyte/macro-
phages in WAT in high-fat diet-fed mice to an impaired 
migratory response to MCP-1 rather than to reduced 
production of this chemokine. 
The amelioration of insulin resistance in high-fat diet-
fed ␣4(Y991A) mice appears to depend on reduction of 
monocyte/macrophages in WAT; these cells are the source 
of cytokines, such as TNF-␣ and IL-6. Abdominal adipose 
gene expression levels of TNF-␣, IL-6, plasminogen acti-
vator inhibitor 1 (PAI-1), and leptin are positively linked 
with insulin resistance. Levels of proinflammatory cyto-
kines TNF-␣ and IL6 were strikingly reduced (70 and 55%, 
respectively) in ␣4(Y991A) compared with wild-type WAT 
(Fig. 5C). In contrast, we observed similar levels for 
fat-derived peptides leptin and PAI-1 in wild-type and 
␣4(Y991A) WAT. Thus, the reduction in monocyte/macro-
phages in WAT in high-fat diet-fed ␣4(Y991A) mice leads 
to reduced production of pro-inflammatory cytokines 
(TNF-␣ and IL-6) in WAT. </p>

<p>Glucose (mg/dL) </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>WT 
YA </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 
WT 
YA </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
80 
100 
120 
140 </p>

<p>WT HFD 
YA HFD 
WT Chow 
YA Chow </p>

<p>HFD </p>

<p>Chow </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>BMT </p>

<p>* 
* 
** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** *** 
*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>n=8 </p>

<p>n=8 </p>

<p>n=3 </p>

<p>n=3 </p>

<p>n=4 
n=5 </p>

<p>n=4 </p>

<p>n=4 </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>ns 
ns 
ns 
ns 
ns 
ns </p>

<p>Glucose (mg/dL) </p>

<p>Glucose (mg/dL) </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>Time after insulin administration (min) </p>

<p>Time after insulin administration (min) </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
80 
100 
120 
140 </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
80 
100 
120 
140 </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Bone marrow cells from ␣4(Y991A) mice are sufficient for 
protection against high-fat diet-induced insulin resistance. GTTs (A) 
and ITTs (B and C) were performed in wild-type mice that received 
bone marrow from either wild-type (ⅷ) or ␣4(Y991A) (□) donors. 
Recipient animals were on high-fat diet (HFD; plain symbols) or normal 
chow (Chow; dotted symbols). The results shown are means ؎ SE for 
each time point. Plasma glucose was significantly lower in high-fat 
diet-fed wild-type mice that received ␣4(Y991A) bone marrow than in 
all other groups during both the GTTs and ITTs. n values per group are 
indicated. *P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; ***P &lt; 0.001; ns, not significant. </p>

<p>C.C. FÉ RAL AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, JULY 2008 </p>

<p>
CHOW 
Monocyte Absolute Number </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>HFD </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>YA </p>

<p>Mixed Population (in % total cells) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>YA </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>ns 
ns </p>

<p>ns 
ns </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>WT 
YA </p>

<p>Mixed Population (in % total cells) </p>

<p>WAT 
Blood 
BM </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>WAT 
Pure Monocytes (in % total cells) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Blood 
BM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>YA </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>HFD 
CHOW </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>YA </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>Pure Monocytes (in % total cells) </p>

<p>WAT 
Blood 
BM </p>

<p>WAT 
Blood 
BM </p>

<p>FIG. 4. High-fat diet-fed ␣4(Y991A) mice exhibit a decreased number of adipose tissue and peripheral blood monocyte/macrophages. A: Stromal 
vascular cells of WAT, peripheral blood (blood) cells, and bone marrow (BM) cells were isolated from wild-type (f) and ␣4(Y991A) (□) mice 
were stained for 7/4 and Ly-6G surface markers. Mice were fed with either high-fat diet (left) or normal chow (right). Quantification of 
7/4 </p>

<p>hi </p>

<p>Ly-6G 
neg (pure monocytes; top) and 7/4 </p>

<p>dim </p>

<p>Ly-6G 
neg (mixed leukocyte population; bottom) cells was performed by flow cytometry. WAT of 
high-fat diet-fed ␣4(Y991A) mice contain a decreased number of pure monocyte (7/4 
hi Ly-6G </p>

<p>neg </p>

<p>) cells compared with wild type. The mixed 
population (7/4 </p>

<p>dim </p>

<p>Ly-6G </p>

<p>neg </p>

<p>) also shows a decrease in the high-fat diet-fed ␣4(Y991A) WAT, although it does not reach significance. A slight 
monocytopenia (7/4 </p>

<p>hi </p>

<p>Ly-6G </p>

<p>neg </p>

<p>) was measured in normal chow-fed ␣4(Y991A) mice, which was aggravated upon high-fat diet feeding. The 
decreased 7/4 </p>

<p>dim </p>

<p>Ly-6G 
neg cell number was observed only in peripheral blood of high-fat diet-fed ␣4 mutant mice. No significant differences were 
observed in monocyte/macrophage numbers in the bone marrow in the two genotypes regardless of diet. Values are means ؎ SE. B: Quantification 
of monocytes from wild-type (f) and ␣4(Y991A) (□) hemograms is shown. Cell morphology was used to identify monocytes. Note that ␣4(Y991A) 
monocytopenia worsen when mice are fed a high-fat diet. Values are means ؎ SE. n values per group are indicated. *P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; ns, not 
significant. </p>

<p>PREVENTING OBESITY-INDUCED INSULIN RESISTANCE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, JULY 2008 </p>

<p>Relative PAI-1 mRNA 
expression </p>

<p>n.s </p>

<p>Relative Leptin mRNA 
expression </p>

<p>n.s </p>

<p>Relative IL6 mRNA 
expression </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Relative TNFalpha mRN 
expression </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>MCP-1 
Number of migrated cells </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Relative MCP-1 mRNA 
expression </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>WT 
YA </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>WT 
YA </p>

<p>WT 
YA 
WT 
YA </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>WT 
YA 
WT 
YA </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>FIG. 5. ␣4(Y991A) monocyte/macrophages show reduced migration in vitro in response to stimulation with MCP-1. A: Bone marrow-derived 
macrophages isolated from wild-type and ␣4(Y991A) mice were added to the top chamber of a VCAM-1-coated transwell. Chemoattractant, 
MCP-1 (1 nmol/l), was added in the lower chamber. Cells were allowed to migrate for 16 h. After fixation, cells were stained with crystal violet, 
and the total number of migrated cells (bottom chamber) was enumerated. B: Levels of MCP-1 mRNA were determined in vivo in epididymal WAT 
from wild-type and ␣4(Y991A) mice by using real-time RT-PCR. The data were normalized to the expression of V-ATPase. No significant difference 
was seen between genotypes. C: Levels of IL-6, PAI-1, TNF-␣, and leptin mRNA were evaluated in vivo in WAT from wild-type and ␣4(Y991A) mice 
by real-time RT-PCR. Both TNF-␣ and IL-6 levels are decreased in ␣4(Y991A) compared with wild-type. Values are means ؎ SE (n ‫؍‬ 14). **P &lt; 
0.01; ns, not significant. </p>

<p>C.C. FÉ RAL AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, JULY 2008 </p>

<p>
DISCUSSION </p>

<p>␣4 integrins are proven therapeutic targets in chronic 
inflammatory diseases, such as multiple sclerosis; how-
ever, complete blockade of ␣4 integrin function can result 
in defects in hematopoiesis, heart, and placental develop-
ment (9,11,38,39) and is associated with progressive mul-
tifocal leukoencephalopathy (13). Chronic low-grade 
inflammation contributes to the development of insulin 
resistance (40), and the adipose tissue macrophage is a 
principal cell type responsible (27). Here, we report that 
mice bearing the ␣4(Y991A) mutation are protected from 
high-fat diet-induced glucose intolerance and insulin re-
sistance. The mutation did not block development of 
monocytes in the bone marrow but impaired their migra-
tion in response to MCP-1, leading to a combination of 
reduced egress into the blood and diminished accumula-
tion in adipose tissue. Reduction of ␣4(Y991A) mono-
cyte/macrophages in WAT consequently diminished pro-
inflammatory cytokine (IL-6 and TNF-␣) production, 
which can explain the amelioration of insulin resistance 
in these mice. This is the first study showing a role for 
integrin signaling in the pathogenesis the metabolic 
consequences of diet-induced obesity. 
␣4 integrins are important in the pathogenesis of high-
fat diet-induced insulin resistance because they mediate 
the localization of monocyte/macrophages to adipose tis-
sue. In particular, we found that a point mutation that 
impairs ␣4 integrin signaling led to markedly improved 
glucose tolerance and insulin sensitivity in high-fat diet-
fed mice. The ␣4(Y991A) mice become obese on a high-fat 
diet, but they remained insulin-sensitive. This insulin-
sensitive phenotype can be conferred by transplanting 
bone marrow from ␣4(Y991A) mice into irradiated wild-
type host animals. In the reverse experiment, fat-fed 
␣4(Y991A) mice receiving wild-type bone marrow were 
insulin resistant. Thus, bone marrow-derived cells are 
responsible for this protective effect, most likely by limit-
ing accumulation of inflammatory adipose tissue macro-
phages. Recent studies have begun to classify macrophage 
subpopulations with differing roles in insulin resistance; 
future studies will be required to define effects of the 
␣4(Y991A) mutation on these subpopulations (41-44). It is 
noteworthy that improvement of glucose tolerance in 
mutant mice fed a high-fat diet is not complete. This 
implies that other factors could contribute to glucose 
intolerance induced by high-fat diet. These results add 
insulin resistance/type 2 diabetes to diseases in which ␣4 
integrins may serve as therapeutic targets. 
Consistent with our results, MCP-1 deficiency or dele-
tion of the MCP-1 receptor (CCR2) reduced monocyte 
egress from the bone marrow (28) and accumulation of 
macrophages in adipose tissue (4), and MCP-1 or CCR2 KO 
mice are partially protected from high-fat diet-induced 
insulin resistance (4,45). Thus, deletion of CCR2 or its 
main ligand leads to a similar phenotype as shown here for 
the ␣4(Y991A) mice. Furthermore, we demonstrated a 
defect in CCR2-driven chemotaxis in ␣4(Y991A) mono-
cytes. These relationships suggest that CCR2-mediated 
monocyte recruitment is linked to the binding of paxillin 
to the ␣4 integrin cytoplasmic domain. 
The phenotypes observed in the ␣4(Y991A) and 
␣4(Y991A)-BMT animals are remarkably similar to those 
observed in mice deficient in Sorbs1 gene, which encodes 
cbl-associated protein (Cap) (19). These mice are also 
protected from high-fat diet-induced insulin resistance, </p>

<p>and this protection can be transferred to wild-type mice by 
BMT of Cap-null bone marrow. Furthermore, Cap deletion 
resulted in reduced numbers of monocytes/macrophages 
in both blood and adipose tissue, and Cap knockdown led 
to decreased migration in the RAW264.7 macrophage cell 
line. Previously, Cap was shown to mediate signals for the 
formation of stress fibers and focal adhesions through 
interaction with the focal adhesion kinase p125 </p>

<p>FAK </p>

<p>, an 
effector directly linked to paxillin binding to ␣4 integrin 
(15), and Cbl is required for macrophage spreading and 
migration. Thus, the relationship between Cap and ␣4-
paxillin interaction in the pathogenesis of insulin resis-
tance is an area of potential future interest. 
Chronic inflammation can be a primary mediator of 
obesity-induced insulin resistance, and inflammation is 
recognized as one of the contributors to the metabolic 
syndrome (or syndrome X) and type 2 diabetes (46). This 
study establishes a new role for ␣4 signaling in the 
development of high-fat diet-induced insulin resistance 
through its action on monocyte/macrophage trafficking. It 
also suggests that blockade of ␣4 signaling can improve 
insulin sensitivity and reduce inflammation, which could 
translate into clinical benefit in type 2 diabetes. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>C.C.F. has received a postdoctoral fellowship from the 
Arthritis Foundation. J.G.N. has received Scientist Devel-
opment Grant 0635408N from the American Heart Associ-
ation. C.K. has received a postdoctoral fellowship from the 
Arthritis Foundation. J.M.O. has received a University of 
California Discovery Biostar Grant and NIH Grants DK-
033651 and DK-074868. M.H.G. has received National In-
stitutes of Health (NIH) Grants AR-27214, HL-078784, and 
HL-31950. </p>



<p>PREVENTING OBESITY-INDUCED INSULIN RESISTANCE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, JULY 2008 </p>



<p>C.C. FÉ RAL AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, JULY 2008 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>