<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2585846" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:48+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Tpl2 (Tumor progression locus 2), also known as Cot/MAP3K8, is a hematopoietically ex-
pressed serine-threonine kinase. Tpl2 is known to have critical functions in innate immu-
nity in regulating tumor necrosis factor -␣ , Toll-like receptor, and G protein -coupled 
receptor signaling; however, our understanding of its physiological role in T cells is limited. 
We investigated the potential roles of Tpl2 in T cells and found that it was induced by 
interleukin-12 in human and mouse T cells in a Stat4-dependent manner. Defi ciency of 
Tpl2 was associated with impaired interferon (IFN)-␥ production. Accordingly, Tpl2 ؊ / ؊ mice 
had impaired host defense against Toxoplasma gondii with reduced parasite clearance and 
decreased IFN-␥ production. Furthermore, reconstitution of Rag2 ؊ / ؊ mice with Tpl2-
defi cient T cells followed by T. gondii infection recapitulated the IFN-␥ defect seen in the 
Tpl2-defi cient mice, confi rming a T cell -intrinsic defect. CD4 + T cells isolated from Tpl2 ؊ / ؊ 
mice showed poor induction of T-bet and failure to up-regulate Stat4 protein, which is 
associated with impaired TCR-dependent extracellular signal-regulated kinase activation. 
These data underscore the role of Tpl2 as a regulator of T helper cell lineage decisions and 
demonstrate that Tpl2 has an important functional role in the regulation of Th1 responses. </p>



<p>TPL2 REGULATES CD4 + T CELL IFN-␥ PRODUCTION | Watford et al. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Tpl2 is induced by IL-12 stimulation 
To identify genes rapidly induced by IL-12, microarray analysis 
was conducted using human PBMC enriched for CD3 + T cells 
after stimulation for 6 h. Approximately 90 genes were diff eren-
tially induced by IL-12 stimulation. The top 30 most highly IL-
12 -inducible genes are depicted in Fig. S1 (available at http:// 
www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20081461/DC1). These 
include known IL-12 -inducible genes such as IFNG, IL12RB2, 
IL18R1, TBX21 (T-bet), and GZMB, lending validity to this 
study ( 17 ). In addition, the MAPK family member Tpl2 (also 
known as MAP3K8) was noted to be IL-12 inducible. A previ-
ous microarray study of polarized Th1 cells stimulated with IL-
12 also included Tpl2 as a Th1-specifi c gene, but these results 
were not verifi ed ( 17 ). To confi rm these microarray results, we 
fi rst performed Northern blot analysis on PBMC stimulated 
with various cytokines. Consistent with the microarray data, IL-
12 alone specifi cally induced Tpl2 mRNA ( Fig. 1 A , lane 5). 
Furthermore, Tpl2 was preferentially induced in human naive 
CD4 + cord blood T cells that had been cultured under Th1, 
compared with Th2, diff erentiating conditions for 7 d ( Fig. 1 B ). 
IFN-␥ and IL-4 mRNA levels were measured by real-time 
PCR to confi rm the proper polarization of the Th1 and Th2 
cells, respectively (unpublished data). 
Because IL-12 is a potent inducer of IFN-␥ and Th1 cells 
produce IFN-␥ , these studies did not discriminate between in-
duction of Tpl2 directly by IL-12 or indirectly through IFN-␥ . 
The time course of Tpl2 mRNA induction in response to IL-12 
was very rapid, within 1 h of stimulation ( Fig. 1 A , right), sug-
gesting a direct mode of regulation. To formally test this hypoth-
esis, we stimulated cells directly with IL-12 or IFN-␥ . IL-12 
stimulation of human PBMC induced Tpl2 expression, whereas 
direct stimulation with IFN-␥ did not (unpublished data). The 
same was true in purifi ed mouse CD4 + T cells, demonstrating 
that Tpl2 was regulated by IL-12 directly in both human and 
mouse cells ( Fig. 1 C ). Furthermore, IL-12 stimulation induced 
Tpl2 expression even in IFN-␥ -defi cient mouse T cells, exclud-
ing an indirect mode of regulation through IFN-␥ ( Fig. 1 D ). 
To determine if Tpl2 induction is specifi c to IL-12 stimula-
tion, we investigated whether IL-23, which shares the p40 
ligand subunit and the IL-12R ␤ 1 receptor chain with IL-12 
( 26 ), could induce Tpl2 expression. Although IL-23 induced 
production of IL-17 mRNA as expected (not depicted), IL-23 
failed to induce Tpl2 expression ( Fig. 1 E ). These data provide 
further evidence of direct and specifi c induction of Tpl2 by 
IL-12. However, previous studies on cell lines have suggested 
that Tpl2 is also induced by TCR signaling ( 18, 24, 27 ). Indeed, 
activation of CD4 + T cells with plate-bound anti-CD3 and 
-CD28 led to rapid and sustained induction of Tpl2 ( Fig. 1 F ). 
We therefore conclude that Tpl2 is dynamically regulated in T 
lymphocytes by both T cell receptor engagement and IL-12. 
Because the major IL-12 signaling intermediate is Stat4, 
we investigated whether Tpl2 up-regulation is dependent on 
this transcription factor. Notably, IL-12 stimulation failed 
to induce Tpl2 mRNA expression in Stat4-defi cient CD4 + 
T cells, suggesting that Tpl2 gene expression is regulated by </p>

<p>of NK cells, and promoting the diff erentiation of Th1 cells. 
The importance of both IL-12 and IFN-␥ in host defense has 
been clearly demonstrated by cytokine and receptor KO mice, 
which have increased susceptibility to infection ( 8 -11 ). 
Despite the obvious importance of IL-12 in both innate 
and adaptive immunity, our understanding of the molecular 
basis of this cytokine ' s action is far from complete. The fi rst 
step is that IL-12 activates the receptor-associated kinases Jak2 
and Tyk2, which subsequently activate the transcription fac-
tor Stat4 ( 12 ). The importance of Tyk2, Jak2, and Stat4 in 
IL-12 signaling is substantiated by strong genetic evidence 
( 8 -11 ). Defi ciency of Tyk2 greatly diminishes IL-12 signal-
ing ( 13 ), but defi ciency of Jak2 has even more profound con-
sequences, including embryonic lethality caused by its role in 
erythropoiesis ( 14 ). Other signaling molecules, such as the 
p38 mitogen-activated protein kinse (MAPK), have also been 
implicated in IL-12 signaling, but their actions have not yet 
been fully defi ned ( 15, 16 ). 
Further delineation of genes regulated by IL-12 and Stat4 
and elucidation of how they contribute to the biology of de-
veloping CD4 + T cells will be important in understanding the 
actions of this cytokine and transcription factor and aid in the 
development of therapeutic interventions for infl ammatory 
and autoimmune diseases exacerbated by IL-12 and IFN-␥ . 
To this end, we and others have performed microarray anal-
ysis to identify IL-12 -regulated genes ( 17 ). One gene that was 
prominently induced by IL-12 was Tpl2/Cot (tumor progres-
sion locus 2/Cancer Osaka thyroid; also known as MAP3K8). 
Originally identifi ed as a protooncogene ( 18 ), Tpl2 is a serine-
threonine kinase belonging to the MAPK family that has 
essential functions in innate immune cells where it transmits 
signals via Toll-like receptors, the TNF family of receptors ( 19 ), 
and G protein -coupled receptors ( 20 ). When overexpre ssed 
in a variety of cell types, it activates all of the MAPK path-
ways, NFAT, and NF-B ( 21 -24 ). Its signaling output, how-
ever, appears to be cell type dependent and signal dependent 
( 20, 25 ). In APCs, it is reported to be an obligatory upstream 
activator of the extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK) 
pathway and to function as a critical regulator of TNF-␣ pro-
duction in response to TLR signals ( 19 ). However, surpris-
ingly little is known about its functions in normal T cells. 
Herein, we demonstrate that Tpl2 is induced by IL-12 and 
is required by T cells for optimal IL-12 -induced IFN-␥ pro-
duction. In vitro stimulation of Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ CD4 + T cells revealed 
impaired IL-12 -and TCR-induced IFN-␥ production and 
ineffi cient polarization toward the Th1 phenotype. Further-
more, in response to infection with the Th1-inducing parasite 
Toxoplasma gondii , Tpl2-defi cient mice developed a higher 
pathogen load associated with decreased systemic IFN-␥ pro-
duction, defi ning Tpl2 as a positive regulator of Th1 responses 
both in vitro and in vivo . Interestingly, Tpl2 appears to con-
tribute to Th1 diff erentiation by ensuring proper induction 
of two key transcription factors, T-bet and Stat4. Thus, in 
addition to its key functions in the innate immune response, Tpl2 
also has critical functions in T cells in promoting expression of 
transcription factors that drive optimal Th1 diff erentiation. </p>

<p>JEM VOL. 205, November 24, 2008 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>ent regions of the promoter (unpublished data). IL-12 -induc-
ible association was quantitated by ChIP using real-time PCR 
( Fig. 2 B ). To further confi rm the specifi city of this associa-
tion, an intronic sequence within the Tpl2 gene was ampli-
fi ed and failed to show any signifi cant Stat4 binding, which is 
similar to what was seen using Stat4-defi cient T cells ( Fig. 2 C ). 
Thus, we conclude that Stat4 binds to the Tpl2 promoter in 
an IL-12 -inducible manner and is required for IL-12 -depen-
dent Tpl2 gene expression. </p>

<p>Tpl2 regulates T cell IFN-␥ production 
Because Tpl2 is induced by IL-12, we reasoned that Tpl2 might 
also be involved in IFN-␥ expression and Th1 diff erentiation. 
As has previously been reported, Tpl2-defi cient mice displayed 
normal lymphoid development, with normal numbers and pro-
portions of thymocytes and splenocytes ( 19 ). To test the ability 
of T cells from Tpl2-defi cient mice to respond to IL-12 </p>

<p>Stat4 ( Fig. 2 A ). Examination of the mouse Tpl2 locus re-
vealed several putative Stat binding motifs within 1 kb upstream 
of the Tpl2 transcriptional start site. Therefore, we performed 
chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) experiments to test 
for direct binding of Stat4 to the Tpl2 promoter. ChIP with 
an anti-Stat4 antibody revealed binding to the Tpl2 promoter 
using two diff erent primer sets designed to interrogate diff er-</p>

<p>Figure 1. Tpl2 is an IL-12 -inducible gene in human and mouse cells. 
(A, left) Human PBMC were cultured for 3 d in RPMI containing 1 μ g/ml 
PHA followed by an additional day of culture in 40 U/ml IL-2 to maximize 
expression of IL-12R ( 43 ). The cells were then rested for 12 h in serum-
free medium, followed by stimulation with medium alone (lane 1), IL-2 
(lane 2), IL-4 (lane 3), IL-7 (lane 4), IL-12 (lane 5), or IL-15 (lane 6) at 
10 ng/ml for 6 h, and Tpl2 mRNA expression was determined by Northern 
blot analysis using a Tpl2-specifi c probe. (A, right) A kinetic analysis of 
Tpl2 mRNA induction was performed by Northern blot analysis of 10 ng/ml 
IL-12 -stimulated human PHA blasts. Data are representative of two inde-
pendent experiments. White lines indicate that intervening lanes have 
been spliced out. (B) Human cord blood CD4 + T cells were cultured under 
Th1 or Th2 inducing conditions, as described in Materials and methods, 
and analyzed for Tpl2 message level by real-time PCR. Data are represen-
tative of two separate experiments. (C -E) For analysis of Tpl2 expression 
in mouse cells, CD4 + T cells were purifi ed from mouse spleens. Cells were 
then grown for 3 d on plates coated with anti-CD3 and -CD28, rested for 
5 h in cytokine-free medium, restimulated with IL-12 or IFN-␥ (C), IL-12 
(D), or IL-23 (E) for 4 h, and subsequently analyzed for Tpl2 expression by 
real-time PCR. Mouse cells analyzed were from WT (C and E; n = 3 repli-
cate experiments) or IFN-␥ -defi cient mice (D; representative of two bio-
logical replicates from one experiment). (F) For transcriptional analysis of 
Tpl2 in response to TCR signals, 2 × 10 6 CD4 + T cells were stimulated in 
2 ml of media on a 12-well plate coated with anti-CD3 and -CD28 for the 
indicated times and analyzed for Tpl2 expression by real-time PCR. Data 
are representative of two independent experiments. Error bars represent 
SD from replicates within a representative experiment. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Tpl2 is a direct Stat4 target gene. (A) The Stat4 depen-
dency of Tpl2 induction by IL-12 was examined by stimulating WT or 
Stat4-defi cient mouse CD4 + T cell blasts with IL-12 for 4 h and analyzing 
Tpl2 mRNA induction. n = 3 replicate experiments. (B) ChIP using an anti-
Stat4 antibody or nonimmune rabbit serum (NRS) was analyzed quantita-
tively by real-time PCR using primers designed around putative Stat sites 
within 1 kb upstream of the Tpl2 transcriptional start site. n = 4 indepen-
dent experiments. (C) To further test the specifi city of the binding, we 
compared the binding to the promoter region to that seen within an in-
tronic region of the gene (intron 5). n = 1 experiment. Error bars represent 
SD from replicates within a representative experiment. </p>



<p>TPL2 REGULATES CD4 + T CELL IFN-␥ PRODUCTION | Watford et al. </p>

<p>cells is not caused by a developmental abnormality because 
these cells developed in the presence of Tpl2. 
Given that Tpl2 is also induced by TCR signals, we con-
sidered that it might also aff ect IFN-␥ production in response 
to TCR-mediated signals. To this end, splenocytes were stim-
ulated with soluble anti-CD3, and cytokine secretion was 
measured 24 h later. As shown in Fig. 3 C , Tpl2-defi cient 
splenocytes produced signifi cantly less IFN-␥ than WT cells 
in response to TCR stimulation. 
To investigate the role of Tpl2 in T helper polarization, 
we isolated naive CD62L hi CD44 lo CD4 + T cells from WT 
or Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ mice by FACS sorting and cultured the cells 
with appropriate cytokines and anticytokine antibodies to 
generate Th0, Th1, Th2, or Th17 cells. Under neutral con-
ditions (Th0), fewer IFN-␥ + cells were generated by Tpl2-
deficient cells ( Fig. 4 A , left). Even when Tpl2-deficient 
cells were cultured under optimal Th1-polarizing condi-
tions, differentiation into Th1 cells was still attenuated as 
measured by intracellular cytokine staining, ELISA, and real-
time PCR ( Fig. 4, A -C ). However, Th2 diff erentiation was 
not further augmented by Tpl2 defi ciency under optimal Th2 
conditions ( Fig. 4 A , right). Interestingly, IL-17 produc-
tion was also impaired in Tpl2-defi cient cells cultured under 
Th17 conditions ( Fig. 4 D ). These data are consistent with 
the idea that Tpl2 defi ciency is associated with an intrinsic 
impairment of TCR-and IL-12 -dependent Th1 responses. </p>

<p>stimulation, WT or Tpl2-defi cient CD4 + T cells were fi rst ac-
tivated with anti-CD3 and -CD28 for 3 d to induce IL-12R ex-
pression, rested in cytokine-free medium for 5 h, and stimulated 
with IL-12. Tpl2-defi cient T cells were signifi cantly diminished 
in their capacity to produce IFN-␥ ( Fig. 3 A , left). Furthermore, 
this defect could not be overcome by stimulation with IL-12 in 
combination with IL-2 and was only partially rescued by IL-12 
plus IL-18 ( Fig. 3 A , middle and right), both of which are known 
to synergize with IL-12 for IFN-␥ production. Although IL-12 
stimulation alone was insuffi cient to visualize intracellular 
IFN-␥ staining (not depicted), the combination of IL-12 and 
IL-18 yielded 14% IFN-␥ + cells in WT compared with only 
1% in Tpl2-defi cient T cells ( Fig. 3 B ). These data clearly indi-
cate that there is a decrease in the proportion of Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ CD4 + 
T cells capable of making IFN-␥ under these conditions. 
The IFN-␥ defect was also confi rmed in human cells using 
a small interfering RNA (siRNA) knockdown approach 
(Fig. S2, available at http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/ 
jem.20081461/DC1). The siRNA approach additionally dem-
onstrates that altered IFN-␥ production by Tpl2-defi cient T </p>

<p>Figure 3. Tpl2 is required for optimal IL-12 -induced IFN-␥ pro-
duction. (A and B) IL-12 -induced IFN-␥ production was analyzed in WT 
and Tpl2-defi cient CD4 + T cells. CD4 + T cells isolated from WT or Tpl2-
defi cient mouse LN and spleens were activated and expanded on anti-
CD3 -and -CD28 -coated fl asks for 3 d. Cells were then rested for 5 h in 
cytokine-free medium before stimulation with 0 -10 ng/ml IL-12 alone 
or in combination with 50 U/ml IL-2 or 10 ng/ml IL-18 for 24 h. Cyto-
kine production was measured in cell culture supernatants using cyto-
metric bead array (A) or intracellular cytokine staining (B). (C) For 
intracellular cytokine staining, rested cells were restimulated with IL-12 
and IL-18 for 24 h with the addition of Golgi transport inhibitor for the 
last 5 h of culture. Whole splenocytes were stimulated with soluble 
anti-CD3 for 48 h, and the production of IFN-␥ was measured by cyto-
metric bead array. A, n = 3 experiments; B, n = 2 experiments; C, n = 3 
experiments. Error bars represent SD from replicates within a represen-
tative experiment. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Tpl2 defi ciency leads to impaired Th1 differentiation 
in vitro. Naive CD44 lo CD62L hi CD4 + T cells were purifi ed by FACS sorting and 
cultured with immobilized anti-CD3 and -CD28 plus the appropriate cyto-
kines and anti-cytokine antibodies for 7 d to generate Th0, Th1, Th2, or Th17 
T helper lineages. Effi ciency of polarization was determined based on IFN-␥ , 
IL-4/IL-13, or IL-17 production, as measured by intracellular cytokine stain-
ing for IFN-␥ and IL-13 or IL-4 (A), cytometric bead array for IFN-␥ (B), real-
time PCR for IFN-␥ mRNA (C), and ELISA for IL-17 protein (D). Data shown 
for A -C are representative of at least three independent experiments; data in 
D are representative of two experiments. Error bars indicate SEM; *, P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>JEM VOL. 205, November 24, 2008 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>defi cient mice as measured by real-time PCR ( Fig. 5 A , top) 
and surface staining ( Fig. 5 A , bottom). Despite normal recep-
tor expression, both IL-12 -dependent Stat4 serine and tyro-
sine phosphorylation were dramatically reduced in Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ 
mice, owing to reduced levels of total Stat4 protein and 
mRNA ( Fig. 5, B and C ). Specifi cally, freshly isolated Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ </p>

<p>Tpl2-defi cient T cells have reduced levels of Stat4 
and T-bet 
We next examined potential mechanisms underlying the IL-
12 hyporesponsiveness in Tpl2-defi cient T cells. Assessment 
of IL-12R ␤ 1 and IL-12R ␤ 2 showed similar expression levels 
of both subunits in activated CD4 + T cells from WT or Tpl2-</p>

<p>Figure 5. Tpl2 regulates Stat4 and T-bet levels. (A) CD4 + T cell blasts were generated over 3 d of culture on immobilized anti-CD3 and -CD28. Ex-
pression of IL-12 receptor ␤ 1 and ␤ 2 were determined by real-time PCR or surface staining. n = 3 separate experiments each. (B) Cells were then stimu-
lated with IL-12 for the indicated times. Whole cell lysates were analyzed for ERK (not depicted) or Stat4 activation by Western blotting. n = 3 
independent experiments. (C) TCR-dependent regulation of Stat4 was determined by culturing 2 × 10 6 cells in 2 ml of media on a 12-well plate coated 
with anti-CD3 and -CD28 for the indicated times. Stat4 expression was determined by real-time PCR analysis. Error bars represent SD from replicates 
within a representative experiment. n = 2 independent experiments. (D) ChIP was performed to determine whether Tpl2 defi ciency affected IL-12 -induced 
Stat4 binding to the Ifng promoter. Cells were activated and rested as in A, plated at 10 6 /ml in 10-cm petri dishes, and stimulated for 1 h with 10 ng/ml 
IL-12. Immunoprecipitation was performed using anti-Stat4 antibody or nonimmune rabbit serum, and binding to the Ifng promoter was analyzed by 
real-time PCR. Data represent means and SE of the mean of three independent experiments. (E, left) Purifi ed CD4 + T cells were activated with anti-CD3 
and -CD28 for 3 d and analyzed by intracellular staining for T-bet and Gata3 expression. n = 2 independent experiments with a total of three individual 
mice. (E, right) Additionally, purifi ed CD4 + T cells were analyzed for Gata3 and T-bet mRNA expression by real-time PCR relative to an 18S control, and the 
ratio of Gata3/T-bet message is shown. The ratio of Gata3/T-bet was calculated by ⌬ Ct method. Data represent means and SEM for a total of four mice 
per group in two separate experiments. *, P &lt; 0.05. (F) Tpl2-dependent TCR signaling events were analyzed in WT and Tpl2-defi cient mice. Five million 
cells/point were stimulated with biotinylated anti-CD3 on ice for 15 min before cross-linking with streptavidin at 37 ° C for the indicated times. Western 
blots were probed with antibodies recognizing phospho-ERK, total ERK, and actin. Data are representative of two independent experiments. </p>



<p>TPL2 REGULATES CD4 + T CELL IFN-␥ PRODUCTION | Watford et al. </p>

<p>Figure 6. Tpl2 is required for normal host responses to T. gondii . 
WT or Tpl2-defi cient mice were infected with 20 cysts of the avirulent 
T. gondii strain ME49 and analyzed for host responses during acute and 
chronic stages of infection. Both WT and Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ mice survived the infec-
tion for &gt; 8 wk. To explore their immune responses further, mice were 
killed on day 7 after infection and several parameters were analyzed, in-
cluding systemic cytokine levels in serum (A), LN recall responses to STAg 
(B), and proportion of infected PECs (C and D). Arrowheads in D indicate 
intracellular T. gondii parasites. Host responses of chronically infected 
mice were assessed at week 5 by quantifying the numbers of encysted 
bradyzoites in the brain (E). Rag2-defi cient mice were reconstituted with 
10 million purifi ed CD4 + T cells and infected with T. gondii &gt; 1 wk later. 
Survival of reconstituted infected mice was monitored (F). Serum levels of 
IFN-␥ were also determined 7 d after infection (G). Data indicate means 
from at least seven mice per group from two separate infections for A, B, 
and G and are from four mice per group in C, E, and F, respectively. Error 
bars indicate standard errors of the mean. </p>

<p>Encysted bradyzoites are found in the muscle and nervous 
tissue of chronically infected animals, and their abundance can 
be related to parasite control during the acute phase. Consis-
tent with the defect in IFN-␥ production and increased patho-
gen load, Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ mice developed fourfold greater numbers 
of brain cysts after 5 wk of infection ( Fig. 6 E ). Collectively, </p>

<p>CD4 + T cells did not have altered levels of Stat4 expres-
sion (Fig. S3, available at http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/ 
full/jem.20081461/DC1). However, Stat4 is inducible upon 
T cell activation ( 12 ), and this Stat4 induction was diminished 
in TCR-activated Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ T cells ( Fig. 5, B and C ). The re-
duced levels of Stat4 protein in cultured CD4 + T cells were 
associated with reduced recruitment of Stat4 to the mouse 
Ifng promoter in response to IL-12 signaling, demonstrating 
that this diff erence is functionally relevant ( Fig. 5 D ). Addi-
tionally, purifi ed CD4 + T cells from Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ mice failed to 
properly induce T-bet protein when stimulated with anti-CD3 
and -CD28 ( Fig. 5 E , left), whereas Gata3 protein was regu-
lated normally. Accordingly, at the transcriptional level a 
greater than twofold increase in the ratio of Gata3/T-bet 
mRNAs was seen by real-time PCR ( Fig. 5 E , right). Col-
lectively, these data demonstrate that Tpl2 contributes to Th1 
diff erentiation in activated T cells by ensuring proper induc-
tion of the key transcription factors T-bet and Stat4. These 
defects appeared to arise during the TCR activation phase. 
Therefore, we examined Tpl2-dependent events in response 
to TCR activation. We analyzed ERK activation in response 
to CD3 cross-linking and, consistent with recently published 
data ( 28 ), we found that ERK activation is impaired in the 
Tpl2-defi cient T cells ( Fig. 5 F ). Based on these data, we 
propose a model for the role of Tpl2 in Th1 diff erentiation as 
depicted in Fig. S4. </p>

<p>Tpl2 is required for the normal host defense against 
the Th1-inducing parasite Toxoplasma gondii 
To determine whether Tpl2 plays a critical role in IFN-␥ 
production in vivo, WT or Tpl2-defi cient mice were in-
fected i.p. with T. gondii , an obligate intracellular parasite, re-
sistance to which critically depends upon IFN-␥ production 
( 29 ). 7 d after infection, mice were killed and examined for 
markers of acute infection. Despite the fact that Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ 
APCs overproduce IL-12 both in vitro in response to TLR 
ligands ( 19, 30 ) and in vivo in response to T. gondii infection 
( Fig. 6 A ), T. gondii -infected Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ mice produced signifi -
cantly less IFN-␥ systemically than WT mice. Additionally, 
reduced amounts of MCP-1 (CCL2), an IFN-␥ -inducible 
chemokine, were present in sera of infected mice, whereas 
IL-6 levels were unaff ected by Tpl2 defi ciency ( Fig. 6 A ). 
There were similar numbers and proportions of T cells and NK 
cells in spleens and peritoneal exudate cells (PECs) isolated 
from infected and uninfected WT or Tpl2-defi cient mice 
(unpublished data), suggesting that altered cellular respon-
siveness and not development/recruitment was responsible 
for the defective IFN-␥ production. Recall responses of lym-
phocytes to soluble T. gondii antigen (STAg) taken from day-7 
infected mice also showed impaired antigen-specifi c T cell 
responses in the Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ cells as measured by IFN-␥ secre-
tion ( Fig. 6 B ). The susceptibility of Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ mice to T. gondii 
was further assessed by quantifying the number of infected 
PECs persisting at day 7 after infection. Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ mice retained 
detectable parasites within the PECs, whereas WT mice had 
cleared the local infection by this time point ( Fig. 6, C and D ). </p>

<p>JEM VOL. 205, November 24, 2008 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>cus is likely to be of interest to examine as a model gene reg-
ulated jointly by TCR and cytokine signals. In preliminary 
experiments, we have begun to examine epigenetic modifi -
cations in the Tpl2 gene in diff erentiating T cells. It will be 
of interest to determine whether Stat4 is essential for epigen-
etic regulation of this locus as it is for the Ifng locus. 
Second, although several studies have examined the po-
tential function of Tpl2 by overexpression of WT or mutant 
alleles in cell lines ( 18, 35 ), very little is known about the physi-
ological role for Tpl2 in T cells. In this paper, we demonstrate 
that this kinase has an important nonredundant function in T 
cells in vivo as an inducible positive regulator of IFN-␥ . It is 
clear that Tpl2 has a T cell -intrinsic role in IL-12 signaling and 
IFN-␥ production because in vitro polarization of naive CD4 + 
T cells toward the Th1 phenotype is impaired in Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ cells, 
even under conditions antagonistic to Th2 polarization (i.e., in 
the presence of neutralizing IL-4 antibody). In this setting, 
continued neutralization of Th2 responses did not reverse the 
Th1/IFN-␥ defect in vitro, indicating that impaired IFN-␥ 
production by Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ CD4 + T cells cannot be explained 
simply by enhanced Th2 responses. 
Mechanistically, it appears that Tpl2 exerts its eff ect by 
infl uencing the levels of T-bet and Stat4 protein in activated 
T cells. Although this results in impaired IL-12 signaling as 
determined by Stat4 recruitment to the Ifng promoter, the 
impaired expression of Stat4 apparently arises during initial 
TCR-dependent actions. A recent study has shown that Tpl2 
is required for the optimal activation of ERK and MEK in 
response to TCR stimulation ( 28 ). Our data have confi rmed 
that ERK phosphorylation induced by TCR occupancy is 
partially Tpl2-dependent in T cells ( Fig. 5 F ). Whether Stat4 
induction by TCR signals is ERK dependent remains to be 
determined. However, T cells defi cient in the ERK-activated 
transcription factor Ets-1 have been shown to have impaired 
Th1 responses and reduced levels of Stat4 ( 36 ). Precisely how 
Tpl2 contributes to the regulation of Stat4 and T-bet protein 
levels is unclear but is worthy of future investigation. 
In addition to its role in TCR signaling, Tpl2 might also 
be involved in T cell costimulatory pathways. Kane et al. ( 37 )  have reported that Tpl2 associates with and is phosphorylated 
by protein kinase B (Akt) ( 38 ). Furthermore, they demon-
strate that overexpression of an activated form of Akt mimics 
CD28 costimulation of IFN-␥ induction in T cells. If Tpl2 is 
indeed involved in CD28 costimulatory signals, Tpl2 defi -
ciency may impair CD28 costimulation and, consequently, 
IFN-␥ production. 
The in vivo relevance of Tpl2 functions in normal T cell 
responses was most dramatically indicated by the challenge of 
Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ mice with T. gondii , a pathogen which is known to 
induce a vigorous Th1 response. Although Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ mice 
survived the infection, the parasite burden was increased rela-
tive to WT mice. Furthermore, specifi c impairment of T cells 
was evident as assessed by recall responses to STAg. The pres-
ent data stand in apparent contrast to a study indicating that 
enhanced TLR-induced IL-12 production by Tpl2-defi cient 
APCs is associated with increased Th1 responses ( 30 ). We too </p>

<p>these data indicate that Tpl2 is essential for proper host resis-
tance against a parasite that requires an appropriate Th1 re-
sponse and is a critical mediator of IFN-␥ production in vivo. 
The overproduction of IL-12 by Tpl2-defi cient APCs 
would be expected to promote Th1 diff erentiation and might 
complicate the interpretation of the preceding experiment. 
To more carefully assess the in vivo function of Tpl2-defi cient 
T cells, we reconstituted Rag2-defi cient mice with WT or 
Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ CD4 + T cells and then infected the mice with T. gondii . 
As expected, Rag2-defi cient mice that did not receive any 
T cells rapidly succumbed to infection, whereas mice re-
ceiving WT T cells were protected ( Fig. 6 F ). Similar to what 
was observed in Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ mice, mice adoptively transferred 
with Tpl2-defi cient T cells produced signifi cantly less IFN-␥ 
than mice receiving WT T cells ( Fig. 6 G ). Furthermore, mice 
receiving Tpl2 KO T cells died shortly after infection with 
kinetics similar to Rag-defi cient mice that had not received 
any T cells ( Fig. 6 F ), although no diff erences were found in 
reconstitution potentials between WT and Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ CD4 + T 
cells (not depicted). We interpret these data to suggest that 
hyperproduction of IL-12 by Tpl2-defi cient APCs in the 
complete Tpl2-defi cient mice likely partially masks a more 
dramatic T cell phenotype in this model. Regardless though, 
the adoptive transfer experiment argues strongly for an in-
trinsic role for Tpl2 in promoting Th1 differentiation and 
IFN-␥ production. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Although Tpl2 has been reported to be critical in innate im-
munity and oncogenesis, remarkably little attention has been 
given to its role in normal T cells. In this study, we show that 
Tpl2, which is inducible by TCR occupancy and IL-12, is 
important for T cell diff erentiation and eff ector functions. 
Activation of Tpl2-defi cient CD4 + T cells via cross-linking of 
the TCR led to impaired development of Th1 responses. 
Furthermore, IL-12 stimulation of activated Tpl2-defi cient T 
cells also showed major defects in IFN-␥ production. Accord-
ingly, Tpl2-defi cient T cells had reduced levels of Stat4 and 
T-bet, two factors which are critical for Th1 diff erentiation. 
This abnormal response was physiologically relevant in host 
defense against the model pathogen T. gondii , in which IFN-␥ 
induction was impaired and the pathogen burden was in-
creased. Using adoptive transfer experiments, we established that 
this increased susceptibility was caused by an intrinsic T cell de-
fect. These fi ndings are interesting from several perspectives 
and have multiple implications. 
First, the study defi nes Tpl2 as a novel IL-12 -inducible 
gene that is a direct target of Stat4. Stat4 is clearly critical in 
host defense and immunoregulation, and several Stat4-de-
pendent genes have been identifi ed ( 31 ). However, a paucity 
of direct Stat4 targets have been defi ned. These include IFN-␥ 
( 32 ), Cd25 ( 33 ), the proprotein convertase Furin ( 34 ), and 
now Tpl2 (Map3k8). These genes are inducible in response 
to TCR cross-linking as well as by cytokines. Potential tran-
scription factors required for TCR-induced Tpl2 regulation 
have not been examined, but like the Ifng locus, the Tpl2 lo-</p>



<p>TPL2 REGULATES CD4 + T CELL IFN-␥ PRODUCTION | Watford et al. </p>

<p>Mice and mouse cells. All animal experiments were performed according 
to the National Institutes of Health guidelines for laboratory animals and were 
approved by the National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin 
Diseases Animal Care and Use Committee. Mice were housed in a specifi c 
pathogen-free facility. Mouse CD4 + T cells were purifi ed from single-cell 
suspensions of mouse splenocytes and LN using CD4 microbeads (positive se-
lection) or CD4 + T cell isolation kit (negative selection) and the AutoMACS 
cell separation system (Miltenyi Biotec). All mouse cells were cultured in 
complete mouse medium (complete RPMI supplemented with 10 mM Hepes, 
1 mM sodium pyruvate, and 50 μ M ␤ -mercaptoethanol). For IL-12 stimula-
tions, cells were fi rst activated by culturing on fl asks that had been precoated 
with anti-CD3 and -CD28 (5 μ g/ml PBS each) for 3 d in the presence of 40 
U/ml IL-2 to induce IL-12 receptor expression. Cells were then washed and 
rested in complete mouse medium for 5 h before restimulation with IL-12 and 
various other cytokines. Secreted cytokines were measured from cell culture 
supernatants by cytokine bead array (BD) or ELISA (R &amp; D Systems). 
For T helper cell polarization experiments, naive CD44 lo CD62L hi CD4 + 
T cells were purifi ed by FACS sorting, and 4 × 10 5 cells/500 μ l of media 
were plated on 24-well plates that had been precoated with 5 μ g/ml of anti-CD3 
and 5 μ g/ml of anti-CD28 (Th0 condition). For Th1 conditions, 10 μ g/ml 
anti -IL-4 and 20 ng/ml of exogenous IL-12 were also added. For Th2 con-
ditions, 10 μ g/ml of anti -IL-12, 10 mg/ml of anti -IFN-␥ , and 40 ng/ml of 
exogenous IL-4 were added. For Th17 conditions, 10 μ g/ml of anti -IL-4 
and 10 μ g/ml of anti-IFN-␥ , along with 10 ng/ml IL-6 and 5 ng/ml TGF-␤ , 
were added. Cells were cultured for 3 d and transferred into T75 fl asks con-
taining 15 ml of medium with 40 U/ml IL-2 alone (Th0) or in combination 
with IL-12 (Th1) or IL-4 (Th2) and grown an additional 4 d. Fully polarized 
Th0, Th1, or Th2 cells were harvested after 7 d culture, counted, and re-
stimulated for IFN-␥ production. Th17 cells were analyzed after the initial 
3-d culture. For cytokine secretion, 2 × 10 5 cells/200 μ l were stimulated with 
5 μ g/ml of anti-CD3 and 5 μ g/ml of anti-CD28 for 24 h, and IFN-␥ in cell 
culture supernatants was quantifi ed by cytometric bead array. For mRNA 
analysis, 2 × 10 6 cells/2 ml were stimulated under the same conditions for 
6 h, and IFN-␥ mRNA was measured by real-time PCR. For intracellular 
cytokine staining, 2 × 10 6 cells/2 ml were stimulated with anti-CD3, anti-
CD28, PMA, and ionomycin for 6 -8 h and with Golgi transport inhibitor, 
which was present for the fi nal 4 h of culture. Cells were fi xed, permeabi-
lized, and stained using Cytofi x/Cytoperm Fixation/Permeabilization kit 
with GolgiPlug (BD) according to the manufacturer ' s protocol. </p>

<p>Microarray analysis of IL-12 -inducible genes </p>

<p>PBMC were cultured as described in Human cells and left unstimulated or 
were stimulated with 10 ng/ml IL-12 for 6 h. Total RNA was isolated with 
the RNeasy Midi kit (QIAGEN). For microarray analysis, samples were fur-
ther purifi ed with Trizol (Invitrogen), followed by use of the RNeasy Mini 
kit (QIAGEN) according to the manufacturer ' s protocols. Biotin-labeled 
cRNA was synthesized using the High Yield RNA transcript labeling kit 
(BioArray; Enzo Biochem, Inc.) and hybridized to human genome U133A 
and U133B microarray chips according to the manufacturer ' s instructions 
(Aff ymetrix). Data from unstimulated or IL-12 -stimulated PBMC from seven 
human donors were obtained. <rs type="software">MAS5</rs> software (Aff ymetrix) was used to ana-
lyze the images from each human genome U133A and U133B GeneChip 
Array and to obtain expression values for each probe set along with corre-
sponding calls of present, marginal, or absent. Genes were judged to be signifi -
cantly up-regulated if the expression levels for a least one corresponding probe 
set (as determined by Entrez Gene identifi ers) satisfi ed the following three cri-
teria: (1) a p-value of ≤ 0.05 from the right-tailed paired Student ' s t test on the 
log of the stimulated and control expression levels; (2) a geometric mean fold 
change of ≥ 1.7; and (3) at most, one of the calls for the stimulated expression 
levels failed to be present. <rs type="software">Custom</rs> software written in the Interactive Data 
Language (IDL; ITT Visual Information Solutions, Boulder, CO) was used to 
conduct this analysis. The data discussed in this publication have been depos-
ited in the National Center for Biotechnology Information ' s Gene Expression 
Omnibus and are accessible through the GEO Series accession no. GSE12839 
(http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE12839). </p>

<p>have found enhanced IL-12 production in Tpl2-defi cient 
DC in vivo and in vitro ( Fig. 6 A and Fig. S5, available at 
http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20081461/DC1); 
however, our data also indicate that Tpl2-defi cient T cells are 
nonetheless impaired in IFN-␥ production and Th1 polariza-
tion. We believe that some important factors distinguish these 
studies. First, the previous study used adjuvants in in vitro 
and in vivo experiments that may have inadvertently magni-
fi ed the IL-12 overproduction defect by the APC population 
and led to an apparent Th1 bias in the Tpl2 Ϫ / Ϫ . Additionally, 
although the earlier study focused on Tpl2 ' s functional role 
in APCs, we have tailored our study to specifi cally address its 
role in T cells, particularly with the Rag Ϫ / Ϫ reconstitution ex-
periment ( Fig. 6, F and G ). These data clearly support our 
contention that Tpl2 is required for optimal IFN-␥ produc-
tion by CD4 T cells. 
Further delineation of Tpl2 functions downstream of the 
TCR will provide valuable information about the balance of 
T helper lineages and may prove useful in the treatment of in-
fl ammatory diseases. Tpl2 defi ciency has already been reported 
to attenuate a TNF-dependent model of infl ammatory bowel 
disease ( 39 ). Because TNF blockade has been shown to be effi -
cacious in the treatment of several infl ammatory diseases ( 40 ), 
Tpl2 kinase has been suggested as a potential therapeutic target. 
A Tpl2 inhibitor has been generated and shown to inhibit LPS-
induced TNF-␣ production by human monocytes and in LPS-
treated mice ( 41, 42 ). Despite the fact that Tpl2 inhibition might 
also be benefi cial in treating autoimmunity driven by IFN-␥ 
and IL-17, our data suggest that targeting Tpl2 might attenuate 
Th1 diff erentiation and impair T cell responses to infection. 
Clearly, further studies are needed to give a more complete 
understanding of the risks versus benefi ts of therapeutic Tpl2 
blockade and the consequences in terms of T cell function. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Cytokines, antibodies, and reagents </p>

<p>Human IL-2 was provided by C. Reynolds (National Cancer Institute, 
Frederick, MD). All other cytokines were purchased from R &amp; D Systems. 
The following antibodies were purchased: anti -IFN-␥ , IL-4 (BD), anti-
actin, T-bet, and Gata3 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.). PHA was purchased 
from Sigma-Aldrich. Anti-CD3 and -CD28 antibodies used to activate T cells 
were purchased from BD. </p>

<p>Cell culture and cytokine stimulation </p>

<p>Human cells. Human cells were cultured in complete RPMI (RPMI 1640 
supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated FCS, 2 mM l-glutamine, 100 U of 
penicillin/ml, 100 μ g/ml streptomycin, and 2.5 μ g/ml fungizone). Because 
resting T cells do not express IL-12R, PBMC from healthy adult donors 
(Department of Transfusion Medicine, Clinical Center, National Institutes 
of Health) were activated by culturing for 72 h in complete RPMI contain-
ing 1 μ g/ml PHA, followed by an additional 24 h in complete medium con-
taining 40 U/ml IL-2 to maximize IL-12R expression ( 43 ). Before cytokine 
stimulation, cells ( &gt; 95% CD3 + ) were washed with CO 2 -acidifi ed RPMI and 
rested overnight in serum-free RPMI supplemented with 1% BSA. The cells 
were then stimulated with cytokines for the indicated times. For T cell dif-
ferentiation experiments, naive cord blood CD4 + cells (Cambrex) were cul-
tured in complete RPMI containing 50 U/ml IL-2 with either 20 ng/ml 
IL-12 and 20 μ g/ml anti -IL-4 for Th1 diff erentiation, or 25 ng/ml IL-4 and 
20 μ g/ml anti -IFN-␥ for Th2 diff erentiation. </p>

<p>JEM VOL. 205, November 24, 2008 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data represent mean ± SD, except where indicated. P-values were determined 
by one-tailed Student ' s t test with the null hypothesis that Tpl2 KO have 
decreased IL-12 -induced responses or IFN-␥ production where appropriate. </p>

<p>Online supplemental material </p>

<p>Fig. S1 shows the 30 genes most highly induced in human T cells by 
IL-12. Fig. S2 demonstrates that siRNA knockdown of Tpl2 in human 
PBMC impairs IL-12 -dependent IFN-␥ production. Fig. S3 shows that 
Stat4 dysregulation in Tpl2-defi cient T cells is a consequence of defective 
TCR signaling. Fig. S4 depicts a model for the proposed role of Tpl2 
in the regulation of Th1 diff erentiation. Fig. S5 shows that Tpl2-defi cient 
BM-derived DCs overproduce IL-12p70 and are impaired in IL-10 pro-
duction. Online supplemental material is available at http://www.jem.org/ 
cgi/content/full/jem.20081461/DC1. </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank Jim Simone and the fl ow cytometry core of the 
National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases Offi ce of 
Science and Technology for excellent advice and technical service. Additionally, we 
are grateful to Sandy White (Laboratory of Parasitic Diseases, National Institute of 
Allergy and Infectious Diseases) for animal technical support. 
This research was supported, in part, by the Intramural Research Program of 
the National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases of the 
National Institutes of Health. W.T. Watford is supported by National Institutes of 
Health grant #1 K22 AR53953-01. P. Tsichlis is supported by National Institutes of 
Health grant #R01 CA095431. 
The authors have no confl icting fi nancial interests. </p>

<p>Submitted: 7 July 2008 
Accepted: 16 October 2008 </p>



<p>Tpl2 silencing with siRNA </p>

<p>The target sequence for the Tpl2-specifi c siRNA was 5 Ј -AAGUCU-
CUGCUGCUUAGUGGC-3 Ј , which is 106 bp downstream of the Tpl2 
open reading frame ATG. This sequence had no sequence similarity to any 
other gene as determined by a BLAST search. Freshly isolated PBL were 
cultured overnight in complete RPMI 1640 without stimulation. The cul-
tured cells were washed three times in PBS and then resuspended in T cell 
Nucleofector solution (Amaxa Biosystems) containing 10 nmol of either a 
Tpl2-specifi c siRNA or a scrambled siRNA (Dharmacon Research Inc., La-
fayette, CO). The cells were placed in a nucleofection cuvette and electro-
porated in a Nucleofector instrument (Amaxa Biosystems) using program 
U-14. Immediately after transfection, the cells were placed in RPMI 1640 
containing 1 μ g/ml PHA and cultured for 24 h. The cells were then washed 
and cultured in RPMI with or without 10 ng/ml IL-12 for 24 h. </p>

<p>In vivo challenge with T. gondii </p>

<p>Age-matched female WT and Tpl2 KO mice were challenged i.p. with 20 
cysts of the avirulent ME49 strain of T. gondii . In vivo persistence of the local 
infection was assessed 7 d after infection by microscopic examination of 
hematoxylin and eosin -stained cytospins of PECs. Serum was collected, and 
infl ammatory cytokines were measured to monitor the acute immune re-
sponse in vivo. For antigen-specifi c recall responses, LN were isolated and 
stimulated at 2 × 10 6 /ml in a volume of 200 μ l with 5 μ g/ml STAg for 48 h. 
IFN-␥ production was measured by cytometric bead array. The number of 
cysts within the brains of 5-wk-infected mice was also quantifi ed. In brief, 
brains were isolated and homogenized by sequential passage through 19-and 
21-gauge needles, and cysts were counted microscopically. 
To assess the T cell -intrinsic requirement for Tpl2 in resistance to 
T. gondii , we generated chimeric mice by reconstituting Rag2-defi cient 
mice with ‫ف‬ 10 million purifi ed WT or Tpl2-defi cient CD4 + T cells. 
Transferred cells were allowed to homeostatically expand for &gt; 1 wk before 
i.p. challenge of mice with 20 cysts of T. gondii strain ME49. Serum cyto-
kines were assessed at day 7, and mice were subsequently observed for sur-
vival for 30 d. </p>



<p>TPL2 REGULATES CD4 + T CELL IFN-␥ PRODUCTION | Watford et al. </p>



</text></tei>