<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2955740" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Lincomycin-treated pumpkin leaves were illuminated with either continuous light or saturating single-turnover xenon 
flashes to study the dependence of photoinactivation of photosystem II (PSII) on the mode of delivery of light. The 
flash energy and the time interval between the flashes were varied between the experiments, and photoinactivation 
was measured with oxygen evolution and the ratio of variable to maximum fluorescence (F v /F m ). The photoinhibitory 
efficiency of saturating xenon flashes was found to be directly proportional to flash energy and independent of the 
time interval between the flashes. These findings indicate that a low-light-specific mechanism, based on charge 
recombination between PSII electron acceptors and the oxygen-evolving complex, is not the main cause of 
photoinactivation caused by short flashes in vivo. Furthermore, the relationship between the rate constant of 
photoinactivation and photon flux density was similar for flashes and continuous light when F v /F m was used to 
quantify photoinactivation, suggesting that continuous-light photoinactivation has a mechanism in which the quantum 
yield does not depend on the mode of delivery of light. A similar quantum yield of photoinhibition for flashes and 
continuous light is compatible with the manganese-based photoinhibition mechanism and with mechanisms in which 
singlet oxygen, produced via a direct photosensitization reaction, is the agent of damage. However, the classical 
acceptor-side and donor-side mechanisms do not predict a similar quantum yield for flashes and continuous light. </p>

<p>Light is needed for photosynthesis, but light also damages 
the photosynthetic machinery. Light-induced inhibition of 
the activity of photosystem II (PSII) has been termed photo-
inhibition (for reviews, see Aro et al., 1993; Melis, 1999; 
, 2008; Vass and Aro, 2008). A characteristic 
feature of photoinhibition is that degradation and de novo 
synthesis of the D1 protein are needed for restoration of the 
activity of PSII. All light intensities cause inactivation of 
PSII with a rate constant directly proportional to the light 
intensity ( and Aro, 1996), and therefore plants 
need to repair the inactive PSII units continuously. The rate 
of inactivation of PSII can be measured by illuminating </p>

<p>leaves in the presence of an inhibitor such as lincomycin 
that prevents the concurrent synthesis of the D1 protein. 
Photoinhibition is usually caused by continuous light, but 
strong, short single-turnover flashes also inactivate PSII 
(Keren et al., 1995, 1997). Single-turnover flashes do not 
occur in nature, but short flashes are valuable tools in 
studies of the mechanism of photoinactivation of PSII (see, 
for example, Keren et al., 1995, 1997, 2000; Szilard et al., 
2005;  et al., 2008). 
Photoinactivation of PSII has been explained by several 
hypothetical mechanisms. In the acceptor-side hypothesis 
(Vass et al., 1992), PSII is inactivated when the primary </p>

<p>Abbreviations: Chl, chlorophyll; cytD, cytochalasin D; F m , maximum fluorescence of a dark-adapted leaf; F 0 , minimum fluorescence of a dark-adapted leaf; fps, flashes 
per second; F v , variable fluorescence (F m -F 0 ); k PI , reaction rate constant of photoinhibition; NPQ, non-photochemical quenching of chlorophyll excitation energy; P 680 , 
P 680 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, 3 P 680 *, the ground state, oxidized state and excited triplet state of the primary donor of PSII; PPFD, photosynthetic photon flux density; PSII, photosystem II; Q A 
and Q B , the primary and secondary quinone electron acceptor of PSII, respectively. 
ª 2010 The Author(s). </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-
nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>quinone electron acceptor of PSII, already in state Q A 
-, 
becomes double reduced to Q A 
2-or stabilized by proton-
ation. Simulations imply that double reduction would not 
occur under low light ( et al., 2005) or during 
illumination with single-turnover flashes. However, if Q A 
remains reduced from flash to flash, then double reduction 
might occur even during illumination with single-turnover 
flashes. It has also been suggested that photoinactivation is 
caused by chlorophyll (Chl) triplets produced in the 
presence of unstabilized Q A 
-(Vass and Aro, 2008). 
In the 'statistical' donor-side hypothesis (Anderson et al., 
1998), PSII is inactivated when the oxygen-evolving com-
plex is occasionally unable to donate an electron, that is 
a miss occurs in the oxygen-evolving complex (Kok, 1970; 
Antal et al., 2009). After a miss, the oxidized primary donor 
P 680 
+ lives for 100-200 ls and then recombines with Q A </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>(Renger and Wolff, 1976; Renger and Holzwarth, 2005) or 
damages PSII by oxidizing an inappropriate target. Saturat-
ing single-turnover flashes would saturate the formation of 
long-lived P 680 
+ , and therefore donor-side photoinhibition 
would be saturated at the same flash energy that saturates 
PSII electron transfer. 
Generation of singlet oxygen by uncoupled Chls (Santa-
barbara et al., 2001) or by iron-sulphur centres and cyto-
chromes (Jung and Kim, 1990) only requires the formation 
of the triplet state of the photoreceptor and would therefore 
have the same quantum yield in continuous light and short 
flashes. Also manganese-dependent inactivation of PSII 
(Hakala et al., 2005; Ohnishi et al., 2005) would have the 
same quantum yield in continuous and flash light because 
manganese ions have low absorbance in the visible range, 
and therefore xenon flashes would not saturate absorption. 
The low-light photoinhibition hypothesis (Keren et al., 
1995, 1997, 2000; Szilard et al., 2005) applies to inactivation 
of PSII with short pulses of light or with low light. Accord-
ing to this hypothesis, generation of the triplet excited state 
of the primary donor ( 3 P 680 *) by recombination reactions 
(e.g. S 2 Q B 
-/S 1 Q B ) triggers the inactivation of PSII. The 
hypothesis is supported by the finding that nanosecond 
laser pulses fired with long dark intervals are more photo-
inhibitory than pulses fired with short intervals (Keren 
et al., 1997, 2000). This flash interval dependence has 
been explained by the fact that the flash yield of charge 
recombination increases with the length of the dark interval 
between the flashes. The low-light hypothesis is also 
supported by data showing that in the green alga Chlamy-
domonas, less degradation of the D1 protein per flash is 
caused by pairs of microsecond xenon flashes than by single 
flashes (Keren et al., 1995). In vitro experiments of in-
activation of PSII with xenon flashes have produced 
contrasting results. The measurements of Szilard et al. 
(2005) suggest that the photoinhibitory efficiency of xenon 
flashes depends on the length of the interval between 
flashes, but the data of Hakala et al. (2005) did not show 
any flash interval dependence. The low-light hypothesis 
predicts that flash-induced inactivation of PSII becomes 
saturated at the same flash energy that saturates PSII 
electron transport. </p>

<p>The aim of the present study was to probe the mechanism 
of photoinactivation of PSII by comparing the effects of 
short flashes and continuous light in intact leaves. For this, 
photoinhibition from lincomycin-treated pumpkin (Cucur-
bita maxima) leaves was measured under continuous white 
light and under illumination with 3 ls single-turnover xenon 
flashes, varying the energy of the flashes and the time interval 
between the flashes. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Plant material and growth conditions 
Pumpkin (C. maxima) plants were grown in a research greenhouse 
under the rhythm of 18 h light/6 h dark until leaves were fully 
expanded. Photosynthetic photon flux density (PPFD) was 
150 lmol m À2 s À1 , relative air humidity was 70%, and temperature 
was 24 °C. </p>

<p>In vivo photoinhibition treatments 
Prior to illumination, leaves were incubated overnight with their 
petioles in 2.3 mM lincomycin. The leaf petioles were also kept in 
2.3 mM lincomycin throughout the photoinhibition treatments 
during which the leaf blades were gently pressed on moist paper. A 
400 W Philips HPI-T Plus lamp was used for continuous-light 
photoinhibition experiments at a PPFD of 0.025, 3, 30, or 50 lmol 
m À2 s À1 (duration 45 h) and 300 lmol m À2 s À1 or 500 lmol m À2 s À1 
(duration 4 h). A 10 cm water filter and a cooling fan were used to 
remove heat. For photoinhibition experiments at a PPFD of 900, 
1500, 1800, or 2300 lmol m À2 s À1 (duration 6-12 h), a 300 W high-
pressure ozone-free xenon lamp (Oriel Instruments, Stratford, CT, 
USA) equipped with a 9 cm water filter and a Schott GG400 UV-
blocking filter was used. Neutral density filters (Lee Filters, Andover, 
UK) were used to fine-tune the PPFD, which was measured with 
a LI-189 quantum sensor (LiCor, Lincoln, NE, USA). 
Photoinhibition experiments with xenon flashes were done by 
illuminating lincomycin-treated pumpkin leaves with 3 ls flashes 
from an FX-200 xenon flash lamp (EG&amp;G, Gaithersburg, MD, 
USA) through a Schott GG400 filter. The upper surface of the 
filter was cooled with an air flow. Capacitors were used to adjust 
the flash energy, and the time interval between the flashes was 
adjusted with a computer. The durations and flash energies of the 
flash treatments are listed in Table 1. Each flash treatment was 
done with 1800 flashes and the duration of the treatment was 
varied in accordance with the time interval between the flashes, as 
indicated in Table 1. The average PPFD of each flash treatment 
was determined as previously described (Hakala et al., 2005). 
Prior to photoinhibition treatments, two leaf disks (2.8 cm 2 ) were 
always cut off from each leaf and analysed as control samples. In 
the middle and at the end of each continuous-light illumination 
treatment, two leaf disks were cut off from the illuminated area and 
used for measurements of fluorescence and oxygen evolution. One 
time point was used in the flash photoinhibition treatments. Pearson 
correlation coefficients and P-values reflecting their statistical 
significance were calculated with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., 
Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>Flash energy dependence of oxygen evolution in vivo 
The dependence of the amount of oxygen evolved per flash on the 
energy of the xenon flashes was measured from pumpkin leaf disks 
(9.6 cm 2 ) with a Clark-type oxygen electrode (Hansatech, King's 
Lynn, UK) at 23 °C in ;5% carbon dioxide, essentially as in Lee 
et al. (1999). The FX-200 xenon lamp was put in place of the 
standard lamp of the device, 5.7 cm above the leaf, and the flash 
energy was adjusted to 0.1-1.35 J. During the measurements, </p>



<p>xenon flashes were applied for 4 min, followed by 4 min of 
darkness. As high a repetition rate of the flashes was used as 
technically possible in order to obtain a reasonable signal to noise 
ratio of the oxygen measurements, and therefore flashes of 0.1-
0.4 J were applied at 30 flashes per second (fps), flashes of 0.5-
0.6 J at 20 fps, and flashes of 0.7-1.35 J at 10 fps. Several cycles of 
flashing (each with different energy, in random order) and 
darkness were measured from each leaf disk, and the measure-
ments were repeated with several leaf disks. </p>

<p>Dark inactivation 
Experiments were also done to determine the extent of dark 
inactivation of PSII activity during the maximum time span of the 
experiments (45 h). These assays were done in the same set-up as 
was used for photoinhibition treatments, except that the leaves 
were covered with several layers of aluminium foil. </p>

<p>Fluorescence measurements 
Chl a fluorescence of leaves was measured with a PAM-101 fluo-
rometer (Heinz Walz GmbH, Effeltrich, Germany) and the FIP 
fluorescence program ( and Karunen, 1990) was used to 
control the fluorometer. For measurements of F v /F m , unillumi-
nated and illuminated pumpkin leaf disks were dark-incubated for 
20 min. The initial fluorescence level (F 0 ) was measured under 
a weak measuring beam, and a saturating white light pulse (2 s; 
5800 lmol m À2 s À1 ) was used to induce maximum fluorescence 
(F m ). For measurements of non-photochemical quenching (NPQ), 
pumpkin leaf disks were dark-incubated for at least 30 min and 
NPQ was induced by 20 min actinic illumination, either with 
continuous light (175, 300, 930, or 1350 lmol m À2 s À1 ) or with 
xenon flashes of 1.35, 9.3, or 13.5 J fired at 1 fps. The respective 
PPFD values are 130, 930, and 1350 lmol m À2 s À1 . NPQ was 
calculated as (F m -F m #)/F m # (Bilger and  rkman, 1990). 
The effect of the xenon flashes on the openness of PSII centers 
was tested with the Walz PAM-2000 fluorometer by flashing 
pumpkin leaf disks from 1 cm distance through a GG400 filter 
under the light guide. After 2 min of flashing with a xenon lamp, 
a saturating pulse of 0.8 s (4500 lmol m À2 s À1 ) was fired to 
measure F m #, and then flashing was switched off and a far red 
light-emitting diode (LED) was switched on for 2 s to measure F 0 #. 
These measurements were done using the flash rates of 1, 10, 20, or </p>

<p>30 fps, and the respective flash energies of 13.5, 1.35, 0.6, and 
0.1 J. </p>

<p>Determination of Chl concentration and oxygen evolution activity 
Thylakoids were isolated from illuminated and unilluminated leaf 
disks as described by Sarvikas et al. (2010). Chl concentration was 
determined according to Porra et al. (1989) and adjusted to 10 lg 
ml À1 with PSII measuring buffer (40 mM HEPES-KOH pH 7.6; 
0.33 M sorbitol; 5 mM MgCl 2 ; 5 mM NaCl; 1 M glycine betaine; 
1 mM KH 2 PO 4 ; 5 mM NH 2 Cl). Oxygen evolution activity was 
measured with an oxygen electrode (Hansatech, King's Lynn, UK) 
in saturating red light with 0.125 mM 2,6-dichlorobenzoquinone 
as electron acceptor. Chl concentrations of pumpkin leaves were 
determined in N,N-dimethylformamide (Inskeep and Bloom, 1985) 
before and after the illumination treatments. </p>

<p>Measurements of transmittance 
Pumpkin leaves were first kept at a PPFD of 20 lmol m À2 s À1 for 
30 min. Leaf petioles were then immersed either in control solution 
containing water and 2.5% dimethylsulphoxide (DMSO) or in 
solution containing 5 lM cytochalasin D (cytD), in 2.5% (v/v) 
DMSO, and the leaves were kept at a PPFD of 20 lmol m À2 s À1 
until the transmittance was measured the following morning. Leaf 
disks (4.5 cm 2 ) were then placed on wet paper on a temperature-
controlled surface and illuminated from the adaxial side at a PPFD 
of 1350 lmol m À2 s À1 with either a 300 W high-pressure ozone-
free xenon lamp (continuous light) or an FX-200 flash lamp 
(xenon flashes, 13.5 J, 1 fps). Before the illumination treatment 
and every 10 min after the beginning of illumination, the trans-
mittance of the leaf was measured in a separate set-up in which the 
leaf was illuminated from the adaxial side with continuous light 
(PPFD 1350 lmol m À2 s À1 ) and transmission was measured from 
the abaxial side with an LI-189 quantum sensor. The positions of 
the lamp and the quantum sensor were fixed and the leaf was 
always placed in exactly the same position in the transmission set-
up. Measurement of transmission of light through a leaf is a 
standard method for measuring chloroplast movements (see, for 
example, Berg et al., 2006). </p>

<p>Confocal microscopy 
Laser scanning confocal microscopy was performed with an 
inverted confocal laser scanning microscope (Zeiss LSM510 Meta) 
with a 320/0.50 water objective. Chloroplasts were imaged by Chl 
autofluorescence excited at 488 nm with an argon diode laser and 
detected through a 650 nm emission filter. Maximal projections of 
the sequential confocal images were created with Zeiss LSM Image 
Browser. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Xenon flash-induced photoinhibition in vivo depends on 
flash energy but not on the time interval between 
flashes </p>

<p>Properties of the flashes. In the photoinhibition experiments, 
flash energies above the saturation of PSII electron transfer 
were used. Such flashes cause one turnover of PSII irres-
pective of the flash energy. To ensure saturation, the flash 
energy response of PSII oxygen evolution was measured. In 
these measurements, the lamp to leaf distance was five times 
longer than in the photoinhibition set-up, and therefore the 
flash energy response of oxygen evolution provides an 
upper limit for the flash energy required to saturate PSII </p>

<p>Table 1. Photoinhibition treatments with xenon flashes </p>

<p>The average PPFD of each flash treatment of lincomycin-treated 
pumpkin leaves was determined as previously described (Hakala 
et al., 2005). The flash treatments were done with 1800 flashes by 
varying the flash energy, the time interval between the flashes, and 
the duration of the experiment, as indicated. </p>

<p>PPFD (mmol 
m À2 s À1 ) </p>

<p>Flash 
energy (J) </p>

<p>Flash 
interval (s) </p>

<p>Duration of the 
experiment (h) </p>

<p>1.5 
1.35 
90 
45 
15 
1.35 
9 
4.5 
15 
13.5 
90 
45 
40 
3.4 
9 
4.5 
130 
1.35 
1 
0.5 
150 
13.5 
9 
4.5 
340 
3.4 
1 
0.5 
530 
5.3 
1 
0.5 
930 
9.3 
1 
0.5 
1350 
13.5 
1 
0.5 </p>

<p>Photoinhibition with short flashes and continuous light | 4241 </p>

<p>electron transport in the photoinhibition set-up. The results 
indicate that saturation of oxygen evolution of intact leaves 
occurred at 0.7-0.9 J (Fig. 1). Pumpkin leaves contain 
;600 lmol Chl m À2 , and therefore the maximum rate of 
oxygen evolution (1.2 lmol O 2 per four flashes) corre-
sponded to 88% of reaction centres, assuming one PSII per 
440 Chl molecules. Separate fluorescence measurements 
showed that PSII reaction centres remain open between the 
flashes when pumpkin leaves are flashed at 10-30 fps as in 
the flash energy response measurements (Supplementary 
Table S1 available at JXB online). 
For comparison of flashes and continuous light, average 
PPFD values for flash treatments were calculated, using the 
known relationship between the flash energy and flash 
photon content of this lamp (Hakala et al., 2005). In the 
original flash photon content measurements, the number 
of visible-light photons per flash was first measured at a 
narrow wavelength range (475-610 nm) by illuminating 
meso-diphenylhelianthrene, a chemical actinometer sub-
stance (Brauer et al., 1983), and the flash photon content in 
the 400-700 nm range was obtained by correcting these 
data with the emission spectrum of the flash lamp (Supple-
mentary Fig. S2 at JXB online). Average PPFD values, used 
to compare flashes with continuous light, were obtained by 
dividing the flash photon content by the target area and 
multiplying by the number of flashes in unit time. 
Experiments were also carried out to measure how 
efficiently the flashes induce NPQ, as compared with 
continuous light. For this, pumpkin leaves were illuminated 
for 20 min either with continuous light of different in-
tensities up to a PPFD of 1350 lmol m À2 s À1 or with xenon 
flashes of 1.35, 9.3, or 13.5 J fired at 1 fps, producing an 
average PPFD range similar to continuous light (Table 1). 
Measurements of NPQ at the end of the illumination 
showed a linear increase of NPQ with PPFD of continuous 
light (Fig. 2). Illumination with xenon flashes at 1 fps at the 
same PPFD range caused much less NPQ than continuous 
light, and flashes of 9.3 J and 13.5 J caused the same NPQ 
response (Fig. 2). Flashes fired at 90 s intervals did not 
cause NPQ, and the NPQ response caused by flashes fired 
at 9 s intervals was not statistically significant (data not 
shown). The coefficient of photochemical quenching q P 
remained at 0.98 during flashing of pumpkin leaf disks at 
1 fps with the flash energy of 13.5 J (Supplementary Table 
S1 at JXB online). 
Dependence of photoinactivation of PSII on flash energy. 
To induce photoinhibition with flashes, a lincomycin-
treated pumpkin leaf was placed under the xenon flash lamp 
and flashing was repeated until 1800 flashes had been fired. 
Two alternative methods were used to measure photo-
inhibition: light-induced decrease in F v /F m , measured from 
leaves, and light-induced decrease in the light-saturated rate 
of PSII oxygen evolution, measured from thylakoids iso-
lated from treated leaves. The flash number-based rate 
constant of photoinactivation (k PI ) was calculated by fitting 
the original data to the first-order reaction equation using 
the formula k PI ¼(1/1800) flash À1 3ln(100/Act), where Act is the 
percentage of PSII activity (F v /F m or oxygen evolution, as </p>

<p>indicated) left after treatment with 1800 flashes. Slow loss of 
PSII activity in the dark was measured separately and taken 
into account by subtracting the rate constant of dark 
inactivation from the raw k PI . The Chl content of the leaves 
remained at 80-100% of the control for 45 h. 
Comparison of photoinhibition induced with saturating 
xenon flashes of different energies indicated that the k PI of 
flash photoinactivation was directly proportional to the 
flash energy, regardless of whether k PI was determined from 
oxygen evolution or from F v /F m (Fig. 3). The correlation 
between k PI and flash energy was statistically highly 
significant whether the correlation was calculated from all 
data or from subsets with the same flash interval (Supple-
mentary Table S2 at JXB online). No saturation of photo-
inactivation could be detected. Larger k PI values were 
obtained from oxygen evolution measurements than from 
fluorescence measurements (Fig. 3). 
Dependence of photoinactivation on flash interval. To 
measure the effect of the flash to flash interval on 
inactivation of PSII in vivo, xenon flashes with 1, 9, and 
90 s intervals were applied on pumpkin leaves. The photo-
inhibitory efficiency of the flashes did not show a consistent 
dependence on the flash interval when F v /F m was used to </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Rate of oxygen evolution during illumination of pumpkin 
leaf disks with xenon flashes of 0.1-1.35 J. The error bars show 
the SD of 2-5 experiments. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. NPQ induced by 20 min illumination at different PPFDs of 
continuous light (circles) and with xenon flashes (triangles). The 
flash to flash interval was 1 s and the flash energies were 1.35, 
9.3, and 13.5 J. Prior to the experiments, pumpkin leaves were 
dark-adapted for at least 30 min. Each symbol represents an 
average of 3-5 individual experiments, and the error bars, drawn if 
larger than the symbol, show the SD. </p>



<p>measure PSII activity, and independence or a slight increase 
of photoinhibitory efficiency with flash interval was seen in 
the oxygen evolution data (Fig. 4). However, no statistically 
significant correlations between k PI values and flash interval 
could be found (Supplementary Table S2 at JXB online). 
Thus, when k PI values are plotted as a function of flash 
energy, all experiments were found to fall on the same line 
independently of the flash interval (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>Photon flux density dependence of flash-induced 
photoinhibition </p>

<p>The k PI values used to compare continuous-light-induced and 
flash-induced photoinactivation were obtained by fitting the 
data to the first-order reaction equation Act¼1003exp(-
k PI 3t), where Act is the percentage activity remaining at 
time t. The k PI values of the flash and continuous-light treat-
ments showed an essentially direct proportionality to PPFD 
irrespective of the measurement method (F v /F m or oxygen 
evolution) (Fig. 5), although some deviation from direct 
proportionality could be found both in very low light and at 
the high PPFD of 2300 lmol m À2 s À1 . The slope of the plot 
describing dependence of k PI on PPFD was the same for 
flash and continuous-light treatments when F v /F m was used 
to measure photoinhibition (Fig. 5A). Essentially the same </p>

<p>slope was also obtained for continuous-light-induced photo-
inhibition measured with oxygen evolution (Fig. 5B, circles), 
whereas single-turnover flashes had a stronger inhibitory 
effect on oxygen evolution (Fig. 5B). </p>

<p>Chloroplast movements under short xenon flashes and 
continuous light </p>

<p>The oxygen evolution measurements represent all cell layers, 
whereas Chl fluorescence is emitted by the cell layers close to 
the leaf surface. Therefore, the difference between F v /F m and 
oxygen evolution in flash-photoinhibited leaves (Fig. 5) prom-
pted measurement of chloroplast movements, as the avoid-
ance response in which chloroplasts stack on each other can 
obviously not protect the topmost chloroplasts of the leaf. 
During 30 min illumination with continuous light, PPFD 
1350 lmol m À2 s À1 , the transmittance of pumpkin leaves 
increased from 7.5% to 10.4% (Fig. 6A). Transmission of 
blue light increased more than transmission of red light, and 
that of green light was intermediate (Fig. 6B). 
The increase in transmission was apparently caused 
by chloroplast movements, as 5 lM cytD, an actin-
depolymerizing agent, partially inhibited the increase. For 
comparison, changes in the transmittance of Arabidopsis 
leaves were also studied, and it was found that 30 min 
illumination induced an increase in transmission from 13% 
to 25%, twice as much as in pumpkin, and confocal 
microscopy showed light-induced movement of chloroplasts </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Flash energy dependence of the rate constant of photo-
inhibition (k PI ) calculated per xenon flash. The k PI values were 
determined from both the photoinhibitory loss of F v /F m (A) and the 
decrease in the light-saturated rate of oxygen evolution (B). The 
photoinhibition treatments were done by illuminating lincomycin-
treated pumpkin leaves with xenon flashes of the indicated 
energies. F v /F m was measured from the leaf surface, and oxygen 
evolution was measured from thylakoids isolated from treated 
leaves. In thylakoids isolated from untreated leaves, the rate of 
oxygen evolution was 335645 lmol O 2 mg Chl À1 h À1 . The time 
interval between xenon flashes was either 1 s (diamonds), 9 s 
(triangles), or 90 s (squares). Each data point represents 4-9 
independent experiments, and the error bars, drawn if larger than 
the symbol, show the SE. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Dependence of k PI , calculated per flash, on the time 
interval between xenon flashes. The k PI values were determined 
from the photoinhibitory loss of F v /F m (A) or from the decrease in 
the light-saturated rate of oxygen evolution (B). Fluorescence was 
measured from leaves, and oxygen evolution was measured from 
thylakoids isolated from the treated leaves. The energies of the 
xenon flashes were 13.5 J (circles), 9.3 J (squares), 5.3 J (stars), 
3.4 J (triangles), or 1.35 J (diamonds). Each data point represents 
4-9 individual experiments, and the error bars, drawn if larger than 
the symbol, show the SE. </p>

<p>Photoinhibition with short flashes and continuous light | 4243 </p>

<p>to the anticlinal cell walls in Arabidopsis (Supplementary 
Fig. S1 at JXB online). However, both before and after 
illumination, pumpkin chloroplasts appeared to stay in the 
anticlinal position in the mesophyll cells accessible with the 
confocal microscope (Supplementary Fig. S1). 
When pumpkin leaves were illuminated for 30 min with 
xenon flashes (13.5 J, 1 fps, 1350 lmol m À2 s À1 ), leaf 
transmission increased only to 8.4% from the initial value 
of 7.5% (Fig. 6A). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The aim of the present study was to gain insight into the 
mechanism of photoinactivation of PSII by illuminating 
intact lincomycin-treated pumpkin leaves with saturating 
3 ls single-turnover xenon flashes. The single-turnover 
nature of the flashes was ensured by showing that flashing 
does not cause accumulation of reduced Q A (Supplementary 
Table S1 at JXB online) and that flashing causes very little 
NPQ even at the highest flash rate of 1 fps (Fig. 2). Meas-
urements of both oxygen evolution and F v /F m show that the 
photoinhibitory efficiency of single-turnover flashes is di-</p>

<p>rectly proportional to flash energy (Fig. 3). Furthermore, the 
fluorescence data showed that the photoinhibitory efficiency 
of photons of single-turnover flashes is similar to the photo-
inhibitory efficiency of photons of continuous light (Fig. 5). 
Direct proportionality between light intensity and k PI is a key 
feature of continuous-light photoinhibition (Jones and Kok, 
1966; Park et al., 1995;  and Aro, 1996; Allakhver-
diev and Murata, 2004). Thus, the finding that the same 
proportionality constant applies to photoinhibition under 
flashing light and under continuous light (Fig. 5) suggests 
that the mechanism of photoinactivation is the same in both 
conditions. 
Similar photoinhibitory efficiency of continuous light and 
flash light can be used as a criterion for evaluation of 
photoinhibition hypotheses. Full opening of PSII reaction 
centres between the flashes (Supplementary Table S1 at JXB 
online) allows the possibility that the acceptor-side mecha-
nism (Vass et al., 1992) causes flash photoinhibition to be 
excluded, as neither double reduction of Q A nor production 
of singlet oxygen by charge recombination due to stabilized </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Dependence of k PI on PPFD in lincomycin-treated pumpkin 
leaves. The k PI value was calculated per hour from the photo-
inhibitory decrease in F v /F m (A) or from the photoinhibitory loss of 
oxygen evolution (B). The leaves were illuminated with continuous 
light (open circles) or with xenon flashes (filled symbols). The flash 
to flash intervals of the flash photoinhibition treatments were 1 s 
(diamonds), 9 s (triangles), or 90 s (squares). The flash energies of 
the xenon flash treatments were adjusted between 1.35 J and 
13.5 J, and the mean PPFD values of the xenon flash treatments 
were calculated by multiplying the photon content of one flash by 
the number of flashes in unit time and dividing by the area of the 
illuminated spot. Each data point represents 3-9 independent 
experiments, and the error bars, drawn if larger than the symbol, 
show the SD. </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Light-induced increase in transmission, measured from the 
adaxial to the abaxial side of pumpkin leaves with a Li-189 
quantum sensor. (A) Increase in transmission measured during 
illumination with continuous light (PPFD 1350 lmol m À2 s À1 , 
circles) in the absence (open symbols) or presence (filled circles) of 
cytochalasin D (cytD), or with xenon flashes (13.5 J, 1 fps, 
triangles). (B) Relative changes in transmission at the wavelength 
ranges of 450-500 nm (diamonds), 550-600 nm (triangles), and 
650-700 nm (squares). The wavelength-specific values were 
measured by using a pair of low-pass and high-pass filters 
between the leaf and the quantum sensor. Each data point 
represents an average of 3-5 experiments, and the error bars, 
drawn if larger than the symbol, show the SD. Different letters (a, 
b, c) indicate that the 30 min treated values differ significantly from 
each other according to the t-test (P &lt;0.05). </p>



<p>Q A 
-can happen unless Q A is singly reduced when a single-
turnover flash is fired. Proportionality between k PI and the 
energy of the saturating flashes also indicates that the 
'statistical' donor-side mechanism (Anderson et al., 1998) 
cannot be responsible for flash photoinhibition, as the 
amount of long-lived P 680 
+ cannot depend on how over-
saturating a flash is. 
The in vivo photoinhibitory efficiency of the flashes did 
not consistently depend on the time interval between the 
flashes (Fig. 4). This finding is in agreement with earlier in 
vitro data (Hakala et al., 2005). The flash interval range of 
1-90 s was chosen on the basis of the 35 s half-time of the 
charge recombination reaction S 2 Q B 
-/S 1 Q B , measured 
with thermoluminescence (Keren et al., 1997). At 90 s 
intervals, 83% of Q B 
-produced by a flash recombines with 
the S 2 state of the oxygen-evolving complex before the next 
flash comes, while at 1 s intervals only 2% recombines and 
most Q B 
-is converted to Q B 
2-and replaced by oxidized 
plastoquinone. Thus, flashes fired at 90 s intervals cause 40 
times as many recombination reactions as flashes fired at 1 s 
intervals. Lack of dependence on flash interval (Fig. 4) 
indicates that the low-light photoinhibition hypothesis 
which assumes that photoinactivation starts with charge 
recombination (Keren et al., 1997, 2000) does not explain 
flash photoinhibition in vivo. Furthermore, the low-light 
hypothesis cannot explain why the photoinhibitory effi-
ciency of saturating flashes depends on flash energy, as the 
same number of recombination reactions is induced with all 
saturating flashes. The results of the present study are in 
agreement with the finding that the quantum yield of 
photoinactivation of PSII is the same from 6 lmol m À2 s À1 
to 2000 lmol m À2 s À1 of continuous light ( and 
Aro, 1996). Thus, a specific mechanism for photoinactiva-
tion of PSII under low light is improbable. 
The manganese mechanism (Hakala et al., 2005) and gen-
eration of singlet oxygen by uncoupled Chls (Santabarbara 
et al., 2001) or by iron-sulphur centres (Jung and Kim, 
1990) would have the same quantum yield for continuous 
light and single-turnover flash illumination, and therefore 
these mechanisms qualify as explanations for the present in 
vivo photoinhibition data. The manganese mechanism 
functions in parallel with photoinactivation mediated by 
the PSII antenna (Sarvikas et al., 2010). The results of the 
present study do not define the Chl-dependent mechanism, 
but generation of singlet oxygen may have a role in it. 
In the present study, three flash intervals and five flash 
energies were tested. The possibility that use of subsaturat-
ing flashes or a larger number of flash intervals might 
provide more insight cannot be excluded. 
A similar photoinhibitory efficiency of continuous light in 
F v /F m and oxygen evolution measurements (Fig. 5) is in 
agreement with earlier data (Krause et al., 1992; Schnettger 
et al., 1994). Flash-induced and continuous-light-induced 
photoinactivation had the same quantum yield in F v /F m 
measurements (Fig. 5A), but flashes were more efficient at 
causing photoinhibition of oxygen evolution (Figs 3, 5). 
This finding can be explained by assuming that the photo-
inhibitory efficiency of flashes and continuous light is </p>

<p>similar but chloroplasts of deep cell layers are more 
efficiently illuminated by flashes than by continuous light. 
The chloroplast avoidance response (Wada et al., 2003) 
would not protect the top layer of chloroplasts, and the 
finding that flashes cause very little chloroplast movements 
may partially explain why the flashes penetrate better in the 
leaf. The chloroplast avoidance response affects mostly 
transmission of blue light (Fig. 7), which is the most 
effective visible-light wavelength range in photoinhibition 
in vivo (Sarvikas et al., 2006). Chloroplast movements have 
little effect on leaf reflectance (Park et al., 1996) and 
therefore transmission measurements estimate changes in 
leaf absorptance. 
The data presented in this paper lead to two important 
conclusions about the mechanism of photoinhibition in vivo. 
First, the finding that the photoinhibitory efficiency of 
saturating flashes depends on flash energy but is indepen-
dent of flash to flash interval indicates that charge re-
combination between PSII electron acceptors and the 
oxygen-evolving complex cannot be the trigger of photo-
inhibition caused by short flashes in vivo. Secondly, photons 
of continuous light and photons of short flashes were found 
to have similar photoinhibitory efficiency, suggesting that 
continuous-light photoinhibition has a mechanism in which 
the quantum yield does not depend on the mode of delivery 
of light. </p>

<p>Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data are available at JXB online. 
Figure S1. Confocal microscope images from pumpkin 
and Arabidopsis leaves. 
Figure S2. Emission spectra of the xenon flash lamp and 
the continuous-light lamps used in this study. 
Table S1. Effect of illumination with xenon flashes on 
photochemical quenching in pumpkin leaves. 
Table S2. Pearson correlation coefficients between k PI 
and flash energy, and between k PI and flash interval. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work was financially supported by the Academy of 
Finland (grant number 110409), the Turku University 
Foundation, the Finnish Cultural Foundation, and the Emil 
Aaltonen Foundation. </p>

<p>References </p>

<p>Allakhverdiev SI, Murata N. 2004. Environmental stress inhibits the 
synthesis de novo of proteins involved in the photodamage-repair 
cycle of photosystem II in Synechocystis sp. PCC 6803. Biochimica et 
Biophysica Acta 1657, 23-28. </p>

<p>Anderson JM, Park Y-I, Chow WS. 1998. Unifying model for the 
photoinactivation of photosystem II in vivo: a hypothesis. 
Photosynthesis Research 56, 1-13. </p>

<p>Photoinhibition with short flashes and continuous light | 4245 </p>







<p>Photoinhibition with short flashes and continuous light | 4247 </p>

</text></tei>