<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2708934" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The IKK [IκB (inhibitory κB) kinase] complex is a key 
regulatory component of NF-κB (nuclear factor κB) activation 
and is responsible for mediating the degradation of IκB, thereby 
allowing nuclear translocation of NF-κB and transcription of 
target genes. NEMO (NF-κB essential modulator), the regulatory 
subunit of the IKK complex, plays a pivotal role in this process 
by integrating upstream signals, in particular the recognition 
of polyubiquitin chains, and relaying these to the activation of 
IKKα and IKKβ, the catalytic subunits of the IKK complex. The 
oligomeric state of NEMO is controversial and the mechanism 
by which it regulates activation of the IKK complex is poorly 
understood. Using a combination of hydrodynamic techniques 
we now show that apo-NEMO is a highly elongated, dimeric 
protein that is in weak equilibrium with a tetrameric assembly. 
Interaction with peptides derived from IKKβ disrupts formation 
of the tetrameric NEMO complex, indicating that interaction with 
IKKα and IKKβ and tetramerization are mutually exclusive. </p>

<p>Furthermore, we show that NEMO binds to linear di-ubiquitin 
with a stoichiometry of one molecule of di-ubiquitin per NEMO 
dimer. This stoichiometry is preserved in a construct comprising 
the second coiled-coil region and the leucine zipper and in one that 
essentially spans the full-length protein. However, our data show 
that at high di-ubiquitin concentrations a second weaker binding 
site becomes apparent, implying that two different NEMO-
di-ubiquitin complexes are formed during the IKK activation 
process. We propose that the role of these two complexes is 
to provide a threshold for activation, thereby ensuring sufficient 
specificity during NF-κB signalling. </p>

<p>NF-κB (nuclear factor κB) transcription factors are key regulators 
of immune and inflammatory responses (reviewed in [1,2]). In 
unstimulated cells they are found in complex with IκB (inhibitory 
κB) proteins, an interaction that prevents their translocation to the 
nucleus and retains NF-κBs in the cytosol. Stimulus-dependent 
phosphorylation of IκBs induces their Lys 
48 -linked ubiquitination 
and subsequent degradation by the 26S proteasome, thereby liber-
ating NF-κB and allowing nuclear translocation. A key regulator 
of this process is the multi-subunit IKK (IκB kinase) complex 
(sometimes referred to as the signalosome), which is composed 
of two kinases, IKKα and IKKβ, and a non-catalytic regulatory 
subunit called IKKγ or NEMO (NF-κB essential modulator) [3- 5]. The apparent molecular mass of the resting IKK complex 
has been shown to be in the 700-900 kDa range, suggesting 
that it may contain multiple copies of its constituents [6-8]. 
Nonetheless, its precise composition is controversial, and it may 
be that its size varies in a stimulus-dependent manner [9]. NEMO 
is the regulatory hub of the IKK complex and integrates multiple 
signals, including phosphorylation, ubiquitination and interaction 
with ubiquitin chains [10]. In addition to being the target of 
multiple post-translational modifications, NEMO also acts as an 
assembly platform that facilitates the incorporation of a variety 
of proteins into the IKK signalosome, such as the viral proteins 
vFLIP {viral FLICE [FADD (Fas-associated death domain)-like 
interleukin 1β-converting enzyme]-inhibitory protein} and Tax, 
which can act as potent activators of NF-κB [11,12]. </p>

<p>NEMO is a ∼ 50 kDa protein predicted to consist of two coiled-
coil regions, CC1 and CC2, a LZ (leucine zipper) and a ZF (zinc 
finger) (Figure 1). In spite of extensive studies aimed at defining 
the assembly of NEMO, its oligomeric state still remains a matter 
of some controversy. The apo form of the full-length protein 
has variously been described as monomeric, dimeric, trimeric or 
tetrameric state [13-15]. A number of studies have suggested that 
the second coiled-coil region, together with the LZ, constitutes the 
minimal oligomerization domain (from now on referred to as 
CoZi) [15,16]. However, similar to the full-length protein, the 
oligomeric state of this region is not clear and has, for example, 
been described as a trimer that can associate to 'pseudo-hexamers' 
upon appropriate stimulation [16]. In contrast, two recent crystal 
structures of this region have shown it forms a parallel, dimeric 
coiled-coil, in accordance with other studies that reported 
a dimeric assembly [15,17-19]. The oligomeric state of the 
N-terminal coiled-coil region is similarly unresolved, and a range 
of oligomeric states have been reported [20-22]. 
A key step towards a better understanding of the regulatory 
role of NEMO in NF-κB activation was the observation that 
NEMO interacts specifically with polyubiquitin chains ([23], 
but see [23a], [24]). These experiments initially utilized linear 
('genetically linked', i.e. Gly 
76 to Met 
1 linked) polyubiquitin 
chains in a yeast two-hybrid screen. However, Lys 
63 -linked 
ubiquitin chains attached to RIP1 (receptor interaction protein 
kinase) are believed to be the physiological targets ([23], but see 
[23a]). This interaction is suggested to recruit the IKK complex 
to receptor complexes and thereby promote the subsequent </p>

<p>Abbreviations used: AUC, analytical ultracentrifugation; CoZi, C-terminal portion of NEMO encompassing the second coiled-coil region and the leucine 
zipper domain; IκB, inhibitory κB; IKK, IκB kinase; IKK NBD , IKKβ NEMO-binding domain; ITC, isothermal titration calorimetry; LZ, leucine zipper; MALS, 
multi-angle laser light scattering; NF-κB, nuclear factor κB; NEMO, NF-κB essential modulator; NEMO 355 , NEMO residues 1-355, with mutations C54S and 
K285N; SEC, size-exclusion chromatography; TCEP, tris-(2-carboxyethyl)phosphine; RI, refractive index; RIP1, receptor interaction protein kinase; vFLIP, 
viral FLICE [FADD (Fas-associated death domain)-like interleukin 1β-converting enzyme]-inhibitory protein; ZF, zinc finger. 
1 These authors contributed equally to this work. 
2 Present address: UCL Medical School -Royal Free Campus, Rowland Hill Street, London NW3 2PF, U.K. 
3 To whom correspondence should be addressed (email katrin.rittinger@nimr.mrc.ac.uk). </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2009 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>www.biochemj.org </p>

<p>Biochemical Journal </p>



<p>F. J. Ivins and others </p>

<p>Figure 1 Structure and purity of protein constructs used in the present study </p>

<p>(A) Schematic representation of the domain structure of NEMO and the constructs used in the present study. (B) Coomassie Blue-stained SDS/polyacrylamide gel showing the purity of the protein 
preparations used. The faint bands on the NEMO 355 and CoZi lanes at twice the molecular mass represent incompletely denatured dimers. Molecular masses are shown to the left in kDa. </p>

<p>activation of the kinase activity of IKKα and IKKβ. The 
binding site for ubiquitin has been mapped to a region of 
NEMO that has homology with ABIN (A20-binding inhibitor 
of NF-κB) and optineurin and has been named the NUB or 
UBAN motif ([23], but see [23a], [24,25]). This conserved 
binding region is located within the CoZi domain. Although 
a number of studies have shown that specific recognition of 
K63-linked ubiquitin chains is important for NF-κB activation 
([23], but see [23a], [24]), it has recently been reported that 
linear di-ubiquitin binds with a 100-fold higher affinity to the 
CoZi domain than K63-linked di-ubiquitin [17,18,26]. This 
observation is particularly interesting in the light of a recent 
report that NEMO itself becomes modified with linear ubiquitin 
chains that are attached by the ligase complex LUBAC [27]. 
In the present study we have applied a combination of 
complementary hydrodynamic methods to define the oligomeric 
state of NEMO and resolve the current controversy surrounding 
its self-association. We show that apo-NEMO forms a tight dimer 
that is in a relatively weak equilibrium with a tetrameric assembly. 
Importantly, binding of IKKβ-derived peptides prevented 
formation of the tetramer, indicating that the IKK-binding region 
in the N-terminal portion of NEMO is responsible for the 
formation of higher-molecular-mass species and that IKK binding 
and tetramerization are mutually exclusive. Furthermore, we show 
that the CoZi domain and a nearly full-length NEMO construct 
bind di-ubiquitin with similar affinities but slightly different 
energetics. These results suggest that no major conformational 
changes take place upon interaction with ubiquitin chains, but that 
minor rearrangements may be induced in the N-terminal coiled-
coil region. Surprisingly, only one di-ubiquitin chain binds to 
the symmetrical NEMO dimer. However, a second binding site 
becomes apparent at high ubiquitin concentrations, implying that 
two different NEMO/polyubiquitin complexes are formed during 
the activation process. This observation may have implications 
for the in vivo function of NEMO and suggests that association 
with protein assemblies that provide a high density of poly-
ubiquitin chains might induce clustering of NEMO, which in 
turn will lead to activation of the IKK complex. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL </p>

<p>Plasmids </p>

<p>The cDNA for full-length mouse and human NEMO and the 
expression plasmid for di-ubiquitin were kindly provided by Dr 
F. Randow (MRC-LMB, Cambridge, U.K.). NEMO residues 251-
355 (CoZi), NEMO (residues 1-355, C54S, K285N referred to 
as NEMO 355 ) and human NEMO residues 218-363 were cloned 
into the pGEX-6P1 expression vector. The C54S mutation was 
introduced to prevent disulfide bond formation, K285N has been 
described in [19]. Bovine mono-ubiquitin was purchased from 
Sigma. </p>

<p>Protein purification </p>

<p>For CoZi purification, Escherichia coli BL21(DE3) cells 
containing the plasmid were grown in LB (Luria-Bertani) broth 
at 37 
• C to a D 600 of ∼ 0.8. Protein expression was induced by 
the addition of 0.5 mM IPTG (isopropyl β-D-thiogalactoside) 
and cells were incubated for a further 3 h. Cell pellets were 
resuspended in Buffer A {50 mM Tris/HCl, pH 8, 500 mM NaCl 
and 0.5 mM TCEP [tris-(2-carboxyethyl)phosphine]}, lysed by 
sonication and the crude lysate was applied to a pre-equilibrated 
glutathione-Sepharose column (GE Healthcare) at 1 ml/min. 
Bound protein was eluted with Buffer A containing 20 mM 
reduced glutathione. The GST affinity tag was removed by the 
addition of 3C protease and incubation at 4 
• C overnight. 
The sample was concentrated in 10-kDa-molecular-mass-cut-off 
Vivaspin concentrators (Sartorius) and applied to a Superdex 75 
column (GE Healthcare) pre-equilibrated with Buffer B (50 mM 
Tris/HCl, pH 8, 100 mM NaCl and 0.5 mM TCEP). Fractions 
containing CoZi were pooled and loaded on to another GSH 
column to remove contaminating GST and 3C protease. CoZi 
was concentrated to 20 mg/ml. 
For NEMO 355 purification, expression was carried out in 
Rosetta2(DE3)pLysS cells at 18 
• C for 16 h. Cell pellets were 
resuspended in Buffer 
GST (20 mM Tris/HCl, pH 8, 500 mM NaCl, 
10 % glycerol and 0.25 mM TCEP) and lysed by sonication. </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2009 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>Nemo oligomerization and interaction with ubiquitin </p>



<p>Crude lysate was applied to a column of glutathione-Sepharose 
resin followed by extensive washing with Buffer 
GST . The GST 
affinity tag was removed on-column by overnight incubation 
with 1.5 mg of 3C protease. GST-free NEMO 355 was eluted in 
Buffer 
Q (20 mM Tris/HCl, pH 8, 50 mM NaCl, 10 % glycerol 
and 0.25 mM TCEP) and applied to a Source Q ion-exchange 
column (GE Healthcare). The sample was eluted with a 1 M 
NaCl 20 column volume gradient in Buffer 
Q , and concentrated to 
5 ml on a 50-kDa-molecular-mass-cut-off Vivaspin concentrator. 
The sample was then applied to a Superdex 200 size-exclusion 
column pre-equilibrated in Buffer 
GST . The relevant fractions were 
concentrated to 13.7 mg/ml. 
For linear di-ubiquitin purification, expression was carried out 
in BL21(DE3) cells for 3 h at 37 
• C. Purification was carried 
out as described previously for CoZi, except that the affinity tag 
was removed by incubation with TEV protease instead of 3C 
protease. Pure protein was concentrated using-5-kDa-molecular-
mass-cut-off Vivaspin columns to 13.3 mg/ml. 
Protein concentrations were determined by UV spectrometry 
using calculated 280 nm molar absorption coefficients. Con-
centrations were confirmed by analysis of the differential RI 
(refractive index) eluate peaks from the SEC (size-exclusion 
chromatography)-MALS (multi-angle light scattering) experi-
ments described below. Specifically, integration of an RI peak 
yields a total mass that, in conjunction with known loading 
volume, allows determination of the loading concentration in-
dependent of UV absorbance. Concentration values from both 
methods were in good agreement. Furthermore, expected formula 
molecular masses were confirmed for each protein using MS. </p>

<p>ITC (isothermal titration calorimetry) </p>

<p>All samples were extensively dialysed into fresh buffer [50 mM 
Tris/HCl, pH 8, 0.5 mM TCEP and 100 mM NaCl (CoZi) or 
150 mM NaCl (NEMO 355 )]. Protein concentration was determined 
by UV absorbance and confirmed by the integration of RI 
peaks from SEC-MALS (see below). ITC measurements were 
carried out at 10 
• C, 18 
• C and 25 
• C on a VP-ITC or ITC200 
MicroCalorimeter (MicroCal Inc). In most cases, ITC titrations 
were carried out with 29 consecutive 10 μl injections of ubiquitin 
into the cell containing NEMO on the VP-ITC or alternatively 
with 19 consecutive 2 μl injections on the ITC200 instrument (all 
at various concentrations). ITC data were analysed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">Origin</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">7</rs> 
software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">MicroCal</rs>) supplied by the manufacturer. The heat capa-
city change was determined from the slope of a linear regression 
fit of H plotted against the temperature of the titration. </p>

<p>MALS </p>

<p>Molecular mass and molecular-mass distributions were deter-
mined using on-line SEC-MALS. Samples were applied in 
a volume of 100 μl to a Superdex 200 10/300 GL column 
equilibrated in 20 mM Tris/HCl, 150 mM NaCl and 0.25 mM 
TCEP, pH 8.0, at a flow rate of 0.5 ml/min. The column was 
mounted on a Jasco HPLC controlled by the <rs type="software">Chrompass</rs> software 
package. The scattered light intensity of the column eluate 
was recorded at 16 angles using a DAWN-HELEOS laser 
photometer (Wyatt Technology, Santa Barbara, CA, U.S.A.). 
The protein concentration of the eluent was determined from the 
RI(n) change (dn/dc = 0.186) (where c is solute concentration) 
using an OPTILAB-rEX differential refractometer equipped 
with a Peltier temperature-regulated flow cell, maintained at 
25 
• C (Wyatt Technology). The wavelength of the laser in the 
DAWNHELEOS and the light source in the OPTILABrEX 
was 658 nm. The weight-averaged molecular mass of material </p>

<p>contained in chromatographic peaks was determined using 
the ASTRA software version 5.1 (Wyatt Technology Corp., 
Santa Barbara, CA). Briefly, at 1 s intervals throughout the 
elution of peaks, the scattered-light intensities, together with 
the corresponding protein concentrations, were used to construct 
Debye plots [KC/R θ against sin 
2 (θ /2)]. The weight-averaged 
molecular mass was then calculated at each point in the 
chromatogram from the intercept of an individual plot. An overall 
average molecular mass and polydispersity term for each species 
was calculated by combining and averaging the results from the 
individual measurements. </p>

<p>Sedimentation-velocity AUC (analytical ultracentrifugation) </p>

<p>Sedimentation-velocity experiments were performed in a 
Beckman Optima Xli analytical ultracentrifuge, using conven-
tional charcoal-filled Epon double-sector quartz cells or 
aluminium double-sector sapphire cells in an An-50 Ti rotor. The 
rotor speed was 40 000 rev./min or 50 000 rev./min respectively, 
and the temperature was maintained at 293 K. Prior to centri-
fugation, protein samples were dialysed exhaustively against 
the buffer blank (10 mM Tris/HCl, pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl and 
0.25 mM TCEP). The protein concentration was varied from 
0.37 mg/ml to 1.76 mg/ml. Interference images were collected 
every 180 s during the sedimentation run. The data recorded from 
moving boundaries were analysed by the program SEDFIT in 
terms of both discrete species and continuous distribution function 
of sedimentation coefficient [c(s)]. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>NEMO 355 exists in a dimer/tetramer equilibrium </p>

<p>In order to resolve the discrepancies concerning the exact 
multimeric state of NEMO, the solution molecular mass of 
a construct containing all of the predicted coiled-coil regions 
was examined by SEC coupled to MALS (SEC-MALS). This 
construct is missing only the C-terminal ZF, which has been 
shown to be monomeric [28] and will be referred to from now 
on as NEMO 355 (Figure 1). SEC-MALS allows the determination 
of an absolute molecular mass during analytical gel filtration, 
independent of the shape of the molecule under investigation, 
and hence is well suited to determine the oligomeric state 
of proteins. An initial MALS experiment reports a weight-
averaged molecular mass (M W ) of 85.7 kDa for an average 
peak concentration of 1.4 μM, a value in close agreement with 
the formula molecular mass of dimeric NEMO 355 (83.8 kDa). 
However, at increased concentrations, elevated M W values are 
apparent, a phenomenon that was unaffected when the NaCl 
concentration was increased to 500 mM (results not shown). We 
therefore analysed the concentration-dependent M W of NEMO 355 
further with a sequence of SEC-MALS analyses ranging from 1.4 
to 16.9 μM (average peak concentration), as shown in Figure 2. 
These experiments reported corresponding M W values of 85.7-
113.8 kDa and clearly demonstrate that NEMO 355 is subject to 
concentration-dependent self-association based upon a minimum 
assembling unit equivalent to a dimer. The assembly of dimers 
into tetramers is the simplest model explaining these data. 
In order to characterize further the size of the multimers 
involved in self-association, we investigated NEMO 355 using 
sedimentation velocity AUC at three concentrations: 8.8 μM, 
17.6 μM, and 42 μM (monomer concentration). C(S) distribution 
analyses of the data clearly showed the presence of two 
major species centred at s 20,w values of approx. 3 and 4 S 
(Figure 2). Consistent with the MALS data above, the relative peak 
proportions varied in a concentration-dependent manner. At low </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2009 Biochemical Society </p>



<p>F. J. Ivins and others </p>

<p>Figure 2 NEMO 355 is dimeric and exists in a concentration-dependent equilibrium with a higher order species </p>

<p>(A) SEC-MALS measurements of NEMO 355 (dimeric formula M r 83.8 kDa) loaded at concentrations ranging from 0.5 to 8.0 mg/ml. Refractive index-derived weight concentrations (mg/ml) of the 
peaks are shown to the right. For clarity, derived M w (kDa) of the peaks are shown separately to the left along with a legend detailing the peak M w for each experiment. (B) NEMO 355 exists in a 
dimer/tetramer equilibrium. Sedimentation velocity experiments of NEMO 355 at three concentrations (8.8, 17.6 and 42 μM) shown as best-fit c(s) functions. </p>

<p>concentration, the predominant peak was centered on the lower 
s 20,w value, whereas the reverse was true at higher concentration. 
At intermediate concentration (17.6 μM), the peaks were nearly 
indistinguishable. As the peaks were fully separated in the c(s) 
function for the low-concentration experiment, we were able to 
analyse these data as discrete species. The data fitted well to a 
two-component discrete species model with s 20,w values of 3.00 
and 4.23 and D t,20,w (translational diffusion coefficient) values 
of 3.48 and 2.30 respectively (Figure 2 and Table 1). The 
respective M W values calculated from these values are 77.6 
and 164.9 kDa. These values are in good agreement with the 
molecular mass expected from NEMO 355 dimers (83.8 kDa) 
and tetramers (167.6 kDa). Using the relative peak proportions 
from the c(s) function for the low concentration experiment </p>

<p>(8.8 μM), an apparent dissociation constant (K d ) of 25.6 μM 
(dimer-tetramer equilibrium) was obtained. Notably, a fit of the 
SEC-MALS concentration-dependent data to a two-state self-
association model resulted in an apparent K d of 27.5 μM (results 
not shown). 
In order to help identify the region responsible for NEMO 
tetramerization, isolated NEMO CoZi domain was also subjected 
to sedimentation-velocity analysis at 46, 93 and 139 μM 
monomer concentration (results not shown). The data from this 
experiment fitted well to a discrete species model showing 
a single significant component and M w with a range of 
25.0-27.8 kDa, consistent with the formula molecular mass 
of dimeric CoZi domain (25.9 kDa) (see Table 3). These results do 
not indicate the presence of the tetramers evident in the NEMO 355 </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2009 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>Nemo oligomerization and interaction with ubiquitin </p>



<p>Table 1 Hydrodynamic parameters of the 8.8 μM NEMO 355 sedimentation 
velocity experiment (discrete species model) </p>

<p>M r , formula molecular mass; V bar , partial specific volume; M w , reported by experiment; s 20,w , 
sedimentation coefficient; D t,20,w , translational diffusion coefficient; f /f 0 , frictional coefficient 
ratio; K d , dissociation constant, calculated from known loading concentration and relative peak 
proportions for a dimer-tetramer equilibrium; RMSD, average root mean square deviation of the 
fit. Parameters with only one value are independent of the particular species involved. </p>

<p>Parameters 
Dimer 
Tetramer </p>

<p>M r (kDa) 
83.8 
167.6 
V bar 
0.728 
0.728 
M w (kDa) 
77.6 
164.9 
s 20,w 
3.00 
4.23 
D t,20,w 
3.5 
2.3 
f /f 0 
2.3 
2.6 
Relative proportions 
0.87 
0.13 
K d (μM) 
25.6 
25.6 
RMSD 
0.057 
0.057 </p>

<p>construct, suggesting that the N-terminal region of NEMO is 
responsible for higher-order self-association. </p>

<p>NEMO adopts a highly elongated conformation </p>

<p>Importantly, the discrete species analysis of the AUC data also 
allowed us to calculate the frictional ratio (f /f 0 ) for CoZi and the 
NEMO 355 dimer and tetramer. The frictional ratio is a measure 
of the degree of asymmetry in a molecule with respect to an 
anhydrous sphere of the same mass. For CoZi, an f /f 0 of 1.7 
was measured, which deviates considerably from the value (1.0) 
characteristic of a spherical protein molecule and points towards 
a highly elongated structure. Remarkably, the frictional ratios for 
NEMO 355 dimers and tetramers were significantly higher, 2.3 and 
2.6 respectively, demonstrating that both are unusually elongated 
and asymmetric molecules in solution (Table 1). </p>

<p>IKK binding abolishes NEMO 355 tetramerization </p>

<p>The most highly recognized function of NEMO within the NF-
κB signalling pathway is in the recruitment and regulation of 
IKKs responsible for the phosphorylation and inactivation of IκB. 
In order to further investigate the nature of the NEMO/IKK 
interaction, we analysed a complex of NEMO 355 and a 41-mer 
peptide comprising the IKKβ NEMO-binding domain (IKK NBD ; 
4.7 kDa) by SEC-MALS analysis. The resulting M w of the 
complex (92 kDa) was in close agreement with the formula 
molecular mass expected of dimeric NEMO 355 bound to two 
IKK NBD peptides (93.3 kDa) (Figure 3). This result agrees with a 
recently published heterotetrameric crystal structure comprising 
a short, dimeric NEMO N-terminal fragment bound to two 
IKK peptides [29]. Interestingly, the M w reported by SEC-
MALS remained constant over a wide NEMO 355 concentration 
range, demonstrating that the interaction is tight in accordance 
with previous studies [20,29]. Moreover, it shows that binding 
of IKK NBD completely abrogates the concentration-dependent 
tetramerization of NEMO 355 . These results indicate that the IKK 
binding and tetramerisation regions are overlapping. Importantly, 
these data demonstrate that the oligomeric state of NEMO is 
modulated by binding of specific ligands. </p>

<p>The CoZi/di-ubiquitin interaction </p>

<p>Most ubiquitin-binding domains characterized so far interact 
with mono-ubiquitin, often with relatively low affinities [30,31]. </p>

<p>Figure 3 IKKβ C-terminal peptide tightly binds NEMO 355 and abrogates 
tetramerization </p>

<p>SEC-MALS measurements of high concentration NEMO 355 (dimeric formula M r 83.8 kDa) bound 
to excess 41-mer C-terminal IKKβ peptide (4.7 kDa). RI-derived weight concentrations (mg/ml, 
left axis) of the peaks are shown for the entier run. In corresponding line types, derived apparent 
molecular mass (kDa, right axis) are shown for the centre of each peak. Shown for comparison is 
a measurement of a comparable concentration of NEMO 355 alone demonstrating an increase in 
M w caused by tetramerization. Apparent molecular mass for the binding experiments (∼ 92 kDa) 
agree with the formula molecular mass of dimeric NEMO 355 bound to two IKK peptides (93.3 kDa). </p>

<p>NEMO also binds very weakly to mono-ubiquitin [19] and 
surprisingly, only weakly to K63-linked di-ubiquitin, whereas the 
interaction with linear di-ubiquitin is around 100-fold stronger 
[17,18,26]. In order to understand better the thermodynamics 
of the interaction with linear ubiquitin chains, we used ITC to 
follow complex formation. No binding was detected between the 
CoZi domain and mono-ubiquitin at three different temperatures 
at concentrations of 50 μM CoZi in the cell and 500 μM ubiquitin 
in the syringe, indicating that any interaction must be very 
weak (results not shown). Titration of CoZi with increasing 
concentrations of di-ubiquitin at 18 
• C resulted in heats of 
interaction that were too small for quantitative analysis. However, 
titrations at 25 
• C and 10 
• C produced sufficient signal to be able 
to fit the binding isotherm, resulting in dissociation constants 
of 1.4 and 2.6 μM respectively (see Table 2 and Figure 4A). 
Surprisingly, the stoichiometry of complex formation was ∼ 0.5 in 
terms of polypeptide chains, demonstrating that one CoZi dimer 
interacts with one molecule of di-ubiquitin. Given the pseudo-
symmetrical structure of dimeric CoZi [17,18], one might expect 
that equivalent binding sites on each NEMO chain exist, and 
hence that two molecules of di-ubiquitin would bind, one either 
side (CoZi dimer /2 × di-ubiquitin). In contrast, these binding studies 
suggest that the di-ubiquitin molecule interacts with NEMO in an 
asymmetric fashion. To test if this binding mode is preserved 
in the context of full-length NEMO, we titrated NEMO 355 
with di-ubiquitin. As observed with the isolated CoZi domain, 
the enthalpy of complex formation was strongly temperature-
dependent and endothermic at lower temperatures, but exothermic 
at room temperature (25 
• C) and above. Notably, the binding 
stoichiometry and strength of complex formation are similar 
to that found for the CoZi domain with K d values of 0.95 μM 
and 3.45 μM at 25 
• C and 10 
• C respectively (Table 2 and 
Figure 4B). However, there is some difference in the heat capacity 
change of complex formation, which is − 587 cal · mol 
− 1 · K </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>(1 cal ≈ 4.184 J) for CoZi and − 360 cal · mol 
− 1 · K 
− 1 for the 
NEMO 355 di-ubiquitin interaction (Figure 4C). </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2009 Biochemical Society </p>



<p>F. J. Ivins and others </p>

<p>Figure 4 NEMO complexes with di-ubiquitin </p>

<p>ITC titrations of (A) 49.5 μM NEMO 355 titrated with 453 μM di-ubiquitin and (B) 112 μM CoZi titrated with 693 μM di-ubiquitin, both at 10 • C. (C) Enthalpies of complex formation are plotted as 
a function of temperature. The change in heat capacity is the slope of a linear regression fit. </p>

<p>Table 2 Thermodynamic parameters for the NEMO-di-ubiquitin interaction </p>

<p>All titrations were carried out three or four times and the estimated error is the S.D. between 
measurements. </p>

<p>Component in cell 
T 
N 
K d (μM) 
H (kcal/mol) </p>

<p>Mouse CoZi 
10 • C 
0 . 5 3+ − 0.06 
2.6 + 
− 0.4 
4.8 + 
− 0.6 
25 • C 
0 . 6 2+ − 0.07 
1.4 + 
− 1.0 
− 4.0 + 
− 0.6 
Mouse NEMO 355 
10 • C 
0 . 4 4+ − 0.05 
3.45 + 
− 0.4 
4.1 + 
− 0.7 
25 • C 
0 . 5 2+ − 0.04 
0.95 + 
− 0.2 
− 1.3 + 
− 0.5 </p>

<p>Analysis of NEMO-ubiquitin interaction by AUC </p>

<p>To investigate further the composition of the CoZi-di-ubiquitin 
complex and confirm the stoichiometry suggested by our ITC 
experiments, we characterized the CoZi-di-ubiquitin interaction 
by sedimentation-velocity AUC, which allows direct observation 
of the complex(es) under investigation. Multiple experiments 
were performed in which molar ratios of CoZi dimer and 
di-ubiquitin were varied (1:1, 1:2, 1:4 and 1:8; CoZi dimer /di-
ubiquitin). Molar concentrations and the resulting hydrodynamic 
data from these experiments are detailed in Table 3. In each 
of the three experiments where di-ubiquitin was present in 
stoichiometric excess, two discrete species were observed. The 
smallest component in each experiment clearly represents free di-
ubiquitin, as the s 20,w D t,20,w and M W values closely correspond 
to the values obtained from analysis of di-ubiquitin alone 
(Table 3). In the 1:1 experiment, the largest and most abundant 
component has a mass of 45.3 kDa, close to the predicted 
molecular mass of a complex consisting of dimeric CoZi bound 
to one di-ubiquitin chain (CoZi dimer -di-ubiquitin = 43.5 kDa). 
As expected, increasing the excess of di-ubiquitin resulted 
in increasing proportions of free di-ubiquitin. Unexpectedly, </p>

<p>Figure 5 CoZi and di-ubiquitin interact to form CoZi dimer /di-ubiquitin and at 
higher ubiquitin ratios CoZi dimer /(di-ubiquitin) 2 </p>

<p>Best fit C(S) functions for sedimentation velocity analysis of CoZi/di-ubiquitin (Ub2) 
interaction(s). </p>

<p>however, the apparent molecular mass of the complex component 
also increased with increasing excess of di-ubiquitin (Figure 5 
and Table 3). At the highest ratio (1:8 CoZi dimer /di-ubiquitin), 
the apparent mass increased to 53.3 kDa. This trend suggests 
formation of a complex containing a second di-ubiquitin bound 
to dimeric CoZi. We used the weight-averaged molecular mass 
(53.3 kDa) for the 1:8 experiment to determine the proportions 
of CoZi dimer /di-ubiquitin and CoZi dimer /(di-ubiquitin) 2 , from which 
we can estimate a 100-fold weaker binding constant for the second 
di-ubiquitin binding site. </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2009 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>Nemo oligomerization and interaction with ubiquitin </p>



<p>Table 3 Hydrodynamic parameters of the CoZi/di-ubiquitin interaction(s) </p>

<p>The first three columns denote the composition, reduced ratio, and molar ratios respectively at which the sedimentation-velocity experiments were carried out. All parameters are derived from discrete 
species modelling. Formula molecular mass: CoZi dimer , 25.9 kDa; di-ubiquitin, 17.5 kDa; CoZi dimer -di-ubiquitin, 43.5 kDa; CoZi dimer -(di-ubiquitin) 2 , 61.0 kDa. Partial specific volumes (V bar ): CoZi, 
0.737; di-ubiquitin, 0.746; and averaged V bar was used for CoZi-di-ubiquitin complexes. M w , reported by experiment; s 20,w , sedimentation coefficient; D t,20,w , translational diffusion coefficient; f /f 0 , 
frictional ratio; RMSD, average root mean square deviation of the fit. Data are organized into sections pertaining either to free (unbound) or complex species and the nature of the free species is noted 
as CoZi dimer , di-ubiquitin or Mixture (a weight-averaged mixture of unbound species). </p>

<p>Concn. 
Free 
Complex </p>

<p>Ratio 
(μM) 
Free species 
s 20,w 
D t,20,w 
f /f 0 
M w 
s 20,w 
D t,20,w 
f /f 0 
M w 
RMSD </p>

<p>COZI dimer 
-
23 
COZI dimer 
1.76 
6.5 
1.7 
25.0 
-
-
-
-
0.0042 
Di-ubiquitin 
-
103 
Di-ubiquitin 
1.69 
9.0 
1.4 
18.0 
-
-
-
-
0.0063 
COZI dimer /di-ubiquitin 
1:1 
25:25 
Mixture 
2.08 
9.3 
1.6 
20.9 
2.55 
5.3 
1.7 
45.3 
0.0077 
COZI dimer /di-ubiquitin 
1:2 
45:90 
Di-ubiquitin 
1.76 
9.1 
1.3 
17.9 
2.67 
5.7 
1.6 
43.7 
0.0180 
COZI dimer /di-ubiquitin 
1:4 
25:100 
Di-ubiquitin 
1.71 
9.0 
1.3 
17.9 
2.76 
5.7 
1.5 
45.9 
0.0180 
COZI dimer /di-ubiquitin 
1:8 
25:200 
Di-ubiquitin 
1.71 
9.7 
1.3 
16.6 
2.89 
5.1 
1.5 
53.3 
0.0160 </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>NEMO is the key regulatory component of the IKK complex 
that senses upstream stimulatory events and relays them to the 
activation of IKKα and IKKβ. A large proportion of the protein 
is predicted to form coiled coils, including the regions that 
are involved in ubiquitin recognition and interaction with the 
catalytic IKK subunits. The molecular mechanism by which 
NEMO induces activation of IKKα and IKKβ remains largely 
unknown, although various models have been suggested. One 
model assumes the CoZi domain undergoes stimulus-dependent 
conformational changes that in turn might induce activation of 
the kinases [19]. Alternatively, NEMO might act as a carrier 
or platform that is responsible for bringing IKKα and IKKβ in 
close proximity to activators such as TAK1 [TGFβ (transforming 
growth factor β)-activated kinase-1] to promote phosphorylation 
and activation ([23], but see [23a], [24]). On the other hand, the 
interaction with ubiquitin chains may induce clustering of NEMO, 
which could lead to IKK activation, possibly by inducing trans-
phosphorylation. 
In the present study we have characterized the oligomeric state 
of NEMO and its interaction with di-ubiquitin in order to provide 
a molecular basis for a better understanding of its role in NF-κB 
activation. </p>

<p>The oligomeric state of NEMO </p>

<p>The oligomeric state of NEMO has been controversial, and 
a number of different models have been suggested for the 
quaternary structure of the full-length protein as well as various 
fragments. Using a combination of MALS and AUC, we show 
that NEMO forms a very tight dimer that exists in a relatively 
weak equilibrium (∼ 27 μM) with tetramers. Importantly, our ex-
tensive analysis shows that the protein preparations used in our 
study are homogeneous and monodisperse, and that no aggregates 
are present that may interfere with the measurements. Our results 
partially agree with a previous study that described human NEMO 
to predominantly form tetramers [15], but contradict a number of 
others that described NEMO as monomers and trimers [13,14,16]. 
The most likely explanation for this discrepancy is the presence 
of detergent in the work by Agou and co-workers, which was, 
apparently, required to prevent the formation of aggregates, 
suggesting that the protein used in those studies may not have 
been in its native conformation [13,14,16]. This interpretation 
is supported by the presence of chaperone protein DnaK in the 
protein preparations used for some of the studies. Furthermore, we 
believe that the various and highly contradicting oligomeric states </p>

<p>determined for different N-terminal constructs of NEMO [20,21]  are due to an inherent instability and heterogeneity of shorter 
NEMO fragments, which may have compromised previous work. 
This interpretation is supported by Rushe et al. [29] who reported 
a similar lack of homogeneity for shorter N-terminal fragments 
of NEMO. 
In contrast with NEMO 355 , the CoZi domain has no tendency to 
tetramerize over a range of concentrations. Furthermore, complex 
formation with an IKKβ-derived peptide completely abolished 
the ability of dimeric NEMO 355 to form higher-order oligomers, 
showing that the region surrounding the IKK-binding site is 
responsible for tetramerization. These results from the present 
study are in contrast with those of previous cross-linking studies, 
which suggested that NEMO binds the IKKs in its tetrameric 
form and that tetramerization is required for kinase activity [15]. 
It now seems likely that cross-linking studies have overestimated 
the oligomeric state of NEMO due to non-specific association. 
Nevertheless, the model that oligomerization of NEMO might be 
part of the IKK activation mechanism is intriguing and is fully 
compatible with the notion that binding to polyubiquitin chains 
induces clustering of NEMO as described below. Importantly, the 
observation that interaction with IKK abolishes tetramerization 
clearly illustrates that the oligomeric state of NEMO in its ligand 
complexes might differ from that of the apoprotein. 
Similarly to full-length NEMO, the state of the minimal 
oligomerization domain, CoZi, has been controversial. Two recent 
crystal structures of the apo form of this domain show it to form a 
parallel coiled-coil domain that is approx. 120 Å (1 Å = 0.1 nm) 
in length [17,18]. This is in accordance with the results reported 
here, yet contradicts a number of other studies that reported tri-
meric and hexameric assemblies [13,16]. A CoZi construct 
comprising amino acids 250-339 has been reported to exist in 
a monomer-dimer equilibrium with a K d of 30 μM [19]. The 
fragment used in the present study is slightly extended at 
the C-terminus and includes amino acids 340-355, which are 
not predicted to be part of the LZ. Interestingly, the inclusion 
of this region significantly strengthens dimerization, suggesting 
that this C-terminal extension, which is absent in the crystallised 
fragments, is part of the coiled-coil domain. 
AUC studies of NEMO 355 show that it adopts an extremely 
elongated conformation, as illustrated by the frictional ratios 
for NEMO 355 dimers and tetramers (2.3 and 2.6 respectively). 
These values are significantly higher than would be expected 
for a globular protein and are in fact similar to the value 
measured for fibrinogen (2.3), a rod-like protein that has been 
shown by electron microscopy to have an average axial ratio 
(length divided by diameter) of 7.5 [32-34]. The recently reported </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2009 Biochemical Society </p>



<p>F. J. Ivins and others </p>

<p>structures of NEMO 44−111 bound to IKK-derived peptides [29] and 
NEMO 150−272 bound to vFLIP [35] show the respective ligand-
bound fragments of NEMO form an elongated dimeric coiled-
coil. In combination with our AUC studies, these observations 
indicate that binding of target proteins will not induce gross 
conformational changes, but can alter oligomerization. Instead, 
apo-NEMO forms a highly elongated coiled-coil that is poised to 
accommodate the binding of different proteins, apparently without 
major structural rearrangements. Nevertheless, it is tempting to 
speculate that binding to ligands may induce slight local changes 
that are propagated along the coiled-coil, ultimately inducing 
activation of IKKα and IKKβ. </p>

<p>The NEMO-polyubiquitin interaction </p>

<p>The interaction of NEMO with polyubiquitin chains is important 
for the activation of the IKK complex in response to TNFα 
stimulation ([23], but see [23a], [24]). Binding occurs via the 
UBAN motif within the CoZi domain. The interaction of mono-
ubiquitin with CoZi is extremely weak, and we could not 
detect any binding under the conditions of our ITC experiments, 
although high sensitivity LUMIER (LUminescence-based 
Mammalian IntERactome) assays showed weak binding can occur 
[19]. In contrast, linear di-ubiquitin binds with an affinity in the 
low-micromolar range, clearly indicating that the interaction with 
each individual ubiquitin is additive. Unexpectedly, binding of 
NEMO to K63-linked di-ubiquitin is significantly weaker than 
to linear chains [17,18,26], suggesting that linear polyubiquitin 
chains may be the true physiological targets [18]. 
The stoichiometry of the CoZi-di-ubiquitin interaction deter-
mined in our ITC experiments indicated that one NEMO dimer 
interacts with one molecule of di-ubiquitin. This stoichiometry 
is in accordance with an independent study by Lo et al. [17]  that also detected a 2:1 complex in solution. On the basis 
of NMR chemical shift perturbations and mutagenesis studies, 
these authors suggested a model for the complex in which di-
ubiquitin clasps around dimeric NEMO roughly perpendicular 
to the long axis of the NEMO coiled-coil domain. However, 
this stoichiometry and the derived model strongly contradict 
the recently published CoZi/di-ubiquitin structure, which instead 
shows two molecules of di-ubiquitin to bind to a NEMO dimer 
in an orientation that is parallel with the coiled-coil axis [18]. 
Moreover, the authors of this study present NF-κB activation 
assays with NEMO mutants defective in ubiquitin binding, which 
support the notion that binding of two di-ubiquitin molecules 
to NEMO is physiologically important. A simple explanation 
for the apparent discrepancy between these studies could be the 
partial dissociation of CoZi in the solution studies. However, this 
explanation seems highly unlikely, as our AUC sedimentation 
analysis of CoZi at concentrations used in the ITC experiments 
shows that CoZi exists entirely in its dimeric form. 
Interestingly, in solution NEMO 355 shows similar binding 
properties towards di-ubiquitin in terms of stoichiometry and 
apparent affinity as the CoZi domain, whereas the thermodynamic 
characteristics of complex formation show small but distinctive 
differences. This observation implies that binding of ubiquitin 
does not induce any large conformational changes in the region 
N-terminal to the CoZi domain, since this would probably be 
reflected in the affinity of the interaction. Nevertheless, it indicates 
that some communication exists between the CoZi domain and 
the N-terminal part of NEMO. 
To gain further insight into the CoZi-di-ubiquitin interaction 
and understand the apparently conflicting binding stoichiometries, 
we analysed complexes at different NEMO/di-ubiquitin ratios 
by AUC. Sedimentation velocity experiments, at equimolar </p>

<p>concentrations of CoZi dimers and di-ubiquitin, showed a 
complex of the molecular mass expected from the stoichiometry 
observed in our ITC studies. Intriguingly, however, increases in 
the relative ratio of di-ubiquitin over CoZi led to an increase 
in the apparent molecular mass of the complex, suggesting that 
at higher concentrations of di-ubiquitin a second binding site 
in NEMO becomes occupied. Affinity for this second site is 
significantly weaker, and thus it is possible that binding of 
the first molecule of di-ubiquitin may occlude binding of a 
second. However, high ubiquitin concentrations might induce 
slight structural rearrangements in NEMO, which in turn allow 
the second binding site to become accessible. Alternatively, apo-
NEMO might exist in an equilibrium between two states, of which 
only one may be capable of binding two di-ubiquitin chains. This 
state might be unfavourable and hence would only be occupied at 
high ubiquitin concentrations. However, crystallization conditions 
might have selected for this state over the other. 
It is tempting to speculate that, in vivo, a multi-protein complex 
containing ubiquitinated proteins such as RIP1 may provide the 
high ubiquitin density required for occupation of the second site. 
Population of the second site might be the trigger to initiate 
IKK activation, possibly through clustering of NEMO. In fact, 
this two-site binding event might constitute a 'threshold for 
activation' to prevent non-specific activation of NF-κB, which 
can have detrimental consequences for the host. Further studies 
are now required to better characterize the in vivo role of these 
two binding sites and understand the molecular events leading to 
their formation. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTION </p>

<p>Frank Ivins designed and performed experiments, analysed data and wrote the manuscript; 
Mark Montgomery designed and performed experiments and analysed data; Susan Smith 
and Aylin Morris-Davies performed experiments; Ian Taylor designed experiments and 
analysed data; and Katrin Rittinger designed the study, analysed data and wrote the 
manuscript. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Steve Smerdon [NIMR (National Institute for Medical Research)], Felix Randow 
[MRC-LMB (Medical Research Council-Laboratory of Molecular Biology)] and Ben 
Stieglitz (NIMR) for helpful discussions and critical reading of the manuscript before 
its submission. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Medical Research Council, U.K. </p>



<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2009 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>Nemo oligomerization and interaction with ubiquitin </p>





<p>Received 13 March 2009/1 May 2009; accepted 7 May 2009 
Published as BJ Immediate Publication 7 May 2009, doi:10.1042/BJ20090427 </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2009 Biochemical Society </p>

</text></tei>