<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2248739" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The sxy (tfoX) gene product is the central 
regulator of DNA uptake by naturally competent 
c-proteobacteria such as Haemophilus influenzae, 
Vibrio cholerae and probably Escherichia coli. 
However, the mechanisms regulating sxy gene 
expression are not understood despite being key 
to understanding the physiological role of DNA 
uptake. We have isolated mutations in H. influenzae 
sxy that greatly elevate translation and thus 
cause competence to develop in otherwise non-
inducing conditions (hypercompetence). In vitro 
nuclease analysis confirmed the existence of an 
extensive secondary structure at the 5' end of sxy 
mRNA that sequesters the ribosome-binding site 
and start codon in a stem-loop. All of the hyper-
competence mutations reduced mRNA base 
pairing, and one was shown to cause a global 
destabilization that increased translational effi-
ciency. Conversely, mutations engineered to add 
mRNA base pairs strengthened the secondary 
structure, resulting in reduced translational effi-
ciency and greatly reduced competence for genetic 
transformation. Transfer of wild-type cells to starva-
tion medium improved translational efficiency of 
sxy while independently triggering the sugar starva-
tion regulator (CRP) to stimulate transcription at the 
sxy promoter. Thus, mRNA secondary structure is 
responsive to conditions where DNA uptake will be 
favorable, and transcription of sxy is simultaneously 
enhanced if CRP activation signals that energy 
supplies are limited. </p>

<p>Natural competence, the ability to take up DNA 
molecules directly from the environment, is tightly </p>

<p>regulated in most bacteria, indicating that the costs and 
benefits of DNA uptake depend on changes in the 
extracellular and intracellular environments. Because 
the mechanisms regulating competence evolved to allow 
cells to track these changes, understanding the mecha-
nisms provides a window on the importance of DNA 
uptake to the cell. 
Bacteria 
in 
the 
families 
Pasteurellaceae, 
Enterobacteraceae and Vibrionaceae appear to share a 
common regulatory mechanism, with competence genes 
organized in a regulon whose transcription is controlled 
by two activator proteins, Sxy (also known as TfoX) and 
CRP (also known as CAP) (1). Although competence 
genes are ubiquitous in these families, only a few species 
are known to be naturally competent, and the only well-
studied competence regulon is that of Haemophilus 
influenzae (Pasteurellaceae). H. influenzae becomes mod-
erately competent as growth slows during late log phase in 
rich medium, and becomes maximally competent when log 
phase cells are transferred to the defined starvation 
medium MIV (2). 
The sxy gene was first identified and named as the site of 
the H. influenzae mutation sxy-1, which causes greatly 
increased 
competence 
(hypercompetence) 
during 
growth in rich medium (3). Cells lacking sxy cannot 
induce the 25 genes (13 transcription units) of the 
competence regulon; many of these genes are known to 
contribute directly to DNA uptake (2). Conversely, 
overexpression of sxy from multi-copy plasmids induces 
competence under what are normally non-inducing con-
ditions in H. influenzae, Actinobacillus actinomycetemco-
mitans and Vibrio cholerae (4-6). Unlike Sxy, CRP is a 
global regulator. It activates a broad array of genes united 
by their roles in obtaining or utilizing alternative carbon 
or energy sources, or in sparing the wasteful use of 
the preferred sources; its action has been very well studied 
in Escherichia coli. When activated by its allosteric 
effector cyclic AMP (cAMP), CRP binds specifically to 
22 bp sites in promoters where it stimulates transcription. 
Competence regulon promoters contain a novel type of </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +604 822 3744; Fax: +604 827 4135; Email: redfield@zoology.ubc.ca </p>

<p>ß 2007 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>CRP site (CRP-S sites, previously called competence 
regulatory elements), whose sequences differ at critical 
positions from the canonical CRP sites previously 
characterized in E. coli (CRP-N sites) (1). 
Understanding how competence is regulated depends 
on understanding how both CRP and Sxy are regulated. 
In H. influenzae and in E. coli, CRP is activated by a rise in 
cAMP that occurs when preferred sugars are unavailable 
for transport by the phosphotransferase system (7,8). 
We have previously shown that H. influenzae sxy mRNA 
levels rise when cells experience competence-inducing 
conditions (2), but nothing is known about the molecular 
events that control this expression. 
The original sxy-1 mutation causes only a very 
conservative change in the Sxy protein sequence 
(Val 19 Ile), and it was proposed to cause hypercompetence 
by increasing the amount of Sxy rather than by changing 
the nature of Sxy's action (4). Here we report the isolation 
and characterization of additional hypercompetence-
causing point mutations in sxy, none of which alter the 
protein sequence. We show that all the hypercompetence 
mutations act by increasing sxy expression, and that this 
effect arises by destabilization of an mRNA secondary 
structure that normally limits sxy translation in rich 
medium. In maximal competence-inducing conditions, </p>

<p>CRP induces sxy; together CRP and Sxy then induce the 
genes of the CRP-S regulon. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Strains, plasmids and DNA </p>

<p>Bacterial strains and plasmids used in this study are listed 
in Table 1. </p>

<p>Culture conditions and transformation assays </p>

<p>H. influenzae cells were cultured at 378C in brain heart 
infusion (BHI) supplemented with NAD (2 mg/ml) and 
hemin (10 mg/ml) (sBHI), and with novobiocin (2.5 mg/ml), 
kanamycin (7 mg/ml) or chloramphenicol (2 mg/ml) added 
when required. Competence was induced by transferring 
log-phase cells to the defined starvation medium MIV as 
previously described (9). E. coli cells were grown in Luria 
Bertani (LB) medium, with kanamycin (25 mg/ml) and 
ampicillin (100 mg/ml) when required. 
Competent H. influenzae cells were transformed with 
chromosomal or plasmid DNA as previously described 
(10). Cells (1 ml) were incubated with 1 mg/ml of MAP7 
chromosomal DNA for 15 min, the DNA was degraded by 
incubation with DNase I for 5 min and cells were diluted </p>

<p>Table 1. Strains used in this work </p>

<p>Strain or plasmid 
Relevant genotype 
Source or reference </p>

<p>H. influenzae 
KW20 
Wild-type Rd; Sequenced strain 
(37) 
MAP7 
KW20 Nov </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>(38) 
RR648 
KW20 sxy::Kan </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>(4) 
RR668 
KW20 cyaA::miniTn10kan 
(39) 
RR699 
KW20 sxy-1 
(4) 
RR700 
KW20 sxy-2 
This study 
RR723 
KW20 sxy-3 
This study 
RR724 
KW20 sxy-4 
This study 
RR844 
KW20 sxy 89 ::lacZKan </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>(operon fusion) 
This study 
RR845 
KW20 sxy 89 ::lacZKan </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>(protein fusion) 
This study 
RR846 
KW20 sxy 11 ::lacZKan </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>(operon fusion) 
This study 
RR847 
KW20 sxy 11 ::lacZKan </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>(protein fusion) 
This study 
RR850 
KW20 sxy-5 
This study 
RR852 
KW20 sxy-6 
This study 
RR854 
KW20 sxy-7 
This study 
E. coli 
DH5a 
F80lacZ D(lacIZYA-argF) endA1 
JM109 
endA1, recA1 
Promega 
M15 
lacZ, pREP4 
Qiagen 
RR1128 
M15 pQEsxy 
This study 
Plasmids 
pDJM90 
UTR and 5 
0 -half of sxy ORF 
(4) 
pLZK80 
lacZKan 
r operon fusion cassette 
G. Barcak 
pLZK81 
lacZKan 
r protein fusion cassette 
G. Barcak 
pLBSF1 
sxy 89 ::lacZKan 
r (operon fusion) 
This study 
pLBSF2 
sxy 89 ::lacZKan 
r (protein fusion) 
This study 
pLBSF3 
sxy 11 ::lacZKan 
r (operon fusion) 
This study 
pLBSF4 
sxy 11 ::lacZKan 
r (protein fusion) 
This study 
pGEM-7Zf-
T7 promoter 
Promega 
pGEMsxy 
sxy ORF and UTR cloned in pGEM-7Zf-
This study 
pGEMsxy-1 
sxy-1 ORF and UTR cloned in pGEM-7Zf-
This study 
pGEMsxy-7 
sxy-7 ORF and UTR cloned in pGEM-7Zf-
This study 
pREP4 
lacIq 
Qiagen 
pQEsxy 
sxy ORF cloned in pQE-30UA (Qiagen) 
This study </p>

<p>Nov </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>, novobiocin resistance; Kan 
r , kanamycin resistance; Cam </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>, chloramphenicol resistance. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 1 11 </p>

<p>and plated on sBHI agar with and without novobiocin. 
Transformation frequencies were calculated as the number 
of novobiocin-resistant (Nov </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>) transformants per cell. 
The sxy-2, -3, -4 and -5 mutants were isolated by selection 
of exponentially growing EMS-mutagenized cells for 
transformation to Nov 
R , as described for sxy-1 (3). 
E. coli cells were made chemically competent with 
RbCl and transformed with plasmids as previously 
described (11). </p>

<p>Site-directed mutagenesis </p>

<p>The 1.8 kb EcoRI-BamHI fragment of pDJM90 (sxy) was 
cloned into the EcoRI-BamHI site of pAlter-1 (Promega) 
to create the plasmid pAltersxy. Site-directed mutagenesis 
was carried out using the Altered Sites II kit (Promega), 
following the manufacturer's protocol. Sequencing was 
used to confirm mutations, and the sequenced regions 
between ScaI-ClaI sites were subcloned into pDJM90 to 
ensure that the plasmid inserts contained no additional 
mutations. </p>

<p>Generation of polyclonal anti-Sxy antibodies </p>

<p>The sxy coding sequence was cloned under lac promoter 
control in the His-tag vector pQE30-UA (Qiagen) in 
E. coli M15, and sxy expression was induced at A 600 0.6 
with 1 mM IPTG. Cells were harvested after 4.5 h by 
centrifugation and the pellet was frozen overnight at 
À208C. Because Sxy invariably formed inclusion bodies in 
expression cultures, even when induced with low concen-
trations of IPTG and at 308C, it was denatured and 
purified as follows. The frozen cell pellet was resuspended 
in lysis buffer (100 mM NaPO 4 , 10 mM Tris-HCl, 6 M 
guanidine HCl, pH 8.0), then cells were incubated 1 h at 
308C with shaking followed by brief, gentle vortexing until 
the solution was translucent. Cellular debris was removed 
by centrifugation at 10 000g for 25 min and the super-
natant was incubated with nickel-nitriloacetic acid agarose 
beads for 1 h at 48C with gentle rocking. Agarose beads 
were packed in a column and washed twice with 12 
column volumes of wash buffer (100 mM NaPO 4 , 10 mM 
Tris-HCl, 8 M urea, pH 6.3), and protein was eluted 
using 2 vol of wash buffer pH 4.5. Eluted fractions were 
pooled and concentrated by precipitation with 10% TCA. 
Residual TCA was removed with cold 100% ethanol, and 
protein was dried and resuspended in SDS sample buffer 
(45 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 10% glycerol, 1% SDS, 50 mM 
DTT, 0.01% bromophenol blue). Proteins were then 
separated by electrophoresis on a 15% polyacrylamide 
SDS gel, and the section of gel containing Sxy 
(MW 25 kDa) was excised and macerated by repeated 
passage through a small-bore syringe. Protein was eluted 
overnight in water, and then concentrated by TCA 
precipitation. Dried protein was resuspended in phos-
phate-buffered saline (137 mM NaCl, 10 mM phosphate, 
2.7 mM KCl, pH 7.4) and purity was assessed with 
SDS-PAGE and quantified using the Bradford assay. 
Protein was emulsified in incomplete Freund's adjuvant 
(250 mg/ml) for injection in rabbits. Blood serum was 
collected 10 days after booster shots and stored at À208C 
until use. </p>

<p>Western blot and spot blot analysis </p>

<p>For western blots, cells were pelleted and resuspended in 
SDS sample buffer and proteins were separated on 15% 
polyacrylamide SDS gels. All gels were run in duplicate 
to provide one gel for western blot analysis and a second 
for Coomassie staining to confirm that a consistent 
amount of protein was loaded in each well. Gels were 
equilibrated in transfer buffer (48 mM Tris-HCl, 39 mM 
glycine) and proteins were transferred to PVDF mem-
brane at 10 V for 30 min using a Trans-blot semi-dry 
(Bio-Rad) apparatus. Samples from in vitro translation 
reactions were spotted in duplicate on pre-wetted PVDF 
membrane; after drying, spotted membranes were 
re-wetted with methanol then washed with water and 
TBS-T (20 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 137 mM NaCl, 0.05% 
Tween-20). 
All membranes were blocked overnight at 48C in 5% 
non-fat powdered milk in TBS-T, followed by incubation 
at room temperature for 1 h with rocking in rabbit anti-
Sxy serum diluted 1/10 000 in TBS-T (1% blocking agent). 
Blots were washed thoroughly and probed with alkaline 
phosphatase-linked anti-rabbit antibody diluted 1/10 000 
in TBS-T (1% blocking agent) for 1 h at room temperature 
with rocking, followed by thorough washing. Blots were 
incubated in ECF reagent (Amersham) for 1 min. Bands 
were visualized using a Typhoon 9400 scanner (GE 
Healthcare) and quantified using Image Quant (GE 
Healthcare). Several other H. influenzae proteins in 
addition to Sxy were recognized by the polyclonal 
antiserum in western blots. These unidentified H. influen-
zae proteins were also bound by pre-immune serum, 
indicating that antigenicity is not an artifact of non-
specific binding by anti-Sxy antibodies. The unidentified 
proteins demonstrated highly consistent abundance in all 
culture conditions and growth phases and so were used as 
internal standards for the quantification of Sxy. Sxy 
protein levels were calculated after subtracting back-
ground signal generated by sxy 
-cells (western blots) or by 
in vitro transcription/translation reactions lacking tem-
plate DNA (spot blots). </p>

<p>Template preparation for RNase analysis </p>

<p>Gene sequences used as templates for in vitro preparation 
of mRNAs were cloned adjacent to the T7 promoter of 
pGEM-7Zf-(Sigma). The 51 nt long sxy untranslated 
region (UTR) together with the full sxy coding region 
(654 nt) was PCR amplified from genomic DNA isolated 
from H. influenzae KW20 and RR699 (sxy-1) using 
primers PR13 5 
0 -AAAGGGCCCCAGAAGTACTTCTA 
CTGACTC and PR12 5 
0 -CAAGTAAGTTTATTAAAA 
AAGCTTAAGCAT. Amplicons were digested and 
cloned into ApaI and EcoRI restriction sites, generating 
plasmids pGEMsxy and pGEMsxy-1 in host strain 
JM109. Because the primer PR13 overlaps one of the 
sxy-7 mutations (Figure 3A), pGEMsxy-7 was con-
structed by site-directed mutagenesis of pGEMsxy 
using a QuikChange site-directed mutagenesis kit 
(Stratagene). </p>



<p>RNA preparation </p>

<p>Wild-type sxy, sxy-1 and sxy-7 RNAs were prepared by 
transcription in vitro (MEGAscript T7 kit, Ambion) from 
plasmids linearized at position 323, resulting in 340 nt long 
run-off transcripts. RNAs were purified from the tran-
scription mix, first by a DNase treatment using a DNA-
Free Kit (Ambion) and next by a spin column (RNA Easy 
kit, Qiagen) following the manufacturers' instructions. At 
this point the concentration of each RNA sample was 
measured by spectrophotometry, and quality and purity 
were assessed by agarose gel electrophoresis and A 260/280 
ratios. Next, RNAs ($20 pmol) were dephosphorylated in 
100 ml reactions at 378C for 2 h in reaction buffer using 
0.5 U of calf intestinal alkaline phosphatase (Roche). 
RNAs were recovered by phenol-chloroform purification 
and ethanol precipitation. Dephosphorylated RNAs 
($10 pmol) were labeled in 50 ml reactions in reaction 
buffer using 20 U of T4 polynucleotide kinase (BioLabs, 
New England) and at least 20 pmol of g-P 
32 ATP (6000 Ci/ 
mmol; GE Amersham) at 378C for 1 h. Finally, RNAs 
were purified by a spin column (RNA Easy kit, Qiagen) 
and eluted in nuclease-free water. </p>

<p>RNA secondary structure mapping </p>

<p>End-labeled RNAs were denatured for 5 min at 958C, 
allowed to refold for 15 min at 378C, and partially digested 
with RNase A (0.005 U/ml) or RNase TI (0.05 U/ml) 
(both from Ambion), and the resulting fragments were 
resolved on sequencing gels. Both partially digested RNAs 
and control RNAs (ladders) were prepared following the 
manufacturer's directions. Alkaline-digested end-labeled 
RNA was used as a ladder to assign gel bands to specific 
residues in the RNA sequence. 
After electrophoresis for 3 h at 900 V and 12 mA, gels 
were dried, exposed to a PhosphorScreen overnight and 
visualized using a PhosphorImager (Molecular 
Dynamics). <rs type="software">ImageQuant</rs> software was used to measure 
cleavage intensities at each residue position. Positions 78 
and 80 were used as standards to normalize cleavage 
intensities at all other positions because they were con-
sistently strongly cleaved in independent reactions. To 
calculate fold differences in cleavage intensities between 
mutant and wild-type RNA, sxy-1 or sxy-7 values were 
divided by wild-type values at each position. At positions 
where mutant RNAs were more weakly cut than wild-
type, wild-type values were instead divided by mutant and 
then expressed as a negative value. </p>

<p>In silico RNA secondary structure predictions </p>

<p>Mfold (12) was used to predict secondary structure of 
the full-length in vitro sxy transcript [comprising pGEM-
7Zf-(15 nt), UTR (51 nt) and partial coding region 
(274 nt) sequences]; default parameters were used. </p>

<p>Construction of b-galactosidase fusions and enzyme assays </p>

<p>To fuse lacZ at sxy position 317 (codon 89), lacZkan 
cassettes ($4.5 kb) were excised from pLZK80 and 
pLZK81 with BamHI and ligated to BclI digested 
pDJM90, 
generating 
pLBSF1 
and 
pLBSF2 </p>

<p>(Supplementary Figure 1A). To eliminate Stems 1 and 3, 
PCR was used to create an EcoRI site at position 83 
(codon 11) using primers PR6 5 
0 -GAATTCTGTGATTA 
TATCTGTATTGATG and PR15 5 
0 -AGGGAATTCCG 
CTATCTATATGCTCATCC. The amplicon was then 
digested with EcoRI and BclI, ligated to lacZkan cassettes 
and cloned into ScaI + BclI-digested pLBSF1 to generate 
pLBSF3 and pLBSF4 (Supplementary Figure 1B). All 
gene fusions were transferred to the KW20 chromosome 
by excision from plasmids with ApaI + BamHI followed 
by transformation into competent cells, with selection for 
kanamycin resistance [method described in (9)]. 
H. influenzae strains containing lacZ fusions were 
grown in sBHI and sampled in duplicate at regular time 
intervals. For cells in the mid-to late-log phase of growth 
(A 600 ! 0.5), 0.1 ml of cells was usually sampled; for cells 
in the early-log phase of growth, 0.5 ml samples were 
taken. After sampling, cells were immediately pelleted by 
centrifugation, supernatants were removed and cell pellets 
were frozen at À808C for later assays of b-galactosidase 
activity (13). Simultaneously, the main cell culture was 
assayed for A 600 and, in some cases, for cfu/ml. </p>

<p>In vitro transcription and translation </p>

<p>The E. coli S30 extract system for linear templates 
(Promega) was used for in vitro coupled transcription/ 
translation according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
Plasmid templates (pGEMsxy, pGEMsxy-1, pGEMsxy-7) 
were isolated using a GenElute plasmid miniprep kit 
(Sigma) and residual RNases were removed using a 
GenElute PCR clean-up kit (Sigma). T7 RNA polymerase 
(1.4 U/ml final concentration) was added to reactions and 
transcription was initiated by addition of template DNA 
(4.5 nM final concentration). Some reactions also con-
tained the DNA oligonucleotide 5 
0 -AGTCAGTAGAAG 
TACTTC at 75 mM final concentration. Reactions were 
incubated at 258C and stopped by mixing with 4 vol of ice-
cold acetone. </p>

<p>Quantitative PCR measurement of sxy transcript </p>

<p>Total RNA was isolated from cultures using RNeasy Mini 
Kits (Qiagen), and purity and quality were assessed by 
electrophoresis on 1% agarose (1 Â TAE). RNA was 
DNase treated twice with a DNA Free kit (Ambion), 
followed by cDNA synthesis using the iScript cDNA 
synthesis kit (Bio-Rad). For each PCR primer set, 
reactions were carried out in duplicate on a 7000 
Sequence Detection System (Applied Biosystems) using 
iTaq SYBR Green Supermix with ROX (Bio-Rad). PCR 
primers: sxyRTF 5 
0 -TGAACCTTTTACAACGAATGA 
AT; sxyRTR 5 
0 -ACACAATCTATTACTACGTAAAAT 
CTGATCAG; murGRTF 5 
0 -TGCTTGGGCTGATGTG 
GTTA; murGRTR 5 
0 -TCCCACTGCTGCAATTTCAC. 
murG RNA served as an internal control for each sample 
because this gene's expression is constant in the culture 
conditions used in this study (2). Standard curves were 
generated using five serial 10-fold dilutions of MAP7 
chromosomal DNA. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 1 13 </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Isolation and characterization of additional 
hypercompetence mutations in sxy </p>

<p>The original sxy-1 hypercompetent mutant was isolated 
from a pool of EMS-mutagenized H. influenzae cells 
created in a search for genes that regulate competence 
development (3). The present study began by using the 
same strategy to select additional hypercompetence 
mutations from the same population. Wild-type cells 
growing at low cell density in rich medium do not express 
competence genes or take up DNA, so an EMS-
mutagenized culture was incubated with DNA carrying 
a novobiocin-resistance allele and Nov 
R transformants 
were selected. Screening of the rare transformants 
identified four additional strains with mutations that 
mapped to sxy; the alleles were named sxy-2, sxy-3, sxy-4 
and sxy-5. As shown in Figure 1, all four mutants 
demonstrated the same 50-fold to 500-fold increased 
transformation frequencies as the sxy-1 mutant, during 
both log phase growth (A 600 0.2) and late-log phase 
growth (A 600 1.0). All mutants grew normally in rich 
medium (sBHI). In MIV starvation medium, mutants and 
wild-type cells survived equally well and transformed at 
equally high frequencies (right panel of Figure 1). 
Sequencing revealed that each strain carried a 
distinct single-point mutation in sxy; these are shown in 
Figure 2A. The sxy-2 mutation (G 102 A) is a silent 
substitution in the coding region, 4 bp upstream of the 
site of the sxy-1 mutation (G 106 A, V 19 I). The other three 
mutations are clustered outside the coding region, near the 
5 
0 end of the 51 nt UTR (sxy-3: C 14 T; sxy-4: T 15 C; sxy-5: 
G 16 T). 
Because these mutations did not alter the Sxy protein 
sequence, site-directed mutagenesis was used to confirm 
that no other mutations, either in sxy or elsewhere in the 
genome, were responsible for the hypercompetence 
phenotypes. As had been done for sxy-1 (4), each of the 
four mutations was re-created in a H. influenzae sxy 
plasmid cloned in E. coli, and introduced into wild-type </p>

<p>H. influenzae chromosomes by transformation; these 
mutants all had phenotypes identical to the originals and 
were used in the experiments described here. This 
confirmed that all of the four new hypercompetence 
mutations increased competence without changing the 
sequence of Sxy or any other protein. We thus hypothe-
sized that all five mutations acted by altering control of 
sxy expression rather than by changing Sxy function. 
As Sxy is an activator of competence genes, and as we 
observed elevated expression of all CRP-S regulon genes 
in microarray analysis of the sxy-1 mutant in rich 
medium (data not shown), we predicted that the muta-
tions would cause hypercompetence by increasing rather 
than decreasing sxy expression. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Analysis of Sxy levels in wild-type and mutant cells under 
different growth conditions. (A) Locations of key features and 
mutations in the sxy gene. Regulatory elements (À10, À35) are 
shown relative to the transcription start site (16). Sequences and circled 
numbers identify sxy hypercompetence mutations. (B) Quantitation of 
Sxy in wild-type and hypercompetent mutants in log (A 600 0.2) and 
late-log (A 600 1.0) growth. The average and standard deviation of four 
independent cultures are shown in the graph; protein levels are 
normalized to wild-type cells at A 600 0.2. The western blots below the 
graph show Sxy protein and an unidentified protein used for internal 
standardization (see Materials and Methods section). (C) 
Transformation frequencies as a function of Sxy protein levels for 
wild-type cells (triangles) and sxy hypercompetent mutants (circles), in 
sBHI at A 600 0.2 (filled symbols) and A 600 1.0 (open symbols). </p>

<p>Figure 1. Natural competence assayed by transformation to novobiocin 
resistance. Transformation frequencies of wild-type (black) and sxy-1-5 
mutants (gray) under non-inducing conditions (log phase: sBHI at A 600 
0.2), partially inducing conditions (late log: sBHI at A 600 1.0) and fully 
inducing conditions (90 min in MIV). </p>



<p>Hypercompetence mutations lead to elevated Sxy 
under non-inducing and semi-inducing conditions </p>

<p>To compare Sxy levels between wild-type and mutant 
cells, we generated polyclonal anti-Sxy antibodies and 
used western blot analysis to quantify protein levels. 
In exponential growth (A 600 0.2), all hypercompetence 
mutants (sxy-1-5) had elevated Sxy levels, with 7-to 
16-fold more protein than wild-type cells (Figure 2B; light 
gray bars). In late-log phase (A 600 1.0), the difference 
was even more striking, with mutants having 13-to 
25-fold more Sxy protein than wild-type cells (Figure 2B, 
dark gray bars). Figure 2C graphs transformation 
frequencies as a function of Sxy protein levels for wild-
type and mutant cells in the log and late-log phases 
of growth. The strong positive correlation between Sxy 
abundance and transformation frequencies confirms 
that Sxy levels limit competence development during 
growth in rich medium, and that changes in the amount 
of Sxy are responsible for the hypercompetence of the sxy 
mutants. 
How do the sxy-1-5 mutations cause increased Sxy 
production? Their locations rule out several possible 
modes of action. The mutations do not improve 
the affinity of the core promoter elements (À10 and À35 
sequences), nor create a more efficient start codon or 
Shine-Dalgarno (SD) sequence, so they are unlikely to act 
by changing factors that determine baseline expression. 
The transformation frequencies and Sxy levels of the 
sxy-1-5 mutants increase as the culture medium becomes 
exhausted, so the mutations must change the sensitivity </p>

<p>of the inducing mechanism rather than ablating repres-
sion. The mutations are unlikely to act by changing the 
binding site for a transcription factor, as they are outside 
of the promoter and spread over 94 bp of transcript 
sequence. 
The clustering of the mutations into two regions 
suggested that mRNA secondary structure might play a 
role in regulation. Examination of sxy mRNA for possible 
base pairing between these regions revealed a long stretch 
of potential base pairing between positions 9-26 of 
the UTR and positions 94-111 of the coding region, 
with only a single 2 Â 2 bubble. All five hypercompetence 
mutations fall within this predicted stem. Moreover, 
each of the mutations eliminates a base pair within this 
stem, so that each is expected to destabilize the secondary 
structure. Analysis of this region with the RNA-folding 
program Mfold supported this folding model, and also 
predicted pairing between segments internal to this stem, 
creating two additional stems and three loops, as shown in 
Figure 3A. 
Mfold analysis predicted the same optimal topology for 
sxy-1-5 mRNAs as for wild-type mRNAs, but the sxy-1-5 
structures were not as thermodynamically stable and 
were predicted to have higher frequencies of single 
strandedness throughout. Supplementary Figure 2A 
plots the stability of Stem 1 in hypercompetent mutants, 
calculated by Mfold, showing that each point mutation is 
predicted to reduce the stability of Stem 1. In addition, 
this analysis predicts that Stem 1 will be the most 
important contributor to the overall stability of the </p>

<p>Figure 3. RNase analysis of sxy mRNA secondary structure. (A) Secondary structure predicted by Mfold. The Shine-Dalgarno site (SD) and start 
codon are shaded dark gray, and regions of predicted pairing are shaded light gray. Positions of sxy mutations are circled and numbered. 
(B) Cleavage intensity of sxy mRNA by single-strand-specific nucleases RNase A and RNase T1. Shaded bars correspond to stem regions shown 
in A. (C) Fold difference in cleavage intensity of mutant RNAs relative to wild type. Examples of gels used for this analysis are provided in 
Supplementary Figure 3. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 1 15 </p>

<p>mRNA secondary structure, and thus may help explain 
why all five hypercompetence mutations were found in 
this region. Supplementary Figure 2B presents the 
analysis of single-strandedness across multiple thermo-
dynamically stable folding predictions for the bases 
in Stem 1. The sxy point mutations are predicted to 
cause 2-to 3-fold increases in single-strandedness. </p>

<p>Nuclease mapping confirms the predicted sxy mRNA 
secondary structure </p>

<p>Nuclease mapping was used to test whether sxy mRNA 
folds into the predicted secondary structure in vitro, and to 
test whether hypercompetence mutations alter RNA 
folding. We first examined cleavage of wild-type sxy 
RNA by the structure-specific ribonucleases RNase T1 
and RNase A, using a cloned sxy fragment extending 
from base 1 to base 323. RNase T1 cuts specifically at 
single-stranded Gs, while RNase A cuts single-stranded 
Cs and Us. Figure 3B shows the cleavage intensities 
of all scorable positions between positions 1 and 122, 
normalized to positions 78 and 80, which were consistently 
cleaved. (Data for some Cs and Us are not shown because 
they were not cut by RNase A even when the RNA was 
denatured.) The strong cleavages between positions 42 
and 48, and between positions 72 and 80, confirm that 
Loops B and C form in vitro, and that they are separated 
by segments that are protected by pairing. The moderate 
cleavage at position 29 is consistent with the presence 
of Loop A. Only three positions in the upstream side of 
Stem 1 are informative; positions 12 and 16 are protected 
but position 24 is moderately cleaved, suggesting 
that Stem 1b may be weak. (Cleavage of position 24 
could also be explained by a slight modification to the 
predicted pairing, with nucleotide 24 bulged out and the 
3 nt below it shifted up one in their pairings.) The segment 
that forms the downstream side of Stem 1 (94-111) has 
more informative positions; these are consistently 
protected. 
The nuclease-assay support for Stems 2 and 3 and 
Loops B and C suggests that the sxy SD site and start 
codon may by sequestered within a small loop and stem, 
respectively, likely preventing the initiation of translation. 
The biochemical evidence for Stem 1 is fairly strong, with 
most of the informative positions protected from cleavage. 
Importantly, of the sites of the five hypercompetence 
mutations, the three that are scorable in these assays are 
all strongly protected, supporting the hypothesis that they 
normally are paired. 
We then examined mutant sxy-1 RNA for changes in 
secondary structure; Figure 3C (upper panel) shows the 
effect of this single mutation. Note that this figure shows 
ratios of sxy-1 cleavages to cleavages of wild-type sxy 
RNAs, not absolute intensities, so that bars above the line 
represent positions with increased nuclease sensitivity. 
The expected moderate destabilization of Stem 1a by the 
loss of base pairing between positions 14 and 106 is 
confirmed by the increased cleavage of positions 12 and 
16 and positions 102-110. Modest increases in nuclease 
sensitivity were also seen in Stem 1b (position 24) and </p>

<p>Stem 2 (positions 57 and 59), and position 115 was very 
strongly cleaved. </p>

<p>Mutations that strengthen Stem I reduce sxy expression </p>

<p>The definitive test of whether a mutant phenotype 
results from disruption of base pairing is creation of 
compensatory mutations that restore the hypothesized 
base pairing. The test is especially clear here, as the sxy-1 
and sxy-3 mutations make complementary substitutions 
disrupting the same proposed base pair. If both do 
increase sxy expression by destabilizing the secondary 
structure, then a double mutant carrying both substitu-
tions will have base pairing restored and thus will have a 
more normal phenotype (lower competence) than either 
single mutant, rather than the more extreme phenotype 
expected if the mutations increase expression in some 
other way. The desired double mutant, sxy-6, was created 
by site-directed mutagenesis in E. coli, followed by 
transformation into the H. influenzae chromosome. 
This combined the sxy-1 and sxy-3 mutations to generate 
an A:U pair where wild-type sxy has a G:C pair 
(Figure 3A). Figure 2B shows that sxy-6 cells produced 
wild-type levels of Sxy protein, much less than either 
parent mutant, confirming that the sxy-1 and sxy-3 
mutations act by disrupting base pairing. The altered 
sequence but wild-type phenotype of the sxy-6 mutant is 
strong evidence that the single mutant phenotypes are not 
due to sequence-dependent interactions with a regulatory 
protein or RNA. 
To further characterize the ability of base pairing to 
limit sxy expression, a second mutant with enhanced base 
pairing was constructed. In sxy-7, two adjacent substitu-
tions (C 20 G and U 21 A) create two new base pairings at the 
site of the 2 Â 2 bubble separating Stems 1a and 1b 
(Figure 3A), so Stem 1 of sxy-7 has 18 contiguous base 
pairings. Figure 3C (lower panel) shows that this change 
strongly reduced RNase cleavages at positions 16 and 
102-107 (Stem 1b), 37 and 54 (Stem 2), 69 and 86 (Stem 3) 
of the RNA (again the values are relative to those in 
Figure 3B); the generally decreased cleavage in the entire 
region indicates stronger base pairing throughout. 
As expected, C 100 , the predicted pairing partner of what 
is now G 20 , was not cleaved. Sxy protein was barely 
detectable in this mutant (Figure 2B) and cells could 
not be transformed even after transfer to MIV (data not 
shown). Together the sxy-6 and sxy-7 mutations confirm 
that base pairing in Stem 1 limits sxy expression and 
competence development. </p>

<p>How does mRNA secondary structure regulate 
sxy expression? </p>

<p>In principle, the secondary structure of sxy mRNA could 
limit production of Sxy protein by interfering with 
elongation of transcription or by reducing the resulting 
mRNA's stability or translation efficiency. As described 
below, two independent methods (measurements of 
b-galactosidase production from sxy::lacZ fusions and 
direct measurements of sxy RNA and protein levels) 
both showed that the structure affects both accumulation 
and translation of sxy mRNA. </p>



<p>The relative impacts of the sxy secondary structure 
on transcription and translation were first investigated 
using transcriptional and translational fusions of positions 
83 and 317 of the wild-type sxy sequence to the E. coli 
lacZ gene (Figure 4A). The position 317 fusions maintain 
all of the secondary structure shown in Figure 3A. 
The position 83 fusions eliminate the downstream 
strands of Stems 1 and 3 and thus eliminate these stems. 
Full characterization of these and related lacZ fusions is 
provided by reference 14. 
Expression from the sxy317 transcriptional fusion 
(black triangles) revealed that transcription from the sxy 
promoter is quite stable during exponential growth </p>

<p>and early stationary phase in rich medium. The absence 
of the lacZ translation start site in the corresponding 
translational fusion (white triangles) did not significantly 
change the amount of b-galactosidase activity produced, 
indicating that the sxy and lac translation start sites 
have comparable activities. Elimination of Stems 1 and 
3 in the sxy83 transcriptional fusion increased expression 
2-fold (black circles). The 5-fold increase in expression 
from the corresponding translational fusion (white circles) 
therefore represents a 2.5-fold increase in the amount of 
protein produced from each mRNA. 
A parallel experiment directly tested whether the 
increased Sxy protein in hypercompetence mutants 
results from changes in accumulation and/or translation 
of sxy mRNA. Figure 4B plots mRNA abundance 
measured by quantitative PCR (upper panel), and the 
corresponding translational efficiencies (lower panel) 
calculated for wild-type cells and hypercompetent mutants 
from the protein levels in Figure 2B. Although hypercom-
petent mutants in early log produced 7-to 16-fold 
more protein than wild-type cells, they produced only 
slightly more mRNA, indicating that mutant translational 
efficiencies were elevated 3.5-to 6.5-fold. When wild-type 
cells entered late-log growth, the amount of sxy transcript 
and Sxy protein both doubled, so the translational 
efficiency did not change. However, when the hypercom-
petent mutants entered late log they showed an even 
greater disproportion between mRNA and protein than in 
early log, implying a greater increase in translational 
efficiency. Transfer of exponentially growing wild-type 
cells to MIV resulted in a 2.5-fold increase in the amount 
of sxy mRNA and a 9-fold increase in protein after 
90 min, implying a 3.5-fold increase in translational 
efficiency. These results suggest that transfer to MIV 
maximizes competence in wild-type cells because it 
releases the translation limitation caused by mRNA 
secondary structure in rich medium. </p>

<p>mRNA secondary structure impedes translation in vitro </p>

<p>We used an in vitro coupled transcription/translation 
system to directly test the influence of mRNA secondary 
structure on the translation efficiency of sxy transcripts. 
Reactions were carried out at 258C because this tempera-
ture reduces the transcription rate of T7 RNAP to a 
rate comparable to bacterial RNAP at 378C, allowing 
nascent RNAs to fold correctly (15). All input DNAs 
(wild-type, sxy-1 and sxy-7 alleles) produced indistin-
guishable amounts of mRNA from the T7 promoter 
(data not shown), but wild-type and mutant mRNAs 
produced very different amounts of Sxy protein 
(Figure 5A). Spot-blot quantification of Sxy protein 
levels revealed that sxy-1 mRNA was translated 3-fold 
more efficiently than wild-type mRNA, whereas sxy-7 
mRNA was translated about 4-fold less efficiently than 
wild-type mRNA. 
We also tested whether a ssDNA oligonucleotide 
complementary to nucleotides 2-19 in Stem 1a (see inset 
of Figure 5B) could compete with formation of sxy 
mRNA secondary structure and thus improve translation 
efficiency. The oligonucleotide was designed to hybridize </p>

<p>Figure 4. Effect of sxy mutations on sxy mRNA levels and translation 
efficiency. (A) Expression from sxy::lacZ transcriptional and transla-
tional fusions. Triangles, fusions to sxy position 317; circles, fusions to 
sxy position 83. Filled symbols, transcriptional fusions; open symbols, 
translational fusions. Each point is the mean of two replicate cultures. 
Error bars representing the range of the replicates are shown only 
where the range was !100 Miller units. The A 600 of each sBHI culture 
increased from 0.085 to $1.2 over the course of the experiments 
(i.e. cells divided 3-4 times). (B) Translational efficiency of sxy 
transcripts in vivo. Wild-type cells, black bars; hypercompetent mutants, 
gray bars. (upper panel) sxy mRNA levels measured using real-time 
PCR; error bars represent the range of levels from two or more 
independent cultures. (lower panel) In vivo translation efficiencies of 
these transcripts, calculated as the ratios of the protein levels in 
Figure 2 to the mRNA levels in the upper panel and normalized to 
wild-type cells at A 600 0.2. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 1 17 </p>

<p>with the 5 
0 -terminus of sxy, sxy-1 and sxy-7 mRNAs, 
allowing it to compete with formation of Stem 1a 
(the location of all 5 hypercompetence mutations) without 
interfering with ribosome binding to the SD (Figure 3A). 
Figure 5B shows that inclusion of the oligonucleotide 
in reaction mixtures allowed wild-type mRNA to be 
translated as efficiently as sxy-1 mRNA, but had no 
significant effect on the translatability of sxy-1 or sxy-7 
mRNA. These results suggest that, in vitro, secondary 
structure does not inhibit translation of sxy-1 mRNA. 
Conversely, the high stability of the sxy-7 mRNA 
secondary structure not only prevents translation but 
also prevents competition of Stem 1a by the complemen-
tary oligonucleotide. The ability of this oligonucleotide to 
increase translation of wild-type sxy mRNA confirms 
that the wild-type secondary structure is strong enough to 
inhibit translation but sufficiently labile to respond to 
changing conditions. </p>

<p>CRP and cAMP strongly induce sxy transcription </p>

<p>Zulty and Barcak reported that the sxy promoter 
contained two CRP-binding sites, one centered at À5.5 
and one at À61.5 relative to the transcription start point, 
and that sxy expression in rich medium was CRP-
dependent (16). However the site they reported at À5.5 
(overlapping the transcription start site) was created by an 
A ! G substitution at position À12, and the authentic 
sequence of this site (17) (also confirmed in our lab) has 
no significant resemblance to known H. influenzae CRP 
sites (2). The site centered at À61.5 scored as an excellent 
CRP site when tested for goodness-of-fit with 58 experi-
mentally determined H. influenzae CRP sites, as previously 
described (1), and is at the optimal position to activate 
transcription through a class I mechanism (18). 
To test whether CRP induces and/or represses sxy in 
starvation medium (MIV), we measured sxy transcript </p>

<p>levels in a cyaA 
À mutant that cannot synthesize CRP's 
allosteric effector cAMP (Figure 6). Transcription was 
induced only slightly in a cyaA 
À mutant. Adding 1 mM 
cAMP resulted in very strong induction of sxy, indicating 
that CRP does activate the sxy promoter. The promoter 
could be induced by cAMP added after 20 min in MIV, 
but the amount of sxy transcript still fell back to pre-
induction levels after 40 min in MIV. Thus, CRP is a 
strong inducer of sxy expression, but continuing expres-
sion appears to be overridden by a repressing mechanism 
after 40 min. This mechanism is unlikely to be auto-
repression of the crp gene by CRP, because sxy repression 
did not depend on when cAMP was added. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We have identified and characterized an extensive 
5 
0 stem-loop structure in the sxy transcript, which 
negatively regulates this competence-inducing transcrip-
tion factor. Mutations that destabilize the secondary 
structure increase both the amount of sxy mRNA 
and the efficiency of its translation, causing greatly 
elevated competence under otherwise non-inducing con-
ditions. These large phenotypic effects arise from minor 
perturbations in mRNA secondary structure; a mutation 
decreasing by one the number of base pairs in Stem 1 
(sxy-1) destabilizes the structure while one increasing the 
number of base pairs by two (sxy-7) stabilizes folding. 
In some mRNAs, secondary structure regulates expres-
sion by forming riboswitches or by preventing degradation 
by the single-strand-specific endoribonuclease RNase 
E (19,20), but these are unlikely to contribute to post-
transcriptional regulation of sxy mRNA. The sxy 
secondary structure has no similarities to the well-
conserved structures of known riboswitches (19). A role 
for RNase E can also be ruled out because weakening 
the secondary structure led to elevated transcript levels, 
contrary to the expectation if RNase E targets the sxy 
transcript. 
The increased translation efficiency of sxy mutants 
with weakened mRNA secondary structure is most readily </p>

<p>Figure 5. Sxy protein generated by in vitro transcription/translation. 
(A) Protein production from wild-type (WT), sxy-1 and sxy-7 DNA 
templates. The average and standard deviation of three independent 
time courses are shown. (B) Protein production in reactions containing 
a ssDNA oligonucleotide complementary to the 5 
0 -end of sxy mRNA. 
The inset illustrates the oligonucleotide (black) binding to nucleotides 
2-19 of the sxy transcript (gray), thus directly competing with 
formation of Stem 1a. The average and standard deviation of two 
independent time courses using WT and sxy-7 template, and one time 
course using sxy-1 template are shown. All Sxy protein levels are 
normalized to wild type at 10 min in (A). </p>

<p>Figure 6. Control of sxy transcription by cAMP-CRP. RR668 cells 
(cyaA </p>

<p>À </p>

<p>) at A 600 0.2 in sBHI were transferred to MIV, with 1 mM 
cAMP added at t = 0 
0 or t = 20 
0 . sxy transcript was measured using 
real-time PCR. </p>



<p>explained by a simple model in which the secondary 
structure of wild-type mRNA limits ribosome binding. 
Ribosomes require that a 35-50 nt segment including 
the SD site be free of stable secondary structure (21). 
Indeed, extensive regions of double-stranded RNA at or 
near the SD site and start codon, like the secondary 
structure we have detected in sxy mRNA, are known 
to preclude ribosome binding to (and consequently 
translation of) several bacterial mRNAs (22-25). Under 
this model of sxy expression, the moderate increase in 
transcript abundance in the sxy83 transcriptional fusion 
strain (Figure 4A) and in hypercompetent mutants 
(Figure 4B) arises because mutant mRNAs are more 
often occupied by ribosomes and thus protected from 
degradation [see (26) for a recent review of ribosome 
protection], rather than because hypercompetence 
mutations activate the sxy promoter. Furthermore, use 
of a T7 promoter to generate sxy mRNA for in vitro 
translation confirmed that the hypercompetence pheno-
type can be explained primarily by improved translation 
efficiency and not by mutational effects on sxy's native 
promoter. 
The rise in the ratio of sxy protein to mRNA induced by 
transfer to MIV starvation medium suggests that the 
secondary structure does more than establish a 
baseline level of translation. Rather, it has the potential 
to play a sensory role that explains the repression of 
competence by purine nucleotides (27). In bacteria, 
multiple regulatory mechanisms link nucleotide availabil-
ity to transcription initiation, promoter escape and 
elongation (28-32). For example, translation of E. coli's 
pyrimidine biosynthesis operon pyrBI is contingent on 
nucleotide starvation (33). When cells are starved for 
the pyrimidine nucleotide UTP, transcription pausing in 
the pyrBI leader sequence allows ribosome loading to 
prevent folding of an mRNA-terminating hairpin (34). 
However, unlike the small pyrBI terminator hairpin 
($20 nt), the &gt;100 nt sxy mRNA structure allows two 
other kinetic factors to come into play. First, large mRNA 
secondary structures require time to fold after their 
synthesis is complete, especially if the final structure 
involves pairing between non-adjacent segments as in 
Stem 1 of sxy mRNA (35). Translation thus may initiate 
more easily on newly synthesized transcripts than on ones 
that have had time to fold. Even so, the ability of an 
oligonucleotide to compete with the secondary structure 
of sxy, but not sxy-7 indicates that double-stranded 
regions of the wild-type transcript are sufficiently dynamic 
to allow invasion by more stable partners (Figure 5B), 
suggesting that sxy mRNA secondary structure never 
completely precludes ribosome binding. 
A more important contribution to regulation may come 
from a second kinetic factor: the distance RNAP must 
transcribe between synthesis of the translation initiation 
signals (SD and start codon) and synthesis of the 
downstream portion of the secondary structure that 
would block access to them. In sxy mRNA this distance 
is 60 nt. Dynamic modeling of sxy mRNA folding using 
the RNA Kinetics server (http://www.ig-msk.ru/RNA/ 
kinetics/) predicted that the segment of sxy mRNA 
containing the SD site and the start codon will remain </p>

<p>largely unstructured until more than 100 nt have been 
synthesized. The availability of this potential landing 
platform for ribosomes will in turn depend on the rate of 
transcription, thus making the progress of RNA poly-
merase a potential transducer of nutritional signals. 
Nucleotide pools are not limiting to H. influenzae 
during growth in rich medium, so the resulting rapid 
transcription may allow sxy mRNA to usually fold before 
ribosomes load. Under these conditions, translation may 
only be able to initiate during rare unfolding events, 
consistent with the dramatic effects in rich medium of the 
sxy-1-5 mutations that decrease thermodynamic stability. 
Transfer to MIV causes abrupt depletion of nucleotide 
pools, and the resulting slowing of transcription may be 
sufficient to allow translation to initiate on most nascent 
wild-type transcripts. The combination of increased 
translation efficiency with the increased transcription 
caused by rising cAMP would then lead to a burst of 
Sxy production, followed by expression of competence 
genes. 
Sxy is not the only regulator of competence in MIV; 
CRP activity at the CRP-S promoters of competence 
genes is known to be elevated because MIV-treated cells 
produce more cAMP than cells in rich medium (36). 
Consistent with this, wild-type cells in MIV produce less 
Sxy protein but become more competent than hypercom-
petent mutants in rich medium. In addition, at least one 
essential competence gene has a candidate PurR-binding 
site in its promoter, and PurR repression of purine 
biosynthesis genes is relaxed in MIV (2). We are currently 
testing whether PurR represses competence when 
nucleotide pools are high. Understanding the interplay 
of signals transduced by CRP/cAMP, Sxy and possibly 
PurR will clarify how nutritional sensing controls DNA 
uptake. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Qing Qian and Caixia Ma for technical support, 
and George Mackie, Kristian Baker, George Spiegelman, 
Brett McLeod and Arina Omer for technical advice. 
This work was supported by an Operating Grant from the 
Canadian Institutes for Health Research to R.J.R. 
Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for 
this article was provided by the Canadian Institute of 
Health Research. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 1 19 </p>





</text></tei>