<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2999698" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The management of diabetes mellitus requires an accurate 
evaluation of blood glucose control to assess the efficiency 
of a particular therapy. Whole blood hemoglobin A1c 
(HbA1c) measurements have been widely used in diabetes 
patients for more than 25 years to monitor long-term 
glycemic control. 
1,2 The measurement indicates a patient's 
average blood glucose level during the previous 60-90 days. 
It is recommended that diabetes patients have their HbA1c 
levels checked at least two times per year because 
quantitative and direct relationships have been identified 
between HbA1c concentration and the risk of diabetic 
microvascular complications. 
3 Therefore, clinicians use 
HbA1c test results to guide treatment decisions, and the 
test has become the cornerstone for assessing diabetes care. </p>

<p>4   Various analytical methods based on different assay 
techniques, such as ion-exchange chromatography, affinity 
chromatography, immunoassays and electrophoresis, have 
been used to measure glycated hemoglobin levels. 
5 As a </p>

<p>result, HbA1c results can vary considerably when measured 
by different laboratories or methods. Recently, the 
International Federation of Clinical Chemistry and 
Laboratory Medicine (IFCC) developed a new reference 
method that specifically measures the concentration of a 
single molecular species of glycated A1c. 
4 However, the new 
method results in values that are 1.5%-2.0% lower than 
current values, and the results are expressed in different 
units (millimoles per mole of unglycated hemoglobin), 
which may cause confusion for patients and health care 
providers. </p>

<p>6   The relationship between the mean blood glucose level 
and the level of HbA1c has been investigated in different 
studies, and various equations have been obtained. </p>

<p>2,7,8   Using Nathan's regression equation, which has been 
recommended by the American Diabetes Association 
(ADA), the estimated average glucose (eAG) level calcula-
tion and its relationship to the fasting plasma glucose (FPG) 
level were investigated in the present study. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>The fasting plasma glucose levels of 3891 diabetic patient 
samples (1497 male, 2394 female) were obtained from a 
laboratory information system at the Izmir Bozyaka 
Training and Research Hospital in Turkey. Blood samples </p>

<p>Copyright ß 2010 CLINICS -This is an Open Access article distributed under 
the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits unrestricted non-
commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the 
original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2010;65(11):1077-1080 
DOI:10.1590/S1807-59322010001100003 </p>



<p>were taken on the same day for the determination of both 
FPG and HbA1c. The study group was selected from patient 
samples that had hemoglobin levels between 12 and 
16 g/dL because HbA1c results can be influenced by 
several factors, including anemia. In addition, samples from 
patients with hemoglobin abnormalities or uremia or who 
were pregnant were excluded. The estimated glucose levels 
(mg/dL) were calculated using the following formula: 28.7 x 
HbA1c -46.7. 
6 According to the patients' levels of blood 
glucose control, we divided the samples into three groups: 
group A: FPG , 126 mg/dL; group B: FPG = 126-200 mg/ 
dL; and group C: FPG . 200 mg/dL. Glucose levels were 
determined using the hexokinase method in an Olympus 
2700 analyzer with commercially available Olympus kits 
(Olympus Optical Co. Ltd, Shizuoka-ken, Japan). HbA1c 
levels were determined using an HPLC method and an 
Agilent Technologies 1200 Series analyzer with commer-
cially available kits (Chromsystems Instruments and 
Chemicals GmbH, Mü nchen, Germany). Hemoglobin (Hb) 
levels were determined using a Beckman Coulter Gen S 
system (Beckman Coulter Inc., Fullerton, CA, USA). 
All statistical analyses were performed using the 
Statistical Package for Social Sciences (<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs>, version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">11</rs>.0 
for Windows, Chicago, IL, USA). Data were expressed as 
the means ¡ standart error of the mean (SEM). A p-value 
,0.05 was accepted as significant. The Kolmogorov-
Smirnov test was performed to assess the normality of the 
variables. The Wilcoxon signed-rank test was used to 
compare the FPG and eAG levels, and the Mann-Whitney 
U test was used to compare the variables between males 
and females. The Spearman correlation coefficient (r) was 
used to test the relationship between the FPG and eAG 
levels. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>According to the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test, the distribu-
tions of age, HbA1c, FPG, eAG and Hb were abnormal 
(p,0.05). The study group consisted of 3891 individuals 
with a mean age of 56.5 ¡0.2 (ranging from 18 to 92 years 
old) (Table1). The mean FPG, eAG, HbA1c and Hb levels in 
the whole group presented in Table1. A strong positive 
correlation was found between FPG and eAG levels 
(r = 0.757, p,0.05). 
Although the mean levels of FPG and eAG were close, 
according to the Wilcoxon signed-rank test, they were 
statistically significantly different (p,0.05). 
The mean age and the HbA1c, FPG, eAG and Hb levels in 
groups A, B and C are shown in Table1. The similarities in 
the average levels of FPG and eAG that were present for the </p>

<p>group as a whole disappeared when the patient samples 
were separated into groups A, B and C. The correlation 
coefficients for these groups are presented in Table1 
(p,0.05). The eAG levels were higher in groups A and B 
than in group C compared to FPG levels. 
The relationship between the levels of FPG and eAG was 
investigated for males and females using Spearman's 
correlation coefficients after verifying the normality of 
variables with the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. The correla-
tion coefficient was higher in women (r = 0.779) than in men 
(r = 0.723) (p,0.05). In addition, the mean levels of FPG, 
eAG, HbA1c and Hb were higher in males than in females 
(Table2). A statistically significant difference was found for 
eAG, HbA1c and Hb levels between men and women 
(Table2). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The HbA1c measurement is used to determine the 
average level of glycemic control over the previous 8-12  weeks; this measurement is accepted as a gold-standard 
measurement of chronic glycemia. 
4 Despite its wide inter-
national use, there is a substantial lack of standardization 
among HbA1c determination methods. The desire to 
standardize the HbA1c results obtained from different 
techniques led the IFCC to create a reference method, but 
this method created problems in reporting measurement 
results. 
7 One problem is the risk of decreasing a patient's 
glycemic control; when a patient's HbA1c measurement is 
lower than previous results, he or she might become 
confused and perhaps change diet, which could negatively 
impact his or her metabolic control. 
9 The other problem is 
the reporting of HbA1c levels in mmol HbA1c per mol total 
Hb, which could confuse patients. In addition, guidelines 
for diabetes have been based on standard levels that are 
derived from reports of the Diabetes Control and 
Complications Trial (DCCT) and the U.K. Prospective 
Diabetes Study (UKPDS). The equivalent of the current 
HbA1c targets of 6.5% and 7.5% are 48 milimoles per mole 
and 59 milimoles per mole in the new units. To resolve these 
problems, the ADA, the European Association for the Study 
of Diabetes (EASD) and the International Diabetes 
Federation (IDF) sponsored an international study to define 
a mathematical relationship between HbA1c and the eAG 
level. 
6 The following formula describes this relationship: 
28.7 x HbA1c -46.7 = eAG. This formula will assist health 
care providers and their patients in interpreting HbA1c 
values in units similar to those that the patients see 
regularly through self-monitoring. </p>

<p>6   Using this formula, we calculated the eAG levels of our 
study group and investigated their relationship with the 
FPG levels. Surprisingly, the eAG levels were closely </p>

<p>Table 1 -The levels of the glycemic parameters and the 
correlation coefficients for all groups (mean ¡SEM). </p>

<p>Entire 
group </p>

<p>Group A FPG: 
, 126 mg/dL </p>

<p>Group B FPG: 
126-200 mg/dL </p>

<p>Group C FPG: 
. 200 mg/dL </p>

<p>N 
3891 
1736 
1313 
842 
Age (y) 
56.5 ¡0.2 
54.7 ¡0.3 
58.8 ¡0.3 
56.6 ¡0.4 
FPG (mg/dL) 159.4 ¡0.9 103.2 ¡0.3 
155.3 ¡0.6 
281.7 ¡2.3 
eAG (mg/dL) 159.7 ¡1.2 125.1 ¡0.7 
160.6 ¡1.0 
229.6 ¡1.9 
Hb (g/dL) 
13.7 ¡0.02 13.6 ¡0.02 
13.7 ¡0.02 
13.8 ¡0.04 
HbA1c (%) 
7.2 ¡0.03 
6.0 ¡0.02 
7.2 ¡0.04 
9.6 ¡0.07 
FPG vs. eAG r = 0.757 
r = 0.300 
r = 0.443 
r = 0.450 </p>

<p>Table 2 -A comparison of the glycemic parameter levels 
in males and females (mean ¡SEM). </p>

<p>Male 
Female 
p-value </p>

<p>n 
1497 
2394 
Age (y) 
56.4 ¡0.3 
56.5 ¡0.3 
0.711 
FPG (mg/dL) 
160.4 ¡2.0 
158.7 ¡1.55 
0.374 
eAG (mg/dL) 
162.8 ¡1.5 
157.6 ¡1.1 
0.001 
Hb (g/dL) 
14.2 ¡0.03 
13.3 ¡0.02 
0.001 
HbA1c (%) 
7.3 ¡0.05 
7.1 ¡0.04 
0.001 </p>

<p>Glucose levels: estimated vs fasting 
Bozkaya G et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2010;65(11):1077-1080 </p>



<p>associated with the FPG levels when the measurements 
were taken the same day. There was not only a strong 
correlation between the eAG and FPG levels, but their mean 
levels were also very similar (159.7 mg/dL and 159.4 mg/ 
dL, respectively). We at first thought that the eAG and FPG 
levels could be used interchangeably. It appeared that 
determining a patient's HbA1c level might be unnecessary if 
we could determine his or her FPG level because we could 
simply calculate it with the aforementioned formula. We 
decided to directly compare the eAG and FPG levels 
statistically. Although their mean levels seemed to be 
similar, they were actually significantly different 
(p = 0.001). Although we observed a significant difference 
between the average levels, this difference was not clinically 
meaningful. For 1567 samples, the eAG levels were lower 
than the FPG levels, whereas for 2324 samples, the eAG 
levels were higher than the FPG levels. These findings 
clearly demonstrate that the eAG and FPG values cannot be 
used interchangeably. We accepted the similar means of the 
eAG and FPG levels as a coincidence. This similarity in the 
FPG and eAG levels for the entire group disappeared when 
the subgroups were separated according to FPG level. In 
addition, the decrease in the significant strong correlation 
coefficient showed that the association depended on the 
patients' levels of glucose control. As glucose control 
worsened, the association became stronger. 
On the other hand, most patients who come to the clinic 
for plasma glucose determination pay more attention to 
fasting and diet rules. The eAG levels in the study group 
were higher than the FPG levels not only because patients 
come to the lab in a fasting state but also because the eAG 
level is reflective of all plasma glucose levels over the 
previous three months, including the postprandial glucose 
levels. Sixty percent of patients had higher eAG levels than 
FPG levels. When we evaluated the eAG levels of patients in 
group C, we found that their eAG levels were lower than 
their FPG levels, in contrast with the findings for groups A 
and B (Table1). We assumed that patients with higher FPG 
levels experienced stress before coming to the hospital to 
give blood or did not take their anti-diabetic drugs, since 
their FPG levels were higher than their average blood 
glucose levels. 
We also wanted to understand the effect of gender on the 
eAG and FPG levels. Among age-matched samples, females 
had lower eAG and FPG levels than males (Table2). The 
decreased levels of eAG and HbA1c in women were 
significantly different from those of males. In addition, 
there was a significant difference between the eAG and FPG 
levels in both men and women (p = 0.000). The eAG levels of 
females and males were higher than the FPG levels in most 
patients (58% and 62%, respectively), similar to the results 
found for the group as a whole (60%). 
The IDF estimates that 285 million people worldwide 
have diabetes. This total number is expected to rise to 438 
million within 20 years. Turkey, with approximately 70 
million inhabitants, is a country where diabetes and 
impaired glucose tolerance are moderately common, but 
awareness of diabetes remains poor. 
10 It is thought that 
diabetic patients require better strategies to improve self-
management. 
11 One of these strategies is the use of eAG 
levels together with HbA1c values. Although the clinical 
usefulness of eAG is not clear, 
12,13 we believe that every 
patient's eAG level should be calculated and reported along 
with his or her HbA1c level. This strategy will help patients </p>

<p>better understand the importance of keeping their blood 
glucose levels within acceptable limits and maybe will 
rescue them from some invasive approaches for glucose 
homeostasis. </p>

<p>14   CONCLUSION </p>

<p>According to our data, patients with good to moderate 
blood glucose control are not entirely successful at mana-
ging their blood glucose, as reflected by their eAG levels, 
and the association between the FPG and eAG levels 
depends on the extent of blood glucose control. </p>







<p>Glucose levels: estimated vs fasting 
Bozkaya G et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2010;65(11):1077-1080 </p>



</text></tei>