<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2919713" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Rad51 protein promotes homologous recombin-
ation in eukaryotes. Recombination activities are 
activated by Rad51 filament assembly on ssDNA. 
Previous studies of yeast Rad51 showed that 
His352 occupies an important position at the 
filament interface, where it could relay signals 
between subunits and active sites. To investigate, 
we characterized yeast Rad51 H352A and H352Y 
mutants, and solved the structure of H352Y. H352A 
forms catalytically competent but salt-labile 
complexes on ssDNA. In contrast, H352Y forms 
salt-resistant complexes on ssDNA, but is defective 
in nucleotide exchange, RPA displacement and 
strand exchange with full-length DNA substrates. 
The 2.5 A ˚ crystal structure of H352Y reveals a 
right-handed helical filament in a high-pitch (130 A ˚ ) 
conformation with P6 1 symmetry. The catalytic core 
and dimer interface regions of H352Y closely 
resemble those of DNA-bound Escherichia coli 
RecA protein. The H352Y mutation stabilizes 
Phe187 from the adjacent subunit in a position that 
interferes with the c-phosphate-binding site of the 
Walker A motif/P-loop, potentially explaining the 
limited catalysis observed. Comparison of Rad51 
H352Y, RecA-DNA and related structures reveals 
that the presence of bound DNA correlates with 
the isomerization of a conserved cis peptide near 
Walker B to the trans configuration, which appears 
to prime the catalytic glutamate residue for ATP 
hydrolysis. </p>

<p>Homologous recombination (HR) is essential for the 
accurate repair of DNA double-strand breaks and for 
the maintenance of genomic stability. HR also provides 
a key mechanism for the generation of genetic diversity. In 
eukaryotes, the central steps of HR require the 
ATP-dependent DNA strand exchange activity of Rad51 
protein, which is a member of the highly conserved RecA 
recombinase family (1). DNA strand exchange reactions 
occur between homologous molecules of single-and 
double-stranded DNA. The first step of DNA strand 
exchange is the formation of a competent presynaptic 
filament of Rad51 protein on single-stranded DNA. 
Filament assembly allosterically activates the enzymatic 
activities of Rad51 including ssDNA-dependent ATP hy-
drolysis, homology search and DNA strand exchange. The 
proper assembly and activation of Rad51-ssDNA fila-
ments are critical for DSB repair and cancer avoidance, 
as illustrated by defects in this process that are associated 
with cancer predisposition syndromes in humans (2). 
Presynaptic filament assembly, turnover and DNA 
strand exchange activity are coupled to the binding and 
hydrolysis of ATP by Rad51. Therefore signaling between 
binding sites for DNA and nucleotide ligands is critical for 
Rad51 recombination activity. It is known that ATP 
induces or stabilizes a high-affinity ssDNA-binding con-
formation of Rad51 that is required for the assembly of 
catalytically competent presynaptic filaments (3). The hy-
drolysis of ATP to ADP weakens Rad51-DNA inter-
actions, facilitating filament turnover. In the RecA/ 
Rad51 family, high-affinity binding to ssDNA in the 
presence of ATP or of non-hydrolyzable ATP analogs 
correlates with a high-pitch filament morphology 
detected by electron microscopy and crystallographic </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 802 656 8260; Fax: +1 802 656 8220; Email: smorrica@uvm.edu 
Correspondence may also be addressed to Mark A. Rould. Tel: +1 802 656 9532; Fax: +1 802 656 0747; Email: mrould@uvm.edu </p>

<p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. </p>

<p>Published online 5 April 2010 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 14 4889-4906 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkq209 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>methods (4,5). The high-pitch filament is generally 
referred to as the active form of the filament. 
Low-affinity binding to ssDNA in the presence of ADP 
or no nucleotide correlates with a low-pitch filament 
morphology that is generally referred to as the inactive 
form of the filament. The mechanism of inter-conversion 
between these forms, if it occurs during recombination, is 
unknown. 
The assembly of Rad51 filaments on ssDNA is 
modulated by RPA, the eukaryotic ssDNA-binding 
protein. RPA promotes filament assembly by removing 
regions of secondary structure from ssDNA that would 
otherwise impede Rad51 binding, but the high affinity of 
RPA for ssDNA imposes a potential barrier to Rad51 
filament assembly in vitro (6,7). Biochemical data demon-
strate that to form a competent presynaptic filament, 
Rad51 must displace RPA in order to bind to sites on 
ssDNA. In vitro, strand exchange occurs optimally when 
Rad51 is pre-incubated with ssDNA and ATP prior to 
RPA addition. When the ssDNA is pre-saturated with 
RPA, however, as is likely to occur in vivo, strand 
exchange is inhibited due to the rate-limiting displacement 
of RPA from ssDNA by Rad51. The inhibition is reversed 
by recombination mediator proteins (Rad52, Rad51 
paralogs, or Brca2) that promote RPA displacement by 
Rad51 (2,8). The importance of Rad51/RPA competition 
in recombination is illustrated by the observation that 
recombination-deficient mutations in yeast recombination 
mediator proteins Rad55 and Rad57 are complemented by 
mutations in Rad51 that increase its ssDNA-binding 
affinity and therefore its ability to compete with RPA 
for binding sites on ssDNA (9). 
The coupling of ssDNA binding to catalysis is of cen-
tral importance in the recombination activities of all 
Rad51/RecA enzymes, but the mechanism of signaling 
between the various DNA-bound states and catalytic 
sites is poorly understood. This signaling to and from 
the active site is coordinated by loops L1 and L2, which 
are disordered in recombinase structures lacking DNA, 
but ordered in RecA-DNA structures (4). Major ssDNA 
binding determinants occur in L2, which is connected 
at its N-terminal end to a conserved glutamine residue 
(Gln194 in Escherichia coli RecA, Gln326 in 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae Rad51) that is proposed to act 
as a sensor for the presence of ATP in the active site (10). 
Other interactions that span the protomer-protomer inter-
face are proposed to play key roles in coordinating DNA 
binding to the activation of catalysis. Crystal structures of 
high-pitch filaments show that the ATPase active site itself 
spans the protomer-protomer interface (4,11). In the 
RecA-DNA structures, Lys248 and Lys250 from one 
protomer coordinate the g-phosphate of ATP bound to 
the P-loop region of the adjacent protomer, with Lys250 
interacting with the putative catalytic glutamate residue of 
the adjacent protomer (4). These interactions are proposed 
to stabilize the interface and activate hydrolysis in 
response to DNA binding (4). This mechanism is 
unlikely to be conserved outside of the eubacteria, 
however, since the sequence and structural motifs contain-
ing the two lysine residues are missing from eukaryotic 
Rad51 and archaeal RadA enzymes. </p>

<p>To date only one structure of a eukaryotic Rad51 
filament has been published. The S. cerevisiae Rad51 
I345T mutant is a gain-of-function mutant with 
enhanced ssDNA-binding affinity (9). The crystallograph-
ic structure of I345T revealed a filament with P3 1 
symmetry (11). An interesting feature of the I354T struc-
ture is that the repeating unit is a dimer, so that 
alternating momomers are in different conformations, 
creating two classes of interfaces and thus two classes of 
ATPase active sites. The I354T structure shows that 
residue His352, which is highly conserved among Rad51, 
Dmc1 and RadA recombinases, occupies an important 
position at the protomer-protomer interface near the 
ATPase site. The equivalent residue in E. coli RecA is 
Phe217, which is known to be important for allosteric 
communication within RecA-ssDNA filaments (12). In 
yeast Rad51 filaments, His352 interacts with P-loop/ 
Walker A residue Phe187 from the adjacent protomer. 
His352-Phe187 interactions occur in two distinct 
geometries at alternating interfaces within the 3 1 
filament (11). The relative positioning of His352 and 
Phe187 appears to be coupled to the movements of 
other elements of the interface and ATPase sites. 
Therefore His352 is a strong candidate for a residue that 
couples ssDNA binding and filament formation with the 
nucleotide state of Rad51 protein. Consistent with this 
idea, site-directed mutagenesis of His352 reduces the 
ability of Rad51 to perform DNA strand exchange 
between simple oligonucleotide substrates (13). 
In this study we examined the biochemical defects 
caused by two different site-directed mutations at the 
His352 locus of S. cerevisiae Rad51 protein, H352A and 
H352Y, and we solved the X-ray crystallographic struc-
ture of the H352Y protein filament. We find that these 
mutants are defective in DNA strand exchange but for 
different reasons: H352A has the hallmarks of a classic 
weak ssDNA binder that forms catalytically competent 
but salt-labile complexes on ssDNA. In contrast the 
H352Y mutant is a strong ssDNA binder, but is unable 
to undergo multiple turnovers of the nucleotide state. ATP 
hydrolysis by H352Y appears to be limited to a single 
turnover, consistent with a defect in nucleotide exchange 
(replacement of ADP product with new ATP substrate). 
The results indicate that cross-interface interactions 
mediated by His352 are important for normal signaling 
between ssDNA-binding and catalytic sites in Rad51. 
The filament structure reveals that His ! Tyr substitution 
at position 352 stabilizes Phe187 from the adjacent 
subunit in a position that interferes with the 
g-phosphate-binding site of Walker A, potentially explain-
ing the limited catalysis observed in H352Y. Comparison 
of the Rad51 H352Y structure to other RecA/Rad51 
structures suggests that Phe187 (Glu68 in E. coli RecA) 
of Walker A either plays a role in detecting the presence/ 
absence of the g-phosphate of ATP, or in preventing nu-
cleotide exchange. Comparison further reveals that the 
presence of bound DNA correlates with the isomerization 
of a conserved cis peptide at the end of the Walker B motif 
to the trans configuration, which appears to prime the 
putative nucleophilic activator Glu221 (Glu96 in E. coli 
RecA) for hydrolysis of the ATP. </p>

<p>4890 Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 14 </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Reagents </p>

<p>Chemicals, biochemicals and enzymes were purchased 
from Sigma-Aldrich unless specifically stated. All restric-
tion enzymes were purchased from New England Biolabs. 
The crystallization screens, trays and plates were 
purchased from Hampton Research. All reagents were 
analytical grade and solutions were made with Barnstead 
NANO-pure water. TE buffer contained 10 mM Tris-
HCl, pH 8.0 and 1 mM EDTA. </p>

<p>Nucleic acids </p>

<p>Circular single-stranded uX174 virion DNA (5.4 kb) and 
double-stranded uX174 DNA (replicative form I DNA, 
RFI) were purchased from New England Biolabs. RFI 
was linearized by digestion with PstI restriction endo-
nuclease and purified using standard procedures. The con-
centrations of ssDNA and dsDNA stock solutions were 
determined according to manufacturer's instructions. 
Etheno-modified ssDNA (eDNA) was prepared from 
M13mp19 virion ssDNA (7.3 kb) and quantified as previ-
ously described (14,15). All DNA molecules were stored 
at À20 C in TE buffer and the concentrations were 
expressed in units of micromoles of nucleotide residues 
per liter. </p>

<p>Site-directed mutagenesis of yeast Rad51 protein </p>

<p>Plasmid pLant2B (RIL) encoding yeast Rad51 was a 
generous gift from Dr Tom Ellenberger at Washington 
University in St Louis. Two mutants, H352A and 
H352Y at residue 352 of Rad51 protein were introduced 
using the QuikChange site-directed mutagenesis protocol 
(Stratagene). To construct the Rad51-H352A mutant, 
forward primer 1, 5 0 GTAATATTATGGCAGCGTCTTC 
CACCACGCGAT 3 0 and reverse primer 2, 5 0 ATCGC 
GTGGTGGAAGACGCTGCCATAATATTAC 3 0 were 
designed. Similarly, forward primer 3, 5 0 GTGGTAATA 
TTATGGCATATTCTTCCACCACGCG 3 0 and reverse 
primer 4, 5 0 CGCGTGGTGGAAGAATATGCCATAAT 
ATTACCAC 3 0 were used for introducing the Rad51-
H352Y mutant. PCR reactions were conducted according 
to the QuikChange protocol and the resulting plasmids 
were sequenced at the Vermont Cancer Center DNA 
Sequencing Facility to verify successful mutagenesis. </p>

<p>Purification of yeast RPA and Rad51 proteins </p>

<p>Yeast RPA protein expression plasmid p11d-tRPA was a 
kind gift from Dr Mark Wold of the University of Iowa. 
RPA was expressed in E. coli strain BL21(DE3) and the 
protein was purified as described (16). 
Rad51 proteins were expressed from plasmid pLant2B 
(RIL) harboring wild-type or mutant versions of the 
RAD51 gene, which was transformed into E. coli strain 
BLR(DE3)/pLysS (Novagen, Inc., Madison, WI). 
Identical purification protocols were used for Rad51 
wild-type, H352A and H352Y proteins. The purification 
steps were a modified version of a published protocol (17). 
In brief, the cells were grown at 37 C to a cell density of 
A 600 = 0.6. Cells were shifted to 16 C and induced with </p>

<p>0.1 mM IPTG for 16 h. Cell pellets from 6-l cultures were 
harvested by centrifugation and resuspended in 120 ml of 
Buffer A containing 600 mM KCl, 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 
7.5), 
5 mM 
EDTA, 
10% 
sucrose, 
10 mM 
b-mercaptoethanol, 0.1 mM benzamidine and 5 mg/ml 4-
(2-aminoethyl) benzenesulfonyl fluoride (AEBSF, 
Sigma). Cells were lysed by sonication, and extracts were 
clarified by centrifugation (40 000 rpm, 2 h). The extract 
was treated with ammonium sulfate (0.22 g/ml), and the 
protein pellet was resuspended in 120 ml of Buffer P 
[20 mM potassium phosphate (pH 7.5), 10% glycerol, 
0.5 mM EDTA, 0.5 mM DTT], containing 50 mM KCl, 
5 mg/ml AEBSF and 0.1 mM benzamidine. This solution 
was loaded at a flow rate of 120 ml/h onto a 50-ml 
Cybacron Blue-agarose column pre-equilibrated with 
Buffer P. The column was washed with Buffer P contain-
ing 100 mM KCl until the A 280 of the flow-through ap-
proached zero, and then 200 ml of a 0.2-1.0 M KCl 
gradient in Buffer P was applied. Fractions containing 
Rad51 protein were combined and dialyzed against 
Buffer P containing 100 mM KCl, 5 mg/ml AEBSF and 
0.1 mM benzamidine, and then loaded onto a 50-ml 
Q-Sepharose column, which was pre-equilibrated with 
Buffer P containing 100 mM KCl. Proteins were 
fractionated with a 600 ml KCl gradient (200-800 mM 
KCl) in Buffer P; Rad51 protein eluted at about 400 mM 
KCl. Pooled fractions were dialyzed against Buffer H 
[5 mM potassium phosphate (pH 6.5), 0.5 mM DTT, 
10% glycerol, 40 mM KCl] containing 5 mg/ml AEBSF 
and 0.1 mM benzamidine, and then loaded onto a 50-ml 
Bio-Gel hydroxyapatite column that was equilibrated with 
Buffer H. Bound proteins were eluted with a 300 ml linear 
gradient of 20-200 mM potassium phosphate (pH 6.5) in 
Buffer H at a flow rate of 60 ml/h. These fractions were 
pooled and dialyzed against Buffer P containing 200 mM 
KCl and then loaded onto a MonoQ (HR 5/5) column. A 
linear gradient (160 ml) of 200-600 mM KCl in Buffer P 
was used to elute Rad51 protein (at about 400 mM KCl). 
Fractions containing purified Rad51 protein were dialyzed 
against storage buffer [20 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 1 mM 
DTT, 10% glycerol, 0.5 mM EDTA, 100 mM KCl], ali-
quoted, and stored at À80 C. The final yield of wild 
type Rad51 protein was about 25 mg from 6 l of culture. 
The concentrations of WT and H352A proteins were 
calculated using an extinction coefficient (determined 
from amino-acid composition) of 1.29 Â 10 4 M -1 cm -1 at 
280 nm. H352Y protein concentration was calculated 
using an extinction coefficient (determined from 
amino-acid composition) of 1.4 Â 10 4 M -1 cm -1 at 280 nm. 
The purity of Rad51 protein was above 99% based on 
SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. The presence of 
tyrosine at position 352 of the H352Y mutant was con-
firmed by mass spectrometry at the Proteomics Facility of 
the Vermont Genetics Network, University of Vermont 
College of Medicine. 
All protein stock solutions were tested for 
contaminating nuclease activities by the following proced-
ures (18): Aliquots of each protein stock were incubated 
for 2 h at 37 C in solutions containing either circular 
ssDNA, linear ssDNA, linear dsDNA, or supercoiled 
plus nicked plasmid dsDNA, in buffer used for DNA </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 14 4891 </p>

<p>strand exchange assays (see below). Samples were then 
deproteinized, electrophoresed on agarose gels, and 
visualized by ethidium bromide staining as described 
below for DNA strand exchange assays. The gels were 
examined visually for evidence of nuclease degradation 
of the various DNA species (smearing, appearance of 
low molecular weight species, nicking or linearization of 
circular DNA species). All protein stocks used in this 
study were found to be nuclease-free according to these 
criteria. </p>

<p>Etheno-DNA (eDNA) fluorescence enhancement assays 
for Rad51-ssDNA interactions </p>

<p>The binding site sizes of Rad51 wild-type, H352A and 
H352Y proteins on single-stranded DNA were determined 
from titrations of eDNA with protein under low-salt, tight 
binding conditions, while monitoring the increase in 
eDNA fluorescence as previously described (17). 
Fluorescence measurements were made in a PTI 
Quantamaster QM-6 fluorometer (Photon Technology 
International, South Brunswick, NJ) at excitation and 
emission wavelengths of 300 nm and 405 nm, respectively. 
The bandwidths for excitation and emission were set at 
2 nm and 5 nm, respectively. Titrations were carried out 
at 37 C in a quartz cuvette containing a starting volume of 
700 ml of solution consisting of 3 mM eDNA, 2 mM ATP, 
30 mM Tris-acetate (pH 7.5), 10 mM magnesium acetate 
and 0.1 mM DTT. Control titrations of protein into buffer 
lacking eDNA were used to correct for the contribution of 
intrinsic tryptophan fluorescence to signal. All data were 
corrected for dilution. Photobleaching and inner filter 
effects were assessed using standard procedures (19) and 
found to be negligible. </p>

<p>Electrophoretic mobility shift assays for 
Rad51-ssDNA interactions </p>

<p>Rad51-ssDNA interactions were analyzed by native 
agarose gel electrophoretic mobility shift assay (EMSA). 
A constant concentration of 30 mM uX174 ssDNA was 
mixed with varying amounts of wild-type or mutant 
Rad51 protein in 30 mM Tris-acetate (pH 7.5), 5 mM 
MgCl 2 , 0 or 2 mM ATP depending on the experiment 
and 0-1000 mM NaCl depending on the experiment, in a 
total volume of 20 ml and incubated at 37 C for 30 min. 
Immediately after incubation sample loading buffer [3 ml 
of 40 mM Tris-acetate (pH 7.5), 50% glycerol and a trace 
of bromphenol blue] was added to each reaction, and the 
protein-ssDNA complexes were separated from unbound 
ssDNA by electrophoresis through 0.8% agarose gels in 
TAE buffer (40 mM Tris-acetate, pH 8.0, 2 mM EDTA) at 
120 V for 2 h and were visualized by ethidium bromide 
staining. </p>

<p>EMSAs for nucleotide binding </p>

<p>The binding of radiolabeled nucleotide (a-[ 32 P]-ATP or -
ADP) to Rad51 in the presence/absence of ssDNA was 
monitored by native polyacrylamide gel EMSA. In total 
reaction volumes of 20 ml, a constant concentration of 
10 mM a-[ 32 P]-ATP (10 mCi/ml final specific activity) was 
incubated with 10 mM wild-type or mutant Rad51 protein </p>

<p>in the presence or absence of 30 mM uX174 ssDNA. 
Reaction buffer contained 30 mM Tris-acetate (pH 7.5), 
10 mg/ml BSA, 1 mM DTT, 10 mM magnesium acetate, 
30 mM KCl and 5% glycerol. Otherwise identical control 
reactions lacking protein, lacking both ssDNA and 
protein, or lacking nucleotide (background control) were 
carried out in parallel. Reactions mixtures were incubated 
at 37 C for 2 h. Samples were then loaded onto 12% 
non-denaturing polyacrylamide gels in a modified buffer 
containing 30 mM Tris-acetate (pH 7.5), 10 mM magne-
sium acetate and 30 mM KCl. The gels were made from a 
75:1 mixture of acrylamide to bisacrylamide in the 
modified buffer. Complexes were separated from free nu-
cleotide by electrophoresis at 150 V for 2 h. The gels were 
dried and exposed to a K-screen (Kodak) and analyzed in 
a <rs type="software">Bio-Rad Personal Molecular Imager-FX with Quantity 
One</rs> software v4.5.1. Concentrations of bound and free 
nucleotide (N bound and N free , respectively) were calculated 
according to the equations N bound = N total I bound / 
(I bound +I free ) and N free = N total I free /(I bound +I free ), where 
N total is the total nucleotide concentration (10 mM), 
I bound is the phosphorimage intensity of the bound 
nucleotide spot in a given lane, and I free is the 
phosphorimage intensity of the free nucleotide spot in 
the same lane. </p>

<p>ATPase assays </p>

<p>Steady-state rates of ATP hydrolysis were measured using 
thin-layer chromatography (TLC) assays. Reactions at 
37 C contained 30 mM MES (pH 6.2), 6 mM MgCl 2 , 
30 mM KCl, 1 mM DTT and 0.1 mg/ml BSA in a final 
volume of 50 ml. The monovalent salt concentration was 
increased to 80 mM in certain reactions by the addition of 
50 mM NaCl. In addition the reaction mixtures contained 
2.0 mM wild-type or mutant Rad51 protein and 12 mM 
uX174 ssDNA. Reactions were initiated by the addition of 
a-[ 32 P]-ATP to a final concentration of 3 mM (10 mCi/ml 
final specific activity). Aliquots (8 ml) were removed at 
various time points and quenched with 8 mM EDTA 
and 1% SDS (final concentrations). Quenched samples 
were spotted out at 1 ml volume onto PEI-cellulose TLC 
plates (20 Â 20 cm) at 1-cm intervals. After all the samples 
were spotted and dried the TLC plates were developed 
with 0.75 M KH 2 PO 4 and allowed to air dry. The TLC 
plates were exposed for 1.5 h to a K-screen (Kodak) and 
scanned by a Bio-Rad Personal Molecular Imager-FX. 
Quantification of the phosphorimage was performed by 
Quantity One v4.5.1 (Bio-Rad) software and subsequently 
fit using <rs id="software-1" type="software">KaleidaGraph</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">v 3.6.2</rs> (Synergy Software). The 
TLC assay was also used to measure the hydrolysis of 
ATP in samples identical to those used in nucleotide-
binding EMSA experiments. Following incubation at 
37 C for 2 h, 8 ml aliquots were removed and quenched 
with 8 mM EDTA and 1% SDS, spotted onto TLC 
plates and developed as described above. </p>

<p>DNA strand exchange assays </p>

<p>DNA strand exchange reactions using uX174 DNA sub-
strates were carried out as described (20) with minor 
changes. Reactions were assembled as follows (final </p>



<p>volume 12.5 ml, final concentrations are given): 11 mM 
wild-type or mutant Rad51 protein, 33 mM circular 
uX174 ssDNA and 2.5 mM ATP were preincubated for 
5 min at 37 C in buffer containing 35 mM MOPS (pH 7.2), 
100 mg/ml bovine serum albumin, 1 mM DTT, 3 mM 
MgCl 2 and 10 mM KCl. To each reaction 1.65 mM RPA 
was added and the mixture was incubated at 37 C for 
another 10 min. Finally, 33 mM PstI-linearized uX174 
dsDNA and 4 mM spermidine (pH 7.2) were added to 
start the reaction. After incubation at 37 C for the 
indicated time, the reactions were stopped by adding 
SDS and proteinase K to final concentrations of 1% and 
0.5 mg/ml, respectively, followed by 15-min incubation at 
37 C. The deproteinized samples were mixed with loading 
buffer (3 ml of 40 mM Tris-acetate, pH 7.5, 50% glycerol 
and a trace of bromphenol blue) and electrophoresed on a 
0.8% agarose gel in TAE buffer at 120 V for 2 h. The 
DNA substrates and strand exchange products were 
visualized by exposure to ultraviolet light after staining 
by ethidium bromide. Results were quantified by 
measuring the intensity of the nicked circle product 
band and joint molecules in a Bio-Rad Personal 
Molecular Imager-FX using Quantity One v4.5.1 
software. </p>

<p>RPA displacement assays </p>

<p>The ability of wild-type and mutant Rad51 proteins to 
displace RPA from ssDNA was monitored by the 
recovery of intrinsic RPA tryptophan fluorescence in 
the free compared with the ssDNA-bound state as 
described (21). RPA fluorescence was monitored continu-
ously in the PTI Quantamaster QM-6 fluorometer at 
excitation and emission wavelengths of 290 and 345 nm, 
respectively. The bandwidths for excitation and emission 
were set at 2 and 5 nm, respectively. Reactions were 
carried out at 37 C in a quartz cuvette containing 700 ml 
final volume of 30 mM Tris-acetate (pH 7.5), 5 mM 
magnesium acetate, 50 mM KCl, 1 mM DTT, 2.5 mM 
ATP, 0.25 mM RPA and 5 mM uX174 ssDNA. The mono-
valent salt concentration was increased to 100 mM in 
certain experiments by the addition of 50 mM NaCl. 
This mixture was pre-incubated for 3 min while monitor-
ing the starting fluorescence signal of RPA-ssDNA. 
Then the reaction was started by adding 2 mM of 
wild-type or mutant Rad51 and resulting changes in fluor-
escence signal were monitored over time. Data were cor-
rected for the residual fluorescence of Rad51 protein 
and for the effects of dilution, photobleaching and inner 
filter effects as described (18,22,23). A control reaction 
lacking Rad51 but containing all other components 
including Rad51 storage buffer was used to establish the 
minimum fluorescence signal of the RPA-ssDNA mixture 
(F 0 ), which was subtracted from all data. A separate 
control reaction lacking ssDNA was used to establish 
the maximum fluorescence signal of free RPA, against 
which all data were normalized. Thus the value F -F 0 
has a minimum value of zero representing RPA that is 
fully saturated with ssDNA, and a maximum value 
of one representing RPA that is completely displaced 
from ssDNA. </p>

<p>Crystallization procedures </p>

<p>Rad51 H352Y crystals were grown in hanging drop by 
vapor diffusion. Rad51 H352Y protein from storage 
buffer was dialyzed into 20 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 
1 mM DTT and concentrated to 20 mg/ml using vivaspin 
(Sartorius Stedim Biotech) ultrafiltration spin columns. By 
mixing 1:1 (v/v) of well solution and protein solution the 
protein was crystallized using the hanging drop method at 
a temperature of 18 C. Optimal yet small crystals were 
obtained using reservoir solution containing 35% (v/v) 
pentaerythritol propoxylate (5/4 PO/OH), 300 mM KCl 
and 50 mM HEPES (pH 7.5 adjusted by KOH). </p>

<p>X-ray diffraction and structure determination </p>

<p>Diffraction data were collected at beamline 23-ID-B at the 
APS synchrotron at a wavelength of 1.03 A ˚ , and reduced 
using HKL2000 (HKL Research) (24) with statistics 
given in Table 1. EPMR 8.10 (25) readily identified a mo-
lecular replacement solution using a protomer of the 
Rad51-I345T structure (11) (PDB code 1SZP) as the 
search model. The model, containing a single protomer 
in the asymmetric unit, was rebuilt with Coot (26) into a 
composite omit map generated after overall B-factor and 
rigid-body refinement but prior to any other refinement of 
the model. After several rounds of crystallographic refine-
ment with CNS 1.21 (27), an alternate conformation of the 
Tyr352 sidechain was identified and built in. The occu-
pancy of the carboxyl group of Glu221 was reduced to 
0.5 based on inspection of residual Fourier maps, 
although no other single conformation for this group 
was apparent. The peptide linkage between residues 280-
281 was initially modeled as trans; Residual Fourier maps 
clearly revealed that the linkage was cis, and the model 
was corrected. A simple modification to the protein par-
ameters file in the standard distribution of CNS 1.21 was 
necessary to allow for the existence of non-prolyl cis 
peptide linkages. A peak of strong density seen in the 
P-loop of the protein was modeled as a chloride ion as 
there was no phosphate or sulfate in the crystallization 
mixture. There was no clear density for the N-terminal 
extension (residues 1-77), nor for the DNA-binding 
loops 1 (288-293) and 2 (328-347). The model, after in-
clusion of 79 waters and three chloride ions, gave final 
refinement statistics as listed in Table 1. A representative 
F o -F c simulated annealing omit map in the region of 
Tyr352 is shown in Supplementary Figure S1. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Effects of mutations of His352 on Rad51 DNA strand 
exchange activity </p>

<p>Purified Rad51 H352A, H352Y and wild-type proteins 
were tested for the ability to catalyze DNA strand 
exchange reactions using full-length uX174 DNA sub-
strates in the presence of RPA protein. Under these con-
ditions, strand exchange requires the formation of 
catalytically competent presynaptic filaments on the long 
(5.4 kb) uX174 ssDNA substrate, which in turn requires 
Rad51 to successfully compete with RPA for binding sites </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 14 4893 </p>

<p>on ssDNA. A schematic of the DNA strand exchange 
reaction is shown in Figure 1A. Wild-type Rad51 
promotes a strong DNA strand exchange reaction as 
shown by the appearance of nicked circle and joint 
molecule products over the 2-h timecourse of the 
reaction (Figure 1B). The H352A mutant retains DNA 
strand exchange activity under these conditions, but its 
activity is much lower than wild-type (Figure 1B). No 
nicked circle product is visible in reactions with the 
H352Y mutant (Figure 1B). Strand exchange results 
were quantified by fluorescence imaging of the nicked 
circle band (Figure 1C). Results show that the rate of 
nicked circle product formation catalyzed by H352A is 
reduced $4-fold compared with wild-type, while that of 
H352Y is reduced by at least 25-fold compared with 
wild-type. </p>

<p>Linear ssDNA formation is a poor indicator of 
Rad51-catalyzed DNA strand exchange activity, since 
previous studies showed that the concentration of this 
species in reaction mixtures is non-stoichiometric with 
respect to the concentration of nicked circular 
heteroduplex (34,42). In our experiments, linear ssDNA 
increases anomalously in reactions with H352A and 
H352Y (Figure 1B, lanes 6-10 and 11-15), which does 
not correlate with the observed low rates of heteroduplex 
formation. We considered that the linear ssDNA present 
in these reaction mixtures could be the result of a 
contaminating nuclease activity, although this does not 
appear to be the case since all of the Rad51 and RPA 
stocks used in this study were nuclease-free according to 
sensitive criteria described in 'Materials and Methods' 
section. We conclude that the anomalous appearance of 
linear ssDNA in these reactions is most likely caused by 
random strand breaks in the ssDNA that can occur during 
sample processing steps. </p>

<p>Effects of His352 mutations on Rad51-ssDNA 
interactions </p>

<p>Both H352A and H352Y mutants show severe defects in 
DNA strand exchange reactions, but the underlying mech-
anisms could differ in detail. To determine whether 
changes in protein-ssDNA interactions contribute to 
strand exchange deficiency, we compared the 
ssDNA-binding properties of both mutants and 
wild-type Rad51. The binding site sizes of wild-type, 
H352A and H352Y on ssDNA were quantified using 
etheno-DNA (eDNA) fluorescence enhancement assays. 
Under low-salt conditions, all three enzyme species bind 
tightly to eDNA in the presence of ATP, and enhance 
eDNA fluorescence by 3.1-to 3.3-fold at saturation 
(Figure 2). This degree of fluorescence enhancement is 
characteristic of proteins that extend and unstack the 
ssDNA (15,28). All three proteins yielded very similar 
titration profiles (Figure 2), which were reproducible 
between different batches of eDNA and protein. 
Titration endpoints were estimated from the intersection 
of asymptotic lines drawn through the ascending and 
plateau portions of each curve, and used to calculate the 
value of the binding site size parameter, n. The calculated 
values in nucleotide residues/protomer were n = 3.3 ± 0.3 
for wild-type, n = 2.9 ± 0.2 for H352A, and n = 3.1 ± 0.1 
for H352Y. Therefore mutations of His352 do not signifi-
cantly affect the apparent ssDNA-binding site size. The 
overall average for all three proteins was n = 3.0 ± 0.4, 
which is indicated by the asymptotic lines drawn in 
Figure 2, with the vertical line indicating the enzyme con-
centration at the average endpoint. The measured binding 
site size of 3-nt residues is similar to previous estimates for 
wild-type Rad51, including n &amp; 4 from etheno-DNA titra-
tions (17) and n &amp; 3 from DNA strand exchange concen-
tration optima (29). 
The similar binding site sizes do not rule out the possi-
bility that His352 mutations alter other features of 
Rad51-ssDNA interactions such as affinity, cooperativity, 
ATP dependence, or salt effects. Therefore protein inter-
actions with uX174 ssDNA were qualitatively assessed </p>

<p>Table 1. Data collection and model refinement statistics </p>

<p>Data collection 
Wavelength (A ˚ ) 
1.03320 
Space group 
P6 1 
Unit cell [a, b, c (A ˚ )] 
78.905, 78.905, 130.333 
Resolution (A ˚ ) 
50-2.50 (2.59-2.50) a 
No. of total reflections 
152140 
No. of unique reflections 
15937 (1566) 
Redundancy 
9.6 (5.3) 
Completeness (%) 
99.7 (98.2) 
&lt;I&gt;/&lt;(I)&gt; 
19.8 (2.0) 
R merge </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>13.0 (66.2) 
Refinement 
No. protein atoms 
2269 
No. chloride atoms 
3 
No. solvent atoms 
79 
R cryst </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>20.03 
R free </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>24.57 
Estimated coordinate error (A ˚ ) e 
0.310/0.385 
Deviations from ideal stereochemistry 
RMSD bonds (A ˚ ) 
0.0063 
RMSD angles ( 
) 
1.347 
RMSD B-factors (A ˚ 2 ) f 
1.370/1.825 
Average B-factors (A ˚ 2 ) g 
39.4/42.2/56.7 
Ramachandran plot analysis h 
Most favored (%) 
92.0 
Additionallly allowed (%) 
7.6 
Generously allowed (%) 
0.4 
Disallowed (%) 
0.0 
PDB ID 
3LDA </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Values in parentheses are for the highest resolution shell (2.59-2.50 A ˚ ). </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>R merge = AE(|I i -&lt;I&gt;|)/AE(I), where AE is over all reflections measured 
more than once, and &lt;I&gt; is the mean intensity of all measured obser-
vations equivalent to reflection I i . </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>R cryst = AE(|F obs -F calc |)/AE(F obs ), where AE is over all reflections used in 
refinement, F obs are the observed diffraction amplitudes, and F calc are 
their corresponding calculated amplitudes from inverse Fourier trans-
formation of the model. </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>R free is defined identically to R cryst , but involves 9% of the measured 
reflections not used in refinement and set aside for cross-validation 
purposes (38). </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>Estimated coordinate error is via a Luzzati plot (39) using all reflec-
tions and based on cross-validated reflections only. </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>RMSD in B-factor between covalently-bonded main chain atoms and 
side chain atoms. </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>Average B-factors for protein/solvent/chloride ions (40). </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>Ramacchandran plot analysis is from PROCHECK (41). </p>



<p>by agarose gel EMSA while varying ATP, salt concentra-
tion and protein concentration parameters (Figure 3). 
The salt-sensitivities of protein-ssDNA interactions 
provide a means for comparing the relative stabilities of 
the mutant vs. wild-type complexes. The top row of panels 
(Figure 3a-e) shows experiments performed with 
wild-type Rad51. In low-salt buffer containing 30 mM 
Tris-acetate (pH 7.5), 5 mM MgCl 2 , and no NaCl, </p>

<p>Rad51 complex formation on uX174 ssDNA strongly 
requires ATP, since little ssDNA mobility shift is 
observed in its absence (apo conditions-Figure 3a), 
even at the highest protein concentration where Rad51 is 
in 3-fold molar excess over potential ssDNA-binding sites. 
Under otherwise identical conditions, the addition of 
2 mM ATP causes a gradual shift to slower migrating 
species with increasing Rad51 concentration (Figure 3b), </p>

<p>Figure 1. DNA strand exchange activities of wild-type and mutant Rad51 proteins. DNA strand exchange assays were carried out using full-length 
uX174 DNA substrates as described under 'Materials and Methods' section. (A) Schematic of in vitro DNA strand exchange reaction, showing 
interconversion of single-and double-stranded DNA species. (B) Timecourses of DNA strand exchange reactions visualized by separating DNA 
substrates and products via agarose gel electrophoresis and staining with ethidium bromide. All reactions contained 33 mM each of uX174 circular 
ssDNA and uX174 linear dsDNA, 11 mM Rad51 enzyme, 1.65 mM RPA and 2.5 mM ATP (final concentrations). Other reaction components and 
assay conditions are described under 'Materials and Methods' section. Lanes 1-5, reaction with wild-type Rad51. Lanes 2-10, reaction with H352A 
Rad51 mutant. Lanes 11-15, reaction with H352Y Rad51 mutant. (C) Results of panel B quantified by fluorescence imaging. Data are averages from 
three separate experiments. Filled circles, wild-type Rad51. Open squares, H352A Rad51 mutant. Filled triangles, H352Y Rad51 mutant. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 14 4895 </p>

<p>indicative of Rad51-ssDNA presynaptic filament forma-
tion. These results are consistent with previous reports of 
ATP-stabilized ssDNA binding by Rad51 (17). In the 
presence of 2 mM ATP, Rad51-ssDNA complexes are 
stable at the moderate salt concentration of 150 mM 
NaCl (Figure 3c), but mobility shift decreases in 
500 mM NaCl and is undetectable in 1000 mM NaCl 
(Figure 3d-e). Therefore wild-type Rad51 forms 
ATP-stabilized complexes on ssDNA that are moderately 
salt-resistant. 
The middle row of panels (Figure 3f-j) shows experi-
ments with the Rad51 H352Y mutant. The results demon-
strate major differences in the ssDNA-binding properties 
of H352Y and wild-type. Like wild-type, H352Y forms 
ATP-stabilized complexes on ssDNA. The ATP require-
ment is not absolute, however, since a small amount of 
mobility shift is detectable at the highest H352Y concen-
tration under apo, low-salt conditions (Figure 3f). The 
addition of 2 mM ATP leads to a much greater degree 
of ssDNA mobility shift that, remarkably, persists at all 
salt concentrations tested (0-1000 mM) (Figure 3g-j). This 
mobility shift is not a result of non-specific aggregation 
since no material appears in the wells and solutions are 
non-turbid at all salt concentrations (data not shown). 
Therefore the H352Y mutation induces a more </p>

<p>Figure 3. Electrophoretic mobility shift assays for ssDNA-binding activities of wild-type and mutant Rad51 proteins-effects of ATP and salt. 
Protein-ssDNA complexes were assembled at a constant concentration of 30 mM uX174 ssDNA and at variable concentrations of 0-30 mM wild-type 
or mutant Rad51 enzyme as described under 'Materials and Methods' section. Complexes were assembled in buffer containing 30 mM Tris-acetate, 
pH 7.5, 5 mM MgCl 2 , with or without ATP and NaCl as indicated. Samples were electrophoresed on agarose gels and visualized by staining with 
ethidium bromide. Top row-experiments with wild-type Rad51. Nucleotide and salt conditions were as follows: (a) 0 mM ATP (apo conditions), 
0 mM NaCl; (b) 2 mM ATP, 0 mM NaCl; (c) 2 mM ATP, 150 mM NaCl; (d) 2 mM ATP, 500 mM NaCl; (e) 2 mM ATP, 1000 mM NaCl. Middle 
row-experiments with Rad51 H352Y mutant. Nucleotide and salt conditions were as follows: (f) 0 mM ATP (apo conditions), 0 mM NaCl; (g) 2 mM 
ATP, 0 mM NaCl; (h) 2 mM ATP, 150 mM NaCl; (i) 2 mM ATP, 500 mM NaCl; (j) 2 mM ATP, 1000 mM NaCl. Bottom row-experiments with 
Rad51 H352A mutant. Nucleotide and salt conditions were as follows: (k) 0 mM ATP (apo conditions), 0 mM NaCl; (l) 2 mM ATP, 0 mM NaCl; (m) 
2 mM ATP, 20 mM NaCl; (n) 2 mM ATP, 150 mM NaCl; (o) 2 mM ATP, 500 mM NaCl. Note the lower NaCl concentrations used with H352A 
compared with H352Y and wild-type Rad51. </p>

<p>Figure 2. ssDNA-binding site size determination for wild-type and 
mutant Rad51 proteins. Etheno-modified M13mp19 ssDNA (eDNA) 
was titrated with Rad51 wild-type (open circles), H352A (filled 
squares), or H352Y (crosses) under low-salt conditions while monitor-
ing the enhancement of eDNA fluorescence as described under 
'Materials and Methods' section. Solutions contained 3 mM eDNA 
and 2 mM ATP in buffer consisting of 30 mM Tris-acetate (pH 7.5), 
10 mM magnesium acetate and 0.1 mM DTT. The apparent binding site 
sizes of proteins on this single-stranded lattice are estimated from the 
titration endpoints. The average endpoint is indicated in this figure by 
the intersection of the solid asymptotic lines, with the vertical line 
showing the protein concentration at the average endpoint, correspond-
ing to one Rad51 protomer per three eDNA nucleotide residues. </p>



<p>salt-resistant, higher-affinity form of ssDNA binding than 
is seen with wild-type Rad51. The H352Y-ssDNA 
complexes observed at the highest protein concentrations 
have a tendency to migrate slower with increasing salt 
concentration (Figure 3h-j), which could be an indication 
of complex morphology change such as increasing 
filament stiffness (30,31). H352Y-ssDNA interactions 
show characteristics of all-or-none binding-this is par-
ticularly noticeable at higher protein concentrations in ex-
periments at 500 and 1000 mM NaCl, where highly shifted 
and free ssDNA co-exist (Figure 3i-j), which raises the 
possibility of enhanced cooperativity in this mutant. 
This pattern is never observed with wild-type Rad51, 
which within its stable salt range shows gradually slower 
migration with increasing protein concentration, and no 
free ssDNA, suggesting relatively distributive binding 
(Figure 3b-d). 
The bottom row of panels (Figure 3k-o) shows experi-
ments with the Rad51 H352A mutant. Like wild-type 
and H352Y, H352A forms ATP-stabilized complexes 
on ssDNA. Like H352Y, the ATP requirement for 
H352A-ssDNA binding is not absolute, since a small 
amount of mobility shift is detectable at the highest 
H352A concentration under apo, low-salt conditions 
(Figure 3k). The addition of 2 mM ATP leads to a much 
greater degree of ssDNA mobility shift, but complex for-
mation occurs only at relatively low salt concentrations, 
0-20 mM NaCl (Figure 3l and m). Complex formation is 
reduced in 150 mM NaCl, and abolished in 500 mM NaCl 
(Figure 3n and o). Therefore in contrast to H352Y, the 
H352A mutant exhibits much weaker ssDNA-binding 
activity than wild-type Rad51. Also, at permissive salt 
concentrations the binding of H352A resembles the dis-
tributive pattern of wild-type more than the apparent co-
operative pattern of H352Y. </p>

<p>Effects of His352 mutations on steady-state rates 
of ATP hydrolysis </p>

<p>To further assess the functional defect of H352A and 
H352Y mutants, steady-state rates of ATPase activity 
were measured in the presence and absence of ssDNA. 
Experiments were performed under approximate V max 
conditions for wild-type Rad51-3 mM ATP and a 
2-fold excess of uX174 ssDNA-binding sites over 
enzyme. Reactions were carried out at pH 6.2 to 
maximize the ATPase activities of H352A and H352Y 
(13,32). Results are shown in Figure 4. Generally 
speaking, the relative order of ATPase activity is 
wild-type &gt; H352A &gt; H352Y, although each activity is 
condition-dependent as shown in Figure 4. In the presence 
of 50 mM salt, wild-type Rad51 shows the highest level of 
ssDNA-dependent ATPase activity, which is 23-fold 
higher than its basal ATPase rate attained in the absence 
of ssDNA (Figure 4). The rate of $0.65 min -1 measured 
for wild-type Rad51 under these conditions is consistent 
with published results (13,33,34). Wild-type Rad51's 
ssDNA-dependent ATPase rate decreases only slightly as 
the salt concentration is increased to 80 mM (Figure 4). 
Like wild-type, the ATPase activity of H352A is strongly 
stimulated by ssDNA in 50 mM salt, although its basal </p>

<p>and ssDNA-dependent rates are only $40% of wild-type 
(Figure 4). Strikingly, increasing the salt concentration 
from 50 to 80 mM inhibits H352A's ssDNA-dependent 
ATPase activity by $12-fold (Figure 4). Therefore the 
ssDNA-dependent ATPase activity of H352A is dramat-
ically more salt-sensitive than that of wild-type Rad51. 
The ATPase properties of H352Y differ dramatically 
from both wild-type and H352A in several ways: The 
basal rate of hydrolysis in 50 mM NaCl is $2.6-fold 
higher than wild-type, and is not stimulated by ssDNA 
(Figure 4). In fact ssDNA appears to slightly inhibit 
ATP hydrolysis by H352Y, as does increasing salt 
(Figure 4). 
We note that the ATPase rates observed for Rad51 
wild-type, H352A and H352Y in the presence of ssDNA 
are essentially independent of ssDNA concentration as 
long as the ssDNA is saturating with respect to enzyme 
concentration (J. Chen and S. Morrical, unpublished 
results). We also note that our results differ from those 
of a previous study wherein a 63-mer oligonucleotide 
appeared to stimulate the ATPase activity of H352Y 
(13). To explore this difference, we repeated the ATPase 
assays in Figure 4 using a 62-mer random-sequence 
ssDNA oligo in place of 5400-base uX174 ssDNA. 
The results were essentially identical to those shown in 
Figure 4 (data not shown). In addition our results were 
highly reproducible using two different preparations of 
H352Y. Therefore the different results obtained in our 
study and (13) are not due to differences in ssDNA 
length, but could conceivably be due to differences in 
other reaction parameters such as the higher ATP and 
magnesium concentrations used in (13). </p>

<p>Nucleotide binding and turnover by Rad51 and mutants </p>

<p>We investigated whether the reduced ATPase activities of 
Rad51 mutants are caused by defects in nucleotide binding </p>

<p>Figure 4. Steady-state rates of ATP hydrolysis by wild-type and 
mutant Rad51 proteins. ATP hydrolysis was measured by TLC radio-
metric assay as described under 'Materials and Methods' section. 
Reaction mixtures contained 3 mM ATP and 2.0 mM of either Rad51 
wild-type, H352A, or H352Y as indicated below the figure. Reactions 
were performed either in the absence (gray bars) or in the presence 
(white bars) of 12 mM uX174 ssDNA. Monovalent salt was added to 
reactions at the concentrations indicated below the figure. All other 
buffer components and assay conditions were as described under 
'Materials and Methods' section. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 14 4897 </p>

<p>or turnover. Experiments were performed under 
'single-turnover' conditions in which equal concentrations 
of protein and a-labeled ATP probe were incubated in the 
presence or absence of excess ssDNA. Probe binding was 
then measured by native polyacrylamide gel EMSA, while 
probe hydrolysis in identical samples was measured by 
TLC (Figure 5). All experiments were performed under 
salt conditions permissive for H352A catalytic activity. 
As shown in Figure 5A, the electrophoretic mobility of 
free a-labeled ATP (Figure 5A, lanes 1-2) is distinct 
from that of the protein-nucleotide complexes that form 
either in the absence (lanes 3-5) or presence (lanes 6-8) of </p>

<p>ssDNA. The Rad51-ADP complex appears to dissociate 
from the ssDNA as suggested by the similar mobility shifts 
seen in the presence/absence of ssDNA (Figure 5A) and by 
previous studies (1,3,35). This allowed quantification of 
the nucleotide-binding data in Figure 5A by 
phosphorimaging, the results of which are shown in 
Figure 5B. In the absence of ssDNA, H352A has 
$3-fold weaker nucleotide-binding activity than 
wild-type, whereas H352Y binds nucleotide slightly 
better than wild-type (Figure 5B). ssDNA stimulates nu-
cleotide binding &gt;2.5-fold for wild-type and &gt;5-fold for 
H352A, but has little effect on nucleotide binding by </p>

<p>Figure 5. Binding and hydrolysis of stoichiometric ATP by Rad51 and mutants. ATP binding and hydrolysis was measured at a 1:1 concentration 
ratio of protein to ATP. Nucleotide binding was measured by polyacrylamide gel EMSA, and hydrolysis was measured by TLC, as described under 
'Materials and Methods' section. (A) 10 mM wild-type or mutant Rad51, as indicated, was incubated with 10 mM a-[ 32 P]-ATP (10 mC i /ml) for 2 h 
either in the absence (lanes 3-5) or presence (lanes 6-8) of 30 mM uX174 ssDNA. Control experiments lacking enzyme or lacking both enzyme and 
ssDNA are shown in lanes 1 and 2, respectively. Samples were electrophoresed on native 12% polyacrylamide gels to separate free from bound 
nucleotide, which were detected and quantified by phosphorimaging. Other buffer components and assay conditions are described under 'Materials 
and Methods' section. (B) The percentage of bound nucleotide in (A), was quantified for each form of Rad51 in the absence (gray bars) and presence 
(white bars) of ssDNA. (C) The percentage of ATP hydrolyzed in samples identical to those analyzed in (A), was measured for each form of Rad51 
protein in the absence (gray bars) and presence (white bars) of ssDNA. </p>



<p>H352Y (Figure 5B). Even when stimulated by ssDNA, 
H352A-nucleotide binding remains weaker than 
wild-type (Figure 5B). Therefore H352A appears to bind 
nucleotide relatively weakly, but can still be stimulated by 
ssDNA, at least under low salt conditions. On the other 
hand nucleotide binding is relatively insensitive to ssDNA 
binding in H352Y. 
Figure 5C shows the percentage of ATP hydrolyzed 
during incubation of wild-type or mutant enzymes 
with stoichometric ATP. For wild-type Rad51, the per-
centage of ATP hydrolyzed (Figure 5C) closely parallels 
the percentage of nucleotide bound (Figure 5B) in both 
the absence and presence of ssDNA. This suggests 
that both free and ssDNA-bound Rad51 quantitatively 
hydrolyze bound ATP to ADP under these conditions, 
and subsequently remain in an ADP-bound state. Figure 
5C also shows that hydrolysis of ATP by H352A is 
strongly dependent on ssDNA (13-fold stimulation) 
under single-turnover conditions; similar to what was 
observed in steady-state reactions under multiple-turnover 
(V max ) conditions (Figure 4). Comparison of Figure 5B 
and C indicates that most of the ATP bound by H352A 
in the absence of ssDNA is not hydrolyzed, whereas most 
of the substrate is hydrolyzed in the presence of ssDNA. 
The single-turnover conditions may allow H352A to 
remain bound to ADP following catalysis (Figure 5B 
and C), although the mutant is clearly capable of 
multiple turnovers as demonstrated in Figure 4. 
H352Y exhibits the highest level of ssDNA-independent 
ATP hydrolysis and is weakly stimulated by ssDNA 
(&lt;1.5-fold) under single-turnover conditions (Figure 5C). 
Comparison of Figure 5B and C suggests that similar to 
wild-type Rad51, both free and ssDNA-bound H352Y 
quantitatively hydrolyze bound ATP to ADP and 
remain in the ADP-bound state thereafter. Taken 
together, the data in Figures 4 and 5 indicate that 
H352Y is proficient in catalyzing a single round of ATP 
hydrolysis, but deficient in performing multiple rounds of 
ATP hydrolysis. </p>

<p>Effects of His352 mutations on RPA displacement 
from ssDNA </p>

<p>RPA has a high level of intrinsic tryptophan fluorescence 
that is quenched $40% upon binding to ssDNA, whereas 
Rad51 has no tryptophan residues and a low intrinsic 
fluorescence that is not quenched by ssDNA (21). These 
properties have been exploited to measure the displace-
ment of RPA by Rad51 during presynaptic filament 
assembly, by following the increase in RPA tryptophan 
fluorescence upon addition of Rad51 to RPA-ssDNA 
(21). We used this technique to compare the abilities of 
wild-type and mutant Rad51 proteins to displace RPA 
protein from ssDNA (Figure 6). Control reactions dem-
onstrate the maximum fluorescence signal for free RPA in 
red, and the minimum signal for intact RPA-ssDNA 
complex in black (Figure 6B). In the presence of ATP, 
the addition of wild-type Rad51 (Figure 6B, cyan) to 
pre-formed RPA-ssDNA causes a time-dependent 
increase in RPA fluorescence, consistent with published 
results (21,36). RPA displacement by wild-type Rad51 </p>

<p>approaches 95% and is $90% complete within the first 
5 min of the reaction (Figure 6B, cyan). The RPA fluores-
cence increase occurs with multi-phasic kinetics; i.e. there 
is a fast component of the reaction that is complete before 
signal acquisition occurs (dead time &amp;5 s) that accounts 
for $25% of the total signal change. A similar fluores-
cence burst was observed in an earlier study (21). The 
H352A mutant (Figure 6B, blue) also displaces RPA 
from ssDNA at low salt and in the presence of ATP, i.e. 
conditions in which H352A is catalytically active. The 
reaction with H352A is slower than wild-type, and the 
total extent of RPA displacement only approaches 75% 
over 35 min. Like wild-type, the RPA fluorescence increase 
caused by H352A includes an unresolved fast component 
(Figure 6B, blue). Raising the salt concentration from 50 
to 100 mM eliminates the slower component of RPA dis-
placement by H352A so that only the unresolved compo-
nent remains (Figure 6B, orange). Thus there is an 
immediate jump to $25% of the signal of free RPA 
upon addition of H352A, but the signal remains flat for 
35 min thereafter. No fluorescence change occurs upon 
addition of Rad51 and ATP to RPA in the absence of 
ssDNA (data not shown). One possible interpretation of 
these results is that Rad51 rapidly forms an intermediate 
complex with RPA-ssDNA (partial recovery of fluores-
cence) before slowly displacing RPA from ssDNA 
(complete recovery of fluorescence). According to this 
scenario, with H352A the slow displacement phase is in-
hibited by salt while the formation of the intermediate 
complex is unaffected. An alternative interpretation is </p>

<p>Figure 6. RPA displacement assays. (A) The displacement of RPA 
protein from ssDNA by Rad51 wild-type and mutant proteins was 
monitored by the increase in RPA tryptophan fluorescence as described 
under 'Materials and Methods' section. (B) Continuous fluorescence 
assays for RPA displacement. All reactions contained 2.5 mM ATP, 
0.25 mM RPA and 5 mM uX174 ssDNA, except for the 'RPA alone' 
control reaction (red) which lacked ssDNA. Reactions contained 2 mM 
of either wild-type (cyan), H352A (blue, orange), or H352Y (green) 
Rad51, except for the 'RPA alone' and 'RPA-ssDNA' (black) 
controls which lacked Rad51. All reactions contained 50 mM monova-
lent salt except for one reaction with H352A that contained 100 mM 
monovalent salt (orange). Other buffer components and reaction con-
ditions are described under 'Materials and Methods' section. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 14 4899 </p>

<p>that there are different populations of RPA-ssDNA in the 
reactions, some of which are easily disrupted by Rad51 
while others are more resistant. Further experimentation 
will be necessary to resolve between these and other 
models. 
The H352Y mutant (Figure 6B, green) does not remodel 
or displace RPA from ssDNA, since the fluorescence 
signal of RPA-ssDNA does not change upon addition 
of H352Y in the presence of ATP. Thus the intrinsically 
high ssDNA-binding affinity of H352Y is insufficient for 
RPA displacement from ssDNA. </p>

<p>Structure of the Rad51 H352Y mutant </p>

<p>Like the majority of RecA-like proteins, Rad51 H352Y 
crystallizes as a filament with 6 1 helical symmetry. 
Figure 7 (center) shows one helical turn of the Rad51 
H352Y filament containing six crystallographically identi-
cal subunits. The pitch of the filament, 130.3 A ˚ , places it in 
the 'high-pitch' category for this family of proteins. For 
comparison, Figure 7 (left) shows the structure of the 
Rad51 I345T filament (11) (PDB code 1SZP), and the 
two filaments are superimposed on the right of Figure 7. 
The two filaments are remarkably similar in overall struc-
ture even though the I345T filament is composed of 
dimers with 3 1 helical symmetry. The protomer of 
Rad51 H352Y is also remarkably similar to the protomers 
of the I345T crystal structure, with RMS residuals 
after superimposing all C-a atoms of 1.10 and 1.21 A ˚ 
(Figure 8A and B). The only significant variation in 
overall conformation between these protomers lies in the 
disposition of the 78-158 sub-domain, which rotates 
relative to the core of the protein. Omitting this 
sub-domain, which replaces the long N-terminal helix of 
the bacterial RecA proteins, the RMS residuals are cut 
nearly in half to 0.52 and 0.71 A ˚ for the two protomers 
of the I345T dimer. 
The active site in Rad51/RecA proteins is formed by 
two adjacent protomers of the filament, one of which 
contains the nucleotide-binding pocket with Walker A 
(P-loop) and Walker B motifs, the other providing one </p>

<p>wall of the cleft, with residue 352 located centrally on 
this latter surface. Since alternate protomers in the 
Rad51 I345T crystal structure are different, there are 
two different interfaces present in that filament. Both are 
very similar to the single protomer-protomer interface in 
H352Y: The 'A-D' dimer (named using the chain identi-
fiers within the 1SZP PDB file, with the first chain being 
the one that presents its nucleotide-binding pocket at the 
dimer interface) of I345T superimposes with an RMS 
residual of 1.47 A ˚ (Figure 8A), and the 'D-A' dimer super-
imposes with a residual of 1.05 A ˚ (Figure 8B) (using all 
C-a atoms but excluding the 78-158 sub-domain in both 
cases). Interestingly, if the 'A-D' dimer of I345T is 
superimposed on the H352Y dimer using only the core 
(residues 159-396) of the 'A' protomer, the 78-158 
sub-domain of the 'D' protomer (not used in the super-
position) overlays remarkably well (0.72 A ˚ RMS) on the 
corresponding sub-domain that bridges the dimer inter-
face of H352Y (Figure 8A). When only the core of the 
'D' protomer of the 'D-A' dimer is used, however, such 
a good overlap of the 78-158 sub-domains is not obtained 
(1.53 A ˚ RMS) (Figure 8B). 
The mutated residue, Tyr352, is seen to adopt two con-
formations in the H352Y crystal structure with approxi-
mately equal occupancy (Figure 9A and B). One of these is 
in nearly the same conformation as His352 of protomer D 
in the I345T structure; the second conformation of Tyr352 
is substantially different from any of the others, involving 
changes to the backbone that allow the sidechain to lie 
almost parallel to the axis of the a-helix that precedes it. 
In the former conformation, Tyr352 forms a hydrogen 
bond to the carboxyl sidechain of Glu221 (2.6 A ˚ ) of the 
adjacent protomer, the putative nucleophilic activator for 
ATP hydrolysis. In the latter conformation, the tyrosine 
packs against Phe187 and Thr223 of the adjacent 
protomer. Other than a difference in rotamer for Phe187 
and a concomitant shift in Arg188, sidechains in the active 
sites of the H352Y and I345T structures are essentially the 
same. 
Surprisingly, the dimers comprising the active site of 
Rad51 superimpose remarkably well on dimers of the 
E. coli RecA-DNA crystal structures (4) (Figures 8C and 
9C), with an RMS residual of 2.13 A ˚ for 317 C-a atoms of 
the RecA-ssDNA-ADP-AlF4 complex (PDB code 
3CMW.) In contrast, the Rad51 dimers do not superim-
pose well on dimers of the DNA-free form of E. coli RecA 
(4) (Figure 8D). The Walker A/B motifs are in nearly an 
identical overall conformation, with an RMS residual of 
0.58 A ˚ for the 13 C-a atoms, despite the presence of a 
bound ADP-AlF 4 in the RecA-ssDNA structure and 
only a chloride ion in the P-loop of the Rad51 H352Y 
structure (Figure 10A). The sidechain of the putative cata-
lytic glutamate (Glu221 in Rad51, Glu96 in RecA) is 
located similarly in these structures. Sidechains of some 
key residues in the active site region are significantly dif-
ferent, however, with potential mechanistic implications. 
The conformation of Phe187 in Rad51 H352Y, which is 
in the middle of the Walker A (P-loop) motif, sterically 
overlaps with the AlF 4 moiety that mimics the g-phosphate 
of an ATP in the RecA-ssDNA-ADP-AlF4 complex 
(Figure 10A and Supplementary Figure 2). A similar </p>

<p>Figure 7. The H352Y interface mutant of yeast Rad51 (center, blue) 
forms a 6 1 helical filament with a pitch of 130 A ˚ . In comparison, the 
I345T mutant of this protein (left, green and gold, PDB code 1SZP) 
forms a filament of the same pitch but as a 3 1 helix of dimers. Despite 
the difference in helical symmetry, the filaments superimpose remark-
ably well (right.) Both proteins crystallized in the nucleotide-free state. </p>

<p>4900 Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 14 </p>

<p>conformation of Phe187 and subsequent steric overlap also 
occurs in protomer D of Rad51 I345T (Figure 10C); in 
protomer A, Phe187 is swung out but still sterically 
excludes the g-phosphate (Figure 10B). The equivalent 
residue in RecA, Glu68, points away from the P-loop 
pocket. 
At the end of the Walker B motif, the peptide linkage 
between the highly conserved Asp280 and Ser281 residues 
is in the relatively rare cis conformation (i.e. with both the 
backbone carbonyl oxygen and amide hydrogen on the 
same side of the amide linkage) in both the Rad51 
H352Y (Figure 11B) and I345T structures, as it is in 
nearly all crystal structures of RecA family proteins 
except those which have DNA bound. In the cis conform-
ation (as represented by the Rad51 H352Y structure in 
Figure 11B), the backbone amide NH of the cis peptide 
linkage hydrogen bonds to the hydroxyl sidechain of 
Thr220, the residue preceding the putative catalytic 
Glu221. No such bond is formed involving the trans 
backbone amide NH in the RecA-DNA complexes (rep-
resented by 3CMW, with similar interactions in the other 
RecA-DNA complexes) (Figure 11A, and shown in super-
position with Rad51 H352Y in Figure 11C). Interactions 
of the backbone carbonyl of this linkage differ markedly 
between the cis and trans states: In Rad51, the cis carbonyl 
hydrogen bonds to the backbone amide of residue 220, 
whereas in the RecA-DNA complex it forms a hydrogen </p>

<p>bond to the backbone amide of Glu96 (the putative cata-
lytic residue in RecA.) Ser281/145 undergoes a major con-
formational rearrangement in going from the cis to trans 
state: In both states it bonds to the carboxyl of the catalytic 
glutamate, but in the cis state the serine is shifted away 
from the P-loop, thus pulling the carboxyl group away 
from the active site (Figure 11A and C); whereas in the 
trans state in the RecA-DNA complex, the equivalent 
Ser145 is pushed towards the P-loop and makes very 
close contact (2.42 A ˚ ) with the carboxyl group of Glu96, 
resulting in a shift of this putative nucleophilic activator 
toward the g-phosphate of the ATP (Figure 11B and C). 
Furthermore, as a consequence of the backbone geometry 
imposed by the cis/trans linkage, residues 146-148 in the 
trans state in RecA-DNA are shifted toward the P-loop, 
placing Ala148 in close VDW contact with the Cg (4.19 A ˚ ) 
and a-carbon (3.84 A ˚ ) of Glu96 (Figure 11B and C); 
whereas in the cis state represented by Rad51, the corres-
ponding residues 282-284 are again shifted away from the 
P-loop, and Ala284 is seen to be no closer than 5.7 A ˚ to 
Glu221 (Figure 11A and C). The net difference in position 
of the putative catalytic glutamate sidechain is a shift of 
1.25 A ˚ towards the g-phosphate of the ATP in the trans 
peptide state represented by the DNA-bound RecA 
complex relative to the cis peptide state as seen in the 
DNA-free Rad51 states (of either the H352Y or I345T 
structures.). </p>

<p>Figure 8. The protomers and the dimer interfaces of the yeast Rad51 H352Y, Rad51 I345T and E. coli RecA recombinases are remarkably similar. 
(A) The ATPase core of the 'A' protomer of Rad51 I345T (magenta, PDB code 1SZP) was superimposed onto a protomer of Rad51 H352Y (dark 
blue), carrying along the adjacent protomer 'D' (salmon for I345T, cyan for H352Y) but not including it in the superposition; (B) Likewise, 
superimposing only the 'D' protomer of I345T onto H352Y. (C) While the ATPase core of one protomer of the RecA-ssDNA-ADP.AlF 4 
complex (yellow, PDB code 3CMW) superimposes well onto that of Rad51-H352Y (dark blue), the adjacent protomer (not included in the super-
position, orange for RecA, light blue for Rad51) overlays well only in the region of the dimer interface. The ADP-AlF 4 (green) and ssDNA backbone 
trace (gray) of the RecA complex are shown for reference. (D) In contrast, the DNA-free form of E. coli RecA (PDB 3CMV) presents a substantially 
different dimer interface than the others. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 14 4901 </p>

<p>Figure 9. Tyrosine 352 of the Rad51 H352Y mutant is present in two 
predominant alternate conformations. Detailed view of the dimer inter-
faces from the perspective of the ssDNA, using the superpositions as 
described in Figure 8, with the protomers on the right half of each 
figure used in the superposition. (A) One of the alternate conformations 
of Tyr352 of H352Y (cyan) is similar to His352 of the 'D' protomer 
(salmon) in the 'AD' dimer of I345T. (B) Neither conformation of 
Tyr352 (cyan) is similar to His352 of the 'A' protomer (magenta) of 
the 'DA' dimer of I345T. (C) While there is a good match between the 
dimer interfaces of Rad51 H352Y (dark blue and cyan) and RecA-
ssDNA-ADP-AlF4 (yellow and orange), Phe217, equivalent to 
residue 352 of yeast, is disposed differently than either alternate con-
formation of Tyr352. </p>

<p>Figure 10. Superposition of the Walker A and B motifs of E. coli RecA-
ssDNA-ADP-AlF4 onto the Rad51-H352Y and -I345T mutants 
suggests a key role for P-loop residue Phe187 (Glu68 in E. coli) in 
sensing the gamma-phosphate or preventing the binding of ATP, and 
for residue 352 in assisting in catalysis. RecA is shown in yellow with its 
adjacent protomer in orange and its bound ADP-AlF 4 in light green in 
these figures. (A) Superimposed Rad51-H352Y (purple) and its adacent 
protomer (cyan); (B) Superimposed 'A' protomer of Rad51-I345T 
(magenta) with its adjacent 'D' protomer (salmon); (C) Superimposed 
'D' protomer of Rad51-I345T (salmon) with its adjacent protomer 
(magenta.) In (A) and (C), Phe187 of the P-loop is only 1.65 A ˚ and 
1.70 A ˚ , respectively, from the AlF 4 mimic of the g-phosphate of the 
ATP. In (B), the d-nitrogen of His352 is seen to be located almost 
exactly in between the amine groups of lysines 248 and 250 of E. coli, 
residues which have been shown to be essential for nucleotide hydrolysis. </p>

<p>4902 Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 14 </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Role of His352 in Rad51 ssDNA-binding and 
catalytic activities </p>

<p>The biochemical data demonstrate that residue His352 at 
the filament interface plays a critical role in modulating </p>

<p>the affinity and/or cooperativity of Rad51-ssDNA inter-
actions, and in the coupling of ssDNA binding to cataly-
sis. Mutation of His352 is detrimental to strand exchange 
activity under the relatively stringent conditions imposed 
by long DNA substrates and by the presence of RPA. In 
addition, the opposite effects of the alanine and tyrosine 
substitutions on ssDNA-binding activity indicate different 
mechanisms for the strand exchange defects of Rad51 
H352A and H352Y. 
The H352A mutant appears to be a classic weak ssDNA 
binder, based on the increased salt-sensitivity of H352A-
ssDNA interactions compared with wild-type Rad51. The 
instability of H352A-ssDNA interactions could be a result 
of lower intrinsic affinity for ssDNA, lower cooperativity 
(e.g. weak protomer-protomer interactions), or both. 
Fundamentally, H352A is catalytically competent. At 
low salt concentrations H352A catalyzes a robust 
ssDNA-dependent ATPase reaction (Figure 4), consistent 
with results of a previous study (13), and it displaces RPA 
from ssDNA, albeit at a slower rate and efficiency than 
wild-type (Figure 6). Both ATPase and RPA displace-
ment activities are suppressed by small increases in salt 
concentration that weaken H352A-ssDNA interactions 
(Figures 3, 4 and 6). H352A exhibits reduced DNA 
strand exchange activity compared with wild-type in reac-
tions using either long DNA substrates in the presence of 
RPA (Figure 1) or short oligonucleotide substrates in the 
absence of RPA (13). These findings suggest that the DNA 
strand exchange defect of H352A is due to the formation 
of relatively unstable filaments on ssDNA. 
In contrast, the H352Y mutant is a constitutively strong 
ssDNA binder (Figure 3), but it is incapable of DNA 
strand exchange using either long DNA substrates in the 
presence of RPA (Figure 1) or short oligonucleotide sub-
strates in the absence of RPA (13). H352Y is capable of 
ATP hydrolysis, but this activity is effectively limited to a 
single turnover (Figures 4 and 5), indicating a defect in the 
exchange of ADP product for a new ATP substrate 
molecule. This nucleotide exchange defect of H352Y is 
observed both in the absence and in the presence of 
ssDNA. The data indicate that nucleotide exchange is im-
portant for the DNA strand exchange activity of Rad51. 
Despite its constitutively strong ssDNA-binding activity 
(Figure 3), H352Y fails to displace RPA from ssDNA in 
the presence of ATP (Figure 6). This finding demonstrates 
that tight ssDNA binding alone is insufficient for RPA 
displacement. Rather, the data indicate that ssDNA 
binding by Rad51 must be coupled to ATP hydrolysis 
and nucleotide exchange in order for RPA displacement 
to occur. This is consistent with the observation that the 
alanine mutant does promote RPA displacement under 
salt conditions that are permissive for multiple turnovers 
of its ssDNA-dependent ATPase activity. Although our 
RPA displacement and DNA strand exchange assays 
used opposite orders of protein addition to ssDNA, it is 
possible that the inability of H352Y to displace RPA from 
ssDNA may be a contributing factor to its inability to 
promote DNA strand exchange reactions on long DNA 
substrates. The data suggest that the coupling of ssDNA 
binding to ATP hydrolysis (or to a conformational change 
to a hydrolysis-competent form) is essential for Rad51 to </p>

<p>Figure 11. A role for cis to trans isomerization of the peptide linkage 
at the end of the conserved Walker B motif in configuring the active 
site for nucleotide hydrolysis. (A) The only RecA-family structures to 
clearly possess a trans peptide linkage between residues 144-145 at the 
end of Walker B contain DNA, as represented here by the active site of 
E. coli RecA-ssDNA-ADP-AlF4 complex (PDB code 3CMW). (B) As 
in nearly all other RecA-family structures, the active site of Rad51-
H352Y shows a cis configuration at this peptide (between residues 
280-281). (C) Compared with the cis configuration, in the trans config-
uration Ser281 (145 in E. coli) and Ala284 (148 in E. coli) move toward 
the active site, and push the putative nucleophilic activator Glu221 
(96 in E. coli) 1.25 A ˚ closer to the g-phosphate (mimicked by the 
AlF 4 moiety) of the ATP. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 14 4903 </p>

<p>displace RPA from ssDNA. This coupling is achieved by 
the H352A mutant under permissive salt conditions, 
despite its lower ssDNA-binding affinity, but not by 
H352Y. </p>

<p>Structure of the Rad51-H352Y mutant </p>

<p>The structure of the Rad51 H352Y mutant is remarkably 
similar overall and in detail to the I345T mutant (11), 
suggesting that the I345T and H352Y mutations within 
the two crystallized proteins do not affect the overall 
form or pitch of the DNA-free Rad51 filament (or coinci-
dentally do so to the same extent.) The yeast-specific 
N-terminal extension (residues 1-79), which is present in 
our protein but disordered within the crystal, and which 
was deleted in order to obtain crystals of I345T, likewise 
does not affect the structure of the DNA-free, 
nucleotide-free Rad51 filament. Both filaments are in the 
'high-pitch' form, generally regarded as the active form 
(5). The main difference between the two structures is 
that the H352Y filament exhibits 6 1 symmetry with the 
protomer as the repeating unit, while the I345T filament 
exhibits 3 1 symmetry with the dimer as the repeating unit 
(11). As a result, I345T filaments contain two different 
types of protomer-protomer interfaces and two different 
types of active sites, involving different interactions of 
His352 with the active site and with Phe187 from the 
adjacent subunit. In contrast the H352Y filament 
contains one type of interface, one type of active site, 
and a single geometry for Phe187. 
It is interesting to note that the crystal structure of the 
I345T mutant actually contains six independent protomers 
arranged as three distinct filaments (11). While the A-D 
and F-E filaments are essentially identical, the third 
filament, B-C, is nearly a 6 1 helix like that in the H352Y 
filament, and also shows conformational disorder in the 
helix that contains His352 and in the Phe187 sidechain. 
The alternating dimers in the A-D and F-E filaments, 
with Phe187 alternately projecting into and away from 
the g-phosphate-binding region of the Walker A motif, 
along with the multiple conformations seen for Tyr352 
(which interacts with Phe187) in our structure, suggests 
that the active site configurations represented by 
protomers A, D, E and F in the I345T structure may rep-
resent stable intermediates along the recombination 
pathway, and that our structure and the B and C 
protomers of the I345T structure are transient intermedi-
ates between those two structures. </p>

<p>Role of Phe187 in Rad51 mechanism </p>

<p>Our structure in comparison with other RecA family 
proteins supports a key role for Phe187 in the recombinase 
pathway. Crystallized Rad51 filaments (H352Y and 
I345T) are captured in a conformation that does not 
allow binding of the triphospho nucleotide: This is sup-
ported by the fact that no nucleotide was seen in the I345T 
crystal structure, in spite of the presence of 10 mM ATPgS 
in the crystallization mixture (11). Superimposing the 
RecA-DNA-ADP-AlF 4 structure on the Rad51 struc-
tures shows that Phe187 sterically excludes the 
g-phosphate. The I354T filament structure must represent </p>

<p>a transient intermediate, since the mutant is strand 
exchange-competent. This suggests that in the Rad51 
mechanism, Phe187 could either serve as a sensor of the 
nucleotide state, forced out of the nucleotide-binding 
pocket by the presence of ATP, or as a regulator of 
ATP binding, preventing binding of ATP by steric exclu-
sion of the g-phosphate. In the case of H352Y, however, 
the filament becomes trapped in this conformation after 
hydrolyzing 1 ATP, resulting in an inability to exchange 
the nucleotide. This is a potential structural explanation 
for the greatly reduced hydrolytic activity of the H352Y 
mutant. By virtue of its interactions with residue 352 of 
the adjacent protomer comprising the active site, the con-
formation of Phe187 appears to be dependent on the con-
figuration of the protomer-protomer interface, or 
conversely, that the configuration of the interface 
depends on the conformation of Phe187. In either case, 
this provides a structural mechanism for the roles that 
Phe187 (Glu68 in E. coli RecA) and His352 (Phe217 in 
RecA) have been observed to play in communication 
between the active site and the state of the filament inter-
face. Given the similarity of the dimer interface observed 
in the E. coli RecA-ssDNA-ADP-AlF4 crystal structure 
with that seen in both S. cerevisiae Rad51 crystal struc-
tures, it is tempting to speculate that after hydrolysis of 
the ATP, Glu68 of the Walker A motif, equivalent to 
Phe187 in Rad51, forms a salt bridge to either or both 
of Lys248 and Lys250 that sterically blocks nucleotide 
exchange and holds the filament in this conformation 
until an appropriate 'signal' is obtained. </p>

<p>Role of cis/trans peptide linkage in signaling the 
DNA-bound state </p>

<p>In comparison with the RecA-DNA structures (4), our 
structure provides a possible role for the cis/trans 
peptide linkage at the end of the Walker B motif 
(Figure 11). In virtually all RecA family structures 
except those that contain DNA, this peptide linkage 
(e.g. between residues 280 and 281 in Rad51, 144 and 
145 in E. coli RecA) is in the relatively rare cis conform-
ation (4,11,37). In this conformation, the putative catalytic 
glutamate (Glu221 in Rad51, 96 in E. coli RecA) is pulled 
away from the g-phosphate (as modeled by the ADP-AlF 4 
analog in the RecA-DNA structures) by Ser281/145 and 
backbone interactions between the cis peptide and the 
backbone and sidechain of Thr220. In contrast, the trans 
linkage enforces three structural changes in its vicinity that 
result in a shift of Glu221/96 towards the g-phosphate and 
that greatly reduce that sidechain's degrees of freedom. 
The trans linkage induces a substantial rearrangement of 
Ser281/145, placing it in close steric contact with the carb-
oxylate of Glu221/96 while maintaining reasonable 
H-bonding geometry. The carbonyl of the trans peptide 
bonds with the backbone of Glu221/96, further locking 
that residue in place. And thirdly, as a consequence of 
the trans peptide, Ala284/148 pushes the sidechain of 
Glu221/96 closer to the g phosphate. The trans linkage 
thus appears to orient and lock the glutamate residue 
in its catalytically competent conformation for ATP 
hydrolysis. </p>



<p>It does not appear that the cis/trans peptide linkage is 
dictated by the nucleotide state, since the cis state is 
observed in virtually all structures of RecA family 
proteins, whether in the apo, ADP-bound, or ATP-
analog bound forms (4,11,37). Occurrence of the trans 
peptide linkage correlates only with the presence of the 
ssDNA or dsDNA. The propagation pathway is not 
clear from the structures, but it is noteworthy that 
DNA-binding loop L1 (289-296/157-164) follows the 
Walker B motif, and that DNA-binding loop L2 
(327-344/195-209) follows the 'sensor residue' Gln326/ 
194 and extends from the beta-strand adjacent to the 
Walker A motif. Indeed, across the RecA family, there 
is significant variation in the sequence and structure of 
the protein from residue 283/147 through the disordered 
loop. Thus, while the mechanism for conveying the signal 
remains to be determined, it appears that the presence of 
DNA is responsible for the cis to trans state change that 
ultimately results in pushing the putative catalytic glutam-
ate closer to the g phosphate and holding it in place to 
activate a water molecule for nucleophilic attack. </p>

<p>ACCESSION NUMBER </p>

<p>PDB ID 3LDA. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank Drs Tom Ellenberger and Marc Wold, 
respectively, for providing us with expression plasmids for 
the yeast Rad51 and RPA proteins. We thank Pierre Aller 
and Karl Zahn for data collection at Advanced Photon 
Source synchrotron. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>National Cancer Institute, NIH, HHS, USA (Program 
Project Grant no. P01 CA098993); NCI (Y1-CO-1020 to 
GM/CA-CAT); NIGMS, NIH, HHS, USA (Y1-GM-
1104); US Department of Energy, Basic Energy Sciences, 
Office 
of 
Science 
(under 
contract 
No. 
DE-AC02-06CH11357 for the use of Advanced Photon 
Source). Funding for open access charge: National 
Institutes of Health (grant no. P01 CA098993). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>4906 Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 14 </p>

</text></tei>