<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2649809" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>1 The abbreviations used are: HD, Huntington disease; CSF, cerebro-
spinal fluid; IPI, International Protein Index; AMT, accurate mass and 
time; LTQ-FT, hybrid linear ion trap-Fourier transform ICR mass spec-
trometer designed by Thermo Finnigan; LTQ OrbiTrap XL, mass spec-
trometer by Thermo Finnigan that is based on LTQ XL TM linear ion trap </p>

<p>and the patented Orbitrap TM technology; HCT-Ultra ion trap, High-
Capacity Trap (HCT TM ) mass spectrometer system by Bruker Dalton-
ics; mzXML, XML (extensible markup language)-based common file 
format for proteomics mass spectrometric data; FDR, false discovery 
rate; MAS5, Affymetrix microarray suite version 5 software; GSEA, 
gene set enrichment analysis; IS, internal standard; BA, Brodmann 
area; MA plots, intensity-dependent ratio plots. </p>

<p>diseases (14 -17), and oligoclonal bands in CSF have long 
been used to aid in diagnosis of multiple sclerosis and en-
cephalitis (18 -20). CSF is an ultrafiltrate of arterial blood 
produced by the choroid plexus in the lateral, third, and fourth 
ventricles. However, it has been estimated that about 20% of 
the proteins in CSF are derived from brain (21), making CSF 
an attractive source of potential disease biomarkers in neu-
rodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer and Parkinson 
diseases (16, 22, 23). We report here an integrated proteom-
ics approach to characterize the constituents of CSF and 
identify potential markers in CSF for human Huntington 
disease. 
In this study, we analyzed and interpreted human HD CSF 
proteomics data generated by four laboratories using different 
proteomics approaches, including separation strategies, 
pooling strategies, depletion of proteins, quantitation meth-
ods, and mass spectrometry instruments. Although acquired 
using different biochemical approaches, all data were inter-
preted using a common protein database, algorithms for da-
tabase search (24), and peptide and protein identification (25, 
26) and quantitation (27) methods to allow comparison across 
laboratories. 
The preplanned primary analysis of these data includes 
deriving rankings for protein changes in HD based on the 
synthesized data from all laboratories and then assessing 
biological and statistical significance by interrogating the 
rankings with gene annotations derived from independent 
data sets (e.g. gene set enrichment style analyses (28)). An-
notations include the tissue specificity of a gene (e.g. brain or 
liver) and whether a gene is significantly changed in human 
HD brain when compared with non-HD brain, both derived 
from previously published data sets profiling the transcripts of 
normal human tissues (29) and human HD and non-HD brains 
(2). 
This analysis reveals that proteins that have specifically 
high expression in the brain (brain-specific) are 1.8 times more 
enriched in CSF than in human plasma. These brain-specific 
proteins overall have lower concentrations in HD than normal 
CSF, and 81% of them are concordant with previously iden-
tified mRNA changes in HD versus normal brain. Altogether 
these results suggest that measuring proteins in CSF may be 
a useful way to assess the health of the brain, track progres-
sion of the disease, and improve our understanding of the 
disease. 
Secondary analysis was also performed to investigate the 
concordance of protein changes across laboratories. Overall 
at the protein (e.g. International Protein Index (IPI) sequence) 
level, there is a low concordance of the disease/control ratios 
among laboratories, meaning that each laboratory would re-
port different highest (or lowest) ranking proteins. However, 
the laboratories are consistent with respect to the overall 
trends that brain-specific proteins decline and liver-specific 
proteins increase in HD samples. Concordance in protein 
ratios and overall trends is greatest between the two labora-</p>

<p>tories identifying the highest number of proteins. This sup-
ports an argument that future studies with resource limitations 
should emphasize the depth of protein coverage and include 
multiple laboratories only if their experimental methods com-
plement each other in terms of the protein observations (30). 
Our study also suggests that data integration plays a central 
role in studies to identify biomarkers as statistical significance 
could not have been demonstrated without the ability to eval-
uate changes in predefined groups of proteins using the gene 
set enrichment analysis (GSEA) approach. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>Sample Collection </p>

<p>CSF samples were collected and processed by a single study site 
described previously (10). Briefly CSF was obtained by lumbar punc-
ture from 20 HD gene-positive patients and 10 gene-negative controls 
with matched ages recruited through the University of British Colum-
bia HD Medical Clinic. On the day of the lumbar puncture, all subjects 
had a comprehensive clinical evaluation including assessment on the 
complete United Huntington Disease Rating Scale. Based on the 
United Huntington Disease Rating Scale independence score as de-
fined by the Huntington Study Group (31), 10 of the 20 gene-positive 
individuals were categorized as early stage (independence score 
80), and the other 10 were categorized as moderate stage (65 
independence score 80). About 5-7 ml of CSF samples were 
collected in four or five standard lumbar puncture kit tubes (Cardinal-
Health, safe-t-LP kit) (catalog number 4301CSDF). Each collected 
sample was placed on ice and then centrifuged at 2000 g (4000 
rpm) for 10 min to eliminate cells and other insoluble material. The 
collected CSF was examined by microscopy, aliquoted, and frozen 
immediately on dry ice in polypropylene tubes in 1-or 3-ml aliquots 
and stored at 80 °C. Tubes were filled to the top to minimize 
oxidation during storage. Average total processing time was 76 min 
from the start of collection to final storage. No anticoagulants, pre-
servatives, and protease inhibitors were added. The lumbar punctures 
were atraumatic with CSF cell counts revealing red blood cells from 0 
to 171 counts/l and white blood cells from 0 to 17 counts/l, 
indicating no significant blood cell contamination (supplemental Table 
S1). Samples were stored at 80 °C for various lengths of time 
ranging from 17 to 27 months before they were thawed and subdi-
vided into aliquots of 0.5 ml to be shipped using dry ice to individual 
labs for analysis. The duration of shipment was between 1 and 3 days, 
and dry ice was replenished during the shipment to keep samples 
frozen. All 30 samples were stored at 80 °C before thawing once 
again for analysis. Therefore, except one (HDU-2) that was thawed 
three times, all samples were thawed twice before analysis. </p>

<p>Proteomics Platforms </p>

<p>Five different laboratories received aliquots of CSF collected from 
the same 30 individuals described above. The disease statuses of the 
10 HD gene-negative controls, 10 HD gene-positive early stage sam-
ples, and 10 HD gene-positive mid-stage samples were blinded to the 
research laboratories and labeled as group B, C, and A, respectively, 
with identifiers provided to labs only after raw data from all labs were 
received by the bioinformatics data core analysis group. 
Each lab designed experiments based on their preferred compre-
hensive proteomics platform(s) (Table I) for the purpose of discovering 
biomarkers that can classify Huntington disease. These approaches 
include four quantitative mass spectrometry approaches and one 
gel-based quantitative approach that used the mass spectrometer for 
protein identification. Experimental designs varied in many respects </p>

<p>Huntington Disease Cerebrospinal Fluid </p>

<p>452 Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics 8.3 </p>

<p>across the labs, including the use of pooled and non-pooled designs, 
depletion and non-depletion of abundant proteins in the samples, and 
label-free and isotopically labeled quantitation. After evaluation, data 
from four laboratories were reported in this study. One of the five 
laboratories reported quality control issues that were also detected in 
the data analyses (fewer than 80 total peptides were identified), and 
therefore this data set was not considered for further analysis. De-
tailed experimental designs of the other four laboratories are de-
scribed in the supplemental text, Part A. </p>

<p>Individual Lab Data Processing and Analysis </p>

<p>All data files were transmitted to the bioinformatics data-process-
ing lab for analysis after converting to the standard mzXML format 
(32, 33) and then searched with <rs id="software-31" type="software">X! Tandem</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-31" type="version-date">January 1, 2007</rs> release) 
configured with a scoring function (24) compatible with <rs type="software">Peptide-
Prophet</rs> (25) and <rs type="software">ProteinProphet</rs> (26). The same database (human 
IPI version 3.20 consisting of 61,225 IPI numbers) was used to search 
all data. <rs id="software-17" type="software">PeptideProphet</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-17" type="version-number">version 3.0</rs>) and <rs id="software-8" type="software">ProteinProphet</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-number">version 3.0</rs>) 
were used to assign identified peptide and protein confidence scores 
for all but Lab 1 (details described below) where the complexity of 
samples interrogated was not sufficient to estimate the Peptide-
Prophet error model. Quantitation was performed following tryptic 
search and protein inference. Finally multiple experiments within a lab 
were then aligned to create analytic data sets sufficient to determine 
relative disease status. 
The following common criteria were applied to all searches. A 
2.0-Da error from the calculated peptide monoisotopic mass was 
allowed to determine whether a particular peptide sequence is to be 
considered as a possible model for a spectrum. Mass tolerance for 
fragment ions was 1 Da (24). The maximal number of missed cleav-
ages permitted was 2. A static modification on cysteines of 57.021 
Da was used for all labs except Lab 4, which performed acrylamide 
labeling on cysteines. A potential modification on methionines of 
15.9949 Da was used. A weighted average mass was used to 
calculate the masses of the fragment ions in a tandem mass spec-
trum. A minimum number of one ion was required for a peptide to be 
scored. A default minimum <rs type="software">PeptideProphet</rs> probability of 0.2 was 
used to calculate the protein group probability. Only peptides with 
probability 0.75 and mass error 20 ppm were selected for quan-
titation. Specific search parameters for the different labeling schemes 
by different labs are specified in the supplemental text, Part B. The 
following are descriptions of the software used for each lab's data 
and quantitation methods (summarized in supplemental Table S2) 
during data processing. 
Lab 1-Lab 1 used a DIGE method and quantitated a large number 
of fluorescent spots with two commercial software algorithms (<rs id="software-9" type="software">DeCyder</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-9" type="version-number">6.5</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-9" type="creator">GE Healthcare</rs>) and <rs id="software-38" type="software">SameSpots</rs> <rs corresp="#software-38" type="version-number">2.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-38" type="creator">Nonlinear Dynamics</rs>)). A </p>

<p>t test was performed on the log ratios using <rs id="software-26" type="software">Statistica</rs> for Windows 
(<rs corresp="#software-26" type="creator">StatSoft, Inc.</rs>.) <rs corresp="#software-26" type="version-number">version 7</rs> to estimate the significant difference of a 
protein. Only those spots found to have significant changes, based on 
fluorescence, between the HD and the control were selected for 
tandem MS analysis. Peak lists of MS/MS spectra acquired on the 
HCT-Ultra ion trap instrument (Bruker Daltonics) were generated us-
ing the software tool <rs id="software-28" type="software">DataAnalysis</rs> <rs corresp="#software-28" type="version-number">3.4.179</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-28" type="creator">Bruker Daltonics</rs>) with 
default parameters. The built-in algorithm version 2.0 was used, and 
neither smoothing nor any signal-to-noise filter was applied for com-
pound detection. A maximum charge state of 3 was considered for 
deconvolution. Data were then converted to mzXML files using 
<rs id="software-20" type="software">CompassXport</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-20" type="version-number">version 1.2.3</rs>). Peptides were identified using decoy 
database methods with an approach described by Elias and Gygi (34). 
After proteins were identified for selected spots using false discovery 
rate (FDR) and <rs type="software">ProteinProphet</rs> (see details in the supplemental text, 
Part B), quantitation of -fold changes among different disease sta-
tuses was processed based on the following rules. 1) If a spot was 
quantitated by both <rs id="software-12" type="software">DeCyder</rs> <rs corresp="#software-12" type="version-number">6.5</rs> and <rs type="software">SameSpots</rs> methods, -fold 
changes by DeCyder 6.5 were selected because the differential ex-
pression resulting from this method is more significant on average. On 
the other hand, if only one quantitation method was used, results from 
that method were selected. 2) When multiple spots have the same 
protein identification, -fold changes were averaged for that protein. 3) 
When a spot resulted in several protein identifications, the same -fold 
changes were assigned to all proteins. 
Lab 2-Lab 2 performed label-free analysis. Peak lists were gen-
erated using <rs id="software-11" type="software">MassLynx</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-11" type="version-number">4.0</rs>) based on signals obtained by Q-ToF 
Micro spectrometer from Waters Micromass. The MS duty cycle was 
set at 1,1,4 as described in detail in the supplemental text, Part A. 
These data were converted to mzXML files using <rs id="software-7" type="software">MassWolf</rs> <rs corresp="#software-7" type="version-number">1.02</rs> with 
the Waters Datafile Access Component (DAC) library. Following the 
database search using the common criteria, quantitation was per-
formed using a spectral count approach (35), which sums the number 
of total spectra assigned to the protein group in that sample. Only 
peptide spectra with <rs type="software">PeptideProphet</rs> probability greater than 0.75 or 
an error rate of 5% were counted for each IPI entry identified. Be-
cause individual level variation can be determined for this design, we 
used a straightforward procedure that tracks all proteins that are 
members of a single ProteinProphet group within the experiment to 
associate groups across multiple experiments and to flag groups that 
are not directly comparable (supplemental text, Part B). After sum-
ming up to master protein groups across samples, the average spec-
tral count of all IPI entries within a "master group" was assigned to 
that group. For each master group, total spectral counts from 10 
HD-mid samples, 10 HD-early samples, and 10 control samples were 
summed up and used to calculate HD-mid/control, HD-early/control, 
and HD-mid/HD-early ratios. Intensity-dependent ratio plots (MA </p>

<p>TABLE I 
Experimental designs of five proteomics laboratories </p>

<p>1D, one-dimensional; 2D, two-dimensional; iTRAQ, isobaric tags for relative and absolute quantitation. </p>

<p>Group 
Mass 
spectrometer 
Quantitative method 
Pooling 
Immunodepletion 
Separation </p>

<p>Lab 1 
HCT-Ultra 
DIGE 
No 
No 
2D gels 
Lab 2 
Q-ToF Micro 
Label-free (spectral counts) 
No 
IgY-12 High Capacity LC2 
1D SDS-PAGE 
Lab 3 
LTQ-FT 
d 0 /d 3 acetylation 
Yes 
ProteoExtract Albumin/IgG 
Removal kit </p>

<p>1D SDS-PAGE </p>

<p>Lab 4 
LTQ OrbiTrap XL 
Acrylamide labeling and 
label-free (AMT) </p>

<p>Yes 
Multiple Affinity Removal 
System </p>

<p>Anion exchange and reverse 
phase chromatography 
Lab 5 a LC-MALDI-TOF/TOF iTRAQ 
Yes 
Multiple Affinity Removal 
System </p>

<p>1D SDS-PAGE </p>

<p>a Data from Lab 5 was dropped prior to data synthesis across labs because of quality control issues (see "Experimental Procedures"). </p>



<p>Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics 8.3 453 </p>

<p>plots) and histograms of light/heavy ratios were examined to ensure 
the quality of data for the labeled experiments. M is the y-axis and A 
is the x-axis, where in this paper, M Log 2 (Heavy) Log 2 (Light); 
A [ 1 ⁄2] (Log 2 (Heavy) Log 2 (Light)). 
Lab 3-Data from Lab 3 were acquired from the LTQ-FT instrument 
(Thermo Finnigan). Peak lists were generated by <rs id="software-18" type="software">Xcalibur</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-18" type="version-number">version 1.1</rs>) 
and converted to mzXML files using <rs id="software-6" type="software">ReAdW</rs> <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">1.1</rs> with XRawfile library. 
Default parameters were used. Database search was carried out 
using the common parameters and the designated specific modifica-
tions (supplemental text, Part B). Protein groups with probability 
score 0.9 (corresponding to an overall error rate of 0.01) were 
considered confident proteins for downstream analysis. The Q3 al-
gorithm (27), developed to accommodate a 3-dalton mass shift in 
heavy and light peptides, was used to compute the ratios between the 
light and heavy isotopic pairs using peak areas. More specifically, 
only confidently identified peptides (<rs type="software">PeptideProphet</rs> probability 
0.75 and mass error 20 ppm) were selected for further quantita-</p>

<p>tion at the protein level. In three pairwise comparisons, the internal 
standard (IS) containing equal amounts of 30 samples was labeled 
with light acetyl group, and each of the three disease statuses (A, B, 
or C) was labeled with heavy acetyl group (for details, see supple-
mental text, Part A). Preliminary analysis found that light/heavy ratios 
were skewed for both IS versus HD-early and IS versus HD-mid 
experiments. Because the same amount of protein was loaded into 
the MS instrument and, in theory, most proteins in the disease and 
control should remain unchanged, we normalized these ratios. Nor-
malization at the peptide level was performed by median centering 
the log ratios. Experiments were then aligned to infer the protein 
changes of different disease status comparisons. Protein inference 
was performed using the <rs type="software">ProteinProphet</rs> analysis tool at the lab level, 
and light/heavy ratios of these protein groups were inferred from 
ratios at the experiment level by comparing IPI numbers. HD-mid 
versus control, HD-early versus control, and HD-mid versus HD-early 
ratios for each protein group were calculated using IS/control, IS/HD-
mid, and IS/HD-early ratios from the three experiments. 
Lab 4 -LTQ OrbiTrap XL mass spectrometer from Thermo Finni-
gan was used, and <rs id="software-33" type="software">Xcalibur</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-33" type="version-number">version 2.2</rs>) was applied to generate 
peak lists. Data were converted to mzXML files using <rs id="software-29" type="software">ReAdW</rs> <rs corresp="#software-29" type="version-number">1.1</rs> with 
XRawfile library. Default parameters were used. Data were then 
searched with the common criteria plus specific modifications. Pro-
tein groups with probability score 0.9 (corresponding to an overall 
error rate of 0.01) were considered confident proteins for downstream 
analysis. For the labeled analysis, as with Lab 3, the Q3 algorithm (27) 
was used to compute ratios between light and heavy isotopic pairs. 
And similarly to the methods used for Lab 3, peptides with Peptide-
Prophet scores greater than 0.75 and a mass error of less than 20 
ppm were selected for the protein level quantitation. Histograms of 
light/heavy ratios based on the number of cysteines in the peptides 
revealed that peptides with one cysteine have better normal distribu-
tions than peptides with more than one cysteine. Because 80% of 
peptides contain only one cysteine, only peptides with one cysteine 
were selected for protein level analysis. To ensure a high confidence 
of quantitation at the protein level, only those proteins with at least 
three quantitated peptides were used for further analysis. For the 
label-free analysis, accurate mass and time (AMT) methods were used 
to identify peptides in LC-MS data using a single AMT database 
containing all high quality (<rs type="software">PeptideProphet</rs> probability 0.95) peptide 
identifications from all labeled (fractionated) and unlabeled (unfrac-
tionated) data from Lab 4. The LC-MS peptide features from each 
unlabeled sample were matched against the combined AMT data-
base to provide peptide assignments. Each match was assigned a 
probability value based on mass error and normalized retention time 
error between the MS1 feature and the AMT peptide entry, and only 
matches with probability 0.95 or a false assignment rate 0.05 were </p>

<p>kept. LC-MS peptide intensity values for the peptides were normal-
ized across runs, and peptide ratios were calculated. The AMT data-
base and matching were performed using the <rs type="software">msInspect/AMT</rs> soft-
ware platform (36, 37). Protein inference was performed using 
<rs type="software">ProteinProphet</rs>, and protein ratios were calculated as well. As with the 
Lab 3 analysis, experiments were aligned using the ProteinProphet 
analysis tool at the lab level to infer the protein changes of different 
disease status comparisons for the labeled and unlabeled methods. 
Ratios of these protein groups were inferred from ratios at the exper-
iment level by IPI numbers. </p>

<p>Gene Name and Group Assignments </p>

<p>Proteins, identified by their IPI sequence, were assigned to gene 
symbols by IPI protein cross-reference. Because the peptide level 
evidence cannot uniquely identify all IPI sequences, proteins were 
assembled by <rs type="software">ProteinProphet</rs> into groups (26). Some of these protein 
groups contain unique protein sequences and gene symbols, and some 
contain multiple sequences that may result from the same gene symbol 
or from multiple genes within the same family (e.g. a protein group is 
assigned with HBG2, HBE1, HBG1, HBB, and HBD, all of which belong 
to the hemoglobin gene family) or multiple incompatible genes. </p>

<p>Deriving a List of Consensus Proteins </p>

<p>To facilitate comparison across labs, a comprehensive list of pro-
tein groups consisting of all proteomics data reported in this study 
was generated by running ProteinProphet on all data. A minimum 
probability of 0.9 was used to generate the confident protein group list, 
resulting in an overall error rate of 0.01. A total of 1574 protein groups 
were identified, corresponding to 2012 gene symbols (supplemental 
Table S3). Only 34 of the protein groups were based on single peptides. 
Scores, sequences, and spectra for these single peptide-based pro-
teins are provided in supplemental Table S4. HD-early/control, HD-mid/ 
control, and HD-mid/HD-early ratios for each protein group were in-
ferred from lab level analysis by comparing IPI numbers. For a few 
cases, multiple ratios were found for a protein group in HD-early versus 
control, HD-mid versus control, or HD-mid versus HD-early compari-
sons, and in those cases we took the geometric mean of these ratios. 
Detailed results of this search are available upon request. We have 
also deposited the comprehensive list of proteins at the PRoteomics 
IDentifications (PRIDE) database (accession number 3701). </p>

<p>Deriving the Rank of Proteins Changes by Combining Ratios 
across Laboratories </p>

<p>Because various methods report protein changes on different 
scales, to make an effective and meaningful comparison (38) we 
integrated protein ratios across laboratories using the following meta-
analysis procedures that combine the scale-free effect size measure-
ments (z-scores). We first transformed the ratios to logarithm scale so 
that all the data were in a similar range, and then we standardized the 
scores by centering and scaling log ratios in each lab to have mean 0 
and variance 1. The resulting z-score represents the number of stand-
ard deviations above or below the mean ratios within each lab. To 
combine z-scores, we chose to sum them across laboratories. Although 
one might have considered averaging the z-scores because not all 
proteins are quantified in the same number of experiments, we chose to 
sum them so that a protein quantified by only one laboratory must have 
a higher ratio to achieve the same rank as proteins observed across all 
laboratories with consistent and modest changes. For the purpose of 
finding proteins that classify HD, we combined the two HD groups and 
summed together the sum of z-scores of HD-mid/control and HD-early/ 
control (sums of z-scores). Proteins that are most altered in HD are 
those with the highest and lowest sums of z-scores. </p>

<p>Huntington Disease Cerebrospinal Fluid </p>



<p>Annotating Proteins for Tissue Specificity and for Changes in 
HD Brain </p>

<p>We next annotated each protein in the synthesized protein list 
based on its behavior found in human transcriptional profiles of HD 
and normal brain (2) and other tissues (29). Specifically we annotated 
proteins based on 1) tissue specificity score: the relative expression of 
transcript in human brain, liver, and 25 other normal human tissues; 
and 2) changes in HD brain: the ratio of transcript abundance be-
tween HD and non-HD brains. All annotations were made by com-
paring gene symbols. IPI numbers identified in our proteomics study 
were associated with gene symbols by reference to the data 
(ipi.HUMAN.v3.20.dat) provided by the International Protein Index 
managed by the European Bioinformatics Institute. 
Annotation of Protein Changes in CSF with Changes in the HD 
Brain by Microarray Analysis-We compared protein changes from 
this proteomics study with the log 2 -fold changes of mRNA in HD 
versus normal brain in caudate nucleus, cerebellum, and motor cortex 
(Brodmann area 4 (BA4)) based on a previously published study by 
Hodges et al. (2). Probe sets with significant changes (p values 
0.001) were selected and collapsed to gene level based on gene 
symbols. When a gene has multiple probe sets, the median log 2 -fold 
change of that gene was selected as the estimate of the mRNA 
change. As a result, 6183 genes in caudate nucleus, 1143 genes in 
BA4 cortex, and 440 in cerebellum have significant mRNA changes in 
HD brains from the normal. 
Signal Processing of Tissue Transcriptional Expression Data-Be-
cause a significant fraction of plasma proteins is derived from various 
tissues and so are CSF proteins, which are filtered from plasma, to 
annotate proteins for their source tissues, it is critical that the tran-
scriptional data set includes tissues of human major organs. The 
normal human tissue expression data set was acquired from pub-
lished data provided by Ge et al. (29) that includes a total of 36 types 
of normal human tissue, covering the complexity of human tissues. 
Because all CSF samples are from adult human, the annotation will 
focus on the adult tissue expression pattern. Therefore, data from 
three fetal tissues were removed. Ge et al. (29) examined a "whole 
brain" and six subregions of the brain (amygdala, corpus callosum, 
caudate nucleus, cerebellum, hippocampus, and thalamus). How-
ever, the cortex region that is noted to have severe cell loss in 
Huntington disease patients was not included. We removed the 
"whole-brain" data because it is not obvious to us how this RNA 
sample was prepared. We added the cortex signals and substituted 
cerebellum and caudate nucleus data with data derived from an 
extensive study that was carried out on four parts of human normal 
brain (caudate nucleus, cerebellum, and BA4 and BA9 cortex) using 
the same microarray chips (2). After these brain data were obtained 
from Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) DataSets, signals detected 
using <rs id="software-10" type="software">Affymetrix microarray suite</rs> <rs corresp="#software-10" type="version-number">version 5</rs> software (MAS5) for each 
probe were averaged over 21 caudate nucleus, 21 cerebellum, and 24 
cortex (12 BA4 and 12 BA9) arrays. We plotted log 2 MAS5 signal of 
the caudate nucleus and cerebellum from Ge et al. (29) versus those 
from Hodges et al. (2) and found that the correlations are both 0.90 
(supplemental Fig. S1). These high correlations suggest that data 
from the two studies may be combined. So far, we have data for 
seven subregions of the brain. Because we want to annotate a gene 
as being active in the brain if it is active in any part of the brain, we 
summarized the brain expression data by taking the maximum across 
all seven subregions. As a result, transcriptional data of "brain tis-
sues" and 26 other types of human tissues were included in our 
analysis. These tissues are from brain, heart, thymus, spleen, ovary, 
kidney, muscle, pancreas, prostate, intestine, colon, placenta, blad-
der, breast, uterus, thyroid, skin, salivary, trachea, adrenal, bone 
marrow, pituitary, spinal cord, testis, liver, stomach, and lung (sup-
plemental Table S5). Finally many genes have multiple probes; one </p>

<p>can choose to use the average signal or the maximum signal for each 
gene. In our analysis, the one with maximum signal among all tissues 
was selected because we considered that the maximum signal is the 
highest above the noise level. As a result, we observed 1941 tissue 
markers based on human array data (supplemental Table S6). The 
definition of tissue-specific genes/proteins may vary with tissues 
included in the study and when the thresholds change. 
Defining Tissue Specificity of a Gene-Tissue specificity was de-
rived from the human transcriptional data set profiling seven brain 
tissues plus 26 other normal tissues based on publicly available 
resources after processing as described above. The tissue specificity 
score for a gene is determined by the relative intensity of its probe on 
the array across tissues. We defined a gene as tissue-specific if the 
maximum intensity of its probe was highest in that tissue and the 
maximum intensity in every other tissue was at least 2.5 times lower. 
These tissue-specific genes were used to annotate the CSF 
proteome. 
Verification of Protein Tissue-specific Annotation-The definition of 
tissue-specific genes/proteins may vary with tissues included in the 
study, with detailed processing methods, and when thresholds are 
changed. To validate our definition of tissue-specific genes, we 
checked the description and functions of some genes chosen at 
random. For instance, muscle-specific genes include myosin, actinin, 
troponin, creatine kinase, and calcium channels. And testis-specific 
genes are associated with terms such as spermatogenic, sperm-
specific, or male-enhanced antigen. In addition, normal mouse gene 
expression data from Zapala et al. (39) covering 20 subregions of the 
brain plus 14 tissues from other parts of the adult mouse was used to 
confirm the human array-based analysis. Similar to human tissue data 
processing, we combined data from 20 subregions of the brain in-
cluding striatum, cortex, cerebellum, etc. into one data set called 
"brain" to simplify the analysis using the maximum MAS5 signal of the 
20 brain subregions computed for each probe set. As a result, 15 
mouse tissues were considered for further analysis: adrenal, pituitary, 
testis, thymus, spinal cord, choroid plexus, retina, brown adipose 
tissue, white adipose tissue, kidney, liver, heart, muscle, spleen, and 
brain (supplemental Table S7). Corresponding human orthologous 
genes were inferred by human-mouse ortholog data provided by the 
Human Gene Organisation Gene Nomenclature Committee. Using the 
same tissue specificity-defining methods, 1333 tissue markers with 
human orthologous genes were observed (supplemental Table S8). </p>

<p>Summary of Statistical Analysis Procedures Used to Interrogate 
the Protein List </p>

<p>Statistical procedures were used to interrogate the synthesized 
protein list for three hypotheses that the experiments were designed 
to address: 1) that CSF is enriched for brain-specific proteins com-
pared with plasma, 2) that brain-specific proteins change in CSF with 
HD development, and 3) that brain-specific protein changes in CSF 
are concordant with transcriptional changes in the brain. 
To evaluate hypothesis 1, we performed Pearson's 2 tests on an 
over-representation analysis to compare the fraction of proteins an-
notated as being brain-specific in CSF and the Human Proteome 
Organization Plasma Proteome Project plasma data (results summa-
rized in Table IV). To evaluate hypothesis 2, we used GSEA, which 
uses a non-parametric Wilcoxon test (40, 41) to compare the distri-
bution of ratios between brain-specific and non-brain-specific pro-
teins (see "Results"). For hypothesis 3, we coded all brain-derived 
proteins as up or down based on the sign of their sums of z-scores 
and all transcripts as up or down based on the sign of their log 2 -fold 
changes of mRNA from the array and then applied Pearson's 2 tests 
to evaluate the association (results are summarized in Table V). </p>

<p>Huntington Disease Cerebrospinal Fluid </p>

<p>Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics 8.3 455 </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>General Work Flow of the Primary Data Analysis-All pro-
teomics data acquired by four laboratories utilizing different 
proteomics platforms were interpreted using a common pro-
tein database as well as the same search engine and peptide 
and protein validation methods to allow comparison across 
labs. The flow of data analysis is as follows. 1) Data sets 
generated based on each experimental design were searched 
with protein database independently. 2) Multiple data sets 
from the same experiment were aligned to determine the 
protein changes between different disease statuses. 3) Data 
were aligned across labs, and protein ratios were synthesized 
for the consistency of protein changes. 4) Proteins identified 
were assessed for their dominant expression tissues based 
on published human and mouse tissue expression data. The 
abundances of brain and liver proteins in CSF were compared 
with those in plasma. 5) Finally protein changes were inte-
grated with the genomics profiling of mRNA changes in nor-
mal versus HD brain. Results from each step of analysis are 
presented sequentially. 
Analysis of Proteomics Data-Search engine performance 
and <rs type="software">PeptideProphet</rs> details (25) were inspected (supplemen-
tal Fig. S2A) to assure that sensitivity and error distributions 
were sufficient to determine correct and incorrect identifica-
tions from Labs 2, 3, and 4. The quality of data quantitation 
was determined by examining MA plots, histograms of light 
labeled/heavy labeled ratios at the peptide level, and histo-
grams of the HD-early/control, HD-mid/control, and HD-mid/ 
HD-early ratios at the protein level (supplemental Fig. S2, 
B-D). We observed that the distributions of logarithms of 
ratios are around 0 before normalization for all experiments 
except two interrogations from Lab 3. The log ratios for these 
two data sets were normalized to have a median of 0. 
Lab 1 used a DIGE method (see "Experimental Proce-
dures") and quantitated a large number of fluorescent spots. 
Only those spots found to have significantly different changes 
based on fluorescence between the HD and control CSF were 
selected for tandem MS analysis. As a result, a total of 19 
unique proteins for 42 spots were identified based on the 
MS/MS data (Table II), each of which is a putative biomarker </p>

<p>candidate. As a verification of these protein identifications 
("Experimental Procedures"), we compared them with the 
results provided by Lab 1 using the Mascot search engine 
(supplemental Table S9) and found that there is a high con-
sistency between the two results. In addition, proteins from 
more spots have been identified in this study. Lab 2 is the only 
lab that performed individual (non-pooled) interrogation. 335 
confident protein groups (with <rs type="software">ProteinProphet</rs> probability 0.9) 
were found and of these, 319 were quantitated using spectral 
counting (35) of highly confident peptide spectra ("Experimen-
tal Procedures"). Lab 3 pooled samples by disease status and 
analyzed by d 0 /d 3 acetylation of the N terminus of the pep-
tides. 263 confident protein groups were found after aligning 
the three experiments using <rs type="software">ProteinProphet</rs>. After protein ra-
tios were inferred from individual experiments, 161 were con-
fidently quantitated. Lab 4 pooled samples by disease status 
and gender. In three pairwise comparisons, proteins in pooled 
CSF of two disease statuses were differentially labeled with 
light and heavy acrylamide on cysteine residues. Because a 
more extensive prefractionation strategy was used, these 
data resulted in identification of the majority of proteins (1179 
groups) reported in this study of which 377 were confidently 
quantitated by the Q3 algorithm (27) ("Experimental Proce-
dures"). In addition, Lab 4's label-free analysis using AMT 
methods (37) identified and quantitated 277 protein groups 
(Table II), 100 of which are not quantitated by the labeled 
approach (Table III). 
Overall the number of proteins identified is highly related to 
the number of sample fractions and to the number of MS/MS 
spectra obtained. Because of the limited publication space 
and the large amount of data, all the confident protein groups 
identified and their quantitation results from each lab are 
provided in supplemental spreadsheets (supplemental Table 
S3). For each protein group (probability 0.9) identified, the 
number of total and unique peptide identifications are pro-
vided in the spreadsheets. p values (Lab 1 and Lab 2) and 
standard deviations (Lab 3 and Lab 4) are also included to 
indicate the significant changes and accuracy of the quanti-
tations. In practice, one can use these values as filters to </p>

<p>TABLE II 
Numbers of peptides and protein groups identified with 
different methods </p>

<p>Methods 
Total 
peptides a </p>

<p>Unique 
peptides a </p>

<p>Unique 
protein 
groups </p>

<p>Quantitated 
unique protein 
groups </p>

<p>Lab 1 
2,041 
403 
19 b 
19 b 
Lab 2 
122,353 
3,556 
335 
319 
Lab 3 
19,563 
1,696 
263 
161 
Lab 4 (labeled) 
143,405 
9,397 
1,179 
377 
Lab 4 (unlabeled) 
2,502 
1,357 
277 
277 </p>

<p>a Number of peptides with FDR 0.1 for Lab 1 and PeptideProphet 
probability 0.75 for Labs 2-4. 
b These are number of unique proteins, not protein groups. </p>

<p>TABLE III 
Numbers of overlapping protein groups identified and quantitated 
among five methods </p>

<p>Methods 
Lab 1 
Lab 2 
Lab 3 
Lab 4 
labeled </p>

<p>Lab 4 
unlabeled </p>

<p>Lab 1 
23 (23) a 22 (22) b 20 (19) 
23 (20) 
20 (20) 
Lab 2 
339 (327) 190 (144) 300 (197) 187 (183) 
Lab 3 
267 (170) 235 (137) 164 (135) 
Lab 4 labeled 
1158 (376) 293 (199) 
Lab 4 unlabeled 
298 (298) </p>

<p>a The underlined numbers are the total of protein groups identified 
and quantified by each laboratory. These numbers are a little different 
with those in Table II because of the regrouping of proteins when 
combining all data across laboratories. 
b The numbers of overlapping protein groups quantitated are 
shown in parentheses. </p>

<p>Huntington Disease Cerebrospinal Fluid </p>



<p>generate lists by lab for protein groups that significantly 
change with disease status. Because of limitations in the 
accuracy and comprehensiveness of any one data set due to 
the complex nature of the samples (19, 30) and current tech-
nology (42), a combination of these results across labs using 
completely different experimental designs and proteomics 
platforms will improve the accuracy, consistency, and com-
prehensiveness of protein candidate lists. Here we used a 
method described under "Experimental Procedures" of first 
performing a comprehensive search on all applicable data 
and then synthesizing the quantitation results. 
The integrated analysis of all proteomics data was per-
formed by a comprehensive search combining Lab 2, Lab 3, 
and Lab 4 labeled and unlabeled data. This resulted in a total 
of 12,430 peptides and 1574 high confidence protein groups 
identified (supplemental Table S3). The greatest overlaps in 
both proteins identified and proteins quantitated are between 
Lab 2 and Lab 4 labeled methods (Table III). From the across-
lab comparison, 577 protein groups (corresponding to 762 
genes) have been quantitated by at least one experimental 
method, and 301 protein groups (419 genes) have been quan-
titated by more than one method (Fig. 1). We synthesized 
protein ratios across laboratories by methods described un-
der "Experimental Procedures." The resulting score (sum of 
z-scores) estimates the relative protein change in the HD 
versus normal CSF. Specifically a negative sum of z-scores 
indicates that the protein declines in the HD CSF when com-
pared with normal, and a positive sum of z-scores indicates </p>

<p>that the protein inclines. This score for each identified protein 
is shown in supplemental Table S3. 
Annotation of HD CSF Proteins with Human and Mouse 
Tissue Expression Data-The general perception of HD is that 
the most important clinical signs and symptoms can be traced 
to neurodegeneration in the brain. Furthermore by definition, 
the most powerful and useful biomarkers are intimately re-
lated to the etiology of a disease. This raises the question of 
the precise source of the proteins detected in CSF and 
whether they can be traced to brain and substructures within 
the brain or they arise from other sources. Formally one 
cannot definitively identify the source of each particular CSF 
protein. Direct evidence must come from some type of tracer 
experiment. But we can begin to make a circumstantial argu-
ment that a substantial fraction of our identified CSF proteins 
are based upon mRNA expression patterns. 
Several human brain gene expression profiling data have 
been published in recent years (29, 43). We selected an ex-
pression data set that was generated by Ge et al. (29) using a 
total of 36 types of normal human tissues. Data on four 
regions of brain (amygdala, corpus callosum, hippocampus, 
and thalamus) and other adult tissues were selected and 
combined with data from a comprehensive study carried out 
on four parts of normal human brain (caudate, cerebellum, 
and BA4 and BA9 cortex) (2) ("Experimental Procedures"). 
Based on the algorithm described under "Experimental Pro-
cedures," 1941 tissue-specific proteins are identified: 445 are 
brain-and 225 are liver-specific (supplemental Table S6). 
Integration with the CSF proteomics data found that 298 
proteins/genes of 1574 are tissue markers, among which two 
major species are brain-specific (30%) and liver-specific 
(33%) (Table IV). One intriguing question is how represent-
ative these proteins are compared with plasma. Starting from 
a list of 3020 proteins identified with two or more peptides 
provided by the Human Proteome Organization Plasma Pro-
teome Project, we aligned the 1941 tissue markers and found 
that of 414 proteins that are annotated as tissue-specific 
proteins 17% are brain-and 53% are liver-specific (Table IV). 
Therefore, brain-specific proteins are 1.8-fold enriched in CSF 
over plasma, whereas liver-specific proteins are about half as 
represented in CSF as in plasma. The Pearson's 2 test shows 
that brain-specific proteins significantly predominate in CSF </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>protein groups </p>

<p>genes </p>

<p>counts </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Number of total protein groups and genes identified and 
quantitated by different numbers of methods. Protein groups are in 
solid bars, and genes are in empty bars. </p>

<p>TABLE IV 
Comparisons of brain-and liver-specific proteins in CSF and plasma </p>

<p>Tissue </p>

<p>Marker genes detected in 
-Fold of enrichment 
(CSF/plasma) 
p value a 
CSF (all 298) 
Plasma (all 414) </p>

<p>Number 
Percentage 
Number 
Percentage </p>

<p>Brain 
88 
0.3 (88/298) 
71 
0.17 (71/414) 
1.8 
0.0001 
Liver 
97 
0.33 (97/298) 
113 
0.53 (113/414) 
0.6 
0.15 </p>

<p>a p value is based on Pearson's 2 test to evaluate the significance of differences of representativeness of brain (liver) proteins in CSF and 
plasma. Numbers of brain (88) versus non-brain (210) marker genes in CSF were tested against those numbers in plasma (71 versus 340). 
Likewise for liver proteins, numbers of liver (97) versus non-liver (201) proteins in CSF were tested against those numbers in plasma (113 versus 
301). </p>

<p>Huntington Disease Cerebrospinal Fluid </p>

<p>Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics 8.3 457 </p>

<p>compared with plasma (Table IV). This observation can also 
be confirmed by performing the same analysis using the 
normal mouse gene expression data from Zapala et al. (39) 
that covered 20 neural tissues from the adult mouse central 
nervous system plus 14 tissues from other parts of the body 
(data not shown). 
Next we examined whether the brain-specific proteins are 
specific to any regions of the brain. Seven regions of the brain 
were included in this human tissue array data: amygdala, 
corpus callosum, hippocampus, thalamus, caudate, cerebel-
lum, and cortex. Among 88 CSF proteins considered to be 
brain-specific, 29 are cerebellum-specific, 26 are cortex-spe-
cific, 12 are amygdala-specific, eight are caudate-specific, 
and 13 belong to the other regions. This suggests that more 
than 60% of these brain-specific proteins are specifically 
expressed in cerebellum and frontal cortex. 
To have an overview of the relative abundance of these 
tissue-specific proteins/genes in CSF, we used the overall 
spectral count for each protein as a surrogate for the concen-
tration. When the spectral counts were sorted in descending 
order, most of the liver-specific proteins (colored in green in 
Fig. 2A) show up at the top of the list. The brain-specific 
proteins (red) are distributed from upper middle to the bottom. 
The observation that liver-specific proteins are abundant 
makes sense because most CSF proteins come from plasma 
in which liver-derived proteins are highly represented. 
Finally we evaluated the trends of changes for these tissue-
specific proteins in normal versus HD patients. When 150 
tissue-specific proteins were sorted by sums of z-scores (Fig. 
2B), there is a clear bias of liver proteins (colored in green) at 
higher scores and brain proteins at lower scores, indicating 
that liver-specific proteins tend to increase and brain-specific 
proteins decrease in HD CSF. The p value based on Wilcoxon 
test on sums of z-scores of brain-specific proteins versus 
other proteins is 6.3 10 9 , and that on sums of z-scores of 
liver-specific proteins versus others is 3.3 10 8 . This result 
indicates that the trends of changes in HD CSF from the 
normal are significant for brain-and liver-specific proteins. 
Comparison of Protein Changes with Human HD Brain 
Transcriptional Profiling Data-Gene expression changes in 
four brain regions of Huntington disease patients have been 
studied by Hodges et al. (2). Their results revealed that 21, 1, 
and 3% of probe sets were significantly differentially ex-
pressed in HD caudate, cerebellum, and BA4, respectively, 
and that no significant changes were found for BA9. An im-
mediate question raised is what the concordance of changes 
in HD patients is between the proteomics and microarray 
studies. Among the genes that are significantly differentially 
expressed in HD caudate, cerebellum, and BA4 cortex, 665, 
57, and 165 of their products are identified in CSF, respec-
tively. Because the most significant mRNA changes occur in 
HD caudate and the expression profile of HD BA4 is strikingly 
similar to that of HD caudate (2), we compared all CSF protein 
changes with HD caudate data and additionally looked at </p>

<p>cerebellum-and cortex-specific proteins when mRNA expres-
sion data were available. 
To examine the concordance of changes, we used a sign 
test that compares the negative or positive signs of sums of 
z-scores from our proteomics study with the log 2 -fold 
changes from the microarray study because in both data sets 
positive values indicate an increasing trend of proteins/genes 
in HD status and negative values indicate a decreasing trend. 
Therefore, proteins/genes with these two values in the same 
signs were considered concordant. Overall about half (111 of 
227) of protein groups that have both sums of z-scores and 
significant mRNA changes are concordant (Table V). Among 
the 227 proteins, 47 have tissue annotations, and 16 are 
brain-specific. We found that 13 of 16 (81%) brain-specific 
proteins are concordant. However, only 42 and 47% of the 
proteins are concordant for non-brain tissue-specific proteins 
and proteins with unknown tissue origin, respectively. The 2 
tests on the numbers of concordant and discordant for 1) 
brain-specific versus other tissue-specific proteins and 2) </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Patterns of tissue-specific proteins in CSF. A, proteins 
were sorted in descending order by spectral counts that reflect the 
relative concentration in CSF with highest concentrations at the top. 
B, proteins were sorted in descending order by sums of z-scores that 
indicate the trends of changes in HD-affected individuals relative to 
control with the most increasing one at the top. Red, brain-specific 
proteins; green, liver-specific proteins; black, muscle-and heart-
specific proteins; white, other tissue-specific proteins. </p>

<p>Huntington Disease Cerebrospinal Fluid </p>



<p>brain-specific versus those that are not tissue markers both 
gave a p value 0.024, indicating that the consistency of 
expression changes in HD status measured by a proteomics 
and genomics approach are significant for brain-specific pro-
teins compared with other proteins (Table V). This concord-
ance suggests that these proteins might be derived from 
neurons or glial cells in the brain. Moreover 11 of the 13 
brain-specific genes that have concordant mRNA and protein 
changes show the trend of declining in HD, consistent with 
the above observation that brain-specific proteins tend to 
decline in HD samples. 
The Most Significantly Changed Proteins in HD CSF Based 
on Proteomics Data-With sums of z-scores that estimate 
protein changes between disease states across labs (Table 
VI), we were able to select 20 most increasing and 20 most 
decreasing proteins in HD CSF (relative to controls). This 
selection is naturally biased toward proteins that are ob-
served by many labs and that have consistent trends of 
changes in HD CSF. 
Among the identified proteins, 12 of them (CHGB, SIAE, 
IDS, NRXN3, GSN, ENDOD1, GRIA4, GGH, GC, C4B, and 
PRNP; see Table VI for the full protein names) have a trend of 
declining with disease progression (control HD-early 
HD-mid). Among the most increasing proteins, seven of them 
(C1QC, HPX, TPI1, PKM2/PKLR, LYZ, FAM3C, and LMAN2) 
follow the trend consistent with elevating as disease 
progresses (control HD-early HD-mid). C1QC, C2, and 
C3 are complement factors. PGLYRP2 and APOA4 are also 
associated with the inflammatory pathway. SERPINC1, 
APOH, FGG, FGB, and KNG1 are related to the coagulation 
system that cross-talks to the immune system (44). The im-
mune system is activated in Huntington disease patients (45), 
and recently Dalrymple et al. (10), who used a proteomics 
approach to profile plasma rather than CSF in Huntington 
disease, found several inflammatory proteins. Because CSF is </p>

<p>a filtration of plasma, our observations are consistent with 
their findings. 
Integration of these most altered proteins in HD CSF with 
the tissue expression data shows that although most increas-
ing proteins are liver-specific only three of the decreasing 
proteins are brain-specific (Table VII). This result is expected 
given that the method we used to generate this list of 40 
proteins is biased toward more abundant proteins and given 
the above result suggesting that most liver-specific proteins 
are abundant and increased in HD CSF, whereas most brain-
specific proteins are decreased, but not all of them are abun-
dant enough to be selected. However, some of the decreased 
proteins may come from other substructures of the brain. For 
example, CHGB has the highest mRNA level in the mouse. 
TTR, ENPP2, and GGH are choroid plexus-specific genes 
according to the mouse array data and Allen Brain Atlas data. 
Moreover although not exclusively expressed in the brain, 
MEGF8, ALDOC, ENPP2, ENDOD1, and PRNP have the high-
est mRNA expression level in the brain. In addition, TTR, 
CHGB, and PAM have high mRNA expressions in the brain 
when compared with the median expression level. It is pos-
sible that a majority of these proteins found in CSF were 
derived from the brain. 
The changes of three brain-specific proteins (EPHA4, IDS, 
and NRXN3) in HD CSF agree with their transcriptional changes 
in HD brain. In addition, CHGB, ZNF503, PAM, ENPP2, GGH, 
and PRNP have the same trend at both the protein and mRNA 
levels. These proteins are potentially interesting biomarker can-
didates once validated. Many liver-specific proteins shown to 
be increased in HD CSF according to the proteomics analysis 
are not significantly changed based on transcriptional profiling 
of the brain. However, these proteins can provide additional 
information on the peripheral manifestations of Huntington dis-
ease and may be used in combination with the brain-specific 
CSF proteins as biomarkers. 
Assessing Cross-lab Comparability-As shown above, the 
labeled methods of Lab 2 and Lab 4 have the greatest overlap 
in both protein identification and quantitation (Table III), and 
301 protein groups have been quantitated by more than one 
method (Fig. 1). Questions we addressed include the con-
cordance of protein ratios and the concordance of each lab-
oratory with the overall trends of brain-and liver-specific 
protein changes identified by the integrated analysis. 
Scatter plots of relative protein abundance ratios between 
two disease states across different proteomics methods are 
shown in Fig. 3. The apparent low proteome-wide correlation 
of protein ratios should be expected given the nature of data 
we were interrogating. Specifically whenever high dimen-
sional analyses such as proteomics (or genomics) are used for 
comparisons, as in our example, one expects that most pro-
teins do not change between the two conditions (HD versus 
control). For these proteins the sources of variation are ran-
dom (from experiments) and so will not correlate across lab-
oratories. Only proteins that systematically changed as a re-</p>

<p>TABLE V 
Concordance of proteomics and genomics data for brain-specific 
proteins, non-brain specific proteins, and proteins from unknown 
tissue origins </p>

<p>NA, not applicable. </p>

<p>Proteins 
Concordant Discordant Total 
Percentage of 
concordance </p>

<p>p 
value </p>

<p>Brain-specific 
13 
3 
16 
0.81 
NA 
Non-brain 
specific </p>

<p>13 
18 
31 
0.42 
0.024 a </p>

<p>Unknown origin 
85 
95 
180 
0.47 
0.019 b 
All 
111 
116 
227 
0.49 
NA </p>

<p>a This p value is from the Pearson's 2 test of brain-specific proteins 
versus non-brain specific proteins. Numbers of concordant and dis-
cordant brain-specific proteins versus the two numbers for non-brain-
specific proteins were used for the test. 
b This p value is from the Pearson's 2 test of brain-specific pro-
teins versus proteins of unknown sources. Numbers of concordant 
and discordant brain-specific proteins versus the two numbers for 
proteins with unknown tissue origin were used for the test. </p>

<p>Huntington Disease Cerebrospinal Fluid </p>

<p>Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics 8.3 459 </p>

<p>TABLE VI 
The most significantly changed proteins in CSF of HD-affected individuals compared with unaffected ones </p>

<p>Accession </p>

<p>number </p>

<p>Gene </p>

<p>symbol 
Description 
/unique </p>

<p>peptides </p>

<p>identified </p>

<p>Coverage 
z-scores </p>

<p>for each </p>

<p>lab a </p>

<p>Decreasing proteins </p>

<p>IPI00008318 EPHA4 
Ephrin type-A receptor 4 precursor 
566/16 
26.6 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00022432 
TTR 
Transthyretin precursor 
19501/18 
77.6 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00647027 
CHGB chromogranin B/Secretogranin-1 precursor 
74.7 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00006601 
CHGB chromogranin B/Secretogranin-1 precursor 
67.9 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00010949 </p>

<p>IPI00383385 </p>

<p>IPI00759728 </p>

<p>SIAE 
Isoform I of Sialate O-acteylesterase </p>

<p>precursor 
141/9 
6.9-23.7 1 2 3 4 5 </p>

<p>IPI00027310 MEGF8 
Isoform I of multiple epidermal growth </p>

<p>factor-like domain 8 
967/38 
23.3 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00011229 
CTSD 
Cathepsin D precursor 
1231/18 
52.7 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00026104 
IDS 
Isoform long of iduronate 2-sulfatase </p>

<p>precursor 
285/10 
25.3 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-3 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00418262 ALDOC 
Fructose-bisphosphate aldolase C 
743/23 
58.1 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00177543 </p>

<p>IPI00040158 </p>

<p>IPI00219041 </p>

<p>IPI00749176 </p>

<p>IPI00219042 </p>

<p>IPI00219043 </p>

<p>IPI00749003 </p>

<p>PAM 
Isoform 1 of peptidyl-glycine alpha </p>

<p>amidating monooxygenase precursor 
526/28 
14.1-63.6 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-3 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00216728 NRXN3 
Neurexin 3-alpha 
830/42 
37.4 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00304992 </p>

<p>IPI00419970 
ZNF503 
zinc finger protein 503 
737/5 
10.4-10.9 1 2 3 4 5 </p>

<p>IPI00005794 
PGCP 
Blood plasma glutamate carboxypeptidase </p>

<p>precursor 
243/13 
32.3 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00007664 
PGCP 
Blood plasma glutamate carboxypeptidase </p>

<p>precursor 
237/13 
39.4 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00156171 ENPP2 
Isoform 1 of Ectonucleotide </p>

<p>pyrophosphatase/ 
3019/41 
61.4 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00026314 
GSN 
Isoform 1 of gelsolin precursor 
5264/38 
62.7 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00001952 ENDOD1 
Endonuclease domain-containing 1 protein </p>

<p>precursor 
406/15 
48 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00007632 
GRIA4 
Glutamate receptor 4 precursor 
201/10 
12.9 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00023728 
GGH 
Gamma-glutamyl hydrolase precursor 
230/11 
44.3 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00555812 
GC 
Vitamin D-binding protein 
5396/52 
88.8 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00022284 </p>

<p>IPI00382843 
PRNP 
Major prion protein precursor 
331/6 
27.7-31.2 1 2 3 4 5 </p>

<p>IPI00418163 
C4B 
complement component 4B preproprotein 
5611/93 
65.7 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>Huntington Disease Cerebrospinal Fluid </p>



<p>TABLE VI-continued </p>

<p>Increasing proteins </p>

<p>IPI00032179 SERPINC1 
Antithrombin III variant 
1893/28 
60.6 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00298828 
APOH 
beta-2 glycoprotein 1 precursor 
876/24 
78 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00021891 </p>

<p>IPI00219713 
FGG 
Isoform of gamma B fibrinogen gamma </p>

<p>chain precursor 
448/22 
55.6-57.7 1 2 3 4 5 </p>

<p>IPI00163207 </p>

<p>IPI00394992 
PGLYRP2 
Isoform 1 of N-acetylmuramoyl-alanine </p>

<p>amidase precursor 
284/17 
45.3-49.8 1 2 3 4 5 </p>

<p>IPI00304273 APOA4 
apolipoprotein A4 precursor 
1630/37 
80.1 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00783987 
C3 
complement C3 precursor 
13720/137 
86 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00298497 
FGB 
fibrinogen beta chain precursor 
635/25 
58.9 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00032328 
KNG1 
Isoform HMW of kininogen-1 precursor 
1416/32 
43.3 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00215894 
KNG1 
Isoform HMW of kininogen-1 precursor 
1467/30 
60.4 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00022394 
C1QC 
complement component 1, q subunit, c </p>

<p>chain precursor 
303/6 
34.7 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00303963 
C2 
complement C2 precursor 
790/32 
52.5 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00022488 
HPX 
Hemopexin 
5047/32 
73.4 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00465028 
TPI1 
(Triosephosphate isomerase 
480/18 
77.5 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00029658 </p>

<p>IPI00220813 </p>

<p>IPI00220814 </p>

<p>IPI00220815 </p>

<p>EFEMP1 
Isoform 1 of EGF-containing fibulin-like </p>

<p>extracellular matrix protein 1 precursor 
1137/21 
55.2-56.1 1 2 3 4 5 </p>

<p>IPI00002147 CHI3L1 
chitinase-3-like protein 1 precursor 
1434/27 
72.1 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00220644 </p>

<p>IPI00027165 </p>

<p>IPI00334779 </p>

<p>IPI00743713 </p>

<p>IPI00479186 </p>

<p>IPI00604528 </p>

<p>IPI00607698 </p>

<p>IPI00735524 </p>

<p>IPI00783061 </p>

<p>IPI00784179 </p>

<p>PKM2/ </p>

<p>PKLR </p>

<p>Isoform M1 of Pyruvate kinase isozymes </p>

<p>M1/M2; Isoform R-type of Pyruvate kinase </p>

<p>isozymes R/L </p>

<p>614/32 
17.5-67.7 12 345 </p>

<p>IPI00019038 
LYZ 
Lysozyme C precursor 
86/10 
62.2 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00022420 </p>

<p>IPI00480192 </p>

<p>IPI00744715 </p>

<p>RBP4 
Plasma retinol-binding protein precursor 
2089/11 
72.6-73.4 1 2 3 4 5 </p>

<p>IPI00021923 FAM3C 
Protein FAM3C precursor 
1082/17 
69.2 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00328609 SERPINA4 
Kallistatin precursor 
415/21 
61.4 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>IPI00009950 LMAN2 
Vesicular integral-membrane protein 
278/17 
63.8 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>Accession </p>

<p>number </p>

<p>Gene </p>

<p>symbol 
Description 
/unique </p>

<p>peptides </p>

<p>identified </p>

<p>Coverage 
z-scores </p>

<p>for each </p>

<p>lab a </p>

<p>a Each bar in this column represents the sums of z-scores based on logarithm of early/control and mid/control ratios for each lab. The 
negative scores are plotted in blue, and the positive scores are in red. </p>

<p>Huntington Disease Cerebrospinal Fluid </p>

<p>Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics 8.3 461 </p>

<p>sult of differences in the case and the control are concordant. 
Thus, instead of inspecting the correlation of all data points in 
Fig. 3, one should focus on those ratios with higher magnitude 
and determine the concordance among them as these should 
be enriched for proteins having the systematic change. We 
can see that this trend of changes is rather consistent among 
laboratories for the 40 most altered proteins, especially for 
those increasing proteins that are more abundant and quan-
tified by more laboratories (Table VI). Concordance was 
strongest among laboratories identifying the largest number 
of proteins. 
We also evaluated whether single laboratories could dem-
onstrate the overall trend of changes in HD versus normal for 
brain-versus liver-specific proteins. As shown in Table VIII, </p>

<p>each lab's sum of z-scores are negative for brain-specific 
proteins and positive for liver-specific proteins, and the dif-
ferences are statistically significant based on Wilcoxon test. 
This suggests that all laboratories are concordant in observing 
the trend that brain-specific proteins tend to decrease and 
liver-specific proteins tend to increase in HD CSF. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, we report an extensive list of proteins identi-
fied in CSF with a high degree of confidence and provide their 
concentrations in human HD relative to control CSF. Because 
of the complexity of the CSF proteome and the current shot-
gun proteomics technology (42), there is a limitation in the 
accuracy and comprehensiveness of a single proteomics ex-</p>

<p>TABLE VII 
Integration of HD CSF most significantly changed proteins with tissue expression data and HD-brain transcriptional data </p>

<p>NA, not available. </p>

<p>Protein 
mRNA changes 
(HD vs. control) </p>

<p>Specific 
tissue </p>

<p>Highest mRNA 
expression tissue </p>

<p>Expression ratio a </p>

<p>Brain/median 
Liver/median </p>

<p>A. Decreasing proteins 
EPHA4 
Decrease 
Brain 
Brain 
41.2 
0.7 
CHGB 
Decrease 
NA 
Pituitary 
23.9 
0.8 
TTR 
No change 
NA 
Liver 
145.7 
218.9 
SIAE 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
MEGF8 
NA 
NA 
Brain 
5.2 
2.1 
CTSD 
Increase 
NA 
Lung 
1.1 
1.8 
IDS 
Decrease 
Brain 
Brain 
10.2 
0.5 
ALDOC 
No change 
NA 
Brain 
12.2 
1.5 
ZNF503 
Decrease 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NRXN3 
Decrease 
Brain 
Brain 
142.6 
0.41 
PAM 
Decrease 
NA 
Salivary 
1.9 
0.11 
PGCP 
Increase 
NA 
Thyroid 
1.2 
1.5 
ENPP2 
Decrease 
NA 
Brain 
10 
0.5 
GSN 
Increase 
NA 
Bladder 
1.2 
0.2 
ENDOD1 
NA 
NA 
Brain 
4.1 
0.6 
GRIA4 
No change 
NA 
Pancreas 
1.8 
1.4 
GGH 
Decrease 
NA 
Liver 
2.7 
8.1 
GC 
No change 
Liver 
Liver 
4.2 
154.7 
C4B 
Increase 
Liver 
Liver 
1.3 
15.1 
PRNP 
Decrease 
NA 
Brain 
2.82 
0.58 
B. Increasing proteins 
SERPINC1 
No change 
Liver 
Liver 
10.6 
688.9 
APOH 
No change 
Liver 
Liver 
16.2 
603.9 
FGG 
No change 
Liver 
Liver 
6 
231.4 
PGLYRP2 
No change 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
APOA4 
No change 
Intestine 
Intestine 
3.7 
15 
C3 
Increase 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
FGB 
No change 
Liver 
Liver 
7.5 
352.7 
KNG1 
No change 
Liver 
Liver 
6.7 
581.3 
C1QC 
No change 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
C2 
NA 
Liver 
Liver 
NA 
NA 
HPX 
No change 
Liver 
Liver 
2.1 
190 
TPI1 
Decrease 
NA 
Adrenal 
1.9 
1 
EFEMP1 
Increase 
NA 
Placenta 
1.8 
0.15 
CHI3L1 
Increase 
Liver 
Liver 
2.1 
26.8 
PKM2 and PKLR 
Increase 
NA 
Brain 
2.5 
0.1 
LYZ 
No change 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
RBP4 
Decrease 
Liver 
Liver 
10.7 
242.9 
SERPINA4 
No change 
Liver 
Liver 
1 
13.5 
FAM3C 
Decrease 
NA 
Intestine 
2.7 
0.9 
LMAN2 
No change 
NA 
Thyroid 
0.6 
1.2 </p>

<p>a Expression ratios are calculated from the human tissue transcription data by dividing the brain or liver MAS5 signal by the median MAS5 
signal of each tissue. This value represents how many -fold the mRNA expression level of the brain or liver tissue is above the average. </p>

<p>Huntington Disease Cerebrospinal Fluid </p>



<p>periment. It was suggested that, similarly to gene expression 
profiling, which cannot draw meaningful conclusions from a 
single quantitative gene expression profile, multiple profiles 
from related samples allow extraction of signature patterns 
containing diagnostic or functional information (42, 46). For 
example, to comprehensively characterize the human CSF 
proteome, Pan et al. (30) have used several different separa-
tion strategies and proteomics platforms. The analysis of the 
same samples by four different proteomics platforms pro-
vides a rather in-depth characterization of HD CSF. 
From a practical standpoint, the protein changes identified 
in CSF of Huntington disease patients are candidate biomar-
kers that may be useful for tracking the HD progression or as 
surrogate end points in clinical trials. Integrating results be-
tween laboratories provided confirmation of both protein </p>

<p>identification and quantitation. The universality of our findings 
will require further validation with additional CSF samples 
using specific technologies such as multiple reaction moni-
toring and ELISA rather than shotgun proteomics. 
Before a candidate protein can serve as a biomarker, it is 
important to understand its role in the pathophysiology of the 
disease process. In the case of Huntington disease this is not 
yet possible because the exact sequence of pathological 
events downstream from expression of mutant huntingtin pro-
tein remains elusive. However, the predominant view is that 
the most clinically important signs and symptoms of HD relate 
to neurodegeneration and dysfunction in the brain. The hall-
mark neuropathology of HD is degeneration of medium spiny 
neurons in the striatum accompanied by extensive astrocyto-
sis (47) and microgliosis (12). Gene expression profiling of 
postmortem human HD brain has been performed using stri-
atal tissue as well as cerebellum and two cortical areas (2, 6). 
The known pathology and gene expression changes provide a 
perspective from which to view the proteomic changes. 
To identify the most probable origin of the proteins de-
tected in CSF, we queried a published microarray survey of 
gene expression in human tissues. Although the assumptions 
and methods used were somewhat crude and only constitute 
circumstantial evidence for the source tissue, this created a 
very biologically plausible list of "tissue markers." Integrating 
the expression data tissue markers with the CSF proteomics 
results revealed that many of the most abundant CSF proteins </p>

<p>A HD-early / control </p>

<p>B HD-mid / control </p>

<p>C HD-mid / HD-early </p>

<p>Lab 2 
Lab 3 
Lab 4-labeled </p>

<p>Lab 2 
Lab 3 
Lab 4-labeled </p>

<p>Lab </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Lab </p>

<p>4-labeled </p>

<p>Lab </p>

<p>4-unlabeled </p>

<p>-1.5 -0.5 
0.5 
1.5 
-2 
0 
2 
4 
-1.5 
-0.5 
0.5 
1.5 </p>

<p>-1.5 -0.5 
0.5 1.0 
-4 
-2 
0 
2 </p>

<p>-2 0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Lab </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Lab </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 -2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Lab 
4-labeled Lab </p>

<p>4-labeled </p>

<p>Lab 
4-unlabeled Lab </p>

<p>4-unlabeled </p>

<p>-1.5 
-0.5 0.5 1.5 </p>

<p>-4 -2 </p>

<p>0 
2 4 </p>

<p>-1.0 
0 -1.0 -1.5 -0.5 </p>

<p>0.5 1.5 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-2 
0 -4 
4 -2 0 2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>-1.0 
0 
1.0 
-4 -2 0 
2 
4 
-1.5 -0.5 0.5 
1.5 </p>

<p>-1.0 
0 
1.0 </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Correlations of relative pro-
tein abundance ratios of two disease 
statuses among different proteomics 
methods. Both axes are the following 
three ratios on a logarithm scale based 
on different quantitation methods: HD-
early/control (A), HD-mid/control (B), 
and HD-mid/HD-early (C). </p>

<p>TABLE VIII 
The significant differences of protein changes for brain-specific and 
liver-specific proteins observed by each laboratory </p>

<p>Methods 
Brain-specific 
Liver-specific 
p value c 
Count a Mean b Count a Mean b </p>

<p>Lab 2 
9 
1.28 
27 
0.96 
0.0039 
Lab 3 
6 
1.15 
21 
0.25 
0.025 
Lab 4 (labeled) 
9 
0.94 
31 
1.64 
0.0002 
Lab 4 (unlabeled) 
8 
1.26 
30 
1.26 
0.0009 </p>

<p>a Numbers of proteins that are counted in the test. 
b Mean sum of z-scores of the individual lab. 
c p value is derived by performing Wilcoxon test on the sum of 
z-scores of brain-and liver-specific proteins for each individual lab. </p>

<p>Huntington Disease Cerebrospinal Fluid </p>

<p>Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics 8.3 463 </p>

<p>were probably derived from the liver. This is consistent with 
the known origin of CSF, which is a complex filtrate of blood 
produced by the choroid plexus. Importantly many proteins 
likely to have been derived from the brain were also detected 
in CSF. This was not seen in a re-examination of a protein 
component list for blood plasma. In plasma, liver-specific 
proteins are also highly over-represented, whereas very few 
brain-specific proteins are detected. The over-representation 
of brain-specific proteins in CSF supports the hypothesis that 
it is feasible to monitor some aspects of the health of the brain 
using CSF. This has important implications for biomarker 
discovery in neurological disease. However, proving that 
these proteins are derived from brain tissue is difficult and 
requires some type of labeling experiment. 
The overall trends between changes in concentrations of 
brain-specific proteins and their corresponding mRNAs in HD 
brain tissues were consistent. This provides further support 
for the hypothesis that the concentration of some proteins in 
HD CSF may provide a window into the health of the brain 
and that CSF may be a fruitful source of HD biomarkers. 
However, to the extent that the candidate brain-specific 
proteins can be traced to a particular region of the brain, 
most appear to be cerebellum-and cortex-specific rather 
than specific to the striatum. This may be because the 
greater mass and surface area of the cortex and cerebellum 
provide more exposure to the CSF. 
Two noticeable trends in the data were for the brain-spe-
cific proteins to decrease in concentration in HD CSF, 
whereas most proteins we detected with higher concentra-
tions in HD CSF were functionally associated with the immune 
system. The latter may relate to astrocytosis, microgliosis, 
and neuroinflammation. Neuroinflammation is a common 
component of many neurodegenerative diseases, and these 
changes are unlikely to be specific to Huntington disease. 
Thus, although we did not detect a large number of protein 
changes that can be directly linked to striatal degeneration in 
HD, we did detect a general trend for brain-related proteins to 
decrease in HD CSF, and we detected increases in proteins 
that may reflect neuroinflammatory processes. Both trends 
are consistent with the known neuropathology of HD and 
bolster the biological relevance of our findings. 
However, an interesting alternative mechanism may cause 
or contribute to the increase of blood-derived proteins and 
decrease of brain-derived proteins in HD CSF. Disruption of 
the blood-brain barrier is widely accepted in inflammatory 
conditions such as neurosystemic lupus erythematosus (48, 
49) and multiple sclerosis (50, 51) and increasingly in condi-
tions traditionally seen as degenerative with secondary neu-
roinflammation, like Alzheimer disease (52). Interestingly mi-
croglial activation and the presence of inflammatory cytokines 
could alter the properties of brain microvascular endothelial 
cells and the tight junctions that link them (53, 54), raising the 
possibility that the blood-brain barrier is also disturbed in 
Huntington disease patients. This hypothesis is consistent </p>

<p>with the observed differences of brain-and blood-derived 
proteins in HD CSF. The integrity of the blood-brain barrier in 
HD can be examined by detecting changes of brain proteins 
in HD versus normal plasma or more directly using magnetic 
resonance imaging. 
Because of the large source of variation among multiple 
laboratories, no general consensus can be made with regard 
to the specific ranking of proteins or their magnitude of 
change. In our experiments the statistical significance was not 
derived from establishing the significance of the top ranked 
individual proteins by traditional FDR (55) but rather based on 
interrogating the rankings based on protein sets using GSEA 
(28) methods where the gene sets were derived from external 
transcriptional data. We also found that results in this study 
are most strongly supported by laboratories that obtained the 
greatest depth of protein coverage. Our results suggest that 
additional biomarker studies should focus on designs that 
obtain the greatest depth of coverage and that interrogate the 
data analysis with externally derived hypotheses, perhaps 
from data integration. Our study could not have led to a 
positive finding without taking these advantages. 
In summary, we provide a comprehensive profiling of the 
human HD CSF proteome. The integration of the proteomics 
data with various genomics data supports the idea of CSF as 
a rich source of biomarkers for neurological diseases. For 
Huntington disease in particular we derived a list of proteins 
that are altered in HD CSF and that have the potential to be 
used as a specific signature of HD progression. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments-We thank Allan Tobin from the High Q Foun-
dation for the suggestions and encouragement in this project and 
Sara Lynn Zriny for project administration. Yan Liu, Jimmy K. Eng, Ted 
Holzman, and Lynn Amon each provided technical help in various 
aspects during the data analysis. Peter Hussey, from LabKey, as-
sisted in developing the Web site. </p>

<p>* This work was supported by the High Q Foundation, Inc. The 
Canary Foundation provided financial support for publishing and 
disseminating data. </p>

<p>□ S The on-line version of this article (available at http://www. </p>

<p>mcponline.org) contains supplemental material. 
The comprehensive list of proteins has been deposited in the 
PRoteomics IDentifications (PRIDE) database under accession 
number 3701. 
 § § To whom correspondence should be addressed: Fred Hutchin-
son Cancer Research Center, 1100 Fairview Ave. N., M2-B230, Se-
attle, WA 98109. Tel.: 206-667-4612; Fax: 206-667-7264; E-mail: 
mmcintos@fhcrc.org. </p>



<p>Huntington Disease Cerebrospinal Fluid </p>





<p>Huntington Disease Cerebrospinal Fluid </p>

<p>Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics 8.3 465 </p>



<p>Huntington Disease Cerebrospinal Fluid </p>



</text></tei>