<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2518490" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVE-Mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) contribute to 
endothelial cell (EC) migration by producing proteases, thereby 
paving the way into the tissues for ECs. MSCs were added to our 
previously described composite EC islets as a potential means to 
improve their capacity for islet angiogenesis. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS-Human islets were 
coated with primary human bone marrow-derived MSCs and 
dermal microvascular ECs. The capacity of ECs, with or without 
MSCs, to adhere to and grow into human islets was analyzed. The 
survival and functionality of these composite islets were evalu-
ated in a dynamic perifusion assay, and their capacity for 
angiogenesis in vitro was assessed in a three-dimensional fibrin 
gel assay. </p>

<p>RESULTS-ECs proliferated after culture in MSC-conditioned 
medium, and MSCs improved the EC coverage threefold com-
pared with EC islets alone. Islet survival in vitro and the 
functionality of the composite islets after culture were equal to 
those of control islets. The EC-MSC islets showed a twofold 
increase in total sprout formation compared with EC islets, and 
vascular sprouts emanating from the EC-MSC-islet surface 
showed migration of ECs into the islets and also into the 
surrounding matrix, either alone or in concert with MSCs. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS-EC proliferation, sprout formation, and in-
growth of ECs into the islets were enhanced by MSCs. The use of 
composite EC-MSC islets may have beneficial effects on revas-
cularization and immune regulation. The technique presented 
allows for pretreatment of donor islets with recipient-derived 
ECs and MSCs as a means of improving islet engraftment. 
Diabetes 57:2393-2401, 2008 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>he islets of Langerhans are micro-organs, with 
afferent and efferent blood vessels connecting 
the capillary network of the islets to the circula-
tion system (1). Intra-islet endothelial cells 
(ECs) are fenestrated, and the density of the capillary 
network in the islets is 10 times higher than that of the </p>

<p>surrounding exocrine tissue (2,3). During the process of 
islet isolation before transplantation, the ECs in the islets 
lose their external vascular support; this situation contrib-
utes to their dedifferentiation, apoptosis, and necrosis 
during subsequent in vitro culture (4). 
The formation of new capillaries during revasculariza-
tion is a complex process that involves digestion of the 
vascular wall by proteases and the migration, prolifera-
tion, and differentiation of ECs (5). When blood vessels are 
assembled, ECs produce platelet-derived growth factor, 
which attracts supportive cells, including mesenchymal 
stem cells (MSCs) that can differentiate into pericytes (6). 
We hypothesized that adding MSCs to our previously 
described composite EC islets (7) might improve the 
adherence of the ECs to the islets and subsequent vascu-
larization because MSCs contribute to EC migration by 
producing proteases, thereby paving the way into the 
surrounding tissue for the immature EC sprouts (8). MSCs 
have also been shown to upregulate the expression of 
angiopoietin and vascular endothelial growth factor 
(VEGF) in ECs, contributing to an increase in angiogenesis 
and stabilization of the vasculature (9). Moreover, MSCs 
have been shown to possess important immune-modulat-
ing properties (10), and they do not trigger adaptive 
immune reactions, which could make them ideal in islet 
transplantation setting (11,12). 
The present study describes a gentle and reproducible 
technique for forming EC-MSC islets that is designed to 
take into consideration the inherent characteristics of the 
various cell types involved and to take advantage of the 
anchorage-dependent growth of ECs and MSCs. Our data 
demonstrate that addition of MSCs to our composite islets 
enhanced the capacity of ECs to enclose the islets without 
compromising the functionality of the islets. Importantly, 
the MSCs stimulated EC sprout formation not only into the 
surrounding matrices, but also into the islets where intra-
islet capillary-like structures were formed. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>Isolation of islets of Langerhans. Human islets of Langerhans were isolated 
at the Division of Clinical Immunology at Uppsala University by using a 
modified semi-automated digestion-filtration method, then cultured in CMRL-
1066 with supplements (islet medium) (13-15). 
Islets were released for research after approval by the ethics committee at 
Uppsala University Hospital. Pancreata from 20 donors were used (4 -7 
donors per experiment). The purity of the islet preparations was 75-95%, with 
the exception of one preparation that was 45% pure. 
Cell culture. MSCs were isolated from human adult bone marrow as 
previously described (10). In brief, bone marrow was harvested from the iliac 
crest of adult volunteers (n 8) after approval from the ethics committee at 
Huddinge University Hospital. The cells were classified as MSCs on the basis 
of their ability to differentiate into bone, fat, and cartilage and by flow 
cytometric analysis (positive for CD29, CD44, CD73, CD166, and CD105, but </p>

<p>From the negative for CD14, CD34, and CD45) and were used from passage 3-9 
(FACScalibur; Becton Dickinson, Franklin Lakes, NJ). Potential EC contami-
nation of the MSC population was assessed by flow cytometry (Becton 
Dickinson) (n 3). The cells were stained for CD90 (1:100; BD Bioscience 
Pharmingen, San Diego, CA), the EC pan marker CD31 (1:100; Becton 
Dickinson), and the lectin Ulex europeaus agglutinin-1 (UEA-1, 1:100; Vector 
Laboratories, Peterborough, U.K.). Human dermal microvascular ECs 
HDMECs (PromoCell, Heidelberg, Germany) derived from adult dermis were 
cultured on 1% gelatin-coated flasks in EC Growth Medium Microvascular 
with supplements (EC medium; PromoCell). The ECs were used from passage 
3-12. 
Cell labeling. MSCs and ECs were labeled using CellTracker (CT) green and 
CT orange CMRA, respectively, according to the manufacturer's protocol 
(Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR). 
Thymidine assay and coculture of cells. Thymidine assays were performed 
according to a standard proliferation protocol measuring [ 3 H]thymidine 
(1Ci/ml) incorporation (16). ECs were plated in 24-well plates, with 25 10 3 
cells/well in EC medium with supplements for 24 h and then cultured in EC 
medium without supplements but containing 0.5% fetal bovine serum (starva-
tion medium) for an additional 24 h (basal control) or stimulated with either 
VEGF-A (20 ng/ml; Peprotech, London, U.K.) in starvation medium or MSC-
conditioned medium (supernatant from 24-h MSC cultures in starvation 
medium). [ 3 H]thymidine incorporation (at 20 -24 h) was determined by liquid 
scintillation counting. Triplicate samples were assayed in three individual 
experiments. A mixture of 25 10 3 CT green-labeled MSCs and 25 10 3 CT 
orange-labeled ECs were cocultured in eight-well glass culture slides (Becton 
Dickinson) with EC medium and analyzed by fluorescence microscopy after 
3 days. 
Coating of islets of Langerhans with ECs and MSCs. Islets of Langerhans 
(10,000 -30,000 islet equivalents) were incubated within 2-5 days after isola-
tion with 0.5 10 6 CT orange-labeled ECs (EC islets) or with 0.25 10 6 CT 
green-labeled MSCs in combination with 0.25 10 6 CT orange-labeled ECs 
(EC-MSC islets) in a total volume of 500 l. The cell suspensions were 
incubated at 37°C for 2-3 h in suspension culture tubes in EC medium and 
mixed gently twice per hour during the incubation. Thereafter, the EC islets, 
EC-MSC islets, and untreated control islets were cultured for up to 6 days at 
37°C in EC medium or islet medium (CMRL; Invitrogen) until analyzed. The 
medium was changed every second day. Quantification of EC adherence was 
performed on EC islets and EC-MSC islets after 1 and 4 days of culture. 
In vitro islet survival assay and cytokine and insulin content determi-
nation. A total of 100 islets per donor (n 6) were hand picked: 50 islets 
were coated with 5 10 3 MSCs and 5 10 3 ECs, and 50 islets were untreated. 
All islets were cultured for 6 days in EC medium, with a medium change every 
second day. The number of remaining islets in the respective groups were 
counted after 1, 3, and 6 days of culture, and the islet number was confirmed 
after 6 days by dithizone staining (18). Control and EC-MSC islets were 
collected after 6 days of culture. Total DNA (Picogreen; Invitrogen), interleu-
kin (IL)-8, IL-6 (R&amp;D Systems, Oxford, U.K.), monocyte chemotactic protein-1 
(MCP-1) (Serotec, Oxford, U.K.), tissue factor (TF) (Imubind; American 
Diagnostica, Stamford, CT), and insulin (Mercodia) contents were measured 
on a Gyrolab workstation (Gyros, Uppsala, Sweden), and the values were 
divided with total DNA. Four or more different islet isolations with 20 islets in 
each condition were analyzed. 
Dynamic perifusion. The functionality of the islets coated with EC-MSC and 
of untreated islets from the same isolation was tested at different time points 
after coating (at 24 h and day 3-4). EC medium was used during the first 24 h 
of suspension culture; thereafter, the medium was changed to islet medium 
with supplements (17). Islets were challenged in a dynamic perifusion system, 
beginning with a low glucose concentration (1.67 mmol/l) during the first 36 
min, followed by a high-glucose challenge (20 mmol/l) for 42 min, then 
reexposure to the low glucose concentration during the last 48 min. Fractions 
were collected at 6-min intervals over 126 min and analyzed for insulin content 
using commercial ELISA kits (Mercodia Insulin ELISA; Mercodia, Uppsala, 
Sweden). The area under the curve was calculated to evaluate the insulin 
secretion during high glucose stimulation with subtracted basal insulin 
secretion. Four different islet isolations with 20 islets in each condition were 
analyzed. 
Fibrin gel in vitro angiogenesis assay. Control, EC, and EC-MSC islets 
were placed between two layers of fibrin gel (2.5 mg/ml fibrinogen and 2 g/ml 
thrombin; Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO). After polymerization, EC medium 
supplemented with VEGF (30 ng/ml; Peprotech) was added. The islet prepa-
rations (n 6) were cultured for 24 h, 48 h, and 3-4 days and then fixed in 4% 
paraformaldehyde. Sprouts were counted manually by the same person 
(blinded to the composition of the islet preparation), and 4 -20 islets were 
counted per group in each experiment. The EC sprout length was measured 
using <rs id="software-3" type="software">Leica Qwin</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Leica Microsystems</rs>, Nussloch, Germany) on 
pictures taken on day 4 of EC and EC-MSC islets in fibrin gel. The total EC </p>

<p>sprout length per islet was calculated for each experiment (groups of 2-10 
islets, n 6). The mean total sprout length per islet for all the experiments 
(n 6) was then calculated. The frequencies of the various sprout types were 
calculated by analyzing micrographs of EC-MSC islets from the fibrin gel 
experiments (n 6). 
Immunohistochemical staining. Composite and control islets were fixed in 
4% paraformaldehyde for 30 min, washed in PBS, and incubated in 20% 
sucrose/PBS overnight at 4°C, then embedded in optimal cutting temperature 
medium (Tissue Tech; Sakura Finetek, Zoeterwoude, Netherlands), frozen, 
cryosectioned, and permeabilized in 0.3% Triton X-100/PBS for 15 min. 
Immunohistochemical staining was performed using guinea pig anti-human 
insulin (1:400; Fitzgerald Industries International, Concord, MA) followed by 
Alexa Fluor 488-labeled goat anti-rabbit (1:1,000; Molecular Probes) or Alexa 
Fluor 488 -conjugated mouse anti-human CD31 (1:100; Becton Dickinson). 
Counterstaining was performed with DAPI (10 g/ml; Sigma-Aldrich). 
Production of DsRed-expressing lentiviral particles and lentiviral vec-
tor infection of ECs. Stocks of Discosoma species-derived red fluorescent 
(DsRed)-expressing lentiviral vectors (Lv-DsRed) were produced by cotrans-
fection of three plasmids, the viral core packaging construct pCMVdeltaR8.74, 
the VSV-G envelope protein vector pMDG.2, and the transfer vector pRRLsin-
PPThCMV-MCS-wpre containing DsRed cDNA (a gift of W.T. Hendriks), into 
human embryonic kidney 293T cells as previously described (19,20). 
HDMECs at passage 3 were seeded onto 1% gelatin-coated six-well plates 
(1 10 5 cells/well; AH Diagnostics) and cultured for 48 h. Virus at a titer of 
2 10 5 TU/ml Lv-DsRed was added to the subconfluent cells in combination 
with 2 g/ml Sequa-Brene (Sigma-Aldrich) in EC medium. The plate was spun 
for 60 min during the Lv-DsRed infection of the ECs, and, thereafter, 
additional fresh medium was added to the cells. The DsRed ECs were then 
used in the long-term islet culture experiments according to the previously 
described protocol for coating of islets. 
Image analysis and quantification. Coating, morphology, and sprout anal-
yses were performed using confocal laser scanning microscopy (Zeiss LSM 
510 Meta; Carl Zeiss International, Oberkochen, Germany) and/or fluores-
cence microscopy (Nikon Elipse E600, Nikon TS100; Nikon, Tokyo, Japan). 
Confocal z-stack images composed of 10 pictures were merged to produce a 
picture for use in analyzing EC adherence. Micrographs were analyzed using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Leica Qwin</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Leica microsystems</rs>) to determine the surface area and 
total sprout length. The frequency of particular types of sprout composition 
was calculated from pictures using <rs type="software">Adobe Photoshop</rs> software. Quantification 
of islet number was accomplished by the use of a stereomicroscope (Leica 
Microsystems), and pictures were analyzed using <rs type="software">Adobe Photoshop</rs> software. 
Ingrowth of DsRed ECs into the islets was evaluated using confocal micros-
copy z-stack images, visualizing ECs at a defined depth of 30 m into the islets 
after 3 or 6 days of culture, with a majority of samples being analyzed after 6 
days. A defined distance of 30 m from the islet surface was chosen to yield 
good confocal resolution. The presence of ECs was scored as 0 -3, with 0 
indicating the absence of ECs from the islet section and scores of 1-3 
indicating a scarce (1), intermediate (2), or abundant (3) amount of ECs 
present. 
Statistical analysis. Data are presented as means SEM. Mean values were 
compared using a two-tailed Wilcoxon test for paired data, with significance 
set at P 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Interaction between ECs and MSCs. Before coculture, 
the purity of each cell population (EC and MSC) was 
assessed by fluorescence-activated cell sorter analysis. 
This analysis showed that the MSCs stained positive for 
the stem cell marker CD90 but were negative for the EC 
marker CD31 and did not bind the human EC lectin UEA-1 
(Fig. 1A), indicating an absence of contaminating ECs. 
The ECs were negative for CD90 but were positive for 
CD31 and bound UEA-1 (Fig. 1B). MSC-conditioned 
medium induced an increase in EC proliferation, with 
the magnitude of the increase being similar to that 
produced by the addition of 20 ng/ml VEGF-A to the 
culture medium (Fig. 1C). 
To analyze the potential cell growth effects by MSCs on 
ECs, we cocultured MSCs (CT green) and ECs (CT orange) 
in EC medium at defined cell densities for 3 days. Morpho-
logical analysis of these cultures showed that the cells 
grew either on top of each other or aligned with one 
another, indicating interactions between the cells (Fig. </p>

<p>COMPOSITE EC-MSC ISLET REVASCULARIZATION </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>1D). Growth of ECs in double layers is an atypical phe-
nomenon, indicating unusual growth interactions between 
the ECs and MSCs. 
Improved islet coating by combining ECs and MSCs. 
ECs are adherent cells that interact with the extracellular 
matrix. We therefore evaluated the adherence of ECs (CT 
orange) and MSCs (CT green) to isolated islets. After 3-h 
incubation of islets and ECs (EC islets), a few ECs were 
found to adhere to the islet surface (Fig. 2A, left panel). 
Combining ECs and islets with MSCs (EC-MSC islets) had 
no apparent effect on the coating of the islets by ECs at 
this early time point (Fig. 2A, right panel). However, after 
only 1 day of incubation, a threefold increase in the islet 
surface covered by ECs was observed in the presence of 
MSCs, as compared with EC islets (Fig. 2B, quantification 
in Fig. 2C). Morphological characterization of the ECs 
adhering to the islet surface repeatedly showed that the 
ECs flattened out and aligned themselves with the surface 
of the islets in the presence of MSCs (Fig. 2D). Analyses of 
sectioned EC islets and EC-MSC islets stained for insulin </p>

<p>showed ECs adhering to both insulin-positive and insulin-
negative cells in the islet preparations after 24 h of 
incubation (Fig. 2E-G). After 4 days in suspension culture, 
there was a tendency toward a decrease in the islet surface 
area covered by ECs in both EC islets and EC-MSC islets; 
however, this difference did not reach statistical signifi-
cance (n 6; P 0.16 and P 0.06, respectively). A few 
cell clusters remained uncoated in all groups (Fig. 2B, 
right panel, arrowheads). 
EC islet and EC-MSC islet survival and function. Islet 
loss during the process of coating was evaluated by 
incubation of 50 hand-picked islets with ECs and MSCs 
according to the coating protocol. No loss of islets was 
observed during the formation of EC-MSC islets; however, 
a gradual decrease of 20% in islet number was observed 
in both groups during the 6-day culture period (Fig. 3A). 
Cytokine analysis showed insignificant differences in the 
levels of IL-6 (0.005 0.005, 0.07 0.06 pmol/g DNA), 
IL-8 (0.3 0.1, 0.9 0.04 pmol/g DNA), TF (0.1 0.01, 
0.3 0.07 pmol/g DNA) and MCP-1 (0.2 0.2, 0.6 0.1 </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>Basal 
MSC Conditioned </p>

<p>Relative value (%) </p>

<p>VEGF </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>EC MSC </p>

<p>FITC 
FITC </p>

<p>Counts </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>240 </p>

<p>Counts </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>240 </p>

<p>10 0 
10 1 
10 2 
10 3 
10 4 
10 0 
10 1 
10 2 
10 3 
10 4 </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>300 
300 </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Interactions between ECs and MSCs. Expression of CD90 (green line) and CD31 (orange line) and binding of UEA-1 (red line) to MSC 
(green, A) and EC (red, B), as assessed by flow cytometry (A and B show representative results of three experiments). C: EC proliferation in 
basal (gray), MSC-conditioned (white), or VEGF (black) medium. Results are expressed as the percentage of the basal response (means SEM) 
from three separate experiments performed in triplicate. D: Coculture of MSCs (green) and ECs (red). The cells grew either on top of one another 
(D, arrow) or aligned with each other (D, arrowhead). Scale bars 50 m. (Please see http://dx.doi.org/10.2337/db07-0981 for a high-quality 
digital representation of this figure.) </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>U. JOHANSSON AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>
pmol/g DNA) in control islets and EC-MSC islets, respec-
tively. The insulin content/DNA was 1.5 0.4 ng insulin/ng </p>

<p>DNA for the control islets and 0.9 0.3 ng insulin/ng DNA 
for the EC-MSC islets on day 6. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>EC 
EC-MSC </p>

<p>Surface area (% of total islet area) </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>A 
E </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>EC 3 hours </p>

<p>EC 24 hours </p>

<p>EC MSC 3 hours </p>

<p>EC MSC 24 hours </p>

<p>EC MSC 24 hours </p>

<p>Control islets </p>

<p>EC-islets </p>

<p>EC-MSC-islets 
EC-MSC-islets </p>

<p>EC-islets </p>

<p>Control islets </p>

<p>Insulin </p>

<p>EC Insulin </p>

<p>EC Insulin </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Islet coating by ECs and MSCs. Islets were incubated with ECs (red; A and B, left panel) or ECs and MSCs (red and green, 
respectively; A and B, right panel) for 3 h (A) or 24 h (B). Some islets remained uncovered in all groups (B, right panel, arrowheads). EC 
adherence was quantified by calculating the surface area of digital micrographs of EC islets (black) and EC-MSC islets (white) (% of total 
islet area) after 1 day of culture (C) (means SEM; n 7; *P 0.03). ECs in the presence of MSCs were seen to flatten and coat the surface 
of the islets (D, enlarged islet from B, right panel). Insulin expression was determined by immunofluorescent staining of sectioned control 
islets (E), EC islets (F), and EC-MSC islets (G) after 24 h of culture. The images E-G show insulin (green), EC (red), and nuclear staining 
with DAPI (blue). Scale bars 100 m. (Please see http://dx.doi.org/10.2337/db07-0981 for a high-quality digital representation of this 
figure.) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Islet numbers, functionality, and dynamic insulin release of EC-MSC islets. Control islets (black) and EC-MSC islets (white) were counted 
after 1, 3, and 6 days (A) (mean of islet number SEM; n 6; *P 0.03; when the numbers of control islets on day 6 were compared with those 
of control islets on day 1). Insulin release was measured from control islets (black) and EC-MSC islets (white) cultured for 1 day (B) or 3-4 days 
(C). B and C show means SEM, n 4. </p>

<p>COMPOSITE EC-MSC ISLET REVASCULARIZATION </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>Insulin release by EC-MSC islets showed preserved 
dynamics during high-glucose stimulation after 1 and 3-4 
days compared with control islets (Fig. 3B-C). No signif-
icant differences were seen in the stimulation indexes 
between control islets and EC-MSC islets at 1 day (5,090 
2,190 and 4,540 1,300 pmol min 1 l 1 , respectively) or 
3-4 days of culture (4,560 1,330 and 5,090 800 pmol 
min 1 l 1 , respectively). 
Sprouting and invasion of fibrin gels. To evaluate the 
effect of angiogenesis, uncoated and coated islets were 
cultured in three-dimensional fibrin gels (Fig. 4A and 
C-D), in which ECs formed defined sprouts of patched 
ECs, and MSCs formed thin cords of aligned cells (21,22). 
After only 48 h, the total number of sprouts in the 
composite EC-MSC islets was higher than that in the 
control or EC islets. This difference remained after 3-4 
days of culture (Fig. 4B). 
When the islets came into close contact with each other, 
sprouts of ECs were formed between the EC-MSC islets, 
indicating paracrine stimulation (Fig. 4C, arrowhead). 
EC-MSC islets retained sprout formation over time, 
whereas in EC islets, the sprouts were disrupted and the 
ECs were separated from the islets (Fig. 4C-D). The 
median ( 1 quartile) EC sprout length in the EC-MSC 
islets was 900 m (700 -1,380 m) and only 680 m 
(300 -840 m) in the EC islets. Also, the total EC sprout 
length per islet was longer in the EC-MSC islets than in the 
EC islets (Fig. 4E). </p>

<p>Figure 5 shows the typical morphology of sprouts 
emanating from a composite EC-MSC islet after 2 days in 
culture. At this early stage, the sprouting was character-
ized by a complex course of events involving EC sprouts 
interacting with MSCs at the EC sprout base (Fig. 5A), ECs 
in close contact with MSCs (Fig. 5B-C), ECs at the leading 
tip of an MSC-initiated sprout (Fig. 5D), and MSCs at the 
leading tip of an EC sprout (Fig. 5E). ECs also migrated in 
groups to form a completely naked sprout with no appar-
ent connection to the islet (Fig. 5F). Sprouts of ECs in 
close interaction with MSCs occurred twice as frequently 
as EC sprouts with nonaligned MSC cords. In the sprouts 
in which close cell interactions occurred between ECs and 
MSCs, there was a preference for ECs as the leading tip 
cells. 
Vessel formation in islets coated with ECs and MSCs. 
After 24 h of culture in EC medium, the EC islets were 
stained for CD31 to reveal endogenous islet capillaries 
(Fig. 6A, green). An ingrowth of added ECs (CT orange) 
connecting to the native CD31-positive islet capillary net-
work was frequently observed (Fig. 6A, arrowheads). To 
achieve a stable expression of DsRed, we infected the ECs 
with DsRed-labeled lentiviral particles. DsRed-infected 
ECs showed almost complete transduction after 2 weeks 
of culture, as visualized by merged phase-contrast and 
fluorescence microscopy images (Fig. 6B). The prolifera-
tive capacity of the DsRed EC in response to VEGF was 
unaffected (data not shown). </p>

<p>.2 
.6 </p>

<p>Mean of total sprout length/islet (mm) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>24 hours 
48 hours 
Day 3-4 </p>

<p>Mean of total sprouts /islet </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D 
C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>E </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>EC-MSC-islets </p>

<p>EC 
EC </p>

<p>EC-MSC-islets 
EC-islet </p>

<p>FIG. 4. Sprout formation in fibrin gels. Phase-contrast microscope images of control islets (upper left corner) and EC-MSC islets in fibrin gel after 
4 days of culture (A). The number of sprouts per islet after 1-4 days in culture for control islets (gray), EC islets (black), and EC-MSC islets 
(white) (B) (mean of total sprout count SEM; n 6; *P 0.03; when EC-MSC islets were compared with control islets and EC islets at 48 h 
and 3-4 days). C and D: MSC-induced EC (red) with elongated sprouts in EC-MSC islets (C), as compared with EC-islets (D). E: EC sprout length 
measured in EC-MSC islets (white) and EC islets (black) (mean of total EC sprout length/islet SEM; n 6; *P 0.03). Scale bars 100 m. 
(Please see http://dx.doi.org/10.2337/db07-0981 for a high-quality digital representation of this figure.) </p>

<p>U. JOHANSSON AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>
Confocal microscopy analyses of DsRed EC islets and 
DsRed EC-MSC islets after 6 days of suspension culture 
showed that the DsRed ECs had penetrated into the islets 
(Fig. 6C). Especially in the EC-MSC islets, the DsRed ECs 
had formed a dense network of capillary-like structures 
penetrating into the islets (Fig. 6D). The presence of 
DsRed ECs within the islets was scored at day 3 and 6. 
Whereas the EC islets had a mean score of 0.7 0.2, the 
EC-MSC islets showed a higher level of penetration, with a 
mean score of 1.6 0.4 (Fig. 6E). A comparison of the 
score distribution for the EC islets and EC-MSC islets 
showed that those with a score of 0 or 1 were predomi-
nantly EC islets, whereas the islets reaching a score of 2 or 
3 were predominantly EC-MSC islets (Fig. 6F). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In the present study, modern tissue engineering was 
applied as a strategy to enhance the process of islet 
angiogenesis by combining ECs and supportive MSCs with 
isolated islets in culture. The capacity of the ECs to cover 
the islet surface was markedly enhanced by the presence 
of MSCs. This effect is most likely not only a result of 
enhanced adherence, but also a reflection of a change in 
the phenotype of the ECs that allowed them to stretch 
toward and interact with the islet surface, together with an 
increase in their proliferation. Importantly, in an estab-
lished in vitro model of angiogenesis, the MSCs also 
stimulated EC sprout formation, not only into the sur-
rounding matrices, but also into the islets where intra-islet 
capillary-like structures were formed. 
Microvascular ECs were used to obtain an active EC 
phenotype with a capacity for angiogenesis that resembles 
a tentative future clinical situation involving harvesting 
autologous ECs from fat tissue (23). As compared with the 
aortic ECs that were used earlier (7), microvascular ECs 
are less covered by pericytes and, therefore, relatively 
more susceptible to remodeling (24). The relative capacity 
of EC populations to coat microcarrier surfaces is affected 
by the source from which they were obtained (25) and 
their expression of integrins, such as 5 1, 1 1, and v 
5. The same relationship, possibly reflecting variations in 
integrin expression (25), seems to hold true for their 
ability to coat islet surfaces (cf. [7]). </p>

<p>Established in vitro models of angiogenesis involve 
culturing ECs in three-dimensional polymers, such as 
fibrin or collagen gels (26,27). By using this model system, 
we were able to demonstrate the induction of sprout 
formation of ECs in the presence of MSCs, a response that 
could be monitored over time by confocal microscopy. 
Similarly, Ghajar and colleagues (8) have demonstrated 
stimulatory effects of MSCs on angiogenesis in three-
dimensional fibrin gels. The induced vessel formation was 
due in part to degradation of the fibrin matrix by proteases 
produced by the MSCs, and sprout formation was en-
hanced even in matrices in which the matrix density was 
too high for the ECs to invade when cultured alone (8). 
This capacity of MSCs may be of particular importance in 
facilitating EC migration into dense micro-organs such as 
islets. In addition, MSCs most likely contributed growth 
factors and extracellular matrix production that serve to 
encourage the stabilization and maturation of the EC 
sprouts (9). This effect of MSCs was evidenced by the 
increased sprout formation by EC-MSC islets in fibrin gels, 
where close interactions between EC sprouts and MSCs 
occurred to a high degree. The MSCs express platelet-
derived growth factor (PDGF) receptors and may respond 
to PDGF production by the ECs, leading to enhanced cell 
interactions (6,28). A majority of the EC sprouts that 
interacted closely with MSCs in the fibrin gel also showed 
a thicker sprout phenotype, suggesting that a maturation 
process occurred. In contrast, several of the sprouts 
emanating from the EC islets eventually collapsed and 
detached from their base at the islet surface. 
Examination of sections of composite islets showed that 
the added ECs formed connections to the native islet 
capillaries. This growth of ECs into the islets was analyzed 
by scoring confocal microscopy z-stacks. A marked in-
crease in the number of ECs growing into the islets was 
observed in the presence of MSCs. In these samples, the 
ECs formed capillary-like structures deep within the EC-
MSC islets, indicating a prompt and enhanced angiogenic 
capacity. 
The technique described here for forming EC-MSC islets 
has been designed to take into consideration the specific 
needs for in vitro support of the various cell types involved 
and to take advantage of the anchorage-dependent growth </p>

<p>EC MSC </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>a 
e </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>b 
f </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Confocal scanning of sprout formation from composite islets with ECs and MSCs showing islets coated with MSC (green) and EC (red) 
cultured in three-dimensional fibrin gel (enlarged pictures to the right). A-F: MSCs at the base of an endothelial sprout (A), MSCs and ECs in 
close contact (B), ECs and MSCs growing side-by-side (C), an endothelial sprout tip (D), an MSC cord tip (E), and a naked, unconnected 
endothelial sprout (F). Scale bars 100 m. (Please see http://dx.doi.org/10.2337/db07-0981 for a high-quality digital representation of this 
figure.) </p>

<p>COMPOSITE EC-MSC ISLET REVASCULARIZATION </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E 
F </p>

<p>EC </p>

<p>Phase contrast </p>

<p>Top section </p>

<p>EC-islets </p>

<p>DsRed </p>

<p>EC-islet </p>

<p>Mid section 
Base section 
Overlay </p>

<p>Top section </p>

<p>EC-MSC-islets </p>

<p>Mid section 
Base section 
Overlay </p>

<p>CD31 
Merged </p>

<p>Merged </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>Score 0 
Score 1 
Score 2 
Score 3 
Score distribution (%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>Mean score </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>FIG. 6. Analysis of intra-islet vessel formation by accompanying ECs. Sectioned islets, coated with EC (red) and stained for CD31 (green), showed 
connections between accompanying EC and intra-islet capillaries (A, arrowheads). Yellow-colored vessels indicate CD31-positivity on added ECs. The 
last figure in panel A shows an enlargement of the connecting ECs. The merged phase-contrast and DsRed fluorescence microscope images/micrographs 
of infected human dermal microvascular ECs show an almost complete transduction efficiency with the DsRed lentiviral vector (B). C and D: DsRed ECs 
visualized in composite islets after 6 days of culture, EC islets alone (C), and EC islets in the presence of unlabeled MSCs (D). The insert in the last 
panel shows islets in bright-field with a DsRed EC overlay. Scale bars in A 50 m. Scale bars in B-D 100 m. Scoring of DsRed ECs in the islets 
showed an increased EC ingrowth in EC-MSC islets (white) compared with EC islets (black) (E) (mean score SEM; n 7; *P 0.03). F: Score 
distribution for DsRed EC ingrowth into EC-MSC islets (white), as compared with EC islets (black). (Please see http://dx.doi.org/10.2337/db07-0981 
for a high-quality digital representation of this figure.) </p>

<p>U. JOHANSSON AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>
of ECs and MSCs. By utilizing the inherent characteristics 
of the different cell types, we were able to establish a 
gentle and reproducible technique. Most importantly, no 
additional loss of islets occurred during the formation of 
EC-MSC islets and their subsequent culture (6 days), when 
compared with untreated islets. A culture medium de-
signed to support microvascular EC survival was applied 
to promote EC adhesion and proliferation on the islet 
surface unaffecting the islet function. Equally important is 
that the culture conditions applied did not promote the 
pro-inflammatory and procoagulant capacity of ECs 
(29,30), i.e, there was no difference in the level of expres-
sion of TF, IL-6, IL-8, or MCP-1 between the EC-MSC and 
control islets. 
In the present communication, human ECs, MSCs, and 
islets were used. One limitation of this approach in the 
experimental setting is that evaluation of composite EC-
MSC islet grafts in small animal models are not easily 
performed because of several significant species-specific 
differences in important areas such as angiogenesis, tissue 
repair, and innate immunity (31). Also, severely immuno-
deficient mice (SCID, nu/nu, and Rag) trigger strong innate 
immune responses that mainly target the vasculature of a 
transplanted organ due to the phylogenetic disparity be-
tween the two species, i.e., human-to-mouse is a discor-
dant xenotransplantation model triggering activation of 
neutrophils, natural killer cells, macrophages, the comple-
ment and coagulation systems, and naturally occurring 
xenoreactive antibodies (32-39). 
MSCs are currently being evaluated in clinical trials for 
their capacity to control severe graft-versus-host disease 
(40). Composite EC-MSC islet grafts could benefit from the 
immune regulatory effects of MSCs and from improved 
revascularization, thereby promoting transplantation at an 
extrahepatic site. This strategy requires a reliable source 
of recipient-derived ECs or endothelial precursor cells; 
however, human endothelial precursor cells can be ob-
tained in relatively large numbers by sorting for circulating 
angiopoietin receptor Tie-2-positive cells (41) or from 
adipose-derived stem cells in human fat tissue (42,43). Our 
promising results with EC-MSC islets strongly suggest that 
they can contribute to the success of future clinical islet 
transplantation. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by grants from the Swedish 
Medical Research Council (K2005-72X-12219-09A and 
K2008-55X-12219-12-3), the Swedish Medical Research 
Council/Vinnova/Swedish Foundation for Strategic Re-
search (60761701), the National Institutes of Health, the 
Novo Nordisk Foundation, Barndiabetesfonden, the Swed-
ish Diabetes Association, and the Juvenile Diabetes Re-
search Foundation. 
The authors thank Daniel Brandhorst for assistance in 
statistical analysis, Deborah McClellan for editorial assis-
tance, and the Nordic Network for Clinical Islet Transplan-
tation for providing islet preparations. </p>



<p>COMPOSITE EC-MSC ISLET REVASCULARIZATION </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>



<p>U. JOHANSSON AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>