<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2556094" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T14:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Sgt1 is an adaptor protein implicated in a variety of 
processes, including formation of the kinetochore complex 
in yeast, and regulation of innate immunity systems in 
plants and animals. Sgt1 has been found to associate with 
SCF E3 ubiquitin ligases, the CBF3 kinetochore complex, 
plant R proteins and related animal Nod-like receptors, 
and with the Hsp90 molecular chaperone. We have deter-
mined the crystal structure of the core Hsp90-Sgt1 com-
plex, revealing a distinct site of interaction on the Hsp90 
N-terminal domain. Using the structure, we developed 
mutations in Sgt1 interfacial residues, which specifically 
abrogate interaction with Hsp90, and disrupt Sgt1-depen-
dent functions in vivo, in plants and yeast. We show that 
Sgt1 bridges the Hsp90 molecular chaperone system to the 
substrate-specific arm of SCF ubiquitin ligase complexes, 
suggesting a role in SCF assembly and regulation, and 
providing multiple complementary routes for ubiquitina-
tion of Hsp90 client proteins. 
The Hsp90 molecular chaperone, in collaboration with a 
plethora of co-chaperones, is involved in the assembly and 
stabilization of key regulatory proteins in the eukaryotic cell 
(Pearl and Prodromou, 2006). Although the protein clientele </p>

<p>of Hsp90 covers a broad range of structural classes, it is 
nonetheless selective and specific; the biochemical basis for 
this remains one of the least understood aspects of Hsp90 
biology. Recruitment of one important class of Hsp90 clients, 
protein kinases, requires the adaptor co-chaperone Cdc37, 
which interacts simultaneously with the kinase and Hsp90, 
and regulates Hsp90s ATPase cycle in the process (Roe et al,  2004; Pearl, 2005; Caplan et al, 2007). Coupling of the Hsp90 
chaperone system to the ubiquitin-regulated signalling and 
targeted destruction systems is mediated by a dimeric co-
chaperone adaptor, CHIP (Connell et al, 2001), which binds to 
Hsp90 through its tetratricopeptide repeat (TPR) domain and 
E2 ubiquitin conjugating enzymes through its U-box domain 
(Zhang et al, 2005). Other co-chaperones, such as p23 and 
Aha1, have no apparent role in mediating interactions with 
clients or other systems, but exert an effect instead as 
regulators of Hsp90s inherent ATPase cycle (Sullivan et al,  1997; Panaretou et al, 2002; Meyer et al, 2004; Ali et al, 2006). 
One of the most recently recognized co-chaperones of 
Hsp90, Sgt1 (Takahashi et al, 2003), was originally identified 
as a suppressor of a temperature-sensitive defect in the 
budding yeast Skp1 protein (Kitagawa et al, 1999). Sgt1p 
associates with Skp1p as an essential component of the CBF3 
kinetochore complex, and is required for the assembly of 
yeast and human kinetochores (Bansal et al, 2004;  Steensgaard et al, 2004). Sgt1p also associates with Skp1p 
in the context of the SCF (Skp1p-Cdc53p-F-box protein) class 
of E3 ubiquitin ligases (Kitagawa et al, 1999). Sgt1 is not 
exclusively associated with Skp1 and interacts independently 
of Skp1 with adenylate cyclases (Dubacq et al, 2002; Schadick  et al, 2002), the CHORD-domain protein RAR1 (Azevedo  et al, 2002), and members of a family of proteins including 
plant disease resistance R-gene products (Bieri et al, 2004;  Leister et al, 2005) and animal Nod-like receptors (Mayor  et al, 2007; da Silva Correia et al, 2007), that mediate innate 
immunity to parasites and infection. The ability of Sgt1 to 
bind to Hsp90 and simultaneously interact with other pro-
teins (Takahashi et al, 2003; Lingelbach and Kaplan, 2004;  Catlett and Kaplan, 2006; Mayor et al, 2007; da Silva Correia  et al, 2007) implicates it as a client protein adaptor co-
chaperone in a similar manner to Cdc37, albeit with a more 
structurally varied clientele. 
Sgt1 consists of three identifiable domains: an N-terminal 
tetratricopeptide repeat (TPR) domain similar to those found 
in many other Hsp90 and Hsp70 co-chaperones; a central 
'CHORD and Sgt1' (CS) domain related to the b-sandwich 
domain of small heat-shock proteins, a-crystallin and the 
Hsp90 co-chaperone p23/Sba1; and a C-terminal Sgt-specific 
(SGS) domain. All three domains mediate protein-protein 
interactions. The SGS region has been implicated in interac-
tion with leucine-rich repeat domains in the yeast adenylate 
cyclase Cdc35p (Dubacq et al, 2002), plant R proteins (Bieri </p>

<p>Received: 30 April 2008; accepted: 2 August 2008; published online: 
25 September 2008 </p>

<p>*Corresponding authors. K Shirasu, Plant Immunity Research Group, 
RIKEN Plant Science Center, 1-7-22 Suehiro-cho, Tsurumi, Yokohama 
230-0045, Japan. Tel.: +81 45 503 9574; Fax: +81 45 503 9573; 
E-mail: ken.shirasu@psc.riken.jp or LH Pearl, Section of Structural 
Biology, The Institute of Cancer Research, Chester Beatty Laboratories, 
237 Fulham Road, London SW3 6JB, UK. Tel.: þ 44 207 970 6045/6; 
Fax: þ 44 207 970 6051; E-mail: laurence.pearl@icr.ac.uk. </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal (2008) 27, 2789-2798 | &amp; 2008 European Molecular Biology Organization | Some Rights Reserved 0261-4189/08 </p>

<p>www.embojournal.org </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 27 | NO 20 | 2008 </p>

<p>EMBO </p>

<p>THE </p>

<p>EMBO </p>

<p>JOURNAL </p>

<p>THE </p>

<p>EMBO </p>

<p>JOURNAL </p>



<p>et al, 2004; Leister et al, 2005) and the mammalian Nod1 
receptor (da Silva Correia et al, 2007). Although initial studies 
implicated the TPR domain as essential for interaction 
with both Hsp90 and Skp1 (Bansal et al, 2004), further 
analysis suggests that the N-terminal TPR domain mediates 
interactions with Skp1, whereas the central CS domain is 
responsible for the recruitment of Sgt1 to Hsp90 (Lee et al,  2004; Lingelbach and Kaplan, 2004; Catlett and Kaplan,  2006). Immunoprecipitation and yeast two-hybrid (Y2H) 
assays identify the N-terminal half of Hsp90 as sufficient for 
interaction with Sgt1 (Takahashi et al, 2003). 
To gain some insight into the coupling of the Hsp90 and 
Sgt1 protein interaction 'hubs', we have determined the 
crystal structure of the Hsp90-N-Sgt1-CS core complex. The 
structure reveals a hitherto unknown locus of interaction on 
Hsp90, and facilitates a targeted mutational analysis that 
reveals the Hsp90 dependence of Sgt1 functions in vivo. 
Biochemical analysis of Sgt1 interactions suggests a role 
for Hsp90-Sgt1 in the assembly of SCF ubiquitin ligase 
complexes. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>We explored a range of Hsp90 and Sgt1 constructs from 
different species and obtained diffracting crystals of the 
core Hsp90-Sgt1 complex using an N-terminal domain con-
struct of Hordeum vulgare (barley) Hsp90 and a CS domain 
construct from the Arabidopsis thaliana homologue, AtSgt1a. 
HvHsp90 is 64% identical to yeast Hsp82 and 70% identical 
to human Hsp90b, whereas AtSgt1a is 32 and 36% identical, 
respectively, to its yeast and human homologues. The struc-
ture of the complex was solved by molecular replacement 
with the crystal structure of yeast Hsp90-N domain and the 
NMR structure of human Sgt1-CS domain. The crystals con-</p>

<p>tain three independent copies of the complex, each with a 
bound ADP molecule, and has been refined at 3.3-Å resolu-
tion (see Materials and methods and Table I). 
The structure of yeast and human Hsp90-N domains has 
been described earlier (Prodromou et al, 1997; Stebbins et al,  1997) and the barley Hsp90-N domain is essentially identical 
in structure (r.m.s.d. B0.75 and 0.67 Å , respectively for 198 
and 172 common Ca positions). The mobile 'lid' segment, 
which closes over the nucleotide-binding pocket in the ATP-
bound closed state of the Hsp90 (Ali et al, 2006), is in a fully 
open conformation in the Hsp90-N-Sgt1-CS complex, and an 
ADP molecule is present in the nucleotide-binding pocket. 
The AtSgt1a CS domain has the same b3-b4 'sandwich' 
structure seen in the NMR structure of HsSgt1-CS domain 
(Lee et al, 2004), with small differences in the conformation 
of the loops connecting the b-strands. </p>

<p>Hsp90-N-Sgt1-CS interface 
The crystal lattice is such that each of the b-sheet faces of the 
Sgt1-CS domain structure contacts a different Hsp90-N 
domain through distinct regions (Figure 1A). Although a 
single Sgt1 molecule might interact simultaneously with 
both-N domains in an Hsp90 dimer, this is inconsistent 
with the B1:1 binding stoichiometry suggested by ITC 
(Supplementary Figure 1). It is most likely that one of the 
Hsp90-Sgt1 interfaces is the biologically significant inter-
action, whereas the other is a lattice contact necessary for 
crystal formation. To identify the biologically significant 
interface, we analysed the conservation of the residues 
involved. In the case of Hsp90, which is highly conserved 
throughout, there was no clear difference between the two 
points of contact with Sgt1-CS in the crystal. However, 
Sgt1 showed a marked difference, with the residues involved 
in one interaction being very much more conserved overall, 
and with some contributing residues (Tyr157, Lys221 and 
Glu223) identical in all species (Figure 1B; Supplementary 
Figure 2). 
The conserved interface is formed by residues from strands 
one, two and three from the four-stranded face of Sgt1-CS 
and the first strand and third helix of Hsp90-N domain 
(Figure 1C). The core interaction is provided by Tyr157 
from AtSgt1a, the hydroxyl group of which hydrogen bonds 
to the side chains of Glu6 and Lys88 of HvHsp90, whereas its 
aromatic face packs into a hydrophobic recess on HvHsp90 
formed by the side chains of Phe8, Val92 and Lys88, and the 
main chain of Ser89. Sgt1 Tyr157 is absolutely conserved, as 
are all the interacting residues in Hsp90, apart from Ser89, 
which is alanine in non-plant Hsp90s. Phe168 provides a 
second hydrophobic interaction, packing between the side 
chains of Thr87, Asp144 and Asp145 on Hsp90. Phe168 is 
also highly conserved, being phenylalanine in plants and 
yeast, and methionine in metazoa. These hydrophobic inter-
actions are supported by an extensive network of polar 
interactions involving Arg153, Glu155, Thr166, Lys170, 
Lys221 and Glu223 from Sgt1, and Ser89, Asn93, Asp144, 
Asp145 and Glu146 from Hsp90 (Figure 1C). All the Sgt1 
residues involved are at least very highly conserved, whereas 
the Hsp90 residues, with the exception of Ser89, are invar-
iant. The Sgt1-CS interaction site on Hsp90 does not involve 
the mobile lid segment nor does it impinge upon the ATP-
binding pocket at the heart of the N domain (Figure 1D). </p>

<p>Table I Crystallographic statistics </p>

<p>Data collection 
HvHsp90-N-AtSgt1a-CS 
Space group 
P2 1 2 1 2 1 
a, b, c (Å ) 
100.268, 129.654, 135.998 
Wavelength (Å ) 
0.9537 
Resolution (Å ) 
38.1-3.3 (3.48-3.3) 
R merge 
0.161 (0.561) 
I/sI 
8.5 (2.3) 
Completeness (%) 
99.5 (99.9) 
Redundancy 
3.6 (3.6) </p>

<p>Refinement 
Number of reflections 
50 605 
R work /R free 
0.20/0.24 </p>

<p>Number of atoms 
Protein+ADP 
7404 </p>

<p>B-factors 
Protein+ADP 
59.7 </p>

<p>r.m.s.d. 
Bond lengths (Å ) 
0.012 
Bond angles (deg) 
1.483 </p>

<p>Ramachandran statistics 
Preferred 
88.8% 
Allowed 
8.7% 
Outliers 
2.4% </p>

<p>Hsp90-and Sgt1-centred multi-protein complexes 
M Zhang et al </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 27 | NO 20 | 2008 </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>



<p>Targeted disruption of Hsp90-Sgt1 interaction 
Although the conservation pattern clearly identifies the bio-
logically significant Hsp90-Sgt1 interface, we were concerned 
to verify this interaction outside the context of a crystal 
lattice. We examined the effect of mutations in residues on 
the surface of AtSgt1a-CS, on its ability to interact with the 
HvHsp90-N domain, using the Y2H system (Boter et al,  2007). Mutations of AtSgt1a-Tyr199, at the heart of the non-
conserved crystal lattice contact, had no effect on the Y2H 
interaction with Hsp90, nor did mutation of AtSgt1a-Thr220 </p>

<p>on the periphery of the conserved interface. However muta-
tions of Tyr157, Phe168, Lys221 and Glu223, in the conserved 
interface, all significantly diminished the interaction, con-
firming its functional significance (Figure 2A). None of these 
mutations affected the Y2H interaction with AtRAR1, the 
interaction of which is mediated by a different region of the 
AtSgt1a-CS domain (Boter et al, 2007), confirming that these 
mutations do not disrupt CS domain folding. 
To confirm that this interaction was conserved across 
species, we used an in vitro co-precipitation assay with </p>

<p>Figure 1 Crystal structure of Hsp90-N-Sgt1-CS complex. (A) In the crystals, opposite faces of the Sgt1-CS domain b-sandwich structure interact 
with different parts of adjacent Hsp90-N domains. (B) Conservation colouring of the Sgt1-CS surface (blue-red; most-least conserved) based 
on the alignment in Supplementary Figure 2. The surface shown on the left is highly conserved with a ridge of essentially invariant residues 
that form the interface with Hsp90. The very high degree of conservation suggests that this interface is biologically authentic, whereas that on 
the right is a crystal lattice contact. (C) Detail of the conserved Hsp90-N-Sgt1-CS interface. The interface is built around two hydrophobic 
patches, centred on Sgt1-Tyr157 and Phe168, reinforced by a network of hydrogen bonding interactions (dotted lines). Formation of the 
complex buries B1100 Å 
2 of molecular surface, which is consistent with a reversible interface. (D) Overview of the Hsp90-N-Sgt1-CS 
interaction based on the conserved interface. The ADP bound in the pocket of the Hsp90-N domain and the mobile 'lid' segment that closes in 
the ATP-bound state of Hsp90 are indicated. </p>

<p>Hsp90-and Sgt1-centred multi-protein complexes 
M Zhang et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 27 | NO 20 | 2008 2791 </p>

<p>human homologues to follow Hsp90-Sgt1 interactions in 
solution (see Materials and methods), and compared the 
interaction of wild-type Sgt1 with mutants intended to disrupt 
the conserved Sgt1-Hsp90 interface. GST-tagged full-length 
wild-type human Sgt1 efficiently co-precipitated hHsp90b 
(Figure 2B). In contrast, Arg or Ala mutations of Tyr145 
(equivalent to AtSgt1a-Tyr157), significantly decreased the 
ability of hSgt1 to co-precipitate hHsp90b. 
Using the plant system, we mutated several residues in the 
wheat (Triticum aestivum) Hsp90-N domain that are involved 
in the interface with Sgt1, which also involves the equivalent 
of Tyr157. Mutation of TaHsp90 Ser89 and Val92, both of 
which directly contact AtSgt1a Tyr157 to Glu and Thr, respec-
tively, significantly decreased their ability to be co-precipi-
tated by GST-AtSgt1a when compared with wild type. By 
contrast an Ala99Glu mutant, which is not directly involved 
in this interface, was efficiently co-precipitated (Figure 2C). 
Taken together, the strong conservation of the residues on 
the four-stranded face involved in interaction with Hsp90 and 
the disruption of that interaction, in vitro and in the Y2H 
system, by mutations on either side of that interface argue </p>

<p>very strongly that this is the biologically authentic site of 
interaction between the two proteins and that it is both 
necessary and sufficient for that interaction. </p>

<p>Sgt1 couples Hsp90 to SCF complexes 
Yeast Sgt1p binds simultaneously to yHsp90 (Hsp82p) and 
ySkp1p, suggesting that it functions as an adaptor linking the 
two proteins (Catlett and Kaplan, 2006). We verified this 
interaction using the human proteins and observed co-
precipitation of hSkp1 with His 6 -tagged hHsp90a only in 
the presence of hSgt1 (Figure 3A). With the Tyr145Arg or 
Tyr145Ala hSgt1 mutants, no hSkp1 was co-precipitated. 
However, GST fusions of both hSgt1 mutants were fully 
competent in co-precipitating hSkp1, confirming that the 
Hsp90-and Skp1-interacting regions of Sgt1 are functionally 
independent (Figure 3B). </p>

<p>Figure 2 Targeted disruption of Hsp90-N-Sgt1-CS interaction. 
(A) Yeast two-hybrid analysis of AtSgt1a-CS mutants. AtSGT1a 
or its derivatives were assayed for interaction with AtRAR1 and 
HvHSP90-N using LexA Yeast Two-Hybrid system. Mutation of 
residues Tyr157, Phe168, Lys221 or Glu223, in the conserved inter-
face with Hsp90-N, abrogated reporter activation. (B) Co-precipita-
tion assay with His 6 -tagged human Hsp90b, and human Sgt1. Hsp90 
efficiently co-precipitates wild-type Sgt1, but not mutants of the 
core interface residue, Tyr145 (equivalent to Tyr157 in the plant 
protein). (C) Co-precipitation assay with GST-tagged Arabidopsis 
Sgt1a, and plant Hsp90. AtSgt1a co-precipitates wild-type TaHsp90 
or TaHsp90 with mutation of a residue not in the observed interface, 
but does not efficiently co-precipitate TaHsp90 with mutations in 
interfacial residues Ser89 or Val92. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Sgt1 interactions with SCF complex. (A) Bridged co-pre-
cipitation assay with His 6 -tagged human Hsp90b, Sgt1 and Skp1. 
Hsp90 efficiently co-precipitates Skp1 (visualized by western blot) 
only when wild-type Sgt1 is present to bridge the interaction. 
Mutations in the Sgt1 Hsp90-binding residue Tyr145 prevent Skp1 
co-precipitation. (B) Direct co-precipitation of Skp1 by Sgt1 (visua-
lized by western blot) is not affected by Sgt1 Tyr145 mutations. 
(C) Sgt1 is co-precipitated by GST-Skp1-Skp2 or GST-Skp1-Skp2 
(F-Box) complexes, with no competitive displacement of Skp2 by 
increasing concentrations of Sgt1. Input protein loadings (10%) are 
visualized with Coomassie Brilliant Blue (CBB) and co-precipitated 
proteins are visualized by western blot. (D) Co-precipitation of Skp1 
by GST-tagged Sgt1 is diminished by increasing concentrations of 
Cul1, showing competition between Sgt1 and Cul1 for binding to 
Skp1. Protein is visualized as in (C). (E) His 6 -tagged Cul1 efficiently 
co-precipitates Skp1, but not Sgt1, showing that there is no direct 
interaction between Cul1 and Sgt1, and that Skp1 cannot bind Cul1 
and Sgt1 simultaneously. Increasing concentrations of Sgt1 fail to 
displace Cul1, which binds Skp1 B70-fold tighter than Sgt1. </p>

<p>Hsp90-and Sgt1-centred multi-protein complexes 
M Zhang et al </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 27 | NO 20 | 2008 </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>



<p>Skp1 is functionally associated with a variety of proteins 
containing an 'F-box'-a small helical-coil domain that med-
iates interaction with the C-terminal part of Skp1 in the 
context of SCF E3 ubiquitin ligases (Hao et al, 2005). 
Previous studies have shown that interaction with Skp1 is 
mediated by the TPR domain of Sgt1 (Catlett and Kaplan,  2006). As TPR domains are also helical-coil structures, we 
considered the possibility that Sgt1 might be a cryptic 'F-box' 
protein and interact with the same site on Skp1. To test this, 
we co-expressed human Skp1 with Skp2, an F-box protein 
that mediates the recruitment of p27 
kip1 to SCF complexes 
(Hao et al, 2005), which would therefore compete with Sgt1 if 
it interacted with the F-box-binding site on Skp1. We found 
that the Skp1-Skp2 complex or a Skp1-Skp2(F-box) complex 
was fully able to co-precipitate Sgt1, without competitive 
displacement of Skp2 with increasing concentrations of Sgt1 
(Figure 3C). This suggests that Sgt1 interacts primarily with 
the N-terminal lobe of Skp1 and can coexist in Skp1 com-
plexes with Skp2 (and probably other F-box proteins), the 
binding site of which is in the C-terminal lobe. 
As well as binding F-box proteins, Skp1 binds to Cullin 
scaffold proteins such as Cul1, through its N-terminal lobe. 
Cullins couple Skp1 to the Rbx1 ring-finger protein that 
catalyses transfer of ubiquitin from an E2 ubiquitin conju-
gate, to a lysine on the target protein bound by the F-box 
protein, or to a ubiquitin molecule already attached to the 
target. Again, we considered the possibility that the TPR 
domain of Sgt1 might bind to Skp1 in competition with 
Cul1. Although GST-Sgt1 was able to co-precipitate Skp1 in 
isolation, the presence of Cul1 in the reaction decreased 
the co-precipitation of Skp1 in a dose-dependent manner 
(Figure 3D). In the inverse experiment, Cul1 co-precipitated 
Skp1, but not Sgt1 present in the same reaction (Figure 3E), 
confirming that Cul1 and Sgt1 do not interact directly, and 
that they bind to Skp1 with mutual exclusion. However, we 
were not able to decrease the amount of Skp1 co-precipitated 
by Cul1 with increasing amounts of Sgt1. To analyse this 
further, we directly determined the affinities of Sgt1 and 
of Cul1, for Skp1, using isothermal titration calorimetry 
(Supplementary Figure 3). Although Sgt1 bound in the low 
micromolar range (K D ¼ 1.64 mM), Cul1 bound Skp1 B70-fold 
more tightly, with a dissociation constant of B24 nM, so that 
Cul1 could not be competed off a Cul1-Skp1 complex by 
comparable levels of Sgt1. Taken together, these data are fully 
consistent with Sgt1 and Cul1 binding in mutual exclusion at 
a common or at least overlapping binding site on the 
N-terminal half of Skp1. </p>

<p>In vivo coupling of Hsp90-and Sgt1-centred complexes 
Hsp90 is the hub of a nexus of physical and functional 
interactions with complexes involved in signalling and tran-
scriptional regulation, the component proteins of which form 
the dependent clientele of the Hsp90 chaperone system (Pearl  and Prodromou, 2006; Zhao and Houry, 2007). Sgt1 has also 
been implicated in the assembly and function of diverse 
protein complexes, including CBF3 kinetochore, SCF E3 
ubiquitin ligase and adenyl cyclase complexes in yeast 
(Kitagawa et al, 1999; Dubacq et al, 2002) and R-proteins 
and Nod-like receptors in plants and animals (Peart et al,  2002; Bieri et al, 2004; Leister et al, 2005; da Silva Correia  et al, 2007; Mayor et al, 2007). Sgt1 therefore also has the 
characteristics of an interaction hub. However, it is not clear </p>

<p>whether Sgt1 has an independent function in any of these 
systems, or whether it functions purely as a scaffold protein, 
coupling them to Hsp90. 
To gain some insight into this, we utilized our structural 
and biochemical data to engineer mutations in plant Sgt1, 
in vivo, which would be expected to specifically disrupt its 
interaction with Hsp90, but not with other known ligand 
proteins. Using a GFP-tagged fluorescent virus propagation 
assay, as described earlier (Azevedo et al, 2006; Boter et al,  2007), we determined the Rx-protein-mediated resistance to 
infection by potato virus X (PVX), of tobacco leaves 
(Nicotiana benthamiana) silenced for endogenous Sgt1, and 
heterologously complemented with wild-type or mutant 
AtSgt1a (see Materials and methods). Alanine mutations of 
Tyr199 on the three-stranded face of AtSgt1a-CS domain or of 
Thr220 on the four-stranded face, but not involved in direct 
contact with Hsp90, had no effect on the ability of the mutant 
protein to confer resistance to infection. Alanine mutations of 
Glu223 or Thr166, which are part of the Hsp90-interacting 
surface, also had little effect on resistance. However, alanine 
mutation of Tyr157, at the heart of the interface with Hsp90, 
or a charge reversal mutation of Lys221 close by, caused a 
substantial loss of resistance, comparable to an Sgt1a null 
(Figure 4A). The ability of a single missense mutation in Sgt1 
that specifically disrupts its interaction with Hsp90 in vitro, to 
disrupt R-gene-mediated viral resistance in vivo, provides 
definitive evidence for the direct dependence of this class of 
innate immunity system on the Hsp90 chaperone system, 
with Sgt1 acting as a molecular scaffold coupling the two. 
Although yeast lacks homologues of plant R-proteins or 
animal Nod-like receptors, Sgt1 is essential in yeast, not least 
due to its involvement in the CBF3 kinetochore complex, and 
the SCF E3 ubiquitin ligases that regulate cell cycle transitions 
(Kitagawa et al, 1999). To determine whether essential Sgt1 
functions in yeast are also dependent on its interaction with 
Hsp90, we engineered similar interface-disrupting point 
mutations, singly and in combination, into yeast Sgt1 and 
determined their ability to confer viability in the absence of 
a wild-type Sgt1 allele (see Materials and methods). 
Unlike the plant system, single-point mutations in either 
of the main hydrophobic Sgt1 interface residues (Tyr190, 
Phe201Tyr157, Phe168 in plants) had little effect 
(Figure 4B). However, double mutants abrogated viability. 
This is consistent with the observation of multiple missense 
mutations in previously identified ts SGT1 alleles (Kitagawa  et al, 1999). Furthermore, although viable under normal 
conditions, yeast harbouring Sgt1 single-point mutants were 
significantly more sensitive to the Hsp90 inhibitor, geldana-
mycin, than wild type (Figure 4C). Taken together, these data 
confirm the dependence of essential Sgt1 functions in yeast 
on its ability to form a stable complex with Hsp90. </p>

<p>TPR co-chaperone compatibility 
The extreme C terminus of Hsp90 consists of an MEEVD 
motif that provides the binding site for a range of co-chaper-
ones containing TPR domains. Although Sgt1 possesses a 
TPR domain, this is not essential for Hsp90 binding (Lee et al,  2004; Lingelbach and Kaplan, 2004). Furthermore, a yeast 
TPR domain co-chaperone, Sti1 known to interact with the C 
terminus of Hsp90, bound simultaneously with Sgt1 (Catlett  and Kaplan, 2006). We found that the human TPR domain 
co-chaperone CHIP was also able to bind to Hsp90 at the </p>

<p>Hsp90-and Sgt1-centred multi-protein complexes 
M Zhang et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 27 | NO 20 | 2008 2793 </p>

<p>same time as Sgt1 (Figure 5), showing that Sgt1 can most 
likely coexist in Hsp90 complexes with a range of TPR 
domain co-chaperones. As Sgt1 is able to couple Hsp90 to 
the Skp1 and F-box components of SCF E3 ligase systems, its 
ability to coexist in Hsp90 complexes with CHIP, an active E3 
ubiquitin ligase, is particularly interesting. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Hsp90 interaction and nucleotide dependence 
The Hsp90-Sgt1 core complex structure reveals a previously 
unknown site of co-chaperone interaction on the chaperone. 
Binding sites have been characterized in the middle domain </p>

<p>for the ATPase activator Aha1 (Meyer et al, 2004), and at the 
C-terminal MEEVD motif for a variety of TPR domain co-
chaperones (reviewed in Pearl and Prodromou, 2006). Sgt1 
also possesses a TPR domain, but this does not bind to Hsp90 
in isolation, and Hsp90 constructs lacking the MEEVD motif 
are still able to bind Sgt1 (Catlett and Kaplan, 2006). Cdc37 
interacts with the open conformation of the lid segment in the 
N-terminal nucleotide-binding domain and arrests Hsp90's 
ATPase cycle (Roe et al, 2004). p23/Sba1 also interacts with 
the lid segment in the N domain, but only in its closed 
conformation within the closed ATP-bound state of the 
chaperone, and in doing so reinforces the interaction of the 
N domains within the closed dimer to each other and to the 
middle domains (Ali et al, 2006). Although the CS domain of 
Sgt1 and the globular core domain of p23/Sba1 have similar 
three-dimensional structures, they bind to different regions of 
the Hsp90 surface, using different parts of their own struc-
tures. Sgt1 utilizes residues on the surface of the four-
stranded b-sheet, whereas a C-terminal strand, not present 
in Sgt1-CS, provides the majority of p23/Sba1a interaction 
with Hsp90-N (Figure 6A). 
Most significant mechanistically are the different sites of 
interaction of p23/Sba1 and Sgt1-CS on Hsp90-N, and their 
effect on the conformational changes associated with Hsp90s 
ATPase cycle. p23/Sba1 interacts with residues on the lid 
segment of Hsp90 that are only available in the ATP-bound 
conformation of the chaperone (Ali et al, 2006), explaining 
the strongly ATP-dependent binding of p23/Sba1 (Sullivan  et al, 1997; Siligardi et al, 2004). Sgt1-CS binds to Hsp90-N 
away from the lid and ATP-binding pocket, so that its 
preferential binding in the absence of ATP (Lee et al, 2004;  Catlett and Kaplan, 2006) is difficult to explain at first sight. 
However, part of the interaction is provided by Glu6 and Phe8 
from the N-terminal strand of Hsp90, which undergoes a 
large movement during the ATPase cycle, swapping from its 
own N domain in the open ATP-free state (Prodromou et al,  1997) to bind to the other N domain in the closed ATP-bound 
conformation (Ali et al, 2006), recapitulating its previous 
interactions. Although Sgt1-CS could interact with the N-
terminal strand in the ATP-free or ATP-bound states, it 
would certainly be displaced during the ATP-driven confor-
mational change, so that in the presence of ATP the equili-
brium concentration of Hsp90-Sgt1 complexes would be 
lower than in its absence. Furthermore, when the Hsp90-
N-Sgt1-CS complex is used to model binding of Sgt1-CS 
domains to both Hsp90-N domains in the closed ATP-bound </p>

<p>Figure 5 Co-binding of TPR domain E3 ligase CHIP and Sgt1. His 6 -
tagged human Hsp90b efficiently co-precipitates Sgt1 and CHIP, 
confirming that the TPR domain of Sgt1 does not interact with the 
C-terminal MEEVD sequence of Hsp90, which provides the binding 
site for CHIP, and other TPR domain co-chaperones. </p>

<p>Figure 4 Functional dependence of Sgt1 on Hsp90 interaction in 
vivo. (A) Functional assay of SGT1a mutants in Rx-mediated 
resistance against potato virus X (PVX). Rx-containing N. benthami-
ana plants silenced for NbSGT1 were co-infiltrated with 
Agrobacterium expressing wild-type AtSGT1a (lower left, positive 
control), or AtSGT1a mutants as indicated (right half of the leaf) or 
GUS (upper left, negative control) together with PVX-GFP. Virus 
accumulation was monitored by GFP fluorescence under UV illu-
mination 5 days after inoculation. Mutations in residues not in-
volved in the core interface (Tyr199 and Thr220) with Hsp90 had 
little effect on the ability of AtSgt1a to facilitate viral resistance. 
Mutations of the hydrophobic Hsp90 interface residues Tyr157 or 
Phe168, and charge-reversal mutations in polar interface residues 
Lys221 or Glu223, severely impaired the biological function of 
Sgt1a. (B) Single-point mutations in Hsp90-interacting residues 
did not significantly impair essential Sgt1 functions in yeast (left), 
but double mutants abolished viability (right). (C) Single-point 
mutations in Hsp90-interacting residues in yeast Sgt1 sensitize 
yeast to killing by the Hsp90 inhibitor geldanamycin (GA). </p>

<p>Hsp90-and Sgt1-centred multi-protein complexes 
M Zhang et al </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 27 | NO 20 | 2008 </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>



<p>structure of the dimer (Figure 6B), there is a steric clash 
between the two Sgt1-CS domains. This may be exacerbated 
by the presence of the N-terminal TPR and C-terminal SGS 
domains, the disposition of which within the overall Hsp90-
Sgt1 complex is not currently known. </p>

<p>Function of the Hsp90-Sgt1 couple 
The range of functions in which Hsp90 is an essential 
participant continues to increase (Pearl et al, 2008). Rather </p>

<p>than clarifying the biochemical basis of Hsp90 involvement, 
the diversity of the expanding protein clientele makes it 
increasingly difficult to understand selective interaction 
with Hsp90 in terms of any common structural motif. At 
least part of this selectivity comes from co-chaperones such 
as Cdc37 that function as adaptors, recruiting specific classes 
of clients to Hsp90. 
Sgt1 fulfils the requirements of an Hsp90 adaptor co-
chaperone, interacting with Hsp90 through its CS domain, 
and with a range of putative client proteins through its TPR 
and SGS domains. Unlike Cdc37 however, it does not appear 
to regulate the ATPase activity of Hsp90 (Catlett and Kaplan,  2006). In plant innate immunity systems, Sgt1 is essential not 
only for the activity of R-proteins but also for their stable 
accumulation (Bieri et al, 2004; Azevedo et al, 2006; Boter  et al, 2007). However, the related mammalian Nod-like 
receptors lose activity, but not stability, when Sgt1 is knocked 
down (da Silva Correia et al, 2007). They are nonetheless 
depleted by pharmacological inhibition of Hsp90, suggesting 
that this biologically widespread family of proteins are bone 
fide Hsp90 clients. 
Chaperone-client relationships are less clear in the Sgt1-
mediated coupling of Hsp90 and SCF complexes. A variety of 
different SCF subassemblies can be expressed in a functional 
state in bacteria, which argues against a stringent client 
dependence on Hsp90, and no depletion of SCF components 
on Hsp90 inhibition has been reported. Sgt1 physically 
couples Hsp90 and Skp1 (Catlett and Kaplan, 2006) and we 
have extended that observation to show that Sgt1 binds Skp1 
in the presence of an F-box protein. Thus, Sgt1 links Hsp90 to 
the target-specific 'arm' of an SCF complex. The ability of 
Sgt1 to bind Skp1 alongside an F-box protein explains the 
association of Hsp90-Sgt1 with the yeast CBF3 kinetochore 
complex (Kitagawa et al, 1999; Stemmann et al, 2002; Bansal  et al, 2004; Lingelbach and Kaplan, 2004; Rodrigo-Brenni  et al, 2004; Steensgaard et al, 2004), as the Ctf13 component 
of CBF3 is an F-box protein, that is itself the target of 
ubiquitin-dependent degradation (Kaplan et al, 1997). 
In contrast to F-box proteins, we found that Sgt1 binding to 
Skp1 was mutually exclusive with binding of Cul1, which 
provides the generic arm of the SCF complex, recruiting the 
ring-finger E3 ubiquitin ligase enzyme Rbx1. At first sight, 
this appears to be in contradiction to a reported co-precipita-
tion from yeast lysates of the cullin Cdc53p, as well as Skp1p, 
by Sgt1p (Kitagawa et al, 1999). However, when SCF compo-
nents were expressed in insect cells in the same study, the 
amount of Sgt1p co-precipitated by the F-box protein Cdc4p 
was decreased when Cdc53p was also present, consistent 
with our clear observation using purified human proteins that 
Cul1 and Sgt1 compete for Skp1 binding. 
Association of the cullin arm with the specific arm of SCF 
complexes, through binding to Skp1, is regulated by a com-
plex cycle of reversible modification involving covalent at-
tachment of NEDD8, a ubiquitin-like protein, to Cul1. 
Neddylated Cul1 in complex with Rbx1 associates with 
Skp1 and its attendant F-box protein and is fully competent 
to recruit E2 ubiquitin conjugates and ubiquitinate the sub-
strate protein bound to the F-box protein (Wu et al, 2006). 
This active SCF complex is inactivated when NEDD8 is 
removed by the COP9 signalosome complex (Lyapina et al,  2001). De-neddylated Cul1 is then bound by Cand1 with 
concomitant displacement of the Skp1-F-Box subcomplex </p>

<p>Figure 6 CS domain interactions. (A) Comparison of the binding 
surfaces used by the structurally homologous CS domains of the 
Hsp90 co-chaperones Sgt1 (left) and p23/Sba1 (right). Sgt1-CS uses 
residues on the face of its four-stranded b-sheet, whereas p23/Sba1 
interacts with Hsp90-N through a C-terminal extension not present 
in Sgt1. The interaction site on Hsp90-N (bottom, magenta) is also 
completely different, with Sgt1-CS binding the side of the domain, 
whereas p23/Sba1 binds directly to the lid segment in its closed 
ATP-bound conformation. (B) Hypothetical model of Sgt1-CS bind-
ing to Hsp90 in the closed ATP-bound conformation, made by 
superimposing the Hsp90-N domain from the present structure on 
to the crystal structure of the full-length Hsp90-AMPPNP-p23/Sba1 
structure (PDB code 2CG9). Consistent with the preference of Sgt1 
for binding to the open ADP-bound state of Hsp90, the docked Sgt1-
CS domains clash sterically, and this is likely to be exacerbated in 
the context of the full-length protein by the TPR and SGS domains, 
which extend from the N-and C terminus, respectively. </p>

<p>Hsp90-and Sgt1-centred multi-protein complexes 
M Zhang et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 27 | NO 20 | 2008 2795 </p>

<p>and blockade of the NEDD8 attachment site on the cullin 
(Goldenberg et al, 2004). Regeneration of an active SCF 
complex thus requires displacement of Cand1, neddylation 
and association with a new Skp1-F-Box substrate complex 
(Wu et al, 2006). The ability of Sgt1 to couple Hsp90 to the 
specific arm of SCF complexes, along with its competitive 
displacement by the cullin arm, suggests a clear chaperone 
role for Hsp90-Sgt1 in binding and stabilizing a Skp1-F-Box 
substrate complex in the absence of Cul1-Rbx1. This is fully 
consistent with the observation of the B70-fold higher affi-
nity we observe with Cul1, as compared with Sgt1, for 
binding to Skp1, which would ensure efficient displacement 
of Hsp90-Sgt1 from a new Skp1-F-Box substrate complex by 
Cul1, once freed of its inhibitory association with Cand1. The </p>

<p>ATPase cycle of Hsp90 could have a function in facilitating 
the release of Cul1 from Cand1, and allowing its re-associa-
tion with Skp1 to regenerate an active SCF complex 
(Figure 7A and B); however, further work will be required 
to test this possibility. A role for Hsp90-Sgt1 in facilitating the 
assembly of SCF complexes is fully consistent with observa-
tions that defective SGT1 alleles in yeast impair SCF-depen-
dent turnover of Sic1p in vivo, and extracts from SGT1-
impaired strains are defective in cyclin ubiquitination 
in vitro (Kitagawa et al, 1999). 
Hsp90 might also have a function in facilitating or regulat-
ing access of the substrate protein to the SCF system. A 
number of proteins known to be Hsp90 clients are degraded 
through SCF complexes, most significant of which is probably 
the cell cycle regulatory tyrosine kinase Wee1 (Aligue et al,  1994; Watanabe et al, 2004). However, the interplay between 
these two Wee1-interacting pathways has not so far been 
characterized, although both are required for proper mitotic 
entry. It has long been known that inhibition of Hsp90 
promotes ubiquitin-dependent degradation of its client pro-
teins (Mimnaugh et al, 1996), but the E3 systems responsible, 
particularly for protein kinases, have not been unambigu-
ously identified. The TPR domain U-box protein CHIP is an 
E3 ubiquitin ligase able to associate with Hsp90 or Hsp70 
through the C-terminal EEVD motif (Cyr et al, 2002; Zhang  et al, 2005), and is a clear candidate for that role, although 
there are only a few clear demonstrations of CHIP's involve-
ment in the degradation of major Hsp90 clients such as 
protein kinases (Xu et al, 2002; Zhang et al, 2007). The ability 
of CHIP to bind to an Hsp90-Sgt1 complex raises the possi-
bility that it could have a function in ubiquitination of 
Skp1-F-Box-bound substrate proteins, possibly as a backup 
under stress conditions, or in some circumstances in direct 
collaboration with the SCF system (Nelson et al, 2006). </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Y2H analysis 
AtSGT1a point mutations were obtained by site-directed mutagen-
esis (BIO S&amp;T) using AtSGT1a-pGEX-6P-1 construct. AtSGT1a WT 
and mutant derivates were cloned in pLexA (Clontech) as EcoRI/ 
NotI. AtRAR1 and HvHSP90-NTD clones in pB42AD were described 
earlier (Takahashi et al, 2003). Interaction analyses were carried out 
as described in the manufacturer's protocol (MATCHMAKER; 
Clontech). </p>

<p>Rx-mediated resistance assay in N. benthamiana 
AtSGT1a and mutant derivates were PCR amplified, cloned into 
pBIN61 as XbaI/BamHI and transformed into Agrobacterium 
tumefaciens C58C1 carrying plasmid pCH32. Transgenic 
N. benthamiana plants expressing Rx:HA under the control of its 
own promoter were silenced for NbSGT1 as described earlier 
(Azevedo et al, 2006) and co-infiltrated with Agrobacterium 
expressing AtSGT1a or mutant derivates (OD ¼ 0.3) and PVX-GFP 
(OD ¼ 0.001). PVX accumulation was monitored by GFP fluores-
cence under UV illumination 5 days after inoculation. </p>

<p>Strains and plasmids 
The Saccharomyces cerevisiae YKK39 (mata ura3-52, lys2-801, ade2-
101, trp1-D63 his3-D200 leu2-D1 sgt1D1HHIS31) was used as the 
host strain for the expression of SGT1 mutant alleles (Kitagawa  et al, 1999). Its viability was maintained by the SGT1 gene of the 
centromeric (single copy) URA3 plasmid pRS316-SGT1 (Kitagawa  et al, 1999). </p>

<p>Figure 7 A role for Hsp90-Sgt1 in SCF assembly. (A) Previous 
observations and data presented here that Hsp90-Sgt1 can interact 
with Skp1 in complex with an F-box protein such as Skp2. In such a 
complex, a client/substrate protein (S) could be bound to either the 
chaperone or to the F-box protein, and in principle could be 
transferred from one to the other. (B) Competitive displacement 
of Hsp90-Sgt1 from Skp1 by Cul1-Rbx1, concomitant with the 
release of Cul1-Rbx1 from Cand1, would permit formation of an 
active SCF complex, able to be neddylated and bind E2. Disruption 
of the Cand1-Cul1 interaction might require the ATPase activity of 
Hsp90. (C) Alternatively, as a parallel pathway during stress con-
ditions or when the SCF route is overloaded, an Hsp90-Sgt1-Skp1-
F-box protein complex could allow ubiquitination of a client/sub-
strate protein by the recruitment of CHIP to the C-terminal binding 
site on Hsp90. </p>

<p>Hsp90-and Sgt1-centred multi-protein complexes 
M Zhang et al </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 27 | NO 20 | 2008 </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>



<p>Mutagenesis and plasmid construction 
Amino-acid changes were generated in the SGT1 gene of the 
centromeric (single copy) LEU2 plasmid pRS315-SGT1 (Lingelbach 
and Kaplan, 2004), using the QuickChange site-directed mutagen-
esis kit (Stratagene). The following mutations were introduced 
and confirmed by sequencing: Y190A, Y190R, Y90F (TAT to 
GCT, AGA and TTT, respectively); F201A, F201R (TTT to GCT and 
AGA, respectively) and the double mutants Y190R/F201R and 
Y190F/F201R. </p>

<p>Media and genetic techniques 
The S. cerevisiae strain YKK39 was transformed with pRS315-SGT1 
bearing wild-type or mutant SGT1, as indicated in figure legends 
(Rose et al, 1990). Transformants were selected on drop-out media 
without uracil and leucine. The ability of SGT1 mutants to maintain 
cell viability was assessed by curing for pRS316-SGT1 by incubating 
the transformants on drop-out media without leucine, but contain-
ing uracil (25 mg/l) and 5-FOA (0.1%). </p>

<p>DNA constructs 
cDNAs for H. vulgare Hsp90 and A. thaliana Sgt1a were as 
described (Boter et al, 2007). Human Hsp90b was as described 
(Panaretou et al, 2002). Human Skp1, Skp2, Sgt1 and Cul1 were 
amplified from IMAGE ESTs (4 243 711, 2 962 938, 2 985 858 and 
40118 923, respectively). Different constructs of Skp1 (residues 
1-163, 1-70, 81-163 and D71-80) and Sgt1 were cloned into 
pGEX6P-1, Skp2 constructs (residues 1-411 and 89-141) were 
cloned into pET28a. Cul1 coding region was split into two halves 
(residues 1-410 and 411-776) as described earlier (Zheng et al,  2002) and cloned into pST38 (Tan, 2001) for co-expression. </p>

<p>Protein expression and purification 
Plant and mammalian Hsp90 and Sgt1 constructs were all expressed 
in the Escherichia coli strain Rosetta (DE3) pLysS. Hsp90 constructs, 
were purified as described earlier (Prodromou et al, 1997). GST-
tagged Sgt1 constructs were purified by ion exchange on 
Q-Sepharose and immobilized on glutathione Sepharose beads. 
Sgt1 was then released by PreScission cleavage and further purified 
on a Superdex 75 PG gel-filtration column. Human Skp1, Skp2 and 
Cul1 constructs were all purified as described earlier (Zheng et al,  2002). </p>

<p>In vitro protein co-precipitation assay 
In total, 50 mg of each indicated protein (except protein in gradient 
titrations) was incubated in 50 ml glutathione Sepharose resin or 
Talon 
TM metal affinity resin in 200 ml of binding buffer consisting of 
50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 0.1% NP-40 and 1 mg/ml BSA 
(pH 7.5). For gradient titration experiments, 5 mg of gradient protein </p>

<p>was used in the first reaction, with three-fold increase in subsequent 
reactions (i.e. 15, 45 mg and so on). Reactions were performed 
overnight at 41C. Resin was washed three times with 1 ml binding 
buffer later. One-fiftieth of the washed resin was resolved by 
SDS-PAGE, electroblotted and probed with antibody to the 
particular protein construct ('a-') as indicated. Quantities of protein 
consumed were shown by SDS-PAGE using 10% of each input 
proteins and visualized with Coomassie Brilliant Blue. </p>

<p>Crystallization, data collection and structure determination 
HvHsp90-N and AtSgt1a-CS were combined in a 1:1 molar ratio in 
the presence of 5 mM ADP, incubated for 30 min and concentrated 
to 10 mg/ml by ultrafiltration. Initial multiple crystals were grown 
by vapour diffusion at 41C against 26% w/v PEG4000, 100 mM Tris 
(pH 8.5) and 200 mM magnesium sulphate. Subsequent streak 
seeding into solutions of 16% w/v PEG4000, 100 mM Tris (pH 8.5) 
and 200 mM magnesium sulphate produced single thin plates. 
Crystals were harvested into reservoir solution with addition of 
glycerol (20% v/v) before flash cooling to 100 K. X-ray data were 
collected on beamline ID23 at the ESRF, Grenoble, from single 
crystals, and processed by using <rs type="software">MOSFLM</rs> (Leslie, 1995) and the 
<rs id="software-5" type="software">CCP4</rs> package (CCP4, <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version">1994</rs>). Crystals had space group P2 1 2 1 2 1 , with 
three copies of the complex in the asymmetric unit. The thin plate 
crystals have a high solvent content (59% v/v) and only gave useful 
diffraction to 3.3 Å . The structure was solved by molecular 
replacement with Phaser (McCoy, 2007) using ADP-bound yeast 
Hsp90-N (PDB code: 1AMW) and the solution structure of human 
Sgt1-CS domain (PDB code: 1RL1) as search models, built using 
COOT (Emsley and Cowtan, 2004), and refined with CNS in <rs type="software">PHENIX</rs> 
(Adams et al, 2002), using NCS restraints. Data collection and 
refinement parameters are given in Table I. Crystallographic data 
have been deposited in the Protein Databank with code: 2JKI </p>

<p>Supplementary data 
Supplementary data are available at The EMBO Journal Online 
(http://www.embojournal.org). </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We are grateful to Kenneth Kaplan for the kind gift of yeast strain 
YKK39 and the pRS315-SGT1 vector, to Mark Roe for help with data 
collection and processing and to Cara Vaughan for useful discus-
sion. This study was supported by The Wellcome Trust (LHP), 
The Gatsby Foundation and KAKENHI 19678001 (KS), Marie Curie 
Fellowship Program (MB) and the Japan Society for the Promotion 
of Science (YK). </p>



<p>Hsp90-and Sgt1-centred multi-protein complexes 
M Zhang et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 27 | NO 20 | 2008 2797 </p>



<p>The EMBO Journal is published by Nature 
Publishing Group on behalf of European 
Molecular Biology Organization. This article is licensed 
under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-
No Derivative Works 3.0 Licence. [http://creativecommons. 
org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0] </p>

<p>Hsp90-and Sgt1-centred multi-protein complexes 
M Zhang et al </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 27 | NO 20 | 2008 </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>



</text></tei>