<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3749346" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>In established obesity, inflammation and macrophage recruitment 
likely contribute to the development of insulin resistance. In the 
current study, we set out to explore whether adipose tissue in-
filtration by neutrophils that occurs early (3 days) after initiating 
a high-fat diet (HFD) could contribute to the early occurrence of 
hepatic insulin resistance and to determine the role of cytosolic 
phospholipase A 2 a (cPLA 2 a) in this process. The 3-day HFD caused 
a significant upregulation of cPLA 2 a in periepididymal fat and in the 
liver. A specific antisense oligonucleotide (AS) effectively prevented 
cPLA 2 a induction, neutrophil infiltration into adipose tissue (likely 
involving MIP-2), and protected against 3-day HFD-induced impair-
ment in hepatic insulin signaling and glucose over-production from 
pyruvate. To sort out the role of adipose neutrophil infiltration in-
dependent of cPLA 2 a induction in the liver, mice were injected in-
traperitoneally with anti-intracellular adhesion molecule-1 (ICAM-1) 
antibodies. This effectively prevented neutrophil infiltration without 
affecting cPLA 2 a or MIP-2, but like AS, prevented impairment in 
hepatic insulin signaling, the enhanced pyruvate-to-glucose flux, 
and the impaired insulin-mediated suppression of hepatic glucose 
production (assessed by clamp), which were induced by the 3-day 
HFD. Adipose tissue secretion of tumor necrosis factor-a (TNF-a) 
was increased by the 3-day HFD, but not if mice were treated with AS 
or ICAM-1 antibodies. Moreover, systemic TNF-a neutralization pre-
vented 3-day HFD-induced hepatic insulin resistance, suggesting its 
mediatory role. We propose that an acute, cPLA 2 a-dependent, 
neutrophil-dominated inflammatory response of adipose tissue contrib-
utes to hepatic insulin resistance and glucose overproduction in the 
early adaptation to high-fat feeding. to a 3-day HFD, with emphasis on whether these early in-
flammatory responses could underlie the development of 
hepatic insulin resistance. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>Animals and diets. The study was approved by Ben-Gurion University In-
stitutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IL-35-2006) and conducted 
according to the Israeli Animal Welfare Act, following the guidelines of the 
Guide for Care and Use of Laboratory Animals (National Research Council,  1996). Male C57BL/6J mice (The Jackson Laboratory, Bar Harbor, ME) at 6 
weeks of age were fed a low-fat diet (LFD; 6% calories from fat; Harlan Teklad 
2018sc) or an HFD (60% calories from fat; Research Diets #12492), as pre-
viously performed (17). 
Mice were killed by CO 2 at the indicated times, and periepididymal fat was 
dissected out and immediately fixed in 4% formaldehyde or snap-frozen and 
stored in liquid nitrogen until further analyzed. A combination of two oligonu-
cleotides antisenses (AS) (TCAAAGGTCTCATTCCACA, GCTGTCAGGGGTTG-
TAG) and their corresponding senses, with phosphorothioate modifications 
on the last three bases at both 59 and 39 ends, was used as described pre-
viously (18). 
For insulin stimulation, insulin was administered intravenously 5 min before 
the mice were killed, and livers or epididymal fat pads were immediately ob-
tained and flash-frozen until analysis. Insulin doses of 0.5 and 2 units/kg gave 
identical signaling responses. LEAF-purified anti-mouse Ly-6G antibodies, LEAF-
purified anti-mouse tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-a antibodies (MP6-XT22), and 
LEAF-purified anti-mouse CD54 antibodies and their isotype control IgG anti-
bodies (BioLegend, San Diego, CA) were used for neutrophil depletion, TNF-a 
neutralization, and ICAM-1 neutralization, respectively. 
Immunoblot analysis. Epididymal fat pads were lysed in ice-cold lysis buffer 
exactly as done earlier (9). Samples underwent 7.5% SDS-PAGE (for each 100-
mg sample). The resolved proteins were electrophoretically transferred onto 
a nitrocellulose membrane, blocked in 5% milk in TBS-T (TBS containing 0.1% 
Tween-20), and incubated overnight at 4°C with goat anti-mouse MPO (1:100; 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology Inc., Santa Cruz, CA), anti-mouse b-actin (1:10,000), 
anti-phosphorylated (p)-Ser473 Akt (1:1000), anti-Akt (1:1000), anti-p-Ser9 
glycogen synthase kinase (GSK; 1:1000), anti-GSK (1:1000), anti-cPLA 2 a 
(1:200; Cell Signaling, Beverly, MA), anti 5-lipoxygenase (5-LOX; 1:1000; Cay-
man Chemical, Ann Arbor, MI), or anti-cyclogenase-2 (COX-2; 1:1000; Abcam, 
Cambridge, U.K.). After being washed with TBS-T (four washes for 15 min 
each), the membranes were incubated with 1:10,000 dilutions of the respective 
horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated secondary antibodies for 1.5 h at 
room temperature. Proteins were quantified using video densitometry analysis 
(<rs id="software-0" type="software">ImageGauge</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4.0</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Fuji</rs>), as described previously (19,20). 
Preparation of neutrophils. Heart blood was withdrawn before mice were 
killed. Neutrophils, at 95% purity, were obtained by Ficoll-Hypaque centrifu-
gation, dextran sedimentation, and hypotonic lysis of erythrocytes. Cells were 
counted, and their viability was determined by trypan blue exclusion. 
Immunohistochemistry for neutrophil detection. Epididymal fat tissues 
were embedded in paraffin and sectioned using a Leica microtome (Leica 
Biosystem, Vienna, Austria). Neutrophil staining by rat anti-mouse monoclonal 
anti-NIMP-R14 antibody to identify neutrophils (Novus Biological Inc.) was 
analyzed as done before (9,13), based on an earlier study (21). Nonspecific 
reactivity was blocked by incubating the slides with 20% normal rabbit serum 
for 20 min with avidin-biotin VECTA-STAIN Kit Elite PK 6105 (Vector Labo-
ratories, Burlingame, CA). Sections were then incubated in 1:10 dilution of 
anti-NIMP-R14 antibodies in PBS for 1 h at room temperature, washed, and 
further incubated with 1:200 dilution of biotinylated anti-rat IgG, followed by 
avidin-biotin complex/HRP-DAB, which resulted in brown staining of neu-
trophils. For each treatment, a negative control was prepared without the 
primary antibody. The sections were counterstained with hematoxylin and 
analyzed in a blinded fashion using an Olympus BX-60 microscope. </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Short-term HFD induces liver, but not adipose tissue insulin 
resistance. A: Liver insulin resistance was determined by impaired 
insulin-stimulated p-Akt on serine 473 after intravenous injection of 
insulin. Representative immunoblot of p-Akt in liver lysates from mice at 
day 0 up to day 28 on HFD compared with liver lysates of a mouse that 
was not treated with insulin (-). After densitometry analysis, the ratio of 
the intensity of the p-Akt band to total Akt (t-Akt) was calculated and 
presented, as arbitrary units, by the mean 6 SEM of 10 mice studied in 
three independent experiments. 1, treated with insulin. B: Normal in-
sulin signaling in epididymal fat of 3-day HFD mice. A representative </p>

<p>immunoblot of p-Akt in epididymal fat tissue lysates from mice at day 0, 
and HFD and control mice on LFD at day 3. Densitometry analysis was 
performed as in A. Results are mean 6 SEM of 15 mice studied in five 
independent experiments. C: Epididymal fat mass of 10 mice fed the 
HFD and 10 mice fed the LFD at day 3 of the diet show a significant 
difference. *P &lt; 0.001 between the groups. Results are mean 6 SEM of 
two different experiments. D: Histological sections of epididymal adi-
pose tissues and immunolocalization of neutrophils (shown by arrows) 
using anti-NIMP-R14 antibodies and hematoxylin counterstaining 
(original magnification 3400). E: Histological sections of liver stained 
by hematoxylin and eosin (original magnification 3200). Shown are 
representative images of 10 mice in each group. </p>

<p>ADIPOSE cPLA 2 a IN HEPATIC INSULIN RESISTANCE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 62, SEPTEMBER 2013 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>Superoxide generation. The production of the superoxide anion by intact 
neutrophils was measured as the superoxide dismutase inhibitable reduction of 
acetyl ferricytochrome c by the microtiter plate technique, as previously de-
scribed (22). 
Cytokines and eicosanoids release measurements. Epididymal fat tissue 
from mice was removed, weighed, sliced, and incubated for 3 h in 1 mL medium 
containing 0.1% BSA. The collected media were measured using commercial 
ELISA kits for TNF-a (Biolegend, San Diego, CA), 15 mg tissue for each 
sample, MIP-2, KC, leukotriene B4 (LTB 4 ), IL-6 (all from R&amp;D Systems, Inc., 
Minneapolis, MN), 150 mg tissue for each sample. Prostaglandin E 2 (PGE 2 ) 
levels were determined according to a dextran-coated charcoal radioimmu-
noassay protocol, using PGE 2 standard, anti-PGE 2 anti-serum (Sigma Israel, 
Rehovot, Israel), and [ 
3 H]PGE 2 (Amersham Biosciences Corp., Piscataway, 
NJ), exactly as previously described (23). 
Pyruvate tolerance test. Pyruvate tolerance test was performed by intra-
peritoneal injection of pyruvate (2 g/kg body weight) in saline after an 
overnight fast. Blood glucose concentrations were measured in tail blood 
before and after injection at the times indicated (24). All glucose measure-
ments were made using a glucometer (Abbott, Alameda, CA). 
Homeostasis model assessment of insulin resistance. Homeostasis model 
assessment of insulin resistance (HOMA-IR) was calculated by multiplying 
fasting plasma insulin concentration (mU/L) with fasting plasma glucose 
(mmol/L) divided by 22.5 (25-27). Plasma insulin levels were determined by 
ELISA (ALPCO Diagnostics, Salem, NH). 
Glucose clamp studies. Glucose clamp studies in freely moving mice were 
performed as described (28). Steady-state glucose infusion rate was calculated 
once glucose infusion reached a near-constant rate to maintain glucose at 5 
mmol/L for 20 min. The glucose disposal rate was calculated by dividing the 
rate of [3-  3   H]glucose infusion by the plasma [3-  3   H]glucose-specific activity 
(29,30). Endogenous glucose production during the clamp was calculated by 
subtracting the glucose infusion rate from the glucose disposal rate (29,30). 
Insulin-stimulated glucose disposal rate was calculated by subtracting basal 
endogenous glucose production (equal to basal glucose disposal rate) from 
the glucose disposal rate during the clamp (31). 
Statistical analysis. Data are presented as the mean 6 SEM. Statistical 
significance for comparison between two groups was determined using the 
Student paired two-tailed t test, and by ANOVA for more than two treatment 
groups, followed by Bonferroni correction or by Newman-Keuls post hoc test, 
using GraphPad Prism 5.03 software. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The time-course of development of insulin resistance in 
response to the HFD was determined in liver and in peri-
epididymal fat pads by assessing insulin-stimulated phos-
phorylation of Akt. At different times after initiating the 
HFD, mice received an intravenous insulin injection 5 min 
before livers were harvested. Three days after initiating the 
HFD, hepatic insulin-stimulated Ser473-Akt phosphoryla-
tion was markedly attenuated (Fig. 1A). At this time point 
of marked diminution of insulin signaling in the liver, adi-
pose tissue exhibited normal insulin-stimulated Ser473-Akt 
phosphorylation (Fig. 1B). Insulin resistance in this tissue 
required a longer duration of HFD to manifest (data not 
shown). Nevertheless, the 3-day HFD was already sufficient 
to induce a statistically significant increase in adipose tissue 
weight (Fig. 1C) and a notable increase in adipocyte cell 
size (Fig. 1D). As reported in a previous study (9), multiple 
neutrophils were visible between adipocytes, indicating in-
filtration of the tissue parenchyma. (Fig. 1D). Concomi-
tantly, histologic analysis showed hepatic lipid content was 
notably mildly increased in mice fed the 3-day HFD (Fig. 
1E), as were fasting glucose levels (Table 1). Calculated 
HOMA-IR values revealed systemic insulin resistance in-
duced by the 3-day HFD (Table 1). 
We hypothesized that adipose tissue neutrophil infiltration 
induced by the 3-day HFD (9) could participate in the early 
induction of hepatic insulin resistance. To test this hypoth-
esis, adipose neutrophil recruitment was first prevented us-
ing oligo-AS against cPLA 2 a. This approach was based on 
previous findings demonstrating 1) the effectiveness of AS 
administration in inhibiting neutrophil recruitment to the </p>

<p>site of inflammation (13) and 2) that the 3-day HFD indu-
ces cPLA 2 a upregulation in adipose tissue (12). Mice re-
ceived an intravenous tail vein injection of 1 mg/kg AS, 
1 mg/kg corresponding (control) sense oligonucleotide, or 
saline 1 day before and then daily during the 3-day HFD. 
Weight gain was not affected by the AS or sense treat-
ments (Fig. 2A), but AS treatment significantly prevented 
the elevated cPLA 2 a protein expression detected in 
lysates of adipose tissue of the 3-day HFD mice (Fig. 2B). 
The AS treatment also significantly prevented the recruit-
ment of neutrophils to the adipose tissue of the HFD mice, 
as detected by adipose protein levels of MPO (Fig. 2C) and 
by quantitation of neutrophils by NIMP-R14 immunos-
taining (Fig. 2D). 
To analyze whether AS protected against hepatic insulin 
resistance, insulin induction of liver p-Ser473-Akt or p-
Ser9-GSK-3b was assessed (32,33). AS, but not sense 
treatment, prevented HFD-induced impairment of insulin-
stimulated Akt and GSK-3b phosphorylation (Fig. 2E and 
F ), without affecting liver histology (data not shown). AS 
treatment did not affect the normal insulin signaling in the 
adipose tissue (data not shown). At the whole-body met-
abolic level, the 3-day HFD was associated with an exag-
gerated glucose production during a pyruvate tolerance 
test compared with LFD mice, and this enhanced pyruvate-
to-glucose flux was prevented by AS compared with the 
sense-treated mice (Fig. 2G). 
Liver cPLA 2 a was also upregulated by the 3-day HFD, and 
as in adipose tissue, this increased expression was pre-
vented by AS treatment (Fig. 3A). However, neutrophil in-
filtration to adipose tissue seemed to constitute a unique 
response of this tissue to the 3-day HFD, because no similar 
elevation occurred in the levels of the neutrophil-selective 
protein MPO in the liver (Fig. 3B). Thus, AS directed against 
cPLA 2 a decreased the elevated expression of this phos-
pholipase in adipose tissue and in the liver and concomi-
tantly prevented the tissue-selective neutrophil infiltration 
into adipose tissue that was induced by the 3-day HFD. 
These effects were associated with prevention of impaired 
hepatic insulin signaling and enhanced pyruvate-to-glucose 
flux that developed during early adaptation to the HFD. 
To further support the role of neutrophil recruitment to 
adipose tissue in inducing liver insulin resistance and to 
differentiate its effect from the possible consequences of 
increased expression of cPLA 2 a in the liver, anti-ICAM-1 
antibodies were used to prevent neutrophil recruitment. 
Mice were injected intraperitoneally with 100 mg anti-mouse 
ICAM-1 antibodies or isotype control IgG antibodies every 
other day, beginning 2 days before the HFD was initiated. 
Treatment with anti-ICAM-1 antibodies, but not with con-
trol IgG antibodies, reduced MPO expression in adipose </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Metabolic changes induced by the 3-day HFD </p>

<p>LFD 
HFD </p>

<p>3-day body weight gain (g) 
0.28 6 0.09 2.28 6 0.11* 
Epididymal adipose tissue weight (g) 0.17 6 0.01 0.26 6 0.01* 
Nonfasting serum insulin (mg/L) 
1.19 6 0.2 1.34 6 0.3 
Fasting blood glucose (mg/dL) 
110 6 9.1 136 6 11.1** 
Fasting serum insulin (mg/L) 
0.31 6 0.03 0.36 6 0.04 
HOMA-IR 
2.1 6 0.19 3.0 6 0.25** </p>

<p>The results are mean 6 SEM of 10 mice in each group. Mice were fed 
LFD or HFD for 3 days. *P , 0.001 and **P , 0.05 in HFD compared 
with LFD. </p>

<p>N. HADAD AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 62, SEPTEMBER 2013 </p>

<p>
FIG. 2. Inhibition of neutrophil recruitment to epididymal adipose tissue by cPLA 2 a-specific AS oligonucleotide prevents hepatic insulin re-
sistance. Mice were intravenously injected 1 day before the initiation of the HFD and every day during the diet with 2 mg/kg AS against cPLA 2 a. 
The HFD control mice were administrated with 100 mL saline or 2 mg/kg sense (SE) oligonucleotide, and because there was no difference between 
the two groups, they were combined (SE). Control LFD mice were fed a normal diet for 3 days. Half of the control LFD mice were administrated 100 
mL saline, which did not cause any effect compared with the noninjected mice. The weight and the densitometry of the immunoblot of the individual 
mice in each group performed in three independent experiments are presented. A: *P &lt; 0.001 between the two groups of mice on the HFD and the 
LFD mice at day 3 of the diet. B: A representative immunoblot of cPLA 2 a and the corresponding b-actin protein expression in epididymal adipose 
tissue lysates of the different groups of mice. The intensity of each cPLA 2 a band was divided by the intensity of the respective b-actin band after 
quantitation by densitometry and expressed as arbitrary units. *P &lt; 0.001 for control HFD mice (SE) compared with HFD mice with AS treatment 
or LFD mice. C: A representative immunoblot and densitometry analyses of MPO (a specific neutrophil marker) and b-actin in epididymal fat from </p>

<p>ADIPOSE cPLA 2 a IN HEPATIC INSULIN RESISTANCE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 62, SEPTEMBER 2013 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>tissue (Fig. 4A) and the number of neutrophils, as analyzed 
histologically by NIMP-R14, from 11.56 6 1.2 to 3.49 6 0.9 
neutrophils per high-power field (P , 0.001), indicating the 
prevention of adipose neutrophil recruitment, without af-
fecting body weight (Fig. 4B). Importantly, this approach to 
prevent HFD-induced adipose neutrophil infiltration did not 
attenuate the diet-induced elevation in cPLA 2 a protein ex-
pression in the liver (Fig. 4C). Inhibition of neutrophil in-
filtration to adipose tissue significantly improved hepatic 
insulin signaling, as detected by insulin-stimulated p-Akt 
and p-GSK (Fig. 4D and E), without affecting liver histology 
(data not shown) or adipose insulin signaling (not shown) 
and, consistently, alleviated the augmented gluconeogenic 
flux from pyruvate induced by the 3-day HFD (Fig. 4F). 
To further confirm that prevention of adipose infiltration 
by neutrophils improved hepatic insulin sensitivity, 
hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp studies were conducted. </p>

<p>The glucose infusion rate was significantly decreased in 
HFD-fed mice (Fig. 4G and Supplementary Fig. 1). However, 
no difference was observed between IgG-and ICAM-treated 
mice (Fig. 4G and Supplementary Fig. 1). Insulin-mediated 
inhibition of endogenous (mainly reflecting hepatic) glucose 
production was significantly reduced in IgG-treated HFD-fed 
mice (Fig. 4H). In contrast, ICAM-treated HFD-fed mice 
showed a conserved response to insulin, suggesting im-
proved hepatic insulin sensitivity in ICAM-treated com-
pared with IgG-treated HFD-fed mice (Fig. 4H). Of note, 
the 3-day HFD did not significantly affect the insulin-
stimulated glucose disposal rate (mainly reflecting skel-
etal muscle insulin sensitivity), although a slight decrease 
was apparent in the group treated with anti-ICAM-1 
(Fig. 4I). High variability in the insulin-stimulated glucose 
disposal rate may have prevented a significant difference 
in the glucose infusion rate between the two HFD-fed 
groups (Fig. 4G). These hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp 
results are consistent with a state of selective hepatic in-
sulin resistance induced by the 3-day HFD, which can be 
alleviated by anti-ICAM-1 antibodies that prevent adipose 
tissue neutrophil infiltration. 
To gain further support for the role of adipose neutrophil 
infiltration in the induction of hepatic insulin resistance, 
neutrophil infiltration was prevented by an alternative ap-
proach (i.e., by neutrophil depletion using Ly6G-specific 
monoclonal antibody), as described (34,35). Mice were 
injected intraperitoneally with 150 mg anti-mouse Ly-6G 
antibodies or isotype control IgG antibodies 1 day before 
the 3-day HFD was initiated. Neutrophil depletion was 
validated by fluorescence-activated cell sorter analysis 
using rat anti-mouse neutrophils antibodies (MCA771F, 
Serotec), as performed in a previous study (13). Neutro-
phil depletion significantly improved hepatic insulin re-
sponsiveness, as detected by insulin-stimulated p-Akt 
(Fig. 4J) and p-GSK (Fig. 4K). Collectively, inhibiting adi-
pose neutrophil infiltration, independent of attenuating 
cPLA 2 a induction early after initiating the HFD, prevented 
the early diet-induced hepatic insulin resistance and glucose 
overproduction. 
We next assessed possible mechanisms related to 1) 
neutrophil adaptation to HFD and recruitment to adipose 
tissue and 2) the induction of hepatic insulin resistance in 
this specific model of short-term hypernutrition. Neutro-
phil tissue infiltration is a process associated with cellular 
activation and with specific chemoattractants that direct 
these cells to the site of inflammation. Indeed, peripheral 
blood neutrophils from mice fed the 3-day HFD released 
significantly higher levels of superoxides (Fig. 5A), sug-
gesting that neutrophil activation is induced by the diet. 
Consistent with our previous report (13), the AS treatment 
attenuated the release of superoxides. 
Several putative adipose tissue-derived neutrophil che-
moattractants are known as potent activators. These factors 
include the cPLA 2 -dependent metabolite LTB 4 , previously 
shown by us to recruit neutrophils to the peritoneal cavity </p>

<p>LFD mice, AS-treated HFD mice, and control mice (SE). The intensity of each MPO band was divided by the intensity of the respective b-actin band 
after quantitation by densitometry and expressed as arbitrary units. *P &lt; 0.001 in control HFD mice (SE) compared with AS-treated HFD mice or 
LFD mice. D: The presence of stained neutrophils using mouse anti-neutrophils antibody (NIMP-R14) in sections of epididymal adipose tissues. 
Results are the mean 6 SEM number per field, derived from 20 individual fields for each mouse from two independent experiments. *P &lt; 0.001 in 
control HFD mice (SE) compared with AS-treated HFD mice or LFD mice. E and F: For each group of mice, liver lysate of a mouse that was not 
treated with insulin (-) and lysates from two different mice treated with insulin (+) are presented. Densitometry analysis for p-Akt and p-GSK 
were performed as in Fig. 1A. *P &lt; 0.001, significant decrease of control HFD mice (SE) compared with HFD mice with AS treatment or LFD mice. 
G: Pyruvate tolerance test (PTT) in 3-day HFD mice after overnight fast. The results are the mean 6 SEM of six mice in each group performed in 
two independent experiments. The inset describes the area under the curve (AUC). *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01 compared with SE-treated HFD mice 
(SE) by two-way ANOVA and Bonferroni post-test analysis. t, total. </p>

<p>FIG. 3. The effect of cPLA 2 a AS treatment in livers of HFD mice. A: 
A representative immunoblot analysis of cPLA 2 a and the corresponding 
b-actin protein expression in liver lysates of the different groups of 
mice. Densitometry analysis for cPLA 2 a was performed as in Fig. 2B. 
*P &lt; 0.001 significant increase of control HFD mice (SE) compared 
with HFD mice with AS treatment or LFD mice. B: A representative 
immunoblot of MPO in liver of LFD mice, control HFD mice (SE), and 
AS-treated HFD mice. Densitometry analysis for MPO was performed as 
in Fig. 2C. There are no differences among the various groups of mice. 
d, day. </p>

<p>N. HADAD AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 62, SEPTEMBER 2013 </p>

<p>
FIG. 4. Prevention of neutrophil recruitment to epididymal adipose tissue by anti-ICAM-1 antibodies prevented hepatic insulin resistance in 
response to 3-day HFD. Mice were intraperitoneally injected (100 mg/kg) with anti-ICAM-1 antibodies 2 days before the initiation of the HFD and 
every other day thereafter. The HFD control mice were administrated 100 mL saline or rat IgG2b, isotype control. The weight and the densitometry 
of the immunoblot of the individual mice in each group performed in three different experiments are presented. A: A representative immunoblot of 
MPO in epididymal fat. Densitometry analysis for MPO was performed as described in Fig. 2C. *P &lt; 0.001, significant increase of control HFD mice 
(open circles) and anti-IgG-treated HFD mice (down gray triangles) compared with HFD mice treated with anti-ICAM-1 antibodies (up gray 
triangles) and LFD mice (filled circles). B: Effect of treatment on body weight. *P &lt; 0.001 between the groups of mice fed the HFD and the group 
fed the LFD at day 3 of the diet. C: A representative immunoblot analysis of cPLA 2 a and the corresponding b-actin protein expression in adipose 
tissue lysates of the different groups of mice. Densitometry analysis for cPLA 2 a was performed as in Fig. 2B. There is a significant difference (*P &lt; 
0.001) among the groups of mice fed the HFD compared with the LFD at day 3 of the diet. D and E: Representative immunoblots and densitometry </p>

<p>ADIPOSE cPLA 2 a IN HEPATIC INSULIN RESISTANCE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 62, SEPTEMBER 2013 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>of a mouse model of sterile peritonitis (13), and the neutrophil-
selective chemoattractant IL-8. The IL-8 ortholog in mice is 
keratinocyte chemoattractant (KC or CXCL1), and MIP-2 
(CXCL2), both ligands for the chemokine receptor CXCR2 
(36). Epididymal fat tissue from 3-day HFD-fed mice and 
control (3-day LFD) mice expressed similar levels of 5-LOX 
protein and released similar levels of LTB 4 , with no effect 
on these parameters by AS treatment (Fig. 5B and C). 
Similarly, secretion of the neutrophil chemoattractant KC 
was not affect by 3-day HFD or by the AS treatment 
(Fig. 5D). Yet, a significantly increased secretion of MIP-2 
from adipose tissue of the 3-day HFD mice was detected 
(Fig. 5E and F). AS-treated 3-day HFD mice secreted sig-
nificantly lower levels of MIP-2, similar to those of the 
control mice (Fig. 5E), suggesting that cPLA 2 a is involved in 
regulation of MIP-2 production. In contrast, treatment of 
the 3-day HFD mice with anti-ICAM-1 antibodies did not 
attenuate MIP-2 secretion (Fig. 5F), suggesting that cPLA 2 a 
upregulation, but not the consequential neutrophil in-
filtration, is involved in adipose tissue MIP-2 production. 
Jointly, these findings suggest a putative role for adipose 
MIP-2 as a chemoattractant involved in neutrophil re-
cruitment to the epididymal fat tissue early after initiating 
the HFD. 
To shed light on the mechanisms by which neutrophil 
infiltration to adipose tissue might induce hepatic insulin 
resistance, we determined if secretion/expression of PGE 2 , 
COX2, and the proinflammatory cytokines IL-6 and TNF-a 
are increased already 3 days after initiating the HFD. 
cPLA 2 a and COX2 are both robustly increased in various 
tissues during active inflammatory processes, and PGE 2 , 
the metabolite of arachidonic acid, has been recently im-
plicated in insulin resistance (37). Yet, no increase in 
COX2 expression or PGE2 secretion from adipose tissue 
was observed in 3-day HFD mice (Fig. 6A) compared with 
control mice (Fig. 6B). There was also no increase in the 
secretion of IL-6 (Fig. 6C), but TNF-a (Fig. 6D and E) was 
significantly elevated in adipose tissue of the HFD-fed 
mice, an effect of the diet, prevented by AS or anti-ICAM-1 
antibodies. To further establish the mediatory role of TNF-a 
in hepatic insulin resistance after the 3-day HFD, TNF-a was 
neutralized, using anti-mouse IgG1 monoclonal antibody, 
as in a previous study (38). Mice were injected intra-
peritoneally with 150 mg anti-mouse TNF-a antibodies or 
isotype control IgG1 antibodies 1 day before initiation of 
the HFD and at day 2 of the HFD. The elevated serum TNF-a 
levels in HFD mice (8.7 6 0.9 compared with 5.5 6 0.7 
pg/mL in LFD mice) was significantly (P , 0.001) reduced 
by anti-TNF-a antibodies treatment (4.5 6 0.6 pg/mL) but 
not by control IgG1 antibodies (8.1 6 0.7 pg/mL). Serum 
TNF-a neutralization significantly improved hepatic in-
sulin responsiveness, as detected by insulin-stimulated 
p-Akt and p-GSK (Fig. 6F and G). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The current study shows that hepatic insulin resistance 
induced by a short-term HFD reflects a dysregulated 
adipose-to-liver axis that is initiated by a cPLA 2 a-mediated, 
neutrophil-predominated, adipose tissue inflammation. Our 
studies reveal that: </p>

<p>1) Hepatic insulin resistance develops as early as 3 days 
after initiating an HFD, consistent with recently pub-
lished studies (7,8). 
2) Recruitment of neutrophils to adipose tissue is critical 
for the induction of hepatic insulin resistance in response 
to the 3-day HFD. Increased adipose tissue TNF-a secre-
tion may constitute a mediator in this response, because 
increased TNFa secretion and hepatic insulin resistance 
were both prevented when neutrophil infiltration was 
attenuated, and neutralizing TNF-a significantly pre-
vented hepatic insulin resistance. 
3) The recruitment of neutrophils to adipose tissue likely 
involves cPLA 2 a-dependent MIP-2 secretion. </p>

<p>Consistent with our previous (9) and present studies, 
recruitment of neutrophils to adipose tissue after 3 days of 
the HFD was recently confirmed by others (10), and the 
role of adipose tissue neutrophils in insulin resistance was 
also demonstrated. Adipose tissue recruitment of neu-
trophils is also consistent with a study demonstrating in-
creased leukocyte-endothelial cells-platelet interaction in 
the microcirculation of visceral adipose tissue in obesity 
(39). Moreover, in humans, pregnant obese women with 
preeclampsia exhibited extensive vascular inflammation 
characterized predominantly by neutrophils, demonstrable 
in adipose tissue blood vessels (40). The current study, 
however, offers several novel observations and mecha-
nistic insights: the 3-day HFD constitutes a unique state 
predominantly affecting hepatic insulin responsiveness, 
independent of skeletal muscle, and/or adipose tissue 
insulin resistance that apparently takes longer to develop. 
Under such conditions of "isolated hepatic insulin resis-
tance," we were able to demonstrate that neutrophil re-
cruitment, specifically to adipose tissue (and not to the 
liver), is necessary for hepatic insulin resistance to develop. 
Moreover, induction of adipose cPLA 2 a upregulation is 
deemed necessary for adipose tissue neutrophil infiltration 
and is upstream of an inflammatory pathway involving the 
upregulation of the neutrophil chemoattractant MIP-2, the 
upregulation of the endothelial adhesion molecule ICAM-1 
(12), and the adipose tissue neutrophil-dependent increased 
production of TNF-a. Importantly, although cPLA 2 a is 
upregulated also in the liver, as was neutrophil elastase in 
a recent study,(10) our results assign a role specifically 
for adipose, and not hepatic, cPLA 2 a upregulation in the 
induction of hepatic insulin resistance and glucose </p>

<p>analyses of p-Akt (serine 473) and p-GSK (serine 9). For each group of mice, liver lysate of a mouse that was not treated with insulin (-) and 
lysates from two different mice treated with insulin (+) are presented. Densitometry analyses for p-Akt and p-GSK were performed as in Fig. 1A. 
*P &lt; 0.001, significant decrease of control HFD mice and anti-IgG-treated HFD mice compared with HFD mice treated with anti-ICAM-1 anti-
bodies and LFD mice. F: Pyruvate tolerance test (PTT) after an overnight fast. The inset describes the area under the curve (AUC). The results are 
the mean 6 SEM of six mice in each group performed in two independent experiments. **P &lt; 0.01, *P &lt; 0.05 compared with ICAM-1 antibody-
treated HFD mice by two-way ANOVA and Bonferroni post-test analysis. Hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp studies with glucose infusion rate 
(GIR) (G), insulin-inhibited endogenous glucose production (EGP) (H), and insulin-stimulated glucose disposal rate (IS-GDR) (I) were conducted 
in chow-fed (open), IgG-treated HFD-fed (gray), and ICAM-treated HFD-fed (black) mice. (Further clamp results are in Supplementary Fig. 1.) 
Results are the means of four (chow-fed) or four (HFD-fed) animals. All error bars represent SEM. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01 ANOVA, followed by 
Newman-Keuls post hoc test. J and K: Neutrophil depletion prevented insulin resistance in the 3-day HFD liver. Representative immunoblots and 
densitometry analyses are shown for p-Akt (serine 473) and p-GSK (serine 9). For each group of mice, liver lysate of a mouse that was not treated 
with insulin (-) and lysates from two different mice treated with insulin (+) are presented. Densitometry analyses for p-Akt and p-GSK were 
performed as in Fig. 1A. *P &lt; 0.001, significant decrease of control HFD mice compared with neutrophil-depleted HFD mice and LFD mice. t, total. </p>

<p>N. HADAD AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 62, SEPTEMBER 2013 </p>

<p>
overproduction: By antagonizing ICAM-1, 3-day HFD-
induced increase in cPLA 2 a was still present, but adipose 
tissue neutrophil infiltration was prevented, and hepatic 
insulin resistance was still averted. We thus provide com-
pelling evidence that adipose cPLA 2 a-mediated neutrophil 
infiltration, specifically to adipose tissue, contributes to 
hepatic insulin resistance in response to acute short-term 
high-fat feeding. It may be speculated that this early in-
flammatory response to a HFD, consistent with studies in 
human circulating leukocytes (14-16), represents, at least in 
the short-term, a physiological adaptation: isolated hepatic 
insulin resistance with preserved adipose tissue insulin 
sensitivity would assist in directing more storage of excess 
calories in adipose tissue and less in ectopic sites. 
Recruitment of different immune cell types to adipose 
tissue and consequential changes in secretion of cytokines 
have been documented in recent years, mainly at much 
later time points of diet-induced obesity. These include 
CD11c 
+ , M1-like macrophages (2,4,41,42), and B and CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cells (43-45). However, the recruitment of lymphocytes 
to adipose tissue was not directly linked with induction of 
insulin resistance (5). Although Kupffer cells were proposed 
to mediate the induction of hepatic insulin resistance by 
3-day HFD (7), another study reported opposite results (8), 
suggesting that whereas macrophage-mediated tissue in-
flammation is a key component of chronic obesity-associated 
insulin resistance, it is not critical for the decrease in in-
sulin sensitivity at the early adaptation to HFD feeding. We 
therefore propose that most likely, in the acute response to 
HFD, neutrophils may well constitute the major driver of 
adipose tissue inflammation and hepatic insulin resistance. 
cPLA 2 a was recently suggested to be involved in the 
storage of lipids in the adipose tissue and liver during pro-
longed obesity (46) and in 3T3-L1 cells (47). In the current 
study, prevention of cPLA 2 a upregulation by AS treatment 
in the 3-day HFD mice did not interfere with weight gain. 
Thus, cPLA 2 a regulates the adaptation to the 3-day HFD 
independent of weight gain or adipocyte hypertrophy. The 
results of the current study suggest that MIP-2, a mouse 
ortholog of human IL-8, signals neutrophils recruitment 
downstream of cPLA 2 a (Fig. 6). This observation may also 
be highly relevant for humans in whom adipose tissue IL-8 
levels were elevated (48-50). MIP-2 has been shown to be 
one of the major inducible chemokines with the ability to 
attract neutrophils to the site of inflammation (51). KC and 
MIP-2 have temporally distinct patterns of expression and 
cell type-specificity (52). MIP-2 was shown to be produced 
by resident macrophages and by neutrophils (36,51). There-
fore, in response to the 3-day HFD, MIP-2 is likely produced 
by resident macrophages and not by neutrophils, because 
MIP-2 production was reduced only with the AS treatment 
and not with anti-ICAM-1 antibodies treatment, whereas in 
both treatments, the recruitment of neutrophils to the adi-
pose fat was prevented. Because MIP-2 synthesis is Toll-like 
receptor (TLR)-dependent (36) and saturated free fatty 
acids act as a naturally occurring ligands of macrophage 
TLR4 (53), it is possible that elevation of free fatty acid in 
the intra-abdominal adipose tissue by the 3-day HFD triggers </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Peripheral blood neutrophil and adipose tissue release of MIP-2 
after the 3-day HFD. A: Spontaneous superoxide production by isolated 
peripheral blood neutrophils from individual HFD mice and LFD mice at 
day 3 of the diet performed in three different experiments is presented. 
*P &lt; 0.001, significant increase of control HFD mice (SE) compared 
with HFD mice with AS treatment or LFD mice. There are no differ-
ences between HFD mice with AS treatment and LFD mice. B: A rep-
resentative immunoblot of 5-LOX in epididymal fat lysates of LFD mice, 
control HFD mice (SE), and AS-treated HFD mice. Densitometry 
analyses were performed as for cPLA 2 a in Fig. 2A. Results are mean 6 </p>

<p>SEM of 12 mice. Release of LTB 4 (C) and KC (D) from adipose tissue 
explants of the different groups. There are no significant differences 
among the groups. E: MIP-2 release from adipose tissue explants was 
significantly increased (*P &lt; 0.001) in control HFD mice (SE) com-
pared with HFD mice with AS treatment or LFD mice. F: MIP-2 release 
from adipose tissue explants was significantly higher (*P &lt; 0.001) in 
the groups of mice fed the HFD compared with mice fed the LFD at day 
3 of the diet. </p>

<p>ADIPOSE cPLA 2 a IN HEPATIC INSULIN RESISTANCE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 62, SEPTEMBER 2013 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>the production of cPLA 2 a-dependent MIP-2 in resident mac-
rophages, leading to neutrophil recruitment. Thus, cPLA 2 a 
facilitates neutrophil recruitment by two important steps of 
the process: the secretion of the chemoattractant MIP-2 and 
the production of the adhesion molecule ICAM-1 (12). 
We show here that circulating neutrophils are activated 
in mice fed the 3-day HFD, as shown by the release of 
superoxides (Fig. 5A). This is consistent with the imme-
diate activation of circulating neutrophils, the release of 
superoxides, increased expression of NADPH oxidase, and 
the increased proinflammatory cytokines demonstrated in 
healthy human subjects exposed to a high-fat meal or </p>

<p>a high-fat-carbohydrate meal or during a glucose challenge 
(14-16,54-57). The activated adipose neutrophil-produced 
factors that mediate hepatic insulin resistance have yet to 
be identified. Although neutrophil elastase is a likely can-
didate (10), it should be remembered that this was dem-
onstrated at 12 weeks of the HFD, when its expression was 
also elevated in the liver. LTB 4 or PGE 2 were shown to 
impair insulin signaling (37,58), and adipose tissue LTB 4  secretion was recently reported to contribute to elevation 
of adipose macrophages and T cells at 15 weeks of an HFD 
(59). Yet, they are unlikely to be involved in the response 
to the 3-day HFD. Elevated local and circulating levels of </p>

<p>FIG. 6. TNF-a is the possible adipose mediator for the induction of hepatic insulin resistance in response to short-term HFD. A: A representative 
immunoblot of COX-2 in adipose lysates of LFD mice, control HFD sense (SE)-treated mice, and AS-treated HFD mice. Densitometry analyses were 
performed as for cPLA 2 a in Fig. 2A. Release of PGE 2 (B) and IL-6 (C) from adipose tissue explants. No statistically significant differences among 
the groups were noted. D: TNF-a release from adipose tissue explants was significantly increased (*P &lt; 0.001) in control HFD mice (SE) compared 
with HFD mice with AS treatment or LFD mice. E: TNF-a release from adipose tissue explants was significantly increased (*P &lt; 0.001) in control 
HFD mice (open circles) and HFD mice with IgG treatment (down gray triangles) compared with HFD mice with anti-ICAM-1 treatment (up gray 
triangles) or LFD mice (filled circles). F and G: TNF-a neutralization prevented insulin resistance in the 3-day HFD liver. Representative 
immunoblots and densitometry analyses are shown for p-Akt (serine 473) and p-GSK (serine 9). For each group of mice, liver lysate of a mouse 
that was not treated with insulin (-) and lysates from two different mice treated with insulin (+) are presented. Densitometry analyses for p-Akt 
and p-GSK were performed as in Fig. 1A. *P &lt; 0.001, significant decrease in control and IgG-treated HFD mice compared with TNF-a-depleted HFD 
mice or LFD mice. 3-day LFD (filled circles), 3-day HFD (open circles), 3-day HFD treated with anti-TNF antibodies (up gray triangles), and 3-day 
HFD treated with control IgG (down gray triangles). t, total. </p>

<p>N. HADAD AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 62, SEPTEMBER 2013 </p>

<p>
TNF-a and IL-6 are known to be associated with obesity in 
humans and rodent models (60-62), and both cytokines have 
been shown to induce hepatic insulin resistance (63,64). Al-
though there was no increase in adipose secretion of IL-6 at 
the 3-day HFD, here we show that adipose tissue released 
significantly higher levels of TNF-a and that prevention of 
neutrophil infiltration to adipose tissue significantly attenu-
ated this response. TNF-a blood levels were significantly el-
evated by the short-term HFD, consistent with a recent study 
(8), and neutralizing these elevated TNF-a levels prevented 
the development of hepatic insulin resistance by the 3-day 
HFD, further supporting its causal role in the process. In 
accordance with our results, a much higher increase in 
TNF-a than in IL-6 gene expression in adipose tissue at 
day 3 of the HFD was reported (8). We thus propose TNF-a 
as a potential mediator of primed adipose tissue neutrophils 
in causing hepatic insulin resistance induced by the 3-day 
HFD. 
In conclusion, we show here that adipose cPLA 2 a has a 
profound role in initiating hepatic insulin resistance during 
the early response to hypernutrition. Adipose cPLA 2 a has 
a major role in promoting infiltration of activated neu-
trophils to adipose tissue in a short-term HFD, probably by 
increasing the production of the neutrophil chemoattractant 
MIP-2 and upregulating ICAM-1. The presence of neu-
trophils in the adipose tissue induces elevated secretion 
of TNF-a, which likely contributes to the early development 
of isolated hepatic insulin resistance. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>N.H. was supported by a grant from Goldman Faculty Fund 
for Medical Research in Community Health of the Faculty of 
Health Sciences, Ben-Gurion University of the Negev, Beer-
Sheva, Israel. A part of the work was supported by research 
grants from the Swiss National Science Foundation (No. 
310030-141238, to D.K.). 
No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article 
were reported. 
N.H. researched the data and reviewed the manuscript. 
O.B., V.E.-C., and Y.S. researched the data. S.W., F.I., and 
D.K. conducted and interpreted the clamp studies. A.R. 
contributed to study conceptualization, results interpreta-
tion, and participated in writing and reviewing the manu-
script. R.L. designed the study and wrote the manuscript. 
R.L. is the guarantor of this work and, as such, had full 
access to all the data in the study and takes responsibility for 
the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. </p>



<p>ADIPOSE cPLA 2 a IN HEPATIC INSULIN RESISTANCE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 62, SEPTEMBER 2013 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>



<p>N. HADAD AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 62, SEPTEMBER 2013 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>