<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3778302" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Chondrosarcomas are malignant cartilage-forming tumours of bone. Because of their resistance to conventional 
chemotherapy and radiotherapy, currently no treatment strategies exist for unresectable and metastatic chondrosarcoma. 
Previously, PI3K/AKT/GSK3b and Src kinase pathways were shown to be activated in chondrosarcoma cell lines. Our aim was to 
investigate the role of these kinases in chemoresistance and migration in chondrosarcoma in relation to TP53 mutation status. </p>

<p>Methods: We used five conventional and three dedifferentiated chondrosarcoma cell lines and investigated the effect of 
PI3K/AKT/GSK3b pathway inhibition (enzastaurin) and Src pathway inhibition (dasatinib) in chemoresistance using WST assay and 
live cell imaging with AnnexinV staining. Immunohistochemistry on tissue microarrays (TMAs) containing 157 cartilaginous tumours 
was performed for Src family members. Migration assays were performed with the RTCA xCelligence System. </p>

<p>Results: Src inhibition was found to overcome chemoresistance, to induce apoptosis and to inhibit migration. Cell lines with 
TP53 mutations responded better to combination therapy than wild-type cell lines (P ¼ 0.002). Tissue microarray immuno-
histochemistry confirmed active Src (pSrc) signalling, with Fyn being most abundantly expressed (76.1%). </p>

<p>Conclusion: These results strongly indicate Src family kinases, in particular Fyn, as a potential target for the treatment of 
inoperable and metastatic chondrosarcomas, and to sensitise for doxorubicin especially in the presence of TP53 mutations. </p>

<p>Chondrosarcoma is a malignant cartilage-forming neoplasm of 
bone and the second most common bone sarcoma in humans 
(Hogendoorn et al, 2013). Conventional chondrosarcoma does not 
respond to existing chemo-and radiotherapy modalities 
(Gelderblom et al, 2008). Metastasis formation eventually occurs 
in 71% of grade III chondrosarcoma cases, and with a 10-year 
survival rate of 29%, this poses a serious treatment problem (Evans 
et al, 1977). 
Chemoresistance in chondrosarcoma has long been ascribed to 
poor vascularisation, hyaline extracellular matrix production and 
slowly dividing cells (Staals et al, 2006; David et al, 2011). Though 
this is true for low-grade chondrosarcomas, high-grade </p>

<p>chondrosarcomas typically are composed of rapidly dividing cells 
with more myxoid matrix production (Gelderblom et al, 2008; 
 et al, 2010). In the search for molecular targets, negative 
regulators of the apoptotic pathway, such as BCL-2 ( et al, 
2000; Hameetman et al, 2005; Rozeman et al, 2005; Soderstrom 
et al, 2010) and survivin (Lechler et al, 2011), were identified to be 
upregulated in chondrosarcoma, and shown to have a role in 
chemoresistance (Lechler et al, 2011; van Oosterwijk et al, 2012a). 
Apart from defective apoptotic pathways, deregulated kinase 
pathways are of growing interest in the field of cancer and have 
been suggested to have a role in chondrosarcoma ( et al, 
2010). We have previously shown activating hyperphosphorylation </p>

<p>*Correspondence: Dr JVMG  e; E-mail: J.V.M.G.Bovee@lumc.nl </p>

<p>Received 22 March 2013; revised 8 July 2013; accepted 10 July 2013; published online 6 August 2013 </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Cancer Research UK. All rights reserved 0007 -0920/13 </p>

<p>FULL PAPER </p>

<p>Keywords: chondrosarcoma; Src; TP53; Fyn </p>

<p>British Journal of Cancer (2013) 109, 1214-1222 | doi: 10.1038/bjc.2013.451 </p>

<p>1214 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.451 </p>

<p>of AKT, and Src family kinases and inactivating hyperpho-
sphorylation of GSK3b using kinome profiling of chondrosarcoma 
cell lines and primary cultures (Schrage et al, 2009). 
Both PI3K/AKT/GSK3b and Src signalling pathways are 
described in a variety of different cancer types as well as in 
progression to malignancy (Verbeek et al, 1996; Aligayer et al, 
2002; Gelman, 2011; McNamara and Degterev, 2011) and can be 
activated by receptor tyrosine kinases (RTKs) (Goode et al, 1992; 
Wheeler et al, 2009; Saini et al, 2011). Activation of the 
Src pathway promotes cell survival, proliferation and migration, 
but can also activate the PI3K/AKT/GSK3b pathway through 
phosphorylation of PI3K, thereby leading to increased AKT 
phosphorylation (Johnson et al, 2000). Activation of protein kinase 
C (PKC) by RTKs can also activate the PI3K/AKT pathway, either 
through phosphorylation of PI3K or through direct phosphoryla-
tion of AKT (Aeder et al, 2004; Kawakami et al, 2004; Figure 1A). 
Moreover, PKC and AKT can both phosphorylate GSK3b at Ser9 
(Goode et al, 1992; Fang et al, 2002). 
Because of the intricate interplay of PI3K/AKT/GSK3b and Src 
signalling pathways in cancer and the observation that both 
pathways are activated in chondrosarcoma, we hypothesised that 
the activation of these pathways in chondrosarcoma contributes 
to chemoresistance. 
We therefore investigated the role of both pathways in 
cell proliferation and chemoresistance. Our data indicate that Src 
family kinases, Fyn in particular, have a role in chemoresistance 
and cell migration, and that TP53-mutated cells are especially 
sensitive to combination therapy with doxorubicin and the Src 
inhibitor dasatinib. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Compounds. Doxorubicin and cisplatin were obtained from the 
in-house hospital pharmacy in a 0.9% NaCl solution. Therapeutic 
concentrations of doxorubicin in patients are 5-50 mM with 
an in vitro range of 1-10 mM, for cisplatin these are 3-13 mM with 
an in vitro range of 1-50 mM (Shrivastav et al, 1980). The PKC 
inhibitor enzastaurin (Faul et al, 2003; Eli Lilly, IN, USA) and the 
Src inhibitor dasatinib (Lombardo et al, 2004) (Bristol-Meyers 
Squibb, Princeton, NJ, USA) were dissolved in DMSO. </p>

<p>Cell culture. Chondrosarcoma cell lines (Table 1), as well as 
MCF-7 and HeLa cell lines were cultured in RPMI 1640 (Gibco, 
Invitrogen Life Technologies, Scotland, UK) supplemented 
with 1% L-glutamax, 1% penicillin-streptomycin (100 U ml À 1 ) 
and 10% heat-inactivated fetal calf serum (Gibco, Invitrogen Life 
Technologies, Scotland, UK). Cells were grown at 37 1C in a 
humidified incubator with 95% air and 5% CO 2 . Cells were 
cultured until they started multiplying stably. Chondrogenic 
phenotype was confirmed using RT-PCR for collagen I, IIB, III 
and X, aggrecan and SOX9 (Cleton-Jansen et al, 2005). Identity of 
cell lines was confirmed using the Cell ID System after completion 
of experiments (Promega Benelux BV, Leiden, The Netherlands). </p>

<p>Cell viability assay. Chondrosarcoma cell lines were plated in 
96-well plates for viability assessment (2 Â 10 4 -2 Â 10 5 cells per 
well depending on growth rate) and allowed to grow and adhere 
overnight after which the respective drugs were added in their 
corresponding concentrations. Combination assays were per-
formed as described (van Oosterwijk et al, 2012b) with alternating 
treatments combining enzastaurin, dasatinib and/or doxorubicin. 
All experiments were performed in triplicate and at least three 
times. Graphs show data from one representative experiment. 
Error bars indicate the s.d. </p>

<p>Immunoblotting. Immunoblotting using AKT, pAKT, Fyn 
(Cell Signaling, Leiden, the Netherlands) and pSrc antibody </p>

<p>(pSrc pY418, Invitrogen Life Technologies, Bleiswijk, the 
Netherlands) to investigate the Src and PI3K/AKT signalling 
pathway and p53 (Do7, Dako, Heverlee, Belgium), MDM2 
(IF2, Zymed, Bleiswijk, the Netherlands) and p21 (Santa Cruz, 
Heidelberg, Germany) was performed as previously described 
(Schrage et al, 2009), using 20 mg of each sample. </p>

<p>Mutation analysis. To identify mutations in AKT1, direct 
sequencing was performed as described (Pansuriya et al, 2011), 
using DNA derived from 57 tumours, 8 cell lines and 1 primary 
culture (L3310) using forward <rs type="software">primer 3</rs> 0 -TAGAGTGTGCGTGGC 
CTCTCA-5 0 and reverse primer 3 0 -CTGAATCCCGAGAGGCC 
AA-5 0 to screen for hotspot mutations in the AKT1-E17K 
pleckstrin homology domain. </p>

<p>Apoptosis assay and immunofluorescence. Apoptosis assay and 
immunofluorescence for caspase 3 and cytochrome C were 
performed as described (Puigvert et al, 2010; van Oosterwijk 
et al, 2012b). In short, 20 000 chondrosarcoma cells were grown 
in black 96-well microclear plates (Greiner, Sigma-Aldrich, 
Zwijndrecht, the Netherlands) to perform a live cell apoptosis 
assay (Puigvert et al, 2010), with AnnexinV-Alexa633 conjugate 
using the BD Pathway 855 (Becton Dickinson, Breda, the 
Netherlands). Time series were quantified using in-house-
developed macros for Image-Pro Plus (Media Cybernetics, 
Bethesda, MD, USA). Drugs were added 0, 24, and 48 h before 
imaging and Annexin V-Alexa633 conjugate was added 
immediately before imaging. For all treatments, a pan-caspase 
inhibitor, z-VAD-fmk (Bachem-Holding AG, Weil am Rhein, 
Germany), was added 30 min before drug addition and imaging to 
establish apoptosis specificity of the assay. Before imaging, live 
nuclei were stained with HOECHST-33342 at 100 ng ml À 1 . All 
experiments were performed in triplicate and at least three times. 
Error bars show s.d. from one representative experiment. </p>

<p>Migration assays. The RTCA xCelligence system (Roche Applied 
Sciences, Almere, the Netherlands), based on cell-electrode 
substract impedance detection technology, was used for migration 
assays. For migration assays, lower wells of the SIM plates 
(migration plates) were filled with growth medium (20% fetal calf 
serum in RPMI). Cell lines were plated at a density of 80 000 cells 
per well in the top wells in empty buffer (RPMI only) containing 0, 
0.2, 0.4, 0.6, 0.8 or 1.0 mM dasatinib. SIM plates were loaded into the 
RTCA station in the cell culture incubator immediately after 
plating and cell index was acquired every 5 min. Cell index as 
acquired by the software was set to 100% migration after flattening 
of the slope. Experiments were performed in triplicate. </p>

<p>Tissue microarray (TMA) construction and clinicopathological 
data. Tissue microarrays were constructed from formalin-fixed, 
paraffin-embedded tissue using standard procedures (Kononen 
et al, 1998) using a 2.0-mm diameter punch-automated tissue 
arrayer (3DHistech Ltd, Budapest, Hungary). Each array contained 
three cores per tumour wherever possible including seven control 
tissues (skin, colon, tonsil, prostate, mamma carcinoma, spleen and 
liver). Using a tape-transfer system (Instrumedics, Hackensack, NJ, 
USA), 4-mm sections were transferred to glass slides. All specimens 
in this study were handled according to the ethical guidelines 
described in 'Code for Proper Secondary Use of Human Tissue in 
The Netherlands' of the Dutch Federation of Medical Scientific 
Societies. A total of 157 patients with cartilaginous tumours were 
selected from the archives of the Leiden University Medical Centre. 
Selected cases included 137 conventional chondrosarcomas 
(central chondrosarcoma, n ¼ 92; peripheral chondrosarcoma, 
n ¼ 45) and 20 benign cartilage tumours (osteochondroma, 
n ¼ 9; enchondroma, n ¼ 11). Only primary tumours were selected. 
Histology was reviewed by an experienced bone tumour pathol-
ogist (JVMGB). Clinicopathological data are shown in Table 2. 
Total follow-up was available for 136 of 157 patients, with </p>

<p>Src signalling in chondrosarcoma chemoresistance 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.451 
1215 </p>

<p>14 patients showing metastasis at completion of this study. 
Histological grading of chondrosarcoma was performed according 
to Evans et al (1977). Rare chondrosarcoma subtypes were 
excluded. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry. Immunohistochemistry was performed 
on the TMAs. Slides were incubated with antibodies against Src, 
Lck, Fyn, Yes and phosphorylated Src (pSrc, recognises active Src 
family members phosphorylated at Y419). Details of antibodies 
and procedures are provided in Supplementary Table 1. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemical reactions were performed according to 
standard laboratory methods ( et al, 2000) and visualised 
using DAB þ Substrate Chromogen System (Dako, Heverlee, 
Belgium). Tissue microarray slides were scanned using a 
high-resolution Mirax Desk Instrument (Zeiss, Mirax 3DHistech) 
and scored independently by two observers (JVMGB and JGvO) 
and discrepancies were discussed. Staining intensity (0 ¼ absent, 
1 ¼ weak, 2 ¼ moderate, 3 ¼ strong) and extent of the staining 
(0 ¼ 0%, 1 ¼ 1-24%, 2 ¼ 25-49%, 3 ¼ 50-74% and 4 ¼ 75-100%) 
were assessed. Staining was considered high (score X4) or low </p>

<p>RTKs </p>

<p>PI3K </p>

<p>AKT </p>

<p>GSK3β </p>

<p>Erk1/2 </p>

<p>Survival/ proliferation/ migration </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>DMSO </p>

<p>Enzastuarin 1 M </p>

<p>Enzastaurin 10 M </p>

<p>DXR 10 M </p>

<p>DXR 10 M Enz 10 M DXR 10 M </p>

<p>Enz 10 M DXR 10 M Enz 10 M </p>

<p>DMSO </p>

<p>Enzastaurin 10 M </p>

<p>Mock </p>

<p>Dasatinib 1 M </p>

<p>Das 1 M Enz 10 M Das 1 M </p>

<p>Enz 10 M Das 1 M Enz 10 M </p>

<p>TP53 wild type </p>

<p>Cell line </p>

<p>Cell line </p>

<p>TP53 wild type 
TP53 mutant </p>

<p>TP53 mutant </p>

<p>P = 0.002 </p>

<p>P = 0.38 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>H 
e la </p>

<p>C 
H 
2 8 7 9 
O 
U 
M 
S 2 7 
L 8 3 5 
L 2 9 7 5 
L 3 2 5 2 
S W 
1 3 5 3 
J J 0 1 2 
N 
D 
C 
S -1 </p>

<p>C 
H 
2 8 7 9 
O 
U 
M 
S 2 7 
L 8 3 5 
L 2 9 7 5 
L 3 2 5 2 
S W 
1 3 5 3 
J J 0 1 2 
N 
D 
C 
S -1 </p>

<p>Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>MEK1/2 </p>

<p>Ser9 
Enzastaurin </p>

<p>PKC </p>

<p>Raf </p>

<p>Ras 
Dasatinib </p>

<p>SRC </p>

<p>Figure 1. Chondrosarcoma cell lines are not sensitive to PKC inhibition. (A) Schematic representation of activation of PI3K and Src pathway 
by RTKs. Receptor tyrosine kinases can activate PKC, phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K) and Src. PKC and Src can also activate the PI3K/AKT/ 
GSK3b pathway, promoting survival, proliferation and migration. The Src pathway activates the Ras/Raf pathway. Enzastaurin is a selective 
PKC inhibitor also reported to inhibitin activating phosphorylation of GSK3b. Dasatinib is a Src inhibitor. Adapted from Fizazi (2007). (B) HeLa 
cell line showing 70% decrease in cell viability after treatment with enzastaurin. Chondrosarcoma cell lines poorly respond to enzastaurin alone, 
and an additive effect is observed when alternating 10 mM doxorubicin (DXR) and 10 mM enzastaurin (Enz) for 24 h each for 72 h in total. No 
difference is observed when order of administration is reversed. Significant difference between TP53 mutant and wild-type cell lines (P ¼ 0.002). 
(C) Combination of enzastaurin with Src inhibitor dasatinib (Das) showing additive effect in chondrosarcoma cell lines. No significant difference 
is observed between TP53 mutant and wild-type cell lines (P ¼ 0.38). </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Src signalling in chondrosarcoma chemoresistance </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.451 </p>

<p>(score o4). As external positive and negative control for all the 
antibodies, specimens of normal tonsil were used. Cores with a 
negative internal control or loss of tissue were excluded from the 
analysis. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Survival was evaluated by Kaplan-Meier 
analysis and the log-rank test. Values of Pp0.05 were considered 
statistically significant. Variables that achieved significance 
(Pp0.05) were entered subsequently into a multivariate analysis 
using the Cox regression model. Cox regression analysis was 
carried out with clinical outcome (overall survival) as the 
independent variable. Correlation between expression and grade 
and individual stainings were evaluated using Pearson chi-squared 
test for independent variables. Values of Pp0.05 for asymptomatic 
two-sided testing were considered significant. The data were 
analysed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 17.0</rs> software (Chicago, IL, USA). 
For combination assays, the combination index according to the 
method of Chou and Talalay (1984) was calculated. A combination 
index (CI) of below 1 indicates synergy, and CI of above 1 indicates 
additive effect. Correlation between combination indices was 
evaluated using independent two-sided t-test using GraphPad 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">Prism 5</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">La Jolla, CA, USA</rs>). Values of Pp0.05 were 
considered significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>PI3K/AKT/GSK3b pathway is not involved in chemoresistance 
of chondrosarcoma cell lines. To investigate the PI3K/AKT/ 
GSK3b pathway, chondrosarcoma cells were treated with 1 mM and 
10 mM enzastaurin (Faul et al, 2003), a PKCb inhibitor shown to </p>

<p>inhibit AKT signalling and GSK3b phosphorylation (Graff et al, 
2005). Whereas the cervical cancer cell line HeLa shows 70% 
reduction in cell viability after treatment with 10 mM enzastaurin 
(Figure 1B), chondrosarcoma cell lines were less sensitive to 
enzastaurin treatment. Two chondrosarcoma cell lines showed 
complete resistance (NDCS-1 and L2975), whereas in the two most 
responsive cell lines (SW1353 and L3252) a maximum reduction in 
cell viability of B40% was achieved (Figure 1B). As the PI3K/AKT/ 
GSK3b pathway is involved in cell survival, we set out to examine 
its role in chemoresistance. Enzastaurin was combined with 
doxorubicin over the course of 72 h, alternating treatments every 
24 h, as we previously showed that drug administration on separate 
days was most effective (van Oosterwijk et al, 2012b). While there 
was no difference in response between IDH-mutated and IDH 
wild-type cell lines, cell lines with TP53 mutations responded 
better to combination treatment than TP53 wild-type cell lines 
(P ¼ 0.002; Figure 1B). However, a lack of synergy between the two 
drugs was observed (combination indices 42), as reduction in cell 
viability was attributed to the effect of doxorubicin alone (NDCS-
1) or the additive effect of enzastaurin and doxorubicin. Activation 
of AKT1 can be through mutations in the pleckstrin homology 
domain, found mostly in solid tumours (Mahajan and Mahajan, 
2012), leading to activated downstream signalling and decreased 
sensitivity to kinase inhibitors (Carpten et al, 2007). Hotspot 
mutations in the pleckstrin homology domain of AKT1 were 
absent in the primary chondrosarcoma tumour tissues or cell lines. </p>

<p>Inhibition of Src family kinases with dasatinib does not 
potentiate the effect of enzastaurin in chondrosarcoma cell 
lines. To exclude active Src signalling causing the limited response 
we observed to enzastaurin, we combined enzastaurin with the Src 
inhibitor dasatinib. In five cell lines (CH2879, OUMS27, SW1353, 
NDCS-1 and L3252), cell viability after combination treatment 
dropped below 50% (Figure 1C). However, the reduction in cell 
viability could not be ascribed to a synergistic effect in any of the 
cell lines. Rather it was found to be due to the effect of dasatinib 
(L835, NDCS-1 and L3252) or the additive effect of dasatinib and 
enzastaurin (combination indices 42, Figure 1C). TP53 mutation 
status was not correlated to response (P ¼ 0.38, Figure 1C). 
Interestingly, treatment with 1 mM dasatinib for 24 h was found to 
decrease phosphorylation of AKT in OUMS27, L835, L3252 and 
NDCS-1 cell lines (Figure 2A). </p>

<p>Src signalling contributes to chemoresistance of chondrosar-
coma cells. We have previously shown Src signalling to be 
involved in chondrosarcoma cell proliferation (Schrage et al, 2009). 
Immunoblotting confirmed the presence of phosphorylated Src 
(Y418) in the chondrosarcoma cell lines, with lowest expression in </p>

<p>Table 1. Chondrosarcoma cell lines </p>

<p>Cell Line 
Tumour type 
Grade 
Gender 
Age 
Passage 
TP53 a 
IDH1 b 
IDH2 b 
Reference </p>

<p>SW1353 
Solitary central 
II 
F 
72 
21 
V203L 
wt 
R172S 
Commercial (ATCC) </p>

<p>OUMS27 
Solitary central 
III 
M 
65 
27 
wt 
wt 
wt 
Kunisada et al (1998) </p>

<p>CH2879 
Solitary central 
III 
F 
35 
480 
wt 
wt 
wt 
Gil-Benso et al (2003) </p>

<p>JJ012 
Solitary central 
II 
M 
39 
9 
G199V 
R132G 
wt 
Scully et al (2000) </p>

<p>L835 
Solitary central 
III 
M 
55 
50 
wt 
R132C 
wt 
van Oosterwijk et al (2012a) </p>

<p>L2975 
Dedifferentiated 
M 
57 
60 
wt 
R172W 
wt 
van Oosterwijk et al (2012a) </p>

<p>NDCS1 
Dedifferentiated 
M 
38 
60 
C242S 
wt 
wt 
Kudo et al (2007) </p>

<p>L3252 
Dedifferentiated 
F 
52 
30 
wt 
wt 
wt 
van Oosterwijk et al (2012a) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>IDH mutations for used cell lines were described in Pansuriya et al (2011) and van Oosterwijk et al (2012a). </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>TP53 mutations for used cell lines were described in van Oosterwijk et al (2012a,b). </p>

<p>Table 2. Clinicopathological data </p>

<p>Peripheral 
(n ¼ 45) </p>

<p>Central 
(n ¼ 92) </p>

<p>Male vs female 
27 vs 18 
39 vs 53 </p>

<p>Median age at diagnosis (years) 
37 (14-82) 
50 (20-84) </p>

<p>Histology </p>

<p>Grade I 
31 
42 
Grade II 
11 
36 
Grade III 
3 
14 </p>

<p>Metastasis 
4/45 
10/92 </p>

<p>Median follow-up (months) 
121 (15-299) 
103 (7-292) </p>

<p>Src signalling in chondrosarcoma chemoresistance 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.451 </p>

<p>
L835 cells, and 24 h with 1 mM dasatinib resulted in decreased pSrc 
levels (Figure 2A). To examine the role of Src signalling in 
chemoresistance, dasatinib was combined with doxorubicin. A 
synergistic effect was observed in cell lines CH2879, OUMS27, </p>

<p>SW1353, JJ012, NDCS-1 and L2975 (combination indices ranging 
from 0.09 to 0.88; Figure 2C), and the order of drug administration 
did not influence efficacy. Interestingly, a significant difference 
between both the cell viability (P ¼ 0.002) and the combination </p>

<p>Mock 
Mock </p>

<p>1M Dasatinib 
1M Dasatinib </p>

<p>AKT </p>

<p>pAKT 
p53 
MDM2 
p21 
a tub </p>

<p>Fyn </p>

<p>pSRC </p>

<p>a tub </p>

<p>150 
TP53 wild type </p>

<p>0.25 
0.88 
1.07 
0.47 
1.22 </p>

<p>P = 0.043 </p>

<p>P = 0.002 
0.18 
0.09 
0.19 
Mock 
DMSO 
DXR 100 nM </p>

<p>DXR 100 nM Das 100 nM DXR 100 nM 
Das 100 nM DXR 100 nM Das 100 nM 
DXR 5 M Das 100 nM DXR 5 M 
Das 100 nM DXR 5 M Das 100 nM </p>

<p>Das 100 nM </p>

<p>TP53 mutant </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>CI: </p>

<p>50 
Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 
Apoptosis (% of living cells) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>50 
Migration (%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>C 
H 
2 8 7 9 
O 
U 
M 
S 2 7 
L 8 3 5 
L 2 9 7 5 
L 3 2 5 2 
S W 
1 3 5 3 
J J 0 1 2 
N 
D 
C 
S -1 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>SW1353 </p>

<p>Mock </p>

<p>40 
Migration (%) 
60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
0 
2 0 
4 0 </p>

<p>Mock 
DXR-Das-DXR 
Das-DXR-Das </p>

<p>Time (h) </p>

<p>TP53 wild type </p>

<p>Cell line </p>

<p>TP53 mutant </p>

<p>Mock </p>

<p>Dasatinib 200 nM </p>

<p>Dasatinib 1 M </p>

<p>60 
0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>Time (h) </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1M Dasatinib 
800 nM Dasatinib 
600 nM Dasatinib 
400 nM Dasatinib 
200 nM Dasatinib </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>CH2879 OUMS27 </p>

<p>Apoptosis during 
combination treatment </p>

<p>L835 
L2975 
Cell line </p>

<p>L3252 </p>

<p>MCF7 
OUMS27 
CH2879 
SW1353 
JJ012 
L835 
L2975 
L3252 
NDCS-1 
OUMS27 
CH2879 
SW1353 
JJ012 
L835 
L2975 
L3252 
NDCS-1 </p>

<p>U2OS 
OUMS27 
CH2879 
SW1353 
JJ012 
L835 
L2975 
L3252 
NDCS-1 
OUMS27 
CH2879 
SW1353 
JJ012 
L835 
L2975 
L3252 
NDCS-1 </p>

<p>SW1353 
NDCS-1 
JJ012 </p>

<p>Figure 2. The Src pathway is involved in chondrosarcoma chemoresistance. (A) Immunoblotting showing AKT, pAKT, Fyn, pSrc and loading 
control a-tubulin (a tub) for untreated chondrosarcoma cell lines and after 24-h 1 mM dasatinib. MCF-7: breast cancer cell line, shown as positive 
control. Presence of all kinases in all cell lines phophorylated Src in all cell lines, although levels are very low in L835. After 24-h 1 mM dasatinib 
treatment, levels of pSrc (at Y418) are decreased in all cell lines, and of pAKT in OUMS27, L835, L3252, JJ012 and NDCS-1. 
(B) Immunoblotting showing p53, MDM2 and p21 in untreated chondrosarcoma cell lines (Mock) and after 24-h 1 mM dasatinib. U2OS 
(osteosarcoma) cell line is shown as positive control. MDM2 expression is low in all cell lines. TP53 wild-type cell lines are negative for p53 protein 
expression, with low p21 protein expression, except for CH2879. TP53 mutant cell lines show high TP53 protein expression with low p21 protein 
expression. No change in protein levels is observed after 24-h 1 mM dasatinib treatment. (C) Combination of dasatinib (Das) with doxorubicin (DXR) 
leads to synergistic loss of cell viability at concentrations, which are ineffective on their own in most cell lines. Combination treatment was more 
effective in TP53 mutant cell lines than in TP53 wild-type cell lines (P ¼ 0.002 for cell viability, P ¼ 0.043 for combination indices). (D) Apoptosis 
assay in JJ012 cell line alternating 1 mM dasatinib (Das) and 1 mM doxorubicin (DXR) demonstrates the occurrence of apoptosis during combination. 
Apoptosis is calculated as percentage of AnnexinV-Alexxa633-stained cells per total number of HOECHST-stained cells. (D and E) Dasatinib 
successfully inhibits migration in chondrosarcoma cell lines in concentrations as low as 200 nM. (E) SW1353 cell line shown as representative 
over the course of 4 h; (F) bar chart showing migration for all cell lines. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Src signalling in chondrosarcoma chemoresistance </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.451 </p>

<p>indices (P ¼ 0.043) was observed between cell lines with and 
without TP53 mutations, and both cell lines that were resistant to 
combination treatment (L835 and L3252) were wild type for TP53 
mutations. We continued to investigate p53 accumulation as well 
as MDM2 and p21 expression in cells treated with and without 
treatment with dasatinib (Figure 2B). As expected, high p53 
protein expression with low to absent p21was seen in the three 
TP53 mutant cell lines. All TP53 wild-type cell lines demonstrated 
low p53 and p21 protein expression with the exception of CH2879, 
demonstrating high levels of p53 and p21. Protein levels were not 
affected by dasatinib treatment. All cell lines showed low MDM2 
protein expression. 
No correlation with IDH mutations was found. </p>

<p>Src inhibition combined with doxorubicin induces apoptosis. 
Using annexinV-binding live cell imaging, we confirmed our 
previous findings (Schrage et al, 2009) that dasatinib monotreat-
ment does not induce apoptosis (Figure 2D, first 24 h). However, 
when combined with doxorubicin, up to 50% of cells had entered 
apoptosis after completion of the third cycle of combination 
treatment (JJ012 cell line shown as a representative cell line, 
Figure 2D). Because of the effect of doxorubicin during the first </p>

<p>24 h, 10% more cells had entered apoptosis during combination 
treatment starting doxorubicin, than during combination treat-
ment starting with dasatinib. Apoptosis could be inhibited using 
the pan-caspase inhibitor z-VAD-fmk (results not shown). </p>

<p>Dasatinib inhibits migration of chondrosarcoma cell lines. As 
Src family members also have a role in motility and adhesion 
(Saito et al, 2010), we continued to investigate the migratory 
capacity of the chondrosarcoma cell lines. Using a transwell 
system, all chondrosarcoma cell lines showed migratory properties, 
and started migrating B30 min after plating, except for JJ012 cells, 
which started migrating only 4 h after plating (results not shown). 
In the presence of dasatinib, however, a complete inhibition of cell 
migration was achieved for all cell lines at concentrations as low as 
200 nM (Figure 2E and F). No difference between cell lines 
harbouring TP53 mutations and wild-type cell lines was observed. </p>

<p>Fyn is the most important Src family member in chondrosar-
coma tissues. To identify the most important Src family member 
in chondrosarcoma, we evaluated the expression of the 4 family 
members Src, Yes, Fyn and Lck, as well as pSrc in primary 
tumour samples. Active Src signalling as evidenced by positive 
staining for pSrc was found in 88-100% of the tumours (Table 3, </p>

<p>Table 3. Protein expression in tumours using immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Peripheral chondrosarcoma 
Central chondrosarcoma </p>

<p>Osteochondroma 
Grade I 
Grade II 
Grade III 
Enchondroma 
Grade I 
Grade II 
Grade III </p>

<p>pSrc 
3/3 (100%) 
12/13 (92%) 
6/6 (100%) 
3/3 (100%) 
4/5 (80%) 
21/24 (88%) 
21/22 (96%) 
10/10 (100%) </p>

<p>Src 
1/7 (14%) 
7/17 (41%) 
8/8 (100%) 
2/3 (67%) 
4/7 (57%) 
12/31 (39%) 
12/31 (39%) 
7/13 (54%) </p>

<p>Yes 
0/7 (0%) 
3/23 (13%) 
0/10 (0%) 
0/3 (0%) 
0/7 (0%) 
0/36 (0%) 
3/30 (10%) 
0/14 (0%) </p>

<p>Fyn 
7/8 (88%) 
16/20 (80%) 
9/10 (90%) 
3/3 (100%) 
5/5 (100%) 
17/35 (49%) 
31/35 (89%) 
13/14 (93%) </p>

<p>Lck 
0/3 (0%) 
1/23 (4%) 
2/10 (20%) 
0/3 (0%) 
0/7 (0%) 
1/38 (3%) 
0/33 (0%) 
2/13 (15%) </p>

<p>50 μm 
50 μm 
50 μm </p>

<p>50 μm 
50 μm </p>

<p>pSrc 
Fyn 
Src </p>

<p>Lck </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Scoring sum </p>

<p>Scr family member </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0 
pSrc 
Src 
Yes 
Fyn 
Lck </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Figure 3. Immunohistochemistry demonstrating expression of Src family members in conventional chondrosarcoma tissue. (A) High pSrc 
expression in grade I chondrosarcoma. (B) High-intensity nuclear Fyn expression in grade I chondrosarcoma. (C) High-intensity cytoplasmic and 
nuclear Src expression in grade I chondrosarcoma. (D) Absence of Yes expression in grade II chondrosarcoma. (E) Absence of Lck in grade II 
chondrosarcoma. Scale bars, 50 mm. (F) Scatterplot showing distribution of staining scores among chondrosarcoma tissue samples. </p>

<p>Src signalling in chondrosarcoma chemoresistance 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.451 </p>

<p>
Figure 3A and F). Of the four Src family members, we found Fyn 
(76.1% high expression, 89 out of 117) and Src (46.6% high 
expression, 48 out of 103) to be most abundantly expressed in 
chondrosarcoma (Table 3, Figure 3B, C and F). In contrast, high 
expression of Yes and Lck was observed in only 5% of all 
chondrosarcoma cases (6 out of 116 and 6 out of 120, respectively) 
(Table 3, Figure 3D-F). During the staining procedures, some 
cores were lost due to inherent structural instability of the tissue. A 
significant increase in Src expression was seen between grade I and 
grade II peripheral CS (P ¼ 0.005, Pearson chi-squared test). 
Though not significant, Src expression in tumours was found to be 
inversely correlated with overall survival (P ¼ 0.3, log rank). Fyn 
expression was found to significantly increase with increasing 
histological grade in both peripheral chondrosarcoma (P ¼ 0.05 
Pearson chi-squared test) and central chondrosarcoma (P ¼ 0.000, 
Pearson chi-squared test). No significant correlations to metastasis 
were found. Using western blot, we confirmed expression of Fyn in 
all cell lines, with low expression in L835 (Figure 2A). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Chondrosarcomas are resistant to conventional chemotherapy. 
Despite ongoing research, there is still nothing to offer patients 
with unresectable or metastatic disease and the need for new, 
targeted therapies is high. We here explored the effects of increased 
PI3K/AKT/GSK3b and Src signalling on chondrosarcoma chemo-
resistance and cell migration using enzastaurin and dasatinib, 
respectively. We show that dasatinib is more effective in 
overcoming chondrosarcoma chemoresistance than enzastaurin, 
and acts synergistically with doxorubicin to inhibit cell viability 
and induce apoptosis. Most importantly, we show that in cell lines 
with TP53 mutations, the combination of tyrosine kinase inhibitors 
with doxorubicin is more beneficial than in wild-type TP53 
cell lines. 
Chondrosarcoma is a heterogeneous disease, and this hetero-
geneity is represented in the cell lines. Recently, IDH1 and IDH2 
mutations were found in chondrosarcoma (Amary et al, 2011), and 
we published that these mutations are retained in chondrosarcoma 
cell lines (Pansuriya et al, 2011; van Oosterwijk et al, 2012a). Of the 
two cell lines that were non-responsive to combination treatment 
of doxorubicin with dasatinib, one central chondrosarcoma cell 
line (L835) carried an IDH1 mutation, whereas the other 
(dedifferentiated chondrosarcoma cell line (L3252)) was wild type 
for IDH. Thus, no correlation between IDH mutation status and 
response to dasatinib monotreatment or combination treatment 
with doxorubicin was observed. More likely, the lack of sensitivity 
to dasatinib in the L835 cell line is caused by the low pSrc activity 
in this cell line. 
Src inhibition with dasatinib resulted in successful sensitisation 
for doxorubicin treatment, especially in TP53 mutant chondro-
sarcoma cell lines. Approximately 30% of chondrosarcomas carry 
TP53 mutations, and these mutations are found especially in high-
grade chondrosarcomas (Oshiro et al, 1998; Terek et al, 1998). 
Three of the eight cell lines carry a TP53 mutation (SW1353, JJ012 
and NDCS-1), and these cell lines also showed a better response to 
combination treatment with low combination indices when 
compared with TP53 wild-type cell lines. This is an interesting 
result as mutant TP53 is described to actively inhibit apoptosis 
through activation of p21 (Donzelli et al, 2012) or to confer 
chemoresistance through engaging in oncogenic transcription 
complexes (Huang et al, 2012). Previously, dasatinib was found 
to interfere with the p53 transcriptional activity induced by the 
MDM2 inhibitor nutlin-3 (Zauli et al, 2011). We show that 
dasatinib does not affect p53 nor p21 protein expression in 
chondrosarcoma cells. Dasatinib as a single agent proved </p>

<p>ineffective in chondrosarcoma patients (Schuetze et al, 2010). 
However, recent clinical studies with dasatinib in other malig-
nancies have shown its efficacy not only irrespective of TP53 status 
as a single agent (Bosco et al, 2012) but also to overcome TP53 
mutation status-related chemoresistance (Amrein et al, 2008). The 
results of these clinical studies in combination with the data we 
show here strongly suggest clinical evaluation of the efficacy of 
dasatinib in combination with doxorubicin in chondrosarcoma 
patients harbouring TP53 mutations. 
As we demonstrate Src signalling to have a role in chemore-
sistance, we further explored the expression of the different Src 
family kinases (SFKs) in human chondrosarcoma tissues. Fyn was 
most widely expressed (89 out of 117) and was found to increase 
with increasing histological grade, suggesting a role in chondro-
sarcoma progression. Fyn is reported to be upregulated in multiple 
cancers, and to be associated with malignant progression and 
metastasis formation (Posadas et al, 2009; Chen et al, 2010; Saito 
et al, 2010). We confirmed that indeed the Src pathway is 
important in chondrosarcoma cell motility, as dasatinib completely 
inhibited migratory capacity of all chondrosarcoma cell lines even 
at low dose. 
Clinical trials with dasatinib have shown the efficacy and low 
toxicity of dasatinib in combination with conventional chemother-
apeutic agents in solid tumours (Montero et al, 2011). In a phase II 
study of dasatinib with hyper-CVAD in patients with Philadelphia 
chromosome-positive lymphoblastic leukaemia, long-term remis-
sion was achieved in newly diagnosed patients (Ravandi et al, 
2010), and in a phase I-II study of dasatinib with doxetaxel in 
castration-resistant prostate cancer, disappearance of bone lesions 
was obtained (Araujo et al, 2012). The results obtained with 
dasatinib in combination with chemotherapy strongly encourage 
the exploration of dasatinib in combination with doxorubicin in 
patients with chondrosarcoma. 
Both the PI3K/AKT/GSK3b and Src kinase pathways are 
activated by RTKs (Goode et al, 1992; Wheeler et al, 2009), and 
have diverse roles in promoting growth, survival and metastasis 
(Aligayer et al, 2002; Wheeler et al, 2009; Yang et al, 2010; 
McNamara and Degterev, 2011; Saini et al, 2011). We show here 
that constitutive activation of AKT due to mutations does not have 
a role in chondrosarcoma, and further research should elucidate 
which RTK is responsible for the high AKT, GSK3b and Src 
phosphorylation (Schrage et al, 2009). A possible candidate is 
IGF-1, which can activate the PI3K/AKT and Src pathway through 
the RTK IGF-1R (Grimberg, 2003), and has been shown to induce 
PI3K/AKT signalling and migration in chondrosarcoma cell lines 
(Wu et al, 2011). Src family kinases can induce phosphorylation of 
the RTK domains of IGF-1 as well as the PDGF receptors through 
SHP-2 leading to receptor internalisation. This increases binding 
efficacy with PI3K, leading to increased proliferative capacity of 
cancer cells (Wu et al, 2001; Carver et al, 2010). Moreover, AKT 
functions as a gatekeeper of apoptosis through phosphorylation of 
BAD. AKT-mediated phosphorylation of BAD inhibits its binding 
capacity to antiapoptotic BCL-2 family members, which will 
prevent a cell from entering apoptosis (Gilmore et al, 2002; 
Maddika et al, 2007). We recently published that the antiapoptotic 
BCL-2 family members also have a role in chondrosarcoma 
chemoresistance (van Oosterwijk et al, 2012b). Combined with the 
results of the present study, this is suggestive of a common 
mechanism. However, more studies are needed to explore whether 
the activation of the IGF pathway by Src leading to the inhibition 
of BH3 proteins and apoptosis through AKT may be involved in 
chondrosarcoma chemoresistance. 
In conclusion, we found that inhibition of the Src pathway was 
successful in overcoming chemoresistance and inhibited migration. 
A synergistic response to combination treatment was observed, 
which was significantly stronger (P ¼ 0.002) in cell lines harbour-
ing TP53 mutations. Moreover, as we observed the Src family </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Src signalling in chondrosarcoma chemoresistance </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.451 </p>

<p>member Fyn to be the most prevalent in chondrosarcoma tissues, 
we hypothesise Fyn to have a major role in the chemoresistance 
and malignant progression of chondrosarcoma. These results aid in 
the understanding of signalling pathways in chondrosarcoma and 
may lead to the development of effective therapeutic strategies for 
currently untreatable metastatic chondrosarcoma. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Dorien van der Geest and Pauline Wijers-Koster for 
technical assistance. We also thank Bristol Myers Squibb for 
providing dasatinib and Eli Lilly for providing enzastaurin. We are 
grateful to Dr JA Block (Rush University Medical Centre, Chicago, 
IL, USA), who kindly provided us with the JJ012 cell line, to 
Professor A Llombart Bosch (University of Valencia, Spain) for the 
cell line CH2879, M Namba (Okayama University Medical School, 
Shikata, Japan) for the OUMS27 cell line and Dr T Ariizumi 
(Niigata University Graduate School of Medical and Dental 
Sciences, Niigata, Japan) for the cell line NDCS-1. This work was 
financially supported by Dutch Cancer Society (UL2010-4873: 
JGvO, JVMGB and BvdW) and Netherlands Organization 
for Scientific Research (917-67-315: JVMGB). This study was 
performed in the context of EuroSARC, a collaborative project 
within the EC's 7th Framework programme under grant 
agreement278742. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>



<p>Src signalling in chondrosarcoma chemoresistance 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.451 </p>



<p>
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Src signalling in chondrosarcoma chemoresistance </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.451 </p>

</text></tei>