<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3357263" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Increased morbidity and mortality associated with ischemic heart 
failure (HF) in type 2 diabetic patients requires a deeper under-
standing of the underpinning pathogenetic mechanisms. Given 
the implication of microRNAs (miRNAs) in HF, we investigated 
their regulation and potential role. miRNA expression profiles 
were measured in left ventricle biopsies from 10 diabetic HF 
(D-HF) and 19 nondiabetic HF (ND-HF) patients affected by non-
end stage dilated ischemic cardiomyopathy. The HF groups were 
compared with each other and with 16 matched nondiabetic, non-
HF control subjects. A total of 17 miRNAs were modulated in 
D-HF and/or ND-HF patients when compared with control sub-
jects. miR-216a, strongly increased in both D-HF and ND-HF 
patients, negatively correlated with left ventricular ejection frac-
tion. Six miRNAs were differently expressed when comparing 
D-HF and ND-HF patients: miR-34b, miR-34c, miR-199b, miR-
210, miR-650, and miR-223. Bioinformatic analysis of their mod-
ulated targets showed the enrichment of cardiac dysfunctions 
and HF categories. Moreover, the hypoxia-inducible factor path-
way was activated in the noninfarcted, vital myocardium of D-HF 
compared with ND-HF patients, indicating a dysregulation of the 
hypoxia response mechanisms. Accordingly, miR-199a, miR-199b, 
and miR-210 were modulated by hypoxia and high glucose in 
cardiomyocytes and endothelial cells cultured in vitro. In conclu-
sion, these findings show a dysregulation of miRNAs in HF, shed-
ding light on the specific disease mechanisms differentiating 
diabetic patients. RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patient selection and tissue collection. Left ventricle cardiac biopsies were 
derived from consecutive patients affected by dilated hypokinetic ischemic 
cardiomyopathy and obtained during surgical ventricular restoration proce-
dures performed as described previously (23). For each patient, two biopsies 
were harvested: one from the peri-infarctual area (border zone) and one from 
the nonischemic, remote myocardium (remote zone). Samples were immedi-
ately immersed in RNAlater (QIAGEN GmbH) and stored at 4°C for ,24 h 
before RNA extraction. D-HF (n = 10) and ND-HF (n = 19) patients were se-
lected as described in Table 1. D-HF and ND-HF patients did not differ sig-
nificantly for any clinical parameter other than type 2 diabetes (Table 1). In the 
validation procedure, the ND-HF group was extended to 4 more patients, with 
characteristics similar to those shown in Table 2. The control (CTR) cohort 
was constituted by age-and sex-matched subjects who died from causes other 
than stroke, ischemia, or cachexia for chronic diseases (n = 16, [7 females/9 
males], aged 57 6 3.2 years). Left ventricle samples were harvested ,24 h 
after death and snap frozen at 280°C. 
Bioptic specimens were taken after informed consent disclosing future use 
for research. The investigation conformed to the principles outlined in the 
Helsinki Declaration and to Italian laws and guidelines and was authorized by 
a local ethics committee. 
RNA isolation and miRNA profiling. Total RNA was extracted using TRIzol 
(Invitrogen) and the TissueLyser system (QIAGEN). TaqMan Low Density 
miRNA arrays (Applied Biosystems), containing quantitative real-time RT-PCR </p>

<p>(qRT-PCR) assays for 365 human mature miRNAs, were performed using 100 ng 
total RNA as indicated by the manufacturer. Samples were normalized according 
to the median cycle threshold (Ct) value. Relative miRNA expression was cal-
culated with the 2 -DDCt method. miRNAs with a Ct #33 and a DDCt $ |1| in at 
least one of the three comparisons were further analyzed. Data distribution was 
evaluated by the Kolmogorov-Smirnov normality test. Permutational multivariate 
ANOVA was performed by the multivariate nonparametric PERMANOVA test, 
using 9,999 permutations, Bonferroni post hoc test, and Gower test for distance 
measurement. Adjusted P , 0.05 was considered statistically significant. 
mRNA profiling. Gene expression profiles were measured using Affymetrix 
GeneChips Human Gene 1.0ST arrays in 7 D-HF, 11 ND-HF, and 5 CTR sub-
jects. Total RNA (100 ng) was analyzed according to the manufacturer's 
instructions. Gene expression profiles were analyzed using the class compari-
son between-groups function of BRB-ArrayTools (Richard Simon and BRB-
ArrayTools Development Team). Since our arrays have a small number of 
samples per class, differentially expressed genes were evaluated using the 
random variance version of the two-sample t test, as suggested by the BRB-
ArrayTools user manual. The class comparison function also performs random 
permutations of the class labels, recomputing the random variance t tests of 
each gene for each random permutation. False discovery rate was computed 
per gene using the Benjamini and Hochberg (24) method. Differentially modu-
lated genes were identified using the random variance version of the two-
sample t test, with P , 0.001 and false discovery rate ,0.05 as significance 
thresholds. The complete dataset of our study is available from the National </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Experimental plan. miRNA (blue) and mRNA (red) expression profiles were determined, and class comparison analysis identified sig-
nificantly modulated miRNAs and mRNAs in the indicated classes of patients. Validation was performed by qRT-PCR for both miRNAs and mRNAs. 
IPA was used to analyze the molecular pathways and functions enriched among the differentially expressed mRNA (far right branch). For the 
miRNAs identified by class comparison, target mRNAs were predicted by dedicated software. Next, predicted target datasets were intersected with 
significantly modulated mRNAs deriving from class comparison analysis. Only miRNA/mRNA couples displaying inverse significant correlations 
were selected (purple) and further analyzed by IPA. </p>

<p>miRNA DYSREGULATION IN DIABETIC HF PATIENTS </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, JUNE 2012 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>Center for Biotechnology Information Gene Expression Omnibus database 
(GEO GSE26887). 
qRT-PCR assays. Individual mature miRNAs were measured using TaqMan 
MicroRNA single assays (Applied Biosystems) (25). Samples were normalized 
to miR-16 expression. 
mRNA levels were measured using the SYBR Green qRT-PCR method (Applied 
Biosystems), and samples were normalized to the average level of glyceraldehyde-
3-phosphate dehydrogenase and ubiquitin C. For both miRNAs and mRNAs, 
relative expression was calculated using the comparative Ct method (2 -DDCt ). 
To determine miRNA scores, the mean fold change of all the miRNAs be-
longing to each specific analysis (D-HF vs. CTR, ND-HF vs. CTR, and ND-HF vs. 
D-HF) was calculated for each patient and the minus sign was inverted before 
calculating the mean. 
Bioinformatic analysis. Bioinformatic prediction of miRNA target genes was 
performed using miRonTop (26,27). Predicted miRNA target genes were </p>

<p>compared with differently expressed genes (P # 0.01) displaying an opposite 
modulation with their corresponding miRNA. The correlation analysis be-
tween mRNA and miRNA expression was evaluated by the quantitative trait 
tool in BRB-ArrayTools (P # 0.01). 
Pathway analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Ingenuity Pathways Knowledge Base</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 8.8</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Ingenuity Systems</rs>) as reference set and assuming direct and in-
direct relationships. Fisher exact test P value ,0.05 without multiple-testing 
correction was deemed statistically significant. 
Cell cultures. Mouse neonatal cardiomyocytes were prepared and cultured as 
previously described (28) from CD-1 mice (Harlan Laboratories, Inc.). All 
animal procedures complied with the Guidelines of the Italian National Insti-
tutes of Health and with the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals 
(Institute of Laboratory Animal Resources, National Academy of Sciences, 
Bethesda, MD) and were approved by the institutional animal care and use 
committee. Primary human coronary artery endothelial cells (HCAECs), hu-
man umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs) (Clonetics Corp.), and human 
HEK293T cell line (American Type Culture Collection) were cultured as 
previously described (25). For transforming growth factor (TGF)-b stim-
ulations, HUVECs were cultured in 1% FBS endothelial basal medium (Lonza 
Group Ltd.) for 14 h and then stimulated for 48 h with 0-50 ng/mL TGF-b 
(R&amp;D Systems). For hypoxia and high glucose stimulations, cells were cul-
tured in the presence of either 25 mmol/L glucose or 5 mmol/L glucose plus 
20 mmol/L mannitol (iso-osmotic control) for 72 h. Next, they were in-
cubated in hypoxia (1.0% O 2 ) or normoxia for a further 24 h, as previously 
described (25). 
Statistics. Continuous variables are expressed as mean 6 SE. Gaussian 
distribution was tested by using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. For group-wise 
comparisons, Mann-Whitney test (two groups), ANOVA, Kruskal-Wallis test 
(n groups), or t test (two groups) were used as appropriate. For categorical 
variables, x 2 test was used. Spearman rank correlation was used to compare 
levels of miRNAs with clinical factors. All tests were performed two-sided and 
P # 0.05 was considered statistically significant. For statistical analysis and 
heat map data visualization, <rs id="software-2" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 4.03</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">GraphPad Software Inc.</rs>.) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">Genesis</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">1.7.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Graz University of Technology, Institute for Genomics and Bioinformatics</rs>) software were used, respectively. </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Selection criteria of HF patients </p>

<p>Selection criteria </p>

<p>Inclusion criteria 
For D-HF patients, glycemia $126 mg/dL or previous type 2 
Ć 
diabetes diagnosis and antidiabetic therapy. For both 
Ć 
diabetic and nondiabetic patients, HF diagnosis according 
Ć 
to European Society of Cardiology 2008 guidelines. 
Exclusion criteria 
Type 1 diabetes 
Matching parameters 
End-systolic volume, LVEF, age, sex, ethnic distribution, 
Ć 
smoking habits, hypertension, glomerular filtration rate, 
Ć 
and BMI </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
Clinical characteristics of study population </p>

<p>Characteristics 
D-HF patients (n = 10) 
ND-HF patients (n = 19) 
P </p>

<p>Age (years) 
61.8 6 2.3 
60.2 6 2.8 
NS 
Sex (male/female) 
9/1 
18/1 
NS 
Current/previous/nonsmoker (%) 
20/50/30 
18/76/6 
NS 
BMI (kg/m 2 ) 
27.4 6 1.3 
26.0 6 0.8 
NS 
Glomerular filtration rate (mL/min) 
71.4 6 7.0 
76.3 6 5.1 
NS 
Glucose (mg/dL) 
125.1 6 9.8 
97 6 3.6 
,0.05 
HbA 1c (%) (IFCC) 
5.5 6 0.3 
4.3 6 0.2 
,0.05 
Total cholesterol (mg/dL) 
149.4 6 11.4 
155 6 14.9 
NS 
HDL (mg/dL) 
34.4 6 2.1 
38.8 6 7.5 
NS 
LDL (mg/dL) 
90 6 7.8 
86.8 6 11 
NS 
Triglycerides (mg/dL) 
127.6 6 18.5 
206.8 6 64.5 
NS 
Time from MI (months), median 
7.6 
6.8 
NS 
LVEF (%) 
27.2 6 2.5 
27.6 6 1.9 
NS 
EDV (mL) 
186.4 6 12.3 
265.2 6 30.8 
NS 
ESV (mL) 
132.3 6 9.5 
197.3 6 26.9 
NS 
ESVI (mL/mm 2 ) 
72.9 6 0.04 
103.7 6 14 
NS 
EDVI (mL/mm 2 ) 
102.6 6 6.1 
139.3 6 15.9 
NS 
Stroke volume (mL) 
51.1 6 6.0 
67.8 6 5.3 
NS 
Type-Q MI (%) 
80 
83 
NS 
Medications (%) 
Oral antidiabetic agents 
60 
0 
,0.05 
Insulin 
40 
0 
,0.05 
Statins 
90 
78 
NS 
ACE inhibitors 
90 
75 
NS 
b-Blockers 
70 
94 
NS 
Aspirin 
100 
89 
NS 
Loop diuretics 
90 
89 
NS 
Nitrates 
30 
11 
NS </p>

<p>Values are mean 6 SE unless otherwise indicated. IFCC, International Federation of Clinical Chemistry and Laboratory Medicine; MI, myocardial 
infarction; EDV, end-diastolic volume; ESV, end-systolic volume; ESVI, ESV/body surface area; EDVI, EDV/body surface area; Type-Q MI, MI with 
abnormal Type-Q waves on electrocardiogram. Boldface type indicates statistically significant differences between D-HF and ND-HF groups. </p>

<p>S. GRECO AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, JUNE 2012 </p>

<p>
RESULTS </p>

<p>Identification of differentially expressed miRNAs in 
D-HF and ND-HF patients. Patients were carefully se-
lected so that D-HF and ND-HF patients displayed similar 
heart function impairment (Table 1). The aim was mini-
mizing miRNA expression differences due to disease pro-
gression per se, highlighting differences resulting from the 
concomitant occurrence of diabetes. Myocardial biopsies 
were derived from the nonischemic, remote area of the left 
ventricle of 19 ND-HF and 10 D-HF patients. None of the 
clinical parameters other than the occurrence of type 2 
diabetes and HbA 1c concentration were significantly dif-
ferent between these patient groups (Table 2). A total of 16 
age-and sex-matched nondiabetic individuals were used as 
CTR subjects. Total RNA was extracted, and miRNA pro-
filing showed that out of 365 miRNAs measured, ;250 were 
readily detectable in all groups. We found that 41 miRNAs 
were significantly modulated greater than or equal to two-
fold in D-HF and/or in ND-HF compared with CTR subjects. 
Moreover, 10 of these miRNAs were also expressed differ-
ently in D-HF compared with ND-HF patients (Fig. 2A). 
Significantly modulated miRNAs were validated by more 
sensitive and specific qRT-PCR assays. This validation step 
included the same patients and CTR subjects used for pro-
filing and was extended to four more ND-HF patients. We 
found that 17 miRNAs were significantly modulated in 
D-HF and/or ND-HF patients compared with CTR subjects. 
Comparing D-HF with ND-HF, we observed that 6 miRNAs 
were differently modulated: miR-34b, miR-34c, miR-199b, 
miR-210, miR-650, and miR-223 (Fig. 2A and Supplemen-
tary Table 1). 
In addition, the average fold changes of the differentially 
expressed miRNAs in each patient group were summa-
rized in three scores: D-HF versus CTR, ND-HF versus 
CTR, and D-HF versus ND-HF. Figure 2B shows that each 
score exhibited highly significant differences in the cor-
responding patient cohorts. 
miR-216a is induced in HF patients and by TGF-b. 
miR-216a is the miRNA displaying the highest induction in 
both HF patient classes. Of interest, we found that miR-216a 
expression was inversely correlated with LVEF (Fig. 2C). 
TGF-b is particularly expressed in the hypertrophic 
myocardium progressing toward HF (29) and can also in-
duce miR-216a expression in diabetic nephropathy (30). 
Thus, we asked whether TGF-b may trigger miR-216a ex-
pression in the heart as well. While miR-216a is barely de-
tectable in isolated mouse cardiac myocytes and fibroblasts 
(not shown), it was readily detectable in human endothelial 
cells. Upon TGF-b stimulation of these cells, we found that 
miR-216a expression was significantly induced in a dose-
dependent (Fig. 2D) and time-dependent (not shown) fash-
ion, suggesting that TGF-b may play a similar role in HF. 
miRNA deregulation in the border zone. We tested 
whether miRNA expression differences observed in the 
myocardial portion remote from the infarction region were 
also present in the border zone (i.e., in the myocardial 
portion around the scar tissue formed after the infarction). 
We found that all tested miRNAs were similarly dysregu-
lated in the remote zone and in the border zone (not 
shown). It is intriguing that miR-216a increase was even 
higher in the border than in the remote zone (D-HF = 65 6 
3.8 and ND-HF = 49 6 2.5 vs. CTR, P , 0.0001, for both). We 
also found that most expression differences between D-HF 
and ND-HF patients were attenuated in the border zone 
(Fig. 3 and Supplementary Table 2). For miR-34b, miR-34c, 
miR-210, and miR-199b, the expression differences were not </p>

<p>due to less severe dysregulation in diabetic patients but, 
rather, to the opposite; indeed, expression levels for these 
miRNA were induced in ND-HF as well. Likewise, miR-223 
decrease in the border zone was attenuated for both D-HF 
and ND-HF, in keeping with the less pronounced miR-223 
downmodulation in D-HF than in ND-HF, as observed in the 
remote zone (Supplementary Table 1). Thus, at least for the 
analyzed miRNAs, the dysregulations observed only in di-
abetic patients when the remote myocardium was analyzed 
were found in the border zone of both patient classes. 
Impact of HF dysregulated miRNAs on the transcriptome. 
To investigate the functional implications of miRNA dys-
regulations identified in both D-HF and ND-HF patients, we 
tested their impact on the transcriptome. 
First, we measured gene expression profiles using high-
density oligonucleotide microarrays. As expected, unsup-
ervised hierarchical clustering analysis segregated the 
profiles of D-HF, ND-HF, and CTR subjects (Supplementary 
Fig. 1). Class comparison analysis versus the CTR group was 
performed and qRT-PCR validated (Supplementary Fig. 2), 
identifying 389 genes differentially expressed in D-HF and 
1,180 genes differentially expressed in ND-HF. Moreover, 
the comparison between D-HF and ND-HF groups identified 
376 modulated genes that could be attributed to diabetes 
(data not shown; see Gene Expression Omnibus database, 
GEO GSE26887 for a complete gene list). 
Next, experimentally validated and predicted targets of 
each miRNA were analyzed, and mRNA/miRNA couples 
displaying reciprocal modulation were selected. Statistical 
analysis allowed the identification of 140, 329, and 11 
miRNA/mRNA interactions in the D-HF versus CTR, ND-HF 
versus CTR, and D-HF versus ND-HF groups, respectively 
(Supplementary Table 3). A subset of the identified miRNA-
target modulations was further validated by qRT-PCR in 
cardiac biopsies (Fig. 4) and in a cell culture system (Sup-
plementary Fig. 3). 
Gene interaction and pathway analysis of global gene 
expression changes. To facilitate the interpretation of the 
complex gene expression changes observed in the different 
experimental groups, we used Ingenuity Pathway Analysis 
software (IPA), exploring for enriched biological functions 
and pathways. We applied a low-stringency approach, pri-
oritizing sensitivity to maximize the identification of the 
potentially involved categories. 
To assess the potential functional relevance of the global 
gene expression changes observed in D-HF and ND-HF 
patients, class comparison genes were uploaded to the IPA 
database (Table 3). Several interesting network functions 
were enriched significantly in the D-HF group compared 
with the ND-HF group, such as the cardiovascular system 
development and function (Table 3). It is remarkable that 
IPA analysis also revealed a significant association of the 
hypoxia-inducible factor (HIF) signaling pathway to the 
mRNAs modulated in the D-HF group. In addition, a sig-
nificant association of the transmembrane potential of 
mitochondria decrease and notch signaling pathway to 
the D-HF mRNAs was found (Table 3). 
Gene interaction and pathway analysis of miRNA 
target genes. To investigate the specific functional im-
pact of miRNA-dependent gene expression deregulation, IPA 
analysis was performed considering only predicted miRNA 
target genes displaying an inverse correlation with their 
corresponding miRNA (Supplementary Table 3). This anal-
ysis identified several interesting functions, canonical path-
ways, toxic functions, and toxic lists significantly enriched 
for the ND-HF or D-HF versus CTR groups (Table 3). Most of </p>

<p>miRNA DYSREGULATION IN DIABETIC HF PATIENTS </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, JUNE 2012 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>these categories were enriched in both HF groups. However, 
other functions were associated with the D-HF versus CTR 
group only (e.g., free radical scavenging, oxidative stress, 
cardiac damage, cardiac dysfunction, cardiac fibrosis, and </p>

<p>HF) (Table 3), suggesting the involvement of the identified 
miRNAs in these events. The low number of targets cor-
relating with D-HF versus ND-HF miRNAs precluded IPA 
analysis. </p>

<p>FIG. 2. miRNAs modulated in D-HF and ND-HF patients. Validation of the significantly modulated miRNAs by qRT-PCR. D-HF (n = 10) and ND-HF 
(n = 23) patients were compared with each other and with CTR subjects (n = 16). A: Average values are expressed using a log 2 scale (-DDCt) in 
a heat map where green and red colors indicate down-or upregulation, respectively; yellow boxes indicate those miRNAs statistically deregulated 
in D-HF vs. ND-HF patients. B: Scores summarizing miRNA differences observed in each patient were calculated. The fold change of all the miRNAs 
belonging to each specific analysis (D-HF vs. CTR, ND-HF vs. CTR, and ND-HF vs. D-HF) was calculated for each patient. Next, the sign of negative 
values was inverted and the mean of all values was calculated. Statistical difference between each group couple was identified by unpaired, two-tailed 
t test. C: Inverse correlation of miR-216a fold change compared with CTR subjects and LVEF values (Spearman analysis; P &lt; 0.05). D: miR-216a mod-
ulation by TGF-b in vitro. HUVEC cells were growth-factor starved for 14 h and then stimulated with 1, 5, 10, or 50 ng/mL TGF-b or with vehicle only (CTR) 
for 48 h. miR-216a levels were measured by qRT-PCR and expressed as fold change compared with CTR subjects. n = 4. *P £ 0.05, **P £ 0.01, ***P &lt; 0.001. </p>

<p>S. GRECO AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, JUNE 2012 </p>

<p>
Activation of the HIF signaling pathway in D-HF 
patients. HIF signaling pathway enrichment among genes 
modulated comparing D-HF with ND-HF patients appeared 
particularly significant, since one of the modulated miRNAs, 
miR-210, is a known HIF-1a target (26). Thus, the activation 
of the HIF pathway was investigated further in HF bi-
opsies by qRT-PCR. We found that HIF-1a mRNA levels 
were increased in the remote myocardium of D-HF pa-
tients compared with ND-HF patients, while the other 
members of the HIF family, HIF-2a and HIF-3a, were not 
modulated (Fig. 5A). This HIF-1a increase appeared func-
tionally relevant since it was associated with higher levels 
of HIF target genes (Fig. 5A). 
miR-199a, miR-199b, and miR-210 modulation by 
hypoxia and high glucose. These findings prompted us 
to investigate whether hypoxia was a significant stimulus 
regulating HF miRNA expression. The experiments were 
conducted in the presence or absence of high glucose, 
a crucial pathogenic component of diabetes, in both car-
diomyocytes and endothelial cells. 
Hypoxia stimulated miR-210 expression in both cell 
types (Fig. 5B). In endothelial cells, the combination of 
hypoxia with high glucose slightly but significantly in-
creased this induction (Supplementary Table 4); when 
miR-199a and miR-199b levels were measured, we found 
that hypoxia decreased their expression in both cell 
types. This is in apparent contradiction with our obser-
vation in D-HF patients. However, we also found that 
high glucose strongly modified hypoxia response, since 
miR-199a and miR-199b downmodulation was prevented 
in endothelial cells (changes not significant) (Supple-
mentary Table 4) and inverted in cardiomyocytes: Fig. 5B 
shows that the combination of hypoxia and high glucose 
led to miR-199a and miR-199b induction. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>As a result of its high morbidity and mortality, HF has been 
the objective of many gene expression studies in the past 
few years. For the first time, we compared D-HF and ND-HF 
patients with similar functional impairment, identifying 
a subset of miRNAs that were specifically dysregulated in 
D-HF, in ND-HF, or in both. It is interesting that some of 
these miRNAs were previously identified as dysregulated 
in a variety of heart disease studies performed in humans, 
as summarized in Supplementary Table 5. One limitation of 
this study is the low number of female patients recruited, 
which did not allow us to determine the possible effects 
of sex. </p>

<p>Of interest, miR-216a significantly increased in both 
D-HF and ND-HF patients compared with CTR subjects, and 
although miR-216a has been found to be induced in 
senescent-cultured endothelial cells (31), this is the first time 
that miR-216a overexpression has been related to human 
HF. Accordingly, several miR-216a-predicted targets (Sup-
plementary Fig. 3) are involved in heart diseases. PDE4D, 
an miR-216a-predicted target downmodulated in HF pa-
tients, is one of the isoforms of the enzyme that hydrolyzes 
and inactivates cAMP and finely tunes cAMP levels in 
different cardiomyocyte subcellular compartments. In-
activation of PDE4D potentiates epinephrine-evoked (32) 
or exercise-induced arrhythmias in mice and the deve-
lopment of cardiomyopathy, increasing mortality after 
cardiac infarction (33). Another miR-216a target is CAV2, 
a member of the caveolin family of scaffolding proteins, </p>

<p>FIG. 3. miR-34b, miR-34c, miR-210, miR-199b, and miR-223 are deregu-
lated in the border zone (BZ) of both D-HF and ND-HF patients. miRNAs 
deregulated comparing ND-HF with D-HF in the myocardial portion re-
mote from the infarction region (REM) were measured in the BZ as well. 
The top panel shows a heat map representing the average values 
expressed using a log 2 scale (-DDCt), where green and red colors in-
dicate down-or upregulation, respectively. </p>

<p>FIG. 4. A-C: Validation by qRT-PCR of miRNA predicted targets. We 
measured the mRNA expression of selected miRNA predicted targets 
(34 mRNAs), and modulation of the indicated miRNA predicted targets 
was validated in the relevant patient groups. The modulation of the 
corresponding targeting miRNA is also shown. ND-HF (n = 16), D-HF 
(n = 6), and CTR (n = 15). *P £ 0.05, **P £ 0.01, ***P £ 0.001. </p>

<p>miRNA DYSREGULATION IN DIABETIC HF PATIENTS </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, JUNE 2012 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>which regulates signal transduction pathways and lipid 
metabolism. Loss of caveolin expression results in the 
activation of a program of progressive hypertrophy in 
cardiac myocytes, and their deletion results in severe 
cardiomyopathy (34). Thus, the inhibitory activity of miR-
216a on the expression of these transcripts could be del-
eterious for the cardiac activity. Moreover, ventricular 
myocytes from the infarcted myocardium overexpress 
TGF-b protein and mRNA (35), and TGF-b is particularly 
overexpressed in myocardium during transition from sta-
ble hypertrophy to HF (29). We found that TGF-b induced 
miR-216a expression increase in endothelial cells. In view 
of these findings, the release of TGF-b from myocytes after 
infarction and/or during transition to HF may be the cause 
for the miR-216a expression increase in HF patients. 
We found that the expression of six miRNAs (miR-34b, 
miR-34c, miR-199b, miR-210, miR-223, and miR-650) changed 
specifically in the failing myocardium of diabetic patients. It 
is intriguing that most of these miRNAs also were similarly 
deregulated in ND-HF patients when the border zone was 
analyzed, suggesting a link with tissue damage. 
Indeed, we previously showed that miR-34c was induced 
after acute ischemic damage (36), and the upregulation of 
miR-34b was also found in end-stage HF patients by Thum </p>

<p>et al. (18), who, however, did not stratify patients for 
diabetes. miR-34b and miR-34c belong to an evolutionary 
conserved miRNA family that plays a fundamental role in 
the p53 tumor suppressor network (37). Since hyperglyce-
mia promotes p53-dependent apoptosis (38), it is tempting 
to speculate that the p53/miR-34 axis may be involved in 
a hyperglycemia-induced death pathway. 
We also found that miR-223 levels were sharply decreased 
in the failing myocardium. While further studies are needed, 
miR-223 downmodulation likely represents a compensatory 
adaptive mechanism, since its decrease is less evident both in 
the remote zone of D-HF patients and in the border zone of 
ND-HF patients. In keeping with our data, Lu et al. (39) found 
that miR-223 levels were increased in the myocardium of di-
abetic patients in the absence of concomitant myocardial in-
farction, indicating that diabetes-associated miR-223 induction 
might, at least in part, counteract miR-223 decrease triggered 
by other stimuli. Likewise, van Rooij et al. (40) reported that 
miR-223 is increased in end-stage ischemic cardiomyopathy, 
suggesting that miR-233 downmodulation may represent an 
adaptive mechanism lost in end-stage patients. 
We also demonstrated that miR-199 is upregulated in the 
diabetic failing heart. Of interest, da Costa Martins et al. 
(41) found that miR-199b was activated by a calcineurin/ 
nuclear factor of activated T cells pathway and that its 
overexpression in mice caused a significant left ventricular 
fibrosis and HF (41). When miR-199a and miR-199b levels 
were examined in cultured cardiomyocytes and endothe-
lial cells, the levels were decreased by hypoxia as expected 
(26,42). However, the concomitant stimulus of high glucose 
prevented this decrease, and miR-199a and miR-199b levels 
were actually induced in cardiomyocytes exposed to hyp-
oxia and high glucose. Since nuclear factor of activated T 
cells acts as a glucose sensor in smooth muscle cells (43), 
one can hypothesize that the same mechanism also may be 
at work in D-HF patients. 
There is evidence that diabetic hearts have a compro-
mised hypoxia signaling pathway (44). Indeed, in the 
healthy heart, responses to reductions in cellular O 2 con-
centrations are conveyed mostly by the transcription factor 
family HIF (45). The HIF pathway is inactive in the presence 
of physiological levels of O 2 and is activated in hypoxia, 
thereby upregulating a gene expression program facilitating 
O 2 -independent ATP synthesis. 
IPA analysis of the transcriptomic changes observed in 
D-HF patients identified the HIF signaling pathway as sig-
nificantly deregulated. Indeed, HIF-dependent genes and 
miRNAs were induced in the remote, noninfarcted myo-
cardium of D-HF patients. These data are in keeping with 
previous evidence of HIF mRNA and HIF-pathway induction 
in the nonischemic myocardium observed in rat diabetic 
models of myocardial infarction (46) and, more general, 
with a pseudohypoxia metabolic state induced by hyper-
glycemia (47). It is also worth noting that while steady-state 
HIF levels are increased in diabetic subjects, several reports 
exist of impaired HIF induction by hypoxia, leading to an 
overall inhibition of HIF-dependent hypoxic response in 
diabetic patients (44,48). 
Among different potential HIF activation mechanisms in 
D-HF patients, increased oxidative stress is a likely candi-
date. Indeed, reactive oxygen species can induce the HIF/ 
HIF pathway (45), and increased oxidative stress levels are 
a hallmark of diabetes (49). 
Accordingly, we found that oxidative stress and free rad-
ical scavenging functions were associated with the genes 
targeted by the miRNA deregulated in D-HF. Paradoxically, </p>

<p>TABLE 3 
IPA analysis of mRNA class comparison and mRNA/miR 
interaction </p>

<p>Score 
P value </p>

<p>mRNA class comparison 
Associated network functions 
Cardiovascular system development 
and function 
28 
Biological functions 
Cellular development 
4.0E-07 
Cell morphology 
5.1E-07 
Cellular growth and proliferation 
2.9E-05 
Cardiovascular system development 
and function 
2.6E-07 
Canonical pathways 
Notch signaling 
3.5E-05 
Toxic lists 
HIF signaling 
1.1E-03 
Decreased transmembrane potential 
of mitochondria membrane 
2.2E-02 </p>

<p>mRNA/miR interaction 
Associated network functions 
Carbohydrate metabolism 
47 
Cellular assembly and organization, 
cellular function 
23 
Developmental disorder, gene 
expression 
23 
Biological functions 
Cardiovascular disease 
7.0E-04 
Cell signaling 
6.2E-04 
Free radical scavenging 
5.5E-03 
Cardiovascular system development 
and function 
6.7E-04 
Toxic functions 
Cardiac damage 
5.5E-03 
Cardiac dysfunction 
8.3E-03 
Cardiac fibrosis 
1.1E-02 
HF 
4.5E-02 
Toxic lists 
Oxidative stress 
3.9E-02 </p>

<p>S. GRECO AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, JUNE 2012 </p>

<p>
increased oxidative stress may also contribute to the damp-
ening of HIF activation after ischemia (50). In this respect, 
PARK7, a predicted miR-210 target downregulated in HF 
diabetic patients and a ubiquitous redox-responsive cyto-
protective protein (51), may be particularly important. 
Among the multitude of genes modulated by HIF-1a, 
miR-210 can be considered a "master" miRNA of hypoxic 
response (26). It is not clear whether miR-210 activation in 
the noninfarcted myocardial region represents an adaptive 
or a maladaptive mechanism. PARK7 targeting suggests 
that miR-210 induction may be detrimental. However, we 
and others have found that miR-210 protected endothelial 
cells and cardiomyocytes from apoptosis (25,52,53), high-
lighting a possible protective role of miR-210 in D-HF. 
Thus, while the role played by the HIF/HIF pathway in 
diabetic patients needs further investigation, it seems clear 
that HIF-dependent response to hypoxia is disrupted in the 
failing heart of diabetic patients. 
In conclusion, HF in patients with or without diabetes is 
a result of the concomitant cross-talk between various del-
eterious and compensatory signaling pathways. The balance 
and the interaction between these two dynamic forces ulti-
mately determine how the pathology will evolve. We iden-
tified a subset of miRNAs that are specifically dysregulated 
in D-HF. Gene expression analysis strongly implicated them 
in the pathogenetic disease mechanisms. Future investiga-
tions of the deregulated miRNA actions and functions will </p>

<p>substantially improve our understanding of diabetic cardiac 
and vascular complications. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by Ministero della Salute. 
No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article 
were reported. 
S.G. designed and performed most experiments and wrote 
the manuscript. P.F. and D.A. contributed to bioinformatic 
analysis. S.C., M.D.D., A.M., and L.M. enrolled and character-
ized patients and harvested biopsies. Y.D. and M.C.C. contrib-
uted to discussion. F.M. designed the experiments and wrote 
the manuscript. All authors reviewed the manuscript. F.M. is 
the guarantor of this work and, as such, had full access to all 
of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the 
integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. 
Part of this study was presented as an oral communica-
tion at the European Society of Cardiology Congress, Paris, 
France, 27-31 August 2011. 
The authors thank Dr. Daniele Catalucci, Institute of 
Biomedical Technologies, National Research Council, Milan, 
Italy, for his help in cardiomyocyte isolation and Mauro 
Helmer-Citterich, Istituto Dermopatico dell'Immacolata 
IRCCS, and Lucia Cicchillitti, IRCCS Policlinico San 
Donato, for their contribution to Affymetrix gene expression 
analysis. </p>

<p>FIG. 5. HIF pathway activation in D-HF patients and miR-199a, miR-199b, and miR-210 regulation by hypoxia (HYP) and high glucose (HG) in vitro. 
A: mRNA expression level of the HIF family and HIF target genes were assayed by qRT-PCR in D-HF (n = 6) and ND-HF (n = 16) samples. *P £ 0.05, 
**P £ 0.01. B: Neonatal mouse cardiomyocytes (nCMs) and HCAECs were cultured in HYP (1% O 2 ), in HG (25 mmol/L), in HG followed by HYP (HG 
+HYP), or in normoxic and iso-osmotic control conditions. Next, total RNA was extracted and miR-199a, miR-199b, and miR-210 levels were 
assayed. Data are expressed using a log 2 scale (-DDCt) by a heat map, where green and red colors indicate down-or upregulation, respectively. As 
a reference, miR-199a, miR-199b, and miR-210 levels observed in D-HF and ND-HF heart biopsies are indicated as well. </p>

<p>miRNA DYSREGULATION IN DIABETIC HF PATIENTS </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, JUNE 2012 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>



<p>S. GRECO AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, JUNE 2012 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>