<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3587895" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:28+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: The Motricity Index was used to measure strength in upper and lower extremities after stroke. 
The weighted score based on the ordinal 6 point scale of Medical Research Council was used to measure maxi-
mal isometric muscle strength. There is dearth of articles dealing with the reliability of this method. Therefore, 
the aim of this study was to determine the test retest reliability of Motricity Index strength assessments for paret-
ic lower limb in 20 chronic stroke patients with one week interval. 
Methods: In a cross sectional study, intrarater reliability of lower extremity Motricity Index strength assess-
ments with one week interval were measured. 
Result: The <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">18</rs> was used for analysis of data. Two-way random-consistency model of ICC was used for 
assessment of test-retest reliability. The ICC values showed high reliability of strength measurement of 
Motricity Index (ICC=0.93). 
Conclusion: The Motricity Index can be a reliable instrument for measuring the strength of involved lower ex-
tremity when assessment is done by one rater following chronic stroke. </p>

<p>Keywords: Reliability, Motricity Index, Hemiparesis, Chronic stroke. 
________________________________________________________________________________________ </p>

<p>Introduction 
The most important motor deficit after 
stroke is the paresis of the affected side, 
contralateral to vascular lesion in the brain 
(1). Muscle weakness, as one of the nega-
tive features of upper motor neuron syn-
drome is characterized by the loss of ability 
to generate normal levels of muscle force. It 
is also associated with physiological chang-
es as abnormal force coupling with agonists 
and antagonists and abnormal muscle acti-
vation patterns. Due to such deficits the ca-
pacity of the paretic lower limb to maintain 
normal functions such as balance, initiation </p>

<p>and control of movement would decrease 
(2). However, weakness happens on the 
ipsilateral side as early as one week follow-
ing stroke. Post stroke weakness and its ac-
companying motor impairments result in 
diminished performance of daily living and 
loss of independence (3). Therefore, it is 
important for clinicians to identify 
hemiparetic weakness. In other words, there 
is a need to have a reliable tool to assess 
muscle strength in the clinical basis. 
Among many experimental and clinical 
tools such as isokinetic dynamometer and 
handheld dynamometer which are expen-
sive and time consuming for measuring </p>

<p>Reliability of lower extremity Motricity index </p>



<p>Table 1. The lower extremity scores for muscle strength using the Motricity index. 
Quality of muscle contraction 
Motricity scores 
MRC Grade 
No Movement 
0 
0 
Palpable contraction in muscle, but No 
Movement </p>

<p>9 
1 </p>

<p>Visible Movement, but not full range 
against Gravity </p>

<p>14 
2 </p>

<p>Full range of Movement against Gravity, 
but not against resistance </p>

<p>19 
3 </p>

<p>Full Movement against gravity, but 
weaker than the other side </p>

<p>25 
4 </p>

<p>Normal Power 
33 
5 </p>

<p>Demeurisse (1990)   muscle force, Motricity Index is a more fea-
sible measure that can demonstrate the 
overall patients' impairment. It is a simple, 
brief measure of general motor function that 
can predict the mobility outcomes post-
stroke (4). In 1980, Demeurisse et al devel-
oped a new method to assess isometric 
muscle strength on post stroke hemiparesis. 
They studied thirty one movements at prox-
imal, middle and distal joints of upper and 
lower extremities. They decided to reduce 
many movements to just one essential 
movement at each joint that was the repre-
sentative of general strength at that joint. In 
upper extremity the movements were 
shoulder abduction, elbow flexion and 
pinch grip. In lower limb the three move-
ments were hip flexion, knee extension and 
ankle dorsiflexion (4). In order to grade 
muscle force, they used the ordinal six 
points scale of Medical Research Council 
(5). The MRC grades were converted into 
modified weighted scores according to pa-
tients' difficulty in progressing from one 
grade to the next (Table1). The three scores 
were summed and added by one, and total 
score was ranged from 0 (complete paresis) 
to 100 (normal strength). 
Collen et al (1990) assessed the inter 
rater reliability of Motricity Index. Their 
results implicated reliability and sensitivity 
of motricity index (6). In another study, 
they investigated the reliability of six im-
pairment measures and disability of 
Motricity Index (leg score) in 25 patients 
suffered from a chronic stroke. Quantifica-
tion was done by 3 therapists on 3 sessions 
over 5 weeks. All six measures were relia-</p>

<p>ble in statistical terms (7). It seemed that 
there is dearth of articles dealing with the 
reliability of strength measurement with 
Motricity Index. Therefore, the purpose of 
this study was to estimate the test-retest re-
liability of Motricity Index strength meas-
urement in the affected lower limb muscles 
in two sessions over one week in chronic 
stroke patients. </p>

<p>Methods 
In a cross sectional-analytical study, 20 
subjects (10 female and10 male) with age 
range of 37 to 76 years and post stroke du-
ration of 3 months to 4 years who could fol-
low instructions, were participated in this 
study. All of them had referred to neurolog-
ical Physical therapy Clinic in Rehabilita-
tion Faculty of Tehran University of Medi-
cal Sciences from May to July of 2011. 
Those who had the experience of articular 
pain as a result of arthrosis, surgery or 
trauma on their lower extremity were ex-
cluded. Initially, a written consent was ob-
tained from each participant. Then they be-
came familiar with the procedure. One 
physical therapist assessed the strength of 
hip flexor, knee extensor and ankle 
dorsiflexor muscles in two sessions over 
one week. All the assessments were per-
formed at the same time of day on two ses-
sions. The rater was blind to total Motricity 
Index score and to data analysis on two ses-
sions conducted with someone else. It took 
less than five minutes to perform Motricity 
Index. The participants were placed in a 
chair that had back support. Hip flexion was 
tested with the hip joint with a 90 ̊ bent. The </p>

<p>M. Fayazi, et al. </p>



<p>MJIRI, Vol. 26, No. 1, Feb 2012, pp. 27-30 </p>

<p>Table 2. Interpretation of statistical value for reli-
ability testing. 
Strength of 
agreement </p>

<p>Statistical value </p>

<p>Poor 
Fair 
Moderate 
Good 
Very good </p>

<p>0/2 &lt; </p>

<p>0/21-0/40 
0/41-0/60 
0/61-0/80 
0/81-1 </p>

<p>Paul Brennan(1992) </p>

<p>Table 3. Subject baseline characteristics of 20 
chronic stroke patients </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Subject (n= 20) Freq. (%) 
Age (Years) 
Mean ± SD 
Range 
Gender 
Male 
Female 
Type of Stroke 
Ischemic 
Hemorrhagic 
Side of involvement 
Right 
Left 
Duration of illness (months) 
Mean ± SD 
Range </p>

<p>55.58±13.45 
37-76 </p>

<p>10 
10 </p>

<p>17 
3 </p>

<p>8 
12 </p>

<p>19.41±17.37 
3 -48 </p>

<p>50 
50 </p>

<p>85 
15 </p>

<p>40 
60 </p>

<p>Table 4. Descriptive values for Motricity Index value . </p>

<p>Std. Deviation 
Mean 
Variable 
17.683 
58.20 
Motricity Index 
(first session) 
19.632 
56.60 
Motricity Index 
(second session) </p>

<p>Table 5. Test-retest reliability of Motricity Index on the involved side of 20 chronic stroke patients. </p>

<p>Significance level </p>

<p>SEM 
95% CI 
ICC Value 
Motricity Index 
0.000 
4.66 
0.84 -0.97 
0.93 </p>

<p>rater instructed the patients to bring the 
knee towards the chin, while she monitored 
the contraction of hip flexors by placing her 
hand on the anterior of the distal of thigh. 
Then the therapist resisted the movement. 
According to the quality of muscle contrac-
tion the score was recorded. Rater was also 
aware of any trick motion such as leaning 
the back during the movement by placing 
one hand on their back. The knee extension 
was examined while it was bent at 90 ̊ flex-
ion with the unsupported foot, followed by 
the examiner asked the subjects to extend 
the knee and touch her hand which was held 
at the level of the knee. Meanwhile, she 
monitored the contraction of quadriceps 
with the other hand which gave resistance 
to movement. Then the score was recorded. 
Furthermore, the movement of dorsiflexion 
was assessed as the ankle relaxed in a plan-
tar flexed position, then the examiner 
placed her hand on the forefoot, while the 
patient was asked to dorsiflex the foot, the 
examiner palpated and also resisted the con-
traction of tibialis anterior with the other 
hand on the forefoot (5). Finally, all three 
scores were summed and the Motricity In-
dex for lower extremity was calculated. Re-
test was done with one week interval, and 
hand placement was identical on two ses-
sions. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis 
Data analysis was done using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> v. 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">18</rs>. Two way random-consistency model of 
ICC (2,1) was used for assessment of test-
retest reliability. Table 2 demonstrated the 
suggested interpretation of statistical value 
for reliability testing (8). </p>

<p>Results 
Table 3 is shown the characteristics of all 
20 participants and descriptive statistics 
shown in Table 4. Two-way random-
consistency model of ICC was used for as-</p>

<p>sessment of test-retest reliability. As Table 
5 is indicated, all scores of Motricity Index 
in lower limbs of 20 patients on two ses-
sions assessments were strongly reliable(8). </p>

<p>Discussion 
Although reliability of strength assess-
ments in neurologic conditions have been 
suspected by many researchers, our results 
showed that Motricity Index has high relia-
bility on two session assessment by one 
rater. Despite the fact that manual muscle 
testing is the most common approach in 
clinical assessment, traditional manual </p>

<p>Reliability of lower extremity Motricity index </p>



<p>muscle testing (MMT) could not be a valid 
indicator of muscle strength in neurologic 
patients in acute phase due to presence of 
strong spasticity and synergistic movement 
pattern and loss of selective contractions. In 
chronic stage of neurologic conditions 
when some improvement had occurred in 
motor control, MMT could provide precise 
information about muscle strength (9). 
Many factors affect on strength evaluations 
by manual muscle testing in neurologic pa-
tients such as position changes, altered 
muscle tone, variations in producing force 
in rater's hand over two sessions. Despite 
all these confounding factors, Motricity In-
dex based on manual testing of strength, 
could provide the overall estimation of low-
er extremity strength. In addition, it seemed 
that this index was a better representative of 
gross changes of motor recovery than MMT 
overtime, because it used the weighted 
scores. The result of this study was further 
supported by the Collen et al (r=0.87)(6), 
but with the difference that we investigated 
the reproducibility of strength measures by 
one rater because using another rater intro-
duced another source of variation while 
Collen et al measured interrater reliability 
that could be expected to reduce correla-
tions between tests. These studies mainly 
focused on "break test" in which the exam-
iner pushes against the subject maximal ef-
fort to hold the position. Accordingly the 
results of these studies could not be gener-
alized to ones which incorporated "make 
test" like handheld dynamometry that was 
held stationary while the patients exerted 
the maximal force required. Bohannon 
(2000) found that Motricity Index in the 
comparison with the dynamometer, have 
high criterion validity. Hence, he suggested 
that in the absence of such tools, clinicians 
could implement this index for strength 
testing of lower extremity (10). Therefore it 
seemed that the Motricity Index is a simple 
and reliable measure of muscle strength 
post stroke that can be applied readily and </p>

<p>does not need any especial equipment and 
training. Further reliability testing in upper 
extremity is recommended. </p>

<p>Conclusion 
Motricity Index strength assessments for 
involved lower extremity in chronic stroke 
can be highly reliable when assessment is 
done by one rater following chronic stroke. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments 
This study was a part of MS thesis sup-
ported by Tehran University of Medical 
Sciences, grant no. p/26/54/317. We thank 
all the volunteers that participated in this 
study. </p>



</text></tei>