<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3905558" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: The direct effect of some opioids on immune cells has been demonstrated. The aim of this study 
was to assess the apoptotic effect of opium on Jurkat T lymphocyte cells. </p>

<p>Methods: Different concentrations of opium (2.86 × 10 -3 to 2.86 × 10 -11 g/ml) were added to 24-well plates 
containing 5 × 10 5 Jurkat cells. Apoptotic events were assessed after 6, 24, and 72 hours by flow-cytometric 
detection of surface phosphatidylserine. </p>

<p>Findings: Significant differences in apoptosis of Jurkat cells were seen at 24 and 72 hours in different 
concentrations of opium (P &lt; 0.05). After 72 hours, significant increase in necrosis of Jurkat cells was seen in 
opium concentration of 2.85 × 10 -3 g/ml compared to cells without opium (control) (P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Conclusion: These results showed that opium directly increases apoptosis and necrosis of T lymphocytes. 
This effect may play a role in immune dysfunction in opium addicts. </p>

<p>Keywords: Opium, Apoptosis, Necrosis, Jurkat cells </p>

<p>Citation: Igder S, Asadikaram GR, Sheykholeslam F, Sayadi AR, Mahmoodi M, Kazemi Arababadi M, 
et al. Opium Induces Apoptosis in Jurkat Cells. Addict Health 2013; 5(1-2): 27-34. </p>

<p>Received: 29.07.2012 
Accepted: 16.11.2012 </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Opium Induces Jurkat Cell Apoptosis </p>

<p>Igder et al. </p>

<p>28 
Addict Health, Winter &amp; Spring 2013; Vol 5, No 1-2 </p>

<p>http://ahj.kmu.ac.ir, 4 April </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Programmed cell death or apoptosis is a natural 
process for removing damaged and aged cells. 1 
Apoptosis is an essential physiological process in 
differentiation and development of normal brain. 
It also has an important role in a number of 
neurodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer's 
and Parkinson's disease. 2 Various internal and 
external stimuli can result in apoptosis. 1 Different 
studies have already been performed about the 
apoptotic cell death due to many chemical, 
synthetic, and natural compounds. The apoptotic 
effects of some alkaloids such as morphine, 
heroine, codeine, noscapine, and papaverine have 
been demonstrated. 3 Opium includes 8-17% 
morphine, 1-10% noscapine, 0.5-1.5% papaverine, 
and 0.7-5% codeine. 4 Our previous study showed 
that chronic opium treatment can induce brain 
and liver cell apoptosis in rats. It was, however, 
the only report on apoptotic effects of opium. 1 
It has been reported that opiate addicts are 
vulnerable to common infections. 5 Morphine 
induces apoptotic pathways in Jurkat cells. 6 In 
addition, chronic use of morphine can inhibit the 
immune system by reducing both the spleen and 
inguinal lymph node volume, and white blood 
cells (B and T lymphocytes and plasmablasts). 7 
Moreover, it has been reported that opioids 
modulate antibody and cytokine secretion and 
decrease the proliferation rate of multiple myeloma 
cells through opioid receptor activation. 8 The 
alteration of peripheral blood T and B lymphocyte 
proliferative responses were seen in heroin 
addicts. 9 According to another study, clinical 
concentration of morphine (10 -8 M) induces 
apoptosis in human leukemia (HL-60) and human 
alveolar epithelial (A549) cell lines and necrosis in 
breast cancer (Michigan Cancer Foundation-7 or 
MCF7) cell line. 10 Contrary to the above results, 
Ohara et al. concluded that morphine does not 
induce apoptosis in lymphocytes. 11 
Noscapine, an opium derivative, induces 
apoptosis via increasing the activity of caspase 
-2, -3, -6, -8 and -9 and deoxyribonucleic acid 
(DNA) fragmentation in human myeloid 
leukemia cells (HL-60 cell line). 12 Apoptotic effect 
of papaverine, another opium derivative, on 
mouse aortic smooth muscle cells and coronary 
endothelial cells has also been recognized. 13 
Codeine decreases proliferation, genotoxicity, and </p>

<p>apoptosis in Ramos cells. 14 
However, opium is a mixture of 20 different 
alkaloids 15 and 70 various compounds. 16 Its effects 
on cell functions can hence be different from pure 
morphine, noscapine, codeine, and papaverine. 
Since most of the studies on morphine and other 
opium derivatives have been performed on 
specific cells in culture medium, we decided to 
investigate the apoptotic effect of opium on Jurkat 
cells, as a T lymphocyte model, to evaluate the 
effects of opium on immune cells. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Cell culture 
Jurkat cells (purchased from Iran Pasteur 
Institute, Tehran, Iran) were cultured in Roswell 
Park Memorial Institute (RPMI) 1640 medium 
(Invitrogen Co., Germany) supplemented with 
10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) (Invitrogen Co., 
Germany), 50 U/ml penicillin (Sigma-Aldrich Co., 
Germany) 
and 
50 
mg/ml 
streptomycin 
(Sigma-Aldrich Co., Germany). </p>

<p>Adding opium to culture medium 
Opium was provided by anti-drugs section of 
Kerman Police (Iran). Based on their information, 
the origin of opium was Helmand in Afghanistan. 
Gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) 
showed more than 30% of the opium to consist of 
alkaloids. Morphine (16%), codeine (5.5%), 
thebaine (4.4%), and papaverine (3.2%) were the 
most abundant alkaloids. The rest of the provided 
opium contained non-alkaloid organic and non-
organic substances from which 13.5% was water 
(moisture). 17 
The stock solution of opium (2.86 g/ml) was 
diluted to concentrations of 2.86 × 10 -1 , 2.86 × 10 -3 , 
2.86 × 10 -5 , 2.86 × 10 -7 , 2.86 × 10 -9 , and 2.86 × 10 -11 
g/ml in PRMI1640 medium. These calculations 
were based on different effective concentrations of 
morphine on Jurkat cells 18 and the assumption 
that opium contains 16% morphine. </p>

<p>Evaluating Jurkat cell survival 
The 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl) -2,5-diphenyl 
tetrazolium bromide (MTT) assay was used to 
determine the number of viable cells in culture. In 
this method, soluble salt of tetrazolium (yellow 
color) changes to insoluble colorful compound of 
formazan (blue color) as a result of reduction by 
succinate dehydrogenase in the mitochondria of </p>

<p>Opium Induces Jurkat Cell Apoptosis </p>

<p>Igder et al. </p>

<p>Addict Health, Winter &amp; Spring 2013; Vol 5, No 1-2 </p>

<p>
http://ahj.kmu.ac.ir, 4 April </p>

<p>living active cells. 19 
Equal numbers (100,000 cells/well) of Jurkat 
cells were seeded in 96 well plates and exposed to 
different concentrations of opium (2.86 × 10 -1 , 2.86 
× 10 -3 , 2.86 × 10 -5 , 2.86 × 10 -7 , 2.86 × 10 -9 , and 
2.86 × 10 -11 g/ml) (three wells for each 
concentration). The plates were incubated at 37ºC 
in a humidified incubator containing 95% oxygen 
and 5% carbon dioxide for 4, 6, and 24 hours. At 
the end of each incubation time, the medium was 
removed and 20 µl MTT (5 mg/ml) was added to 
each well. The wells were then incubated at 37ºC 
for 4 hours. Afterward, 100 µl of 0.04 mol/l 
hydrochloric acid (HCL) in isopropanol (Merck 
Co., Germany) was added to each well and optical 
density (OD) was read on an enzyme linked 
immunosorbent 
assay 
(ELISA) 
reader 
(Multiskan-MS, Germany) using test wavelength 
of 570 nm and reference wavelength of 630 nm. </p>

<p>Flow cytometry analysis of apoptosis induction 
During the primary stages of apoptosis, 
phosphatidylserine, normally found in the inner 
surface of plasma membrane, transfers to the 
extracellular surface due to the disturbance of 
adenosine 
triphosphate 
(ATP)-dependent 
translocase enzyme or activation of other 
enzymatic systems such as scramblase. Location 
of phosphatidylserine on extracellular surface is a 
kind of normal signal causing recognition and 
phagocytosis of apoptotic cells by macrophages 
and neighboring cells. Annexin V is an 
anticoagulant protein with molecular weight of 35 
kDa and high affinity for binding to 
phosphatidylserine in the presence of calcium ion 
(Ca +2 ). A combination of annexin V and 
propidium iodide is used in the staining of cells 
with cellular membrane loss. Annexin V 
conjugates with fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC) 
are used widely in flow cytometry studies of 
apoptosis. In the present study, equal numbers 
(500,000 cells/well) of Jurkat cells were grown in 
24-well plates containing RPMI 10% FCS with 
different concentrations of opium (2.86×10 -11 to 
2.86×10 -3 g/ml) and time periods as described 
above. At the end of incubation time, 100,000 cells 
were transferred into each microtube and 
centrifuged at 1000 rounds per minute for 10 
minutes. After the removal of the surface 
medium, 500 µl binding buffer (1x) (Biovision Co., 
UK), 5 µl annexin V (Biovision Co., UK), and 5 µl </p>

<p>propidium iodide (Biovision Co., UK) were added 
to the cells and incubated at the room temperature 
for 10 minutes. Labeled samples were then read 
by flow cytometry (FACSCalibur, BD Biosciences, 
New Jersey, USA). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
The results were presented as mean ± standard 
errors (SE). Analysis was performed by <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> for 
Windows <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">16.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). 
One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed 
by Bonferroni post-hoc tests were performed to 
compare 
differences 
between 
various 
concentrations at each time point. For comparison 
of response to different concentrations at different 
times, repeated measure ANOVA with Bonferroni 
post-hoc test was used. P values less than 0.05 
were considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Effects of opium on cell survival in Jurkat cell line 
As it is shown in figure 1, after 4 hours, opium at 
high (2.86 × 10 -1 and 2.86 × 10 -3 g/ml), moderate 
(2.86 × 10 -5 g/ml), and low (2.86 × 10 -11 g/ml) 
concentrations decreased cell survival in 
comparison to cells without opium (control cells) 
(P &lt; 0.05). At the 24 th hour, only moderate 
concentration of opium (2.86 × 10 -5 g/ml) 
decreased cell survival compared to the control. </p>

<p>Effects of opium on apoptosis of Jurkat cell line 
using annexin V 
The apoptotic effects of opium on Jurkat cells are 
shown in figure 2. There were significant 
differences between different concentrations of 
opium at the 24 th and 72 nd hours. Apoptosis of 
Jurkat cells in opium concentrations of 2.85 × 10 -11 
to 2.86 × 10 -3 g/ml was different at the 6 th , 24 th , 
and 72 nd hours. After 24 hours, all concentrations 
of opium induced apoptosis in Jurkat cells 
compared to the control. In addition, opium 
concentration of 2.86 × 10 -7 g/ml caused higher 
apoptosis compared to the control at the 72 nd hour 
(P &lt; 0.05) (Figure 2). 
After 72 hours, the opium concentration of 
2.86 × 10 -3 g/ml increased necrosis in comparison 
to the control (P &lt; 0.01) (Figure 3). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The results of the present study showed reductions 
in cell survival due to increased opium in the </p>

<p>Opium Induces Jurkat Cell Apoptosis </p>

<p>Igder et al. </p>

<p> 
Addict Health, Winter &amp; Spring 2013; Vol 5, No 1-2 </p>

<p>http://ahj.kmu.ac.ir, 4 April </p>

<p>Figure 1. The percent of Jurkat cells viability at different concentrations of opium and different time intervals 
MTT: 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyl tetrazolium bromide </p>

<p>Figure 2. The percent of Jurkat cells apoptosis at different concentrations of opium and different time intervals </p>

<p>Figure 3. The percent of Jurkat cells necrosis at different concentrations of opium and different time intervals </p>

<p>a b </p>

<p>e 
d </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>4 
hours 
6 
hours 
24 
hours </p>

<p>MTT reduction (% of control ) </p>

<p>Time (hours) </p>

<p>control 
2.86×10-1gr/ml </p>

<p>2.86 
× 
10 
-
3 
gr/ml 
2.86 
× 
10 
-
5 
gr/ml 
2.86 
× 
10 
-
7 
gr/ml 
2.86 
× 
10 
-
9 
gr/ml 
2.86 
× 
10 
-
11 
gr/ml </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>hours 4 
hours 6 
hours 24 </p>

<p>Control 
2.86  10 -1 g/ml 
2.86  10 -3 g/ml 
2.86  10 -5 g/ml 
2.86  10 -7 g/ml 
2.86  10 -9 g/ml 
2.86  10 -11 g/ml </p>

<p>a b c d e f </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>6 
hours 
24 
hours 
72 
hours </p>

<p>Apoptotic cells (Percent) </p>

<p>Time </p>

<p>control 
2.86 
× 
10 
-
3 
g/ml 
2.86 
× 
10 
-
5 
g/ml 
2.86 
× 
10 
-
7 
g/ml 
2.86 
× 
10 
-
9 
g/ml 
2.86 
× 
10 
-
11 
g/ml </p>

<p>P = 0.13 </p>

<p>P = 0.01 
P = 0.02 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>hours 6 
hours 24 
hours 72 </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>2.86  10 -3 g/ml 
2.86  10 -5 g/ml </p>

<p>2.86  10 -7 g/ml </p>

<p>2.86  10 -9 g/ml 
2.86  10 -11 g/ml </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>6 
hours 
24 
hours 
72 
hours </p>

<p>Necrotic cells (Percent) </p>

<p>Time </p>

<p>control 
2.86 
× 
10 
-
3 
g/ml 
2.86 
× 
10 
-
5 
g/ml 
2.86 
× 
10 
-
7 
g/ml 
2.86 
× 
10 
-
9 
g/ml 
2.86 
× 
10 
-
11 
g/ml </p>

<p>P= 0.001 </p>

<p>P = 0.001 
P = 0.006 </p>

<p>a b c d e f </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>2.86  10 -3 g/ml </p>

<p>2.86  10 -5 g/ml </p>

<p>2.86  10 -7 g/ml </p>

<p>2.86  10 -9 g/ml </p>

<p>2.86  10 -11 g/ml </p>

<p>P = 0.13 </p>

<p>P = 0.01 
P = 0.02 </p>

<p>hours 6 
hours 24 
hours 72 </p>

<p>Opium Induces Jurkat Cell Apoptosis </p>

<p>Igder et al. </p>

<p>Addict Health, Winter &amp; Spring 2013; Vol 5, No 1-2 </p>

<p>
http://ahj.kmu.ac.ir, 4 April </p>

<p>culture medium. The apoptotic effects of various 
concentrations of opium on Jurkat cells were 
significantly different at 24 and 72 hours. 
Apoptosis of Jurkat cells in opium concentrations 
of 2.85 × 10 -3 to 2.86 × 10 -11 g/ml was significantly 
different at 6, 24, and 72 hours. 
Some people believe in therapeutic effects of 
opium in many disorders. 20 This is the main 
reason for their tendency toward drugs. 
According to the World Health Organization 
(WHO), 2.8% of Iranian adults are opium-
dependent. 21 In spite of the widespread and long 
history of opium consumption, studies in this 
regard have been very limited. Despite the 
existence of several reports about the effects of the 
most important components of opium including 
morphine, codeine, noscapine, and papaverine on 
programmed cell death in various tissues and 
cells, these studies have specifically focused on 
effects of one derivative. 6,12-14 
Morphine increases the synthesis of regulating 
pro-apoptotic proteins (e.g. P53 and Bax) in the 
exposed cells. 22 It also induces apoptosis in Jurkat 
cell line. 6 Previous research has emphasized on 
the role of morphine in increasing DNA 
degradation in human peripheral blood cells. 19-23 
It has been reported that morphine enhances 
apoptosis in murine macrophages 24 and reduces 
macrophages and B-cells in the spleen. 8 It has also 
been demonstrated that morphine induces 
macrophage apoptosis and thereby leads to 
bacterial infections in mice. 25 
However, long-term and short-term effects of 
morphine are different. 26 In a study about the 
effects of morphine on cell proliferation, it was 
claimed that morphine at concentrations higher 
than 10 µmol inhibits tumor cells proliferation. Its 
concentrations of above 500 µmol were found to 
induce apoptosis. 27 In contrast to many researchers 
who have shown morphine-induced apoptosis in 
various cells including lymphocytes, some others 
have indicated that morphine does not have 
apoptotic effects on lymphocytes. 11 Suppressive 
effects of morphine on lymphocyte apoptosis via 
blocking P53-mediated death signals have also 
been suggested. 28 
Apoptotic role of some other major derivatives 
of opium, such as noscapine and papaverine, has 
also been reported. One study showed that 
noscapine induces apoptosis through increasing 
the activity of caspase-2, -3, -6, -8 and -9 and DNA </p>

<p>fragmentation in human myeloid leukemia cells 
and HL-60 cell line. 12 Moreover, pharmacologic 
doses of noscapine induce apoptosis of tumor 
cells in breast, lung, colon, and ovarian cancers. 29 
It can act as an anti-tumor agent which arrests cell 
mitosis and induces apoptosis. Noscapine binds 
tubulin and alters its conformation. It arrests 
mitosis through affecting microtubules assembly 
in mammalian cells. 30 
Papaverine, which is commonly used in the 
treatment of spinal vascular spasm, induces 
apoptosis in endothelial cells and vascular smooth 
muscles. 13 Toxic effects of codeine on human 
cancer cells has been demonstrated in various 
studies. Codeine, at concentrations of 1-6 mM, 
dose-dependently decreases proliferation and 
causes genotoxicity and apoptosis in Ramos 
cells. 14 Codeinone, an oxidized derivative of 
codeine, dose-dependently induces apoptosis in 
HL-60 cell line through DNA fragmentation, 
cytochrome C release, and inducing caspase-3. 31,32 . 
Singhal et al. showed that morphine at 
concentrations of 10 -4 , 10 -6 , 10 -8 and 10 -10 M 
induces apoptosis in Jurkat cells after 24 and 48 
hours of incubation. 19 In another study, the same 
researchers concluded that morphine at 
concentrations of 10 -4 , 10 -6 , and 10 -8 M induces 
apoptosis in J774A cell line of mouse 
macrophages. 33 This finding is consistent with the 
results of the present study which showed opium 
to increase Jurkat cell line apoptosis at all 
concentrations at 24 hours. 
Ohara et al. reported that morphine at 
concentrations of 10 -4 , 10 -5 , 10 -6 , and 10 -8 M did not 
induce pathway apoptosis in lymphocytes at 3, 6, 
12, 24, and 48 hours. 11 We found contrasting 
results using opium concentrations of 2.86 × 10 -5 , 
2.86 × 10 -7 , 2.86 × 10 -9 , and 2.86 × 10 -11 g/ml at 
72 hours. Another study indicated that clinical 
concentration of morphine (10 -8 M) induces 
apoptosis in HL-60 and A549 cell lines and 
necrosis in MCF7 cell line. 12 We obtained the same 
results at opium concentration of 2.86 × 10 -3 g/ml 
at 6 hours and all concentrations at 24 hours. 
Moreover, opium concentration of 2.86 × 10 -5 
caused in similar results at 72 hours. 
According to the results of MTT test, we 
concluded that opium decreased cell survival in 
comparison to the control at 4 hours. At 
6 hours, some metabolic pathway will be 
activated by opium derivatives and hence the </p>

<p>Opium Induces Jurkat Cell Apoptosis </p>

<p>Igder et al. </p>

<p> 
Addict Health, Winter &amp; Spring 2013; Vol 5, No 1-2 </p>

<p>http://ahj.kmu.ac.ir, 4 April </p>

<p>reduction of MTT enhanced in spite of decreased 
survival of cells. In other word, after 6 hours, the 
apoptotic effects of opium derivatives are 
defeated by activating effects of some opium 
derivatives on succinate dehydrogenase (or other 
reducing enzymes). This process will in turn lead 
to reduction of MTT and formazan formation. 
However, after 24 hours, the apoptotic effects of 
opium derivatives will overcome the activation 
which had reduced MTT. Apparently, the precise 
mechanisms involved in these observations 
remain to be determined by future studies. 
All studies about the effects of opiates on 
immune and humoral immunity systems, 
including in vivo studies on experimental animals 
or in vitro studies on immune cells isolated from 
human and animals, agree on decreased number of 
activated T-lymphocytes as well as the percent of 
activated T-lymphocytes in the peripheral blood </p>

<p>of opiate-addicts. 5,34,35 Our findings confirmed 
these effects </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Overall, the results of the present study showed 
that opium has apoptotic as well as necrotic 
effects on Jurkat T-lymphocyte cells. Therefore, 
opiate-addicts are prone to infectious diseases. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>The Authors have no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This study was supported by grants from 
Rafsanjan University of Medical Sciences. Helpful 
scientific advices of Professor Hamid Najafipur 
are greatly appreciated. The authors confirm that 
there is no conflict of interest in this study. </p>



<p>Opium Induces Jurkat Cell Apoptosis </p>

<p>Igder et al. </p>

<p>Addict Health, Winter &amp; Spring 2013; Vol 5, No 1-2 </p>



<p>
Opium Induces Jurkat Cell Apoptosis </p>

<p>Igder et al. </p>

<p>1 
-
‫ﻛﺎرﺷﻨﺎﺳﻲ‬ ‫داﻧﺸﺠﻮي‬ 
‫رﻓﺴﻨﺠﺎن،‬ ‫ﭘﺰﺷﻜﻲ‬ ‫ﻋﻠﻮم‬ ‫داﻧﺸﮕﺎه‬ ‫ﺑﻴﻮﺷﻴﻤﻲ،‬ ‫ﮔﺮوه‬ ‫ارﺷﺪ،‬ 
‫ﻛﺮﻣﺎن‬ 
‫اﻳﺮان‬ ، 
2 
-
‫اﺳﺘﺎد،‬ 
‫ﻣﺮﻛﺰ‬ 
‫ﺗﺤﻘ‬ 
‫ﻴ‬ 
‫ﻘﺎت‬ 
‫ﻓ‬ 
‫ﻴ‬ 
‫ﺰ‬ 
‫ﻳ‬ 
‫ﻮﻟﻮژ‬ 
‫ي‬ 
‫و‬ 
‫ﮔﺮوه‬ 
‫ﺑ‬ 
‫ﻴ‬ 
‫ﻮﺷ‬ 
‫ﻴ‬ 
‫ﻤ‬ 
‫ﻲ،‬ 
‫اﻳﺮان‬ ‫ﻛﺮﻣﺎن،‬ ‫ﻛﺮﻣﺎن،‬ ‫ﭘﺰﺷﻜﻲ‬ ‫ﻋﻠﻮم‬ ‫داﻧﺸﮕﺎه‬ ‫ﭘﺰﺷﻜﻲ،‬ ‫داﻧﺸﻜﺪه‬ 
3 
-
‫اﺳﺘﺎد‬ 
‫ﻳ‬ 
‫ﺎر‬ 
، 
‫اﻧﺴﺘ‬ 
‫ﻴ‬ 
‫ﺘﻮ‬ 
‫ﭘﺎﺳﺘﻮر‬ 
‫ا‬ 
‫ﻳ‬ 
‫ﺮان‬ 
، 
‫ﺗﻬﺮان‬ 
، 
‫ا‬ 
‫ﻳ‬ 
‫ﺮان‬ 
4 
-
‫ﻣﺮﺑﻲ‬ 
، 
‫روا‬ ‫ﮔﺮوه‬ 
‫ن‬ 
‫ﭘﺰﺷﻜﻲ‬ 
‫رﻓﺴﻨﺠﺎن،‬ ‫ﭘﺰﺷﻜﻲ‬ ‫ﻋﻠﻮم‬ ‫داﻧﺸﮕﺎه‬ ‫ﭘﺰﺷﻜﻲ،‬ ‫داﻧﺸﻜﺪه‬ ، 
‫ﻛﺮﻣﺎن‬ 
‫اﻳﺮان‬ ، 
5 
-
‫اﺳﺘﺎد‬ 
، 
‫ﺑﻴﻮﺷﻴﻤﻲ‬ ‫ﮔﺮوه‬ 
‫رﻓﺴﻨﺠﺎن،‬ ‫ﭘﺰﺷﻜﻲ‬ ‫ﻋﻠﻮم‬ ‫داﻧﺸﮕﺎه‬ ‫ﭘﺰﺷﻜﻲ،‬ ‫داﻧﺸﻜﺪه‬ ، 
‫ﻛﺮﻣﺎن‬ 
‫اﻳﺮان‬ ، 
6 
-
‫اﻳﻤﻮﻧﻮﻟﻮژي،‬ ‫ﮔﺮوه‬ ‫اﺳﺘﺎدﻳﺎر،‬ 
‫رﻓﺴﻨﺠﺎن‬ ‫ﭘﺰﺷﻜﻲ‬ ‫ﻋﻠﻮم‬ ‫داﻧﺸﮕﺎه‬ 
، 
‫ﻛﺮﻣﺎن‬ 
‫اﻳﺮان‬ ، 
7 
-
‫اﺳﺘﺎد‬ 
، 
‫ﺑﻴﻮ‬ ‫ﮔﺮوه‬ 
‫ﺗﻜﻨﻮﻟﻮژي،‬ 
‫ﭘﺰﺷﻜﻲ‬ ‫داﻧﺸﻜﺪه‬ 
، 
‫ﻣﺪرس‬ ‫ﺗﺮﺑﻴﺖ‬ ‫داﻧﺸﮕﺎه‬ 
، 
‫ﺗﻬﺮان‬ 
‫اﻳﺮان‬ ، 
‫ﻧﻮﻳﺴﻨﺪه‬ 
‫ﻣﺴﺆول‬ 
: 
‫دﻛﺘﺮ‬ 
‫ﻛﺮم‬ ‫اﺳﺪي‬ ‫ﻏﻼﻣﺮﺿﺎ‬ 
Email: gh_asadi@kmu.ac.ir </p>

<p> 
Addict Health, Winter &amp; Spring 2013; Vol 5, No 1-2 </p>

<p>http://ahj.kmu.ac.ir, 4 April </p>

<p>‫اﻟﻘﺎ‬ 
‫ي‬ 
‫ﺑﺮﻧﺎﻣﻪ‬ ‫ﻣﺮگ‬ 
‫ر‬ 
‫ﻳﺰي‬ 
‫ﺳﻠﻮﻟ‬ ‫رده‬ ‫در‬ ‫ﺷﺪه‬ 
‫ﻲ‬ 
Jurkat 
‫ﺗﺮ‬ ‫ﺗﻮﺳﻂ‬ 
‫ﻳﺎك‬ </p>

<p>‫اﻳﮕﺪر‬ ‫ﺳﻤﻴﻪ‬ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>، 
‫دﻛﺘﺮ‬ 
‫ﻛﺮم‬ ‫اﺳﺪي‬ ‫ﻏﻼﻣﺮﺿﺎ‬ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>، 
‫دﻛﺘﺮ‬ 
‫ﺷﻴﺦ‬ ‫ﻓﺮزاﻧﻪ‬ 
‫اﻻﺳﻼم‬ </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>، 
‫ا‬ 
‫ﺣﻤﺪ‬ 
‫ﺻﻴﺎدي‬ ‫رﺿﺎ‬ </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>، 
‫دﻛﺘﺮ‬ 
‫ﻣﺤﻤﻮدي‬ ‫ﻣﻬﺪي‬ </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>، </p>

<p>‫ﻋﺮب‬ ‫ﻛﺎﻇﻤﻲ‬ ‫ﻣﺤﻤﺪ‬ ‫دﻛﺘﺮ‬ 
‫آﺑﺎدي‬ </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>، 
‫دﻛﺘﺮ‬ 
‫ﻣﺤﻤﺪ‬ 
‫رﺳﺎﻳﻲ‬ ‫ﺟﻮاد‬ </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>‫ﭼﻜﻴﺪه‬ </p>

<p>‫ﻣﻘﺪﻣﻪ‬ 
: 
‫ﺑﺮﺧﻲ‬ ‫ﻣﺴﺘﻘﻴﻢ‬ ‫اﺛﺮ‬ 
‫ﺳﻠﻮل‬ ‫ﺑﺮ‬ ‫اﭘﻴﻮﺋﻴﺪﻫﺎ‬ ‫از‬ 
‫اﻳﻤﻨﻲ‬ ‫ﻫﺎي‬ 
‫ﻣﺸﺨﺺ‬ 
‫اﺳﺖ‬ ‫ﺷﺪه‬ 
. 
‫ﻣﻄﺎﻟﻌﻪ‬ ‫از‬ ‫ﻫﺪف‬ 
‫ﺣﺎﺿﺮ،‬ 
‫ﺗ‬ 
‫ﺄ‬ 
‫ﺳﻠﻮل‬ ‫ﺑﺮ‬ ‫ﺗﺮﻳﺎك‬ ‫آﭘﺎﭘﺘﻮزي‬ ‫ﺛﻴﺮ‬ 
‫ﻫﺎي‬ 
‫ﻟﻨﻔﻮﺳﻴﺘﻲ‬ 
T 
‫ﻧﻮع‬ 
Jurkat 
‫ﺑﻮد‬ 
. </p>

<p>‫روش‬ 
‫ﻫﺎ‬ 
: 
‫ﻏﻠﻈﺖ‬ 
‫ﺗﺮﻳﺎك‬ ‫ﻣﺨﺘﻠﻒ‬ ‫ﻫﺎي‬ 
) </p>

<p>11 
-</p>

<p>10 
 
8 
/ 
2 
-</p>

<p>3 
-</p>

<p>10 
 
86 
/ 
2 
‫ﻣﻴﻠﻲ‬ ‫ﺑﺮ‬ ‫ﮔﺮم‬ 
‫ﻟﻴﺘﺮ‬ 
( 
‫ﭼﺎ‬ ‫ﺑﻪ‬ 
‫ﻫ‬ 
‫ﻚ‬ 
‫ﭘﻠﻴﺖ‬ ‫ﻫﺎي‬ 
24 
‫ﺣﺎوي‬ ‫ﺗﺎﻳﻲ‬ 
10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>× 
5 
‫ﺳﻠﻮل‬ 
Jurkat 
‫اﺿﺎﻓﻪ‬ 
‫ﮔﺮدﻳﺪ‬ 
‫و‬ 
‫از‬ ‫ﭘﺲ‬ ‫ﺳﻠﻮﻟﻲ‬ ‫آﭘﺎﭘﺘﻮز‬ ‫ﻣﻴﺰان‬ 
6 
، 
24 
‫و‬ 
72 
‫ﺑ‬ ‫ﺳﺎﻋﺖ‬ 
‫ﻪ‬ 
‫ﻓﺴﻔﺎﺗﻴﺪﻳﻞ‬ ‫ﻛﻪ‬ ‫ﻓﻠﻮﺳﺎﻳﺘﻮﻣﺘﺮي‬ ‫وﺳﻴﻠﻪ‬ 
‫ﻣﻲ‬ ‫ﻧﺸﺎن‬ ‫را‬ ‫ﺳﻠﻮﻟﻲ‬ ‫ﺳﻄﺢ‬ ‫ﺳﺮﻳﻦ‬ 
‫دﻫﺪ‬ 
، 
‫ﺷﺪ‬ ‫ﻣﺸﺨﺺ‬ 
. </p>

<p>‫ﻳﺎﻓﺘﻪ‬ 
‫ﻫﺎ‬ 
: 
‫ﻳﺎﻓﺘﻪ‬ 
‫ﻫﺎ،‬ 
‫اﺛﺮات‬ 
‫آﭘﺎﭘﺘﻮزي‬ 
‫ﻣﻌﻨﻲ‬ 
‫دار‬ 
‫ﺗﺮﻳﺎك‬ 
‫ﻏﻠﻈﺖ‬ ‫در‬ ‫را‬ 
‫ﻣﺨﺘﻠﻒ‬ ‫ﻫﺎي‬ 
‫ﺳﻠﻮل‬ ‫ﺑﺮ‬ 
‫ﻫﺎي‬ 
Jurkat 
‫در‬ 
24 
‫و‬ 
72 
‫ﺳﺎﻋﺖ‬ 
‫داد‬ ‫ﻧﺸﺎن‬ 
) 
05 
/ 
0 
&lt; 
P 
( 
. 
‫ﻫﻤﭽﻨﻴﻦ‬ </p>

<p>‫ﺗﺮﻳﺎك‬ 
‫ﺑﺎ‬ 
‫ﻏﻠﻈﺖ‬ </p>

<p>3 
-</p>

<p>10 
 
86 
/ 
2 
‫ﻣﻴﻠﻲ‬ ‫ﺑﺮ‬ ‫ﮔﺮم‬ 
‫ﻟﻴﺘﺮ‬ 
‫در‬ 
72 
‫ﺳﻠﻮﻟﻲ‬ ‫ﻧﻜﺮوز‬ ‫ﻣﻴﺰان‬ ‫ﺳﺎﻋﺖ‬ 
‫را‬ 
‫ﮔﺮوه‬ ‫ﺑﻪ‬ ‫ﻧﺴﺒﺖ‬ 
‫ﺷﺎﻫﺪ‬ 
‫ﺷﺪت‬ ‫ﺑﻪ‬ 
‫اﻓﺰاﻳﺶ‬ 
‫داد‬ 
) 
05 
/ 
0 
&lt; 
P 
( 
. </p>

<p>‫ﻧﺘﻴﺠﻪ‬ 
‫ﮔﻴﺮي‬ 
: 
‫ﺗﺮﻳﺎك‬ 
‫ﻣﺴﺘﻘﻴﻢ‬ ‫ﻃﻮر‬ ‫ﺑﻪ‬ 
‫ﻟﻨﻔﻮﺳﻴﺖ‬ ‫آﭘﺎﭘﺘﻮز‬ ‫ﻃﺮﻳﻖ‬ ‫از‬ ‫را‬ ‫اﻳﻤﻨﻲ‬ ‫ﺳﻴﺴﺘﻢ‬ 
‫ﻫﺎي‬ 
T 
‫ﺗ‬ ‫ﺗﺤﺖ‬ 
‫ﺄ‬ 
‫ﻣﻲ‬ ‫ﻗﺮار‬ ‫ﺛﻴﺮ‬ 
‫دﻫﺪ‬ 
. 
‫ﻧﻘﺶ‬ ‫اﺳﺖ‬ ‫ﻣﻤﻜﻦ‬ ‫اﺛﺮ‬ ‫اﻳﻦ‬ 
‫در‬ ‫ﻣﻬﻤﻲ‬ 
‫ﻛﻨﺪ‬ ‫ﺑﺎزي‬ ‫ﺗﺮﻳﺎك‬ ‫ﺑﻪ‬ ‫ﻣﻌﺘﺎدان‬ ‫در‬ ‫اﻳﻤﻨﻲ‬ ‫ﺳﻴﺴﺘﻢ‬ ‫ﻋﻤﻠﻜﺮدي‬ ‫اﺧﺘﻼل‬ 
. </p>

<p>‫ﻛﻠﻴﺪي‬ ‫واژﮔﺎن‬ 
: 
‫ﺳﻠﻮل‬ ‫ﻧﻜﺮوز،‬ ‫آﭘﺎﭘﺘﻮز،‬ ‫ﺗﺮﻳﺎك،‬ 
Jurkat </p>

<p>‫ارﺟﺎع‬ 
: 
‫اﻳﮕﺪر‬ 
‫ﻛﺮم‬ ‫اﺳﺪي‬ ‫ﺳﻤﻴﻪ،‬ 
‫ﺷﻴﺦ‬ ‫ﻏﻼﻣﺮﺿﺎ،‬ 
‫اﻻﺳﻼم‬ 
‫ﻓﺮزاﻧﻪ،‬ 
‫ﺻﻴﺎدي‬ 
‫ا‬ 
‫ﺣﻤﺪ‬ 
‫رﺿﺎ‬ 
‫ﻣﺤﻤﻮدي‬ ، 
‫ﻣﻬﺪي،‬ 
‫ﻋﺮب‬ ‫ﻛﺎﻇﻤﻲ‬ 
‫آﺑﺎدي‬ 
‫ﻣﺤﻤﺪ‬ 
‫ﻣﺤﻤﺪ‬ ‫رﺳﺎﻳﻲ‬ ، 
‫ﺟﻮاد‬ 
. 
‫اﻟﻘﺎ‬ 
‫ي‬ 
‫ﻣﺮگ‬ </p>

<p>‫ﺑﺮﻧﺎﻣﻪ‬ 
‫ر‬ 
‫ﻳﺰي‬ 
‫ﺳﻠﻮﻟ‬ ‫رده‬ ‫در‬ ‫ﺷﺪه‬ 
‫ﻲ‬ 
Jurkat 
‫ﺗﺮ‬ ‫ﺗﻮﺳﻂ‬ 
‫ﻳﺎك‬ 
. 
‫ﺳﻼﻣﺖ‬ ‫و‬ ‫اﻋﺘﻴﺎد‬ ‫ﻣﺠﻠﻪ‬ 
1392 
‫؛‬ 
5 
) 
2 
-
1 
( 
: 
34 
-
27 
. </p>

<p>‫درﻳﺎﻓﺖ‬ ‫ﺗﺎرﻳﺦ‬ 
: 
8 
/ 
5 
/ 
91 
‫ﭘﺬﻳﺮش‬ ‫ﺗﺎرﻳﺦ‬ 
: 
26 
/ 
8 
/ 
91 </p>

<p>‫ﭘﮋوﻫﺸﻲ‬ ‫ﻣﻘﺎﻟﻪ‬ </p>

</text></tei>