<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3281721" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Golgi is a potential target for cancer treatment, but no inhibitor became an anticancer drug. 
Results: Using a unique bioinformatics approach, we identified a novel Golgi inhibitor, AMF-26, targeting Arf1 activation and 
possessing potent antitumor activity. 
Conclusion: AMF-26 is a promising new anticancer drug lead. 
Significance: Our data indicate that Arf1 activation is a promising target for cancer treatment. </p>

<p>ADP-ribosylation factor 1 (Arf1) plays a major role in mediating 
vesicular transport. Brefeldin A (BFA), a known inhibitor of the 
Arf1-guanine nucleotide exchange factor (GEF) interaction, is 
highly cytotoxic. Therefore, interaction of Arf1 with ArfGEF is an 
attractive target for cancer treatment. However, BFA and its deriv-
atives have not progressed beyond the pre-clinical stage of drug 
development because of their poor bioavailability. Here, we aimed 
to identify novel inhibitors of the Arf1-ArfGEF interaction that dis-
play potent antitumor activity in vivo but with a chemical structure 
distinct from that of BFA. We exploited a panel of 39 cell lines 
(termed JFCR39) coupled with a drug sensitivity data base and 
COMPARE algorithm, resulting in the identification of a possible 
novel Arf1-ArfGEF inhibitor AMF-26, which differed structurally 
from BFA. By using a pulldown assay with GGA3-conjugated 
beads, we demonstrated that AMF-26 inhibited Arf1 activation. 
Subsequently, AMF-26 induced Golgi disruption, apoptosis, and 
cell growth inhibition. Computer modeling/molecular dynamics 
(MD) simulation suggested that AMF-26 bound to the contact sur-
face of the Arf1-Sec7 domain where BFA bound. AMF-26 affected 
membrane traffic, including the cis-Golgi and trans-Golgi net-
works, and the endosomal systems. Furthermore, using AMF-26 
and its derivatives, we demonstrated that there was a significant 
correlation between cell growth inhibition and Golgi disruption. In 
addition, orally administrated AMF-26 (83 mg/kg of body weight; 5 
days) induced complete regression of human breast cancer BSY-1 
xenografts in vivo, suggesting that AMF-26 is a novel anticancer 
drug candidate that inhibits the Golgi system, targeting Arf1 
activation. </p>

<p>Protein-protein interactions (PPIs) 
2 play an important role 
in many biological processes, such as growth, cell survival, and 
intercellular signal transduction (1, 2). Therefore, inhibitors of 
specific PPIs can act as novel therapeutic agents including anti-
cancer drugs. Indeed, several small molecule-PPI inhibitors 
have been developed, such as Nutlin-3 for HDM2-p53 interac-
tion (3), and ABT-737, a Bcl-2 family protein inhibitor (4). 
Nonetheless, the number of promising PPI inhibitors for cancer 
treatment remains limited. 
In this study, we focused on the activation of ADP-ribosyla-
tion factors (Arfs) by its guanine nucleotide exchange factors 
(GEFs). Arfs are members of the Ras superfamily of small 
GTPases that play a major role in mediating vesicular transport 
in the secretory and endocytic pathways (5). The cellular activ-
ity of Arfs is stimulated by the Sec7 domain of GEFs that pro-
mote the exchange of inactive GDP-bound forms to active 
GTP-bound forms (6). Arf1, the best characterized Arf, local-
izes primarily to the Golgi apparatus and regulates both antero-
grade and retrograde vesicular traffic (7). The first identified 
small molecule PPI that targets the interaction between Arf-
ArfGEF was brefeldin A (BFA, Fig. 1A), a lactone isolated from 
fungi, which inhibits the activation of Arf1 by a subset of its 
GEFs (8, 9). Treatment of BFA causes rapid but reversible dis-
ruption of the Golgi apparatus leading to the vesiculation of the 
cis-Golgi and trans-Golgi network (TGN) (10, 11). Further-
more, BFA showed tumor growth inhibition in vitro (12) and in 
vivo at an early stage (13). Therefore, inhibitors of Arf1-ArfGEF 
interaction are valuable tools for studying membrane traffic as 
well as anticancer drug candidates. However, BFA and its deriv-</p>

<p>* This work was supported by Grants-in-aid for Scientific Research (A) </p>

<p>22240092 from the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (to T. Y.) and 
Grant-in-aid for Scientific Research on Priority Areas 11177101 from the 
Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology (to T. Y.). 
Author's Choice-Final version full access. 
□ S This article contains supplemental Tables S1 and S2, Fig. S1, "Experimental 
Procedures," and Video S1. 
1 To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel.: 81-3-3520-0111; Fax: 
81-3-3570-0484; E-mail: yamori@jfcr.or.jp. </p>

<p>2 The abbreviations used are: PPI, protein-protein interaction; Arf, ADP-ribo-
sylation factor; BFA, brefeldin A; BIG, brefeldin A-inhibited guanine nucle-
otide-exchange proteins; CLCa, clathrin light chain a; COP, coat protein 
complex; ER, endoplasmic reticulum; ERGIC, ER-Golgi intermediate com-
partment; GBF1, Golgi-specific brefeldin A resistance factor 1; GEF, gua-
nine nucleotide exchange factor; JFCR39, a panel of 39 human cancer cell 
lines; TGN, trans-Golgi network; PARP, poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase; MD, 
molecular dynamics; HP, hydrophobic. </p>

<p>THE JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY VOL. 287, NO. 6, pp. 3885-3897, February 3, 2012 </p>

<p>Author's Choice </p>

<p>© 2012 by The American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Inc. Published in the U.S.A. </p>

<p>FEBRUARY 3, 2012 • VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 6 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 3885 </p>

<p>atives have not progressed beyond the pre-clinical stage of drug 
development (13, 14). 
We previously established a panel of 39 cell lines (termed 
JFCR39) coupled with our own drug sensitivity data base, which 
is comparable with that of the NCI60 panel from the National 
Cancer Institute (NCI) (15-19). Using the COMPARE com-
puter algorithm (details described under "Results"), it is possi-
ble to correlate the growth inhibitory patterns of JFCR39 
(termed "fingerprints") of a test compound with those of known 
anticancer drugs and inhibitors (20, 21). Here, we have 
attempted to identify new Arf1-ArfGEF inhibitors with equiv-
alent functions to BFA but with a different chemical structure, 
by using COMPARE-guided in silico screening instead of struc-
ture-based screening. 
This approach enabled us to discover a novel small molecule 
AMF-26 (Fig. 1B), an octahydronaphthalene derivative, which 
disrupts the Golgi system probably by inhibiting the Arf1 acti-
vation. AMF-26 shows strong growth inhibition against 
JFCR39 cell lines in vitro. Furthermore, it showed potent anti-
tumor activity against xenografts of the human breast cancer 
cell line BSY-1 via oral administration. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>Chemicals-AMF-26 ((2E,4E)-5-((1S,2S,4aR,6R,7S,8S,8aS)-
7-hydroxy-2,6,8-trimethyl-1,2,4a,5,6,7,8,8a-octahydronaphtha-
len-1-yl)-2-methyl-N-(pyridin-3-yl-methyl)penta-2,4-dienamide) 
and its derivatives were synthesized from AMF-14, a natural prod-
uct from the genus Trichoderma, and kindly provided by the 
Research Laboratories Kyoto, Nippon Shinyaku Co., Ltd. (Kyoto, 
Japan). Details of the synthesis methods and the chemical proper-
ties of the final product are described under supplemental "Exper-
imental Procedures." BFA and nocodazole were purchased from 
Sigma, and bafilomycin A1 was purchased from Tocris Bioscience 
(Bristol, UK). For in vitro studies, these compounds were reconsti-
tuted to 10 mM in DMSO (Sigma) and stored at Ϫ20°C. For animal 
experiments, AMF-26 was suspended in 0.05% Cremophor EL 
(Sigma-Aldrich) in water as a solid dispersion. The antibodies for 
immunostaining were as follows: monoclonal to anti-GBF1 (clone 
25), anti-adaptin ␥ (clone 88), and anti-adaptin ␦ (clone 18) were 
purchased from BD Biosciences (San Jose, CA), anti-ERGIC53 
(clone G1/93) was from ALEXIS Biochemicals (Farmingdale, NY), 
anti-Arf (clone 1D9) and anti-Arf1 (clone EP442Y) were from 
Abcam (Cambridge, United Kingdom), and anti-␣ tubulin (clone 
B-5-1-2) was from Sigma. Rabbit polyclonal to anti-␤COP was 
from Abcam, and anti-cleaved poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase 
(PARP) was from Cell Signaling Technology (Boston, MA). Fluo-
rescent probe LysoTracker was purchased from Invitrogen. For 
Western blotting, horseradish peroxidase-conjugated donkey 
anti-rabbit or sheep anti-mouse IgG (GE Healthcare) was used as a 
secondary antibody. For immunofluorescence microscopy, Alexa 
488-conjugated goat anti-rabbit or anti-mouse IgG (Molecular 
Probes, Eugene, OR) was used as a secondary antibody. 
Cell Lines-A panel of 39 human cancer cell lines (termed 
JFCR39, described previously (22)) was used for the in vitro 
experiments. BSY-1 (human breast cancer) cells were also used 
for in vivo studies. MDA-MB-435 (human breast cancer) cells 
stably expressing GFP-tagged human clathrin light chain a 
(MDA-MB-435/GFP-CLCa) were prepared as described previ-</p>

<p>ously (23). HEK293T (human embryonic kidney) cells were 
purchased from American Type Culture Collection (Manassas, 
VA). JFCR39 and MDA-MB-435/GFP-CLCa cells were cul-
tured in RPMI 1640 medium (Wako Pure Chemical Industries) 
supplemented with 5% fetal bovine serum, penicillin (100 units/ 
ml), and streptomycin (100 g/ml) in a humidified atmosphere 
including 5% CO 2 at 37°C. HEK293T was cultured in DMEM 
(Wako Pure Chemical Industries) supplemented with 10% 
heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum and kanamycin, at 37°C 
under 5% CO 2 . For in vivo studies, BSY-1 cells were grown as 
subcutaneous tumors in nude mice. 
Analysis of Cell Growth Inhibition-The inhibition of cell 
proliferation was assessed by measuring changes in total cellu-
lar protein in a culture of each of the JFCR39 cell lines after 48 h 
of drug treatment by use of a sulforhodamine B assay (24). The 
50% growth inhibition (GI 50 ) value was calculated as described 
previously (18, 19). 
COMPARE Analysis-Based on these sets of GI 50 values, fin-
gerprints are presented in the graphic profiles of relative sensi-
tivity within JFCR39. To analyze the correlation between the 
fingerprints of drug A and drug B, we exploited the COMPARE 
computer algorithm as described previously (18, 20, 22). The 
Pearson correlation coefficient between the fingerprints of 
drug A and drug B was calculated (n ϭ 39). 
Live Imaging-MDA-MB-435/GFP-CLCa cells were grown 
in a 35-mm glass-bottomed dish (Matsunami Glass Ind., Osaka, 
Japan) for 48 h. Subsequently, the cells were treated with chem-
icals and imaged on the temperature-controlled stage top incu-
bator (Tokai Hit Co., Shizuoka, Japan) of fluorescent micros-
copy IX81 (Olympus Corp.) with a ϫ60 oil, NA 1.35 objective at 
37°C under 5% CO 2 . Temperature and CO 2 concentration 
were maintained with an INUG2A control unit (Tokai Hit Co.). 
<rs id="software-9" type="software">MetaMorph</rs> Software (<rs corresp="#software-9" type="creator">Molecular Devices</rs>, Downingtown, PA) 
was used to control image acquisition and manipulation. For 
time-lapse observation, images were recorded as described pre-
viously by Sakaushi et al. (23). 
Arf-GTP Pulldown Assay-The pulldown assay to estimate 
the signals of GTP-bound Arfs was performed as described pre-
viously (25, 26). Every pulldown assay was performed with the 
VHS and GAT domains of human GGA3, cloned, and purified 
according to a published protocol (25, 26) with modifications as 
described under supplemental "Experimental Procedures." 
We examined the guanine nucleotide exchange activity of 
endogenous Arfs as follows. BSY-1 cells treated with chemicals 
for 1 h were scraped into 0.5 ml of cold pulldown buffer con-
taining 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 100 mM NaCl, 2 mM MgCl 2 , 
0.1% SDS, 0.5% sodium deoxycholate, 1% Triton X-100, 10% 
glycerol, and protease inhibitors mixture (Nacalai Tesque Inc., 
Kyoto, Japan). The cell lysate was cleared using GSH-Sepharose 
4B beads. Then the lysate was gently rotated with the beads 
containing 50 g of rGST-GGA3 protein for 30 min at 4°C. 
Bound proteins were washed three times with cold wash buffer 
(50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 100 mM NaCl, 2 mM MgCl 2 , 1% Non-
idet P-40, 10% glycerol and protease inhibitors mixture), fol-
lowed by boiling for 5 min with SDS sample buffer. Proteins in 
the samples were separated in 10 -20% Multi-Gel II mini 
(Cosmo Bio Co., Tokyo, Japan), followed by electroblotting 
onto a polyvinylidene difluoride membrane (GE Healthcare). </p>

<p>Novel Golgi Inhibitor Shows Potent Antitumor Activity </p>



<p>VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 6 • FEBRUARY 3, 2012 </p>

<p>After immunoblotting analysis using anti-pan-Arf and Arf1-
specific antibody, immunoreactive bands were identified with 
the ECL Plus Western blotting detection system (GE Health-
care). Band intensity was determined using the program ImageJ 
(National Institute of Health). 
To confirm the inhibitory efficacy of Arf1 activation, 
HEK293T/Arf1-HA cells were used to measure exogenous 
Arf1-GTP. Using the Lipofectamine 2000 reagent (Invitrogen) 
according to the manufacturer's instructions, HEK293T cells 
were transfected with the Arf1-HA expression vector, prepared 
as described under supplemental "Experimental Procedures." 
For transfection, HEK293T cells were seeded at a density of 3 ϫ 
10 
6 cells/10 ml in a 10-cm plate. The transfectants were then 
incubated for 24 h, and subsequently treated with chemicals for 
1 h. The cell lysates were assayed as described above. Because of 
a difference in molecular weight, the exogenous band of 
Arf1-HA can be differentiated from the endogenous band 
of intact Arf1. In HEK293T/Arf1-HA cells, the expression of 
intact Arf1 was very low. Therefore, the intensity of the band 
corresponding to Arf1 was apparently weaker than that of the 
exogenous Arf1-HA. 
Conformational Sampling of AMF-26-Conformational 
analysis of AMF-26 was performed on an Apple Power Mac G5 
(PowerPC G5, 2.5 GHz; two central processing units), using the 
Conformational Analyzer with Molecular Dynamics and Sam-
pling (<rs id="software-10" type="software">CAMDAS</rs>) <rs corresp="#software-10" type="version">2.1</rs> program (27). Ten molecular dynamic 
(MD) calculations were simultaneously performed using differ-
ent initial structures. Each of the MD calculations was carried 
out for 1 ns with an integral time step of 1 fs. The lengths of the 
covalent bonds were fixed. The temperature of the system was 
maintained at 1,200 K to enhance the sampling efficiency. Con-
formers were sampled every 100 steps, and then each con-
former was minimized until the root mean square of the gradi-
ents of the potential energy was below 0.001 kcal mol 
Ϫ1 Å </p>

<p>Ϫ1 </p>

<p>. 
All conformations were clustered with torsion angles of 
heavy atoms using a threshold of Ϯ30°. The Merck Molecu-
lar Force Field 94s was used to evaluate the potential energy 
surface of the molecule (28, 29). The dielectric constant was 
80, but no cut-off distance for non-bonded interactions was 
used. Because of the low probability of the existence of con-
formers with higher energies, the conformers within 15 kcal 
mol 
Ϫ1 of the minimum energy of the molecule were adopted 
for superposition. 
Molecular Modeling of the Arf1-AMF-26-Sec7 Domain 
Complex-To obtain the initial structure of the Arf1-AMF-26-
Sec7 domain complex, the sampled conformers of AMF-26 
were superposed onto BFA in the X-ray structure of the 
Arf-BFA-Sec7 domain complex (PDB code 1r8q) (8) using the 
parallel version of the SUPERPOSE program (30). This super-
poses two molecules based on the physicochemical properties 
of the atomic groups, which is useful for estimating the binding 
conformation of a molecule by distinguishing it from the many 
conformations that are generated by <rs type="software">CAMDAS</rs>. The program 
considers five types of physicochemical property: hydrophobic 
(HP), aromatic (AR), hydrogen-bond donors (HD), hydrogen-
bond acceptors (HA), and hydrogen-bond donors/acceptors 
(DA). Each type is represented as a sphere with a predefined 
radius (1.0 or 0.5 Å) and is assigned to a functional group in a </p>

<p>molecule (Fig. 4, A and B). After molecular superposition, the 
matching spheres were scored using the scoring matrix (sup-
plemental Table S1). One AMF-26 conformation was chosen as 
the binding conformation based on the scores and the over-
lapped molecular volumes (Fig. 4C). The superposition calcu-
lations were performed using 28 nodes of a Dell PowerEdge 
1950III (Intel Quad Core Xeon X5460; 3.16 GHz; 56 central 
processing units in total). The overlapped molecular volumes 
were calculated by SYBYL 7.3 (Tripos Inc., St. Louis, MO) on an 
Hewlett Packard work station xw8200 (Intel Xeon; 3.60 GHz; 2 
central processing units). 
To relieve the steric hindrances, the coordinates of AMF-26 
and of the residues within 4 Å from AMF-26 were optimized to 
reduce the root mean square of the gradients of potential 
energy below 0.05 kcal mol 
Ϫ1 Å 
Ϫ1 using <rs type="software">SYBYL</rs>. The simplex 
minimization method before the conjugate-gradient minimiza-
tion procedure was used. The Tripos force field was employed 
for the molecular energy calculation. The <rs id="software-15" type="software">AMBER</rs> <rs corresp="#software-15" type="version">4.1</rs> charges 
(31) were used as the atomic charges for the proteins and the 
Gasteiger-Hückel charges (32-35) were used as the charges for 
AMF-26. The cut-off distance for the non-bonded interactions 
was 8 Å. The distance-dependent dielectric constant of 4r was 
used. The initial positions of the missing atoms in the crystal 
structure were generated by the <rs type="software">SYBYL</rs>. 
Molecular Dynamics Simulation for Model Refinement-To 
refine the model of the Arf1-AMF-26-Sec7 domain complex, 
<rs id="software-17" type="software">AMBER</rs> <rs corresp="#software-17" type="version">9</rs> (36) was used for further minimization and MD sim-
ulations on 7 nodes of an Appro 1122Hi (AMD Opteron 248; 
2.20 GHz; 14 central processing units in total). The ff99 (37)  and gaff (38) force fields were used for the proteins and 
AMF-26, respectively. The partial charges for AMF-26 were 
derived from the restraint electrostatic potential method 
(39) using an ab initio calculation at the HF/6 -31G* level 
using Gaussian 03 (40). The complex was solvated in a box of 
34616 TIP3P (41) water molecules. Six K 
ϩ ions were added 
to neutralize the system. The system was minimized until the 
root mean square of the gradients of potential energy was 
below 0.005 kcal mol 
Ϫ1 Å 
Ϫ1 . The 3.5-ns MD simulation was 
carried out at constant pressure (1 atm) and temperature 
(310 K), under periodic boundary conditions, and with par-
ticle-mesh Ewald treatment (42) of electrostatics. SHAKE 
(43) was applied to all bonds involving hydrogen, and a time 
step of 1 fs was used. An 8-Å cutoff was used for the non-
bonded interactions. 
Immunofluorescence Microscopy-After being cultured in a 
24-well glass bottom plate for 48 h, cells were treated with 
chemicals for various periods of time (as indicated in the rele-
vant figure). Cells were washed with PBS, fixed with cold 3.8% 
paraformaldehyde in PBS (Wako Pure Chemical Industries, 
Osaka, Japan) for 20 min, and then washed and permeabi-
lized with 0.4% Triton X-100 (Sigma) in PBS for 10 min at 
room temperature. Cells were incubated in blocking buffer 
containing 1% BSA and 2% normal goat serum (Dako, 
Glostrup, Denmark) for 30 min before overnight incubation 
at 4°C with primary antibodies diluted in blocking buffer. 
After being washed, cells were incubated for 1 h with sec-
ondary antibodies. Cells were then washed, stained with 
DAPI (Molecular Probes), and mounted with fluorescent </p>

<p>Novel Golgi Inhibitor Shows Potent Antitumor Activity </p>

<p>FEBRUARY 3, 2012 • VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 6 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 3887 </p>

<p>mounting medium (Dako). The immunostained cells were 
imaged using a fluorescent microscope IX81 (Olympus 
Corp., Tokyo, Japan) with a ϫ100 oil, NA 1.40 objective or 
with a ϫ40, NA 0.95 objective, and <rs id="software-18" type="software">MetaMorph</rs> Software 
(<rs corresp="#software-18" type="creator">Molecular Devices</rs>, Sunnyvale, CA). 
Transferrin Recycling Assay-Transferrin recycling was 
monitored by modification of a previously published assay 
(44). 6 ϫ 10 
4 cells were incubated in 24-well glass bottom 
plates for 48 h, and then in serum-free medium for 3 h to 
deplete endogenous transferrin. After incubation with 20 
g/ml of Alexa Fluor 488-tagged transferrin (Molecular 
Probes) in PBBS for 1 h, cells were treated with chemicals for 
1 h. Cells were then fixed with 3.8% paraformaldehyde in PBS 
for 20 min at RT, washed with PBS containing 0.1% 1,4-
diazabicyclo[2.2.2]octane (DABCO, Sigma), and mounted with 
fluorescent mounting medium (Dako). 
Flow Cytometry-Cells were harvested, washed with ice-cold 
PBS, and fixed in 70% ethanol. Cells were then washed twice 
with ice-cold PBS again, treated with RNase A (500 g/ml; 
Sigma) at 37°C for 1 h, and stained with propidium iodide (25 
g/ml; Sigma). The DNA content of the cells was analyzed with 
a flow cytometer (FACSCalibur, BD Biosciences). 
Animal Experiments-Antitumor effect of AMF-26 was 
tested in vivo against human BSY-1 xenografts in mice. Animal 
care and treatment was performed in accordance with the 
guidelines of the Animal Use and Care Committee of the Japa-
nese Foundation for Cancer Research, and conformed to the 
NIH Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. Female 
nude mice with BALB/c genetic backgrounds were purchased 
from Charles River Japan, Inc. (Yokohama, Japan), maintained 
under specific pathogen-free conditions, and provided with 
sterile food and water ad libitum. Each nude mouse was subcu-
taneously inoculated with the generated tumor fragment of size 
3 ϫ 3 ϫ 3 mm. When the tumors reached a volume of 100 -300 
mm 
3 , animals were randomly divided into control and AMF-26 
groups (each group containing five mice) and daily administra-
tion of AMF-26 was then started (day 0). We examined the toxic 
dose of AMF-26 at a single oral administration. The maximum 
tolerable dose turned out to be 100 mg/kg of body weight. The 
experimental group of mice was orally administered a given 
dose of AMF-26 (83 or 100 mg/kg of body weight) on a daily 
basis from day 0 to 5. The control group of mice was orally 
administered with 0.05% Cremophor EL (Sigma) instead of 
AMF-26. Tumor volume of the tumor-bearing mice was mea-
sured as described previously (22). The length (L) and width 
(W) of the subcutaneous tumor mass of live mice were meas-
ured using calipers. Tumor weight was calculated as tumor 
weight ϭ (L ϫ W 
2 )/2. To assess toxicity, the body weights of the 
tumor-bearing mice were measured. 
Statistical Analysis-Pearson correlation coefficients were 
calculated for the COMPARE analysis and statistical correla-
tion. The two-sided Mann-Whitney U test was used to assess 
the statistical significance of the antitumor efficacy of AMF-26 
in relative tumor growth ratio on days 3, 7, 11, 14, 17, and 21. 
The number of samples is indicated in the description of each 
experiment. All statistical tests were two-sided. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Identification of AMF-26 as a Possible Arf1-ArfGEF Inhibitor 
by COMPARE Analysis-The JFCR39 panel is a powerful tool 
for the in silico screening of compounds with specific pharma-
cological activities but with different chemical structures. Seed 
compounds with desirable pharmacological activities can be 
used to extract candidates with a similar mode of action in the 
data base by COMPARE analysis. The data base of our cell line 
panel holds information on 4,000 compounds, including anti-
cancer drugs and known inhibitors of various biological path-
ways. Employing this protocol, JFCR39 has been successful in 
identifying several new anticancer agents, such as a new telo-
merase inhibitor (FJ5002) (45), an inhibitor of topoisomerase I 
and II (MS-247) (19), and a novel phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase 
inhibitor (ZSTK474) (22, 46, 47). For instance, the novel PI3K 
inhibitor ZSTK474 was structurally different from the known 
PI3K inhibitor LY294002, although their respective finger-
prints were similar. We therefore reasoned that COMPARE 
analysis would be a suitable method for screening structurally 
diverse compounds to identify those with a similar mode of 
action to BFA. 
When BFA was used as a seed in COMPARE analysis, 
AMF-26 was identified to be the compound with a highest cor-
relation coefficient (r ϭ 0.831) in the data base based on the 
fingerprint profile. AMF-26 was the only compound whose r 
value was higher than 0.8 of 4,000 compounds. As shown in Fig. 
1C, the fingerprint of AMF-26 was similar to that of BFA, which 
suggested that AMF-26 has a similar biological mode of action 
to BFA. The mean logarithm of GI 50 for AMF-26 was Ϫ7.33 (at 
47 nM), which is comparable with that of BFA (Ϫ7.37 at 43 nM). 
These results indicated that AMF-26 possesses strong growth 
inhibitory activity as well as that of BFA. 
Disassembly of the Golgi Apparatus Caused by AMF-26-
COMPARE analysis indicated that AMF-26, like BFA, may be a 
Golgi disruptor. Therefore, we first examined whether AMF-26 
induces Golgi disassembly by immunofluorescence staining 
with a monoclonal antibody to Golgi brefeldin A-resistant gua-
nine nucleotide exchange factor 1 (GBF1). GBF1 is localized to 
the cis-Golgi apparatus and plays a role in vesicular trafficking 
by activating Arf1 (48). In control cells, GBF1 was observed in 
the perinuclear region, forming a ribbon-like structure (Fig. 
2A). However, addition of BFA caused a rapid release of GBF1 
into the cytoplasm (Fig. 2B). These results were in agreement 
with previously published reports (48). When the cells were 
treated with AMF-26, GBF1 was observed to be dispersed from 
the perinuclear region throughout the cytoplasm (Fig. 2C), 
which indicated that AMF-26 disrupted the Golgi apparatus. 
Moreover, this observation was confirmed by live imaging 
using the MDA-MB-435 stably expressing GFP-conjugated 
clathrin light chain a (CLCa) cells (supplemental Video S1, 
A-C). In MDA-MB-435/GFP-CLCa cells, the intensity of fluo-
rescence signals of GFP-CLCa were periodically increased and 
decreased at the TGN, suggesting that the formation of clath-
rin-coated pits occurs synchronously and periodically at the 
TGN (23). Disruption of the Golgi apparatus was concurrent 
with the disappearance of GFP-CLCa signals suggesting that 
CLCa was affected by AMF-26. Next, we examined whether the </p>

<p>Novel Golgi Inhibitor Shows Potent Antitumor Activity </p>



<p>VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 6 • FEBRUARY 3, 2012 </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Discovery of AMF-26 as a potent Golgi disruptor. Chemical structure of (A) BFA and (B) AMF-26. C, growth inhibition against a panel of 39 human 
cancer cell lines. The mean graph was produced by computer processing of the 50% growth inhibition (GI 50 ) values as described under "Experimental 
Procedures." Logarithm of the GI 50 value for each cell line is indicated. In the plot, columns to the right of zero indicate sensitivity of the cell line to the 
compound, and columns to the left indicate resistance to the compound. The x axis represents the logarithm of difference between the mean of GI 50 values for 
39 cell lines and the GI 50 value for each cell line in the JFCR39 panel. The mean graph of AMF-26 (right column) is very similar to that of BFA (left column) (Pearson 
correlation coefficients; r ϭ 0.831). MG-MID, the mean of log GI 50 values for 39 cell lines; Delta, the logarithm of difference between the MG-MID and the log GI 50 
of the most sensitive cell line; Range, the logarithm of difference between the log GI 50 of the most resistant cell line and the log GI 50 of the most sensitive cell 
line. One scale represents one logarithm difference. Quantification of the GI 50 value was represented as the mean of four different experiments. Br, breast; CNS, 
central nervous system; Co, colon; Lu, lung; Me, melanoma; Ov, ovarian; Re, renal; St, stomach; xPg, prostate. </p>

<p>Novel Golgi Inhibitor Shows Potent Antitumor Activity </p>

<p>FEBRUARY 3, 2012 • VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 6 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 3889 </p>

<p>AMF-26-induced disruption of Golgi was a reversible process. 
The normal Golgi structure reappeared in the perinuclear area 
4 h after washout of drugs with drug-free medium (Fig. 2D), 
which indicated that the effect of AMF-26 against Golgi was 
fully reversible like that of BFA (49). 
Several tubulin polymerization inhibitors (e.g. nocodazole 
and vincristine) and ionophores (e.g. bafilomycin A1 and 
monensin) are known to disperse the Golgi apparatus (50, 51) 
as a consequence of disrupting microtubules (supplemental Fig. 
S1C) or intracellular pH (supplemental Fig. S1F). However, 
AMF-26 had no apparent effect on the structure of tubulin 
(supplemental Fig. S1B) or localization of lysosomes (supple-
mental Fig. S1E), suggesting that Golgi disruption induced by 
AMF-26 did not result from the disruption of microtubules or 
an alteration of intracellular pH. 
Inhibition of Arf1 Activation by AMF-26 in Human Cells-By 
analogy to BFA, we reasoned that the disruption of Golgi via 
AMF-26 might be mediated through Arf1 inactivation. Then 
we measured the Arf activity in AMF-26-treated cells by an 
Arf-GTP pulldown assay that monitored the signals of Arf-GTP 
using the rGST-GGA3 protein (25, 26). The GAT domain of 
GGA3, an effector of Arf, preferentially binds the active Arf-
GTP over the inactive Arf-GDP (25, 26). Treatment with 
AMF-26 or BFA for 1 h dramatically reduced the signals of 
endogenous pan-Arf-GTP in a dose-dependent manner within 
a range of submicromolar concentrations compared with the 
control state (Fig. 3A). 
To further confirm that AMF-26 inhibited the activation of 
Arf1, we evaluated the signals of the exogenous Arf1 in 
HEK293T cells transiently transfected with human Arf1-HA. 
The signals of exogenous Arf1-GTP in the AMF-26 or BFA-</p>

<p>treated cells for 1 h was significantly reduced in a dose-depen-
dent manner compared with the control cells (Fig. 3B). At a 
concentration of 100 M, AMF-26 and BFA reduced the signals 
of exogenous Arf1-GTP to 28.6 and 37.1%, respectively. These 
data suggested that AMF-26 caused Golgi disassembly by 
blocking Arf1 activation. 
Comparison between the BFA and AMF-26 Complexes-To 
support this conclusion, we performed computer model-
ing/MD simulations. The octahydronaphthalene ring of 
AMF-26 (HP1, HP2, and DA1) was superimposed onto the lac-
tone ring of BFA (HP1, HP2, and HA1) by <rs type="software">SUPERPOSE</rs> (Fig. 
4C). During the MD trajectory, the octahydronaphthalene ring 
of AMF-26 resided in the initial position. The refined model of 
the Arf1-AMF-26-Sec7 domain complex was compared with 
the X-ray structure of the Arf1-BFA-Sec7 domain complex 
(Fig. 4, D and E, supplemental Table S2). The same hydropho-
bic residues (Val-53, Thr-64, Trp-66, and Tyr-81 of Arf1 and 
Met-194, Thr-197, and Val-204 of Sec7 domain) interacted 
with the octahydronaphthalene ring of AMF-26 and the lactone 
ring of BFA. The hydrophobic interactions correspond to the 
matching of hydrophobic property spheres (HP1 and HP2) by 
<rs type="software">SUPERPOSE</rs>. The positively charged Arg-19 of Arf1 interacted 
with the hydroxyl oxygen of AMF-26 and the carbonyl oxygen 
of BFA. This electrostatic interaction accounted for the match-</p>

<p>FIGURE 2. AMF-26 disrupts Golgi apparatus in BSY-1 cells. A-C, dispersion 
of Golgi in AMF-26-treated cells. BSY-1 cells were either untreated (A) or 
treated with (B) BFA (1 M) or (C) AMF-26 (1 M) for 1 h. Cells were fixed and 
labeled with anti-GBF1 (green) and DAPI (blue). GBF1 was dispersed from the 
perinuclear region, which gave a ribbon-like appearance (white arrowhead), 
into the cytoplasm of AMF-26-or BFA-treated cells. Scale bar, 20 m. D, BSY-1 
cells were treated with AMF-26 (1 M) or BFA (1 M) for 1 h, then washed with 
fresh medium and subsequently cultured without drugs for the indicated 
time. Thereafter, cells were fixed and stained with an antibody against GBF1. 
The images were analyzed by <rs type="software">MetaMorph</rs> software. After the cells were cul-
tured in medium without AMF-26 for 4 h, the normal Golgi structure reap-
peared in the perinuclear area. Symbols represent the following: open circle, 
AMF-26; cross, BFA. Error bar, S.D. </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. AMF-26 causes the decrease in Arf1 activation. A, BSY-1 cells 
were treated with DMSO, BFA, or AMF-26 at different concentrations for 1 h 
after 2 days preincubation. The cells were then lysed, and the extracts were 
incubated with immobilized GST-GGA3. Bound proteins were released and 
separated by SDS-PAGE and Western blotted. The signals of endogenous 
pan-Arfs-GTP was determined from the band intensity using ImageJ soft-
ware. Treatment with AMF-26 or BFA for 1 h dramatically reduced the signals 
of endogenous pan-Arf-GTP in a dose-dependent manner. The relative sig-
nals of pan-Arf-GTP are represented as the mean of three different experi-
ments. B, HEK293T cells transfected transiently with ARF1-HA for 24 h were 
exposed to DMSO, BFA, AMF-26, or nocodazole at the indicated concentra-
tions for 1 h before lysis. The signals of exogenous Arf1-GTP were determined. 
Statistical analysis (Student's t test) was performed based on experiments 
done in triplicate. Asterisks represent statistically significant differences from 
untreated samples (p Ͻ 0.05). Abbreviations represent the following: BFA, 
brefeldin A; Noc, nocodazole. Error bar, S.D. </p>

<p>Novel Golgi Inhibitor Shows Potent Antitumor Activity </p>



<p>VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 6 • FEBRUARY 3, 2012 </p>

<p>ing of hydrogen-bond acceptors (DA1 of AMF-26 and HA1 of 
BFA). In addition, the hydroxyl group of AMF-26 hydrogen-
bonded to the side chain of Thr-64 of Arf1. Instead of the 
hydrogen bond between the hydroxyl oxygen of the lactone ring 
of BFA and the amide nitrogen of Asp-67 of Arf1, the amide 
oxygen of AMF-26 hydrogen-bonded with the main chain of 
Glu-54 of Arf1. This computer modeling/MD simulation sug-
gested that AMF-26 bound to the contact surface of the Arf1-
Sec7 domain where BFA is known to bind. 
Effects of AMF-26 on the cis-Golgi, TGN, and Recycling 
Endosomes-To clarify the mechanism of Golgi disruption by 
AMF-26, we first examined the effect of AMF-26 on localiza-</p>

<p>tion of cis-Golgi-associated proteins, ␤COPI, GBF1, and p58/ 
ERGIC53. COPI is the most important coat protein in facilitat-
ing retrograde intracellular transport from Golgi to the 
endoplasmic reticulum (ER) (52). In control cells, most of the 
␤COPI was localized on the cis-Golgi membrane, whereas 
the addition of AMF-26 caused a rapid release of ␤COPI into 
the cytoplasm (Fig. 5A). GBF1, primarily localized in cis-
Golgi as shown in Fig. 2, was dispersed into the cytoplasm of 
cells treated with AMF-26. Furthermore, treatment with 
AMF-26 caused the redistribution of p58/ERGIC53, a marker for 
the ER-Golgi intermediate compartment (ERGIC) (53), from its 
normal compact localization to a dispersed cytoplasmic </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Property spheres on BFA and AMF-26. A, property spheres of BFA. B, property spheres of AMF-26. The spheres on each molecule are property 
spheres for molecular superposition. The colors of the spheres indicate the following properties: hydrophobic (HP; black), aromatic (AR; green), hydrogen-bond 
donors (HD; blue), hydrogen-bond acceptors (HA; red), and hydrogen-bond donors/acceptor (DA; purple). Large and small spheres indicate radii of 1 and 0.5 Å, 
respectively. C, superimposition of AMF-26 on BFA by the <rs type="software">SUPERPOSE</rs> program. AMF-26 is shown in green, and BFA is shown in orange. Sphere colors indicate 
the following properties: hydrophobic (white), aromatic (green), hydrogen-bond donors (blue), hydrogen-bond acceptors (red), and hydrogen-bond donors/ 
acceptor (purple). Large and small spheres represent radii of 1 and 0.5 Å, respectively. The AMF-26 and BFA spheres are represented by dotted and solid spheres, 
respectively. Only matched spheres are indicated. D and E, comparison between the BFA and AMF-26 complexes. D, X-ray structure of the Arf1-BFA-Sec7 
domain complex (PDB ID 1r8q). E, refined model of the Arf1-AMF-26-Sec7 domain complex. A and E chains are Arf1 and Sec7 domain, respectively. The 
hydrogen bonds and the electrostatic interactions are indicated by yellow and pink dashed lines, respectively. </p>

<p>Novel Golgi Inhibitor Shows Potent Antitumor Activity </p>

<p>FEBRUARY 3, 2012 • VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 6 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 3891 </p>

<p>localization (Fig. 5B). These effects were similar to those of 
BFA. 
We also examined the effects of AMF-26 on proteins associ-
ated with the TGN. AMF-26 affected adaptin ␥ or adaptin ␦, 
constituents of AP-1 or AP-2, respectively (54), and eventually </p>

<p>resulted in redistribution from the perinuclear region into the 
cytosol (Fig. 5, C and D). 
Concerning recycling endosomes, treatment of BFA is 
known to induce extensive formation of membrane tubules 
from endosomes (10, 55). Using Alexa 488-labeled transferrin, </p>

<p>FIGURE 5. Effects of AMF-26 on cis-Golgi, TGN, and recycling endosomes. BSY-1 cells were incubated with DMSO, BFA (1 M), or AMF-26 (1 M) for 1 h. The 
labeling with each Golgi marker protein (white) was as follows: A, ␤-COP (cis-Golgi); B, ERGIC-53 (cis-Golgi and ERGIC); C, adaptin ␥ (TGN); or D, adaptin ␦ (TGN). 
The localization of cis-Golgi and TGN resulted in redistribution from the perinuclear region (white arrowhead) into the cytosol. Scale bar, 20 m. E, BSY-1 cells 
were incubated with Alexa 488-labeled transferrin (white) for 1 h, and then treated with DMSO, BFA (1 M), or AMF-26 (1 M) for 1 h. AMF-26 induced extensive 
formation of membrane tubules from endosomes (white arrow). A similar result was found with BFA. Scale bar, 10 m. </p>

<p>Novel Golgi Inhibitor Shows Potent Antitumor Activity </p>



<p>VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 6 • FEBRUARY 3, 2012 </p>

<p>we analyzed the effect of AMF-26 on the formation of tubular 
endosomes. AMF-26 induced enlargement and tubulation of 
transferrin-positive endosomes (Fig. 5E), suggesting that 
AMF-26 has a similar effect on early/recycling endosomes as 
BFA. 
Correlation between Cell Growth Inhibition and Golgi 
Disruption-It is still uncertain whether the growth-inhibitory 
activity of BFA is related to its effects on Golgi disruption (56,  57). We examined the correlation between cell growth inhibi-
tion and Golgi disruption activity to investigate the causal rela-
tionship of these two events. Specifically, we examined the 
activities of AMF-26 and its five derivatives AMF-14, AMF-35, 
AMF-46, AMF-48, and AMF-59 (structural formula of each 
compound shown in Fig. 6A). In BSY-1 cells, AMF-26 exhibited 
the strongest activity of cell growth inhibition with a GI 50 of 12 
nM and that of Golgi disruption with an EC 50 of 27 nM. AMF-35 
displayed the weakest activities with a GI 50 and EC 50 of 14 and 
4.9 M, respectively, (Fig. 6, B and C). We next investigated 
whether the Golgi disruption activities (the logarithm of EC 50 ) 
of these six compounds were related to their growth inhibitory 
activities (the logarithm of GI 50 ). Our analysis revealed a statis-
tically significant correlation (r ϭ 0.92 and p ϭ 0.009) between 
these two activities (Fig. 6D). A statistically significant correla-
tion between the logarithm of EC 50 and the logarithm of GI 50  was also observed when six other cell lines were treated with 
AMF-26 (r ϭ 0.93 and p ϭ 0.02, Fig. 6E). Taken together, our 
results suggested that there was a causal relationship between 
the Golgi disruption and cell growth inhibition. 
AMF-26 Caused Apoptotic Cell Death-After a 24-h incu-
bation with AMF-26, the sub-G 1 population increased in a 
dose-dependent manner over that of the DMSO-treated 
controls, i.e. 8.4 (AMF-26, 100 nM) versus 1.9% (Fig. 7A). 
These differences in the sub-G 1 population were even 
greater after 48 h, i.e. AMF-26-treated cells 13.1 (AMF-26, 
100 nM) versus 2.1% (Fig. 7A). Furthermore, cleavage prod-
ucts of PARP were assessed by Western blot analysis of cell </p>

<p>lysates (Fig. 7B). After incubation for 24 h, a band corre-
sponding to cleaved PARP (89-kDa) was significantly stron-
ger in cell extracts of AMF-26-treated cells compared with 
DMSO-treated cells. After 48 h, the larger accumulation of 
cleaved PARP in AMF-26-treated cells was obvious, suggest-
ing apoptosis of AMF-26-treated cells. 
Analysis of the Antitumor Efficacy of Orally Administrated 
AMF-26 Using Xenografts of Human Breast Cancer BSY-1-Fi-
nally, we evaluated the antitumor activity of AMF-26 against 
human breast cancer BSY-1 xenografts. After formation of the 
tumors (100 -300 mm 
3 ), mice were orally administered 0 (con-
trol vehicle), 83, or 100 mg/kg of AMF-26 for 5 consecutive 
days. Administration of AMF-26 at 83 or 100 mg/kg induced 
almost complete tumor regression on day 21 (Fig. 7C, upper 
panel). To assess toxicity, we measured the body weight of the 
tumor-bearing mice. The weight of the tumor-bearing mice 
was slightly reduced by administration of AMF-26. After termi-
nation of the administration, the weight was rapidly regained 
but was not fully recovered during the observation (Fig. 7C, 
lower panel). These data suggested that AMF-26 treatment did 
not cause serious irreversible side effects. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, we identified a novel Golgi disruptor, AMF-26 
using COMPARE analysis followed by computer modeling/MD 
simulation and biological validations. AMF-26 is thought to 
induce Golgi disruption via the inhibition of Arf1 activation. 
The Golgi disrupting activity of AMF-26 was significantly cor-
related with its growth-inhibiting activity. Finally, our results 
showed that oral administration of AMF-26 induced the regres-
sion of human breast cancer BSY-1 xenografts. 
The Arf family of small GTPases plays a major role in main-
taining Golgi structure and driving Golgi membrane traffic (5,  7). It is known that the BFA-sensitive large ArfGEFs, such as 
GBF1, BIG1, and BIG2, are predominantly localized to the cis-
Golgi and TGN. After activation by GBF1, Arf1 mediates COPI </p>

<p>FIGURE 6. Correlation between cell growth inhibition and Golgi disruption. A, chemical structures of AMF-26 derivatives: AMF-14, AMF-35, AMF-46, 
AMF-48, and AMF-59. B, BSY-1 cells were treated with DMSO, AMF-26, and its derivatives, or BFA at different concentrations for 1 h, and then stained with 
antibodies against GBF-1. The numbers of cells whose Golgi was dispersed were then counted. Over 100 features were measured under each condition. C, the 
proliferation of BSY-1 cells treated with drugs was monitored as described above. Changes in the amounts of total cellular protein after 48 h of drug treatment 
were analyzed using the sulforhodamine B assay. D, Golgi dispersal activities were correlated with growth inhibitory activities between AMF-26 and its 
derivatives (Pearson correlation coefficients; r ϭ 0.92, p ϭ 0.009). Symbols represent the following: open circle, AMF-26; open square, AMF-48; closed square, 
AMF-59; open triangle, AMF-46; closed triangle, AMF-14; open diamond, AMF-35; cross, BFA-treated cells. E, Golgi dispersal activities were correlated with growth 
inhibitory activities between six cell lines of JFCR39 (Pearson correlation coefficients, r ϭ 0.93, p ϭ 0.02). </p>

<p>Novel Golgi Inhibitor Shows Potent Antitumor Activity </p>

<p>FEBRUARY 3, 2012 • VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 6 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 3893 </p>

<p>coat recruitment and enables vesicle transport between Golgi 
and ER (48). On the other hand, when activated by BIG1 or 
BIG2, Arf1 recruits adapter proteins, AP-1, AP-3, and 
AP-4(58), and Golgi-associated ␥-adaptin ear-containing Arf-
binding proteins, GGA1, GGA2, and GGA3 (59). These Arf1-
effector molecules mediate transport between TGN and endo-
somes (58). BFA inactivates Arf1 by inhibiting PPIs between 
Arf1 and Arf1GEFs, and subsequently induces the disruption of 
cis-Golgi and TGN, or affects the endosomal systems (10, 11). 
Furthermore, BFA showed tumor growth inhibition in vitro 
(12) and in vivo at an early stage (13). From the viewpoint of 
developing molecular-targeted drugs, BFA is attractive because 
its target, Arf1 and ArfGEF interaction, is unique. However, 
BFA and its derivatives have not progressed beyond the pre-
clinical stage of drug development (13, 14). 
Here we used COMPARE analysis to screen for compounds 
showing a BFA-like fingerprint, and identified AMF-26. BFA 
has a lactone ring, whereas AMF-26 has an octahydronaphtha-
lene ring with a side chain including a pyridine moiety. 
Although the chemical structure of AMF-26 is distinct from 
that of BFA, we verified that the two compounds share a similar 
molecular mode of action as expected from the COMPARE 
analysis. Moreover, computer modeling/MD simulation and bio-
logical validations suggested that AMF-26 inhibited the interac-
tion between Arf1 and BFA-sensitive large ArfGEFs. AMF-26 
induced the disruption of cis-Golgi and TGN at almost the same 
concentrations as BFA, and inhibited recycling of transferrin. 
These results indicate that AMF-26 is a novel inhibitor of Arf1 
activation whose chemical structure is different from BFA. 
Several other Golgi disruptors related to Arf activation have 
been reported (44, 57, 60 -62). These compounds showed inhi-</p>

<p>bition of membrane traffic. However, their precise modes of 
action appear to be different from that of AMF-26 and BFA. 
Moreover, compared with AMF-26 or BFA, these compounds 
resulted in much weaker inhibition of cell growth. 
It remains uncertain whether cell growth inhibition by BFA 
arises from Golgi disruption. Citterio et al. (56) indicated that 
decreased expression of GBF1, BIG1, or BIG2 by siRNA caused 
dispersion of the Golgi-localized protein and the inhibition of 
cell growth. We observed similar results in BSY-1 cells in our 
preliminary data. 
3 However, Pan et al. (57) reported that 
AG1478 showed a weak loss of cell viability. In the present 
study, we demonstrated that AMF-26 inhibited both Arf1 acti-
vation and tumor cell growth in BSY-1 cells. Moreover, 
AMF-26 and its derivatives showed a positive correlation 
between the Golgi-disrupting activity and the cell growth-in-
hibiting activity. We also found a positive correlation between 
the two when six other cancer cell lines were treated with AMF-
26. In our preliminary experiments, inactivation of the phos-
phatidylinositol 3-kinase pathway or Ras-MAPK pathway was 
not observed by exposure of cells to AMF-26 for 10 min (data 
not shown). Collectively, our results suggested a causal rela-
tionship between Golgi disruption and cell growth inhibition by 
AMF-26. Furthermore, in the present study, we found that 
AMF-26 induced apoptosis in tumor cells. Our observations 
agree with the report of Citterio et al. (56) indicating that 
decreased expression of GBF1 causes apoptosis. 
A previous study described the antitumor activity of BFA in 
early stage mouse subcutaneous models (13). In the course of </p>

<p>3 Y. Ohashi, H. Iijima, N. Yamaotsu, K. Yamazaki, S. Sato, M. Okamura, K. Sug-
imoto, S. Dan, and T. Yamori, unpublished data. </p>

<p>FIGURE 7. Antitumor activity of AMF-26. A and B, AMF-26 caused apoptosis on BSY-1 cell. A, cells were incubated with DMSO or with AMF-26 for 24 or 48 h. 
Percentages of the sub-G 1 population are indicated. AMF-26 influenced the sub-G 1 population in a dose-dependent manner. B, effect of AMF-26 on PARP 
cleavage. BSY-1 cells were incubated with AMF-26 for 24 or 48 h. Cells were lysed and the proteins in the cell extract were separated by SDS-PAGE and 
electroblotted onto a membrane. The membrane was then probed with antibodies against cleaved PARP and ␣-tubulin. Cleaved PARP protein was observed 
in AMF-26-treated cells. C, tumor growth and body weight in nude mice bearing human breast cancer BSY-1 xenografts. Fifteen nude mice were subcutane-
ously inoculated with a tumor fragment of 3 ϫ 3 ϫ 3 mm from the subcutaneous tumor developed in nude mice. When tumors reached a volume of 100 -300 
mm 
3 , animals were divided randomly into test groups, each with five mice (day 0). AMF-26 (83 or 100 mg/kg) was orally administered daily from day 0 to 5. 
AMF-26 data are the means of data from five mice. The upper panel shows the relative tumor volume. The lower panel shows the body weight change. 
Administration of AMF-26 induced complete tumor regression on day 21. Asterisks represent statistically significant differences from the control group (*, p Ͻ 
0.01; **, p Ͻ 0.005). Symbols represent the following: open circle, control vehicle; open square, AMF-26 (83 mg/kg); open triangle, AMF-26 (100 mg/kg) was orally 
administrated group; error bar, S.E. </p>

<p>Novel Golgi Inhibitor Shows Potent Antitumor Activity </p>



<p>VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 6 • FEBRUARY 3, 2012 </p>

<p>these studies, BFA was injected intraperitoneally twice a day. 
Frequent administration was necessary because the clearance 
of BFA is rapid (less than 20 min) (13), consistent with the 
observation that this compound is a substrate of glutathione 
S-transferase (63). Here, we demonstrated that oral administra-
tion of AMF-26 once a day induced almost complete regression 
of human breast cancer BSY-1 xenografts in nude mice. To the 
best of our knowledge, this is the first report describing the oral 
administration of an inhibitor targeting Arf1 activation that 
elicits strong antitumor activity without severe body weight 
loss. Further study on the pharmacokinetic profile of AMF-26 
remains to be performed. 
Very recently, AMF-26 was identified as an angiogenesis 
inhibitor by Watari et al. (64), who revealed that inhibition of 
VEGF receptor phosphorylation and NF-B signaling was 
involved in antiangiogenic activity in human umbilical vein 
endothelial cells. Therefore, the in vivo antitumor activity of 
AMF-26 shown in the present study may have partly resulted 
from its antiangiogenic activity in addition to its direct tumor 
growth inhibition. 
The COMPARE analysis is a powerful tool that can be used to 
identify small-molecule enzyme inhibitors, for example, telo-
merase inhibitor (FJ-5002) (45), a topoisomerase I and II inhib-
itor (MS-247) (19), and PI3K inhibitor (ZSTK474) (22, 46, 47). 
In this study, we exploited the COMPARE analysis to screen 
BFA-like small molecule inhibitors. Using this approach, we 
identified AMF-26 as a novel inhibitor of Arf1 activation, 
despite the fact that its chemical structure does not resemble 
that of BFA. From these results, the screening of chemicals 
guided by COMPARE analysis appears to be useful for the dis-
covery of novel drug candidates targeting various biological 
functions including the Golgi system. 
In conclusion, we identified a novel Golgi disruptor targeting 
Arf1 activation, AMF-26, and showed that it induced complete 
regression of human breast cancer BSY-1 xenografts. These 
data suggest that AMF-26 is a novel drug candidate for cancer 
treatment targeting Arf1 activation. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments-We thank Dr. R. H. Shoemaker and Dr. K. D. 
Paull for discussion on the establishment of JFCR39 and COMPARE 
analysis; Y. Nishimura, M. Seki, Y. Mukai, and Y. Yamazaki for tech-
nical assistance; NIPPON SHINYAKU CO., Ltd. for provision of 
AMF-26 and its derivatives and for discussion concerning the nature 
of the compounds; and Dr. S Sakaushi (Osaka Prefecture University, 
Osaka, Japan) for advice on time lapse analysis. </p>



<p>Novel Golgi Inhibitor Shows Potent Antitumor Activity </p>

<p>FEBRUARY 3, 2012 • VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 6 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 3895 </p>



<p>Novel Golgi Inhibitor Shows Potent Antitumor Activity </p>



<p>VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 6 • FEBRUARY 3, 2012 </p>



<p>Novel Golgi Inhibitor Shows Potent Antitumor Activity </p>

<p>FEBRUARY 3, 2012 • VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 6 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 3897 </p>

</text></tei>