<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3368359" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>† These authors contributed equally </p>

<p>to this work. </p>

<p>Acetylcholinesterase (AChE) expression was found to be induced in the mammalian CNS, 
including the retina, by different types of stress leading to cellular apoptosis. Here, we 
tested possible involvement of AChE in hyperglycemia-induced apoptosis in a retinal 
cell line. Y79 retinoblastoma cells were incubated in starvation media (1% FBS and 
1 mg/ml glucose) for 16-24 h, and then exposed to hyperglycemic environment by raising 
extracellular glucose concentrations to a final level of 3.5 mg/ml or 6 mg/ml. Similar levels 
of mannitol were used as control for hyperosmolarity. Cells were harvested at different 
time intervals for analysis of apoptosis and AChE protein expression. Apoptosis was 
detected by the cleavage of Poly ADP-ribose polymerase (PARP) using western blot, 
and by Terminal deoxynucleotidyl-transferase-mediated dUTP nick-end-labeling (TUNEL) 
assay. AChE protein expression and activity was detected by western blot and by the 
Karnovsky and Roots method, respectively. Mission TM shRNA for AChE was used to 
inhibit AChE protein expression. Treating Y79 cells with 3.5 mg/ml of glucose, but not 
with 3.5 mg/ml mannitol, induced apoptosis which was confirmed by TUNEL assay and 
by cleavage of PARP. A part of the signaling pathway accompanying the apoptotic process 
involved up-regulation of the AChE-R variant and an N-extended AChE variant as verified 
at the mRNA and protein level. Inhibition of AChE protein expression by shRNA protected 
Y79 cell from entering the apoptotic pathway. Our data suggest that expression of an 
N-extended AChE variant, most probably an R isoform, is involved in the apoptotic pathway 
caused by hyperglycemia in Y79 cells. </p>

<p>Acetylcholinesterase (AChE) is an essential enzyme in choliner-
gic synapses since it hydrolyses acetylcholine, thereby terminating 
cholinergic excitation. However, AChE was also found in tissues 
devoid of cholinergic innervations (Small et al., 1996), indicat-
ing potential non-cholinergic functions for this enzyme includ-
ing response to stress (Grisaru et al., 2001) and neurogenesis 
(Robitzki et al., 1998; Bytyqi et al., 2004). There are three dif-
ferent isoforms of AChE resulting from alternative splicing of a 
single gene: synaptic (S), erythrocytic (E), and read-through (R) 
(Soreq and Seidman, 2001). Each of these three C-terminal vari-
ants can appear in one of two forms depending upon the length of 
its N-terminus; a normal N-terminus and an extended one. Thus, 
in principal AChE can appear in six different isoforms. Different 
AChE variants are believed to be involved in different physiolog-
ical and/or pathological processes. AChE-S is the variant located 
in cholinergic synapses and responsible for termination of cholin-
ergic excitation (reviewed in Meshorer and Soreq, 2006). AChE-R 
was found to play a role in the response to stress in laboratory 
animals (Kaufer et al., 1998; Shohami et al., 2000). Forced swim-
ming (physiological stress) induced AChE-R mRNA expression in </p>

<p>FVB/N mice (Kaufer et al., 1998). 2 -O-methyl RNA-capped anti-
sense oligonucleotide (AS-ODN) against AChE mRNA blocked 
over-expression of AChE-R in head-injured mice, reducing the 
number of dead CA3 hippocampal neurons and facilitating neu-
rological recovery (Shohami et al., 2000). A novel AChE variant 
with an extended N-terminus was found to exacerbate light-
induced photoreceptor degeneration in albino rats. Treatment 
with AS-ODNs significantly reduced the expression of this pro-
tein, and lowered the degree of light-induced functional damage 
as expressed by electroretinogram recordings (Kehat et al., 2007). 
AChE was found to be expressed during apoptosis in different cell 
types in which the apoptotic pathway could be prevented by AS-
ODNs of AChE (Soreq et al., 1994; Zhang et al., 2002). It was 
later reported that the AChE variant involved in apoptosis was 
the N-extended AChE-S one (Toiber et al., 2008, 2009). There is 
evidence regarding the correlation between stress-activated pro-
tein kinase family and apoptosis-associated AChE expression. 
Phosphorylation of c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK) and its down-
stream transcription factor, c-Jun, was enhanced during apopto-
sis induced by the DNA topoisomerase inhibitors etoposide or 
excisanin A, in colon cancer cell line SW620. A corresponding </p>

<p>Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>June 2012 | Volume 5 | Article 69 | 1 </p>

<p>MOLECULAR NEUROSCIENCE </p>

<p>Shehadeh Masha'our et al. </p>

<p>AChE involvement in hyperglycemia-induced apoptosis </p>

<p>increase in AChE expression in the apoptotic cells was observed. 
This up-regulation in AChE was eliminated by administering a 
JNK inhibitor, silencing JNK with siRNA or antagonizing c-Jun 
with a dominant-negative c-Jun mutant (Deng et al., 2006). 
Apoptosis-programmed cell death, is an active process that 
has well-documented biochemical and morphological character-
istics, including nuclei break into several pycnotic granules as 
a result of DNA fragmentation and cell shrinkage (Majno and  Joris, 1995). In the retina, apoptosis plays a major role in the 
loss of visual cells in degenerative disorders such as Retinitis 
Pigmentosa and Age-Related Macular Degeneration (reviewed in 
Wenzel et al., 2005), and also occurs in Diabetic Detinopathy 
(Barber et al., 1998). Biochemical, physiological, and morpholog-
ical alterations have been observed in non-vascular retinal cells 
(Barber et al., 1998; Li et al., 2002; Mohr et al., 2002; Kusner et al.,  2004; Xi et al., 2005) during early stages of diabetes in animal 
models, raising the possibility that hyperglycemia is detrimental 
to retinal neurons prior to any vascular involvement. Rats with 
streptozotocin-induced-diabetes exhibited reduced electroretino-
gram responses as early as two weeks after the onset of the 
diabetes. The rats also expressed glial fibrilary acidic protein 
(GFAP) in Muller cells before any vascular abnormality was 
detected in the retina, a sign of early retinal damage (Li et al.,  2002). Several studies have shown that Muller cells incubated 
in elevated glucose concentrations undergo apoptosis as deter-
mined in part by annexin-V staining and activation of caspase 
3 (Lorenzi and Gerhardinger, 2001; Mohr et al., 2002; Kusner  et al., 2004; Xi et al., 2005). Our goals were to test the hypoth-
esis that AChE is involved in hyperglycemia-induced apoptosis 
of retinal cell line and to identify the AChE variant included in 
this process. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>CELL CULTURE </p>

<p>Y79 (HTB18) retinoblastoma cell line was obtained from 
the American Type Culture Collection (ATCC, The global 
Bioresource Center, USA), and cultured in DMEM containing 
10% fetal bovine serum (FBS), 4.5 mg/ml glucose, 1% glutamine, 
1% penicillin, and streptomycin (HG-medium) at 37 • C in a 
humidified atmosphere with 5% CO2/95% air. Culture medium 
was changed twice weekly. Twenty-four hours before experi-
ments, the cells were transferred to a starvation medium con-
taining 1 mg/ml glucose, mimicking physiologic levels of blood 
glucose concentrations and 1% FBS, 1% glutamine, 1% peni-
cillin, and streptomycin (LG-medium). Then, glucose was added 
to the Y79 cells to reach a final concentration of 3.5 mg/ml 
or 6 mg/ml mimicking hyperglycemia (final concentrations in 
media: 3.5 mg/ml, 19.4 mM, 350 mg/dl and 6 mg/ml, 33.3 mM, 
600 mg/dl, respectively). Identical mannitol concentrations were 
added to the media instead of glucose, to isolate the effect of 
hyperglycemia from hyperosmolarity. 
Cells were harvested at different time points (1, 2, and 24 h 
after the addition of glucose/mannitol) and analyzed for apopto-
sis and AChE expression and activity. It is important to note that 
since serum is known to contain a complex mixture of growth fac-
tors, cytokines, and other signaling molecules that stimulate the 
expression of several genes like c-fos, c-myc, cyclin D1, and VEGF </p>

<p>in cultured cells (Harris et al., 2001), it was important to reduce 
the percentage of the FBS to the minimum (1%) needed for 
the Y79 retinoblastoma cells to maintain the cells in a quiescent 
un-stimulated phase. </p>

<p>DETECTION OF APOPTOSIS BY TUNEL </p>

<p>Apoptosis was detected by Terminal Deoxynucleotidyl-
transferase-mediated dUTP nick-end-labeling (TUNEL) using 
the fluorescein-dUTP-in situ cell death detection kit (Roche 
Diagnostic GmbH, Mannheim, Germany). For TUNEL assay, cells 
were seeded on microscope cover glasses pre-coated with 0.1% 
poly-D-lysine [prepared in 100 mM Na 2 B 4 O 7 .10(H 2 O) buffer 
at pH 8.2], and cultured over-night in the HG-medium. After 
confirming attachment of cells to the cover slips, medium was 
changed to LG-medium for over-night starvation. Glucose was 
added to the starved cells at different concentrations and for 
different time periods, after which TUNEL was performed accord-
ing to manufacturer's instructions. Briefly, cells were fixed in 4% 
paraformaldehyde for 1 h, and then washed in PBS. Cells were 
permeabilized in a solution containing 0.1% Triton X-100 in 0.1% 
sodium citrate on ice, washed twice with PBS and incubated with 
TUNEL reaction mixture for 60 min at 37 • C in a humidified 
atmosphere in the dark. Slides were washed twice with PBS, stained 
with DAPI for nuclei detection, and washed again with PBS. The 
cover glasses with cells were flapped on glass slides covered with a 
few drops of mounting media (DakoCytomation), photographed 
using an upright fluorescence microscope (Axioscop 2, ZEISS), 
and processed by the <rs type="software">Image Pro</rs> software. </p>

<p>WESTERN BLOT ANALYSIS </p>

<p>Apoptosis was also detected by PARP cleavage from 116 kDa into 
89 kDa fragments using western blot analysis. Since PARP is a 
nuclear protein, we decided to test its cleavage in nuclear extracts 
and not in whole-cell extracts to prevent dilution. Nuclear extracts 
were prepared and collected as described previously (Schreiber  et al., 1989). Proteins were separated by 10% polyacrylamide gel 
electrophoresis and transferred onto a nitrocellulose membrane. 
Membranes were incubated in 5% non-fat dry milk in PBS for 
1 h, and subsequently probed with a primary monoclonal anti-
body: anti-PARP (SeroTec, UK) that detects the full length as 
well as the cleaved PARP. HRP-conjugated Donkey-anti-mouse 
(Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories, Inc., USA) was used 
as secondary antibody. Bound antibodies were detected using 
enhanced chemiluminescence reagent-ECL (prepared locally) and 
visualized by autoradiography. AChE expression was also detected 
using western blot analysis. Cytoplasmic extracts were prepared 
(Schreiber et al., 1989), and separated on 12.5% polyacrylamide gel 
electrophoresis and transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane as 
described above. A rabbit anti-human polyclonal AChE antibody, 
which detects all isoforms of AChE, was used (sc-11409, diluted 
1:500 from Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc., USA). A mouse 
monoclonal antibody anti-α-Tubulin (T6199, diluted 1:4000 
from Sigma-aldrich, USA) was used for normalizing cytoplas-
mic protein loading. HRP-conjugated Donkey-anti-rabbit or anti 
mouse (1:5000 diluted in 50% glycerol, Jackson ImmunoResearch 
Laboratories, Inc., USA) was used as secondary antibody. 
Densitometry analysis was done by <rs type="software">TotalLab Quant</rs> software. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>June 2012 | Volume 5 | Article 69 | 2 </p>

<p>Shehadeh Masha'our et al. </p>

<p>AChE involvement in hyperglycemia-induced apoptosis </p>

<p>AChE ACTIVITY </p>

<p>The method of AChE cytochemical staining is based on the ability 
of AChE to hydrolyze acetylthiocholine, which contains a sul-
fur atom substituted for oxygen in the ester linkage. Enzymatic 
cleavage of acetylthiocholine by AChE yields acetate and thio-
choline, whose sulphydryl group reduces ferricyanide to fer-
rocyanide. Brown copper ferrocyanide (Hatchett's brown), is 
formed at the site of enzymatic activity and immediately pre-
cipitates thus marking the site of AChE activity. The proce-
dure for detecting AChE activity was originally described by 
Karnovsky and Roots (Karnovsky and Roots, 1964), and mod-
ified by Hanker et al. (Hanker et al., 1973) and Kobayashi  et al. (Kobayashi et al., 1994). Briefly, cells were seeded on 
microscope cover glasses while cultured in the DMEM cul-
turing medium. Upon being dried at room temperature, the 
cells were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for 1 h, and then 
washed in PBS. The cover glasses were then covered with 
1 ml per slide of a mixture containing: 65 mM sodium phos-
phate pH 6.0 containing 0.5 mg acetylthiocholine iodide, 5 mM 
sodium citrate solution, 10 mM copper sulphate solution, 0.5 mM 
potassium ferricyanide, 0.1 ml DDW, and 10 −2 mM of Iso-
OMPA (Tetra-isopropyl pyrophosphoramide for inhibition of 
Butyrylcholinesterase) at room temperature for overnight incu-
bation. The cover glasses were flapped on glass slides covered 
with few drops of immuno-mount (Thermo scientific, USA). 
Cells preparations were viewed and photographed under light 
microscopy. </p>

<p>RNA EXTRACTION AND REAL-TIME RT-PCR </p>

<p>Total RNA was extracted by TRI-REAGENT™ (Sigma Aldrich, 
St. Louis, USA), according to Sigma's product information. RNA 
samples (0.2 μg) were used for cDNA synthesis prepared by the 
Verso™ cDNA Kit (Thermo SCIENTIFIC, UK). Real-time RT-
PCR was performed using the Rotor-Gene Q (Qiagen, Corbett 
life science, Germany) and SYBR green master mix ABsolute™ 
Blue (Thermo SCIENTIFIC, UK). Different primer sequences for 
human AChE variants were used according to previous descrip-
tion; Primer sequences (listed below), for AChE-S, AChE-R, 18S 
rRNA (house-keeping reference transcript) (Berson et al., 2008)  and for N-extended AChE (Ofek et al., 2007). Serial dilutions of 
samples served to evaluate primers efficiency and the appropriate 
cDNA concentration that yields linear changes. Annealing tem-
perature was 60 • C for all primers. Melting curve analysis verified 
the identity of end products. 
PCR primers were employed as follows: </p>

<p>hAChE-S (Accession no NM000665); 
(Forward primer position 1789-1807) -5 -cttcctccccaaattgctc-3 
(Reverse primer position 1901-1920) -5 -tcctgcttgctgtagtggtc-3 
hAChE-R (Accession no AY750146); 
(Forward primer position 7092-7110) -5 cttcctccccaaattgctc-3 
(Reverse primer position 7177-7196) -5 -ggggagaagagaggggt 
tac-3 </p>

<p>h N-extended-AChE (Accession no AY389977); 
(Forward primer position 189-207) -5 -atgctaggcctggtgatgt-3 
(Reverse primer position 285-303) -5 -ggcagtggaaacttctgga-3 </p>

<p>h18S rRNA (Accession no M10098); 
(Forward primer position 1049-1068) -5 -cgccgctagaggtgaaa 
ttc-3 
(Reverse primer position 1092-1110) -5 -ttggcaaatgctttcgctc-3 </p>

<p>MISSION™ shRNA FOR AChE </p>

<p>shRNA packed in Lenti viral particles were prepared using Lenti 
compatible vectors; VSVG and delta-NRF which were kindly pro-
vided by Prof. Gera Neufeld (Faculty of Medicine, Technion), 
and five pLKO.1-puro vectors each cloned with a potential 
translational-blocker-complimentary sequence (21 bp long) to 
AChE exons (Sigma Aldrich, St. Louis, USA). Each pLKO.1 
vector together with the two vectors mentioned above were co-
transfected in 293-T cell line (using TransIT®-LT-1 Transfection 
reagent, Mirus Corporation, USA). Forty-eight hours post-
transfection, medium containing viruses was collected and fil-
tered through a 0.45 μm filter, and was used to infect Y79 cells 
for 48 h. Puromycin (2.5 μg/ml) was added to culture media for 
an additional 48 h for selecting positive-Lenti-infected-cells. Prior 
to the addition of 3.5 mg/ml glucose, infected-Y79 cells were 
serum starved under the same conditions as mentioned above. 
At different time intervals following exposure to glucose, cells 
were harvested for testing by Western Blot and TUNEL assays as 
mentioned above. </p>

<p>STATISTICS </p>

<p>Statistically significant differences were calculated by t-test (2 
tails). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>APOPTOSIS INDUCTION BY HYPERGLYCEMIA </p>

<p>Keeping Y79 cells for 1 or 24 h in 1 mg/ml glucose (5.5 mM), 
mimicking physiologic conditions did not induce apoptosis 
(Figure 1A). Raising the level of glucose to 3.5 mg/ml (19.4 mM) 
or to 6 mg/ml (33.3 mM), for 1 h also did not result in apopto-
sis (Figure 1A). However, after 24 h in high glucose (3.5 mg/ml 
or 6 mg/ml-mimicking hyperglycemia in diabetes), apoptosis 
was stimulated as evident by abundance of TUNEL positive cells 
(Figure 1A). 
Counting TUNEL positive cells, indicated that incubating cells 
in 3.5 mg/ml or 6 mg/ml glucose for 24 h increased apoptosis sig-
nificantly (p = 0.05), by 7-and 10-fold, respectively, as compared 
to cells exposed to the same concentrations of glucose for 1 h 
(Figure 1B). 
Full-length PARP is an 116 kDa nuclear protein involved in the 
repair of DNA, in differentiation and in chromatin structure for-
mation. During apoptosis this protein is cleaved by caspase-3, and 
possibly by other caspases, into an 89 kDa fragment (Lazebnik  et al., 1994). Thus, demonstration of PARP cleavage is accepted 
as a molecular indicator for the induction of an apoptotic pro-
cess. Since cleavage of PARP is an early stage (between 1 and 
3 h) in apoptosis, we used western blot to measure its cleav-
age in nuclear extracts of cells prepared after 1 h incubation in 
different glycemic conditions as shown in Figure 2A. PARP cleav-
age was induced in cells exposed to 3.5 mg/ml or 6 mg/ml of 
glucose for 1 h, as compared to 1 mg/ml of glucose. To test a 
possible osmotic effect induced by hyperglycemia and leading </p>

<p>Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>June 2012 | Volume 5 | Article 69 | 3 </p>

<p>Shehadeh Masha'our et al. </p>

<p>AChE involvement in hyperglycemia-induced apoptosis </p>

<p>FIGURE 1 | Hyperglicemia (3.5 mg/ml or 6 mg/ml of glucose)-induced 
apoptosis induction in Y79 cells. (A) Cells tested by TUNEL to detect 
apoptosis (green) and stained with DAPI for detecting nuclei (blue). Y79 cells 
were pre-treated for 16-24 h in starvation medium (1% FBS and 1 mg/ml 
glucose), and then incubated for 1 h with 3.5 mg/ml glucose did not show </p>

<p>signs of apoptosis (left); while cells incubated for 24 h in 3.5 mg/ml or 
6 mg/ml glucose are TUNEL positive. Scale bar is 50 μm. (B) TUNEL positive 
cells were counted and calculated as fold of control (cells cultured in 
starvation media containing 1% FBS and 1 mg/ml glucose) and plotted in 
histograms. Values are means ± SEM, (N = 3).  *  p &lt; 0.05, #p = 0.05. </p>

<p>to apoptosis, identical mannitol concentrations were added to 
starved-Y79 cells and PARP cleavage was examined after 1 h. We 
assessed quantitatively the magnitude of PARP cleavage and its 
significance from the cleaved/non-cleaved PARP ratio, as sug-
gested by others (Biggs et al., 2001; Grader-Beck et al., 2007). We 
scanned the western blots and calculate the ratio of cleaved/non-
cleaved PARP as shown in Figure 2B. PARP cleavage was similar 
in cells treated with 6 mg/ml of glucose or mannitol, but was more </p>

<p>prominent, and statistically significant (p &lt; 0.05), in cells treated 
with 3.5 mg/ml of glucose which showed 2.2 ± 0.16-fold of con-
trol, as compared to the same concentration of mannitol which 
showed 1.3 ± 0.22-fold of control. These results indicate that 
hyperglycemia caused by 6 mg/ml of glucose, induced apoptosis 
primarily as a result of hyperosmolarity, while at a lower concen-
tration of 3.5 mg/ml of glucose, apoptosis was induced mainly as a 
result of hyperglycemia and to a lesser extent by hyperosmolarity. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>June 2012 | Volume 5 | Article 69 | 4 </p>

<p>Shehadeh Masha'our et al. </p>

<p>AChE involvement in hyperglycemia-induced apoptosis </p>

<p>FIGURE 2 | Cleavage of PARP in nuclear extracts of Y79 cells 
treated by adding glucose or mannitol. Y79 cells were incubated for 
16-24 h in starvation medium (1% FBS and 1 mg/ml glucose), and then 
glucose or mannitol was added (except in control) to reach a concentration 
of 3.5 mg/ml or 6 mg/ml and incubated for 1 or 2 h. (A) Nuclear extracts 
were prepared and run on SDS-PAGE, blotted, and probed with </p>

<p>anti-PARP as described under Materials and Methods. (B) Three 
independent experiments were conducted and densitometry values 
were calculated for cleaved to non-cleaved ratios, and plotted in 
histograms as fold of control (cells cultured in starvation media containing 
1% FBS and 1 mg/ml glucose). Values are means ± SEM, (N = 3). 
 *  p &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>FIGURE 3 | AChE expression in Y79 cells treated by adding glucose 
or mannitol. Y79 cells were treated first for 16-24 h in starvation medium 
(1% FBS and 1 mg/ml glucose), and then incubated with 3.5 mg/ml or 
6 mg/ml of glucose or mannitol for 1 or 2 h. Following 1 or 2 h incubation </p>

<p>cytoplasmic extracts were prepared and run on SDS-PAGE, blotted, and 
probed with anti-AChE or anti-α-Tubulin (for loading control) as described 
under Materials and Methods. The western blot shown is one of two 
independent experiments. </p>

<p>AChE EXPRESSION INDUCED BY HYPERGLYCEMIA </p>

<p>Figure 3 shows western blot analysis for AChE expression in Y79 
cells following 1 h or 2 h incubation in different media. AChE 
expression was increased in Y79 cells treated with 3.5 mg/ml 
glucose (G) for 1 h and decreased after 2 h to control lev-
els. AChE expression was not increased in cells treated with </p>

<p>6 mg/ml glucose or in cells treated with either 3.5 mg/ml or 
6 mg/ml mannitol (M). The dispersed bands seen in Figure 3 
in the range of 50-75 kDa probably reflect the formation 
of covalent PRiMA-AChE complexes or differences in the 
degree of glycosylation of AChE subunits (Darreh-Shori et al.,  2004). </p>

<p>Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>June 2012 | Volume 5 | Article 69 | 5 </p>

<p>Shehadeh Masha'our et al. </p>

<p>AChE involvement in hyperglycemia-induced apoptosis </p>

<p>To test whether the hyperglycemia-induced expression of 
AChE is also accompanied by increased AChE activity, we tested 
AChE activity in Y79 cells exposed to glucose concentrations that 
induced apoptosis. AChE activity, as demonstrated by Karnovsky 
and Roots staining (Karnovsky and Roots, 1964) (Figure 4A), 
was calculated relative to control conditions (1 mg/ml glucose), 
and was found to increase by 7.0 ± 1.9-fold in cells treated with 
3.5 mg/ml glucose for 1 h. In agreement with AChE expression 
pattern, AChE activity decreased with time after exposure to 
high glucose (3.5 mg/ml) and after 24 h was only 1.3 ± 0.34-
fold relative to control (Figure 4B). This decrease within 24 h was 
statistically significant (p &lt; 0.05). AChE activity in cells exposed 
to 3.5 mg/ml glucose for 1 h was significantly (p &lt; 0.05) higher 
compared to cells exposed for the same time period to 6 mg/ml 
glucose. AChE activity was not increased in cells treated with 
6 mg/ml glucose for the same time intervals (Figure 4B). 
Since AChE was detected in the cytoplasmic (Figure 3) frac-
tion, and in part of the experiments also in the membranous 
fraction (data not shown), we hypothesized that the isoforms 
detected by the western blot assays might be the short cytoplas-
mic R monomeric soluble isoform, and the membranous one 
might be the longer N-extended AChE (R or S variants) and/or 
the AChE-S variant. To test this hypothesis, Reverse Transcription 
(RT) real-time PCR was performed. As seen in Figure 5, mRNA </p>

<p>expression levels corresponding to the AChE-S isoform were low 
and did not change significantly after 15-, 30-or 60-min incu-
bation with 3.5 mg/ml of glucose. However, mRNA expression 
transcripts tested for the AChE-R or the N-extended isoforms, 
were significantly (p &lt; 0.05) up-regulated by 1.5 ± 0.15 and by 
1.4 ± 0.14-fold respectively, compared to control Y79 cells. </p>

<p>AChE EXPRESSION AND APOPTOSIS </p>

<p>In order to examine whether AChE expression plays a role in 
the hyperglycemia-induced apoptosis of Y79 cells, we tested five 
AChE shRNA sequences each cloned in pLKO.1-Lenti compat-
ible vector (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, USA). An empty pLKO.1 
vector (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, USA), devoid of a relevant 
shRNA sequence was used as control. As shown in Figure 6A, the 
expression of AChE tested under glucose exposure in the pres-
ence of the first sequences sh-1 (lane 3), was high and similar to 
that expressed in the presence of the sh-control-sequence (lane 2). 
The expression of AChE in these samples was considerably higher 
compared to sh-control Lenti-infected Y79 cells, which remained 
under 1 mg/ml glucose (lane1). These data indicate that sh-1 was 
not an efficient sequence for blocking AChE translation. 
A partial inhibition of AChE protein expression was observed 
with sh-2, sh-3, and sh-5 (lanes 4, 5, and 7, respectively), as indi-
cated by the weaker band of AChE protein. The most efficient </p>

<p>FIGURE 4 | AChE activity in Y79 cells treated with glucose. Y79 cells 
were pre-treated for 16-24 h in starvation medium (1% FBS and 1 mg/ml of 
glucose), and then with 3.5 mg/ml or 6 mg/ml glucose for 1 h or 24 h, after 
which Karnovsky and Roots assay was performed. Positive Karnovsky and 
Roots staining is seen in (A) on the right side compared to the negative </p>

<p>control at the left. Scale bar is 50 μm. (B) Three independent experiments at 
which about 20 fields of cells (from each experiment) were counted for each 
treatment, calculated, and plotted as fold of control (cells cultured in 
starvation media containing 1% FBS and 1 mg/ml glucose) in histograms. 
Values are mean ± SEM, (N = 3).  *  p &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>June 2012 | Volume 5 | Article 69 | 6 </p>

<p>Shehadeh Masha'our et al. </p>

<p>AChE involvement in hyperglycemia-induced apoptosis </p>

<p>FIGURE 5 | mRNA expression of N-extended AChE, AChE-S, and 
AChE-R isoforms following treatment of Y79 cells with glucose for 1 h. 
Y79 cells were pre-treated for 16-24 h in starvation medium (1% FBS and 
1 mg/ml of glucose) and then with 3.5 mg/ml glucose for different time 
intervals. Total RNA was extracted and cDNA was prepared for real-time 
PCR procedure as described under Materials and Methods. Results are 
presented as fold of control cells cultured in starvation media. Values are 
means ± SEM, (N = 4).  *  p &lt; 0.05, #p = 0.12. </p>

<p>blockage of translation was found with sh-4 (lane 6) in which 
the AChE band is barely visible. Equal loading of total protein is 
confirmed by the α-Tubulin band, shown in Figure 6A. 
We chose Y79 cells, expressing either AChE mRNA sh-4 or 
AChE mRNA sh-5 to test the effectiveness of sh-4 and sh-
5 in blocking hyperglycemia-induced apoptosis. Starved Lenti-
infected Y79 cells with sh-4, sh-5, or sh-control were incubated 
for 24 h in 3.5 mg/ml or left in 1 mg/ml glucose media and 
TUNEL assay was performed. Figure 6B shows representative pic-
tures of cells undergoing TUNEL assay, and Figure 6C shows the 
fraction (percentage) of TUNEL positive cells of total number 
of cells. Y79 cells expressing sh-control underwent a signifi-
cant apoptotic effect 24 h after incubation in 3.5 mg/ml glucose 
(Figure 6B, 2nd row), compared to sh-control Lenti-infected 
Y79 cells which remained under 1 mg/ml glucose (Figure 6B, 
1st row); 75 ± 7.1% and 14.9 ± 3.0%, respectively (p &lt; 0.05) 
(Figure 6C). A significant (p &lt; 0.05) inhibition of apoptosis 
was seen in sh-4 Lenti-infected Y79 cells following 24 h incu-
bation in 3.5 mg/ml of glucose addition (Figure 6B, 4th row), 
compared to sh-control Lenti-infected Y79 treated under the 
same conditions (Figure 6B, 2nd row), 25.2 ± 8.4% and 75 
± 7.1%, respectively (Figure 6C). No significant induction of 
apoptosis was seen between sh-4 Lenti-infected Y79 cells incu-
bated under 3.5 mg/ml glucose (Figure 6B, 4th row), and sh-4 
Lenti infected Y79 cells, which remained under 1 mg/ml glucose 
(Figure 6B, 3rd row), 25.2 ± 8.4% and 36.5 ± 7.2%, respectively 
(Figure 6C). sh-5 was also effective in blocking hyperglycemia-
induced apoptosis. The fraction of TUNEL positive cells was 
significantly (p &lt; 0.05) reduced by sh-5 in Y79 cells incubated 
for 24 h in 3.5 mg/ml glucose (Figure 6B, 6th row) compared to 
sh-control cells incubated under the same conditions (Figure 6B, 
2nd row); 52.8 ± 3.4% and 75 ± 7.1%, respectively (Figure 6C). </p>

<p>No significant differences were found in the fraction of TUNEL 
positive cells between sh-5 Lenti-infected Y79 cells incubated in 
3.5 mg/ml glucose for 24 h (Figure 6B, 6th row), compared to sh-
5 Lenti-infected Y79 cells which remained under 1 mg/ml glucose 
(Figure 6B, 5th row), 52.8 ± 3.4% and 36 ± 8%, respectively 
(Figure 6C). 
The TUNEL results were strengthened by measurements of 
PARP cleavage in nuclear extracts of the sh-Lenti infected lines; 
sh-control, sh-4, and sh-5. The western blot shown in Figure 7A 
and the densitometry results plotted in Figure 7B, show that 
PARP was cleaved by almost 3-fold in sh-control Lenti infected 
Y79 cells following 1 h incubation in 3.5 mg/ml glucose com-
pared to cells remaining in 1 mg/ml glucose. In contrast, cleavage 
of PARP could not be detected in the sh-4 and sh-5 Lenti-
infected Y79 cells, where AChE translation was blocked. The 
TUNEL and PARP results and the AChE protein expression data 
seen in Figures 6 and 7, suggest that inhibition of AChE protein 
expression prevents Y79 cells from entering into the apoptotic 
cascade. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Apoptosis is an essential process during development and differ-
entiation, and following exposure to damaging insults. It removes 
unwanted cells, which may be injured or misplaced, thus pre-
venting the spread of pathological processes from injured cells to 
healthy ones. This naturally occurring cell death is prominent in 
neurons of CNS including the retina during development (Young,  1984; Rodier, 1995). Apoptosis also occurs in the adult CNS tis-
sue subjected to a variety of stressful events such as pathological 
changes observed in both Alzheimer's disease and other neurode-
generative disorders in brain (Sasaki et al., 1998). In the adult 
retina, apoptosis is observed after subjecting it to photic stress 
(Hafezi et al., 1999; Grimm et al., 2001), or to metabolic stress 
such as hyperglycemia (Barber et al., 1998; Mohr et al., 2002;  Kusner et al., 2004; Xi et al., 2005). 
Here, apoptosis was induced in a retinal Y79 cell line by 
exposure to hyperglycemia, and was assessed by PARP cleav-
age as a molecular indication for apoptosis process (Figure 2), 
and by positive TUNEL staining as indication of apoptotic cells 
(Figure 1). Part of this effect could be attributed to hyperosmo-
larity, as tested by comparing the effects of adding glucose to 
those induced by adding mannitol, but exposure to 3.5 mg/ml 
glucose induced apoptosis mainly by hyperglycemia (Figure 2). 
These results are comparable to previous findings in different 
cell types such as endothelial cells (McGinn et al., 2003), peri-
cytes (Naruse et al., 2000), myocytes (Shizukuda et al., 2002), and 
neuronal cells (Lelkes et al., 2001), undergoing apoptosis when 
exposed to glucose, but not to mannitol until a specific osmolarity 
level was reached (0.33-0.8%), depending on the cell type. 
It should be noted that 6 mg/ml glucose induced a lesser degree 
of apoptosis compared to 3.5 mg/ml glucose, as indicated by 
PARP cleavage (Figure 2), but not by TUNEL (Figure 1). This 
suggests different pathways for hyperglycemia-induced apoptosis 
compared to hyperosmolarity-induced apoptosis. Indeed, dif-
ferent mechanisms for apoptosis induction by hyperglycemia 
and hyperosmolarity were described (Igarashi et al., 1999), 
showing that glucose concentrations in the range 11-16.5 mM </p>

<p>Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>June 2012 | Volume 5 | Article 69 | 7 </p>

<p>Shehadeh Masha'our et al. </p>

<p>AChE involvement in hyperglycemia-induced apoptosis </p>

<p>FIGURE 6 | Continued </p>

<p>(2-3 mg/ml, respectively), could activate p38 kinase associated 
with apoptosis, via a PKC-delta isoform-dependent pathway, 
while higher glucose or mannitol concentrations activated p38 
kinase by hyperosmolarity via a PKC-independent pathway 
(Igarashi et al., 1999). </p>

<p>Although the molecular mechanisms underlying apoptosis 
have been extensively studied, these mechanisms and the inter-
actions between the proteins which are involved seem to be very 
complex and much remains to be elucidated. Increasing body 
of evidence has shown that AChE may be involved in apoptosis </p>

<p>Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>June 2012 | Volume 5 | Article 69 | 8 </p>

<p>Shehadeh Masha'our et al. </p>

<p>AChE involvement in hyperglycemia-induced apoptosis </p>

<p>FIGURE 6 | Inhibiting AChE protein expression by different sh-RNA 
sequences reduces apoptosis in Y79 cells treated with glucose. (A) Y79 
sh-RNA lenti-infected and selected cells (as described under Materials and 
Methods), were pre-treated in starvation medium containing 1% FBS and 
1 mg/ml of glucose for 16-24 h and then treated with 3.5 mg/ml glucose for 
1 h except for sh-control in lane 1. Cytoplasmic extracts were prepared and 
run for western blot analysis to detect AChE expression or anti α-Tubulin (for 
loading control) as described under Materials and Methods. The sample in 
lane 1 and those in 2-7 were run in separate lanes on the same gels. The </p>

<p>western blot shown is one of two independent experiments. (B) Y79 sh-RNA 
lenti-infected and selected cells (as described under Materials and Methods), 
were pre-treated in starvation medium as described in A and then assayed by 
TUNEL (green) to detect apoptosis after 24 h in 3.5 mg/ml glucose. Nuclei 
were stained with DAPI (blue). Cells were photographed under an upright 
fluorescence microscope (Zeiss). Scale bar is 100 μm. (C) TUNEL positive 
Y79 sh-RNA lenti-infected and selected cells were counted and calculated as 
fold of control cells incubated under starvation medium, and plotted in 
histograms. Values are means ± SEM, (N = 3).  *  p &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>(Zhang et al., 2002; Jin et al., 2004; Deng et al., 2006; Toiber et al.,  2008). Under control conditions, AChE expression (Figure 3) 
and activity (Figure 4) in Y79 cells is very low, probably reflect-
ing de-differentiation of this retinoblastoma-derived cell line. 
However, when Y79 cells were treated with 3.5 mg/ml glucose for 
an hour, AChE expression and activity (Figures 3 and 4, respec-
tively) were significantly increased compared to control. AChE 
expression decreased almost back to the control level, when tested </p>

<p>2 h after exposure to 3.5 mg/ml glucose (Figure 3), reminiscent of 
an immediate early gene mRNA and protein expression (Kaufer  et al., 1998). AChE expression was not increased in cells treated 
with 6 mg/ml glucose or in cells treated with mannitol although 
Y79 cells exposed to these conditions were shown to undergo 
apoptosis, probably as a result of hyperosmolarity (Figures 2, 3). 
This may indicate that AChE induction is involved in apopto-
sis induced by selective stress types, e.g., hyperglycemia but not </p>

<p>Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>June 2012 | Volume 5 | Article 69 | 9 </p>

<p>Shehadeh Masha'our et al. </p>

<p>AChE involvement in hyperglycemia-induced apoptosis </p>

<p>FIGURE 7 | Cleavage of PARP in nuclear extracts of sh-RNA lenti-infected 
Y79 cells treated by adding glucose. Nuclear extracts were prepared from 
starved Y79 sh-RNA lenti-infected and selected cells, after raising glucose 
concentration to 3.5 mg/ml glucose for 1 h or keeping the cells in 
control (1 mg/ml glucose) conditions (-). Extracts were run on SDS-PAGE, 
blotted and probed with anti-PARP as described under Materials and </p>

<p>Methods. Five independent western experiments were conducted; one is 
shown in (A). Densitometry values were calculated for cleaved to 
non-cleaved ratios, and then calculated as fold of cells incubated under 
starvation medium (containing 1% FBS and 1 mg/ml glucose) and 
plotted in histograms as shown in (B). Values are mean ± SEM, (N = 5). 
 *  p = 0.05. </p>

<p>by hyperosmolarity. These results shown involvement of AChE-
stress-induced apoptosis, agree with multiple previous reports 
demonstrating stress-induced expression of AChE following a 
variety of stress episodes to the central nervous system, e.g., forced 
swimming (Kaufer et al., 1998), head trauma (Shohami et al.,  2000), and photic stress to the retina (Kehat et al., 2007). The 
findings that apoptosis and AChE were induced by hyperglycemia 
can reflect two unrelated pathways linked by a common trig-
ger or can reflect a single pathway in which AChE expression 
leads to apoptosis. To differentiate between these possibilities we 
blocked AChE expression with shRNA. We found that preventing 
AChE expression using shRNA was accompanied by prevention of 
apoptosis (Figures 6 and 7), thus supporting the hypothesis that </p>

<p>AChE is involved in the apoptosis induced by hyperglycemia in 
Y79 cells. 
Our RT-PCR studies indicated that hyperglycemia-induced 
the expression of an N-extended AChE variant and an AChE-R 
variant (Figure 5). The trivial conclusion is that hyperglycemia 
(3.5 mg/ml glucose) induced the expression of an N-extended 
AChE-R variant and of an AChE-R variant with regular 
N-terminus. The former is found in the membrane fraction and 
the latter in the cytoplasm fraction. This conclusion is contrary 
to recent findings suggesting that the N-extended AChE-S is 
the detrimental variant causing apoptosis (Toiber et al., 2008,  2009). These differences may be related to the type of stress 
and/or to the stressed tissue, but the common feature of the </p>

<p>Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>June 2012 | Volume 5 | Article 69 | 10 </p>

<p>Shehadeh Masha'our et al. </p>

<p>AChE involvement in hyperglycemia-induced apoptosis </p>

<p>two variants, the N-extended terminus, probably includes ele-
ments that are involved in cellular apoptosis. This is supported 
by a previous retinal study demonstrating that photic stress 
induced the expression of an N-extended AChE variant that was 
involved in cell apoptosis, but its specific C-terminus type could 
not be identified at the protein level (Kehat et al., 2007). In 
the same study, in-situ hybridization showed up-regulation of 
AChE-R mRNA (Kehat et al., 2007). It should be noted that 
our findings cannot rule-out that hyperglycemia induced the 
expression of a low-level of N-extended AChE-S that was suffi-
cient to cause apoptosis, but was not detected by the RT-PCR 
experiments. A potential mechanism for the role of AChE in 
the induction of apoptosis was suggested recently emphasiz-
ing the role of the extended N-terminus (Toiber et al., 2008,  2009). According this suggestion, the extended N-terminus pro-
trudes into the cytoplasm, while the core domain is exposed 
to the extracellular compartment (Toiber et al., 2008). Several 
proteins, known to be involved in the apoptotic signaling cas-
cade, i.e., GSK3, GAK (cyclin G associated kinase), JAB1/CSN5, 
integrin, and Fas (TNF receptor super-family, member 6), were 
found to interact with the extended N-terminus of AChE-S 
(Toiber et al., 2009), thus probably linking this AChE variant 
to apoptosis. It should be stressed that this hypothesis empha-
sizes the role of the extended N-terminus in apoptosis and not 
of the C-terminus. Therefore, it is possible that, depending upon 
the studied cells, the N-extended AChE-R or the N-extended </p>

<p>AChE-S can equally play a role in inducing cell apoptosis. 
Therefore, the protein partners, mentioned above, would be very 
interesting to test in our in vitro system. Our in vitro findings 
on retinoblastoma cell line are consistent with the hypothe-
sis that AChE expression pattern in the mammalian retina is 
altered by hyperglycemia in a manner affecting its roles. A pre-
vious study reported a reduction in AChE catalytic activity in 
the diabetic rat retina probably due to loss of the hydrophobic 
variant of AChE (Sanchez-Chavez and Salceda, 2001). Here we 
showed, in a retinoblastoma cell line, that hyperglycemia altered 
the expression pattern of AChE causing up-regulation of the 
AChE-R and the extended N-terminus AChE variants. The lat-
ter variant is the prime candidate to induce the observed cell 
apoptosis, reminiscent of retinal cells' apoptosis that was observed 
during early stages of diabetes (Barber et al., 1998), before any 
vascular alteration. These findings need to be expanded to iden-
tify with certainty the AChE variant involved in hyperglycemia-
induced apoptosis, and to test this effect in vivo, in experimen-
tal diabetic models, before new therapeutic approaches can be 
suggested. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors wish to thank Ms. Irit Mann for her excellent 
technical assistance. This research was partially supported by 
the Technion V.P.R fund-The Macular Degeneration Research 
Fund. </p>



<p>June 2012 | Volume 5 | Article 69 | 11 </p>

<p>Shehadeh Masha'our et al. </p>

<p>AChE involvement in hyperglycemia-induced apoptosis </p>



<p>Conflict of Interest Statement: The 
authors declare that the research 
was conducted in the absence of any 
commercial or financial relationships 
that could be construed as a potential 
conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Received: 11 December 2011; paper 
pending published: 03 January 2012; 
accepted: 14 May 2012; published online: 
06 June 2012. 
Citation: Shehadeh Masha'our R, 
Heinrich R, Garzozi HJ and Perlman 
I (2012) Acetylcholinesterase (AChE) 
is an important link in the apoptotic 
pathway induced by hyperglycemia in 
Y79 retinoblastoma cell line. Front. 
Mol. Neurosci. 5:69. doi: 10.3389/fnmol. 
2012.00069 
Copyright 
© 
2012 
Shehadeh 
Masha'our, Heinrich, Garzozi and 
Perlman. This is an open-access article 
distributed under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution Non 
Commercial License, which permits 
non-commercial use, distribution, and 
reproduction in other forums, provided 
the original authors and source are 
credited. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>June 2012 | Volume 5 | Article 69 | 12 </p>

</text></tei>