<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3032512" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Nerve cell death is the key event in all neurodegenerative disorders, with apoptosis and necrosis being central to both acute and 
chronic degenerative processes. However, until now, it has not been possible to study these dynamically and in real time. In this 
study, we use spectrally distinct, well-recognised fluorescent cell death markers to enable the temporal resolution and 
quantification of the early and late phases of apoptosis and necrosis of single nerve cells in different disease models. The 
tracking of single-cell death profiles in the same living eye over hours, days, weeks and months is a significant advancement on 
currently available techniques. We identified a numerical preponderance of late-phase versus early-phase apoptotic cells in 
chronic models, reinforcing the commonalities between cellular mechanisms in different disease models. We showed that 
MK801 effectively inhibited both apoptosis and necrosis, but our findings support the use of our technique to investigate more 
specific anti-apoptotic and anti-necrotic strategies with well-defined targets, with potentially greater clinical application. The 
optical properties of the eye provide compelling opportunities for the quantitative monitoring of disease mechanisms and 
dynamics in experimental neurodegeneration. Our findings also help to directly observe retinal nerve cell death in patients as 
an adjunct to refining diagnosis, tracking disease status and assessing therapeutic intervention. 
media allow a direct visualisation of disease processes as 
they occur. Recently, we described a technique for real-time 
imaging of retinal ganglion cell (RGC) apoptosis in the 
mammalian eye using confocal scanning laser ophthalmo-
scopy and fluorescent-labelled annexin V. 1 In this study, we 
used PI and 1,1 0 -dioctadecyl-3,3,3 0 ,3 0 -tetramethylindocarbo-
cyanine perchlorate (DiI) as additional cellular markers to 
distinguish between early and late apoptotic and necrotic 
phases of single nerve cell death in vivo. We carried this out in 
established acute, chronic and treated models of neuro-
degeneration 1,6,8 to highlight the capabilities of snapshot and 
longitudinal assessment. Changes in individual neurons were 
visualised in the retina over hours, days and weeks, as were 
the effects of modulating and neuroprotective agents, and 
levels of cell death phase quantified. 
In conclusion, our new technique shows the retina to be an 
ideal experimental model that provides compelling opportu-
nities for the quantitative monitoring of disease mechanisms 
and dynamics in experimental neurodegeneration. It also 
helps to directly observe retinal nerve cell death in patients as 
an adjunct to refining diagnosis, tracking disease status and 
assessing therapeutic intervention. 6,9 </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Customising imaging equipment enables fluorescent 
triple-labelling detection. To simultaneously detect three 
different fluorochromes, we first customised a prototype 
Zeiss (Oberkochen, Germany) confocal scanning laser 
ophthalmoscope (cSLO) 1 to enable the detection of 
different emission wavelengths. The parameters used were 
based on well-established fluorescently tagged cell markers, 
selected because of their distinct spectral properties and 
minimal overlap, and the emitted light collection was 
optimised with appropriate filters (Figure 1). For 
identification of apoptotic cells, we used Alexa Fluor 488-
labelled annexin V (Invitrogen, Paisley, UK), which has an 
excitation and emission maxima of 495 and 519 nm, 
respectively, with an argon laser and a solid-state 
photodetector with a 521 nm cut-off filter and a 550 nm 
cut-on filter. 1 To identify necrotic and late-apoptotic RGCs, we 
used PI with an excitation and emission maxima of 532 and 
649 nm, respectively, with detection using a diode-pumped 
crystal green laser with a wavelength of 532 nm and a 650 nm 
cut-off filter on the photodetector. After an empirical assessment </p>

<p>Figure 1 Confocal scanning laser ophthalmoscopy (cSLO) and detection of fluorescent-labelled cells. Simultaneous detection of multiple markers was achieved by 
customising the cSLO as follows: for identification of annexin 488, an argon laser wavelength of 488 nm and a solid-state photodetector with a 521 nm cut-off filter and a 
550 nm cut-on filter were used; for DiI, a diode-pumped crystal green laser with a wavelength of 532 nm was used with 550 nm cut-off and 600 nm cut-on filters; the same laser 
was used for PI visualisation but with a 650 nm cut-off. The inset graph shows the emission spectra of cellular marker fluorochromes used in this study. Alexa Fluor 488-
labelled annexin V (green; annexin 488), DiI (blue; 1,1 0 -dioctadecyl-3,3,3 0 ,3 0 -tetramethylindocarbocyanine perchlorate) and propidium iodide (red; PI) have excitation/emission 
maxima of 495/519, 550/570 and 532/649 nm, respectively. (a-d) Monochrome images from each retinal area were acquired using the appropriate laser setup and colourised. 
Three-colour images were produced by combining each of the grey scale images from the cLSO into the green (a, annexin 488), blue (b, DiI) and red channels (c, PI) of an 
RGB colour image, and merged to form the image shown in (d) (scale bar 100 mm) </p>

<p>Imaging multiple phases of neurodegeneration 
MF Cordeiro et al </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>of several different compounds, including DiAsp (4-(4-
(didecylamino)styryl)-N-methylpyridinium iodide (4-Di-10-Asp)), 
Fluorogold and Rhodamine B, we determined that DiI was the 
most suitable RGC marker in our rat models, with an excitation 
and emission maxima of 550 and 570 nm, respectively. The 
same laser used for PI was used for DiI visualisation, but with 
550 nm cut-off and 600 nm cut-on filters. 
This system permitted multi-wavelength imaging with 
high resolution and sensitivity, and minimal bleed-through 
(Figure 1). Filters were specifically chosen for the fluoro-
chromes used, but in principle, a diverse number of 
fluorescent markers used in a wide range of established cell 
biology protocols could be studied with appropriate modifica-
tion to the cSLO system -highlighting the use of the retina as 
a model for studying in vivo cellular processes. </p>

<p>In vivo imaging allows longitudinal tracking of changes 
in cell markers over time. Having defined the functional 
parameters of the technology, we next investigated its appli-
cation in vivo using animal models of neurodegeneration. 
Staurosporine (SSP), a well-known non-selective protein 
kinase inhibitor, is routinely used as a potent inducer of 
neuronal apoptosis in in vitro assays. 10 We have previously 
established that SSP may be conveniently used in vivo to 
induce a rapid and fairly synchronous wave of RGC 
apoptosis that is readily detected using annexin V. 1,11 
Therefore, we first studied the effects of SSP in rats in which </p>

<p>RGCs had been retrogradely labelled with DiI, followed by 
intravitreal delivery of SSP, annexin V-488 and PI. 
In this model, time-lapse video sequences (Figures 2a-e 
and Supplementary Videos 1 and 2) of single retinal areas 
over 5 h revealed a random distribution and appearance of 
apoptotic and necrotic cells, which was particularly highlighted 
by the 3D surface plot (Supplementary Video 2), and the 
average intensity projections of the time-lapse sequence 
shown in Figures 2f and g (generated by <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> RGB 
Zprojector plugin). A graphical analysis of the image 
sequence histograms demonstrated that the average intensity 
profiles of annexin V and PI changed significantly over time 
(examples shown in Figure 2h). 
These results demonstrate proof of principle that this 
technique enables the tracking of changes in individual retinal 
cells in the same eye over time, with the ability to temporally 
and quantitatively analyse changes in fluorescence intensity. 
To our knowledge, this is the first demonstration of the use of 
high-resolution multi-wavelength imaging in visualising the 
death of single neurons in vivo. </p>

<p>Identifying patterns of tracked single-cell death markers 
over time in vivo. We next assessed whether the multi-
labelling of cells in vivo allowed the resolution of different 
patterns of apoptotic and necrotic cell death. Owing to the 
rapid kinetics and predominantly apoptotic mode of cell death 
induced by SSP, we again investigated simultaneous triple 
labelling in rats. Although the precise kinetics of the onset of </p>

<p>Figure 2 Time-lapse video analysis showing changes in cell markers in vivo. (a-g) Stills taken from video sequence (Supplementary Video 1) in an SSP-treated rat eye 
with labelled RGCs (DiI, blue) and intravitreal annexin V (green) and propidium iodide (PI, red) reveal a random distribution and appearance of annexin V-and PI-stained cells, 
but demonstrate the clear increase in PI staining over time. (DI, blue; annexin V, green; propidium iodide, red; time points and scale bar 100 mm as indicated). (f, g) Average 
fluorescence intensity projections of video sequences using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> RGB Zprojector plugin with annexin/PI (f) and all three channels (g). (h) Temporal analysis of the average 
annexin (green) and PI (red) intensities taken from each image sequence histogram demonstrates that the profiles of annexin and PI change significantly over time, with a 
marked increase in late PI staining </p>

<p>Imaging multiple phases of neurodegeneration 
MF Cordeiro et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>annexin-V positivity and the development of PI staining 
varied from cell to cell, single-cell tracking allowed the 
delineation of the natural history of the fluorescence patterns. 
In this SSP model, 1,9 single cells were identified from stills, 
and a random sample (n ¼ 30) was selected based on 
whether they were DiI positive (i.e., white spots identifying 
single RGCs, Figure 3a) and stained with annexin V-488, PI or 
both. A video analysis of selected tracked individual cells 
fulfilling these criteria (artificially labelled as light blue spots in 
Figure 3b) using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software and the Time Series 
Analyzer plugin allowed us to construct the intensity profiles 
of annexin V and PI. From these profiles, it was found that 
typically three patterns of fluorescent labelling were observed, </p>

<p>as illustrated in Figure 3c, which is a colour map showing the 
distribution of cells and their staining patterns. First, some 
cells were found to be labelled only with PI ('PI only', red spots, 
Figure 3c), others were initially annexin V positive and 
subsequently became PI positive ('Annexin first', green spots, 
Figure 3c), whereas others became positive for both dyes at 
approximately the same time ('similar profiles', yellow spots, 
Figure 3c). The patterns of fluorescent labelling seemed to be 
randomly distributed. 
The tracking of annexin V-488 and PI staining in single cells 
is clearly shown in the magnified video stills illustrating 
representative cells displaying specific patterns of fluorescent 
labelling (arrows in Figures 3e-g indicating 'PI only'; i-k </p>

<p>Figure 3 Identification of different patterns and phases of cell death in vivo. (a, b) Random sample (n ¼ 30) of single cells selected according to whether they were DiI 
positive (white spots, DiI retrogradely labelled retinal ganglion cells, a) and stained with annexin V-488, PI or both during time-lapse video (light blue spots, b). (c-p) Three 
patterns of fluorescent labelling were identified: 'PI only' (red spots, (c), and the representative cell, arrowed in (e-g) video stills with the corresponding signal intensity profile in 
(h)), 'Annexin first' (annexin-V positive and subsequently PI positive, green spots (c, i-l)), 'similar profiles' (positive labelling for both dyes at the same time, yellow spots, (c, m-p)). 
The mean times to peak intensity (d) revealed that the appearance of the 'PI only' cells was significantly quicker than either the 'annexin first' or the 'similar profiles' cells. 
Intensity profiles of annexin V and PI changed significantly over time (h, l, p). These results provide evidence that neuronal cells in vivo show considerable heterogeneity with 
regard to the kinetics of necrotic and apoptotic cell death, and also the relative timing of phosphatidylserine exposure (early phase) and nuclear condensation (late phase). 
Time points and scale bar 100 mm as indicated </p>

<p>Imaging multiple phases of neurodegeneration 
MF Cordeiro et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>'Annexin first'; and m-o 'similar profiles'), with the correspond-
ing graphs of signal intensity over time (Figure 3h, l and p). In 
each illustrative case, the intensity profiles of annexin V and PI 
changed significantly over time. The mean timings to peak 
intensity of this random sample (Figure 3d) revealed that 'PI 
only' cells tended to show significantly shorter kinetics than 
either the 'Annexin first' or the 'similar profiles' cells. In 
addition, cells that became annexin V positive invariably also 
became PI positive, either within an hour or coincidentally. 
These results provide evidence that neuronal cells in vivo 
show considerable heterogeneity with regard to the kinetics of 
necrotic and apoptotic cell death marker staining, and also, by 
inference, the relative timing of phosphatidylserine exposure 
(early-phase apoptosis) and nuclear condensation (late-
phase apoptosis). </p>

<p>Assessing the phases of cell death in vivo. In vitro FACS 
analysis enables cells to be classified as being in early 
apoptosis (annexin V positive only), necrosis (PI only) or 
late-phase apoptosis (both annexin V and PI positive). To 
quantify the magnitude of late-phase apoptosis in vivo, we 
studied individual levels of annexin V, PI and their co-
localisation using our recently developed Ab model of RGC 
death. 6 The advantages of this methodology are well 
established in the field of cell biology, and provide a 
snapshot of the status of RGC death at any one time. We 
also evaluated the effects of treatment with the N-methyl-D-
aspartic acid (NMDA) channel blocker MK801, using the 
same analytical methods. 
Using the Ab model, we assessed the effects of intravitreal 
Ab (Ab 25À35 ), which was recently shown by us to induce RGC 
apoptosis in rodent eyes. 6 Significant RGC death occurred 
72 h after intravitreal administration of 3.40 nmol Ab 25À35 to 
the right eye, a time that, in previous studies, was shown by us 
to yield peak levels of apoptosis (Figure 4). The left eye of 
each animal was treated with intravitreal 0.40 nmol MK801 at 
the same time as Ab. Wide-angle retinal images were 
recorded 2 h after intravitreal annexin (green) and PI (red) 
staining, as previously described. A typical image of an 
Ab 25À35 -treated right eye (Figure 4a) compared with the left 
MK801-treated eye of the same mouse (Figure 4b) demon-
strates that MK801 treatment reduces the numbers of annexin 
V (green)-and PI (red)-positive cells. 
To assess the relative levels of early apoptosis, late 
apoptosis and necrosis, we studied the co-localisation of PI 
and annexin V using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software with the Intensity 
Correlation Analysis plugin. 12 Colour and raw scatter plots of 
annexin and PI fluorescence intensity were constructed from 
plugin-generated data for each animal. The corresponding 
scatter plots (blue) from the eyes shown in Figures 4a and b 
are illustrated in Figures 4c and d. Data were analysed in a 
manner similar to that of data derived by in vitro FACS 
analysis, with four quadrants (midlines shaded in colour 
overlay as red, green, blue and yellow) enabling separation of 
the different phases of cell death as annexin V positive (early 
apoptosis, green), annexin V and PI double positive (late 
apoptosis, yellow) and PI positive (necrosis, red). Thresholds 
were set automatically by the plugin for the analysis of each 
eye. We then used fluorescence intensity counts from the raw 
scatter plots to quantify each phase of cell death. MK801 </p>

<p>treatment clearly reduced the overall levels of cell death 
(total), but more particularly, the number of cells in late-phase 
apoptosis and necrosis (Figure 4e). Interestingly, there was a 
small increase in the number of early-phase apoptotic cells 
(Anx þ ) in MK801-treated eyes (Figure 4e). As these are 
destined to become Anx þ /PI þ , this suggests that, although 
the results generally support the neuroprotective role of 
NMDA antagonists in Ab-induced neuronal cell death, 13 it 
may be that the protective effects of MK801 seem transient 
because of its single application in these experiments. 
To further assess the analytical power of the technique, we 
next investigated whether the level of oxidative stress in Ab-
treated eyes influenced the phase of cell death and whether 
this was possible to be visualised in vivo. Live cell imaging of 
glial/neuronal cultures has suggested that Ab increases 
neuronal oxidative stress by activating NADPH oxidase in 
microglia, an effect that is potentiated by phorbol myristate 
acetate (PMA). 14 Figures 4f and g are taken from the right 
untreated (f) and left PMA-treated (g) eye of an animal treated 
72 h previously with 3.40 nmol Ab 25À35 . PMA (0.016 nmol) or 
vehicle was administered at the same time as intravitreal 
annexin V and PI, with imaging performed 2 h later. PMA 
increased the numbers of annexin V (green)-positive cells 
(Figures 4f and g), which was confirmed by the co-localisation 
scatter plots (Figures 4h and i). Quantification of fluorescence 
in all animals revealed that PMA significantly (Po0.05) 
increased the overall levels of cell death in the Ab model, in 
particular, the number of cells undergoing early-phase 
apoptosis (Figure 4j). These results support the hypothesis 
that PMA potentiates Ab-induced ROS damage via predomi-
nantly apoptotic pathways. 14 
Using the same methodology, we next compared the 
relative levels of cell death phases between the SSP and Ab 
acute models of RGC death, at the time points at which we 
previously showed peak RGC annexin V positivity to occur, 
that is, at 2 and 72 h, respectively. 1,6 Images were reanalysed 
for all treated animals using co-localisation scatter plots and 
the same methodology as described above. Figure 4k 
illustrates that both SSP and Ab models exhibit similar 
patterns of cell death at the time of peak apoptosis. The cell 
death profiles in both models showed significantly more cells 
in the late phase of apoptosis (Po0.05) as opposed to 
necrosis or early apoptosis. </p>

<p>The natural history of cell death in chronic glaucoma-
related models. Having demonstrated the application of this 
technique in two acute models of RGC death, we next 
investigated models of chronic retinal neurodegeneration, 
which more closely resemble human disease. Our group has 
previously characterised, using in vivo and histological 
profiling of RGC apoptosis, an experimental glaucoma rat 
model of ocular hypertension (OHT) caused by chronically 
elevated intraocular pressure (IOP). 1,9 RGCs were retrogradely 
labelled using previously described methods with DiI 1,6 and 
animals were imaged repeatedly after administration of 
intravitreal annexin V at different time points to generate 
time-lapse 
video 
sequences 
(Figures 
5a-f 
and 
Supplementary Video 3). Assessment of intact labelled 
RGCs in the glaucoma model (identified by DiI, blue, 
Figure 5a) revealed dramatic changes in single RGCs. As </p>

<p>Imaging multiple phases of neurodegeneration 
MF Cordeiro et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>expected, when compared with the number of cells identified 
at baseline (Figure 5b) and at 3 weeks (Figure 5c), the 
number of labelled RGCs evident at 8 weeks was markedly 
reduced (Figure 5d) after surgical induction of elevated IOP. 
Analysis of apoptosis induction in these retinas revealed 
that those RGCs that were annexin V positive at </p>

<p>3 weeks (Figure 5e) disappeared by 8 weeks (Figure 5f), 
suggesting that a wave of apoptosis follows the initial IOP 
elevation insult, which is followed in turn by the clearance of 
dead cells. 
We next analysed the time sequence of annexin V and DiI 
changes during this period. Using a method similar to that </p>

<p>Imaging multiple phases of neurodegeneration 
MF Cordeiro et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>described earlier for Figure 2, we constructed a maximum 
intensity 3D projection of the time-lapse video sequences 
(Supplementary Video 3), using the Image J RGB Zprojector 
and JaCoP plugin. The projection enabled the quantitative 
assessment of maximal annexin V and DiI staining at each 
pixel in the same retinal area studied over time. Although there 
was a high overlap ratio of annexin V staining with DiI (0.63, 
confirming the presence of apoptosis at the level of the 
RGCs), there was a very low ratio (0.072) of DiI cells also 
positive for annexin V. This demonstrates either that only 
some RGCs were ever annexin V positive and that apoptosis 
is not the only pathway responsible for cell death in this model, 
or that annexin V positivity is transient (as shown in Figure 3). 
We then investigated the presence of apoptotic and 
necrotic cells using PI and annexin V. At 3 weeks, in the 
OHT model, only a small proportion of RGCs was identified in 
early apoptosis compared with late apoptosis, as seen in a 
typical image in Figure 5g. Quantification of cell death phases 
was performed using the co-localisation scatter plots 
described previously. There was a significant (Po0.05) 
increase in cells in late-phase apoptosis compared with either 
necrosis or early-phase apoptosis (Figure 5i). Indeed, most 
labelled cells were in late-phase apoptosis (Anx þ /PI þ ), with 
relatively few cells exhibiting the diagnostic markers of necrosis 
(PI þ ) or early-phase apoptosis (Anx þ ). This distribution of 
dying cells is broadly similar to that seen in both the SSP and Ab 
models (Figure 4k) at the time of peak apoptosis. 
We next assessed whether neuroprotective treatment 
altered the relative numbers of cells in each of the cell death 
phases, using the NMDA antagonist MK801, which we have 
previously shown to be effective in this model. 9 Treatment 
with MK801 at the time of IOP elevation significantly reduced 
the numbers of both annexin V-and PI-positive cells 
(Figure 5h). Co-localisation scatter plot analysis showed a 
significant reduction in total cell death markers (Po0.05), and 
specifically a significant reduction in both late-phase apoptosis 
and necrosis, compared with untreated OHT eyes at 3 weeks 
after elevated IOP induction. </p>

<p>Assessing phases of cell death in the Alzheimer triple 
transgenic model. There is growing evidence of retinal 
involvement in AD, with the demonstration using histological 
techniques that RGC apoptosis occurs in double transgenic 
AD models. 3,4 To determine whether phasing of RGC death 
could be assessed in vivo in another model of chronic 
neurodegeneration, we next applied our technique to a triple 
transgenic AD model (3xTg-AD). This is an increasingly used 
model of AD, which overexpresses APPSwe and tauP301L, </p>

<p>as well as carries a PS1M146V knock-in mutation, and is 
currently the only existing transgenic model with both Ab and 
tau neuropathology. 8 An accumulation of intraneuronal Ab 
occurs early, which decreases as extracellular plaques are 
deposited, similar to the development of disease and in 
brains of patients with Down's syndrome. 15 
Previous transgenic studies 3,4 have shown that in the 
double AD APP/PS1 mouse line, the level of RGC apoptosis 
increased with age, being more preponderant at 27 than at 7.8 
months. However, in these studies aged (27-months old) wild-
type congeners were not assessed. Figure 6a demonstrates 
the typical appearance of the eye of a 14-month-old 3xTg-AD 
model imaged at 2 h after intravitreal PI and annexin-IR 
treatment alongside the similarly imaged eye of an 18-month-
old control (PS1KI transgenic mouse that shows no Ab and 
tau neuropathology 16 ) (Figure 6b). To quantify the levels of 
the different phases of cell death, we again used data 
generated from co-localisation scatter plot analysis, which 
showed significantly more RGCs in the phase of early 
apoptosis (Po0.05, green, Anx þ ) and less necrosis 
(Po0.05, red, PI þ ) in 3xTg-AD compared with aged control 
(Figure 6c). These data show that, although a low level of 
apoptotic and necrotic cell death occurs as a correlate of 
normal healthy ageing in mice, in AD mice, there is a 
significant increase in the relative numbers of RGCs in 
early-phase apoptosis. 
We next investigated whether oxidative stress in AD eyes 
influenced the phase of cell death and whether this could be 
visualised in vivo. As intraneuronal Ab accumulation and 
extracellular Ab plaques are the characteristics of this model, 15 
we hypothesised that the addition of PMA would reveal whether 
the level of Ab in this transgenic mouse is sufficient to modulate 
the retinal response in vivo. 14 We therefore compared the 
effects of PMA in 14-month-old 3xTg-AD animals (Figure 6d) 
and control aged animals (Figure 6e). PMA seemed to increase 
the level of annexin staining in the treated eyes of both animals. 
However, quantification revealed that although PMA treatment 
significantly increased early-phase apoptosis in both control 
and 3xTg-AD eyes (Po0.05, Figures 6f and g), the magnitude 
of the increase was far less in control eyes than in 3xTg-AD 
(30.3% in aged control, 61.4% in 3xTg-AD). PMA also 
decreased late apoptosis (Po0.05) in the 3xTg-AD model 
and necrosis (Po0.05) in control eyes. 
These findings show that PMA stimulates a higher rate of 
early-phase apoptosis (annexin V staining alone) in 3xTg-AD 
animals, and are consistent with the data in Figure 4 showing 
a similar effect of PMA in the model of acute RGC death 
mediated by Ab. </p>

<p>Figure 4 Analysis of cell death phases in a mouse model of Ab-induced RGC death. (a, b) Wide-angle retinal images showing the Ab-treated right eye (a) and 
Ab þ MK801-treated left eye (b) of a single mouse. MK801 reduces the number of annexin V (green)-and PI (red)-positive cells 72 h after intravitreal Ab(25-35) application. 
To assess the magnitude of late apoptosis, we studied the co-localisation of PI and annexin V using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software with the Intensity Correlation Analysis plugin. 12 (c, d) 
Scatter plots show the distribution of annexin and PI fluorescence intensity in the eyes shown in (a, b), Ab alone (c) and Ab þ MK801 (d). (e) Thresholds were set 
automatically by the plugin for each analysis (colour overlay in (c, d)), and quantification of each cell death phase was performed from generated data (e). MK801 treatment 
reduced the overall levels of cell death (blue, total), mostly by reducing the number of cells in late-phase apoptosis (yellow, Anx þ /PI þ ) and necrosis (red, PI þ ). (f, g) Wide-
angle retinal images showing the Ab-treated right eye (f) and Ab þ PMA-treated left eye (g) of a single mouse. (h, i) PMA increased the level of annexin V (green) and PI (red) 
positivity, as shown in the corresponding scatter plots. (j) Quantification of all treated animals shows that PMA significantly (Po0.05) increases the overall levels of cell death 
(blue, total), most of this being due to a significant (Po0.05) increase in the number of cells in the early phase of apoptosis (green, Anx þ ). (k) Comparison of cell phases in all 
Ab and SSP models using co-localisation scatter plot analysis. At the previously established time points of maximal apoptosis (Ab ¼ 72 h and SSP ¼ 2 h), both models show a 
similar trend, with no significant difference in the magnitude of any phase of cell death. However, both models show significantly more RGCs in the phases of late apoptosis 
(P40.05, yellow, Anx þ /PI þ ) and necrosis (P40.05, red, PI þ ) than early apoptosis (green, Anx þ ). Error bars 95% confidence intervals, *Po0.05 </p>

<p>Imaging multiple phases of neurodegeneration 
MF Cordeiro et al </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Neuronal cell loss is the key functional event in all 
neurodegenerative disorders, with apoptosis and necrosis 
being central to both acute and chronic degenerative 
processes. 17 We report here, for the first time in vivo, a </p>

<p>technique that enables temporal resolution and quantification 
of the early and late phases of apoptosis and necrosis of 
single nerve cells using different models of disease. 
The methodology permits the tracking of changes in the 
same cell in the same eye over hours, days, weeks and 
months in acute, chronic and treated glaucoma and Alzheimer </p>

<p>Figure 5 Natural history of cell death in a chronic ocular hypertensive (OHT) model of neurodegeneration. (a-f) Cells were retrogradely labelled using DiI (a), and analysed 
at intervals over 8 weeks. The higher magnification image (green box in (a)) taken at time zero (b) shows the normal density of RGCs, with little change at 3 weeks (c). 
However, there was marked RGC dropout 8 weeks after surgical induction of elevated IOP (d). When the data were analysed with respect to the identification of apoptosis in 
these same cells, it was clear that those RGCs that were annexin V positive at 3 weeks (e) were no longer identifiable at 8 weeks (f), confirming that cells originally classified as 
undergoing apoptosis degenerated 5 weeks later. (g) Only a small proportion of RGCs was identified in early-phase apoptosis (annexin V only) compared with late-phase 
apoptosis (both annexin V and PI staining) at 3 weeks. (h) MK801 treatment of animals at the time of surgery significantly reduced the number of both apoptotic and necrotic 
cells 3 weeks after treatment. (i) Quantitative analysis of the co-localisation data for PI and annexin V confirmed that significantly more cells were in late-phase apoptosis 
(P40.05, yellow, Anx þ /PI þ ) than in necrosis (red, PI þ ). Treatment with MK801 led to a significant reduction (Po0.05) in the number of dying cells (total), mostly because 
of a significant decrease in the levels of necrosis (P40.05, red, PI þ ) and late apoptotic (P40.05, yellow, Anx þ /PI þ ) cell death. Scale bar 100 mm as indicated, error bars 
represent 95% confidence intervals, *Po0.05 </p>

<p>Imaging multiple phases of neurodegeneration 
MF Cordeiro et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>models of neurodegeneration. It has enabled us to identify a 
numerical preponderance of late-phase versus early-phase 
apoptotic cells in vivo, and reinforced the commonalities 
between disease mechanisms in the different models studied. 
The predominance of late-phase apoptosis may reflect not 
only the relatively short duration of the early phase compared 
with the late phase (previously estimated as within 1 hour 
ex vivo, 18 and suggesting that the relative likelihood of 
detecting cells in early apoptosis is low at any given time 19 ) 
but also, as we show here ('similar profiles' in Figure 3), the 
coincidental appearance of annexin V and PI positivity in 
many apoptotic cells. 
The shared characteristics of cell death patterns in different 
disease models is an important aspect of the technique 
presented here, with particular relevance to the design of 
more effective and targeted therapeutics. NMDA antagonists </p>

<p>have long been advocated in neuroprotective strategies 20,21 
in both AD 22 and glaucoma, 9,21 and MK801 effectively 
inhibited both apoptosis and necrosis in our different models, 
consistent with the role of Ca 2 þ in mediating both forms of cell 
death. However, these findings support the use of our 
technique to investigate more specific anti-apoptotic and 
anti-necrotic strategies with well-defined targets, with poten-
tially greater clinical application. It may be that the use of these 
strategies will depend on the stage of the disease in the 
patient, which may eventually be defined by an apoptotic/ 
necrotic index, a ratio that may indicate disease severity and 
progression. 
A major advantage of our approach is that it allows a 
temporal delineation of the natural history of neuronal loss. 
Various attempts to discriminate between the various modes 
of cell death in neurodegenerative diseases such as AD have </p>

<p>Figure 6 Retinal cell death in the Alzheimer Triple Transgenic model. (a, b) Representative wide-angle retinal images of a 14-month-old Alzheimer Triple Transgenic 
(3xTg-AD, a) mouse acquired 2 h after intravitreal PI (red) and annexin (green), compared with (b) an 18-month-old PS1KI control mouse. (c) Quantitation of co-localisation 
scatter plot data showing significantly more RGCs in the early phase of apoptosis (Po0.05, green, Anx þ ) and relatively fewer necrotic cells (Po0.05, red, PI þ ) in the 3xTg-
AD model compared with control. (d, e) Retinal images of the eyes of a 14-month-old 3xTg-AD animal (d) and a control aged animal (e) acquired 2 h after PMA was 
administered at the same time as intravitreal annexin (green) and PI (red). (f, g) Quantification of the data generated by co-localisation scatter plot analysis showed that PMA 
treatment significantly increased early apoptosis (Po0.05, green, Anx þ ) and decreased late apoptosis (Po0.05, yellow, Anx þ /PI þ ) in the 3xTg-AD model (g). PMA also 
increased the level of early apoptosis in aged control animals (Po0.05, green, Anx þ ), although not to the same extent (30.3% in aged control as opposed to 61.4% in 3xTg-
AD). *Po0.05 </p>

<p>Imaging multiple phases of neurodegeneration 
MF Cordeiro et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>been inconclusive, with mixed features of apoptosis, necrosis 
and autophagy being detected through a variety of histological 
and biochemical strategies, which are difficult to extrapolate to 
the dynamic events that occur in vivo. 23 The overlap between 
apoptosis and necrosis pathways has been linked to insult 
exposure, 24 with necrosis being associated with excessive 
pathological neuronal loss, 25 now considered to be the 
'default' cell death pathway when apoptotic cell death is 
inhibited. 26 Further investigation to elucidate whether the 
mode of neurodegenerative cell death is directly determined 
by the strength of the cell death stimulus is needed. 
On the whole, most glaucoma studies have focused on the 
development of generic RGC loss rather than on the specific 
mode of cell death, although some have proposed apoptosis 
as the predominant pathway. 27-29 Our results lead us to 
suggest that, although apoptosis may be involved in the 
primary phase of degeneration in animal models, necrosis 
is probably the major cell death pathway in secondary 
degeneration 30 in glaucoma. It will be interesting to use the 
imaging technique developed in this study, in combination 
with the many fluorescent cell-permeant probes available for 
caspase activation, Ca 2 þ fluxes, mitochondrial function and 
so on, to examine degeneration phases in other transgenic 
neurodegeneration models, as the balance between apopto-
sis and necrosis is still unclear in chronic disease. Further-
more, delineation of the timing of such events and their 
association with RGC apoptosis will highlight processes that 
precede the irreversible stages of cellular degeneration, and 
provide improved and specific targets for neuroprotection. 
Annexin 5 is already used systemically and safely in 
patients, 31,32 and there are a number of necrosis markers 
that are already being used in clinical trials, such as 99mTc-
pyrophosphate, 111In-antimyosin and 99mTc-glucarate. 32 
Hence, although it is unlikely that PI can be used in patients, 
there are alternative agents that are potentially available to 
allow this methodology to be translated directly to the clinic. 
The ability to differentiate between apoptosis and necrosis 
and non-invasively track cell death in neurodegenerative 
pathologies could have an important role in medical diag-
nostics and therapy management. Furthermore, we believe 
that the concept of an early apoptotis/necrosis ratio with a 
correlation to disease activity may provide an invaluable tool 
for staging neurodegeneration. There is increasing evidence 
of the potential reversibility of early apoptosis, suggesting that 
a high early apoptosis/necrosis ratio may offer a good 
prognosis for treatment. 33,34 
In conclusion, the application of this new technology has 
far-reaching implications for studying intracellular processes 
at the single-cell level in vivo. Although the equipment we use 
in these studies has been customised to suit animal models, 
the instruments are essentially the same as those used in 
hospitals and clinics around the world. This raises the 
possibility that in the near future, clinicians may be able to 
assess retinal nerve cell death in vivo as a method of 
monitoring disease progression and treatment efficacy. 
Whether a single snapshot or long-term in vivo observation 
over many weeks is needed, the ability to visualise and track 
changes in cell viability offers the potential for major advances 
in the diagnosis and management of neurodegenerative 
diseases. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods 
Animal models. For our investigations in rats, we used established models of 
retinal neuronal apoptosis. 1 All procedures complied with local and national 
regulations and were performed under general anaesthesia. Adult dark Agouti (DA) 
rats, 150-200 g, were used in all rat experiments. 
For the experimental glaucoma studies, we used an established model of ocular 
hypertension. Eighteen rats were operated to elevate their IOP by injection of 
hypertonic saline solution (1.8 M) into episcleral veins as previously described. 1 
Contralateral, unoperated eyes were used as controls. Animals were imaged at 0, 3, 
8 and 16 weeks, with at least three animals at each time point being killed for 
histological analysis immediately after imaging. A subgroup of animals (n ¼ 4) was 
treated at the time of surgery with the NMDA antagonist MK801 (0.6 nmol; Tocris 
Cookson, Bristol, UK). These animals were imaged at 3 weeks and then killed for 
histology. 
For analysis of SSP-induced RGC apoptosis, 14 DA rats were given 0.5 mg of 
intravitreal SSP in 5 ml phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), both from Sigma-Aldrich 
(Dorset, UK), to induce RGC apoptosis as previously described. 1 Animals were 
imaged immediately for up to 6 h, after which they were killed for histology. 
For the analysis of Ab, freshly prepared Ab 25À35 (Sigma-Aldrich, 3.40 nmol) 35 
was intravitreally injected into C57 mice (n ¼ 10). 11 The animals were imaged at 
72 h. For AD 3xTg-AD studies, four eyes (all female, 14 months), with two eyes from 
aged control mice (PS1KI; female, 18 months), were assessed. 3xTg-AD and 
control PS1KI mice were obtained from a colony (maintained at CeSI) established 
after they were received as a generous gift from Frank Laferla. Intravitreal PMA (1 ml 
of 10 mg/ml) was administered to the left eyes of 3xTg-AD animals, at the same time 
as annexin V and PI. </p>

<p>Fluorescent in vivo labelling. To identify RGC, retinas were retrogradely 
labelled using different agents in pilot studies by their application to both superior 
colliculi, as previously described. 1 Pilot studies identified DiI (10% solution; 
Molecular Probes, Cambridge Biosciences, Cambridge, UK) as being better than 
DiAsp (4-Di-10-Asp, Fluorogold or Rhodamine B). DiI was applied 10 days before all 
the rat treatment procedures detailed above. DiI is a long-chain dialkylcarbocyanine 
lipophilic neuronal tracer, which does not affect cell viability, development or the 
basic cellular physiological properties. 36 
Using a method that we recently described, rats were administered 2.5 mg of 
intravitreal Alexa Fluor 488-labelled annexin V in 5 ml PBS for identification of RGC 
apoptosis, 2 h before in vivo imaging. 1 For mice, we used 1 ml of a 0.25 mg/ml 
solution of IR-labelled annexin (Annexin-IR) through intravitreal injections as 
previously described. 37 
To identify necrotic RGCs in rats (2 ml) and mice (1 ml), PI (0.4 mg/ml, 1% 
solution, Sigma-Aldrich) was administered intravitreally at the same time as 
annexin, 2 h before in vivo imaging. PI intercalates into nucleic acids, binding to 
double-stranded DNA, but only crosses the plasma membrane of non-viable cells. 
Cells that have lost membrane integrity are thus identified by fluorescent red PI 
staining throughout the nuclei. </p>

<p>Imaging. All rats had in vivo retinal imaging performed at regular and set 
intervals after experimental treatment using a prototype Zeiss cSLO, as previously 
described. 1,11 Imaging was performed under general anaesthesia with animals 
being held in a stereotaxic frame, with their pupils dilated. Different lasers and filters 
were used for different fluorochromes: for excitation of Alexa Fluor 488, an argon 
laser wavelength of 488 nm and a solid state photodetector with a 521 nm cut-off 
filter and a 550 nm cut-on filter were used; for DiI, a diode-pumped crystal green 
laser with a wavelength of 532 nm was used with 550 nm cut-off and 600 nm cut-on 
filters; the same laser was used for PI visualisation, but with a 650 nm cut-off. The 
cSLO used in this study is the same as that described previously, with modifications 
complying with the established standards for safety and light exposure. 1,37 We have 
developed a purpose-written software to allow optimal processing of low-light 
fluorescent signals, which has greatly aided our live cell imaging. 1 Monochrome 
images from each area were acquired using the appropriate laser setup and 
colourised. Three-colour images were produced by combining each of the grey 
scale images from the cSLO into the red (PI), green (annexin 488) and blue 
channels (DiI) of an RGB colour image. Images were processed in this way because 
red, green and blue (RGB) colours are universally accepted as the most informative 
methods for showing co-localisation. The <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> Intensity Correlation Analysis 
plugin was applied to generate co-localisation scatter plots and colour thresholds. 12 
Colour and raw scatter plots of annexin and PI fluorescence intensity were 
constructed; hence, the data could be analysed in a similar manner to that of the </p>

<p>Imaging multiple phases of neurodegeneration 
MF Cordeiro et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>data derived by in vitro FACS analysis. Separation of the different phases of cell 
death according to whether they were annexin V positive (early apoptosis), annexin 
V and PI double positive (late apoptosis) or PI positive (necrosis) was enabled by 
the adoption of thresholds set automatically by the plugin for each analysis. 
Fluorescence intensity counts derived from raw scatter plots were used to quantify 
each phase of cell death. 
In mice, we used instrumentation as previously described, 11,37 with a modified 
cSLO (Heidelberg Retina Angiograph 2, Heidelberg Engineering, Dossenheim, 
Germany) and a wide-field lens (551). The fluorescein angiogram (488 nm argon 
laser) and indocyanine green (IR 790 nm diode laser) settings were used to detect 
PI-and IR-labelled annexin, respectively. The same software was used to analyse 
video-sequenced images as described before, with whole retinal monochrome 
images of each eye recorded and colourised. Dual-color images were produced by 
combining each of the grey scale images from the cSLO into the red (PI) and green 
(IR annexin) channels of an RGB colour image. </p>

<p>Analysis. <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software was used with specific plugins to create 3D surface 
plots, RGB projections and to analyse co-localisation (JaCoP and Intensity 
Correlation Analysis). Graphical data for mean values were contrived with 95% 
confidence intervals, and comparisons across groups were performed using 
ANOVA or Student's t-test for paired eyes, with Po0.05 as the significance level. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest 
Professors M Francesca Cordeiro, Frederick W Fitzke and Stephen E Moss are 
named inventors on a patent application covering the technology disclosed in this 
report. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements. We acknowledge support from The Wellcome Trust, 
The Foundation Fighting Blindness, Dr. Annelie Maass and Mr. Vy Luong. </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease is an open-access journal 
published by Nature Publishing Group. This article is 
licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-No 
Derivative Works 3.0 License. To view a copy of this License, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies the paper on Cell Death and Disease website (http://www.nature.com/cddis) </p>

<p>Imaging multiple phases of neurodegeneration 
MF Cordeiro et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

</text></tei>