<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3037501" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:45+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: The objective of this study was to investigate the diagnostic accuracy of mul-
ti-detector computerized tomography urography (MDCTU) for the detection of bladder 
tumors. 
Materials and Methods: We retrospectively reviewed the medical records of 143 pa-
tients who were scanned by use of 64-channel MDCTU and who underwent cystoscopy 
due to painless hematuria or a clinical suspicion of bladder tumor. We examined the 
accuracy of MDCTU for the detection of bladder tumors by comparing the results ob-
tained by MDCTU with those obtained by cystoscopy. The associations between tumor 
characteristics, frequency of transurethral resection (TUR), and bladder volume and 
detectability of bladder tumors on MDCTU were also analyzed. 
Results: Of 143 patients, 50 patients had a history of urothelial carcinomas. In these 
patients, the sensitivity and specificity of MDCTU were 60.0% and 80.0%, respectively. 
In 93 patients without previous urothelial carcinomas, the sensitivity and specificity 
of MDCTU were 86.7% and 96.8%, respectively. Falsely diagnosed cases had a smaller 
distended bladder volume (p=0.014) and a smaller tumor size (p=0.022) than did true 
diagnosed cases. The false-negative rate increased when the bladder tumor was located 
at the bladder neck. In the univariate analysis, the tumor location, size, frequency of 
TUR, bladder volume, and initial hematuria were associated with detectability by 
MDCTU (p&lt;0.05). 
Conclusions: To improve the accuracy of MDCTU for diagnosing bladder tumors, blad-
der filling is recommended. Thus, cystoscopy should be considered as a standard diag-
nostic tool for bladder tumors even in patients with normal MDCTU results, especially 
in the evaluation of recurrent, bladder neck-located, small, or sessile bladder tumors. </p>

<p>Traditionally, physicians use imaging modalities, such as 
excretory urography, to diagnose bladder tumors preo-
peratively. Currently, abdominal ultrasonography (USG), 
computed tomography (CT), and magnetic resonance 
imaging (MRI) are also used. With excretory urography </p>

<p>and USG, there are some limitations in visualizing the en-
tire urinary tract. However, the latest technology, mul-
ti-detector computerized tomography urography (MDCTU), 
uses the newly developed MDCT, which emerged with the 
development of spiral CT technology and has the advant-
age of visualizing the entire urinary tract, including the re-
nal pelvis, the ureter, the bladder, and the renal paren-</p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2011;52:13-18 </p>



<p>Hwang et al </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Urothelial carcinomas of the 
bladder and left distal ureter. (A) Axial 
2D and (B) 3D volume rendering (VR) 
CT urograms obtained during the 
excretory phase show an 11 mm mass 
(arrow) near the left ureterovesical 
junction and a 5 mm mass (arrowhead) 
in the left distal ureter in a 51-year-old 
man evaluated for gross hematuria. 
The masses were also detected during 
the cystoscopy performed after CT 
urography. </p>

<p>chyma [1-3]. 
MDCTU has recently been used in patients with hema-
turia for detecting urinary tract lesions. However, MDCTU 
can be performed more quickly than an so that bladder fill-
ing may be inadequate for the evaluation of bladder lesions. 
We therefore sought to determine the diagnostic accuracy 
of MDCTU for detecting bladder tumors and the factors af-
fecting the detection rate by MDCTU. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>The study was carried out in accordance with the Declara-
tion of Helsinki, and informed consent was obtained from 
all subjects after they were provided a detailed description 
of the procedures. </p>

<p>1. Patients 
We retrospectively reviewed the medical records of 323 pa-
tients who underwent MDCTU between January 2008 and 
May 2009. We enrolled patients who underwent MDCTU 
due to painless hematuria or as a follow-up study for ur-
othelial cancer. Patients who were lost to follow-up, de-
clined cystoscopy, or underwent transurethral surgery for 
clinically suspicious bladder tumors were excluded from 
the analysis. Additionally, patients with more than a 
1-month interval from MDCTU to cystoscopy were exclu-
ded. One hundred eighty patients were excluded; 143 pa-
tients who underwent both MDCTU and cystoscopy were 
included in the final analysis. Bladder tumors were patho-
logically diagnosed by cystoscopic biopsy or transurethral 
resection (TUR). Patients were considered negative for 
bladder tumor if no tumor was detected cystoscopically or 
if the biopsy specimen was determined to be nonmalignant 
on histopathologic examination. </p>

<p>2. MDCTU 
MDCTU was performed by using a 64-channel volume CT 
(Lightspeed VCT; GE Healthcare, Milwaukee, WI, USA). 
All patients drank 700 to 1,200 ml of water before imaging. </p>

<p>All examinations were supplemented with 250 ml of intra-
venous saline infused by gravity after the administration 
of contrast medium. All patients were scanned in the su-
pine position. A three-scan CT protocol included an un-
enhanced scan (5 mm slice thickness, 5 mm interval, pitch 
of 1, 120 kVp, and 170-280 mA) of the abdomen and pelvis, 
a nephrographic phase scan of the kidneys (3.75 mm slice 
thickness, 3.75 mm interval, pitch of 1,120 kVp, and 170-280 
mA) 90 seconds after intravenous administration of 125 to 
140 ml of iopromide (Ultravist 300; Berlex Laboratories, 
Madison, NJ, USA) at a rate of 3 ml/sec, and an excretory 
phase scan of the abdomen and pelvis (3.75 mm slice thick-
ness, 3.75 mm interval, pitch of 1,120 kVp, and 170-280 
mA) 10 minutes after the injection of contrast medium. 
Excretory phase scans were reconstructed in the coronal 
and sagittal planes with a 2 mm slice thickness. The aver-
age scanning time of MDCTU was 15 minutes. 
CT scanning data of the excretory phase were sent to a 
workstation (Advantage Windows 4.2; GE Healthcare 
Technologies). Three-dimensional images with volume 
rendering (VR) and maximum-intensity-projection (MIP) 
techniques were reconstructed on the workstation. 
MDCTU images, including two-dimensional (axial, coro-
nal, and sagittal images) and three-dimensional images, 
were interpreted by one radiologist (KJW) who was blinded 
to the clinical data (Fig. 1). The average interpretation time 
of the MDCTU, including two-and three-dimensional im-
ages, was 10 minutes. 
Positive findings for bladder tumors were as follows: an 
intraluminal bladder mass, an asymmetrically thickened 
bladder wall, or a mass within the urethra. 
Excluding the cases with asymmetrically thickened 
bladder walls, the longest diameter of the tumor was 
measured. In patients with multiple bladder tumors, the 
longest diameter of the largest tumor was measured. We 
calculated the capacity of the bladder by using the coronal, 
sagittal, and axial images of the excretory phase from the 
MDCTU by using an ellipsoid formula, as follows: front and 
rear diameter x width diameter x the head and tail diame-</p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2011;52:13-18 </p>

<p>Bladder Tumor Detection on MDCTU </p>



<p>TABLE 1. MDCTU outcomes according to variables </p>

<p>Variables 
MDCTU 
p-value </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Negative (%) Positive (%) </p>

<p>Total 143 
Cancer− (88) 
Cancer＋ (55) 
Hematuria group (93) 
Cancer− (63) 
Cancer＋ (30) 
F/U group (50) 
Cancer− (25) 
Cancer＋ (25) 
Frequency of TUR in F/U 
group (50) 
n=1 (30) Cancer− (13) 
Cancer＋ (17) 
n＞1 (20) Cancer− (12) 
Cancer＋ (8) 
Tumor location 
Bladder neck (11) 
Intravesical (42) 
Urethra (2) 
Multiplicity 
Solitary (1-2) (38) 
Multiple (3-) (17) 
Mass size 
Sessile (11) 
＜1 cm (9) 
≥1 cm (35) 
Bladder volume 
＜200 cc 
200-300 cc 
300-400 cc </p>

<p>81 (92) 
14 (25.5) </p>

<p>61 (96.8) 
4 (13.3) </p>

<p>20 (80) 
10 (40) </p>

<p>12 (92.3) 
4 (23.5) 
8 (66.7) 
6 (75) </p>

<p>7 (63.6) 
6 (14.3) 
1 (50) </p>

<p>10 (26.3) 
4 (23.5) </p>

<p>2 (18.2) 
6 (66.7) 
6 (17.1) </p>

<p>11 (36.7) 
1 (7.1) 
2 (18.2) </p>

<p>7 (8) 
41 (74.5) </p>

<p>2 (3.2) 
26 (86.7) </p>

<p>5 (20) 
15 (60) </p>

<p>1 (7.7) 
13 (76.5) 
4 (33.3) 
2 (25) </p>

<p>4 (36.4) 
36 (85.7) 
1 (50) </p>

<p>28 (73.7) 
13 (76.5) </p>

<p>9 (81.8) 
3 (33.3) 
29 (82.9) </p>

<p>19 (63.3) 
13 (92.9) 
9 (81.8) </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>＞0.05 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>＞0.05 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.09 </p>

<p>Reference standard diagnosis of bladder tumor made by cystoscopy. 
MDCTU: multi-detector computerized tomography urography, 
F/U: follow-up, TUR: transurethral resection, </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>: chi-square test </p>

<p>ter x π/6 [4]. 
We examined the sensitivity, specificity, positive pre-
dictive value (PPV), negative predictive value (NPV), accu-
racy, and factors associated with the detection of bladder 
tumors by MDCTU by comparing the results obtained by 
MDCTU with those obtained by cystoscopy. Also, we com-
pared the clinical characteristics of the two subgroups of 
patients. The first subgroup consisted of falsely diagnosed 
patients who were diagnosed as false-negatives or false-
positives by MDCTU, and the second subgroup consisted 
of patients in whom bladder tumors were correctly diag-
nosed by MDCTU. </p>

<p>3. Statistical analysis 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> ver. <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">12.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA) was used for 
statistical analyses. Student's t-test, the chi-square test, 
and the univariate analysis were used. Results were con-
sidered statistically significant when the p-value was 
＜0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>1. Patient characteristics and accuracy of MDCTU 
The average age of the 143 patients was 63.38±12.13 years. 
There were 110 males (76.9%) and 33 females (23.1%) en-
rolled in the study. Ninety-three patients were evaluated 
for hematuria and 50 patients were evaluated as a fol-
low-up for urothelial cancer. 
In the 143 patients who underwent cystoscopy, 55 were 
diagnosed with bladder tumors (Table 1). On the basis of 
the 55 patients who were diagnosed with bladder tumors, 
the sensitivity, specificity, PPV, and NPV of MDCTU in all 
patients were 74.5%, 92.0%, 85.4%, and 86.3%, respec-
tively. 
In the 93 patients who underwent evaluation for hema-
turia, 30 were diagnosed with bladder tumors (Table 1); the 
sensitivity, specificity, PPV, and NPV of MDCTU were 
86.7%, 96.8%, 92.9%, and 93.8%, respectively. 
In the 50 patients who had a history of urothelial cancer, 
25 were diagnosed with bladder tumors (Table 1); the sensi-
tivity, specificity, PPV, and NPV of MDCTU were 60.0%, 
80.0%, 75.0%, and 66.7%, respectively. 
The sensitivity of MDCTU according to the frequency of 
TUR, tumor location, multiplicity of tumor, mass size, and 
distended bladder volume is shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>2. Characteristics of the patients who were diagnosed as 
false-negative and false-positive by MDCTU 
There were 14 false-negative patients in whom MDCTU 
did not detect a tumor. Of the 14 patients, 7 (50.0%) had 
bladder neck tumors (mean size, 1.10 ±0.50 cm; 0.5, 0.7, 1, 
1, 1, 1.5, and 2 cm, respectively), 4 (28.6%) had intraluminal 
bladder tumors (mean size, 0.53±0.21 cm; 0.3, 0.5, 0.5, and 
0.8 cm, respectively), 2 (14.3%) had flat-shaped bladder tu-
mors, and 1 (7.1%) had a prostate urethral tumor (size, 1.5 
cm) (Table 2). 
On the basis of the MDCTU examinations, 7 patients </p>

<p>were false-positives, and the bladder walls were partially 
thickened in all patients. These patients were diagnosed 
as having benign lesions (cystitis) on biopsy. </p>

<p>3. Comparison between patients diagnosed with bladder 
tumors on MDCTU and the false-negative and false-pos-
itive patients 
When comparing the 21 false-negative and false-positive 
patients and the 41 patients with MDCTU-diagnosed blad-
der tumors that were confirmed by biopsy, the former group 
of patients were more likely to have a history of urothelial 
cancers (71.4% vs. 36.6%; p=0.015) (Table 3), had smaller 
tumor sizes (0.89±0.49 cm vs. 1.95±1.39 cm; p=0.022) (Table 
3), and had a less distended bladder volume (145.9±107.6 
ml vs. 226.9±124.0 ml; p=0.014) (Table 3). </p>

<p>4. Factors affecting the positive outcomes of MDCTU 
In the univariate analysis, the tumor location, size, fre-
quencies of TUR, bladder volume, and initial hematuria 
were factors associated with the outcomes of MDCTU </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2011;52:13-18 </p>



<p>Hwang et al </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Clinical characteristics of 14 patients with false-nega-
tive diagnoses on MDCTU </p>

<p>No. of patients Mean size 
(n=14) 
(cm) (range) </p>

<p>Bladder neck papillary tumor (%) 
7 (50.0) 
1.10 (0.5-2.0) 
Bladder papillary tumor 
a (%) 
4 (28.6) 
0.53 (0.3-0.8) 
Bladder sessile tumor (%) 
2 (14.3) 
-
Prostatic urethra tumor (%) 
1 (7.1) 
1.5 </p>

<p>MDCTU: multi-detector computerized tomography urography, </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>: bladder papillary tumor, except bladder neck area </p>

<p>TABLE 3. Comparison of clinical characteristics between false 
diagnoses and MDCTU-detected tumors (Mean±SD) </p>

<p>False-
MDCTU-
diagnosed 
detected tumor p-value </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>cases (n=21) 
cases (n=41) </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
67.4±9.25 
66.0±13.0 
0.658 
Male patient (%) 
19 (90.4) 
35 (85.4) 
0.652 
Previous UC 
15 (71.4) 
15 (36.6) 
0.015 
patient (%) 
Size (cm) 
0.89±0.49 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.95±1.39 
0.022 
Distended bladder 145.9±107.6 
226.9±124.0 
0.014 
volume 
b (ml) </p>

<p>MDCTU: multi-detector computerized tomography urography, 
UC: urothelial carcinoma, </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>: tumor size of 14 false-negative diag-
nosed patients, </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>: measured by MDCTU with the ellipsoid formula, </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>: Student's t-test </p>

<p>TABLE 4. Univariate analyses of MDCTU detectability </p>

<p>Odds 95% confidence 
Variables 
p-value </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>ratio 
intervals </p>

<p>Age (＞68 yr) 
1.8 
0.5-6.6 
0.3 
Gender (female) 
1.4 
0.14-13.7 
0.7 
Bladder volume 
4.2 
1.05-17.5 
0.04 
(≥200 cc) 
Tumor size (sessile and 
9.5 
1.95-46.2 
0.005 
＞1 cm) 
Tumor location 
9.6 
2.33-38.4 
0.002 
(intravesical tumors) 
Frequencies of TUR 
14.6 
2.4-86.0 
0.003 
(less than 2) 
Patients without previous 
4.33 
1.15-16.2 
0.03 
urothelial carcinomas </p>

<p>MDCTU: multi-detector computerized tomography urography, 
TUR: transurethral resection, </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>: binary logistic regression </p>

<p>(Table 4). However, there were no significant factors in the 
multivariate analysis (data not shown). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The current study focused on the diagnostic efficiency of 
MDCTU for detecting bladder tumors and the factors af-
fecting the sensitivity of MDCTU. 
In evaluating hematuria and to establish an accurate di-
agnosis, physicians depend on various methods, which re-
quire exceptionally high clinical sensitivity and specificity. 
CT, with and without intravenous contrast, is being used 
more than excretory urography in the evaluation of hema-
turia. With computer-assisted reconstruction, longitudinal 
views of the urinary tract can now be made. MDCTU can 
promptly produce thin layers of the unenhanced, nephro-
graphic, and excretory phases and can be used to recon-
struct three-dimensional images (Fig. 1). Hence, MDTCU 
can generate further enhanced resolution of the pre-exist-
ing excretory urography [5]. Also, gases inside the organs, 
adjacent bone structures, and fecal material that hinder 
reading the results from excretory urography are overcome 
with MDCTU. 
Kim et al reported the sensitivity and specificity of 
MDCT in diagnosing bladder cancer to be 89% and 95%, re-
spectively [6]. According to several reports that examined </p>

<p>the results of MDCTU in diagnosing bladder cancer, the 
sensitivity varied from 64 to 96% and the specificity also 
varied from 89 to 99% [7-10]. In our study, the sensitivity 
and specificity of MDCTU in screening examinations for in-
itial hematuria were 86.7% and 96.8%; however, as a fol-
low-up for urothelial cancer, MDCTU had a sensitivity and 
specificity of 60.0% and 80.0%, respectively, which is lower 
in patients with a history of urothelial cancer. This is prob-
ably because, in contrast with the initial hematuria pa-
tients, the follow-up patients had smaller tumors and had 
inflammatory changes to the bladder wall as a result of pre-
vious treatment. 
We also analyzed the sensitivity of MDCTU according to 
the frequency of TUR, tumor multiplicity, size, location, 
and distended bladder volume. Jinzaki et al reported that 
the sensitivity of MDCT in distinguishing bladder tumors 
that were ＜0.5 cm in size was 58%, whereas the sensitivity 
for tumors between 0.5 and 1 cm in size was 94%; tumors 
that were ＞1 cm in size had a 100% sensitivity rate. In our 
study, the sensitivity of sessile tumors was 81.8%, and that 
of tumors that were ＜1 cm was 33%; tumors that were ≥1 
cm in size had an 82.8% sensitivity rate compared with tu-
mor size ＜1 cm, and sessile tumor and tumor size ≥1 cm 
were factors affecting positive outcomes [11]. Discrepan-
cies between Jinzaki's results and ours were probably be-
cause our number of patients with tumors ＜1 cm or dis-
tended bladder volume was smaller than in Jinzaki's 
report. 
The location of tumors may also affect the sensitivity of 
MDCTU. When we analyzed sensitivity stratified by tumor 
location, bladder neck tumors showed a low sensitivity 
(36%). Because of the effect of prostatic enlargement, parti-
al opacification [with fluid-fluid (contrast) level] of the 
bladder may make bladder neck tumors more difficult to 
detect by MDCTU compared with intravesical tumors. 
The frequency of TUR is also related to the accuracy of 
MDCTU. It was shown in patients with urothelial cancer 
previously treated by several TURs that the sensitivity of </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2011;52:13-18 </p>

<p>Bladder Tumor Detection on MDCTU </p>



<p>MDCTU was lower because the previous transurethral 
procedures led to injury or inflammation of the bladder 
mucosa. 
Another important factor in diagnosing bladder tumors 
with MDCTU is distended bladder volume. In the current 
study, the sensitivity of MDCTU was increased with in-
creasing distended bladder volume, and true-positive pa-
tients had an acceptable bladder volume (227 ml). The 
average bladder volume in patients who were diagnosed as 
false-negative and false-positive was 146 ml, which is 
unacceptable. It is not surprising to miss the diagnosis of 
a bladder tumor in a poorly distended bladder. If the blad-
der is less distended, the bladder wall more thickened, and 
small tumors less protruded, this may affect the false-pos-
itive rate. Also, cases of severe bladder trabeculations may 
preclude detection of tumors in this situation. 
Shimizu et al reported that when diagnosing gastric can-
cer with MDCT and using the water-filling method, having 
the patient drink 300 to 600 ml of water before the CT scan 
not only enhances the sensitivity but also provides in-
formation on the rate of gastric wall permeation [12]. Like 
the stomach, the bladder is a hollow organ in which dis-
tended bladder volume affects the diagnostic accuracy of 
MDCTU. To prevent inappropriate bladder distention, we 
previously checked virtual cystoscopy with MDCT by dis-
tension of the bladder with approximately 300 to 500 cc of 
room air through a urethral catheter after drainage of 
urine and showed sensitivity of 70% to 100% [13]. There-
fore, when using MDCTU to examine the bladder, it is rec-
ommended to instruct the patients not to empty their blad-
der before the examination. 
MDCTU has progressively become a powerful tool in the 
evaluation of patients presenting with painless hema-
turia, and during the past few years has been able to demon-
strate a wide spectrum of diseases affecting the urinary 
tract. The reliable depiction of the entire urinary tract, in-
cluding the renal collecting systems, the ureters, and the 
bladder, is possible, and an important advantage of the 
technique is its ability to detect uroepithelial malignan-
cies. 
The disadvantage of MDCTU or MDCT is a radiation ex-
posure dose higher than that with excretory urography or 
conventional CT. To prevent this, there are some reports 
recommending that MDCTU be avoided in patients who 
are ＜40 years of age with a lower incidence of urothelial 
cancer or who are sensitive to radiation [14,15]. Additional-
ly, many reports have focused on maintaining the image 
quality of MDCTU and lowering the radiation exposure 
dose at the same time [16,17]. 
Although our data showed that the overall sensitivity of 
MDCTU was not sufficiently high to replace cystoscopy 
within the diagnostic pathway, the high specificity enables 
an early diagnosis and treatment in patients with initial 
hematuria and in follow-up patients. Furthermore, be-
cause this study clinically applied MDCTU to patients with 
initial hematuria and to the follow-up of patients with ur-
othelial cancer as opposed to only patients with tumors, </p>

<p>this study appears to be more significant. 
This study is not without limitations, including its retro-
spective nature and small number of cases; also, we did not 
perform any manipulations such as log-rolling or retro-
grade dye instillation to obtain adequate opacification of 
the urinary bladder in the excretory phase. The multi-
variate analysis did not show any independent factors af-
fecting MDCTU outcomes (results not shown). Further 
prospective studies might be needed to obtain adequate 
opacification of the urinary bladder without additional ra-
diation exposures and to verify the independent factors af-
fecting positive MDCTU results. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>The diagnostic accuracy of MDCTU is affected by a history 
of urothelial cancer, tumor location, size, and distended 
bladder volume. The sensitivity of MDCTU in patients 
with a history of urothelial cancer is lower than in patients 
with hematuria. The falsely-diagnosed cases were more 
likely to have a history of urothelial cancer, less distended 
bladder volume, and a smaller tumor size than did the true 
diagnosed cases. The false-negative rate is increased when 
the bladder tumor is located at the bladder neck. The accu-
racy of MDCTU for diagnosing bladder tumors depends on 
bladder distension; therefore, bladder filling is recommen-
ded. 
Cystoscopy should be considered as a standard diag-
nostic tool for bladder tumors, even in patients with normal 
MDCTU, especially in the evaluation of recurrent tumors, 
those located at the bladder neck located, small tumors, or 
sessile bladder tumors. </p>

<p>Conflicts of Interest 
The authors have nothing to disclose. </p>



<p>Korean J Urol 2011;52:13-18 </p>



<p>Hwang et al </p>



</text></tei>