<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3241662" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>SR proteins promote spliceosome formation by 
recognizing exonic splicing enhancers (ESEs) 
during pre-mRNA splicing. Each SR protein binds 
diverse ESEs using strategies that are yet to be 
elucidated. Here, we show that the RNA-binding 
domain (RBD) of SRSF1 optimally binds to 
decameric purine rich ESE sequences although 
locations of purines are not stringently specified. 
The presence of uracils either within or outside of 
the recognition site is detrimental for binding with 
SRSF1. The entire RBD, comprised of two RRMs and 
a glycine-rich linker, is essential for ESE binding. 
Mutation within each segment reduced or nearly 
abolished binding, suggesting that these segments 
mediate cooperative binding. The linker plays 
a decisive role in organizing ESE binding. The 
flanking basic regions of the linker appear to com-
municate with each other in bringing the two RRMs 
close together to form the complex with RNA. Our 
study thus suggests semi-conservative adaptable 
interaction between ESE and SRSF1, and such 
binding mode is not only essential for the recogni-
tion of plethora of physiological ESE sequences 
but may also be essential for the interaction with 
various factors during the spliceosome assembly. </p>

<p>SR proteins are sequence-specific RNA-binding factors. 
RNA binding is a requirement for all of their known 
cellular activities including the spliceosome assembly. 
RNA binding is mediated by the RNA recognition 
motifs (RRMs) within the N-terminal portions of SR 
proteins. The spliceosome assembly is facilitated by the 
interaction between the RRMs and exonic splicing enhan-
cers (ESEs) (1,2). The C-terminal RS domain(s) of SR </p>

<p>proteins are thought to serve as modifiers of diverse 
interactions within the spliceosome. 
SRSF1, one of the SR proteins, contains two RRMs 
at its N-terminus and a relatively short RS domain 
at the C-terminus. The C-terminal RS domain plays a 
modulatory role in the SRSF1:ESE complex formation 
through phosphorylation and dephosphorylation of 
the serine residues (3). The N-terminal RRM-containing 
region is responsible for sequence-specific RNA binding. 
The more N-terminal RRM (RRM1) exhibits clear 
sequence similarity to the canonical RRM consensus by 
virtue of its RNP1 and RNP2 motifs. The RRM2 of 
SRSF1 lacks these motifs. SRSF1-specific ESE sequences 
have been determined by both binding affinity and func-
tional SELEX experiments (4-6). In addition to selection 
based and physiological ESE identification, significant 
progress has been made in identifying ESEs from 
genome-wide sequences through the use of computational 
methods (7). All these studies suggest that SRSF1 binds 
a broad spectrum of ESEs with only a loose consensus 
among these sequences. ESE bound SRSF1 does not 
only active but also represses splicing. Other SR proteins 
also behave similarly as SRSF1 in terms of loose consen-
sus for their respective ESEs and ability to both activate 
and repress splicing. The NMR solution structure of the 
single-RRM containing SR protein SRSF3 (SRp20) 
bound to a 4-nt ESE RNA demonstrated that SRSF3 
recognizes the ESE in a semi-sequence specific manner 
by using conserved motifs and amino acid residues 
within its RRM (8). This mode of ESE recognition by 
SRSF3 provides some clues as to how numerous degener-
ate ESE sequences within various pre-mRNA might be 
recognized by SR proteins. RNA-bound structures of 
non-SR protein splicing factors, Sxl (9), U2AF65 (10), 
HuD (11) and PTB (12), have also been elucidated. In 
each case, the complex structure contains two RRMs 
bound to cognate RNA. These structures reveal diverse 
modes by which individual RRMs articulate with one 
another in recognizing specific target RNA. In one case, 
for example, each RRM of U2AF65 binds to a </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 858 822 0469; Fax: +1 858 534 7042; Email: gghosh@ucsd.edu </p>

<p>Published online 18 August 2011 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 21 9413-9421 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkr663 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>polypyrimidine tract independent of one another. In 
contrast, the two PTB RRMs recognize their target 
RNA as a single unit with extensive interdomain 
protein-protein contacts. The Sxl RRMs exhibit clear 
cooperativity in their binding to RNA. In all of these 
cases the conserved RNP1 and RNP2 motifs are directly 
involved in RNA recognition. The RNA recognition 
sequences of these splicing factors are highly specific in 
general. However, it is unclear how SR proteins with 
two RRMs bind to such a large and diverse collection of 
cognate sequences. 
This study investigates the mechanism of how the 
SRSF1 RNA-binding domain (RBD) binds to a large rep-
ertoire of putative ESEs in cells. We found that the protein 
optimally binds RNA sequences of 10-nt in length with no 
stringent position-specific base requirement with the 
exception of uracil. The presence of uracils both inside 
and outside of the recognition sequence is detrimental to 
binding. All three segments of SRSF1, RRM1, RRM2 
and the linker are essential for ESE binding. The flexibly 
linked segments in SRSF1 RBD recognize RNA using 
cooperative interactions. Our result thus explains how 
SRSF1 binds to a large number of ESE to promote 
splicing. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Cloning and protein expression </p>

<p>His-SRSF1 (RBD, 1-196) and GST-SRSF1 (R1, 1-98) 
mutants were generated using a site-directed mutagenesis 
kit (Stratagene). DNA fragments corresponding to WT 
and mutant SRSF1-RBDs were cloned into pET24dTEV 
vector, and His-SRSF1 (R1, 1-90 and 1-98), His-SRSF1 
(LR2, 90-196 and 105-196) and His-SRSF1 R2 (118-196) 
were expressed by cloning the corresponding DNA frag-
ments in pET15b. GST-SRSF1 R1 construct was made 
by cloning the DNA fragment in pGEX-4T2 vector. 
All proteins were expressed in Escherichia coli BL21 
(DE3) pLysS cells and grown in M9-based minimal 
media. Cells were induced with 1 mM IPTG at O.D. 600 
0.8 and grown for 3 h at 25 
C. The cell pellet in 
His-SRSF1 constructs was lysed in 20 mM Tris-HCl 
(pH 7.5), 500 mM NaCl, 50 mM urea, 5 mM imidazole, 
10% glycerol, 10 mM b-mercaptoethanol, 1 mM PMSF 
and 0.1Â protease inhibitor cocktail and soluble fractions 
were loaded onto DEAE column to remove non-specific 
RNA or DNA at room temperature. The flow through 
was loaded onto a Ni </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-NTA agarose column at room 
temperature followed by washing and elution in 
three steps using lysis buffers containing 20 and 250 mM 
imidazole in the absence of urea. Proteins were further 
purified by size exclusion chromatography (Superdex 75, 
16/60; GE Health care). GST-SRSF1 (RRM1) wt and 
mutant proteins were lysed in 20 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 
500 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, 1 mM DTT, 1 mM PMSF 
and 0.1Â protease inhibitor cocktail. Soluble fraction was 
loaded on glutathione S-transferase sepharose column. 
The proteins were eluted using 20 mM L-glutathione 
after washing with lysis buffer. Protein was purified </p>

<p>further by size exclusion chromatography (Superdex 200, 
16/60; GE Health care). </p>

<p>Filter-binding assay </p>

<p>An amount of 10 fmol of [g-</p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>P]-ATP labeled ESEs RNAs 
was incubated with SRSF1 in 100 ml binding buffer 
(20 mM Tris-HCl, 75 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, 0.1% 
NP40, 1 mM DTT, 2.5 mM MgCl 2 , 10 U RNase inhibitor) 
at 25 
C for 40 min. The reaction mixtures were diluted 
1:10 with 900 ml binding buffer and immediately filtered 
through nitrocellulose membranes (Millipore, 0.45 mm) 
at a flow rate of 0.5 ml/min and rinsed with 3 ml binding 
buffer. Membranes were soaked in scintillation cocktail 
solution (4 ml) after drying at 60 
C for 1 h and then the 
amount of bound RNA was measured using liquid 
scintillation counter. The membrane after filtering and 
washing steps with only probe was determined and used 
as the base line (0%), and the membrane after just 
spotting of probe without washing was determined and 
used as 100% binding. The K d was estimated as 50% 
RNA bound fraction. None of the RNAs used in the 
binding experiment showed any secondary structure as 
judged by the RNAstructure (ver.5.03) program. </p>

<p>GST pull-down assay </p>

<p>GST-fusion proteins of 10 mg were mixed with purified 
target proteins of 15 mg in buffer containing 20 mM Tris 
(pH 7.9), 100 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, 1 mM DTT and 
0.05 % NP40 at 4 
C for 40 min. The mixture was further 
incubated with 15 ml glutathione sepharose resin 
(Amersham) for 30 min at 4 
C. Resins were washed 
three times with 400 ml buffer and the bound protein was 
eluted by boiling with 4Â gel loading dye for 5 min at 80 
C 
and was resolved by SDS-PAGE. Separated proteins were 
visualized by Coomassie staining. </p>

<p>In vitro splicing assay </p>

<p>b-Globin (Ron) in pCDNA with Ron ESE sequence 
was linearized by EcoRI and transcribed with T7 RNA 
polymerase, in the presence of [a-
32 P]-UTP as shown pre-
viously (3). For in vitro splicing, proteins were dialyzed in 
20 mM HEPES (pH 8.0), 300 mM KCl, 20% glycerol, 
0.5 mM DTT and 0.2 mM EDTA. Pre-mRNA was 
incubated with HeLa nuclear or cytoplasmic S100 
extracts in the presence of wt and mutant SRSF1-RBD 
as described before (13). Extracted RNA was resolved in 
denatured 5% acrylamide gel and its phosphorimage was 
analyzed using typhoon fluorescence scanner (GE 
healthcare). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>SRSF1 RBD recognizes ESEs with specificity </p>

<p>To elucidate the mechanism of ESE RNA recognition by 
SRSF1, we prepared SRSF1 RBD as a highly purified 
recombinant protein (Supplementary Figure S1 and 
Figure 1A). We tested the binding affinity of this protein 
in vitro with the ESEs present in the proto-oncogene Ron 
(Ron-ESE), which encodes a receptor tyrosine kinase, the </p>



<p>breast cancer-associated gene 1 (BRCA1) (BRCA-ESE), 
and the survival motor neuron protein gene 1 (SMN1) 
(SMN-ESE) (Figure 1B). In order to investigate the spe-
cificity of these ESEs, we also tested binding of the SRSF1 
RBD to mutated versions of each of these ESEs. The 
mutant Ron ESE used was tested previously and showed 
no splicing activity in cells while the naturally occurring 
BRCA1-ESE and SMN1-ESE mutants have been linked 
to disease (Figure 1B) (14-16). A filter-binding (FB) assay 
was used to evaluate the protein: RNA-binding affinity 
(Figure 1C). Of the three, the Ron ESE exhibited the 
highest affinity for SRSF1 RBD. However, binding 
affinity was moderate, measuring in the low micromolar 
range. The BRCA1 and SMN1 ESEs displayed weaker 
binding affinity. As expected, none of the three mutant 
ESEs showed any detectable binding (Figure 1C). 
We next tested SRSF1 RBD binding to the 5 
0 -SS RNA 
from the simian virus 40 (SV40) small T antigen (5 
0 -SS) 
as earlier reports suggested its possible involvement in 
SRSF1 binding (Figure 1B) (17). We found that the 
SRSF1 RBD exhibits modest binding to 5 
0 -SS with an 
affinity that is similar to the SMN1 ESE (Figure 1C). 
No interaction was observed when SRSF1 RBD binding 
to poly-U RNA was assayed as a control (Figure 1C). 
As an alternative approach, we next ran electrophoretic 
mobility shift assays (EMSA) to measure the binding 
affinity of the SRSF1 RBD for Ron ESE and the 5 
0 -SS 
(17) (Supplementary Figure S2A and B). EMSA analysis 
revealed a similar binding pattern as the FB assay with the 
Ron ESE binding more strongly than 5 
0 -SS to the SRSF1 
RBD. Also in agreement with the FB assay results, 
the poly-U RNA failed to interact with the protein 
(Supplementary Figure S2C). Therefore, despite their 
relatively low affinity, SRSF1 RBD binds to ESEs with 
sequence specificity. 
Even though these 5 
0 -SS sequences display some affinity 
for the SRSF1 RBD, our results do not necessarily imply 
that SRSF1 binds to these sequences within their natural </p>

<p>cellular context. Our binding data simply suggest that the 
5 
0 -SS sequences bear some characteristics of a functional 
ESE, as predicted by <rs type="software">ESEfinder</rs>. Moreover, we find 
that binding affinity does not agree with predictions of 
the <rs type="software">ESEfinder</rs> scoring system that were developed based 
upon ESEs identified by functional SELEX method 
(Figure 1B and C). This suggests that SRSF1:ESE-
binding affinity and splicing efficiency are not necessarily 
correlated. </p>

<p>SRSF1 RBD optimally binds to 10-mer ESE sequences 
with variable modes </p>

<p>In order to more clearly define the determinants of 
SRSF1:ESE binding, we employed the Ron ESE and 
SRSF1 RBD and investigated their interactions in 
greater detail. ESE sequences derived from functional 
SELEX exhibit only modest conservation with natural 
ESEs through a region of weak consensus that spans 
only 7 nt (15,18,19). Curiously, in vitro selection for 
ESEs based solely upon binding affinity identified 
octameric and decameric consensus sequences (4). To 
determine whether the SRSF1 RBD binds to RNA 
sequences that are heptameric or longer, we tested a 
13-nt sequence that contained the 7-nt core Ron ESE at 
the center and uridines nucleotides in all the flanking 
positions as a 7-mer sequence cannot be efficiently 
radiolabeled (Figure 2A). FB assay revealed little or no 
binding of this ESE by SRSF1 RBD (Figure 2B). 
Although a negative role for uracils in the flanking 
regions cannot be eliminated, this result strongly sug-
gested that SRSF1 mediates base-specific contacts with 
nucleotides beyond the 7-nt consensus core sequence. 
We next tested several RNA sequences that each con-
tained the 7-nt Ron ESE core sequence and progressively 
incorporated natural nucleotide sequences at the flanking 
regions up to the maximum length of 15 nt (Figure 2A). 
Initially, we tested five different RNA lengths: 7, 9, 11, 13 </p>

<p>Figure 1. ESE binding by SRSF1-RBD. (A) Cartoon representation of SRSF1 domain organization. (B) List of RNA sequences used in in vitro 
binding assay. The bar on the bottom indicates the mutation site. (C) Filter-binding assay showing the binding of SRSF1 RBD to Ron ESE, mutant 
Ron ESE (mRon), BRCA1, mBRCA1, SMN1, mSMN1, 5 
0 -SS and polyU. Errors (indicated by bar) were obtained from at least three independent 
experiments. The number in parenthesis denotes the apparent K d of binding. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 21 9415 </p>

<p>and 15-nt sequences (Figure 2B). All of the RNA possess-
ing 11 natural Ron ESE nucleotides or more bound 
SRSF1 RBD with similar affinities, whereas the 9-nt 
RNA bound only poorly. These results suggest that the 
minimal RNA length for native-like Ron ESE:SFRS1 
RBD interactions might be 10 or 11 nt. To further define 
the length of recognition sequence, we generated ESE 
sequences by adding nucleotide(s) at the 5 
0 -end or 3 
0 -end 
of the 9-nt core to create 10L, 10R, 12L, 12R, 14L and 
14R (Figure 2C). Unexpectedly, both 10L and 10R bound 
the protein with similar affinities and these affinities are 
comparable to the longer RNA sequences. Sequence 
comparison of 10L and 10R shows that 6 of 10 positions 
are different (Figure 2A, bottom). This observation is 
consistent with the idea that none or only a few base pos-
itions within the recognition sequence are stringently fixed 
to mediate unique interactions with the protein. This 
mode of binding explains how SRSF1 can accommodate 
large number of ESE sequences to impose splicing 
regulation. </p>

<p>The presence of uracils within or flanking the ESE 
reduces binding affinity </p>

<p>The failure of binding in the 7-mer core Ron ESE with 
flanking uracils to protein suggested that the flanking 
uracils may also play a negative role in the protein-
RNA recognition process. This observation is further sup-
ported by the very low binding affinity of SMN1 and 
BRCA1 ESEs; both of which contain several Us. We 
further examined the role of uracils within and outside 
of the core Ron ESE sequence in complex formation 
with the SRSF1 RBD. Having established that a 10-nt </p>

<p>sequence is required for full SRSF1 binding, we altered 
three flanking nucleotides of the 13-nt long Ron-ESE to U 
(3U) (Figure 3A). Filter-binding assay revealed that 
the 3U mutant bound with lower affinity to SRSF1 
RBD (Figure 3B). Reduced binding by the addition of 
three Us flanking to the optimized 10-nt sequence 
suggested that indeed uracils play a negative role in the 
RNA:protein recognition process. It is well established 
that poly U sequences are highly flexible as uracils are 
unstacked compared to adenines in poly A ribonucleotide 
sequences, which undergo temperature-dependent unfold-
ing (20). Therefore, the possible explanation for negative 
role of flanking uracils might arise due to the enhanced 
flexibility of the core RNA sequence in solution resulting 
in a greater entropic penalty for the complex formation. 
We further tested whether uracils within ESE sequences 
affect SRSF1 RBD:ESE complex formation. We focused 
on two positions, 1 and 7, within the core sequence of 
the Ron ESE (Figure 3A). Previous reports based on func-
tional splicing assays suggested that position 1 prefers 
C or G and discriminates against U and A, whereas 
position 7 prefers A or U (5). We altered position 1 to 
either A or U, and position 7 to either U or G and used 
FB assays to measure the binding affinities of these 
mutant ESEs for SRSF1. We found that, although the 
presence of U at either of these positions is detrimental 
to SRSF1 binding, the defect was more severe for U at 
position 7. Although these binding defects might be due to 
the loss of direct protein:RNA contact(s), or reduced 
ability of stacking interactions between the protein and 
uracils, it is also possible that a U at any position within 
the protein-binding region increases flexibility of ESE, 
which in turn negatively affects binding. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Determination of optimal ESE length for stable ESE:SRSF1-RBD complex formation. (A) The list of different variants of Ron ESE 
sequences tested for binding (top). Alignment of 10L and 10R sequences (bottom). Highlighted positions denote differences in the nucleotide identity. 
(B and C) Filter-binding assay showing the binding of SRSF1-RBD to Ron ESEs of varying lengths indicated in (A). Error bars represent results 
from three independent experiments. The number in parenthesis denotes the apparent K d of binding. </p>



<p>The linker region plays an essential role in ESE binding </p>

<p>In order to investigate the role played by the SRSF1 RBD 
in ESE recognition, we generated a series of constructs 
that encompass individual RRM domains alone, RRM1 
(R1) and RRM2 (R2), and with the adjacent linker (L), 
R1L and LR2 (Figure 4A). Neither R1 (SRSF1 residues 
1-90), nor R2, showed any binding to ESE. LR2 (residues 
90-196), but not R1L (1-118), showed partial binding 
(Figure 4B; Supplementary Figure S3A and B). The 
respective binding affinities displayed by R1 and LR2 
fragments defied the standard RNA-binding norms of 
RRM as R1, but not R2, contains the RNP motifs. 
However, the binding affinity of LR2 for ESE was signifi-
cantly lower when compared to that exhibited by the 
SRSF1 RBD. Taken together, these results suggest that 
the linker converts R2 into a RNA-binding motif, and 
that R1 and LR2 mediate cooperative ESE binding. 
This conclusion is further supported by the fact that no 
binding was observed when the linker was deleted. 
The amino acid composition of the 34-residue long 
linker indicates it to be highly flexible as it contains 
14 glycines. Nine contiguous glycines at the center 
(G9 segment) separate the two flanking segments contain-
ing several arginines interspaced with serines, threonines 
and tyrosines (Figure 5A). To further elucidate the role of 
the SRSF1 linker region in ESE binding, we mutated </p>

<p>several residues in both segments of the linker: R90A, 
R93A, R97A, R109A, R111A, Y112A, S116A, R117A/ 
R118A and S119A (Figure 5A). Upon evaluating the 
SRSF1 RBD mutants by FB assay we found that each 
was defective for binding to Ron ESE when compared to 
native SRSF1 RBD (Figure 5B). The R117A/R118A 
double mutant showed the most severe defect while both 
Y112A and S119A single mutants exhibited moderate 
binding. The remaining mutants showed varying degrees 
of weakened binding affinity. These observations are con-
sistent with a previous crosslinking-based binding assay 
that showed defective ESE binding by R117A/R118A 
mutants in RRM2 construct (107-215) (21). 
We also examined how the RBD mutants described 
above affect splicing in S100 splicing complement assay. 
It was previously shown that RBD alone was able to com-
plement constitutive splicing of b-globin pre-mRNA (3). 
Therefore, we used the same pre-mRNA in our assay. 
As expected, wt RBD efficiently complemented splicing; 
however, none of the linker mutant tested showed any 
splicing (Figure 5C). Next, we tested the effect of the 
F56D/F58D mutant that had been previously shown to 
be defective in splicing. As expected, this mutant failed 
to complement splicing in vitro. These results further 
support the importance of the linker in ESE binding and 
consequently in splicing. </p>

<p>Figure 4. The entire RBD of SRSF1 is required for optimal ESE binding. (A) Cartoon representation of SRSF1 fragments, R1 (RRM1), R2 
(RRM2), R1L (RRM1 with linker), LR2 (linker with RRM2) and LR2Á15, used for RNA-binding experiments. (B) Filter-binding assay 
showing the binding of His-tagged SRSF1 constructs (R1, R1L, R2 and LR2) to the 13-mer Ron ESE. Error bars obtained from three independent 
experiments. </p>

<p>Figure 3. The role of uridine in SRSF1-RBD binding. (A) The list of the mutated ESE sequences. (B) Filter-binding assay showing the binding of 
SRSF1-RBD to wt and mutant Ron ESE sequences. Errors (shown by bars) were calculated from three independent experiments. The number in 
parenthesis denotes the apparent K d of binding. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 21 9417 </p>

<p>The linker region mediates cooperative binding 
interactions between ESE and SRSF1-RBD </p>

<p>Relatively lesser role of R1 in ESE binding than R2 made 
us wonder if the most common RNA-binding motif 
(RNP1), present only in R1 is involved in ESE recogni-
tion. To examine the role of RNP1 in R1, conserved 
RNP1 residues, F56 and F58, were mutated to aspartates 
and the double mutant was tested for ESE binding by 
FB assay. We found that the RBD (F56D/F58D) 
mutant binds Ron ESE poorly implicating the involvement 
of these two residues in cognate ESE binding (Figure 6A). 
This result also explains why the F56D/F58D mutant 
impairs splicing (22,23). Intriguingly, the apparent 
binding affinity of this RBD mutant is comparable to 
that of the LR2 fragment suggesting that cooperation 
between R1 to the rest of the protein in ESE binding is 
mediated through its conserved RNP1 motif. We next 
investigated how residues in the R2 domain also partici-
pate in ESE binding. R2 domain does not contain consen-
sus RNP motifs but it includes a conserved heptapeptide 
sequence SWQDLKD, which has been implicated in 
RNA binding (21). As indicated by the RRM2 structure, 
W134, Q135 and R154, all reside close to one another on 
the same positively charged face of R2 (21). Therefore, we 
hypothesized that this face might likely be involved in 
ESE recognition. Although R154A was not defective in 
ESE binding, the W134A and Q135A mutants exhibited 
highly defective in ESE binding (Figure 6A). Dramatic 
defect in ESE binding by these two single mutants 
suggest cooperation between the protein segments in 
ESE recognition. Moreover, the involvement of four 
aromatic residues in ESE binding led us to propose that 
these residues might make stacking interactions as 
commonly observed in other RNA-protein complexes. 
To further test extensive nature of aromatic-RNA </p>

<p>contacts, we mutated four other tyrosines (Y79A and 
Y82A in R1, Y149A and Y153A in R2) located in the 
same face as F56/F58 or W134. Tyrosine mutants in the 
R2 (Y149A and Y153A), but not in the R1, showed defects 
in ESE binding (Figure 6B). This observation further em-
phasizes more significant role of the R2 in ESE binding. 
Since LR2 retains only partial ESE binding, the linker 
appears to play a special role in bringing R1 to complete 
the binding event. We hypothesized that the two ends of 
the linker separated by the central glycine-rich segment are 
involved in the R1-R2 cooperation. We have measured 
the binding of LR2 fragments to ESE both in the 
absence and presence of R1. An enhancement of ESE 
binding was observed when LR2 was mixed with R1 
(Figure 6C and Supplementary Figure S3C-D). 
However, this enhancement was not observed when the 
N-terminal part of the linker was removed (LR2ÁN15) 
(Figure 6C). To further test the coupling between the 
two segments of the linker, we created two double 
mutants one located in the N-terminal part (S91E/T95E) 
and the other in the C-terminal part of the linker. Both 
mutants were constructed in the context of the entire RBD 
(1-196). The S91E/T95E double mutant showed partial 
defect in ESE binding (Figure 6D). S119A single mutant 
was highly defective in ESE binding (Figure 5B), while 
S116E/S119E double mutant was only marginally defect-
ive (Figure 6D). However, when both double mutants 
were combined (S91E/T95E/S116E/S119E), the resultant 
quadruple mutant showed no measurable binding affinity 
(Figure 6D). That is, the defect is not additive but 
cooperative. Taken together these results suggest that 
the two end of the linker cooperate with each other in 
ESE binding and together they cooperate with the 
R2. Finally, this LR2-ESE subcomplex completes the 
binding process by recruiting the RNP1 motif of the R1 </p>

<p>Figure 5. The linker in RBD promotes differential ESE binding by SRSF1. (A) The linker sequence and the sites of mutations are denoted in the 
carton. (B) Filter-binding assay showing the binding of His-SRSF1-RBD wt and different linker mutants. Error bars obtained from three 
independent experiments. The number in parenthesis denotes the apparent K d of binding and (À) indicates not determined. (C) In vitro splicing 
assay of the b-gb (Ron) pre-mRNA substrate by SRSF1-RBD and the linker mutants using 20 or 40 pmol with S100 extracts. The template, 
intermediate and spliced products are marked in the right side of the gel. </p>



<p>domain. Our model further highlights a novel extensive 
role played by a large linker in RNA binding. 
We further tested if the direct interactions between the 
two RRMs also play a role in cooperative interaction 
using GST pull-down assay. In this assay, interactions 
between GST-R1 and wt or mutants LR2 were tested in 
the absence or in the presence of Ron-ESE. We found that 
the two wt fragments do not interact in the absence of 
RNA (Supplementary Figure S4A). They interact only 
in the presence of native Ron-ESE suggesting that the 
RNA mediates the binding of two protein fragments 
(Supplementary Figure S4A). Significant weakening of 
LR2 retention by the linker mutations further confirms 
that the linker interaction with RNA is critical for the 
recruitment of R1 and R2 (Supplementary Figure S4B). 
However, this result does not preclude if ESE induces 
further contact between the two RRMs. </p>

<p>Cooperative binding brings the two RRMs in close 
proximity </p>

<p>To further investigate if the two SRSF1 RRMs directly 
cooperate in ESE binding, we first created a model of the 
ESE:R1 complex based upon the NMR structures of the 
SRSF3:RNA complex (8) and free SRSF1-RRM1 
(PDB,1X4A) assuming these canonical RRMs of these 
two SR proteins bind RNA using a similar mode. For 
the protein-protein interaction, exposed surface of R1 
away from the putative RNA-binding surface might 
be involved. We identified four surface-exposed patches </p>

<p>that might play such a role (Figure 7A). These 
patches are composed of residues D68/D69, Y72, 
Y39/Y77 and D62/D63/D66. We mutated residues in 
each patch to create mutants M1 (E68A/D69A), M2 
(Y72A), M3 (Y39E/Y77A) and M4 (E62A/D63A/D66A). 
FB assay revealed only minor defects in ESE binding by 
these mutants (Figure 7B). Our results, therefore, suggest 
that these patches are not involved in ESE binding. 
To test if the two domains interact with each other 
when present as separate fragments, we carried out GST 
pull-down experiments using GST-R1 and LR2 as 
described earlier (Figure 7C). We found that M1, M2 
and M4 showed no defect in LR2 retention suggesting 
that the global RNA-binding modes by R1 and LR2 
were preserved (Figure 7C). However, M3 was drastically 
defective in LR2 retention activity through ESE binding. 
Our result thus suggests that both or one of the two 
residues, Y39 and Y77, play a role in ESE binding when 
two RRMs are not covalently linked. This result also 
indicates plasticity in ESE binding by the protein. We 
propose that when the intact protein binds ESE, two 
RRMs do not directly bind but they might lie in close 
proximity. 
We have further tested these RRM1 mutants for their 
ability to complement in vitro splicing (Figure 7D). 
We found that these are severely defective in splicing 
even though they are able to bind ESE. We cannot 
predict the precise reason for their defectiveness. It 
appears that these residues play roles in the spliceosome 
assembly in steps other than the RNA recognition. </p>

<p>Figure 6. The linker region mediates cooperative binding interactions between ESE and SRSF1-RBD. (A) Filter-binding assay of His-tagged 
SRSF1-RBD wt and mutants, F56D/F58D from R1, W134A, Q135A and R154A from R2 to Ron ESE of 13 nt. Error bars obtained from three 
independent experiments. (B) Filter-binding assay of His-tagged SRSF1-RBD wt, and four different tyrosine to alanine mutants, Y79A and Y82A 
from R1, and Y149A and Y153A from R2 to 13-mer Ron ESE. Error bars obtained from three independent three experiments. (C) Filter-binding 
assay showing cooperative interactions between ESE and mixtures of R1 and different constructs of R2 (R2, LR2Á5 and LR2) of SRSF1. Error bars 
obtained from three independent three experiments. (D) Filter-binding assay showing cooperation between the N-terminal and C-terminal of the 
linker of SRSF1 by using three different mutants (S91E/T95 from N-terminal, S116E/S119E from C-terminal, and S91E/T95E/S116E/S119E). 
The number in parenthesis denotes the apparent K d of binding and (À) indicates not determined. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 21 9419 </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>SRSF1 regulates splicing by binding to a broad spectrum 
of ESE sequences. SELEX experiments in which selection 
was based either purely on binding or splicing (functional) 
activity identified significantly different SRSF1-specific 
RNA sequences: RGAAGAAC and AGGACRRAGC 
obtained through binding SELEX (4) and SRSASGA 
(S = C or G) by functional SELEX (5). Recent CLIP 
method identified an even more diverse consensus 
sequence for SRSF1 (UGRWG, R:purine; W:A/G) (24). 
Results presented here explain how diverse ESE sequences 
can be recognized: we show that the decameric ESE 
sequences, but not the shorter sequences as generally 
thought, are optimal for SRSF1 binding. Our finding 
that the 10th nucleotide can be added to the either end 
to obtain maximal binding affinity strongly points toward 
a semi-conservative binding mode since seven positions 
are different between these two sequences. A and G sub-
stitute each other in these differed positions. Since A and 
G are decorated with different functional groups and their </p>

<p>hydrogen bonding capacity is different, we conclude 
that the complex formation is dominated by stacking 
interactions. Therefore, we suggest sequence-specific 
hydrogen bonding contacts between the protein and 
RNA might not be as distinctive a feature as the 
stacking interactions between bases and aromatic side 
chains. Purines are better suited for stacking than pyrimi-
dines, this explains why SRSF1-specific ESEs are 
dominated by the purine residues. The presence of uracil 
both inside and flanking the recognition sequence is less 
permissible to SRSF1 binding. The presence of uracil 
destabilizes the complex, perhaps, due to its higher flexi-
bility compared to other bases in the oligonucleotide 
and/or due to its reduced stacking interactions with the 
protein. The NMR solution structure of the single 
RRM-containing SR protein, SRSF3 (SRp20), bound 
to a 4-nt (CAUC) ESE shows interesting property of the 
complex: this structure shows protein bound to the RNA 
primarily through stacking interactions with only one 
base-specific hydrogen-bonding contact (8). However, 
the significance of this base-specific contact awaits </p>

<p>Figure 7. Residues remote from the RNA-binding surface affect ESE recognition (A) The ribbon presentation of the RRM1 domain of SRSF1. The 
RNP1 residues F56 and F58 are shown in blue. Backbones of residues in four exposed surfaces are denoted by different colors (M1 (E68A/D69A; 
yellow), M2 (Y72A; gray), M3 (Y39E/Y77A; pink) and M4 (E62A/D63A/D66A; magenta). Additionally, side chains of two M3 residues are shown. 
(B) Filter-binding assay of His-tagged SRSF1 RBD wt and mutants, (M1, M2, M3 and M4) to Ron ESE of 13 nt. Error bars obtained from three 
independent experiments. The number in parenthesis denotes the apparent K d of binding. (C) GST pull-down assay was performed to examine the 
interaction between 10 mg wt GST-SRSF1 (R1) wt or four mutants (M1, M2, M3 and M4) and 15 mg His-SRSF1 (LR2) in each the presence of wt 
Ron ESE or mutant Ron ESE. As a control, GST protein was used instead of GST-SRSF1 (R1) with wt His-SRSF1 (LR2). SDS-PAGE was resolved 
in 12.5% acrylamide gel and stained by Coomassie blue. (D) In vitro splicing of the b-gb (Ron) pre-mRNA substrate using wt SRSF1-RBD and 
SRSF1-RBD containing M1, M2, M3a (Y39E), M3b (Y77A) and M4 mutants. An amount of 25 and 50 pmol S100 extracts were used for the 
splicing reactions. (E) A cartoon depicting the mechanism of ESE binding by SRSF1-RBD. In the absence of ESE, the linker domain of the SRSF1 
is flexible and probably remains unstructured. However, in the presence of ESE, LR2 binds to ESE and then R1 makes contact to ESE. This binding 
mode brings R1 and LR2 adjacent each other. </p>



<p>further investigation. Our results when considered 
through this structural study a novel RNA: protein recog-
nition strategy can be predicted between SR proteins and 
ESE sequences. All three segments of the RBD; the linker 
and the RRMs are required for ESE binding. Most of the 
single or double mutations drastically reduced binding 
affinity suggesting that the RNA contacting residues are 
in a part of interaction network and recognize RNA in 
a cooperative manner. These observations suggest a novel 
ESE-binding mechanism by SRSF1 RBD where the distal 
protein segments assembles around the target RNA 
stabilize the protein-RNA complex through strongly 
cooperative 
intra-molecular 
protein-protein 
and 
inter-molecular protein-RNA contacts. Since the linker 
is flexible in natures, it can bind to a variety of sequences 
with low sequence specificity before properly orienting the 
RRMs to make specific and semi-specific contacts. In such 
a binding, protein-protein contact between the linker and 
RRM2 or RRM1 may contribute significant binding 
energy in forming the complex. This explains why so 
many single or double mutants practically abolish the 
complex formation. This coupled binding also explains 
how small variation in the linker can greatly inhibit the 
association process. For instance, the modification of the 
linker would greatly affect RNA binding. Indeed, it has 
been shown that methylation of arginines (R93, R97 and 
R109) impact on splicing (25). It is possible that phos-
phorylation of serines and threonine will reduce RNA 
binding and hence would negatively affect splicing. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank Drs Simpson Joseph, Joseph Adams, 
Xiang-Dong Fu and Tom Huxford for their comments on 
the manuscript. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Funding for open access charge: National Institutes of 
Health (NIH) in U.S. (grant number GM084277 to G.G.). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 21 9421 </p>

</text></tei>