<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3558131" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:28+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Gonadotropin releasing hormone (GnRH) plays a key role in reproduction. 
This decapeptide is synthesized and released by hypothalamus and induces 
the pituitary gonadotrop cells to release pituitary gonadotropin hormones. In 
some extrapituitary compartments GnRH and its receptor act as part of the 
autocrine regulatory system of cell proliferation. The anticancer activity of 
GnRH and its analogues has been observed by many researchers. In this study 
the anticancer activity of a new analogue of GnRH and triptorelin was 
investigated by cell proliferation assay. Results indicate that proliferation of 
human breast and ovarian cancer cell lines are dose-dependently inhibited. 
The inhibitory efficiency of the new analogue is proved to be higher than the 
original triptorelin. In addition to its antimitogenic activity, evidence was 
found for the involvement of the apoptotic mechanism in the action of the 
new analogue and triptorelin. In conclusion, the new analogue can be 
considered as a good pharmaceutical candidate. </p>

<p>sexes (1) . Therefore, GnRH analogues have 
been used in the assisted reproduction 
(in vitro fertilization and embryo transfer), 
treatment of infertility due to polycystic 
ovarian diseases and fibroids. Also the effi-
ciency of analogues of GnRH for the treat-
ment of children with precocious puberty, 
endometrial carcinoma, estrogen-dependent 
breast cancer and prostate cancer is well 
established (2) . There is growing evidence of 
autocrine/ paracrine GnRH systems in human </p>

<p>*Corresponding author: 
Hossein Naderi-Manesh, 
Ph.D., Department of 
Biophysics, School of Basic 
Science, Tarbiat Modares 
University, Tehran, Iran 
E-mail: 
Naderman@modares.ac.ir 
Tel: +98 21 88006652 
Fax: +98 21 88006652 
Received: 26 Jul 2009 
Accepted: 13 Sep 2009 </p>

<p>The Anticancer Activity of Triptorelin </p>

<p>Avicenna Journal of Medical Biotechnology, Vol. 1, No. 2, July-September 2009 </p>



<p>reproductive tissues (3-6) . Recent studies sug-
gest that about 50% of breast cancer and 80% 
of ovarian cancer cell lines express high-
affinity binding site for GnRH and its 
analogues as part of the autocrine regulatory 
system of cell proliferation. Therefore anti-
cancer activity of GnRH analogues has been 
observed by many others (7-11) . 
Since 1972 systematic work has been 
preceding to synthesize agonistic and antag-
onistic analogues of GnRH. A powerful 
interest in medical applications of GnRH 
derivatives stimulated this undertaking. Thus, 
the intense activity that has occurred in this 
field was caused by the desire to synthesize 
super active analogue with prolonged biologic 
activity. Many agonistic and antagonistic ana-
logues more potent than the parent hormone 
have been made. Several of these analogues 
such as triptorelin, goserelin, leuprorelin and 
buserelin are being used clinically and the list 
of their applications is steadily expanding (2) . 
Considerable effort has been devoted to the 
synthesis of peptidomimetic structures to 
overcome the unfavorable properties and a 
therapeutic deficiency of peptides (12,13) . 
Among them is insertion of some chemical 
groups in the peptide sequences to increase 
their activity efficiency. In the present work 
the anticancer activity of a new GnRH ana-
logue was investigated in comparison with 
triptorelin. The new analogue structure is 
similar to triptorelin with two extra chemical 
groups inserted between Leu7 and Arg8 in 
order to increase peptide hydrophobic prop-
erties (Figure 1). Based on previous report on 
the molecular mechanism of ligand inter-
action with the GnRH receptor (14) , the 
hydrogen bonding and π-stacking interaction 
play main roles in GnRH and its receptor 
interaction. Therefore we expect stronger 
interaction between new analogue and GnRH 
receptor leading to greater peptide activity. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Material </p>

<p>[D-Trp 6 ] LHRH (Triptorelin) was synthe-
sized in our laboratory by solid phase method </p>

<p>and the new analogue was kindly provided by 
Dr Balalaie et al (15) . Human breast cancer cell 
line (T47D) and ovarian cancer cell line 
(OVCAR3) were obtained from Pasteur Insti-
tute of Iran. RPMI 1640 and Fetal Bovine 
Serum (FBS) were purchased from Gibco 
(USA) and Biosera (UK). Multiple 6 well-
dishes were Greiner bio-one (Germany) prod-
uct. Annexin V-FITC apoptosis detection kit 
was obtained from BD Bioscience, Pharmin-
gen (US). </p>

<p>Cell culture </p>

<p>Human breast cancer cell line (T47D) and 
ovarian cancer cell line (OVCAR3) were 
maintained in RPMI 1640 medium supple-
mented with 10% heat-inactivated bovine 
serum albumin and kept at 37 °C in a humidi-
fied 5% CO 2 atmosphere. </p>

<p>Cell proliferation assay </p>

<p>To determine the anti-proliferation activity 
of the new analogue, the dose-dependent 
proliferation experiments were performed. In 
brief following steps were carried out: 2×10 4 
cells of each cell line were plated in multiple 
6 well-dishes. After 24 hr, the cells were 
treated with 10 -11 , 10 -9 , 10 -7 and 10 -5 M con-
centrations of each peptide. This treatment 
was repeated three times during six days. On 
the six th day, cells were trypsinized and after 
Trypan-blue staining, the viable cells were 
counted with Neubauer-type hemocytometer 
and the data was expressed as the percentage 
of control. All proliferation assays were 
performed at least three times. </p>

<p>Apoptotic assay </p>

<p>Cytomorphological changes were observed 
only in treated OVCAR3 cells in 10 -9 M 
concentration of triptorelin with an Olympus 
phase-contrast microscope. Cell death by 
apoptosis was confirmed using Annexin V-
FITC apoptosis detection kit with a vital dye 
such as Propidium-Iodide (PI) according to 
the manufacturer′s instructions. Briefly, 
OVCAR3 adherent cells that were treated 
with triptorelin and the new analogue were 
washed with the culture medium. Surface 
exposure of Phosphatidyl Serine (PS), as a </p>

<p>Mirzaei Saleh-Abady M, et al </p>

<p>Avicenna Journal of Medical Biotechnology, Vol. 1, No. 2, July-September 2009 </p>



<p>plasma membrane asymmetry in apoptotic 
cells, was detected by adding annexin V-FITC 
to the culture medium in a final concentration 
of 5 μg/ml. The cells incubated for 5 min at 
room temperature, then PI was added 
(1 μg/ml) (16,17) . After rinsing with culture 
medium to remove excess dyes, the cells were 
observed by fluorescence microscope 
(Olympus). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The data from three or four dose-dependent 
experiments were tested by ANOVA followed 
by post-hoc analysis (Duncan test). All analy-
sis performed with <rs type="software">SPSS</rs> software. </p>

<p>Results 
In T47D and OVCAR3 cell lines, prolifera-
tion was dose-dependently inhibited with 
different concentrations (10 -11 , 10 -9 , 10 -7 and </p>

<p>10 -5 M) of the new analogue and triptorelin 
(Figures 2 and 3). The anticancer activity of 
the new analogue was higher than triptorelin 
at all concentrations. Table 1 gives a compari-
son of the cell number percent of cancer cell 
lines after treatment with triptorelin and the 
new analogue. 
After treatment of OVCAR3 cell line with 
the new analogue and triptorelin, some mor-
phologic signs of programmed cell death 
could be detected by invert phase contrast 
microscope. The vacuoles in the cytoplasm, 
rounding-up of cells, apoptotic bodies and 
bleb formation were seen as characteristic 
signs of the apoptotic process, while control 
cells had normal morphology (Figure 4). 
Apoptosis was also confirmed by annexin 
V-FITC apoptosis detection kit. OVCAR3 
cells with annexinV -/PI -were alive, annexin 
V + /PI -were undergoing early apoptosis and 
annexinV + /PI + were either in the end of 
apoptosis or were dead (Figure 5). </p>

<p>Discussion 
The anticancer activity of the new analogue </p>

<p>Figure 1. Chemical structures of the triptorelin and the new 
analogue </p>

<p>Figure 3. Effect of 6 days of treatment with different 
concentrations of triptorelin and the new analogue on 
OVCAR3 cell line. Each column represents the cell number 
percent in comparison with control. The data are 
representative of three independent experiments. Analysis of 
variance: P&lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Effect of 6 days of treatment with different 
concentrations of triptorelin and the new analogue on 
T47D cell line. Each column represents the cell 
number percent in comparison with the control. The 
data are representative of three independent 
experiments. Analysis of variance: P&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>Table 1. Cell number percent of cancer cell lines after treatment with 
(10 -11 , 10 -9 , 10 -7 , and 10 -5 M) concentration of triptorelin and the new 
analogue </p>

<p>Cells, % of control </p>

<p>Triptorelin (M) 
New analogue (M) 
10 -11 10 -9 10 -7 10 -5 
10 -11 
10 -9 
10 -7 
10 -5 </p>

<p>Cell lines </p>

<p>T47D 
93 
81 
70 
35 
78 
65 
58 
10 
OVCAR3 
90 
66 
66 
33 
83 
50 
17 
17 </p>

<p>The Anticancer Activity of Triptorelin </p>

<p>Avicenna Journal of Medical Biotechnology, Vol. 1, No. 2, July-September 2009 </p>



<p>was higher than triptorelin at different 
concentrations. The improved activity of the 
new analogue is probably due to its stronger 
interaction with the GnRH receptor. Söderhäll 
et al reported that the insertion of hydropho-
bic groups in GnRH sequence would increase 
the π-stacking interaction of the peptide with 
the hydrophobic pocket of GnRH receptor 
and therefore improved its activity (18) 
. Further-
more the presence of such chemical groups in 
the new analogue sequence is thought to 
increase the protease stability of the new 
analogue and therefore increase its biological 
activity. 
The results of our proliferation assay </p>

<p>correspond to similar observations obtained 
by other groups and are explained by the fact 
that GnRH and its receptor are parts of the 
negative autocrine regulatory system of cell 
proliferation (7-10) . The most important features 
of GnRH signaling in tumors are the inhibi-
tory interference with mitogenic pathway that 
results in antiproliferative actions. This 
peptide activates a protein tyrosine phospha-
tase that could inhibit the mitogenic signal 
transduction of growth factor receptors and 
therefore down regulates the cell proliferation </p>

<p>(10) </p>

<p>. In another way our findings support 
previous studies that some GnRH analogues 
can prompt apoptosis in breast, ovarian, 
endometrium and prostate cancer cell lines </p>

<p>(1,19-28) </p>

<p>. However the mechanism underlying 
the apoptotic effect of the analogues in the 
human counterpart is not fully known. 
In conclusion our results show that the 
anticancer activity of the new analogue is 
more than triptorelin and it seems to be due to 
the known mechanisms of GnRH effect on 
extrapituitary compartments that was ex-
plained before. Therefore this new analogue 
can be considered as a good pharmaceutical 
candidate. </p>

<p>Acknowledgement 
We appreciate the helpful discussion and 
comments given by Dr. Sadjady. The authors 
also express their gratitude to the Research 
Council of Tarbiat Modares University. </p>

<p>Figure 4. (a) Normal OVCAR3 cell line. (b)Apoptotic forms of OVCAR3 cell line observed 
by invert phase-contrast microscope. Arrows show the morphologic signs of programmed 
cell death in early apoptosis </p>

<p>Figure 5. Apoptotic forms of OVCAR3 cell line observed by 
fluorescence microscope. OVCAR3 cell line was stained 
with annexinV-FITC/PI. Arrows show the plasma membrane 
asymmetry in early apoptotic cells. Boxes show different 
stage of apoptosis such as early and late / already dead cells </p>

<p>Mirzaei Saleh-Abady M, et al </p>

<p>Avicenna Journal of Medical Biotechnology, Vol. 1, No. 2, July-September 2009 </p>





<p>The Anticancer Activity of Triptorelin </p>

<p>Avicenna Journal of Medical Biotechnology, Vol. 1, No. 2, July-September 2009 </p>





</text></tei>