<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3575798" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:39+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Uracil analogs with halogen substitution at the 5-position 
represent an important class of compounds with regard to 
their mutagenic activity (1). Such analogs were first 
synthesized in the 1950s as potential anti-tumor agents 
(2,3). The 5-fluorouracil (FU) analog is a well-known 
anti-cancer drug for treatment of human malignancies 
(4). 5-Chlorouracil and 5-bromouracil (ClU and BrU, 
respectively) are associated with inflammation and are 
considered to be carcinogenic (5). 5-Iodouracil (IU) was 
shown to have lethal and mutagenic effects on bacterio-
phage T4 (6). 
Halogenated uracil residues are expected to exhibit base 
pairing properties in double-stranded nucleic acids that 
are closely related to those of thymine, thus involving 
complementary pairs with A or wobble pairs with G 
that are stabilized via Watson-Crick (W-C) hydrogen 
bonds. However, substitution at the 5-position of uracil 
can substantially alter the physical (electronic) and 
chemical properties of the nucleobase, as evidenced by 
changes in the UV spectra and the values of the pK a (7). 
The effects of incorporation of FU into DNA on the struc-
ture and dynamics of the latter have been studied quite 
extensively, arguably as a result of the interesting pharma-
cological properties of this U analog as an anti-cancer 
agent (8-10). Interest in other halouracil analogs was pri-
marily focused on their use as radiosensitizing agents in 
human cancers. BrU and IU were shown to be more ef-
fective in killing tumor cells using ionizing radiation 
(11,12). However, ClU, though an effective mutagen, 
clastogen and toxicant, as well as an effective inducer of 
sister-chromatid exchange, is not as sensitive to ionizing 
radiation as other thymine analogs (3). The relative lack of 
interest in ClU may explain the fact that a thorough in-
vestigation of the impact of the replacement of T with ClU 
on the base pairing geometry and duplex conformation 
using structural tools is presently lacking. </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 615 343 8070; Fax: +1 615 322 7122; Email: martin.egli@vanderbilt.edu </p>

<p>Published online 28 December 2012 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 4 2689-2697 
doi:10.1093/nar/gks1316 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), which 
permits non-commercial reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact 
journals.permissions@oup.com. </p>

<p>Marlie`re et al. (13) recently evolved genomic DNA 
composed of the three canonical bases A, C and G and 
the artificial base ClU in an Escherichia coli 
strain lacking thymidylate synthase and requiring exogen-
ous T. Selection over 25 weeks in a specially developed 
cultivation device yielded descendants that grew essen-
tially with only ClU instead of T. The DNA of adapted 
bacteria contained 90% ClU and 10% T and this residual 
fraction was forced to &lt;2% by disrupting the trmA gene 
for tRNA U54 methyltransferase. 
The above pioneering study prompted us to analyze the 
base pair geometries of ClU with A and G in more detail. 
To date, no crystallographic study of a DNA duplex 
comprising ClU:A or ClU:G base pairs has been 
reported. A nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) investiga-
tion by Theruvathu et al. (14) did not bring to light any 
substantial difference in the geometries of ClU:A and T:A 
base pairs. Also, the geometries of ClU:G and T:G wobble 
pairs exhibited similar geometries (15). In another study, 
the stacking patterns of a halogenated (F, Cl or Br) 
uridine overhang at the 3 
0 -terminus of an octamer 
RNA:DNA hybrid duplex were analyzed in presence of 
rhodium or iridium hexamine salt (16). The crystal struc-
tures with ClU and BrU were similar in that the dangling 
ends were located atop the terminal base pair, whereas FU 
was ejected from the helical stack. 
To compare the geometries of ClU:A and ClU:G base 
pairs with those of the corresponding T:A and T:G pairs, 
respectively, and to examine possible effects of these 
artificial pairs on the conformation of duplex DNA, we 
determined crystal structures of four Dickerson-Drew 
Dodecamer (DDD) B-form duplexes containing 
two ClU:A pairs ([d(CGCGAA{ClU}TCGCG)] 2 , 
referred to as ClU7 here, and [d(CGCGAAT 
{ClU}CGCG)] 2 ; ClU8), four ClU:A pairs ([d(CGCGAA 
{ClUClU}CGCG)] 2 ; ClU7/8), or two ClU:G base pairs 
([d(CGCGAATT{ClU}GCG)] 2 , ClU9) in complex with 
Bacillus halodurans RNase H (BhRNase H) at resolutions 
between 1.5 and 1.7 Å . Crystals grown for the duplexes 
alone were not of diffraction-quality and we therefore 
resorted to using RNase H as a scaffold. DNA duplexes 
act as inhibitors of RNase H (17) and the enzyme binds 
double-stranded DNA non-specifically and without 
perturbing the structure of the central T:A region of the 
duplex (18), thus not compromising our geometric 
analysis of ClU:A or ClU:G pairs (the latter being 
adjacent to the four central T:A pairs). 
Our structures reveal nearly identical geometries of the 
ClU:A and ClU:G base pairs compared with T:A and 
T:G, respectively. In line with the structural similarities, 
UV melting experiments of DNA duplexes with ClU pairs 
uncovered only very minor consequences of the replace-
ment of T by ClU opposite A or G relative to the parent 
duplexes with T:A or T:G pairs, respectively. These obser-
vations regarding structure and stability were mirrored at 
the level of function. Thus, the restriction endonuclease 
EcoRI did not display a preference in its ability to recog-
nize and cleave the natural recognition sequence GjAATT 
C ('j' marks the cleavage site) in the native DDD 
compared with duplexes featuring the modified recogni-
tion sequences GjAA(ClU)TC or GjAAT(ClU)C. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Protein expression and purification </p>

<p>Bacillus halodurans genomic DNA was purchased from 
American Type Culture Collection (ATCC, Manassas, 
VA, USA). The Asp132!Asn mutant of BhRNase H 
(Met58 to Lys196) was expressed in E. coli and purified 
as described previously (18). The protein solution was 
concentrated to 25 mg/ml. </p>

<p>Synthesis of 5 
0 -O-dimethoxytrityl-5-chloro-2 
0 -
deoxyuridine, 3 
0 -[(2-cyanoethyl)-(N,N-diisopropyl)]-
phosphoramidite and incorporation of ClU into 
oligonucleotides </p>

<p>To a colorless solution of 5-chloro-2 
0 -deoxyuridine (19) 
(600 mg, 2.28 mmol) in pyridine (20 ml), 4,4 
0 -
dimethoxytrityl chloride (930 mg, 2.75 mmol) was added 
in one portion at room temperature (RT). The reaction 
mixture was stirred for 12 h and turned to a yellow-orange 
color. After the starting material had disappeared, the 
reaction mixture was cooled in an ice bath, methanol 
(1 ml) was added and the reaction mixture was 
concentrated and co-evaporated twice with toluene. The 
residue was dissolved in dichloromethane, washed with 
H 2 O, dried over Na 2 SO 4 and purified by column chroma-
tography on silica gel to yield 5 
0 -O-dimethoxytrityl-5-
chloro-2 
0 -deoxyuridine (1.08 g, 84%). This compound 
(1.08 g, 1.91 mmol) was dissolved in dichloromethane (10 
ml) and cooled in an ice bath. N,N-Diisopropylethylamine 
(1.5 ml, 8.76 mmol) and 2-cyanoethyl N,N-diisopropyl-
chlorophosphoramidite (0.58 ml, 2.6 mmol) were added. 
The reaction solution was stirred for 30 min at RT. 
Upon completion, the reaction mixture was concentrated 
and co-evaporated twice with toluene. The crude material 
was purified by column chromatography on silica to 
yield 5 
0 -O-dimethoxytrityl-5-chloro-2 
0 -deoxyuridine, 3 
0 -
[(2-cyanoethyl)-(N,N-diisopropyl)]-phosphoramidite (1.0 g, 
68%). </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P NMR (CDCl 3 , 25 
C): d = 149.08, 148.7. High-
resolution mass spectrometry (HRMS) calculated for 
C 39 H 46 ClN 4 O 8 P, [MH+] 765.2794, found 765.2820. 
All four ClU-modified, high-pressure liquid chromatog-
raphy-purified DDD oligonucleotides were purchased 
from Trilink (San Diego, CA, USA). The DNAs were 
annealed and mixed with the protein at 1.2:1 molar ratio 
in the presence of 5 mM MgCl 2 . </p>

<p>Crystallization and structure determination </p>

<p>Crystallization experiments were performed by the sitting 
drop vapor diffusion technique at 4 
C using a sparse 
matrix screen (Hampton Research, Aliso Viejo, CA, 
USA) (20). A quantity of 1 ml complex solution was 
mixed with 1 ml of reservoir solution and equilibrated 
against 40 ml reservoir wells. Crystals appeared in 
droplets containing 0.2 M magnesium acetate, 0.1 M 
sodium cacodylate (pH 6.5) and 20% (w/v) PEG 8000 
within 2-3 days. Crystals were mounted in nylon loops, 
cryo-protected in reservoir solution containing 20% 
glycerol and frozen in liquid nitrogen. Diffraction data 
were collected using either a Mar225 or Mar300 CCD 
detector on the 21-ID F/D beam lines of the Life </p>



<p>Sciences Collaborative Access Team (LS-CAT) at the 
Advanced Photon Source, Argonne National Laboratory 
(Argonne, IL, USA). Data were integrated and scaled with 
the program <rs type="software">HKL2000</rs> (21). The structures were 
determined by the Molecular Replacement technique 
using the program MOLREP (22,23) and the BhRNase 
H structure with PDB ID code 3D0P (protein alone) as 
the search model. Initial refinement was carried out with 
the program <rs type="software">REFMAC</rs> (24) and DNA duplexes were then 
gradually built into the electron density, 2-3 bp at a time, 
followed by further refinement. Manual rebuilding was 
performed with the program <rs type="software">COOT</rs> (25). Water molecules 
and metal ions were added gradually and isotropic/ 
Translation Libration Screw-motion (TLS) refinement 
was continued with the program <rs type="software">PHENIX</rs> (26). A 
summary of crystallographic parameters is provided in 
Table 1. Helical parameters were calculated with the 
program <rs type="software">CURVES</rs> (27). Illustrations were generated 
with the program <rs type="software">UCSF Chimera</rs> (28). </p>

<p>UV thermal melting </p>

<p>Melting of each oligonucleotide (7.5 mM duplex concen-
tration) was performed in 10 mM sodium phosphate, pH 
7.4 and 0.1 mM EDTA in the presence of 150 mM NaCl. 
Absorbance versus temperature profiles were measured 
with a Varian Cary 300 spectrophotometer at 260 nm 
wavelength and 1-cm path length at heating or cooling 
rates of 0.5 
C/min. Melting temperatures were determined 
with Varian Cary UV T m Analysis software and are 
averages of the maxima of the first derivative of the 
95-point smoothed curves from heating and cooling 
experiments. The final T m values are based on six inde-
pendent measurements. Hyperchromicities were determ-
ined by calculating the difference of absorbance between 
high-and low-temperature baselines and dividing by the 
absorbance of the low-temperature baseline. </p>

<p>Cleavage assays </p>

<p>Cleavage assays with EcoRI were conducted following a 
previous protocol (29) with modifications. Briefly, 5 mM </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>P-labeled DNA was incubated at 37 
C with EcoRI 
buffer and 20 U of EcoRI (high fidelity; New England 
Biolabs, Ipswich, MA, USA) in a volume of 10 ml, with 
final concentrations of 50 mM potassium acetate, 20 mM 
Tris-acetate, pH 7.5, 10 mM magnesium acetate and 
1 mM dithiothreitol. Reactions were started by adding 
EcoRI and were stopped by removing an aliquot of 1 ml 
reaction mixture at various times and adding it to 9 ml of 
20 mM EDTA (pH 9.0) in 95% (v/v) formamide, followed 
by 20% PAGE analysis. </p>

<p>Coordinates </p>

<p>Final coordinates and structure factors for all four 
dodecamers have been deposited in the Protein Data 
Bank (http://www.rcsb.org.) The PDB ID codes are 
4HUF (ClU7), 4HTU (ClU8), 4HUG (ClU7/8) and 
4HUE (ClU9). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Overall structures of the ClU-modified DDD:RNase 
H complexes </p>

<p>To gain a better understanding of the potential structural 
change due to the replacement of the thymine 5-methyl 
group by chlorine, we selected the DDD B-form DNA 
as a template and synthesized four modified DDDs with 
ClU either located opposite A (ClU7, ClU8, ClU7/8) or 
opposite G (ClU9). We used crystals of these modified 
DDDs in complex with BhRNase H to study the 
geometries of ClU:A and ClU:G pairs as the crystals of 
the oligonucleotides alone were not of sufficient quality 
for a detailed structural analysis. In the crystal of the </p>

<p>Table 1. Crystal data, data collection parameters and structure refinement statistics </p>

<p>Structure/duplex 
ClU8 
ClU9 
ClU7 
ClU7/8 </p>

<p>Space group 
P2 1 2 1 2 1 </p>

<p>Cell dimensions 
a (Å ) 
64.08 
64.36 
64.19 
63.83 
b (Å ) 
64.76 
64.81 
64.75 
64.64 
c (Å ) 
116.47 
116.62 
116.47 
116.29 </p>

<p>Data collection 
Wave length (Å ) 
0.97872 
Resolution (Å ) 
35.88-1.49 
33.28-1.56 
33.22-1.69 
43.23-1.64 
Outer shell (Å ) 
1.52-1.49 
1.59-1.56 
1.72-1.69 
1.67-1.64 
Unique reflections (outer shell) 
77 514 (3752) 
68 234 (3339) 
54 372 (2620) 
59 446 (2888) 
Completeness (outer shell) (%) 
96.9 (95.1) 
97.3 (96.6) 
98.3 (97.3) 
99.7 (99.3) 
R-merge (outer shell) 
0.071 (0.824) 
0.082 (0.800) 
0.061 (0.675) 
0.072 (0.674) 
I/s(I) (outer shell) 
27.3 (2.5) 
19.8 (2.1) 
29.8 (2.9) 
26.7 (3.0) </p>

<p>Refinement 
Working set reflections 
74 662 
68 154 
54 301 
59 370 
Test set reflections 
3759 
3453 
2766 
2996 
R-work/R-free 
0.196/0.223 
0.197/0.226 
0.202/0.237 
0.197/0.220 
No. of protein/DNA atoms 
2244/896 
2203/897 
2192/833 
2215/833 
No. H 2 O/Mg </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>/ligands 
476/2/4 
523/2/4 
375/2/4 
341/2/4 
Average B-factors 
30.18 
33.43 
27.80 
27.96 
RMSD bonds (Å ) 
0.009 
0.009 
0.008 
0.008 
RMSD angles ( 
) 
1.4 
1.3 
1.3 
1.4 </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 4 2691 </p>

<p>native DDD bound to RNaseH studied earlier (18), 
protein-DNA contacts in the complex were limited to 
the backbone of the C:G tracts (underlined) at both 
ends: CGCGAATTCGCG. Thus, we expected base 
pairing in the central GAATTC region where we 
replaced T opposite either A or G by ClU not to be 
affected by binding of RNase H (Figure 1). 
Crystals diffracted to resolutions between 1.5 and 1.7 Å 
and belong to space group P2 1 2 1 2 1 (Table 1). The struc-
tures were solved by the molecular replacement technique 
using the protein portion of the complex between RNase 
H and the native DDD (18) as the search model. All four 
crystals of the complexes with ClU-modified DDDs are 
isomorphous (Table 1). However, unlike in the structure 
of the complex between RNase H and the native DDD 
where the duplex sits on a dyad and the asymmetric unit 
contained two protein molecules and two DNA single 
strands, crystals of the complexes with ClU-modified 
DDDs feature two independent complexes consisting of 
RNase H bound to a duplex (Figure 1A and B). The 
first of these displays clear electron density around all nu-
cleotides, whereas in the second, the density around the </p>

<p>DNA is only partially resolved and either three or four 
base pairs at one end of the duplex are missing in the 
individual complex crystals (Figure 1B and C). Similarly, 
two (ClU7 crystal structure) and three N-terminal amino 
acids (ClU7/8 crystal structure) in the RNase H molecules 
from the second complex could not be resolved in the 
electron density maps. Examples of the quality of the 
final electron density are shown in Figure 2 and 
Supplementary Figures S1-S3. 
Inspection of the lattice interactions in the structures of 
the complexes reveals the origin of the diminished order of 
four base pairs in the second duplex. Three RNase H 
molecules interact with the duplex from the first 
complex, whereby two proteins cradle one end and a 
loop entailing residues T90, G91 and E92 of a third is 
stacked against the terminal base pair at the other end 
(Figure 1A). In contrast, the second duplex only exhibits 
interactions with RNase molecules at one end, with the 
other not being stabilized by protein contacts and jutting 
out into the solvent (Figure 1B). The comparison between 
the orientations of RNase H molecules around the two 
independent duplexes reveals similar positions of the </p>

<p>Figure 1. Overall structure of the BhRNase H:ClU8-DDD (ClU8) complex. The asymmetric unit contains two independent complexes, both con-
sisting of a single RNase H molecule bound to a modified DDD duplex. Protein chains in all four structures are labeled a (complex 1) and b 
(complex 2) and duplex strands are labeled c and d (complex 1) and e and f (complex 2), with nucleotides numbered 1-12 (c/e) and 13-20 (d/f). 
(A) The duplex in the first complex (colored green) is fully resolved in the electron density map and is contacted by three RNase H molecules 
(colored in white, gray or dark gray, whereby symmetry mates are marked with hash symbol). (B) The duplex in the second complex (colored in 
beige) is contacted by two RNase H molecules (colored in pink or magenta) and four C:G pairs at one end of the duplex are not visible in the 
electron density map. (C) The superimposition of the two independent complexes illustrates that the ClU8-DDDs exhibit similar conformations and 
virtually identical orientations of the original RNase H molecule relative to the DNA duplex. ClU residues are labeled and chlorine atoms are 
highlighted as light green spheres, selected water molecules are shown as cyan spheres, RNase H amino acids interacting with the DNA are labeled 
and the so-called phosphate (P-) binding site is marked by an arrow. </p>



<p>protein that binds a phosphate group at its P-binding 
site but a considerable shift between the second protein 
molecules contacting the same end of the two duplexes 
(Figure 1C). </p>

<p>Protein-DNA interactions in the ClU-DDD:RNase 
H complex structures </p>

<p>The two complexes per asymmetric unit in the four crystal 
structures exhibit similar interactions between RNase H 
and the ClU-modified DDD (Figure 1A, white RNase H a 
and green duplex; Figure 1B, pink RNase H b and beige 
duplex). In both cases, the phosphate group of C3 is 
lodged at the phosphate-binding pocket (Figure 3) that 
harbors a phosphate of a DNA nucleotide separated by 
2 bp from the scissile RNA phosphate in the structure of 
an RNA:DNA hybrid bound to BhRNase H (30). In the 
crystal structure of the complex between RNase H and 
the native DDD, the phosphate of the terminal G12 sits 
at the active site and thus mimics a phosphate from the 
RNA strand (18). The phosphate of residue G4 from the 
paired strand is anchored at the phosphate-binding 
pocket. Compared with these interaction modes between 
RNA:DNA hybrid and native DDD and RNase H, 
ClU-modified duplexes thus exhibit a less intimate inter-
action with the protein as only phosphates from one 
strand are contacted by amino acids (P3 by T104, S147 
and T148 and P4 by W139; Figure 3). As a consequence, 
only one Mg 
2+ ion (Mg B ) is observed at the protein active 
site, whereby the ion coordination sphere comprises D71, 
E109 and four water molecules (Figure 3). In addition to 
the protein-DNA contacts involving phosphate groups, 
four residues from a symmetry-related RNase H 
molecule interact with the terminal base pair of the first 
duplex. R126 and P177 stack onto the nucleobases of G24 
and C1, respectively, and I64 and L179 form hydrophobic 
interactions with the base and sugar moieties, respectively, 
of nucleotide C1 (Figures 1A and 3). In the case of the 
second complex where the symmetry-related RNase H 
molecule adopts a somewhat different orientation 
(Figure 1A, gray RNase H b# versus Figure 1B, 
magenta RNase H a#), amino acids establishing contacts 
with the terminal base pair include K143, N170 and T173 
(Figure 1B). However, neither duplex 1 nor duplex 2 in the 
four crystal structures exhibits interactions between </p>

<p>RNase H and A or ClU/T nucleotides from the central 
tetramer. </p>

<p>Geometry of ClU:A and ClU:G base pairs </p>

<p>A central question that we wanted to address with our 
structural studies is whether there are any changes in the 
pairing modes and/or geometries of ClU:A and ClU:G 
base pairs relative to the native T:A and T:G pairs, 
respectively. Analysis of the duplexes containing either 
two or four ClU:A pairs reveals that they are of the 
standard W-C type with formation of two hydrogen 
bonds. Comparison between the geometries of ClU:A 
and T:A pairs by superimposing the ClU7 and ClU8 
duplexes (Figure 4A) or the ClU7/8 and native DDD 
(31) duplexes (Figure 4C) demonstrates that replacing 
the methyl group of T by chlorine is of little consequence. 
Except for the methyl group carbon and chlorine, whose 
positions deviate somewhat as a result of the longer C-Cl 
bond relative to C-CH 3 , the ClU:A and T:A pairs neatly 
overlap. Similarly, like T:G the ClU:G pair adopts the 
familiar wobble geometry, with G and ClU being shifted 
into the minor and major grooves, respectively, under for-
mation of two hydrogen bonds (Figure 4B). As with the 
ClU:A and T:A pairs, the superimposition of the ClU9 
duplex and a DDD featuring T:G pairs (32) illustrates 
the nearly identical geometries of the two pairs. 
Moreover, calculated geometric parameters for these 
duplexes (27), including rise, twist, x-and y-displacement, 
etc. (see the Supplementary Material) confirm that 
chlorine attached at the 5-position of thymine in place 
of a methyl group does not trigger a substantial difference 
in either pairing behavior or base pair geometry. 
The similarities observed at the level of individual base 
pairs extend to the overall conformations of the 
dodecamer duplexes. As mentioned above, RNase H mol-
ecules in the crystal structures of the complexes with 
ClU-modified DDDs contact the duplexes exclusively in 
the CG portions, either at both ends (duplex 1, Figure 1A) 
or at only one end (duplex 2, Figure 1B). As a result, a 
hallmark of the DDD, the narrow A-tract minor groove 
remains largely unaffected by the interactions with the 
protein (Figure 5). Introduction of T:G mismatches at 
the border of the A-tract results in a wider minor groove 
in the ClU9 and G:T DDDs at the location of the 
mismatch pairs. However, replacement of T by ClU has 
no obvious effect on the change in groove width. The 
depth of the minor groove along the entire dodecamer 
exhibits much less variation compared with the width 
and neither G:T mismatch pairs nor ClU:A/G pairs 
cause any significant changes relative to the native DDD 
(Figure 5). </p>

<p>Thermodynamic stability of ClU-modified duplexes </p>

<p>To examine whether replacement of T by ClU affects 
duplex stability, we carried out UV melting studies with 
the native DDD, a DDD with T:G mismatches and all 
four ClU-modified DDDs (Table 2). The melting tempera-
tures for duplexes with two (ClU7, ClU8) or four ClU:A 
pairs (ClU7/8) vary only slightly and are similar to the 
T m of the native DDD. Insertion of T:G mismatches is </p>

<p>Figure 2. Quality of the final electron density. Fourier (2F o -F c ) sum 
electron density drawn at the 1.0 s threshold (A) around the central 
ApApTpClU tetramer in the ClU8 duplex, and (B) around base pair 
A5:ClU20 (top) and base pair ClU8:A17 (bottom). Atoms are colored 
beige, red, blue, orange and light green for carbon, oxygen, nitrogen, 
phosphorus and chlorine, respectively. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 4 2693 </p>

<p>accompanied by a steep drop in the stability that is similar 
for the duplex featuring two ClU:G pairs (ClU9). Overall, 
these data argue against an either stabilizing or 
destabilizing effect of the ClU nucleotide analog in 
B-form DNA. </p>

<p>EcoRI cleavage assays with ClU-modified DDDs </p>

<p>The EcoRI endonuclease recognizes the self-com-
plementary hexamer 5 
0 -GjAATTC-3 
0 :3 
0 -CTTAAjG-5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>and cleaves between G and A (j) under formation of </p>

<p>Figure 3. Interactions between RNase H and ClU modified DDDs. The original RNase H molecule (white ribbon) binds phosphates from one DNA 
strand; the phosphate of C3 (P3) is lodged at the phosphate-binding pocket and W139 forms a hydrogen bond to the phosphate of G4. The active 
site that normally harbors the scissile phosphate from the RNA strand (18) remains unoccupied and only one of the two Mg 
2+ ions (purple sphere) is 
present, with some water molecules (cyan spheres) taking the place of phosphate oxygens. Amino acid side chains from a symmetry-related RNase H 
molecule (I64, L179, P177 and R126) interact with the terminal C1:G24 base pair. Hydrogen bonds and Mg 
2+ coordination sphere are indicated with 
thin solid lines and two glycerol molecules trapped at the protein-DNA interface are highlighted with carbon atoms colored in black. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Comparison between the geometries of ClU:A and ClU:G and those of T:A and T:G base pairs, respectively. (A) Superimposition of the 
d(ClU7pT8pC9):d(G16pA17pA18) (light blue carbon atoms) and d(T7pClU8pC9):d(G16pA17pA18) (gray carbon atoms) trimer portions from the 
ClU7 and ClU8 structures, respectively. (B) Superimposition of the d(T8pClU9pG10):d(C15pG16pA17) (gray carbon atoms) and 
d(T7pT8pC9):d(G16pA17pA18) (light blue carbon atoms) trimer portions from ClU9 and a G:T mismatch-containing DDD structure [PDB ID 
113D (32)], respectively. (C) Superimposition of the central hexamers from the ClU7/8 structure (gray carbon atoms) and the native DDD [PDB ID 
436D (31)] (light blue carbon atoms). Chlorine atoms are highlighted in green, hydrogen bonds are indicated with thin solid lines (omitted in panel C 
for clarity), and fluorine atoms of two 2 
0 -deoxy-2 
0 -fluoroarabino-Ts in the reference structure are highlighted in purple (panel C). </p>



<p>sticky ends with 5 
0 -overhangs. We carried out cleavage 
assays with the restriction enzyme and ClU-modified 
DDDs, as well as the native DDD and a DDD with 
T:G mismatch pairs as reference duplexes (Figure 6). As 
expected, T:G and ClU:G mismatches abrogated cleavage. 
Conversely, the native DDD and all three modified 
duplexes with ClU:A pairs were cleaved by EcoRI 
without obvious effects of the ClU modification in terms 
of the time course of cleavage. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our investigation of the structure, stability and function 
of DNA duplexes with ClU in place of T was motivated by 
the recently demonstrated genome-wide transliteration of 
T with ClU in E. coli by combining tight metabolic selec-
tion and long-term automated cultivation of bacterial 
populations (13). Among nucleobases, only thymine is 
unique to DNA and the fact that its metabolism is 
separated from RNA biosynthesis provides an </p>

<p>opportunity to replace it in vivo by starvation and exogen-
ous introduction of unnatural alternatives (33). 
Incorporation of 5-halogenopyrimidines into DNA was 
established decades ago (34). Among the analogs with 
fluoro-, bromo-, chloro-or iodo-substituents, ClU 
exhibits the closest likeness to T (14), is readily converted 
to the nucleoside triphosphate in the cell (35) and lacks the 
photolabile behavior of BrU and IU (36). Starting from an 
E. coli strain lacking thymidylate synthase and furnishing 
exogenous ClU instead of T, 25 weeks of selection in a 
cultivation device yielded a strain with A, G, C and 90% 
ClU and 10% T in its genome (13). Through additional 
disruption of the tRNA U54 methyltransferase gene, the 
ClU content was further reduced to &lt;2%. This T!ClU 
transliteration was accompanied by more than 1500 A to 
G and G to A transitions in a particular culture, whereby 
the former was about twice as common. The frequency of 
these transitions suggests that ClU is prone to mispairing 
with G, although it is not clear whether ClU:G resembles 
the T:G pair in the wobble configuration with two 
hydrogen bonds or whether the mismatch pair exhibits a 
different hydrogen bonding pattern as a consequence of 
subtle changes in pK a , dipole moment and/or hydration of 
the chlorouracil base compared with thymine (15). 
We selected the DDD B-form DNA as a template to 
analyze the base pairing behavior of ClU opposite either A 
or G by X-ray crystallography. Because crystals of the 
DNAs alone did not diffract to high resolution, we 
decided to determine the structures of their complexes 
with BhRNase H. We previously found that crystals of 
complexes between the endonuclease and the native 
DDD or chemically modified DDDs diffract X-rays to 
resolutions of around 1.5 Å (18,29,37). Indeed, all 
crystals of complexes with ClU-modified DDDs diffracted 
to better than 1.7 Å resolution (Table 1). Two of the 
complexes feature duplexes with two T:A pairs replaced 
by ClU:A (ClU7 and ClU8) and a third contains a duplex 
with all four T:A pairs in the central A-tract of the DDD 
replaced by ClU:A (ClU7/8). A fourth complex is between 
BhRNase H and a DDD in which two ClU:G pairs </p>

<p>Figure 6. PAGE assay of EcoRI cleavage experiments with ClU-modiEed DDDs, the native DDD d(CGCGAATTCGCG) and the DDD 
d(CGCGAATTTGCG) with T:G mismatch pairs (underlined). </p>

<p>Figure 5. Minor groove widths (solid lines) and depths (dashed lines) 
in ClU-modified DDD duplexes in complex with RNase H compared 
with native DDD d(CGCGAATTCGCG) [PDB ID 436D; (31)] and a 
DDD d(CGCGAATTTGCG) with T:G mismatch pairs [underlined, 
PDB ID 113D; (32)]. All parameters were calculated with the 
program Curves (27). </p>

<p>Table 2. UV-melting temperatures of the native DDD, ClU-modified DDDs and a DDD with T:G mismatches </p>

<p>Duplex 
DDD 
ClU7 
ClU8 
ClU7/8 
ClU9 
T:G DDD </p>

<p>T m ( 
C) 
62.6 ± 0.9 
61.8 ± 1.2 
64.0 ± 0.5 
63.8 ± 0.6 
35.4 ± 0.7 
36.5 ± 0.5 
Hyperchromicity (%) 
15.5 
14.3 
15.7 
13.5 
15.6 
16.3 </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 4 2695 </p>

<p>bracket the central T:A tract. The first three structures 
illustrate that ClU:A and T:A pairs adopt nearly identical 
configurations with two hydrogen bonds (Figures 2, 4A 
and 4C), thus confirming the earlier observations based on 
the structure of a B-form DNA duplex with ClU:A pairs 
analyzed by solution NMR (14). Similarly, the geometry 
of ClU:G mismatch pairs in the structure of the fourth 
complex closely resembles that of the T:G pair in the 
structure of the B-form duplex of the same sequence (32) 
(Figure 4B). Crystals of the RNase H complexes were 
grown at near neutral pH (6.5) and the wobble configur-
ation with two hydrogen bonds confirms previous reports 
of the similarity of the ClU:G and T:G pairs as analyzed 
by NMR in solution (15). 
The similarities at the level of conformation indicate 
that chlorine appears to closely mimic the methyl substitu-
ent of thymine. Indeed, when both bond length and van 
der Waals radius are taken into account, the two substitu-
ents exhibit very similar sterics. The length of the C(5)-Cl 
bond is clearly longer than that of the C(5)-CH 3 bond 
(1.73 Å versus 1.5 Å , respectively), but the van der Waals 
radius of a methyl group (2 Å ) exceeds that of chlorine 
(1.75 Å ) by roughly the same amount. Thus, the two 
substituents will be nearly indistinguishable for a protein 
probing the major groove of a B-form duplex. Indeed, we 
demonstrate here that EcoRI cuts the ClU7-, ClU8-and 
ClU7/8 DDDs with two or more Ts in the recognition site 
replaced by ClU (Figure 6). Conversely, replacing the C:G 
pairs in the target sequence with either T:G or ClU:G 
mismatches abolishes cleavage by EcoRI. Chlorine not 
only mimics the native methyl substituent of thymine, 
thus allowing ClU:A pairs to evade recognition by 
enzymes, but replacement of T opposite A by ClU does 
not lead to any obvious changes in the thermodynamic 
stability of B-form DNA (Table 2). Also, T:G and 
ClU:G mismatch pairs result in very similar losses of sta-
bility. The stability data support the notion that chlorine 
and methyl at the 5-position of uracil are basically inter-
changeable. Although chlorine can, in principle, partici-
pate in halogen bonds (38), the observed distances 
between chlorine and phosphate oxygens in the 
ClU-modified DDD structures are all clearly above the 
sum of the van der Waals radii for Cl and O (3.27 Å ): 
minimum 5.09 Å , maximum 6.23 Å and average 5.49 Å . 
Chlorine atoms are also poorly hydrated and the 
shortest contact between a chlorine and water in our struc-
tures is 3.71 Å and thus not indicative of a hydrogen bond. 
Similar melting temperatures established for the native 
DDD and the ClU-modified DDDs are also inconsistent 
with differential polarizations of the thymine and 
chlorouracil nucleobases as this should affect stacking 
and thus stability. 
The similarity between ClU and T in terms of pairing 
properties, conformation and duplex stability helps 
rationalize the successful outcome of the in vivo evolution 
of E. coli strains that rely on a ClU, A, C, G alphabet 
instead of T, A, C, G (13). It is unlikely that a similar 
success could be achieved with the FU or BrU analogs 
that exhibit more significant steric and stereoelectronic de-
viations from T compared with ClU. Although we found 
in one instance (EcoRI) that an enzyme appeared to </p>

<p>ignore the switch from a methyl group to chlorine in the 
major groove, T ! ClU base substitution changes groove 
geometry and electrostatics in a subtle fashion and may 
affect nucleic acid recognition by proteins involved in 
replication and transcription. Indeed, in vitro kinetic 
assays of DNA polymerization using human polymerase 
b and E. coli DNA polymerase I exo 
-Klenow fragment 
with templates containing either ClU or T showed 
facilitated incorporation of dGTP opposite ClU 
compared with T, particularly at increased values of pH 
(i.e. 9.0) (39). A high mutation rate is important for the 
evolutionary process and the massive number of A ! G 
mutations seen in the adaptation of E. coli to ClU in place 
of T is consistent with facile formation of the ClU:G 
wobble pair. </p>

<p>ACCESSION NUMBERS </p>

<p>4HUF (ClU7), 4HTU (ClU8), 4HUG (ClU7/8), and 
4HUE (ClU9). </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online: 
Supplementary Tables 1-6 and Supplementary Figures 
1-4. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>P.H. is indebted to KU Leuven, FWO and ERC for finan-
cial support. We are grateful to Dr. Z. Wawrzak, 
Northwestern University, for assistance with X-ray dif-
fraction data collection. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Funding for open access charge: US National Institutes of 
Health [R01 GM55237 to M.E.]. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>







<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 4 2697 </p>

</text></tei>