<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3365791" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Summary </p>

<p>Objectives To explore the integration of online patient Record Access 
within UK Primary Care, its perceived impacts on workload and service 
quality, and barriers to implementation. </p>

<p>Design Mixed format survey of clinicians, administrators and patients. 
Telephone interviews with non-users. </p>

<p>Setting Primary care centres within NHS England that had offered 
online record access for the preceding year. </p>

<p>Participants Of the 57 practices initially agreeing to pilot the system, 
32 had adopted it and 16 of these returned questionnaires. The 42 
individual respondents included 14 practice managers, 15 clinicians and 
13 patients. Follow-up interviews were conducted with one participant 
from 15 of the 25 non-adopter practices. </p>

<p>Results Most professionals believed that the system is easy to 
integrate within primary care; while most patients found it easy to 
integrate within their daily lives. Professionals perceived no increase in the 
volume of patient queries or clinical consultations as a result of Record 
Access; indeed some believed that these had decreased. Most clinicians 
and patients believed that the service had improved mutual trust, 
communication, patients' health knowledge and health behaviour. 
Inhibiting factors included concerns about security, liability and resource 
requirements. Non-adoption was most frequently attributed to competing 
priorities, rather than negative beliefs about the service. </p>

<p>Conclusions Record access has an important role to play in 
supporting patient-focused healthcare policies in the UK and may be 
easily accommodated within existing services. Additional materials to 
facilitate patient recruitment, inform system set-up processes, and assure 
clinicians of their legal position are likely to encourage more widespread 
adoption. </p>

<p>DECLARATIONS </p>

<p>Competing interests </p>

<p>BF leads the UK </p>

<p>Record Access </p>

<p>Collaborative (RAC) </p>

<p>and is co-director of </p>

<p>PAERS Ltd which </p>

<p>wrote the software </p>

<p>that enables EMIS </p>

<p>practices to offer </p>

<p>online Record </p>

<p>Access. He did not </p>

<p>participate in the </p>

<p>survey, interviews, </p>

<p>or data analysis in </p>

<p>order to avoid </p>

<p>influencing the </p>

<p>results </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>TS received an </p>

<p>honorarium from the </p>

<p>RAC in order to </p>

<p>undertake the field </p>

<p>work. </p>

<p>Ethical approval </p>

<p>The study was </p>

<p>conducted under a </p>

<p>service development </p>

<p>remit and did not </p>

<p>involve identifiable </p>

<p>patient data </p>

<p>The past decade has seen an increasing appreci-
ation of the role of Information and Communi-
cations Technologies (ICT) in modernizing 
healthcare systems. Central to the 'eHealth' 
vision espoused by many governments is the 
promise of networked ICT (internet and mobile) 
to help engage citizens as partners in healthcare, 
chiefly through increasing the accessibility of rel-
evant information and services. 1 This reflects a 
growing emphasis, in many Western nations, on 
patient-centred healthcare models and comp-
lements wider citizen-centric policy initiatives 
around public engagement, freedom of infor-
mation and civic transparency. 
Electronic Health Records (EHR) represent the 
central pillar of eHealth strategies worldwide, 
since they offer the capacity to support patient 
care, quality improvement, population health 
surveillance and research. 2 Until recently the 
topics of EHR and 'Consumer Health Infor-
matics' tended to be considered separately; dis-
cussions of the former being mainly centred on 
healthcare institutions. Across North America 
and Europe there has been a gradual realization 
of the synergies between these two areas, mani-
fested in the growing attention that is being 
paid to Personal Health Records (PHR) in both 
the scientific and policy literatures. The PHR is 
a complex construct and many have bemoaned 
the lack of consensus on its precise definition. 3 
The central feature is a patient-accessible Elec-
tronic Health Record, although models vary in 
the source and controller of the information 
(healthcare provider or patient; single or multiple 
providers), the medium (e.g. web, kiosk, USB) 
and the additional functionalities associated with 
the software (e.g. education, prescription reorder-
ing, provider messaging, decision support). 4,5 
This report is concerned with one particular 
aspect of the PHR concept, namely online access 
by patients to provider-generated information 
that is specific to their health history and current 
conditions, and held in the computer systems of 
primary healthcare centres. We refer to this as 
Record Access, in line with the language adopted 
in recent guidelines from the Royal College of 
General Practitioners, 6 although similar appli-
cations have also been characterised as 'tethered 
Personal Health Records'. 7 </p>

<p>The idea of patients accessing their own health 
records is not a new one. 8 However, the accessibil-
ity afforded by the Internet, and the capacity of 
emerging PHR to integrate personal health appli-
cations with provider-owned record systems, 
creates interesting new challenges and research 
questions. 
The more complex and interactive models of 
PHR have yet to penetrate the UK market, in con-
trast to the US, where many healthcare manage-
ment organizations are providing such services, 
although 'patient portals' i are beginning to feature 
in NHS programmes 9 This may reflect differences 
in the organization of healthcare services. In the 
UK the established role of the GP as the manager 
and integrator of patient-specific health infor-
mation removes the imperative for patients them-
selves to undertake this role, as can be the case in 
more disaggregated, multi-provider, health 
economies. ii Reflecting this history, the origins of 
the PHR movement in the UK lie with a small 
number of enthusiastic GPs who pioneered record 
sharing with patients using computer printouts 
and portable downloads, latterly partnering with 
GP systems suppliers to provide waiting-room 
kiosks and online portals. 10 This has yielded 
favourable user responses and positive impacts 
on knowledge, mutual trust and record accuracy, 
despite some concerns over security and confiden-
tiality 11,12,13 This ground-up approach sits in stark 
contrast to the top-down one used to introduce 
patient access to the NHS Summary Care Record 
via '<rs type="software">HealthSpace</rs>', which has so far met with 
limited success. 14 
Despite the enthusiastic response of early adop-
ters, Record Access services remain uncommon in 
UK primary care and, given the caveats around 
privacy and liability indicated in the RCGP guide-
lines, more evidence is needed if they are to </p>

<p>i This term has been used to describe emerging systems that </p>

<p>offer Record Access as part of a broader suite of online 
consumer tools for administrative tasks such as 
appointment booking. 
ii The UK has a single National Health Service in which the </p>

<p>GP acts as the first point of care, the conduit to specialist 
services and the coordinator of community-based 
follow-up. As a result they generally receive core 
documentation pertaining to their patients from other parts 
of the service, although more detailed records will remain 
with the specialist host. </p>

<p>J R Soc Med Sh Rep 2012;3:34. DOI 10.1258/shorts.2012.012009 </p>

<p>Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine Short Reports </p>



<p>Contributorship </p>

<p>BF conceived the </p>

<p>study as part of the </p>

<p>RAC and facilitated </p>

<p>links to practices via </p>

<p>the GP software </p>

<p>supplier EMIS. CP </p>

<p>and TS </p>

<p>co-developed the </p>

<p>questionnaires. TS </p>

<p>undertook the </p>

<p>survey, follow-up </p>

<p>interviews and initial </p>

<p>analysis. CP wrote </p>

<p>the paper with input </p>

<p>from the other </p>

<p>authors </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>None </p>

<p>Reviewer </p>

<p>Ray Jones </p>

<p>become mainstream. Questions also remain about 
the feasibility of integrating Record Access into pro-
fessional workflow in light of the potential adminis-
trative requirements. This study aimed to examine 
how practices had integrated record access during 
the course of a one year pilot, and to identity 
human, organizational or technical barriers war-
ranting attention prior to wider rollout. It also 
sought to explore whether some of the benefits 
demonstrated in US studies of PHR, such as 
improved provider-patient relationships, patient 
self-care and reduced consulting time, 15 were also 
being felt in British health centres adopting 
record access. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Sample and setting </p>

<p>One year prior to our survey, the GP software sup-
plier EMIS had sought expressions of interest from 
practices wishing to pilot its new online Record 
Access system. This was publicized via the email 
network of the UK Record Access Collaborative 
and local EMIS user groups. iii Fifty-seven practices 
had volunteered to participate and these were tar-
geted by our survey. Record Access was available 
for a year prior to the survey, in order to allow the 
service to become embedded, although practices 
varied in their timescales for implementation. </p>

<p>Research tools </p>

<p>Questionnaires contained closed, open and scaled 
items, tailored to user group (manager, GP, 
patient), covering reasons for enrollment, 
implementation methods, perceived benefits or 
drawbacks for patient care or workload, system 
usability and support requirements. iv </p>

<p>Procedure </p>

<p>Questionnaires were disseminated to practice 
managers for self-completion (some items requir-
ing consultation with receptionists) and relay to </p>

<p>one GP and at least one patient representative 
per practice. Managers were asked to collect and 
return all questionnaires. Non-respondents were 
followed-up by email at 4 and 6 weeks, and then 
by telephone. Brief telephone interviews were 
conducted with representatives from centres 
whose original agreement to participate had not 
translated to use of the system. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Sample characteristics </p>

<p>Of the 57 centres originally enrolled in the pilot, 
only 32 (56.1%) had proceeded with implemen-
tation, of which 16 (50%) returned questionnaires. 
In total, 42 questionnaires were received from 14 
practice managers; 15 clinicians; and 13 patients. 
All patients completing the questionnaire were 
aged 41 years or over with 46.2% falling between 
the ages of 71 and 80 years. Of these, 79.9% 
reported having a long-term condition and 30% 
indicated that they were receiving specialist care. </p>

<p>Clinicians' responses </p>

<p>Impacts on workload </p>

<p>Overall 79.9% of clinicians felt that record access 
could be provided without creating a significant 
additional burden on the health centre. A total of 
86.7% perceived no adverse effect on consultation 
length and 13.3% stated that it had decreased this. 
Furthermore, 66.7% believed that it had not 
affected the frequency of consultations, and 13.3% 
that it had reduced it. </p>

<p>Impacts on patient communication 
and trust </p>

<p>Most clinicians (80%) believed that Record Access 
had been well received by patients; the remainder 
believing it had made no difference. Just over half 
(53.3%) thought it had facilitated shared decision 
making and trust during consultations and 20% 
felt more confident in communicating with patients 
as a result. The remainder reported no change, with 
several citing their practice's pre-existing culture of 
openness with patients as the reason. </p>

<p>Impacts on patient self-management </p>

<p>While most clinicians (66.7%) did not perceive that 
record access had changed the way patients </p>

<p>iii eHealth Insider. EMIS seeks 100 pilot practices for patient </p>

<p>record access. http://www.ehi.co.uk/news/primary-care/ 
2685 </p>

<p>iv </p>

<p>Questionnaires are reproduced in our detailed report for 
the Record Access Collaborative, available online via the 
University of Edinburgh Library. http://www.era.lib.ed.ac. 
uk/handle/1842/5831 </p>

<p>J R Soc Med Sh Rep 2012;3:34. DOI 10.1258/shorts.2012.012009 </p>

<p>Embedding patient record access in primary care </p>



<p>manage their health, 26.7% did (one did not com-
plete this item). Narrative responses revealed a 
belief, by some, that it had increased patients' 
involvement in the monitoring and management 
of their conditions; for example, through viewing 
results and seeking information before coming to 
see a clinician. </p>

<p>Challenges to service integration </p>

<p>When asked if record access had been easily inte-
grated into workflow, almost half the clinicians 
(46.6%) agreed, 20% disagreed and the remainder 
gave a neutral response. Reported challenges 
included the time and resources available to 
recruit patients and to check records for third-
party references, and concerns about the legality 
of providing patients with access to medical 
records in light of the UK Data Protection Act. 
While 80% had not changed the way in which 
they write patient records as a result of providing 
this service, 20% reported having done so, indicat-
ing that it had motivated them to use clearer 
language and avoid subjective comments. 
Despite the challenges, three quarters of clinicians 
(73.3%) said they would be willing to recommend 
record access to another health centre. </p>

<p>Health centre managers' responses </p>

<p>Precursors to Record Access </p>

<p>In total, 42.0% of managers had heard about record 
access prior to the study, usually via a clinical 
colleague. Most (64.3%) reported that participation 
was agreed during a health centre meeting. Eleven 
out of the fourteen centres (78.6%) already offered 
some type of online service including, appointment 
booking (all) and repeat prescriptions (nine). 
Most (85.7%) indicated that all clinicians in their 
centre supported the provision of record access. </p>

<p>Patient Enrolment Processes </p>

<p>Most centres had recruited patients using waiting 
room leaflets or posters (71.4%), or opportunisti-
cally during consultations (57.1%). Over half 
(64.2%) had found this easy or very easy, and 
21.4% had found it somewhat difficult (none had 
found it 'very difficult' and three failed to com-
plete this item). Perceived barriers included 
patients' concerns about security, lack of interest, 
poor understanding of potential benefits and </p>

<p>insufficient time for receiving instruction. Patients 
were typically enrolled by completing a consent/ 
registration form. Organizational challenges 
included the time required to complete the regis-
tration process and review patient notes. </p>

<p>Impacts on workload </p>

<p>Most managers (78.6%) stated that it was easy to 
manage record access within their centre, whilst 
14.5% reported that it was difficult to manage. 
One response was left blank. 
Around half reported no change in the frequency 
of requests to reception staff for clarification over 
drugs (57.1%), consultation booking (57.1%) or pre-
scription reordering (42.9%), while some reported a 
decrease (21.4%; 14.3% 14.3% respectively). A small 
number reported an increase in consultation 
requests (7.1%) and prescription reordering (21.4%). </p>

<p>Challenges to service integration </p>

<p>Managers mentioned similar challenges to clini-
cians regarding the availability of staff time for 
patient registration and record checking, and 
uncertainties over the Data Protection Act. They 
also highlighted difficulties in raising patients' 
awareness of the service, and operational chal-
lenges such as user error (forgotten passwords), 
and hardware problems. 
Recommendations included the provision of 
publicity materials for patients and further train-
ing and technical support for staff. </p>

<p>Patients' responses </p>

<p>Service integration </p>

<p>Most patients (92.3%) had found it easy or very 
easy to set up record access at home (one found 
it somewhat difficult) and all found the system 
easy or very easy to use. All were comfortable 
with the way in which their consent was 
requested, and most (92.3%) had no concerns 
about creating an online account. Narrative 
responses indicated that clear information about 
how security and confidentiality would be pro-
tected provided reassurance. One patient had con-
cerns about security, despite this. </p>

<p>Lifestyle integration </p>

<p>All but one patient had been using record access 
for 10 or more months. Most (84.6%) had viewed </p>

<p>J R Soc Med Sh Rep 2012;3:34. DOI 10.1258/shorts.2012.012009 </p>

<p>Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine Short Reports </p>



<p>their record 6 or more times since registering, and 
30.8% more than 10 times. Most (84.6%) had used 
the system once or more within the preceding fort-
night. Reported uses included accessing test 
results (84.6% of respondents) or clinician letters 
(53.8%), checking condition (53.8%), and support-
ing hospital consultations (53.8%); for example 
through reviewing records beforehand or sharing 
records during the clinical encounter. Most had 
shared their record with a spouse, partner or 
other family member (76.9%) </p>

<p>Impacts on knowledge and self-care </p>

<p>All patients found record access 'somewhat 
useful' (38.5%) or 'very useful' (61.5%). Most 
believed it had improved their knowledge of 
their condition (92.3%) or their understanding of 
its clinical management (76.9). Overall, 76.9% 
believed it had helped them to manage their 
health through encouraging them to take medi-
cation on time (23.1%), follow lifestyle advice 
(46.2%) or become aware of how their behavior 
is influencing their health (46.2%). </p>

<p>Impacts on satisfaction </p>

<p>A total of 46.2% of patients indicated that record 
access had improved their satisfaction with the 
health centre and 46.2% that it had made no differ-
ence. One reported a negative influence. </p>

<p>Impacts on communication and trust </p>

<p>38.5% of patients indicated that record access had 
improved their trust in the health centre and their 
confidence in sharing information or decisions 
with their doctor, while 61.5% indicated that it 
had not affected these factors. </p>

<p>Interviews with non-users </p>

<p>Representatives from 15 of the practices that had 
opted not to proceed with Record Access agreed 
to be interviewed. 
Explanations included a lack of priority (in most 
cases it was regarded positively but had simply 
not yet been implemented), lack of internal agree-
ment (e.g. only one GP advocate in the practice), 
perceived workload (e.g. time required to check 
records; patients seeking clarification); uncertainly 
about operating procedures or likely benefits (lack of 
information); lack of patient demand (e.g. service </p>

<p>offered but no take-up) and security concerns 
( privacy). None expressed concerns about litiga-
tion, citing confidence in the information held in 
their systems, although there was some uncer-
tainty about their position if record access were 
to reveal third-party information. While confiden-
tiality was a concern, inappropriate sharing by 
patients was felt to be potentially more proble-
matic than a technical breach. The potential for 
medical records to confuse or upset some patients 
was also acknowledged. Overall, these non-users 
supported the principle of record access and 
regarded it as 'an inevitability', but felt that more 
information and support should be available to 
help them prepare to deliver this service. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Statement of principal findings </p>

<p>The generally favourable attitudes revealed by all 
three stakeholder groups in this survey reflect a 
common finding in the research literature on 
record access and personal health records; 
namely that where these are available, such 
systems are well liked by patients and accepted 
by most professionals. 16 -19 The results also 
support previous studies that have identified pro-
fessional concerns around security, privacy and 
liability, for which technical, educational and 
regulatory steps may be warranted. 20 Only one 
patient in our sample expressed concern about 
having their detailed GP record available online 
( possibly as a result of the experience) and all 
felt comfortable with the way in which consent 
had been requested. Moreover the majority had 
shared their record with a partner or family 
member, indicating that patients and clinicians 
may have rather different views of the costs and 
benefits of data transparency, an observation also 
made in the recent evaluation of the Summary 
Care Record in England. 21 
Despite some concerns about operational 
resourcing, the relative ease with which record 
access appears to have been integrated into work 
practices and its lack of impact (or its positive 
impact) on administrative time and clinical work-
flow bode well for more widespread use. It is note-
worthy that practices which had yet to implement 
the service remained positive about it and 
intended to do so in the future. </p>

<p>J R Soc Med Sh Rep 2012;3:34. DOI 10.1258/shorts.2012.012009 </p>

<p>Embedding patient record access in primary care </p>



<p>Both patients and clinicians' believed that 
record access had facilitated shared decision 
making, health knowledge and self-management, 
suggesting greater patient empowerment. Our 
survey also gives early signals to the potential effi-
ciency gains that may come from record access 
once it has become more widely embedded. For 
example, some clinicians felt that it had reduced 
the frequency and length of consultations, and 
some patients reported having used it to help 
make more effective use of hospital appointments. </p>

<p>Strengths and weaknesses of the study </p>

<p>This is the largest UK survey of primary care 
centres offering online access to a detailed elec-
tronic health record. By including administrative 
staff, in addition to patients and clinicians, it has 
usefully highlighted operational considerations 
for general practices wishing to deliver these 
systems as well as possible outcomes for patient 
health, satisfaction, empowerment and practice 
efficiency. 
However, the number of respondents within 
each sub-group is too small to generate definitive 
conclusions about impact. The study also relies 
on users' perceptions and will have been influ-
enced both by experiences of using record access 
and expectations about its potential to deliver 
benefits, which are hard to disentangle. 
Recruitment to the pilot targeted clients of one 
system supplier, who coordinated the request 
in conjunction with the UK Record Access 
Collaborative v . Those agreeing to participate and 
then proceeding to implement the service and 
complete our survey may conceivably be more 
patient-centred, more technologically literate or 
have more patients with long term illnesses, than 
the others. Little is known about how the practices 
recruited patients to complete the questionnaire, 
and their decisions may have been influenced by 
knowledge of individuals' health characteristics 
or involvement in relevant groups. In this respect 
the high proportion of over 40s with long-term 
conditions is noteworthy. Nevertheless, such 
factors may, paradoxically, increase the ecological 
validity of this study, since these technologies are </p>

<p>most likely to be adopted by those for whom the 
potential benefits are greatest and who are most 
interested. 22 </p>

<p>Meaning of the study: possible 
mechanisms and implications for 
clinicians or policymakers </p>

<p>Mindful of these caveats, our results indicate that 
online record access offers great potential to 
address patient and citizen-centred agendas in 
the UK. 
Some of our findings are consistent with 
American research indicating that such portals can 
increase efficiencies by changing the way in which 
patients seek professional interaction, such as 
via telephone rather than in-person consultations. 15 
While not all patients are likely to use this type 
of Personal Health Record, it may be a useful 
resource for some and should be provided as an 
option alongside other online services. The UK 
primary care sector is in an excellent position to 
integrate these services at relatively low cost, 
given the universal use of electronic health 
record systems, state-mandated interoperability 
requirements and competition between suppliers 
for the lucrative general practice systems market, 
in which patient-facing services are likely to offer 
an advantage. </p>

<p>Unanswered questions and future 
research </p>

<p>Quantitative studies of use and impacts are 
required to verify these observations, although 
the positive responses revealed in this study 
suggest that it may be appropriate to conduct 
such research in tandem with implementation, 
so as to avoid delaying a useful service. Vigilance 
will nevertheless be required in order to monitor 
unintended consequences, particularly given the 
sensitivity of personal health data. Research to 
explore patient characteristics associated with the 
use of record access would be useful, 23 as would 
studies examining the mediating influence of clin-
ician characteristics. 24 Poor public awareness of 
Personal Health Record technologies has been 
cited as a barrier to their adoption 25 and is 
among the inhibiting factors noted in this study. 
Given the apparently low impact of the NHS </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>An informal community of interest including representatives 
from general practice, patient groups, academia, policy and 
industry. http://www.record-accesscollaborative.org/ </p>

<p>J R Soc Med Sh Rep 2012;3:34. DOI 10.1258/shorts.2012.012009 </p>

<p>Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine Short Reports </p>



<p>information campaign around HealthSpace, 
research exploring how best to bring these 
systems to the attention of potential users may 
be warranted. 
The effort involved in masking third party 
references remains a practical challenge to 
scaling this service and evaluating alternative 
methods for achieving this would be worthwhile. </p>



<p># 2012 Royal Society of Medicine Press 
This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/), which permits non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in 
any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>J R Soc Med Sh Rep 2012;3:34. DOI 10.1258/shorts.2012.012009 </p>

<p>Embedding patient record access in primary care </p>

<p>7 </p>

</text></tei>