<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3944114" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>was developed to characterize the effect of covariates including body mass index (BMI) and lung function (forced 
expiratory volume in 1 s as percent of the predicted value (FEV 1 % predicted) at baseline) on the serum exposure parameters. 
A two-compartment model with first-order elimination and first-order absorption was developed. Across a range of baseline 
demographic values in the study population, the predicted mean values for the maximum (C max ) and trough (C trough ) plasma 
concentrations at steady state were at least 7.5 and 5-fold lower, respectively, than the recommended thresholds for tobramycin 
toxicity (12 µg/ml for C max and 2 µg/ml for C trough ). This model adequately described the tobramycin serum concentration-time 
course in CF patients following inhalation of TIP. The results indicate that no BMI-or FEV 1 -based dose adjustment is needed for 
use of TIP in CF patients. 
CPT: Pharmacometrics &amp; Systems Pharmacology </p>

<p>Inhaled Tobramycin Powder in CF Patients 
Ting et al. </p>



<p>and first-order absorption. Interindividual variability (IIV) was 
estimated on apparent clearance (CL/F), apparent central vol-
ume of distribution (V d /F), and absorption rate constant (k a ). 
Interoccasion variability was estimated on CL/F. The residual 
error was modeled to be a combination of proportional and 
additive errors. The proportional residual variability of study 
C2301 and study C2302 was more than threefold higher than 
that in study TPI001, reflecting the many doses and sampling 
times that were not recorded in the two phase III studies and 
had to be imputed. The parameter estimates are listed in 
Table 2. The final covariates identified on the model were BMI 
and FEV 1 % predicted on V d /F. The relationship between V d /F 
with FEV 1 % predicted and BMI was defined as follows: </p>

<p>V F </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>/ 
85.1 ( 
FEV 
( 
BMI 
= 
⋅ 
⋅ </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>% 
. 
) 
. 
) </p>

<p>. 
. </p>

<p>62 1 
1 8 8 </p>

<p>0 303 
0 624 </p>

<p>None of the other investigated variables were found to be 
statistically significant covariates in the model. </p>

<p>Visual predictive checks and goodness-of-fit plots 
For single doses, the central trend predicted by the model 
matched the central trend of observed data in visual predic-
tive check plots (Figure 1). The variability observed in the 
data was adequately captured by the model. In general, 
observed data at multiple doses were also matched well by 
the model at the 5th to 95th percentiles (Figure 1b), although 
the median value of the maximum plasma concentration at 
steady state (C max ) was slightly underpredicted. For multiple 
doses, for the time interval 13-60 h, the 97.5th percentile was 
underpredicted, which may be explained by the small amount 
of data (six concentration observations), including one at a 
significantly higher concentration than the others. Similarly, 
at the time interval 6-13 h, the observed data at the 97.5th </p>

<p>Table 1 Demographic description of the TIP population </p>

<p>Individual study </p>

<p>Combined 
TPI001 
C2301 
C2302 </p>

<p>N 
64 
62 
13 
139 </p>

<p>Age, years: median (SD) [range] 
21 (11.1) [7-50] 
14 (4.0) [6-21] 
31 (13.0) [18-58] 
17 (10.8) [6-58] </p>

<p>Age group, n (%) </p>

<p>6-11 years 
9 (14.1) 
20 (32.3) 
0 (0) 
29 (20.9) </p>

<p>12-17 years 
16 (25) 
28 (45.2) 
0 (0) 
44 (31.7) </p>

<p>≥18 years 
39 (60.9) 
14 (22.6) 
13 (100) 
66 (47.5) </p>

<p>Body weight, kg: median (SD) [range] 
57.1 (16.4) [18.9-100.9] 37.5 (13.9) [16.2-68.9] 58.8 (11.9) [49.5-91.8] 
49.5 (17.7) [16.2-100.9] </p>

<p>BMI, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>: median (SD) [range] 
20.4 (3.6) [13.4-31] 
16.2 (3.4) [11.4-25.7] 22.1 (3.5) [16.3-30.7] 
18.8 (4.1) [11.4-31] </p>

<p>Creatinine clearance, ml/min: median (SD) [range] 114.9 (32.5) [63.9-222.5] 108.7 (26.9) [69-175.1] 104.8 (22.0) [76.1-150.7] 112.5 (29.5) [63.9-222.5] </p>

<p>FEV 1 % predicted at baseline: median (SD) [range] 70.0 (20.4) [40.7-119.7] 58.5 (18.2) [24.1-96.2] 50.4 (14.2) [29.7-73.4] 
62.1 (20.6) [24.1-119.7] </p>

<p>Sex, n (%) </p>

<p>Female 
35 (54.7) 
33 (53.2) 
6 (46.2) 
74 (53.2) </p>

<p>Male 
29 (45.3) 
29 (46.8) 
7 (53.8) 
65 (46.8) </p>

<p>Race, n (%) </p>

<p>Black 
2 (3.1) 
1 (1.6) 
0 (0) 
3 (2.2) </p>

<p>Caucasian 
55 (85.9) 
52 (83.9) 
13 (100) 
120 (86.3) </p>

<p>Hispanic 
4 (6.2) 
8 (12.9) 
0 (0) 
12 (8.6) </p>

<p>Other 
3 (4.7) 
1 (1.6) 
0 (0) 
4 (2.9) </p>

<p>FEV 1 % predicted, forced expiratory volume in 1 s as percent of the predicted value; TIP, tobramycin inhalation powder. </p>

<p>Table 2 Summary of the final model parameter estimates </p>

<p>Parameter 
Estimate (% RSE) </p>

<p>95% 
Confidence 
interval </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>CL/F (l/h) 
14.5 (5.0) 
13.1 to 15.9 </p>

<p>V d /F (l) 
85.1 (3.6) 
79.1 to 91.1 </p>

<p>k a (h </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>) 
2.39 (4.8) 
2.17 to 2.61 </p>

<p>Q/F (l/h) 
6.43 (12.9) 
4.81 to 8.05 </p>

<p>V 2 /F (l) 
210 (29.9) 
87.0 to 333 </p>

<p>Covariates </p>

<p>FEV 1 % on V d /F 
-0.303 (36.0) 
-0.517 to -0.089 </p>

<p>BMI on V d /F 
0.624 (24.6) 
0.323 to 0.925 </p>

<p>IIV </p>

<p>IIV of CL/F (variance) 
0.164 (28.2) 
0.073 to 0.255 </p>

<p>IIV of V d /F (variance) 
0.152 (12.3) 
0.115 to 0.189 </p>

<p>IIV of k a (variance) 
0.129 (23.7) 
0.069 to 0.189 </p>

<p>COV of CL/F and V d /F 
(variance) </p>

<p>0.123 (20.0) 
0.075 to 0.171 </p>

<p>IOV of CL/F (variance) </p>

<p>Occasion 1 
0.078 (48.0) 
0.005-0.151 </p>

<p>Occasion 2 
Same as above 
Same as above </p>

<p>Occasion 3 
Same as above 
Same as above </p>

<p>Occasion 4 
Same as above 
Same as above </p>

<p>Residual SD, proportional component </p>

<p>TPI001 
0.073 (10.0) 
0.059 to 0.087 </p>

<p>C2301 and C2302 
0.308 (8.7) 
0.256 to 0.36 </p>

<p>Residual SD, additive component 
0.007 (25.8) 
0.004 to 0.011 </p>

<p>BMI, body mass index; CL/F, apparent clearance; COV, covariance 
between parameters; FEV 1 , forced expiratory volume in 1 s; IIV, 
interindividual variability of parameter as variance; IOV, interoccasion 
variability; k a , absorption rate constant; <rs type="software">NONMEM</rs>, non-linear mixed 
effects modeling; Q/F, apparent intercompartmental clearance; RSE, 
root-mean-square error as percent of the parameter estimate; V d /F, 
apparent central volume of distribution; V 2 , apparent peripheral volume 
of distribution. 
a Derived from NONMEM-provided standard errors. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/psp </p>

<p>Inhaled Tobramycin Powder in CF Patients 
Ting et al. </p>



<p>percentile was also not well matched by the model because 
of observations of high concentrations (in the range of 1-3 
µg/ml) compared with the majority (less than 1 µg/ml). Good-
ness-of-fit plots (see Supplementary Figures S1 and S2) 
also indicate that the model described the data reasonably 
well. Plots of population and individual predictions against 
observations showed good agreement between population 
predictions and data, as indicated by the overlay of unity 
line and locally weighted scatter plot smoothing (LOESS) 
line, with a slight underestimation at high concentrations. 
The residual error model was also found to be appropriate </p>

<p>(comparing individual predictions against individual weighted 
residuals) and there was no bias in the model predictions 
against time. </p>

<p>Covariate effect on exposure 
The model-predicted mean C max and C trough values at steady 
state for a typical CF patient either with 62.1% FEV 1 % pre-
dicted at baseline (the population median) and different val-
ues of BMI or with 18.8 kg/m 
2 BMI (the population median) 
and different values of FEV 1 % predicted at baseline are 
shown in Figure 2 and Supplementary Tables S1 and S2. 
Simulations showed that when BMI decreases from the 
95th percentile (25.1 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) to the 5th percentile (13.3 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
of the study population distribution, C max increases 21% from 
1.3 to 1.57 µg/ml, whereas C trough decreases 16% from 0.38 
to 0.32 µg/ml. When FEV 1 % predicted at baseline increases 
from the 5th percentile (29.7% predicted) to the 95th percen-
tile (102.5% predicted) of the study population distribution, 
C max increases 21% from 1.22 to 1.48 µg/ml, whereas C trough 
decreases 18% from 0.39 to 0.32 µg/ml. Across the range 
of values of BMI or FEV 1 % predicted at baseline evaluated, 
the predicted mean C trough values were at least fivefold lower 
than the recommended maximum C trough (2 µg/ml) for avoid-
ance of tobramycin-associated toxicity (Figure 2). 
6 These </p>

<p>Figure 1 Visual predictive check of the model for tobramycin 
concentrations. (a) Visual predictive check of the model for 
tobramycin concentrations at first visit of each cycle. The shaded area 
indicates 2.5th and 97.5th percentiles for bins over time of simulated 
concentrations. Open circles show observed concentrations. 
Solid and dashed lines indicate medians and the 2.5th and 
97.5th percentiles over simulated and observed concentrations, 
respectively. (b) Visual predictive check of the model for tobramycin 
concentrations at second visit of each cycle. Open circles show 
observed concentrations. Dashed lines indicate medians and the 
2.5th and 97.5th percentiles over observed concentrations. The 
solid lines indicate medians and the 2.5th and 97.5th percentiles 
over simulated concentrations, and the shaded rectangles illustrate 
binned time intervals over which the percentiles were evaluated. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
6 </p>

<p>Time since last dose (h) </p>

<p>8 
1 0 
1 2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 
Concentration (µg/ml) </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
6 </p>

<p>Time since last dose (h) </p>

<p>8 
1 0 
1 2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 
Concentration (µg/ml) </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Figure 2 Effect of the covariates body mass index (BMI) and forced 
expiratory volume in 1 s as percent of the predicted value (FEV 1 % 
pred) at baseline on tobramycin serum C max and C trough with 95% 
predictive interval (PI)*, assuming a typical cystic fibrosis patient 
with FEV 1 % predicted of 62.1% and BMI of 18.8 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. Gray area 
represents 95% PI, and solid line represents mean tobramycin 
concentration. *Obtained by simulation with interindividual 
variability in pharmacokinetics; PI values are presented for each 
covariate value, not for the slope of best fit. C max , maximum plasma 
concentration at steady state; C trough , trough plasma concentration 
at steady state. </p>

<p>14 16 18 20 </p>

<p>Covariate value </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 
Concentration (µg/ml) </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 
Concentration (µg/ml) </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>40 50 60 70 80 90 100 </p>

<p>Covariate value </p>

<p>The effect of BMI on C max with 
FEV 1 % pred set at 62.1% 
The effect of FEV 1 % pred on 
C max with BMI set at 18.8 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>The effect of BMI on C trough with 
FEV 1 % pred set at 62.1% 
The effect of FEV 1 % pred on 
C trough with BMI set at 18.8 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>22 24 </p>

<p>14 16 18 20 </p>

<p>Covariate value </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 
Concentration (µg/ml) </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 
Concentration (µg/ml) 
0.8 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>40 50 60 70 80 90 100 </p>

<p>Covariate value </p>

<p>22 24 </p>

<p>CPT: Pharmacometrics &amp; Systems Pharmacology </p>

<p>Inhaled Tobramycin Powder in CF Patients 
Ting et al. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>results illustrate that the effect of BMI and FEV 1 % predicted 
on the concentration of tobramycin after administration of TIP 
112 mg b.i.d are not expected to be clinically relevant. 
The highest value of the upper end point of the 95% pre-
dictive interval for C max is 3.08 µg/ml and for C trough is 1.33 µg/ 
ml. The C max and C trough levels are 7.5-and 5-fold lower than 
the maximum recommended concentrations of serum tobra-
mycin (12 µg/ml for C max and 2 µg/ml for C trough ), with 97.5% 
of patients predicted to have C max and C trough values 4-and 
1.5-fold lower than the maximum recommended levels. 
6 This 
inference is applicable to patient populations with baseline 
values of BMI and FEV 1 % predicted similar to the values in 
the study populations. </p>

<p>Influence of excluded data 
The final structural model developed was rerun after reintro-
ducing concentrations that were excluded due to lack of FEV 1 
measurements as described previously, and the difference in 
the parameter values was examined. There was little change 
in all the parameter estimates after inclusion of these concen-
trations, suggesting no influential observations or subjects in 
these data records. The final model was also rerun with the 
outliers included, and the difference in the parameter values 
was not deemed significant (data not shown). There was no 
pronounced change in the fixed-effects parameter estimates 
except for the estimate of the apparent peripheral volume of 
distribution (V 2 /F), which increased from 162 to 313 l, result-
ing in a longer terminal half-life. This increase is probably 
due to the fact that some of the outliers were measured at 
more than 20 h after the previous dose but still had detectable 
concentration levels. However, this change is not considered 
clinically relevant as the second phase dose not contribute 
significantly to the overall kinetics or accumulation. </p>

<p>DISCUSSIOn </p>

<p>Population pharmacokinetic modeling is an established 
method for identifying the sources of variability in drug expo-
sure in a target population receiving clinically relevant doses 
of a drug. 
18 Some patient or disease characteristics, e.g., 
weight, renal function, and FEV 1 , may alter dose-concentra-
tion relationships. Modeling approaches have been used to 
characterize the pharmacokinetics of inhalation solutions for 
use in nebulizers or aerosols (e.g., (R)-albuterol and (S)-alb-
uterol inhalation solutions in pediatric patients with asthma, </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>levofloxacin inhalation solution for patients with CF). </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Systemic C max and C trough of tobramycin above 12 and 2 µg/ 
ml, respectively, are associated with higher risk of nephro-
toxicity and ototoxicity in CF patients and should be carefully 
monitored. 
6 A population pharmacokinetic model was there-
fore developed to describe the tobramycin serum concentra-
tion-time course in CF patients following inhalation of TIP, 
which demonstrates that systemic levels of tobramycin via 
TIP inhalation are well below the known toxicity levels asso-
ciated with nephrotoxicity and ototoxicity. Although the sys-
temic C max of 12 µg/ml is a general guidance for intravenous 
tobramycin, the recommended C max for CF patients are similar 
(8-12 µg/ml) for t.i.d. tobramycin regimen; no specific recom-
mended C max value is available for q.d. regimen. 
21 Therefore, </p>

<p>for conservative estimation of toxicity risk, a 12-µg/ml thresh-
old was used for C max in this study. 
In the present study, BMI and FEV 1 % predicted were found 
to be statistically significant covariates for V d /F. Previously, 
patients with CF and low BMI measurements have been 
found to be six times more likely to have severely impaired 
FEV 1 values (&lt;40% predicted) than those with a "normal" 
BMI. 
22 In addition, low FEV 1 % predicted associated with 
worsening lung disease in CF has been shown to increase 
total lung deposition of aerosols, mainly to the central airways 
and areas of obstruction. 
17 This would likely account for the 
increased V d /F observed with decreasing FEV 1 % predicted in 
this population. Despite this effect on V d /F, however, model-
based simulation showed that neither C max nor C trough were 
substantially affected by change in BMI or FEV 1 % predicted 
at baseline. Across the range of baseline BMI or FEV 1 % pre-
dicted values assessed, the predicted mean C max and C trough 
values were low relative to the maximum systemic concentra-
tions recommended for avoidance of tobramycin-associated 
toxicity. 
6 C max and C trough values were at least 7.5-and 5-fold 
lower, respectively, than the maximum recommended C max 
(12 µg/ml) and C trough (2 µg/ml). 
6 Hence, the effect of BMI and 
FEV 1 % predicted at baseline on the concentration of tobramy-
cin after administration of TIP 112 mg b.i.d. are not expected 
to be clinically relevant with regard to systemic toxicity. 
After adjustment for the effect of BMI, there was no influence 
of age on the pharmacokinetics of tobramycin. These find-
ings are consistent with the results of previous studies 
23,24 or 
of other inhaled therapies and consistent with the concept that 
lung dose increases with age but is proportional to body size. 
Thus, TIP can be dosed at fixed doses (with no dose adjust-
ment necessary) in adults and children above 6 years of age, 
with an acceptable safety margin due to low systemic exposure. 
Although tobramycin is known to be eliminated via the renal 
route and its clearance is dependent on renal function, the cur-
rent population pharmacokinetic model indicated that creatinine 
clearance did not affect the pharmacokinetics of tobramycin 
after TIP administration. This is likely due to the fact that only 
patients with normal renal function or mild renal impairment 
were included in the study population (minimum creatinine 
clearance was 63.9 ml/min in the pharmacokinetic population). 
Similar to TIS, monitoring of serum tobramycin concentration is 
recommended if TIP is used in patients with renal dysfunction. 
We recognize that different ways of handling concentra-
tions that are below the lower limit of quantification (LLOQ) 
may influence the final model. 
25,26 Common ways of handling 
data below the limit of quantification (BLOQ) include excluding 
them from the model, replacing them with a value of LLOQ/2, 
replacing them with a value of zero, and estimating likelihood 
of BLOQ and all other observations by maximum likelihood 
estimation method, to name a few. 
25 Although we acknowl-
edge that a potential issue in excluding the BLOQ obser-
vations may create bias in the model fit because the lower 
remaining observations are selectively too high, 
25 the extent 
of such bias is variable and would depend on the structural 
model and relative proportion of BLOQ data. 
27 For example, 
Xu et al. 
27 demonstrated that ignoring ≤10% of BLOQ data 
has minimal impact on the model parameter estimates for 
one-compartment models, whereas more pronounced impact 
on the estimation of peripheral compartment parameters (V p , </p>

<p>www.nature.com/psp </p>

<p>Inhaled Tobramycin Powder in CF Patients 
Ting et al. </p>



<p>Q, and their associated IIV) becomes apparent when the 
percentage of BLOQ data is &gt;5%, but with limited impact on 
precision of estimates on the central parameters such as CL, 
V d , and k a . Considering that the assay for tobramycin concen-
trations is sensitive, with a LLOQ of 0.05 µg/ml, the BLOQ 
values were low in incidence (6.8%) and observed at times 
well into the terminal clearance phase, and because the ter-
minal phase contributes minimally to the relevant exposure 
metrics, excluding the BLOQ concentrations from the model 
is not expected to affect the final model significantly. 
Population pharmacokinetic modeling plays an impor-
tant role in drug development, enabling the investigation of 
factors that may explain some of the variability of the data 
and leading to a better prediction of clinical response in 
individual patients, 
18,28 even when sampling is minimal. Two 
previous population pharmacokinetic modeling studies of 
inhaled products have looked at the variability of pharma-
cokinetic parameters caused by demographic variables. </p>

<p>20,29 </p>

<p>The population pharmacokinetic model of an inhalation solu-
tion of levofloxacin for use via a nebulizer in patients with CF 
showed overlap in pharmacokinetic exposure with each dose 
of levofloxacin, representing interpatient variability, 
20 whereas 
modeling of an inhaled powder form of zanamivir for patients 
with influenza showed that demographic variables or levels 
of infection did not affect the variability of pharmacokinetic 
parameters. 
29 Here we have developed a population phar-
macokinetic model to describe the serum concentration-time 
course of tobramycin in CF patients following inhalation of 
TIP. Our results demonstrate a statistically significant effect of 
BMI and FEV 1 % predicted on V d /F but no clinically significant 
impact on tobramycin C max or C trough in CF patients. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Included studies 
Serum concentration data for TIP from three clinical stud-
ies (one phase I (TPI001) and two phase III studies (C2301 
and C2302)) were pooled to generate a pharmacokinetic 
analysis data set for modeling (Table 3). 
9,15,16 After exclusion </p>

<p>of missing data, 662 concentration-time observations from 
139 CF patients dosed with 28, 56, 84, or 112 mg single 
dose, as well as 112 mg b.i.d. multiple doses, were included. </p>

<p>Missing and outlying data 
Missing sampling time was imputed from the corresponding 
dose-time course if the study protocol specified the sampling 
time schedule. Missing values for FEV 1 % predicted were 
replaced with the most recent previous value. In total, 28/1,031 
tobramycin concentration observations were omitted from 
analysis due to missing sampling time or dose information. 
In study C2301, 72 tobramycin concentrations from 21 
subjects did not have FEV 1 % assessment information. All 72 
concentration records were excluded from the analysis. After 
the above exclusions, there were a total of 931 concentration 
records left in the analysis data set, with 6.8% of them (63 
concentrations) below LLOQ. After exclusion of concentrations 
below LLOQ and outlying concentrations identified from the 
original report, there were 859 concentrations in the analysis 
data set before exclusion of samples beyond validated stabil-
ity storage period in study C2302. After exclusion of affected 
C2302 samples, there were 662 concentration values from 139 
subjects in the population pharmacokinetic analysis data set. 
Outlying data were identified by visual inspection and 
excluded from the analysis. Four subjects from study TPI001 
were excluded, either because they did not receive the dose 
or because they received less than a full dose of tobramycin. 
Three outliers in study C2301 and six outliers in study C2302 
(incorrect sample dates/times or discrepancy between 
elapsed time and visit) were excluded. </p>

<p>Data analysis and modeling methods 
The model was developed using the nonlinear mixed-effects 
modeling (<rs id="software-0" type="software">NONMEM</rs>) software program NONMEM VI <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 2</rs> (Reagents of the University of California, San Francisco, CA) 
Standard and the first-order conditional estimation method 
with interaction (NONMEM coding provided in Supplementary 
Appendix). The change in the NONMEM objective function </p>

<p>Table 3 Summary of included studies </p>

<p>Study 
number 
Design 
TIP doses 
PK sampling times 
Dose regimen </p>

<p>number of enrolled 
patients with PK observation </p>

<p>TPI001, ref. 8 Randomized, open-label, 
active-controlled, se-
quential cohort </p>

<p>28 mg (2 × 14 mg) 
Predose; 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 8, and 12 h 
postdose </p>

<p>Single dose 
TIP: 64 CF patients </p>

<p>56 mg (4 × 14 mg) 
Control (TIS): 20 CF patients </p>

<p>56 mg (2 × 28 mg) </p>

<p>84 mg (3 × 28 mg) </p>

<p>112 mg (4 × 28 mg) </p>

<p>C2301, ref. 15 Multicenter, randomized, 
placebo-controlled, three-
cycle, two-arm study </p>

<p>112 mg (4 × 28 mg) 
Sparse sampling; predose; and 1 h 
postdose at weeks 1, 5, 17, and 21 </p>

<p>Multiple doses, 
b.i.d. for 28 
days (per cycle) </p>

<p>Cycle 1: </p>

<p>TIP: 41 CF patients </p>

<p>Control (placebo): 42 CF 
patients </p>

<p>Cycles 2 and 3: All patients 
received TIP. There were 76 
patients with TIP PK obser-
vations in cycle 2 </p>

<p>C2302, ref. 14 Multicenter, randomized, 
open-label, three-cycle, 
two-arm, active-con-
trolled study </p>

<p>112 mg (4 × 28 mg) 
Four serum samples: predose, one 
sample between 0 and 2 h, and 
two samples between 2 and 5 h 
postdose at weeks 1, 5, 17, and 21 </p>

<p>Multiple doses, 
b.i.d. for 28 
days (per cycle) </p>

<p>TIP: 13 CF patients with PK 
observations </p>

<p>Control (TIS): 6 CF patients 
with PK observations </p>

<p>Week 1 corresponds to day 1 (first dose taken at site) of cycle 1, week 5-day 28 of cycle 1, week 17-day 1 of cycle 3, week 21-day 28 of cycle 3. 
CF, cystic fibrosis; PK, pharmacokinetics; TIP, tobramycin inhalation powder; TIS, tobramycin inhalation solution. </p>

<p>CPT: Pharmacometrics &amp; Systems Pharmacology </p>

<p>Inhaled Tobramycin Powder in CF Patients 
Ting et al. </p>



<p>value and goodness-of-fit plots were used to guide the model 
development. One-and two-compartment disposition mod-
els with first-order absorption and first-order elimination were 
evaluated based on the previous knowledge of the pharmaco-
kinetic properties of the compound from a single-dose study. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>IIV was assessed on all structural model parameters, as was 
interoccasion variability (the occasion variable was derived 
based on the visit number: it was assumed that concentra-
tions measured at different study visits represented distinct 
occasions). The pharmacokinetic parameters (k a , volumes, 
and clearances) were assumed to be log-normally distrib-
uted around the population mean, but the random effects to 
describe both IIV and interoccasion variability were assumed 
to be distributed with a mean of zero. The effects of covari-
ates (age, BMI, creatinine clearance, sex, FEV 1 % predicted 
at baseline, and weight) on the pharmacokinetic model were 
investigated once an adequate structural and stochastic model 
had been finalized. Age was categorized into three groups: 
6-11, 12-17, and ≥18 years. Each covariate was tested indi-
vidually against the key structural model parameters k a , V d /F, 
and CL/F in a stepwise fashion (forward inclusion). After each 
step, the strongest covariate relationship was incorporated 
into the model, and the others sequentially and individually 
retested, until no further covariates could be added with statis-
tical significance. The inclusion of a covariate term was consid-
ered statistically significant if it produced a difference of 3.84 
(P = 0.05, given a single degree of freedom) in the <rs type="software">NONMEM</rs> 
objective function value during the forward inclusion and if it 
produced an objective function value difference of 6.64 (P = 
0.01, given a single degree of freedom) during the backward 
elimination. A combination of proportional and additive error 
models was used. The visual predictive check was used to 
provide an assessment of the model's ability to describe the 
data and the model's suitability for simulation. For the covari-
ates identified after the stepwise process, 1,000 simulations 
were performed to evaluate their effect on the drug exposure 
at steady state using the following metrics: C max and C trough . The 
sensitivity of each metric to a given covariate was evaluated 
by simulation using different percentile values of the covariate 
distribution in the pharmacokinetic population, while keeping 
values of the other identified covariates in the model fixed at 
their median values in the pharmacokinetic population. These 
simulations were undertaken using the population parameter 
estimates from the final model and the IIV values of pharmaco-
kinetic parameters, and they yielded the metrics of interest and 
their 95% predictive intervals. Further details of the modeling 
methods can be found in the Supplementary appendix. </p>

<p>acknowledgments. The authors thank the participants with 
CF and their families who took part in these studies, as well 
as the investigators and coordinators at each study site. The 
authors acknowledge Ivan Demin from Novartis and former 
Novartis employees Srikumar Sahasranaman, Kai Wu, and 
Alison Carter for their scientific contribution to the research. 
The authors were assisted in the preparation of the manu-
script by Mary Sayers and Naomi Marshall, professional 
medical writers contracted to CircleScience (Macclesfield, 
UK), and Mark Fedele (Novartis). Writing support was funded 
by the study sponsor. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest. This research was sponsored by Novar-
tis Pharma AG, Basel, Switzerland, who had involvement in 
the study design; the collection, analysis, and interpretation 
of data; writing of the report; and the decision to submit the 
paper. D.E.G. has received income from Aptalis, Genentech, 
KaloBios, and Novartis Pharmaceuticals, for consulting ac-
tivities (in the past 12 months), and from Novartis and Vertex 
for speaking engagements. S.A., S.G.B., L.T., R.R., and P.T. 
are employees of Novartis. </p>

<p>author Contributions. L.T., S.A., S.G.B., R.R., P.T., and 
D.E.G. wrote the manuscript. L.T. and S.G.B. designed the 
research. L.T. and S.G.B. performed the research. S.A., R.R., 
and L.T. analyzed the data. </p>

<p>1. Ballmann, M., Rabsch, P. &amp; von der Hardt, H. Long-term follow up of changes in FEV1 and 
treatment intensity during Pseudomonas aeruginosa colonisation in patients with cystic 
fibrosis. Thorax 53, 732-737 (1998). 
2. Cystic Fibrosis Foundation. Cystic Fibrosis Foundation Patient Registry Annual Data 
Report. &lt;http://www.cff.org/UploadedFiles/research/ClinicalResearch/Patient-Registry-
Report-2009.pdf&gt; Accessed 26 September 2011. </p>

<p>Study Highlights </p>

<p>WHaT IS THE CURREnT KnOWLEDgE On THE 
TOPIC? </p>

<p>3 Studies have shown nebulized tobramycin to </p>

<p>be well tolerated and efficacious within cer-
tain dose concentrations, but the nebulization 
process (setup, administration, and cleaning) 
adds considerably to the burden of treatment 
for patients with CF. TIP was developed to 
reduce this burden while maintaining efficacy 
and tolerability relative to tobramycin delivered 
via nebulizer. </p>

<p>WHaT QUESTIOn DID THIS STUDY aDDRESS? </p>

<p>3 A population pharmacokinetic model was </p>

<p>developed to describe the tobramycin serum 
concentration-time course and evaluate the 
influence of covariates on systemic exposure 
following inhalation of TIP in CF patients. </p>

<p>WHaT THIS STUDY aDDS TO OUR KnOWLEDgE </p>

<p>3 Within a population of CF patients with varied </p>

<p>baseline demographics, no dose adjustment of 
TIP is expected irrespective of BMI, lung func-
tion, age, creatinine clearance, sex, or weight 
of the patient. </p>

<p>HOW THIS MIgHT CHangE CLInICaL 
PHaRMaCOLOgY anD THERaPEUTICS </p>

<p>3 No covariates were found to have a clini-</p>

<p>cally significant effect on the pharmacokinetic 
parameters of TIP, suggesting that TIP can be 
used without the need for dose adjustment by 
demographics. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/psp </p>

<p>Inhaled Tobramycin Powder in CF Patients 
Ting et al. </p>





<p>CPT: Pharmacometrics &amp; Systems Pharmacology is an 
open-access journal published by Nature Publishing 
Group. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivative Works 3.0 License. To view a copy of 
this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper on the CPT: Pharmacometrics &amp; Systems Pharmacology website 
(http://www.nature.com/psp) </p>

</text></tei>