<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3223056" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Oilseed rape (Brassica napus L.) is a major oil crop which is grown worldwide. Adaptation to different environments 
and regional climatic conditions involves variation in the regulation of flowering time. Winter types have a strong 
vernalization requirement whereas semi-winter and spring types have a low vernalization requirement or flower 
without exposure to cold, respectively. In Arabidopsis thaliana, FRIGIDA (FRI) is a key regulator which inhibits floral 
transition through activation of FLOWERING LOCUS C (FLC), a central repressor of flowering which controls 
vernalization requirement and response. Here, four FRI homologues in B. napus were identified by BAC library 
screening and PCR-based cloning. While all homologues are expressed, two genes were found to be differentially 
expressed in aerial plant organs. One of these, BnaA.FRI.a, was mapped to a region on chromosome A03 which co-
localizes with a major flowering time quantitative trait locus in multiple environments in a doubled-haploid mapping 
population. Association analysis of BnaA.FRI.a revealed that six SNPs, including at least one at a putative functional 
site, and one haplotype block, respectively, are associated with flowering time variation in 248 accessions, with 
flowering times differing by 13-19 d between extreme haplotypes. The results from both linkage analysis and 
association mapping indicate that BnaA.FRI.a is a major determinant of flowering time in oilseed rape, and suggest 
further that this gene also contributes to the differentiation between growth types. The putative functional 
polymorphisms identified here may facilitate adaptation of this crop to specific environments through marker-
assisted breeding. </p>

<p>Oilseed rape or rapeseed (Brassica napus L.) is one of the 
most important oilseed crops worldwide. B. napus is an 
allotetraploid species with 2n¼38 chromosomes and two 
genomes, AA derived from B. rapa and CC from 
B. oleracea. Because of its high seed oil and protein content, </p>

<p>rapeseed is mainly grown as animal feed, for the production 
of vegetable oil for human consumption, and for biodiesel 
production. The yield potential of rapeseed to a large extent 
depends on flowering time, and flowering time adaptation is 
a major breeding goal. Three different growth types can be </p>

<p>ª 2011 The Author(s). </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-
nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>distinguished. Spring types flower early without vernaliza-
tion and are grown in geographical regions such as Canada 
with strong winters which do not allow the cultivation of 
winter types due to unsatisfactory winter hardiness 
(Thomas, 2003), or in subtropical climates such as in parts 
of Australia. By contrast, winter types have an obligate 
requirement for prolonged periods of cold temperatures for 
flowering to occur and are grown in moderate temperate 
climates such as Western Europe. Semi-winter types are 
sown before winter and flower after winter, but lack frost 
hardiness and are therefore grown in geographical regions 
with moderate winter temperatures (&gt;0 °C) such as central 
China. In addition to cold temperatures, the length of the 
daily light period (photoperiodism) is a second major 
environmental cue affecting floral induction, with longer 
days promoting flowering in B. napus. Increasing demands 
for plant oil with altered quality traits and a changing 
climate impose new challenges for rapeseed breeding. 
Crossings between different rapeseed types (e.g. spring3 
winter) are generally avoided because the offspring are non-
adapted to the respective growing conditions, particularly 
with respect to disease resistance traits and flowering time 
(Qian et al., 2006). For example, the introduction of genes 
into European rapeseed from different geographical origins 
is hampered by non-adapted flowering time traits and 
requires extensive backcrossing (Qian et al., 2007). Thus, 
functional markers for flowering time traits are desirable for 
the selection of adapted material (Jung and  ller, 2009). 
Because of the low genetic diversity within B. napus 
( mez-Campo, 1999) knowledge of the mechanism un-
derlying flowering time variation is expected to have 
considerable impact on breeding strategies. 
In the model species Arabidopsis thaliana, several floral 
transition pathways have been identified which regulate the 
timing of flowering in response to different environmental 
and endogenous cues ( and Dean, 2006; Albani and 
Coupland, 2010; Amasino, 2010; Amasino and Michaels, 
2010). The key regulator in the photoperiod pathway, which 
mediates the effect of day length on flowering time, is the 
CCT (CONSTANS, CONSTANS-LIKE, TIMING OF CAB 
EXPRESSION 1) domain transcription factor gene CON-
STANS (CO). Under long-day conditions, CO protein 
accumulates at the end of the light phase and promotes 
flowering by activating the expression of FLOWERING 
LOCUS T (FT), a central integrator of input signals from 
different pathways whose protein product is a major 
component of the mobile signal that moves to the shoot 
apical meristem and initiates flowering (Turck et al., 2008). 
The key regulator of vernalization requirement and re-
sponse is the MADS box transcription factor gene FLOW-
ERING LOCUS C (FLC), which is a repressor of FT but is 
down-regulated by vernalization, thus enabling promotion 
of flowering by FT. Both FLC and its upstream regulator 
FRIGIDA (FRI) are major determinants of natural varia-
tion in flowering time (Johanson et al., 2000; Le Corre 
et al., 2002; Gazzani et al., 2003; Michaels et al., 2003; 
Caicedo et al., 2004; Hagenblad et al., 2004; Stinchcombe 
et al., 2004; Le Corre, 2005; Shindo et al., 2005; Werner </p>

<p>et al., 2005). Dominant alleles of FRI confer a vernalization 
requirement causing plants to overwinter vegetatively, and 
several loss-of-function mutations are associated with early 
flowering (Johanson et al., 2000). FRI was suggested to up-
regulate FLC expression through interaction with the 
histone methyltransferase EARLY FLOWERING IN 
SHORT DAYS (EFS), which results in the modification of 
FLC chromatin (Ko et al., 2010), and interaction with 
a nuclear cap-binding complex (CBC) with concomitant 
effects on FLC transcription and splicing (Geraldo et al., 
2009). 
In B. napus and related Brassica species, many flowering 
time quantitative trait loci (QTL) with large effects and high 
heritabilities have been mapped, and several studies 
reported the identification of flowering time gene homo-
logues, including FLC homologues in B. napus (BnFLC1-5; 
Tadege et al., 2001), B. oleracea (BoFLC1, BoFLC2/ 
BoFLC4, BoFLC3, and BoFLC5; Schranz et al., 2002; Lin 
et al., 2005; Okazaki et al., 2007; Razi et al., 2008), and 
B. rapa (BrFLC1, BrFLC2, BrFLC3, and BrFLC5; Schranz 
et al., 2002; Lin et al., 2005; Kim et al., 2007), CO 
homologues in B. napus and B. nigra (Robert et al., 1998; 
Osterberg et al., 2002), and FT homologues in B. napus 
(Wang et al., 2009). A comprehensive QTL analysis of 
a DH population (TNDH) derived from a cross between the 
European winter cultivar Tapidor and the Chinese semi-
winter cultivar Ningyou7, which flowered 9 d or 13 d earlier 
than the winter type parent under winter and semi-winter 
conditions, respectively (Shi et al., 2009), revealed a total of 
32 unique flowering time QTL, corresponding to five to 
13 QTL in each of 11 winter or spring crop environments 
(Long et al., 2007). Of the 32 QTL, 25 could be aligned to 
syntenic regions in the A. thaliana genome containing 
known flowering time genes. The largest-effect QTL, which 
corresponds to a major vernalization-responsive flowering 
time QTL (VFN2) identified by Osborn et al. (1997), 
explained up to 50% of the phenotypic variation for 
flowering time in the spring crop environments and co-
localized with the FLC homologue BnFLC1 (Tadege et al., 
2001) on linkage group N10. In addition, several other QTL 
in the TNDH and other populations are located in regions 
where other FLC homologues (BnFLC2-5) were mapped 
(Osborn and Lukens, 2003; Udall et al., 2006; Long et al., 
2007). Similarly, three FLC homologues in B. rapa 
(BrFLC1, BrFLC2, BrFLC5) co-segregate with flowering 
time loci, including two alleles which affect flowering time 
in a completely additive manner (Schranz et al., 2002; Zhao 
et al., 2010), while in B. oleracea thus far there is only 
evidence for the co-localization of a single FLC homologue 
(BoFLC2) with a flowering time QTL (Okazaki et al., 2007; 
Razi et al., 2008). Constitutive expression of BnFLC1-5 and 
BrFLC1-3 in A. thaliana, and BrFLC3 in B. rapa, signifi-
cantly delayed flowering (Tadege et al., 2001; Kim et al., 
2007), thus further supporting the notion that, at least in 
B. rapa and B. napus, the role of FLC homologues as floral 
regulators is largely conserved. 
Functional conservation of flowering time control by CO 
homologues in Brassica species was shown by </p>



<p>complementation analysis in A. thaliana co mutants with the 
B. napus allele BnCOa1 (Robert et al., 1998) and two alleles 
of the B. nigra gene Bni COa (Osterberg et al., 2002). In 
addition, a naturally occurring InDel variation in the 
B. nigra CO-like gene Bni COL1 gene is associated with 
variation in flowering time (Osterberg et al., 2002). Bni COa 
and Bni COL1 are located adjacent to each other (Osterberg 
et al., 2002) and co-localize with a major QTL that explains 
53% of the phenotypic variation for flowering time under 
long-day conditions (Lagercrantz et al., 1996). Among the 
six B. napus homologues of FT, three (BnA2.FT, 
BnC6.FT.a, and BnC6.FT.b) co-localize with major QTL 
clusters identified in the TNDH population on chromo-
somes A02 and C06 (Wang et al., 2009). Interestingly, 
a consensus QTL for seed yield co-localized precisely with 
consensus QTL for the yield-associated traits flowering 
time, maturity time, and plant height (Shi et al., 2009). 
Because the respective quantitative trait values are more 
easily measurable than seed yield, these QTL were named 
'indicator QTL'. The co-localization of flowering time QTL 
with yield and yield-related QTL in B. napus has also been 
reported in other studies (Udall et al., 2006; Long et al., 
2007; Basunanda et al., 2010; Chen et al., 2010). Finally, 
a major flowering time QTL in B. napus (VFN1 on linkage 
group N2) was found to be located in a region of fractured 
collinearity with several chromosomal regions in 
A. thaliana, including the region carrying the FRI locus 
(Osborn et al., 1997; Osborn and Lukens, 2003). Similar to 
the QTL co-localizing with BnFLC1 (VFN2; Osborn et al., 
1997) and a third vernalization-responsive QTL (VFN3 on 
linkage group N3; Osborn et al., 1997; Butruille et al., 
1999), this QTL was detected in non-vernalized populations 
derived from crosses between winter and spring type 
accessions, but not in vernalized populations, suggesting 
that the QTL may contribute to the regulation of vernaliza-
tion requirement. However, despite these earlier results and 
the prominent function of FRI in flowering time regulation 
in A. thaliana, thus far FRI homologues have not been 
identified and further analysed in B. napus. 
Linkage disequilibrium (LD)-based association analysis 
(also known as association mapping or LD mapping) has 
attracted the attention of plant researchers due to its high 
resolution and because there is no need for producing 
structured populations (e.g. F 2 or DH; Gupta et al., 2005). 
As a result of the limited number of crossover events during 
meiosis, recombination-based linkage analysis typically local-
izes QTL to 10 to 20 cM intervals (Doerge, 2002; Holland, 
2007). By contrast, association mapping which is based on 
large germplasm collections can localize the genetic basis of 
phenotypic variation to very small regions of the genome or 
even single genes. However, spurious associations can occur 
and QTL with small phenotypic effects can go undetected. 
Here, a combination of association analysis and recombina-
tion mapping is used to unravel the contribution of 
a candidate gene to phenotypic variation of a complex 
quantitative trait. Four B. napus homologues of FRI were 
identified, one of which (BnaA.FRI.a) co-localizes with 
a cluster of major flowering time QTL. Furthermore, </p>

<p>evidence is provided that allelic variation at the gene locus is 
associated with variation in flowering time in a worldwide 
panel of B. napus accessions. Together, the data suggest that 
BnaA.FRI.a is a major determinant of flowering time and 
contributes to the differentiation between growth habits of 
rapeseed. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Plant material and growth conditions 
The B. napus TNDH population encompassing 202 lines (Qiu 
et al., 2006) was used as a mapping population. The parents of 
this doubled-haploid (DH) population are B. napus cv. Tapidor 
and Ningyou7, with the former being a European winter type 
rapeseed which flowers late and the latter being a Chinese semi-
winter type which flowers early under winter field conditions in 
central China (Long et al., 2007). Flowering time data for the 
TNDH population grown at five different locations in China in 
successive field trials over a period of four years (2002-2006), 
which included both winter and spring growing conditions, were 
recorded by Long et al. (2007). 
A collection of 248 B. napus accessions was used for 
association mapping (see Supplementary Table S1 at JXB 
online). These accessions included registered varieties and 
breeding lines from all over the world, with emphasis on 
European and Chinese material. Seeds were obtained from the 
Leibniz Institute of Plant Genetics and Crop Plant Research 
(Gatersleben, Germany), Norddeutsche Pflanzenzucht Hans-
Georg Lembke KG (Hohenlieth, Germany), and from breeding 
material available at the College of Agronomy and Biotechnol-
ogy, Southwest University (Chongqing, China). Plants were 
grown in three-row plots with 30 plants plot À1 in a semi-winter 
growth environment in Chongqing, China (29°31' N, 106°35' E) 
in 2007/2008 and 2008/2009 (referred to in the following by the 
year in which flowering time was recorded, i.e. 2008 and 2009, 
respectively). Under these growth conditions, in central China 
both semi-winter and winter types are generally sufficiently 
vernalized to flower after winter. Spring type accessions grown 
under these conditions do not usually start flowering before the 
onset of winter. During the winter months, plant growth slows 
down or comes to a halt, but the relatively mild winter 
temperatures at the chosen location in central China generally 
allows the spring types to survive as well. Flowering time in 
both field trials was recorded as the days from sowing to the 
date when the first flower had opened on half of the plants of an 
accession. Furthermore, accessions were classified as spring, 
semi-winter or winter types according to the annotation of the 
original cultivars (Chinese Crop Germplasm Information Sys-
tem (CGRIS), http://icgr.caas.net.cn/cgris_english.html) or their 
general performance in the field (see Supplementary Table S1 at 
JXB online; W Qian, unpublished data). Genomic DNA was 
extracted from a pooled sample of approximately equal amounts 
of leaves from all 30 plants of a plot. 
For gene expression experiments, three different B. napus 
accessions were used, the German winter type variety Express, the 
Chinese semi-winter type variety Ningyou7, and the spring type 
variety Haydn. Seeds were sown on 3 August 2009, and plants 
were grown in the greenhouse under long-day conditions. For 
vernalization, 30-d-old plants were transferred to a climate cham-
ber, grown at 5 °C for 42 d, and returned to the greenhouse. 
Leaves, stems, floral buds, and flowers were harvested at the 
flowering stage 63-65 according to the BBCH scale (Meier, 2001). 
Non-vernalized Haydn plants flowered at 50 d, non-vernalized 
Ningyou7 plants and vernalized Haydn plants at 88-89 d, 
vernalized Ningyou7 plants at 95 d, and vernalized Express plants </p>

<p>Association of BnaA.FRI.a with flowering time variation in Brassica napus | 5643 </p>

<p>at 127-136 d after sowing. Biological replicates were obtained by 
harvesting samples from three different plants. </p>

<p>Identification of FRIGIDA homologues in B. napus 
The genomic, cDNA and protein sequences of A. thaliana FRI 
(At4g00650) were used as queries for BLASTN and TBLASTN 
homology searches of the nt/nr and EST sections of GenBank (as 
of 27 November 2005), which identified a B. napus EST (GenBank 
accession number CD836567, derived from B. napus cv. Jet Neuf) 
with 74% sequence identity over 578 bp of FRI exon 1. A genomic 
fragment corresponding to the EST was amplified from B. napus 
cv. Express genomic DNA using an EST sequence-derived primer 
pair (A102-A103; see Supplementary Table S2 at JXB online). The 
PCR product of 614 bp had 99% sequence identity to the EST and 
was used as probe to screen a B. napus cv. Express BAC library 
(obtained from Deutsches Ressourcenzentrum  r Genomfor-
schung GmbH (RZPD), Berlin, Germany) according to standard 
protocols for radioactive hybridization (Sambrook et al., 1989). 
DNA of positive BAC clones was extracted using the 
NucleoBondÒ PC 500 plasmid DNA purification kit (Macherey &amp; 
Nagel GmbH &amp; Co. KG,  ren, Germany). Sequence identity or 
homology to the probe fragment was confirmed by PCR amplifi-
cation and sequencing of BAC DNA using primer pair A102-
A103. The BAC clones were grouped into three sequence groups 
according to a multiple sequence alignment using the AlignX 
module of the <rs type="software">Vector NTI</rs> software package (Invitrogen Corpora-
tion, Carlsbad, USA). To identify the full-length genomic sequen-
ces, one BAC of each group was selected for primer walking using 
primers A127, A133, A201, A248, A249, A250, A260, A261, A262, 
A372, and A378 (see Supplementary Table S2 at JXB online). The 
genes were annotated using pairwise sequence alignments 
(BLAST2; http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov) with FRI and the <rs id="software-32" type="software">FGE-
NESH+</rs> and <rs type="software">FGENESH_C</rs> gene prediction programs (<rs corresp="#software-32" type="url">http://linux1.softberry.com/berry.phtml</rs>). Orthology was inferred by 
bidirectional best hit analysis (Overbeek et al., 1999) using 
the B. napus genes as queries for BLASTX searches against 
the A. thaliana protein database at TAIR (http://www. 
arabidopsis.org). Following the nomenclature for Brassica genes 
(Ostergaard and King, 2008), the three FRI homologues were 
designated as BnaA.FRI.a, BnaX.FRI.b, and BnaX.FRI.c. 
A primer pair derived from the exon 3 region of the B. napus genes 
(A249-A374), was used for PCR amplification from B. napus cv. 
Express genomic DNA. PCR products were cloned into the pGEM-
T vector (Promega Corporation, Madison, USA) according to the 
manufacturer's protocol. Twenty positive clones were selected and 
sequenced. A multiple sequence alignment identified four sequence 
groups, three of which corresponded to BnaA.FRI.a, BnaX.FRI.b, 
and BnaX.FRI.c. The fourth sequence was designated as BnaX.-
FRI.d. BnaX.FRI.d-specific primers N010 and A156 were designed 
(see Supplementary Table S2 at JXB online). By using primer A102 
in combination with the BnaX.FRI.d-specific primer N010, and 
primer A157 together with the BnaX.FRI.d-specific primer A156, the 
5' and 3' regions of BnaX.FRI.d were obtained. The sequences of 
BnaA.FRI.a, BnaX.FRI.b, BnaX.FRI.c, and BnaX.FRI.d were 
deposited at GenBank (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank). </p>

<p>Genetic mapping and QTL detection 
Specific primers were designed for each of the four B. napus FRI 
homologues. The following primer combinations covered the 
respective genes: N036-A385 and N053-N020 (BnaA.FRI.a), 
A379-A386 and N030-N032 (BnaX.FRI.b), A370-N004 (BnaX.F-
RI.c), and A102-N010 (BnaX.FRI.d; see Supplementary Table S2 
at JXB online). The primers were used to amplify genomic DNA 
of the two parents of the DH mapping population, and the PCR 
products were sequenced. Upon detection of polymorphisms 
between Tapidor and Ningyou7 in the promoter region of 
BnaA.FRI.a, a new primer (N016) was designed which is specific </p>

<p>for the Tapidor allele and was used in combination with A385 to 
genotype all 202 DH lines by PCR amplification. Genotypes were 
scored according to the presence or absence of the target fragment 
after agarose gel electrophoresis. 
BnaA.FRI.a was mapped onto the framework map constructed 
by Long et al. (2007) using <rs id="software-25" type="software">JoinMap</rs> <rs corresp="#software-25" type="version-number">3.0</rs> (Van Ooijen and 
Voorrips, 2001) and a LOD score of 2.5. The resulting genetic 
map and the flowering time data for 11 environments recorded by 
Long et al. (2007) were used for detection of QTL for flowering 
time by composite interval mapping (CIM) with <rs id="software-18" type="software">Windows QTL 
cartographer</rs> <rs corresp="#software-18" type="version-number">2.5</rs> (Wang et al., 2011). </p>

<p>SNP detection and inference of haplotypes in a collection of 
B. napus accessions 
According to the flowering time data of 248 accessions from two 
growth seasons (see Supplementary Table S1 at JXB online), 
a subset of 95 accessions including similar numbers of early, 
intermediate, and late flowering accessions were selected for a first 
genotypic analysis. The BnaA.FRI.a-specific primer combinations 
N036-A385 and N053-N020 were used to genotype these acces-
sions by PCR amplification and sequencing. Two primers (N018 
and A385) were used for sequencing the N036-A385 PCR 
products, and three primers (N020, N054, and N057) were used 
for sequencing the N053-N020 products. Whole gene sequences 
were obtained by assembling the sequence data from these 
sequencing reactions for each accession. Sequences were aligned 
using <rs id="software-21" type="software">VectorNTI 10.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-21" type="creator">Invitrogen Corporation</rs>, Carlsbad, USA) or 
<rs id="software-8" type="software">CLC main workbench</rs> <rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-number">5</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-8" type="creator">CLC bio</rs>, Aarhus, Denmark), and 
alignments were edited manually using the <rs id="software-62" type="software">BioEdit</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-62" type="url">http://www.mbio.ncsu.edu/bioedit/bioedit.html</rs>). Haplotypes were 
inferred using the <rs id="software-28" type="software">software HAP</rs> at default parameters (<rs corresp="#software-28" type="url">http://research.calit2.net/hap</rs>). Three primers (N069, N076, and N078; 
see Supplementary Table S2 at JXB online) were designed to 
differentiate between the two nucleotides for each of the three 
haplotype tagging SNPs (htSNPs) detected by HAP in haplotype 
block 2. All 248 accessions were genotyped at these htSNP 
positions by PCR with primer combinations N069-N020, N053-
N076, and N053-N078. Haplotypes were scored according to the 
presence or absence of the respective bands after agarose gel 
electrophoresis of the PCR products (see Supplementary Table S1 
at JXB online). </p>

<p>Population structure evaluation 
28 publicly available SSR markers (see Supplementary Table S3 at 
JXB online) were selected from Cheng et al. (2009) which were 
distributed equally across the genetic map of B. napus. To reduce 
costs, an M13-tailing PCR technique was used (Schuelke, 2000). 
For each SSR primer combination, the forward sequence of the 
M13 primer was added to the 5# end of the forward SSR primer 
and the reverse sequence of the M13 primer was added to the 
5' end of the reverse SSR primer. PCR reactions were performed 
with four primers, the M13F-forward SSR primer, the M13R-
reverse SSR primer, an IRD700-labelled M13F primer (MWG 
Operon, Ebersberg, Germany) and an unlabelled M13R primer. 
The 28 SSR markers were used to assay the 95 accessions which 
were selected for the first round of genotyping. The DNA analyser 
system Li-Cor 4300 (Li-Cor Biosciences, Lincoln, Nebraska, USA) 
was used for electrophoresis and detection of PCR products. The 
presence or absence of PCR product bands was scored as 1 or 0, 
respectively. The software <rs id="software-17" type="software">STRUCTURE</rs> <rs corresp="#software-17" type="version-number">2.2.3</rs> was used to 
estimate population structure (http://pritch.bsd.uchicago.edu/ 
structure.html) (Pritchard et al., 2000). K values ranging from 1 to 
10 were tested with a burn-in of 100 000 iterations and 100 000 
Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) iterations according to the 
software's instructions. 
The effect of population structure on flowering time was tested 
using <rs id="software-36" type="software">SAS</rs> GLM (<rs corresp="#software-36" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, North Carolina, USA). The </p>



<p>model included two components of the Q matrix (Q1 and Q2) 
obtained with STRUCTURE 2.2.3. R 2 (variance explained by the 
model) was considered as an estimate of the proportion of 
phenotypic variation explained by population structure. </p>

<p>Linkage-disequilibrium and association analysis 
<rs type="software">TASSEL 2.01</rs> was used to calculate linkage disequilibrium (LD) 
based on the parameter R 2 (Bradbury et al., 2007). Only SNPs 
with frequencies larger than 0.05 were included for LD calculation. 
To avoid redundancy, each InDel was considered as a single 
polymorphic site. 
For SNP/InDel-based association analysis, a structure-based 
model which takes population structure into account to reduce 
spurious associations was used. Associations between markers and 
the total trait variation were tested using a general linear model 
(GLM) which was implemented in <rs id="software-22" type="software">TASSEL</rs> <rs corresp="#software-22" type="version-number">2.01</rs>. A Q matrix 
which was obtained with <rs type="software">STRUCTURE 2.2.3</rs> was used to account 
for population structure. The null hypothesis of this study was that 
the occurrence of polymorphisms in BnaA.FRI.a is independent of 
the variation in flowering time, whereas the alternative hypothesis 
was that polymorphisms are associated with flowering time 
variation. Only polymorphisms with frequencies above 0.05 were 
included and 1000 permutations were performed. An adjusted 
P value &lt;0.05 was considered as a criterion for association. For 
haplotype association analysis, block 1 and block 2 were regarded 
as two polymorphic loci. Different haplotypes in the same block 
were regarded as allelic variants at one locus. For further analysis 
of association between haplotype and flowering time variation in 
a larger panel which included 248 accessions, the software <rs id="software-30" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-30" type="version-number">9.0</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-30" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, North Carolina, USA) was used to conduct 
an analysis of variance (ANOVA) and multi-comparison analyses 
with least significant differences (LSD). </p>

<p>Transcript and expression analysis 
Total RNA was extracted using the RNeasy kit (QIAGEN, 
www.qiagen.com) according to the manufacturer's protocol. RNA 
concentration was determined by spectrometry (NanoDrop; 
Thermo Scientific, Wilmington, USA) and quality was checked by 
agarose gel electrophoresis. Total RNA was treated with DNAse I 
(Fermentas Inc., Maryland, USA). First-strand cDNA was 
synthesized using Oligo(dT) 18 primers and the M-MuLV Reverse 
Transcriptase (Fermentas). cDNA was diluted to produce approx-
imately equal amounts of products by RT-PCR with the reference 
gene primers. 
For sequencing of PCR products and RT-PCR, cDNA was 
amplified with DreamTaq polymerase (Fermentas). For cloning of 
full-length coding sequences, the proof-reading polymerases Pfu 
(Fermentas) or Phusion (Biozym Inc., Los Angeles, USA) were 
used. The coding sequences of BnaA.FRI.a and BnaX.FRI.d were 
amplified from cDNA of vernalized floral buds of cultivar Express 
using primers FRI3_nested_fwd and FRI3_nested_rev or 
FRI4_fwd2 and FRI4_rev, respectively. BnaX.FRI.b and BnaX. 
FRI.c were amplified from cDNA of non-vernalized roots of 
B. napus cv. Express sampled 50 d after sowing at BBCH 19 (nine 
or more leaves unfolded) using primers A459 and A454 or A458 
and A455, respectively, and reamplified using nested primers 
FRI1_nested_fwd and FRI1_nested_rev or FRI2_nested_fwd and 
FRI2_nested_rev, respectively. PCR products were cloned into the 
pGEMT-vector (Promega Corporation, Madison, USA) according 
to the manufacturer's protocol. 
For semi-quantitative RT-PCR of BnaA.FRI.a and BnaX.FRI.d, 
cDNA was amplified with primers FRI34_RT_fwd_2 and N008. 
The resulting product sizes differ by 30 bp. For semi-quantitative 
RT-PCR of BnaX.FRI.b and BnaX.FRI.c, cDNA was amplified 
with primers FRI12_RT_fwd_2 and FRI12_RT_rev in a final 
volume of 25 ll, followed by restriction enzyme digestion of 15 ll 
of the resulting PCR product with XhoI (Fermentas) in a final 
volume of 20 ll to distinguish between the two genes. The expected </p>

<p>fragment sizes are 418 bp (BnaA.FRI.a), 617 bp (BnaX.FRI.b), 374 
bp and 246 bp (BnaX.FRI.c digested by XhoI), and 388 bp 
(BnaX.FRI.d). As a reference gene, a B. napus tubulin gene 
(GenBank accession number AF258790) was amplified with 
primers BnTubulin_fwd and BnTubulin_rev, resulting in PCR 
products of 224 bp for cDNA templates and 0.3 kb for genomic 
DNA templates. 
Quantitative real-time RT-PCR (RT-qPCR) was performed with 
SYBR qPCR Supermix w/ROX (Invitrogen Corporation, 
Carlsbad, USA) using a CFX96 Real-Time System (Bio-Rad 
Laboratories GmbH,  nchen, Germany). Reactions were per-
formed in a total volume of 15 ll containing 100 nM of each 
primer and 2 ll of diluted cDNA templates, and amplified using 
the following cycling conditions: 95 °C for 3 min, 40 cycles of 95 
°C for 10 s, 61.4 °C for 30 s, and 72 °C for 30 s, followed by 95 °C 
for 10 min. A melting curve was generated using a temperature 
range from 65 °C to 95 °C with increments of 0.5 °C every 5 s. 
BnaA.FRI.a cDNA was amplified with forward primer 
FRI34_RT_fwd_2, which spans the junction of exons 2 and 3, 
and the gene-specific reverse primer FRI3_RT_rev. As a reference 
gene, a B. napus actin gene (GenBank accession number FJ529167) 
was amplified with primers N062 and N063. For each sample at 
least three technical replications were performed. For data 
analysis, the mean Ct value of the target gene was normalized 
against the average Ct value of B. napus actin, using the DCt 
method implemented in the <rs type="software">CFX manager</rs> software (Bio-Rad 
Laboratories GmbH,  nchen, Germany). Primer efficiencies for 
the different targets (95% for BnaA.FRI.a, 104% for B. napus 
actin) were determined using four 2-fold serial dilutions of cDNA 
and were included in the calculation of relative expression levels in 
CFX manager. Melting curves showed a single peak for each target 
with PCR products of BnaA.FRI.a and B. napus actin peaking 
both between 82.5 °C and 83.0 °C. 'No template controls' (NTCs), 
included in triplicates for each target in each run, were either not 
amplified (Ct values below baseline threshold) or had very high 
(&gt;36-39) Ct values, with melting curves peaking at clearly 
distinguishable temperatures (76.0-78.0 °C and 75.5-77.0 °C) from 
the respective PCRs with templates. Normalized expression was 
averaged over three biological replicates in each case. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>FRIGIDA homologues in B. napus </p>

<p>BAC library screening and PCR amplification from geno-
mic DNA of B. napus identified four putative rapeseed 
orthologues of FRI, which were designated as BnaA.FRI.a, 
BnaX.FRI.b, BnaX.FRI.c, and BnaX.FRI.d. The predicted 
protein sequences range from 569 to 596 amino acids and 
are thus somewhat shorter than FRI (609 amino acids for 
the functional allele in the A. thaliana accession H51; 
Johanson et al., 2000). All four genes are predicted to carry 
a conserved, centrally located 'Frigida' domain (Fig. 1; 
http://pfam.sanger.ac.uk, accession number PF07899; Finn 
et al., 2010) which is characteristic for the superfamily of 
FRI and FRI-LIKE genes (Risk et al., 2010). Furthermore, 
on the basis of sequence conservation within a 37 amino-
acid region in the N-terminal part of the protein (Fig. 1), all 
four B. napus genes can be assigned to the FRI family I as 
defined by Risk et al. (2010), which includes FRI but not 
FRI-LIKE genes. In contrast to FRI in A. thaliana, where 
this region and a second region at the C-terminal end of the 
Frigida domain are predicted to form coiled-coil structures 
(Johanson et al., 2000; , 2006), only the C-terminal </p>

<p>Association of BnaA.FRI.a with flowering time variation in Brassica napus | 5645 </p>

<p>coiled-coil structure is also predicted for all four B. napus 
genes at a stringent probability threshold (90% for a window 
size of 28 residues; http://www.ch.embnet.org/software/coils/ 
COILS_doc.html; Lupas et al., 1991). In two genes, </p>

<p>BnaA.FRI.a and BnaX.FRI.d, the N-terminal coiled-coil 
domain is predicted with lower probabilities (;50% and 
;80%, respectively), whereas this domain is not predicted 
for BnaX.FRI.b and BnaX.FRI.c (probabilities &lt;5%). The 
largest of the B. napus genes, BnaA.FRI.a, was found to 
carry an additional 17 amino acids in a region of three 
eight-amino-acid repeat elements (MEEARSIS; Fig. 1). 
Only two of these repeat elements are present in BnaX.-
FRI.d., whereas BnaX.FRI.b, BnaX.FRI.c, and A. thaliana 
FRI each carry only a single copy of this or a closely related 
motif, respectively. The repeat region is located at the 
C-terminal end of the Frigida domain and overlaps with the 
coiled-coil domain. The overall amino acid identities of 
BnaA.FRI.a, BnaX.FRI.b, BnaX.FRI.c, and BnaX.FRI.d. to 
A. thaliana FRI are, respectively, 58%, 61%, 61%, and 59%. </p>

<p>B. napus FRI genes are differentially expressed </p>

<p>The exon-intron structure of all four FRI homologues was 
identified by RT-PCR and sequencing and was found to be 
conserved between the B. napus genes and functional FRI 
alleles in A. thaliana (Fig. 2A). Gene expression was analysed 
in leaves, stems, floral buds, and flowers of three different 
B. napus accessions, the winter type Express, the semi-winter 
type Ningyou7 (with or without prior vernalization), and the 
spring type Haydn (with or without prior vernalization), 
using primer combinations specific for either the gene pair 
BnaA.FRI.a/BnaX.FRI.d or BnaX.FRI.b/BnaX.FRI.c. Indi-
vidual genes of a gene pair were distinguished by gel 
electrophoresis on the basis of size differences (BnaA.FRI.a/ 
BnaX.FRI.d), or by gel electrophoresis following XhoI re-
striction (BnaX.FRI.b and BnaX.FRI.c). RT-PCR fragments 
of the expected sizes were obtained in most samples from all 
three accessions, demonstrating that all four B. napus FRI 
genes are expressed in accessions of different growth types 
(Fig. 2B). Expression levels were similar between the different 
ecotypes and between vernalized and non-vernalized plants. 
However, while BnaX.FRI.b and BnaX.FRI.c transcripts were 
ubiquitously and relatively evenly expressed across all tissues 
analysed, BnaA.FRI.a and BnaA.FRI.d exhibited marked 
differences in expression, which ranged from barely detect-
able in leaves and stems to very high in flowers (Fig. 2B). For 
BnaA.FRI.a, differential spatial expression was confirmed by 
transcript-specific RT-qPCR in Ningyou7 (Fig. 2C). </p>

<p>BnaA.FRI.a co-localizes with a major flowering time QTL 
cluster </p>

<p>The four B. napus FRI genes in the parents of the TNDH 
mapping population (B. napus cv. Tapidor and Ningyou7) 
were sequenced to detect sequence polymorphisms for 
mapping. Whereas BnaX.FRI.b, BnaX.FRI.c, and BnaX.-
FRI.d are monomorphic across the entire gene sequences, 
several polymorphisms were identified for BnaA.FRI.a (see 
Supplementary Fig. S1 at JXB online). A marker (primer 
combination N016-A385; see Supplementary Table S2 at 
JXB online) was developed and used to genotype the 202 
DH lines of the mapping population. The newly developed </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Multiple sequence alignment of A. thaliana FRI and the 
B. napus homologues BnaA.FRI.a, BnaX.FRI.b, BnaX.FRI.c, and 
BnaX.FRI.d. The functional FRI allele in the A. thaliana accession 
H51 (GenBank accession number AF228500; Johanson et al., 
2000) was used for the alignment. The conserved 'Frigida' domain 
according to <rs id="software-51" type="software">Pfam 24.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-51" type="url">http://pfam.janelia.org</rs>) is indicated by 
vertical brackets. The regions corresponding to the two coiled-coil 
domains in FRI are marked by the grey horizontal brackets below 
the alignment. The nine residues within a 37 amino acid N-terminal 
region (marked by the black bar above the alignment) which are 
typical for family I proteins among FRI homologues (Risk et al., 
2010) and are conserved in all four B. napus genes are indicated 
by asterisks. The arrows mark the three eight amino acid 
(MEEARSIS) repeats in BnaA.FRI.a. </p>



<p>Fig. 2. Exon-intron structure and expression analysis of B. napus FRI homologues. (A) Exon-intron structure of BnaA.FRI.a, BnaX.FRI.b, 
BnaX.FRI.c, BnaX.FRI.d, and AtFRI (accession H51, accession number AF228499) between start and stop codons. Exons are indicated 
as black rectangles. Numbers indicate base pair positions relative to the start codon. Arrows mark the positions of primers used for 
semi-quantitative RT-PCR (black) and real-time qPCR (grey), with the forward primers spanning across splice sites (dotted lines). 
(B) Semi-quantitative RT-PCR of B. napus FRI homologues in aerial parts of three different growth types of rapeseed at the flowering 
stage. (Top panel) Spring type accession Haydn (non-vernalized or vernalized as indicated). (Bottom panel) Semi-winter type accession 
Ningyou7 (non-vernalized or vernalized) and winter type accession Express (vernalized). '+', Positive control, i.e. PCR on pGEM-T 
plasmids carrying cloned full-length coding sequences of the respective B. napus genes as template DNA, or PCR on genomic DNA 
from rapeseed for the B. napus tubulin gene. H 2 O, negative control. Numbers on the left indicate the fragment length in base pairs of 
a DNA size marker (GeneRulerä 1 kb DNA Ladder; Fermentas Inc., Maryland, USA). (C) RT-qPCR analysis of tissue-specific expression 
of BnaA.FRI.a in non-vernalized and vernalized Ningyou7 plants at the flowering stage. Expression was normalized using B. napus actin 
as a reference gene. </p>

<p>Association of BnaA.FRI.a with flowering time variation in Brassica napus | 5647 </p>

<p>BnaA.FRI.a marker was integrated into the genetic map 
generated with the TNDH population (Long et al., 2007) 
and was mapped on chromosome A03 at position 49.8 cM 
between markers S15M04-2-85 and RA2E11. Using the 
genetic map containing the BnaA.FRI.a marker, the QTL 
map for flowering time data from 11 environments (Long 
et al., 2007) was recalculated. A flowering time QTL cluster 
with two major peaks was detected on chromosome A03 
between 10 cM and 60 cM (Fig. 3). BnaA.FRI.a is centrally 
located within the narrow confidence intervals (48.8-50.9 
cM) of QTL detected in seven environments at the position 
of one of the two major QTL peaks (Table 1; Fig. 3). 
Interestingly, the flowering time QTL co-localizing with 
BnaA.FRI.a were detected in both winter (Fig. 3A) and 
spring environments (Fig. 3B). The QTL explained up to 
12.0% of the phenotypic variation in winter environments </p>

<p>and up to 8.1% in spring enviroments. The early-flowering 
allele is derived from the semi-winter type parent Ningyou7. </p>

<p>Linkage disequilibrium at the BnaA.FRI.a locus </p>

<p>A panel of 95 B. napus accessions was genotyped at the 
BnaA.FRI.a locus by PCR amplification from genomic 
DNA with primer pairs N036-A385 and N053-N020 and 
sequencing of the products with primers A385, N018, N020, 
N054, and N057 (Fig. 4). The sequenced fragments covered 
2179 bp from the start codon to the stop codon and ;140 
bp of the 5# UTR. In total, 35 SNPs and five InDels with 
frequencies &gt;0.05 were identified (Table 2). Of these 40 
polymorphic sites, four were located within the 5# UTR, 
five were located within introns, and 31 were located within 
the coding sequence. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. BnaA.FRI.a co-localizes with major flowering time QTL on chromosome A03 in both winter (A) and spring environments (B): y-
axis, LOD values; x-axis, genetic map positions on chromosome A03 (in centiMorgan, cM). The black horizontal line indicates a LOD 
value of 2.5. The arrowhead marks the genetic map position of BnaA.FRI.a (49.8 cM), which was integrated into the map developed by 
Long et al. (2007). In (A), the LOD profiles are only shown for the winter environments in which the three most significant QTL were 
detected. The numerical QTL data are given in Table 1. </p>



<p>To determine the degree of LD within BnaA.FRI.a, 
<rs id="software-39" type="software">TASSEL</rs> <rs corresp="#software-39" type="version-number">2.01</rs> (Bradbury et al., 2007) was used to 
calculate R 2 values for each pair of polymorphisms. Out 
of 780 pairs of polymorphic sites, 646 showed significant 
linkage with P &lt;0.05. LD decay for BnaA.FRI.a is </p>

<p>illustrated in Fig. 4A. For distances larger than approxi-
mately 2 kb, the R 2 value is lower than 0.2. This indicates 
that LD decays rapidly within this gene, suggesting that 
BnaA.FRI.a is suitable for an analysis of gene-trait 
associations. </p>

<p>Table 1. Flowering time QTL co-localizing with BnaA.FRI.a on chromosome A03 </p>

<p>No. 
QTL a 
Environment b 
LOD 
Position (cM) 
QTL confidence interval (95%) 
R 2 </p>

<p>1 
W03D 
Winter 
2.6 
49.8 
48.8-50.9 
3.1% 
2 
W04D 
Winter 
&lt;2.5 
n.a. d 
n.a. 
n.a. 
3 
W03W1 
Winter 
5.5 
49.8 
49.3-50.0 
8.2% 
4 
W04W1 
Winter 
8.8 
49.8 
49.4-49.9 
10.9% 
5 
W05W1 
Winter 
9.4 
49.8 
49.4-49.9 
12.0% 
6 
W05W3 
Winter 
&lt;2.5 
n.a. 
n.a. 
n.a. 
7 
S05H 
Spring 
5.7 
49.8 
49.2-50.3 
6.0% 
8 
W06W1 
Winter 
&lt;2.5 
N/A 
n.a. 
n.a. 
9 
W06W2 
Winter 
6.3 
49.8 
49.3-50.2 
6.8% 
10 
W06D 
Winter 
&lt;2.5 
n.a. 
n.a. 
n.a. 
11 
S06H 
Spring 
8.5 
49.8 
49.5-50.0 
8.1% </p>

<p>a The first letter (W or S) indicates winter or spring environments, the number in the middle indicates the year of harvest, and the last letter or 
letter and number (D, W1, W2, or H) indicate different locations in China (Long et al., 2007). 
b In winter environments, plants were grown from October to May; in spring environments, plants were grown from May to September. 
c Phenotypic variation explained by this QTL. 
d Not applicable; values are only given for QTL with LOD &gt;2.5. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Linkage disequilibrium and polymorphisms at the BnaA.FRI.a locus. (A) 40 polymorphisms (SNPs and InDels) in BnaA.FRI.a were 
used to calculate their paired R 2 values (y-axis) with <rs type="software">TASSEL</rs>. The x-axis indicates distances in base pairs between paired 
polymorphisms. The logarithmic trend line is shown in grey. (B) The position of polymorphisms in BnaA.FRI.a. Only polymorphisms 
showing association with flowering time are included in the figure. Black circles indicate amino acid substitutions, whereas open circles 
indicate synonymous SNPs. Exonic regions between the translational start (1) and stop positions (2179) are indicated as black 
rectangles. Arrows mark the position and orientation of primers used for LD and association analysis. </p>

<p>Association of BnaA.FRI.a with flowering time variation in Brassica napus | 5649 </p>

<p>Population structure and impact on flowering time 
variation </p>

<p>Using 28 SSR markers which are distributed equally across 
the whole genome (Cheng et al., 2009; see Supplementary 
Table S3 at JXB online) to evaluate population structure in </p>

<p>the panel of 95 B. napus accessions, 52 polymorphisms were 
detected in total with frequencies larger than 0.05. Four SSR 
primer combinations amplified more than one locus according 
to Cheng et al. (2009). These four primer combinations and 
12 additional SSR markers revealed multiple allelic diversity </p>

<p>Table 2. SNPs and InDels within the BnaA.FRI.a gene and their association with flowering time as determined in two consecutive years 
in a panel of 95 accessions. </p>

<p>SNPs and InDels with frequencies &gt;0.05 are listed in the table. The probability of association with flowering time is given for P values &lt;0.05. </p>

<p>Position within gene 
Polymorphism 
Location 
Predicted amino acid change 
Association with 
flowering time 
(P value) </p>

<p>2008 
2009 </p>

<p>-133 a 
30/0 b 
5' UTR 
-28 
T/C c 
5' UTR 
-26 
C/T 
5' UTR 
-25 
11/0 
5' UTR 
99 
21/0 
exon1 
VETVPTN/deletion d 
137 
A/G 
exon1 
G46E 
138 
A/G 
exon1 
140 
A/C 
exon1 
Q47P 
189 
A/T 
exon1 
198 
G/A 
exon1 
0.046* f 
206 
T/C 
exon1 
V69A 
254 
A/G 
exon1 
E85G 
0.005** 
282 
C/T 
exon1 
323 
C/A 
exon1 
P108L 
324 
G/A 
exon1 
0.013* 
343 
G/A 
exon1 
V115I 
348 
G/T 
exon1 
0.050* 
417 
T/C 
exon1 
0.029* 
762 
C/A 
exon1 
801 
C/G 
exon1 
854 
C/A 
exon1 
A285D 
900 
C/G 
exon1 
958 
A/G 
intron1 
971 
A/G 
intron1 
972 
4/0 
intron1 
994 
T/G 
intron1 
1042 
T/A 
intron1 
1224 
T/A 
exon2 
F309I 
1276 
T/A 
exon2 
M325K 
1615 
C/T 
exon3 
1702 
C/T 
exon3 
1790 
G/A 
exon3 
A467T 
0.017* 
1796 
G/T 
exon3 
A469S 
1824 
3/0 
exon3 
H/deletion e 
1888 
C/T 
exon3 
1949 
G/T 
exon3 
V520F 
1974 
G/C 
exon3 
1980 
C/A 
exon3 
2084 
G/C 
exon3 
2158 
A/G 
exon3 </p>

<p>a Basepair positions are given relative to the ATG start codon. '-' indicates positions upstream of the start codon. At sites of InDel 
polymorphisms, the basepair positions refer to the start of the respective insertion in the BnaA.FRI.a allele in B. napus cv. Tapidor. 
b At sites of InDel polymorphisms, the numbers preceding the slash indicate the size of the insertion in the Tapidor allele. 
c Letters preceding the slash indicate the nucleotide at the respective position in the Tapidor allele. 
d The 7 amino acid tract VETVPTN is present in Tapidor, but deleted in some accessions. 
e The additional H residue is present in Tapidor, but deleted in some accessions. 
f *P &lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01. </p>



<p>among accessions. The population structure was calculated 
using these SSR markers and the software <rs type="software">STRUCTURE 
2.3.2</rs> (Pritchard et al., 2000). The highest likelihoods were 
calculated for subpopulation numbers (K values) of K¼3 and 
K¼6, which were almost equally likely [Ln p (D)¼ -2198 for 
K¼3; Ln p (D)¼ -2168 for K¼6], whereas the variance for 
the respective Ln p (D) values differed considerably (152.7 for 
K¼3; 376.5 for K¼6) (Table 3). Because the variance was 
lower for K¼3, this K value was used to select the Q matrix. 
By variance analysis of flowering time data from 2008 and 
2009, population structure was found to explain 53.6% of the 
variation. This indicates that population structure had a large 
effect on flowering time. </p>

<p>Association of BnaA.FRI.a with flowering time variation </p>

<p>Because a strong population structure was observed and 
a large percentage of the observed phenotypic variation could 
be explained by population structure, association analysis 
may identify spurious associations. Therefore, a structure-
based association analysis was performed. This analysis 
revealed an association of SNP1790 with flowering time 
variation in 2008, and an association of SNP198, SNP254, 
SNP324, SNP348, and SNP417 with flowering time variation 
in 2009 (P &lt;0.05; Table 2). All of these six SNPs were 
located within exons, including five (SNP198, SNP254, 
SNP324, SNP348, and SNP417) in exon 1 and one 
(SNP1790) in exon 3 (Fig. 4B). Two of these SNPs, SNP254 
and SNP1790, are predicted to result in amino acid changes. 
As there was no SNP with significant association to 
flowering time in both years, a haplotype-based association 
analysis was performed. Using the software <rs id="software-7" type="software">HAP</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-7" type="url">http://research.calit2.net/hap</rs>) to infer haplotypes for BnaA.FRI.a 
among all accessions, two haplotype blocks were found within 
this gene. 27 SNPs or InDels were located in block 1 (position 
-140 to 1223, including exon 1) and 13 SNPs or InDels in 
block 2 (position 1224 to 2182, including exons 2 and 3). 
Three common haplotypes (represented by more than two 
accessions each) were identified in block 1, while four common 
haplotypes were found in block 2. Three polymorphic sites </p>

<p>(InDel99, SNP282, and SNP348) in block 1 and three 
polymorphic sites (SNP1224, SNP1615, and SNP1790) in 
block 2 were identified as haplotype tagging SNPs (htSNPs) 
or InDels (Table 4; see Supplementary Fig. S2 at JXB online). 
Taking population structure into account, block 2 showed 
association with flowering time for both years (P &lt;0.05). 
To analyse the effects of different haplotypes in block 2 on 
flowering time variation further, htSNPs of this block were 
genotyped in a larger panel with 248 accessions including the 
95 accessions described above. In total, 52 accessions were 
inferred as haplotype 1, 54 accessions as haplotype 2, 74 
accessions as haplotype 3, and 46 accessions as haplotype 4. 22 
accessions were inferred as rare haplotypes and were excluded 
from further analysis. To analyse the possible differential 
effects of haplotypes on flowering time, a one-way ANOVA 
and a pair-wise comparison by LSD analysis were performed. 
In the year 2008, haplotypes 1, 2, and 3 were significantly 
different with regard to the respective means of days to 
flowering (P &lt;0.001), whereas haplotype 1 (163.968.7) and 
haplotype 4 (162.265.4) were not different (Fig. 5). In 2009, 
the flowering times of all haplotypes (haplotype 1, 150.769.7; 
haplotype 2, 156.9613.3; haplotype 3, 164.1611.6; and 
haplotype 4, 144.767.1) were significantly different from each 
other. The two alleles in the parents of the mapping 
population, Tapidor and Ningyou7, correspond to haplotype 
3 and haplotype 4, respectively. The difference between the 
averages of flowering time in these two groups was 12.6 d in 
2008 and 19.4 d in 2009. In addition, to estimate association 
between haplotypes and the three growth types in B. napus, the 
226 accessions represented by haplotypes 1-4 were classified as 
spring (27 accessions), semi-winter (104 accessions) or winter 
type (95 accessions; see Supplementary Table S1 at JXB 
online), and a three by four Chi square analysis was performed 
(Table 5). The results suggest that BnaA.FRI.a haplotypes are 
non-randomly distributed among the different growth types. 
Whereas the 'late-flowering' haplotype 3 occurs predominantly 
in winter accessions, the 'early-flowering' haplotype 4 is 
common among semi-winter and spring types. Finally, 
ANOVA was used again to test whether flowering time differs 
between haplotypes among the accessions of a given growth 
type (Table 6). While there was no significant effect of 
haplotype on flowering time among spring type accessions, 
which constituted the smallest group, the ANOVA indicated 
a significant effect at least in one year (2008) among semi-
winter types. Furthermore, although the means of flowering 
time were higher for each of the haplotypes in winter rapeseed 
than the respective means in the 226 accessions encompassing 
all growth types, the analysis indicated a highly significant effect 
of haplotype on flowering time among winter type accessions in 
both years. As observed for the whole panel of accessions, 
winter type accessions carrying haplotype 4 flowered earliest, 
whereas accessions with haplotype 3 flowered the latest. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In A. thaliana, FLC and FRI are key regulators of 
vernalization requirement and life cycle adaptation to </p>

<p>Table 3. Analysis of population structure: estimation of k (number 
of populations) for 95 B. napus accessions </p>

<p>k 
Ln p (D) a 
Variance </p>

<p>1 
-2519.0 
25.6 
2 
-2274.7 
92.6 
3 
-2198.2 
152.7 
4 
-2275.9 
405.2 
5 
-2204.6 
341.5 
6 
-2168.2 
376.5 
7 
-2421.2 
914.7 
8 
-2268.7 
661.4 
9 
-2401.9 
931.3 
10 
-2760.8 
1668.2 </p>

<p>a Ln p (D), Natural logarithm of the probability of data. </p>

<p>Association of BnaA.FRI.a with flowering time variation in Brassica napus | 5651 </p>

<p>climate, with allelic variation at these loci differentiating 
between summer annual and winter annual growth habits. 
While there is evidence for FLC homologues in Brassica 
species being important determinants of vernalization re-
quirement, homologues of FRI and their role in flowering </p>

<p>time regulation have not yet been described in Brassica. The 
main results of the current study are (i) the identification of 
four FRI homologues in B. napus, (ii) evidence for 
expression and differential regulation of these genes, 
(iii) the finding that BnaA.FRI.a co-localizes with a major </p>

<p>Table 4. Haplotypes and their association with flowering time in 95 B. napus accessions. </p>

<p>Only SNPs and InDels with frequencies &gt;0.1 are included. </p>

<p>Haplotype block 
Position within gene 
Haplotype 
Number of accessions 
htSNPs/InDels 
Association with 
flowering time 
(P value) b </p>

<p>99 a 
282 
348 
2008 
2009 </p>

<p>1 
-140 to 1123 
1 
44 
T 
C 
G 
0.639 
0.091 
2 
2 3 
T 
T 
T 
3 
1 5 
A 
C 
T 
1224 
1615 
1790 
2 
1224 to 2182 
1 
10 
A 
C 
A 
0.002** 
0.021* 
2 
1 3 
A 
C 
G 
3 
4 5 
T 
C 
G 
4 
2 1 
T 
T 
G </p>

<p>a The polymorphism at position 99 in haplotype block 1 is an Indel. The nucleotide 'A' corresponds to the first position 3# of the 21nt sequence 
tract which is missing in the sequence of haplotype 3. 
b *P &lt;0.05, **P &lt;0.01. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Flowering time variation among 95 (A, B) or 248 (C, D) B. napus accessions grouped according to haplotypes in BnaA.FRI.a 
haplotype block 2. The means of days to flowering in 2008 (A, C) and 2009 (B, D) are shown. Error bars indicate standard deviations. 
Capital letters indicate significant differences according to LSD multi-comparison analysis (a¼0.01). </p>



<p>QTL cluster for flowering time on chromosome A03, and 
(iv) the finding that allelic variation within BnaA.FRI.a is 
associated with natural variation for flowering time, thus 
providing independent support for a role of BnaA.FRI.a in 
flowering time control in B. napus. 
The QTL co-localizing with BnaA.FRI.a explained up to 
12% of the phenotypic variation for flowering time (Table 1) 
and thus has a somewhat intermediate effect among the 32 </p>

<p>flowering time QTL detected in the TNDH population 
(Long et al., 2007). The QTL also explains less of the 
phenotypic variation than the maximal effects of two major 
flowering time QTL in the same population that previously 
have been shown to co-localize with flowering time genes, 
i.e. a QTL on chromosome A10, which co-localizes with 
BnFLC1 and explains up to 50% of the phenotypic 
variation in a spring environment (Long et al., 2007), and </p>

<p>Table 5. Chi-square association analysis of BnaA.FRI.a haplotypes in haplotype block 2 and B. napus growth types. </p>

<p>334 Chi-square test for panel of 95 accessions </p>

<p>Hap1 a 
Hap2 
Hap3 
Hap4 
Rare haplotypes 
Total </p>

<p>Spring 
5 
0 
4 
1 
1 
11 
Semi-winter 
5 
4 
4 
20 
3 
36 
Winter 
0 
9 
37 
0 
2 
48 
Total 
10 
13 
45 
21 
6 
95 </p>

<p>Chi-square value 
P value 
Level 
df b 
Threshold 
Contingency coefficient </p>

<p>70.15 
3.82310 À11 
0.05 
6 
12.59 
0.67 </p>

<p>334 Chi-square test for panel of 248 accessions </p>

<p>Hap1 
Hap2 
Hap3 
Hap4 
Rare haplotypes 
Total </p>

<p>Spring 
8 
0 
8 
11 
3 
30 
Semi-winter 
17 
40 
17 
30 
11 
115 
Winter 
27 
14 
49 
5 
8 
103 
Total 
52 
54 
74 
46 
22 
248 </p>

<p>Chi-square value 
P value 
Level 
df 
Threshold 
Contingency coefficient </p>

<p>61.493 
2.24310 À11 
0.05 
6 
12.59 
0.46 </p>

<p>a Hap 1-Hap 2, haplotypes 1-4. 
b df, degrees of freedom. </p>

<p>Table 6. Analysis of variance of flowering time within each growth type </p>

<p>Haplotype in block 2 
Spring (n¼27) 
Semi-winter (n¼104) 
Winter (n¼95) </p>

<p>DTF6SD a 2008 
DTF6SD 2009 
DTF6SD 2008 
DTF6SD 2009 
DTF6SD 2008 
DTF6SD 2009 </p>

<p>Haplotype 1 
161.069.1 
154.266.1 
161.565.2 
143.664.0 
176.063.9 
167.264.0 
(n¼8) 
(n¼8) 
(n¼17) 
(n¼17) 
(n¼27) 
(n¼27) 
Haplotype 2 
n.a. 
n.a. 
162.263.3 
144.064.3 
177.366.6 
165.9610.9 
(n¼0) 
(n¼0) 
(n¼40) 
(n¼40) 
(n¼14) 
(n¼14) 
Haplotype 3 
161.3610.2 
153.169.2 
165.065.4 
146.468.0 
180.365.2 
170.765.9 
(n¼8) 
(n¼8) 
(n¼17) 
(n¼17) 
(n¼49) 
(n¼49) 
Haplotype 4 
160.166.3 
149.567.5 
160.763.7 
142.263.6 
174.064.8 
158.6614.0 
(n¼11) 
(n¼11) 
(n¼30) 
(n¼30) 
(n¼5) 
(n¼5) 
Degrees of freedom 
3 
3 
4 
4 
4 
4 
P value 
0.9505 
0.3857 
0.0117* c 
0.0556 
0.0013** 
0.0009** 
LSD b 
Hap1-Hap2 
Hap1-Hap2 
Hap1-Hap2 
Hap1-Hap3** 
Hap1-Hap3** 
Hap1-Hap3** 
Hap1-Hap4 
Hap1-Hap4 
Hap1-Hap4** 
Hap2-Hap3** 
Hap2-Hap3 
Hap2-Hap3** 
Hap2-Hap4 
Hap2-Hap4 
Hap2-Hap4** 
Hap3-Hap4** 
Hap3-Hap4** 
Hap3-Hap4** </p>

<p>a Days to flowering 6standard deviation. 
b Fisher's Least Significant Difference analysis. 
c *P &lt;0.05, **P &lt;0.01. </p>

<p>Association of BnaA.FRI.a with flowering time variation in Brassica napus | 5653 </p>

<p>a QTL on chromosome C06 which colocalizes with two FT 
homologues (BnC6.FTa and BnC6.FTb) and explains up to 
52% of the phenotypic variation in winter environments 
(Long et al., 2007; Wang et al., 2009). The fact that 
cultivation over winter (and thus vernalization) abolishes 
the effect of allelic variation at the QTL co-localizing with 
BnFLC1 (Osborn et al., 1997; Long et al., 2007) suggests 
that BnFLC1 is involved in the regulation of vernalization 
requirement, similar to the role of FLC in A. thaliana. 
Interestingly, in contrast to BnFLC1, BnaA.FRI.a was 
found to co-localize with a QTL which occurs in both 
spring and winter environments and at comparable maxi-
mal LOD (8.5 and 9.4, respectively) and R 2 values (8.1% 
and 12.0%, respectively; Table 1). This suggests that 
BnaA.FRI.a regulates flowering time both with and without 
prior vernalization and is consistent with our observation 
that BnaA.FRI.a is expressed both in non-vernalized and in 
vernalized plants. Similarly, allelic variation of FRI in 
A. thaliana is not only associated with variation in flowering 
time of non-vernalized plants, with loss-of-function muta-
tions accelerating flowering (in accessions from Northern 
latitudes; Stinchcombe et al., 2004), but also affects flower-
ing time after vernalization (Caicedo et al., 2004; Stinch-
combe et al., 2004; Le Corre, 2005). The co-localization at 
the BnaA.FRI.a locus of QTL in both spring and winter 
environments also distinguishes this locus from the QTL co-
localizing with BnC6.FT.a/b, which only occurs in winter 
environments and thus may contribute to the regulation of 
flowering time in response to vernalization, but in apparent 
contrast to BnFLC1 and BnaA.FRI.a, may not control the 
vernalization requirement. The map position of BnaA.FRI.a 
on chromosome A03 precludes the possibility of co-
localization with the vernalization-responsive flowering time 
QTL VFN1 on linkage group N2 (Osborn et al., 1997; 
Osborn and Lukens, 2003), whereas BnaA.FRI.a cannot be 
ruled out as a candidate gene for VFN3 on linkage group 
N3 (Osborn et al., 1997; Butruille et al., 1999). The presence 
of FLC homologues on this linkage group and previous 
QTL co-localization studies in B. rapa and B. napus suggest 
that, besides BnaA.FRI.a, FLC homologues may also 
contribute to QTL effects on chromosome A03 (Schranz 
et al., 2002; Osborn and Lukens, 2003; Udall et al., 2006). 
With regard to a role of BnaA.FRI.a in the regulation of 
vernalization requirement, it is interesting to note that 
43 DH lines did not flower under spring cultivation 
conditions in both years, possibly due to insufficient 
exposure to cold temperatures. Of the 42 of these lines 
which were genotyped at both the BnaA.FRI.a locus (this 
study) and the BnFLC1 locus (Long et al., 2007), all carried 
at least one allele derived from the winter type parent 
Tapidor at either of these loci, and the majority (32/42) of 
the non-flowering lines carried the Tapidor alleles at both 
loci (data not shown; see Supplementary Table S4 at JXB 
online). Among 30 additional DH lines which did not 
flower in one year, all except two carried the Tapidor allele 
at least at one of the two loci, and 11 carried the Tapidor 
alleles at both loci. Among the remaining 17 lines which 
carry the Tapidor allele only at one locus, only two carry </p>

<p>the Tapidor allele at the BnFLC1 locus, whereas 15 carry 
the Tapidor allele only at the BnaA.FRI.a locus. Further-
more, the distribution of Tapidor and Ningyou7 alleles at 
the BnaA.FRI.a locus among the non-flowering plants of 
the TNDH population differs significantly from random 
(see Supplementary Table S4 at JXB online). These data are 
consistent with a role for BnaA.FRI.a in the regulation of 
vernalization requirement in rapeseed, and tend to suggest 
further that the winter type alleles at both loci may act 
together to increase the vernalization requirement. 
The data obtained with the structured population are 
supported by our association analysis with a worldwide 
panel of accessions encompassing winter, semi-winter, and 
spring type rapeseed. Time to flowering varied substantially 
and ranged from 144 to 192 d in 2008 and from 137 to 182 
d in 2009. In the earliest flowering haplotype group 
(haplotype 4) compared with the latest flowering haplotype 
group (haplotype 3) the number of days to flowering was 
reduced by 12.6 (in 2008) and 19.4 (in 2009), respectively. 
Taking population structure into account, flowering time 
variation was significantly associated with haplotype varia-
tion in both years. Evidence for population structure was 
obtained by genotypic analysis using SSR markers. Selec-
tion for different growth habits of oilseed rape in different 
geographical environments may contribute to population 
structure, and growth habit is generally thought to affect 
flowering time strongly. In particular, winter type rapeseed 
generally flowers late, whereas spring and semi-winter type 
rapeseed flower early in the field, which is consistent with 
our own data (see Supplementary Table S1 at JXB online). 
Consistent with these observations, haplotype variation of 
BnaA.FRI.a is not only associated with flowering time 
variation, but the different haplotypes are also non-
randomly distributed among the three growth habits 
(Table 5). Because the non-parametric test applied does not 
control for population structure, it is possible that popula-
tion structure contributes to the observed non-random 
distribution. However, as discussed above with regard to 
the QTL co-localization data, BnaA.FRI.a may indeed 
contribute to differential regulation of vernalization re-
quirement and thus the differentiation between growth 
types. Finally, our finding that haplotype variation corre-
lates with flowering time variation not only among all the 
accessions analysed but also among the accessions of a given 
growth type, at least for the winter type accessions (Table 6), 
further supports the notion that BnaA.FRI.a has dual, 
though possibly overlapping, roles in the regulation of 
vernalization requirement and flowering time. 
Consistent with the phase relationships in the QTL 
population, the BnaA.FRI.a allele in the parental accession 
Ningyou7 corresponds to the earliest flowering haplotype 4, 
whereas the Tapidor allele corresponds to the latest flower-
ing haplotype 3. Although there are several non-
synonymous SNPs within haplotype block 2, including the 
htSNP at position 1790 which shows a SNP-trait associa-
tion in one year (P¼0.017 in 2008; Table 2) and could 
possibly affect protein function, the protein sequence in this 
region is identical between the two extreme haplotypes 3 </p>



<p>and 4. However, the two haplotypes differ at two positions 
at the nucleotide sequence level, i.e. the htSNP at position 
1615 and the SNP at position 1702, which are both located 
within the coding sequence. In addition to the SNPs 
observed between haplotypes 3 and 4, the two alleles in the 
TNDH population carry multiple additional polymor-
phisms, including several SNPs and a 3 bp indel in the 
promoter region, two indels in the 5# UTR and six non-
synonymous SNPs in exon 1 (see Supplementary Fig. S1 at 
JXB online). Among the six non-synonymous SNPs, two 
are located within the Frigida domain, but not at positions 
which are conserved among FRI family I proteins in 
A. thaliana and other rosid species (Risk et al., 2010), and 
two are located in the non-conserved region between the 
Frigida domain and the N-terminal putative coiled-coil 
domain. The remaining two non-synonymous SNPs are 
located within the N-terminal putative coiled-coil domain. 
One of these SNPs (SNP254) results in the substitution of 
a charged residue (glutamate) by an uncharged amino acid 
(glycine). Charged residues are present at high percentages 
in coiled-coil domains and are thought to stabilize the 
domain through electrostatic interactions (McFarlane et al., 
2009). Interestingly, a glutamate to glycine substitution in 
the winter type allele in Tapidor (in an otherwise un-
changed, theoretical molecule) would reduce the probability 
of a coiled-coil domain in the N-terminal region from 
;50% to &lt;5%, and the probability of a coiled-coil domain 
in the semi-winter type allele in Ningyou7 is also low 
(&lt;10%; predictions according to COILS for a window size 
of 28 residues; http://www.ch.embnet.org/software/coils/ 
COILS_doc.html; data not shown). The glutamate residue 
is conserved between A. thaliana and the Tapidor allele and 
corresponds to the position with the most significant 
P value for SNP-trait association within the entire gene 
(0.005 in 2009; Table 2). Furthermore, it was recently 
demonstrated that the N-terminal region including the 
coiled-coil domain of FRI in A. thaliana is required for 
protein-protein interaction with FRL1 as part of a tran-
scriptional activator complex which establishes an active 
chromatin state of FLC (Choi et al., 2011). It is conceivable 
that the polymorphism within the N-terminal coiled-coil 
domain in BnaA.FRI.a contributes to functional differences 
between the segregating alleles in the TNDH population 
and may also play a part in natural variation at least in 
some environments. 
The relatively high number of polymorphisms in exon 1 
compared with the number of SNPs in exons 2 and 3, which 
together are of comparable size to exon 1, between the 
parents of the mapping population as well as in our panel of 
natural accessions (Table 2) is consistent with data for A. 
thaliana, which indicate that exon 1 is hypervariable and 
may be under different selection constraints than exons 2 
and 3 (Le Corre et al., 2002). Interestingly, these regions 
largely coincide with the two haplotype blocks that were 
identified in BnaA.FRI.a, with one including exon 1 and the 
other including exons 2 and 3. The notion of a hypervariable 
region and the existence of two haplotype blocks in 
BnaA.FRI.a is consistent with the observed rapid decay of </p>

<p>LD within this gene. Furthermore, the recent data from 
Arabidopsis (Risk et al., 2010; Choi et al., 2011) suggest that 
N-terminal and C-terminal regions of FRI differentially 
affect protein function and are involved in different pro-
tein-protein interactions which could, at least partially, 
explain why different parts of the gene appear to be subject 
to different evolutionary forces. Conceivably, functional 
heterogeneity may also account for differences between 
haplotype blocks 1 and 2 as well as between SNPs in the 
corresponding regions of the gene in regard to statistical 
significance of their association with flowering time in the 
two growth seasons investigated (Tables 2, 4). The average 
winter temperatures differed substantially between the 
growth seasons, with temperatures in the winter 2008/2009 
(average temperature 7 °C) being two degrees colder, on 
average, than in 2007/2008, and a low temperature of -1 °C 
in 2008/2009 and +2 °C in 2007/2008 (temperature data 
provided by the Chongqing city government). These obser-
vations may suggest that temperature differences of a few 
degrees between years differentially affect the functionality 
of the N-terminal part (represented by haplotype block 1) 
and the C-terminal part of the gene (represented by 
haplotype block 2). Genotype3environment interactions 
are indeed apparent when comparing the flowering time 
data for both growth seasons. While the winter type 
accessions always flowered latest, as expected, semi-winter 
types flowered slightly later than spring types in 2008, but 
earlier in 2009 (see Supplementary Table S1 at JXB online). 
Although both spring and semi-winter types (as well as 
winter types) flowered earlier in 2009 than in 2008, the 
promotive effect of a decrease in temperature in the semi-
winter environments under study appears to be strongest in 
semi-winter types. It is tempting to speculate that BnaA. 
FRI.a is involved in the fine-tuning of vernalization re-
quirement and response, and that this may be achieved at 
the molecular level by differential interaction of the N-and/ 
or C-terminal regions of the protein with other components 
of a transcriptional activator complex. The SNPs at 
positions 254 and 1790, which are located in the respective 
N-(Choi et al., 2011) or C-terminal regions (Risk et al., 
2010), could thus be candidate sites for functional analyses, 
for example, through site-directed mutagenesis and for the 
development of functional markers for flowering time in 
rapeseed. 
Previous studies in Arabidopsis have focused mainly on 
phenotypic differences between functional and loss-
of-function alleles of FRI, whereas, to our knowledge, there 
is little known about phenotypic variation within popula-
tions or between accessions with different functional alleles. 
Several lines of evidence suggest that the winter type alleles 
(represented by the identical alleles in Express and Tapidor) 
and the semi-winter type allele (in Ningyou7) analysed in 
the current study are functional orthologues of FRI. First, 
BnaA.FRI.a contains an uninterrupted open reading frame, 
a conserved central Frigida domain, and the nine residues 
within an N-terminal sequence tract which are characteristic 
of the members of the FRI family I (Risk et al., 2010). 
Second, the gene is expressed and differentially regulated, </p>

<p>Association of BnaA.FRI.a with flowering time variation in Brassica napus | 5655 </p>

<p>with the spatial expression profiles being similar for both 
the winter and semi-winter type alleles. Interestingly how-
ever, while FRI in Arabidopsis is ubiquitously expressed and 
the levels of expression are similar in leaves and flowers 
(Risk et al., 2010), our data suggest elevated expression in 
floral buds and flowers. The two observations differentiate 
both the winter and semi-winter type alleles from the 
majority of mutant alleles or sequence variants which have 
been correlated with phenotypic effects in Arabidopsis, and 
comprise mainly frameshift mutations or deletion alleles 
including a promoter deletion which abolishes FRI expres-
sion (Johanson et al., 2000; Le Corre et al., 2002; Gazzani 
et al., 2003; Shindo et al., 2005). By comparison with the 
data for Arabidopsis, the fact that the winter type rapeseed 
accessions have a strong vernalization requirement (Qiu 
et al., 2006; Long et al., 2007), together with our QTL co-
localization data for BnaA.FRI.a, suggest that, at least, the 
winter type parental accession carries a functional BnaA. 
FRI.a allele. Although our finding that the BnaA.FRI.a 
locus co-localizes with a QTL indicates that the two alleles 
differ in their functionality, it is conceivable that the 
Ningyou7 allele is not a complete loss-of-function allele but 
retains at least part of its function. A relatively weak activity 
could contribute to confer the low vernalization requirement 
generally found in semi-winter rapeseed accessions, and may 
provide a selective advantage in regions with mild winters. 
The contribution of the additional three members of the FRI 
family I in B. napus, which were identified in the present 
study and also all contain uninterrupted open reading frames 
and are expressed, to the regulation of flowering time and/or 
vernalization requirement remains to be determined. Among 
these three genes, BnaX.FRI.d shares the highest degree of 
homology to BnaA.FRI.a (89% amino acid identity) and is 
most similar to BnaA.FRI.a with regard to sequence features 
and spatial expression profiles, and thus may be the closest 
functional relative. 
Association mapping has become increasingly important to 
analyse quantitative traits in crop plants, and can involve 
candidate gene and genome-wide approaches. As the cost of 
genome-wide genotyping is high, candidate gene analysis is 
often more suitable for crops where complete sequence 
information is not yet available. In contrast to linkage 
mapping approaches which focus on trait variation resulting 
from allelic differences between the two parents of a segregat-
ing population and generally have relatively low resolution 
(10-20 cM), association mapping has a high resolution 
(sometimes at the level of or even within single genes) but 
can also identify spurious associations (Nordborg and 
Weigel, 2008). In the current study, the results from linkage 
and association mapping are highly consistent with each 
other, thus demonstrating the high potential of combining 
these two types of quantitative research techniques to assess 
the contribution of a gene to phenotypic variation. 
Flowering time is a quantitative trait that is crucial for an 
appropriate timing of reproduction so as to obtain a high seed 
or biomass yield, as has been demonstrated for A. thaliana, 
rice, and maize (Izawa, 2007; Buckler et al., 2009). Moreover, 
flowering time control can prevent plants from suffering from </p>

<p>adverse growth conditions as they occur during drought, frost, 
or in the presence of pests (Blum, 1996; Jung and , 
2009). An understanding of the molecular basis of flowering 
time variation offers the possibility of direct selection for 
favourable alleles. One example is gene introgression from 
non-adapted varieties such as Chinese semi-winter types into 
European rapeseed material to increase heterosis (Qian et al., 
2007). The SNPs and haplotypes in BnaA.FRI.a which 
showed significant association with flowering time variation 
could be used as functional markers to assist in the breeding 
of cultivars with different growth habits and flowering times. 
In addition, other studies have reported other genes which 
affect flowering time in B. napus and can be used as functional 
markers, such as CO, FLC, and FT homologues (Robert 
et al., 1998; Tadege et al., 2001; Wang et al., 2009). The 
combination of these markers with those discovered in the 
present study is expected to facilitate the selection of oilseed 
rape breeding material with distinct flowering times to help 
improve adaptation to specific local environments or changing 
climatic conditions. </p>

<p>Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data can be found at JXB online. 
Supplementary Fig. S1. Sequence alignment of the winter 
type allele in Tapidor and the semi-winter type allele in 
Ningyou7 at the nucleotide (A) and amino acid sequence 
level (B). 
Supplementary Fig. S2. Multiple sequence alignment of 
BnaA.FRI.a nucleotide (A) and amino acid (B) sequences of 
the four haplotypes in block 2. 
Supplementary Table S1. Phenotypic and genotypic data 
for 248 B. napus accessions. 
Supplementary Table S2. Primer sequences. 
Supplementary Table S3. SSR primers used for evaluating 
population structure. 
Supplementary Table S4. Distribution of BnFLC1 and 
BnaA.FRI.a alleles among non-flowering plants of the 
TNDH population. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The project was funded by the Deutsche Forschungsge-
meinschaft (grant no. DFG JU 205/14-1) and the National 
Natural Science Foundation of China (project code 
30900788). The authors wish to thank Verena Kowalewski 
and Cay Kruse for excellent technical assistance. The 
Institute of Clinical Molecular Biology, University Kiel, 
Germany is acknowledged for performing the complete 
Sanger-based sequence analyses of the study. </p>









</text></tei>