<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3199877" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Background: Although cognitive decline is a common finding among the elderly and is consid-
ered a risk factor for developing dementia, it is rarely diagnosed by general practitioners (GPs). 
Aim: To evaluate cognitive function with the Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) and the 
Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) in asymptomatic subjects in daily GP practice and com-
pare subjects who confirmed having cognitive problems with subjects who did not. Methods: 
388 consecutive subjects 1 65 years of age who consulted their GP were interviewed and tested 
with MMSE and MoCA. Results: None of the study subjects spontaneously complained of cog-
nitive or memory problems. 155 subjects (39.94%) confirmed having cognitive problems and 
233 (60.05%) did not even when asked. The prevalence of mild cognitive impairment (MCI) was 
18.30% (95% CI 14.36-22.04) and the prevalence of cognitive impairment/no dementia (CIND) 
was 17.27% (95% CI 13.50-21.04). Delayed memory recall as a separate cognitive domain in 
MoCA was significantly worse in subjects with MCI (p = 0.00958) and in those with CIND (p = 
0.0208). Conclusion: There is a significant number of patients in daily GP practices with unrec-
ognized, but objectively verifiable, cognitive deficits who do not report having cognitive prob-
lems. They can be identified by assessment with MMSE and MoCA already in the GP practice. </p>

<p>Severity of cognitive deficit varies significantly in the elderly, and numerous attempts 
have been made to classify the boundaries between normal and pathological aging [1] . The 
following two concepts have most frequently been used in the literature: (1) The concept of 
mild cognitive impairment (MCI) describes a heterogeneous condition with cognitive char-
acteristics between normal aging and dementia [1-3] . MCI is currently defined as a syn-
drome with memory impairment or other cognitive deficits that does not interfere substan-
tially with personal affairs nor result in inability to live independently [4] . (2) 'Cognitive 
impairment/no dementia' (CIND) is a classification term that has been used in population-
based epidemiological studies to capture a broad range of these milder forms of impairment 
in cognition [4, 5] . By definition, CIND permits the inclusion of all individuals whose cogni-
tive performance is below average but who do not meet dementia criteria within a diagnostic 
category [4, 5] . CIND does not require any specific domain(s) of cognitive impairment [4, 5] . 
It can also be applied to patients seeking assessment of their cognitive difficulties in clinical 
settings. However, the breadth of this categorization implies a significant heterogeneity of its 
clinical, behavioral, and neuropsychological features [6, 7] . 
Patients or caregivers usually wait and only report a cognitive complaint to a profes-
sional when the symptoms are already obvious and advanced. In that light, one would expect 
especially patients satisfying the criteria for MCI or CIND rarely to complain of their deficits. 
In general, cognitive impairment frequently remains unrecognized even by medical person-
nel [5] . There are estimations that only 25% of patients with MCI or Alzheimer's disease are 
recognized in the general practice [6] . It has been established that screening with formalized 
screening tests is superior to general clinical judgment [7] . 
General practitioners (GPs) are the professionals with the most detailed insight into their 
patients' daily activities; they are able to evaluate patients' complaints and may inquire about 
certain complaints if appropriate. Their central position in health care enables them to col-
lect additional information regarding cognitive decline compared to a previous cognitive 
level and to detect loss of competence. They should be the first person informed on any psy-
chological illness and are thus able to initiate and implement cognitive evaluation from a 
comprehensive biopsychosocial point of view [8] . 
To our knowledge, this is the first study which evaluates cognitive impairment and its 
prevalence with two brief global cognitive tests -the Mini-Mental State Examination 
(MMSE) and the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) -in the daily routine of a GP 
[9-14] . The aim of the study was to evaluate cognitive function with the MMSE and the 
MoCA in asymptomatic subjects in the daily GP practice and compare subjects who con-
firmed having cognitive problems with subjects who did not. </p>

<p>Subjects and Methods </p>

<p>This cross-sectional study included a random sample of 388 consecutive subjects 1 65 
years of age who consulted their GPs in their practice. It is part of a longitudinal epidemio-
logical study in Zagreb, Croatia, aimed to evaluate the early clinical manifestations of de-
mentia in primary care. The approval of the ethical committees has been obtained at the 
health care institutions where the study was implemented. The study was performed accord-
ing to the institutional guidelines and the principles outlined in the Declaration of Helsinki 
[15] . Written informed consent was obtained from all the study subjects. 
Patients with medical documentation confirming dementia or psychosis, deafness or 
blindness, or those who refused to participate were excluded. The study was performed by 4 </p>



<p>Dement Geriatr Cogn Disord Extra 2011;1:93-102 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000327076 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Hanzevacki et al.: Detecting Cognitive Decline in the Elderly </p>

<p>www.karger.com/dee </p>

<p>© 2011 S. Karger AG, Basel 
Published online: April 8, 2011 </p>

<p>trained GPs in 4 independent GP practices from June 1 to October 31, 2010. Included GP 
practices covered the total population of 7,850 people in the Zagreb area. 
Nurses in each of the practices informed the patients briefly about the study upon ar-
rival at the GP practice. The physician completed the regular visit and immediately after that 
asked for informed consent and completed the MMSE and MoCA standard questionnaires 
[16, 17] . The time needed to complete each questionnaire was recorded. Then, patients were 
asked two questions: (1) Did you observe any problems with your memory or any other cog-
nitive function lately? (2) How do you perceive your general health status during the last 4 
weeks? For the second question, one of the following options could be chosen: much worse, 
worse, no change, better, and much better. Age, sex, years of education and presence or ab-
sence of depression or other psychiatric disorders were recorded. 
Patients who confirmed having problems with memory or other cognitive functions and 
who had an MMSE score 1 24 and an MoCA score ! 26 were diagnosed as having MCI [18, 
19] . CIND was diagnosed based on the results of the MMSE [20] . Patients with results ! 1 SD 
below the mean adjusted for age and education were classified as having CIND. Those with 
MMSE scores ^ 19 were excluded since they were very likely to have dementia. 
We used the MMSE despite a known lack of sensitivity, which is in some studies as low 
as 18%, but it was the appropriate instrument for our study due to its specificity of 100% in 
detecting general cognitive decline, its efficacy in a GP practice setting, and the fact that it 
is still the most widely used cognitive screening instrument [9, 21] . 
Based on published results obtained with the MoCA test [10, 22] designed to measure 
visuospatial/executive function, naming, memory, attention, language, abstraction, delayed 
recall, and orientation with 90% sensitivity and 87% specificity, we used it as an additional 
test in order to assure sensitivity in detecting subjects with very mild cognitive deficit [10] . 
MoCA cutoff scores in Croatia proved to be equivalent to western European countries [17] . 
Basic demographic characteristics of study subjects are presented in table 1 . </p>

<p>Statistics 
For assessment of qualitative variables we used the 2 test with Yates corrections for the 
2 ! 2 contingency tables. Correlation for quantitative data was assessed with Pearson's cor-</p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic characteristics of subjects included into the study stratified according to cognitive 
impairment on MoCA, on MMSE, on MoCA and MMSE, and no impairment </p>

<p>MoCA 
MMSE 
MoCA/ 
MMSE </p>

<p>No 
impairment </p>

<p>Total study 
sample </p>

<p>Subjects, n 
316* 
153* 
150 
67 
388 
Sex 
Male 
120 
58 
57 
29 
151 
Female 
196 
95 
93 
38 
237 
Age 
65-74 years 
125 
71 
68 
27 
153 
75-84 years 
132 
49 
46 
23 
168 
≥85 years 
59 
33 
36 
17 
67 
Self-perception of cognitive problems 
Confirming cognitive problems 
121 
59 
58 
31 
155 
Not confirming cognitive problems 195 
94 
92 
36 
233 </p>

<p>* The number of patients identified as cognitively impaired on MoCA and MMSE was significantly 
different. McNemar 
2 = 29.49309; d.f. = 1; p &lt; 0.0001. </p>



<p>Dement Geriatr Cogn Disord Extra 2011;1:93-102 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000327076 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Hanzevacki et al.: Detecting Cognitive Decline in the Elderly </p>

<p>www.karger.com/dee </p>

<p>© 2011 S. Karger AG, Basel 
Published online: April 8, 2011 </p>

<p>relation. Differences between average quantitative variables were analyzed with Student's t 
test. MMSE and MoCA results were compared with the McNemar test. The calculations were 
performed by the commercially available software <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistica</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">6.0</rs>. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>There were 237 women (61.08%) and 151 men (38.92%) included in the study. None of 
them spontaneously mentioned any memory or other cognitive problems. Among them, 155 
subjects (39.94%) confirmed having cognitive problems and 233 (60.05%) did not when asked 
by a physician ( table 2 ). Women confirmed cognitive problems statistically more often than 
men. Among those who confirmed cognitive problems, 104 (66.23%) were women and 51 
(33.77%) men (p = 0.04751). 
Mean MMSE score 8 SD was 25 8 2.39 and mean MoCA score 8 SD was 23 8 2.46. 
On MMSE, 34.20% of subjects who confirmed having a cognitive problem and 34.14% of 
those who did not scored above the median. On MoCA, 41.94% of subjects who confirmed 
having a cognitive problem and 33.90% of those who did not scored above the median. There 
was no significant difference in MMSE and MoCA scores between those confirming a defi-
cit and those who did not confirm a memory or cognitive problem [MMSE score (mean 8 
SD): confirming 24.40 8 2.39 vs. not confirming 24.53 8 2.39; MoCA score (mean 8 SD): 
confirming 22.65 8 2.68 vs. not confirming 22.47 8 2.31; table 2 ]. Subjects who confirmed 
cognitive problems more frequently rated their general health as declining during the past 4 
weeks, and those who did not confirm cognitive problems rated their general health as re-
cently unchanged. The difference was significant (p ! 0.0001). 
Cognitive impairment according to the MMSE and MoCA questionnaires was recog-
nized in 150 subjects [93 (62.00%) female, 57 (38.00%) male]. 153 subjects [95 (62.09%) fe-
male, 58 (37.91%) male] were cognitively impaired according to MMSE, and 316 patients [196 
(62.03%) female, 120 (37.97%) male] were cognitively impaired according to MoCA. The dif-
ference between the results on MMSE and MoCA was statistically significant (McNemar </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparison of patients who confirmed having cognitive deficits when asked 
and patients who did not </p>

<p>Confirming 
Not confirming </p>

<p>Sex 
Male 
51* 
100 
Female 
104* 
133 
Cognitive status** 
Impaired on MoCA 
121 
195 
MoCA score 
22.6582.68 
22.4782.31 
Impaired on MMSE 
59 
94 
MMSE score 
24.4082.39 
24.5382.39 
Impaired on MoCA and MMSE 
58 
92 
No impairment 
31 
36 
Total 
155 
233 </p>

<p>V alues are numbers or mean 8 SD. * Among patients confirming cognitive defi-
cits, there were significantly more women (Pearson's 
2 =3.927497; d.f. = 1; p = 
0.04751). ** Scores on MoCA and MMSE were not significantly different between 
subjects confirming and subjects not confirming cognitive or memory problems. </p>



<p>Dement Geriatr Cogn Disord Extra 2011;1:93-102 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000327076 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Hanzevacki et al.: Detecting Cognitive Decline in the Elderly </p>

<p>www.karger.com/dee </p>

<p>© 2011 S. Karger AG, Basel 
Published online: April 8, 2011 </p>

<p>
2 = 29.49309; d.f. = 1; p ! 0.0001; table 1 ). There were 163 subjects (42.01%) who were diag-
nosed as cognitively impaired by MoCA, but not by MMSE. Only 3 patients were classified 
as cognitively impaired by MMSE and not by MoCA. 319 patients (82.22%) proved to be cog-
nitively impaired on both MMSE and MoCA, and 69 patients (17.78%) were diagnosed as 
being cognitively without deficit on both tests. 
The prevalence of MCI was 18.30% (95% CI 14.36-22.04) or 71 subjects. Among them, 
47 (66.18%) were women and 24 (33.82%) men. The difference between sexes was significant 
(p = 0.019; table 3 ). The prevalence of CIND was 17.27% (95% CI 13.50-21.04) or 67 subjects. 
Among them, 38 (56.72%) were women and 29 (43.28%) men (the difference was not signifi-
cant; table 3 ). Delayed memory recall analyzed as a separate cognitive domain on MoCA was 
significantly worse in subjects with MCI (p = 0.00958) and in those with CIND (p = 0.0208; 
fig. 1 ). All subjects who were diagnosed as having MCI did not have CIND, and all subjects 
diagnosed as having CIND did not have MCI. Among CIND subjects, 28 (48.18%) confirmed 
having a cognitive or memory problem. Female CIND subjects admitted cognitive problems 
significantly more often than male CIND subjects [21/40 (52.50%) women vs. 5/28 (17.86%) 
men; p = 0.00382]. 
Subjects who confirmed cognitive deficits scored significantly better on orientation to 
time. The highest score (5) was achieved by 107/155 subjects (69.03%) who confirmed versus 
132/233 subjects (56.65%) who did not confirm cognitive deficits. The lowest recorded score 
(3) was reached by 3/155 subjects (1.94%) who confirmed versus 27/233 subjects (11.59%) who 
did not confirm cognitive deficits (p = 0.00103). In orientation to space, all subjects scored 
either 4 or 5 among 5 possible scores. Significantly more subjects confirming cognitive prob-
lems scored 5 [117/155 (75.48%) vs. 139/233 (59.66%); p = 0.00127]. In the clock-drawing test, 
possible scores were 0, 1, 2, or 3. Those confirming cognitive problems scored 3 significant-
ly more often [96/155 (61.94%) vs. 90/233 (38.63%)]. Those not confirming cognitive prob-
lems scored either 1 or 2 significantly more often [143/233 (61.37%) vs. 59/155 (38.06%); p = 
0.00002]. In serial discounting, possible scores were 0, 1, 2, or 3. Those confirming cognitive 
problems scored 3 significantly more often [110/155 (70.97%) vs. 135/233 (57.94%)]. Those 
who did not confirm cognitive problems scored 1 or 2 significantly more often [98/233 
(42.06%) vs. 45/155 (29.03%); p = 0.03357]. 
In contrast, those who did not confirm cognitive problems scored significantly better on 
delayed memory recall and on writing a sentence. In delayed memory recall, possible scores 
were 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, or 5. Those who did not confirm having cognitive problems more frequent-
ly scored 3, 4, or 5 [199/233 (85.41%) vs. 75/155 (48.39%)]. Those who did confirm cognitive 
problems had significantly more often scores 1 or 2 [80/155 (51.61%) vs. 34/233 (14.50%); p ! 
0.000001]. For writing a sentence, possible scores were 0 or 1. Those who did not confirm 
cognitive problems scored significantly more often 1 [177/233 (75.97%) vs. 102/155 (65.81%)]. </p>

<p>Table 3. Key characteristics of the subjects classified as having MCI or CIND, and total sample </p>

<p>MCI 
CIND 
Total sample </p>

<p>MMSE score, mean 8 SD 
25.9481.03 
21.0281.48 
24.4882.39 
MoCA score, mean 8 SD 
23.0881.47 
20.0782.58 
22.5482.46 
Subjects, n 
71 
67 
388 
Age, years 
75.2187.00 
76.1187.64 
75.1287.19 
Sex, female/male 
47/24 
38/29 
237/151 
Self-perception: subjects confirming cognitive 
problems, % 
100 
44.07 
40.20 </p>



<p>Dement Geriatr Cogn Disord Extra 2011;1:93-102 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000327076 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Hanzevacki et al.: Detecting Cognitive Decline in the Elderly </p>

<p>www.karger.com/dee </p>

<p>© 2011 S. Karger AG, Basel 
Published online: April 8, 2011 </p>

<p>Those who confirmed cognitive problems scored significantly more often 0 [53/155 (34.19%) 
vs. 56/233 (24.03%); p = 0.02920]. 
Older subjects scored worse on MMSE with r = -0.1509 and p = 0.003 ( fig. 2 ). We did 
not observe any significant correlation with duration of education. Average time needed for 
MMSE completion as a separate part of the visit was 7 min 23 s (7.44 8 2.59 min) and for 
MoCA 10 min 6 s (10.10 8 2.50 min). </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Correlation between the results scored on MMSE and age. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Scores on delayed memory recall in subjects with different cognitive status [total sample, MCI, 
CIND, and subjects with no detectable cognitive deficit (normal)]. * Subjects with MCI had significantly 
worse results than all other groups (Pearson's 
2 test = 11.43724; d.f. = 3; p = 0.00958. * * CIND subjects 
had significantly worse results than subjects without CIND (Pearson's 
2 test = 11.57726; d.f. = 4; p = 
0.02079). Delayed recall was evaluated as part of the MoCA test. </p>



<p>Dement Geriatr Cogn Disord Extra 2011;1:93-102 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000327076 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Hanzevacki et al.: Detecting Cognitive Decline in the Elderly </p>

<p>www.karger.com/dee </p>

<p>© 2011 S. Karger AG, Basel 
Published online: April 8, 2011 </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The individual's subjective evaluation of his/her own memory and cognitive function 
may not reflect actual functional capabilities and, consequently, performance on objective 
testing [23, 24] . Inaccurate self-perception may indicate a lack of awareness of changes in 
cognitive function or may be connected with difficulties with memory [24-27] . 
In our results, there was no difference in average scores on brief global cognitive tests 
between those subjects who confirmed and those who did not confirm cognitive deficits, 
which is in accordance with findings by Luck et al. [14] . We separately analyzed cognitive 
functions within the MMSE and MoCA and found only delayed memory recall significant-
ly worse in MCI and CIND subjects. This is in accordance with other authors [27, 28] . Worse 
memory function could play a role in patients' perception of actual cognitive status. 
One can speculate that when a person's delayed memory recall is impaired, he/she will 
probably assume that cognitive function as a whole is impaired, still assuming that the 
awareness of memory deficit is preserved. Similar to delayed memory recall, subjects who 
confirmed having a cognitive problem reported a significantly lower score for their general 
health status during the preceding 4 weeks. It is difficult to decide whether this general ob-
servation concerning health influences the self-perception of a person's cognition or wheth-
er, on the other hand, persons with really impaired cognitive function judge their general 
health as impaired. 
It is possible that memory complaints or perceived decline in cognitive function in old 
age are not solely determined by actual cognitive ability but also by other variables, such as 
personality traits, personal and psychological well-being, and subjective health [29-31] . The 
influence of cognitive functions, such as memory-related cognitive domains, attention, 
working memory, and information processing speed, probably exists but has not been ex-
plained [32] . There is ample evidence that slower information processing due to aging can 
cause slower rehearsal and impoverishment of information, resulting in a poorer memory 
performance [33, 34] . In that light, we also observe a discrepancy in our results since less than 
half of the subjects characterized as having CIND confirmed a cognitive deficit. The mean 
MMSE score of these subjects was almost 5 points lower than the score of those diagnosed 
as having MCI (who confirmed having a cognitive problem even as a diagnostic criteria), 
suggesting that worse cognitive function might be an explanation for worse self-perception 
of cognitive function. 
In order to achieve an early detection of cognitive problems, it would be important to 
benefit from the fact that persons with an increased risk or even early signs of dementia are 
frequently present at the GP practice with some other medical problem not explicitly related 
to memory or cognition. A GP thoroughly examining a patient from a biopsychosocial point 
of view will most probably evaluate the patient's complaint or absence of complaint in the 
right way and initiate further workup if necessary [9] . 
Among all subjects confirming a cognitive problem we found significantly more women. 
This was evident also in the subgroups characterized as having MCI or CIND. This finding 
correlates with the PAQUID study in 1994 [35] . It is also in agreement with data by Aposto-
lova and Cummings [36] on the most frequent neuropsychiatric symptoms associated with 
MCI, i.e. depression, apathy, and anxiety, which is known to be more frequent among wom-
en [36-38] . However, Luck et al. [14] discovered the opposite in GP patients: significantly 
more male subjects complained about cognitive problems. In the same study, a significantly 
higher prevalence of MCI was observed among female patients when subjective complaint 
was not part of the diagnostic criteria for MCI. This was not the case when self-complaint 
was part of the criteria [14] . In line with our results, Mol et al. [38] found significantly more 
women among GP patients reporting forgetfulness. Depression has been more frequent but </p>



<p>Dement Geriatr Cogn Disord Extra 2011;1:93-102 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000327076 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Hanzevacki et al.: Detecting Cognitive Decline in the Elderly </p>

<p>www.karger.com/dee </p>

<p>© 2011 S. Karger AG, Basel 
Published online: April 8, 2011 </p>

<p>not statistically significantly among female subjects in our study. Verified depressive symp-
toms were equally present in subjects who confirmed having cognitive problems and in sub-
jects who did not. We intend to evaluate the possible influence of concomitant neuropsycho-
logical disorders on cognitive or memory complaints in the future. 
We found the prevalence of MCI to be 18.30%, which is in accordance with prior studies 
[11] . Cooper et al. [12] found a rate of 17% for 'milder non-disabling degrees of cognitive im-
pairment' in GP patients aged 6 65 years diagnosed by a short rating scale [12] . More re-
cently, population-based studies have revealed prevalence rates of MCI diagnosed according 
to Petersen's criteria [39, 40] . The special prevalence of MCI among GP patients approached 
in their homes has been thoroughly researched by Artero et al. [13] and reported to be 16.6%. 
Luck et al. [14] interviewed GP patients in a similar setting and found a prevalence of 14.8% 
among patients 75-79 years of age. The CIND prevalence of 17.27% in our study is very sim-
ilar to the MCI prevalence; however, the affected subjects were completely different. This 
strongly points to a heterogeneity of patients with cognitive deficits. 
One limitation of our study is that we used solely the brief global cognitive screening 
tests MMSE and MoCA in order to characterize cognitively impaired subjects. As expected, 
MoCA proved to be significantly more sensitive [10, 22] . However, it is appropriate to con-
sider both tests for the early detection and initial evaluation of cognitive function in the GP 
practice, although a majority of subjects were recognized as cognitively impaired by MoCA, 
since we do not know the false-positive rate at this point and since MMSE was invented and 
proven valid for the early evaluation of dementia. The primary objective in the GP practice 
would be to identify high-risk individuals and to transfer them to further evaluation in a 
specialized clinical setting. 
In Croatia, there is a very limited number of specialized centers treating patients with 
cognitive problems, and they mostly focus on more advanced stages of cognitive deficits and 
different types of dementia [41] . Consequently, primary care physicians have an important 
role in detecting patients' problems and especially in their evaluation and follow-up. A GP's 
insight into daily activities and family dynamics evaluated by a biopsychosocial approach 
could additionally improve the quality of clinical judgment in the daily practice with elderly 
patients with different levels of cognitive deficits. 
In the light of time constraints, the time of almost 18 min needed to implement the 
MMSE and MoCA tests incorporated into a regular GP visit represents a significant burden 
for the GP during daily practice. This puts delayed memory testing in the focus of our inter-
est since delayed memory proved to be significantly correlated with general cognitive decline 
[42] . As it has also been described to be correlated with the risk of progression to dementia, 
it could be considered as one of the first tests to be implemented for recognizing potential 
patients with a cognitive deficit at the primary care level where the priority is to recognize 
the deficit. A delayed memory recall test could increase awareness of possible cognitive prob-
lems among patients and could cause them to pay more attention to cognitive functions in 
daily activities [43] . </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>There is a significant proportion of unrecognized subjects in the daily GP practice with 
an objectively verifiable cognitive deficit who do not report it even when asked. They can be 
diagnosed with MMSE and MoCA testing already in the GP practice. Further research is 
needed to understand factors such as sex or psychiatric conditions which have an influence 
on whether or not subjects complain about cognitive problems and to recommend the opti-
mal procedure for early detection of subjects with cognitive impairment. </p>



<p>Dement Geriatr Cogn Disord Extra 2011;1:93-102 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000327076 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Hanzevacki et al.: Detecting Cognitive Decline in the Elderly </p>

<p>www.karger.com/dee </p>

<p>© 2011 S. Karger AG, Basel 
Published online: April 8, 2011 </p>





<p>Dement Geriatr Cogn Disord Extra 2011;1:93-102 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000327076 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Hanzevacki et al.: Detecting Cognitive Decline in the Elderly </p>

<p>www.karger.com/dee </p>

<p>© 2011 S. Karger AG, Basel 
Published online: April 8, 2011 </p>



</text></tei>