<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3203616" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases (aaRSs) are remark-
able enzymes that are in charge of the accurate 
recognition and ligation of amino acids and tRNA 
molecules. The greatest difficulty in accurate 
aminoacylation appears to be in discriminating 
between highly similar amino acids. To reduce 
mischarging of tRNAs by non-cognate amino 
acids, aaRSs have evolved an editing activity in a 
second active site to cleave the incorrect 
aminoacyl-tRNAs. Editing occurs after translocation 
of the aminoacyl-CCA 76 end to the editing site, 
switching between a hairpin and a helical conform-
ation for aminoacylation and editing. Here, we 
studied the consequence of nucleotide changes in 
the CCA 76 accepting end of tRNA Leu during the 
aminoacylation and editing reactions. The analysis 
showed that the terminal A 76 is essential for both 
reactions, suggesting that critical interactions 
occur in the two catalytic sites. Substitutions of 
C 74 and C 75 selectively decreased aminoacylation 
keeping nearly unaffected editing. These mutations 
might favor the regular helical conformation 
required to reach the editing site. Mutating the 
editing domain residues that contribute to CCA 76 
binding reduced the aminoacylation fidelity leading 
to cell-toxicity in the presence of non-cognate 
amino acids. Collectively, the data show how 
protein synthesis quality is controlled by the CCA 76 
homogeneity of tRNAs. </p>

<p>Protein synthesis is a central process in organisms from all 
three domains of life, providing the link between the </p>

<p>genetic information encoded in DNA and functional 
proteins. This process critically relies on the correct for-
mation of aminoacyl-tRNA (aa-tRNA) by aminoacyl-
tRNA synthetase (aaRS) to establish the genetic code 
through rigorous control of the two-step aminoacylation 
(1,2). The amino acid is first activated with ATP to syn-
thesize the aa-AMP intermediate with the release of pyro-
phosphate; the amino acid moiety of the intermediate is 
subsequently transferred to the tRNA bearing the cognate 
nucleotide triplet (1). Mis-translation arising from disrup-
tion in the fidelity of these interactions has profound con-
sequences (3). However, the presence of various types of 
amino acids and their analogs, and the fact that amino 
acids only differ in the side chain, greatly challenge the 
specificity of aaRS. About half of the aaRSs misactivate 
non-cognate amino acids (4). To solve this problem, the 
proofreading (editing) mechanism of aaRS has evolved to 
hydrolyze the mis-products. Editing can occur at the 
aa-AMP level (pre-transfer editing) and/or mischarged 
tRNA level (post-transfer editing), depending on the 
specific aaRS (4). 
Leucyl-tRNA synthetase (LeuRS), isoleucyl-tRNA 
synthetase (IleRS) and valyl-tRNA synthetase (ValRS) 
belong to the class Ia of aaRSs, characterized by the con-
nective peptide 1 (CP1) and 2 (CP2) in the Rossmann fold 
nucleotide binding domain where the synthetic active site 
is located (5). The CP1 domain of LeuRS is located 35 A ˚ 
away from the Rossmann fold domain and is responsible 
for post-transfer editing (6,7). Recent studies have 
revealed that Escherichia coli, Aquifex aeolicus and 
human cytoplasmic LeuRSs (EcLeuRS, AaLeuRS and 
hcLeuRS) all employ three different pathways (tRNA-
independent, tRNA-dependent pre-transfer editing and 
post-transfer editing), but in different proportions 
relative to the total editing activity, to remove 
non-cognate amino acids (8,9). Similar results were also 
found with E. coli IleRS and ValRS (10). 
X-ray crystal structures of LeuRS and tRNA Leu in 
aminoacylation and post-transfer editing states clearly </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +86 21 5492 1241; Fax: +86 21 5492 1011; Email: edwang@sibs.ac.cn </p>

<p>Published online 20 July 2011 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 20 8857-8868 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkr595 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>revealed that the tRNA Leu main body conformation is 
indistinguishable between the two states (6,11). 
However, the CCA 76 -end shifts to the CP1 domain from 
the aminoacylation active site and is specifically 
recognized by several conserved residues, including 
Lys300, Tyr330, Arg344 and Leu327 (6,11). Therefore, 
these residues in CP1 collectively constitute the tRNA 
entrance pathway in post-transfer editing (6). In vitro 
studies have shown that the interaction between the 
Tyr330 and tRNA Leu CCA 76 -end is critical for both 
tRNA-dependent pre-transfer editing and post-transfer 
editing (8). However, the role of other crucial resides 
in editing and their significance in vivo are unclear. 
In addition, the contribution of the CCA 76 -end to the 
aminoacylation and editing still remains elusive. 
The CCA 76 sequence is conserved at the 3 0 -end of all 
mature tRNA molecules to function as the site of amino 
acid attachment (12). This sequence is gene encoded in E. 
coli and related bacteria or acquired in eukaryotes and 
maintained by stepwise nucleotide addition by the ubiqui-
tous CCA-adding enzyme (tRNA nucleotidyltransferase, 
CCase), which is an unusual RNA polymerase that does 
not use a nucleic acid template for nucleotide addition 
(13,14). 
The CCA 76 sequence is a universal ligand during several 
critical steps of protein biosynthesis. It is successively 
recognized by aaRSs (1,12), elongation factor (EF-Tu) 
(15) and rRNA (16,17). In F. Crick's adaptor hypothesis, 
the CCA 76 sequence is the ultimate adaptor group that 
carries the amino acid to the decoding center of the 
ribosome, whereas at the other end of the molecule, the 
anticodon triplet is needed to fit with the codon triplet of 
the mRNA. Because all the tRNAs have to fit to the 
unique ribosome decoding center, evolution has selected 
a unique CCA 76 sequence shared by all tRNAs. 
Additional constraints for CCA 76 conservation result 
from the interactions with the EF-Tu and the 20 aaRSs. 
With the later enzymes, the CCA 76 acceptor end is the 
substrate of two successive reactions starting with the 
aminoacylation reaction then followed by a proofreading 
reaction catalyzed in a second catalytic site (6,11). A 
critical conformational change, resulting from the flexibil-
ity of the single-stranded CCA 76 sequence, is required to 
allow transition from the synthetic to the editing site 
(6,11). 
The starting point of the present study was to clarify the 
role of the ubiquitous CCA 76 -end in the leucine 
aminoacylation system. Therefore, we generated a series 
of CCA 76 -end mutants and tested their impact on the 
aminoacylation and editing reactions catalyzed by E. coli 
LeuRS (EcLeuRS). Furthermore, mutants were generated 
in the CP1 editing domain of LeuRS in order to disrupt 
the interaction with the CCA 76 -end during the editing 
process. The in vivo effect of the mutations was then 
analyzed in a LeuRS-deficient strain in stress conditions 
under the pressure of elevated concentrations of 
non-cognate amino acid. Combining in vitro and in vivo 
results of protein and tRNA mutagenesis showed how life 
can regulate protein synthesis and control the 
aminoacylation quality by using the universally conserved 
sequence. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>L-leucine, dithiothreitol, NTP, 5 0 -GMP, tetrasodium pyro-
phosphate, inorganic pyrophosphate, ATP, Tris-HCl, 
MgCl 2 , NaCl, mouse anti-His 6 antibody and activated 
charcoal were purchased from Sigma (USA). [ 3 H]leucine, 
[ 3 H]isoleucine and [a-32 P]ATP were obtained from 
Amersham Biosciences (England). Pfu DNA polymerase, 
the DNA fragment rapid purification kit and a plasmid 
extraction kit were purchased from Biotech Company 
(China). KOD-plus mutagenesis kit was obtained from 
TOYOBO (Japan). T4 ligase and restriction endonucle-
ases were obtained from MBI Fermentas. Phusion 
high-fidelity DNA polymerase was purchased from 
New England Biolabs (USA). Ni 2+ -NTA Superflow was 
purchased 
from 
Qiagen, 
Inc. 
(Germany). 
Polyethyleneimine cellulose plates were purchased from 
Merck (Germany). Pyrophosphatase was obtained from 
Roche Applied Science (China). Pyrobest DNA polymer-
ase and the dNTP mixture were obtained from Takara 
(Japan). Oligonucleotide primers were synthesized by 
Invitrogen (China). Escherichia coli BL21 (DE3) cells 
were purchased from Stratagene (USA). The E. coli 
KL231 strain [F À , leuS31(ts), thyA6, rpsL120(strR), 
deoC1] was purchased from the E. coli genetic stock 
center (CGSC, Yale University, USA) (18). T7 RNA poly-
merase was purified from an overproduction strain in our 
laboratory (19). </p>

<p>Gene cloning and mutagenesis </p>

<p>The plasmid pET30a-EcleuS encoding EcLeuRS with 
N-terminal His 6 -tag previously constructed by our lab 
(8) was used as the template to construct genes encoding 
various EcLeuRS mutants using KOD-plus mutagenesis 
kit for the in vitro activity measurements. EcleuS was 
amplified, cleaved by NcoI and HindIII and cloned into 
pTrc99a (pre-cleaved by NcoI and HindIII) to produce 
pTrc99a-EcleuS. The 18 nucleotides encoding His 6 -tag at 
the N-terminus were incorporated into the forward primer 
during the construction of pTrc99a-EcleuS. The pTrc99a-
EcleuS construct was used as the template to construct 
genes encoding various EcLeuRS mutants using the 
KOD-plus mutagenesis kit for the in vivo complementa-
tion assays in the KL231 strain. </p>

<p>In vitro transcription of tRNAs </p>

<p>Six DNA fragments covering the T7 promoter and tRNA 
gene double strands were synthesized by Invitrogen, 
phosphorylated and ligated into pUC19 (pre-cleaved by 
EcoRI and BamHI) to construct the plasmid 
pUC19-tRNA. To prepare the wild-type (WT) 
tRNA Leu 
GAG transcript, the forward primer (5 0 -ctgcagtaata 
cgactcactatagccgaggtggtgg-3 0 , with T7 promoter sequence 
in italics) and the reverse primer (5 0 -tggtaccgaggacgg 
gacttgaacccgtaagccctattg-3 0 ) were synthesized to amplify 
the T7 promoter and the gene encoding tRNA Leu 
GAG using 
the Phusion high-fidelity DNA polymerase, which does 
not add an additional adenosine to the PCR product. 
The PCR product was separated on a 2% agarose gel, </p>



<p>extracted by phenol/chloroform and precipitated in the 
presence of cold ethanol and 0.3 M NaAc (pH 5.2). The 
T7 in vitro transcription was carried out at 37 C in a 100 ml 
reaction mixture containing 40 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 
22 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM spermidine, 5 mM DTT, 0.5% 
Triton X-100, 60 ng ml À1 tDNA template, 5 mM ATP, 
5 mM CTP, 5 mM GTP, 5 mM UTP, 0.8 U ml À1 ribonucle-
ase inhibitor, 20 mM GMP and 500 U ml À1 T7 RNA poly-
merase. One hour later, 2 U of pyrophosphatase was 
added to remove the pyrophosphate for 30 min, and 
then 5 U of DNase I (RNase I free) was added and 
incubated for 1 h to digest the transcription template. 
The transcript was then loaded into a 15% PAGE-8M 
Urea gel of 1-mm thickness and 40 cm length, and the 
gel was run at constant 25 W for 10 h to carefully 
remove any non-specific bands. The tRNA was cut from 
the gel and eluted with 0.5 M NaAc (pH 5.2) at room 
temperature, ethanol precipitated at À20 C after phenol/ 
chloroform extraction two times and dissolved in 5 mM 
MgCl 2 . The tRNA was denatured at 80 C for 5 min and 
slowly cooled down to 30 C. The tRNA Leu mutants were 
prepared by the same procedure, except that the different 
reverse primer was synthesized and used in preparing the 
DNA template. </p>

<p>Protein expression and purification </p>

<p>The WT LeuRS (EcLeuRS) and its mutants were 
produced by transformation of E. coli BL21 (DE3) cells 
with the corresponding plasmids. A single colony from 
each of the transformants was chosen and cultured in 
500 ml of 2Â YT medium at 37 C. When the cells were 
grown to mid-log phase (A 600 = 0.6), IPTG (isopropyl-
1-thio-b-D-galactopyranoside) was added to a final con-
centration of 0.2 mM, and cultivation continued for 6 h at 
22 C. The proteins were purified by Ni 2+ -NTA chroma-
tography, as described previously (8). </p>

<p>Aminoacylation, mis-aminoacylation and deacylation </p>

<p>The kinetic constants of EcLeuRS for WT tRNA and its 
variants were tested in a reaction mixture containing 
100 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.8), 30 mM KCl, 12 mM MgCl 2 , 
0.5 mM dithiothreitol, 4 mM ATP, 40 mM [ 3 H]leucine, 
0.25-12 mM EctRNA Leu and 5 nM EcLeuRS at 37 C. 
Mis-aminoacylation assays were carried out at 37 C in a 
reaction mixture containing 100 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.8), 
30 mM KCl, 12 mM MgCl 2 , 0.5 mM dithiothreitol, 4 mM 
ATP, 5 mM EctRNA Leu , 40 mM [ 3 H]isoleucine and 1 mM 
EcLeuRS. Preparation of mischarged Ile-tRNA Leu was 
carried out in a similar system with mis-aminoacylation, 
except that 20 mM EctRNA Leu and 1 mM EcLeuRS-T252E 
were used (20). Hydrolytic editing assays of EcLeuRS or 
its mutants were performed at 37 C in 100 mM Tris-HCl 
(pH 7.5), 30 mM KCl, 12 mM MgCl 2 , 0.5 mM 
dithiothreitol and 1 mM [ 3 H]Ile-tRNA Leu , and the reac-
tions were initiated with 5 nM enzyme. Nine microliter 
aliquots of the reaction solution were added to 
Whatman filter pads and quenched with cold 5% tri-
chloroacetic acid (TCA) at various time intervals. The 
pads were washed three times for 15 min each with cold 
5% TCA and then three times for 10 min each with </p>

<p>100% ethanol. The pads were dried under a heat lamp. 
The radioactivities of the precipitates were quantified with 
a scintillation counter (Beckman Coulter). </p>

<p>Charging plateau measurements </p>

<p>Charging plateau measurements of transcripts were per-
formed in 40 ml reaction mixtures each containing 100 mM 
Tris-HCl (pH 7.8), 30 mM KCl, 12 mM MgCl 2 , 0.5 mM 
dithiothreitol, 4 mM ATP, 20 mM [ 3 H]leucine (15 Ci/ 
mmol), 1 mM tRNA (ÁA 76 , ÁC 75 A 76 , ÁC 74 C 75 A 76 , 
ÁA 76 /C75A, ÁA 76 /C75U and ÁA 76 /C75G) and 100 nM 
EcLeuRS at 37 C. Aliquots of 9 ml of the reaction 
solution were removed at various time intervals, 
quenched on Whatman filter pads and processed as men-
tioned in the procedures above. The blank experiment 
without tRNA Leu was performed under the same condi-
tions. In another control experiment, RNase I (final 
0.25 U/ml) was added to the aliquot at various time inter-
vals to digest the aminoacylation product and incubated 
at 37 C for another 5 min. The plateau value of WT 
tRNA Leu was &gt;1400 pmol/A 260 . </p>

<p>AMP formation </p>

<p>In the editing Nva reaction of EcLeuRS, AMP formation 
was measured in a reaction mixture containing 100 mM 
Tris-HCl (pH 7.8), 30 mM KCl, 12 mM MgCl 2 , 5 mM 
dithiothreitol, 5 U ml À1 pyrophosphatase, 3 mM ATP, 
20 nM [a-32 P]ATP and 15 mM Norvaline (Nva) in the 
presence or absence of 5 mM tRNA Leu or its variants. 
The reaction was initiated by the addition of 0.2 mM 
EcLeuRS or its mutants and incubated at 37 C. 
Aliquots (1.5 ml) were quenched in 6 ml of 200 mM NaAc 
(pH 5.0). The quenched aliquots (1.5 ml each) were spotted 
in duplicate on polyethyleneimine cellulose plates 
pre-washed with water. Separation of Nva-[ 32 P]AMP, 
[ 32 P]AMP and [ 32 P]ATP was performed by developing 
thin layer chromatography (TLC) on polyethyleneimine 
cellulose plates in 0.1 M NH 4 Ac and 5% acetic acid. The 
plates were visualized by phosphorimaging, and the data 
were analyzed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Multi Gauge</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">Version 3.0</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">FUJIFILM</rs>). The gray densities of [ 32 P]AMP spots were 
compared with the gray density of known [ 32 P]ATP con-
centrations. Rate constants were obtained from graphs of 
[ 32 P]AMP formation plotted against time (8). </p>

<p>KL231 complementation assay </p>

<p>Competent KL231 cells were electro-transformed with 
various plasmids, including pTrc99a (negative control), 
pTrc99a-EcleuS, 
pTrc99a-EcleuS-L327G, 
-L327R, 
-K300E, -Y330D, -R344D, -K300E/Y330D, -K300E/ 
R344D, -Y330D/R344D and -K300E/Y330D/R344D. 
Transformants were grown on solid LB plates supple-
mented with 100 mg ml À1 ampicillin and 200 mg ml À1 
thymine at 30 C. A single colony was selected and 
grown in liquid LB medium supplemented with 
100 mg ml À1 ampicillin, 200 mg ml À1 thymine and 0.1 mM 
IPTG at 30 C. The cells harboring these plasmids were 
diluted and adjusted to the same A 600 value of 0.2. To 
test the effect of non-cognate Nva on cell growth, 5 ml of 
the diluted mixture were dropped on a solid LB plate </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 20 8859 </p>

<p>(supplemented with 100 mg ml À1 ampicillin, 200 mg ml À1 
thymine and 0.1 mM IPTG) containing 0, 5, 10, 20, 50, 
100 or 200 mM Nva, and the plates were incubated at 
42 C to observe the growth of cells. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Mutation of the CCA 76 -end impacts the tRNA 
aminoacylation reaction </p>

<p>All tRNA Leu isoacceptors from various species contain the 
absolutely conserved A 73 (12), which functions as the dis-
criminator during recognition by LeuRSs in different 
species (12,21). However, the effect of the CCA 76 -end on 
tRNA aminoacylation has not been reported. Here, each 
nucleotide of the CCA 76 -end of tRNA Leu 
GAG was individu-
ally mutated to one of the three other nucleotides 
(Figure 1A), and the aminoacylation kinetic constants of 
EcLeuRS for these tRNA Leu s were assayed. In 
aminoacylation of the tRNA Leu A76U and A76C 
mutants, the catalytic efficiency of EcLeuRS was obvious-
ly decreased (155.8 and 87.2 s À1 mM À1 , respectively) as 
compared with that of the WT tRNA transcript 
(923.1 s À1 mM À1 ). The amino acid-accepting activity of </p>

<p>the A76G mutant was too low to accurately measure the 
kinetics. Similarly, the three C 75 mutants reduced the 
amino acid-accepting activity to 2-46% of the native 
tRNA Leu , with the C75G mutant showing the greatest 
decrease (14.6 s À1 mM À1 ). Additionally, the three tRNA 
variants from C 74 showed obvious decreases in amino 
acid-accepting activity; their catalytic constants for 
EcLeuRS ranged from 8% (C74G, 69.4 s À1 mM À1 ), 41% 
(C74U, 381.8 s À1 mM À1 ) to 50% (C74A, 460.3 s À1 mM À1 ) 
of that with the WT tRNA Leu (Table 1). All the decreases 
were mainly due to a reduced k cat value of EcLeuRS and/ 
or changed K m for these tRNA Leu mutants. These results 
clearly showed that the CCA 76 -end mutations negatively 
impacted the aminoacylation of these mutants to various 
levels, and the presence of guanosine at each of the 3-nt 
positions resulted in the lowest level of tRNA 
aminoacylation. </p>

<p>LeuRS can aminoacylate tRNA Leu lacking the terminal 
adenosine </p>

<p>Besides point mutations, we also performed progressive 
deletions from the CCA 76 -end of tRNA in order to 
obtain the following three mutants: ÁA 76 (ending </p>

<p>Figure 1. Secondary structures of tRNA Leu s and location of the mutations. Cloverleaf structures of tRNA Leu 
GAG (A) and tRNA Leu 
CAG (B) used in the 
present work. The point and deletion mutations on the tRNA Leu 
GAG are shown. </p>

<p>Table 1. Aminoacylation kinetics of transcripts of tRNA Leu 
GAG by EcLeuRS </p>

<p>tRNA 
K m (mM) 
k cat (s À1 ) 
k cat /K m (s À1 mM À1 ) 
k cat /K m (relative) </p>

<p>tRNA Leu </p>

<p>GAG </p>

<p>1.95 ± 0.23 
1.80 ± 0.27 
923.1 
1 
A76U 
1.99 ± 0.30 
0.31 ± 0.04 
155.8 
0.17 
A76G 
-
&lt;&lt;0.002 
-
-
A76C 
3.90 ± 0.48 
0.34 ± 0.03 
87.2 
0.09 
C75A 
0.38 ± 0.05 
0.16 ± 0.03 
421.1 
0.46 
C75U 
1.18 ± 0.17 
0.10 ± 0.02 
84.7 
0.09 
C75G 
1.78 ± 0.22 
0.026 ± 0.004 
14.6 
0.02 
C74A 
0.63 ± 0.05 
0.29 ± 0.04 
460.3 
0.50 
C74U 
0.55 ± 0.07 
0.21 ± 0.03 
381.8 
0.41 
C74G 
0.36 ± 0.05 
0.025 ± 0.002 
69.4 
0.08 </p>



<p>with C 75 ), ÁC 75 A 76 (ending with C 74 ) and ÁC 74 C 75 A 76 
(ending with A 73 ) (Figure 1A). In initial charging 
plateau measurements for accepting activity with a large 
excess of 1 mM enzyme, it was surprising to observe that 
LeuRS could charge ÁA 76 mutant obviously. As it has 
been reported that some aaRSs can ligate their cognate 
amino acids to themselves without tRNA (by self-
aminoacylation occurring at high enzyme concentration 
and excess of adenylate formation) (22-24), we tested 
the self-aminoacylation of EcLeuRS at different 
concentrations without tRNA. We found that self-
aminoacylation of EcLeuRS was negligible at low concen-
trations (&lt;300 nM). However, EcLeuRS at higher 
concentrations &gt;500 nM could be self-aminoacylated and 
was resistant to RNase I (Supplementary Figure S1). 
Therefore, we tested the ÁA 76 charging plateau value by 
using 100 nM EcLeuRS and found that 70% of ÁA 76 
could be charged with 3 H-Leu. In the same conditions, 
no detectable labeled product could be measured at the 
absence of tRNA (Figure 2). To further confirm that, the 
tRNA but not the enzyme itself was ligated with 3 H-Leu, 
we treated the aminoacylation product in the presence of 
RNase I, and the values dropped down to the same level 
with that in the absence of tRNA (Figure 2). These results 
confirmed that LeuRS could aminoacylate tRNA Leu with 
the terminal A 76 deleted. However, reliable aminoacyla-
tion kinetics could not be measured because of the very 
low k cat . However, the other two tRNA mutants, ÁC 75 A 76 
and ÁC 74 C 75 A 76 , could not be aminoacylated at 100 nM 
or higher concentrations of EcLeuRS (data not shown). 
To further analyze the ÁA 76 mutant, we mutated the 
terminal C 75 to the three other nucleotides in order to 
identify potential interactions that could be more product-
ive in aminoacylation. The resulting mutants, ÁA 76 / 
C75A, ÁA 76 /C75U and ÁA 76 /C75G, could be </p>

<p>aminoacylated by EcLeuRS to plateau levels of 70, 61 
and 35%, respectively (Figure 2). Therefore, more pro-
ductive interactions were not induced by these nucleotides, 
and here again, the mutant harboring a guanosine 
mutation was the least active compared to those with 
the other nucleotides. </p>

<p>Role of CCA 76 -end in total editing </p>

<p>Usually, more than one ATP molecule is consumed by an 
aaRS in the presence of a non-cognate amino acid due to 
repetitive cycles of synthesis-hydrolysis of the non-cognate 
products. The excess of ATP consumption can be deter-
mined by measuring the release of AMP in the TLC assay 
(25). In the presence of tRNA, the TLC assay measures 
the global editing activity, including the tRNA-
independent and tRNA-dependent pre-transfer editing in 
addition to the post-transfer editing (8,26). In the absence 
of tRNA, the assay measures the AMP produced from the 
sole tRNA-independent pre-transfer editing activity (26). 
In the presence of non-cognate Nva, the observed rate 
constant (k obs ) of WT LeuRS for AMP formation without 
tRNA in the editing reaction was 0.56 ± 0.07 s À1 , ac-
counting for 13% of that in the presence of tRNA tran-
script (4.42 ± 0.64 s À1 ) (Table 2). The tRNA transcript 
without the modified bases was tested to determine if it 
was as efficient as the native tRNA in stimulating the 
editing activity. The k obs for AMP formation in the 
presence of EctRNA Leu 
GAG purified from the overproducing 
E. coli strain (27) was 5.59 ± 0.76 s À1 . This value was only 
slightly larger than that in the presence of transcript 
(4.42 ± 0.64 s À1 ), indicating that the modified bases in 
EctRNA Leu did not play a critical role in stimulating 
editing activity (Table 2). 
Different variants of the CCA 76 -end were also tested for 
their abilities to stimulate AMP formation in editing reac-
tions with EcLeuRS. The AMP formation rates for A76U, 
A76G and A76C mutants dropped down to a level similar 
to that without tRNA, indicating only tRNA-independent 
pre-transfer editing remained and the tRNA-dependent </p>

<p>Figure 2. Aminoacylation of tRNA Leu -ÁA 76 , -ÁA 76 /C75A, -ÁA 76 / 
C75U or -ÁA 76 /C75G by EcLeuRS.Charging plateaus of EctRNA Leu -
ÁA 76 (filled diamond), -ÁA 76 /C75A (filled square), -ÁA 76 /C75U (filled 
triangle) or -ÁA 76 /C75G (filled inverted triangle) were measured as 
described in the Materials and methods section. The control (unfilled 
circle) was performed without tRNA. The charging plateaus were 
determined using <rs type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> software. According to the plateau 
values (to calculate the amount of tRNA Leu charged leucine) and total 
tRNA Leu used in the reaction, EctRNA Leu -ÁA 76 , -ÁA 76 /C75A, -ÁA 76 / 
C75U and -ÁA 76 /C75G are aminoacylated to 70, 70, 61 and 35%, 
respectively. Digestion of aminoacyl-EctRNA Leu -ÁA 76 by RNase I di-
gestion (unfilled triangle) and no product accumulation in control 
excluded the self-aminoacylation of the enzyme. </p>

<p>Table 2. k obs of AMP formation by EcLeuRS in the presence of Nva 
and tRNA Leu 
GAG or its variants </p>

<p>tRNA 
k obs (s À1 ) 
Relative k obs </p>

<p>No tRNA Leu </p>

<p>GAG </p>

<p>0.56 ± 0.07 
0.13 
tRNA Leu 
GAG (in vivo) a 
5.59 ± 0.76 
1.27 
tRNA Leu 
GAG (transcript) b 
4.42 ± 0.64 
1 
A76U 
0.24 ± 0.04 
0.05 </p>

<p>A76G 
0.20 ± 0.04 
0.05 
A76C 
0.48 ± 0.06 
0.11 
ÁA 76 
0.71 ± 0.08 
0.16 </p>

<p>C75A 
8.34 ± 1.03 
1.89 
C75U 
6.26 ± 0.81 
1.42 
C75G 
0.64 ± 0.07 
0.15 </p>

<p>C74A 
7.48 ± 0.98 
1.69 
C74U 
8.87 ± 1.34 
2.01 
C74G 
2.65 ± 0.32 
0.60 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>tRNA Leu 
GAG obtained from the overproducing E. coli strain (27). </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>tRNA Leu 
GAG obtained by T7 in vitro transcription. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 20 8861 </p>

<p>editing was abolished (Table 2). As a consequence of this 
loss of editing ability, the two A 76 -mutants of tRNA Leu 
(A76U and A76C) were obviously mischarged with Ile 
(Figure 3A). The decreased formation of Ile-tRNA Leu of 
A76G may be due to its deficiency in accepting the amino 
acid. Among the other six variants of tRNA Leu , only 
C75G with a k obs value of 0.64 ± 0.07 s À1 had tRNA-
independent pre-transfer editing and lost the tRNA-
dependent editing, indicating that C75G could not play 
a role in the tRNA-dependent editing; C74G with a k obs 
value of 2.65 ± 0.32 s À1 decreased the tRNA-dependent 
editing to nearly half of that of the WT tRNA Leu ; the 
four mutants of tRNA Leu , C75A, C75U, C74A and 
C74U stimulated more AMP formation than WT 
tRNA Leu , with the k obs values of 8.34 ± 1.03, 
6.26 ± 0.81, 7.48 ± 0.98 and 8.87 ± 1.34 s À1 , respectively 
(Table 2), indicating that these mutations did not affect 
the tRNA-dependent editing but rather stimulated it. 
The six variants of nucleotides 74 and 75 did not form 
any detectable Ile-tRNA Leu in the misacylation assay 
(data not shown). Additionally, in the presence of the 
ÁA 76 mutant, EcLeuRS had comparable editing activity 
with that in the absence of tRNA (Table 2). 
Correspondingly, EcLeuRS catalyzed the synthesis of an 
obvious amount of mischarged ÁA 76 mutant 
(Ile-tRNA Leu -ÁA 76 ) (Figure 3B). These results clearly 
showed that the terminal A 76 is a critical element in the 
tRNA-dependent editing activity of EcLeuRS, and the 
nucleotides C 74 and C 75 crucial for aminoacylation do 
not play an indispensible role to the tRNA-dependent 
editing of EcLeuRS. </p>

<p>Role of CCA 76 -end in post-transfer editing </p>

<p>It is now universally accepted that after aminoacylation, 
the CCA 76 -end of the tRNA is translocated $35 A ˚ from 
the aminoacylation active site to the editing active site 
embedded in the CP1 domain (6). Both tRNA CCA 76 -
end and mischarged amino acid moieties are recognized 
by the active site of post-transfer editing within the CP1 
domain of LeuRS. To test the contribution of the CCA 76 -
end to the post-transfer editing, we first mischarged 10 
variants of the tRNA with non-cognate 3 H-Ile using 
an editing-deficient LeuRS-T252E mutant (20). </p>

<p>The deacylation of the mischarged Ile-tRNA Leu by WT 
LeuRS was then measured. The mutants of tRNA Leu 
could be mischarged with Ile by the LeuRS-T252E 
mutant. However the three mis-acylated mutants of A 76 
(A76C, A76G and A76U) were resistant to deacylation 
catalyzed by LeuRS (Figure 4A), indicating the crucial 
role of this nucleotide in post-transfer editing. This 
result was also consistent with their inability to stimulate 
total editing in the TLC assay (Table 2). In addition, 
Ile-tRNA Leu -ÁA 76 could not be hydrolyzed by the 
post-transfer editing (Figure 4A). This is consistent with 
the fact that the A 76 base is specifically recognized by the 
main chain carbonyl-and amino-groups of EcLeuRS 
Leu327 in the Nva2AA-containing structure (analog of 
the post-transfer editing substrate) (28) and Thermus 
thermophilus LeuRS-tRNA Leu structure (in post-transfer 
editing conformation) (6). Obviously, changing the termin-
al base affects the proper positioning of the CCA 76 -end 
into the CP1 domain and thus blocks the hydrolytic 
editing reaction. 
In general, mutations of nucleotides 75 and 74 did not 
influence the tRNA deacylation properties, except when 
the guanosine mutations C75G and C74G were 
introduced (Figure 4B and C). The result suggested that 
guanine residues at either position of CCA 76 -end may 
prevent proper interaction with the enzyme and/or 
tRNA end translocation. </p>

<p>The tRNA entrance pathway critically contributes to 
quality control </p>

<p>According to the crystal structure, the CP1 editing domain 
binds only with CCA 76 -end residues without any inter-
action with the main tRNA body. In detail, the equivalent 
side chains in EcLeuRS interacting specifically with the 
C 74 base and the phosphates of C 75 and A 76 are Lys300, 
Arg344 and Tyr330, respectively (6). Additionally, the 
main chain carbonyl-and amino-group of Leu327 
interact with the A 76 base (Figure 5A). These amino 
acid residues are absolutely conserved in prokaryotic 
LeuRSs and thus constitute an entrance pathway to 
orient the aminoacylated CCA 76 -arm into the editing 
active site. Previous studies have demonstrated the essen-
tial role of Tyr330 of EcLeuRS in tRNA-dependent </p>

<p>Figure 3. Misacylation of tRNA-A 76 mutants with Ile. (A and B) WT tRNA Leu (filled circle) and mutated derivatives A76U (unfilled circle), A76G 
(filled inverted triangle) or A76C (unfilled triangle) and ÁA 76 (unfilled inverted triangle) were mischarged with non-cognate Ile. </p>

<p>8862 Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 20 </p>

<p>Figure 5. The tRNA entrance pathway contributes critically to the quality control. (A) View of tRNA Leu CCA 76 -end bound to the CP1 do-
main (gray) (6), showing the binding pattern between C 74 (yellow), C 75 (cyan), A 76 (blue) and the key amino acids (green) in the CP1 
editing domain (upper). The tRNA main body before nucleotide A 73 (orange) and LeuRS main body except for the editing domain were omitted 
for clarity. The lower panel shows the closer protein-CCA 76 interaction network. Distances between the amino-acid residues here studied and the 
nucleotides are shown. (B) Mischarging of tRNA Leu 
GAG with non-cognate Ile by WT EcLeuRS (filled circle), -Y330D (unfilled circle), -K300E/Y330D 
(filled inverted triangle), -K300E/R344D (unfilled triangle), -Y330D/R344D (filled square), -K300E/Y330D/R344D (unfilled square) and -R344D 
(filled diamond) with significant misaminoacylation ability. Mutants that did not accumulate Ile-tRNA Leu are not shown. (C) Deacylation curves of 
Ile-tRNA Leu by WT EcLeuRS (filled circle), -L327G (unfilled circle), -L327R (filled inverted triangle), -K300E/R344D (unfilled triangle), -K300E 
(filled square) and -R344D (filled diamond). Editing-defective mutants (EcLeuRS-Y330D, -K300E/Y330D, -Y330D/R344D and -K300E/ 
Y330D/R344D) are not shown for clarity. Spontaneous hydrolysis without enzyme addition was carried out as a control (unfilled square) as 
indicated. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Effect of the CCA 76 mutations on deacylation of mischarged tRNA Leu . Mischarged tRNA mutants from A 76 , C 75 or C 74 were prepared 
by editing-deficient EcLeuRS-T252E (20). Mischarged tRNA-ÁA 76 mutant was obtained with WT EcLeuRS. Deacylation of mischarged WT 
tRNA Leu was indicated (unfilled circle). The deacylation assay of mischarged ÁA 76 (unfilled square), A76U (filled inverted triangle), 
A76G (unfilled triangle), A76C (filled square) in (A), C75A (filled inverted triangle), C75U (unfilled triangle), C75G (filled square) in (B) or 
C74A (filled inverted triangle), C74U (unfilled triangle), C74G (filled square) in (C) was performed at 37 C with 1 mM [ 3 H]Ile-tRNA Leu and 
5 nM EcLeuRS. The spontaneous hydrolysis of each mischarged tRNA (control) was carried out without enzyme. For clarity, a single representa-
tive control is shown (filled circle). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 20 8863 </p>

<p>editing (8). However, other sites (Leu327, Lys300 and 
Arg344) and their functions in vivo have not been 
determined. We studied here the roles of residues 
Leu327, Lys300, Tyr330 and Arg344 by mutating them 
individually or in combination. The in vitro and in vivo 
assays were then performed in order to analyze the 
effects of these mutations. 
The following single, double and triple mutants were 
constructed in EcLeuRS to form EcLeuRS-L327G, 
-L327R, -K300E, -Y330D, -R344D, -K300E/Y330D, 
-K300E/R344D, -Y330D/R344D and -K300E/Y330D/ 
R344D. All these mutants displayed intact synthetic 
activities (Leu activation and aminoacylation) as 
expected from their location in the discrete CP1 editing 
domain (data not shown). However, EcLeuRS-Y330D, 
-K300E/Y330D, -Y330D/R344D and the triple mutant 
were completely defective in post-transfer editing (data 
not shown), and they produced significant amounts of 
Ile-tRNA Leu (Figure 5B). The other mutants were 
impaired in post-transfer editing to different extents 
(Figure 5C), and only EcLeuRS-R344D and EcLeuRS-
K300E/R344D synthesized mischarged tRNA Leu , but ob-
viously at lower levels than that with EcLeuRS-Y330D 
and the derived double and triple mutants (Figure 5B). 
In the TLC assay, EcLeuRS-Y330D, its derived double 
and triple mutants and EcLeuRS-K300E/R344D only 
retained the tRNA-independent pre-transfer editing 
activity (Table 3). Altogether, the data showed that the 
Tyr330 residue plays a major role in tRNA-dependent 
editing as previously demonstrated (8). The negative 
effect of Y330D on editing was dominant, and the 
derived multiple mutants exhibited similar defects. Only 
the combination mutant EcLeuRS-K300E/R344D could 
reach the same level of tRNA-independent editing of the 
single EcLeuRS-Y330D mutation. Other individual 
mutants showed more limited decreases in post-transfer 
editing activity, inducing no measurable tRNA 
mischarging (data not shown). These in vitro data con-
firmed that mutating the CCA 76 entrance pathway of the 
CP1 domain has a negative effect on the accuracy of 
tRNA Leu aminoacylation. 
To evaluate if these losses of accuracy could affect the 
fidelity of protein synthesis in vivo, complementation </p>

<p>assays using the leuS temperature-sensitive strain KL231 
were performed (18). The strain KL231 was transformed 
with various plasmids encoding EcLeuRS and different 
mutants. At 42 C, all the transformants grew on 
medium supplemented with 100 mg ml À1 ampicillin and 
200 mg ml À1 thymine (Figure 6), and the mutants were 
well expressed at a level similar to that of WT EcLeuRS 
(Supplementary Figure S2). The growth was then 
observed at 42 C in the presence of increasing concentra-
tions of Nva in the growth medium. No growth difference 
could be observed below 20 mM of Nva. However, in the 
presence of 50 mM Nva, the strains harboring the 
genes-encoding 
EcLeuRS-Y330D, 
-K300E/Y330D, 
-K300E/R344D, -Y330D/R344D and -K300E/Y330D/ 
R344D grew slowly or were inhibited completely, especial-
ly those containing the last double and triple mutants 
(Figure 6). With a 100 mM of Nva no strains containing 
mutants were able to grow, except for the strain expressing 
WT enzyme which only grew at a very slow rate. All 
strains died in the presence of 200 mM Nva. 
Altogether, the in vivo data are consistent with the 
in vitro results, demonstrating that perturbing the tRNA 
CCA 76 -end entry pathway in the CP1 domain has a sig-
nificantly negative effect on the fidelity of protein 
biosynthesis. </p>

<p>Figure 6. In vivo toxicity resulting from mutations in the CP1 tRNA 
entrance pathway of EcLeuRS. The complementation assay was per-
formed using E. coli thermosensitive strain KL231 at 42 C, on solid LB 
plates supplemented with 100 mg ml À1 ampicillin, 200 mg ml À1 thymine, 
0.1 mM IPTG and increasing concentrations of non-cognate Nva. 
KL231 was transformed with mutated copies of LeuRS-encoding 
genes, and growth was compared with the negative control (empty 
pTrc99a vector) and positive control (WT EcLeuRS). Expression of 
all LeuRSs proteins was controlled by Western blot (Supplementary 
Figure S2). </p>

<p>Table 3. k obs of AMP formation by EcLeuRS or mutated derivatives 
in the presence of Nva </p>

<p>EcLeuRS 
tRNA Leu </p>

<p>GAG </p>

<p>(transcript) </p>

<p>k obs (s À1 ) 
Relative k obs </p>

<p>WT 
+ 
4.42 ± 0.64 
1 
WT 
-
0.56 ± 0.07 
0.13 
-L327G 
+ 
1.86 ± 0.26 
0.42 
-L327R 
+ 
3.60 ± 0.45 
0.81 
-K300E 
+ 
2.54 ± 0.41 
0.57 
-Y330D 
+ 
0.59 ± 0.06 
0.14 
-R344D 
+ 
1.26 ± 0.19 
0.29 
-K300E/Y330D 
+ 
0.46 ± 0.03 
0.10 
-K300E/R344D 
+ 
0.82 ± 0.07 
0.19 
-Y330D/R344D 
+ 
0.49 ± 0.06 
0.11 
-K300E/Y330D/R344D 
+ 
0.59 ± 0.06 
0.14 </p>

<p>8864 Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 20 </p>

<p>Different tRNA Leu isoacceptors stimulate LeuRS editing 
with the same efficiency </p>

<p>In E. coli, there are five different tRNA Leu isoacceptors 
with two types of first base pairs in its accepting stem 
(Figure 1). tRNA Leu 
GAG and tRNA Leu 
UAA harbor the wobble 
base pair (G 1 -U 72 ); while tRNA Leu 
CAG , tRNA Leu 
CAA and 
tRNA Leu 
UAG contain the standard Watson-Crick one 
(G 1 -C 72 ). It has been shown that EcLeuRS has the same 
specificity and activity toward different isoacceptors in 
aminoacylation (29). We transcribed the EctRNA Leu </p>

<p>GAG </p>

<p>(with G 1 -U 72 ) and tRNA Leu 
CAG (with G 1 -C 72 ) to represent 
two types of tRNA Leu and compared their capacity to 
stimulate editing by EcLeuRS. The data showed that 
they stimulated EcLeuRS editing activity with nearly iden-
tical efficiency (4.42 ± 0.64 and 4.54 ± 0.36 s À1 , respect-
ively) (Table 4). To explore the possible role of the first 
base pair in EcLeuRS editing, we mutated the U 72 to C 72 
of tRNA Leu 
GAG or the C 72 to U 72 of tRNA Leu 
CAG to change the 
first base pair pattern. Measurements of AMP formation 
showed that the tRNA Leu 
GAG (G 1 -C 72 ) had the editing k obs of 
3.75 ± 0.50 s À1 , while the tRNA Leu 
CAG (G 1 -U 72 ) mutant 
stimulated the editing with k obs of 6.10 ± 0.81 s À1 
(Table 4). The above results suggested that EcLeuRS 
editing has no preference among WT isoacceptors with 
different first base-pairs. However, changing the first 
base-pair obviously led to distinct editing-stimulating 
capacities among isoacceptors. Therefore, the first base 
pair pattern may cooperate with other sequence differ-
ences between the two tRNA Leu s to confer the same 
level of editing-stimulating capacity of the two 
isoacceptors of WT tRNA Leu . </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The CCA 76 -end sequence is critical for both 
aminoacylation and editing reactions </p>

<p>The CCA 76 sequence is conserved at the 3 0 -end of all 
mature tRNA molecules. Although it is an indispensable 
prerequisite for a functional tRNA, very few organisms 
like E. coli encode the CCA 76 triplet in their tRNA 
genes. Most of the time, the CCA 76 tail is to be added 
post-transcriptionally in eukaryotes, archaea and many 
bacteria, where the tRNA genes do not encode the 
CCA 76 terminus (30). This sequence is acquired and main-
tained by step-wise nucleotide addition by the ubiquitous 
tRNA nucleotidyltransferase that synthesizes this specific 
triplet without a nucleic acid template. The CCA sequence 
plays key roles during several steps of protein </p>

<p>biosynthesis. During tRNA charging catalyzed by 
aaRSs, the 2 0 or 3 0 hydroxyl of ribose in A 76 is the 
group involved in the esterification reaction with the 
carboxyl of the amino acid. Although the CCA 76 -end 
does not play a critical role in recognition between 
tRNA and aaRS, it is essential in terms of catalytic effi-
ciency for the aminoacylation reaction (31-33). The uni-
versal CCA 76 sequence is also involved in EF-Tu binding 
and during peptide bond formation by interacting with 
specific nucleotides of the 23S rRNA (17). Little is 
known about the precise role of the CCA 76 nucleotides 
during the editing reaction catalyzed by aaRSs. It has 
been shown that only chargeable tRNA Val mutants are 
able to stimulate the editing reaction of ValRS, suggesting 
that the enzyme required prior charging of tRNA 
(31,32,34). Although tRNA is not a strict prerequisite 
for the editing of both classes I and II aaRSs (26,35-37), 
its presence strongly stimulates editing (38). Remarkably, 
both classes of aaRSs use effectively the ability of the 
CCA 76 -end of tRNA to switch between a hairpin and a 
helical conformation during the aminoacylation and 
editing reactions. Our previous investigations have 
shown that the interaction between the tRNA Leu CCA 76 -
end and the CP1 domain of LeuRS is critical for 
tRNA-dependent editing (post-transfer and pre-transfer 
editing) (8). However, the molecular basis of the phenom-
enon is not yet understood in detail. Here, we extended the 
investigations to the three CCA 76 nucleotides and assayed 
the effect of mutations on the tRNA-dependent 
pre-transfer editing and post-transfer editing. 
We showed that the universally conserved A 76 is essen-
tial for tRNA Leu to trigger both aminoacylation and 
editing reaction of LeuRS. The mutants of tRNA Leu 
with any base substituted for A 76 showed significant de-
creases of aminoacylation properties and total loss of the 
ability to stimulate the editing activity and catalyze 
deacylation of pre-formed Ile-tRNA Leu . As a consequence 
of this loss of editing activity, two of these mutants 
(A76U, A76C) were misacylated by Ile. Mutations of the 
other bases of the CCA 76 -end had negative effects on the 
aminoacylation properties, ranging between 2-and 50-fold 
decreases of the catalytic efficiency of EcLeuRS, with the 
strongest effect being observed when C 75 and C 74 were 
substituted 
by 
G 75 
and 
G 74 , 
respectively. 
Correspondingly, the mutant A76G was totally inactive, 
showing that the bulky guanosine substitutions were the 
least accepted in the synthetic active site. The three guano-
sine mutants also decreased the deacylation of the 
mischarged Ile-tRNA Leu , but failed in misacylating 
tRNA Leu with Ile. Comparison of the global editing 
activity of EcLeuRS in the presence of the tRNA Leu 
mutants revealed that four mutations (C75A, C75U, 
C74A and C74U) led to an increase in the editing up to 
2-fold despite the fact that their accepting capacity with 
Leu were impaired during the aminoacylation reaction. 
EcLeuRS deacylated these mischarged mutants of 
tRNA Leu with Ile with unchanged ability, suggesting 
that these mutants of tRNA Leu preferred binding at the 
editing active site rather than at the synthetic site. Previous 
studies have shown that both classes of aaRSs use effect-
ively the ability of the CCA 76 -end of tRNA to switch </p>

<p>Table 4. k obs of AMP formation in the presence of different tran-
scripts of tRNA Leu isoacceptors or mutants </p>

<p>tRNA 
k obs (s À1 ) 
Relative k obs </p>

<p>tRNA Leu </p>

<p>GAG </p>

<p>4.42 ± 0.64 
1 
tRNA Leu 
GAG (G 1 -C 72 ) 
3.75 ± 0.50 
0.85 
tRNA Leu </p>

<p>CAG </p>

<p>4.54 ± 0.36 
1 
tRNA Leu 
CAG (G 1 -U 72 ) 
6.10 ± 0.81 
1.34 </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 20 8865 </p>

<p>between a hairpin and a helical conformation of aaRSs for 
aminoacylation and editing. In class I aaRSs, their 
cognate tRNA CCA 76 -ends adopt a regular helical con-
formation into the editing site of aaRSs, and a distorted 
hairpin conformation into the synthetic site (6). A mirror 
image is observed in class II aaRSs, as already seen for 
tRNA binding and amino acid activation. The stimulation 
of the editing activity of C75A, C75U, C74A and C74U 
mutants strongly suggests that these mutations may favor 
the helical conformation, which is more suitable for the 
editing reaction. Moreover, the fact that these mutated 
tRNAs are poorly aminoacylated in the synthetic active 
site may favor stagnation of the non-cognate adenylate 
into the synthetic active site and its subsequent editing 
by the tRNA-dependent pre-transfer editing also 
measured in the global editing assay. </p>

<p>The CCA 76 -end entrance pathway into editing domain of 
EcLeuRS critically contributes to protein synthesis fidelity </p>

<p>Despite the importance of the interaction between CCA 76 -
end of tRNA and the CP1 domain of class Ia aaRSs 
revealed by in vitro methods, the corresponding in vivo 
evidence is generally lacking. In the present work, we de-
veloped an efficient system with the combination of 
non-cognate Nva and leuS temperature-sensitive E. coli 
strain to assess the significance of LeuRS tRNA-
dependent editing in vivo. Our evaluation of the tRNA 
CCA 76 -end entrance pathway using the leuS 
temperature-sensitive KL231 strain revealed the following 
aspects. (i) Without or at a low concentration of 
non-cognate amino acid (e.g. 20 mM Nva here), 
mutation of pivotal residues controlling protein biosyn-
thesis fidelity had no obvious effect on the bacterial cell 
viability. The discrimination by EF-Tu and/or the 
ribosome may have prevented Nva mis-incorporation, or 
the E. coli cells could endure low level of Nva 
mis-incorporation at Leu codons; (ii) at extremely high 
concentrations of non-cognate amino acids, even the 
WT enzyme had no ability to prevent all the mis-activated 
amino acids from entering the newly synthesized polypep-
tide on the ribosome, and the mis-translation led to an 
obvious inhibitory effect on cell growth; (iii) our in vitro 
results were consistent with in vivo data, demonstrating the 
importance of conserved amino acid residues in aaRS and 
nucleotides in tRNA in protein synthesis quality control, 
especially under severe environmental stress. </p>

<p>Multiple steps to monitor and control the CCA acceptor 
sequence </p>

<p>As mentioned above, the trinucleotide CCA 76 sequence is 
present at the 3 0 terminus of all mature tRNAs. Despite 
this high conservation, transcripts of E. coli tRNA Val with 
altered 3 0 termini are readily aminoacylated and can 
function in polypeptide synthesis (32). Accordingly, the 
present study performed on LeuRS shows that the 
aminoacylation reaction admits some sequence flexibility 
at the CCA 76 end. Several CCA-mutated tRNAs can be 
efficiently aminoacylated, and LeuRS can even 
aminoacylate a tRNA Leu lacking the terminal adenosine, 
showing a remarkable plasticity of the synthetic site of </p>

<p>LeuRS and tRNA Leu acceptor end. Several studies 
suggest that the aminoacylation of similar molecules 
may occur naturally in vivo. Despite the high fidelity of 
the CCA-adding enzyme, in some conditions, CCase can 
add a wrong nucleotide to the 3 0 -end of the tRNA, leading 
to CCA-modified tRNAs (39). Moreover, mutations of 
CCase may exist in vivo with relaxed active sites as those 
engineered in vitro that lead to nucleotide mis-
incorporation at the end of tRNA (40). In some bacteria 
the CCA-adding activity is naturally split into a 
CC-adding enzyme and an A-adding enzyme (41). 
Therefore, a tRNA deprived of the terminal A 76 might 
temporarily exist in vivo and may be the substrate of 
LeuRS. 
However, if under these exceptional circumstances 
aminoacylation of CCA-mutated tRNAs can occur, 
these tRNAs would have to face additional discrimination 
processes based on EF-Tu recognition (42) and interaction 
with ribosomal RNA during translation (43). Both 
processes would monitor and exclude these molecules 
according 
to 
different 
nucleotide 
recognition 
specificities (32). 
In summary, the study highlighted the significant role of 
the conserved nucleotides from the CCA 76 -end and the 
strong collaboration with amino acid residues of the 
CP1 editing domain during the aminoacylation and 
editing catalysis. The CCA 76 nucleotides are critical for 
both aminoacylation and editing; and in combination 
with the amino acids located in the entrance path of the 
editing domain, they critically contribute to the fidelity of 
protein synthesis. It is a remarkable example of a con-
trol mechanism that prevent damaged tRNAs from 
entering the protein synthesis based on the single discrim-
ination of a triplet sequence that is universally found in all 
tRNAs. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank Dr Franck Martin for the help during 
the experiment. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Natural Science Foundation of China (Nos. 30930022 and 
31000355); Committee of Science and Technology in 
Shanghai (No. 09JC1415900); a Visiting Professorship 
for Senior International Scientists from the Chinese 
Academy of Sciences (No. 2009S2-19); Programme 
International de Coope´ration Scientifique from CNRS 
(Grant 3606). Funding for open access charge: Natural 
Science Foundation of China. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>

<p>8866 Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 20 </p>



<p>8868 Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 20 </p>

</text></tei>