<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3600596" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The molecular mechanism to regulate energy balance is not completely understood. Here we observed that 
Egr-1 expression in white adipose tissue (WAT) was highly correlated with dietary-induced obesity and 
insulin resistance both in mice and humans. Egr-1 null mice were protected from diet-induced obesity and 
obesity-associated pathologies such as fatty liver, insulin resistance, hyperlipidemia and hyperinsulinemia. 
This phenotype can be largely explained by the increase of energy expenditure in Egr-1 null mice. 
Characterization of these mice revealed that the expression of FOXC2 and its target genes were significantly 
elevated in white adipose tissues, leading to WAT energy expenditure instead of energy storage. Altogether, 
these studies suggest an important role for Egr-1, which, by repressing FOXC2 expression, promotes energy 
storage in WAT and favored the development of obesity under high energy intake. </p>

<p>diet-induced obesity and obesity-associated pathologies such as fatty 
liver, insulin resistance, hyperlipidemia and hyperinsulinemia. This 
phenotype can be largely explained by increase of energy expenditure 
in Egr-1 null mice. Characterization of these mice revealed that the 
expression of FOXC2 and its target genes was significantly elevated 
in white adipose tissues, which led WAT to expend instead to store 
energy. Taken together, these studies suggest an important role for 
Egr-1, which, by repressing FOXC2 expression, promotes energy 
storage in WAT and favors the development of obesity under high 
energy intake. </p>

<p>Results 
Egr-1 expression in white adipose tissue is associated with obesity 
and insulin resistance. As a stress response gene, Egr-1 is often 
rapidly and transiently activated by a variety of signals, including 
hypoxia, cytokines, growth factors and hormones </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>. Dietary-induced 
obesity is often associated with local hypoxia and inflammatory 
response in adipose tissues. To examine whether Egr-1 expression </p>

<p>in adipose is associated with BMI and insulin resistance, 48 Cau-
casian non-diabetic men underwent euglycemic-hyperinsulinemic 
clamp for insulin sensitivity and biopsy of subcutaneous abdo-
minal fat for real-time, quantitative PCR (QPCR). As shown in 
Fig. 1a&amp;b, Egr-1 mRNA level was highly positively correlated with 
BMI, but negatively correlated with glucose disposal rate. In another 
compared experiment, 22 lean persons (BMI 5 25 6 1.6) and 7 obese 
persons (BMI 5 55 6 8.7) underwent biopsy of subcutaneous 
abdominal fat for QPCR. As shown in Fig. 1c, Egr-1 mRNA level 
was 80 folds higher in obese group than that in lean group. To further 
confirm that dietary obesity induces Egr-1 expression in adipose 
tissues, we tested the effect of HF diet feeding on the expression of 
Egr-1 in C57BL/6J mice. As shown in Fig. S1a, the body weight was 
significantly increased after 20 weeks of HF diet feeding. In the 
meantime, the fast glucose started to increase at 12 weeks and 
further increased significantly at 20 weeks of HF diet feeding (Fig. 
S1b). The level of Egr-1 mRNA in WAT was markedly increased after 
12 weeks of high-fat feeding and further increased at 20 weeks of HF </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Egr-1 mRNA levels in WAT are associated with obesity and insulin resistance. (a&amp;b) Egr-1 mRNA levels in WAT from 48 Caucasian non-</p>

<p>diabetic men were measured by QPCR. Glucose disposal rate was measured by hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamps and the data on Rd were computed 
in mg/min/kg of lean body mass for those lean persons (n 5 48, BMI, 24.0 6 0.75). After log transformation, linear regression analysis revealed a strong 
correlation (r 
2 5 0.6838, p , 0.0001) between Egr-1 mRNA level in WAT and body mass index of the donor subject (a) and a weak negatively correlation 
(r 
2 5 0.2423, P 5 0.0023) between Egr-1 mRNA level in WAT and Glucose disposal rate (mg/min/kg) (b). (c) Egr-1 mRNA levels in WAT from lean 
(n 5 22, BMI, 24.0 6 0.75) and obese (n 5 7, BMI, 52 6 3.1) humans were measured by QPCR. (d). C57BL/6J mice were purchased from Jackson 
laboratories and divided into two groups fed with chow-diet or high-fat diet, respectively. Egr-1 mRNA level was examined by QPCR both in chow-fed or 
high-fat fed mice after 4, 12 and 20 weeks of feeding (n 5 5). Values were normalized by 18S and fold changes to 4-week, chow-fed group were represented. 
(e) Egr-1 mRNA levels in adipose tissues from ob/ob and its control mice. Male, 12-week-old mice were sacrificed and RNA was isolated from adipose 
tissues as indicated. QPCR was performed to measure Egr-1 mRNA levels using the primers as shown in Table S1. Data represent mean 6 SD, n 5 5. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1476 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01476 </p>

<p>
diet feeding, which was closely associated with dietary-induced 
obesity and insulin resistance (Fig. 1d). In contrast, no significant 
alteration in expression level of Egr-1 mRNA was observed in other 
tissues that also contribute to energy homeostasis including 
hypothalamus, liver, skeletal muscle, and adrenal upon high-fat 
feeding (data not shown). In ob/ob mice, Egr-1 mRNA level was 
significantly increased in visceral and subcutaneous WAT, but not 
in brown adipose, compared with control mice (Fig. 1e). Taken 
together, these results suggest that Egr-1 expression in WAT is 
highly associated with dietary-induced obesity and insulin resistance. </p>

<p>Loss of Egr-1 protects against diet-induced obesity. To define the 
functional relevance of dietary obesity-induced adipocyte Egr-1 
upregulation in mice, we challenged 9-to 10-week-old wild-type 
and Egr-1 null mice with a high-fat (HF) diet (60% calories from 
fat) for 15 weeks. The Egr-1 
2/2 mice showed blunted weight gain in 
response to this dietary challenge, which was evident after the first 5 
weeks of feeding (Fig. 2a). After 15 weeks, the wild-type mice showed 
105 6 13% weight gain, but the Egr-1 null mice gained only </p>

<p>one-third as much, 38 6 20%. The weight gain of the chow-fed 
Egr-1 
2/2 (26%) mice was also lower than that of wild-type (38%) 
mice, but the difference was not significant. This phenotype was 
observed in both male and female mice and in both mid-term 
feeding (12 weeks) and long-term feeding (20 weeks) (Fig. S2). The 
body-weight difference was largely due to a decrease in fat mass. 
Nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) analysis showed that the fat 
mass ratio in Egr-1 
2/2 mice was 61% lower than that in wild-type 
mice under HF diet feeding (Fig. 2b). The fat ratio of chow-fed Egr-
1 
2/2 (13%) mice was also lower than that of wild-type (23%) mice, 
but the difference was not significant. Adipocytes were enlarged in the 
white fat of the HF fed wild-type mice but were smaller in Egr-1 null 
mice (Fig. 2c). In brown fat, HF diet induced more lipid accumulation 
in wild-type mice, but not in Egr-1 null mice. The HF diet also 
induced fatty liver in the wild-type mice, but the livers of the HF 
fed Egr-1 
2/2 animals contained almost no visible lipid droplets, which 
were confirmed by marked differences in Oil Red O staining (Fig. 2c). 
Consistent with this, hepatic triglyceride and cholesterol contents 
were significantly lower in Egr-1 
2/2 mice (Fig. 2d&amp;e). </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Resistance of Egr-1 null mice to diet-induced obesity. (a) Growth curves of wild-type and Egr-1 </p>

<p>2/2 mice (n 5 3-6) fed chow or high-fat diet 
for 15 weeks. (b) Body fat mass was evaluated by NMR scanning (n 5 3-6) and the ratio of fat mass to body weight was shown. (c) White fat and 
brown fat pads were collected, fixed, and subjected to hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) staining (n 5 2/group). A representative image is shown 
(103 magnification); Livers were collected, fixed, and subjected to Oil Red O staining (103 magnification). (d&amp;e) Hepatic triglycerides (d) and 
Cholesterol (e) were measured (n 5 3-6). All data are expressed as the mean 6 SD; *P , 0.05; **P , 0.01. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1476 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01476 </p>

<p>
Loss of Egr-1 protects from diet-induced insulin resistance and 
hyperlipidemia. To further characterize the obesity resistant 
phenotype in Egr-1 
2/2 mice fed a HF diet, carbohydrate and lipid 
metabolism were analyzed. As expected, the leaner Egr-1 
2/2 mice 
showed greater insulin sensitivity. Their plasma glucose levels were 
not significantly different from those in wild-type mice on either 
chow or HF diet. However, plasma insulin levels were 9% lower in 
the chow-fed Egr-1 
2/2 mice compared to the wild-type mice, and 
were markedly lower (65%) in the HF diet-fed Egr-1 
2/2 mice than in 
HF-fed wild-type mice (Fig. 3a). As an indicator of body fat, 
consistent with their obesity, leptin level in wild-type mice was 
increased substantially (3-fold) by HF diet feeding. In comparison, 
basal level of leptin was lower in Egr-1 
2/2 mice than in wild-type 
mice and was not increased significantly by HF diet feeding (Fig. 3a). 
We next performed glucose and insulin tolerance tests. On chow-
diet, both wild-type and Egr-1 null mice showed normal response 
after glucose or insulin perfusion. However, the HF-fed Egr-1 </p>

<p>2/2 </p>

<p>mice showed relatively normal responses, while the HF-fed wild-
type mice showed insulin intolerance (Fig. 3b) and glucose 
intolerance (Fig. 3c). As expected, HF diet feeding induced 
hyperlipidemia in wild-type mice, while this was much attenuated 
in HF-fed Egr-1 null mice. Lipoprotein analysis revealed that on HF 
diet, Egr-1 
2/2 mice had substantially lower triglycerides and 
cholesterol in their VLDL and LDL/HDL fractions respectively 
compared with wild-type mice (Fig. 3d). These differences were 
not seen in the mice on chow diet (data not shown). Total plasma 
triglyceride and free fatty acid levels were not different in the wild-
type compared with Egr-1 null mice, indicating that the reduced fat 
weight was not secondary to decreased lipid availability. However, 
total plasma cholesterol levels were significantly decreased in Egr-
1 
2/2 mice compared with wild-type littermates (Fig. 3e). </p>

<p>Loss of Egr-1 increases energy expenditure. To examine whether 
obesity resistance in Egr-1 
2/2 mice was due to alterations in feeding 
behavior, food intake and fat absorption were measured. Despite of 
their inability to gain weight on HF diet, Egr-1 
2/2 mice exhibited a 
food intake per body weight that was comparable to that of wild-type 
mice fed the same diet (Fig. 4a). When integrated into a formula that 
takes into consideration food intake, stool output, and lipid content, 
no significant changes in fat absorption were observed in Egr-1 </p>

<p>2/2 </p>

<p>mice compared to wild-type mice both on chow and HF diet 
(Fig. 4b). These results indicated that resistance to obesity of Egr-1 
null mice was not due to decreased energy intake. Thus, their resis-
tance to diet induced obesity should be a consequence of increased in 
energy expenditure. This was confirmed by both direct and indirect 
approaches, including analysis of oxygen consumption, CO2 
generation and body temperature. The body temperature was 
higher in the HF fed Egr-1 null mice compared to that in HF fed 
wild-type mice (Fig. 4c). HF-fed Egr-1 
2/2 mice showed significantly 
higher O2 consumption (Fig. 4d and Fig. S3a)) and CO2 generation 
than control wild-type littermates over 24 h (Fig. 4e and Fig. S3b). 
We also monitored the physical activity during a three-day period 
and did not observe any difference in the movement rate between 
Egr-1 
2/2 and wild-type mice (Fig. 4f and Fig. S3c)). Together, these 
results indicated that resistance to obesity of Egr-1 
2/2 mice was due 
to increased energy expenditure by increasing metabolic rate. </p>

<p>Loss of Egr-1 increases FOXC2 expression in white adipose 
tissues. It was interestingly to note that the phenotype of Egr-1 </p>

<p>2/2 </p>

<p>mice resistant to obesity is very similar to that of aP2-FOXC2 
transgenic mice </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>. Thus, we measured FOXC2 mRNA levels in 
liver, muscle, white and brown fats from wild-type and Egr-1 null 
mice. At first, we confirmed the Egr-1 expression in adipose from 
wild-type and Egr-1 null mice by Northern blot (Fig. 5a). 
Interestingly, FOXC2 was increased by 2 folds in white fat of Egr-1 
null mice on chow diet and further increased by 4 folds by HF diet 
feeding. FOXC2 was not expressed in liver, muscle and brown fat </p>

<p>(Fig. 5b). To further confirm the expression changes of FOXC2 in 
Egr-1 
2/2 white fat, we measured FOXC2 protein levels by Western 
blotting. As shown in Fig. 5c, FOXC2 protein is expressed in white 
fat, but not in liver and muscle. Consistent with its mRNA changes, 
FOXC2 protein was also increased in the white fat of Egr-1 
2/2 mice 
both on chow diet and HF diet feeding. </p>

<p>Loss of Egr-1 increases UCP1 expression in white adipose tissues. 
As reported, WAT in mice with an overexpression of FOXC2 
acquired certain BAT-like properties with increased expression of 
PGC1, UCP1 and cAMP pathway proteins such as b1-adrenoceptor 
(b1-AR) 
20 . So we have measured the expression of b1-AR, PGC-1a, 
PGC1b and UCP1 in WAT from both wild-type and Egr-1 null mice 
under chow and HF diet feeding by QPCR. As showed in Fig. 6a, the 
expression of b1-AR was significantly increased in Egr-1 null WAT 
compared that in wild-type WAT under both chow and HF diet 
feeding. Though PGC1a and PGC1b were not changed in WAT 
under chow diet feeding, they were increased in Egr-1 null WAT 
under HF diet feeding. UCP1 was not expressed in WAT from both 
wild-type and Egr-1 null mice under chow diet, but UCP1 expression 
was higher in Egr-1 null WAT than that in wild-type WAT under HF 
diet feeding, which was further confirmed by Western blot 
(Fig. 6b&amp;c). These results suggest the WAT in Egr-1 null mice 
gains some BAT-like features under HF diet feeding. </p>

<p>Loss of Egr-1 decreases inflammatory cytokine production in 
white adipose tissues. It is well documented that obesity is an 
inflammatory condition leading to chronic activation of the innate 
immune system and Egr-1 is an inflammatory transcription factor 
controlling many cytokines expression including TNFa, PAI-1 etc </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>. 
Therefore, we measured the plasma levels of these cytokines as well as 
their mRNA levels. As expected, the production of TNFa was 
increased after HF diet feeding in wild-type mice, but not in Egr-
1 
2/2 mice (Fig. 7a). PAI-1 level was also increased in wild-type mice 
after HF diet feeding. The PAI-1 level was lower in HF diet-fed Egr-1 
null mice, but no statistical significance. The production of 
adiponectin was not changed between two genotypes under both 
chow and HF diet feeding. Consistent with this, the TNFa mRNA 
level was also significantly increased in wild-type WAT after HF diet 
feeding, but not in Egr-1 
2/2 WAT (Fig. 7b). </p>

<p>Discussion 
Through the story of evolution, animals and humans have developed 
potent and redundant mechanisms that promote the accumulation 
of energy in fat tissue during periods of ''feast'', thus enabling survival 
during periods of ''famine'' </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>. As a consequence, obesity has reached 
epidemic proportions in the current ''obesigenic'' environment of 
readily available high-energy foods and little need for physical activ-
ity </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>. Understanding the regulatory pathways that govern energy 
storage (i.e., fat accumulation) versus energy expenditure (i.e., fat 
oxidation) is a key to understanding the diseases of obesity and its 
associated metabolic syndrome. Here we demonstrate a key role of 
dietary obesity-induced Egr-1 in adipocytes in the preservation and 
progression of obesity and obesity-associated pathologies, such as 
fatty liver, hyperlipidemia, and insulin resistance. Our findings sup-
port a model wherein nutrition overload leads to significant expan-
sion of adipose tissue, which further induces Egr-1 expression 
probably by creating a stress and hypoxic environment. Egr-1 
expression not only induces the synthesis and release of adipokines, 
such as TNFa, to promote insulin resistance, but also suppresses the 
FOXC2-cAMP-PKA metabolic regulatory system to facilitate energy 
storage and promote the development of obesity and obesity-assoc-
iated pathologies (Fig. 8). 
As an early response gene, Egr-1 is often rapidly and transiently 
activated by a variety of signals including stress, growth factors, </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1476 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01476 </p>

<p>
Figure 3 | Improvement of insulin sensitivity and lipid profiles in Egr-1 null mice. (a) Plasma glucose, insulin and leptin levels in chow-fed or high fat </p>

<p>fed, overnight fasted mice (n 5 6). (b) Plasma glucose levels after an acute injection of insulin (0.75 UI/kg) in chow-fed or high-fat fed, overnight 
fasted mice (n 5 5-8). (c) Plasma glucose levels after a glucose load (2 g/kg) in chow fed or high-fat fed, overnight fasted mice (n 5 5). 
(d) Measurements of triglycerides and cholesterol in fractionated lipoproteins were taken from wild-type and Egr-1 
2/2 mice after high-fat feeding (n 5 5). 
(e) Plasma levels of triglycerides, cholesterol and free fatty acids in chow fed or high fat fed, overnight fasted mice (n 5 6). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1476 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01476 </p>

<p>
cytokines and hormones. And as a transcription factor, Egr-1 is able 
to regulate many genes expression and thus is involved in the regu-
lation of cell growth, differentiation and apoptosis. Here we found 
sustained expression of Egr-1 in WAT under obese and diabetic 
conditions both in mice and human. The sustained expression of 
Egr-1 may be caused by nutrition overload-created stress and hyp-
oxic environment in WAT or by obesity-associated hyperinsuline-
mia. It was previously reported that Egr-1 remains insulin sensitive 
in insulin-resistant adipocytes </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>. We further found that the sustained 
expression of Egr-1 in adipocytes facilitated energy storage and thus 
promoted the development of obesity and obesity-associated pathol-
ogies, so that loss of Egr-1 led to brown adipose-like change of WAT 
(Fig. 6), leading to energy expenditure over energy storage and thus </p>

<p>protected mice from nutrition overload-induced obesity and obesity-
associated pathologies. It is interesting to note that dietary obesity-
induced Hif1a in adipocytes also restricts fatty acid oxidation and 
energy expenditure via suppression of the Sirt2-NAD1 system </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>, 
suggesting there are some redundant mechanisms to promote energy 
storage under nutrition overload status. To further examine the spe-
cific effect of Egr-1 overexpression in adipocytes, we have generated 
an adipocyte-specific Egr-1 transgenic mouse line by using aP2 pro-
moter (Fig. S4). Interestingly, forced expression of Egr-1 in adipo-
cytes without nutrition overload did not cause the changes of weight 
gain and insulin sensitivity, suggesting that Egr-1 participates in the 
management of energy only under chronic nutrition overload-
induced stress. </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Increased energy expenditure in Egr-1 </p>

<p>2/2 mice. (a) Food intake of wild-type and Egr-1 
2/2 mice (n 5 6) at first week and ninth week of feeding. 
(b) Fat absorption of wild-type and Egr-1 
2/2 mice (n 5 6) measured on week 9 of feeding. Fat absorption 5 ([food intake 3 food lipid 
content]-[stool output 3 stool lipid content])/(food intake 3 food lipid content) 3 100. (c) Rectal temperature was measured at week 9 of feeding in 
chow-fed or high-fat fed mice. (d) Oxygen consumption (VO 2 ) and (e) carbon dioxide production (VCO 2 ) were measured by metabolic cage system 
(CLAMS, Columbia Instrument) during a period of three days after 16 week of high-fat feeding (n 5 5). Values from nighttime and daytime were 
presented. Values are expressed as the mean 6 SD. (*, P , 0.001). (f) Physical activity was measured with CLAMS. The average movement counts during 
the nighttime and daytime were presented. </p>

<p>Figure 5 | FOXC2 expression was increased in WAT from Egr-1 </p>

<p>2/2 mice. (a) Expression of Egr-1 in WAT from high-fat fed wild-type and 
Egr-1 null mice was examined by Northern blotting. (b) Expression of FOXC2 in WAT, BAT, liver and muscle from chow-fed or high-fat fed mice was 
analyzed by QPCR. Values are normalized by 18S. (c) Expression of FOXC2 protein in WAT was analyzed by Western blotting. Left: a 53-Kd band was 
detected only in WAT, but not in liver and muscle by FOXC2 antibody; Middle: 3 samples of WAT from each group were run on SDS-PAGE and detected 
by FOXC2 antibody; Right: Fold changes of FOXC2 protein in WAT from chow-fed or high-fat fed mice were determined by densitometry and 
normalized to b-actin. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1476 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01476 </p>

<p>
Mechanistically, we found that the Egr-1-dependent effects on 
adipocyte lipid catabolism were mediated through regulation of the 
FOXC2-cAMP-PKA pathway. FOXC2 is a member of forkhead tran-
scription factors and normally expressed only in adipose tissue. 
FOXC2 promoter polymorphism and abnormal expression had been 
shown associated with obesity and insulin resistance </p>

<p>26-29 </p>

<p>. Over-
expression of FOXC2 in adipose tissue causes a profound gene </p>

<p>expression change including b-adrenergic receptors, PPARs and 
PGC-1, and BAT-specific gene UCP1 in WAT depot, which drives 
WAT depot to acquire a brown fat-like histology and to dissipate 
energy rather than to store energy </p>

<p>20,30,31 </p>

<p>. To address the molecular 
mechanisms underlying the phenotype of Egr-1 
2/2 mice resistant to 
diet-induced obesity, we found a significant increase in the express-
ion of FOXC2 in WAT of Egr-1 
2/2 mice on both chow diet and HF </p>

<p>Figure 6 | Egr-1 null WAT expressed some BAT-specific genes under HF diet feeding. (a) Expression of b1-AR, PGC1a, PGC1b and UCP1 in WAT </p>

<p>from both wild-type (WT) and Egr-1 null mice (KO) under both chow or HF diet feeding was analyzed by QPCR. Values are normalized by 18S. 
(b) Expression of UCP1 protein in WAT from both wild-type (WT) and Egr-1 null mice (KO) under HF diet feeding was analyzed by Western blotting with 
UCP1 antibody (Sigma). (c) Fold changes of UCP1 protein in WAT high-fat fed mice were determined by densitometry and normalized to b-actin. </p>

<p>Figure 7 | Alteration of Adipocytokines in Egr-1 </p>

<p>2/2 mice. (a) Plasma level of TNFa was measured by an ELISA kit from eBiosense; Plasma levels of 
PAI-1 and adiponectin were measured by a luminex kit from LINCO (n 5 3-6). (b) mRNA levels of TNFa, PAI-1 and adiponectin in WAT from chow-fed 
or high-fat fed mice were analyzed by QPCR. Values are normalized by 18S rRNA. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1476 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01476 </p>

<p>
diet. Consistently, Egr-1 null WAT expressed some BAT-specific 
genes such as UCP1 and PGC1 under HF diet feeding. These results 
suggest that Egr-1 may function as a repressor of FOXC2 gene 
expression and suppresse FOXC2-mediated energy expenditure pro-
gram in WAT to facilitate energy storage in WAT under high caloric 
intake. Further investigation to uncover the mechanisms by which 
Egr-1 regulates FOXC2 expression will help to understand the reg-
ulatory networks underlying obesity and obesity-associated pathol-
ogies. A recent report showed that Egr-1 promotes insulin resistance 
under chronic high-insulin-induced stress by controlling PI3K/Akt 
and MAPK signal balance via direct induction of the gene expression 
of PTEN and GGPPS in adipocytes </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>, suggesting that Egr-1 may 
regulate glucose and lipid metabolisms through multiple mechan-
isms. 
As the body's largest endocrine organ and one of the most import-
ant insulin targeting tissues, adipose tissue has a critical role in insu-
lin sensitivity and glucose homeostasis </p>

<p>32,33 </p>

<p>. Although we cannot at 
present fully exclude a contribution of tissues beyond WAT to the 
metabolic alterations in Egr-1 
2/2 mice, several arguments support 
the concept that WAT play a predominant role. First, thermogenic 
effectors such as PGC-1 and UCP-1 were increased in WAT but not 
in BAT and skeletal muscle. Second, the absence of major changes in 
non-adipose-derived endocrine modulators of adaptive thermogen-
esis and fat accumulation suggests that these metabolic alterations 
were not due to neuroendocrine defects. Finally, ingestion of a 
chronic high-fat diet induced changes in Egr-1 expression only in 
WAT, but not in other organs involved in metabolism (hypothal-
amus, adrenal and liver). A recent study also supported this con-
cept 
18 . Yu et al. inhibited Egr-1 transcriptional activity in diabetic db/ 
db mice by injecting adenovirus carrying dominant-negative Egr-1 
(dnEgr-1) into epididymal fat pads, which is the predominant fat 
tissue in mice intra-abdominal cavity. They found that expression of 
dnEgr-1 epididymal fat was able to significantly improve glucose 
tolerance and increase insulin sensitivity in db/db mice </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>. 
High-fat feeding causes adipose expansion not only by lipid accu-
mulation but also by adipogenesis. As reported, Egr-2, another </p>

<p>member in Egr family, is an important regulator of adipogenesis </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>. 
Boyle et al. reported that Egr-1 and Egr-2 exert opposing influence on 
adipocyte differentiation </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>. We found that Egr-1, -2 and -3 were all 
rapidly induced and transiently expressed at early stage during 3T3-
L1 adipogenesis. The transient expression of Egr-1 was required for 
3T3-L1 adipogenesis as loss of Egr-1 decreased adipogenesis (Fig. 
S5). So the reduction of adipogenesis in Egr-1 null mice may also 
contribute to its lean phenotype. 
In conclusion, our work identified Egr-1 as a central regulator of 
adipocyte energy storage. Egr-1 mediates these effects, at least in part, 
by interfering with the FOXC2-cAMP-PKA pathway, thereby cre-
ating a metabolic state permissive for the development of obesity in 
the face of nutrient overload. Since adipose Egr-1 accumulation in 
human obese subjects correlates with obesity and insulin resistance, 
intervention of Egr-1 activity may represent a therapeutic approach 
for obesity in humans. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Human study. Volunteers were recruited through public advertisement and were 
screened for hematological and blood chemistry abnormalities. The study was 
approved by the Institutional Review Board of the University of Texas Southwestern 
Medical Center at Dallas. All subjects signed a written informed consent. Subjects 
with diabetes mellitus and other endocrine disorders, coronary heart disease, and 
liver function test abnormalities, and those receiving any form of therapies, were 
excluded from the study. At the time of enrollment, each volunteer was administered 
a health history questionnaire. Height, weight, and blood pressure measurements 
were taken on all of the subjects. Hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamps was 
performed as described previously </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>. The rate of glucose disposal (Rd) was calculated 
by subtracting the urinary glucose excretion from the Ra and using space correction. 
The data on Rd were computed in mg/min/kg of lean body mass. Samples of 
subcutaneous adipose tissue are taken from both the abdomen and right buttock 
under local anesthesia using a biopsy needle. About 140 mg of subcutaneous adipose 
tissue is taken from each site and QPCR was performed as described below. </p>

<p>Animal experiments. The generation of the Egr-1 null mouse line has been described 
previously </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>. Egr-1 
1/2 breeding pairs was kindly provided by Dr. David Pinsky. Egr-1 
null mice are on mixed C57BL/6/129/Sv backgrounds and have been backcrossed to 
C57BL/6J background more than 10 generations. Age-and sex-matched groups of 8-
to 9-week-old wild-type and Egr-1 
2/2 siblings derived from heterozygous intercrosses 
of Egr-1 
1/2 were used in the experiments. C57BL/6J mice used in the chronic high-fat 
feeding study were purchased from Jackson Laboratories (Bar Harbor, Maine, USA). 
All mice were housed in a temperature-controlled environment with 12 hr light/dark 
cycles. For high-fat diet experiments, one group of mice were fed a chow diet 
(D12450B, Research Diets, New Brunswick, NJ) containing 10 kcal% fat and the 
other group were fed a high-fat diet (D12492) containing 60 kcal% fat for 12 to 20 
weeks. Body weight was recorded weekly, and food intake and fast blood glucose were 
measured biweekly. Total body fat mass was analyzed by NMR using the Minispec mq 
spectrometer (Bruker). Rectal temperature was measured using Thermalert 
(Physitemp, Clifton, NJ, USA). At the end of the feeding period, mice were 
anesthetized with halothane and exsanguinated via the ascending vena cava prior to 
organ harvest. Blood was kept on ice in heparin-coated tubes (Microvette 500 LH; 
Sarstedt, Inc.) and centrifuged (1500 3 g for 15 min at 4uC), and the plasma was 
stored at 220uC until analysis. Tissues were harvested for analyses as described 
below. All experiments were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Research 
Advisory Committee at the University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center. </p>

<p>Lipid absorption. In week 10 of high-fat diet study, stools were collected from 
individually housed mice over 72 h. Lipid content of diets and stools was determined 
gravimetrically and used to calculate the fraction of consumed lipid that was absorbed 
as described in Figure 1B </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Liver triglycerides and cholesterol. Cholesterol was extracted from saponified liver 
(0.3 g) with petroleum ether and quantitated by gas chromatography using 
stigmasterol as an internal standard. Other lipids were extracted from liver (0.2 g) in 
chloroform:methanol (251, v/v). Extracts were then washed once in 50 mM NaCl and 
twice in 0.36 M CaCl 2 /methanol. The organic phase was separated and brought up to 
5 ml with chloroform. Ten microliters of chloroform:Triton X-114 (151, v/v) were 
added to duplicate 100 ml aliquots of each extract and standards (Sigma Diagnostics), 
which were then air dried overnight. Colorimetric enzymatic assays were performed 
using 1 ml triglyceride reagent (ThermoTrace). After 20 min, optical densities of 
each sample were read at 520 nm and compared to prepared standards. </p>

<p>Plasma analyses and glucose and insulin tolerance. For glucose tolerance, mice were 
fasted overnight before receiving an intraperitoneal injection of 20% D-glucose 
(Sigma) (2 g/kg body weight). At 0, 15, 30, 60, 90, and 120 min after injection, 
5-10 ml of blood was drawn from the tail and blood glucose levels assayed using an 
Elite XL Glucometer (Bayer). For insulin tolerance, mice were fasted for 6 h before 
receiving an intraperitoneal injection of insulin 10 U/ml (sigma) (0.75 U/kg body </p>

<p>Figure 8 | Schematic representation of Egr-1 mediated obesity model. </p>

<p>Nutrition overload leads to significant expansion of adipose tissue, which 
further induces Egr-1 expression probably by creating a stress and hypoxic 
environment. Egr-1 expression not only induces the synthesis and release 
of adipokines, such as TNFa, to promote insulin resistance, but also 
suppresses the FOXC2-cAMP-PKA metabolic regulatory system to 
facilitate energy storage and promote the development of obesity and 
obesity-associated pathologies. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1476 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01476 </p>

<p>
weight). Then the blood glucose levels were assayed following the procedures above. 
Different enzymatic assays were used for each analyte, including total cholesterol 
(Roche Diagnostics), plasma triglycerides (ThermoTrace), free fatty acids (Roche). 
Plasma lipoprotein levels were analyzed by fast protein liquid chromatography using 
two serial Superose HR6 columns, followed by enzymatic analysis of their cholesterol 
and triglyceride contents using the kits described above. Plasma leptin, insulin, 
adiponectin, tPAI-1 were determined by using Lincoplex Luminex kit (LINCO 
Research, St. Charles, Missouri, USA). TNFa level was determined using mouse 
TNFa ELISA Kit (eBioscience, Boston, MA, USA). </p>

<p>Metabolic rate and movement measurements. Metabolic monitoring was 
performed using a Comprehensive Lab Animal Monitoring System (CLAMS, 
Columbia Instruments) that simultaneously measures whole-body O 2 consumption 
and physical movements for 16 mice. Mice were acclimated in the monitoring 
chambers for 2 days before the experiment to minimize the changes in housing 
environments. Data was collected every 48 min for each mouse over a period of 3 
days. Metabolic rate and physical activity were averaged for the whole study period 
with the exception of the first five data points that tend to be influenced by animal 
handling at the beginning of studies. </p>

<p>Real-time PCR analysis. Total RNA was extracted from tissues using RNA STAT-60 
(Tel-Test, Inc.), treated with DNase I (RNase-free, Roche Molecular Biochemicals), 
and reversely transcribed into cDNA with random hexamers using the SuperScript II 
First-Strand Synthesis System (Invitrogen). Primers for each mRNA were designed 
using <rs type="software">Primer Express Software</rs> (PerkinElmer Life Sciences) based on sequence data 
from GenBankTM (Table S1 and ref. 38) and were validated as described </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>. Real-time 
PCR reactions contained 10-25 ng cDNA, 150 nM of each primer, and 5 ml 2X-Jump 
Start SYBR Green PCR Master Mix (Sigma) in 10 ml total volume. PCR reactions were 
performed in triplicate using an Applied Biosystems Prism 7900 HT instrument. 
Relative mRNA levels were calculated using either the comparative C T or standard 
curve methods normalized to cyclophilin mRNA or 18S RNA, respectively. </p>

<p>Western blotting and northern blotting. Proteins were isolated by the kit from 
Perkin Elmar and resolved on a 12% SDS-polyacrylamide gel, and electrotransferred 
to a PVDF membrane (Amersham). The membrane was then hybridized with rabbit 
anti-mouse FOXC2 (Chemicon, Temecula, CA), UCP-1 (Sigma) at a 151000 dilution, 
followed by secondary antibody incubation at a 151000 dilution. FOXC2 and UCP-1-
specific bands were detected by chemiluminescence (ECL kit, Amersham). Northern 
blotting was performed as described previously </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Histological procedures. Tissues were dissected and fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde 
overnight and rinsed with phosphate-buffered saline. White and brown fat were 
subsequently dehydrated and embedded in plastic (JB-4, Electron Microscopy 
Sciences) and sectioned at 1.5 mm for H&amp;E staining. For oil red O staining, Liver was 
incubated in 10% sucrose, paraffin embedded, and sectioned at 4 mm for Oil Red O 
staining. Sections were examined under a bright-field microscope at 1003 
magnification. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses. Values are expressed as Mean 6 standard error (SD). Significant 
differences between mean values were evaluated using two-tailed, unpaired Student's 
t test (when two groups were analyzed) or one-way ANOVA followed by Student 
Newman-Keuls test (for three or more groups). P , 0.05 was considered significant. </p>

<p> </p>

<p>
phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase/Akt signaling pathway. Circ Res. 89, 1058-1064 
(2001). </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Drs. Jian Liang, Angie Bookout, Vicky Lin, Ms. Norma Anderson and Donna 
Floyd for technical helps on animal experiments. We also thank Drs. David J. Mangelsdorf 
and Steven A. Kliewer for helpful discussion. M.F. is a recipient of a Junior Faculty Award 
from American Diabetes Association (ADA). This work was supported by ADA 
(7-03-JF-18 to M.F.) and National Institutes Health Grants (HL068878 and HL03676 to 
Y.E.C., DK072158 to N.A. &amp; M.C.). </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>M.F. and J.Z. designed, performed the experiments and wrote the manuscript; Y.Z. and T.S. 
helped with the animal experiments; G.F. and S.H. did the UCP1 Western blot; M.C. and </p>

<p>N.A. provided the human data; D.F., H.-B. X. and Y.E.C. provided helpful discussion and 
revised the manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>License: This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this 
license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Zhang, J.F. et al. Dietary obesity-induced Egr-1 in adipocytes 
facilitates energy storage via suppression of FOXC2. Sci. Rep. 3, 1476; DOI:10.1038/ 
srep01476 (2013). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1476 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01476 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>