<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3031000" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>To confirm the effect of 7-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV7), pneumococcal 
nasopharyngeal (NP) carriage was compared between vaccinated (3 + 1 doses PCV7) and 
non-vaccinated children. Vaccinated subjects were recruited from highly vaccinated 
regions (≥ 60%), Seoul and Incheon whereas control subjects were recruited from Jeju 
Island where vaccination rates are low (&lt; 15%). NP swabs were obtained from 400 
children aged 18-59 months. Serotype and antibiotic susceptibility was analyzed. 
Pneumococcal carriage rate was 18.0% (36/200) and 31.5% (63/200) for the vaccinated 
and control group, respectively. Among those vaccinated, 41.7% (15/36) of the serotypes 
were vaccine-related type (VRT: 6A, 6C, 19A) with the most common serotype 6C. The 
next common type was non-typable/non-capsule 30.6% (11/36) followed by non-vaccine 
type 16.7% (6/36) and vaccine type (VT) serotypes were found in only 11.1% (4/36). In 
contrast, 52.4% (33/63) of the isolates in the control group were VT. Resistance rates for 
penicillin and erythromycin were lower in the vaccine group (vaccine vs control; penicillin 
45.2% vs 71.4%, erythromycin 74.2% vs 90.5%, P &lt; 0.05). Multi-drug resistance was 
also lower in vaccinated subjects (vaccine vs control; 45.2% vs 69.8%, P &lt; 0.05). PCV7 
reduces carriage in VT which leads to replacement of pneumococci by antibiotic susceptible 
VRT or non-vaccine type strains. </p>

<p>Streptococcus pneumoniae (pneumococcus) is an important 
cause of meningitis, pneumonia, and bacteremia, especially 
among young children and older adults (1). Pneumococcal con-
jugate vaccines were developed to prevent invasive pneumo-
coccal diseases (IPD), and after the introduction of the 7-valent 
pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV7, Prevenar </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, Pfizer Inc, 
Philadelphia, PA, USA), a substantial decrease in incidence of 
IPD has been reported in the target population of age &lt; 5 yr (2). 
PCV7 also showed a herd effect among non-vaccinated popu-
lations by reducing nasopharyngeal (NP) colonization and trans-</p>

<p>mission of vaccine-type (VT) pneumococci from vaccinated chil-
dren (3). Since NP carriage serves as the reservoir of pneumococ-
cal transmission in the community and is the immediate source 
of IPD in the host (4), many studies have been done about the 
impact of PCV7 on NP pneumococcal carriage rate (5, 6). 
Up to date there are few data on the epidemiology of pneu-
mococcal diseases in Asia and especially about the impact of 
PCV7 on carriage. In a multicenter, prospective observational 
study, we studied the effect of PCV7 on pneumococcal NP car-
riage by comparing the differences in carriage rates, pneumo-
coccal serotypes and antibiotic sensitivity between vaccinated 
children and non-vaccinated controls. </p>

<p>Kim K-H, et al. • Pneumococcal Nasopharyngeal Carriage in Korean Children </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>DOI: 10.3346/jkms.2011.26.2.184 </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study design and subjects 
This study was a multicenter, prospective observational study of 
the epidemiology of NP carriage. Healthy children aged 18-59 
months attending daycare centers for more than 4 hr a day, five 
days a week in Seoul, Incheon and Jeju Island were recruited. 
Subjects of the vaccinated group were recruited from Seoul and 
Incheon and the control group was recruited from Jeju Island. 
The regional difference in recruitment was due to distinct dif-
ferences in vaccination rates between the regions. PCV7 is not 
yet included in the national immunization program and vacci-
nation rates show a difference between regions in Korea; vacci-
nation rates for PCV7 in Seoul and Incheon are more than 60%, 
whereas the vaccination rate in Jeju Island is lower than 15%. 
Children fully vaccinated with 3 primary doses and 1 booster 
dose of PCV7 were enrolled in the vaccinated group and chil-
dren with no vaccination history of PCV7 were enrolled in the 
control group from June to December, 2008. 
Subjects were excluded if they had 1) febrile illness, 2) pres-
ent respiratory illness, 3) antibiotics within 7 days before enroll-
ment, 4) immunodeficiency status or 5) nephrotic syndrome. </p>

<p>Cultures of nasopharyngeal samples 
NP samples were collected from subjects by trained physicians 
using flexible pediatric calcium alginate swab (Fisher Scientific, 
Pittsburgh, PA, USA). Swabs were inserted into the posterior na-
sopharynx, rotated 180 degrees or left in place for &gt; 5 sec, removed 
and placed in 1.0 mL skim milk or STGG (skim milk, tryptone-
glucose-glycerin) transport medium (7). NP swabs were direct-
ly transported in ice to the local laboratory, vortexed and frozen 
at -70°C until analysis. 
After fully thawing the frozen specimen at room temperature, 
the specimen was mixed thoroughly using a vortex. Each speci-
men was inoculated onto a 5% defibrinated horse or sheep blood 
agar plate (including crystal violet and nalidixic acid) and incu-
bated for 24-72 hr at 37°C in 5% CO2 chamber. Identification of 
S. pneumoniae was based on the presence of α-hemolysis and 
inhibition by optochin. For each detected isolate, the serotype 
and antibiotic susceptibility were determined. </p>

<p>Serotyping 
Serotyping was done with the multibead assay method (8) at 
the University of Alabama at Birmingham, AL, USA. Serotypes 
were classified as vaccine type (VT; 4, 6B, 9V, 14, 18C, 19F, and 
23F), vaccine-related serotype (VRT; 6A, 6C, 6D, and 19A), non-
vaccine type (NVT) and non-typable/non-capsulated (NT/NC). 
PCR was additionally done for isolates classified as 6A to differ-
entiate these isolates from 6C and 6D as previously described 
(9, 10). </p>

<p>Antibiotic susceptibility test 
Minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) was determined by 
broth microdilution, according to the guidelines of the Clinical 
and Laboratory Standards Institute (11) at the Catholic Univer-
sity of Korea, Incheon St. Mary's Hospital. In vitro susceptibility 
was tested for four antimicrobial agents including penicillin 
(oral penicillin V criteria), amoxicillin, erythromycin and cefa-
clor. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Differences in carriage rates and serotypes between the vacci-
nated group and control group were assessed using Fisher's ex-
act test or chi-squared test, as appropriate by <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> for Windows 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 11.5</rs> software package; SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA). These 
tests were also used to determine the differences in antibiotic 
resistance. </p>

<p>Ethics statements 
The study protocol was approved by the institutional review 
board at Ewha Womans University Mokdong Hospital (Seoul, 
Korea), the Catholic University of Korea, Incheon St. Mary's Hos-
pital (Incheon, Korea), and Jeju National University Hospital 
(Jeju, Korea) (IRB registration number-OCMC08BR013). An in-
formed consent was obtained from parents or guardians of all 
subjected children before enrollment. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Demographic characteristics of subjects 
Two-hundred children were enrolled in the vaccinated group 
and 200 children in the control group. The age (standard devia-
tion) of the subjects in vaccine group and control group was 
35.2 (11.6) months and 42.3 (10.5) months, respectively. The 
male subjects were 47.5% (95/200) in the vaccine group and 
53.5% (107/200) in the control group. There was no difference 
in gender distribution between study group and control group. </p>

<p>Carriage rate and Serotype distribution 
Pneumococcal carriage rate was lower in the vaccinated group 
compared with the control group (18.0% [36/200] vs 31.5% [63/ 
200] [P &lt; 0.05]) (Table 1). There was a distinct difference in pro-
portion of VT and VRT serotypes between the vaccinated and 
control group (P &lt; 0.05) (Table 1). Among the isolates from vac-
cinated group, 41.7% (15/36) of the serotypes were VRT (6A, 6C, 
19A). The next common serotypes were composed of NT/NC 
by 30.6% (11/36), 16.7% (6/36) were NVT and only 11.1% (4/36) 
were VT (6B, 19F, and 23F). Serotype 6C (16.7%, 6/36) was the 
most common serotype followed by 6A (13.9%, 5/36) in the vac-
cinated group. Among all vaccinated subjects, the pneumococ-
cal carriage rates for VT and VRT were 2.0% (4/200) and 7.5% 
(15/200), respectively. </p>

<p>Kim K-H, et al. • Pneumococcal Nasopharyngeal Carriage in Korean Children </p>



<p>DOI: 10.3346/jkms.2011.26.2.184 </p>

<p>In contrast, a majority of the isolates in the control group were 
VT by 52.4% (33/63), 14.3% (9/63) of the isolates were VRT and </p>

<p>among these serotypes, two of the isolates were determined as 
6D. This serotype has recently been discovered from natural 
pneumococcal isolates in two distant parts of the world, includ-
ing this study (9, 12). NT/NC isolates were also a large propor-
tion of the control group (22.2%, 14/63). Serotypes 14 (14.3%, 
9/63), 6B (12.7%, 8/63), 23F (12.7%, 8/63) and 19F (11.1%, 7/63) 
were the most common serotypes in the control group. The car-
riage rates for VT and VRT among all control subjects were 16.5% 
(33/200) and 4.5% (9/200), respectively. </p>

<p>Antibiotic susceptibility test 
The antibiotic susceptibility test was done for 31 isolates in the 
vaccinated group and 63 isolates of the control group. Accord-
ing to the antibiotic susceptibility analysis, regardless of sero-
type, the resistance rates for penicillin and erythromycin were 
lower in the vaccine group (vaccine vs control; penicillin 45.2% 
vs 71.4%, erythromycin 74.2% vs 90.5%, P &lt; 0.05) (Table 2). There 
was no difference in resistance rate between the vaccine and 
control group for amoxicillin and cefaclor (vaccine vs control; 
amoxicillin 22.6% vs 19.0%, cefaclor 96.8% vs 96.8%). Among all 
pneumococcal isolates, 61.7% (58/94) were found to be multi-
drug resistant strains (MDR, resistant to three or more classes 
of antimicrobial agents) (Table 3). In a comparison between the 
two study groups, more MDR strains were detected in the con-
trol group (vaccine vs control; 45.2% vs 69.8%, P &lt; 0.05). 
When the strains were classified according to serotype, all VT 
strains isolated in vaccinated subjects showed high resistance 
to penicillin, erythromycin and cefaclor. VT strains isolated in </p>

<p>Table 1. Serotypes of Streptococcus pneumoniae isolated from vaccinated and non-
vaccinated subjects </p>

<p>Serotype 
Vaccine* 
Control* 
P value 
No. 
% 
No. 
% </p>

<p>VT </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>14 
6B 
23F 
19F 
4 
Subtotal </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
1 
0 
4 </p>

<p>0.0 
2.8 
5.6 
2.8 
0.0 
11.1 </p>

<p>9 
8 
8 
7 
1 
33 </p>

<p>14.3 
12.7 
12.7 
11.1 
1.6 
52.4 
&lt; 0.05 
VRT </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>6C 
6A 
6D 
19A 
Subtotal </p>

<p>6 
5 
0 
4 
15 </p>

<p>16.7 
13.9 
0.0 
11.1 
41.7 </p>

<p>3 
1 
2 
3 
9 </p>

<p>4.8 
1.6 
3.2 
4.8 
14.3 
&lt; 0.05 
NVT </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>10A 
11A 
15B/C 
22F 
35B 
45 
Subtotal </p>

<p>2 
0 
1 
1 
1 
1 
6 </p>

<p>5.6 
0.0 
2.8 
2.8 
2.8 
2.8 
16.7 </p>

<p>2 
2 
3 
0 
0 
0 
7 </p>

<p>3.2 
3.2 
4.8 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
11.1 
NT/NC </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Subtotal </p>

<p>11 
11 </p>

<p>30.6 
30.6 </p>

<p>14 
14 </p>

<p>22.2 
22.2 
Total 
36 
18.0 
63 
31.5 
&lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>*Total number of subjects, vaccine group (200 subjects), control group (200 subjects); </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Carriage rate for serotypes was calculated over the total number of S. pneumoniae 
strains isolated in the vaccine (n = 36) and control (n = 63) groups. VT, vaccine-type; 
VRT, vaccine-related type; NVT, non-vaccine type; NT/NC, non-typeable/non-capsule. </p>

<p>Table 2. Antibiotic susceptibility test for pneumococcal nasopharyngeal carriage strains isolated from vaccinated and non-vaccinated controls </p>

<p>Serotypes Group 
No. </p>

<p>Penicillin 
(Oral Penicillin V Criteria) 
Amoxicillin 
Erythromycin 
Cefaclor </p>

<p>S 
No. (%) </p>

<p>I 
No. (%) </p>

<p>R 
No. (%) </p>

<p>S 
No. (%) </p>

<p>I 
No. (%) </p>

<p>R 
No. (%) </p>

<p>S 
No. (%) </p>

<p>I 
No. (%) </p>

<p>R 
No. (%) </p>

<p>S 
No. (%) </p>

<p>I 
No. (%) </p>

<p>R 
No. (%) </p>

<p>VT 
Vaccine 
4 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
4 
(100) </p>

<p>1 
(25.0) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
3 
(75.0) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
0 (0) 
4 
(100) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
0 (0) 
4 
(100) 
Control 
33 
1 
(3.0) </p>

<p>6 
(18.2) </p>

<p>26 
(78.8) </p>

<p>22 
(66.7) </p>

<p>5 
(15.2) </p>

<p>6 
(18.2) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
0 (0) 
33 
(100) </p>

<p>1 
(3.0) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
32 
(97.0) 
VRT 
Vaccine 
15 
5 
(33.3) </p>

<p>3 
(20.0) </p>

<p>7 
(46.7) </p>

<p>11 
(73.3) </p>

<p>1 
(6.7) </p>

<p>3 
(20.0) </p>

<p>3 
(20.0) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
12 
(80.0) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
0 (0) 
15 
(100) 
Control 
9 
0 (0) 
0 (0.0) 
9 
(100) </p>

<p>4 
(44.4) </p>

<p>2 
(22.2) </p>

<p>3 
(33.3) </p>

<p>1 
(11.1) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
8 
(88.9) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
0 (0) 
9 
(100) 
NVT 
Vaccine 
3 
1 
(33.3) </p>

<p>2 
(66.7) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
3 
(100) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
0 (0) 
3 
(100) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 
(33.3) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
2 
(66.7) 
Control 
14 
0 (0) 
2 
(28.6) </p>

<p>5 
(71.4) </p>

<p>5 
(71.4) </p>

<p>1 
(14.3) </p>

<p>1 
(14.3) </p>

<p>2 
(28.6) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
5 
(71.4) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
0 (0) 
7 
(100) 
NT/NC 
Vaccine 
9 
0 (0) 
6 
(66.7) </p>

<p>3 
(33.3) </p>

<p>7 
(77.8) </p>

<p>1 
(11.1) </p>

<p>1 
(11.1) </p>

<p>2 
(22.2) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
7 
(77.8) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
0 (0) 
9 
(100) 
Control 
7 
1 
(7.1) </p>

<p>8 
(57.1) </p>

<p>5 
(35.7) </p>

<p>12 
(85.7) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
2 
(14.3) </p>

<p>3 
(21.4) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
11 
(78.6) </p>

<p>1 
(7.1) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
13 
(92.9) 
Total 
Vaccine 
31 
6 
(19.4) </p>

<p>11 
(35.5) </p>

<p>14 
(45.2)* </p>

<p>22 
(71.0) </p>

<p>2 
(6.5) </p>

<p>7 
(22.6) </p>

<p>8 
(25.8) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
23 
(74.2)* </p>

<p>1 
(3.2) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
30 
(96.8) 
Control 
63 
2 
(3.2) </p>

<p>16 
(25.4) </p>

<p>45 
(71.4) </p>

<p>43 
(68.3) </p>

<p>8 
(12.7) </p>

<p>12 
(19.0) </p>

<p>6 
(9.5) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
57 
(90.5) </p>

<p>2 
(3.2) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
61 
(96.8) </p>

<p>*P &lt; 0.05; vaccine vs control group. S, Susceptible; I, Intermediate; R, Resistant; VT, vaccine-type; VRT, vaccine-related type; NVT, non-vaccine type; NT/NC, non-typable/non-
capsule. </p>

<p>Kim K-H, et al. • Pneumococcal Nasopharyngeal Carriage in Korean Children </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>DOI: 10.3346/jkms.2011.26.2.184 </p>

<p>control subjects also showed a penicillin resistance rate of 78.8% 
(26/33) and erythromycin and cefaclor resistance was noted in 
almost all VT serotypes. Therefore the proportion of MDR strains 
among VT isolates were 100% and 78.8% (26/33) in the vaccine 
and control group, respectively (Table 3). 
Regardless of vaccination status, there was an overall high re-
sistant rate for cefaclor for all isolates (66.7%-100%) and for eryth-
romycin (except for NVT strains in vaccinated subjects). How-
ever, amoxicillin was sensitive to more than 68.3%-71.0% of the 
isolates regardless of serotype. When isolates were classified ac-
cording to serotype group, although more strains were resistant 
against penicillin for VT serotypes in the vaccine group, the pro-
portion of penicillin resistant strains were lower in the VRT and 
NVT compared with the control group. The penicillin resistant 
strains showed a similar proportion in NT/NC strains in both 
groups. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Up to date, there are few studies about impact of PCV7 to pneu-
mococcal carriage in Asia. This is the first study of pneumococ-
cal carriage among vaccinated children in Korea. We evaluated 
the impact of PCV7 on NP pneumococcal carriage by compar-
ing differences in carriage rates, pneumococcal serotypes and 
antibiotic sensitivity between fully vaccinated (3 dose primary 
series + 1 booster dose) and non-vaccinated control children 
aged 18-59 months attending daycare centers in Korea. The over-
all NP pneumococcal carriage rate was higher in the control group 
compared with the vaccinated group. We also found a significant 
difference in serotypes according to vaccination status. The car-
riage rate in the vaccinated population for VT strains was lower 
compared with control subjects. Also, changes in serotype dis-
tribution were seen in comparison with previous studies on pneu-
mococcal carriage in Korea, which were done before the intro-
duction of PCV7 throughout 1998-2001 (13, 14). VT serotypes 
were approximately 46.6% and 56.9% of the pneumococcal se-
rotypes in those previous studies; these results are similar with 
the control subjects in this study (52.4%), however a decrease 
in VT was seen among the vaccinated subjects (11.1%). Chang-
es in serotype distribution such as decrease in VT in vaccinated </p>

<p>populations and increase in prevalence of serotypes not covered 
by the vaccine has been previously reported in other countries 
also (15-17). These studies reported decrease in VT with an in-
crease in NVT, and stationary prevalence of VRT in vaccinated 
subjects. The explanation of this finding is based on the hypoth-
esis that PCV7 provides protection against VRT serotypes. How-
ever recent reports have shown an increase of VRT including 
Pn 6C and 19A in NP carriage and IPD isolates (18, 19). Also, it 
has been stated that PCV7 does not elicit functional antibodies 
against Pn 19A in infants (20). In this study, we found a higher 
proportion of VRT isolated in the vaccinated group compared 
with the control group, with Pn 6C as the most prevalent sero-
type among the vaccinated subjects. These results are consis-
tent with the recent epidemiologic data questioning the extent 
of PCV7 cross-protection for particular VRT serotypes such as 
Pn 6C and 19A. 
In this study, Pn 6D was isolated from two subjects in the con-
trol group. Following the discovery of serotype 6C, the presence 
of a new serotype, 6D was proposed but was not found in nature 
until recently (21). The two 6D isolates described here were found 
to be 6D based on serologic, genetic, and biochemical charac-
terization (9). Serotype 6D was also recently discovered in Fiji 
(12). In that study, 86% (12/14) of the subjects from which sero-
type 6D was isolated, had received at least 1 dose of PCV-7. How-
ever, in our study, serotype 6D was detected in children who had 
no history of vaccination and lived in an area where PCV7 vac-
cination coverage is low (under 15%). To fully understand the 
epidemiologic features and characteristics of 6D, further stud-
ies will be needed on isolates from sterile sites (IPD), otitis me-
dia and NP carriage from different regions. 
Another interesting finding was that NT/NC isolates were de-
tected from 30.6% and 22.2% of the vaccinated and control sub-
jects. A previous report of pneumococcal NP carriage before in-
troduction of PCV7 in Korea showed 8% (6/73) of NT isolates 
(13). Pneumococcal NP carriage serotype acquisition is a com-
plex process with various determinants including age of host, 
pressure from environment, antibiotics, epidemics, vaccination, 
capsular switching, competition for predominant serotype or 
other yet undefined selective forces (22). Up to date there are 
more than 93 distinct pneumococcal serotypes which are increas-
ing with the development in new methods for detection and 
serotyping (10, 23, 24). Isolates lacking a capsule rarely cause 
invasive disease in humans and are attenuated in virulence in 
animal models of disease (25), however close monitoring on 
the epidemiologic changes in serotypes of clinical diseases in-
cluding IPD and otitis media will reveal the significance of this 
increase in NT/NC isolates. 
Antibiotic susceptibility tests showed that penicillin and eryth-
romycin resistance rates were higher in control subjects com-
pared with vaccinated subjects. VT isolates showed a high resis-
tance rate for penicillin, erythromycin and cefaclor in both vac-</p>

<p>Table 3. Multi-drug resistance rate for pneumococcal nasopharyngeal carriage strains </p>

<p>Number of MDR Isolates/ Total number (%) 
P 
Vaccine group 
Control group </p>

<p>VT 
4/4 (100) 
26/33 (78.8) 
VRT 
7/15 (46.7) 
8/9 (88.9) 
&lt; 0.05 
NVT 
0/3 (0) 
5/14 (35.7) 
NT/NC 
3/9 (33.3) 
5/7 (71.4) 
Total 
14/31 (45.2) 
44/63 (69.8) 
&lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>MDR is defined as resistant to three or more classes of antimicrobial agents. MDR, 
multi-drug resistance; VT, vaccine-type; VRT, vaccine-related type; NVT, non-vaccine 
type; NT/NC, non-typable/non-capsule. </p>

<p>Kim K-H, et al. • Pneumococcal Nasopharyngeal Carriage in Korean Children </p>



<p>DOI: 10.3346/jkms.2011.26.2.184 </p>

<p>could influence the pneumococcal carriage rate or serotype 
distribution. However it is difficult to estimate the impact of 
these regional differences or differences in background cover-
age rates on the carriage rate and serotype distribution. None-
theless, these factors should be considered in interpretation of 
the data. 
Despite these limitations, through a multicenter, prospective 
observational study, we studied the effect of PCV7 on pneumo-
coccal NP carriage by comparing the differences in carriage rates, 
pneumococcal serotypes and antibiotic sensitivity between vac-
cinated children and non-vaccinated controls. This study gives 
an insight of the impact of PCV7 on the epidemiology of pneu-
mococcal NP carriage in Korean children. With the impressive 
reduction in carriage of VT serotypes in vaccinated subjects, and 
considering the high antibiotic resistance rates of these strains, 
we find that pneumococcal protein conjugate vaccines reduce 
transmission of these serotypes in the community. Also, the most 
prevalent serotypes among the vaccinated subjects were VRT 
and NT/NC. The epidemiologic features regarding the promi-
nent serotype in a community is determined by various envi-
ronmental factors. PCV7 was introduced in Korea in late 2002 
and is still vaccinated on a private sector basis. Continuous mon-
itoring on serotype changes of NP carriage as well as isolates 
from IPD will be important in making decisions on the national 
immunization strategy. 
Through this study, up to now, we find that PCV7 reduces car-
riage in VT which leads to replacement of pneumococci by an-
tibiotic susceptible VRT or non-vaccine type strains. </p>



<p>cinated and control subjects. Also, the penicillin resistance rate 
was higher in control subjects for VRT and NVT strains with a 
relatively low penicillin resistance rate for NT/NC isolates in both 
control and vaccinated subjects. Although there are few studies 
in Korea, we discovered that the total penicillin resistance rate 
showed a striking increase from 15% in 1999 (26), 27.1% in 2002 
(27), 39.7% in 2004 (13) and 71.4% in 2009 (this study) in non-
vaccinated subjects compared with a less increase in vaccinat-
ed subjects (45.2%, 2009). Therefore with the increase in vacci-
nation of PCV7, decrease in proportion of VT serotypes might 
lead to a decrease in antibiotic resistance for pneumococcal 
strains. 
According to our findings, resistance rates against cefaclor 
and macrolide were high regardless of vaccination status or se-
rotype resistance rate. In Korea, erythromycin resistance rates 
were high (up to 76.3%-88%) among pneumococcal carriage 
isolates in children 10 yr ago (26, 27). 
The overall MDR rate for pneumococcus was 61.7% among 
all NP carriage isolates regardless of serotype and vaccination 
status. Although MDR rate was higher in controls compared 
with vaccinated subjects, increase in vaccination rates of PCV 
will not be the only solution for this problem. The high antibiot-
ic resistance rate emphasizes the need for policies or guidelines 
on antibiotic usage to slow done the resistance rate. 
There are certain limitations of our study. Samples were col-
lected only a single time from each subject and subjects were 
recruited throughout summer, autumn and early winter seasons. 
Pneumococcal carriage rates have been reported to show a sig-
nificant difference between summer and winter months (28). 
Considering NP colonization is not a constant process, and pneu-
mococcal isolates and serotypes can differ at different periods 
of time, a time sequenced sample collection study might give 
us a better understanding of the local epidemiology. Moreover 
serotyping was done for a single colony of pneumococcus from 
each subject. However, pneumococcal serotypes can coexist in 
the NP of an individual. In studies using methods designed to 
detect multiple-serotype carriage, the carriage rate for more 
than one serotype range from 1.3% to 30% (29, 30). Although 
most studies on the impact of PCV on NP carriage report only 
the dominant serotype, detection of multiple-strain coloniza-
tion is also warranted. In the antibiotic sensitivity analysis, iso-
lates were classified by according to serotype such as VT, VRT, 
NVT or NT/NC. However the antibiotic sensitivity was analyzed 
for only four VT strains and three NVT strains in the vaccination 
group. The results of these strains showed a distinct disposition, 
however it is difficult to make conclusions with this limited data. 
Also, the subjects of the vaccinated group and control group 
were recruited from different regions in Korea. The reason for 
this regional difference in recruitment was due to distinct dif-
ferences in vaccination rates between the regions. There is also 
a mild difference in climate between the regions. These factors </p>

<p>Kim K-H, et al. • Pneumococcal Nasopharyngeal Carriage in Korean Children </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>





<p>Kim K-H, et al. • Pneumococcal Nasopharyngeal Carriage in Korean Children </p>



<p>DOI: 10.3346/jkms.2011.26.2.184 </p>

<p>AUTHOR SUMMARY </p>

<p>Nasopharyngeal Pneumococcal Carriage of Children Attending Day Care Centers in 
Korea: Comparison between Children Immunized with 7-valent Pneumococcal 
Conjugate Vaccine and Non-immunized </p>

<p>Kyung-Hyo Kim, Jung Yun Hong, Hyunju Lee, Ga Young Kwak, Chan Hee Nam, Soo Young Lee, Eunsang Oh, Jigui Yu, 
Moon H. Nahm, and Jin Han Kang </p>

<p>To study the impact of the 7-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV7), pneumococcal nasopharyngeal (NP) carriage was 
evaluated among vaccinated and nonvaccinated children. Among 400 children aged 18-59 months, carriage rate was 18.0% and 
31.5% for the vaccinated and control group, respectively. Among those vaccinated, 41.7% of the serotypes were vaccine-related 
type (VRT: 6A, 6C, 19A) with the most common serotype 6C. The next common type was non-typable/non-capsule 30.6% 
followed by non-vaccine type 16.7% and vaccine type (VT) serotypes were found in only 11.1%. In contrast, 52.4% of the isolates 
in the control group were VT. Resistance rates for penicillin and erythromycin were lower in the vaccine group and multi-drug 
resistance was also lower in vaccinated subjects. We conclude that PCV7 reduces carriage in VT which leads to replacement of 
pneumococci by antibiotic susceptible VRT or non-vaccine type strains. </p>

</text></tei>