<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3315194" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Exercise training can improve strength and lead to adaptations in the skeletal muscle and nervous 
systems. Skeletal muscles can develop into two types: fast and slow, depending on the expression pattern 
of myosin heavy chain (MHC) isoforms. Previous studies reported that exercise altered the distribution of 
muscle fiber types. It is not currently known what changes in the expression of caveolins and types of 
muscle fiber occur in response to the intensity of exercise. This study determined the changes in 
expression of caveolins and MHC type after forced exercise in muscular and non-muscular tissues in rats. 
A control (Con) group to which forced exercise was not applied and an exercise (Ex) group to which 
forced exercise was applied. Forced exercise, using a treadmill, was introduced at a speed of 25 m/min 
for 30 min, 3 times/day (07:00, 15:00, 23:00). Homogenized tissues were applied to extract of total RNA 
for further gene analysis. The expression of caveolin-3 and MHC2a in the gastrocnemius muscle of 
female rats significantly increased in the Ex group compared with the Con group (P&lt;0.05). Furthermore, 
in the gastrocnemius muscle of male rats, the expression of MHC2x was significantly different between 
the two groups (P&lt;0.05). There was an increased expression in caveolin-3 and a slightly decreased 
expression in TGFβ-1 in muscular tissues implicating caveolin-3 influences the expression of MHC 
isoforms and TGFβ-1 expression. Eventually, it implicates that caveolin-3 has positive regulatory function 
in muscle atrophy induced by neural dysfunction with spinal cord injury or stroke. </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>



<p>Sookyoung Park et al. </p>

<p>Lab Anim Res | March, 2012 | Vol. 28, No. 1 </p>

<p>animals [5], including alterations in antioxidant 
mechanisms [6] and the induction of hypertrophy [7]. 
Depending on the muscle type and the nature of the 
exercise, different studies have reported increases in 
oxidative capacity [8], the number and size of 
mitochondria [9], muscle weight [10], the appearance of 
split muscle fibers [11], and an altered distribution of 
muscle fiber types [4]. 
Skeletal muscles are one of the most important 
components responsible for physical performance and 
adaptation to exercise [12]. They can be characterized 
into functionally distinct slow (type I) and fast (type II) 
muscles, according to the expression pattern of myosin 
heavy chain (MHC) isoforms in the fibers. The MHC 
gene family consists of eight isoforms and four types are 
expressed in adult skeletal muscle: slow MHC and fast 
MHC, of which there are three isoforms, 2a, 2x, and 2b 
(or MHC 2A , MHC 2X , and MHC 2B ) [13]. The three adult 
fast MHC isoforms are expressed in different types of 
skeletal muscle fibers and have different physiological 
characteristics, with 2A fibers being smaller, slower, and 
more oxidative, 2B fibers typically being the largest, 
fastest, and most glycolytic, and 2X or 2D/X fibers 
falling between these extremes [14]. Physical activity, 
including exercise, can alter the properties of MHC 
isoforms and change the isoform content [15]. 
It is well known that exercise can have beneficial 
effects on insulin resistance, through the activation of 
glucose transporters, especially caveolin-1, which plays 
an important role in glucose uptake in L6 skeletal muscle 
cells [16]. Caveolins are integral membrane proteins that 
play a role in essential cellular functions. They normally 
have two main functions: intracellular transport of 
signaling molecules and transmitters [17]. The caveolin 
gene family consists of caveolin-1, -2, and -3. Caveolin-
1 has been reported to interact with various intracellular 
signaling molecules, including growth factors, such as 
the epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) [18] and 
estrogen receptor (ER) [19]. Caveolin-3 is expressed in 
a muscle-specific manner and mutations in caveolin-3 
cause limb girdle muscular dystrophy, leading to apoptosis 
of skeletal muscle [20]. Loss of caveolin-3 resulting 
from dominant-negative mutations in the caveolin-3 
gene causes autosomal dominant limb-girdle muscular 
dystrophy 1C (LGMD1C). 
Myostatin is a member of the transforming growth 
factor beta (TGFβ) superfamily and plays an important 
role in the negative regulation of skeletal muscle volume </p>

<p>[21]. Over-expression of myostatin causes severe muscular 
atrophy [22,23], whereas targeted disruption of myostatin 
markedly increases muscle mass in mice [21,24]. 
Recently, caveolin-1 was reported to inhibit the 
activation of the type I receptor for TGFβ-1, which 
induces growth arrest in non-muscle cells [25]. 
Accordingly, an increase in myostatin activity, resulting 
from loss of caveolin-3 in muscle, might participate in 
the pathogenesis of skeletal muscle atrophy in LGMD1C 
patients [26]. However, it remains unclear how caveolin 
gene expression changes after forced exercise and the 
relevance of such on shifts on the type of MHC isoforms. 
Thus, the purpose of this study was to investigate the 
changes of expression of caveolins, MHC type, and 
TGFβ-1 after forced exercise, using treadmills, in 
muscular and non-muscular tissues. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>The materials and chemicals used in this study, 
including Tri-reagent, were obtained from company 
(Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>Sprague Dawley (SD) rat males (n=16) and females 
(n=16), 10-12 weeks of age, and between 290-300 g 
were used. The animals were housed in an air-conditioned 
room with a constant temperature of 22±2 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C with free 
access to food and water, and subject to a photoperiod of 
12 h of light and 12 h of darkness. All animal experiments 
were performed according to a protocol set out in the 
guidelines of the Animal Experiments Ethics Committee 
at Inje University (Approval No. 2009-083). </p>

<p>Forced Exercise </p>

<p>All experimental rats performed the forced exercise 
over a period of 4 weeks using treadmills. The protocol 
for treadmill exercise is as follows: the speed of the 
treadmill was 25 m/min, with a frequency of 6 days per 
week, for 30 min. The rat was exercised three times a 
day, 07:00, 15:00, 23:00 (8 h intervals). </p>

<p>Sample preparation, RNA isolation, and RT-PCR </p>

<p>Brain (fore, mid, and hind) tissue, heart, kidneys (from 
females) and skeletal muscles (gastrocnemius and 
soleus, from males and females) were homogenized in 
1 mL of Tri-Reagent, and total RNA was extracted </p>

<p>Caveolins and MHC in exercised rats </p>



<p>Lab Anim Res | March, 2012 | Vol. 28, No. 1 </p>

<p>according to the manufacturer's instructions. Total RNA 
was treated with RNase-free distilled water, and then 
reverse transcribed by reverse transcriptase and oligo-dT 
primers in a Px2 Thermal cycler (Thermo Electron Co., 
Waltham, MA, USA), using the RT-PCR method. 
Primers were used as following : caveolin isoforms (cav-
1, -2, and -3), MHC isoforms (MHC-1β, MHC-2a, -2x, 
and -2b), and TGFβ-1. The primers were sequenced to 
confirm the specificity of amplification and the 
sequences are shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data were collected from repeated experiments and 
are presented as mean±SEM. Independent T-test was 
used to compare the significant difference of gene 
expression in each group. A P value less than 0.05 
denoted significant differences. All analyses were 
performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS</rs>) ver.<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">16</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs>, New York, NY, 
USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>To determine how the expression of caveolin isoform 
genes changed in non-muscular and skeletal muscular 
tissue, which type(s) of MHC genes were expressed in 
the muscles, and the changes in MHC gene expression 
and TGFβ-1 after forced exercise, we analyzed the </p>

<p>expression of caveolin isoforms, MHC-1β, MHC-2a, 
-2x, -2b, and TGFβ-1 by RT-PCR. The RT-PCR results 
were semi-quantitatively analyzed using a densitometric 
method. </p>

<p>Expression of caveolins in brain tissue </p>

<p>Cav-1 and -2 expression was slightly increased in the 
forebrain in the Ex group, compared with the Con group; 
however, cav-3 expression decreased in the Ex group 
(Figure 1-A). In the mid-brain, cav-1, -2, and -3 
expression was slightly decreased in the Ex group, 
compared with the Con group (Figure 1-B). In the hind-
brain, expression of cav-1 was increased in the Ex group, 
compared with the Con group, whereas expression of 
cav-2 in both groups was similar. Expression of cav-3 
was slightly decreased in the Ex group, compared with 
the Con group. Stable expression of cav-3 was detected 
in all brain tissues (Figure 1-C). </p>

<p>Expression of caveolins in heart and kidney tissue </p>

<p>Expression of caveolin genes in the heart and kidneys 
was analyzed after forced exercise. Cav-1 expression in 
the heart was slightly decreased in the Ex group, 
compared with the Con group; however cav-2 and -3 
expression was slightly increased in the Ex group 
(Figure 2-A). In the kidneys, cav-1 and -2 expression 
was slightly decreased in the Ex group, compared with 
the Con group, while cav-3 expression was increased in </p>

<p>Table 1. Oligonucleotide primers used for RT-PCR </p>

<p>Gene 
Primer sequence (5'-3') 
Tm ( </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C) 
Product length 
(bp) </p>

<p>GenBank 
accession No. </p>

<p>Cav-1 
F: GATCAAGCTTATGTCTGGGGGCAAATAC 
R: GATCGAATTCTCATATCTCTTTCTGC 
55 
537 
AY439333 </p>

<p>Cav-2 
F: GATCAAGCTTATGGGGCTGGAGACCGAG 
R: GATCGAATTCTCAGTCGTGGCTCAGTTG 
60 
489 
NM_016900 </p>

<p>Cav-3 
F: GATCAAGCTTATGATGACCGAAGAGCAC 
R: GATCGAATTCTTAGCCTTCCCTTCGCAG 
60 
456 
NM_007617 </p>

<p>MyHC-1β 
F : ACAGAGGAAGACAGGAAGAACCTAC 
R : GGGCTTCACAGGCATCCTTAG 
60 
288 
K01463 </p>

<p>MyHC-2A 
F : CCTCTTACTTCCCAGCTGCACCTTCT 
R : ACTTTCCCTGCGTCTTTGCTCTGAAT 
60 
239 
DQ872905 </p>

<p>MyHC-2X 
F : ACGGTCGAAGTTGCATCCCTAAAG 
R : CACCTTCGGTCTTGGCTGTCAC 
60 
263 
DQ872906 </p>

<p>MyHC-2B 
F : AGCCTGCCTCCTTCTTCATCTGG 
R : CACGGTTGCTTTCACATAGGACTC 
60 
229 
DQ872907 </p>

<p>TGFβ-1 
F: ATACGCCTGAGTGGCTGTCT 
R: TGGGACTGATCCCATTGATT 
60 
153 
NM_021578 </p>

<p>GAPDH 
F: GTATGACTCCACTCACGGCAAA 
R: GGTCTCGCTCCTGGAAGATG 
60 
100 
BC094037 </p>



<p>Sookyoung Park et al. </p>

<p>Lab Anim Res | March, 2012 | Vol. 28, No. 1 </p>

<p>the Ex group, compared with the Con group (Figure 2-
B). Stable expression of cav-3 was detected in both the 
heart and kidneys. </p>

<p>Expression of caveolins in gastrocnemius tissue </p>

<p>Expression of caveolin genes was analyzed in the 
gastrocnemius tissue of male and female rats after forced 
exercise. In the gastrocnemius of male rats, expression of 
cav-1, -2, and -3 increased in the Ex group, compared 
with the Con group, but it was not significantly different 
(Figure 3-A). In female rats, cav-1 expression increased 
in the Ex group, compared with the Con group; however, 
there was no difference in cav-2 expression between the 
groups. Cav-3 expression was significantly increased in 
the Ex group, compared with the Con group (P&lt;0.05; 
Figure 3-B). </p>

<p>Expression of caveolins in soleus tissue </p>

<p>In the soleus of male rats, cav-1 and -2 expression was 
decreased in the Ex group, compared with the Con 
group; however, there was no difference in cav-3 
expression between the groups (Figure 4-A). In female 
rats, cav-1 and -2 expression was increased in the Ex 
group, compared with the Con group; however, there 
was no difference in cav-3 expression between the 
groups (Figure 4-B). </p>

<p>Expression of MHCs and TGFβ-1 in gastrocnemius 
tissue </p>

<p>In male rats, MHC-2x expression was significantly 
increased in the Ex group compared to the Con group 
(P&lt;0.05), whereas, there was no significant difference in 
MHC-1β, MHC-2a, and -2b expression between both </p>

<p>Figure 1. Expression of caveolin-1, -2, and -3 in the brain of female rats. (A) fore-brain, (B) mid-brain, and (C) hind-brain. Con: non-
treadmill exercised group, Ex: treadmill exercised group. </p>

<p>Caveolins and MHC in exercised rats </p>



<p>Lab Anim Res | March, 2012 | Vol. 28, No. 1 </p>

<p>groups (Figure 5-A). In female rats, MHC-2a expression 
was significantly increased in the Ex group, compared 
with the Con group (P&lt;0.05); however, there were no 
significant differences in MHC-1β, MHC-2x, and -2b 
expression between the two groups (Figure 5-B). In both 
male and female rats, TGFβ-1 expression was slightly </p>

<p>decreased, but not significantly so. </p>

<p>Expression of MHCs in soleus tissue </p>

<p>To determine which types of MHC genes were 
expressed in the muscles, and the change in expression 
of MHC genes and TGFβ-1, we analyzed the expression </p>

<p>Figure 2. Expression of caveolin-1, -2, and -3 in the heart and kidney of female rats. (A) heart, (B) kidney. Con: non-treadmill 
exercised group, Ex: treadmill exercised group. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Expression of caveolin-1, -2, and -3 in the gastrocnemius muscle of male and female rats. (A) male, (B) female. Con: 
non-treadmill exercised group, Ex: treadmill exercised group. </p>



<p>Sookyoung Park et al. </p>

<p>Lab Anim Res | March, 2012 | Vol. 28, No. 1 </p>

<p>patterns of MHC-1β, MHC-2a, -2x, -2b, and TGFβ-1 in 
gastrocnemius muscle by RT-PCR. There was no </p>

<p>significant difference in MHC-1β, MHC-2a, -2x, or -2b 
expression between the groups in male rats (Figure 6-A). </p>

<p>Figure 4. Expression of caveolin-1, -2, and -3 in the soleus muscle of male and female rats. (A) male, (B) female. Con: non-
treadmill exercised group, Ex: treadmill exercised group. </p>

<p>Figure 5. The expression of MHC-1β, MHC-2a, -2x, and -2b, and TGFβ-1 in the gastrocnemius muscle of male and female rats. (A) 
male, (B) female. Con: non-treadmill exercised group, Ex: treadmill exercised group. </p>

<p>Caveolins and MHC in exercised rats </p>



<p>Lab Anim Res | March, 2012 | Vol. 28, No. 1 </p>

<p>Additionally, there was no significant difference in 
MHC-1β, MHC-2a, -2x, or -2b expression between the 
groups in female rats (Figure 6-B). In male and female 
rats, TGFβ-1 expression was slightly decreased, but not 
significantly so. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present study was designed to determine the 
expression of caveolins in non-muscular and muscular 
tissue and the distribution of MHC isoforms in muscular 
tissue after forced exercise, and to reveal the relationship 
between caveolins and MHC isoform expression. 
Therefore, forced exercise was applied to SD rats, and 
the results were analyzed. 
First, cav-1 and -2 expression differed between non-
muscular and muscular tissues after forced exercise, and 
caveolin isoforms were differentially expressed in different 
tissues. Previous studies reported that caveolin-1 and -2 
are co-expressed in many cell types, including adipocytes, 
fibroblasts, and endothelial cells [27], while the 
expression of caveolin-3 is muscle-specific [28]. Stable 
expression of cav-3 was detected in all tissues, including </p>

<p>the brain. More recently, caveolin-1, -2, and -3 expression 
was identified in the brain [29]. Caveolin-1 and -2 are 
widely expressed in brain microvessels, endothelial cells, 
astrocytes, oligodendrocytes, Schwann cells, dorsal root 
ganglia, and hippocampal neurons. Caveolin-3 is also 
prominently expressed in astroglial cells [30-32]. 
Interestingly, the expression of cav-3 increased 
significantly in the Ex group, compared with the Con 
group, in the gastrocnemius of female rats. In the 
gastrocnemius of male rats, the expression of MHC-2x 
increased significantly in the Ex group, compared with 
the Con group. Moreover, in the gastrocnemius of 
female rats, the expression of MHC-2a was significantly 
increased in the Ex group compared to the Con group. 
These results suggest that forced exercise may induce 
shifts between the MHC-2a and -2x isoforms in the 
gastrocnemius of male and female rats. In the 
gastrocnemius of female rats, it appears that increased 
cav-3 expression was related to increased MHC-2a 
expression, as seen in the Ex group compared with the 
Con group. 
Increased neuromuscular activity results in MHC 
isoform shifts from fast to slow muscle fibers [33], and </p>

<p>Figure 6. The expression of MHC-1β, MHC-2a, -2x, and -2b, and TGFβ-1 in the soleus muscle of male and female rats. (A) male, 
(B) female. Con: non-treadmill exercised group, Ex: treadmill exercised group. </p>



<p>Sookyoung Park et al. </p>

<p>Lab Anim Res | March, 2012 | Vol. 28, No. 1 </p>

<p>inactivity results in a general shift in MHC expression 
and metabolic properties along a progression, from 
1→2A→2X→2B [34]. Reduced synthesis rates of MHC 
are also observed [35], and mitochondrial dysfunction, 
which may arise as a result of oxidative stress, together 
with a decline in glycolytic enzyme activity, may lead to 
decreased energy production in aging skeletal muscles 
[36]. Furthermore, the paralyzed muscles of individuals 
with chronic traumatic spinal cord injury (SCI) are 
characterized by a high distribution of "fast" muscle 
fibers (type II), and in some instances by the complete 
exclusion of any slow fibers in what would normally be 
mixed fiber type muscles. Thus, MHC isoform expression 
appears to be altered by an increase in MHC II [37,38]. 
Oxidative stress, such as by nitric oxide (NO), down 
regulates caveolin-3 levels, due to an alteration in the 
DNA-binding activity of the muscle transcription factor 
myogenin, resulting in cachexia [39], while endurance 
training promotes a shift in the opposite direction, 
2B→2X→2A→1 [34]. Many previous studies have 
reported the effects of exercise on changes in muscle 
fiber type [1,40-42]. 
In our results, the expression patterns of cav-3 and 
TGFβ-1 were contrary to each other in the gastrocnemius, 
and the gastrocnemius of male rats showed an increased 
expression of MHC2x in the Ex group, compared with 
the Con group. The gastrocnemius of female rats showed 
an increased expression of MHC2a in the Ex group, 
compared with the Con group. These results suggest that 
caveolin-3 may regulate shifts in the expression of MHC 
isoforms by inhibiting the expression of TGFβ-1. Further 
studies are needed to investigate how caveolins are 
related to the physiology of skeletal muscles and the 
mechanism of interaction between caveolins and TGFβ-1 
in shifts in MHC type after physical exercise. 
In summary, to investigate that pattern of caveolins 
and MHC isoforms expression, the relevance of changes 
of expression in caveolins and MHC isoforms, and 
influence of caveolin-3 to TGFβ-1 expression, male and 
female SD rat were applied forced exercise through 
treadmill running. We obtained the following results: 
The expression of MHC-2x was increased significantly 
in gastrocnemius of male-exercise group compared with 
the male-contol group. Also, the expression of caveolin-
3 and MHC-2a were increased significantly in 
gastrocnemius of female-exercise group compared with 
the female-conrol group. Also there was a slightly 
decreased expression in TGFβ-1 in all muscular tissue. </p>

<p>These results indicate that caveolin-3 may influence the 
expression of MHC isoforms and TGFβ-1 expression 
and prevent atrophy in skeletal muscle. Finally, it is 
necessary to understand physiology of muscular system 
in molecular level, in order to develop protocol of 
therapeutic exercise adjusted pathologic states. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The study was funded by the KRIBB Research 
Initiative Program (KGM0501113 to Y. Hong); 
BioGreen 21 Program (Code No. 20110301-061-542-
03-00 to Y. Hong), Rural Development Administration, 
Republic of Korea. </p>



<p>Caveolins and MHC in exercised rats </p>



<p>Lab Anim Res | March, 2012 | Vol. 28, No. 1 </p>



</text></tei>