<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3058730" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T16:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Aims </p>

<p>Resveratrol (RV), an antioxidant, inhibits angiotensin II (Ang II)-induced hypertrophy and Ang II-or epidermal growth 
factor (EGF)-induced Akt phosphorylation in rat vascular smooth muscle cells (VSMCs). Both signalling pathways are 
reported to utilize reactive oxygen species (ROS). The aim of this study was to show whether RV reduces the ROS 
level in Ang II-or EGF-activated VSMCs and whether reduction of ROS causes the impeded signalling towards Akt in 
the presence of RV. </p>

<p>Methods 
and results </p>

<p>We show here that RV reduces intracellular ROS and extracellular H 2 O 2 release from VSMCs as measured using 
2 
′ ,7 
′ -dichlorodihydrofluorescein-diacetate and Amplex Red 
TM . Since NADPH oxidases (Nox) 1 and 4 are major 
ROS sources in VSMCs, we examined their need for Akt phosphorylation in response to Ang II or EGF. Experiments 
using the blocking peptide gp91ds-tat verified a role for Nox1 in Ang II signalling towards Akt, but excluded a role for 
Nox1 in the respective EGF signalling. A small interfering RNA-mediated knock-down of Nox4 showed that Nox4 
was not required for Ang II-or EGF-induced Akt phosphorylation. Use of the flavoprotein inhibitor diphenyleneio-
donium, N-acetyl-cysteine, and non-antioxidant RV derivatives revealed that the antioxidant capacity of RV is not 
required for the inhibition of Akt phosphorylation, in both rat and human VSMCs. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Thus, although RV acts as an antioxidant, the antihypertrophic response of RV in VSMCs and the signalling down-
stream of the EGF receptor towards Akt seem to be largely redox independent. </p>

<p>---The small polyphenol resveratrol (RV), found in various plant-derived 
sources, including grapes, is considered to contribute to the beneficial 
effect of red wine in cardiovascular diseases. 
1 -3 Pharmacological </p>

<p>activities of RV relevant for a putative cardio-and vasoprotective 
effect include the reduction of platelet aggregation, low-density lipo-
protein oxidation, prostaglandin synthesis, and tumour necrosis 
factor-a-induced activation of endothelial cells, as well as the </p>

<p>promotion of endothelial nitric oxide (NO) synthase expression 
and activity. 
2,3 In addition, RV has been shown to inhibit </p>

<p>growth-related signalling pathways in cardiac fibroblasts and to 
protect against ischaemia-reperfusion injury. 
2,3 Previous work of </p>

<p>our group has demonstrated an antihypertrophic action of RV in 
angiotensin II (Ang II)-activated vascular smooth muscle cells 
(VSMCs), which is mediated by a selective inhibition of Akt phos-
phorylation. 
4,5 Angiotensin II is a potent vasoconstrictor, but is also </p>

<p>involved in inflammatory processes, vascular oxidative stress, cell </p>

<p>* Corresponding author. Tel: +43 1 4277 55270 (V.M.D.) and +43 1 4277 55993 (E.H.H.), Fax: +43 1 4277 55969, Email: verena.dirsch@univie.ac.at (V.M.D.) and elke.heiss@univie.ac.at </p>

<p>(E.H.H.) </p>

<p>Published on behalf of the European Society of Cardiology. All rights reserved. &amp; The Author 2010. For permissions please email: journals.permissions@oup.com. </p>

<p>The online version of this article has been published under an open access model. Users are entitled to use, reproduce, disseminate, or display the open access version of this article for non-
commercial purposes provided that the original authorship is properly and fully attributed; the Journal, Learned Society and Oxford University Press are attributed as the original place of 
publication with correct citation details given; if an article is subsequently reproduced or disseminated not in its entirety but only in part or as a derivative work this must be clearly indicated. 
For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com. </p>

<p>Cardiovascular Research (2011) 90, 140-147 
doi:10.1093/cvr/cvq355 </p>

<p>growth, and extracellular matrix deposition, promoting endothelial 
dysfunction and vascular remodelling. 
6,7 In the vessel wall, VSMCs </p>

<p>are the principal target cells of Ang II in which it promotes contraction 
contraction, cell growth (hypertrophy), migration, and increased 
extracellular matrix deposition via activation of the Ang II type 1 AT 1 
receptor. 
7 In VSMCs, the cellular signalling pathways mediating hyper-</p>

<p>trophy are complex. Important steps are the activation of NAD(P)H 
oxidase, a major source of cellular reactive oxygen species (ROS), 
and the transactivation of the epidermal growth factor (EGF) receptor 
(EGF-R) in a ROS-and c-Src-dependent manner. 
6 -9 Downstream of </p>

<p>the EGF-R, Akt and extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK) signalling 
pathways are activated. 
9 We have previously shown that RV does not </p>

<p>interfere with the transactivation of the EGF-R in Ang II-activated 
VSMCs when inhibiting Akt phosphorylation. In accordance with this, 
EGF-induced Akt phosphorylation was also inhibited by RV in 
VSMCs. 
5 Thus, RV interferes with the signalling towards Akt down-</p>

<p>stream of the EGF-R in Ang II-or EGF-activated VSMCs. The exact 
mode of action of RV in VSMCs has remained elusive, although 
some data have suggested activation of the redox-sensitive protein-
tyrosine phosphatase (PTP) Shp2 (Src homology-2-containing protein-
tyrosine phosphatase-2) as a mechanism. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Many activities of RV that are thought to contribute to its cardio-
and vasoprotective effect, including the activation of redox-sensitive 
PTPs, such as Shp2, may be explained by its antioxidant activity. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ROS are involved in cell signaling, leading to cell growth and migration, 
activation of MMPs, altered function of many kinases and phospha-
tases, and activation of pro-inflammatory transcription factors. 
10 In </p>

<p>addition, ROS oxidize low-density lipoprotein and may inactivate 
NO. 
11 In VSMCs, the most important source of ROS are the </p>

<p>NAD(P)H oxidases Nox1 and Nox4. 
12 -14 Nox1 is highly expressed </p>

<p>in proliferating VSMCs and is activated by a variety of growth 
factors, such as Ang II and platelet-derived growth factor, contributing 
to their activation of p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase and 
Akt. 
13,15,16 The function of Nox4, the only constitutively active </p>

<p>NAD(P)H oxidase, is less clear. 
15,16 In VSMCs, Nox4 was found </p>

<p>within distinct subcellular locations, such as the nucleus or the endo-
plasmic reticulum, but also at focal adhesions where the transactivated 
EGF-R and phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K) can be found after 
Ang II stimulation. 
15 -18 While Nox1 is known to be required for </p>

<p>Ang II-induced EGF-R transactivation, little is known how the 
EGF-activated EGF-R induces ROS production 
19,20 that may lead to </p>

<p>PTP oxidation and signal transduction. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>The aim of this study, therefore, was to investigate the following: (i) 
whether RV reduces the ROS level in or H 2 O 2 released from Ang II-
or EGF-activated VSMCs; (ii) whether Nox1 or Nox4 proteins, or 
ROS in general, are required for the phosphorylation of Akt down-
stream of the EGF-R; and thus (iii) whether RV may act directly or 
indirectly as an 'antioxidant' when inhibiting the phosphorylation of 
Akt. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>2.1 Reagents </p>

<p>Materials were obtained from the following suppliers: antibodies against 
phospho-Akt (Ser </p>

<p>473 </p>

<p>) and phospho-p38 were from Cell Signaling Technol-
ogy, anti-tubulin antibody was obtained from Santa Cruz Biotechnology. 
Resveratrol, Ang II, diphenyleneiodonium (DPI) and N-acetyl-cysteine 
(NAC) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich. Epidermal growth factor 
was obtained from Upstate. 2 
′ ,7 
′ -Dichlorodihydrofluorescein-diacetate </p>

<p>(H 2 DCF-DA) and the Amplex Red 
TM reagent were from Molecular 
Probes/Invitrogen. The blocking peptide for Nox1 (Nox2 is not expressed 
in rat VSMCs; 
22 and own unpublished results), gp91ds-tat, was </p>

<p>[H]-RKKRRQRRRCSTRIRRQL-NH 2 , and the control peptide used was 
[H]-RKKRRQRRRAGAGAGAGA-NH2, both from CASLO Laboratory 
ApS. All chemicals used for the synthesis of RV derivatives, unless otherwise 
stated, were analytical grade and obtained from Sigma-Aldrich Chemie 
GmbH (Schnelldorf, Germany), TCI Europe (Zwijndrecht, Belgium) and 
Apollo Scientific Limited (Bredbury, UK) and used without further 
purification. </p>

<p>2.2 Cultivation of cells </p>

<p>The VSMCs were provided by Drs Kathy K. Griendling and Dan Sorescu 
(Emory University School of Medicine) and were obtained by three inde-
pendent isolations from male Sprague-Dawley rat (200 -250 g, 5 -8 
weeks old) thoracic aortas by enzymatic digestion as described pre-
viously. 
8,23 Cells were grown in phenol red-free Dulbecco's modified </p>

<p>Eagle's medium supplemented with 10% calf serum, 2 mM glutamine, 
100 U/mL penicillin, and 100 mg/mL streptomycin (growth medium). For 
experiments, cells between passage 7 and 15 were used at 70% conflu-
ence. Prior to all growth factor stimulation experiments, cells were 
starved for 24 h in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium containing 0.1% 
calf serum supplemented with 2 mM glutamine, 100 U/mL penicillin, and 
100 mg/mL streptomycin (starve medium). </p>

<p>2.3 SDS-PAGE and western blotting </p>

<p>For experiments, cells were grown in 60 mm dishes and serum starved 
overnight in starve medium, then treated with Ang II (100 nM) or EGF 
(100 ng/mL) for the indicated time. Resveratrol (50 mM), vehicle control 
[dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) 0.1%], gp91ds-tat or the respective control 
peptide (100 mM) were added 30 min before stimulation. The VSMCs 
were pretreated with DPI (10 mM) for 1 h and NAC (10 mM) for 2 h 
before stimulation. Cells were then suspended in lysis buffer (50 mM 
HEPES, 50 mM NaCl, 5 mM EDTA, 10 mM sodium pyrophosphate, 
50 mM NaF, 1 mM sodium orthovanadate, 1% Triton X-100, 1 mM phe-
nylmethylsulfonyl fluoride and 1× complete protease inhibitor cocktail). 
Western blot analysis was performed as described previously. 
4 Proteins </p>

<p>of interest were visualized by the use of specific antibodies, an ECL 
system and a CCD camera (Fuji LAS 3000). Densitometric evaluation 
was performed by employing the <rs id="software-0" type="software">AIDA image analyser</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4.06</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Raytest</rs>). </p>

<p>2.4 Measurement of intracellular ROS </p>

<p>For detection of the intracellular total ROS level, cells were grown in 
six-well plates and treated as indicated. Quiescent cells were washed 
once with pre-warmed HEPES buffered saline solution and incubated at 
378C for 30 min with 20 mM H 2 DCF-DA before stimulation with EGF 
(100 ng/mL) or Ang II (100 nM) for the indicated periods of time. Cells 
were then immediately analysed by flow cytometry (FACSCalibur, BD 
Bioscience). The mean fluorescence of 10 000 analysed cells (corrected 
for autofluorescence) was detected and used as a measurement for 
total ROS. </p>

<p>2.5 Determination of extracellular H 2 O 2 level </p>

<p>The VSMCs were grown in 24-well plates and serum starved for 24 h. 
Cells were washed once with prewarmed phosphate-buffered saline, 
then krebs ringer phosphate glucose buffer containing the Amplex 
Red 
TM reagent was applied to the cells. Plates were incubated for 
15 min at 378C before VSMCs were stimulated as indicated. Resorufin, 
the fluorescent product, was measured in triplicate by a fluorescence 
multi-well plate reader with an excitation wavelength of 535 nm and an 
emission wavelength of 590 nm (Genios Pro, Tecan, Switzerland). </p>

<p>Resveratrol and redox signalling </p>



<p>2.6 Transfection with small interfering RNA 
and quantitative real-time PCR </p>

<p>Five hours after seeding, VSMCs were transfected with small interfering 
RNA (siRNA; siNox4 from ThermoFisher Scientific, 50 nM; or scrambled 
siRNA control from Invitrogen) using Oligofectamine (Invitrogen) and 
Opti-MEM 1 (Gibco). For Nox4, the sequences used were sense 
5 
′ -ACUGAGGUACAGCUGGAUGUU-3 
′ , and antisense 5 
′ -CAUCCAG 
CUGUACCUCAGUUU-3 
′ . Experiments were performed 72 h after 
siRNA transfection. The knock-down efficiency was verified by quantitat-
ive real-time PCR (qPCR). For this, mRNA was isolated using the 
pegGOLD total RNA Kit (Peqlab), and reverse transcription was per-
formed using Superscript 
TM First-Strand Synthesis System (Invitrogen) 
according to the manufacturer's protocol. PCR was carried out with a 
LightCycler 
TM LC480 SYBR Green I Master reagent (Roche Diagnostics) 
and the LightCycler 
TM LC480 (Roche Diagnostics) system. </p>

<p>2.7 Synthesis of RV derivatives </p>

<p>Methylated resveratrol derivatives were synthesized according to the litera-
ture. 
24 Both </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>H and </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>C nuclear magnetic resonance spectra were recorded </p>

<p>on a Bruker Advance DPx200 (200 and 50 MHz). Mass spectra (MS) were 
obtained by a Shimadzu (GC-17A; MS-QP5050A) spectrometer. </p>

<p>2.8 Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Results are expressed as means + SEM. Statistical analysis was performed 
by ANOVA followed by Dunnett's multiple comparison test or by one-
sample t-test using <rs id="software-1" type="software">GraphPad PRISM</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 4.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>, 
San Diego, CA, USA). Differences with P , 0.05 were considered 
significant. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1 Resveratrol reduces intracellular total 
ROS level and H 2 O 2 release from VSMCs </p>

<p>First, we asked whether RV reduces intracellular total ROS level 
and/or H 2 O 2 released from VSMCs and thereby leads to inhibition 
of Akt phosphorylation as described earlier. 
4,5 Since NAD(P)H </p>

<p>Figure 1 Resveratrol (RV) diminishes intracellular reactive oxygen species (ROS) level and attenuates both basal and angiotensin II (Ang II)-or </p>

<p>epidermal growth factor (EGF)-induced extracellular H 2 O 2 . Quiescent vascular smooth muscle cells (VSMCs) were pre-incubated with 
dichlorodihydrofluorescein-diacetate (H 2 DCF-DA; 20 mM, 15 min) and then incubated with 50 mM RV or vehicle control for 30 min or 10 mM diphe-
nyleneiodonium (DPI) for 1 h and finally stimulated with 100 nM Ang II for 15 min (A) or 100 ng/mL EGF for 10 min (B). ROS production (equivalent 
to the amount of formed DCF) was analysed by flow cytometry. The average fluorescence signal obtained in the presence of Ang II or EGF was set to 
100% (**P , 0.01; one-way ANOVA vs. Ang II or EGF treatment, n ¼ 3). Serum-starved VSMCs were stimulated in Amplex Red 
TM buffer with Ang II 
(100 nM; C) or EGF (100 ng/mL; D) for 5 -15 min after pre-incubation with RV (50 mM) or vehicle control for 30 min. H 2 O 2 production was quanti-
fied by fluorescence measurement. Absolute values were correlated to catalase-treated cells used as a negative control. Graphs show the relative 
extracellular H 2 O 2 production expressed as a percentage of vehicle-treated control cells (open square, vehicle-treated cells; filled squares, RV-treated 
cells; ***P , 0.001; t-test, n ¼ 4). </p>

<p>C.E. Schreiner et al. </p>



<p>oxidases play a pivotal role in VSMC-derived ROS production, DPI, 
an unspecific inhibitor of flavin-containing enzymes including 
NAD(P)H oxidases, 
25 was used as positive control. For detection </p>

<p>of intracellular ROS, we loaded VSMCs with 20 mM H 2 DCF-DA. 
Angiotensin II (100 nM) was able to induce ROS production 
twofold compared with the vehicle control. Resveratrol (50 mM) 
and DPI (10 mM) pre-treatment reduced this ROS production 
almost to the basal level (Figure 1A). In contrast, treatment of 
cells with 100 ng/mL EGF, a concentration that readily induced 
Akt phosphorylation, did not lead to a significant activation of intra-
cellular ROS production in comparison with the vehicle control. 
Resveratrol and DPI, however, were able to inhibit basal intracellu-
lar ROS level by about 50% (Figure 1B), verifying a strong ROS 
reducing activity for both compounds. Activation of the EGF-R 
has been reported to lead to increased extracellular H 2 O 2 levels 
in A431 cells. 
19 Therefore, we also measured extracellular H 2 O 2 </p>

<p>level using Amplex Red 
TM . Both Ang II and EGF were able to 
induce the extracellular release of H 2 O 2 in a time-dependent 
manner (Figure 1C and D). Whereas EGF treatment led to a con-
tinuous accumulation of H 2 O 2 , which was highest after 15 min 
(20% above basal level), H 2 O 2 production after Ang II stimulation 
peaked at 10 min (15% above basal level). Resveratrol reduced 
Ang II-and EGF-induced H 2 O 2 but also basal levels far below </p>

<p>control values (Figure 1C and D). These findings demonstrate that 
RV blocks both H 2 O 2 detected in the extracellular environment 
and intracellular total ROS produced in VSMCs. </p>

<p>3.2 A Nox4 knock-down does not influence 
the phosphorylation of Akt in Ang II-or 
EGF-activated VSMCs </p>

<p>To investigate whether Nox4 is important for the EGF-or Ang 
II-induced signalling towards Akt in our cell system, Nox4 was 
knocked down by siRNA. After 72 h, Nox4 mRNA level was analysed 
by qPCR. The siRNA reduced the Nox4 mRNA level to 15% com-
pared with scrambled control, whereas the mRNA level of Nox1 
was unchanged (Figure 2A and B). As expected, knock-down of 
Nox4 had no impact on the phosphorylation of Akt after Ang II 
(100 nM, 10 min) stimulation. Moreover, the inhibitory effect of RV 
on Akt phosphorylation remained unaffected (Figure 2C). Interestingly, 
the EGF-induced Akt phosphorylation and the inhibitory effect of RV 
also remained unaltered in Nox4 knock-down cells (Figure 2D). Thus, 
Nox4 seems not to be involved in Ang II-or EGF-mediated phos-
phorylation of Akt, and therefore Nox4-derived ROS are not a poten-
tial target of RV. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Ang II-and EGF-induced Akt phosphorylation and its </p>

<p>inhibition by RV occur independent of Nox4. Knock-down of 
Nox4 was achieved by treating cells with 50 nM small interfering 
RNA (siRNA) against Nox4 or 50 nM scrambled control siRNA 
for 72 h. The mRNA was isolated, and expression of Nox4 and 
Nox1 detected by qPCR. Graphs (A and B) show mean + SEM of 
Nox4 mRNA (A) or Nox1 mRNA (B) level relating to 18S mRNA. 
Data were normalized by setting scrambled control to 100% 
(***P , 0.001; n ¼ 3). Serum-deprived Nox4 siRNA-treated cells 
(50 nM, 72 h) were pre-treated with RV (50 mM, 30 min) or 
vehicle control followed by stimulation with 100 nM Ang II for 
10 min (C ) or 100 ng/mL EGF for 5 min (D). Akt phosphorylation 
and tubulin (tub, serving as a loading control) were detected by 
western blot analysis. One representative blot out of three, which 
were densitometrically analysed, is shown. The graphs represent 
the mean densitometric values + SEM of three independent exper-
iments. Akt phosphorylation in response to Ang II or EGF of 
scrambled control was set to 100% (*P , 0.05, **P , 0.01; 
one-way ANOVA, n ¼ 3). </p>

<p>Figure 3 Inhibition of Nox1 blunts phosphorylation of Akt and </p>

<p>p38 induced by Ang II but does not alter EGF-induced Akt and 
p38 phosphorylation. Quiescent VSMCs were pre-treated with 
100 mM of the gp91ds-tat blocking peptide (gp91ds), 50 mM RV or 
vehicle control for 30 min, and were then stimulated with 100 nM 
Ang II for 10 min (A and B) or 100 ng/mL EGF (C and D) for 
5 min. Akt (A and C) and p38 phosphorylation (B and D) as well 
as tubulin (tub, as loading control) were detected by western blot 
analysis. One representative blot out of three, which were densito-
metrically analysed, is shown. The graphs depict the mean densito-
metric values + SEM of three independent experiments. Signals 
obtained in response to Ang II or EGF were set to 100% 
(*P , 0.05, **P , 0.01; n.s., not significant; one-way ANOVA vs. 
Ang II or EGF treatment, n ¼ 3). </p>

<p>Resveratrol and redox signalling </p>



<p>3.3 Down-regulation of Nox1 inhibits Akt 
phosphorylation in response to Ang II but 
not EGF stimulation </p>

<p>In Ang II-activated VSMCs, Nox1 has been shown to be the major 
ROS-producing component necessary for the transactivation of the 
EGF-R, leading finally to Akt activation. 
16 To the best of our knowl-</p>

<p>edge, however, it is unknown whether EGF utilizes Nox1 to transduce 
its growth signal, although in transactivated settings prolonged Nox1 
activation seems to need Rac1 activation via PI3K downstream of the 
EGF-R. 
16 To inhibit Nox1 we employed 100 mM of the blocking </p>

<p>peptide gp91ds-tat that prevents assembly of the Nox protein with 
cofactors 
12 or a control peptide. As expected, gp91ds-tat pre-</p>

<p>treatment led to an inhibition of Ang II-mediated Akt phosphorylation 
(Figure 3A). In contrast to RV, gp91ds-tat also inhibited the phos-
phorylation of p38, a known redox-sensitive kinase, by more than 
50% (Figure 3B). In EGF-activated VSMCs, gp91ds-tat, in contrast to 
RV, had no effect on Akt phosphorylation (Figure 3C). A putative 
effect of gp91ds-tat on p38 phosphorylation did not reach significance 
(Figure 3D). The unspecific control peptide used had no influence on 
Akt or p38 phosphorylation in response to either stimulus (data not 
shown). These data show that Nox1 is important for Ang II-but not 
for EGF-mediated phosphorylation of Akt and p38. Inhibition of Nox1 
is not able to mimic the effect of RV in our setting, and thus renders 
Nox1-derived ROS an unlikely target of RV. </p>

<p>3.4 Both DPI and NAC inhibit Akt 
phosphorylation upon Ang II but not 
EGF stimulation </p>

<p>To further clarify the general dependency of EGF-and Ang II-induced 
signalling towards Akt and p38 on ROS we applied the Nox/flavopro-
tein inhibitor DPI (10 mM) and the precursor of glutathione, NAC 
(10 mM). We found that Ang II-induced phosphorylation of Akt was 
blocked by NAC as effectively as by RV, while DPI was less effective 
(Figure 4A). In contrast to RV, which had no effect on the phosphoryl-
ation of p38 after Ang II stimulation, NAC and DPI were able to block 
the phosphorylation to basal levels (Figure 4B). Phosphorylation of Akt 
upon EGF stimulation was inhibited effectively only by RV; NAC and 
DPI had no consistent inhibitory effect (Figure 4C). Resveratrol, NAC 
or DPI did not inhibit p38 phosphorylation in response to EGF stimu-
lation (Figure 4D). These data indicate that Ang II, as described, utilizes 
ROS for its signal transduction towards Akt and p38, but EGF does 
not. Moreover, RV seems not to require its antioxidant activity to 
inhibit Akt phosphorylation. </p>

<p>3.5 A non-antioxidant RV derivative 
inhibits Ang II and EGF-mediated Akt 
phosphorylation </p>

<p>To confirm that RV, although redox-active, does not act as an antiox-
idant when inhibiting Akt phosphorylation we employed the following 
two non-antioxidant derivatives of RV: trans-3,5,4 
′ -trimethoxystilbene </p>

<p>(RV-3M) with all three hydroxyl groups methylated (Figure 5A) and 
thus 
blunted 
redox 
activity, </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>and 
trans-3,5-dihydroxy-
4 
′ -methoxystilbene (RV-1M), methylated at the 4 
′ -OH group only </p>

<p>Figure 5 Non-antioxidant derivatives of RV, trans-3,5,4 </p>

<p>′ -trimethoxystilbene (RV-3M; A), and trans-3,5-dihydroxy-4 
′ -methoxystilbene (RV-1M; B). </p>

<p>Figure 4 DPI and NAC inhibit Ang II-induced phosphorylation of </p>

<p>Akt and p38. Serum-deprived cells were pre-treated with 50 mM RV 
or vehicle control for 30 min, 10 mM DPI for 1 h or 10 mM NAC for 
2 h, and then stimulated with 100 nM Ang II for 10 min (A and B), or 
100 ng/mL EGF for 5 min (C and D). Lysates were subjected to 
western blot analysis using antibodies against pAkt (A and C), pp38 
(B and D) and tubulin (tub). Representative blots out of three are 
shown. The graphs depict the mean + SEM of the densitometric ana-
lyses. Signals obtained in response to Ang II or EGF were set to 100% 
(*P , 0.05, **P , 0.01; n.s., not significant; one-way ANOVA vs. Ang 
II or EGF treatment, n ¼ 3). </p>

<p>C.E. Schreiner et al. </p>



<p>(Figure 5B). Mono-methylation at the 4 
′ -OH group renders RV largely </p>

<p>redox inactive, since Queiroz et al. have recently shown that the 
prime antioxidant pharmacophore of RV is 4 
′ -hydroxystilbene, 
27 a </p>

<p>finding that is also supported by others 
26 and confirmed by our syn-</p>

<p>thesized derivatives in vitro (see Supplementary material online, Figure 
S1). To test their redox activity in the presence of cells we used 
Amplex Red 
TM to detect extracellular H 2 O 2 in the presence of RV 
or its derivatives, RV-3M and RV-1M. As expected, neither of the 
two derivatives was found to reduce extracellularly detected H 2 O 2 
significantly after stimulation of VSMCs with Ang II (Figure 6A). 
Using Akt phosphorylation as read-out, RV-3M inhibited neither 
Ang II-nor EGF-induced Akt phosphorylation. Most interestingly, 
however, the derivative RV-1M, despite its lack of influence on 
H 2 O 2 , reduced phosphorylation of Akt in response to Ang II treat-
ment by over 50%, which was comparable to RV-mediated inhibition. 
The EGF-induced phosphorylation of Akt was inhibited equally well 
by RV-1M compared with RV (Figure 6B and C). These data clearly 
show that RV inhibits Akt phosphorylation by a mechanism that is 
not related to its antioxidant activity in both Ang II-and EGF-
stimulated VSMCs. In contrast, the 3-and 5-OH groups of RV seem 
to be critically involved in mediating Akt inhibition. A consistent 
picture of redox-independent inhibition of Akt phosphorylation by 
RV and RV-1M was observed in human primary aortic smooth 
muscle cells (see Supplementary material online, Figure S2). </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>We show here for the first time that although RV reduces total intra-
cellular ROS level and extracellular H 2 O 2 release, its antioxidant 
activity is not required for the inhibition of Akt phosphorylation in 
Ang II-or EGF-activated VSMCs. Moreover, we show that in 
VSMCs, EGF leads to an increase of extracellular H 2 O 2 level but 
not of intracellular ROS production. This H 2 O 2 seems not to play a 
major role for the signal transduction towards Akt and p38. Further-
more, we confirm that the Ang II-induced signalling pathways towards 
Akt and p38 require Nox1, and clearly show that Nox4 is not 
required for Ang II-or EGF-induced Akt activation. 
Many pharmacological effects of RV are believed to be related to its 
antioxidant activity. In the field of cardiovascular diseases, Opie &amp; 
Lecour recently summarized several of the RV effects that could be 
linked to an antioxidant action, including inhibition of low-density lipo-
protein oxidation, inhibition of prostaglandin synthesis, down-
regulation of intercellular adhesion molecule-1 and nuclear factor-kB, 
reduction of platelet activation and inhibition of Ang II-induced cardio-
myocyte hypertrophy, and they speculated that even more RV effects 
might be redox related, although not proven yet. 
2 Especially the </p>

<p>report showing that RV inhibits Ang II-induced cardiomyocyte hyper-
trophy by its antioxidant activity may be of interest in our context. 
The authors show that RV (1-100 mM) inhibits Ang II-induced 
[ 
3 H]leucine incorporation as a measure for hypertrophy, beta-myosin </p>

<p>heavy chain promoter activity, intracellular ROS level and ERK phos-
phorylation (although not examining other kinases) in cardiomyocytes. 
To link the antioxidant activity to the antihypertrophic effect of RV, they 
show that RV and the antioxidant NAC inhibit Ang II-or H 2 O 2 -induced 
[ 
3 H]leucine incorporation in cardiomyocytes comparably. 
28 In some </p>

<p>Figure 6 Non-antioxidant trans-3,5-dihydroxy-4 </p>

<p>′ -methoxystilbene 
(RV-1M) inhibits phosphorylation of Akt after Ang II and EGF stimu-
lation. (A) Starved VSMCs were stimulated in Amplex Red 
TM buffer 
with Ang II (100 nM) for 10 min after pre-incubation with RV or RV 
derivatives (RV, RV-3M, RV-1M; all 50 mM), or vehicle control for 
30 min. H 2 O 2 production was quantified by fluorescence measure-
ment. The graph shows the relative extracellular H 2 O 2 production 
(**P , 0.01; one-way ANOVA vs. Ang II or EGF treatment, n ¼ 3). 
(B and C). Serum-deprived cells were pre-treated with RV or RV 
derivatives, RV-3M or RV-1M, for 30 min (50 mM), followed by 
stimulation with 100 nM Ang II for 10 min (B), or 100 ng/mL EGF 
for 5 min (C ). Protein levels were detected by western blot using 
antibodies against pAkt and tubulin. One representative blot out 
of three per stimulation is shown. Graphs show the mean + SEM 
of the densitometric signals; Ang II or EGF stimulation is set to 
100% (**P , 0.01; one-way ANOVA vs. Ang II or EGF treatment, 
n ¼ 3). </p>

<p>Resveratrol and redox signalling </p>



<p>parts, the above report is in agreement with this and previous studies of 
our group, although we used VSMCs instead of cardiomyocytes; we 
found an inhibition of Ang II-induced hypertrophy measured by 
[ 
3 H]leucine incorporation 
4 and now also ROS production by RV. </p>

<p>Next to a minor effect on ERK phosphorylation, we found a strong inhi-
bition of the PI3K -Akt pathway leading more downstream to an effec-
tive inhibition of p70 S6 kinase important for cellular hypertrophy. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Here we show, however, that inhibition of ROS and Akt phosphoryl-
ation are two parallel events mediated by RV that could not be causally 
linked in our system. 
Our data also imply that the transduction of the signal induced by 
EGF in VSMCs is less redox dependent than that of Ang II, at least 
towards Akt and p38. Indeed, data regarding the ROS production 
of the EGF-activated (not transactivated) EGF-R and their importance 
for subsequent signal transduction are limited. The first report 
showing an intracellular increase in H 2 O 2 production in response to 
EGF used epithelial A431 cells and concentrations of EGF as high as 
500 ng/mL for stimulation. 
29 Halvey et al., 
20 also detecting an increase </p>

<p>of intracellular ROS after EGF stimulation in HaCaT cells, still used 
200 ng/mL EGF. In agreement with our data, DeYulia et al. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>showed in 293T cells transiently transfected with EGF-R that the 
addition of EGF (50 ng/mL) results in elevated extracellular H 2 O 2 . 
They even found that solely the receptor -ligand interaction using iso-
lated proteins was sufficient to produce H 2 O 2 . The exact mechanism 
by which ROS is produced, however, remained elusive. Regarding the 
ROS source that might be used by the EGF-R to transduce the EGF 
signal, Chen et al. proposed Nox4 that is localized at the endoplasmic 
reticulum and is critical for the regulation of PTP1B. Using human 
aortic endothelial cells (HAECs), and for transfection studies COS-7 
cells, they suggest that Nox4-mediated oxidation and inactivation of 
PTP1B in the endoplasmic reticulum serves as a regulatory switch 
for EGF-R trafficking that terminates the EGF signal. 
30 Moreover, </p>

<p>both the activated EGF-R as well as Nox4 were shown to be localized 
at focal adhesions in VSMCs. 
31 Knocking down Nox4 in our system, </p>

<p>however, had no influence on EGF-as well as Ang II-induced Akt 
phosphorylation, which excludes Nox4 as essential mediator of 
signal transduction towards Akt downstream of the AT 1 -and 
EGF-R as well as a potential target of RV. 
While the impact of Nox4-derived ROS for a variety of physiologi-
cal processes, including cell growth, death, and differentiation is not 
completely understood, the role of Nox1 in VSMC is much better 
defined. 
16 Nox1-derived ROS was shown to regulate smooth </p>

<p>muscle cell growth (hypertrophy and hyperplasia) and migration. 
The best-studied mechanism by which Nox1 is activated is that via 
the AT 1 receptor by Ang II, including activation of phospholipase C 
and subsequently protein kinase C that phosphorylates p47phox, a 
regulatory subunit of Nox1. Transactivation of the EGF-R leads to a 
PI3K-dependent activation of Rac1 that is required for continued acti-
vation of Nox1 by Ang II. 
16 Our data presented here again verify this </p>

<p>model; the blocking peptide gp91ds-tat effectively inhibited the Ang 
II-induced signalling towards Akt and p38. In contrast, EGF-mediated 
phosphorylation of Akt and p38 was not significantly altered. We, 
therefore, excluded a Nox1-dependent mechanism activating Akt or 
p38 downstream of the EGF-R in our cells. 
Several reports suggest an influence of RV on NAD(P)H oxidases in 
non-phagocytic cells. 
32 -34 In our experimental set-up, however, </p>

<p>neither knock-down of Nox4 nor inhibition of Nox1 assembly 
could mimic the RV effect. In addition, previous studies showed that 
RV was unable to inhibit the transactivation of the EGF-R in Ang </p>

<p>II-activated VSMCs, 
5 a process highly regulated by Nox1. Neverthe-</p>

<p>less, it remains conceivable that RV contributes to the inhibition of 
Nox1-derived ROS production by the inhibition of PI3K-dependent 
Rac1 at later time points. 
The strongest argument against a redox-dependent mechanism of 
the inhibition by RV of Ang II-or EGF-induced Akt activation came 
from RV derivatives that were not acting as antioxidants but were 
highly effective in inhibiting Akt phosphorylation (Figure 6). Most inter-
estingly, we found that the hydroxyl groups in the 3-and 5-positions 
are sufficient to block Ang II-or EGF-induced Akt phosphorylation. 
Although not detected, we cannot completely exclude the possibility 
that small or local rises in intracellular H 2 O 2 are quenched by these 
remaining two hydroxyl groups. 
In summary, we could verify that Nox1 but not Nox4 is important 
for the Ang II-induced activation of Akt and p38 in VSMCs. The signal-
ling triggered by EGF downstream of the EGF-R towards Akt and p38 
phosphorylation seems to occur independently of Nox1, Nox4 or in 
general of ROS. Most interestingly, we showed that RV, although 
reducing intracellular ROS and extracellular H 2 O 2 levels in VSMCs, 
does not use an antioxidant mechanism to inhibit Akt phosphoryl-
ation in Ang II-or EGF-activated VSMCs. </p>

<p>Supplementary material </p>

<p>Supplementary material is available at Cardiovascular Research online. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors would like to express their gratitude to H. Beres, B. Gindl 
and R. Leitner for expert technical assistance. We also wish to thank 
Drs Kathy K. Griendling and Dan Sorescu (Emory University School of 
Medicine) for providing rat VSMCs as well as for useful advice and 
fruitful discussions. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest: none declared. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>The work was supported by the Austrian Science Fund (FWF) [grant 
number P18982-B17 to V.M.D.]. Funding to pay the Open Access publi-
cation charge was provided by the Austrian Science Fund (FWF). </p>



<p>C.E. Schreiner et al. </p>





<p>Resveratrol and redox signalling </p>



</text></tei>