<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3880232" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>aBstract </p>

<p>introduction: The Heaviness of Smoking Index (HSI) is validated to measure nicotine dependence in nonpregnant smokers, 
and in these smokers, mean salivary and serum cotinine levels are related by a ratio of 1.25. However, as nicotine metabolism 
increases during gestation, these findings may differ in pregnancy. We investigated the validity of HSI in pregnancy by compar-
ing this with 3 biochemical measures; in a search for a less-invasive cotinine measure in pregnancy, we also explored the relation-
ship between mean blood and salivary cotinine levels. </p>

<p>Methods: Cross-sectional analyses using baseline data from the Smoking, Nicotine, and Pregnancy Trial. Participants were 
16-46 years old, 12-24 weeks gestation, smoked more than 5 cigarettes per day, and had exhaled carbon monoxide (CO) read-
ings of at least 8 ppm. Linear regression was used to examine correlations between HSI and blood cotinine and salivary cotinine 
and exhaled CO. Correlation between blood and salivary cotinine was investigated using linear regression through the origin. </p>

<p>results: HSI scores were associated with blood cotinine (R 2 = 0.20, n = 662, p &lt; .001), salivary cotinine (R 2 = 0.11, n = 967, 
p &lt; .001), and exhaled CO (R 2 = 0.13, n = 1,050, p &lt; .001). Salivary and blood cotinine levels, taken simultaneously, were highly 
correlated (R 2 = 0.91, n = 628, p &lt; .001) and the saliva:blood level ratio was 1.01 (95% CI 0.99-1.04). </p>

<p>conclusions: Correlations between HSI and biochemical measures in pregnancy were comparable with those obtained outside 
pregnancy, suggesting that HSI has similar validity in pregnant smokers. Salivary and blood cotinine levels are roughly equiva-
lent in pregnant smokers. </p>

<p>intrODuctiOn </p>

<p>Smoking in pregnancy is a modifiable risk factor for much 
morbidity, which carries a significant risk to both the mother 
and fetus, including long-term child health (Albrecht et al., 
1999; Fang, Dukic, Pickett, Wakschlag, &amp; Espy, 2012; Ward, 
Vander Weg, Sell, Scarinci, &amp; Read, 2006). A large American 
retrospective cohort study found infant mortality rates to be 
40% higher in pregnant smokers than nonsmokers (Salihu, 
Aliyu, Pierre-Louis, &amp; Alexander, 2003). Despite this, stud-
ies in the United States (Colman &amp; Joyce, 2003; Mathews &amp; 
Rivera, 2004) and United Kingdom (Health and Social Care 
Information Centre, 2012) showed that at least one third to one 
half of female smokers continue to smoke during pregnancy. 
Nonpregnant smokers with higher levels of nicotine 
dependence find it harder to quit smoking (Chaiton, Cohen, 
McDonald, &amp; Bondy, 2007; Courvoisier &amp; Etter, 2010) and 
nicotine replacement therapy can assist with this (Tang, Law, 
&amp; Wald, 1994). Hence, nicotine dependence may be a crucial 
factor in the maintenance of smoking behavior in pregnant 
women (Albrecht et al., 1999). One measure of nicotine </p>

<p>dependence, the six-item Fagerstrom Test for Cigarette 
Dependence (FTCD) has been validated and widely used 
outside of pregnancy (Burling &amp; Burling, 2003; Carpenter, 
Baker, Gray, &amp; Upadhyaya, 2010; Fagerström, 2012; 
Heatherton, Kozlowski, Frecker, &amp; Fagerström, 1991). Of the 
six items included in FTCD, "How soon after you wake up do 
you smoke your first cigarette?" and "How many cigarettes/ 
day do you smoke?" have been shown to account for most of 
the FTCD predictive value for smoking cessation (Burling &amp; 
Burling, 2003; Chabrol, Niezborala, Chastan, &amp; de Leon, 2005; 
Chaiton et al., 2007; Etter, Duc, &amp; Perneger, 1999; Fagerström, 
Russ, Yu, Yunis, &amp; Foulds, 2012; Haberstick et al., 2007; 
Heatherton et al., 1991; Kozlowski, Porter, Orleans, Pope, 
&amp; Heatherton, 1994; Pérez-Ríos et al., 2009) and correlate 
most strongly with biochemical measures of tobacco smoke 
exposure (Etter et al., 1999; Heatherton, Kozlowski, Frecker, 
Rickert, &amp; Robinson, 1989). Hence, these two items have 
been combined in a shorter alternative measure of nicotine 
dependence, the Heaviness of Smoking Index (HSI), which has 
also been used widely outside of pregnancy (Borland, Yong, 
O'Connor, Hyland, &amp; Thompson, 2010; Chaiton et al., 2007; </p>

<p>Advance Access publication August 13, 2013 </p>

<p>145 </p>

<p>nicotine &amp; tobacco research, volume 16, number 2 (February 2014) 145-154 </p>

<p>nicotine dependence measures in pregnancy </p>

<p>Etter et al., 1999; John et al., 2004; Kozlowski et al., 1994; Lim 
et al., 2012). The notion that nicotine dependence is variable 
and can be measured (Burling &amp; Burling, 2003) is important 
for characterizing smoking populations; measures of nicotine 
dependence are frequently used to describe participants in 
research studies and to guide smoking cessation treatment used 
by smokers (Tang et al., 1994). 
Nicotine metabolism increases during gestation (Rebagliato 
et al., 1998; Tricker, 2006), and this is likely to affect smok-
ing behaviors that the HSI measures, such as the number of 
cigarettes smoked. However, the timing and magnitude of 
gestational changes in nicotine metabolism are not known, 
and it is also not known if the relationship between smoking 
behaviors and nicotine metabolism remains constant as the 
latter changes. Consequently, it is not certain that the HSI, 
which has been validated to measure nicotine dependence 
in nonpregnant smokers, remains valid in pregnancy. After a 
review of the literature, we found no studies investigating the 
validity of HSI in pregnancy. However, we did find two stud-
ies that assessed two other nicotine dependence measures in 
pregnancy; one studied the FTCD (Panaretto et al., 2009) and 
the other, the Fagerstrom Tolerance Questionnaire (FTQ), a 
predecessor of FTCD. The first study (Panaretto et al., 2009) 
examined the use of FTCD in 152 urban, indigenous pregnant 
smokers in Australia. This found a statistically significant rela-
tionship between increasing FTCD scores and urinary cotinine 
concentrations. The other study (Albrecht et al., 1999) found 
a significant relationship between increasing FTQ scores and 
salivary cotinine levels in 42 pregnant adolescents recruited 
from three different smoking cessation studies. Although 
these studies suggest that both questionnaire-based measures 
may have some validity for measuring nicotine addiction in 
pregnancy, their sample sizes were small and more evidence 
is needed, particularly regarding the utility of the HSI in 
pregnancy. 
Cotinine is the primary metabolite of nicotine and is often 
used as an objective biochemical measure of nicotine expo-
sure to investigate validity of nicotine dependence measures 
(Benowitz, Hukkanen, &amp; Jacob, 2009; Tricker, 2006). Cotinine 
levels can be measured in blood or saliva samples; however, the 
relationship between blood and salivary cotinine in pregnancy 
remains unclear due to the changes in nicotine metabolism 
(Dempsey, Jacob, &amp; Benowitz, 2002; Rebagliato et al., 1998) 
and saliva composition during gestation (Eliasson, Birkhed, 
Osterberg, &amp; Carlén, 2006; Guidozzi, Maclennan, Graham, 
&amp; Jooste, 1992; Laine et al., 1988). Epidemiological studies 
of nonpregnant smokers found that mean salivary cotinine 
levels are closely related to serum cotinine but are around 
25% higher (Jarvis, Primatesta, Erens, Feyerabend, &amp; Bryant, 
2003). Quantification of the relationship in pregnancy would 
enable researchers to compare findings from studies of preg-
nant smokers, which use either serum or saliva samples and 
would permit researchers the flexibility to be pragmatic when 
deciding whether to use saliva or blood samples for cotinine 
estimation in research studies (Tricker, 2006). 
We aimed to investigate the validity of HSI as nicotine 
dependence measure in pregnancy by comparing this to three 
biochemical measures of nicotine and smoking exposure: 
blood cotinine, salivary cotinine, and exhaled carbon monox-
ide (CO); and we also investigated the relationship between 
blood and salivary cotinine samples taken simultaneously from 
pregnant smokers. </p>

<p>MethODs </p>

<p>Data for analyses in this report were collected at baseline in the 
Smoking, Nicotine and Pregnancy (SNAP) multicenter rand-
omized trial that investigated the efficacy and safety of nico-
tine replacement patches in pregnancy (Coleman et al., 2012). 
Full methods and the study protocol were published elsewhere 
(Coleman et al., 2012, 2007). </p>

<p>Sample Population </p>

<p>From May 2007 to February 2010, 1,050 pregnant women 
who attended antenatal ultrasonography appointments at seven 
hospital sites in East Midlands, England, were recruited. Trial 
participants were pregnant smokers aged 16-46 years and 
12-24 weeks of gestation. They smoked 10 or more cigarettes 
daily before pregnancy and five or more cigarettes daily at trial 
enrolment, as well as provided an exhaled CO sample of at 
least 8 ppm. </p>

<p>Measures </p>

<p>During enrolment, trial participants gave demographic infor-
mation including age, height, weight, ethnicity, age at leaving 
full-time education, weeks of gestation, and parity. They were 
also asked the number of cigarettes smoked per day before 
pregnancy, the time which had elapsed since smoking their last 
cigarette, their partner's smoking status, whether they had used 
nicotine replacement therapy during their current pregnancy, 
and if so, when they had last used it. </p>

<p>Heaviness of Smoking Index 
The two following HSI questions were asked by trained 
research midwives during trial enrolment: "How soon after you 
wake up do you smoke your first cigarette?" (TTFC) and "How 
many cigarettes per day do you currently smoke?" (CPD). The 
actual value of TTFC in minutes and number of CPD were 
then categorized to derive HSI scores as suggested by previous 
study (Heatherton et al., 1989). </p>

<p>Biochemical Measures of Nicotine and Tobacco Exposure 
Research midwives obtained biochemical samples from par-
ticipants; labeled blood and saliva samples were placed in a 
−20°C freezer on the day of collection. The samples were later 
taken to the University of Nottingham where they continued 
to be stored at −20°C before being collated and transferred 
in three batches (November 2007, December 2008, and July 
2010) to the University of Dundee for further storage at −80°C 
until analysis. Freezers were regularly checked with records 
kept of minimum and maximum temperatures, and when being 
transported, samples were placed in insulated containers, using 
dry ice where necessary, to ensure they remained frozen. 
Blood samples used to derive blood cotinine levels were 
taken in BD Vacutainer Gold top tubes. Due to the samples 
being hemolyzed, the University of Dundee was unable to 
analyze these and transferred them to ABS Laboratories, 
Hertfordshire, in November 2011. They were subsequently 
analyzed between December 2011 and January 2012 and the 
stability of cotinine while frozen was assured by the laboratory. 
For salivary cotinine analysis, at least 5 ml of saliva were 
collected unstimulated by drooling into a sterile polypropylene 
container after rinsing mouth with cold water 5 min prior to </p>



<p>nicotine &amp; tobacco research </p>

<p>sampling. A strict protocol for saliva collection was adhered 
to. Samples were not taken if participants admitted to hav-
ing drunk grapefruit juice within the previous week or if they 
had eaten, drunk, chewed gum, or brushed their teeth in the 
hour prior to sampling. The saliva samples were analyzed by 
the University of Dundee in batches from July 2009 to August 
2009 and December 2010 to January 2011. 
Both the salivary and blood cotinine levels were measured 
with a widely used liquid chromatography tandem mass spec-
trometry assay (Bernert et al., 2009; Doig et al., 2012). The 
blood cotinine analyses were performed blind to the results of 
salivary cotinine analyses. Exhaled CO levels were obtained 
using Micro 4 Smokerlyzer (Bedfont Scientific Limited, 
Rochester, Kent). </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Trial data collected at enrolment prior to randomization were 
used in all analyses. For blood and salivary cotinine analyses, 
women who did not provide samples were excluded as were 
those who reported having used nicotine replacement therapy 
(NRT) in the previous 7 days. NRT used by this latter group 
would potentially affect cotinine levels (Benowitz et al., 2009). 
Demographics were compared between pregnant women 
included and excluded from each analysis using Mann-
Whitney test for continuous data and Pearson chi-square test 
for categorical data. Internal reliability of HSI was examined 
using Cronbach's alpha. 
Linear regression was used to investigate the associations 
between HSI with each of the biochemical measures: blood 
cotinine, salivary cotinine, and exhaled CO. Assumptions of 
linear regression for each of the analyses were found to be 
adequately met. The relationships modeled appeared linear, 
and the residuals of the regression were normally distributed, 
showing no heteroscedasticity. Previous studies have found 
that age (Benowitz et al., 2009; Boyd, Windsor, Perkins, &amp; 
Lowe, 1998), ethnicity (Benowitz et al., 2009; Boyd et al., 
1998; Tricker, 2006), body mass index (BMI) (Jarvis et al., 
2003; Tricker, 2006), and weeks of gestation (Benowitz et al., 
2009; Dempsey et al., 2002; Rebagliato et al., 1998) affect 
nicotine metabolism and hence could be expected to influence 
salivary and blood cotinine levels. Having a smoking partner 
exposes the women to passive smoking, which would also 
affect the cotinine or CO levels (Boyd et al., 1998; Gilligan 
et al., 2010). As CO has a short half-life of 2-3 hr, CO levels 
are relatively easily affected by the time elapsed since smok-
ing prior to measuring the CO level (Javors, Hatch, &amp; Lamb, 
2011; Marrone, Paulpillai, Evans, Singleton, &amp; Heishman, 
2010). Hence, adjustment for these a priori factors was per-
formed. The linearity of the association between HSI with each 
of the biochemical measures was assessed by fitting the effect 
of HSI in seven quantiles and compared with a trend through 
these categories using likelihood ratio test. In order to compare 
the coefficient of determination (R 2 ) between associations of 
HSI with different biochemical measures, sensitivity analyses 
using subgroup of pregnant smokers who provided all three 
biochemical measures were done. 
Linear regression through the origin was used to investi-
gate the estimate of ratio between blood and salivary cotinine. 
Age and BMI had been found to affect the regression coef-
ficient in identical analysis performed in nonpregnant smok-
ers (Benowitz et al., 2009; Jarvis et al., 2003; Tricker, 2006), </p>

<p>whereas gestational age affects nicotine metabolism (Benowitz 
et al., 2009; Dempsey et al., 2002; Rebagliato et al., 1998). 
Hence, the effects of these a priori factors on the regression 
coefficient were investigated by interaction testing. All statisti-
cal analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">STATA</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 11.2</rs>. All 
CIs were at 95% and level of significance was at 5%. </p>

<p>results </p>

<p>Demographics </p>

<p>As all trial participants provided CO readings, all 1,050 preg-
nant women were included in the analyses that used exhaled 
CO readings. However, only 970 women provided saliva 
samples, and three of these had used NRT in the past 7 days, 
giving a sample size of 967 for the salivary cotinine analyses. 
Similarly, the sample size for the analyses using blood cotinine 
samples was 662, where 664 women provided blood samples, 
but two had used NRT in the previous 7 days. Six hundred 
twenty-eight women provided both blood and saliva samples 
and hence were included in the investigation of the relation-
ship between blood and salivary cotinine. Demographics of the 
participants included in the analyses and the comparison with 
participants excluded are shown in Table 1. 
The 662 women who were included in the blood cotinine 
analyses were primarily White British with a mean (SD) age of 
26.8 (6.2), mean (SD) gestation of 16.3 (3.5) weeks, and mean 
BMI (SD) of 26.8 (5.7) kg/m 2 . They smoked a median (inter-
quartile range) of 20 (15-20) and 13 (10-20) cigarettes before 
pregnancy and at the time of enrolment, respectively. Pregnant 
women included in the blood cotinine analyses were found to 
be older (26.8 years in the included group vs. 25.6 years in 
the excluded group, p = .002) and less likely to have a partner 
who smokes than women excluded from the analyses (71.4% 
vs. 79.6%, p = .005). They also took longer to light their first 
cigarette after waking (10 min vs. 7 min, p = .02). There were 
no statistically significant differences between remaining base-
line characteristics, including HSI scores (mean HSI of 2.57 
and 2.75 in the included and excluded group, respectively, 
p = .058). 
The 967 pregnant women used for salivary cotinine analy-
ses generally had similar characteristics to all women enrolled 
in the SNAP trial except that pregnant women in this group 
also took longer to light their first cigarette of the day (10 min 
vs. 7 min, p = .04). </p>

<p>Internal Reliability </p>

<p>The Cronbach's alpha coefficient calculated for HSI in preg-
nant smokers was .49. </p>

<p>Relationship Between HSI With Biochemical Measures 
of Nicotine and Tobacco Exposure </p>

<p>Scatter plots showed a fairly linear relationship between HSI and 
biochemical measures (Figure 1). Linear regression revealed that 
HSI accounted for 20%, 11%, and 13% of the variations in blood 
cotinine, salivary cotinine, and exhaled CO, respectively. After 
controlling for a priori factors, HSI was still significantly associ-
ated with blood cotinine, salivary cotinine, and exhaled CO (all 
p values &lt;.001). For every 1 unit rise of the HSI score, blood and </p>



<p>nicotine dependence measures in pregnancy </p>

<p>salivary cotinine increased by 20.4 ng/ml and 18.9 ng/ml, respec-
tively, whereas exhaled CO increased by 2.16 ppm. Sensitivity 
analyses using linear regression of only pregnant women who 
provided all three biochemical measures (n = 628) revealed 
similar R 2 and regression coefficient for HSI scores for each 
of the three biochemical measures: blood cotinine (R 2 = 0.21, </p>

<p>p &lt; .001), salivary cotinine (R 2 = 0.13, p &lt; .001), and exhaled CO 
(R 2 = 0.14, p &lt; .001). 
Likelihood ratio testing revealed no significant improvement 
in the fit of model using HSI as seven quantiles rather than as 
a trend across the categories for the salivary cotinine (p = .35) 
and exhaled CO analyses (p = .28). These indicated that HSI </p>

<p>table 1. Baseline Characteristics of Pregnant Women Included and Excluded From the Blood Cotinine 
(n = 662), Salivary Cotinine (n = 967), and Exhaled Carbon Monoxide (CO) (n = 1050) Analyses </p>

<p>Characteristics </p>

<p>CO analysis 
(n = 1050) </p>

<p>Blood cotinine analysis 
Salivary cotinine analysis </p>

<p>Included 
(n = 662) </p>

<p>Excluded 
(n = 388) </p>

<p>Included 
(n = 967) </p>

<p>Excluded 
(n = 83) </p>

<p>Age in years (M ± SD) 
26.3 ± 6.2 
26.8 ± 6.2* 
25.6 ± 6.0* 
26.3 ± 6.2 
26.2 ± 6.0 
Gestational age in weeks (M ± SD) 
16.2 ± 3.5 
16.3 ± 3.5 
16.1 ± 3.5 
16.2 ± 3.5 
16.3 ± 3.3 
Body mass index in kg/m 2 (M ± SD) a 
27.0 ± 6.2 
26.8 ± 5.7 
27.2 ± 7.0 
27.0 ± 6.2 
26.0 ± 6.3 
Ethnicity, n (%) b 
White British 
1018 (97.0%) 
643 (97.1%) 
375 (96.6%) 
940 (97.2%) 
78 (94.0%) 
Others 
32 (3.0%) 
19 (2.9%) 
13 (3.4%) 
27 (2.8%) 
5 (6.0%) 
Number of cigarettes smoked per day 
before pregnancy, (n) 
Median 
20 
20 
20 
20 
20 
Interquartile range 
15-20 
15-20 
15-20 
15-20 
15-20 
Number of cigarettes smoked per day 
at enrolment (n) 
Median 
13.5 
13 
15 
13 
15 
Interquartile range 
10-20 
10-20 
10-20 
10-20 
10-18 
Time from awakening to lighting 
first cigarette (min) 
Median 
10.0 
10.0* 
7.0* 
10.0* 
7.0* 
Interquartile range 
3.0-21.0 
3.0-31.0 
3.0-21.0 
3.0-28.0 
3.0-21.0 
Heaviness of Smoking Index, n (%) 
0 
65 (6.2%) 
45 (6.8%) 
20 (5.2%) 
61 (6.3%) 
4 (4.8%) 
1 
134 (12.8%) 
91 (13.7%) 
43 (11.1%) 
128 (13.2%) 
6 (7.2%) 
2 
259 (24.7%) 
161 (24.3%) 
98 (25.3%) 
238 (24.6%) 
21 (25.3%) 
3 
321 (30.6%) 
202 (30.5%) 
119 (30.7%) 
295 (30.5%) 
26 (31.3%) 
4 
209 (19.9%) 
132 (19.9%) 
77 (19.8%) 
186 (19.2%) 
23 (27.7%) 
5 
52 (5.0%) 
29 (4.4%) 
23 (5.9%) 
50 (5.2%) 
2 (2.4%) 
6 
10 (1%) 
2 (0.3%) 
8 (2.1%) 
9 (0.9%) 
1 (1.2%) 
Blood cotinine (ng/ml) c 
Median 
127.1 
127.1 
142.3 
Interquartile range 
88.0-174.1 
88.8-174.1 
92.6-176.9 
Salivary cotinine (ng/ml) d 
Median 
121.5 
120.5 
124.0 
Interquartile range 
78.1-177.2 
74.9-180.1 
81.2-167.7 
Exhaled carbon monoxide (ppm) 
Median 
14 
15 
14 
14 
15 
Interquartile range 
11-20 
11-21 
11-19.8 
11-20 
11-21 
Women with partner who smokes, n (%) e 
716 (74.4%) 
439 (71.4%)* 
277 (79.6%)* 
662 (74.3%) 
54 (75.0%) 
Previous use of nicotine replacement 
therapy during current pregnancy, n (%) </p>

<p>47 (4.5%) 
27 (4.1%) 
20 (5.2%) 
41 (4.2%) 
6 (7.2%) </p>

<p>Note. a Body mass index was not recorded for 22 women in the included group and 34 women in the excluded group (blood 
cotinine analysis); 47 women in the included group and 9 women in the excluded group (salivary cotinine analysis); 56 women in 
the overall group (exhaled CO analysis). 
b Self-reported ethnicity was categorized according to standard U.K. census category. "Other" included other White categories (e.g., 
White Irish or White other). 
c Three hundred and thirty-nine women in the included group and 47 women in the excluded group (salivary cotinine analysis); 386 
women in the overall group (exhaled CO analysis) did not have blood cotinine collected at the time of enrolment. 
d Thirty-four women in the included group and 46 women in the excluded group (blood cotinine analysis); 80 women in the overall 
group (exhaled CO analysis) did not have salivary cotinine collected at the time of enrolment. 
e Forty-seven women in the included group and 40 women in the excluded group (blood cotinine analysis); 76 women in the 
included group and 11 women in the excluded group (salivary cotinine analysis); 87 women in the overall group (exhaled CO 
analysis) did not have a partner at the time of enrolment. 
*Difference in baseline characteristics between pregnant women included and excluded in the analyses was statistically significant (p &lt; .05). </p>



<p>nicotine &amp; tobacco research </p>

<p>had linear relationships with salivary cotinine and exhaled CO. 
However, for the analysis using blood cotinine, the model using 
HSI as seven quantiles was found to fit significantly better than 
that of a trend across the categories (p = .03). However, there 
was no obvious nonlinear relationship between HSI and blood 
cotinine on inspection of the scatter plot (Figure 1). </p>

<p>Relationship Between Blood and Salivary Cotinine </p>

<p>Figure 2 showed a good correlation between blood and salivary 
cotinine levels (R 2 = 0.91, n = 628, p &lt; .001). Univariate linear 
regression through the origin provided an estimate of ratio of 
1.01 (95% CI 0.99-1.04) for the relationship between mean 
salivary and blood cotinine. Even after controlling for a priori 
factors, the regression coefficient for the relationship remained 
very similar at 1.03 (95% CI 0.97-1.09). </p>

<p>Interaction Testing </p>

<p>Age (p = .74) and gestation (p = .39) were not significant mod-
erators to the relationship between blood and salivary cotinine. 
A statistically significant interaction effect was found between </p>

<p>linear continuous variable of BMI and blood cotinine levels in 
predicting salivary cotinine levels (p = .02), suggesting that the 
slope of the regression line between blood and salivary cotinine 
varies with BMI. However, the estimate of this slope did not 
alter markedly at the two extremes of BMI of 1 SD below and 
above the mean, respectively (0.98 [95% CI 0.94-1.02] in low 
BMI vs. 1.04 [95% CI 1.00-1.08] in high BMI; Figure 2). </p>

<p>DiscussiOn </p>

<p>This study found that in pregnant smokers, higher HSI scores 
were associated with increasing tobacco exposure as indicated 
by biochemical measures. The relationships observed were of 
a similar magnitude to those obtained in studies done in non-
pregnant smokers, suggesting that HSI is similarly valid in 
pregnancy. Our study also found a high correlation between 
salivary and blood cotinine levels in pregnancy. Unlike the pre-
viously observed ratio of 1.25 in nonpregnant smokers (Jarvis 
et al., 2003), the ratio of mean salivary to blood cotinine levels 
in pregnancy was 1, even after adjustment for a priori factors. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Scatter plots showing correlations between Heaviness of Smoking Index (HSI) score and (A) blood cotinine, (B) 
salivary cotinine, and (C) exhaled carbon monoxide in 662, 967, and 1,050 pregnant women, respectively, with their relevant linear 
regression lines. </p>



<p>nicotine dependence measures in pregnancy </p>

<p>Study Limitations and Strengths </p>

<p>Smokers included in our study mainly described their ethnic group 
as "White British" and were all enrolled in a clinical trial, which 
specifically sought participants who were in their second trimes-
ter of pregnancy, smoked at least five cigarettes daily and moti-
vated to quit smoking. Hence, findings in the study may not be 
generalizable to pregnant smokers of other racial background and 
who smoke fewer cigarettes or who have not expressed a desire to 
quit. However, our pregnant women smoked a mean of 14 ciga-
rettes daily with mean HSI of 2.64, which was similar to previ-
ous studies in pregnant (England et al., 2001; Pollak et al., 2007; 
Office for National Statistics, 2013) and nonpregnant smokers 
(Courvoisier &amp; Etter, 2010; Health and Social Care Information 
Centre, 2012). It is unclear if similar findings could be extrapo-
lated to the first and third gestation of pregnancy. However, this 
may not affect the clinical importance of the findings as the first 
clinical encounter of the majority pregnant women would be dur-
ing their booking visit when they are in the end of their first or 
beginning of their second trimester of pregnancy. 
Although our study found similar magnitude of the associa-
tions between HSI and biochemical markers with other studies 
of nonpregnant smokers, this was not tested formally using a 
control nonpregnant group due to study design. 
Participants in the study were aware that biological speci-
mens would be used to monitor their smoking behavior. We 
found some evidence that participants who refused to provide 
biological specimens may have been more nicotine dependent 
than others; these women were found to light their first ciga-
rette after waking earlier than those who provided samples. It 
is not clear how the likelihood that participants who provided 
samples differed from others might have affected study find-
ings. However, as a sensitivity analysis conducted in the much 
smaller group of women who provided all three biochemical 
measures revealed similar findings to those in the larger, less 
self-selected groups, we believe that any biases in women's 
propensity to provide samples are unlikely to have had a major 
effect on the relationships between HSI and biochemical meas-
ures observed in our study. </p>

<p>One of the strengths of our study was the large sample sizes 
available for analyses and the ability to adjust for key potential 
confounders of cotinine and CO levels obtained after smok-
ing exposure. As such, the analyses should have had sufficient 
power and confounder adjustments to permit relationships 
between HSI and biochemical measures to be accurately quan-
tified. An additional strength was the use of trained research 
midwives who followed a well-defined protocol to collect 
all questionnaire data and biological samples. Finally, to our 
knowledge, this was the first study to investigate the validity 
of HSI as a self-reported nicotine dependence measure in preg-
nancy, so findings are likely to be of widespread interest. </p>

<p>Relationship Between HSI With Biochemical Measures 
of Nicotine and Tobacco Exposure </p>

<p>Cotinine is the primary metabolite of nicotine found in ciga-
rettes. Although there may be a lack of agreement about the 
gold standard measure for nicotine dependence in pregnancy, 
blood cotinine is a sensitive and stable biochemical nicotine 
exposure measure from cigarette smoking (Dempsey et al., 
2002; Kvalvik et al., 2012; Tricker, 2006) and has previously 
been used to validate nicotine dependence measures (Carpenter 
et al., 2010; SRNT Subcommittee on Biochemical Verification, 
2002). In our study, after controlling for factors considered, a 
priori, to possibly affect cotinine or CO levels, a significant 
positive correlation was found between HSI scores and the 
three biochemical measures. Of the three biochemical meas-
ures, blood cotinine, which has previously been used as a "gold 
standard" in similar studies (Carpenter et al., 2010; SRNT 
Subcommittee on Biochemical Verification, 2002), was found 
to correlate best with HSI. Although the relationships observed 
were not strong, associations between salivary cotinine levels 
and HSI scores were comparable with those obtained in the 
very few studies conducted within nonpregnant smokers of 
similar sample size (Table 2). However, we could not find any 
previous studies comparing HSI with blood cotinine levels for 
comparison. This similarity in findings was observed despite 
women in our sample smoking fewer cigarettes per day (mean </p>

<p>Figure 2. Scatter plot showing correlation between blood and salivary cotinine in 628 pregnant smokers with linear regression 
line without taking into account of a priori factors as well as regression lines at high and low body mass index (BMI). </p>



<p>nicotine &amp; tobacco research </p>

<p>table 2. 
Studies Investigating the Relationship of Heaviness of Smoking Index (HSI) With Biochemical Measures of Nicotine and Tobacco Exposure </p>

<p>Study </p>

<p>Sample size </p>

<p>Population characteristics </p>

<p>HSI score 
(M ± SD) 
TTFC in minutes 
(M ± SD) </p>

<p>CPD (M ± SD) </p>

<p>Questionnaire </p>

<p>Biochemical 
measure </p>

<p>R 2 </p>

<p>Heatherton et al. 
(1989): Sample 1 </p>

<p>168 
Visitors to science centre; 52% male and 48% female; mean 
age was 30.7 ± 9.6 years </p>

<p>N/A </p>

<p>43.3 ± 56.9 </p>

<p>22.1 ± 9.3 </p>

<p>HSI 
Salivary cotinine .30 
Exhaled CO </p>

<p>.30 </p>

<p>Heatherton et al. 
(1989): Sample 2 </p>

<p>736 
Population recruited by visiting randomly selected addresses; 
51% male and 49% female; mean age was 39.6 ± 13.7 years </p>

<p>N/A </p>

<p>46.4 ± 90.5 </p>

<p>21.5 ± 11.3 </p>

<p>HSI 
Salivary cotinine .10 
Exhaled CO </p>

<p>.07 </p>

<p>Heatherton et al. (1991) </p>

<p>254 
Visitors to science center; 44% male and 56% female; mean 
age was 33.5 ± 12.7 years. </p>

<p>N/A </p>

<p>47.2 ± 86.8 </p>

<p>20.7 ± 10.5 </p>

<p>HSI 
Salivary cotinine .31 
Exhaled CO </p>

<p>.26 </p>

<p>Kozlowski et al. (1994) </p>

<p>932 
Smoking cessation program participants; 35% male and 65% 
female. mean age was 40 ± 11.3 years </p>

<p>3.9 ± 0.05 </p>

<p>N/A </p>

<p>27.0 ± 12.2 </p>

<p>HSI </p>

<p>Exhaled CO </p>

<p>.06 </p>

<p>Burling (2003) </p>

<p>191 
All male drug/alcohol dependent cigarette smokers in 
residential rehabilitation; mean age was 40.0 ± 6.7 years </p>

<p>3.0 ± 1.2 </p>

<p>N/A </p>

<p>17.2 ± 7.3 </p>

<p>HSI 
Urine cotinine </p>

<p>.10 </p>

<p>Exhaled CO </p>

<p>.17 </p>

<p>Note. 
TTFC = time taken from awakening to first cigarette smoked; CPD = number of cigarettes smoked per day; R 2 </p>

<p>= coefficient of determination of linear regression; N/A = data not </p>

<p>reported in the study; CO = carbon monoxide. </p>



<p>nicotine dependence measures in pregnancy </p>

<p>number smoked daily, 14 compared with 17-27 in Table 2 
studies); but lighting their first cigarette of the day was sub-
stantially earlier than in other studies (mean time to first ciga-
rette, 21 min compared with 43-47 min in Table 2 studies). The 
stability of the relationship between HSI and cotinine measures 
in these varied samples of smokers suggests that HSI's valid-
ity for measuring nicotine dependence may be generic across 
smokers with very different characteristics. 
Our study found a generally linear relationship between 
HSI scores and biochemical measures of exposure, which was 
consistent with studies of nonpregnant smokers (Table 2). The 
nonlinearity of the relationship between HSI scores and blood 
cotinine as suggested by the likelihood ratio testing must be 
interpreted with caution. Pregnant smokers with HSI scores of 
6 had blood cotinine levels that were substantially higher than 
those predicted by linear regression (Figure 1), but as there 
are very few participants who had such high HSI scores, this 
finding could reflect the very small numbers of participants 
contributing to this analysis. Internal reliability of HSI in our 
sample of pregnant women was comparable with studies in 
nonpregnant smokers, which obtained Cronbach's α of .49 to 
.56 (Burling &amp; Burling, 2003; de Meneses-Gaya et al., 2009). </p>

<p>Relationship Between Blood and Salivary Cotinine </p>

<p>Similar to analyses conducted in nonpregnant smokers, blood 
and salivary cotinine in pregnant smokers were closely related 
(Jarvis et al., 2003; Tricker, 2006). Although BMI was found 
to influence the relationship between blood and salivary coti-
nine in pregnant smokers, it did not alter the regression coef-
ficient substantially. The effect of age on the relationship found 
in studies of nonpregnant smoker (Jarvis et al., 2003) was not 
noted in our study; however, as all participants in our study 
were pregnant, the range of their ages was restricted, which 
could explain this difference. 
Interestingly, the ratio of salivary to blood cotinine lev-
els in our sample of pregnant smokers was around unity. 
This contrasts to findings of a recent review (Tricker, 2006), 
which reported the range of salivary:plasma cotinine ratio in 
nonpregnant smokers as 1.1-1.4, with most empirical studies 
being small or having wide CIs (Bernert, McGuffey, Morrison, 
&amp; Pirkle, 2000; Machacek &amp; Jiang, 1986; van Vunakis et al., 
1989). The largest study included in the review (Jarvis et al., 
2003) included 270 female nonpregnant smokers and found a 
ratio of salivary to plasma cotinine of 1.23 (95% CI 1.21-1.25). 
Although this study used plasma cotinine analyzed by gas 
chromatography rather than blood cotinine measured by liquid 
chromatography, blood samples from this study and from ours 
were processed by the same laboratory, and no difference in 
cotinine levels due to variation in sample analysis method was 
expected (Bernert et al., 2009). Hence, it seems appropriate 
that in samples of pregnant women, mean salivary and blood 
cotinine values can be treated virtually interchangeable. 
The closer relationship between salivary and blood coti-
nine levels observed in our pregnant sample may be due to the 
effects of hormonal changes in pregnancy on saliva character-
istics and composition. The rise in estrogen in pregnancy may 
lower the pH and buffer capacity of saliva in pregnant women, 
affecting absorption of cotinine (Laine et al., 1988; Lukacs &amp; 
Largaespada, 2006; Rebagliato et al., 1998). An alternative 
explanation may be that the increased nicotine metabolism in 
pregnancy (Rebagliato et al., 1998; Tricker, 2006) may affect </p>

<p>salivary cotinine more than blood cotinine leading to the lower 
ratio, and further research is required. </p>

<p>suMMary </p>

<p>Our study had shown that HSI is a valid, brief measure of nico-
tine dependence in pregnancy, producing comparable results 
and psychometric properties to those observed in nonpregnant 
smokers. Future studies involving pregnant smokers can rou-
tinely incorporate HSI as a measure of nicotine dependence 
and, if preferred, cotinine assays can be performed using sali-
vary samples rather than blood samples because these produce 
roughly equivalent cotinine values and obtaining saliva sam-
ples is less invasive. In pregnancy, when calculating mean sali-
vary cotinine values from mean blood cotinine values, a ratio 
of 1 should be used instead of 1.25, which has been suggested 
for nonpregnant smokers. </p>

<p>FunDing </p>

<p>The original Smoking, Nicotine and Pregnancy (SNAP) rand-
omized control trial was supported by a grant from the National 
Institute for Health Research (NIHR) Health Technology 
Assessment Programme (grant number 06/07/01). </p>

<p>DeclaratiOn OF interests </p>

<p>The views and opinions expressed in this article are those of 
the authors and do not necessarily reflect those of the HTA 
programme, NIHR, NHS or the Department of Health. T.C. and 
S.L. are members of the UK Centre for Alcohol and Tobacco 
Studies; T.C. and S.C. are members of the NIHR National 
School for Primary Care Research, and J.T. is funded via an 
NIHR fellowship. </p>

<p>acknOwleDgMents </p>

<p>We would like to thank Mira V. Doig and ABS Laboratories for 
their contribution in blood cotinine analyses and interpretation 
of the blood cotinine values. We would also like to thank Dr 
Sheila Sharp and the University of Dundee for their contribu-
tion in analyzing the salivary cotinine samples. </p>





<p>nicotine &amp; tobacco research </p>





<p>nicotine dependence measures in pregnancy </p>





</text></tei>