<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3249287" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: The aim of the present study was to identify chromosomal loci that contribute to the pathogenesis of </p>

<p>aortic dissection (AD) in a Korean population using array comparative genomic hybridization (CGH) and to confirm 
the results using real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR). Materials and Methods: Eighteen patients with ADs 
were enrolled in this study. Genomic DNA was extracted from individual blood samples, and array CGH analyses 
were performed. Four corresponding genes with obvious genomic changes were analyzed using real-time PCR in 
order to assess the level of genomic imbalance identified by array CGH. Results: Genomic gains were most fre-
quently detected at 8q24.3 (56%), followed by regions 7q35, 11q12.2, and 15q25.2 (50%). Genomic losses were 
most frequently observed at 4q35.2 (56%). Real-time PCR confirmed the results of the array CGH studies of the 
COL6A2, DGCR14, PCSK6, and SDHA genes. Conclusion: This is the first study to identify candidate regions by </p>

<p>array CGH in patients with ADs. The identification of genes that may predispose an individual to AD may lead to 
a better understanding of the mechanism of AD formation. Further multicenter studies comparing cohorts of patients 
of different ethnicities are warranted. </p>

<p>Aortic dissection (AD) is an uncommon but highly lethal </p>

<p>disease that leads to the gradual deterioration of the mechan-</p>

<p>ical properties of the aortic wall. It is caused by weak aortic </p>

<p>structure, incompetent repair mechanisms and powerful de-</p>

<p>structive forces. Although genetic factors may play an im-</p>

<p>portant role in the pathogenesis of AD [1-3], studies inves-</p>

<p>tigating the genetic determinants of AD have been superficial, </p>

<p>and reports of genetic risk factors for AD in Koreans are ex-</p>

<p>tremely rare. 
Several chromosomal loci with evidence of linkage were </p>

<p>found in studies of thoracic aortic diseases [4-6], but the </p>

<p>mode of genetic transmission for AD remains uncertain. The </p>

<p>identification of genetic markers associated with an increased </p>

<p>risk of AD formation and growth will improve the treatment </p>

<p>outcomes of patients with AD. </p>

<p>Array Comparative Genomic Hybridization (CGH) is a </p>

<p>Jong Hui Suh, et al </p>

<p>− 124 − </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic characteristics of the 18 subjects </p>

<p>Characteristic 
n </p>

<p>No. of patients 
18 
Sex, female/male 
8/10 
Age, yr 
54.17±11.76 
Operative therapy 
14 
Conservative therapy 
4 
DeBakey classification 
Type I 
5 
Type II 
10 
Type III 
3 
Combined diseases 
Coronary artery disease 
5 
Atherosclerosis 
4 
Bicuspid aortic valve 
2 
Hypertension 
15 
Hyperlipidemia 
2 
Diabetes mellitus 
2 
COPD 
0 
Current smoking 
5 
Peripheral vascular disease 
0 
Stroke 
0 
Familial history of aortic disease 
0 </p>

<p>COPD=Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. </p>

<p>powerful technique, allowing the simultaneous quantitative </p>

<p>analysis of entire genomes, including a higher resolution, more </p>

<p>dynamic range, direct mapping of aberrations to genomic se-</p>

<p>quences, and higher throughput [7,8]. Therefore, array CGH </p>

<p>has been used to detect chromosomal aberrations in mental </p>

<p>retardation, epilepsy, and schizophrenia [9-12]. Real-time pol-</p>

<p>ymerase chain reaction (PCR) has been used to empirically </p>

<p>confirm the results of array CGH [13,14]. Moreover, quantita-</p>

<p>tive real-time PCR has great advantages in measuring DNA </p>

<p>copy-number changes owing to the economy, simplicity, and </p>

<p>flexibility of the technique [15]. 
The aim of the present study was to identify possible chro-</p>

<p>mosomal loci associated with the pathogenesis of AD in </p>

<p>Koreans using array CGH and to confirm the results with re-</p>

<p>al-time PCR. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>1) Patient population </p>

<p>A total of 18 patients with ADs were recruited from the </p>

<p>single hospital. The mean age of the patients was 54.17 </p>

<p>years, ranging from 41 to 77 years. The demographic data </p>

<p>and range of aortic pathologic disease are summarized in </p>

<p>Table 1. Genomic DNA was extracted from individual blood </p>

<p>samples using the Puregene DNA isolation kit (Qiagen, </p>

<p>Hilden, Germany). Reference DNA was pooled from ten gen-</p>

<p>der-matched (male), normal, healthy control subjects. Approval </p>

<p>was obtained from the institutional review board of the </p>

<p>College of Medicine of our university, and informed consent </p>

<p>was provided according to the Declaration of Helsinki. </p>

<p>2) Array-CGH analysis </p>

<p>Array-CGH analyses were conducted on 18 individual </p>

<p>samples. Array CGH was performed as described previously </p>

<p>[16] using a commercial MACArray </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>-Karyo 4K BAC-chip </p>

<p>(Macrogen, Seoul, Korea) with 4,030 bacterial artificial chro-</p>

<p>mosome (BAC) clones duplicating the whole human genome </p>

<p>with a resolution of 1 Mbp. DNA was labeled using the </p>

<p>BioPrime labeling kit (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA). Each DNA </p>

<p>(target and reference DNA) sample (500∼700 ng) with ran-</p>

<p>dom primers was boiled at 98∼100 
o C for 5 min for denatu-</p>

<p>ration and then cooled on ice for 5 min. The denatured DNA </p>

<p>was differentially labeled with 3μL of 1 mM Cy3-dCTP </p>

<p>(references DNA), Cy5-dCTP (Target DNA), respectively </p>

<p>(PerkinElmer, Boston, MA), and 1μL Klenow fragments </p>

<p>were added to the mixture (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA). DNA </p>

<p>was incubated at 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C overnight for labeling. Subsequently, </p>

<p>unincorporated nucleotides were removed using MicroSpin </p>

<p>G-50 columns (Amersham Biosciences, Buckinghamshire, </p>

<p>England). Cy3 and Cy5 labeled DNA (Target DNA and refer-</p>

<p>ence DNA, repectively) was mixed with 50μg of human </p>

<p>Cot-1 DNA for blocking of repeat sequences. After purifica-</p>

<p>tion, the mixture was resolved in hybridization buffer contain-</p>

<p>ing yeast tRNA for blocking binding of non-specific </p>

<p>nucleotides. After the chips were in hybridization buffer with </p>

<p>salmon sperm DNA for 1 h, the chips were hybridized with </p>

<p>the purification mixture. Then they were incubated for 72 h </p>

<p>in the 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C hybridization chamber (BioMicro Systems, Salt </p>

<p>Lake City, UT). After hybridization was complete, the array </p>

<p>chips were washed and dried and then the arrays were scan-</p>

<p>ned with a Genepix 
Ⓡ (Axon Instruments, Foster City, CA). </p>

<p>Genomic Aberrations in Aortic Dissections </p>

<p>− 125 − </p>

<p>Table 2. Recurrent Gains/Losses in aortic dissecting aneurysms (＞30 frequencies) (UCSC genome browser: May 2004) </p>

<p>Chromosomal 
region </p>

<p>Frequency 
(%) </p>

<p>Bac_start 
(bp) </p>

<p>Bac_end 
(bp) </p>

<p>Size 
(bp) 
Contained genes </p>

<p>Gains 
1p11.2 
6 (33%) 120390109 
120485103 
94994 
NOTCH2 
1q23.1 
6 (33%) 155045002 
155148010 
103008 
SH2D2A, NTRK1, INSRR 
2p13.1 
8 (44%) 
74539520 
74620052 
80532 
WBP1, MRPL53, LBX2, PCGF1, TLX2, DQX1, AUP1, 
HTRA2, LOXL3 
2q31.1 
6 (33%) 177310814 
177395162 
84348 
FUCA1P 
2q37.3 
7 (39%) 240550837 
240713841 
163004 
NDUFA10, OR6B2, OR6B3, OR5S1P 
3q21.3 
6 (33%) 131099654 
131218467 
118813 
TRH 
4q13.3 
8 (44%) 
74536267 
74654547 
118280 
AFP, AFM 
4q24 
6 (33%) 105045356 
105165560 
120204 
5p15.33 
6 (33%) 
203859 
298137 
94278 
SDHA* 
5p15.33 
6 (33%) 
557250 
688780 
131530 
SLC9A3, CEP72 
6p12.2 
6 (33%) 
51985699 
52087584 
101885 
PKHD1 
7p14.3 
7 (39%) 
33392813 
33486178 
93365 
7q11.23 
7 (39%) 
74705985 
74764828 
58843 
7q11.23 
8 (44%) 
72089609 
74747885 
2658276 
FKBP6, NSUN5, TRIM50, FZD9, BAZ1B, BCL7B, TBL2, 
MLXIPL, VPS37D, WBSCR18, STX1A, ABHD11, CLDN3, 
CLDN4, WBSCR27, ELN, LIMK1, WBSCR1, LAT2, RFC2, 
CYLN2, GTF2IRD1, WBSCR23, GTF2I, PMS2L5, 
WBSCR16, NCF1, GTF2IP1 
7q35 
9 (50%) 143557352 
143585922 
28570 
OR2A42, OR2A9P 
8p21.2 
6 (33%) 
23582247 
23671417 
89170 
NKX3-1 
8p22 
6 (33%) 
18268730 
18357165 
88435 
AACP, NAT2 
8p23.3 
6 (33%) 
649638 
867290 
217652 
ERICH1, C8orf68 
8q13.2 
6 (33%) 
68343074 
68444177 
101103 
ARFGEF1 
8q24.3 
10 (56%) 145298570 
145384455 
85885 
10p15.3 
6 (33%) 
795549 
881206 
85657 
LARP5 
10q11.23 
7 (39%) 
52453706 
52563182 
109476 
PRKG1 
10q22.3 
6 (33%) 
79941269 
80019660 
78391 
10q23.1 
6 (33%) 
86354131 
86459920 
105789 
10q26.3 
6 (33%) 134654530 
134754530 
100000 
GPR123 
11q12.2 
9 (50%) 
60669725 
60731709 
61984 
VPS37C </p>

<p>3) Data analysis </p>

<p>The scanned images were analyzed to determine Cy3：Cy5 </p>

<p>ratios for each array element using <rs id="software-0" type="software">MAC Viewer</rs> 
TM <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v1.6.3</rs> </p>

<p>software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Macrogen</rs>, Seoul, Korea). Data are presented as </p>

<p>log2 (Cy3 intensity/Cy5 intensity ratios) plotted against the </p>

<p>position of clones within the particular chromosome in the </p>

<p>current version of the genome. Ratios were normalized by us-</p>

<p>ing the median of fluorescence ratios computed as log2 values </p>

<p>from the housekeeping DNA control fragments linearly dis-</p>

<p>tributed across the genome. Measurements flagged as un-</p>

<p>reliable by <rs id="software-1" type="software">MAC Viewer</rs> 
TM <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">v1.6.3</rs> were excluded from sub-</p>

<p>sequent analyses. The threshold corresponds to 2 standard de-</p>

<p>viation (SD) values from the mean. The information on each </p>

<p>individual clone was obtained from the UCSC Genome </p>

<p>Bioinformatics database (May 2004 freeze, http://genome.ucsc. </p>

<p>edu). Then log2 ratios of chromosomal aberration regions </p>

<p>were identified via t test analysis using the Sigma Plot </p>

<p>program. All chromosome regions indicated as aberrant in </p>

<p>Table 2 were calculated via t test analysis. </p>

<p>4) Quantitative real-time PCR </p>

<p>To validate genomic imbalances identified by array CGH </p>

<p>in this study, four genes with obvious genomic changes were </p>

<p>Jong Hui Suh, et al </p>

<p>− 126 − </p>

<p>Table 2. Continued </p>

<p>Chromosomal 
region </p>

<p>Frequency 
(%) </p>

<p>Bac_start 
(bp) </p>

<p>Bac_end 
(bp) </p>

<p>Size 
(bp) 
Contained genes </p>

<p>12p13.33 
7 (39%) 
183679 
257363 
73684 
SLC6A12, SLC6A13 
12q13.13 
6 (33%) 
52345803 
52436777 
90974 
ATP5G2, CALCOCO1 
13q33.3 
6 (33%) 107569780 
107652035 
82255 
14q24.2 
6 (33%) 
71175267 
71266409 
91142 
SIPA1L1 
14q32.33 
7 (39%) 105541523 
105648959 
107436 
15q25.2 
9 (50%) 
80539371 
80776796 
237425 
RPS17 
15q26.3 
6 (33%) 
99653473 
99758817 
105344 
PCSK6* 
17q12 
6 (33%) 
31081633 
31171045 
89412 
RASL10B, GAS2L2, C17orf50, MMP28, TAF15 
17q21.31 
7 (39%) 
39133290 
39273024 
139734 
SOST, DUSP3, MPP3 
17q25.3 
6 (33%) 
77755881 
77849251 
93370 
SLC16A3, CSNK1D 
19p13.11 
8 (44%) 
17691080 
17784835 
93755 
BPY2IP1, FCHO1, B3GNT3 
19q13.43 
6 (33%) 
63514606 
63629648 
115042 
HKR2, A1BG, ZNF497, RPS5, ZNF584 
21q22.11 
6 (33%) 
31352497 
31450699 
98202 
UBE3AP2, TIAM1 
21q22.3 
7 (39%) 
46373142 
46463667 
90525 
COL6A2*, FTCD, C21orf56, LSS 
Losses 
4q35.2 
10 (56%) 190963818 
191006683 
42865 
7q22.1 
7 (39%) 100407386 
100480418 
73032 
MUC12, MUC17 
10q26.3 
7 (39%) 134755203 
134904547 
149344 
GPR123, KNDC1, UTF1, VENTX 
14q32.33 
8 (44%) 105821330 
105907464 
86134 
15q11.2 
8 (44%) 
19958100 
20053879 
95779 
VSIG6 
16p12.3 
6 (33%) 
16274784 
16391850 
117066 
NOMO3, PKD1P1, PKD1P2 
16p13.11 
7 (39%) 
14873336 
14958740 
85404 
NOMO1, PKD1P3, NPIP 
22q11.21 
7 (39%) 
17158480 
18962782 
1804302 
GGT2, DGCR6, PRODH, DGCR5, DGCR2, TSSK7P, 
DGCR13, TSSK2, DGCR14*, GSCL, SLC25A1, CLTCL1, 
HIRA, MRPL40, UFD1L, CDC45L, CLDN5, SEPT5, GP1BB, 
TBX1, GNB1L, TXNRD2, COMT, ARVCF, C22orf25, 
DGCR8, RANBP1, ZDHHC8, RTN4R, DGCR6L </p>

<p>*=Verified by real-time PCR. </p>

<p>analyzed using real-time PCR. For relative quantification, the </p>

<p>reactions were performed in a total volume of 50μL, includ-</p>

<p>ing 25μL of 2× IQ 
TM SYBR 
Ⓡ green supermix (Bio-Rad, </p>

<p>Hercules, CA), 10 ng of DNA, and 10 pmol of each primer. </p>

<p>Forty cycles of amplification, data acquisition, and data anal-</p>

<p>ysis were performed in an iCycler (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). </p>

<p>Primers for four genes (COL6A2, DGCR14, PCSK6, and </p>

<p>SDHA) were selected and the position of each clone was ob-</p>

<p>tained from the UCSC genome database (May 2004). The </p>

<p>primer sequences used were as follows: COL6A2, forward, </p>

<p>5'-TCCATGTCTCAAGCGTTCTG-3'; reverse, 5'-TGGGTT-</p>

<p>CTGCCCTATGACTC-3'; DGCR14, forward, 5'-GACAGT-</p>

<p>TCAGCAGGCTTTCC-3'; reverse, 5'-TGATCTTGGCTCAC-</p>

<p>TGCAAC-3'; PCSK6, forward, 5'-GGCAACAAAAGAAA-</p>

<p>GCAAGC-3'; reverse, 5'-TCTCAACAGCTGGGAGAGGT-3'; </p>

<p>SDHA, forward, 5'-CTGAGTGATGCCCTGCAGTA-3'; re-</p>

<p>verse, 5'-TTCCACGAGCAGAGGAAACT-3'. All real-time </p>

<p>PCR procedures were performed three times and the normal </p>

<p>control was different from each experiment (all three normal </p>

<p>samples). The relative genomic copy number was calculated </p>

<p>using the comparative CT method [17]. CT for each gene was </p>

<p>determined using thermocycler software, and the average of </p>

<p>three independent experiments was calculated. The copy num-</p>

<p>ber of the target gene was normalized to an endogenous ref-</p>

<p>erence, GAPDH, which showed no significant copy number </p>

<p>change in each genome [18]. The fold change from normal </p>

<p>samples was set at 1-fold and the ratio of the normalized fold </p>

<p>change in TAD compared to that of control samples was </p>

<p>calculated. </p>

<p>Genomic Aberrations in Aortic Dissections </p>

<p>− 127 − </p>

<p>Table 3. Examples of t test analysis in specific alterative regions </p>

<p>Chromosome 
region </p>

<p>Log2 ratio 
means±SD 
T value 
p-value </p>

<p>7q35 
0.43±0.12 
−11.06 
6.6E-09 
8q24.3 
0.35±0.13 
−8.40 
1.21E-07 
11q12.2 
0.38±0.13 
−8.78 
1.64E-07 
15q25.2 
0.28±0.06 
−13.54 
4E-10 
4q35.2 
−0.63±0.34 
5.88 
1.45E-05 </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>1) Pattern of aberration in individual chromosomal </p>

<p>region </p>

<p>Chromosomal copy-number changes were detected by array </p>

<p>CGH in blood samples obtained from AD patients. The iden-</p>

<p>tified regions of genomic aberrations, ranging from 6 in 18 </p>

<p>samples (33% frequency of chromosomal gain and loss) to 10 </p>

<p>in 18 samples (56% frequency of chromosomal gain at 8q </p>

<p>and loss at 4q) (Table 2). Overall, the individual chromoso-</p>

<p>mal aberration pattern was not random and tended to be con-</p>

<p>sistent, showing DNA gains at 1p, 1q, 2p, 2q, 3q, 4q, 5p, 6p, </p>

<p>7p, 7q, 8p, 8q, 10p, 10q, 11q, 12p, 12q, 13q, 14q, 15q, 17q, </p>

<p>19p, 19q and 21q, and DNA losses at 4q, 7q, 10q, 14q, 15q, </p>

<p>16p and 22q. Chromosomal copy number gains were ob-</p>

<p>served more frequently than copy number losses. The most </p>

<p>frequently detected gains were at 8q24.3 (56%). DNA gains </p>

<p>were also frequently observed at 7q35, 11q12.2 and 15q25.2 </p>

<p>in 9 samples (50%), and in 2p13.1, 4q13.3, 7q11.23 and </p>

<p>19p13.11 in 8 samples (44%). Regions with a 39% frequency </p>

<p>of gains were 2q37.3, 7p14.3, 7q11.23, 10q11.23, 12p13.33, </p>

<p>14q32.33, 17q21.31 and 21q22.3. Other regions with 33% </p>

<p>frequency of DNA gains included 1p11.2, 1q23.1, 2q31.1, </p>

<p>3q21.3, 4q24, 5p15.33, 6p12.2, 8p21.2, 8p22, 8p23.3, 8q13.2, </p>

<p>10p15.3, 10q22.3, 10q23.1, 10q26.3, 12q13.13, 13q33.3, </p>

<p>14q24.2, 15q26.3, 17q12, 17q25.3, 19q13.43 and 21q22.11. </p>

<p>Genomic losses were most frequently observed in 4q35.2 </p>

<p>(56%). Regions with 44% frequency of losses were 14q32.33 </p>

<p>and 15q11.2. Other regions with 33∼39% frequency of DNA </p>

<p>loss included 7q22.1, 10q26.3, 16p12.3, 16p13.11, and </p>

<p>22q11.21 (Table 2). 
To attempt to correlate a diagnosis with a specific region, </p>

<p>we applied statistics for each potential loci. All aberrant chro-</p>

<p>mosomal locations (＞30%) detected in array CGH (Table 2) </p>

<p>were selected in t test analysis. Although all 48 regions were </p>

<p>calculated, only t test analysis of five regions is shown in </p>

<p>Table 3. Because a high association was detected in all re-</p>

<p>gions, examples which indicated higher p-value (＞50% fre-</p>

<p>quency) are shown in the Tables </p>

<p>2) Real-time PCR </p>

<p>Four genes with obvious genomic changes were analyzed </p>

<p>using real-time PCR in order to assess the level of genomic </p>

<p>imbalance identified by array CGH in this study. Of the more </p>

<p>than 30% frequency clones, those considered to have vascular </p>

<p>related aberrations in the chromosome were selected for re-</p>

<p>al-time PCR. We evaluated the change in fold difference in </p>

<p>samples from normal and AD patients. Fig. 1 shows the re-</p>

<p>gions of chromosomal aberration in the four genes. Gains </p>

<p>were seen in 5p15.33, 15q26.3, and 21q22.3, which contain </p>

<p>the SDHA, PCSK6, and COL6A2 genes (A, B, and C), while </p>

<p>a loss was observed at 22q11.21, which contains the DGCR14 </p>

<p>genes (D). The fold difference obtained from the real-time </p>

<p>PCR was in accordance with the array CGH results and the </p>

<p>p-values of all samples was ＜0.05. The gain regions (A∼C; </p>

<p>COL6A2, PCSK6, and SDHA) in the results from the re-</p>

<p>al-time PCR were equal to all of the gain regions in the ar-</p>

<p>ray CGH. The relative fold decreases in DGCR14 (D) were </p>

<p>reflected similarly. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Aortic dissection is a life-threatening disease that develops </p>

<p>without warning. Despite significant advances in diagnostic </p>

<p>and therapeutic techniques, the overall in-hospital mortality </p>

<p>was 27.4% according to the international registry of aortic </p>

<p>dissection [19]. It occurs in 2∼9% of the population over 65 </p>

<p>years old, and the prevalence may be increasing [20]. Modern </p>

<p>diagnostic methods, such as computed or magnetic resonance </p>

<p>tomography, are able to show an aortic wall hematoma at the </p>

<p>acute onset of the disease. This hematoma will develop into </p>

<p>an aortic wall dissection over time [6]. Early recognition and </p>

<p>management are crucial, and it is therefore important to be </p>

<p>able to rapidly identify aortic dissection, initiate supportive </p>

<p>therapy, and refer patients to appropriate specialty care [2]. </p>

<p>Jong Hui Suh, et al </p>

<p>− 128 − </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Relative fold differences selected from 4 genes in which the most frequent gains and losses detected were in the 5p, 15q, 21q, 
and 22q regions. Each sample is depicted (x axis), and the fold difference of the N-value was delineated in real-time PCR (y axis). A 
threshold level of 2 indicates significant DNA gain (A∼C), and 0.5 indicates significant DNA loss (D). At the chromosomal 21q22.3 loca-
tion, COL6A2 (A), the fold change of the sample was 2.25-to 3.14-fold (seven samples) versus 1-fold for the reference sample. The fold 
difference for the SDHA (B) was 2.4-to 4.57-fold (six samples). For the PCSK6 (C), in the chromosomal 15q26.3 region, the fold change 
of the sample was 2.11-to 4.76-fold (six samples) with a gain at the location. Finally, DGCR14 (D) had a 0.08∼0.4-fold change (seven 
samples) with a loss at the location (p＜0.05). </p>

<p>Current research is aimed at determining the phenotypic </p>

<p>consequences of specific copy number abnormalities in pa-</p>

<p>tients with ADs [21]. Cytogenetic analyses have revealed that </p>

<p>numerous somatic genetic changes in the pathogenesis of hu-</p>

<p>man diseases are involved in region-specific gains or losses </p>

<p>of DNA copy number; however, such changes have not yet </p>

<p>been reported in most ADs. Including classical cytogenetics, </p>

<p>fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH), Southern blot analy-</p>

<p>sis, quantitative PCR based assays, and CGH have been used </p>

<p>to detect copy number changes in human diseases, but these </p>

<p>techniques have several limitations [22]. Therefore, we at-</p>

<p>tempted to use array CGH. Unlike chromosomal CGH, array </p>

<p>CGH highly improves resolution and provides quantitative in-</p>

<p>formation of the level of chromosomal gain or loss [16,23]. </p>

<p>BAC array CGH has been used in several diseases but has </p>

<p>not been applied to ADs. 
In this report, the DNA copy number alterations frequently </p>

<p>identified in 18 patients with AD were analyzed using array </p>

<p>based CGH. Many regions throughout the entire genome were </p>

<p>altered. The DNA copy number alterations observed in the </p>

<p>Genomic Aberrations in Aortic Dissections </p>

<p>− 129 − </p>

<p>ADs were not random; they involved particular regions of the </p>

<p>genome and most usually involved parts of or the entire </p>

<p>DNA. DNA gains were found in regions 1p, 1q, 2p, 2q, 3q, </p>

<p>4q, 5p, 6p 7p, 7q, 8p, 8q, 10p, 10q, 11q, 12p, 12q, 13q, 14q, </p>

<p>15q, 17q, 19p, and 21q, and losses were found in 4q, 7q, </p>

<p>10q, 14q, 15q, 16p, and 22q (Table 2). DNA gains were </p>

<p>more frequently observed than DNA losses. 
Real-time PCR can be used to validate and quantify the </p>

<p>genomic changes identified by BAC array CGH [17]. Of the </p>

<p>more than 30% frequency clones in array CGH results, those </p>

<p>considered to have vascular related aberrations in the chromo-</p>

<p>some were selected for real-time PCR. Frequently, gains of </p>

<p>chromosomal DNA at COL6A2 were detected by CGH in pa-</p>

<p>tients with ADs. The collagen, type VI, alpha-2 (COL6A2) </p>

<p>gene encodes 1 of the 3 subunits that comprise the full colla-</p>

<p>gen VI protein. Collagen VI is expressed in developing hu-</p>

<p>man hearts [24]. The finding that collagen VI is a structural </p>

<p>protein supports that collagen VI is a candidate gene involved </p>

<p>in the development of congenital heart disease in Down </p>

<p>syndrome. The most frequent locus alteration was a gain at </p>

<p>the 15q26.3 region containing the PCSK6 gene. PCSK6 </p>

<p>(PACE4) is expressed at high levels in the anterior pituitary, </p>

<p>central nervous system, the developing olfactory bulb, heart, </p>

<p>and liver [25]. Moreover, SDHA is Complex II of the mi-</p>

<p>tochondrial respiratory chain, also known as succinate de-</p>

<p>hydrogenase or succinate ubiquinone oxidoreductase, and it </p>

<p>consists of four nuclear-encoded polypeptides. The specific </p>

<p>function of this gene has not yet been determined. Bourgeron </p>

<p>et al. identified a homozygous mutation in the SDHA gene in </p>

<p>two siblings with a mitochondrial complex II deficiency pre-</p>

<p>senting as Leigh's syndrome. Their study results demonstrated </p>

<p>that the flavoprotein subunit gene is duplicated in the human </p>

<p>genome and located on chromosome 5p15 [26]. Chromosome </p>

<p>arm 22q, which includes the COMT and DGCR14 genes, was </p>

<p>frequently under-represented. Chromosome 22q11.21 includes </p>

<p>the catechol O-methyltransferase (COMT) gene, and its dele-</p>

<p>tion syndrome is a common microdeletion syndrome asso-</p>

<p>ciated with a markedly elevated risk of several diseases [27]. </p>

<p>In addition to this region, DiGeorge syndrome critical region </p>

<p>gene 14 (DGCR14) has been associated with an elevated risk </p>

<p>of several diseases. A group of developmental disorders, in-</p>

<p>cluding DiGeorge syndrome (DGS), velocardiofacial syn-</p>

<p>drome (VCFS), conotruncal anomaly face syndrome, and </p>

<p>some familial or sporadic conotruncal cardiac defects have </p>

<p>been associated with microdeletion of 22q11.2 [28]. The four </p>

<p>altered regions (5p15.33, 15q26.3, 21q22.3 and 22q11.21) that </p>

<p>showed frequent genomic alteration were confirmed by re-</p>

<p>al-time PCR. 
In summary, array based CGH analysis of 18 patients with </p>

<p>AD showed that DNA copy number alterations are common </p>

<p>in AD. Real-time PCR confirmed that array CGH properly </p>

<p>detected gains in AD related genes. Aortic dissection is be-</p>

<p>lieved to develop through a chronic degeneration of the aortic </p>

<p>wall associated with aging, atherosclerosis, or hypertension. </p>

<p>But its etiology remains unresolved [20]. In this study, we </p>

<p>were able to delineate discrete regions of DNA copy number </p>

<p>alterations in several regions of the chromosomes that are </p>

<p>likely to harbor some relevant genes. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>These data support the utility of array CGH for the identi-</p>

<p>fication of genomic alterations in AD. Although our results </p>

<p>suggest a new aspect of genomic alteration in patients with </p>

<p>ADs, our study was limited by a small sample number (n= </p>

<p>18) and the fact that it only included individuals of Korean </p>

<p>descent. Therefore, further studies should be carried out using </p>

<p>CGH techniques to validate our results. Information on chro-</p>

<p>mosomal variability can be generated by comparing the re-</p>

<p>sults of array CGH with information from the Human </p>

<p>Structural Variation Database and increasing patient numbers. 
This study is the first to use array CGH to search for can-</p>

<p>didate regions in Korean aortic dissection patients, these find-</p>

<p>ings might contribute to the understanding of important chro-</p>

<p>mosomal regions and the identification of candidate genes, </p>

<p>and may be used to investigate the pathogenesis of aortic </p>

<p>dissections. </p>



<p>Jong Hui Suh, et al </p>

<p>− 130 − </p>



</text></tei>