<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3198080" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs type="software">ImageJ</rs><rs type="software">Lucia</rs><rs id="software-2" type="software">Prism</rs><rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">V4.02</rs><rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA</rs>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Using two established preclinical models for the early and 
late stages of diabetic retinopathy, we show that a novel 
EPO-derived peptide has a significant protective effect. 
When administered for 1 month after 6 previous months 
of diabetes, pHBSP can prevent several important lesions 
of diabetic retinopathy. These include GFAP upregulation </p>

<p>in the Müller glia, neuronal death, retinal inflammatory 
responses, and capillary degeneration. The current investi-
gation builds on a previous study using a full-length pHBSP, 
which demonstrates prevention of BRB dysfunction during 
diabetes (22), and adds compelling evidence that elements 
of EPO-R signaling can be harnessed for treating diabetic 
retinopathy. </p>

<p>FIG. 3. pHBSP protects against DNA damage in diabetic retina. pHBSP treatment prevents diabetes-induced ganglion cell death. Cntl, control; Sc, 
scrambled pHBSP; and Db, diabetic. A: Cell count of terminal deoxynucleotidyl TUNEL-positive cells in the GCL was assessed by counting the 
number of fluorescent TUNEL-positive cells in the GCL divided by total number of cells present in the GCL. TUNEL of pHBSP-treated rats showed 
a significant increase in the percentage of cells with DNA strand breaks in the GCL of diabetic rats compared with control (*P &lt; 0.05; ***P &lt; 0.001). 
Treatment with pHBSP decreased TUNEL positivity by 49% when compared with diabetic rat with scrambled pHBSP (++P &lt; 0.01). Counts were 
assessed by image analysis in multiple sections. Images were taken at three separate points (three fields at 300 mm 2 each) on the central retina at 
340 magnification and presented as the average nuclei in the GCL. B: Cell count of TUNEL-positive cells in the entire retina was assessed by counting 
the number of fluorescent TUNEL-positive cells divided by total number of cells present. The diabetic retina treated with the scrambled peptide 
displayed TUNEL-positive cells. This was reduced to control levels of ;10% with the pHBSP peptide (**P &lt; 0.01). Data are mean 6 SEM; n = 6 per 
group. Counts were assessed by image analysis in multiple sections. Images were taken at three separate points (three fields at 300 mm 2 each) on the 
central retina at 340 magnification and presented as the average nuclei in the GCL. pHBSP treatment prevents diabetes-induced ganglion cell death 
because there are more TUNEL-positive cells in the diabetic with scrambled pHBSP-treated animals relative to the control and scrambled pHBSP in 
the GCL and in the entire retina. Retinal nuclei were also counterstained with PI. This is evident in the images showing TUNEL positivity in control 
and Sc (C), control and pHBSP (D), diabetic and Sc (E), and diabetic and pHBSP (F). (A high-quality digital representation of this figure is available 
in the online issue.) </p>

<p>preretinal neovascularization (15). Therefore, a major find-
ing of the current study is that pHBSP not only prevents 
early stage pathology but also fails to evoke preretinal 
neovascularization and, thus, carries considerably less risk 
than recombinant EPO if used in diabetic patients. 
Proinflammatory pathways contribute to neuroglial and 
microvascular lesions during diabetic retinopathy, as evi-
denced by the upregulation of proinflammatory cytokines 
from the Müller glia (35) and microglia (36), which show 
strong associative links to capillary degeneration (37). 
Microglia in particular are the resident immune cells of the 
retina, and their activation, combined with infiltration of 
circulating monocytes into the neuropile, could play an 
important regulatory role in diabetic retinopathy through 
cytokine expression and related cell responses (38). It 
is interesting that pHBSP reduced constitutive expression 
levels of some cytokines in normal retina, for example, 
IL-1b. The reason for this is unclear but may be related to 
slightly elevated levels in older rats and the potential for 
pHBSP to interfere with proinflammatory signaling. In brain 
ischemia, microglial responses have been shown to be 
suppressed by EPO-related therapy (39), and there may be 
similar dampening of microglial activation, and associated 
proinflammatory cytokine expression is suppressed by 
pHBSP in diabetic retinopathy. 
Protection against neuroglial apoptosis and associated 
inflammatory cascades is an established benefit of EPO </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Cytokine expression in the diabetic retina is regulated by pHBSP A: IL-10 was decreased in the diabetic rat with scrambled pHBSP relative 
to the control with scrambled pHBSP (***P &lt; 0.001). The level of IL-10, the anti-inflammatory cytokine, was elevated again with pHBSP in the 
diabetic rat when compared with the scrambled pHBSP (+P &lt; 0.05). B: TNF-a was increased in the diabetic rat, which received 10 mg/kg of 
scrambled pHBSP, relative to the control, which received the scrambled pHBSP (***P &lt; 0.001). This elevated level in the diabetic rat was sig-
nificantly decreased with the active pHBSP (+++P &lt; 0.001). C: IL-6 was increased in the diabetic rat, which received 10 mg/kg of scrambled pHBSP, 
relative to the control, which received the scrambled pHBSP (***P &lt; 0.001). This elevated level in the diabetic rat was significantly decreased with 
the active pHBSP (+++P &lt; 0.001). D: STZ-induced diabetes caused a reduction in IL-1b levels when compared with control tissue treated with 
scrambled peptide (***P &lt; 0.001). Treatment with pHBSP caused a reduction in IL-1b levels both in nondiabetic tissue and diabetic tissue (***P &lt; 
0.001; +++P &lt; 0.001). The number of animals in each group was six. Cntl, control; Sc, scrambled pHBSP; and Db, diabetic. </p>

<p>C.M. MCVICAR AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 </p>

<p>
treatment to damaged tissues such as ischemic brain. There 
are likely to be comparable benefits for the diabetic retina 
since progressive retinal neuronal and Müller cell dys-
function, DNA damage, and cell death have been pre-
viously demonstrated (40), although in rats this may take 
.4 months to become evident (25). In the current study, 
the TUNEL-positive cells in the retina are likely to repre-
sent DNA damage in a range of neurons and glia but not 
necessarily apoptotic death. This argument is strengthened 
by the caspase-3 data in this study. The 8-OHdG staining 
observed in the ONL of the diabetic retina suggests that 
there is extensive DNA damage, which is also indicated 
by TUNEL. While EPO can inhibit neural cell apoptosis 
(14), it can also upregulate enzymes that scavenge oxygen 
radicals during brain ischemia (41) and protect against 
DNA damage (42). Wang et al. (18) have recently reported </p>

<p>EPO-mediated protection against oxidative damage in the 
diabetic retina long before ischemia is present, and this 
may account for the observed reduction in DNA damage 
evoked by pHBSP treatment. In the current study, pHBSP 
(1 mg/kg) reduced retinal ischemia in the murine model, 
although the response was more apparent at the lower 
concentration. This may reflect commonly observed cyto-
kine responses that are likely related to receptor dynamics 
and are often characterized by a U-shaped dose response 
curve (hormesis). 
Suppression of DNA damage, apoptosis, inflammation, 
and oxidative stress-related pathways undoubtedly affect 
capillary degeneration during diabetic retinopathy (43). 
While pHBSP treatment could significantly modulate all 
these pathways, it is perhaps surprising that 1 month of 
treatment with pHBSP after 6 previous months of diabetes </p>

<p>FIG. 6. pHBSP prevents retinal capillary degeneration during diabetes. The retinal vasculature was visualized in flat mounts using concomitant 
labeling of endothelium (isolectin) and basement membrane (collagen IV). Acellular capillaries can be visualized by continuance of collagen IV 
positivity but loss of endothelium. Cntl, control; Sc, scrambled pHBSP; and Db, diabetic. A: Graph showing the number of acellular capillaries in 
retina in the peripheral and central retina. Diabetic rats with scrambled pHBSP displayed more acellular capillaries than control rats, which re-
ceived the scrambled pHBSP (*P &lt; 0.05). The pHBSP peptide significantly reduced the number of the acellular capillaries to normal levels in the 
inner retina (+P &lt; 0.05). Data are mean 6 SEM; n = 6 per group. B and C: Images showing acellular capillaries (arrows) in the diabetic animals that 
received the scrambled peptide. Acellular capillaries are observed when vessels are collagen IV positive (red) and negative for lectin (green). 
There are more acellular vessel profiles present in the diabetic retina that received the scramble peptide relative to the diabetic animals that 
received the pHBSP peptide. Sc'pHBSP, scrambled pHBSP. (A high-quality digital representation of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>EPO PEPTIDE PROTECTS RETINA DURING DIABETES </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>could have such a marked effect on reversal of acellular 
vessels. Death of retinal capillary component cells during 
diabetes is not necessarily linear, and the progressive 
nature of many pathogenic pathways indicates that endo-
theliopathy and pericyte death are the result of accumu-
lative abnormalities in the early stages of diabetes. Indeed, 
acellular capillaries are not usually evident until at least 
4-5 months of hyperglycemia (44). Although not evaluated 
in the current investigation, it should also be considered 
that activation of the EPO-Rs could mobilize vasoreparative 
endothelial progenitor cells (EPCs) into the circulating 
blood to target areas of hypoxia. The mechanism(s) by 
which EPCs mobilize and home to areas of ischemia are 
complex but involve stimulatory factors such as EPO (45) 
and VEGF (46). Diabetes causes EPC dysfunction, and this </p>

<p>is associated with impaired vascular repair in diabetic 
retinopathy (47); it is possible that systemic delivery of 
pHBSP in diabetic rats could have enhanced EPC mobi-
lization and thereby improved reparative function in a 
comparable manner to that described for EPO (48). This 
requires further study. 
In summary, the current study indicates that the TPR 
pathway could play a key role in preventing early stage 
diabetic retinopathy and thereby progression to the sight-
threatening late stages. The ability to use a therapeutic 
approach that harnesses all the tissue-protective and anti-
inflammatory benefits of EPO without risking the poten-
tially damaging collateral effects would be a major advance 
for neurovascular degenerative diseases such as diabetic 
retinopathy. </p>

<p>FIG. 7. pHBSP decreases ischemia at 1 mg/kg and exacerbates preretinal neovascularization in OIR. The murine retinal vasculature was assessed in 
flat mounts after OIR using isolectin labeling and confocal microscopy. A: Retinal ischemia: pHBSP at 1 mg/kg decreases the ischemic region (***P &lt; 
0.001), while the higher doses of 10 and 30 mg/kg have no effect on ischemia. B: Retinal neovascularization: upon quantification of preretinal 
vessels, pHBSP had no significant effect on neovascularization at any of the doses tested (1, 10, and 30 mg/kg) when compared with the scrambled 
peptide or PBS control. Data are mean 6 SEM; n = 6 per group. PBS, PBS control; Sc, scrambled pHBSP. C and D: Retinal flat mounts showing 
hyperfluorescent preretinal neovascularization in PBS-treated (C) and 1 mg/kg of pHBSP-treated (D) OIR mice (arrow). (A high-quality color 
representation of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>C.M. MCVICAR AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 </p>

<p>
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This research was funded by Fight for Sight (Grant number 
1688), the Juvenile Diabetes Research Foundation (JDRF), 
and the Department of Education and Learning, Northern 
Ireland. A.W.S. holds a Royal Society Wolfson Foundation 
Merit Award. M.B. and A.C. are employed by Araim 
Pharmaceuticals. No other potential conflicts of interest 
relevant to this article were reported. 
C.M.M. designed the experiments, researched data, and 
wrote the manuscript. R.H. designed the experiments and 
researched data. L.M.C. researched data. T.A.G. was in-
volved in the design of the experiments and contributed to 
the manuscript. M.B. designed the peptide for the study 
and was involved in the design of the experiments. A.C. 
designed the peptide for the study and contributed to the 
manuscript. A.W.S. led the project, obtained funding, 
designed the experiments, and wrote the manuscript. </p>



<p>EPO PEPTIDE PROTECTS RETINA DURING DIABETES </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>



<p>C.M. MCVICAR AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>