<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3212666" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: Our purpose was to conduct a screening test for urethritis or cervicitis as a 
sexually transmitted disease (STD) by using multiplex polymerase chain reaction 
(PCR) and to determine the prevalence of Chlamydia trachomatis, Neisseria gonor-
rhoeae, Mycoplasma genitalium, Ureaplasma urealyticum, Mycoplasma hominis, and 
Trichomonas vaginalis in asymptomatic people. 
Materials and Methods: From July 2010 to December 2010, 709 persons who came to 
the hospital for a general checkup were tested. Multiplex PCR assays were done with 
first voided urine samples or endocervical swabs by use of the Seeplex 
Ⓡ STD6 ACE 
Detection kit. 
Results: The mean age in this study was 45.4±8.1 years. Among the 709 persons, 229 
(32.3%) had a positive result for at least one microorganism, 48 (6.8%) had two different 
species, 6 (0.8%) had three different species, and 1 person had four different species. 
The overall prevalence of asymptomatic STDs such as urethritis or cervicitis was 7.1% 
(50/709). The prevalence rates of Chlamydia trachomatis, Neisseria gonorrhoeae, 
Mycoplasma genitalium, Ureaplasma urealyticum, Mycoplasma hominis, and 
Trichomonas vaginalis infection in asymptomatic persons were 5.6% (40/709), 0.4% 
(3/709), 0.3% (2/709), 22.1% (157/709), 11.6% (82/709), and 1.1% (8/709), respectively. 
Conclusions: With only a single sample, we could identify the prevalence rates of six 
microorganisms and the overall proportion of urethritis or cervicitis in asymptomatic 
people. This proportion cannot be neglected; therefore, screening tests for sexually 
transmitted diseases such as urethritis or cervicitis should be recommended to asymp-
tomatic people. </p>

<p>Chlamydia trachomatis, Neisseria gonorrhoeae, Myco-
plasma genitalium, and Trichomonas vaginalis are known 
pathogens in sexually transmitted infection (STI). Howev-
er, most of those species present atypical symptoms and 
some patients have no symptoms [1-3]. Therefore, physi-
cians sometimes have difficulty in making a differential </p>

<p>diagnosis. Moreover, except for Chlamydia trachomatis 
and Mycoplasma genitalium, the treatment regimens be-
tween the species differ. 
In addition, routine bacterial culture may give negatives 
result for commercial sexual workers or asymptomatic peo-
ple who recently experienced unprotected sexual contact 
and have acquired an STI [1-3]. Thus, there are neglected 
asymptomatic patients in the community who can serve as </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2011;52:703-708 </p>



<p>Kim et al </p>

<p>a reservoir of the STI [1-4]. 
There are limited studies about Ureaplasma ure-
alyticum and Mycoplasma hominis in asymptomatic 
people. Generally, Ureaplasma urealyticum is not known 
as a clinical pathogen but it can be a cause of urethritis, es-
pecially in patients resistant to routine treatment [5]. 
Mycoplasma hominis also does not play a great role in the 
pathogenesis of urethritis, but it can be a heavy pathogen 
in immunocompromised patients [6]. Recently, many re-
ports have revealed that microorganisms such as Urea-
plasma urealyticum and Mycoplasma hominis can contrib-
ute not only to lower genitourinary infection but also to in-
fertility [7]. 
Therefore, identification of the incidence of asympto-
matic STI such as urethritis or cervicitis and determi-
nation of the prevalence of these 6 species in asymptomatic 
people is very important. Accordingly, we conducted a 
screening test for STI by using multiplex polymerase chain 
reaction (PCR) in asymptomatic people. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>This study was a point prevalence study. The institutional 
review board of The Catholic University of Korea, College 
of Medicine, approved the study protocol, and all patients 
provided written informed consent to participate in the 
study (IRB no: SC10SNSI0091). </p>

<p>1. Sample collection 
From July 2010 to December 2010, 802 persons who came 
to the hospital for a general checkup participated volun-
tarily and a brief questionnaire was obtained. Sexually ac-
tive, asymptomatic people aged between 20 and 60 years 
were enrolled. We defined 'sexually active' as having had 
sexual intercourse in the preceding 3 months. People who 
had a recently cured genitourinary infectious disease with-
in 3 months were excluded. People with genitourinary 
symptoms such as urethral or cervical discharge, dysuria, 
or itching in the genital area were also excluded. Finally, 
709 persons were assigned to be tested. Among these, 430 
were men and 279 were women. In men, first-voided urine 
specimens were collected in sterile 50 ml screw-cap plastic 
bottles. In women, specimens were obtained via endocer-
vical swabs by one gynecologist. </p>

<p>2. Pretreatment of clinical specimens and DNA extraction 
The specimens from the 709 men and women were equili-
brated to room temperature and centrifuged at 5000xg for 
15 minutes. The supernatant was discarded, and the pellet 
was resuspended in 1 ml 1xPBS before DNA extraction. 
Genomic DNA was extracted from the pretreated speci-
mens (swab or urine) by using the QIAamp 
Ⓡ DNA mini kit 
(Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) according to the manufactur-
er's instructions. </p>

<p>3. Multiplex polymerase chain reaction assay 
PCR amplification was performed with the Seeplex 
Ⓡ STD6 </p>

<p>ACE detection kit (Seegene, Seoul, Korea) according to the 
manufacturer's instructions. The kit contains sets of pri-
mers that were specifically designed from highly conserved 
regions of genetic sequences for the 6 organisms (Chlamy-
dia trachomatis, Neisseria gonorrhoeae, Mycoplasma geni-
talium, Ureaplasma urealyticum, Mycoplasma hominis, 
and Trichomonas vaginalis) by use of Seegene DPO tech-
nology [8]. An internal control was included in the PCR mix 
to detect the presence of PCR inhibitors. For the negative 
control, sterile deionized water was used as the PCR tem-
plate instead of nucleic acid. The positive control contained 
in the kit was assayed to check the integrity of the primers 
used in the PCR assay. Amplified fragments were sepa-
rated by use of the LabChip 
Ⓡ DX Seeplex 
Ⓡ Assay system 
(Caliper, Hopkinton, MA, USA). </p>

<p>4. LabChip 
Ⓡ DX Seeplex 
Ⓡ assay system 
Amplified PCR products were separated and detected by 
automated gel electrophoresis with the LabChip 
Ⓡ DX 
Seeplex 
Ⓡ assay system (Caliper, Hopkinton, MA, USA). 
The PCR products from each sample (20 μl) were trans-
ferred to 96-well plates and placed in the LabChip 
Ⓡ DX 
instrument. The samples were loaded automatically on the 
Seeplex 
Ⓡ Chip and detected sequentially according to the 
sample order. Analysis was performed with designated 
software (<rs type="software">Seegene viewer</rs>) that presents each of the sam-
ples and identifies the fragments that yield a positive read-
out for the bands of interest in the presented results. A tabu-
lated matching matrix provides a simple readout, identify-
ing matching bands to the type of STI pathogens. A text file 
is automatically generated and saved for each tape. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The mean age in this study was 45.4±8.1 years. Among the 
709 persons, 229 (32.3%) had at least one microorganism 
in his or her genitourinary tract. The prevalences of 
Chlamydia trachomatis, Neisseria gonorrhoeae, Myco-
plasma genitalium, Ureaplasma urealyticum, Mycoplas-
ma hominis, and Trichomonas vaginalis in asymptomatic 
people were 5.6% (40/709), 0.4% (3/709), 0.3% (2/709), 
22.1% (157/709), 11.6% (82/709), and 1.1% (8/709) re-
spectively (Table 1). Among all persons, 50 (7.1%) had 
pathogens of STI in their urinary tract (Table 2). Of these 
patients, the number of patients with a single pathogen 
was 47 (6.6%), for which the number with isolated 
Chlamydia trachomatis, Neisseria gonorrhoeae, Myco-
plasma genitalium, or Trichomonas vaginalis was 37, 1, 1, 
and 8, respectively. Three double-infections, i.e., samples 
containing 2 or more pathogens, were identified, and each 
sample had Chlamydia trachomatis. When Trichomonas 
vaginalis was identified, it was either isolated alone or 
co-infected with Mycoplasma hominis only and no other 
species. The total number of people who had at least two 
microorganisms in their genitourinary tract was 55 (7.5%). 
Among these 55 persons, 48 (6.8%) had two different spe-
cies whether they were pathogens or not, 6 (0.8%) persons </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2011;52:703-708 </p>

<p>The Prevalnece and Clinical Significance of Urethritis and Cervicitis in Asymptomatic People </p>



<p>TABLE 1. Species isolated from an asymptomatic general popula-
tion </p>

<p>Total 
Men 
Women 
Species in 709 samples 
no. 
(430) 
(279) </p>

<p>Free of microorganisms 
480 (67.7) 282 (65.6) 198 (71.0) 
C. trachomatis </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>40 (5.6) 
29 (6.7) 
11 (3.9) 
N. gonorrhoeae </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>3 (0.4) 
2 (0.5) 
1 (0.4) 
M. genitalium </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2 (0.3) 
1 (0.2) 
1 (0.4) 
U. urealyticum </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>157 (22.1) 112 (26.0) 
45 (16.1) 
M. hominis </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>82 (11.6) 
39 (9.1) 
43 (15.4) 
T. vaginalis </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>8 (1.1) 
1 (0.2) 
7 (1.0) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%), </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>: regardless of the existence 
of other species </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Samples containing clinical pathogens </p>

<p>Combinations with C. trachomatis 
Total no. (40) 
Men (29) 
Women (11) </p>

<p>C. trachomatis only 
22 (55.0) 
18 (62.1) 
4 (36.4) 
C. trachomatis+U. urealyticum </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>7 (17.5) 
4 (13.8) 
3 (27.3) 
C. trachomatis+M. hominis </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2 (5.0) 
0 
2 (18.2) 
C. trachomatis+U. urealyticum+M. hominis </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>6 (15.0) 
4 (13.8) 
2 (18.2) 
C. trachomatis </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>37 (92.5) 
26 (90.0) 
11 (100) 
C. trachomatis+N. gonorrhoeae </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2 (5.0) 
2 (6.9) 
0 
C. trachomatis+M. genitalium+U. urealyticum+M. hominis 
1 (2.5) 
1 (3.4) 
0 
C. trachomatis+U. urealyticum </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>14 (35.0) 
9 (31.0) 
5 (45.5) 
C. trachomatis+M. hominis </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>9 (22.5) 
5 (17.2) 
4 (36.4) </p>

<p>Combinations with N. gonorrhoeae 
Total no. (3) 
Men (2) 
Women (1) </p>

<p>N. gonorrhoeae only 
1 (33.3) 
0 
1 (100) 
N. gonorrhoeae+C. trachomatis 
2 (66.7) 
2 (100) 
0 </p>

<p>Combinations with M. genitalium 
Total no. (2) 
Men (1) 
Women (1) </p>

<p>M. genitalium+U. Urealyticum+M. hominis 
1 (50.0) 
0 
1 (100) 
M. genitalium+C. trachomatis+U. Urealyticum+M. hominis 
1 (50.0) 
1 (100) 
0 </p>

<p>Combinations with T. vaginalis 
Total no. (8) 
Men (1) 
Women (7) </p>

<p>T. vaginalis only 
6 (75.0) 
0 
6 (85.7) 
T. vaginalis+M. hominis </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2 (25.0) 
1 (100) 
1 (14.3) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%), C. trachomatis: Chlamydia trachomatis, U. urealyticum: Ureaplasma urealyticum, M. hominis: 
Mycoplasma hominis, N. gonorrhoeae: Neisseria gonorrhoeae, M. genitalium: Mycoplasma genitalium, T. vaginalis: Trichomonas vagi-
nalis, </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>: samples not containing other species, </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>: samples not containing other pathogens, regardless of the existence of commensal micro-
organisms, </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>: regardless of the existence of other species </p>

<p>had three different species, and 1 patient had four different 
species. 
The prevalences of Ureaplasma urealyticum and Myco-
plasma hominis were 22.1% and 11.6%, respectively. In 
people who were infected with Chlamydia trachomatis, the 
prevalences of Ureaplasma urealyticum (35.0%) and 
Mycoplasma hominis (22.5%) were higher than in those not 
infected with Chlamydia trachomatis (Table 1, 2). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Chlamydia trachomatis infection is the most prevalent </p>

<p>sexually transmitted bacterial infection among women 
and men worldwide. Chlamydia trachomatis is usually de-
scribed as an obligate intracellular pathogen and accounts 
for 30% to 40% of the etiopathogenesis of urethritis [9]. 
However, about half of infected subjects are asymptomatic. 
Thus, there are many silent infections in the community. 
Mason et al showed that the prevalence of Chlamydia tra-
chomatis in asymptomatic men was 4% (14/349) [10]. 
Takahashi et al reported that Chlamydia trachomatis was 
detected in 6% of samples from healthy people [11]. 
Similarly, in our study, Chlamydia trachomatis was ob-
served in 40 persons (5.6%). Unfortunately, it is usually not 
detected by routine microbiological diagnosis [1,12]. Thus, 
most asymptomatic patients are neglected unless they vis-
it the clinic to be evaluated for STI by chance or face compli-
cations such as pelvic inflammatory disease. 
Neisseria are fastidious Gram-negative cocci that re-
quire nutrient supplementation to grow in laboratory 
cultures. Although gonorrhea can be diagnosed by in-
spection of the yellowish discharge from the urethra, many 
patients infected with Neisseria gonorrhoeae have no 
discharge. Furthermore, it is known that 10% of infected 
males and 50% of infected females are asymptomatic. Hein 
et al studied 2672 sexually active adolescents and reported 
that prevalence rates of asymptomatic gonorrhea were 
1.9% among boys and 7.0% among female adolescents [13]. 
Regardless of age group, a surveillance study reported 
prevalence rates of gonorrhea in healthy people of 0.06% </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2011;52:703-708 </p>



<p>Kim et al </p>

<p>to 0.18% [14]. In our study, the prevalence in asymptomatic 
people was 0.4%, and the result was easily obtained by PCR 
test with a urine or endocervical swab sample. 
Mycoplasma genitalium was first isolated in 1981 from 
two men with nongonococcal urethritis (NGU) [15]. 
Nowadays, Mycoplasma genitalium is known as a causa-
tive pathogen of NGU. Results from a meta-analysis of 19 
studies on patients with NGU showed that Mycoplasma 
genitalium was found in 21% compared with 7% of patients 
without NGU [16]. Ross et al reported a detection rate of 
0.6% for Mycoplasma genitalium in asymptomatic British 
persons [17]. In Japan, the detection rate of this organism 
was 1% [11]. Our study showed a prevalence of this myco-
plasma of 0.3% in asymptomatic people. Mycoplasma geni-
talium is difficult to identify by routine culture. Currently, 
nucleic acid amplification tests (NAATs) are usually rec-
ommended to detect this pathogen [1]. Wikström and 
Jensen reported that Mycoplasma genitalium is a common 
cause of persistent or recurrent urethritis among men 
treated with doxycycline, and erythromycin appears to be 
less efficient than azithromycin in eradicating the in-
fection [18]. Therefore, when physicians encounter pa-
tients who complain of continuous symptoms of urethritis, 
they should consider drug-refractory urethritis such as 
that caused by Mycoplasma genitalium. 
Trichomonas vaginalis is an anaerobic flagellated 
protozoan. It is another pathogen of STI of the urogenital 
tract, and men with this infection rarely exhibit symptoms 
[19]. In women, greenish-yellow frothy vaginal discharge 
and itching can develop. Trichomoniasis is treated and 
cured with metronidazole or tinidazole, which should be 
prescribed to any sexual partners as well because they may 
be asymptomatic carriers. Sutton et al reported that the 
prevalence of Trichomonas vaginalis in reproductive-aged 
women was 3.1% [20]. In our study, the total prevalence 
rate was 1.1% in asymptomatic people, and prevalence 
rates in asymptomatic men and women were 0.2% and 
2.5%, respectively. 
Screening for these pathogens is important not only to 
identify infected symptomatic individuals for the diag-
nosis and management of their infections but also to identi-
fy asymptomatic individuals who serve as reservoirs for in-
fection [1-4]. In our study, there were 50 (7.1%) infected peo-
ple among 709 asymptomatic people; thus, this proportion 
should not be neglected. Among the 50 infected patients, 
37 with Chlamydia trachomatis, 1 with Neisseria gonor-
rhoeae, 1 with Mycoplasma genitalium, 8 with Trichomo-
nas vaginalis, 2 with Chlamydia trachomatis with 
Neisseria gonorrhoeae, and 1 with Chlamydia trachomatis 
with Mycoplasma genitalium were confirmed. Thus, re-
gardless of Chlamydia trachomatis, 13 patients should be 
considered as candidates for antimicrobial treatment. 
Moreover, there were 3 double-infections among the 709 
asymptomatic people. These facts suggest the possibility 
of prescribing the wrong medicines if practitioners give 
symptomatic patients some regimens empirically. There-
fore, the need to detect multiple species at once should be </p>

<p>raised. In this sense, use of the multiplex PCR assay to 
screen asymptomatic people may be important because the 
treatment regimen could be optimized for people with pos-
itive results, especially for those with multiple organisms. 
This concept can be also applied to symptomatic patients. 
Ureaplasma urealyticum has been recognized as a patho-
gen for NGU since the 1950s [21]. However, Ureaplasma 
urealyticum is frequently isolated from the urethra of 
healthy men, and some studies have reported that there is 
no significant difference in its prevalence between men 
with NGU and men without NGU [22]. Nevertheless, there 
are some reports that Ureaplasma urealyticum serves as 
a cause of persistent NGU [23,24]. For that reason, 
Ureaplasma urealyticum is sometimes recognized as a 
pathogen and sometimes as a commensal organism. 
Therefore, Ureaplasma infection must be considered in pa-
tients with treatment failure for NGU or patients with mul-
tiple sexual partners. If no species except Ureaplasma are 
detected, symptoms and leukocyte numbers in first voided 
urine samples are helpful for clarifying the diagnosis of 
Ureaplasma infection [25]. 
Mycoplasma hominis is frequently identified from the 
genitourinary tract. In general, it is known as a commensal 
species but it can work as a pathogen in special conditions 
such as in an immunocompromised state [6]. Generally, the 
rate of colonization of Mycoplasma hominis in the urogen-
ital tract was reported to be between 4% and 13% in men 
and between 21% an 54% in women [26]. Our study showed 
that the incidence of this species was 9.1% in men and 
15.4% in women. 
In our study, the incidences of Ureaplasma urealyticum 
and Mycoplasma hominis were 22.1% and 11.6%. Never-
theless, those incidences were increased up to 35.0% and 
22.5% when the samples had Chlamydia trachomatis. The 
reason for this increase with chlamydial infection is not 
clear, and a limitation of our study is that we did not include 
people who had symptoms. Therefore, comparison of the 
prevalence of these species in symptomatic urethritis pa-
tients is necessary. 
As described previously, most pathogens causing STI as 
well as commensal microorganisms are difficult to culti-
vate by routine microbiological diagnosis. However, 
NAATs, such as PCR, are useful for the identification of mi-
croorganisms that are difficult to cultivate and for those 
that grow slowly [25]. In another recent study in Korea, the 
multiplex PCR kit (Seegene Inc., Seoul, Korea) was used 
to detect causative microorganisms of STI in patients with 
chronic prostatitis and vaginitis [27]. In multiplex PCR, 
more than one target sequence can be amplified by includ-
ing more than one pair of primers in the reaction. Multiplex 
PCR has the potential to produce considerable savings of 
time and effort within the laboratory without compromis-
ing test utility. Furthermore, when the clinical sample 
amount is limited, multiplexing allows more targets to be 
analyzed by using a single aliquot of sample material [28]. 
Although there are some worries that multiplex PCR in the 
clinical setting may have difficulties such as poor sensi-</p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2011;52:703-708 </p>

<p>The Prevalnece and Clinical Significance of Urethritis and Cervicitis in Asymptomatic People </p>



<p>tivity or specificity, false-negative results, and nonspecific 
interactions, Horii et al showed that the multiplex PCR as-
say had an overall sensitivity of 96% and specificity of 100% 
compared with uniplex PCR assays. Furthermore, there 
was no cross-reaction with other microorganisms [29]. 
The multiplex PCR assay has recently made it con-
venient for clinicians to test for causative organisms simul-
taneously from many clinical fields [30]. Similarly, we suc-
ceeded in easily generating results by use of multiplex PCR 
with only a single sample per person. 
Asymptomatic individuals play a role as reservoirs for 
STI. In our study, there were 50 (7.1%) infected people 
among 709 asymptomatic people; therefore, this pro-
portion should not be neglected. An STI screening test 
should be considered as a part of a general checkup, espe-
cially in high-risk groups, e.g., commercial sexual workers, 
people who have multiple sexual partners, and im-
munocompromised persons [1-3,6,25]. By use of multiplex 
PCR, physicians can easily identify many microorganisms 
at once, and treating asymptomatic persons contributes to 
the prevention of STI in the community. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>The prevalences of Chlamydia trachomatis, Neisseria gon-
orrhoeae, Mycoplasma genitalium, Ureaplasma ure-
alyticum, Mycoplasma hominis, and Trichomonas vagi-
nalis in asymptomatic people were 5.6%, 0.4%, 0.3%, 
22.1%, 11.6%, and 1.1%, respectively. We hope that these 
results will be used as baseline data for future studies. 
In our study, about 32.3% of asymptomatic people had 
at least one microorganism, and excluding Ureaplasma 
urealyticum and Mycoplasma hominis from the count, the 
prevalence rate of silent STI was 7.1% with multiplex PCR. 
These asymptomatic people would be a source of STI. 
Therefore, screening for STI should be considered as a part 
of a general checkup, especially in high-risk groups. </p>

<p>Conflicts of Interest 
The authors have nothing to disclose. </p>



<p>Korean J Urol 2011;52:703-708 </p>



<p>Kim et al </p>



</text></tei>