<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3020640" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Essential telomere 'capping' proteins act as a safeguard 
against ageing and cancer by inhibiting the DNA damage 
response (DDR) and regulating telomerase recruitment, 
thus distinguishing telomeres from double-strand breaks 
(DSBs). Uncapped telomeres and unrepaired DSBs can 
both stimulate a potent DDR, leading to cell cycle arrest 
and cell death. Using the cdc13-1 mutation to conditionally 
'uncap' telomeres in budding yeast, we show that the 
telomere capping protein Cdc13 protects telomeres from 
the activity of the helicase Pif1 and the exonuclease Exo1. 
Our data support a two-stage model for the DDR at 
uncapped telomeres; Pif1 and Exo1 resect telomeric DNA 
o5 kb from the chromosome end, stimulating weak </p>

<p>checkpoint activation; resection is extended 45 kb by 
Exo1 and full checkpoint activation occurs. Cdc13 is also 
crucial for telomerase recruitment. However, cells lacking 
Cdc13, Pif1 and Exo1, do not senesce and maintain their 
telomeres in a manner dependent upon telomerase, Ku 
and homologous recombination. Thus, attenuation of the 
DDR at uncapped telomeres can circumvent the need for 
otherwise-essential telomere capping proteins. 
Telomeres consist of double-stranded DNA (dsDNA) and 
single-stranded DNA (ssDNA), bound by dsDNA-and 
ssDNA-binding proteins (Blackburn et al, 2006; Lydall, 
2009). This nucleoprotein 'cap' has at least two functions: 
to shield the telomeric DNA from stimulating the DNA 
damage response (DDR) and to regulate elongation of </p>

<p>the telomere by telomerase. In human senescent cells, 
dysfunctional telomeres induce a sustained DDR (d'Adda di 
Fagagna et al, 2003). In both budding yeast and mice, nuclease 
activities that attack dysfunctional telomeres contribute to 
telomere-driven senescence (Maringele and Lydall, 2004; 
Schaetzlein et al, 2007). Therefore, understanding the regula-
tion of nuclease activities at dysfunctional telomeres in yeast is 
likely to be informative about similar processes occurring at 
mammalian telomeres and the human ageing process. 
dsDNA-binding proteins and accessory factors are required 
at both human telomeres (TRF1, TRF2, TIN2, TPP1, RAP1) 
and budding yeast telomeres (Rap1, Rif1, Rif2) to prevent 
DDRs (Wotton and Shore, 1997; de Lange, 2005; Celli and 
de Lange, 2005; Marcand et al, 2008; Bonetti et al, 2010; 
Vodenicharov et al, 2010). In budding yeast, telomeric ssDNA 
is bound by Cdc13 with accessory proteins Stn1 and Ten1, 
whereas in human cells, it is bound by POT1 (de Lange, 2005; 
Gao et al, 2007). Cdc13-Stn1-Ten1 forms an evolutionarily 
conserved complex (the CST complex) that has telomeric 
roles in most organisms studied so far (Miyake et al, 2009; 
Surovtseva et al, 2009). POT1 binds telomeric ssDNA and is 
connected to the dsDNA-binding proteins of the telomere cap 
by TPP1 and TIN2 (de Lange, 2009). Inactivation of POT1 or 
Cdc13 induces 'telomere uncapping' and has similar conse-
quences-initiation of a DDR and resection of the telomeric 
DNA by nuclease activities (Garvik et al, 1995; Baumann and 
Cech, 2001; Pitt and Cooper, 2010). 
The response to telomere uncapping is readily studied in 
budding yeast by inactivation of Cdc13 using the thermo-
sensitive allele cdc13-1 (Garvik et al, 1995). Following Cdc13 
inactivation, a potent DDR is initiated; telomeric DNA is 
resected by nucleases, which degrade the AC (5 
0 ) strand to 
generate extensive TG (3 
0 ) ssDNA that stimulates activation 
of the DNA damage checkpoint, in a manner analogous to 
that at DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs) (Figure 1A) (Garvik 
et al, 1995; Lydall and Weinert, 1995; Vodenicharov and 
Wellinger, 2006). There is relatively little understanding of 
the nuclease activities responsible for generating ssDNA at 
uncapped telomeres (Zubko et al, 2004). In contrast, there 
has been much recent progress identifying nuclease activities 
that function at DSBs (Gravel et al, 2008; Mimitou and 
Symington, 2008; Zhu et al, 2008). 
Exo1 is the only nuclease known to generate ssDNA at 
uncapped telomeres in budding yeast (Maringele and Lydall, 
2002). Exo1 is a 5 
0 to 3 
0 dsDNA exonuclease involved in DSB 
resection and in mismatch repair (Tsubouchi and Ogawa, 
2000; Gravel et al, 2008; Mimitou and Symington, 2008; 
Zhu et al, 2008). In the absence of Exo1, ssDNA is still 
generated following Cdc13 inactivation, demonstrating that </p>

<p>Received: 27 April 2010; accepted: 29 September 2010; published 
online: 2 November 2010 </p>

<p>*Corresponding author. Institute for Cell and Molecular Biosciences, 
Newcastle University, Newcastle upon Tyne, Tyne and Wear NE2 4HH, 
UK. Tel.: þ 44 191 222 5318; Fax: þ 44 191 222 7424; 
E-mail: d.a.lydall@ncl.ac.uk </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal (2010) 29, 4020-4034 | &amp; 2010 European Molecular Biology Organization | Some Rights Reserved 0261-4189/10 </p>

<p>www.embojournal.org </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 29 | NO 23 | 2010 </p>

<p>&amp; 2010 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>

<p>EMBO </p>

<p>THE </p>

<p>EMBO </p>

<p>JOURNAL </p>

<p>THE </p>

<p>EMBO </p>

<p>JOURNAL </p>



<p>other nuclease activities must also function at uncapped 
telomeres. The determinant(s) of this Exo1-independent 
ssDNA generation have not so far been identified, but at 
least two hypothetical nuclease activities have been proposed 
(ExoX and ExoY) (Zubko et al, 2004). 
We sought to identify additional nuclease activities func-
tioning at uncapped telomeres following inactivation of 
Cdc13. Bioinformatic analysis of genetic interactions found 
the helicase Pif1 to be a candidate for contributing to nucle-
ase activity. Consistent with this hypothesis, we found 
that Pif1 and Exo1 are required for different nuclease acti-
vities that generate ssDNA and activate the DNA damage </p>

<p>checkpoint following Cdc13 inactivation. Furthermore, deletion 
of both PIF1 and EXO1 permits yeast cells to tolerate complete 
loss of the essential telomere capping protein Cdc13. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>PIF1 and EXO1 define parallel pathways that inhibit 
growth of cdc13-1 mutants 
To identify potential nuclease(s) active in cdc13-1 mutants, we 
reasoned that genes responsible for such activities would 
interact with similar genes to those that EXO1 interacts with. 
We used the BioGRID database to create a ranked list of genes </p>

<p>Deletion increases 
telomere length </p>

<p>Deletion decreases 
telomere length </p>

<p>Deletion not known to 
affect telomere length </p>

<p>Shared genetic 
interactions </p>

<p>Deletion suppresses cdc13-1 
growth defect </p>

<p>Deletion enhances cdc13-1 
growth defect </p>

<p>Deletion not known to affect 
cdc13-1 growth defect </p>

<p>RAD50 </p>

<p>ASF1 NUP84 
SRS2 </p>

<p>ELG1 </p>

<p>POL30 </p>

<p>POL32 </p>

<p>RAD51 </p>

<p>RAD1 </p>

<p>RAD52 </p>

<p>EXO1 </p>

<p>RAD27 </p>

<p>MRC1 </p>

<p>SGS1 </p>

<p>TOF1 </p>

<p>RAD53 </p>

<p>MRE11 </p>

<p>RAD9 </p>

<p>RAD24 </p>

<p>PIF1 </p>

<p>30°C 
27°C </p>

<p>cdc13-1 
cdc13-1 
pif1Δ cdc13-1 
pif1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>exo1Δ cdc13-1 
exo1Δ cdc13-1 
pif1Δ exo1Δ cdc13-1 
pif1Δ exo1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>1108 
1195 
4874 
4875 </p>

<p>1296 
1297 
5323 
5324 </p>

<p>36°C 
23°C </p>

<p>5′ </p>

<p>5′ </p>

<p>5′ TGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGG </p>

<p>3′ ACCACCACCACCACCACCACC </p>

<p>3′ 
5′ 
GGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTG </p>

<p>Cell cycle 
arrest </p>

<p>3′ </p>

<p>3′ ACCACC 5′ </p>

<p>3′ </p>

<p>ACCACCACC 
3′ 
5′ </p>

<p>Cdc13-1 </p>

<p>Nuclease(s) </p>

<p>Exo1 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Mec1 
Rad53 
Dun1 </p>

<p>Rad9 
Chk1 
Pds1 </p>

<p>Checkpoint </p>

<p>36°C </p>

<p>23°C 
Capped 
telomeres </p>

<p>Uncapped 
telomeres </p>

<p>ssDNA </p>

<p>TGGTG </p>

<p>Figure 1 Pif1 and Exo1 inhibit growth of cdc13-1 mutants. (A) Inactivation of Cdc13 by use of the temperature-sensitive allele cdc13-1 leads to 
telomere uncapping. Exo1 and additional nuclease(s) generate ssDNA at uncapped telomeres, which is the stimulus for Mec1-dependent 
checkpoint activation and cell cycle arrest. (B) Ranked diagram of genes that share genetic interactions with EXO1 and are important in the 
context of telomeres. (Thicker lines mean more shared genetic interactions). (C) Strains of the genotypes shown were serially diluted across 
agar plates and grown at the temperatures indicated for 3 days. In this and other figures, strain numbers (DLYs) are shown adjacent. </p>

<p>Pif1 and Exo1 resect uncapped telomeres 
JM Dewar and D Lydall </p>

<p>&amp; 2010 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 29 | NO 23 | 2010 4021 </p>

<p>that had similar genetic interactions to EXO1 (Figure 1B) (Stark 
et al, 2006). Of these, 9/19 affected cdc13-1 growth or telomere 
length. Deletion of EXO1 suppresses cdc13-1 growth defects, 
so we focussed on those genes that also suppressed cdc13-1 
growth defects. By these criteria, two previously characterized 
checkpoint genes (RAD9 and RAD24) and the helicase-encod-
ing PIF1 behaved similarly to EXO1 (Figure 1B). Rad9 and 
Rad24 do indeed regulate nuclease activities at uncapped 
telomeres and are required for checkpoint activation (Garvik 
et al, 1995; Lydall and Weinert, 1995; Zubko et al, 2004). 
Pif1 has been shown to inhibit growth of cdc13-1 mutants 
(Downey et al, 2006), whereas overexpression of Pif1 has been 
shown to enhance growth defects seen in cdc13-1 mutants, but 
the contribution of Pif1 to the nuclease activity and check-
point activation in cdc13-1 mutants had not been assessed 
(Vega et al, 2007; Chang et al, 2009). 
Pif1 is a helicase with both mitochondrial and nuclear 
functions (Van Dyck et al, 1992; Schulz and Zakian, 1994). In 
the nucleus, Pif1 has been implicated in negative regulation 
of telomerase, generation of long flaps during Okazaki frag-
ment processing, unwinding of G-quadruplexes and disas-
sembly of stalled replication forks (Zhou et al, 2000; Boule 
et al, 2005; Budd et al, 2006; Chang et al, 2009; George et al, 
2009; Makovets and Blackburn, 2009; Pike et al, 2009; 
Ribeyre et al, 2009; Zhang and Durocher, 2010). To test the 
hypothesis that Pif1 contributes to a nuclease activity at 
uncapped telomeres in cdc13-1 mutants, we compared the 
effects of Pif1 and Exo1 on cell growth after Cdc13-1 inactiva-
tion. At the permissive temperature (231C), Cdc13-1 is func-
tional and efficiently caps the telomeres, permitting growth of 
cdc13-1 mutants. At the non-permissive temperature (361C), 
Cdc13-1 is completely defective and cdc13-1 mutants are 
unable to grow (Figure 1A and C). At semi-permissive 
temperatures (25-291C), moderate Cdc13-1 inactivation oc-
curs and growth of cdc13-1 mutants is inhibited (Figure 1C). 
As previously reported, cdc13-1 pif1D and cdc13-1 exo1D 
mutants are able to grow at 271C, whereas cdc13-1 mutants 
are not (Figure 1C) (Zubko et al, 2004; Downey et al, 2006). 
These effects on growth are consistent with the hypothesis 
that Pif1, like Exo1, contributes to nuclease activity at 
uncapped telomeres. 
Pif1 and Exo1 inhibit growth of cdc13-1 mutants, possibly 
by contributing to nuclease activity at uncapped telomeres. 
To test whether the two proteins worked in the same path-
way/complex or in different pathways, we examined the 
effect Pif1 on growth of cdc13-1 exo1D mutants. cdc13-1 
exo1D mutants were unable to grow at 301C, whereas 
cdc13-1 exo1D pif1D mutants were able to grow at 30 and 
361C (Figure 1C). Remarkably, at 361C, the growth of cdc13-1 
exo1D pif1D mutants was barely distinguishable from that of 
CDC13 
þ exo1D pif1D mutants (Supplementary Figure S1A). </p>

<p>We confirmed that this effect was due to the pif1D and exo1D 
mutations and not due to second site suppressors arising in 
our strains by crossing a cdc13-1 mutant able to grow at 361C, 
with a cdc13-1 strain and confirming that all cdc13-1 exo1D 
pif1D progeny could all grow at 361C (Supplementary Figure 
S1B). We conclude that Pif1 and Exo1 inhibit growth of 
cdc13-1 mutants through different pathways, and inacti-
vation of these pathways may eliminate the requirement for 
telomere capping by Cdc13. 
At DSBs, parallel nuclease activities dependent upon Exo1, 
the helicase Sgs1 and nuclease Dna2 generate extensive </p>

<p>ssDNA (Gravel et al, 2008; Mimitou and Symington, 2008; 
Zhu et al, 2008). We hypothesized that, as with Exo1, 
elimination of Sgs1 or Dna2 in cells lacking Pif1 might 
improve the growth of cdc13-1 mutants and perhaps even 
permit growth at 361C. However, we found that cdc13-1 pif1D 
dna2D mutants grew less well than cdc13-1 pif1D mutants 
(Supplementary Figure S2A). We were unable to examine the 
effect of dna2D on the growth of cdc13-1 PIF1 
þ mutants, as </p>

<p>DNA2 is an essential gene unless PIF1 is deleted (Budd et al, 
2006). We also found that cdc13-1 pif1D sgs1D mutants grew 
slightly less well than cdc13-1 pif1D mutants and that cdc13-1 
sgs1D mutants grew slightly less well than cdc13-1 mutants 
(Supplementary Figure S2B), consistent with other work 
from our laboratory (Ngo and Lydall, 2010). We conclude 
that Exo1 inhibits the growth of cdc13-1 mutants with un-
capped telomeres, whereas Sgs1 and Dna2 contribute to the 
vitality of such cells. Therefore, we chose to focus on the 
roles of Pif1 and Exo1 at uncapped telomeres. </p>

<p>Elimination of Pif1 and Exo1 permits telomere 
maintenance following inactivation of Cdc13 
Yeast cells can overcome the requirement for Cdc13 by 
altering telomere structure, as observed in rare variants, 
which can be selected for after inactivation of telomerase or 
after attenuation of nuclease/checkpoint activities at un-
capped telomeres (Larrivee and Wellinger, 2006; Zubko and 
Lydall, 2006). To test whether elimination of Pif1 and Exo1 
caused alterations in telomere structure that could explain the 
growth of cdc13-1 cells at 361C, we performed Southern blots 
to examine telomere structure, probing for Y 
0 sequences 
(Figure 2B), which are components of the majority of yeast 
telomeres (Supplementary Figure S3A and B). The Y 
0 probe 
contained G-rich sequences and weakly cross-hybridized to 
telomeres that did not contain Y 
0 sequences, so we also 
probed for TG repeat sequences to detect telomeres that 
lacked Y 
0 elements (Supplementary Figure S4). 
pif1D mutants have long telomeres (Schulz and Zakian, 
1994) and consistent with this, CDC13 
þ exo1D pif1D mutants </p>

<p>have longer telomeres than CDC13 
þ EXO1 
þ PIF1 
þ strains </p>

<p>(compare lanes 1-2, 3-4 and 7-8; Figure 2B). The telomeres 
of cdc13-1 exo1D pif1D mutants grown at 361C were longer 
than those of CDC13 
þ exo1D pif1D mutants grown at 231C </p>

<p>(compare lanes 9-10 with lanes 7-8, Figure 2B) but indis-
tinguishable from those of cdc13-1 exo1D pif1D mutants 
grown at 231C (compare lanes 9-10 with lanes 17-18, 
Figure 2B). This demonstrates that no gross alterations in 
telomere structure occur when cdc13-1 exo1D pif1D mutants 
are grown at 361C. Furthermore, cdc13-1 exo1D pif1D mutants 
are able to grow at 361C, whereas cdc13-1 pif1D mutants are 
not, but are indistinguishable in telomere structure (compare 
lanes 13-14 with lanes 17-18, Figure 2B). We conclude that 
alterations in telomere structure most likely do not account 
for the growth of cdc13-1 exo1D pif1D mutants at 361C. 
Pif1 exists as both nuclear and mitochondrial isoforms 
(Schulz and Zakian, 1994). Therefore, we wanted to know 
whether the nuclear or mitochondrial function of Pif1 inhibited 
growth of cdc13-1 exo1D mutants at 361C. The pif1-m2 allele, 
lacking nuclear Pif1, permitted growth of cdc13-1 exo1D 
mutants at 361C, whereas the pif1-m1 allele, lacking mitochon-
drial Pif1, did not (Figure 2C). We note that the growth of 
cdc13-1 exo1D pif1-m2 mutants at 361C is less than cdc13-1 
exo1D pif1D mutants (Figure 2C). This is consistent with other </p>

<p>Pif1 and Exo1 resect uncapped telomeres 
JM Dewar and D Lydall </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 29 | NO 23 | 2010 </p>

<p>&amp; 2010 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>



<p>reports that low levels of nuclear Pif1 activity persist in pif1-m2 
mutants (Schulz and Zakian, 1994; Ribeyre et al, 2009). We 
also confirmed that helicase activity of Pif1 inhibited growth of 
cdc13-1 exo1D mutants because the pif1-hd allele, deficient 
in helicase activity, also permitted growth at 361C (Figure 2C) 
(Zhou et al, 2000; Ribeyre et al, 2009). We conclude that 
nuclear, helicase-dependent activity of Pif1 inhibits growth of 
telomere capping-defective cdc13-1 mutants. </p>

<p>Pif1-and Exo1-dependent nucleases initiate the DDR 
following Cdc13 inactivation 
Upon Cdc13 inactivation, nuclease activities generate ssDNA, 
which stimulates checkpoint kinase cascades and induces </p>

<p>metaphase arrest (Figure 1A) (Garvik et al, 1995). To test the 
role of Pif1 in cell cycle arrest, cdc13-1 mutants were syn-
chronized in G1 using a factor at 231C, then released to 361C 
to assess metaphase arrest (Figure 3A). All strains also 
harboured the cdc15-2 mutation so that any cells that over-
came cdc13-1-induced metaphase arrest would arrest in late 
anaphase due to cdc15-2 and be unable to enter another cell 
cycle (Figure 3A) (Lydall and Weinert, 1995; Zubko et al, 
2004). As expected, cdc13-1 mutants accumulated at meta-
phase and did not pass through to anaphase (Figure 3B and C). 
cdc13-1 exo1D mutants accumulated at metaphase with simi-
lar kinetics to cdc13-1 mutants but, as previously reported, 
a subpopulation of cdc13-1 exo1D cells escaped metaphase </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>23°C 
30°C 
36°C </p>

<p>1296 
1297 </p>

<p>5323 
5324 </p>

<p>5460 
5461 </p>

<p>5682 
5683 </p>

<p>5780 
5781 </p>

<p>exo1Δ cdc13-1 
exo1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>pif1-m2 exo1Δ cdc13-1 
pif1-m2 exo1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>pif1Δ exo1Δ cdc13-1 
pif1Δ exo1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>pif1-m1 exo1Δ cdc13-1 
pif1-m1 exo1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>pif1-hd exo1Δ cdc13-1 
pif1-hd exo1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 
1 </p>

<p>1195 
4874 
4875 
1296 
1297 
5323 </p>

<p>12 13 14 15 16 17 18 
11 </p>

<p>Y′ 5.5 kb </p>

<p>Y′ 6.5 kb </p>

<p>Terminal </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>1.9 </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>5324 
1108 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Load </p>

<p>KB </p>

<p>5323 
5324 
3001 
4872 
4873 
1272 
1273 
5395 
5396 
640 </p>

<p>TG </p>

<p>AC </p>

<p>3′ 
5′ </p>

<p>Y′ 
Y′ </p>

<p>TG </p>

<p>AC </p>

<p>Y′ probe </p>

<p>5.5 or 6.5 kb </p>

<p>Y′ fragment </p>

<p>XhoI 
XhoI </p>

<p>1.05 -1.35 kb </p>

<p>Terminal fragment </p>

<p>CDC13 
+ + + + + + + + TS TS </p>

<p>EXO1 
+ + + + ------</p>

<p>PIF1 
+ + --+ + ----</p>

<p>Temp (°C) 
23 23 23 23 23 23 23 23 36 36 </p>

<p>TS TS TS TS TS TS TS TS </p>

<p>+ + + + ----</p>

<p>+ + --+ + --</p>

<p>23 23 23 23 23 23 23 23 </p>

<p>Figure 2 Exo1 and nuclear, helicase activity of Pif1 prevent telomere maintenance following inactivation of Cdc13. (A) Cartoon of yeast 
telomeres, indicating the fragments detected by telomere Southern blots using Y 
0 probe. Arrows represent XhoI cut sites. (B) Genomic DNA was 
prepared from two independent CDC13 
þ ( þ ) or cdc13-1 (TS) strains, grown at 23 or 361C, digested with XhoI and Southern blotted to detect 
telomeric Y 
0 and terminal fragments. Blots were reprobed to detect CDC15 as a loading control. Also see Supplementary Figure S4. (C) cdc13-1 
exo1D mutants defective in nuclear Pif1 (pif1-m2), mitochondrial Pif1 (pif1-m1) or carrying the helicase-deficient allele of Pif1 (pif1-hd) were 
serially diluted across agar plates and grown at the temperatures indicated for 3 days. </p>

<p>Pif1 and Exo1 resect uncapped telomeres 
JM Dewar and D Lydall </p>

<p>&amp; 2010 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 29 | NO 23 | 2010 4023 </p>

<p>arrest and accumulated in late anaphase due to the cdc15-2 
mutation (Figure 3B and C) (Zubko et al, 2004). cdc13-1 pif1D 
mutants behaved like cdc13-1 mutants and did not pass 
through to anaphase (Figure 3B and C). Interestingly, cdc13-
1 exo1D pif1D mutants did not accumulate in metaphase at all 
and passed readily through to anaphase (Figure 3B and C). 
Taken together, these results show that Pif1 has no effect on 
metaphase arrest of cdc13-1 mutants at 361C when Exo1 is 
present, but it is responsible for the arrest of a subpopulation 
of cells when Exo1 is absent. 
Following inactivation of Cdc13, Mec1-dependent check-
point activation occurs, leading to activation and hyperphos-
phorylaiton of the kinase Rad53 (Figure 1A) (Sweeney 
et al, 2005; Morin et al, 2008). We used the synchronous 
cultures to examine Rad53 phosphorylation by western blot 
(Figure 3A). cdc13-1 and cdc13-1 pif1D mutants exhibited 
strong Rad53 phosphorylation, indicated by a marked 
upward mobility shift of Rad53 (upper panels, Figure 3D). 
A reduction in Rad53 phosphorylation was seen in cdc13-1 
exo1D mutants, correlating with the recovery from metaphase 
arrest displayed by cdc13-1 exo1D mutants following telomere 
uncapping (Figure 3C and D). Interestingly, no discernable 
change in the mobility of Rad53 could be seen in cdc13-1 
exo1D pif1D mutants, consistent with their complete 
failure to arrest cell division at 361C (Figure 3C and D). We 
conclude that in the absence of Pif1 and Exo1, the checkpoint </p>

<p>kinase Rad53 is not activated after telomere uncapping in 
cdc13-1 mutants. 
To see whether cdc13-1 exo1D pif1D strains were defective 
in the DDR after other types of DNA damage as well as after 
telomere uncapping, we treated cells with bleomycin to 
induce DSBs. At both DSBs and uncapped telomeres, 
ssDNA is an important stimulus for the Mec1-dependent 
checkpoint. We treated the same set of strains examined in 
Figure 3B-D, with bleomycin at 231C after release from G1 
arrest. cdc13-1, cdc13-1 pif1D, cdc13-1 exo1D and cdc13-1 
exo1D pif1D mutants all behaved similarly, phosphorylating 
Rad53 and arresting at methaphase (Figure 3E; 
Supplementary Figure S4). We conclude that a functional 
DDR pathway operates in (cdc13-1) exo1D pif1D cells but that 
these cells are specifically defective in responding to telomere 
uncapping. 
Telomeric ssDNA stimulates metaphase arrest following 
telomere uncapping (Garvik et al, 1995). We used synchro-
nous cultures (Figure 3A) and quantitative amplification 
of ssDNA (QAOS) to measure subtelomeric ssDNA in repeti-
tive Y 
0 elements (present on Chromosome V and most other 
chromosome ends) following Cdc13 inactivation (Figure 4A) 
(Booth et al, 2001). cdc13-1 mutants with uncapped telo-
meres generated ssDNA at both the Y 
0 600 and Y 
0 5000 loci 
(Figure 4B and C). cdc13-1 exo1D mutants generated 
less ssDNA following telomere uncapping at the Y 
0 loci, as </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 </p>

<p>G1 
arrest </p>

<p>G1 
release </p>

<p>cdc15-2 arrest 
(anaphase) 
cdc13-1 arrest 
(metaphase) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B 
C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Time after telomere uncapping (h) 
Cells at anaphase (%) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
Time after telomere uncapping (h) 
Cells at metaphase (%) </p>

<p>36°C (h) </p>

<p>Rad53 </p>

<p>Tubulin </p>

<p>0 2 4 6 
0 2 4 6 </p>

<p>0 2 4 6 
0 2 4 6 
36°C (h) </p>

<p>Rad53 </p>

<p>Tubulin </p>

<p>E Bleo (h) </p>

<p>Rad53 </p>

<p>Tubulin </p>

<p>0 2 4 6 
0 2 4 6 </p>

<p>0 2 4 6 
0 2 4 6 
Bleo (h) </p>

<p>Rad53 </p>

<p>Tubulin </p>

<p>cdc15-2 cdc13-1 </p>

<p>cdc15-2 cdc13-1 pif1Δ </p>

<p>cdc15-2 cdc13-1 exo1Δ </p>

<p>cdc15-2 cdc13-1 exo1Δpif1Δ </p>

<p>5358 </p>

<p>5359 </p>

<p>5360 </p>

<p>5361 </p>

<p>cdc13-1 </p>

<p>exo1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>pif1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>pif1Δ exo1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>pif1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>pif1Δ exo1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>cdc13-1 </p>

<p>exo1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>Time after telomere uncapping (h) </p>

<p>Figure 3 Pif1 and Exo1 stimulate cell cycle arrest following inactivation of Cdc13. (A) Synchronous culture experiments to examine the effect 
of Pif1 and Exo1 on cell cycle arrest following telomere uncapping. cdc15-2 cdc13-1 cells were synchronized in G1 using a-factor then released 
at 361C. Cells arrest at metaphase from telomere uncapping (cdc13-1) or at anaphase from Cdc15 inactivation (cdc15-2). Samples taken at the 
time points indicated were stained with DAPI and 4100 cells of each genotype scored for cell cycle position (Zubko et al, 2006). (B) Percentage 
of cells at metaphase. (C) Percentage of cells at late anaphase. (D) Western blots of Rad53 following shift to 361C. Upper and lower panels were 
run in parallel on separate gels, but transferred, detected and imaged simultaneously. (E) Western blots of Rad53 following treatment with 
bleomycin. Corresponding scoring of cells at metaphase and anaphase given as Supplementary Figure S5. </p>

<p>Pif1 and Exo1 resect uncapped telomeres 
JM Dewar and D Lydall </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 29 | NO 23 | 2010 </p>

<p>&amp; 2010 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>



<p>previously reported (Maringele and Lydall, 2002; Zubko et al, 
2004). Interestingly, cdc13-1 pif1D mutants, like cdc13-1 
exo1D mutants showed reduced ssDNA generation in the 
Y 
0 600 and Y 
0 5000 loci following telomere uncapping. 
Furthermore, cdc13-1 exo1D pif1D mutants generated no 
detectable ssDNA at Y 
0 600 or Y 
0 5000 loci following telomere 
uncapping (Figure 4B and C). We confirmed that ssDNA 
generation occurred on the TG (3 
0 ) strand due to degradation 
of the AC (5 
0 ) strand, as we were unable to detect ssDNA </p>

<p>on the AC strand (Figure 4D). We conclude that Pif1, like 
Exo1, is important for ssDNA generation after telomere 
uncapping in cdc13-1 mutants and appears to regulate a 
nuclease activity, which functions in parallel to Exo1 at 
chromosome ends. 
To examine how Pif1 and Exo1 affect ssDNA accumulation 
further from chromosome ends, we measured ssDNA at single-
copy loci on Chromosome V after Cdc13 inactivation. At 4 h, 
cdc13-1 mutants generated ssDNA at all loci examined, with </p>

<p>TG strand </p>

<p>TG repeats </p>

<p>ssDNA (%) </p>

<p>Time after telomere uncapping (h) </p>

<p>29700 bp 
14500 bp 
8500 bp </p>

<p>Single-copy sequence 
(ChrV only) </p>

<p>Repetitive sequence 
(multiple chromosomes) </p>

<p>600-7000 bp 
200-500 bp </p>

<p>TG </p>

<p>AC </p>

<p>Y′ 
YER188W 
YER186C 
PDA1 </p>

<p>Y′-5000 bp 
TG strand </p>

<p>Time after telomere uncapping (h) </p>

<p>ssDNA (%) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B 
C </p>

<p>E 
D </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
0 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 </p>

<p>3′ 
5′ </p>

<p>cdc13-1 </p>

<p>cdc13-1 pif1Δ </p>

<p>5358 </p>

<p>5359 </p>

<p>cdc13-1 exo1Δ </p>

<p>cdc13-1 exo1Δ pif1Δ </p>

<p>5360 </p>

<p>5361 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
Time after telomere uncapping 
(h) </p>

<p>Load </p>

<p>TG ssDNA </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>ssDNA (%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>0 
Time after telomere uncapping (h) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
Distance from chromosomal end (kb) </p>

<p>4 hours after 
telomere uncapping </p>

<p>ssDNA (%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 </p>

<p>Y′-600 bp 
TG strand </p>

<p>Y′-600 bp 
AC strand </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>3.1 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>4.1 </p>

<p>6.1 </p>

<p>KB </p>

<p>ssDNA (KUs) </p>

<p>YKU70 -</p>

<p>CDC13 + </p>

<p>EXO1 + </p>

<p>PIF1 + </p>

<p>36°C (h) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>TS </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>0 
NA </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>TS 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>TS 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>TS 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>TS 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>TS 
+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>TS 
+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>TS 
+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>TS 
+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>TS 
+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>TS 
+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>TS </p>

<p>5358 
5359 
5360 
5361 
1412 </p>

<p>Figure 4 Pif1 and Exo1 generate ssDNA at uncapped telomeres. (A) Physical map of the right telomere of Chromosome V. Synchronous 
cultures were subjected to telomere uncapping as in Figure 3A, and samples were taken to measure ssDNA. (B) TG-strand ssDNA 600 bp from 
the end of the telomere (Y 
0 600) measured by QAOS. (C) TG-strand ssDNA 5000 bp away from the end of the telomere (Y 
0 5000). (D) AC-strand 
ssDNA 600 bp away from the end of the telomere. (E) TG-strand ssDNA generated at loci indicated in (A), 4 h after telomere uncapping. Dashed 
line represents 1.56% (1/64), corresponding to the value expected for 1 single-stranded locus per yeast cell in G2. (F) TG-strand ssDNA in the 
telomeric TG repeats detected by in-gel assay, comparing cdc13-1 mutants (TS) to a yku70D control. Loading determined by Southern 
hybridization with a CDC15 probe. Lanes were run and detected on the same gel and cropped for presentation purposes. (G) Quantification of 
the ssDNA signal in each lane in (F). ssDNA is measured in KUs (Ku units). In all, 1 Ku Unit is the ssDNA signal in an asynchronously dividing 
yku70D control at 231C. </p>

<p>Pif1 and Exo1 resect uncapped telomeres 
JM Dewar and D Lydall </p>

<p>&amp; 2010 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 29 | NO 23 | 2010 4025 </p>

<p>the amount of ssDNA decreasing at loci further from the 
chromosome end, as previously reported (Zubko et al, 
2004). cdc13-1 exo1D mutants generated less ssDNA in the Y </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>repeats and no ssDNA in single-copy loci on Chromosome V, 
also as previously reported (Figure 4E) (Zubko et al, 2004). 
cdc13-1 pif1D mutants generated similar amounts of ssDNA to 
cdc13-1 exo1D mutants in the Y 
0 repeats. However, at more 
distal, single-copy loci, cdc13-1 pif1D mutants generated less 
ssDNA than cdc13-1 mutants but more than exo1D cdc13-1 
mutants. The higher levels of ssDNA generated further from 
the chromosome end in cdc13-1 pif1D mutants, in comparison 
with cdc13-1 exo1D mutants, most likely accounts for their 
sustained metaphase arrest following telomere uncapping 
(Figure 3B and C). Furthermore, the ssDNA generated by 
cdc13-1 and cdc13-1 pif1D mutants o10 kb from the chromo-
some end is 41.6% (1/64) (Figure 4E). Assuming 1 single-
stranded telomere per cell is sufficient to stimulate arrest, this 
suggests that ssDNA extending o10 kb on one of the 64 G2 
telomeres in Saccharomyces cerevisiae is sufficient to stimulate 
metaphase arrest (Figure 4E) (Sandell and Zakian, 1993; Vaze 
et al, 2002; Zubko et al, 2004). 
No checkpoint activation was detected in cdc13-1 exo1D 
pif1D mutants following telomere uncapping, and no ssDNA 
was detected in the Y 
0 elements (Figures 3D and 4B). However, 
yku70D mutants at 231C have detectable ssDNA in the telo-
meric TG repeats but do not undergo checkpoint activation 
(Gravel et al, 1998; Polotnianka et al, 1998; Maringele and 
Lydall, 2002). Thus, we hypothesized that cdc13-1 exo1D 
pif1D mutants might still generate detectable ssDNA in the 
TG repeats. We used synchronous cultures (Figure 3A) and 
measured ssDNA by in-gel assay to measure ssDNA in the TG 
repeats in cdc13-1 mutants (Figure 4F and G). cdc13-1 mutants 
generated large amounts of TG ssDNA at 2 and 4 h following 
telomere uncapping (Figure 4F), corresponding to an approxi-
mately five-fold increase in signal compared with yku70D 
mutants (Figure 4G). cdc13-1 exo1D pif1D mutants also gen-
erated detectable ssDNA 2 h following telomere uncapping, 
but at a level approximately equal to that of a yku70D mutant 
(Figure 4F and G). However, the ssDNA generated in cdc13-1 
exo1D pif1D mutants was transient and was no longer detect-
able 4 h after telomere uncapping (Figure 4F and G). 
Surprisingly, cdc13-1 pif1D mutants displayed only a modest 
decrease in ssDNA generation in the TG repeats following 
telomere uncapping, whereas cdc13-1 exo1D mutants gener-
ated very little ssDNA (Figure 4F and G). We conclude that 
cdc13-1 exo1D pif1D mutants generate limited, transient 
ssDNA that is insufficient to stimulate checkpoint activation 
and that Exo1 is much more important than Pif1 for ssDNA 
generation in the TG repeats following telomere uncapping. </p>

<p>Pif1 has important functions in cells lacking telomerase 
It has been suggested that increased levels of telomerase at 
the telomeres of cdc13-1 pif1D cells shields uncapped telo-
meres from nuclease activities (Vega et al, 2007). However, 
this is somewhat inconsistent with our observation that Pif1 
has relatively little effect on ssDNA generation in the telo-
meric TG repeats, where telomerase presumably binds 
(Figure 4G). Therefore, we wanted to know whether the 
ability of the pif1D mutation to improve the growth of 
cdc13-1 mutants was dependent upon the telomerase tem-
plate component (TLC1) or catalytic subunit (Est2). 
Interestingly, we found that cdc13-1 tlc1D pif1D and cdc13-1 </p>

<p>tlc1D exo1D mutants grew better at 251C than cdc13-1 tlc1D 
mutants (compare rows 7-8 and 11-12 with 3-4, Figure 5A; 
Supplementary Figure S6). We also found that cdc13-1 
est2D pif1D and cdc13-1 est2D exo1D mutants were able to 
grow at 251C, whereas cdc13-1 est2D mutants were not 
(Supplementary Figure S7). We conclude that Pif1 has a 
telomerase (TLC1, Est2) independent effect at uncapped 
telomeres. However, we note that est2D cdc13-1 and tlc1D 
cdc13-1 mutants grow worse than cdc13-1 mutants, demon-
strating that telomerase contributes to telomere capping 
following inactivation of Cdc13. 
Pif1 is responsible for the residual checkpoint activation in 
cdc13-1 exo1D mutants (Figure 3D) and inhibits growth of 
cdc13-1 mutants lacking telomerase (Figure 5A). We hypothe-
sized that Pif1 would contribute to ssDNA generation at 
uncapped telomeres and subsequent checkpoint activation, 
even in cdc13-1 mutants lacking telomerase. To test this, we 
measured Rad53 phosphorylation (Supplementary Figure 
S8A) and telomeric TG repeat ssDNA (Supplementary 
Figure S8B and C) in cdc13-1 and cdc13-1 tlc1D mutants, 
before and after telomere uncapping. In cdc13-1 tlc1D exo1D 
pif1D mutants, there was a decrease in Rad53 phosphoryla-
tion compared with cdc13-1 tlc1D exo1D mutants 
(Supplementary Figure S8A). We also found that cdc13-1 
tlc1D pif1D and cdc13-1 tlc1D exo1D pif1D mutants generated 
less ssDNA than cdc13-1 tlc1D and cdc13-1 tlc1D exo1D 
mutants, respectively, following telomere uncapping 
(Supplementary Figure S8B and C). We conclude that Pif1 
has a contribution to ssDNA generation and checkpoint 
activation following telomere uncapping that is independent 
of telomerase. However, we note that 40% of cdc13-1 tlc1D 
cells were at metaphase at 231C compared with 30% of 
cdc13-1 tlc1D pif1D cells (Supplementary Figure S8D). Thus, 
we cannot exclude the possibility that reduced ssDNA gen-
eration in cdc13-1 tlc1D pif1D mutants is due to altered 
kinetics of accumulation at metaphase. 
Although Pif1 clearly demonstrates a telomerase-indepen-
dent effect in cdc13-1 mutants, we note that cdc13-1 tlc1D 
exo1D mutants could grow at 271C, whereas cdc13-1 tlc1D 
pif1D mutants could not (compare rows 11-12 with 7-8, 
Figure 5A). In contrast, cdc13-1 TLC1 
þ exo1D mutants and </p>

<p>cdc13-1 TLC1 
þ pif1D mutants could both grow similarly at </p>

<p>271C (compare rows 9-10 with 5-6, Figure 5A). This shows 
that Pif1 is less potent than Exo1 at inhibiting growth of 
cdc13-1 tlc1D mutants than cdc13-1 TLC1 
þ mutants. </p>

<p>To help clarify the role of Pif1 in cdc13-1 tlc1D and cdc13-1 
TLC1 
þ mutants, we examined the effect of Pif1 in CDC13 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>tlc1D mutants. Yeast strains that cannot recruit telomerase 
(e.g. tlc1D) lose telomeric DNA with each cell division until 
the cultures senesce and lose proliferative capacity, much like 
mammalian fibroblasts. Senescent, telomerase-deficient 
yeast cultures usually recover, using telomerase-independent, 
recombination-dependent mechanisms of telomere mainte-
nance, leading to clear changes in telomere structure 
(Lundblad and Blackburn, 1993; Teng and Zakian, 1999). 
Therefore, we germinated spores containing combinations 
of null mutations in telomerase (TLC1), PIF1 and EXO1, 
and assessed growth at various passages (Figure 5B). As 
expected, tlc1D mutants grew well at passage 1, poorly from 
passages 2-5 (senescence) and grew well again from passage 
7 (recovery) (Figure 5B). tlc1D exo1D mutants showed a 
similar pattern of growth to tlc1D mutants but grew slightly </p>

<p>Pif1 and Exo1 resect uncapped telomeres 
JM Dewar and D Lydall </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 29 | NO 23 | 2010 </p>

<p>&amp; 2010 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>



<p>better prior to senescence, as previously reported (passages 3 
and 4, Figure 5B) (Maringele and Lydall, 2004). In contrast, 
tlc1D pif1D and tlc1D pif1D exo1D strains showed a rapid 
decline in growth from passages 2-6 (senescence) and 
exhibited a protracted senescence period but slowly recovered 
by passage 15 (Figure 5B). We conclude that Pif1 inhibits 
entry into senescence and promotes recovery. Taken with the 
data discussed earlier, Pif1 contributes to good growth of tlc1D </p>

<p>mutants from passage 2 onwards, yet inhibits growth of 
cdc13-1 mutants (Figures 1C and 5A). In contrast, Exo1 has 
only a small effect on the growth of tlc1D mutants, yet inhibits 
growth of cdc13-1 mutants (Figures 1C and 5A). Thus, it is 
likely that the relatively poor growth of cdc13-1 tlc1D 
pif1D compared with cdc13-1 tlc1D exo1D mutants is due to 
the poor growth of tlc1D pif1D mutants compared with tlc1D 
exo1D mutants. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1 
3 
5 
7 
9 
11 
13 
15 </p>

<p>tlc1Δ 
tlc1Δ pif1Δ 
tlc1Δ exo1Δ 
tlc1Δ exo1Δ pif1Δ </p>

<p>Passage 
Growth relative to TLC1 + </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>tlc1Δ exo1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>exo1Δ cdc13-1 
exo1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>tlc1Δ exo1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>tlc1Δ pif1Δ exo1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>pif1Δ exo1Δ cdc13-1 
pif1Δ exo1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>tlc1Δ pif1Δ exo1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>tlc1Δ pif1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>pif1Δ cdc13-1 
pif1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>tlc1Δ pif1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>tlc1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>cdc13-1 
cdc13-1 </p>

<p>tlc1Δ cdc13-1 </p>

<p>23°C 
25°C 
26°C 
27°C 
36°C </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>5 
6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>13 
14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>9 
10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Load </p>

<p>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 
1 </p>

<p>5925 
5926 
5927 
5928 
5929 
5936 
5935 
5934 
5933 
5932 
5931 
5930 
5937 
5938 
5939 
5940 
5941 
5947 
5946 
5945 
5944 
5943 
5942 
5948 </p>

<p>Terminal </p>

<p>Y′ 5.5 kb </p>

<p>Y′ 6.5 kb </p>

<p>Passage </p>

<p>TLC1 </p>

<p>EXO1 </p>

<p>PIF1 </p>

<p>1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 15 15 15 15 15 15 15 15 15 15 15 15 </p>

<p>+ + + + --------+ + + + --------</p>

<p>+ + --+ + + + ----+ + --+ + + + ----</p>

<p>+ -+ -+ + --+ + --+ -+ -+ + --+ + --</p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1.9 </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>KB </p>

<p>Figure 5 Pif1 has telomerase-independent effects at telomeres. (A) A cdc13-1/CDC13 
þ tlc1D/TLC1 
þ exo1D/EXO1 
þ pif1D/PIF1 
þ diploid 
(DLY1628 x DLY5324) was sporulated, dissected and germinated at 231C to generate strains of the indicated genotype at 231C. These were 
taken from the germination plate, grown to saturation, then serially diluted across agar plates and grown at the temperatures indicated for 3 
days. (B) Strains of the genotypes indicated were passaged repeatedly by restreaking at 301C for 3 days along with TLC1 
þ controls. At the 
passages indicated, strains were assayed for growth, which was then quantified (Supplementary Figure S9). Growth at each passage is given as 
a fraction of the growth of the relevant TLC1 
þ strain and the mean of two independent strains is shown. (C) At passages 1 and 15, strains 
assayed for growth in (B) had genomic DNA isolated and were Southern blotted with Y 
0 probe, as in Figure 2B. See Supplementary Figure S10 
for detection with TG probe. </p>

<p>Pif1 and Exo1 resect uncapped telomeres 
JM Dewar and D Lydall </p>

<p>&amp; 2010 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 29 | NO 23 | 2010 4027 </p>

<p>After long cultivation (passage 15, 45 days growth) tlc1D 
pif1D and tlc1D pif1D exo1D mutants could be distinguished 
from those of tlc1D and tlc1D exo1D mutants by their poor 
growth (Figure 5B). Telomerase-deficient survivors typically 
show clear alterations in telomere structure-type I survivors 
undergo dramatic amplification of Y 
0 elements and retain 
short TG overhangs, whereas type II survivors show modest 
amplification of Y 
0 elements but amplify their TG overhangs 
(Teng and Zakian, 1999). Therefore, we examined the telo-
meres of tlc1D pif1D and tlc1D pif1D exo1D mutants. At 
passage 1, before entry into senescence, tlc1D, tlc1D exo1D, 
tlc1D pif1D and tlc1D pif1D exo1D mutants all had short 
telomeres (compare lanes 1-4 with lanes 5-12, Figure 5C). 
At passage 15, tlc1D mutants and tlc1D exo1D mutants had 
amplified Y 
0 elements and terminal fragments to generate 
type II (lanes 17-18, Figure 5D) or type I (lanes 21-22, 
Figure 5D) survivors. In contrast, tlc1D pif1D and tlc1D 
pif1D exo1D mutants at passage 15 had shorter telomeres 
than at passage 1 and had undergone a reduction in Y </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>elements, but did not appear to have generated type I or 
type II survivor telomere structures (compare lanes 7-8 with 
19-20 and lanes 11-12 with 23-24, Figure 5D). We noted that 
tlc1D pif1D and tlc1D pif1D exo1D mutants resembled type I 
survivors in that our TG probe did not detect any individual 
telomeres further up the gel (marked with arrows, compare 
lanes 7-8 with 19-20 and lanes 11-12 with 23-24, 
Supplementary Figure S10), indicating that all telomeres in 
these strains had acquired a terminal Y 
0 fragment. However, 
the terminal fragments of tlc1D pif1D and tlc1D pif1D exo1D 
were even shorter than those of type I survivors and they had </p>

<p>undergone a reduction, not an amplification in Y 
0 elements, 
clearly distinguishing them from typical type I survivors 
(compares lanes 19-20, 23-24 with lanes 21-22, Figure 5D). 
We conclude that Pif1 is required for the generation of type I 
and type II survivors and that in the absence of Pif1, cells 
lacking telomerase can improve growth following senescence 
without adopting typical type I or type II survivor structures. </p>

<p>Telomerase is crucial for survival in the absence 
of Cdc13 
Cdc13 has two crucial functions at telomeres-one, to shield 
telomeres from nuclease activities and the second to recruit 
telomerase to the telomere (Nugent et al, 1996). Although 
elimination of Pif1 and Exo1 permits cdc13-1 mutants to grow 
at 361C (presumably when cdc13-1 is completely inactivated), 
this does not permit cdc13-1 tlc1D mutants to grow at 361C 
(compare rows 13-14 with 15-16, Figure 5A), demonstrating 
that telomerase has a function in cdc13-1 mutants at 361C. 
Therefore, we hypothesized that at 361C, Cdc13-1 might 
retain the ability to recruit telomerase, and Cdc13-dependent 
telomerase activity might be essential for growth. 
Alternatively, telomerase might be recruited to telomeres in 
a Cdc13-independent manner. 
To test whether Cdc13-1 retained the ability to recruit 
telomerase in cdc13-1 exo1D pif1D cells at 361C, we decided 
to delete CDC13. We generated diploid strains heterozygous 
for pif1D, exo1D and cdc13D mutations. Diploids were sporu-
lated, tetrads dissected and vegetative cells containing com-
binations of the three deletion mutations were allowed to 
form colonies. Figure 6A shows a representative image of one </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 
a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>1 
2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 
a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CDC13 
PIF1 
EXO1 </p>

<p>PIF1 or pif1Δ 
EXO1 or exo1Δ </p>

<p>cdc13Δ 
pif1Δ 
exo1Δ </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>tlc1Δ cdc13Δ pURA3[CDC13] </p>

<p>TLC1 cdc13Δ pURA3[CDC13] </p>

<p>pif1Δ exo1Δ TLC1 cdc13Δ pURA3[CDC13] 
pif1Δ exo1Δ tlc1Δ cdc13Δ pURA3[CDC13] </p>

<p>tlc1Δ CDC13 pURA3[CDC13] </p>

<p>TLC1 CDC13 pURA3[CDC13] </p>

<p>pif1Δ exo1Δ TLC1 CDC13 pURA3[CDC13] 
pif1Δ exo1Δ tlc1Δ CDC13 pURA3[CDC13] </p>

<p>YEPD 
-URA 
FOA </p>

<p>6097 </p>

<p>6098 </p>

<p>6099 </p>

<p>6100 </p>

<p>6093 </p>

<p>6094 </p>

<p>6095 </p>

<p>6096 </p>

<p>Mutation </p>

<p>Phenotype in 
cdc13Δ pif1Δ exo1Δ </p>

<p>tlc1Δ 
yku70Δ 
rad52Δ 
pol32Δ </p>

<p>Inviable 
Inviable 
Inviable 
Viable </p>

<p>Figure 6 cdc13D exo1D pif1D cells are viable but depend upon telomerase and homologous recombination for survival. (A) cdc13D/CDC13 
exo1D/EXO1 pif1D/PIF1 diploids (DDY341) were dissected. Viable cdc13D exo1D pif1D meiotic progeny are circled. Spores were incubated for 5 
days at 231C before genotypes were determined by replica plating to selective medium. (B) Strains of the genotypes indicated, all carrying a 
pURA3[CDC13] plasmid (pDL1012) were germinated, grown to saturation, then serially diluted across YEPD, ÀURA and FOA agar plates. Plates 
were incubated at 301C for 4 days, YEPD plate shown after 2 days, ÀURA plate shown after 3 days and FOA plate shown after 4 days. 
(C) Summary of the roles of various telomere-related genes and their role in the survival of cdc13D pif1D exo1D mutants as assessed in 
Supplementary Figures S11 and S12. </p>

<p>Pif1 and Exo1 resect uncapped telomeres 
JM Dewar and D Lydall </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 29 | NO 23 | 2010 </p>

<p>&amp; 2010 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>



<p>tetrad dissection plate. Importantly, we found that cdc13D 
exo1D pif1D strains were viable and had a germination 
efficiency of B90% compared with CDC13 exo1D pif1D 
strains (Figure 6A; Supplementary Table SI). However, it 
was clear that cdc13D exo1D pif1D mutants grew less well 
than CDC13 
þ exo1D pif1D mutants on the tetrad dissection </p>

<p>plates (Figure 6A). No viable colonies were formed from 
cdc13D cells that were either PIF1 
þ or EXO1 
þ . We conclude </p>

<p>that neither Cdc13-dependent telomerase activity nor 
Cdc13-dependent capping activities are required for growth 
following elimination of Pif1 and Exo1. 
The viability of cdc13D exo1D pif1D strains was surprising 
in the light of the requirement for telomerase in cdc13-1 
exo1D pif1D strains. We hypothesized that Cdc13-indepen-
dent telomerase activity was essential for the viability of 
cdc13D exo1D pif1D strains. To test this, we generated diploid 
strains heterozygous for pif1D, exo1D, cdc13D and tlc1D 
mutations, containing a plasmid that carried a wild-type 
copy of CDC13. Diploids were sporulated and tetrad dissec-
tion was performed to generate strains containing combina-
tions of the four deletion mutations, in addition to the wild-
type copy of CDC13. These strains were diluted across agar 
plates either fully supplemented (YEPD), lacking uracil 
(ÀURA) or containing FOA (FOA). FOA is toxic to cells with 
an active uracil biosynthetic pathway so only cells able to 
survive in the absence of the URA3-and CDC13-containing 
plasmid would be able to grow. As expected, cdc13D TLC1 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>and cdc13D tlc1D mutants were able to grow on YEPD and 
-URA, but not on FOA medium, demonstrating that CDC13 
was essential for survival of these cell types (Figure 6B). 
cdc13D TLC1 
þ exo1D pif1D strains were able to grow on </p>

<p>FOA, YEPD and -URA, demonstrating that CDC13 was not 
essential in this background (Figure 6B). However, cdc13D 
TLC1 
þ exo1D pif1D cells grew much more poorly on FOA </p>

<p>than on -URA and YEPD consistent the poor growth of 
cdc13D exo1D pif1D cells on the tetrad dissection plate(s) 
(Figure 6A). Importantly, cdc13D tlc1D exo1D pif1D cells were 
able to grow on YEPD and -URA but not on FOA, demon-
strating that they could not survive in the absence of 
Cdc13. We conclude that telomerase is essential for the 
survival of cdc13D exo1D pif1D mutants, suggesting that 
Cdc13-independent recruitment of telomerase is essential 
for their survival. 
We used the same plasmid-based method to assess the 
requirement for various proteins involved in telomere main-
tenance to the growth of cdc13D exo1D pif1D mutants. We 
confirmed that TLC1 was required for the viability of cdc13D 
pif1D exo1D as cdc13D pif1D exo1D tlc1D mutants could not 
lose a plasmid carrying CDC13 (p[URA3]CDC13) (Figure 6C). 
We also found that Yku70 (a component of the Ku complex, 
which binds TLC1 to aid in recruitment of telomerase to the 
telomere) and Rad52 (required for homologous recombina-
tion and the generation of type I and type II survivor telomere 
structures) were required for the viability of cdc13D pif1D 
exo1D mutants (Figure 6C). However, we found that Pol32 
(subunit of Polymerase d, required for the generation of 
type I and type II survivor telomere structures) was dispen-
sable for the viability of cdc13D pif1D exo1D mutants 
(Figure 6C), although elimination of Pol32 did reduce the 
frequency at which cdc13D pif1D exo1D mutants were able to 
lose the pURA3[CDC13] (Supplementary Figure S12). We 
conclude that cdc13D pif1D exo1D mutants are distinct </p>

<p>from type I and type II survivors, as they do not require 
Pol32, and their telomeres are maintained through a combi-
nation of homologous recombination, Ku and telomerase 
activity. 
If cdc13D exo1D pif1D mutants are able to recruit telomer-
ase then they may not senesce or undergo the rearrangements 
in telomere structure characteristic of telomerase-deficient 
strains. To test this hypothesis, we compared the growth 
and telomere structure of cdc13D exo1D pif1D strains with 
tlc1D and tlc1D exo1D pif1D strains. As expected, telomerase-
deficient tlc1D mutants senesced and recovered (Figure 7A) 
and by passage 11 they had generated type I (lane 15, 
Figure 7B) and type II (lane 16, Figure 7B) survivors. 
Interestingly, cdc13D exo1D pif1D strains showed a slight 
growth defect at passage 1 (Figure 7A), consistent with the 
small colonies formed by cdc13D exo1D pif1D mutants on the 
tetrad dissection plate (Figure 6A) and the growth defect of 
cdc13D TLC1 
þ exo1D pif1D pURA3[CDC13] mutants grown </p>

<p>on FOA (Figure 6B). However, by passage 5 and in 
all subsequent passages cdc13D exo1D pif1D mutants had 
improved in growth (Figure 7A). The telomeres of cdc13D 
exo1D pif1D mutants were long with more variation in length, 
and by passage 11, the median telomere length and variance 
in length increased (lanes 9-12, 21-24, Figure 7B). This is 
consistent with previous work showing that hypomorphic 
alleles of Cdc13 can cause increased telomere length and 
variance in telomere length (Chandra et al, 2001). No clear 
alterations in the telomere structure of cdc13D exo1D pif1D 
mutants were observed, and at passage 1, their telomeres 
most closely resembled those of cdc13-1 exo1D pif1D mutants 
with capped telomeres, which notably do not senesce (com-
pare lanes 2, 14 with lanes 9-12, Figure 7B). The growth and 
telomere structure of cdc13D exo1D pif1D mutants was clearly 
distinct from that of telomerase-deficient tlc1D exo1D pif1D 
mutants, which rapidly senesced and slowly recovered 
(Figure 7A), while maintaining a relatively normal telomere 
structure (compare lanes 7-8 with lanes 19-20, Figure 7B). 
We conclude that cdc13D exo1D pif1D mutants do not under-
go senescence and maintain their telomeres for at least 11 
passages (44 days). This is consistent with our notion that 
cdc13D exo1D pif1D mutants are able to maintain telomeres 
in a telomerase-dependent manner, even in the absence 
of Cdc13. 
Finally, although we observed that cdc13-1 exo1D 
pif1D mutants generated ssDNA only in the TG repeats, 
transiently over the course of a single cell cycle, we wished 
to know whether repeated cell division in the absence of 
telomere capping would lead to accumulation of ssDNA. By 
in-gel assay, we found that cdc13-1 exo1D pif1D mutants 
grown at 361C for 4 h (B2 population doublings with un-
capped telomeres) and cdc13D exo1D pif1D mutants 
from Passage 1 (B50 population doublings with uncapped 
telomeres) generated comparable levels of ssDNA in the 
TG repeats to a yku70D mutant (Figure 7C and D). 
This was comparable to the transient level of ssDNA seen 
in cdc13-1 exo1D pif1D mutants 2 h after telomere uncapping, 
within a single cell cycle (Figure 4G). We conclude 
that continued growth following telomere uncapping in 
exo1D pif1D mutants does not lead to ssDNA accumulation. 
This suggests that no residual nuclease activities continue 
to resect uncapped telomeres in the absence of Pif1 
and Exo1. </p>

<p>Pif1 and Exo1 resect uncapped telomeres 
JM Dewar and D Lydall </p>

<p>&amp; 2010 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 29 | NO 23 | 2010 4029 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>YKU70 </p>

<p>CDC13 </p>

<p>PIF1 
EXO1 </p>

<p>Temp (°C) </p>

<p>+ 
-
+ 
-
+ + --</p>

<p>+ 
-
+ 
T S 
TS TS + TS </p>

<p>+ 
-
+ 
-
+ + --</p>

<p>-
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ + + + 
23 
23 
23 
36 
23 36 23 23 </p>

<p>Load </p>

<p>TG ssDNA 
2.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>3.1 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>4.1 </p>

<p>6.1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>cdc13-1 
CDC13 
+ cdc13-1 
cdc13-1 cdc13-1 cdc13Δ 
CDC13 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>exo1Δ exo1Δ exo1Δ exo1Δ 
pif1Δ 
pif1Δ 
pif1Δ 
pif1Δ </p>

<p>23°C 
23°C 
36°C 
23°C 
23°C 
36°C 
23°C </p>

<p>ssDNA (KUs) </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>1412 </p>

<p>640 </p>

<p>1108 
1108 
5915 
5323 
5323 
5860 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1 
3 
5 
7 
9 
1 1 13 15 </p>

<p>PIF1 
+ EXO1 
+ tlc1Δ </p>

<p>pif1Δ exo1Δ tlc1Δ </p>

<p>pif1Δ exo1Δ cdc13Δ </p>

<p>Passage number 
Growth relative to TLC1 + </p>

<p>CDC13 + </p>

<p>Terminal </p>

<p>Y′ 5.5 kb </p>

<p>Y′ 6.5 kb </p>

<p>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 
1 
13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 
Load </p>

<p>5913 
5914 
5915 
5916 
5917 
5918 
5909 
5910 
5911 
5912 
5919 
5920 
5921 
5922 
5923 
5924 
5860 
5861 
5862 
5863 
640 
3001 
5323 
5324 </p>

<p>Passage </p>

<p>CDC13 </p>

<p>TLC1 </p>

<p>EXO1 </p>

<p>PIF1 </p>

<p>--1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 </p>

<p>+ TS + + + + + + </p>

<p>+ + --+ + --</p>

<p>+ -+ + ----</p>

<p>+ -+ + ----</p>

<p>--11 11 11 11 11 11 11 11 11 11 </p>

<p>+ TS + + + + + + </p>

<p>+ + --+ + --</p>

<p>+ -+ + ----</p>

<p>+ -+ + ----</p>

<p>+ + + + 
----</p>

<p>----</p>

<p>----</p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1.9 </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>KB </p>

<p>+ + + + 
----</p>

<p>----</p>

<p>----</p>

<p>Figure 7 Cells lacking Cdc13 maintain telomeres and do not senesce. (A) Strains of the genotypes indicated were passaged repeatedly at 231C 
for 4 days along with TLC1 
þ CDC13 
þ controls. At the passages indicated, strains were assayed for growth (Supplementary Figure S13). Growth 
at each passage is given as a fraction of the growth of the relevant TLC1 
þ CDC13 
þ strain. The mean of two tlc1D strains or four cdc13D strains 
is shown. (B) At passages 1 and 11, strains that were assayed for growth in (A) had genomic DNA isolated and were Southern blotted, as in 
Figure 2B. PIF1 
þ EXO1 
þ CDC13 
þ and exo1D pif1D cdc13-1 (TS) strains were grown independently. See Supplementary Figure S14 for original 
blot probed with Y 
0 and TG probe. (C) CDC13 
þ ( þ ), cdc13D (À) and cdc13-1 (TS) strains of the genotypes indicated were either grown 
exponentially at 23 or 361C for 4 h before their DNA was isolated and telomeric TG ssDNA was detected by in-gel assay as in Figure 4F. 
(D) Quantification of ssDNA from the in-gel assay shown in (C), as in Figure 4F. </p>

<p>Pif1 and Exo1 resect uncapped telomeres 
JM Dewar and D Lydall </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 29 | NO 23 | 2010 </p>

<p>&amp; 2010 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>



<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We have shown that Pif1 and Exo1 are responsible for 
extensive ssDNA generation at uncapped telomeres in 
cdc13-1 mutants and also that Pif1 has telomerase-indepen-
dent functions at telomeres. This leads us to propose a model 
where Pif1 can initiate the DDR at uncapped telomeres by 
controlling nuclease activity. Furthermore, and remarkably, 
cells lacking Pif1 and Exo1 are viable and grow well in the 
absence of the usually essential telomere capping protein 
Cdc13. 
In our model (Figure 8), Pif1 unwinds telomeric duplex 
DNA, generating ssDNA that is cleaved by an unidentified 
ssDNA endonuclease in a manner analogous to the function 
of Pif1 in Okazaki fragment processing and at stalled replica-
tion forks (Budd et al, 2006; Chang et al, 2009; George et al, 
2009; Pike et al, 2009). We propose that close to the chromo-
some end (o5 kb) both Pif1-and Exo1-dependent activities 
generate ssDNA, causing weak initial checkpoint activation. 
We propose that Exo1 subsequently generates ssDNA 45 kb 
from the chromosome end, leading to stronger checkpoint 
activation that is sufficient to arrest all cells with uncapped 
telomeres. Our model is consistent with Pif1 being ExoY, a 
hypothetical nuclease proposed to function in parallel to Exo1 
at uncapped telomeres (Zubko et al, 2004). Pif1, like ExoY, is 
more important for ssDNA generation at the end of the 
chromosome than further away (Figure 4E). 
In our model, Exo1 recognizes the junction between 3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>(TG) ssDNA and duplex DNA, at native telomeric overhangs 
as previously suggested (Maringele and Lydall, 2002) or at 
stalled replication forks (Segurado and Diffley, 2008). We 
propose that Pif1 binds and unwinds 5 
0 (AC) overhangs 
because Pif1 is a 5 
0 -3 
0 helicase (Lahaye et al, 1991; Zhou 
et al, 2000; Pike et al, 2009). If Pif1 does engage telomeric 
dsDNA and convert it to ssDNA, 5 
0 (AC) ssDNA presumably 
exists (Supplementary Figure S15A). Interestingly, 5 
0 telo-
meric ssDNA has been observed both in mammalian cells 
and in Caenorhabditis elegans (Cimino-Reale et al, 2003; </p>

<p>Raices et al, 2008) and but not so far in S. cerevisiae. 
However, 5 
0 ssDNA overhangs could in principle occur at 
stalled replication fork structures (Supplementary Figure 
S15B) or Okazaki fragments. 
DSBs that can be repaired by homologous recombination 
and DSB-induced shortened telomeres are processed by 
nucleases dependent upon Sgs1/Dna2, Exo1 and MRX/Sae2 
(Gravel et al, 2008; Zhu et al, 2008; Mimitou and Symington, 
2009). Other work recently published from our laboratory 
demonstrates that Sgs1 also contributes to resection of 
uncapped telomeres, but elimination of Sgs1 and Exo1 is 
insufficient to prevent the resection of uncapped telomeres 
in cdc13-1 mutants (Ngo and Lydall, 2010). The work pres-
ented here demonstrates that elimination of Pif1 and Exo1 
prevents resection of uncapped telomeres in cdc13-1 mutants. 
However, at DSBs that can be repaired by homologous 
recombination or at DSB-induced shortened telomeres, Pif1 
has little effect on resection (Zhu et al, 2008; Bonetti et al, 
2009). Interestingly, Pif1 has been shown to have a critical 
role repair of DSBs where break-induced replication (BIR) 
is the main repair pathway (Chung et al, 2010). A major 
challenge will be to determine which substrates are exposed 
at DSBs, shortened telomeres and uncapped telomeres and 
how nuclease activities are coordinated to process them. 
Pif1 contributes to the vitality of cells lacking telomerase, 
both before and after recovery from senescence (Figure 5B). 
Interestingly, pif1D cells improve their growth following 
senescence without adopting typical survivor-like telomeric 
DNA structures (Figure 5C). Usually following senescence, 
survivors are generated by homologous-recombination-and 
BIR-dependent alterations in telomere structure (Teng and 
Zakian, 1999; Lydeard et al, 2007). If BIR is eliminated, cells 
lacking telomerase senesce and undergo a complete loss in 
viability (Lydeard et al, 2007). The relatively unaltered 
telomere structure and poor growth following senescence in 
cells lacking Pif1 and telomerase is consistent with the 
impaired BIR seen in cells lacking Pif1 (Chung et al, 2010). 
Therefore, reduced BIR in pif1D cells may be sufficient to </p>

<p>TGGTGGTGGTGG 
ACCACCACCACCACCACCACCACC </p>

<p>3′ 
5′ </p>

<p>3′ 
5′ 
ACCACCACCACC </p>

<p>TGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGG 
3′ 
5′ </p>

<p>3′ 
5′ </p>

<p>ACCACCACC </p>

<p>TGGTGGTG 
GGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGG 
3′ 
5′ </p>

<p>3′ 
5′ </p>

<p>Exo1 </p>

<p>ACCACCACC </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>5′ </p>

<p>3′ </p>

<p>3′ </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>ssDNA 
Endonuclease </p>

<p>TGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGGTGG </p>

<p>AC 
AATTGGGGACAGACTCAAGATTGGTGGA 
TGA </p>

<p>3′ 
5′ </p>

<p>3′ 
5′ </p>

<p>A 
C 
C 
A 
C 
C </p>

<p>Exo1-dependent, weaker checkpoint activation 
Pif1-dependent, weaker checkpoint activation </p>

<p>Exo1-dependent, stronger checkpoint activation </p>

<p>Exposed 5′ (AC) ssDNA? 
Exposed 3′ (TG) ssDNA </p>

<p>Terminal overhangs? 
Stalled replication forks? </p>

<p>Okazaki fragments? 
Stalled replication forks? </p>

<p>0 -5 kb </p>

<p>5 -30 kb </p>

<p>Pif1 </p>

<p>Figure 8 A model for the roles of Pif1 and Exo1 in the DDR at uncapped telomeres. Following telomere uncapping, 5 
0 and 3 
0 ssDNA is exposed 
within 5 kb of the chromosome end, serving as a substrate for resection. 5 
0 ssDNA is unwound by Pif1 and presumably cleaved by an 
unidentified ssDNA endonuclease, whereas the junction between 3 
0 ssDNA and dsDNA is recognized and resected by the exonuclease Exo1. 
This low-level processing leads to weak checkpoint activation. Resection of 3 
0 ssDNA overhangs beyond 5 kb requires Exo1. This further 
processing causes robust checkpoint activation. </p>

<p>Pif1 and Exo1 resect uncapped telomeres 
JM Dewar and D Lydall </p>

<p>&amp; 2010 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 29 | NO 23 | 2010 4031 </p>

<p>maintain comparatively normal telomere structure in telo-
merase-deficient cells but insufficient to permit the typical 
amplification of Y 
0 elements or terminal TG repeats seen in 
survivors. The absence of telomeric repeat amplification 
could prevent these cells from achieving the high levels of 
post-senescence growth seen in other telomerase-deficient 
mutants. 
We have demonstrated that attenuation of the DDR at 
uncapped telomeres, by elimination of Pif1 and Exo1 permits 
telomere maintenance in a Cdc13-indpendent but telomerase 
and Ku-dependent manner. This is surprising because Cdc13 
is considered crucial for efficient recruitment of telomerase 
and thus to prevent senescence (Nugent et al, 1996). We 
propose that in the absence of Cdc13, Yku80 binds TLC1, the 
telomerase RNA, to help recruit telomerase to the telomere 
(Peterson et al, 2001). The requirement for Rad52 for the 
survival of cdc13D exo1D pif1D mutants is surprising. It will 
be interesting to investigate whether telomeric repeats from 
extremely long telomeres in cdc13D exo1D pif1D mutants 
(Figure 7B) can be distributed to shorter telomeres by homo-
logous recombination, thus preventing short telomeres from 
becoming critically short. Finally, it will also be paramount to 
determine whether the requirement for telomerase in cdc13D 
exo1D pif1D mutants is a consequence of the increased 
utilization of telomerase that has been reported at the telo-
meres of cells lacking Pif1 (Boule et al, 2005). 
We show that following inactivation of Cdc13 or telomer-
ase, telomeric DNA can be stabilized by elimination of Pif1, 
eliminating resection of uncapped telomeres in cells lacking 
Cdc13 or permitting telomere maintenance without the gen-
eration of typical type I or type II survivor structures in cells 
lacking telomerase. As Pif1 and Exo1 are conserved from 
yeast, to mice, to humans, Pif1 might also contribute to 
the premature mortality caused by telomere dysfunction in 
telomerase knockout mice (Lahaye et al, 1991; Huang and 
Symington, 1993; Wei et al, 2003; Mateyak and Zakian, 2006; 
Snow et al, 2007). pif1 
À/À and exo1 
À/À mice have previously </p>

<p>been examined (Wei et al, 2003; Snow et al, 2007), and 
it might be interesting to combine these mutations in a 
telomerase knockout background to investigate the conse-
quences of telomere dysfunction in pif1 
À/À exo1 
À/À mice, as </p>

<p>EXO1 contributes to the telomere dysfunction and premature 
mortality seen in telomerase knockout mice (Schaetzlein 
et al, 2007). </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Bioinformatics/analysis 
A genetic interaction network was created in Cytoscape using 
S. cerevisiae genetic interactions from BioGRID (v2.0.53) (Stark 
et al, 2006; Cline et al, 2007). Genes that had genetic interactions 
with EXO1 were identified (first neighbours of EXO1). A ranked list 
of all known genes was created, according to how many of the first 
neighbours of EXO1 they had a genetic interaction with. The top 
10% of this ranked list were then shown. Nodes for each gene were 
coloured according to whether the genes affected cdc13-1 growth 
defects or telomere length (Askree et al, 2004; Zubko et al, 2004; 
Downey et al, 2006; Gatbonton et al, 2006; Tsolou and Lydall, 2007; 
Addinall et al, 2008; Ungar et al, 2009). </p>

<p>Yeast strains 
All strains used in this study are RAD5 
þ and in the W303 genetic 
background (Strain Table, Supplementary data). Standard genetic 
procedures of transformation and tetrad analysis were used. New 
gene deletions were constructed by transforming a diploid with </p>

<p>PCR-based deletion modules (Goldstein and McCusker, 1999). Point 
mutations were generated integrated into the genome as described 
(Schulz and Zakian, 1994; Ribeyre et al, 2009). </p>

<p>Yeast growth assays 
Growth assays were performed as previously described (Zubko 
et al, 2004). Pooled colonies were inoculated into 2 ml of YEPD and 
grown to saturation at 231C. Five-fold serial dilutions were 
replicated onto agar plates and grown at a range of temperatures. 
Plates were photographed using an SPimager (S&amp;P Robotics). 
Levels were adjusted with <rs id="software-0" type="software">Photoshop</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">CS4</rs>. </p>

<p>Passage experiments and quantification of growth 
To passage cultures, multiple individual colonies were pooled and 
restruck. Where growth was quantified, unmodified images were 
analysed with Colonyzer (Lawless et al, 2010) and the sum of the 
trimmed greyscale pixel values for all pixels corresponding to spots 
and colonies of each strain were used as a measure of growth. 
Growth was then expressed relative to a TLC1 
þ or TLC1 
þ CDC13 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>strain included on the same plate. </p>

<p>Telomere length detection 
Southern hybridization to examine telomere length and structure 
was performed similarly to previously described (Maringele and 
Lydall, 2004). Genomic DNA was extracted, digested with XhoI then 
run overnight on a 1% agarose gel at 1 V/cm. Southern transfer and 
detection was then performed using DIG-High Prime Labelling and 
Detection Kit (Roche) as per the manufacturer's instructions and 
visualized on a FUJI LAS4000. Telomeric probes were synthesized 
using PCR DIG Probe Synthesis Kit (Roche). TG probe was B180 bp 
of TG repeats, whereas Y 
0 probe was B820 bp of Y 
0 sequence, both 
amplified from pDL987 (pHT128) (Tsubouchi and Ogawa, 2000) 
using oligos m933 and m934 or m935 and m936, respectively. 
CDC15 probe was synthesized using oligos m1045 and m1046 as 
previously described (Foster et al, 2006). </p>

<p>Synchronous cultures, cell cycle scoring and QAOS 
Experiments to measure cell cycle progression and ssDNA following 
telomere uncapping were carried out in bar1D cdc15-2 cdc13-1 cells 
and performed as described (Zubko et al, 2006). Where indicated, 
cells were treated with Bleomycin at a final concentration of 
50 mg/ml (Morin et al, 2008). </p>

<p>Rad53 phosphorylation 
Western blotting to detect Rad53 phosphorylation was performed 
essentially as described (Morin et al, 2008). Antibodies against 
Rad53 were from Dan Durocher, Toronto. Anti-tubulin antibodies 
were from Keith Gull, Oxford. Multiple gels were run to process all 
samples from a single experiment, but were transferred and 
detected in parallel and imaged simultaneously. </p>

<p>In-gel assay 
In-gel assays were performed essentially as previously described 
(Zubko and Lydall, 2006) using a Cy5-labelled oligonucleotide 
(m2188) detected on a GE Healthcare Typhoon Trio imager. 
Following detection of ssDNA, the gel was subjected to Southern 
transfer and hybridization to detect CDC15. To quantify ssDNA, the 
fluorescent signal from the 0.7 to 12 kb range on the gel was 
measured, relative to the intensity of an exponentially dividing 
yku70D mutant on the same gel. All values were then normalized 
relative to the CDC15 signal as determined by Southern blot. </p>

<p>Supplementary data 
Supplementary data are available at The EMBO Journal Online 
(http://www.embojournal.org). </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We gratefully acknowledge the members of our laboratory for input, 
particularly H Ngo and A Greenall and especially for A Leake's 
invaluable assistance. We thank our colleagues in the ONDEX 
project, particularly J Weile. We thank V Zakian, A Nicolas, H 
Tsubouchi, V Geli, D Durocher, A Bianchi and K Gull for providing 
strains, plasmids or antibodies. B Connolly, T Richardson and J 
Brown provided invaluable advice on fluorescent labelling 
of oligonucleotide probes and detection by phosphorimager. </p>

<p>Pif1 and Exo1 resect uncapped telomeres 
JM Dewar and D Lydall </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 29 | NO 23 | 2010 </p>

<p>&amp; 2010 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>





<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest. </p>



<p>Pif1 and Exo1 resect uncapped telomeres 
JM Dewar and D Lydall </p>

<p>&amp; 2010 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 29 | NO 23 | 2010 4033 </p>



<p>Pif1 and Exo1 resect uncapped telomeres 
JM Dewar and D Lydall </p>

<p>The EMBO Journal VOL 29 | NO 23 | 2010 </p>

<p>&amp; 2010 European Molecular Biology Organization </p>



</text></tei>