<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3691566" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Phagocytosis is crucial for triggering host defenses against invading pathogens in animals. However, the 
receptors on phagocyte surface required for phagocytosis of virus have not been extensively explored. This 
study demonstrated that white spot syndrome virus (WSSV), a major pathogen of shrimp, could be engulfed 
but not digested by Drosophila S2 cells, indicating that the virus was not recognized and taken up by a 
pathway that was silent and would not activate the phagosome maturation and digestion pathway. The 
results showed that the activation of receptors on S2 cell surface by lipopolysaccharide or peptidoglycan 
resulted in the phagocytosis of S2 cells against WSSV virions. Gene expression profiles revealed that the 
dally-mediated Wnt signaling pathway was involved in S2 phagocytosis. Further data showed that the Wnt 
signaling pathway played an essential role in phagocytosis. Therefore, our study contributed novel insight 
into the molecular mechanism of phagocytosis in animals. </p>

<p>not digested by S2 cells, leading to the consideration that the virus 
was recognized and engulfed by phagocytes, but phagosome matura-
tion was not occurring in S2 cells against WSSV virions. The results 
further revealed that the dally-receptor-mediated Wnt signaling 
pathway played an essential role in phagocytosis in Drosophila. </p>

<p>Results 
Requirement of specific receptors on phagocyte surface to trigger 
phagocytosis. In order to evaluate the infectivity of WSSV in Dro-
sophila, S2 cells were inoculated with WSSV. To observe the distri-
bution of the virions within the cells, the WSSV-inoculated cells were 
examined using transmission electron microscopy (TEM). The re-
sults showed that the WSSV virions were engulfed and enveloped by 
vesicles for 5 days (Fig. 1A). This phenomenon indicated that WSSV, </p>

<p>as a non-pathogenic virus of Drosophila, could not be digested by S2 
cells which have strong phagocytic activity. Quantitative real-time 
polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) data showed that the viral 
copies did not change in S2 cells at 1-5 days after WSSV inocu-
lation (Fig. S1), suggesting that the WSSV virions were engulfed 
but did not replicate in S2 cells. These findings suggested that 
WSSV could be recognized and engulfed by S2 cells but not 
digested/degraded and this virus was not infectious since it could 
not replicate inside S2 cells and trigger its release from these S2 
cells to further propagate and infect other cells. 
Pathogenic and non-pathogenic bacteria (Escherichia coli and 
Shewanella xiamenensis, respectively) as well as pathogenic and non-
pathogenic viruses (Drosophila C virus [DCV] and WSSV, respect-
ively) were used to evaluate whether pathogenic and non-pathogenic </p>

<p>Figure 1 | The phagocytosis of microbes by Drosophila S2 cells. (A) The white spot syndrome virus (WSSV) virions in S2 cells. The S2 cells were </p>

<p>inoculated with WSSV. At 5 d post-inoculation, the S2 cells were examined using transmission electron microscopy (TEM) (right). The box indicated the 
enlarged WSSV virions in a vesicle. The S2 cells without WSSV were used as a control. Scale bar: control, 2 mm; WSSV, 1 mm. (B) The phagocytosis of 
microbes by S2 cells using TEM. Pathogenic and non-pathogenic bacteria (Escherichia coli and Shewanella xiamenensis) as well as pathogenic and non-
pathogenic viruses (DCV and WSSV) were inactivated and then inoculated into S2 cells for the phagocytosis assays. Non-inactivated WSSV [WSSV 
(live)] was included in the inoculation as a control. The S2 cells were examined at different time points after inoculation using TEM. The boxes showed 
enlarged images. The numbers indicated the time after inoculation. Scale bar, 1 mm. (C) S2 phagocytosis of microbes under confocal microscopy (1003). 
Inactivated pathogenic and non-pathogenic bacteria or viruses as well as the non-inactivated WSSV were labeled with fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC). 
The S2 cells were then inoculated with the FITC-labeled microbes. The lane headings showed the microbes used. At 15 min and 24 hr after inoculation, 
the S2 cells were fixed and stained with rhodamine phalloidin to label the actin (red) and with 49,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole to label the DNA (blue), 
followed by examination using confocal microscopy. The FITC-labeled microbes (green) were indicated with arrows. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 2069 | DOI: 10.1038/srep02069 </p>

<p>
bacteria and viruses could elicit the same innate immune response 
and phagocytic response. The inactivated bacteria, inactivated 
viruses and non-inactivated WSSV [WSSV (live)] were inoculated 
into S2 cells for the phagocytosis assays. The TEM results showed 
that the inactivated E. coli and S. xiamenensis were engulfed in S2 
cells at 1 hr after inoculation (Fig. 1B). At day 1 after inoculation, 
they were completely digested in the S2 cells (Fig. 1B). Because E. coli </p>

<p>is a pathogenic bacterium of D. melanogaster, lipopolysaccharide 
(LPS) located on the outer membrane of E. coli can activate the 
Imd pathway via Drosophila peptidoglycan recognition protein LC 
(PGRP-LC), leading to the activation of phagocytes. Peptidoglycan 
(PG), which is distributed on the outer membrane of S. xiamenensis, 
a non-pathogenic bacterium of D. melanogaster, can initiate the Toll 
pathway via PGRP-SA (SD) and Gram-negative bacteria binding </p>

<p>Figure 2 | LPS and PG -induced S2 phagocytosis of WSSV. (A) The phagocytic process of fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC)-labeled microbes under </p>

<p>confocal microscopy (4003). The FITC-labeled inactivated Escherichia coli or non-inactivated WSSV virions [WSSV (live)] were inoculated into S2 cells. 
LPS or PG was included in the inoculation to activate the receptors recognizing LPS or PG. The cells were fixed at different time points after inoculation. 
The cells were then stained with rhodamine phalloidin to label the actin and with DAPI to label the DNA. The numbers indicated the examined time 
points. (B) Phagocytosis of pHrodo-labeled microbes under confocal microscopy. The pHrodo-labeled inactivated E. coli, inactivated WSSV, or WSSV 
(live) were inoculated into S2 cells. LPS or PG was simultaneously inoculated. At 1 hr after inoculation, the cells were examined using confocal 
microscopy (up, 1003). The red fluorescence inside the S2 cells represented the phagolysosome acidification. The images were enlarged (down, 4003). 
(C) S2 phagocytosis percentages of the pHrodo-labeled microbes. The number of S2 cells phagocytosing the pHrodo-labeled microbes was quantified 
using flow cytometry at 1 hr after microbial inoculation. Non-treated S2 cells were used as a control. Statistically significant differences between 
treatments were indicated with asterisks (** P , 0.01). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 2069 | DOI: 10.1038/srep02069 </p>

<p>
protein 1 (GNBP-1), resulting in the activation of S2 phagocytosis. 
These data suggested that both the pathogenic and the non-patho-
genic bacteria could be digested by S2 cells. It was shown that both 
the inactivated pathogenic virus (DCV) and non-pathogenic virus 
(WSSV) were engulfed and subsequently digested in S2 cells 
(Fig. 1B), yielding the same results as those of the pathogenic and 
non-pathogenic bacteria. However, the non-inactivated WSSV 
[WSSV (live)] was engulfed but not digested by S2 cells even at 5 
days after the WSSV incubation (Fig. 1B). 
Phagocytosis of these bacteria and viruses was examined by con-
focal microscopy to further confirm the TEM results. The results 
demonstrated that the inactivated pathogenic or non-pathogenic 
bacteria and viruses were observed in S2 cells at 15 min after inocu-
lation and then digested by S2 cells at 24 hr after inoculation 
(Fig. 1C). However, the non-activated WSSV [WSSV (live)] could 
not be digested by S2 cells at all examined time points (Fig. 1C). The 
results were the same as those of TEM. This demonstrated that the 
virus itself was capable of subverting the host cell immune system to 
prevent its targeting to phagosome-lysosome degradation via mat-
uration of the phagosome. </p>

<p>Initiation of phagocytosis by receptors recognizing LPS or PG. 
The time course results showed that the inactivated E. coli was 
engulfed by S2 cells at 15-60 min after inoculation and then 
digested in 24 hr after inoculation (Fig. 2A). On the other hand, 
the non-inactivated WSSV virions [WSSV (live)] were also 
engulfed but not digested by S2 cells and the virions could not 
replicate and escape S2 cells to infect other cells, thereby being 
non-infectious (Fig. 2A). To activate the immune system by 
stimulating the Imd and Toll pathways using LPS and PG, the S2 
cells were treated with LPS or PG for 1 hr followed by WSSV 
inoculation. The results showed that the LPS-or PG-activated S2 
cells could engulf and subsequently digest the WSSV virions 
(Fig. 2A), indicating that the activation of the Imd or Toll 
pathways could promote the degradation of the live WSSV 
presumably by restoring phagosome maturation. 
During maturation, the phagosome fuses with the lysosomes 
resulting in its acidification which allows for the digestion of engulfed 
particles. A pH-sensitive dye, pHrodo can be used to label bacteria 
and monitor their engulfment in a fully mature phagosome simply by 
examining whether these pHrodo-labeled bacteria fluoresce when 
found in this acidified environment. To investigate the phagocytosis 
of WSSV by LPS-or PG-activated S2 cells, non-activated (live) 
WSSV virions were labeled with pHrodo and examined by confocal 
microscopy. The results indicated that inactivated E. coli and WSSV 
were engulfed by S2 cells into an acidified mature phagosome at one 
hour after inoculation, whereas the non-inactivated WSSV virions 
could not induce the phagolysosome acidification (Fig. 2B). When 
the S2 cells were pretreated with LPS or PG activating the Imd or Toll 
pathway, respectively, live WSSV was taken up by S2 cells into a fully 
mature phagosome (Fig. 2B) at one hour after inoculation, showing 
that the engulfed non-inactivated WSSV virions were digested/ 
degraded into fully mature acidified phagosome. 
To evaluate the effects of LPS or PG receptor activation on pha-
gocytosis, the phagocytic percentage of LPS-or PG-activated S2 cells 
against the pHrodo-labeled WSSV was characterized. The data 
showed that the phagocytic percentage of LPS-or PG-activated S2 
cells was significantly increased (P , 0.01) compared with the con-
trol at 1 hr after WSSV inoculation (Fig. 2C). S2 cells inoculated with 
the pHrodo-labeled inactivated WSSV or inactivated E. coli yielded 
similar phagocytosis results (Fig. 2C). However, the percentage of 
phagocytic S2 cells inoculated with the non-inactivated WSSV vir-
ions (live WSSV) only was very low, which was similar to that of the 
control. The results suggested that activation of the LPS-or PG-
induced Imd and Toll pathways favored the uptake of live WSSV </p>

<p>through a phagocytic pathway that allowed for the uptake and diges-
tion of this virus into a fully matured phagosome. </p>

<p>Identification of the signaling pathways required for phagocy-
tosis. To assess effects of the pathogenic DCV and non-pathogenic 
WSSV on the gene expressions of S2 cells, the gene expression 
profiles of S2 cells treated with DCV and WSSV were charac-
terized using the GeneChip Drosophila Genome 2.0 Array. The 
array analysis showed that the gene expression profiles of S2 cells 
treated with inactivated or non-inactivated DCV or WSSV differed 
largely from those of the control (non-treated S2 cells) (Fig. 3a). 
Compared with the control, 802, 737, 524, and 877 genes were 
altered by at least two fold for inactivated DCV, non-inactivated 
DCV [DCV (live)], inactivated WSSV, and non-inactivated WSSV 
[WSSV (live)], respectively (Fig. 3a). The results showed that 626 
genes (250 up-regulated genes and 376 down-regulated genes) in S2 
cells treated with inactivated or non-inactivated DCV had the same 
gene expression patterns, indicating that infection and phagocytosis 
of the pathogenic virus might share many same or similar pathways. 
However, the gene expression profiles of S2 cells treated with 
inactivated or non-inactivated WSSV differed largely (Fig. 3a), 
suggesting that the live non-pathogenic virus activated different 
pathways than the non-pathogenic inactivated virus. The results 
were consistent with the TEM and confocal microscopy findings. 
In order to identify the pathways being activated in S2 cells in 
response to inactivated and non-inactivated DCV, and inactivated 
and non-inactivated WSSV, the DNA microarray data were further 
analyzed. The results showed that 120 genes shared the same express-
ion profiles (up-regulation or down-regulation) in three treatments 
[inactivated DCV, DCV (live), and inactivated WSSV] but not in 
WSSV(live) treatment, suggesting that these genes were required for 
phagosome maturation and digestion of inactivated and live DCVs 
and inactivated WSSVs. Among these genes, 53 genes were up-regu-
lated and 67 genes were down-regulated. The analysis showed that 
the 120 genes participated in diverse biological processes including 
defense responses, signal transduction, cytoskeleton regulation, ves-
icle transport, apoptosis, and proteolysis (Fig. 3b). 
These down-regulated and up-regulated genes were further ana-
lyzed to investigate the cell receptors and receptor-mediated path-
ways involved in phagocytosis. Gene ontology and KEGG analysis 
revealed that the dally (division abnormally delayed) receptor and 
its corresponding Wnt pathway was involved in phagocytosis 
(Fig. 3C). The results showed that dally receptor, located on the cell 
surface, could interact with eight proteins including amphiphysin 
(Amph), glutactin (Glt), inscuteable (insc), pericardin (prc), heart-
less (htl), matrix metalloproteinase 1 (Mmp1), frizzled 2 (fz2) and 
disheveled associated activator of morphogenesis (DAAM) (Fig. 3c). 
Among the eight proteins, fz2 and DAAM were the components of 
the Wnt signaling pathway. We found that DAAM interacted with 
myosin 31DF (Myo31DF), a cytoskeletal protein that demonstrated 
actin binding and motor activities. These data suggested that the 
Wnt pathway may be involved in phagosome maturation (Fig. 3d). 
The analysis showed that Amph (required in endocytosis of synaptic 
vesicles and vesicle fission), Glt (acidic sulphated glycoprotein of 
basement membrane), and insc (a cytoskeletal adaptor) could inter-
act with the dally receptor (Fig. 3c). In this context, the interaction 
between the dally receptor and Amph, Glt, or insc led to the sug-
gestion that the dally receptor played a key role in phagosome 
maturation through regulating cytoskeletal organization (Fig. 3d). 
The findings indicated that prc, htl, and Mmp1 might be related to 
phagosome maturation, but the corresponding pathways mediated 
by the three proteins were unknown. Taken together, the results 
suggested that the dally receptors on the cell surface might me-
diate Wnt signaling pathway that was involved in phagosome 
maturation. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 2069 | DOI: 10.1038/srep02069 </p>

<p>
Figure 3 | Receptors and signaling pathways required for phagocytosis of virus. (a) The gene expression profiles of Drosophila genes in response to virus. </p>

<p>The gene expression profiles were conducted with a DNA microarray using S2 cells treated with inactivated Drosophila C virus (DCV) or white spot 
syndrome virus (WSSV) and non-inactivated DCV [DCV (live)] or WSSV [WSSV (live)] (up). Non-treated S2 cells were used as a control. Red indicated 
the up-regulation and green showed the down-regulation. The differentially expressed genes were evaluated (down). The numbers represented the genes 
up-regulated or down-regulated (more than twofold) compared with the control. (b) The biological processes mediated by the differentially expressed 
genes. (c) The gene network of the dally mediated pathways. The green and blue lines indicated the GenMAPP and KEGG databases, respectively. The 
numbers indicated the times that two genes occurred in a pathway. (d) The model of the dally mediated pathways in phagocytosis. The dally receptor was 
distributed on the cell membrane. The solid lines showed the known interactions or pathways. The dashed lines indicated the unknown interactions or 
pathways. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 2069 | DOI: 10.1038/srep02069 </p>

<p>
Figure 4 | Roles of the dally-mediated pathways in phagocytosis. (A) The expression profiles of genes belonging to the dally-mediated pathways in S2 cells </p>

<p>in response to LPS or PG challenge. The rp49 gene was used as a control. Statistically significant differences between treatments were indicated with asterisks 
(** P , 0.01). Control, non-treated S2 cells. (B) The expression profiles of other genes belonging to the Wnt pathways in S2 cells in response to LPS or PG 
challenge. (C) Effects of dally gene silencing on gene expressions of the Wnt pathway. To evaluate the involvement of dally in phagocytosis, expression of the 
dally gene in S2 cells was silenced using sequence-specific siRNA. The expression profiles of the genes related to the dally-mediated pathways were then 
examined using quantitative RT-PCR. The rp49 gene was used as a control. Statistically significant differences between treatments were indicated with 
asterisks (*P , 0.01 or **P , 0.01). Control, non-treated S2 cells. (D) Effects of dally gene silencing on expressions of genes belonging to the dally-mediated 
pathways. (E) Percentages of S2 phagocytosis against the pHrodo-labeled WSSV virions. The number of S2 cells phagocytosing the pHrodo-labeled WSSV 
virions was quantified using flow cytometry at 1 hr after virus inoculation. The inactivated WSSV (WSSV) and non-inactivated WSSV [WSSV (live)] were 
included in the experiments. Non-treated S2 cell was used as a control. Statistically significant differences between treatments were indicated with asterisks 
(** P , 0.01). (F) The model of the dally-mediated pathways involved in phagocytosis. The Wnt pathway was shown in the box. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 2069 | DOI: 10.1038/srep02069 </p>

<p>
Roles of the dally-mediated Wnt pathway in phagocytosis. In order 
to evaluate the roles of the dally-mediated pathways in phagocytosis, 
we examined the expression profiles of eight genes (Amph, Glt, insc, 
prc, htl, Mmp1, fz2, and DAAM) encoding proteins that interacted 
with dally, as well as dally and Myo31DF, using S2 cells in response to 
LPS or PG stimulation. The quantitative RT-PCR results indicated 
that the expressions of dally, Amph, Glt, prc, htl, fz2, DAAM, and 
Myo31DF were very significantly up-regulated (P , 0.01) compared 
to that of the control gene rp49 after LPS or PG stimulation (Fig. 4A). 
The results showed that the dally-mediated pathways (Fig. 3d) were 
involved in phagosome maturation. However, the expression profiles 
of insc and Mmp1 did not change after LPS or PG stimulation 
(Fig. 4A). Of the dally-mediated pathways (Fig. 3d), fz2 and 
DAAM belong to the Wnt pathway. To characterize the role of 
Wnt pathway in phagosome maturation, we detected the gene 
expression profiles of the Wnt pathway in response to LPS or PG 
stimulation. The results indicated that dally, wnt2, fz2, dsh, DAAM, 
sgg, and arm were very significantly up-regulated (P , 0.01) after 
LPS or PG stimulation (Fig. 4A and B). The data suggested that the 
Wnt pathway may take great effects on phagosome maturation. 
To further evaluate the role of dally in phagosome maturation, 
the dally gene was silenced using sequence-specific siRNA in S2 
cells. We investigated the expression levels of wnt2, fz2, dsh, 
DAAM, sgg, and arm to reveal the effects of dally gene silencing 
on the expression of genes belonging to the Wnt pathway. The 
results showed that dsh and arm were very significantly down-
regulated (P , 0.01) whereas sgg and wnt2 were very significantly 
up-regulated (P , 0.01) when dally was knocked down (Fig. 4C). 
The silencing of dally gene expression led to up-regulation or 
down-regulation of seven genes (Amph, Glt, prc, htl, fz2, 
DAAM, and Myo31DF) that were involved in dally-mediated path-
ways (Fig. 4D). However, insc and Mmp1 gene expressions were 
not affected largely. The data were consistent with the quantitative 
RT-PCR results. We found that Amph, prc, fz2, and Myo31DF 
were significantly up-regulated (P , 0.05) whereas Glt, htl, and 
DAAM were significantly down-regulated (P , 0.05) when dally 
was knocked down (Fig. 4D). The results showed that the pha-
gocytic percentage of pHrodo-labeled inactivated WSSV in dally-
siRNA-treated S2 cells was significantly decreased (P , 0.01) com-
pared with that of the control at 1 hr after inoculation (Fig. 4E). 
LPS and PG could induce the uptake and digestion of live WSSV 
into a fully matured phagosome (Fig. 4E). The silencing of dally 
expression significantly inhibited the phagosome maturation pro-
cess. These findings suggested that the dally-mediated Wnt path-
way might be essential for phagocytosis (Fig. 4F). </p>

<p>Discussion 
Widespread evidence indicates that phagocytosis, an actin-depend-
ent process involving the internalization of bacteria and viruses, 
represents an essential branch of the immune system of organ-
isms 2,23 . The phagocytic process begins with particle recognition 
and binding with receptors on host cell surface, leading to the engulf-
ment of particles into cell and subsequent formation of phagosomes 
to initiate the digestion of microbes. Phagocyte-microbe contact is 
accompanied by intracellular signals that trigger diverse cellular pro-
cesses such as cytoskeletal rearrangement, alterations in membrane 
trafficking, and activation of microbial killing mechanisms 24 . It is 
believed that the engulfment of particles into cell represents the 
initiation of phagocysotis. In this study, the results showed that 
the non-pathogenic WSSV could be engulfed by phagocytes (S2 
cells), but the WSSV virions were not digested in S2 cells, suggesting 
that the phagosome maturation might not occur. The findings indi-
cated that the engulfed particles could be digested by phagocytes 
when the phagosome maturation was induced. Now that the engulf-
ment of particles by phagocytes does not represent triggering the 
digestion of engulfed particles, the strategy used for the evaluation of </p>

<p>phagocytosis with fluorescently labeled latex beads 25-27 needs to be 
improved. The fluorescently labeled latex beads may be used to 
assess the ability of phagocyte engulfment only. If they are used 
for examining the phagocytic activity of phagocytes, the beads can 
be coated with LPS or PG to induce the phagosome maturation 
leading to digestion/degradation of particles. 
Our study demonstrated that the non-pathogenic virus WSSV 
would not be completely digested by phagocytes, although the 
WSSV virions were engulfed into S2 cells. Recently this similar phe-
nomenon was observed in Ehrlichia chaffeensis, a member of the 
order Rickettsiales. It was found that Drosophila S2 cells were per-
missive for the growth of E. chaffeensis, and the cells could comple-
tely digested E. chaffeensis after LPS stimulation 23 . It is well 
documented that the recognition of bacterial and fungal pathogens 
by receptors on cell surface leads to activations of the Toll and Imd 
pathways in invertebrates 16,17,21 . Lipopolysaccharide (LPS), a major 
component of the outer membranes of gram-negative bacteria, is one 
of the most powerful activators of macrophages via the Imd pathway, 
while peptidoglycan (PG), a major component of gram-positive bac-
terial cell walls, can activate macrophages via the Toll pathway 28,29 . 
Recent studies show that some microbes can be engulfed but not 
digested by the phagocytes of mammals and insects 20,30 . These find-
ings suggest that some receptors, except for the known receptors, are 
essential for phagocytosing intracellular pathogens efficiently by host 
phagocytes. The present and previous studies show that activation of 
the LPS-or PG-induced Imd and Toll pathways favor the uptake and 
digestion of microbes into a fully matured phagosome 31,32 . Up to date, 
the well-documented receptor for phagocytosis is Fc receptor in 
vertebrates 32 . In this context, there must be some unrevealed recep-
tors on invertebrate phagocyte surface to trigger the phagocytosis 
response, which may be comparable to the Fc receptor. In this study, 
based on the genome-wide microarray analysis of Drosophila, the 
results showed that the dally-mediated Wnt signaling pathway 
played important roles in phagocytosis. As reported, the Wnt path-
way is highly conserved between flies and humans despite the evolu-
tionary distance between the species 33 . The Wnt family of signaling 
proteins participates in multiple developmental events during 
embryogenesis, and Wnt signals are pleiotropic, with effects that 
include mitogenic stimulation, cell fate specification, and differenti-
ation 34,35 . Recently, it is found that the Wnt-induced endocytosis can 
initiate synapse formation and endosomes may constitute a crucial 
signaling organelle 36-38 . In our study, the results indicated that the 
dally-mediated Wnt pathway took effects on phagocytosis. This find-
ing contributed a novel aspect of Wnt pathway in immune responses 
of animals, and the dally-mediated pathways in phagocytosis merited 
to be further investigated. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Shrimp culture, WSSV purification and WSSV inoculation in drosophila S2 cells. 
Cultures of Marsupenaeus japonicus shrimp, approximately 10 g and 10-12 cm each, 
were performed keeping in groups of 20 individuals in 80 L aquariums at 20uC. Then 
the virus-free shrimp were infected with WSSV. The WSSV-infected shrimp were 
collected and homogenized for virus purification according to the previous 
methods 39 . For quantitative analysis of viral DNA, the real-time PCR was conducted 
as described before 40 . The WSSV virions were UV-inactivated by exposure to a total of 
12,000 mJ UV light (5 3 3 min). Subsequently the WSSV virions (1 3 10 7 copies/ 
mL) or inactivated WSSV virions (1 3 10 7 copies/mL) were inoculated in Drosophila 
S2 cells (1 3 10 6 cells/mL) for culture at 28uC, respectively. At different time, the S2 
cells were collected and subjected to transmission electron microscopy, confocal 
microscopy, DNA microarray and quantitative real-time PCR analyses. </p>

<p>Maintenance of drosophila S2 cell Line and drosophila C virus (DCV) purification 
and infection. Drosophila S2 cells were cultivated at 28uC in Schneider's Drosophila 
medium (Ivitrogen, USA) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (Gibco, USA). 
DCV was inoculated in S2 cells at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 1 for 5 days and 
collected for purification as described before 1 . DCV at a multiplicity of infection 
(MOI) of 1 was UV-inactivated by exposure to a total of 12,000 mJ UV light (5 3 
3 min) as inactivated virus. Then S2 cells were inoculated with UV-inactivated DCV. 
At different time, the S2 cells were collected and subjected to transmission electron </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 2069 | DOI: 10.1038/srep02069 </p>

<p>
microscopy, confocal microscopy, DNA microarray and quantitative real-time PCR 
analyses. </p>

<p>Culture of bacteria and bacterial inoculation in S2 cells. Escherichia coli DH5a 
strain was grown in Luria-Bertani (LB) medium at 37uC for 24 hr and collected by 
centrifugation at 10,000 3 g for 10 min. Shewanella xiamenensis strain S4 T was 
obtained from a sediment sample that was collected from a coastal area of Xiamen, 
China 41 . The strain was grown in LB medium at 30uC for 24 hr and collected by 
centrifugation at 10,000 3 g for 10 min. E. coli and S. xiamenensis were inactivated at 
80uC for 1 hr, respectively. Then S2 cells were inoculate with inactivated bacteria 
(heat-inactivated E. coli or S. xiamenensis) at a density of 5 3 10 6 /mL and incubated 
for 1 hr at 28uC. At different time, the S2 cells were collected for analysis. </p>

<p>Activation of S2 phagocytosis with lipopolysaccharide (LPS) or peptidoglycan 
(PG). To determine whether the activation of receptors recognizing LPS or PG on S2 
cell surface could initiate the phagocytosis of WSSV, the S2 cells were plated at a 
concentration of 1 3 10 6 cells well in six-well plates and were allowed to adhere for at 
least 30 min. The LPS or PG (Sigma, USA) was sonicated for 1 hr and then added to 
S2 cells at a concentration of 10 mg per ml. After incubation with LPS or PG for 1 hr, 
the S2 cells were inoculated with the purified WSSV virions for 15 min-1 hour. </p>

<p>Transmission electron microscopy assay. The S2 cells were pelleted and fixed in the 
fixative containing 2% paraformaldehyde and 2% glutaraldehyde in 0.1 M sodium 
cacodylate buffer (pH 7.4) for 18 hr at room temperature. Each sample was washed 
three times with 0.1 M sodium cacodylate buffer at room temperature. Then the 
sample was postfixed with 2% osmium tetroxide in 0.1 M sodium cacodylate buffer 
with constant rotation for 1 hr, followed by washes three times using 0.1 M sodium 
cacodylate buffer at room temperature. The sample was stained with 2% uranyl 
acetate in 0.2 M sodium acetate buffer (pH 5.2) for 1 hr at room temperature and 
subsequently washed three times with 0.2 M sodium acetate buffer at room 
temperature. The sample was dehydrated in an ascending acetone series (50, 60, 70, 
80, 90, 95, and 100%) and then in 100% propylene oxide for 10 min with constant 
rotation at room temperature. After infiltration of sample with EMBED 812/Araldite 
502 resin at room temperature, sections were prepared in a Reichert Ultracut OMU3 
microtome (Leica, Germany) at 100 nm thickness, followed by staining with 2% 
uranyl acetate/70% methanol. The images were collected on a Hitachi 7650 
transmission electron microscope (Hitachi, Japan) operating at 70 kV. </p>

<p>Confocal microscopy analysis. Drosophila S2 cells were plated in 12-well plastic 
tissue culture plate in 1 ml of Schneider's medium with 10% FBS. FITC-labeled 
(Invitrogen, USA) microbes were added to each well containing S2 cells at a density of 
5 3 10 6 , followed by incubation for 1 hr at 28uC. After washes with PBS, the S2 cells 
were transferred to Poly-Prep glass slides (Sigma, USA) and fixed. Then the S2 cells 
were incubated with rhodamine phalloidin (Invitrogen, USA) or DAPI (Sigma, USA) 
to label actin or nucleus DNA, respectively. Fluorescent images were taken with a 
Zeiss Laser scanning systems LSM 510 Meta (Carl Zeiss, Germany) and processed 
using <rs type="software">Zeiss LSM Image</rs> Examiner Version software. </p>

<p>Detection of phagolysosome acidification with pHrodo labeling. The pHrodo dye, 
a novel fluorogenic dye that dramatically increased the fluorescence as the pH of its 
surroundings became more acidic 42 , was used to label E. coli or WSSV using the 
pHrodo phagocytosis particle labeling kit (Invitrogen, USA) according to the 
manufacturer's manual. The unique pHrodo-based system could measure the 
phagocytic activity based on acidification of particles as they were ingested. The S2 
cells (1 3 10 6 ) were inoculated with the pHrodo-labeled inactivated E. coli (5 3 10 6 / 
mL), inactivated WSSV virions (1 3 10 7 copies/mL) or non-inactivated WSSV 
virions (1 3 10 7 copies/mL), respectively. After incubation at 28uC for 1 hr, the S2 
cells were collected and immediately analyzed with confocal microscopy. To activate 
the LPS-or PG-mediated receptors of phagocytosis, the pHrodo-labeled inactivated 
E. coli, inactivated WSSV or non-inactivated WSSV were co-inoculated with LPS or 
PG into S2 cells. The percentages of S2 cells phagocytosed pHrodo-labeled microbes 
were calculated. The differences between different treatments were statistically 
analyzed by t-test assuming unequal variances. A P-value , 0.05 or , 0.01 was 
considered to be significant. </p>

<p>Analyses of gene expressions with oligonucleotide microarray. S2 cells (1 3 10 6 ) 
were inoculated with DCV at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 1 for 1 hr. 
Inactivated DCV was treated in the same way. The WSSV virions (1 3 10 7 copies/ 
mL) or inactivated WSSV virions (1 3 10 7 copies/mL) were inoculated into S2 cells 
(1 3 10 6 cells/mL) for 1 hr. Then total RNA was extracted from treated S2 cells by 
using Trizol reagent (Invitrogen, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
The total RNA samples were then analyzed by CapitalBio Corp for Chip (Affymetrix) 
assay. Gene expression analysis was performed by using the Affymetrix (Santa Clara, 
CA, USA) Drosophila GeneChip, using the laboratory methods in the Affymetrix 
GeneChip expression manual. Gene expression analysis was performed using 
multiple arrays and multiple independent mRNA samples for each treatment. 
Microarray data were analyzed by using Bio MAS (<rs id="software-1" type="software">molecule annotation system</rs>) <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">3.0</rs> 
software (CapitalBio Corporation, Beijing, China). Using the criterion of cutoff 
limitation as a fold change $2 or #0.5 and q-value #5%, differential expression genes 
were screened and clustered. </p>

<p>Biological pathway analysis. Through array analysis, the commonly altered genes 
were screened from DCV, and WSSV treatments. The selected genes were further 
analyzed in the context of Gene Ontology (GO) biological process and Kyoto 
Encyclopaedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) biological pathway. Then the results 
of signaling pathway and protein interaction about these genes were analyzed by <rs id="software-2" type="software">MAS</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">3.0</rs> software. To reveal the functions of predicted target genes, we used the ontology 
classification of genes based on gene annotation and summary information available 
through DAVID (Database for Annotation, Visualization and Integrated Discovery). </p>

<p>RNAi assays in S2 cells. To silence the expression of dally gene, the dally-specific 
siRNA (59-GCGAAAC GAAAUUGUGCUATT-39) was prepared using a Takara T7 
in vitro transcription kit (Takara, Japan) according to the manufacturer's protocol. 
The siRNAs were quantified by Nanodrop 2000 Spectrophotometer (Thermo, USA) 
and stored at 280uC for use. RNAi in S2 cells was performed with Lipofectamine 
RNAi MAX Transfection Reagent (Invitrogen, USA) according to the manufacturer's 
instructions. </p>

<p>Quantitative real-time PCR. Total RNAs were extracted from S2 cells (1 3 10 6 ) using 
Trizol reagent (Invitrogen, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Then 
the total RNA (5 mg) was reversely transcribed to synthesize cDNA in a volume of 
20 mL with reverse transcriptase M-MLV (Takara, Japan). Quantitative real-time 
PCR was performed using gene-specific primers and TaqMan probe (Table S2). 
Relative expression levels of interest genes were calculated as previously described 43 , 
using rp49 as an internal control in S2 cells. Real-time PCR was carried out in a final 
volume of 20 ml, which contained 10 ml Premix Ex Taq (TaKaRa, Japan), 1 ml diluted 
cDNA template, 7.2 ml distilled water, 0.3 ml of each TaqMan probe and 0.4 ml of each 
primer. PCR conditions were as follows, 95uC for 30 seconds, followed by 50 cycles of 
95uC for 5 seconds and 60uC for 30 seconds. Resultant data were analyzed using the 
<rs type="software">iQTM5</rs> software. </p>

<p>WSSV quantitative analysis by TaqMan real-time PCR. TaqMan real-time PCR 
was performed by using a Perfect Real Time premix (Takara, Japan) containing a 
high-performance Taq antibody, Takara Ex Taq HS, for hotstart real-time PCR. 
<rs type="software">Primer 3</rs> software was used to design primers and the TaqMan probe with the WSSV 
whole sequence (GenBank accession no. AF332093). Primers WSSV-RT1 (59-TTGG 
TTTCATGCCCGAGATT-39) and WSSV-RT2 (59-CCTTGGTCAGCCCCTTGA-
39) produced a fragment of 154 bp after amplification. The TaqMan probe was 
synthesized and labeled with the fluorescent dyes 5-carboxyfluorescein (FAM) (59-
FAM-TGCTGCCGTCTCCAA-TAMRA-39). The reaction mixture consisted of 
DNA aliquot, 200 nM of each primer, 100 nM of each TaqMan probe, and 1 3 PCR 
reaction buffer containing DNA polymerase in a final reaction volume of 20 ml. PCR 
amplification was performed for 4 min at 50uC, followed by 45 cycles of 45 s at 95uC, 
45 s at 52uC and 45 s at 72uC. Thermal cycling was performed on an iCycle IQ5 real-
time PCR detection system (Bio-RAD, USA). </p>

<p>Statistics. Statistical significance was determined by Student's t-test (two-tailed 
distribution with a two sample equal variance). P-values of less than 0.05 were 
considered significant and less than 0.01 were considered very significant. </p>

<p> </p>



<p>
Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors are grateful to Jian Hong and Guifeng Xiao (Zhejiang University) for 
transmission electron microscopy and confocal microscopy in the manuscript. This work 
was financially supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (31001127), 
the National Basic Research Program of China (2012CB114403), and Hi-Tech Research 
and Development Program of China (863 program of China) (2012AA092205-2). </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>X.Z. and F.Z. conceived the experiments; F.Z. carried out the experiments; X.Z. and F.Z. 
analyzed the data. All the authors wrote and reviewed the manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Zhu, F. &amp; Zhang, X. The Wnt signaling pathway is involved in the 
regulation of phagocytosis of virus in Drosophila. Sci. Rep. 3, 2069; DOI:10.1038/srep02069 
(2013). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported license. To view a copy of this license, 
visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 2069 | DOI: 10.1038/srep02069 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>