<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3698303" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: We evaluated the performance of three chromogenic media (Brilliance agar 
I [Oxoid, UK], Brilliance agar II [Oxoid], and ChromID MRSA [Biomérieux, France]) com-
bined with broth enrichment and the Xpert MRSA assay for screening of methicillin-resis-
tant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA). </p>

<p>Methods: We obtained 401 pairs of duplicate nasal swabs from 321 patients. One swab 
was suspended overnight in tryptic soy broth; 50-µL aliquots of suspension were inoculated 
on the three chromogenic media. Brilliance agar I and II were examined after 24 hr, and 
ChromID MRSA, after 24 and 48 hr. The paired swab was processed directly using real-
time PCR-based Xpert MRSA assay. </p>

<p>Results: True positives, designated as MRSA growth in any of the culture media, were de-
tected with the prevalence of 17% in our institution. We report the sensitivity, specificity, 
positive predictive value, and negative predictive value of MRSA growth as follows: 92.3%, 
94.0%, 75.9%, and 98.4% in Brilliance agar I (24 hr); 92.7%, 97.9%, 90.0%, and 98.5% in 
Brilliance agar II (24 hr); 95.6%, 95.8%, 82.3%, and 99.1% in ChromID MRSA (24 hr); 
100%, 92.5%, 73.1%, and 100% in ChromID MRSA (48 hr); 92.6%, 96.7%, 85.1%, and 
98.5% in Xpert MRSA assay. The agreement between the enriched culture and Xpert 
MRSA assay was 96.0%. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Three chromogenic culture media combined with enrichment and Xpert 
MRSA assay demonstrated similar capabilities in MRSA detection. The Xpert MRSA assay 
yielded results comparable to those of culture methods, saving 48-72 hr, thus facilitating 
earlier detection of MRSA in healthcare settings. </p>

<p>Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) is one of </p>

<p>the important nosocomial pathogens worldwide [1]. Patients 
carrying MRSA are at a greater risk for developing an S. aureus 
infection, compared with methicillin-susceptible S. aureus </p>

<p>Lee S, et al. 
Comparison of MRSA screening methods </p>



<p>www.annlabmed.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3343/alm.2013.33.4.255 </p>

<p>(MSSA)-colonized or non-colonized patients in the intensive 
care unit (ICU) [2]. Active surveillance and isolation policy have 
been recommended for controlling the spread of MRSA in 
healthcare facilities [3]. In Korea, S. aureus is the second most 
common isolate (16.6%) among hospital isolates, and the meth-
icillin-resistance rate of S. aureus was about 69%, according to 
the 2009 KONSAR study [4]. A timely, affordable, and reliable 
screening method for MRSA is essential to improve hospital in-
fection control, and there is a continued debate about the turn-
around time, cost per test, and cost benefit. 
The Xpert MRSA assay (Cepheid, Sunnyvale, CA, USA) is a 
real-time PCR assay that targets the staphylococcal cassette 
chromosome mec (SCCmec)-orfX junction created by incorpo-
ration of the genetic element carrying mecA into the S. aureus 
chromosome [5, 6]. The assaycan detect, within only 2 hr, 
strains with all SCCmec types, including SCCmec I, II, III, IVa, V, 
and VI found in healthcare-acquired (HA) and community-ac-
quired (CA) MRSA [7, 8]. Currently, various selective and differ-
ential chromogenic media are available that allow direct colony 
color-based identification of the pathogen from the primary cul-
ture 18-24 hr after incubation. However, broth enrichment and 
incubation for 48 hr are necessary to increase the detection 
sensitivity, especially in cases with low bacterial density [9, 10]. 
In this study, we compared the clinical performance of three 
chromogenic media (Brilliance agar I [Oxoid Ltd., Cambridge, 
UK], Brilliance agar II [Oxoid], and ChromID MRSA [Bioméri-
eux, Lyon, France]) combined with broth enrichment and the 
Xpert MRSA assay for MRSA detection by using nasal swabs 
from ICU patients. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>1. Sample collection </p>

<p>This study was performed during March-May 2010. A total of </p>

<p>401 nasal samples were collected consecutively from 321 pa-
tients admitted to the ICU. The screening for MRSA was carried 
out on the first day in the ICU (321 initial samples) and was re-
peated weekly in 55 patients (80 follow-up samples) with pro-
longed hospitalization. The paired swabs (Copan, Brescia, Italy) 
were collected from each nostril of the same patient, respec-
tively. The swab pair was transported at room temperature, and 
each swab was randomly used in the following process within 2 
hr of collection. </p>

<p>2. Culture screening methods </p>

<p>One of the paired swabs was suspended in tryptic soy broth </p>

<p>(TSB) (Becton, Dickinson and Company, Sparks, MD, USA) with </p>

<p>6.5% NaCl; after overnight incubation, 50 µL aliquots of suspen-
sion were inoculated on Brilliance agar I, Brilliance agar II, and 
ChromID MRSA. The two Brilliance agars were incubated for 24 
hr (Brilliance agar I [24 hr] and Brilliance agar II [24 hr], respec-
tively), and they were examined according to the manufacturer's 
recommendation. ChromID MRSA was incubated for 48 hr, and 
it was then examined at 24 and 48 hr (ChromID MRSA [24 hr] 
and ChromID MRSA [48 hr], respectively) by two investigators. 
Potential colonies were captured and identified as S. aureus if 
they tested positive for catalase production and latex agglutina-
tion tests (Eiken Chemical Co., Tokyo, Japan). Methicillin resis-
tance was confirmed by oxacillin (1 µg) (Becton, Dickinson and 
Company) and cefoxitin (30 µg) (Becton, Dicksinson, and Com-
pany) disk diffusion susceptibility tests, according to the Clinical 
and Laboratory Standards Institute guideline [11]. The remain-
ing TSB was frozen at -70˚C for further evaluation. A true-posi-
tive culture was defined as growth with phenotypic features 
compatible with MRSA and was affirmed by confirmatory test-
ing (catalase and latex agglutination tests). A false-positive cul-
ture was defined as growth with phenotypic features compatible 
with MRSA, but was affirmed as non-MRSA by confirmatory 
testing. </p>

<p>3. Xpert MRSA assay </p>

<p>The second swab of the pair was processed directly using the 
GeneXpert system (Cepheid) with Xpert MRSA cartridge (Ce-
pheid) according to the manufacturer's instruction. In brief, the 
swab was placed in the elution reagent (black cap), vortexed at 
high speed for 10 sec, and dispensed into the port "S" of the 
Xpert MRSA cartridge. The cartridge was inserted and subjected 
to real-time PCR in the <rs type="software">GeneXpert</rs> system, and the result was 
reported by the GeneXpert software (Cepheid). If the MRSA 
threshold (CT) value of the sample was ≤ 36, it was positively 
identified as MRSA. </p>

<p>4. Multiplex PCR for SCCmec typing </p>

<p>Staphylococcal cassette chromosome mec (SCCmec) typing 
and subtyping was performed by the multiplex PCR assay [12], 
which was updated to properly identify SCCmec types IV and V 
[13]. </p>

<p>5. Data analysis </p>

<p>A true-positive result, which was used as a reference result, was 
presumed as growth of MRSA in any one of the enriched chro-
mogenic media. The sensitivity (%), specificity (%), positive </p>

<p>Lee S, et al. 
Comparison of MRSA screening methods </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3343/alm.2013.33.4.255 </p>

<p>www.annlabmed.org </p>

<p>predictive value (PPV, %), and negative predictive value (NPV, 
%) of each method was determined. For cases showing dis-
crepant results between Xpert MRSA assay and cultures, both 
tests were repeated using the remaining TSB. 
The CT values between two groups (initial screening samples 
versus follow-up screening samples; concordant samples versus 
discordant samples) were compared using the one-way ANOVA 
test (SPSS 13.0; SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). The threshold for 
statistical significance was a P value &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>1. Comparison of three culture media </p>

<p>MRSA was identified in 68 (68/401, 17.0%) samples in at least 
one of the culture media. The prevalence of MRSA was 13.4% 
(43/321) for initial screening and 31.3% (25/80) for follow-up 
screening samples. The comparison of four screening methods 
is summarized in Table 1. The sensitivity was highest with Chro-
mID MRSA (48 hr) (68/68, 100%), followed by ChromID MRSA 
(24 hr) (65/68, 95.6%), and lowest in both Brilliance agar I (24 
hr) and Brilliance agar II (24 hr) (63/68, 92.6%). The specificity 
and PPV was highest with Brilliance agar II (24 hr) (95.8% and </p>

<p>90.0%, respectively) of all the culture media. NPVs were ≥ 98% 
in all the culture methods. </p>

<p>There were 25, 14, 20, and 7 samples in which growth on 
ChromID MRSA (48 hr), ChromID MRSA (24 hr), Brilliance agar 
I (24 hr), and Brilliance agar II (24 hr), respectively, was initially 
mistaken for MRSA, resulting in false-positive findings. The im-
plicated isolates were mainly Enterococcus spp. (15/25), fol-
lowed by coagulase-negative Staphylococcus (4/25) in ChromID 
MRSA; Bacillus spp. (8/20), followed by coagulase-negative 
Staphylococcus (5/20) and methicillin-susceptible S. aureus 
(4/20) in Brilliance agar I; and methicillin-resistant coagulase-
negative Staphylococcus (4/7) and methicillin-susceptible S. au-
reus (3/7) in Brilliance agar II. </p>

<p>2. Comparison of Xpert MRSA assay with enriched culture </p>

<p>The Xpert MRSA assay showed positive results for 74 samples. 
Moreover, when growth of MRSA on any of the enriched culture 
media was designated as a reference method, the total agree-
ment with the culture was 96.0% (385/401) in the initial analy-
sis. The sensitivity, specificity, PPV, and NPV of the Xpert MRSA 
assay were 92.6%, 96.7%, 85.1%, and 98.5%, respectively (Ta-
ble 1). An "invalid" result was obtained in 0.7% (3/401) sam-
ples, indicating the sample processing control (SPC) did not 
meet the acceptable criteria; invalidity might be caused by in-
adequate processing of MRSA, specimen-associated inhibition 
of the real-time PCR assay, or air bubbles formed in the reac-</p>

<p>Table 1. Comparison of Brilliance agar I, Brilliance agar II, ChromID MRSA, and Xpert MRSA assay for screening of MRSA from 401 nasal 
swabs </p>

<p>Screening method 
Positive* 
Negative 
Sensitivity (%) 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Specificity (%) 
(95% CI) 
PPV (%) 
NPV (%) </p>

<p>Brilliance agar I (24 hr) </p>

<p>Positive 
63 
20 
92.6 
94.0 
75.9 
98.4 </p>

<p>Negative 
5 
313 
(86.4-98.8) 
(91.4-96.5) </p>

<p>Brilliance agar II (24 hr) </p>

<p>Positive 
63 
7 
92.6 
97.9 
90.0 
98.5 </p>

<p>Negative 
5 
326 
(86.4-98.8) 
(96.3-99.4) </p>

<p>ChromID MRSA (24 hr) </p>

<p>Positive 
65 
14 
95.6 
95.8 
82.3 
99.1 </p>

<p>Negative 
3 
319 
(90.7-100) 
(93.6-97.9) </p>

<p>ChromID MRSA (48 hr) </p>

<p>Positive 
68 
25 
100 
92.5 
73.1 
100 </p>

<p>Negative 
0 
308 
(98.9-100) 
(89.6-95.3) </p>

<p>Xpert MRSA assay </p>

<p>Positive 
63 
11 
92.6 
96.7 
85.1 
98.5 </p>

<p>Negative 
5 
322 
(86.4-98.8) 
(94.7-98.6) </p>

<p>*A true positive culture was determined if MRSA was detected in one or more of the three culture media tested, and it was used as a reference culture result. 
Abbreviations: MRSA, Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus; PPV, positive predictive value; NPV, negative predictive value; CI, confidence interval. </p>

<p>Lee S, et al. 
Comparison of MRSA screening methods </p>



<p>www.annlabmed.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3343/alm.2013.33.4.255 </p>

<p>tion tube. 
The discrepant results were observed in 16 samples (5 cul-
ture-positive, PCR-negative; 11 culture-negative, PCR-positive) 
(Table 2). For 5 samples showing culture-positive and PCR-neg-
ative results, the repeated Xpert MRSA assay using remaining 
TSB revealed all positive results and the CT values were variable 
(Table 2). For 11 samples showing culture-negative and PCR-
positive results, the repeated Xpert MRSA assay using the re-
maining TSB revealed negative results for 10 samples. The 
mean CT value of 11 discordant samples with culture-negative 
and PCR-positive results was significantly higher than that of 63 
concordant samples (31.0 vs. 24.6, respectively, P = 0.001). 
However, the mean CT values between initial screening samples 
and follow-up screening samples were similar (25.9 vs. 25.1, re-
spectively, P = 0.597). </p>

<p>3. SCCmec typing of isolates </p>

<p>By re-culturing the remaining frozen TSB from 54 culture-posi-
tive patients, 52 MRSA isolates were obtained. For two TSB sam-
ples, the re-culturing failed. SCCmec type II was the most com-
mon (34/52); it was followed by SCCmec type IV (13/52), SCC-
mec type III variant (3/52), and SCCmec type IV variant (2/52). 
There was no difference in the detection rates of these SCCmec 
types among chromogenic agars and the X-pert MRSA assay. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, three enriched-culture methods showed good 
overall performance for detecting MRSA. In particular, ChromID 
MRSA showed higher sensitivity, but its specificity was lower 
than Brilliance agar II. The detection sensitivity using ChromID 
MRSA increased up to 4.4% (from 95.6% at 24 hr to 100% at 48 
hr) with extended incubation; inversely, the specificity de-
creased to 3.3% (from 95.8% at 24 hr to 92.5% at 48 hr), which 
corresponds to a previous report [10]. The results of Brilliance 
agar II (24 hr) were satisfactory at ≥ 90% with respect to sensi-
tivity, specificity, PPV, and NPV for MRSA detection. ChromID 
MRSA (48 hr) showed the lowest specificity due to false-positive 
growth of Enterococcus spp. and methicillin-resistant coagu-
lase-negative Staphylococci (MRCoNS). In contrast to the previ-
ous report where the MRCoNS and enterococci were the major 
species producing false-positive results on Brilliance agar I [10], 
Bacillus spp. was the major isolate in this study, and this prob-
lem was not observed with Brilliance agar II. 
When the enriched culture was designated as a reference 
method, the sensitivity and specificity of the Xpert MRSA assay 
in this study were 92.6% and 96.7%, respectively, which were 
higher than those in the previous studies with a similar design. 
In one study for the comparison of Xpert MRSA assay with broth-</p>

<p>Table 2. Analysis of 16 samples showing discrepancy between enriched culture and Xpert MRSA assay for MRSA screening </p>

<p>No. 
Initial tests for duplicate nasal swabs 
Repeated tests for the remaining enrichment broth </p>

<p>Enriched culture 
Xpert MRSA assay (CT value) 
Xpert MRSA assay (CT value) 
Culture on BAP 
SCCmec type </p>

<p>1 
Positive 
Negative 
Positive (12.3) 
Positive 
Type II </p>

<p>2 
Positive 
Negative 
Positive (24.5) 
Positive 
Type II </p>

<p>3 
Positive 
Negative 
Positive (24.8) 
Positive 
Type II </p>

<p>4 
Positive 
Negative 
Positive (33.1) 
Positive 
Type IV </p>

<p>5 
Positive 
Negative 
Positive (13.5) 
Positive 
Type IIIv </p>

<p>6 
Negative 
Positive (28.0) 
Negative 
Negative 
Not tested </p>

<p>7 
Negative 
Positive (32.5) 
Negative 
Negative 
Not tested </p>

<p>8 
Negative 
Positive (34.2) 
Negative 
Negative 
Not tested </p>

<p>9 
Negative 
Positive (32.9) 
Positive (29.0) 
Negative 
Not tested </p>

<p>10 
Negative 
Positive (28.3) 
Negative 
Negative 
Not tested </p>

<p>11 
Negative 
Positive (34.9) 
Negative 
Negative 
Not tested </p>

<p>12 
Negative 
Positive (31.1) 
Negative 
Negative 
Not tested </p>

<p>13 
Negative 
Positive (27.1) 
Negative 
Negative 
Not tested </p>

<p>14 
Negative 
Positive (25.3) 
Negative 
Negative 
Not tested </p>

<p>15 
Negative 
Positive (34.8) 
Negative 
Negative 
Not tested </p>

<p>16 
Negative 
Positive (31.7) 
Negative 
Negative 
Not tested </p>

<p>Abbreviations: MRSA, Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus; BAP, blood agar plate; SCCmec, staphylococcal cassette chromosome mec. </p>

<p>Lee S, et al. 
Comparison of MRSA screening methods </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3343/alm.2013.33.4.255 </p>

<p>www.annlabmed.org </p>

<p>enriched MRSA-Select chromogenic agar (Bio-Rad Life Science 
Group, Marnes-La-Coquette, France) with a prevalence of </p>

<p>22.1%, the sensitivity and specificity were 84% and 92%, re-
spectively, for detecting MRSA from a nasal site [8]. In a multi-
center study for the comparison of Xpert MRSA assay with broth-
enriched CHROMagar (Becton, Dickinson and Company) with 
the prevalence of 5.2-44%, the sensitivity and specificity were </p>

<p>86.3% and 94.9%, respectively [6]. The analytical sensitivity 
(limit of detection, LoD) of the Xpert MRSA assay was about 50 
colony-forming units (CFU) per swab, according to the manu-
facturer's instruction. It was also reported by Rossney et al. [8] 
that the LoD of the Xpert MRSA assay was 58 CFU per swab, 
and it was threefold lower but six-fold higher than those of direct 
and enrichment cultures, respectively. The higher specificity in 
this study might be due to the use of three kinds of media and a 
longer incubation time up to 48 hr. The mean CT value of the 
false-positive (culture-negative and PCR-positive) samples was 
significantly higher than that of concordant samples (31.0 vs. </p>

<p>24.6). These findings are in line with the previous studies show-
ing that the discrepancies between the Xpert MRSA assay and 
culture method occurred exclusively when the bacterial density 
was low [9] and agree with the fact that the CT value in the Xpert 
MRSA assay correlates strongly with the bacterial density in the 
samples [9, 14]. The discordance from the five false-negative 
results might be partially explained by the cases with low bacte-
rial density of MRSA in the nostrils or disparity in the specimens 
from two nostrils (Table 2). The reason for the one discrepancy 
of a sample yielding culture-negative and PCR-positive results, 
even in the repeated test using the remaining enrichment TSB, 
might be the fact that SCC elements lacking the functional mecA 
gene can be detected by the Xpert MRSA assay, because it does 
not specifically target the mecA gene [5]. Another explanation 
for the one culture-negative and PCR-positive sample is the lim-
itation in the experimental design for S. aureus strains that may 
require anaerobic incubation [15]. 
There was no difference in the detection rates of SCCmec 
types among chromogenic agars and Xpert MRSA assay. The 
majority of the isolates were SCCmec type II that is known as 
HA-MRSA clone [12], followed by SCCmec type IV that is emerg-
ing as a CA-MRSA clone in Korea [16, 17]. 
In conclusion, the performance of the three chromogenic 
media combined with enriched culture and the Xpert MRSA as-
say was good ( &gt; 92% of both sensitivity and specificity). Nota-
bly, the agreement rate between the Xpert MRSA assay and the 
enriched-culture methods was high (96%) in this study. The 
Xpert MRSA assay could give results comparable to culture </p>

<p>methods within 1 hr. This early detection can help save 48-72 hr, 
and help in prevention and control of MRSA infection in health-
care settings. </p>

<p>Authors' Disclosures of Potential Conflicts of 
Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were re-
ported. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Oxoid and Cepheid for providing chromogenic media 
and Xpert MRSA assay kits, respectively. </p>



<p>Lee S, et al. 
Comparison of MRSA screening methods </p>





</text></tei>