<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3644108" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Physicists have long wondered whether the gravitational interactions between matter and 
antimatter might be different from those between matter and itself. Although there are many 
indirect indications that no such differences exist and that the weak equivalence principle 
holds, there have been no direct, free-fall style, experimental tests of gravity on antimatter. 
Here we describe a novel direct test methodology; we search for a propensity for anti-
hydrogen atoms to fall downward when released from the ALPHA antihydrogen trap. In the 
absence of systematic errors, we can reject ratios of the gravitational to inertial mass of 
antihydrogen 475 at a statistical significance level of 5%; worst-case systematic errors 
increase the minimum rejection ratio to 110. A similar search places somewhat tighter bounds 
on a negative gravitational mass, that is, on antigravity. This methodology, coupled with 
ongoing experimental improvements, should allow us to bound the ratio within the more 
interesting near equivalence regime. </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>here are many compelling experimental and theoretical 
arguments 1-10 that suggest that the gravitational mass of 
antimatter cannot differ from the gravitational or inertial 
mass of normal matter, that is, that the weak equivalence 
principle holds. For instance, one such argument comes from the 
absence of anomalies in Eötvös experiments conducted with 
differing atoms 4 ; the differing number of virtual particle-
antiparticle pairs in such atoms might have caused gravitational 
anomalies to occur. However, all of these arguments are indirect 
and are not universally accepted 11-14 ; they rely on assumptions 
about the gravitational interactions of virtual antimatter, on 
postulates such as CPT invariance, or on other theoretical 
premises. Although these arguments may well be correct, in a 
world in which physicists have only recently discovered that we 
cannot account for most of the matter and energy in the universe, 
it would be presumptuous to categorically assert that the 
gravitational mass of antimatter necessarily equals its inertial 
mass. Moreover, the baryogenesis problem suggests that our 
understanding of antimatter is incomplete; gravitational 
asymmetries have been proposed as an explanation 7,15,16 . (Note 
that ref. 7 ultimately rejected gravity as a solution to the 
baryogenesis problem because of a thermodynamic proof of the 
weak equivalence principle. This proof was later challenged 10 .) 
There have not yet been any direct 14 , free-fall or gravitational 
balance, tests of the gravitational interactions of observable 
matter and antimatter. Direct gravitational experiments with 
non-neutral antimatter, for example, isolated positrons or 
antiprotons, are exceedingly difficult because the electrical 
forces overwhelm the gravitational forces 17 . Employing neutral 
antihydrogen 18-25 or positronium 26 eliminates this complication. 
The AEGIS project 27 at CERN was formed to conduct direct 
experimental tests of gravity on antihydrogen, and is now in its 
final construction phase. A second experiment, GBAR, has 
recently been approved at CERN 28 , and a third experiment was 
proposed at Fermilab 29 . 
This article describes a novel method that yields directly 
measured limits on the ratio of the gravitational to inertial mass 
of antimatter, accomplished essentially by searching for the free 
fall (or rise) of 434 ground-state antihydrogen atoms in the 
ALPHA 30-32 experiment at CERN. Our results set statistical 
bounds on the value of FM g /M, the ratio of the gravitational 
mass M g to the inertial mass M of antihydrogen. (M is assumed 
numerically equal to the mass of hydrogen.) In the absence of 
systematic errors, we find that F must be o75 at a statistical 
significance level of 5%; worst-case systematic errors increase this 
limit to Fo110. A similar search places somewhat tighter bounds 
on a negative F, that is, on antigravity. Refinements of our 
technique, coupled with larger numbers of cold-trapped anti-
atoms, should allow us to bound F more tightly in future 
experiments and approach the |F|E1 regime of widespread 
interest. </p>

<p>Results 
Antihydrogen trapping. ALPHA traps antihydrogen atoms by 
producing and capturing them in a minimum-B trap 33 . These 
traps confine those anti-atoms whose magnetic moment l H is 
aligned such that they are attracted to the minimum in the trap 
magnetic field B, and whose kinetic energy is below the trap well 
depth, m H ð jB j Wall À jB j Centre Þ. In ALPHA (see Fig. 1), this 
magnetic minimum is created by an octupole magnet that 
produces transverse fields of magnitude 1.54 T at the trap wall at 
R Wall ¼ 22.3 mm, and two mirror coils that produce axial fields of 
1 T at their centres. The mirror coil centres are offset by 
±138 mm from the trap centre. (The relative orientation of these 
coils and the trap boundaries are shown in Fig. 1.) These fields are </p>

<p>superimposed on a uniform axial field of 1 T produced by an 
external solenoid 34,35 . 
The general methods by which anti-atoms are captured are 
described in refs 30-32,36; in this article we concentrate only on 
the last phase of the experiments, during which anti-atoms are 
released from the minimum-B trap by turning off the octupole 
and mirror fields. The escaping anti-atoms are then detected 
when they annihilate on the trap wall; a silicon-based annihilation 
vertex imaging detector 37 records the times (binned to 0.1 ms) 
and locations (azimuthal FWHM of 8 mm) of these annihilations. </p>

<p>Annihilation time history on release. The time history of the 
annihilations is critical to our analysis. This history is governed 
by the near-exponential decay of the octupole and mirror fields 
after the magnet turn-off is initiated. The fields decay with time 
constants of B9.5 ms (ref. 38). (Throughout this paper, times t 
are referenced to the initiation of the magnet shutdown.) At 
t ¼ 20 ms, for example, the maximum octupole field is B0.18 T 
and the mirror fields are B0.12 T. The trapping potential depth, 
which was originally B540 mK at t ¼ 0 ms, is reduced to 
B11 mK in the radial direction at t ¼ 20 ms. (Here we use 
kelvin as an energy unit.) Note that the 1 T solenoidal field, which 
is oriented parallel to the trap axis (theẑ direction), is never 
varied. The well depth, which is proportional to the change in the 
magnitude of the total magnetic field as one progresses outwards 
from the trap centre, diminishes more slowly (B80 mK at 20 ms) 
in the axialẑ direction than in the radial direction. This is because 
theẑ-directed mirror fields add linearly to the solenoidal field, 
while thex-andŷ-directed octupole fields add in quadrature to 
this field. Consequently, almost all of our trapped antihydrogen 
escapes radially 31 . 
Previous studies using the ALPHA apparatus have shown that 
the anti-atoms have a distribution in centre-of-mass energy e that 
scales approximately like 
ffiffi 
e 
p 
de below the trapping threshold 31,38 . 
An anti-atom can escape the ever-shallower trap when its energy 
is greater than the trap depth. However, there is no one-to-one </p>

<p>Mirror coils </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>y 
x </p>

<p>Electrodes </p>

<p>Annihilation 
detector </p>

<p>Octupole </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Experimental schematic. A schematic, cut-away diagram of the 
antihydrogen production and trapping region of the ALPHA apparatus, 
showing the relative positions of the cryogenically cooled Penning-
Malmberg trap electrodes, the minimum-B trap octupole and mirror magnet 
coils, and the annihilation detector. The trap wall is on the inner radius of 
the electrodes. Not shown is the solenoid, which makes a uniform field inẑ. 
The components are not drawn to scale. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2787 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1785 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2787 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>correspondence between the escape time of an anti-atom and its 
initial energy because it can take some time for an anti-atom to 
find the 'hole' in the trap potential. Computer simulations of this 
process, described in ref. 38, show that anti-atoms of a given 
initial energy escape over a temporal range of at least 10 ms. The 
simulations discussed in ref. 38 did not include a gravitational 
force; to aid in our interpretation of the current experimental 
data, we extended these simulations to include gravity by the 
addition of a gravitational term to the equation of motion: </p>

<p>M 
d 
2 q </p>

<p>dt 2 ¼ rðl H Á Bðq; tÞÞ À M g gŷ; 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>where q is the centre-of-mass position of the anti-atom, and g is 
the local gravitational acceleration. Previous measurements 39 on 
ALPHA established that the magnitude of the magnetic moment 
l H equals that of hydrogen to the accuracy required in this paper; 
its direction is assumed to adiabatically track the external 
magnetic field. </p>

<p>Simulation studies. To model the experiment, we simulated the 
effects of gravity on an ensemble of ground-state antihydrogen 
atoms randomly selected from the 
ffiffi 
e 
p 
energy distribution 
described above. These anti-atoms are first propagated for 50 ms 
in the full-strength trap fields to effectively randomize their 
positions, and then propagated in the post-shutdown decaying 
fields until they annihilate on the trap wall. The results of a typical 
simulation are shown in Fig. 2 for F ¼ 100, which exaggerates the 
effects of gravity relative to the baseline of F ¼ 1 expected from 
the equivalence principle. As can be seen in Fig. 2, there is a 
tendency for the anti-atoms to annihilate in the bottom half 
(yo0) of the trap. This tendency is pronounced for anti-atoms 
annihilating at later times. This is because, as shown in Fig. 3 and 
in Table 1, the confining potential well associated with the 
magnetic and gravitational forces in equation 1 is most skewed by </p>

<p>gravitational effects late in time when the magnetic restoring 
force is relatively weak, and the remaining particles are those with 
the lowest energy. We note that while the number of late anni-
hilating anti-atoms is dependent on the exact energy distribution 
used to initialize the simulations, the annihilation locations of 
these anti-atoms are not; for the purposes of this paper, the exact 
distribution is unimportant. </p>

<p>Reverse cumulative average analysis. To determine an experi-
mental limit on F, we compare our data set of 434 observed 
antihydrogen annihilation events to computer simulations at 
various F's. Our statistics suffer from the fact that escaping anti-
atoms are most sensitive to gravitational forces at late times, but 
relatively few of the events occur at late times. For example, even 
with the cooling due to the adiabatic expansion that occurs as the 
trap depth is lowered, only 23 anti-atoms out of the 434 anni-
hilate after 20 ms. Moreover, inspection of the simulation data in 
Fig. 2 shows that even when there is a pronounced tendency for 
the anti-atoms to fall down, some still annihilate near the top of 
the trap. To obtain a qualitative understanding of the data, we use 
the reverse cumulative average /y|tS: the average of the y 
positions of all the annihilations that occur at time t or later (see 
Methods). This reverse cumulative average highlights the more 
informative late-time events while still including as many events 
as possible into the average. Figure 4 plots /y|tS for the events 
and the simulations at several values of F. These plots suggest that 
an upper bound on F can be established from the data, at a value 
somewhere between F ¼ 60 and 150. </p>

<p>Monte Carlo analysis. Although the visual approach taken in 
Fig. 4 is striking, a more sophisticated analysis is necessary for a 
quantitative assessment of F. Specifically, our problem is this: 
given our event set of experimental annihilations {(y,t)} Ev , where 
y is the observed position of a given annihilation and t is the time 
of this annihilation, and given a family of similar sets of simulated 
pseudo-annihilations {(y,t)} F at various F, how can we determine </p>

<p>Time (ms) </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 </p>

<p>Annihilation y (mm) </p>

<p>−20 </p>

<p>−10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Annihilation locations. The times and vertical (y) annihilation 
locations (green dots) of 10,000 simulated antihydrogen atoms in the 
decaying magnetic fields, as found by simulations of equation 1 with 
F ¼ 100. Because F ¼ 100 in this simulation, there is a tendency for the anti-
atoms to annihilate in the bottom half (yo0) of the trap, as shown by the 
black solid line, which plots the average annihilation locations binned in 
1 ms intervals. The average was taken by simulating approximately 
900,000 anti-atoms; the green points are the annihilation locations of a 
sub-sample of these simulated anti-atoms. The blue dotted line includes the 
effects of detector azimuthal smearing on the average; the smearing 
reduces the effect of gravity observed in the data. The red circles are the 
annihilation times and locations for 434 real anti-atoms, as measured by 
our particle detector. Also shown (black dashed line) is the average 
annihilation location for B840,000 simulated anti-atoms for F ¼ 1. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>y (mm) </p>

<p>−20 
−10 
0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>Potential (mK) </p>

<p>−3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>10 ms </p>

<p>20 ms </p>

<p>0 ms </p>

<p>30 ms </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Potential well. The potential well, for F ¼ 100, at the indicated 
times and at z ¼ 0. The flat-bottomed appearance of the well at early times 
results from the quadratic addition of the solenoidal field to the r 3 </p>

<p>dependent octupole field. (Here, r is the transverse radius r ¼ 
ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
x 2 þ y 2 
p 
.) </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2787 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1785 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2787 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>which values of F can be excluded with reasonable confidence? In 
other words, which sets {(y,t)} F are unlikely to be compatible with 
{(y,t)} Ev ? (In this paper, the phrase 'pseudo-annihilations' or 
'pseudo-events' always refers to simulation results. The unquali-
fied word 'events' always refers to experimental results.) We make 
this determination with a Monte Carlo analysis based on an 
overall test statistic, that is, a figure-of-merit, F, which is sensitive 
to discrepancies between the real and simulated data. Our choice 
of F is closely related to a Fisher's combined test 40 based on 
Kolmogorov-Smirnov (K-S) 41 statistics. The exact definition of F 
is described in the Methods section. In brief, for every F, we 
calculate the test statistic F Ev for the experimental events. This 
F Ev compares {(y,t)} Ev to a reference distribution compiled from 
a third (B300,000 simulated annihilations) of the simulation data 
set {(y,t)} F . The test statistic F is small when it is likely that the 
434 events could have been drawn from the reference 
distribution, and large when it is unlikely that the events could 
have been so drawn, that is, when there is a significant disparity 
between the distribution of the actual events and the reference 
distribution of the simulated annihilations at the hypothesized F. 
Next, to approximate the sampling distribution for F, we 
distribute the remaining pseudo-annihilations in {(y,t)} F into N 
pseudo-event subsets of 434 points. In total there are about 
900,000 pseudo-events in {(y,t)} F , so N is about 1,400. Each of 
these pseudo-event sets is representative of what we would have 
observed if the ratio of the inertial to the gravitational mass really 
was F. Then, we calculate the set of test statistics {F i;F } for each of 
these pseudo-event sets, and count the number N 4 for which 
F i;F ZF Ev , that is, the number of pseudo-event sets that are less 
compatible with the reference distribution than the actual events. 
From N 4 , we obtain a Monte Carlo estimate of the overall P-
value, P ¼ N 4 /N, for the goodness-of-fit test on the actual data set 
compared with the simulations. The results of this analysis are 
shown in Fig. 5, from which we conclude that F475 is excluded 
at a significance level of 5%. 
A similar Monte Carlo analysis comparing the actual event 
data to F ¼ 1 simulations gives an unsurprising overall P-value of 
0.3. Thus, the event data are not incompatible with F ¼ 1, but we 
cannot conclude that FE1. </p>

<p>Systematic error analysis. In the B800 trapping trials used to 
obtain our 434 point event set, we would expect approximately 
one cosmic ray to be misclassified as an antihydrogen atom 30,32 . 
Thus, cosmic rays are an insignificant source of error in this 
analysis. The cosmic ray background does, however, preclude our 
using annihilation data from times later than 30 ms, as the 
current data rate would not be comfortably above the cosmic rate 
at such late times. </p>

<p>Previously, we calculated 31 that more than 99.5% of 
antihydrogen atoms held longer than 400 ms will have decayed 
to the ground state. The 434 trapped anti-atoms employed in the 
analysis were all held for times longer than this. Thus, we expect 
that virtually all of our anti-atoms are in the ground state, and are 
largely immune to Stark effect/polarization forces that might have 
otherwise overwhelmed the gravitational forces. The largest 
electric fields in our trap during the magnet shutdown phase 
come from the 'bias' potential that we use to discriminate 
between antihydrogen atoms and antiprotons 30,31,38 and exist in </p>

<p>Table 1 | Trap depths. </p>

<p>Energy (mK) 
Condition 
Minimum-B trap depth (without 
540 
0 ms 
gravitational effects) 
100 
10 ms 
11 
20 ms 
1.2 
30 ms 
Gravitational 
0.053 
F ¼ 1 
Potential energy 
5.3 
F ¼ 100 
Polarization 
2.7 Â 10 À 7 
Gap 10 V mm À 1 
Potential energy 
2.7 Â 10 À 9 
Patch 1 V mm À 1 </p>

<p>The minimum-B trap depth at various times, the change in the gravitational potential energy 
going from the top (y ¼ þ RWall) to the bottom (y ¼ À RWall) of the trap, and the polarization 
potential energies. The 'Gap' polarization potential energy is the energy gained entering the gap 
between the electrodes, and the 'Patch' potential energy is the energy gained approaching a 
typical patch field region on the electrodes 17 . </p>

<p>F =1 </p>

<p>&lt;y|t &gt; (mm) </p>

<p>−20 </p>

<p>−10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>|F | =60 </p>

<p>&lt;y|t &gt; (mm) </p>

<p>−20 </p>

<p>−10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>|F | =150 </p>

<p>Time (ms) </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 </p>

<p>&lt;y|t &gt; (mm) </p>

<p>−20 </p>

<p>−10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Reverse cumulative average analysis. Comparison of the 
reverse cumulative average /y|tS of the event data to the reverse 
cumulative average of the simulation data. Each plot is identified by the 
value of F used in the simulations. In all graphs, the red-circle line is the 
/y|tS of the y annihilation positions of the event data. The green-triangle 
line is the reverse cumulative average of the x annihilation positions of the 
event data, and is included as a comparison. The black solid line is the 
/y|tS of approximately 900,000 simulated antihydrogen atoms. The black 
dashed line mirrors the black-solid line around /y|tS ¼ 0, and is equivalent 
to a simulation study of antigravity, i.e., negative F. The grey bands demark 
the 90% confidence region (95% when interpreted as a one-sided 
confidence test) for 434 annihilations around the gravity and antigravity 
/y|tS. The procedures for computing the /y|tS and the error bands are 
described in the Methods. The error bars on the event data give the 
standard error of the mean for /y|tS. The calculated lines do not include 
the effects of systematic errors. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2787 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1785 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2787 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>the 0.75-mm gap between the electrodes. These fields are on 
the order of 10 V mm À 1 . The energy that a ground-state 
antihydrogen atom would acquire approaching this gap is about 
five orders of magnitude less than the F ¼ 1 gravitational potential 
drop across the trap diameter. Furthermore, such a high field 
exists only in a very small volume of the trap. The 'patch' fields 17 
that plague charged particle gravity tests perturb the anti-atom 
energy by about two orders of magnitude less than the bias 
electric fields. The annihilation detection algorithm determines 
the locations of the anti-atom annihilations from the tracks of the 
pions that result from each annihilation. The smearing that 
results from the limited spatial resolution of the detector is well 
characterized 37 and is incorporated into our analysis (see 
Methods). 
The largest uncertainty in limiting F comes from our neglect, 
up to this point, of systematic effects from mechanical 
misalignments and from magnetic field errors. For example, the 
detector might not be perfectly centred on the trap axis. This 
misalignment is limited by mechanical constraints to be no more 
than ± 5 mm. Such a misalignment would cause an apparent </p>

<p>shift in the annihilation locations at early times as well as late, 
resulting in a bias in the average of the entire event set, 
/y|t ¼ 0S, of ±2.5 mm if at the constraint limit. (These errors 
differ from the detector smearing errors, which were calculated 
assuming that the detector was perfectly centred.) A somewhat 
smaller error would result from the octupole axis being displaced 
from the trap axis, which would cause a shift in the real 
annihilation locations. Like the detector displacement error, this 
displacement would cause a bias in overall average /y|t ¼ 0S. 
A bias of unknown origin is indeed visible in the event data: 
/y|t ¼ 0S ¼ À 1.3 ± 0.8 mm. Simulations incorporating an 
octupole axis displacement show that this overall bias would 
correspond to aŷ axis displacement of only À 0.06 mm. Perhaps 
coincidentally, this is nearly identical to the maximum 
displacement allowed by mechanical constraints. We have 
performed a broad survey (see Supplementary Note 1) of other 
magnetic field errors consistent with the mechanical tolerances of 
our device. This survey shows that the largest biases that could 
result from magnetic errors are usually smaller than, and at worst 
comparable to, the largest bias possible from an octupole axis 
displacement. Thus, in the absence of fortuitous cancelations, the 
relatively small measured bias in /y|t ¼ 0S limits the size of the 
effects of these errors at the late times when the experiment is 
most sensitive to gravity. Taking the maximally allowed detector 
and octupole displacement errors as representative of the worst-
case systematic errors, we have modelled their effects in the 
statistical calculations and, as shown in Fig. 5, determined that the 
worst-case exclusion region is F4110, still at a significance level 
of 5%. Similarly, analysis of favourable systematic errors, say 
because of a fortuitous octupole axis displacement of À 0.05 mm 
that would eliminate the /y|t ¼ 0S bias, yields a best case 
exclusion of F465 based on statistics alone. 
Some perspective on the size of the systematic errors can be 
found by calculating /y|t ¼ 0S for the untrapped antihydrogen 
atoms and antiprotons that annihilate on the wall during the 
antihydrogen synthesis process. In an observed sample of over 
270,000 of such anti-atoms, the y mean was þ 0.86 ± 0.03 mm. 
However, the orbital dynamics of untrapped antihydrogen and 
antiprotons are quite different from the dynamics of trapped 
antihydrogen, and there are effects that can lead to average 
vertical displacements of the opposite sign. A Monte Carlo 
simulation of our detector, which includes the effects of dead 
regions, gives a mean value for y of þ 0.01±0.06 mm. A hitherto 
unutilized experimental sample of 120 trapped antihydrogen 
atoms had a y mean of þ 2.2±1.4 mm. (This sample was not 
otherwise utilized because the atoms in this sample could not be 
guaranteed to have been trapped for more than 400 ms. Hence, 
these atoms were not necessarily in the ground state 31 .) These 
means do not entirely reconcile with each other or with the y 
mean of the standard sample of trapped atoms ( À 1.3 ± 0.8 mm), 
and we have no certain explanation of their differences. However, 
the range of means predicted by our analysis of the detector axis 
displacements encompasses all these values; thus, we allow for 
larger errors in our worst-case analysis. 
We set a limit on antigravity by inverting the sign of g in 
equation 1, or, equivalently, by making F negative. We find that 
Fo À 12 is excluded by statistics alone, with a worst-case limit 
from systematic errors of Fo À 65. However, because the 
systematic effects are not very well characterized for such small 
|F|, it is more conservative to only exclude FoÀ 65. </p>

<p>Importance of detailed studies of the orbital dynamics. We 
stress that our determination of F relies on detailed simulations of 
anti-atom trajectories in the time-dependent trap magnetic fields; 
other gravitational measurements using trapped antihydrogen </p>

<p>60 
80 
100 
120 </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>0 
−20 
−40 
−60 
−80 
−100 </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Monte Carlo analysis. Estimated P-values for the combined test 
statistic F as a function of F for (a) gravitational interactions (F40), and 
(b) anti-gravitational interactions (Fo0). The probabilities are computed 
using a Monte Carlo study of the Fisher combined statistic, as discussed in 
the Methods. The red solid circle lines assume no systematic errors; the 
blue hollow square line assumes a detector displacement of À 5 mm; the 
green solid triangle line assumes an octupole axis displacement of 
þ 0.05 mm; the green solid square lines assume an octupole axis 
displacement of À 0.05 mm; the blue hollow triangle lines assume a 
detector displacement of þ 5 mm. (For (b), the P-values for a detector 
displacement of À 5 mm or for an octupole axis displacement of 
þ 0.05 mm are essentially zero.) These four systematic errors encompass 
the range allowed by mechanical constraints. </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2787 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1785 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2787 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>would likely require a similar analysis. A recent publication, 
ref. 42, briefly mentions an experimental bound on F of 200. So 
far as we can discern from the one-paragraph description of the 
experiment, the measurement implicitly assumes thorough 
dynamical mixing between the transverse and axial directions. 
Previous antihydrogen simulations 31,38 show that these two 
directions are poorly coupled. This is because the trapping 
potential is nearly separable, and approximate independent 
constants of the motion exist for the transverse and axial 
degrees-of-freedom. Mixing only occurs due to end effects from 
the finite axial length of the magnetic system or from large size, 
small-spatial-scale magnetic errors unlikely to be present. Indeed, 
analytic calculations show that these constants of motion are 
adiabatically conserved for a broad range of parameters 43 . 
Furthermore, experiments 44 on the evaporative cooling of 
hydrogen atoms-a procedure closely analogous to the 
procedure outlined in ref. 42-show that the evaporation is 
essentially one dimensional, not three; that is, the transverse and 
axial directions do not couple. Thus, it is not surprising that 
simulations based on the best model we can construct from the 
limited information available in ref. 42 show that no effects of 
gravity could be observed using the techniques described in 
ref. 42 for |F|r200, or indeed, for |F|'s significantly greater than 
200 (ref. 45). </p>

<p>Discussion 
We report directly measured limits on the ratio of the 
gravitational mass to the inertial mass of antimatter. On the 
basis of goodness-of-fit tests comparing the positions of actual 
and simulated annihilation events, we can rule out ratios above 
F ¼ 75 (statistics alone) and F ¼ 110 (including worst-case 
systematic effects) for gravity, and below F ¼ À 65 (combined 
systematic and statistical effects) for antigravity, at the 5% </p>

<p>significance level. Obviously, our limits are far from the F ¼ 1 
regime where one could test for small deviations from the weak 
equivalence principle, but the methodology described here, 
coupled with planned and ongoing improvements to the ALPHA 
apparatus, should allow us to improve the measurement 
substantially. Simulations show that by cooling the anti-atoms, 
perhaps with lasers, to 30 mK or lower, and by lengthening the 
magnetic shutdown time constant to 300 ms, we would have the 
statistical power to measure gravity to the F ¼ ± 1 level (see 
Fig. 6). Cooling obviously increases the relative influence of 
gravity on the anti-atom trajectories. The longer shutdown times 
are necessary to take full advantage of adiabatic expansion cooling 
of these slower anti-atoms. They also allow the anti-atoms to find 
and annihilate on the portions of the trap wall where the trapping 
well depth is lowest. Systematic errors pose a significant challenge 
for low F measurements, however, and will need to be addressed. 
In summary, our experiments are an important first step towards 
a precise gravitational measurement with trapped, neutral 
antimatter. The current work clearly demonstrates the potential 
for using a carefully prepared, well-characterized sample of 
trapped antihydrogen atoms as a source for direct, ballistic studies 
of the gravitational behaviour of antimatter. The use of untrapped 
neutral antimatter for gravitational measurements, as pursued by 
other groups 27,28 , is, as yet, unproven. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Simulations. Antihydrogen trajectories were simulated using codes developed to 
establish that ALPHA trapped antihydrogen 38 . The codes use an adaptive Runge-
Kutta stepper to propagate antihydrogen atoms in the magnetic and gravitational 
fields of the trap. The model for the spatial structure and temporal behaviour of the 
magnetic field was experimentally verified by studying the trajectories of 
antiprotons 38 . (Also see Supplementary Note 2.) The numeric value of the 
antihydrogen magnetic moment used in the simulations was set equal to that of the 
positron alone; the small deviations to the antihydrogen magnetic moment from 
the antiproton are not significant for the experiments reported here. </p>

<p>Fraction of events </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>&lt;y 
|t &gt; (mm) </p>

<p>−20 </p>

<p>−10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1,000 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>Escape time (ms) </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1,000 </p>

<p>−20 </p>

<p>−10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>T =100 mK </p>

<p>T =10 mK 
T =3 mK </p>

<p>T =30 mK </p>

<p>Figure 6 | Cooled antihydrogen analysis. The reverse cumulative averages /y|tS for antihydrogen atoms cooled to the temperatures T listed in each 
graph. The magnet shutdown has been slowed by a factor of ten. The magenta dash-dot line is for F ¼ À 1, the red solid line is for F ¼ 0, and the green 
dashed line is for F ¼ þ 1. The dark yellow vertical band indicates the region in which the signal-to-cosmic-noise ratio (S/N) exceeds 5 for the current 
trapping rate 31 , and the light yellow vertical band indicates this same region (S/N45) for an antihydrogen trapping rate ten times greater. The grey bands 
demark the 90% confidence region (95% when interpreted as a one-sided confidence test) for 500 annihilations around the gravity and antigravity /y|tS; 
for simplicity, these bands are not plotted for F ¼ 0, and are only plotted within the regions of the high S/N bands. The thin black solid line shows the 
fraction of anti-atoms that have escaped as a function of time. Only counting statistics and signal-to-cosmic-noise effects are included in this graph; 
systematic effects at low F need to be further investigated. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2787 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1785 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2787 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>As described previously, the simulations are initiated with anti-atoms with a 
random energy consistent with a 
ffiffi 
e 
p 
de distribution. Anti-atoms with energies up 
to 650 mK, well above the nominal trapping depth of B540 mK, are included. 
Most of the anti-atoms with energy above 540 mK are lost during the 50 ms 
randomization period before the magnet shutdown is initiated, but some, those 
on quasitrapped orbits 31,38,46 , are retained. The gravity analysis is almost 
independent of the exact distribution of these quasitrapped anti-atoms, however, 
because they are lost at very early t. Spatially, the simulations were initiated with 
anti-atoms that originate in a region mimicking the dimensions of the 
experimental positron plasma. The 50 ms randomization period is sufficient to 
distribute these anti-atoms within the trap 38 , but may not entirely randomize 
them. To look for effects of insufficient randomization, simulations were also run 
with randomization times of 1 and 10 s. Some differences were observed, but 
these differences were significantly smaller than the differences caused by the 
detector displacement errors discussed above. We note that almost 75% of the 
anti-atoms used in this analysis were held for times between 0.4 and 1.4 s, so the 
1-s simulations model the approximate entire lifetime of the majority of the 
anti-atoms. </p>

<p>Antihydrogen energy distribution. To model the behaviour of anti-atoms 
during the magnet shutdown, we need to know the initial antihydrogen velocity 
distribution. ALPHA synthesizes antihydrogen atoms by injecting antiprotons 
into a positron plasma. The positron plasma is typically at a temperature 
of B40 K (ref. 30); before antihydrogen forms, the antiprotons thermalize on the 
positrons, giving them a temperature that approaches 40 K ref. 47. The 
resultant antihydrogen inherits the centre-of-mass kinetic energy of the 
antiprotons from which they are formed, so it too has an initial temperature of 
about 40 K. Most of these antihydrogen atoms are far too energetic to be trapped; 
only those with an energy near or below the trapping depth of 540 mK are 
sufficiently cold to be trapped. These trapped anti-atoms are deep within the 
Maxwellian distribution, where the energy distribution scales like 
ffiffi 
e 
p 
de. Strong 
evidence that the true energy distribution is close to this comes from comparing 
the annihilation times of the actual anti-atoms with the annihilation times of 
simulated anti-atoms for several different distributions (see Fig. 7a). This com-
parison is shown in Fig. 7b, where it is clear that the Maxwellian distribution best 
fits the experimental events. However, there are some differences between the 
two; for example, the simulations slightly underpredict the number of late 
annihilating anti-atoms. Fortunately, the analysis is not very sensitive to the 
details of the distribution, so the small deviations from Maxwellian visible in 
Fig. 7b are unimportant. For instance, Fig. 7c shows the annihilation locations for 
anti-atoms that annihilate between 20 and 22 ms, and the differences between the 
three distributions plotted are barely discernible. Figure 7d shows the influence of 
the choice of distribution on the reverse cumulative average /y|tS, and the 
differences are also small. </p>

<p>Reverse cumulative average. The reverse cumulative average is formally defined 
to be /y|tS ¼ (1/N t )S n y n , where {y n } is the set of annihilation locations, and the 
sum is over all of the N t elements of {y n } that occur after time t and before the late 
cutoff at 30 ms used to exclude the cosmic ray background. In Fig. 4, /y|tS is 
shown for both the event data and the simulation data at the given F's. The Monte 
Carlo error bands in Fig. 4 are calculated by dividing the B900,000 point 
simulation set at given F into about 2,100 subsets of length 434-the size of the 
actual event sample. Then, at every t, /y|tS is calculated for each subset and 
the results ordered. The error band at every t is then defined by the 5 and 95% 
quantiles of the ordered /y|tS. </p>

<p>Detector resolution. The detector determines the locations of the anti-atom 
annihilations by triangulation of the pion tracks produced by each annihilation. 
This process was extensively studied using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">GEANT</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">3</rs> code 48 , and a probability 
density function for the azimuthal resolution error was determined 37 . This error 
was incorporated into the simulation results by adding random angular offsets 
consistent with this probability density function to each of the simulated 
annihilation angular locations. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. To find the probability that the events are compatible with the 
simulations at a given F, we employ a test statistic akin to Fisher's combined 
statistic 40 aggregating K-S tests in different (overlapping) time windows: </p>

<p>F ¼ À </p>

<p>Z </p>

<p>30ms </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>ln P KS ðt; FÞdt; 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>where P KS (t;F) is the approximate P-value for a one-sided, two-sample K-S test 41,49  for a given F. The K-S test, described in the next paragraph, indicates how 
compatible the y annihilation distribution of a specific trial data set, windowed 
between t and 30 ms, is with the y annihilation distribution of a similarly windowed 
reference data set. Specifically, at every F we extract a B300,000 point subset from 
the simulation data to serve as a reference data set. Then we compute P KS (t;F) at 
every start time t and integrate using a numerical quadrature rule with a fixed time 
increment of 0.3 ms. Carrying out this procedure using the event data set for the 
trial distribution, we get the F Ev defined earlier. Carrying out this identical 
procedure using the remaining NE1,400 pseudo-event sets as the trial 
distributions, we get the set {F i;F }. Under the null hypothesis, namely, that there is 
no difference between the distributions for a given F, the P KS (t;F) themselves 
should be uniformly distributed. As originally introduced, Fisher's combined test 
statistic was intended for independent tests, for which the overall P-value is w 2 
distributed. In our case, the K-S P-values are correlated in t because the t windows 
overlap, so the P-value of the combined test statistic is estimated by Monte Carlo 
sampling. Thus, P ¼ N 4 /N, where the integer N 4 counts the number of F i,F for 
which F i,F 4F Ev . </p>

<p>Energy (K) </p>

<p>0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
f(E ) (arb. units) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Time (ms) </p>

<p>0.1 
0.3 
0.5 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 
Time-reversed CDF </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>y (mm) </p>

<p>−20 
−10 
f(y) (arb. units) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Time (ms) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 
&lt;y|t &gt; (mm) </p>

<p>−20 </p>

<p>−10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>M ax w el lia n </p>

<p>L in e a r </p>

<p>Uniform </p>

<p>Figure 7 | Energy distribution analysis. The effect on the annihilation location for (a) three postulated initial energy distributions. As the trap depth is 
about 540 mK, most, but not all, of the anti-atoms beyond 540 mK will be untrapped 31,38 . (b) The F ¼ 1 time-reversed CDF of the simulated annihilations 
during the magnet shutdown for the three distributions, following the labelling in (a). The black points plot the time-reversed CDF of the experimental 
events (which mainly appear as a band behind the red Maxwellian line.) The event data agrees well with the Maxwellian distribution. (c) A typical 
distribution in y of late annihilations (those occurring between 20 and 22 ms). (d) The reverse cumulative average, /y|tS, for the three distributions, as 
defined in the text. For (c) and (d), F ¼ 80; as expected, the plotted lines in these last two graphs show little dependence on the postulated energy 
distribution. </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2787 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1785 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2787 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>For each time window and F, the K-S test computes a 'distance' between the 
cumulative distribution function (CDF) for y for a trial event or pseudo-event set, 
and a reference distribution CDF. A greater distance reflects a lower probability that 
samples drawn from the reference set could deviate from the 'average' of that set by 
more than the trial set. These distances translate to approximate K-S P-values, 
P KS (t;F), through a well-studied universal function 49,50 . As our reference CDFs are 
rigorously stochastically ordered, yielding strictly declining P KS (t;F) for increasing F 
(t held fixed) once P is small, we can employ a one-sided K-S test rather 
than the more typical two-sided test. When the number of samples between t and 
30 ms in the trial set, k is greater than 4, we use the standard asymptotic expansion 49  for the distance to P KS function; for smaller k we use the direct small-sample 
formulae. The P KS for small k are generally close to unity, and contribute little 
to F. The estimated P KS include 'two-sample' corrections to account for the 
sampling error in the reference CDFs; however, these corrections are very small 
because the simulation sample sizes are large. Any approximations involved in 
calculating the P KS do not greatly affect the overall P-value, as the former are 
not interpreted directly in terms of Type I (false positive) errors, but are only 
used to compute the combined test statistic F whose P-value is determined by 
Monte Carlo methods. 
Note that for the analysis of the compatibility of the events with F ¼ 1, which 
yielded an overall P-value of 0.3, the K-S P-values are not small and the use of the 
one-sided K-S test is not justified. Hence, in this case only, we used the two-sided 
K-S test. 
We have approached the statistical analysis from the perspective of significance 
testing, that is, by seeking to reject hypotheses corresponding to sufficiently large 
values of |F| for which the data appear incompatible. If desired, however, the 
unrejected interval, À 65oFo110, which includes systematic errors, could also be 
interpreted as a confidence region for F (with a coverage probability of 95% 
corresponding to our 5% significance level). </p>

<p>Event data set. The event data set analysed here includes all those antihydrogen 
atoms trapped in the ALPHA apparatus in 2010 and 2011 that were held for more 
than 400 ms, escaped the trap within 30 ms of the magnet shutdown initiation, and 
whose annihilation locations reconstructed to be within z ¼ ±138 mm of the trap 
centre. Regions beyond z ¼ ± 138 mm were excluded because the trap wall has a 
significant inward step at these z locations. </p>



<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work was supported by: CNPq, FINEP/RENAFAE (Brazil); ISF (Israel); FNU 
(Denmark); VR (Sweden); NSERC, NRC/TRIUMF, AITF, FQRNT (Canada); DOE, NSF, 
LBNL-LDRD (USA); and EPSRC, the Royal Society and the Leverhulme Trust (UK). </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2787 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1785 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2787 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>



<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>This retrospective analysis was based on data collected in 2010 and 2011 by the entire 
ALPHA collaboration, using the antihydrogen trapping apparatus and methods 
developed by the collaboration. The gravity analysis described here was proposed and 
first carried out by J.F. and J.S.W. The analysis employed computer simulations 
developed by J.F.; the results of these simulations were checked with independent 
simulations developed by F.R. The statistical techniques were refined by A.E.C., 
and the final implementation of these techniques was carried out by A.Z. E.B., A.O. 
and F.R. proposed alternative statistical treatments that yielded similar results. This 
article was written by J.F. and J.S.W., with help from A.E.C., M.C., J.S.H. and A.Z., and 
then improved and approved by all the authors. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
naturecommunications </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Reprints and permission information is available online at http://npg.nature.com/ 
reprintsandpermissions/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: The ALPHA Collaboration and Charman, A.E. Description and 
first application of a new technique to measure the gravitational mass of antihydrogen. 
Nat. Commun. 4:1785 doi: 10.1038/ncomms2787 (2013). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of 
this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>C. Amole 2 , M.D. Ashkezari 3 , M. Baquero-Ruiz 1 , W. Bertsche 4,5,6 , E. Butler 7,w , A. Capra 2 , C.L. Cesar 8 , 
M. Charlton 4 , S. Eriksson 4 , J. Fajans 1,9 , T. Friesen 10 , M.C. Fujiwara 11 , D.R. Gill 11 , A. Gutierrez 12 , J.S. Hangst 13 , 
W.N. Hardy 12,14 , M.E. Hayden 3 , C.A. Isaac 4 , S. Jonsell 15 , L. Kurchaninov 11 , A. Little 1 , N. Madsen 4 , 
J.T.K. McKenna 16 , S. Menary 2 , S.C. Napoli 4 , P. Nolan 16 , A. Olin 11 , P. Pusa 16 , C.Ø. Rasmussen 13 , 
F. Robicheaux 17 , E. Sarid 18 , D.M. Silveira 8 , C. So 1 , R.I. Thompson 10 , D.P. van der Werf 4 , J.S. Wurtele 1,9 &amp; 
A.I. Zhmoginov 1,9 </p>

<p>2 Department of Physics and Astronomy, York University, Toronto, Ontario M3J 1P3, Canada. 3 Department of Physics, Simon Fraser University, Burnaby, 
British Columbia V5A 1S6, Canada. 4 Department of Physics, College of Science, Swansea University, Swansea SA2 8PP, UK. 5 School of Physics and 
Astronomy, University of Manchester, Manchester M13 9PL, UK. 6 The Cockcroft Institute, Daresbury Laboratory, Warrington WA4 4AD, UK. 7 Department 
of Physics, CERN, CH-1211, Geneva 23, Switzerland. 8 Departmento de Física Nuclear, Instituto de Física, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro 
21941-972, Brazil. 9 Accelerator and Fusion Research Division, Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, Berkeley, California 94720, USA. 10 Department of 
Physics and Astronomy, University of Calgary, Calgary, Alberta T2N 1N4, Canada. 11 Science Division, TRIUMF, 4004 Wesbrook Mall, Vancouver, British 
Columbia V6T 2A3, Canada. 12 Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia V6T 1Z1, Canada. 
13 Department of Physics and Astronomy, Aarhus University, Aarhus C DK-8000, Denmark. 14 Canadian Institute of Advanced Research, Toronto, Ontario 
M5G 1ZA, Canada. 15 Department of Physics, Stockholm University, Stockholm SE-10691, Sweden. 16 Department of Physics, University of Liverpool, Liverpool 
L69 7ZE, UK. 17 Department of Physics, Auburn University, Auburn, Alabama 36849-5311, USA. 18 Department of Physics, NRCN-Nuclear Research Center 
Negev, Beer Sheva IL-84190, Israel. w Present address: Centre for Cold Matter, Imperial College, London SW7 2BW, UK </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2787 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1785 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2787 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

</text></tei>