<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3709511" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Deep subsurface formations (for example, high-temperature oil reservoirs) are candidate 
sites for carbon capture and storage technology. However, very little is known about how the 
subsurface microbial community would respond to an increase in CO 2 pressure resulting from 
carbon capture and storage. Here we construct microcosms mimicking reservoir conditions 
(55°C, 5 MPa) using high-temperature oil reservoir samples. Methanogenesis occurs under 
both high and low CO 2 conditions in the microcosms. However, the increase in CO 2 pressure 
accelerates the rate of methanogenesis to more than twice than that under low CO 2 
conditions. Isotope tracer and molecular analyses show that high CO 2 conditions invoke 
acetoclastic methanogenesis in place of syntrophic acetate oxidation coupled with hydro-
genotrophic methanogenesis that typically occurs in this environment (low CO 2 conditions). 
Our results present a possibility of carbon capture and storage for enhanced microbial energy 
production in deep subsurface environments that can mitigate global warming and energy 
depletion. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>arbon capture and storage (CCS) is a candidate technology 
to reduce the emission of CO 2 from factories and power 
plants 1,2 . The underlying idea is to capture CO 2 rather 
than emitting it into the atmosphere and to sequester it in deep 
subsurface formations such as deep saline aquifers or depleted oil 
and gas reservoirs 3 . This technology has the potential to reduce 
future global CO 2 emissions by 20% 2,4 . The economical and 
technological feasibilities of CCS have been extensively studied 
over the past decade, mainly from a geological perspective 5-8 . 
Recently, microbial effects associated with CO 2 storage also have 
been investigated in deep saline aquifers 9,10 , and the influence of 
CO 2 injection on microbial community structure has been 
reported. A study revealed that CO 2 injection changed the 
constituent of methanogens and sulfate reducers in the deep 
subsurface microbial community 10 . Oil reservoirs are also unique 
subsurface environments that are potential repositories for CO 2 
sequestration 11,12 and often harbor active methane-producing 
microbial communities 13-15 . However, very little is known about 
the effect of CO 2 sequestration on microbial communities and 
their functional role in deep subsurface oil reservoirs. 
In the present study, we aimed to reveal how the microbial 
community and functions associated with methanogenesis 
respond to the increase in CO 2 concentration in the oil reservoirs. 
We performed laboratory experiments that simulated field 
conditions from where samples were collected. Based on stable 
isotope tracer analysis, molecular analysis and thermodynamic 
calculations, we report the possibility that drastic changes of 
microbial communities and methanogenic functions can be 
induced by CO 2 injection into deep subsurface high-temperature 
oil reservoirs. </p>

<p>Results 
Effect of CO 2 on methanogenesis in oil field microcosms. We 
selected a high-temperature oil reservoir, Yabase oil field, Japan, 
where we previously demonstrated the occurrence of in situ 
methanogenic activity 15 . Acetate, which is highly abundant in this 
reservoir (6-9 mM), is a primary precursor to methane. We 
previously found that methane was produced from acetate via 
syntrophic acetate oxidation coupled with hydrogenotrophic 
methanogenesis in the reservoir 15 . To determine if methano-
genesis would continue if CO 2 concentrations increased in 
subsurface oil reservoirs, we set up high-temperature and 
high-pressure incubation apparatuses (working volume: 1 l; 
Supplementary Fig. S1), mimicking the in situ oil reservoir 
(1,000-1,300 m deep, 53-65°C, 5 MPa; Supplementary Table S1). 
Production water from the reservoir used in this study contained 
6.4 mM of acetate, 39.6 mM of bicarbonate and indigenous 
microbes. We inoculated 8 ml of crude oil and 800 ml of the 
production water as a source of indigenous microbes and nutrients 
into the apparatuses, pressurized with either N 2 or N 2 /CO 2 (90:10) 
gas to a final pressure of 5 MPa, and incubated at 55°C. The 
microcosms incubated under an N 2 atmosphere were designated 
'control microcosms', and those incubated under an N 2 /CO 2 
atmosphere were designated as 'CO 2 -injected microcosms'. 
Control and CO 2 -injected microcosm experiments were prepared 
in triplicate. Two of the three microcosms were amended with 
either a trace amount of 13 C-bicarbonate (final 400 mM) or 
[2-13 C]-acetate (final 87.5 mM) to track the methanogenic pathway. 
After 1 week of incubation, CO 2 partial pressures and 
bicarbonate concentrations in the control microcosms stabilized 
at B0.004 MPa ( ¼ 0.04 atm) and 47.7 mM and in the 
CO 2 -injected microcosms at 0.2 MPa ( ¼ 2.0 atm) and 86.4 mM; 
decrease in CO 2 was due to dissolution into the production water. 
The pH levels in both microcosms were stable at B8.2 and 7.3, 
respectively, during incubation. The conditions in the </p>

<p>CO 2 -injected microcosms were likely to reflect the bicarbonate 
concentration and pH in previously reported CCS sites 
(Supplementary Table S1). In all microcosms, methane produc-
tions increased after at least 50 days of incubation, whereas 
methane productions in CO 2 -injected microcosms completed 
B30 days earlier than the control microcosms (Fig. 1a,b). Acetate 
present in the original production water decreased concomitantly 
with increased methane production. Methane production and 
acetate degradation in microcosms labeled with stable isotope 
tracers were almost similar to unlabeled microcosms. Methane 
production was nearly equivalent to the acetate consumed. This 
stoichiometric methanogenic reaction suggests that almost all 
the methane formed was derived from acetate. Interestingly, 
the methane production rate in CO 2 -injected microcosms 
(0.36 ± 0.04 mmol d À 1 ml À 1 water at the growing phase) was 
twice as high as in control microcosms (0.17±0.02 mmol d À 1 ml 
water at the growing phase), indicating that CO 2 injection 
stimulated methanogenesis. </p>

<p>CO 2 -driven change in methanogenic pathway in microcosms. 
To identify the methanogenic pathways in the control and </p>

<p>0 
2 0 
4 0 
6 0 
8 0 
1 0 0 
1 2 0 
Time (day) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Control microcosms </p>

<p>0 
2 0 
4 0 
6 0 
8 0 
1 0 0 
1 2 0 
Time (day) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>CH 4 </p>

<p>or </p>

<p>acetate 
(mM) CH 4 </p>

<p>or </p>

<p>acetate </p>

<p>(mM) </p>

<p>CO 2 -injected microcosms </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Methanogenesis in control and CO 2 -injected microcosms. 
Methanogenesis shown in (a) three individual control microcosms and 
(b) three individual CO 2 -injected microcosms under high-temperature and 
high-pressure conditions (55°C and 5 MPa). Methane (circles) and acetate 
(squares) concentrations over time in the unlabeled (closed symbols), 
[2-13 C]-acetate (gray symbols) and 13 C-bicarbonate (open symbols)-
labeled microcosms. All six microcosms were constructed using high-
temperature oil reservoir samples. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2998 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1998 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2998 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>CO 2 -injected microcosms, the carbon isotopic compositions 
(d 13 C) of methane and dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC) were 
measured during incubation. In the control microcosms labeled </p>

<p>with 13 C-bicarbonate, elevated d 13 C methane values (4450%) 
were detected (Fig. 2a), showing that the amended 13 C-bicarbo-
nate was converted to 13 CH 4 . In the [2-13 C]-acetate-labeled </p>

<p>Carbon isotopic ratio of CH </p>

<p>4 (‰) </p>

<p>700 </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>-100 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>Carbon isotopic ratio of CH </p>

<p>4 (‰) </p>

<p>1100 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>-100 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>U 
n 
l 
a 
b 
e 
l 
e 
d </p>

<p>[ 2 -</p>

<p>1 3 </p>

<p>C 
] -a c e t a t e </p>

<p>1 3 </p>

<p>C 
-b i c a r b o n a t e </p>

<p>U 
n l a b e l e d [ 2 -</p>

<p>1 3 </p>

<p>C 
] -a c e t a t e </p>

<p>1 3 </p>

<p>C 
-b i c a r b o n a t e </p>

<p>Control microcosms 
CO 2 -injected microcosms </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Carbon isotopic ratios of methane in control and CO 2 -injected microcosms after incubation. Carbon isotopic ratios of methane in the (a) 
control microcosms and (b) CO 2 -injected microcosms after incubation of 103 days. Carbon isotopic ratios of methane and dissolved inorganic carbon 
(DIC) in each microcosm during incubation are shown in Supplementary Table S2. </p>

<p>Arc </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>MMB </p>

<p>MBT </p>

<p>MSL </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 6 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Original 
Control 
CO 2 -injected 
16S rRNA gene concentration (copies per ml) </p>

<p>MBT1 
MBT2 </p>

<p>M S L 1 </p>

<p>MSL3 </p>

<p>MBT1 
MBT2 </p>

<p>ND </p>

<p>MSL2 </p>

<p>MMB1 </p>

<p>M 
M 
B 
1 </p>

<p>Other </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Archaeal methanogenic community compositions. Archaeal methanogenic community compositions in the original production water, 
control (day 116) and CO 2 -injected microcosms (day 103). (a) The 16S rRNA gene copy concentrations of the domain Archaea (Arc), the orders 
Methanobacteriales (MBT), Methanomicrobiales (MMB), and Methanosarcinales (MSL) quantified by qPCR assays. ND, not detected. (b) Relative abundance 
of archaeal clones. MBT1: Methanothermobacter thermautotrophicus KZ3-1 (DQ657903) (499% similarity), MBT2: Methanothermobacter wolfeii KZ24a 
(DQ657904) (495% similarity), MSL1: Methanosaeta sp. (AJ133791) (99% similarity), MSL2: Methanolobus psychrophilus R15 (EF202842) (98% 
similarity), MSL3: Methanosaeta thermophila PT (AB071701) (99% similarity), MMB1: Methanoculleus receptaculi ZC-3 (DQ787475) (99% similarity), Other: 
Thermococcus litoralis DSM5474 (AY099180) (99% similarity). Details of archaeal clone library analysis are shown in Supplementary Table S4. </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2998 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1998 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2998 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>control microcosm, d 13 C DIC values gradually increased and 
methane also became enriched in 13 C following DIC 
(Supplementary Table S2), indicating that the 13 C-methyl group 
of acetate was oxidized to CO 2 and incorporated into a large CO 2 
pool, and a small fraction of 13 CO 2 was converted to 13 CH 4 
(acetate oxidation: CH 3 COO À þ H þ þ 2H 2 O-4H 2 þ 2CO 2 ; 
methanogenesis from H 2 : 4H 2 þ CO 2 -CH 4 þ 2H 2 O; over all, 
CH 3 COO À þ H þ -CH 4 þ CO 2 ). In contrast, the [2-13 C]-acet-
ate added to a CO 2 -injected microcosm resulted in elevated d 13 C 
methane values (4850%) (Fig. 2b). This indicates that the 
13 C-methyl group of acetate was directly converted to 13 CH 4 
( 13 CH 3 COO À þ H þ -13 CH 4 þ CO 2 ). 
These 
observations 
demonstrated that the dominant methanogenic pathway in the 
control microcosms was syntrophic acetate oxidation coupled 
with hydrogenotrophic methanogenesis, while acetoclastic 
methanogenesis was the dominant methanogenic pathway in the 
CO 2 -injected microcosms. The values of carbon isotopic fractio-
nation between CH 4 and DIC in the unlabeled control (e C ¼ 
À 83.3 ± 1.3%) and CO 2 -injected (e C ¼ À 10.9 ± 1.0%) micro-
cosms during incubation (Supplementary Table S2) were also 
consistent with the hydrogenotrophic and acetoclastic methano-
genesis, respectively 16 . The reproducibility of the impact of CO 2 
on the methanogenic pathway and community resiliency were 
confirmed by an additional stable isotope tracer experiment, 
which showed that the dominant methanogenic community and 
pathway switched from one to the other when the headspace gas 
of the control microcosm was replaced with N 2 /CO 2 (90:10) and 
the CO 2 -injected microcosm was replaced with 100% N 2 
(Supplementary Note 1; Supplementary Figs. S2 and S3, and 
Supplementary Tables S3, S4 and S5). </p>

<p>CO 2 -induced alteration of methanogenic microbial 
community. Quantitative PCR (qPCR) and 16S rRNA gene clone 
library analysis showed differences in microbial community 
structure in the original production water compared with the 
incubated microcosms. The qPCR assays (Fig. 3a) of the archaeal 
16S rRNA genes showed that (1) the original production water 
contained mostly the order Methanobacteriales and a smaller 
population of Methanosarcinales; (2) the control microcosm was 
similarly dominated by hydrogenotrophic methanogens affiliated 
with the order Methanobacteriales; whereas (3) the CO 2 -injected 
microcosms differed and were dominated by the order Metha-
nosarcinales, many of which are acetoclastic methanogens. Clone 
library analyses supported the qPCR results. In the original 
production water and control microcosm, the genus Metha-
nothermobacter dominated the archaeal community (Fig. 3b and 
Supplementary Table S4). The control microcosm bacterial 
community was dominated by a limited number of phylotypes 
that includes the genus Thermacetogenium 17 , a known syntrophic 
acetate-oxidizing bacterium (99.8% sequence similarity) 
(Supplementary Table S5). In contrast, all archaeal clones in the 
CO 2 -injected microcosms were affiliated with the acetoclastic 
species Methanosaeta thermophila strain PT (99% sequence 
similarity) (Fig. 3b and Supplementary Table S4). In addition, in 
the CO 2 -injected microcosms, heterotrophic fermentative 
bacteria such as Coprothermobacter proteolyticus dominated in 
the bacterial community and the known syntrophic acetate-
oxidizing bacteria disappeared (Supplementary Table S5). These 
results clearly demonstrated that the main constituents of the 
control microcosm methanogenic microbial community were 
hydrogenotrophic methanogens and syntrophic acetate-oxidizers; 
CO 2 injection changed the community and led to the dominance 
of acetoclastic methanogens. These findings are consistent with 
the change in methanogenic pathways assessed by the stable 
isotope tracer experiment. </p>

<p>Thermodynamic constraints on methanogenic reactions. To 
elucidate the underpinning mechanisms of the shift in metha-
nogenic pathways in conjunction with microbial community 
transition by injecting CO 2 , we conducted thermodynamic 
calculations for the following reactions under various partial 
pressures of CO 2 : acetate oxidation, hydrogenotrophic methano-
genesis and acetoclastic methanogenesis. The thermodynamics 
showed that hydrogenotrophic methanogenesis becomes 
energetically more favorable with increasing CO 2 partial pressure, 
whereas acetate oxidation and acetoclastic methanogenesis 
become less favorable (Fig. 4a,b). However, acetoclastic metha-
nogenesis is less sensitive to high CO 2 partial pressure than 
acetate oxidation because acetate oxidation produces two moles of </p>

<p>-3 
-2 
-1 
0 
1 
2 
3 
Log CO 2 (atm) </p>

<p>-40 </p>

<p>-30 </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>ΔG (kJ per reaction) </p>

<p>Hydrogenotrophic methanogenesis </p>

<p>Acetate oxidation </p>

<p>Acetoclastic methanogenesis </p>

<p>-3 
-2 
-1 
0 
1 
2 
3 
Log CO 2 (atm) </p>

<p>-40 </p>

<p>-30 </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>ΔG (kJ per reaction) </p>

<p>Hydrogenotrophic methanogenesis </p>

<p>Acetate oxidation </p>

<p>Acetoclastic methanogenesis </p>

<p>Figure 4 | CO 2 partial pressure effect on change in Gibbs free energy for 
acetate oxidation and methanogeneses. Effect of CO 2 partial pressure on 
the change in Gibbs free energy for acetate oxidation, hydrogenotrophic 
methanogenesis and acetoclastic methanogenesis. (a) The setup 
conditions are at 116 days of incubation in the control microcosm: acetate at 
0.3 mM, methane at 0.51 atm, hydrogen at 1.5 Â 10 À 4 atm, pH ¼ 8.1, at 
55°C and 50 atm. (b) The setup conditions are at 77 days of incubation in 
the CO 2 -injected microcosm: acetate at 0.4 mM, methane at 0.66 atm, 
hydrogen at 1.2 Â 10 À 4 atm, pH ¼ 7.3, at 55°C and 50 atm. Dashed lines 
indicate actual CO 2 partial pressures (0.04 and 2.0 atm) in the control and 
CO 2 -injected microcosms, respectively. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2998 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1998 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2998 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>CO 2 per mole of acetate, whereas acetoclastic methanogenesis 
produces one mole of CO 2 . The DG values calculated for the three 
reactions in the control and CO 2 -injected microcosms showed 
that acetate oxidation in the CO 2 -injected microcosm would be 
endergonic (Fig. 4a,b and Table 1), indicating that syntrophic 
acetate oxidation coupled with hydrogenotrophic methanogenesis 
could not proceed under high CO 2 partial pressures but acet-
oclastic methanogenesis could proceed. A cultivation experiment 
verified the effect of CO 2 partial pressure on microbes; a pure 
syntrophic defined coculture 17 of Thermacetogenium phaeum 
strain PB and Methanothermobacter thermoautotrophicus strain 
TM was also inhibited by increasing CO 2 partial pressure 
(Supplementary Note 2 and Supplementary Fig. S4). </p>

<p>Discussion 
This study illustrates the possibility that an increase in CO 2 
partial pressure will change the microbial ecosystem in a deep 
subsurface high-temperature oil reservoir. Our results suggest 
that CO 2 injection into deep subsurface oil reservoirs can alter the 
in situ methanogenic pathway and lead to the dominance of 
acetoclastic methanogenesis. Acetate is often the most abundant 
organic acid in oil reservoirs 18,19 and an important intermediate 
in methanogenesis from crude oil 20 . Given that acetoclastic 
methanogenesis generally leads to a faster methanogenic reaction 
than syntrophic acetate oxidation coupled to hydrogenotrophic 
methanogenesis (Supplementary Note 2 and Supplementary 
Fig. S4), the shift to this pathway may result in an acceleration 
of methane production in oil reservoirs as observed in this study 
(Fig. 1a,b). Furthermore, the thermodynamics, in theory, suggests 
that the shift to acetoclastic methanogenesis can ease the 
thermodynamic constraint of crude oil biodegradation 
(Supplementary Fig. S5). Perhaps, the largest window of 
opportunity for crude oil biodegradation via acetoclastic 
methanogenesis alone 21 may lend further support to the 
hypothesis that CCS may increase energy recovery in the form 
of methane through crude oil biodegradation. Our results present 
a possibility of CCS for enhanced microbial energy production in 
deep subsurface environments that can mitigate global warming 
and energy depletion at the same time. To date, very little is 
known about the influence of CO 2 sequestration on the 
subsurface microbial communities and their functions, despite 
their important contribution to global biogeochemical 
processes 22,23 . This study would intrigue not only geochemists 
but also microbiologists for further investigation of CCS in 
connection with utilization of microbial activities in deep 
subsurface. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study site and sampling. Yabase oil field is one of the oldest and largest onshore 
oil fields in Japan, located in Akita Prefecture (39°42 
0 N, 140°5 
0 E). Currently, the 
oil field is almost depleted and characterized by high overall water cut (B90% basic 
sediment and water). The main reservoir rocks are tuffaceous sandstone of 
Miocene-Pliocene age. The depth of the oil horizon ranges from 1000 to 1300 m, 
with in situ temperature and pressure estimated to be 53-65°C and 5 MPa, 
respectively. </p>

<p>In Yabase oil field, there are some production wells in which crude oil along 
with production water has been produced by pumping. In this study, reservoir 
samples were collected from one of the wells where water injection to enhance oil 
recovery has never been applied. The samples were taken from production flow at 
the wellhead by discharging the fluid mixture through a metal tube into gas-tight 
glass bottles flushed in advance with nitrogen gas in September 2009. Immediately 
before each bottle was sealed, the headspace was flushed and pressurized with 
nitrogen gas to minimize air contamination. The samples were maintained 
at 50°C for 3 days until use. 
Geochemical characteristics of the production water and gas sample from this 
reservoir have been previously described in the study by Mayumi et al. 15 Briefly, 
the water had low salinity (Cl À ; 4690 mg l À 1 ) and À 239 mV of reduction 
potential, and concentrations of nitrate and sulfate as electron acceptors were 
14.5 mM and below 0.5 mM, respectively. Gas compositions of the sample collected 
from the production flow were H 2 : 0.1%, CO 2 : 2.4%, CH 4 : 77.2%, C 2 H 6 : 10.8%, 
C 3 H 8 : 5.2%, i-C 4 H 10 : 0.8% and n-C 4 H 10 : 1.5%. </p>

<p>Microcosms. Six microcosms were prepared with 800 ml of production water and 
8 ml of crude oil in 1 l sterile stainless-steel cylinder bottles (304L-HDF4-1000; 
Swagelok, Ohio, USA) and stable isotope tracers were added as described in 
Supplementary Fig. S1. Control microcosms were pressurized with nitrogen gas, 
and CO 2 -injected microcosms were pressurized with N 2 /CO 2 (90:10; d CO2 ¼ 
À 34.8%) at 5 MPa. Before pressurization of CO 2 -injected microcosms, sodium 
bicarbonate (d NaHCO3 ¼ À 4.2%) was added to a final concentration of 74 mM to 
mimic in situ conditions where formation water is highly buffered due to the 
presence of minerals such as calcite (CaCO 3 ) and dolomite (CaMg(CO 3 ) 2 ) in oil 
reservoirs 9,12 . The microcosms were incubated at 55°C, and the mixing ratios of 
CH 4 and CO 2 in the headspace gases and organic acids in production water were 
periodically measured with a gas chromatograph and an ion chromatograph 15 . 
H 2 concentrations in the headspace gases were measured with an EAGanalyzer gas 
chromatograph equipped with a semiconductor detector (Sensortec Co., Ltd., 
Shiga, Japan). </p>

<p>Carbon isotope analysis. Headspace gas and the incubated water were collected 
into gas-tight glass cylinder bottles and vials, respectively, from all microcosms 
periodically. Carbon isotopic compositions of CH 4 in gas-tight glass cylinder 
bottles were determined with a Finnigan gas chromatograph combustion isotope 
ratio mass spectrometer (GC-C-IRMS) consisting of a Hewlett Packard 5890 GC, 
a Finnigan MAT 252 IRMS and a ThermoQuest combustion interface (Thermo 
Finnigan Inc., Texas, USA). Carbon isotopic composition of DIC in the incubated 
water was measured after the addition of 1 M H 2 SO 4 to liberate total CO 2 . All 
measurements were conducted in triplicate, and the s.e. values were less than 1%. 
The isotopic values were expressed in d notation relative to the Vienna Pee Dee 
Belemnite (VPDB) standard. The values of isotopic fractionation (e C ) between DIC 
and CH 4 were determined by e C ¼ (d CH4 À d DIC )/(1 þ d DIC /10 3 ). </p>

<p>Molecular biological analyses. Molecular analyses were carried out for the 
original production water and incubated water from [2-13 C]-acetate labeled 
microcosms (at day 116 and 103 for the control and the CO 2 -injected microcosms, 
respectively). Total DNA was extracted from a 0.22-mm-pore-size polycarbonate 
membrane filter (Millipore, MA, USA), concentrating 250 ml of the original pro-
duction water, 15 ml of the control microcosm water and 40 ml of the CO 2 -injected 
microcosm water, using a FastDNA Spin kit (MP Biomedicals, CA, USA) 
according to the manufacturer's protocol. Bacterial and archaeal 16S rRNA genes 
were amplified with primer sets Eub8F/Univ1490R 24 and Ar109F 25 /Univ1490R, 
respectively. PCR products were cloned using the pT7 Blue T-vector kit (Novagen, 
CA, USA). Clones were randomly selected (in archaeal libraries, original 
production water; 32 clones, control microcosm; 39 clones, CO 2 -injected 
microcosm; 35 clones, in bacterial libraries, original production water; 49 clones, 
control microcosm; 92 clones, CO 2 -injected microcosm; 84 clones), and the 
inserted 16S rRNA gene was directly amplified with T7 promoter primer and 
U-19mer primer (Novagen). Sequence analysis of 16S rRNA genes was carried out 
with a BigDye Version 3.1 reaction on an ABI3730xl DNA Analyzer (Applied 
Biosystems, CA, USA). Chimeric sequences were detected with the Bellerophon 
server 26 and removed from the sequence data sets. To group the OTUs and draw </p>

<p>Table 1 | Thermodynamic parameters and Gibbs free energies of three reactions in the control and CO 2 -injected microcosms. </p>

<p>DG 55, 50 (kJ) w </p>

<p>Reaction 
DH o (kJ) DG o (kJ) DG o 
55, 1 (kJ)* DG o 
55, 50 (kJ)* Control CO 2 -injected 
Acetoclastic methanogenesis (CH 3 COO À þ H þ -CH 4 þ CO 2 ) 
17.7 
À 75.8 
À 85.2 
À 85.0 
À 22.4 
À 17.1 
Acetate oxidation (CH 3 COO À þ H þ þ 2H 2 O -4H 2 þ 2CO 2 ) 
270.6 
55.0 
33.3 
33.8 
À 6.3 
6.1 
Hydrogenotrophic methanogenesis (4H 2 þ CO 2 -CH 4 þ 2H 2 O) 
À 252.9 
À 130.8 
À 118.5 
À 118.8 
À 16.1 
À 23.1 </p>

<p>*The Gibbs free energies, DG o 
55, 1 and DG o 
55, 50, were calculated under the conditions at 55°C and 1 atm, and at 55°C and 50 atm, respectively. 
wThe Gibbs free energies in the control and CO2-injected microcosms were calculated using actual conditions in the unlabeled microcosms at day 116 and 77 of the control and CO2-injected microcosms, 
respectively, at 55°C and 50 atm. </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2998 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1998 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2998 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>rarefaction curves, sequences were analyzed using FastGroupII program 27 with 
97% sequence similarity. Representative sequences from each OTU were compared 
with those in public databases using the <rs type="software">Seqmatch</rs> program from the Ribosomal 
Database Project (Release 10, Update 12) to identify the nearest neighbors. 
The specific primer and probe set for archaea, hydrogenotrophic methanogens 
(the orders Methanobacteriales and Methanomicrobiales), and acetoclastic 
methanogens (the order Methanosarcinales) used in quantitative real-time PCR to 
determine the 16S rRNA gene copy numbers were previously designed in the study 
by Yu et al. 28 All real-time PCR assays were performed with iCycler iQ using the iQ 
Supermix reaction kit (Bio-Rad, California, USA), as previously described in 
the study by Mayumi et al. 15 Standard curves for each assay were constructed using 
nearly full-length 16S rRNA gene fragments amplified from Methanothermobacter 
thermautotrophicus strain delta H (DSM 1053) for the Archaea and the 
Methanobacteriales assays, Methanoculleus bourgensis strain MS2 (DSM3045) for 
the Methanomicrobiales assay, Methanosaeta thermophila strain PT (DSM 6194) 
for the Methanosarcinales assay. </p>

<p>Thermodynamics calculations. Gibbs free energy calculations were made 
according to the study by Dolfing et al. 21 Temperature corrections were 
made with the Gibbs-Helmholz equation according to DG o 
Tact ¼ DG o 
Tref . 
(T act /T ref ) þ DH o 
Tref Á (T ref À T act )/T ref with T in K; T act ¼ 328.15 K, T ref ¼ 298.15 K. 
The effect of pressure on DG (in kJ per reaction) was approximated as 
DG o 
Tref,Pact ¼ DG o 
Tref,Pref þ DV o Á (P act À P ref )/10000 where DG o 
Tref,Pact is the Gibbs 
free energy of reaction at the reference temperature (298.15 K) and in situ pressure 
(5 MPa; 50 atm), DG o 
Tref,Pref is the standard Gibbs free energy of reaction at the 
reference temperature and pressure (0.1 MPa; 1 atm), P act is the in situ pressure in 
atm, P ref is the reference pressure in atm and DV o is the partial molar volume change 
of the reaction at the reference temperature and pressure in cm 3 mol À 1 , as outlined 
in the study by Wang et al. 29 . The calculations were made for acetate (pKa ¼ 4.75) 
at the appropriate pH values 30 . For the reaction CO 2 þ 4H 2 -CH 4 þ 2H 2 O, 
DV o ¼ À 62.3; for CH 3 COO À þ H þ þ 2H 2 O-4H 2 þ 2CO 2 , DV o ¼ 92.25; for 
CH 3 COO À þ H þ -CH 4 þ CO 2 , DV o ¼ 29.95. Neglecting activity coefficients 
yields an error in calculated Gibbs free energy values of at most 2 kJ mol À 1 for 
all reported values at an ionic strength of 0.1 M (Debye-Huckel calculations). </p>



<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We gratefully acknowledge the Akita District Office of INPEX Corporation for their help 
with sample collection. We also thank Hua Zhang in National Institute of Advanced 
Industrial Science and Technology for technical support. We are grateful to Masao Sorai 
in National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology for helpful com-
ments about changes in physicochemical conditions of the deep subsurface after CCS was 
carried out. This study was financially supported in part by JSPS KAKENHI Grant 
Numbers 22654066, 23244109, 23657069, 23681044, 24780089 and 25289333. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>This study was designed by S.S. and H.M. The construction of the microcosms and the 
monitoring of gas compositions were performed by D.M., Y.M., and M.I. Analysis of 
carbon isotopic compositions was performed by D.M. and S.S. The 16S rRNA gene clone 
library and qPCR analyses were conducted by D.M. Thermodynamic calculations were 
performed by D.M. and J.D. The manuscript was written by D.M., H.T., J.D., S.S., M.T., 
C.H.N. and Y.K., assisted by all co-authors. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Accession codes: All 16S rRNA gene sequences obtained in this study have 
been deposited at DDBJ under accession numbers AB668482-AB668513 and 
AB710350-AB710376. </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
naturecommunications </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Reprints and permission information is available online at http://npg.nature.com/ 
reprintsandpermissions/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Mayumi, D. et al. Carbon dioxide concentration dictates 
alternative methanogenic pathways in oil reservoirs. Nat. Commun. 4:1998 doi: 10.1038/ 
ncomms2998 (2013). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of 
this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/ </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2998 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1998 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2998 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

</text></tei>