<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3198080" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVE-Erythropoietin (EPO) may be protective for early 
stage diabetic retinopathy, although there are concerns that it 
could exacerbate retinal angiogenesis and thrombosis. A pep-
tide based on the EPO helix-B domain (helix B-surface peptide 
[pHBSP]) is nonerythrogenic but retains tissue-protective proper-
ties, and this study evaluates its therapeutic potential in diabetic 
retinopathy. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS-After 6 months of 
streptozotocin-induced diabetes, rats (n = 12) and age-matched 
nondiabetic controls (n = 12) were evenly split into pHBSP and 
scrambled peptide groups and injected daily (10 mg/kg per day) 
for 1 month. The retina was investigated for glial dysfunction, 
microglial activation, and neuronal DNA damage. The vasculature 
was dual stained with isolectin and collagen IV. Retinal cytokine 
expression was quantified using real-time RT-PCR. In parallel, 
oxygen-induced retinopathy (OIR) was used to evaluate the 
effects of pHBSP on retinal ischemia and neovascularization 
(1-30 mg/kg pHBSP or control peptide). </p>

<p>RESULTS-pHBSP or scrambled peptide treatment did not alter 
hematocrit. In the diabetic retina, Müller glial expression of 
glial fibrillary acidic protein was increased when compared with 
nondiabetic controls, but pHBSP significantly reduced this stress-
related response (P , 0.001). CD11b+ microglia and proinflamma-
tory cytokines were elevated in diabetic retina responses, and 
some of these responses were attenuated by pHBSP (P , 0.01-
0.001). pHBSP significantly reduced diabetes-linked DNA damage 
as determined by 8-hydroxydeoxyguanosine and transferase-
mediated dUTP nick-end labeling positivity and also prevented 
acellular capillary formation (P , 0.05). In OIR, pHBSP had no 
effect on preretinal neovascularization at any dose. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS-Treatment with an EPO-derived peptide after 
diabetes is fully established can significantly protect against 
neuroglial and vascular degenerative pathology without altering 
hematocrit or exacerbating neovascularization. These findings 
have therapeutic implications for disorders such as diabetic 
retinopathy. Diabetes 60:2995-3005, 2011 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>eyond its established hormonal role in main-
taining erythrocyte mass, erythropoietin (EPO) 
also functions in a paracrine manner to protect 
tissues during ischemic, toxic, and traumatic in-
sults (1). EPO is highly expressed in many organs (2), and 
its upregulation can prevent apoptosis and associated in-
flammation (3). Preclinical studies demonstrate that ex-
ogenous recombinant EPO can prevent ischemia-related 
damage in the brain (4) and heart (5). 
Although used clinically to reverse anemia, recombinant 
EPO or erythropoiesis-stimulating agent treatment of 
patients with stroke or myocardial infarction has shown 
variable efficacy (6-8). Some trials have also highlighted 
significant safety issues related to unwanted erythrogenesis 
and thrombosis (6). Furthermore, for cancer patients be-
ing treated for anemia, there has been considerable con-
cern that EPO could activate the EPO receptor (EPO-R) on 
tumor cells and accelerate growth or metastasis (9). This, 
combined with the known proangiogenic effects of EPO, 
suggests that there are considerable limitations on using 
recombinant EPO for its tissue-protective effects, especially 
in at-risk patients such as those with cancer, thrombotic 
disorders, or diabetes (10). 
As the most common complication of diabetes, reti-
nopathy is the leading cause of blindness in the working 
population of many industrialized countries (11). The vaso-
degenerative phase of diabetic retinopathy is also accom-
panied by neuroglial abnormalities and eventual depletion 
of ganglion cells (12). Retinal nonperfusion leads to in-
creasing hypoxia (13), and this eventually drives break-
down of the blood-retinal barrier (BRB) and preretinal 
neovascularization, which constitute the sight-threatening 
end points of diabetic retinopathy. 
In degenerative retinopathies, exogenous EPO can in-
hibit neuronal apoptosis (14); however, during retinal is-
chemia, this cytokine may enhance pathological, preretinal 
neovascularization (15). Blockade of EPO expression us-
ing interference RNA (16) or antagonism of EPO-R (17) 
can effectively prevent neovascularization, and this has 
raised concerns that using EPO in diabetic patients could 
serve to accelerate proliferative retinopathy. This asser-
tion has been countered by recent studies that show some 
forms of erythropoiesis-stimulating agent could prevent 
lesions associated with early stage diabetic retinopathy 
(18,19) and reverse retinal ischemia (20) in rodent models. 
While it is clear that EPO has the capacity to protect 
against pathology, its constitutive hormonal role and di-
versity of action on different cells currently limits its clin-
ical potential. </p>

<p>From the </p>

<p>The molecular basis for the multiple roles of EPO is 
incompletely understood but may be linked to the differ-
ential binding affinities of its two main receptors (21). 
Classically, EPO binds to the homodimeric EPO-R, with 
high affinity on cells within the bone marrow, and controls 
erythrogenesis. In other tissues, a heterodimer of EPO-R 
and the b-common receptor can form similarly to receptors 
for other type I cytokines (21). This so-called tissue-pro-
tective receptor (TPR) is primarily expressed only during 
metabolic stress and tissue injury, and since it binds with 
lower affinity than to the EPO-R dimer, it responds only to 
local rather than circulating EPO (22). The nature of the TPR 
has been exploited by recent studies that demonstrate a helix 
B-surface peptide (pHBSP) mimics the three-dimensional 
structure of EPO. This does not bind to the EPO-R dimer 
and is nonerythrogenic (23) but is tissue protective (24). 
In the current study, we have sought to evaluate the 
potential of the TPR using a unique peptide analog in two 
models of diabetic retinopathy-one reproducing the early 
vascular and neuroglial degenerative stage and the other 
the ischemia-induced neovascular stage. In the clinical con-
text, it is important to evaluate the most likely scenario in 
which patients can be treated; therefore, we devised an 
intervention strategy in which treatment was given after 
diabetic retinopathy was well established. We show that 
pHBSP is highly effective at preventing clinically relevant 
lesions of diabetic retinopathy without exacerbating neo-
vascularization. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>Diabetic rat model. All experiments conformed to U.K. Home Office regu-
lations and were approved by Queen's University Belfast Ethical Review 
Committee. Diabetes was induced in male SD rats (n = 12) at ;160 g body wt 
by a single intraperitoneal injection of streptozotocin (STZ; Sigma, Dorest, 
England, U.K.) (65 mg/kg in 0.1 mol/L citrate buffer, pH 4.6). A control group 
received citrate buffer alone (n = 12). At 1 week after STZ injection, hyper-
glycemia was confirmed using glucometric analysis of tail prick blood samples 
(Ascensia Breeze; Bayer, Cambridge, U.K.). Animals with blood glucose con-
centrations .15 mmol/L were considered to have diabetes and enrolled into the 
study. Blood glucose and weight were monitored monthly. 
After 6 months the diabetic rats and age-matched, non-diabetic controls 
were randomly assigned to treatment with daily intraperitoneal injections for 
a further 28 days of either 10 mg/kg scrambled peptide (pLSEARNQSEL) 
or active drug (10 mg/kg pHBSP). pHBSP is an 11-amino acid peptide of 
molecular weight 1,258 synthesized by standard F-moc solid phase peptide 
synthesis and purified by high-performance liquid chromatography and ion-
exchange chromatography (23). A total of 24 rats were divided into four 
groups. Groups 1 (n = 6) and 2 (n = 6) consisted of control, nondiabetic rats 
treated with either scrambled peptide or pHBSP. Groups 3 (n = 6) and 4 (n = 6) 
were diabetic rats that received scrambled peptide or pHBSP. 
Blood analysis. At killing, whole blood from a cardiac puncture was taken for 
analysis. To determine the long-term diabetic state of the rats, HbA 1c (glycated 
hemoglobin) was assessed (Glyo-tek Affinity column; Helena Biosciences 
Europe, Gateshead, U.K.). For rats, hematocrit was quantified using the Sysmex 
SC9500 analyzer (Japan). 
Preparation of rat retina and immunofluorescence staining. At killing, 
the eyes (one eye per rat; n = 6 per group) were immediately enucleated. One 
eye was fixed by immersing in freshly prepared 4% paraformaldehyde for 1 h 
at 4°C then washed in PBS. For immunofluoresence, the eye was dissected 
into two. The retina was removed from the eyecup for flat-mount staining. 
The other half of the eye was embedded in optimal cutting temperature (OCT) 
medium and cryosections were cut at 12 mm. A range of primary antibodies 
were used (as outlined below) in combination with appropriate fluorescent-
conjugated secondary antibody (Alexa Fluor 
488 or Alexa Fluor </p>

<p>568 </p>

<p>; Invitrogen, 
Paisley, U.K.). Negative controls were performed in parallel by omission of 
primary antibody. Fluorescence was visualized by using a Nikon TE-2000 C1 
confocal system (Nikon, Surrey, U.K.). 
Retinal component layer thickness was measured for each group. In ad-
dition, we assessed glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP) immunoreactivity 
(anti-GFAP polyclonal antibody; Dako, Cambridgeshire, U.K.). Immunoreactivity 
was assessed by confocal microscopy and <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software (Wayne Rasband, </p>

<p>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD) (25). GFAP-positive fibers in the 
Müller cells crossing the inner plexiform layer (IPL) and the inner nuclear layer 
(INL) were quantified. 
Analysis of retinal DNA damage and caspase-3. DNA damage in the retina 
was determined with a transferase-mediated dUTP nick-end labeling (TUNEL) 
assay using a kit according to the manufacturer's instructions (Roche, Mannheim, 
Germany). Two retinal cryosection slides per animal were designated as nega-
tive controls, and one slide per animal was a positive control. The positive 
control slide was incubated in DNase 1 solution (200 mg/mL in PBS; Qiagen) 
for 10 min at room temperature while the rest were incubated in PBS (n = 6 
per group). To aid in orientation of the retinal samples, the nuclear stain 
propidium iodide (PI; 5 mg/mL in PBS; Sigma) was used. Positive cell counts 
were assessed by image analysis in multiple sections. In addition, images were 
taken at three separate points on the central retina at 340 magnification and 
presented as the average nuclei in the ganglion cell layer (GCL) or in the entire 
retina. In total per animal, there were two positive slides (three fields at 300 mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>each), one negative slide (three fields), and one test slide (three fields) assessed 
(n = 6 per group of animals). 
DNA oxidative damage in the retina was determined with the oxidative 
stress marker 8-hydroxydeoxyguanosine (8-OHdG). Briefly, the sections of 
retina were blocked with goat serum, and the monoclonal antibody 8-OHdG 
(Japan Institute for Control of Ageing, Japan) was added overnight followed by 
the appropriate fluorescent-conjugated secondary antibody (Alexa Fluor </p>

<p>488 </p>

<p>, 
Invitrogen). 
Sections of retina were incubated with a monoclonal antibody cleaved 
caspase-3 (Cell Signaling Ltd.) followed by the appropriate fluorescent-
conjugated secondary antibody (Alexa Fluor </p>

<p>488 </p>

<p>, Invitrogen) for 1 h. In all cases, 
the slides were qualitatively viewed using epifluorescence with excitation 
wavelength of 488 nm and analyzed using ImageJ. 
Acellular capillary quantification. Retinal flat mounts were prepared for 
immunofluorescence as previously described (20). The retinal flat mounts were 
stained with biotinylated isolectin GS-IB4 overnight (Sigma) or for collagen IV 
immunoreactivity (Acris Antibodies GmbH, Germany). Appropriate ligand 
(streptavidin Alexa Fluor </p>

<p>488 </p>

<p>) and secondary antibody was used (Alexa Fluor </p>

<p>568 </p>

<p>goat anti-rabbit IgG) (both from Molecular Probes). Stained retinae were im-
aged using the Nikon TE-2000 C1 confocal system. Five regions were taken 
at 340 magnification in the central and peripheral retina for collagen IV and lectin. 
Retinal microglia analysis. Retinal cryosections were stained for microglia 
using CD11b (1:200, AbD Serotec) for 72 h followed by secondary anti-mouse 
Alexa Fluor </p>

<p>488 </p>

<p>. PI was added to visualize the nuclear layers. The total number 
of microglial cell counts was subdivided according to whether the cells dis-
played dendritic or amoeboid morphology, the latter indicating activation. A 
small number of CD11b +ve cells whose identity could not be determined on 
the basis of their morphology were omitted from the counts. 
The mean cell counts of CD11b-positive cells were taken from three separate 
points within the central retina at 340 magnification. Therefore, in total per 
animal, there were three fields at 300 mm 
2 assessed (n = 6 per group of ani-
mals). Microglia were also assessed within the flat mounts, which were stained 
with biotinylated isolectin (GS-IB4) for acellular capillary quantification. Again, 
the total number of microglial cells was subdivided according to whether the 
cells displayed dendritic or amoeboid morphology. 
Quantitative RT-PCR. The fellow eye from each animal (n = 6) was dissected 
and the retina was excised and placed into RNAlater (Ambion, U.K.) RNA 
stabilization solution at a volume of 10 mL per 1 mg of tissue. Quantitative 
RT-PCR (qPCR) was conducted as previously reported (20). Rat sequence-
specific primers for tumor necrosis factor-a (TNF-a), interleukin (IL-6), and 
IL-10 were as follows: TNF-a (forward: 59TGCCTCAGCCTCTTCTCATT'3; re-
verse: 59GGGCTTGTCACTCGAGTTTT'3), IL-6 (forward: 59AGTTGCCTTCTT-
GGGACTGA'3; reverse: 59CAGAATTGCCATTGCACAC'3), and IL-10 (forward: 
59CCTGCTCTTACTGGCTGGAG'3; reverse: 59GTCCAGCTGGTCCTTCTTT'3). 
b-Actin (forward: 59TGTCACCAACTGGGACGATA'3; reverse: 59GGGGTGTT-
GAAGGTCTCAAA'3) was the housekeeping gene used. 
Oxygen-induced retinopathy model. Oxygen-induced retinopathy (OIR) was 
conducted in neonatal C57/BL6 wild-type mice (20), during which there is 
acute retinal ischemia in the central retina followed by a potent preretinal 
neovascular response between postnatal day (P) 15 and P21. A total of 34 mice 
were divided into six groups. Group 1 consisted of P12 controls (n = 4) and 
was used to confirm that consistent central vaso-obliteration occurred after 
hyperoxia exposure. In the period from P12 to P16, inclusive, group 2 received 
daily intraperitoneal injections of PBS (n = 6), group 3 received scrambled 
control peptide (10 mg/kg; n = 6), and groups 4-6 received 1, 10, or 30 mg/kg of 
pHBSP, respectively (n = 6 pups per group). 
Blood analysis in mice. Blood was obtained from each pup by cardiac 
puncture, and reticulocytes were assessed because of the acute time frame of 
EPO peptide treatment, which would not have been expected to alter he-
matocrit. Murine reticulocyte counts were conducted manually as previously 
described (20). </p>

<p>EPO PEPTIDE PROTECTS RETINA DURING DIABETES </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>OIR pathology assessment. One eye from each animal (n = 6) had retinal 
RNA isolated and qPCR conducted as outlined above. The fellow eye (n = 6) 
was enucleated and immediately fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde (n = 6 per 
treatment group). Retinal flat mounts were stained with isolectin B4 (Sigma) 
and the corresponding streptavidin Alexa Fluor 
488 (Invitrogen). Stained reti-
nae were visualized and imaged using Nikon TE-2000 C1 confocal system. 
Avascular and preretinal neovascularization were quantified using Lucia Ver-
sion 4.60 software as previously described (20). 
Retinal hypoxia can be assessed using the bioreductive drug pimonidazole 
(hypoxyprobe [HP], 60 mg/kg), which forms irreversible adducts with thiol 
groups on tissue proteins when pO 2 ,10 mmHg (26). Retinal flat mounts were 
incubated with an anti-HP rabbit polyclonal antibody (HP2-100kit; HPI Inc., 
MA) used at a dilution of 1:500 in PBS/0.1% TX-100 and then a goat anti-rabbit 
antibody labeled with Alex Fluor 
594 (Molecular Probes). 
qPCR was conducted as for rat retina, except that mouse sequence-specific 
primers for vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) and the housekeeping 
gene phosphoprotein PO (ARP/36B4) were used as previously described (27). 
Statistical analysis. Data are presented as mean 6 SEM. Statistical analyses 
were performed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">V4.02</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA</rs>). All 
datasets were tested to verify that they fulfilled requirements for a normal 
distribution. Two-way ANOVA was conducted to compare overall treatment 
differences and P , 0.05 was deemed significant. When a statistically signifi-
cant difference was detected, post hoc multiple pairwise comparisons were 
performed using Tukey multiple comparison test. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Characteristics of diabetic animals. Analysis of body 
weight revealed a 50% reduction in diabetic rats compared 
with age-matched nondiabetic controls (Fig. 1A). HbA 1c at </p>

<p>killing showed a 2.5-fold increase in diabetic rats compared 
with control rats (P , 0.001) (Fig. 1B). pHBSP peptide did 
not alter these diabetes parameters, nor did it alter hemat-
ocrit counts (Fig. 1C). Diabetes induced a significant in-
crease in the number of reticulocytes and pHBSP prevented 
this change (Fig. 1D). 
We assessed the thickness of the retinal layers and 
found that the outer nuclear layer (ONL) was reduced in 
the diabetic retina with both the scrambled pHBSP and the 
pHBSP (P , 0.001). No significant difference was observed 
in the GCL, IPL, INL, and outer plexiform layer between 
control and diabetic retina groups (Supplementary Fig. 1). 
pHBSP attenuates diabetes-related glial and neuronal 
dysfunction. In the nondiabetic retina, GFAP was local-
ized to the astrocytes and a population of retinal Müller 
glia (Fig. 2A and B). This was typical of the GFAP staining 
pattern in aging rat retina (28). Diabetes induced a strong 
upregulation of this protein in both astrocytes and retinal 
Müller glia (P , 0.05). pHBSP peptide treatment of di-
abetic rats significantly prevented this gliosis response in 
Müller glia, as indicated by a reduction in the intensity of 
GFAP staining in the innermost retinal layers and the num-
ber of GFAP-positive fibers in the IPL (P , 0.05) (Fig. 2A 
and B). 
As has been previously reported in rats of comparable 
diabetes duration (29), there was a significant increase in </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Characterization of STZ-induced diabetes. The extent of diabetes was assessed in the various rat groups at the end of the experiment 
(8.5 months of age) using body weight and hyperglycemia as indicators. Cntl, control; Sc, scrambled pHBSP; and Db, diabetic. A: Analysis of body 
weight showed a 50% reduction in diabetic rats compared with age-matched controls. B: HbA 1c levels were elevated by 2.5-fold in diabetic rat blood 
compared with control. Neither pHBSP nor the scrambled peptide influenced these parameters. (***P &lt; 0.001). C: The hematocrit levels (% blood 
volume occupied by erythrocytes) were not altered in the blood of the animals that received the pHBSP. D: Diabetes increased the percentage of 
circulating reticulocytes (*P &lt; 0.05), while treatment with pHBSP prevented this change. Data are mean 6 SEM; n = 6 per group. One-way ANOVA. </p>

<p>C.M. MCVICAR AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 </p>

<p>
TUNEL-positive cells in the retina (P , 0.001) (Fig. 3A 
and B). TUNEL-positive cells, indicating DNA strand breaks, 
were apparent in the GCL, INL, and ONL. Treatment with 
pHBSP decreased TUNEL positivity in the GCL by 49% 
when compared with diabetic controls (P , 0.01) (Fig. 3B). 
In terms of overall diabetes-related TUNEL positivity in the 
retina, pHBSP provided significant protection when com-
pared with diabetic with scrambled peptide (P , 0.005) 
(Fig. 3C). Caspase-3-positive cells were observed in the INL 
mainly, but there were no differences observed between the 
groups (Supplementary Fig. 2). And 8-OHdG-positive cells 
were found only in the diabetic retinae on the border of the 
ONL both in those that received the scrambled peptide and 
to a lesser extent in those that received the active pHBSP 
(Supplementary Fig. 3). 
pHBSP regulates microglial activation and cytokine 
expression in the diabetic retina. As depicted in retinal 
sections, diabetes was associated with an increase in 
CD11b-positive microglia in the neuropile, especially within 
the IPL (P , 0.05) (Fig. 4A and B). There was also a sig-
nificant shift in phenotype toward activated, amoeboid cells </p>

<p>(Fig. 4C-F). pHBSP had no influence on overall microglia 
numbers, but this treatment significantly increased the 
proportion of cells with a dendritic phenotype and re-
duced amoeboid cells when compared with diabetic rats 
treated with the scrambled pHBSP (P , 0.05) (Fig. 4A 
and B). Lectin-stained microglia also showed that di-
abetes was associated with an increase in microglia com-
pared with the controls in the inner plexus in the central 
(P , 0.01) and peripheral retina (P , 0.05) (Supplementary 
Fig. 4). 
In keeping with the pattern observed with the resi-
dent immune cells within the retina, transcripts for the 
anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10 were significantly de-
creased in the diabetic rat retina relative to age-matched 
controls (P , 0.001), and pHBSP treatment returned these 
expression levels close to levels seen in controls (Fig. 5A). 
By contrast, mRNAs for the proinflammatory cytokines 
TNF-a and IL-6 were significantly elevated in diabetic ret-
ina (P , 0.001), and pHBSP prevented this increase and 
restored expression to normal levels in both cases (Fig. 5B 
and C). STZ-induced diabetes caused a reduction in IL-1b 
levels when compared with control tissue treated with 
scrambled peptide (P , 0.001). Treatment with pHBSP 
caused a reduction in IL-1b levels both in nondiabetic tis-
sue and diabetic tissue (P , 0.001) (Fig. 5D). 
pHBSP protects retinal capillaries during diabetes. 
As diabetes progresses, the death of retinal pericytes and 
endothelium results in acellular capillary formation, a lesion 
that takes ;5-6 months to become obvious in diabetic rats 
(30). While various approaches have been used to visualize 
acellular capillaries, we used the fact that such naked 
basement membrane tubes remain positive for collagen IV 
and negative for isolectin and can be quantified using con-
focal microscopy (Fig. 6A). The diabetic retina contained 
approximately fourfold increased numbers of acellular 
capillaries when compared with nondiabetic control ret-
ina (P , 0.05) (Fig. 6A and B). pHBSP treatment for 1 
month, after 6 previous months of diabetes, significantly 
reduced acellular capillaries in the retina, and there were 
no differences between these treated patients with di-
abetes in comparison with nondiabetic control groups 
(Fig. 6B). 
pHBSP does not exacerbate ischemia-induced 
neovascularization. As determined in the murine OIR 
model, pHBSP did not increase the percentage of retic-
ulocytes in peripheral blood over an acute time frame (Sup-
plementary Fig. 5). A dose of 1 mg/kg of pHBSP resulted in 
a decrease in the ischemic region of the retina. The higher 
doses of the peptide returned the ischemic region to nor-
mal (Fig. 7A). Consistent with the well-characterized OIR 
response, hyperoxia induced a temporal pattern of central 
retina vascular insufficiency upon return to room air at P12, 
which led to a reproducible preretinal neovascularization 
observable on flat mounts (Fig. 7B). Over a dose response 
range, pHBSP administered from P12 to P16 inclusive dem-
onstrated no significant increase in ischemia-driven pre-
retinal neovascularization (Fig. 7B-D). 
In OIR, neovascularization is driven by ischemic hypoxia 
(akin to that observed in long-term diabetic retinopathy in 
patients), so the degree of hypoxia was evaluated. Retinal 
HP deposition was reduced in the pHBSP-treated mice 
when compared with controls (Fig. 8A). The hypoxia-
induced angiogenic factor VEGF was increased at the 
P17 time point as previously reported (27), and pHBSP 
decreased this expression in a dose-dependent manner 
(Fig. 8B). </p>

<p>FIG. 2. pHBSP prevents diabetes-related GFAP expression in Müller 
cells. Retinal sections were processed for GFAP immunoreactivity and 
assessed by confocal microscopy. Cntl, control; Sc, scrambled pHBSP; 
and Db, diabetic. A: Bar chart shows the numbers of GFAP-positive 
fibers crossing the IPL and INL, which is significantly increased in diabetic 
rats receiving scrambled peptide when compared with nondiabetic con-
trols (*P &lt; 0.05). pHBSP prevented the diabetes-related increase in 
GFAP, and there was no significant difference between this group and 
the nondiabetic groups. Data are mean 6 SEM; n = 6 per group. B-E: 
Retinae from nondiabetic and diabetic groups treated with pHBSP or 
scrambled peptide exhibit GFAP immunoreactivity within astrocytes 
and a subpopulation of Müller cells. More extensive GFAP was observed 
in the Müller cells crossing the IPL and INL (depicted by dashed line) in 
the diabetic animals that received the scrambled peptide. This was re-
duced in the diabetic animals receiving the pHBSP peptide. (A high-
quality digital representation of this figure is available in the online 
issue.) </p>

<p>EPO PEPTIDE PROTECTS RETINA DURING DIABETES </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Using two established preclinical models for the early and 
late stages of diabetic retinopathy, we show that a novel 
EPO-derived peptide has a significant protective effect. 
When administered for 1 month after 6 previous months 
of diabetes, pHBSP can prevent several important lesions 
of diabetic retinopathy. These include GFAP upregulation </p>

<p>in the Müller glia, neuronal death, retinal inflammatory 
responses, and capillary degeneration. The current investi-
gation builds on a previous study using a full-length pHBSP, 
which demonstrates prevention of BRB dysfunction during 
diabetes (22), and adds compelling evidence that elements 
of EPO-R signaling can be harnessed for treating diabetic 
retinopathy. </p>

<p>FIG. 3. pHBSP protects against DNA damage in diabetic retina. pHBSP treatment prevents diabetes-induced ganglion cell death. Cntl, control; Sc, 
scrambled pHBSP; and Db, diabetic. A: Cell count of terminal deoxynucleotidyl TUNEL-positive cells in the GCL was assessed by counting the 
number of fluorescent TUNEL-positive cells in the GCL divided by total number of cells present in the GCL. TUNEL of pHBSP-treated rats showed 
a significant increase in the percentage of cells with DNA strand breaks in the GCL of diabetic rats compared with control (*P &lt; 0.05; ***P &lt; 0.001). 
Treatment with pHBSP decreased TUNEL positivity by 49% when compared with diabetic rat with scrambled pHBSP (++P &lt; 0.01). Counts were 
assessed by image analysis in multiple sections. Images were taken at three separate points (three fields at 300 mm 
2 each) on the central retina at 
340 magnification and presented as the average nuclei in the GCL. B: Cell count of TUNEL-positive cells in the entire retina was assessed by counting 
the number of fluorescent TUNEL-positive cells divided by total number of cells present. The diabetic retina treated with the scrambled peptide 
displayed TUNEL-positive cells. This was reduced to control levels of ;10% with the pHBSP peptide (**P &lt; 0.01). Data are mean 6 SEM; n = 6 per 
group. Counts were assessed by image analysis in multiple sections. Images were taken at three separate points (three fields at 300 mm 
2 each) on the 
central retina at 340 magnification and presented as the average nuclei in the GCL. pHBSP treatment prevents diabetes-induced ganglion cell death 
because there are more TUNEL-positive cells in the diabetic with scrambled pHBSP-treated animals relative to the control and scrambled pHBSP in 
the GCL and in the entire retina. Retinal nuclei were also counterstained with PI. This is evident in the images showing TUNEL positivity in control 
and Sc (C), control and pHBSP (D), diabetic and Sc (E), and diabetic and pHBSP (F). (A high-quality digital representation of this figure is available 
in the online issue.) </p>

<p>C.M. MCVICAR AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 </p>

<p>
Many previous studies have used an array of therapeutic 
approaches and shown effective protection against various 
pathological end points during diabetic retinopathy. How-
ever, these treatments were commenced at establishment 
of experimental diabetes, and very few studies have eval-
uated efficacy once diabetes is well advanced. It is sig-
nificant that the current investigation provides evidence 
that an intervention strategy, evoking EPO-mediated tis-
sue protection in the diabetic retina, has significant ben-
efits. Such a regimen has considerable clinical relevance 
since many diabetic patients have established retinopathy 
at diagnosis. 
While EPO has established protective properties in a 
range of tissues, there are major drawbacks to its clini-
cal use for tissue injury. A typical dose for treatment of 
anemia in patients is ;100 IU/kg, although to achieve tis-
sue protection, much larger doses are needed (;500 IU/kg). 
While EPO can sometimes be delivered directly to a dam-
aged tissue, this therapy can result in unwanted elevations </p>

<p>in hematocrit with associated vascular thrombosis and 
hypertension (31). Although delivered systemically in both 
models, pHBSP induced no changes in reticulocytes or he-
matocrit in the mouse or rat, respectively, despite the latter 
being delivered over a 28-day period. Such a delivery 
method appears valid since EPO crosses the BRB (14) and, 
therefore, it is likely that this 11aa peptide also crosses the 
retinal vascular endothelium. As demonstrated, this EPO 
analog appears to possess the tissue-protective advan-
tages of EPO without the disadvantages. 
Hyperglycemia is known to be associated with an in-
creased erythrocyte turnover and therefore increased 
reticulocyte production, and in the current study, we ob-
served increased reticulocytes in diabetic rats, a response 
that was attenuated by pHBSP treatment. Diabetes in-
creases marrow production of reticulocytes to maintain 
hematocrit, and there is evidence that diabetes-induced 
oxidative damage may be more prominent in reticulocytes 
compared with other tissues as a result of their high </p>

<p>FIG. 4. pHBSP and microglial activation in the diabetic retina. Retinal microglia were labeled using CD11b immunoreactivity in retinal sections and 
visualized using confocal microscopy. Cntl, control; Sc, scrambled pHBSP; and Db, diabetic. A: Mean cell counts of CD11b-positive cells were taken 
from three separate points within the central retina. There was a significant increase in microglial numbers after 7.5 months of diabetes (*P &lt; 
0.05; **P &lt; 0.01). pHBSP (10 mg/kg) had no significant effect on this diabetes-related increase (P &gt; 0.05). B: After subdividing the total number of 
microglial cell counts, there is a significant difference in the number of dendritic (nonactivated) and amoeboid (activated) cells between control 
and diabetic rats (*P &lt; 0.05). Compared with diabetic rats treated with the scrambled peptide, there are more dendritic microglia and fewer 
amoeboid in the retinae of the diabetic rats that received the scrambled pHBSP (**P &lt; 0.01 and *P &lt; 0.05). Data are mean 6 SEM; n = 6 per group. 
Sc'pHBSP, scrambled pHBSP. C-F: Images of CD11b-positive cells: control and Sc (C), control and pHBSP (D), diabetic and Sc (E), and diabetic 
and pHBSP (F). (A high-quality color representation of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>EPO PEPTIDE PROTECTS RETINA DURING DIABETES </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>content of iron and polyunsaturated fatty acids. Indeed, 
diabetic reticulocytes show increased lipid peroxidation 
and decreased levels of antioxidants when compared with 
nondiabetic counterparts. The assay we used did not as-
sess viability of reticulocytes, so there may be a greater 
turnover in the diabetic rats. Certainly there was no in-
crease in erythrocytes between groups. Tissue-protective 
molecules, such as pHBSP, are active in attenuating these 
pathological processes, and although not determined in 
our experiments, presumably this peptide could serve to 
reduce early erythrocyte senescence. 
EPO is known to be strongly proangiogenic through 
typical VEGF-mediated pathways (20). While EPO-mediated 
angiogenesis can significantly improve wound repair (32), 
postinfarction myocardial vascular remodeling (33), and 
reperfusion of cerebral ischemia (34), such angiogenic 
responses in the context of retinopathy raise significant 
concerns. This is reinforced by reports that EPO levels are 
raised in the vitreous of patients with proliferative diabetic 
retinopathy (17). However, several experimental studies 
show that early administration of EPO can protect neurons, 
prevent vessel degeneration, and subsequently suppress 
the stimulus for hypoxia-induced neovascularization (15) 
by evoking beneficial intraretinal angiogenesis (20). Nev-
ertheless, the disease phase at which EPO is introduced 
may alter the outcome, and EPO treatment-while the 
retina is experiencing hypoxia-may enhance pathological, </p>

<p>preretinal neovascularization (15). Therefore, a major find-
ing of the current study is that pHBSP not only prevents 
early stage pathology but also fails to evoke preretinal 
neovascularization and, thus, carries considerably less risk 
than recombinant EPO if used in diabetic patients. 
Proinflammatory pathways contribute to neuroglial and 
microvascular lesions during diabetic retinopathy, as evi-
denced by the upregulation of proinflammatory cytokines 
from the Müller glia (35) and microglia (36), which show 
strong associative links to capillary degeneration (37). 
Microglia in particular are the resident immune cells of the 
retina, and their activation, combined with infiltration of 
circulating monocytes into the neuropile, could play an 
important regulatory role in diabetic retinopathy through 
cytokine expression and related cell responses (38). It 
is interesting that pHBSP reduced constitutive expression 
levels of some cytokines in normal retina, for example, 
IL-1b. The reason for this is unclear but may be related to 
slightly elevated levels in older rats and the potential for 
pHBSP to interfere with proinflammatory signaling. In brain 
ischemia, microglial responses have been shown to be 
suppressed by EPO-related therapy (39), and there may be 
similar dampening of microglial activation, and associated 
proinflammatory cytokine expression is suppressed by 
pHBSP in diabetic retinopathy. 
Protection against neuroglial apoptosis and associated 
inflammatory cascades is an established benefit of EPO </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Cytokine expression in the diabetic retina is regulated by pHBSP A: IL-10 was decreased in the diabetic rat with scrambled pHBSP relative 
to the control with scrambled pHBSP (***P &lt; 0.001). The level of IL-10, the anti-inflammatory cytokine, was elevated again with pHBSP in the 
diabetic rat when compared with the scrambled pHBSP (+P &lt; 0.05). B: TNF-a was increased in the diabetic rat, which received 10 mg/kg of 
scrambled pHBSP, relative to the control, which received the scrambled pHBSP (***P &lt; 0.001). This elevated level in the diabetic rat was sig-
nificantly decreased with the active pHBSP (+++P &lt; 0.001). C: IL-6 was increased in the diabetic rat, which received 10 mg/kg of scrambled pHBSP, 
relative to the control, which received the scrambled pHBSP (***P &lt; 0.001). This elevated level in the diabetic rat was significantly decreased with 
the active pHBSP (+++P &lt; 0.001). D: STZ-induced diabetes caused a reduction in IL-1b levels when compared with control tissue treated with 
scrambled peptide (***P &lt; 0.001). Treatment with pHBSP caused a reduction in IL-1b levels both in nondiabetic tissue and diabetic tissue (***P &lt; 
0.001; +++P &lt; 0.001). The number of animals in each group was six. Cntl, control; Sc, scrambled pHBSP; and Db, diabetic. </p>

<p>C.M. MCVICAR AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 </p>

<p>
treatment to damaged tissues such as ischemic brain. There 
are likely to be comparable benefits for the diabetic retina 
since progressive retinal neuronal and Müller cell dys-
function, DNA damage, and cell death have been pre-
viously demonstrated (40), although in rats this may take 
.4 months to become evident (25). In the current study, 
the TUNEL-positive cells in the retina are likely to repre-
sent DNA damage in a range of neurons and glia but not 
necessarily apoptotic death. This argument is strengthened 
by the caspase-3 data in this study. The 8-OHdG staining 
observed in the ONL of the diabetic retina suggests that 
there is extensive DNA damage, which is also indicated 
by TUNEL. While EPO can inhibit neural cell apoptosis 
(14), it can also upregulate enzymes that scavenge oxygen 
radicals during brain ischemia (41) and protect against 
DNA damage (42). Wang et al. (18) have recently reported </p>

<p>EPO-mediated protection against oxidative damage in the 
diabetic retina long before ischemia is present, and this 
may account for the observed reduction in DNA damage 
evoked by pHBSP treatment. In the current study, pHBSP 
(1 mg/kg) reduced retinal ischemia in the murine model, 
although the response was more apparent at the lower 
concentration. This may reflect commonly observed cyto-
kine responses that are likely related to receptor dynamics 
and are often characterized by a U-shaped dose response 
curve (hormesis). 
Suppression of DNA damage, apoptosis, inflammation, 
and oxidative stress-related pathways undoubtedly affect 
capillary degeneration during diabetic retinopathy (43). 
While pHBSP treatment could significantly modulate all 
these pathways, it is perhaps surprising that 1 month of 
treatment with pHBSP after 6 previous months of diabetes </p>

<p>FIG. 6. pHBSP prevents retinal capillary degeneration during diabetes. The retinal vasculature was visualized in flat mounts using concomitant 
labeling of endothelium (isolectin) and basement membrane (collagen IV). Acellular capillaries can be visualized by continuance of collagen IV 
positivity but loss of endothelium. Cntl, control; Sc, scrambled pHBSP; and Db, diabetic. A: Graph showing the number of acellular capillaries in 
retina in the peripheral and central retina. Diabetic rats with scrambled pHBSP displayed more acellular capillaries than control rats, which re-
ceived the scrambled pHBSP (*P &lt; 0.05). The pHBSP peptide significantly reduced the number of the acellular capillaries to normal levels in the 
inner retina (+P &lt; 0.05). Data are mean 6 SEM; n = 6 per group. B and C: Images showing acellular capillaries (arrows) in the diabetic animals that 
received the scrambled peptide. Acellular capillaries are observed when vessels are collagen IV positive (red) and negative for lectin (green). 
There are more acellular vessel profiles present in the diabetic retina that received the scramble peptide relative to the diabetic animals that 
received the pHBSP peptide. Sc'pHBSP, scrambled pHBSP. (A high-quality digital representation of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>EPO PEPTIDE PROTECTS RETINA DURING DIABETES </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>could have such a marked effect on reversal of acellular 
vessels. Death of retinal capillary component cells during 
diabetes is not necessarily linear, and the progressive 
nature of many pathogenic pathways indicates that endo-
theliopathy and pericyte death are the result of accumu-
lative abnormalities in the early stages of diabetes. Indeed, 
acellular capillaries are not usually evident until at least 
4-5 months of hyperglycemia (44). Although not evaluated 
in the current investigation, it should also be considered 
that activation of the EPO-Rs could mobilize vasoreparative 
endothelial progenitor cells (EPCs) into the circulating 
blood to target areas of hypoxia. The mechanism(s) by 
which EPCs mobilize and home to areas of ischemia are 
complex but involve stimulatory factors such as EPO (45) 
and VEGF (46). Diabetes causes EPC dysfunction, and this </p>

<p>is associated with impaired vascular repair in diabetic 
retinopathy (47); it is possible that systemic delivery of 
pHBSP in diabetic rats could have enhanced EPC mobi-
lization and thereby improved reparative function in a 
comparable manner to that described for EPO (48). This 
requires further study. 
In summary, the current study indicates that the TPR 
pathway could play a key role in preventing early stage 
diabetic retinopathy and thereby progression to the sight-
threatening late stages. The ability to use a therapeutic 
approach that harnesses all the tissue-protective and anti-
inflammatory benefits of EPO without risking the poten-
tially damaging collateral effects would be a major advance 
for neurovascular degenerative diseases such as diabetic 
retinopathy. </p>

<p>FIG. 7. pHBSP decreases ischemia at 1 mg/kg and exacerbates preretinal neovascularization in OIR. The murine retinal vasculature was assessed in 
flat mounts after OIR using isolectin labeling and confocal microscopy. A: Retinal ischemia: pHBSP at 1 mg/kg decreases the ischemic region (***P &lt; 
0.001), while the higher doses of 10 and 30 mg/kg have no effect on ischemia. B: Retinal neovascularization: upon quantification of preretinal 
vessels, pHBSP had no significant effect on neovascularization at any of the doses tested (1, 10, and 30 mg/kg) when compared with the scrambled 
peptide or PBS control. Data are mean 6 SEM; n = 6 per group. PBS, PBS control; Sc, scrambled pHBSP. C and D: Retinal flat mounts showing 
hyperfluorescent preretinal neovascularization in PBS-treated (C) and 1 mg/kg of pHBSP-treated (D) OIR mice (arrow). (A high-quality color 
representation of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>C.M. MCVICAR AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 </p>

<p>
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This research was funded by Fight for Sight (Grant number 
1688), the Juvenile Diabetes Research Foundation (JDRF), 
and the Department of Education and Learning, Northern 
Ireland. A.W.S. holds a Royal Society Wolfson Foundation 
Merit Award. M.B. and A.C. are employed by Araim 
Pharmaceuticals. No other potential conflicts of interest 
relevant to this article were reported. 
C.M.M. designed the experiments, researched data, and 
wrote the manuscript. R.H. designed the experiments and 
researched data. L.M.C. researched data. T.A.G. was in-
volved in the design of the experiments and contributed to 
the manuscript. M.B. designed the peptide for the study 
and was involved in the design of the experiments. A.C. 
designed the peptide for the study and contributed to the 
manuscript. A.W.S. led the project, obtained funding, 
designed the experiments, and wrote the manuscript. </p>



<p>EPO PEPTIDE PROTECTS RETINA DURING DIABETES </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>



<p>C.M. MCVICAR AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>