<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3392846" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective Competing tools are available online to assess 
the risk of developing certain conditions of interest, such 
as cardiovascular disease. While predictive models have 
been developed and validated on data from cohort 
studies, little attention has been paid to ensure the 
reliability of such predictions for individuals, which is 
critical for care decisions. The goal was to develop 
a patient-driven adaptive prediction technique to improve 
personalized risk estimation for clinical decision support. 
Material and methods A data-driven approach was 
proposed that utilizes individualized confidence intervals 
(CIs) to select the most 'appropriate' model from a pool 
of candidates to assess the individual patient's clinical 
condition. The method does not require access to the 
training dataset. This approach was compared with other 
strategies: the BEST model (the ideal model, which can 
only be achieved by access to data or knowledge of 
which population is most similar to the individual), 
CROSS model, and RANDOM model selection. 
Results When evaluated on clinical datasets, the 
approach significantly outperformed the CROSS model 
selection strategy in terms of discrimination (p&lt;1ee14) 
and calibration (p&lt;0.006). The method outperformed the 
RANDOM model selection strategy in terms of 
discrimination (p&lt;1ee12), but the improvement did not 
achieve significance for calibration (p¼0.1375). 
Limitations The CI may not always offer enough 
information to rank the reliability of predictions, and this 
evaluation was done using aggregation. If a particular 
individual is very different from those represented in 
a training set of existing models, the CI may be 
somewhat misleading. 
Conclusion This approach has the potential to offer 
more reliable predictions than those offered by other 
heuristics for disease risk estimation of individual 
patients. </p>

<p>Complexity in decisions involving multiple factors 
and variability in interpretation of data motivate 
the development of computerized techniques to 
assist humans in decision-making. 1e3 Predictive 
models are used in medical practice, for example, 
for automating the discovery of drug treatment 
patterns in an electronic health record, 4 improving 
patient safety via automated laboratory-based 
adverse event grading, 5 prioritizing the national 
liver transplant 'queue' given the severity of 
disease, 6 predicting the outcome of renal trans-
plantation, 7 guiding the treatment of hypercholes-
terolemia, 8 making prognoses for patients 
undergoing certain procedures, 9 10 and estimating 
the success of assisted reproduction techniques. 11 </p>

<p>Numerous risk assessment tools for medical deci-
sion support are available on the web 12e14 and are 
increasingly available for smart phones. 15e17 
While many predictive models have been devel-
oped and validated on data from cohort studies, 
little attention has been paid to ensure the reli-
ability of a prediction for an individual, which is 
critical for point-of-care decisions. Because the goal 
of predictive models is to estimate outcomes in new 
patients (who may or may not be similar to the 
patients used to develop the model), a critical 
challenge in prognostic research is to determine 
what evidence beyond validation is needed before 
practitioners can confidently apply a model to their 
patients. 18 This is important to determine 
a patient's individual risk. 19e21 As each model is 
constructed using different features, parameters, 
and samples, specific models may work best for 
certain subgroups of individuals. For example, 
many calculators and charts use the Framingham 
model to estimate cardiovascular disease (CVD) 
risk. 8 22e24 These models work well, but may 
underestimate the CVD risk in patients with dia-
betes. 25 Table 1 illustrates a case in which a patient 
can get significantly different CVD risk scores from 
different online risk estimation calculators. This 
type of inconsistency provides another motivation 
for selecting an appropriate model. 29 
In order to obtain a patient-specific recommen-
dation at the point of care, it is necessary that 
physicians interpret the information in the context 
of that patient. These scenarios are related to 
personalized medicine, which emphasizes the 
customization of healthcare. 30 31 In this research, 
we address the problem of selecting the most 
appropriate model for assessing the risk for 
a particular patient. We developed an algorithm for 
online model selection based on the CI of predic-
tions so that clinicians can choose the model at the 
point of care for their patients, as illustrated in 
figure 1. 
Our approach is purely data driven because it 
adapts to any 'appropriate' model that is available 
for assessing the risk of a patient without the 
need for external knowledge. The 'appropriateness' 
refers to the ability of the model to generate 
a narrow CI for the individualized prediction. 
The article is organized as follows: the following 
paragraphs present related work, the Methods 
section introduces the details of the proposed 
method, the Results section presents results on 
simulated and clinically related datasets, and the 
Discussion section discusses advantages and 
limitations. </p>

<p>&lt; Additional appendices are 
published online only. To view 
these files please visit the 
journal online (www.jamia.bmj. 
com/content/19/e1.toc). </p>

<p>A possible approach to determining the best model for 
a patient is to compare the patient with individuals in the study 
population used to build the model. However, it is non-trivial to 
gather datasets from every published study. The barriers are 
partly related to the laws and regulations on privacy and 
confidentiality. 32 Therefore, we aimed at developing a new 
method to determine the most reliable predictive model for an 
individual from a candidate pool of models without requiring 
the availability of training datasets. Note that our motivation 
for selecting the appropriate model in a distributed environment 
is somewhat different from the one that motivates adaptive 
model selection. Adaptive model selection operates in a central-
ized environment and searches for an optimal subset of patterns 
from the entire training set to minimize certain loss functions. 33 
The idea of data-driven model selection for medical decision 
support is related to dynamic switching and mixture models, 34 
which emphasize capturing the structural changes over time to 
adapt a predictive model. Fox et al 35 proposed a method for learning 
and switching between an unknown number of dynamic modes 
with possibly varying state dimensions. Huang et al 36 presented 
a segmentation approach that divided deterministic dynamics in 
a higher-dimensional space into segments of patterns. Siddiqui and 
Medioni 37 developed an efficient and robust method of tracking 
human forearms by leveraging a state transition diagram, which 
adaptively selected the appropriate model for the current observa-
tion. Other methods were used in the context of wireless sensor 
networks in which the goal was to provide an effective way to 
reduce the communication effort while guaranteeing that user-
specified accuracy requirements were met. For example, Le Borgne 
et al 38 suggested a lightweight, online algorithm that allowed 
sensor nodes to determine autonomously a statistically good 
performing model among a set of candidate models. 
However, most of the aforementioned methods describing 
real-world physical systems are not directly applicable to 
medical decision support because they rely on physical laws that 
are not applicable to medical decision-making. We propose </p>

<p>a novel data-driven method to estimate the probability of the 
binary outcome for each new patient. In particular, based on 
patient characteristics, our method chooses the model that is 
most appropriate (ie, the one with the narrowest CI) from a set 
of candidate models and uses its predicted probability. </p>

<p>METHODS 
A patient-driven adaptive prediction technique </p>

<p>We consider a binary classification task. Let Y K ˛f0; 1g and X K ¼ 
&lt; x 1 ,.,x i .,x n &gt;, respectively be the true class label (ie, the 
outcome of interest) and the vector of feature values (ie, the 
vector representing values for age, gender, blood pressure, etc) of 
the kth individual. Then, X j and Y j (j˛ð1; .; mÞ correspond to 
the jth subpopulation of individuals from the training popula-
tion (X j 4 X, Y j 4 Y), where X and Y denote the corpus of 
features and class labels in the entire population, respectively. 
Note that m denotes the number of models, which are trained 
from individual pairs of feature vectors X j and label vectors Y j . 
In particular, we can build a classifier f j : X J /Y J by minimizing 
some loss function, for example, the hinge loss for a support 
vector machine 39 40 or the Hamming distance for a model based 
on conditional random fields. 41 42 
To simplify the analysis, we assume that all candidate models 
are constructed by minimizing the log loss function commonly 
used in logistic regression, as this is a model widely used and 
published in biomedical research, 21 43e45 but that they use 
different training populations. Under this scenario, imagine 
a test pattern X* (ie, feature values of a new patient) that 
corresponds to the clinical findings and demographic informa-
tion of a patient for whom we want to assess the risk of 
developing CVD. Given a finite number of models f 1 ,.,f i ,.,f m 
built on different training data in previous studies, the question 
is which model would be most appropriate for a novel pattern 
X* encountered at the point of care. 
Intuitively, we can think of finding out which model used 
a training set population that best matches X*, and choose that 
model built to predict the outcome of X*. In reality, however, 
this is often impossible because the training data are often 
unavailable. In addition, the computational burden of case-wise 
comparisons is huge, and thus may not be applicable at the 
point of care. Therefore, a practical solution to the problem 
should avoid the need for accessing the training data. Our 
approach, a patient-driven adaptive prediction technique 
(ADAPT), only needs the model coefficients (ie, the weights of 
a logistic regression model), and the covariance matrix of these 
coefficients to assess the reliability of their predictions. In 
particular, we pick the model f* that generates the narrowest 
CI for the prediction of a test pattern X* </p>

<p>f Ã </p>

<p>X Ã </p>

<p>¼ argmin jCIjðXÃÞj f j ðX Ã </p>

<p>; cj˛ </p>

<p>1; .; m </p>

<p>
(1) </p>

<p>where CI j (X*) is the CI of the jth model predicting the test 
pattern X*, and m is the number of available models to choose </p>

<p>Table 1 The same patient can get different risk scores from different 
online tools </p>

<p>Patient: Bob 
Age, years 
38 
Smoker 
Yes 
Total cholesterol 
235 mg/dl 
HDL cholesterol 
39 mg/dl 
Treatment for HBP 
Yes 
. 
. </p>

<p>Systolic blood pressure 
145 mm Hg 
Family history of early heart disease 
Yes </p>

<p>Bob's cardiovascular disease risk 
<rs type="software">NHLBI risk assessment web tool</rs> 26 
16% 
American Heart Association online 27 
25% 
Cleveland Clinic 28 
20% </p>

<p>HBP, high blood pressure; HDL, high-density lipoprotein; NHLBI, National Heart, Lung, and 
Blood Institute. </p>

<p>Figure 1 A clinician has to decide at 
the point of care which model to use, 
given the characteristic of the patient. 
Note that p* is the probability estimate 
for this particular patient. CI is the 
confidence interval for this estimate, or 
prediction. The clinician chooses the 
model that produces the prediction with 
the narrowest CI. </p>

<p>e138 
J Am Med Inform Assoc 2012;19:e137ee144. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2011-000751 </p>

<p>Research and applications </p>

<p>from. The CI of individual predictions are calculated using the 
covariance matrix of the coefficients 46 and the feature values for 
the individual. In well-specified models, the non-diagonal </p>

<p>elements of this matrix should be close to zero. For a well-
specified model, the CI is wider if a test pattern is closer to the 
decision boundary; it is narrower if a test pattern (ie, feature </p>

<p>Figure 2 Applying a logistic regression (LR) model to four 
test patterns (stars) in two dimensions. The dots correspond 
to positive and negative samples drawn from two Gaussian 
distributions N ((2,1), (2,0;0,2)) and N ((À2,À1), (4,0;0,3)), 
respectively. Each graph illustrates a test pattern, a 95% CI 
in the output space, and its neighborhood convex hull (ie, 
points that receive similar estimates by the model). </p>

<p>-8 
-6 
-4 
-2 
0 
2 
4 
6 
-6 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Attribute 1 </p>

<p>Attribute 2 </p>

<p>Dense region close to the decision boundary </p>

<p>Data positive </p>

<p>Data negative </p>

<p>Decision Boundary 
Test Point 
Convex Hull </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 
400 
0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Index of the test samples </p>

<p>Probability </p>

<p>LR Ouputs 
Lower bound 
Upper bound 
95% Confidence Interval </p>

<p>95% CI </p>

<p>-10 
-8 
-6 
-4 
-2 
0 
2 
4 
6 
8 
-6 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Attribute 1 </p>

<p>Attribute 2 </p>

<p>Dense region far from the decision boundary </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 
400 
0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Index of the test samples </p>

<p>Probability </p>

<p>95% 
CI </p>

<p>-8 
-6 
-4 
-2 
0 
2 
4 
6 
-6 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Attribute 1 </p>

<p>Attribute 2 </p>

<p>Sparse region close to the decision boundary </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 
400 
0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Index of the test samples </p>

<p>Probability 
95% CI </p>

<p>-8 
-6 
-4 
-2 
0 
2 
4 
6 
-6 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Attribute 1 </p>

<p>Attribute 2 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D Sparse region from the decision boundary </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 
400 
0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Index of the test samples </p>

<p>Probability </p>

<p>95% CI </p>

<p>J Am Med Inform Assoc 2012;19:e137ee144. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2011-000751 
e139 </p>

<p>Research and applications </p>

<p>values of a new patient) is further away from the decision 
boundary. Another factor determining the width of the CI is 
associated with the 'local density' in the region where the test 
pattern would lie if it were part of the training set. That is, in 
areas with high density, the prediction is more stable, and thus it 
has a smaller CI. Away from high-density areas, the predictions 
become less stable, as there is weaker evidence to support the 
predictions. 
Both situations are illustrated in figure 2, where simulated 
data are used to build a logistic regression model. Different test 
patterns were arbitrarily selected to illustrate the effects of 
a point (1) being in a dense region (ie, several individuals with 
similar characteristics) versus a sparse region (ie, few individuals 
with similar characteristics), and (2) being close the zone of 
highest uncertainty, the decision boundary. We illustrate the 
four possible combinations, ie, a point close to the decision 
boundary in a dense region, close to the decision boundary in 
a sparse region, far from the decision boundary in a dense region, 
and far from the decision boundary in a sparse region. The 
widths of their CI are summarized in table 2. The values in the 
first column are smaller than those in the second column. This 
illustrates our first point that the CI get narrower when the test 
pattern is further away from the decision boundary. On the 
other hand, the values in the first row are smaller than those in 
the second row, which illustrates our second point that narrow 
CI are associated with dense regions. The narrowest CI (ie, 0.02) 
among these four arbitrarily selected illustration points corre-
sponds to the prediction of the pattern lying in a dense region far 
from the decision boundary. For details, please refer to our 
discussion about mathematical implications of individualized CI 
in supplementary appendix A (available online only). </p>

<p>Data description </p>

<p>We used both simulated data and a clinical dataset to demon-
strate the algorithm. The simulated data were simple and 
designed to make it easy to understand how the algorithm 
works through visualization and perfect knowledge of the gold 
standard. The clinical data were used to illustrate the algorithm 
in a more realistic scenario. </p>

<p>Simulated data </p>

<p>To verify the efficacy of the proposed method, we simulated two 
datasets (X A , X B ) by sampling from two-dimensional Gaussian </p>

<p>distributions, Nðð1:5; 1:5Þ; 
h 1; 0 </p>

<p>0; 1 </p>

<p>i 
and, NððÀ1; À1Þ; 
h 1; 0 </p>

<p>0; 1 </p>

<p>i 
, </p>

<p>respectively. Next, we assigned class labels of these simulated 
data using the logistic regression model, ie, drawing random 
samples from the binomial distribution using probability 
pÀ ¼ logit À1 ðu 0 þ + </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i¼1 u i x l </p>

<p>i Þ, where x l 
i is the ith feature of the ith </p>

<p>sample in one of the simulated datasets and W ¼ ½u 0 ; u 1 ; u 2  9 is </p>

<p>the weight (ie, intercept and coefficients) parameter. In particular, 
we used weight vectors that are nearly orthogonal to each other 
(W A ¼ ½À0:3; 0:5; 0:5 9 ), W B ¼ ½0; À0:5; 0:5 9 so that class labels 
generated by one model would generalize poorly to the other. 
For both datasets, we drew 300 samples, of which 80% were 
used for training, and the remaining 20% were used for testing. 
Figure 3 illustrates an instance of both datasets, and decision 
boundaries of logistic regression models learned from them. One 
can see that the decision boundaries are close to orthogonal, 
which matches our simulation. 
We repeated the sampling process 50 times to evaluate the 
overall performance of our proposed method for picking the 
right prediction model. We compared it with two other model 
selection techniques. Table 3 lists different strategies for model 
selection. Note that BEST, which includes A2A and B2B, was 
meant to have the best performance (ie, expected to have the 
best results because data from a test set from population X are 
used in a model built from a training set from population X), 
CROSS, which includes B2A and A2B that were meant to be 
baselines of the CROSS model selection strategy (ie, expected to 
have the worst performance, because models trained on 
a training set from population X are tested on a sample 
from population Y), and RANDOM, which refers to 
a RANDOM model selection strategy, was meant to represent 
what online users might be doing (ie, they use any calculator 
they can find online), which is expected to have an intermediary 
performance between the best and worst model selection 
strategies. We acknowledge that the simulation data cannot 
serve as a 'perfect benchmark'. The goal was to illustrate the 
efficacy of ADAPT in a simple and intuitive two-dimensional 
case. An evaluation in a more realistic dataset is certainly </p>

<p>Table 2 Width of CI of predictions of test patterns in figure 1AeD </p>

<p>Local density </p>

<p>Distance to decision boundary </p>

<p>Near 
Far </p>

<p>High 
0.19 
0.02 
Low 
0.58 
0.17 </p>

<p>-4 
-3 
-2 
-1 
0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
-4 </p>

<p>-3 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Attribute 1 </p>

<p>Attribute 2 </p>

<p>Positive 
Negative 
LR </p>

<p>-4 
-3 
-2 
-1 
0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
-4 </p>

<p>-3 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Attribute 1 </p>

<p>Attribute 2 </p>

<p>Positive 
Negative 
LR </p>

<p>-4 
-3 
-2 
-1 
0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
-4 </p>

<p>-3 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Attribute 1 </p>

<p>Attribute 2 </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Figure 3 Simulated datasets for model evaluation. The first and second subfigures show datasets XA, XB, and decision boundaries logistic 
regression (LR)(A), LR(B) learned from each dataset. We show both datasets combined, and their nearly orthogonal decision boundaries in the last 
figure. </p>

<p> 
J Am Med Inform Assoc 2012;19:e137ee144. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2011-000751 </p>

<p>Research and applications </p>

<p>warranted, so we also compared those four strategies using 
clinical data. </p>

<p>Clinical data </p>

<p>We applied our method to two clinical datasets for illustration 
purposes. The myocardial infarction (MI) data contain infor-
mation about patients with and without MI. These patients 
were seen at emergency departments at two medical centers in 
the UK, 47 where 500 patients with chest pain were observed in 
Sheffield, England, and 1253 patients with the same symptoms 
were observed in Edinburgh, Scotland. The total number of 
patients is 1753, and the feature size is 48. The target is a binary 
variable indicating whether a patient had an MI or not. 
We preprocessed those data by replacing every categorical 
feature by a number of binary ones to preserve the categorical 
information. To construct learning models, we randomly split 
both datasets into (80%/20%) training and test sets. Note that 
the proportion of the positive outcomes of training and test sets 
were approximately the same. We compared our proposed 
method, ADAPT, with other strategies, as indicated in table 4. 
Similar to the simulation study, E2E and S2S were meant to 
represent the best performing strategies, S2E and E2S represent 
baselines of CROSS model selection (ie, the worst performing 
strategy), and RANDOM refers to the RANDOM model selec-
tion strategy, similar to what we did for the simulated data. 
We repeated the random split 50 times, and evaluated 
discrimination and calibration, as explained next. </p>

<p>Evaluation methods </p>

<p>We used two measures, the area under the receiver operating 
characteristic curve (AUC) 48 and the HosmereLemeshow good-
ness-of-fit test (HL test), 49 to evaluate the performance of </p>

<p>predictive models in terms of discrimination and calibration, 
respectively. In particular, we used a one-tailed paired t test to 
compare the performance of the models through cross-validation. </p>

<p>Area under the receiver operating characteristic curve </p>

<p>The AUC measures the predictive model's ability to discriminate 
positive and negative cases: an AUC of 0.5 corresponds to 
a random assignment into one of the two categories, and an 
AUC of 1.0 corresponds to a perfect assignment. Predictive 
models used in medical decision-making vary widely between 
these two extremes, but most published models have AUC 
exceeding 0.7, and just a few have AUC over 0.9. </p>

<p>HL test </p>

<p>The HL test measures how well the model fits the data. As there 
is no gold standard for the probability estimate for one indi-
vidual, cases are pooled into groups and the sum of probabilities 
in the groups is compared with the sum of positive cases in these </p>

<p>groups using a c 2 test. When the p value for the test is below </p>

<p>0.05, we reject the hypothesis that the model fits the data well. 
Note that we adopted the C version of the HL test for which 
equal-sized subgroups (ie, deciles in our case) are sorted by 
probability estimates. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Figure 4 shows the AUC and p values of the HL test obtained by 
applying different model selection strategies to the simulated 
data (described in the Simulated data section). The strategies of 
comparison include the BEST strategy (ie, A2A and B2B), the 
CROSS strategy (ie, B2A and A2B), the RANDOM strategy, and 
the ADAPT strategy. There are four plots in this figure. The first 
two plots (ie, subfigures on the first row) correspond, respec-
tively, to AUC and to the p values of the HL test, after applying 
all four strategies to the test set originating from A. The last two 
plots (ie, subfigures on the second row) show the results of 
applying the model on the test set originating from B. Our 
method labeled ADAPT significantly outperforms the CROSS 
and RANDOM model selection strategies for both indices, as 
indicated by the p values in the figure. As expected, the CROSS 
strategy (ie, B2A and A2B) performed poorly. 
In figure 5, we illustrate the results of applying different 
model selection strategies to the clinical data (described in the 
Clinical data section). The strategies compared include BEST (ie, 
E2E and S2S), CROSS (ie, E2S and S2E), RANDOM, and 
ADAPT. 
In the first experiment with the Sheffield data, ADAPT has 
higher discrimination than the CROSS strategy E2S (p&lt;1ee14) 
and the RANDOM strategy (p&lt;1ee12) based on a one-tailed 
paired t test. Our method also demonstrates better calibration 
performance than the CROSS strategy E2S (p¼0.006), but it is 
not significantly better than the RANDOM strategy (p¼0.14). 
Our approach demonstrated very comparable discrimination 
(p¼0.85) and calibration (p¼0.84) with the BEST strategy S2S, 
the ideal situation of using the same population to evaluate 
a test case. 
The second experiment with the Edinburgh data involves 
more testing samples compared with the Sheffield experiment. 
The AUC of our proposed method was significantly higher than 
both the CROSS strategy S2E (p&lt;1ee43) and the RANDOM 
strategy (p&lt;1ee33), and it was comparable to that of the BEST 
strategy E2E (p¼1.0). The calibration of our method was better 
than those of two other strategies (S2E p¼0.0017, RANDOM 
p¼0.0072), and it was comparable to the BEST strategy E2E 
(p¼0.60), the ideal scenario for testing. Figure 6 shows the </p>

<p>Table 3 Different strategies (BEST, CROSS, RANDOM, and ADAPT) to 
choose a model to predict simulated test cases </p>

<p>Strategies 
Details </p>

<p>BEST 
A2A 
Trained on A (80%), evaluated on A (20%). 
B2B 
Trained on B (80%), evaluated on B (20%). 
CROSS 
A2B 
Trained on A (80%), evaluated on B (20%). 
B2A 
Trained on B (80%), evaluated on A (20%). 
RANDOM 
Randomly selected model learned from either 
training set of A or B to evaluate the test cases. 
ADAPT 
Use our proposed method to choose a model 
for each of the test cases. </p>

<p>Table 4 Different strategies (BEST, CROSS, RANDOM, and ADAPT) to 
choose the model to predict test cases </p>

<p>Strategies 
Details </p>

<p>BEST 
E2E 
Trained on Edinburgh data (80%), evaluated 
on Edinburgh data (20%). 
S2S 
Trained on Sheffield data (80%), evaluated 
on Sheffield data (20%). 
CROSS 
E2S 
Trained on Edinburgh data (80%), evaluated 
on Sheffield data (20%). 
S2E 
Trained on Sheffield data (80%), evaluated 
on Edinburgh data (20%). 
RANDOM 
Pick a random model learned from either 
training set to evaluate a given test set. 
ADAPT 
Use our proposed method to choose model. </p>

<p>J Am Med Inform Assoc 2012;19:e137ee144. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2011-000751 
e141 </p>

<p>Research and applications </p>

<p>distributions of models picked by ADAPT. As expected, most 
Sheffield test cases selected the model based on the Sheffield 
training data, and the equivalent result was true for the Edin-
burgh test cases. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We investigated challenges in selecting models to predict risks 
for individual patients. While many previous studies have 
shown good predictive accuracy for cohort studies, they did not 
always make clear which model would be most appropriate for 
an individual. Due to the real-world concerns related to privacy 
and confidentiality, 50 it is often difficult to access the raw data 
that were used to construct these predictive models. We devel-
oped ADAPT to consider the model-specific information that 
may be published without the accompanying training datasets. 
Many articles describe the coefficients and their p values, but the 
publication of variance of coefficients or their CI is less frequent. 
Even rarer is the publication of the full covariance matrices, 
although preprocessing to eliminate variables with high corre-
lation makes the non-diagonal elements relatively unimportant. 
The matrix diagonal (ie, the variance of the parameters) contains 
the information that is critical for our method. We believe </p>

<p>authors would be willing to disclose these matrix diagonals, as 
they do not increase the risk of subject re-identification signifi-
cantly. In addition, if online calculators included the CI for 
a prediction (which is currently not the case), it would be trivial 
to 'manually' select the model associated with the narrowest CI 
for a particular prediction. Our approach automates this process 
and exhibits adequate discrimination and calibration, as 
measured by the AUC and the HL test in the prediction of risks 
for an individual patient. It adaptively picks the model that is 
most appropriate for the individual at hand given the available 
information. 
Another advantage of ADAPT is that the approach can assess 
models trained differently. In practice, even for the same risk 
prediction task, different institutions might build their models 
with different features, for example, the three CVD risk 
models 26e28 shown in table 1 used seven, 17, and eight feature 
variables, respectively. The model from the American Heart 
Association 27 consists of a superset of features included in the 
other models (ie, National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute 26 
and Cleveland Clinic). 28 Such differences, however, would not be 
an obstacle for ADAPT, as our model always evaluates 'appro-
priateness' in output space, which is one-dimensional. As long as </p>

<p>Figure 4 Comparison of different 
strategies including BEST (A2A and 
B2B), CROSS (A2B and B2A), 
RANDOM, and ADAPT in discrimination 
(area under the receiver operating 
characteristic curve; AUC) and 
calibration (p value for 
HosmereLemeshow (HL) decile-based 
test) using simulated data. Note that 
x6y in the labels of the x-axis indicates 
that the mean equals x, and the 
standard deviation equals y. </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>B 2B (0 .6 7± 0. 07 ) 
A 2B (0 .4 9± 0. 08 ) 
R A N D O M (0 .5 6± 0. 08 ) 
A D A P T (0 .6 0± 0. 1 0) </p>

<p>AUCs based on test data originating from B </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B 2B (0 .3 3± 0. 25 ) 
A 2B (0 .0 2± 0. 07 ) 
R A N D O M (0 .0 4± 0. 10 ) 
A D A P T (0 .1 5± 0. 2 2) </p>

<p>p values of the HL test on test data originating from B </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>A 2A (0 .6 9± 0. 08 ) 
B 2A (0 .5 1± 0. 09 ) 
R A N D O M (0 .5 8± 0. 08 ) 
A D A P T (0 .6 5± 0. 0 8) </p>

<p>AUCs based on test data originating from A </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>A 2A (0 .3 4± 0. 24 ) 
B 2A (0 .0 8± 0. 18 ) 
R A N D O M (0 .1 1± 0. 22 ) 
A D A P T (0 .3 3± 0. 2 5) </p>

<p>p values of the HL test on test data originating from A </p>

<p>p=0.03 </p>

<p>p&lt;0.01 
p&lt;0.01 
p&lt;0.01 
p=0.97 
p&lt;0.01 
p=0.82 </p>

<p>p&lt;0.01 
p&lt;0.01 
p=0.99 
p&lt;0.01 
p=1.00 </p>

<p>Figure 5 Comparison of effectiveness 
of different strategies (ie, BEST, 
CROSS, RANDOM, and ADAPT) in 
discrimination (area under the receiver 
operating characteristic curve; AUC) 
and calibration (p value for 
HosmereLemeshow (HL) decile-based 
test) for the clinical data. Note that 
x6y in the labels of the x-axis indicates 
that the mean equals x, and the SD 
equals y. </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.85 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>S 2S 
(0 .8 6± 0. 03 ) 
E 2S 
(0 .8 3± 0. 03 ) </p>

<p>R A N D O M (0 .8 3± 0. 03 ) 
A D A P T (0 .8 6± 0. 03 ) </p>

<p>AUCs based on test Sheffield data </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>S 2S 
(0 .1 3± 0. 23 ) 
E 2S 
(0 .0 4± 0. 14 ) </p>

<p>R A N D O M (0 .0 7± 0. 15 ) 
A D A P T (0 .1 0± 0. 17 ) </p>

<p>p values of the HL test on test Sheffield data </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.85 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>E 2E 
(0 .8 9± 0. 02 ) 
S 2E 
(0 .8 4± 0. 03 ) </p>

<p>R A N D O M (0 .8 5± 0. 02 ) 
A D A P T (0 .8 8± 0. 02 ) </p>

<p>AUCs based on test Edinburgh data </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>E 2E 
(0 .1 5± 0. 23 ) 
S 2E 
(0 .0 4± 0. 13 ) </p>

<p>R A N D O M (0 .0 5± 0. 20 ) 
A D A P T (0 .1 4± 0. 21 ) </p>

<p>p values of the HL test on test Edinburgh data </p>

<p>p&lt;0.01 
p&lt;0.01 
p&lt;0.01 
p=0.14 </p>

<p>p&lt;0.01 
p&lt;0.01 
p&lt;0.01 
p&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>p=0.85 
p=0.84 </p>

<p>p=0.60 
p=1.00 </p>

<p> 
J Am Med Inform Assoc 2012;19:e137ee144. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2011-000751 </p>

<p>Research and applications </p>

<p>a comprehensive set of patient feature values is available (ie, 17 in 
the case of CVD), we can calculate individualized CI for each of 
the models listed above without determining how many features 
were used to train the model at each hospital/institution. 
Evidently, if just certain feature values are available for a given 
patient, only certain models will generate a prediction. The model 
resulting in the narrowest individualized CI for the prediction 
would be the one selected, such as the one conducted in our study 
(see supplementary appendix B, available online only). Regarding 
evaluation matrices, although we believe AUC and HL tests are 
general evaluation standards that are used by many, we noticed 
that models could be evaluated using other evaluation indices, 
which we would like to explore in our future work. 
Despite results showing performance advantages of ADAPT 
over other strategies in terms of discrimination and calibration 
using simulated data, our simulation study has important 
limitations. Orthogonal training patterns are not common in 
real-world data: we used this two-dimensional simulated data 
mainly for illustration purposes. Although our preliminary 
results from the application of ADAPT to the MI data confirm 
the performance advantage of ADAPT over CROSS model 
adaption and RANDOM model selection strategies, these data-
sets were relatively small. In the future, we plan to use larger 
datasets that are increasingly being collected at healthcare 
institutions for predictive model building and validation. Addi-
tional concerns relate to the fact that CI may not always offer 
enough information to rank the reliability of predictions, and 
our evaluation was done on the aggregate. If a particular indi-
vidual is very different from those represented in the training set 
of existing models, the CI may be somewhat misleading. Indeed, 
the problem of assessing the best result for the particular indi-
vidual at hand is still an open question, as the individual gold 
standard for the prediction is not available (ie, the observation is 
binarydthe patients develop or do not develop CVD, but the 
true gold standard for an individual prediction is the true 
probability for the patient to develop the condition, which is not 
known). In the future, we would like to work towards the 
development of better proxies for the gold standard than the 
ones currently available, investigate data-driven model selection </p>

<p>for models constructed using larger datasets across multiple 
sites, and extend our framework to include kernel methods. 
In summary, this article describes a new method for selecting 
one among several competing models for a given individual, and 
our results show that there are positive effects on discriminatory 
performance. All experiments described in this article were 
conducted in a laboratory environment. The evaluation of 
the method as a part of a clinical decision support system 
is certainly warranted to verify its performance in a clinical 
environment. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments The authors would like to thank Dr Hamish Fraser of Harvard 
Medical School for making the datasets available for this study. </p>

<p>Contributors The first and last authors contributed equally to the writing. The rest of 
the authors are ranked according to their contributions. </p>

<p>Funding The authors were funded in part by the National Library of Medicine 
(R01LM009520), NHLBI (U54 HL10846), AHRQ (R01HS19913), and NCRR 
(UL1RR031980). </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Patient consent Obtained. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement The authors will make their simulation data used in this 
manuscript available upon acceptance. </p>



<p>Figure 6 Distribution of model 
selected using ADAPT. AUC, area under 
the receiver operating characteristic 
curve; HL, HosmereLemeshow test. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>S 
h e f f i e ld </p>

<p>[ m 
e a n = 5 8 . 1 0 </p>

<p>s t d = 5 . 4 8 ] </p>

<p>E 
d i n b u r g h </p>

<p>[ m 
e a n = 4 1 . 9 0 </p>

<p>s t d = 5 . 4 8 ] </p>

<p>ADAPT: Sheffield test data selection </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>S 
h e f f i e ld </p>

<p>[ m 
e a n = 6 9 . 9 8 </p>

<p>s t d = 8 2 . 1 7 ] </p>

<p>E 
d i n b u r g h </p>

<p>[ m 
e a n = 1 8 1 . 0 2 </p>

<p>s t d = 8 2 . 1 7 ] </p>

<p>ADAPT: Edinburgh test data selection </p>

<p>J Am Med Inform Assoc 2012;19:e137ee144. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2011-000751 
e143 </p>

<p>Research and applications </p>



<p> 
J Am Med Inform Assoc 2012;19:e137ee144. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2011-000751 </p>

<p>Research and applications </p>

</text></tei>