<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3388559" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>BACKGROUND: This randomised phase II trial compared gemcitabine alone vs gemcitabine and S-1 combination therapy in advanced 
pancreatic cancer. 
METHODS: Patients were randomly assigned to 4-week treatment with gemcitabine alone (1000 mg m 
À 2 gemcitabine by 30-min 
infusion on days 1, 8, and 15) or gemcitabine and S-1 combination therapy (1000 mg m 
À 2 gemcitabine by 30-min infusion on days 1 
and 15 and 40 mg m 
À 2 S-1 orally twice daily on days 1-15). The primary end point was progression-free survival (PFS). </p>

<p>RESULTS: Between July 2006 and February 2009, 106 patients were enrolled. The PFS in gemcitabine and S-1 combination arm was 
significantly longer than in gemcitabine arm (5.4 vs 3.6 months), with a hazard ratio of 0.64 (P ¼ 0.036). Overall survival (OS) for 
gemcitabine and S-1 combination was longer than that for gemcitabine monotherapy (13.5 vs 8.8 months), with a hazard ratio of 
0.72 (P ¼ 0.104). Overall, grade 3 or 4 adverse events were similar in both arms. 
CONCLUSION: Gemcitabine and S-1 combination therapy demonstrated longer PFS in advanced pancreatic cancer. Improved 
OS duration of 4.7 months was found for gemcitabine and S-1 combination therapy, though this was not statistically significant. 
British Journal of Cancer (2012) 106, 1934-1939. doi:10.1038/bjc.2012.183 www.bjcancer.com 
Published online 3 May 2012 
&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK </p>

<p>Keywords: chemotherapy; gemcitabine; pancreatic cancer; randomised controlled trial; S-1 </p>





















































<p>Despite extensive research, the prognosis of advanced pancreatic 
cancer remains poor. Because gemcitabine is superior to bolus 
5-fluorouracil (5-FU), with a response rate of 5% and a median 
overall survival (OS) of 5.7 months (Burris et al, 1997), 
combination therapy with gemcitabine and cytotoxic drugs or 
molecular-targeted agents has been intensely investigated. 
Only erlotinib in combination with gemcitabine showed a 
statistically significant but clinically small improvement in OS 
(Moore et al, 2007), but most phase III clinical trials have 
failed to demonstrate significant differences in OS. Recently, 
the efficacy of multiagent regimens was reported in two 
randomised controlled trials (Reni et al, 2005; Conroy et al, 
2011); however, multiagent regimens have potentially increased 
adverse effects. 
S-1 is an oral fluoropyrimidine consisting of tegafur, a prodrug 
of 5-FU, and two biochemical modulators, 5-chloro-2,4-dihydrox-
ypyridine and potassium oxonate, with single-agent activity in 
advanced pancreatic cancer and an objective response rate (ORR) 
comparable to that for gemcitabine monotherapy (Ueno et al, 
2005b; Okusaka et al, 2008). Combination chemotherapy with </p>

<p>gemcitabine and S-1 is reportedly well tolerated and active against 
advanced pancreatic cancer (Nakamura et al, 2005, 2006; Ueno 
et al, 2005a; Kim et al, 2009; Lee et al, 2009; Oh et al, 2010). 
Initially, combination chemotherapy with gemcitabine and S-1 was 
reported as a 3-week regimen, but our modified 4-week regimen 
demonstrated a time to progression of 10.0 months and OS of 20.4 
months with mild adverse effects in patients with advanced 
pancreatic cancer (Nakai et al, 2009). 
Here, we conducted a multicentre, randomised phase II trial of 
gemcitabine alone vs combination therapy with gemcitabine and 
S-1 in patients with advanced pancreatic cancer. </p>

<p>PATIENTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Trial design </p>

<p>This multicentre, open-label randomised phase II trial was 
conducted at six centres in Japan. The protocol was approved by 
the institutional review board at each centre. Informed consent 
was obtained from each participant. The study, which was 
registered in the UMIN Clinical Trials Registry (UMIN000000498), 
was conducted according to the Declaration of Helsinki. 
The primary trial end point was progression-free survival (PFS). 
The secondary end points were OS, ORR, and safety. </p>

<p>*Correspondence: Dr H Isayama; E-mail: isayama-2im@h.u-tokyo.ac.jp 
Received 12 December 2011; revised 27 March 2012; accepted 3 April 
2012; published online 3 May 2012 </p>

<p>British Journal of Cancer (2012) 106, 1934-1939 
&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK All rights reserved 0007 -0920/12 </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com </p>

<p>Clinical Studies </p>

<p>Eligibility </p>

<p>The eligibility criteria were as follows: (1) pancreatic adenocarci-
noma diagnosed by pathological examination or typical radio-
graphic findings; (2) unresectable locally advanced or metastatic 
disease; (3) no prior treatment for pancreatic cancer including 
surgery or radiation therapy; (4) Eastern Cooperative Oncology 
Group (ECOG) performance status of 0-2; (5) age 420 years; 
(6) capability of oral intake; (7) life expectancy 412 weeks; and 
(8) adequate organ function, as indicated by a white blood cell 
count 43000 per mm 
3 , platelet count 4100 000 per mm 
3 , 
haemoglobin 410.0 g dl </p>

<p>À 1 </p>

<p>, serum creatinine o1.5 times the 
normal upper limit, creatine clearance 450 ml per min, total 
bilirubin o2 times the normal upper limit, and aspartate 
aminotransferase and alanine aminotransferase levels o5 times 
the normal upper limit. The exclusion criteria were as follows: (1) 
severe complications, such as active infection, cardiac or renal 
disease, marked pleural effusion, or ascites; (2) active gastro-
intestinal bleeding; (3) severe drug hypersensitivity; (4) active 
concomitant malignancy; and (5) pregnancy or lactation. </p>

<p>Randomisation </p>

<p>Patients were randomly assigned to each treatment arm on a 1 : 1 
basis according to a computer-generated minimisation 
method, stratified by enrolling centre and extent of disease (locally 
advanced vs metastatic). </p>

<p>Treatment </p>

<p>Patients randomly allocated to the gemcitabine arm received 
gemcitabine intravenously at 1000 mg m 
À 2 over 30 min on days 1, 
8, and 15 of each 4-week cycle. Patients randomly allocated to 
the gemcitabine and S-1 arm received gemcitabine intravenously at 
1000 mg m 
À 2 over 30 min on days 1 and 15 and S-1 orally 
twice daily for 2 weeks followed by a 2-week rest between each 
4-week cycle. Three doses of S-1 were established according 
to the body surface area (BSA) as follows: BSA p1.25 m 
2 , 80 mg 
per day; 1.25 m 
2 oBSAp1.5 m 
2 , 100 mg per day; and BSA X1.5 m 
2 , 
120 mg per day. All treatments were given until disease progres-
sion, unacceptable toxic effects, or withdrawal of consent. </p>

<p>Assessments </p>

<p>Tumour responses were measured by computed tomography, 
which was performed at baseline, and then every two cycles 
(8 weeks); tumour responses were evaluated using the 
Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours (RECIST) 1.0 
(Therasse et al, 2000). CA19-9 levels were measured at baseline and 
at each cycle. </p>

<p>Adverse events and dose modification </p>

<p>All adverse events were evaluated at each cycle according to National 
Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events 
(NCI-CTCAE) version 3.0 (see http://ctep.cancer.gov/reporting/ctc. 
html). Treatment was temporarily suspended in the case of 
grade 3/4 haematological toxicity or grade 2 or higher non-
haematological toxicity. After recovery to grade 1 toxicity or 
lower, treatment was restarted at the following reduced doses. 
In the gemcitabine arm, gemcitabine was reduced by 200 mg m </p>

<p>À 2 </p>

<p>. 
In the gemcitabine and S-1 arm, S-1 was reduced to: BSA 
p1.25 m 
2 , 50 mg per day; 1.25 m 
2 oBSA p1.5 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, 80 mg per day; 
and BSA X1.5 m 
2 , 100 mg per day. When dose reduction was 
necessary after the reduction of S-1, gemcitabine was reduced by 
200 mg m 
À 2 . No dose escalation was allowed following dose 
reduction. </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>The primary end point hypothesis used for sample-size estimation 
was that combination therapy with gemcitabine and S-1 would 
increase the median PFS by 2 months (from 3 to 5 months) 
compared with gemcitabine monotherapy with a type I error 
probability of 5% (one-sided) and power of 80%. The required 
number of patients was 50 and a 5% dropout was accounted for in 
the sample-size calculation. The OS from randomisation was 
calculated from the date of randomisation to the date of death 
from any cause or censored at the last follow-up. The PFS was 
calculated from the date of randomisation to the date of either 
disease progression or death or censored at the last follow-up. 
The OS and PFS were estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method, 
and were compared between treatment arms using the log-rank 
test. A Cox proportional hazards model was used to estimate the 
hazard ratios with a 95% confidence interval (CI). The ORRs were 
reported as best achieved response rates. Proportions between the 
arms were compared using the w 
2 test or Fisher's test; quantitative 
variables were compared using Student's t-test or the Wilcoxon 
test. All analyses were conducted based on the intention-to-treat 
principle. Two-sided P-values o0.05 were considered to be 
significant. The final analysis was based on follow-up information, 
which was collected until February 2011. <rs id="software-0" type="software">JMP</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">8.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>., Cary, NC, USA) was used for all statistical analyses. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>A total of 106 patients were randomly assigned in six hospitals in 
Japan between July 2006 and February 2009. The patients' 
characteristics are shown in Table 1. The baseline characteristics 
were well balanced between the two arms. The study flow diagram 
is shown in Figure 1. One patient in the gemcitabine arm and two 
patients in the gemcitabine and S-1 arm received no study drug. 
All 106 patients were assessable for OS, PFS, and response; 
103 patients were assessable for safety. 
At the time of analysis, six patients (two in the gemcitabine arm 
and four in the gemcitabine and S-1 arm) were still alive. The total 
number of cycles was 277 and 328 in the gemcitabine and 
gemcitabine plus S-1 arms, respectively. The median follow-up 
period was 10.0 months. </p>

<p>Efficacy </p>

<p>The ORR according to RECIST 1.0 (Table 2) was 18.9% (95% CI: 
10.6-31.4%) in the gemcitabine and S-1 arm, compared with 9.4% 
(95% CI: 4.9-20.3%) in the gemcitabine arm (P ¼ 0.265). Only one 
patient in the gemcitabine and S-1 arm had a complete response. 
The median response duration was 10.0 months in the gemcitabine 
and S-1 arm and 10.6 months in the gemcitabine arm. The disease 
control rate of 79.2% in the gemcitabine and S-1 arm was 
significantly higher than that (56.6%) in the gemcitabine arm 
(P ¼ 0.021). Table 2 summarises our efficacy results. 
The median PFS (Figure 2) for combination therapy with 
gemcitabine and S-1 was 5.4 months (95% CI: 3.7-9.4 months) 
while that for gemcitabine monotherapy was 3.6 months (95% CI: 
2.0-5.1 months). Combination therapy with gemcitabine and S-1 
demonstrated a significantly improved PFS over gemcitabine 
monotherapy, with a hazard ratio of 0.64 (95% CI: 0.42-0.97; 
P ¼ 0.036). 
The median OS was 13.5 months (95% CI: 7.8-16.3 months) in 
the gemcitabine and S-1 arm and 8.8 months (95% CI: 7.0-10.6 
months) in the gemcitabine arm (Figure 3). The 1-year survival 
rate was 52.8% in the gemcitabine and S-1 arm and 30.2% in the 
gemcitabine arm (P ¼ 0.031). The improvement in OS did not </p>

<p>Gemcitabine vs Gemcitabine and S-1 in pancreatic cancer 
Y Nakai et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK 
British Journal of Cancer (2012) 106(12), 1934 -1939 </p>

<p>Clinical Studies </p>

<p>reach statistical significance, with a hazard ratio of 0.72 (95% CI: 
0.48-1.07; P ¼ 0.104). 
Median PFS and OS in locally advanced disease are 12.6 vs 8.1 
months and 23.9 vs 11.0 months in gemcitabine and S-1 arm vs </p>

<p>gemcitabine arm, respectively. Meanwhile, median PFS and OS in 
metastatic disease are similar (4.0 vs 2.4 months) and (8.9 vs 
7.9 months), respectively (Table 2). 
Post hoc subgroup analysis with a Karnofsky performance status 
(KPS) score of 100 showed that combination therapy with 
gemcitabine and S-1 demonstrated a longer OS of 15.0 months 
(95% CI: 8.9-23.9 months), compared with 8.5 months (95% CI: 
7.0-11.0 months) for gemcitabine monotherapy (P ¼ 0.011). Mean-
while, in patients with a KPS o100, no significant difference was 
found in OS of 6.8 months (95% CI: 3.7-15.4 months) in the 
gemcitabine and S-1 arm and 8.8 months (95% CI: 5.0-11.3 
months) in the gemcitabine arm (P ¼ 0.997). 
Eight patients without pathological diagnosis were included in 
our study. There were no differences in OS between patients with 
and without pathological diagnosis (10.0 vs 10.1 months, 
P ¼ 0.982). When patients with pathological diagnosis were 
analysed, PFS was 5.4 vs 2.9 months (P ¼ 0.011) and OS was 15.0 
vs 8.2 months (P ¼ 0.022) in gemcitabine and S-1 arm vs 
gemcitabine arm. </p>

<p>Table 1 Patient characteristics </p>

<p>Gemcitabine 
(n ¼ 53) </p>

<p>Gemcitabine 
and S-1 (n ¼ 53) 
P-value </p>

<p>Age, years 
Median (range) 
67 (42-84) 
63 (40-82) 
0.200 </p>

<p>Sex, n (%) 
Male 
33 (62.3%) 
42 (79.2%) 
0.087 
Female 
20 (37.8%) 
11 (20.8%) </p>

<p>ECOG performance status, n (%) 
0 
32 (60.4%) 
31 (58.5%) 
0.843 
1 
20 (37.7%) 
22 (41.5%) 
2 
1 (1.9%) 
0 </p>

<p>Karnofsky performance status, n (%) 
100 
18 (34.0%) 
27 (50.9%) 
0.131 
90 
29 (54.7%) 
21 (39.6%) 
80 
3 (5.7%) 
5 (9.4%) 
70 
2 (3.8%) 
0 
60 
1 (1.9%) 
0 </p>

<p>Disease extent, n (%) 
Locally advanced 
13 (24.5%) 
15 (28.3%) 
0.668 
Metastatic 
40 (75.5%) 
38 (71.7%) </p>

<p>Site of primary tumour, n (%) 
Head 
18 (34.0%) 
20 (37.7%) 
0.850 
Body 
12 (22.6%) 
10 (18.9%) 
Tail 
23 (43.4%) 
23 (43.4%) </p>

<p>Site of metastasis, n (%) 
Liver 
25 (47.2%) 
24 (45.3%) 
1.000 
Lung 
3 (5.7%) 
1 (1.9%) 
0.618 
Lymph node 
20 (37.7%) 
21 (39.6%) 
1.000 
Peritoneum 
10 (18.9%) 
7 (13.2%) 
0.598 
Biliary stent, n (%) 
22 (41.5%) 
17 (32.1%) 
0.421 </p>

<p>CA19-9, IU l </p>

<p>À 1 </p>

<p>Median (range) 
1204 (1-465 511) 
822 (1-130 800) 
0.800 </p>

<p>Abbreviation: ECOG ¼ Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group. </p>

<p>Gemcitabine 
Gemcitabine and S-1 
Allocated to 
gemcitabine 
monotherapy (N = 53) </p>

<p>Allocated to 
gemcitabine and S-1 
combination therapy (N = 53) </p>

<p>Patients randomly assigned 
N = 106 </p>

<p>Did not receive 
allocated treatment 
-deteriorated conditon (N = 1) </p>

<p>Lost to follow-up (N = 0) 
Alive (N = 2) 
Dead (N = 51) </p>

<p>Analysed 
-For efficacy (N = 53) 
-For safety (N = 52) </p>

<p>Analysed 
-For efficacy (N = 53) 
-For safety (N = 51) </p>

<p>Lost to follow-up (N = 0) 
Alive (N = 4) 
Dead (N = 49) </p>

<p>Did not receive 
allocated treatment 
-consent withdrawn (N = 2) </p>

<p>Figure 1 The study population. </p>

<p>Table 2 Efficacy results </p>

<p>Gemcitabine 
(n ¼ 53) </p>

<p>Gemcitabine 
and S-1 (n ¼ 53) 
P-value </p>

<p>Best response, n (%) 
Complete response 
0 
1 (1.9%) 
Partial response 
5 (9.4%) 
9 (17.0%) 
Stable disease 
25 (47.2%) 
32 (60.4%) 
Progressive disease 
21 (39.6%) 
9 (17.0%) 
Not evaluable 
2 (3.8%) 
2 (3.8%) 
Response rate 
9.4% 
18.9% 
0.265 
Disease control rate 
56.6% 
79.2% 
0.021 </p>

<p>Median progression-free survival, months (95% CI) 
Overall 
3.6 (2.0-5.1) 
5.4 (3.7-9.4) 
0.035 
Locally advanced 
8.1 (2.2-13.0) 
12.6 (3.4-16.5) 
0.112 
Metastatic 
2.4 (1.9-3.9) 
4.0 (3.6-5.5) 
0.099 </p>

<p>Median overall survival, months (95% CI) 
Overall 
8.8 (7.0-10.6) 
13.5 (7.8-16.3) 
0.102 
Locally advanced 
11.0 (5.8-23.6) 
23.9 (13.5-26.4) 
0.297 
Metastatic 
7.9 (5.0-9.5) 
8.9 (6.3-14.2) 
0.311 </p>

<p>One-year survival rate 
30.2% 
52.8% 
0.031 </p>

<p>Abbreviation: CI ¼ confidence interval. </p>

<p>Gemcitabine vs Gemcitabine and S-1 in pancreatic cancer 
Y Nakai et al </p>



<p>British Journal of Cancer (2012) 106(12), 1934 -1939 
&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK </p>

<p>Clinical Studies </p>

<p>The treatment after study drug failure was selected at the 
discretion of the individual investigator. No patients with locally 
advanced disease received chemoradiation therapy after study 
drug failure. Second-line chemotherapy was administered to 31 
patients (58.5%) in the gemcitabine arm and 18 (34.0%) in the 
gemcitabine and S-1 arm, respectively (P ¼ 0.019). Notably, S-1 
was administered alone or as combination therapy in all 31 
gemcitabine-failure patients receiving second-line chemotherapy. 
Overall survival after the introduction of second-line chemo-
therapy was 5.0 and 5.3 months in the gemcitabine and 
gemcitabine plus S-1 arms, respectively (P ¼ 0.296). The regimens 
of chemotherapy after study drug failure are shown in Figure 4. 
The number of administered drugs during the clinical course was 
X2 in 58.5% vs 96.2%, X3 in 15.1% vs 34.0%, and 4 in 3.8% vs 
9.4% in the gemcitabine and gemcitabine plus S-1 arms, 
respectively. </p>

<p>Safety and dose intensity </p>

<p>Treatment-related adverse events are shown in Table 3. The overall 
number of grade 3 or greater toxicities did not increase in the 
gemcitabine and S-1 arm (53.8% in the gemcitabine arm and 43.1% 
in the gemcitabine and S-1 arm). Neutropenia was the 
most frequent grade 3 or greater toxicity in both arms. 
Non-haematological grade 3 or greater toxicities were infrequent 
in both groups, but stomatitis, diarrhoea and rash were more often </p>

<p>seen in the gemcitabine and S-1 arm. No chemotherapy-related 
death occurred. 
The mean dose intensity for gemcitabine was 618.2 mg m 
À 2 per 
week (82.4% of the planned dose) in the gemcitabine arm and 
489.0 mg m 
À 2 per week (97.8% of the planned dose) in the 
gemcitabine and S-1 arm. The mean dose intensity for S-1 
was 251.4 mg m 
À 2 per week (89.8% of the planned dose) in the 
gemcitabine and S-1 arm. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In the present randomised phase II trial, combination therapy with 
gemcitabine and S-1 demonstrated a longer median PFS and 
higher 1-year survival rate with similar severe adverse effects 
compared with gemcitabine monotherapy. The addition of S-1 to 
gemcitabine led to a 4.7-month improvement in the median OS; 
however, this result was not statistically significant. 
Combination therapy with gemcitabine and other cytotoxic 
drugs or molecular-targeted agents has been thoroughly investi-
gated in patients with pancreatic cancer, but no significant 
improvement in OS has been confirmed in a single, randomised 
controlled trial, except for combination therapy with gemcitabine 
and erlotinib (Moore et al, 2007). However, the improvement in OS 
was modest with a median survival of 6.24 months for combination 
therapy with gemcitabine and erlotinib vs 5.91 months for 
gemcitabine monotherapy. In a meta-analysis, capecitabine, an 
oral fluoropyrimidine similar to S-1, in combination with 
gemcitabine, was shown to improve OS compared with gemcita-
bine alone with a hazard ratio of 0.86 (Cunningham et al, 2009). 
Recently, Conroy et al (2011) reported a significantly longer OS 
with FORFIRINOX than gemcitabine alone in patients with 
metastatic pancreatic cancer. Thus, fluoropyrimidine is currently 
a key drug in the treatment of advanced pancreatic cancer. In 
adjuvant settings (Neoptolemos et al, 2010), the OS with 5-FU plus 
folinic acid was as effective as gemcitabine. S-1 is also an oral 
fluoropyrimidine that has been reported to be active against 
pancreatic cancer. We previously reported promising data for 
combination therapy with gemcitabine and S-1 using a 4-week 
schedule (Nakai et al, 2009). This subsequent randomised 
controlled trial demonstrated a significantly longer PFS 
(the primary end point) and higher 1-year survival rate. Despite 
an improvement in OS of 4.7 months with a hazard ratio of 0.72 for 
combination therapy with gemcitabine and S-1, this difference did 
not reach statistical significance. In a post hoc analysis of patients 
with a KPS of 100, the median OS was significantly longer in 
patients treated with gemcitabine and S-1 (15.0 vs 8.5 months; 
P ¼ 0.011). The trend toward improved results with combination 
therapy in patients with a good performance status was also 
reported for combination therapy with gemcitabine and capecita-
bine (Herrmann et al, 2007). By contrast, OS with gemcitabine 
monotherapy showed similar results regardless of the KPS score in 
our study (8.5 months with KPS ¼ 100 vs 8.8 months with KPS 
o100). 
The problem often encountered with randomised controlled 
trials of combination therapy with gemcitabine and other drugs is 
the crossover to experimental drugs in the gemcitabine arm. In our 
study, 31 patients (58.5%) in the gemcitabine monotherapy 
arm received S-1 as second-line chemotherapy. In Japan, both 
gemcitabine and S-1 are approved for the treatment of pancreatic 
cancer and are widely used in clinical practice. Therefore, patients 
in gemcitabine arm had easy access to S-1 as second-line 
treatment. Although second-line chemotherapy has not been 
established in patients with gemcitabine-refractory pancreatic 
cancer, S-1 has been reported to be useful in this setting 
(Morizane et al, 2009; Sudo et al, 2011). This crossover might 
obscure the efficacy of combination therapy with gemcitabine and 
S-1 over gemcitabine monotherapy. As S1 improved the prognosis </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>No. at risk </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>53 
53 </p>

<p>22 
17 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Time (months) </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>4 
3 </p>

<p>Gemcitabine and S-1 
Gemcitabine alone </p>

<p>Gemcitabine and S-1 
Gemcitabine alone </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.50 
Progression-free survival </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>6 
12 
18 
24 </p>

<p>Figure 2 Kaplan-Meier estimates of progression-free survival according 
to treatment group. </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>No. at risk 
Gemcitabine and S-1 53 
53 </p>

<p>40 
37 </p>

<p>29 
17 </p>

<p>18 
11 </p>

<p>12 
6 </p>

<p>5 
3 </p>

<p>0 
1 
Gemcitabine alone </p>

<p>0 
6 
12 
18 
Time (months) </p>

<p>24 
30 
36 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.50 
Overall survival </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>Figure 3 Kaplan-Meier estimates of overall survival according to 
treatment group. </p>

<p>Gemcitabine vs Gemcitabine and S-1 in pancreatic cancer 
Y Nakai et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK 
British Journal of Cancer (2012) 106(12), 1934 -1939 </p>

<p>Clinical Studies </p>

<p>of advanced pancreatic cancer using a historical cohort design 
(Nakai et al, 2010a, b), the introduction of new effective drugs 
could lead to improved survival even in patients with pancreatic 
cancer refractory to gemcitabine. In addition to gemcitabine and 
S-1, oxaliplatin (Isayama et al, 2011) and irinotecan were 
administered to refractory patients in the present study. However, 
drugs other than gemcitabine and S-1 were not approved for 
treatment of pancreatic cancer and were administered only as 
clinical trials. As a result, the introduction rate of second-line 
treatment was lower in gemcitabine and S-1 arm compared with 
gemcitabine arm (34.0% vs 58.5%). The rate of patients receiving 
three or four anticancer drugs was higher in the combination 
therapy arm. As shown for colorectal cancer (Grothey et al, 2004), 
the availability of multiple drugs might be associated with </p>

<p>prolonged survival in pancreatic cancer. Thus, the development 
of multiple effective drugs and appropriate combination regimens 
is as important as randomised controlled trials of first-line 
chemotherapy. 
Given the palliative role of chemotherapy in patients with 
advanced pancreatic cancer, safety is as important as efficacy. Our 
4-week regimen of combination therapy with gemcitabine and S-1 
did not significantly increase the overall severe toxicity. This 
regimen allowed a biweekly hospital visit compared with three 
times a month for gemcitabine monotherapy, which could also 
decrease the treatment burden for incurable patients. In this sense, 
FORFIRINOX (Conroy et al, 2011), the first regimen without 
gemcitabine that was demonstrated to be superior to gemcitabine, 
was associated with severe toxicities, including febrile neutropenia. 
Some limitations to our study exist. First, the sample size (106 
patients) was relatively small. Although combination therapy with 
gemcitabine and S-1 achieved the primary end point of PFS and 
improved the median OS duration by 4.7 months, this difference in 
OS did not reach statistical significance. At the Annual meeting of 
the American Society of Clinical Oncology 2011, two other 
randomised controlled trials of gemcitabine alone vs gemcitabine 
and S-1 combination therapy were reported (Ioka et al, 2011; 
Omuro et al, 2011). While one phase II trial (Omuro et al, 2011) 
demonstrated significant superiority of combination arm in ORR, 
time-to-progression and OS, the other large phase III trial (Ioka 
et al, 2011) showed significantly longer PFS, but failed to 
demonstrate superiority in OS. The results might differ because 
the schedule and planned dose intensity were somewhat different 
in these three trials. Given the failure of one phase III trial, another 
large scale phase III trial is necessary to confirm the survival 
benefit of this combination therapy but we should select patients 
who are most likely to benefit from combination therapy, that is, 
better PS. In addition, the best dose intensity should be considered 
in those study population. Second, our 4-week regimen was safely 
administered to patients with advanced pancreatic cancer without 
a significant increase in overall severe toxicity compared with 
gemcitabine monotherapy, but the planned dose intensity was 
lower than the 3-week regimen used in other studies (Nakamura 
et al, 2005, 2006; Ueno et al, 2005a). This difference in dose 
intensity might influence the efficacy of the gemcitabine and S-1 
arm, although our 4-week regimen showed high tolerability with a 
relatively high actual dose intensity. 
In conclusion, this randomised trial demonstrated a longer PFS 
and higher 1-year survival rate for combination therapy with 
gemcitabine and S-1 in patients with advanced pancreatic cancer. 
Overall survival was also significantly longer in patients with a </p>

<p>Gemcitabine 
Gemcitabine and S-1 </p>

<p>S-1 
(N = 30) </p>

<p>S-1 and Ox 
(N = 1) </p>

<p>Gemcitabine and Ox 
(N = 7) </p>

<p>Gemcitabine and Ox 
(N = 4) </p>

<p>Irinotecan 
(N = 2) </p>

<p>Irinotecan 
(N = 3) </p>

<p>Irinotecan 
(N = 2) </p>

<p>S-1 and Ox 
(N = 3) </p>

<p>Irinotecan 
(N = 11) </p>

<p>Figure 4 Treatment after study drug failure. Abbreviation: OX ¼ oxaliplatin. </p>

<p>Table 3 Adverse events </p>

<p>Gemcitabine 
(n ¼ 52) </p>

<p>Gemcitabine 
and S-1 (n ¼ 51) </p>

<p>All 
grades </p>

<p>Grade 
3-4 </p>

<p>All 
grades </p>

<p>Grade 
3-4 </p>

<p>Haematological 
Neutropenia 
32 (61.5%) 18 (34.6%) 29 (56.9%) 17 (33.3%) 
Febrile neutropenia 
1 (1.9%) 
1 (1.9%) 
0 
0 
Anaemia 
43 (82.7%) 
6 (11.5%) 40 (78.4%) 
6 (11.8%) 
Thrombocytopenia 
35 (67.3%) 
1 (1.9%) 
30 (58.8%) 
2 (3.9%) </p>

<p>Non-haematological 
Fatigue 
25 (48.1%) 
2 (3.8%) 
20 (39.2%) 
1 (2.0%) 
Anorexia 
27 (51.9%) 
5 (9.6%) 
32 (62.7%) 
2 (3.9%) 
Nausea 
18 (34.6%) 
0 
18 (35.3%) 
1 (2.0%) 
Vomiting 
9 (17.3%) 
0 
9 (17.6%) 
0 
Constipation 
26 (50.0%) 
1 (1.9%) 
19 (37.3%) 
1 (2.0%) 
Diarrhoea 
6 (11.5%) 
0 
17 (33.3%) 
1 (2.0%) 
Elevated liver function 24 (46.2%) 
7 (13.5%) 25 (49.0%) 
4 (7.8%) 
Stomatitis 
5 (9.6%) 
0 
13 (25.5%) 
3 (5.9%) 
Rash 
5 (9.6%) 
0 
11 (21.6%) 
2 (3.9%) 
GI haemorrhage 
0 
0 
2 (3.9%) 
2 (3.9%) 
Pneumonitis 
0 
0 
1 (2.0%) 
1 (2.0%) 
Taste alteration 
1 (1.9%) 
0 
3 (5.9%) 
0 
Alopecia 
2 (3.8%) 
0 
1 (2.0%) 
0 
Peripheral oedema 
1 (1.9%) 
0 
2 (3.9%) 
0 
Pruritus 
0 
0 
1 (2.0%) 
0 </p>

<p>Any grade 3-4 
28 (53.8%) 
22 (43.1%) </p>

<p>Abbreviation: GI ¼ gastrointestinal. The data are shown as value (%). </p>

<p>Gemcitabine vs Gemcitabine and S-1 in pancreatic cancer 
Y Nakai et al </p>



<p>British Journal of Cancer (2012) 106(12), 1934 -1939 
&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK </p>

<p>Clinical Studies </p>

<p>good performance status (KPS ¼ 100). Thus, a large-scale, phase III 
randomised controlled trial is warranted. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank the participating patients and their families, as well as 
the additional investigators, study coordinators (Miyuki Tsuchida, </p>

<p>Makiko Otake at Clinical Research Support Center, The University 
of Tokyo Hospital). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>



<p>This work is published under the standard license to publish agreement. After 12 months the work will become freely available and the 
license terms will switch to a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. </p>

<p>Gemcitabine vs Gemcitabine and S-1 in pancreatic cancer 
Y Nakai et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK 
British Journal of Cancer (2012) 106(12), 1934 -1939 </p>

<p>Clinical Studies </p>

</text></tei>