<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3763098" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The past five decades have witnessed the so-called data deluge 
and publication explosion across all branches of science (1). 
Numerous academic journals have been launched that use a 
systematic approach to the submission, peer review, and pub-
lishing of information. To facilitate the wide use of published 
sources, libraries across the world have expanded cataloguing 
and advanced literature search techniques. 
The first major step towards indexing academic journals and 
helping libraries acquire the most influential sources was made 
by the Institute for Scientific Information (ISI) in Philadelphia, 
USA, in 1960. The idea behind indexing and distributing infor-
mation on published articles was to facilitate scientific commu-
nication between authors and readers (2). In other words, in-
dexing was proposed as a tool for finding relevant sources of in-
terest to the consumers. The originator of the idea, Eugene Gar-
field, also the founder of the ISI, formulated several critical points 
in bibliometrics that have shaped citation indexes, for example, 
libraries with limited funding should be selective about the jour-
nals they acquire; most read and highly cited journals consti-
tute 'quality' sources; highly cited articles influence science; ci-
tations from highly-cited journals are weighed more than those 
from low-cited ones; and a bibliography should selectively cov-
er 'high quality' sources. </p>

<p>DEFINITION </p>

<p>Bibliographic databases are broadly defined as digital collec-
tions of references to published sources, particularly to journal 
articles and conference proceedings, which are tagged with spe-
cific titles, author names, affiliations, abstracts, and IDs. The 
PubMed ID (PMID) and Digital Object Identifier (DOI) are fre-
quently used encodings that help locate individual published 
items. Bibliographic databases may also use a specific set of 
keywords, or thesaurus, to better organise the indexing and to 
improve the retrievability of the indexed items. Prime examples 
are Medical Subject Headings (MeSH) and EMtree collections 
of keywords utilised by Medical Literature Analysis and Retrie-</p>

<p>val System Online (MEDLINE; US National Library of Medicine) 
and EMBASE (Elsevier), respectively. The databases are also 
classified as abstracting and citation-tracking. Examples of the 
former are MEDLINE and EMBASE, and the latter -Scopus and 
Science Citation Index Expanded. 
Depending on the scope of coverage, databases are divided 
into large groups of multidisciplinary, specialised, and narrow-
specialised ones. Most prestigious databases cover periodicals 
of global/international importance, while there are also region-
al and even country-based abstracting and/or citation-tracking 
platforms (for example, KoreaMed and Korean Medical Cita-
tion Index). Finally, there are databases requiring subscription 
and those free to all users. Many leading academic and research 
institutions worldwide secure paid access to subscription data-
bases. The databases can also be accessed through digital search 
interfaces such as <rs type="software">Ovid</rs> and <rs type="software">EBSCO</rs>, and they can link the in-
dexed items to the full-texts in digital search platforms (for ex-
ample, Elsevier's ScienceDirect, Springer's SpringerLink, and 
Wiley Online Library) and free online libraries (for example, 
PubMed Central and SpringerOpen). </p>

<p>SELECTION CRITERIA </p>

<p>Despite the fact that most bibliographic databases have upgrad-
ed their information storage capacities, they maintain selective-
ness and accept for indexing only a small proportion of journals. 
Periodicals are required to meet certain technical standards to 
be readable by online software. Each journal item should be 
noticeably separated from others, particularly in the form of 
separate PDF files, and contain the item information for index-
ers. The title page of the item is an essential section, where the 
publication type, title, author names, affiliations, correspon-
dence, copyright details, processing history (submission, revi-
sion, acceptance, and online availability dates), citation mode, 
digital access (DOI), abstract, and author keywords are usually 
displayed to correctly index the item in an abstracting database. 
Additional information on research funding needs to be disclos-
ed in the footnotes, particularly for PubMed/MEDLINE. Criti-
cally important is the correctness of the references section, which </p>

<p>Gasparyan AY, et al. • Multidisciplinary Bibliographic Databases </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2013.28.9.1270 </p>

<p>is processed by citation-tracking databases. 
Apart from the basic technical quality criteria, bibliographic 
databases have sets of selection criteria, aiming to pick the most 
influential periodicals (3). Depending on the aims, professional 
scope, and indexed sources, the selection criteria may differ. 
Peer review and timeliness of publications are the main criteria 
which help choose quality periodicals with streamlined pub-
lishing. An editorial board with experts who are active in resear-
ch and publishing and represent most geographic and profes-
sional areas of the journal is another critical criterion. It is high-
ly desirable to have profiles of the editors visible in prestigious 
databases and research platforms. Selection committees of ci-
tation indexes (for example, Web of Science) pay special atten-
tion to citation profiles of editors and articles in their journals, 
giving priority to the journals with increasing citations in the 
target databases. More emphasis is now also placed on editorial 
credentials, which can be obtained from learned associations 
such as the European Association of Science Editors (EASE), 
Council of Science Editors (CSE), and the Committee on Publi-
cation Ethics (COPE). </p>

<p>THOMSON REUTERS' WEB OF KNOWLEDGE </p>

<p>Web of Science 
The Web of Science 
® (WoS) is the oldest subscription-based ci-
tation index for more than 250 disciplines, and it is provided by 
Thomson Reuters (formerly the Institute for Scientific Informa-
tion, Philadelphia, USA). It covers more than 12,000 journals 
and 150,000 conference proceedings. It is the most prestigious 
database, and the world's top academic and research institu-
tions strongly encourage publications in WoS-indexed journals, 
which affect the institutions' research productivity indicators 
and their place in global ranking systems such as the Times High 
er Education World University Rankings. More than 5,600 aca-
demic institutions in more than 100 countries are now subscrib-
ed to WoS and other services available through the Web of Know-
ledge 
® platform (4). 
Distinguishing features of the WoS database are high selec-
tivity and coverage of historical papers expanded to 1900 for so-
cial sciences and other disciplines (5). The database is biased 
towards English periodicals, particularly in the natural sciences. 
However, journals in other languages are also increasingly cov-
ered, provided that the titles, abstracts, and keywords of the ar-
ticles are in correct English and references are in Roman script. 
Non-English periodicals are particularly well represented in the 
arts and humanities. 
From the very beginning, the journal selection in WoS was 
based on Bradford's Law of Scattering, which assumed that 'very 
productive periodicals' are few in number (6). The initial cita-
tion analyses in the 1960s suggested that the top-tier multidisci-
plinary periodicals influencing global science are Nature and </p>

<p>Science. The strict selection criteria result in the inclusion of a 
small number of influential journals (about 10% of the annual 
applications) and elimination of indexed journals with no or 
substantially decreased citations in WoS (7). 
Abstracting and citation tracking is now possible through the 
following main divisions of WoS: 
• Science Citation Index Expanded 
® (SCI-E, also known as 
SciSearch </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>); 
• Social Sciences Citation Index 
® (SSCI); 
• Arts &amp; Humanities Citation Index 
® (AHCI); 
• Conference Proceedings Citation Index -Science </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>; 
• Conference Proceedings Citation Index -Social Science and 
Humanities </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>. 
The WoS database also includes Index Chemicus 
® and Cur-
rent Chemical Reactions </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, which index chemical compounds 
and reactions, respectively. Recently, the Book Citation Index </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>(BKCI) database was launched to analyse citations of scholarly 
online books in English and other languages with references to 
original research and reviews (8). 
The results of the citation analyses through SCI-E, SSCI and 
AHCI are published annually in the Journal Citation Reports </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>(JCR), a product of Thomson Reuters, which includes the highly 
popular Journal Impact Factor (JIF) and other indices used for 
journal rankings in specific subject categories. The same cita-
tion analyses justify the elimination from WoS journals with no 
citations or those with citation manipulations (more than 80% 
of the total citations included in the calculation of JIF). Citations 
in WoS are also used for the calculation of the h index of indivi-
dual researchers and are displayed at the ResearcherID author-
identifying platform of Thomson Reuters (from 2008). </p>

<p>Current Contents Connect 
The Web of Knowledge platform aggregates information from 
another highly prestigious product of Thomson Reuters, namely 
Current Contents Connect 
® (CCC). It is a current awareness da-
tabase of bibliographic information, which is updated daily to 
incorporate information from rapidly evolving fields of science. 
Its coverage, which is notoriously selective, includes 11,460,000 
records from 1998 to the present. Over 8,000 leading scholarly 
journals, 2000 books and 3,500 web sites are represented in CCC. 
Full bibliographic information of each processed journal item 
along with DOIs, author contact details, and abstracts are avail-
able for searches. 
A large study, analysing overlaps between CCC-and PubMed-
indexed publications (1,167 journals), found 11% more cover-
age of clinical medicine and life sciences journals and 81% more 
coverage of agriculture, biology, and environmental sciences 
journals in CCC (9). Though there was an 89% overlap in bio-
medical journal titles, the study suggested that CCC alerts its 
subscribers on the publications from more influential biomedi-
cal journals. </p>

<p>Gasparyan AY, et al. • Multidisciplinary Bibliographic Databases </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2013.28.9.1270 </p>

<p>Another landmark study found that Web of Science indexes 
approximately 10% more journals across all disciplines than CCC, 
while CCC provides much faster updates (10). 
CCC has the following seven editions: Agriculture, Biology &amp; 
Environmental Sciences; Social &amp; Behavioral Sciences; Clinical 
Medicine; Life Sciences; Physical, Chemical &amp; Earth Sciences; 
Engineering, Computing &amp; Technology; and Arts &amp; Humanities. 
Additionally, the database encompasses two relatively small 
collections of journals and other publications in trade and busi-
ness: Business Collection (240 journals) and Electronics &amp; Tele-
communications Collection (210 journals). </p>

<p>SciVerse SCOPUS </p>

<p>SciVerse Scopus is a relatively new subscription database of ab-
stracts and citations, which was launched in 2004 as a service of 
Elsevier. It is the most comprehensive and well-organised data-
base, with more than 19,500 peer-reviewed journals across vari-
ous disciplines being indexed. The coverage also includes con-
ference proceedings, patents, book series, and scholarly web 
pages. The latter is facilitated by Scirus, a search engine owned 
by Elsevier. Importantly, all MEDLINE-indexed journals are sub-
ject to coverage by Scopus. 
Scopus mainly indexes items from 1996 onwards. However, 
more expanded or even all-inclusive abstract and citation-track-
ing is available for some journals published by Elsevier, particu-
larly for The Lancet, which is listed in the database back to its in-
augural issue in 1823. 
As a European database, Scopus is less biased towards Eng-
lish sources than WoS. However, even non-English journals are 
required to meet a set of quality and publishing ethics criteria 
to get indexed by Scopus. The availability of English-language </p>

<p>abstracts and web pages, readability of abstracts and full-texts, 
and reference lists in Roman alphabet are currently the main 
quality criteria. Additionally, the journal selection for this cita-
tion index, which shares some features with WoS, considers cit-
edness of the articles and editors in the same database. Services 
of SciVerse Scopus are widely used in peer review. In fact, all El-
sevier journals offer one-month access to Scopus and the Sci-
enceDirect full-text library to the reviewers of those journals. 
Scopus retrieves 20% more citations than WoS (11). The dif-
ferences in citation counts in these databases are mainly due to 
citations from non-English sources, more extensively covered 
by Scopus (12). The Scopus database records individual resear-
chers' h index. The SCImago laboratory in Spain relies on cita-
tions in Scopus for regularly calculating open-access metrics 
such as the SCImago Journal Rank (SJR) and average citations 
per paper over a 2-yr period (Cites per Doc 2y), which are wide-
ly viewed as alternatives to the Eigenfactor score and JIF com-
puted by Thomson Reuters (13). Finally, Scopus citations are 
counted for ranking academic institutions by the famous QS 
World University Rankings. </p>

<p>GOOGLE SCHOLAR </p>

<p>Google Scholar is a multidisciplinary search engine which shares 
common features with other search engines such as Elsevier's 
Scirus and bibliographic databases such as WoS and Scopus 
(Table 1). It was launched in 2004 by Google as a free web-based 
search engine. Over the past few years, it has substantially ex-
panded its indexing of full texts of journal articles and books 
due to the agreements with Elsevier and other big and small 
publishers, online libraries, and repositories (for example, In-
gentaConnect </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>). The search engine also covers patents, confer-</p>

<p>Table 1. Main characteristics of Web of Science, Scopus, and Google Scholar </p>

<p>Web of Science 
Scopus 
Google Scholar </p>

<p>Owner 
Thomson Reuters 
Elsevier 
Google 
Year of launching 
1960 
2004 
2004 
Subscription 
Yes 
Yes 
No 
Covered items 
Peer-reviewed sources, conference 
proceedings, book series </p>

<p>Peer-reviewed sources, patents, 
conference proceedings, book series, 
articles in press </p>

<p>Preprint articles (eg from arXiv [physics], 
journal articles, books, patents, conference 
proceedings, theses, presentations, 
web-pages, non-peer-reviewed sources 
Coverage timespan 
1900-present (Science), 
1956-present (Social Science), 
1975-present (Arts &amp; Humanities) </p>

<p>1996-present (for most journals), 
1966-present (for some journals) </p>

<p>Uncertain </p>

<p>Citation tracking 
1900-present 
1996-present 
Inconsistent 
Citations per article 
Retrieves less citations than Scopus 
or Google Scholar </p>

<p>Retrieves more citations than WoS, 
particularly from non-English sources </p>

<p>Retrieves more citations than WoS 
or Scopus 
Number of indexed peer-reviewed journals 
&gt; 12,000~19,500 
Uncertain 
Journal impact indicators 
Available 
Available 
Not available 
Individual performance indicators 
(the h index) </p>

<p>Available 
Available 
Available </p>

<p>Main feature/motto 
Selective coverage of journals based on 
the scientific quality and impact </p>

<p>Comprehensive coverage of journals 
"Stand on the shoulders of giants" </p>

<p>Gasparyan AY, et al. • Multidisciplinary Bibliographic Databases </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2013.28.9.1270 </p>

<p>ence proceedings, theses, presentations, web-pages, newspa-
pers, and other non-peer-reviewed sources. 
Google Scholar has gained a place in basic or back-up litera-
ture search algorithms for its comprehensive coverage of infor-
mation across multiple disciplines, publishing formats and lan-
guages, as well for its simplistic approach to literature searches 
(14). Searches through Google Scholar are not linked to an or-
ganised vocabulary of scholarly keywords, and therefore do not 
require expert searching skills. The indexed sources, including 
web pages, are tagged with web-based keywords, which are 
found in the titles, abstracts, or full-texts of journal, book, and 
website articles. 
The comprehensiveness and easy accessibility of Google sear-
ches can be used to detect plagiarised sentences and larger por-
tions of text, particularly in the absence of a specialised plagia-
rism-detecting software (15). A study comparing Google Schol-
ar with PubMed and Cochrane Library searches for coverage of 
the literature for top systematic reviews in medicine proved that 
searches through Google Scholar alone are sufficient for retrie-
ving all the necessary sources (16). 
Though Google Scholar's indexing criteria and list of covered 
periodicals have not been publicised, it is well known that the 
chances of being indexed and retrieved through the search en-
gine increase with increasing citations and web links to the schol-
arly articles and web-pages of the periodicals. The more an item 
is cited and downloaded, the higher its rank in the Google Schol-
ar's ranking algorithm. 
Similar to WoS and Scopus, Google Scholar has a 'cited by' 
function to track citations of the indexed sources and calculate 
the h index for individual researchers. Journal citation counts in 
Google Scholar substantially outnumber those in WoS and Sco-
pus (17) and constitute important indicators for small journals 
from non-Anglophone countries, where a large proportion of 
citations come from local and non-English journals, PhD the-
ses, and books (18). Unlike WoS and Scopus, no journal perfor-
mance indicator, similar to JIF or SJR, is calculated by Google 
Scholar. 
Despite its comprehensiveness, searches through Google 
Scholar may retrieve irrelevant and non-scholarly materials, 
making it mandatory to critically analyse each retrieved source 
and to perform additional searches through WoS, Scopus, or 
specialised databases (19). Google citations, though large in 
number, may contain those from non-scholarly sources or du-
plicates due to the simultaneous archiving of the citing sources 
in several online platforms. Therefore, Google citation reports 
require additional data from WoS and Scopus citation analytics. </p>

<p>BIOMEDICAL DATABASES </p>

<p>PubMed/MEDLINE 
PubMed is a freely accessible search platform of the US NLM at </p>

<p>the National Institutes of Health, which was first released in 1996. 
It employs the Entrez search engine, which interlinks all the da-
tabases of the National Centre for Biotechnology Information 
(NCBI) at the NLM, including PubMed, PubMed Central, and 
MEDLINE. PubMed is the largest and most well-organised ab-
stract database, which is often accessed by biomedical and oth-
er specialists. As of 24 March 2013, it contains over 22.6 million 
records of journal articles and books indexed by MEDLINE, In-
dex Medicus, and PubMed, going back to 1966 and selectively 
to 1809. Some of the old journals have full citation records in this 
database. For example, over 171,130 articles of the BMJ are in-
dexed from the first issue in 1857, with over 155,900 items being 
linked to the related full-text articles in PubMed Central. With 
over 162,700 indexed items, complete PubMed coverage has 
also been achieved for the top journal Science. PubMed is also 
linked to the NCBI Bookshelf, which is an increasingly popular 
database of selected online books in the life and health sciences. 
Rapid updates, ease of access, diverse functionality, and re-
trieval of relevant information make PubMed the primary bio-
medical search platform. Although individual and journal im-
pact factors are not calculated by PubMed, it is still widely sear-
ched by editors and publishers looking for editorial team mem-
bers and reviewers with current and most relevant research ac-
tivity (20). Searches through PubMed also form the basis for sys-
tematic literature reviews (21). 
Authors, reviewers, and editors may greatly benefit from the 
services of PubMed by improving their knowledge of its core 
components. MEDLINE is the premier abstract database of the 
US NLM, which became freely available via PubMed in 1997. 
Several database vendors such as EBSCO and Web of Knowl-
edge also provide access to the same database. Over 5,500 jour-
nals in medicine, nursing, pharmacy, biochemistry, dentistry, 
and veterinary medicine are indexed in MEDLINE, with most 
abstracts dating back to the 1950s. The number of journals is 
growing, with about 120 journals being newly indexed each year 
(22). Many journals in chemistry, physics, engineering, sociolo-
gy, and science communication with relevance to the life sci-
ences have also been accepted for indexing since 2000. MED-
LINE indexes more than 8,800 articles of The Cochrane Data 
base of Systematic Reviews (Online), which is the core compo-
nent of The Cochrane Library and the premier source of eviden-
ce in health care. 
Another distinctive feature of MEDLINE is its reliance on the 
MeSH controlled vocabulary of the US NLM, which helps re-
trieve specifically tagged items through the Entrez search en-
gine. The indexed journal articles initially appear on the PubMed 
interface without anchoring in the MeSH vocabulary. It takes 
several months, if not a year, to link the articles with the MeSH 
terms. The process of updating and expan ding the list of search 
terms also takes a long time, which limits the functionality of 
MEDLINE. As a prime example, 'bibliogra phic databases' was </p>

<p>Gasparyan AY, et al. • Multidisciplinary Bibliographic Databases </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2013.28.9.1270 </p>

<p>introduced as a MeSH term in 1991, though the first article tagg-
ed with this term was published back in 1966 (23). 
Currently, approximately 2.7 million articles indexed in Pub-
Med are also archived in PubMed Central, a free (full text) digi-
tal archive of the US NLM. However, not all of these articles are 
indexed in MEDLINE. PubMed Central has its own literature 
selection committee, which have archived many online jour-
nals based on their own technical and scientific criteria. Appli-
cations from journals wishing to be archived in PubMed Cen-
tral require the journals to provide contents of at least 50 recent-
ly published articles, presented in a compatible XML (Extensi-
ble Markup Language) format. The archived items receive uni-
que identifiers in PubMed Central (PMCID) and PubMed (PMID), 
with abstracting in PubMed and corresponding entries in the 
Web of Knowledge and EBSCO platforms. 
The PubMed Central archive also serves as a repository for 
NIH-funded authors, who are required to submit any article 
published in any journal to the NIH Manuscript Submission 
system for XML conversion and permanent archiving. Many 
other funders, such as The Medical Research Council (UK), Can-
cer Research UK, have also adopted similar policies for their re-
searchers. Finally, some publishers operating both subscription 
and open-access publishing models may opt to selectively de-
posit their journal articles in PubMed Central. Relevant exam-
ples are the Springer Open Choice and Bentham Science Pub-
lishers Open Access Plus projects, which offer authors the op-
tion of depositing their articles from subscription journals in 
PubMed Central after payment of open-access fees. 
Despite the visibility in PubMed, journals archived in PubMed 
Central but not indexed in MEDLINE are poorly retrievable be-
cause their abstracts are not tagged with MeSH terms. The web-
site provides some tips on effective searching using Boolean 
terms, for example, to effectively search within a journal the ti-
tle should be included as a keyword, using the Advanced search. </p>

<p>EMBASE 
EMBASE is the largest subscription-based biomedical and phar-
macological abstracts database. EMBASE, an Elsevier product, 
contains over 25 million records from 1947 to the present. It in-
dexes over 7,600 journals. Similar to Scopus, EMBASE covers all 
items indexed by MEDLINE. However, EMBASE contains 5 mil-
lion more records than MEDLINE, including many European 
and non-English sources. The distinctive features of EMBASE 
are its focus on drug-related sources and reliance on the EM-
TREE thesaurus, an Elsevier product which lists over 56,000 drug 
and medical terms for EMBASE and EMBiology (a specialised 
database launched by Elsevier in 2005). 
Several studies have found that EMBASE covers controlled 
clinical trials more comprehensively than MEDLINE. For ex-
ample, 16% more trials on rheumatoid arthritis, osteoporosis, 
and low back pain are indexed in EMBASE (24). More extensive </p>

<p>coverage in EMBASE also relates to therapeutics and adverse 
effects of drugs (25). However, more extensive coverage does 
not necessarily mean more quality items, and this is why it is 
recommended that EMBASE is complemented by MEDLINE 
and/or other evidence-based databases (26). </p>

<p>The Cochrane Library 
The Cochrane Library is a specialised collection of databases 
for evidence-based information, which was designed by the 
Cochrane Collaboration. It is part of the Wiley Online Library. 
Though the Cochrane databases are subscription-based, these 
are now freely accessible in most developed and developing 
countries, partly due to the WHO's HINARI project. The follow-
ing three databases are developed by the Cochrane Collabora-
tion experts: 
• The Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews is an online 
periodical, indexed in MEDLINE and Web of Science, which 
contains peer-reviewed systematic reviews of the Cochrane 
Review Groups. 
• The Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials (CEN-
TRAL) is the main hub for articles on controlled trials. 
• The Cochrane Methodology Register (Methodology Regis-
ter) contains a bibliography of articles on methods of con-
trolled trials. 
The Cochrane systematic reviews and trials registry are the 
main sources of evidence-based medicine, which may offer 
references for systematic reviews and meta-analyses, comple-
menting those from MEDLINE and EMBASE databases. 
The Centre for Reviews and Dissemination, a UK-based or-
ganisation, designed three additional databases of the Cochrane 
Library: 
• Database of Abstracts of Reviews of Effects (DARE); 
• National Health Service Economic Evaluation Database 
(NHS EED); 
• Health Technology Assessment Database (HTA Database). 
These three databases focus on systematic reviews and other 
articles of economic assessments of drug therapies and health 
technologies around the world. Health policy experts and ad-
ministrators often refer to these databases when they take evi-
dence-based decisions. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Some of the current databases combine features of libraries, 
search engines, indexing, and citation tracking services (for ex-
ample, PubMed Central). Others list journal titles and provide 
access to their websites and contents, but do not have a system 
of keywords tagging and tracking citations (for example, Direc-
tory of Open Access Journals, UlrichsWeb </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>). Most international 
databases predominantly index English sources. This limitation 
is partly overcome by national abstract and/or citation indexes. </p>

<p>Gasparyan AY, et al. • Multidisciplinary Bibliographic Databases </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2013.28.9.1270 </p>

<p>Though the coverage of national databases may overlap with 
international databases, they often provide basic visibility for 
unique local, non-English periodicals, books, and other items 
(27). Not all national indexes, however, have strict indexing cri-
teria and list quality items. The proliferation of specialised jour-
nals and the multidisciplinary direction of current research stu-
dies allow most authors to publish their works in directories 
which are far from their narrow field of specialisation. As a good 
example, in a landmark study on bibliographic performance of 
rheumatology in MEDLINE, EMBASE, and BIOSIS, 45% of pa-
pers on hot topics in the field were found in non-rheumatology 
journals and each of these databases was capable of retrieving 
no more than 50% of the relevant citations (28). </p>



<p>Address for Correspondence: </p>

<p>Armen Yuri Gasparyan, MD </p>

<p>Chief Editor, European Science Editing; Departments of Rheumatology and 
Research and Development, Dudley Group NHS Foundation Trust (A Teaching Trust 
of the University of Birmingham, UK), Russells Hall Hospital, Dudley DY1 2HQ, 
West Midlands, UK 
E-mail: a.gasparyan@gmail.com </p>

<p>Note: This is a secondary publication of the article titled "Gas-
paryan AY, Ayvazyan L, Kitas GD. Multidisciplinary bibliograph-
ic databases. In: Smart P. et al. (eds) Science Editors' Handbook. 
EASE, 2013. www.ease.org.uk". </p>

</text></tei>