<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3771852" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2013:7 953-961 </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 
Dovepress </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>953 </p>

<p>O r i g i n a l r e s e a r c h </p>

<p>open access to scientific and medical research </p>

<p>Open access Full Text article </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.2147/DDDT.S47057 </p>

<p>hologram quantitative structure-activity 
relationship and comparative molecular field 
analysis studies within a series of tricyclic 
phthalimide hiV-1 integrase inhibitors </p>

<p>Abstract: Acquired immunodeficiency syndrome is a public health problem worldwide caused 
by the Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV). Treatment with antiretroviral drugs is the best 
option for viral suppression, reducing morbidity and mortality. However, viral resistance in HIV-1 
therapy has been reported. HIV-1 integrase (IN) is an essential enzyme for effective viral replica-
tion and an attractive target for the development of new inhibitors. In the study reported here, 
two-and three-dimensional quantitative structure-activity relationship (2D/3D-QSAR) stud-
ies, applying hologram quantitative structure-activity relationship (HQSAR) and comparative 
molecular field analysis (CoMFA) methods, respectively, were performed on a series of tricyclic 
phthalimide HIV-1 IN inhibitors. The best HQSAR model (q 
2 = 0.802, r 
2 = 0.972) was obtained </p>

<p>using atoms, bonds, and connectivity as the fragment distinction, a fragment size of 2-5 atoms, 
hologram length of 61 bins, and six components. The best CoMFA model (q 
2 = 0.748, r 
2 = 0.974) </p>

<p>was obtained with alignment of all atoms of the tricyclic phthalimide moiety (alignment II). The 
HQSAR contribution map identified that the carbonyl-hydroxy-aromatic nitrogen motif made 
a positive contribution to the activity of the compounds. Furthermore, CoMFA contour maps 
suggested that bulky groups in meta and para positions in the phenyl ring would increase the 
biological activity of this class. The conclusions of this work may lead to a better understanding 
of HIV-1 IN inhibition and contribute to the design of new and more potent derivatives. 
Acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS) is a public health problem worldwide 
caused by the Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV). It is estimated that 33.3 million 
people are infected with HIV-1 and about 2.1 million deaths are reported every year 
that are related to AIDS. 
1 HIV-1 infection is characterized by destruction of immune 
cells, especially T lymphocytes, which are responsible for the immune response against 
antigens, pathogens, and cancer cells. </p>

<p>2   The HIV-1 replication cycle depends on different macromolecules, including three 
viral enzymes, namely, reverse transcriptase, protease, and integrase (IN). Currently, 
reverse transcriptase and protease are targets for several antiretroviral US Food and 
Drug Administration-approved drugs, such as efavirenz and indinavir, respectively, 
while for IN there are just two, raltegravir and elvitegravir. </p>

<p>3,4   Treatment with antiretroviral drugs is the best option for viral suppression, reduc-
ing morbidity and mortality. However, as viral resistance in HIV therapy has been </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Drug Design, Development and Therapy 
4 September 2013 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2013:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>954 </p>

<p>Magalhães et al </p>

<p>reported, 
5-7 additional therapeutic approaches are needed. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>HIV-1 IN is one of three essential enzymes required for viral 
replication, and the absence of a host-cell equivalent target 
means that IN inhibitors may not interfere with cellular physi-
ological process, suggesting that they are an attractive target 
for biological active compounds. 
8 Thus, resistance to HIV-1 
IN inhibitors is the greatest problem and the discovery of new 
potential inhibitors is essential for AIDS treatment. </p>

<p>5,7   In an attempt to design new chemical entities with effi-
cient antiretroviral activity, we explored the two-dimensional 
(2D) and three-dimensional (3D) molecular features of a 
series of tricyclic phthalimide HIV-1 IN inhibitors developed 
by Verschueren et al, 
9 using two-and three-dimensional 
quantitative structure-activity relationship (2D/3D-QSAR) 
approaches, namely, hologram quantitative structure-
activity relationship (HQSAR) 
10 and comparative molecular 
field analysis (CoMFA) 
11 methods, respectively, which are 
powerful ligand-based strategies in drug design. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Dataset </p>

<p>The same dataset was used for the HQSAR and CoMFA 
studies containing the 42 tricyclic phthalimides developed 
by Verschueren et al 
9 showing HIV IN inhibitory activity 
(Table 1). The biological activity of all compounds was used 
as originally expressed, as pIC 50 (M) values (−Log of the 
half maximal inhibitory concentration, IC 50 ) values. The 42 
compounds were divided into training (30 compounds) and 
test (12 compounds) sets, ensuring that both sets contained 
structurally diverse compounds with high, medium and 
low activity, to avoid possible problems during the external 
validation. </p>

<p>Molecular modeling design 
and conformational analysis </p>

<p>All tricyclic phthalimides (1-42) were built using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPARTAN</rs>'<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">10</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Wavefunction, Inc</rs>, Irvine, CA, USA) 
for Windows XP </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>. Conformational analysis was performed 
with the conformer distribution Monte Carlo method, using 
Merck Molecular Force Field 94 (MMFF94). The lowest 
energy conformations were geometrically optimized by the 
Parameterized Model number 3 (PM3) semi-empirical method 
available in the program. In the absence of a compound from 
the phthalimide class co-crystallized with HIV-1 IN, the lowest 
energy conformations were used as the bioactive conforma-
tion, a methodology successfully used by other authors. </p>

<p>12-14   hQsar models </p>

<p>The structures of tricyclic phthalimides were converted into 
fragments initially using the default fragment size of 4-7 
atoms per fragment. All fragments were allocated in defined 
molecular hologram lengths (53, 59, 61, 71, 83, 97, 151, 199, 
257, 307, 353, 401 bins) and fragment distinction analysis 
was performed in terms of atoms, bonds, connectivity, 
hydrogen, and donor/acceptor atoms. Since these parameters 
may affect HQSAR models, different combinations of these 
parameters were considered during the HQSAR runs. </p>

<p>15   After the partial least-squares (PLS) analysis, several 
QSAR models were generated for each distinguishing 
fragment (Table 2). Importantly, in the HQSAR method, 
the alignment step is not necessary for the generation of a 
model. All QSAR models were generated using PLS and the 
internal validation was performed by leave-one-out (LOO) 
cross-validation. An external validation was performed with 
the test set compounds, which was not considered in the 
HQSAR model development. </p>

<p>3D-Qsar molecular alignment </p>

<p>Conformer selection and molecular alignment are the most 
essential steps in 3D-QSAR studies. The accuracy and reliability 
of the CoMFA model is directly dependent on the molecular 
alignment rule. 
11 In this study, the alignments were carried out 
using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">SYBYL-X</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">1.1</rs> software package (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Tripos International, St Louis, MO, USA</rs>) and made based on the presence of a moiety 
common to all derivatives, by adopting the RMS (root mean 
square) atom-fit rule for superposition of individual atoms. Two 
different alignments were performed and three models were 
generated from each one. The most active compound from 
the series (33) was used as the template for both alignments 
(Figure 1). In alignment I, all atoms of the tricyclic phthalimide 
moiety were chosen, except for the hydroxyl groups and external 
carbon atoms of the pyrazine ring. In alignment II, all atoms of 
tricyclic phthalimide moiety were chosen (Figure 1). </p>

<p>coMFa 3D-Qsar models </p>

<p>For CoMFA calculations, steric and electrostatic interac-
tions were calculated using three different probes: an 
sp 
3 -hybridized carbon atom with +1.0 charge (Csp 
3 + 1), a 
hydrogen atom with +1.0 charge (H + 1), and an sp 
3 oxygen 
atom with -1.0 charge (Osp 
3 -1). Tripos standard and indica-
tor force fields with a distance-dependent dielectric constant 
at all intersections in a regularly spaced grid (1 and 2 Å) were 
evaluated (Tables 4 and 5). The default value of 30 kcal/mol 
was set as the maximum steric and electrostatic energy </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2013:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>955 </p>

<p>hQsar and coMFa studies in tricyclic phthalimide hiV-1 integrase inhibitors </p>

<p>Table 1 chemical structures and biological data of 42 tricyclic phthalimide hiV-1 integrase inhibitors </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>N 
C 
H 3 </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>N 
N </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>5-42 </p>

<p>No 
R1 
pIC 50 (M) 
pIC 50 (M) 
pIC 50 (M) 
No 
R1 
No 
R1 </p>

<p>1* </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>&lt;4.00 
15 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>5.85 
29* </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>6.43 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Br </p>

<p>6.42 
16* </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>6.09 
30 </p>

<p>Cl </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>6.75 </p>

<p>3* </p>

<p>Br </p>

<p>6.59 
17 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>6.25 
31* </p>

<p>Cl </p>

<p>6.66 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Br </p>

<p>5.44 
18* </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>5.70 
32 </p>

<p>Cl </p>

<p>6.38 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Br </p>

<p>6.68 
19 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>6.37 
33 </p>

<p>Cl </p>

<p>Cl </p>

<p>6.95 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>CH 3 </p>

<p>4.31 
20 </p>

<p>O 
O </p>

<p>6.37 
34* </p>

<p>Cl </p>

<p>Cl </p>

<p>6.73 </p>

<p>7 
4.98 
21 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>6.11 
35 </p>

<p>Br </p>

<p>6.20 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>NH </p>

<p>&lt;4.00 
22* 
5.80 
36 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>5.17 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>5.62 
23 </p>

<p>O 
F </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>5.69 
37 
5.85 </p>

<p>10 
5.66 
24 </p>

<p>F 
F 
F </p>

<p>6.37 
38 </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>6.17 </p>

<p>11 
5.98 
25* </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>6.25 
39 </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>6.30 </p>

<p>12 
5.69 
26 </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>6.38 
40 </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>6.00 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>5.00 
27* </p>

<p>Br 
F </p>

<p>6.36 
41* 
5.84 </p>

<p>14* </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>6.25 
28 </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>Br </p>

<p>6.45 
42 
5.69 </p>

<p>Notes: *Test set compounds. pic 50 represents the -log ic 50 , where ic 50 is the half maximal inhibitory concentration. 
Abbreviation: hiV, Human immunodeficiency virus. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2013:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>956 </p>

<p>Magalhães et al </p>

<p>showing HIV-1 IN inhibitory activity. The chemical structures 
and biological data of these inhibitors are listed in Table 1. 
The compounds' distribution in the training (30) and test 
(12) sets, an important step in the development of QSAR 
models, was careful, aiming to maximize the test set diversity 
and to analyze the model prediction accuracy. 
HQSAR studies require values to be selected for the para-
meters that specify the hologram length, as well as the size 
and type of fragments to be encoded. 
16 The molecular frag-
ments were generated using the following fragment distinc-
tion parameters: atoms, bonds, connections, hydrogen atoms, 
chirality, and donor/acceptor atoms. The HQSAR models were 
first generated using the default fragment size (4-7 atoms) 
combined with various fragment types and various hologram 
lengths (Table 2). To identify how the fragment size could influ-
ence the statistical parameters, we tested different fragment 
sizes (2-5, 3-6, 4-7, 5-8, 6-9, and 7-10 atoms) on the three 
best fragment distinction parameters of this model having the 
highest statistical indexes (models 1, 10, and 15) (Table 2). 
The best HQSAR model for these HIV-1 IN inhibitors was 
found to be model 28, with atoms, bonds, and connectivity 
as the fragment distinction parameters, and 2-5 atoms as the 
fragment size, showing good predictive capacity (q 
2 = 0.802), 
high data fitting (r 
2 = 0.972), and low cross-validated standard 
error (SE cv = 0.340) (Table 3). </p>

<p>hQsar contribution maps </p>

<p>According to the HQSAR method, it is possible to predict 
the activity value of a molecule by mapping its structural 
fragments. Thus, HQSAR contribution map analysis is an 
important step toward understanding the individual atomic </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>Cl </p>

<p>Cl </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* * </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>Cl </p>

<p>Cl </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* * </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>Figure 1 selected atoms to alignment i (A) and three-dimensional (3D) view of superimposed aligned molecules (B). selected atoms to alignment ii (C) and 3D view of 
superimposed aligned molecules (D). </p>

<p>cutoff. A PLS approach was used to derive 3D-QSAR and 
the cross-validation with the LOO method 
11 to maximize the 
probability that the results would have predictive validity. </p>

<p>Results and discussion 
hQsar models </p>

<p>The dataset used for the HQSAR studies contained the 
42 tricyclic phthalimides developed by Verschueren et al </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Table 2 summary of hologram quantitative structure-activity 
relationship (HQSAR) statistical indexes for the influence of 
various fragment distinctions (FD), using 4-7 as the fragment size 
parameter </p>

<p>Model 
FD 
Statistical indexes </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>SE cv 
PC 
HL </p>

<p>1 
A 
0.765 
0.965 
0.370 
6 
97 
2 
B 
0.362 
0.668 
0.574 
3 
97 
3 
c 
0.517 
0.918 
0.520 
5 
97 
4 
h 
0.258 
0.465 
0.608 
2 
97 
5 
Da 
0.625 
0.889 
0.458 
5 
199 
6 
a/B 
0.644 
0.963 
0.456 
6 
59 
7 
a/c 
0.551 
0.972 
0.512 
6 
401 
8 
a/h 
0.474 
0.942 
0.555 
6 
151 
9 
a/Da 
0.482 
0.926 
0.550 
6 
83 
10 
B/C 
0.660 
0.976 
0.446 
6 
353 
11 
B/h 
0.362 
0.668 
0.574 
3 
97 
12 
B/Da 
0.454 
0.959 
0.553 
5 
307 
13 
c/h 
0.517 
0.918 
0.520 
5 
97 
14 
c/Da 
0.250 
0.474 
0.600 
1 
401 
15 
A/B/C 
0.649 
0.959 
0.453 
6 
61 </p>

<p>Note: Models 1, 10 and 15 are indicated in bold to show that they are the three 
best models using 4-7 as the fragment size parameter. 
Abbreviations: a, atoms; B, bonds; c, connectivity; Da, donor/acceptor atoms; 
h, hydrogen; hl, hologram length; Pc, principal components; q 
2 , leave-one-out 
cross-validated correlation coefficient; r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, non-cross-validated correlation coefficient; 
se cv , cross-validated standard error. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2013:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>957 </p>

<p>hQsar and coMFa studies in tricyclic phthalimide hiV-1 integrase inhibitors </p>

<p>contributions to the biological activities through a color code. 
This code ranges from red to green in a spectrum indicating 
favorable (yellow, green blue, and green), neutral (white), 
and unfavorable (red, red orange, and orange) contributions 
(Figure 2). 
The fragment contribution map of the most active 
compound, 33, shows no fragments with negative contribution 
(Figure 2). As can be seen, the carbonyl-hydroxy-aromatic 
nitrogen motif was colored white and green, indicating </p>

<p>neutral and positive contributions to activity, respectively, 
since this moiety is common for all compounds and provides 
a structural scaffold for holding the pharmacophoric groups 
in suitable orientation for maximum complementarity with 
the catalytic site of HIV-1 IN. 
9 Furthermore, the carbonyl and 
hydroxyl oxygens could chelate the Mg 
2+ ion in the active site, 
an essential interaction for enzyme inhibition. </p>

<p>9,17,18   In addition, the methylene spacer (colored green) that 
links the phthalimide nitrogen to the 3,4-dichlorophenyl 
group (mostly colored green and yellow) in compound 33 
appears to be important for directing this bulky aromatic 
group in the active site of the enzyme, as suggested by dock-
ing studies. 
7 This is consistent with benzodioxoles 13, 14, 
and 15, since the compound with one methylene spacer (14)  was more potent than that with none (13) or with two (15) 
methylene spacers. </p>

<p>7   coMFa models </p>

<p>In the present work, all CoMFA models were derived using 
the same training and test sets as in the HQSAR analysis. 
To validate the reliability of these models, all important 
statistical parameters were analyzed, including LOO cross-
validated correlation coefficient (q 
2 ), non-cross-validated 
correlation coefficient (r 
2 ), standard error of the estimate 
(SEE) and F-statistic values. To see how the alignment rule 
could influence the predictive capability of a model, two dif-
ferent alignments, I and II, were proposed, and three different 
probe atoms and lattice spacing (1 and 2 Å) were performed 
to obtain the best model. The statistical results obtained from 
the CoMFA models are summarized in Table 4. 
The PLS statistical analyses performed for alignment I 
showed that the best model generated was self-consistent 
(r 
2 = 0.973), with good predictive ability (q 
2 = 0.625), and 
low SEE (0.130), with optimum number of components (six) 
determined by SAMPLS (sample-distance PLS) analysis </p>

<p>(33) 
(8) </p>

<p>Positive 
Neutral 
Negative </p>

<p>Figure 2 The hologram quantitative structure-activity relationship contribution maps of the most (33) and least (8) potent hiV-1 integrase inhibitors. 
Abbreviation: hiV, Human immunodeficiency virus. </p>

<p>Table 3 summary of hologram quantitative structure-activity 
relationship statistical indexes for the influence of various 
fragment sizes (Fs), using atoms (Models 16-21); bonds and 
connectivity (Models 22-27); or atoms, bonds, and connectivity 
(Models 28-33) as the fragment distinction parameter </p>

<p>Model 
FS 
Statistical indexes </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>SE cv 
PC 
HL </p>

<p>16 
2-5 
0.568 
0.905 
0.502 
6 
257 
17 
3-6 
0.706 
0.927 
0.639 
5 
401 
18 
4-7 
0.765 
0.965 
0.370 
6 
97 
19 
5-8 
0.776 
0.959 
0.362 
6 
59 
20 
6-9 
0.491 
0.956 
0.545 
6 
353 
21 
7-10 
0.611 
0.945 
0.477 
6 
59 
22 
2-5 
0.739 
0.964 
0.391 
6 
199 
23 
3-6 
0.731 
0.972 
0.397 
6 
353 
24 
4-7 
0.660 
0.976 
0.446 
6 
353 
25 
5-8 
0.618 
0.982 
0.472 
6 
401 
26 
6-9 
0.542 
0.978 
0.517 
6 
401 
27 
7-10 
nD 
nD 
nD 
nD 
nD 
28 
2-5 
0.802 
0.972 
0.340 
6 
61 
29 
3-6 
0.671 
0.964 
0.438 
6 
61 
30 
4-7 
0.649 
0.959 
0.453 
6 
61 
31 
5-8 
0.599 
0.971 
0.484 
6 
83 
32 
6-9 
0.545 
0.978 
0.516 
6 
199 
33 
7-10 
0.455 
0.976 
0.564 
6 
401 </p>

<p>Note: Models 19, 22 and 28 are shown in bold to indicate that they are the three 
best models in each fragment distinction parameter. 
Abbreviations: hl, hologram length; nD, not determined; q </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, leave-one-out cross-
validated correlation coefficient; r 
2 , non-cross-validated correlation coefficient; 
Pc, principal components; se cv , cross-validated standard error. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2013:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>958 </p>

<p>Magalhães et al </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Color legend 
20.000 
10.000 </p>

<p>Color legend 
20.000 
10.000 </p>

<p>Color legend </p>

<p>20.000 </p>

<p>10.000 </p>

<p>Color legend 
20.000 
10.000 </p>

<p>Figure 3 comparative molecular field analysis contour maps for steric field with the most (33; A) and least (8; B) active compounds. 
Note: left images show front view; right images show side view. </p>

<p>Table 4 Comparative molecular field analysis for alignments I and 
II using Tripos standard and indicator force fields with a lattice 
spacing of 2 Å </p>

<p>PLS 
statistics </p>

<p>Tripos standard 
Tripos indicator </p>

<p>Probe atom (charge) 
Probe atom (charge) </p>

<p>Csp </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>(+1) </p>

<p>H 
(+1) </p>

<p>Osp </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>(-1) </p>

<p>Csp </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>(+1) </p>

<p>H 
(+1) </p>

<p>Osp </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>(-1) </p>

<p>Alignment I 
q </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.588 
0.471 
0.573 
0.625 
0.336 
0.597 
F-value 
253.085 333.547 296.312 125.159 56.323 104.418 
r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.957 
0.799 
0.991 
0.973 
0.941 
0.968 
see 
0.156 
0.323 
0.073 
0.130 
0.190 
0.142 
Pc 
4 
2 
6 
6 
6 
6 
Alignment II 
q </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.557 
0.490 
0.484 
0.748 
0.317 
0.597 
F-value 
445.728 361.309 287.329 130.192 55.905 104.418 
r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.992 
0.990 
0.988 
0.974 
0.941 
0.968 
see 
0.069 
0.077 
0.086 
0.127 
0.191 
0.142 
Pc 
4 
5 
5 
6 
3 
6 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: Pc, principal components; Pls, partial least squares; q 
2 , leave-
one-out cross-validated correlation coefficient; r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, non-cross-validated correlation 
coefficient; SEE, standard error of the estimate. </p>

<p>Table 5 Comparative molecular field analysis for alignment II 
using lattice spacing of 1 Å and csp 
3 (+1) as the probe atom </p>

<p>PLS statistics 
Standard 
Indicator </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.477 
0.583 
F-value 
675.001 
399.966 
r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.995 
0.991 
see 
0.056 
0.073 
Pc 
3 
6 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: Pc, principal components; Pls, partial least squares; q 
2 , leave-
one-out cross-validated correlation coefficient; r 
2 , non-cross-validated correlation 
coefficient; SEE, standard error of the estimate. </p>

<p>implemented in SYBYL-X 1.1. As can be seen in Table 4, this 
model was obtained using a carbon sp 
3 (+1) probe atom in 
an indicator force field, 
19 with a lattice spacing of 2 Å. In 
alignment II, the PLS statistical parameters were better than 
those generated for alignment I (q 
2 = 0.748, r 
2 = 0.974, and 
SEE = 0.127) (Table 4). Despite the fact that the statistical 
results for alignments I and II both provided consistent data, 
alignment II was selected as the best model. 
With the objective of evaluating the influence of steric and 
electrostatic interaction energies for model generation, the value 
of the grid spacing was decreased to 1 Å using both force fields 
(standard and indicator) and the carbon sp 
3 (+1) probe atom 
(Table 5). After reducing the cell size to 1 Å, no improvement 
was observed in q 
2 values (predictive model), although some 
statistical parameters, such as r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, F-value, and SEE, presented 
with better values when compared with the best model gener-
ated with the 2 Å cell size. Normally, 3D-QSAR studies with 
a q 
2 value .0.5 are considered statistically significant, but 
q 
2 alone is not sufficient to assess the predictive power of a 
QSAR model. 
20 Thus, external validation is the only way to 
establish a reliable QSAR model. In this study, the best model 
was validated using the test set of 12 compounds, which was 
used to predict the activities of the test set. </p>

<p>coMFa contour maps </p>

<p>CoMFA steric and electrostatic contour maps are useful in the 
context of ligand-receptor interactions. Furthermore, these 
contour maps can help identify areas where changes in </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2013:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>959 </p>

<p>hQsar and coMFa studies in tricyclic phthalimide hiV-1 integrase inhibitors </p>

<p>steric or electrostatic fields can affect biological activity 
and indicate important regions for ligand interaction with 
the receptor site. Moreover, the absence of a field does not 
necessarily mean that a particular pharmacophore is not 
important for activity; but, according to the generated model, 
all derivatives exert the same influence at that point. 
The analysis of the steric and electrostatic contour maps 
was made only with the model generated by alignment II 
(q 
2 = 0.748). The steric and electrostatic contributions of the 
final model were 97% and 3%, respectively. This means that 
the model was more influenced by the steric field around tri-
cyclic phthalimides than the electrostatic field. The CoMFA 
contour maps of the most (33) and least (8) active compounds 
are shown in Figure 3. 
The green contour characterizes the regions where bulky 
substituents would increase the HIV-1 IN inhibitory activity, 
whereas the yellow contour indicates the regions where steric 
bulk would decrease the activity. The contributions of the 
green and yellow contours were maintained at the default 
values of 80% and 20%, respectively. 
Figure 3A shows two favorable green regions for 
compound 33 located close to the meta and para positions 
of the benzyl group (R1 substituent), mainly near the two 
(orto and para) chlorine atoms. This indicates that bulky 
groups at those positions are favorable and this accounts for 
the high biological activity of 33. The several unfavorable 
yellow regions spread around the benzyl group indicate that 
bulky groups at those positions would significantly reduce 
the binding affinity. In the contour map of the most active 
compound, 33 (Figure 3A), it can be observed that the benzyl 
group is planar and does not touch the yellow regions, while 
in the map of the least active compound, 8 (Figure 3B), the 
piperidine ring (R1 substituent) is localized in the yellow 
prohibitive regions. </p>

<p>external validation of the best hQsar 
and coMFa models </p>

<p>The experimental pIC 50 , predicted pIC 50 , and residual values 
of the tricyclic phthalimide HIV-1 IN inhibitors obtained 
for the best HQSAR and CoMFA models are reported in 
Table 6. The comparison plots between the experimental and 
predicted potencies of both the training and test sets using the 
best HQSAR and CoMFA models are shown in Figure 4. 
In this work, we considered as outliers all compounds 
of the training and test sets whose differences between 
experimental and predicted activities exceeded 2.0 standard 
deviations (SD) from the mean of the residuals 
(HQSAR 2*SD = 0.68 and CoMFA 2*SD = 0.90). 
21 According </p>

<p>Table 6 experimental and predicted pic 50 values of training and 
test set compounds </p>

<p>No Experimental HQSAR 
CoMFA </p>

<p>Predicted Residual Predicted Residual </p>

<p>1* 
4.00 
5.95 
-1.95 
4.12 
-0.12 
2 
6.42 
6.35 
0.07 
nD 
nD 
3* 
6.59 
6.63 
-0.04 
4.00 
2.59 
4 
5.44 
5.54 
-0.10 
nD 
nD 
5 
6.68 
6.39 
0.29 
6.65 
0.03 
6 
4.31 
4.40 
-0.09 
4.22 
0.09 
7 
4.98 
4.92 
0.06 
4.97 
0.01 
8 
4.00 
3.92 
0.08 
4.09 
-0.09 
9 
5.62 
5.67 
-0.05 
5.67 
-0.04 
10 
5.66 
5.71 
-0.05 
5.56 
0.10 
11 
5.98 
5.93 
0.05 
5.90 
0.08 
12 
5.69 
5.93 
-0.24 
5.69 
0.00 
13 
5.00 
5.01 
-0.01 
4.97 
0.03 
14* 6.25 
6.45 
-0.20 
5.80 
0.45 
15 
5.85 
5.93 
-0.08 
5.83 
0.02 
16* 6.09 
6.23 
-0.14 
5.53 
0.56 
17 
6.25 
6.17 
0.08 
6.12 
0.13 
18* 5.70 
6.26 
-0.56 
5.44 
0.27 
19 
6.37 
6.35 
0.02 
6.44 
-0.07 
20 
6.37 
6.20 
0.17 
6.31 
0.06 
21 
6.11 
6.24 
-0.13 
6.13 
-0.02 
22* 5.80 
6.41 
-0.61 
6.14 
-0.34 
23 
5.69 
5.68 
0.01 
5.81 
-0.12 
24 
6.37 
6.35 
0.02 
6.34 
0.03 
25* 6.25 
6.29 
-0.04 
6.14 
0.11 
26 
6.38 
6.26 
0.12 
6.04 
0.34 
27* 6.36 
6.53 
-0.17 
6.15 
0.21 
28 
6.45 
6.53 
-0.08 
6.47 
-0.02 
29* 6.43 
6.47 
-0.04 
6.18 
0.25 
30 
6.75 
6.73 
0.02 
6.77 
-0.01 
31* 6.66 
6.48 
0.18 
6.18 
0.48 
32 
6.38 
6.43 
-0.05 
6.53 
-0.15 
33 
6.95 
6.95 
0.00 
7.00 
-0.04 
34* 6.73 
6.79 
-0.06 
6.57 
0.16 
35 
6.20 
6.45 
-0.25 
6.23 
-0.03 
36 
5.17 
5.14 
0.03 
5.50 
-0.33 
37 
5.85 
5.85 
0.00 
5.79 
0.06 
38 
6.17 
6.13 
0.04 
6.14 
0.03 
39 
6.30 
6.14 
0.16 
6.30 
0.00 
40 
6.00 
6.15 
-0.15 
6.06 
-0.06 
41* 5.84 
6.05 
-0.21 
6.17 
-0.33 
42 
5.69 
5.64 
0.05 
5.67 
0.02 </p>

<p>Notes: *Test set compounds; "nD" indicates that a value was not determined 
because the molecules did not show any atoms common to the core used for 
alignment, resulting in the withdrawal of the same training set. 
Abbreviations: CoMFA, comparative molecular field analysis; HQSAR, hologram 
quantitative structure-activity relationship; pic 50 , -log ic 50 ; ic 50 , half maximal 
inhibitory concentration. </p>

<p>to this criterion, there was one outlier for each model: 
compound 1 for HQSAR and compound 3 for CoMFA. 
The HQSAR outlier, 1, presented the highest residual 
value (-1.95), but it must be remembered that this compound 
belonged to the test set and did not take part in the model 
building process. Derivative 1 is analogous to 26, one of the </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2013:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Magalhães et al </p>

<p>most potent tricyclic phthalimide inhibitors, and both have 
the same 4-fluorobenzyl group as the R1 substituent, dif-
fering only in the first ring (Table 1). The HQSAR models 
overestimated the biological potency of 1 probably because 
it has a similar fingerprint to compound 26. 
The CoMFA outlier, 3, which also belongs to the test 
set, presented the highest residual value (2.59). In this case, 
the CoMFA model underestimated the biological activity 
of 3 because this derivative has structural difference in the 
first ring. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The methylene spacer that links the phthalimide nitrogen 
to the 3,4-dichlorophenyl group in compound 33 appears to 
be important for directing this bulky aromatic group in the 
active site of the enzyme, as suggested by docking studies. </p>

<p>7   Predictable and statistically significant CoMFA and HQSAR 
models of tricyclic phthalimide HIV-1 IN inhibitors were 
obtained. The CoMFA model emphasized the importance 
of the steric descriptor field, as it explained nearly 97% of 
the variance in HIV-1 IN inhibitory activity. The inhibi-
tory activities of the external test set of compounds were 
well predicted and explain the statistical robustness of the 
CoMFA and HQSAR models created. This could be useful 
in the development of newer molecules that are structurally 
related to these HIV-1 IN inhibitors. The CoMFA contour 
map analysis showed two favorable green regions located 
close to the meta and para positions of the benzyl group 
(R1 substituent), mainly near the two (orto and para) chlorine 
atoms for compound 33. This indicates that bulky groups at 
those positions are favorable for activity, which accounts 
for the increased activity of the inhibitors in this series. </p>

<p>Training set compounds </p>

<p>Test set compounds </p>

<p>Experimental pIC 50 </p>

<p>7.50 </p>

<p>6.50 </p>

<p>5.50 </p>

<p>4.50 </p>

<p>Predicted pIC </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>3.50 
3.50 
4.50 
5.50 
6.50 
7.50 </p>

<p>Training set compounds </p>

<p>Test set compounds </p>

<p>Experimental pIC 50 </p>

<p>7.50 </p>

<p>6.50 </p>

<p>5.50 </p>

<p>4.50 </p>

<p>Predicted pIC </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>3.50 
3.50 
4.50 
5.50 
6.50 
7.50 </p>

<p>Figure 4 Plot of experimental versus predicted pic 50 values of the training and test sets of the tricyclic phthalimide HIV-1 integrase inhibitors by comparative molecular field 
analysis (A) and hologram quantitative structure-activity relationship (B). 
Abbreviations: pic 50 , -log ic 50 ; ic 50 , half maximal inhibitory concentration; hiV, Human immunodeficiency virus. </p>

<p>A successful HQSAR model should provide important 
information about which molecular fragments are directly 
related to the biological activity, apart from predicting the 
activities of the untested molecules. Together, these data 
would be useful for designing new compounds with potent 
HIV-1 IN inhibitory activity. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Financial support from Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do 
Estado do Rio de Janeiro (FAPERJ), Conselho Nacional 
de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico (CNPq), and 
Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Supe-
rior (CAPES) was received for this study. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>Other than the funding received for this study outlined in the 
Acknowledgments section, the authors declare no conflicts 
of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/drug-design-development-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy is an international, peer-
reviewed open-access journal that spans the spectrum of drug design 
and development through to clinical applications. Clinical outcomes, 
patient safety, and programs for the development and effective, safe, 
and sustained use of medicines are a feature of the journal, which </p>

<p>has also been accepted for indexing on PubMed Central. The manu-
script management system is completely online and includes a very 
quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2013:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>