<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3085624" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:45+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: To investigate the efficacy of tazobactam/piperacillin (TAZ/PIPC) plus levo-
floxacin (LVFX) as a prophylactic administration in transrectal prostate biopsy (TPBX). 
Materials and Methods: We investigated 201 consecutive patients who underwent 
TPBX in one Japanese hospital during the period of 2009-2010. The patients received 
TAZ/PIPC 4.5 g i.v. once just before and 3 hours after TPBX, plus oral LVFX 300 mg 
or 500 mg daily for 3 days. We examined the infectious adverse events and laboratory 
data (serum white blood cell [WBC] count and C-reactive protein [CRP]) before and 1 
day after TPBX. 
Results: Only one patient (0.50%) in 201 cases had febrile complications after TPBX. 
Serum WBC and CRP did not rise significantly on the day after TPBX compared with 
before TPBX (p＞0.05). There was no significant difference in the rise of serum WBC 
and CRP before and after TPBX in the comparison of LVFX 500 mg with LVFX 300 
mg in the TAZ/PIPC plus LVFX regimen. 
Conclusions: TAZ/PIPC plus LVFX can be considered as a prophylactic regimen for pre-
venting infectious complications in TPBX. </p>

<p>Infectious adverse events after transrectal prostate biopsy 
(TPBX) have been increasing, and even septic and fatal cas-
es have been reported [1,2]. Fluoroquinolones have long 
been used for prophylactic administration owing to their 
good efficacy and high concentration in the prostate after 
dosing. However, especially in urinary tract infections 
(UTIs), fluoroquinolone-resistant Escherichia coli (FQRE) 
has been rapidly increasing. Resistance ratios to levo-
floxacin (LVFX) have jumped up to 5% to 20% [3]. Because 
TPBX is increasingly used to detect prostate cancer, ad-
verse events are a growing concern [2]. Intravenous anti-
biotics should be considered, partly for preventing septic 
cases as mentioned above. Another resistant strain, exten-
ded-spectrum beta-lactamase (ESBL)-producing E. coli, </p>

<p>also poses difficulties for treatment. Some kinds of carba-
penems are available for this resistant strain, but it has the 
potential to be an intractable infection. Some authors pre-
viously reported a case of prostatitis caused by ESBL-pro-
ducing E. coli and it could be treated by imipenem and tazo-
bactam/piperacillin (TAZ/PIPC) [4]. 
Beta-lactamase inhibitors have generally been combined 
with penicillins partly because this combination can bring 
out the antibiotic activity fully and prevent the emergence 
of antibiotic-resistant strains [5]. TAZ/PIPC (Zosin </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>) is an 
intravenous antibiotic agent consisting of 4 g of piperacillin 
and 0.5 g of tazobactam at an 8:1 ratio and is a modification 
of Tazosin </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, which was used before and consisted of 2 g of 
piperacillin and 0.5 g of tazobactam [5,6]. Penicillins com-
bined with beta-lactamase inhibitors such as TAZ/PIPC 
are widely used to treat UTIs and show good efficacy for E. </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2011;52:289-292 </p>



<p>Shigemura et al </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Patients </p>

<p>No. of patients 
Age (yr) (medium) 
Serum prostate-specific antigen (ng/ml) 
(medium) 
Prostate cancer 
Febrile complication </p>

<p>201 
54-91 (72) 
1.5-1,815 (8.21) </p>

<p>83/201 
1/201 </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Analysis of laboratory data in serum WBC and CRP </p>

<p>Before TPBX value 
After TPBX value (day 1) 
p-value </p>

<p>WBC (/mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) (n=201) 
CRP (μg/ml) (n=198 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>6,123±1,655 
0.1702±0.4020 </p>

<p>6,427±1,898 
0.2602±0.4534 </p>

<p>＞0.05 
＞0.05 </p>

<p>WBC: white blood cell, CRP: C-reactive protein, TPBX: transrectal prostate biopsy, </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>: three patients did not have a valuable data regard-
ing serum CRP </p>

<p>coli, including FQRE and ESBL-producing E. coli, and are 
recommended for TPBX in the Japanese UTI association 
guidelines especially in high risk group [7]. In this study, 
we examined whether TAZ/ PIPC plus LVFX could sup-
press infectious adverse events after TPBX. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>1. Prostate biopsy 
We performed a study of 201 consecutive men scheduled 
for TPBX because of an elevated prostate-specific antigen 
(PSA) level, an abnormal digital rectal examination (DRE), 
or abnormal magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) or trans-
rectal ultrasound (TRUS) findings. TPBXs were performed 
in Akashi Municipal Hospital from March 2009 to Septem-
ber 2010. All biopsies were performed with an 18-gauge 
Bard Max Core disposable biopsy instrument biopsy nee-
dle (C.R. Bard Inc., Convington, GA, USA) in conjunction 
with a medical ultrasound console (Aloka SSD-2000, Aloka 
Co. Ltd., Tokyo, Japan). Acetylsalicylic acid or oral anti-
coagulant agents were stopped appropriately before TPBX 
with the approval of the prescribing physician as a rule. We 
took 8 (sextant＋2 transitional zone) cores. No preparatory 
cleansing enemas were used, and the TPBX procedure was 
performed with only sacral anesthesia with 1% lidocaine 
and povidone iodine sterilization just before the TPBX. </p>

<p>2. Prophylactic antibiotic administration 
For prophylactic antibiotic medication, each patient re-
ceived TAZ/PIPC 4.5 g i.v. and LVFX 100 mg or 500 mg tak-
en orally 30 minutes before TPBX. Patients continued to 
take 100 mg after every meal or 500 mg LVFX once a day 
for 3 days with or without styptic or anti-plasmin. The dose 
of LVFX was changed to 500 mg from 300 mg per day from 
August 2009 in this study. Another TAZ/PIPC was given 
3 hours after TPBX. Patients were examined for infectious 
adverse events after TPBX and white blood cell (WBC) 
counts (/mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) and C-reactive protein (CRP) (μg/ml) in plas-
ma were measured before and 1 day after TPBX. 
All patients undergoing TPBX were hospitalized on the 
day of TPBX and were discharged the next day if there were 
no adverse events requiring further hospitalization. The 
day after TPBX, patients' laboratory data were checked in-
cluding WBC and CRP in serum. If a patient had symptoms 
from infectious complications such as chills or fever greater 
than 38.0 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C after TPBX, he was asked to return to the emer-
gency department. He immediately underwent a urinalysis, 
urine culture, and blood analysis, and any other complica-</p>

<p>tions were recorded. As a rule, if acute prostatitis was diag-
nosed, the patient was hospitalized and treated with the 
third-or fourth-generation cephalosporin or carbapenem 
i.v., and blood and urine culture tests were performed. </p>

<p>3. Statistical analyses 
Statistical analysis was performed by use of Student's 
t-test or Welch's t-test or Fisher's exact test with the <rs id="software-0" type="software">JSTAT 
-Java Virtual Machine Statistics Monitoring Tool</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Sun Microsystems Inc.</rs>., Santa Clara, CA, USA). Statistical sig-
nificance was set at p-value＜0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Patient data are shown in Table 1. One of 201 patients 
(0.50%) had a febrile complication such as acute prostatitis 
after TPBX. Our data from laboratory tests done the day 
after TPBX, including serum WBC count and CRP, did not 
demonstrate a significant rise in these variables compared 
with the pre-TPBX data as shown in Table 2 (p＞0.05). The 
serum WBC count before and after TPBX (day 1) was 6,123 
±1,655 and 6,427±1,898 (/mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>), respectively. Serum CRP 
before and after TPBX (day 1) was 0.1702±0.4020 and 
0.2602±0.4534 (μg/ml), respectively (Table 2). No patients 
showed obvious side effects from this regimen (TAZ/PIPC 
plus LVFX). 
A case with febrile complication had fever (37.6 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C) from 
the night of TPBX and his serum WBC and CRP rose up 
(18,100/mm 
3 and 4.1 μg/ml, respectively) on the next day. 
He had dysuria and was diagnosed as having acute pro-
statitis. He was treated by i.v. doripenem 0.5 g/day and his 
symptoms and laboratory data reacted very well and im-
proved. His urine culture test on the day after TPBX showed 
no growth of bacteria. His TPBX pathological result was 
prostate cancer. 
In addition, we compared LVFX 500 mg with LVFX 300 
mg in the TAZ/PIPC plus LVFX regimen; however, there 
were no significant differences between the two groups re-</p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2011;52:289-292 </p>

<p>Beta-Lactamase Inhibitor for Prostate Biopsy </p>



<p>TABLE 3. Comparison of change of serum WBC and CRP before and after TPBX between LVFX doses (300 mg and 500 mg) </p>

<p>WBC (/mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) (after TPBX-before TPBX) 
CRP (μg/ml) (after TPBX-before TPBX) </p>

<p>TAZ/PIPC plus LVFX 300 mg (n=61) 
172.1±1,690 
0.0295±0.6412 
p＞0.05 
p＞0.05 
TAZ/PIPC plus LVFX 500 mg (n=140) 
397.1±1,422 
0.0876±0.4057 </p>

<p>WBC: white blood cell, CRP: C-reactive protein, TPBX: transrectal prostate biopsy, LVFX: levofloxacin, TAZ/PIPC: tazobactam/piper-
acillin </p>

<p>garding the febrile complication rate (p＞0.05) or change 
in serum WBC and CRP before and after TPBX (Table 3). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Prostate biopsies can cause infectious adverse events, es-
pecially with the transrectal approach [8]. TPBX is a test 
for the detection of prostate cancer and most patients have 
cancer-negative results in general [9]; therefore, severe ad-
verse events must be prevented. Recently, the ratio of in-
fectious complications after TPBX has risen and even sep-
tic or fatal cases have been reported [1,2]. One of the main 
reasons for this unfortunate fact is the increase of anti-
biotic-resistant Enterobacteriaceae [10,11]. Naturally, E. 
coli is one of the main targets to suppress in this procedure, 
and infectious adverse events may be partly caused by anti-
biotic-resistant bacteria [1,4]. 
Fluoroquinolones are often used for prophylactic medi-
cation in TPBX, partly because they are retained at high 
concentrations in the prostate as mentioned above [12,13]; 
however, fluoroquinolone-resistant E. coli are spreading, 
especially in UTI [3]. A guideline for prophylactic antibiotic 
medication for TPBX in 2006 and 2007 recommends fluo-
roquinolones in low-risk groups and TAZ/PIPC in high-risk 
groups [7,14]. However, infectious complications and sep-
tic cases after TPBX increased after the publication of this 
guideline [15]. Our regimen was set for the following rea-
sons: 1) good efficacy of TAZ/PIPC for E. coli including be-
ta-lactamase-producing bacteria, 2) good intra-prostate 
concentrations and permeability of LVFX, 3) the data on 
TAZ/PIPC alone mentioned below, and 4) the higher resist-
ance ratio of E. coli to LVFX in our previous study (data not 
shown) than before [3], and 5) the higher ratio of ESBL-pro-
ducing E. coli among all E. coli isolated recently than before 
in our institution (data not shown). Guidelines need to be 
updated to reflect the current antibiotic susceptibilities of 
emergent bacterial strains [16]. As reported in the liter-
ature, the ratios of febrile infectious complications range 
from 0.51% to 7.27% [2,8,17], which suggests that our 
method could be one of the recommendations for this 
purpose. In addition, our previous method [LVFX plus ami-
noglycoside (isepamicin)] has shown good efficacy for this 
purpose [8]; however, partly because of the spread of re-
sistant strains, the previous method should be reconsid-
ered and revised by the current data. For instance, Kato et 
al reported a case of septic shock caused by fluoroquino-
lone-resistant E. coli after TPBX [15], and Carlson et al re-</p>

<p>ported multi-drug-resistant E. coli urosepsis cases includ-
ing a death case following TPBX [18]. In addition, Kim et 
al reported 923 cases of TPBX and concluded that almost 
cases of acute prostatitis (2.0%) were caused by fluoro-
quinolone-resistant E. coli [19]. This may suggest that the 
trend in infection and resistant strains could change and 
should be monitored and the guidelines revised if 
necessary. 
Regarding antibiotic-resistant E. coli, ESBL-producing 
E. coli have been reported as problematic to treat even in 
UTIs as mentioned above [20,21]. Lee et al reported the 
prevalence of ESBL-producing uropathogens in UTI pa-
tients, and the overall prevalence ratio was 12.6% in their 
3-year study [22]. This trend is apparently growing and 
raises some doubt as to whether we can decrease the dose 
of TAZ/PIPC or LVFX for future's study. Our laboratory da-
ta for serum WBC and CRP demonstrate that our regimen 
offers good efficacy for suppressing inflammation and in-
fectious adverse events after TPBX. Our ratio of infectious 
complications after TPBX was 0.50%, indicating its suit-
ability even for high-risk patients. Our next step will, as 
mentioned above, be to consider reducing the dose of TAZ/ 
PIPC and LVFX to once each on the day of TPBX (just before 
the procedure) for low-risk patients, while strictly monitor-
ing for resistant strains. 
Some authors report the efficacy of oral antibiotics for 
this purpose, but it might be necessary to combine intra-
venous antibiotics for suppression of septic cases. Because 
TPBX detects prostate cancer in only 20% to 30% of cases, 
and because most of these patients have organ-confined 
cancer that may not cause early death [8,23], serious com-
plications from the diagnostic procedure itself should be re-
garded as unacceptable as mentioned above. Our results 
of only one febrile complication in 201 consecutive cases and 
no influence on infection-related laboratory data (WBC 
and CRP) support an updated methodology for prophy-
lactic medication. 
Guidelines need to be updated regularly, because long 
repetition of a single recommendation may lead to wide-
spread emergence of resistant bacterial strains. In general, 
more than two different regimens should be offered. Our 
data definitely showed a lower infectious complication ra-
tio after TPBX, even though direct comparison could not 
be done because of the difference in core number, compared 
with the regimen of TAZ/PIPC alone (13.5 g per day, once 
daily) as used in Kobe University Hospital [7/180: 3.89% 
in 10 (sextant＋2 transitional zone＋2 far lateral periphe-</p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2011;52:289-292 </p>



<p>Shigemura et al </p>

<p>ral zone) cores; data not shown]. In addition, the data ana-
lyzed to observe an effect of LVFX dosing (300 mg or 500 
mg per day as shown in Table 3) suggested that our TAZ/ 
PIPC plus LVFX protocol was not affected by LVFX doses. 
In addition, the TPBX cases from Kobe University Hospital 
reported here included low-risk patients because the data 
were from consecutive TPBX cases. Moreover, our previous 
regimen and study [8] was performed from 2003 to 2008, 
and the high prevalence of ESBL-producing E. coli was re-
ported from the study done from 2007 to 2009 [22]. Taken 
together, these data suggest that our current regimen could 
be considered as one of the recommendations for not only 
high-risk patients but also non-high-risk patients. 
Even though we showed good efficacy, this study may have 
limitations and further comparison study with the same 
patient group, study period, and method may be required. 
This single-arm study was also performed to confirm not 
only the effect of this regimen but also the safety for patients 
without any severe side effects. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>TAZ/PIPC plus fluoroquinolones can be considered a valu-
able prophylactic regimen for preventing infectious com-
plications in TPBX. TAZ/PIPC plus fluoroquinolones is one 
of the options for prophylactic antimicrobial administra-
tion in TPBX, especially in high-risk groups. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Dr. Kunito Yamanaka for taking care of the pa-
tients and Gary Mawyer M.F.A. for English editing. </p>

<p>Conflicts of Interest 
The authors have nothing to disclose. </p>



</text></tei>