<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3881477" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. [Purpose] The aim of this study was to investigate the changes of baseball pitching velocity and elec-
tromechanical reaction times (EMG-RT) of the teres major of young amateur baseball players after neuromuscular 
joint facilitation (NJF) treatment. [Subjects] The subjects were 18 healthy males who were divided into two groups: 
a NJF group and a control group. The NJF group consisted of 10 subjects, and the control group consisted of 8 sub-
jects. [Methods] Participants in the NJF group received NJF treatment. The baseball pitching velocity, the EMG-RT, 
the premotor time (PMT), and the motor time (MT) during shoulder internal rotation movement were measured 
before and after 8 weeks of exercise. [Results] There were no significant differences among the results of the control 
group. In the NJF group, there were significant differences in baseball pitching velocity, EMG-RT and MT after 
NJF treatment. [Conclusion] NJF intervention shortens not only EMG-RT but also MT, which implies that NJF is 
effective for motor processes. Since the baseball pitching velocity increased, NJF may be recommended for the 
improvement of the performance of baseball players. 
Neuromuscular Joint Facilitation (NJF) is a new thera-
peutic exercise based on kinesiology. It integrates the facili-
tation element of proprioceptive neuromuscular facilitation 
and the joint composition movement, aiming to improve the 
movement of the joint through passive exercise, active exer-
cise and resistance exercise 1) . It is used to increase strength, 
flexibility and ROM, and shorten the electromechanical re-
action time (EMG-RT) 2, 3) . 
The EMG-RT is an index of the shrinkage characteristic 
of the muscle. The EMG-RT is composed of the premotor 
time (PMT) and the motor time (MT). The PMT is defined 
as the interval between the stimulation signal and the on-
set of voluntary electromyographic (EMG) activity of a re-
sponse agonist. The MT is defined as the interval between 
the onsets of voluntary EMG activity to the mechanical 
response 4) . The PMT reflects the movement position, the </p>

<p>movement pattern, the movement programming, and the 
state of consciousness, the level of alertness, and the time 
of the central process. The MT chiefly reflects factors at the 
periphery level, including muscle contraction, series elas-
ticity, and difficulties in loosening of connective tissue and 
the joint capsule 5) . 
According to a biomechanical analysis, an increase in 
the time maximizing shoulder horizontal adduction and a 
decrease in the time maximizing shoulder internal rotation 
are significantly related to increased ball velocity 6) . 
The aim of this study was to investigate the changes of 
baseball pitching velocity and electromechanical reaction 
times of the teres major of the young amateur baseball play-
ers after neuromuscular joint facilitation treatment. </p>

<p>SUBJECTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>The subjects were eighteen young amateur baseball play-
ers, who were divided into two groups: a NJF group and a 
control group. The NJF group consisted of 10 subjects, and 
the control group consisted of 8 subjects. Subject charac-
teristics are detailed in Table 1. They had played baseball 
for 9.1 ± 1.0 years. All subjects were screened before the 
start of the study using out a medical history questionnaire. 
The questionnaire addressed whether subjects had a history 
of cardiopulmonary, musculoskeletal, somatosensory, or </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. 
25: 1459-1461, 2013 </p>

<p>*Corresponding author. Ming Huo (e-mail: huoming8@ 
gmail.com) </p>

<p>©2013 The Society of Physical Therapy Science </p>

<p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms 
of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No 
Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License &lt;http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/&gt;. </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. Vol. 25, No. 11, 2013 </p>

<p>
neurological disorders. If so, they were excluded from the 
study. All subjects gave their informed consent to participa-
tion in the study. All experimental procedures in this study 
were reviewed and approved by the Ethical Review Com-
mittee of Jilin Dianli hospital. 
To measure the baseball pitching velocity, a pitch dis-
tance of 18.44 m between the batteries was used as stipu-
lated in the official baseball rules. The velocity of five balls, 
pitched into the strike zone as quickly as possible were mea-
sured, and the average value was used in the analysis. The 
pitching velocity was measured with used a sports radar 
gun, SR3600 (Dainatecc). 
We measured the EMG-RT of the teres major, the PMT 
of the teres major, and the MT of the teres major in response 
to an auditory stimulus. The EMG-RT was measured with 
a digital storage oscilloscope DCS-7040 (Kenwood). Af-
ter cleaning the skin with alcohol and abrasion paste, Ag/ 
AgCl disposable electrodes (Vitrode F, Nihonn Kohden) 
were placed over the muscle bellies of the teres major, with 
a 2-cm inter-electrode distance. The on-off signal was gen-
erated by the contact of an electrode attached to the dorsum 
manus with an aluminum board. At the onset of voluntary 
shoulder internal rotation, the electrode lost contact with 
the aluminum board, generating the off signal (Fig. 1). 
The subjects sat on a backless adjustable seat with the 
right upper limb fixed in a position of 90° of shoulder flex-
ion and 90° of elbow flexion. The subjects were given an 
oral warning of "Set", 2 to 3 seconds before the stimulus au-
ditory signal (2,500 Hz, 50 ms). The subjects were required 
to respond to the auditory cues by performing shoulder in-
ternal rotation as quickly as possible. 
The EMG waveform and the on-off signal of the foot 
switch were synchronized on the display of the oscillo-
scope. The latency time between the onset of voluntary 
EMG activity and the stimulus auditory signal (PMT), and 
the latency time between the onset of voluntary EMG activ-
ity and the off signal (MT) were measured by setting the 
image on the display to a standstill each time and moving 
the cursor. Prior to the experiment, the subjects were in-
formed about what would be done in the experiment and 
made several practice trials to accustom themselves to it. 
The reaction time was measured repeatedly five times at 
each scheduled measurement. 
The EMG-RT, the premotor time (PMT) and the motor 
time (MT) during shoulder internal rotation movement, and 
the baseball pitching velocity were measured before the in-
tervention, and after 8 weeks of the intervention. </p>

<p>Four shoulder patterns of NJF were used. The pat-
terns were shoulder extension-adduction-internal rotation, 
shoulder flexion-abduction-external rotation, shoulder ex-
tension-abduction-internal rotation, and shoulder flexion-
adduction-external rotation pattern. Each pattern was per-
formed three times at random as a passive exercise and as 
a resistance exercise, respectively. The subjects in the NJF 
group received the intervention three times a week for 8 
weeks. The intervention was performed by the same physi-
cal therapist to avoid individual variations in therapy. For 
the control group, the intervention was not performed. 
To determine whether there were differences between 
the NJF group and the control group, the independent t-
test was performed on subject characteristics. Two-way 
ANOVA and multiple comparisons (Bonferroni test) were 
used to test for statistically significant differences, and the 
factors were intervention and group. If a significant interac-
tion was found, the paired t-test was performed to compare 
before and after the intervention. Data were analyzed using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> Ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">17.0</rs> for Windows. The level of statistical signifi-
cance was chosen as 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>There were no significant differences between the sub-
ject characteristics of the NJF group and the control group. 
Table 2 shows the results for the baseball pitching veloc-
ity. There were no significant differences among the results 
of the control group. In the NJF group, there were signifi-
cant differences in baseball pitching velocity between be-
fore and after the 8 weeks of NJF training. 
Table 3 shows the results for the reaction time. Two-way </p>

<p>Table 1. Subject characteristics </p>

<p>NJF a 
(n=10) </p>

<p>Control b 
(n=8) </p>

<p>Sum total 
(n=18) </p>

<p>Age (y) 
19.5 ± 1.2 
18.6 ± 0.9 
19.1 ± 1.1 
Height (cm) 
173.8 ± 2.8 
174.9 ± 3.0 
174.3 ± 3.0 
Weight (kg) 
68.8 ± 7.1 
66.5 ± 7.0 
67.8 ± 6.9 </p>

<p>Values are mean ± SD. No significant differences between groups 
at the 0.05 alpha level. 
a : NJF group: neuromuscular joint facilitation group, b : Control: 
control group </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Schema of electromyographic reac-
tion time </p>

<p>Upper trace: electromyographic 
waveform. 
Lower trace: on-off signal of the 
foot switch. 
Vertical line shows the auditory 
stimulus signal. 
PMT: premotor time; MT: motor 
time; RT: reaction time. RT = 
PMT + MT </p>



<p>analyses of variance showed there was a significant interac-
tion of group, indicating that the change in RT was different 
between the groups. There were no significant differences 
among the results of the control group. In the NJF group, 
there were significant differences in EMG-RT and MT be-
tween before and after the 8-week intervention. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This study investigated the effects of a neuromuscular 
joint facilitation treatment on EMG-RT. The subjects of the 
NJF group showed not only shortened EMG-RT, but also 
shortened MT in the teres major. MT was shortened after 
the intervention, suggesting that the contractile character-
istic of the muscle was changed by the NJF intervention. 
MT is influenced by the muscle tone before a movement 
appears 7) , and the shortening of MT has been suggested to 
be the result of an increase in muscular tension induced by 
changes in the mechanical properties of the muscle tissue 8) . 
NJF uses a diagonal spiral pattern, which is similar to the 
pitching movement. Moreover, as the EMG-RT shortened, 
the internal rotation speed of the shoulder joint improved 
in the pitching motion, and the pitching velocity was in-
creased. Therefore NJF may be recommended for improve-
ment of the performance of baseball players. </p>



<p>Table 2. Comparison of before and after intervention 
values of baseball pitching velocity (km/h) </p>

<p>before 
after </p>

<p>NJF a 
101.9 ± 6.6 
106.4 ± 8.1** 
Control b 
102.1 ± 7.0 
102.3 ± 7.3 </p>

<p>Values are mean ± SD, Comparison with before inter-
vention: **: p&lt;0.01. 
a : NJF group: neuromuscular joint facilitation group, b : 
Control: control group </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparison of before and after intervention values of 
reaction time (msec) </p>

<p>before 
after </p>

<p>NJF a </p>

<p>PMT c 
111.6 ± 22.9 
107.7 ± 15.4 
MT d 
52.8 ± 7.1 
42.0 ± 6.3** 
RT e 
164.4 ± 19.6 
149.7 ± 10.3* </p>

<p>Control b </p>

<p>PMT 
115.7 ± 24.4 
113.0 ± 14.6 
MT 
53.6 ± 7.8 
52.4 ± 5.2 
RT 
169.3 ± 20.9 
165.5 ± 15.7 </p>

<p>Values are mean ± SD, Comparison with before intervention: *: 
p&lt;0.05; **: p&lt;0.01. 
a : NJF group: neuromuscular joint facilitation group, b : Control: 
control group, c :PMT: premotor time, d : MT: motor time, e : RT: 
electromechanical reaction time; RT = PMT + MT. </p>

</text></tei>