<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3909089" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Soil salinity is one of the most severe abiotic stresses for crops 
worldwide, affecting several million hectares of agricultural 
land. 
1 Therefore, characterization of Na 
+ transport and its dis-
tribution in plants has been a prime area of research for decades. 
High concentration of sodium ion (Na 
+ ) is toxic to plants pri-
marily due to its adverse effects on cellular metabolism and ion 
homeostasis. 
2,3 Therefore, maintenance of low level of Na 
+ in 
cells is essential for plants. 
3,4 Plants remove Na 
+ from the cyto-
plasm by using vacuolar and plasma membrane localized Na 
+ / 
H 
+ transporters. 
4,5 Na 
+ /H 
+ transporters are membranous proteins 
that transport protons (H 
+ ) across the membrane in exchange for 
Na 
+ . 
6,7 This exchange activity requires H 
+ electrochemical gradi-
ent across the membrane which is generated by the H 
+ pumps 
such as H 
+ -ATPase present on plasma membrane or vacuole and 
H 
+ -pyrophosphatase. 
5 In plants, the exchange activity of the 
plant vacuolar Na 
+ /H 
+ transporters has been well studied. 
5,8,9 In 
addition, enhanced salinity tolerance has been reported by over-
expression of a vacuolar Na 
+ /H 
+ antiporter in Arabidopsis. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>In plants, three salt overly sensitive genes (SOS1, SOS2 and 
SOS3) have been found to function in a common pathway that 
contributes to salt tolerance. 
11-14 SOS1 gene encodes a membrane </p>

<p>The diurnal rhythm controls many aspects of plant physiology such as flowering, photosynthesis and growth. Rice is one 
of the staple foods for world's population. Abiotic stresses such as salinity, drought, heat and cold severely affect rice 
production. Under salinity stress, maintenance of ion homeostasis is a major challenge, which also defines the tolerance 
level of a given genotype. Salt overly sensitive (SOS) pathway is well documented to play a key role in maintaining the Na </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>homeostasis in plant cell. However, it is not reported yet whether the transcriptional regulation of genes of this pathway 
are influenced by diurnal rhythm. In the present work, we have studied the diurnal pattern of transcript of SOS pathway 
genes in rice at seedling stage. To rule out the effect of temperature fluctuations on the expression patterns of these 
genes, the seedlings were grown under constant temperature. We found that OsSOS3 and OsSOS2 exhibited a rhythmic 
and diurnal expression pattern, while OsSOS1 did not have any specific pattern of expression. This analysis establishes a 
cross-link between diurnal rhythm and SOS pathway and suggests that SOS pathway is influenced by diurnal rhythm in 
rice. </p>

<p>Salt overly sensitive pathway members are 
influenced by diurnal rhythm in rice </p>

<p>Praveen Soni, 
1, † Gautam Kumar, 
1, † Neelam Soda, 
1 Sneh L. Singla-Pareek 
2 and Ashwani Pareek </p>

<p>1, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Stress Physiology and Molecular Biology Laboratory; School of Life Sciences; Jawaharlal Nehru University; New Delhi, India; 
2 Plant Molecular Biology; International Centre for 
Genetic Engineering and Biotechnology; New Delhi, India </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>These authors contributed equally to this work. </p>

<p>Keywords: diurnal rhythm, Oryza sativa, salinity, SOS, salt tolerance </p>

<p>Abbreviations: d, days; LD, light/dark cycles; h, hours; min, minutes </p>

<p>protein containing 12 putative trans-membrane domains and a 
long hydrophilic tail at the C-terminal end. 
15 SOS1 transports 
sodium ions across the plasma membrane. Expression of SOS1 
gene is induced significantly in roots and to a much lesser extent 
in shoots in seedlings by exposure to high levels of NaCl. 
15 SOS2 
is a Ser/Thr protein kinase, which contains an auto-inhibitory 
domain. 
16 SOS3 is a Ca 
2+ binding protein with strong similar-
ity with the regulatory β subunit of the protein phosphatase cal-
cineurin and with related proteins of the neuronal Ca 
2+ sensor 
family. 
13 Hence, it has been hypothesized that SOS3 perceives 
the Ca 
2+ transients elicited by salt stress and activates SOS2 by 
relieving auto-inhibition. 
16 These SOS pathway genes are later 
grouped into large protein families of calcineurin B-like pro-
teins (CBL) and CBL-interacting protein kinases (CIPK), there-
fore SOS2 and SOS3 are also known as CIPK24 and CBL4, 
respectively. 
17 Furthermore, the orthologous-OsSOS1, OsSOS2 
(OsCIPK24) and OsSOS3 (OsCBL4) have also been isolated from 
rice and it has been demonstrated that all OsSOS proteins could 
coordinately function with AtSOS proteins and nicely comple-
mented mutations in the corresponding sos mutant of Arabidopsis 
plants. 
18 Recent work from our lab has also reported various SOS 
orthologs from Brassica species involved in maintenance of Na </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>©2013 Landes Bioscience. Do not distribute. </p>

<p>e24738-2 </p>

<p>Plant Signaling &amp; Behavior 
Volume 8 Issue 7 </p>

<p>with time but do not show a clear rhythmicity. Its expression level 
drops before dawn (Fig. 1D). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The biological clock is an endogenous timing mechanism pres-
ent in almost all organisms examined to date. This time-keeping 
mechanism is able to generate 24 h rhythms in a wide variety 
of biological processes. Regulation of cellular ion homeostasis 
during stresses is critical for plant survival. One of the responses 
of plant cell to stresses is the generation of a cytosolic Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>transient and the subsequent activation of Ca 
2+ sensor protein 
expression and/or activity. 
32 The components (SOS1, SOS2 
and SOS3) of SOS pathway transduce a salt stress induced Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>signal to reinstate cellular ion homeostasis. 
33 Although, these 
three members (proteins) coordinate in sequential manner but 
do not show diurnal co-expression as OsSOS3 and OsSOS2 have 
expression peaks at different times of 24 h cycle; during night 
and dusk transition respectively, while OsSOS1 does not have a 
clear rhythmicity. It has been reported that changes in mRNA 
levels may not be correlated with changes in protein or enzyme 
activity levels. 
34 It has also been suggested that the clock-regu-
lated proteins in rice are modulated at not only transcriptional 
but also at post-transcriptional and/or post-translational lev-
els. 
26 Whether SOS2 and SOS3 show diurnal rhythm at protein 
level and whether specific activities of these proteins also oscil-
late during the 24 h day-night cycle, these are the important 
questions to be answered. Nevertheless, expression profiles do 
provide a useful starting point for more in depth analyses. For 
instance, in the present study, SOS2 and SOS3 represent good 
candidates to study the relationship between salinity stress and 
diurnal rhythm. Plants are always changing and adapting to 
their changing environments. Thus, experimental changes are 
always being observed in a background of uncertain variation. 
Although clocks are temperature compensated, which means 
that overall clock period is constant over a range of tempera-
tures and temperature changes can act to entrain or reset the 
clock patterns. 
It has also been shown in Brassica juncea that BjSOS3 mRNA 
is downregulated in presence of calcium chelator EGTA. 
35 It 
indicates that Ca 
2+ has a dual role as signaling agent, control-
ling the expression of SOS pathway genes at transcript level and 
initiating signaling at protein level. Diurnal oscillations of cyto-
solic and chloroplastic Ca 
2+ have been reported in A. thaliana 
and Nicotiana plumbaginifolia. 
36 The relationship between this 
diurnally regulated Ca 
2+ and SOS genes is still unexplored. The 
purpose of the diurnal oscillations of Ca 
2+ is not known but it 
has been reportedly involved in regulating numerous signaling 
events. 
37 Calcium is suggested to be a part of the light signal 
transduction chain regulating the rhythm as well as gene expres-
sion. 
37 These reports are in support to our study, as we are also 
reporting a diurnal expression pattern of genes of SOS pathway 
which is related to Ca 
2+ signaling. 
As, the expression of SOS pathway genes and Ca 
2+ ion level 
show rhythmic oscillation, it would be interesting to study 
whether the diurnal changes in Ca 
2+ signatures mediate cross-talk </p>

<p>homeostasis in Brassica. 
19 Together, these results suggested that 
the SOS-like salinity tolerance mechanism is conserved in plants. 
Plant diurnal oscillation is a 24 h period cycle. Genes of mul-
tiple pathways have been implicated in stress responses and regu-
lated by diurnal rhythm. 
20-24 Time course transcriptome analysis 
has revealed that genes involved in several biological pathways 
like lipid and carbohydrate metabolic processes, photosynthe-
sis, nucleotide binding, translation, amino acid and nucleotide 
metabolism, nitrogen metabolism and hormone biosynthesis, 
etc., show rhythmicity. </p>

<p>25-28 </p>

<p>Rice, a salt sensitive crop, is the staple food for about half 
of the world's population. Hence, in order to improve salinity 
tolerance in this crop plant, it is imperative to develop a "thor-
ough understanding" of the complex molecular mechanisms and 
gene regulatory networks operative under stress conditions. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Recently, proteomics approach has revealed that a set of 91 pro-
teins, involved in diverse processes including stress response, is 
controlled by diurnal cycles in developing endosperm of rice. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>However, there is still no report about the diurnal transcriptional 
regulation of salt stress related genes like SOS1, SOS2 and SOS3. 
Rice has been reported to be most sensitive to salinity stress at 
seedling stage. 
29,30 The aim of the present study was to see if the 
expression of SOS pathway members is influenced by the diurnal 
rhythm in seedlings of rice. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>OsSOS3 and OsSOS2 show diurnal rhythmicity. The diurnal 
expression profiles of OsSOS genes were observed under entrain-
ing conditions of 12 h light/12 h dark (LD) with a constant tem-
perature 28 ± 2°C during day and night in IR-64 genotype of 
rice at seedling stage. OsTOC1 has been reported to be expressed 
rhythmically during 12 h light and 12 h dark cycle in rice. 
31 Level 
of mRNA of OsTOC1 oscillates with light-dark cycles and shows 
peak in the late day (Fig. 1A). Changes in OsTOC1 levels coin-
cide with dusk transition as reported earlier. 
31 OsTOC1 expresses 
with a period of about 24 h and an evening specific phase. This 
result is consistent with the prior published reports, which in 
turn validates the experimental conditions used by us. 
The nucleotide sequences of the cDNA clones used for probe 
preparation were taken as query in BLASTN search in Rice 
Genome Annotation Project Database (http://rice.plantbiology. 
msu.edu/) which revealed that regions of clones used for probe 
preparation were specific to the corresponding genes, thus giv-
ing a clear signal on northern blots. In case of OsSOS genes, we 
found that OsSOS2 and OsSOS3 were expressed in diurnal man-
ner. Diurnal rhythms of these two genes have a characteristic 
waveform, described by peaks and troughs. OsSOS3, with a phase 
of 24 h show higher expression level during night. Its expression 
shoots up in night and goes down during day, creating rhythmic-
ity (Fig. 1B). Similarly, the transcript of OsSOS2 also shows a 
clear oscillation profile. MRNA levels of OsSOS2 cycles in light-
dark periods, showing higher expression around the transition 
period of light to dark with a period of 24 h (Fig. 1C). The ampli-
tude of OsSOS2 diurnal expression was higher in comparison to 
that of OsSOS3. mRNA level of OsSOS1 transcript fluctuates </p>

<p>©2013 Landes Bioscience. Do not distribute. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>Plant Signaling &amp; Behavior 
e24738-3 </p>

<p>profiles in sos1, sos2 and sos3 mutants implicating this as transcrip-
tional output requiring all components of the SOS pathway. </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>Expression of CCR1 as well as its homolog CCR2 is regulated by 
diurnal rhythm. </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Not only downstream genes of SOS pathway, but also the 
interacting partners of SOS pathway show the diurnal rhythm. 
It has been reported that SOS2 interacts with catalase 2 (CAT2) 
and catalase 3 (CAT3) connecting SOS2 to H 2 O 2 metabolism 
and signaling. Expression of CAT2 is under circadian control, 
with the highest expression during the light period, consistent 
with a primary role in detoxifying H 2 O 2 derived from photo-
synthesis or photorespiration. 
41 Interestingly, CAT3 is also cir-
cadian regulated, but in the opposite manner as CAT2. CAT3 </p>

<p>between diurnal rhythm of SOS pathway genes and salinity 
stress tolerance. In Arabidopsis, elimination of SOS1 leads to the 
changes in expression of genes related to circadian rhythm. 
38 It 
suggests that though SOS1 does not show any diurnal rhythm 
but it regulates diurnal rhythm of several other genes. It also indi-
cates toward unknown and unexplored connection between SOS 
pathway and circadian clock. 
It is also interesting to find out whether the activities of down-
stream components of SOS2-SOS3 complex oscillates and coin-
cides with diurnally regulated SOS2 and SOS3 transcripts. One 
of the downstream components, regulated by this complex is 
CCR1 (cold-circadian rhythm-RNA binding1) which encodes 
a Gly-rich RNA-binding protein. CCR1 has similar expression </p>

<p>Figure 1. RNA gel blot analyses showing diurnal rhythm of OsSOS genes in shoots of IR64 rice seedlings. Seedlings were grown under the 12 h 
light/12 h dark cycle for 14 d. Shoot samples were harvested at 3 h intervals for 2.5 d under the 12 h light/12 h dark. Twenty μg RNA samples was used 
for northern blot hybridization. Ethidium bromide (EtBr) stained RNA-gel has been shown as the loading control. Y-axis shows relative transcript 
abundance of genes while numbers on X-axis shows different time points. Shaded area indicates dark period and white area indicates light period. 
(A) OsTOC1 shows rhythmic expression and has a peak during light to dark transition. (B) OsSOS3 expression peaks during night. (C) mRNA level of 
OsSOS2 show rhythmicity in 24 h cycles and show higher expression during the transition period of light to dark. (D) Transcript level of OsSOS1 doesn't 
show any clear rhythmicity. </p>

<p>©2013 Landes Bioscience. Do not distribute. </p>

<p>e24738-4 </p>

<p>Plant Signaling &amp; Behavior 
Volume 8 Issue 7 </p>

<p>RNA extraction and northern blot analysis. Total RNA was 
extracted from tissue using TRIzol method as per the manufac-
turer's instructions (T9424; Sigma-Aldrich). Northern blots were 
prepared using 20 μg total RNA. Appropriate probes [partial 
for OsSOS1(AK065608) corresponding to its N-terminal part 
and full length for other genes; OsSOS2 (AK102270); OsSOS3 
(AK101368); OsTOC1 (AK111828)] were amplified using the 
primers listed in Table 1 and radiolabeled using the DecaLabel™ 
DNA labeling kit, (K0621; Fermentas). To avoid any error due to 
unequal loading of RNA samples, same blot was re-probed each 
time with different gene probes after washing. Northern blots 
were hybridized at 65°C in 5 × SSC, 5 × Denhardt's reagent, 
0.1% SDS and 100 μg/ml denatured salmon sperm DNA for 
16-18 h. Membrane was washed twice in 0.5 × SSC, 0.1% SDS 
and 0.1 × SSC, 0.1% SDS for 15 min each at 65°C and scanned 
on phosphorimager using the software <rs type="software">Fujifilm Image Reader</rs>. 
The relative transcript abundance was calculated using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">Image 
Gauge</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Fuji Photofilm Co. Ltd.</rs>.). </p>

<p>Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest were disclosed. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>A.P. acknowledges financial support received from the 
Department of Biotechnology, Government of India and inter-
nal grants of JNU. P.S. and N.S. would like to acknowledge the 
receipt of Senior Research Fellowship award by CSIR and UGC 
(India) respectively. </p>

<p>expression is highest in the dark period. 
41 Circadian oscillation of 
interacting members and downstream components of SOS path-
way revalidate our results. 
Our data demonstrates that OsSOS3, OsSOS2 genes show 
rhythmic expression profile under diurnal condition at the tran-
scription level. This study also strongly establishes a possible 
molecular link of diurnal rhythm with SOS pathway. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Plant materials and growth conditions. Seeds of Oryza sativa 
L. cv "IR-64" were germinated in half Yoshida medium under 
hydroponic system for 48 h in dark and then grown for 14 d 
under control conditions (28 ± 2°C, 12 h light and 12 h dark 
cycle) in plant growth room. 
42 Shoot samples were harvested for 
2.5 d at an interval of 3 h starting from the dawn of 15 d. </p>

<p>Table 1. List of primers used in the present study </p>

<p>OsTOC1 forward primer 
5'-CGG AAT TCA TGG TGG GCG 
CCG GCG AG-3' </p>

<p>OsTOC1 reverse primer 
5'-ACG CGT CGA CCT ACT CTG GAG 
AAG AAA CCA TC-3' </p>

<p>OsSOS1 forward primer 
5'-ATG TGA CTG GAA GGG TTT GC-3' </p>

<p>OsSOS1 reverse primer 
5'-TCT AGC CTC CTC TCC CTC AG-3' </p>

<p>OsSOS2 forward primer 
5'-ATG GGA GGG GAG GAG GGA ATG-3' </p>

<p>OsSOS2 reverse primer 
5'-CTA GCA TGT GGC TGT CCT CAG-3' </p>

<p>OsSOS3 reverse primer 
5'-TCA GTC ATG GGC TTC TGA ATG-3' </p>



<p>©2013 Landes Bioscience. Do not distribute. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>Plant Signaling &amp; Behavior 
e24738-5 </p>



<p>©2013 Landes Bioscience. Do not distribute. </p>

</text></tei>