<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3040438" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: The aim of the present study was to determine the effect-site concentration of remifentanil needed to </p>

<p>prevent haemodynamic instability during tracheal intubation with inhaled desflurane induction. </p>

<p>Methods: One hundred American Society of Anesthesiologists I and II female patients were randomized to receive </p>

<p>an effect-site concentration of remifentanil of 0, 1, 2, 3, or 4 ng/ml. Induction of anaesthesia was started with </p>

<p>intravenous injection of propofol 2 mg/kg. Ninety seconds after the completion of propofol injection, rocuronium (0.8 </p>

<p>mg/kg) and remifentanil were administered simultaneously with 3% desflurane inhalation. Tracheal intubation was </p>

<p>attempted 150 sec after the commencement of remifentanil administration. </p>

<p>Results: A probit model of remifentanil concentration was predictive of successful intubation without development </p>

<p>of hypertension (P for goodness-of-fit = 0.419). The effect-site concentration of remifentanil needed to achieve </p>

<p>successful intubation without development of hypertension in 95% of the patients was 3.3 ng/ml (95% confidence </p>

<p>interval, 2.6-4.8 ng/ml). </p>

<p>Conclusions: The effect-site concentration of remifentanil of 3.3 ng/ml is effective in blunting the haemodynamic </p>

<p>response in 95% of the patients when 2.0 mg/kg of propofol induction was followed by 3% desflurane inhalation. </p>

<p>(Korean J Anesthesiol 2011; 60: 8-11) </p>

<p>Autonomic responses to laryngoscopy and tracheal intubation 
might be minimized by a combination of hypnotic and 
analgesic drugs during induction. Opioids are normally used 
for analgesia, and hypnosis is usually induced with intravenous 
anaesthetics such as propofol or thiopental sodium. 
With increasing popularity of total intravenous anaesthesia, 
various studies have reported the optimal dose of remifentanil 
for reduction of the haemodynamic responses to tracheal 
intubation with propofol [1-5]. Nevertheless, inhalation 
anaesthesia is frequently used in clinical practice, but few data 
have been reported on the optimal dose of remifentanil with 
inhalation anaesthetics during intubation [6]. 
This study was designed to determine the effect-site 
concentration (EC) of remifentanil for preventing development 
of hypertension during tracheal intubation with inhaled 
desflurane induction. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>After hospital Ethics Committee approval and patients informed 
consent, American Society of Anesthesiologists physical status 
I and II female patients (n = 100) between the age 18 to 60 years 
who were scheduled for elective surgery were enrolled in this 
study. The five groups were similar with respect to age, weight, 
and height (Table 1). 
Exclusion criteria included a history of hypertension, cardiac, 
pulmo nary, hepatic, or renal disease. Patients with systolic 
blood pressure (SBP) higher than 140 mmHg or diastolic blood 
pressure higher than 90 mmHg at pre-induction were also 
excluded. 
Heart rate, pulse-oximetry, capnography, and end-tidal 
desflurane concentration were monitored continuously. 
Noninvasive blood pressure was measured at a 1-min interval 
during the study period. Patients were randomly allocated 
to receive an infusion of remifentanil which was designed 
to achieve and maintain a predicted target EC of 0, 1, 2, 3, or 
4 ng/ml. Remifentanil was infused with a target-controlled 
infusion system (Orchestra </p>

<p>Ⓡ </p>

<p>, Fresenius Vial, Brezims, France) 
using the Minto's model. After preoxygenation, 3 ml of 1% 
lidocaine was injected to reduce the pain associated with IV </p>

<p>administration of propofol. Then, propofol 2 mg/kg was infused. 
Ninety seconds after the completion of propofol injection and 
confirmation of loss of consciousness, rocuronium (0.8 mg/kg) 
and remifentanil were administered simultaneously with 3% 
desflurane inhalation. Intubation was attempted 150 sec after 
the commencement of remifentanil administration. 
Heart rate and blood pressure were recorded at pre-induction, 
after the propofol injection, immediately before and after intu-
bation, and at 1 and 2 minutes after intubation. Any incidences 
of hypotension were recorded. Hypotension was defined as SBP 
that did not exceed 80 mmHg, or mean arterial blood pressure 
equal to or less than 55 mmHg. Hypotension was treated with 
an intravenous bolus of ephedrine 5 mg unless immediate 
intubation was anticipated. Any incidences of hypertension 
were also recorded, and this was defined as SBP higher than 
120% of the pre-induction baseline values. 
Data are presented as mean ± SD or number of patients. In 
the Cochran-Armitage test for trend in proportions, a sample 
size of 19 patients per group was required from the five groups 
with remifentanil dose corresponding to EC of 0, 1, 2, 3, and 
4 ng/ml, and the proportion of successful intubation without 
development of hypertension was equal to 0.50, 0.60, 0.70, 0.80, 
and 0.90 respectively. A total sample size of 95 patients was 
required to achieve an 86% power to detect a linear trend using 
a two-sided Z test with continuity correction and a significance 
level of 0.05 (version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">8.0.05</rs>, <rs id="software-1" type="software">PASS</rs> </p>

<p>Ⓡ </p>

<p>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">NCSS</rs>, Kaysville, UT, USA) [7]. 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> (version <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">13.0</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA) was used 
for statistical analysis, and a P value of 0.05 was considered as 
statistically significant. Goodness-of-fit tests were considered 
to be passed when P value was ≥ 0.05. Patient characteristics 
between the five groups were compared using analysis of 
covariance (ANCOVA). A probit analysis was used to calculate 
the EC of remifentanil required to achieve intubation without 
developing hypertension in 95% of patients. Repeated measures 
of the haemodynamic value were analyzed using repeated 
measured analysis of variance with Bonferroni adjustment for 
multiple comparisons when appropriate. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>In all the five groups, SBP was significantly decreased prior 
to intubation, with no significant difference in SBP between </p>

<p>Table 1. Patient Characteristics </p>

<p>Effect-site 
concentration (ng/ml) </p>

<p>0 
(n = 20) </p>

<p>1 
(n = 20) </p>

<p>2 
(n = 20) </p>

<p>3 
(n = 20) </p>

<p>4 
(n = 20) </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
Height (cm) 
Weight (kg) </p>

<p>37.8 ± 7.2 
158.7 ± 5.6 
56.1 ± 6.6 </p>

<p>36.9 ± 6.9 
156.5 ± 4.2 
54.0 ± 7.3 </p>

<p>37.7 ± 7.5 
159.6 ± 5.3 
60.1 ± 9.2 </p>

<p>39.3 ± 9.0 
160.7 ± 4.6 
57.2 ± 5.9 </p>

<p>39.2 ± 8.0 
159.2 ± 5.2 
56.9 ± 7.4 </p>

<p>Data represent mean ± SD. No statistical differences were found between the five groups. </p>



<p>www.ekja.org </p>

<p>Remifentanil for preventing hypertension 
Vol. 60, No. 1, January 2011 </p>

<p>the groups (P &lt; 0.001, Fig. 1). Compared to the baseline, SBP 
was significantly increased by laryngoscopic stimulation in the 
groups with an EC of remifentanil of 0 or 1 ng/ml (P &lt; 0.05, Fig. 1). 
After tracheal intubation, SBP was significantly lower in the 
patient group with an EC of remifentanil of 3 ng/ml than that in 
the patient groups who had received an EC of remifentanil of 0, 
1, or 2 ng/ml (P &lt; 0.05, Fig. 1); whereas, there was no difference 
in SBP between the groups with an EC of remifentanil of 3 and 4 
ng/ml. 
A probit model of remifentanil concentration was predictive 
of successful intubation without development of hypertension 
(P for goodness-of-fit = 0.419). An EC of remifentanil needed 
to achieve successful intubation without development of 
hypertension in 95% of the patients was 3.3 ng/ml (95% 
confidence interval [CI], 2.6-4.8 ng/ml, Fig. 2). A probit 
model with remifentanil concentration for development 
of hypotension during induction was also predictive (P 
for goodness-of-fit = 0.648). However, the remifentanil </p>

<p>concentration for provoking hypotension in 50 or 90% of 
the patients could not be estimated because the observed 
probability was too low (Table 2). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The aim of this study was to determine the optimal EC of 
remifentanil for achievement of successful intubation without 
development of hypertension during inhaled desflurane 
induction. 
It has been reported that the EC 95 of remifentanil for smooth 
intubation without muscle relaxants during inhaled desflurane 
induction is 8.0 ng/ml (95% CI, 5.0-14.3 ng/ml) [6], which 
is higher than the EC of remifentanil of 3.3 ng/ml needed 
to achieve successful intubation in 95% of the patients 
without development of hypertension in the present study. 
This discrepancy could be due to the differences in study 
design, such as use of muscle relaxants or due to the different 
definitions of successful intubations. Even though we used a 
lower concentration of desflurane compared to that used in 
the previous study, we think that the muscle relaxant probably 
reduced the effective remifentanil concentration in this study. 
With regards to the drug regimen, we used steady-state 
infusion of remifentanil during the study period in all the </p>

<p>Table 2. A Probit Model of Remifentanil Concentration for Development of Hypotension </p>

<p>Effect-site concentration (ng/ml) 
0 (n = 20) 
1 (n = 20) 
2 (n = 20) 
3 (n = 20) 
4 (n = 20) </p>

<p>Observed responses (n) 
Expected probability 
Ephedrine requirement (n) </p>

<p>3 
0.14 
1 </p>

<p>3 
0.17 
1 </p>

<p>5 
0.21 
0 </p>

<p>3 
0.24 
2 </p>

<p>7 
0.29 
1 </p>

<p>P for goodness-of-fit = 0.648. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Systolic blood pressure (SBP) changes in the five groups. Error 
bars represent the 95% confidence interval. In all the five groups 
of patients, SBP was significantly decreased prior to intubation, 
with no significant difference in SBP between the five groups. SBP 
was significantly increased after tracheal intubation compared to 
the baseline value in the groups EC0 and EC1. SBP after tracheal 
intubation was significantly lower in group EC3 than SBP in the 
groups EC0, 1 and 2 (P &lt; 0.05). SBP after tracheal intubation was 
significantly lower in group EC4 than that in group EC0. EC0: 
remifentanil 0 ng/ml, EC1: remifentanil 1 ng/ml, EC2: remifentanil 
2 ng/ml, EC3: remifentanil 3 ng/ml, EC4: remifentanil 4 ng/ml, *P &lt; 
0.05 compared with baseline values. 
 † P &lt; 0.05 compared with group 
EC3. </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 compared with group EC4. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Effect-site concentration and response curve of remifentanil 
from the probit analysis. The effect-site concentration of remifentanil 
for successful intubation without development of hypertension 
in 95% of the patients was 3.3 ng/ml (95% CI: 2.6-4.8 ng/ml). EC: 
effect-site concentration. </p>

<p> 
www.ekja.org </p>

<p>Korean J Anesthesiol 
Kim, et al. </p>

<p>patients, in order to avoid fluctuations in drug concentrations. 
There have been many studies in which a bolus injection of 
remifentanil has been used [4,8,9], but this could result in 
haemodynamic instability. Continuous infusions, and not bolus 
doses of opiates have been proven to provide a better quality of 
anesthesia [10]. 
Hypotension occurred more frequently at a higher remi-
fentanil concentration. However, the incidence of hypotension 
was estimated to be around 25% with EC 95 of remifentanil (3.3 
ng/ml), and less than 30% even at the highest remifentanil 
concentration (EC of 4 ng/ml). We could have used a higher 
remifentanil concentration if we wanted to use an EC of remi-
fentanil that could provoke hypotension in 50 or 95% of the 
patients; however, we chose a clinically relevant concentration 
that could also reveal the possible difference in SBP between the 
five groups during the transition period between the admini-
stration of propofol and the inhaled anaesthetic induction. 
Desflurane is an inhalational anaesthetic with a low solubility. 
Its low solubility allows for rapid induction and emergence from 
anaesthesia. These favorable pharmacokinetic characteristics 
are useful in ambulatory surgery because of the shorter post-
anaesthetic recovery time. However, neurocirculatory activation 
with tachycardia and hypertension during rapid increase in the 
inspired desflurane concentration prevents its widespread use, 
particularly in the patients with hypertension or ischemic heart 
disease [11,12]. 
These unfavorable responses to desflurane have been 
effectively blunted with a bolus of alfentanil [13] and have been 
partially reduced with fentanyl [14]. Remifentanil, a derivative 
of fentanyl, is a rapid onset, ultra-short acting agonist [15], and 
its rapid kinetics are well matched with those of desflurane. 
Little is known about the dose of remifentanil that can effec-
tively prevent the haemodynamic response to desflurane inha-
lation. Weiskopf et al. [16] have reported that maintenance 
of anaesthesia with 4% desflurane produced no sympathetic 
or cardiovascular stimulation. To eliminate the possible 
sympathetic response evoked by desflurane, a 3% inhalation 
concentration of desflurane was used in this study. There was 
no difference in the end-tidal concentration of desflurane 
between the five groups of this study. 
In conclusion, the EC of remifentanil for successful intubation 
without development of hypertension in 95% of patients was 3.3 
ng/ml when 2.0 mg/kg of propofol induction was followed by 3% 
desflurane inhalation. Also, the incidence of hypotension was 
estimated to be approximately 25% following this drug regimen. </p>



</text></tei>