<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3749580" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine have demonstrated a survival benefit over gemcitabine alone in advanced 
pancreatic cancer (PDA). This study aimed to investigate the clinical, biological, and imaging effects of the regimen in patients 
with operable PDA. </p>

<p>Methods: Patients with operable PDA received two cycles of nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine before surgical resection. FDG-PET 
and CA19.9 tumour marker levels were used to measure clinical activity. Effects on tumour stroma were determined by endoscopic 
ultrasound (EUS) elastography. The collagen content and architecture as well as density of cancer-associated fibroblasts (CAFs) 
were determined in the resected surgical specimen and compared with a group of untreated and treated with conventional 
chemoradiation therapy controls. A co-clinical study in a mouse model of PDA was conducted to differentiate between the effects 
of nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine. </p>

<p>Results: A total of 16 patients were enrolled. Treatment resulted in significant antitumour effects with 50% of patients achieving a 
475% decrease in circulating CA19.9 tumour marker and a response by FDG-PET. There was also a significant decrement in 
tumour stiffness as measured by EUS elastography. Seven of 12 patients who completed treatment and were operated had major 
pathological regressions. Analysis of residual tumours showed a marked disorganised collagen with a very low density of CAF, 
which was not observed in the untreated or conventionally treated control groups. The preclinical co-clinical study showed that 
these effects were specific of nab-paclitaxel and not gemcitabine. </p>

<p>Conclusion: These data suggest that nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine decreases CAF content inducing a marked alteration in 
cancer stroma that results in tumour softening. This regimen should be studied in patients with operable PDA. </p>

<p>The outcome of patients with PDA remains poor (Hidalgo, 2010). 
One important characteristic of this disease is the formation of a 
rich stromal reaction that accompanies the malignant transformed 
epithelium (Mahadevan and Von Hoff, 2007). The stroma is 
composed of extracellular matrix proteins such as collagen, 
hyaluronic acid, and SPARC (secreted protein acidic and rich in 
cysteine) and cellular elements such as cancer-associated fibroblast 
(CAF), endothelial, immune, and inflammatory cells (Mahadevan 
and Von Hoff, 2007). The stroma in PDA contributes to poor 
vascularisation and high intratumoural pressure that decreases </p>

<p>drug diffusion (Von Hoff et al, 2009). There is an increasing 
interest in targeting different components of the cancer stroma in 
PDA and several preclinical studies using genetically engineered 
mouse models (GEMMs) of PDA show promising results (Olive 
et al, 2009; Provenzano et al, 2012; Jacobetz et al, 2013). The 
elimination of the cancer stroma leads to decrease intratumour 
pressure, heighted vascularisation, and improved drug delivery. 
One interesting stromal target of PDA is SPARC, which is 
overexpressed in PDA (Infante et al, 2007). Although the functions 
of this protein are not fully understood, it is implicated in stromal </p>

<p>*Correspondence: Dr M Hidalgo; E-mail: mhidalgo@cnio.es </p>

<p>Received 25 February 2013; revised 26 June 2013; accepted 1 July 2013; published online 1 August 2013 </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Cancer Research UK. All rights reserved 0007 -0920/13 </p>

<p>FULL PAPER </p>

<p>Keywords: PDA; stroma; nab-paclitaxel; CAF </p>

<p>British Journal of Cancer (2013) 109, 926-933 | doi: 10.1038/bjc.2013.415 </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.415 </p>

<p>formation and trafficking, invasion and metastasis, and has been 
linked to a worse prognosis (Infante et al, 2007; Arnold et al, 2010). 
SPARC binds albumin leading to the hypothesis that it may 
facilitate the delivery to the tumour of albumin-bound therapeutics. 
A phase 2 clinical trial of nab-paclitaxel in combination with 
gemcitabine in patients with advanced PDA showed significant 
antitumour activity with an objective response rate of 48%, median 
survival of 12.2 months, and 1-year survival of 48% (Von Hoff 
et al, 2011). A recently reported phase 3 study has shown 
improvement in survival with nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine, as 
compared with gemcitabine in patients with advanced PDA. In a 
parallel preclinical study using patient-derived xenograft models of 
PDA, we showed that exposure to nab-paclitaxel collapsed the 
PDA stroma increasing the intratumour concentration of 
gemcitabine by approximately three-fold (Von Hoff et al, 2011). 
A subsequent study in GEMM of PDA indicated that nab-
paclitaxel increases the intratumour concentration of gemcitabine 
by inactivation of the cytidine deaminase, an enzyme involved in 
the catabolism of gemcitabine (Frese et al, 2012). 
This study aimed to determine the clinical, biological, and 
imaging effects of nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine in patients with 
operable PDA. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Clinical trial eligibility criteria. Patients with histological or 
cytological proven PDA with resectable or borderline resectable 
disease were eligible. Other eligibility criteria included: ageX18 
years old; no prior treatment for PDA; Eastern Cooperative 
Oncology Group performance status 0 or 1; adequate renal 
(creatinineo0.6 mg dl </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>), liver (bilirubino2 mg dl 
-1 , AST and 
ALTo1.5 Â upper limit of normal); and bone marrow 
(ANC41.5 Â 10 
9 cells ml </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>, platelets4100 000 cells ml </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>, haemoglobin 
49 g dl </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) function. All patients provided written informed consent. 
The study was approved by the institutional review board. </p>

<p>Study design, evaluations, and treatment. Before study entry, 
patients were studied with a complete medical history and physical 
exam; complete blood counts and serum chemistry; CA19.9 
tumour marker; high-resolution CT scan of the abdomen, FDG-
PET scan; and endoscopic ultrasound (EUS) elastography. 
Treatment consisted of nab-paclitaxel 125 mg m 
-2 followed by 
gemcitabine 1000 mg m 
-2 administered on days 1, 8, and 15, every 
28 days for two cycles. Treatment-related toxicities were evaluated 
by National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria of 
Adverse Events version 3.0. A CT scan, FDG-PET, elastography, 
and CA19.9 were used to determine tumour response after two 
cycles of treatment. Objective tumour responses were evaluated 
according to <rs id="software-1" type="software">RECIST</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 1.1</rs> criteria (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Eisenhauer et al</rs>, 2009). 
EUS elastography was performed with the linear Pentax EUS 
(Montvale, NJ, USA) and the Hitachi EUB900 equipment 
(Tokyo, Japan). Representative areas of the tumour and surround-
ing normal tissues were selected for analysis. The results of the 
elastography evaluation was defined by the quotient strain ratio 
between the normal and tumour regions as previously described 
(Iglesias-Garcia et al, 2010). Patients with stable or responding 
tumours were schedule for surgical resection 6-8 weeks after the last 
chemotherapy dose. The degree of tumour regression in the surgical 
specimen was determined adapting the Ryan's classification utilised 
in rectal cancer including four categories: GRT-0, complete 
response; GRT-1, important partial response with only single cells 
or isolated cell groups left; GRT-2, partial response but large residual 
tumour, and GRT-3 low or no response and large residual cancer 
(Ryan et al, 2005). R1 resection was considered if there were tumour 
cells present p1 mm of the resection margin. Postoperative 
treatment consisted in four cycles of standard dose of gemcitabine. </p>

<p>Preclinical study. The compound K-Ras </p>

<p>þ /LSLG12Vgeo </p>

<p>; p53 
flox/flox ; 
Elas-tTA/tetO-Cre mice used in this study were kindly provided by 
Dr Mariano Barbacid (Guerra et al, 2011). Mice were treated with 
nab-paclitaxel at a final concentration of 50 mg kg 
-1 paclitaxel I.V. 
once a week and gemcitabine at a final concentration of 50 mg kg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>I.P. twice a week for 3 weeks. Tumour growth was monitored 
in vivo by high-resolution ultrasound. Average tumour volumes at 
baseline in the nab-paclitaxel, gemcitabine, and combination 
groups were 20.8 (4.7), 113.3 (39.3), and 87.9 (34.1) mm 
3 , 
respectively. Responses upon chemotherapy were evaluated as 
follow: progression, when tumour volumes at the end of the study 
were 450% larger than at the start point; partial response, when 
tumour volumes regressed by 450% when compared with initial 
volumes and complete response, and when tumours at the end of 
the study could not be detected by ultrasound. All experiments 
were approved by the CNIO Ethical Committee and performed in 
accordance with the guidelines for Ethical Conduct in the Care and 
Use of Animals as stated in the International Guiding Principles 
for Biomedical Research Involving Animals, developed by the 
Council for International Organizations of Medical Sciences. </p>

<p>Tissue assessments. The primary end point of the study was to 
determine the effects of treatment on tumour stroma including 
assessment of collagen content and structure and CAFs. In 
addition to study samples obtained from patients and mouse 
models, we also analysed a set of six samples from patients with 
untreated PDA and six samples from patients treated with 
conventional chemotherapy and radiation therapy. Collagen 
analysis was assessed using collagen I primary rabbit antibody 
(1 : 100; Rockland Immunochemicals, Gilbertsville, PA, USA) for 
1 h at 37 1C and as secondary antibody Alexa Fluor 555 donkey 
anti-rabbit IgG (1 : 200; Invitrogen, Paisley, UK). Activated 
fibroblasts were determined with double staining using vimentin, 
as total fibroblasts marker (1 : 50; Cell Signaling Technology, 
Danvers, MA, USA) and smooth muscle actin (SMA) as an 
activated fibroblast marker (1 : 100; DakoCytomation, Glostrup, 
Denmark). The secondary antibodies used were Alexa Fluor 488 
donkey anti-rabbit IgG (1 : 200; Invitrogen) for vimentin and Alexa 
Fluor 555 donkey anti-mouse IgG (1 : 200; Invitrogen) for SMA. 
Sections were counterstained with DAPI (Invitrogen) and mounted 
with Prolong Gold Antifade reagent (Invitrogen). Samples were 
acquired using a laser scanning confocal microscope TCS-SP5 
(AOBS) Leica (Leica Microsystems, Wetzlar, Germany) with two 
magnifications Â 20 HCX PL APO CS (0.7 NA) and Â 40 HCX 
PL APO CS (1.25 NA) oil immersion objectives. Acquisition 
Software was <rs id="software-3" type="software">LAS AF</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">v.2.4.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Leica Microsystems</rs>). Fibroblast 
quantification was performed with <rs type="software">Definiens Developer XD</rs> Software 
(Munich, Germany). Detected cells were classified depending on the 
ratio between mean layer intensities of both, vimentin and SMA. 
Activated fibroblasts were considered when they co-expressed SMA 
and vimentin. We determined the fibroblast density index by 
adjusting the number of cells counted to the proportion of tumour 
fibrosis observed in the specimen (adapted from Erkan et al, 2008). 
The quantification was done in two different and representative 
fields (20 steps) for each sample. In the preclinical study, 
immunohistochemistry was performed using antibodies against 
mouse SPARC (R&amp;D Systems, MAB942, Minneapolis, MN, USA) 
and cleaved caspase 3 (Cell Signaling Technology, 9661). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. The analysis was made by 'intention to treat' 
with all patients included using the <rs id="software-4" type="software">IBM SPSS Statistics</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">Version 20.0</rs> 
(IBM, Madrid, Spain). Quantitative variables pre-and post-
treatment were compared using ANOVA test, Student's t-test, and 
non-parametric Mann-Whitney U-test and Wilcoxon test for two 
related samples. The correlation between the outcome variables was 
tested with the Spearman correlation coefficient. In the preclinical 
study, all values are represented as mean ± s.e.m. Immunohisto-
chemistry quantifications were evaluated for significance using the </p>

<p>Stromal targeting in PDA 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.415 </p>

<p>
unpaired t-test with a P-value below 0.05 considered significant for 
all analyses. Significant differences between experimental groups 
were: *Po0.05 or **Po0.01. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Clinical activity of nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine in PDA. 
A total of 16 patients, whose principal characteristics are listed in 
Table 1, received two cycles of nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine 
before surgical resection using the previously published dose and 
schedule (Von Hoff et al, 2011). Three patients developed disease 
progression during the preoperative treatment and were not 
resected. One additional patient with potentially resectable cancer 
was not operated because of high surgical risk. A total of 12 
patients underwent surgery. Overall treatment was well tolerated 
with side effects in the range of what has been previously reported. 
Figure 1 shows the results of the main clinical parameters 
studied. The mean CA19.9 level decreased from 2588 U dl 
-1 pre-
treatment to 1056 U dl 
-1 post-treatment (P ¼ 0.001) with 50% of 
patients having a 475% reduction. Similarly, the max standardised 
uptake value (SUV) of FDG decreased from a mean of 7.2 (range, 
2.98-13.4) before treatment to 4.5 (range, 1.9-9) after treatment 
(P ¼ 0.005), including eight (50%) of the patients with a partial 
metabolic response by FDG-PET (Supplementary Figure 1 shows a 
representative case). There was a statistically significant correlation 
between improvement in CA19.9 tumour marker and FDG PET 
response (P ¼ 0.05). However, no objective responses were 
observed. We also determined tumour stiffness by elastography. 
The ratio value, a measurement of tumour stiffness, diminished 
from a value 36 pre-treatment to 18 post-treatment (P ¼ 0.002). 
These data suggest that tumours became softener after treatment. 
There was a statistically significant correlation between changes 
from baseline in elastography ratio and CA19.9 response 
(P ¼ 0.019). </p>

<p>Of the 12 patients operated, 11 had R0 resection and 1 patient 
had R1 resection. In the final pathological analysis, two cases were 
neuroendocrine carcinomas and 10 were pancreatic adenocarci-
noma. Of the 10 patients with PDA, 1 had a complete pathological 
response, 6 had major pathological responses (GRT-1), 1 had a 
partial response (GRT-2) and 2 did not response (GRT-3). 
Supplementary Figure 1 shows pathological analysis of a 
representative patient. </p>

<p>Tissue effects of nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine. Nine of the 10 
patients with PDA had SPARC-positive tumours. In the subset of 
patients with SPARC expression in the tumour stroma, there was 
no correlation between the degree of SPARC expression and 
clinical or pathological responses. As shown in Figure 2A, type I 
collagen analysis of tumour tissue samples from patients treated 
with nab-paclitaxel plus gemcitabine revealed a less abundant 
fibrillar collagen matrix around tumour glands. In areas of tumour 
regressions the collagen had an amorphous structure, with a 
discontinuous and disorganised network of type I collagen fibres. 
This is in contrast with samples of untreated PDA used as control 
that showed long, continuous well-organised, and imbricated 
fibres. Similarly, in tumours treated with conventional chemo-
radiation studied for comparison, there was an increased in 
collagen matrix with dense bundles of organised collagen around 
tumour glands. 
In addition, patients treated with nab-paclitaxel plus gemcita-
bine had a lower number of CAF. The average number of CAF in 
the nab-paclitaxel plus gemcitabine-treated group was 267 ± 179 
while samples from untreated patients and samples from patients 
treated with conventional chemotherapy and radiation therapy was 
642±378 (P ¼ 0.01) and 557±140 (P ¼ 0.037). Interestingly, the 
proportion of SMA þ fibroblasts was similar in all these cases 
ranging from 76 to 78% (Figure 2B and C). 
As the proportion of tumour stroma changed from one setting 
to another, we calculated the CAF density index on these samples. 
As shown in Figure 2D, the CAF density in untreated PDA 
tumours was 15±10. In cases treated with conventional chemo-
radiation, because the stroma content increased the density 
decreased to 12 ± 11. In nab-paclitaxel plus gemcitabine-treated 
cases, this number decreased to 6 ± 3 because of higher stromal 
content and decrease number of CAF. </p>

<p>Preclinical study in GEMM of PDA. In order to determine the 
specific contributions of nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine to these 
results, we performed an in vivo study in GEMM of PDA (Guerra 
et al, 2011). As shown in Supplementary Figure 2, the cancer, 
induced in these models by activation of KRAS and inactivation of 
TP53, is SPARC þ in CAF. Mice were enrolled in this study as 
individual subjects when tumours were detected by two 
consecutive ultrasound measurements. As expected, the combination 
of nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine was very effective and resulted in 
a complete tumour regression in two mice and a partial tumour 
regressions in one mouse, as determined by ultrasound after 21 
days of treatment (Figure 3A). Gemcitabine alone treatment 
resulted in minor responses, while nab-paclitaxel alone did not 
show any antitumour activity (Figure 3A). Consistently, nab-
paclitaxel plus gemcitabine significantly increased the proportion 
of apoptotic cells compared with control (Figure 3B and C). 
Average increase in tumour volumes in the nab-paclitaxel, 
gemcitabine, and combination groups on day 21 compare with 
baseline were 14.1, 4.6, and 0.96, respectively. 
Analysis of type I collagen revealed a decrease in collagen matrix 
in nab-paclitaxel and nab-paclitaxel plus gemcitabine groups 
compared with control and gemcitabine groups (Figure 4A). Type 
I collagen matrix showed a heterogeneous pattern alternating 
between areas with moderate extracellular matrix and areas with 
very low collagen matrix. Collagen bundles were composed 
of disrupted and disorganised fibres. However, control and </p>

<p>Table 1. Patient characteristics (n ¼ 16) </p>

<p>Median age (range) 
58 (41-80) </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Male 
10 
Female 
6 </p>

<p>ECOG </p>

<p>0 
6 
1 
1 0 </p>

<p>Tumour location </p>

<p>Head 
14 
Body 
1 
Tail 
1 </p>

<p>Clinical staging </p>

<p>I 
2 
II 
11 
III 
3 </p>

<p>Resectability </p>

<p>Resectable 
7 
Borderline resectable 
9 
Pre-treatment CA19.9 (U dl </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) 
2588 (1-36 376) </p>

<p>Abbreviation: ECOG ¼ Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Stromal targeting in PDA </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.415 </p>

<p>gemcitabine groups showed a dense collagen matrix with long and 
imbricated collagen fibres around tumour glands (Figure 4A). The 
total number of CAF in nab-paclitaxel group and nab-paclitaxel 
plus gemcitabine group was 37±17.4 and 35±24.5, respectively, 
with 68% of SMA þ fibroblasts in both treated groups (Figure 4B 
and C). The total number of CAF in control group was similar to 
the former groups, 39 ± 18.4 and 69% of SMA þ fibroblasts. 
However, the gemcitabine-treated group showed a higher number 
of fibroblasts, 173 ± 125.2 than the other groups with a similar 
proportion of SMA þ (65.2%). The CAF density ranged between 
2.8 and 2.3 in nab-paclitaxel and nab-paclitaxel plus gemcitabine </p>

<p>group and this parameter increased to 7 in the gemcitabine group; 
however, because low number of cases, there were no statistically 
significant differences. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This study aimed to investigate the effects of nab-paclitaxel and 
gemcitabine in PDA stroma. To this end, we conducted a clinical 
and co-clinical study in patients with operable PDA and in </p>

<p>-100.00 </p>

<p>4 16 2 9 13 12 7 8 
Patient number </p>

<p>1 5 6 11 3 15 14 10 </p>

<p>-75.00 </p>

<p>-50.00 </p>

<p>-25.00 </p>

<p>Changes in CA19.9 levels from baseline </p>

<p>25.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>-100.00 </p>

<p>-100.00 
-75.00 
-50.00 
-25.00 </p>

<p>Changes in CA19.9 levels from baseline </p>

<p>0.00 
25.00 </p>

<p>-50.00 
Changes in elastograpy ratio from baseline </p>

<p>50.00 </p>

<p>100.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>-100.00 
-75.00 
-50.00 
-25.00 </p>

<p>Changes in CA19.9 levels from baseline </p>

<p>0.00 
25.00 </p>

<p>-50.00 </p>

<p>-25.00 </p>

<p>-75.00 
Changes in SUV uptake from baseline </p>

<p>25.00 </p>

<p>50.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>13 16 6 12 4 1 3 7 
Patient number </p>

<p>8 14 11 10 9 15 5 </p>

<p>-75.00 </p>

<p>-50.00 </p>

<p>-25.00 </p>

<p>Changes in SUV uptake from baseline </p>

<p>25.00 </p>

<p>50.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>6 14 8 5 11 3 10 
Patient number </p>

<p>15 12 4 9 1 13 2 </p>

<p>-100.00 </p>

<p>-50.00 
Changes in elastography ratio from baseline </p>

<p>100.00 </p>

<p>50.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Antitumour effects of nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine in PDA. Panels (A-C) show waterfall plots of changes from baseline variation in the 
levels of the CA19.9 tumour marker, SUV FDG uptake and elastrography strain ratio of patients treated with nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine. 
Studies were performed at baseline, before treatment, and after two 4 weeks cycles of treatment and best response is shown. As depicted, in all 
patients but one, there was evidence of antitumour effects, which was marked in more than half of the patients. Panels (D) and (E) show a scatter 
plot graph of the change from baseline in FDG SUV and elastography strain ratio with CA19.9 levels, respectively, which is an accepted parameter 
of clinical efficacy. As shown, improvement in both imaging parameters were correlated with improvement in CA19.9 with a P ¼ 0.05 and 0.01, 
respectively. </p>

<p>Stromal targeting in PDA 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.415 </p>

<p>
GEMM of the disease. The study shows that nab-paclitaxel and 
gemcitabine was very effective inducing marked tumour responses 
by FDG-PET and CA19.9 levels. Seven of 10 patients with PDA 
had major pathological responses. Analysis of residual tissues 
indicated an important disruption of collagen architecture and a 
decrease in CAF, albeit the number of activated CAF remained 
unchanged. These effects translated into diminished tumour 
stiffness as measure by EUS elastography. In the co-clinical mouse 
study, we observed that nab-paclitaxel-treated animals have also a 
distorted collagen with low cellular content while gemcitabine-
treated mice showed a marked increase in CAF. 
Although the main objective of the study was not clinical 
outcome, and thus the sample size is limited to make any strong 
conclusion in that sense, the antitumour effects as shown by FDG-
PET, CA19.9 response, rate of R0 resections, and pathological 
responses, are notable and certainly support additional definitive 
studies in this setting (Chun et al, 2011; Andriulli et al, 2012). Of 
interest, and in agreement with the tissue-based analysis discussed 
below, we did not observe objective responses by RECIST. 
However, the majority of patients showed improvement in SUV 
uptake by FDG-PET and elastography ratio. This discrepancy 
between morphological and functional imaging is consistent with </p>

<p>the tissue results and suggest that as a tumour respond to 
treatment there is a replacement of actively growing glucose 
consuming cells to an oligocellular, quiescent stroma. The lack 
of concordance between RECIST, metabolic, and pathological 
responses points to the need to incorporate other measurements of 
efficacy in preoperative studies in PDA. Three patients, however, 
develop rapid disease progression indicating that there is a group 
of patients who progress rapidly to nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine. 
Biomarkers to identify these patients are of mayor interest. 
One of the goals of this work was to incorporate new methods to 
evaluate stromal changes. To this end, we focused on EUS-based 
elastography. This imaging modality is currently used to determine 
the degree of liver fibrosis in patients with end-stage liver disease. 
In PDA, its main application has been the differential diagnosis of 
benign and malignant pancreas masses (Janssen et al, 2007; 
Iglesias-Garcia et al, 2010; Dawwas et al, 2012). In this study, we 
show that tumour stiffness decreased during treatment and that 
this effect correlated with improvement in CA19.9 and FDG 
uptake likely reflecting modification in the cancer stroma as shown 
in the tissue analysis. Elastography should be further studied in 
preoperative trials in PDA and in particular in those with agents 
targeting the stroma. </p>

<p>Untreated 
Chemoradiation </p>

<p>Untreated 
Chemoradiation 
Nab-paclitaxel + 
gemcitabine </p>

<p>Nab-paclitaxel + 
gemcitabine </p>

<p>1200 
Total CAF 
SMA+ CAF 
1000 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>600 
Number of cells </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>U n tr e a te d 
P D A 
C h e m o ra d ia ti o n </p>

<p>P D A </p>

<p>N a b -p a c li ta x e l+ g e m </p>

<p>P D A </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>* 
** </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Media CAF density 
10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>U n tr e a te d 
P D A 
C h e m o ra d ia ti o n </p>

<p>P D A </p>

<p>N a b -p a c li ta x e l+ g e m </p>

<p>P D A </p>

<p>Figure 2. Tissue effects of nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine in human PDA. Panel (A) shows confocal microscopy analysis of type I collagen 
immunofluorescence as main component of extracellular matrix in untreated sample, a sample of a patient treated with chemoradiation, and a 
sample of a patient treated with nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine ( Â 20, top, and the same field at Â 40, bottom; scale bar ¼ 100 mM, Â 20 field, 
and 50 mM, Â 40 field). Panel (B) shows the effects of treatment in CAF stained for aSMA (red) and vimentin (green) immunofluorescence for 
quantification of activated and total fibroblasts in untreated sample (left), sample treated with chemoradiation (middle) and sample treated with 
nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine (right; Â 40; scale bar ¼ 50 mM). Panel (C) shows a quantification of total and activated CAFs in untreated samples, 
primary PDA tumours treated with chemoradiation, primary tumour PDA tumours treated with nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine in two (20 steps) 
Â 40 HCX PL APO CS (1.25 NA) oil immersion objectives high-power fields. Samples treated with nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine show a 
statistically significant lower activated CAF (Mann-Whitney tests were used for statistical analysis: *P ¼ 0.037). Panel (D) represents the average 
CAF density index determined by dividing the number of CAF by proportion of stromal content in two Â 40 HCX PL APO CS (1.25 NA) oil 
immersion objectives high-power fields. As shown, nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine-treated groups have a statistically significant lower activated 
CAF density (Mann-Whitney tests were used for statistical analysis: *P ¼ 0.037; **P ¼ 0.015). </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Stromal targeting in PDA </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.415 </p>

<p>The effects of nab-paclitaxel in PDA stroma are not fully 
understood and to some extent controversial. In our prior studies 
in patient-derived xenograft mouse models treated for short period 
of time, we observed an almost complete elimination of cancer 
stroma (Von Hoff et al, 2011). These results, however, were not 
reproduced in studies using GEMM of PDA (Frese et al, 2012). 
Here we show, in patient samples, that the effect is predominantly 
stromal remodelling with marked alteration of collagen architecture 
and elimination of CAF. This is best reflected by changes in 
CAF density and appears to be different from patients treated with 
conventional chemoradiation. Similar observations were made in 
GEMM of PDA driven by distinct engineered genetic changes as 
the models tested before: the most striking observation was the 
increase collagen and CAF in the gemcitabine only treated group. 
The reasons for these differences across models and patients are 
not known. Duration of treatment can be a factor as mice studies 
are conducted with short, 5-21 days, exposure while in human 
studies the treatment duration is 8 weeks allowing time for some of 
the tissue remodelling effects to occur. Another factor is differences 
between models. Human-derived xenografts models form less 
stroma of murine origin and have abnormal tumour vascularisa-
tion, particularly in subcutaneous implanted tumours. In contrast, 
the KPC GEMM model used in prior studies forms abundant 
and exuberant stroma (Olive et al, 2009). The GEMM model used 
in these studies, carrying different engineered genetic changes, has 
an intermediate stromal content not as manifested as the 
KPC model. 
There are, however, limitations to this work that need to be 
taken into account when considering the implications of these data. </p>

<p>The sample size is small and includes patients with different stages, 
even within a group of patients with localises PDA, making any 
conclusion hypothesis generating. Indeed, the content of stroma 
and CAF may change with different cancer stages. Another 
limitation is that the study does not include a pre-and post-
treatment tissue biopsy to determine tissue changes but rather an 
untreated control. Finally, there is no randomised control arm 
treated with gemcitabine alone that would make the comparison 
more conclusive. 
In summary, this clinical study shows that nab-paclitaxel 
plus gemcitabine exerts significant antitumour activity in 
primary PDA as seen by the high rate of responses by different 
imaging methods and tumour marker studies that led to margin-
free resection in 92% of patients and pathological responses in 
70% of cases. Although the number of patients is small, the 
results are striking enough to warrant additional studies in 
this setting. At the tissue level, the most interesting observation 
of the study is that, in marked contrast with tumour exposed 
preoperatively to conventional chemoradiation, tumours 
treated with nab-paclitaxel contained less abundant CAFs, a 
clearly altered collagen, and had became softer as determined 
by elastography. Parallel mouse studies indicate that the 
main effects are due to nab-paclitaxel and not gemcitabine. 
Based on these data, this approach should be tested in a 
larger randomise trial to determine the clinical impact of 
tumour down staging before surgery and the long-term 
impact of pathological tumour regression. In addition, EUS 
elastography appears an attractive method to monitor stromal 
changes with treatment. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Untrreated </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>0 
Relative tumour growth (%) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Nab-paclitaxel+gemcitabbine </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 
c.Caspase 3-positive cells </p>

<p>G 
e m 
c i t a b i n e </p>

<p>N 
a b -p a c l i t a x e l 
N 
a b -p a c l i t a x e l 
+ g e m 
c i t a b i n e </p>

<p>G 
e m 
c i t a b i n e 
U 
n t r e a t e d </p>

<p>N 
a b -p a c l i t a x e l 
N 
a b -p a c l i t a x e l 
+ g e m 
c i t a b i n e </p>

<p>Figure 3. Antitumour effects of nab-paclitaxel and gemcitabine in GEMM of PDA. Panel (A) shows tumour growth inhibition of individual mouse 
treated with gemcitabine, nab-paclitaxel, or the combination. As depicted, the combined treatment was more effective than treatment with either 
gemcitabine alone (P ¼ 0.01) or nab-paclitaxel (P ¼ 0.001). Panel (B) shows representative microphotograph of caspase 3 expression showing 
increased level of apoptosis in the treated tumours. Panel (C) shows the quantification of caspase 3-positive cells in the different treatment groups 
showing a statistically significant increased in the combination treated group compared with control (*P ¼ 0.047, assessed by Student's t-test 
related to the untreated group). </p>

<p>Stromal targeting in PDA 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.415 </p>

<p>
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank JI Gordon (Washington University School of Medicine, 
St Louis, MO, USA) for providing the tetO-PhCMV-Cre mice and 
Eric Sandgren (University of Wisconsin, Madison, WI, USA) for 
providing the Elastase-tTA strain. This study was supported by the 
Fondo de Investigaciones Sanitarias (FIS) PI10-01996 and Celgene 
Inc. to MH; the European Research Council (ERC-AG/250297-
RAS AHEAD) and Spanish Ministry of Economy and Competi-
tiveness (SAF2011-30173) to MB. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>



<p>400 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>Total CAF 
SMA+ CAF </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 
Number of cells </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Gemcitabine 
Nab-paclitaxel 
Nab-paclitaxel + 
gemcitabine </p>

<p>Control 
Gemcitabine 
Nab-paclitaxel 
Nab-paclitaxel + 
gemcitabine </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>G 
e m 
c it a b in </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>N 
a b -p a c li t a x e l N </p>

<p>a b -p a c li t a x e l+ </p>

<p>g e m </p>

<p>Figure 4. Tissue effects of treatment regimens in GEMM of PDA. Panel (A) shows confocal microscopy analysis of type I collagen 
immunofluorescence as main component of extracellular matrix in untreated tumours and tumours treated with gemcitabine, nab-paclitaxel, and 
the combination ( Â 20, top, and detail of collagen network at Â 20, bottom; scale bar ¼ 75 mM, Â 20 field). Panel (B) shows the effects of treatment 
in CAF stained for aSMA (red) and vimentin (green) immunofluorescence for quantification of activated and total fibroblast in samples of mice 
treated with the indicated agents ( Â 40, scale bar ¼ 50 mM). Panel (C) shows a quantification of total and activated CAFs in untreated tumours and 
tumours treated with gemcitabine, nab-paclitaxel and the combination in two (20 steps) Â 40 HCX PL APO CS (1.25 NA) oil immersion objectives 
high-power fields. Statistical analysis was not significant because of heterogeneity of samples. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Stromal targeting in PDA </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.415 </p>



<p>This work is published under the standard license to publish agree-
ment. After 12 months the work will become freely available and 
the license terms will switch to a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on British Journal of Cancer website (http://www.nature.com/bjc) </p>

<p>Stromal targeting in PDA 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.415 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>