<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3717584" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Background The intensive physical and psychological 
stress of emergency medicine has evoked concerns 
about whether emergency physicians could work in the 
emergency department for their entire careers. Results 
of previous studies of the attrition rates of emergency 
physicians are conflicting, but the study samples and 
designs were limited. 
Objective To use National Health Insurance claims data 
to track the work status and work places of emergency 
physicians compared with other specialists. To examine 
the hypothesis that emergency physicians leave their 
specialty more frequently than other hospital-based 
specialists. 
Methods Three types of specialists who work in 
hospitals were enrolled: emergency physicians, surgeons 
and radiologists/pathologists. Every physician was 
followed up until they left the hospital, did not work 
anymore or were censored. A KaplaneMeier curve was 
plotted to show the trend. A multivariate Cox 
regression model was then applied to evaluate the 
adjusted HRs of emergency physicians compared with 
other specialists. 
Results A total of 16 666 physicians (1584 emergency 
physicians, 12 103 surgeons and 2979 radiologists/ 
pathologists) were identified between 1997 and 2010. 
For emergency physicians, the KaplaneMeier curve 
showed a significantly decreased survival after 10 years. 
The log-rank test was statistically significant (p value 
&lt;0.001). In the Cox regression model, after adjusting for 
age and sex, the HRs of emergency physicians compared 
with surgeons and radiologists/pathologists were 5.84 
(95% CI 2.98 to 11.47) and 21.34 (95% CI 8.00 to 
56.89), respectively. 
Conclusion Emergency physicians have a higher 
probability of leaving their specialties than surgeons and 
radiologists/pathologists, possibly owing to the high 
stress of emergency medicine. Further strategies should 
be planned to retain experienced emergency physicians 
in their specialties. </p>

<p>The intensive physical and psychological stress of 
emergency medicine has evoked concerns about 
whether emergency physicians could work in 
the emergency department (ED) for their 
entire careers. 
1e3 Compared with other specialists, 
emergency physicians have more stress factors. 
Workefamily conflict, overnight shifts, general 
uncertainty and difficult patients often cause </p>

<p>physical and emotional exhaustion among emer-
gency physicians. 
1 4e9 Most previous studies using 
survey data found that the attrition rates of emer-
gency physicians were varied, 
10e14 and no obser-
vational study has illustrated the working life of 
emergency physicians compared with other 
specialists. 
In addition to estimation of the numbers of 
emergency physicians needed in one nation, it is 
also important to evaluate how long emergency 
physicians will be active in the clinical practice of 
emergency medicine. We aimed to use National 
Health Insurance (NHI) claims data to track the 
work status of emergency physicians compared 
with other specialists. The hypothesis is that 
emergency physicians will leave their specialty 
more frequently than other hospital-based special-
ists because of high stress and burnout. </p>

<p>PATIENTS AND METHODS 
Data sources </p>

<p>The healthcare providers files of the NHI claims 
data were used in this study. Study subjects were 
physicians who were specialists certified by 
Department of Health in Taiwan between 1 
January 1997 and 31 December 2010. We enrolled 
three types of specialists for comparison: emer-
gency physicians, surgeons and radiologists/ 
pathologists. Surgeons included neurosurgeons, 
general surgeons, plastic surgeons and orthopaed-
ists. Radiologists/pathologists included radiologists, 
pathologists and nuclear medicine specialists. 
Physicians have to pass the board-certification 
examinations to become specialists. </p>

<p>Identification of attrition </p>

<p>In Taiwan, it is uncommon for emergency physi-
cians, surgeons and radiologists/pathologists to 
practise in institutes other than hospitals. As 
a result, if a specialist changed his or her licence 
registration institute to an outpatient-based clinic, 
it would be recognised as 'failure'. If the work 
status was labelled as 'inactive' in the NHI data-
base, he or she would not perform any kind of 
medical-related practice and it would also be 
recognised as 'failure'. If the physician kept 
working in the hospital during the study period, 
he would be labelled censored (non-event). Finally, 
if the physician was not registered in any health-
care institutions during the study period, he or she 
would also be labelled as 'censored'. The follow-up 
period would be defined from the authorisation </p>

<p>1 Emergency Department, 
Buddhist Tzu Chi Dalin General 
Hospital, Chiayi, Taiwan 
2 School of Medicine, Tzu Zhi 
University, Hualien, Taiwan 
3 Community Medicine Research 
Center and Institute of Public 
Health, National Yang-Ming 
University, Taipei, Taiwan 
4 Department of Otolaryngology, 
Buddhist Dalin Tzu Chi General 
Hospital, Chiayi, Taiwan 
5 Cancer Center, Buddhist Dalin 
Tzu Chi General Hospital, Chiayi, 
Taiwan 
6 Division of Emergency 
Medicine, Keelung Hospital, 
Department of Health, Executive 
Yuan, Keelung, Taiwan </p>

<p>Correspondence to 
Dr Yung-Cheng Su, Emergency 
Department, Buddhist Tzu Chi 
Dalin General Hospital, No 2, 
Minsheng Rd., Dalin Township, 
Chiayi County 622, Taiwan (R.O. 
C.); drsu119@gmail.com </p>

<p>Accepted 28 June 2012 </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>620 
Emerg Med J 2013;30:620-622. doi:10.1136/emermed-2012-201440 </p>

<p>Published Online First 
25 April 2013 </p>

<p>Open Access 
Scan to access more 
free content </p>

<p>date of the specialty licence until the date of failure or 
censoring. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Continuous variables were compared with one-way analysis of </p>

<p>variance, and categorical variables with c </p>

<p>2 test. 95% CI and p 
value were reported. A p value of &lt;0.05 was considered signifi-
cant. We first used log-rank test to examine whether different 
types of specialists had statistically different survival functions, 
and KaplaneMeier curves were plotted to show the trend. 
We further used a multivariate Cox regression model to adjust 
for age when the physician became the specialist and gender to 
calculate the HR of failure. All analyses were performed using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Analysis Software for Windows</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V9.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc</rs>) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">STATA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">V11.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">StataCorp</rs>). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>A total of 16 666 physicians (1584 emergency physicians, 12 103 
surgeons and 2979 radiologists/pathologists) were identified 
between 1997 and 2010. The average follow-up period was 
9.5 years. The mean age (SD) at the time when the specialty was 
certified was 36.7 (8.3) years. A total of 1395 (8.4%) physicians 
left the clinical practice of their specialties during the 14 years' 
observation period. The baseline characteristics of the three 
groups of specialists are summarised in table 1. 
We first divided the cohort into three groups (emergency 
physicians, surgeons and radiologists/pathologists) and plotted 
the KaplaneMeier curve to evaluate the survival function 
(figure 1). A sharp decrease of the slope in the emergency 
physicians group was noted after observation for 10 years, </p>

<p>indicating higher attrition compared with other two groups 
after 10 years. The log-rank test was also statistically significant 
(p value &lt;0.0001) (table 1). 
We than used the multivariate Cox regression model to eval-
uate the HRs of attrition from specialties compared with other 
two types of specialists. In comparison with surgeons, the 
adjusted HR of emergency physicians was 5.84 (95% CI 2.98 to 
11.47) (table 2). In these two groups, male specialists seemed to 
remain in their specialties longer than female specialists 
(HR¼0.43; 95% CI 0.22 to 0.83). As age increased, more 
specialists left their specialties. When specialists were older than 
45 years old, the HR of leaving their specialties was 2.01 (95% CI 
1.73 to 2.35) compared with those aged &lt;35 years. In compar-
ison with radiologists/pathologists, the adjusted HR of emer-
gency physicians was 21.34 (95% CI 8.00 to 56.89). (table 3) 
Gender did not significantly increase attrition in this subgroup. 
In this group, specialists older than 45 years had a higher HR 
(1.87; 95% CI 1.05 to 3.35) than those aged &lt;35 years. The 
statistical results are summarised in tables 2 and table 3. </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>This NHI database has potential limitations. First, although this 
is the largest and most comprehensive public source for infor-
mation about specialists in Taiwan, we cannot check the accu-
racy of these secondary data and some information is missing. 
Second, physicians might have different certified specialties and 
might register in the institutes using specialties other than our 
study interests. For example, an emergency physician might also 
be a certified cardiologist, and work in the hospital as a cardiol-
ogist and a part-time emergency physician. In our study cohort, 
he would be labelled as censored. 
Many physicians work in the emergency department (ED) 
without this being their specialism, but in our database, we can 
capture only physicians with certified specialties. As a result, in </p>

<p>Table 1 Baseline characteristics of physicians with different specialties </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Emergency physicians (N[1584) 
Surgeons (N[12 103) 
Radiologists/pathologists (N[2979) 
p Value </p>

<p>Men, n (%) 
1473 (93.0) 
11 347 (93.8) 
2308 (77.5) 
&lt;0.0001 
Age (years), n (%) 
&lt;0.0001 
&lt;35 
958 (60.5) 
6842 (56.5) 
1889 (63.4) 
35e45 
530 (33.5) 
3501 (28.9) 
774 (26.0) 
$45 
96 (6.0) 
1760 (14.6) 
316 (10.6) 
Mean (SD) 
34.7 (5.5) 
37.2 (8.5) 
35.9 (8.4) 
Observed person-years 
54 51.3 
124 483.1 
28 580.3 
NA 
Failure, n (%) 
10 (0.63) 
1298 (10.7) 
87 (2.9) 
&lt;0.0001* 
Attrition rate (per 1000 person-year) 
1.83 
10.42 
3.04 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>Figure 1 Survival curve of three kinds of specialists. </p>

<p>Table 2 Crude and adjusted HRs of attrition among emergency 
physicians and surgeons </p>

<p>Factors </p>

<p>Crude HR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Adjusted HR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>p Value for 
adjusted HR </p>

<p>Surgeons 
1.00 (reference) 
1.00 (reference) 
Emergency physicians 5.48 (2.80 to 10.72) 5.84 (2.98 to 11.47) &lt;0.0001 
Sex 
Female 
1.00 (reference) 
1.00 (reference) 
Male 
0.46 (0.24 to 0.89) 
0.43 (0.22 to 0.83) 
0.0119 
Age 
&lt;35 
1.00 (reference) 
1.0 (reference) 
35e45 
1.21 (1.05 to 1.40) 
1.22 (1.06 to 1.40) 
0.0069 
$45 
1.99 (1.70 to 2.31) 
2.01 (1.73 to 2.35) 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>Emerg Med J 2013;30:620-622. doi:10.1136/emermed-2012-201440 </p>

<p>
the study we evaluated only the attrition of specialists instead of 
all physicians working in the ED. Finally, attrition was defined 
by primary type of practice and it is possible that physicians 
labelled as 'failure' work part time in emergency medicine clin-
ical practice. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>To our knowledge, this observational study is the first to use 
a large cohort to follow up the working lives of emergency 
physicians. Based on the available information, only 0.63% of 
emergency physicians left emergency medicine clinical practice 
during the 14 years of observation. Cross-sectional examination of 
the data shows that the attrition rate is extremely low compared 
with reported rates. 
2 4 11e15 However, if individual observation 
periods are taken into account, we found that the 'survival' was 
significantly decreased after 10 years. In comparison with the 
other two kinds of specialists, the adjusted HRs were also 
significantly high. The findings demonstrate that the low annual 
attrition rate of emergency physicians may be too optimistic. 
According to our findings, emergency physicians are about to 
leave this field when they are fully experienced. This would be 
a loss for the training programme of this specialty, and also for 
patients. Strategies to keep experienced emergency physicians in 
their 'battlefields'dfor example, by developing a less labour-
intensive subspecialty (eg, disaster preparedness)dshould be 
emphasised. In this way, emergency physicians might continue 
to work in hospitals passing on their experience when their 
physical ability declines. 
In summary, our study found that despite the low annual 
attrition rate, in the long term there is a high probability that 
emergency physicians will leave their specialties compared with 
other specialists, possibly owing to the high stress of emergency </p>

<p>medicine. Further strategies should be planned to retain experi-
enced emergency physicians in their specialties. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements This study is based in part on data from the National Health 
Insurance Research Database provided by the Bureau of National Health Insurance, 
Department of Health, and managed by the National Health Research Institutes 
(registered number 99018 &amp; 99321). The interpretation and conclusions contained 
herein do not represent those of the Bureau of National Health Insurance, 
Department of Health, or National Health Research Institutes. </p>

<p>Contributors Y-KL helped in data analysis, and wrote the paper. C-CL was involved in 
design, implementation, and data analysis. C-CC was involved in the data 
management. C-HW contributed to the writing of the paper. Y-CS was involved in the 
design, analysis, and contributed to the writing of the paper. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>



<p>Table 3 Crude and adjusted HRs of attrition among emergency 
physicians and radiologists/pathologists </p>

<p>Factors </p>

<p>Crude HR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Adjusted HR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>p Value for 
adjusted HR </p>

<p>Radiologists/pathologists 1.00 (reference) 
1.00 (reference) 
Emergency physicians 
20.75 (7.81 to 55.15) 21.34 (8.00 to 56.89) &lt;0.0001 
Sex 
Female 
1.00 (reference) 
1.00 (reference) 
Male 
1.13 (0.57 to 2.24) 
0.94 (0.47 to 1.89) 
0.8646 
Age 
&lt;35 
1.00 (reference) 
1.00 (reference) 
35e45 
1.58 (0.98 to 2.55) 
1.55 (0.96 to 2.50) 
0.0754 
$45 
1.75 (0.99 to 3.10) 
1.87 (1.05 to 3.35) 
0.0339 </p>

<p>PAGE fraction trail=2.75 </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>622 
Emerg Med J 2013;30:620-622. doi:10.1136/emermed-2012-201440 </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the 
Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 3.0) license, which permits 
others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license 
their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited 
and the use is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/ </p>

</text></tei>