<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3464772" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T16:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>BACKGROUND: High BCAR4 and ERBB2 mRNA levels in primary breast cancer associate with tamoxifen resistance and poor patient 
outcome. We determined whether BCAR4 expression sensitises breast cancer cells to lapatinib, and identifies a subgroup of patients 
who possibly may benefit from ERBB2-targeted therapies despite having tumours with low ERBB2 expression. 
METHODS: Proliferation assays were applied to determine the effect of BCAR4 expression on lapatinib treatment. Changes in cell 
signalling were quantified with reverse-phase protein microarrays. Quantitative reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain reaction 
(RT-PCR) of ERBB2 and BCAR4 was performed in 1418 primary breast cancers. Combined BCAR4 and ERBB2 mRNA levels were 
evaluated for association with progression-free survival (PFS) in 293 oestrogen receptor-a (ER)-positive patients receiving tamoxifen 
as first-line monotherapy for recurrent disease. 
RESULTS: BCAR4 expression strongly sensitised ZR-75-1 and MCF7 breast cancer cells to the combination of lapatinib and 
antioestrogens. Lapatinib interfered with phosphorylation of ERBB2 and its downstream mediators AKT, FAK, SHC, STAT5, and 
STAT6. Reverse transcriptase-PCR analysis showed that 27.6% of the breast cancers were positive for BCAR4 and 22% expressed 
also low levels of ERBB2. The clinical significance of combining BCAR4 and ERBB2 mRNA status was underscored by the finding that 
the group of patients having BCAR4-positive/ERBB2-low-expressing cancers had a shorter PFS on tamoxifen treatment than the 
BCAR4-negative group. 
CONCLUSION: This study shows that BCAR4 expression identifies a subgroup of ER-positive breast cancer patients without 
overexpression of ERBB2 who have a poor outcome and might benefit from combined ERBB2-targeted and antioestrogen therapy. 
Keywords: BCAR4; ERBB2; targeted therapy; breast cancer; tamoxifen resistance </p>































































<p>Tamoxifen has an important role in the treatment of patients with 
oestrogen receptor-a (ER)-positive primary breast cancer, both in 
the adjuvant and metastatic setting (Davies et al, 2011). Its efficacy 
is limited by primary (intrinsic) or secondary (acquired) 
resistance. A better understanding of the mechanisms involved is 
required to overcome resistance and for developing more effective 
therapies. Several genes and mechanism causing antioestrogen 
resistance were identified (Dorssers and Veldscholte, 1997; Van 
Agthoven et al, 1998; Brinkman et al, 2000; Massarweh and Schiff, 
2007; Riggins et al, 2007; Musgrove and Sutherland, 2009; Barone 
et al, 2010; Van Agthoven et al, 2010), including the novel breast 
cancer antioestrogen resistance 4 (BCAR4) gene (Meijer et al, 
2006). Ectopic expression of BCAR4 causes antioestrogen resis-
tance, anchorage independence, and tumour growth in nude mice 
(Meijer et al, 2006; Godinho et al, 2011). BCAR4 mRNA is detected 
in 22-29% of primary breast cancers. High levels are associated 
with shorter progression-free survival (PFS) in patients treated 
with tamoxifen for recurrent disease, and associate with poor </p>

<p>metastasis-free survival (MFS) and overall survival (OS), reflecting 
tumour aggressiveness (Godinho et al, 2010). 
BCAR4 has been found in several mammalian species, being well 
conserved in higher primates (Meijer et al, 2006; Godinho et al, 
2011). In the functional screening for genes causing tamoxifen 
resistance, it was isolated from a human placenta cDNA library 
only (Meijer et al, 2006; Godinho et al, 2011). Searches in public 
expression databases and in the literature showed that high BCAR4 
expression is only found in placenta and the oocyte (Meijer et al, 
2006; Godinho et al, 2011). In other normal adult tissues, 
expression of BCAR4 was not found. The species and tissue-
specific expression strongly indicates a role for BCAR4 in 
mammalian early development and pregnancy. Surprisingly, the 
BCAR4 gene is absent in the mouse and rat (Godinho et al, 2011). 
Important differences exist between human and mouse placental 
development and function. In the mouse, in contrast to the human 
situation, trophoblast implantation is superficial, the transforma-
tion of the uterine arteries depends on maternal factors, and 
mouse placenta produces fewer placental hormones (Malassine 
et al, 2003; Carter, 2007). At this point it is only possible to 
speculate on the function of this gene, but it is likely that 
differences in placental development and function could explain the </p>

<p>*Correspondence: Dr T van Agthoven; E-mail: a.vanagthoven@erasmusmc.nl 
Received 17 April 2012; revised 12 July 2012; accepted 13 July 2012; 
published online 14 August 2012 </p>

<p>British Journal of Cancer (2012) 107, 947-955 
&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK All rights reserved 0007 -0920/12 </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com </p>

<p>Clinical Studies </p>

<p>absence in these organisms. BCAR4 may have a function in placenta 
and early development, therefore it cannot be excluded that in mouse 
and rat its function has been taken over by other genes. 
BCAR4-induced tamoxifen resistance depends on the presence 
of ERBB2 (HER2) and ERBB3 receptors (Godinho et al, 2010). We 
hypothesised that BCAR4 expression may sensitise breast cancer 
cells to the small-molecule tyrosine kinase activity inhibitor of 
EGFR and ERBB2. In this study, BCAR4-expressing cells were 
assessed for their sensitivity to lapatinib, given alone and 
in combination with antioestrogens. In addition, the effects of 
treatment on ERBB2 and ERBB3 downstream signalling were 
measured. As increased ERBB2 activity has been associated with 
resistance to cytotoxic agents in breast cancer, the impact of 
BCAR4 expression on sensitivity to several cytotoxic drugs was 
assessed. The results of our cell line studies showed that ectopic 
expression of BCAR4 results in activation of the ERBB2 signalling 
pathway without overexpression of ERBB2. Therefore, we deter-
mined the incidence of breast cancers expressing BCAR4 and low 
ERBB2 levels, and how this group of patients fares when treated 
with tamoxifen for advanced disease. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Cell lines and culture conditions </p>

<p>ZR-75-1 and MCF7 cell lines were kind gifts of RJB King (ICRF, 
London) and RB Dickson (NCI, Bethesda), respectively. Cell lines 
were initially authenticated by karyotyping, and in November 2011 
using the AmpFlSTR Identifiler Direct PCR Amplification Kit 
(Applied Biosystems International, Nieuwerkerk a/d Ijssel, The 
Netherlands). Cell lines derived from the breast cancer cell line 
ZR-75-1 containing empty vector, or expression constructs with 
BCAR4 (Meijer et al, 2006), BCAR1 (Brinkman et al, 2000), BCAR3 
(Van Agthoven et al, 1998), or EGFR (Van Agthoven et al, 1992), 
and MCF7 breast cancer cells with a construct containing BCAR4 
were cultured as previously described (Van Agthoven et al, 1998). </p>

<p>Drug sensitivity assays </p>

<p>Cells were seeded in 96-well plates at a density of 5000 cells per well 
in 100 ml RPMI 1640 medium (Invitrogen, Breda, The Nether-
lands). After 24 h, serial dilutions of lapatinib (GlaxoSmithKline, 
Stevenage, UK), doxorubicin (Pharmachemie B.V., Haarlem, The 
Netherlands), 5-fluorouracil (EBEWE Pharma, Unterach, Austria), 
methotrexate (Emthexate PF, Pharmachemie B.V.), ifosfamide 
(Holoxan, Baxter B.V., Utrecht, The Netherlands), or paclitaxel 
(Paclitaxel, EBEWE Pharma) were added. All drugs were tested in 
combination with 17 b-oestradiol or 4-hydroxytamoxifen (Sigma-
Aldrich Chemie, Zwijndrecht, the Netherlands) or ICI182,780 
(Zeneca Pharmaceuticals, Macclesfield, UK). To assay the effects of 
oestrogen, cells were seeded at a density of 5000 cells per well in 
100 ml RPMI 1640 without phenol red, supplemented with 6% heat-
inactivated bovine calf serum (Hyclone, Logan, UT, USA). Twenty-
four hours after seeding, 100 ml of medium containing 0.01, 0.1, or 
1 mM lapatinib and increasing concentrations of oestradiol were 
added. WST-1 proliferation assays (Roche Diagnostics, Almere, 
The Netherlands) were performed on ZR-75-1-or MCF7-derived 
cell lines after 5 or 6 days, respectively. IC 50 values were estimated 
by sigmoid inhibitory effect models 107 and 108 as implemented in 
the software programme <rs id="software-0" type="software">Phoenix WinNonLin</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">6.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Pharsight</rs>, 
Mountain View, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Inhibition of gene expression by small interfering 
(si)RNAs </p>

<p>Transfections with HiPerfect (Qiagen, Venlo, The Netherlands) 
were performed according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
Small interfering RNAs were On TARGETplus-SMARTpools, each </p>

<p>consisting of three different oligonucleotides: EGFR (L-003114-00-
0005), ERBB2 (L-003126-00-005), ERBB3 (L-003127-00-0005), and 
ERBB4 (L003128-00-0005; Dharmacon, Perbio-Science, Etten Leur, 
The Netherlands). Final concentration of siRNA was 5 nM. WST-1 
assays were performed after 6 days. </p>

<p>Reverse-phase protein microarrays </p>

<p>Cells cultured in oestradiol-or 4-hydroxytamoxifen-containing 
medium were treated without or with 0.01 or 0.1 mM lapatinib for 
17 h. Cells were rinsed with ice-cold DPBS (Gibco, Invitrogen), and 
lysed with pre-heated (75 1C) extraction buffer consisting of equal 
parts of T-PER (Pierce, Thermo Scientific, Etten-Leur, The 
Netherlands) and Tris-Glycine-SDS Sample Buffer (Invitrogen) 
containing PhosSTOP Phosphatase Inhibitors, Complete Mini 
Protease Inhibitors (Roche Diagnostics), and 4% of b-mercap-
toethanol (Merck, Schiphol-Rijk, The Netherlands). Lysates were 
boiled for 8 min and stored at À 80 1C. Reverse-phase protein 
microarray analysis was performed as described (Van Agthoven 
et al, 2012). A list of antibodies used is presented in Supplementary 
Table 1. </p>

<p>Patient samples </p>

<p>ERBB2 and BCAR4 mRNA levels were measured in 1418 
ER-positive and negative primary breast cancers as described in 
Van Agthoven et al (2009) and Godinho et al (2010). Here we 
assessed the prognostic and predictive values of a combined 
BCAR4 and ERBB2 status. BCAR4 and ERBB2 were determined 
according to the definitions/cut points in the aforementioned 
studies. To determine the association of the combination of BCAR4 
and ERBB2 mRNA levels and PFS, 293 samples from patients with 
ER-positive cancers who received tamoxifen treatment as first-line 
therapy for metastatic disease were analysed. The associations of 
the combined BCAR4 and ERBB2 levels with tumour aggressive-
ness in terms of MFS and OS were determined on 497 ER-positive 
cancers from patients with lymph node-negative disease. None 
received systemic adjuvant therapy. Statistical analyses were 
performed as previously detailed (Godinho et al, 2010). </p>

<p>Quantification of gene expression </p>

<p>RNA isolation of cell lines, complementary DNA synthesis, 
normalisation to reference genes and quantification were per-
formed as described (Sieuwerts et al, 2005; Van Agthoven et al, 
2009; Godinho et al, 2010). TaqMan gene expression assays for 
EGFR-Hs01076091_m1, 
ERBB2-Hs00170433_m1, 
ERBB3-
Hs00176538_m1, 
ERBB4-Hs00171783_m1, 
and 
BCAR4-
Hs00415922_m1 were used according the recommendations of 
the supplier Applied Biosystems International. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Inhibition of ERBB2/3 expression abrogates BCAR4-
induced antioestrogen-resistant proliferation </p>

<p>Previously we have shown that BCAR4-induced tamoxifen-
resistant proliferation of ZR-75-1 cells depends on the presence 
of ERBB2 and ERBB3 (Godinho et al, 2010), while ERBB2 is not 
overexpressed or amplified in this cell line (Hollestelle et al, 2010). 
In MCF7 cells, we investigated whether BCAR4 expression also 
induces ERBB2/3-mediated proliferation. The expression of the 
four ERBB receptors were inhibited with siRNAs, in the absence or 
presence of the pure antioestrogen ICI182,780. In contrast to 
4-hydroxytamoxifen, this antioestrogen fully inhibits growth of 
wild-type MCF7 cells. Inhibition of mRNA transcripts was verified 
by quantitative real-time reverse transcriptase polymerase chain </p>

<p>BCAR4 sensitises breast cancer cells to lapatinib 
MFE Godinho et al </p>

<p>948 </p>

<p>British Journal of Cancer (2012) 107(6), 947 -955 
&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK </p>

<p>Clinical Studies </p>

<p>reaction (RT-PCR, and was more than 70% for EGFR, 88% for 
ERBB2, 66% for ERBB3, and 75% for ERBB4. 
In foetal bovine serum-containing medium, the proliferation 
capacity of MCF7 cells expressing BCAR4 (MCF7/BCAR4) and 
MCF7 vector-containing cells was not affected by the inhibition of 
the expression of the ERBB receptors (Figure 1A and B). Similarly 
to BCAR4 expression in ZR-75-1 cells, MCF7/BCAR4 cells were 
antioestrogen resistant and able to grow in the presence of 
ICI182,780 (Figure 1A). Under this culture condition, the 
inhibition of ERBB2, ERBB3, and ERBB4 expression resulted in 
decreased cell proliferation, indicating that also in MCF7/BCAR4 
cells, ERBB signalling is involved in antioestrogen resistance. 
Growth of MCF7/vector cells was fully inhibited by ICI182,780, and 
inhibition of the ERBB receptor expression had no further effect 
(Figure 1B). </p>

<p>BCAR4 expression increases the sensitivity of cells 
to lapatinib </p>

<p>We speculated that BCAR4 expression may increase the sensitivity 
to the EGFR/ERBB2 tyrosine kinase inhibitor lapatinib. Sensitivity 
to lapatinib was determined in ZR-75-1 cells containing empty 
expression vector (ZR/vector) or BCAR4 (ZR/BCAR4). Cells 
expressing BCAR1 (ZR/BCAR1), BCAR3 (ZR/BCAR3), or EGFR 
(ZR/EGFR) were used for comparison. These latter genes were 
shown to induce tamoxifen resistance by mechanisms independent 
of ERBB2 and ERBB3 (Van Agthoven et al, 1992, 1998; Brinkman </p>

<p>et al, 2000; Meijer et al, 2006). Titration experiments showed that 
cells expressing BCAR4 were the most sensitive to lapatinib in the 
presence of oestradiol (Figure 2A). The IC 50 values for ZR/BCAR4 
cells were 10-to 20-times lower than the IC 50 determined for the 
other cell lines. In the presence of oestradiol and lapatinib 
expression of BCAR1, BCAR3, or EGFR had no impact on 
proliferation, which was similar to the empty vector-containing 
cells. 
Lapatinib sensitivity was also determined in MCF7 cells. In the 
presence of fetal bovine serum alone, the determined IC 50 values 
for MCF7/BCAR4 cells were similar to the IC 50 values determined 
for MCF/vector cells (7-9 mM and 8-12 mM, respectively). This is in 
agreement with the inhibition of the ERBB receptors having no 
effect on proliferation of MCF7/BCAR4 under this culture 
condition (Figure 1). Under these culture conditions, the cells 
apparently depend on the ER pathway for proliferation. </p>

<p>Antioestrogens enhance the sensitivity of BCAR4-
expressing cells to lapatinib </p>

<p>We tested whether antioestrogens could enhance the sensitivity to 
lapatinib. Proliferation of wild-type ZR-75-1 cells is fully inhibited 
by 1 mM 4-hydroxytamoxifen in the culture medium. ZR/BCAR4 
was also the most sensitive cell line to the combination of lapatinib 
and 4-hydroxytamoxifen compared with ZR/BCAR1, ZR/BCAR3, 
or ZR/EGFR cells (Figure 2B). Tamoxifen further increased 
the sensitivity of ZR/BCAR4 cells to lapatinib by approximately </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>Absorbance (AU) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>No siRNA siEGFR 
siERBB2 </p>

<p>siRNAs </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>siERBB3 siERBB4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>Absorbance (AU) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>No siRNA siEGFR 
siERBB2 
siRNAs </p>

<p>siERBB3 siERBB4 </p>

<p>Figure 1 Knockdown of ERBB receptors reduces proliferation of 
antioestrogen-resistant MCF7/BCAR4 cells. MCF7/BCAR4 (A) and 
MCF7/vector (B) cells were cultured in the absence (open bars) or 
presence (closed bars) of the antioestrogen ICI182,780. The inhibition of 
ERBB receptors by specific siRNAs was measured with a proliferation assay. 
Average of five replicates and SDs are shown. Significance was determined 
by the Mann-Whitney U-test. *Po0.05, compared with cells cultured 
without siRNAs. Abbreviation: AU ¼ arbitrary units. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0.0001 0.001 
0.01 
0.1 
Lapatinib ( M) </p>

<p>1 
10 
100 </p>

<p>0.0001 0.001 
0.01 
0.1 
Lapatinib ( M) </p>

<p>1 
1 0 
100 </p>

<p>40 
Relative growth (%) </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 
Relative growth (%) </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Figure 2 BCAR4 sensitises ZR-75-1 cells to lapatinib. ZR/vector control 
(m), ZR/BCAR4 (J), ZR/BCAR1 (B), ZR/BCAR3 (D) or ZR/EGFR cells 
(&amp;) were plated in oestradiol-containing medium (A), or 4-hydroxyta-
moxifen-containing medium (B) with increasing doses of lapatinib as 
indicated. Concentrations of lapatinib (X axis) are presented on a 
logarithmic scale. Results are expressed as a percentage of maximal 
growth as measured with a WST-1 proliferation assay. Average of five 
replicates and SDs are presented. </p>

<p>BCAR4 sensitises breast cancer cells to lapatinib 
MFE Godinho et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK 
British Journal of Cancer (2012) 107(6), 947 -955 </p>

<p>Clinical Studies </p>

<p>three-fold. A very similar lapatinib dose-response curve was 
obtained with the presence of ICI182,780 (data not shown). 
ZR-75-1 cells with forced expression of the EGFR are tamoxifen 
resistant and oestrogen-independent in the presence of 10 ng/ml of 
EGF (Van Agthoven et al, 1992). Compared with oestradiol-
stimulated cultures, ZR/EGFR cells were six-fold more sensitive 
than controls to the combination of lapatinib, 4-hydroxytamox-
ifen, and EGF. ZR/BCAR1 and ZR/BCAR3 cells showed similar 
lapatinib dose-response curves in oestradiol and 4-hydroxyta-
moxifen-containing medium, approximately 35-fold less sensitive 
than ZR/BCAR4 cells. Growth of ZR/vector cells was fully inhibited 
by 4-hydroxytamoxifen, therefore the sensitivity to lapatinib under 
this culture condition is not informative (data not shown). 
ICI182,780 increased the sensitivity of MCF7/BCAR4 cells to 
lapatinib by approximately 10-fold. </p>

<p>Lapatinib inhibits ERBB2 signalling in BCAR4-expressing 
cells </p>

<p>Reverse-phase protein microarray analysis was used to determine 
the effects of lapatinib treatment on the levels of 68 total or 
phosphorylated proteins having a role in survival, motility, death, 
growth, metabolism, and inflammation (Supplementary Table 2). 
To circumvent the problem that changes in phosphorylation were 
solely due to toxicity, cells were cultured in medium without 
lapatinib or with low doses of 0.01 or 0.1 mM lapatinib for 17 h. 
These concentrations resulted in limited growth inhibition after 5 
days in culture (Figure 2A and B). Lapatinib treatment had no 
prominent effects on protein phosphorylation in ZR/vector, ZR/ 
BCAR1, ZR/BCAR3, or ZR/EGFR cells, while clear changes were 
observed for ZR/BCAR4 cells (Figure 3A). We quantified the effects 
on the phosphorylation of its target, the ERBB2 receptor, the 
ERBB3 receptor, and several downstream mediators. ZR/BCAR4 
cells do not express EGFR (Van Agthoven et al, 2012), therefore 
changes caused by the addition of lapatinib cannot be attributed to 
this pathway. 
As observed before (Van Agthoven et al, 2012) in oestradiol-
containing medium, phosphorylation of ERBB2 (Tyr1248) was 
12-fold higher in ZR/BCAR4 cells compared with the phosphor-
ylation levels in control cells (Figure 3B). Under this culture 
condition, 0.01 mM lapatinib completely inhibited ERBB2 phos-
phorylation. The combination of 4-hydroxytamoxifen and 0.1 mM 
lapatinib resulted in a two-fold decrease in ERBB2 phosphoryla-
tion (Figure 3B). Lapatinib exerted no effect on ERBB2 phosphor-
ylation in the other cell lines. 
ZR/BCAR4 cells showed the highest levels of phosphorylated 
ERBB3 (Tyr1289; Figure 3C; Van Agthoven et al, 2012). Lapatinib 
treatment in oestradiol-containing cultures resulted in moderately 
decreased ERBB3 phosphorylation, but had no effect in the 
presence of 4-hydroxytamoxifen. In the other cell lines, lapatinib 
did not modulate ERBB3 phosphorylation (Figure 3C). Phosphor-
ylation of several downstream mediators, such as AKT (Ser473), 
FAK (Tyr576-577), SHC (Tyr317), STAT5 (Tyr694), and STAT6 
(Tyr349), was higher in ZR/BCAR4 cells compared with control 
cell lines (Figure 3D-H). Similar to the effect on ERBB2 
phosphorylation, in oestradiol-containing medium, 0.01 mM lapa-
tinib inhibited phosphorylation of these downstream mediators. In 
medium containing 4-hydroxytamoxifen, a higher dose of 
lapatinib was needed to reduce phosphorylation levels. In the 
remaining cell lines, lapatinib treatment had little or no effect on 
the phosphorylation of these signalling molecules. </p>

<p>BCAR4-expressing cells alternate between signalling 
pathways to survive </p>

<p>Proliferation of ZR/BCAR4 cells was more sensitive to the 
combination of lapatinib and 4-hydroxytamoxifen than to the 
combination of lapatinib and oestradiol (Figure 2). Moreover, </p>

<p>phosphorylation of ERBB2 and downstream targets is inhibited in 
the presence of oestradiol and lapatinib. The addition of 
4-hydroxytamoxifen increased ERBB2 levels and downstream 
signalling. Therefore, we hypothesised that if the ERBB2 signalling 
pathway is inhibited by lapatinib, BCAR4-expressing cells may 
switch to the ER pathway to sustain survival and proliferation. To 
test this, we analysed the effects of lapatinib treatment on 
oestradiol dependence in short-term cultures. While ZR/BCAR4 
cells showed maximal proliferation capacity in the absence of 
oestradiol (Figure 4A), ZR/vector cells required supplementation 
of 10-100 pM of oestradiol. Figure 4B shows that in the presence of 
0.01 or 0.1 mM lapatinib, oestrogen dependence of ZR/vector cells 
remained unchanged. In contrast, proliferation of ZR/BCAR4 cells 
was less inhibited by lapatinib in the presence of more than 10 pM 
of oestradiol (Figure 4A). These results indicate that ZR/BCAR4 
cells can evade the growth inhibitory effects of lapatinib in part 
through ER signalling. </p>

<p>BCAR4 and chemotherapy </p>

<p>As several studies indicate an association between ERBB2 
overexpression and resistance to chemotherapy (reviewed in Tan 
and Yu, 2007), and BCAR4 expression enhances ERBB2 signalling, 
we determined the sensitivity of BCAR4-expressing cells to drugs 
currently included in common breast cancer treatment regimens. 
To investigate alterations in drug sensitivity, cells were cultured in 
oestradiol-or 4-hydroxytamoxifen-containing medium and 
increasing concentrations of the different chemotherapeutics. 
As a typical example, a dose-response curve of ZR/vector, 
ZR/BCAR4, ZR/BCAR1, ZR/BCAR3, and ZR/EGFR cells to 
methotrexate is shown in Supplementary Figure S1. No major 
differences in sensitivity to the drug between the different cell 
lines, either in the presence of oestradiol (Supplementary Figure 
S2A) or 4-hydroxytamoxifen (Supplementary Figure S2B), were 
observed. Similar results were obtained for ifosfamide, 
5-fluorouracil, doxorubicin, and paclitaxel, indicating no changes 
in sensitivity of conventional drugs due to the expression of 
BCAR4. Moreover, no major differences were found between the 
IC 50 values determined for all the BCAR cell lines and for the 
control cells (Supplementary Table 3), with exception of ZR/ 
BCAR1 cells being less sensitive to doxorubicin, and ZR/EGFR cells 
being less sensitive to doxorubicin and 5-fluorouracil. </p>

<p>BCAR4 mRNA levels may define a subgroup of patients 
who are eligible for treatment with established ERBB2 
inhibitors </p>

<p>At present, only patients with breast cancers overexpressing 
ERBB2 or with gene amplification are eligible for ERBB2-targeted 
therapies. Our functional in vitro studies show that BCAR4 
activates the ERBB2 pathway yielding resistance against anti-
oestrogens in cell lines not overexpressing ERBB2. This could 
imply that BCAR4 expression identifies an additional subgroup of 
patients with activated ERBB2, but lacking ERBB2 overexpression. 
To investigate the prevalence of this group, both BCAR4 and 
ERBB2 mRNA status were determined in a large cohort of primary 
breast cancers previously measured by RT-PCR (Van Agthoven 
et al, 2009; Godinho et al, 2010). BCAR4 was detected in 392 out of 
1418 (27.6%) samples (Figure 5A). High expression of ERBB2 was 
detected in 233 specimens (16.4%). Among the BCAR4-positive 
samples, 80 had high and 312 had low expression of ERBB2, 
indicating the existence of a group of patients (22%) with BCAR4-
positive cancers and low expression of ERBB2. </p>

<p>Clinical relevance of combined BCAR4 and ERBB2 status </p>

<p>BCAR4 and ERBB2 have been found to be independently predictive 
for tamoxifen resistance in recurrent breast cancer. While ERBB2 </p>

<p>BCAR4 sensitises breast cancer cells to lapatinib 
MFE Godinho et al </p>



<p>British Journal of Cancer (2012) 107(6), 947 -955 
&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK </p>

<p>Clinical Studies </p>

<p>was not associated with the natural course of the disease in 
untreated lymph node-negative ER-positive patients with primary 
breast cancer, patients with BCAR4-positive tumours had a shorter 
MFS and OS compared with BCAR4-negative tumours (Van 
Agthoven et al, 2009; Godinho et al, 2010). 
Here we assessed the associations of combined BCAR4 and 
ERBB2 status and clinical tamoxifen resistance in recurrent breast 
cancer. mRNA levels of 293 ER-positive primary cancers of 
patients treated with tamoxifen as first-line therapy for metastatic 
disease were analysed for association with the length of PFS. The 
individual clinical associations of BCAR4 and ERBB2 mRNA levels 
for PFS (Table 1) were in agreement with our previous data (Van 
Agthoven et al, 2009; Godinho et al, 2010). Univariate Cox 
regression analysis of the combined mRNA status showed that 
patients with BCAR4-positive tumours with low levels of ERBB2 
had a shorter PFS than patients with BCAR4-negative tumours 
with low ERBB2 levels (HR ¼ 1.64, P ¼ 0.001; Table 1). Patients </p>

<p>with high ERBB2 levels had the shortest PFS, regardless of BCAR4 
status (Table 1). The Kaplan-Meier analysis visualises the different 
outcomes of the patients stratified according to the combined 
BCAR4 and ERBB2 status (Figure 5B). In the multivariate analysis, 
the power of the combination of BCAR4 expression and low levels 
of ERBB2 was independent of the traditional predictive factors for 
PFS (BCAR4-negative/ERBB2-low vs BCAR4-positive/ERBB2-low, 
HR ¼ 1.50, P ¼ 0.011; Table 1). 
To assess the associations of combined BCAR4 and ERBB2 levels 
and tumour aggressiveness, we analysed mRNA status in 497 
primary breast cancers. All patients had ER-positive, lymph node-
negative cancer and did not receive adjuvant systemic therapy, 
allowing the analysis of the natural course of the disease. The 
mRNA levels were analysed for association with the end points 
MFS and OS. Metastasis-free survival in patients with BCAR4-
positive/ERBB2-low tumours was not significantly different from 
patients with BCAR4-negative/ERBB2-low tumours. Patients with </p>

<p>E 
T 
E 
T 
E 
T + E </p>

<p>BCL2 (T56) 
PKAC (T197) 
ERK1/2 (T202/Y204) 
SAPK/J (T183/Y185) 
EIF4EBP1 (S65) 
AKT (S473) 
FOXO1/3 (T24/32) 
CREB (S133) 
CRAF (S338) 
NOS3 (S116) 
PRKAA1 (S485) </p>

<p>SMAD2 (S465/467) </p>

<p>MTOR (S2481) </p>

<p>EIF4G (S1108) 
CASP3cl 
Total ERBB4 </p>

<p>Total ERBB2 
CASP7cl </p>

<p>AKT (T308) </p>

<p>STAT5 (Y694) 
ERBB2 (Y1248) 
SHC (Y317) 
ERBB3 (Y1289) 
STAT6 (Y641) 
FAK (Y576/577) 
CCND1 
CCNA1 
CCNE1 
Total ESR1 
NFKB (S536) 
PKCA (S657) </p>

<p>BCAR3 
BCAR4 
EGFR Vector </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>7 
Phosphorylation </p>

<p>intensity (103) </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 
Phosphorylation </p>

<p>intensity (103) 
10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 
Phosphorylation </p>

<p>intensity (103) 
4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Vector BCAR4 BCAR3 
BCAR4 BCAR3 
EGFR 
EGFR 
Vector BCAR4 BCAR3 
BCAR4 BCAR3 
EGFR 
EGFR </p>

<p>pERBB3 </p>

<p>pERBB2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>E 
T 
T + </p>

<p>pAKT </p>

<p>pAKT </p>

<p>pSHC </p>

<p>pSTAT6 </p>

<p>pSTAT5 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>E 
T 
T + </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>14 
Phosphorylation </p>

<p>intensity (103) </p>

<p>Phosphorylation </p>

<p>intensity (103) </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Figure 3 Lapatinib treatment inhibits ERBB2 and ERBB3 signalling in ZR/BCAR4 cells. (A) Molecular network analysis of ZR-75-1-derived antioestrogen-
resistant cell lines (horizontal axis) treated with lapatinib. Lysates were analysed with reverse-phase protein microarrays. The heatmap presents the different 
total and phosphorylated proteins (n ¼ 31; vertical axis) that showed at least two-fold difference with the vector control cultured in the presence of 
oestradiol (colour version in Supplementary Figure 1 and protein data in Supplementary Table 1). Higher relative levels are represented in white; lower levels 
in black. Cells were cultured with oestradiol (E) or 4-hydroxytamoxifen (T), or T and EGF (T þ ) and treated for 17 h, without, or with 0.01 or 0.1 mM 
lapatinib (triangles represent increasing lapatinib concentrations, from left to right). (B-H) Effects of lapatinib treatment on ERBB2 and ERBB3 signalling. 
Phosphorylation intensity (Y axis) of ERBB2 (B), ERBB3 (C), AKT (D), FAK (E), SHC (F), STAT5 (G), and STAT6 (H) in the different cell lines (horizontal 
axis) is presented. Results of two independently derived pools of transduced cells were averaged. Phosphorylation intensity values for antibody staining were 
negative control subtracted and normalised for total protein concentration. An average of three measurements is presented. SD values o2% across the 
replicates, the three bars for each cell line represent the three different conditions (no or 0.01 or 0.1 mM lapatinib). </p>

<p>BCAR4 sensitises breast cancer cells to lapatinib 
MFE Godinho et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK 
British Journal of Cancer (2012) 107(6), 947 -955 </p>

<p>Clinical Studies </p>

<p>BCAR4-positive/ERBB2-high tumours had the shortest MFS 
(multivariate HR ¼ 1.95, P ¼ 0.026; Supplementary Table 4). Ana-
lysis for OS indicated that patients with BCAR4-positive/ERBB2-
low tumours had a significantly shorter OS than patients with 
BCAR4-negative/ERBB2-low tumours. This difference was inde-
pendent of the traditional prognostic factors (multivariate 
HR ¼ 1.54, P ¼ 0.021). Patients with BCAR4-positive/ERBB2-high 
tumours had the shortest OS from all groups (multivariate 
HR ¼ 2.25, P ¼ 0.004; Supplementary Table 4). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study we show that BCAR4 expression sensitises two breast 
cancer models to lapatinib. As BCAR4 expression in cell lines did 
not change the sensitivity to different chemotherapeutic agents, the 
increased sensitivity to lapatinib is not due to a general mechanism 
of drug resistance. The combination of lapatinib and tamoxifen 
treatment is more effective at inhibiting breast cancer cell growth 
than lapatinib alone (Chu et al, 2005; Leary et al, 2010). Also in our 
BCAR4-expressing cell models, the combination of lapatinib and 
antioestrogens was more potent in inhibiting cell growth than 
lapatinib alone; indicating that blocking the ERBB2 pathway with 
lapatinib re-sensitises BCAR4-expressing cells to antioestrogens. 
Breast tumours have been shown to alternate between ER and 
ERBB2 signalling, and inhibition of one of the pathways 
reactivated the other (Gutierrez et al, 2005; Lipton et al, 2005; 
Massarweh and Schiff, 2006; Munzone et al, 2006; Creighton et al, </p>

<p>2008). It has also has been reported that increased ER signalling 
occurs in lapatinib-treated breast cancer cell lines (Xia et al, 2006; 
Leary et al, 2010). In the presence of lapatinib and increasing levels 
of oestradiol, ZR/BCAR4 cells exhibited comparable cell growth 
kinetics as oestrogen-dependent parental cells (Figure 5A). In 
culture medium containing lapatinib without oestradiol growth of 
ZR/BCAR4 cells was strongly inhibited. This suggests that BCAR4 
cells use the ER signalling pathway to survive in the presence of 
low concentrations of lapatinib. Likewise, MCF7/BCAR4 cells 
cultured in medium without antioestrogens use the ER pathway to </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>1E-16 
1E-14 
1E-12 </p>

<p>Oestradiol (M) </p>

<p>1E-10 
1E-08 </p>

<p>40 
Relative growth (%) </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>1E-16 
1E-14 
1E-12 </p>

<p>Oestradiol (M) </p>

<p>1E-10 
1E-08 </p>

<p>40 
Relative growth (%) </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Figure 4 Lapatinib-treated cells utilise ER signalling for survival. ZR/ 
BCAR4 (A) and ZR/vector (B) cells were plated in the absence (K), 
0.01 mM lapatinib (J), 0.1 ('), or 1 mM (&amp;) of lapatinib and different 
concentrations of oestradiol, as indicated. Results are expressed as a 
percentage of maximal growth (cultures with 1 nM oestradiol but without 
lapatinib), as measured with a WST-1 proliferation assay. Average of three 
replicates and SD values are presented. </p>

<p>873 
(61.6%) </p>

<p>BCAR4 neg/ERBB2 low </p>

<p>BCAR4 pos/ERBB2 
low </p>

<p>Group 1: BCAR4 neg/ERBB2 low 
100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 
Progression-free survival (%) </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
0 
1 2 
Time (months) 
No. of patients at risk </p>

<p>Group 1: </p>

<p>Group 2: </p>

<p>Group 3: </p>

<p>191 </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>93 </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>44 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>24 
36 </p>

<p>Group 2: BCAR4 pos/ERBB2 low </p>

<p>Group 3: ERBB2 high </p>

<p>BCAR4 pos/ERBB2 high </p>

<p>BCAR4 neg/ERBB2 high </p>

<p>153 
(10.8%) 
80 
(5.6%) </p>

<p>312 
(22.0%) </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Figure 5 Clinical relevance of combined BCAR4 and ERBB2 status. 
Expression of BCAR4 and ERBB2 mRNA levels was measured in a cohort of 
primary breast carcinomas. Patients were stratified according to the 
combined BCAR4 and ERBB2 status as indicated. BCAR4 was divided in 
negative (no call), and positive low and high by the mean. There is no 
relation observed between BCAR4 and ERBB2 expression. (A) Prevalence 
of breast tumours expressing BCAR4 and low levels of ERBB2. Number of 
tumours and percentages are shown for each group. (B) Progression-free 
survival of patients with ER-positive breast cancer who received first-line 
tamoxifen monotherapy for recurrent breast cancer. Patients with ERBB2-
high tumours were grouped irrespective of their BCAR4 status. The 
patients at-risk at 12-month intervals are indicated. Abbreviations: 
neg ¼ negative, pos ¼ positive. </p>

<p>BCAR4 sensitises breast cancer cells to lapatinib 
MFE Godinho et al </p>



<p>British Journal of Cancer (2012) 107(6), 947 -955 
&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK </p>

<p>Clinical Studies </p>

<p>proliferate. These cells are antioestrogen-resistant, but similar to 
ZR/BCAR4 cells, proliferation is reduced when ERBB2 or ERBB3 
are knocked-down. This indicates that MCF7/BCAR4 cells are also 
dependent on the ERBB2 and ERBB3 pathway to overcome the 
inhibitory effects of antioestrogens. Apparently, BCAR4 expression 
enables cells to alternate between signalling pathways to escape the 
inhibition of one of them. 
The mechanism by which BCAR4 activates the ERBB2 and 
ERBB3 receptors is still unknown, but several hypotheses can be 
considered. BCAR4 may encode a very small protein, and its 
predicted anchor signal and two transmembrane domains suggest 
that the protein is located at cell membranes. Because of its 
possible location and interaction with ERBB receptors, there is a 
possibility that BCAR4 may be a target for ADAM proteins, which 
cleave ERBB ligands (Mochizuki, 2007). This way, cleaved BCAR4 
would be free to bind ERBB3, activating ERBB2 and ERBB3 
signalling. BCAR4 may interact with ERBB2 through the cell 
membrane, similar to MUC4 (Carraway et al, 2001). A mechanism 
similar to nucleolin, which interacts intracellular and activates the 
ERBB receptors (Di Segni et al, 2008). The hypothesis that BCAR4 
may be a secreted protein can also not be excluded. Another 
possibility is that the BCAR4 protein interacts with and stabilises 
the ERBB2/ERBB3 dimer, or interferes with the internalisation 
and/or intracellular transport of the receptors. It has been shown 
that mucins can influence receptor trafficking and localisation, and 
because of that, can modulate receptor tyrosine kinase signalling 
(Funes et al, 2006). 
Lapatinib treatment has been shown to prevent ubiquitination 
and degradation of ERBB2, resulting in the accumulation of 
inactive receptors at the plasma membrane (Scaltriti et al, 2009). 
Exposure of ZR/BCAR4 cells to lapatinib resulted in modestly 
increased ERBB2 protein levels. Addition of 4-hydroxytamoxifen 
to ZR/BCAR4 cells further increased ERBB2 levels, in agreement 
with earlier observations (Van Agthoven et al, 1994; Bates and 
Hurst, 1997). In other studies, lapatinib was shown to inhibit 
phosphorylation of ERBB2 downstream kinases in ERBB2-over-
expressing breast cancer (Xia et al, 2002, 2004; Chu et al, 2005; 
Spector et al, 2005; Konecny et al, 2006). In our model, activity of 
ERBB2, ERBB3, and the downstream mediators studied are efficiently 
inhibited in medium containing oestradiol and a low dose of lapatinib. 
However, cell proliferation was only partially inhibited, again 
suggesting an escape route via the ER signalling pathway. 
EGFR and ERBB2 overexpression is well documented as being 
involved in tamoxifen resistance (Riggins et al, 2007; Musgrove 
and Sutherland, 2009; Van Agthoven et al, 2009). EGFR is not </p>

<p>involved in our cell models of endocrine resistance because 
oestrogen-dependent ZR-75-1 and MCF7 cells are devoid of 
detectable EGFR expression (Van Agthoven et al, 1992), and 
ERBB2 is present but not overexpressed nor amplified (Hollestelle 
et al, 2010). Introduction of BCAR4 activates ERBB2 signalling and 
induces resistance against antioestrogens (Van Agthoven et al, 
2012). This suggests that not only ERBB2 overexpression or 
amplification is associated with tamoxifen resistance, but that the 
mere activation of the receptor may also have a role in the process. 
This is in agreement with earlier findings that other models of 
endocrine resistance, LTED and LTAM cells, showed increased 
activation of ERBB2 and downstream signalling (Leary et al, 2010). 
In addition, it has been hypothesised that moderate, as well as low 
ERBB2 levels, may generate a strong mitogenic signal when the 
receptor is activated by dimerisation with EGFR or ERBB3 (Frogne 
et al, 2009). 
In ZR/BCAR4 cells cultured with 4-hydroxytamoxifen, the IC 50 
for lapatinib was approximately 1 mM. This concentration is 
achieved in the plasma of patients treated with the recommended 
daily dose of 1.5 mg (Burris et al, 2005), emphasising the potential 
feasibility of lapatinib as treatment for antioestrogen resistant 
breast cancer due to BCAR4 expression. Activated ERBB2 has been 
found in ER-positive tumours classified as negative for ERBB2 
expression according to the standard criteria (Frogne et al, 2009). 
Moreover, emerging evidence shows that some tumours scoring 
negative for ERBB2 expression benefit from trastuzumab therapy 
(Paik et al, 2008; Esteva et al, 2010). At present, treatment with 
ERBB2-targeted therapies is restricted to patients with breast 
cancers overexpressing ERBB2. Until now, there are no biomarkers 
to select patients with ER-positive/ERBB2-negative tumours, which 
are dependent on ERBB2 signalling (Mayer and Arteaga, 2010), 
and may benefit from ERBB2-targeted therapies. Although it has 
been shown that the combination of lapatinib and an aromatase 
inhibitor is not beneficial for ERBB2-negative, endocrine sensitive 
or endocrine naive metastatic breast cancer patients (Johnston 
et al, 2009), this remains to be established for BCAR4-positive 
tumours. 
We have shown that co-expression of BCAR4 and low level of 
ERBB2 occurs frequently, and that these patients have less benefit 
from tamoxifen treatment. Although our observations do not 
prove that the ERBB2 signalling pathway is activated in these 
tumours, our experimental data suggest that this group might 
benefit from the combination of lapatinib and antioestrogens. The 
focus of our future studies will be to determine the phosphoryla-
tion status of ERBB2 and downstream mediators on micro tissue </p>

<p>Table 1 Associations of combined mRNA levels of BCAR4 and ERBB2 in primary breast tumours with progression-free survival </p>

<p>Univariate analysis 
Multivariate analysis </p>

<p>PFS 
No. 
HR 
95% CI 
P 
HR 
95% CI 
P </p>

<p>ERBB2 
High vs low 
37/256 
1.86 
1.31-2.65 
0.001 
1.90 
1.28-2.80 
0.001 </p>

<p>BCAR4 
Pos vs neg 
78/215 
1.57 
1.20-2.05 
0.001 
1.46 
1.10-1.93 
0.009 </p>

<p>Combined addition 
BCAR4 neg/ERBB2 low 
191 
1 
1 
BCAR4 pos/ERBB2 low 
65 
1.64 
1.23-2.20 
0.001 
1.50 
1.10-2.04 
0.011 
BCAR4 neg/ERBB2 high 
24 
2.17 
1.40-3.36 
0.001 
2.09 
1.32-3.29 
0.002 
BCAR4 pos/ERBB2 high 
13 
2.03 
1.15-3.58 
0.014 
2.02 
1.09-3.73 
0.026 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: PFS ¼ progression-free survival; HR ¼ hazard ratio; CI ¼ confidence interval; pos ¼ positive; neg ¼ negative. To study a possible independent relationship of the 
genes studied with PFS, Cox multivariate regression analyses were performed, including the base model comprising the traditional predictive factors: age, menopausal status, 
disease-free interval, dominant site of relapse, and ESR1 and PGR mRNA levels. Clinicopathological and biological factors of ERa-positive metastatic breast cancers are presented 
in Supplementary Table 5. </p>

<p> 
MFE Godinho et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK 
British Journal of Cancer (2012) 107(6), 947 -955 </p>

<p>Clinical Studies </p>

<p>arrays of a large cohort of breast cancers with known follow-up. 
Patients with primary tumours with high levels of ERBB2 had the 
shortest PFS, irrespective of their BCAR4 levels. On the basis of our 
results it will now be highly relevant to establish whether these 
BCAR4-positive/ERBB2-low cancers have indeed an activated 
ERBB2 signalling pathway. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We are thankful to GlaxoSmithKline for providing Lapatinib, to 
Walter Loos for performing the IC 50 calculations, Johan Boender 
for performing the siRNA transfections and Leendert Looijenga for </p>

<p>critical reading of the manuscript. This study was funded by 
Erasmus MC MRACE grant 2007. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>JDW: ownership interest and paid consultant for Theranostics 
Health, LLC. EFP: ownership interest, member of advisory board 
and unpaid consultant for Theranostics Health, LLC. The 
remaining authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies the paper on British 
Journal of Cancer website (http://www.nature.com/bjc) </p>



<p> 
MFE Godinho et al </p>



<p>British Journal of Cancer (2012) 107(6), 947 -955 
&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK </p>

<p>Clinical Studies </p>



<p>BCAR4 sensitises breast cancer cells to lapatinib 
MFE Godinho et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK 
British Journal of Cancer (2012) 107(6), 947 -955 </p>

<p>Clinical Studies </p>

</text></tei>