<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3029787" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>The resistant dextrin NUTRIOSE </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, developed from starch, is expected to act as a prebiotic. The aim of this study was to determine the effects 
of NUTRIOSE 
® on cecal parameters, short-chain fatty acid (SCFA) concentrations, and fecal excretion in rats. In an initial experiment, twenty-four 
male Fischer F344 rats were randomly assigned to one of the following four treatments for 14 days: G0 (control diet), G2.5 (control diet + 2.5% 
of dextrin), G5 (control diet + 5% of dextrin), and G10 (control diet + 10% of dextrin). After 14 days, total cecal weight, cecal content, and cecal 
wall weight were significantly increased in G5 and Ga second trial based on a similar 
design, eighteen male Fischer F344 rats were treated with a control diet supplemented with 5% of dextrin or 5% of fructo-oligosaccharide. The 
results obtained with NUTRIOSE 
® were similar to those obtained with the fructo-oligosaccharide. In a third experiment, two groups of 5 Fischer 
F344 rats were orally treated with 100 and 1,000 mg/kg NUTRIOSE </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, respectively, and from 18% to 25% of the dextrin was excreted in the 
feces. The results of these three studies show that the consumption of NUTRIOSE </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, by its effects on total cecal weight, cecal content, cecal wall 
weight, pH, and SCFA production, could induce healthy benefits since these effects are reported to be prebiotic effects. </p>

<p>Prebiotics are defined as non-digestible food ingredients that 
beneficially affect the health of the host by selectively stimulating 
the growth and activity of specific species of bacteria in the gut 
[1]. Fibre-rich diets are considered to be protective against weight 
gain, cardiovascular disease, and colon cancer, and have 
beneficial effects on the human gastrointestinal tract [2-5]. In 
the second part of the last century, fibre intake decreased due 
to the evolution of food habits and is currently relatively low 
as compared to dietary recommendations (ANC "Apports 
Nutritionnels Conseillés" for the French population or recommended 
nutrient intakes). One way to increase fibre intake without 
increasing energy intake, is to replace some full-energy nutrients 
by low energy constituents, such as dietary fibres. Among them, 
and according to the new definition of dietary fibres published 
by Prosky 2001 [6], non digestible oligosaccharides (fructo-
oligosaccharides, galactosaccharides, etc.) and resistant dextrins 
are two different types of fibres. The presence of their specific 
linkages (β, α1-2, α1-3...) does not permit the hydrolysis of these 
indigestible dextrins in the small intestine of mammals, and their 
energy content can be available for colonic flora. In the colon, 
they are fermented by intestinal bacteria. This bacterial fermen-</p>

<p>tation in the colon leads to the production of short chain fatty 
acids (SCFA), mainly acetate, propionate, butyrate, and lactate 
[7-9]. A great proportion (80-85%) of these SCFA is absorbed 
by the mucosa of the colon and the other part is either evacuated 
in the feces or is used for growth and multiplication of bacteria. 
These indigestible dextrins can, as dietary fibres, have an action 
on fat and carbohydrate metabolism [7,10], on transit time [11], 
on mineral bioavailability [12], and on the densities of 
bifidobacteria and lactobacilli in the gastrointestinal tract [13]. 
Among the soluble fibres, some have already been largely 
studied, like fructo-oligosaccharides (FOS), oligofructoses, and 
xylooligosaccharides (XOS) [13-18]. The major disadvantage of 
these oligosaccharides is that as other indigestible carbohydrates, 
they induce digestible complaints often "incompatible" with their 
low energy substituent doses. There is a need to develop new 
dietary fibres that can be well tolerated at high doses. This is 
the case of the branched NUTRIOSE 
® dextrin, which is </p>

<p>well-tolerated up to 45 grams per day [19,20]. Contrary to other 
dextrins, it is rich in α1-6, α1-2, and α1-3 linkages. Therefore, 
this dextrin is partly hydrolyzed and absorbed in the small 
intestine (15%). Large amounts of the ingested product reach 
the colon and are fermented by the gut microflora (75%). 
The purpose of this rat study was to evaluate the nutritional </p>

<p> § Corresponding Author: Laetitia Guerin-Deremaux, Tel. 33-3-21-63-36-00, Fax. 33-3-21-63-94-10, Email. laetitia.guerin-deremaux@roquette.com 
Received: May 12, 2010, Revised: October 19, 2010, Accepted: October 21, 2010 
ⓒ2010 The Korean Nutrition Society and the Korean Society of Community Nutrition 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Laetitia Guerin-Deremaux et al. </p>

<p>471 </p>

<p>Component 
Value </p>

<p>Protein (g/100 g) 
14.5 to 18.0 </p>

<p>Carbohydrate (g/100 g) 
57.0 to 63.0 </p>

<p>Fat (g/100 g) 
1.7 to 3.7 </p>

<p>Cellulose (g/100 g) 
3.0 to 5.5 </p>

<p>Minerals (g/100 g) </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>4.0 to 6.0 </p>

<p>Calcium (mg/kg) 
6,000-10,000 </p>

<p>Phosphorus (mg/kg) 
4,500-7,000 </p>

<p>Sodium (mg/kg) 
1,500-3,500 </p>

<p>Potassium (mg/kg) 
5,500-8,500 </p>

<p>Manganese (mg/kg) 
40-100 </p>

<p>Copper (mg/kg) 
10-35 </p>

<p>Vitamins </p>

<p>Vitamin A (IU/kg) 
4,000-11,000 </p>

<p>Vitamin D3 (IU/kg) 
≤ 3,000 </p>

<p>Moisture (g/100 g) 
9.0 to 14.0 </p>

<p>Gross energy (MJ/kg) 
13.6 </p>

<p>1) Minerals: calcium, phosphorus, sodium, potassium, manganese, copper </p>

<p>Table 1. Composition of the basal AO4C diet </p>

<p>Reducing sugars (%) 
2.3 </p>

<p>Molecular weight (Mn) (g/Mol) 
2,600 </p>

<p>Molecular weight (Mw) (g/Mol) 
5,000 </p>

<p>1,2 linkages (%) 
13 </p>

<p>1,3 linkages (%) 
14 </p>

<p>1,4 linkages (%) 
41 </p>

<p>1,6 linkages (%) 
32 </p>

<p>Table 2. Chemical analysis of NUTRIOSE 
® (indicative values) </p>

<p>effects of different doses of NUTRIOSE </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>. The results are focused 
on cecal parameters like cecal weight, cecal wet content, wall 
weight, pH, and SCFA concentrations. Moreover, the proportion 
of excreted NUTRIOSE 
® in the feces was also determined in </p>

<p>the present study. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>Rats were given free access to feed and fresh potable water. 
Prior to the experiment, the rats were fed a standard non-purified 
AO4C diet (SAFE, Villemoisson sur Orge, France, see composi-
tion in Table 1) and housed two rats per cage in Makrolon cages 
(37.5×23.5×16 cm) in an environmentally controlled room (21℃ 
± 2, 50% ± 10) with a 12 h light/dark cycle. The animal use 
and experiments were performed according to the procedures 
described in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory 
Animals (NIH, 1996) and in-house Standard Operating 
Procedures. The centre had a statement from the National 
Ministry of Agriculture to conduct preclinical research. </p>

<p>Test substance </p>

<p>NUTRIOSE 
® (ROQUETTE Frères, Lestrem, France) is a </p>

<p>glucose polysaccharide produced from maize, wheat, or other 
edible starch heated at high temperature and adjusted to a low 
moisture level in the presence of an acid catalyst. The dextrin 
obtained is purified with activated carbon and demineralised by 
exchange resins. Afterwards, the product is subjected to 
chromatographic partitioning that removes glucose and lower 
molecular weight oligosaccharides. As described in Table 2, the 
final product, NUTRIOSE </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, is a mixture of glucose polymers 
with a fairly narrow range of molecular weight (number average 
Mol. Wt., Mw = 2,600 g/Mol; weight average Mol. Wt., Mw = 
5,000 g/Mol). The degree of polymerization is 12-25. In 
comparison, starch may contain up to a million glucose units. 
During the heating step, hydrolysis and repolymerization occur. 
In addition to the typical starch α-1,4 and α-1,6 glucosidic 
linkages, the recombination can result in other specific glucosidic 
linkages that are not found in starch. Mass spectrometry is used 
following methylation of NUTRIOSE 
® to determine the bond </p>

<p>distribution, which can include both linear and branched linkages: 
(α-1,6 and / or β-1,6), (α-1,2 and / or β-1,2), (α-1,3 and / or β 
-1,2), and β-1,4. This point confers to the resistance of 
NUTRIOSE 
® against the action of endogenous glucidolytic </p>

<p>enzymes and permits classification of the product among soluble 
dietary fibres with a total fibre content of nearly 85.0%. 
ACTILIGHT 
® (BEGHIN-MEIJI, Marckolsheim, France) is a </p>

<p>fructo-oligosaccharide (FOS) obtained industrially from the 
action of fructosyl furanosidase (from Aspergillus niger) on 
sucrose. ACTILIGHT 
® is considered a soluble dietary fibre with </p>

<p>prebiotic properties [4]. It was therefore chosen in this study as 
the reference product. </p>

<p>Experimental design </p>

<p>In the first trial, 24 male Fischer F344 rats, aged 5 weeks and 
weighing approximately 120 g at receipt, were supplied by 
CHARLES RIVER (L'Arbresle, France). They were randomly 
assigned to one of four dietary treatments (6 rats / treatment) and 
housed two rats per cage in Makrolon cages. The dextrin was 
added to the non-purified AO4C diet (composition in Table 1) 
as follows: G0: control diet; G2.5: control diet + 2.5% (w/w) 
dextrin; G5: control diet + 5% (w/w) dextrin; G10: control diet 
+ 10% (w/w) dextrin. The duration of the experiment was 14 
days. Food and water consumption and body weights were 
recorded weekly. The animals were individually observed each 
day. Stool consistency was recorded daily. After this 14-day 
period, cecal effects were evaluated. 
In a second trial, 18 male Fischer F344 rats, aged 5 weeks 
and weighing approximately 120 g at receipt were supplied by 
CHARLES RIVER (L'Arbresle, France). They were randomly 
assigned to one of three dietary treatments (6 rats / treatment) 
and housed two rats per cage in Makrolon cages. Dextrin was 
added to the non-purified AO4C diet (composition in Table 1) </p>



<p>Effects of a fibre on colonic fermentation in rats </p>

<p>Treatment 
P 
G0 
G2.5 
G5 
G10 </p>

<p>Food intake (g/animal/day) </p>

<p>1 
st week 
20.33 ± 1.00 19.43 ± 0.60 20.03 ± 1.21 19.60 ± 0.36 NS </p>

<p>2 
nd week 
23.40 ± 1.28 21.40 ± 0.40 23.13 ± 0.91 22.43 ± 0.25 NS </p>

<p>Weight (g) </p>

<p>Basal 
152 ± 9 
151 ± 5 
151 ± 10 
149 ± 8 
NS </p>

<p>1 
st week 
200 ± 12 
197 ± 6 
199 ± 12 
196 ± 8 
NS </p>

<p>2 
nd week 
236 ± 10 
231 ± 3 
240 ± 9 
234 ± 7 
NS </p>

<p>Weight gain 
(g/day) </p>

<p>6.02 ± 0.43 5.65 ± 0.36 6.33 ± 0.44 6.11 ± 0.37 NS </p>

<p>Food efficiency ratio </p>

<p>1 
st week 
0.33 ± 0.03 0.33 ± 0.02 0.34 ± 0.04 0.34 ± 0.02 NS </p>

<p>2 
nd week 
0.22 ± 0.04 0.23 ± 0.03 0.26 ± 0.04 0.25 ± 0.02 NS </p>

<p>The values are the mean ± SEM, n = 6. Data were analyzed using Kruskall Wallis 
test for non parametric data to test the dose effect. NS: not significantly different </p>

<p>(P &gt; 0.05 ; global P-value (Kruskal-Wallis)). </p>

<p>Table 3. Effects of NUTRIOSE 
® on diet intake, food efficiency ratio, body weight, 
and weight gain </p>

<p>as follows: G0: control diet; GD5: control diet + 5% (w/w) 
dextrin; GA5: control diet + 5% (w/w) ACTILIGHT </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>. The 
dietary supplementation duration was 14 days. Food and water 
consumption, and body weights were recorded weekly. The 
animals were individually observed each day. Stool consistency 
was recorded daily. After this 14-day period, cecal effects were 
evaluated. 
In the third experiment, 15 male Fischer F344 rats, aged 5 
weeks and weighing approximately 150 g at reception, were 
supplied by CHARLES RIVER (L'Arbresle, France). They were 
randomly assigned to one of three dietary treatments (5 rats / 
treatment) and individually housed in metabolic cages. The 
control group (GO) was treated orally by gastric intubation with 
a single dose of water at 10 mL/kg of body weight. The second 
group (G1) was treated orally with a single dose of a 10 mg 
per mL dextrin solution at 10 mL/kg of body weight, which 
corresponds to 100 mg/kg of body weight. The third group (G2) 
was treated orally with a single dose of a 100 mg per mL dextrin 
solution at 10 mL/kg of body weight, which corresponds to 1,000 
mg/kg of body weight. The rat feces was collected for 48 hours 
to determine the fecal excretion of NUTRIOSE </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Collection of samples </p>

<p>Regarding the first and second experiments, after a 14-day 
treatment and an 18-h starvation period, the rats were sacrificed 
by CO2 asphyxia. A ventral midline incision was made and the 
caecum was removed. Immediately after removal, the caeca with 
contents were weighed. The cecal wall was weighed and the cecal 
contents were collected. The pH value was measured using a 
CG-825 Schott pH-meter, equipped with a microelectrode. 
Immediately there after, the caecum contents were mixed with 
a preservative solution (2.5 ml per g caecum content) consisting 
of phosphoric acid (0.63% v/v) and mercury chloride (0.091% 
w/v). One gram of cecal content was adjusted to 25 mL and 
centrifuged at 25,000 × g for 20 min. The supernatants were 
colorimetrically analyzed for acetate and lactate (Roche, Meylan, 
France), and for propionate and butyrate via gas chromatography 
using a VARIAN 3400 gas chromatograph and a capillary 
column for free fatty acids (DBFFAP, J&amp;W Scientific FOLSOM, 
CA; 30 m × 0.32 mm i.d. film thickness: 0.25 micron). Helium 
was used as the carrier gas with a pressure of 10 psi with a 
split flow rate of 50 mL/minute. The oven temperature was 140℃ 
and increased by 2℃/minute up to 170℃. The detector 
temperature was 240℃ and injector temperature was 245℃. The 
employed detector was a flame ionization detector. 
At the end of the third experiment, rat feces was collected 
for 24 and 48 h and weighed (wet weight). It were freeze-dried 
for 48 h (dry weight) and finally ground. The NUTRIOSE </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>residue was assessed by determining the fecal branched residual 
glucose. To do so, soluble carbohydrates were extracted from 
the feces using a 0.1% (w/v) chloramphenicol solution. Free 
glucose was determined enzymatically in the supernatant using </p>

<p>a glucose oxidase kit (Roche, Meylan, France). Total glucose 
(polymerized plus free) was determined after acid hydrolysis 
(HCl 4N) for 45 minutes at 100℃ using the same reagent kit 
as the one used for free glucose. The NUTRIOSE 
® residue was </p>

<p>estimated by deducting the fecal free glucose from the total fecal 
glucose. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The data were analysed using Kruskall Wallis tests for non 
parametric data to test the dose effect. When global analysis was 
significant (P &lt; 0.05), the Kolmogorov Smirnov test was used 
to compare the different treated groups to the control group. The 
tests were carried out on <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> 
® software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 8</rs>. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Effects of NUTRIOSE 
® on diet intake and body weight </p>

<p>From experiment 1, the mean dietary preparation intakes 
ranged from 19.4 ± 0.6 to 20.3 ± 1.0 g/animal/day during week 
1 (Table 3). During week 2, the animals consumed from 21.4 
± 0.4 to 23.4 ± 1.3 g/animal/day. There were no differences 
between the groups (Table 3). The mean tested product 
consumptions were 0.51, 1.08, and 2.10 g/animal/day for groups 
G2.5, G5, and G10, respectively. Slightly softer feces was 
observed in the 10% treated animals, but at this level, as in the 
other group, no diarrhea was observed. Animal behaviour and 
external aspects were similar in the treated animals compared 
to the controls. 
There was no difference in body weight evolution (Table 3). 
At the beginning of the experiment the animals weighed from 
149 ± 8 g (G10) to 152 ± 9 g (G0), and 14 days later from 231 
± 3 g (G2.5) to 240 ± 9 g (G5). No significant differences were </p>

<p>Laetitia Guerin-Deremaux et al. </p>



<p>Treatment 
P -value </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>G0 
G2.5 
G5 
G10 </p>

<p>Total cecal weight (g) 
5.70 ± 0.56 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>5.89 ± 0.61 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>7.74 ± 0.73 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>9.39 ± 1.12 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>Cecal content (g) 
4.70 ± 0.53 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>4.90 ± 0.57 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>6.55 ± 0.68 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>8.09 ± 1.08 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>Wall weight (g) 
1.00 ± 0.08 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.99 ± 0.07 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.19 ± 0.08 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>1.30 ± 0.12 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>pH 
6.58 ± 0.13 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>6.58 ± 0.13 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>6.39 ± 0.19 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>6.01 ± 0.18 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Acetate (mg/caecum content) 
17.19 ± 1.65 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>17.88 ± 4.42 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>24.45 ± 4.72 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>32.36 ± 3.42 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>Propionate (mg/caecum content) 
2.15 ± 0.53 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>3.37 ± 0.77 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>4.17 ± 1.45 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>5.48 ± 0.84 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Butyrate (mg/caecum content) 
16.70 ± 3.03 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>17.38 ± 2.84 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>22.48 ± 3.68 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>24.55 ± 2.61 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Total SCFA (mg/caecum content) 
36.04 ± 4.32 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>38.63 ± 7.02 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>51.10 ± 8.04 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>62.39 ± 3.16 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>The values are the mean ± SEM, n = 6. Data were analysed using Kruskall Wallis test for non parametric data to test the dose effect. When global analysis was significant 
(P &lt; 0.05), the Kolmogorov Smirnov test was used to compare the different treated groups to the control group. </p>

<p>a,b,c,d significantly different from G0 (a : NS; b : P &lt; 0.05; c : P &lt; 0.01; d : P &lt; 0.001) 
1) global P-value (Kruskal-Wallis) * &lt; 0.05, ** &lt; 0.01, *** &lt; 0.001. </p>

<p>Table 4. Effects of NUTRIOSE 
® on cecal parameters and SCFA production </p>

<p>Treatment 
P-value </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>G0 
GD5 
GA5 </p>

<p>Total cecal weight (g) 
5.07 ± 0.53 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>6.39 ± 0.47 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>7.14 ± 1.73 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>Cecal content (g) 
4.40 ± 0.55 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>5.51 ± 0.41 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>6.19 ± 1.69 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>Wall weight (g) 
0.67 ± 0.06 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.88 ± 0.15 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.95 ± 0.19 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>pH 
6.89 ± 0.21 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>6.41 ± 0.12 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>6.58 ± 0.25 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>Acetate 
(mg/caecum content) </p>

<p>16.23 ± 2.86 
a 21.59 ± 2.27 
c 21.62 ± 5.86 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>Propionate 
(mg/caecum content) </p>

<p>2.17 ± 0.69 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>3.63 ± 1.10 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>3.33 ± 0.87 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>Butyrate 
(mg/caecum content) </p>

<p>12.56 ± 2.49 
a 17.45 ± 3.01 
b 16.30 ± 3.85 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>Total SCFA 
(mg/caecum content) </p>

<p>30.01 ± 4.17 
a 42.67 ± 5.77 
c 41.25 ± 7.94 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>The values are the mean ± SEM, n = 6. Data were analyzed using Kruskall Wallis 
test for non parametric data to test the dose effect. </p>

<p>a,b,c significantly different from G0 (a : NS; b : P &lt; 0.05; c : P &lt; 0.01) 
1) P-value between GD5 and GA5 (Kruskal-Wallis): NS (not significantly different) </p>

<p>Table 5. Effects of 5% NUTRIOSE 
® and 5% ACTILIGHT 
® on cecal parameters 
and SCFA production </p>

<p>noted between the groups. There was also no difference in water 
consumption (from 19.3 ± 0.6 to 21.5 ± 1.4 g/animal/d; data not 
shown). </p>

<p>Effects of NUTRIOSE 
® on cecal parameters </p>

<p>The results for cecal weight, cecal contents, cecal walls, and 
cecal pH, obtained from experiment 1, are presented in Table 
4. There was a dose-effect relationship between the dose of the 
product consumed and the cecal effects. There were significant 
differences at the doses of 5% and 10% in the feed for total 
cecal weight, cecal content, and cecal wall weight. In group G10, 
these 3 parameters were, on average, 65%, 72%, and 31% higher, 
respectively, than in G0 group (Table 4). 
The cecal pH fell 2.9% in the 5% group compared to the G0 
group (6.39 ± 0.19 versus 6.58 ± 0.13). This difference was not 
significant, whereas at 10% dextrin in the feed (Table 4), the 
decrease was significantly different (8.7% decrease; P &lt; 0.01). </p>

<p>Effects of NUTRIOSE 
® on cecal short chain fatty acid and lactic </p>

<p>acid concentrations </p>

<p>The cecal SCFA concentrations are presented in Table 4 
(experiment 1). The cecal concentrations of acetate were 42% 
and 88% higher in the groups fed additions of 5% and 10% 
of NUTRIOSE </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, respectively, compared to rats fed the control 
diet [G5: 24.45 mg/caecum content ± 4.72; G10: 32.36 mg/ 
caecum content ± 3.42 with P &lt; 0.01 and P &lt; 0.001, respectively, 
compared to the control group (G0: 17.19 mg/caecum content 
± 1.65)]. For propionate, the smallest dose of 2.5% NUTRIOSE </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>induced a 57% significant increase in propionate concentration 
compared to the control group (3.37 mg/caecum ± 0.77 versus 
2.15 mg/caecum ± 0.53; P &lt; 0.05). At 5% and 10%, the dextrin 
led to increases of 94% (4.17 mg/caecum ± 1.45 versus 2.15 
mg/caecum ± 0.53; P &lt; 0.05) and 155% (5.48 mg/caecum ± 0.84 
versus 2.15 mg/caecum ± 0.53; P &lt; 0.001), respectively. Finally, 
in the 5% group, there was a statistically significant increase 
of 35% in butyrate concentration (22.48 mg/caecum ± 3.68 versus </p>

<p>16.70 mg/caecum ± 3.03; P &lt; 0.05). This was confirmed in the 
10% group with a 47% increase (24.55 mg/caecum ± 2.61 versus 
16.70 mg/caecum ± 3.03; P &lt; 0.001) in butyrate concentration 
(Table 4). 
When expressed in mg/caecum (Table 4), total short chain fatty 
acids were increased from the 5% dose. This augmentation was 
from 42% (P &lt; 0.01) to 73% (P &lt; 0.001) for the 5% and 10% 
groups, respectively. The results for lactic acid are not presented 
because there was no production of this acid by any group. </p>

<p>Effects of 5% NUTRIOSE 
® compared to 5% ACTILIGHT 
® on </p>

<p>cecal parameters and short chain fatty acid production </p>

<p>The results for cecal weights, cecal contents, cecal wall, and 
cecal pH in experiment 2 are presented in Table 5. Both products 
induced significant increases of cecal weight, cecal contents, and 
wall weight (Table 5). Inversely, pH values were decreased in 
both groups treated by 5% NUTRIOSE 
® and 5% ACTILIGHT </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>. 
For SCFA, propionate and total SCFA were significantly </p>



<p>Effects of a fibre on colonic fermentation in rats </p>

<p>G0 
G1 
100 mg/kg BW </p>

<p>G2 
1,000 mg/kg BW </p>

<p>NUTRIOSE 
® intake (mg) 
0 
25.12 ± 0.24 
253.4 ± 6.59 </p>

<p>Fecal branched residual 
glucose (mg) </p>

<p>12.33 ± 2.48 
18.78 ± 3.66 
57.29 ± 15.82 </p>

<p>% fecal glucose 
-
25% 
18% </p>

<p>"% fecal glucose" represents: 
[fecal branched residual glucose G1 or G2-fecal branched residual glucose G0] 
NUTRIOSE 
® intake </p>

<p>Table 6. Effects of 100 mg and 1,000 mg NUTRIOSE 
® oral administration on 
fecal excretion </p>

<p>increased in both groups. Acetate and butyrate were significantly 
different after treatment with 5% NUTRIOSE </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>. After treatment 
with 5% ACTILIGHT </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, acetate and butyrate increased but the 
differences were not significantly different. </p>

<p>Fecal excretion of NUTRIOSE </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>After treatment with 5% NUTRIOSE </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, fecal branched residual 
glucose values were increased (Table 6). The variations in fecal 
glucose between the control and treated groups were 6.45 mg 
and 44.96 mg for 100 mg/kg bwt and 1,000 mg/kg bwt 
NUTRIOSE 
® intake, respectively. The percentages of glucose </p>

<p>excretion in the rats for both tested doses were rather similar: 
25% and 18% for 100 mg/kg bwt and 1,000 mg/kg bwt 
NUTRIOSE </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, respectively. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Carbohydrates that reach the large intestine, so-called low 
digestible carbohydrates (LDC), induce laxative effects 
essentially due to the stimulation of peristalsis [9] and to the 
osmotic power of LDC. FOS and inulin exhibit laxative effects 
at relatively small dosages in animals and in human [11,21]. In 
our study, animals in group G10 consumed up to 10 g/kg 
animal/day of dextrin and only soft feces was observed. At this 
level, as for the other groups, no sign of diarrhea was observed. 
NUTRIOSE 
® at all tested doses did not modify the appearance </p>

<p>of the feces compared to the control group, suggesting no effects 
on peristalsis and secretion in the colon. There was no difference 
in body weight evolution. At the beginning of the experiment, 
the animals ranged from 149 g (G10) to 152 g (G0) and 14 
days later from 231 g (G2.5) to 240 g (G5). No significant 
differences were noted between the groups. Thus, this dextrin 
did not increase dietary intake. Several studies have demonstrated 
that low digestible carbohydrates were fermented by bacteria and 
fecal recovery was found to be zero [1]. Such is the case for 
fructo-oligosaccharides. In contrast, for our study, fecal recovery 
was about 20% of the ingested dose, demonstrating the 
incomplete digestion of this dextrin in rats and resulting in a 
low caloric value. After 2 weeks of NUTRIOSE 
® consumption, </p>

<p>no physiopathologic damage was observed, whatever the dose </p>

<p>as compared to the control group. Thus, the tolerance of the 
product was excellent. Similar levels of excretion were found 
in humans fed this dextrin [22]. Taken together, the results 
indicate that the product was well tolerated, and more particularly 
in the gastrointestinal tract. These results are in good accordance 
with the digestive tolerance and fecal excretion of this dextrin 
in humans [20,22,23]. 
In our study, the dextrin tested is a very good substrate for 
cecal fermentation. The highly fermentable product leads to an 
increase in cecal weight due to the production of bacterial mass 
in the caecum [13]. The minimum dose to induce cecal 
enlargement seems to be between 2.5% and 5%. Effectively, there 
was a high increase in absolute cecal weight (more than 35%) 
in the 5% treated animals, whereas the increase observed in the 
2.5% group (3%) was not statistically significant. The increase 
of cecal wall may be attributed to an increase in intestinal mucosa 
thickness as a consequence of the large amount of SCFA 
produced and as an adaptive process to highly fermentable 
carbohydrates. Indeed, SCFA production induces the proliferation 
of cecal cells. It was demonstrated that FOS and XOS increased 
cecal weight and cecal wall weight compared to a diet without 
fibres [13]. All the three major short chain fatty acids (acetate, 
propionate, and butyrate) were increased by NUTRIOSE </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>. Based 
on the data, it also appears that the minimal dose to induce a 
positive effect is between 2.5 and 5%. High levels of SCFA, 
particularly of butyrate, in the lower part of the gastrointestinal 
tract are important for a healthy large intestine. Butyrate, known 
to be the preferred energy substrate for colonocytes, was 
increased to a large extent in this study and may be correlated 
with cecal wall augmentation. Indeed, in addition to the trophic 
effect of butyrate on the mucosa, it is an important source of 
energy for the colonic epithelium and can regulate both the 
growth and the differentiation of colonic cells. The fact that at 
the 2.5% dose there was a statistically significant increase in 
propionate production suggests that this dextrin is a high 
propiogenic oligosaccharide. The effect of a diet containing 
propionate was found to be associated with lower fasting 
glycemia in rats [10]. An in vitro study on rat hepatocytes showed 
that propionate can decrease gluconeogenesis, while on the other 
hand stimulate glycolysis [7]. Another study in humans [24] 
showed that the addition of propionate to bread inhibited the 
activity of amylase. Thus, in the present study, the observed 
increase of propionate production allows one to expect an affect 
of this low digestible carbohydrate on glycemia. The acetate 
increase observed in this type of experiment is often related to 
fermentable carbohydrates [13,25-27]. Lactic acid accumulation 
was not noted during the study. This would indicate that the 
process of fermentation was not overdosed even at the highest 
dose of 10%. 
Similar effects on cecal parameters and SCFA production were 
observed with the reference FOS ACTILIGHT </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>. In conclusion, 
NUTRIOSE 
® was as efficient as ACTILIGHT 
® to promote the </p>

<p>production of cecal SCFA. </p>

<p>Laetitia Guerin-Deremaux et al. </p>



<p>In rats, fermentation is essentially localized in the caecum. The 
caecum has the highest level of SCFA available for absorption/ 
utilization. As a result of fermentation, pH decreases. This 
phenomenon was indicated as a statistical decrease in the 5% 
treated group in the second experiment and in the 10% treated 
group in the first experiment. An acidic cecal pH is probably 
caused by greater levels of total SCFA production, but it can 
also be caused by a decrease of nitrogen compounds, which are 
quite basic [20]. This increased acid production can prevent the 
colonization of potentially pathogenic microorganisms [28]. This 
phenomenon can also be associated with the proliferation of 
bifidobacteria and lactobacilli in the GI tract. Indeed, the 
lowering of pH and the production of metabolites stimulate the 
growth of prebiotic bacteria and the promotion of bacteriostatic 
effects against potentially harmful bacteria like enterobacteria 
and clostridia [3]. Vermorel et al. [29] showed that NUTRIOSE </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>can improve magnesium and calcium absorption, and their 
retention, in humans. The authors indicated that this phenomenon 
could be linked to the decrease of pH of gut content as 
encountered in our study. Prebiotics are not only nutrients for 
bacteria, but can also induce environmental changes such as 
changes in luminal pH, mineral absorption [30], trophicity, and 
improvement of the immune system [31]. 
In conclusion, NUTRIOSE 
® dextrin increased SCFA production </p>

<p>in the caecum of rats. Butyrate can provide a source of energy 
for the large bowel; suggesting that this indirect energy source 
may play a role in mucosal cell differentiation. An increase in 
SCFA may be due to an increase in the colonic bacteria that 
are able to ferment NUTRIOSE 
® residues. This possible effect </p>

<p>on microflora may prevent the colonization of potential 
pathogens and enhance the immune system. Further studies of 
the effects of this dextrin on intestinal microflora composition 
and the immune system are necessary to sustain their beneficial 
health effects. </p>





<p>Effects of a fibre on colonic fermentation in rats </p>



</text></tei>