<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3702283" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Cytokines such as interleukins are known to be involved in the development of neuropathic pain through activation of neuroglia. 
However, the role of chemokine (C-C motif) ligand 1 (CCL-1), a well-characterized chemokine secreted by activated T cells, in the 
nociceptive transmission remains unclear. We found that CCL-1 was upregulated in the spinal dorsal horn after partial sciatic 
nerve ligation. Therefore, we examined actions of recombinant CCL-1 on behavioural pain score, synaptic transmission, glial cell 
function and cytokine production in the spinal dorsal horn. Here we show that CCL-1 is one of the key mediators involved in the 
development of neuropathic pain. Expression of CCL-1 mRNA was mainly detected in the ipsilateral dorsal root ganglion, and the 
expression of specific CCL-1 receptor CCR-8 was upregulated in the superficial dorsal horn. Increased expression of CCR-8 was 
observed not only in neurons but also in microglia and astrocytes in the ipsilateral side. Recombinant CCL-1 injected 
intrathecally (i.t.) to naive mice induced allodynia, which was prevented by the supplemental addition of N-methyl-D-aspartate 
(NMDA) receptor antagonist, MK-801. Patch-clamp recordings from spinal cord slices revealed that application of CCL-1 
transiently enhanced excitatory synaptic transmission in the substantia gelatinosa (lamina II). In the long term, i.t. injection of 
CCL-1 induced phosphorylation of NMDA receptor subunit, NR1 and NR2B, in the spinal cord. Injection of CCL-1 also 
upregulated mRNA level of glial cell markers and proinflammatory cytokines (IL-1b, TNF-a and IL-6). The tactile allodynia induced 
by nerve ligation was attenuated by prophylactic and chronic administration of neutralizing antibody against CCL-1 and by 
knocking down of CCR-8. Our results indicate that CCL-1 is one of the key molecules in pathogenesis, and CCL-1/CCR-8 
signaling system can be a potential target for drug development in the treatment for neuropathic pain. 
There are many reports that nerve injury triggers reactive 
changes in peripheral immune system and in neuroglial cells 
in both peripheral and central nervous systems. 
4,11,12 In the 
periphery, activation of Schwann cells and resident macro-
phages recruit hematogenous immune cells, which subse-
quently invade the injured nerves. 
12-14 In the spinal dorsal 
horn receiving the injured sensory afferents, activation of 
microglia is commonly associated with early establishment 
stages of neuropathic pain. 
2,15,16 Cytokines such as inter-
leukin-1b (IL-1b), tumour necrosis factor-a (TNF-a) and IL-6, 
which originate from the peripheral injured area or from 
activated neuroglial cells in the spinal cord, are known to alter 
synaptic transmission in the dorsal horn. </p>

<p>13,14 </p>

<p>Chemokines and their receptors are widely expressed in 
immune cells and in the nervous system. 
17,18 Recent studies 
have shown that chemokines C-C motif ligand 2 (CCL-2) and 
CX3CL-1 induce tactile allodynia (when non-painful innoxious 
stimuli become painful) through activation of spinal cord 
microglia. 
17,19 These reactive changes mediated through cyto-
kines and chemokines develop in parallel with tactile allodynia, 
the latter being the main symptom of neuropathic pain. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>CCL-1 (also known as thymus-derived chemotactic 
agent 3) is one of the well-characterized chemokines and is 
classified into the same CC chemokine group as CCL-2. CCL-
1 is secreted by activated T cell, mast cells and endothelial </p>

<p>cells and has important role as the chemoattractant for 
neutrophils and monocytes. 
21 Although effects of CCL-1 on 
the immune cells are well characterized, the roles of CCL-1 in 
the central nervous system, and especially in the develop-
ment of neuropathic pain, remain unclear. In this report, we 
found that CCL-1 is involved in the development of tactile 
allodynia following peripheral nerve injury through enhance-
ment of spinal nociceptive transmission and activation of glial 
cells with subsequent release of cytokines. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Expression of CCL-1 in the spinal cord in neuropathic 
mice. We first examined the development of allodynia in a 
partial sciatic nerve ligation (PSNL) model. Mice showed a 
significant increase in withdrawal response to mechanical 
stimulus in the ipsilateral hind-paw (tactile allodynia) at 
7 days after PSNL. The pain score in the ipsilateral hind-paw 
was 7.5±0.8 (n ¼ 8), while contralateral hind-paw was 
1.9 ± 0.6 (n ¼ 8) (Figure 1a). In parallel, the protein level 
of CCL-1 significantly increased 7 days after PSNL in the 
ipsilateral spinal cord (relative protein level, 0.14±0.01; 
n ¼ 4) compared with the contralateral spinal cord (relative 
protein level, 0.10 ± 0.01; n ¼ 4) (Figure 1b). On the other 
hand, levels of other cytokines, TNF-a, interferon-g and IL-1b </p>

<p>Figure 1 Increase in CCL-1 in the spinal cord after nerve ligation. (a) Mice showed tactile allodynia in the ipsilateral hind-paw at 7 days after PSNL. Data represent 
mean±S.E. (n ¼ 8). **Po0.01: versus before ligation contralateral (two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Tukey-Kramer test). (b) Cytokine arrays on spinal 
cord samples at 7 days after nerve ligation. The relative values of cytokine and chemokine proteins were normalized to positive control values in the array Kit. Data represent 
mean ± S.E. (n ¼ 4). **Po0.01: versus contralateral (two-tailed Student's paired t-test). (c) Comparing CCL-1 mRNA between spinal cord and DRG. Data represent 
mean ± S.E. (n ¼ 4). *Po0.05: versus spinal cord (two-tailed Student's paired t-test). (d) Time course of CCL-1 mRNA levels in the DRG after nerve ligation was evaluated by 
quantitative reverse transcriptase (RT)-PCR. (e) Time course of CCL-1 mRNA levels in the spinal cord after nerve ligation was evaluated by quantitative RT-PCR. 
Data represent mean ± S.E. (d, n ¼ 4; e, n ¼ 6). **Po0.01, *Po0.05: versus before ligation (one-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni test) </p>

<p>CCL-1 contributes to neuropathic pain 
N Akimoto et al </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>were not significantly changed 7 days after nerve ligation 
(Figure 1b). </p>

<p>Time course of CCL-1 mRNA expression in the spinal 
cord and dorsal root ganglion (DRG) after nerve ligation. 
First, we compared CCL-1 mRNA between the spinal cord 
and DRG before nerve ligation. CCL-1 mRNA was expressed 
in DRG (12428 ± 3606.7%; n ¼ 4) more than the spinal 
cord (Figure 1c). Next, we examined the expression of 
CCL-1 mRNA in a PSNL model. CCL-1 mRNA level 
significantly increased at 3 h, 1 and 3 days (194.4 ± 19.9%, 
147.3±17.3%, 142.0±2.0%, respectively; n ¼ 4) after nerve 
ligation in the DRG (Figure 1d). In the spinal cord, CCL-1 
mRNA level significantly increased at 3 h after nerve ligation 
(361.1±74.5%; n ¼ 6; Figure 1e). </p>

<p>Time course of CCR-8 protein expression in the spinal 
cord. CCR-8 is a specific receptor for CCL-1. 
22 Nerve ligation 
increased protein levels of CCR-8 in the ipsilateral dorsal 
spinal cord 6 h after surgery (Figures 2a and c). The relative 
protein level of CCR-8 compared with b-actin also showed 
significant increase at 6 h after ligation (relative protein level, 
0.9 ± 0.1; n ¼ 9; Figure 2b). We performed co-staining of CCR-
8 with neuronal or glial markers 6 h after nerve ligation in the 
spinal cord. Increased expression of CCR-8 was observed not </p>

<p>only in neurons but also in microglia and astrocytes in the 
ipsilateral side (Figure 3). In addition, we showed that CCR-8 
was expressed not only on glutamatergic neurons but also on 
GABAergic neuronal fibers in primary cultured neurons 
(Supplementary Figure S1). </p>

<p>Injection of a neutralizing antibody against CCL-1 
inhibited nerve ligation-induced allodynia. To examine 
the prophylactic effect of blocking CCL-1 against tactile 
allodynia, a neutralizing antibody against CCL-1 (anti-CCL-1, 
2.5, 25 and 50 ng) was injected i.t. 10 min before nerve ligation 
and for 6 consecutive days after nerve ligation. The injection of 
50 ng anti-CCL-1 antibody significantly reduced tactile allodynia 
in 3, 5 and 7 days after nerve ligation (pain score at each time 
point, 5.2±0.8, 6.0±0.8 and 6.0±0.9; n ¼ 15, respectively; 
Figure 4a). The inhibition by prophylactic administration of anti-
CCL-1 antibody was concentration-dependent (Figure 4b). In 
order to test the effects of post-chronic administration, daily 
injection of anti-CCL-1 antibody was started 3 days after nerve 
ligation and continued for 7 days. Unlike prophylactic admin-
istration, the tactile allodynia was not blocked once it was 
induced by nerve ligation (Figure 4c). </p>

<p>Injection of CCL-1 induced allodynia, which was 
attenuated by NMDAR inhibitor. We next examined the </p>

<p>Figure 2 Expression of CCR-8 in the spinal cord following nerve ligation. (a and b) Protein levels of CCR-8, a selective receptor for CCL-1, in the spinal cord at different 
time points after nerve ligation were evaluated by western blotting. C, contralateral;I, ipsilateral. Data represent mean ± S.E. (b, n ¼ 9). **Po0.01: versus ipsilateral before 
ligation, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>Po0.05: versus contralateral (two-way analysis of variance followed by Tukey-Kramer tests). (c) Immunostaining for CCR-8 in contralateral (Contra-) and ipsilateral 
(Ipsi-) spinal cord before and 6 h after nerve ligation. Bars ¼ 200 mm (upper panels), 100 mm (lower panels) </p>

<p>CCL-1 contributes to neuropathic pain 
N Akimoto et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Figure 3 CCR-8 expression in neurons, microglia and astrocytes after nerve ligation. (a) Immunostaining for NeuN (red) and CCR-8 (green) 6 h after nerve ligation in the 
spinal cord. Bars ¼ 10 mm. (b) Immunostaining for Iba1 (red) and CCR-8 (green) 6 h after nerve ligation in the spinal cord. Bars ¼ 10 mm. (c) Immunostaining for GFAP (red) 
and CCR-8 (green) 6 h after nerve ligation in the spinal cord. Bars ¼ 10 mm </p>

<p>CCL-1 contributes to neuropathic pain 
N Akimoto et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>effect of an intrathecal (i.t.) injection of CCL-1 on nociceptive 
behaviour. The effect of CCL-1 was dose-and time-dependent; 
25 ng CCL-1 significantly increased the pain score after 10, 20, 
30, 40 and 80 min (pain score at each time point, 8.6 ± 1.2, 
11.3±1, 11.4±1.7, 11.6±0.9, 9.2±1.4 and 7.4±0.9, respec-
tively; n ¼ 8; Figure 5a). The pain score 20 min after i.t. injection 
of different concentration of CCL-1 is presented in Figure 5b. 
NMDARs are critical in pathogenesis of allodynia. 
5,6 In our 
model, the allodynia induced by i.t. injection of CCL-1 (25 ng) 
was dose-dependently blocked by co-injection of MK-801, a 
non-competitive use-dependent NMDAR antagonist, at con-
centration of 125, 250 and 500 pM (Figure 5c). MK-801 
showed dose-dependent inhibition of allodynia induced by 
CCL-1 at 10, 20, 30, 40 and 50 min after injection (pain score at 
each time point, 3.0±0.7, 4.6±0.7, 6.4±1.0, 4.3±0.8, 
4.0±0.7, respectively; n ¼ 8; Figure 5c). The IC 50 for MK-801 
effects was 354 pM (n ¼ 8) when determined in 20 min after i.t. 
injection of CCL-1 (Figure 5d), suggesting the role of NMDA-
mediated transmission in allodynia. </p>

<p>CCL-1 increased glutamate release in the superficial 
dorsal horn of the spinal cord. We examined the action of 
CCL-1 on excitatory synaptic transmission in the superficial 
spinal dorsal horn, in the substantia gelatinosa (lamina II), by 
using whole-cell patch-clamp recordings from mouse spinal 
cord slices. When holding the cell at À 70 mV, substantia 
gelatinosa neurons exhibited spontaneous excitatory </p>

<p>postsynaptic currents (sEPSCs) with average frequency 
of 7.1±1.0 Hz and amplitude of 11.4±0.9 pA (n ¼ 9). In four 
of the nine cells examined, bath application of CCL-1 
(50 ng/ml) for 60-90 s enhanced the excitatory synaptic 
transmission as shown in Figure 5e; this action lasted for 
more than 3-5 min. In the CCL-1-sensitive cells, the 
frequency and amplitude of sEPSCs in the presence of 
CCL-1 were 174 ± 11% and 110 ± 6.3% of controls, respec-
tively (Figure 5e). In the presence of TTX (1 mM), such 
excitatory effect of CCL-1 was also detected in two out of the 
six cells tested (data not shown). </p>

<p>NMDAR phosphorylation after injection of CCL-1 in the 
spinal cord. We examined whether CCL-1 induced phos-
phorylation of NR1 and NR2B subunits of NMDAR in the 
spinal cord using western blotting (Figures 6a and b). CCL-1 
affected phosphorylation levels of NR1 subunit at Ser896 
(p-NR1) in the spinal cord at 3 h, 1 and 3 days after injection 
of CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.) (relative protein levels, 2.7±0.75, 
4.5 ± 1.16, 3.5 ± 0.88, respectively; n ¼ 3; Figure 6c). After 
immunoblotting, the membrane was stripped and reprobed 
with anti-NR1 antibody (Figure 6a). However, CCL-1 had no 
effect on the increase of NR1 protein level (Figure 6d). The 
protein level of p-NR1/NR1 was increased at 1, 3 h, 1 and 3 
days after injection of CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.) (relative protein 
levels, 5.5 ± 0.69, 5.5 ± 1.32, 9.8 ± 1.84, 7.3 ± 1.46, respec-
tively; n ¼ 3; Figure 6e). CCL-1 induced phosphorylation of </p>

<p>Figure 4 Inhibition of ligation-induced allodynia by neutralizing antibody against CCL-1. (a and c) Effects of CCL-1 neutralizing antibody (anti-CCL-1) on allodynia induced 
by nerve ligation. CCL-1 neutralizing antibody (anti-CCL-1) or vehicle (control serum) was first injected 10 min before nerve ligation (a) or 3 days after nerve ligation 
(c), followed by daily administration (shown by arrows). Scores were measured using a von Frey filament (vehicle, n ¼ 17; each concentration of anti-CCL-1, n ¼ 15). 
0 ¼ before ligation. (b) Concentration-dependent inhibition of allodynia by anti-CCL-1 antibody 7 days after nerve ligation by the method of prophylactic and chronic 
administration. Each data represent mean±S.E. *Po0.05: versus vehicle (two-way analysis of variance followed by Tukey-Kramer test) </p>

<p>CCL-1 contributes to neuropathic pain 
N Akimoto et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>NR2B subunit at Tyr1472 (p-NR2B) in the spinal cord at 1 and 
3 h after injection of CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.) (relative protein levels, 
2.4±0.24, 4.7±0.18, respectively; n ¼ 3; Figure 6f). After 
immunoblotting, the membrane was stripped and reprobed 
with anti-NR2B antibody (Figure 6b). CCL-1 increased level of 
NR2B protein at 1, 3 and 7 days after injection of CCL-1 
(25 ng, i.t.; relative protein levels, 2.9±0.33, 2.9±0.35, 
3.2 ± 0.65, respectively; n ¼ 3; Figure 6g). The protein level 
of p-NR2B/NR2B was increased at 1 and 3 h after injection of 
CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.; relative protein levels, 0.90±0.34, 
0.97 ± 0.34, respectively; n ¼ 3; Figure 6h). </p>

<p>Effects of CCL-1 injection on glial cells and cytokines in 
the spinal cord. Activation of glial cells contributes to the 
development and maintenance of tactile allodynia. 
11,13 We </p>

<p>examined microglia and astrocytes in the spinal cord after 
injection of CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.). Iba1 mRNA levels significantly 
increased in the spinal cord at 1, 3 h and 1 day after 
injection of CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.; 179.8±12.0, 168.4±20.0, 
149.5 ± 20.0%, respectively; n ¼ 4; Figure 7a). And 
we showed that CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.) induced increase and 
morphological change of Iba1-positive microglia 1 day after 
injection (Supplementary Figure S3). CD11b mRNA levels 
also significantly increased in the spinal cord at 1 day after 
injection of CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.; 249.5±51.2%; n ¼ 4; 
Figure 7b). It was reported that P2X 4 R on microglia are 
important for the development of neuropathic pain. 
2,3 We 
examined the expression of P2X 4 R mRNA after injection of 
CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.). However, P2X 4 R mRNA had not changed 
after injection of CCL-1 (Figure 7c). Glial fibrillary acid protein </p>

<p>Figure 5 Induction of allodynia by CCL-1 and attenuation of CCL-1-induced allodynia by NMDA antagonist and effect of CCL-1 on excitatory synaptic transmission in the 
superficial spinal dorsal horn. (a) Intrathecal (i.t.) injection of CCL-1 to naive mice induced allodynia (vehicle, n ¼ 12; each concentration of CCL-1, n ¼ 8). (b) Concentration 
dependence of CCL-1-induced allodynia 20 min after i.t. injection of CCL-1. (c) Co-injection of MK-801 blocked allodynia induced by CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.) (vehicle, n ¼ 12; each 
concentration of MK-801, n ¼ 8). (d) Concentration-dependent inhibition of allodynia by MK-801 50 min after injection. The concentration of MK-801 for 50% inhibition (IC 50 ) 
was 354 pmol. Data represent mean ± S.E. **Po0.01, *Po0.05 versus vehicle; </p>

<p>## </p>

<p>Po0.01, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>Po0.05: versus CCL-1 (25 ng) (two-way analysis of variance followed by 
Tukey-Kramer tests). (e) Representative excitatory effect of CCL-1 (50 ng/ml) on sEPSCs evoked in substantia gelatinosa neurons at a holding potential of À 70 mV (the left 
traces). CCL-1 elicited a barrage of sEPSCs. The excitatory action of CCL-1 was detected in about 40% of neurons tested (see Result section). Graphs in the right show CCL-1 
actions on the frequency and amplitude of sEPSCs (n ¼ 9) </p>

<p>CCL-1 contributes to neuropathic pain 
N Akimoto et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>(GFAP) mRNA level significantly increased in the spinal cord 
at 1, 3 h and 1 day after injection of CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.; 
199.1±19.0, 163.5±16.6, 169.7±20.8%, respectively; n ¼ 4; 
Figure 7d). In addition, we observed that CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.) 
induced morphological change and the number of GFAP-
positive astrocytes 1 day after injection (Supplementary Figure 
S3). Furthermore, we examined activation of microglia and 
astrocytes after injection of CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.) using phosphor-
p38 MAPK antibody (p-p38). CCL-1 induced phosphorylation of 
p38 MAPK on microglia and astrocytes (Supplementary Figure 
S2). Cytokines and growth factors are important mediators of 
neuronal-glial interactions. 
12,23 We examined cytokine (IL-1b, </p>

<p>TNF-a, IL-6) and brain-derived neutrophic factor (BDNF) in the 
spinal cord after injection of CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.). Though protein 
levels of IL-1b, TNF-a and IL-6 were not changed after 7 days 
of nerve ligation (Figure 1b), IL-1b mRNA significantly 
increased in the spinal cord at 1 and 3 h after injection of 
CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.; 688.0 ± 150.8, 609.2 ± 148.1%, respectively; 
n ¼ 4; Figure 7e), as well as TNF-a mRNA at 30 min, 1 and 3 h 
(25 ng, i.t.; 368.1 ± 150.1, 485.8 ± 94.4, 408.1 ± 97.4%, respec-
tively; n ¼ 4; Figure 7f), and IL-6 mRNA at 1 and 3 h (25 ng, i.t.; 
248.7±40.8, 318.0±68.8%, respectively; n ¼ 4; Figure 7g) 
after injection of CCL-1. On the other hand, BDNF mRNA did 
not change after injection of CCL-1 (Figure 7h). </p>

<p>Figure 6 NMDAR phosphorylation after injection of CCL-1 in the spinal cord. (a) The phosphorylation levels of NR1 subunit at Ser896 (p-NR1) in the spinal cord at different 
time points after injection of CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.) were evaluated by western blotting. The membrane was stripped and reprobed with anti-NR1 antibody. (b) The phosphorylation 
levels of NR2B subunit at Tyr1472 (p-NR2B) in the spinal cord at different time points after injection of CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.) were evaluated by western blotting. The membrane 
was stripped and reprobed with anti-NR2B antibody. (c) The graph summarizes the protein level of p-NR1. (d) The graph summarizes the protein level of NR1. (e) Comparison 
of the levels of p-NR1 normalized to NR1. (f) The graph summarizes the protein level of p-NR2B. (g) The graph summarizes the protein level of NR2B. (h) Comparison 
of the levels of p-NR2B normalized to NR2B. Data represent mean±S.E. (n ¼ 3). **Po0.01, *Po0.05: versus control (cont) (one-way analysis of variance followed by 
Bonferroni's test) </p>

<p>CCL-1 contributes to neuropathic pain 
N Akimoto et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Effects of i.t. CCR-8 siRNA treatment on allodynia. We 
next examined the effects of CCR-8 downregulation on 
tactile allodynia. We made CCR-8 knockdown model 
using transfection of siRNA against CCR-8. We confirmed 
that protein level of CCR-8 was reduced in the spinal 
cord 5 days after injection of CCR-8 siRNA (Figure 8a). The 
CCR-8 knockdown mice were subjected to PSNL 5 days 
after injection of CCR-8 siRNA. We examined the 
effect of CCR-8 knockdown on allodynia and coordinated 
motion using von Frey filament test and rota-rod test. 
Downregulation of CCR-8 reduced PSNL-induced tactile 
allodynia for 2 weeks (n ¼ 5; Figure 8c). By contrast, 
downregulation of CCR-8 had no effect on coordinated 
motion (n ¼ 5; Figure 8d). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present study, for the first time, demonstrates that 
expression of CCL-1 in the spinal cord and DRG at the mRNA 
and protein levels is increased after nerve ligation, and 
the nerve ligation-induced tactile allodynia is attenuated by 
treatment with neutralizing antibody against CCL-1 and in 
CCR-8 knockdown mice. We further show that CCL-1 has an 
excitatory action on the glutamatergic synaptic transmission 
and phosphorylation of NMDAR subunits, NR1 and NR2B, in 
the spinal dorsal horn and increase expression of glial cells 
activation markers (Iba1, CD11b and GFAP) and cytokines 
(IL-1b, TNF-a and IL-6). Our results therefore indicate that 
CCL-1 may be one of the key mediators of chronic tactile </p>

<p>Figure 7 CCL-1 increased the expression of glial cells and cytokines in the spinal cord. Expression of mRNA of (a) Iba1, (b) CD11b, (c) P2X 4 R, (d) GFAP, (e) IL-1b, 
(f) TNF-a, (g) IL-6 and (h) BDNF after injection of CCL-1 (25 ng, i.t.) were evaluated by RT-PCR. Each value was normalized to the control level (cont). 
Data represent mean ± S.E. (n ¼ 4). **Po0.01, *Po0.05: versus control (one-way analysis of variance followed by Bonferroni's test) </p>

<p>CCL-1 contributes to neuropathic pain 
N Akimoto et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>allodynia acting through an acute modulation of nociceptive 
synaptic transmission, phosphorylation of NR1 and NR2B, 
glial activation and increase of cytokines in the spinal cord. 
In this study, we showed that CCL-1-specific receptor, 
CCR-8, was expressed in not only neurons but also glial cells 
6 h after nerve ligation in the ipsilateral side (see Figure 3). We 
suggested that increase of total CCR-8 protein after nerve 
ligation in the spinal cord by increase of CCR-8 expression on 
glial cells. CCL-1 mRNA showed only a transient increase in 
the spinal cord (see Figure 1e) and at 3 h, 1 and 3 days after 
nerve ligation in DRG (see Figure 1d). This indicates that 
CCL-1 may be mainly produced in DRG after nerve ligation. In 
the case of CCL-21 and CCL-2, they were produced in DRG 
after nerve ligation and were transported to neuronal terminals 
in the dorsal horn. 
24,25 CCL-2 was released from neuronal 
synaptic vesicles in the spinal cord. 
26 Similarly, we assume 
that CCL-1, which is produced in DRG neurons after nerve 
ligation, is subsequently transported to the spinal cord and 
then released. CCL-1 mRNA in the spinal cord at 3 h after 
nerve ligation was also produced in glial cells albeit only 
transiently; this however, requires further investigation. 
Immune cells and glial cells interact with neurons to alter 
pain sensitivity and to mediate the transition from acute to 
chronic pain. 
11,14,19 It is generally believed that microglia are 
involved in the development and astrocytes in the main-
tenance of neuropathic pain. 
27-29 Cytokines are important 
messengers for the communication between neurons and 
glia. 
11,13,30 Injection of CCL-1 into the spinal cord increased 
the mRNA level of microglial (CD11b or Iba1) and astroglial 
(GFAP) markers, as well as that of cytokines (IL-1b, TNF-a 
and IL-6) (see Figure 7). We also observed double staining of 
GFAP or CD11b with p-P38 after i.t. injection of CCL-1, 
suggesting that microglia and astrocytes were in reactive 
states (see Supplementary Figure S2). Activation of microglia 
in the spinal dorsal horn following peripheral nerve injury is </p>

<p>well characterized. 
2,31 The mechanisms of nerve injury-
induced microglial activation are complex and involve several 
signaling systems. 
32 Purinergic signaling mediated through 
P2X 4 , P2X 7 and P2Y 12 receptors seems to contribute to the 
initial activation of microglia following acute nerve 
injury. 
2,3,16,31,33,34 We, however, failed to identify changes in 
P2X 4 receptor mRNA in the spinal cord after injection of CCL-
1. This suggests that CCL-1-mediated activation of microglia 
does not involve the upregulation of P2X 4 receptors but 
engages distinct signaling cascade(s). Several reports have 
previously demonstrated that cytokines and chemokines 
activate microglia and astrocytes, inducing secretion of 
proinflammatory factors (e.g., IL-1b, TNF-a, BDNF, IL-6, IL-
17, CCL-2). 
2,12,27 Several proinflammatory cytokines and 
chemokines have been implicated in altered nociceptive 
processing. 
12 TNF-a enhanced synaptic efficacy by increas-
ing surface expression of AMPA receptors. 
35 IL-1b modulates 
sensory neuron transmission via increased release of the 
nociceptive neuropeptides substance P and calcitonin gene-
related peptide. 
36-38 IL-1b also induced the phosphorylation 
of NR1. 
39 IL-6 was reported to be involved in the development 
of neuropathic pain. 
40 By contrast, there are some reports that 
IL-6 has neuroprotective effect in the central nerve system. </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>IL-1b and TNF-a induced IL-6 expression in cultured neurons 
and astrocytes. 
42 According to these reports, it might be 
reasonable that a peak expression of IL-6 in the spinal cord 
occurred later compared with that of TNF-a and IL-1b after 
injection of CCL-1 (see Figure 7g). These results indicate that 
CCL-1 is involved in the development of allodynia through glial 
activation and expression of cytokines. However, other 
signaling molecules can be also involved in the pathogenesis 
of neuropathic pain. Effects of CCL-1 on glial function need to 
be investigated in more detail in the future. 
We showed that allodynia induced by injection of 
CCL-1 was blocked by co-injection of NMDAR antagonist. </p>

<p>Figure 8 Intrathecal siRNA against CCR-8 treatment inhibited allodynia-induced nerve ligation. (a) Protein level of CCR-8 in the spinal cord after transfection of CCR-8 
siRNA. (b) Schedule for making model mice and behavioural analysis. (c) CCR-8 siRNA inhibited allodynia-induced nerve ligation. (d) There was no change in coordinated 
motion after siRNA treatment. Data represent mean ± S.E. (n ¼ 5). **Po0.01 versus contralateral; 
## Po0.01, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>Po0.05: versus scramble siRNA (two-way analysis of 
variance followed by Tukey-Kramer tests) </p>

<p>CCL-1 contributes to neuropathic pain 
N Akimoto et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>We assumed that CCL-1 enhanced glutamate release from 
presynaptic terminal or affected postsynaptic NMDARs. We 
confirmed that CCL-1 affected both, increasing glutamate 
release transiently and inducing phosphorylation of NR1 and 
NR2B gradually. As for the presynaptic effect, we showed that 
CCL-1 increased glutamate release only in some but not all 
neurons (see Figure 5e). Similarly, double immunostaining 
with anti-CCR-8 and anti-NeuN showed that CCR-8 expres-
sion was only in sub-population of neurons (see Figure 3), 
the reason of which requires further investigation. As for the 
postsynaptic effect, it is already reported that activation of 
NMDAR is important for initiating long-lasting changes in 
synapses and has been implicated in persistent pain by 
strengthening glutamatergic sensory transmission. 
5 Though 
we did not directly check whether postsynaptic NMDA 
currents were enhanced by CCL-1 or not, we observed that 
both phosphorylation of NMDAR and increase in the number 
of NMDARs take place in response to CCL-1. Phosphoryla-
tion of NMDAR is known to modulate NMDAR activity and 
facilitate transmission of nociceptive inputs in inflammatory 
and neuropathic pain models. 
39 Partial ligation of sciatic nerve 
significantly increased the phosphorylated proportion of NR1 
and NR2B subunits in the dorsal horn. 
43,44 The phosphoryla-
tion of NR1 subunit is related to enhancement of synaptic 
efficacy and the development of central sensitization 7 days 
after nerve injury. 
45 On the other hand, NR2B selective 
antagonist attenuated neuropathic pain. 
46 Tyrosine phos-
phorylation of NR2B, but not NR2A, is associated with 
the development of persistent pain. 
47 In our experiments, 
CCL-1 induced phosphorylation of NR1 and NR2B albeit with 
different time course: Phosphorylation of NR2B was transient, 
whereas phosphorylation of NR1 continued for 3 days. In our 
behavioural experiments on pain score, injection of CCL-1 
induced allodynia transiently, as phosphorylation of NR2B. As 
there is a report that NR2B is particularly important for 
pain perception, 
5 we speculate that phosphorylation of 
NR2B would be more important than phosphorylation of 
NR1 together with upregulation of NR2B. As for the 
phosphorylation of NR1, IL-1b was reported to induce 
phosphorylation of NR1. 
45,48 As IL-1b mRNA was increased 
in the spinal cord after injection of CCL-1 at 1 and 3 h 
(Figure 7e), we speculate that NR1 would be phosphorylated 
not only by CCL-1 but also by IL-1b. 
In conclusion, our study provides evidence that CCL-1 is 
produced mainly in DRG after nerve ligation, supposed to be 
transported to the spinal cord, where it increases glutamate 
release together with local upregulated CCL-1, and then 
activates glial cells and cytokine release. CCL-1 also induced 
phosphorylation of NMDAR subunits, NR1 and NR2B. Treat-
ment with neutralizing antibody against CCL-1 and CCR-8 
siRNA blocked nerve ligation-induced tactile allodynia. There-
fore CCL-1 is one of the key molecules in pathogenesis of 
allodynia, and CCL-1/CCR-8 signaling system can be a 
potential target for drug development in the treatment for 
neuropathic pain. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods 
Animals. Male ddY mice (20-30 g, Kyudo Co. Ltd., Tosu, Saga, Japan) were 
used. Mice were housed at 23 ± 2 1C with 12 h light: 12 h dark cycle (light on from 
0700 to 1900 hours) and were given free access to commercial food and tap </p>

<p>water. Experimental procedures were based on the Guidelines of the Committee 
for Animal Care and Use of Kyushu University, Fukuoka University and National 
Institute for Physiological Sciences. </p>

<p>Drugs. Recombinant mouse CCL-1 and neutralizing antibody CCL-1 were 
purchased from R&amp;D Systems (Minneapolis, MN, USA). MK801 was purchased 
from Sigma Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA). </p>

<p>PSNL. The mice were anesthetized with an intraperitoneal (i.p.) injection of 
pentobarbital (65 mg/kg). A PSNL was produced by tying a tight ligature with a No. 8 
nylon thread around approximately 1/3-1/2 the diameter of the sciatic nerve located 
on the left side (ipsilateral side) based on the Seltzer method. 
49 On the right side 
(contralateral side), the nerve was exposed without ligation. </p>

<p>Behavioural analysis. Behavioural analysis was performed to assess 
the development of tactile allodynia in mice. Tactile allodynia was measured using 
a von Frey filament (North Coast Medical, Gilroy, CA, USA). Mice were placed in 
glass cages with a wire mesh bottom and allowed to habituate for at least 1 h. A 
von Frey filament with bending forces of 0.16 g (innocuous stimulation) was 
pressed perpendicularly against the plantar skin of a hind-paw. The paw 
withdrawal responses to the mechanical stimulus were evaluated by scoring as 
follows: 0, no response; 1, lifting the hind-paw within 3 s; 2, lifting the hind-paw 
over 3 s; and 3, immediate flinching or licking of the hind-paw. The stimulation of 
the same intensity was applied seven times to each hind-paw at several seconds 
intervals and the total served as the pain-related score (score) in the SNL model. 
The behavioural data were analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Origin</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Microcal software Inc.</rs>., 
Sunnyvale, MA, USA) software to determine the IC 50 values. 
We performed a rota-rod (KN-75 Rota-rod, Natume, Japan) test to measure 
motor balance and coordination. Mice were pre-trained on rota-rod apparatus for 3 
days and then tested on the accelerating rod in which the speed of the spindle was 
10 r.p.m. Latency until fall was automatically recorded. To eliminate stress and 
fatigue, mice were given a maximum cutoff latency of 120 s. </p>

<p>Intrathecal injection. Intrathecal (i.t.) injection was performed using a 25-ml 
Hamilton syringe with a 28-gauge needle (Muranaka Medical Instruments co. 
LTD., Osaka, Japan), as described previously. 
50,51 The needle was inserted into 
the intervertebral space of a conscious mouse between the lumbar 5 (L5) and 6 
(L6) regions of the spinal cord. A reflexive flick of the tail was considered to be an 
indicator of the accuracy of each injection. A volume of 5 ml was used for the i.t. 
injections. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemical analyses. Mice were anesthetized by pentobar-
bital sodium (50 mg/kg, i.p.) and perfused transcardially with saline followed by 4% 
paraformaldehyde in 0.1 M phosphate-buffered saline (PBS; 80 mM Na 2 HPO 4 , 
20 mM KH 2 PO 4 , 150 mM NaCl, pH 7.4). The L4-L6 segment of the lumbar spinal 
cord was removed, postfixed in the same fixative and placed in 20% sucrose 
solution for 24 h at 4 1C. Transverse L4-L6 spinal cord section (20 mm) were sliced 
by a HM 550 cryostat (Micro-edge Instruments Co., Tokyo, Japan) and incubated 
for 1 h at room temperature in 5% donkey serum (Jackson Immuno Research, 
West Grove, PA, USA). Then, the sections were incubated with the following: 
NeuN (1 : 200, Millipore, Bilerica, MA, USA), CCR-8 (1 : 500, Enzo, New York, NY, 
USA), Iba1 (ionized calcium-binding adapter molecule-1, 1 : 2000, Wako, Osaka, 
Japan), CD11b (1 : 500, Serotec, Oxford, UK), GFAP (1 : 800, Millipore) or p-p38 
(phosphor-p38 MAPK, 1 : 100, Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, MA, USA) for 
24 h at 4 1C. The sections were incubated for 4 h at room temperature in the 
secondary antibody (IgG-conjugated Alexa Fluor 488 or 594, 1 : 1000, Molecular 
Probes, Eugene, OR, USA). Sections were mounted on coverslips with permafluor 
aqueous mounting medium (Thermo Scientific, Yokohama, Japan). The sections 
were analyzed using a fluorescence microscope (BZ9000, Keyence, Japan) and a 
confocal laser scanning microscope (LSM510META, Carl Zeiss, Hallbergmoos, 
Germany). In confocal imaging, we used a series of Z-stack images (images taken 
at multiple focal points of an objective lens through the z -axis) for 3D analysis of 
each slice. </p>

<p>Cytokine array. Mouse cytokine array kit was purchased from R &amp; D Systems 
and was assessed as described previously. 
52 The L4-L6 segment of the lumbar 
spinal cord was isolated and homogenized in the lysis buffer (10 mM Tris-HCl, 
0.5 mM EDTA, 0.5 mM EGTA, 1% Triton X-100, pH 7.4) containing protease 
inhibitor cocktail (Sigma) and centrifuged at 15 000 r.p.m. for 20 min at 4 1C. Each </p>

<p>CCL-1 contributes to neuropathic pain 
N Akimoto et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>reaction was performed according to the protocol of the manufacturer using 20 mg 
of protein collected from the sample. The protein sample was incubated with a blot 
array precoated with 40 cytokine/chemokine antibodies overnight at 4 1C. These 
blots were visualized using Lumi GLO Reserve Chemiluminescent Substrate Kit 
(Cell Signaling Technology) and quantified by a luminoimage analyzer (Fluor 
Chem Imaging System, Alpha Innotech Corporation, San Leandro, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Real-time reverse transcription (RT) PCR. The L4-L6 segment of the 
lumbar spinal cord and DRG were subjected to total RNA extraction according 
to the protocol of the manufacture and purified with QIAamp RNA Blood Mini 
(Qiagen, Valencia, CA, USA). The amount of total RNA concentration was 
measured using Smart Spec 3000 (Bio-Rad, Tokyo, Japan). Total RNA (175 ng) 
was converted to cDNA by reverse transcription, using random 9 mer (Takara, 
Otsu, Japan) and RNA PCR kit (Takara). The primers were as follows: CCL-1 
primers (forward: 5 
0 -TTCCCCTGAAGTTTATCCAGTGTT-3 
0 , reverse: 5 
0 -TGAACC 
CACGTTTTGTTAGTTGAG-3 
0 ); b-actin primers (forward: 5 
0 -TTGCTGACAGGATG 
CAGAAGGAG-3 
0 , reverse: 5 
0 -GTGGACAGTGAGGCCAGGAT-3 
0 ); TNF-a primers 
(forward: 5 
0 -CCACCACGCTCTTCTGTCTAC-3 
0 , reverse: 5 
0 -TGGGCTACAGGCTT 
GTCACT-3 
0 ); IL-1b primers (forward: 5 
0 -CTCCATGAGCTTTGTACAAGG-3 
0 , 
reverse: 5 
0 -TGCTGATGTACCAGTTGGGG-3 
0 ); IL-6 primers (forward: 5 
0 -ACACTC 
CTTAGTCCTCGGCCA-3 
0 , reverse: 5 
0 -CACGATTTCCCAGAGAACATGTG-3 
0 ); 
BDNF primers (forward: 5 
0 -TGCAGGGGCATAGACAAAAGG-3 
0 , reverse: 5 
0 -CTTA 
TGAATCGCCAGCCAATTCTC-3 
0 ); Iba1 primers (forward: 5 
0 -CCTGATTGGAGGT 
GGATGTCAC-3 
0 , reverse: 5 
0 -GGCTCACGACTGTTTCTTTTTTCC-3 
0 ); CD11b 
primers (forward: 5 
0 -AATGATGCTTACCTGGGTTATGCT-3 
0 , reverse: 5 
0 -TGATAC 
CGAGGTGCTCCTAAAAC-3 
0 ); GFAP primers (forward: 5 
0 -CCAGCTTCGAGCCAA 
GGA-3 
0 , reverse: 5 
0 -GAAGCTCCGCCTGGTAGACA-3 
0 ); and P2X 4 R primers 
(forward: 5 
0 -TGGCCGACTATGTGGTCCCA-3 
0 , reverse: 5 
0 -GGTTCACGGTGACG 
ATCATG-3 
0 ). All primers were purchased from Sigma Aldrich Japan (Tokyo, 
Japan). PCR amplification was undertaken for Sybr qPCR Mix (Takara) in Applied 
Biosystems 7500 Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems Japan, Tokyo, 
Japan). Each reaction volume consisted of 10 ml Sybr qPCR Mix, 0.4 ml 50 Â ROX 
reference dye, 0.4 ml mix of forward and reverse primers (0.2 mM each) and 7.8 ml 
RNAase free water containing cDNA (17.5 ng). PCR was done by 15 s 
denaturation at 95 1C and annealing/extending at 60 1C for 40 cycles. Each 
mRNA expression level was normalized by b-actin. The mRNA expression was 
calculated relative to b-actin using the DDC T algorithm. </p>

<p>Western blotting. Expression protein level of CCR-8 in lumbar spinal cord 
was examined by western blotting relative to b-actin. The L4-L6 segments of the 
lumbar spinal cord were isolated and homogenized in a lysis buffer containing 
protease inhibitor (Sigma); subsequently 20 mg of proteins were loaded for each 
lane and separated by SDS-PAGE gel (7.5%), and transferred to PVDF 
membrane (Bio-Rad). The membrane was blocked with 5% low-fat dried milk (anti-
CKR8/CCR-8), 5% BSA (anti-p-NR2B, anti-NR2B) or 3% BSA (anti-p-NR1, anti-
NR1) and incubated with the following for 1 h at room temperature: Rabbit 
monoclonal anti-CKR8/CCR-8 (1 : 500, Epitomics, Burlingame, CA, USA), anti-
phospho-NR1 (Ser896; 1 : 1000, Millipore), anti-NR1 (1 : 1000, Millipore), anti-
phospho-NMDAR2B (Y1472; 1 : 1000, R&amp;D Systems), anti-NMDAR2B (D15B3) 
(1 : 1000, Cell Signaling Technology), and anti-b-actin (1 : 1000, Sigma). The 
membrane was washed and incubated with specific secondary antibodies 
(Amersham ECL anti-rabbit IgG and anti-mouse IgG, horseradish peroxidase-
linked species-specific whole antibody, 1 : 5000, GE Healthcare, Piscataway, NJ, 
USA). The blots were detected by use of ECL western blotting detection system 
(GE Healthcare) and LAS-4000 imaging system (Fujifilm, Tokyo, Japan). Bands 
were quantified using the software Multi Gauge (Fujifilm). </p>

<p>Preparation of spinal cord acute slices. The methods used for 
obtaining spinal cord slice preparations are identical to those described 
elsewhere. 
53,54 Mice were anesthetized with urethane (1.2-1.5 g/kg, i.p.), and a 
thoracolumbar laminectomy was performed. The lumbosacral segments of the 
spinal cord (L1-S1) were placed in an ice-cold Krebs solution equilibrated with 
95% O 2 /5% CO 2 . The Krebs solution contained (in mM) 117 NaCl, 3.6 KCl, 2.5 
CaCl 2 , 1.2 MgCl 2 , 1.2 NaH 2 PO 4 , 25 NaHCO 3 and 11 glucose. Immediately after 
removal of the spinal cord, the mice were exsanguinated under the urethane 
anesthesia. The pia-arachnoid membrane was removed after cutting all of the 
ventral and dorsal roots. The spinal cord was mounted on a vibratome and a 500-
mm thick transverse or sagittal slices were cut. The slice was placed on a nylon 
mesh in the recording chamber with a volume of 0.5 ml and was completely </p>

<p>submerged and perfused with Krebs solution saturated with 95% O 2 and 5% CO 2 
at 36 ± 1 1C at a flow rate of 10-15 ml/min. </p>

<p>Whole-cell patch-clamp recordings from substantia gelatinosa 
neurons. The substantia gelatinosa was easily discernible with transmitted 
illumination as a relatively translucent band across the dorsal horn in the 
transverse or parasagittal slice preparations. Blind whole-cell voltage-clamp 
recordings were made from SG neurons, as previously described. 
53,54 The patch 
pipettes were filled with potassium gluconate solution, a solution containing (in 
mM); 135 K-gluconate, 5 KCl, 0.5 CaCl 2 , 2 MgCl 2 , 5 EGTA, 5 HEPES, and 
5 ATP-Mg (pH 7.2). The tip resistance of the patch pipettes was 6-12 MO. Series 
resistance was assessed from current in response to a 5-mV hyperpolarizing step. 
Series resistance was monitored during the recording session and data were 
rejected if its value changed by 415%. Ion currents were monitored with a patch-
clamp amplifier (Axopatch 700A, Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA, USA). The 
data were digitized with an analog-to-digital converter (Digidata 1321A, Molecular 
Devices), stored on a personal computer using a data acquisition program 
(<rs id="software-1" type="software">Clampex</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 10</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Molecular Devices</rs>) and analyzed using a software package 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">Clampfit</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 10</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Molecular Devices</rs>). Recordings were made in a voltage-
clamp mode at holding potential of À 70 mV to isolate EPSCs. Drugs were 
dissolved in the Krebs solution and applied by superfusion. </p>

<p>Transfection of CCR-8 siRNA by electroporation. siRNA against 
CCR-8 were obtained from Bonac Corporation (Kurume, Japan) (GenBank accession 
number: NM_007720, mCcr8#1 sense 5 
0 -GCAAGAAACUGAGGAGCAU-3 
0 , 
anti-sense 5 
0 -AUGCUCCUCAGUUUCUUGC-3 
0 , mCcr8#2 sense 5 
0 -GAGCAGUC 
UUUGAGGUGGA-3 
0 , anti-sense 5 
0 -UCCACCUCAAAGACUGCUC-3 
0 , and mCcr8#3 
sense 5 
0 -GAGAGAAGUUUAAGAAACA-3 
0 , anti-sense 5 
0 -UGUUUCUUAAACUUCU 
CUC-3 
0 ). Mice were anesthetized by pentobarbital sodium (50 mg/kg, i.p.). Mixed 
siRNA (0.2 mg/ml, 10 ml) was injected i.t. using a 25-ml Hamilton syringe with a 28-
gauge needle (Muranaka Medical Instruments co. LTD.). 
55,56 Scrambled siRNA 
(sense 5 
0 -UACUAUUCGACACGCGAAG-3 
0 , anti-sense 5 
0 -CUUCGCGUGUCGAAUA-
GUA-3 
0 ; Bonac Corporation) was used as a negative control. A volume of 5 ml was 
used for the i.t. injections at each points. Electric pulses (poring pulse: 75 V, 5 ms of 
length with 50-ms interval, transfer pulse: 20 V, 50 ms of length with 50-ms interval) 
were delivered using NEPA21 (Nepa Gene, Ichikawa, Japan). 
57,58 Knock-down effects 
were evaluated by western blotting. </p>

<p>Cell culture. Cortex neurons were obtained from embryonic days 14-16 ddY 
mice as described previously. 
59 Briefly, neurons were cultured at 37 1C in a 10% 
CO 2 incubator for 5-7 days with neurobasal medium (GIBCO, Grand Island, NY, 
USA) containing 2% B27 supplement (GIBCO) and 0.5 mM L-glutamine (GIBCO). </p>

<p>Immunocytochemical analysis. Primary cultured cells were fixed with 4% 
paraformaldehyde for 30 min at room temperature and permeabilized with 0.1% 
TritonX-100 in PBS for 5 min, followed by treating with blocking solution (Block 
Ace; Dainippon Pharmaceutical, Osaka, Japan) for 30 min at room temperature. 
Cells were incubated with primary antibodies: CCR-8 (1 : 200, Epitomics), MAP2 
(1 : 1000, Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA), VGLUT1 (1 : 1000, Synaptic Systems, 
Göttingen, Germany) or VGAT (1 : 500, Synaptic Systems) overnight at 4 1C. The 
cells were washed in PBS and then incubated for 3 h at room temperature with 
secondary antibody (IgG-conjugated Alexa Fluor 488 or 568 or 633, 1 : 1000, 
Molecular Probes). The cells were washed in PBS and treated with 4 
0 , 6-
diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI, 300 nM, Molecular Probes) for 10 min and then 
washed with PBS. Slides were cover-slipped with permafluor aqueous mounting 
medium. The sections were analyzed using a confocal laser scanning microscope 
(LSM510META, Carl Zeiss). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. All data are presented as mean ± S.E.M. The statistical 
analyses of the results were evaluated by using two-tailed Student's paired or 
unpaired t-test, one-way ANOVA followed by Student-Newman-Keuls test, 
one-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni's test or two-way ANOVA followed by 
Tukey-Kramer test. Po0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest 
The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>CCL-1 contributes to neuropathic pain 
N Akimoto et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Acknowledgements. This work was supported, in part, by a Grant-in-
Aid from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology 
of Japan (No. 22590084 to MN, No. 22590252 to YT, No.23590731 to KH 
No. 23390156 to Dr. Hidemasa Furue and No. 5269 to NA). And this work was 
also supported by fund from the Central Research Institute of Fukuoka University. 
We appreciate the Research Support Center, Graduate School of Medical 
Sciences, Kyushu University for the technical support. We also thank Dr. 
Hidemasa Furue (National Institute for Physiological Sciences, Japan) for helping 
with the electrophysiological experiments, Professor Kazuhide Inoue and Dr. 
Hidetoshi Tozaki-Saitoh (Kyushu University) for an experimental equipment for 
behavioural test. </p>





<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease is an open-access journal 
published by Nature Publishing Group. This work is 
licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit 
http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/ </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on Cell Death and Disease website (http://www.nature.com/cddis) </p>

<p>CCL-1 contributes to neuropathic pain 
N Akimoto et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

</text></tei>