<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3973247" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-12T00:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>In Alzheimer's disease (AD), different types of neurons and different brain areas show differential patterns of vulnerability 
towards neurofibrillary degeneration, which provides the basis for a highly predictive profile of disease progression throughout 
the brain that now is widely accepted for neuropathological staging. In previous studies we could demonstrate that in AD cortical 
and subcortical neurons are constantly less frequently affected by neurofibrillary degeneration if they are enwrapped by a 
specialized form of the hyaluronan-based extracellular matrix (ECM), the so called 'perineuronal net' (PN). PNs are basically 
composed of large aggregating chondroitin sulphate proteoglycans connected to a hyaluronan backbone, stabilized by link 
proteins and cross-linked via tenascin-R (TN-R). Under experimental conditions in mice, PN-ensheathed neurons are better 
protected against iron-induced neurodegeneration than neurons without PN. Still, it remains unclear whether these 
neuroprotective effects are directly mediated by the PNs or are associated with some other mechanism in these neurons 
unrelated to PNs. To identify molecular components that essentially mediate the neuroprotective aspect on PN-ensheathed 
neurons, we comparatively analysed neuronal degeneration induced by a single injection of FeCl 3 on four different mice 
knockout strains, each being deficient for a different component of PNs. Aggrecan, link protein and TN-R were identified to be 
essential for the neuroprotective properties of PN, whereas the contribution of brevican was negligible. Our findings indicate that 
the protection of PN-ensheathed neurons is directly mediated by the net structure and that both the high negative charge and the 
correct interaction of net components are essential for their neuroprotective function. 
plasticity. 9,17,18 In addition, the glycoprotein components of 
the PNs carry numerous glycosaminoglycan (GAG) side 
chains, which are long unbranched polymers of repetitive 
disaccharide units consisting of an amino-sugar (N-acetylga-
lactosamine). 19 Sulphate groups attached to these GAGs in 
concert with the negatively charged hyaluronic acid generate 
a highly polyanionic microenvironment around PN-
ensheathed neurons. 20,21 Most likely, they can, thus, interact 
with calcium, potassium and sodium ions, providing a local 
'buffer reservoir' for physiologically relevant cations. In 
cortical areas, PN-wearing interneurons are often associated 
with the calcium-binding protein parvalbumin (PV). These 
interneurons are identified as highly active and fast 
spiking, which requires high ionic currents and a tightly 
regulated ion homeostasis. The anionic features of PNs 
surrounding these neurons might contribute to meet these 
requirements. 20,22-25 
In addition to this physiological mechanism, the polyanionic 
components might also interact with ions of potential 
pathophysiological relevance such as iron ions involved in 
generating oxidative stress. 20,22,26,27 We have, thus, put 
forward the hypothesis that PNs, through scavenging and 
binding of redoxactive iron, are able to reduce the potentially 
deleterious local oxidative potential in the neuronal micro-
environment, thereby protecting neurons ensheathed by PNs 
against oxidative damage. 22,28 In support of this suggestion, 
we previously observed that both in normal-aged brain and </p>

<p>AD neurons ensheathed by a PN are less frequently affected 
by lipofuscin accumulation than neurons without a net. 
As lipofuscin is an intralysosomal pigment composed of 
cross-linked proteins and lipids generated by iron-catalysed 
oxidative processes, this finding suggests a neuroprotective 
function of PNs against neurodegeneration induced by 
oxidative stress. 22,23,29-31 In an effort to validate our 
hypothesis, we analysed the effects of iron injection into 
mice brain on neurons with or without PN. We could show 
that net-associated neurons were less severely affected 
by degeneration than neurons without PNs. 28 Still, it 
remains unclear whether these neuroprotective effects are 
directly mediated by the PN or its components are associated 
with some other mechanism in these neurons unrelated 
to PNs. 
Therefore, in the present study, we intended, first, to verify 
that PNs are directly involved in the neuroprotective mechan-
ism and second, to identify those molecular components of 
PNs that essentially mediate these neuroprotective proper-
ties. To this end, we comparatively analysed the sequalae of 
iron-induced neuronal damage in four different mice knockout 
strains, each deficient for a different molecular component of 
the PN, such as aggrecan (ACAN þ / À ), brevican (BCAN À / À ), 
tenascin-R (TN-R À / À ) or link protein 1 (HAPLN1 À / À ). (for the 
principal structure of PNs in the used mouse models see 
Figures 1b-e). We could identify aggrecan, tenascin and link 
protein HAPLN1 as PN components essential to mediate their </p>

<p>Figure 1 Schematic synopsis of molecular composition of PNs in the barrel field cortex. (a) Hyaluronan synthases are located at the neuronal surface, synthesizing and 
secreting hyaluronan to the perineuronal area. Members of the lectican family (aggrecan, neurocan and brevican) bind to this hyaluronic backbone. So far, versican could not 
be identified as part of PN in the barrel field cortex. Binding of CSPGs to hyaluronan is stabilized by the link proteins. TN-R crosslinks the lecticans to form stable PNs. (b) PNs 
of heterozygous deficient aggrecan mice (ACAN þ / À ) lacking about 50% of the originally included aggrecan. (c) In mice lacking brevican (BCAN À / À ), neurocan partially 
compensates for it. (d) PNs of mice lacking link protein (HAPLN1 À / À ) or TN-R À / À (e) are structured loosely, preventing the formation of stable meshworks </p>

<p>Essential components of the perineuronal net to protect neurons 
A Suttkus et al </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>neuroprotective properties. These results clearly show a 
direct albeit differential contribution of ECM components to 
the neuroprotective function of PNs. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>In the present study, we analysed whether the neuroprotec-
tive properties associated with the presence of PN, previously 
observed, 28 are directly mediated by the PN or whether the 
PN only provides a surrogate marker of some unidentified 
mechanism. Further, we defined the molecular components of 
the PN that are essential to mediate these neuroprotective 
properties. To this end, protection of PN-ensheathed neurons 
was differentially analysed after microinjection of FeCl 3 into 
the barrel field cortex, in four different mice knockout strains, 
each being deficient for a different component of PNs, such as 
aggrecan (ACAN þ / À ), lacking brevican (BCAN À / À ), link 
protein (HAPLN1 À / À ) or tenascin-R (TN-R À / À ) knockout mice. </p>

<p>PN-associated phenotypes of different mice knockout 
strains. The constitutive deficiency of defined molecular net 
components had some phenotypic effects on the appearance 
but not on the number of PNs in all tested mouse strains. The 
phenotypic appearance of PNs in mice either lacking 
brevican (BCAN À / À ) or being deficient in aggrecan 
(ACAN þ / À ) did not differ noticeably from wild type, enwrap-
ping the neuronal soma as well as the proximal dendrites as 
a sharply contoured, lattice-like meshwork. PNs of mice 
lacking link protein (HAPLN1 À / À ) or tenascin-R (TN-R À / À ) 
in contrast appeared somewhat more fuzzy and granular with 
reduced staining around dendrites (Figures 2a-e). Similar 
observations were made previously. 13,32-34 
To determine whether the deficiency of defined molecular 
components of PNs had a constitutive effect on the number of 
PNs, we assessed the numerical density of neurons with and 
without PN in the barrel field cortex of each different mouse 
knockout strain (Figures 2a1-e1). There were no effects on 
the total numerical density of neurons in any of the knockout 
strains compared with wild type. 
Next, we analysed whether different knockout genotypes 
had any effects on the number of neurons enwrapped by PNs. 
In addition, PN-associated neurons were stratified according 
to the presence or absence of PV. In wild-type animals, 
PN-ensheathed neurons amounted to about 10% of all 
neurons, with about half of them (49%) containing PV. This 
was in accordance with Nowicka et al. 35 The lack of brevican 
as well as the deficit of aggrecan had no effects on the 
presence of PN-ensheathed neurons. In contrast, net-
associated neurons as well as net-associated PV positive 
neurons were significantly reduced in number in HAPLN1 À / À 
and TN-R À / À mice. The ratio of PN-associated neurons with 
and without PV was only shifted in TN-R À / À mice, with a 
significant reduction of PV containing PN-ensheathed 
neurons. </p>

<p>Knockout genotypes of PN-associated components 
have differential effects on brain lesions. To define 
molecular components, essential to mediate the neuropro-
tective properties of PNs, we investigated the effects of 
deficiency of a defined PN component on the size of </p>

<p>experimentally induced brain lesion. After injection of FeCl 3 
into the barrel cortex, a widespread degeneration of brain 
tissue was observed around the injection site in all mice 
strains, which could clearly be delineated by Fluoro-Jade B 
staining (Figures 3a-e). Quantification of the lesion size, 
however, clearly showed that all transgenic mice strains 
showed significantly larger degeneration than wild-type mice 
(Figure 3f). A lack of tenascin-R (TN-R À / À ) mediated the 
most extensive degeneration with a radius of about 1500 mm 
of the affected cross-sectional area. Somewhat smaller 
dimensions of degeneration were observed in mice lacking 
link protein 1 (HAPLN1 À / À ), aggrecan (ACAN þ / À ) or 
brevican (BCAN À / À ) with average radii of the lesion 
between 1300 and 1350 mm. However, no significant 
differences could be measured. Control injections with 
0.9% NaCl revealed only marginal lesions with maximum 
degeneration radii of 200 mm (data not shown). Again, no 
significant differences could be investigated within the 
different mice strains or in comparison to WT mice. </p>

<p>Aggrecan, TN-R and link protein 1 are essential for the 
neuroprotective properties of PNs. Next, we analysed in 
our lesion paradigm whether neurons ensheathed by a PN 
lacking a specific matrix compound were affected differen-
tially compared with neurons without PN. To this end, we 
labelled the net structure either with Wisteria floribunda 
agglutinin (WFA), which binds to chondroitin sulphate side 
chains most likely on aggrecan, 36-38 or with an antibody that 
labels the aggrecan core protein (HAG), the main proteogly-
can component of PNs. 4,10,18,39 
Three independent methods were used to detect degen-
erating neurons, namely Fluoro-Jade B staining, a caspase-3 
antibody and an antibody against H2AX in combination with 
histochemical labelling of the net structures. The vast majority 
of degenerating neurons, detected with any of these methods, 
were devoid of PNs (Figure 4). Only occasionally, PN-
ensheathed neurons were positive for a stain detecting 
degenerating neurons. Still these rare cases, as exemplified 
in Figure 4, clearly ruled out any systemic bias with respect to 
accessibility of the detection dye to neurons ensheathed by 
PN compared with neurons without PN. 
To obtain a quantitative measure on the effects of PNs upon 
neurodegeneration, degenerating neurons were quantified 
after a combination of PN labelling by either WFA histochem-
istry or anti-HAG immunocytochemistry with Fluoro-Jade B 
and NeuN (Figure 5). 
In Figures 6a-e the percentage of Fluoro-Jade B-positive 
neurons without PN (light grey), in regard to the total number 
of neurons without PN, is compared with the percentage of 
Fluoro-Jade B-positive neurons with a PN (dark grey), relating 
to the total number of neurons ensheathed by a PN. 
The results of cell counting revealed clear differences for 
affected neurons, depending on the knockout mice strain. In 
brevican knockout mice (BCAN À / À ), PN-associated neurons 
were significantly less frequently affected by degeneration 
than neurons without PN. This effect was independent of the 
detection method of PNs (Figure 6c). In aggrecan-deficient 
mice (ACAN þ / À ), neurons ensheathed by a PN, visualized 
with WFA, were also less frequently affected by degeneration 
compared with neurons without PN (Figure 6b). This difference </p>

<p>Essential components of the perineuronal net to protect neurons 
A Suttkus et al </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Essential components of the perineuronal net to protect neurons 
A Suttkus et al </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>disappeared, however, when aggrecan immunocytochemis-
try (HAG) was used for detection of PNs. Differences in 
vulnerability between neurons with and without PN were 
abolished completely in mice lacking either the 
link protein 1 (HAPLN-1 À / À ) (Figure 6d) or tenascin-R 
(TN-R À / À ) (Figure 6e). 
To evaluate any potential contribution of PV to the 
neuroprotective properties on PN-ensheathed neurons, </p>

<p>triple-stained sections, labelled for PV and Fluoro-Jade B in 
combination with either HAG or WFA were analysed likewise 
for differential effects of degeneration. As summarized in 
Figures 6a1-e1, no increased protection of PV-associated 
net-wearing neurons could be observed. In BCAN À / À mice, 
PN-associated neurons with PV detected by WFA as well as 
HAG were even significantly more frequently affected than 
those without PV. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Morphological and numerical appearance of neurons with and without PN in different mice knockout strains compared with wild type, detected in layers II and III 
of the barrel field cortex. Double fluorescence staining of PNs by WFA (pink) and the Ca-binding protein PV (green). Sections of wild-type mice (a) show intensely labelled, 
robust lattice-like structures enwrapping the neuronal soma and the proximal dendrites; PN of mice deficient for aggrecan (ACAN þ / À ) (b) or brevican (BCAN À / À ) (c) look 
slightly fuzzy, but not disturbed. In contrast, PN of mice lacking the cartilage link protein (HAPLN1 À / À ) are attenuated and disturbed with almost no staining around dendrites. 
(d) Furthermore, Tenascin-R (TN-R À / À ) knockout mice (e) display granular structures with lesser overall staining around dendrites. (a1-e1) Numerical density of neurons 
stained by NeuN (dark grey), of PN-associated neurons detected by (WFA, light grey) or an antibody against aggrecan core protein (HAG, light grey) and of 
PN-associated neurons expressing PV (white) in the barrel field cortex. In mice deficient for aggrecan (b1), link protein 1 (d1) or TN-R (e1), numbers of PN-associated as well 
as PN-associated, PV-expressing neurons were significantly reduced. The lack of brevican (c1) had no effect on the numerical density of neurons. Data are mean values, 
± S.D. Statistical analysis by Mann-Whitney test, n ¼ 5. *Po0.05, scale bar 20 mm </p>

<p>Figure 3 Extent of neurodegeneration induced by single-sided injection of FeCl 3 into the barrel field cortex of mice knockout strains lacking specific components of PNs. 
(a-e) Typical examples of coronal sections cut through the lesion at its maximal extension. A volume of 0.2 ml 20 mM FeCl 3 was injected into the left barrel field cortex; 
degenerating cells were detected by Fluoro-Jade B staining 24 h later. Note that brain tissue volume affected by degeneration is significantly different in different mice strains. 
(a) WT; (b) ACAN þ / À ; (c) BCAN À / À ; (d) HAPLN-1 À / À , (e) TN-R À / À . Scale bar 500 mm. Quantification of lesion size determined on serial sections after staining with 
Fluoro-Jade B (f). In all mice knockout strains, lesion size was significantly larger than in wild type (WT). A lack of tenascin (TN-R À / À ) results in the most extensive spreading 
of degeneration. In brevican knockout mice (BCAN À / À ), heterozygous aggrecan knockout mice (ACAN þ / À ) and mice lacking the link protein 1(HAPLN-1 À / À ), lesion size 
is somewhat smaller. Data are expressed as mean values. Statistical analysis by Mann-Whitney test, n ¼ 5. *Po0.05 </p>

<p>Essential components of the perineuronal net to protect neurons 
A Suttkus et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Aggrecan is upregulated after FeCl 3 induced injury. In 
addition, we investigated the aggrecan expression in the 
injured CNS by western blotting. For this analysis, the 
hemisphere of iron-induced lesion as well as the correspon-
dent contralateral hemisphere were dissected and prepared 
for subsequent processing. Protein extracts were run in a 6% 
gel. Western blot analysis with the anti-aggrecan antibody 
AB1031 revealed a single band at B450 kDa in injured and 
uninjured hemispheres (Figure 7a). A comparative quantifi-
cation with TINA software (Raytest, Straubenhardt, Germany) 
revealed higher contents of aggrecan in iron-injected 
hemispheres for all tested mouse lines, with significant 
differences in mice lacking brevican or HAPLN1 (Figure 7b). 
Here, the content of aggrecan is increased by 45% (BCAN À / À ) 
and 67% (HAPLN1 À / À ). Furthermore, a significant decrease 
of aggrecan in mice heterozygous deficient for aggrecan 
(ACAN þ / À ) could be confirmed. Here, the overall content of 
aggrecan is reduced by 60% compared with the analysed 
tissue of WT mice. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In the present study, we defined molecular components of 
PNs that essentially mediate neuroprotective properties. 
Using a comparative approach, provoking a neurotoxic insult 
in four different transgenic mice strains, each lacking or being 
deficient in a different molecular component of PNs, we could 
identify clear differences with respect to both lesion size and 
neuronal population affected by degeneration. Neurons </p>

<p>ensheathed by a PN in wild-type mice were less frequently 
affected by degeneration than neurons without PN. These 
neuroprotective properties associated with the presence of 
PNs were lost when TN-R and HAPLN-1 were lacking, while 
the deficiency of aggrecan had a partial effect and the lack of 
brevican had no effect. 
In addition, mice deficient for TN-R, link protein 1, brevican 
or aggrecan showed a significantly higher spreading of 
degeneration than wild-type mice after single sided injection 
of FeCl 3 . This increase in tissue volume, which is affected by 
degeneration, was observed for all mice strains lacking a 
specific matrix component. On the background of previous 
reports on the contribution of lecticans 40,41 and TN-R 42 to the 
diffusion and hydration properties of the neural ECM, a 
facilitated diffusion of dissociated FeCl 3 due to the lack of PN 
components most likely accounts for these effects. 
Our main interest was the identification of hyaluronan-
based ECM molecules, which essentially mediate the 
neuroprotective properties of PNs. Aggrecan is one of the 
main components of the ECM and the key component of the 
PNs. 43,44 It is the largest member of the lectican family and 
carries up to 100 negatively charged chondroitin sulphate side 
chains. 10,45 Thus, aggrecan interacting with hyaluronan, also 
highly negatively charged, mainly contributes to the poly-
anionic character of the PN. Our data show that PN detected 
by the aggrecan antibody HAG in mice heterozygous deficient 
for aggrecan (ACAN þ / À ), have lost their neuroprotective 
properties. Most likely, the content of aggrecan in these PNs is 
reduced below a critical level, which is not sufficient to exert </p>

<p>Figure 4 Different detection methods for neuronal death in the barrel field cortex. Degenerated cells after injection of FeCl 3 can be visualized with Fluoro-Jade B (a), an 
active caspase-3 antibody (b) and an antibody against H2AX (c). All three markers visualize degenerated cells to a similar extent. A microscopic picture with a higher 
magnification of the different markers (a1-c1), followed by the combination with WFA histochemistry (red) and the neuronal marker NeuN (pink) (a2-c2) allows a 
determination of affected neurons with and without PN. Scale bar (a-c) 500 mm and (a1-c2) 20 mm </p>

<p>Essential components of the perineuronal net to protect neurons 
A Suttkus et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>the neuroprotective effects. 44 Neurons with PNs, however, 
detected in the same mice with WFA were significantly less 
frequently affected by iron-induced degeneration. This might 
indicate that other matrix compounds providing binding sites 
for WFA might partially compensate for the loss of aggrecan. 
In addition, it might show that WFA binding, indicating the 
presence of highly charged anionic binding sites, provides a 
signature for the neuroprotective properties of PNs. The 
hypothesis that aggrecan is one of the key factors for 
mediating neuroprotective properties is supported by the data 
received from the western blotting analysis. Here, the 
decreased level of aggrecan in ACAN þ / À mice in comparison 
with WT mice could be demonstrated. Furthermore, the 
content of aggrecan in the hemisphere containing the iron 
injection is increased compared with the not-injected hemi-
sphere in all mouse lines. Here, significant differences could 
be shown for mice lacking brevican and link protein HAPLN1. 
However, this clear trend could confirm a certain neuroprotec-
tion of aggrecan itself. An upregulation of aggrecan could 
already be seen in studies concerning neurodegenerative 
diseases. Lendvai et al. 7 could demonstrate increased 
aggrecan contents in the hippocampal formation of AD 
patients as well as in the hippocampal tissue of the AD </p>

<p>mouse model APPswe/PS1dE9. 7 They suggested that this 
upregulation of aggrecan could be based on neuroprotective 
mechanisms. An upregulation of PN components has so far 
been shown only for versican and neurocan in the context of 
forming a glial scar after brain injury. 14 However, versican and 
neurocan most likely do not contribute to neuroprotective 
mechanisms, but rather to the inhibition of axonal outgrowth 
and regeneration, respectively. So, aggrecan represents the 
most potential CSPG in the context of protective processes. 
Another proteoglycan component we investigated is brevi-
can. Here, brevican showed the smallest contribution to 
neuroprotective features of PNs, if any. This could be 
demonstrated irrespectively of whether the remaining net 
was detected by WFA binding sites or HAG. Brevican is an 
important proteoglycan in the adult rodent and to some extent 
part of the PN. It is mainly enriched in the perisynaptic 
structure of the axonal coats while it contributes only margin-
ally to enwrapping of the neuronal soma (unpublished results). 
Brakebusch et al. 32 could demonstrate a certain upregulation 
of neurocan in brevican knockout mice, which may partially 
compensate for the loss of brevican. But, the expression of 
neurocan, highly upregulated during embryonic development, 
indicates a strong influence of neurocan mainly during early </p>

<p>Figure 5 Detection of death neurons with and without PN in different mice knockout strains detected by triple staining. PNs were visualized by HAG (red), degenerating 
cells were labelled by Fluoro-Jade B (green) and neurons were detected by NeuN (pink). Merged images were used for quantitative analysis. Scale bar 20 mm </p>

<p>Essential components of the perineuronal net to protect neurons 
A Suttkus et al </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Essential components of the perineuronal net to protect neurons 
A Suttkus et al </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>developmental processes. Brevican, however, is highly 
expressed during the formation of PNs until the end of the 
critical period. Neurocan and brevican have a largely 
complementary expression profile during ontogenesis. Thus, 
it is assumable that the upregulation of neurocan in BCAN À / À 
mice beyond embryonic development may be in order to 
reduce developmental deficits. So, it is comprehensible that 
the loss of brevican does not have a major effect on the 
'shielding' properties of PNs against oxidative damage. 46-48 
The next matrix component we have analysed is the link 
protein HAPLN-1. HAPLN-1, next to HAPLN-4, stabilizes the 
interaction between hyaluronan and CSPGs by binding to 
both components. 49 Of the several PN elements, HAPLN1 
starts to be expressed exactly at the time PNs begin to 
develop. So, it might be a trigger for PN development. 
Furthermore, animals lacking HAPLN-1 do not form normally 
shaped PNs. PNs of HAPLN1 knockout mice are diffuse and 
seem to be less close to the plasma membrane than those of 
wild-type mice. 13 Our experiments show that PNs lacking 
HAPLN1 have completely lost their neuroprotective proper-
ties. HAPLN1, thus, represents a matrix component that is 
essential for this function of PNs. </p>

<p>Results obtained on mice lacking tenascin-R (TN-R À / À ) 
were similar to those of HAPLN-1 À / À mice. As a large ECM 
glycoprotein, TN-R participates in macromolecular organiza-
tion of PNs. 50 It interacts with the cell surface as well as with 
CSPGs, including aggrecan, versican, neurocan and, with 
highest affinity, brevican. 51 While the general histology 
appeared to be unaffected in TN-R-deficient mice, changes 
were observed in the shape and appearance of PNs, like in the 
HAPLN-1 knockouts. They showed a reduced WFA-staining 
intensity and were characterized by a more granular and less 
punctuate structure. 33 In addition, these alterations were 
accompanied by a reduction of immunohistochemical staining 
intensity in other major matrix components, such as hyalur-
onan, neurocan, brevican and phosphacan. 34 Altogether, 
these structural and molecular changes of the ECM might 
directly affect the physiology of neurons. This includes a 
disturbed synaptic stability as well as an inefficient main-
tenance of the ionhomeostasis . 52 Our present data show 
that TN-R is also essential for the neuroprotective properties 
of PNs. 
In summary, our findings indicate that the different ECM 
components of PNs contribute differently to their protective </p>

<p>Figure 6 Neuronal degeneration after injection of FeCl 3 into the barrel field cortex separately quantified for neurones with and without PN, respectively, for the presence or 
absence of PV. PNs were visualized by either anti-HAG immunocytochemistry (left) or WFA lectin histochemistry (right). In WT mice (a), PN-associated neurons are 
significantly protected compared with neurons without PN. This difference can still be detected in mice lacking brevican (BCAN À / À , c), but is somewhat attenuated in 
heterozygous aggrecan (ACAN þ / À , b) knockout mice. The protective effect of PNs, however, is completely abolished in mice lacking the link protein (HAPLN1 À / À , d) or 
tenascin-R (TN-R À / À , e). Comparing PN-associated neurons without PV to PN-associated neurons with PV reveals no contribution of PV to the neuroprotective function of 
PN. Brevican knockout mice (c1) indicate an even less severe affection of PN-wearing neurons without PV. No significant differences were obtained on wild-type mice (a1), 
heterozygous aggrecan knockout mice (b1), mice lacking the link protein (d1) or TN-R (e1). Data are expressed as mean values. Statistical analysis by Wilcoxon rank test, 
n ¼ 5. *Po0.05, **Po0.01, ***Po0.001 </p>

<p>Figure 7 Western blot analysis of aggrecan contents. Protein extracts (30 mg/lane) from homogenized neuronal sections from the ipsilateral site of injection were 
compared with the contralateral control site. Samples were subjected to SDS PAGE in a 6% gel. Blots were probed by use of an antibody against aggrecan (AB1031) (a). 
Mean±S.D. intensity of chemiluminescence was quantified for bands at 450 kDa (b) in relation to the bands of HSP90. An upregulation of aggrecan was evident with 
significant increases in BCAN À / À and HAPLN1 À / À mice. Statistical analysis by Mann-Whitney test, n ¼ 4. *Po0.05 </p>

<p>Essential components of the perineuronal net to protect neurons 
A Suttkus et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>properties. Brevican plays no direct part in protecting cells 
against iron-induced cell death. However, a contribution to 
diffusion properties is likely. On the contrary, aggrecan as the 
main proteoglycan component seems to be essential for 
protection against iron-induced cell death. Aggrecan is 
besides hyaluronan in charge of imparting the PN, a 
polyanionic character. 45 This highly negative charge could 
be the main aspect of the protective feature. This assumption 
is supported by our observation that even in heterozygous 
aggrecan-deficient mice the neuroprotective properties are 
still preserved in those PNs where sufficient negatively 
charged chondroitin sulphate side chains are present to 
generate a WFA binding. 53 
Further, our data indicate that the two matrix components, 
HAPLN1 and TN-R, are also essential for the neuroprotective 
function of PNs. HAPLN1 consolidates the binding of CSPGs 
to hyaluronan. 13 Therefore, a strong connection of the CSPGs 
to hyaluronan seems to be an essential factor. Similar 
evidence was received from analysing TN-R À / À mice. This 
leads to the assumption that TN-R, by way of forming stable 
aggregates, has a relevant part in mediating a protective 
aspect of the PNs. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Taken together, our findings indicate that the neuroprotection 
of neurons ensheathed by a PN against iron-induced cell 
death is directly mediated by the PN and that both the high 
negative charge and the correct interaction of net components 
to form a stable barrier against ions are essential factors for 
their neuroprotective properties. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods 
Animals. The following mouse lines were used in the present study: C57BL/6J 
mice, heterozygote aggrecan-deficient (ACAN þ / À ) mice were obtained from 
Prof. Dr. RT Matthews (State University of New York, Upstate Medical University, 
Syracuse, NY, USA); 36,43,54 brevican knockout mice (BCAN À / À ) mice were 
obtained from Dr. C Seidenbecher (Leibniz Institute for Neurobiology, Magdeburg, 
Germany); 32,55 TN-R knockout mice (TN-R À / À ) were obtained from Prof. Dr. 
M Schachner (Center for Molecular Neurobiology Hamburg (ZMNH), University of 
Hamburg, Germany); 33,34 and link protein-deficient (HAPLN1 À / À ) mice were 
obtained from Prof. Dr. J Fawcett (MRC Brain Repair, University of Cambridge, 
UK) and Prof Dr. T Pizzorusso (Instituto Neuroscienze CNR, Pisa, Italy). 13,56 Male 
and female mice were bred and housed at the Medizinisch-Experimentelles </p>

<p>Zentrum of the Medical Faculty of the University of Leipzig. Animals had free 
access to food and water and were maintained on an artificial 12 : 12-h light-dark 
cycle under conditions of constant temperature (22 1C) and humidity. All 
experimental procedures on animals were carried out in accordance with the 
European Council Directive of 24 November 1986 (86/609/EEC) and had been 
approved by the local authorities (TVV50/10). </p>

<p>In vivo injection. Mice at an age of 3 months were deeply anaesthetized by 
intraperitoneal injection with a cocktail of ketamine (100 mg/kg, ratiopharm, Ulm, 
Germany) and xylazine (5 mg/kg, Rompun, Bayer, Germany). Animals, fixed to a 
stereotaxic apparatus (Stoelting, Wood Dale, IL, USA), received injections of 0.2 ml 
20 mM FeCl 3 dissolved in a 0.9% NaCl solution over 10 min at AP À 1.7 mm, 
L þ / À 3 mm, V À 2 mm (from bregma and dura, head flat between bregma and 
dura; somatosensory cortex, barrel field S1BF according to Paxinos and 
Franklin 57 ) using a 33-gauge needle (33/51/4, Hamilton) attached to a Hamilton 
syringe (Type 75-RN, Switzerland). Five animals per group were used. Animals of the 
control group received an equal volume of 0.9% NaCl, which was adjusted to the pH 4 
analogue to the FeCl 3 solution (n ¼ 3). Animals were analysed 24 h post injection. </p>

<p>Tissue preparation. Animals were perfused transcardially under deep CO 2 
anaesthesia with 0.9% NaCl and 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) in phosphate-
buffered saline (PBS). Animals were decapitated; brains were removed 
immediately, fixed in 4% buffered PFA (24 h) and cryoprotected in 30% sucrose 
with 0.01% sodium azide in PBS (48 h). Series of coronal sections were cut on a 
freezing microtome at 30 mm thickness and collected in PBS with 0.01% sodium 
azide. </p>

<p>Detection of cellular death. Degenerated neurons were detected by three 
different methods: staining sections with (i) Fluoro-Jade B (0.001%, Chemicon, 
Temecula, CA, USA), using an (ii) anti-caspase-3 antibody (AB3623, 1 : 50, 
Millipore, Darmstadt, Germany) or an (iii) antibody against phosphoS139 H2AX, a 
well-established marker for double-stranded DNA breaks (ab2893, 1 : 50, Abcam, 
Cambridge, UK). 58 To clearly distinguish between degeneration of neurons 
ensheathed by PN or neurons without PN, sections were processed for one of 
these detection methods for degenerating neurons in combination with antibodies 
against aggrecan core protein (HAG7D4, mouse-anti-human aggrecan, 1 : 10, 
AbD Serotec, , Germany) combined with biotinylated NeuN (mouse-
anti-NeuN clone A60, ab77315, 1 : 100, Millipore) or biotinylated WFA, 1 : 100, 
Sigma, Taufkirchen, Germany ) combined with NeuN (mouse-anti-NeuN clone A60 
MAB 377, 1 : 100, Millipore). Fluoro-Jade B as anionic dye specifically stains 
degenerating neurons by binding to a currently unknown, most likely a poly-amine, 
basic substance in the neuron. 59,60 For counting procedures, Fluoro-Jade B was 
chosen because of its high technical feasibility and reproducibility. To evaluate a 
potential contribution of PV to the neuroprotective properties of the PNs, sections 
were also stained with an antibody against PV (PV25, 1 : 500, Swant, Marly, 
Switzerland) in combination with WFA and Fluoro-Jade B as well as HAG and 
Fluoro-Jade B. 
Briefly, sections were washed in PBS, and preincubated in a blocking solution 
(2% bovine serum albumin, 0.3% casein, 0.5% donkey normal serum) for 1 h 
followed by 48 h incubation with the primary antibodies at 4 1C. After washing, 
sections were incubated with Cy3-conjugated donkey-anti-mouse IgG (1 : 300, 
Dianova, Hamburg, Germany) or Cy3-conjugated donkey-anti-rabbit IgG (1 : 300, 
Dianova) and Cy5-conjugated streptavidin (1 : 150, Dianova) for 3 h. Sections were 
washed, mounted on gelatine-coated slides and incubated with 0.001% Fluoro-Jade 
in 0.1% acetic acid for 30 min. Slides were washed with distilled water, placed onto a 
slide warmer until fully dry, immersed in xylene for 3 min and coverslipped using 
DePeX (Serva, Heidelberg, Germany). Furthermore, combining anti-caspase-3 or 
anti-H2AX with WFA and NeuN requires incubation with Cy2-conjugated donkey-
anti-rabbit IgG (1 : 250, Dianova), Cy3-conjugated streptavidin (1 : 300, Dianova) 
and Cy5-conjugated donkey-anti-mouse IgG (1 : 100, Dianova). Here, sections were 
washed, mounted on gelatine coated slides and coverslipped with Entellan (MercK, 
Darmstadt, Germany). </p>

<p>Quantification of degeneration. The extent of degeneration was 
examined after Fluoro-Jade B staining. For quantification of cell death, the 
cross-sectional tissue area covered by degenerated cells, identified after Fluoro-
Jade B staining, was determined on serial sections cut throughout the entire 
extension of the lesion at an interval of 120 mm. For each animal, the largest 
cross-sectional area was defined as region of interest (ROI) and copied to all </p>

<p>Figure 8 Illustration of the evaluation method. (a) For the quantification 
of neuronal death after injection of 0.2 ml FeCl 3 (white arrow assigns point of 
injection) the largest cross-sectional area covered by Fluoro-Jade B-positive cells 
was defined as reference area (white circle) and copied to all analysed sections. 
Within this area, counting of Fluoro-Jade B-positive neurons was performed within 
three rectangles of a size of 0.18 mm 2 , randomly placed to the reference area (b). 
Scale bar 500 mm </p>

<p>Essential components of the perineuronal net to protect neurons 
A Suttkus et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>sections (Figure 8a). Fluoro-Jade B-positive neurons (detected by NeuN) were 
counted within three rectangles of a cross-sectional area of 0.18 mm 2 , randomly 
placed to the ROI (Figure 8b).Counts were performed using the optical fractionator 
method 8 on a Zeiss (Jena, Germany) Axioskop 2 plus microscope equipped with a 
motorized stage (, Wetzlar, Germany), a Ludl MAC 5000 (LEP, 
Hawthorne, NY, USA) and a digital camera CX 9000 (MicroBrightField, Williston, 
VT, USA). <rs id="software-1" type="software">Stereo Investigator</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">6</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">MicroBrightField</rs>) was used to analyse 
serial sections (19 mm thick). Statistical analyses were performed by Mann-
Whitney test and Wilcoxon rank test. </p>

<p>Determination of numerical neuronal density. To evaluate the 
potential effects of knockout genotypes on the numerical density of neurons 
associated with PN, as well as on PV immunoreactive neurons, frontal brain sections 
of all mouse strains were investigated. The contralateral brain area of the injection 
site was used as internal control and analysed by using the optical fractionator 
method, too. Counting procedures were performed in the defined ROI as described 
above. Statistical analyses were done by Mann-Whitney Test. </p>

<p>Sample preparation for SDS-PAGE. For this analysis, mice received 
an injection of 0.2 ml 20 mM FeCl 3 into the barrel field as described previously. 
Twenty-four hours after injection, mice were deeply anaesthetized by CO 2 , 
decapitated, their brains removed and immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen. On a 
dry ice-cooled worktop, the frozen brain was dissected in 2 mm thick frontal 
sections. The slice displaying the strongest lesion was picked, bisected and 
transferred (separated by an injected and control hemisphere) to 2-ml tubes. 
Then, hemisphere sections were homogenized on ice, using an Ultra-Turrax tube 
drive (IKA), in homogenization buffer (0.02 M Tris-HCl, 0.15 M NaCl, 5 mM NaF, 
1 mM Na 3 VO 4 , 2 mM MgCl 2 , pH 7.4) containing a protease inhibitor (Complete, 
Roche, Mannheim, Germany). The homogenate was centrifuged at 10 000 Â g for 
14 min at 4 1C, followed by determination of the protein concentration in the 
supernatant by using the BCA Assay. 
To evaluate the content of aggrecan, the main proteoglycan component of the 
PN, the single supernatant was digested with 0.25 U Chondroitinase ABC (Sigma-
Aldrich, Hamburg, Germany) at 37 1C for 3 h to erase sulphated GAG side chains of 
the proteoglycan core protein, according to Matthews et al. 44 </p>

<p>Electrophoresis and western blotting. To run the SDS page, the 
volume of the supernatant containing 30 mg protein was added to the same 
volume of 1 Â SDS sample buffer and denaturized at 75 1C for 15 min. Then the 
samples were subjected to electrophoresis on 6% SDS-polyacrylamide gels with a 
4.3% stacking gel and transferred to a poly vinylidene difluoride membrane (Perkin 
Elmer, Rodgau, Germany). The membrane was probed with anti-aggrecan 
(AB1031, 1 : 0000, Millipore) and anti-HSP 90 (4874, 1 : 1000, Cell Signaling, 
Beverly, MA, USA) antibodies and finally detected with an enhanced 
chemiluminescence western blot system (DNR Bio-Imaging systems, Biostep, 
Jahnsdorf, Germany). The blots were scanned and the ratios of optical band 
intensities of aggrecan normalized to HSP 90 were calculated using <rs type="software">TINA</rs> 
software. Experiments were done in duplicates. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest 
The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements. We thank Prof. Dr. RT Matthews, Dr. C Seidenbecher, 
Prof. Dr. M Schachner, Prof. Dr. J Fawcett and Prof. Dr. T Pizzorusso for providing 
the different transgenic mice strains. This work was granted by the European Union 
and the Free State of Saxony (Project: Neuron 48-038), the German Research 
Foundation GRK 1097 'INTERNEURO', COST Action BM1001 'Brain Extracellular 
Matrix in Health and Disease', German Research Foundation MO 2249/2-1 within 
the PP 1608, the European Union, the Free State of Saxony (grant number 
SAB 100154907) and the Alzheimer Forschungsinitiative e.V. (AFI #11861) to 
M Morawski. </p>





<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease is an open-access journal 
published by Nature Publishing Group. This work is 
licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit 
http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/ </p>

<p>Essential components of the perineuronal net to protect neurons 
A Suttkus et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

</text></tei>