<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3575799" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The transcriptional co-activator BOB.Regulated gene expression is a complex process, as dif-
ferent signals need to be integrated in a cell-type-specific 
manner in accordance with the particular developmen-
tal stage and activation state. This complexity is 
achieved by the architecture of a given promoter and/or 
enhancer and therefore by the integrated action of differ-
ent transcription factors in conjunction with recruited 
co-activators or -repressors. These proteins act together 
on promoter DNA finally leading to the formation of 
specific transcriptional complexes based on the DNA 
sequence they bind as well on the activity of each com-
ponent itself. 
The octamer element ATGCAAAT is one of such DNA 
sequences and plays an important role in mediating 
promoter activity of a large array of ubiquitous and 
lymphocyte-specific genes. Octamer-dependent transcrip-
tion is achieved in first line by transcription factors that 
belong to the Oct family. The selectivity of Oct factors 
to octamer sequences and their transcriptional activity 
can be enhanced by the recruitment of either ubiquitously 
expressed or cell type-specific co-activators. For instance, 
the histone H2B promoter activity depends on 
Oct1 (Pou2f1) and its interaction with the transcriptional 
co-activator OCA-S, a protein complex containing 
GAPDH as a key component, whose expression is 
highly increased during the S phase of the cell cycle (1). 
In lymphocytes, the transcriptional co-activator BOB.1/ 
OBF.1 (B cell Oct binding factor 1/Oct binding factor 1; 
Pou2af1) is responsible for the cell type-specific 
octamer-dependent transcription. BOB.1/OBF.1 is re-
cruited to DNA by the interaction with Pit-1/Oct1,2/ 
Unc-86 domains of the ubiquitously expressed Oct1 or 
the lymphocyte specific factor Oct2 (Pou2f2) (2-8), the 
two Oct family members expressed in lymphocytes (9). </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +49 7315 003 3846; Fax: +49 7315 002 2892; Email: cornelia.brunner@uni-ulm.de </p>

<p>2138-2154 Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 4 
Published online 4 January 2013 
doi:10.1093/nar/gks1349 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0/), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>However, not all octamer-regulated promoters depend 
on the presence of BOB.1/OBF.1 (10,11). The ability of 
Oct1 or Oct2 to recruit BOB.1/OBF.1 to the DNA might 
be conferred by different octamer sequences that favor or 
disfavor the ternary complex formation of these proteins 
at the octamer motif (12). In addition, we and others 
demonstrated that the presence of BOB.1/OBF.1 enables 
Oct factors to bind to unfavorable non-consensus octamer 
motifs (13,14). Together, the lymphocyte-specific regula-
tion of octamer-dependent transcription depends on an 
appropriate DNA sequence, on the activity of Oct1 and 
Oct2 transcription factors and on the presence of the tran-
scriptional co-activator BOB.1/OBF.1. Furthermore, 
the latter is posttranslationally modified by phosphoryl-
ation at Ser184, which is required for its constitutively or 
inducible transcriptional activity in B or T cells, respect-
ively (15). 
The importance of octamer-dependent transcription is 
underlined by the phenotypes of Oct1-, Oct2-and BOB.1/ 
OBF.1-deficient mice. The deletion of the ubiquitously ex-
pressed Oct1 protein leads to embryonic lethality (16), and 
deletion of the lymphocyte specific Oct2 protein causes 
death of newborn mice shortly after birth (17). Fetal 
liver cell transfer into immuno-compromised mice 
revealed that Oct1 is dispensable for B cell development 
and function (18). In contrast, Oct2-deficient B cells are 
unable to differentiate into immunoglobulin-secreting cells 
(17). This phenotype is similar to that observed for 
BOB.1/OBF.1-deficient mice. Although viable, these 
mice are unable to form germinal centers on administra-
tion of T cell-dependent antigens. Hence, the production 
of secondary immunoglobulins is severely compromised 
(19-21). Besides missing germinal centers, BOB.1/ 
OBF.1 
À/À mice show multiple defects at several stages of 
B cell development (22-24). Although the relevance of Oct 
proteins and BOB.1/OBF.1 for B cell development and 
function cannot be dismissed, these proteins are also im-
portant for T cells. Functional octamer motifs could be 
detected within the promoter regions of the chemokine 
receptor CCR5 (25) as well as IL2 (26-30) and IL4 
(28,31,32) genes. Also, the IFN promoter contains an 
octamer motif that is bound by Oct proteins together 
with BOB.1/OBF.1. As a consequence, the secretion of 
IFN by BOB.1/OBF.1-deficient TH1 cells is reduced to 
a level that disabled these mice to efficiently combat a 
Leishmania major infection (33). Given the importance 
of the octamer-dependent transcription for B and T cell-
development and function, it is, on the one hand, import-
ant to search for octamer-dependent target genes and, on 
the other, to understand the regulatory mechanisms 
underlying the octamer-dependent transcription itself. 
Regulation of transcription is one major mechanism 
to determine the capacity of a given protein. The pro-
moters of ubiquitously expressed Oct1 gene or the 
lymphocyte-specific Oct2 gene have not been described 
until today. In contrast, the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter was 
extensively studied to investigate its cis-acting elements 
controlling its activity in B cells (34-36) where BOB.1/ 
OBF.1 is constitutively expressed at all stages of B cell 
development (37), albeit at different levels. The highest 
expression of BOB.1/OBF.1 was found in germinal </p>

<p>center B cells. Accordingly, signals important for 
germinal center formation, like the stimulation with 
anti-CD40 antibodies plus IL4, are able to increase the 
expression of BOB.1/OBF.1 in vitro (38,39). In contrast, 
in T cells BOB.1OBF.1 expression is inducible by treat-
ment of T cells with Phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate 
(PMA)/Ionomycin (P/I) or by antigen receptor engage-
ment (15,40), suggesting that different signals and 
possibly also transcription factors might be responsible 
for the expression of BOB.1/OBF.1 in B versus T cells. 
Interestingly, also the expression of the lymphocyte-spe-
cific Oct2 protein is upregulated in activated T cells with a 
kinetic similar to that obtained for BOB.1/OBF.1 (41,42). 
As the expression and function of Oct proteins together 
with BOB.1/OBF.1 was also found to be important for 
the control of TH1 and TH2 immune responses (33), the 
present study focuses on the regulation of octamer-
dependent transcription in T cells. Our analyses revealed 
the involvement of the Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>/calmodulin-dependent phos-
phatase calcineurin (CN), as Oct2 and BOB.1/OBF.1 
expression are efficiently suppressed in the presence 
of the immunosuppressant cyclosporin A (CsA) or by 
the siRNA-mediated suppression of CN-A. On T cell 
receptor (TCR) stimulation, CN turned out to be a key 
signaling molecule essential for the induction of both 
Nuclear Factor of Activated T cells (NFAT) and NF-kB 
transcription factors (43-45). CN dephosphorylates 
NFAT transcription factors enabling them to translocate 
into the nucleus where they control the expression of 
numerous genes essential for T cell activation and differ-
entiation (46). In addition, CN is involved in the regula-
tion of the TCR-induced NF-kB signaling pathway by 
regulating the complex assembly of Carma1, Bcl10 and 
Malt1 by dephosphorylating Bcl10. Carma1, Bcl10 and 
Malt1 complex formation is an essential prerequisite for 
the activation of the IkB-kinase complex that in turn 
phosphorylates the inhibitor of NF-kB (IkB) leading to 
its proteasomal degradation. Consequently, cytosolic 
NF-kB becomes released and translocates into the 
nucleus where it regulates, similar to NFAT, the 
promoter activity of numerous genes crucial for T cell 
development, differentiation and function (46). 
Therefore, both signaling pathways were analysed for 
their capacity to mediate Oct and/or BOB.1/OBF.1 gene 
expression and were identified as important regulators of 
octamer-dependent transcription in T cells. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Cell lines and culture </p>

<p>The Jurkat-4 x Octamer-Luc cell line was generated by 
electroporation of Jurkat cells with a luciferase reporter 
construct bearing four copies of the octamer motif cloned 
earlier (47) together with a plasmid expressing the 
Puromycin resistant gene (pSV-Puro) and selected by 
Puromycin. Jurkat-NEMO 
À/À was described (48). Jurkat 
cells and derivates (Jurkat-4 Â Octamer-Luc, Jurkat-
NEMO 
À/À ) and jNX amphotropic retrovirus producer 
cells were cultured in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's 
medium (Gibco, Invitrogen), containing 10% fetal calf </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 4 2139 </p>

<p>serum (FCS) (Biochrome), 2 mM of L-glutamine, 100 U/ 
ml of penicillin and 100 mg/ml of streptomycin (Gibco, 
Invitrogen) and 50 mM of b-mercaptoethanol at 37 
C 
and 5% CO 2 . A3.01 T cells and Namalwa B cells as well 
as primary CD4 
+ cells were cultured in RPMI-1640 
medium containing 10% FCS, 2 mM of L-glutamine, 
penicillin/streptomycin and 50 mM of b-mercaptoethanol 
at 37 
C and 5% CO 2 . </p>

<p>CD4 
+ T cell isolation </p>

<p>Primary CD4 
+ T cells were isolated from lymph nodes of 
mice either by positive or negative selection using 
magnetic microbead technology (Miltenyi). </p>

<p>Mice </p>

<p>C57BL/6 wild-type and TNFRI/p65 double-deficient mice 
(and all their wild-type/heterozygous combinations) were 
generated and obtained from our breeding facility. The 
NFATc1/c2 double knockout mice were generated by 
crossing the Nfatc2 
À/À mouse (49) with the Nfatc1 </p>

<p>flx/flx </p>

<p>[described in (50)] Â Cd4-Cre mouse. Mice were analysed 
3-4 or 10-12 weeks after birth, respectively. </p>

<p>Cell stimulation </p>

<p>Cells were stimulated in the presence of the following 
agents: 100 ng/ml of CsA and 200 ng/ml of FK506 (CN 
inhibitors), 1, 2 or 4 mM of Bay-117082 (a NF-kB inhibitor) 
as indicated, 25 ng/ml of PMA, 500 ng/ml of Ionomycin, 
200 nM of OH-tamoxifen (OHT) (all obtained from 
Sigma-Aldrich), 15 or 30 mM of SB203580 (Upstate) as 
indicated, 4 mg/ml of aCD3 and 0.5 mg/ml of aCD28 
(BD). The NEMO-binding peptide and the NFAT inhibi-
tory peptide 11 R-VIVIT were obtained from Calbiochem. </p>

<p>Promoter sequence analyses </p>

<p>In silico search for binding sites in BOB.1/OBF.1 pro-
moters of different species was performed using the 
MatInspector tool (<rs id="software-0" type="software">Matrix Family Library</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 8.3</rs>) 
of the <rs id="software-1" type="software">Genomatrix</rs> software tool (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Genomatrix Company</rs>). </p>

<p>Electrophoretic mobility shift assays </p>

<p>Preparation of whole cell extracts for electrophoretic 
mobility shift assays (EMSA) and the protocol of the 
EMSA procedure have been described earlier (33). The 
used oligonucleotides bearing the appropriate transcrip-
tion factor binding site were annealed and subsequently 
labeled using </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>P-adCTP in a fill in reaction. Sequences 
are presented in the Supplementary Table S1. </p>

<p>Promoter cloning </p>

<p>The 1500 and 500 bp BOB.1/OBF.1 promotor constructs 
were cloned into the pTKL/2 vector containing the 
HSV-thymidine kinase promoter (À105 to +52) from the 
pBLCAT2 in front of the firefly luciferase coding region. 
The HSV-thymidine kinase promoter was excised by a re-
striction endonuclease digest using HindIII and BglII and 
replaced by the 1500 bp or 500 bp BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter 
constructs cloned via genomic polymerase chain reaction 
(PCR) using the following primers: mBOB.1/OBF.1prom </p>

<p>1500 bp 5 
0 (HindIII): GCC AGG AAG CTT AGG GGT 
TGA G; mBOB.1/OBF.1prom 1500 bp 3 
0 (BglII): GCC 
TTT TCT CTT TGA AGC AGA GAT CTT GGC TTC 
TTT ACT. For amplification of the 500 bp promoter 
fragment, the same 3 
0 primer as for the 1500 bp 
fragment was used in combination with the following 
primer: mBOB.1/OBF.1prom 500 bp 5 
0 (HindIII): GAC 
CAA TGG TAA GCT TAG TCC TGC. Cloning of the 
BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter mBOB.1/OBF.1prom Á500 bp 
construct was achieved using the following combination 
of primers for genomic PCR: mBOB.1/OBF.1prom 
1500 bp 5 
0 (HindIII) as indicated earlier in the text, 
together with mBOB.1/OBF.1prom Á500 bp 3 
0 (BglII): 
CCA TTT ACA GGA CAG ATC TTA CCA TTG GTC. 
The BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter mBOB.1/OBF.1prom 
Á500 bp+TATA construct was generated by cloning of 
an insert that was amplified by genomic PCR using the 
following primers: mBOB.1/OBF.1prom 1500 bp 5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>(HindIII): GCC AGG AAG CTT AGG GGT TGA G 
and mBOB.1/OBF.1prom Á500 bp 3 
0 (HindIII): GCA 
GGA CTA AGC TTA CCA TTG GTC, into the HindIII 
site of the pTATA vector harboring the TATA box of the 
HSV-thymidine kinase promoter from pBLCAT2 (À38 to 
+52) in front of the firefly luciferase coding region. </p>

<p>In vitro mutagenesis </p>

<p>Mutations of the predicted NFAT/NF-kB sites within the 
BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter were generated using the 
QuickChange 
TM Mutagenesis kit (Promega). Primers 
were ordered from Biomers, and sequences are provided 
in Supplementary Table S4. </p>

<p>Transfection of cells </p>

<p>Transfections of Jurkat T and Namalwa B cells were per-
formed by electroporation (Bio-Rad) with 450 V and 
250 mF in phosphate buffered saline. The expression 
vector for the constitutive active version of CREB 
(c2CREB) is a kind gift of G. Tiel (51). Expression 
vectors for NFATc1 and RelA/p65 have been described 
(52,53). The pRL-CMV plasmid (Renilla Luciferase 
control reporter vector; Promega) was cotransfected in 
all experiments and used for normalization of different 
transfection efficiencies in the individual experiments. 
For suppression of CN A isoforms by siRNA, Jurkat T 
cells were transfected with 75 nM of each SMARTpool 
siRNA (CnBa: PPP3CA # L008300-0005; CnBb: 
PPP3CB # L009704-0005) or with the appropriate concen-
tration of control siRNA (OnTARGETplus # 
D001810-01-05) using the Nucleofection Kit V (Amaxa/ 
Lonza). The cells were subsequently incubated for 72 h 
before analysis. Used SMARTpool siRNA were 
obtained from Dharmacon. </p>

<p>Retroviral infection of cells </p>

<p>For virus production, the retroviral vectors expressing 
NF-ATc1/aA-ER, NF-ATc1/aC-ER (54), IKK2-EE, 
IKK2-KD (55) or the respective empty vectors were trans-
fected into the amphotropic jNX retrovirus producer 
cells by use of the calcium phosphate method. </p>



<p>Supernatant containing the retrovirus was collected 24 h 
and 48 h after transfection and used to infect A3.01 T cells 
in the presence of 8 mg/ml of polybrene. At 2 consecutive 
days, spin infection was performed at 2700 rpm (1300g) 
and 37 
C for 120 min. Positive cells were selected with 
Zeocin until all cells were nearly 100% positive for green 
fluorescent protein. </p>

<p>Western blots </p>

<p>For western blot analysis, 5-10 mg of total protein extracts 
were separated on 12.5% polyacrylamid gels and 
transferred onto nitrocellulose membranes (Schleicher&amp; 
Schuell). Membranes were blocked (TBS, 0.1% Tween, 
5% milk); stained with anti-BOB.1/OBF.1 (Sigma), 
Oct2, ERK2, IKK2 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology) and 
NFATc1 (Alexis) antibodies followed by incubation with 
HRP-coupled secondary antibodies (Pierce); and 
visualized by enhanced chemiluminescence (Pierce). </p>

<p>Reverse transcriptase-PCR </p>

<p>Total RNA was isolated using Trizol reagent (Qiagen) and 
reverse transcribed using moloney murine leukemia virus 
reverse transcriptase (Roche). Quantitative PCR were per-
formed using qPCR-SYBR-Green (Roche). Primers 
ordered from Biomers were designed using '<rs id="software-2" type="software">Universal 
Probe Library Assay Design Center</rs>' Software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Roche</rs>). 
Primer sequences are given in Supplementary Table S2. 
Quantification of gene regulation was performed by the 
ÁÁCp method using RPL13 as house-keeping gene. </p>

<p>Chromatin immunoprecipitation </p>

<p>Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) experiments were 
performed using the ChIP-IT 
Õ Express Chromatin 
Immunoprecipitation Kit and the Re-ChIP-IT 
Õ magnetic 
chromatin re-immunoprecipitation kit from Active Motif, 
according to the manufacturer's protocol with slight 
modifications: after enzymatic digestion for 10 min, the 
chromatin was sheared by two cycles of sonication (10 
pulses each cycle) in the same buffer. The chromatin was 
precleared for 2 h with protein G microbeads (Invitrogen) 
and then incubated with rabbit polyclonal anti-p65 
antibody sc-372 (2 mg/ml; Santa Cruz Biotechnology), 
mouse monoclonal anti-NFATc1 antibody 7A6 (4 mg/ml; 
Alexis), mouse IgG (Dianova) or normal rabbit serum 
(Pierce) at the appropriate concentrations for 4 h 
followed by incubation with protein G microbeads for 
1 h. The amount of precipitated DNA was evaluated by 
quantitative PCR using the Roche Light Cycler LC480. 
The used primers and primer positions are depicted in 
Figure 6 and presented in Supplementary Table S3. The 
relative amount of precipitated DNA was calculated using 
the following formula: E </p>

<p>(crossing point 1/10 total input À crossing </p>

<p>point sample) and is depicted as amount of precipitated 
genomic DNA relative to that precipitated by control 
antibodies (mouse IgG or normal rabbit serum). 
E = efficiency of the PCR determined by serial dilutions 
of total input. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>NFAT and NF-iB inhibitors restrain the inducible 
expression of BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 in T cells </p>

<p>To elicit the signaling pathways controlling the octamer-
dependent transcription in T cells, human Jurkat T cells 
were stably transfected with a luciferase reporter construct 
harboring four consecutive sequences bearing the octamer 
binding motif ATGCAAAT in front of a luciferase gene. 
As expected, the octamer activity was strongly 
upregulated on treatment with P/I but remained un-
affected by stimulation with either P or I alone, suggesting 
the requirement of a combined calcium influx and protein 
kinase C activation for octamer-dependent transcription 
in T cells (Figure 1A). Several transcription factors are 
known to depend on such a combinatorial calcium and 
protein kinase C signaling, including NF-kB and NFAT. 
To further specify the signaling pathways controlling 
octamer-dependent transcription, we used a panel of 
specific pharmacological inhibitors. Indeed, complete sup-
pression of the inducible octamer activity was seen when 
the cells were pre-treated with the CN inhibitor CsA. Also 
the NF-kB inhibitor Bay11-7082 and the p38 inhibitor 
SB203580 interfered with the inducible octamer activity, 
although less efficiently. These data suggest that Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>/CN, 
NF-kB and mitogen activated protein kinase-dependent 
signaling pathways are involved in the regulation of 
octamer-dependent transcriptional activity (Figure 1A). 
We next wondered whether the same pharmacological 
inhibitors could influence the activity of the known 
BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter. Therefore, a reporter construct 
harboring the previously described 1500 bp BOB.1/OBF.1 
promoter (34) was transiently transfected into Jurkat 
T cells, which were either left untreated or pre-treated 
with inhibitors for CN, NF-kB or p38 for 30 min before 
the stimulation with P/I. These experiments revealed 
that the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter is sensitive to all of the 
analysed inducers and inhibitors, similar to the 
octamer-dependent reporter (Figure 1B). To explore 
whether protein expression of BOB.1/OBF.1 mirrors its 
promoter activity, Jurkat T cells and primary CD4 
+ cells 
isolated from lymph nodes of C57BL/6 wild-type mice 
were either left untreated or pre-treated for 30 min with 
the inhibitors used in the previous experiments and subse-
quently stimulated with P/I. Interestingly, we found a 
striking coregulation of Oct2 and BOB.1/OBF.1 in 
Jurkat (Figure 1C and D) and primary CD4 
+ T cells 
(Figure 1E and F). Thus, the same inducers and inhibitors 
control the expression of Oct2 and BOB.1/OBF.1 at 
protein and mRNA levels. However, although the 
BOB.1/OBF.1 expression was completely abolished by 
treatment of Jurkat or CD4 
+ T cells with CsA even at 
low concentrations (50-100 ng/ml), low levels of Oct2 ex-
pression were still detectable (Figure 1C and E). In 
contrast, the NF-kB inhibitor Bay11-7082 had only a 
moderate influence on BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 expression 
in Jurkat T cells even at high concentrations (2-4 mM), 
whereas in primary CD4 
+ T cells, the inhibition of the 
NF-kB pathway led to an almost complete abrogation 
of Oct2 expression and to a marked reduction in BOB.1/ 
OBF.1 expression at low concentrations (1 mM) of the </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 4 2141 </p>

<p>inhibitor. The insufficient block of BOB.1/OBF.1 and 
Oct2 expression by Bay11-7082 might be owing to a 
residual NF-kB activity, as seen in EMSA experiments 
(Supplementary Figure S1). However, higher concentra-
tions of the inhibitor Bay11-7082 were toxic for primary 
T cells. Also, pre-treatment of primary CD4 
+ T cells with 
CN inhibitors CsA or FK506 or by the NF-kB inhibitor 
Bay11-7082 completely inhibited the strong BOB.1/OBF.1 
and Oct2 induction seen after the more physiological 
stimulation with anti-CD3 and anti-CD28 antibodies 
(Figure 1G and H). The p38 inhibitor SB-203580 had a 
moderate effect on BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 expression 
only at higher concentrations (Figure 1C), suggesting a 
rather minor and/or indirect effect of p38 on the regula-
tion of octamer-dependent transcription in T cells. </p>

<p>Interestingly, EMSA studies (Supplementary Figure S1) 
revealed that the NF-kB inhibitor Bay11-7082 inhibits 
additionally NFAT binding to DNA and, vice versa, the 
CN inhibitors CsA and FK506 interfere with NFAT 
binding but also with the NF-kB signaling pathway, as 
it was described recently (44,45). Therefore, the observed 
effect of CsA and FK506 on BOB.1/OBF.1 expression is 
not only mediated by inhibiting NFAT activity, as these 
compounds also affect the activity of NF-kB, but rather 
by the combined activity of NFAT and NF-kB. However, 
treatment of murine primary CD4 
+ T cells or transfected 
Jurkat cells with specific NFAT and NF-kB signaling 
pathway inhibitors, like the NFAT inhibitory peptide 
11 R-VIVIT and the NF-kB essential modulator 
(NEMO)-binding 
peptide, 
respectively, 
clearly </p>

<p>Figure 1. Inhibition of octamer function by CsA, p38 and NF-kB inhibitors in T cells. (A) A luciferase reporter construct bearing four copies of the 
consensus octamer element was stabily transfected into Jurkat T cells. Cells were either left untreated or stimulated with P, I alone or together (P/I), 
or were pretreated with CsA (100 ng/ml), SB203580 (20 mM) or Bay11-7082 (2 mM) before the stimulation with P/I. Mean values ± s.d. of five 
experiments are shown. (B and J) The 1500 bp BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter construct cloned in front of a luciferase gene was transfected together with 
the appropriate empty vector (ev) into Jurkat T cells that were subsequently treated as described in (A) or as indicated. The determined relative 
luciferase activity of the empty vector without stimulation was set one, and the fold increase of the promoter activity was calculated. Mean values ± 
s.d. of three (in B) and two (in J) independent experiments are shown. The analyses of the pTATA promoter construct served as internal control. (C-
I) Jurkat or isolated primary CD4+ T cells were treated as indicated. After 18 h of stimulation, cells were harvested. One part was used for protein 
extraction and immunoblotting (C, E, G, I), and the other half was used for RNA isolation and quantitative RT-PCR (D, F, H) for the detection of 
BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 mRNA expression levels that were determined relative to the expression of the housekeeping gene RPL13. Analyses of 
HPRT mRNA expression also normalized to RPL13 expression served as internal control (data not shown). The analyses of ERK2 expression (C, E, 
G, I) served as loading control. </p>



<p>demonstrates that both pathways are involved in the regu-
lation of BOB.1/OBF.1 expression via the regulation of 
BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity (Figure 1I and J). </p>

<p>The BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter contains several binding sites 
for NFAT and NF-iB </p>

<p>Previously, the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter was analysed to 
identify regulatory elements responsible for its activity in 
B cells (34-36). In those studies, a functional cAMP 
responsive element-binding protein (CREB)/Activating 
Transcription Factor (ATF) site could be identified, 
which is crucial for the B lymphocyte specific activity of 
the promoter. In addition, a sequence related to a NFAT 
binding site was described, however without any func-
tional relevance for the B cell-specific BOB.1/OBF.1 
promoter activity. In search for possible additional tran-
scription factor binding sites using the <rs type="software">Genomatrix</rs> 
Software, we identified two combined NFAT/NF-kB 
binding sites within the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter. Both 
newly identified sites are conserved between rat, mouse 
and man, suggesting a possible functional relevance of 
these regulatory elements. In contrast to B cells, where a 
function of the predicted NFAT binding site has not been 
revealed (34), an inducible complex formation could be 
detected after P/I treatment of primary CD4 
+ T cells. 
This complex resembles that formed at the NFAT site of 
the IL2 promoter used in control experiments (Figure 2B, 
lane 2; and C, lane 2). In addition, an inducible complex </p>

<p>formation could also be observed using the newly 
identified combined composite and consecutive NFAT/ 
NF-kB sites of the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter as probes 
(Figure 2D and E, lane 2). In supershift experiments, 
antibodies against NF-kB p50 were able to compete 
against the observed inducible complexes formed at the 
predicted NFAT/NF-kB binding sites within the BOB.1/ 
OBF.1 promoter (Figure 2D and E, lane 3) in a similar 
way like anti-p50 antibodies prevent p50 binding to a con-
sensus NF-kB site (Figure 2F, lane 3). Interestingly, 
anti-p50 antibodies are also able to interfere with the in-
ducible complex formed at the predicted NFAT site of the 
BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter (Figure 2B, lane 3) and with the 
NFAT binding observed at the IL2 promoter site (Figure 
2C, lane 3). Similarly, anti-p65 antibodies interfere with 
binding to the consecutive and composite NFAT/NF-kB 
sites, which is comparable with the competition seen at the 
consensus NF-kB site (Figure 2D, E and F, lane 4). 
Additionally, anti-p65 antibodies also interfere with the 
complex formation on the NFAT site of the BOB.1/ 
OBF.1 and IL2 promoters (Figure 2B and C, lane 4). 
The use of NFATc1 antibodies reduces the binding to 
the NFAT and NFAT/NF-kB sites of the BOB.1/OBF.1 
promoter and generates supershifted complexes (marked 
by clamp in Figure 2B, D and E, lane 5). Also, NFATc2 
antibodies prevent complex formation to these specific 
sites (Figure 2B, D and E, lane 6). Control experiments 
using IgG antibodies or normal rabbit serum revealed the </p>

<p>Figure 1. Continued. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 4 2143 </p>

<p>specificity of antibody binding (Supplementary Figure S2). 
Moreover, unlabeled oligonucleotides bearing the consen-
sus NFAT or NF-kB binding site could efficiently 
compete against labeled NFAT or NFAT/NF-kB sites 
identified in the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter (Supplementary 
Figure S2). Together, our data suggest that NFAT and 
NF-kB family members are able to bind to all of these 
newly identified potential cis-acting elements of the 
BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter in vitro. </p>

<p>Newly identified NFAT/NF-iB binding sites contribute to 
BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity </p>

<p>To demonstrate the importance of the potential NFAT 
or NFAT/NF-kB binding site for the BOB.1/OBF.1 
promoter activity, mutation analyses were performed. In 
these experiments, specific point mutations were </p>

<p>introduced to prevent either NFAT or NF-kB binding 
to these sites (Figure 3). Point mutation (G!T; Figure 
3A) within the previously identified NFAT motif within 
the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter did not lead to alterations in 
complex binding to this site. However, introduction of a 
point mutation (G!T) within the second core motif for 
NFAT and NF-kB clearly prevents inducible by P/I 
complex formation, indicating the importance of this 
residue within this potential transcription factor binding 
site (Figure 3B). Within the consecutive NFAT/NF-kB 
binding site of the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter, both muta-
tions, preventing NF-kB (GG!TT) and NFAT binding 
(CC!AA), abolish inducible complex formation on treat-
ment of T cells with P/I (Figure 3C). Therefore, both sites 
possibly contribute to the inducible BOB.1/OBF.1 
promoter activity in T cells. In contrast, although muta-
tions of critical residues within the NF-kB motif </p>

<p>Figure 2. Inducible complex formation on potential NFAT and NF-kB sites within the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter. (A) Schematic representation of the 
murine BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter. Indicated are the positions of the TATA box, of the CREB/ATF binding site and the positions/sequences of the 
potential NFAT and NF-kB sites. (B-F) Primary murine CD4+ T cells were either left untreated or stimulated for 18 h with P/I. Whole protein 
extracts were prepared and analysed in EMSA. In supershift experiments, the indicated antibodies were used. </p>



<p>(GG!TT) of the composite NFAT/NF-kB site within the 
BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter lead to a clear reduction of 
complex binding on P/I treatment of CD4 
+ T cells, 
mutations within the potential NFAT binding site 
(CC!TT) slightly enhance the ability of complex 
binding to this site (Figure 3D). For comparison, the </p>

<p>mutated consensus NFAT and NF-kB sites were also 
analysed (Figure 3E). 
Additionally, the introduction of mutations into the 
1500 bp BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter construct that was 
cloned in front of a luciferase gene and transfected into 
Jurkat T cells (Figure 3F) revealed that all three newly </p>

<p>Figure 3. Mutation analyses of potential NFAT and NF-kB sites within the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter. (A) Potential NFAT and NF-kB sites within 
the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter as well as consensus NFAT and NF-kB site were mutated as indicated and used (B-E) in EMSA experiments together 
with whole cell extracts of isolated murine CD4+ T cells that were either left untreated or were stimulated for 18 h with P/I as indicated. (F) Potential 
NFAT and NF-kB sites within the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter that was cloned in front of a luciferase gene were mutated as indicated. Mutated 
constructs were transfected into Jurkat T cell that were subsequently stimulated with P/I over night. The percentage inhibition of promoter activity 
was calculated relative to the activity of the wild-type 1500 bp BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter was set as 100%. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 4 2145 </p>

<p>identified NFAT and NFAT/NF-kB site are important for 
full BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity, as mutation of each 
reduces BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity by $15-20%. 
Mutation of all three NFAT/NF-kB sites led to a reduc-
tion of BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity by 40%. 
Interestingly, additional mutation of the previously 
identified CREB/ATF site, important for BOB.1/OBF.1 
promoter activity in B cells, almost completely abrogates 
BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity in T cells. </p>

<p>A 500 bp sequence is necessary and sufficient for the 
highest inducible BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity in 
Jurkat T cells </p>

<p>For the full activity of the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter in B 
cells, a sequence spanning 1500 bp was identified (34). To 
define regions important for the inducible activity in T 
cells, additionally a shorter promoter construct was 
generated encompassing $500 bp upstream of the start 
site of transcription of the BOB.1/OBF.1 gene </p>

<p>(Figure 4A). To compare the behavior of these constructs 
with respect to the basal and inducible BOB.1/OBF.1 
promoter activity in B and T cells, the constructs were 
transfected into Namalwa B or Jurkat T cells. In accord-
ance with previous findings (34), the 1500 bp promoter 
showed the highest basal activity in Namalwa B cells 
that could be further increased (3-fold) by treatment of 
cells with P/I (Figure 4B and C). In B cells, the activity 
of 500 bp construct was $3 times lower when compared 
with the 1500 bp fragment with respect to basal and indu-
cible promoter activity. As expected, in T cells, no basal 
BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity could be observed. 
However, it was strongly induced when cells were 
treated with P/I (Figure 4C). Notably, in T cells, the 
500 bp promoter construct showed the highest inducibility 
after P/I treatment (Figure 4B and C). The importance of 
the 500 bp sequence of the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter was 
further underscored by deleting this promoter element, 
which led to the complete loss of basal and inducible 
BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity in B and T cells </p>

<p>Figure 4. The BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter spanning 500 bp is necessary and sufficient for full inducible activity in T cells. (A) Schematic representation 
of the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter. The positions of the analysed cis-elements and of the promoter fragments used in reporter assays are indicated. 
(B and C) Namalwa B and Jurkat T cells were transiently transfected with the empty vector (ev) or with reporter constructs bearing either the 
1500 bp or the 500 bp BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter construct or a deletion mutant of the longer version were the first 500 bp are missing (1500Á500 bp). 
The relative luciferase activity (B) or the fold induction (C) of different promoter fragments was determined without or after stimulation of cells with 
P/I, were in the second case the fold induction was determined relative to the luciferase activity of the empty vector without stimulation that was set 
to one. (D) Jurkat T cells were transiently transfected with either the empty vector or the 1500 or 500 bp BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter constructs as 
indicated, either alone or together with expression vectors for NFATc1, RelA or combination of both. Transfected cells were either left untreated or 
stimulated subsequently with P/I. Next day, the cells were harvested to determine the relative luciferase activity. The relative luciferase activity 
resulting from the transfection of the empty vector without induction was set to one. The fold induction relative to the empty vector was calculated 
and is depicted. (B-D) Shown are the mean values ± s.d. of three independently performed experiments. </p>



<p>(Figure 4B and C). This loss of activity was not caused by 
the deletion of regulatory elements necessary for the re-
cruitment of the basal transcriptional complex, as the 
fusion of the same promoter construct to a TATA box 
element of the thymidine kinase promoter did also not 
lead to enhanced BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity in T 
cells (Supplementary Figure S3). 
To investigate the contribution of NFAT and NF-kB to 
the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity in T cells, Jurkat cells 
were transfected with the 500 bp or 1500 bp BOB.1/OBF.1 
promoter constructs, together with expression vectors 
for NFATc1 or RelA/p65. Although overexpression of 
NFATc1 had only a moderate effect, overexpression of 
RelA/p65 already significantly enhanced the inducible 
activities of the 1500 and 500 bp promoters. Coexpression 
of both factors together leads to a further increase of 
BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity, although this effect was 
modest (Figure 4D). Again, the 500 bp promoter construct 
was sufficient to achieve full BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter 
activity induced by NFAT/NF-kB overexpression. 
In B cells, the CREB/ATF site was found to be import-
ant for BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity. To investigate 
whether this site is also important for the inducible expres-
sion of BOB.1/OBF.1 in T cells, the 1500 bp promoter 
construct was transfected into Jurkat T cells, together 
with expression vectors coding for NFATc1, RelA/p65 
or a constitutive active version of CREB either alone or 
in different combinations of these vectors. Also in T cells, 
the CREB/ATF site seems to be of relevance, as 
overexpression of a constitutive active CREB protein 
leads to a significant increase of BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter 
activity that was further enhanced by overexpression of 
NFAT and NF-kB (Supplementary Figure S4). These 
data together with our data obtained from EMSA and 
transfection experiments in that the CREB site was 
inactivated indicate that this CREB site is also of consid-
erable importance for BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity in 
T cells. </p>

<p>Modulation of NFAT activity interferes with the 
expression levels of BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 </p>

<p>One major regulator of NFAT activity is the Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>/ 
calmodulin-dependent protein phosphatase CN that 
dephosphorylates cytosolic NFAT proteins. NFAT, in 
turn, translocates into the nucleus where it binds to 
DNA and regulates gene expression, a process that can 
be efficiently inhibited by CsA. Down modulation of 
CN by Amaxa transfection of siRNA directed against 
the isoforms a and b of the catalytic subunit CN A 
revealed a clear dependence of BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 
expression on CN activity (Figure 5A). Obviously, 
Amaxa transfection of the indicated siRNA itself 
pre-activated Jurkat T cells, as BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 
expression could be detected even in the unstimulated 
state. However, the expression of both proteins could 
be further enhanced by P/I treatment. Although the 
downregulation of CN expression was incomplete, a 
clear inhibition of inducible BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 ex-
pression could be observed, indicating the importance of 
CN for BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 expression in T cells. </p>

<p>In peripheral T cells, mainly two members of the NFAT 
family are expressed, NFATc1 and NFATc2. On T cell 
activation, the NFATc1 isoform NFATc1/aA is predom-
inantly expressed (56). To study the influence of NFAT on 
BOB.1/OBF.1 or Oct2 expression, human A3.01 T cells 
were retrovirally infected using vectors expressing either 
the NF1ATc1/aA or NFATc1/aC isoform that were fused 
to a part of the modified hormone binding domain of the 
estrogen receptor a (ERa) (54), which is controlled by 
OH-Tamoxifen (OHT). Although the OHT treatment of 
cells infected with the empty vector left BOB.1/OBF.1 and 
Oct2 expression unaffected, a significant increase in their 
protein expression level could be observed when NFATc1/ 
aA or NFATc1/aC became functional active in the 
presence of OHT (Figure 5B).To test whether the 
absence of endogenous NFAT protein expression would 
influence BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 expression, CD4 
+ T 
cells were isolated from Nfatc2 
À/À xNfatc1 
flx/flx xCD4-Cre 
mice in which all T cells are devoid of the expression of 
NFATc1 and NFATc2. After stimulation of purified 
CD4 
+ T cells with either P/I or aCD3+aCD28 for 18 h, 
the mRNA expression of BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 was 
analysed by quantitative PCR. The mRNA levels of 
BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 were sensitive to the combined 
ablation of NFATc1 and NFATc2 protein expression 
(Figure 5C and D), indicating the importance of these 
factors for octamer-dependent transcription in T cells. </p>

<p>Modulation of NF-iB activity affects the expression levels 
of BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 </p>

<p>Next, we investigated the influence of the NF-kB activity 
on 
BOB.1/OBF.1 
or 
Oct2 
expression. 
First, 
NEMO-deficient or wild-type Jurkat cells were stimulated 
with P/I. Western blot analysis revealed a clear depend-
ence of BOB.1/OBF.1 expression on the presence of 
NEMO in T cells (Figure 6A). NEMO is essential for 
the canonical NF-kB signaling, as its deficiency leads 
to a specific block of IKK (IkB kinase) activity (48). 
Therefore, these findings clearly indicate a contribution 
of NF-kB to the regulation of BOB.1/OBF.1 gene 
transcription. 
In another approach, human A3.01 T cells were 
retrovirally transduced using vectors expressing either a 
constitutive active version (EE) or a kinase dead mutant 
(KD) of IKK2 (55) (Figure 6B). In EMSA, the modula-
tion of NF-kB activity was monitored. Overexpression of 
a kinase dead version of IKK2 led to a clear reduction in 
the inducible NF-kB binding activity, whereas over-
expressing a constitutive active IKK2 led to an enhanced 
basal and inducible NF-kB activity. In EMSA, a clear 
correlation between NF-kB and Oct2 binding activity to 
the appropriate consensus DNA binding sites could be 
observed. Again, western blot analyses revealed a clear 
dependence of the expression level of BOB.1/OBF.1 and 
Oct2 on the level of NF-kB activity. To analyse the effect 
of defective NF-kB activity on BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 
expression in vivo, we have used RelA/p65-deficient mice 
that were bred into the TNFR type 1 (TNFRI; Tumor 
Necrosis Factor Receptor I)-deficient background to 
overcome the TNF-a-induced liver toxicity and embryonic </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 4 2147 </p>

<p>lethality (57) observed in RelA/p65 
À/À mice (58). CD4 
+ T 
cells were isolated from lymph nodes of mice deficient for 
TNFRI and RelA/p65 (double knock out) or from mice 
that were wild-type or heterozygous for one or the other 
or both genes and stimulated with P/I for 18 h. When the 
expression of RelA/p65 was abolished, the expression of 
BOB.1/OBF.1 was almost completely restrained, whereas 
Oct2 protein is still detectable, although the level of ex-
pression was severely reduced (Figure 6C). Together, these 
data indicate an essential role of NF-kB signaling for the 
induction of Oct2 and BOB.1/OBF.1 expression in T cells. 
To address the question whether the loss or gain of NF-
kB or NFAT transcription factors leads to changes in 
expression and/or binding activity of the other factor, 
we have used the advantage of CD4 
+ T cells obtained 
from mice bearing genetic mutations either for 
NFATc1/NFATc2 or for TNFRI/p65. Additionally, we </p>

<p>overexpressed NFATc1A and RelA/p65 in Jurkat T cells 
(Supplementary Figure S5). Interestingly, these experi-
ments revealed that the deletion or overexpression of 
NFAT does not significantly lead to changes neither in 
NF-kB p65 expression as seen in western blot ana-
lyses nor in NF-kB binding activity analysed in EMSA 
experiments using a consensus NF-kB binding site 
(Supplementary Figure S5A and C). However, deletion 
of RelA/p65 in primary CD4 
+ T cells leads to a clear re-
duction of NFATc1 expression and consequently to a con-
siderable reduction in NFAT binding activity to the DNA 
motif of the IL2 promoter. Vice versa, overexpression of 
RelA/p65 in Jurkat cells clearly enhances NFAT binding 
activity (Supplementary Figure S5B and C). These data 
indicate that the observed effect on BOB.1/OBF.1 and 
Oct2 expression in TNFRI/p65 double deficient murine 
CD4 
+ T cells and in human Jurkat or A3.01 T cells </p>

<p>Figure 5. CN and NFAT factors control the inducible BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 expression in T cells. (A) Jurkat T cells were nucleoporated either 
with scrambled siRNA or siRNA pools directed against the a and b isoforms of CN A subunit (CN A a+b). Subsequently, cells were stimulated for 
8 h with P/I. Whole cell extracts were prepared and used for protein expression analyses of CN A a+b, BOB.1/OBF.1 or Oct2 by immunoblotting. 
The detection of ERK2 expression served as loading control. (B) Human A3.01 T cells were infected retrovirally with vectors expressing either the 
NF1ATc1/aA-ER or NFATc1/aC-ER or just the empty control vector (HA-ER). Afterwards, cells were either left untreated or treated with OHT, I, 
P/I or with combinations of these inducers as indicated. After 18 h of stimulation, cells were harvested and subjected for immunoblotting, using 
primary antibodies against NFATc1, BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2. The detection of ERK2 expression levels served as loading control. (C and D) Primary 
CD4+ T cells were isolated from wild-type (wt) or mutant mice in which the expression of NFATc1 and NFATc2 was simultaneously deleted in T 
cells specifically (NFATc1c2-double knock out). After stimulation of cells with P/I or with aCD3+aCD28 antibodies for 18 h cells were harvested to 
analyse BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 expression at mRNA levels by quantitative RT-PCR. The relative mRNA expression levels are expressed relative to 
that determined in unstimulated wild-type cells that were set as one. The experiments were performed twice in triplicates and using different dilutions 
of the cDNA reveling the same result. One representative experiment is depicted as mean values ± s.d. </p>



<p>expressing various mutants interfering with NF-kB 
signaling (Figure 6) could be mediated, at least in part, 
also by changes in NFAT activity. </p>

<p>Analyses of contribution of NFAT and NF-iB to the 
BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity in vivo </p>

<p>To clarify whether the observed NFAT and NF-kB effects 
on BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 expression are direct or rather 
indirect, primary CD4 
+ T cells were used in ChIP experi-
ments in which a fragment encompassing 189 bp from the 
first 500 bp of the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter containing the 
already described NFAT binding site was analysed. 
Additionally, a second fragment of 161 bp was analysed 
containing the combined NFAT/NF-kB sites described 
here. The locations of analysed binding sites and of 
primers used for amplification of genomic DNA are 
depicted in Figure 7A. After induction with P/I, both frag-
ments of the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter could be efficiently 
enriched by NFATc1 and RelA/p65 antibodies (Figure 7B </p>

<p>and C), indicating that NFAT and NF-kB transcription 
factors exert a direct effect on the BOB.1/OBF.1 
promoter. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Stimulation of the TCR triggers the activation of different 
signaling cascades leading finally to the activation of 
NFAT, NF-kB and AP-1, which act together with 
several other transcription factors to orchestrate gene ex-
pression important for T cell function, survival, prolifer-
ation and differentiation. Oct2 and BOB.1/OBF.1 are 
among these induced genes in activated T helper cells. 
Owing to their ability to act in concert at the octamer 
motif identified within the promoter region of the IFN 
gene (33), BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 are important for the 
balanced TH1 and TH2 cytokine secretion by T helper 
cells. While investigating signaling pathways, which 
regulate octamer-dependent transcription, we found that </p>

<p>Figure 6. NF-kB activity influences BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 expression levels in T cells. Wild-type (wt) or NEMO-deficient (NEMOÀ/À) Jurkat T 
cells were stimulated for the time indicated with P/I or left untreated. The expression of BOB.1/OBF.1 was analysed by western blotting. (B) Human 
A3.01 T cells were retrovirally infected using vectors expressing either a constitutive active version of IKK2 (EE), a kinase dead version (KD) or the 
empty vector (ev). After selection, cells were stimulated with P/I for 18 h and subsequently analysed for the protein expression levels of BOB.1/OBF.1 
and Oct2 by western blotting (WB). The detection of IKK or ERK2 expression levels served as internal control or loading control experiments, 
respectively. Additionally, the same extracts were used in EMSA to monitor the NF-kB and Oct2 binding activity to DNA using labeled consensus 
sites. (C) Primary CD4+ T cells of mice of the indicated genotype were either left untreated or stimulated with P/I for 18 h. Afterwards, the protein 
expression levels of BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 were analysed in immunoblots. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 4 2149 </p>

<p>Figure 7. NFAT and NF-kB transcription factors bind to different BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter regions in vivo. (A) The nucleotide sequence of the 
analysed mouse BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter region is depicted. The NFAT and the predicted combined NFAT/NF-kB sites are shown. The position of 
used primers for amplification of DNA fragments after chromatin immunoprecipitation are shown with bold, italic letters. Underlined letters indicate 
the position of the TATA box. The start site of transcription is marked as +1. (B and C) Murine primary CD4+ T cells were treated for 18 h with P/ 
I. The chromatin was cross-linked, sheared and immunoprecipitated using the indicated antibodies. Immunoprecipitations using mouse IgG or 
normal rabbit serum served as negative controls. Immunoprecipitated DNA was purified and used as template in quantitative PCR reactions using 
primers as indicated in (A) for the detection of fragments bearing either the NFAT site (B) or both combined NFAT/NF-kB sites (C). (D) As an 
internal control, precipitated DNA was amplified using primers (Supplementary Table S3) located upstream of analysed potential NFAT and NF-kB 
sites of the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter. </p>



<p>the expression of BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 critically 
depends on the expression and function of CN. Down 
modulation or inhibition of the Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>/calmodulin-depend-
ent serine/threonine-specific protein phosphatase using 
either siRNA or CsA attenuated the expression of both 
proteins. The fact that CsA affects NFAT and NF-kB 
activity (43-45) prompted us to investigate the involve-
ment of both signaling cascades in the regulation of 
BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 expression in T cells. Using 
NEMO and NFAT inhibitory peptides, blocking the 
NF-kB and the NFAT pathway in a specific manner, 
revealed that both transcriptional activities are involved 
that process. 
Indeed, we found several transcription factor binding 
sites within the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter region conserved 
between mouse and man that can be bound on stimulation 
by both NFAT and NF-kB family members in vitro and 
in vivo. The most distally located 'composite' NFAT/NF-
kB site (see Figure 2A) contains the classical NFAT core 
motif TTTCC that is also found in the distal promoter of 
the IL2 gene and an adjacent overlapping NF-kB binding 
motif AGGTGT that was recently described as an active 
NF-kB site within the human prostatic acid phosphatase 
gene promoter (59). Composite NFAT/NF-kB binding 
sites are described for numerous of promoters. For those 
identified within the HIV LTR and the human IL8 
promoter binding of NFATc2 as a homodimer has been 
detected (60,61). Others have shown that NFATc2 
competes for binding with NF-kB to the composite 
NFAT/NF-kB site within the HIV LTR (62), indicating 
that either NFAT or NF-kB factors bind to this site. 
Indeed, there is no experimental evidence for a 
heterodimer formation between NFAT and NF-kB 
family members. Although in supershift experiments, 
antibodies against NF-kB and NFAT are able to 
prevent inducible complex formation on this composite 
NFAT/NF-kB site, introduction of specific mutations 
revealed that rather NF-kB than NFAT transcription 
factors are bound to this site. 
The second combined, 'consecutive' NFAT/NF-kB site 
also contains the classical NFAT core motif TTTCC that 
is followed at the 5 
0 site by the sequence 5 
0 -GGGAATCG 
CA-3 
0 . The latter represents the canonical NF-kB decamer 
from position 1 to 6 and bears also a cytidine at position 9. 
At such consecutive sites, NFAT and NF-kB complexes 
can be formed simultaneously, not competing for binding 
among each other. However, in Re-ChIP experiments, we 
were not able to show the mutual binding of NFATc1 
together with RelA/p65 (data not shown) to this site. 
Yet, both the NF-kB and the NFAT motif are important 
for transcription factor binding, as individual mutation of 
both motifs prevents inducible by P/I complex formation. 
The third important site for the regulation of BOB.1/ 
OBF.1 promoter activity is the already described 
non-consensus NFAT binding site GAAGAAA that has 
no functional relevance for the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter 
activity in B cells (34). In contrast, in T cells, an inducible 
complex formation could be detected to this site in vitro. 
Moreover, a 500 bp BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter construct 
bearing this site was sufficient for full inducible 
promoter activity in T cells that could be further </p>

<p>enhanced by cotransfection of expression vectors for 
NFATc1 and RelA/p65. Cotransfection of both expres-
sion vectors together could further increase the promoter 
activity in comparison with that achieved by an individual 
overexpression of each factor, indicating that both cooper-
ate in the regulation of the 500 bp BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter 
activity. Additionally, supershift experiments and chroma-
tin immunoprecipitations revealed a binding of both, 
NFAT and NF-kB, to this part of the promoter. Hence, 
a not-yet identified NF-kB binding site should be present 
in close proximity to the mentioned non-canonical NFAT 
site. Because of a high homology between the DNA 
binding domains of NF-kB and NFAT family members, 
they generate a similar conformation and therefore 
contact identical nucleotides at the core motif GGAAA 
(63). The non-canonical NFAT site GAAGAAA within 
the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter is followed by the sequence A 
AAAAAG (Figure 2A). Both sites share high similarity 
with the core sequence GGAAA to which both factors, 
NF-kB and NFAT, are able to bind. The second motif 
AAAG seems to be of biologically relevance, as the 
point mutation G!T prevents inducible complex 
binding in T cells. Possibly, this part of the BOB.1/ 
OBF.1 promoter is essential for the cooperative action 
of NFAT and NF-kB necessary for the high inducible 
activity of the 500 bp promoter. 
Additionally, the CREB/ATF binding site, important 
for the promoter activity in B cells (34), seems also to be 
relevant in T cells, as overexpression of an active version 
of CREB further increased the NFAT/NF-kB induced 
BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity in Jurkat T cells, 
whereas mutation of this site abrogates significantly 
BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity. Therefore, the observed 
decreasing effect of the p38 inhibitor SB203580 on the 
BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter and on the activity of 
octamer-dependent transcription in general could be 
mediated by the inhibition of CREB and/or ATF-1 that 
can also bind to the same site, as both factors need p38 
kinase function for full transcriptional activity (64). 
Otherwise, an inhibition of p38 could affect NFAT 
proteins, as p38-mediated signaling activates NFATc1 
(NFAT2) promoter activity and also increases its 
mRNA stability (65). 
Together, here we identified three different functional 
NF-kB binding sites close to NFAT binding sites import-
ant for BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity. One of these NF-
kB sites (identified in the composite NFAT/NF-kB site) 
was recently identified as an alternative NF-kB binding 
site different from the canonical, the second (identified 
in the consecutive NFAT/NF-kB site) shares high 
homology to the canonical site; however, there are vari-
ations within the second kB half-site, and the third 
(around the previously identified NFAT site) displays 
similarities to just the core motif to which NFAT and 
NF-kB proteins can bind. Indeed, deviations from the 
consensus NF-kB site were described for several pro-
moters leading finally to the modulation of the affinity 
of different factors of the family to the appropriate site 
(66) and also influences the composition of the interacting 
heterodimers bound [reviewed in (67)]. This leads to the 
assumption that the expression of BOB.1/OBF.1 is </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 4 2151 </p>

<p>differentially regulated under certain conditions, like 
primary or secondary T cell activation or in different T 
helper subtypes, by different homo-or heteromeric 
complexes that are bound to one or the other NF-kB 
site within the promoter. 
The fact that the NF-kB sites identified here are in close 
proximity to NFAT sites and thereby build either com-
posite or consecutive combined NFAT/NF-kB binding 
motifs suggests that either NFAT or NF-kB complexes 
or both together are able to transactivate the BOB.1/ 
OBF.1 promoter. This conclusion is in line with our 
overexpression data, where the modulation of NFAT or 
NF-kB activity alone has already significant influence on 
BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct2 expression. Additionally, the use 
of specific inhibitory peptides revealed that both the 
NFAT and the NF-kB signaling pathways are important 
for BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity and BOB.1/OBF.1 
expression in T cells. Otherwise, we were not able to 
show simultaneous binding of both NFAT and NF-kB 
factors in Re-ChIP experiments. The fact that the 
deletion of RelA/p65 leads to a complete loss of BOB.1/ 
OBF.1 expression in primary CD4 
+ T cells, whereas the 
deletion of NFATc1/c2 decreases BOB.1/OBF.1 expres-
sion by $50%, indicates that NF-kB activation is 
possibly of higher importance for sufficient BOB.1/ 
OBF.1 expression in T cells than NFAT factors. But the 
activity of NFAT and NF-kB depends on Ca 
2+ oscillation 
(68), which differs in different cell types, including TH1, 
TH2 and TH17 T helper subpopulations (69,70). This 
leads to distinct levels of NFAT and NF-kB nuclear lo-
calization and finally to differential cytokine expression by 
different T helper subtypes. Therefore, it seems likely that 
also the availability and activity of NFAT or NF-kB 
family members in different T helper subpopulations or 
under certain differentiation conditions may determine 
whether the one or the other or both factors together con-
tribute to the BOB.1/OBF.1 promoter activity in vivo. 
In fact, the regulation of BOB.1/OBF.1 expression in T 
cells seems to be complex, as in natural regulatory T cells 
(nTreg), its expression is down modulated (71), whereas in 
T cells, which are energized or suppressed by nTreg, its 
expression was found &gt;10 times higher than in 
non-suppressed CD4 
+ T cells (72). Although we have 
already described the importance of BOB.1/OBF.1 for 
balanced TH1/TH2 cytokine secretion (33), the precise 
regulation of BOB.1/OBF.1 and Oct expression in differ-
ent T helper subpopulations that possibly affects the 
induction of a different set of genes, remains to be 
elucidated. 
In summary, by an array of in vitro and in vivo 
approaches, we provide evidences for the importance of 
NFAT together with NF-kB transcription factors for the 
regulation of octamer-dependent transcription in T cells. 
Further work is required to identify the promoter region 
and regulatory cis-acting elements responsible for the Oct2 
gene regulation. Additionally, it will be interesting to 
address the question whether the same transcription 
factors/transcription factor binding sites, identified as im-
portant elements for the inducible BOB.1/OBF.1 expres-
sion in T cells, have also relevance for its basal and 
inducible expression in B cells. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online: 
Supplementary Tables 1-4 and Supplementary Figures 1-5. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors are very grateful to Alexander Mayer and 
to Nina Ushmorova for excellent help and technical 
assistance. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) [DFG; TR52, 
TP A3 to F.B.-S.], [DFG; TR52, TP B2; W. Sander and 
M. Schell foundations to E.S.], [DFG; SFB 497, TP C5 to 
T.W.], [DFG; BR-2891/4-1 to C.B.]. Funding for open 
access charge: Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) 
[BR-2891/4-1 to C.B.]. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>







<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 4 2153 </p>





</text></tei>