<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3805007" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. [Purpose] The job of secondary school teachers involves a lot of head down posture as frequent read-
ing, assignment correction, computer use and writing on a board put them at risk of developing occupational related 
neck pain. Available studies of neck pain experienced by teachers are limited. The purpose of this study was to 
determine whether training of deep cervical flexor muscles with pressure biofeedback has any significant advantage 
over conventional training for pain and disability experienced by school teachers with neck pain. [Subjects] Thirty 
teachers aged 25-45 years with neck pain and poor craniocervical flexion test participated in this study. [Methods] 
A pretest posttest experimental group design was used in which experimental group has received training with pres-
sure biofeedback and conventional exercises while control group received conventional exercises only. Measure-
ments of dependent variables were taken at baseline, and after 2 and 4 weeks of training. Pain intensity was assessed 
using a numeric pain rating scale and functional disability was assessed using the neck disability index. [Results] 
The data analysis revealed that there was significant improvement in pain and disability in both the groups and 
the results were better in the experimental group. [Conclusion] Addition of pressure biofeedback for deep cervical 
flexor muscles training gave a better result than conventional exercises alone. Feedback helps motor learning which 
is the set of processes associated with practice or experience leading to permanent changes in ability to respond. 
Neck pain (NP) is becoming increasingly prevalent in 
society. Estimates indicate that 67% of individuals will suf-
fer neck pain at some stage of their life 1) . NP is a significant 
health problem not only for adults but also for the young. 
The onset and course of NP is affected by multiple factors 
with physical, psychosocial and individual factors interact-
ing in the development of these disorders 2, 3) . 
Teaching is one of the professions in which NP is very 
common. It was found that 69.3% of secondary school 
teachers suffer from it 3) . The lifetime prevalence of NP in 
secondary school teachers is 68.2% 4) . The job nature of sec-
ondary school teachers involves a lot of head down posture, 
such as in frequent reading, assignment correction, and 
writing on the blackboard 5) . Thus, secondary school teach-
ers are at risk of developing occupationally related NP and 
upper limb pain. High workload, low colleague support, 
high anxiety and some psychological factors have been 
found to be significant risk factors for the development of 
NP in teachers 3) . The transition from conventional to mod-</p>

<p>ern methods of teaching is a major cause of teachers de-
veloping NP. Available studies of NP and its causes among 
teachers are limited. According to one study back pain, 
neck pain and headache, are the most common ailments of 
the workers in the school environment 20) . Another study of 
nursery school teachers found 26.5% of them complained 
of neck stiffness 5) . 
The learning environment for children is progressively 
being facilitated by new forms of information technol-
ogy (IT). Traditional methods of teaching, such as school 
textbooks, are gradually being enhanced and replaced by 
new forms of IT such as internet sources and interactive 
multimedia software. These initiatives have resulted in an 
increase in the number of classes that involve computing. 
Several studies have shown associations between physi-
cal exposures and neck/upper extremity symptoms during 
computer work 6, 7) . Long duration of computer work is asso-
ciated with prolonged periods of holding a static posture 2) , 
which is most pronounced in the neck and shoulder region, 
resulting in increased forward neck flexion and increased 
static muscle tension in this region 2, 8-10) . Increased forward 
neck flexion may result in increased tension in posture, sta-
bilizing muscles as well as increasing compression forces in 
the articulation of the cervical spine, resulting in a higher </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. 
25: 657-661, 2013 </p>

<p>* To whom correspondence should be addressed. 
E-mail: z_iqbal001@yahoo.com </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. Vol. 25, No. 6, 2013 </p>

<p>
risk of work related muscular disorders 2) . 
The Deep Cervical Flexor muscles (DCF) are considered 
to be an important stabilizer of the head-on-neck posture. 
It has been theorized that when muscle performance is im-
paired, the balance between the stabilizers on the posterior 
aspect of the neck and the DCFs will be disrupted, result-
ing in loss of proper alignment and posture, which is then 
likely to contribute to cervical impairment 10) . Therefore 
DCF training is recommended for increasing the endur-
ance of these postural muscles, leading to improvement in 
NP. Research recommends that training that emphasizes 
the correct use of DCF, before introducing strengthening 
of the global cervical spine musculature, is more effective 
in the rehabilitation of the cervical spine than nonspecific 
strengthening of neck muscles. The craniocervical flexion 
test (CCFT) regime appears to be an ideal strategy for spe-
cifically activating DCFs and reducing augmented activity 
of the SCM muscle. There is evidence that restoration of the 
supporting capacity of DCF parallels reduction in neck pain 
and cervicogenic headache. Hence, DCF muscle training is 
recommended for the clinical management of neck pain 11) . 
Jull et al. endorse a specific craniocervical flexion exer-
cise (CCFEx) protocol in the supine position. This program 
initially involves retraining a static holding contraction of 
the target muscles at a submaximal level to improve their 
tonic postural function. The type of training employed is 
based on the nature of the dysfunction presenting in these 
muscles 9, 12) , as well as their normal functional role 1) . These 
exercises constituted the conventional exercises of our 
study. 
The purpose of this study was to determine whether, 
there is an improvement in pain and disability of school 
teachers with NP after 4 weeks of deep cervical flexor train-
ing with pressure biofeedback. </p>

<p>Significance of study </p>

<p>In India, the teacher is considered equivalent to God. 
Thus future of students depends more or less on teachers. If 
teachers suffer, it directly affects the future of students as 
well. So, we need to make teachers physically, mentally and 
functionally better so that they can focus on the betterment 
of students. This study also emphasizes the role of DCF 
training in decreasing pain and disability among teachers. </p>

<p>SUBJECTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Thirty teachers (24 females and 6 males) aged group 
25 to 45 years participated in this study. The subjects were 
teachers of the Central Board of Secondary Education af-
filiated schools who had more than 5 years of experience. 
The teachers were included if they had a neck pain score on 
the numeric pain rating scale (NPRS) of greater than 5, mild 
to moderate disability scores on the neck disability Index 
(NDI) and poor CCF test results. Subjects were excluded if 
they had undergone any cervical spine surgery or reported 
any neurological signs. Subjects with a history of congeni-
tal or acquired postural deformity, spinal cord compression, 
tumor, instability, fracture, inflammatory disease or infec-
tion were also excluded. </p>

<p>The proposal for the study was presented before the Re-
view Committee of Hamdard University and received ap-
proval. 
A pretest, posttest experimental group design was used 
in the study. After selection, subjects were randomly allo-
cated to one of the two groups with 15 subjects in each: 
Group A: the experimental group received deep cervical 
flexor muscles training with pressure biofeedback and con-
ventional exercises. Group B: the control group received 
deep cervical flexor muscles training with only conven-
tional exercises. 
The independent variable in the study was DCF mus-
cles training and the dependent variables were pain (P) on 
NPRS, and functional disability (D) on NDI. 
We used a pressure stabilizer, Pressure Biofeedback Unit 
(Stabilizer TM, Chattanooga Group, INC., Chattanooga, 
TN), a height adjustable bed, markers and papers. 
A letter was sent to the principals of CBSE affiliated 
schools with details of the research and their consent was 
obtained. The study was conducted on school premises in 
the medical room. The teachers were selected based on in-
clusion and exclusion criteria. Then, their informed consent 
was sought. Selected subjects were randomly allocated to 
the two groups. Subjects were informed about nature and 
procedure of study and all their questions were answered. 
Baseline information of the dependent variables was tak-
en at the beginning of study, on day 1 (P0, D0), before com-
mencement of the training protocol. Data were collected at 
the end of 2 weeks of training (P14, D14) and at the end of 4 
weeks (P28, D38). NPRS and NDI were used to evaluate the 
level of pain and functional disability, respectively. 
Both experimental and control groups performed con-
ventional exercises. In addition the experimental group 
also performed deep cervical flexor muscles training using 
pressure biofeedback. The exercise session was conducted 
under the supervision of the examiner. Subjects were asked 
not to receive any other specific intervention for neck pain. 
Training was done for 4 weeks, 4 days a week with 2 min-
utes rest between sets. Exercise duration did not exceed 20 
minutes per day. The CCFT exercise program included 3 
sets in a session 10 repetitions per set. 
The data was analyzed using <rs type="software">SPSS</rs> software. The inde-
pendent t test was used to compare age and baseline values 
of pain and disability between groups. The paired t test was 
used to compare pain on NPRS and Disability on NDI with-
in groups. All dependent variables were compared between 
baseline, their values at 2 weeks and their values at end of 4 
weeks. The independent t test was used to compare pain on 
NPRS and disability on NDI between the groups. The val-
ues of both groups, group A and group B, were compared at 
baseline and for the difference from baseline, at the end of 
2 weeks and at the end of 4 weeks. We used 95% CI and the 
results were accepted as significant if p&lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Thirty teachers, 24 females and 6 males, participated in 
the study. Subjects had a mean age of 36.33±6.42 in group 
A and 36.40±5.99 in group B. Subject's characteristics were </p>



<p>homogenous at baseline. (All p&gt; 0.05) 
NDI: In the comparison of disability, values between the 
baseline (D0), after 2 weeks (D14) and after 4 weeks (D28), 
significant improvement was noted in both groups A and B 
(p&lt;0.05). The mean reduction in NDI scores in group A was 
6.715±0.67 at p= 0.000, and the mean reduction in group B 
was 2.207 ± 0.1059 at p = 0.000. 
The difference between D0 and D14 (D14-D0) for both 
groups A and B was significant (p=0.015). The difference 
between D14 and D28 (D28-D14) between the groups was 
significant (p=0.022). The difference between D0 and D28 
(D28-D0) between the groups was significant difference 
was obtained (p=0.003) (Table 1). 
NPRS: In the comparison of pain, the values at baseline 
(P0), after 2 weeks (P14) and after 4 weeks (P28), showed 
significant improvements in both groups A and B (p&lt;0.05). 
The mean reduction in NPRS scores in group A was 
3.137±0.41 and in group B was 1.797 ± 0.1514. 
The difference between P0 and P14 (P14-0) for both 
groups A and B was significant (p=0.05). The difference 
between P14 and P28 (P28-P14) between the groups was 
significant (p=0.04). The difference between P0 and P28 
(P28-P0) between the groups was significant (p=0.01) (Ta-
ble 2). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This study was designed to determine the effects of deep 
cervical flexor muscles training using pressure biofeedback 
on neck pain and disability experienced by school teachers 
with neck pain. The results of our study show that there was 
a significant change in both pain and disability in both the 
groups after the intervention. However, the experimental 
group showed better results than the control group in terms 
of reduction of pain and disability. 
The amount of NP and disability were not significantly 
different between the members of the two groups at the start 
of the study (baseline measurement). This could be attrib-
uted to the same nature of the duties performed by teachers 
at school. 
To our knowledge, this is the first study in which cranio-
cervical flexion training was given to teachers having neck 
pain. Therefore the lack of literature in this area limited the 
scope for direct comparison with other studies. The results 
of our study can be compared to other studies in a general </p>

<p>way only, due to differences in treatment protocols, subject 
population, measures taken, and duration of treatment. 
The level of pain decrease in both the groups was signifi-
cant. This is explained by research on mechanisms of pain 
reduction through exercises. The increase in endorphins 
that occurs after training and better neuromuscular control 
may decrease pain. Muscle contractions activate muscle 
ergoreceptors (stretch receptors). Afferent from these mus-
cles cause endogenous options to be released and also the 
beta-endorphins from the pituitary gland. These secretions 
may cause both peripheral and central pain to be blocked 
13) . 
Neck exercises may allow the musculotendinous proprio-
ceptors to downgrade their stretch reflex responses using 
operant conditioning techniques and multiple practice ses-
sions. The intrafusal fibers may be reset, discontinuing the 
cycle of muscle tension, impaired circulation with metabo-
lite accumulation and pain associated with myogenic (myo-
fascial) pain 14) . 
The neck disability index in our study showed significant 
changes in both groups. This result may be explained by the 
reduction in pain intensity which can bring about improve-
ment in disability. Herman et al. 21) also proposed that the 
relationship between pain and neck disability index is quite 
strong as pain intensity is one of the ten areas addressed 
in NDI. A relationship between these variables would be 
expected. 
Literature on NDI reports that the minimal detectable 
score and the minimal clinically important difference is 5 
points. Moreover it is recommended that the NDI be used 
at baseline and for every 2 weeks thereafter to measure 
the progress of therapy. This protocol was followed in this 
study. 
Deep cervical flexor training as a treatment for neck 
pain and resulting disability is based on the rationale that 
deep cervical flexors, the longus colli muscle in particu-
lar, have a major postural function in supporting cervical 
lordosis, since in the functional mid-ranges of the cervical 
spine the lose their endurance capacity in patients with neck 
pain 11, 15) . Therefore, it is thought that pressure biofeedback 
specifically targets DCF muscles and decreases neck pain. 
Our results are supporting the initial hypothesis, are in 
agreement with those obtained in a randomized controlled 
trial conducted by Jull et al. 9) , to determine the effect of 6 
weeks of low-load craniocervical flexion exercise on cer-
vicogenic headache patients. The results showed that the </p>

<p>Table 1. Comparison of NDI between the groups </p>

<p>NDI 
GROUP A 
(Mean±SD) </p>

<p>GROUP B 
(Mean±SD) 
D0 
15.23 ± 5.60 
12.93 ± 3.89 
* 
D14 
11.84 ± 4.04 
11.95 ± 3.88 
D14 
11.84 ± 4.04 
11.95 ± 3.88 
* 
D28 
8.51 ± 4.39 
10.72 ± 4.01 
D28 
8.51 ± 4.39 
10.72 ± 4.01 
* 
D0 
15.23 ± 5.60 
12.93 ± 3.9 </p>

<p>D 0 Pretest reading on day 1, D 14 reading at the end of 2 weeks, 
D 28 Posttest reading after 4 weeks A-Experimental group, B-
control group *p &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparison of NPRS between the groups </p>

<p>NDI 
GROUP A 
(Mean±SD) </p>

<p>GROUP B 
(Mean±SD) 
P0 
6.47 ± 1.36 
7.07 ± 1.49 
* 
P14 
4.73 ± 1.22 
5.93 ± 1.28 
P14 
4.73 ± 1.22 
5.93 ±1.28 
* 
P28 
3.33 ± 1.77 
5.27 ± 1.34 
P28 
3.33 ± 1.77 
5.27 ± 1.34 
* 
P0 
6.47 ± 1.36 
7.07 ± 1.49 </p>

<p>P 0 Pretest reading on day 1, P 14 reading at 2 weeks and P28 
Posttest reading after 4 weeks A-Experimental group, B-con-
trol group *p &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. Vol. 25, No. 6, 2013 </p>

<p>
treatment significantly reduced the pain associated with 
neck movements and joint palpation. 
A single case study done by Grant et al. 10) , also reported 
that the endurance of the deep cervical flexors improved 
and there was a reduction in mechanosensitivity of selected 
neural, muscular and articular structures of a screen based 
keyboard operator after four weeks of active stabilization 
training of the deep cervical flexors and lower scapular 
muscle group 9) . 
A possible explanation for our findings is that the fac-
tors influencing the school teachers are multifactorial. No 
one single factor contributes to their pain 3, 16) . Anthropo-
metric variations, the possible adverse developmental ef-
fects of prolonged exposure to postural stresses, computer 
furniture, mental stress and reports of pain and vision fac-
tors can all influence school teachers' posture 17) . Most of 
the teachers complained that they didn't have the time to 
take care of themselves due to school work 3) . Accordingly 
a dedicated 20 min for exercises at school itself as a part of 
their schedule for 4 weeks may have had a good psychologi-
cal impact on them, indirectly resulting in pain relief apart 
from the physiological effect. Therefore, a multidimension-
al approach may be needed if sustainable improvements are 
to be made including psychological assurance. 
The experimental group may have shown better results 
because doing exercises with constant feedback encourages 
patients doing the exercise to perform it correctly and gets 
them more involved in the treatment. There are two types of 
extrinsic feedback-knowledge of results (KR) and knowl-
edge of performance (KP). Pressure biofeedback is a type 
of KP, which is given during and after performance of a 
task and is related to how the task is performed. A therapist 
provides the information through the apparatus and by at-
tending to the information the patient forms a "closed loop". 
Feedback helps in motor learning which is a set of processes 
associated with practice or experience leading to permanent 
changes in the capability of responding. Patients become 
more motivated. Biofeedback techniques are used to aug-
ment the patient's sensory feedback mechanisms through 
precise information about body processes that might other-
wise be inaccessible. Positive reinforcement is the operative 
learning model 18) . 
The treatment duration of the deep cervical flexor train-
ing protocol we used in our study was modified to four 
weeks, four days a week, once a day with every session 
monitored by a therapist following an original protocol pre-
scribed by Jull et al., which was performed by patients at 
home with pressure biofeedback, twice a day for 6 weeks 
and monitored by therapist only once a week 19) . The pur-
pose of modification was to inculcate the treatment protocol 
in teachers' school timetable and to suit their schedule. Also 
conducting every session under supervision of therapist 
was considered more suitable for teachers than unsuper-
vised performance with biofeedback at home. This could 
have psychologically assured the teachers and contributed 
to the positive results. 
This study may help to prevent neck pain or arrest it in 
the early stages in the teaching population. It may also im-
prove the functional status of teachers. Once the teachers </p>

<p>feel better this would make their job easier and more pro-
ductive. 
Given that computer use in schools is increasing day by 
day 2, 6) , the risk of development of musculoskeletal disor-
ders within the teaching population has also increased re-
sulting in a potentially greater number of disorders. Mus-
culoskeletal disorders have been associated with a decline 
in productivity in adults and seriously affect work perfor-
mance. Supposing that these symptoms now emerge earlier 
in a lifespan than in previous generations, we should expect 
increasing sick leave and early retirement. This study is a 
step towards prevention of such possibilities in the future. 
This study was performed on limited number of sub-
jects, 15 subjects in each group. Furthermore, subject and 
researcher blinding was not implemented, and teacher's 
posture was not included in the study. Also the effect of 
DCF muscles training on posture and endurance of DCF 
muscles was not evaluated, and due to limitation of time we 
could not conduct a follow up of the patients. 
To our knowledge, this is the first study in which deep 
cervical flexor training was used for teachers having neck 
pain. To give this protocol a more grounded base of prac-
tice, further studies need to be carried out on this group 
with larger samples. 
Further studies using 6 weeks or longer duration with 
subsequent follow up are recommended, and the relation-
ship of forward head posture and NP in this group also 
needs documentation. Electromyography could be used to 
provide additional information on muscle activation associ-
ated with any observed postural changes. Moreover, future 
studies could be designed to address the potential contri-
bution of various factors, including musculoskeletal imbal-
ances, that might possibly influence neck pain and forward 
head posture in this group. More dynamic, objective and 
functional outcome measures should be taken that better 
reflect the improvement in the postural endurance of deep 
cervical flexors resulting from therapy. 
The results of this study show that there was significant 
improvement in pain and disability after 4 weeks of deep 
cervical flexor training for school teachers with neck pain. 
Moreover training using both pressure biofeedback and 
conventional exercises was found to be superior to training 
which only used conventional exercises. </p>

<p>ACKNOwLEDgEMENT </p>

<p>The Authors extend their appreciation to the Deanship of 
Scientific Research at King Saud University for funding the 
work through the research group project NO RGP-VPP-209. </p>







</text></tei>