<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3984197" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>O bjective: This study evaluated experimentally-induced periapical bone loss sites using </p>

<p>digital radiographic and histopathologic parameters. Material and Methods: Twenty-
seven Wistar rats were submitted to coronal opening of their mandibular right first molars. 
They were radiographed at 2, 15 and 30 days after the operative procedure by two digital 
radiographic storage phosphor plates (Digora ® ). The images were analyzed by creating 
a region of interest at the periapical region of each tooth (<rs type="software">ImageJ</rs>) and registering the 
corresponding pixel values. After the sacrifice, the specimens were submitted to microscopic 
analysis in order to confirm the pulpal and periapical status of the tooth. Results: There was 
significant statistically difference between the control and test sides in all the experimental 
periods regarding the pixel values (two-way ANOVA; p&lt;0.05). Conclusions: The microscopic 
analysis proved that a periapical disease development occurred during the experimental 
periods with an evolution from pulpal necrosis to periapical bone resorption. </p>

<p>Digital intraoral radiographic systems have 
several advantages compared with conventional 
film-based radiography. These advantages, in 
Endodontics, include the potential of a lower 
radiation exposure to the patient and faster 
image display 25 . Moreover, it was introduced 
the opportunity of evaluating the progression of 
periapical bone loss by digital tools as the pixel 
values 3,15 . 
Radiographs do not always reflect the extent 
of the destructive process in the periapical tissues 
and generally under-represent the size of a lesion 12 . 
Studies have suggested that pathologic involvement 
of the cortical plate, or at least junctional trabeculae, 
is a prerequisite for radiographic detection of 
periapical pathoses 16 . Nevertheless, periapical 
lesions confined to cancellous bone could be </p>

<p>detected radiographically using pixel values using 
one of the tools of the digital image, the histogram 2 . 
Only a few studies employing animal models 3,7,8 or 
human biopsies 10,21,23 have compared the diagnostic 
and quantifying accuracy of radiographs to the gold 
standard represented by the histology. The aim of 
this study was to induce periapical disease in rats 
to assess the pixel values in different experimental 
periods to evaluate the bone loss progression. </p>

<p>MATERIAL AND METhODS </p>

<p>general and radiographic procedures </p>

<p>This study was approved by the Animal 
Research ethics Committee of the Bauru School of 
Dentistry, University of São Paulo. The experimental 
groups were composed of 27 Wistar rats (Rattus 
novergicus), divided into three groups with nine 
animals each, according to the sacrifice date, Group </p>

<p>2011;19(5):500-4 </p>

<p>J Appl Oral Sci. 501 </p>

<p>Mean of pixel values </p>

<p>Test -Plate I 
Control -Plate I 
Test -Plate II 
Control -Plate II </p>

<p>Group I 
191.88*±4.234** 
184.17±4.197 
188.86±4.186 
179.40±4.180 </p>

<p>Group II 
195.97±4.312 
180.48±4.320 
193.53±5.274 
178.77±4.290 </p>

<p>Group III 
199.70±4.718 
186.23±4.319 
196.71±6.185 
184.36±4.568 </p>

<p>*Mean pixel value from 9 animal samples. 
**Standard deviation for mean pixel from 9 animal samples. </p>

<p>Table 1-Means and standard deviation of the pixel values on the test and control sides for the Digora® system phosphorus 
plates 1 and 2, in the rats of Groups I, II and III </p>

<p>Radiological and histopathological evaluation of experimentally induced periapical lesion in rats </p>

<p>1: 2 days, Group 2: 15 days, Group 3: 30 days 6 . The 
animals were submitted to general intramuscular 
anesthesia. In each animal, a cavity was made on 
the occlusal face of the mandibular first molar on the 
right side with a spherical burr size ¼, at high speed 
without cooling 28 . The left side was set as control. </p>

<p>Radiographic analysis </p>

<p>The material for study was obtained after 
euthanizing the animal with an anesthetic overdose. 
The right and left hemi-mandibles of each rat were 
separated and radiographed with two phosphor 
plates (PSPs/ Digora-Soredex-Tuusula, Finland). 
The exposition was performed according to the 
parameters: 70 kVp, 7 mA, focus-film distance of 30 
cm, exposure time of 0.09 s. A standard aluminum 
stepwedge was set in each image, and an acrylic 
plate measuring 0.3x0.4x0.2 cm was positioned 
over the hemi-mandibles to simulate soft tissue. 
The stepwedge was used as a standard image 
technique, which is essential for control of day-to-
day variations in the sensitivity of the detector 29 . 
The radiographic evaluation was performed 
using the public domain software Image J (version 
1.33 µ, National Institute of Health, Washington, 
DC) A region of interest (ROI/252 pixels) was 
opened in the periapical region of the every tooth, 
closest to the mesial root, without touching it. 
Only the periapical bone was enclosed in the ROI. 
Using the histogram tool, the pixel values of the 
ROIs were established. The normalized pixel values 
of the images (NPI) were then obtained by using 
the following equation 29 : NPI=PI/CR. Where PI is 
the mean pixel intensity of the ROI, and CR is the 
pixel intensity of the ROI of the standard aluminum 
stepwedge. The pixel value of zero corresponded to 
black and the pixel value of 255 to white. </p>

<p>histomorphometrical analysis </p>

<p>Hemi-mandibles were fixed in formalin 10%, 
decalcified in EDTA and processed histologically. 
Five semi-serial sections of each hemi-mandible 
with 5 µm thickness were cut and stained with 
hematoxylin and eosin. All histological sections 
were identified with a random numerical sequence </p>

<p>and periapical tissues were histomorphometrically 
analyzed for both test and control sites. In the test 
site it was noted whether the tooth had pulpitis, 
necrosis or presented any sign of inflammation, 
and whether or not there was presence of periapical 
bone resorption. The percentages of bone tissue in 
the apical region of the root, soft tissue (connective 
tissue and inflammatory infiltrate, when present), 
bone marrow and inferior alveolar nerve were 
obtained in a digital image analysis system, 
composed of a Zeiss Axioskop II microscope, CCD-
IRIS RGB -Sony camera (Sony DXC-151A RGB 
Video Camera-Sony Corporation, Tokyo, Japan) 
and <rs id="software-1" type="software">Kontron KS300</rs> ® software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Kontron Electronic GMBM</rs>, Munich, Germany). For this purpose, an 
image was captured at 10x objective from each 
histologic slice, which contained the apical portion 
of the mesial root perpendicular to the alveolar 
nerve, positioned centrally. The studied area was 
established in numbers of pixels. each image 
captured had 307,200 pixels and evaluated total 
area was 1536,000 pixels. The area (in pixels) was 
measured to quantify the area occupied by bone 
tissue in the apical region of the root, soft tissue 
(connective tissue and inflammatory infiltrate, when 
present), bone marrow and inferior alveolar nerve. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Radiographic analysis </p>

<p>The radiographic analysis showed that the pixel 
values in the three experimental periods increased 
on the test side in comparison with the control 
side, indicating bone loss in a similar manner both 
PSPs plates used. The Student's T test showed a 
statistically significant difference between control 
and test sites for the three groups tested (p&lt;0.05) 
(Table 1). The influence of the time on periapical 
disease was studied using one-way ANOVA and 
Tukey's tests. ANOVA showed no statistically 
significant variation for any of the time intervals in 
Plate 1 (p&gt;0.05), as well as for the control side of 
Plate 2 (p&gt;0.05). This variation was only shown to 
be significant in Plate 2 (p&lt;0.05) between the test 
groups 2 and 3 (Figures 1A, D, G, J). </p>

<p>2011;19(5):500-4 </p>

<p>J Appl Oral Sci. 502 </p>

<p>Histologic pixel values </p>

<p>GROUP I 
GROUP II 
GROUP III </p>

<p>Region 
Control 
Test 
Control 
Test 
Control 
Test </p>

<p>415.48* 
410.28 
394.58 
318.24 
414.23 
284.29 </p>

<p>Root 
±42.958** 
±45.078 
±34.707 
±44.579 
±68.810 
±22.345 </p>

<p>215.71 
295.46 
207.28 
696.98 
205.14 
806.63 </p>

<p>Soft tissue 
±28.582 
±31.593 
±20.498 
±61.367 
±32.021 
±45.912 </p>

<p>554.40 
476.99 
616.39 
375.94 
610.70 
297.40 </p>

<p>Bone tissue 
±35.857 
±34.094 
±11.7848 
±33.248 
±63.826 
±41.971 </p>

<p>211.70 
208.89 
176.63 
Absent 
169.99 
Absent </p>

<p>Bone marrow 
±37.217 
±41.078 
±65.085 
Absent 
±66.325 
Absent </p>

<p>138.68 
144.36 
141.11 
144.82 
135.92 
147.67 </p>

<p>Alveolar nerve 
±43.952 
±51.711 
±51.624 
±48.180 
±24.432 
±42.113 </p>

<p>*Mean pixel value from 9 animal samples. 
**Standard deviation for mean pixel from 9 animal samples. </p>

<p>Table 2-Mean and standard deviation of the total number of pixels of each structure present in the periapical region of the 
mesial root of the mandibular first molar in the control and test groups in the experimental periods </p>

<p>Figure 1-Control group: A) radiographic image of hemi-mandible; B-C) photomicrograph of the left first molar showing 
healthy pulp (black arrow) and periapical tissues with cementum (ce), fibers of periodontal ligament (li) and alveolar bone 
(ab). Group 1: D) radiographic image of hemi-mandible similar at the control group; E-F) photomicrograph of the right first 
molar exhibiting inflammatory cells (black arrow) in the periapical region. Group 2: G) radiographic image of hemi-mandible 
showing radiolucent area in the periapical region; H-I) photomicrograph of the right first molar showing extensive bone (b) 
resorption by osteoclasts (red arrow) and connective tissue (ct). Group 3: J) radiographic image of hemi-mandible exhibiting 
extensive radiolucent area in the periapical region; K-L) photomicrography of the right first molar showing abscess (red 
arrow), increase of connective tissue area (ct) and decrease of bone tissue (b) in relation to the other groups </p>

<p>TEIXEIRA RC, RUBIRA CMF, ASSIS GF, LAURIS JRP, CESTARI TM, RUBIRA-BULLEN IRF </p>

<p>2011;19(5):500-4 </p>

<p>J Appl Oral Sci. 503 </p>

<p>Radiological and histopathological evaluation of experimentally induced periapical lesion in rats </p>

<p>histopathological analysis </p>

<p>The histological analysis of the left first molars 
of the rats, which served as control, showed no 
alterations in the pulp or periapical tissues, and 
evidenced that 100% of these teeth presented 
healthy pulp and periapical tissues (Figures 1B, 
C). The teeth submitted to coronal opening in 
group 1, showed in 100% of the cases, necrosis 
in the coronal region and pulp inflammation with 
the presence of inflammatory cells and increased 
vascularization in the medial and apical thirds. 
It was possible to observe inflammatory cells 
and small bone and cementum resorption in the 
periapical region (Figures 1E, F). Group 2 showed 
necrosis in the coronal and middle radicular pulp 
and extensive inflammatory process in the apical 
third. In the periapical region exhibited increase 
of bone resorption and replaced by conjunctive 
tissue rich in inflammatory cells (Figures 1H, I). 
The group 3 showed total pulp necrosis, extensive 
area of abscess and bone, cementum and dentine 
resorption and few bone trabeculae surrounded by 
conjunctive tissue in the apical portion (Figures 
1K, L). 
The area measured histomorphometrically was 
given in number of pixels. The total numbers of 
pixels obtained for each of the measured regions 
in the control and tests sides, in the various 
experimental periods are presented in Table 2. Two-
way ANOVA and Tukey's tests showed statistically 
significant difference between the test and control 
sides and among the experimental periods as well. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In the present study, the periapical inflammation 
was induced by coronal opening of the mandibular 
right first molar and confirmed that only coronal 
opening and pulp contact with the oral cavity were 
sufficient for inducing periapical disease. Various 
other studies have described this technique for 
induction of pulpal and periapical inflammatory 
reactions in rat teeth 19,28 . The inflammatory process 
was observed in the pulp region in the experimental 
period of 2 days. This is in agreement with the 
findings of a previous study that showed that pulp 
inflammation is already observed 6 h after the 
operative procedure 19 . In the present study, pulp 
necrosis was observed in the experimental periods 
of 15 and 30 days. This is also in agreement with 
a previous study that showed the presence of 
complete pulp necrosis between the 8 th and 20 th 
days 27 . 
Hamachi, et al. 16 (1995) affirmed that bone 
resorption is present from the 3 rd day after the 
operative procedure. Bone resorption in the present 
study, although very subtle, could already be 
observed in the Group 1. Resorptive bone activity </p>

<p>was actively present on the 15 th day (Group 2). Some 
authors affirmed that this activity begins to diminish 
from then on, with a decrease in the number of 
osteoclasts 1 . Although the lesion appeared to be 
stabilized, with diminished bone resorption, new 
bone formation did not occur due to the presence 
of aggressive factors 30 . In the 30-day experimental 
period, a large area of resorption could be observed, 
but a smaller number of osteoclasts were present. 
The amount of periapical bone was minimal, and it 
was replaced by inflammatory tissue. 
Statistical analysis showed a significant difference 
between test and control sides in the 3 experimental 
periods, except for the root region, in which this 
difference was not significant between the test and 
control sides, in the 2-day period, and between the 
experimental periods of 15 and 30 days. This was 
probably because resorption in periapical disease is 
greater in the bone region than in the root region, 
which was not very evident. 
The present study confirmed radiographically the 
presence and intensity of bone resorption observed 
by the histological study. Jett, et al. 18 (2004) and 
Shrout, et al. 26 (2003) removed medullar bone 
from cadaver mandibles, radiographed the areas 
to measure the pixel value respectively. These 
studies showed that it is possible to detect bone 
loss in the mandibular region by analyzing the pixel 
value, even if it is not yet visible radiographically. 
Conversely, studies that compared images obtained 
by conventional radiographs (without pixel value 
analysis) and bone resorption seen microscopically, 
showed that this relationship is not established with 
precision 4,14, 
De Rossi, et al. 9 (2007) concluded that although 
image digitization could not improve the detection 
of the early stages of periapical lesions, it provides 
valuable quantitative assessment of extensive 
periapical lesions. 
In order to diminish the noise level in the 
images captured directly, the phosphorus plates 
were covered by a protective envelope, as they 
are sensitive to light 24 . The images were always 
downloaded immediately after the radiograph was 
taken, as the time between taking the radiograph 
and downloading the plates also influences the 
pixel values 5,13 . 
In the direct photostimulable phosphorus plate 
systems, such as Digora ® , there is a correlation 
between the radiation dose and the quantity of 
capture plate luminescence 11,20,22 . The capture 
plates present less noise and a better quality image 
than the other direct systems, in addition to being 
more sensitive to small variations of the exposure 
source in comparison with conventional films, and 
should be used when small differences in contrast 
are important 17,20 . The noise and coefficient of 
variability of pixel value calculations showed low </p>

<p>2011;19(5):500-4 </p>

<p>J Appl Oral Sci. 504 </p>

<p>TEIXEIRA RC, RUBIRA CMF, ASSIS GF, LAURIS JRP, CESTARI TM, RUBIRA-BULLEN IRF </p>

<p>noise and small variation in the images in this study. 
In spite of resistance by many professionals, 
the high cost of the technology and the ethical 
implications because of the risk of manipulating the 
images, the use of digital imaging has increased 
and is constantly being perfected. Computerization 
tends to make this one the method of choice for 
daily radiographs. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>The methodology applied was efficient for 
causing pulpitis and pulpal necrosis in the studied 
rats. Teeth with pulpitis microscopically presented 
periapical bone resorption, but the teeth with 
necrosis presented greater resorption. The control 
teeth presented healthy pulp, without signs of 
periapical bone resorption. The means of the pixel 
values in the areas of periapical disease induced 
in rats indicated greater bone resorption than the 
means of these values on the control side for the 
three experimental periods (p&lt;0.05). even small 
periapical bone resorption was already sufficient 
for determining changes in the pixel values of that 
area in the direct digital method, when compared 
to their respective controls. </p>



<p>2011;19(5):500-4 </p>

</text></tei>