<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3130168" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>The DREB genes code for important plant transcription factors involved in the abiotic stress response and signal 
transduction. Characterization of DREB genes and development of functional markers for effective alleles is 
important for marker-assisted selection in foxtail millet. Here the characterization of a cDNA (SiDREB2) encoding 
a putative dehydration-responsive element-binding protein 2 from foxtail millet and the development of an allele-
specific marker (ASM) for dehydration tolerance is reported. A cDNA clone (GenBank accession no. GT090998) 
coding for a putative DREB2 protein was isolated as a differentially expressed gene from a 6 h dehydration stress 
SSH library. A 5' RACE (rapid amplification of cDNA ends) was carried out to obtain the full-length cDNA, and 
sequence analysis showed that SiDREB2 encoded a polypeptide of 234 amino acids with a predicted mol. wt of 
25.72 kDa and a theoretical pI of 5.14. A theoretical model of the tertiary structure shows that it has a highly 
conserved GCC-box-binding N-terminal domain, and an acidic C-terminus that acts as an activation domain for 
transcription. Based on its similarity to AP2 domains, SiDREB2 was classified into the A-2 subgroup of the DREB 
subfamily. Quantitative real-time PCR analysis showed significant up-regulation of SiDREB2 by dehydration 
(polyethylene glycol) and salinity (NaCl), while its expression was less affected by other stresses. A synonymous 
single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) associated with dehydration tolerance was detected at the 558th base pair 
(an A/G transition) in the SiDREB2 gene in a core set of 45 foxtail millet accessions used. Based on the identified 
SNP, three primers were designed to develop an ASM for dehydration tolerance. The ASM produced a 261 bp 
fragment in all the tolerant accessions and produced no amplification in the sensitive accessions. The use of this 
ASM might be faster, cheaper, and more reproducible than other SNP genotyping methods, and thus will enable 
marker-aided breeding of foxtail millet for dehydration tolerance. </p>

<p>Foxtail millet (Setaria italica L.), an elite drought-tolerant 
crop, is an important food and fodder grain crop in arid 
and semi-arid regions of Asia and Africa. Its genome is 
being sequenced by the US Department of Energy Joint 
Genomic Institute and BGI (formerly the Beijing Genomics 
Institute), China. Foxtail millet together with proso millet 
(Panicum miliaceum) ranks second in the total world 
production of millets (FAO STAT data 2005; http://faostat. 
fao.org/). It is a diploid (2n¼2x¼18), self-pollinating, C 4 </p>

<p>panicoid crop, with a small genome of ;490 Mb having 
a low repetitive DNA content (30%) and a highly conserved 
genome structure relative to the ancestral grass lineage, 
making it a suitable model species for genetic and molecular 
studies (Devos et al., 1998; Jayaraman et al., 2008). Further, 
it is a close relative of several important biofuel crops such 
as, switchgrass, napiergrass, and pearl millet, and hence 
has been suggested to represent an appropriate model for 
this class of crop species (Doust et al., 2009). Water use </p>

<p>ª 2011 The Author(s). </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-
nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>efficiency of foxtail millet has been shown to be higher than 
that of maize, wheat, and sorghum (Gu et al., 1987). The 
adaptation of foxtail millet to low water conditions has 
been ascribed to its relatively small leaf area, the cell 
arrangement in its epidermis, its thick cell walls, and its 
ability to form a dense root system (Li, 1987). However, the 
molecular mechanism of its drought adaptation is still not 
clear. To gain a better understanding of the molecular 
responses of this crop to dehydration stress, two SSH 
forward libraries were constructed (Lata et al., 2010). A 
differentially expressed expressed sequence tag (EST) from 
a 6 h dehydration stress library was found to encode 
a dehydration-responsive element-binding protein 2 
(DREB2). 
The DREBs are important transcription factors that 
induce a set of abiotic stress-related genes and impart stress 
tolerance to plants. They could broadly be grouped as 
DREB1 and DREB2, involved in two separate signal 
transduction pathways under low temperature and de-
hydration, respectively (Agarwal et al., 2006). They belong 
to the ERF (ethylene-responsive element-binding factor) 
family, a subfamily of AP2/EREBP (APETALA2/ethylene-
responsive element-binding protein) plant-specific transcrip-
tion factors (Riechmann et al., 2000). These proteins share 
a conserved DNA-binding domain of ;58-59 amino acids 
that bind to two cis-elements, namely a GCC box and 
a CRT/DRE (C-repeat/dehydration-responsive element) 
motif playing an important role in regulating gene expres-
sion in response to dehydration, high salinity, and cold in 
plants (Yamaguchi-Shinozaki and Shinozaki, 2005; Agarwal 
et al., 2006). The 14th and 19th amino acids of the AP2/ 
ERF domain are highly distinctive as they distinguish the 
DREB (valine and glutamic acid, respectively) from the 
ERF (alanine and aspartic acid, respectively) gene classes 
(Sakuma et al., 2002). Abscisic acid (ABA)-independent 
stress-responsive gene expression is generally regulated by 
DREBs that bind to DRE cis-elements (5#-TACCGACAT-
3#). The first cDNA clone for a DREB, CBF1 (CRT-
binding factor 1) was isolated in a yeast one-hybrid 
screening (Stockinger et al., 1997). Since then several 
DREBs have been identified from Arabidopsis, rice, maize, 
and other plants that specifically interact with the DRE 
sequence (Liu et al., 1998; Dubouzet et al., 2003; Chen 
et al., 2007; Qin et al., 2007). Overexpression of Arabidopsis 
DREB2A results in significant drought stress tolerance, 
water stress, and heat stress tolerance, but only slight 
freezing tolerance in transgenic plants (Sakuma et al., 
2006a, b). GmDREB2 also conferred drought and high-
salinity tolerance to transgenic Arabidopsis and tobacco 
plants (Chen et al., 2007). However, to the best of our 
knowledge, no studies on AP2/EREBP transcription factors 
in foxtail millet have been reported. 
Single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) are the source 
of DNA variation in most of the plant and animal genomes 
(Garcés-Claver et al., 2007). SNPs are single base changes 
or indels at a specific nucleotide position and have recently 
been developed into genetic markers. SNPs can serve as 
a powerful tool for marker-assisted selection (MAS) and </p>

<p>map-based cloning since they are considered as highly stable 
markers and often contribute directly to a phenotype 
(Andersen and Luebberstedt, 2003; Kim et al., 2005). 
Among the many SNP genotyping methods, allele-specific 
PCR largely satisfies the requirements for MAS since it is 
simple, user friendly, cost-effective, and reproducible. 
In the present study, the cloning and characterization of 
a novel DREB2 homologous gene, SiDREB2, isolated from 
foxtail millet and classified into the A-2 subgroup in the 
DREB subfamily, are reported. An SNP in the SiDREB2 
gene was also identified and an allele-specific PCR-based 
marker associated with dehydration tolerance was devel-
oped and validated in a core set of 45 foxtail millet 
accessions. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Plant materials and growth conditions 
Seeds of a core set of 45 foxtail millet [S. italica (L.)] accessions 
originating from different eco-geographic regions were obtained 
from the National Bureau of Plant Genetic Resources, Hyderabad 
and the University of Agricultural Sciences, GKVK, Bangalore, 
India (Table 1). Seeds were surface sterilized in 3% sodium 
hypochlorite for 20 min and rinsed 10-12 times (1 min each time) 
in distilled water. Five seeds of each accession were germinated, 
and sown in square black pots (93939.8 cm) containing composite 
soil (peat compost to vermiculite, 3:1) in triplicate. The seedlings 
were grown in a plant growth chamber containing two cabinets 
(PGC-6L; Percival Scientific Inc., USA) for 10 d after germination 
at 2861°C day/2361°C night/7065% relative humidity with 
a photoperiod of 14 h and a photosynthetic photon flux density of 
500 lmol m 
À2 s </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>. The plants were watered daily with one-third 
strength Hoagland's solution. Ten-day-old seedlings were used for 
dehydration treatment. They were pre-cultured for 24 h in one-
third strength Hoagland's solution. Dehydration stress was applied 
by transferring seedlings into the same solution containing 20% 
polyethylene glycol (PEG-6000). The control plants were cultured 
in the same way as the dehydration treatments but without the 
addition of PEG (Zhang et al., 2007). Whole seedlings were 
collected and used as such. All experimental data are the means of 
at least three independent experiments and, for each experiment, 
;100 mg seedling samples were collected by random sampling. </p>

<p>Estimation of relative water content (RWC) 
Leaf RWC was measured in control and stressed seedlings as 
reported earlier (Lata et al., 2010). Fully expanded leaves were 
excised and fresh weight (FW) was recorded immediately; then 
leaves were soaked for 4 h in distilled water at room temperature 
under a constant light, and the turgid weight (TW) was recorded. 
Total dry weight (DW) was recorded after drying for 24 h at 80°C 
in a hot air oven. RWC was calculated according to the formula 
given by Barrs and Weatherley (1962): RWC (%)¼[(FW-DW)/ 
(TW-DW)]3100. </p>

<p>Estimation of lipid peroxidation (LP) 
The LP level in plant tissues was determined by measuring the 
malondialdehyde (MDA) content via the 2-thiobarbituric acid 
(TBA) reaction (Hodgson and Raison, 1991). Seedlings (100 mg) 
were homogenized in 1 ml of 10 mM sodium phosphate buffer 
(pH 7.4) and centrifuged at 4000 g for 5 min at room temperature. 
A 200 ll aliquot of the supernatant was added to a reaction 
mixture containing 100 ll of 8.1% (w/v) SDS, 750 ll of 20% (w/v) 
acetic acid (pH 3.5), 750 ll of 0.8% (w/v) aqueous TBA, and </p>



<p>Table 1. Description of 45 foxtail millet (Setaria italica) accessions used in the present study along with the level of lipid peroxidation and 
relative water content in the control and after 24 h of dehydration stress </p>

<p>Sl no. Accession no. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Origin 
Lipid peroxidation </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>24 h 6SD 
Relative water content </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>24 h 6SD 
Allele Overall grade </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Control 6SD 
Control 6SD </p>

<p>1 
GS-464 
USA 
8.2261.1 
4.1160.5 
91.6162.01 
36.4065.26 
A 
HT 
2 
IC-403579 
India 
24.560.34 
15.260.99 
96.9161.11 
42.0762.65 
A 
HT 
3 
Prasad 
India 
39.160.86 
24.661.28 
91.7862.06 
40.4763.86 
A 
HT 
4 
IC-403476 
India 
25.160.8 
16.661.56 
96.1961.26 
38.4063.87 
A 
HT 
5 
IC-436928 
India 
37.561.29 
24.762.37 
95.3161.45 
34.3462.07 
A 
T 
6 
IC-328716 
India 
29.061.96 
20.861.38 
96.5161.18 
35.3460.73 
A 
T 
7 
GS-1646 
Russia 
15.0660.54 
11.6260.74 
94 9061.98 
36.4063.26 
A 
T 
8 
IC-426735 
India 
29.260.87 
2562.41 
97.6061.49 
36.3061.43 
A 
T 
9 
IC-436863 
India 
32.460.48 
27.862.39 
96.60 61.08 
34.7361.08 
A 
T 
10 
IC-438725 
India 
32.461.57 
27.962.36 
87.7462.03 
33.1862.43 
A 
T 
11 
IC-519642 
India 
47.460.26 
41.762.37 
94.7761.94 
32.9761.27 
A 
T 
12 
IC-438725-1 
India 
33.561.26 
29.660.77 
94.3660.85 
34.5062.42 
A 
T 
13 
GS-1636 
Pakistan 
16.1964.63 
5.5560.18 
95.0461.20 
34.6163.62 
A 
T 
14 
GS-455 
USA/Africa 
15.0665.75 
24.9460.35 
93.3461.98 
32.5461.98 
A 
T 
15 
GS-496 
Kenya 
10.6760.35 
10.7961.44 
94.5762.46 
32.2762.86 
A 
T 
16 
GS-493 
Turkey 
7.7960.49 
8.0160.32 
93.2961.65 
28.0662.52 
G 
S 
17 
GS-457 
USA/Africa 
11.9761.08 
12.5760.74 
95.163.13 
28.4262.87 
G 
S 
18 
GS-459 
USA 
9.6060.35 
10.9160.41 
93.8561.43 
27.3462.31 
G 
S 
19 
GS-494 
Kenya 
12.4560.00 
14.2360.62 
94.3862.14 
26.8962.01 
G 
S 
20 
GS-1928 
Bangladesh 
5.7760.96 
6.7960.11 
90.2562.04 
25.8361.92 
G 
S 
21 
IC-404103 
India 
38.760.44 
58.4461.39 
96.3161.79 
26.8961.83 
G 
S 
22 
GS-1926 
Bangladesh 
5.2360.18 
8.1260.18 
95.0462.01 
27.0163.22 
G 
S 
23 
IC-479989 
India 
38.661.27 
60.362.36 
96.762.31 
27.0663.38 
G 
S 
24 
IC-403871-A 
India 
44.161.56 
78.860.69 
89.1664.31 
23.9363.00 
G 
S 
25 
IC-479481 
India 
41.161.32 
75.361.38 
94.5762.46 
27.2862.86 
G 
S 
26 
IC-345014 
India 
38.263.28 
70.363.68 
93.3461.98 
27.5461.98 
G 
S 
27 
IC-480185 
India 
38.161.35 
76.261.06 
85.1663.54 
24.662.16 
G 
S 
28 
IC-403834 
India 
48.863.16 
101.860.98 
88.3463.05 
23.5362.50 
G 
S 
29 
IC-404133 
India 
37.361.28 
77.962.37 
93.661.91 
25.8962.17 
G 
S 
30 
IC-479442 
India 
35.863.65 
8161.68 
94.1262.17 
27.6761.87 
G 
S 
31 
IC-404144 
India 
26.060.39 
59.3962.64 
91.561.85 
25.862.37 
G 
S 
32 
IC-479985 
India 
28.660.42 
65.661.36 
92.1762.14 
25.2161.70 
G 
S 
33 
IC-479479 
India 
34.362.4 
78.962.39 
92.0861.81 
23.8061.53 
G 
S 
34 
IC-403832 
India 
37.862.28 
8961.27 
8961.74 
24.8661.94 
G 
S 
35 
IC-403739 
India 
37.061.49 
87.461.24 
89.763.67 
25.3362.86 
G 
S 
36 
IC-480104 
India 
36.661.23 
8761.39 
93.1062.05 
25.2061.70 
G 
S 
37 
IC-403522-A 
India 
38.6 61.28 
93.961.69 
92.262.75 
24.6362.51 
G 
S 
38 
IC-403522 
India 
40.261.59 
97.961.68 
91.5462.54 
23.7362.67 
G 
S 
39 
IC-403717 
India 
42.161.45 
108.362.37 
91.9061.69 
24.7363.63 
G 
S 
40 
IC-479586 
India 
30.560.89 
79.561.6 
94.861.31 
25.2361.63 
G 
S 
41 
IC-479731 
India 
33.760.76 
91.961.38 
91.0864.00 
26.4662.59 
G 
S 
42 
IC-403521 
India 
31.162.56 
85.261.24 
89.9363.61 
21.8161.53 
G 
HS 
43 
IC-404178 
India 
31.360.76 
89.0961.38 
91.3662.54 
21.6562.35 
G 
HS 
44 
Lepakshi 
India 
31.561.26 
91.561.07 
88.4561.66 
17.9763.01 
G 
HS 
45 
IC-480117 
India 
29.460.92 
87.461.02 
89.9464.28 
18.462.74 
G 
HS </p>

<p>Standard deviations (6SD) were calculated from three independent experiments and were statistically significant at P &lt;0.05. 
a Accession no. refers to the serial number of the accession preserved in NBPGR(IC), Hyderabad and UAS (GS), Bangalore, India. 
b The values of lipid peroxidation (LP) obtained in the control and after 24 h dehydration stress are expressed as lmol g 
À1 FW MDA 
concentration. 
c The values of the relative water content (RWC) obtained in the control and after 24 h dehydration stress are expressed as the percentage in 
20% polyethylene glycol (PEG-6000). 
d HT, highly tolerant (&gt;30% decline in LP, 0-60% decline in RWC); T, tolerant (&lt;30% decline in LP, 61-66% decline in RWC); S, sensitive 
(&lt;170 % increase in LP, 70-75% decline in RWC); HS, highly sensitive (&gt;170% increase in LP, &gt;75% decline in RWC). </p>

<p>Association of an SNP with dehydration stress in foxtail millet | 3389 </p>

<p>200 ll of Milli-Q water. An identical reaction mixture in which 
200 ll of supernatant was substituted by an equal volume of buffer 
was simultaneously set up as a blank. Both reaction mixtures were 
then incubated at 98°C for 1 h. After cooling to room tempera-
ture the mixtures were centrifuged for 5 min. Absorbance at 
535 nm was measured and corrected for non-specific absorbance 
at 600 nm. The level of LP was expressed as lmol of MDA formed 
derived from the difference in absorbance at 535 nm and 600 nm 
using an extinction coefficient of 156 mM 
À1 cm 
À1 . </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
All experimental data are the means of at least three independent 
experiments and the results are presented as the mean values 6SD. 
The significance of differences between mean values of control and 
each dehydration-stressed samples was statistically determined 
using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and comparison 
among means was carried out using the Tukey-Kramer multiple 
comparisons test. The differences in the effects of PEG-induced 
dehydration stress on various parameters in 45 foxtail millet 
accessions were considered statistically significant at P &lt;0.05, 
P &lt;0.01, and P &lt;0.001. </p>

<p>Stress treatments and total RNA extraction 
For time course analysis of SiDREB2 expression, 21-day-old 
seedlings (Prasad, IC-403579, Lepakshi, IC-480117) were exposed 
for 0, 0.5,1, 3, 6, 12, 24, or 48 h to the following treatments: 
dehydration, solutions containing 20% PEG 6000; salinity, saline 
solutions containing 250 mM NaCl; cold, chilling at 4°C in 
a growth chamber; ABA, solutions containing 100 lM ABA; SA, 
solutions containing 100 lM salicylic acid; methyl jasmonate, 
solutions containing 100 lM MeJA; and ethylene, solutions 
containing 100 lM ethephone or water. The seedlings were then 
transferred to tubes containing fresh, distilled water (Dubouzet 
et al., 2003; Lata et al., 2010). Total RNA was extracted by the 
modified hot phenol method using lithium chloride (Longeman 
et al., 1987). DNA contamination was removed from the RNA 
samples using RNase-free DNase I (50 U ll 
À1 , Fermentas). </p>

<p>Rapid amplification of 5' cDNA ends (5' RACE) 
An EST sequence, FIII E5 (GenBank accession no. GT090998), 
was chosen from a 6 h PEG-induced forward SSH library, and 
was used to design three gene-specific reverse PCR primers using 
Primer 3.0. 5# RACE was performed using the 5# RACE kit 
version 2.0 (Invitrogen) following the manufacturer's instructions. 
First-strand cDNA was synthesized using GSP (5#-
GTGCCGTTACAGAGAAATAACT-3#). The adaptor-ligated 
first-strand cDNA was used as template for PCR amplification 
with GSP1 (5#-GAAGCGTTTCCTAACAGCTAGAAC-3#) and 
NGSP1 (5#-CTAATATGCAAAAAGACTAAATC-3#). A 5 ll 
aliquot of the RACE reaction product was separated by electro-
phoresis in a 1.2% (w/v) agarose gel. The band was then excised 
from the gel using a Qiagen gel extraction kit, cloned into 
the pGEM-T Easy vector (Promega), and sequenced in both 
directions. </p>

<p>Cloning of the SiDREB2 gene 
The SiDREB2 gene was amplified using the primer pair SiDREB2 
ORF_F (5#-ATGAGGAGGAAAAGCACTGG-3#) and NGSP1. 
PCR thermal cycles were performed as follows: initial denatur-
ation at 94°C for 3 min, followed by 35 cycles of 94°C for 30 s, 
55°C for 1 min, and 72°C for 1 min, and then an extension at 
72°C for 10 min. A PCR product of 705 bp was then purified 
from the gel, cloned into the pGEM-T Easy vector, and sequenced. 
Similarly, the primer pair SiDREB2 FL_F (5#-CAACTCAGGAA-
GAAGAGGAT-3#) and SiDREB2 FL_R (5#-ATCTGGCA-
CAAAAGGTAAGA-3#) was used to amplify the entire full-length </p>

<p>cDNA of the SiDREB2 gene. A PCR product of 1103 bp was then 
precipitated by sodium acetate and sequenced. </p>

<p>Sequence analysis and structure prediction 
Sequencing of the recombinant plasmids and the PCR amplifica-
tion products was performed according to Lata et al. (2010). 
Alignments were carried out by <rs type="software">ClustalW</rs> with default parameters 
(Thompson et al., 1994). The phylogenetic tree for the SiDREB2 
gene was built using the software program <rs id="software-1" type="software">MEGA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">4.0</rs> based on 
protein sequences. The phylogenetic tree was set up with the 
distance matrix using the Neighbor-Joining (NJ) method with 
1000 bootstrap replications. Secondary structure prediction of the 
SiDREB2 protein was performed using the program <rs type="software">PSIPRED</rs> 
(Jones, 1999). The ab intio structure prediction of the protein was 
done with the help of <rs type="software">I-TASSER</rs> (Zhang, 2008). Automated 
homology model building of the DNA-binding domain was 
performed using the protein structure modelling program <rs type="software">MOD-
ELLER</rs> which models protein tertiary structure by satisfaction of 
spatial restraints. The input for <rs type="software">MODELLER</rs> consisted of the 
aligned sequences of 1gcc and the SiDREB2, a steering file that 
gives all the necessary commands to the MODELLER to produce 
a homology model of the target on the basis of its alignment with 
the template. Energy minimization was performed by the steepest 
descent followed by the conjugate gradient method using a 20 Å 
non-bonded cut-off and a constant dielectric of 1.0. Evaluation of 
the predicted model involved analyses of the geometry and the 
stereochemistry of the model. The reliability of the model structure 
was tested using the ENERGY commands of <rs type="software">MODELLER</rs> (Sali 
and Blundell, 1993). The modelled structures were also validated 
using the program <rs type="software">PROSA</rs> (Wiederstein and Sippl, 2007). </p>

<p>Southern blot analysis 
Genomic DNA of foxtail millet was extracted from leaves using 
the cetyltrimethylammonium bromide (CTAB) method (Saghai-
Maroof et al., 1984), digested with PvuII and HindIII (New 
England Biolabs), fractioned in a 1.0% agarose gel, and blotted on 
a Hybond N 
+ membrane (Amersham). The blots were hybridized 
to a 705 bp SiDREB2 probe radioactively labelled with [a-
32 P] 
dCTP using a High Prime DNA labeling kit (Roche, USA). 
Hybridization was carried out in 0.5 M sodium phosphate (pH 
7.2), 7% SDS, and 1 mM EDTA. </p>

<p>Subcellular localization of the SiDREB2 protein 
The SiDREB2 gene was fused to the 5' end of the green fluorescent 
protein (GFP) reporter gene using the pCAMBIA 1302 plant 
expression vector without a stop codon between the NcoI and SpeI 
sites. Recombinant DNA constructs encoding the SiDREB2-GFP 
fusion protein downstream of the cauliflower mosaic virus (CaMV) 
35S promoter were introduced into onion epidermal cells by gold 
particle bombardment using the PDS-1000 system (Bio-Rad) at 
1100 psi helium pressure. Onion cells were also transiently trans-
formed with the pCAMBIA 1302-GFP vector as a control. Trans-
formed cells were placed on MS solid medium at 22°C and 
incubated for ;48 h before being examined. The subcellular 
localization of GFP fusion proteins was visualized with a confocal 
microscope (TCS_SP2; Leica). </p>

<p>Quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) analysis 
About 2 lg of total RNA was used to synthesize first-strand 
cDNA primed with oligo(dT) in a 20 ll reaction mix using Pro-
toscript M-MuLV reverse transcriptase (New England Biolabs, 
USA) following the manufacturer's instructions. qRT-PCR was 
performed using Power SYBER-Green dye (Applied Biosystems) on 
a step one real-time PCR system of Applied Biosysytems in 
triplicate. The constitutive actin gene (CAA33874.1) was used as 
the endogenous control (Actin RT_F, 5#-CTGACGCCGAGGATATCCA-3#; </p>



<p>and Actin RT_R, 5#-GCCTTGACCATACCAGTTCCA-3#). The 
amount of transcript accumulated for the SiDREB2 gene 
(SiDREB2 RT_F, 5#-GCCTTGTAGTCATTTGTGGTTT-3#; 
and SiDREB2 RT_R, 5#-CCTCACAACTCCTTTTCTCAAGCT-
3#) normalized to the internal control actin was analysed using 
the 2-
DD Ct method (Livak and Schmittgen, 2001). The primers 
used for real-time PCR analysis were designed by using <rs id="software-9" type="software">Primer 
Express</rs> <rs corresp="#software-9" type="version-number">version 3.0</rs>. The PCR cycling conditions were: initial 
denaturation at 95°C for 10 min, 95°C for 15 s, 60°C for 1 min 
for 40 cycles, 95°C for 15 s, and 60°C for 1 min and 95°C for 
15 s. </p>

<p>SNP assay 
A core set of 45 foxtail millet accessions, listed in Table 1, were 
analysed for SNP discovery by re-sequencing of the SiDREB2 
gene. Genomic DNA was extracted as mentioned earlier. The 
SiDREB2 FL_F/SiDREB2 FL_R primer pair was used to amplify 
full-length SiDREB2 in all 45 accessions. PCR was performed 
using Sigma Taq DNA polymerase (1 U) in a 20 ll reaction 
volume containing ;50 ng of gemonic DNA, 13 PCR buffer 
(1.5 mM MgCl 2 ), 10 lM of each dNTP, and 10 pmol of each 
primer. PCR cycling was done as mentioned earlier. Amplified 
PCR products were precipitated and sequenced in both directions. 
Sequences were aligned by <rs type="software">ClustalW</rs>. </p>

<p>Development of a marker for an allele of SiDREB2 
To obtain primers specific to the identified SNP, the segment of 
the SiDREB2 sequence containing the SNP site was entered into 
the Primer 3.0 program. Three primers designed corresponding to 
the SNP, namely DREB.AP2_F, SNP.TS_R, and SNP.Tol_R, 
were tested using standard PCR amplification as mentioned above. 
Amplified products were separated on a 1% agarose gel to estimate 
each allele in the SNP site as the presence or absence of a band. </p>

<p>Results and Discussion </p>

<p>Screening of foxtail millet accessions for dehydration 
tolerance </p>

<p>In this study, a core set of 45 foxtail millet (S. italica L.) 
accessions were studied for their dehydration tolerance on 
the basis of LP and RWC. The total amount of TBA-
reacting substances reflects the level of LP resulting from 
oxidative stress (Guo et al., 2006). The increased accumula-
tion of lipid peroxides upon oxidative stress indicates 
enhanced production of toxic reactive oxygen species 
(ROS). ROS are responsible for stress-induced peroxidation 
of membrane lipids and are often used as an indicator of 
increased oxidative damage (Smirnoff, 1995). The level of 
MDA increased significantly in the sensitive accessions 
during 24 h of dehydration stress with respect to the control 
(sensitive, &lt;100% increase; highly sensitive, &gt;100% increase; 
P &lt;0.05), whereas the level of LP in the tolerant accessions 
declined significantly in comparison with the control (highly 
tolerant, &gt;30% decline; tolerant, &lt;30% decline; P &lt;0.05) 
(Table 1). Sreenivasulu et al. (1999) also observed an 
increase in MDA content in the sensitive foxtail millet cv. 
Lepakshi as compared with the tolerant cv. Prasad in 
response to 150 mM salinity stress in 5-day-old seedlings. 
LP was demonstrated as a function of membrane integrity in 
chickpea plants exposed to dehydration stress for 7 d and, 
together with electrolytic leakage, has been shown to be </p>

<p>a direct indicator of dehydration stress tolerance (Bhushan 
et al., 2007). Further, enhanced H 2 O 2 scavenging ability and 
low levels of LP provide tolerance to various crop plants 
including pigeonpea, sesame, and alfalfa (Shigeoka et al., 
2002; Fazeli et al., 2007; Kumutha et al., 2009). 
The choice of RWC as the best representation of plant 
water status for assessing genetic differences in dehydration 
tolerance is supported by genetic association between RWC 
and plant production under dehydration (Blum, 1996; 
Bhushan et al., 2007). Although having the same water 
potential, genotypes may vary in their RWC due to the 
respective difference in osmotic adjustment. Leaf RWC was 
determined in 45 foxtail millet accessions exposed to 24 h of 
PEG-induced dehydration stress. Stress treatments signifi-
cantly decreased the RWC in all accessions (Table 1). The 
tolerant accessions showed the capacity to maintain a rela-
tively high RWC in comparison with the sensitive acces-
sions during stress (0-60% decline in highly tolerant, 
61-66% decline in tolerant; 70-75% decline in sensitive, 
&gt;75% decline in highly sensitive; P &lt;0.05). The above 
observations are in accordance with previous reports on 
several other water-stressed crop plants such as Cenchrus 
sp., chickpea, groundnut, wheat, sorghum, and maize (Nagy 
et al., 1995; El Hafid et al., 1998; Madhusudan et al., 2006; 
Bhushan et al., 2007; Chandra and Dubey, 2010). </p>

<p>Cloning and sequence analysis of the SiDREB2 gene </p>

<p>An EST (GenBank accession no. GT090998) coding for 
putative DREB2 was isolated from a 6 h SSH library as 
a differentially expressed sequence in response to PEG-
induced dehydration stress. The original 529 bp truncated 
cDNA clone was complete at its 3' end and aligned to 
a maize gene encoding a DREB2. Hence, a 5' RACE was 
carried out to obtain the 5' end of the cDNA. Finally the 
open reading frame (ORF) of this gene was amplified by 
RT-PCR and cloned. This gene, designated as SiDREB2 
(GenBank ID HQ132744), had a full-length cDNA of 
1119 bp, with an ORF of 705 nucleotides. The deduced 
protein contained 234 amino acids with a predicted molec-
ular mass of 25.72 kDa and a theoretical pI of 5.14. The 
SiDREB2 protein has a highly conserved AP2/ERF DNA-
binding domain of 58 amino acids. It also had two 
conserved functional amino acids (valine and glutamic acid) 
at the 14th and 19th residues, respectively, in the DNA-
binding domain, thought to be crucial sites for the binding 
of DREBs and DRE core sequences (Liu et al., 1998). An 
alkaline N-terminal amino acid region (RRK), which might 
act as a nuclear localization signal, and a conserved Ser/ 
Thr-rich region adjacent to the AP2/ERF DNA-binding 
domain were also present (Fig. 1A). The protein contained 
an acidic C-terminal region which might be functional in 
trans-activation activity (Stockinger et al., 1997). Most of 
the positively charged residues are found to be conserved in 
the N-terminal domain of SiDREB2. 
Multiple sequence alignment revealed that SiDREB2 
has high similarity to DREB proteins from other plants 
(Supplementary Fig. S1 available at JXB online). High </p>

<p>Association of an SNP with dehydration stress in foxtail millet | 3391 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Homologue analysis of the deduced amino acid sequence of the SiDREB2 protein. (A) Sequence analysis of the SiDREB2 gene. 
The nuclear localization signal (RRK) in the N-terminus is underlined in bold. The serine/threonine-rich region has dashed underlining. 
Two conserved amino acid residues, valine (V) and glutamic acid (E), in the AP2 domain of the SiDREB2 protein are double underlined. 
The AP2/ERF conserved domain of SiDREB2 is single underlined. The start (ATG) and stop (TAG) codons are boxed. Full-length 
primer-binding sites are marked with arrows. (B) Comparison of the deduced amino acid sequence of the AP2/ERF domain of the 
SiDREB2 protein with other DREB proteins using <rs id="software-12" type="software">CLC</rs> free workbench <rs corresp="#software-12" type="version-number">version 3.0</rs>. The amino acid residues with 100% homology are 
light in colour while the partially conserved residues are in different colours. The consensus sequence is shown in bold in black at the 
bottom of the alignment. (C) Phylogenetic analysis of AP2/ERF domains of published AP2/EREBP proteins in the NCBI database. The 
phylogenetic tree was generated by <rs id="software-13" type="software">MEGA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-13" type="version-number">4.0</rs> software. Branch lengths indicate the distance. A-1 to A-6 indicate the groups proposed 
by Sakuma et al. (2002). SiDREB2 is indicated by a circle. The appended proteins are as follows: Arabidopsis thaliana DREB1 
(BAA33434), DREB1B (BAA33435), DREB1C (BAA33436), RAP2.1 (NP564496), RAP2.10 (NP195408), RAP2.3 (NP188299), RAP2.4 
(NP177931), RAP2.6 (AAC36019), CBF1 (NP567721), DREB2A (AAU93685), DREB2B (BAA36706), DREB2C (Q8LFR2), ABI4 
(AF085279), RAV1 (NP172784), RAV2 (AB013887), ERF1 (AB008103), ERF3 (AB008105), TINY (AAC29139); Oryza sativa OsDREB1A </p>



<p>Le C BF1 </p>

<p>ERF Subfamily </p>

<p>RAV Subfamily </p>

<p>DREB1B </p>

<p>C BF1 </p>

<p>DREB1 </p>

<p>DREB1C </p>

<p>NtDREB2 </p>

<p>Gh DREB1A </p>

<p>BjDREB1B </p>

<p>BnC BF7 </p>

<p>HvC BF1 </p>

<p>BC BF1 </p>

<p>TaDB F </p>

<p>HvDBF2 </p>

<p>O sDREB1B </p>

<p>BSBF3 </p>

<p>Zm DBF3 </p>

<p>FaDREB1 </p>

<p>O sDREB1A </p>

<p>TINY </p>

<p>Gm TINY </p>

<p>RAP2.1 </p>

<p>RAP2.10 </p>

<p>ABI4 </p>

<p>O sDREB2C </p>

<p>O RCA1 </p>

<p>DREB2C </p>

<p>S bDREB2 </p>

<p>ZmDREB2A </p>

<p>Si DREB2 </p>

<p>O sDREB2 </p>

<p>Pe DREB2 </p>

<p>HvDRF1.3 </p>

<p>HvDRF1.1 </p>

<p>O sDREB2B </p>

<p>DREB2B </p>

<p>DREB2A </p>

<p>ThDREB2B </p>

<p>RAP2.4 </p>

<p>Zm DBF1 </p>

<p>O sDBF1 </p>

<p>ERF1 </p>

<p>RAP2.3 </p>

<p>ERF3 </p>

<p>O sERF3 </p>

<p>TS I1 </p>

<p>RAP2.6 </p>

<p>Gl ossy15 </p>

<p>RAV1 </p>

<p>RAV2 </p>

<p>81 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>99 </p>

<p>99 </p>

<p>99 </p>

<p>93 </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>79 </p>

<p>67 </p>

<p>68 </p>

<p>95 </p>

<p>91 </p>

<p>89 </p>

<p>87 </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>69 </p>

<p>84 </p>

<p>73 </p>

<p>76 </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>63 </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>74 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>97 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>A-1 </p>

<p>A-4 </p>

<p>A-5 
A-3 </p>

<p>A-2 </p>

<p>A-6 </p>

<p>AP2 Subfamily </p>

<p>DREB 
Subfamily </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Continued. </p>

<p>Association of an SNP with dehydration stress in foxtail millet | 3393 </p>

<p>sequence similarity in the AP2/ERF domain indicated that 
DREB genes were well conserved among gramineous crops 
(Fig. 1B). To determine further the relatedness of SiDREB2 
to the other AP2/EREBP proteins, a systematic phyloge-
netic analysis was carried out based on the similarities of 
AP2 domains in the proteins isolated from Arabidopsis, 
rice, maize, wheat, sorghum, barley, Festuca, Phyllostachys, 
tomato, tobacco, cotton, Catharanthus, and Brassica species 
using <rs id="software-14" type="software">MEGA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-14" type="version-number">4.0</rs> by the NJ method (Fig. 1C). SiDREB2 
was classified into the A-2 subgroup of the DREB sub-
family on the basis of the phylogenetic tree constructed. </p>

<p>Structure of the full-length protein </p>

<p>Knowledge of the three-dimensional (3D) structure of 
a protein is a necessary prerequisite for understanding its </p>

<p>molecular function. To create a 3D structure of SiDREB2, 
a BLAST search was performed in protein databases for 
proteins with similar sequence and known 3D structure, but 
no significant homologous template was found to model the 
complete sequence. Thus, ab initio modelling of SiDREB2 
was done with the help of the <rs type="software">I-TASSER</rs> server. In brief, 
this is a hierarchical protein structure modelling approach 
based on the secondary structure-enhanced Profile-Profile 
threading alignment (Zhang, 2008). The model structure 
was validated with <rs type="software">PROSA</rs> (z-score of -5.58) which was in 
the range of native conformations of other experimentally 
determined protein structures of the same size (Wiederstein 
and Sippl, 2007). The overall structure has an a-b fold and 
the DNA-binding domain contained antiparallel b-sheets 
and an a-helix packed approximately parallel to the b-sheet 
(Fig. 1D). This domain, which is highly positively charged, </p>

<p>(AAN02486), OsDREB1B (AAX28958), OsDREB2 (AAN02487), OsDREB2B (Q5W6R4), OsDREB2C (Q84ZA1), OsERF3 
(NP_001064506), OsDBF1 (AAP56252); Zea mays ZmDREB2A (ACG47772), ZmDBF1 (AAM80486), ZmDBF3 (NP 001105651), 
Glossy15 (NP_001105890); Triticum aestivum TaDBF (AAL37944); Sorghum bicolor SbDREB2 (ACA79910); Hordeum vulgare HvDBF2 
(AAM13419), HvCBF1 (AAX23686), BCBF1 (AAK01088), BCBF3 (AAK01089), HvDRF1.1 (AAO38209), HvDRF1.3 (AAO38211); Festuca 
arundinacea FeDREB1 (CAG30550); Phyllostachys edulis PeDREB2 (ABY19376); Solanum lycopersicum (formerly Lycopersicon 
esculentum) LeCBF1 (AAS77820); Nicotiana tabacum NtDREB2 (ACE73694), Tsl1 (AAC14323); Gossypium hirsutum GhDREB1A 
(AAP83936); Glycine max GmTINY (ACP40513); Catharanthus roseus ORCA1 (CAB93939); Brassica juncea BjDREB1B (ABX00639), 
Brassica napus BnCBF7 (AAM18959); Thellungiella halophila ThDREB2B (ABV08790). (D) 3D structure of the full-length SiDREB2 
protein. The DNA-binding domain which spans from 56 to 113 amino acid residues in the peptide chain is coloured blue. The 
electrostatic surface potential is shown in a colour gradient from positive (blue) to negative (red). The DNA-binding domain is highly 
positively charged which complements the negatively charged DNA double helix. (E) The N-terminal DNA-binding domain of SiDREB2 is 
shown on the left as a cartoon, and on the right the electrostatic surface potential is shown in a colour gradient from positive (blue) to 
negative (red). </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Continued. </p>



<p>binds the negatively charged DNA double helix. The 
tertiary structure is stabilized by 224 intramolecular hydro-
gen bonds as determined by the program <rs type="software">HBPLUS</rs> 
(McDonald and Thornton, 1994). The majority of these 
hydrogen bonds (44%) are formed by atoms where both the 
acceptor and donor are from the main chain of the amino 
acid residues. Only in 25% of the cases are both the 
acceptor and donor atoms the side chain atoms. The rest 
(31%) are observed where both main chain and side chain 
atoms are participating. </p>

<p>Structure of the DNA-binding domain </p>

<p>The structure of the AP2 domain of AtERF1 from 
Arabidopsis thaliana (PDB code 1gcc) was taken as a tem-
plate for the comparative modelling of the DNA-binding 
domain of SiDREB2 (Fig. 1E) (Allen et al., 1998). The 
sequence alignment between the target and the template is 
shown in Supplementary Fig. S1 at JXB online. In addition, 
the secondary structure of this domain as predicted by 
several secondary structure prediction servers (<rs id="software-18" type="software">PHDsec</rs>: 
<rs corresp="#software-18" type="url">www.predictprotein.org</rs>/; <rs id="software-19" type="software">PSIPRED</rs>: <rs corresp="#software-19" type="url">http://bioinf.cs.ucl.ac.uk/psipred</rs>/) is quite similar to the secondary structure of 
1gcc (Supplementary Fig. S1, and Fig. 1E). This finding 
supports the results obtained from several fold recognition 
servers 
(<rs id="software-20" type="software">FUGUE</rs>: 
<rs corresp="#software-20" type="url">www-cryst.bioc.cam.ac.uk/;fugue</rs>/; 
<rs id="software-21" type="software">3DPSSM</rs>: <rs corresp="#software-21" type="url">www.sbg.bio.ic.ac.uk</rs>/), suggesting that SiDREB2 
has the fold of the DNA-binding domain of the DREB 
superfamily. Based on the above information, the 'A' 
subunit of 1gcc was used as a template to predict the 3D 
structure of SiDREB2 by applying the comparative model-
ling strategy as described in the Materials and methods. The 
overall rmsd (root mean square deviation) between the 
template and the target structure is 0.2 Å . The calculated 
angle between the b-sheet and a-helices is ;172°. The 
amino acid residues Arg6, Arg8, Trp10, Glu16, Arg18, 
Arg25, and Trp27 that are known to make direct 
contact with the DNA double helix for deciphering the 
DNA-binding activity are also fully conserved. </p>

<p>Genomic organization of SiDREB2 </p>

<p>The copy number of SiDREB2 in the foxtail millet genome 
was determined by DNA gel blot (Southern analysis). 
Genomic DNA was digested with PvuII and HindIII 
restriction enzymes, and transferred to the membrane. After 
digestion with HindIII, which did not cut this gene, a single 
hybridization band was detected, whereas with PvuII, which 
cuts the gene once, two major hybridization bands of high 
intensity with a few minor bands were detected (Supple-
mentary Fig. S2 at JXB online). These results indicate that 
this gene has a low copy number in the foxtail millet 
genome; however, the minor bands indicate the presence of 
a low number of homologous copies of SiDREB2. Such an 
observation has also been confirmed in wheat for Wdreb2 
(Egawa et al., 2006). In addition, a comparison of the 
genomic clone with the cDNA clone showed that SiDREB2 
is an intron-less gene (Supplementary Fig. S3). </p>

<p>Nuclear localization of SiDREB2 protein </p>

<p>To investigate the subcellular localization of the SiDREB2 
protein, the coding region of the SiDREB2 gene was fused 
in-frame to the GFP gene, and the resulting construct was 
introduced into onion epidermal cells by particle bombard-
ment. Confocal microscopic observation demonstrated that 
GFP fluorescence was dispersed throughout the entire cell 
when bombarded with the control plasmid 35S-GFP. In 
contrast, the SiDREB2-GFP fusion protein was localized 
exclusively to the nucleus, indicating that SiDREB2 is 
a nuclear-localized protein (Fig. 2A-H). The result obtained 
confirms all previous reports that suggest DREBs to be 
nuclear localized (Mizuno et al., 2006; Liu et al., 2008; Zhao 
et al., 2010). </p>

<p>Expression characteristics of SiDREB2 in response to 
various stresses and hormones </p>

<p>The transcript of SiDREB2 was significantly induced in 
response to dehydration stress in highly tolerant accessions, 
namely Prasad and IC-403579, while its expression declined 
slowly after initial induction in both highly sensitive 
accessions, namely Lepakshi and IC-480117 (Fig. 3A). The 
up-regulation of this gene (up to 12-fold) in tolerant 
accessions suggests that it might impart drought tolerance 
capacity to the tolerant accessions in comparison with the 
sensitive ones. These observations were supported by a re-
cent study which suggested that the susceptibility of IR64 
was probably attributable to the significant down-regulation 
of regulatory components including DREBs that confer 
drought tolerance in rice (Lenka et al., 2010). 
In response to salinity, a strong gradually increasing 
induction pattern was observed from 0.5 h to 24 h with 
a slight decline at 6 h and at 48 h post-stress. However, its 
expression in other stresses was much less in comparison 
with the control (Fig. 3B). The strong responsiveness of the 
SiDREB2 gene to dehydration and salinity implies that its 
role in the transduction of abiotic stress signals is very 
similar to those of Arabidopsis and rice, and occurs more or 
less through an ABA-independent pathway (Liu et al., 1998; 
Sakuma et al., 2002; Dubouzet et al., 2003). </p>

<p>Tissue-specific expression of SiDREB2 </p>

<p>The organ-specific expression of SiDREB2 in foxtail millet 
was detected by qRT-PCR. SiDREB2 expression can be 
detected in leaves, roots, and young and mature spikes 
under normal conditions (Fig. 4). Its transcripts were 
mainly expressed in leaves followed by roots. This expres-
sion pattern indicates that SiDREB2 may function in the 
normal programme of plant growth and development in this 
grass species. In Arabidopsis, DREB2 transcript accumula-
tion could also be detected in roots, leaves, and stems, while 
DREB1 was not expressed under normal growth conditions 
(Liu et al., 1998). This also indicated that SiDREB2 was 
more similar to DREB2. The transcript accumulation in 
young and mature spikes indicated that SiDREB2 may also 
play an important role in development and procreation. </p>

<p>Association of an SNP with dehydration stress in foxtail millet | 3395 </p>

<p>Fig. 3. qRT-PCR analysis of the SiDREB2 gene. (A) Time course expression analysis in two dehydration-tolerant (Prasad and IC-403579) 
and two sensitive accessions (Lepakshi and IC-480117) of foxtail millet in response to dehydration stress. (B) Time course expression 
analysis of the SiDREB2 gene under various stresses: 20% PEG 6000; 250 mM NaCl; cold at 4°C; 100 lM ABA; 100 lM SA; 100 lM 
MeJA; 100 lM ethephone; and water for 0.5, 1, 3, 6, 12, 24, and 48 h. Bars indicate the standard error (6SE) calculated from three 
independent experiments. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Subcellular localization of the SiDREB2 protein in onion epidermal cells. Onion epidermal cells were transiently transformed with 
constructs containing either control pCAMBIA1302-GFP or SiDREB2-GFP under the control of the CaMV 35S promoter by the particle 
bombardment method. The subcellular localization of the SiDREB2-GFP fusion protein or control was viewed with a fluorescent confocal 
microscope ;48 h after bombardment. DAPI (4',6-diamidino-2-phenylindole) images (A and E), fluorescence images (B and F), bright-
field images (C and G), and corresponding overlaid images (D and H) of representative cells expressing pCAMBIA1302-GFP or 
SiDREB2-GFP fusion protein are shown. </p>



<p>Such an observation has also been reported by Liu et al. 
(2008). </p>

<p>Identification and validation of an allele-specific marker 
(ASM) for the DREB2 locus </p>

<p>A core set of 45 foxtail millet accessions were screened for 
their dehydration tolerance on the basis of LP and RWC 
(Table 1). All the accessions were subjected to 24 h of 
dehydration stress as compared with the respective controls. 
The amplified genomic DNA sequence (SiDREB2 FL_F 
and SiDREB2 FL_R primers) analysis of SiDREB2 from 
four highly dehydration-tolerant (GS-464, IC-403579, Pra-
sad, and IC-403476) and four highly sensitive (IC-403521, 
IC-404178, Lepakshi, and IC-480117) accessions revealed 
the synonymous SNP at base pair 558 (A/G transition) 
(Fig. 5A). This A/G transition was further validated by 
sequencing of the SiDREB2 gene with the same primers in 
an additional 11 and 26 dehydration-tolerant and sensitive 
accessions, respectively (Table 1). Based on this sequence 
analysis, locus-specific primers (LSPs) and allele-specific 
primers (ASPs) were developed (Table 2). PCR products 
of LSPs (SiDREB2 FL_F and SNP.TS_R) and ASPs 
(DREB.AP2_F and SNP.Tol_R) in all 45 accessions were 
generated at the same time and checked by resolving them 
on a 1% agarose gel independently. Later, the PCR 
products were mixed and resolved on an agarose gel for 
both locus-specific markers and ASMs (Fig. 5B). LSPs gave 
a 558 bp fragment in all the accessions, while ASPs gave 
a 261 bp fragment in 15 dehydration-tolerant accessions 
only. Therefore, the dehydration-tolerant accessions were 
proven to be linked to the 'A'-specific allele (Table1). 
The importance of allele-specific PCR systems for reliable 
SNP typing has been demonstrated several times in previous 
studies (Wu et al., 1989; Wei et al., 2006). Introduction of 
additional mismatch bases has improved the specificity of 
this technique (Drenkard et al., 2000). Its application is 
especially important for an accurate discrimination of 
different alleles in <rs type="software">MAS</rs>. In the present study, only one pair 
of ASPs was used to amplify the specific products from the 
dehydration-tolerant and sensitive accessions. Therefore, </p>

<p>the ASM can be effectively used to type SNPs as well as to 
avoid unambiguous false scoring. The functional differences 
in trait performance mainly caused by SNPs has also been 
reported in previous studies on several cloned genes (Peng 
et al., 1999; Takahashi et al., 2001; Liu et al., 2002; Jin 
et al., 2003; Toshiyuki et al., 2003; Kim et al., 2005; Garcés-
Claver et al., 2007; Fan et al., 2009). Molecular marker-
assisted breeding technology is a rapid and accurate method 
for any candidate gene, providing a very effective tool for 
backcross breeding (Collard and Mackill, 2008). <rs type="software">MAS</rs> 
efficiency is influenced by several complex factors such as 
recombination between the marker and the candidate gene, 
a low level of polymorphism between the parents with 
contrasting traits, and lower resolution of quantitative trait 
loci (QTLs) due to environmental interactions. In the 
present study, the ASM is part of the candidate gene, thus 
eliminating the main disadvantage of <rs type="software">MAS</rs>. However, the 
ASM developed in this study is a dominant marker, and 
therefore it cannot distinguish the heterozygotes. The 
marker has high reliability and efficiency, and the desired 
PCR product can be identified easily on a simple agarose 
gel. With the help of this marker, dehydration-tolerant 
accessions can be selected at a variety of life stages. This is 
particularly true when the target is the dehydration-tolerant 
allele in backcross breeding and thus the foxtail millet 
breeding process can be accelerated. Further, the ASM 
identified would facilitate allele mining of foxtail millet 
germplasm resources, thereby leading to identification and 
utilization of newer alleles in crop improvement. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>In summary, the findings from the current study suggest that 
SiDREB2 is a novel DREB2-like transcription factor of the 
AP2/EREBP family since the sequence transition of A-G in 
this gene was associated with the differences in the de-
hydration tolerance levels among the foxtail millet acces-
sions. It mediates various stress responses and developmental 
processes in foxtail millet. The structure determination of the 
SiDREB2 gene and the DNA-binding domain may provide 
the framework for understanding the functions of DREBs at 
the molecular level. The higher expression level of SiDREB2 
in tolerant accessions in comparison with sensitive accessions 
could probably be due to some deficiency of a stress-
responsive regulatory cis-element in the promoter regions of 
the sensitive accessions or due to post-transcriptional modi-
fication of its gene. However, this remains to be demon-
strated before any conclusions can be reached. The ASM 
developed in this study requires validation before it can be 
implemented routinely to assist selection for dehydration 
tolerance in foxtail millet breeding. To the best of our 
knowledge, this is the first report of molecular cloning, 
characterization of a DREB2-like gene SiDREB2 in foxtail 
millet, and development of an ASM for dehydration 
tolerance. We are also currently exploring the biological 
functions of SiDREB2 in stress and developmental responses 
of foxtail millet using overexpression, gene silencing, and 
promoter analysis. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Expression patterns of SiDREB2 in various intact tissues of 
foxtail millet. Total RNAs were extracted from whole seedling, 
leaves, roots, young spikelets, and mature spikelets. The results 
are relative to expression in whole seedlings. Actin was used as 
endogenous control. Bars indicate the standard error (6SE) 
calculated from three independent experiments. </p>

<p>Association of an SNP with dehydration stress in foxtail millet | 3397 </p>

<p>Table 2. Sequences of primer pairs specific to the A/G single nucleotide polymorphism of the SiDREB2 gene used in PCR and sizes 
and phenotypes of the PCR products generated by each primer pair </p>

<p>Allele 
Primer sequence (5#-3#) 
PCR product size 
Phenotype </p>

<p>Locus specific 
SiDREB2 FL_F: CAACTCAGGAAGAAGAGGAT 
558 bp 
Monomorphic 
SNP.TS_R: TGAAGTACCTCCACGGACTTGCACT 
DREB.AP2_F: ATGCATACGACGAGGCGGCAAAGG 
261 bp 
Polymorphic 
Allele specific 
SNP.Tol_R: TTGAAGTACCTCCACGGACTTGCAC </p>

<p>Fig. 5. SNP (A/G) transition of a single SNP in four dehydration-tolerant and sensitive accessions. (A) <rs type="software">ClustalW</rs> alignment between partial 
sequence of SiDREB2 containing the SNP in four dehydration-sensitive (IC-404178, Lepakshi, IC-403521, and IC-480117) and four 
tolerant (IC-403579, IC-403476, GS-464, and Prasad) foxtail millet accessions. Asterisks denote similar sequences, the box represents 
the SNP, solid arrows represent allele-specific primers (DREB.AP2_F and SNP.Tol_R), and the dashed arrow represents the locus-
specific reverse primer (SNP.TS_R). The locus-specific forward primer is shown as a dashed arrow in Fig. 1A. (B) Agarose gel image of 
the allele-specific and locus-specific SNP-derived allele-specific marker (ASM) associated with dehydration tolerance. The ASM can 
distinguish the A allele (tolerant), which generates a 261 bp fragment, from the G allele (sensitive), which generates no PCR fragment. 
The 558 bp fragment is common to both alleles and it is used as a positive control. The order of samples is the same as in Table 1. </p>



<p>Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data are available at JXB online. 
Figure S1. Sequence alignment of full-length SiDREB2 
protein with other DRE-binding transcription factors: Sor-
ghum SbDREB2 (ACA79916), maize ZmDREB2A (ACG47 
772), Buchloe BdDREB (ABP52086), Cynodon CdDREB1 
(AAS46284), Zoysia ZjDREB1 (ACV42429), Festuca FaD 
REB2A (CAG30547), Poa PpDREB (AAS59530), oat AsD 
REB2 (ABS11171), barley HvDREB1 (AAY25517), wheat 
DREB6 (AAX13289), rice OsDREB2A (A2WL19.2), 
OsDREB2 (NP_001042107), Phyllostachys PeDREB2 
(ABY19375), and tomato SlDREB (AAN77051). Identical 
amino acid residues in the DNA-binding domain are 
coloured red, strongly similar in green, and weakly similar in 
blue. Predicted secondary structures, helix (H), sheet (S), and 
coil (C) are also shown. 
Figure S2. Southern gel blot analysis of SiDREB2 cDNA. 
A 10 lg aliquot of foxtail millet genomic DNA was digested 
with PvuII and HindIII and fractioned in a 1% agarose gel. 
The SiDREB2 ORF (705 bp) was used as a probe. 
Figure S3. Genome organization of SiDREB2. The 
1103 bp genomic clone as well as the cDNA clone was 
PCR amplified using the primer pair SiDREB2 FL_F and 
SiDREB2 FL_R, and electrophoresed on a 0.8% agarose 
gel. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This study was supported by the Department of Biotech-
nology (grant no. BT/PR9851/AGR/02/521/2007), the Gov-
ernment of India, New Delhi, and a core grant from the 
National Institute of Plant Genome Research. CL acknowl-
edges the award of a SRF from the UGC, New Delhi. We 
are grateful to NBPGR, Hyderabad and UAS, GKVK, 
Bangalore, India for providing the seed materials, and to Dr 
N. K. Singh, IARI, and Dr. D. Chattopadhyay, NIPGR, 
New Delhi for helpful discussions. We would like to thank 
the reviewers for their constructive comments. </p>



<p>Association of an SNP with dehydration stress in foxtail millet | 3399 </p>







<p>Association of an SNP with dehydration stress in foxtail millet | 3401 </p>

</text></tei>