<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3457735" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Cancer immunoediting is the process whereby immune cells protect against cancer forma-
tion by sculpting the immunogenicity of developing tumors. Although the full process 
depends on innate and adaptive immunity, it remains unclear whether innate immunity 
alone is capable of immunoediting. To determine whether the innate immune system can 
edit tumor cells in the absence of adaptive immunity, we compared the incidence and 
immunogenicity of 3methylcholanthrene-induced sarcomas in syngeneic wild-type, 
RAG2 / , and RAG2 / x c / mice. We found that innate immune cells could manifest 
cancer immunoediting activity in the absence of adaptive immunity. This activity required 
natural killer (NK) cells and interferon  (IFN-), which mediated the induction of M1 
macrophages. M1 macrophages could be elicited by administration of CD40 agonists, 
thereby restoring editing activity in RAG2 / x c / mice. Our results suggest that in the 
absence of adaptive immunity, NK cell production of IFN- induces M1 macrophages, 
which act as important effectors during cancer immunoediting. </p>

<p>1870 </p>

<p>Tumor editing by macrophages and NK cells | O'Sullivan et al. </p>

<p>into RAG2 / recipients, RAG2 / x c / regressor sarcoma 
cell lines formed tumors that became heavily infiltrated with 
M1 macrophages. The infiltration of M1 macrophages was 
associated with tumor editing and required host c and IFN- 
activity. In contrast, in the absence of c and IFN- function, 
RAG2 / x c / regressors were infiltrated with more M2 
macrophages, which can promote tumor formation (Sica et al., 
2008). We also found that M1 macrophages can be elicited by 
CD40 agonistic antibodies to restore the editing capacity of 
RAG2 / x c / mice. These studies document that compo-
nents of the innate immune system present in RAG2 / mice 
can manifest certain types of cancer immunoediting capacity 
in the absence of adaptive immunity and point, specifically, to 
M1 macrophages as important effectors in this process. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
MCA-induced sarcoma incidence is increased in RAG2 / x 
c / mice compared with syngeneic RAG2 / and WT mice 
To determine whether the innate immune system of RAG2 / 
mice was capable of tumor immunosurveillance, we compared 
the incidence of MCA-induced sarcomas in immunologically 
intact WT C57BL/6 mice to that of C57BL/6 mice with de-
fects in either adaptive immunity only (RAG2 / mice) or in 
both adaptive and innate immunity (RAG2 / x c / mice). 
Fig. 1 shows that the incidence of sarcomas was higher in 
RAG2 / x c / mice compared with RAG2 / mice at all 
doses tested. For example, at a dose of 25 µg MCA, the inci-
dence of sarcomas in WT, RAG2 / , and RAG2 / x c / 
mice was 35, 60, and 80%, respectively. In addition, at MCA doses 
of 25 or 100 µg, RAG2 / x c / mice developed sarcomas 
slightly faster than RAG2 / mice, indicating that the innate 
immune system in RAG2 / mice controlled MCA-induced 
tumor outgrowth to some extent. The difference in tumor in-
cidence between cohorts of mice were not caused by inherent 
strain differences, as heterozygote RAG +/ littermates did not 
show differences compared with WT mice (unpublished data). </p>

<p>Growth of MCA-induced sarcoma cell lines 
derived from RAG2 / x c / mice is inhibited 
when transplanted into syngeneic WT mice 
To study tumor editing, low-passage cell lines were 
derived from primary MCA tumor masses gener-
ated in C57BL/6 WT, RAG2 / , and RAG2 / x 
c / mice, and the immunogenicity of each cell 
line was assessed by transplanting them into naive 
WT syngeneic mice and monitoring their growth </p>

<p>models. In contrast, other studies have found that the innate 
immune system can promote tumor formation via alterna-
tively activated M2 macrophages (Gordon and Taylor, 2005) 
that augment angiogenesis and promote tissue invasion. M2 
macrophages also inhibit the formation of antitumor adap-
tive immunity, and therefore it is possible that innate im-
munity would promote tumor formation in the absence of 
adaptive immunity. 
Using the 3methylcholanthrene (MCA) model of sar-
comagenesis, we previously found that the immune system 
in WT mice could edit tumors more effectively than the 
immune system in RAG2 / mice (which lack adaptive 
immunity; Shankaran et al., 2001; Takahashi and Yamanaka, 
2006), but we did not assess whether tumors from RAG2 / 
mice were edited by the innate immune system. Because 
RAG2 / mice and other immunodeficient mice such as 
nude and SCID mice are routinely used as "immunodeficient" 
models for xenotransplantation and preclinical studies, it is crit-
ical to assess whether the innate immune system in these mice 
could have an impact, positive or negative, on tumor growth. 
Toward this end, we set out to quantitate tumor editing in 
WT versus RAG2 / versus RAG2 / x c / mice. 
RAG2 / x c / mice lack all lymphocytes, including 
NK, NK-T, -T, classical CD4 + ,and CD8 + -T cells and 
B cells, and thus show deficits in both innate and adaptive 
immunity. If cells of the innate immune system could hinder 
tumor growth, then we would expect RAG2 / x c / mice 
to demonstrate increased tumor incidence and decreased 
tumor editing compared with RAG2 / mice. Indeed, when 
we compared MCA-induced sarcoma incidence and tumor 
cell immunogenicity between the groups of mice, we found 
both increased incidence and immunogenicity of MCA-
induced sarcomas in RAG2 / x c / mice compared 
with RAG2 / mice, which, consistent with previous results 
(Shankaran et al., 2001), had increased incidence and immuno-
genicity of tumors compared with WT mice. When transplanted </p>

<p>Figure 1. RAG2 / x c / mice are more susceptible 
to MCA-induced sarcomas than syngeneic RAG2 / 
and WT mice. The indicated dose of MCA was injected 
into the subcutaneous space of mice, and sarcoma forma-
tion was monitored over time. All cohorts consisted of 
20 mice. Tumor-positive mice were defined as those that 
harbored a progressively growing mass ≥25 mm 2 . Similar 
results were found in a repeat experiment that included 
the 5 and 25 µg doses. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 10 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>sarcoma cell lines from 15 RAG2 / and 9 WT mice formed 
tumors in 64 and 97% of WT recipients, respectively. These 
results were reproduced in an independent MCA induction 
experiment, and the combined results of these two experi-
ments, encompassing 71 total MCA-induced sarcoma cell lines 
transplanted into 474 WT mice, 94 RAG2 / mice, or 51 
RAG2 / x c / mice, are shown in Table 1. Altogether, 
these results support the hypothesis that tumors from mice 
with greater immunodeficiency undergo decreased levels 
of immunoediting. </p>

<p>Tumor cell lines generated in RAG2 / x c / mice 
show an increased regressor frequency compared 
with cell lines from WT and RAG2 / mice 
We reported previously that the percentage of regressors within 
a group of MCA-induced sarcoma cell lines, the "regressor 
frequency" (Fig. 2) was 40% when the MCA-induced sarcoma 
cell lines were generated in RAG2 / mice and 0% when the 
cell lines were generated in WT mice (Shankaran et al., 2001). 
These percentages are remarkably reproducible, and have 
remained so even when experiments have been conducted in 
our three independent laboratories in La Jolla, CA, St. Louis, 
MO, and Melbourne, Australia (Fig. 4). Specifically, we found 
a consistent regressor frequency of 0% when MCA-induced 
sarcoma cell lines are generated in WT mice (50 cell lines 
from two strains and four independent experiments). Notably, 
MCA-induced sarcoma cell lines derived from RAG2 / mice 
displayed a 30-44% regressor frequency (82 cell lines from 
3 strains and 4 independent experiments). MCA-induced sar-
coma cell lines derived from RAG2 / x c / mice had the </p>

<p>(Fig. 2). As described previously (Kripke, 1974; Boon and 
Kellermann, 1977; Flood et al., 1987; Shankaran et al., 2001; 
Dunn et al., 2005), we observed two divergent growth phe-
notypes among the transplanted sarcomas: a regressor pheno-
type, defined by a failure to form a mass of &gt;9 mm in diameter 
in &gt;50% of transplantations into syngeneic WT mice, and a 
progressor phenotype, defined by the formation of masses 
&gt;9 mm in &gt;50% of transplantations into WT mice. When we 
examined groups of MCA-induced sarcoma cell lines gen-
erated from WT, RAG2 / , and RAG2 / x c / mice, we 
found that the proportion of regressor MCA-induced sarcoma 
cell lines was 0/9 WT, 3/10 RAG2 / , and 6/10 RAG2 / x 
c / (Fig. 3 A, right). All cell lines grew when transplanted 
into RAG2 / mice (Fig. 3 A, left), indicating that their 
rejection was caused by the adaptive immune system and 
was not simply a failure to grow in vivo. 
To determine the overall immunogenicity of each group of 
tumors, we examined the tumor-free survival of large cohorts of 
WT and RAG2 / mice challenged with panels of tumor cell 
lines derived from WT, RAG / , or RAG2 / x c / mice 
(Fig. 3 B). All MCA-induced sarcoma cell lines formed tumors 
in RAG2 / mice by 36 d after tumor cell transplant (Fig. 3 B, 
top). In contrast, the kinetics and frequency of tumor forma-
tion in WT recipients was dependent on the level of immune 
function of the original source from which the tumor cells 
were derived. Specifically, when 17 tumor cell lines derived 
from RAG2 / x c / mice were transplanted into a total of 
132 naive, syngeneic WT mice, only 46% of the mice formed 
tumors by 70 d after transplant (Fig. 3 B, bottom; P &lt; 0.001 for 
all comparisons). Over a similar time course, MCA-induced </p>

<p>Figure 2. Generation of MCA sarcoma cell lines of varying immunogenicities to study cancer immunoediting by innate and adaptive immunity. 
(A) The carcinogen MCA is administered to syngeneic mice with three levels of immune function. (n ≥ 20 mice for each cohort). (B) The immunogenicity 
of the MCA sarcomas is postulated to be heterogeneous. (C) MCA sarcoma cell lines are generated from each tumor mass and transplanted into syngeneic 
WT mice (n &gt; 5 for each cell line) to assess growth. (D) Shown is the % growth of each cell line after transplant into WT mice. Cell lines that grow in 
&lt;51% of the mice are termed regressors. Cell lines that grow in &gt;50% of mice are termed progressors. (E) For each genotype, the percentage of tumor 
cell lines that displayed a regressor growth pattern is plotted. The "percent regressor tumors" is postulated to be inversely correlated with the quantity of 
immune pressure that is occurring during tumor formation in each mouse genotype. </p>



<p>Tumor editing by macrophages and NK cells | O'Sullivan et al. </p>

<p>Figure 3. A majority of MCA-induced sar-
coma cell lines derived from RAG2 / x c / 
mice cannot form tumors when transplanted 
into syngeneic WT mice. MCA-induced sarcoma 
cell lines were derived from tumors generated in 
syngeneic C57BL/6-strain WT, RAG2 / , and 
RAG2 / x c / mice. These cell lines were trans-
planted into syngeneic RAG2 / (n ≥ 2 for each 
cell line) or WT (n ≥ 5 for each cell line) hosts, 
and tumor growth was measured over time. 
(A) The mean growth for each cell line is shown 
(open symbols = regressor cell lines; closed sym-
bols = progressor cell lines). (B) The percentage of 
WT mice that developed tumors is shown for 
group of cell lines. Tumor-free mice were defined 
as having a nonenlarging mass &lt;9 mm in average 
diameter. The number of cell lines and mice are 
indicated in the figure. </p>

<p>highest regressor frequency (60-70%), indi-
cating that as a group, these cell lines were 
the most immunogenic and least edited. </p>

<p>RAG2 / x c / regressors 
undergo editing when transplanted 
into RAG2 / mice 
Because regressor cell lines generated 
from RAG2 / x c / mice displayed 
the highest levels of immunogenicity and, 
subsequently, the lowest levels of immuno-
editing compared with RAG2 / and 
WT mice, we hypothesized that the in-
nate immune system of RAG2 / mice 
could edit these tumor cell lines in vivo. 
We tested this by transplanting two in-
dependent sarcoma cell lines generated 
from RAG2 / x c / mice into either 
RAG2 / or RAG2 / x c / mice. To 
determine if in vivo passaging altered the 
immunogenicity of these cell lines, tumor 
masses were harvested at day 25 and con-
verted into cell lines. When these cell lines 
were transplanted into WT mice, 88% of 
RAG2 / -passaged tumor cell lines formed 
progressively growing tumor masses by 
day 40 compared with 46% of RAG2 / x 
c / -passaged and 10% of unpassaged 
cell lines (Fig. 5 A; P = 0.025). These re-
sults suggest a higher level of editing by 
the innate immune system in RAG2 / 
versus RAG2 / x c / mice but also 
indicate that there is some level of measur-
able tumor sculpting in RAG2 / x c / 
mice, which could be caused by residual 
immune function or a nonimmunologi-
cal editing process. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 10 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>regressors over progressors, we performed standard chromium 
release cytotoxicity assays (Bui et al., 2006) and also examined 
the NK cell content in regressor versus progressor tumors. 
We found that the overall susceptibility to NK cell killing of 
10 MCA-induced sarcoma cell lines from RAG2 / x c / 
mice did not differ from that of 10 MCA-induced sarcoma 
cell lines from RAG2 / , or 9 MCA-induced sarcomas from 
WT mice (Fig. 5 B). Even when all tumors were grouped 
based on phenotypic growth in WT mice-grouped into pro-
gressors or regressors-we observed no difference in NK cell-
specific lysis (Fig. 5 B). Additionally, we did not detect a 
difference in NK1.1 + cell infiltration (5%) into any of the 
MCA-induced sarcomas after they were transplanted into 
RAG2 / mice (Fig. 5 C). </p>

<p>MHC class II-positive macrophages are selectively 
present in regressor tumors during immunoediting 
We therefore redirected our focus on myeloid cells, as they 
represent the major hematopoietic lineage cell type that infil-
trates either rejecting or progressively growing tumors (Sica 
et al., 2008). To examine this issue, two RAG2 / x c / re-
gressor cell lines were transplanted into either RAG2 / or 
RAG2 / x c / hosts, and tumors were harvested at day 15 
and analyzed by immunohistochemistry (IHC) to assess the 
number and phenotypes of infiltrating myeloid cells. Strikingly, 
we observed significantly higher numbers of MHC class II-
positive cells in tumors growing in RAG2 / versus RAG2 / x 
c / hosts (Fig. 6, A and B; P = 0.00156 and 0.0071, 
respectively). This was likely caused by increased MHC class 
II induction rather than an increase in macrophages, as no 
differences were detected in the total number of macro-
phages infiltrating tumors growing in either RAG2 / or 
RAG2 / x c / hosts, as detected by the tissue macrophage 
marker CD68 (Fig. 6 B, right). A similar preferential accu-
mulation of MHC class II-positive cells was also observed in 
unedited versus edited tumors growing in RAG2 / mice 
(Fig. 6, C-E). In these studies, total monocyte-lineage cells 
(as marked flow cytometrically by F4/80) 
was similar between edited and unedited 
tumors, but the percentage of F4/80 + 
cells that expressed high levels of MHC 
class II was higher in unedited versus 
edited tumors. </p>

<p>NK cells do not preferentially kill regressor versus 
progressor tumor cells 
Having shown that c is important for the ability of innate 
immunity to control and edit MCA-induced sarcomas, we 
predicted that NK cells, dependent on c for development 
(Cao et al., 1995), would participate in this editing process 
in vivo. To explore whether NK cells preferentially recognize </p>

<p>Table 1. A summary of two independent MCA induction 
immunoediting experiments </p>

<p>Tumor group 
Growth in WT Growth in 
RAG / </p>

<p>Growth in RAG / 
 xc / </p>

<p>9 WT tumors into 87 
WT or 22 RAG hosts 
(exp 1) </p>

<p>97% (84/87) 100% (22/22) 
ND </p>

<p>15 RAG tumors into 
120 WT or 7 into 
15 RAG hosts (exp 
1) </p>

<p>64% (77/120) 100% (15/15) 
ND </p>

<p>17 RAGxc tumors 
into 132 WT or 10 
into 27 RAG hosts 
(exp 1) </p>

<p>46% (61/132) 100% (27/27) 
ND </p>

<p>10 WT tumors into 35 
WT or 21 RAGxc 
hosts(exp 2) </p>

<p>100% (35/35) 
ND 
100% (21/21) </p>

<p>10 RAG tumors into 
50 WT or 30 RAG 
hosts (exp 2) </p>

<p>60% (30/50) 100% (30/30) 
ND </p>

<p>10 RAGxc tumors 
into 50 WT or 30 
RAGxc hosts 
(exp 2) </p>

<p>30% (15/50) 
ND 
100% (30/30) </p>

<p>A total of 71 MCA sarcoma cell lines were generated from the indicated mice and 
then transplanted into 474 WT, RAG / , or RAG2 / x c / mice, and tumor 
growth was monitored. Regressor frequencies from these experiments (1 and 2) 
are shown in Fig. 4. ND, not determined. </p>

<p>Figure 4. The frequency of regressor cell 
lines is greater from tumors generated in 
RAG2 / x c / mice compared with WT and 
other immune deficient mice. A summary of 
two MCA-induction experiments performed in 
this manuscript is plotted in the context of pre-
vious MCA-induction experiments. Previously 
published experiments are included for compari-
son purposes and are from previous studies 
(Shankaran et al., 2001; Dunn et al., 2005; Koebel 
et al., 2007). Absolute numbers of regressors/total 
number of cell lines tested is shown next to the 
bar for each experiment. </p>

<p>1874 </p>

<p>Tumor editing by macrophages and NK cells | O'Sullivan et al. </p>

<p>infiltration did not differ between hosts as determined by CD68 + 
events (Fig. 7 D). These results demonstrate that NK cells and 
IFN- may facilitate editing by activating macrophages. </p>

<p>Tumor-associated macrophages (TAMs) from regressor 
tumors display an M1 phenotype and require NK cells 
and IFN- for polarization in vivo 
Because the MHC class II + macrophages required IFN- 
for their accumulation, we hypothesized that these macro-
phages were classically activated (Gordon and Taylor, 2005) 
M1 macrophages and performed immunophenotyping to 
detect the presence of tumor-associated M1 or M2 macro-
phages, known to have anti-or pro-tumor functions, respec-
tively (Lewis and Pollard, 2006; Sica et al., 2008). For this 
purpose, we used a combination of IHC and FACS analysis 
combined with defining cytokine production in freshly har-
vested tumors. In all cases, we analyzed no fewer than three 
tumors across at least two experiments. We first performed 
IHC analysis for the M2-type macrophage marker CD206 
and compared the staining pattern to that of MHC class II 
(known to be up-regulated on M1 macrophages versus M2 
macrophages; Fig. 8 A). We found that regressor tumors 
harvested from RAG2 / mice had the highest percentage 
of class II high events (29%) and lowest percentage of </p>

<p>Editing of regressor tumor cells from RAG2 / x c / mice 
and induction of MHC class II on tumor-infiltrating cells 
requires NK cells and IFN- production in vivo 
Because c was important for editing, but NK cell-depen-
dent tumor cell killing was not, we hypothesized that NK 
cell-derived IFN- was critical for the editing process we 
observed in RAG2 / mice. We therefore transplanted a re-
gressor cell line derived from a RAG2 / x c / mouse into 
RAG2 / recipients treated either with the neutralizing H22 
IFN--specific monoclonal antibody (mAb), an NK1.1 spe-
cific monoclonal antibody (PK136), or a control mAb (PIP). 
Tumors were harvested at day 20 and converted into cell 
lines, which were subsequently transplanted into naive, syn-
geneic WT hosts to measure tumor-free survival. We observed 
a statistically significant increase in the survival of WT mice 
transplanted with MCA-induced sarcomas that had been pas-
saged through NK cell-depleted and IFN--neutralized mice 
versus control mice (Fig. 7, A and B; P = 0.0042 and 0.0016, 
respectively), indicating that NK cells and IFN- play critical 
roles in activating the editing capacity of the innate immune 
system in RAG2 / mice. Analysis of tumor cross sections 
by IHC at day 20 showed MHC class II-positive macro-
phages were significantly reduced with anti-IFN- treatment 
(Fig. 7, C and D; P = 0.0432), even though total macrophage </p>

<p>Figure 5. RAG2 / x c / regressors are edited when transplanted into RAG2 / mice, but are not specifically recognized by NK cells. Two 
independent MCA-induced sarcoma cell lines generated from RAG2 / x c / mice were transplanted into syngeneic RAG2 / x c / or RAG2 / mice, 
and tumor masses were harvested at day 25 and converted into "passaged" daughter cell lines, which were transplanted into syngeneic WT mice (number of 
cell lines and mice are shown in the figure), and (A) the percentage of WT mice that remained tumor-free is shown for each group of cell lines. Tumor-free 
mice were defined to have a nonenlarging mass &lt;9 mm in average diameter by day 40. (B) MCA sarcoma cell lines were cultured with IL-2-activated 
NK cells in a 5-h chromium release cytotoxicity assay and specific lysis normalized to YAC-1-specific lysis is plotted for each cell line based on immune back-
ground and phenotype. (C) Regressor and progressor cell lines were transplanted into RAG-deficient mice and analyzed for infiltrating NK cells by FACS. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 10 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>that regressor tumors contained significantly higher percentages 
of M1 macrophages when isolated from RAG2 / mice 
treated with control mAb PIP (56%) compared with either 
RAG2 / mice treated with anti-NK1.1 mAb (28%), neutral-
izing IFN- mAb (37%), or RAG2 / x c / (20%) mice 
(Fig. 8 B, top; P &lt; 0.0001 for all populations). Conversely, M2 
macrophage percentages were slightly increased in tumors iso-
lated from RAG2 / mice treated with anti-IFN- (36%) and 
RAG2 / x c / mice (37%), but not anti-NK1.1-treated 
mice (27%) compared with control RAG2 / mice (28%; 
Fig. 8 B, bottom; P = 0.0007 and 0.002, respectively), confirm-
ing our IHC results. Tumor cell suspensions isolated from the 
different groups of mice did not show differences in total 
numbers of CD45 + or CD11b + cells (unpublished data), thus </p>

<p>CD206 + events (33%). In contrast, tumors harvested from 
both RAG2 / mice depleted of IFN- or RAG2 / x c / 
mice had significantly lower percentages of class II events (12 
and 10%, respectively) and significantly higher percentages of 
CD206 + events (60 and 70%, respectively; Fig. 8 A). Thus, 
IHC analysis suggested that M1-phenotype macrophage accu-
mulation within tumors requires both IFN- and c. We next 
used FACS analysis to gate on TAM subsets using combina-
tions of CD11b, Ly6C, and MHC class II to differentiate 
between M1 and M2 macrophages (Fig. 8 C) as previously 
described (Movahedi et al., 2010). This gating strategy identi-
fied M1 macrophages as MHC class II hi , Ly6C lo , CD206 lo , 
F4/80 hi cells and M2 macrophages as MHC class II lo , Ly6C lo , 
CD206 hi , F4/80 hi cells (Fig. 8, C and D). This analysis showed </p>

<p>Figure 6. MHC class II + macrophages preferentially infiltrate unedited regressors. (A) Representative images of tumor sections from RAG2 / 
or RAG2 / x c / hosts stained for MHC class II. (B) Quantification of MHC class II + events and CD68 + events in tumor sections is shown. (C-E) Regressor 
and progressor cell lines were transplanted into RAG2 / mice and analyzed for activated MHC class II + macrophages. (C) Representative FACS plots of 
three regressor and three progressor tumors are shown. Cells were gated on a CD45 + PI  population. (D) Percentages of activated monocyte-lineage 
(F4/80 + ) cell populations are shown for regressor and progressor tumor masses. Each symbol represents a different tumor cell line transplanted into 
1-3 RAG2 / mice. (E) Frozen tumor sections of progressor and regressor tumor masses growing in RAG2 / mice were stained for MHC class II. Nuclei 
were counterstained with hematoxylin. Bar, 100 m. **, P &lt; 0.01. Error bars are represented by ± SEM. IHC results were reproduced at least once. </p>



<p>Tumor editing by macrophages and NK cells | O'Sullivan et al. </p>

<p>To test a functional marker of TAM polarization, we exam-
ined supernatant of matched tumor cell suspensions cultured 
in vitro. Cell suspensions from tumors growing in control 
RAG2 / mice contained high levels of IL-1 and IFN- 
and produced levels of IL-6 and TNF that were similar to 
bone marrow-derived macrophages stimulated with LPS 
and IFN-, indicative of a classically activated M1 macrophage 
cytokine profile. In contrast, cell suspensions derived from 
tumors derived from anti-IFN--treated RAG2 / mice and 
RAG2 / x c / mice produced significantly lower levels 
of each cytokine (Fig. 8 E; P &lt; 0.0001 for all comparisons). 
We did not detect IL-10, or IL-4 production in any of the 
cultures, indicating that the M2 TAMs are not identical to 
alternatively activated M2 macrophages found in certain 
infections. No cytokine production was observed in cultures 
of the tumor cell line alone (unpublished data). This result 
demonstrates that the cytokines that were detected in the cell 
suspensions derived from in vivo growing tumors can be 
attributed to the immune subsets that infiltrate the tumor. 
To identify the phenotype of the infiltrating macrophages, 
cell suspensions from regressor tumors transplanted into 10 
RAG2 / x c / or 10 RAG2 / mice were harvested at 
day 15, and M1 and M2 TAMs were sorted and character-
ized by quantitative PCR, using markers known to be asso-
ciated with an M1-type phenotype (TNF and inducible nitric 
oxide synthase [iNOS]; Martinez et al., 2009) or with an 
M2-type phenotype (arginase and epithelial cadherin [eCAD]), 
growth arrest-specific gene 3 (Gas3; Ghassabeh et al., 2006; 
Fig. 8 F). Macrophages sorted from tumors transplanted into 
RAG2 / hosts that were identified as M1-type MHC class 
II hi , Ly6C lo , CD206 lo , F4/80 hi displayed high levels of both 
TNF and iNOS transcript compared with macrophages sorted 
from RAG2 / x c / that were identified as M2-type MHC 
class II lo , Ly6C lo , CD206 hi , F4/80 hi and displayed higher tran-
script levels of arginase, eCAD, and Gas3. </p>

<p>Polarization of M1 macrophages in vivo by administration 
of a CD40 agonist induces editing in RAG2 / x c / mice 
CD40 agonist administration in vivo has been shown to have 
antitumor properties (Buhtoiarov et al., 2005; Rakhmilevich 
et al., 2008) by activating TAMs to become tumoristatic 
through production of nitric oxide (Lum et al., 2006). We 
hypothesized that CD40 agonist treatment would activate 
macrophages in tumors growing in RAG2 / x c / mice, 
thereby leading to editing of cancer cells in vivo. To test this, 
a regressor cell line was transplanted into RAG2 / x c / 
mice receiving a single injection of either control IgG or anti-
CD40 agonist monoclonal antibodies, tumor masses were 
harvested, and cell lines were generated and transplanted into 
WT mice. We found that cell lines from CD40 agonist-treated 
RAG2 / x c / mice formed tumor masses in 100% of WT 
recipients, whereas cell lines from isotype-treated RAG2 / x 
c / mice formed tumors in 33% of WT recipients in 
RAG2 / x c / mice (Fig. 9 A; P = 0.0009). We then ana-
lyzed the quantity of M1 macrophages in harvested tumor 
cell suspensions and found that M1 macrophage percentages </p>

<p>Figure 7. NK cells and IFN- are necessary for innate editing of a 
regressor tumor and M1 macrophage accumulation. Regressor cell 
line 2 was transplanted into RAG2 / mice treated with anti-NK1.1, 
IFN--blocking antibody, or control antibody, after which tumor growth 
was measured and passaged cell lines were generated. (A and B) The 
passaged cell lines were then transplanted into syngeneic WT hosts 
(number of cell lines and mice are indicated) and tumor-free survival was 
measured. Tumor-free mice were defined to have a nonenlarging mass 
&lt;9 mm in average diameter by day 40. Tumor sections from RAG2 / hosts 
were stained for MHC class II (C) and quantitated (D). *, P &lt; 0.05. Error 
bars are represented by ± SEM. Results were reproduced at least once. </p>

<p>ruling out the possibility that the differences observed in TAM 
subsets were caused by differential recruitment of immune 
cells in mice lacking either IFN- or c function. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 10 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>of host immune-deficiency directly correlates with the level 
of cancer immunoediting. In doing so, we document that the 
innate immune system present in RAG2 / mice can medi-
ate to some extent the immunosurveillance and immuno-
editing of MCA-induced sarcomas. This editing activity is 
associated with M1 macrophages, IFN-, c, and NK cells. 
Consistent with our previous studies (Shankaran et al., 
2001; Koebel et al., 2007; see Fig. 4 for these data plotted in 
the context of our new data), we found that tumors arising in 
RAG-deficient mice are unedited and as a group, more im-
munogenic. Our evidence is based on studies of over 150 cell 
lines generated during a decade of experimentation performed 
in two separate sites, across two strains of mice, and using both 
RAG1-and RAG2-deficient models. A striking finding from 
our studies is that the regressor frequency of MCA-induced </p>

<p>were doubled in mice treated with CD40 agonist (36%) com-
pared with control treatment (18%; Fig. 9 B, top; P = 0.0003). 
Correspondingly, M2 macrophages were decreased (23 vs. 
15%) by anti-CD40 agonist treatment (Fig. 9 B, bottom; P = 
0.0151). These results suggest that TAMs can be activated in 
RAG2 / x c / mice to effectively edit tumors in vivo. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
The cancer immunoediting hypothesis predicts that tumors 
arising in immune-deficient individuals will be more immuno-
genic than tumors that develop in immune-competent indi-
viduals. Although this concept is achieving wide acceptance, 
the relationship between the degree of host immune deficiency 
and the extent of cancer immunoediting have not yet been 
examined. In this study, we provide evidence that the extent </p>

<p>Figure 8. NK cells and IFN- are required to polarize TAMs toward an M1-type phenotype. Regressor cell line 2 was transplanted into synge-
neic RAG2 / mice (injected with isotype control, anti-NK1.1, or anti-IFN- monoclonal antibodies) or RAG2 / x c / mice. Tumor masses were har-
vested 15 d after transplantation, disaggregated into single-cell suspensions, and analyzed by IHC (A) or FACS (B) to measure the percentage of M1 and 
M2 macrophages as defined by MHC class II and CD206 expression of CD68 + events (for IHC) or MHC class II and Ly6C expression of CD11b + populations 
(for FACS), respectively. (C and D) An example of the flow cytometry gating to quantitate M1 and M2 macrophages. M1 macrophages are 7AAD  , CD45 + , 
Ly 6C lo , MHC class II hi , F4/80 + , CD206 lo cells. M2 macrophages are 7AAD  , CD45 + , Ly6C lo , MHC classII lo , F4/80 + , CD206 hi cells. (E) Cultured supernatant from 
single-cell suspensions were assessed for production of the indicated cytokines after 24 h of culture. (F) TAMs were sorted from harvested tumors at day 
15, and genes associated with classically activated M1 type genes, such as iNOS and TNF, or alternatively activated M2 type genes, such as Arginase, 
eCAD, and Gas3, were measured by quantitative PCR. *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01; ***, P &lt; 0.001. Error bars are represented by ± SEM. Each symbol represents 
a different mouse. Results were reproduced at least once. </p>



<p>Tumor editing by macrophages and NK cells | O'Sullivan et al. </p>

<p>in this process. M1 macrophages are activated classi-
cally via IFN- and function in the removal of intra-
cellular pathogens (Gordon and Taylor, 2005). In the 
context of cancer, M1 macrophages can promote tumor 
elimination via activation of Th1 pathways and secretion 
of tumoricidal levels of nitric oxide (Sica et al., 2008). 
In our studies, we have defined CD45 + CD11b + MHC 
class II hi CD206 lo Ly6C lo cells as M1 macrophages based 
not only on their phenotype but also on their classical 
requirement for IFN- for their generation. Using 
this definition, we found a striking correlation between 
the presence of M1 macrophages and productive im-
mune responses to regressor tumors. The administra-
tion of reagents that increased M1 percentages, such 
as CD40 agonist, enhanced editing, whereas treatments 
that decreased M1 percentages, such as NK cell depletion and 
anti-IFN- mAb blocked editing. 
Our findings support an anti-tumor function for macro-
phages that is consistent with studies performed almost 40 yr 
ago, when it was shown that activated macrophages from 
infected mice (Hibbs et al., 1971) could kill syngeneic trans-
formed murine embryonic fibroblasts, but not primary non-
transformed murine embryonic fibroblasts (Hibbs et al., 1972) 
in vitro. This tumoricidal activity of macrophages required 
cell-cell contact and was induced largely by the cytokine IFN- 
(Pace et al., 1983; Schreiber et al., 1983) in combination with 
additional signals such as LPS (Weinberg et al., 1978) or mur-
amyl dipeptide (Kleinerman et al., 1983). Although we have 
not shown that regressor tumor cells are killed by TAMs, we 
have observed that regressor tumor cells can be killed effectively 
by IFN--stimulated bone marrow macrophages in vitro (un-
published data). Our attempts to demonstrate the tumoricidal 
activity of regressor-associated macrophages was limited by 
the poor viability of sorted TAMs. Furthermore, the require-
ment of macrophages in immunoediting could not be tested, 
as treatment with clodronate-encapsulated liposomes failed to 
deplete macrophages in tumors, even though depletion of 
CD11b + macrophages was achieved in the spleens of tumor </p>

<p>sarcoma cell lines derived from RAG-deficient mice repro-
ducibly approximates 40%. Moreover, the regressor frequency 
of MCA-induced sarcomas generated in mice lacking RAG 
and c is 60-70% in two independent experiments. These 
results suggest a quantitative nature to the immunoediting 
process, whereby a certain degree of basal immune function 
is associated with quantifiable levels of tumor sculpting, which 
can be measured by the regressor frequency. Because a ma-
jority of MCA cell lines generated from RAG2 / x c / 
mice are regressors, we speculate that the primary tumor cell 
repertoire consists of mostly immunogenic tumor cells that 
are immunologically heterogeneous (O'Sullivan et al., 2011). 
This heterogeneity can be partially sculpted by innate immu-
nity in RAG2 / mice or fully sculpted by the complete im-
mune system in WT mice. It should be noted that we have 
never been able to isolate regressors from MCA-induced sar-
comas that develop in WT mice (regressor frequency of 0% 
of 50 cell lines). These results confirm that cancer immuno-
editing of MCA-induced sarcomas is quite robust in WT mice 
and further validate that immune escape is an essential hall-
mark of cancer cells (Hanahan and Weinberg, 2011). 
We have provided evidence that the innate immune system 
can edit tumors and point to M1 macrophages as participants </p>

<p>Figure 9. In vivo administration of CD40 agonist in 
RAG2 / x c / mice induces effective immunoediting 
and intratumoral M1 macrophages. Regressor cell line 2 was 
transplanted into RAG2 / x c / mice receiving a single dose 
of either control rat IgG or anti-CD40 agonistic monoclonal 
antibodies on day 5. Tumor growth was measured over time. 
(A) Tumor masses were converted into passaged daughter cell 
lines which were transplanted into syngeneic WT mice and 
assessed for tumor formation (number of cell lines and mice 
are indicated in the figure). Tumor-free mice were defined to 
have a nonenlarging mass &lt;9 mm in average diameter by 
day 40. (B) At day 15 after transplantation, tumor masses 
were disaggregated into single-cell suspensions, and the per-
centage of M1 (top) and M2 (bottom) macrophages of CD11b + 
events for each condition were quantified. *, P &lt; 0.05; 
***, P &lt; 0.001. Error bars are represented by ± SEM. Each symbol 
represents a different mouse. Results were reproduced at 
least once. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 10 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>polarization and subsequent editing in RAG2 / mice. Al-
though we cannot rule out the contribution of myeloid pop-
ulations in IFN- production, sorted M1 and M2 TAMs do 
not show any IFN- transcript (unpublished data), suggesting 
that NK cells are the predominant producers of IFN- in the 
RAG2 / host. It is not known what induces IFN- pro-
duction by NK cells in our system, but our preliminary stud-
ies indicate that MCA-induced sarcoma cells are incapable of 
directly eliciting IFN- production from NK cells in vitro. 
Interestingly, IL-12p40 was shown to be required for MCA 
sarcoma surveillance (Smyth et al., 2000), so it is possible that 
local IL-12 production could stimulate NK cells to produce 
IFN- to mediate editing in the absence of adaptive immu-
nity. It should be noted that in RAG2 / x c / mice lack-
ing NK cells, editing could be restored with CD40 agonist 
treatment, suggesting that direct interaction between NK cells 
and tumor cells is not needed for tumor editing as long as M1 
macrophages are present. 
Our model is based on the postulate that immunogenic 
regressors, in the presence of M1 macrophages, are converted 
into nonimmunogenic progressors, but we have not identified 
the molecular basis of this phenotypic conversion. Recent 
studies have also found that certain tumor cells can evade mac-
rophage killing/phagocytosis by expressing high levels of CD47 
(Jaiswal et al., 2009; Majeti et al., 2009) and/or low levels of 
calreticulin (Chao et al., 2010). Other studies have implicated 
calreticulin exposure as a key initiator of innate immune re-
sponses to tumor cells, leading to antigen presentation and pro-
ductive adaptive antitumor responses, and the blockade of these 
pathways could be a mechanism of tumor escape (Zitvogel et al., 
2010). We did not find differences in the interaction between 
bone marrow-derived macrophages and regressor versus 
progressor tumor cells in vitro (unpublished data). Further-
more, our preliminary studies indicate that CD47 and calretic-
ulin are not different between regressor and progressor cells 
in vitro. Future studies will compare the gene expression 
profiles of regressor and progressor cells to identify path-
ways that may mediate innate cell recognition/editing. Our 
matched regressor/passaged regressor cells will be critical for 
these experiments. 
In summary, we document the generation and initial 
characterization of a novel set of unedited MCA-induced sar-
coma cell lines that may be highly stimulatory for the innate 
immune system. The enhanced accumulation of M1 macro-
phages in these highly immunogenic tumors suggests that 
they can serve as models to study the early events that lead to 
the generation of M1 macrophages in regressing tumors. We 
also show that the innate immune system in RAG / mice 
contains sufficient cellular machinery to perform sculpting 
of MCA-induced sarcomas. This cellular machinery includes 
NK cells that produce IFN- to activate macrophages to func-
tion as innate editors. This cascade can lead to tumor elimina-
tion in the presence of adaptive immunity and/or editing in 
the absence of adaptive immunity. Finally, we introduce a 
quantitative dimension to the sculpting phase of cancer im-
munoediting by showing that the percentage of regressor cell </p>

<p>bearing mice (unpublished data). Nevertheless, we favor the 
interpretation that M1 macrophages are the most likely editor 
in mice that lack adaptive cells, given their abundance in the 
tumor, their enhanced presence in response to IFN- and 
NK cell activity, and their known tumoricidal activity. 
Recent studies indicate that macrophage tumoricidal ac-
tivity could be enhanced in vitro and in vivo upon adminis-
tration of CD40 agonistic antibodies (Buhtoiarov et al., 2005; 
Rakhmilevich et al., 2008; Beatty et al., 2011). Notably, Beatty 
et al. (2011) investigated the role of tumoricidal macrophages 
activated in vivo with CD40 agonist treatments in the rejection 
of pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDA). After demon-
strating the efficacy of the anti-CD40 agonist mAb CP-870,893 
in human patients, the authors used a mouse model of PDA 
to investigate the mechanism of tumor rejection with CD40 
agonist treatment. To their surprise, the results indicated that 
CD40-stimulated macrophages, independent of T cell activity, 
are sufficient to mediate PDA rejection in vivo. Similarly, we 
have found that CD40 agonist treatment of RAG2 / x c / 
mice can induce tumor editing in the absence of adaptive 
immunity and NK cells, thereby suggesting that macrophages 
are sufficient for tumor editing. In contrast to the Beatty study, 
we did not see tumor rejection, suggesting that MCA sarcomas 
require adaptive cells for their regression. Our studies also show 
that unmanipulated macrophages are capable of editing through 
IFN- and NK cells without the use of CD40 agonists. 
We found that the accumulation of M1 macrophages in 
regressor tumors required IFN- and NK cells. The partici-
pation of NK cells in immunosurveillance against certain types 
of tumors has been clearly documented in studies showing 
increased tumor incidences in mice lacking NK cells or mole-
cules associated with NK cell recognition or effector function 
(Smyth et al., 2002, 2006; Raulet and Guerra, 2009), such as 
NKp46 (Gazit et al., 2006), natural killer group 2D (NKG2D; 
Guerra et al., 2008), DNAX accessory molecule-1 (Gilfillan 
et al., 2008; Iguchi-Manaka et al., 2008), perforin (van den 
Broek et al., 1996; Street et al., 2001), IFN- (Street et al., 
2001), or TNF-related apoptosis-inducing ligand (Cretney 
et al., 2002). Therefore, we considered the possibility that 
there might be increased NK cell killing of MCA-induced 
sarcoma cells from RAG2 / x c / versus RAG2 / or 
WT mice. However, we did not find major differences in the 
susceptibility of unedited versus edited tumors to NK cell kill-
ing. These results are consistent with recent studies showing 
that NKG2D, an activating receptor on NK cells that mediates 
tumor recognition and killing, did not play a role in the sur-
veillance of MCA-induced sarcomas (Guerra et al., 2008). In 
this study, NKG2D-deficient mice had similar incidences of 
MCA-induced sarcomas but were more susceptible to tumor 
formation in prostate cancer and B lymphoma model systems, 
suggesting that the role of NK cells in destroying tumor cells 
could be dependent on the site of tumor formation. For MCA-
induced sarcomas, we advocate that one role of NK cells in 
eliminating and/or sculpting tumors in the absence of adaptive 
immunity may be as a source of IFN-. This is based on find-
ings that NK cells and IFN- are necessary for M1 macrophage </p>



<p>Tumor editing by macrophages and NK cells | O'Sullivan et al. </p>

<p>Tumor transplantation. Subconfluent tumor cell lines were harvested 
by trypsinization, washed 3 times with PBS, and injected at 10 6 cells sub-
cutaneously into recipient C57BL/6, (129/Sv x C57BL/6) F1, RAG2 / , or 
RAG2 / x c / strain mice as previously described (Shankaran et al., 
2001; Smyth et al., 2005; Bui et al., 2006). RAG2 / mice were injected i.p. 
with 200 µg of either control hamster IgG (PIP), anti-NK1.1 (PK136), or 
anti-IFN- (H22) on days 2 and 0 and every 4 d after until tumor harvest. 
RAG2 / x c / mice were injected i.p. with 200 µg either control rat IgG 
or anti-CD40 agonist (FGK 45.5) on day 5. Mice were monitored for tumor 
growth by measurement of mean tumor diameter, defined as the mean of the 
two maximum dimensions of the tumor mass. </p>

<p>Antibodies and FACS analysis. On various days after transplantation, 
tumors were excised from mice, minced, and treated with 1 mg/ml type IA 
collagenase (Sigma-Aldrich) as previously described (Weinberg et al., 1978). 
Cells were vigorously resuspended, washed in FACS buffer (PBS + 1% 
FCS+0.05%NaN 3 ; Sigma-Aldrich) and filtered before staining. Antibodies 
to CD45, F4/80, NK1.1, CD69, CD80, CD206, Ly6C, CD11b, I-A/I-E, 1A8, 
and streptavidin PE were obtained from BD. Staining was conducted for 
15-20 min at 4° in FACS tubes containing 1-2 million total cells, 0.5-1 µl 
of antibody, 1 µl of anti-CD16/32, and 100 µl of FACS buffer. 7AAD (EMD 
Millipore) or propidium iodide (Sigma-Aldrich) was added at 1 µg/ml im-
mediately before FACS analysis. M1-type and M2-type macrophages were 
gated as previously described (Movahedi et al., 2010; see Fig. 8). F4/80 
and CD68 were used to detect macrophages in FACS assays or in IHC 
assays. F4/80 marks all monocyte lineage cells, and CD68 marks mature 
tissue macrophages that are in tumors (Van Ginderachter et al., 2006; Wang 
et al., 2012). </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry. Fresh tumor nodules were harvested, OCT-
embedded, and snap frozen in cooled isopentane. Tissue blocks were cut on 
a cryostat into 6-µm-thick sections, mounted onto poly-l-lysine slides, air-
dried overnight, and post-fixed for 10 min in acetone before staining. Puri-
fied rat anti-mouse CD16/CD32 was used to block for 20 min (BD; dilution 
1:50) when appropriate. Biotin-conjugated rat anti-mouse I-A/I-E (eBio-
science; dilution 1:100; 1 h at room temperature) and biotin-conjugated rat 
anti-mouse CD206 (BioLegend; dilution 1:100, 1 h at room temperature) 
staining was revealed using streptavidin-horseradish peroxidase (Vector Lab-
oratories; 30 min at room temperature) followed by amino-ethyl-carbazole 
as chromogen (BD; 10-15 min at room temperature). Purified rat anti-mouse 
CD68 (BioLegend; dilution 1:100) staining was detected using a biotin-
conjugated rabbit polyclonal anti-rat IgG, mouse adsorbed (Vector; dilution 
1:200). Immunostained tissue sections were examined with a Leica DM 
2500 or Nikon Eclipse E800 microscope; images were captured with a Leica 
DFC 420 or Nikon DXM 1200 digital camera, respectively. Quantitative 
analysis of MHC-II + , CD68 + , CD206 + cells was obtained by counting at 
least 10 high power fields of tissue sections at 200× magnification. </p>

<p>Cell sorting. TAMs were sorted from tumor cell suspensions on a BD 
FACSAria. We defined M1 macrophages as 7AAD  , CD45 + , Ly 6C lo , MHC 
class II hi , F4/80 + , CD206 lo cells, and M2 macrophages as 7AAD  , CD45 + , 
Ly6C lo , MHC classII lo , F4/80 + , CD206 hi cells. </p>

<p>Quantitative PCR (qPCR). TAM RNA was isolated with a QIAGEN 
RNeasy Mini kit before reverse transcription with Applied Biosystems 
High-Capacity cDNA Reverse Transcription kit. qPCR reactions were 
performed on the CFX96 Touch Real-Time PCR Detection System (Bio-Rad 
Laboratories). Primers for the detection of other transcripts used are as 
follows: m18s forward, 5-CGCGGTTCTATTTTGTTGGT-3, m18s reverse, 
5-AACCTCCGACTTTCGTTCTTG-3; mTNF forward, 5-CATCTT-
CTCAAAATTCGAGTGACAA-3, TNF reverse, 5-TGGGAGTAGAC-
AAGGTACAACCC-3; miNOS forward, 5-CCCTTCAATGGTTGG-
TACATGG-3, miNOS reverse, 5-ACATTGATCTCCGTGACAGCC-3; 
mArginase forward, 5-GAACACGGCAGTGGCTTTAAC-3, mArginase 
reverse, 5-TGCTTAGCTCTGTCTGCTTTGC-3; mE-cadherin forward, </p>

<p>lines generated from MCA-induced sarcomas is reproducible 
and correlates with the level of immune pressure in the tumor-
bearing host. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Experimental procedures. All experiments involving mice were con-
ducted under animal protocols approved by the Washington University 
Animal Studies Committee and the University of California, San Diego 
Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC protocol #S06201) 
and were in accordance with ethical guidelines determined by the Peter Mac 
Animal Experimental Ethics Committee. </p>

<p>Mice and MCA induction. Tumor induction by MCA was performed as 
previously described (Smyth et al., 2000; Shankaran et al., 2001). In brief, cohorts 
of C57BL/6-strain WT (Taconic), RAG2 / , RAG1 / , and RAG2 / x 
c / mice were injected with MCA dissolved in peanut oil at various doses. 
Experiment 1 was performed in St. Louis and used RAG2 / x c / mice 
generated by breeding IL-2Rc / mice (C57/BL6 N10+1F7-strain; The 
Jackson Laboratory) to C57BL/6 RAG2 / mice (Taconic). Genotyping 
was performed using PCR (for IL-2R c , following The Jackson Laborato-
ries protocol [http://jaxmice.jax.org/strain/003174.html]) or by Southern 
blot for RAG2 (Shinkai et al., 1992). Genomic microsatellite analysis showed 
that the RAG2 / x c / mice contained C57BL/6 markers at 97% of the 
loci tested (3% 129/Sv markers). To control for interinstitutional breeding, 
minor strain differences, and housing variability, the RAG2 / mice used in 
MCA experiment 1 were outcrossed from (RAG2 / x c / ) x RAG2 / 
breeding performed in-house. Tumors in mice were measured as previously 
described (Shankaran et al., 2001; Koebel et al., 2007). In experiment 1, a 
dose of MCA was used such that all MCA-treated mice developed tumors. 
Experiment 2 was performed at the Peter Mac facility in Australia and used 
RAG2 / x c / mice, which were provided by the Walter and Eliza Hall 
Institute (Bundoora), and C57BL/6 and RAG1 / mice as previously described 
(Smyth et al., 2000). To rule out that RAG2 / x c / tumor cell lines were 
rejected based on minor strain differences, we also transplanted RAG2 / x 
c / regressor cell lines into F1 (C57BL/6 × 129) mice (n = 30; Taconic) 
and obtained identical growth patterns as in C57BL/6 mice (National Cancer 
Institute, Frederick Rockville, MD). For some tumor transplantation experi-
ments, RAG2 / x c / recipient mice were purchased from Taconic. No 
differences in tumor growth were observed in RAG2 / x c / recipient 
mice purchased from Taconic Farms or bred in-house. 
We discovered in the process of routine genotyping of our mice for 
the current study that the RAG2 / 129/Sv mice previously obtained 
from Taconic Farms (RAGN12 model) and used in our 2001 publication 
(Shankaran et al., 2001) contained the C57BL/6 NK-C locus. Microsatellite 
analysis confirmed that these mice were virtually congenic at the NK-C locus 
and contained 22 cM of C57BL/6 sequence encompassing the following 
genes/markers: D6MIT261, D6MIT105, D6MIT018, D6MIT111, Nkrp1a, 
Nkrp1c, CD69, Nkg2d, Nkg2a, and Ly49a (Yokoyama and Plougastel, 2003). 
These mice were therefore designated 129/SvEv.cNK-C.B6 RAG2 / mice. 
Because the NK-C gene locus displays allelic polymorphism and can con-
tribute to part of the difference in NK cell activity between the C57BL/6 and 
129/Sv strain (Yokoyama and Plougastel, 2003), new sets of MCA-induced 
sarcomas were generated using RAG2 / mice that had been bred by Taconic 
Farms to be on a pure 129/SvEv background (129S6/SvEvTac-Rag2 tm1Fwa ). 
This new set of MCA-induced sarcomas was published in Koebel et al., 2007 
and further studied in Fig. 3. </p>

<p>Cell lines. MCA-induced and passaged daughter sarcomas were isolated and 
passaged in vitro as previously described (Shankaran et al., 2001; Smyth et al., 
2005). In brief, tumor chunks were made into single-cell suspensions by mincing 
and collagenase treatment in HBSS (1 mg/ml type IA; Sigma-Aldrich), and 
multiple vials were frozen at passage 2. For transplantation and cytotoxicity assays, 
passage 2 cell lines were thawed, expanded, and studied at passage 4-8. Cell lines 
were maintained in RPMI 1640 (Cambrex) supplemented with 10% FCS 
(HyClone) as previously described (Shankaran et al., 2001; Bui et al., 2006). </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 10 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>





<p>Cytokine secretion assay. On day 15 after transplantation, tumors were 
excised from mice, minced, and treated with 1 mg/ml type IA collagenase 
(Sigma-Aldrich) as previously described (Weinberg et al., 1978). Filtered 
tumor/immune cell suspensions were plated in triplicate wells at 40,000 cells/ 
well in 100 µl for 24 h at 37°C. Supernatant was analyzed for cytokines using 
the mouse inflammation cytometric bead array kit from BD. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis. Statistical significance between two groups was deter-
mined by the Welch's t test using two-tailed analysis to obtain p-values. The 
Log-Rank test was used to compare the survival of mice across tumor trans-
plantation or induction conditions. Error bars are depicted using the <rs type="software">SEM</rs>. 
All experiments were done at least twice. </p>

<p>We thank all members of the Schreiber, Smyth, and Bui Laboratories. We would like 
to thank Janelle Sharkey for excellent technical assistance and Jessica Archambault, 
Tiffany Irwin, and Michelle Stirling for animal maintenance. 
J.D. Bui is supported by grants from the Cancer Research Institute, National 
Institutes of Health (NIH; CA128893, CA157885), the American Cancer Society 
(ACS-IRG #70-002), the Cancer Research Coordinating Committee (6-444951-34384), 
the Concern Foundation, and The Hartwell Foundation. R.D. Schreiber is supported by 
NIH grants CA43059 and CA107527, a grant from the Ludwig Institute for Cancer 
Research, and the Rhea Rosemary Finnell Clinical Investigation Grant from the Cancer 
Research Institute. R. Uppaluri is supported by K08 CA090403. M.J. Smyth is 
supported by an Australia Fellowship and a Program Grant from the National Health 
and Medical Research Council of Australia and a project grant from the Association of 
International Cancer Research. M.W.L. Teng is supported by a Cancer Council of 
Victoria project grant and a National Health and Medical Research Council Peter 
Doherty Postdoctoral Fellowship. S.F. Ngiow is supported by a Cancer Research 
Institute Pre-doctoral scholarship. The work cited in this publication was performed in 
a facility supported by National Center for Research Resources grant C06 RR012466. 
The authors do not report any competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Submitted: 6 July 2011 
Accepted: 1 September 2012 </p>





<p>Tumor editing by macrophages and NK cells | O'Sullivan et al. </p>



</text></tei>