<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3832812" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A b s t r a c t </p>

<p>I In nt tr ro od du uc ct ti io on n: : Pulmonary fibrosis occurs due to fibroblast proliferation and col-
lagen production in the lung and begins with alveolar inflammatory edema. 
Aquaporins (AQPs) play pivotal roles in lung fluid transport. In this study we 
establish the experimental model for pulmonary fibrosis in C57BL/6 mice to 
investigate expressions of AQP1 and AQP5 in lung tissue. 
M Ma at te er ri ia al l a an nd d m 
me et th ho od ds s: : Mice in model groups were treated intratracheally with 
bleomycin with the dose of 5 mg/kg body weight. The mice were sacrificed at 
1 week, 2 weeks and 3 weeks respectively. The left upper lungs were harvested 
for histopathologic H-E and Masson's staining. The mRNAs of AQP1 and AQP5 
were analyzed by real-time polymerase chain reaction (real-time PCR) and the 
proteins of AQP1 and AQP5 were analyzed by western blotting. 
R Re es su ul lt ts s: : Real-time PCR showed that AQP1 mRNA in bleomycin 1 w, 2 w, and 3 w 
groups increased by 377%, 880% and 823% respectively compared to that in 
the control group (p &lt; 0.01). Western blotting showed that the expression of 
AQP1 protein in bleomycin 1 w, 2 w, and 3 w groups increased by 53%, 144%, and 
141%, respectively (p &lt; 0.05). AQP5 mRNA in bleomycin 1 w and 2 w group decreased 
by 78% and 66%, respectively (p &lt; 0.05). In bleomycin 2 w and 3 w groups it 
decreased by 69% and 80% (p &lt; 0.05). 
C Co on nc cl lu us si io on ns s: : The expression of AQP1 dramatically increased in pulmonary fibro-
sis. AQP1 plays an important role in the progress of pulmonary fibrosis. </p>

<p>K Ke ey y w wo or rd ds s: : aquaporin 1, aquaporin 5, pulmonary fibrosis, bleomycin. </p>

<p>Aquaporin (AQP) is a cell-membrane protein that exists widely in plants, 
animals, and bacteria. In 1984, the AQP system was separated from bovine 
lens proteins, as the membrane-integral protein 26 [1]. Until now 13 kinds 
of AQP (AQP0 to AQP12) have been described, collectively referred to as 
AQPs [2]. The water that is necessary for cell metabolism is transported 
by AQPs, which have a highly selective ability to aid water to cross bio-
logical membranes [3]. In recent years, more and more attention has been 
paid to the protein expression profile of the aquaporin (AQP) family mem-</p>

<p>C Co or rr re es sp po on nd di in ng g a au ut th ho or r: : 
Prof. Hu Jinhong 
Department of Pharmacy 
Changhai Hospital 
Second Military 
Medical University 
No. 168, Changhai Road 
200433 Shanghai, PR China 
Phone: 86-21-81873747 
Fax: +86 21-81873747 
E-mail: hujinhong2008@sina.com </p>

<p>Experimental research </p>

<p>1 Department of Pulmonary Medicine, Minhang District Central Hospital, Ruijin Hospital 
Group, Shanghai, PR China 
2 Department of Pulmonary Medicine, Zhongshan Hospital, Fudan University, Shanghai, 
PR China 
3 Department of Pharmacy, Changhai Hospital, Second Military Medical University, 
Shanghai, PR China </p>

<p>S Su ub bm mi it tt te ed d: : 7 August 2011 
A Ac cc ce ep pt te ed d: : 13 February 2012 </p>

<p>Arch Med Sci 2013; 9, 5: 916-921 
DOI: 10.5114/aoms.2012.31011 
Copyright © 2013 Termedia &amp; Banach </p>

<p>Arch Med Sci 5, October / 2013 </p>



<p>bers in acute lung injury and lung cancer [4, 5]. To 
different extents, it has been reported that AQP1 
and AQP5 were correlated with lung injury [6], and 
decreased expression of AQP5 in bleomycin-induced 
lung fibrosis was found [7]. But AQP1 in pulmonary 
fibrosis has not been investigated. AQP1 is expres-
sed in the apical and basolateral membrane of the 
microvascular endothelium, as well as in the vis-
ceral pleura [8]. 
Pulmonary fibrosis is a parenchymal lung disease 
characterized by progressive interstitial fibrosis [9]. 
Predicting risk factors remain unknown though lung 
fibroblasts maybe in terms of proinflammatory 
mediators and pro-fibrotic pathways. The persis-
tence of alveolitis causes progressive disruption and 
destruction of the alveolar architecture, which can 
result in end-stage fibrosis [10]. A well-characteri-
zed animal model of human lung fibrosis is induced 
by bleomycin. Administration of bleomycin in ani-
mals results in an acute pan-alveolitis with pul-
monary edema in the first week, followed by a 2 to 
3 week subacute phase characterized by prolifera-
tion of fibroblasts and synthesis of extracellular 
matrix proteins [11, 12]. It is necessary for the res-
olution of acute lung injury to remove the pul-
monary edema fluid from the alveolar space. This 
will probably prevent its late fibrotic consequences. 
The importance of the resolution of alveolitis has 
recently been shown by the fact that the removal of 
alveolar edema fluid early is associated with a better 
clinical outcome, specifically with a lower mortality 
rate in lung injury [13, 14]. We can find new thera-
peutic targets for pulmonary fibrosis resulting from 
lung injury by evaluating changes in the expression 
of aquaporins involved in the clearance of pul-
monary edema. 
Pulmonary inflammation and edema in mice are 
associated with a marked reduction in the expres-
sion levels of AQP1 and AQP5 in the distal lung, sug-
gesting that the AQP1 and AQP5 in abnormal fluid 
fluxes have a role during pulmonary inflammation 
[15]. In the present study, we assessed the expression 
of AQP1 and AQP5 in lung tissue with pulmonary 
fibrosis induced by bleomycin. It showed that AQP1 
dramatic up-regulation was positively related to the 
severity of pulmonary fibrosis. Furthermore, AQP5 
down-regulation is presented at some time. A better 
understanding of the expression of AQP1 in pulmo-
nary fibrosis could be critical in finding new treat-
ments for this life-threatening disease. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>A An ni im ma al ls s </p>

<p>Male eight-week-old C57BL/6 mice purchased 
from Fudan University Animal Breeding and Re-
search Center (Shanghai, China) were housed and 
cared for using protocols approved by Research Ani-</p>

<p>mal Care of Shanghai Changhai Hospital. Mice were 
treated intratracheally with bleomycin (Nippon 
Kayaku Kabushiki Kaisha, Japan) with a dose of 
5 mg/kg body weight on day 0. The mice were sac-
rificed at 1 week, 2 weeks and 3 weeks. The left 
upper lungs were harvested for histopathological 
H-E and Masson's staining. Forty-eight mice were 
divided into 4 groups: a bleomycin 1 w group, 
a bleomycin 2 w group, a bleomycin 3 w group and 
a control group treated with the same volume of nor-
mal saline. </p>

<p>H 
Hi is st to op pa at th ho ol lo og gi ic ca al l e 
ev va al lu ua at ti io on n </p>

<p>The left upper lung tissues dehydrated in graded 
ethanol were embedded in paraffin, for sectioning 
into 4 µm and staining with hematoxylin and eosin 
(H&amp;E). The slides were reviewed by 3 pathologists. 
The overall severity of fibrosis was determined by 
the pattern and intensity of interstitial inflamma-
tion according to the Szapiel 1979 working classifi-
cation scale [16]. </p>

<p>R 
RT T--P PC CR R o of f A AQ QP P1 1 a an nd d A 
AQ QP P5 5 </p>

<p>The samples homogenized with the appropriate 
volume of TRIzol (Invitrogen, USA) solution were 
placed in centrifuge tubes for mRNA extraction and 
RT-PCR. The AQP1 upstream primer sequence was 
5'CTGGCCTTTGGTTTGAGCAT3' and the downstream 
primer sequence was 5'CCACACACTGGGCGATGAT3', 
a total of 150 base pairs (bp). The AQP5 upstream 
primer sequence was 5'GCGCTCAGCAACACAAC3' 
and the downstream primer sequence was 5' GTGT-
GACCGACAAGCCAATG3', a total of 150 bp. The 
β-actin upstream primer sequence was 5'ACGGCCA-</p>

<p>GGTCATCACTATTG3' and the downstream primer 
sequence was 5'TGGATGCCACAGGATTCCAT3'. The 
150 bp PCR products from each sample including 
AQP1, AQP5 and β-actin were analyzed on 1% aga-
rose gels (Promega, USA). The final results visuali-
zed on an ultraviolet light box were photographed 
on Kodak film. The density of each band was com-
pared with a 150-bp band that expressed β-actin. 
The intensity ratio of the difference was later used 
to compare the results after fibrosis. </p>

<p>I 
Im mm mu un no oh hi is st to oc ch he em mi ic ca al l a an na al ly ys si is s o of f A AQ QP P1 1 
a 
an nd d A 
AQ QP P5 5 </p>

<p>Anti-AQP1 specificity antibody (AB3065) and anti-
AQP5 specificity antibody (AB3069) were purchased 
from Chemicon International Group (Canada). The 
sections were washed with phosphate buffered 
saline (PBS) (pH 7.4) thrice for 3 min each time. The 
sections were fixed with 3% H 2 O 2 for 15 min at 
room temperature, and washed with PBS thrice, 
each time for 5 min. After PBS washing 3 more 
times, we added anti-AQP1 or anti-AQP5 antibody 
at 4°C for 12 h, and washed with PBS thrice further. </p>

<p>Expression of pulmonary aquaporin 1 is dramatically upregulated in mice with pulmonary fibrosis induced by bleomycin </p>

<p>Then the second antibody was added and the sec-
tion maintained at 37°C for 12 h, washed with PBS 
3 more times and counterstained. The sections 
were then examined under a microscope. The epi-
thelial cell membranes IN Collection system which 
has a brown staining WAS positive cells. Image 
analysis of the gray value of positive cells (IOD val-
ues) yielded the relative expression of AQP1 and 
AQP5 proteins. </p>

<p>S St ta at ti is st ti ic ca al l a an na al ly ys si is s </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was performed using <rs type="software">SPSS</rs> 
11.0 for Windows and Student's t-test and ANOVA 
for repeated measures considering values of p &lt; 0.05 
to be significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>H Hi is st to op pa at th ho ol lo og gi ic ca al l e 
ex xp pr re es ss si io on n </p>

<p>After 1 week, the mice were treated with bleo-
mycin, we observed the fact that some mice died. 
There was one in the 1 w group, two in the 2 w group 
and four in the 3 w group. The bleomycin groups 
showed pulmonary fibrosis at days 7, 14 and 21 and 
displayed higher scores compared with normal con-
trols (p &lt; 0.05). The PF score increased gradually week 
by week. The PF score was higher in the 3 w group 
compared with the 1 w group (p &lt; 0.05, Table I). </p>

<p>A AQ QP P1 1 a 
an nd d A AQ QP P5 5 m 
mR RN NA A E 
Ex xp pr re es ss si io on n </p>

<p>To evaluate serial changes in AQP1 and AQP5 asso-
ciated with pulmonary fibrosis, RT-PCR was used to 
analyze mRNA expression at days 7, 14 and 21 after 
the mice were treated with bleomycin. Real-time PCR 
showed that AQP1 mRNA expression in bleomycin 1 w, 
2 w, and 3 w groups increased by 3.77, 8.8 and 8.23 
times respectively compared to that in the control 
group (p &lt; 0.05) (Figure 1). AQP5 mRNA expression in 
the bleomycin 1 w and 2 w group decreased by 78% 
and 66% respectively (p &lt; 0.05), while there was no 
significant difference between the bleomycin 3 w group 
and the control group (p &gt; 0.05) (Figure 2). </p>

<p>A AQ QP P1 1 a 
an nd d A AQ QP P5 5 p 
pr ro ot te ei in n e ex xp pr re es ss si io on n </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry results showed that AQP1 
was expressed on microvascular endothelial cells. 
Staining of AQP1 showed increased immunoreac-
tivity in bleomycin groups compared to that in the 
control group, especially in the severe fibrotic areas 
(Figure 3), while AQP5 was expressed on type I pneu-
mocytes in the alveolus. Staining of AQP5 showed 
decreased immunoreactivity in bleomycin groups 
compared to that in the control group (Figure 4). 
Western blotting showed that AQP1 protein 
expression in bleomycin groups was significantly 
upregulated at days 7, 14 and 21 compared with the 
normal control group (p &lt; 0.05). Expression of AQP1 
protein in bleomycin 1 w, 2 w, and 3 w groups in-
creased by 53%, 144%, and 141% respectively of the 
control group value. There were no differences in 
AQP1 protein expression among the bleomycin 
groups (Table II, Figure 5). AQP5 protein expression in 
the bleomycin 1 w group decreased by 13% compared 
to that in the control group (p &gt; 0.05) and in the 
bleomycin 2 w and 3 w groups it decreased by 69% 
and 80% respectively (p &lt; 0.05) (Table III, Figure 6). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The pathogenesis of pulmonary fibrosis is not 
clear but it appears to be the consequence of acute, 
persistent, or recurrent lung injury and inflamma-
tion [17]. Following this inflammatory response, 
increased vascular permeability and pulmonary </p>

<p>918 
Arch Med Sci 5, October / 2013 </p>

<p>G Gr ro ou up p 
n n 
S Sc co or re es s </p>

<p>Control 
12 
1.00 ±0.00 </p>

<p>Bleomycin 1 w 
11 
1.60 ±0.89* </p>

<p>Bleomycin 2 w 
10 
2.00 ±0.71* </p>

<p>Bleomycin 3 w 
8 
3.60 ±0.55* # </p>

<p>T Ta ab bl le e I I. . Semi-quantitative scores of pulmonary fibro-
sis (x -± s) </p>

<p>*p &lt; 0.05 vs. control group, #p &lt; 0.05 vs. bleomycin 1 w group </p>

<p>C Co on nt tr ro ol l 
B Bl le eo om my yc ci in n 1 1 w w B Bl le eo om my yc ci in n 2 2 w w B Bl le eo om my yc ci in n 3 3 w w </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 1 1. . Determine AQP1 mRNA expression by real 
time PCR in mice with pulmonary fibrosis induced 
by bleomycin </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A AQ QP P5 5 </p>

<p>C Co on nt tr ro ol l 
B Bl le eo om my yc ci in n 1 1 w w B Bl le eo om my yc ci in n 2 2 w 
w B Bl le eo om my yc ci in n 3 3 w w </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 2 2. . Determine AQP5 mRNA expression by real 
time PCR in mice with pulmonary fibrosis induced 
by bleomycin </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>A AQ QP P1 1 </p>

<p>Xiwen Gao, Guifang Wang, Wei Zhang, Qing Peng, Min Xue, Hu Jinhong </p>

<p>Arch Med Sci 5, October / 2013 </p>



<p>edema ensue [18]. The pathway for the flow of 
water across the endothelial and epithelial lung bar-
rier is not completely elucidated, but recently AQPs 
have been described as playing a critical role in 
water removal from the lung extracellular space </p>

<p>[19]. Decreased expression of AQP1 and AQP5 has 
also been described in pathological conditions of 
the lung, such as acute lung injury [8]. However, 
alteration of AQP1 and AQP5 expression in chronic 
inflammatory processes such as that observed in </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 3 3. . AQP1 protein expression is showed in immunohistochemistry. A A -Control group, B B -bleomycin 3 w group </p>

<p>A A 
B B </p>

<p>A A 
B B </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 4 4. . AQP5 protein expression is showed in immunohistochemistry. A A -Control group, B B -bleomycin 3 w group </p>

<p>Expression of pulmonary aquaporin 1 is dramatically upregulated in mice with pulmonary fibrosis induced by bleomycin </p>



<p>Arch Med Sci 5, October / 2013 </p>

<p>lung fibrosis has not as yet been reported. In the 
present study, we evaluated the protein and RNA 
expression of AQP1 and AQP5 in a mouse model of 
bleomycin-induced lung fibrosis. Both the protein 
and mRNA expression of AQP1 were significantly 
increased in the fibrotic tissue of our animal mod-
els, suggesting that insufficient AQP1-mediated 
transportation of extracellular liquid may also take 
place in lung fibrosis. However, at the present time 
we cannot be sure that the increase of AQP1 expres-
sion is secondary to the fibrosis. Either way, it is 
clear that AQP1 may be a useful marker for pul-
monary injury owing to fibrosis in the mouse. 
In our fibrosis model, the expression of AQP1 was 
increased in microvascular endothelial cells. The me-
chanism of this AQP1 increase is unclear. Previous 
studies have shown that the majority of osmotically 
driven water transport in lung microvascular endo-
thelial cells occurs by a transcellular route through 
AQP1 water channels. AQP1 facilitates hydrostati-
cally driven lung edema, but is not required for 
active near-isomolar absorption of alveolar fluid [20]. 
In contrast to a previous study [15], AQP1 expression 
was increased in the lungs of rats at 7, 14 and 21 days 
after bleomycin treatment. This suggests that AQPs 
may be differentially expressed according to tissue 
injury type and that epithelial cells' response to 
injury differ. Further studies are needed to evaluate 
the mechanism involved in the regulation of fluid 
movement and inflammation. Towne et al. [15] sug-
gested that decreases in both AQP1 and AQP5 may 
contribute to edema by reducing the transcellular 
rate of excess water removal, thereby effectively 
trapping water in the alveolar and interstitial 
spaces. Although AQP5 expression was decreased 
at some time in our study, AQP1 expression was </p>

<p>increased dramatically. AQP1 may be more impor-
tant in edema development following bleomycin 
inhalation, and the inability of pulmonary vascular 
endothelial cells to clear the air space may be an 
important factor in the inflammatory process of 
pulmonary fibrosis. Increased expression of AQP-1 
has been reported in the frontal cortex of patients 
with Creutzfeldt-Jacob disease [21] and on the pleu-
ra of rats with a tuberculous pleural effusion [22]. 
The different types of injury and the different time 
points of the same injury might cause different 
alterations in AQP-1. 
It was found by Gabazza et al. [7] that the expres-
sion of AQP5 protein was significantly decreased in 
pulmonary edema resulting from bleomycin treat-
ment. But in our study the decrease was less at 
21 days, indicating that the return of AQP5 expres-
sion to baseline levels was coincident with a lesse-
ning of the inflammatory response. Previous stud-
ies [23] have shown that treatment of murine lung 
epithelial cells with tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α) 
results in a dependent decrease of concentration and 
time in AQP5 mRNA and protein expression, sug-
gesting that TNF-α may play an important role in 
AQP5 down-regulation in the inflamed lung. Inter-
estingly, the loss of AQP5 in epithelial cells was not 
only observed in the fibrotic lung of mice that had 
received intratracheal instillation of bleomycin but 
also in those receiving continuous infusion of bleo-
mycin through a subcutaneous mini-pump, sugges-
ting that both acute and chronic lung injuries induce 
reduction in AQP5 expression. In our study AQP5 
mRNA expression started to return but protein 
expression decreased further. It showed that pul-
monary fibrosis impaired the cellular membrane 
not damaged to genetic transcription. 
The biological significance of abnormal extra-
cellular accumulation of fluid in the lung from 
patients with lung fibrosis is unclear. Pulmonary 
edema may play an active role in the development 
of lung fibrosis. Impairment of clearance of edema 
in patients with acute lung injury and interstitial </p>

<p>G Gr ro ou up p 
n n 
G Gr ra ay y s sc ca al le e r ra at ti io o </p>

<p>Control 
8 
0.34 ±0.05 </p>

<p>Bleomycin 1 w 
8 
0.52 ±0.14* </p>

<p>Bleomycin 2 w 
6 
0.83 ±0.17* </p>

<p>Bleomycin 3 w 
6 
0.82 ±0.11* </p>

<p>T Ta ab bl le e I II I. . AQP1 protein expression determined by 
Western blotting (x -± s) </p>

<p>*p &lt; 0.05 vs. control group. Gray scale ratio -AQP1 protein/GAPHD </p>

<p>G Gr ro ou up p 
n n 
G Gr ra ay y s sc ca al le e r ra at ti io o </p>

<p>Control 
8 
3.32 ±0.80 </p>

<p>Bleomycin 1 w 
8 
2.88 ±0.72 </p>

<p>Bleomycin 2 w 
6 
1.04 ±0.25* </p>

<p>Bleomycin 3 w 
6 
0.65 ±0.21* </p>

<p>T Ta ab bl le e I II II I. . AQP5 protein expression determined by 
Western blotting (x -± s) </p>

<p>*p &lt; 0.05 vs. control group. Gray scale ratio -AQP5 protein/GAPHD </p>

<p>C Co on nt tr ro ol l 
1 1 k k 
2 2 k k 
3 3 k k </p>

<p>GAPDH 37 kDa </p>

<p>AQP1 21 kDa </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 5 5. . Determine AQP1 protein expression by 
Western-blotting </p>

<p>C Co on nt tr ro ol l 1 1 k k 
2 2 k k 
3 3 k k </p>

<p>GAPDH 37 kDa </p>

<p>AQP5 21 kDa </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 6 6. . Determine AQP5 protein expression by 
Western-blotting </p>

<p>Xiwen Gao, Guifang Wang, Wei Zhang, Qing Peng, Min Xue, Hu Jinhong </p>

<p>Arch Med Sci 5, October / 2013 </p>



<p>lung disease is associated with poor clinical out-
come [24]. Some previous studies have shown the 
development of lung fibrosis with the presence of 
chronic pulmonary edema after lung injury [25, 26]. 
In our model of lung fibrosis, we found a dramatic 
increase in the expression of AQP1. The chronic lung 
injury induced by bleomycin was probably the result 
of injected bleomycin entering into the systemic 
circulation at slow pace. 
In conclusion, the results of the present study 
show that chronic lung injury and lung fibrosis is 
associated with up-regulated expression of AQP1 in 
the lung. Further studies will be necessary to clarify 
the cause-effect relationship between AQP1 up-reg-
ulation and the development of pulmonary fibrosis. </p>

<p>R e f e r e n c e s </p>



<p>Expression of pulmonary aquaporin 1 is dramatically upregulated in mice with pulmonary fibrosis induced by bleomycin </p>

</text></tei>