<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3200513" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Estrogens play important roles in a wide range of physiolog-
ical and pathophysiological processes, including carcinogenesis 
in estrogen targeted organs. Accordingly, estrogen receptors 
(ER), as mediator of estrogenic effect, are linked to diverse car-
cinomas as diagnostic marker and prognostic factor. In this 
regard, the clinical application of ERα in breast cancers is a suc-
cessful paradigm. Use of tamoxifen (TAM), an endocrine ther-
apeutic agent targeting ERα, has reduced recurrence and im-
proved survival in patients with different stages of breast can-
cer [1]. Thus, TAM has been widely accepted as a fundamen-
tal adjuvant therapy for breast cancers, and ERα is routinely 
detected in the clinical setting. </p>

<p>However, the expression of ERα does not completely parallel 
the response to hormonal therapy. Roughly a quarter of ERα 
positive breast cancers are insensitive to TAM and a substantial 
proportion of sensitive patients would develop resistance [1]. 
The identification of G-protein coupled estrogen receptor 1 
(GPER), also referred to as GPR30 belonging to the family of 
G protein-coupled receptors, provides a potential mechanism 
for these phenomena, for the following reasons: First, the agents 
applied in hormone therapy of breast cancers, including TAM 
and fulvestrant, have been repeatedly described as GPER ago-
nists [2,3]. GPER and its cross-talk with epidermal growth fac-
tor receptor (EGFR) play a key role in acquired resistance in 
breast cancer cells (MCF-7) after long-term treatment with 
TAM [4]. Second, GPER may mediate the cytological prolifer-
ation effect of estrogenic substances [5]. Third, GPER promotes 
cellular migration and mobilization in response to estrogen 
[5,6]. Last, GPER may contribute to the chemoresistance of 
cytotoxic agents [7]. Furthermore, GPER is associated with 
poor survival of endometrial carcinoma and ovarian cancers 
[8,9]. We hypothesize that GPER plays important roles in breast 
cancer progression or mammary carcinogenesis. To evaluate 
GPER in primary breast cancers, we assessed its expression by 
immunohistochemistry, and correlated GPER expression with 
clinicopathological variables in 423 cases of breast cancers. </p>

<p>G-protein Coupled Estrogen Receptor 1 Expression in Primary Breast Cancers 
and Its Correlation with Clinicopathological Variables </p>

<p>Hao-jun Luo*, Ping Luo*, Guang-lun Yang, Qiong-le Peng 1 , Man-ran Liu 1 , Gang Tu </p>

<p>Department of Endocrine and Breast Surgery, The First Affiliated Hospital, Chongqing Medical University, Chongqing; 1 Department of Laboratory Medical 
Diagnosis, The Ministry of Education Key Laboratory of Laboratory Medical Diagnosis, Chongqing Medical University, Chongqing, China </p>

<p>O R I GINAL ARTICLE </p>

<p>J Breast Cancer 2011 September; 14(3): 185-190 
http://dx.doi.org/10.4048/jbc.2011.14.3.185 </p>

<p>Purpose: G-protein coupled estrogen receptor 1 (GPER) proba-
bly play important roles in the progression of breast cancer includ-
ing endocrine therapeutic resistance. We evaluated GPER in pri-
mary breast cancers. Methods: Immunohistochemistry was used 
to detect GPER in paraffin-embedded tissues of primary breast 
cancers from 423 patients and GPER expression was correlated 
with clinicopathological factors. Results: GPER was expressed in 
63.8% of specimens, coexpressed with estrogen receptor alpha 
(ERα) in 36.6% of tumors and was positive in 62.5% of the ERα-
negative tumors. The expression of GPER had no relationship 
with the status of ERα, progesterone receptor and HER2. Although </p>

<p>the expression of GPER was significantly inversely related with 
nodal status (p= 0.045), no correlation between GPER expression 
and other clinicopathological variables (age, menstruation status, 
tumor size, stage, histologic grade, Nottingham Prognostic Index 
or pathological type) was found. Conclusion: GPER and ERα ex-
hibited independent expression pattern of distribution in primary 
breast cancers. A long-term follow-up and a more definite molec-
ular phenotype for ER are necessary in confirming studies. </p>

<p>Key Words: Breast neoplasms, G-protein coupled estrogen receptor 1, 
Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Correspondence: Gang Tu 
Department of Endocrine and Breast Surgery, The First Affiliated Hospital, 
Chongqing Medical University, No.1 Friendship Road, Yuanjiagang, Yuzhong 
District, Chongqing 400016, China 
Tel: +86-2389011191, Fax: +86-2389011192 
E-mail: luoasa2010@gmail.com </p>

<p>This work supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China 
(30872520), the State Ministry of Education (208113), Natural Science 
Foundation of Chongqing (CSTC2008BB5220), and Education Commission 
of Chongqing (KJ080327). </p>

<p>*Hao-jun Luo and Ping Luo contributed to this paper equally. </p>

<p>Received: November 17, 2010 Accepted: June 20, 2011 </p>

<p>J ournal of 
Breast 
Cancer </p>

<p>186 </p>

<p>
Hao-junLuo,etal. </p>

<p>http://ejbc.kr 
http://dx.doi.org/10.4048/jbc.2011.14.3.185 </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Tissue samples and clinicopathological data 
A total of 423 archival paraffin-embedded, formalin-fixed 
breast tumor tissues were obtained from the Clinical Diagnos-
tic Pathology Center, Chongqing Medical University (Chong-
qing, China). All patients underwent surgery at the First Affil-
iated Hospital of Chonqing Medical University during 2006-
2009. For all patients, detailed clinicopathological data includ-
ing pathological diagnoses, results of immunohistochemical 
studies for ERα, progesterone receptor (PR) and HER2, lymph 
node status, tumor grade, and tumor size were obtained from 
hospital records. As routine tests, rabbit monoclonal antibodies 
of ERα (Clone SP1), PR (Clone SP2), and HER2 (Clone SP3) 
(Maxim.Bio, FuZhou, China) were used in the immunohisto-
chemistry assay. A minimum of 1% positively stained in nucleus 
of tumor cells in a specimen was considered positive for ERα 
and PR, whereas if less than 1% of tumor cells stained, the sam-
ple was considered negative. Nottingham Combined Histolog-
ical Grading system was employed to evaluate the tumor grade. 
Nuclear grade, tubule formation and mitotic rate were given a 
score between 1 and 3 and the scores of were added together 
for a total score. Scores of 3-5, 6-7, and 8-9 were defined as the 
low (G1), intermediate (G2) and high (G3) grade, respectively. 
As a well accepted predictor, the Nottingham Prognostic Index 
(NPI= 0.2× S+N+G; S is the size of the index lesion, N is the 
number of involved lymph nodes and G is tumor grade) was 
calculated for all patients. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemical staining 
Commercial rabbit anti-GPER polyclonal antibodies (Ab-
cam, Cambridge, UK) were applied for GPER immunohisto-
chemical staining, utilizing streptavidin-peroxidase assay ac-
cording to the manufacturer's instructions. Briefly, 4 μm thick 
tissues sections were deparaffinized, heated at 95°C in 0.1 mol/ 
L sodium citrate (pH 6.0) for antigen retrieval, and the endo-
genous peroxidase activity was quenched with 3% H2O2. Non-
specific binding sites were blocked by incubating with goat se-
rum. Slides were exposed to primary antibodies at a 1:250 di-
lution, or to phosphate buffered saline (PBS) as a negative con-
trol for 2 hours at 3°C. Sections were incubated in horseradish 
peroxidase-conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG for 20 minutes at 
37°C to detect tissue-associated rabbit antibodies. Diamino-
benezidine was added as the substrate. Nuclei were counter-
stained using Mayer's modified hematoxylin. As indicated by 
Filardo et al. [10], reduction mammoplasty tissue was used as 
a positive control. </p>

<p>Evaluation of the antigen immunohistochemical staining 
pattern 
Two observers microscopically evaluated the intensity, extent 
and distribution of the immunreactive area using a modified 
semiquantitative scoring system [11]. Scores were applied as 
follows: A staining proportion score: 0, negative staining in all 
cells; 1, &lt; 1% cells stained; 2, 1-10% cells stained; 3, 11-33% cells 
stained; 4, 34-66% cells stained; 5, 67-100% cells stained; Stain-
ing intensity score: 1, weak stained; 2, moderately stained; 3, 
strongly stained. Adding the two scores together yielded a max-
imum score of 8. The final scores were grouped into GPER nega-
tive (score 0-4) and positive (score 5-8) categories for statisti-
cal analyses to reduce inter-observer differences. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
The <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 16.0</rs> for Windows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, USA) 
was utilized for the statistical analysis. Associations between 
GPER expression and each clinicopathological determinants 
were evaluated by the χ 2 test, the Fisher's exact test (for nom-
inal variables) or the Kruskal-Wallis test (for ordinary vari-
ables). Referring to measurement data, non-paired t-test or 
ANOVA process was used to test difference between sub-
groups. Two-tailed p-values of 0.05 or less were considered to 
be statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Clinicopathological characteristics 
Of the 423 patients included in this study, 54.3% were post-
menopausal, their mean age was 51.6± 11.5 years (range, 24-
94 years). The majority of the cases were invasive ductal carcin-
omas (90.5%) (Table 1). Distant metastasis was excluded at 
the time of surgery. We applied the greatest dimension from 
the ultrasonography or mammography reports to represent the 
primary tumor size, and the mean tumor size was 26.0± 13.6 
mm (range, 6-89 mm). Lymph node status was graded consider-
ing the number of metastatic reginal lymph nodes, and 40.9% 
of the cases had a positive in pathological node examination. 
The disease staging was applied according to the 7th edition of 
the American Joint Committee on Cancer Staging Manual for 
Breast Cancer, 41.4% of cancers were in stage II. Most tumors 
were graded as G2 (67.4%). Approximately a quarter (23.4%) 
of all patients accepted neoadjuvant chemotherapy. The char-
acteristics of patients and tumors are summarized in Table 1. </p>

<p>GPER staining pattern in breast cancer tissues 
The predominant staining pattern of GPER was cytoplasmic 
in carcinoma tissues regardless of the histopathological type 
(Figure 1). No nuclear or membranous staining was observed. </p>

<p>GPERinPrimaryBreastCancer </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4048/jbc.2011.14.3.185 
http://ejbc.kr </p>

<p>This pattern was consistent with the reports of Filardo et al. [10] 
and Revankar et al. [12]. </p>

<p>Frequency of GPER expression and its association with the 
parameters 
GPER was positive in 63.8% of all specimens, which was 
similar to previous studies [10,13-15], revealing the extensive 
expression of GPER in primary breast carcinomas. ERα was 
positive in 56.5% of tumors. GPER and ERα were coexpressed 
in 36.6% of tumours and concomitantly absent in 16.3% spec-
imens, which was also similar with earlier findings [10].The 
association between GPER and ERα was not significant (p= 
0.617), whereas 62.5% of the ERα-specimens were positive for 
GPER (Table 2), implying the absence of interdependence be-
tween the two ERs, consistent with earlier observations [10,13-</p>

<p>Table 1. Characteristics of the breast cancer specimens </p>

<p>Characteristics 
No. (%) </p>

<p>Age (yr)* 
51.6± 11.5 
Menstruation status 
Premenopause 
197 (46.4) 
Postmenopause 
226 (53.4) 
Neoadjuvant chemotherapy 
Yes 
99 (23.4) 
No 
324 (76.6) 
Histopathologic type 
DCIS 
7 (1.7) 
Invasive ductal carcinoma 
383 (90.5) 
Invasive lobular carcinoma 
7 (1.7) 
Adenoid cystic carcinoma 
9 (2.1) 
Mucinous carcinoma 
10 (2.4) 
Other  † 
7 (1.7) 
Histology grade (n= 409) 
G1 
90 (22) 
G2 
277 (67.7) 
G3 
42 (10.3) 
T (mm)* 
26.0± 13.6 
pN (n= 414) 
0 (LN= 0) 
250 (60.4) 
1 (LN= 1-3) 
72 (17.4) 
2 (LN= 4-9) 
58 (14) 
3 (LN≥ 10) 
34 (8.2) 
Staging 
0 
7 (1.7) 
I 
108 (25.5) 
IIA 
134 (31.7) 
IIB 
42 (9.9) 
IIIA 
54 (12.8) 
IIIB 
6 (1.4) 
IIIC 
35 (8.3) 
X 
37 (8.7) </p>

<p>DCIS= ductal carcinoma in situ; T= greatest dimension of tumor; LN= number 
of lymph node metastasis. 
*Mean± SD;  † Medullary carcinoma (n= 4), papillary carcinoma (n= 2), and se-
cretory carcinoma (n= 1). </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Figure 1. Immunohistochemical staining (DAB) of G-protein coupled estrogen receptor 1 (GPER) in breast cancers. (A) Positive cytoplastic staining 
pattern. (B) Negative staining paradigm (immunohistochemical stain, × 200). </p>

<p>Table 2. Distribution of GPER according to ER, PR, HER2 </p>

<p>Total 
GPER (+) </p>

<p>ER expression 
+ 
239 
155 
-
184 
115 
ER/PR pattern 
ER+/PR+ 
156 
100 
ER+/PR-
83 
55 
ER-/PR+ 
24 
16 
ER-/PR-
160 
99 
PR expression 
+ 
180 
116 
-
243 
154 
HER2 status 
-
219 
140 
+ 
106 
65 
++ 
64 
43 
+++ 
34 
22 </p>

<p>GPER= G-protein coupled estrogen receptor 1; ER= estrogen receptor; PR= 
progesterone receptor. </p>

<p>188 </p>

<p>
Hao-junLuo,etal. </p>

<p>http://ejbc.kr 
http://dx.doi.org/10.4048/jbc.2011.14.3.185 </p>

<p>15]. GPER had no relationship with PR and HER2. In contrast, 
ERα was positive and inversely associated with PR and HER2 
(data not shown), further supporting the notion that GPER is 
independent of ERα. </p>

<p>GPER+ tumors tended to be larger than GPER-tumors (great-
est dimension, 26.5 ± 14.6 mm vs. 25.1 ± 11.4 mm, however, 
the difference was not significant (p= 0.314). The expression 
of GPER was inversely related to nodal status. GPER+ tumors 
displayed a significantly lower mean rank of pathological lymph 
node grade (199.7 vs. 211.2, p= 0.045) in Kruskal-Wallis test. 
No significant difference was found when NPI was compared 
between GPER+ and GPER-tumors. Moreover, no correlation 
was found between GPER expression and the other variables 
analyzed (Table 3). 
"Cross-talk" between GPER and ERα has been suggested. 
We correlated GPER/ERα status to the well known prognostic 
factors, but no significant differences were found among the 
four subgroups, excluding that GPER-/ERα-tumors had higher 
HER2 scores than those of other subgroups (p= 0.046) (Table 4). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>GPER, which has been widely-accepted as an ER, has been 
linked to proliferation, migration enhancement [5], mobiliza-
tion promotion [6], TAM [4], cytotoxic agents [7], resistance 
in breast cancer cells in vitro. However, only four clinical stud-
ies [10,13-15], which included large sample populations have 
focused on GPER in primary breast cancers. We detected GPER 
by immunohistochemistry in 241 primary breast cancers to 
correlate its expression to clinicopathological determinants, 
resulting in some significant associations [14]. To further eval-
uate GPER in breast cancers, we expanded the sample size, col-
lected more details of the tumors in the present paper. 
In our series, GPER was positive in 63.8% of specimens, re-
gardless of ERα and/or PR status, as well as the histopathol-
ogical tumor subtype. This proportion is in the range of previ-
ous studies, indicating wide distribution for this receptor in 
breast cancers [10,15]. As aforementioned, there is not com-
plete concordance between the ERα-targeted therapeutic re-
sponse and its expression [1]. Furthermore, resistance would 
occur in approximately half of the patients who have taken TAM </p>

<p>Table 3. Association between GPER and clinicopathological variables </p>

<p>GPER (+) 
GPER (-) 
p-value </p>

<p>Age (yr)* 
51.8± 11.7 
51.2± 11.1 
NS 
Menstruation status 
NS 
Premenopause 
128 
69 
Postmenopause 
142 
84 
T (mm)* (n= 389) 
26.5± 14.6 
25.1± 11.4 
NS 
pN (n= 414) 
0.045 
0 
168 
82 
1 
43 
29 
2 
34 
24 
3 
18 
16 
Staging 
NS 
0 
4 
3 
I 
71 
37 
II 
116 
59 
III 
55 
41 
X 
25 
12 
Histologic grade (n= 409) 
NS 
G1 
60 
30 
G2 
106 
G3 
32 
10 
NPI* (n= 353) 
3.97± 1.23 
4.05± 1.20 
NS 
Histopathologic type 
DCIS 
3 
4 
Invasive ductal carcinoma 
137 
Ivasive lobular carcinoma 
5 
2 
Adenoid cystic carcinoma 
6 
3 
Mucinous carcinoma 
6 
4 
Others 
4 
3 
Neuajduvant chemotherapy 
NS 
Yes 
62 
37 
No 
208 
116 </p>

<p>GPER= G-protein coupled estrogen receptor 1; NS= not significant; T= greatest 
dimension of tumor; NPI= Nottingham Prognostic Index; DCIS= ductal carci-
noma in situ. 
*Mean± SD. </p>

<p>Table 4. Correlation among GPR30/ER status and prognostic factors </p>

<p>GPER30 (+) 
GPER30 (-) 
p-value 
ERα (+) 
ERα (-) 
ERα (+) 
ERα (-) </p>

<p>No. of cases 
155 
84 
115 
69 
T* (mm) (n= 413) 
25.6± 13.4 
24.6± 11.4 
27.8± 16.1 
25.7± 11.4 
NS 
pN  † (n= 414) 
197.88 
211.87 
202.09 
232.5 
NS 
Stage  † (n= 386) 
182.01 
189.16 
200.77 
211.85 
NS 
Grade  † (n= 409) 
189.66 
194.46 
197.91 
200.58 
NS 
NPI* (n= 353) 
3.95± 1.23 
4.03± 1.10 
4.08± 1.18 
4.31± 1.15 
NS 
HER2  † (n= 423) 
205.01 
219.63 
189.32 
236.8 
0.001 </p>

<p>ER= estrogen receptor; T= greatest dimension of tumor; NS= not significant; NPI= Nottingham Prognostic Index. 
*Mean± SD from analysis of variance;  † Mean rank of cases from Kruskal Wallis test. </p>

<p>GPERinPrimaryBreastCancer </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4048/jbc.2011.14.3.185 
http://ejbc.kr </p>

<p>treatment [1], but the mechanism is not clear. GPER, as an 
alternative estrogen receptor, may provide a potential inter-
pretation. The interaction between ERs and EGFR has focused 
much attention on acquired TAM-resistance, whereas GPER 
can transactivate EGFR in response to TAM, hydroxytamoxi-
fen and fulvestrant [3]. Furthermore, enhanced sensitivity to 
estradiol (E2) and specific agonist of GPER, G1 (1-[4-(6-bro-
mobenzo[1,3]dioxol-5-yl)-3a,4,5,9b-tetrahydro-3H-cyclo-
penta[c] quinolin-8-yl]-ethanone), via GPER, has been ob-
served in MCF-7 cells cultured long-term with TAM, result-
ing in resistance to the inhibitory effect of TAM [4]. Thus, 
GPER probably plays an important role in the non-response 
and acquired-resistance to ERα antagonism in patients with 
breast cancer. In our study, GPER was expressed in 64.9% of 
patients with ER+ tumors who would presumably take endo-
crine therapy. For this subpopulation, GPER signalling-block-
age should be supplemented with current endocrine therapy. 
GPER was also respectively detected in 62.5% and 61.9% of 
ER-, and ER-/PR-cancers, respectively, which would not be 
included in hormonal therapy. Accordingly, GPER-targeted 
drugs is possible as an alternative hormonal therapy and would 
benefit more patients, since a selective GPER antagonist has 
been identified [16,17]. 
Filardo et al. [10] was the first to detect GPER in clinical speci-
mens of breast cancer. GPER expression was positively associ-
ated with tumor size, HER2 immunohistochemical scores and 
distant metastasis in their report, suggesting that GPER may 
be involved in breast cancer progression. In the present series, 
GPER had no significant influence on the tumor size, consis-
tent with Kuo et al. [13] and our previous report [14] in Chi-
nese but Filardo's [10] observations in Americans. Thus, racial 
differences may contribute to the discrepancy. Notably, one 
third (106/321) of the patients in Filardo's series [10] devel-
oped metastases, whereas distant metastatic cases were absent 
in the later reports. This probably underlies the difference. In-
terestingly, we observed a significant protective effect of GPER 
on pathological lymph node invasion because GPER+ tumors 
displayed significant lower mean rank of pathological lymph-
onode grade (Table 3). None of the early reports showed a sig-
nificant association between expression of GPER and lymph 
node invasion [10,13]. There is no more information on this 
point so far. Thus, a confirmative investigation is needed. For 
post-operative breast cancers, NPI is the best-documented prog-
nostic index combining tumor size, nodal status and histol-
ogical grade. ERα had a significant (p= 0.048), negative impact 
on tumor NPI. In contrast, GPER manifested no influence on 
NPI in our series which was consistent with recent reports 
showing that GPER has no impact on long-term outcomes of 
patients with breast cancer [13,15]. The correlation between </p>

<p>GPER and HER2 expression is controversial. In contrast to 
observation by Filardo et al. [10], no significant association 
between GPER and HER2 expression was found in Kuo's [13], 
Arias-Pulido's [15], and our investigation (Table 2). Although 
GPER functionally transactivate EGFR in response to E2, it is 
worth noting that HER2 is not EGFR and a functional relation-
ship between HER2 and GPER is not implied. GPER showed 
no relationship with additional prognostic factors either. Thus, 
GPER may not be an independent prognostic factor. Never-
theless, long-term follow-up outcomes were absent in the pres-
ent report, limiting our preliminary conclusion. 
Coexpression of ERα and GPER has been linked to a better 
outcome, whereas a lack of any of them is associated with worse 
survival in patients with invasive ductal carcinomas [13], and 
inflammatory breast cancer [15], while GPER has no significant, 
independent impact on the outcomes of breast cancer patients 
[13,15]. We correlated the status of both ERs to prognostic fac-
tors. Interestingly, GPER-/ER-tumors tended to have a maximum 
NPI, rank of pathological node grade, stage, and histological 
grade (Table 4), although the differences were not significant 
excluding HER2 scores across subgroups (p= 0.046). This is a 
reminder that GPER is merely a collaborator in estrogenic effects 
[18].The interaction between GPER and ERα has been suggest-
ed [18], and the function of GPER may vary with ERs expres-
sion type in breast cancer cells [19], although the mechanisms 
are far from clear. Thus, a more definite classification of ERs 
molecular phenotype is necessary. Confirming studies and long-
term follow-up in different subgroups of tumors is significant. 
In contrast to studies in vitro, clinical studies have observed 
a few evident relationship between GPER and tumor progres-
sion or survival in patients with breast cancer. Contrary effects 
exist between the two signalling pathways triggered by GPER 
[20], thus, the estrogenic effects may be neutralized. Never-
theless, GPER was expressed in most specimens regardless of 
the status of ER, PR, and HER2. GPER and ERα exhibited an 
independent pattern of distribution in primary breast cancers. 
Thus, more definite classification of ERs molecular phenotype 
is necessary. In addition, confirming studies and a long-term 
follow-up are needed to further evaluate GPER in the progres-
sion of breast cancers and patients' survival. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </p>

<p>All authors declare no conflicts of interest. </p>





<p>
Hao-junLuo,etal. </p>



</text></tei>