<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3632766" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>During smile evaluation and anterior esthetic construction, the anatomic and racial variations should be considered in order to achieve 
better matching results. The aims of this study were to validate an objective method for recording spontaneous smile process and to 
categorize the smile and upper lip curvature of Chinese Han-nationality youth. One hundred and eighty-eight Chinese Han-nationality 
youths (88 males and 100 females) ranged from 20 to 35 years of age were selected. Spontaneous smiles were elicited by watching 
comical movies and the dynamics of the spontaneous smile were captured continuously with a digital video camera. All subjects' smiles 
were categorized into three types: commissure, cuspid and gummy smile based on video editing software and final images. Subjects' 
upper lip curvatures were also measured and divided into three groups: upward, straight and downward. Reliability analysis was 
conducted to obtain intra-rater reliabilities on twice measurements. The Pearson Chi-square test was used to compare differences for 
each parameters (a50.05). In smile classification, 60.6% commissure smile, 33.5% cuspid smile and 5.9% gummy smile were 
obtained. In upper lip measurement, 26.1% upward, 39.9% straight and 34.0% downward upper lip curvature were determined. The 
commissure smile group showed statistically significant higher percentage of straight (46.5%) and upward (40.4%) in upper lip 
curvatures (P,0.05), while cuspid smile group (65.1%) and gummy smile group (72.7%) showed statistically significant higher 
frequency in downward upper lip curvature (P,0.05). It is evident that differences in upper lip curvature and smile classification exist 
based on race, when comparing Chinese subjects with those of Caucasian descent, and gender. 
5-16 </p>

<p>on smile esthetics used static pictures or direct measurements. 
Traditionally, static photographic techniques could only capture still 
smile images at certain time points, which made it difficult to obtain 
the precise and natural moment of smile process, even during a posed 
smile. 
5-6 With the evolution of digital imaging, studies with contem-
porary available digital videography had shown that a spontaneous 
smile of joy can be achieved with a more observational and less 
patient-interfering approach. 
17-21 Although the esthetic smile has 
been well studied and published, these data have been nearly all 
derived from Caucasian samples except for a few data derived from 
Asian countries. 
7,10-11,19,22 Several authors have addressed racial </p>

<p>variations among facial parameters. 
23-24 Richardson 
24 published that 
the components of the face closer to the alveolar and dental areas show 
the greatest differences among ethnic and racial groups. Johnson </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>reported how knowledge of racial 'norms' for facial appearance might 
aid practitioners to determine anterior esthetics. An understanding of 
these norms would lead to better esthetics and treatment plans and 
then be in harmony with the facial appearance for patients of different 
races. Therefore, it would be useful to establish some desirable charac-
teristic features of smiles to help achieve optimum results in esthetic 
oral rehabilitation for Chinese patients. The present study sought to 
establish an objective method for recording dynamic smile process 
and to categorize spontaneous smile and upper lip curvature in 
Chinese Han-nationality youths. The null hypotheses for this study 
were that there were no significant differences in frequencies for smile 
classification and upper lip curvature between Chinese subjects and 
Caucasian descent. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Sampling and selection criteria 
Approval was obtained from the Institutional Review Boards of Peking 
University Medical Ethics Committee (IRB no. 0902-12) for this study 
and the subject selection process. Basically, the subjects obtained were 
students and staff from the Peking University Health Science Center. It </p>

<p>1 Department of Periodontology, Peking University School &amp; Hospital of Stomatology, Beijing, China and </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Restorative Dentistry, University of Washington, Seattle, USA 
Correspondence: Dr WJ Hu, Department of Periodontology, Peking University School &amp; Hospital of Stomatology, Beijing 100081, China 
E-mail: huwenjie2010@yahoo.com.cn 
Received 21 November 2012; accepted 7 March 2013 </p>

<p>International Journal of Oral Science (2013) 5, 49-53 
ß 2013 WCSS. All rights reserved 1674-2818/13 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/ijos </p>

<p>was explained to potential subjects that this was a study on dynamic 
smile and lip shape by watching three short comedic films along with a 
video clip capturing subjects' face continuously for approximate 
3 min. The inclusion criteria were: (i) Chinese Han-nationality youths 
between 20 and 35 years of age; (ii) full maxillary and mandibular 
dentition with erupted second molars; (iii) skeletal and dental class I 
relationships; (iv) no anterior malposition conditions such as severe 
crowding, spacing, tipping, or rotations; (v) no symptoms of facial 
paralysis or lip irregularities; (vi) no anterior caries lesions, restora-
tions or prostheses, active gingival and periodontal disease, gingival 
recessions; and (vii) no history of orthodontic treatment or maxillo-
facial surgery. </p>

<p>Recording and measurement during spontaneous smiling 
Study was conducted in a studio by a professional photographer with 
a digital video camera (HDR-SR12E; Sony Corp., Tokyo, Japan) 
mounted on a tripod at a distance of 150 cm from the subject's upper </p>

<p>lip. The camera lens was adjusted to be parallel to the apparent occlusal 
plane and the camera focused only on the portion between the nose 
and chin. The subject was instructed to sit and hold the head naturally 
after leveling with the Frankfort horizontal plane during the study 
period (Figure 1). In addition, one millimeter scale was placed adja-
cent to the subject's right tragus and used as an external reference. A 
laptop (INSPIRON 1545, Dell, Austin, TX, USA) was placed at the 
subject's eye level behind the camera. In order to prompt spontaneous 
smiling, the subjects were provided three 1-min-long comedic films to 
watch during video recording. Three complete processes of sponta-
neous smile including rest position to full smile were recorded with 
minimal intrusion of the subject while subjects were watching the 
films. 
The video clip was downloaded to a computer and processed with a 
video-editing software (Sony Vegas Pro <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">10.0</rs>; Sony Creative Software 
Inc., Middleton, WI, USA). Each frame was reviewed and analyzed. 
Two frames including the subject's lip at rest position and a maximum 
commissure-to-commissure dynamic smile were captured. These 
frames were converted into a JPEG file and renamed in <rs id="software-2" type="software">Windows 
XP Professional</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Microsoft</rs>, Redmond, WA, USA) with the subjects' 
numbers. Each file was opened in Adobe Photoshop CS3 (Adobe 
Systems Inc., San Jose, CA, USA) and the image size of each file was 
adjusted by using the millimeter ruler as a reference. 
In order to categorize smile patterns of subjects, Rubin classifica-
tion 
1 was adapted and shown in Figure 2. In the commissure smile, the 
corners of the mouth turn upward due to the pull of the zygomaticus 
major. In the cuspid smile, the upper lip is elevated uniformly without 
the corners of the mouth turning upward; the entire lip rises like a 
window shade. In the complex or gummy smile, the upper lip moves 
superiorly, as in the cuspid smile. But the lower lip usually moves 
inferiorly in a smile fashion. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>In addition, curvatures of upper lip during full smile were measured 
and categorized using the following criteria (Figure 3): 
6-7 (i) upward 
lip curvature means that the corner of the mouth is at 1 mm higher 
than a horizontal line drawn through the center of the lower border of 
the upper lip; (ii) straight lip curvature means that the corner of the 
mouth at or within 1 mm above and below a horizontal line drawn </p>

<p>1.5 m </p>

<p>Subject 
Spotlights Video camera Laptop screen </p>

<p>Figure 1 Schematic drawing of the digital videographic method used. </p>

<p>a 
b 
c </p>

<p>Figure 2 Smile classification. (a) Commissure smile. (b) Cuspid smile. (c) Gummy smile. </p>

<p>a 
b 
c </p>

<p>Figure 3 Upper lip curvature. (a) Upward. (b) Straight. (c) Downward. </p>

<p>Dynamic smile and upper lip curvature in Chinese 
LZ Liang et al 
50 </p>

<p>International Journal of Oral Science </p>

<p>through the center of the lower border of the upper lip; (iii)downward 
lip curvature means that the corner of the mouth is at more than 1 mm 
lower than a horizontal line drawn through the center of the lower 
border of the upper lip. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
All hypotheses were tested statistically at a50.05. The kappa statistics 
test was used to exam the reliability of the data recorded by the rater at 
times 1 and 2 with 1 week apart. The Pearson Chi-square test was used 
to analyze the differences between male and female subjects in the 
frequencies of smile classification and curvature of upper lip (a50.05). </p>

<p>RESULTS 
The results of the re-testing in categorizing the dynamic smiles and 
upper lip curvature at different measurements are shown in Tables 1 </p>

<p>and 2. The kappa statistic test obtained a score of 0.85 for smile clas-
sification and a score of 0.86 for upper lip curvature. No statistically 
significant difference was determined in classification of subjects 
between twice measurement by the same rater (P.0.05). 
The frequencies of smile classification and upper lip curvature are 
shown in Tables 3 and 4, respectively. Female subjects obtained sig-
nificantly higher percentage of commissure smile and lower percentage 
of cuspid smile than male subjects (P,0.05) in smile classification. In 
upper lip measurements, female subjects expressed statistically signifi-
cant higher percentage in upward curvature and lower percentage in 
downward curvature during dynamic smile than male subjects in this 
study (P,0.05). 
The distributions of each type of upper lip curvature in different 
smile classifications are shown in Figure 4. Subjects with commissure 
smile displayed predominantly either upward or straight curvature </p>

<p>Table 1 Re-test reliability of smile classification (n5188) </p>

<p>Test 
Commissure smile 
Cuspid smile Gummy smile </p>

<p>Commissure smile 
110 
9 
0 
Cuspid smile 
2 
54 
1 
Gummy smile 
2 
0 
10 </p>

<p>Table 2 Re-test reliability of upper lip curvature (n5188) </p>

<p>Test 
Upward 
Straight 
Downward </p>

<p>Upward 
46 
2 
0 
Straight 
9 
63 
5 
Downward 
0 
2 
61 </p>

<p>Table 3 Frequencies for smile classification in this study </p>

<p>Commissure smile 
Cuspid smile 
Gummy smile </p>

<p>Subjects 
Subject 
Percentage/% 
Subject 
Percentage/% 
Subject 
Percentage/% </p>

<p>All subjects (n5188) 
114 
60.6 
63 
33.5 
11 
5.9 
Males (n588) 
45 
51.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>36 
40.9 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>7 
8 . 0 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Females (n5100) 
69 
69.0 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>27 
27.0 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>4 
4 . 0 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Within a column, percentages having similar lower-case letters (i.e. a, b, c) are statistically significantly different (P,0.05). </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Corner-of-the-mouth smile 
Canine smile 
Full-denture smile </p>

<p>18.20 </p>

<p>Upward </p>

<p>Straight </p>

<p>Downward </p>

<p>72.70 </p>

<p>9.10 </p>

<p>65.10 </p>

<p>31.80 </p>

<p>3.20 </p>

<p>13.20 </p>

<p>46.50 
40.40 
Percentage/% </p>

<p>Figure 4 Distribution of different types of upper lip curvature in spontaneous smiling. </p>

<p>Table 4 Frequencies for upper lip curvature in this study </p>

<p>Upward 
Straight 
Downward </p>

<p>Subjects 
Subject 
Percentage/% 
Subject 
Percentage/% 
Subject 
Percentage/% </p>

<p>All subjects (n5188) 
49 
26.1 
75 
39.9 
64 
34.0 
Males (n588) 
14 
15.9 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>31 
35.2 
43 
48.9 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Females (n5100) 
35 
35.0 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>44 
44.0 
21 
21.0 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Within a column, percentages having similar lower-case letters (i.e. a, b) are statistically significantly different (P,0.05). </p>

<p>Dynamic smile and upper lip curvature in Chinese 
LZ Liang et al 
51 </p>

<p>International Journal of Oral Science </p>

<p>of their upper lip contour. There are statistically significant higher 
percentage of expressing downward curvature of their upper lips in 
both cuspid and gummy type of smiles (P,0.05). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Spontaneous smiling should be the logical focus point for the esthetic 
diagnosis of lip-tooth relationship during smiling. The fast onset and 
fading out of a spontaneous smile makes it impossible to capture in the 
right moment with a static photograph. Therefore, it is proposed to 
switch from static to dynamic video-recording of the smile for diag-
nostic purpose. The results of this study indicated that spontaneous 
smiles were measured reproducibly with the digital videographic 
method which showed a high level of reliability in making judgments 
on the smiles. 
4-5,12,21 The Pearson correlations for the measurements 
obtained from 0.85 for smile classification and 0.86 for upper lip 
curvature respectively, and were highly acceptable. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Comparisons with approximate data of frequencies for smile and 
curvature of upper lip derived from previous studies are shown in 
Tables 5 and 6, respectively. Of all the different kinds of smile, the 
commissure smile was determined to be 60.6%; this agrees with other 
studies measuring smile. 
1,4,8,22 Our finding that 5.9% of the subjects 
had a gummy smile is consistent with previous reports. </p>

<p>1,4,8 </p>

<p>Murakami et al. 
22 reported a higher percentage of gummy smile that 
related to the younger age (1863 years) of the subjects observed. The 
similar results were obtained and reported by Peck et al. 
14 that 26% of 
their samples had a mean age of 15.5 years, demonstrated a high or 
gummy smile. In addition, there was a significant gender difference 
in smile line frequency: low smile lines were predominantly a male 
characteristic (2.5 to 1) and gummy smile was predominantly a female 
characteristic (2 to 1). 
15-16 It was surprising to find significant male-
female difference in frequencies of smile classification and upper lip 
curvatures (Tables 3 and 4). Male displayed significantly more gingival 
tissue was determine and gummy smile was predominantly a male 
characteristic in Chinese youths (Table 3). Therefore, the first hypo-
thesis of no significant differences in frequencies for smile classifica-
tion is partially accepted. 
Regarding the upper lip curvature, the hypothesis of no significant 
differences in frequencies for upper lip curvature is rejected. 
According to the mean smile scores reported by Hulsey, 
8 the group 
of upward lip curvature contained the most subjects, while the group 
of straight lip curvature contained the fewest subject. However, in the </p>

<p>current study, the group of upward lip curvature obtained a lower 
percentage, while the group of straight lip curvature contained the 
most subjects (Table 4). The results were similar to previous studies 
of Korean subjects (Table 6). </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Furthermore, the present study attempted to explore the relationship 
between smile classification and upper lip curvature. Our results 
showed that most of subjects with commissure smile appeared as 
straight (46.5%) or upward (40.4%) upper lip curvatures, while subjects 
with cuspid smile or gummy smiles mostly appeared as downward 
upper lip curvature (65.1% and 72.7%, respectively). It appears that 
good smiles can be found with either a curved-upper lip, a straight 
upper lip, or even a curved-down upper lip. Sawyer et al. 
26 in their 
quantitative analysis of normal smile report indicated that the cuspid 
smile is a subtle smile and usually has a significant overlap with the 
commissure smile. Hulsey 
8 pointed out that smiles with the upper lip 
curving downward were not quite as attractive in his report of esthetic 
evaluation of lip-teeth relationship. Our study firstly indicated that 
there were certain relation between upper lip curvature and Rubin's 
smile classification. Upper lip curvature might be a major factor of 
smile classification based on the anatomical feature of upper lip and 
the relationship of these two parameters still needs further investigation. 
The position and movement of upper lip plays a major role in 
developing smiles. 
1 Particular in the case of gummy smile patients, 
who have the muscular ability to raise the upper lip significantly higher 
than average on smiling. 
13 Chiu and Clark 
27 studied the facial soft 
tissue profile of the southern Chinese and found that a more obtuse 
nasolabial angle, almost 100 6 , occurred among female instead of right-
angled for male. In recent studies about facial movement, men are 
found to have statistically significant wider faces and larger movement 
than women. 
28-30 Tzou et al. 
29 reported the difference of facial move-
ment between Europeans and Asians and found that Europeans had 
generally larger facial movements than Asians. A complete explanation 
for the significant gender differences in frequency of the gummy smile 
remains indeterminable. From a practical point of view, the risk of 
anterior esthetic rehabilitation will increase significantly in a gummy 
case. For example, a natural looking anterior implant restoration, 
including correct shape of the alveolar bone, a harmonious gingival 
line and an interproximal dental papilla to the contact point, is not 
always achievable in clinical practice. In that case, the height of the lip 
line is decisive whether the esthetic shortcomings of esthetic therapy 
are masked by the upper lip or just revealed. 
31 In clinical practice, the </p>

<p>Table 5 Comparison of frequencies for smile classification with other studies </p>

<p>Study 
Reference </p>

<p>Commissure smile 
Cuspid smile 
Gummy smile </p>

<p>Subject 
Percentage/% 
Subject 
Percentage/% 
Subject 
Percentage/% </p>

<p>Sawyer et al., 2010 (n571) 
26 
54 
77.0 
11 
15.0 
6 
8.0 
Desai et al., 2009 (n599) 
4 
64 
63.4 
29 
29.3 
6 
6.1 
Tjan et al., 1984 (n5454) 
16 
313 
68.9 
93 
20.5 
48 
10.6 
Rubin, 1974 (n5100) 
1 
67 
67.0 
31 
31.0 
2 
2.0 
Present study (n5188) 
114 
60.6 
63 
33.5 
11 
5.9 </p>

<p>Table 6 Comparison of frequencies for upper lip curvature with other studies </p>

<p>Study 
Reference </p>

<p>Upward 
Straight 
Downward </p>

<p>Subject 
Percentage/% 
Subject 
Percentage/% 
Subject 
Percentage/% </p>

<p>Hulsey, 1970 (n540) 
8 
26 
65.0 
4 
10.0 
10 
25.0 
Dong et al., 1999 (n5240) 
7 
29 
12.0 
108 
45.0 
103 
43.0 
Present study (n5188) 
49 
26.1 
75 
39.9 
64 
34.0 </p>

<p>Dynamic smile and upper lip curvature in Chinese 
LZ Liang et al 
52 </p>

<p>International Journal of Oral Science </p>

<p>smile classifications also raise additional considerations concerning 
the notions of harmony and symmetry between prosthetic and gin-
gival features. In the second type of smile-the cuspid smile-the lip 
line of the upper cuspids moves upward significantly while smiling, 
making reconstruction of the cuspid area extremely important in these 
patients. With the third type of smile-the gummy smile-though 
relatively infrequent in Chinese patients, extra attention must be paid 
to the exposure of upper and lower gingivae. In these cases, longer 
clinical crown lengths may help compensate for the unbalanced pro-
portion of exposed gingivae to crowns. 
Limitations of sample size, although consistent with previous pub-
lished reports, also must temper extrapolation of outcomes from this 
study. It is evident that differences based on race and gender exist in 
upper lip curvature and smile classifications. Nevertheless, this investi-
gation established some measurable components from which further 
studies may be derived; an example includes further examining the 
racial and genetic basis in the differences found in the present study. 
It may also be worthwhile to investigate whether the present smile 
classification and upper lip curvature may be combined with other 
smile indices, such as smile arc, smile line, buccal corridor, etc., and 
whether these esthetics indices could be efficiently integrated into 
clinical practice. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION 
One hundred and eighty-eight Chinese Han-nationality youths ran-
ged from 20 to 35 years of age were selected and made dynamic smile 
evaluation by using an objective spontaneous smile process capturing 
method. In upper lip curvature and smile classifications, differences 
clearly exist based on race, when comparing Chinese subjects with 
those of Caucasian descent, and gender. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank Dr Hao Zhang and Dr Huan-Xin Meng for their suggestions 
in the preparation of the manuscript. The authors appreciate the technical 
supports provided from Zhan-Qiang Cao (Engineer), and the related 
information provided from Dr Di Le. </p>



<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivative Works 3.0 
Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0 </p>

<p>Dynamic smile and upper lip curvature in Chinese 
LZ Liang et al 
53 </p>

<p>International Journal of Oral Science </p>

</text></tei>