<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3837047" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>We studied the change in the first-phase insulin response (FPIR) 
during the progression to type 1 diabetes (T1D). Seventy-four oral 
insulin trial progressors to T1D from the Diabetes Prevention Trial-
Type 1 with at least one FPIR measurement after baseline and 
before diagnosis were studied. The FPIR was examined longitudi-
nally in 26 progressors who had FPIR measurements during each of 
the 3 years before diagnosis. The association between the change 
from the baseline FPIR to the last FPIR and time to diagnosis was 
studied in the remainder (n = 48). The 74 progressors had lower 
baseline FPIR values than nonprogressors (n = 270), with adjust-
ments made for age and BMI. In the longitudinal analysis of the 26 
progressors, there was a greater decline in the FPIR from 1.5 to 
0.5 years before diagnosis than from 2.5 to 1.5 years before diagno-
sis. This accelerated decline was also evident in a regression anal-
ysis of the 48 remaining progressors in whom the rate of decline 
became more marked with the approaching diagnosis. The patterns 
of decline were similar between the longitudinal and regression 
analyses. There is an acceleration of decline in the FPIR during 
the progression to T1D, which becomes especially marked between 
1.5 and 0.5 years before diagnosis. Diabetes 62:4179-4183, 2013   A </p>

<p>low first-phase insulin response (FPIR) to in-
travenous glucose is considered to be an in-
dicator of faltering b-cell function and is 
a predictor of type 1 diabetes (T1D) (1-4), yet 
there have been no descriptions of changes in the FPIR 
during the progression to T1D. Such information could be 
of value for optimizing the timing of interventions to pre-
vent the loss of b-cells. We have used, therefore, FPIR 
measurements from the serial intravenous glucose toler-
ance tests (IVGTTs) obtained in the oral insulin trial of the 
Diabetes Prevention Trial-Type 1 (DPT-1) (5) to describe 
the decline of the FPIR during the progression to T1D. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>Individuals included in the analysis participated in the DPT-1 oral insulin trial 
(5). All oral insulin trial participants were relatives of T1D patients who were 
positive for islet cell autoantibodies and insulin autoantibodies. The partic-
ipants initially had normal oral glucose tolerance (fasting glucose value ,110 
mg/dL; 30-, 60-, and 90-min values ,200 mg/dL; 2-h value ,140 mg/dL) and 
were above defined FPIR thresholds ($100 mU/mL for $8.0 years [with the 
exception of $60 mU/mL for parents of T1D patients], $60 mU/mL for ,8.0 
years). IVGTTs were performed at baseline and at yearly intervals. DPT-1 
parenteral trial participants (6) were not included in the analyses because they 
only had IVGTTs at 2-year intervals, and many in that trial were selected on 
the basis of having low FPIR values. T1D was diagnosed either through oral 
glucose tolerance test (OGTT) surveillance according to standard American 
Diabetes Association criteria or through clinical presentation. Two non-
progressors with baseline FPIR values of 675 mU/mL and 953 mU/mL (474 
mU/mL being the next highest value) were excluded from the analysis because 
they were outliers. In addition, three others were excluded because of missing 
values. 
The IVGTTs were performed after a minimum 10-h fast. A standard infusion 
of 0.5 g/kg to a maximum of 35 g at a 25% glucose concentration was ad-
ministered over a 3-min period. Samples were obtained in the fasting state and 
at 1, 3, 5, 7, and 10 min. The FPIR was defined as the sum of the insulin 
measurements at 1 and 3 min. Insulin was measured by radioimmunoassay 
(coefficient of variation ,8.5%) (7). There was high cross-reactivity with 
proinsulin. Autoantibody procedures for DPT-1 have been previously de-
scribed (8). 
Data analysis. For progressors to be included in the analysis, in addition to the 
baseline FPIR measurement, at least one additional FPIR measurement before 
diagnosis was required. There were 74 progressors who fulfilled this criterion of 
whom 44 (59%) were diagnosed through OGTT surveillance. (Supplementary 
Table 1 shows that there were no significant differences in baseline charac-
teristics between the progressors included in and the progressors excluded 
from the analysis.) There were no significant differences between the 35 (47%) 
receiving oral insulin and the 39 (53%) receiving placebo in the baseline FPIR 
values or in the changes from the baseline FPIR to the last FPIR. Two analyses 
were used to examine changes in the FPIR during the progression to T1D in 
these individuals. A longitudinal analysis (analysis 1) examined serial FPIR 
values in the 26 progressors who had three IVGTTS after the baseline IVGTT: 
2-3 years before diagnosis, 1-2 years before diagnosis, and within 1 year of 
diagnosis (see flowchart in the Supplementary Data). The mean times from 
diagnosis of the FPIR measurements within each of the yearlong intervals are 
shown in the RESULTS for simplicity. 
In the other analysis (analysis 2), the change in the FPIR value per year from 
the baseline FPIR to the last FPIR before diagnosis was calculated for each 
individual (n = 74). The change in the FPIR per year was then used as the 
dependent variable for simple linear regression and multiple regression 
models. The independent variable of interest was the time to diagnosis from 
the midpoint of the time interval between the baseline FPIR and the last FPIR 
(Fig. 1). The other variables included in the multiple regression analysis were 
the FPIR measurement at baseline and the time between the baseline and the 
last FPIR measurements. Coefficients from the multivariate model were used 
to develop a curve describing the change in the FPIR during the progression to 
T1D (Supplementary Data) in the 48 progressors who were not included in 
analysis 1. The pattern of change in FPIR during progression in those indi-
viduals was then compared with the pattern of change in the 26 progressors 
studied in analysis 1. 
Wilcoxon rank sum and t tests were used for comparisons. Analyses of 
covariance were used to adjust for comparisons between groups. <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> version 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.1.3</rs> software was used for the analyses. The P values are two-sided. Although </p>

<p>From the </p>

<p>P , 0.05 was considered to be statistically significant, Bonferroni corrections 
are also shown. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Table 1 shows comparisons of baseline characteristics 
between the 74 progressors (76% of all progressors in the 
oral insulin trial) who had at least one FPIR measurement 
after the baseline measurement (those included in the 
analyses below) and 270 nonprogressors (those not di-
agnosed during follow-up). Aside from the younger age of 
the progressors (P = 0.003), there were initially no signif-
icant differences in FPIR, log BMI, and sex. However, 
because the FPIR was associated with both age (r = 0.17, 
P = 0.001) and log BMI (r = 0.38, P , 0.001), we compared 
the FPIR between the progressors and the nonprogressors 
after adjusting for those variables. The baseline FPIR was 
significantly lower in the progressors (P , 0.020) with the 
adjustments. Additionally, with adjustments for age and 
sex, the BMI was significantly higher in the progressors 
(P = 0.035). The median duration of follow-up for the oral 
insulin trial participants was 4.3 years. 
Analysis 1. Twenty-six of the 74 progressors analyzed had 
FPIR measurements at baseline (mean 6 SD 4.4 6 3.4 
years before diagnosis), ,3.0 to $2.0 years before diag-
nosis (2.5 6 0.3 years), ,2.0 to $ 1.0 year before diagnosis </p>

<p>(1.5 6 0.3 years), and ,1.0 year before diagnosis (0.5 6 0.2 
years). Table 2 shows FPIR values of the 26 progressors 
according to the time before diagnosis along with the per-
cent change in the FPIR (per year) from the preceding 
FPIR. (Data are presented in the table and below according 
to the mean time from diagnosis of the FPIR measurements 
within each yearlong interval.) There was a small decline in 
the FPIR from baseline until 1.5 years before diagnosis, with 
no evidence of acceleration. The decline then accelerated 
from 1.5 years before diagnosis to 0.5 years before di-
agnosis. The median (25th, 75th percentile) percent change 
in FPIR from 2.5 to 1.5 years before diagnosis was 24.1% 
(229.8%, 30.2%, not significant), whereas the median percent 
change from 1.5 to 0.5 years before diagnosis was 229.3% 
(256.4%, -3.5%, P 5 0.001). Of the 26 progressors, the FPIR 
declined in 21 from 1.5 to 0.5 years before diagnosis and in 
14 from 2.5 to 1.5 years before diagnosis. Compared with 
the change from 2.5 to 1.5 years before diagnosis, there was 
a decline (vs. a prior increase) or a more marked decline 
from 1.5 to 0.5 years before diagnosis in 16. The median 
overall percent change from the baseline FPIR to the last 
FPIR was 247.7% (258.2%, -27.7%, P , 0.001). 
Another measure of the insulin response, the mean of 
the values from 1, 3, 5, 7, and 10 min, was also examined 
longitudinally in 25 progressors (1 fewer because of </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Diagrammatic representations of the variables of interest included in analysis 2. The time to diagnosis and the times between the first and 
last FPIR are shown in four hypothetical individuals. </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Baseline characteristics of progressors to T1D with at least one FPIR measurement after baseline and nonprogressors </p>

<p>Progressors (n = 74) 
Nonprogressors (n = 270) 
P value </p>

<p>FPIR (mU/mL) 
144 6 84 
158 6 74 
0.020* 
Age (years) 
9.9 6 6.4 
12.7 6 8.9 
0.003 
Log BMI (kg/m 
2 ) 
2.97 6 0.20 (n = 71) 
2.97 6 0.23 (n = 259) 
0.035** 
Male sex (%) 
59 
61 
0.752 </p>

<p>Data are mean 6 SD. *Adjusted for age and BMI. **Adjusted for age and sex. With the Bonferroni corrections, the P values were not 
significant [threshold ,0.013] for the differences in the FPIR and the log BMI. </p>

<p>LOSS OF FIRST-PHASE INSULIN RESPONSE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 62, DECEMBER 2013 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>a missing value). The pattern was similar to the FPIR, with 
53 6 22 mU/mL at baseline, 50 6 32 mU/mL at 2.5 years, 
47 6 26 mU/mL at 1.5 years, and 33 6 2 mU/mL at 0.5 
years. The differences were significant from baseline to 2.5 
years and from 1.5 to 0.5 years (P = 0.025 and P , 0.001, 
respectively). 
The longitudinal pattern of FPIR values was also ex-
amined in the 111 nonprogressors who had FPIR mea-
surements ;2 years (2.5-1.5 years) and 1 year (1.5-0.5 
years) from the last FPIR measurement. There was a small, 
nonsignificant increase over time (2 years: 158 6 81 mU/ 
mL; 1 year: 162 6 74 mU/mL; last: 168 6 93 mU/mL). 
Analysis 2. Because the findings in analysis 1 suggested 
that the rate of decline accelerates with progression, we 
performed another analysis to further assess this possi-
bility in all 74 progressors who had at least one FPIR 
measurement after the baseline measurement. For this 
analysis (Fig. 1), the difference between the baseline FPIR 
and last FPIR before diagnosis was calculated for each of 
those progressors. The interval between the last FPIR 
measurement and diagnosis was 0.76 6 0.66 years. In 
univariate linear regression (Table 3), there was a signifi-
cant association between the decline per year from the 
baseline FPIR to the last FPIR and the proximity to di-
agnosis (P , 0.05). The association was more pronounced 
(P , 0.001) with adjustments for the baseline FPIR and the 
length of the interval between the FPIR measurements. 
The same regression analyses were also performed in 
the 48 progressors who did not meet the multiple FPIR 
measurement criteria and, thus, were not included in 
analysis 1; the association was again apparent (Table 3). 
To further examine the association between the decline of 
the FPIR and the time from diagnosis, the 48 progressors 
were divided according to the median time from diagnosis, 
which was 1.66 years. In a univariate analysis, those ,1.66 
years from diagnosis had a greater rate of decline (72.0 6 
29.0 mU/mL per year from diagnosis, P = 0.021) than those 
.1.66 years from diagnosis (11.2 6 13.6 mU/mL, not sig-
nificant). This difference was also evident in the </p>

<p>multivariate analysis (,1.66 years from diagnosis: 76.6 6 
23.9 mU/mL [P = 0.004], .1.66 years from diagnosis: 35.4 6 
12.7 mU/mL [P = 0.011]). 
Comparison of findings between analysis 1 and 
analysis 2. To further examine the consistency of the 
findings between analysis 1 and analysis 2, we used the 
regression coefficients from the 48 progressors excluded 
from analysis 1 to develop a curve to describe the change 
in FPIR with the approaching diagnosis. This curve is 
shown in Fig. 2 along with the curve of those followed 
longitudinally in analysis 1. (Baseline characteristics of the 
two groups are shown in Supplementary Tables 2 and 3. 
There were no significant differences.) Starting from the 
same value (116.4 mU/mL) as the mean of the FPIR 2.5 
years before diagnosis of those followed longitudinally, the 
pattern of decline was almost the same: a gradual decline 
from 2.5 to 1.5 years before diagnosis followed by a steep 
decline from 1.5 to 0.5 years before diagnosis. Thus, using 
separate samples and different analyses, the pattern of 
decline predicted by the regression procedure (analysis 2) 
was consistent with the actual decline (analysis 1). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The findings show that the decline in the FPIR during the 
progression to T1D accelerates as the diagnosis 
approaches. This was evident in the two separate samples 
of the progressors studied. In the longitudinal analysis of 
serial FPIRs (analysis 1), there was a gradual loss that was 
followed by a more substantial loss. In the regression 
analysis (analysis 2), there was an association between the 
rate of loss of the FPIR and the proximity to diagnosis of 
T1D both for all the progressors and with the exclusion of 
those in analysis 1. 
The high degree of consistency of the findings, derived 
from different samples of progressors and different ana-
lyses, provides additional supporting evidence for the ac-
celeration of the decline in the FPIR. Although the curves 
appear to show an abrupt increase in the acceleration of </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
FPIR values and the percent change from the previous values according to the time before diagnosis in 26 progressors </p>

<p>Time before diagnosis* 
4.4 years (baseline) 
2.5 years 
1.5 years 
0.5 years </p>

<p>FPIR (mU/mL) 
127 6 52 
116 6 76 [0.042] 
112 6 71 [0.815] 
75 6 50 [,0.001] 
Percent change 
-
-11.2 (225.1, 0.0) [0.039] 
-4.1 (229.8, 30.2) [0.912] 
-29.3 (256.4, -3.5) [0.001] </p>

<p>Data are mean 6 SD or median (25th, 75th percentile). *The mean times before diagnosis are indicated for baseline and the 2-to 3-year, 1-to 
2-year, and ,1-year intervals. P values for change per year from previous FPIR measurement are in brackets. With the Bonferroni corrections, 
P values were not significant (threshold ,0.017) for the change in the FPIR per year from 4.4 to 2.5 years and for the percent change per year 
from 4.4 to 2.5 years. </p>

<p>TABLE 3 
Multiple regression analysis for the association of change in FPIR* [(last-baseline)/year] with years to diagnosis** in progressors to 
T1D </p>

<p>Univariate 
Multivariate*** 
Coefficient 6 SE 
P value 
Coefficient 6 SE 
P value </p>

<p>All (n = 74) 
13.8 6 5.7 
0.019 
28.3 6 5.8 
,0.001 
Analysis 1 excluded (n = 48) 
15.9 6 7.9 
0.049 
31.0 6 7.4 
,0.001 </p>

<p>The coefficients represent the rate of change in the FPIR per year from the baseline FPIR to the last FPIR vs. the number of years from 
diagnosis. Thus, the positive coefficients indicate that the rate of loss becomes greater as the time from diagnosis decreases. *mU/mL. 
**Defined as time of diagnosis to middle of interval between baseline and last FPIR. ***Covariates in the model were baseline FPIR and 
time between baseline and last FPIR (see Supplementary Data for regression equations). </p>

<p>J.M. SOSENKO AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 62, DECEMBER 2013 </p>

<p>
decline, this is not necessarily the case; the acceleration 
could occur in a more gradual manner. Still, the data show 
that the decline in the FPIR becomes more rapid as the 
diagnosis of T1D approaches. The acceleration appears to 
become especially marked between 1.5 and 0.5 years be-
fore diagnosis. Of note, this time period appears to co-
incide with the time that the loss of b-cell sensitivity to 
glucose becomes appreciable (9). 
The overall loss of the FPIR from the baseline mea-
surement to the last measurement was marked in the 26 
progressors followed longitudinally, with a decline of 
47.7% by 0.5 years before diagnosis. However, the extent of 
insulin loss before diagnosis is almost certainly greater for 
several reasons. It is likely that there already had been 
some loss of the FPIR before the baseline measurement 
because the baseline FPIR values were lower in the pro-
gressors than in the nonprogressors with adjustments for 
age and BMI. In addition, the shape of the curves in Fig. 2 
and data from an analysis of serial OGTTs (10) suggest that 
the rate of decline could be even greater during the last 
6 months before diagnosis. Finally, DPT-1 participants 
were mostly diagnosed through OGTT surveillance rather 
than through clinical presentation (11). 
The longitudinal analysis for the nonprogressors showed 
little change in the FPIR over time. The interpretation of 
FPIR trends in the nonprogressors is complicated by the 
likelihood that a number of them would have been di-
agnosed with further follow-up. 
To our knowledge, no prior studies have described the 
pattern of decline of the FPIR during the progression to 
T1D. The oral insulin trial was unique in that such a large 
number of autoantibody positive individuals were followed 
with serial IVGTTs at yearly intervals. We have previously 
shown that the 30-to 0-min C-peptide difference from 
OGTTs (which correlates with the FPIR) also declines 
appreciably during progression (12). 
It is possible that the findings pertaining to the loss of 
the FPIR are not fully representative. Those studied were 
all relatives of T1D patients. Additionally, the criteria for </p>

<p>inclusion in the longitudinal analyses could have excluded 
faster progressors. However, data from prior studies sug-
gest that T1D characteristics are similar between T1D 
patients who have relatives with T1D and T1D patients 
who have no relatives with the disease (sporadic cases) 
(13-15). Moreover, 76% of the progressors in the oral in-
sulin trial were included in the analyses. 
The basis for the accelerating decline in the FPIR is 
unclear. Although several explanatory hypotheses can be 
formulated, it would be important to discern whether the 
accelerated decline of the FPIR is the result of the primary 
pathogenetic process or whether it relates more to sec-
ondary factors, such as the possible impact of increasing 
glucose levels on b-cells during progression. It is possible 
that an impaired b-cell could be particularly susceptible to 
small changes in glucose concentration; however, there 
are no data available to support this. 
In conclusion, the findings show that the loss of b-cell 
function accelerates well before the diagnosis of T1D. 
Thus, as treatments that preserve insulin secretion become 
available, it will be essential to identify individuals as early 
as possible during progression. With this in mind, there is 
a need to refine our ability to identify very-high-risk indi-
viduals years before diagnosis and to test potential inter-
ventions at that time. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The sponsor of the trial was the Type 1 Diabetes TrialNet 
Study Group, which is a clinical trials network funded by 
the National Institutes of Health through the National 
Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases, 
the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, 
and the Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child 
Health and Human Development through cooperative 
agreements U01-DK-061010, U01-DK-061016, U01-DK-
061034, U01-DK-061036, U01-DK-061040, U01-DK-061041, 
U01-DK-061042, U01-DK-061055, U01-DK-061058, U01-DK-
084565, U01-DK-085453, U01-DK-085461, U01-DK-085463, </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Curves of FPIR values during the progression to T1D from the actual serial values of the progressors in analysis 1 and the values derived 
from the regression model for the other progressors from analysis 2. The curve for analysis 1 is plotted according to the mean times from diagnosis 
of the FPIR measurements within each yearlong interval. For the purpose of comparison, the curve from analysis 2 was assigned the same starting 
value of 2.5 years and plotted according to the same time points. The patterns are similar, with a gradual decline from 2.5 to 1.5 years and a marked 
decline from 1.5 to 0.5 years before diagnosis. </p>

<p>LOSS OF FIRST-PHASE INSULIN RESPONSE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 62, DECEMBER 2013 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>U01-DK-085466, U01-DK-085499, U01-DK-085505, and U01-
DK-085509 and contract HHSN267200800019C; the Na-
tional Center for Research Resources through Clinical 
Translational Science Awards UL1-RR-024131, UL1-RR-
024139, UL1-RR-024153, UL1-RR-024975, UL1-RR-024982, 
UL1-RR-025744, UL1-RR-025761, UL1-RR-025780, UL1-RR-
029890, UL1-RR-031986, and P30-DK-017047 and General 
Clinical Research Center Award M01-RR-00400; JDRF; and 
the American Diabetes Association. 
No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article 
were reported. 
The contents of this article are solely the responsibility 
of the authors and do not necessarily represent the official 
views of the National Institutes of Health, JDRF, or 
American Diabetes Association. 
J.M.S. analyzed the data and wrote the manuscript. J.S.S., 
J.P.K., C.J.G., L.E.R., and D.M. conducted the study and 
reviewed the manuscript. C.A.B. contributed statistical 
support. J.M. and K.C.H. reviewed the manuscript. J.P.P. 
conducted the study, reviewed the manuscript, and assisted 
in writing the manuscript. J.M.S. is the guarantor of this 
work and, as such, had full access to all the data in the 
study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data 
and the accuracy of the data analysis. 
Parts of this study were presented in abstract form at the 
73rd Scientific Sessions of the American Diabetes Associ-
ation, Chicago, Illinois, 21-25 June 2013. </p>



<p>J.M. SOSENKO AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 62, DECEMBER 2013 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>