<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3448398" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:46+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>BACKGROUND: Hypertension is a condition normally detected in people with type II diabetes. 
It eventually leads to cardiovascular diseases in the patient. Visfatin is an adipocytokine which is 
secreted from adipose tissue and can affect the inflammatory reaction and also serum lipid 
levels. Additionally, omega-3 inhibits the accumulation of fat and formation of insulin 
resistance. The current study tried to investigate the effects of omega-3 on blood pressure 
compared to placebo and the relationship between serum visfatin levels and blood pressure. </p>

<p>METHODS: A total number of 71 women with type II diabetes were randomly assigned to 
2 groups to receive either omega-3 capsules or placebo capsules. In the first step, a 
questionnaire consisting age, height, weight, waist and hip circumferences, and systolic and 
diastolic blood pressure was filled out for each subject. Blood samples were then collected for 
laboratory tests. The next step was to conduct 8 weeks of intervention. All variables, except age, 
were measured again after the intervention. Hip circumference was considered as the maximum 
circumference of the buttocks. Waist circumference was measured by placing a tape horizontally 
across the abdomen at the end of a normal exhalation. Laboratory tests included the assessment 
of visfatin, glucose, and glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c) concentrations. Lipid profile, i.e. low 
density lipoprotein (LDL), high density lipoprotein (HDL), triglyceride (TG), and cholesterol, 
was also assessed. Using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">18</rs>, data obtained from the study was analyzed by a variety of 
appropriate statistical tests. </p>

<p>RESULTS: There was a significant change in mean differences of systolic and diastolic blood 
pressure. Blood pressure showed a significant reduction in the omega-3 group compared to the 
placebo group. However, no significant changes were observed in systolic and diastolic blood 
pressure before and after the intervention (P &gt; 0.05). </p>

<p>CONCLUSION: Based on the results of this study, a daily consumption of omega-3 is suggested 
for patients with type II diabetes. </p>

<p>Keywords: Omega 3, Visfatin, Hypertension, Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus. </p>

<p>ARYA Atherosclerosis Journal 2012, 8(1): 27-31 </p>

<p>Date of submission: 11 Dec 2011, Date of acceptance: 10 Mar 2012 </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>According to the World Health Organization (WHO), 
150 million people are currently suffering from type 
II diabetes. This figure is predicted to be doubled by 
the year 2025. 1 Today, the disease is detected in all age 
groups, including women and high risk groups. 
Mortality rates in diabetic individuals after adjusting 
for age is 1.5-2.5 times more than total population. 2 
Since in most cases, insulin resistance and diabetes are 
associated with obesity, obesity and overweight are 
considered as the major causes of diabetes and insulin 
resistance. 3 
In addition, hypertension is common in people with 
diabetes and its prevalence increases substantially over </p>

<p>time. On the other hand, omega-3 intake may reduce 
blood pressure. 4 Alpha lipoic acid reduces hypertension 
in people with type II diabetes. 5 The prevalence of 
hypertension increases with age in both sexes. 6,7 In 
1989, one fourth of America's total population and one 
third of its adults suffered from high blood pressure. 
At the same time, hypertension developed in 30% of 
urban community adults in the East Mediterranean 
region. 8 Visfatin is an adiponectin with insulin-like 
function 9,10 which was discovered in adipose tissues by 
Fukuhara et al. in 2005. 11 Omega 3 increases visfatin 
secretion in patients with type II diabetes. 12 Obesity 
can lead to hyperplasia and hypertrophy of fat cells 
which secrete a variety of compounds with exert </p>

<p>Omega-3 and blood pressure in diabetic patients </p>



<p>ARYA Atherosclerosis Journal 2012 (Spring); Volume 8, Issue 1 </p>

<p>critical roles in the pathogenesis of diseases such as 
metabolic syndrome, hypertension, insulin resistance, 
and cardiovascular diseases. 13 
Omega-3 fatty acids have been demonstrated to 
reduce cholesterol, triglycerides, inflammation, 
cardiovascular diseases, and cancer. They may also 
prevent insulin resistance. Omega-3 fatty acids 
downregulate the expression of genes and hormones 
(such as leptin) involved in obesity. They also prevent 
the construction of omega-6 compounds. In type II 
diabetics, consumption of over 4 grams of 
eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) or docosahexaenoic acid 
(DHA) can increase serum glucose and reduce 
triglyceride. 14 
Visfatin is a regulator of fat metabolism 15 which 
has a direct relation with body mass index (BMI). 16 
Being directly relate with waist to hip ratio (WHR), 
serum visfatin level is higher in diabetics compared to 
normal healthy people. 11 
This study was designed to investigate whether 
omega-3 lowers blood pressure in diabetics and if 
there is any significant relationship between serum 
visfatin level and blood pressure in people with type 
II diabetes. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>This was a double-blind randomized controlled 
clinical study. The study population included 45-65 
year-old female type II diabetes patients who referred 
to Charity Center of Diabetes in Isfahan, Iran. Using 
a formula and considering 15% additional samples, 
the sample size in each group was calculated as 39 in 
each group. Women were only included if they had at 
least a 5-year history of type II diabetes. Exclusion 
criteria were injecting insulin, having secondary 
complications of diabetes such as ophthalmic or renal 
complications and amputation, and having 
inflammatory diseases with C-reactive protein (CRP) 
levels of +++ or more. Finally, 39 patients in the 
omega-3 group and 34 subjects in the placebo group 
completed the study. 
This study was approved by the Ethics 
Committee of Tehran University of Medical 
Sciences, Tehran, Iran. The participants were 
informed about the study procedure. They were then 
requested to sign the consent form. The subjects 
were randomly divided into two groups of omega-3 
supplement recipients and placebo recipients. The 
omega-3 group received two omega-3 capsules 
containing 1,000 mg omega-3, 65% EPA (360 mg), 
and 35% DHA (240 mg) daily for 8 weeks. The 
placebo group received two placebo capsules 
containing 1 g of cornstarch for the same period. </p>

<p>The current study was performed in three phases. 
In the first phase, all patients filled out a 
questionnaire including age, height, weight, waist 
circumference, hip circumference, and systolic and 
diastolic blood pressure. Blood samples were also 
collected for blood tests. In the second stage, after 8 
weeks of intervention, the same parameters were 
measured and blood samples were obtained again. 
Hip circumference was measured at the widest part. 
Waist circumference was also measured by a cord at 
the end of a normal exhalation. Blood pressure was 
measured by a mercury sphygmomanometer in a 
sitting position and after 10 minutes of rest. 
Visfatin level was measured by standard kits using 
enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) 
method with a sensitivity of 30 pg/ml (Human 
Visfatin Kit, Adipogen Inc., South Korea). Both the 
examiner and the participants were blinded to the 
intervention. Blood sampling was conducted after 
10-12 hours of fasting (10 cc in each time) before 
taking the anti-diabetic tablets. 
All the tests were conducted automatically by 
Hitachi 911. Data was analyzed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">18</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, US</rs>). The Fisher's exact test was 
used to analyze qualitative data and student's t-test for 
quantitative data. Weight changes were analyzed by 
chi-square test while Pearson's correlation test was 
used to assess correlations. Moreover, paired t-test 
was used for comparing blood pressure changes 
before and after the intervention in both groups and 
independent t-test was used for comparing mean 
concentration changes between the two groups. To 
detect the correlations between variables, Pearson's 
regression analysis was used. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The results showed no significant differences in the 
mean baseline values of age, socioeconomic 
characteristics such as educational status and 
occupation, health status, medication consumption and 
dietary intake between omega-3 and placebo groups. 
Therefore, these variables had probably no 
confounding effect. The mean age of omega-3 and 
placebo groups were 53.6 ± 4.3 and 53.9 ± 5.4 years, 
respectively. Student's t-test showed no significant 
differences in the mean ages of the two groups 
(P = 0.79). Table 1 presents the obtained data on BMI, 
weight, and systolic and diastolic blood pressure. 
Although the comparison of values of before and 
after intervention showed no significant changes in 
the mean BMI within groups, there were significant 
differences in the mean BMI between groups. The 
same trend was observed for weight, as the changes </p>

<p>MJ. Hosseinzadeh Atar, H. Hajianfar, A. Bahonar </p>

<p>ARYA Atherosclerosis Journal 2012 (Spring); Volume 8, Issue 1 </p>

<p>
Table 1. Anthropometric data and visfatin level in the studied groups 
P 
Placebo 
Omega-3 
0.76 
28 ± 3.8 
27.7 ± 3.4 
Before Intervention 
Body mass index 
(kg/m2) </p>

<p>0.19 
28.7 ± 4.4 
27.4 ± 4.1 
After Intervention </p>

<p>&lt; 0.001 
0.73 ± 1.2 
-0.31 ± 0.7 
Difference between 
After and Before </p>

<p>0.84 
70.1 ± 11.3 
69.6 ± 13.2 
Before Intervention 
Weight 
(kg) </p>

<p>0.33 
71.7 ± 12.8 
68.8 ± 12.4 
After Intervention </p>

<p>&lt; 0.001 
1.5 ± 2.5 
-0.8 ± 1.8 
Difference between 
After and Before </p>

<p>0.007 
118 ± 16.3 
130 ± 19.2 
Before Intervention 
Systolic blood pressure 
(mm Hg) </p>

<p>0.95 
124.1 ± 13.9 
124.3 ± 13.7 
After Intervention </p>

<p>0.003 
6.2 ± 13.7 
-5.4 ± 17.6 
Difference between 
After and Before </p>

<p>0.08 
77 ± 10.7 
82 ± 11.5 
Before Intervention 
Diastolic blood pressure 
(mm Hg) </p>

<p>0.25 
82.6 ± 7.6 
80.5 ± 7.6 
After Intervention </p>

<p>0.002 
5.6 ± 9.4 
-1.2 ± 8.4 
Difference between 
After and Before </p>

<p>after the intervention in each group were not 
significant compared to the value before the 
intervention but significant once comparing the 
two groups. 
The findings of this study revealed that the blood 
pressure of individuals who received placebo showed 
an upward trend during the intervention. However, 
omega-3 was able to reduce blood pressure in 
diabetics. Significant differences were thus detected 
between the two groups. 
While at baseline, there were no significant 
changes in the mean systolic blood pressure within 
groups, the mean differences between groups were 
significant after the intervention (P = 0.003). Diastolic 
blood pressure had a similar trend. No significant 
differences within groups were observed before and 
after the study though, with a P of 0.002 the mean 
changes of DBP in omega-3 group significantly 
differed with what measured in placebo group. No 
significant changes were detected between systolic 
and diastolic blood pressure before and after the 
intervention (Tables 2 and 3). </p>

<p>Table 2. The relationship between visfatin and systolic 
(SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP) at baseline 
Visfatin 
R = 0.177 
P = 0.28 
SBP </p>

<p>Omega-3 group 
R = 0.166 
P = 0.31 
DBP </p>

<p>R = 0.041 
P = 0.81 
SBP 
Placebo group 
R = 0.07 
P = 0.69 
DBP </p>

<p>Table 3. The relationship between visfatin and systolic 
(SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP) after the 
intervention 
Visfatin 
R = -0.121 
P = 0.47 
SBP 
Omega-3 group 
R = -0.149 
P = 0.37 
DBP </p>

<p>R = -0.05 
P = 0.78 
SBP 
Placebo group 
R = -0.08 
P = 0.96 
DBP </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The current study evaluated the efficacy of omega-3 
on blood pressure in type II diabetic patients. It also 
assessed the relationship between visfatin and blood 
pressure. The results showed that consumption of 
omega-3 was effective in people with type 2 diabetes 
since it increased visfatin 12 and might have lowered 
blood pressure. There were no relationships between 
visfatin serum levels and systolic or diastolic blood 
pressure. Haider et al. 9 and 2 studies by Dogru et 
al. 17,18 reported similar results. 
Unlike the studies by Berndt et al. 19 and 
Krzyzanowska et al. 20 but similar to the obtained 
results by Fukuhara et al. 11 and Chen et al., 11 the 
current study indicated a significant positive 
relationship between the amount of abdominal obesity 
and serum levels of visfatin in patients with diabetes. 
In addition, identical to our results, some previous 
studies showed no significant relationship between 
circulating visfatin levels and BMI. 9,10,19,21 On the 
contrary, the findings of the studies by Pagano et al. </p>

<p>Omega-3 and blood pressure in diabetic patients </p>



<p>ARYA Atherosclerosis Journal 2012 (Spring); Volume 8, Issue 1 </p>

<p>on obese nondiabetics 22 and Samara et al. on 
nondiabetic individuals with different weights 23 
showed an inverse relationship between BMI and 
circulating visfatin levels. 
On the other hand, Chen et al. found a significant 
relationship between BMI and circulating visfatin 
levels in patients with diabetes. 9 
Generally, the amount of visceral fat or abdominal 
obesity and body fat, are determined by WHR and 
BMI, respectively. 19 Some researches have revealed 
that consumption of omega-3 can burn more body fat 
and increase metabolism, causing weight loss in 
patients. 24 In the present study, BMI, as measured by 
weight, decreased in patients taking omega-3 and 
increased in the placebo group. Kesavulu et al. proved 
that omega-3 supplements had beneficial effects on 
triglyceride, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol, lipid 
peroxidation, and antioxidant enzymes, which 
eventually lowered vascular complications in 
diabetics. 25 In 1991, Malasanos and Stacpoole 
conducted a study on patients with type 2 diabetes. 
They suggested that EPA could lower the levels of 
serum lipids and lipoproteins, increase fluidity of cell 
membranes, and reduce platelet aggregation and blood 
pressure. 26 Omega-3 intake has also been suggested to 
have a weight control effect on diabetics. 27,28 
In 2007, Dogru et al. conducted a study on 33 
young patients who had recently been diagnosed with 
hypertension. It investigated the relationship between 
visfatin and blood pressure. To omit the possible 
confounding effects and relations between BMI and 
visfatin, patients with BMIs less than 25 were 
recruited to the study. However, no significant 
relationship was detected between serum visfatin level 
and blood pressure which was identical with the 
results achieved in this study. 18 It has also been shown 
that the insulin receptor is associated with 
hypertension. 13 Moreover, the insulin receptor and 
inflammation can be effective on the development of 
hypertension. 29 However, our results did not support 
this role for visfatin. </p>

<p>Recommendations </p>

<p>Based on the positive effects of omega-3 on 
hypertension, daily consupmtion of omega-3 
supplements for diabetics and individuals at high risk 
is highly recommended. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This article was derived from MSc thesis in the 
Isfahan University of Medical Sciences, No: 
IRCT138903164109N1. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interests </p>

<p>Authors have no conflict of interests. </p>

<p>References </p>

<p>1. King H, Aubert RE, Herman WH. Global burden of 
diabetes, 
1995-2025: 
prevalence, 
numerical 
estimates, and projections. Diabetes Care 1998; 
21(9): 1414-31. 
2. Jung CH, Rhee EJ, Kim SY, Shin HS, Kim BJ, Sung 
KC, et al. Associations between two single nucleotide 
polymorphisms of adiponectin gene and coronary 
artery diseases. Endocr J 2006; 53(5): 671-7. 
3. Kleinman JC, Donahue RP, Harris MI, Finucane FF, 
Madans JH, Brock DB. Mortality among diabetics in 
a national sample. Am J Epidemiol 1988; 128(2): 
389-401. 
4. Tribole E. The Ultimate Omega-3 Diet: Maximize the 
Power of Omega-3s to Supercharge Your Health, 
Battle Inflammation, and Keep Your Mind Sharp. 
New York: McGraw-Hill Professional; 2007. 
5. Mazlom Z, Ansari H. Effect of anti oxidan Alfa lipoic 
acid on blood presur in patient with type 2 diabetes . 
Iranian Journal of Endocrinology and Metabolism 
2009; 11(3): 245-50. 
6. Schlat RC. The heart. 8 
th ed. New York: McGraw 
Hill; 1994. p. 190-2. 
7. Finau SA, Prior IA, Salmond CE. Hypertension 
among urban and rural Tongans. Med J Aust 1986; 
144(1): 16-20. 
8. Alwan A. Prevention and control of cardiovascular 
diseases. Geneva: World Health Organization p. 21; 1995. 
9. Chen MP, Chung FM, Chang DM, Tsai JC, Huang 
HF, Shin SJ, et al. Elevated plasma level of 
visfatin/pre-B cell colony-enhancing factor in patients 
with type 2 diabetes mellitus. J Clin Endocrinol 
Metab 2006; 91(1): 295-9. 
10. Haider DG, Schindler K, Schaller G, Prager G, Wolzt 
M, Ludvik B. Increased plasma visfatin 
concentrations in morbidly obese subjects are reduced 
after gastric banding. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 2006; 
91(4): 1578-81. 
11. Fukuhara A, Matsuda M, Nishizawa M, Segawa K, 
Tanaka M, Kishimoto K, et al. Visfatin: a protein 
secreted by visceral fat that mimics the effects of 
insulin. Science 2005; 307(5708): 426-30. 
12. Bailey SD, Loredo-Osti JC, Lepage P, Faith J, 
Fontaine J, Desbiens KM, et al. Common 
polymorphisms in the promoter of the visfatin gene 
(PBEF1) influence plasma insulin levels in a French-
Canadian population. Diabetes 2006; 55(10): 
2896-902. 
13. Reaven GM. Insulin resistance/compensatory 
hyperinsulinemia, essential hypertension, and 
cardiovascular disease. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 
2003; 88(6): 2399-403. </p>

<p>MJ. Hosseinzadeh Atar, H. Hajianfar, A. Bahonar </p>

<p>ARYA Atherosclerosis Journal 2012 (Spring); Volume 8, Issue 1 </p>



<p>
How to cite this article: Hosseinzadeh Atar MJ, </p>

<p>Hajianfar H, Bahonar A. The effects of omega-3 on 
blood pressure and the relationship between serum 
visfatin level and blood pressure in patients with 
type II diabetes. ARYA Atherosclerosis Journal 2012; 
8(1): 27-31. </p>

</text></tei>