<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3318936" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T16:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Background/Aims: ACE inhibitor (ACE-I) treatment effectively inhibits proteinuria and amelio-
rates the course of various renal diseases. In experimental glomerulonephritis, however, angio-
tensin II (AngII) infusion has also been shown to be renoprotective. We evaluated the long-term 
(28 days) course of anti-Thy1 glomerulonephritis in animals with suppressed AngII formation by 
ACE-I treatment. Methods: Brown Norway rats received perindopril (2.8 mg/kg/day, n = 12), di-
hydropyridine calcium-antagonist amlodipine (Ca-A; 13 mg/kg/day, n = 6) or were left untreated 
(n = 14). All animals were monitored for blood pressure, proteinuria, and creatinine clearance 
after anti-Thy1 injection. Renal histology was assessed at day 7 and 28. Results: Systolic blood 
pressure was equally reduced by ACE-I and Ca-A treatment. AngII suppression prevented devel-
opment of proteinuria, but did not protect against glomerular microaneurysm formation or 
reduction in creatinine clearance. After resolution of the microaneurysms, animals with sup-
pressed AngII production showed a modest increase in glomerulosclerosis and vasculopathic 
thickening of intrarenal vessels. Conclusions: In anti-Thy1 glomerulonephritis, suppression of 
AngII formation does not protect against the induction of glomerular damage and is associated </p>

<p>with mild aggravation of adverse renal fibrotic remodeling. Proteinuria, however, is effectively 
prevented by ACE-I treatment. Ca-A treatment did not affect the course of glomerulonephritis, 
indicating that ACE-I effects are blood pressure independent. </p>

<p>The anti-Thy1 glomerulonephritis model is characterized by marked transient protein-
uria and involves both renal injury and repair. It therefore offers the potential to study vari-
ous components of renal disease. Thy1 is expressed on glomerular mesangial cells. Binding 
of the anti-Thy1 antibody delivered by single injection results in complement-mediated me-
sangiolysis with secondary endothelial damage [1, 2] . The model is self-limiting and fully 
reversible in healthy animals, while uninephrectomized rats injected with anti-Thy1.1 anti-
body develop progressive glomerulosclerosis [3] . 
The potent antiproteinuric effects of ACE inhibitors (ACE-I) are well established. An-
giotensin II (AngII) is a pathogenic factor in various renal diseases. However, AngII may 
also have renoprotective effects in early stages of kidney disease development. Stimulation 
of renal angiogenesis by AngII occurs during physiological postnatal kidney development 
[4] and drives the accelerated glomerular recovery seen after infusion of AngII during ear-
ly-phase anti-Thy1 glomerulonephritis [5, 6] . Consistently, glomerular endothelial cell pro-
liferation after anti-Thy1 glomerulonephritis was inhibited with AngII receptor blockade 
[7] . The attenuated glomerular injury with AngII infusion is in apparent contrast with pre-
vious studies in the anti-Thy1 model suggesting attenuation of renal damage by treatment 
with ACE-I or AngII receptor blocker [7-13] . The latter studies reported improvement 
mainly in terms of reduced proteinuria and early reduction of matrix expansion. We hy-
pothesized that the suppression of AngII formation would not improve late-stage renal 
function in anti-Thy1 glomerulonephritis despite possible antiproteinuric effects. There-
fore, we evaluated the effect of ACE-I treatment using perindopril on proteinuria, creatinine 
clearance, induction of glomerular damage and renal histological recovery in nephritic rats. 
To dissociate direct effects of ACE-I treatment from those on blood pressure reduction, 
we also included nephritic rats treated with the dihydropyridine calcium-antagonist amlo-
dipine (Ca-A) in our study. </p>

<p>Animals and Methods </p>

<p>Animals 
Male 11-week-old Brown Norway/RijHsd (BN) rats weighing 280-300 g (Harlan, Horst, 
The Netherlands) housed in a 12/12 h light/dark cycle and receiving food and acidified water 
ad libitum were used for all experiments. The Animal Ethics Committee of our institution 
approved all protocols. </p>

<p>Experimental Design 
Anti-rat Thy1.1 monoclonal antibody (ER4, 1 mg/kg body weight) was injected intrave-
nously on day 0 in all rats. Rats treated with ACE-I perindopril (gift from Servier; 33 mg/l in 
the drinking water, resulting in an average dose of 2.8 mg/kg body weight/day; n = 12) since 
day 3 before anti-Thy1 injection were compared to controls (n = 14) and rats treated with 
Ca-A (gift from Servier; 150 mg/l in the drinking water, resulting in an average dose of 13 
mg/kg body weight/day; n = 6). Rats were placed in metabolic cages with free access to food </p>



<p>Nephron Extra 2012;2:9-16 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000335750 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Westerweel et al.: ACE Inhibition in Anti-Thy1 Glomerulonephritis </p>

<p>www.karger.com/nne </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel 
Published online: January 26, 2012 </p>

<p>and water at several time points to collect 24-hour urine samples. Systolic blood pressure was 
measured in conscious rats by tail-cuff sphygmomanometry (IITC, San Diego, Calif., USA). 
Rats were sacrificed at day 7 (n = 4 control vs. n = 6 ACE-I-treated animals) and day 28 (n = 
10 control vs. n = 6 ACE-I-treated and n = 6 Ca-A-treated animals), and kidneys were excised 
after perfusion at 120 mm Hg with ice-cold 0.9% saline. Kidney specimens were transverse-
ly cut in 1-mm slices, fixed in 4% buffered formaldehyde and embedded in paraffin. </p>

<p>Measurements of Renal Function Parameters 
Urinary protein concentration was determined by Bio-Rad Protein assay (Bio-Rad Lab-
oratories GmbH, München, Germany) in 24-hour urine samples. Plasma and urinary cre-
atinine levels were determined colorimetrically (Sigma Diagnostics Inc., St. Louis, Mo., 
USA). The creatinine clearance, calculated by the standard formula, was used as an estimate 
of glomerular filtration rate (GFR). </p>

<p>Renal Histology 
Renal morphology was evaluated using Periodic Acid Schiff (PAS)-stained 5-m paraf-
fin sections, based on at least 50 glomeruli per kidney section. The percentage of glomeruli 
containing microaneurysms was counted in sections from rats terminated at day 7. The Glo-
merular Sclerosis Index (GSI) was calculated as previously described [14] in sections from 
rats terminated at day 28. For the GSI, glomeruli were scored based on the percentage of the 
glomerular area that was sclerotic (normal = 0, ! 25% = 1, 25-50% = 2, 50-75% = 3, 75-
100% = 4). Renal artery wall thickness of the cortical intrarenal arteries in PAS-stained kid-
ney sections was measured using <rs id="software-0" type="software">AnalySIS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Soft Imaging Systems</rs>, Münster, 
Germany), based on lamina externa and interna diameters and using the average of at least 
five vessels per kidney section. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis 
All values are expressed as mean 8 SEM. Data were analyzed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 11.0</rs> 
software. Differences between groups were analyzed using the Student t test, and one-or 
two-way ANOVA with Kruskal-Wallis post-hoc test if appropriate. A p value ! 0.05 was con-
sidered significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>ACE-I and Ca-A Lowered Systolic Blood Pressure 
Baseline systolic blood pressure was 112 8 3 mm Hg. At the time of anti-Thy1 injection, 
systolic blood pressure was reduced by 19 8 2 mm Hg in ACE-I-treated rats (p ! 0.001) and 
by 22 8 3 mm Hg in Ca-A-treated rats (p = 0.001), and this level of blood pressure reduction 
was sustained. The difference in blood pressure reduction for Ca-A and ACE-I treatment was 
not significant. </p>

<p>ACE-I, but Not Ca-A, Inhibited the Development of Proteinuria after Anti-Thy1 
Injection 
In control rats, induction of glomerulonephritis caused an increase in urinary protein 
excretion peaking at day 7 ( fig. 1 ). ACE-I treatment significantly reduced the development of 
proteinuria and resulted in normalization of proteinuria at day 14 when proteinuria was still 
high in controls (p ! 0.01 for treatment interaction in two-way ANOVA for time and treat-
ment interaction). Ca-A treatment did not affect the development of proteinuria ( fig. 1 ). </p>



<p>Nephron Extra 2012;2:9-16 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000335750 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Westerweel et al.: ACE Inhibition in Anti-Thy1 Glomerulonephritis </p>

<p>www.karger.com/nne </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel 
Published online: January 26, 2012 </p>

<p>ACE-I Did Not Attenuate the Reduction of Creatinine Clearance after Anti-Thy1 
Glomerulonephritis 
Creatinine clearance was reduced at day 28 in all nephritic rats ( table 1 ). In perindopril-
treated animals, creatinine clearance was not beneficially affected. </p>

<p>ACE-I Does Not Prevent Microaneurysm Formation in Early-Phase Anti-Thy1 
Glomerulonephritis 
Consistent with previous reports [2, 15, 16] , injection of anti-Thy1 caused acute mesan-
giolysis, capillary ballooning and microaneurysm formation at day 7 ( fig. 2 ). ACE-I treat-
ment did not affect the percentage of microaneurysmatic glomeruli (40 8 4 vs. 41 8 5% in 
controls; p = not significant) at that time point. At day 28, microaneurysms were only spo-
radically observed in sections from both treated and untreated nephritic animals. </p>

<p>ACE-I Treatment Aggravated Adverse Fibrotic Remodelling during Late-Stage Anti-Thy1 
Glomerulonephritis 
At day 28, nearly all microaneurysms had resolved, but around one third of glomeruli 
showed segmental glomerular sclerosis ( fig. 2 ). At day 28, ACE-I-treated animals had a 
slightly higher average glomerulosclerosis score than controls, which was statistically sig-
nificant (GSI 0.49 8 0.07 vs. 0.36 8 0.03, p ! 0.05; fig. 3 ). To further evaluate possible adverse 
fibrotic remodeling, we assessed intrarenal intima-media thickness as this was pathologi-
cally increased with ACE inhibition in experimental kidney transplantation [17] . Indeed also 
in our model, ACE-I treatment was associated with signs of renal artery vasculopathy, with </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Development of proteinuria over the course 
of anti-Thy1 glomerulonephritis. Induction of anti-
Thy1 glomerulonephritis caused a transient rise in 
proteinuria in untreated rats (CON aThy1), which 
was not affected by treatment with calcium-antag-
onist amlodipine (Ca-A aThy1), but nearly fully 
prevented by treatment with the ACE inhibitor per-
indopril (ACE-I aThy1). * p ! 0.05 compared to un-
treated controls. </p>

<p>Table 1. B iochemical parameters of renal function </p>

<p>Non-nephritic 
controls </p>

<p>aThy-1-nephritic 
controls </p>

<p>aThy-1-nephritic + 
perindopril </p>

<p>aThy-1-nephritic + 
amlodipine </p>

<p>day 7 
day 28 
day 7 
day 28 
day 7 
day 28 </p>

<p>Plasma urea, mM 
8 .881.0 
10.480.9 
8.980.4 
16.580.8* , # 17.081.6* , # 
8.580.4 
7.880.4 
Creatinine clearance 
ml/min/kg BW </p>

<p>7.581.2 
7.981.7 
4.780.4* 
5.980.4 
4.180.5* 
9.680.7 
5.580.5 </p>

<p>Proteinuria, mg/24 h 
13.180.5 
68.5810.7* 20.683.2* 24.383.2* , # 11.081.1* , # 
58.185.6* 15.580.9 </p>

<p>* p &lt; 0.05 compared to non-nephritic controls; # p &lt; 0.05 compared to nephritic controls at the corresponding time point. </p>



<p>Nephron Extra 2012;2:9-16 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000335750 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Westerweel et al.: ACE Inhibition in Anti-Thy1 Glomerulonephritis </p>

<p>www.karger.com/nne </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel 
Published online: January 26, 2012 </p>

<p>a significantly increased wall thickness of the cortical arteries at day 28 (intima-media sur-
face area 4,046 8 419 vs. 2,689 8 195 m 2 , p ! 0.05; fig. 4 ). GSI in Ca-A-treated animals 
did not differ from controls (0.39 8 0.06 vs. 0.36 8 0.03, p = not significant; fig. 3 ), and cor-
tical artery wall thickness was unchanged in untreated controls and Ca-A-treated animals at 
day 28 ( fig. 4 ). </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Morphological features of the anti-Thy1 glomerulonephritis model. Injection of anti-Thy1 in un-
treated rats causes acute mesangiolysis and capillary ballooning, which is visible on PAS-stained sections 
at day 7 as microaneurysms have formed. At day 28, nearly all microaneurysms are resolved, but many 
glomeruli show segmental glomerular sclerosis. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Glomerulosclerosis dur-
ing late-phase anti-Thy1 glomer-
ulonephritis. In kidney sections 
of rats with late-phase anti-Thy1 
glomerulonephritis, a propor-
tion of glomeruli showed signs 
of segmental glomerulosclerosis, 
which was histologically quanti-
fied using the GSI (see Animals 
and Methods section for specifi-
cation of the scoring procedure). 
The GSI was higher in ACE in-
hibitor perindopril-treated ani-
mals (ACE-I aThy1) than in un-
treated controls (CON aThy1). 
Treatment with calcium-antago-
nist amlodipine (Ca-A aThy1) 
did not affect the development of 
glomerulosclerosis. * p ! 0.05 
compared to untreated controls. </p>



<p>Nephron Extra 2012;2:9-16 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000335750 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Westerweel et al.: ACE Inhibition in Anti-Thy1 Glomerulonephritis </p>

<p>www.karger.com/nne </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel 
Published online: January 26, 2012 </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>A single intravenous injection of anti-Thy1 antibody is known to cause reversible glo-
merulonephritis characterized by marked transient proteinuria and multiple stages of struc-
tural glomerular pathology. Here, we show that ACE-I treatment during anti-Thy1 glomeru-
lonephritis effectively reduces the development of proteinuria, but does not protect against 
the induction of glomerular damage or decline in renal function. ACE-I treatment could not 
prevent glomerular microaneurysm formation and was even associated with a modest but 
statistically significant accentuation of glomerulosclerosis and vasculopathic thickening of 
intrarenal vessels. Our study indicates that the multiple pathophysiological components dur-
ing the course of anti-Thy1 glomerulonephritis are differentially affected by the suppression 
of AngII formation. 
We show a potent protective effect of ACE inhibition on the proteinuria occurring dur-
ing the development of glomerular damage. Several previous studies have similarly shown a 
reduction in proteinuria during anti-Thy1 glomerulonephritis by treatment with ACE-I or 
AngII receptor blockers [7-13] . Consistently, proteinuria tended to stay elevated for a longer 
period of time when rats with anti-Thy1 glomerulonephritis received AngII infusion [6] . Pro-
teinuria is a practical and powerful indicator of the course of renal disease [18] . Preventing 
or reducing proteinuria by ACE-I is well-established and likely to make a major contribution 
to the beneficial effects of ACE-I on the course of renal disease. Proteinuria is thought to not 
only reflect renal damage, but also play a pathophysiological role in the progression of renal 
damage itself [19] . Indeed, in the aforementioned studies of ACE inhibition in anti-Thy1 glo-
merulonephritis, early matrix remodelling was inhibited. In our study, glomerular microan-
eurysm formation was not reduced by ACE inhibition. As glomerular microaneurysm for-
mation reflects the degree of endothelial damage, the antiproteinuric effects do not appear 
to be attributable to endothelial protection but may be mediated through another mecha-
nism. Such a specific antiproteinuric effect of ACE-I treatment may be explained by direct 
effects on the selective properties of the glomerular membrane size [20] independent of the 
effects on the glomerulonephritic disease process. 
Our study shows that in anti-Thy1 glomerulonephritis, inhibition of AngII formation 
promoted late-stage adverse sclerotic remodelling in both the glomerulus and intrarenal vas-
culature. This is in line with previous reports indicating that AngII infusion accelerated glo-
merular endothelial recovery [6] , reduced influx of inflammatory cells, reduced mesangial </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Renal artery vessel wall thickness. Com-
pared to untreated rats (CON aThy1), treatment 
with ACE inhibitor perindopril (ACE-I aThy1) was 
associated with vasculopathic thickening of the 
blood vessels in the renal cortex. Calcium-antago-
nist amlodipine (Ca-A aThy1) did not affect intra-
renal vessel morphology. * p ! 0.05 compared to 
untreated controls at the equal time point. </p>



<p>Nephron Extra 2012;2:9-16 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000335750 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Westerweel et al.: ACE Inhibition in Anti-Thy1 Glomerulonephritis </p>

<p>www.karger.com/nne </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel 
Published online: January 26, 2012 </p>

<p>proliferation, and limited matrix production [5] . Similar deterioration of renal function and 
aggravated graft vasculopathy was observed in association with ACE-I treatment in the Fish-
er-to-Lewis experimental rat model of chronic renal transplant failure, even though the de-
velopment of proteinuria and glomerulosclerosis was prevented [17] . Furthermore, in both 
healthy and adriamycin-induced proteinuric rats on a low-sodium diet, ACE-I treatment 
caused interstitial renal damage and vasculopathic hypertrophy of intrarenal arteries [21] . 
We did not observe any effect of dihydropyridine Ca-A treatment on the course of anti-
Thy1 nephritis. Unlike ACE-I, Ca-A treatment did not adversely affect the disease course, 
despite giving comparable blood pressure reduction. Thus, the adverse effects observed with 
ACE-I treatment appear to be independent of the systemic blood pressure-reducing action. 
Nevertheless, we cannot exclude a role for altered renal blood flow and filtration pressure, 
which are affected differently by dihydropyridine Ca-A and ACE-I [22] . 
In conclusion, our study suggests that ACE inhibition is effective in reducing protein-
uria, but does not beneficially affect other pathological components involved in anti-Thy1 
glomerulonephritis. This is in line with the concept that AngII may have specific renopro-
tective effects [23, 24] . Also, these results suggest that in specific conditions, proteinuria may 
thus not be a reliable indicator of the course of renal disease treated with ACE inhibitors. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Dutch Kidney Foundation (grant PC127) and the Neth-
erlands Organization for Scientific Research (NWO VENI grant 016.036.041 and VIDI grant 
917.96.359). 
The technical assistance of Paula Martens, Ria de Winter, and Nel Willekes is gratefully 
acknowledged. </p>





<p>Nephron Extra 2012;2:9-16 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000335750 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Westerweel et al.: ACE Inhibition in Anti-Thy1 Glomerulonephritis </p>

<p>www.karger.com/nne </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel 
Published online: January 26, 2012 </p>



</text></tei>