<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3674238" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Establishment of cell polarity-or symmetry breaking-relies on local accumulation of polarity 
regulators. Although simple positive feedback is sufficient to drive symmetry breaking, it is 
highly sensitive to stochastic fluctuations typical for living cells. Here, by integrating 
mathematical modelling with quantitative experimental validations, we show that in the 
yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae a combination of actin-and guanine nucleotide dissociation 
inhibitor-dependent recycling of the central polarity regulator Cdc42 is needed to establish 
robust cell polarity at a single site during yeast budding. The guanine nucleotide dissociation 
inhibitor pathway consistently generates a single-polarization site, but requires Cdc42 to 
cycle rapidly between its active and inactive form, and is therefore sensitive to perturbations 
of the GTPase cycle. Conversely, actin-mediated recycling of Cdc42 induces robust symmetry 
breaking but cannot restrict polarization to a single site. Our results demonstrate how cells 
optimize symmetry breaking through coupling between multiple feedback loops. </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>he Rho-type GTPase Cdc42 is a central regulator of cell 
polarity in animal and fungal cells 1,2 . At the G1-S 
transition in the cell cycle of Saccharomyces cerevisiae, 
Cdc42 becomes concentrated in a cortical cap that defines the 
future bud site 3,4 . Cdc42 binds to various effectors that control 
essential morphogenetic processes, such as polarized membrane 
transport 5 , assembly of a septin ring 6 and fusion of exocytic 
vesicles with the plasma membrane 7,8 . To fulfill its functions, 
Cdc42 must constantly cycle between GTP-bound/active and 
GDP-bound/inactive states. In budding yeast activation of Cdc42 
is controlled by a single guanine nucleotide exchange factor 
(GEF), Cdc24 and Cdc42 hydrolytic activity is promoted by four 
GTPase-activating proteins (GAPs), Bem2, Bem3, Rga1 and Rga2 
(ref. 7). In addition, Cdc42 is extracted from membranes by a 
single Rho-guanine nucleotide dissociation inhibitor (GDI), Rdi1 
(refs 9,10). 
Concentration of Cdc42 at the polarization site in yeast cells 
can occur via feedback amplification of stochastic fluctua-
tions 11,12 and either requires focused, actin-mediated transport 
of vesicle-bound Cdc42 (refs 13,14) or Bem1-mediated 
recruitment of soluble Cdc42 (refs 14-17). Both pathways drive 
polarization through constant recycling of Cdc42 (refs 14,17). 
Polarized transport of Cdc42-bearing vesicles has been shown 
to underlie spontaneous polarization of constitutively active and 
membrane-restricted Cdc42 via a simple positive feedback 
mechanism 13 . In addition, polarization of wild-type Cdc42 
depends on actin-based secretion, particularly in the absence of 
Bem1 (ref. 14) or Rdi1 (ref. 17). However, although a role for 
membrane transport in polarity establishment has been widely 
established 18,19 , its relevance for polarization of wild-type yeast 
cells is still controversial 11,16,20-22 . A negative role for actin in cell 
polarization has even been proposed based on endocytosis of 
polarity regulators 20,23 or dilution of Cdc42 in the cap region 24,25 . 
Although such mechanisms provide explanations for travelling 
waves 23 or oscillating polarization patches 24 , they cannot account 
for the positive role of actin during the actual process of 
symmetry breaking-both in the presence and absence of Bem1-
driven feedback 13,14 . 
A second polarization mechanism has been proposed to rely 
on activation of Cdc42 through a Bem1-Cdc24-Cla4 com-
plex 15,16,26,27 and on extraction of Cdc42 from membranes by 
Rdi1 (ref. 17). The available experimental evidence has been 
combined in a Turing-type model of yeast polarization 28 . 
However, many details of the proposed reactions remain under 
debate 12,21,29 . Moreover, the precise relationship between actin-
and GDI-dependent mechanisms during establishment of 
polarization in wild-type cells is unclear. 
Here, we built a stochastic model for yeast polarity establish-
ment through actin-and GDI-mediated recycling of Cdc42. We 
established assumptions and parameter values for this model 
through genetic analyses, in vitro reconstitution and live cell 
imaging. Predictions from the model were tested and validated 
experimentally. We demonstrate that the establishment of a stable 
and unique polarization axis requires coordination of two 
pathways. Actin-mediated recycling of Cdc42 is very robust, but 
does not reliably result in formation of a single-polarization site. In 
contrast, GDI-dependent recycling is sensitive to changes in the 
GTPase cycle of Cdc42 but faithfully generates a unique 
polarization site. Our results suggest that correct polarity establish-
ment is achieved through coupling of multiple feedback loops. </p>

<p>Results 
Validation of strains. To build a mechanistic model for yeast 
polarity establishment we sought to firmly establish the connec-
tions between all involved regulators and pathways. Spontaneous </p>

<p>cell polarization has been proposed to occur via amplification of 
stochastic fluctuations through simple positive feedback in the 
presence of low concentrations of reacting molecules 30,31 but this 
model has been recently challenged 24 . In an attempt to resolve 
this issue we varied expression levels of GFP-Cdc42 in control 
and LatB-treated cells with an inducible GAL promoter 30 . We 
indeed found that Cdc42 expression level had no effect on 
polarization efficiency (Supplementary Fig. S1a). 
When we tagged the genomic copy of Cdc42 in haploid cells of 
S288C and W303 backgrounds we confirmed 24 that expression of </p>

<p>30°C 
3 7 °C </p>

<p>ect </p>

<p>End </p>

<p>No tag 
S288C </p>

<p>ect </p>

<p>End </p>

<p>No tag 
W303 </p>

<p>ect </p>

<p>End </p>

<p>No tag 
RWS116 </p>

<p>W303 </p>

<p>MW 
(kDa) 
E n d e c t </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>GM-Cdc42 </p>

<p>GFP-Cdc42 </p>

<p>Cdc42 
25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>N 
o 
t a g </p>

<p>S288C </p>

<p>E n d 
e c t 
N 
o 
t a g </p>

<p>RWS116 </p>

<p>E n d e c t 
N 
o 
t a g </p>

<p>R 
W 
S 1 1 6 
R 
W 
S 1 1 6 
S 2 8 8 C 
W 
3 0 3 </p>

<p>R 
W 
S 1 1 6 
S 2 8 8 C 
W 
3 0 3 </p>

<p>R 
W 
S 1 1 6 
S 2 8 8 C 
W 
3 0 3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Fold change </p>

<p>GFP-Cdc42 ect Cdc42 
GM-Cdc42 </p>

<p>end Cdc42 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Effects of GFP-tagging of Cdc42 on cell growth and 
polarization. (a) Growth of the standard lab strains S288C and W303 
and the arrest-strain RWS116 at different temperatures. Shown are the 
respective control strains (no tag) and strains where Cdc42 has been 
tagged at its endogenous locus (end) or as additional copy integrated in the 
ectopic LEU2 locus (ect). (b) Western blot of different Cdc42 fusion 
proteins in the strains used in (a). Cdc42 was detected with a polyclonal 
serum against Cdc42. A monoclonal antibody against the constitutively 
expressed glyceraldehyde-2-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) was used 
as loading control. Identity of visualized bands is indicated on the right. 
(c) Quantification of Cdc42 expression levels showing fold change 
compared with expression of the endogenous copy in the respective strain 
background. Bars correspond to mean±s.d. from three independent 
experiments. Labels correspond to untagged Cdc42 in strains expressing 
GFP-Cdc42 at the endogenous locus (end Cdc42) or the LEU2 locus (ect 
Cdc42), to GFP tagged Cdc42 at the endogenous locus (GFP-Cdc42) and 
GFP-myc tagged Cdc42 at the LEU2 locus (GM-Cdc42). Strain 
backgrounds are indicated on x axis. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1807 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>GFP-Cdc42 as the only source of Cdc42 leads to impaired growth 
of yeast cells at high temperatures (Fig. 1a). We also tagged Cdc42 
in the strain RWS116, which could be arrested in the cell cycle 
through depletion of the G1 cyclins 14 . The resulting strain 
retained a duplicated version of the untagged Cdc42 expressed to 
half the level of the GFP-Cdc42 fusion (Fig. 1b,c). This strain as 
well as strains expressing GFP-myc-Cdc42 from ectopic 
chromosomal loci (Fig. 1b,c, Supplementary Fig. S1b) exhibited 
no temperature sensitivity (Fig. 1a). Tagging also did not 
affect growth and polarization kinetics, either in the presence 
or absence of actin-dependent transport (Supplementary 
Fig. S1c-f). </p>

<p>Parallel Cdc42 recycling pathways in polarity establishment. 
Overexpressed Cdc42 might be buffered by its GDI, which 
is generally found in a 1:1 complex with its substrates in the 
cytosol 32 . Actin and Rdi1 have been proposed to act in parallel 
during polarity maintenance 17 . To systematically investigate the 
connection between Rdi1-and actin-mediated recycling of Cdc42, 
we analysed genetic interactions of Cdc42 and its regulators with 
synthetic genetic arrays 33 . Genetic lesions in all examined 
components had a negative impact on processes linked to actin 
functions (Fig. 2a, Supplementary Table S1). In contrast, few 
physical interactions of Cdc42 regulators with actin-associated </p>

<p>proteins have been reported (Fig. 2a, Supplementary Table S2). 
These results indicate that, in addition to the role of Cdc42 in 
formation and polarization of actin structures, Cdc42 signalling 
and actin-mediated transport processes also act in parallel during 
essential cellular processes. 
Rdi1 exhibited interactions with several components involved 
in endocytic recycling (Fig. 2a, Supplementary Table S1), 
consistent with a role in actin-independent recycling of Cdc42 
during polarity establishment. To test this, we studied 
synchronized yeast cells expressing GFP-Cdc42 fusions 
(Supplementary Fig. S1b-d), and monitored Cdc42 cap 
formation 14 . As expected from a defect in extraction of 
membrane-bound Cdc42, Drdi1 cells accumulated Cdc42 on 
membranes (Fig. 2b). Nevertheless, polarization kinetics were 
unaffected in Drdi1 cells and in cells expressing Cdc42 R66E , a 
mutant unable to interact with the GDI 34 (Fig. 2b). However, 
depolymerization of actin with latrunculin B (LatB), which has 
moderate effects on control cells 14 (Fig. 2c), blocked polarization 
in Drdi1 and Cdc42 R66E -expressing cells (Fig. 2c). A similar 
synergistic effect was observed when exocytosis was blocked using 
a temperature-sensitive allele of MYO2 (myo2-16, Fig. 2d). 
Reduction of endocytosis by deletion of the ESCRTIII component 
VPS27 (ref. 35) resulted in less efficient polarization of Drdi1 cells 
(Fig. 2e). Colocalization of GFP-Cdc42 and FM4-64-stained 
endocytic membranes in Dvps27 cells revealed Cdc42 </p>

<p>5 25 45 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>Polarized (%) </p>

<p>+LatB </p>

<p>Control 
rdi1 
R66E </p>

<p>FM4-64 </p>

<p>GFPCdc42 </p>

<p>Merge 
Polarized (%) </p>

<p>5 25 45 65 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Δvps27 </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>Δvps27 Δrdi1 </p>

<p>R66E </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Δrdi1 </p>

<p>5 
25 
45 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>100 Control </p>

<p>Δrdi1 </p>

<p>R66E </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>Polarized (%) </p>

<p>5 25 45 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>100 myo2-16 </p>

<p>myo2-16 Δrdi1 </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>Polarized (%) </p>

<p>35°C </p>

<p>Early secretion 
Late secretion 
Endocytic recycling </p>

<p>Actin general 
Early secretion 
Late secretion 
Endocytic recycling </p>

<p>Actin general </p>

<p>CDC42 
CDC24 
BEM2 
BEM3 
RGA1 
RGA2 
RDI1 
BEM1 
CLA4 </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>RDI1 </p>

<p>BEM1 
CDC42 </p>

<p>CLA4 </p>

<p>RGA1 </p>

<p>RGA2 </p>

<p>BEM2 </p>

<p>CDC24 </p>

<p>BEM3 </p>

<p>GEF </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>Ot 
her </p>

<p>16 
16 </p>

<p>Physical 
Genetic </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 
c </p>

<p>d 
e </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Polarity establishment through GDI-and actin-mediated recycling of Cdc42. (a) Heat plots of genetic (blue) and physical (red) interactions 
between Cdc42 regulators and proteins involved in actin-related processes. Colour code: number of interactions. Genetic interactions among Cdc42 
regulators are indicated in the lower panel. (b-e) Effects of genetic and pharmacological perturbations on polarization kinetics of Cdc42. Data points 
represent means of three experiments with n ¼ 50 cells each. Error bars indicate mean ± s.d. Continuous lines are sigmoidal fits. Individual plots depict the 
effects of: (b) inhibiting extraction of Cdc42 from the plasma membrane in Drdi1 cells and cells expressing Cdc42 R66E , a mutant that cannot interact 
with the GDI; (c) disruption of actin polymerization (by LatB) in control, Drdi1 and cdc42 R66E cells; (d) inactivation of the temperature-sensitive myo2-16 
allele in control and Drdi1 cells, and (e) deletion of VPS27 in control and Drdi1 cells. Colocalization of Cdc42 and the membrane dye FM4-64 in 
aberrant endosomal compartments of Dvps27 cells is demonstrated in panel e. Scale bar, 4 mm. </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1807 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>accumulation in aberrant endocytic compartments, confirming 
passage of Cdc42 through the endocytic system (Fig. 2e). 
Our results confirm that Rdi1-and actin-based cycling of 
Cdc42 contribute to polarity establishment via distinct and 
parallel mechanisms. We therefore proceeded to design a particle-
based mathematical model of Cdc42 polarization to study the 
interplay between the two pathways. </p>

<p>A stochastic model for polarity establishment. To build an 
experimentally tractable model, we considered the two recycling 
pathways for Cdc42 separately. Recent studies have stressed the 
importance of considering individual vesicle carriers instead of 
simple protein flux 21,25 . However, many mechanistic details of 
actin-based membrane recycling are unknown, rendering detailed 
models highly speculative. Importantly, the proposed dilution 
effect of vesicle delivery on the Cdc42 cap 21 is not supported by 
our experiments, as Cdc42 cap intensities are significantly higher 
in control cells compared with cells, in which actin-mediated 
transport processes are disrupted (Fig. 3a). A recent study has 
also shown the feasibility of polarity establishment if Cdc42 
exhibits non-uniform diffusion 36 . We therefore opted to simulate 
actin-mediated recycling of Cdc42 using a coarse-grained 
approach (Fig. 3b, Supplementary Methods and Supplementary 
Tables S8, 9). We assumed that membrane-bound Cdc42 
molecules are delivered to the plasma membrane from internal 
membranes along actin cables. Sites of enhanced cable nucleation 
are generated at a rate that depends on the amount of active 
Cdc42 at the respective nucleation site. Endocytosis was modelled 
with a constant extraction rate. 
For Rdi1-mediated recycling (Fig. 3c) we assumed a well-mixed 
pool of Cdc42 in the cytosol and diffusion of Cdc42 in the plasma 
membrane with D ¼ 0.036 mm 2 s À 1 (ref. 37). Nucleotide </p>

<p>exchange can occur spontaneously or catalysed by the GEF 
Cdc24 via a bounded positive feedback loop involving the Cdc42 
effector Bem1 (refs 14,15). Such bounded feedback is essential to 
achieve realistic cap shapes (Fig. 4) and corresponds to depletion 
of limiting components involved in Cdc42 recruitment. GTP 
hydrolysis is modelled with a constant rate depending on GAP 
activity. 
It has been shown that GDIs preferentially extract GDP-bound 
Rho GTPases 38,39 . To firmly establish this important aspect in 
our model, we performed in-vitro extraction experiments with 
purified Cdc42 and RhoGDI 39 . We found that the GDI indeed 
extracted GDP-bound Cdc42 around 10 times faster than GTP-
Cdc42 (Fig. 3d). In the presence of catalytic amounts of GAP 
domain, GTP-Cdc42 was extracted at nearly the same rate as 
GDP-Cdc42 (Fig. 3d), indicating that GTP hydrolysis is rate-
limiting for GDI-mediated Cdc42 extraction. This was supported 
by the extremely slow extraction of Cdc42 bound to non-
hydrolyzable GTP analogue (GMPPNP, Fig. 3d). In living yeast 
cells, we confirmed previous reports 14,17 that constitutively active 
Cdc42 (Cdc42 G12V ) is restricted to membranes and the slow 
actin-mediated recycling pathway (Fig. 3e, Supplementary Table 
S9). Hence, we incorporated selective extraction of GDP-Cdc42 
by the GDI into our model. 
Recruitment from the Rdi1-GDP-Cdc42 pool to the membrane 
was assumed to occur at a background rate and via a second 
positive feedback loop that enhances attachment of cytosolic 
Cdc42 to sites of high Cdc42 activity. This feedback represents the 
previously proposed competition between Rab and Rho GEFs and 
the respective GDIs 40-42 . To observe whether such competition 
indeed occurs for Rho GTPases, we investigated the effect of GEF 
activity on the interaction between GDI and mammalian Rac1, 
which is similar in mechanism and kinetics to GDI-Cdc42 
interaction 39 . Exposure to the GEF domain of Dock180 (DHR2C) </p>

<p>G12V </p>

<p>D57Y </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>T/2 (s) </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
D 
5 7 Y 
G 
1 2 V </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Cdc24 </p>

<p>Bem2 </p>

<p>Cdc42 T 
D57Y </p>

<p>D 
T </p>

<p>Cdc24 </p>

<p>Bem2 </p>

<p>G12V </p>

<p>Cdc42 </p>

<p>500 
1,000 
0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>GDP </p>

<p>GTP+GAP </p>

<p>GTP </p>

<p>Time (s) </p>

<p>Intensity (a.u.) </p>

<p>GMPPNP </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Total intensity (a.u.) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>Control 
LatB </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>Membrane </p>

<p>Cytosol </p>

<p>Cdc42-GTP/-GDP 
Actin bundle </p>

<p>T i / D i 
A i </p>

<p>A cyt 
T IM / D IM </p>

<p>f[A i +G({A i })] 
g 
eT i </p>

<p>Cdc42-GTP Cdc42-GDP </p>

<p>T i 
D i </p>

<p>D cyt </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 1 F({T i })+b 2 </p>

<p>c 1 F({T i }) 
d </p>

<p>k D 
k D </p>

<p>c 2 </p>

<p>Cdc42-GTP/-GDP 
on internal membranes 
Free actin 
Cytosolic Cdc42-GDP </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>d 
e </p>

<p>b 
c </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Building a mathematical model of the combined pathways. (a) Comparison of total intensities of GFPCdc42 caps in controls and LatB-treated 
cells. Bars indicate means±s.e.m. n480. ***t-test, Po0.0001. (b,c) Schematic depiction of model reactions for actin-(b) and GDI-mediated (c) recycling 
pathways. See Supplementary Methods and Supplementary Tables S1,S2 for details of reactions and parameters. Non-linear feedback reactions are 
indicated by dashed boxes. (d) Extractability of Cdc42 from hexadecanoylaminofluorescein (HAF)-labelled liposomes loaded with the indicated 
methylanthraniloyl-modified (Mant-) nucleotides. (e) Halftimes (FRAP T/2) for localization of inactive Cdc42 D57Y (n ¼ 16) and constitutively active 
Cdc42 G12V (n ¼ 16). Bars indicate mean±s.e.m. The schematics illustrate changes in the Cdc42 GTPase cycle. Scale bar, 4 mm. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1807 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>and a non-hydrolyzable GTP analogue was sufficient to dissociate 
soluble GDI-Rac1 complexes, allowing free GMPPNP-bound 
Rac1 to bind to liposomes (Supplementary Fig. S2a). Conversely, 
nucleotide exchange by the GEF was strongly reduced in the 
presence of GDI (Supplementary Fig. S2b), consistent with 
competition for binding to the switch II region of the GTPase 40 . 
These results cannot be directly transferred to living yeast cells. 
However, we found that the dominant-negative mutant 
Cdc42 D57Y , which sequesters its GEF 43,44 , could no longer be 
extracted by the GDI and was instead slowly recycled via actin-
mediated transport 14,17 (Fig. 3e). Our results are consistent with 
competition between GEF and GDI for binding of Cdc42-GDP. 
We therefore implemented interference of GEF activity with 
Cdc42-GDI interaction by increasing the rate of Cdc42 
membrane association in regions of high Cdc42 activity 
(equivalent to high GEF concentrations). 
GDI-mediated polarization is of considerable theoretical 
interest 28,30,45 . Our results indicate that GDI-mediated recycling 
of Cdc42 depends on the latter's catalytic cycle, and both GAP 
and GEF need to be regulated to allow rapid shuttling between 
membrane and cytosol. In a previous model, positive feedback in 
Cdc42 activation was based on non-linear recruitment of Cdc24 
to Cdc42-GTP 28,46 . The model predicts slower turnover of Cdc24 
if Cdc42 activity is increased. However, we found that the level of 
GEF expression or actin or Cdc42 activity had no influence on 
Cdc24 turnover at the polarized site (Supplementary Fig. S3b), 
indicating that feedback must be implemented in a different 
manner. Our model assumes linear recruitment of the GEF to </p>

<p>Cdc42-GTP, but instead incorporates two GEF-mediated, and 
experimentally supported, positive feedback loops for activation 
and physical recruitment of Cdc42 (dashed boxes in Fig. 3c), 
respectively. A short comparison of features and limitations in 
various models for yeast cell polarity is shown in Supplementary 
Table S10. A detailed review on this subject has also been 
published recently 47 . </p>

<p>Determination of quantitative model parameters. Having 
established a general structure for the two Cdc42 recycling 
pathways we set out to determine realistic values for the 
parameters involved in their operation. We aimed to base all 
model reactions (Supplementary Table S8) and parameters 
(Supplementary Table S9) on experimental evidence. Several 
parameter values and data concerning the distribution of Cdc42 
between cell compartments were taken from the literature 
(Supplementary Methods). The remaining values were fitted to 
quantitatively reproduce characteristics of control cells and of the 
individual recycling pathways observed in LatB-treated or Drdi1 
cells (Figs 4,5). In all conditions our model was able to recapi-
tulate polarization profiles of Cdc42 with realistic background 
levels and values for cap width and cap height (Fig. 4). In addi-
tion, the polarization response was robust to considerable varia-
tions in the individual parameter values (Supplementary Fig. S4). 
The mobility of Cdc42 is a major element in any dynamic 
polarization model. We performed fluorescence recovery after 
photobleaching (FRAP) experiments to monitor Cdc42 recycling. </p>

<p>Membrane position (μm) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Cdc42 per lattice site </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>e s e s e s 
Width Height Total 
Change relative to 
control </p>

<p>Change relative to 
control </p>

<p>Change relative to 
control </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 </p>

<p>Simulation (s) 
Experiment (e) </p>

<p>LatB </p>

<p>Cdc42 per lattice site </p>

<p>Width </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Height Total </p>

<p>e s e s e s </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 </p>

<p>Δrdi1 </p>

<p>Cdc42 per lattice site </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 
e s e s e s 
Width Height Total </p>

<p>Membrane position (μm) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
20 
0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Membrane position (μm) 
Membrane position (μm) </p>

<p>Membrane position (μm) 
Membrane position (μm) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Fitting cap shape parameters. (a-f) Examples of simulated (a-c) and experimentally determined (d,e) cap profiles in control cells (a,d), 
LatB-treated cells (b,e) and Drdi1 cells (c,f). Dashed lines in images indicate fields of view used for line scans. Scale bar, 4 mm. (g-i) Comparisons 
of cap size (width), average cap intensity (height) and total cap intensity (total, ¼ width Â height) in experiments (e) and simulations (s) for control 
(g), LatB-treated (h) and Drdi1 cells (i). Bars represent means ± s.e.m. of measurements normalized to values for control cells (n480 for control and 
LatB cells, and n ¼ 35 for Drdi1 cells). Note that total intensity values for control and LatB cells correspond to the values used in Fig. 3a. </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1807 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>In agreement with previous measurements 14,17 , recovery of 
Cdc42 fluorescence in control cells occurred with an average 
T/2 of 2.2 s, and was independent of Cdc42 expression level 
(Fig. 5a,b, Supplementary Fig. S3a). Disruption of actin structures 
with LatB led to a slightly increased T/2 of 2.5 s (Fig. 5a,b, 
Supplementary Fig. S3a). This slower recovery was proposed to 
result from greater accumulation of Cdc42 in caps 21 . However, 
Cdc42 cap intensities in LatB-treated cells were significantly </p>

<p>reduced (Fig. 3a), supporting a positive role for actin in Cdc42 
polarization. Perturbation of Cdc42-Rdi1 interactions by deletion 
of RDI1 or the use of the Cdc42 R66E mutant drastically slowed 
recovery to a T/2 of 10 s (Fig. 5b), confirming previous work on 
polarity maintenance 17 . Our results confirm that Rdi1-and actin-
dependent Cdc42 recycling act in parallel during polarity 
establishment and show that the pathways act on different time 
scales. All values for Cdc42 mobility could be accurately 
reproduced in our model (Fig. 5c-e, Supplementary Table S3). </p>

<p>Validating the model. Our model was able to reproduce char-
acteristics of Cdc42 mobility and distribution under various 
experimental conditions. Next, we searched for model predictions 
that we could validate experimentally. One critical aspect of the 
model is the fact that GDI-mediated extraction is restricted to 
GDP-Cdc42, predicting loss of polarization in LatB-treated cells 
at very low rates of hydrolysis (Fig. 6a). The hydrolysis rate in 
control cells, estimated by fitting values for cap height/width and 
FRAP times, was 2.74 s À 1 (grey dashed line Fig. 6a). To check the 
model-based prediction we reduced GTP hydrolysis on Cdc42 by 
deleting BEM2, the GAP with the largest number of genetic 
interactions with actin (Fig. 2a). Cdc42 in Dbem2 cells was able to 
polarize efficiently, albeit with slightly reduced speed (Fig. 6b). 
However, when actin was disrupted most Dbem2 cells could no 
longer polarize (Fig. 6b). Similar results were obtained when 
monitoring Cdc24 or Bem1 (Supplementary Fig. S3d). In our 
simulations polarization occurred over a wide range of hydrolysis 
values, with the control rate being close to the maximum per-
missible before polarization breaks down (Fig. 6a). To study the 
impact of changes in hydrolysis rates on a more quantifiable 
parameter, we tested the effect of deleting BEM2 on Cdc42 
mobility. The model predicted a gradual increase in T/2 upon 
reduction of the GTP hydrolysis rate (Fig. 6c). This slowdown 
was expected to be more pronounced in LatB-treated cells. 
In agreement with this prediction, in Dbem2 cells and the slow-
acting mutant Cdc42 G60A (ref. 48), FRAP halftimes increased to 
6.7 and 6.8 s, respectively, (Fig. 6d, Supplementary Table S3). In 
our model this recovery rate corresponds to a roughly 16-fold 
decrease in the rate of GTP hydrolysis to (grey dashed lines in 
Fig. 6c). At this hydrolysis rate, Cdc42 in LatB-treated cells is 
predicted to recycle with a T/2 of 8.7 s-a value close to the 
measured 9.6 s for LatB-treated Dbem2 cells (Supplementary 
Table S3). Hence, our results indicate that the contribution of 
actin to Cdc42 recycling is increased in Dbem2, likely due to 
reduced extraction of active Cdc42 by its GDI. </p>

<p>The mechanism of formation of multiple polarization sites. In 
all our simulations, the GDI pathway alone was never able to 
generate multiple stable polarization site. However, yeast cells are 
capable of simultaneously polarizing at two or more sites, for 
example, after deletion of BEM2 (ref. 49), deletion or 
overexpression of BEM1 (refs 14,16) or overexpression of 
constitutively active Cdc42 (ref. 13). Interestingly, we noticed 
that 2.3±0.5% (n ¼ 4 Â 100 cells) of Drdi1 cells formed two 
stable polarization sites (Fig. 7a, Supplementary Table S4), a value 
that could be reproduced in our model after fitting the actin-
mediated pathway (Fig. 7b,c, grey dashed line at a ¼ 2.74 s À 1 ). 
Varying parameters in the model generated two testable predic-
tions. First, increased Cdc42 activation should strongly increase 
the percentage of Drdi1 cells that form multiple polarization sites 
(Fig. 7c, blue curve). Second, even cells with a functional GDI 
should form multiple caps if rates of GTP hydrolysis are reduced 
sufficiently (Fig. 7c, black curve). Rdi1-mediated recycling of 
Cdc42 alone was unable to generate multiple stable caps in our 
simulations. The formation of multiple caps at lower hydrolysis </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>T/2 (s) </p>

<p>Δ r d i 1 R 6 6 E 
C o n t r o l L a t B </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0 
10 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time (s) </p>

<p>Intensity (a.u.) </p>

<p>control </p>

<p>Δrdi 
LatB </p>

<p>-1 
0 
25 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>T/2 (s) </p>

<p>Time (s) </p>

<p>400 
410 
420 
0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>e 
s 
Cdc42 intensity (a.u.) </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>400 
410 
420 
0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>400 
440 
480 
0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>FRAP simulation </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 
T/2 (s) </p>

<p>e 
s </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>T/2 (s) </p>

<p>e 
s </p>

<p>Cdc42 intensity (a.u.) </p>

<p>LatB </p>

<p>Cdc42 intensity (a.u.) </p>

<p>Δrdi1 </p>

<p>Time (s) </p>

<p>Time (s) </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Fitting Cdc42 turnover parameters. (a,b) Representative FRAP 
curves (a) and FRAP T/2 values (b) for GFPCdc42 in controls (n ¼ 56), 
Drdi1 cells (n ¼ 20), cells expressing GFPCdc42 R66E (n ¼ 11) and cells 
treated with LatB (n ¼ 24). The arrowhead in (a) indicates the position 
targeted for FRAP. Bars in (b) represent means ± s.e.m. *: t-test, Po0.05. 
Time is indicated in s. Scale bar, 4 mm. (c-e) Simulated (black) FRAP 
curves and exponential fits (red), and comparison of T/2 values for 
simulated (s) and experimental (e, identical to bars in (b)) recovery. Actual 
and simulated FRAP data are shown for control (c), LatB-treated 
(d) and Drdi1 (e) cells. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1807 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>rates can be explained by the reduction or loss of the ability of 
GDI-mediated recycling to restrict cap formation to a single-
polarization site and the enhanced nucleation of actin at higher 
levels of Cdc42-GTP. To increase Cdc42 activity in Drdi1 cells, we 
exploited the known cell cycle-dependent activation of Cdc42 
after the G1/S transition 49,50 . We released Drdi1 cells from G1 
arrest in the presence of LatB to prevent immediate polarization 
and washed the drug out at different times to allow polarization 
with varying initial Cdc42 activity (Supplementary Fig. S5a). As 
predicted, the number of cells with two polarization sites 
increased from 2.3-13% and 23% with increasing duration of 
drug treatment and hence increasing level of Cdc42 activity 
(Fig. 7d, Supplementary Table S4). Next, we used Dbem2 cells to 
increase Cdc42 activity in the presence of Rdi1. We found that 
similar to a previous report 49 , 8.7% of cells formed two buds 
(Fig. 7e), and this was independent of the GFP tag, strain 
background or Cdc42 expression level (Supplementary Fig. S5, 
Supplementary Table S4). We further increased Cdc42 activity by 
overexpressing Cdc24 (Supplementary Fig. S5d) or expressing a 
Cdc42 mutant with high intrinsic GDP release rate 
(Cdc42 F28L (ref. 51)). Neither treatment induced formation of 
double buds in control cells (Fig. 7e, Supplementary S5c). 
However, in Dbem2 strains the number of cells forming 
multiple polarization sites increased significantly (Fig. 7e, 
Supplementary S5c). Our results indicate that actin-mediated 
recycling of Cdc42 is prone to creating multiple polarization sites, 
and that this effect is sensitive to the level of Cdc42 activity. </p>

<p>Moreover, our results show that perturbation of GDI-mediated 
polarization can induce formation of multiple buds in otherwise 
wild-type cells. 
Although formation of two polarization sites in a small 
percentage of cells in a population might, at first sight, seem 
tolerable, even slight effects on cell division could translate into a 
strong evolutionary disadvantage. Indeed, we found that the 
formation of multiple buds directly correlated with an increased 
number of mis-segregated nuclei (Fig. 8a) and this effect was 
dependent on increased activity of Cdc42 (Fig. 8b). On average, 
more than 20% of cells with double buds also exhibited defects in 
nuclear segregation (Figs 8b,7e). Formation of multiple buds 
therefore likely has direct impact on cell survival. </p>

<p>Discussion 
We have shown that yeast cells can establish polarity by localizing 
the central polarity regulator Cdc42 through a combination of 
two recycling pathways with distinct mechanistic features. GDI-
dependent recycling of Cdc42 is fast and coupled to the GTPase 
cycle of Cdc42. Symmetry breaking in this pathway occurs via a 
combination of positive feedback loops for activation and 
recruitment of Cdc42, is characterized by efficient formation of 
a unique polarization axis, but is sensitive to perturbations in the 
GTPase cycle of Cdc42. In contrast, actin-mediated recycling of 
Cdc42 is slower and depends solely on Cdc42 activity 13 . The use 
of actin cables for delivery of Cdc42 to the plasma membrane </p>

<p>5 
2 5 
4 5 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>Polarized (%) </p>

<p>Δbem2 </p>

<p>Δbem2 
+LatB </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>LatB </p>

<p>Δbem2 </p>

<p>G60A </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>T/2 (s) </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
G 
6 0 A Δ b e m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Cdc24 </p>

<p>Bem2 </p>

<p>Cdc42 </p>

<p>D 
T </p>

<p>G60A </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Cdc24 </p>

<p>Bem2 </p>

<p>Cdc42 T </p>

<p>Δbem2 </p>

<p>Hydrolysis rate a (1 s -1 ) </p>

<p>T/2 (s) </p>

<p>Polarized (%) </p>

<p>Hydrolysis rate a (1 s -1 ) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 . 0 1 
0 . 0 5 
0 . 0 2 
0 . 1 
0 . 2 
0 . 5 </p>

<p>1 
2 
5 
1 0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0.01 0.02 
0.05 0.1 0.2 
0.5 
1 
2 </p>

<p>Δbem2 
Control </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Control LatB Δrdi1 </p>

<p>Control 
LatB 
rdi1 </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>c 
d </p>

<p>Figure 6 | Effects of GTP hydrolysis on polarization efficiency and Cdc42 dynamics. (a) Predicted dependence of polarization efficiencies in control, 
LatB-treated and Drdi1 cells on the rate of GTP hydrolysis. The hydrolysis rate for control cells (a ¼ 2.74 s À 1 ) was estimated by fitting model parameters 
(Figs 4,5), and is indicated by the vertical dashed grey line. (b) Polarization efficiency of Cdc42 in control and Dbem2 cells in the presence or absence of 
LatB. Data points represent means of three experiments with 50 cells each. Error bars indicate s.d. The lines are sigmoidal fits. (c) Plot of simulated 
Cdc42 FRAP T/2 (mean values from 400 runs/data point) against rate of GTP hydrolysis. Fitted and estimated hydrolysis rates in control and Dbem2 cells 
are indicated as vertical dashed grey lines. T/2 values measured in Dbem2 cells without (6.8 s; n ¼ 20) and with LatB (9.6 s, n ¼ 12) are indicated as 
horizontal dashed grey lines. (d) FRAP T/2 and localization of Cdc42 in Dbem2 cells and in cells expressing Cdc42 G60A (n ¼ 11), a mutant with a lower 
GTPase activity. Bars represent means±s.e.m. Schematics illustrate changes in the Cdc42 GTPase cycle. Scale bar, 4 mm. </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1807 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>leads to formation of very stable polarization sites. However, this 
stability comes with a significant risk of stochastically generating 
multiple stable polarization sites-an effect that becomes 
especially prominent if Cdc42 activity is increased. By 
combining the two recycling pathways, yeast cells ensure 
reliable establishment of a unique polarity axis. 
To quantitatively analyse the interplay between Cdc42 
recycling pathways, we built a particle-based mechanistic model 
for polarity establishment and performed extensive stochastic 
simulations. We kept the model complexity at a level that 
was appropriately supported by experimental evidence. We 
used measurements from a variety of quantitative in vivo and 
in vitro experiments to validate and constrain assumptions 
and parameters. This integrated approach allowed us to 
make detailed predictions concerning polarization efficiency, 
protein localization kinetics and number of polarization sites, 
which were confirmed with remarkable accuracy by our 
experimental data. </p>

<p>Two key features in our model should be emphasized. First, we 
found that polarity establishment in yeast did not sensitively 
depend on the quantity of Cdc42 in the cell. This was also 
observed in our simulations, where a 10-fold increase in Cdc42 
concentration failed to prevent polarization (N(Cdc42) ¼ 3,000-
30,000 yield 100% polarization). These findings contradict a 
recent study, in which stochastic polarization of Cdc42 was 
proposed to depend critically on low expression levels 30 . Instead, 
we find that polarization depends on the level of Cdc42 
activity. Second, because of separate positive feedback in Cdc42 
activation (Cdc42 GTP -GEF-Bem1-Cla4 interactions) and Cdc42 
recruitment (GEF-GDI competition), our model does not depend 
on non-linear recruitment of the GEF, which was required for 
polarization in a previous model 28 and was not supported by our 
experiments. 
Our results indicate that yeast cells did not simply evolve two 
redundant polarization pathways to safeguard an essential process 
against random error. Instead they combine positive features of </p>

<p>Δbem2 
Control 
Control Δbem2 
GFPCdc42 
GFPCdc42+24OE </p>

<p>Control Δbem2 </p>

<p>GFPCdc42F28L </p>

<p>Cdc24 </p>

<p>Bem2 </p>

<p>Cdc42 T </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>Double buds (%) </p>

<p>LatB -a b 
-a b 
-a b -a b -a b -a b </p>

<p>Δbem2 24OE </p>

<p>Δbem2 F28L </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Cdc24 </p>

<p>Bem2 </p>

<p>Cdc42 T </p>

<p>F28L </p>

<p>Δrdi1 </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Cdc42 density (a.u.) </p>

<p>Membrane position (μm) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Double buds (%) </p>

<p>Δrdi1 </p>

<p>-
a 
b 
LatB 
Hydrolysis rate a (1/s) 
Double buds (%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>Control 
Δrdi1 </p>

<p>0.02 0.05 0.1 0.2 0.5 1 
2 
5 10 </p>

<p>Cdc24 </p>

<p>Bem2 </p>

<p>Cdc42 T </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Figure 7 | Formation of multiple polarization sites. (a) Examples of simultaneous formation of two Cdc42 caps (arrows) and buds in Drdi1 cells. Scale bar, 
4 mm. (b) Intensity profile illustrating formation of two caps in a simulated Drdi1 cell. (c) Predicted effects of varying the rate of GTP hydrolysis on formation 
of multiple polarization sites in simulations of control and Drdi1 cells. Fitted and estimated hydrolysis rates in control and Dbem2 cells are indicated as 
vertical dashed grey lines. Percentage of double buds observed in Dbem2 cells after washing LatB out (25%, n ¼ 300) and in Drdi1 cells (2.3%, n ¼ 400) are 
indicated as horizontal dashed grey lines. See also Supplementary Table S7. (d) Effect of washout of LatB on the percentage of Drdi1 cells with two buds. 
Cells were treated with LatB for 20 min (a) or 40 min (b) before washout of the drug or without treatment ( À ). See Supplementary Methods for 
experimental details. (e) Effect of Cdc42 activity level on the formation of double buds in control and Dbem2 cells. Cells expressing GFPCdc42, GFPCdc42 
and Cdc24RFP or GFPCdc42 F28L (a mutant with fast intrinsic GDP exchange) were treated with LatB as in (d). Examples of double cap formation in Dbem2 
cells expressing either GFPCdc42 or GFPCdc42 F28L are shown on the right. Bars represent means ± s.e.m. for three experiments with 100 cells each. 
Schematics illustrate changes in the Cdc42 GTPase cycle. Scale bar, 4 mm. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1807 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>both pathways to simultaneously achieve reliability and spatial 
precision in cell polarization. Such an optimized interplay of 
pathways requires precise selection of parameter values. Indeed, 
our results suggest that the GTPase cycle of Cdc42 has a central 
role in coordinating pathways underlying polarity establishment. 
In particular, the Cdc42 hydrolysis rate is restricted to a rather 
narrow range between roughly 1 and 3 s. Faster rates lead to a loss 
of polarization due to insufficient amounts of active Cdc42 in the 
cell (Fig. 6a), although slower hydrolysis leads to formation of 
multiple buds (Fig. 7c). The latter effect is a result of a reduced 
recycling speed and hence smaller contribution for the GDI 
pathway (Fig. 6c) and a simultaneous failure of the actin pathway 
to focus polarization to a single site if Cdc42 activity is increased 
(Fig. 7c). GDI recycling therefore needs to be faster than the actin 
pathway to ensure polarization at a single site and in our 
simulations Cdc42 in control cells seems to indeed hydrolyse 
GTP with nearly maximal possible speed. At the other extreme, if 
the GDI pathway is deleted, cells become very prone to form 
multiple caps (Fig. 7c). 
Our results provide a mechanistic link between the fast GTPase 
cycle and GDI-mediated membrane recycling of Rho GTPases. 
Similar interactions have also been reported for small GTPases of 
the Rab family 52 . The mechanisms we identified for localization 
of Cdc42 might therefore also be applicable for other processes of 
spatial cellular organization. 
Our proposed model was capable of reproducing all our 
experimental results and made several accurate and quantitative 
predictions. However, there are still many open questions 
concerning the biophysical and biochemical basis for cell 
polarization. For example, it has recently been demonstrated that 
lipid composition at the polarized site, in particular negatively 
charged phospholipids, influence the association of Cdc42 with 
the plasma membrane and hence impact on cell polarity 53,54 . 
Furthermore, although we assumed cell cycle-dependent 
activation of Cdc24 and inactivation of Bem2 in the LatB 
washout experiments (Fig. 7, Supplementary Fig. S5), the detailed 
biochemistry of these regulatory processes is not fully understood 
and they were not included in the mathematical model. Finally, 
we did not consider potential regulation of GDI-Cdc42 
interaction or GDI-membrane interaction by phosphorylation 55 . 
All these additional aspects provide ample scope for future 
improvements in both modelling and mechanistic understanding 
of cell polarization. As nicely summarized in a recent review, the </p>

<p>value of a mathematical model should be judged 'not by how 
complex and detailed it is, but by what could be learned from 
it' 47 . Our current model consequently incorporates the minimum 
degree of complexity compatible with generation of meaningful 
forecasts, and was able to reflect and predict basic properties of 
cellular organization that will hopefully help to rationalize a 
variety of different biological processes. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Cell culture and plasmids. All strains are derived from RWS116, in which only 
one G1 cyclin, CLN2, is expressed under the control of a methionine repressible 
promoter. Unless otherwise stated, cells were grown at RT in SC-Met medium 
containing 2% glucose. Cells were arrested in G1 by addition of 3 mM methionine 
for 4 h and released again by washing twice and resuspension in methionine-free 
medium. To verify strain growth, three-fold serial dilutions of an equal amount of 
logarithmically growing cells were spotted as triplicate onto Sc-Met plates and 
incubated at indicated temperatures for 2 days. Standard genomic manipulation 
procedures 56 were used for GFP integrations or gene deletions. Site-directed 
mutagenesis was performed as described 57 . Strains, plasmids and primers are listed 
in Supplementary Tables S8-S10, respectively. </p>

<p>Immunoblot analyses. Total protein extracts of 1.4 Â 10 7 cells were boiled in 
SDS-sample buffer and analysed by SDS-PAGE, transferred to nitrocellulose 
membrane and probed with a polyclonal Cdc42 serum (1:500; sc-6793; Santa 
Cruz Biotechnology) or with a monoclonal glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate 
dehydrogenase antibody (1:1500; ab 125247, Abcam). Immunoblots were 
visualized using a Fuji-Las3000 imager. Quantification of bands was performed 
in ImageJ. </p>

<p>Interaction screen. We used the following set of query proteins: Cdc42, Cdc24, 
Bem2, Bem3, Rga1 and Rga2, Rdi1, Bem1 and Cla4. Physical and genetic inter-
action partners were collected from public databases (BioGRID 58 , MPACT 59 ). 
Physical interactions included data from affinity purification, co-crystallization, 
FRET, PCA, protein-peptide interaction, reconstituted complexes and two-hybrid. 
Genetic interactions represented synthetic growth defects, haploinsufficiencies and 
synthetic lethality. We only considered negative interactions from synthetic genetic 
array screens. Interaction partners involved in actin-related processes were grouped 
in four categories: actin general (actin patches or cables), early secretion (ER-to-
Golgi transport), late secretion (Golgi-to-plasma membrane transport) and 
endocytic recycling. All identified interactions are listed in Supplementary Tables 
S1,S2. For each query the number of interactions with members of each category 
were extracted. The number of unique interactions in each functional group served 
as a measure of the overall strength of interaction with that group and was colour-
coded in a heat map (see Fig. 1a). </p>

<p>Microscopy and imaging. Coverslips were coated with ConA (2 mg ml À 1 , Sigma). 
Raw images were used for all quantifications and analyses. Polarization and 
washout experiments were performed on a Zeiss Axio Imager.A1 upright micro-
scope with 1.4 NA Â 100 objective, an X-Cite120 light source (Lumen Dynamics) </p>

<p>GFP-Cdc42 Δbem2 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>b 
a </p>

<p>Double nuclei (%) </p>

<p>Release 
Arrest </p>

<p>GFPCdc42 
Δbem2 
GFPCdc42 </p>

<p>Release 
Arrest 
Δbem2 
2x Cdc24GFP </p>

<p>Release 
Arrest </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Figure 8 | Multiple polarization sites and DNA segregation (a) Examples of Dbem2 cells displaying two nuclei and two buds. Scale bar, 4 mm. 
(b) Percentage of cells with two nuclei in controls and in Dbem2 cells expressing GFPCdc42 or two copies of Cdc24GFP. Bars represent means ± s.e.m. 
for three experiments with 100 cells each. </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1807 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>and an iXON DU-897 EMCCD camera (Andor) coupled to a Â 2 magnification 
ring. Images were acquired with <rs id="software-1" type="software">Metamorph</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">7.0</rs> software. 
Images for FRAP experiments were acquired on a custom-built setup from Till 
Photonics based on an iMic stand with Olympus 1.45 NA Â 100 objective and 
iXON DU-897 EMCCD camera. Four hundred eighty-eight nanometre (Coherent) 
and 561 nm (Cobolt) lasers were directed through an AOTF and coupled into the 
iMic. A galvanometer allowed switching between FRAP and epifluorescence 
modes. Two additional galvanometers were used to adjust laser incidence angles or 
FRAP positions. For FRAP, caps were selected 10-20 min after release from G1 
arrest. Acquisition was controlled by the Live Acquisition software. </p>

<p>Drug treatments and staining </p>

<p>Actin disruption. Cells were released in medium containing 400 mM LatB. In </p>

<p>washout experiments, LatB was added for 20 or 40 min, and then removed by 
washing twice. Polarization was monitored after 40-60 min. FM4-64 staining: cells 
were incubated in 0.32 mM FM4-64 for 2 min and washed once. </p>

<p>DAPI-staining. One millilitre cells were released for 2-25 h, fixed with 3% </p>

<p>formaldehyde for 2 h, washed twice and resuspended in 30 ml PBS þ 0.1% Triton. 
Fixed cells were then incubated with 0.1 mg ml À 1 DAPI for 10 min and washed 
twice with PBS. </p>

<p>FRAP analysis. To quantify fluorescence recovery <rs id="software-0" type="software">MATLAB</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">MathWorks</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">2010a</rs>) 
routines were implemented. Intensities in the bleached region were corrected for 
background fluorescence and total cellular fluorescence. The recovery curve was 
fitted with a double exponential function y fit (t) ¼ a(1-b(exp(-tc))-d(exp(-te)). The 
fast component corresponded to diffusion of soluble Cdc42 in the cytosol and the 
slower component ro recovery of membrane-bound Cdc42 pool via a combination 
of GDI-and actin-mediated mechanisms. The halftime for the slower component, 
t 2 
1/2 ¼ À log(0.5)/e was used for further comparison. Time stamps were auto-
matically extracted from the metadata. Data points were only used if reliable fits 
could be generated (residual sum of squares 40.95). Means and s.e.m. were 
calculated from 410 independent experiments (Supplementary Table S3). </p>

<p>Calculation of cap width and height. For measurements of cap width and height, 
GFP-Cdc42 caps were identified from medial cross-sections and a region R cap 
was drawn around the perimeter of the cap. A background region R bg was selected 
inside the same cell. Background signal I 0 from the camera chip was 
calculated from a region distant from any cell. Cap height H was calculated as 
H ¼ (I(R cap ) À I 0 )/ (I(R bg ) À I 0 ). Cap width W corresponded to the size of the cap 
area R cap . Total intensitiy I tot was calculated as I tot ¼ H*W. </p>

<p>Protein purification. His 6 -tagged Cdc42 was purified from baculovirus-infected 
Sf21 insect cells. All purification steps were performed at 4 °C. Stirred 1l cultures of 
Sf21 cells were infected for 48 h by Kinnakeet Biotechnology (Midlothian, VA). Cell 
pellets were resuspended in 40 ml hypotonic buffer (20 mM sodium borate pH 10.2, 
5 mM MgCl 2 , 200 mM PMSF, 1 mg ml À 1 aprotinin and leupeptin) and disrupted by 
Dounce homogenization. 
Membrane-containing components of the lysate were spun down at 1,50,000 g in 
a Ti70 rotor (Beckman Coulter) for 20 min and resuspended in 50 ml TBSM 
(50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 5 mM MgCl 2 ). The procedure was repeated 
twice and the final pellet was resuspended in TBSM þ 1% Triton-X100. The lysate 
was further homogenized and agitated for 30 min on a rotisserie, resulting in 
solubilization of geranylgeranylated Cdc42. The remaining insoluble fraction was 
pelleted in a tabletop centrifuge at 9,000 g for 20 min at 4 °C and discarded. The 
supernatant containing detergent-solubilized, isoprenylated His 6 -tagged Cdc42 was 
incubated for 30 min with chelating Sepharose beads (Qiagen) charged with Ni 2 þ . 
Beads were then washed with 400 ml high salt buffer (50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 700 mM 
NaCl, 5 mM MgCl 2 , 0.1% CHAPS, 20 mM imidazole) and protein was eluted with 
10 ml elution buffer (50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 5 mM MgCl 2 , 0.1% 
CHAPS, 500 mM imidazole). The fractions containing Cdc42 were pooled and 
concentrated to 2 ml. His 6 -tagged prenylated Rac1 was purified in the same manner 
as Cdc42. 
N-terminal GST fusions to human RhoGDI and to the GAP domain of Cdc42-
GAP (human, residues 234-462) as well as N-terminally His 6 -tagged DHR2C 
domain of human Dock180 were purified from E. coli cells. Cells were grown at 
37 °C to OD 0.8. Protein expression was induced by 1 mM IPTG for 3 h before 
pelleting at 6,000 g for 10 min. Cell pellets were homogenized in TBSM and lysed 
by sonication. Extracts were spun at 20,000 g for 30 min. Supernatants with GST-
tagged proteins were incubated with glutathione beads and equilibrated with TEDA 
buffer (20 mM Tris pH 8.0, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM DTT, 1 mM sodium azide) for 
30 min at 4 °C. Beads were washed with several column volumes of TEDA-
containing 500 mM NaCl and protein was eluted with 10 mM glutathione in 
TBSM. His 6 -tagged DHR2 domain was purified on Sepharose beads charged with 
Ni 2 þ as described above. All proteins were concentrated in 10 MWC Amicon 
Ultra concentrators. </p>

<p>Liposome binding assays. Liposomes were prepared by extrusion using Avanti 
mini-extruders (1 or 8 mm membranes) followed by centrifugation at 16,000 g for 
10 min and resuspension in TBSM. Lipids were purchased from Avanti Polar 
Lipids. The standard lipid composition in molar percentages was 35% PE, 25% PS, 
5% PI and 35% cholesterol (Nu Chek Preps). 
For Cdc42-liposome association assays a Varian Cary Eclipse fluorimeter was 
used in the counting mode. Excitation and emission wavelengths were 365 and 
440 nm, respectively. Samples were stirred continuously at 25 °C in TBSM. To 
prepare HAF (hexadecanoylaminofluorescein)-labelled lipids for FRET assays, 
1.25 nmol of HAF (Molecular Probes) was vortexed with 50 ml of lipids 
(1 mg ml À 1 ). To monitor release of Cdc42 from liposomes, Cdc42 was preloaded 
with methylanthraniloyl-modified (Mant) nucleotide and incubated with 30 ml of 
HAF-containing liposomes at RT for 5 min. The mixture was added to the cuvette, 
bringing the final Cdc42 concentration to 40 nM. At the indicated time points, 
50 nM RhoGDI and 10 nM Cdc42-GAP were added, and fluorescence was recorded 
for 20 min. Traces monitored the changes in Mant fluorescence due to changes in 
FRET between Mant-nucleotide-bound Cdc42 and liposomes containing HAF. </p>

<p>Statistics and data analysis. Curve fitting for polarization curves was done with 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">4</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>, La Jolla) using a sigmoidal dose-response equation 
y ¼ bottom þ (top-bottom)/(1 þ 10^((LogEC50-X)*Hill Slope)). Unpaired two-
tailed t-tests were performed to validate significance of differences. </p>



<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1807 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>



<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank R. Li for strains and P. Hardy for editing. This work was supported by the 
Max Planck society (R.W.-S.) and the DFG (SFB 863: R.W.-S., E.F.; Nano-Initiative 
Munich (NIM): E.F.). </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>T.F., B.K., E.F. and R.W.-S. conceived the study, analysed the data and wrote the 
manuscript. T.F., G.P. and G.B. performed experiments. B.K. and E.F. built mathematical 
models and performed simulations. J.J. performed protein purifications and liposome 
assays with help from R.A.C. M.C. and C.B. provided SGA data and expertise. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
naturecommunications </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Reprints and permission information is available online at http://npg.nature.com/ 
reprintsandpermissions/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Freisinger, T. et al. Establishment of a robust single axis 
of cell polarity by coupling multiple positive feedback loops. Nat. Commun. 4:1807 
doi: 10.1038/ncomms2795 (2013). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of 
this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/ </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:1807 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms2795 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

</text></tei>