<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3282807" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:48+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Mitochondrial reactive oxygen species (ROS) play an important 
role in diabetes complications, including diabetic nephropathy 
(DN). Plasma free fatty acids (FFAs) as well as glucose are 
increased in diabetes, and peroxisomes and mitochondria par-
ticipate in FFA oxidation in an interconnected fashion. Therefore, 
we investigated whether deficiency of catalase, a major peroxi-
somal antioxidant, accelerates DN through peroxisomal dysfunc-
tion and abnormal renal FFA metabolism. Diabetes was induced 
by multiple injections of low-dose streptozotocin into catalase 
knock-out (CKO) and wild-type (WT) C57BL/6 mice. Murine 
mesangial cells (MMCs) transfected with catalase small interfer-
ing RNA followed by catalase overexpression were used to fur-
ther elucidate the role of endogenous catalase. Despite equivalent 
hyperglycemia, parameters of DN, along with markers of oxida-
tive stress, were more accelerated in diabetic CKO mice than in 
diabetic WT mice up to 10 weeks of diabetes. CKO mice and 
MMCs showed impaired peroxisomal/mitochondrial biogenesis 
and FFA oxidation. Catalase deficiency increased mitochondrial 
ROS and fibronectin expression in response to FFAs, which were 
effectively restored by catalase overexpression or N-acetylcysteine. 
These data provide unprecedented evidence that FFA-induced 
peroxisomal dysfunction exacerbates DN and that endogenous 
catalase plays an important role in protecting the kidney from 
diabetic stress through maintaining peroxisomal and mitochon-
drial fitness. Diabetes 61:728-738, 2012 </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>iabetic nephropathy (DN) is the leading cause 
of end-stage renal disease worldwide and an in-
dependent risk factor for cardiovascular mor-
bidity and mortality (1). DN is characterized by 
albuminuria, decreased glomerular filtration rate, and ex-
cessive deposition of extracellular matrix (ECM) leading 
to glomerular mesangial expansion and tubulointerstitial 
fibrosis (2-4). Large randomized clinical studies show a 
causal relationship between hyperglycemia and renal in-
jury in both type 1 (5) and type 2 (6) diabetes. Numerous 
studies also suggest that hyperglycemia-induced reactive 
oxygen species (ROS) contribute to the development and 
progression of DN (7-10). 
Plasma free fatty acids (FFAs) are also increased under 
the diabetic milieu. However, the role of FFA flux in insulin-
independent tissues, including the kidney, has been </p>

<p>relatively underappreciated compared with the role of 
glucose flux. In this context, recent studies show that 
FFAs stimulate ROS through protein kinase C-dependent 
NADPH oxidase (Nox) in vascular smooth muscle cells and 
endothelial cells (11) and that FFAs reduce acetylcholine-
induced forearm blood flow, which was prevented by 
vitamin C (12). Oleate has been reported to induce 
myofibroblast phenotype in mesangial cells through trans-
forming growth factor (TGF)-b1 activation, which suggests 
that elevated FFAs may induce ECM remodeling and renal 
fibrosis (13). We have observed previously that oleate-
induced ROS upregulate fibronectin (FN) in murine mesangial 
cells (MMCs) (14). 
Peroxisome is an essential organelle for lipid metabolism, 
as evidenced by increased plasma very long-chain FA in pa-
tients with Zellweger syndrome, which is an inherited disease 
of peroxisomal deficiency (15). During FA b-oxidation, 
peroxisomes generate H 2 O 2 , which is mostly decomposed 
to water and oxygen by catalase (16). Mammalian catalase 
is a 240-kDa homotetrameric heme-containing protein lo-
cated exclusively in the peroxisome and abundantly ex-
pressed in liver, lungs, and kidneys (17). In a recent study, 
Elsner et al. (18) reported that overexpression of catalase 
in the peroxisome, but not in the mitochondria, reduces 
H 2 O 2 production and protects insulin-producing cells from 
long-chain FA-induced lipotoxicity. These findings in-
dicate that H 2 O 2 generated by peroxisomal b-oxidation 
plays an important role in lipotoxicity under certain con-
ditions. Consistent with this study, when catalase activity 
in myocardial peroxisomes was inhibited by aminotriazole, 
a catalase inhibitor, lipids were peroxided and accumu-
lated in the heart (19), leading to a severe cardiac failure 
(20). Although peroxisomes contain full enzymatic ma-
chinery for FA b-oxidation, FA shortened through perox-
isomal b-oxidation could be shuttled to mitochondria for 
complete oxidation. For this reason, peroxisomal metabo-
lism is closely related to mitochondria (21). In this context, 
absence of catalase could cause impairment of mitochon-
dria as well as peroxisomes (22). Although catalase over-
expression attenuated diabetic renal injury (23,24), the 
role of endogenous catalase in DN and the molecular 
mechanism linking catalase to lipid flux in renal cells have 
not been studied. 
Therefore, we investigated whether endogenous cata-
lase plays a role in protecting kidney from FFA-induced 
lipotoxicity under diabetic conditions using catalase null 
(CKO) mice. We further investigated whether catalase 
deficiency induces peroxisomal dysfunction leading to 
mitochondrial dysfunction and lipid accumulation using 
small interfering (si)RNA-transfected MMCs cultured under 
phytanic acid (PhA), a branched FA metabolized exclu-
sively in the peroxisome, alone or in combination with high 
glucose (HG). Transgenic catalase was used to verify the 
on-target effect of catalase siRNA (siCat). </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>Materials. Reagents for immunohistochemical staining were purchased from 
DAKO A/S (Glostrup, Denmark), anti-E-cadherin was obtained from BD 
Biosciences (San Jose, CA), anti-catalase was obtained from Young In Frontier 
(Seoul, Korea), and other antibodies were obtained from Santa Cruz Bio-
technology Inc. (Santa Cruz, CA). FBS was purchased from GIBCO BRL 
(Gaithersburg, MD), and MitoSOX was obtained from Molecular Probes 
(Eugene, OR). Other chemicals and tissue culture plates were obtained from 
Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO) and Becton Dickinson Labware (Lincoln Park, 
NJ), respectively, unless otherwise stated. 
Animals. Male catalase wild-type (WT) and CKO C57BL/6 J mice (17) were 
used in this study. All animal experiments were approved by Ewha Womans 
University Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee. Six-week-old mice 
were divided into four groups: nondiabetic and diabetic WT mice and non-
diabetic and diabetic CKO mice. Diabetes was induced by intraperitoneal in-
jection of streptozotocin (STZ; 50 mg/kg/day) for 5 days and mice were kept 
up to 10 weeks of diabetes (25). Blood pressure was measured every week by 
CODA High-Throughout Non-Invasive Tail Blood Pressure system (Kent Sci-
entific Corporation, Torrington, CT). 
Cell culture. MMCs were cultured as described previously (26). Subconfluent 
MMCs were transfected with 20 nmol/L siCat (sense, 59-CCA GAU ACU CCA 
AGG CAA ATT-39; antisense, 59-UUU GCC UUG GAG UAU CUG GTT-39) using 
Lipofectamine RNAiMAX (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) for 24 h. For overexpression 
experiments, MMCs were transfected with 100 ng p-cytomegalovirus (pCMV)-
human catalase (hCat) plasmid (supplied by Professor Sue Goo Rhee, Ewha 
Womans University) after siRNA transfection for 24 h. 
Biochemical data. Blood glucose, urinary creatinine and albumin concen-
trations, and body weight were measured every 2 weeks. Urine was collected 
during two consecutive 24-h periods, during which each mouse was individually 
housed in a metabolic cage with free access to food and water. Blood glucose 
was measured by the glucose oxidase method, plasma creatinine was measured 
by Detect X Serum Creatinine Detection Kit (Arbor Assays, Ann Arbor, MI), and 
plasma FFAs were measured by EnzyChrom Free Fatty Acid Assay Kit (BioAssay 
Systems, Hayward, CA). Urinary protein was analyzed by Bradford assay and 
SDS-PAGE (27). The levels of urinary lipid peroxide (LPO) were measured by 
the thiobarbituric acid method as described previously (28). 
Mitochondrial ROS measurement. Mitochondrial ROS were measured using 
MitoSOX. In brief, after stimulation, the cells were washed and incubated with 
2.5 mmol/L MitoSOX for 10 min. The unbound dye was then removed and 
fluorescence was analyzed using a flow cytometer (BD Biosciences) and vi-
sualized by confocal microscopy (Carl Zeiss, Gottingen, Germany). 
Morpholometric analysis. In each mouse, quantitative analysis of glomerular 
volume and fractional mesangial area (FMA) in the glomeruli stained with 
periodic acid Schiff (PAS) reagent was conducted as described previously (25). 
Immunostaining. Immunohistochemistry for nitrotyrosine and FN ED-A was 
performed as described previously (29) using anti-N-nitrotyrosine (1:200) and 
anti-FN ED-A (1:200). For the detection of peroxin (PEX)5 in MMCs, the cells 
were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 10 min, incubated with serum-free 
blocking solution for 15 min, and then reacted with anti-PEX5 (1:200). After 
washing two times with PBS, the samples were incubated with Alexa Fluor 
488-tagged goat anti-mouse IgG (H+L) (1:100) for 1 h. Images were obtained 
by confocal microscopy (Carl Zeiss). 
Real-time PCR. Isolation of total RNA from the whole kidney and MMCs, 
synthesis of cDNA by reverse transcription, and quantitative real-time PCR 
were performed as described previously (25). PCR primer sequences are listed 
in Supplementary Table 1. 
Western blot analysis. E-cadherin, a-smooth muscle actin (a-SMA), and FN 
protein were measured by a standard Western blot analysis as described pre-
viously (25), using anti-human E-cadherin (1:5,000), anti-mouse a-SMA (1:10,000), 
and anti-human FN (1:2,000). 
Lipid accumulation. For Oil Red O staining, fixed tissues and cells were 
washed and incubated with 0.3% Oil Red O for 10 min. After washing with 
distilled water, images were obtained by microscopy (Carl Zeiss). </p>

<p>Statistical analyses. All results are expressed as mean 6 SE. ANOVA was 
used to assess the differences between multiple groups. If the F statistic was 
significant, the mean values of each group were compared by Fisher least 
significant difference method. P , 0.05 was considered significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Diabetic renal injury was accelerated by catalase 
deficiency. After multiple injections of low-dose STZ, 
both diabetic WT and diabetic CKO mice maintained hy-
perglycemia up to 10 weeks of diabetes, but there was no 
difference between the two groups (Table 1). The kidney 
weight (absolute and adjusted) of diabetic CKO mice was 
significantly increased when compared with diabetic WT 
mice at both 4 and 10 weeks of diabetes (Table 1). Mean 
blood pressure (mmHg) was significantly increased from 5 
weeks of diabetes, but there was little difference between 
diabetic WT and diabetic CKO mice (WT: 108 6 8; diabetic 
WT: 135 6 12; diabetic CKO: 140 6 4 at 10 weeks of di-
abetes), suggesting that blood pressure did not play a sig-
nificant role in accelerated renal injury in diabetic CKO 
mice under our experimental condition. 
Urinary protein excretion was gradually increased up to 
10 weeks of diabetes and was significantly increased 
in diabetic CKO compared with diabetic WT mice at both 
4 weeks and 10 weeks of diabetes (Fig. 1A and B). Plasma 
creatinine levels were also gradually increased in both 
diabetic groups and were significantly higher in diabetic 
CKO mice than in diabetic WT mice at 10 weeks of diabetes 
(Fig. 1C). Glomerular volume in both diabetic groups was 
gradually increased up to 10 weeks of diabetes, and in di-
abetic CKO mice, glomerular volume and FMA were higher 
than that of diabetic WT mice at both 4 and 10 weeks of 
diabetes (Fig. 1D-F). It is important to note that glomerular 
volume and FMA in nondiabetic CKO mice were signif-
icantly higher than age-matched nondiabetic WT mice 
(Supplementary Fig. 1A and B). These results suggest that 
catalase deficiency exacerbates renal injury in early diabetes. 
Renal fibrosis was accelerated by catalase deficiency. 
We next measured the pro-and antifibrotic cytokines 
along with markers of epithelial-to-mesenchymal transi-
tion, which is an early event in DN (30). TGF-b1 (Fig. 2A), 
connective tissue growth factor (CTGF) (Fig. 2B), a-SMA 
(Fig. 2D) mRNA, and a-SMA protein (Fig. 2F) expression 
levels were significantly increased in diabetic CKO com-
pared with diabetic WT mice at 4 and 10 weeks of diabetes. 
CTGF and a-SMA expressions in diabetic CKO kidneys 
were more significantly increased at 10 weeks of diabetes. 
Conversely, bone morphogenic protein 7 (BMP7)-a reno-
protective antifibrotic cytokine-mRNA (Fig. 2C), E-cadherin 
mRNA (Fig. 2E), and protein (Fig. 2G) expressions in di-
abetic CKO kidneys were significantly decreased com-
pared with diabetic WT kidneys at both 4 and 10 weeks of 
diabetes. In nondiabetic CKO kidneys, the expressions of 
TGF-b1, CTGF, a-SMA, and FN mRNA were significantly </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Characteristics of animals </p>

<p>4 weeks of diabetes 
10 weeks of diabetes 
WT 
WTDM 
CKODM 
WT 
WTDM 
CKODM </p>

<p>Body weight (g) 
22.8 6 0.7 
19.0 6 0.9* 
23.1 6 0.9 † 
28.2 6 0.5 
23.3 6 0.4* 
24.1 6 0.6* 
Kidney weight (g) 
0.14 6 0.01 
0.14 6 0.01 
0.17 6 0.01* † 
0.14 6 0.01 
0.18 6 0.01* 
0.23 6 0.01* † 
Kidney-to-body ratio (mg/g) 
7.4 6 0.1 
7.6 6 0.2 
7.8 6 0.1* 
5.1 6 0.2 
7.6 6 0.3* 
9.6 6 0.4* † 
Blood glucose (mg/dL) 
193 6 15 
362 6 50* 
397 6 74* 
159 6 7 
596 6 43* 
657 6 27* </p>

<p>Data are mean 6 SE of n = 5-7 mice per group. DM, diabetic mice. *P , 0.05 vs. WT.  †P , 0.05 vs. WTDM. </p>

<p>I. HWANG AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, MARCH 2012 </p>

<p>
upregulated, while BMP7 and E-cadherin mRNA were sig-
nificantly downregulated compared with nondiabetic WT 
kidneys (Supplementary Fig. 1G). 
Consistently, FN mRNA and protein expressions in dia-
betic CKO kidneys were significantly higher than in dia-
betic WT kidneys. The increase in FN protein levels in both 
diabetic WT and CKO kidneys were more evident at 10 weeks 
of diabetes than at 4 weeks (Fig. 3A and B). Immunohis-
tochemical analysis at 4 weeks of diabetes confirmed that 
FN ED-A was strongly expressed in the glomeruli of dia-
betic WT mice and in the tubules and glomeruli of diabetic 
CKO mice (Fig. 3C). Masson trichrome staining showed 
significantly increased collagen accumulation in diabetic </p>

<p>WT kidneys, which was further increased in diabetic CKO 
kidneys at 10 weeks of diabetes (Fig. 3D). These results 
show that catalase deficiency accelerates renal fibrosis in 
early diabetes. 
Upregulated antioxidative defense mechanisms in 
diabetic kidneys were blunted by catalase deficiency. 
Catalase null state was confirmed by real-time PCR in the 
CKO kidneys (Supplementary Fig. 2A). In diabetic WT kid-
neys, the mRNA levels of antioxidant enzymes, including 
catalase, glutathione peroxidase-1 (GPx1), peroxiredoxin 
(Prx)1, Prx5, superoxide dismutase (SOD)1, SOD2, and 
sulfiredoxin-1, were significantly upregulated compared 
with nondiabetic WT kidneys (Supplementary Fig. 2A-G). </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Diabetic renal injury was accelerated in diabetic CKO mice. At 4 and 10 weeks after the induction of diabetes, parameters of DN were 
analyzed. A and B: Urinary protein excretion was measured by Bradford assay (A) or SDS-PAGE (B). C: Plasma creatinine was measured by Detect 
X Serum Creatinine Detection Kit. D-F: The kidneys were fixed, cut into 4-mm sections, and stained with PAS reagent (D). Scale bar, 20 mm; 
magnification 3630. After PAS staining, the glomerular volume (E) and FMA (F) were analyzed using Image Pro Plus (50 glomeruli per animal). 
WT, nondiabetic control mice; WTDM, STZ-induced diabetic WT mice; CKODM, STZ-induced diabetic CKO mice. Data are mean 6 SE of n = 7-8 
mice per group. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. WT;  †P &lt; 0.05 vs. WTDM at the same duration of diabetes; **P &lt; 0.05 between two groups. </p>

<p>PEROXISOMAL DYSFUNCTION IN DIABETIC NEPHROPATHY </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, MARCH 2012 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>Moreover, Prx1 and Prx5 mRNA expressions in non-
diabetic CKO kidneys were significantly higher than in 
nondiabetic WT kidneys. Unexpectedly, upregulated ex-
pressions of antioxidant enzymes were blunted in diabetic 
CKO kidneys. In fact, renal expressions of GPx1, Prx5, 
SOD1, SOD2, and sulfiredoxin-1 mRNA in diabetic CKO 
mice were significantly lower than in diabetic WT mice. 
Oxidative stress was higher in diabetic CKO kidneys 
than in diabetic WT kidneys. Renal Nox4 plays an im-
portant role in increased oxidative stress leading to DN </p>

<p>(31), and H 2 O 2 upregulates Nox4 mRNA expression in 
MMCs (32). We, therefore, measured Nox4 mRNA ex-
pression in addition to urinary LPO and nitrotyrosine 
accumulation as markers of renal oxidative stress. Renal 
Nox4 mRNA (Fig. 4A) expression, urinary LPO (Fig. 4B), 
and renal nitrotyrosine accumulation (Fig. 4C and D) were 
higher in diabetic CKO mice than in diabetic WT mice at 
4 weeks of diabetes and were continuously increased in 
diabetic CKO mice up to 10 weeks. These results, together 
with the mRNA expression profile of antioxidant enzymes </p>

<p>FIG. 2. The profibrotic pathway was accelerated in diabetic CKO mice. At 4 and 10 weeks after the induction of diabetes, mRNA and protein 
samples were taken from whole kidney. A-E: Renal TGF-b1 (A), CTGF (B), BMP7 (C), a-SMA (D), and E-cadherin (E) mRNA expressions were 
analyzed by real-time PCR. F and G: a-SMA (F) and E-cadherin (G) protein expressions were analyzed by Western blot. WT, nondiabetic control 
mice; WTDM, STZ-induced diabetic WT mice; CKODM, STZ-induced diabetic CKO mice. Data are mean 6 SE of n = 7-8 mice per group. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. 
WT;  †P &lt; 0.05 vs. WTDM at the same duration of diabetes; **P &lt; 0.05 between two groups. </p>

<p>I. HWANG AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, MARCH 2012 </p>

<p>
in diabetic CKO kidneys, demonstrate that renal oxidative 
stress is greatly increased in diabetes by catalase deficiency. 
Catalase deficiency disrupted renal peroxisomal 
biogenesis. We investigated peroxisomal biogenesis as 
the first step in a mechanistic study of the relationships 
among catalase, peroxisome, oxidative stress, and DN. 
Plasma FFAs were significantly upregulated in both dia-
betic WT and diabetic CKO mice compared with control 
WT at 4 weeks and further increased in diabetic CKO at 
10 weeks of diabetes (Fig. 5A). Renal expressions of per-
oxisomal biogenesis markers including, PEX5, PEX11-a, 
and ATP-binding cassette member 3 (Abcd3), were sig-
nificantly higher in diabetic WT mice at 4 weeks but lower </p>

<p>at 10 weeks compared with nondiabetic WT mice (Fig. 5B-E). 
In diabetic CKO kidneys, these peroxisomal biogenesis 
markers were significantly decreased compared with di-
abetic WT kidneys at both 4 and 10 weeks (Fig. 5B-E). 
To investigate a direct role of endogenous catalase in 
the progression of DN, we used MMCs transfected with 
siCat. siCat decreased the endogenous catalase level down 
to 40% of basal in MMCs and was restored by additional 
catalase expression using pCMV-hCAT (Fig. 5F). PEX5, 
PEX11-a, and Abcd3 mRNA expressions were significantly 
upregulated by 100 mmol/L PhA with or without 30 mmol/L 
D-glucose (HG) for 4 h in MMCs, but these increases were 
inhibited by catalase knock-down (Fig. 5G and H and </p>

<p>FIG. 3. ECM expression was further increased in diabetic CKO kidneys. A and B: Renal FN mRNA (A) and protein (B) expressions at 4 and 
10 weeks after the induction of diabetes. C: The renal tissues of 4 weeks of diabetes were immunostained with anti-FN ED-A (1:200; left), and FN 
ED-A positive area was quantified by using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software (right; 15 pictures per animal). Single scale bar, 100 mm; magnification 3200. Double 
scale bar, 20 mm; magnification 3630. D: Renal collagen was measured by Masson trichrome staining at 10 weeks after the induction of diabetes 
(left) and quantified (right; 15 pictures per animal). The upper and lower pictures are magnification 312.5 (scale bar, 1 mm) and 3630 (scale bar, 
20 mm), respectively. WT, nondiabetic control mice; WTDM, STZ-induced diabetic WT mice; CKODM, STZ-induced diabetic CKO mice. Data are 
mean 6 SE of n = 7-8 mice per group. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. WT;  †P &lt; 0.05 vs. WTDM at the same duration of diabetes; **P &lt; 0.05 between two groups. 
(A high-quality digital representation of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>PEROXISOMAL DYSFUNCTION IN DIABETIC NEPHROPATHY </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, MARCH 2012 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>Supplementary Fig. 3B-E). Peroxisomal biogenesis mark-
ers inhibited by catalase deficiency were restored by hCAT 
transfection, confirming the on-target effect of siCat. 
N-acetylcysteine (NAC) also effectively restored the in-
hibition of peroxisomal biogenesis induced by catalase 
deficiency. Decreased PEX5 expression was further con-
firmed by Western blot and immunocytochemistry (Fig. 5J 
and I). It is interesting that 100 mmol/L H 2 O 2 treatment 
significantly increased peroxisomal biogenesis, but not 
at .250 mmol/L (Supplementary Fig. 3A). These results 
suggest that FFA-induced oxidative stress requires cat-
alase for peroxisomal fitness, but severe oxidative stress, 
such as H 2 O 2 at levels .250 mmol/L or catalase deficiency 
under diabetic conditions, disrupts adaptive peroxisomal 
biogenesis. 
Catalase deficiency disrupted renal mitochondrial 
biogenesis. To investigate whether catalase deficiency in-
duces the accumulation of mitochondrial ROS, we measured 
mitochondrial superoxide anion levels using MitoSOX. 
MitoSOX-sensitive ROS were significantly increased by 
PhA with or without HG treatment and further increased 
by catalase knock-down (Fig. 6A and B). Accelerated mi-
tochondrial ROS in catalase knock-down cells were effec-
tively prevented by hCAT transfection or by NAC treatment. 
MitoSOX levels were not significantly different between 
PhA alone and PhA plus HG treatment. 
To determine if catalase deficiency induced impaired 
mitochondrial fitness, we measured cytochrome b mRNA </p>

<p>level, a marker of mitochondrial biogenesis, in MMCs and 
diabetic animals. As a result of increased mitochondrial 
ROS, catalase deficiency inhibited PhA with or without 
HG-induced cytochrome b mRNA expression, which was 
restored by hCAT transfection or NAC treatment (Fig. 6C). 
The PhA plus HG-induced cytochrome b mRNA level was 
higher than PhA treatment alone (Fig. 6D). Similar to 
peroxisomal biogenesis markers, cytochrome b mRNA level 
was higher in diabetic WT kidneys at 4 weeks but lower at 
10 weeks of diabetes compared with nondiabetic WT kid-
neys (Fig. 6E). In diabetic CKO kidneys, cytochrome b mRNA 
level was significantly decreased at both 4 and 10 weeks 
compared with diabetic WT kidneys (Fig. 6E). These results 
suggest that catalase deficiency increases mitochondrial 
ROS, which might play a role in dysregulation of mito-
chondrial biogenesis. 
Catalase deficiency induced renal lipid accumulation. 
To determine if the impaired peroxisomal and mitochon-
drial biogenesis induced by catalase deficiency under the 
diabetic milieu affected renal lipid metabolism, we mea-
sured the peroxisomal and mitochondrial b-oxidation and 
lipid accumulation. mRNA expressions of acyl-CoA oxi-
dase (ACO), a key enzyme of peroxisomal b-oxidation, and 
carnitine palmitoyltransferase (CPT)1-a, a regulator of long-
chain FA entry to mitochondria, were significantly decreased 
in diabetic WT compared with control WT kidneys and 
were further decreased in diabetic CKO kidneys at both 
4 and 10 weeks of diabetes (Fig. 7A). Oil Red O staining </p>

<p>FIG. 4. Oxidative stress was exacerbated in diabetic CKO kidneys. A: At 4 and 10 weeks after the induction of diabetes, renal Nox4 mRNA ex-
pression was measured by real-time PCR. B: Urinary LPO was assessed by thiobarbituric acid assay. C and D: Renal nitrotyrosine accumulation was 
measured by immunohistochemistry using anti-nitrotyrosine (1:200) (C) and quantified by using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> (15 pictures per animal) (D). Single scale 
bar, 100 mm; magnification 3200. Double scale bar, 20 mm; magnification 3630. WT, nondiabetic control mice; WTDM, STZ-induced diabetic WT 
mice; CKODM, STZ-induced diabetic CKO mice. Data are mean 6 SE of n = 7-8 mice per group. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. WT;  †P &lt; 0.05 vs. WTDM at the same 
duration of diabetes; **P &lt; 0.05 between two groups. (A high-quality digital representation of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>I. HWANG AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, MARCH 2012 </p>

<p>
revealed more lipid droplets in the glomeruli and tubules 
of diabetic WT mice than in nondiabetic WT mice at 10 
weeks of diabetes (Fig. 7B). In diabetic CKO mice, lipid 
droplets in the glomeruli were significantly higher than in 
diabetic WT mice (Fig. 7B). 
In MMCs, ACO, and CPT1-a, mRNA expressions were 
significantly upregulated by PhA with or without HG, and </p>

<p>these were inhibited by catalase knock-down (Fig. 7C). 
Again, hCAT transfection or NAC treatment restored the 
decreased ACO and CPT1-a mRNA expressions in catalase 
knock-down cells (Fig. 7C). ACO mRNA levels were not 
different between MMCs treated with PhA alone versus 
PhA plus HG, but CPT1-a mRNA levels were higher in 
MMCs treated with PhA alone compared with PhA plus HG </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Catalase deficiency impaired peroxisomal biogenesis. A: At 4 and 10 weeks after the induction of diabetes, plasma FFAs (A) were measured 
as described in RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS. B-E: Renal PEX5 (B), PEX11-a (D), and Abcd3 (E) mRNA expressions were analyzed by real-time PCR. 
PEX5 protein (C) was measured by Western blot analysis. WT, nondiabetic control mice; WTDM, STZ-induced diabetic WT mice; CKODM, STZ-
induced diabetic CKO mice. Data are mean 6 SE of n = 7-8 mice per group. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. WT;  †P &lt; 0.05 vs. WTDM at the same duration of diabetes; 
**P &lt; 0.05 between two groups. F: The efficacy of siCat or hCAT in MMCs was analyzed by Western blot. MMCs were transfected with 20 nmol/L 
siCat or scramble siRNA for 24 h. Remaining siRNA were washed and then transfected with 100 ng hCAT. G-K: MMCs were then cultured under 
PhA6HG for 4 h (RNA) or 24 h (protein). NAC (5 mmol/L) was pretreated for 24 h where indicated. PEX5 mRNA (G and H) was measured by real-
time PCR, and protein (J and K) was measured by Western blot. After 24 h, MMCs were fixed and then immunostained with anti-PEX5 (1:300) (I). 
Magnification 3630. siCat, MMCs transfected with 20 nmol/L siCat; hCAT, MMCs transfected with 100 ng pCMV-hCat; NAC (5 mmol/L); HG (30 
mmol/L D-glucose); PhA (100 mmol/L). Data are mean 6 SE of n = 4 experiments in the cell culture study. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. scramble siRNA-transfected 
cells;  †P &lt; 0.05 vs. scramble siRNA-transfected cells cultured under PhA6HG; #P &lt; 0.05 vs. siCat-transfected cells cultured under PhA+HG; n.s. 
not significant between two groups. </p>

<p>PEROXISOMAL DYSFUNCTION IN DIABETIC NEPHROPATHY </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, MARCH 2012 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>(Fig. 7C). Oil Red O staining showed significantly in-
creased lipid droplets in catalase knock-down cells in re-
sponse to PhA plus HG, and these were effectively 
inhibited by NAC treatment (Fig. 7D). 
FN mRNA and protein expressions were significantly 
increased in MMCs cultured under PhA plus HG, which 
was more evident than PhA treatment alone, and were 
further increased in catalase knock-down cells (Fig. 7E 
and F). Induction of FN in catalase deficiency was signif-
icantly inhibited by hCAT transfection or NAC treatment 
(Fig. 7E and F). These results suggest that catalase deficiency 
impairs peroxisomal and mitochondrial b-oxidation, lead-
ing to lipid and ECM accumulations. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This study provides experimental evidence that endoge-
nous catalase plays an important role in renal redox reg-
ulation and function under diabetic conditions. Despite 
equivalent hyperglycemia between diabetic WT and di-
abetic CKO mice, parameters of DN together with plasma 
FFAs were significantly upregulated in diabetic CKO mice. 
These accelerations were accompanied by increased uri-
nary LPO and renal nitrotyrosine accumulation in diabetic 
CKO mice, confirming that increased ROS in diabetic CKO 
mice are associated with accelerated diabetic renal injury. 
It should be noted that the compensatory increase of 
antioxidant enzymes observed in diabetic WT kidneys was </p>

<p>FIG. 6. Catalase deficiency induced accumulation of mitochondrial ROS and impairment of mitochondrial biogenesis. A and B: Mitochondrial ROS 
were measured by MitoSOX. After transfection with siCat or scramble siRNA, cells were cultured under PhA6HG for 1 h and then loaded with 2.5 
mmol/L MitoSOX for 10 min. The intensity of MitoSOX was assessed by confocal microscope (A) and flow cytometry (B). Magnification of confocal 
image is 3630; numbers on histogram plot are means as ratio to control. C and D: Cytochrome b (Cyt b) mRNA expression was measured in MMCs 
cultured under PhA6HG for 4 h. siCat, MMCs transfected with 20 nmol/L siCat; hCAT, MMCs transfected with 100 ng pCMV-hCat; NAC (5 mmol/L); 
HG (30 mmol/L D-glucose); PhA (100 mmol/L). Data are mean 6 SE of n = 4 experiments in the cell culture study. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. scramble siRNA-
transfected cells;  †P &lt; 0.05 vs. scramble siRNA-transfected cells cultured under PhA+HG; #P &lt; 0.05 vs. siCat-transfected cells cultured under 
PhA+HG; **P &lt; 0.05 between two groups. E: Cyt b mRNA expression was measured in animals at 4 and 10 weeks after the induction of diabetes. WT, 
nondiabetic control mice; WTDM, STZ-induced diabetic WT mice; CKODM, STZ-induced diabetic CKO mice. Data are mean 6 SE of n = 7-8 mice per 
group. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. WT;  †P &lt; 0.05 vs. WTDM at the same duration of diabetes; **P &lt; 0.05 between two groups. </p>

<p>I. HWANG AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, MARCH 2012 </p>

<p>
FIG. 7. Catalase deficiency induced renal lipid accumulation. A: Renal ACO and CPT1-a mRNA expression were analyzed by real-time PCR. B: The 
renal lipids were detected by Oil Red O staining and quantified using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software (15 pictures per animal). Scale bar, 20 mm; magnification 
3630. WT, nondiabetic control mice; WTDM, STZ-induced diabetic WT mice; CKODM, STZ-induced diabetic CKO mice. Data are mean 6 SE of n = 
7-8 mice per group. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. WT;  †P &lt; 0.05 vs. WTDM at the same duration of diabetes; **P &lt; 0.05 between two groups. C: ACO and CPT1-a 
mRNA expressions were measured in MMCs cultured under PhA6HG for 4 h. D: Scramble-or siCat-transfected MMCs were cultured under 
PhA+HG at presence or absence of NAC for 24 h. Lipid droplets in MMCs were detected by Oil Red O staining and quantified using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> (mean of 
10 cells per picture, 5 pictures per group). Magnification 3400. E: FN mRNA was measured in MMCs cultured under PhA6HG for 4 h. F: Secreted 
FN in the media of MMCs cultured under PhA6HG for 24 h was measured by Western blot. siCat, MMCs transfected with 20 nmol/L siCat; hCAT, 
MMCs transfected with 100 ng pCMV-hCat; NAC (5 mmol/L); HG (30 mmol/L D-glucose); PhA (100 mmol/L). Data are mean 6 SE of n = 4 
experiments in the cell culture study. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. scramble siRNA-transfected cells;  †P &lt; 0.05 vs. scramble siRNA-transfected cells cultured 
under PhA6HG; #P &lt; 0.05 vs. siCat-transfected cells cultured under PhA+HG; **P &lt; 0.05 between two groups; n.s. not significant between two 
groups. (A high-quality digital representation of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>PEROXISOMAL DYSFUNCTION IN DIABETIC NEPHROPATHY </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, MARCH 2012 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>attenuated in diabetic CKO kidneys. Although the under-
lying mechanism is unclear, catalase deficiency might have 
inhibited Nrf2 expression in diabetic kidneys, for in chronic 
obstructive pulmonary disease (33), severe oxidative stress 
inhibits Nrf2, which is the primary transcription factor 
responsible for upregulation of oxidative responses. In this 
connection, diabetic renal injury was enhanced in Nrf2 
null mice (34); however, not all endogenous antioxidant 
enzymes play equal roles in diabetic kidneys. For example, 
GPx1 deficiency rendered similar diabetic renal injury in 
WT mice (35). 
Therefore, it is important to delineate the pathogenic 
mechanism involved in accelerated diabetic renal injury 
by catalase deficiency. Accordingly, we attempted to de-
termine whether catalase deficiency disturbs peroxisomal 
biogenesis, leading to increased mitochondrial ROS and 
lipid accumulation observed in DN. Peroxisomes undergo 
reorganization in response to metabolic demands for FA 
b-oxidation under increased FFAs (21,36). In our in vivo 
and in vitro study, PEX5, PEX11-a, and Abcd3 mRNA 
expressions were upregulated in 4 weeks of diabetic WT 
kidneys and MMCs cultured under PhA with or without HG 
but not in diabetic CKO kidneys and catalase knock-down 
MMCs. We also observed increased peroxisomal biogen-
esis markers in response to 100 mmol/L H 2 O 2 , but not .250 
mmol/L, suggesting context-dependent ROS effects (37). 
In the case of mitochondria, under oxidative/metabolic 
stress, initial adaptive increase in mitochondrial biogenesis 
takes place, while excessive ROS can result in mitochon-
drial damage (38). Likewise, H 2 O 2 produced during FA 
b-oxidation may increase peroxisomal biogenesis-related 
genes to meet its metabolic demand, but H 2 O 2 above a 
threshold by catalase deficiency may result in peroxisomal 
damage. NAC and additional catalase using hCAT trans-
fection confirmed that ROS inhibition results in restoration 
of peroxisomal biogenesis in catalase knock-down cells. 
Measurement of in situ H 2 O 2 in kidneys by using recently 
developed methods (39) would be needed to assess the 
effects in vivo. In addition, although the selectivity of siCat 
was confirmed partly by hCAT transfection, use of primary 
MMCs from CKO mice is needed. 
Short-and medium-chain FA derived from the diet are 
exclusively degraded in the mitochondria, whereas per-
oxisomes catalyze very long-chain FA or branched-chain 
FA (40). This specifically implies that there would be a 
metabolic interconnection between the two organelles. In-
deed, mitochondrial abnormalities were described in PEX5-
deficient mice (41) and patients with Zellweger syndrome 
(42). In addition, Elsner et al. (18) showed that accumulated 
H 2 O 2 in the mitochondria was reduced by overexpression 
of peroxisomal catalase in insulin-producing cells. Con-
sistently, the MitoSOX experiment clearly showed that 
basal as well as PhA-induced mitochondrial ROS were 
significantly upregulated in catalase knock-down cells. It is 
notable that mitochondrial ROS, as well as markers of 
peroxisomal biogenesis (PEX5, PEX11-a, and Abcd3) and 
peroxisomal b-oxidation (ACO), were significantly increased 
by PhA treatment alone, which were not significantly dif-
ferent from PhA plus HG treatment, suggesting that PhA 
plays an important role in the regulation of mitochondrial 
ROS, peroxisomal biogenesis, and b-oxidation. We next 
evaluated whether ROS-induced mitochondrial biogenesis 
was also impaired by catalase deficiency. As expected, 
mitochondrial biogenesis estimated by cytochrome b ex-
pression (Fig. 6C and D) and mitochondrial DNA and 
PGC1-a expression (data not shown) were upregulated in </p>

<p>MMCs cultured under PhA with or without HG, which were 
inhibited in catalase knock-down cells. Again, NAC and 
hCAT transfection restored inhibitory effects of catalase 
deficiency, suggesting that mitochondria also are damaged 
at higher levels of ROS. These observations suggest that 
peroxisomal impairment under catalase deficiency may 
result in overexpression of mitochondrial ROS and mito-
chondrial impairment. 
Finally, we determined whether peroxisomal and mito-
chondrial disruption of catalase deficiency influenced lipid 
metabolism in diabetic kidneys. In contrast to increased 
peroxisomal/mitochondrial biogenesis at 4 weeks of dia-
betes, ACO and CPT1-a mRNA expressions were signifi-
cantly decreased in both diabetic groups, and a greater 
decrease was observed in diabetic CKO kidneys than in 
diabetic WT kidneys. Although discrepancies between 
peroxisomal/mitochondrial biogenesis and b-oxidation at 
4 weeks of diabetes are not clear, decreased ACO mRNA 
in diabetic kidneys has been previously observed (43). It is 
conceptually supposed that in early diabetes, increased 
FFAs induce both peroxisomal/mitochondrial biogenesis 
and b-oxidation. However, when ROS are increased with 
development of diabetes, b-oxidation is downregulated. We 
observed that ACO and CPT1-a mRNA expressions were 
increased in response to PhA with or without HG in control 
MMCs, but these were inhibited in catalase knock-down 
cells. We also observed that 100 mmol/L H 2 O 2 decreased 
ACO mRNA expressions but increased peroxisomal bio-
genesis markers (Supplementary Fig. 3A and F), suggesting 
that there might be different thresholds for H 2 O 2 concen-
tration between biogenesis and b-oxidation. However, fur-
ther increased ROS in 10 weeks of diabetes inhibited both 
biogenesis and b-oxidation. Consistent with decreased 
b-oxidation, lipid droplets were increased in diabetic CKO 
kidneys and in catalase knock-down cells cultured under 
PhA plus HG, which were effectively inhibited by NAC. 
Therefore, increased ROS in catalase deficiency impair 
peroxisomal/mitochondrial FA oxidation and subsequently 
increase lipid accumulation, which might induce renal in-
jury, represented by FN expression in MMCs and diabetic 
kidney. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study 
to focus on peroxisomal dysfunction as a cause of redox 
dysregulation leading to diabetes complications under 
catalase deficiency. In summary, the present data provide 
evidence that FFA-induced peroxisomal dysfunction ex-
acerbates diabetic renal injury and that endogenous cat-
alase is an important antioxidant protecting the kidney 
through maintaining peroxisomal and mitochondrial fit-
ness under diabetic stress. Further studies elucidating the 
renoprotective pharmacological and molecular methods 
to restore peroxisomal biogenesis will provide new in-
sight into the therapeutic strategy against diabetic renal 
injury. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by National Research Founda-
tion grants 2011-0006244 and R31-2008-000-10010-0 funded 
by the Korean Ministry of Education, Science, and Tech-
nology; the second stage of the Brain Korea 21 Project; and 
RP-Grant 2009 (2009-1949-1-1) from Ewha Womans Uni-
versity to J.P. 
No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article 
were reported. 
I.H. researched data and wrote the manuscript. J.L. 
and J.P. researched data. J.Y.H. and H.B.L. contributed to </p>

<p>I. HWANG AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, MARCH 2012 </p>

<p>
discussion. Y.-S.H. created the CKO mice. H.H. contributed 
to discussion and reviewed and edited the manuscript. H.H. 
is the guarantor of this work and, as such, had full access to 
all the data in the study and takes responsibility for the 
integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. 
Parts of this study were presented in abstract form at the 
44th Annual Meeting of the American Society of Nephrol-
ogy (abstract TH-PO541), Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 8-13 
November 2011, and at the XLVII ERA-EDTA Congress 
(abstract 451358), Munich, Germany, 25-28 June 2010. 
The authors thank Professors Sue Goo Rhee and Hyun-
Ae Woo at Ewha Womans University for supplying CKO 
mice and pCMV-hCat. </p>



<p>PEROXISOMAL DYSFUNCTION IN DIABETIC NEPHROPATHY </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, MARCH 2012 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

</text></tei>