<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3630384" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>In cancer genome studies, the annotation of newly detected oncogene/tumor suppressor gene candidates is a challenging 
process. We propose using concept lattice analysis for the annotation and interpretation of genes having candidate somatic 
mutations in whole-exome sequencing in acute myeloid leukemia (AML). We selected 45 highly mutated genes with 
whole-exome sequencing in 10 normal matched samples of the AML-M2 subtype. To evaluate these genes, we performed 
concept lattice analysis and annotated these genes with existing knowledge databases. </p>

<p>Acute myeloid leukemia (AML) is one of the most well-
studied diseases in the genomic research area [1, 2]. AML 
occurs usually in middle-aged people and is diagnosed by 
increasing leukemic myeloblasts in blood over 30% [3]. AML 
is a genetically heterogeneous disease, since 1/3 of AML 
patients have chromosomal rearrangements, like t(8;21) and 
t(15;17), but other AML patients have normal karyotypes 
[4]. With recent advances of high-throughput genomic 
technology, a favorable prognosis has been observed with 
some genetic changes in cytogenetically normal AML [5]. 
These results were reflected by the World Health 
Organization (WHO) diagnostic criteria; the NMP1 and 
CEBPA mutations were included in the 2008 revision of 
these criteria [6]. The molecular change of AML is con-
sidered to be the accumulation of somatic mutations in 
hematopoietic progenitor cells [7]. Next-generation sequen-
cing technology gave us new insights into the clonal hete-
rogeneity of leukemic mutations so that we can make an 
explanation why some of these mutations are highly re-</p>

<p>producible but others are very rare [8]. Still, in 30% of 
cytogenetically normal AML, the genetic causality origin or 
strongly associated genetic changes have not yet been 
discovered [9, 10]. 
With advances of high-throughput technology, discovery 
of disease-associated genes is growing [11]. As a conse-
quence, the genetic knowledge databases are growing ra-
pidly. Accordingly, the annotation of candidate causal genes 
in genetic studies is a very challenging process for resear-
chers. We propose a workflow of the detection of somatic 
mutation candidates in 10 normal matched AML samples 
and introduce concept lattice analysis for clustering the 
samples that have highly mutated genes in common. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Primacy sequence analysis </p>

<p>We received the fastq files of whole-exome sequencing 
results of tumor and matched normal sample data of 10 AML 
patients from the Korea Genome Organization in December 
2012. There were no patient-related medical or charac-</p>

<p>www.genominfo.org </p>



<p>Genomics &amp; Informatics Vol. 11, No. 1, 2013 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Primary sequence analysis 
pipeline. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Workflow of detection of somatic mutation candidate from 
exome sequencing of normal matched samples from 10 acute 
myeloid leukemia. </p>

<p>teristic data. We aligned the sequencing reads to the human 
reference genome (hg 19, GRCh37) from USCC by <rs id="software-11" type="software">BWA</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-11" type="version-number">0.6.2</rs> [12] (Figs. 1 and 2). To filter the known single nucle-
otide polymorphisms (SNPs), we used dbSNP bulid 137. We 
removed PCR duplicates and filtering low-quality SNPs by 
<rs id="software-8" type="software">Samtools</rs> <rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-number">0.1.18</rs> [13], <rs id="software-9" type="software">Picard</rs> <rs corresp="#software-9" type="version-number">1.68</rs> [14], and <rs id="software-10" type="software">GATK</rs> <rs corresp="#software-10" type="version-number">2.3.4</rs> 
[15]. After the filtering process, the SAM file was converted 
to VCF file by <rs id="software-15" type="software">VCF Tools</rs> <rs corresp="#software-15" type="version-number">0.1.10</rs> [16]. For detecting somatic 
mutation candidates, we obtained the difference in VCF files 
between tumor and normal samples. For annotation of these 
somatic mutation candidates, we used the ANNOVAR tool 
[17]. </p>

<p>Formal concept analysis </p>

<p>We used formal concept analysis (FCA) for the con-
struction of hierarchical relationships among samples 
sharing highly mutated genes [18]. FCA is a useful method 
in conceptual clustering of objects, attributes, and their 
binary relationship. In FCA, the sets of formal objects and 
formal attributes together with their relation to each other 
form a "formal context," which can be represented by a 
crosstable. In our case, the objects are 10 AML samples, and 
the attributes are 45 highly mutated genes. We defined the 
formal context as K = (G, M, I), where G is a set of objects 
(i.e., samples), M is a set of attributes (i.e., mutated genes), 
and I ⊆ G × M is the incidence relations where (g, m) ⊆ I if 
object g has attribute m. For A ⊆ G and B ⊆ M, we define the 
operators A' = {m ∈ M|gIm for all g ∈ A} (i.e., the set of 
attributes common to the objects in A) and B' = {g ∈ G|gIm 
for all m ∈ B} (i.e., the set of objects common to the 
attributes in B). A pair of (A, B) is a formal concept of k(G, 
M, I) if and only if A ⊆ G, B ⊆ M, A' = B, and A = B'. A is 
called the extent and B is the intent of the concept (A, B). The 
extent consists of all objects belonging to the concept while 
the intent contains all attributes shared by the objects. The 
concept of a given context is naturally ordered by the 
subconcept-superconcept relation, defined by (A1, B1) ≤ 
(A2, B2): ＜=＞ A1 ⊆ A2 (＜=＞ B2 ⊆ B1). </p>

<p>The ordered set of all concepts of the context (G, M, I) is 
denoted by C(G, M, I) and is called the concept lattice of (G, 
M, I). We represent the structure of this concept lattice with 
a Hasse diagram, in which nodes are the concepts and the 
edges correspond to the neighborhood relationship among 
the concepts. All concepts above an object label (below the 
attribute label) include that object (attribute). The top 
element of a lattice is a unit concept, representing a concept 
that contains all objects. The bottom element is a zero 
concept having no object. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Overview of mutations </p>

<p>We have identified 12,908 somatic mutation candidates in 
10 AML sequenced exomes, including 1,281 point muta-
tions, 625 insertion/deletions (Indels) (Table 1, Fig. 3). The </p>



<p>www.genominfo.org </p>

<p>KH Lee, et al. Clustering of Candidate Oncogenes in Acute Myeloid Leukemia Using Concept Lattice Analysis </p>

<p>Samle 
No. 
Synonymous 
SNP 
NS SNPs 
Stopgain 
SNV 
Stoploss 
SNV 
Frameshift 
substitution 
Frameshift 
insertion 
Frameshift 
deletion 
Nonframeshift 
Indel 
Unknown </p>

<p>1 
729 
409 
23 
2 
0 
26 
34 
10 
21 
2 
603 
352 
17 
2 
0 
19 
29 
9 
12 
3 
840 
482 
22 
0 
1 
30 
40 
6 
23 
4 
568 
333 
22 
1 
0 
18 
30 
5 
13 
5 
838 
480 
33 
0 
1 
32 
35 
12 
19 
6 
1,099 
649 
47 
3 
0 
21 
39 
5 
40 
7 
751 
411 
33 
3 
1 
31 
34 
7 
15 
8 
828 
469 
36 
3 
0 
30 
26 
4 
21 
9 
534 
317 
21 
0 
1 
21 
9 
4 
15 
10 
693 
395 
28 
0 
1 
19 
34 
6 
23 
Mean 
748.3 
429.7 
28.2 
1.4 
0.5 
24.7 
31 
6.8 
20.2 
SD 
166.25 
97.16 
9.07 
1.34 
0.5 
5.65 
8.83 
2.69 
8.05 </p>

<p>AML, acute myeloid leukemia; SNP, single nucleotide polymorphism; NS, nonsynonymous; SNV, single nucleotide variation. </p>

<p>Table 1. The distribution of somatic mutation candidates in 10 AML samples </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Distribution of somatic mutation candidates in all samples. 
NS SNV, nonsynonymous single nucleotide variation. </p>

<p>point mutations include 7,483 synonymous single nucle-
otide variations (SNVs), 4,297 nonsynonymous SNVs, 282 
stopgain SNVs, 14 stoploss SNVs, and 5 frameshift sub-
stitutions, and the Indels include 247 frame shift insertions, 
310 frameshift deletions, and 68 nonframe shifts (Fig. 4). 
For each patient, the average nonsynonymous mutation 
count was 429.7 (SD, 97.16). 
About 342 to 665 genes have nonsynonymous somatic 
mutation candidates at least once in each AML sample (Table 
2). Recurrent mutated genes were observed in all samples. </p>

<p>Mutation analysis </p>

<p>The most frequently mutated genes across all samples 
were USP9Y and MUC5B; these genes were mutated in 5 
samples. These genes were also highly mutated in each 
sample; for USP9Y genes, it had 6 nonsynonymous muta-
tions in sample 3. We have selected 45 highly mutated genes 
(1.5%) from 2981 mutated genes. We defined highly mu-
tated genes as genes having 3 or more nonsynonymous 
mutations in each sample (Table 3). In a comparison of 
mutations with the <rs type="software">COSMIC</rs> database [19], among 45 
highly mutated genes, 21 genes matched to hematopoietic 
and lymphoid tissue malignancy terms, and 21 genes 
matched to other cancer types. In 3 genes, there was no 
matched term in <rs type="software">COSMIC</rs> (Table 4). 
We used the concept lattice to construct the hierarchical 
relationship between the samples that had 45 highly 
mutated genes. Concept Biolattice analysis is a mathe-
matical framework based on concept lattice analysis for 
better biological interpretation of genomic data. The top 
element of a lattice is a unit concept, representing a concept 
that contains all objects. The bottom element is a zero 
concept having no object [20, 21]. For comparing with the 
Concept lattice (Fig. 5), we also performed hierarchical 
clustering analysis by Ward method. In hierarchical clus-
tering, cluster 1 has 5 samples (nos. 1, 2, 5, 9, and 10), 
cluster 2 has 2 samples (nos. 4 and 7), and others have 1 
sample each (Fig. 6). We divided the samples into 4 
subgroups by interpretation of the concept lattice result (Fig. 
7). Lattice subgroup 1 shared SYNE1 gene mutation, and 
samples 3, 4, and 7 were included in this subgroup. 
Subgroup 2 was comprised of 5 samples (nos. 1, 2, 5, 6, and 
9) that had MUC5 gene mutations in common. Samples 10 
and 8 could be isolated by the uniqueness of their mutated </p>

<p>www.genominfo.org </p>



<p>Genomics &amp; Informatics Vol. 11, No. 1, 2013 </p>

<p>Sample no. 
No. with more than 
1 mutated genes 
No. with more than 
2 mutated genes 
No. with more than 
3 mutated genes 
No. with more than 
4 mutated genes </p>

<p>1 
454 
30 
7 
3 
2 
369 
31 
3 
1 
3 
513 
47 
9 
3 
4 
370 
30 
4 
0 
5 
532 
39 
7 
3 
6 
665 
72 
14 
5 
7 
465 
41 
5 
2 
8 
506 
46 
10 
1 
9 
342 
20 
2 
0 
10 
442 
29 
5 
1 
Mean 
465.8 
38.5 
6.6 
1.9 </p>

<p>Table 2. Classification of genes according to the count of mutations in each sample </p>

<p>Sample 
no. 
Symbols of 3 or more mutated genes </p>

<p>1 
USP9Y </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, MUC5B </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, TCF19 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>, MUC2 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>, C6orf10, VPS13A, TMEM131 
2 
USP9Y </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, MUC5B </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, BRD2 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>3 
USP9Y </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, SYNE1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>, CDH23, TCF19 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>, MYH10, KIF16B, ITGAX, GRIK1, DMBT1 
4 
SYNE1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>, LAMC3, HELZ2, DNAH8 
5 
MUC5B 
a , MUC6 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>, TCF19 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>, FOXD4L6, ZC3H7B, MYOM2, USP48 
6 
USP9Y </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, MUC5B </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, MUC6 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>, CDSN </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>, WDR81, DMBT1, CYFIP1, TMUB2, PITRM1, PCDHB10, MUC17, KIFC2, KIAA1199, 
ABCA7 
7 
USP9Y </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, SYNE1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>, THAP3, CYFIP1, ANKRD18A 
8 
MUC2 
c , HELZ2, TNRC6C, TNRC18, TECTA, MUC16, MLL3, KANSL1, GPR98, FAM195A 
9 
MUC5B 
a , CDSN </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>10 
MUC6 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>, BRD2 
c , CDH23, OR6V1, DNAH17 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Genes mutated in 5 samples; </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Genes mutated in 3 samples; 
c Genes mutated in 2 samples. </p>

<p>Table 3. List of 3 more mutated genes in 10 AML samples </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Distribution of nonsynonymous somatic mutations in 10 acute myeloid leukemia samples. NS SNPs, nonsynonymous single nucleotide 
polymorphisms. </p>



<p>www.genominfo.org </p>

<p>KH Lee, et al. Clustering of Candidate Oncogenes in Acute Myeloid Leukemia Using Concept Lattice Analysis </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Concept lattice of 45 genes 
and 10 acute myeloid leukemia 
patients having 3 or more non-
synonymous mutations, annotated 
by <rs type="software">COSMIC</rs> database. Red rectan-
gles represent annotated hemato-
poietic and lymphoid tissue malig-
nancy; yellow rectangles represent 
other cancer type annotated in the 
<rs type="software">COSMIC</rs> database. </p>

<p>COSMIC 
cancer type </p>

<p>Hematopoietic and 
lymphoid_tissue </p>

<p>Other cancer 
type 
None </p>

<p>Gene symbol 
ABCA7 
BRD2 
KANSL1 
ANKRD18A 
C6orf10 
FOXD4L6 
CDH23 
CDSN 
HELZ2 
CYFIP1 
DMBT1 
DNAH17 
GRIK1 
DNAH8 
KIF16B 
FAM195A 
KIFC2 
GPR98 
MUC5B 
ITGAX 
MUC6 
KIAA1199 
MYH10 
LAMC3 
OR6V1 
MLL3 
PITRM1 
MUC16 
TCF19 
MUC17 
THAP3 
MUC2 
TMUB2 
MYOM2 
TNRC18 
PCDHB10 
TNRC6C 
SYNE1 
USP48 
TECTA 
USP9Y 
TMEM131 
WDR81 
VPS13A 
ZC3H7B 
Count 
21 
21 
3 </p>

<p>Table 4. Comparison of list of 3 more mutated genes with 
<rs type="software">COMIC</rs> database </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Hierarchical clustering of samples by binarized score of 45 
highly mutated gene states. </p>

<p>gene sharing pattern. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, we proposed a workflow of matched normal 
AML exome sequencing analysis and the framework for 
defining sample subgroups. We observed every sample 
having a nonsynonymous mutation associated with hema-
tological and lymphoid malignancy genes, but the candidate </p>

<p>oncogenes showed diverse characters. 
We selected 45 genes that had 3 or more nonsynonymous 
mutations and performed hierarchical clustering analysis of 
the samples by these genes. In classic hierarchical clustering 
analysis by Ward's method, we could not identify the genetic 
relationship of those clusters. On the other hand, the result 
of concept lattice analysis gave us insight into the mutational 
pattern of each sample. 
In subgroup 1, samples 3, 4, and 7 shared SYNE1 gene 
mutations. SYNE1 gene encodes a spectrin repeat-con-
taining protein expressed in skeletal and smooth muscle and 
peripheral blood lymphocytes that localizes to the nuclear 
membrane [21]. This gene is not a well-known leukemic 
gene but is observed in some hematological malignancies </p>

<p>www.genominfo.org </p>



<p>Genomics &amp; Informatics Vol. 11, No. 1, 2013 </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Subgroup analysis by concept lattice. (A) Subgroup 1 shares SYNE1 mutation in samples 3, 4 and 7. (B) Subgroup 2 shares MUC5B 
mutation in samples 1, 2, 5, 6, and 9. Continued on next page. </p>

<p>and other cancer types [22]. In glioblastoma, SYNE1 muta-
tion is significantly correlated with the overexpression of 
several known glioblastoma survival genes [23]. In the case 
of sample 3, the ITGAX gene, encoding ankyrin repeat 
domain 18A, was mutated. This gene is well known by the 
association with leukemia [24] and lung cancer [25]. For </p>

<p>sample 4, the possible oncogene is LAMC3. LAMC3 gene 
encodes laminins, which are the major non-collagenous 
constituent of basement membrane. LAMC3 mutations are 
associated with several cancers, including colon cancer, lung 
cancer, and melanoma, and candidate tumor suppressor 
genes in bladder transitional cell carcinoma [26]. LAMC3 is </p>



<p>www.genominfo.org </p>

<p>KH Lee, et al. Clustering of Candidate Oncogenes in Acute Myeloid Leukemia Using Concept Lattice Analysis </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Continued from previous page. (C) Subgroup 3 sample 8 only has mutated genes, such as MUC2 and HELZ2. (D) Subgroup 4 
has sample 10, having only mutated genes, like MUC6, CDH23, BRD2, OR6V1, and DNAH17. </p>

<p>involved in the phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase-Akt signaling 
pathway, since it has a role in cell adhesion. The ANKRD18A 
gene is the oncogene candidate for sample 7 and is a novel 
epigenetic regulation gene in lung cancer [25]. Therefore, it 
is possible that the pair relationship of those genes </p>

<p>(ITGAX-SYNE1, LAMC3-SYNE1, and ANKRD18A-SYNE1) 
could contribute together to evolve the leukemic cell 
transformation. 
The major limitation of our study is that we could not 
validate the mutation results by Sanger method or deep </p>

<p>www.genominfo.org </p>



<p>Genomics &amp; Informatics Vol. 11, No. 1, 2013 </p>

<p>sequencing. We selected highly mutated genes having 3 
mutations or more, but this definition is arbitrary, so we 
might have lost candidate oncogenes in some patients. 
In this study, we suggest the concept of clustering samples 
that have diverse mutated genes. AML is very heterogeneous 
genetic disease. Despite the small number of samples we 
have studied, the genetic variation patterns were not com-
mon for all samples. It could have been better to evaluate 
more sample data for analysis by clustering analysis. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by the basic science research 
program through the National Research Foundation of 
Korea (NRF), funded by the Ministry of Education, Science 
and Technology (2012-0000994). This material is based 
upon work supported by the Korea Genome Organization. </p>



</text></tei>