<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3776217" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>This study reports the first set of synthetic molecules that act as broad spectrum agglutination 
agents and thus are complementary to the specific targeting of antibodies. The molecules have 
dendritic architecture and contain multiple copies of zinc(II)-dipicolylamine (ZnDPA) units that 
have selective affinity for the bacterial cell envelope. A series of molecular structures were 
evaluated, with the number of appended ZnDPA units ranging from four to thirty-two. Aggluti-
nation assays showed that the multivalent probes rapidly cross-linked ten different strains of 
bacteria, regardless of Gram-type and cell morphology. Fluorescence microscopy studies using 
probes with four ZnDPA units indicated a high selectivity for bacteria agglutination in the presence 
of mammalian cells and no measurable effect on the health of the cells. The high bacterial selectivity 
was confirmed by conducting in vivo optical imaging studies of a mouse leg infection model. The 
results suggest that multivalent ZnDPA molecular probes with dendritic structures have great 
promise as selective, broad spectrum bacterial agglutination agents for infection imaging and 
theranostic applications. </p>

<p>Increased awareness of microbial resistance to 
clinical antibiotics is motivating researchers to explore 
novel ways of detecting and treating bacterial infec-
tions [1-5]. As an alternative to small molecule phar-
maceuticals, various therapeutic antibody strategies 
have been investigated to either directly target the 
bacterial cells at a site of infection, or alternatively 
neutralize the toxins released by the bacteria [6-8]. The 
exquisite targeting ability of antibodies makes them 
attractive as potential antibiotics. However, despite 
intensive efforts, the first antibacterial antibody has 
only just been approved in the US by the FDA [9]. As 
therapeutics, antibodies have several potential phar-
maceutical drawbacks such as susceptibility to deg-
radation by protease action and poor diffusion into </p>

<p>tissues sites with size restrictions. In order to address 
these challenges, there is ongoing research effort to 
engineer antibodies or antibody fragments with en-
hanced stability and smaller sizes [10, 11]. 
An alternative molecular approach to antibody 
engineering is the development of synthetic molecules 
that are decorated with multiple copies of bacteria 
targeting units. Perhaps the best known structures are 
glycodendrimers with ability to target carbohydrate 
receptors on the surface of bacteria or bacterial toxins 
and thus block adhesion to host cell surfaces [12-16], 
or alternatively act as bacterial imaging agents [17-20]. 
A large fraction of the published glycodendrimer 
work has focused on molecular synthesis, and efforts 
to demonstrate practical utility are ongoing. Other </p>

<p>Ivyspring </p>

<p>International Publisher </p>

<p>Theranostics 2013, Vol. 3, Issue 9 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>structural approaches have employed cationic den-
drimers to target and disrupt bacterial membranes, or 
appended peptides or drugs to the dendrimers to 
create antibiotics with improved pharmacokinetic 
properties [21]. In most of these cases, the bacterial 
cell surface target is a protein or a specific structural 
component of the bacterial cell wall, and thus the 
probe targeting is not necessarily universal to all 
genera of bacteria. Our own efforts to target bacterial 
cell 
surfaces 
has 
focused 
on 
synthetic 
zinc(II)-dipicolylamine (ZnDPA) coordination com-
plexes, such as bZnDPA and mZnDPA (Figure 1), that 
have affinity for the phosphorylated amphiphiles that 
are ubiquitous within the bacterial envelope [22, 23]. 
To date, our work has produced a portfolio of fluo-
rescently labeled bZnDPA probe molecules that act as 
in vitro and in vivo optical imaging agents for bacteria 
[24-30]. One example, that is the starting point for this 
present 
study, 
is 
the 
molecular 
probe 
Bis-SR-bZnDPA (Chart 1/Figure A) [30]. The mole-
cule has two bZnDPA units appended to a central 
squaraine rotaxane scaffold that is intensely fluores-
cent with deep-red absorption/emission wavelengths 
that are well suited for in vitro and in vivo optical im-
aging. We have reported previously that 
Bis-SR-bZnDPA is an effective bacterial imaging 
agent and enables in vivo fluorescence imaging of 
bacterial infection in a mouse model [30]. Here, we 
describe bacterial targeting studies using the multi-
valent probe molecules in Chart 1/Figure A that have </p>

<p>more than two appended ZnDPA units [31]. The pro-
ject goal was to determine if molecular probes with 
multiple ZnDPA units would exhibit selective tar-
geting of bacterial cells in the presence of mammalian 
cells. We find that multivalent ZnDPA probes are 
potent agglutination agents for virtually all strains of 
bacteria. Microscopy studies using the fluorescent 
probe, Tetra-SR-bZnDPA, with four bZnDPA units, 
demonstrated that bacteria targeting in the presence 
of healthy mammalian cells is quite selective. The 
high bacterial selectivity was confirmed by conduct-
ing in vivo imaging studies of a mouse leg infection 
model. Our results suggest that multivalent ZnDPA 
probes with dendritic structures have great promise 
as broad spectrum bacterial agglutination agents for 
potential application in bacterial imaging, diagnostics, 
and antibiotic therapy. </p>

<p>Fig 1. Structures of mZnDPA and bZnDPA affinity units coordinated to a 
generic phosphate diester. </p>

<p>Figure A. (Chart 1). Chemical structures. </p>

<p>Theranostics 2013, Vol. 3, Issue 9 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>General </p>

<p>The synthesis and complete structural charac-
terization of all molecular probes used in this study 
was recently reported elsewhere [31]. Phosphate 
buffered saline refers to a solution containing 4.3 mM 
sodium phosphate, 137 mM sodium chloride, 2.7 mM 
potassium chloride, 1.4 mM potassium phosphate, 
and pH 7.2. DMEM refers to phenol-free Dublecco's 
Minimum Essential Medium containing 2 mM 
L-glutamine and 4.5 g/L glucose. </p>

<p>Cell Culture </p>

<p>The Gram positive bacterial strains were Bacillus 
licheniformis (ATCC # 25972), Staphylococcus aureus 
NRS11, and Staphylococcus epidermidis (ATCC # 
14990). The Gram negative bacterial strains were 
Pseudomonas aeruginosa (ATCC# 27853), Escherichia 
coli K12, Escherichia coli UTI89, Escherichia coli 
MC1655, Klebsiella pneumonia (ATCC# 33495), En-
terobacter aerogenes (ATCC# 35029), and Proteus 
vulgaris (ATCC# 49132). Broth cultures were grown 
at 37 °C in LB (lysogeny broth) medium at a shaker 
speed of 200 rpm. Assays were typically performed 
with cultures undergoing log phase growth and an 
optical density of 0.5 at 600 nm (OD600 = 0.5). The 
mammalian cells lines employed in this study were 
V79 (Chinese Hamster Lung cells, adherent), A594 
(Human Lung Carcinoma, adherent), and HeLa 
(Human cervical adenocarcinoma, adherent). The 
cells were grown to 60% confluence and cultured in 
accordance with ATCC protocols in a humidified in-
cubator maintained at 37°C, in a 5% CO2 atmosphere. </p>

<p>Fluorescence Microscopy </p>

<p>Microscopy experiments typically used 8-well 
microscope chambered slides and a Nikon Eclipse 
TE-2000 U epifluorescence microscope equipped with 
blue DAPI (Exciter: D360/40x, Dichroic: 400DCLP, 
Emitter: 460/50m), green FITC (Exciter: D360/40X, 
Dichroic: 400DCLP, Emitter: HQ535/50m), and 
deep-red Cy5 (Exciter: HQ620/60X, Dichroic: 660LP, 
Emitter: HQ700/75m) filters. Images were acquired 
using a Photometrics 512 B black and white digital 
camera using Metamorph Software V6.2. Images were 
analyzed and prepared using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">ImageJ</rs> open source 
software package (available for free download at 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij</rs>). </p>

<p>Bacteria Agglutination Studies </p>

<p>Aliquots (1 mL) from separate cultures of ten 
different strains of bacteria (grown to OD 600 = 0.5) 
were centrifuged at 5000 x g for 5 minutes. The pellets 
were washed with and then resuspended in 1 mL of 
10 mM HEPES buffer (pH 7.3). The bacterial disper-
sions were added to separate glass slides and each 
slide sample was treated with one of four Tet-
ra-ZnDPA probes (10 µM); 15 minutes later multiple 
brightfield image fields were acquired of each of the 
forty probe/bacteria samples. Using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software, 
five digital images of each bacteria/probe sample 
were randomly selected; the bacterial clusters within 
each image field were digitally encircled as regions of 
interest and the average area of these clusters was 
calculated. For each strain of bacteria, the average 
cluster size induced by each of the four different 
probes was normalized by setting the largest ob-
served cluster size to a relative value of 1.0. The final 
results listed in Table 1. </p>

<p>Table 1. Relative agglutination ability of molecular probes measured by Slide Agglutination Assay. </p>

<p>Relative Agglutination Ability For Each Strain of Bacteria </p>

<p>Bacteria 
Gram 
Tetra-SR-mZnDPA 
Tetra-SR-bZnDPA 
Tetra-mZnDPA 
Tetra-bZnDPA </p>

<p>B. licheniformis 
+ 
0.3 
1.0 
0.5 
0.2 </p>

<p>S. aureus NRS 11 
+ 
1.0 
0.3 
0.2 
1.0 </p>

<p>S. epidermidis 
+ 
&gt;0.1 
1.0 
&gt; 0.1 
0.2 </p>

<p>E. aerogenes 
-
0 
1.0 
&gt; 0.1 
0.4 </p>

<p>E. coli K12 
-
0.1 
0.5 
&gt; 0.1 
1.0 </p>

<p>E. coli MC1655 
-
0.2 
1.0 
0.9 
0.8 </p>

<p>E. coli UTI89 
-
0.4 
1.0 
0 
0.3 </p>

<p>K. pneumoniae 
-
0.4 
1.0 
0.2 
0.8 </p>

<p>P. aeruginosa 
-
0.2 
1.0 
&gt; 0.1 
0.1 </p>

<p>P. vulgaris 
-
0 
1.0 
0 
0.2 </p>

<p>Theranostics 2013, Vol. 3, Issue 9 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>Bacterial agglutination was also studied by flu-
orescence microscopy. After washing, the bacteria 
(OD 600 0.5) were resuspended in 1 mL of 10 mM 
HEPES buffer, pH 7.3, and added to separate glass 
slides. An aliquot of Tetra-SR-bZnDPA or Tet-
ra-SR-mZnDPA (10 µM) was added and the sample 
was incubated at ambient temperature, in the dark, 
for 15 minutes. Excess reagent was removed by cen-
trifuging the samples at 5,000 x g for 5 minutes and 
removing the supernatant. The bacterial pellets were 
resuspended in 1 mL of HEPES buffer and appropri-
ate aliquots were pipetted onto glass slides and im-
aged using fluorescence microscopy. </p>

<p>Microscopy Studies of Mammalian and Bacte-
rial Cell Mixtures </p>

<p>A series of related microscopy experiments vis-
ualized probe-induced agglutination of bacteria in the 
presence of mammalian cells. The mammalian cells 
(A549, HeLa, or V79) were grown to ~60% confluence, 
then washed with phosphate buffered saline (PBS) 
twice, replenished with serum free DMEM, incubated 
with 1 µg/mL DAPI (4',6-diamidino-2'-phenylindole, 
dihydrochloride) for 15-30 minutes at 37 °C in the 
dark. Excess DAPI was removed by washing the 
treated cells with PBS twice, replenishing with serum 
free DMEM media. The DAPI stained mammalian 
cells were then treated with Tetra-SR-bZnDPA or 
Tetra-SR-mZnDPA (10 µM), followed by 50 µL of 
bacteria grown to OD600 of 0.3-0.4, and the samples 
imaged after 15 minutes incubation in serum free 
DMEM. Essentially the same imaging outcome was 
obtained when the bacteria were added to the mam-
malian cells prior to the agglutination agent. A related 
set of studies included Calcein AM (Calce-
in-acetoxymethylester) as an intracellular fluorescent 
probe of cell vitality. In these experiments, the HeLa 
cells were washed with PBS twice, replenished with 
serum free DMEM, then incubated with Tet-
ra-SR-bZnDPA (10 µM) for 15 minutes followed by 
rapid sequential addition of Calcein AM (1 µg/mL) 
and bacterial E. coli K12 cells. After 15 minutes, the 
samples were imaged and healthy HeLa cells were 
indicated by an intense and steady green fluorescence 
signal within the cell cytosol. </p>

<p>Animal Imaging Studies </p>

<p>All animal care and procedures were approved 
by the Notre Dame Institutional Advisory Committee 
of Animal Care. Hairless mice (strain SKH1) were 
anesthetized using 2-3 % v/v isoflurane before infec-
tion, probe injection, and imaging. Infection was 
achieved by injecting a bolus of S. aureus Xen29 (~10 8 
CFU) into the left rear leg of each mouse and 50 µL of </p>

<p>sterile growth media was injected into the right rear 
leg. The mice were then allowed to recover for 3 hours 
before 
intravenous 
injection 
with 
either 
Bis-SR-bZnDPA or Tetra-SR-bZnDPA (10 nmol in 
water) via the tail vein. Fluorescent dorsal images of 
the anesthetized mice were acquired for 5 s (Ex 640 ± 
25, Em 732 ± 37 nm, binning 2 x 2, f/stop 2, 
field-of-view 125 mm), using a Xenogen IVIS Lumina 
that generated 16-bit TIFF format files. Re-
gion-of-interest analysis of the in vivo images was 
performed using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software and circling the ap-
propriate anatomical location of each mouse. The av-
erage pixel intensities of the target (T), non-target 
(NT), and were measured and statistical analyses of 
the cohort produced an average ratio for T/NT with a 
standard error of the mean. 
After imaging studies, the mice were anesthe-
tized by isoflurane inhalation (2-3 % v/v) and eu-
thanized by cervical dislocation. The major organs 
were dissected, placed on low reflectance paper, and 
imaged using the same fluorescence settings de-
scribed above. The biodistribution was determined by 
region-of-interest analysis using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software. 
Free-hand shapes were drawn around each organ and 
mean pixel intensity values were measured. The dif-
ferent organs attenuate a probe's deep-red emission 
intensity to a slightly different degree, depending on 
tissue thickness and pigmentation. The biodistribu-
tion analysis in Figure 8 assumes that fluorescence 
from both probes in a specific organ suffer the same 
amount of signal attenuation and thus, the average 
pixel intensities reflect relative probe concentration in 
the organ. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Bacteria Agglutination Studies </p>

<p>Brightfield microscopy was used to rapidly 
screen the probe molecules in Chart 1/Figure A for 
bacteria agglutination ability. Appropriate aliquots of 
the ten separate cultures of bacteria in HEPES buffer, 
pH 7.3, were placed on microscopy slides and treated 
separately with the four different Tetra-ZnDPA 
probes (10 μM). The typical imaging results in Figure 
2 illustrate a general trend that the two bZnDPA de-
rived probes, Tetra-SR-bZnDPA and Tetra-bZnDPA, 
caused all strains of bacteria to agglutinate, whereas 
the two mZnDPA probes, Tetra-SR-mZnDPA and 
Tetra-mZnDPA, were only partially effective (see 
Supplementary Material: Figure S1 for micrographs of 
the complete series). The importance of the multiple 
ZnDPA units for agglutination effect is highlighted by 
the images in Fig. 2E and 2F which show, respectively, 
extensive 
agglutination 
induced 
by </p>

<p>Theranostics 2013, Vol. 3, Issue 9 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>PAMAM-G4-bZnDPA, a multivalent dendrimer with 
~32 ZnDPA units per molecule, and no agglutination 
induced by the cationic, PAMAM-G4 polyamine 
dendrimer. No agglutination was the observed out-
come when the apo-DPA forms of the probes (lacking 
Zn 2+ ) were tested indicating that the Zn 2+ ions are a 
necessary probe component. Another set of control 
experiments demonstrated that the presence of bovine 
serum albumin (50 mg/mL) did not inhibit the bacte-
rial cell agglutination process. 
A more quantitative assessment of relative ag-
glutination potency for each probe molecule was 
gained by conducting Slide Agglutination Assays, all 
on the same day and under the same conditions 
[32-37]. Appropriate aliquots of the ten bacterial cul-</p>

<p>tures in HEPES buffer were placed on separate mi-
croscopy slides and then treated with separate ali-
quots of the four Tetra-DPA probes (10 μM). This 
process produced forty different probe/bacteria 
mixtures that were imaged using brightfield micros-
copy. For reach mixture, the area of each bacterial 
cluster within five randomly chosen image fields was 
measured digitally and an average cluster area was 
calculated. With each strain of bacteria, the average 
cluster size induced by each of the four probes was 
normalized relative to the largest average cluster size. 
The data in Table 1 lists the relative order of probe 
agglutination ability for each strain of bacteria. The 
data shows that Tetra-SR-bZnDPA was usually the 
most potent agglutination agent. </p>

<p>Fig 2. Representative brightfield images showing agglutination of planktonic bacteria immediately after addition of molecular probes (10 µM) in HEPES 
buffer. E. coli K12 treated with: (A) Tetra-SR-mZnDPA, (B) Tetra-SR-bZnDPA, (C) Tetra-mZnDPA, and (D) Tetra-bZnDPA. S. aureus NRS11 
treated with (E) PAMAM-G4 dendrimer and (F) PAMAM-G4-bZnDPA. </p>

<p>Theranostics 2013, Vol. 3, Issue 9 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>The bactericidal activity of one agglutination 
agent (Tetra-bZnDPA) was assessed using Ethidium 
Bromide III (EtD III), a red fluorescent nucleic acid 
dye that only stains dead bacteria with damaged cell 
membranes. The EtD III was incubated with E. coli 
K12, E. coli UTI89 and S. aureus NRS11 in the presence 
and absence of Tetra-bZnDPA (10 µM). Fluorescence 
microscopy showed that each bacterial population 
contained about 15% of dead cells that were stained 
with EtD III. This was corroborated by plating ex-
periments that incubated the cross-linked bacteria 
overnight on LB agar plates at 37°C. With each bacte-
rial strain, a sample that was cross-linked with Tet-
ra-bZnDPA exhibited similar growth and colony 
formation as an equivalent amount of untreated bac-
teria, indicating no significant bactericidal activity. 
These results indicate that crosslinking of the bacteria 
with a multivalent bZnDPA probe does not affect 
bacteria viability, a conclusion that matches with our 
previous observations that molecular probes with the 
same type of bZnDPA affinity units have low antibi-
otic activity [26]. </p>

<p>Microscopy Studies of Mammalian and Bacte-
rial Cell Mixtures </p>

<p>The highly fluorescent squaraine rotaxane 
probes enabled fluorescence microscopy studies of the 
probe-treated bacteria. In Figure 3 are representative 
images of planktonic E. Coli and S. Aureous bacteria 
that have been cross-linked by Tetra-SR-bZnDPA 
(micrographs for all other bacterial strains crosslinked 
by Tetra-SR-bZnDPA or Tetra-SR-mZnDPA are re-
produced in Supplementary Material: Figure S2). 
Identical imaging experiments with the divalent 
probe, Bis-SR-amide-bZnDPA, showed that it only 
stains the envelope of individual bacteria with very 
little crosslinking (for E. coli K12 see Supplementary 
Material: Figure S3). 
A series of related fluorescence microscopy ex-
periments were conducted to demonstrate the high 
selectivity of the squaraine rotaxane probes for bacte-
ria in the presence of healthy mammalian cells. The 
first set of experiments looked for cell selective agglu-
tination of the bacteria. Live mammalian cells (A549, 
HeLa, or V79) were stained with DAPI, followed by 
treatment with Tetra-SR-bZnDPA and E. coli K12 
cells. The representative bright field and fluorescence 
micrographs in Figure 4 show that the red-emitting 
probes induced agglutination of the bacterial cells 
with no evidence of probe association with the 
mammalian cells. Essentially identical microscopy 
results were obtained with HeLa (human cervical 
adenocarcinoma) and V79 (Chinese hamster lung) 
cells (see Supplementary Material: Figure S4 and </p>

<p>Figure S5). Changing the addition order of Tet-
ra-SR-bZnDPA agglutination agent and bacterial 
cells did not alter the imaging outcome. Additional 
evidence that the Tetra-SR-bZnDPA probe was tar-
geting the agglutinated bacteria was gained by ob-
serving strong colocalization of the red-emitting 
probe with green-emitting P. aeruginosa-GFP, a ge-
netically modified variant of the bacterium that ex-
presses green fluorescent protein (Figure 5). 
Another set of experiments evaluated if the Tet-
ra-SR-bZnDPA probe could enter mammalian cells or 
alter mammalian cell health. One hour incubations at 
37° C of the probe with cultures of healthy mamma-
lian cells (A549, HeLa, or V79) showed no evidence of 
probe entry into the cells (data not shown). Additional 
studies employed Calcein AM, a green-emitting dye 
that measures cell vitality. After cell entry and sub-
sequent hydrolysis, the dye remains trapped in the 
cytosol as long as the cell is viable. The micrographs in 
Figures 6 and Supplementary Material: Figure S6 
show HeLa cells after they were incubated with Tet-
ra-SR-bZnDPA (10 µM) for 15 minutes and then 
treated with Calcein AM (1 µg/mL) and bacterial E. 
coli K12 cells. The intense and steady green fluores-
cence inside the HeLa cells indicated that they re-
mained healthy, while the bacterial cells were 
cross-linked by the red-emitting Tetra-SR-bZnDPA. 
The lack of cell toxicity is consistent with a previous 
report that studied the interaction of multivalent 
ZnDPA nanoparticles with mammalian cells [38]. </p>

<p>Fig 3. Representative deep-red fluorescence and brightfield micrographs 
of agglutinated bacteria after treatment with Tetra-SR-bZnDPA (10 µM) 
in HEPES buffer. (A,C) E. coli K12 and (B,D) S. aureus NRS11. </p>

<p>Theranostics 2013, Vol. 3, Issue 9 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>Fig 4. Representative multicolor fluorescence microscopy images taken 
after the following sequence: human A-549 cells were stained with DAPI (1 
µg/mL), and treated 15 minutes later with Tetra-SR-bZnDPA (10 µM) 
and bacterial E. coli K12 cells, then incubated for another 15 minutes in 
serum free DMEM. Brightfield image (A); blue fluorescence image showing 
DAPI staining of human cell nuclei (B); deep-red fluorescence image 
showing bacteria selectively stained and agglutinated by Tet-
ra-SR-bZnDPA (C); composite image (D). Scale bar = 30 μm. </p>

<p>Fig 5. Representative multicolor fluorescence microscopy images taken 
after the following sequence: human HeLa cells were stained with DAPI (1 
µg/mL), and treated 15 minutes later with Tetra-SR-bZnDPA (10 µM) 
and fluorescent bacterial P. aeruginosa-GFP cells (50 µL, OD 600 = 0.3-0.4), 
then incubated in serum free DMEM for another 15 minutes. Blue fluo-
rescence image showing DAPI staining of human cell nuclei (A); green 
fluorescence image showing P. aeruginosa-GFP cells (B); deep-red fluo-
rescence image showing Tetra-SR-bZnDPA colocalized with bacteria 
(C); composite image (D). Scale bar = 30 μm. </p>

<p>Fig 6. Representative multicolor fluorescence microscopy images of 
human HeLa cells after they were treated with Tetra-SR-bZnDPA (10 
µM) for 15 minutes followed by rapid sequential addition of Calcein AM (1 
µg/mL) and bacterial E. coli K12 cells. Brightfield image (A); green fluo-
rescence indicating viable human cells (B); deep-red fluorescence indicating 
bacteria selectively stained and agglutinated by Tetra-SR-bZnDPA (C); 
composite image (D). Scale bar = 30 μm. </p>

<p>Animal Imaging Studies </p>

<p>The intense, deep-red fluorescence of squaraine 
rotaxane probes permits effective in vivo fluorescence 
imaging of living animals. Indeed, we have already 
reported that Bis-SR-bZnDPA probe enables in vivo 
fluorescence imaging of bacterial infection in mice 
[30]. In this present study, a leg infection imaging 
study was designed to compare the biodistribution of 
tetravalent Tetra-SR-bZnDPA (a potent bacterial ag-
glutination agent) with divalent Bis-SR-bZnDPA 
(does not induce bacterial agglutination). Two cohorts 
of hairless mice (each N=3) were infected with S. au-
reus Xen29 in the left leg. After three hours, the mice 
were injected with 10 nmol of either Bis-SR-bZnDPA 
or Tetra-SR-bZnDPA and imaged at regular intervals 
over a period of 48 hours (Figure 7, a quantitative 
analysis of the in vivo images is provided in Supple-
mentary Material: Figure S7). Bis-SR-bZnDPA exhib-
ited similar imaging performance as previously re-
ported. The amount of probe signal in the infected leg 
reached a peak by 6 hours (T/NT ~ 7.2) and was 
nearly eliminated after 24 hours. The Tet-
ra-SR-bZnDPA showed a similar high degree of se-
lective targeting to the infected leg (T/NT ~ 8.3), with 
maximum accumulation by 6 hours. However, probe 
washout was significantly slower and at 48 hours post 
probe injection, measurable fluorescence signal re-</p>

<p>Theranostics 2013, Vol. 3, Issue 9 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>mained in the infected leg of the living animal. The 
mice were then sacrificed and imaging analysis of the 
excised organs confirmed that there was more Tet-
ra-SR-bZnDPA 
than 
Bis-SR-
bZnDPA in the infected leg (Figure 8). Another nota-
ble difference in the ex vivo biodistribution data is a 
significantly higher amount of Tetra-SR-bZnDPA in 
the lungs. The reason(s) for this are not exactly clear, 
however, one possibility is that crosslinking induced 
by the Tetra-SR-bZnDPA leads to aggregates in the 
blood stream that are trapped by the lung capillaries. </p>

<p>Fig 7. Representative comparison of Bis-SR-bZnDPA and Tet-
ra-SR-bZnDPA targeting S. aureus leg infection in a living mouse. Animals 
were injected with S. aureus (~10 
8 CFU) in the left leg and sterile broth in 
the right leg. Three hours later, 10 nmol of Bis-SR-bZnDPA (series 1) or 
Tetra-SR-bZnDPA (series 2) was injected via the tail vein, and 
whole-animal images were acquired at the stated time points after probe 
dosage. The intensity scale bars (arbitrary units) apply to all images in each 
series. N = 3 for each group. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>To the best of our knowledge, multivalent 
ZnDPA probe molecules are the first examples of 
broad spectrum bacterial agglutination agents. The 
cell discrimination is remarkably high, with fluores-
cence microscopy evidence for selective bacterial ag-
glutination in the presence of healthy mammalian 
cells and no apparent impact on the health of the 
mammalian cells. The high bacterial cell selectivity 
ZnDPA probes agrees with previous reports from our </p>

<p>group [24, 25, 27-30], and others [39], and is also con-
sistent with our independent work to develop these 
probes as selective imaging agents for the anionic 
surfaces of dead and dying mammalian cells [40]. 
Control studies demonstrated that the zinc cations are 
necessary recognition components since apo-versions 
of the molecular probes (lacking Zn 2+ ) did not induce 
agglutination. Agglutination effectiveness increased 
with a higher number of ZnDPA units attached to the 
central organic scaffold (i.e., faster formation of bacte-
rial aggregates and increased mechanical stability of 
the aggregates). Comparative experiments showed 
that bZnDPA probes were more effective than 
mZnDPA probes as agglutination agents. This agrees 
with previous observations that bZnDPA units have 
higher affinity for anionic phospholipid headgroups 
than mZnDPA units due to enhanced electrostatic 
attraction and stronger bidentate coordination bonds 
[41]. 
The Tetra-SR-bZnDPA and Bis-SR-bZnDPA 
probes were compared directly for in vivo fluores-
cence imaging performance using a mouse leg infec-
tion model. Both were effective as bacteria-seeking 
probes. Clearance of the Tetra-SR-bZnDPA probe 
from the site of infection was slower, an observation 
that is consistent with in vivo agglutination. Concep-
tually, the broad spectrum targeting of the multiva-
lent ZnDPA probes is complementary to the specific 
targeting of antibodies. Antibodies have additional 
attributes that promote cell killing and recruitment of 
the host immune response. The multivalent ZnDPA 
probes reported here are not directly bactericidal but 
they may nonetheless have therapeutic value as bac-
teria immobilization agents or be useful as theranostic 
agents. </p>

<p>Fig 8. Bar graph comparing the deep-red fluorescence of organs harvested 
from the infected mice described in Figure 7 that were sacrificed at 48 
hours after dosing with Bis-SR-bZnDPA (blue bars) or Tet-
ra-SR-bZnDPA (red bars). The mean pixel intensity for each organ is 
normalized to the value for the uninfected leg. N = 3 for each group. </p>

<p>Theranostics 2013, Vol. 3, Issue 9 </p>

<p>http://www.thno.org </p>



<p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL </p>

<p>Fig.S1 -S7. http://www.thno.org/v03p0658s1.pdf </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by the NIH (GM 
059078), Walther Cancer Foundation, the University 
of Notre Dame, the Notre Dame Integrated Imaging 
Facility, and the Freimann Life Sciences Center. </p>

<p>COMPETING INTERESTS </p>

<p>The authors have declared that no competing 
interest exists. </p>



</text></tei>