<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3276104" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Cadmium (Cd) is a phytotoxic heavy metal that causes rapid growth reduction. To investigate if Cd interferes with 
the metabolism of auxin, a major growth hormone in plants, poplars (Populus3canescens) expressing a heterologous 
GH3::GUS reporter gene were exposed to 50 mM Cd in hydroponic solutions. Growth, photosynthetic performance, 
lignification, peroxidase activity, auxin concentration, and GUS staining were determined in order to record the 
activities of GH3 enzymes in the stem apex, the elongation zone, wood in the zone of radial growth, and in roots. Cd-
induced growth reductions were tissue-specific decreasing in the order: roots&gt;wood&gt;shoot elongation and leaf 
initiation, whereas Cd concentrations increased in the order: leaves&lt;wood&lt;roots. Cd almost abolished the GH3 
signal in the stem apex but caused strong increases in the vascular system of roots as well as in parenchymatic 
cells in the xylem. These changes were accompanied by increases in lignin and peroxidase activities and decreases 
in auxin concentrations. Since GH3 enzymes remove auxin from the active pool by conjugation and act as mediators 
between growth and defence, our data suggest that Cd stress triggered increases in GH3 activities which, in turn, 
depleted auxin in wood and thereby shunted the metabolism to enhanced formation of lignin. </p>

<p>Cadmium (Cd) is an environmental pollutant that is toxic to 
many plant species at low concentrations (Schü tzendü bel 
and Polle, 2002). Although it has no known physiological 
functions, plants cannot prevent its uptake since it occurs 
via metal transporters required for essential elements 
(Verbruggen et al., 2009). Cd can be accumulated to high 
concentrations in roots, whereas only a minor portion is 
loaded into the xylem and transported to the above-ground 
tissues with the transpiration stream (Polle and Schü tzendü -
bel, 2003). Cd causes inhibition of photosynthesis resulting 
in biomass loss and may eventually cause plant death 
(Sanita di Toppi and Gabrielli, 1999). 
The mechanisms by which Cd causes plant injury are not 
yet fully understood. Cd toxicity was attributed to the </p>

<p>formation of reaction oxygen species and uncontrolled cell 
death when the antioxidative capacity of the cells was 
overwhelmed (Gratao et al., 2005; Sharma and Dietz, 
2009). However, reductions in growth occur much faster 
than the visible symptoms of injury. For example, root 
elongation in herbaceous as well as in tree species was 
retarded rapidly within hours of Cd exposure (Godbold and 
Hü ttermann, 1985; Arduini et al., 1994; Schü tzendübel 
et al., 2001, 2002; Wojcik and Tukiendorf, 2005; Weber 
et al., 2006). This suggests that interactions with growth 
regulators may occur. 
Auxin (indole-3-acetic acid, IAA) is the most abundant 
natural growth hormone in plants controlling apical 
dominance, tropism, shoot elongation, and root initiation </p>

<p>ª 2011 The Author(s). </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-
nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>(Vanneste and Friml, 2009). Apical dominance is maintained 
by an auxin gradient that is formed by IAA transport from 
the shoot apical meristem to the base (Vernoux et al., 2010). 
Meristematic tissues are the main source of auxins. There-
fore, cellular concentrations in the plant body are mainly 
controlled by transport processes, degradation or conjuga-
tion with other metabolites (e.g. amino acids, carbohydrates, 
etc) into inactive forms (Normanly et al., 1995). The 
conjugation to amino acids is catalysed by auxin amido 
synthases (group II GH3 enzymes). Their promoters are 
regulated by common auxin-responsive promoter elements 
(Staswick et al., 2005). Recently, it was discovered that GH3 
enzymes constitute a link between plant growth adaptation 
and environmental constraints since they decrease the 
concentrations of active auxin, thereby inactivating auxin-
regulated genes and shifting the resources to defence (Park 
et al., 2008). 
There is increasing evidence that auxins play important 
roles in the seasonal adaptation of trees to climatic stress, 
but also to other environmental constraints (Schrader et al., 
2003; Popko et al., 2010). In poplar stems exposed to salt 
stress, decreases in free auxin were paralleled by decreases in 
vessel lumina and increased wall strengths as an adaptation 
to the increased osmotic pressure (Junghans et al., 2006). 
Recently, Teichmann et al. (2008) observed cell-specific 
developmental patterns and changes in response to bending 
or salinity using poplars transformed with the well charac-
terized auxin-responsive soybean GH3::GUS reporter gene 
(Hagen et al., 1991). Their results indicated that adjustment 
of the internal auxin balance in wood in response to 
environmental cues involves GH3 auxin conjugate syn-
thases, pointing to a role of these enzymes in plant stress 
adaptation. 
In the present study, GH3::GUS poplar (Popu-
lus3canescens) was used to characterize the effect of Cd on 
auxin physiology along the stem axis and in roots in 
relation to growth performance and photosynthesis. It is 
shown that growth decreases in the stem were related to 
high GUS activity, decreased auxin concentrations, 
increased peroxidase activities, and increased lignification. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Preparation of plants, growth conditions, and Cd exposure 
Populus3canescens (a hybrid of P. tremula3P. alba, clone 
INRA717 1-B4) wild type and three independent GH3::GUS 
reporter lines (31, 51, and 54) were multiplied by in vitro micro-
propagation after the method of Leplé et al. (1992). The 
construction of the GH3::GUS reporter lines has been described 
elsewhere (Teichmann et al., 2008). Rooted plantlets were accli-
mated to ambient conditions [22°C air temperature, 18 h 
photoperiod with 200 lmol quanta m 
À2 s 
À1 photosynthetically 
active radiation (PAR) and 60% relative air humidity] in hydro-
ponic Long Ashton nutrient solution (Hewitt and Smith, 1975) in 
a growth room for 40 d. The nutrient solution was changed 
regularly once a week. Subsequently, the plants were transferred to 
a greenhouse equipped with supplementary lighting of 180-200 
lmol quanta m 
À2 s 
À1 PAR (16 h photoperiod, F58 W/125 T8 </p>

<p>fluorescent lamps, Havells Sylvania GmbH, Erlangen, Germany). 
The temperature fluctuated between 21°C and 25°C. 
Plants with shoot heights of 17.964.4 cm were selected. The 
plants were transferred to containers (n¼6 per 20 litre container) 
with Long Ashton nutrient solution mixing three transgenic lines 
and wild-type (WT) poplars. The nutrient solution in the contain-
ers was aerated with filtered air and was renewed regularly once 
a week. The plants were acclimatized to greenhouse conditions for 
2 weeks. 
For Cd exposure, eight containers were supplied with 50 lM 
CdSO 4 in the nutrient solution. Cd was applied with every renewal 
of the nutrient solution. The plants were exposed for 24 d to Cd. 
The same amount of plants was maintained in solutions without 
cadmium. </p>

<p>Photosynthetic performance 
Photosynthetic gas exchange measurements were performed using 
a portable photosynthesis system (HCM-1000, Walz, Effeltrich, 
Germany) with additional light of 700 lmol quanta m 
À2 s 
À1 PAR. 
Chlorophyll fluorescence was determined with a pulse-modulated 
chlorophyll fluorometer (MINI-PAM, Walz, Effeltrich, Germany) 
on the upper surface of the first fully expanded leaf at the top of 
each plant on three occasions in the light (180-200 lmol quanta 
m 
À2 s 
À1 PAR) and pre-dawn. The quantum yield of photosystem II 
(U) was calculated according to Genty et al. (1989):U dark ¼(F m -F 0 )/ 
F m and U light ¼ </p>

<p>F ' 
m À F ' </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>
=F ' 
m where U dark ¼maximum quantum 
yield of photosystem II, U light ¼actual quantum yield of photosys-
tem II, F m ¼maximum fluorescence in darkness, F ' 
m ¼maximum 
fluorescence in light, F ' 
o ¼basic fluorescence in light, and F 0 ¼basic 
fluorescence in darkness. </p>

<p>Growth and biomass 
To monitor growth, shoot lengths, stem diameters at the root 
neck, leaf numbers, and root lengths were determined regularly 
twice a week. Root length was determined as the distance between 
the root-shoot junction and tip of the main root. After 24 d of Cd 
exposure, plants were harvested. Each plant was separated into 
stem, leaves, and coarse and fine roots. The fresh mass of each 
fraction was determined. Aliquots were frozen in liquid nitrogen 
and stored at -80°C for biochemical analysis. Fresh materials 
were used for GUS staining. All residual materials were oven-dried 
at 70°C for 7 d and used for dry mass determination. </p>

<p>Biochemical analysis 
Frozen plant tissues were ground in liquid nitrogen, extracted in 
phosphate buffer, gel-filtered, and used to determine peroxidase 
activities (POD) with guaiacol as the substrate (Polle et al., 1990). 
Total soluble protein content was determined with a bicinchoninic 
acid assay (Uptima, Montflucon, France) and bovine serum 
albumin as the standard. Indole-3-acetic acid was quantified in 
stem wood by GC-MS analysis as reported previously by 
Teichmann et al. (2008). Six plants were used per treatment and 
tissue. </p>

<p>Quantification of lignin 
Oven-dried materials were ground to a fine powder and used to 
determine lignin content with the acetylbromide method as de-
scribed by Brinkmann et al. (2002). Six plants were used per 
treatment and tissue. </p>

<p>Cadmium analysis 
Dry and powered plant materials were pressure digested in HNO 3 
and the extracts were used for elemental analysis by induced 
coupled plasma atomic emission spectroscopy (SPECTRO CIRO </p>



<p>CCD, GmbH &amp; Co KG, Kleve, Germany) in the laboratory of soil 
sciences (Heinrichs et al., 1986). </p>

<p>GUS activity staining and histochemical lignin analysis 
b-Glucuronidase (GUS) staining was performed after the method 
of Hagen et al. (1991) with minor modifications as described by 
Teichmann et al. (2008). Stem sections of three regions: apex, 
elongation zone (2.5 cm below apex), and secondary growth zone 
(about 150 mm above the root-shoot junction) were used (see 
scheme in Supplementary Fig. S1 at JXB online). Three small 
lateral roots were carefully removed from the longest root of each 
plant. GUS staining was conducted with fresh tissues. The stem 
apex was cut longitudinally, other parts were cross-sectioned by 
hand and whole root tips were used for infiltration with the GUS 
staining buffer. Initially, materials from six plants per line and 
treatment were harvested, of which materials from three plants per 
line and per treatment were processed further. The materials were 
incubated for 24 h in buffer, destained, and photographed using 
a digital camera (CoolPix 4500, Nikon Corporation, Tokyo, 
Japan) under a stereo microscope (Stemi SV11, Zeiss, Oberkochen, 
Germany). Magnification used was in the range of 1.0 to 3.2. 
For lignin staining frozen stem sections were cut to a thickness 
of 20 lm with a freezing microtome (CryoCut, Reichert-Jung, 
Wien, Austria) and were either stained with Mäule reagent and 
mounted in glycerol as described previously (Rana et al., 2010) or 
were directly observed under an epifluorescence microscope 
(Axioplan, Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany) with the filter combina-
tion G365, FT395, LP420 (Zeiss) and photographed as above. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Data were analysed with a statistical programme <rs id="software-0" type="software">JMP</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.1</rs> Start 
Statistics, third edition (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Inc., Cary, North Carolina, 
USA). Differences between WT and reporter lines were tested 
using One-Way-ANOVA and data were pooled when no difference 
was found. Data are means (6SE). Separation of means was 
performed by t test. A probability level of P &lt;0.05 was considered 
to indicate significant differences. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Effect of Cd on photosynthesis, growth and biomass 
production in WT poplar and transgenic lines 
expressing the GH3::GUS auxin reporter gene </p>

<p>WT poplars and three independent GH3::GUS lines were 
analysed, but no differences between WT and reporter 
plants with respect to plant performance were observed. 
Therefore, the data of the WT and GH3::GUS lines were 
pooled to investigate the influence of Cd. In all plant lines, 
Cd treatment caused significant reductions in carbon 
assimilation and in the quantum yield of photochemistry in 
light as well as in darkness compared with the controls 
(Table 1). 
Cd treatment caused significant growth reductions in leaf 
formation, shoot height growth, stem radial growth, and 
root elongation compared with the controls (Fig. 1A-D), 
which resulted in significant decreases in plant biomass 
(Table 1). However, the growth reductions differed between 
the different tissues: shoot elongation and leaf formation 
almost stopped after 1 week of Cd exposure (Fig. 1A, B), 
whereas stem radial growth was reduced from 2 weeks of 
Cd exposure onwards (Fig. 1C). From the beginning, the </p>

<p>root lengths of Cd exposed plants were lower than those of 
control plants but their growth rates were less affected than 
those of the other tissues (Fig. 1D). During the last week of 
Cd exposure, the growth rates of roots were diminished by 
50%, whereas the radial increment and height increment 
decreased by 64% and 100%, respectively, compared with 
untreated plants (Table 2). These growth reductions did not 
correspond to Cd accumulation, which was higher in roots 
than in stem and leaves, respectively (Table 3). </p>

<p>Effect of Cd on auxin physiology and lignification </p>

<p>To examine whether the observed differences in growth 
responses were related to effects of Cd on the auxin 
physiology of poplar, GUS activity in plants transformed 
with GH3::GUS was monitored along the vertical axis from 
the root to the stem apex. 
Control roots showed GUS activity in the meristematic 
region of the root tips but not in young developing vascular 
tissues (Fig. 2A, cross-section). By contrast, the vascular 
system of Cd-exposed plants showed strong GUS staining 
(Fig. 2B). Cross-sections revealed that the GUS activity was 
confined to the living cells within the endodermis, i.e. 
pericycle, procambium, and primary phloem (Fig. 2B). 
Lignification and peroxidase activities of fine roots were 
increased in response to Cd treatment, whereas the protein 
concentration of the tissues remained unaffected (Table 4). 
In the apical stem region, untreated poplars showed 
strong GUS activity in the top meristem, the procambium, 
leaf primordia, and the ground parenchyma, whereas in Cd-
exposed poplars the signal was low and mainly detected in 
subapical leaf primordia (Fig. 3A). 
In the elongation zone, GUS activity of controls was 
mainly confined to the primary xylem, which appeared in 
bundles, and in the adjacent perimedullary zone towards the 
pith, but not in the pith (Fig. 3B). Cd-treated plants showed 
stronger GUS activity compared with the controls, forming 
a continuous strip in vascular tissues (Fig. 3B). Fibres of the 
secondary phloem appeared as a brown dashed ring 
separating unstained outer cortical tissues from the inner 
stained phloem (Fig. 3B). 
In the secondary growth zone towards the stem base, 
strong GUS activity was observed in the bark of untreated </p>

<p>Table 1. Effect of cadmium on photosynthetic and growth 
performance of Populus3canescens 
Plants were analysed after 24 d of exposure to 50 lM Cd in 
hydroponic solution. Data for chlorophyll fluorescence U and 
biomass are means of n¼48 (6SE) and n¼5 (6SE) for photosyn-
thetic gas exchange. Different letters in rows indicate significant 
differences at P &lt;0.05. </p>

<p>Parameter 
Control 
Cd (50 mM) </p>

<p>U (light) 
0.69060.018 b 
0.59760.049 a 
U (darkness) 
0.80160.012 b 
0.73560.021 a 
Net photosynthesis (lmol CO 2 m 
À2 s </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>) 
1 0 . 5 60.3 b 
3.262.8 a 
Total plant dry mass (g) 
9.060.9 b 
5.160.4 a </p>

<p>Poplar and cadmium stress | 1415 </p>

<p>plants as well as in the region of the primary xylem 
(Fig. 3C). In Cd-treated plants, a clear shift in GUS staining 
was found: while the phloem retained GUS activity, it was 
no longer detected in the outer bark (Fig. 3C). Woody 
tissues of Cd-treated plants exhibited higher GUS activity 
along ray and axial parenchyma than controls leading to </p>

<p>the impression of strong blue staining of the whole xylem 
(Fig. 3C). The wood of Cd-exposed poplars contained about 
2-fold higher lignin concentrations than that of the controls. 
The increased lignification corresponded to increased perox-
idase activities, while auxin concentrations dropped below 
the detection limit (Table 4). Histochemical lignin analysis in 
stem cross-sections showed that the gross pattern of lignifica-
tion was unaffected, but that Cd-exposed plants displayed 
a darker outer xylem ring compared to untreated controls 
(see Supplementary Fig. S2 at JXB online). The difference in 
staining intensity was clearer at higher magnification and 
particularly pronounced in the zone of the young xylem, 
which displayed almost no coloration in controls and strong 
staining in Cd-exposed plants (Fig. 4A, B). Similarly, lignin 
autofluorescence appeared dampened in the young develop-
ing xylem of controls (Fig. 4C) and bright, especially around 
the new vessels, in Cd-exposed plants (Fig. 4D). The vessels 
formed under the influence of Cd were smaller than those of 
controls (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, it has been shown that the growth responses 
of poplar to Cd differ between different organs and do not 
correspond to Cd accumulation. This indicates tissue-
specific Cd sensitivity. Previous studies revealed that Cd 
also caused tissue-specific oxidative stress in poplar with </p>

<p>Table 3. Cadmium concentrations after 24 d of exposure in 
different Populus3canescens tissues 
Measurements were performed after 24 d of Cd exposure in the 
tissues of leaf, stem, and fine roots. Data are means of n¼4 (6SE) 
for leaves and fine roots and of n¼6 and n¼12 (6SE) for the 
controls and Cd-treated plants of stem tissues, respectively. 
Different letters indicate significant differences at P &lt;0.05. </p>

<p>Cd treatment 
(mM) </p>

<p>Leaves 
(mg g 
À1 DW) </p>

<p>Stem 
(mg g 
À1 DW) </p>

<p>Root 
(mg g 
À1 DW) </p>

<p>0 
2 1 63 a 
30616 a 
36610 a 
50 
76627 a 
1376638 b 
65206930 c </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Growth of Populus3canescens during exposure to 50 lM 
cadmium in the nutrient solution. Leaf formation (A), shoot height (B), 
stem radial diameter (C), and root lengths (D). Growth measure-
ments started after Cd addition for treated (closed circles) and 
untreated control plants (open circles). Data are means of n¼48 
(6SE). Different letters indicate significant differences at P &lt;0.05. </p>

<p>Table 2. Effect of cadmium treatment on the growth rates of 
different Populus3canescens organs 
Plants were exposed for 24 d to 50 lM Cd in hydroponic 
solutions. Growth rates of leaf initiation, shoot height, stem radial 
diameter, and root lengths were determined in the last week of Cd 
exposure. Data are means of n¼48 (6SE). Different letters indicate 
significant differences at P &lt;0.05. </p>

<p>Cd 
treatment 
(mM) </p>

<p>Number of 
leaves 
(leaves d </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Shoot 
height 
(mm d 
À1 ) </p>

<p>Stem 
diameter 
(mm d </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Root 
length 
(mm d 
À1 ) </p>

<p>0 
0.7760.04 b 
16.560.7 b 
0.1160.01 b 
15.560.7 b 
50 
0.0960.01 a 
-0.460.1a 
0.0460.01 a 
7.860.9 a </p>



<p>higher H 2 O 2 formation in wood than in roots (He et al., 
2011). In Cd-exposed roots H 2 O 2 accumulation was con-
fined to the root elongation zone and growth reductions 
have been attributed to peroxidase-mediated cell wall cross-</p>

<p>linking and lignification (Schü tzendübel et al., 2001, 2002). 
Morphological and anatomical changes such as reduced root 
elongation and the formation of smaller vessels have also 
been detected in Cd-exposed pea roots (Rodriguez-Serrano </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Representative pictures of GH3::GUS induction in fine roots of P.3canescens of untreated control plants (A) and of Cd-exposed 
plants (B). Tissues of wild-type plants (WT) and three independent GH3::GUS reporter lines were treated with or without cadmium (50 lM) 
for 24 d and analysed afterwards. Images of two lines are shown. The third line showed the same pattern. Figures indicate the following 
cells types: 1, endodermis; 2, pericycle; 3, primary phloem; 4, procambium; 5, primary xylem; and 6, cortex. </p>

<p>Poplar and cadmium stress | 1417 </p>

<p>et al., 2006). The present data suggest that an up-regulation 
of GH3 enzymes might have contributed to growth 
attenuation and the activation of defences since, in addition 
to the increases in lignin found here, strong accumulation of 
phenolic compounds has also been reported for Cd-exposed 
poplar roots (He et al., 2011). Our cytochemical data 
indicate that these increases were particularly pronounced 
in the young developing xylem, thereby probably leading to 
a loss in tissue extensibility, and thus, the observed growth 
reduction. 
The activation of secondary metabolism and lignification are 
common responses to Cd in plants across different kingdoms, 
such as conifers (Radotic et al., 2000; Schützendübel et al. 
2001), poplars (this study; He et al., 2011) as well as in 
herbaceous species including Arabidopsis (Van de Mortel </p>

<p>et al., 2008). Early studies have demonstrated links between 
auxin and lignin formation. For example, incubation of wheat 
internodes with auxin inhibited lignin formation (Parish, 
1969). Stimulation of auxin catabolism by Cd resulted in 
increased lignification in the stems of pea (Chaoui and El 
Ferjani, 2005). In Arabidopsis, copper stress decreased auxin 
levels, increased lignification, and decreased root elongation 
(Lequeux et al., 2010). Our data show that Cd has a strong 
effect on auxin physiology by affecting the pattern of GH3 
enzymes (Figs 2, 3). It has previously been shown that 
GH3::GUS was inducible by external auxin application and 
that high GUS staining intensity in the apex corresponded to 
high auxin concentration in this tissue (Teichmann et al., 
2008). Decreased GUS activities in the stem apex of Cd-
exposed plants probably indicate decreases in auxin bio-
synthesis. Similarly, Arabidopsis seedlings expressing GUS 
under the synthetic auxin-sensitive DR5 promoter suggested 
reductions in auxin in cotyledons of Cd-exposed plants (Xu 
et al., 2010). 
In poplar, the GUS response pattern to Cd was unexpect-
edly complex. While untreated poplars displayed decreasing 
GUS staining from the apex to the base, which correlated with 
decreasing IAA concentrations (Teichmann et al., 2008), Cd 
exposure reversed the staining pattern, even though Cd-
stressed wood contained almost no free auxin (Table 4). At 
first glance, this result appears paradoxical. However, it is 
important to note that tissue sensitivity to auxin changes with 
environmental and physiological stage (Ludwig-Müller, 2011). 
Furthermore, GH3 promoters contain other regulatory ele-
ments in addition to auxin response motives, in particular 
binding sites for bZIP and Myb transcription factors (Liu 
et al., 1994; Ulmasov et al., 1995; Heinekamp et al., 2004; Shin 
et al., 2007). Screening of Arabidopsis microarrays retrieves </p>

<p>Table 4. Effect cadmium treatment on soluble protein contents, 
peroxidase activities, lignin and auxin concentrations in roots and 
stem wood of Populus3canescens 
Measurements were performed in the stem wood and fine roots 
after 24 d of exposure to 50 lM Cd in hydroponic solutions. Data 
are means of n¼6 (6SE) per treatment and tissue. Different letters 
in rows indicate significant differences at P &lt;0.05. </p>

<p>Tissue 
Parameter 
Control 
Cd </p>

<p>Root 
Protein (mg g 
À1 DM) 
92614 a 
82616 a 
Root 
Peroxidase (nkat g 
À1 DM) 
12336268 a 
22376240 b 
Root 
Lignin (mg g 
À1 DM) 
10.460.4 a 
14.960.8 b 
Stem 
Protein (mg g 
À1 DM) 
4361 a 
4061 a 
Stem 
Peroxidase (nkat g 
À1 DM) 
1463 a 
639670 b 
Stem 
Lignin (mg g 
À1 DM) 
8.460.2 a 
17.060.6 b 
Stem 
Auxin (nmol g 
À1 DM) 
0.87660.150 a 
0.02160.010 b </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Changes in GH3::GUS induction along the stem axis of P.3canescens. GUS staining was performed in the stem apex (A), the 
elongation zone, 25 mm below the apex (B), and in the secondary growth zone, 150 mm above the bottom (C). The three panels 
represent WT and two independent GH3::GUS reporter lines, which were treated with or without cadmium (50 lM) in the nutrient 
solution for 24 d. The scale bar for each panel is indicated in one picture. The numbers from 1 to 7 indicated in (B) indicate the following 
tissues: pith (1), secondary xylem (2), sclerenchyma (3), primary xylem (4), epidermis (5), cortex (6), and secondary phloem (7), 
respectively. </p>



<p>several MYB and bZIP genes that are up-regulated in 
response to Cd stress, while a number of auxin-responsive 
genes are down-regulated (Weber et al., 2006; Van de Mortel 
et al., 2008). Myb77 senses energy limitations and regulates 
GH3 enzymes accordingly (Shin et al., 2007). The mechanistic 
details in poplar remain elusive, but the decreases in CO 2 
assimilation (Table 1) indicate reduced carbohydrate supply in 
Cd-stressed poplars. The strong activation of GH3 enzymes in 
the wood of these plants suggests that, under these conditions, 
high IAA conjugation rates take place depleting the pool of 
active auxin. Since the loss of auxin was high (Table 4), it 
is likely that the conjugates were targeted to oxidative 
degradation (Ö stin et al., 1998). This, together with lacking 
replenishment of the cellular pools by import, might have </p>

<p>switched the metabolism from growth to defence involving the 
activation of peroxidases and lignification. 
In conclusion, the present study shows that GH3 enzymes 
are involved in the Cd-response of poplar in a tissue-specific 
manner. Since poplar contains 12 putative IAA-amido 
synthases (Teichmann et al., 2008), further studies are 
needed to disentangle their functions in environmental 
adaptation of growth responses of wood. </p>

<p>Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data can be found at JXB online. 
Supplementary Fig. S1. Overview of a typical poplar 
plantlet and sampling positions. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Lignin in cross-sections of the secondary growth zone of the stem of P.3canescens in the absence (A, C) or presence of 50 lM 
Cd (B, D). The bark was removed. In each subfigure, the age of the tissue increases from the top (young) to the bottom (old). Lignin was 
stained with Mä ule reagent (A, B) or observed as autofluorescence (C, D). Scale bar: 50 lm. </p>

<p>Poplar and cadmium stress | 1419 </p>

<p>Supplementary Fig. S2. Overview of lignification in 
poplar cross-section of plants treated without (A) or with 
(B) 50 lM cadmium in the nutrient solution. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We are grateful to the University of Khartoum, Sudan for 
providing a scholarship to ME and to the Poplar Research 
Group (PRG) for support via the German Science Founda-
tion (DFG). The excellent technical assistance of C Kettner, 
M Smiatacz, P Meyer, and S Elend is gratefully appreciated. </p>







<p>Poplar and cadmium stress | 1421 </p>

</text></tei>