<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3077646" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Transcription, the synthesis of RNA from a DNA template, is 
performed by multisubunit RNA polymerases (RNAPs) in all 
cellular organisms. The bridge helix (BH) is a distinct feature of 
all multisubunit RNAPs and makes direct interactions with sev-
eral active site-associated mobile features implicated in the 
nucleotide addition cycle and RNA and DNA binding. Because 
the BH has been captured in both kinked and straight confor-
mations in different crystals structures of RNAP, recently sup-
ported by molecular dynamics studies, it has been proposed that 
cycling between these conformations is an integral part of the 
nucleotide addition cycle. To further evaluate the role of the BH, 
we conducted systematic alanine scanning mutagenesis of the 
Escherichia coli RNAP BH to determine its contributions to 
activities required for transcription. Combining our data with 
an atomic model of E. coli RNAP, we suggest that alterations in 
the interactions between the BH and (i) the trigger loop, (ii) fork 
loop 2, and (iii) switch 2 can help explain the observed changes 
in RNAP functionality associated with some of the BH variants. 
Additionally, we show that extensive defects in E. coli RNAP 
functionality depend upon a single previously not studied lysine 
residue (Lys-781) that is strictly conserved in all bacteria. It 
appears that direct interactions made by the BH with other con-
served features of RNAP are lost in some of the E. coli alanine 
substitution variants, which we infer results in conformational 
changes in RNAP that modify RNAP functionality. </p>

<p>Multisubunit RNA polymerases (RNAPs) 
3 function as com-
plex molecular machines that are central to regulated gene 
expression in all cellular organisms (1-3). Multiple conforma-
tional changes accompany and are required for the action of 
RNAP. These can be modulated in magnitude and frequency by 
control factors that act as regulatory signals. The catalytically 
competent core enzyme (␣ 2 ␤␤Ј; in bacteria) is highly con-
served across all domains of life in its ternary structure and </p>

<p>sequence (1-4). The acquisition of high resolution structures 
of RNAPs and their complexes from bacteria, yeast, and 
archaea, coupled with biochemical and biophysical analyses of 
RNAP domain functionalities, has led to a detailed molecular 
level appreciation of how the enzyme functions in promoter 
recognition, transcription initiation, elongation, and pausing 
(1, 3, 5). 
One prominent conserved structural feature of RNAP is the 
␤Ј bridge helix (BH) (see Fig. 1A), an ␣-helical domain that 
spans the active site of the enzyme (5, 6). Other conserved 
structural features of the RNAP active center include ␤ fork 
loop 2 (FL2), which maintains the downstream edge of the tran-
scription bubble, and the ␤Ј lid domain, which helps maintain 
the upstream edge of the RNA-DNA hybrid (3, 5, 7, 8). Along 
with the BH, another feature of the RNAP catalytic center is the 
trigger loop (TL); both are involved in NTP binding and trans-
location and have been captured in distinctly different confor-
mations, implying that they possess dynamic characteristics 
(9 -15). Proposed mechanisms of the translocation event, asso-
ciated with extension of the RNA chain, postulate that binding 
of the incoming NTP is coupled with a conformational change 
in the BH-TL assemblage for stepwise forward movement of 
RNAP (7, 9, 13, 14, 16, 17). An additional feature of the RNAP 
catalytic site, the ␤Ј F-loop (also termed conserved region 
␤Јa15) (3), has also been demonstrated to play an essential role 
(alongside the BH and TL) in catalysis by bacterial RNAPs (18). 
Several RNAP-interacting factors function through or with the 
BH and TL. The phytotoxin tagetitoxin binds in the vicinity of 
the active center, inhibiting RNAP elongation (19) potentially 
by restricting movements of the BH and TL. Streptolydigin 
binds to the BH and interferes with the nucleotide addition 
cycle, thereby inhibiting RNAP activity (11, 20). Furthermore, 
the transcript cleavage factor Gre appears to assist in RNAP 
backtracking and stimulates RNA cleavage via the BH and TL 
(21-24). 
Mutating residues in the BH can result in fast (F773V in 
Escherichia coli) (25) or "super-active" (S824P in Methanocal-
dococcus jannaschii) (26) variants of RNAP. To gain further 
insights into the contributions the BH makes to RNAP activi-
ties, we conducted comprehensive alanine scanning mutagen-
esis of the BH feature of E. coli RNAP (see Fig. 1B). Mutants 
were assayed for (i) promoter-specific (i.e. -dependent), (ii) 
nonspecific promoter-independent, and (iii) specific (RNA 
primer-dependent) promoter-independent transcription activ-
ities (see "Experimental Procedures" and Fig. 1C), as well as 
effects on in vivo growth. Taken together, our results generate a </p>

<p>. 
3 The abbreviations used are: RNAP, RNA polymerase; BH, bridge helix; FL2, 
fork loop 2; TL, trigger loop; STA, srandard transcription assay. </p>

<p>comprehensive activity map of the E. coli RNAP BH (see Fig. 2). 
A number of residues important for transcript formation were 
identified. Inspection of an atomic model of E. coli RNAP (Pro-
tein Data Bank code 3LU0) (27) determined that altered inter-
actions between the BH and (i) the TL, (ii) the F-loop, (iii) FL2, 
and/or (iv) switch 2 of RNAP may be linked to the observed 
defects (in the BH alanine substitution mutants). In particular, 
lysine at position 781, which is invariant in bacteria, appears to 
be essential in all of the in vitro activities tested. The BH vari-
ants that fail in elongation and pyrophosphate-mediated RNA 
cleavage harbor potential defects in the catalytic activity used 
for RNA synthesis. BH variants that display significantly 
reduced in vivo growth activities (in contrast to their observed 
in vitro activities) could display defects not directly tested by 
our in vitro assays, e.g. promoter pausing. Finally, two BH vari-
ants (V801A and D802A) exhibited severely impaired minimal 
scaffold-binding activities; we infer that these represent forms 
of RNAP in which the clamp domain may adopt a more closed 
conformation. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>Mutagenesis of E. coli rpoC-Single alanine substitutions of 
amino acids 770 -803 (except residues that were already ala-
nine or glycine) of the E. coli rpoC gene (pIA661) were intro-
duced using QuikChange 
TM (Agilent Technologies). The com-
plete rpoC gene was reconstituted in pVS10 (a gift from I. 
Artsimovitch) (28) by replacement cloning of an MsnI-HindIII 
fragment. The pVS10 construct encodes the E. coli rpoA-rpoB-
rpoC-His 6 and rpoZ ORFs under the control of the T7 pro-
moter. Recombinant plasmids were verified by sequencing. 
In Vivo Growth Complementation-E. coli strain EC397c 
(29) has a temperature-sensitive rpoC allele that fails to grow at 
43.5°C. Growth complementation of this strain was performed 
using the rpoC BH variants expressed from pVS10 in strain 
EC397c(DE3) (formed by infecting EC397c with DE3 using a 
DE3 lysogenization kit (Novagen) following the manufactur-
er's guidelines). Cells for growth curves were cultured over-
night in LB medium at 30°C and used to inoculate fresh 
medium at an A 600 of ϳ0.01. Replicates were incubated at 30 
and 43.5°C, and growth was monitored every 2 h (for the first 
8 h) by apparent absorbance at 600 nm. 
DNA Probes and Proteins-The Sinorhizobium meliloti nifH 
DNA probes (Sigma) used in the small primed RNA (abortive 
transcription) assays and promoter complex formation assays 
were 5Ј-
32 P-labeled (where appropriate) and annealed to the 
complementary strand as described (30). E. coli RNAP (WT 
and BH variants), PspF(1-275), and Klebsiella pneumoniae </p>

<p>54 </p>

<p>were overexpressed in E. coli and purified as described (30 -32). 
E. coli 
70 was purified as described (33). 
Transcription Assays (see Fig. 1C)-Promoter-dependent 
transcription assays were performed in STA buffer (25 mM Tris 
acetate (pH 8.0), 8 mM magnesium acetate, 10 mM KCl, and 
3.5% (w/v PEG) 6000) in a 10-l reaction volume containing 
100 nM 
54 /RNAP or 
70 /RNAP (reconstituted using a 1:4 ratio 
of core RNAP (WT or variants) to ) and 20 nM promoter DNA 
probe. For full-length assays, a supercoiled plasmid containing 
the S. meliloti nifH promoter (pMKC28) was used. For small 
primed RNA (abortive) assays, either the supercoiled plasmid </p>

<p>pMKC28 or a linear probe composed of positions Ϫ60 to ϩ28 
of the S. meliloti nifH promoter that was mismatched between 
positions Ϫ10 and Ϫ1 (believed to mimic the state of the promoter 
within the open complex) (34) was used as described (35). (For </p>

<p>
70 </p>

<p>-dependent assays, the supercoiled lacUV5 promoter was used 
(33).) Open promoter complexes were formed by adding 4 M 
PspF(1-275) and 4 mM dATP to the reaction. All reactions were 
incubated for 10 min at 37°C prior to addition of an elongation 
mixture. Synthesis of the full-length product was initiated by add-
ing a mixture containing 100 g/ml heparin; 1 mM ATP, CTP, and 
GTP; 0.05 mM UTP; and 3 Ci of [␣-</p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>P]UTP. Synthesis of the 
abortive product (UpGGG) was initiated by addition of a mixture 
containing 100 g/ml heparin, 0.5 mM UpG, and 4 Ci of 
[␣-</p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>P]GTP. Both sets of reactions were incubated at 37°C for a 
further 20 min. Reactions were quenched by addition of loading 
buffer, and full-length and abortive transcripts were analyzed on 6 
and 20% denaturing gels, respectively. All transcripts were visual-
ized and quantified using a Fuji FLA-5000 PhosphorImager. Tran-
scription assays were performed at least three times, and activation 
time points were specifically chosen to be within the linear range of 
this assay (36). 
Specific promoter-independent transcription assays were 
performed using a minimal scaffold template that was con-
structed by first annealing the DNA strands 5Ј-GGTCCTGT-
CTGAAATTGTTATCCGCTAC (template) and 5Ј-ACAAT-
TTCAGACAGGACC (non-template) to which a priming RNA 
molecule either 7 bases (5Ј-GUAGCGG) or 8 bases (5Ј-GUA-
GCGGA) in length was annealed (similar to Refs. 7 and 18). 
Promoter-independent transcription assays used 100 nM mini-
mal scaffold assembly and were conducted in STA buffer. RNA 
synthesis was initiated by addition of 100 nM core RNAP (WT 
or BH variants) and 4 Ci of [␣-</p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>P]UTP. Reactions were incu-
bated at 37°C for 10 min and quenched by addition of loading 
buffer, and products were analyzed on 20% denaturing gels. 
Products were visualized and quantified using a Fuji FLA-5000 
PhosphorImager. All minimal scaffold assays were performed 
at least three times within the linear range of the assay, and the 
data were normalized to account for differences in minimal 
scaffold-binding affinities. 
Nonspecific promoter-independent transcription (TCA pre-
cipitation) assays were conducted essentially as described (26) 
using sonicated calf thymus DNA as a template except that the 
reaction temperature was lowered from 70 to 37°C. Activity 
was measured by recording the amount of TCA-precipitated 
counts arising from the incorporation of [␣-
32 P]UTP. All TCA 
assays were performed at least three times. 
Minimal Scaffold-binding Assays-Assays were conducted in 
STA buffer using a minimal scaffold template (see above) in 
which the RNA was 5Ј-
32 P-labeled (see above) and 100 nM core 
RNAP (WT or BH variants). Reactions were incubated at 37°C 
for 10 min and quenched by addition of native buffer, and prod-
ucts were analyzed on 4.5% nondenaturing gels. Products were 
visualized and quantified using a Fuji FLA-5000 Phosphor-
Imager. All binding assays were performed at least three times. 
Pyrophosphorolysis (PP i ) Assays-Assays used 100 nM mini-
mal scaffold assembly with a 
32 P-labeled 7-nucleotide RNA 
primer. Assays were conducted in STA buffer using 100 nM core 
RNAP (WT or BH variants) and 5 M PP i (Na 4 O 7 P 2 ⅐10H 2 O; </p>

<p>Activity Map of the RNA Polymerase Bridge Helix </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 16 • APRIL 22, 2011 </p>

<p>Sigma). Reactions were then incubated at 37°C for 10 min and 
quenched by addition of loading buffer, and products were ana-
lyzed on 20% denaturing gels. Products were visualized and 
quantified using a Fuji FLA-5000 PhosphorImager. All PP i 
experiments were performed at least three times, and the data 
were normalized to account for differences in minimal scaffold-
binding affinities. Importantly, the 10-min time point coincides 
with ϳ40% PP i -catalyzed cleavage by WT RNAP and as such is 
within the linear range of this assay. </p>

<p>Misincorporation Assays-Assays used 100 nM minimal scaf-
fold assembly with 
32 P-labeled 8-nucleotide RNA primer. 
Assays were conducted in STA buffer using 100 nM core RNAP 
(WT or BH variants) and 2 mM nucleotide extension mixtures 
that lacked a single nucleotide (as indicated). Reactions were 
incubated at 37°C for 10 min and quenched by addition of 
loading buffer, and products were analyzed on 20% denaturing 
gels. Products were visualized and quantified using a Fuji FLA-
5000 PhosphorImager. All misincorporation assays were per-</p>

<p>FIGURE 1. RNAP BH. A, atomic model of E. coli RNAP (Protein Data Bank code 3LU0) (27) viewed into the secondary channel, colored as follows: ␣ subunits 
(green/cyan), ␤ (magenta), ␤Ј (yellow), (light pink), active site Mg 
2ϩ (red sphere), and RNA-DNA hybrid (orange). The gray box contains a close-up of the BH and 
surrounding motifs colored as follows: BH (dark blue), TL/TL helices (dark pink), FL2 (teal), and switch 2 (olive green). Also labeled are the ␤Ј-jaw, F-Loop, ␤Ј-G 
recovered domain (␤Ј-GNCD). The BH residues targeted in this study (green sticks) are indicated. Upstream and downstream faces of RNAP are labeled. B, 
sequence alignment of representative BH sequences from bacteria (E. coli K12, T. thermophilus, and Thermus aquaticus), archaea (M. jannaschii, and Sulfolobus 
solfataricus), and eukaryotes (S. cerevisiae and Homo sapiens). The mutated residues in E. coli are highlighted by yellow boxes. Blue lettering indicates where the 
sequence differs from the mutated E. coli residues. The M. jannaschii sequence numbering is based on the intein-free final product. C, schematic representation 
of the catalytic activities monitored in this study (adapted from Ref. 5). i and iϩ1 represent the product and substrate-binding sites of the catalytic center, 
respectively. Solid red lines represent the nascent RNA, and curved arrows indicate the direction of nucleophilic attack. P and N refer to phosphate and 
nucleotide residue, respectively. </p>

<p>Activity Map of the RNA Polymerase Bridge Helix </p>

<p>APRIL 22, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 16 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 14471 </p>

<p>formed at least three times within the linear range of the assay, 
and the data were normalized to account for differences in min-
imal scaffold-binding affinities. 
Structural Analysis-We used the atomic model of E. coli 
RNAP (Protein Data Bank code 3LU0) (27) to guide our inter-
pretation of the activity data sets. All structural interpretations 
and figures were produced using <rs id="software-0" type="software">PyMOL</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 1.2r3pre</rs>, 
Schrödinger LLC). </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>E. coli BH-To uncover the roles of the E. coli RNAP BH, we 
constructed single alanine substitution mutants comprising 
residues 770 -803 (omitting positions that were naturally 
either alanine or glycine, generating 27 variants in total) (Fig. 
1B). Alanine substitutions provide evidence of potentially 
important side chain interactions made by the BH. Such inter-
actions may be involved in one or more of the following: </p>

<p>54 </p>

<p>factor-dependent promoter recognition, DNA melting, and 
RNA synthesis. We specifically choose 
54 because it allows the 
holoenzyme, closed complex, and open complex and their asso-
ciated activities to be readily assessed. The effects of the BH 
variants on the aggregated outcomes of the following RNAP 
activities were then examined in vitro: (i) promoter-dependent/ 
independent DNA binding and melting, (ii) nucleotide addition 
and phosphodiester bond formation (i.e. catalysis), (iii) translo-
cation of RNAP along the DNA, (iv) translocation of RNA to the 
iϩ1 site, (v) minimal scaffold binding, and (vi) phosphodiester </p>

<p>bond cleavage (Fig. 1C). The functionality of the mutant RNAPs 
was also measured in vivo by examining growth complementa-
tion of the E. coli strain EC397c at 43.5°C (see "Experimental 
Procedures" and supplemental Fig. S1). Transcription defects 
were scored as severe if displaying Ͻ20% of WT activity and 
classified as reduced with ϳ50% of WT levels. 
Current crystal structures of bacterial RNAPs indicate that 
the BH makes direct interactions with a number of conserved 
RNAP features, namely the TL, FL2, the F-loop, and switch 2. 
Using an atomic model of E. coli RNAP (Protein Data Bank 
code 3LU0) (27), we provide possible explanations for the 
defects associated with the BH alanine mutants. Substitution of 
certain BH residues with alanine is proposed to result in disrup-
tion of interhelix interactions, as well as interactions with other 
conserved features of RNAP, which we infer leads to an altered 
conformation or a change in the normal distribution of confor-
mations of RNAP and hence loss of (some) functionality (Fig. 2) 
(26, 37-39). 
Silent Mutations-Of the 27 alanine substitutions studied, 
nine (L770A, Q771A, Y772A, L783A, N792A, S793A, Y795A, 
R798A, and R799A) displayed no significant transcription 
defects (Ͼ50% of WT activity levels) in vivo and in vitro under 
the experimental conditions used here (Fig. 2 and supplemental 
Figs. S1-S5). Leu-770, Gln-771, and Tyr-772 are located at the 
N terminus of the BH, proximal to the ␤ subunit but do not 
appear to directly interact with any motifs recognized as being </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Summary of the activities of the BH variants. Upper, atomic model of the E. coli BH with positions of the residues mutated in this study indicated. 
Lower, summary table listing the activities of the BH variants obtained using the assays performed in this study. Red designates severe (Ͻ20% of WT activity) 
defects, pink indicates reduced activity (Ͻ50% of WT activity), and blue denotes impaired minimal scaffold binding. The gray lettering refers to residues not 
mutated in this study. Sites in the M. jannaschii (Mj) BH denoted as the N-and C-terminal hinge regions (BH-H N and BH-H C , respectively), required for helix 
stabilization or to be structurally labile, are also shown (26, 39, 49). </p>

<p>Activity Map of the RNA Polymerase Bridge Helix </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 16 • APRIL 22, 2011 </p>

<p>critical for transcription. Tyr-795, Arg-798, and Arg-799 are 
located toward the C-terminal end of the BH, and at least one 
residue, Arg-798, has been proposed to interact with the tem-
plate strand at ϩ2 (1-3). Nonspecific promoter-independent 
transcription assays, which measure RNA synthesis, demon-
strated that a positively charged side chain at Arg-829 (M. jan-
naschii), corresponding to Arg-798 (in E. coli), was highly sen-
sitive to mutagenesis in RNAP from M. jannaschii (26). 
However, we observed ϳ55% of WT activity for R798A in the 
nonspecific assay (see "Experimental Procedures" and supple-
mental Fig. S2). This assay measures RNA synthesis in the 
absence of (i) a single defined (minimal scaffold) template and 
(ii) the stringency associated with the correct placement of the 
3Ј-end of the RNA primer within the active site (of RNAP). The 
basis for the observed discrepancy in activity may result from 
differences in (i) the temperature at which the reactions were 
conducted, which could impact on the tolerance to different 
amino acid side chains at a particular position, and/or (ii) dis-
tinct ranges of co-dependences between the BH and TL in 
M. jannaschii versus E. coli. Potentially, the activity difference 
could arise from the particular amino acid residue immediately 
N-terminal to this position. We note that the residue immedi-
ately N-terminal to Arg-798, Thr-797, is invariant among bac-
terial species, whereas in archaea and eukaryotes, this residue is 
often glutamine. Furthermore, the different side chains at this 
site could impact on the outcomes of substituting the adjacent 
conserved arginine. In line with this suggestion, Arg-799 toler-
ates a range of amino acid substitutions, similar to Arg-830 in 
M. jannaschii (supplemental Fig. S2) (26). 
Interestingly, R798A exhibited reduced activity in the </p>

<p>54 </p>

<p>promoter-specific small primed (abortive) RNA assay (which 
effectively measures the activity of stable open complexes that 
form) using the supercoiled template (Fig. 3 and supplemental 
Fig. S2). This assay uses an elongation mixture that contains 
only the dinucleotide primer UpG and GTP (preventing syn-
thesis of an RNA product longer than 4 nucleotides in length, 
UpGGG) (35). The activity of R798A was recovered by pre-
opening the template (between positions Ϫ10 and Ϫ1, which 
mimics the state of DNA within the open complex) (34) or by 
addition of the full-length elongation mixture, permitting syn-
thesis of the full-length transcript product (Fig. 3). Given the 
observation that the effect of the R798A substitution was less 
evident in (i) full-length 
54 -dependent transcription (when the 
RNA-DNA hybrid is longer than 4 nucleotides) or (ii) when the 
promoter DNA was pre-opened, we infer that Arg-798 is 
required to stabilize the transcription bubble prior to elonga-
tion, when only a short RNA-DNA hybrid is present, consistent 
with the observation that Thermus thermophilus Arg-1096 
interacts with ϩ2 of the template strand (3). 
FL2 Interactions-FL2 is an highly conserved motif that 
appears to maintain the downstream edge of the transcription 
bubble, interfering with the non-template strand upstream of 
position ϩ3 and thus sterically preventing reannealing of the 
DNA strands (3, 7, 8, 10, 40). The N-terminal region of FL2 
forms an extensive hydrophobic interface with the ␤ pincer 
(particularly the downstream lobe), which serves to increase 
the ability of RNAP to translocate following nucleotide addition 
(13). Numerous structures (including the E. coli model) posi-</p>

<p>tion the N-terminal region of the BH (residues 773-780) in 
close proximity to FL2. 
Using a nonspecific primer-dependent transcription assay 
(Fig. 4A) and a pyrophosphorolysis (PP i )-catalyzed RNA cleav-
age (of the 3Ј-end of RNA) assay (Fig. 4B), we measured nucle-
otide addition (catalysis/polymerization) and hydrolytic cleav-
age (the reverse of the polymerization reaction) in artificially 
assembled elongation (minimal scaffold) complexes to provide 
an indication of the catalytic activity of the mutant RNAPs. Of 
the mutants proposed to interact with FL2 (Fig. 4C), only 
H777A exhibited reduced PP i -dependent cleavage activity 
(ϳ50% of WT levels) (Fig. 4B and supplemental Fig. S3). These 
assays were performed using a previously characterized mini-
mal scaffold template (7, 18); however, further activity differ-
ences might be revealed if the PP i assays were conducted in 
other contexts (i.e. fully complementary scaffolds). Because 
His-777 is located some distance (Ͼ20 Å) from the active center 
Mg 
2ϩ ion, we reasoned that the H777A mutation could result in </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Promoter-dependent transcription activities of BH residues 
795-799. The bar graphs depict the relative intensities (expressed as a per-
centage of WT RNAP activity, where WT ϭ 100%) of the 
54 -dependent prod-
ucts formed on the supercoiled (SC; upper panel), pre-opened (mismatched 
between positions Ϫ10 and Ϫ1 (Ϫ10Ϫ1/WT); middle panel) and supercoiled 
(full-length transcripts (FL); lower panel) templates in the presence of the BH 
variants Y795A, L796A, T797A, R798A, and R799A. Gel slices of the corre-
sponding small primed RNA (UpGGG) and full-length (FL transcript) products 
(obtained using the supercoiled template) are shown above the respective 
bar graphs. Black bars represent WT (100%) activity. All assays were per-
formed at least three times, and S.D. values are shown. </p>

<p>Activity Map of the RNA Polymerase Bridge Helix </p>

<p>APRIL 22, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 16 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 14473 </p>

<p>changes in the interhelix interactions within the BH or the sur-
rounding RNAP features, negatively impacting on the organi-
zation of the catalytic site for RNA cleavage and/or correct 
presentation of the 3Ј-RNA. In line with this observation, the </p>

<p>residue equivalent to His-777 in M. jannaschii, Met-808, was 
found to be super-active when mutated to a variety of other 
amino acids. Met-808 was therefore proposed to be the site of a 
molecular hinge, where kinking at this position would result in </p>

<p>Activity Map of the RNA Polymerase Bridge Helix </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 16 • APRIL 22, 2011 </p>

<p>localized changes in the BH interhelix interactions, length, flex-
ibility, and topology (39). Furthermore, in Saccharomyces 
cerevisiae, the equivalent of His-777, His-816, constitutes a 
binding target for the transcription inhibitor ␣-amanitin, indi-
cating that this residue is important for ␣-amanitin binding and 
may be the route through which ␣-amanitin exerts its action 
(41). 
Interestingly, a significant in vivo growth defect was observed 
with the F773A variant (and to some extent, reduced growth 
activities of H777A and R780A) (Fig. 4D and supplemental Fig. 
S1). Western blot analysis confirmed that F773A was (i) 
expressed and (ii) catalytically active at 43.5°C (supplemental 
Fig. S1), thereby eliminating gross protein instability as a basis 
for the observed growth defect. Promoter-specific in vitro full-
length transcription assays performed in the presence of </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>showed no loss of elongation activity (supplemental Fig. S1). 
However, it has previously been observed that the F773V 
mutant results in a fast form of RNAP that displays pause-free 
RNA chain extension (25). Given this observation, we reasoned 
that the in vivo defect associated with the F773A variant may 
also result from altered pausing/chain extension activities in 
vivo. 
Role of Lys-781 in the E. coli BH-The strongest in vitro 
defects were observed with the K781A variant (Fig. 5 and sup-
plemental Fig. S2-S4). According to studies on the M. jann-
aschii BH, Lys-781 is located within a segment of the BH pro-
posed to be flexible (between Gly-778 and Leu-783), located 
some distance from the site of promoter DNA binding (Fig. 5A) 
and potentially interacting with the F-loop via Pro-750 and 
other domains such as ␤ D-loop II. The F-loop is located 
between the secondary channel rim helices and the N terminus 
of the BH (Fig. 5B) (3). It has been proposed that this flexible 
region ( </p>

<p>778 </p>

<p>GARKGL 
783 ) undergoes spontaneous kinking, par-
ticularly around the glycine residue(s), which have low ␣-helix-
forming propensity (38, 39). This "kinked" conformation is sta-
bilized through noncovalent interhelix interactions potentially 
via Lys-781. Recent studies strongly suggest that the BH oper-
ates through being "flexible" at certain hinge regions (poten-
tially centered at Gly-778 or Gly-782), enabling the BH to kink 
during the nucleotide addition cycle (37-39). Given that ala-
nine has a similar helix-forming propensity as lysine, we do not 
envisage the K781A mutation impacting on the local ␣-helical 
nature of the BH (42). In line with these observation, we infer 
that the severely reduced RNA synthesis and cleavage activities 
associated with the K781A variant (Fig. 5, C-F), may arise from 
the K781A mutation disrupting the interhelix (and F-loop) 
interactions made by the lysine side chain and thereby impact-
ing on the conformation of the BH (37-39). An altered confor-</p>

<p>mation of the BH in this region would be expected to impact 
upon interactions with adjacent RNAP domains such as ␤ 
D-loop II and the F-loop. Because the F-loop appears to have no 
discernable effect on RNA cleavage (18), we infer that the PP i -
associated defects observed for K781A are due to altered inter-
actions with ␤ D-loop II, which is in direct contact with the 
3Ј-end of the nascent transcript. Differences observed in the 
nucleotide addition activity of the K781A variant in the misin-
corporation assays (supplemental Fig. S4) versus minimal scaf-
fold extension assays (supplemental Fig. S2) may be due to the 
different nucleotide concentrations used or the placement of 
the 3Ј-end of the RNA primer with respect to the active site 
residues of RNAP. 
TL Interactions-The TL makes a number of specific inter-
actions with the BH along an extensive generally hydrophobic 
interface (Fig. 6A). A number of BH residues studied here (Asp-
785-Thr-790) have the potential to disrupt this interface, 
thereby impairing TL functionality. Interestingly, molecular 
dynamics studies identified this region (in particular, residues 
786 -789) as structurally labile, implying that these residues 
might contribute to interhelix interactions that directly impact 
upon the structural flexibility of the BH (in this region) (38, 39). 
D785A exhibited severely reduced (Ͻ20% of WT activity) </p>

<p>54 promoter-specific transcription activity (Fig. 6B). Control 
reactions addressing the effect of the D785A mutation on 
54 -
associated activities implied that the BH did not contribute to </p>

<p>54 binding or promoter complex formation (supplemental Fig. 
S5), suggesting that the observed defects are not due simply to 
altered 
54 -dependent interactions. The D785A variant also 
showed reduced nonspecific transcription (Fig. 6C) and misin-
corporation (supplemental Fig. S4) activities. Asp-785 is posi-
tioned close to the TL interface but is not known to make a 
direct interaction with the TL. Similar to D785A, T786A exhib-
ited reduced nonspecific promoter-independent transcription 
(Fig. 6C) and altered misincorporation (supplemental Fig. S4) 
activities. L788A, akin to D785A, exhibited reduced 
54 pro-
moter-specific (Fig. 6B) and nonspecific promoter-indepen-
dent (Fig. 6C) transcription activities, as well as altered misin-
corporation activities (supplemental Fig. S4). Lys-789 has been 
shown to undergo large conformational movement upon TL 
folding (8) and, according to the atomic model, interacts with 
Leu-930 of the TL (Fig. 6A). K789A exhibited impaired in vivo 
growth (Fig. 6D), which was not due to gross protein instability, 
inactivity at 43.5°C, or 
70 -associated in vitro transcription 
defects (supplemental Fig. S1), and reduced (ϳ50% of WT 
activity) PP i activity (Fig. 6E), which we suggest is due to altered 
interactions with Leu-930 that disfavor TL folding. T790A also 
exhibited reduced PP i cleavage activity (Fig. 6E), possibly </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Proposed FL2 interactions with BH residues 773-780. A, bar graph depicting the activities of the BH variants (F773A, I774A, S775A, T776A, H777A, 
and R780A) expressed as a percentage of WT activity (where WT ϭ 100%) in the specific promoter-independent minimal scaffold extension assay (using a 
minimal scaffold with an RNA-DNA hybrid length of 7 nucleotides; RNA-7). Gel slices of the corresponding RNA (RNA-8) product formed after incorporation of 
[␣-
32 P]UTP are shown above the bar graph. B, activities of the same BH variants in the PP i -catalyzed RNA cleavage assay (using the same minimal scaffold as in 
A). Gel slices of the corresponding RNA products (RNA-6) formed after PP i -catalyzed cleavage (of RNA-7) are shown above the bar graph. C, structural 
relationship between BH (blue) residues 773-780 and FL2 (teal) (derived from the E. coli atomic model (Protein Data Bank code 3LU0)) (27), with E. coli 
numbering. D, growth curves depicting the effect of the BH variants (see above) on growth complementation. Gray solid lines represent WT RNAP (i.e. wild-type 
RpoC), gray dashed lines represent the temperature-sensitive strain alone (TS; i.e. no plasmid-encoded RpoC present), and black lines represent the BH variants. 
In A and B, black bars indicate WT (100%) activity, and gray lettering refers to residues not mutated in this study. All assays were performed at least three times, 
and where appropriate, S.D. values are shown. Assays performed using the minimal scaffold template have all been normalized to account for differences in 
minimal scaffold binding. </p>

<p>Activity Map of the RNA Polymerase Bridge Helix </p>

<p>APRIL 22, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 16 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 14475 </p>

<p>resulting from altered interactions with the incoming nucleo-
tide (at the iϩ1 site) (3). 
The minimal scaffold template resembles an artificial elon-
gation complex in which the position of the transcription bub-
ble and the 3Ј-end of the nascent RNA strand is predefined. 
Notably, the activity of the majority of the residue 785-790 
variants was recovered in the minimal scaffold extension assays 
(Fig. 6F). Given this observation, we suggest that residues 785-
790 could be involved in (i) translocating the 3Ј-end of RNA in 
the absence of the cognate incoming rNTP or (ii) aligning the 
incoming nucleotide for phosphodiester bond formation. 
Given that molecular dynamics and M. jannaschii saturation 
mutagenesis studies have identified residues 786 -789 as a 
structurally labile region, the defects associated with the BH 
variants (Asp-785-Thr-790) may result in altered interhelix 
interactions that directly impact upon the conformation of the 
BH and hence the interactions it makes with the TL and nascent 
RNA. 
Switch Region Interactions-Mutating BH residues 800 -803 
resulted in altered 
54 promoter-specific transcription (Fig. 7A) 
and misincorporation (supplemental Fig. S4) activities. The 
promoter-specific transcription defects associated with V801A 
and D802A were partially rescued by pre-opening the DNA 
(Fig. 7A), implying that these mutations may result in altered 
interactions between RNAP and the promoter DNA during 
DNA melting. Interestingly, these residues form part of an 
extensive hydrophobic interface with the RNAP switch regions 
(located at the base of the clamp domain) (3, 9, 10, 17). The 
switch regions act as a hinge, enabling clamp movement during 
transcription initiation (9, 10, 17). Consequently, the switch 
regions adopt different conformations relating to the open and 
closed clamp conformational states. Several residues in switch 2 
have been shown to directly interact with DNA phosphates in 
the elongation complex (8, 10). Furthermore, switch 2 has been 
identified as the binding site for the antibiotics myxopyronin 
(43, 44) and lipiarmycin (45). In light of these observations, it 
has been suggested that the role of switch 2 is to act as a molec-
ular checkpoint for DNA loading in response to regulatory sig-
nals (43). 
The E. coli atomic model predicts that BH Asp-802 interacts 
with switch 2 via Lys-1348 and Ser-1313 (Fig. 7B). Disruption of 
these interactions via introduction of the alanine substitution 
potentially inhibits conformational rearrangements of switch 2 
(communicated via the BH) necessary for clamp closure. The 
defects associated with the Val-801 and Asp-802 variants in 
terms of their implied effect on the switch regions are similar to 
the mechanism suggested for the transcription modifier DksA, 
which binds within the RNAP secondary channel and is pro-
posed to interact with the BH and TL (46). Interestingly, vari-
ants V801A and D802A displayed impaired minimal scaffold-
binding activities (Fig. 7C), which we interpret as a result of 
these residues impacting on the ability of RNAP to "capture" </p>

<p>FIGURE 5. Proposed role of Lys-781, an invariant lysine in bacterial 
RNAPs. A and B, atomic models of E. coli RNAP depicting the structural rela-
tionship between BH (blue) Lys-781, TL helices (dark pink), FL2 (teal), the ␤Ј 
F-loop (orange), and ␤Ј rim helices (yellow). Interactions are indicated by 
dashed lines. C, bar graph showing the relative intensities (where WT ϭ 100%) 
of the 
54 -dependent (abortive and full-length (FL)) RNA products formed on 
the supercoiled (SC) template with BH variant K781A. D, relative activity of BH 
variant K781A in the nonspecific promoter-independent transcription (TCA) 
assay (expressed as a percentage of WT activity). E, relative activity of K781A in 
the specific promoter-independent transcription (minimal scaffold exten-
sion) assays expressed as a percentage of WT activity (using a minimal scaf-
fold template with a RNA-DNA hybrid length of 8 nucleotides; RNA-8). F, rel-
ative activity of K781A in the PP i cleavage assay expressed as a percentage </p>

<p>of WT activity. In C-F, black bars indicate WT (100%) activity, and gray lettering 
refers to residues not mutated in this study. All assays were performed at least 
three times, and S.D. values are shown. Assays performed using the minimal 
scaffold template have all been normalized to account for differences in min-
imal scaffold binding. </p>

<p>Activity Map of the RNA Polymerase Bridge Helix </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 16 • APRIL 22, 2011 </p>



<p>Activity Map of the RNA Polymerase Bridge Helix </p>

<p>APRIL 22, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 16 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 14477 </p>

<p>the nucleic acid template. Strikingly, mutations in RNAP II 
switch regions seem to phenocopy the reduced nucleic acid 
scaffold-binding activities observed with V801A and D802A 
(47). We suggest that the interface between the BH C-terminal 
region (residues 800 -803) and switch 2 may allow the confor-
mational state of the BH (which alternates between kinked and 
straight conformations during the nucleotide addition cycle) to 
influence the function of the clamp domain. By inference, the 
alanine substitutions at Val-801 and Asp-802 confer a closed 
configuration upon RNAP, which disfavors nucleic acid entry. </p>

<p>Final Comments-On the basis of the outcomes of the assays 
we performed, nine of the BH variants were classified as largely 
silent in our studies (Fig. 2). Interestingly F773A and, to some 
extent, K789A failed to support in vivo growth although they 
were (i) produced at comparable levels to WT RNAP and (ii) 
transcriptionally competent at the higher growth temperature 
(43.5°C), implying that high temperature had no adverse effect 
on the stability and functionality of these variants (supplemen-
tal Fig. S1), yet they were judged to be largely competent in the 
in vitro assays performed here. In vivo failure of variants F773A 
and K789A may reflect a factor-dependent outcome not stud-
ied in vitro. Techniques employed when conducting the in vitro 
assays can favor strong interactions, so weaker yet important 
interactions that could be of significance in vivo may not be 
observed. 
BH variants that displayed transcription defects in vitro were 
often proximal to or, in some cases, appeared to directly inter-
act with important and dynamic structural features of RNAP, 
namely the TL, FL2, the F-loop, ␤ D-loop II, and switch 2 (Fig. </p>

<p>FIGURE 7. Proposed switch 2 interactions with BH residues 800 -803. 
A, bar graphs depicting the relative intensities (expressed as a percentage of 
WT activity, where WT ϭ 100%) of the small primed RNA products formed on 
the supercoiled (SC) and pre-opened (Ϫ10Ϫ1/WT) templates obtained in the 
presence the BH variants L800A, V801A, D802A, and V803A. B, atomic model 
of E. coli RNAP depicting the structural relationship between BH (blue) resi-
dues 800 -803, the TL helices (dark pink), and switch 2 (olive green), with polar 
contacts indicated by dashed lines. C, minimal scaffold-binding activities of 
the above BH variants expressed as a percentage of WT RNAP activity. In A and 
C, black bars indicate WT (100%) activity. All assays were performed at least 
three times, and S.D. values are shown. </p>

<p>FIGURE 8. Schematic illustration of the proposed key residues/interac-
tions arising from this study. The schematic representation of the BH and 
surrounding motifs is colored as follows: BH (dark blue), TL helices (pink), FL2 
(teal); and switch 2 (green). The BH residues targeted in this study are indi-
cated by the ruler. BH residues identified as potentially important for interhe-
lix interactions are indicated by blue arrows. BH residues inferred (from this 
study) to interact with surrounding RNAP motifs are shown. </p>

<p>Activity Map of the RNA Polymerase Bridge Helix </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 16 • APRIL 22, 2011 </p>

<p>8). The relationship between the BH and these features appears 
to be important for RNAP activity (Fig. 8) (3, 6, 38, 39, 48). Key 
BH residues include the alanine substitution at Lys-781 (the 
invariant lysine in bacteria), which failed in all the in vitro cat-
alytic assays performed; D785A, L788A, V801A, and D802A, 
which exhibited reduced 
54 promoter-specific transcription; 
and V801A and D802A, which showed dramatic defects in 
minimal scaffold-binding activities (summarized in Fig. 8). 
Together, these observations serve to highlight the importance 
of the BH in binding and stabilizing the melted DNA template 
in the transcription bubble, as well as selecting and ensuring the 
register of the incoming rNTP. Side chain interactions made by 
the BH with other features of the RNAP could serve to simply 
organize these features or more probably participate in confor-
mationally coupling the BH to these features (38). 
Multisubunit RNAPs from all cellular organisms show clear 
overall similarity. The active site and the nucleic acid-binding 
features of RNAP are highly conserved. A picture is now emerg-
ing of a set of defined interactions, centered on the BH, that link 
conformational changes in the active site during the nucleotide 
addition cycle to structural elements responsible for control-
ling wider RNAP functionality and RNAP interactions with 
promoter DNA. Interactions between the BH and the TL, FL2, 
the F-loop, ␤ D-loop II and the switch regions may therefore 
extend beyond the architectural (and propagate, in an active 
sense) conformational signals to and from the active site. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments-We thank the members of the M. B. laboratory 
and N. Joly and F. Werner for comments on the manuscript and N. 
Zenkin and Y. Yuzenkova for technical advice. </p>



<p>Activity Map of the RNA Polymerase Bridge Helix </p>

<p>APRIL 22, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 16 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 14479 </p>

</text></tei>