<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3148455" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:39+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVE: To evaluate the correlation between transforming growth factor beta (TGF-b1) expression and 
prognosis in prostate cancer. </p>

<p>PATIENTS AND METHODS: TGF-b1 expression levels were analyzed using the quantitative real-time polymerase 
chain reaction to amplify RNA that had been isolated from fresh-frozen malignant and benign tissue specimens 
collected from 89 patients who had clinically localized prostate cancer and had been treated with radical 
prostatectomy. The control group consisted of 11 patients with benign prostate hyperplasia. The expression levels of 
TGF-b1 were compared between the groups in terms of Gleason scores, pathological staging, and prostate-specific 
antigen serum levels. </p>

<p>RESULTS: In the majority of the tumor samples, TGF-b1 was underexpressed 67.0% of PCa patients. The same 
expression pattern was identified in benign tissues of patients with prostate cancer. Although most cases exhibited 
underexpression of TGF-b1, a higher expression level was found in patients with Gleason scores $7 when compared 
to patients with Gleason scores ,7 (p = 0.002). Among the 26 cases of TGF-b1 overexpression, 92.3% had poor 
prognostic features. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS: TGF-b1 was underexpressed in prostate cancers; however, higher expression was observed in tumors 
with higher Gleason scores, which suggests that TGF-b1 expression may be a useful prognostic marker for prostate 
cancer. Further studies of clinical specimens are needed to clarify the role of TGF-b1 in prostate carcinogenesis. </p>

<p>Prostate cancer (PCa) is the most common male malig-
nancy and is the second-highest cause of death in many 
countries, including Brazil. 
1 Pathological staging, Gleason 
scores, and prostate-specific antigen (PSA) serum levels are 
the most reliable prognostic factors; however, even when 
combined, they do not perfectly identify patients who are at 
risk of progression. 
2 Therefore, research has been aimed at 
identifying molecular markers that can predict PCa predis-
position and progression. </p>

<p>Transforming growth factor beta (TGF-b) is the proto-
typical member of a superfamily that includes more than 25 
members, including inhibin, bone morphogenetic protein, 
and Mü llerian inhibiting substance. The TGF-b subfamily 
contains five members named TGF-b1 through b5. TGF-b1, 
-b2, and -b3 have been identified in mammals. 
3,4 Although 
TGF-b is a pleiotropic growth factor, it inhibits growth in 
most cell types, especially cells of epithelial lineage. TGF-b 
also inhibits prostatic epithelial cell proliferation and 
induces apoptosis. 
5,6 In addition to its numerous effects on 
cell proliferation, phenotype, and differentiation, 
7 TGF-b is 
an important transcriptional regulator of extracellular 
matrix components. 
Malignant transformation is characterized by multiple 
genetic mutations that confer a growth advantage to 
transformed cells compared with benign cells. The devel-
opment of prostate cancer follows this paradigm. TGF-b 
is involved in two critical events that are consistently </p>

<p>Copyright ß 2011 CLINICS -This is an Open Access article distributed under 
the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits unrestricted non-
commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the 
original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2011;66(7):1143-1147 
DOI:10.1590/S1807-59322011000700004 </p>



<p>associated with the conversion from a benign state to a 
malignant state: 1) a reduction or loss of the sensitivity to 
the inhibitory effects of TGF-b and 2) an increase in the 
ability to elevate TGF-b expression levels, which in turn 
promotes carcinogenesis by stimulating extracellular matrix 
production, promoting angiogenesis, and inhibiting the host 
immune system. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>To evaluate whether the expression levels of TGF-b1 in 
prostate cancer cells are associated with prognosis, as 
predicted by the TGF-b elevation in carcinogenesis, we 
investigated a putative correlation between TGF-b gene 
expression and Gleason score, pathological stage, and PSA 
serum level. </p>

<p>PATIENTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>This study was conducted using surgical specimens from 
79 patients with clinically localized PCa who underwent 
radical prostatectomy in our institution between 1993 and 
2007; patients with a minimum follow-up of five years were 
randomly selected from a frozen tumor tissue database 
(Table 1). Benign tissue samples from an additional 10 
patients with PCa who also underwent radical prostatect-
omy were included in this group. Patients who had 
undergone other treatments for PCa were excluded. All of 
the subjects provided their informed consent to participate 
in the study and to allow their biological samples to be 
genetically analyzed. Approval for the study was given by 
the Institutional Board of Ethics (n˚0453/08). 
We correlated the expression levels of the TGF-b1 genes 
in each sample with the patient's Gleason score, pathologic 
stage according to the TNM 2002 staging system, and serum 
PSA level (in ng/ml). For the analysis, the pathologic stage 
was considered as an organ-confined (pT2) or non-organ-
confined (pT3) disease. The Gleason score was classified as 
low grade (,7) or high grade ($7), and preoperative PSA 
was used to identify patients at high ($10 ng/ml) or low 
risk (,10 ng/ml) for disease recurrence. In addition, at a 
mean follow-up time of 60 months, we analyzed the gene 
expression levels in patients with biochemical recurrence, 
which was defined as a PSA level .0.4 ng/ml. 
The control group consisted of tissue specimens from 11 
patients with benign prostate hyperplasia (BPH) who 
presented with lower urinary tract symptoms and had an 
interest in undergoing surgery (mean age 64¡6.0 years). </p>

<p>RNA Isolation and cDNA Synthesis </p>

<p>All of the tumor samples were obtained from surgical 
specimens and immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen at 
-170˚C. A mirror image slide of the frozen fragment was 
stained with hematoxylin and eosin to verify that the tumor 
represented at least 75% of the fragment in the cancer 
patients and that no tumors were present in the control 
patients with BPH. 
Total RNA was isolated using the RNAaqueous Kit 
(Applied Biosystems, CA, USA) according to the manufac-
turer's instructions. The RNA concentration was deter-
mined by the ratio of the absorbance at 260 and 280 nm 
using a NanoDrop ND-1000 spectrophotometer (Thermo 
Scientific, USA). cDNA was generated using the High 
Capacity cDNA Reverse Transcription Kit (Applied 
Biosystems). The reactions were incubated at 25˚C for 
10 min, followed by 37˚C for 120 min and 85˚C for 5 min. 
The cDNA was stored at -20˚C until use. </p>

<p>Quantitative Real-Time Polymerase Chain Reaction 
and Gene Expression </p>

<p>The expression level of the TGF-b1 gene was analyzed using 
quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) 
with the ABI 7500 Fast system (Applied Biosystems). The 
target sequences were amplified in a 10 ml reaction volume 
containing 5 ml TaqMan Universal PCR Master Mix, 0.5 ml 
TaqMan Gene Expression Assays (TGF-b Hs00852894_m1 and 
B2M Hs99999907_m1), 1 ml cDNA, and 3.5 ml DNase-free 
water. The polymerase chain reaction (PCR) cycling conditions 
were 2 min at 50˚C and 10 min at 95˚C, followed by 40 cycles 
of 15 seconds at 95˚C and 1 min at 60˚C. The TaqMan 
endogenous control assay utilized b-2-microglobulin (B2M). 
We used the DDCT method to calculate the relative 
expression levels of the two target genes using the formula 
DDCT = (CT target gene, PCa sample -CT endogenous 
control, PCa sample) -(CT target gene, BPH sample -CT 
endogenous control, BPH sample). The fold change in gene 
expression was calculated as 2 
-DDCT . </p>

<p>Statistical Analyses </p>

<p>Quantitative variables were expressed as median values, 
interquartile ranges (Q1-Q3), and minimum and maximum 
values. Qualitative variables were expressed as numbers and 
percentages. We constructed a box plot for a descriptive 
analysis of TGF-b expression according to pathologic stage, 
Gleason score, and PSA level. We used the Mann-Whitney test 
to compare categories. Statistical analyses were performed 
using <rs type="software">GraphPad Prism 3</rs>, and significance was set at p#0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>As shown in Figure 1, an analysis of the 79 patients with 
PCa showed that TGF-b1 was underexpressed (median 
6.07610 
-1 -fold) in malignant prostatic tissue as compared to 
the BPH samples. 
The TGF-b1 expression levels in relation to the Gleason 
scores are shown in Table 2. The median TGF-b1 expression 
levels were significantly higher (p = 0.0065) among patients 
with a Gleason score $7 (9.4610 
-1 -fold) compared with 
those patients with a Gleason score ,7 (4.6610 
-1 -fold). 
With regard to the pathologic stage, the expression of 
TGF-b1 was similar (p = 0.2514) between stage pT3 patients 
(median 4.9610 
-1 -fold) and stage pT2 patients (median 
6.6610 
-1 -fold). When the results were evaluated according </p>

<p>Table 1 -Age and clinical characteristics of 79 men who 
underwent radical prostatectomy to treat prostate 
cancer. </p>

<p>Age (years) 
Mean 
63 
Min -Max 
41 -79 
PSA (ng/ml) 
Mean 
10.8 
Min -Max 
2.0 -37.0 
,10 n (%) 
47 (59.5) 
$10 n (%) 
32 (40.5) 
Stage 
pT2 n (%) 
38 (48) 
pT3 n (%) 
41 (52) 
Gleason Score 
,7 n (%) 
32 (41.7) 
$7 n (%) 
46 (58.3) </p>

<p>TGF-b in prostate cancer 
Reis ST et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2011;66(7):1143-1147 </p>



<p>to preoperative PSA values, the median TGF-b1 expression 
levels were also similar (p = 0.5110) between patients with 
PSA levels $10 ng/ml (6.7610 
-1 -fold) and patients with PSA 
levels ,10 (5.5610 
-1 -fold). 
We found an overexpression of TGF-b1 in 26 cases, of 
which 21 (80.7%) had a Gleason score $7, 13 (50%) had a 
PSA level $10 ng/ml, 12 (46%) were staged as pT3 and 9 
(35%) had biochemical recurrence. Only 2 (7.7%) of the 
patients with TGF-b1 overexpression exhibited no unfavor-
able prognostic factors. 
We also evaluated the expression levels of TGF-b1 in 
patients with biochemical recurrence (which was defined as a 
PSA level above 0.4 ng/ml) at a mean follow-up period of 60 
months. Median TGF-b1 expression levels were statistically </p>

<p>similar (p = 0.528) among patients with and without recur-
rence (5.4610 
-1 and 6.1610 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>, respectively). 
We performed a multivariate analysis, and the Gleason 
score was the unique independent prognostic factor in our 
series (p = 0.022). 
Additionally, we tested the expression of TGF-b1 in the 
prostatic tissues from 10 patients with benign PCa and 
found the same expression patterns as observed in the 
malignant tissues (median 1.7610 
-1 ) (p = 0.05). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, we found that TGF-b1 was underexpressed in 
malignant prostatic tissue as compared to BPH samples 
(median 7610 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>-fold). Thus, we may assume that TGF-b 
contributes to the development of prostate cancer by acting as 
an inhibitor of cell proliferation and an inducer of apopto-
sis. 
8,9 Furthermore, we identified higher TGF-b expression 
levels in tumors with higher Gleason scores, suggesting that 
this gene may play a role in PCa progression and prognosis. 
Soulitzis et al 
10 also reported a decrease in TGF-b 
expression in PCa. TGF-b is generally a growth inhibitor 
of both benign prostatic epithelial cells 
11 and prostate cancer 
cells in vitro 
12 and has been shown to inhibit proliferation 
and induce apoptosis in prostatic epithelial cells. </p>

<p>8,13 </p>

<p>Moreover, TGF-b stimulates the synthesis of collagen, 
fibronectin, and integrins, and it inhibits matrix degradation 
through the downregulation of proteinases such as collage-
nases, stromelysins, and plasminogen activators. 
14 Paired with 
its downregulation of proteinases, TGF-b upregulates protei-
nase inhibitors such as the following endogenous matrix 
metalloproteinases (MMP) inhibitors: the tissue inhibitor of 
metalloproteinase-1 (TIMP-1) 
15 and plasminogen activator 
inhibitor-1. 
16 TGF-b also acts as a repressor of matrix 
metalloproteinase expression through the TGF-b inhibitory 
element (TIE), which is found in the 59-flanking region of 
several genes in the MMP family, namely interstitial collage-
nase (MMP-1) and 92-kDa type IV collagenase (MMP-9). </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>Figure 1 -Quantitative expression of TGF-b1 messenger RNA in malignant prostatic tissue compared with BPH. Fold change in 
expression was calculated using the 2-DDCT method. </p>

<p>Table 2 -Relative expression of the TGF-b1 gene in the 
malignant prostatic tissues according to Gleason score, 
pathologic stage, PSA level and biochemical recurrence. 
Fold changes in gene expression were calculated using 
the DDCT method (QRel = 2 
-DDCT ). </p>

<p>TGF-b1 </p>

<p>Gleason Score 
,7 (n = 32) 
0.46 (0.02 -6.20) 
$7 (n = 36) 
0.93 (0.02 -33.3) 
p-value 
0.006 
Pathologic Stage 
pT2 (n = 37) 
0.65 (0.02 -33.3) 
pT3 (n = 40) 
0.48 (0.04 -18.9) 
p-value 
0.249 
PSA Level 
,10 (n = 45) 
0.55 (0.04 -33.3) 
$10 (n = 33) 
0.67 (0.02 -14.3) 
p-value 
0.508 
Biochemical Recurrence 
Without (n = 29) 
0.60 (1.12 -33.3) 
With (n = 28) 
0.54 (0.04 -18.9) 
p-value 
0.523 </p>

<p>CLINICS 2011;66(7):1143-1147 
TGF-b in prostate cancer 
Reis ST et al. </p>



<p>Interestingly, a quantitative analysis revealed a positive 
association between increased TGF-b1 mRNA levels and 
elevated Gleason scores (p = 0.002). Although controversial, 
this finding is consistent with that of a previous study in which 
TGF-b plasma levels were higher in men with PCa metastases 
than in healthy men. 
18 Shariat et al 
19 also found a strong 
correlation between elevated plasma TGF-b and prostate 
cancer progression and the development of metastases in 
patients with locally advanced disease. Faria et al 
20 demon-
strated that among patients with PCa, the relative levels of 
TGF-b1 mRNA increased during the late stages of the disease. 
Some studies have suggested that decreased expression of 
TGF-b is not entirely necessary, as some tumor cells might 
escape the inhibitory effects of TGF-b through mutations 
that could provide a growth advantage over their benign 
counterparts. It has also been established that both TGF-b 
receptors (TbR-I and TbR-II) are required for the proper 
transduction of TGF-b signaling, 
21 and prostate cancer cells 
might reduce the expression or function of either TbR-I or 
TbR-II to escape the growth-inhibiting effects of TGF-b. This 
loss of sensitivity to TGF-b by its receptors could induce a 
compensatory overexpression of TGF-b, thereby leading to 
more aggressive phenotypes. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Research has suggested that whether TGF-b exerts a 
tumor-suppressive or oncogenic effect is contextual and/or 
depends upon the temporal stage of cellular transforma-
tion. 
23 A recent study reported that the activation of TGF-b 
signaling pathways might be responsible for mediating the 
epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT), thereby enhan-
cing the invasiveness and survival of transformed cells. </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Moreover, TGF-b can alter the host-tumor interaction, thus 
facilitating tumor growth, promoting angiogenesis, and 
inhibiting the host immune system. </p>

<p>9,25 </p>

<p>By examining benign tissues from the removed prostates of 
patients with PCa who were treated by radical prostatect-
omy, we observed the same TGF-b expression pattern as in 
malignant tissue. This result is interesting because it allows 
us to propose the use of TGF-b as a tumor marker, there-
by overcoming the sampling error that commonly occurs 
in conventional prostate biopsies; however, larger studies 
should be conducted to further validate our findings. 
In conclusion, we showed for the first time in clinical 
specimens that decreased expression of TGF-b is a char-
acteristic of prostate cancer and may be related to cancer 
initiation and promotion; the role of TGF-b as a regulator of 
cell growth and apoptosis should be confirmed in a wider 
series. On the other hand, TGF-b superexpression might be 
related to tumor progression, as it is more highly expressed 
in more aggressive tumors, and this finding could be 
explained by mutations that confer resistance to TGF-b 
receptors. This hypothesis also warrants further experi-
mental studies to analyze the potential of TGF-b as a 
diagnostic or prognostic marker. 
Grant sponsors: This study was supported by FAPESP 
(Fundaçã o de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de Sao Paulo) 
under protocol number 2009/50368-9. </p>



<p>TGF-b in prostate cancer 
Reis ST et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2011;66(7):1143-1147 </p>







</text></tei>