<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3808809" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Reversible molecular switches with molecular orientation as the information carrier have been achieved on 
individual fullerene molecules adsorbed on Si (111) surface at room temperature. Scanning tunneling 
microscopy imaging directly demonstrates that the orientation of individual fullerene with an adsorption 
geometry of 5-6 bond is rotated by integral times as 30 degree after a pulse bias is applied between the STM 
tip and the molecule. Dependences of the molecular rotation probability on the voltage and the process of 
applied bias reveal that the rotation of a fullerene molecule takes place in two successive steps: the bonding 
between the fullerene and the Si surface is firstly weakened via electronic excitation and then low energy 
electron bombardment causes the molecule to rotate by certain degree. </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>olecular device designed at a molecular level to efficiently perform a particular function have attracted 
wide attentions due to the promotion of electronic devices miniaturization at the nanometer scale. Great 
efforts have been devoted to construct the prototypes of molecular devices such as switches, motors, data 
storage bits, magnets, and diodes 1-11 . Scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) has been demonstrated to be a useful 
tool to manipulate a single atom or molecule on a solid surface with atomic-scale precision and explore the 
process of lateral/vertical motions 12,13 , rotations 14,15 , dissociation and dissociation-recombination 16-19 and con-
formational change 20,21 of molecules for the purpose of constructing molecular devices with novel functions. To 
date, most of single-molecule manipulations are performed at low temperature (5 K-100 K). Molecular devices 
working at room temperature are especially desirable in the viewpoint of realistic applications. 
Fullerene (C 60 ), a molecule with unique symmetry and electronic properties, forms covalent bonds with Si 
atoms and has stable adsorption geometries at room temperature when it adsorbs on Si surfaces 22-24 , providing a 
feasible system to achieve molecule manipulation at room temperature. Fullerene molecules are moved along the 
Si dimer rows on a Si (100) surface and positioned to form regular patterns at room temperature by a STM tip 25,26 . 
Single target fullerene molecules are removed in the close-packed fullerene layer by electron injection from an 
STM tip 27 . It is worth noting that fullerene molecules are treated as point particles without any intramolecular 
information in most STM manipulation attempts. One of interests on using organic molecules as active parts to 
build molecular devices is that organic molecules have much richer intramolecular properties compared to 
inorganic materials. Distinct intramolecular fine patterns and adsorption orientations of individual fullerene 
molecules have been evidently observed on Si surface 28 , even at room temperature 29 , providing the possibility of 
building a molecular device with such molecular properties. Here, we report an approach to construct reversible 
molecular switches with intramolecular orientations as information carrier based on individual fullerene mole-
cule adsorbed on a Si (111)-(7 3 7) surface at room temperature by STM manipulation. </p>

<p>Results 
Fullerene molecules on five available adsorption sites of Si (111)-(7 3 7) surface take different and stable 
adsorption geometries due to the covalent interactions between the molecules and the Si surface, as a con-
sequence, unique and distinct intramolecular fine patterns of individual fullerene molecules can be clearly 
recorded by STM 29 . Fig. 1a gives a representative STM image for fullerene molecules adsorbed on a Si (111)-(7 
3 7) surface at room temperature. The fullerene molecule highlighted in yellow frame is adsorbed on the top of 
the rest atoms in the faulted part of a Si (111)-(7 3 7) unit cell and takes such adsorption geometry in which one of 
the 5-6 bonds within the fullerene molecule faces toward the Si surface (noted as ''5-6 bond fullerene'' here-
inafter). The high-resolution STM image in the inset reveals that the intramolecular fine pattern for such 5-6 bond </p>

<p>fullerene is described as a mirror-symmetry structure in which a 
regular pentagon can be unambiguously distinguished. Accord-
ingly, the in-plane molecular orientation for such 5-6 bond fullerene 
on Si surface labeled as an pink arrow is defined as the line along the 
symmetric axis with the direction from the middle of one side to the 
opposite apex of the regular pentagon. The fully relaxed structure 
calculate by density-functional theory (DFT) in Figure 1b shows that 
the in-plane molecular orientation for such 5-6 bond fullerene forms 
an angle of 15u with the surface directions ½01 1 of Si (111)-(7 3 7) 
reconstitution. Ignoring the influence of stacking fault across the unit 
cell for the in-plane molecular orientation of fullerene, it is approx-
imatively considered that Si(111)-(7 3 7) reconstruction has sex-
tuple rotation symmetry. Accordingly, it is immediately deduced 
that 5-6 bond fullerene molecules on Si surface have 12 available 
in-plane molecular orientations. Figure 1d gives the STM images </p>

<p>for the 5-6 bond fullerene molecules on the Si surface with various 
in-plane molecular orientations. Taking the ½10 1 surface direction as 
a reference, these in-plane molecular orientations form 12 angles 
(615u, 6 45u, 6 75u, 6 105u, 6 135u and 6 165u) with the reference 
direction as what expected. Such observations suggest that a 5-6 bond 
fullerene moleclule randomly takes one of these 12 in-plane orienta-
tions when this molecule lands on the Si surface. Therefore, for a 5-6 
bond fullerene moleclule on the Si surface, 12 energy-equivalent 
states are available and can be labeled by only in-plane molecular 
orientation. On the other hand, the fact that the in-plane molecular 
orientations for 5-6 bond fullerene remain unchangeable during the 
STM scanning processes demonstrates that a 5-6 bond fullerene 
molecule with one in-plane molecular orientation can not sponta-
neously rotate to another orientation at room temperature due to the 
strong interactions between the molecule and the Si surface. </p>

<p>Figure 1 | STM images of individual 5-6 bond C 60 absorbed on Si(111)-(7 3 7) surface at room temperature. (a) STM images of individual 5-6 </p>

<p>bond C 60 absorbed on Si (111)-(7 3 7) surface at room temperature, V t 5 2.28 V, I t 5 0.12 nA. The faulted and unfaulted parts of a Si (111)-(7 3 7) unit 
cell are labeled as F and U. Inset: high-resolution STM image of a single 5-6 bond C 60 , in which the molecular orientation of the C 60 is defined as the pink 
arrow. (b) The relaxed structure for 5-6 bond C 60 molecule absorbed on Si(111)-(7 3 7) surface calculated by DFT. The pink arrow represents the 
orientation of 5-6 bond C 60 and the red arrow represents direction ½01 1 of Si (111)-(7 3 7). (c) Simulated STM image of 5-6 bond C 60 based on the 
relaxed structure model in (b). (d) 5-6 bond fullerenes with 12 in-plane orientations. The white arrows represent the molecular orientations of the C 60 , 
and the yellow arrows represent the surface direction of ½10 1. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 3062 | DOI: 10.1038/srep03062 </p>

<p>
Therefore, for a 5-6 bond fullerene molecule on Si surface, the avail-
ability of multiple equivalent states and the stability of these states at 
room temperature provide the possibility of switching such fullerene 
from one state to another equivalent state by STM manipulation at 
room temperature. 
Fig. 2a shows two individual fullerene molecules adsorbed on a Si 
(111)-(7 3 7) surface at room temperature. One of these two mole-
cules is distinguished as a 5-6 bond fullerene in the yellow frame with 
an angle of 75u between its in-plane orientation and the directions 
½10 1 of Si surface and chosen as the target molecules for STM 
manipulation. The other fullerene molecule with a regular pentagon 
feature in its intramolecular fine structures acts as an indicator for 
manipulation experiment. After placing the STM tip right on the top 
of the apex angle of the regular pentagon within this 5-6 bond full-
erene molecule, a positive bias of 7 V is applied between the tip and 
the surface. The changes on the intramolecular fine structures of this 
targeted molecule can be clearly observed immediately after the 
application of the bias, as shown in Fig. 2b. The STM image after 
the manipulation in Fig. 2c evidently demonstrates that the targeted 
fullerene molecule remains in 5-6 bond adsorption geometry but its 
in-plane orientation forms an angle of 2165u with the ½10 1 direc-
tions rather than 75u for the initial state. In other words, the in-plane 
molecular orientation of this 5-6 bond fullerene molecule is rotated 
by 180u before and after the STM manipulation. The fact that the 
intramolecular fine structure of the indicative fullerene molecule 
remains unchangeable before and after the manipulation rules out 
the possibility that the changes on the molecular orientation of the 
targeted fullerene is due to the transformation of the STM tip and 
evidently demonstrates that the in-plane orientation of this targeted 
fullerene molecule can be indeed manipulated by applied a bias 
between the STM tip and the molecule. As shown in Fig. 2d-g, the 
molecular orientation of 5-6 bond fullerene can be also rotated by 
60u, 90u, 120u and 150u in the same manipulation process with the 
suitable parameters. It is worth noting that all the rotation angles 
before and after the manipulation for 5-6 bond fullerene molecules in 
our study are integral times of 30u,suggesting that the in-plane 
molecular orientation of 5-6 bond fullerene can only be manipulated 
from one of the 12 equivalent orientations to another equivalent 
orientation as what is expected from DFT calculations. 
Fig. 3a-d shows a successive manipulation process on a 5-6 bond 
fullerene on Si surface at room temperature. At the beginning, this 
targeted 5-6 bond fullerene highlighted in yellow frame has an in-
plane orientation of 45u with respect to the ½10 1 surface direction, as 
shown in Fig. 3a. After the first manipulation, the orientation of the 
targeted molecule is rotated by 90u in clockwise direction and 
becomes of 135u with the respect to the ½10 1 direction in Fig. 3b. 
The second manipulation on this molecule rotates the molecular 
orientation by 90u in anticlockwise direction, as a consequence, the 
orientation of this molecule returns to the initial status. Such obser-
vations clearly demonstrate that the manipulations on the molecular 
orientation for 5-6 bond fullerene on Si surface by applying a bias 
between the STM tip and the molecule are reversible processes. 
Moreover, this reversible manipulation process on the molecular 
orientation can be repeated, as shown in Fig. 3c-d. As shown in 
Fig. 3e, supposed that the in-plane molecular orientation is an indi-
cator for molecular state, the states of the 5-6 bond molecule in 
Fig. 3a and Fig. 3b are named as ''on'' and ''off'', respectively. By 
applied a bias between the STM tip and the molecule, 5-6 fullerene 
molecule can be switched to be ''on'' or ''off'' states. In addition, the 
state of the molecule remains unchangeable at room temperature 
once the molecule is in ''on'' or ''off'' state. Since the changes on 
the intramolecular fine structures within the targeted fullerene mole-
cule can clearly observed at the immediate scanning line right after 
the manipulation process, the upper limit for the time that the 
changes on the in-plane molecular orientation occur is estimated 
to be 400 ms from the time gap between two neighbored scan lines, </p>

<p>while the lower limit of that is 7.6 ms. The reversibility and repeat-
ability of the rotations on the in-plane orientation for 5-6 bond full-
erene caused by STM manipulations makes a fullerene molecule 
adsorbed on Si surface feasible to build a single molecule switch 
working at room temperature with its orientation as the information 
carrier. </p>

<p>Discussion 
As shown in Fig. 4a, when the STM tip is placed on a fullerene 
molecule, the feedback of the control unit is switched off and a bias 
can be applied between the tip and the molecules in three different 
ways: Type I is a sweep-up process in which a applied bias is linearly </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Manipulations of individual 5-6 bond C 60 molecules by STM </p>

<p>tip at room temperature. (a-c) STM images of a 5-6 bond C 60 molecule for 
a successive manipulation process at room temperature. Initial status (a) 
middle status (b) and final status (c). Insets to (a) and (b) show high-
resolution STM images in which the molecular orientations are indicated 
by blue and green arrows. (d-g) Various manipulation cases for 5-6 bond 
C 60 molecules. The STM images in the left column are for 5-6 bond C 60 
molecules before manipulations and the images in the right column show 
the final states of the C 60 molecules after manipulation. The middle 
column shows the rotation angles of the molecular orientations before and 
after the manipulations. The initial and final orientations of fullerene are 
indicated by the blue and green arrows. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 3062 | DOI: 10.1038/srep03062 </p>

<p>
increased from zero to a set value with time; type II is a non-sweep 
process in which a constant bias at a set value is applied; type III is the 
sweep-down process in which a applied bias is gradually decreased 
from a set value to zero with time. The dependence of the rotation 
probability on the bias and the distance between the tip and fullerene 
molecule have been derived from about three hundreds manipula-
tions in Type I process to understand the mechanism for rotating the 
molecular orientations of fullerene molecules. As shown in Fig. 4b, 
when the distance between the tip and the molecule is kept to be d 1 5 
4.5 A ˚ , the orientation of fullerene molecules can not be rotated until 
the bias voltage is increased to be 6 V. Once the bias voltage is higher 
than 6 V, the rotating probability dramatically increases from 16.1% 
at 6 V to 66.7% at 9 V. Under a shorter tip-molecule distance (d 2 5 
3.4 A ˚ ), the rotation events can not take place until the applied bias 
voltage is higher than 6 V. Such observations directly rule out that 
the electrical field between the STM tip and the molecule is the cause 
for such rotations of molecular orientation. The requirement for 
rotating fullerene molecule by high bias voltage and extremely high 
success probability (80%) at high voltage observed here is similar 
with those found in the dissociation of decaborane molecules on Si 
(111) by STM manipulation 30 . In decaborane/Si (111) system, the 
bombardment of low energy electrons emitted from a STM tip is 
suggested to account for the dissociation and fragmentation of dec-
aborane molecules. The energy level alignment (Fig. 4c) for the situ-
ation in which a 6 V is applied between the tip and the fullerene 
molecule clearly shows that the Fermi level of the STM tip is 1 eV 
above the vacuum level on fullerene molecule and the tunneling 
channels are open for low energy electrons from the STM tip into 
vacuum. The shorter tip-molecule distance causes a narrower barrier 
between the tip and the vacuum and then produces more low energy 
electrons at the same bias voltage. As a consequence, the rotation 
probability for fullerene molecules is significantly increased at 
shorter tip-molecule distance, which is consistence with what 
observed here. Therefore, the bombardment of low energy electron 
onto fullerene molecule is tentatively believed to be a major cause for 
the rotation of molecular orientation. 
The probability for rotating fullerene molecules is also found to be 
strongly relied on the process how a bias is applied between the tip 
and the molecule. Fig. 4d shows the possibilities to rotate fullerene </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Reversible and repeatable switching process of individual 5-6 bond C 60 molecules. (a) Initial status of an individual C 60 molecule before STM </p>

<p>manipulation. Inset: The molecular orientation is indicated by the blue arrow and forms a angle of 45u with the respect to the ½10 1 surface direction 
labeled as the white arrow. (b-d) States of C 60 after the first, second and third manipulations. The inset shows the magnified views of the molecular 
orientations of the manipulated C 60 molecule. (e) Sketch diagram for the working principle of a reversible and repeatable molecular switch. The in-plane 
molecular orientations are indicators for two distinguished states. The states of the 5-6 bond molecules in (a) and (b) are defined as ''on'' and ''off '' states. 
The pointer reversibly switches between ''on'' and ''off '' by STM manipulation. </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Mechanism for rotating the orientation of individual 5-6 bond </p>

<p>C 60 by STM manipulation. (a) Three processes to apply a bias between the 
STM tip and fullerene molecule for manipulating. (b) Dependence of the 
rotation probability on the applied bias and the distance between the tip 
and fullerene molecule. The bias is applied between the tip and the target 
molecules in Type I process. The red circle and blue square represent the 
switching probability at the tip-molecule distance at d 1 5 4.5 A ˚ and d 2 5 
3.4 A ˚ , respectively. (c) Energy level alignment between the tip and the 
molecule under a bias of 6 V. (d) Rotation possibilities for three process of 
applying a bias between the tip and the molecule. (e) Diagram for 
electronic excitation. (step 1) electron capture and resonance, (step 2) 
nuclear motion, (step 3) electron detrapping and formation of a 
vibrationally excited state. The gained energy weakens or even breaks the 
bond between the molecule and surface (step 4). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 3062 | DOI: 10.1038/srep03062 </p>

<p>
molecule for three types of processes with the same set value of 6 V. It 
is worth noting that all three processes are performed under the same 
tip-molecule distance of 3.4 A ˚ within the same time period of 
25.6 ms. Although the time for a bias at 6 V in type II process is 
much longer than that in type I process, the probability (45.8%) for 
type I process is almost 1.6 times as that (27.8%) for type II process. 
This suggests that the bombardment of low energy electrons which 
are produced only at high voltage (i.e. 6 V) can not account for 
rotating molecular orientation by itself. The obvious difference 
between type I and type II processes is the sweeping-up of the applied 
voltage in type I process. When the applied voltage is monotonically 
increased to the set value in type I process, the Fermi level of the STM 
tip could match certain molecular orbitals, i.e. the 3s* orbital of the 
Si-C bond formed between the fullerene molecule and the Si surface, 
consequently, the incident electrons resonantly tunnel into the 
molecular orbital and are trapped within the molecule, as shown in 
Fig. 4e. After the trapped electron is escaped, the fullerene/Si under-
goes an essentially vertical transition to form a vibrational excited 
state. If sufficient energy has been gained, the molecule can even 
break the bond formed between the molecule and the surface 31 . 
The efficiency of the electronic excitations in type I process due to 
electron resonant trapping is much higher than that in type II process 
in which the energies of the incident electrons are higher than that for 
resonant trapping, therefore, the probability of rotating molecular 
orientation for type I process is much higher than that for type II 
process. 
On the other hand, the probability for type I process is almost 
three times as that (14%) for type III process while the residence time 
at each of the applied voltages are the same for type I and type III 
processes. Such dramatic difference on the probability for type I and 
type III processes reveals that the sequence to apply a tip-molecule 
bias has greatly influences on rotating fullerene molecules. Therefore, 
a two-step model is proposed for rotating the orientation of fullerene 
molecule adsorbed on Si surface, as shown in Fig. 5. The first step is so 
called ''weakening'' process in which the interactions between full-
erene molecules and Si surface are weakened by electronic excitation 
due to the trapping of the incident electrons. The second step is 
''rotation'' process in which the weakened fullerene molecules are 
bombarded to rotate to another orientation by low energy electrons </p>

<p>emitted from the STM tip at higher bias. The fact that the great 
enhancement on the probability of rotating molecular orientation 
is achieved by increasing the applying time of a bias for type II 
process in Fig. 4d further confirms the validity of this two-step 
model. 
In conclusion, we have demonstrated the construction of a revers-
ible molecular switch with the intramolecular orientations as 
information carrier on individual fullerene at room temperature. 
The dependence of rotating probability on the process how a bias 
is applied and the high threshold voltage to rotate fullerene molecules 
give the evidences that the orientation of a 5-6 bond fullerene is 
rotated in two steps in which the bonding of the fullerene with the 
Si surface is weakened due to electronic excitation and then the 
rotation of the molecule is caused by low energy electron bombard-
ment. Such reversible fullerene switch may potentially form building 
elements for molecular logic circuits and high-density data storage 
devices. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>The experiments were carried out in a multi-chamber with ultrahigh vacuum (UHV) 
system housing a SPECS variable temperature STM with a base pressure of less than 
2 3 10 210 mbar. Si (111)-(7 3 7) surfaces were cleaned by degassing samples at 
, 600uC for 12 h and then flash annealing at , 1200uC with direct current sample 
heating for 15-30 s under UHV conditions. After several hours of degassing, full-
erene (Aldrich, purity 99%) was evaporated from a Knudsen cell at 623 K onto the Si 
surfaces at room temperature. STM-images were acquired at room temperature with 
a chemically etched W tip. Positive voltage indicates that the samples were biased 
positively with respect to the tip. Density functional theory (DFT) calculations were 
performed by plane-wave-based <rs type="software">Vienna Ab-initio simulations package [VASP</rs>] 32 . 
The local density appproxmiation according to Ceperley and Alder 33 as parametrized 
by Perdew and Zunger 34 was applied to the exchange-correlation functional while 
optimized relativistic Verderbilt-type ultrasoft pseudopotentials were chosen. A 2.67 
3 2.67 3 2.9 nm 3 surface slab model was built with 400 Si and 60 C atoms. </p>



<p>Figure 5 | Diagram for two-step model for rotation of C 60 by pulse bias. The first step is a weakening process in which the bonds between the C 60 and the </p>

<p>Si atoms are weakened or broken due to the electronic excitation of the tunneling electrons. The second step is that the low energy electrons bombard the 
weakened C 60 to make this molecule rotate by certain degree. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 3062 | DOI: 10.1038/srep03062 </p>



<p>
Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work was financially supported by National Key Basic Research Program of China 
(2013CB934200) and Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant Nos 10979015). L. W. 
acknowledges the Program for New Century Execellent Talents in University, Ministry of 
Education of China (NCET -11-1003) and Jiangxi Provincial ''Ganpo Talentes 555 
Projects''. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>L.W. conceived and designed the experiments. L.L. and S.L. performed the STM 
manipulations. X.C., C.L., J.L. and X.L. contributed analysis tools and assisted the STM 
experiments. Y.C. and S.L. carried out theoretical calculations. L.W. supervised the project. 
All authors discussed the results and analyzed the data. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Liu, L. et al. Switching Molecular Orientation of Individual 
Fullerene at Room Temperature. Sci. Rep. 3, 3062; DOI:10.1038/srep03062 (2013). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported license. To view a copy of this license, 
visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 3062 | DOI: 10.1038/srep03062 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>