<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3567485" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Pseudogenes are genomic DNA sequences homologous to 
functional genes yet are not translated into proteins (1). 
Although pseudogenes are often considered the structur-
ally defective non-functional copies of protein-coding 
genes, the human genome comprises more numbers of 
pseudogenes than corresponding functional genes (2). 
Despite the previous assumption of pseudogenes as </p>

<p>genomic fossils, the genome-wide investigations have 
demonstrated actively transcribed pseudogenes (TPGs) 
with functional potential (3-12). For instant, TPG of nitric 
oxide synthase ( NOS) acts as an antisense regulator of 
neuronal NOS protein synthesis in snails (13, 14). Another 
study has established that binding of transcriptional repres-
sor to receptor of makorin1-p1 could activate the hom-
ologous parental gene Mkrn1 (15), despite contradictory </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, 
provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Page 1 of 9 </p>

<p>(page number not for citation purposes) </p>

<p>Database, Vol. 2013, Article ID bat001, doi:10.1093/database/bat001 </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>result was also reported (16). In addition, the TPG of 
PTENP1 ( PTEN), a highly conserved processed pseudogene 
of tumour suppressor PTEN, acts as a miRNA-decoy by bind-
ing to PTEN-targeting miRNAs (17). Moreover, human 
pseudogene myosin light chain kinase pseudogene 1 is par-
tially duplicated from the original MYLK gene and pro-
motes cancer cell proliferation (18). Above findings clearly 
suggest that the non-coding RNA products of TPGs may 
play an important role in biogenesis pathway and func-
tional processes. 
The RNA interference (RNAi) is an important component 
of the RNA modulation pathway and is incorporated into 
the RNA-induced silencing complex (RISC) with a 
sequence-specific manner (19). In mice and fruit flies, 
double-stranded RNAs arising from the antisense/sense 
transcripts of processed pseudogene, and its cognate 
gene, or hairpin structures from inversion and duplication, 
are cut by Dicer into 21 nt endogenous short interfering 
RNAs (esiRNAs) with the ability to bind RISC and regulate 
the expression of parental gene (20-25). Such regulatory 
mechanism in human remains unclear. 
To demonstrate that in human, as in animal models, TPGs 
may generate naturally occurring siRNAs and Piwi interact-
ing RNAs (piRNAs) to regulate the expression of 
protein-coding genes, we have developed a computational 
pipeline and constructed a database-pseudoMap, the map 
for studying pseudogenes. pseudoMap pre-processes the 
raw data of public microarray and deep sequencing data 
into gene expression profiles for both TPG and its cognate 
gene and small RNA (sRNA) profiles for TPG-derived esiRNAs. 
pseudoMap further combined the gene expression profiles 
to construct the TPG-derived esiRNA-target interactions 
(eSTIs). In addition, according to the previous study of 
pseudogene, PTENP1 exerts a miRNA decoy by binding to </p>

<p>cognate-targeting miRNAs (17), and pseudoMap also pro-
vided the 'miRNA regulator' to elucidate the relationship 
of TPG and its cognate gene with miRNA target regulation. </p>

<p>Data generation </p>

<p>In total, more than 20 000 human pseudogenes and their 
cognate genes were obtained from the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Ensembl Genome Browser</rs> (Ensembl <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">63</rs>, GRCH37) (26) using <rs id="software-1" type="software">BioMart</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http:// www.ensembl.org/index.html</rs>). 
Affymetrix 
GeneChip </p>

<p>Õ </p>

<p>Human Genome U133A/U133Plus2 is a microarray com-
posed of oligonucleotide probes to measure the level of 
transcription of each sequence represented, which included 
transcribed pseudogenes. 1404 pseudogenes have been de-
tectable by this chip, thus considered being transcribed and 
referred as TPGs. Functional sRNAs (fsRNAs) with sequence 
length between 18 to 40 nt were collected from the 
Functional RNA Database (27), which hosts a large collec-
tion of known/predicted non-coding RNA sequences from 
public databases: H-invDB v5.0 (6), FANTOM3 (28), miRBase 
17.0 (29, 30), NONCODE v1.0 (31), Rfam v8.1 (32), RNAdb 
v2.0 (33) and snoRNA-LBME-db rel. 3 (34). The public deep 
sequencing data from sRNA libraries (35-38) were experi-
mented with on human embryo stem cells, liver tissues or 
hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) tissues. Supplementary 
Table 1 summarizes the statistics of the deep sequencing 
data from various sRNA libraries. The genomic sequences 
were obtained from UCSC hg19 (39). Table 1 lists the inte-
grated databases and tools for mining potential regulators 
and functions of human TPGs. </p>

<p>System flow of pseudoMap </p>

<p>The system flow of pseudoMap is shown in Figure 1, mainly 
including the collection of datasets such as TPGs, parental </p>

<p>Table 1. Supported databases and tools in pseudoMap </p>

<p>Integrated database or tools 
Dataset 
Description </p>

<p>miRBase (29, 30) 
miRNA annotation 
This database not only provides published miRNA sequences and 
annotations but also supplies known/predict targets </p>

<p>Functional RNA Database (27) 
sRNA annotation 
A database to support mining and annotation of functional RNAs </p>

<p>Ensembl Genome Browser (26) 
Pseudogene, protein-coding gene 
It produces genome databases for vertebrates and other eukary-
otic species </p>

<p>UCSC Genome Browser (39) 
Conserved region and 
Genomic view of genes </p>

<p>This browser provides a rapid and reliable display of any re-
quested portion of genomes at any scale, together with dozens 
of aligned annotation tracks </p>

<p>GeneCards (52) 
Gene annotation 
GeneCards is a searchable, integrated, database of human genes 
that provides concise genomic-related information of all known 
and predicted human genes </p>

<p>Mfold (40) 
RNA folding tool 
Folding RNA structure </p>

<p>GEO (47) 
Gene expression profiles and 
deep sequencing data </p>

<p>A public functional genomics data </p>

<p>BLAST (51) 
Sequence alignment tool 
BLAST finds regions of similarity between biological sequences </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>Page 2 of 9 </p>

<p>Database tool </p>

<p>Database, Vol. 2013, Article ID bat001, doi:10.1093/database/bat001 </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>genes, fsRNAs, sRNA deep sequencing data, expression pro-
files, integration of various tools and identification of func-
tions and regulations of TPGs. Based on a genome-wide 
computational pipeline of sequence-alignment approaches, 
this work constructed pseudoMap database for elucidation 
of two major discoveries: TPG-derived eSTI and 
miRNA-decoy mechanism of TPGs. The detailed analyses 
are described below. </p>

<p>Identification of TPG-derived 
esiRNAs by public next-generation 
sequencing data </p>

<p>A computational pipeline was developed to verify the 
hypotheses that human TPGs may generate esiRNAs to regu-
late protein-coding genes (Figure 2). An attempt was made 
to identify the candidates of TPG-derived esiRNAs, by align-
ing the sequences of TPGs and fsRNAs. These candidates 
were verified using the deep sequencing data from various </p>

<p>sRNA libraries (35-38) experimented with on human embryo 
stem cells, liver tissues or HCC tissues. The hairpin structure 
by Mfold (40) was then determined by using the extended 
sequences of these candidates of esiRNAs. In pseudoMap, a 
total of 1232 TPGs may produce esiRNAs, which were profil-
ing by deep sequencing data, within 1404 human TPGs were 
characterized. The information of these TPGs is shown in 
Supplementary File 1. The results showed that 4 miRNAs 
and 326 piRNAs may derive from TPGs. We also found that 
miRNA has-miR-622 was identified, which was derived from 
keratin 18 pseudogene 27, located on nt 858-879, as similar 
as miRBase database. Table 2 summarizes the entire statis-
tical analysis of pseudoMap. </p>

<p>Identification of TPG-derived 
esiRNA-target interactions </p>

<p>Our previous approach (41) was modified to identify 
TPG-derived esiRNA targets. Briefly, the esiRNA target </p>

<p>Figure 1. System flow of pseudoMap. The system flow of pseudoMap mainly includes the collection of datasets such as TPGs, 
parental genes, miRNAs, piRNAs, sRNA deep sequencing data and expression profiles; integration of various tools and identifi-
cation of functions and regulations of TPGs. Based on a genome-wide computational pipeline of sequence-alignment approaches 
and gene expression profiles, this work constructed pseudoMap database for elucidation of two major discoveries: TPG-derived 
esiRNA-target interaction and miRNA-decoy mechanism of TPGs. </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>Page 3 of 9 </p>

<p>Database, Vol. 2013, Article ID bat001, doi:10.1093/database/bat001 </p>

<p>Database tool </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>sites within the conserved regions of coding, 5'-UTR and 
3'-UTR of genes were identified in 12 metazoan genomes 
by using three computational approaches, TargetScan (42- 44), miRanda (45) and RNAhybrid (46). The minima free 
energy (MFE) threshold was À20 kcal/mol with a score 
more than or equal to 150 for miRanda and default param-
eters for TargetScan and RNAhybrid. The targets were iden-
tified using the following criteria: (i) the potential target 
sites were determined by at least two approaches; (ii) mul-
tiple target sites were prioritized and (iii) target sites must 
be located in accessible regions. Finally, we provided the 
gene expression profiles of TPG and its cognate gene to 
construct the eSTIs. </p>

<p>Gene expression analysis </p>

<p>The mRNA abundances of TPGs and protein-coding genes 
were obtained from Gene Expression Omnibus (47), such as 
GDS596 examined from 79 human physiologically normal 
tissues (48), GSE2109 examined from 2158 samples with 61 
tumour tissues, GSE3526 examined from 353 samples with 
65 normal tissues (49) and GSE5364 examined from primary 
human tumours and adjacent non-tumour tissues, which 
include 270 tumours and 71 normal-cancer pairs from pa-
tients with breast, colon, liver, lung, oesophagal and thy-
roid cancers (50). Moreover, the Pearson correlation 
coefficient was computed from TPGs and protein-coding 
genes. </p>

<p>Determination of miRNA-target 
interactions </p>

<p>According to the study by Poliseno et al. (17), pseudogenes 
PTENP1 and KRAS1P act as a 'miRNA decoy', binding to and 
thereby reducing the effective cellular concentration of </p>

<p>Figure 2. Computational pipeline for identification of TPG-derived esiRNA-target interactions. </p>

<p>Table 2. Summarizes the entire statistical analysis of 
pseudoMap </p>

<p>Dataset 
Counts </p>

<p>No. of miRNA regulators 
5771/1014 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>No. of TPG-derived miRNAs 
4 </p>

<p>No. of TPG-derived piRNAs 
326 </p>

<p>Deep sequencing data for profiling TPG-derived esiRNAs </p>

<p>Human embryo stem cell-hB 
247 </p>

<p>Human embryo stem cell-hESC 
553 </p>

<p>Human embryo stem cell-hues6 
190 </p>

<p>Human embryo stem cell-hues6NP 
81 </p>

<p>Human embryo stem cell-hues6Neuron 
16 </p>

<p>HBV(+) adjacent tissue sample 1 
917 </p>

<p>HBV(+) adjacent tissue sample 2 
4377 </p>

<p>HBV(+) distal tissue sample 1 
1011 </p>

<p>HBV(+) HCC tissue sample 1 
1281 </p>

<p>HBV(+) HCC tissue sample 2 
2649 </p>

<p>HBV-infected liver tissue 
3056 </p>

<p>HBV(+) side tissue sample 1 
1087 </p>

<p>HCV(+) adjacent tissue sample 
14 297 </p>

<p>HCV(+) HCC tissue sample 
9277 </p>

<p>HBV(À) HCV(À) adjacent tissue sample 
2324 </p>

<p>HBV(À) HCV(À) HCC tissue sample 
6579 </p>

<p>Human normal liver tissue sample 1 
1220 </p>

<p>Human normal liver tissue sample 2 
1290 </p>

<p>Human normal liver tissue sample 3 
1209 </p>

<p>Severe chronic hepatitis B liver tissue 
1247 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1014 distinct miRNAs involved in 5771 miRNA regulators. </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>Page 4 of 9 </p>

<p>Database tool </p>

<p>Database, Vol. 2013, Article ID bat001, doi:10.1093/database/bat001 </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>miRNAs, therefore resulting their cognate genes to escape 
miRNA-mediated repression. In this study, we analyse the 
relationships between TPG and its cognate gene with 
miRNA decoys mechanism to examine miRNA-target inter-
actions (MTIs) by performing a pipeline. First, the parental 
genes were obtained by mapping the TPGs and genomic 
sequences with the BLAST (51) program. The MTIs with 
TPGs and parental genes were then investigated using 
our previous approach (41). The MFE threshold was 
À20 kcal/mol with a score more than or equal to 150 for 
miRanda and default parameters for TargetScan and 
RNAhybrid. Finally, the TPGs and their cognates 
co-regulated by miRNAs were obtained. The miRNA and 
3'UTR sequences were obtained from miRBase R18 </p>

<p>(29, 30) and <rs type="software">Ensembl</rs> Genome Browser release 63 (26), re-
spectively. Analysis results indicated that 874 miRNAs with 
MFE À20 and Score ! 150 interact with many possible 
target sites in 248 TPGs and their cognate genes and 
might potentially co-regulate this pair of TPG and parental 
gene (Supplementary File 2). </p>

<p>Web interface </p>

<p>As a web-based system, pseudoMap can thoroughly iden-
tify TPGs, including TPGs act as a miRNA regulators and 
TPGs-derived eSTIs in humans. There are two ways to 
access pseudoMap: by browsing the database content or 
by searching for a particular TPG. Figure 3A displays the </p>

<p>Figure 3. Web interface of pseudoMap. (A) Browse interface of pseudoMap illustrates general information of TPGs, miRNA 
regulators, esiRNAs and gene expression profiles. (B) The miRNA regulator indicates the miRNA decoys mechanisms between TPG 
and its cognate. (C) Gene expression profiles of TPG and its cognate gene in various experimental conditions. (D) The diagram of 
esiRNA represents TPG-derived siRNAs as profiled by deep sequencing data. It displays the more fine-grained information of 
(E) esiRNA-target interaction and (F) RNA folding structure of TPG-derived esiRNA. In addition, pseudoMap also incorporates the 
external sources, such as (G) UCSC genome browser for a genomic view, GeneCards for gene annotation and miRBase for miRNA 
annotation. </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>Page 5 of 9 </p>

<p>Database, Vol. 2013, Article ID bat001, doi:10.1093/database/bat001 </p>

<p>Database tool </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>interface of output results of the browse gateway. The 
interface contains general information of TPGs, the rela-
tionships of TPG and its cognate gene with miRNA-
mediated repression termed as 'miRNA Regulator', 
TPG-derived eSTIs named as 'esiRNA', and 'Expression' 
showed the gene expression profiles. Figure 3B provides a 
detailed view of miRNA regulator, which displays more 
fine-grained information. Above results indicated the rela-
tionships between TPGs and cognate genes by a miRNA 
decoy mechanism such as that observed by Poliseno et al. 
(17). The 'Expression' presents the gene expression profiles 
of not only distinct TPG and corresponding parental gene 
but also TPG referenced by cognate in various experimental 
conditions (Figure 3C). Moreover, the view of esiRNA indi-
cates the TPG-derived esiRNAs and graphical display of 
deep sequencing data (Figure 3D). The red line represents </p>

<p>the TPG and the blue line refers to esiRNAs. We also esti-
mate the eSTIs (Figure 3E) and the RNA folding structure of 
TPG-derived esiRNA (Figure 3F). All the results and se-
quences can be downloaded for further experimental 
tests. In pseudoMap, we also incorporate the external 
sources, such as UCSC genome browser (39) for a genomic 
view, GeneCards (52) for gene annotation and miRBase (29)  for miRNA annotation (Figure 3G). In addition, pseudoMap 
also consists of a tutorial and knowledge of pseudogenes. 
In the search gateway, the TPG ID, <rs type="software">Ensembl ID</rs>, TPG 
symbol and parental gene symbol are allowed for further 
analysis. Figure 4 displays the interface of output results 
with the search a particular TPG ID/<rs type="software">Ensembl ID</rs>/TPG 
symbol/parental gene symbol. The interface contains the 
general information of TPG, miRNA regulators, gene ex-
pression profiles and TPG-derived esiRNAs. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Search interface of pseudoMap. </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>Page 6 of 9 </p>

<p>Database tool </p>

<p>Database, Vol. 2013, Article ID bat001, doi:10.1093/database/bat001 </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>Construction and content </p>

<p>In pseudoMap, various databases are integrated and main-
tained with <rs id="software-5" type="software">MySQL</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="url">http://www.mysql.com</rs>/) relational 
database management system. While operating on an 
<rs id="software-6" type="software">Apache HTTP server</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-6" type="url">http://www.apache.org</rs>/) and PHP 
(http://www.php.net/) on a <rs id="software-7" type="software">Linux operation system</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-7" type="url">http:// www.linux.com</rs>), pseudoMap was constructed using the 
Smarty template engine (http://www.smarty.net). Based 
on PHP, JavaScript (http://www.javascriptsource.com/), CSS 
(http://www.w3schools.com/css/) and HTML (http://www. 
w3schools.com/html/) languages, the web interface enables 
dynamic <rs type="software">MySQL</rs> queries with user-friendly graphics. Above 
software are open source technologies. </p>

<p>Discussion and conclusions </p>

<p>Comparison with other previous databases related to 
pseudogenes </p>

<p>A few databases have been constructed to explore pseudo-
genes. In particular, PseudoGene database (53) identifies 
pseudogenes using various computational methods in 
genomes; HOPPSIGEN (54) represents the homologous pro-
cessed pseudogenes shared between the mouse and human 
genomes that contains location information and potential 
function; as a web-based system, <rs type="software">PseudoGeneQuest</rs> (55)  identifies novel human pseudogenes based on a user-
provided protein sequence; in addition, the University of 
Iowa's UI Pseudogenes website contains human pseudo-
genes and the candidates for gene conversion (56). 
However, these databases focus on automatic detection 
of pseudogenes by using a variety of homology-based 
approaches. Our database, pseudoMap, aims at providing 
comprehensive resource for genome-wide identifying the 
functions and regulators of human TPGs. In briefly, there 
are three major differentiating features from currently 
public databases of pseudogenes. First, pseudoMap eluci-
dates the relationships of TPG and its cognate gene with 
miRNA decoys mechanism. Second, to explore the inter-
action of TPG and its parental gene, pseudoMap provides 
the gene expression profiles of TPG and its cognate gene in 
various experimental conditions. Third, pseudoMap curates 
the TPG-derived esiRNAs, which supported by deep sequen-
cing data, as well as their interacting gene targets in the 
human genome. Table 3 lists the detailed comparisons of 
pseudoMap with other previous databases related to 
pseudogenes. </p>

<p>Applications </p>

<p>PseudoMap provides two major applications. One is the 
non-coding RNA products of TPGs, as like animal models, 
that may generate esiRNAs to regulate protein-coding 
genes in humans. In this process, pseudoMap supplies 
next-generation sequencing data from sRNA libraries to </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparisons of pseudoMap with currently public databases of pseudogenes </p>

<p>Supported features </p>

<p>pseudoMap (our database) </p>

<p>PseudoGene database </p>

<p>UI pseudogene </p>

<p>Hoppsigen </p>

<p>Web interface </p>

<p>http://pseudomap.mbc.nctu.edu.tw/ </p>

<p>http://www.pseudogene.org/ </p>

<p>https://genome.uiowa.edu/pseudogenes/ </p>

<p>http://pbil.univ-lyon1.fr/databases/hopp </p>

<p>sigen.html </p>

<p>Description 
pseudoMap provides a comprehensive re-
source for genome-wide identifying the 
functions and regulators of human 
pseudogenes. </p>

<p>This site contains a comprehensive 
database of identified pseudogenes, 
utilities used to find pseudogenes, 
various publication data sets and a 
pseudogene knowledgebase. 
This site serves as a repository for all 
pseudogenes in the human genome and </p>

<p>provides a ranked list of human 
pseudogenes that have been identified </p>

<p>as candidates for gene conversion. </p>

<p>Hoppsigen is a nucleic database of 
homologous processed pseudogenes. </p>

<p>Species supported </p>

<p>Human </p>

<p>Eukaryote and prokaryote </p>

<p>Human </p>

<p>Human </p>

<p>Sequence download </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Pseudogene information </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Parental gene information </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Knowledge of pseudogenes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>miRNA-pseudogene interactions </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>miRNA-parental gene interactions Yes </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Gene expression profiles 
Yes (both pseudogene and its parental gene) -</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Pseudogene-derived siRNAs </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Deep sequencing data for 
profiling TPG-derived siRNAs </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>Page 7 of 9 </p>

<p>Database, Vol. 2013, Article ID bat001, doi:10.1093/database/bat001 </p>

<p>Database tool </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>support the candidates of TPG-derived esiRNAs and 
gene expression profiles to verify the target interactions, 
respectively. Another application is that both the gene 
and pseudogene contain miRNA target sites, if the 
pseudogene competes for the freely available repressor 
molecules that would be free the gene to reduce the 
miRNA-mediated repression. Another words, the 
pseudogene may act as a 'miRNA decoy' to release the re-
pression of its cognate gene. pseudoMap provides another 
insight into the pathway of MTIs with TPG-mediated 
mechanism. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In this study, we performed a computational pipeline to 
identify TPG-derived esiRNAs-target interactions and con-
structed a comprehensive database to represent the poten-
tial functions and regulators of TPGs in human. To our 
knowledge, the pseudoMap is the first database to identify 
TPGs to enable biologists and bioinformaticians to eluci-
date two major discoveries, the relationships between 
TPG and its cognate gene with miRNA decoyed mechanisms 
and TPG-derived eSTIs. Efforts are underway in our labora-
tory to expand the methods used in pseudoMap to other 
species such as mice, fruit flies and plants. The pseudoMap 
will be updated frequently by continuingly surveying ex-
perimentally validated sRNAs and will be maintained with 
a long-term support from National Chiao Tung University 
and National Science Council at Taiwan. This novel and cre-
ative resource is now freely available at http://pseudomap. 
mbc.nctu.edu.tw/. </p>

<p>Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at Database online. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>National Science Council of the Republic of China [NSC 
99-2320-B-037-006-MY3 to J.G.C., NSC 98-2314-B039-
010MY3 to W.K.Y., NSC 98-2311-B-009-004-MY3 to H.D.H., 
NSC 99-2627-B-009-003 to H.D.H., NSC 101-2311-B-
009-003-MY3 to H.D.H. and NSC 100-2627-B-009-002 to 
H.D.H.]; UST-UCSD International Center of Excellence in 
Advanced Bio-engineering sponsored by the Taiwan 
National Science Council I-RiCE Program [NSC 101-2911-I-
009 -101 -to H.D.H., in part]; Veterans General Hospitals 
and University System of Taiwan (VGHUST) Joint Research 
Program [VGHUST101-G5-1-1 to H.D.H., in part]; MOE ATU 
[in part]. Funding for open access charge: National Science 
Council of the Republic of China. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>Page 8 of 9 </p>

<p>Database tool </p>

<p>Database, Vol. 2013, Article ID bat001, doi:10.1093/database/bat001 </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>



<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>Page 9 of 9 </p>

<p>Database, Vol. 2013, Article ID bat001, doi:10.1093/database/bat001 </p>

<p>Database tool </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

</text></tei>