<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3894438" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background/Aims: Infectious mononucleosis (IM) is the clinical presentation of primary infection with Epstein-Barr 
virus. Although the literature contains a massive amount of information on IM, most of this is related specifically 
to only children or adults separately. In order to distinguish any differences between preschool children and youth 
patients, we retrospectively analyzed their demographic and clinical features. 
Methods: Records of patients hospitalized from December 2001 to September 2011 with a diagnosis of IM were 
retrieved from Peking University First Hospital, which is a tertiary teaching hospital in Beijing. The demographic data 
and clinical characteristics were collected. 
Results: IM was diagnosed in 287 patients during this 10-year period, with incidence peaks among preschool children 
(≤7 years old, 130/287, 45.3%) and youth patients (&gt;15 and &lt;24 years old, 101/287, 35.2%). Although the complaints 
at admission did not differ between these two patient groups, the incidence of clinical signs (tonsillopharyngitis, 
lymphadenopathy, hepatomegaly, and edema of the eyelids) was much higher in preschool children. The incidence 
of liver lesion and percentage of atypical lymphocytes were significantly higher in the youth group (P&lt;0.001), and the 
average hospital stay was longer in this group. Pneumonia was the most common complication, and there was no 
case of mortality. 
Conclusions: The incidence of IM peaks among preschool children and youth patients in Beijing, China. The levels of 
liver enzymes and atypical lymphocytes increase with age. (Clin Mol Hepatol 2013;19:382-388) 
Infectious mononucleosis (IM) is the clinical syndrome caused 
by Epstein-Barr virus (EBV), which presents with fever, pharyngitis, 
cervical adenopathy, and other various manifestations. EBV is a 
member of the human herpesvirus family, which has a double 
stranded DNA genome. As other members of herpesivirus family, </p>

<p>lifelong latent infection in B lymphocytes is the result of the pri-
mary EBV infection. The virus could be reactivated when host im-
mune response is severely impaired, like organ transplant recipi-
ent, taking glucocorticoids or other immunosuppressant for a long 
time, or infected with human immunodeficiency virus. 
Seroprevalence of antibodies to EBV varied with socioeconomic 
conditions. In Tokyo (Japan), the positive rate of IgG antibody to </p>



<p>Yan Wang, et al. 
Markedly elevated liver enzymes in youth with IM </p>

<p>http://www.e-cmh.org 
http://dx.doi.org/10.3350/cmh.2013.19.4.382 </p>

<p>viral capsid antigen (VCA) in children aged 5-to 7-year old was 
higher than 80% in early 1990s, contrasting to 59% in years 
1995-1999. 
1 An early study published in 1994 addressed that al-</p>

<p>most all the children younger than 10 years in Hong Kong had 
been infected with EBV. 
2 A recent survey in year 2006 found that </p>

<p>the overall seropositive rate of EBV VCA IgG was 83.6% in chil-
dren under 14 years old in Beijing. 
3 The positive rate in rural areas </p>

<p>was significantly higher (86.2%) than that in urban areas (80.8%). 
There is a delay trend of EBV infection in mainland China along 
with the improved economic and sanitary conditions. 
Primary infection of EBV is frequently asymptomatic in infants 
and children. Even in susceptible youths and young adults, only 
30-50% of the infected persons present as IM. 
4 In the USA, there </p>

<p>is about 500 IM patients per 100,000 persons per year and the 
most of the patients are aged 15 to 24 years old. 
5 A retrospective </p>

<p>study enrolled 418 hospitalized patients with IM younger than 18 
years old in Beijing found that the incidence of IM peaked in chil-
dren aged from 4 to 6 years. 
6 This was coincident with the study </p>

<p>in Taiwan in 2005. 
7 Hospitalized children were their research </p>

<p>group in both studies. 
There was not comparison study focusing the different clinical 
features between children and youth patients with IM in a same 
area. Our study observed the similarities and differences of the 
clinical appearance between these 2 age groups. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>Records of patients discharged with diagnosis of Infectious 
mononucleosis (IM) between December 2001 and September 
2011 were retrieved in Peking University First Hospital, a tertiary 
teaching hospital in Beijing, China. 
All the patients in this study had at least 3 symptoms of fever, 
tonsillopharyngitis, rash, lymphadenopathy, hepatomegaly, or 
splenomegaly apart from more than 10% of atypical-lymphocytes 
in peripheral blood and positive result of anti-EBV IgM. 
5 We ex-</p>

<p>cluded chronic active EBV infection patients and co-infection pa-
tients. </p>

<p>Data collecting </p>

<p>The demographic data and clinical information were obtained 
from each patient's record, the latter including underlying diseas-</p>

<p>es, presenting symptoms and signs, laboratory parameters, and 
anti-EBV-IgM, serum EBV DNA load, patients' responses to treat-
ment and outcome. 
EBV DNA was detected by using fluorescent polymerase chain 
reaction diagnostic kit (Da An Gene Co., Ltd. Of Sun Yat-sen Uni-
versity, China), the lower limit for detection was 500 copies/ml. 
Anti-EBV IgM was detected by ELISA kit (Sino-American bio-
technology Co. Ltd, China) before 2005 and by chemiluminescence 
(DiaSorin LIAISON 
® Analyzer, Italy) after 2005. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Descriptive statistics were used to characterize the study sub-
jects and were summarized as the mean±standard deviation or 
the median (range) for continuous data. The Student's t-test or the 
Mann-Whitney U-test was employed to compare continuous vari-
ables between the groups, where appropriate. The chi-square test 
or the Fisher exact test was performed to compare categorical 
variables between groups. 
All statistical analyses were performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> software, 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 9.1.3</rs>; a two-sided P-value of &lt;0.05 was considered statis-
tically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Demographic data of all patients </p>

<p>We identified 287 patients with diagnosis of IM out of 484 pa-
tients that had EBV infection. 
IM patients were aged from 0.6-to 39-year old with the median 
11-year old. There were 2 peak ages of incidence: one was pre-
school children (≤7-year old, 130/287, 45.3%), the other one was </p>

<p>Figure 1. Age distribution of all patients with infectious mononucleosis. </p>



<p>Clin Mol Hepatol 
Volume_19 Number_4 December 2013 </p>

<p>http://www.e-cmh.org 
http://dx.doi.org/10.3350/cmh.2013.19.4.382 </p>

<p>youth (older than 15-but younger than 24-year old, 101/287, 
35.2%). Patients' age distribution was shown in Figure 1. 
There were 163 males (male:female=1:1.3). Only 46 patients 
(16%) had underlying diseases (Bacterial infections, cardiomyopa-
thy, viral hepatitis caused by hepatitis A or B virus, fatty liver, and 
hyperthyroidism). </p>

<p>Clinical features of all patients </p>

<p>Fever (96.9%) and tonsillopharyngitis (94.1%) were the most 
common complains on admission. The median day of fever was 11 
with ranging from 1 to 67 days. Rash (18.8%) was found in less 
than 1/5 of all IM patients of all ages. Lymphadenopathy could be 
found in 90.2% of patients. In laboratory examination, abnormal 
elevated liver enzymes were shown in nearly 4/5 of patients. There 
were less than 10% (28/287) patients with pneumonia. Patients' 
clinical characteristics on admission were shown in Table 1. 
The results of blood regular test and liver enzymes were most 
common abnormal laboratory on admission. The median atypical-
lymphocytes were 20% with the highest 85% on their first pre-
sentation in hospital. Nearly half (48.4%, 139/287) of patients' </p>

<p>atypical-lymphocytes had recovered to less than 10% before they 
left hospital. More than half of them (57.6%, 80/139) were pre-
school children. Liver aminotransferases increased when admis-
sion and recovered before discharge from hospital. Total bilirubin 
elevated in 12.6% (32/254) patients on admission and did not re-
turn to normal in only 3.3% patients (6/183) before released from 
hospital. Over half of patients (52.8%, 133/252) had increased 
glutamyltranspetidase on admission at median 59 IU/L. Although 
the median gamma-glutamyl transferase (GGT) returned to normal 
range, there were nearly half of the patients (47.8%, 85/178) need 
to wait this parameter recovered at home. The comparison of lab-
oratory parameters presented on Table 2. 
All the patients stayed in hospital for a median 12 days. Only 21 
(7.4%) patients had been treated with glucocorticoid during hos-
pitalization. There was no dead case. 
We confirmed that only 2 patients had complicated hemo-
phagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. 
8 All these 2 patients were older </p>

<p>than 7-year old and had detectable EBV DNA in serum samples on 
admission. They recovered well when they were released from 
hospital. </p>

<p>Table 1. Clinical features of all patients with infectious mononucleosis on admission </p>

<p>Percentage 
Number of patients 
Available of patients </p>

<p>Fever 
96.9 
278 
287 </p>

<p>Tonsillopharyngitis 
94.1 
270 
287 </p>

<p>Rash 
18.8 
54 
287 </p>

<p>Cervical lymphadenopathy 
90.2 
259 
287 </p>

<p>Splenomegaly 
60.6 
174 
287 </p>

<p>Hepatomegaly 
49.8 
143 
287 </p>

<p>Edema of the eyelids 
23.8 
68 
286 </p>

<p>Elevated ALT 
74.7 
213 
285 </p>

<p>Elavated AST 
74.1 
209 
282 </p>

<p>Elevated GGT 
52.8 
133 
252 </p>

<p>Elevated Tbil 
12.6 
32 
254 </p>

<p>Detectable serum EBV DNA 
54.2 
32 
59 </p>

<p>Neutropenia 
45.3 
130 
284 </p>

<p>Thrombocytopenia 
4.5 
11 
244 </p>

<p>Pneumonia 
9.8 
28 
286 </p>

<p>Bronchitis 
2.8 
8 
286 </p>

<p>Tonsillitis 
2.8 
8 
286 </p>

<p>Neutropenia, neutrophil &lt;1.5×10 
9 /L. Thrombocytopenia, thrombocyte &lt;100×10 
9 /L. Pneumonia, parenchymal and interstitial impairments according to X-ray. 
ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase; GGT, gamma-glutamyl transferase; PLT, platelet; Tbil, total bilirubin; EBV, Epstein-Barr virus. 
Elevated ALT, AST, GGT and Tbil, above upper normal limits. </p>



<p>Yan Wang, et al. 
Markedly elevated liver enzymes in youth with IM </p>

<p>http://www.e-cmh.org 
http://dx.doi.org/10.3350/cmh.2013.19.4.382 </p>

<p>Table 3. Differences in clinical features between preschool children and youth patients </p>

<p>Preschool children 
Youth </p>

<p>Percentage 
Number of 
patients </p>

<p>Available of 
patients 
Percentage 
Number of 
patients </p>

<p>Available of 
patients </p>

<p>Fever 
96.9% 
126 
130 
97.0% 
98 
101 </p>

<p>Tonsillopharyngitis 
97.7% 
127 
130 
90.1% 
91 
101 </p>

<p>Rash 
21.5% 
28 
130 
13.9% 
14 
101 </p>

<p>Cervical lymphadenopathy </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>94.6% 
123 
130 
85.1% 
86 
101 </p>

<p>Hepatomegaly </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>78.5% 
102 
130 
15.8% 
16 
101 </p>

<p>Splenomegaly 
61.5% 
80 
130 
58.4% 
59 
101 </p>

<p>Edema of the eyelids 
35.4% 
46 
130 
8.0% 
8 
101 </p>

<p>Elevated AST </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>63.2% 
79 
125 
85.1% 
86 
101 </p>

<p>Elevated ALT </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>55.5% 
71 
128 
91.1% 
92 
101 </p>

<p>Elevated GGT </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>23.9% 
27 
113 
78.9% 
71 
90 </p>

<p>Elevated Tbil </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>1.7% 
2 
116 
26.4% 
24 
91 </p>

<p>Neutropenia </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>22.3% 
29 
130 
73.3% 
74 
101 </p>

<p>Thrombocytopenia 
2.3% 
3 
130 
5.0% 
5 
101 </p>

<p>Detectable serum EBV DNA 
35.7% 
5 
14 
61.8% 
21 
34 </p>

<p>Pneumonia </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>20.0% 
26 
130 
0.0% 
0 
101 </p>

<p>Bronchitis 
5.4% 
7 
130 
1.0% 
1 
101 </p>

<p>Tonsillitis 
0.0% 
0 
130 
6.9% 
7 
101 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>There were significant differences between preschool children and adolencent patients, P&lt;0.050. Elevated ALT, AST, GGT and Tbil, above upper normal limits. 
Neutropenia, neutrophil &lt;1.5×10 
9 /L. Thrombocytopenia, thrombocyte &lt;100×10 
9 /L. Pneumonia, parenchymal and interstitial impairments according to X-ray. </p>

<p>Table 2. Laboratory results of all patients with infectious mononucleosis on admission and before leaving hospital </p>

<p>On admission 
Discharge from hospital </p>

<p>WBC count (×10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L) 
13.9 (3.5-36.5) 
6.5 (2.8-21.4) </p>

<p>Lymphocytes (%) 
63.4 (15.5-86.8) 
62.9 (3.7-85.6) </p>

<p>Atypical-lymphocytes (%) 
20 (10-85) 
4 (1-35) </p>

<p>PLT (×10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L) 
172.5 (22-380) 
253.5 (5-562) </p>

<p>ALT (IU/L) 
104 (8-1110) 
50 (9-391) </p>

<p>AST (IU/L) 
72 (16-1204) 
38 (12-254) </p>

<p>GGT (IU/L) 
59 (0.3-596) 
46.5 (3-302) </p>

<p>Tbil (umol/L) 
8.8 (1.8-133.5) 
8.4 (1.2-76.2) </p>

<p>Dbil (umol/L) 
2.29 (0.1-84.7) 
1.45 (0-47.3) </p>

<p>LDH (IU/L) 
410 (156-1448) 
288 (101-715) </p>

<p>CK (IU/L) 
41 (13-1482) 
45 (11-144) </p>

<p>All the data presented here were medians and range (minimum-maximum). 
WBC: white blood cell; PLT: platelet; ALT: alanine aminotransferase; AST: aspartate aminotransferase; GGT, gamma-glutamyl transferase; Tbil, total bilirubin; 
Dbil, direct bilirubin; LDH, lactic dehydrogenase; CK, creatine kinase. </p>



<p>Clin Mol Hepatol 
Volume_19 Number_4 December 2013 </p>

<p>http://www.e-cmh.org 
http://dx.doi.org/10.3350/cmh.2013.19.4.382 </p>

<p>More clinical signs in preschool children on 
admission </p>

<p>We noticed that there existed 2 age peaks of our 287 patients: 
preschool (≤7-year old, 45.3%) and youth (from 15-to 24-year old, 
35.2%), as shown in Figure 1. We sought the similarities and di-
versities between these 2 groups of patients. We didn't find any 
difference in their sex distribution, underlying diseases, and the 
incident rates of fever and rash when they first presented at hospi-
tal. Interestingly, there were much more children with tonsillopha-
ryngitis (97.7% vs. 90.1%, P&lt;0.050), lymphadenopathy (94.6% 
vs. 85.1%, P&lt;0.050), hepatomegaly (78.5% vs. 15.8%, P&lt;0.001), 
and edema of the eyelids (35.4% vs. 8.0%, P&lt;0.001) than that of 
youth on admission physical exam, as shown in Table 3. All of 
these indicated that there was no difference in complaints be-
tween the children and youth, but more signs were found on ad-
mission physical examinations. </p>

<p>Significantly liver lesion and higher percentage 
of atypical-lymphocytes in youth </p>

<p>We found a significantly higher atypical-lymphocytes (median 
22.0 vs. 18.0, P&lt;0.001) but lower white blood cell count (13.6 
±5.72 vs. 16.3±6.7, P&lt;0.001) and platelet count (165.4±44.9 vs. 
187.4±64.0, P=0.010) in youth than preschool children. 
Youth patients had significantly increased liver enzymes (includ-
ing alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase 
(AST), and GGT, all P-values &lt;0.001) than that of preschool chil-</p>

<p>dren. Although the median value of total bilirubin was normal in 
both age groups, we found much more youth patients with abnor-
mal total bilirubin (26.4%, 24/91) than preschool children (1.8%, 
2/114). All the lab results listed in Table 4. 
Youth patients stayed in hospital for a longer time than that of 
preschool children (15.1±7.5 days vs. 11.2±4.7 days, P&lt;0.001). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We retrospectively analyzed the demographic and clinical re-
cords of 287 hospitalized patients admitted during 2001 to 2011. 
Preschool children and youth were 2 incident peak groups of IM. 
Previous studies found that preschool children had the highest in-
cidence of IM in China. 
3,6-7,9 Youths aged 15-to 24-year old were </p>

<p>the most common patients with IM in west countries. 
4-5,10 There </p>

<p>were 2 explanations for the dissimilarities. Firstly, this shifting 
trend in the onset age of IM in Beijing probably reflects the im-
provement of China's socioeconomics. This consists with the sero-
logical survey in 2008. The seropositive rate decreased from 90% 
in 1970's to 82.5% in 2008 in preschool children in Beijing. The 
study also found that much more children in the rural areas 
(75.3%) suffered primary EBV infection than those lived in the ur-
ban areas (67.7%). 
3 Similarly shift was found in Japan 
1 by compar-</p>

<p>ing seropositive rate in 1995-1999 (59%) with the early 1990s 
(&gt;80%). Secondly, different study objects from previous reports 
could be another reasonable explanation. Previous reports only in-
cluded patients younger than 18-year old 
6-7,9,11-12 or in university </p>

<p>Table 4. Differences in laboratory results and hospital charges between preschool children and youth patients on admission </p>

<p>Preschool children 
Youth 
P-vaule </p>

<p>WBC count(10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L), mean±SD 
16.3±6.7 
13.6±5.7 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>PLT (10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L), mean±SD 
187.4±64.0 
165.4±44.9 
0.010 </p>

<p>Lymphocytes (%), mean±SD 
60.4±16.9 
62.6±10.9 
0.270 </p>

<p>Atypical-lymphocytes (%), median (range) 
18.0 (73.0-10.0) 
22.0 (85.0-10.0) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>ALT (IU/L), median (range) 
45.5 (505.0-8.0) 
193.5 (1110.0-10.0) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>AST (IU/L), median (range) 
51.0 (402.0-21.0) 
116.0 (1204.0-16.0) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>GGT (IU/L), median (range) 
19.0 (247.0-1.0) 
113.5 (596.0-0.3) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Tbil (μmol/L), median (range) 
6.5 (108.7-1.8) 
12.4 (107.0-2.8) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>LDH (IU/L), mean±SD 
418.0±119.9 
470.1±169.9 
0.050 </p>

<p>CK (IU/L), median (range) 
43.0 (190.0-21.0) 
40.0 (1482.0-16.0) 
0.290 </p>

<p>The data presented here were medians and range or mean±SD. 
WBC, white blood cell; PLT, platelet; ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase; GGT, gamma-glutamyl transferase; Tbil, total bilirubin; 
Dbil, direct bilirubin; LDH, lactic dehydrogenase; CK, creatine kinase. </p>



<p>Yan Wang, et al. 
Markedly elevated liver enzymes in youth with IM </p>

<p>http://www.e-cmh.org 
http://dx.doi.org/10.3350/cmh.2013.19.4.382 </p>

<p>students. 
13-14 We collected patients with confirmed diagnose of IM </p>

<p>at all ages, hospitalized in paediatrics department and non-paedi-
atrics department. 
Youth patients with over 10% of atypical-lymphocytoes without 
typical clinical triad of IM also need to find the evidence of EBV in-
fection. The incidence of triad was significant lower in youth pa-
tients (74.3%) than in preschool children (90.8%), P&lt;0.001. A sig-
nificant higher atypical-lymphocyte percentage was one of 
notable features of our youth patients (Table 4). These were coin-
cident with a previous study in patients aged 18-23 years. 
15 They </p>

<p>also found a low incidence of triad of 68.2% and the specificity of 
clinical triad was 41.9% for IM diagnosis. 
Higher occurrence of liver injury in youth patients was promi-
nent in our study. Elevated aminotransferase and gamma-glutamyl 
transferase were the features of liver lesion in our study (Tables 1 
and 4). Hyperbilirubinemia was not common in our patients 
(26.4%, 24/91) and disappeared before discharging from hospital. 
On the contrary, 36.8% of preschool patients had normal liver 
function and only 2 children had increased total bilirubin. Our re-
sults were consistent with previous studies in different age groups. 
Over 80% of older than 16-year IM patients presented abnormal 
aminotransferase, especially alanine aminotransferase. 
5,10,16 Jaun-</p>

<p>dice was uncommon. 
5,10,16 Less than half of children (30.9%, </p>

<p>48.6%) with IM had liver dysfunction. 
6,11,17 The mechanism of liver </p>

<p>involvement in IM patients was unclear, much less in the discrep-
ancy between different age group. CD3 positive T lymphocytes 
were identified as the main lymphocytic infiltrate in EBV hepatitis, 
which were mainly cytotoxic CD8 positive T lymphocytes. 
18-20 Sev-</p>

<p>eral studies have shown increased level of inflammatory cytokines 
in the sera of IM patients. 
10,21 Interferon-γ was a prominent one </p>

<p>among these inflammator y c y tokine. Increased level of 
Interferon-γ and its catabolic product may induce liver dysfunc-
tion. 
10,18 Further research about the pathogenesis was warranted. </p>

<p>There were pure clinical presentations of hospitalized patients 
with IM, which was the limitation of our study. Monitoring cyto-
kine profile in serum and organs would be the next step. 
In summary, both preschool children and youth were high-inci-
dence group of IM in Beijing. Much more preschool children pre-
sented with clinical triad of IM. Youth patients with IM were 
marked with significant higher percentage of atypical-lymphocytes 
and elevated liver enzymes. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by The National Natural Science Foun-</p>

<p>dation of China [81170386 and 81241013 to H. Z.]. </p>

<p>Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>The authors have no conflicts to disclose. </p>





<p>Clin Mol Hepatol 
Volume_19 Number_4 December 2013 </p>



</text></tei>