<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3279886" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:46+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Background: In Anzali Lagoon, there are some endemic and exotic fishes. The present study 
was conducted to compare the parasitic fauna of Blicca bjeorkna, as an endemic fish and 
Hemiculter leucisculus, as an introduced fish to the lagoon. 
Methods: A parasitological investigation was done on 78 specimens of B. bjoerkna and 114 of H. 
leucisculus. The fishes were collected from August 2009 to April 2010 by the electro fishing 
from Anzali Lagoon. 
Results: Eleven parasites species were found in 192 fish samples. The prevalence and mean 
intensity of parasites in each host were as follows: Parasites from B. bjorkna were Trichodina 
perforata (53.85%); Myxobolus musayevi (27.19%, 1±0.79); Dactylogyrus difformis (88.05%, 
8±7.24) and D. sphyrna (5.18%, 0.95±0.51), Diplostomum spataceum (98.72%, 9.51±9.01), Post-
hodiplostomum cuticula (15.38%, 4.25±2.5), Ripidocotyle sp. (1.28%, 2±0.74); Contracaecum 
osculatum (17.95%, 1.64±0.79), Philometra rischta (12.8%, 1.4±0.54), and Raphidascaris acus 
(1.04%, 0.03±0.26). The H. leucisculus were infected with T. perforata (27.19%), D. spataceum 
(7.89%, 1.33±0.54), Ps. tomentosa (7.02%, 1.62±0.49) and R. acus (0.88%, 3±0.28). B. bjoerkna 
was presented as a new host for M. musayevi and C. osculatum, while H. leucisculus was intro-
duced as a new host for T. perforata and Ps. tomentosa. 
Conclusion: The prevalence of parasites was significantly more in native fish than that of exotic 
fish (P&lt;0.05). This reduction in parasitic infection in H. leucisculus may be due to its immune 
system resistance, well adaptation to the new environment, host-specific limitation for endemic 
parasites and disability of introduced parasite to complete its life cycle in the new host as well. 
nzali Lagoon is a very important 
reservoir in the Caspian Sea Fauna 
Region (North of Iran), there are 
some fish parasites recorded from this area 
such as: Diplostomum spathaceum from 
Esox lucius, Perca fluviatilis, Carassius 
carassius, Ctenopharyngodon idella, Cypri-
nus carpio, Hypophthalmichthys molitrix, 
Tinca tinca, and Abramis brama; Raphidas-
caris acus from Esox lucius, Abramis brama, 
Tinca tinca, Carassius carassius and Perca 
fluviatilis. There some more parasites from 
different fishes such as: Tetraonchus menon-
teron and Gyrodactylus elegans, Eus-
trongilides excisus, Rhabdochona hellichi 
from Esox lucius, Chalcalburnus chalcoides 
and Cucullanus mulleri from Carassius 
carassius, Anisakis schupakovi from Silurus 
glanis, Argulus foliaceus from Hypophthal-
michthys molitrix, Piscicola geometra and 
Asymphylodora tincae from Tinca tinca (1). 
A number of exotic fish species were intro-
duced in Iranian freshwaters. These species 
encompass 18.7% from the 81% of the fish 
inhabiting in south part of the Caspian Sea. 
Hemiculter leucisculus (Saw belly) is one of 
these species with low economic value. This 
species might be accidentally transferred to 
this region with fertilized egg and or larvae 
of Chinese carp for aquaculture, the place 
and origin of this fish is Yunnan, south-west 
of China (2-5). 
None-indigenous fish may have undesirable 
effects on endemic fish species, including 
destruction of habitat and water quality, 
predation, aggressive behavior such as fin 
nipping, retardation of reproductive activity, 
food competition, and introduction of para-
sites and disease to the new environment. 
Levels of parasitism and parasite diversity 
were significantly greater in native fishes 
than in exotic species, and this may contrib-
ute to an enhanced demographic perform-</p>

<p>ance and competitive ability in invading 
exotics. Levels of parasitism and parasite 
diversity in native fishes were negatively re-
lated to habitat disturbance, in particular to a 
suite of factors that indicate increased hu-
man use of the river and surrounding 
environment (6-11). 
Native parasites infecting exotic fish will 
increase their bio-potential through a vast 
host range. The exotic fish may play as a 
reservoir role for maintenance of parasite (8). 
The aims of this study were to survey the 
parasite fauna on Blicca bjeorkna, as a na-
tive fish, and Hemiculter leucisculus, as an 
exotic fish, and to compare the prevalence of 
parasitic infection in these two species. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>A parasitological investigation was done on 
Blicca bjeorkna; the local name is Sim Parak 
(n= 78, Fig.1) and Hemiculter leucisculus; 
the local name is Tiz Kooli (n=114, Fig. 2). 
The fishes were collected from August 2009 
to April 2010 by the electro fishing from 
same locality of Anzali Lagoon. The live 
specimens were transferred to Iranian Aqua-
culture Research Center (Guilan, Anzali) 
and were kept in aquariums. Parasitological 
studies implemented for protozoa and 
Monogenea on fresh smears of gills, eyes, 
skin, and fins by stereo and light microscope. 
Examined fish were fixed in formalin (10%) 
and transferred to Aquatic Research Labora-
tory (Shahid Beheshti University) for further 
study of other metazoan parasites. The para-
sites were identified according to key of Mo-
ravec 1994, 1998, Bykhovskaya 1964, Shul-
man 1984 and Lom &amp; Dykova 1992 (10, 12-
16). </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Iranian J Parasitol: Vol. 6, No.3, 2011, pp.66-73 </p>



<p>Statistical analysis 
Statistical analysis was performed by the 
software package of <rs type="software">SPSS</rs>. Data were sub-
jected to the analysis of variance (ANOVA). 
Significant differences in prevalence and 
mean intensity of parasitism between exotic 
and endemic fish was detected by Chi square 
test when α= 0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Eleven parasite species were found in both 
of fishes (Fig. 3 and 4, Table 1). One hun-
dred percent of Blicca bjeorkna and 49.12% 
of Hemiculter leucisculus were contami-
nated by various parasites. Presented find-
ings showed a significant difference in 
prevalence of parasitic infection between 
exotic and endemic fishes (P&lt;0.05). The en-
demic fish was infected more than exotic 
fish and more parasites diversity was ob-
served in endemic fish than exotic species. 
Some of parasitic species were seen in both 
fishes, but some others were only in B. 
bjoerkna or H. leucisculus. More specific 
parasites were found in B. bjoerkna whereas 
they were not identified in H. leucisculus. 
B. bjoerkna was presented as a new host for 
M. musajevi and C. osculatum; and H. 
leucisculus was introduced as a new host for 
T. perforata, Ps. tomentosa and R. acus. </p>

<p>Fig. 1: Hemiculter leucisculus (Tiz kooli) </p>

<p>Fig. 2: Blicca bjoerkna (Sim Parak) </p>

<p>Pazooki et al.: Parasitic Infection of an Endemic Fish … </p>



<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>E 
F </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>Fig. 3: A. T. perforata from skin, gills and fins. B. Myxobolus musajevi from gills. C. Dac-
tylogyrus difformis from gills. D. Dactylogyrus sphyrna from gills. E. Metacercaria of 
Posthodiplostomum cuticula from skin and fins. F. Rhaphidocotyle sp. from gills. G. Metacer-
caria of Diplostomum spataceum from the eyes </p>

<p>10 µm </p>

<p>Iranian J Parasitol: Vol. 6, No.3, 2011, pp.66-73 </p>



<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>E 
F </p>

<p>G 
H </p>

<p>Fig. 4: A. posterior part of Contracaecum osculatum. B. anterior part of C. osculatum. C. poste-
rior part of Raphidascaris acus. D. anterior part of Rh. acus. E. posterior part of Pseudocapillaria 
tomentosa. F. anterior part of Ps. tomentosa. G. posterior part of Philometra rischta. H. anterior 
part of Ph. rischta with released larvae </p>

<p>Pazooki et al.: Parasitic Infection of an Endemic Fish … </p>



<p>Table 1: Intensity and prevalence of parasite species of the host fishes in Anzali Lagoon </p>

<p>Parasite species 
Hf 
Efn 
Ifn 
Int±S.D. 
Prv (%) </p>

<p>T. perforata 
B. bjoerkna 
H. leucisculus </p>

<p>78 
114 </p>

<p>42 
31 </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>53.85 
27.19 </p>

<p>M. musajevi 
B. bjoerkna 
78 
1 
1±0.79 
27.19 </p>

<p>D. difformis &amp; 
D. sphyrna </p>

<p>B. bjoerkna 
78 
69 
8.058±7.24 
88.46 </p>

<p>Diplostumum 
spataceaum </p>

<p>B. bjoerkna 
H. leucisculus </p>

<p>78 
114 </p>

<p>77 
9 </p>

<p>9.51±9.09 
1.33±0.54 </p>

<p>98.72 
7.89 </p>

<p>P. cuticula 
B. bjoerkna 
78 
12 
4.25±2.5 
15.38 </p>

<p>Ripidocotyle sp 
B. bjoerkna 
78 
1 
2±0.74 
1.28 </p>

<p>C. osculatum 
B. bjoerkna 
78 
14 
1.64±0.79 
17.95 </p>

<p>Ph. rischta 
B. bjoerkna 
78 
10 
1.4±0.54 
12.8 </p>

<p>Ps. tomentosa 
H. leucisculus 
114 
8 
1.62±0.49 
7.02 </p>

<p>R. acus 
B. bjoerkna 
H. leucisculus </p>

<p>78 
114 </p>

<p>1 
1 </p>

<p>0.03±0.26 
3±0.28 </p>

<p>1.04 
0.88 </p>

<p>Hf: host fishes, Efn: examined fish number, Ifn: infected fish number, S.D: standard deviation, Prv: preva-
lence (%), *: The number of parasites was not clear for calculated their intensity </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>One of the factors affecting on specification 
of parasitic infection is origin of the fish spe-
cies, whether native or exotic. Several 
investigations revealed that parasitic infec-
tion is more common in native fish species 
than exotic one (6). In a previous, parasitic 
species richness and parasitic diversity were 
significantly ( P&lt;0.05) more in native fish 
than in exotic one (9, 10). Some studies 
about roles of parasites in animal invasions 
and missing parasites in introduced species, 
demonstrated several reasons for reduced 
parasitic load of exotic species. Firstly, those 
parasites that contaminated the introduced </p>

<p>exotic fish may not be able to continue their 
life cycle in the new environment. This re-
duced parasitic charge increased the 
competitive ability and the size of exotic 
species in comparison with native species 
(17, 18). 
The second one is the absence of other re-
quired host (intermediate or reservoir host) 
in the new environment. Thirdly, the highly 
host specifications caused limitations in 
transfer of parasite from native fish species 
to the exotic ones. Conversely, parasites may 
transfer from exotic fish to the native ones. 
The parasite transfer is greater when it has </p>

<p>Iranian J Parasitol: Vol. 6, No.3, 2011, pp.66-73 </p>



<p>low host specifications and the hosts have 
close relationship (2). In a case, at which a 
parasite is introduced to a new host, this 
could damage the host even more because 
there is no identified relationship between 
the host and parasite. Furthermore, the host 
may not have enough defensive strength 
against the parasite (5, 7). In the present 
study, both the prevalence of parasitic infec-
tion and diversity were more in B. bjoerkna 
than in H. leucisculus. Parasites with low 
host specifications such as T. perforata, Ps. 
tomentosa and D. spataceaum were found in 
H. leucisculus can easily contaminate differ-
ent host. The origin of fish is one of the most 
important and affecting factors on the preva-
lence of parasite infection. Other factors are 
included food diet, immune competence, and 
fish dispersion in its habitat. The exotic fish 
may have a role in maintenance of a parasite 
and transfer the infection to other host fish in 
the environment according to their immune 
system resistance. There are many parasites 
recorded from different fish species in An-
zali Lagoon but there is not any comparative 
study between endemic and exotic fishes. 
During this study, the examined fishes are 
introduced as new hosts: H. leucisculus for 
Trichodina perforata, Dactylogyrus sphyrna, 
Pseudocapillaria tomentosa, Raphidascaris 
acus and B. bjoerkna for Myxobolus mosa-
jevi, Contracaecum osculatum. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This research was supported by Shahid Be-
heshti University, G. C. The authors declare 
that there is no conflict of interests. </p>



<p>Pazooki et al.: Parasitic Infection of an Endemic Fish … </p>





</text></tei>