<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3281244" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Transmissible spongiform encephalopathies (TSE) are characterized by the misfolding of 
the host encoded prion protein (PrP C ) into a pathogenic isoform (PrP Sc ) which leads to the 
accumulation of β-sheet-rich fibrils and subsequent loss of neurons and synaptic functions. 
Although many compounds have been identified which inhibit accumulation or dissolve 
fibrils and aggregates in vitro there is no therapeutic treatment to stop these progressive 
neurodegenerative diseases. Here we describe the effects of the traditional medicinal herb 
Scutellaria lateriflora (S. lateriflora) and its natural compounds, the flavonoids baicalein and 
baicalin, on the development of prion disease using in vitro and in vivo models. S. lateriflora 
extract as well as both constituents reduced the PrP res accumulation in scrapie-infected 
cell cultures and cell-free conversion assays and lead to the destabilization of pre-existing 
PrP Sc fibrils. Moreover, tea prepared from S. lateriflora, prolonged significantly the incuba-
tion time of scrapie-infected mice upon oral treatment. Therefore S. lateriflora extracts as 
well as the individual compounds can be considered as promising candidates for the devel-
opment of new therapeutic drugs against TSEs and other neurodegenerative diseases like 
Alzheimer's and Parkinson's disease. </p>

<p>Transmissible spongiform encephalopathies (TSEs) are neurode-
generative diseases which are characterized by the accumulation 
and deposition of a pathogenic isoform (PrP Sc ) of the host 
encoded cellular prion protein (PrP C ) designated PrP Sc . Both 
isoforms share the same amino acid sequence but differ in con-
formation, resistance to proteinase K (PK), and pathogenicity. 
PrP Sc tends to oligomerize by a seeded polymerization mecha-
nism followed by the formation of multimers and eventually of 
fibril structures. This aggregation can be reproduced in an anal-
ogous manner in vitro, using cell-based as well as cell-free assays. 
The evolved PrP Sc like isoforms -termed PrP res -harbor simi-
lar biochemical characteristics like resistance to Proteinase K and 
detection by same antibodies. 
Accumulation of PrP Sc in the central nervous system (CNS) 
is accompanied by neurological dysfunctions, neuronal vacuola-
tion, and astrocytic gliosis. Although the exact disease causing 
mechanism is unknown to date, there is evidence for a general 
neurotoxicity of these aggregates, which deteriorate synaptic func-
tion and induce oxidative stress and membrane disruption (Soto 
and Estrada, 2008). Prion diseases belong to the group of protein 
misfolding diseases like Alzheimer's (AD), Parkinson's (PD), and 
Huntington's disease (HD), which are generally characterized by 
an incorrect folding process of a host encoded protein with a con-
formation different from its native structure. The misfolding is 
followed by a self-aggregation and polymerization of the protein 
according to a "seeding-nucleation" process (Jarrett and Lansbury, 
1993). </p>

<p>As PrP Sc formation and aggregation is the central event in 
prion diseases, the inhibition of oligomer formation and fibril 
extension as well as the enhancement of fibril degradation are 
major targets for the development of therapeutic strategies against 
TSEs. Several substances have been identified which inhibit PrP res 
formation and accumulation in vitro and prolonged survival in 
scrapie-infected animals: Congo red (Caughey and Race, 1992), 
branched polyamines (Supattapone et al., 2001), porphyrins and 
phthalocyanines (Priola et al., 2000; Caughey et al., 2007), heparan 
sulfate mimetics (Adjou et al., 2003), amphotericin (Mange et al., 
2000), curcumine (Caughey et al., 2003; Yang et al., 2009), and 
tetracyclines (De Luigi et al., 2008). However, for various reasons 
none of these compounds has been included in prevention and 
treatment regimes for humans yet. Most recently two new sub-
stance classes, benzothiazoles (Geissen et al., 2011) and diphenyl-
pyrazoles (Leidel et al., 2011), were identified by high-throughput 
screening approaches that inhibit PrP res accumulation in cell cul-
ture models and prolong incubation times in scrapie-infected 
mice. 
Other therapeutic strategies rely on passive immunization 
(White et al., 2003), RNA interference (Pfeifer et al., 2006), 
RNA aptamers (Proske et al., 2002), copper chelating antibiotics 
(Murakami-Kubo et al., 2004), or on the induction of autophagy 
by Lithium (Heiseke et al., 2009). 
Recent studies on AD suggest that phenolic compounds like 
green tea epigallocatechin gallate (Rezai-Zadeh et al., 2005), herb 
extracts like grape seed polyphenolic extract (Wang et al., 2009; Liu 
et al., 2011), or medicinal herbs like Paeonia suffruticosa (Fujiwara </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 9 | 1 </p>

<p>Eiden et al. </p>

<p>Scutellaria lateriflora inhibits prion replication </p>

<p>et al., 2009) can be used for the treatment of neurodegenerative 
diseases. 
The here presented study shows that the American skullcap 
Scutellaria lateriflora, a traditional medical herb in North Amer-
ica, exhibits strong anti-prion activity. Extracts of this plant have 
been traditionally used as sedative and for the treatment of insom-
nia, anxiety, or neuralgia (Foster, 1996). Moreover, we can show 
here that the crude aqueous extract inhibits prion propagation 
and dissolves prion aggregates in vitro. Continuous oral adminis-
tration of S. lateriflora tea (water extract) significantly prolonged 
incubation times in scrapie-infected mice. Notably, the natural 
constituents, the flavonoids baicalein and baicalin-hydrate, exhibit 
the same inhibitory effects on prion propagation and dissolve 
existing fibrils. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>FLAVONOIDS AND TEA OF SCUTELLARIA LATERIFLORA </p>

<p>Baicalein and baicalein-hydrate were purchased from Sigma-
Aldrich and solubilized in DMSO. The dried herb S. lateriflora 
was purchased from Goldener Zweig (Buchholz, Germany). Water 
extracts (tea) were prepared by mixing 30 g of sliced dry herbs in 
1.0 l boiling water for 30 min. After cooling the tea was adminis-
tered directly to mice. For in vitro experiments tea was lyophilized 
to yield dried extracts. In cell-based assays the dried material was 
resuspended in H 2 O, concentrated by a factor of 10 (termed tea 
concentrate) and added to the cell culture medium. In cell-free 
conversion assay the dried extract was directly resuspended in the 
conversion buffer in a final volume of 20 μl. </p>

<p>PROPAGATION OF SCRAPIE STRAINS </p>

<p>C57Bl/6 mice were inoculated with cloned mouse scrapie strains 
RML intracerebrally (i.c.; 30 μl of 1% mouse brain homogenate) 
or intraperitoneally (i.p.; 50 μl of 1% brain homogenate). The 
health status of the mice was inspected daily, and their body 
weights were recorded weekly. After the onset of TSE-associated 
clinical symptoms (and weight loss, abnormal tail tonus, hind 
limb paralysis), the animals were euthanized. The incubation times 
were calculated as the time between inoculation and death. The 
brains were removed and kept as following: one half of each brain 
was stored at −20˚C, and the other half was fixed in 4% neutral 
buffered formalin. 
Pathogenic isoform for PrP conversion reactions was purified 
from brains of C57/Bl6 mice i.c. inoculated with mouse scrapie 
strain Me7. Brains were taken at the beginning of clinical symp-
toms in the animals and stored at −20˚C. PrP Sc was purified 
according to Eiden et al. (2006). </p>

<p>HEMATOXYLIN AND EOSIN STAINING AND IMMUNOHISTOCHEMISTRY </p>

<p>Before embedding in paraffin the formalin fixed brain was cut 
at five different levels to reveal caudal medulla, rostral medulla, 
midbrain, thalamic, and frontal slices. Lesion profile scoring was 
carried out on Hematoxylin and Eosin (H&amp;E) stained sections 
according to standard methodology (Fraser and Dickinson, 1968). 
For immunohistochemistry samples were processed (with minor 
modifications) as described previously (Hardt et al., 2000). Three 
micrometers section were de-paraffinized and rehydrated. Pre-
treatment included an incubation step with 98% formic acid </p>

<p>(15 min) and blocking of the endogenous peroxidase activity with 
3% H 2 O 2 /methanol (30 min) followed by autoclaving in citrate 
buffer (pH 6.0, 20 min). The monoclonal antibody SAF 84 was 
applied at a dilution of 1:2000 for 2 h at room temperature and 
detected by avidin-biotin-horseradish peroxidase (Vector Elite). 
Color reactions were finally developed using diaminobenzidine 
(DAB) substrate. </p>

<p>PROTEINASE K DIGESTION AND SODIUM PHOSPHOTUNGSTIC ACID 
PRECIPITATION </p>

<p>Mouse brain samples 10% (w/v) were prepared in lysis buffer 
(0.42 mM sucrose solution containing 0.5% deoxycholic acid 
sodium salt (DOC) and 0.5% Non-idet P40) and incubated with 
PK (50 μg/ml, final concentration) for 60 min at 55˚C. Reactions 
were stopped with pefabloc (Roche) followed by incubation with 
0.3% (w/v) phosphotungstic acid precipitation (PTA) and selective 
precipitation of PrP Sc according to Gretzschel et al. (2005). </p>

<p>PRP CONVERSION REACTION </p>

<p>Cell-free conversion studies were performed as described before 
(Eiden et al., 2006; Kupfer et al., 2007). For the conversion reac-
tion 400 ng of recombinant ovine PrP C , expressed in E. coli, was 
incubated with 200-400 ng of purified PrP Sc in a conversion buffer 
[50 mM citrate buffer (pH 6.0), 200 mM KCl, 5 mM MgCl 2 , and 
1.25% sarkosyl; Horiuchi et al., 2000]. Standard conversion reac-
tions were carried out for 3 days at 37˚C. Afterward, samples were 
incubated with PK (final concentration of 30 μg/ml) for 1 h at 
37˚C. PK was diluted in TN-buffer (0.15 M NaCl, 0.05 M Tris/HCl 
pH 7.4). The reaction was stopped with PMSF (phenyl methansul-
fonyl fluoride; 10 mM). Twenty micrograms of a carrier protein 
(thyroglobulin) was added and the samples were incubated with 
a fourfold volume of methanol at -20˚C to precipitate the pro-
teins. After centrifugation at 12000 g for 15 min, the proteins were 
pelleted and resolubilized by heating to 95˚C for 5 min in SDS-
PAGE loading buffer [1% (w/v) SDS, 25 mM Tris/HCl pH 7.4, 
0.5% mercaptoethanol, and 0.001% bromophenol blue]. 
Samples were separated on SDS-polyacrylamide gels contain-
ing 16% (w/v) acrylamide/bisacrylamide, 0.375 M Tris/HCl (pH 
8.8), 0.5% (w/v) SDS (sodium dodecyl sulfate), 0.06% (w/v) 
APS (ammonium peroxydisulfate), and 0.06% (v/v) TEMED 
(N,N,N ,N -tetramethylethylenediamine) with a 4% stacking gel 
[4% (w/v) acrylamide/bisacrylamide, 0.12 M Tris/HCl (pH 6.8), 
0.5% (w/v) SDS, 0.2% APS, 0.2% (v/v) TEMED]. 
For immunoblotting proteins were transferred in a semi-
dry chamber to a polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) membrane. 
Membranes were then incubated in blocking buffer (PBS-0.1% 
Tween 20, 5% non-fat dry milk powder) followed by incuba-
tion for 60 min with the monoclonal antibody (mab) P4 (R-
Biopharm), mab SAF-70 (SPIbio), or polyclonal antibody (pab) 
Ra 10 (Groschup et al., 1994, 1997). In contrast to mab P4, which 
detects ovine PrP C/res , pab Ra10 detects only murine PrP C/Sc . 
Membranes were washed three times for 10 min with PBS con-
taining 0.1% Tween 20 and then incubated with a secondary anti-
body bound to alkaline phosphatase (Goat-anti-mouse-alkaline 
phosphatase or goat anti-rabbit-peroxidase). After washing, the 
chemiluminescence substrate CDP-Star (Tropix) was applied and 
membranes were incubated for 5 min before the light signals were </p>

<p>Frontiers in Psychiatry | Neurodegeneration </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 9 | 2 </p>

<p>Eiden et al. </p>

<p>Scutellaria lateriflora inhibits prion replication </p>

<p>recorded on a Versadoc Imaging System (Biorad). Visualization 
was carried out with the <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Biorad</rs> VersaDoc™quantification soft-
ware <rs id="software-1" type="software">Quantity One</rs>. The percentage of converted substrate was 
calculated as: signal volume of PrP res digested with PK/signal vol-
ume of PrP C without PK  *  10. Conversion rates were calculated for 
each time point as a mean value from four independent reactions. 
For stripping, membranes were incubated twice for 15 min with a 
buffer containing 0.2 M glycine (pH 2.0) and 1% SDS. </p>

<p>PRP 
RES DETECTION FROM CELL CULTURE </p>

<p>Two scrapie-infected mouse cell lines were used: ScN 2 A-
cells [RML infected neuroblastoma-(N 2 A)-cells] and SMB-cells 
("scrapie-mouse-brain," infected with strain 22F, a gift of TSE 
Resource Centre at the Institute for Animal Health, UK). ScN 2 A-
cells were cultured in Opti-MEM, 10% fetal calf serum (FCS), and 
5% CO 2 at 37˚C. SMB-cells were cultured in MEM+ [MEM199, 
10% newborn calf serum (NCS), 5% FCS] and 5% CO 2 at 
35˚C. 
The cell-based assay was carried out according to Leidel et al. 
(2011) with two scrapie-infected mouse cell lines: ScN 2 A-cells and 
SMB-cells. These cells were adapted for dot blot procedure in 
96-well plate format to identify potential inhibitors of PrP Sc for-
mation. Compounds were resolved in DMSO and added to cells in 
eight replicates in concentrations of 10, 100, and 1000 μM (final 
concentration). After 3 days of incubation in a CO 2 -incubator, 
the supernatants were removed and cells lysed in 100 μl lysis 
buffer (50 mM Tris/HCl, 150 mM NaCl, 0.5% Na-deoxycholate, 
0.5% TX-100, pH 8.0). Lysates were or electrophoresed and 
immunoblotted as described in the previous section or dot blot-
ted on PVDF membranes using a 96-well dot blot apparatus 
(Transblotter, Roth). Dot blotting membranes were dried for 1 h 
at 37˚C and fixed sample incubated with DNAse (100 μg/ml) 
for 1 h at 37˚C. After rinsing the membranes twice with dis-
tilled water, the membrane was incubated with PK (25 μg/ml) 
for 90 min at 37˚C. The digestion was terminated using PMSF 
(2 mM) and membranes were rinsed in 3 M guanidium thio-
cyanate for 10 min followed by washing them five times in distilled 
water. 
The incubation of the membrane with blocking buffer (PBS-
0.1% Tween 20, 5% non-fat dry milk powder) was followed by 
an incubation for 60 min with polyclonal antibody (pab) Ra 10. 
Membranes were washed three times for 10 min with PBS contain-
ing 0.1% Tween 20 and then incubated with a secondary antibody 
bound to peroxidase (Goat anti-rabbit-PO). Afterward, the chemi-
luminescence substrate ECL (Roche) was applied and incubated 
on the membrane for 1 min before the light signals on the mem-
brane were detected directly in a camera. The intensity of the 
PrP Sc signal of each well was quantified by using the Versadoc 
imaging system. The half maximal (50%) inhibitory concentration 
(IC 50 ) of each compound was calculated from eight independent 
reactions. </p>

<p>STATISTICAL ANALYSIS </p>

<p>Survival times were analyzed by Kaplan-Meier Survival analysis 
using the log-rank test to compare the curves. The Statistical analy-
sis was done using <rs type="software">SigmaBlot</rs> statistical software (San Jose, CA, 
USA). Survival times are expressed as mean ± SD. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The effect of S. lateriflora tea on the PrP res formation was first 
analyzed in vitro using two different scrapie-infected cell lines 
(SMB and ScN 2 A-cells), which permanently accumulate PrP res . 
When tea concentrate was added to the culture medium, a dose 
dependent reduction of PrP res accumulation was observed in SMB 
as well as ScN 2 A-cells (Figure 1). Cells were cultivated in T25 
flasks and incubated with increasing amounts of S. lateriflora 
tea for 3 days. After this time, cells were harvested and the level 
of PK-resistant PrP res was assessed by Western blotting. A dilu-
tion of 1:500 induced a reduction of PrP res to 58% for ScN 2 A 
(Figure 1A, lane 2) and to 64% for SMB (Figure 1B, lane 2) cells 
compared to the control (Figures 1A,B, lane 1). Dilutions of 1:50 
resulted in a reduction to 33% for ScN 2 A-cells (Figure 1A, lane 
3) and 57% for SMB-cells (Figure 1B, lane 3). About 1:20 dilu-
tions displayed reduction to 28% for ScN 2 A (Figure 1A, lane 4) 
and 47% for SMB-cells (Figure 1B, lane 4) and reached values of 
28.7% for ScN 2 A-cells (Figure 1A, lane 5) and 42.3% for SMB-
cells (Figure 1B, lane 5). Relative inhibition by tea is depicted in 
Figure 1C. 
To test the direct effects of tea on the conversion of PrP C to 
PrP res , a cell-free conversion assay was used in which a purified 
murine PrP Sc template induced the conversion of recombinant 
cellular PrP C into a PK-resistant PrP res fragment (Eiden et al., 
2006; Kupfer et al., 2007). Newly converted PrP res -fragments were 
detected by mab P4 (Figure 2A, lanes 1-2), while PrP Sc aggre-
gates were visualized by the polyclonal antibody Ra10 (Figure 2B, 
lanes 1-2). Dried tea extract (3, 0.3, and 0.03 mg respectively) 
was added to the conversion assay, inhibited PrP res formation 
and led to clearance of PrP res -fragments (Figure 2A, lanes 3-6). 
Even 0.03 mg caused a reduced PrP res formation compared to the 
control (Figure 2A, lanes 7-8) by 23%. 
Similar results were seen in the case of dissolution of PrP Sc 
aggregates after PK digestion (Figure 2B). In contrast to the con-
trol (Figure 2B, lanes 1-2), PrP Sc aggregates were completely 
digested if co-incubated with 3.0 mg dried tea extract (Figure 2B, 
lanes 3-4), as well as with 0.3 mg (Figure 2B, lanes 5-6). About 
0.03 mg dried tea extract induced a partial disaggregation of 
PrP Sc aggregates (Figure 2B, lanes 7-8) by 40% compared to the 
control. 
To further characterize the underlying inhibitory mechanisms, 
two main polyphenolic compounds of this herbal extract, the 
flavonoids Baicalin (baicalein 7-O-glucuronide) and its aglycone 
baicalein (5,6,7-trihydroxyflavone), were studied with regard to 
their inhibitory properties. Both components have been isolated 
from this herb previously (Awad et al., 2003) und were also iden-
tified in this study as ingredients in the tea by LCMS-IT-TOF 
hybrid mass spectrometry (data not shown). In addition, a struc-
tural analog to baicalein, the flavonoid epicatechin and quercetin 
were analyzed. 
The potentially inhibitory effects on the PrP res accumulation 
and conversion were assayed by a cell-based dot blot assay system 
(Geissen et al., 2011) and the cell-free conversion assay. Struc-
tures, assay results, and half maximal (50%) inhibitory concen-
trations (IC 50 ) of both compounds are summarized in Table 1. 
The cell-based dot blot assay was carried out with two different 
scrapie-infected SMB and ScN 2 A-cells again. Cells were seeded </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 9 | 3 </p>

<p>Eiden et al. </p>

<p>Scutellaria lateriflora inhibits prion replication </p>

<p>FIGURE 1 | Western blot analysis of inhibition of PrP 
res formation in 
scrapie-infected cells by tea concentrate of S. lateriflora. (A) Tea 
concentrate of S. lateriflora inhibits PrP 
res formation in ScN 2 A-cells. 
Lane 1 shows PK-resistant fragments of the untreated control, lanes 
2-5 a sample incubated with increasing concentrations of tea 
concentrate of S. lateriflora: 1:500 (lane 2), 1:50 (lane 3), 1:20 (lane 4), 
and 1:10 (lane 5). (B) Inhibition of PrP 
res formation in SMB-cells by tea </p>

<p>concentrate of S. lateriflora. PK-resistant fragments were detected in 
untreated control (lane 1), after incubation with tea in a 1:500 dilution 
(lane 2), 1:50 (lane 3), 1:20 and 1:10 (lane 5). Detection was carried out 
with pab Ra10 and analyzed by standard chemiluminescence method. 
(C) Relative inhibition (%) of PrP 
res formation by tea concentrate for 
SMB (red line) and ScN 2 A (blue line) cells. +, incubation with 
proteinase K (PK); u.d., undiluted. </p>

<p>in 96 wells and incubated with decreasing concentrations of the 
corresponding flavonoids (1 mM, 100 and 10 μM). IC 50 values of 
Baicalein ranged from 138 μM (SMB-cells) to 63.7 μM (ScN 2 A-
cells). Baicalin showed significantly lower inhibitory effects com-
pared to baicalein in SMB-cells (IC 50 : &gt;1000 μM) as well as in 
ScN 2 A-cells (IC 50 : 239.8 μM). Two additional flavonoids with 
similar structure, epicatechin, and quercetin, showed also strong 
inhibitory effects in both cell-types: epicatechin IC 50 values were 
96.6 μM (ScN 2 A-cells) and 106.8 μM (SMB-cells) and quercetin 
IC 50 values were 36.8 μM (ScN 2 A-cells) and 274.3 μM (SMB-cells; 
Table 1). Baicalein displayed a strong dose dependent inhibitory 
effects to PrP res formation (IC 50 : 18.48 μM) and dissolution of 
PrP Sc aggregates (IC 50 : 41.56 μM) in the cell-free conversion assay, 
in contrast to baicalin which yielded IC 50 values of &gt;1000 μM for 
PrP res inhibition and 440 μM for PrP Sc dissolution. Epicatechin 
and quercetin, although highly similar in structural to baicalein, 
showed no inhibitory effects in cell-free conversion with regards 
to PrP res formation and PrP Sc disintegration. 
In summary, these data demonstrate that tea of S. lateriflora 
contains two active compounds, baicalein and baicalin, which are 
specific inhibitors of PrP C conversion and PrP res amplification 
in vitro as well as enhance the degradation of PrP Sc fibrils. </p>

<p>In another set of experiments in vivo effects of S. lateriflora 
tea were assessed. Wild-type mice were infected either by intrac-
erebrally (i.c.) or intraperitoneally (i.p.) inoculation with mouse 
scrapie strain RML and the drinking water was replaced by freshly 
brewed tea starting 2 weeks prior to their inoculation and for 
the whole lifetime of the mice. Survival times are depicted in 
Figure 3. Six Bl6/C57 mice were used for the treatment and 
compared to six intracerebrally inoculated mice which received 
normal drinking water. The mean life spans of the control group 
(Figure 5A, bold line) was 147 ± 3.1 dpi (Figure 3B) whereas the 
tea treated mice (Figure 5A dashed line) survived significantly 
longer (184 ± 26.7 dpi; Figure 3B). Three of the treated mice sur-
vived up to 60 days compared to the control mice. In the case of 
i.p. inoculation of RML strain, a mean prolongation of 15 days was 
achieved (Figures 3C,D). The mean incubation time of the con-
trol group (Figure 3C, bold line) was 191 ± 8.6 dpi (Figure 3D) 
whereas the tea treated mice (Figure 3C, dashed line) survived 
significantly longer (206 ± 8.6 dpi; Figure 3D). 
Brains of the i.c. infected mice were subjected to compara-
tive biochemical and immunohistochemical investigations. PrP 
immunoblot analysis revealed no differences of PrP Sc banding pat-
terns and total amounts of PrP Sc in both groups. The PrP Sc content </p>

<p>Frontiers in Psychiatry | Neurodegeneration </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 9 | 4 </p>

<p>Eiden et al. </p>

<p>Scutellaria lateriflora inhibits prion replication </p>

<p>in all brains was analyzed after PK digestion and selective precip-
itation of PrP Sc from corresponding mouse brain homogenates 
with sodium phosphotungstic acid (Figure 4). No differences </p>

<p>FIGURE 2 | Western blot analysis of inhibition of PrP 
res formation and 
disaggregation of pre-existing PrP 
Sc fibrils in a cell-free conversion 
assay. (A) Tea of S. lateriflora inhibits formation of PrP 
res . Lanes 1-2 show 
PK-resistant PrP 
res -fragments in samples without tea, lanes 3-4 samples 
after co-incubation with 3.0 mg dried tea extract, lanes 5-6 with 0.3 mg 
dried tea extract, and lanes 7-8 co-incubation with 0.03 mg dried tea 
extract. Detection was carried out with mab P4. (B) Tea of S. lateriflora 
disaggregates pre-existing fibrils after digestion with PK. The membrane 
from (A) was stripped and incubated another time with pab Ra10. Lanes 
1-2 show PK-resistant PrP 
res -fragments in samples without tea, lanes 3-4 
samples after co-incubation with 3.0 mg dried tea extract, lanes 5-6 with 
0.3 mg dried tea extract, and lanes 7-8 co-incubation with 0.03 mg dried tea 
extract. Western blot was analyzed by standard chemiluminescence 
method. +: incubation with proteinase K (PK). </p>

<p>in PrP Sc banding patterns or PK resistances was detected in 
mice which eventually developed scrapie in the tea treated and 
control group (Figure 4, lanes 2-13). The brain lesion pro-
files and PrP Sc deposition patterns in the different mouse brain 
regions were similar for the treated and the untreated mice 
(Figures 5A-D). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The here presented study demonstrates that solubilized ingredi-
ents of S. lateriflora not only inhibit the scrapie fibril formation but 
also destabilize pre-formed PrP Sc fibrils in a concentration depen-
dent manner. Main constituents of the herb were the polyphenolic 
flavonoids baicalin and baicalein, which were found at high con-
centrations in corresponding extracts. Both components in puri-
fied form showed dose dependent inhibitory properties and thus 
were the active constituents responsible for the herbs effects on 
scrapie fibril regulation. 
The strongest effects displayed baicalein, the main metabolite 
of baicalin, which inhibited PrP res accumulation in both cell-based 
and cell-free assays and promoted the destabilization of PrP Sc 
fibrils at low concentrations. A possible molecular mechanism 
is based on direct binding to the PrP C and the formation of a 
stable PrP-baicalein/baicalin complex, which blocks PrP conver-
sion and/or accumulation. In the same way the destabilization 
of pre-existing fibrils would be caused by a specific intercalation 
of baicalein/baicalin into β-sheet structures of the PrP Sc aggre-
gates which may lead to a forced PrP Sc degradation by lysosomal 
proteases. Similar effects by Baicalein have been described for the 
inhibition of α-synuclein (Zhu et al., 2004) and amyloid-β peptide 
(Aβ) fibrillization (Lu et al., 2011). </p>

<p>Table 1 | Chemical structures of flavonoids and in vitro analyses. </p>

<p>Compound 
Dot blot 
IC 50 (μM) 
Cell-free conversion assay 
IC 50 (μM) </p>

<p>ScN 2 A 
SMB 
ScN 2 A SMB 
Prp res 
Prp Sc 
Prp res 
Prp Sc </p>

<p>63.7 
139 
18.48 
41.56 </p>

<p>239.8 
&gt;1000 
&gt;1000 440 </p>

<p>96.9 
106.8 
n.e. 
n.e. </p>

<p>36.8 
274.3 
n.e. 
n.e. </p>

<p>IC 50 , Half maximal (50%) inhibitory concentration; n.e., not effective. </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 9 | 5 </p>

<p>Eiden et al. </p>

<p>Scutellaria lateriflora inhibits prion replication </p>

<p>FIGURE 3 | Tea of S. lateriflora prolongs incubation time in 
scrapie-infected mice after oral treatment. (A) Oral treatment of 
intracerebrally infected mice: Kaplan-Meier survival analysis of 
intracerebrally scrapie (RML) infected C57/Bl6 mice after oral treatment 
with tea of S. lateriflora. Treatment groups consisted of untreated 
controls ( ), and tea treated mice ( ). (B) Mean survival times in primary 
efficiency test ± SD. Comparison of tea versus untreated controls was </p>

<p>carried out by log-rank test, p &lt; 0.01( *  * ). (C) Oral treatment of 
intraperitoneally infected mice: Kaplan-Meier survival analysis of 
intraperitoneally scrapie (RML) infected C57/Bl6 mice after oral 
treatment tea of S. lateriflora. Treatment groups consisted of untreated 
controls ( ), and tea treated mice ( ). (D) Mean survival times in 
primary efficiency test ± SD. Comparison of tea versus untreated 
controls, was carried out by log-rank test, p &lt; 0.05( * ). </p>

<p>FIGURE 4 | Western blot analysis of sodium phosphotungstic acid 
precipitation of PrP 
Sc from brain homogenate of RML infected mice. 
Proteinase K digested and sodium phosphotungstic acid precipitated PrP </p>

<p>Sc </p>

<p>was detected by mab SAF-70. Lane 1 shows an uninfected control, lanes 2-7 </p>

<p>PrP 
Sc from RML infected mouse brains and lanes 8-13 PrP 
Sc from RML 
infected mouse brains that were treated with tea from S. lateriflora. Western 
blot was carried out with pab Ra10 and analyzed by chemiluminescence 
method. </p>

<p>In our present study oral administration of S. lateriflora tea 
significantly prolonged incubation of mice either infected intrac-
erebral or intraperitoneal. These effects can be explained by direct 
interference of baicalein to evolving PrP aggregates in the CNS. 
Baicalein is able to cross the blood brain barrier and ultimately 
reach the CNS (Tsai et al., 2002). Baicalin, on the other hand, may 
act as pro-drug: After oral uptake, the sugar residue is cleaved by 
enzymes in the intestinal tract to generate baicalein. The more </p>

<p>lipophilic baicalein is better absorbed in the gastrointestinal tract 
and can then enter the brain via the blood system (Tarragó et al., 
2008). 
Within the CNS, the inhibition and dissolution of prion aggre-
gates by Baicalein could protect neuronal cells from membrane 
disruption and subsequent neuronal cell death. Additional anti-
oxidant properties of baicalein on reactive oxygen species (ROS), 
which evolve during protein aggregation, may reinforce this </p>

<p>Frontiers in Psychiatry | Neurodegeneration </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 9 | 6 </p>

<p>Eiden et al. </p>

<p>Scutellaria lateriflora inhibits prion replication </p>

<p>FIGURE 5 | PrP 
Sc accumulation in the brains of mice challenged with 
RML. Immunohistochemistry: moderate diffuse PrP 
Sc accumulation in the 
cerebral cortex and multifocally in the corpus callosum of both (A) untreated 
and (B) with tea treated mice. Detection was carried out with mab SAF 84. 
Bar 200 μm. H&amp;E staining: mild vacuolation in the cerebral cortex of both 
(C) untreated and (D) with tea treated mice, H&amp;E staining, Bar 200 μm. </p>

<p>neuroprotective effect (Li et al., 2010). Baicalein is able to minimize 
ROS by directly quenching free radicals or indirectly inducing anti-
oxidant enzymes like superoxide dismutase and catalase (Shieh 
et al., 2000; Kang et al., 2011). 
Direct effects on the prion conversion were also seen in 
other plant derived polyphenols like curcumin which is a strong 
inhibitor of prion conversion replication in vitro (Caughey et al., </p>

<p>2003). It is in vivo efficacy, however, remains controversial: the 
oral administration of curcumin had no significant effect on 
the onset of scrapie in hamsters (Caughey et al., 2003), whereas 
scrapie-infected mice significantly survived longer after oral treat-
ment (Riemer et al., 2008). Effects of other polyphenols (e.g., 
tannic acid, katacine, and 2 -2 -bis epigallocatechin gallate) that 
interfere with PrP conversion in vitro were also studied in vivo 
(Kocisko et al., 2003). However, neither these substances nor mix-
tures of natural compounds including polyphenolic tea extract 
and pine bark extracts displayed any effects on incubation periods 
in scrapie-infected animals (Kocisko et al., 2004). 
Up to now only few compounds have been reported that delay 
onset on prion diseases after oral treatment. This includes pravas-
tatin (Vetrugno et al., 2009), which is involved in cholesterol 
biosynthesis and influences membrane structure and function, 
fucoidan (Doh-Ura et al., 2007), as well as amyloid dye derivatives 
(Kawasaki et al., 2007). However, possible drug associated side-
effects have to be further evaluated. Recently, diphenyl-pyrazoles 
(Leidel et al., 2011) were identified as a new class of anti-prion 
compounds, which prolong incubation time of scrapie-infected 
mice even after oral application. 
In conclusion, beneficial effects of S. lateriflora tea can be 
explained by the anti-aggregatory and potential anti-oxidative 
effects of its natural constituents, baicalein and baicalin. Only 
few studies were conducted with herbal extracts of S. lateriflora 
for prevention and therapy of protein misfolding diseases to date. 
Results shown here for prion diseases are promising also in the 
context of other diseases in this group. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The LCMS-IT-TOF analysis was carried out by Andreas Link 
and Andrea Bodtke, Institute of Pharmacy, Ernst-Moritz-Arndt-
University Greifswald, Greifswald, Germany. </p>





<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 9 | 7 </p>

<p>Eiden et al. </p>

<p>Scutellaria lateriflora inhibits prion replication </p>



<p>Conflict of Interest Statement: The 
authors declare that the research was 
conducted in the absence of any com-
mercial or financial relationships that 
could be construed as a potential con-
flict of interest. </p>

<p>Received: 12 December 2011; paper 
pending published: 30 December 2011; 
accepted: 02 February 2012; published 
online: 17 February 2012. 
Citation: Eiden M, Leidel F, Strohmeier 
B, Fast C and Groschup MH (2012) 
A medicinal herb Scutellaria lateri-
flora inhibits PrP replication in vitro 
and delays the onset of prion disease 
in mice. Front. Psychiatry 3:9. doi: 
10.3389/fpsyt.2012.00009 
This article was submitted to Frontiers in 
Neurodegeneration, a specialty of Fron-
tiers in Psychiatry. 
Copyright © 2012 Eiden, Leidel, 
Strohmeier, Fast and Groschup. This is 
an open-access article distributed under 
the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution Non Commercial License, 
which permits non-commercial use, 
distribution, and reproduction in other 
forums, provided the original authors 
and source are credited. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Psychiatry | Neurodegeneration </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 9 | 8 </p>

</text></tei>