<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3374006" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Knee Surgery &amp; Related Research </p>

<p>Purpose: To compare the extramedullary femoral alignment guide system with the conventional intramedullary alignment guide system for bleeding 
and transfusion rate after total knee arthroplasty (TKA). 
Materials and Methods: Forty-nine female TKA patients were randomized into two groups: intramedullary (IM) group vs. extramedullary (EM) 
group. Drained volume of blood, hemoglobin concentration, hemoglobin drop, and transfusion rate were compared between the two groups. Wound 
problems, bleeding-related problems and thromboembolic complications were collected. 
Results: The mean drained volume via vacuum drainage was less in the EM group than that in the IM group (482.9 mL vs. 266.8 mL, p=0.001). 
Hemoglobin at 5 days after surgery was higher in the EM group (9.3 g/dL vs. 9.9 g/dL, p=0.002) than that in the IM group. The drop in hemoglobin 
after 5 days was smaller in the EM group (3.5 g/dL vs. 2.9 g/dL, p=0.003) than that in the IM group. The EM group had a lower prevalence of 
allogeneic transfusion (45.0% vs. 20.5%, p=0.026) than that in the IM group. No significant complications developed in either group. 
Conclusions: The results suggest that the extramedullary femoral alignment guide technique is an advantageous method that can reduce the drained 
volume of blood and the allogeneic transfusion rate. </p>

<p>Total knee arthroplasty (TKA) involves significant blood loss 
that may require a blood transfusion, which carries its own risks 
including transmission of infection, abnormal immunological 
responses, febrile transfusion reactions, and allergic reactions </p>

<p>1,2) </p>

<p>. 
Accordingly, continuous efforts have been made to avoid 
complications associated with allogeneic blood transfusion, </p>



<p>100 Jeon et al. Efficacy of Extramedullary Guide System for Blood Saving after TKA </p>

<p>The purpose of this study was to investigate whether the 
extramedullary femoral alignment system is advantageous over 
the traditional intramedullary system in terms of blood loss and 
transfusion after TKA. Our hypothesis is that the extramedullary 
system will result in less blood loss and fewer transfusions. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>This study included 80 female patients who underwent 
unilateral TKA under the diagnosis of degenerative arthritis 
between October 2010 and September 2011 at our institution. 
Exclusion criteria were a diagnosis other than degenerative 
arthritis, anticoagulation therapy, liver failure, and renal failure. 
The enrolled patients were randomized into a extramedullary 
(EM) group (n=40) and a intramedullary (IM) group (n=40). 
Excluding one patient in the EM group in whom internal fixation 
was required due to an intraoperative fracture, the remaining 79 
patients were included for analysis. No intergroup differences 
were observed in age, weight, height, body mass index, or 
preoperative hemoglobin concentration (Table 1). 
The surgical protocol was the same for both groups, besides 
the type of the alignment guide for the distal femoral resection 
(extramedullary/intramedullary). In particular, all patients 
received epidural and spinal anesthesia and the preoperative and 
postoperative procedures and surgical techniques were identical. 
Patient-controlled analgesia was implemented postoperatively 
using a 100 mL mixture of 90 mL of 0.125% bupivacaine and 0.5 
mg/10 mL fentanyl via an epidural catheter. All operations were 
performed by the same surgeon (first author) using a medial 
parapatellar approach introduced by Insall. The posterior cruciate 
ligament (PCL) was removed and the same PCL-sacrificing 
prosthesis (Scorpio NRG, Stryker, Kalamazoo, MI, USA) 
was implanted in all knees. The patella was replaced, and the 
prosthetic components were cemented in all cases. Lateral release 
was not performed in all patients. Two markers indicating the </p>

<p>center of the femoral head and the anterior margin of the greater 
trochanter were firmly attached to the patient's skin in the EM 
group prior to surgery so the surgeon could palpate the markers 
and identify the mechanical axis of the lower limb during surgery. 
A femoral cutting block was aligned along the coronal and axial 
axes using new surgical equipment 
16) and the two markers. The </p>

<p>distal femur was cut without placing a rod into the medullary 
canal (Fig. 1). The angle between the anatomical axis and the 
mechanical axis of the femur in the IM group was measured 
using a PACS system on a preoperative anterioposterior long 
leg standing radiograph. An intramedullary alignment rod was 
inserted based on the preoperative measurements, and the distal 
femur was cut. The entrance hole for the alignment rod in the 
femoral medullary canal was sealed with bone fragments before 
inserting the implant. An extramedullary alignment guide was 
used in both groups for proximal tibial cutting. A drainage tube 
was placed in the intra-articular space. After wound closure, a 
compression dressing using gauze and a bandage was applied, 
and the tourniquet was deflated. Drainage was discontinued 
from immediately after surgery until 2 hours after tourniquet 
deflation. All drains were removed 24 hours after surgery. 
Blood transfusion was performed when hemoglobin was &lt;8 
g/dL or when dyspnea, palpitation, dizziness, or abnormal 
vital signs were noted even if the hemoglobin was 8-10 g/dL. 
Rivaroxaban, an oral anticoagulant, was administered from 
immediately after the drain removal until the postoperative week 
2 to prevent thromboembolic disorders. The anticoagulant was 
discontinued if hemarthrosis due to intra-articular bleeding was 
present or effusion from the surgical wound continued. Tests for 
thromboembolic disorders were not performed unless clinical 
symptoms appeared. 
Statistical analyses were conducted using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">12.0</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). A p-value &lt;0.05 was considered </p>

<p>Table 1. Comparison of the Demographic Data between the Intramed-
ullary (IM) and the Extramedullary (EM) Groups </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Variable 
IM (n=40) 
EM (n=39) 
Significance 
(p-value) </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
69.2 (6.7) 
70.1 (8.2) 
0.612 </p>

<p>Body weight (kg) 
63.6 (10.3) 
62.7 (7.9) 
0.594 </p>

<p>Body height (cm) 
152.8 (6.8) 
151.9 (5.7) 
0.748 </p>

<p>Body mass index (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
27.1 (3.8) 
26.8 (2.5) 
0.655 </p>

<p>Preoperative Hb (g/dL) 
12.8 (0.6) 
12.9 (0.9) 
0.754 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Values are presented as means with standard deviations in parentheses. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Placing the distal femoral block to match the coronal and sagittal 
plane of the femur. </p>

<p>Knee Surg Relat Res, Vol. 24, No. 2, Jun. 2012 101 </p>

<p>statistically significant. The continuous variables, drained blood 
volume and preoperative hemoglobin level, were analyzed using 
Student's t-test. The hemoglobin level at 5 days after surgery and 
the hemoglobin drop (hemoglobin level at 5 days after surgery-
hemoglobin level before surgery) were compared between 
groups using analysis of covariance. The prevalence of allogeneic 
transfusion, a categorical variable, was compared between the 
groups using Fisher's exact test. Additionally, the presence of 
other related symptoms were also investigated, including the 
duration of effusion, subcutaneous hematomas, hemarthrosis, 
hemorrhagic complications such as infections, painful leg 
swelling, acute chest pain, dyspnea, lower limb thrombosis, and 
pulmonary embolism. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The mean drained volume via vacuum drainage was 
significantly less in the EM group compared to that in the IM 
group (266.8±164.1 mL vs. 482.9±323.3 mL) (p=0.001). The 
mean hemoglobin at 5 days after surgery was significantly higher 
in the EM group compared to that in the IM group (9.9 g/dL 
vs. 9.3 g/dL) (p=0.002). The hemoglobin drop at 5 days after 
surgery was notably lower in the EM group compared to that in 
the IM group (2.9 g/dL vs. 3.5 g/dL) (p=0.003). The prevalence 
of allogeneic transfusion was remarkably lower in the EM group 
compared to that in the IM group (8 in 39 patients, 20.5% vs. 18 
in 40 patients, 45%) (p=0.026) (Table 2). The transfusion was 
prophylactic in five in the IM group and in two in the EM group. 
A transfusion was required in one patient with a hemoglobin 
level ≥8 g/dL in each group due to complaints of dizziness. 
No severe complications occurred in either group. Antico-
agulation therapy was discontinued due to continuous effusion 
from the surgical wound in two patients in the IM group, but they 
recovered without further complications after discontinuation. 
Thromboembolic disorders were not observed in any of the 
patients. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>TKA is commonly performed in elderly patients and 
substantial blood loss during TKA can result in increased risks 
and disruption of recovery in patients with poor systemic 
condition </p>

<p>17,18) </p>

<p>. Accordingly, a blood transfusion is often required 
after TKA. In an attempt to reduce the adverse effects of blood 
transfusion, many studies have provided various methods, 
including preoperative autologous donation </p>

<p>3-5) </p>

<p>, use of the call 
saver 
19) and fibrinogen concentrates 
20) , subcutaneous suction </p>

<p>drainage </p>

<p>6) </p>

<p>, drain clamping </p>

<p>7) </p>

<p>, hypotensive anesthesia </p>

<p>8) </p>

<p>, and other 
methods </p>

<p>17-21) </p>

<p>. 
In this study, the EM group had more favorable results than 
those in the IM group in terms of blood savings. The mean 
drained volume via the vacuum drainage was smaller in the 
EM group, hemoglobin at 5 days after surgery was higher, the 
hemoglobin drop was smaller, and the prevalence of allogeneic 
transfusion was lower. These results are congruent with the 
hypothesis that the extramedullary alignment guide system 
reduces blood loss and transfusion rate. In this study, we 
measured blood volume drained via vacuum drainage and the 
hemoglobin but did not calculate the blood loss based on some 
reports 
22,23) in which the measured blood loss reflects calculated </p>

<p>blood loss. The extramedullary alignment guide system and 
intramedullary alignment guide system have been compared in 
terms of blood loss in many studies. In 2005, Kalairajah et al. </p>

<p>15) </p>

<p>reported that mean blood drainage volume was significantly 
smaller in the group in which a computer-assisted technique 
was used compared to that in the control group (1,351 mL vs. 
1,747 mL). In 2006, Kandel et al. 
14) documented that mean blood </p>

<p>drainage volume was significantly lower in a extramedullary 
guide system group compared to that in a intramedullary guide 
system group (613 mL vs. 758 mL), and transfusion volume 
appeared to be less in the former group. Our results were 
comparable with those of other studies 
14,15,24,25) that showed </p>

<p>blood loss could be reduced by 145-396 mL when the medullary 
canal was not breached during TKA. Although the frequency </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparisons of the Hematological Data between the Intramed ullary (IM) and Extramedullary (EM) Groups </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Variable 
IM (n=40) 
EM (n=39) 
Significance (p-value) </p>

<p>Hemovac drainage (mL) 
482.9 (323.3) 
266.8 (164.1) 
0.001 </p>

<p>Hb at postoperative day 5 (g/dL) 
9.3 (0.7) 
9.9 (1.2) 
0.002 </p>

<p>Hb drop after 5 days (g/dL) 
3.5 (0.9) 
2.9 (1.1) 
0.003 </p>

<p>Allogeneic blood transfusion 
45.0% (18) 
20.5% (8) 
0.026 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Values are presented as means with standard deviations in parentheses except allogeneic blood transfusion, for which values are presented as 
percents and numbers (in parentheses) of patients who had the conditions. </p>



<p>of transfusion was lower in the EM group in our study, it was 
still higher compared to some recent studies </p>

<p>4,6) </p>

<p>. We attributed 
this to the broad indications for transfusion we set in this study; 
a blood transfusion was performed when hemoglobin was 
&lt;8 g/dL or when dyspnea, palpitation, dizziness, or abnormal 
vital signs were noted, even if the hemoglobin was 8-10 g/dL. 
In addition, prophylactic transfusions that were carried out 
considering the patient's history of illness were counted in the 
transfusion rate calculation. However, when these prophylactic 
cases (5 in the IM group and 2 in the EM group) were not 
counted as transfusions, the frequency decreased to 37.1% (13 
in 35 patients) in the IM group and 16.2% (6 in 37 patients) in 
the EM group. Furthermore, if a higher transfusion threshold of 
7 g/dL hemoglobin was set, the frequency would have declined 
to 27.5% (11 in 40 patients) in the IM group and to 5.1% (2 in 
39 patients) in the EM group. A limitation of this study was the 
lack of diversity in the study population. We think that it would 
be difficult to extrapolate our findings to other patient groups, 
considering that our data were obtained only from female 
patients with a diagnosis of degenerative arthritis. Additionally, 
we did not assess intergroup differences regarding fat embolisms 
or postoperative complications, including hypoxia, pain, or lower 
limb alignment accuracy. 
The intramedullary femoral alignment guide system can result 
in various complications and may not be applicable when a 
long-stemmed femoral component implanted during a previous 
surgery remains or a rod cannot be inserted due to severe 
deformity of the femur 
26) . It has not been clearly elucidated </p>

<p>which system is more advantageous over the other regarding 
component alignment accuracy. However, some recent studies 
have introduced techniques to improve the accuracy of the 
extramedullary alignment guide system 
16,27-30) . Therefore, we </p>

<p>believe that the extramedullary alignment guide system could be 
useful for decreasing blood loss and transfusion frequency during 
TKA unless it is inferior to the intramedullary system in terms of 
component alignment accuracy. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>We believe the extramedullary alignment guide system can be 
effective for reducing blood loss and transfusion rate after TKA. </p>



</text></tei>