<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3194040" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Deg/HtrA proteases are a large group of ATP-independent serine 
endoproteases found in almost every organism. Their usual 
domain arrangement comprises a trypsin-type protease domain 
and one or more PDZ domains. All Deg/HtrA proteases form 
homo-oligomers with trimers as the basic unit, where the active 
protease domain mediates the interaction between individual 
monomers. Among the members of the Deg/HtrA protease 
family, the plant protease DEG7 is unique since it contains 
two protease domains (one active and one degenerated) and 
four PDZ domains. In the present study, we investigated the 
oligomerization behaviour of this unusual protease using yeast </p>

<p>two-hybrid analysis in vivo and with recombinant protein in vitro. 
We show that DEG7 forms trimeric complexes, but in contrast 
with other known Deg/HtrA proteases, it shows a new principle of 
oligomerization, where trimerization is based on the interactions 
between degenerated protease domains. We propose that, during 
evolution, a duplicated active protease domain degenerated and 
specialized in protein-protein interaction and complex formation. </p>

<p>INTRODUCTION </p>

<p>Deg/HtrA (for degradation of periplasmic proteins/high tempera-
ture requirement A) proteases are ATP-independent serine 
proteases found in almost every organism [1,2]. They are generally 
defined by a trypsin-type protease domain (S1B, glutamylpepti-
dase I subfamily according to the nomenclature proposed by 
the MEROPS database [3], http://merops.sanger.ac.uk/) and one 
or more PDZ domains (originally identified in the postsynaptic 
density 95 protein, the Drosophila tumour-suppressor protein 
Discs large and the tight-junction protein zonula occludens 
1) responsible for protein-protein interaction. Members of 
this family without a PDZ domain have also been described 
[4-6]. 
Deg/HtrA proteases form homo-oligomeric complexes, with 
trimers as the basic unit and oligomerization mediated by the 
protease domain [7-9]. Exceptions are plant DEG5 and DEG8 
which form a heterohexameric complex in the thylakoid lumen 
of chloroplasts [6]. Biochemical and crystallographic analysis 
indicated that purified DegP from Escherichia coli [9,10] or HtrA 
from Thermotoga maritima [11] mainly exist as proteolytically 
inactive hexamers, where two homotrimers are stacked in a face-
to-face manner. In solution, these hexamers assemble into large 
catalytically active spherical structures around their substrates 
forming 12-or 24-mers composed of four or eight homotrimers 
respectively [12,13]. 
Deg/HtrA proteases are involved in a variety of processes, 
including signalling [14,15], degradation of damaged proteins 
and housekeeping [16,17], apoptosis [18] and protein processing 
[4,5,19]. The Arabidopsis thaliana genome contains 16 genes 
encoding Deg/HtrA proteases [20]. Phylogenetic comparison of 
Deg/HtrA proteases from various organisms (including plants, 
animals, fungi and bacteria) revealed that this family is divided 
into four distinct groups [4]. DEG7 was the only protease 
from A. thaliana that clustered with Deg/HtrA proteases from </p>

<p>fungi, forming a group of Deg/HtrA enzymes with an unusual 
domain arrangement. All members of this group are twice as 
long as other Deg/HtrA proteases, possess two protease domains 
(one degenerated) and up to four PDZ domains [2,4]. The 
best examined protease from this group is the Ynm3p protein 
(also called Nma111p, for nuclear mediator of apoptosis) from 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae [21-23]. It is a nuclear protein [21,22] 
interacting with the nuclear core complex [22] and long-chain 
acyl-CoA synthetases [23], as assayed by Y2H (yeast two-hybrid) 
screens. In contrast with the yeast protease, DEG7 from A. 
thaliana (At3g03380) was identified as a chloroplast protein 
involved in the degradation of photodamaged D1 protein, a core 
protein of the Photosystem II reaction centre [24]. 
In the present study, we investigated the taxonomic distribution 
of DEG7-like proteases and analysed how the unusual domain 
arrangement affects the oligomerization of DEG7 from A. 
thaliana. We demonstrated that DEG7 orthologues are restricted 
to fungi and plants, including various algae and land plants. 
Using Y2H assays and SEC (size-exclusion chromatography) 
with recombinant DEG7 purified from E. coli, we show that 
trimerization of DEG7 monomers is mediated by the second 
(degenerated) protease domain. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL </p>

<p>Bioinformatics </p>

<p>We searched annotated protein databases for the presence of 
DEG7 orthologues using the BLAST algorithm [25] with default 
parameters as implemented on the web pages of the National 
Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI, http://www.ncbi. 
nlm.nih.gov/blast), The Gene Index Project (TGI, http://compbio. 
dfci.harvard.edu/tgi/), and the Joint Genome Institute (JGI, http:// 
genomeportal.jgi-psf.org/). A list of DEG7 orthologues with their 
respective accession numbers is presented in Supplementary </p>

<p>DegP and DEG1 from A. 
thaliana, representing the best examined Deg/HtrA proteases 
from animals, bacteria and plants respectively, were chosen as 
outgroups, since they do not belong to the DEG7 group [4]. 
Models of the first and second half of DEG7 were created using 
the <rs id="software-0" type="software">MODELLER</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9v6</rs> program [30] with multiple template 
alignment, using the structure files 2pzd.pdb [31], 1lcy.pdb [7], 
3cs0.pdb [12] and 1ky9.pdb [9] as templates. Manual assembly 
of the obtained structures into a DEG7 trimer was performed 
using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">PyMOL</rs> program (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://www.pymol.org/.</rs>/). </p>

<p>Plasmid construction </p>

<p>General molecular biological procedures were conducted using 
the method described in [32]. Sequences of primers used in 
this study are given in Supplementary Table S2 (at http://www. 
BiochemJ.org/bj/435/bj4350167add.htm). A DNA fragment 
encoding A. thaliana DEG7 (At3g03380) was generated by 
PCR with SALK cDNA clone U21730 [33] as a template, 
using primers 0734 and 0740. The resulting cDNA fragment 
was cloned into the pET151-D/TOPO plasmid (Invitrogen), 
resulting in plasmid pHS36. This plasmid was mutagenized with 
primers 0724 and 0725 using the QuikChange ® II site-directed 
mutagenesis kit (Stratagene) according to the manufacturer's 
instructions, resulting in plasmid pHS52 encoding DEG7 Ser206Ala . 
This mutation was introduced to prevent downstream applications 
(purification, expression in yeast) from negative effects of 
potential uncontrolled proteolysis. A change of the active-site 
serine residue to alanine does not influence the oligomerization 
behaviour of the protease domain, as was shown for human HtrA2 
and E. coli DegP [7,9,12]. Amplification of the DEG7 cDNA 
with primers 0740 and 0799, using pHS52 as a template, and 
ligation of the respective DNA into pET151-D/TOPO, created a 
vector for overexpression of full-length His 6 -tagged DEG7 in E. 
coli (pHS166). Plasmids for the overexpression of DEG7 cDNA 
fragments were constructed by amplifying DEG7 Ser206Ala with the 
following primers: first half, primers 0740 and 0771; second half, 
primers 0747 and 0777; active protease domain, primers 0765 and 
0774; degenerated protease domain, primers 0793 and 0797) and 
cloning the fragment into pET151-D/TOPO, resulting in pHS183 
(active protease domain), pHS184 (first half), pHS185 (second 
half) and pHS186 (degenerated protease domain). 
For the Y2H assay, vectors were created using gateway 
technology (Invitrogen). Entry vectors were created by a TOPO 
reaction using cDNA fragments coding for DEG7 Ser206Ala full-
length (DEG7-fl, pHS73, primers 0740 and 0747), DEG7 Met1−Gln563 
(first half, pHS81, primers 0740 and 0771), DEG7 Glu527−Gln1097 
(second half, pHS80, primers 0777 and 0747), DEG7 Ser35−Lys256 
(active protease domain, pHS77, primers 0765 and 0774), </p>

<p>DEG7 Gly581−Gly840 (degenerated protease domain, pHS 172, primers 
0793 and 0797), DEG7 Asp255−Ser373 (PDZ1, pHS78, primers 0775 
and 0767) and DEG7 Ser868−Gln1097 (PDZ3 + 4, pHS88, primers 
0776 and 0747), which were amplified by PCR using pHS52 as 
template. Final vectors for the assay were created by performing 
a gateway reaction with the entry vectors and modified pAD-
GAL4-2.1 (Stratagene), introducing the GAL4 AD (activation 
domain) and modified pBD-Gal4 Cam (Stratagene), introducing 
the GAL4 BD (DNA-binding domain) respectively, resulting in 
pHS82 (AD-DEG7-fl), pHS83 (BD-DEG7-fl), pHS96 (AD-first 
half), pHS91 (BD-first half), pHS95 (AD-second half), pH-
S84 (BD-second half), pHS93 (AD-active protease domain), 
pHS86 (BD-active protease domain), pHS 176 (AD-degenerated 
protease domain), pHS 179 (BD-degenerated protease domain), 
pHS90 (AD-PDZ1), pHS85 (BD-PDZ1), pHS97 (AD-
PDZ3 + 4) and pHS89 (BD-PDZ3 + 4). All primers were 
obtained from Operon Biotechnologies. The inserts of all 
plasmids were sequenced (GATC Biotech), confirming the correct 
nucleotide sequence and insert orientation. </p>

<p>Protein overexpression, purification and SEC </p>

<p>Recombinant DEG7 containing an N-terminal His 6 -tag was pro-
duced in E. coli strain BL21 Star 
TM (DE3) cells (Invitrogen) car-
rying plasmid pHS166. Cells were grown at 30 
• C in 2 litres 
of 2 × YT medium [1.6 % (w/v) tryptone/1 % (w/v) yeast 
extract/0.5 % NaCl] [32] containing 2 % (w/v) glucose and 
100 μg · l 
− 1 ampicillin to a D 600 of 0.8 and cooled down to 20 
• C. 
DEG7 overexpression was induced by adding 0.01 mM IPTG 
(isopropyl β-D-thiogalactopyranoside) (final concentration). 
Cells were harvested after 3 h by centrifugation at 6000 g for 
10 min, resuspended in 2× PBS [32] supplemented with 20 mM 
2ME (2-mercaptoethanol) and Complete 
TM EDTA-free protease 
inhibitor cocktail (Roche) according to the manufacturer's 
instructions, and lysed by ultrasonification for 20 s, followed by 
incubation on ice for 60 s, repeated ten times. After clarification 
of the lysate by centrifugation at 23 000 rev./min for 1 h using a 
Beckman Coulter JS13.1 rotor, the supernatant was applied to a 
Ni 
2 + -NTA (nitrilotriacetic acid) column using anÄKTA FPLC 
system (GE Healthcare) and washed first with 2× PBS containing 
20 mM 2ME, and then with 2× PBS containing 20 mM 2ME 
and 25 % (v/v) glycerol. His 6 -DEG7 was eluted with 50 mM 
imidazole and concentrated using Vivaspin concentrator tubes 
(Vivascience), and subjected to SEC using a Superdex 200 
16/300 GL column (GE Healthcare) and 2× PBS with 20 mM 
2ME to remove any remaining impurities. For a more accurate 
identification of the elution volume, the main fraction containing 
DEG7 (as identified by immunoblotting) was concentrated as 
described above and subjected to a second run on a Superdex 200 
16/300 GL column. To correlate elution volume and molecular 
mass, the column was calibrated with Blue Dextran, ferritin 
(440 kDa), aldolase (158 kDa) and ovalbumin (43 kDa) according 
to the manufacturer's instructions (GE Healthcare). 
Truncated versions of DEG7 with an N-terminal His 6 tag were 
produced at 30 
• C in E. coli strain BL21 Star 
TM (DE3) cells 
carrying plasmid pHS183, pHS184, pHS185 or pHS186. Cells 
were grown in 2 litres of 2 × YT medium [32] containing 2 % 
We searched freely available genome databases for genes encod-
ing DEG7-like proteases and retrieved hits for fungi and plant 
(including green, heterokont and haptophyte algae) genomes. 
All DEG7 orthologues share the unusual domain arrangement 
with two protease domains and up to four PDZ domains 
[2,4] (see Supplementary Figure S1 at http://www.BiochemJ. 
org/bj/435/bj4350167add.htm for sequence alignment data of the 
full-length proteins). The second protease domain is degenera-
ted and lacks the active-site residues, such as histidine, aspartic 
acid and serine (results not shown), but is still recognized when 
scanned against the InterPro database [35] and the <rs type="software">HHpred</rs> 
program [27] (results not shown). In contrast, four PDZ domains 
are not detected in every DEG7 orthologue, although the 
overall length of the proteins is comparable. This indicates 
that, provided the gene models retrieved from the databases 
are correct, some PDZ domains are not conserved enough to 
be detected by the domain prediction programs used in the 
present study. The domain architecture suggests that DEG7-like 
proteases evolved from a whole-gene duplication/fusion event 
of a DegP-like protease (containing a protease domain and two 
PDZ domains), followed by a subsequent degeneration of the </p>

<p>second protease domain (Figure 1, and Supplementary Figure 
S2 at http://www.BiochemJ.org/bj/435/bj4350167add.htm). No 
DEG7 orthologues were found in animals, since all hits have much 
shorter sequences and no hit contained a second protease domain 
(query coverage &lt;30 %; results not shown). Notably, genes 
coding for DEG7 orthologues were also absent from the genomes 
analysed of a primitive red alga (Cyanidioschyzon merolae), 
Cryptophyta (Guillardia theta and Hemiselmis andersenii) 
and diatoms (Phaeodactylum tricornutum and Thalassiosira 
pseudonana). 
Phylogenetic comparison (see Supplementary Figure S3 
at http://www.BiochemJ.org/bj/435/bj4350167add.htm for se-
quence alignment data) confirmed the close evolutionary rela-
tionship of DEG7 orthologues from various organisms (Figure 2). 
Two main clades of DEG7 proteases can be distinguished: 
clade A contains DEG7 proteases from fungi, whereas DEG7 
proteins from green, heterokont and haptophyte algae, mosses 
and higher plants form clade B. Whereas most species investi-
gated possess only one DEG7-like gene, the genomes of the 
yeasts Schizosaccharomyces pombe and Schizosaccharomyces 
japonicus, the ascomycete Giberella zeae, the oomycete Phyto-
phtora soja, the haptophyte alga Emiliania huxleyi and the moss 
Physcomitrella patens contain two, whereas the higher plant 
Populus trichocarpa possesses three DEG7 paralogues (Figure 2). 
Expressed sequence tag data from S. pombe, P. patens and P. 
trichocarpa indicate that all paralogues are expressed in these 
organisms (<rs type="software">TGI</rs>; results not shown), but whether they have 
overlapping/complementary physiological roles is still unknown. 
The distribution of DEG7 proteases to two clades may reflect 
the different intracellular localizations for DEG7-like proteins 
from plants and fungi: DEG7 from A. thaliana was reported to be 
a plastidial [24] protein, whereas Ynm3p from yeast was found in 
the nucleus [21,22]. However, one of the two DEG7 paralogues 
from S. pombe and S. japonicus (Figure 2, marked with asterisks) 
is also present in clade B, together with their plant orthologues. 
Although the intracellular localization of these proteases has not 
been examined so far, a lack of plastids in yeast points to other 
than a plastidial localization. </p>

<p>DEG7 forms homotrimers </p>

<p>Almost all Deg/HtrA proteases examined so far are present as 
homo-oligomers, ranging from trimers, e.g. DegS from E. coli 
[8,36] and mammalian HtrA2 [7], to 24-mers, e.g. DegP from E. 
coli [12,13]. To investigate the oligomerization state of DEG7, 
we performed SEC with recombinant tagged DEG7 purified from 
E. coli (Figure 3). Three absorption peaks at 280 nm were 
observed during the elution (Figure 3A). DEG7 was present 
in one peak, as analysed by immunoblotting with an anti-
DEG7 antibody and SDS/PAGE with subsequent Coomassie Blue 
staining (Figures 3B and 3C). The elution volume of 11.84 ml 
corresponds to an apparent molecular mass of 352 kDa, as 
identified by calibrating the size-exclusion column with proteins 
of known molecular mass. Since the recombinant tagged DEG7 
has a calculated molecular mass of 120 kDa per monomer, this 
result indicates the formation of a trimeric complex. </p>

<p>An ancient Deg/HtrA gene encoding one protease domain and two PDZ domains was duplicated and the gene copy generated was fused within the same open reading frame, resulting in a gene 
encoding a protein with two protease and four PDZ domains. Subsequently, the second protease domain, containing a catalytic triad of histidine (H), aspartate (D) and serine (S), residues, degenerated. 
100aa, 100-amino-acid stretch. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Evolutionary relationship of DEG7 proteases and selected 
members from the Deg/HtrA family </p>

<p>The Neighbour-Joining phylogenetic tree is based on the amino acid sequences of Deg/HtrA 
protease domains. The result of a bootstrap test (1000 replicates) is shown, and branches with 
confident values &gt;75 % are indicated. Maximum-Likelihood and Parsimony methods resulted 
in essentially the same trees (not shown). Human HtrA2, E. coli DegP and DEG1 from A. thaliana 
were chosen as outgroups, since they do not belong to the DEG7 group [4]. Group A contains 
DEG7 orthologues from fungi, Group B contains mainly DEG7 proteases from algae, mosses 
and higher plants. Asterisks mark the distribution of two DEG7 paralogues from S. japonicus 
und S. pombe within groups A and B. </p>

<p>the DEG7 trimer may be compared with the hexameric state 
described for DegP from E. coli [9] rather than the trimers 
observed for DegS from E. coli [8,36] or human HtrA2 [7]. 
However, the unique domain arrangement of DEG7 raises the 
question of which domains mediate the observed trimerization 
(Figure 3). To address this question, a Y2H array was set up 
with protease and PDZ domains and combinations of these as </p>

<p>Figure 3 Recombinant DEG7 forms trimers </p>

<p>(A) Elution profile of purified recombinant DEG7. Three peaks were eluted from the SEC column 
with the indicated elution volumes. Approximate elution volumes of standard proteins are 
indicated by arrows. (B) Immunoblot analysis of proteins from marked fractions, using a DEG7 
specific antibody, indicates the presence of DEG7 in the 11.84 ml elution peak. (C) Coomassie 
Blue staining of an SDS gel loaded with proteins from indicated elution fractions. DEG7 (arrow) 
is the main protein in the 11.84 ml elution peak. Molecular masses are indicated in kDa. </p>

<p>baits and as preys: full-length inactive DEG7 with the catalytic 
serine residue mutated to alanine (DEG7-fl) was fused to the 
AD and BD domain of the yeast GAL4 protein respectively. 
Additionally, the first half (with the catalytic serine residue 
mutated to alanine) and the second half of this protein were 
also fused to the AD domain, as well as the BD domain. To 
analyse individual domains, the predicted active protease domain 
(with the catalytic serine residue mutated to alanine), the second 
(degenerated) protease domain, PDZ1 and PDZ3 + 4 domains 
were fused to the AD and the BD domain. Since the second PDZ 
domain in the first half of the protein was less defined (Figure 1), 
this construct was omitted. The resulting fusion constructs 
were co-expressed in S. cerevisiae in every possible AD/BD 
combination and tested for their ability to activate expression 
of the HIS3 reporter gene that indicates physical interaction of the 
constructs (summarized in Table 1 and Figure 4). No interaction </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>An inactive protease domain mediates DEG7 protease oligomerization </p>



<p>Table 1 Interaction of DEG7 domains assayed by Y2H </p>

<p>Abbreviations: + / + , HIS3 reporter gene activation with both possible AD-and BD-fusion 
combinations; + / − , HIS3 reporter gene activation with one combination only, − / − no 
HIS3 reporter gene activation with either possible combination. Interacting domains are marked 
in bold. </p>

<p>Constructs 
Interaction </p>

<p>DEG7-fl/DEG7-fl 
+ / + 
DEG7-fl/first half 
+ / − 
DEG7-fl/second half 
+ / + 
DEG7-fl/active protease domain 
+ / − 
DEG7-fl/degenerated protease domain 
+ / − 
DEG7-fl/PDZ1 
− / − 
DEG7-fl/PDZ3 + 4 
− / − 
DEG7-fl/empty 
− / − 
First half/first half 
− / − 
First half/second half 
+ / + 
First half/active protease domain 
− / − 
First half/degenerated protease domain 
+ / − 
First half/PDZ1 
− / − 
First half/PDZ3 + 4 
− / − 
First half/empty 
− / − 
Second half/second half 
+ / + 
Second half/active protease domain 
+ / − 
Second half/degenerated protease domain 
+ / + 
Second half/PDZ1 
− / − 
Second half/PDZ3 + 4 
− / − 
Second half/empty 
− / − 
Active protease domain/active protease domain 
− / − 
Active protease domain/degenerated protease domain 
+ / − 
Active protease domain/PDZ1 
− / − 
Active protease domain/PDZ3 + 4 
− / − 
Active protease domain/empty 
− / − 
Degenerated protease domain/degenerated protease domain 
+ / + 
Degenerated protease domain/PDZ1 
− / − 
Degenerated protease domain/PDZ3 + 4 
− / − 
Degenerated protease domain/empty 
− / − 
PDZ1/PDZ1 
− / − 
PDZ1/PDZ3 + 4 
− / − 
PDZ1/empty 
− / − 
PDZ3 + 4/PDZ3 + 4 
− / − 
PDZ3 + 4/empty 
− / − </p>

<p>was detected when BD-and AD-fusion constructs were co-
transformed with the empty AD or the BD vector respectively 
(Table 1), thus excluding autoactivation of the HIS3 reporter gene. 
Similarly, no interaction was observed for constructs containing 
only the PDZ1 domain or PDZ3 + 4 domains, indicating that 
the PDZ domains are not essential for the assembly of the 
oligomeric complex. In all combinations that activated reporter 
gene expression, at least one of the interaction partners contained 
the second (degenerated) protease domain (Figure 4 and Table 1). 
No interaction was observed when this part was lacking in 
both fusion constructs (Figure 4 and Table 1). An additional 
interaction between the active and the degenerated protease 
domain cannot be ruled out, since some combinations (DEG7-
fl/first half, DEG7-fl/active protease domain first half/second 
half, first half/degenerated protease domain, second half/active 
protease domain, active protease domain/degenerated protease 
domain, given as AD/BD combinations) also activated reporter 
gene expression (Table 1, see also Supplementary Figure S4 at 
http://www.BiochemJ.org/bj/435/bj4350167add.htm). This also 
indicates that the lack of reporter gene expression with the 
combinations first half/first half and active protease domain/active 
protease domain is not due to a lack of protein expression 
in the yeast, since some combinations including the AD-first 
half, the BD-first half, the AD-active protease domain, or the </p>

<p>Figure 4 Y2H assay shows that oligomerization of DEG7 is mediated by the 
second (degenerated) protease domain </p>

<p>Growth of S. cerevisiae YRG2 cells on histidine-free medium (indicative for interaction) is only 
visible when the combination of interaction partners contains the second (degenerated) protease 
domain (deg. prot. dom.), which is part of the second half (2nd half) and the full-length protein 
(fl). No interaction occurs with constructs containing only the first half (1st half) or first (active) 
protease domain (act. prot. dom.). The columns show different dilutions of the yeast cultures. A 
dilution factor of 1× corresponds to a D 600 of 1.0. Controls: neg., negative; pos., positive. </p>

<p>BD-active protease domain construct, promoted growth of 
the yeast strain on histidine-free medium (see Supplementary 
Figure S4). In summary, the Y2H data suggest that the second 
(degenerated) protease domain is the key mediator for the 
formation of the trimeric DEG7 complex in plants. The active 
protease domain does not seem to be sufficient for trimer 
formation, in contrast with all Deg/HtrA proteases investigated so 
far. 
To confirm these findings by a method independent of the yeast 
system, the oligomerization status of the first and the second 
half of DEG7, as well as the first (active) and the second (de-
generated) protease domain alone was analysed by SEC with 
recombinant proteins expressed in E. coli. Such truncated DEG7 
constructs were affinity-purified as His 6 -tagged recombinant 
soluble proteins, and subsequently analysed by SEC and 
immunoblotting (Figure 5). Although the constructs representing 
the first and second halves of DEG7 have similar calculated 
molecular masses (65.1 and 66.2 kDa respectively), they exhibit 
totally different elution patterns. The first half of DEG7 elutes as 
one peak in fractions between 14.0 and 14.5 ml (corresponding to 
an apparent molecular mass of approx. 75-100 kDa), whereas the 
second half of DEG7 is present in two distinct peaks (fractions </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>



<p>H. Schuhmann, U. Mogg and I. Adamska </p>

<p>Figure 5 Only recombinant DEG7 containing the second (degenerated) protease domain forms oligomers </p>

<p>Immunoblot (anti-His 5 -tag antibody) showing the distribution of truncated DEG7 after SEC. Fractions are indicated as vertical lines at the bottom, and numbers (in ml) indicate the respective elution 
volume. Truncated DEG7 proteins containing the second (degenerated) protease domain (2nd half, deg. prot. dom.) are eluted in two peaks at lower buffer volumes as compared with truncated 
proteins with the first (active) protease domain (1st half, act. prot. dom.), which are eluted in a single peak at the higher buffer volume. </p>

<p>between 9.5 and 10.0 ml, and 12.5 and 13.0 ml, corresponding 
to apparent molecular masses of 980-1300 and 170-240 kDa 
respectively). Similar differences in the elution patterns are also 
observed for the active protease domain as compared with the 
degenerated protease domain (Figure 5). Whereas the active 
protease domain (calculated molecular mass of 27.9 kDa) is 
present in the fractions between 17.0 and 17.5 ml (corresponding 
to an apparent molecular mass of 13-18 kDa) the degenerated 
protease domain (calculated molecular mass of 31.5 kDa) elutes 
as two poorly resolved peaks between 12.0 and 12.5 ml, and 
14.0 and 14.5 ml, corresponding to apparent molecular masses of 
230-315 and 75-100 kDa respectively). Although the estimation 
of apparent molecular masses of oligomers is too inaccurate to 
determine the exact stoichiometry of the complexes, these data 
suggest that the first half of DEG7 and the active protease domain 
are eluted as monomers, whereas the second half of DEG7 and 
the degenerated protease domains form at least two types of 
oligomer, possibly a trimer and a higher oligomeric complex. The 
inaccuracy in the estimation of molecular masses of monomers 
and oligomers could be due to sterical factors and the fact that 
DEG7 deletion constructs are probably far from a globular shape, 
which might be different for the intact protein. For the deletion 
construct containing the active protease domain, this might also 
explain the difference between the molecular mass according 
to the SEC and that estimated by SDS/PAGE, which matched 
the calculated values (results not shown). In summary, we can 
conclude from these data that only DEG7 deletion constructs 
with the degenerated protease domain are able to form oligomeric 
complexes, thus confirming the data obtained from the Y2H 
screen (Figure 4 and Table 1, and see Supplementary Figure S4). </p>

<p>Modelling of DEG7 structure </p>

<p>To illustrate how DEG7 might form oligomers, we built a model 
based on our findings that DEG7 forms trimers mediated by 
interactions of second (degenerated) protease domains, and the 
available crystal structures of E. coli DegP [9,12] and human 
HtrA2 [7] (Figure 6). For clarity, the approx. 100-amino-acid 
stretch between the second PDZ domain and the degenerated 
protease domain (Figure 1) was omitted. The oligomerization 
via the second (degenerated) protease domain might enable the 
protein to keep the catalytic subunits in close proximity, without 
the actual formation of a proteolytic active complex. This might 
ensure a very rapid initiation of proteolysis after binding of a 
substrate. However, details in this model, especially the relative 
orientations of the active protease domains, need to be resolved 
further. </p>

<p>Figure 6 Homology modelling of a DEG7 trimer </p>

<p>The putative structure of a DEG7 trimer was modelled on the hexameric structure of E. coli 
DegP [9]. The approx. 100-amino-acid stretch between the second PDZ and the degenerated 
protease domain (Figure 1) was omitted for clarity. Relative orientations of the first half of the 
protein are not supported. (A) Cartoon model, side view. Monomeric subunits are coloured blue, 
green and red respectively. The second halves of the protein are at the bottom, coloured darker 
than the first halves. (B) Surface model, side view. The active protease domains are col-
oured blue, the second (degenerated) protease domains involved in oligomerization are coloured 
light blue. This model might represent a protease oligomer in an inactive conformation. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>We have shown that the DEG7 protease from A. thaliana 
has orthologues in green, heterokont and haptophyte algae, in 
fungi, mosses and higher plants, but no orthologues can be 
found in animals. The unusual domain arrangement of DEG7 
with two protease domains (one degenerated) and four PDZ 
domains requires a different mode of oligomerization than the one 
which was described for all other Deg/HtrA proteases. Although 
trimerization through an active protease domain is a common </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>An inactive protease domain mediates DEG7 protease oligomerization </p>



<p>feature of Deg/HtrA proteases in bacteria and mammals, the active 
protease domain of plant DEG7 is not essential for this process. 
Instead, the second (degenerated) protease domain is responsible 
for the trimerization of DEG7 in plants. 
Inactive protease domains were reported from the proteolytic 
active oligomers of other proteases. Clp proteases in bacteria, 
for example, are oligomeric serine proteases with a proteolytic 
core constituted by two heptameric rings, with each heptamer 
composed of identical proteolytically active ClpP subunits [37]. 
In chloroplasts of plants and in cyanobacteria, however, the Clp 
protease core is a heteroheptamer, containing three proteolytically 
active ClpP subunits and four inactive ClpR variants, which show 
sequence similarity to ClpP on the amino acid level, but lack the 
catalytic triad of serine type proteases [38,39]. A high sequence 
similarity between the inactive ClpR and the active ClpP variants 
indicates a common ancestor [40]. This is supported by the fact 
that loss of the catalytic triad appears to be ongoing process since 
some cyanobacterial ClpR variants still retain one of the active-
site residues [39]. 
A similar situation was reported for the 20S proteolytically 
active core unit of the 26S proteasome. This core unit is composed 
of four stacked heptameric rings. In Archaea, the two inner rings 
are homo-oligomers of proteolytically active β-subunits, whereas, 
in eukaryotes, the β-subunit has diverged into seven different 
β-proteins (reviewed in [41,42]). Of these seven β-subunits, only 
three contain the active-site residues and are proteolytically active. 
Despite the lack of enzymatic activity, the inactive β-subunits are 
essential for the correct assembly of the eukaryotic proteasome. 
In the case of ClpP from photosynthetic organisms and the pro-
teasome from eukaryotes, formerly active protease domains (or, 
in these cases, one-domain subunits) evolved into domains with 
tasks other than proteolysis, e.g. mediating subunit contacts in the 
oligomeric protease complex. The second (degenerated) protease 
domain of DEG7, which is described in the present paper, might 
be yet another example, where a formerly active enzymatic entity 
is now involved in the oligomerization of the protease complex. 
For Deg/HtrA proteases, inactive protease domains involved in 
oligomer formation have not been described so far. In contrast 
with ClpP and the proteasome, however, this inactive domain 
is not encoded by a separate gene, but is a part of the same 
polypeptide chain as the active protease domain. </p>

<p>We are grateful to Silvia Kuhn for technical assistance in the Y2H assays, and Dr Dietmar 
Funck for helpful advice. We thank the Nottingham Arabidopsis Stock Centre (NASC) for 
providing the cDNA clones. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>This work was supported by grants from the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft [grant 
numbers AD92/8-2 and AD92/8-3] and Konstanz University (to I.A.). </p>



<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>



<p>H. Schuhmann, U. Mogg and I. Adamska </p>



<p>Received 1 October 2010/19 January 2011; accepted 19 January 2011 
Published as BJ Immediate Publication 19 January 2011, doi:10.1042/BJ20101613 </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Biochem. J. (2011) 435, 167-174 (Printed in Great Britain) doi:10.1042/BJ20101613 </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY ONLINE DATA </p>

<p>A new principle of oligomerization of plant DEG7 protease based on 
interactions of degenerated protease domains </p>

<p>Holger SCHUHMANN, Ulrike MOGG and Iwona ADAMSKA </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Physiology and Plant Biochemistry, University of Konstanz, Universitätsstrasse 10, D-78457 Konstanz, Germany </p>

<p>Table S1 DEG7 orthologues and their accession numbers (SwissProt 
Protein Database) </p>

<p>*JGI protein ID, no entry in SwissProt Database; **GenBank ® accession number, no entry in 
SwissProt Database. </p>

<p>Organism 
Accession number </p>

<p>Arabidopsis thaliana 
Q8RY22 
Aspergillus nidulans 
Q5B1Z4 
Aspergillus niger 
A5AB13 
Aspergillus oryzae 
Q2TYB1 
Aureococcus anophagefferens 
322* 
Candida albicans 
Q5A946 
Chlamydomonas reinhardtii 
A8JH35 
Chlorella sp. NC64A 
37665* 
Emiliania huxleyi (1) 
452178* 
Emiliania huxleyi (2) 
245118* 
Gibberella zeae (1) 
UPI000023D1E1 
Gibberella zeae (2) 
UPI000023F481 
Glycine max 
AK287315** 
Magnaporthe grisea 
A4RJH4 
Micromonas pusilla 
35996* 
Neosartorya fischeri 
A1DP85 
Neurospora crassa 
Q7S9D2 
Oryza sativa 
B9F2C1 
Penicillium marneffei 
B6QAL6 
Phaeosphaeria nodorum 
Q0UY70 
Physcomitrella patens (1) 
A9TIB2 
Physcomitrella patens (2) 
A9RQ61 
Phytophtora capsici 
27218* 
Phytophtora soja (1) 
133655* 
Phytophtora soja (2) 
199402* 
Podospora anserina 
B2ASP9 
Populus trichocarpa (1) 
B9GV35 
Populus trichocarpa (2) 
B9H390 
Populus trichocarpa (3) 
B9H391 
Pyrenophora tritici-repentis 
B2WNT3 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae 
P53920 
Schizosaccharomyces japonicus (1) 
B6K3R7 
Schizosaccharomyces japonicus (2) 
B6JWG1 
Schizosaccharomyces pombe (1) 
Q9P7S1 
Schizosaccharomyces pombe (2) 
O74325 
Sclerotinia sclerotiorum 
A7E9G4 
Selaginella moellendorffii 
165477* 
Solanum lycopersicum 
AK321684** 
Sorghum bicolor 
5004613* 
Vanderwaltozyma polyspora 
A7TGI3 
Volvox carteri 
79278* </p>

<p>Table S2 List of oligonucleotides used as PCR primers </p>

<p>Name 
Sequence (5 →3 ) </p>

<p>0724 
GGTACTAAAGGTGGTTCAGCTGGTTCTCCCGTCATTG 
0725 
CAATGACGGGAGAACCAGCTGAACCACCTTTAGTACC 
0734 
TATGTCGACTTACTGCAAGGCTTTC 
0740 
CACCATGGGAGATCCGTTGGA 
0747 
GCGCCGCGGTTACTGCAAGGCTTTC 
0765 
GCGTTACTTATCCGTCCGCGAGTC 
0767 
GCGTTATGAGTGTAAATCTTGTACTGATA 
0771 
GCGTTATTGTTTCTTTGCTTCTGAGCC 
0774 
CACCTCCGTTGCCACCGCTGAAGATTG 
0775 
CACCGATAAGCCAAAAGCAGTTCATATTC 
0776 
CACCTCAAAAGCCCGGAGTTTTGGTC 
0777 
CACCGAACCCATGCATGAAGTGAATG 
0793 
CACCGGCAGTGAATTTAAATCTGATG 
0797 
CGCTTATCCATTTCCACCGGTTATGATT 
0799 
CGCTTAATCTTGTTTCAGAGTCAATACTC </p>

<p>1 To whom correspondence should be addressed (e-mail iwona.adamska@uni-konstanz.de). </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>H. Schuhmann, U. Mogg and I. Adamska </p>

<p>Figure S1 M-Coffee multiple sequence alignment of the amino acid sequences of the DEG7 orthologues used in the present study </p>

<p>The approximate position of the domains (as determined by using the InterProScan and <rs type="software">HHpred</rs> prediction servers) are indicated by black bars on top of the alignment. Conserved residues of catalytic 
triad are shown as blue letters above the alignment. For full names of organisms, see Supplementary Table S1. cons., consensus; *, identity; :, conserved replacement; ., non-conserved replacement. </p>

<p>Continues... </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>An inactive protease domain mediates DEG7 protease oligomerization </p>

<p>Figure S1 Continued </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>H. Schuhmann, U. Mogg and I. Adamska </p>

<p>Figure S1 Continued </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>An inactive protease domain mediates DEG7 protease oligomerization </p>

<p>Figure S1 Continued </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>H. Schuhmann, U. Mogg and I. Adamska </p>

<p>Figure S1 Continued </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>An inactive protease domain mediates DEG7 protease oligomerization </p>

<p>Figure S1 Continued </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>H. Schuhmann, U. Mogg and I. Adamska </p>

<p>Figure S1 Continued </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>An inactive protease domain mediates DEG7 protease oligomerization </p>

<p>Figure S1 Continued </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>H. Schuhmann, U. Mogg and I. Adamska </p>

<p>Figure S1 Continued </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>An inactive protease domain mediates DEG7 protease oligomerization </p>

<p>Figure S1 Continued </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>H. Schuhmann, U. Mogg and I. Adamska </p>

<p>Figure S1 Continued </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>An inactive protease domain mediates DEG7 protease oligomerization </p>

<p>Figure S2 M-Coffee multiple sequence alignment of the amino acid sequences of protease domains and PDZ domains of A. thaliana DEG7 </p>

<p>(A) Alignment of the first (active) protease domain (A. thaliana DEG7 1st prot. dom.) and the second (degenerate) protease domain (A. thaliana 2nd prot. dom.). The sequence of the protease domain 
of A. thaliana DEG1 is included to facilitate identification of catalytic side chains (shown in blue above the alignment). (B) Alignment of the PDZ domains. PDZ1 and PDZ3 both contain a stretch of 
additional amino acids not present in PDZ2 and PDZ4, indicating a whole-gene-duplication event as presented in Figure 1 of the main text. cons., consensus: *, identity; :, conservative replace-
ment; ., non-conservative replacement. </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>H. Schuhmann, U. Mogg and I. Adamska </p>

<p>Figure S3 Alignment of the amino acid sequences of the active protease domains of DEG7 proteins from higher plants, mosses, algae and fungi </p>

<p>Amino acid sequences of DEG7 active protease domains were aligned with those of the protease domains of DegP from Escherichia coli (EcDegP), human HtrA2 (HsHtrA2) and Deg1 from 
Arabidopsis thaliana (AtDEG1) as described in the Experimental section of the main text. For full names of organisms, see Supplementary Table S1. Identical residues are indicated by asterisks. 
Active-site residues of the catalytic triad are in bold. Conservative replacements are indicated by : symbols; non-conservative replacements are indicated by . symbols. </p>

<p>Continues... </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>An inactive protease domain mediates DEG7 protease oligomerization </p>

<p>Figure S3 Continued </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>H. Schuhmann, U. Mogg and I. Adamska </p>

<p>Figure S3 Continued </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>An inactive protease domain mediates DEG7 protease oligomerization </p>

<p>Figure S3 Continued </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>H. Schuhmann, U. Mogg and I. Adamska </p>

<p>Figure S3 Continued </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>An inactive protease domain mediates DEG7 protease oligomerization </p>

<p>Figure S4 Y2H assay shows that oligomerization of DEG7 is mediated by the second (degenerated) protease domain (extended version) </p>

<p>(A) Schematic outline of the experiment. Yeast drop cultures on medium containing histidine, but lacking tryptophan and leucine were used as transformation controls, indicating that the strain con-
tains both the AD and the BD vector. (B) Y2H assay as summarized in Table 1 and Figure 4 of the main text. Empty AD and BD vectors were used as autoactivation controls. Every yeast strain growing 
on histidine-free medium contains the second protease domain in at least one construct. The AD-first half, BD-first half, AD-active protease domain, and BD-active protease domain constructs 
respectively mediated growth on histidine-free medium in at least some combinations, indicating that lack of gene expression in the combinations first half/first half and active protease domain/active 
protease domain is not due to a lack of protein expression. pos, positive control; neg, negative control. </p>

<p>Received 1 October 2010/19 January 2011; accepted 19 January 2011 
Published as BJ Immediate Publication 19 January 2011, doi:10.1042/BJ20101613 </p>

<p>c The Authors Journal compilation c 2011 Biochemical Society </p>

<p>© 2011 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

</text></tei>