<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3091210" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The determinants of single channel conductance (␥) and ion 
selectivity within eukaryotic pentameric ligand-gated ion chan-
nels have traditionally been ascribed to amino acid residues 
within the second transmembrane domain and flanking se-
quences of their component subunits. However, recent evidence 
suggests that ␥ is additionally controlled by residues within the 
intracellular and extracellular domains. We examined the 
influence of two anionic residues (Asp 
113 and Asp 
127 ) within 
the extracellular vestibule of a high conductance human 
mutant 5-hydroxytryptamine type-3A (5-HT 3 A) receptor 
(5-HT 3 A(QDA)) upon ␥, modulation of the latter by extracellu-
lar Ca 
2؉ , and the permeability of Ca 
2؉ with respect to Cs 
؉ (P Ca / </p>

<p>P Cs ). Mutations neutralizing (Asp 3 Asn), or reversing (Asp 3 
Lys), charge at the 113 locus decreased inward ␥ by 46 and 58%, 
respectively, but outward currents were unaffected. The D127N 
mutation decreased inward ␥ by 82% and also suppressed out-
ward currents, whereas the D127K mutation caused loss of 
observable single channel currents. The forgoing mutations, 
except for D127K, which could not be evaluated, ameliorated 
suppression of inwardly directed single channel currents by 
extracellular Ca 
2؉ . The P Ca /P Cs of 3.8 previously reported for 
the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) construct was reduced to 0.13 and 0.06 by the 
D127N and D127K mutations, respectively, with lesser, but 
clearly significant, effects caused by the D113N (1.04) and 
D113K (0.60) substitutions. Charge selectivity between monova-
lent cations and anions (P Na /P Cl ) was unaffected by any of the 
mutations examined. The data identify two key residues in the 
extracellular vestibule of the 5-HT 3 A receptor that markedly influ-
ence ␥, P Ca /P Cs , and additionally the suppression of ␥ by Ca </p>

<p>2؉ </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>The pentameric ligand-gated ion channel (pLGIC) 
4 super-
family in eukaryotes can be subdivided into two functional </p>

<p>groups based upon the charge selectivity of the ion channel in 
the open state. The excitatory 5-hydroxytryptamine type 3 
(5-HT 3 ) and nicotinic acetylcholine (nACh) receptors, together 
with the zinc-activated channel, are non-selective cation chan-
nels that are permeable to Na 
ϩ , K 
ϩ , and, to varying degrees, 
Ca 
2ϩ and Mg 
2ϩ (1-3). The inhibitory ␥-aminobutyric acid type 
A (GABA A ) and glycine receptors are anion-selective and con-
duct mainly Cl 
Ϫ and HCO 3 
Ϫ under physiological conditions 
(4 -6). 
All eukaryotic pLGIC subunits possess three topologically 
and functionally homologous domains (7-11): (i) an extracel-
lular domain (ECD), (ii) the transmembrane domain, and (iii) 
an intracellular domain. The ECD is rich in ␤-sheet and loop 
motifs and contributes to the ligand binding site, which is 
located at subunit interfaces, and the extracellular vestibule of 
the ion channel. The transmembrane domain comprises four 
␣-helical stretches (TM1-TM4) organized such that TM1, 
TM3, and TM4 shield TM2 from the lipid bilayer (8, 9). The 
TM regions are linked by extracellular (TM2-TM3) and intra-
cellular (TM1-TM2 and TM3-TM4) loops. TM2 forms the lin-
ing of the transmembrane portion of the ion channel and con-
tains the channel gate (9). The TM3-TM4 linker (the large 
intracellular loop) forms the bulk of the intracellular domain 
and is the least conserved region of the subunit peptide across 
the pLGIC receptor family. The structure of the intracellular 
domain is largely unresolved, apart from an ␣-helical region 
(the MA stretch) that is located immediately N-terminal to 
TM4 in images of the Torpedo nACh receptor obtained by cryo-
electron microscopy (cryo-EM) (9, 12). 
It is axiomatic that residues located within TM2 and the 
TM1-TM2 linker influence profoundly (i) single channel con-
ductance (␥), (ii) charge selectivity, and (iii) for cation selective 
channels, di-versus monovalent cation selectivity (13-15) 
(reviewed in Ref. 4). However, several recent studies have 
revealed that regions homologous to the MA stretch of the Tor-
pedo nACh receptor are additional determinants of ␥ in 5-HT 3 , 
nACh ␣4␤2, and ␣1 glycine receptors (16 -19) (reviewed in Ref. 
1). In the case of the 5-HT 3 A receptor, this region also contrib-
utes to di-versus monovalent cation selectivity but not charge 
selectivity (20). The 4 Å resolution structure of the Torpedo 
nACh receptor obtained by cryo-EM and image reconstruc-
tion (8, 9) reveals that the MA stretch, with a contribution 
from the TM1-TM2 linker, frames intracellular fenestra-
tions through which ions must flow to enter or exit the cyto-
plasmic vestibule of the channel, providing a structural basis 
for such observations. </p>

<p>Adding to the concept of an extended permeation pathway 
that influences the biophysical properties of pLGICs, the wide 
extracellular vestibule, surrounded by the pore lining regions of 
the ECD, has long been theorized to localize cations to the 
narrower transmembrane channel (21). Indeed, the cryo-EM 
images of the Torpedo nACh receptor depict an electroneg-
ative vestibule of ϳ60 Å in length and maximally 20 Å in 
width that has been predicted to strongly influence cation 
conduction (9). 
Using a homology model of the closed state of the adult mus-
cle nACh receptor ((␣1) 2 ␤1␥⑀), based upon the cryo-EM 
images of the Torpedo nACh receptor (9), Wang et al. (22) 
conducted in silico molecular dynamics simulations of the tran-
sition of Na 
ϩ ions through the conduction pathway over a time 
frame of 16 ns. The simulation revealed the stabilization of cat-
ions at a number of positions along the channel axis. Notably, 
the extracellular vestibule was highlighted to present negative 
charges corresponding to the ␣1 subunit residues Glu 
83 and 
Asp 
97 , where cations appeared to reside before further translo-
cation to the transmembrane portion of the channel. Numer-
ous additional computational approaches applied to homology 
models of the nACh receptor indicate that the ECD acts to 
concentrate monovalent cations over anions (e.g. see Refs. 23 
and 24). By contrast, a homology model of the GABA A receptor 
indicates the ECD to concentrate anions in preference to cat-
ions (25). 
Direct experimental evidence for a role of the extracellular 
vestibule of human muscle nACh receptors in setting ␥ has 
been provided by Hansen et al. (26), who made mutations 
within a negatively charged ring corresponding to Asp 
97 in the 
␣1 subunit. Mutation of the residues at this locus to lysine in all 
subunits caused a maximal reduction of ␥ to ϳ20% of control, 
as observed in recordings performed on cell-attached patches. 
In this study, we investigate the influence of Asp 
113 and 
Asp 
127 of the 5-HT 3 A receptor, which align with Glu 
83 and 
Asp 
97 of the ␣1 nACh receptor subunit, respectively, upon ␥, 
single current channel rectification, ion selectivity, and modu-
lation of ␥ by extracellular Ca 
2ϩ . The analyses were performed 
in the background of a high ␥ mutant of the human 5-HT 3 A 
receptor (5-HT 3 A(QDA)), because the wild-type 5-HT 3 A 
receptor has a ␥ value too small to quantify by conventional 
single channel recording techniques (1, 16, 27). The muta-
tions introduced into the large intracellular loop of the 
human 5-HT 3 A receptor to generate the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) 
receptor construct are R432Q, R436D, and R440A (16). We 
demonstrate that the extracellular channel vestibule within 
this model cationic pLGIC strongly influences ␥ and is also 
an important determinant of relative permeability to Ca </p>

<p>2ϩ </p>

<p>and the modulation of ␥ by extracellular Ca 
2ϩ . A preliminary 
account of some of the results has appeared in abstract form 
(28). </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>5-HT 3 A Receptor Constructs and Transfection of cDNAs-
The methods employed to generate mutant constructs within 
the 5-HT3A(QDA) cDNA background and to transiently trans-
fect tsA-201 cells with cDNA constructs were as detailed 
previously (20). The mutations generated in this study were 5-</p>

<p>HT3A(QDA) D113N, 5-HT3A(QDA) D113K, 5-HT3A(QDA) 
D127N, and 5-HT3A(QDA) D127K. Cells were maintained in 
Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium supplemented with 10% 
(v/v) fetal bovine serum, 2 mM L-glutamine, 1 mM sodium pyru-
vate, 100 g/ml streptomycin, and 100 units/ml penicillin. Cells 
were incubated at 37°C for 18 -96 h in 95% air, 5% CO 2 at 100% 
humidity prior to electrophysiological recordings. 
Electrophysiological Recordings-The whole-cell and out-
side-out patch configurations of the patch clamp technique 
were used to record macroscopic and single channel currents 
evoked by 5-HT, respectively. Patch electrodes for both modes 
were filled with a solution comprising 140 mM CsCl, 0.1 mM 
CaCl 2 , 1.1 mM EGTA, 10 mM HEPES, pH 7.2 (adjusted with 1 M 
CsOH; final [Cs </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>] o ϭ 143 mM). The intracellular free calcium 
concentration of this solution was estimated to be 10 nM (29). 
The recording chamber comprised a 35-mm Petri dish on 
which the cells were cultivated. Using a gravity-feed system, the 
chamber was superfused routinely at ϳ5 ml/min, at room tem-
perature (20 -23°C), with extracellular solutions of the compo-
sitions described below. Single channel currents evoked by 
pressure-applied 5-HT (10 M) were recorded in an extracellu-
lar solution (E1) consisting of 142.8 mM NaCl, 0.1 mM MgCl 2 , 
0.1 mM CaCl 2 , 10 mM glucose, 10 mM HEPES, pH 7.2 (adjusted 
by 1 M NaOH; final [Na 
ϩ ] o ϭ 146 mM). Whole-cell recording 
was used to determine the reversal potentials (E 5-HT ) of macro-
scopic currents elicited by 5-HT (10 M) by means of a voltage-
ramp protocol using <rs id="software-0" type="software">WinWCP</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V3 9.6</rs> electrophysiology 
software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">J. Dempster</rs>, Department of Physiology and Pharma-
cology, University of Strathclyde, UK; available on the World 
Wide Web). Unless stated otherwise, E 5-HT was determined via 
a protocol wherein the membrane potential was initially set at 
Ϫ60 mV, and a macroscopic current response to 5-HT was 
elicited. During the plateau of the current response, the mem-
brane potential was stepped from Ϫ60 to Ϫ100 mV for 100 ms 
and subsequently ramped to ϩ80 mV within 1 s. Care was taken 
to ensure that the current amplitude at the beginning and ter-
mination of the voltage ramp protocol were similar. An identi-
cal voltage ramp in the absence of 5-HT served to determine the 
leakage current and was subtracted from the currents evoked in 
the presence of 5-HT to generate the current-voltage (I-V) rela-
tionship specifically attributable to the 5-HT-evoked conduct-
ance. E 5-HT was determined from such leak-subtracted cur-
rents. In order to determine the permeability of Na 
ϩ relative to 
Cs 
ϩ (P Na /P Cs ), E 5-HT was determined in solution E1, and the 
permeability ratio was calculated from the Goldman-Hodgkin-
Katz (GHK) (voltage) equation, </p>

<p>E 5-HT ϭ 
RT 
F 
ln 
͑P Na ͞P Cs ͒[Na 
ϩ ] o </p>

<p>͓Cs 
ϩ ] i </p>

<p>(Eq. 1) </p>

<p>where R, T, and F have their usual meaning, and [Na 
ϩ ] o and 
[Cs 
ϩ ] i are the calculated activities of extracellular Na 
ϩ and 
internal Cs 
ϩ ions. This equation ignores the very small error 
anticipated due to the presence of low concentrations of per-
meant divalent ions (e.g. Ca 
2ϩ ) within the extra-or intracellular 
solutions. 
To calculate the permeability of Ca 
2ϩ relative to Cs 
ϩ (P Ca / 
P Cs ), E 5-HT was determined in solution E2, comprising CaCl 2 </p>

<p>The ECD of the 5-HT 3 A Receptor Influences Channel Biophysics </p>

<p>MAY 6, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 18 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 16009 </p>

<p>100 mM, glucose 10 mM, L-histidine 5 mM (pH 7.2), and the ratio 
was derived from a modified GHK (voltage) equation (20, 30), </p>

<p>E 5-HT ϭ 
RT 
F 
ln 
4͑P Ca 
Ј ͞P Cs ͒[Ca 
2ϩ ] o 
͓Cs 
ϩ ] i </p>

<p>(Eq. 2) </p>

<p>where [Ca 
2ϩ ] o is the external activity of Ca 
2ϩ , [Cs 
ϩ ] i is the 
internal activity of Cs 
ϩ , and PЈ Ca /P Cs is a modified term relating 
the permeability of Ca 
2ϩ to Cs </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>. Substituting for PЈ Ca /P Cs , the 
above can be rewritten as follows. </p>

<p>exp 
E5-HTF/RT ϭ 4 
P Ca [Ca 
2ϩ ] o </p>

<p>P Cs ͑1 ϩ exp 
E5-HTF/RT ͓͒Cs 
ϩ ] i </p>

<p>(Eq. 3) </p>

<p>For simplicity, we routinely refer to ion concentrations 
rather than activities throughout, although the latter were 
employed in the calculations of relative permeabilities. 
To examine modulation of ␥ by extracellular Ca 
2ϩ , single 
channel recordings and determinations of E 5-HT were also 
made in extracellular solutions (E3, E4, and E5) containing vari-
able [CaCl 2 ] o (0.1, 1, and 10 mM, respectively) but constant 
[NaCl] o (95 mM), L-histidine (5 mM), and glucose 10 (mM), pH 
7.2. The osmolarity of such solutions was held constant by the 
addition of appropriate amounts of sucrose. An extracellular 
solution (E6) containing 20 mM NaCl, 0.1 mM MgCl 2 , 0.1 mM 
CaCl 2 , 10 mM glucose, 239.4 mM sucrose, 5 mM L-histidine, pH 
7.2 (adjusted by 1 M HCl), in addition to solutions E1 and E3, 
was used to perform dilution potential measurements in order 
to determine relative permeability to chloride. Liquid junction 
potentials between the pipette tip and extracellular solutions 
were measured according to Fenwick et al. (29) and were cor-
rected post hoc. In brief, the zero current voltage was initially 
determined with the intracellular solution present within both 
the patch pipette and the bath. The extracellular solutions (E1-
E6) used in the experiments then replaced the intracellular 
solution, and the change in zero current voltage (i.e. the liquid 
junction potential) was noted. A salt bridge consisting of 3 M 
KCl in 4% (w/v) agar connected the bath to the reference elec-
trode, eliminating changes in the potential of the latter during 
this procedure. 
Single channel currents were low pass-filtered offline at 1 
kHz, digitized at 10 kHz via a <rs id="software-1" type="software">DigiData</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">1302A</rs> (Axon Instru-
ments) interface. Using the <rs id="software-2" type="software">WinEDR</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">V2 7.6</rs> Electrophysiology 
Data Recorder (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">J. Dempster</rs>, Department of Physiology and 
Pharmacology, University of Strathclyde, UK; available on the 
World Wide Web), single channel current amplitude histo-
grams were constructed from sections of single channel activity 
in which unitary events predominated, as described in detail 
previously (20). The ␥ value is routinely reported as the chord 
conductance (i.e. ␥ ϭ i/(V m Ϫ E 5-HT ), where i is single channel 
current amplitude, V m is the holding potential (including liquid 
junction potential correction), and E 5-HT is the reversal poten-
tial of the agonist-evoked macroscopic response determined as 
described above under the appropriate ionic conditions. In the 
case of the 5-HT3A(QDA) D127K mutant, single channel cur-
rents could not be resolved directly in recording from outside-
out membrane patches. Thus, we estimated ␥ by fluctuation 
analysis of whole-cell current evoked by 5-HT (1 M) as previ-
ously described by us (16). A rectification index (RI) is used to </p>

<p>describe the degree of single channel current rectification. The 
RI was calculated as follows, </p>

<p>RI ϭ 
slope ␥ (positive V) 
slope ␥ (negative V) </p>

<p>(Eq. 4) </p>

<p>where slope ␥ (positive V) and slope ␥ (negative V) were obtained 
from obtaining the slope of the line of best fit plotted to data 
points from positive and negative holding potentials, respec-
tively. An RI value of 1 indicates a linear/ohmic i-V relationship. 
An RI of Ͼ1 indicates outward rectification, and RI Ͻ1 indi-
cates inward rectification. 
Statistical Analysis-Data are presented as mean Ϯ S.E. Sta-
tistical analysis was conducted using one-way analysis of vari-
ance (ANOVA) with the post hoc Dunnett's or Dunn's test as 
appropriate. p Ͻ 0.05 was considered to be significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Asp 
113 Is a Determinant of ␥ and Single Channel Current 
Rectification-Asp 
113 is predicted from a homology model of 
the human 5-HT 3 A receptor (18) to reside approximately one-
third of the distance from the entrance to the extracellular 
vestibule to the extracellular border of TM2. Asp 
113 is homol-
ogous to the Torpedo nACh receptor ␣1 subunit Glu 
83 locus 
and is modeled as forming a ring of negative charge within the 
apical extracellular vestibule (Fig. 1). Asp 
113 was mutated to 
either a neutral asparagine or a positively charged lysine, within 
the 5-HT3A(QDA) construct, yielding 5-HT3A(QDA) D113N 
or 5-HT3A(QDA) D113K, respectively. At a holding potential 
of Ϫ80 mV in extracellular (E1) and intracellular solutions con-
taining Na 
ϩ and Cs 
ϩ as the principal charge carriers respec-
tively, 5-HT (10 M) applied by pressure to outside-out patches 
excised from tsA-201 cells expressing 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113N </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Locations of Asp 
113 and Asp 
127 within a homology model of the 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor. A and B, homology model of the human 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor using the nACh receptor of Torpedo marmorata as a 
template (Protein Data Bank entry 2BG9 (9)). The locations of Asp 
113 (D113) 
and Asp 
127 (D127) within the ECD are shown in side (A) and top (B) elevations. 
Note how the residues form two rings of charge that face into the central 
vestibule within the ECD. C, sequence alignment of the ␣1 subunit of the 
human adult skeletal muscle nACh receptor and human 5HT3A subunit 
across the relevant region of the proteins. </p>

<p>The ECD of the 5-HT 3 A Receptor Influences Channel Biophysics </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 18 • MAY 6, 2011 </p>

<p>mutant receptors elicited clearly resolvable single channel 
events. By comparison with the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor con-
struct previously characterized under identical ionic conditions 
(20), inwardly directed single channel currents mediated by the 
5-HT3A(QDA) D113N construct are effectively halved in 
amplitude, the chord conductance (␥) being reduced from 41.2 
pS to 22.2 Ϯ 0.3 pS (Fig. 2, A and B, and Table 1). The 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113K receptor displayed a ␥ value that was </p>

<p>further reduced to 17.1 Ϯ 0.2 pS (Fig. 2, A and B, and Table 1). 
Although the ␥ value of the D113N and D113K 5-HT3A(QDA) 
constructs did not differ strikingly, the reduction caused by 
reversal, rather than neutralization, of charge was significantly 
greater (Table 1). 
Single channel current-voltage (i-V) relationships were gen-
erated by recording unitary currents evoked by 5-HT (10 M) 
from outside-out patches at holding potentials between Ϫ100 
and ϩ100 mV in increments of 20 mV. For the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) 
receptor construct, the single channel current i-V relationship 
is linear at negative potentials with a slope ␥ of 41 pS (20). 
However, at positive potentials, ␥ increases to 46 pS, indicative 
of modest outward rectification quantified as an RI value (see 
"Experimental Procedures") of 1.12 (20) (Fig. 2B). Under iden-
tical ionic conditions, the i-V relationships obtained for the 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113N and the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113K receptor 
constructs reveal that both mutations enhance outward rectifi-
cation, the RI values being 1.7 and 2.63, respectively (Table 1). 
Notably, either mutation reduced only inwardly (and not out-
wardly) directed single channel currents (Fig. 2B). Such results 
are consistent with a scheme whereby the ring of negativity 
formed by the Asp 
113 residues acts via simple coulombic attrac-
tion to raise the availability of cations within the receptor extra-
cellular vestibule for translocation to deeper regions of the 
pore. Neutralization or reversal of charge at this locus would be 
anticipated to reduce the local concentration of cations within 
the extracellular vestibule, leading to the emergence of outward 
rectification. Notably, the effect of neutralizing or reversing the 
charge at the Asp 
113 position was increased when [Na 
ϩ ] o was 
reduced to 95 mM (see below) (see Fig. 5). In comparison with 
the 46 and 58% reductions in ␥ found for the D113N and D113K 
mutations, respectively, with [Na </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>] o set at 146 mM, the corre-
sponding reductions in the Na 
ϩ -deficient solution were 66 and 
72%. The enhanced effect of the mutations at the lower ionic 
strength is once more consistent with a predominantly electro-
static influence of the Asp 
113 residue. This is due to the screen-
ing effect of oppositely charged ions upon amino acid residues 
that have fixed charges that would reduce the influence of the 
Asp 
113 residue at high ionic strength. 
Asp 
127 Is a Major Determinant of ␥ and Influences Single 
Channel Current Rectification-Asp 
127 is predicted from a 
homology model of the human 5-HT 3 A receptor (18) to reside 
approximately two-thirds of the distance from the entrance to 
the extracellular vestibule to the extracellular border of TM2 
(i.e. the 20Ј residue) and occupies a locus homologous to that of 
the Asp 
97 residue of the Torpedo nACh receptor ␣1 subunit 
(Fig. 1). Application of 5-HT (10 M) to outside-out patches 
expressing the human 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127N receptor con-
struct yielded relatively small, yet clearly resolvable, single 
channel currents at a holding potential of Ϫ80 mV, yielding a 
chord ␥ of 7.3 Ϯ 0.1 pS (Fig. 3, A and B, and Table 1). Neutral-
ization of the negative charge of the 127 residues thus reduces ␥ 
by 82% in comparison with the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor. Con-
sistent with a contribution of an electrostatic influence upon 
inwardly directed cation flux, the D127N mutation within the 
5-HT3A(QDA) construct confers a strong outwardly rectifying 
(RI ϭ 3.18) i-V profile, as determined from single channel cur-
rents recorded between the holding potentials of Ϫ100 and </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Neutralization, or reversal, of charge at the Asp 
113 locus 
depresses inwardly directed single channel currents. Single channel 
events, elicited by 5-HT (10 M), were recorded from outside-out patches 
excised from tsA-201 cells transfected with the construct of interest. The Cs 
ϩ -
based pipette solution and extracellular solution E1 were utilized. A, exemplar 
single channel events recorded at Ϫ80 and ϩ80 mV from the 5-HT 3 A(QDA), 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113N, and 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113K mutant receptors. B, i-V pro-
files for the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) (solid circles), 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113N (open circles), and 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113K (inverted triangles) receptors. Note that mutation of the 
Asp 
113 residue does not impact upon outwardly directed single channel cur-
rents. Data points are the mean of a minimum of three observations made 
from separate patches, and error bars, where visible, indicate S.E. Data for the 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor are from Livesey et al. (20). </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
The influence of mutations within the extracellular domain (ECD) 
upon ␥ and single channel current rectification </p>

<p>Single channel currents evoked by 5-HT (10 M) were recorded from outside-out 
membrane patches bathed in Na </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>-containing extracellular medium (solution E1) 
and Cs </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>-based intracellular solution. Chord ␥ values were determined at a holding 
potential of Ϫ80 mV. ND, not determined. </p>

<p>Receptor constructs 
␥ 
n 
Rectification index </p>

<p>pS </p>

<p>5-HT 3 A(QDA) 
41.2 Ϯ 1.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>8 
1.12 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113N 
22.2 Ϯ 0.3 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>9 
1.7 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113K 
17.1 Ϯ 0.2 </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>8 
2.63 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127N 
7.4 Ϯ 0.1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>3 
3.18 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127K 
1.6 Ϯ 0.3 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>6 
ND </p>

<p>a Data reported previously by Livesey et al. (20). 
b Significantly different (p Ͻ 0.001) from the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) mutant receptor, as 
determined by one-way ANOVA with post hoc Dunnett's test. 
c Significantly different (p Ͻ 0.001) from the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113N mutant recep-
tor construct, as determined by unpaired t test. </p>

<p>The ECD of the 5-HT 3 A Receptor Influences Channel Biophysics </p>

<p>MAY 6, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 18 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 16011 </p>

<p>ϩ100 mV at 20-mV increments (Fig. 3B). However, unlike 
mutations at the 113 locus, the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127N receptor 
mediated outwardly directed single channel currents that were 
clearly depressed in comparison with the 5-HT3A(QDA) con-
struct (Fig. 3B). In addition, the effect of the D127N mutation 
was not enhanced when [Na </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>] o was reduced to 95 mM. It is 
likely that the role of Asp 
127 extends beyond that of locally 
concentrating cations within the extracellular vestibule. 
In contrast to the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127N receptor, individual 
single channel events in response to 5-HT (10 M) were not 
discernible when recording at a holding potential of Ϫ80 mV 
from membrane patches expressing the 5-HT3A(QDA) D127K 
construct (Fig. 3A). Instead, a noisy "macroscopic-like" inward 
current evoked by 5-HT was observed, which is reminiscent of 
that previously reported for the human wild-type 5-HT 3 A 
receptor in a similar experimental paradigm (31). To estimate 
the ␥ value of the channels underlying such currents, we 
employed fluctuation analysis of 5-HT-evoked macroscopic 
currents from whole cells voltage-clamped at a holding poten-</p>

<p>tial of Ϫ80 mV, as described previously (16, 27). Such an anal-
ysis yielded a ␥ of 1.65 Ϯ 0.3 pS (Table 1). Outwardly directed 
single channel events mediated by the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127K 
receptor construct in outside-out patches at holding potentials 
as positive as ϩ80 mV were also unmeasurable by direct obser-
vation (data not shown). We were unable to obtain an estimate 
of ␥ by fluctuation analysis of whole-cell currents at such posi-
tive potentials due to a poor signal/noise ratio. Thus, the 127 
locus appears to be a major determinant of both inward and 
outward conduction of cations. 
The Influence of the 5-HT 3 A Receptor Extracellular Vestibule 
upon Ion Selectivity-The suppression of the ␥ of the 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor by the mutations at the 113 and 127 
loci suggests that the residues naturally occupying these posi-
tions participate in the concentration of cations within the 
extracellular vestibule. In addition, residues within the 5-HT 3 A 
receptor cytoplasmic portals, also distant from the TM2 region, 
have been shown to influence ion permeability, namely to Ca </p>

<p>2ϩ </p>

<p>(20). Thus, we sought to examine whether mutations in the 
extracellular vestibule influence the permeabilities of Ca </p>

<p>2ϩ </p>

<p>with respect to Cs 
ϩ (P Ca /P Cs ), Na 
ϩ with respect to Cs 
ϩ (P Na / 
P Cs ), and Na 
ϩ with respect to Cl 
Ϫ (P Na /P Cl ). 
Asp 
113 and Asp 
127 Affect neither Cation versus Anion Selec-
tivity nor Relative Permeability to Monovalent Cations-Dilu-
tion potential experiments were performed in order to deter-
mine P Na /P Cl . In such experiments, Na 
ϩ replaced Cs 
ϩ as the 
permeant monovalent cation that dialyzed the cell interior. A 
whole-cell voltage ramp protocol (see "Experimental Proce-
dures") was employed to obtain E 5-HT values for the extracellu-
lar domain mutants in the presence of variable [Na 
ϩ ] o (146, 95, 
and 20 mM; solutions E1, E3, and E6, respectively), where Na </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>was replaced with sucrose to maintain osmolarity. Plots of 
E 5-HT versus the logarithm of extracellular Na 
ϩ activity 
((Na </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>) o ) were generated to examine the cation versus anion 
selectivity of each of the extracellular domain mutants. No 
appreciable perturbation of charge selectivity was observed in 
comparison with the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor (slope of 59 
mV/decade change in (Na 
ϩ ) o (20)) because the slopes were 
found to be 55.6, 59.5, 57.4, and 57.5 mV/decade change in 
(Na </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>) o for the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113N, 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113K, 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127N, and 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127K receptors, 
respectively (data not shown). The GHK voltage equation pre-
dicts a slope of 58 mV/decade change in (Na 
ϩ ) o (at room tem-
perature) for a channel that is perfectly selective for monova-
lent cations. 
P Na /P Cs determined similarly was generally unaffected at 
5-HT3A(QDA) constructs carrying mutations to the Asp </p>

<p>113 </p>

<p>and Asp 
127 residues, although the 5-HT3A(QDA) D113N 
(0.78 Ϯ 0.02) and 5-HT3A(QDA) D127K (1.02 Ϯ 0.03) con-
structs exhibited modestly shifted, but significantly different, 
ratios compared with the 5-HT3A(QDA) construct (0.87 Ϯ 
0.03). However, the sign of the charge at the 113 and 127 loci 
had no consistent effect upon P Na /P Cs (Table 2). 
Asp 
113 and Asp 
127 Are Determinants of P Ca /P Cs -The pre-
ceding data suggest that Asp 
113 and Asp 
127 are involved in the 
selection of cations within the extracellular vestibule, and they 
would be anticipated to favor the attraction of Ca 
2ϩ over mon-
ovalent cations, potentially increasing the relative permeability </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. The 5-HT3A(QDA) D127N construct single channel i-V relation-
ship. Single channel current events were recorded from excised outside-out 
patches in extracellular solution E1 and the Cs 
ϩ -based pipette solution. 
A, exemplar currents recorded at Ϫ80 mV from the 5-HT3A(QDA), 
5-HT3A(QDA) D127N, and 5-HT3A(QDA) D127K constructs. Note that the lat-
ter construct does not support resolvable single channel events in response 
to 5-HT. B, single channel i-V relationships for the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) construct 
(filled squares) and the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127N mutant receptor (open circles). 
Note that the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127N receptor mediated single channel cur-
rents that rectify outwardly but are additionally substantially reduced at pos-
itive holding potentials. Data points are the mean of at least three indepen-
dent determinations, and error bars, where visible, indicate S.E. Data for the 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor are from Livesey et al. (20). </p>

<p>The ECD of the 5-HT 3 A Receptor Influences Channel Biophysics </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 18 • MAY 6, 2011 </p>

<p>of the channel to the divalent. To evaluate this possibility, P Ca / 
P Cs values were derived from measurements of E 5-HT made 
from whole-cell currents activated during a voltage ramp by 
5-HT (10 M) in the presence of extracellular solution E2, con-
taining 100 mM [Ca 
2ϩ ] o as the sole cationic charge carrier, and 
the Cs 
ϩ -based intracellular solution. The 5-HT 3 A(QDA) 
D113N and 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113K receptors yielded E 5-HT val-
ues of Ϫ11.7 Ϯ 1.1 and Ϫ22.7 Ϯ 1.8 mV, which, when com-
pared with the 5-HT3A(QDA) construct (ϩ9.4 mV) (20), indi-
cates a substantially decreased relative permeability to Ca </p>

<p>2ϩ </p>

<p>(Fig. 4, A-C). Quantitatively, the corresponding P Ca /P Cs ratios 
calculated from a modified form of the GHK voltage equation 
(30) were 1.04 Ϯ 0.08 and 0.60 Ϯ 0.06 (Table 2), both signifi-
cantly less than the value of 3.8 found for the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) 
receptor construct (20). 
Pronounced negative shifts in E 5-HT were found for the 
5-HT3A(QDA) Asp 
127 mutant constructs in the Ca 
2ϩ -based 
extracellular solution E2. As such, modifications to the conven-
tional voltage-ramp protocol employed in this study were 
required. In brief, E 5-HT for the 5-HT3A(QDA) D127N con-
struct was determined by ramping the membrane potential 
over a period of 1 s from ϩ40 to Ϫ100 mV and returning to ϩ40 
mV during the peak of a macroscopic current evoked by 5-HT 
(10 M). The resultant leak-subtracted current exhibited a large 
negative shift in E 5-HT (Ϫ55.6 Ϯ 1.2 mV) compared with that of 
the 5-HT3A(QDA) construct (ϩ9.4 mV), yielding a significant 
reduction of P Ca /P Cs from 3.8 to 0.13 Ϯ 0.01 (Table 2 and Fig. 
4D). For the 5-HT3A(QDA) D127K mutant, a similar voltage 
ramp protocol, but spanning the potential range ϩ40 to Ϫ150 
mV, yielded leak-subtracted whole-cell currents with an E 5-HT 
value (Ϫ74.6 Ϯ 5.4 mV) markedly negative to that of both the 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) and 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127N receptor constructs 
(Fig. 4E). The calculated P Ca /P Cs value is 0.06 Ϯ 0.01 (Table 2), 
which implies that the D127K mutant is effectively imperme-
able to Ca 
2ϩ . 
The Effect of Neutralization and Charge Reversal Mutations 
at the 113 and 127 Loci upon Suppression of 5-HT3A(QDA) ␥ by 
Extracellular Ca 
2ϩ -The ␥ of the human wild-type 5-HT 3 A 
receptor and the 5-HT3A(QDA) construct are depressed by 
extracellular Ca 
2ϩ (20, 27). For the 5-HT3A(QDA) construct, 
such suppression is concentration-dependent over the range 
0.1-30 mM and voltage-independent over the range 0.3-10 mM 
in the presence of a [Na </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>] o fixed at 95 mM (20). The predomi-
nant suppression of ␥ by [Ca 
2ϩ ] o is chiefly observed over the 
concentration range 0.1-10 mM (extracellular solutions E3, E4, </p>

<p>and E5; see Fig. 5). In view of the pronounced influence of the 
extracellular vestibule mutants upon the P Ca /P Cs ratio of the 
5-HT3A(QDA) construct, the effect of extracellular Ca 
2ϩ on 
the ␥ of the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor mutated at either the 
Asp 
113 or Asp 
127 position was investigated with [Ca 
2ϩ ] o set at 
0.1, 1, or 10 mM in the presence of a [Na </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>] o of 95 mM. 
In order to accurately calculate chord ␥ values, E 5-HT for each 
channel construct in each ionic condition was determined by a 
voltage ramp protocol (see "Experimental Procedures") applied 
to macroscopic currents (individual values are reported in Fig. </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
The influence of mutations within the extracellular domain (ECD) upon the permeabilities of Ca 
2؉ and Na 
؉ relative to Cs </p>

<p>؉ </p>

<p>Relative permeabilities (i.e. P Ca /P Cs and P Na /P Cs ) were determined from measurements of E 5-HT in extracellular solutions containing Na 
ϩ (solution E1) or Ca 
2ϩ (solution E2) 
as the permeant cation. </p>

<p>Receptor constructs </p>

<p>E 5-HT of Na 
؉ extracellular 
solution E1 
P Na /P Cs 
n </p>

<p>E 5-HT of Ca 
2؉ extracellular 
solution E2 
P Ca /P Cs 
n </p>

<p>mV 
mV </p>

<p>5-HT 3 A(QDA) 
Ϫ2.1 Ϯ 0.7 
0.87 Ϯ 0.03 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>21 
10.1 Ϯ 1.2 
3.85 Ϯ 0.3 
17 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113N 
Ϫ4.9 Ϯ 0.5 
0.78 Ϯ 0.01 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>15 
Ϫ11.6 Ϯ 1.1 
1.04 Ϯ 0.08 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>6 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113K 
Ϫ4.1 Ϯ 0.9 
0.80 Ϯ 0.03 
7 
Ϫ22.7 Ϯ 1.8 
0.60 Ϯ 0.06 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>8 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127N 
Ϫ4.3 Ϯ 1.0 
0.80 Ϯ 0.03 
8 
Ϫ55.8 Ϯ 1.2 
0.13 Ϯ 0.01 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>6 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127K 
2.1 Ϯ 0.9 
1.02 Ϯ 0.03 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>8 
Ϫ74.6 Ϯ 5.4 
0.06 Ϯ 0.01 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>a Includes data from Livesey et al. (20). 
b Significantly different (p Ͻ 0.01) from the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) construct, as determined by one-way ANOVA on ranks with post hoc Dunn's test. 
c Significantly different (p Ͻ 0.001) from the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) construct, as determined by one-way ANOVA with post hoc Dunnett's test. </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Macroscopic I-V relationships for 5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor con-
structs harboring mutations to Asp 
113 and Asp 
127 within the ECD. I-V 
plots were generated by the voltage ramp protocols detailed under "Experi-
mental Procedures," and 5-HT (10 M)-evoked currents were recorded in an 
extracellular medium containing Ca 
2ϩ as the sole permeant ionic species. 
Representative leak-subtracted whole-cell currents are shown for 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) (A), 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113N (B), 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113K (C), 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127N (D), and 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127K (E) receptor constructs. 
Note that all mutations cause a negative shift in E 5-HT that is indicative of a 
reduced P Ca /P Cs ratio. Paralleling the latter is an enhancement of outward 
rectification of the macroscopic currents due to a progressively diminished 
ability to conduct Ca 
2ϩ inwardly. </p>

<p>The ECD of the 5-HT 3 A Receptor Influences Channel Biophysics </p>

<p>MAY 6, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 18 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 16013 </p>

<p>5A). Single channel current amplitudes were recorded at a 
holding potential of Ϫ80 mV from excised outside-out patches. 
For the 5-HT3A(QDA) D113N construct, an increase in 
[Ca 
2ϩ ] o from 0.1 to 10 mM had no significant effect upon ␥, 
which was 13.9 Ϯ 1.0 and 11.4 Ϯ 0.7 pS, respectively (Fig. 5B). 
Reversal of charge at the Asp 
113 locus by substituting lysine 
resulted in a channel that similarly displayed only a marginal, 
although significant, suppression of ␥ over the 100-fold 
increase in [Ca </p>

<p>2ϩ </p>

<p>] o (i.e. 11.5 Ϯ 0.3 to 9.8 Ϯ 0.3 pS) (Fig. 5B). The 
single channel current amplitudes observed for the 
5-HT3A(QDA) D127N mutant in extracellular solutions com-
posed of Na 
ϩ /Ca 
2ϩ mixtures displayed a low signal/noise ratio, </p>

<p>and thus the sensitivity of ␥ to increased [Ca 
2ϩ ] o cannot be 
evaluated with precision. Despite this, an elevation of extracel-
lular [Ca 
2ϩ ] o from 0.1 mM (␥ ϭ 6.6 Ϯ 0.4 pS) to 10 mM (␥ ϭ 
4.6 Ϯ 0.5 pS) appeared to have no significant effect upon ␥ (Fig. 
5). The 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127K receptor construct was not 
investigated due to its very low ␥. Collectively, mutation of 
Asp 
113 to asparagine and lysine and Asp 
127 to asparagine mark-
edly suppresses the sensitivity of ␥ to [Ca 
2ϩ ] o that is a charac-
teristic of the both the wild-type human 5-HT 3 A receptor (27) 
and the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor construct (20). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The results of this study demonstrate that both Asp 
113 and 
Asp 
127 within the ECD of the 5-HT3A(QDA) receptor have a 
profound effect upon the (i) amplitude of inwardly directed 
single channel currents, (ii) relative permeability to Ca 
2ϩ , and 
(iii) modulation of ␥ by extracellular Ca 
2ϩ . It should be empha-
sized that we have utilized the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor as a 
convenient model system and that not all effects described here 
can readily be extrapolated to the human wild-type 5-HT 3 A 
receptor. For example, the reduction in amplitude of inwardly 
directed single channel currents caused by the neutralization or 
reversal of charge at the Asp 
113 and Asp 
127 cannot be translated 
directly to the wild-type receptor whose ␥ is already severely 
limited by Arg 
432 , Arg 
436 , and Arg 
440 within the large intracel-
lular loop (16, 17). 
All atoms molecular dynamics simulations performed on a 
homology model of the adult human skeletal muscle 
((␣1) 2 ␤1␦⑀) nACh receptor reveal that monovalent cations 
undergo stepwise changes in position as they translocate along 
the axis of the extracellular vestibule to the extracellular 
entrance of the transmembrane pore (22). Specifically, Na </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>dwells for several ns in the vicinity of rings of acidic and polar 
residues that correspond to Glu 
83 and Asp 
97 of the ␣1 subunit, 
and there is direct experimental evidence that ␣1Asp 
97 and 
residues at equivalent positions in the ␤1, ␦, and ⑀ subunits 
influence ␥ in the adult human skeletal muscle nACh receptor 
(22, 26). Glu 
83 and Asp 
97 align with Asp 
113 and Asp 
127 of the 
human 5-HT 3 A receptor (Fig. 1), providing the rationale for 
our mutagenesis program. 
Effects upon ␥-Neutralization of the negative charge at the 
113 or 127 loci by the replacement of aspartate with asparagine 
produced a very substantial reduction in the amplitude of 
inwardly directed single channel currents corresponding to 
decreases in chord ␥ of 46 and 82%, respectively. It is notable 
that neutralization of the charge at the 127 position of the 
5-HT3A(QDA) construct produces a percentage reduction in ␥ 
that closely approximates the effect of reversing the charge at 
the position corresponding to Asp 
97 in all subunits of the adult 
skeletal muscle nACh receptor (26). When we mimicked the 
latter study more closely by the mutation D127K incorporated 
into the 5-HT3A(QDA) construct, 5-HT-evoked single chan-
nel currents could not be observed directly, but a noisy inward 
current was recorded from patches, confirming that the muta-
tion did not ablate receptor expression. By fluctuation analysis 
of whole-cell currents mediated by the 5-HT3A(QDA) D127K 
mutant, we inferred a ␥ of ϳ1.6 pS. Fluctuation analysis applied 
to various 5-HT 3 A receptor mutants tends to underestimate </p>

<p>FIGURE 5. Mutations in the ECD of the 5-HT3A(QDA) construct attenuate 
suppression of ␥ by extracellular Ca 
2؉ . A, exemplar single channel currents 
for the 5-HT3A(QDA), 5-HT3A(QDA) D113N, 5-HT3A(QDA) D113K, and 
5-HT3A(QDA) D127N constructs recorded from outside-out patches held at 
Ϫ80 mV using the Cs 
ϩ -based patch pipette solution and an extracellular solu-
tion containing 95 mM [Na 
ϩ ] o and either 0.1 mM (solution E3), 1 mM (solution 
E4), or 10 mM (solution E5) [Ca 
2ϩ ] o . Note that the mutations alleviate the 
suppression of single channel currents by Ca 
2ϩ in comparison with the 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor. The mean E 5-HT Ϯ S.E. for each construct in such solu-
tions are given beneath the appropriate currents with n values in parenthesis. 
B, single channel conductance versus Ca 
2ϩ activity ((Ca 
2ϩ ) o ) for the 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) (filled circles), 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D113N (open circles), 5-HT 3 A(QDA) 
D113K (inverted solid triangles), and 5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127N (inverted open trian-
gles) receptor constructs. Single channel conductances were calculated using 
the values for E 5-HT given in A. Data points indicate the mean of 3-6 single 
channel amplitude measurements from separate patches, and error bars 
depict S.E. Shown is statistical significance compared with that obtained for 
the 0.1 mM Ca 
2ϩ , 95 mM Na 
ϩ mixture, as determined by one-way ANOVA with 
post hoc Dunett's test (* and ***, p Ͻ 0.05 and p Ͻ 0.001, respectively). Data for 
the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor are from Livesey et al. (20). </p>

<p>The ECD of the 5-HT 3 A Receptor Influences Channel Biophysics </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 18 • MAY 6, 2011 </p>

<p>the true ␥ revealed by single channel recording (17), and, 
extrapolating from previous correlative data, the ␥ of the 
5-HT3A(QDA) D127K mutant could be closer to 3 pS. None-
theless, by comparison with the D127K mutation, the substitu-
tion of aspartate by lysine at the 113 locus was better tolerated 
and caused only a modest decrease in ␥ further than that pro-
duced by charge neutralization (from 22 to 17 pS). 
A parsimonious interpretation of the effect on ␥ of the muta-
tions at the 113 position is through a simple electrostatic mech-
anism. First, the i-V data obtained with both the D113N and 
D113K constructs show that the mutations exclusively depress 
inwardly directed single channels in comparison with the 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor, introducing outward rectification to 
the i-V relationship. The degree of rectification increased as the 
charge at the 113 locus was neutralized (5-HT3A(QDA) 
D113N, RI ϭ 1.70) or reversed (5-HT3A(QDA) D113K, RI ϭ 
2.63). Such an effect is consistent with Asp 
113 acting to increase 
the local concentration of cations within the outer extracellular 
vestibule, facilitating their onward translocation to deeper 
regions of the pore. Simple electrostatic interactions are sensi-
tive to ionic strength, due to the screening of fixed charges by 
counterions (32). Although we did not examine the influence of 
ionic strength in a systematic manner (as elegantly performed 
by Kienker et al. (32) for the skeletal muscle nACh receptor 
harboring mutations in the extracellular (20Ј) and cytoplasmic 
(Ϫ4Ј) rings), we note parenthetically that the percentage 
depression of ␥ caused by the D113N and D113K mutations was 
more pronounced when [Na 
ϩ ] o was reduced from 146 to 95 
mM. Attempts to evaluate the influence of lower concentrations 
of [Na 
ϩ ] o were unsuccessful due to reductions in ␥ that ren-
dered quantification unreliable. 
The affect of mutations at the 127 locus was more complex. 
Although inwardly directed single channel currents were 
reduced to a greater extent than outwardly directed events by 
the D127N mutation (RI ϭ 3.18), suppression of ␥ was apparent 
over a wide range of potentials (Ϫ100 to ϩ100 mV). Unlike the 
D113 mutant, the percentage reduction of the amplitude of 
inwardly directed currents was not increased at reduced ionic 
strength, at least not within the limits examined. Strikingly, the 
D127K mutation reduced ␥ to a value that could not be deter-
mined directly at both negative and positive holding potentials. 
That the effect of mutations at the 127 locus upon inward cur-
rents is more pronounced than at the 113 position is not sur-
prising because the former ring of charge is positioned closer to 
the entrance of the transmembrane region of the pore (Fig. 1). 
Furthermore, it is likely that the position of the 127 residue at 
the tip of the ␤4/5 loop (26, 33) causes it to protrude into the 
vestibule, forming a ring of charge that may be narrower than 
that present at the 113 locus. Indeed, this appears to be the case 
for the aligned region of the Torpedo nACh receptor (9). How-
ever, we refrain from attempting to specify the diameters of the 
forgoing rings because our homology model (Fig. 1) is based on 
the pseudosymmetrical structure of the Torpedo nACh recep-
tor and probably does not reflect with sufficient accuracy the 
fine structure of the homo-oligomeric 5-HT 3 A receptor. 
The data obtained with the 5-HT3A(QDA) D127N construct 
are inconsistent with solely a through-space electrostatic effect 
whereby the Asp 
127 residue simply elevates the local concentra-</p>

<p>tion of cations within the vestibule. Interestingly, Hansen et al. 
(26) demonstrated that suppression of ␥ in the adult human 
muscle nACh receptor is a non-linear function of the net charge 
upon the Asp 
97 ring and that two sets of mutations that resulted 
in the same change in net charge (i.e. the introduction of three 
lysine and two alanine residues versus the insertion of four 
lysine and retention of one aspartate residue) had significantly 
different effects upon ␥. Thus, the side chain substitutions and 
their locations within the mutant subunits of the nACh recep-
tor are at least as important as the net charge on the ring (26). In 
the present study, we observed the suppression of outwardly 
directed single channel currents by the D127N mutation, which 
would not be anticipated if the Asp 
127 residue served only to 
elevate the concentration of permeant cations within the extra-
cellular vestibule. The molecular dynamics simulations per-
formed by Wang et al. (22) upon the adult muscle nACh recep-
tor reveal that cations are stabilized by the homologous Asp </p>

<p>97 </p>

<p>residue within the adult muscle nACh receptor. Such stabiliza-
tion indicates the presence of an energy well that would be 
anticipated to affect both inward and outward ionic move-
ments. Energy wells within the extracellular vestibule are also 
apparent as negative vestibular pore potentials computed for 
the Torpedo nACh receptor (23, 24). We speculate that the 
decrease or possibly reversal in pore potential caused by the 
D127N and D127K mutations, respectively, removes a force 
that facilitates both inwardly and outwardly directed ion fluxes 
or introduces a barrier against such movements. 
Effects upon Charge Selectivity-None of the mutations 
examined in this study had a significant impact upon the charge 
selectivity of the 5-HT3A(QDA) receptor construct, as mea-
sured by the ratio P Na /P Cl . Such results are not surprising. First, 
it has been shown that mutating the inner (Ϫ1Ј) ring of charge 
of the mouse 5-HT 3 A receptor from glutamate to alanine ren-
ders the channel essentially non-selective between cations and 
anions (P Na /P Cl ϭ 0.89) (34). When combined with the 19Ј 
mutation Ser 3 Arg, the channel gained modest anion selec-
tivity (P Na /P Cl ϭ 0.37) (34). Second, extracellularly applied ani-
onic methanethiosulfonate reagents react with cysteine resi-
dues engineered into the mouse 5-HT 3 A receptor at multiple 
locations within the TM2 domain, demonstrating that anions 
can penetrate the extracellular vestibule (35, 36). Finally, 
Brownian dynamics simulations conducted upon the Torpedo 
nACh receptor indicate that although the extracellular vesti-
bule contains a much higher concentration of Na 
ϩ than Cl </p>

<p>Ϫ </p>

<p>, 
the latter is not excluded (24). 
Effects upon Valence Selectivity-In sharp contrast to the 
negative results found for charge selectivity, both the Asp </p>

<p>113 </p>

<p>and Asp 
127 residues were found to have a marked influence 
upon relative permeability to Ca 
2ϩ , as reflected in the ratio 
P Ca /P Cs , previously reported to be 3.8 for the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) 
receptor construct (20). For the D113N, D113K, D127N, and 
D127K mutations, P Ca /P Cs ratios were calculated to be 1.04, 
0.60, 0.13, and 0.06, respectively. It is notable that the decreases 
in P Ca /P Cs parallel the decrements in ␥ caused by such muta-
tions. At each locus, the suppression of P Ca /P Cs increased as the 
negative charge was neutralized or reversed, consistent with a 
simple through-space electrostatic effect. We attribute the 
greater influence of the Asp 
127 residue, in common with its </p>

<p>The ECD of the 5-HT 3 A Receptor Influences Channel Biophysics </p>

<p>MAY 6, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 18 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 16015 </p>

<p>effect upon ␥, as probably being due to its deeper location 
within the pore of the extracellular vestibule and inclusion 
within a narrower ring of charge. Permeant ion species would 
thus be concentrated in proximity to the entrance of the trans-
membrane pore. 
For the ␣7 nACh receptor, it has long been known that muta-
tions at the Ϫ1Ј (inner ring), 16Ј, and 17Ј loci exert a profound 
influence upon P Ca /P Na (15). Similarly, reductions in the nega-
tive charge at the Ϫ1Ј locus of the ␣4␤2 and ␣3␤4 nACh recep-
tors greatly reduces P Ca /P Na (37). Placing the present data in 
context, the D127K and D127N mutations produced effects 
upon relative permeability to Ca 
2ϩ of a magnitude comparable 
with or greater than those reported in the above studies. Asp </p>

<p>127 </p>

<p>appears to be a residue that is critical for the translocation of 
Ca 
2ϩ into the transmembrane pore of the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) 
receptor construct. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first 
report to identify residues within the N-terminal outer vesti-
bule of a pLGIC that influence valence selectivity. Moreover, 
the data add to those of our previous report illustrating relative 
permeability to Ca 
2ϩ in the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor to be influ-
enced at multiple sites that include the extracellular (20Ј) ring 
of charge and residues within the intracellular MA stretch (i.e. 
Arg </p>

<p>436 </p>

<p>) (20). Others (34) have inferred a role for the Ϫ1Ј (inner 
ring) in Ca 
2ϩ permeation based on Ca 
2ϩ imaging assays con-
ducted upon the mouse wild-type 5-HT 3 A receptor. Collec-
tively, the data are consistent with a processional movement of 
Ca 
2ϩ from the extracellular to the intracellular environment, 
where multiple negatively charged residues along the axis of the 
permeation pathway facilitate the inward translocation of the 
ion. It should be noted that the occurrence of positive charge 
(i.e. lysine) at a position most likely homologous to Asp 
127 does 
not prevent permeability to Ca 
2ϩ in ␣1 glycine receptors 
mutated within TM2 and flanking sequences to impart cation 
selectivity (38). 
Effects upon Suppression of ␥ by Extracellular Ca 
2ϩ -Extra-
cellular Ca </p>

<p>2ϩ </p>

<p>, within the concentration range 0.1-10 mM, 
causes a concentration-dependent reduction of the ␥ of the 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor construct, amounting to a suppression 
of ϳ50% (20). By contrast, [Ca 
2ϩ ] o over the same concentra-
tion range had no significant effect upon the ␥ of either the 5-
HT 3 A(QDA) D113N (range 13.9 to 11.4 pS), or 
5-HT 3 A(QDA) D127N (range 6.6 to 4.8 pS), receptor con-
structs. An elevation of [Ca 
2ϩ ] o caused a statistically significant 
depression of the ␥ of the 5-HT3A(QDA) D113K mutant, but 
the effect was modest (range 11.5 to 9.8 pS). We could not 
evaluate the influence of [Ca 
2ϩ ] o upon the 5-HT3A(QDA) 
D127K construct due to its low ␥. Collectively, the data indicate 
that neutralization or reversal of charge at the Asp 
113 or the 
Asp 
127 loci alleviates suppression of ␥ by extracellular Ca 
2ϩ . 
As noted previously, the molecular dynamics stimulations of 
Wang et al. (22) indicate that monovalent cations are stabilized 
at residues homologous to Asp 
113 and Asp 
127 in the adult mus-
cle nACh receptor. From simple considerations of coulombic 
attraction, an even greater degree of stabilization of Ca 
2ϩ would 
be anticipated. The outer vestibule is sufficiently wide (9) to 
accommodate multiple Ca 
2ϩ ions, which, stabilized therein, 
would exert a repulsive force upon monovalent cations moving 
either inwardly or outwardly, thereby depressing ␥. The loca-</p>

<p>tion of the Asp 
113 and Asp 
127 residues outside of the transmem-
brane voltage field is consistent with the voltage-independent 
nature of the block by extracellular Ca 
2ϩ (20). We envisage that 
mutations that neutralize or reverse charge at the 113 and 127 
loci reduce the stabilization of Ca 
2ϩ within the vestibule and 
thus alleviate block by extracellular Ca 
2ϩ . It is notable that 
mutations at either location appear sufficient to reduce the 
influence of Ca 
2ϩ upon ␥. It is possible that the primary site at 
which Ca 
2ϩ is stabilized is the Asp 
127 position, with the Asp </p>

<p>113 </p>

<p>residue acting to facilitate the translocation of the divalent to 
the former site. Such an effect would be consistent with the 
observation that mutations at the 113 position have a more 
modest effect on P Ca /P Cs than those at the 127 locus, which in 
the case of the D127K substitution renders the channel virtually 
impermeable to Ca 
2ϩ . However, it is evident that for either 
mutation, the data show a tendency to a residual suppression of 
␥ by Ca </p>

<p>2ϩ </p>

<p>, perhaps suggesting additional site(s) of action within 
the conduction pathway. We have previously excluded the 
extracellular (20Ј) ring of charge as such a candidate (20). 
Conclusions-The extracellular vestibule within the pLGIC 
family forms the initial obligatory pathway in the translocation 
of ions from the extracellular to intracellular environment (9). 
The results herein indicate that the extracellular vestibule of 
the 5-HT 3 A(QDA) receptor contains at least two rings of neg-
ative charge that strongly impact upon ␥ and P Ca /P Cs and sup-
pression of ␥ by extracellular Ca 
2ϩ . By inference, homologous 
residues in other subunits within the pLGIC family might be 
anticipated to have similar functions, with the caveat that such 
extrapolation is from a receptor construct already modified by 
mutations within the large intracellular loop. In particular, vir-
tually all cation-selective eukaryotic pLGICs contain aspartate 
at a position equivalent to the 127 locus (exceptions are the 
nACh ␣3 and ␣6 subunits), whereas the aligned residue or an 
adjacent residue in the anion-selective members is lysine (3). 
Thus, the sign of the residue at this position is appropriate to 
the charge selectivity of the pLGIC and indeed the simultane-
ous mutation of Lys 
104 and Gly 
105 to alanine and aspartate (the 
aligned residues in the nACh ␣1 subunit) in the ␣1 glycine 
receptor has very recently been shown to depress ␥ (39). By 
contrast, the residue aligned to the 113 locus in cation-selective 
pLGICs is poorly conserved and presents as either a neutral, 
polar, acidic, or basic, but not hydrophobic, residue, suggesting 
that the importance of this position may vary across the recep-
tor family. It is probable that other residues within the ECD 
influence receptor biophysics, a prominent candidate being ␣1 
Asn 
47 of the nACh receptor of adult skeletal muscle highlighted 
in the molecular dynamics simulations of Wang et al. (22). In 
addition, it has already been mentioned by Bernal et al. (40) that 
mutation of the bovine nACh ␣7 Lys 
145 residue (aligned with 
5-HT3A(QDA) Val 
154 ) to alanine is associated with a modest 
but significant increase in ␥. Moreover, it has recently been 
reported that the dual mutation D57I and R59T within the ␣1 
glycine receptor significantly reduces ␥ (39). In aggregate, it is 
now evident, for both cation-and anion-selective pLGICs, that 
to fully account for the biophysical properties of ion perme-
ation, amino acids residing within the TM2/TM1-TM2 linker 
region, the cytoplasmic portals, and the extracellular vestibule 
must be considered collectively. </p>

<p>The ECD of the 5-HT 3 A Receptor Influences Channel Biophysics </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 18 • MAY 6, 2011 </p>

<p>Acknowledgment-We are grateful to Tim G. Hales for critical com-
ments upon a draft of the manuscript. </p>



<p>The ECD of the 5-HT 3 A Receptor Influences Channel Biophysics </p>

<p>MAY 6, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 18 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 16017 </p>

</text></tei>