<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3285716" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: The transobturator adjustable tape (TOA) allows adjustment of tension after 
surgical intervention, thus permitting correction of postoperative incontinence or 
obstruction. The aim of this study was to compare the efficacy and safety of TOA versus 
transobturator tape (TOT) for the treatment of stress urinary incontinence with in-
trinsic sphincter deficiency (ISD). 
Materials and Methods: Patients underwent TOA (n=33 with ISD) or TOT (n=47 with 
ISD) insertion by one experienced surgeon. The patients were considered to have ISD 
on the basis of a Valsalva leak point pressure ＜60 cmH2O or a maximum urethral clo-
sure pressure ＜20 cmH2O. The preoperative evaluation included history taking, phys-
ical examination, voiding diary, stress and 1-hour pad tests, and a comprehensive ur-
odynamic examination. Postoperative evaluation included a stress test, 1-hour pad 
test, questionnaire, and uroflowmetry with postvoid residuals. 
Results: After 6 months of follow-up, the rate of cure (TOA, 75.6% vs. TOT, 72.3%) was 
similar between the two groups. The rate of satisfaction was not significantly higher 
in the TOA group than in the TOT group (84.8% vs. 78.7%; p=0.05). Four patients in 
the TOA group (12.1%) needed a reduction in tension because of urinary obstruction 
(flow ＜10 ml/sec and/or residual urine ＞50 ml). The tension of the mesh was tightened 
in 5 patients (15.2%) because of the persistence of a certain degree of incontinence. The 
residual urine volume at postoperative 7 days was significantly lower in the TOA group 
than in the TOT group (19.5 ml vs. 41 ml; p=0.016, repeated-measures analysis of var-
iance test). 
Conclusions: The TOA allows postoperative readjustment of the suburethral sling pres-
sure for a number of days after surgical intervention, which allows for the achievement 
of good short-term results. These data suggest that better lower obstructive voiding 
symptoms than those achieved with the traditional nonadjustable mesh can be ob-
tained with the TOA. </p>

<p>Mid-urethral sling procedures have been found to be a safe 
and effective treatment of choice in stress urinary incon-
tinence (SUI). Although the tension-free vaginal tape (TVT) </p>

<p>procedure is considered to be the gold standard with ex-
cellent long-term efficacy [1], serious complications have 
been reported with this technique, including vascular and 
bowel injuries [2]. To minimize these complications, an al-
ternative procedure called the tension-free obturator tape </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2012;53:98-103 </p>

<p>Efficacy of TOA Sling Procedure with Intrinsic Sphincter Deficiency </p>



<p>(TOT) procedure was developed in which the tape is in-
troduced through the obturator foramen [3]. The TOT proce-
dure has been shown in several randomized comparative 
studies to be as safe and effective in the surgical treatment 
of stress urinary incontinence as the TVT technique [4,5]. 
However, in a minority of women with stress incontinence, 
stress incontinence surgery may result in failure owing to 
the presence of hidden intrinsic sphincter deficiency (ISD), 
mixed incontinence, hormonal changes, or age-related colla-
gen alteration. The success rates of the tension-free sling in 
women with SUI with ISD range from 24 to 84%, although 
the results were reported differently in research on the suc-
cess of treatment of anatomical urinary incontinence [6,7]. 
Some articles on TVT for intrinsic sphincter deficiency show 
satisfactory outcome with rates of 73 to 91% [8-10]. TOT has 
been used for the treatment of SUI patients along with TVT, 
but there have been only a few reports on its outcomes for 
SUI with ISD. Costantini et al. [11] reported that the cure 
rate of the TOT procedure was 77.3% in women with ISD. 
The most common problem in sling surgery has been ex-
cess tension, and concern over postoperative bladder outlet 
obstruction has led to the development of a number of meth-
ods for determining the proper tension. Thus, the trans-
obturator adjustable tape (TOA) was developed to reduce 
these complications. The adjustable transobturator tape 
has been shown to allow for adjustment of tension for sev-
eral days after surgical intervention, thus permitting cor-
rection of postoperative symptoms. Therefore, it has the 
advantages that urinary retention can be achieved and in-
continence can be minimized [12]. 
In this study, we present a retrospective comparison after 
short-term follow-up of the effectiveness for SUI with ISD 
of the TOA and TOT procedures performed by one urologist. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>1. Patient group 
Patients underwent TOA (n=33 with ISD) or TOT (n=47 
with ISD) performed by one experienced surgeon between 
January 2007 and December 2009. Each patient under-
went one of two techniques (TOA; A.M.I TOA Sling, Agency 
for Medical Innovations GmbH, Austria; TOT, Dowmedics 
Co., Wonju, Korea) in accordance with the scheduling 
order. Subjects were considered to have ISD identified by 
a Valsalva leak point pressure (VLPP) measurement ＜60 
cmH2O in the sitting position with a volume of 150 ml in 
the bladder or by a maximum urethral closure pressure 
(MUCP) measurement ＜20 cmH2O in the sitting position 
with a volume of 200 ml in the bladder [13,14]. Patients 
with neurological disorders or detrusor overactivity were 
excluded from this protocol. Additional minor exclusion 
factors were chronic degenerative diseases that would af-
fect muscular and nerve tissues, advanced genital pro-
lapses, and active or recurrent urinary tract infections. We 
excluded patients who had pelvic prolapse greater than 
stage I on the International Continence Society grading 
system. </p>

<p>2. Study design 
All patients were given a routine workup for incontinence, 
including history, physical examination, stress cough test, 
standard 1-hour pad test, uroflowmetry, post-void residual 
(PVR) urine measurement, and complete multi-channel 
urodynamic study. All medical charts were retrospectively 
reviewed for certain data, including age, body weight, 
height, urodynamic study, and type of suburethral tape. 
We reviewed complications, postoperative urinary symp-
toms, and outcomes. During the pelvic examination, the se-
verity of the vaginal wall defect was determined by using 
the pelvic organ prolapse quantification system [15]. 
The stress cough test was performed with the patient in 
the standing position with 300 ml bladder filling. Urodyna-
mic study was performed with the patient in a birthing 
chair at a 45-degree angle. After catheterization, cystom-
etry was performed by using a Laborie 8 Fr double-lumen 
urodynamic catheter at a fill rate of 50 ml/min. First desire, 
strong desire, and maximal cystometric capacity were 
recorded. The VLPP, a measurement of the lowest abdomi-
nal pressure required to produce urine leakage, was also 
recorded. The VLPP was obtained with the subject seated 
when the total infused volume of sterile water reached 300 
ml. Routine postoperative follow-up for all patients in-
cluded office visits at postoperative 7 days and at 3 and 6 
months. At postoperative 7 days, patients underwent a 
stress cough test and uroflowmetry and residual urine vol-
ume measurement. At the 3-and 6-month follow-up, a 
1-hour pad test was added to the previous tests. Objective 
outcomes were assessed with the cough stress test and 
1-hour pad test. SUI cure was defined as no leakage of urine 
during cough stress testing and a pad weight gain of less 
than 2 g on a 1-hour pad test during the follow-up visit. 
Improvement was defined as a more than 50% reduction 
of urine weight on a 1-hour pad test and a positive result 
on the stress cough test. Failure was defined as less than 
a 50% reduction on a 1-hour pad test and a positive result 
on the cough stress test. Subjective outcomes were classi-
fied as very satisfied, satisfied, fair, or dissatisfied. Pati-
ents who checked 'very satisfied' or 'satisfied' were placed 
in the satisfaction group. Urinary obstruction was defined 
as a flow ＜10 ml/s and/or residual urine ＞50 ml. Groin and 
thigh pain was another potential problem after trans-
obturator sling operations. Severe pain was defined as the 
presence of pain still requiring analgesic therapy 1 week 
after surgery. </p>

<p>3. Operation technique 
TOA is a macroporous, polypropylene, monofilament 
non-elastic-type tape. The TOA method is similar to the 
TOT procedure. The TOA tape is situated below the 
mid-urethra via a small incision in the anterior vaginal 
wall. Two strings on either side are situated 1.5 cm from 
the midline of the tape, which is externalized via the ante-
rior vaginal wall. When it is pulled down to reduce tension, 
the TOA group is formed of three strings in each branch of 
the tape situated at the same distance from both thighs. </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2012;53:98-103 </p>



<p>Oh et al </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Patient characteristics of the TOT and TOA groups </p>

<p>TOT (n=47) TOA (n=33) 
p-value </p>

<p>Age 
Body weight (kg) 
Height (cm) 
Menopause (%) 
Parity 
1-hour pad test (g) 
VLPP (cmH2O) 
MUCP (cmH2O) 
Max flow rate (ml/s) 
Residual urine (ml) 
POPQ system of 
cystocele 
Stage 0 
Stage 1 
Stage 2-3 </p>

<p>54.7±1.3 
63.1±1.1 
154.8±0.9 
28 (59) 
2.6±0.1 
18.1±1.8 
79.0±3.3 
29.5±2.3 
23.0±1.1 
19.8±3.4 </p>

<p>35 (74) 
12 (26) 
0 (0) </p>

<p>54.6±1.6 
61.2±1.4 
156.2±0.9 
19 (59) 
2.4±0.2 
17.7±2.2 
84.8±3.9 
29.8±3.1 
22.5±1.3 
17.2±3.4 </p>

<p>25 (76) 
8 (24) 
0 (0) </p>

<p>0.97 
0.28 
0.30 
1.00 
0.61 
0.89 
0.26 
0.93 
0.75 
0.61 
0.51 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±SD or number (%). 
Data are presented as Mean± SEM. Numbers in parentheses are 
percentages. 
TOT, transobturator tape; TOA, transobturator adjustable tape; 
VLPP, valsalva leakage pressure point; MUCP, maximum ure-
thral closure pressure; POPQ, pelvic organ prolapse quantifica-
tion system. </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Changes in uroflowmetric parameters at postoperative 7 days and 6 months </p>

<p>Preoperative 
value </p>

<p>Postoperative 
value (7 days) 
p-value 
Postoperative 
value (6 months) 
p-value </p>

<p>Max flow rate (ml/s) 
TOT 
TOA 
Residual urine (ml) 
TOT 
TOA 
Flow time (s) 
TOT 
TOA </p>

<p>23.0±7.2 
22.5±7.7 </p>

<p>19.8±23.3 
17.3±19.4 </p>

<p>23.4±7.2 
22.5±6.1 </p>

<p>20.0±7.4 
21.6±9.2 </p>

<p>41.3±35.6 
19.5±37.1 </p>

<p>25.2±7.8 
24.6±6.1 </p>

<p>0.725 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.85 </p>

<p>21.4±8.7 
22.0±6.9 </p>

<p>39.4±31.5 
18.7±28.2 </p>

<p>24.7±7.4 
26.1±7.2 </p>

<p>0.697 </p>

<p>0.031 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.78 </p>

<p>Values are presented as Mean±SEM. 
TOT, transobturator tape; TOA, transobturator adjustable tape. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>: Significant (＜0.05), repeated-measures analysis of variance test. </p>

<p>These are externalized via the same orifice through which 
the mesh is, when pulled up, to increase the tension. The 
tension is adjusted with minimal tension by placing scis-
sors between the tape and the urethra. The plastic envelope 
is removed, and the redundant portion of the mesh is cut. 
Depending on the distance from the urethra to the skin, one 
or two of the lateral superior strings are also cut. Cystos-
copy was performed during the procedure. The Foley cathe-
ter was removed the next day, and the patients underwent 
studies that included measurements of flow rate and PVR 
before being discharged home. </p>

<p>4. Statistical analyses 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 15.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA) was used </p>

<p>for statistical analyses. Comparison of baseline patient 
characteristics as well as baseline uroflowmetric parame-
ters was performed by using the independent t-test and 
chi-square test. The repeated-measures analysis of var-
iance (ANOVA) test was used to compare changes in clin-
ical outcomes between the two groups. Statistical sig-
nificance was set at p＜0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>A total of 80 participants underwent the TOA procedure 
(n=33) or the TOT procedure (n=47). In the TOT group, 22 
of the 47 patients had low VLPP (＜60 cmH2O), and 29 of 
the 47 patients had low MUCP (＜20 cmH2O). In the TOA 
group, 14 of the 33 patients had low VLPP (＜60 cmH2O), 
and 20 of the 33 patients had low MUCP (＜20 cmH2O). 
There were no significant differences in preoperative char-
acteristics between patients in the TOA and TOT groups 
(Table 1). The operating time was 22.7±2.3 minutes in the 
TOT group and 23.5±2.4 minutes in the TOA group (mean± 
SD). The mean hospitalization duration was 3.1 days in the 
TOT group and 3.3 days in the TOA group. There was no 
significant difference. 
Uroflowmetry tests performed before and after surgery 
showed that flow in the TOT group ranged from 23.0±7.2 
ml/sec to 20.0±7.4 ml/sec and that in the TOA group ranged 
from 22.5±7.7 ml/sec to 21.3±9.2 ml/sec (Table 2). No stat-
istically significant differences were found in the change 
in maximal urine flow rate between the two groups. 
However, the change in residual urine volume was sig-
nificantly lower in the TOA group than in the TOT group 
(19.5 ml vs. 41 ml, p=0.016, repeated-measures ANOVA 
test). There was no definite difference in voiding volume or 
maximal urine flow between the two groups. At post-
operative 6 months, the change in maximal urine flow rate, 
voiding volume, and residual urine volume was similar at 
postoperative 7 days. 
Postoperative complications are shown in Table 3. 
Vaginal wall injury occurred in 2 patients (4.3%) in the TOT </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2012;53:98-103 </p>

<p>Efficacy of TOA Sling Procedure with Intrinsic Sphincter Deficiency </p>



<p>TABLE 3. Comparison of operation-related complications bet-
ween the TOT and TOA groups </p>

<p>TOT (n=47) 
TOA (n=33) </p>

<p>Perioperative complications 
Urethral perforation 
Vaginal wall injury 
Early postoperative 
complications (until 1 week) 
Hematoma 
Thigh or groin pain 
UTI 
Obstructive voiding symptom 
Late postoperative complications 
(3 months) 
Vaginal and urethral erosion 
Obstructive voiding symptom </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0 (0) 
2 (4.3) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
5 (10.6) 
0 (0) 
10 (21.3) </p>

<p>2 (4.3) 
4 (8.5) </p>

<p>1 (3.0) 
0 (0) </p>

<p>0 (0) 
2 (6.1) 
0 (0) 
5 (15.2) </p>

<p>1 (3.0) 
1 (3.0) </p>

<p>Values are presented as no. of frequencies (percentages). 
TOT, transobturator tape; TOA, transobturator adjustable tape; 
UTI, urinary tract infection. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>: Flow ＜10 ml/s and/or residual urine ＞50 ml. </p>

<p>TABLE 4. Objective and subjective success rates of the TOT and 
TOA groups at postoperative 6 months </p>

<p>TOT (n=47) 
TOA (n=33) </p>

<p>Objective result 
Negative cough test 
Post-op pad test (g) 
＜2 g 
≥2 g 
Subjective result 
Very satisfied 
Satisfied 
Faired 
Dissatisfied </p>

<p>37 (78.7) </p>

<p>34 (72.3) 
13 (27.7) </p>

<p>31 (66.0) 
6 (12.8) 
6 (12.8) 
4 (8.5) </p>

<p>27 (81.8) </p>

<p>25 (75.6) 
8 (24.4) </p>

<p>21 (63.6) 
7 (21.2) 
3 (9.1) 
2 (6.1) </p>

<p>Values are presented as frequencies (percentages). 
TOT, transobturator tape; TOA, transobturator adjustable tape. </p>

<p>group and urethral perforation occurred in 1 patient (3.0%) 
in the TOA group. We promptly repaired the vaginal wall 
injury, and the patient with urethral perforation was 
catheterized for 3 days. There were no cases of wound in-
fection, tape erosion, or urinary tract infection (white blood 
cell count ＞5 in urine analysis) in either group. Six pa-
tients (18.2%) in the TOA group tended to still have con-
tinuing groin pain 1 day after surgery. The incidence of 
such pain was 10.6% of the TOT group compared with 6.1% 
of the TOA group 7 days after surgery. The cause of these 
results may have been that with the TOA procedure the 
strings remained until the end of the adjustment period. 
The patients received analgesic agents for 7 days. Four pa-
tients in the TOA group had improved pain 1 week after sur-
gery, and two patients (6.1%) had improved pain 4 weeks 
after surgery. Postoperative urinary obstruction was seen 
in 10 patients (21.3%) in the TOT group at the 1-week fol-
low-up visit. Four patients (8.5%) in the TOT group had per-
sistent obstructive voiding symptoms (flow rate ＜10 ml/sec 
and/or residual urine ＞50 ml) at the 6-month follow-up 
visit. These patients still showed no improvement, so we 
performed urethrolysis at 6 to 12 months after surgery. 
Four patients in the TOA group (12.1%) required a reduc-
tion in tension due to urinary obstruction (flow ＜10 ml/sec 
and/or residual urine ＞50 ml) after postoperative day 1. 
In 5 patients (15.2%) in the TOA group, the tension of the 
mesh was tightened because of a certain degree of continu-
ing incontinence after postoperative day 1. One patient 
(3.0%) in the TOA group had a complication of urethral ob-
struction at 5 months after surgery; this case required ure-
throlysis at 6 months after surgery. 
Table 4 shows the objective and subjective outcomes of 
both groups 6 months after surgery. Notably, no statisti-
cally significant differences were found between the two </p>

<p>types. The overall cure rate was 75.6% at 6 months in the 
TOA group vs. 72.3% in the TOT group. The satisfaction 
rate was higher in the TOA group than in the TOT group 
(84.8% vs. 78.7%). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Surgical failure rates increase 4 to 6-fold when there is evi-
dence of ISD (MUCP ＜20 cmH2O or VLPP ＜60 cmH2O at 
capacity) [16]. In one study, Hsiou et al. [17] retrospectively 
analyzed 61 cases of TVT and 60 cases of TOT and found 
that low MUCP (＜40 cmH2O) was an independent risk fac-
tor for sling failure for the TOT group but not the TVT 
group. On the contrary, in ancillary studies from two sepa-
rate RCTs comparing TVT with TOT [11,18], no significant 
differences in objective stress incontinence cure rates in 
ISD cases based on a VLPP of 60 cmH2O or less were 
reported. Surgical failure occurred in 8 of 25 patients (32%) 
in the TOT group compared with 6 (24%) of 25 patients in 
the TVT group (p＞0.05). In another report, Barber found 
no significant association between low VLPP and recurrent 
stress incontinence in a multivariate analysis. However, 
it must be pointed out that both studies contained only be-
tween 14 and 25 ISD patients in each arm and consisted 
of only one patient who had both ISD and fixed urethra. On 
ultrasound assessment, Long et al. [19] compared TVT and 
the transobturator tape (TVT-Obturator) and showed that, 
at rest or during Valsalva, the middle of the TVT-Obturator 
tape localized more distally than the TVT (p=0.01). A high-
er rate of urethral kinking during straining was observed 
in the TVT group than in the TVT-Obturator group after 
surgery (86.9% compared with 23.9%, p=0.01). Also, the 
subjective cure rate was significantly lower for the TVT-
Obturator group than for the TVT group (82.4 vs. 93.4%, 
p=0.042) [19]. The difference was because the mesh tape 
of the TOT, which was more horizontally placed, lacked 
support because it wrapped a smaller part of the urethra 
in comparison with that wrapped by the TVT [7]. The cur-
rent literature would thus suggest that ISD-related SUI in-</p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2012;53:98-103 </p>



<p>Oh et al </p>

<p>creases the surgical failure rate and that mid-urethral 
slings placed retropubically have a higher success rate 
than do those placed with a transobturator approach. In the 
present study, the overall cure rate was 75.6% at 6 months 
in the TOA group vs. 72.3% in the TOT group. The high cure 
rate of the TOA procedure resulted from the adjustable sys-
tem after the immediate postoperative period. The sat-
isfaction rate was higher in the TOA group than in the TOT 
group (84.8% vs. 78.7%). 
In a study by Rezapour et al. [8], the success rate was 86% 
after TVT surgery for SUI with ISD. In an observational, 
retrospective, multicenter study, Lee et al. [20] recently 
evaluated pre-and intraoperative factors that might affect 
long-term (5-year) success rates of the TVT procedure in 
155 consecutive patients with SUI. They found that 64 pa-
tients with abdominal leak point pressure ≥60 cmH2O had 
significantly higher cure rates than did 31 patients with ab-
dominal leak point pressure ＜60 cmH2O (82.8 vs. 51.6%, 
respectively; p=0.003). The success cure rate of the TVT 
procedure with ISD varies from 52 to 86%; we noted a sim-
ilar success rate in both the TOA group with ISD in our pres-
ent study and in the other article's TVT group with ISD. 
The overall goal of the sling operation is to produce ad-
equate urethral resistance to prevent stress incontinence, 
allowing voluntary and complete bladder emptying. The 
two most frequent problems after stress incontinence sur-
gery are persistence of incontinence and voiding dysfunc-
tion, both of which are related to how loose or how tight the 
tape is implanted [21]. Slings that are too tight are asso-
ciated with voiding dysfunction and de novo urge incon-
tinence. Slings that are too loose may still allow stress 
incontinence. Although most urinary retention resolves 
with conservative treatment, including medication, ure-
thral dilation, or intermittent catheterization, refractory 
urethral obstruction ultimately requires midline or lateral 
excision of the tape [22]. If SUI reappears or the patient suf-
fers persistence of urinary leakage after surgery, we will 
need to perform a new intervention to correct it. However, 
the success rate of incontinence reoperations is between 
20% and 40% lower than that of first-time operations, and 
these procedures present a greater number of complica-
tions [23]. In the present study, 13 patients (27.7%) in the 
TOT group had undergone urethral pull-down after post-
operative 1 day. In urethral pull-down, a Hegar dilator is 
inserted in the urethra and pulled down with the aim of 
moving downward and loosening the tape in the TOT 
group. In four patients in the TOA group (12.1%), it was nec-
essary to reduce tension due to urinary obstruction (flow 
＜10 ml/sec and/or residual urine ＞50 ml) after post-
operative day 1. Tension is released from the mesh by pull-
ing down on one side only of the vaginal strings, approx-
imately 1 cm [24]. 
The patients were checked again by uroflowmetry and re-
sidual urine volume after 3 hours. If the patients showed SUI 
in the cough stress test, then we immediately pulled up the 
strings on each side approximately 0.5 cm. Continence was 
tested, and the procedure was repeated until the patient was </p>

<p>continent with a maximum flow rate equal to or greater than 
10 ml/s and when there was less than 50 ml of residual urine. 
The strings were cut and extracted, and the patient was 
discharged. In the present study, the change in residual 
urine volume was significantly lower in the TOA group than 
in the TOT group at postoperative 1 week (19.5 ml vs. 41 ml, 
p=0.016, repeated-measures ANOVA test). Four patients 
(8.5%) in the TOT group had persistent obstructive voiding 
symptoms (flow rate ＜10 ml/sec and/or residual urine ＞50 
ml) at the 3-month follow-up visit. One patient (3.0%) in the 
TOA group had a complication of urethral obstruction at 5 
months after surgery. These patients still showed no im-
provement, so we performed urethrolysis at 6 to 12 months 
after surgery. We think that the adjustable transobturator 
tape allowed for adjustment of tension for several days after 
surgical intervention, thus significantly reducing urethro-
lysis. 
The reported complication rates range from 4.3% to 
75.1% for retropubic and 10.5 to 31.3% for transobturator 
mid-urethral slings. Complications include bladder perfo-
ration, hemorrhage, bowel injury, vaginal extrusion, uri-
nary tract infections, and voiding dysfunction. Retropubic 
mid-urethral slings lead to a higher occurrence of complica-
tions such as bladder perforation (0.7 to 24% vs. 0.5%) and 
hematoma (0.7 to 8% vs. 0% to 2%). In addition, the retro-
pubic approach results in serious complications such as 
bowel injury, major vascular injury, and death [25]. Groin 
pain was more common after the transobturator approach. 
A randomized controlled study from Finland revealed that 
16% of women in the transobturator (inside-to-outside) 
arm had groin pain compared with 1.5% of those in the TVT 
arm, which led to an increased need for analgesia in the 
transobturator group [26]. In the present study, groin pain 
occurred in 2 (6.1%) patients. 
A recent large retrospective series of TVT revealed ure-
thral erosion in 0.3% of cases [26]. Although rare, erosion 
of mesh into the urethra can occur after the transobturator 
approach. Urethral erosions are believed to occur because 
of poor surgical technique that could damage the integrity 
of the urethral tissue or its blood supply, excessive tension 
placed on the tape, or local infection. There were no major 
complications, and no urethral erosion or infection was 
identified. However, the recommendation for cystoscopy 
after passage of the trocars cannot be overemphasized, be-
cause these complications can be treated promptly in the 
operation field. Vaginal erosion occurred in one patient, 
and it was located in the lateral fornix. After local excision, 
it healed without further consequences. The percutaneous 
strings did not seem to increase the risk of tape infection. 
The results of the present study suggest that TOA is an 
effective and simple procedure for treating female stress uri-
nary incontinence with ISD, because the procedure had min-
imal complications and a high success rate. The TOA proce-
dure allows postoperative adjustment of the sling tension. 
This sling system allows the surgeon to leave the sling very 
loose at the time of surgery with the ability to tighten or loos-
en the sling easily in the postoperative period to achieve con-</p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2012;53:98-103 </p>

<p>Efficacy of TOA Sling Procedure with Intrinsic Sphincter Deficiency </p>



<p>tinence and still maintain adequate voiding function. The 
present study was limited in that the study targeted a small 
number of subjects and the follow-up period was short. This 
study suggests that more subjects and a longer follow-up pe-
riod are needed for more specific evaluation. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>The TOA procedure allows postoperative adjustment of the 
suburethral sling pressure for a number of days after surgi-
cal intervention, which allows the achievement of good 
short-term results. These data suggest that better lower 
obstructive voiding symptoms than those achieved with 
the traditional nonadjustable mesh can be obtained. The 
major weakness of this study is its retrospective nature. 
Reassessment with a larger population and a randomized 
controlled trial is required to draw a definite conclusion. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST 
The authors have nothing to disclose. </p>



</text></tei>