<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3598124" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:49+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A b s t r a c t </p>

<p>I 
In nt tr ro od du uc ct ti io on n: : The concept of the study was to compare the morphometry of the 
suprascapular notch (SSN) in females and males because its size and shape may 
be a factor in suprascapular nerve entrapment. 
M 
Ma at te er ri ia al l a an nd d m me et th ho od ds s: : The measurements of 81 scapulae included morpholog-
ical length and width, maximal width and length projection of the scapular spine, 
and width and length of the glenoid cavity. The width-length scapular and gle-
noid cavity indices were calculated. In addition to standard anthropometric mea-
surements three other dimensions were defined and collected for every SSN: 
maximal depth (MD), superior (STD) and middle (MTD) transverse diameters. 
R 
Re es su ul lt ts s: : The analysis of the measurements allowed us to distinguish five types 
of SSN. Type I (26%) had longer maximal depth than superior transverse diam-
eter. Type II (3%) had equal MD, STD and MTD. In type III (57.6%) superior trans-
verse diameter was longer than maximal depth. In type IV (7.4%) a bony fora-
men was present. Type V (6%) was without a discrete notch. Types I and III were 
divided into two subtypes: A (MTD was longer than STD) and B (MTD &lt; STD). 
Distribution of the suprascapular notch types in both sexes was similar. Howe-
ver, MD, STD and MTD were significantly higher in males. The superior trans-
verse suprascapular ligament was completely and partially ossified in 7.4% and 
24.7% respectively. 
C 
Co on nc cl lu us si io on ns s: : The presented classification of the suprascapular notch is simple, 
easy to use, and based on specific geometric parameters which allow one to 
clearly distinguish five types of these structures. All dimensions of SSN were 
significantly higher in males than in females. </p>

<p>K 
Ke ey y w wo or rd ds s: : suprascapular notch, human, variation, female, male. </p>

<p>Suprascapular nerve entrapment is characterized by pain in the pos-
terolateral region of the shoulder, atrophy of the infra-and supraspinatus 
muscles and weakness of the arm's external rotation and abduction. 
Approximately 1-2% of all shoulder pain is caused by this syndrome, and 
therefore can be easily overlooked in the differential diagnoses of shoul-
der discomfort [1-3]. Suprascapular nerve entrapment was first described 
by Kopell and Thompson in 1959 [4]. They reported that abduction or hor-
izontal adduction of the shoulder exerted traction on the suprascapular 
nerve (SN), which led to its compression against the superior transverse 
scapular ligament (STSL). The main site of compression of the suprascapular </p>

<p>C Co or rr re es sp po on nd di in ng g a au ut th ho or r: : 
Michał Polguj 
Department of Normal 
and Clinical Anatomy 
Chair of Anatomy 
Medical University of Lodz 
60 Narutowicza Str. 
90-136 Lodz, Poland 
Phone: +48 42 630 49 49 
E-mail: 
michal.polguj@umed.lodz.pl </p>

<p>Special paper -Anatomical pathology </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Angiology, Chair of Anatomy, Medical University of Lodz, Poland </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Normal and Clinical Anatomy, Chair of Anatomy, 
Medical University of Lodz, Poland </p>

<p>S Su ub bm mi it tt te ed d: : 30 December 2010 
A Ac cc ce ep pt te ed d: : 31 March 2011 </p>

<p>Arch Med Sci 2013; 9, 1: 177-183 
DOI: 10.5114/aoms.2013.33173 
Copyright © 2013 Termedia &amp; Banach </p>



<p>Arch Med Sci 1, February / 2013 </p>

<p>nerve (SN) was the suprascapular notch (SSN), 
which was located at the superior border of the 
scapula, just medial to the base of the coracoid 
process [1, 5]. 
Anatomical variations of the suprascapular notch 
were important as possible predisposing factors for 
compression of the suprascapular nerve in this 
region, especially for individuals who were involved 
in violent overhead activities, such as volleyball pla-
yers and baseball pitchers [2, 6]. 
According to a current professional bibliography 
search, there is not a complete photographically 
documented description of the sexual dimorphism 
of the suprascapular notch based on adequate 
quantitative (measurements of the SSN) material. 
Therefore, the challenge of this study was to gath-
er, analyse and provide photographic documenta-
tion of a large number of specimens. 
The present study, using specific geometric para-
meters, describes a new method of classifying su-
prascapular notch variations. This method is simple, 
easy to reproduce and allows each type to be clearly 
distinguished, so it can be used in further investiga-
tions in ultrasonography or computed tomography. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>A total of 81 dried human scapulas were included 
in the study. The sample consisted of 40 left and 41 
right individuals. All investigations were performed 
in the Chair of Anatomy, the Medical University of </p>

<p>Lodz. The research project and procedures were 
approved by the Bioethics Commission of the Med-
ical University of Lodz (protocol No. RNN/12/10/KE). 
The bones were dated to the second half of the 20 </p>

<p>th </p>

<p>century (1950s). 
The osteometric measurements were carried out 
according to standard definitions and using proce-
dures, precision and equipment as described else-
where [7-10]. Measurements of the scapula were 
made using an electronic digimatic caliper. For con-
sistency, one digimatic caliper was used for all 
measurements, each measurement was made twice 
by one investigator, and the mean of the values 
was taken. Each scapula was measured for the fol-
lowing (Figure 1): 
1. Morphological length (M1), 
2. Morphological width (M2), 
3. Projection length of scapular spine (M7), 
4. Maximal width of scapular spine (M9), 
5. Length of the glenoid cavity (M12), 
6. Width of the glenoid cavity (M13). 
The osteometric measurements and their sym-
bols (M1-M2, M7, M9 and M12-M13), as well as the 
definition of the scapular indices, were taken from 
the standard anthropometry handbook [9] with the 
exception of three suprascapular notch dimensions 
defined as follows (Figures 2-5): 
1. The maximal depth (MD) -the maximum di-
mension of the longitudinal measurements taken 
in the vertical plane from an imaginary line between </p>

<p>Michał Polguj, Kazimierz S. Jędrzejewski, Mirosław Topol </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 1 1. . Osteometric measurements of the scapula </p>

<p>1 -morphological length, 2 -morphological width, 3 -projection length of scapular spine, 4 -maximal width of scapular spine, 
5 -maximal length of glenoid cavity, 6 -width of glenoid cavity </p>

<p>Arch Med Sci 1, February / 2013 </p>



<p>Sexual dimorphism of the suprascapular notch -morphometric study </p>

<p>superior corners of the notch to the deepest point 
of the suprascapular notch. 
2. The superior transverse diameter (STD) -the 
maximum dimension of the horizontal measure-
ments taken in the horizontal plane between cor-
ners of the SSN on the superior border of the sca-
pula. 
3. The middle transverse diameter (MTD) -the di-
mension of the horizontal measurements taken in </p>

<p>the horizontal plane between opposite walls of the 
SSN at half the dimension of MD, perpendicular 
to it. 
The following indices were calculated using given 
values: width-length index (WLI) -WLI = (M2/M1) 
× 100%, and glenoid cavity index (GCI) -GCI = 
(M13/M12) × 100%. 
A photographic technique was used for measu-
rements and typing. The camera and scapula posi-</p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 2 2. . Type I suprascapular notch. Diameters of SSN: A -maximal depth (MD), B -superior transverse (STD), C -middle 
transverse (MTD) </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 3 3. . Type II suprascapular notch. Diameters of SSN: A -maximal depth (MD), B -superior transverse (STD), C -middle 
transverse (MTD) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>A &gt; B 
B &lt; C </p>

<p>A &gt; B 
B &gt; C </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>A = B = C 
A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>



<p>Arch Med Sci 1, February / 2013 </p>

<p>Michał Polguj, Kazimierz S. Jędrzejewski, Mirosław Topol </p>

<p>tions were standardized for all images to obtain an 
anterior view of each scapula. All scapulas were 
fixed with an adjustable clamp and ring stand at 
the same distance from the camera. After digital 
photographic documentation was obtained, three 
dimensions of the suprascapular notch were meas-
ured using MultiScanBase <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v.14.02</rs> software (Com-
puter Scanning System II, Warsaw, Poland). Multi-
ScanBase v. 14.02 is a professional program whose 
functions include visualization, archiving, proces-
sing and analysis of images, with particular empha-
sis on measurement functions. Its advantage is au-
tomation of the process of analysis, even for poor </p>

<p>quality images, allowing measurements of distance, 
density, surface area, and angle. This software has 
been widely used in some research, e.g. measure-
ment of points on the mandible of common shrew 
[11], measurements of Daphniola Radoman shell 
morphometry [12], measurements of the diameters 
and density of vessels [13, 14], and enabling manual 
karyotyping [15]. 
According to the anthropometric rules (Koszelev 
classifications and Olivier classifications) describ-
ing sexual dimorphism, all scapulas were divided 
into three groups: female, male and non-classified 
[9] (Table I). </p>

<p>S St ta at ti is st ti ic ca al l a an na al ly ys si is s </p>

<p>Data analysis was performed using the <rs id="software-2" type="software">Statistica</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">8</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">StatSoft Polska</rs>, Cracow, Poland). Dis-
tribution of continuous variables was investigated 
with the Shapiro-Wilk test in order to check whe-
ther the distribution was normal. Descriptive sta-
tistics were used as the mean and standard deviation 
for continuous variables. The statistical difference 
between the suprascapular notch measurements 
in both sexes were examined using the Mann-Whit-
ney test. A p level of &lt; 0.05 was accepted as sta-
tistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Five types of suprascapular notch were observed 
(Figure 6). Type I (26%) had a longer maximal depth 
(MD) than superior transverse diameter (STD). This </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 4 4. . Type III suprascapular notch. Diameters of SSN: A -maximal depth (MD), B -superior transverse (STD), C -middle 
transverse (MTD) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>A &lt; B 
B &lt; C </p>

<p>A &lt; B 
B &gt; C </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 5 5. . Type IV suprascapular notch </p>

<p>Arch Med Sci 1, February / 2013 </p>



<p>Sexual dimorphism of the suprascapular notch -morphometric study </p>

<p>type was divided into two subtypes: IA and IB (Fig-
ure 2). In IA the middle transverse diameter (MTD) 
was longer than STD, while in IB it was shorter 
(MTD &lt; STD). Type II (3%) had equal maximal depth, 
superior transverse diameter and middle transverse 
diameter (Figure 3). In type III (57.6%) the superior 
transverse diameter was longer than maximal 
depth. This type was divided into two subtypes: IIIA 
and IIIB (Figure 4). In IIIA the middle transverse 
diameter (MTD) was longer than STD, while in IIIB 
it was shorter (MTD &lt; STD). In type IV there was 
a bony foramen (7.4%) (Figure 5). Type V was with-
out a discrete notch (6%) (Figure 7). The frequency 
of the types and subtypes is presented in Figure 6. 
Talking into consideration sex, the maximal notch 
depth (p = 0.009234), middle transverse diameter 
(p = 0.041987) and superior diameter were significan-
tly (p = 0.0027208) higher in males than in females. 
The frequency of subtype IA was lower in fe-
males (9.1%) than in males (14.6%), but in subtype </p>

<p>IB it was higher in females (15.2%) than males (7.3%). 
Also completely ossified superior transverse ligament 
(type IV) was more frequent in females (9.1% vs. 
4.9%). Distribution of other types of the supras-
capular notch in the female and male population was 
very similar. The frequency of types and subtypes in 
males and females is presented in Figure 8. 
The superior transverse suprascapular ligament 
(STSL) was completely or partially ossified in 7.4% 
and 24.7% respectively. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Our investigations were partially similar to the 
ultrasonographic study by Yücesoy et al. [16]. They 
reported that the SSN depth was significantly higher 
in males than in females, but there was no signifi-
cant difference for the notch width between the 
two sexes. However, in our study maximal depth of 
the SSN and its middle and superior transverse </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 7 7. . Type V suprascapular notch </p>

<p>7.40% 
16.10% </p>

<p>9.90% </p>

<p>3% </p>

<p>8.60% </p>

<p>49.00% </p>

<p>6% </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 6 6. . Frequency of the suprascapular notch types </p>

<p>Type IA </p>

<p>Type IB </p>

<p>Type II </p>

<p>Type IIIA </p>

<p>Type IIIB </p>

<p>Type IV </p>

<p>Type V </p>

<p>M Me ea as su ur re em me en nt ts s [ [m mm m] ] 
F Fe em ma al le e 
M Ma al le e </p>

<p>A Av ve er ra ag ge e 
S SD D 
M Mi in n 
M Ma ax x 
A Av ve er ra ag ge e 
S SD D 
M Mi in n 
M Ma ax x </p>

<p>Morphological length 
144.18 
8.14 
130 
162 
165.39 
6.22 
154 
178 </p>

<p>Morphological width 
93.06 
4.53 
79 
101 
105.68 
4.3 
95 
117 </p>

<p>Projection length of scapular spine 
124.91 
5.85 
108 
134 
139.95 
5.07 
125 
149 </p>

<p>Maximal width of scapular spine 
37.9 
4.05 
30 
45 
46.59 
4.04 
37 
56 </p>

<p>Length of the glenoid cavity 
36.09 
2.20 
33 
42 
40.04 
2.97 
32 
48 </p>

<p>Width of the glenoid cavity 
25.65 
1.98 
22 
30 
29.14 
2.14 
25 
34 </p>

<p>Width-length index [%] 
64.65 
3.22 
58.67 69.29 
63.67 
2.82 58.38 71.43 </p>

<p>Glenoid cavity index [%] 
71.88 
5.77 
57.9 81.08 
72.98 
5.34 
61.91 86.84 </p>

<p>Maximal depth of SSN 
5.91 
2.13 
2.00 
12.8 
7.14 
2.60 
1.60 
14.3 </p>

<p>Middle transverse diameter of SSN 
6.91 
1.62 
3.00 
10.8 
8.08 
3.44 
3.50 23.9 </p>

<p>Superior transverse diameter of SSN 
7.48 
1.99 
4.30 
13.2 
8.82 
3.09 
3.90 21.00 </p>

<p>T Ta ab bl le e I I. . Measurements of the scapula </p>

<p>SD -standard deviation, SSN -suprascapular notch. Female (n = 33), male (n = 41) </p>



<p>Arch Med Sci 1, February / 2013 </p>

<p>diameters were significantly higher in males than 
in females. 
In the literature, the incidence of complete ossi-
fication of the superior transverse suprascapular 
ligament (STSL) varies from 3.7% to 12.5% [6, 17-23], 
and our relative percentage was 7.4%. Duparc et al. 
[24] mentioned that in 26.7% the STSL appeared 
calcified and rigid. Dunkelgrun et al. [17] and Ticker 
et al. [21] described partial ossification of this liga-
ment in 18% and 12% respectively, while our rela-
tive percentage was 24.7%. Moriggl [25] mentioned 
that the calcified STSL was a sign of entrapment. 
The size and shape of the suprascapular notch 
may be a factor in suprascapular nerve entrapment 
[17] because narrow SSN has been found in patients 
with this syndrome [26]. Rengachary et al. [20] sta-
ted that the size of the suprascapular notch played 
a role in the predisposition for suprascapular nerve 
entrapment, assuming that a small notch gave a lar-
ger chance of nerve impingement than a large one. 
The SSN typing, apart from the anatomical interest, 
may have clinical significance for suprascapular 
nerve entrapment [27]. 
Rengachary's classification [20] is still used today. 
It classified the SSN into 6 types. Type I was iden-
tical with our type V without a discrete notch. Type 
II was a wide, blunt V-shaped notch, with its max-
imum width along the superior border of the scapu-
la. Type III was a symmetrical U-shaped notch with 
nearly parallel lateral margins. Type IV had a very 
small V-shaped notch. Type V had a U-shaped notch 
and partial ossification of the medial part of the 
STSL, and type VI had a bony foramen with a com-
pletely ossified STSL, identical to our type IV notch. 
In 1998, Ticker et al. [21] conducted a cadaveric 
research study using a different classification sys-
tem, separating the suprascapular notches into two 
types, namely a U-type and a V-type. The degree of 
ossification of the suprascapular ligament was eval-
uated separately. The U-shaped suprascapular 
notch was defined as having approximately paral-
lel sides with a rounded base, and the V-shaped </p>

<p>suprascapular notch was defined as having medi-
al and lateral sides which converge towards a nar-
row base. Next, the degree of ossification of the 
superior transverse scapular ligament was deter-
mined classifying the notches into three groups: no 
ossification, partial ossification, and complete ossi-
fication (resulting in a bony foramen). 
In 2003, Bayramoglu et al. [6] modified the clas-
sification of Rengachary et al. [20] and included only 
the U-and V-shaped notches, and the notch with 
ossification of the STSL. In 2007, Natsis et al. [27] 
described five different types of notches on 423 
dried scapular bones: type I, without a discrete notch, 
35 (8.3%); type II, a notch that was found to be lon-
gest in its transverse diameter, 177 (41.85%); type III, 
a notch that was longest in its vertical diameter, 
177 (41.85%); type IV, a bony foramen, 31 (7.3%); 
type V, a notch and a bony foramen, 3 (0.7%). 
In 2009 Duparc et al. [24] mentioned that a U-shape 
suprascapular notch was seen in 19 shoulders 
(63.3%) and a V-shape notch in 11 (36.7%). In the two 
types, the incisura could be more or less opened, 
narrower or wider. 
The disadvantage of Bayramoglu's et al. [6] and 
Ticker's et al. [21] classifications was that they were 
not based on specific geometric parameters, unlike 
our method. The new classification that we suggest 
simplifies the classification procedure by only requi-
ring three measurements and no further calculations. 
Our method is based on three specific geometric cri-
teria of the notch: maximal depth (MD), middle 
transverse diameter (MTD) and superior transverse 
diameter (STD). Furthermore, it is easy to measure 
these three dimensions on a plain radiograph. 
Dunkelgrun et al. [17] compared Rengachary's 
et al. [20] and Ticker's et al. [21] classifications, and 
in their opinion the suprascapular notch classification 
used by Ticker et al. [21] was more reliable and easy 
to use than the system used by Rengachary. Dunkel-
grun et al. [17] stated that the U-shaped notches 
had a larger area than the V-shaped notches, lead-
ing to the assumption that a V-shaped notch would 
more likely be connected with nerve entrapment. 
The present study aimed to establish a new 
method of classifying the suprascapular notch 
(SSN) morphology, which, contrary to existing meth-
ods, is simple, easy to use, and based on specific 
geometric parameters that clearly distinguish each 
type. Based on this classification, the frequency of 
each type of SSN in females and males was de-
scribed. To our knowledge, the literature contains 
no similar study on this subject based on anthro-
pometric evaluation. The type of notch might then 
be considered in diagnosing the syndrome. The pro-
jection in which the SSN is visualized clearly is the 
anteroposterior projection with the X-ray tube 
angled 15-30°caudally [28]. </p>

<p>Michał Polguj, Kazimierz S. Jędrzejewski, Mirosław Topol </p>

<p>[ [% %] ] </p>

<p>Type IA Type IB Type II Type IIIA Type IIIB Type IV Type V </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 8 8. . Distribution of the suprascapular notch types 
in female and male population </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Female 
Male </p>

<p>9.10 
14.60 
15.20 </p>

<p>7.30 </p>

<p>3.00 
2.40 </p>

<p>9.10 
9.80 </p>

<p>42.40 
48.80 </p>

<p>9.10 
4.90 </p>

<p>12.10 
12.20 </p>

<p>Arch Med Sci 1, February / 2013 </p>



<p>In conclusion, using <rs id="software-3" type="software">MultiScanBase</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">v.14.02</rs> soft-
ware for measurements and typing suprascapular 
notches, we were able to establish a precise clas-
sification of SSN variations, and also, for the first 
time, present their distribution in female and male 
scapulas. 
Although distribution of the suprascapular notch 
types in both sexes was similar, the maximal notch 
depth and middle and superior diameters of SSN 
were significantly higher in males than in females. 
The superior transverse suprascapular ligament, 
as a probable suprascapular nerve entrapment fac-
tor, was completely or partially ossified in 7.4% and 
24.7% respectively. </p>

<p>R e f e r e n c e s </p>



<p>Sexual dimorphism of the suprascapular notch -morphometric study </p>

</text></tei>