<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3334951" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Currently, to our knowledge, quality of output water of 
dental chair units is not covered by specific regulations in the European </p>

<p>Margit Bristela </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Astrid Skolka </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Union, and national recommendations are heterogeneous. In Germany, </p>

<p>Martina 
Schmid-Schwap </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>water used in dental chair units must follow drinking water quality. In 
the United States of America, testing for aerobic heterotrophic bacteria 
is recommended. The present study was performed to evaluate </p>

<p>Eva Piehslinger </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>whether the counts of aerobic heterotrophic bacteria correlate with the </p>

<p>Alexander Indra </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>presence of potentially pathogenic bacteria such as Legionella spp. or 
Pseudomonas aeruginosa. </p>

<p>Günther Wewalka </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Methods: 71 samples were collected from 26 dental chair units with 
integrated disinfection device and 31 samples from 15 outlets of the </p>

<p>Fritz Stauffer </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>water distribution pipework within the department were examined. </p>

<p>1 Bernhard Gottlieb University 
Clinic of Dentistry, </p>

<p>Samples were tested for aerobic heterotrophic bacteria at 35°C and 
22°C using different culture media and for Legionella spp. and for </p>

<p>Department of Fixed and </p>

<p>Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Additionally, strains of Legionella pneumo-</p>

<p>Removable Prosthodontics, </p>

<p>phila serogroup 1 were typed with monoclonal antibodies and repre-</p>

<p>Medical University Vienna, 
Austria </p>

<p>sentative samples of Legionella pneumophila serogroup 1 were typed 
by sequence based typing. </p>

<p>2 Austrian Agency for Health 
and Food Safety (AGES), </p>

<p>Results: Our results showed a correlation between different agars for 
aerobic heterotrophic bacteria but no correlation for the count of aerobic </p>

<p>Institute for Medical </p>

<p>heterotrophic bacteria and the presence of Legionella spp. or Pseudo-
monas aeruginosa. </p>

<p>Microbiology and Hygiene, 
National Reference Centre </p>

<p>Conclusion: Testing for aerobic heterotrophic bacteria in output water 
or water distribution pipework within the departments alone is without </p>

<p>for Legionella Infection, 
Vienna, Austria </p>

<p>any value for predicting whether the water is contaminated with poten-</p>

<p>3 Bernhard Gottlieb University 
Clinic of Dentistry, Hospital </p>

<p>tially pathogenic bacteria like Legionella spp. or Pseudomonas aeru-
ginosa. </p>

<p>Hygiene, Medical University 
Vienna, Austria </p>

<p>Keywords: dental chair unit, water, disinfection, Legionella spp., 
Pseudomonas aeruginosa, aerobic heterotrophic bacteria </p>

<p>Zusammenfassung </p>

<p>Hintergrund: Entsprechend unserer Kenntnis sind die Anforderungen 
an austretendes Wasser in Wasser führenden Elementen von Dental-
einheiten in keiner Europäischen Richtlinie geregelt. Nationale Empfeh-
lungen sind heterogen. In Deutschland muss in Detaleinheiten einge-
speistes Wasser der Trinkwasserverordnung entsprechen. In den Verei-
nigten Staaten wird die Überprüfung auf aerobe heterotrophe Bakterien 
jedoch empfohlen. Das Ziel der vorliegenden Studie war es zu überprü-
fen, ob die Zahl aerober heterotropher Bakterien mit der Anwesenheit 
potentiell pathogener Erreger wie Legionella spp. oder Pseudomonas 
aeruginosa korreliert. 
Methoden: 71 Proben von 26 Dentaleinheiten mit integrierter Desinfek-
tionsanlage und 31 Proben von 15 Wasserauslässen des Wasserversor-</p>

<p>1/8 
GMS Krankenhaushygiene Interdisziplinär 2012, Vol. 7(1), ISSN 1863-5245 </p>

<p>Research Article </p>

<p>OPEN ACCESS </p>

<p>gungsnetzes einer Zahnbehandlungsabteilung wurden untersucht. 
Sämtliche Proben wurden auf Vorhandensein von aeroben heterotrophen 
Bakterien bei 35°C und 22°C sowie auf das Vorkommen von Legionella 
spp. und Pseudomonas aeruginosa analysiert. Zusätzlich wurden alle 
Legionella pneumophilia Serogruppe 1 Isolate mittels monoklonalen 
Antikörpern typisiert und ein Teil dieser mittels Sequenzierung moleku-
larbiologisch näher bestimmt. 
Resultate: Die Untersuchung ergab für aerobe heterotrophe Bakterien 
eine Korrelation zwischen den unterschiedlich verwendeten Nährmedien, 
jedoch keine Korrelation zwischen der Anzahl aerober heterotropher 
Bakterien und der Anwesenheit von Legionella spp. oder Pseudomonas 
aeruginosa. 
Schlussfolgerung: Die Untersuchung von aeroben heterotrophen Bak-
terien im Auslasswasser oder Wasser der wasserführenden Systems 
allein ist demzufolge kein Prädiktor für eine Kontamination mit potentiell 
pathogenen Erregern wie Legionella spp. oder Pseudomonas aeruginosa. </p>

<p>Schlüsselwörter: Dentaleinheit, Wasser, Desinfektion, Legionella spp., 
Pseudomonas aeruginosa, aerobe heterotrophe Bakterien </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Dental chair units (DCUs) are equipped with different 
water lines for supplying instruments like handpieces, 
turbines or ultrasonic scalers with cooling water, for 
supplying water/air syringes or for providing the patient 
with water for rinsing the mouth before/after treatment. 
These waterlines have been shown to host biofilms re-
sulting in a high density of microorganisms in output water 
[1], [2], [3]. The clinical relevance of this finding has been 
discussed controversially. A review article including all 
relevant Medline publications for the time from 1996 to 
February 2007 revealed that infections caused by water 
from DCUs represent rare events [4]. However, contam-
ination of water with bacteria should be avoided for 
medico-legal reasons Growth of biofilms in the waterlines 
was shown to depend on the quality of the supply water 
[5]. 
Studies have shown that adding an antimicrobial com-
pound, especially hydrogen peroxide and silver-ion-con-
taining disinfectants, will result in a significant reduction 
of aerobic heterotrophic bacteria in the output water of 
a DCU [6]. Regrowth of these microorganisms can be 
demonstrated already one week after discontinuing the 
disinfectant [6]. 
The guidelines of the Centers for Disease Control and 
Prevention (CDC) and the American Dental Association 
(ADA) established limits of 500 colony-forming units 
(cfu)/ml and 200 cfu/ml, respectively [7], [8]. Tests for 
Legionella spp. or Pseudomonas aeruginosa are only re-
commended in certain situations [8]. The advise to test 
only aerobic heterotrophic bacteria is based on the as-
sumption, that Legionella spp. or Pseudomonas aeru-
ginosa are part of the biofilm. Disinfection of the water 
lines of the DCU should cover the entire biofilm. Therefore 
according to the guideline of the CDC "… no rationale is 
seen for routine testing for such specific organisms" [8]. 
Currently, to our knowledge, there is no European stand-
ard regarding the quality of output water, and national </p>

<p>recommendations are heterogeneous. A symposium held 
at Trinity College, Dublin, Ireland, in September 2006 
reached the consensus that output water quality should 
comply with the ADA standard (&lt;200 cfu/ml). However, 
it was noted that this count should not include human 
pathogens [9]. In Germany, it is recommended that only 
water of drinking water quality may be used in dental 
chair units [10]. 
The present study was intended to evaluate whether the 
count with aerobic heterotrophic bacteria correlates with 
the count of clinically relevant pathogens such as Legion-
ella spp. or Pseudomonas aeruginosa, and whether such 
testing for aerobic heterotrophic bacteria allowed for any 
prediction of bacterial load with Legionella spp. or 
Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Additionally, the Legionella 
pneumophila serogroup 1 strains identified were typed 
with monoclonal antibodies and isolates belonging to the 
same subtype were additionally examined with the se-
quence based typing. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>Seventy-one samples from 26 DCUs and 36 samples from 
15 outlets of the water distribution pipework within the 
departments (three independent water lines) of the 
Bernhard Gottlieb University Clinic of Dentistry were in-
cluded in this evaluation. The DCUs were exclusively 
supplied with drinking water from the Vienna water supply 
system. All DCUs are equipped with an integrated disin-
fection device. The following DCU types are being used 
in the various departments: Sirona C3 (Sirona Dental 
Systems, Bensheim, Germany), Kavo 1062C and 1065T, 
1066R (KaVo Dental GmbH, Biberach/Riß, Germany). 
The setup of the integrated disinfection system shall be 
described for the type Sirona C3 as representative ex-
ample. The system consists of a tank being filled with a 
disinfectant containing hydrogen peroxide and silver ions 
-Dentosept P (1.41% H 2 O 2 and 25 ppm silver ions) / </p>

<p>2/8 
GMS Krankenhaushygiene Interdisziplinär 2012, Vol. 7(1), ISSN 1863-5245 </p>

<p>Bristela et al.: Testing for aerobic heterotrophic bacteria allows ... </p>

<p>Dentosept PL (1.41% H 2 O 2 and 17 ppm silver ions) 
(Metasys Medizintechnik GmbH, Innsbruck; Austria) and 
Oxygenal 6 (6% H 2 O 2 ) (KaVo Dental GmbH, Biberach/Riß, 
Germany) -under control of a level switch. Via a flow 
limiter with solenoid valve the disinfectant is introduced 
into the water-filled mixing tank and its fluid is flushed 
through the lines of the dental unit. 
Samples of 500 ml (corresponding to the bottle marking) 
were collected in sterile plastic bottles with screw cap 
containing sodium thiosulfate (Sterilin </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, Caerphilly, United 
Kingdom). The samples collected from the DCU were 
taken prior to taking the DCU in operation, after 2 minutes 
of waterflow lead time. Sampling was always done in the 
same sequence, starting from the connection end of the 
handpiece, the ultrasonic scaler and the orifice of the 
air/water spray. Samples were collected from 10 DCUs 
at 4 different time points, from 15 DCUs at 2 different 
time points and from 1 dental chair at one time point. 
Water samples from the water distribution pipework 
within the departments were also collected prior to taking 
the DCU in operation. Samples were taken from 4 pipes 
at 4 time points, from 9 pipes at 2 time points, and from 
2 pipes at one time point. 
For the collection at 4 different time points sampling was 
done in October, November, December 2009, and March 
2010, for the collection at 2 different time points in 
December 2009 and March 2010 and for those at one 
time point in December 2009. The samples were trans-
ferred to the laboratory directly after collection and pro-
cessed still on the same day. 
The water samples were tested for aerobic heterotrophic 
colony-forming units using the pour plate method with 
amounts of 1 ml and 1 ml of samples at 1:100 dilution. 
Two different agar media were applied: initially, a yeast 
extract agar (VWR, Darmstadt, Germany) at 36°C for 48 h 
± 4 h and 22°C for 72 h ± 4 h according to EN ISO 6222 
[11], secondly, the R2A agar (Merck, Darmstadt. Ger-
many) at 35°C for 72 h ± 4 h and 120 h ± 4 h as well as 
at 22°C for 120 h ± 4 h and 168 h ± 4 h according to 
US-EPA [12]. For the detection of Pseudomonas aeru-
ginosa a membrane filter method was used. Portions of 
100 ml were filtered through filters with a pore size of 
0.45 µm and transferred onto Pseudomonas selective 
agar with supplement (Oxoid, Hampshire, United King-
dom) for an incubation time of 48 h ± 4 h at 36°C accord-
ing to EN ISO 16266 [13]. Testing for Legionella spp. was 
also done by using a membrane filter method. Portions 
of 10 and 100 ml were filtered though black filters with 
a pore size of 0.45 µm, which were transferred onto a 
GVPC-medium (Biomerieux, Marcy l'Etoile, France). Addi-
tionally, two portions of 0.5 ml were plated on selective 
and non-selective Legionella agar. All plates were incub-
ated at 36°C for at least 168 h ± 4 h according to EN 
ISO 11731-2 [14]. Differentiation of Legionella pneumo-
phila serogroup (Sg) 1, Sg 2-15 and non-pneumophila 
Legionella was done using test sera (Oxoid, Hampshire, 
United Kingdom). Isolates of Sg 1 were further subdivided 
into nine subtypes by application of monoclonal antibod-
ies (MAb) using the "Dresden Panel" [15]. Molecular </p>

<p>typing of L. pneumophila was performed using the con-
sensus sequence-based scheme (SBT) described by Gaia 
et al. [16] and the EWGLI (European Working Group for 
Legionella Infections) SBT database (version 3.0) [17]. 
Isolates of non-pneumophila Legionella spp. were identi-
fied using a sequence-based classification scheme tar-
geting the mip gene [18]. 
The data were evaluated in <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> -<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 16.0</rs> -(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, USA). Apart from frequency calculations 
(minimum, maximum, median and interquartile range), 
correlation according to Pearson were tested. For all 
statistical analyses, p-values &lt;0.05 were considered as 
significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Output water of DCUs </p>

<p>The 26 DCUs showed a median age of 4.8 years. The 
amount of colony forming units (cfu) of aerobic hetero-
trophic bacteria differed between the agar according to 
the ISO EN 6222 and the R2A agar for the output water 
of DCU. Detailed results are shown in Figure 1. 
With the agar described in EN 6222 a mean cfu of 20/ml 
was detected at 36°C and a mean cfu of 37/ml at 22°C. 
With the R2A agar at 35°C and 3 days incubation period 
a mean cfu of 220/ml and after 5 days of incubation a 
mean cfu of 590/ml was detected. With the R2A agar 
and incubation at 22°C for 5 or 7 days a mean cfu of 
heterotrophic bacteria of 535/ml or 800/ml, respectively, 
could be detected. 
With the agar according to EN 6222 66.4% of the counts 
were within the limits specified in the ADA guidelines 
(&lt;200 cfu/ml) at 36°C and 64.8% at 22°C. With R2A 
agar (35°for 3 days or 5 days, 22°C for 5 days or 7 days) 
only 49.3, 42.3, 38.6 and 37.7 percent of the samples 
were below the limit of 200 cfu/ml for aerobic heterotroph-
ic bacteria. 
A significant correlation (p&lt;0.05) was seen between the 
two different culture media for aerobic heterotrophic 
bacteria regardless of the incubation temperature and 
incubation period. 
Legionella spp. could be found in 39 samples. Out of 
these 39 samples, in 15 samples either Legionella 
pneumophila or Legionella anisa could be differentiated. 
In 9 samples both Legionella pneumophila and Legionella 
anisa could be detected. 
All of the 24 Legionella pneumophila isolates belonged 
to the Legionella pneumophila SG 1. Typing with the 
monoclonal antibodies was performed on 9 samples, 
showing that 8 isolates belonged to the MAb type Ox-
ford/Olda and 1 isolates to the MAb type Bellingham All 
isolates of the MAb type Oxford/Olda belonged to the SBT 
1 while the one isolate of MAb type Bellingham turned 
out as previously new SBT type now assigned as SBT 847. 
In 13 samples, the cfu of Legionella pneumophila SG 1 
was less than 200 cfu/100ml (Figure 2). Only in two 
samples very high counts (11,000 and 14,000/100 ml) </p>

<p>3/8 
GMS Krankenhaushygiene Interdisziplinär 2012, Vol. 7(1), ISSN 1863-5245 </p>

<p>Bristela et al.: Testing for aerobic heterotrophic bacteria allows ... </p>

<p>Figure 1: Aerobic heterotrophic bacteria of 71 samples from the output water of dental chair units. The boxplot diagram shows 
the median, interquatrile range and outlier. 
Abbreviations: R2A3572 = R2A agar at 35°C for 72 h; R2A35120 = R2A agar at 35°C for 120 h; R2A22120 = R2A agar at 22°C 
for 120 h; R2A22168 = R2A agar at 22°C for 168 h </p>

<p>Figure 2: L. pneumophila, L. anisa and P. aeruginosa of 71 samples from the output water of dental chair units; the boxplot 
diagram shows the median, interquartile range and outlier. </p>

<p>4/8 
GMS Krankenhaushygiene Interdisziplinär 2012, Vol. 7(1), ISSN 1863-5245 </p>

<p>Bristela et al.: Testing for aerobic heterotrophic bacteria allows ... </p>

<p>Figure 3: Scatter blot, correlating cfu of Legionella spp. and aerobic heterotrophic bacteria on R2A agar at 35°C after 3 days 
of incubation of 71 samples of output water of DCUs </p>

<p>could be seen. Both samples derived from the same DCU 
and were taken at an interval of one month (October and 
November 2009). This DCU was disinfected with chlorine 
solution by an external contractor after the second detec-
tion of high counts of Legionella pneumophila SG 1. 
Pseudomonas aeruginosa could not be demonstrated in 
one of the examined samples. 
No correlation could be found between the cfu of aerobic 
heterotrophic bacteria (regardless of the culture medium 
used) and the count of Legionella pneumophila and/or 
Legionella anisa. 
In Figure 3, a scatter blot is shown, correlating the cfu of 
Legionella spp. with the cfu of aerobic heterotrophic 
bacteria yielded on the R2A agar at 35°C after 3 days of 
incubation. </p>

<p>Distribution pipework </p>

<p>For the samples from the distribution pipework within the 
departments similar results as in the output water could 
be seen. Higher amounts of aerobic heterotrophic bacteria 
could be detected with the R2A agar as compared with 
the agar used in the EN 6222 (Figure 4). A significant 
correlation (p&lt;0.05) between the two culture media for 
aerobic heterotrophic bacteria could be seen, but the 
correlation depended on the incubation temperature and 
incubation period. 
Legionella spp. could be found in 24 samples. Out of 
these 24 samples, in 9 samples Legionella pneumophila </p>

<p>and in 10 samples Legionella anisa could be differenti-
ated. In 5 samples both Legionella pneumophila and L. 
anisa could be detected. 
All 14 Legionella pneumophila strains belonged to the 
SG 1. Only in two of the samples a cfu higher than 
200/100 ml was found (Figure 5). Typing of the 7 strains 
of Legionella pneumophila SG 1 with monoclonal antibod-
ies showed that 6 belonged to the Oxford/Olda and 1 to 
the Bellingham type. Typing by means of sequence base 
typing showed that the Oxford/Olda belonged to SBT Type 
1 and the one Bellingham to the new sequence type SBT 
847. 
Pseudomonas aeruginosa was detected in only one case. 
No correlation could be seen between the load of Legion-
ella pneumophila and/or Legionella anisa or Pseudomo-
nas aeruginosa and the cfu of aerobic heterotrophic 
bacteria regardless of the culture medium used. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The R2A agar showed higher counts of aerobic hetero-
trophic bacteria as compared to the agar used in the EN 
6222. The R2A agar is seen as the "golden standard" for 
testing of output water of DCU [19]. However, there was 
a significant correlation between the counts obtained 
with the agar used in the EN 6222 and the R2A agar and 
also among the different incubation temperatures and 
incubation periods from the samples of the output water. </p>

<p>5/8 
GMS Krankenhaushygiene Interdisziplinär 2012, Vol. 7(1), ISSN 1863-5245 </p>

<p>Bristela et al.: Testing for aerobic heterotrophic bacteria allows ... </p>

<p>Figure 4: Aerobic heterotrophic bacteria of 36 samples from the water of distribution pipework. The boxplot diagram shows 
the median, interquartile range and outlier. 
Abbreviations: R2A3572 = R2A agar at 35°C for 72 h; R2A35120 = R2A agar at 35°C for 120 h; R2A22120 = R2A agar at 22°C 
for 120 h; R2A22168 = R2A agar at 22°C for 168 h </p>

<p>Figure 5: L. pneumophila, L. anisa and P. aeruginosa of 36 samples from the water of distribution pipework. The boxplot diagram 
shows the median, interquartile range and outlier. </p>

<p>6/8 
GMS Krankenhaushygiene Interdisziplinär 2012, Vol. 7(1), ISSN 1863-5245 </p>

<p>Bristela et al.: Testing for aerobic heterotrophic bacteria allows ... </p>

<p>Independent of the agar used, the incubation time, and 
the incubation period, no prediction can be made regard-
ing the contamination with Legionella spp. or Pseudomo-
nas aeruginosa based on the number of cfus of aerobic 
heterotrophic bacteria in the water evaluated. 
It was surprising that none of the samples of the output 
water of the DCUs showed contamination with Pseudomo-
nas aeruginosa. This finding is in contrast to examinations 
of DCUs in other locations than the Bernhard Gottlieb 
University Clinic of Dentistry in Vienna, which frequently 
showed detection of Pseudomonas aeruginosa. The im-
portance of this pathogen had already been pointed out 
by Martin in 1987 [20]. The reason for the failure to de-
tect this pathogen in the output water may be due to the 
fact that the pathogen was only once identified in the 
supply water. 
As already described in literature, the contamination with 
bacteria in DCU is the direct result of the contamination 
of the supply water [21]. Therefore, the water of the dis-
tribution pipework was also examined in this study. It 
could be shown that only Legionella pneumophila SG 1 
could be isolated and that these isolates derived from 2 
strains as seen on the basis of sequence based typing. 
Depending on the method used only 49.3% (R2A agar 
35°C for 3 days) of the samples in our study were below 
the limits defined by the ADA. This shows that the inte-
grated disinfection system of the DCU alone is not capable 
of coping with the growth of aerobic heterotrophic bac-
teria. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>It can be concluded that exclusive evaluation for aerobic 
heterotrophic bacteria in DCU as contamination indicator 
does not allow for any conclusion as to the presence of 
contamination with Legionella spp. or Pseudomonas 
aeruginosa. 
Therefore, examination of distribution pipework or output 
water of DCUs for Legionella spp. and Pseudomonas 
aeruginosa is strongly recommended. </p>

<p>Notes </p>

<p>Competing interests </p>

<p>The authors declare that they have no competing in-
terests. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Radica Paunovic, Maria Voboril, Sonja Rehak 
and Petra Hasenberger for excellent technical assistance. </p>



<p>7/8 
GMS Krankenhaushygiene Interdisziplinär 2012, Vol. 7(1), ISSN 1863-5245 </p>

<p>Bristela et al.: Testing for aerobic heterotrophic bacteria allows ... </p>



<p>This article is freely available from 
http://www.egms.de/en/journals/dgkh/2012-7/dgkh000196.shtml </p>

<p>Published: 2012-04-04 </p>

<p>Copyright 
©2012 Bristela et al. This is an Open Access article distributed under 
the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/deed.en). You 
are free: to Share -to copy, distribute and transmit the work, provided 
the original author and source are credited. </p>

<p>8/8 
GMS Krankenhaushygiene Interdisziplinär 2012, Vol. 7(1), ISSN 1863-5245 </p>

<p>Bristela et al.: Testing for aerobic heterotrophic bacteria allows ... </p>

</text></tei>