<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3769723" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Trichoderma is one of the fungi genera that produce important metabolites for industry. The growth of these 
organisms is a consequence of the nutritional sources used as also of the physical conditions employed to 
cultivate them. In this work, the automated Bioscreen C system was used to evaluate the influence of 
different nutritional sources on the growth of Trichoderma strains (T. hamatum, T. harzianum, T. viride, and 
T. longibrachiatum) isolated from the soil in the Juréia-Itatins Ecological Station (JIES), São Paulo State -
Brazil. The cultures were grown in liquid culture media containing different carbon-(2%; w/v) and nitrogen 
(1%; w/v) sources at 28ºC, pH 6.5, and agitated at 150 rpm for 72 h. The results showed, as expected, that 
glucose is superior to sucrose as a growth-stimulating carbon source in the Trichoderma strains studied, 
while yeast extract and tryptone were good growth-stimulating nitrogen sources in the cultivation of T. 
hamatum and T. harzianum. </p>

<p>Fungi, in general, possess diverse abilities that form the 
basis for industrial research. Fungi are used in medical/ 
pharmaceutical industries for the manufacture of antibiotics, 
such as penicillin, produced by Penicillium chrysogenum, of 
enzymes such as amylases, pectinases, and of cellulases 
produced by Aspergillus spp. and by Trichoderma spp., as well 
as in food processing (14,17). 
Strains of Trichoderma can produce a great number of 
metabolites like antibiotics (10), degrade complex substrates 
such as cellulose (19), chitin, xylan, and lignin (6), and also 
possess proteolytic activity (25). Because of these properties, 
this genus has high biotechnological potential and is found 
in almost all ecosystems. Several studies have been carried 
out on Brazilian soil, such as in the Paranapiacaba Biological 
Reserve, SP (3). In order to improve knowledge of the </p>

<p>biodiversity of soil microbiota, 112 fungi species were isolated 
and identified from the Juréia-Itatins Ecological Station (JIES), 
São Paulo, Brazil (31). These species are currently being studied 
with respect to their potential for producing macromolecules 
of interest to medicine and industry. The same authors 
determined that some of these strains are able to produce 
enzymes like xylanases and fatty acids including γ-linolenic 
acid (GLA), and observed that the species of Trichoderma 
probably plays an important role in soil nutrient recycling 
(20,28). 
Like in the Bioscreen system, turbidimetric methods have 
been used for studies on microbial growth, providing fast results 
that are expressed in Optical Density (O.D.) units (21). This 
equipment has been used for many purposes in microbiology, 
including basic research (1), to study the effects of chemical 
compounds on microbial growth (17,19), for quality control (21), 
and in pollutant degradation tests (34). </p>

<p>Growth of Trichoderma strains </p>



<p>Considering the importance of a knowledge of the factors 
that influence the growth of fungi and the biotechnological 
potential of the genus Trichoderma, four strains were chosen 
(Trichoderma hamatum, Trichoderma harzianum, Trichoderma 
viride, and Trichoderma longibrachiatum) and isolated from 
the Juréia-Itatins Ecological Station-SP, Brazil (JIES) soil (31), 
in order to compare their potential to grow in submersed 
cultures, in the presence of a carbon source (glucose or sucrose) 
and a nitrogen source (tryptone or yeast extract), by means of 
the Bioscreen C automated system. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Microorganisms 
Four strains were studied -T. hamatum, T. harzianum, T. 
viride, and T. longibrachiatum -that were isolated from the 
soil (0 -15 cm deep) in the Banhado Grande area from JIES 
(LAT 24º 18' to 24º 37' S -LONG 47º 00' to 47º 31' W) in both 
natural-and secondary vegetation areas. The samples were 
collected, packaged into plastic bags, transported to the 
laboratory, and processed immediately to avoid storing them. 
These samples were sifted using 2.38 mm screens and 
homogenized. Isolation involved processing the soil samples 
by saline sterilization, followed by centrifugation, and a series 
of dilutions. Later, each sample was placed in Petri dishes (n = 
3) followed by the respective culture medium (31). 
These strains are kept in culture medium of MEA (29) (malt 
extract agar of composition (in w/v): malt extract 2%; 
bacteriological agar 2%; glucose 2%; peptone 0.1%; yeast 
extract 2% at pH 4.0 and 4ºC), in the laboratory of Centro de 
Estudos Ambientais (CEA), UNESP, Rio Claro, SP, Brazil. 
The inoculum of these strains was prepared from cultures 
grown in 7 days at 25ºC, with a spore suspension of 10 6 to 10 7 
spores.mL -1 in Tween (T-80) 0.1% (v/v). The counting was done 
in a Neubauer chamber in NaCl, 0.85% (w/v). </p>

<p>Cultures 
Strains were cultivated in a Bioscreen C system (Lab Systems 
Helsinki, Finland), in GY Medium, pH 6.5, with a single carbon 
source at 2% (w/v) (glucose or sucrose), and a single nitrogen 
source at 1% (w/v) (tryptone or yeast extract) (24). Accordingly, 
four different cultures were tested, namely Culture 1a (tryptone 
+ glucose); Culture 1b (tryptone + sucrose); Culture 2a (yeast 
extract + glucose), and Culture 2b (yeast extract + sucrose). The 
working volume in the Bioscreen plate was 400 µL/well comprising 
360 µL of each culture medium and 40 µL of each spore solution. 
Temperature was controlled at 28ºC and O.D. at 540 nm. 
Absorbance values of the cell suspensions were automatically 
read at regular intervals of 2 h, over a 72 h period, and before 
each measurement, the cell cultures were automatically shaken 
for 60 seconds. All experiments were performed in quadruplicate. 
The control tubes contained only the culture medium. </p>

<p>Data analysis 
1. Comparative analysis of the strains´growth 
The O.D. values from Bioscreen C were analyzed using 
spreadsheet software (<rs id="software-2" type="software">Microsoft Excel</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">97</rs>) and the averages 
calculated of the quadruplicates for each type of culture medium. 
These averages were used to generate growth curves for each 
type of culture (O.D. 540 nm of the cultures versus incubation 
time). Figures present the data from the average of readings 
(from quadruplicates) taken from every fourth hour of cultivation. 
Because the spore solution of each strain presented different 
colors, at time zero, the initial O.D. values were distinctive to 
each culture in relation to the control culture. This coloration 
difference (defined here as "specific color influence factor" for 
each strain) was calculated as follows: </p>

<p>Color influence = O.D. of each culture (t 0 ) -O.D. of the control 
(t 0 ) 
Next, the influence factor specific to each strain was 
subtracted from all O.D values from 0 to 72 h of each culture, in 
order to express the real growth of the strains. The analysis of 
variance (Kruskal-Wallis test, <rs id="software-1" type="software">BioEstat</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">4.0</rs> software) was applied 
using the data obtained, and confirmed by Dunn post hoc test, 
which was used to verify the significance of the strain's growth 
compared to the control and among the strains (5). The 
experimental results were separated into four classes based on 
the time taken for growth: I) 0 to 18 h, II) 18 to 36 h, III) 36 to 54 
h, and IV) 54 to 72 h. The results were analyzed by triangulation 
of the statistical data with the differences of O.D. per period. </p>

<p>2. Analyses of the growth of individual strains in different 
conditions of cultivation 
After excluding the color influence factor, the growth of 
each strain was calculated as the difference (Δ) between the 
average values of the O.D. 540 nm, final and initial, taking into 
account the fact that each average value of O.D. came from the 
replicas. 
The relative growth of each strain, expressed in percentage, 
was obtained by comparing the performance of a single strain 
in every two different cultivation conditions, considering the 
smallest O.D. value as 100% and the highest O.D. value (greater 
than 100%) as the highest rate of relative growth among them. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The quick determination of optimal growth of industrially 
interesting microorganisms, accompanied by the optimum 
production of economical value molecules, is very important 
for industry. The method used in this study is neither time 
consuming nor requires high costs, since it is no longer 
necessary to perform numerous tests like it is done by the 
traditional method of dilutions in series, while also enabling 
determination of optimal growth that is of industrial interest. </p>



<p>Rodrigues, B.C.R. et al. </p>

<p>In optimizing the growth of Trichoderma sp., some 
parameters were reported for instance, the 72 h period required 
for cultivation (33). As for the temperature, studies on the 
activity of xylanases from mesophilic fungi showed that, the 
activity of these enzymes were optimized between 25ºC and 
30ºC for submerse cultures (under constant agitation) and for 
stationary cultures with solid substrates (13). 
Studies also verified the effect of different temperatures 
on the production of several enzymes, among them 
carboxymethylcellulases and xylanases, on strains of several 
species isolated from JIES -SP -Brazil soil, such as Aspergillus 
and Trichoderma, and found 28ºC to be the optimum temperature 
and which was the temperature chosen for the cultures prepared 
in this study (26). 
Figs. 1 and 2 show the growth curves of the Trichoderma 
strains studied, obtained by their cultivation from 0 to 72 h and 
Table 1 records the results of the statistical analysis. </p>

<p>1. Comparative analysis of the growth of strains 
In the cultures with tryptone and glucose, the growth among 
the strains of T. hamatum, T. harzianum, T. viride and T. 
longibrachiatum was significantly different in all the periods 
(H 0-18h =33.36; H 20-36h =40.21; H 36-54h =40.90; H 56-72h =41.83, and 
p&lt;0.0001). With regard to the differences among the average 
scores per period (Table 1), it can be seen when individually 
analyzed against the control that in T. hamatum vs. T. viride and 
in the strains of T. hamatum, T. harzianum, and T. 
longibrachiatum, all presented values of p&lt;0.05 in most periods, 
and their growth rates were considered highly significant. 
Besides, T. hamatum differed not only from the control but also 
from T. viride, which did not happen with T. harzianum and T. </p>

<p>longibrachiatum; whereas, growth rates of both T. harzianum 
and T. longibrachiatum differed only from the control, but not 
from each other. Thus, it can be concluded from these 
observations that T. hamatum presented the highest value of R 
and consequently higher growth in all periods (Table 2). This 
was followed by T. harzianum and T. longibrachiatum that 
exhibited similar growth rates, and lastly by T. viride, (Fig. 1). 
In the cultures with tryptone and sucrose, the growth rates of 
the strains were also significantly different in all the periods (H 0-</p>

<p>18h =36.96; H 20-36h =41.93; H 36-54h =39.65; H 56-72h =41.24; and 
p&lt;0.0001). The differences among the average scores were not 
significant, especially between T. hamatum vs T. viride, T. 
hamatum vs control, T. harzianum vs T. viride, T. harzianum vs 
control, and T. logibrachiatum vs control. These findings can 
also be confirmed from the growth curves (Fig. 1B) in which T. 
hamatum and T. harzianum presented similar growth. 
Nevertheless, T. logibrachiatum exhibited a slightly smaller 
growth rate, while T. hamatum and T. harzianum showed the 
highest growth among the strains, followed by T. logibrachiatum, 
which is also confirmed by their respective values of R (Table 2). 
It can be seen that T. harzianum showed a similar growth 
rate in the cultures containing tryptone with glucose or sucrose. 
The same was observed of T. longibrachiatum, but the growth 
rate of T. hamatum was higher in the medium containing glucose 
as carbon source than in the one with sucrose (Fig. 1). 
Only few studies use tryptone as growth culture medium for 
fungi, as it is frequently used as nitrogen source for bacteria 
growth. Peptone is a similar molecule frequently used for growth 
of fungi such as Mucor (32), Aspergillus (23), and Trichoderma 
(35). Studies involving Aspergillus flavus growth report that 
tryptone is as effective as peptone (22), and is cheaper. Due to </p>

<p>Figure 1. Growth curves (O.D. 540 nm) of T. hamatum, T. longibrachiatum, T. viride, and T. harzianum in medium containing 
tryptone and glucose (a) or tryptone and sucrose (b) incubated at 28ºC from 0 until 72 h in an automated Bioscreen C system. </p>

<p>Growth of Trichoderma strains </p>



<p>Table 1. Growth differences of the strains for culture periods in different culture media. The z values were obtained from variance analysis (Kruskal-Wallis test) 
and confirmed by Dunn post hoc test (<rs id="software-3" type="software">BioEstat</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">4.0</rs> software). </p>

<p>Culture 1a </p>

<p>Culture 1b </p>

<p>Culture 2a </p>

<p>Culture 2b </p>

<p>(tryptone and glucose) </p>

<p>(tryptone and sucrose) </p>

<p>(yeast extract and glucose) </p>

<p>(yeast extract and sucrose) </p>

<p>0-18h 20-36h 38-54h 56-72h 0-18h 20-36h 38-54h 56-72h 0-18h 20-36h 38-54h 56-72h 0-18h 20-36h 38-54h 56-72h </p>

<p>T. hamatum x 
T. harzianum 
2.010 2.082 1.759 1.561 0.215 1.525 0.628 0.969 2.737 2.261 0.431 1.400 2.530 1.323 1.346 1.454 </p>

<p>T. hamatum x 
T. longibrachiatum 
2.916 2.279 2.602 2.800 2.288 2.835 2.333 2.665 2.351 2.118 2.315 2.880 3.697 2.225 1.507 1.454 </p>

<p>T. hamatum x 
T. viride 
5.133 4.361 4.361 4.361 3.508 4.361 3.894 4.119 5.016 4.343 3.822 4.334 2.862 4.092 2.961 2.907 </p>

<p>T. hamatum x 
controle 
4.477 5.814 5.814 5.814 5.025 5.814 5.348 5.572 4.343 5.814 5.276 5.788 5.447 5.545 4.415 4.361 </p>

<p>T. harzianum x 
T. longibrachiatum 
0.906 0.197 0.843 1.238 2.073 1.310 1.705 1.696 0.386 0.144 1.884 1.481 1.166 0.897 2.853 2.907 </p>

<p>T. harzianum x 
T. viride 
2.271 2.279 2.602 2.800 2.293 2.835 3.266 3.149 2.279 2.082 3.392 2.934 0.332 2.764 4.307 4.361 </p>

<p>T. harzianum x 
controle 
2.468 3.733 4.056 4.253 4.809 4.289 4.720 4.603 1.606 3.553 4.845 4.388 2.916 4.217 5.761 5.814 </p>

<p>T. longibrachiatum 
x T. viride 
2.216 2.082 1.759 1.561 1.220 1.525 1.561 1.454 2.665 2.225 1.507 1.454 0.834 1.866 1.454 1.454 </p>

<p>T. longibrachiatum 
x controle 
1.561 3.535 3.212 3.015 2.737 2.979 3.015 2.907 1.992 3.697 2.961 2.907 1.750 3.320 2.907 2.907 </p>

<p>T. viride x 
controle 
0.655 1.454 1.454 1.454 1.516 1.454 1.454 1.454 0.673 1.472 1.454 1.454 2.584 1.454 1.454 1.454 </p>

<p>Criptical z value for p is 2.807 </p>

<p>z values in bold are significant (p&lt;0.05) </p>

<p>Table 2. R-values of each strain obtained from variance analysis (Kruskal-Wallis test) confirmed by Dunn post hoc test (BioEstat 4.0 software). </p>

<p>Culture 1a </p>

<p>Culture 1b </p>

<p>Culture 2a </p>

<p>Culture 2b </p>

<p>(tryptone and glucose) </p>

<p>(tryptone and sucrose) </p>

<p>(yeast extract and glucose) </p>

<p>(yeast extract and sucrose) </p>

<p>0-18h 20-36h 38-54h 56-72h 0-18h 20-36h 38-54h 56-72h 0-18h 20-36h 38-54h 56-72h 0-18h 20-36h 38-54h 56-72h </p>

<p>T. hamatum </p>

<p>369 </p>

<p>369 </p>

<p>369 </p>

<p>369 </p>

<p>330 </p>

<p>369 </p>

<p>343 </p>

<p>355.5 </p>

<p>368 </p>

<p>369 </p>

<p>339 </p>

<p>367.5 </p>

<p>369 </p>

<p>354 </p>

<p>291 </p>

<p>288 </p>

<p>T. harzianum </p>

<p>257 </p>

<p>253 </p>

<p>271 </p>

<p>282 </p>

<p>318 </p>

<p>284 </p>

<p>308 
301.5 215.5 </p>

<p>243 </p>

<p>315 </p>

<p>289.5 </p>

<p>228 </p>

<p>228 </p>

<p>366 </p>

<p>369 </p>

<p>T. longibrachiatum </p>

<p>206.5 242 </p>

<p>224 
213 202.5 211 </p>

<p>213 </p>

<p>207 </p>

<p>237 </p>

<p>251 </p>

<p>210 </p>

<p>207 </p>

<p>163 </p>

<p>230 </p>

<p>207 </p>

<p>207 </p>

<p>T. viride </p>

<p>83.5 </p>

<p>126 </p>

<p>126 
126 134.5 126 </p>

<p>126 </p>

<p>126 </p>

<p>88.5 </p>

<p>127 </p>

<p>126 </p>

<p>126 
209.5 126 </p>

<p>126 </p>

<p>126 </p>



<p>Rodrigues, B.C.R. et al. </p>

<p>the absence of studies related to the growth of fungi using 
tryptone, it was chosen as the nitrogen source in the present 
study. 
In our study, differences in the growth rates among the 
strains could also be noticed (H 0-18h =30.63; H 20-36h =40.07; H 36-</p>

<p>54h =39.90; H 56-72h =42.15 and p&lt;0.0001) in the cultures containing 
yeast extract and glucose. The results of the average scores 
showed that only T. hamatum exhibited a significant difference 
in the growth in the period of 0 up to 18 h of cultivation. From 
the 38th hour of cultivation, the growth rate of the strains of T. 
hamatum, T. harzianum, and T. longibrachiatum increased 
(Table 1, Fig. 2), and a significant difference in growth could be 
seen from that period for T. harzianum vs T. viride, T. harzianum 
vs control, and T. logibrachiatum vs control (Table 1). 
Considering that the average scores of T. hamatum exhibited a 
significant rate in all the periods and also presented the highest 
value of R (Table 2), it can be assumed that this strain too 
presented the highest growth rate among those tested, followed 
by T. harzianum and T. logibrachiatum. 
In cultures containing yeast extract and sucrose, different 
growth rates were also detected among the strains (H 0-18h =31.38; 
H 20-36h =38.97; H 36-54h =42.12; H 56-72h =42.42 and p&lt;0.0001). The 
average scores of T. hamatum vs T. viride and the scores of T. 
hamatum and of T. harzianum when individually analyzed, against 
the control, were significantly different in all the periods (Table 
1), while T. harzianum vs T. longibrachiatum and T. harzianum 
vs T. viride exhibited significant differences only after 38 h of 
cultivation. On comparing these data, it can be seen in the Fig. 2 
that, from the 38th hour, the growth curve of T. harzianum 
surpassed that of T. hamatum and, consequently, the R-value 
of T. harzianum increased in that period too (Table 2). </p>

<p>2. Analyses of the growth of each individual strain in different 
cultivation conditions 
On comparing the cultivation conditions tested here, it can 
be concluded that in the cultivation of T. harzianum there was 
an increase in the growth rate at approximately the 36th hour in 
all the conditions (Figs. 1, 2). From this period, the strain started 
to differ significantly from both T. viride (in the cultivation with 
yeast extract and glucose) and T. longibrachiatum (when 
cultivated in yeast extract and sucrose) (Table 1). Analyzing 
only the nitrogen sources in function of the carbon sources 
used, it was observed that the growth of T. harzianum was 30% 
higher with yeast extract plus glucose than with tryptone plus 
glucose (Figs. 1, 2). The same pattern was observed with regard 
to media with sucrose, where the growth with yeast extract was 
65% higher than with tryptone (Figs. 1, 2). Thus, yeast extract 
appears to be the best nitrogen source for T. harzianum, 
compared to tryptone, apart from the carbon source used in 
this study. Studies involving xylanase production indicated that 
T. harzianum is a good producer of xylanases in media 
containing yeast extract (7). The comparative analysis of the 
carbon sources in function of the nitrogen sources showed 
that in the presence of tryptone, growth of T. harzianum in the 
cultures with glucose was 15% higher than that in sucrose (Fig. 
1), while in presence of yeast extract the growth was 10% higher 
in the cultures with sucrose than in those with glucose (Fig. 2). 
The data above show that yeast extract is better for growth 
of T. harzianum, especially when combined with sucrose, and 
differs in this respect from T. viride (Table 1). 
As expected with all cultures, the growth of T. hamatum in 
glucose was much better than in sucrose, as glucose is a simpler 
metabolite than sucrose. Considering only the influence of sugar, </p>

<p>Figure 2. Growth curves (O.D. 540nm) of T. hamatum, T. longibrachiatum, T. viride, and T. harzianum in medium containing yeast 
extract and glucose (a) or yeast extract and sucrose (b) incubated at 28ºC from 0 until 72 h in an automated Bioscreen C system. </p>

<p>Growth of Trichoderma strains </p>



<p>it can be seen that growth of T. hamatum was 40% higher in 
glucose than in sucrose in presence of tryptone as nitrogen 
source (Fig. 1). Likewise, the growth of T. hamatum was 45% 
higher in glucose than in sucrose in the medium with yeast 
extract (Fig. 2). These results indicate that for T. hamatum 
cultivation, glucose is better than sucrose as carbon source, 
irrespective of the nitrogen source used. Analyzing influence 
of the nitrogen source on the growth rate of T. hamatum, a 
slightly higher growth (20%) could be observed in yeast extract 
than in tryptone, when glucose was present in the medium (Figs. 
1, 2). Almost the same result was detected when sucrose was 
used as carbon source, in which growth of T. hamatum was 
15% higher than in yeast extract, indicating that in this strain 
yeast extract induces a higher growth rate (Figs. 1, 2). 
T. longibrachiatum presented similar growth rates in all the 
cultivation conditions tested here (with small differences ranging 
from 10 to 15%) which can be observed in both Figures. According 
to the statistical data, this strain differed from the control only 
from the 20th hour of growth, and did not differ from T. viride in 
any period. This last strain did not show a growth pattern 
different from the control or exhibit a significant growth rate. 
This suggests that for these two strains, T. longibrachiatum 
and T. viride, further studies are necessary because the 
nutritional sources tested here may not be suitable for their 
cultivation. 
Different carbon sources were also used in analysis of 
fungi and production of total lipids, as well as γ-linoleic acid, 
maintaining the nitrogen source (yeast extract) constant (26). 
The results showed a five times higher growth rate in the 
culture medium containing glucose, compared to that with 
sucrose. 
Yeast extract has effectively been the best nitrogen source 
for growing filamentous fungi and is the best inducer for 
production of different macromolecules, a characteristic also 
observed, in recent studies, for thermophilic fungi (15). It was 
confirmed that significant mycelial growth resulted in T. 
aureoviride, T. viride, and T. harzianum strains when cultivated 
in media containing yeast extract and agricultural soil (16), this 
last being a nitrogen source considered very stimulating for 
production of enzymes , such as proteases (2,9) and cellulases 
(26), by Trichoderma. 
Studies performed with the Bioscreen C automated system 
(4) on Saccharomyces cerevisiae and Aspergillus niger revealed 
that both of them presented a good growth rate in medium 
containing yeast extract. In another study using Bioscreen C, 
the researchers were able to demonstrate that despite belonging 
to the same species, four strains of Mucor hiemalis differed 
with respect to their capacities for growth with the same carbon-
or nitrogen source (30). 
In our study, other sources of nitrogen were also tested, 
such as casein, gelatin, and ammonium nitrate, in the presence 
of glucose or sucrose, but no significant growth rate was </p>

<p>observed with any of them (data not shown). Ammonium nitrate 
has been used as a stimulating agent for synthesis of different 
enzymes in fungi (24). However, as the ammonium ion and its 
derivates, in general, tend to behave as enzyme inhibitors (11), 
and it may have negatively influenced the fungi growth tested 
here when ammonium nitrate was used in the media. 
Trichoderma is a fungus used for industrial production of 
enzymes such as xylanases and glucanases and many other 
metabolites (8), besides having clinical importance, causing 
infections, as reported for T. viride (18), T. longibrachiatum 
(16) and for T.harzianum (12). Thus, the verification of nutritional 
parameters for the strains tested in our study is promising for 
optimizing their biotechnological-and industrial uses. 
Some studies on microorganisms' growth compared the 
Bioscreen automated system and the traditional cultivation 
method, and many patterns of similarity between them were 
found. One of these studies (34) confirmed that the Bioscreen 
automated system is a promising and reliable method for several 
uses in microbiology. 
Considering that the microorganism cultivation in industries 
must be carried out on large scale for production of innumerable 
commercially interesting metabolites, our results indicate that 
the Bioscreen system provides a fast-and economical way to 
test and optimize growth conditions for further use in such 
large-scale production. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>Rossi-Rodrigues, B.C was a fellow from the Scholarship 
Institutional Program in Scientific Initiation from PIBIC/CNPq 
(Brazilian Research Council) in the São Paulo State University 
(UNESP). </p>

<p>RESUMO </p>

<p>Crescimento de linhagens de Trichoderma em 
diferentes fontes nutricionais, empregando o sistema 
automatizado Bioscreen C. </p>

<p>Trichoderma é um dos gêneros de fungos produtores de 
metabólitos de interesse industrial. O crescimento destes 
organismos é conseqüência das fontes nutricionais utilizadas, 
juntamente com as condições físicas de cultivo. Neste trabalho, 
o sistema automatizado Bioscreen C foi utilizado para avaliar a 
influência de diferentes fontes nutricionais sobre o crescimento 
de linhagens de Trichoderma (T. hamatum, T. harzianum, T. 
viride e T. longibrachiatum) isoladas do solo da Estação 
Ecológica da Juréia-Itatins (JIES), São Paulo -Brasil. Os cultivos 
foram feitos em meios líquidos de cultura contendo diferentes 
fontes de carbono (2%; w / v) e nitrogênio (1%; w / v) a 28ºC, 
pH 6,5 e agitados a 150 rpm durante 72 h. Os resultados 
mostraram, conforme esperado, que a glicose é melhor do que a </p>



<p>Rodrigues, B.C.R. et al. </p>

<p>sacarose como fonte de carbono indutora de crescimento das 
linhagens de Trichoderma testadas, enquanto que, o extrato de 
leveduras e a triptona foram boas fontes de nitrogênio indutoras 
de crescimento para os cultivos de T. hamatum e T. harzianum. </p>

<p>Palavras chave: Bioscreen C, crescimento, Trichoderma, 
triptona, extrato de leveduras. </p>



</text></tei>