<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3936211" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Nanostructured metals achieve extraordinary strength but suffer from low thermal stability, both a 
consequence of a high fraction of interfaces. Overcoming this tradeoff relies on making the interfaces 
themselves thermally stable. Here we show that the atomic structures of bi-metal interfaces in macroscale 
nanomaterials suitable for engineering structures can be significantly altered via changing the severe 
plastic deformation (SPD) processing pathway. Two types of interfaces are formed, both exhibiting a 
regular atomic structure and providing for excellent thermal stability, up to more than half the melting 
temperature of one of the constituents. Most importantly, the thermal stability of one is found to be 
significantly better than the other, indicating the exciting potential to control and optimize macroscale 
robustness via atomic-scale bimetal interface tuning. Taken together, these results demonstrate an 
innovative way to engineer pristine bimetal interfaces for a new class of simultaneously strong and 
thermally stable materials. </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>he materials community has been, and will continue to be, in search of metals that can maintain excep-
tionally high strength at extremely high temperatures to satisfy harsher application requirements </p>

<p>1,2   . To date, 
nanostructured metals have exhibited much higher strengths than possible with traditional coarse-grained 
metals </p>

<p>3-8   . 
However, achieving extraordinary strength together with high temperature tolerance in bulk (. cm 
3 ) nanos-
tructured pure metals has been unattainable with current synthesis methods </p>

<p>9-12   . Metallic multilayers fabricated by 
bottom-up processes, such as physical vapor deposition (PVD), have high strength and thermal stability, but are 
thin films with overall micrometer thicknesses. Nanocrystalline metals produced by top-down process, such as 
SPD, have high strength and are in bulk form, but they are thermally unstable even at slightly above room 
temperatures </p>

<p>13,14   . These mechanical methods produce nanocrystalline metals that contain a high density of 
crystallographically disordered, non-equilibrium grain boundaries (interfaces), which with minimal thermal 
stimulus promote grain coarsening </p>

<p>15-17   . In efforts to engineer stable interfaces, alloying has been shown to 
stabilize grain boundaries in nanocrystalline metals </p>

<p>2,18-20   . Yet still, the long sought after ability to control the 
interface properties down to the atomic scale via directed manufacturing has yet to be achieved. 
Recently, in synthesizing bulk two-phase nanocomposites via SPD, we discovered that a preferred interface 
develops uniformly across the bulk that possesses a highly ordered atomic structure with few detectable extrinsic 
defects </p>

<p>21,22   . The pristine interfaces had two exciting implications. First, it implies microstructural stability in 
extreme conditions. Prior work on PVD foils 
23 has shown that highly ordered bimetal interfaces are much more 
robust against thermally-induced instabilities than ordinary grain boundaries. Accordingly, by virtue of the 
pristine interfaces induced in the SPD process, the SPD composites have proven remarkably strong </p>

<p>24   , thermally 
stable 
21 , and radiation resistant </p>

<p>25   . Second, it implies that this processing technique could in fact be used to tune the 
atomic structures of interfaces. 
Here we demonstrate the ability to control interface character at the atomic scale in bulk metallic materials via 
SPD. Bulk Cu-Nb nanolayered composites with equal individual layer thicknesses were made by a well-developed 
SPD method that accumulative roll bonding (ARB) consisting of repeated roll bonding, cutting, stacking and 
rolling 
26 . </p>

<p>Results 
To tune the interface feature, we alter the SPD processing pathway. 
ARB material was made by maintaining the rolling direction in each 
step until individual Cu and Nb layer thicknesses (h) were reduced to 
58 nm. As demonstrated in figure 1a, to synthesize the ARB-LR 
(longitudinally rolled) material with 20 nm average individual layer 
thickness, we continued to roll the h 5 58 nm ARB material while 
preserving the same rolling direction as used from the start of the 
process. In contrast, the ARB-CR (cross-rolled) material with 20 nm 
individual layer thickness was produced by rolling the 58 nm ARB 
material with a new rolling direction rotated 90u in-plane as shown in 
figure 1d. The two ARB materials experienced the same final total 
strain of 11.51. 
Using neutron diffraction, we found that the two processing path-
ways generate two completely different textures. The measured tex-
tures for the 20 nm composites are presented in the form of inverse 
pole figures (IPFs) in the rolling direction (RD), transverse direction 
(TD) and normal direction (ND) of the processed sheet. As an indica-
tion of their stability, the same textures are generated at 30 nm ARB-
LR and 30 nm ARB-CR textures, respectively (supplementary figure 
1). Analysis of these textures reveals that both deviate from conven-
tional single phase Cu and Nb rolling textures </p>

<p>27   . In figure 1b, the 
20 nm ARB-LR material contains a predominant {112},111. 
Cujj{112},110.Nb texture (where the crystal planes and directions 
are written parallel to the {rolling plane}-,rolling direction.), which 
is consistent with the texture of 58 nm ARB-LR material 
(Supplementary figure 2). Additionally, the minor texture component 
{551},1 1 10. of the Cu phase is due to interface-facilitated Cu 
twinning, which initiates when the individual layer thickness reduces 
below 50 nm </p>

<p>21,27-29 </p>

<p>. The change in processing pathway induced a 
completely different texture, as seen in figure 1e. Mean-field crystal 
plasticity simulations of the cross-rolling successfully predicted these </p>

<p>textures, suggesting that this abrupt alteration is accommodated 
solely by crystallographic slip (see supplement and supplementary 
figure 3). Remarkably, the Cu and Nb textures of the ARB-CR mater-
ial are exceptionally sharp (figure 1e), suggesting a preferential inter-
face character of {110},111.Cujj{001},110.Nb. The stable and 
prevailing interfaces suggested by the texture in the ARB-LR and 
ARB-CR samples are illustrated in figures 1c and 1f. 
To study the morphologies of the grains and layers at these fine 
scales, we used transmission electron microscopy (TEM). For all 
layers in both the ARB-LR (figure 2a) and ARB-CR (figure 2b) mate-
rials, only one crystal spanned the distance between two adjacent 
interfaces. Another notable feature of both materials is the planarity 
of the Cu-Nb interfaces and the regularity of layer thicknesses. Thus, 
changing the processing pathway on the nanomaterial to make the 
ARB-CR nanomaterial preserved the lamellar architecture without 
roughening or breaking up the layers. The TEM analysis also 
revealed that unlike the ARB-CR material, the ARB-LR material 
contains many deformation twins in the Cu layers (figure 2a), which 
leads to its distinct texture development, as mentioned above. 
Twinning occurs in the ARB-LR sample because its interfaces and 
grain orientations favor it, whereas those in the ARB-CR sample do 
not </p>

<p>29,30   . 
To examine the interfacial atomic structures, high resolution (HR) 
TEM analysis was carried out on many regions throughout these 
samples. Figure 2c and 2d display typical HRTEM micrographs of 
the {112},111.Cujj{112},110.Nb interface within the 20 nm 
ARB-LR material and the {110},111.jj{001},110. interface 
within the 20 nm ARB-CR material, respectively. These prevailing 
interfaces are illustrated in figures 1c and 1f. The orientation rela-
tionships of these two interfaces are Kurdjumov-Sachs (K-S) and 
Nishiyama-Wasserman (N-W), respectively. Unlike the familiar K-
S and N-W fcc/bcc interfaces that arise from thermodynamic </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Two straining pathways generating two materials containing completely different textures and interfaces. Schematic diagrams of the two </p>

<p>ARB pathways used: (a) ARB-LR (longitudinally rolled), (d) ARB-CR (cross-rolled); Inverse pole figures of Cu and Nb, in which the main texture 
components are marked with red dots: (b) 20 nm ARB-LR, (e) 20 nm ARB-CR; the predominant interface structures that (c) </p>

<p>(112)[11 1]Cu | |(112)[ 110]Nb in 20 nm ARB-LR and (f) (1 10)[11 1]Cu | |(001)[1 10] in 20 nm ARB-CR resulting from pathways (a) and (d), respectively. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4226 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04226 </p>

<p>
processes 
24 whose interface planes correspond to the closest packed 
planes, the {111}Cu and {110}Nb planes, the mechanically driven 
interfaces emerging in these samples join the fcc and bcc crystals at 
different interface planes, namely the {112}Cujj{112}Nb and 
{110}Cujj{001}Nb planes. Most intriguingly, both interfaces are 
found by HRTEM to be atomically ordered. While the former 
{112}Cujj{112}Nb K-S interface is comprised of a regular array of 
facets, the latter {110}Cujj{001}Nb N-W interface is atomically flat. 
Recent fundamental studies have shown that this difference pro-
foundly affects the ability of the interface to act as a source for dis-
locations and deformation twins </p>

<p>29,31,32   , the two main carriers of 
plastic deformation. Thus, by atomically altering interface structure 
we have a newfound way of controlling the mechanical properties of 
nanomaterials. 
At this point, we have demonstrated for the first time that two 
distinct atomically ordered interfaces can be created by altering the 
bulk mechanical processing pathway. To assess the quality of these 
interfaces, we test their stability in microstructure and hardness with 
respect to high temperature annealing. Figure 3a shows experimental 
results from nanoindentation tests before and after high-temper-
ature annealing. Both materials maintain their high hardness, as well 
as their layered morphologies and layer thickness even after exposure 
to 500uC for one hour (supplementary figures 4b, 4f, 5c and 5d). This 
thermal stability far surpasses that of single-phase nanocrystalline 
Cu fabricated also by SPD techniques </p>

<p>13   . Materials made by non-
equilibrium SPD techniques are expected to be thermally unstable 
because they contain high-energy interfaces </p>

<p>12,17   . Remarkably, our 
SPD materials have an uncharacteristically high-temperature tol-
erance that is comparable to that of Cu-Nb nanolayered films fabri-
cated via PVD </p>

<p>23   , which are comprised of low-energy, semi-coherent 
Cu-Nb interfaces. It is also superior to that of nano-twinned Cu, 
which contain a high density of low-energy, coherent twin bound-
aries </p>

<p>33   . Thus the two interfaces we have formed via mechanical 
means possess the same thermal stabilities as interfaces formed via 
thermal equilibrium processes such as PVD. 
Surprisingly, the two materials possess different thermal stabilities 
at a higher temperature. The ARB-CR maintains its hardness up to </p>

<p>600uC, unlike the ARB-LR 20 nm material which exhibits a 19.3% 
drop. To explain the difference, the increment in the average layer 
thickness with annealing temperature is plotted in figure 3b based on 
TEM measurement (Supplementary figures 4 and 5). Comparing the 
variation of hardness and average layer thickness reveals a significant 
dependence of strength on length scale. After annealing at 600uC for 
one hour, the average layer thickness of the ARB-LR materials 
doubled while the ARB-CR material only increased by 5%. In repeat-
ing the experimental analysis for higher temperatures, we find that 
the threshold of thermal stability for the ARB-CR material lies 
between 600uC and 700uC for one hour annealing (supplementary 
figures 4 h and 5 h). 
A key question that arises is why the two ARB materials exhibit 
different thermal stabilities. To address this question, we first exam-
ined the atomic structures of the bimetal interfaces that prevail 
over these materials--the {112},111.Cujj{112},110.Nb and 
{110},112.Cujj{001},110.Nb interfaces-after heating using 
HRTEM. Remarkably, both interfaces after heating at 600uC were 
stable. Specifically many important structural properties, including 
the atomic scale features of facets or flatness, the chemical sharpness, 
and crystallography, were maintained. Second, in light of earlier 
reports that intra-layer grain boundaries are relatively unstable </p>

<p>23   , 
we considered possible differences in their grain boundary density. 
Using a unique, high-resolution ''wedge-mounting'' electron back-
scatter diffraction (WM-EBSD) </p>

<p>34   , we were able to correlate grain 
boundary density to the statistical distribution of grain sizes in the 
two in-plane directions, the TD and the RD. To ensure statistically 
significant and representative data, we confirmed that the textures 
from the WM-EBSD technique are consistent with those from neut-
ron diffraction (supplementary figure 6). 
Grain size distributions for both Cu and Nb in the original TD and 
RD reference frame (prior to cross-rolling) are illustrated in figure 4. 
For the 58 nm ARB-LR material, on average the grains are shaped 
like ''planks'' with RD:ND:TD ratios of 335157 and 8351516 in the 
Cu and Nb, respectively. The analysis is repeated for the h 5 30 nm 
ARB-LR and ARB-CR samples since the h 5 20 nm materials are too 
fine for the WM-EBSD technique. However, it is reasonable to </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Typical bright field TEM images showing nanolamellar morphologies of the (a) 20 nm ARB-LR sample and (b) 20 nm ARB-CR sample. </p>

<p>A large number of twins are present in the Cu phase of 20 nm ARB-LR material, but not in the 20 nm ARB-CR material. Representative HRTEM images 
of the predominant interface in the (c) 20 nm ARB-LR material, which is noticeably faceted and (d) 20 nm ARB-CR material, which is atomically flat. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4226 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04226 </p>

<p>
deduce that the trends in aspect ratios in the h 5 30 nm are consist-
ent with those in the h 5 20 nm materials. The results show that the 
basic grain shapes in the h 5 58 nm are maintained in the h 5 30 nm 
ARB-LR material. In contrast, for the 30 nm ARB-CR material, we 
find 'pancake-shaped' grains, where the average length of the grains 
in the original RD has not changed, but the average length in the 
original TD has increased three-fold. Due to the extremely large 
aspect ratios, we conclude that the grain boundary fraction in both 
materials is exceedingly small. In the ARB-CR material this fraction 
is even smaller compared to the ARB-LR material. Evidently, the 
differences of grain boundary fraction seen in figure 4 lead to import-
ant differences in their thermal stabilities seen in figure 3. This sug-
gests that controlled SPD processing is a profitable way to improve 
thermal stability of materials by simultaneously increasing the stable 
interface fraction and decreasing unstable grain boundary fraction. </p>

<p>Discussion 
In conclusion, we report here the unprecedented ability to control bi-
metal interface structures at the atomic scale in bulk nanostructured 
composites via SPD. Specifically, two different SPD synthesis path-
ways are shown to both produce interfaces with preferred orientation 
relationships and distinct atomic features. Moreover, both interfaces 
are stable up to 600uC. Thermal stability of nanostructured metals 
can be improved by increasing the stable interface region that is 
grain-boundary-free. These findings open up new ways of engineer-
ing interfaces that are stable and lead to exceptional properties. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Material fabrication. The ARB processing technology can fabricate bulk 
nanomaterials appropriate for industry scale applications. The ARB process used 
for this work started with one polycrystalline sheet of reactor grade Nb (99.97% 
pure, ATI-Wah Chang) of thickness h 5 2 mm and two oxide-free high 
conductivity Cu sheets (99.99% pure, Southern Copper and Supply) of thickness h 
5 1 mm. All the sheets were 20 cm long and 6.5 cm wide. After a five-minute 
ultrasonic acetone bath followed by wire brushing to facilitate bonding, the Cu 
and Nb sheets were stacked in a sandwich-like structure (Cu-Nb-Cu) for the first 
roll-bonding step. A 2-high rolling mill (Waterbury-Farrel, Brampton, Ontario, 
Canada) was used in this roll-bonding step with an approximate 60% reduction in 
thickness. Following each roll-bonding step, a repeating sequence of halving, 
cleaning, restacking, and roll bonding was performed until the average layer 
thickness was 200 nm. From 200 nm, the samples were only subjected to 
conventional rolling with a 10% decrease in total sample thickness per rolling step. 
After individual Cu and Nb layer thicknesses were reduced to 58 nm, the material 
was cut into two pieces. One piece was rolled in the same rolling direction as used 
from the start of the process until the individual layer thickness reduced to 20 nm 
(ARB-LR). The other piece was rotated 90u in-plane and rolled in the new rolling 
direction to get the ARB-CR material with individual layer thickness of 20 nm. 
The whole ARB process was carried out at room temperature. </p>

<p>Texture analysis. Textures of the samples were measured via neutron diffraction 
on the High Pressure Preferred Orientation (HIPPO) 
27 time-of-flight 
diffractometer at the Los Alamos Neutron Science Center at Los Alamos National 
Laboratory. Samples with a surface size of 1.5 cm 
2 were mounted in a way that the 
Cu-Nb interfaces were perpendicular to the incoming neutron beam and the 
rolling direction of the sample was parallel with the notch. Five banks of detector 
panels set at 2h 5 150u, 120u, 90u, 60u, and 40u, respectively, were used to collect 
diffraction data, while each bank created a full rotation (with regards to the 
neutron beam direction) of detection coverage. Each sample was rotated to 
specific angles of v 5 0u, 67.5u, and 90u to increase the coverage of the pole </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Outstanding thermal stability of nanomaterial strength and their interface structures. (a) Hardness reduction as a function of annealing </p>

<p>temperature; (b) percentage increase in average layer thickness as a function of annealing temperatures; (c) typical HRTEM image of the 20 nm ARB-LR 
material after annealing at 600uC for one hour showing the same atomic faceted structure as before annealing (figure 2(c)); (c) typical HRTEM image of 
the 20 nm ARB-CR material after annealing at 600uC for one hour showing the same atomically flat structure as before annealing (figure 2(d)). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4226 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04226 </p>

<p>
figures during the collection. A Rietveld refinement on 150 neutron diffraction 
patterns was performed on the program <rs type="software">MAUD</rs> 
27 . A 10u resolution of the Rietveld 
refinement was chosen in order to simultaneously fit all the diffraction patterns to 
an orientation distribution function (ODF). Then, the rolling, normal, and 
transverse directions were properly aligned via the Matlab-based <rs type="software">mtex</rs> program 
35 . 
Additionally, <rs type="software">mtex</rs> was used for analysis of the ODFs and plotting the inverse pole 
figures (IPFs). </p>

<p>TEM investigation. All TEM samples were prepared by a conventional cross-
sectioning method consisting of mechanical thinning and ion milling on a Gatan 
precision ion polishing system (PIPS). TEM and STEM were carried out on a Cs-
corrected Titan 80-300 (FEI). All the TEM samples were viewed down the TD 
direction, so that the images comprise RD and ND directions. It is worth noting that 
the ARB-CR samples were also viewed down the new TD direction after the rotation. </p>

<p>Heating treatment. Annealing was performed at a 500uC, 600uC and 700uC for one 
hour under vacuum (4E-06 Torr) in a 3310 Series Furnace (Applied Test Systems, 
Inc., Butler, PA). The samples were cooled under vacuum. </p>

<p>Hardness test. All hardness tests were carried out on a Nanoindenter XP (Agilent). 
Hardness measurements were made continuously in the continuous stiffness 
measurement (CSM) mode with a target strain rate of 0.05 1/s. Average hardness 
values were calculated from 25 separate indents, which included hardness data from 
1500 nm to 2000 nm depths, which is the depth range a steady-state hardness value 
been found. In order to ensure an accurate tip area function for the Berkovich tip, a 
silica standard sample was used for calibration before and after indentation of each 
sample. In addition, the onset of loading, which is an indicator of displacement into 
sample, was verified for each indent. </p>

<p>WM-EBSD. To obtain fine-scale information but over a large area of the material, we 
made use of wedge-mounting electron backscatter diffraction (WM-EBSD), where 
crystal orientation and phase data can be uniquely retrieved at fine scales (,30 nm). 
Using WM-EBSD allows us as many as 6 data points across a 30 nm layer on average, </p>

<p>which is much more statistically significant, especially for nanocomposites consist of 
multi-phases. </p>

<p> </p>



<p>
Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors acknowledge support by the Center for Materials at Irradiation and Mechanical 
Extremes, an Energy Frontier Research Center funded by the U.S. Department of Energy, 
Office of Science, Office of Basic Energy Sciences under Award Number 2008LANL1026. 
IJB and RJM would like to acknowledge support through a Los Alamos National Laboratory 
Directed Research and Development (LDRD) project ER20140348. This work was 
performed, in part, at the Center for Integrated Nanotechnologies, an Office of Science User 
Facility operated for the U.S. Department of Energy, Office of Science. This work has also 
benefited from the use of the Lujan Neutron Scattering Center at LANSCE, funded by the 
U.S. Department of Energy, Office of Basic Energy Sciences. The authors appreciate 
collaboration pertaining to the neutron diffraction work with Dr. Sven C. Vogel of Los 
Alamos National Laboratory. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>S.Z. did the TEM and HRTEM characterization and wrote the manuscript. S.Z. and J.S.C. 
designed the experiments. J.S.C. and N.A.M. fabricated the composites. J.S.C. carried out 
neutron diffraction, nanohardness test and annealing. R.J.M. and J.S.C. did the WM-EBSD 
measurement. I.J.B. performed the simulations. All authors discussed the results and 
commented on the manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Zheng, S.J., Carpenter, J.S., McCabe, R.J., Beyerlein, I.J. &amp; Mara, 
N.A. Engineering Interface Structures and Thermal Stabilities via SPD Processing in Bulk 
Nanostructured Metals. Sci. Rep. 4, 4226; DOI:10.1038/srep04226 (2014). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported license. To view a copy of this license, 
visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4226 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04226 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>