<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3027082" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Aim: To determine if acetazolamide, an effective treatment for certain inherited channelopathies, has 
therapeutic effects on infantile nystagmus syndrome (INS) in a well-studied subject, compare them to other therapies in 
the same subject and to tenotomy and reattachment (T&amp;R) in other subjects. </p>

<p>Methods: Eye-movement data were taken using a high-speed digital video recording system. Nystagmus waveforms were 
analyzed by applying an eXpanded Nystagmus Acuity Function (NAFX) at different gaze angles and determining the 
Longest Foveation Domain (LFD). </p>

<p>Results: Acetazolamide improved foveation by both a 59.7% increase in the peak value of the NAFX function (from 
0.395 to 0.580) and a 70% broadening of the NAFX vs Gaze Angle curve (the LFD increased from 20° to 34°). The 
resulting U-shaped improvement in the percent NAFX vs Gaze Angle curve, varied from ~60% near the NAFX peak to 
over 1000% laterally. The therapeutic improvements in NAFX from acetazolamide (similar to T&amp;R) were intermediate 
between those of soft contact lenses and convergence, the latter was best; for LFD improvements, acetazolamide and 
contact lenses were equivalent and less effective than convergence. Computer simulations suggested that damping the 
central oscillation driving INS was insufficient to produce the foveation improvements and increased NAFX values. </p>

<p>Conclusion: Acetazolamide resulted in improved-foveation INS waveforms over a broadened range of gaze angles, 
probably acting at more than one site. This raises the question of whether hereditary INS involves an inherited 
channelopathy, and whether other agents with known effects on ion channels should be investigated as therapy for this 
condition. </p>

<p>Infantile nystagmus syndrome (INS) [1] is an ocular 
motor oscillation with well-defined waveforms and 
characteristics [2]. The pathogenesis of INS is unknown, but 
in some it is an inherited disorder in which several modes of 
inheritance have been identified [3]. The oscillations may be 
present at birth but often develop during early childhood and 
persist to some degree, despite the best current therapy. 
Although adaptive strategies often develop, such as 
foveation periods [4], the basic oscillations persist. 
Therapeutically, several approaches have been successfully 
employed to improve INS waveforms and expand the range 
of gaze angles with higher acuity [5, 6]. They include 
surgical [7-9], optical [10], and pharmaceutical [11-13] 
therapies. </p>

<p>*Address correspondence to this author at the Daroff-Dell'Osso Ocular 
Motility Laboratory, Louis Stokes Department of Cleveland Veterans 
Affairs Medical Center, 10701 East Boulevard, Cleveland, OH 44106 USA; 
Tel: (216) 421-3224; Fax: (216) 231-3461; E-mail: lfd@case.edu </p>

<p>Several underlying functional mechanisms for INS have 
been postulated and subsequently eliminated by ocular motor 
studies except one, loss of smooth-pursuit damping [14, 15]. 
This has been hypothesized to be the direct, functional cause 
of INS in all patients, whether or not they have associated, 
and precipitating afferent visual or genetic deficits. The 
hypothesized loss of smooth-pursuit damping was supported 
when embodied in a behavioral ocular motor system model 
that exhibited many emergent properties (not designed into 
it) [15]. It was further strengthened when the model 
subsequently predicted both the different INS responses to 
the same stimulus (based on its timing with regard to the INS 
cycle) [16, 17] and the therapeutic results of the tenotomy 
and reattachment (T&amp;R) procedure [8, 15, 18-20]. However, 
even if this functional hypothesis proves to be accurate, the 
pursuit-system instability itself could be the result of one or 
more abnormalities at the cellular or neuronal level in 
subsets of INS patients. </p>

<p>Following our fortuitous observation that acetazolamide, 
taken to prevent altitude sickness, improved the nystagmus </p>

<p>Acetazolamide and INS </p>

<p>The Open Ophthalmology Journal, 2010, Volume 4 43 </p>

<p>in a subject with hereditary INS, we set out to compare this 
potential therapy with two other measures that had 
previously been reported to be effective in this subject-
convergence (or wearing prism spectacles to induce 
convergence), and contact lenses. Since acetazolamide is 
known to be an effective treatment for certain inherited, P/Q 
calcium channel disorders, such as episodic ataxia type 2, 
our finding raises the question of whether hereditary INS 
also involves an inherited channelopathy. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODOLOGY </p>

<p>Recording </p>

<p>We used a digital video system (EyeLink II, SR 
Research, Mississauga, ON, Canada) for the eye-movement 
recordings. The system had a linear range of ±30 
horizontally and ±20 
vertically. System sampling 
frequency was 500 Hz, and gaze position accuracy error was 
0.5 -1 
on average. The data from this system were 
digitized at 500 Hz with 16-bit resolution. The EyeLink 
signal from each eye was calibrated with the other eye 
behind cover to obtain accurate position information; the 
foveation periods were used for calibration. For the contact-
lens experiment, calibration was done immediately after the 
subject's prescribed contact lenses were inserted. </p>

<p>Subject and Protocol </p>

<p>This study was approved by the local IRB and written 
consent was obtained from the subject before the testing. The 
subject was a calm 68-year-old male with INS. His 
nystagmus waveforms were well documented previously and 
their characteristics representative of others with INS. 
Because subjects have no voluntary control of their INS 
waveform characteristics, the data are not affected by 
subsequent testing. The subject had a convergence "null" 
and wore either 7 PD base-out prisms added to his refraction 
(OD: +3.00 S -2.50 C ax 150 and OS: +3.50 S -2.75 C ax 20) 
or contact lenses with no added prism. His best-corrected 
distance visual acuities were 20/25 with prisms and 20/40+ 
with contact lenses. For fixation targets, we use small LED's 
and reflected laser spots, which are not acuity limiting and 
yield the same ocular motor data with or without refraction. 
The subject was seated in a chair with a headrest and a chin 
stabilizer, far enough (&gt;5 feet) from the stimulus screen to 
prevent convergence effects. At this distance the target 
subtended less than 0.1 of visual angle. The room light 
was turned off during the recording. The contact-lens 
experiment consisted of five trials performed by the subject 
while wearing contact lenses; we allowed time between trials 
for the subject to rest. Each trial tested fixation of horizontal 
targets from 30° left gaze to 30° right gaze, in 5° steps. We 
used our standard patient paradigm to test the effects of 
acetazolamide on this subject. It consists of two trials, one in 
each direction (as described above), with the target 
remaining at each gaze angle for 5 sec during both the 
stepping out laterally and returning to primary position. 
Subtracting the required target acquisition times, this allows 
approximately 2-3 sec of steady fixation during each 
interval. NAFX values are calculated during steady fixations 
and averaged. This results in a small number of NAFX 
values at each gaze angle that we have found to be </p>

<p>historically very close to each other in value, usually 
differing in the third decimal place in several studies of 
many patients. Our paradigm for taking and analyzing such 
data is based on real-life acquisition and identification of 
new targets in one's visual field. </p>

<p>The subject took 500mg of acetazolamide twice a day for 
three days prior to the study. This dose of drug was chosen 
because it is the conventional dose for treating glaucoma and 
idiopathic intracranial hypertension and is usually tolerated 
with minimal side effects (500 mg to 1000 mg daily, in 
divided doses). The side effects consisted of transient 
paraesthesia of the hands (once on day two and once on day 
three), some abdominal discomfort on day two, and "general, 
mild discomfort" during days two and three. For 
comparisons of therapeutic effectiveness, we retrieved data 
from previous studies using the same subject [5, 10], who 
performed the same trials without any refractive correction at 
far and at near with a convergence angle of 60 PD. </p>

<p>Analysis </p>

<p>All the analysis was performed in the <rs id="software-0" type="software">MATLAB</rs> 
environment (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">The MathWorks</rs>, Natick, MA) using <rs id="software-1" type="software">OMLAB</rs> 
software (OMtools, downloadable from <rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://www.om lab.org</rs>). Eye position was sampled directly; it was pre-
filtered using a low-pass filter with a cutoff frequency of 20 
Hz to reduce the noise while minimally affecting the 
foveation periods. The 20-Hz value is five times the 
maximum frequency present in foveation periods (0-2 Hz) 
and still allows separation of foveating and braking saccades 
from those periods. Analysis was always done on the 
fixating eye. Segments with inattention or blinking were 
discarded. </p>

<p>We analyzed the data using the eXpanded Nystagmus 
Acuity Function (NAFX) [21]. It is an extension of the 
previous Nystagmus Acuity Function (NAF) that consists of 
a mathematical function containing the following waveform 
parameters: foveation-period duration, standard deviations of 
main foveation periods and velocities, and number of cycles 
in a fixation interval. In the <rs id="software-2" type="software">OMtools</rs> software, we use the 
NAFX's graphical user interface for data selection and 
analysis (details can be obtained from <rs corresp="#software-2" type="url">http://www.omlab.org/ OMLAB_page/Teaching/Using_NAFX.html</rs>) [22]. The 
NAFX provides an objective and repeatable measure of 
nystagmus foveation quality that accurately predicts the best-
corrected visual acuity possible for subjects without afferent 
visual system defects, regardless of the eye-movement 
recording system, the nystagmus type, and waveforms [21]. 
In the absence of afferent deficits, the NAFX is highly 
correlated with measured acuity. We averaged the NAFX 
values if several were obtained at each gaze angle. </p>

<p>The longest foveation domain (LFD) [5, 8] is defined as 
the range of gaze angles in which the subject's NAFX stays 
above 90% of the NAFX vs Gaze Angle curve's peak value. 
LFD is a measure of the broadness of the NAFX vs Gaze 
Angle curve, i.e., the INS subject's high-foveation-quality 
field. </p>

<p>Computer Simulations </p>

<p>Ocular motor simulations of the effects of acetazolamide 
on INS were performed in the MATLAB Simulink (The </p>



<p>Thurtell et al. </p>

<p>MathWorks, Natick, MA) environment. The most recent 
version of our behavioral ocular motor system (OMS) model 
(version 1.4) is also available from http://www.omlab.org. 
Details of the model can be found elsewhere [15, 17, 20, 23]. 
To simulate the subject's data, the NAFX peak was set to -2° 
and the breadth of the NAFX vs Gaze Angle curve was set to 
be moderate and symmetrical. To simulate the effects of 
acetazolamide, it was hypothesized to act centrally by </p>

<p>reducing the oscillation, originating in the damping control 
of smooth pursuit, which underlies most INS waveforms. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Subject Data </p>

<p>During fixation of a distant target, the subject had a peak 
NAFX of 0.385 at 2° left gaze. As Fig. (1a) shows, the </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>Fig. (1). a) Plots of NAFX vs Gaze Angle during fixation of far targets with no therapeutic aids, with contact lenses, with acetazolamide, and 
during convergence at 60 PD. The equivalent visual acuities shown are for subjects over 60 years of age. Curves are 2 
nd order polynomial fits 
to the data. N = "null" originally measured in 1963. b) Examples of the pre-and post-acetazolamide (heavy line) INS waveforms. Large 
spikes are blinks or video dropouts. </p>

<p>NAFX vs GAZE ANGLE 
(Contact Lenses, Acetazolamide, Convergence) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>-30 
-20 
-10 
0 
10 
20 
30 
Gaze Angle ( ) </p>

<p>Far 
Far with Contacts 
Far with Acetazolamide 
Conv @ 60 PD 
Poly. (Far) 
Poly. (Far with Contacts) 
Poly. (Far with Acetazolamide) 
Poly. (Conv @ 60 PD) </p>

<p>20/20 </p>

<p>20/25 </p>

<p>20/30 </p>

<p>20/40 </p>

<p>20/50 </p>

<p>20/100 </p>

<p>20/200 </p>

<p>20/70 </p>

<p>Visual 
Acuity 
&gt;60y/o </p>

<p>LFD=20 </p>

<p>LFD=34 </p>

<p>LFD=34 </p>

<p>LFD=59 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>10 
20 
30 
40 
−40 </p>

<p>−30 </p>

<p>−20 </p>

<p>−10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Time (sec) </p>

<p>Eye Position (°) </p>

<p>pre−Acetazolamide </p>

<p>post−Acetazolamide </p>

<p>Acetazolamide and INS </p>

<p>The Open Ophthalmology Journal, 2010, Volume 4 45 </p>

<p>breadth of the NAFX vs Gaze Angle curve given by the LFD 
function was 20°. When using contact lenses, the NAFX 
peak was 0.405 with an LFD of 34°, and when converged at 
60 PD, the NAFX peak was 0.755 with an LFD of 59°. 
During distant fixation while taking acetazolamide, the 
NAFX peak was 0.575 with an LFD of 34°. The NAFX 
values were slightly more variable for the acetazolamide data 
(mean standard deviation across gaze angles of 0.101) than 
for the other three conditions (0.095, 0.089, and 0.026 for 
distance, contact lenses, and convergence respectively). Fig. 
(1b) shows examples of the subject's waveforms pre-and 
post-acetazolamide. </p>

<p>The percent improvements in the NAFX at each gaze 
angle for the three therapies are shown in Fig. (2). Each 
therapy improved the NAFX values by roughly constant 
percentages within the central ±15° range of gaze angles, 15-
40%, 50-100%, and 100-185% for the contact lenses, 
acetazolamide, and convergence therapies respectively. In 
addition, the three therapies produced much greater 
improvements in lateral gaze (600%, 1050%, and 1600%, 
respectively). </p>

<p>Comparisons to Contact Lenses, Convergence, and 
Tenotomy and Reattachment </p>

<p>In addition to comparing the therapeutic effects (on peak 
NAFX and the LFD) of acetazolamide to contact lenses and 
convergence therapies, we also compared each to the 
estimated effects of the T&amp;R based on data from twenty-two 
patients [6]. Fig. (3a) demonstrates that acetazolamide raised 
the peak NAFX by an amount equivalent to that estimated 
for the T&amp;R procedure, whereas contact lenses fell short </p>

<p>while convergence was better. The LFD improvements for 
both acetazolamide and contact lenses were the same as for 
the T&amp;R procedure, but less than for convergence (Fig. 3b). 
Fig. (4) compares the actual post-therapeutic NAFX and 
LFD values of each therapy relative to the estimated T&amp;R 
values. </p>

<p>Computer Simulations </p>

<p>In order to investigate the possible mechanisms involved 
in these waveform improvements, we simulated the 
acetazolamide condition using a behavioral OMS model 
developed to investigate mechanistic ocular motor 
hypotheses ranging from normals to individuals with various 
ocular motor dysfunctions [8, 9, 14, 15, 19, 20, 23-32]. In an 
attempt to mimic the subject's INS characteristics, we used 
the OMS-model's built-in capabilities to set the NAFX peak 
to -2° with a symmetrical, medium Alexander's law 
variation of the INS amplitude with gaze angle. Fig. (5) 
shows the main components of the OMS model (Smooth 
Pursuit, Fixation, Saccadic Pulse Generator, Internal 
Monitor, Fast and Slow Neural Integrators, and Fast and 
Slow Plant pathways) and of the PMC+ Block (part of the 
Smooth Pursuit system responsible for its damping). There, 
we simulated the hypothesized central effect of 
acetazolamide by reducing the gain factor, "Central 
Therapy" from 1.3 (the value required to match this subject's 
pre-acetazolamide INS) to 0.6. As Fig. (6a) shows, the 
simulated INS amplitude increased at gaze angles lateral to -
2° (as did the subject's) and the simulated effects of 
acetazolamide resulted in damped INS waveforms at all gaze 
angles. Calculating the NAFX values from the simulation </p>

<p>Fig. (2). Plots of Percent Improvement in NAFX vs Gaze Angle during fixation of far targets with contact lenses, with acetazolamide, and 
during convergence at 60 PD. Curves are 6 
th order polynomial fits to the data. N = "null" originally measured in 1963. </p>

<p>% NAFX Improvement vs GAZE ANGLE </p>

<p>(Contact Lenses, Acetazolamide, Convergence) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>1400 </p>

<p>1600 </p>

<p>1800 </p>

<p>-30 
-20 
-10 
0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>Gaze Angle ( ) </p>

<p>Far with Acetazolamide </p>

<p>Far with Contacts </p>

<p>Conv @ 60 PD </p>

<p>Poly. (Far with Acetazolamide) </p>

<p>Poly. (Far with Contacts) </p>

<p>Poly. (Conv @ 60 PD) </p>

<p>N </p>



<p>Thurtell et al. </p>

<p>data at those gaze angles resulted in a match to the subject's 
far-fixation data and an improved but not broadened NAFX 
vs Gaze Angle curve (i.e., the LFD values remained the 
same) for the simulated effects of acetazolamide (Fig. 6b). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>Acetazolamide </p>

<p>Acetazolamide, a potent carbonic anhydrase inhibitor is 
the most common and best-studied agent for the amelioration </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>Fig. (3). Comparative plots of a) percent increases in peak NAFX vs Pre-therapy NAFX and b) percent increases in LFD vs pre-therapy LFD 
during fixation of far targets with contact lenses, with acetazolamide, and during convergence at 60 PD. Curves shown are the estimated 
percent increases in peak NAFX and LFD for the tenotomy and reattachment (T&amp;R) procedure. </p>

<p>0 
0.1 
0.2 
0.3 
0.4 
0.5 
0.6 
0.7 
0.8 
0.9 
1 
0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>Pre−Tenotomy NAFX </p>

<p>NAFX Increase (%) </p>

<p>Percent Increase in Peak NAFX </p>

<p>T&amp;R </p>

<p>Acetazolamide </p>

<p>Contact Lenses </p>

<p>60 PD Convergence </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 
35 
40 
0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>Pre−Tenotomy LFD (deg) </p>

<p>LFD Increase (%) </p>

<p>Percent Increase in Longest Foveation Domain </p>

<p>T&amp;R </p>

<p>60 PD Convergence </p>

<p>Contact Lenses 
Acetazolamide </p>

<p>Acetazolamide and INS </p>

<p>The Open Ophthalmology Journal, 2010, Volume 4 47 </p>

<p>of acute mountain sickness; it also is used in the treatment of 
idiopathic intracranial hypertension and as adjunctive 
treatment for primary open angle glaucoma. The aim of our 
study is to evaluate if this subject with INS, who took 
1000mg/day of acetazolamide for three days to prevent 
altitude sickness, showed changes in his nystagmus 
waveforms. However, this subject's INS waveforms at each 
gaze angle were unchanged by acetazolamide, as they have 
been since his first eye-movement recording in the mid 
1960's (compare also the original "null" position shown in </p>

<p>Figs. (1, 2) with the more recent NAFX peaks and % NAFX-
improvement troughs). Such intra-subject consistency is 
common, despite inter-subject variability, and has been 
documented in many patients who have had repeat studies in 
our laboratory years, or even decades, apart. Although 
acetazolamide did improve the average NAFX values over 
contact lenses, there was more variability at each gaze angle 
(possibly related to the subject's mild discomfort); this and 
the other the side effects might be contraindications to using 
acetazolamide (at the dosage used) as a therapy for INS. </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>Fig. (4). Comparative plots of a) post-therapy peak NAFX vs pre-therapy peak NAFX and b) post-therapy LFD vs pre-therapy LFD during 
fixation of far targets with contact lenses, with acetazolamide, and during convergence at 60 PD. Curves shown are the estimated peak 
NAFX and LFD for the tenotomy and reattachment (T&amp;R) procedure. </p>

<p>0 
0.1 
0.2 
0.3 
0.4 
0.5 
0.6 
0.7 
0.8 
0.9 
1 
0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Pre−Tenotomy NAFX </p>

<p>Post−Tenotomy NAFX </p>

<p>Post−Tenotomy Peak NAFX </p>

<p>T&amp;R </p>

<p>60 PD Convergence </p>

<p>Contact Lenses </p>

<p>Acetazolamide </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 
35 
40 
0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>Pre−Tenotomy LFD (deg) </p>

<p>Post−Tenootomy LFD (deg) </p>

<p>Post−Tenotomy Longest Foveation Domain </p>

<p>T&amp;R </p>

<p>Acetazolamide 
Contact Lenses </p>

<p>60 PD Convergence </p>



<p>Thurtell et al. </p>

<p>Underlying Mechanisms </p>

<p>Ocular motility studies of INS have demonstrated that, 
despite minor idiosyncrasies and whether or not there is an 
associated visual abnormality or it is hereditary, all INS is 
the same disorder (i.e., the same common waveforms and 
their characteristic variations with gaze and vergence 
angles). Thus, the ocular motor system instability is 
indistinguishable between patient subpopulations and has the 
same direct, functional cause (e.g., loss of pursuit-system 
damping). As is evident from the literature, the terminology 
used and the questions posed when discussing the "cause" of 
a disorder often reflect one's training or approach to the 
problem. The geneticist speaks of a genetic abnormality, the 
physiologist or anatomist, of the misbehavior of a group of 
cells, their absence, or misrouting of their connections, and 
the control-systems analysist, of an unstable feedback loop. 
However, such diverse putative "causes" of a condition may 
be neither contradictory nor repetitious. Rather, each is a 
meaningful description to those with the corresponding 
background, while the other descriptions may seem 
somehow lacking. Going from initial speculation to a 
realistic hypothesis for INS requires establishing a functional 
connection between the putative "cause" and the resulting </p>

<p>eye oscillation and ocular motor behavior. For example, in 
some with INS, a genetic abnormality or spontaneous 
occurrence could result in a channelopathy of the subset of 
cells that set the smooth-pursuit damping gain. Other INS 
patients might have calibration of that gain altered by lack of 
adequate visual input, still others by another physiological or 
anatomical disorder of the cells controlling pursuit damping. 
In all of these putative scenarios, the INS instability will be 
indistinguishable among patients, the direct, functional cause 
will be the same, but the precipitating factors and lower level 
mechanisms will differ. </p>

<p>Comparative Therapies </p>

<p>As Figs. (3, 4) shows, there are broad ranges of initial 
NAFX and LFD values within which the T&amp;R procedure 
produces significant improvements (e.g., 0.05 NAFX 0.6 
and 2.5° LFD 25°). This use of accurate eye-movement 
data to diagnose INS and determine the therapeutic approach 
with the maximal therapeutic efficacy has also resulted in an 
analysis procedure whereby we can estimate a priori the 
percent improvement and final values for both the NAFX 
and LFD; the former also allows estimation of the 
improvement in measured (not just potential) visual acuity of </p>

<p>Fig. (5). Block diagrams of the behavioral ocular motor system model and the PMC+ block (controlling damping within the Smooth Pursuit 
system) where the hypothesized central effect of acetazolamide was simulated. The gain factor "Central Therapy" (lower input to the final 
multiplier) was adjusted downward from its pre-acetazolamide value of 1.3. </p>

<p>Acetazolamide and INS </p>

<p>The Open Ophthalmology Journal, 2010, Volume 4 49 </p>

<p>INS patients with or without afferent visual deficits [6]. The 
present study demonstrates how, for an individual patient, 
we can determine the relative improvements of several 
different types of therapies and compare them to the 
estimated improvement from the T&amp;R procedure. The 
effects of this drug are independent of, and act at different 
sites from, either convergence or gaze-angle nulls. 
Therefore, the presence or absence of convergence or gaze-
angle nulls would not alter the effects of the drug on INS. 
Therapeutic effects of such diverse treatments have been </p>

<p>shown to be multiplicative, acting in different ways at 
different sites. This is the first time objective INS eye-
movement data analyses have been used for these purposes. </p>

<p>The outcome data from vergence prisms also represents 
the results of performing a bimedial rectus recession 
procedure, since the resulting induced convergence to align 
the eyes has equivalent effects on INS in the two cases. Our 
research has shown that it is the act of convergence that 
damps INS in those patients who demonstrate this effect. </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>Fig. (6). (a) Plots of OMS model outputs simulating far fixation at 0°, ±10°, and ±20° for both the pre-and post-acetazolamide (heavy line) 
conditions. (b) Plots of NAFX vs Gaze Angle for the simulated data in (a). Shown for comparison is the Far curve from the subject's data. </p>

<p>NAFX vs GAZE ANGLE 
(Simulated Far and Acetazolamide) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>-30 
-20 
-10 
0 
10 
20 
30 
Gaze Angle ( ) </p>

<p>Far 
Far Simulation </p>

<p>Acetazolamide Simulation 
Poly. (Far) </p>

<p>Poly. (Far Simulation) 
Poly. (Acetazolamide Simulation) </p>

<p>20/20 </p>

<p>20/25 </p>

<p>20/30 </p>

<p>20/40 </p>

<p>20/50 </p>

<p>20/100 </p>

<p>20/200 </p>

<p>20/70 </p>

<p>Visual 
Acuity 
&gt;60y/o </p>

<p>LFD=20 </p>

<p>LFD=20 </p>

<p>LFD=20 </p>

<p>N </p>



<p>Thurtell et al. </p>

<p>That act of convergence is the same whether or not it is 
induced by prisms or by a surgically induced divergence. 
The static concept of "weakening" a muscle is of little use in 
understanding the dynamic effects of most eye-muscle 
surgery or vergence on an oscillation like INS. Although the 
antagonist muscles of each eye receive different innervations 
for convergence, the resultant force is equal in each muscle. 
Rather, it is alteration of the proprioceptively controlled 
resting muscle tension that is responsible. In fact, we test for 
the efficacy of the bimedial rectus recession procedure in 
binocular patients with an INS convergence null by having 
them wear BO prisms. Also, due to the fact that the muscles 
wrap around the equator and attach closer to the cornea, 
small recessions do not substantially weaken the mechanical 
advantage of the muscle. The different innervations of the 
EOM during convergence result in equal and opposite forces 
in the two antagonist muscles of each eye and are not what 
reduces their small-signal gain. Prism-induced vergence 
produces the same broadening effects as the T&amp;R procedure, 
implying the same mechanism of action and removing the 
requirement for the addition of bilateral rectus muscle T&amp;R 
to the bimedial rectus recession procedure. Based on our 
analyses of hundreds of INS patients, where convergence 
nulls have always been greater than gaze-angle nulls, we 
concluded long ago that inducing convergence in binocular 
patients with convergence damping would have greater 
therapeutic improvement than any other known therapy-
either base-out prisms or the bimedial rectus recession 
procedure should be the therapy of choice in these patients. 
Because the eye-movement data from this subject are 
representative of the INS population in general, if surgery 
were to be considered for the subject of this study, maximal 
therapeutic improvement would result from a bimedial rectus 
recession procedure. There is no evidence that inducing 
convergence by either method will cause strabismus in these 
binocular patients; both therapies have resulted in large, 
sustained improvements in visual function. Further 
neurophysiological study of convergence's effects on 
proprioception is needed to clarify the specific mechanism 
involved. </p>

<p>The past four decades of INS research suggests that the 
direct, functional cause of INS is the miscalibration of 
smooth-pursuit damping [14, 15, 28]. Therapies may either be 
directed: 1) afferently to alleviate the visual condition that 
interfered with damping calibration [33-35]; 2) centrally at the 
cells responsible for damping miscalibration (as some drugs 
may do, although they may also act elsewhere with possibly 
undesirable side effects) [11-13]; or 3) peripherally to reduce 
the effects of the underlying instability (e.g., vergence prisms, 
contact lenses, or the T&amp;R procedure) [7, 8, 36]. It is unclear 
whether acetazolamide affected a channelopathy in a subset of 
central or peripheral neurons (i.e., whether it affected the 
"cause" or merely ameliorated the "effect"-as does the T&amp;R 
procedure). Finally, to the extent that one particular type of 
therapy insufficiently improves the INS waveform, other types 
may be added that will multiply the therapeutic improvement 
[37]. </p>

<p>Recent work on the pathogenesis of some hereditary forms 
of INS has focused on the FRMD7 gene, which is expressed in 
retina and cerebellum. Exactly how mutations of this gene 
could cause INS is debated, although the cerebellum plays an 
important role in smooth tracking eye movements and gaze </p>

<p>holding. Future studies aimed at investigating whether ion 
channels or specific neurotransmitters are affected by the 
FRMD7 gene may lead to identifying more specific drug 
therapies for hereditary INS [38]. </p>

<p>Computer Simulations </p>

<p>We used computer simulations to explore a possible 
mechanism of action of acetazolamide in this subject's INS. 
After simulating the subject's INS waveform variation with 
gaze angle, we investigated the effects on INS of simply 
reducing the oscillatory signal in the smooth-pursuit damping 
circuitry (no other changes to the model were made). That is, 
we hypothesized that acetazolamide has the single ocular 
motor effect of centrally damping the causal INS oscillation. 
Analysis of the simulated results produced an NAFX vs Gaze 
Angle curve that was higher (i.e., allowing better visual 
acuity) but not wider (i.e., allowing high acuity over more 
gaze angles). This did not accurately simulate the subject's 
data, which showed both improvements. Thus, this single-site 
hypothesis for the effects of acetazolamide on this subject was 
disproven; i.e., the model suggested that acetazolamide's 
action was not limited to only that ocular motor site. This 
should not be surprising, given its systemic actions as 
evidenced by the unrelated side effects. </p>

<p>Our computer simulations demonstrated that a central 
reduction in the magnitude of the initial INS instability was 
insufficient to mimic the measured INS-waveform 
improvements and suggested that acetazolamide also acts 
centrally at another site to broaden the Alexander's law 
variation of INS amplitude. That combination could be 
simulated in the same way the pre-acetazolamide simulation 
was matched to the subject's far-fixation data. A third 
possibility is that acetazolamide acted peripherally and 
therefore, affected INS in a manner similar to that of the T&amp;R 
procedure; we have already simulated and reported those 
peripheral therapeutic effects [20]. Finally, acetazolamide 
could have acted both centrally and peripherally. </p>

<p>The efficacy of acetazolamide as a therapy requires studies 
at a reduced dosage to determine if its therapeutic effects can 
be maintained without side effects. In addition, the 
repeatability of its effects over time and the number and type 
of patients (i.e., other than those with hereditary INS) in whom 
it is effective need to be determined. Other, similar drugs (e.g., 
methazolamide) should also be investigated. The results of this 
preliminary study provide a foundation for a randomized, 
double-blind, drug-efficacy study of these drugs in patients 
with INS and a comparison to the known effects of other 
drugs on INS [11, 12] and to the known surgical effects. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT </p>

<p>This work was supported in part by the Office of Research 
and Development, Medical Research Service, Department of 
Veterans Affairs. </p>



<p>Acetazolamide and INS </p>

<p>The Open Ophthalmology Journal, 2010, Volume 4 51 </p>



<p>Received: December 13, 2009 
Revised: January 26, 2010 
Accepted: January 29, 2010 </p>

<p>© Thurtell et al.; Licensee Bentham Open. 
This is an open access article licensed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http: //creativecommons.org/licenses/by-
nc/3.0/) which permits unrestricted, non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the work is properly cited. </p>

</text></tei>