<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3518495" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:48+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The immune system constitutes one of the first-line defenses to 
prevent tumor development, owing to its ability to identify and 
destroy tumor cells. This process, which has been termed can-
cer immunosurveillance, has gained considerable attention in 
the last years. One of the most important immune effector cells 
are macrophages, which exert multiple biological roles, including 
antigen presentation as well as the regulation of inflammation 
and tissue remodeling. Moreover, macrophages are involved in 
the etiology of a variety of pathological conditions including can-
cer. In particular, tumor-associated macrophages (TAMs) have 
been found to contribute to tumor initiation, progression and 
metastasis. TAMs have been proposed to exhibit many similari-
ties in terms of gene expression and functions with "alternatively-
activated" M2 macrophages. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Macrophages are classified in two different polariza-
tion phenotypes according to distinct functional properties: </p>

<p>The aRF locus is frequently inactivated in human cancer. The oncosuppressor aRF has indeed been described as a 
general sensor for different situation of cellular stress. We have previously demonstrated that aRF deficiency severely 
impairs inflammatory responses in vitro and in vivo, establishing a role for aRF in the regulation of innate immunity. 
The aim of the present work was to get further insights into the immune functions of aRF and to evaluate its possible 
contribution to the polarization of macrophages toward the M1 or M2 phenotype. Our results demonstrate that resting 
arf 
−/− macrophages express high levels of Ym1 and Fizz-1, two typical markers of alternatively-activated macrophages 
(M2). additionally, arf 
−/− peritoneal macrophages showed an impaired response to lipopolysaccharide (a classical inducer 
of M1 polaryzation) and a reduced production of pro-inflammatory cytokines/chemokines. Moreover, upon stimulation 
with interleukin-4 (IL-4), an inducer of the M2 phenotype, well established M2 markers such as Fizz-1, Ym1 and arginase-1 
were upregulated in arf 
−/− as compared with wild type macrophages. accordingly, the cytokine and chemokine profile 
associated with the M2 phenotype was significantly overexpressed in arf 
−/− macrophages responding to IL-4. In addition, 
multiple pro-angiogenic factors such as VeGF and MMp-9 were also increased. In summary, these results indicate that 
aRF contributes to the polarization and functional plasticity of macrophages. </p>

<p>Role of the tumor suppressor ARF 
in macrophage polarization </p>

<p>Enhancement of the M2 phenotype in ARF-deficient mice </p>

<p>sandra herranz, 
1 paqui G. Través, 
2 alfonso Luque 
3 and sonsoles hortelano </p>

<p>1, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Unidad de Inflamación y cáncer; Área de Biología celular y Desarrollo; centro Nacional de Microbiología; Instituto de salud carlos III; Madrid, spain; 
2 Molecular Neurobiology Laboratory; The salk Institute; La Jolla, ca Usa; 
3 centro de Investigación en sanidad animal (cIsa-INIa); Madrid, spain </p>

<p>Keywords: ARF, alternative activation, IL-4, macrophage, TAMs </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ARF, alternative reading frame; Arg-1, arginase-1; COX-2, cyclooxigenase-2; Fizz-1, found in inflammatory zone 1; 
IFNγ, interferon γ; LPS, lipopolysaccharide; MMR, mannose receptor; MMP-9, matrix metalloproteinase-9; M1, classically-
activated macrophages; M2, alternatively-activated macrophages; NO, nitric oxide; iNOS, inducible nitric oxide syntase; PGE 2 , 
prostaglandin E2; TAM, tumor-associated macrophages; TIMP-3, metalloproteinase inhibitor 3; TNFα, tumor necrosis factor α; 
VEGF, vascular endotelial growth factor; Ym1, chitinase 3-like 3 </p>

<p>classically-activated (M1) and alternatively-activated (M2) mac-
rophages. 
2 M1 macrophages are induced by interferon γ (IFNγ) 
either alone or in combination with microbial stimuli such as lipo-
polysaccharide (LPS) or cytokines (e.g., tumor necrosis factor α, 
TNFα, and granulocyte macrophage colony-stimulating factor, 
GM-CSF). These macrophages produce pro-inflammatory cyto-
kines including TNFα, interleukin (IL)-1, IL-6, IL-12 or IL-23, 
as well as other pro-inflammatory mediators such as nitric 
oxide (NO, upon the expression of inducible nitric oxide syn-
thase, iNOS), all of which are essential for killing pathogens 
and for priming antitumor immune responses. 
2 In contrast, 
IL-4/IL-13 stimulation induces M2 macrophages, which have 
an important role in the response to parasites, tissue remodel-
ing, angiogenesis and tumor progression. M2 macrophages 
downregulate IL-12 expression and produce the anti-inflam-
matory cytokine IL-10. Additionally, M2 macrophages are 
characterized by the expression of several surface markers includ-
ing arginase 1 (Arg-1) and the mannose receptor (MMR). </p>

<p>2-4 </p>



<p>OncoImmunology 
Volume 1 Issue 8 </p>

<p>Our results demonstrate that ARF deficiency switch mac-
rophages to a M2-like phenotype. Thus, resting Arf 
−/− macro-
phages overexpress typical M2 markers such as Ym1 and Fizz-1, 
as well as the Ccl17 chemokine. Furthermore, compared to their 
wild type (WT) counterparts, ARF-deficient cells showed an 
altered expression of pro-inflammatory mediators and cytokines 
such as NO, IL-12, IL-6 and TNFα after stimulation with LPS. 
The cytokine/chemokine pattern induced by IL-4 stimulation 
appeared upregulated in macrophages isolated from Arf 
−/− mice, 
showing a M2-like phenotype featuring higher levels of IL-10, 
Ccl22, Ccl5, Ccr3 or Ccr5. A significantly enhanced arginase 
activity and the upregulation of surface receptors such as Fizz-1 
and Ym1 were also observed. Finally, important pro-angiogenic 
factors such as vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) and </p>

<p>Interestingly, genes associated with tissue remodelling such 
as found in inflammatory zone 1 (FIZZ1) and chitinase 3-like 
3 (YM1) have been considered new M2-polarization associated 
genes. </p>

<p>5,6 </p>

<p>We have recently described that the tumor suppressor ARF 
(alternative reading frame; p14 
ARF in humans, p19 
ARF in mice) 
plays an important role in the regulation of innate immunity and 
inflammatory processes. 
7 Mice lacking the Arf gene are resistant 
to LPS-endotoxic shock, and Arf-deficient macrophages showed a 
severely impaired production of inflammatory mediators includ-
ing NO, cytokines and chemokines. Since this phenotype showed 
numerous similarities to that of M2 macrophages, we wondered 
whether ARF could contribute to the polarization and functional 
plasticity of macrophages. </p>

<p>Figure 1. expression of M1 and M2 markers in resting WT and aRF-deficient macrophages. peritoneal WT and aRF-deficient macrophages were 
obtained as described in Material and Methods. cells were cultured in RpMI 1640 medium for 24 h, followed by RNa isolation. (A) Mannose macro-
phage receptor (MMR), arginase 1 (arg-1), Ym1 and Fizz-1 expression was assessed by quantitative pcR. Results were obtained from five independent 
experiments performed in triplicate and data are reported as means ± sD (B) iNOs, cOX-2, IL-6 and TNFα expression was assessed by quantitative pcR. 
Results were obtained from five independent experiments performed by triplicate and data are reported as means ± sD (C) Quantitative pcR confir-
mation of selected genes identified by microarray studies. Results were obtained from three independent experiments with 4-5 mice per group and 
data are reported as means ± sD *p &lt; 0.05 and **p &lt; 0.01, as compared with WT macrophages. </p>

<p>We next compared the genetic profiles of WT and Arf 
−/− mac-
rophages after stimulation with LPS. We found that LPS induced 
31 pro-inflammatory genes in WT macrophages including genes 
coding for chemokines (Ccl3, Ccl4, Cxcl1, and Cxcl10), cyto-
kines (IL-1α, IL-1β) and other inflammatory mediators such 
as TNFα and IFNγ (Fig. 3A; Table 2). LPS-treated Arf 
−/− cells 
expressed markedly lower levels of 22 out of these 31 genes, 
and a significant upregulation of 8 genes, including Ccl5 and 
Ccl17. Additionally, we found two genes only upregulated in 
Arf 
−/− macrophages responding to LPS, namely Ccl8 and IL10ra 
(Fig. 3; Table 2). 
The absence of ARF promotes exacerbated M2 polarization 
in response to IL-4 and IL-3. IL-4 and IL-13 are prototypic 
cytokines that induce the alternative activation of macrophages. 
To ascertain the role of ARF in this pathway, we evaluated the 
M2-like response on WT and Arf 
−/− peritoneal macrophages 
generated upon stimulation with IL-4 or IL-13. As shown in 
Figure 4A, LPS or IFNγ treatment induced NO release, a 
marker for classical activation, whereas IL-4 or IL-13 did not 
affect the levels of this pro-inflammatory mediator. Consistently 
with these findings, neither iNOS nor COX-2 overexpression 
was observed in macrophages activated with IL-4 or IL-13 
(Fig. 4C). Opposite to the NO release observed by M1-activated 
macrophages, the alternative polarization is characterized by the 
upregulation of Arg-1, an inducible enzyme that competes with 
iNOS for l-arginine and thus can prevent NO release. 
8 Classical 
activation of macrophages with LPS had no effect on Arg-1 
activation (Fig. 4D). In contrast, IL-4 promoted a &gt; 50-fold 
induction in Arg-1 expression in WT macrophages (Fig. 4D). 
Interestingly, Arf 
−/− macrophages showed a much more strik-
ing and significant increase of Arg-1 after IL-4 stimulation 
(Fig. 4D). The markedly raised mRNA levels for Arg-1 in Arf </p>

<p>−/− </p>

<p>macrophages were confirmed at the protein level by immunob-
lotting analysis (Fig. 4E). Moreover, an increment in arginase </p>

<p>matrix metalloproteinase 9 (MMP-9) were increased in ARF-
deficient macrophages, suggesting that these cells may exert pro-
tumorigenic functions. 
In summary, the current study strongly suggests that ARF 
has a profound influence in regulating the polarization of mac-
rophages and points to ARF as a novel regulator of the immune 
tumor microenvironment. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>ARF deficiency promotes the expression of M2 markers. To 
explore the contribution of the tumor suppressor ARF to mac-
rophage polarization, we first analyzed by quantitative PCR 
the expression levels of typical hallmarks of M2 polarization 
on WT vs. Arf 
−/− resting macrophages. The levels of the genes 
encoding Fizz-1 and Ym1 were significantly higher in ARF-
deficient macrophages than in their WT counterparts. Arg-1 
also showed a tendency to be overexpressed, although the data 
were not statistically significant. Nevertheless, MMR gene was 
unaffected in this situation (Fig. 1A). In contrast, M1 polariza-
tion markers such as iNOS, COX-2, IL-6 or TNFα were not 
altered in Arf 
−/− macrophages. In addition to the modulation of 
surface markers expression, M1 and M2 macrophages display 
different cytokines and chemokines gene expression profiles. 
In order to analyze whether ARF deficiency alters these pro-
files, we performed a microarray analysis of 84 genes coding for 
pro-inflammatory cytokines and their receptors. The full list of 
genes and fold changes are shown in Table S1. As depicted in 
Table 1, ARF appears to play a key role in regulating the basal 
expression of several genes related with M2 polarization. Thus, 
in the group of genes upregulated in Arf 
−/− macrophages, we 
found Ccl12 and Ccl17, two chemokines related to the M2 phe-
notype. In contrast, the expression of M1-related chemokines 
(Ccl2 and Cxcl10) was reduced. Microarray data were validated 
by quantitative PCR (Fig. 1C). These results suggest that ARF 
deficiency might modulate macrophage differentiation toward a 
M2-like phenotype. 
Impaired M1 polarization in ARF-deficient macrophages. 
One of the characteristics of M2-polarized cells is their ability 
to wane the inflammatory/immune response by inhibiting M1 
macrophage-mediated functions. M1 macrophages are mainly 
induced by IFNγ or upon stimulation with bacterial products 
such as LPS. To investigate whether ARF deficiency contributes 
to the downregulation of M1-mediated inflammatory activities, 
we examined the levels of classical inflammatory mediators such 
as NO and prostaglandin E 2 (PGE 2 ). Peritoneal macrophages 
from WT and Arf 
−/− mice were stimulated with LPS or IFNγ. As 
expected, the stimulation of WT macrophages with LPS gener-
ated high NO and PGE 2 levels, whereas a deficient response was 
observed in the absence of Arf (Fig. 2A and B). Accordingly, 
iNOS and COX-2 expression was upregulated in WT cells 
responding to LPS and IFNγ, as compared with Arf 
−/− macro-
phages (Fig. 2C and D). Similar to LPS, IFNγ induced NO 
release and iNOS activation, and once again, Arf 
−/− cells showed 
a significantly reduced response as compared with WT macro-
phages (Fig. 2E-G). </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com 
OncoImmunology </p>

<p>
Table 1. Basal gene expression profiles in arf 
−/− vs. wild type resting 
macrophages </p>

<p>Symbol 
Description 
Fold change p value </p>

<p>ccl12 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 12 
2,7045 
0,29821 </p>

<p>ccl17 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 17 
6,2512 
0,00196 </p>

<p>ccl2 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 2 
0,331 
0,00596 </p>

<p>cxcl10 chemokine (c-X-c motif) ligand 10 
0,2134 
0,00843 </p>

<p>cxcl15 chemokine (c-X-c motif) ligand 15 
2,8189 
0,22657 </p>

<p>Il2rb 
Interleukin 2 receptor, β chain 
2,147 
0,5172 </p>

<p>Il5ra 
Interleukin 5 receptor, α 
3,404 
0,26724 </p>

<p>Ltb 
Lymphotoxin B 
4,4502 
0,20412 </p>

<p>Tnfrsf1b 
Tumor necrosis factor receptor 
superfamily, member 1b 
49,2344 
0,37387 </p>

<p>Xcr1 
chemokine (c motif) receptor 1 
2,6956 
0,27068 </p>

<p>peritoneal macrophages from wild type (WT) and arf 
−/− mice were 
obtained as described in Material and Methods. cells were cultured in 
RpMI 1640 medium for 24 h, followed by lysis and RNa isolation. The 
expression of pro-inflammatory genes was analyzed by RT 
2 pcR analysis. 
p values were calculated based on student's t tests comparing 2 </p>

<p>−Δct </p>

<p>values for each gene. </p>



<p>OncoImmunology 
Volume 1 Issue 8 </p>

<p>treatment (Figs. 5D and E), suggesting a pro-tumoral function 
for these cells. 
Cytokine and chemokine expression profiles in IL-4-treated 
macrophages. To obtain a more comprehensive understanding 
of the cytokine/chemokine repertoire induced by IL-4 in Arf </p>

<p>−/− </p>

<p>macrophages, we performed a microarray-based gene expression 
analysis. After 6 h of stimulation, only 14 genes were upregulated 
(&gt; 2-fold) in WT macrophages (Fig. 6A; Table 3). The over-
expressed genes Ccl24, Ccl6, Ccr3, Ccr5 and Il6st were IL-4 
specific since LPS treatment did not modify their expression 
levels (Fig. 3A). In addition, we also found some chemokines 
and receptors (Ccl11, Ccl22, Ccl5, and CCr3) highly expressed 
in IL-4 stimulated Arf 
−/− macrophages as compared with WT 
cells. These results were validated by quantitative PCR analysis </p>

<p>activity using an urea-based assay was observed in Arf 
−/− macro-
phages as compared with WT cells (Fig. 4F). 
In agreement with the anti-inflammatory activity of M2 
macrophages, the expression of IL-10 was considerably higher 
in Arf 
−/− macrophages (Fig. 5A). The differential expression of 
IL-10 in both types of macrophages was confirmed by measuring 
IL-10 levels in the supernatant (Fig. 5B). Moreover, we observed 
a higher expression of typical M2-surface markers (i.e., Fizz-1, 
Ym1 and MMR) in Arf 
−/− macrophages responding to IL-4, as 
compared with their WT counterparts (Fig. 5C). 
In most tumor types, TAMs resemble alternatively activated 
macrophages in several aspects, including the release of pro-
angiogenic factors. We observed that Arf 
−/− macrophages sig-
nificantly increased VEGF and MMP-9 expression after IL-4 </p>

<p>Figure 2. attenuated inflammatory response of aRF deficient macrophages to classical activation. (A) peritoneal WT and aRF-deficient macrophages 
were stimulated with 200 ng/mL lipopolysaccharide (Lps) for 24 h and NO release was determined by the Griess reaction. (B) pGe 2 levels were assessed 
by eLIsa in cells treated as in (A). (C) peritoneal macrophages from WT and aRF-deficient mice were activated for 6 h with 200 ng/mL Lps and expres-
sion of iNOs and cOX-2 was evaluated by quantitative pcR. (D) protein levels of iNOs and cOX-2 were evaluated by immunoblotting after stimulation of 
peritoneal macrophages with 200 ng/mL Lps for the indicated time. Band intensities were quantified by densitometry, normalized to β-actin levels and 
represented as means ± sD of the fold change from control condition (n = 3). (E) NO release of peritoneal macrophages from WT and arf 
−/− mice after 
stimulation for 24 h with 50 ng/mL interferon γ (IFNγ). (F) iNOs induction was examined by quantitative pcR in WT and arf 
−/− cells after treatment with 
50 ng/mL IFNγ for 6 h. (G) protein levels of iNOs were evaluated by immunoblotting after stimulation of peritoneal macrophages with 50 ng/mL IFNγ for 
24 h. Results were obtained from three independent experiments performed in triplicate and data are reported as means ± sD *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01 and 
***p &lt; 0.001 as compared with the same condition in WT macrophages. (D and G) are representative of one out of three independent experiments. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>OncoImmunology </p>

<p>
state of TAMs. We demonstrate that, in the absence of ARF, mac-
rophages have an impaired ability to develop pro-inflammatory 
properties, rather showing anti-inflammatory characteristics. 
Arf 
−/− macrophages expressed higher levels of IL-10, Fizz-1, Ym1, 
and increased arginase activity and lower levels of IL-12, TNFα, 
IFNγ, PGE 2 and NO. Moreover, Arf 
−/− macrophages showed the 
upregulation of important pro-angiogenic factors (VEGF and 
MMP-9), which might contribute to tumor progression. These 
findings highlight the importance of ARF in the regulation of 
macrophage activation. 
The tumor suppressor ARF is among the genes most frequently 
mutated in human cancer. 
9 Loss of ARF gene expression can abro-
gate immunosurveillance mechanisms and increase the suscepti-
bility to cancer. Indeed, mice lacking p19ARF are highly prone to 
tumor development 
10,11 and deletion of ARF has been described 
in a variety of malignancies, including glioblastoma, melanoma, 
pancreatic adenocarcinoma, and non-small cell lung cancer. 
Interestingly, M2-polarized TAMs have been associated with poor 
prognosis and progression in many of these malignancies. 
Based on these premises and on our previous results show-
ing impairment in the pro-inflammatory activation of </p>

<p>(Fig. 6B). Altogether, these data suggest that ARF deficiency 
promotes an enhanced response to inducers of the M2 polariza-
tion program, promoting a chemokine/cytokine pattern that may 
be viewed as that of a "hyper-M2" phenotype. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Macrophages are dynamic cells that might modify their func-
tional profiles in response to the microenvironment. Moreover, 
macrophages are increasingly recognized as pivotal regulators 
of tumorigenesis. Accumulating evidence suggests that macro-
phages that infiltrate tumors acquire a phenotype of alterna-
tive activation (M2), exerting immunosuppressive functions 
through the release of anti-inflammatory cytokines and facili-
tating the progression of tumors via the production of pro-
angiogenic factors. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Previously, we have described that the tumor suppressor ARF 
is an important mediator of the inflammatory response and of 
macrophage activation. 
7 In the current study, we investigated 
whether ARF deficiency promotes macrophage differentiation 
toward a phenotype that resembles the alternatively-activated </p>

<p>Figure 3. Differential Lps-inducible cytokine/chemokine profile in WT and arf 
−/− cells. (A) DNa microarray analysis of lipopolysaccharide (Lps)-induc-
ible cytokines/receptors differentially expressed in WT macrophages vs. arf 
−/− macrophages. peritoneal macrophages from WT and aRF-deficient mice 
were treated with 200 ng/mL Lps for 6 h, followed by microarray studies. In red and green, genes upregulated and downregulated, respectively, in 
response to Lps are indicated. (B) a panel of genes was selected for validation by quantitative pcR analysis based on microarray results. Results were 
obtained from three independent experiments performed in triplicate and data are reported as means ± sD *p &lt; 0.05, and **p &lt; 0.01, as compared 
with the same condition in WT macrophages. </p>



<p>OncoImmunology 
Volume 1 Issue 8 </p>

<p>Arf 
−/− macrophages. In primary macrophages stimulated with 
LPS or IFNγ, these included genes coding for pro-inflammatory 
cytokines (TNFα, IL-1β), chemokines (Cxcl10, Cxcl1, Ccl4) 
and inflammatory mediators (iNOS/PGE 2 ). Accordingly, the 
absence of Arf is known to reduce the susceptibility of mice to 
septic shock. 
7 Although mechanisms involved in this inhibitory 
effect have not been explored in this study, a decrease in NFκB 
and MAPK activation has been described in Arf 
−/− macrophages 
responding to LPS. 
7 Similarly, inhibited degradation of IκB has 
been observed in ARF-deficient macrophages stimulated with 
the vesicular stomatis virus. 
12 Interestingly, the nuclear transloca-
tion of the p65/p50 heterodimers mainly associated with classical 
NFκB activation was also inhibited in macrophages from Arf </p>

<p>−/− </p>

<p>mice responding to LPS stimulation, 
7 whereas massive accumula-
tion of the p50 homodimer was observed (unpublished results), 
supporting the idea that ARF deficiency favors M2-driven 
inflammatory reactions. 
In addition to the downregulation of pro-inflammatory 
mediators, typical hallmarks of the anti-inflammatory M2 phe-
notype were increased in both resting and IL-4-treated Arf </p>

<p>−/− </p>

<p>macrophages, including Arg-1, Fizz-1 and Ym1. In mice, M2 
macrophages are characterized by an alternative metabolism of 
l-arginine, mainly catalyzed by Arg-1. Arg-1 is a cytosolic enzyme 
expressed at high levels in M2 macrophages that hydrolyzes </p>

<p>Arf 
−/− macrophages, we hypothesized that ARF might modulate 
the M1/M2 polarization and functional plasticity of macrophages. 
We have demonstrated that genes involved in M1 polarization, 
antimicrobial and antitumoral responses are downregulated in </p>

<p>Table 2. Inflammatory gene expression in lipopolysaccharide-activated 
wild type and aRF-deficient macrophages </p>

<p>Symbol 
Description 
Fold change </p>

<p>WT 
Arf </p>

<p>−/− </p>

<p>casp1 
caspase 1 
2,3858 
3,6185 </p>

<p>ccl12 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 12 
339,1902 
293,5526 </p>

<p>ccl17 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 17 
15,46 
31,5263 </p>

<p>ccl2 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 2 
37,6895 
49,6193 </p>

<p>ccl22 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 22 
47,0971 
17,1265 </p>

<p>ccl3 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 3 
65,9904 
36,7995 </p>

<p>ccl4 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 4 
92,4702 
40,9398 </p>

<p>ccl5 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 5 
480,1318 
618,0507 </p>

<p>ccl7 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 7 
95,9741 
50,8313 </p>

<p>ccl8 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 8 
0,9048 
2,4129 </p>

<p>ccl9 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 9 
18,802 
6,4933 </p>

<p>ccr4 
chemokine (c-c motif) receptor 4 
4,175 
0,5347 </p>

<p>ccr9 
chemokine (c-c motif) receptor 9 
8,9115 
5,7009 </p>

<p>cxcl1 
chemokine (c-X-c motif) ligand 1 
423,505 
197,4882 </p>

<p>cxcl10 
chemokine (c-X-c motif) ligand 10 639,2351 
465,289 </p>

<p>cxcl9 
chemokine (c-X-c motif) ligand 9 
184,895 
123,7246 </p>

<p>Ifng 
Interferon gamma 
11,0909 
3,6384 </p>

<p>Il10 
Interleukin 10 
4,7143 
1,6302 </p>

<p>Il10ra 
Interleukin 10 receptor, α 
0,9859 
2,2415 </p>

<p>Il13ra1 
Interleukin 13 receptor, α 1 
1,8425 
3,7824 </p>

<p>Il15 
Interleukin 15 
19,8637 
12,7172 </p>

<p>Il18 
Interleukin 18 
5,4358 
5,6541 </p>

<p>Il1a 
Interleukin 1 α 
55,0694 
44,468 </p>

<p>Il1b 
Interleukin 1 β 
2002,2656 1885,7737 </p>

<p>Il2rb 
Interleukin 2 receptor, β chain 
4,6718 
3,2719 </p>

<p>Il2rg 
Interleukin 2 receptor, gamma 
chain 
2,4378 
3,1741 </p>

<p>Il5ra 
Interleukin 5 receptor, α 
2,5791 
3,6383 </p>

<p>Lta 
Lymphotoxin a 
12,0863 
10,4605 </p>

<p>Ltb 
Lymphotoxin B 
7,0985 
10,909 </p>

<p>Tnf 
Tumor necrosis factor 
465,9427 
189,7928 </p>

<p>Tnfrsf1a 
Tumor necrosis factor receptor 
superfamily, member 1a 
2,0311 
1,8406 </p>

<p>Tnfrsf1b 
Tumor necrosis factor receptor 
superfamily, member 1b 
13,7323 
10,1068 </p>

<p>Xcr1 
chemokine (c motif) receptor 1 
3,5155 
1,3856 </p>

<p>peritoneal macrophages from wild type (WT) and arf 
−/− mice were 
obtained as described in Material and Methods. cells were stimulated 
with 200 ng/mL lipopolysaccharide (Lps) for 6h and the expression 
of pro-inflammatory genes was analyzed by RT 
2 pcR analysis. Genes 
upregulated in Lps-stimulated arf 
−/− cells as compared with WT cells are 
shown in bold. </p>

<p>Table 3. chemokine and cytokine profile in IL-4-stimulated macro-
phages </p>

<p>Symbol 
Description 
Fold change </p>

<p>WT 
Arf </p>

<p>−/− </p>

<p>ccl11 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 11 
0,98 
2,14 </p>

<p>ccl12 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 12 
48,86 
11,83 </p>

<p>ccl17 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 17 
12,97 
13,60 </p>

<p>ccl2 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 2 
2,24 
1,74 </p>

<p>ccl22 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 22 
1,51 
3,52 </p>

<p>ccl24 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 24 
7,80 
6,73 </p>

<p>ccl5 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 5 
1,57 
2,01 </p>

<p>ccl6 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 6 
6,50 
5,51 </p>

<p>ccl7 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 7 
21,92 
11,05 </p>

<p>ccl8 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 8 
5,14 
2,30 </p>

<p>ccl9 
chemokine (c-c motif) ligand 9 
3,71 
3,21 </p>

<p>ccr3 
chemokine (c-c motif) receptor 3 
2,94 
5,55 </p>

<p>ccr4 
chemokine (c-c motif) receptor 4 
0,45 
0,40 </p>

<p>ccr5 
chemokine (c-c motif) receptor 5 
4,54 
4,72 </p>

<p>cxcl9 
chemokine (c-X-c motif) ligand 9 
26,43 
4,50 </p>

<p>Il6st 
Interleukin 6 signal transducer 
3,15 
2,55 </p>

<p>Ltb 
Lymphotoxin B 
3,56 
1,36 </p>

<p>Tnfrsf1b 
Tumor necrosis factor receptor super-
family, member 1b 
2,79 
1,53 </p>

<p>peritoneal macrophages from wild type (WT) and arf 
−/− mice were 
stimulated with 20 ng/mL interleukin-4 (IL-4) for 6 h, and the expression 
of pro-inflammatory genes was analyzed by RT 
2 pcR analysis. Genes 
upregulated in IL-4 stimulated arf 
−/− cells as compared with WT cells are 
shown in bold. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>OncoImmunology </p>

<p>
studies showing a direct correlation between the M2 phenotype 
and a elevated expression of these genes. 
5 Interestingly, Fizz-1 and 
Ym1 have been shown to exert angiogenic effects, stimulating 
actin and collagen expression, and have been implicated in tissue 
repair. </p>

<p>18,19 </p>

<p>M2 macrophages and TAMs play an important role in tumor 
angiogenesis, as they produce critical factors including VEGF 
and MMP-9. 
20 Our results demonstrate that Arf 
−/− macrophages 
produce high levels of these angiogenesis-associated molecules, 
supporting the idea of that these cells exert tumor-supporting 
functions. Consistent with this notion, recent studies have dem-
onstrated a role for ARF in suppressing tumor angiogenesis by </p>

<p>arginine to urea and ornithine. 
8 Elevated Arg-1 expression might 
promote tumor growth via several mechanisms, including the 
downregulation of NO-mediated tumor cytotoxicity, 
13 increased 
tumor proliferation (due to alterations in polyamine and pro-
line synthesis), and enhancements of the capacity of myeloid-
derived suppressor cells to inhibit T cell proliferation. 
14,15 Indeed, 
increased expression of Arg-1 in TAMs has been described in 
3LL murine lung carcinoma, 
14 in human papillomavirus E6/ 
E7-expressing murine tumors 
16 and in CD11b 
+ /CD14 
− myeloid 
cells from renal carcinoma patients. 
17 Together with Arg-1 over-
expression, an increase in Fizz-1 and Ym1 levels was observed 
in Arf 
−/− macrophages. These data are in agreement with other </p>

<p>Figure 4. exacerbated activation of arf 
−/− macrophages in response to IL-4. (A) WT and Arf 
−/− macrophages were treated with 200 ng/mL lipopoly-
saccharide (Lps), 50 ng/mL interferon γ (IFNγ), 20 ng/mL IL-4 and 20 ng/mL IL-13 for 24 h and NO release was determined by the Griess reaction. (B) 
peritoneal macrophages from WT and aRF-deficient mice were treated with 200 ng/mL Lps and 20 ng/mL IL-4 and expression of iNOs and cOX-2 was 
evaluated by quantitative pcR. (C) protein levels of iNOs and cOX-2 were evaluated by immunoblotting after stimulation of peritoneal macrophages 
as in (A). (D) arg-1 expression was examined by quantitative pcR in WT and arf 
−/− cells after stimulation with 200 ng/mL Lps and 20 ng/mL IL-4 for 6 
h. (E) protein levels of arg-1 were evaluated by immunoblotting after stimulation of peritoneal macrophages with 20 ng/mL IL-4 for 24 h. (F) WT and 
arf 
−/− macrophages were treated with 20 ng/mL IL-4 for 24 h and production of urea was determined. Results were obtained from three independent 
experiments performed in triplicate and data are reported as means ± sD *p &lt; 0.05, and **p &lt; 0.01, as compared with WT mice. (B and E) are repre-
sentative of one out of three independent experiments. (C and E) band intensities were quantified by densitometry, normalized to β-actin levels and 
represented as means ± sD of the fold change from control condition (n = 3). </p>



<p>OncoImmunology 
Volume 1 Issue 8 </p>

<p>might result in the recruitment of Tregs, Th2 cells, eosino-
phils and basophils and in the amplification of Th2 responses. 
Moreover, Arf 
−/− macrophages showed a significant increase in 
IL-10 levels, which contribute to the maintenance of an immu-
nosuppressive environment. Taken together, these findings 
indicate that resting Arf 
−/− macrophages acquire an M2-like phe-
notype. Moreover, Arf 
−/− macrophages exhibit a higher expres-
sion of M2-associated immunomodulatory genes in response to 
alternative activation stimuli. 
In summary, we propose that ARF-deficient macrophages can 
contribute to the establishment of a tolerogenic microenviroment, 
faciliting tumor progression as a result of (1) immunosuppres-
sion, through the production of anti-inflammatory IL-10 and the 
secretion of Ccl22 and Ccl2, which attract Tregs, (2) stimulation 
of angiogenesis, through the upregulation of VEGF and MMP-
9, and (3) induction of extracellular matrix remodeling, through 
the production of MMP-9, Fizz-1 and Ym1 (Fig. 7). Further 
experiments analyzing the phenotype of macrophages that </p>

<p>regulating the expression of VEGF 
21 and the activity of its trans-
activator hypoxia-inducible factor-1 (HIF-1). 
22 Notably, ARF has 
also been described to inhibit angiogenesis by upregulating the 
expression of TIMP3, an inhibitor of MMPs activity. </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Another important feature that discriminates M1 and M2 
macrophages is their cytokine and chemokine repertoire. M1 
macrophages produce inflammatory chemokines such as Cxcl9 
and Cxcl10, which induce the recruitment of Th1 cells, whereas 
M2 polarization is accompanied by the production of immuno-
suppressive cytokines (e.g., IL-10 and TGFβ) and chemokines 
such as Ccl17, Ccl22 and Ccl24 
1,4,24 that favor the recruitment 
of immunosuppressive cells such like regulatory T cells (Tregs). 
Analysis of the cytokine and chemokine profile in Arf 
−/− macro-
phages showed a clear correlation with M2 phenotype. Notably, 
chemokines typically involved in lymphocyte recruitment, such 
as Ccl5 and the Ccr4 ligands Ccl17 and Ccl22 were consistently 
higher after the administration of IL-4 treatment in Arf 
−/− , but 
not in WT, macrophages. Thus, the release of these chemokines </p>

<p>Figure 5. M2 phenotype markers and pro-angiogenic factors are increased in IL-4-treated arf 
−/− macrophages. (A) peritoneal macrophages from WT 
and aRF-deficient mice were treated with 20 ng/mL IL-4 for 6 h, and the expression of IL-10 was evaluated by quantitative pcR. (B) IL-10 levels were 
measured by eLIsa in supernatants of WT and arf 
−/− macrophages treated for 24 h with 20 ng/mL IL-4. (C) WT and arf 
−/− macrophages were treated as 
in a and Fizz-1, Ym1 and MMR expression was examined by quantitative pcR. (D) VeGF and MMp-9 expression was examined by quantitative pcR in 
WT and arf 
−/− cells upon stimulation with 20 ng/mL IL-4 for 6 h. (E) VeGF levels were determined by eLIsa after stimulation of WT and arf 
−/− cells with 
20 ng/mL IL-4 for 24 h. Results were obtained from three independent experiments performed in triplicate and data are reported as means ± sD *p &lt; 
0.05, **p &lt; 0.01 and ***p &lt; 0.001, as compared with untreated WT cells, and 
a p &lt; 0.05, 
b p &lt; 0.01, as compared with WT cells. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>OncoImmunology </p>

<p>
infiltrate tumors in Arf 
−/− mice might provide further insights 
into macrophage plasticity, thus facilitating the development of 
new therapeutic strategies. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Materials and reagents. Ultrapure 0111:B4 lipopolysaccharide 
(LPS) from Escherichia coli was purchased from InvivoGen. 
Murine IFNγ, IL-4 and IL-13 were provided by Peprotech. The 
mouse RT 
2 Profiler PCR Inflammatory Cytokines and Receptors 
array, the RT 
2 First Strand kit and SYBR Green/Fluorescein 
qPCR master mix were from SABiosciences. TRIzol reagent was 
from Invitrogen. Difco thioglycollate broth was from Becton-
Dickinson. Anti-iNOS and anti-COX-2 antibodies were from 
Abcam, anti-arginase-1 and anti-β-actin antibodies were from 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology. Immunoblotting reagents (poly-
vinylidene difluoride membranes and ECL kit) were from GE 
Healthcare. Culture media were from Lonza. l-arginine, urea 
and 1-phenyl-1,2-propanedione-2-oxime were from Sigma. 
Animals. All procedures involving animals were performed in 
accordance with European Union guidelines and the Declaration 
of Helsinki principles for the handling and use of laboratory </p>

<p>animals. Studies were performed on 12-week-old Arf 
+/+ (WT), 
and Arf 
−/− C57BL/6J mice. 
Preparation of elicited peritoneal macrophages. Peritoneal 
macrophages were elicited by intraperitoneal injection of 2.5 mL 
3% thioglycollate in distilled water and were prepared as pre-
viously described. 
25 Cells were seeded at 1 × 10 
6 /cm 
2 in RPMI 
medium containing 10% FBS. Non-adherent cells were removed 
2 h after seeding by extensive washing with medium. 
Determination of NO synthesis. NO was measured by the 
Griess reaction as previously described. 
26 Briefly, NO release was 
determined spectrophotometrically as the accumulation of nitrite 
in the medium. Absorbance at 548 nm was compared with stan-
dard NaNO 2 solutions. 
Assay of PGE 2 , VEGF and IL-10 release. Supernatants 
from WT and Arf 
−/− macrophages were tested for the presence 
of PGE 2 VEGF, and cytokines using commercially available 
ELISA following the protocols supplied by the manufacturers 
(R&amp;D Systems). 
Arginase activity measurement. Arginase activity was assessed 
in cell lysates indirectly by measuring urea concentration gener-
ated by the arginase-dependent hydrolysis of l-arginine. 
27 Briefly, 
cells were lysed with 20 mM Tris (pH 7.5), 150 mM NaCl, 2 mM </p>

<p>Figure 6. Gene expression profile of aRF-deficient macrophages after IL-4 stimulation. (A) Microarray analysis was conducted on 3 independent 
preparations of unstimulated macrophages or macrophages treated with 20 ng/mL IL-4 for 6 h. hierarchical clustering of genes induced by IL-4 (fold 
induction &gt; 2 and p &lt; 0.05 on a 2-tailed paired student's t test comparing M2 vs unstimulated macrophages) is shown, together with genes differen-
tially expressed in arf 
−/− macrophages as compared with WT cells. columns report gene names and fold increase upon IL-4 treatment vs. untreated 
conditions, for both WT and arf 
−/− macrophages. (B) a panel of genes was selected for validation by quantitative pcR analysis based on the microar-
ray results. Results were obtained from three independent experiments performed in triplicate and data are reported as means ± sD *p &lt; 0.05, and 
**p &lt; 0.01 as compared with none condition, and 
a p &lt; 0.05, 
b p &lt; 0.01, as compared with WT cells. </p>



<p>OncoImmunology 
Volume 1 Issue 8 </p>

<p>(pH 7.5) to yield a standard range from 1500 to 23.4 μg/mL. 
Lysates and standards (25 μL) were mixed with 25 μL of 10 mM 
MnCl 2 in 50 mM TRIS-HCl (pH 7.5) in a 2 mL Eppendorf tube. </p>

<p>EDTA, and 0.1% Triton X-100-containing protease inhibitor 
mixture (Sigma) for 30 min at room temperature. Standards were 
prepared by serially diluting a stock of urea in 50 mM TRIS-HCl </p>

<p>Figure 7. a simplified view for M2-type activation in aRF-deficient macrophages. In WT macrophages, a balance between the M1 and M2 phenotype 
is established, depending on the initiating stimuli. however, aRF-deficient macrophages establish an immunosuppressive and tolerant microenvi-
ronment upon the impairment of M1 signals, secretion of the M2 chemokines ccl17 and ccl22 as well as of the anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10, and 
stimulation of angiogenesis through expression of VeGF and MMp-9. Green and red arrows depict genes that are downregulated and upregulated, 
respectively, in aRF-deficient macrophages as compared to their WT counterparts. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>OncoImmunology </p>

<p>
Tubes were then incubated for 10 min at 55°C for activation. 
Next, arginine hydrolysis was conducted by incubating 50 μL of 
the lysates and standards with 50 μL of 0.5 M l-arginine at 37°C 
for 75 min, followed by the addition of 400 μL stopping solution 
(H 2 SO 4 /H 3 PO 4 /H 2 O = 1/3/7, v/v/v). To measure the amount of 
urea in each tube, 50 μL of 9% 1-phenyl-1,2-propanedione-2-ox-
ime (Sigma) in 100% ethanol was added to each sample and stan-
dard, and tubes were incubated at 100°C for 60 min. Tubes were 
placed in the dark at 25°C for 30 min. Samples and standards 
(100 μL/well) were transferred in triplicate to a 96-well plate, and 
optical density was read at 540 nm with 690 nm correction. The 
concentration of samples was determined from the standard curve 
and converted to arginase units using the following formula: urea 
produced (μg/mL) / total protein (μg/mL). 
Total extracts and immunoblotting. Cells were lysed at 
4°C with 0.2 mL buffer A (0.5% Chaps, 10mM Tris pH 7.5, 
1mM Cl 2 Mg, 1mM EGTA, 10% Glycerol, 5 mM β) and pro-
tease inhibitor cocktail (Sigma). Protein content was assayed 
with the Bio-Rad protein reagent. All cell fractionation steps 
were performed at 4°C. Protein extracts were subjected to SDS-
PAGE (10-15% gels) and blotted onto polyvinylidene difluo-
ride membranes, which were incubated antibodies specific for 
Arg-1, iNOS, COX-2 and β-actin. After incubation with HRP-
conjugated secondary antibody, protein bands were revealed with 
an enhanced chemiluminescence kit (GE Healthcare). β-actin 
was used as a loading control. After treatment with 100 mM 
β-mercaptoethanol, 2% SDS in TBS and heating at 60°C for 30 
min, blots were sequentially probed with other antibodies. 
RNA isolation and quantitative PCR. Total RNA was iso-
lated from cells with Trizol reagent (Invitrogen). Quantitative 
PCR (SYBR Green) analysis was performed with an ABI 7500 
Fast sequence analyzer as previously described. 
28 Each sample 
was run in duplicate, and all samples were analyzed in parallel for 
the expression of the housekeeping gene 36B4 (acidic ribosomal 
phosphoprotein P0), which was used as an endogenous control 
for normalization of the expression level of target genes. Fold </p>

<p>induction was determined from mean replicate values. Primer 
sequences are available on request. 
Gene expression profile. Expression of inflammatory genes 
was evaluated with the mouse RT 
2 Profiler PCR Inflammatory 
Cytokines and Receptors Array (SABiosciences). Briefly, 2 μg of 
RNA were used for cDNA synthesis with RT 
2 First Standard kit 
(SABiosciences). The RT 
2 Profiler array was probed according to 
the manufacturer's protocol, using the Profiler PCR Array System 
and SYBR Green/Fluorescein qPCR master mix (SABiosciences) 
in an ABI 7500 Fast sequence analyzer (Applied Biosystems). 
Gene expression was compared with the web-based software 
package for the PCR Array System (http://www.superarray.com/ 
pcr/arrayanalysis.php), which automatically performs all ΔΔCt 
based fold-change calculations from the specific uploaded raw 
threshold cycle data. 
Statistical analysis. The data presented are shown as means 
± SD of three or five independent experiments. Statistical sig-
nificance was estimated by Student's t test for unpaired observa-
tions and one-or two-way ANOVA, followed by Bonferroni's, 
Tukey's, or Dunnett's post-hoc comparisons. Differences were 
considered significant at when p values were &lt; 0.05. All statistical 
analyses were conducted using <rs id="software-1" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">5.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>). For immunoblots, a linear correlation was observed 
between increasing amounts of input protein and signal intensity. </p>

<p>Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest were disclosed. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This study was supported by grant PI11.0036 from the FIS and 
MPY 1410/09 from ISCIII to S.H. </p>

<p>Supplemental Materials </p>

<p>Supplemental materials may be found here: 
w w w.landesbioscience.com /journals /oncoimmunolog y/ 
article/21207 </p>





<p>OncoImmunology 
Volume 1 Issue 8 </p>



</text></tei>