<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3595153" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives Biological and behavioural surveillance of 
HIV and sexually transmitted infections (STIs) among 
populations at highest risk have been used to monitor 
trends in prevalence and in risk behaviours. Sex work in 
Panama is regulated through registration with the Social 
Hygiene Programme, Ministry of Health. We estimated 
prevalence of HIV and STIs, and factors associated with 
active syphilis among female sex workers (FSWs). 
Methods A cross-sectional study using venue-based, 
time-space sampling was conducted among FSWs in 
Panama from 2009 to 2010. FSWs were interviewed 
about sociodemographic characteristics, sexual risk 
behaviour, health history and drug use using an 
anonymous structured questionnaire. Blood was collected 
for serological testing of HIV and other STIs. Factors 
associated with active syphilis were studied using logistic 
regression analysis. 
Results The overall HIV-1 prevalence of 0.7% varied by 
FSW category; 1.6% in 379 unregistered, and 0.2% in 
620 registered FSWs. Overall prevalence (and 95% CI) of 
STIs were: syphilis antibody, 3.8% (2.7% to 5.2%); 
herpes simplex virus type 2 antibody (anti-HSV-2), 74.2% 
(71.4% to 76.9%); hepatitis B surface antigen, 0.6% 
(0.2% to 1.3%); hepatitis B core antibody, 8.7% (7.0% to 
10.6%); and hepatitis C antibody, 0.2% (0.0% to 0.7%). 
In multivariate analysis, registration (adjusted OR (AOR) 
=0.35; 95% CI 0.16 to 0.74), having a history of 
STI (AOR=2.37; 95% CI 1.01 to 5.58), forced sex 
(AOR=2.47; 95% CI 1.11 to 5.48), and anti-HSV-2 
(AOR=10.05; 95% CI 1.36 to 74.38) were associated 
with active syphilis. 
Conclusions Although HIV prevalence is low among 
FSWs in Panama, unregistered FSWs bear a higher 
burden of HIV and STIs than registered FSWs. 
Programmes aimed at overcoming obstacles to 
registration, and HIV, STI and harm reduction among 
unregistered FSWs is warranted to prevent HIV 
transmission, and to improve their sexual and 
reproductive health. </p>

<p>Central and South America and the Caribbean 
together accounted for the second highest adult 
HIV prevalence in the world in 2009. 
1 The overall 
estimated adult HIV prevalence in Central and 
South America is 0.5% and ranges from 2.3% in 
Belize, to at least 1% in Guyana and Suriname, </p>

<p>and 0.9% in Panama. 
2 In most of these countries, 
the HIV epidemic is concentrated in populations at 
highest risk: men who have sex with men (MSM) 
and commercial sex workers. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>In countries with concentrated epidemics, the 
second-generation HIV surveillance approach 
among populations at highest risk provides valu-
able data to monitor trends in prevalence of infec-
tion, and the risk behaviours driving these trends 
which, together, inform the evaluation of existing 
national AIDS control programmes. 
3 Some of the 
key methods in second-generation HIV surveillance 
include repeated cross-sectional HIV sentinel sur-
veillance combined with behavioural and sexually 
transmitted infections (STIs) surveillance. 
An estimated 3105 women worked as sex workers 
in 2010 in Panama (Office of Registration and 
Health Statistics, Ministry of Health, Panama); 98% 
were under 50 years of age. The Ministry of 
Health (MoH) has regulated work at adult entertain-
ment venues by registration through the Social 
Hygiene Programme, introduced in Panama in 1918. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>The penalty for non-registration is a fine of US 
$500 levied on the owner of the venue employing 
the sex worker. Registration costs, US$100-150 
every 3 months, which includes costs of a manda-
tory photo-identification card, mandatory testing 
(weekly, for bacterial STIs; quarterly, for HIV and 
syphilis) at MoH health centres; a positive HIV 
result leads to revocation of registration and deport-
ation for non-Panamanian female sex workers 
(FSWs) with a work visa. HIV testing is available at 
laboratories in all health districts. Treatment and 
care for HIV-positive persons are an individual's 
right under Panamanian law. 
As a transit point between Central and South 
America, and between the Atlantic and Pacific 
Oceans, Panama is vulnerable to HIV and STIs 
prevalent in its migrant population. 
5 6 Women and 
children from neighbouring countries have been 
trafficked into the sex trade both within and 
through Panama. 
6 In-depth interviews of various 
at-risk populations in transit areas in Central 
America identified the MSM population in Panama 
as having considerable contact with mobile popu-
lations. 
5 Continued HIV and STI surveillance is 
necessary to guide prevention programmes among 
high-risk groups to prevent the spread of the HIV 
epidemic from such groups serving as a bridge to 
the general population. The last HIV and STI </p>

<p>Open Access 
Scan to access more 
free content </p>

<p> 
Sex Transm Infect 2013;89:156-164. doi:10.1136/sextrans-2012-050557 </p>

<p>Epidemiology </p>

<p>second-generation surveillance conducted in 2003 in Panama 
and Colón, two port cities, indicated a HIV prevalence of 2% 
among FSWs. 
7 We report results from a repeat HIV and STI 
biobehavioural survey conducted among FSWs in Panama. The 
objectives were to determine the prevalence of HIV, active 
syphilis and other viral STIs, and to assess factors associated 
with active syphilis. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Study design and study population </p>

<p>Panama's administrative division consists of nine provinces and 
three indigenous territories. A cross-sectional biobehavioural 
survey among FSWs was conducted from October 2009 to May 
2011 in eight provinces: Panama, Colón, Coclé, Herrera, Los 
Santos, Veraguas, Chiriquí and Bocas del Toro; the Darien 
region was excluded for security reasons. Herrera and Los 
Santos were combined for recruitment and analysis; the two 
provinces share geographic boundaries and considerable inter-
migration for health and other services. Accounting for diffi-
culty in accessing this hard-to-reach population, 
8 an enrolment 
of 1200 participants, 25% unregistered/street and 75% regis-
tered, was the estimated target sample size for 80% power, 
HIV prevalence of 1%, and prevalence precision of 1.3%. 
Criteria for enrolment were: (1) female gender; (2) age 18 years 
or older; (3) self-identified sex worker and (4) willingness to 
provide written informed consent. </p>

<p>Sampling methodology </p>

<p>FSWs were recruited using venue-based, time-space sampling 
(TSS). 
9 Activities included: (1) formative research to identify 
venues and time to recruit FSWs; (2) development of sampling 
frames of eligible venues and day-time periods; (3) random 
selection of venues and day-time periods; (4) recruitment and 
referral and (5) interviewing, and testing at study sites. 
Survey staff identified venues for registered and unregistered 
FSWs or 'clandestinas' by contacting non-governmental organi-
sations (NGOs) who had worked with FSWs in the year before 
the survey began, and key informants who worked at FSW 
work locations for 3 months or more. In two visits or more, 
survey staff estimated the FSW population size at various 
daytime and night-time hours at all identified venues (bars, 
taverns, night clubs, brothels, parks, city blocks, health clinics, 
street corners and pimps). Venues were chosen based on accessi-
bility and overall interest in study participation. At venues 
with an estimated FSW population of 8-20, all women were 
invited to participate, whereas at venues with 20-plus FSWs, 
women were invited randomly with a simple coin toss. 
At 67 venues, women self-identifying as registered FSWs 
were informed of the survey, invited to participate, and handed 
a coded pocket-sized calendar which indicated MoH health 
centres' staff availability. The code indicated the site and 
month of recruitment and an invitation number. At an add-
itional 54 venues, and through two pimps in one province, 
women self-identifying as unregistered FSWs were handed a 
second coded invitation card to recruitment dinners for enrol-
ment and blood collection. 
All interested and eligible women with invitation cards were 
enrolled in the study at either MoH health centres or recruitment 
dinners. Trained female interviewers administered an anonymous 
structured questionnaire after obtaining informed consent from 
participants. A rapid HIV test was performed on-site. 
Participants' questionnaires and blood samples were assigned 
unique codes. Survey and MoH staff conducted pretest counsel-
ling before HIV-1 rapid testing of participants. Participants were </p>

<p>asked to return in 2 weeks for the test results-health centres for 
registered FSWs or NGOs for unregistered-FSWs-and if positive, 
were provided post-test counselling and referred to MoH clinics 
for free medical care, treatment and contact tracing. All partici-
pants were given an incentive-a grocery store gift card or a US 
$15.00 cosmetic kit. </p>

<p>Ethical considerations </p>

<p>The study was approved by two institutional review boards: 
Instituto Conmemorativo Gorgas para Estudios de la Salud 
(ICGES, Panama), Walter Reed Army Institute of Research 
(WRAIR, USA). Only the Panama study team had access to 
informed consent forms. </p>

<p>Data collection </p>

<p>Staff conducted face-to-face interviews with a structured ques-
tionnaire which elicited information about sociodemographic 
characteristics, sexual risk behaviour, health history and alcohol 
and drug use. Sociodemographic variables included age, nation-
ality, education level, current marital status, race, current 
monthly income and employment, dependents and children, 
current residence and registration card on-person. Sexual risk 
behaviour history included age of sexual debut with a male, 
duration as sex worker, type of and number of sexual contacts 
in the past 6 months, condom use and sex work locations. 
Health history included contraceptive use, STI history, transfu-
sion, tattoos, abortions, reasons for abortion, HIV testing and 
last time of testing, sexual contact during menstrual period, 
forced sex and whether a regular partner had HIV/AIDS. 
Alcohol and drug use questions included lifetime drug or 
alcohol use, frequency and timing of alcohol use. </p>

<p>Laboratory procedures </p>

<p>Rapid HIV testing (US Food and Drug Administration-approved 
HIV 1/2 STAT PAK, Assay Chembio Diagnostic System, Inc, 
Medford, New York, USA) via fingerstick was performed at 
recruitment sites. In addition, 10 ml of blood via peripheral 
venipuncture was collected, centrifuged and separated into 
aliquots on-site, and transported to the study laboratory for 
storage at 4°C. 
Samples were evaluated for HIV (antibody to HIV (anti-HIV) 
and p24 antigen, AxSYM HIV Ag/Ab Combo), antibody to hepa-
titis C virus ((anti-HCV), AxSYM HCV V.3.0), hepatitis B surface 
antigen ((HBsAg), AxSYM HBsAg (V2)), antibody to hepatitis B 
core antigen ((anti-HBc), AxSYM CORE), antibody to herpes 
simplex type 2 virus ((anti-HSV2), ELISA, HerpeSelec-2, Focus 
Diagnostics, Cypress, California, USA), and syphilis (rapid 
plasma reagin (RPR), Arlington Scientific, Inc, Springville, Utah, 
USA). HIV, hepatitis B virus (HBV), and HCV testing was per-
formed on an AxSYM analyser (Abbott, Wiesbaden, Germany) 
using microparticle enzyme immunoassay technology. 
All initially reactive serological AxSYM tests were repeated in 
duplicate; HIV samples were repeated in duplicate irrespective 
of initial results. Positive screening results were confirmed for 
HIV (GS HIV-1 Western Blot, BioRad Laboratories, Redmond, 
Washington, USA), HCV (recombinant immunoblot assay 
(RIBA), Chiron RIBA HCV 3.0, Emeryville, California, USA) 
and syphilis (Treponema pallidum haemagglutination (TPHA), 
Arlington Scientific, Inc). Participants with laboratory-
confirmed syphilis-positive results, defined as RPR and TPHA 
positivity, were considered to have active syphilis infection. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>(Henceforth, the term syphilis denotes active syphilis). </p>

<p>Sex Transm Infect 2013;89:156-164. doi:10.1136/sextrans-2012-050557 </p>

<p>
Epidemiology </p>

<p>Analysis </p>

<p>Prevalence was estimated for HIV, HBV, HCV, HSV-2 and syph-
ilis. Exact binomial or binomial 95% CIs were calculated for 
prevalence estimates. Characteristics were compared by registra-
tion status using χ 
2 or Fisher's exact test for categorical vari-
ables and t test or Kruskal-Wallis test for continuous variables. 
Prevalence ORs were estimated in a univariate analysis. 
Characteristics associated with syphilis in a univariate analysis 
( p&lt;0.20) were evaluated for correlation and entered in a multi-
variate logistic regression model. Characteristics that were not 
statistically significant ( p&lt;0.05) in the multivariate model 
were removed in a stepwise manner, and independent associ-
ation with syphilis was assessed after adjustment for other 
variables retained in the model. Double data entry for all ques-
tionnaire and laboratory data were conducted at the ICGES. All 
data management and analyses were conducted using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.9.2</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc</rs>, Cary, North Carolina, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Study population </p>

<p>Of 1250 invitations issued, 1000 (80%) FSWs participated; one 
participant consented only to the questionnaire; 62% self-
identified as registered FSWs of whom 86% had a registration 
card at interview. Of 999 participants, 79% registered and 61% 
unregistered FSWs returned for the test results. The majority of 
FSWs (46%) were recruited from Panama. FSWs averaged 
29.4 years in age (SD±8.2 years) and most were single (74%). </p>

<p>Prevalence of HIV, syphilis and other STIs </p>

<p>The overall HIV prevalence among FSWs was 0.7% (95% CI 0.3 
to 1.4%); unregistered FSWs had a higher prevalence than regis-
tered FSWs (1.6% (95% CI 0.6 to 3.4%), 0.2% (95% CI 0.0 to 
0.9%), respectively; p=0.014; figure 1). HIV prevalence varied 
by province among participants (Bocas Del Toro: 2.1%, 95% CI 
0.3 to 7.4%; Coclé, Chiriquí, Herrera and Los Santos, and 
Veraguas: 0.0%, 95% CIs 0.0 to 12.3%). 
Among all participants, 3.8% (95% CI 2.7 to 5.2) were 
infected with syphilis (figure 1). Syphilis was higher among 
unregistered FSWs (6.6%, 95% CI 4.3 to 9.6%) than in regis-
tered FSWs (2.1%, 95% CI 1.1 to 3.6%, p=0.0003).The preva-
lence of syphilis varied by province ranging from 8.4% (Bocas 
Del Toro, 95% CI 3.7 to 15.9%) to 1.6-2.6% (Coclé, Herrera 
and Los Santos, Colón, and Chiriquí, 95% CIs 0.0 to 10.3%). 
The overall prevalence of HSV-2, anti-HBc, and HCV were 
74.2% (95% CI 71.4 to 76.9%), 8.7% (95% CI 7.0 to 10.6%), and 
0.2% (95% CI 0.0 to 0.7%), respectively. Of the six (0.6%, 95% 
CI 0.2 to 1.3%) HBsAg-positive participants, five were anti-HBc 
positive. One participant was coinfected with HIV and syphilis. </p>

<p>Comparison between registered and unregistered FSWs </p>

<p>In bivariate analysis, registered and unregistered FSWs differed sig-
nificantly by nationality, education levels, income, number of 
dependents, number of children, sexual risk behaviour, health 
history and drug use (p&lt;0.01, table 1). Unregistered FSWs were 
mostly Panamanian (89%) with lower levels of education (68% 
incomplete secondary or less vs 45%), more children (mean: 2.5 vs </p>

<p>Figure 1 Seroprevalence and 95% confidence intervals of HIV, syphilis and other viral sexually transmitted diseases among 999 female sex workers from 
eight provinces, Panama, October 2009-May 2011. Female sex workers (FSWs) category: unregistered FSWs n=379, registered FSWs n=620; Province: 
Panama n=455, Coclé n=64, Colón n=150, Chiriquí n=155, Herrera and Los Santos n=52, Bocas del Toro n=95, Veraguas n=28. Of 999 FSWs, 0.4% 
had HCV indeterminate results (n=4; unregistered FSWs n=3, registered FSWs n=1). Anti-HBc seroprevalence varied significantly by site (p=0.01) and 
registration status (p=0.001); HIV (p=0.014), syphilis (p&lt;0.0005), anti-Hbc, and HSV-2 (p=0.001) varied significantly by registration status. </p>

<p> 
Sex Transm Infect 2013;89:156-164. doi:10.1136/sextrans-2012-050557 </p>

<p>Epidemiology </p>

<p>Table 1 Characteristics of female sex workers (FSWs) and comparisons between unregistered and registered FSWs recruited from eight provinces, Panama, October 2009-May 2011 </p>

<p>Category 
Characteristic </p>

<p>Overall (n=999) 
Unregistered (n=379) 
Registered (n=620) </p>

<p>p Value 
n/total 
% 
n/total 
% 
n/total 
% </p>

<p>Sociodemographics 
Province 
Panama 
455 
46 
157 
41 
298 
48 
Coclé 
64 
6 
15 
4 
49 
8 
Colón 
150 
15 
57 
15 
93 
15 
Chiriquí 
155 
15 
66 
17 
89 
14 
Herrera, Los Santos 
52 
5 
0 
0 
52 
8 
Bocas del Toro 
95 
9 
65 
17 
30 
5 
Veraguas 
28 
3 
19 
5 
9 
1 
Age, mean (range) 
29.4 
(18-61) 
29.4 
(18-61) 
29.5 
(18-57) 
0.8193 
24 or less 
320/999 
32 
149/379 
39 
171/620 
28 
25-29 
261/999 
26 
69/379 
18 
192/620 
31 
30-39 
271/999 
27 
90/379 
24 
181/620 
29 
40+ 
139/999 
14 
70/379 
18 
69/620 
11 
Nationality 
&lt;0.0001 
Panama 
487/987 
49 
338/377 
89 
149/610 
24 
Colombia 
412/987 
41 
12/377 
3 
400/610 
65 
Dominican Republic 
67/987 
7 
19/377 
5 
48/610 
8 
Other* 
21/987 
2 
8/377 
2 
13/610 
2 
Education 
&lt;0.0001 
None or primary school or less 
146/992 
15 
58/378 
15 
88/614 
14 
Incomplete secondary school 
390/992 
39 
200/378 
53 
190/614 
31 
Complete secondary/ technical school or university 
456/992 
46 
120/378 
32 
336/614 
54 
Marital status 
0.0427 
Single 
741/990 
74 
268/376 
71 
473/614 
76 
Other † 
249/990 
25 
108/376 
29 
141/614 
23 
Other dependents 
672/965 
70 
205/363 
56 
467/602 
77 
&lt;0.0001 
Mean number of children (range) 
2 
(0-11) 
2.5 
(0-11) 
1.7 
(0-11) 
&lt;0.0001 
Median income, USD (IQR) 
485 
(250-800) 
250 
(120-430) 
500 
(350-1000) 
&lt;0.0001 
Work location ‡ 
&lt;0.0001 
Premises 
675/832 
68 
140/296 
37 
535/536 
86 
Street 
157/832 
16 
156/296 
41 
1/536 
0 
Sexual risk behaviour 
Mean age at sexual debut with male, years (range) 
15.9 
(7-27) 
15.6 
(7-25) 
16.1 
(9-27) 
0.0007 
Median number of males, sexual contact in past 6 months (IQR) 
20 
(5-100) 
10 
(4-30) 
40 
(6-180) 
&lt;0.0001 
Median number of years worked as sex worker (IQR) 
2 
(0.6-5) 
3 
(1-6) 
1 
(0.5-3) 
&lt;0.0001 
Client 
Vaginal sex 
864/895 
97 
335/339 
99 
529/556 
95 
0.0035 
Oral sex 
517/882 
59 
177/337 
53 
340/545 
62 
0.0039 
Anal sex 
130/883 
15 
76/339 
22 
54/544 
10 
&lt;0.0001 
Not regular partner 
Vaginal sex 
852/968 
88 
327/363 
90 
525/602 
87 
0.1787 </p>

<p>Continued </p>

<p>Sex Transm Infect 2013;89:156-164. doi:10.1136/sextrans-2012-050557 </p>



<p>Epidemiology </p>

<p>Table 1 Continued </p>

<p>Category 
Characteristic </p>

<p>Overall (n=999) 
Unregistered (n=379) 
Registered (n=620) </p>

<p>p Value 
n/total 
% 
n/total 
% 
n/total 
% </p>

<p>Oral sex 
504/950 
53 
173/363 
48 
331/587 
56 
0.0088 
Anal sex 
141/935 
15 
78/360 
22 
63/575 
11 
&lt;0.0001 
Current regular partner 
Vaginal sex 
502/735 
68 
201/282 
71 
301/453 
66 
0.1711 
Oral sex 
339/697 
49 
114/266 
43 
225/431 
52 
0.0165 
Anal sex 
158/691 
23 
79/262 
30 
79/429 
18 
0.0004 
Alcohol/drug use by regular partner before/during sex, sometimes-always 
158/447 
35 
75/188 
40 
83/259 
32 
0.0008 
Sex during menstruation 
514/991 
52 
177/377 
47 
337/614 
55 
0.0152 
Forced sex 
132/987 
13 
62/374 
17 
70/613 
11 
0.0209 
Sexual contact with an injection drug user 
136/727 
19 
67/289 
23 
69/438 
16 
0.0119 
Sexual contact with male sex workers 
66/955 
7 
41/365 
11 
25/590 
4 
&lt;0.0001 
Sex work in another country 
178/890 
20 
16/333 
5 
162/557 
29 
&lt;0.0001 
Currently travel to another country for sex work 
76/879 
9 
11/331 
3 
65/548 
12 
&lt;0.0001 
Sexual contact ever in another country 
687/967 
71 
210/367 
57 
477/600 
80 
&lt;0.0001 
Sexual contact on travel in past 6 months, non regular partner 
127/961 
13 
14/363 
4 
113/598 
19 
&lt;0.0001 
Regular client construction worker 
346/999 
35 
156/379 
41 
190/620 
31 
0.0007 
Regular client in military 
79/999 
8 
24/379 
6 
55/620 
9 
0.1491 
Regular client a foreigner 
292/999 
29 
101/379 
27 
191/620 
31 
0.1609 
Health history 
Mean days since ever HIV tested (range) 
211.6 
(1-6496) 
463.7 
(1-6496) 
114.7 
(1-3090) 
&lt;0.0001 
Transfusions 
94/968 
10 
47/370 
13 
47/598 
8 
0.0134 
Medications by injections 
637/976 
65 
210/367 
57 
427/609 
70 
&lt;0.0001 
Have tattoos 
409/994 
41 
174/378 
48 
235/616 
38 
0.0142 
Have piercings 
204/992 
21 
61/377 
16 
143/615 
23 
0.0075 
Drug use 
Never used drugs 
737/999 
74 
257/379 
68 
480/620 
77 
0.0008 
Used marijuana 
152/999 
15 
77/379 
20 
75/620 
12 
0.0004 
Used cocaine 
93/999 
9 
43/379 
11 
50/620 
8 
0.0833 </p>

<p>*Bolivia, Costa Rica, Guatemala, Nicaragua, USA. 
 †Married, divorced, widowed, separated, living with someone. 
 ‡'Premises' included work locations bar/taberna, discotheque, whorehouse, motel, house/home, saunas/masseuse, gym, public bath, theatres, and night clubs. </p>



<p>Sex Transm Infect 2013;89:156-164. doi:10.1136/sextrans-2012-050557 </p>

<p>Epidemiology </p>

<p>1.7), and lower income (median USD: 250 vs 500) than registered 
FSWs. Registered FSWs were predominantly Colombian (65%). 
Unregistered FSWs reported fewer sexual contacts in the past 
6 months (median number of males, 10 (IQR: 4-30) vs 40 (IQR: 
6-180)), were younger at sexual debut with a male (mean years: 
15.6 vs 16.1), had worked longer as sex workers (median years: 3 
vs 1), and more frequently reported engaging in anal sex with 
clients (22%), regular (30%) and non-regular (22%) partners 
than registered FSWs (10%, 18%, 11%, respectively, table 1). 
Unregistered FSWs more frequently reported having had sexual 
contact with an injection drug user (23% vs 16%), male sex 
workers (11% vs 7%), using marijuana (20% vs 12%), and 
having a regular partner who sometimes or always used alcohol 
or drugs before sex (40% vs 32%). Unregistered FSWs reported 
having had a HIV test less recently than registered FSWs (mean 
days since last HIV test, 463.7 vs 114.7). Unregistered FSWs 
more frequently reported never or inconsistently using condoms 
for anal sex with clients (27% vs 10%, p=0.02), and for vaginal 
sex with clients (19% vs 4%, p&lt;0.0001) and non-regular part-
ners (20% vs 8%, p&lt;0.0001, figure 2). Both unregistered and 
registered FSWs reported never or inconsistently using condoms 
with regular partners (66%-80%, figure 2). </p>

<p>Factors associated with syphilis </p>

<p>In the univariate analysis, factors associated with syphilis were: 
registration, age of 40 years or older, having Panamanian </p>

<p>nationality, being of African descent, having lower levels of 
education, working on the street, anti-HBc or HSV-2 positivity, 
forced sex, having clients who worked in construction or trans-
portation or who were in the military, anal sex with a non-
regular partner, inconsistently or never using condoms for 
vaginal sex, sexual contact with foreigners, having a history of 
STI and never using drugs ( p&lt;0.05, table 2). 
All factors associated with syphilis in the univariate analysis 
( p&lt;0.20, table 2) were entered into a multivariate model. 
Factors not retained in the final model ( p&lt;0.05)-nationality, 
education level, race, work location, sexual contact with for-
eigners, sex work in another country and contraceptive use-
were highly correlated with registration status ( p&lt;0.0001, data 
not shown). In the final model, four factors showed independ-
ent association with syphilis: registration (adjusted OR (AOR) 
=0.35; 95% CI 0.16 to 0.74), having a STI history (AOR=2.37; 
95% CI 1.01 to 5.58), forced sex (AOR=2.47; 95% CI 1.11 to 
5.48), and having HSV-2 antibody (AOR=10.05; 95% CI 1.36 
to 74.38) (table 2). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This biobehavioural survey was conducted among FSWs in eight 
provinces of Panama to monitor the prevalence of HIV, other 
viral STIs, syphilis among women at high risk for STIs, and to 
assess factors associated with syphilis. The overall HIV preva-
lence while low differed markedly by registration status. The </p>

<p>Figure 2 Percent of condom use reported by registered and unregistered female sex workers for sexual partners. </p>

<p>Sex Transm Infect 2013;89:156-164. doi:10.1136/sextrans-2012-050557 </p>

<p>
Epidemiology </p>

<p>Table 2 Factors associated with syphilis in female sex workers from eight provinces in Panama, October 2009-May 2011 </p>

<p>Category 
Characteristic † </p>

<p>Syphilis (n=38) 
Unadjusted OR 
p Value </p>

<p>Adjusted OR 
p Value 
n positive/ total (%) 
(95% CI) 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Sociodemographics 
Regulation 
Registered 
13/620 
(2.1) 
0.30 (0.15-0.60) 
0.0006 
0.35 (0.16-0.74) 
0.0058 
Unregistered 
25/379 
(6.6) 
1.00 
Province 
Panama 
19/455 
(4.2) 
0.82 (0.39-1.73) 
0.6091 
Colón 
3/150 
(2.0) 
0.39 (0.11-1.39) 
0.1457 
Chiriquí 
4/155 
(2.6) 
0.50 (0.16-1.58) 
0.2390 
Other* 
11/175 
(6.3) 
1.00 
Age, years 
24 or less 
9/320 
(2.8) 
1.00 
25-29 
11/261 
(4.2) 
1.54 (0.65-3.69) 
0.3284 
30-39 
7/271 
(2.6) 
0.94 (0.34-2.62) 
0.9062 
40+ 
11/139 
(7.9) 
3.02 (1.25-7.27) 
0.0139 
Nationality 
Panamanian 
25/487 
(5.1) 
2.03 (1.02-4.01) 
0.0423 
Foreigner 
13/500 
(2.6) 
1.00 
Race 
African descent 
12/164 
(7.3) 
2.76 (1.34-5.69) 
0.0060 
Other 
22/791 
(2.8) 
1.00 
Education 
Incomplete secondary or less 
29/536 
(5.4) 
2.84 (1.33-6.06) 
0.007 
Complete Secondary or technical school or university 9/456 
(2.0) 
1.00 
Work location 
Street 
17/157 
(10.8) 4.43 (2.23-8.81) 
&lt;0.0001 
Premises 
18/675 
(2.7) 
1.00 
Serology 
Anti-HIV 
Positive 
1/7 
(14.3) 4.30 (0.50-36.65) 
0.1819 
Negative 
37/992 
(3.7) 
1.00 
Anti-HBc 
Positive 
7/87 
(8.0) 
2.49 (1.06-5.83) 
0.0360 
Negative 
31/912 
(3.4) 
1.00 
Anti-HSV-2 
Positive 
37/741 
(5.0) 
13.51 (1.84-98.94) 0.0104 
10.05 (1.36-74.38) 0.0239 
Negative 
1/257 
(0.4) 
1.00 
Sexual risk behaviour Forced sex 
Yes 
12/132 
(9.1) 
3.19 (1.57-6.49) 
0.0014 
2.470 (1.11-5.48) 
0.0262 
No 
26/855 
(3.0) 
1.00 
Regular client construction worker 
21/346 
(6.1) 
2.42 (1.26-4.65) 
0.0081 
Regular client transportation worker 
14/204 
(6.9) 
2.37 (1.20-4.66) 
0.0127 
Regular client police officer 
10/180 
(5.6) 
1.66 (0.79-3.49) 
0.1790 
Regular client in military 
7/79 
(8.9) 
2.79 (1.19-6.55) 
0.0187 
Anal sex with non-regular partner 
Yes 
10/141 
(7.1) 
2.26 (1.06-4.79) 
0.0341 
No 
26/794 
(3.3) 
1.00 
Condom use with non-regular partner 
Vaginal sex 
Never/inconsistent 
11/104 
(10.6) 3.84 (1.81-8.18) 
0.0005 
Always 
22/737 
(3.0) 
1.00 
Anal sex 
Never/inconsistent 
4/27 
(14.8) 3.69 (0.92-14.80) 
0.0658 
Always 
5/111 
(4.5) 
1.00 
Sexual contact with foreigners 
No 
19/280 
(6.8) 
1.00 
Yes 
17/687 
(2.5) 
0.35 (0.18-0.68) 
0.0020 
Sex work, another country 
Yes 
4/178 
(2.2) 
0.47 (0.16-1.35) 
0.1627 
No 
33/712 
(4.6) 
1.00 </p>

<p>Continued </p>

<p> 
Sex Transm Infect 2013;89:156-164. doi:10.1136/sextrans-2012-050557 </p>

<p>Epidemiology </p>

<p>difference by registration status was seen in STI prevalence and 
HIV risk. Furthermore, registration was protective for syphilis. 
Among FSWs who participated in the survey, the overall 
seroprevalence of HIV, syphilis and HSV-2 were 0.7%, 3.8% and 
74.2%, respectively. In the two port cities, Panama and Colón, 
the HIV, syphilis and HSV-2 seroprevalences were 0.8%, 3.6% 
and 72.6%, respectively. A multicentric, multicountry, cross-
sectional survey conducted in 2003 among FSWs, with 15% of 
404 FSWs recruited from streets and parks in the two port 
cities, reported a HIV, syphilis and HSV-2 seroprevalences of 
1.9%, 4.8% and 73.0%, respectively. 
7 The HSV-2 seroprevalence 
reported in the 2003 study was the lowest among the five 
Central American countries. 
8 Panama ranked above average in 
the region in prioritising domestic resources to AIDS treatment 
and HIV prevention. 
11 While it is possible our findings are 
reflective of the HIV epidemic stabilising from 2001 to 2009 in 
Central and South America, and an increased public spending 
on HIV prevention and treatment programmes in the region, 
the difference in our findings from the previous study is pos-
sibly the result of differing sampling methodologies, TSS versus 
cluster sampling. </p>

<p>2 11 </p>

<p>As reported previously in Panama, the prevalence of HIV and 
STIs varied widely by sex worker registration status. 
Unregistered FSWs had an eightfold higher HIV prevalence 
than registered FSWs. Similarly for syphilis, unregistered FSWs 
had a threefold higher prevalence than registered FSWs. 
Compared with registered FSWs, unregistered FSWs reported 
higher levels of HIV risk, were socioeconomically disadvantaged 
and predominantly Panamanian. Among other factors, unregis-
tered FSWs reported higher frequency of anal sex, lower fre-
quency of condom use for anal sex, more contact with 
high-risk groups like injection drug users and male sex workers, 
and longer duration since the last HIV test. Contact with high-
risk groups and lower condom use indicate unregistered FSWs 
may serve as an active bridging group for HIV and STI trans-
missions. Significant differences in income, education, exposure 
to violence, drug use, STIs, HIV risk and nationality by sex 
worker category have been reported in other countries. 
12-14 In 
Tijuana, Mexico, unregistered FSWs were predominantly local 
to the region, had lower income and fewer dependents, had 
worked as a sex worker for longer, reported more drug use, and 
had higher levels of STIs and HIV positivity than registered 
FSWs. 
13 The authors proposed that migrants to Tijuana who 
engaged in sex work were more likely to work in establish-
ments, thereby facilitating registration. It is possible that in 
Panama, poverty, social discrimination and economic need may 
preclude unregistered FSWs from affording the registration fees </p>

<p>required to work at entertainment establishments, leaving 
them with no other option except working on the streets. 
HSV-2, forced sex and having a history of STIs were asso-
ciated positively and independently with syphilis while regis-
tration was protective for syphilis. Sexual violence by clients is 
a barrier to condom negotiation, consequently increasing STIs 
and HIV risk. 
12 14-16 Observational studies have shown that 
prevalent serological syphilis and HSV-2 infections increase the 
risk of HIV acquisition two-to threefold. 
17 18 HSV-2 antibody 
prevalence and HIV incidence is higher among women who 
reported intimate partner violence. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>The potential threat of HIV spreading among unregistered 
FSWs in Panama is possible. HIV prevalence may increase in 
unregistered FSWs since they bear a higher burden of STIs, 
especially syphilis (&gt;6% overall prevalence), and reported more 
contact with high-risk groups like MSM and injection drug 
users. An STI prevalence rate of 3% or more, especially for 
curable STIs, influences the rate of HIV transmission in popula-
tions with low HIV prevalence. 
19 STI cofactors have accounted 
for 50% or more of HIV transmission in low and high 
HIV-prevalence cities. 
20 Multipronged prevention interventions 
which encompass peer outreach services, HIV counselling and 
testing, education sessions and STI syndromic management 
and testing at clinics have led to a decline in HIV incidence, 
and HIV and STI prevalence among FSWs. 
21 22 The low sero-
prevalence of HCV indicates that injection drug use possibly is 
rare in the surveyed population. 
The seroprevalences of HIV and STIs may have been underes-
timated in this survey. It is probable that sampling at venues 
where accessibility and the likelihood of participation was 
greater, excluded FSWs with higher risk. Areas in Colón and 
the Darien region were unapproachable for security reasons. 
FSWs in these areas and those fearful of authorities may be at 
greater risk of violence, have lower access to health services, 
and subsequently have higher risk for HIV and STIs. 
Although HIV prevalence among FSWs in Panama was low, 
compared with registered FSWs, unregistered FSWs or 'clandes-
tinas' bear a higher burden of HIV and STIs, were socio-
economically disadvantaged, reported higher frequencies of 
HIV risk behaviour, and higher risk for syphilis. Preliminary 
findings from this survey prompted the Panamanian MoH to 
open health clinics in areas easily accessible to unregistered 
FSWs. An assessment of obstacles to registration, and removal 
of these obstacles such that easy access to medical management 
of STIs for unregistered FSWs, such as those offered to regis-
tered FSWs, harm reduction, peer-based support and legal pro-
tections for those at risk of violence, are essential. </p>

<p>Table 2 Continued </p>

<p>Category 
Characteristic † </p>

<p>Syphilis (n=38) 
Unadjusted OR 
p Value </p>

<p>Adjusted OR 
p Value 
n positive/ total (%) 
(95% CI) 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Health history 
Sexually transmitted infection history 
Yes 
9/111 
(8.1) 
2.61 (1.20-5.68) 
0.0152 
2.37 (1.01-5.58) 
0.0486 
No 
29/888 
(3.3) 
1.00 
Use contraceptives 
No 
15/285 
(5.3) 
0.63 (0.32-1.23) 
0.1768 
Yes 
23/678 
(3.4) 
1.00 
Drug use 
Never used drugs 
22/737 
(3.0) 
0.47 (0.24-0.91) 
0.0262 
Used marijuana 
11/152 
(7.2) 
2.37 (1.15-4.89) 
0.0194 </p>

<p>*'Other' included Coclé, Herrera, Los Santos, Bocas del Toro, and Veraguas. 
 †Only characteristics significant at p&lt;0.20 are shown and were considered in multivariate analysis. </p>

<p>Sex Transm Infect 2013;89:156-164. doi:10.1136/sextrans-2012-050557 </p>

<p>
Epidemiology </p>

<p>Key messages </p>

<p>▸ HIV prevalence was low among female sex workers in 
Panama. 
▸ Unregistered sex workers had a higher burden of HIV and 
sexually transmitted infections (STI). 
▸ Four factors, HSV-2, forced sex, having a history of STIs and 
registration status, were associated with syphilis. 
▸ Prevention interventions for medical management of STIs 
among unregistered sex workers should be a priority. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The members of the Panama HIV EPI Group were: Sonia 
Morales Miranda (Director of the HIV Unit, Universidad del Valle, Guatemala), 
Bulbulgul Aumakhan, Juana R Torres (Mujeres con Dignidad de Panamá), Iris Reyes 
de González, Wendy González, and Jeymy P Trujillo. We thank the staff of the 
Ministry of Health, Panama, for their assistance in recruitment, interviews and blood 
collection; the Faculty of Medicine at the University of Panama for providing 
laboratory facilities for all serological testing conducted for the survey; key informants 
at community-based non-governmental organisations PASMO/Panama (Pan American 
Social Marketing Organization), PROBIDSIDA (Pro Bienestar y Dignidad de las 
Personas con SIDA), and APLAFA (Asociación Panameña para la Planificación 
Familiar). Last, but not least, we thank the owners and management of all 
establishments for their full support of the survey in the numerous visits the survey 
staff conducted to gather information and recruit women. </p>

<p>Contributors Concept and design: SH, GA, AN, CB, SP, GP, PS, JP; acquisition of 
data: GA, AN, AB, MV; analysis and interpretation of data: SH, PS; drafting of 
manuscript: SH; critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content: 
GA, AN, AB, MV, SP, GP, PS, JP. </p>

<p>Funding This work was supported by funds from the Military Infectious Disease 
Research Program, Secretary of Science and Technology of the Republic of Panama, 
Pan American Health Organization, Global Funds, Centers for Disease Control and 
Prevention, Panama National Program of HIV. </p>

<p>Disclaimer The views expressed are those of the authors and should not be 
construed to represent the positions of the US Department of Defense. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Ethics approval ICGES, WRAIR. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the 
Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 3.0) license, which 
permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and 
license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is 
properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/3.0/ </p>



<p> 
Sex Transm Infect 2013;89:156-164. doi:10.1136/sextrans-2012-050557 </p>

<p>Epidemiology </p>

</text></tei>