<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3287198" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Microsatellite DNA synthesis represents a signifi-
Repetitive DNA sequences make up at least 50% of the 
human genome, and many correspond to a DNA struc-
tural complexity that is not found in other regions of the 
genome (1). Microsatellites, one type of interspersed </p>

<p>tandem repeat, are ubiquitous throughout the genome 
(2) and can be important functional regulators of gene 
expression and phenotypic variability (3). Microsatellite 
allele length polymorphisms have been implicated as 
genetic risk factors in human disease (4,5), and expansions 
at specific microsatellites are responsible for at least 40 
inherited human disorders (6). Despite their importance 
for genome function and disease association, the fidelity 
mechanisms needed to maintain repetitive sequence stabil-
ity have not been fully elucidated. 
Stability of the eukaryotic genome requires the coopera-
tive activity of multiple DNA polymerases (7,8). The 
Y-family DNA polymerases are a distinct group of 
enzymes and are present in bacteria, archaea and 
eukarya species (9). Initial biochemical characterization 
of the eukaryotic enzymes focused on their involvement 
in translesion synthesis (TLS), guided by the homology of 
eukaryotic genes to Escherichia coli genes that are 
involved in the DNA damage response. The identification 
of Pol as the gene product affected in xeroderma 
pigmentosum-variant patients (10), together with the bio-
chemical demonstration that Pol promotes error-free 
bypass of several types of DNA lesions (11,12), solidified 
the concept that eukaryotic Y-family polymerases 
promote genetic stability through accurate TLS. 
Y-family polymerases can be distinguished by their sub-
strate preferences, in that the enzymes catalyze error-free 
TLS for a variety of DNA lesions but with differential 
efficiencies (7). For example, Pol has been implicated 
in the accurate bypass of adducts at the exocyclic N </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>position of guanine, such as benzo[a]pyrene diolepoxide 
(13) and furfuryl (14) lesions. The abilities of Pols and 
to catalyze DNA synthesis past specific DNA lesions 
with high fidelity demonstrates that inherent polymerase 
accuracy is dependent upon the structure of the DNA 
substrate. 
More recently, several investigations have garnered 
support for more widespread roles of Y-family polymer-
ases in genome function. Human cells deficient in Pol </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 717 531 4065; Fax: +1 717 531 5634; Email: kae4@psu.edu </p>

<p>1636-1647 Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 4 
Published online 22 October 2011 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkr889 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>display aberrant S-phase progression and increased 
chromosomal fragility in the absence of exogenous 
exposure to DNA damaging agents (15). Genetic knock-
down of Pol or Pol increases the sensitivity of human 
cells to telomestatin, a compound that stabilizes G 
tetraplex DNA secondary structures (16). In human fibro-
blasts, complete DNA synthesis associated with nucleotide 
excision repair requires both Pol and Pol as well as Pol 
e (17). The spontaneous germline mutation rate within 
two highly repetitive, expanded short tandem repeat 
alleles is higher for Pol -deficient mice, relative to 
isogenic Pol wild-type mice (18). Although limited, 
these studies suggest that Y-family polymerases have 
roles in genome maintenance beyond TLS. 
DNA polymerases and e are generally assumed to be 
responsible for the bulk of DNA replication as well as 
DNA synthesis associated with repair and recombination 
(19). These polymerases display highly accurate in vitro 
DNA synthesis using undamaged DNA templates 
(20,21). However, we reported that the replicative holoen-
zyme forms of yeast Pol and Pol e do not possess high 
fidelity during in vitro microsatellite DNA synthesis (22). 
Because Y-family polymerases perform accurate TLS of 
specific lesions, we hypothesized that the structural or 
biochemical features underlying accurate TLS may also 
allow increased polymerase discrimination of alternative 
DNA structures, such as those formed by repetitive micro-
satellite sequences. In this study, we demonstrate that 
the human Y-family polymerase, Pol , displays a 
high accuracy during dinucleotide microsatellite DNA 
synthesis. We postulate that accurately maintaining 
microsatellites and possibly other repeated DNA </p>

<p>sequences may be an additional cellular function for 
specialized DNA polymerases. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>In vitro gap-filling HSV-tk mutagenesis assay </p>

<p>The 4-subunit recombinant human Pol 4 and 
proliferating cell nuclear antigen (PCNA) were purified 
as described (23). Purified full-length Pol (99 kDa) and 
Pol (78 kDa) were purchased from Enzymax (Lexington, 
KY, USA). Microsatellite-containing Herpes simplex 
virus type 1 thymidine kinase (HSV-tk) vectors have 
been previously described (24,25). The MluI (position 
83) to StuI (position 180) HSV-tk target sequence within 
the gapped duplex (GD) molecule contains 89-91 bp of 
HSV-tk gene coding region sequence, and 8 bp ([T] 8 ), 
20 bp ([GT] 10 ), or 22 bp ([TC] 11 ) of microsatellite 
sequence (Figure 1A). In vitro gap-filling reactions 
(Figure 1B) contained 0.075-0.125 pmol of gapped sub-
strate and 250 mM deoxynucleotide triphosphates 
(dNTPs) in 100 ml final volume. Pol 4 reactions contained 
40 mM Tris pH 7.8, 10 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM DTT, 5 mM 
NaCl, 200 mg/ml BSA and 1.2-4 pmol pol 4. Pol 4 reac-
tions containing accessory factors were supplemented with 
2 mM ATP, 40 ng (450 fmol) PCNA and 5 ng (17 fmol) 
replication factor C (RFC). Reactions were incubated at 
37 
C for 30 min-1 h. Pol and Pol reactions contained 
25 mM potassium phosphate buffer pH 7.2, 5 mM MgCl 2 , 
5 mM DTT, 100 ug/mL BSA, 10% glycerol and 1.9-
9.4 pmol of polymerase. Reactions were incubated at 
37 
C for 2 h. All reactions were terminated with 15 mM </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Figure 1. Schematic of the HSV-tk experimental system. (A) HSV-tk mutational target. Short tandem repeat (STR) sequences were inserted in-frame 
between bases 111 and 112 of the HSV-tk mutational target to create artificial microsatellites (MS). Inactivating mutations can arise within the MS 
sequence (MS mutation frequency in Tables 1 and 2), as well as within the approximately 100 base pair region (MluI-StuI) of the in vitro HSV-tk 
gene mutational target (HSV-tk coding mutation frequency in Tables 1 and 2). The sum of these mutations is shown as the overall Pol EF in 
Tables 1 and 2. (B) Cartoon of experimental approach. HSV-tk gene cassettes were cloned into two sister plasmids, one of which encodes a 
functional chloramphenicol acetyltransferase (cat) gene (pRStu) and one which encodes a nonfunctional cat gene (pSStu) (24,25). The location of 
the MS sequences is indicated by an inverted triangle. Gapped heteroduplex molecules were created by hybridizing the MluI-StuI large fragment 
from the pRStu vector to ssDNA derived from pSStu vectors. Gel purified gapped substrates were used as templates for DNA synthesis reactions 
containing purified human DNA polymerases. Product DNAs were introduced into E. coli (upp, tdk) for mutational analyses. Chloramphenicol (Cm) 
selects for bacteria derived from the heteroduplex Cm 
R strand; FUdR selects for HSV-tk-deficient bacteria. DNA sequence changes of independent 
FUdR 
R mutants are determined to derive a mutational spectrum. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 4 1637 </p>

<p>Ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA), and exchanged 
into Tris-EDTA (TE) buffer. Complete gap filling by all 
three polymerases was verified as described (22)  (Supplementary Figure S1). An aliquot of DNA from 
complete gap-filling reactions was used to transform E. 
coli strain FT334 for mutant frequency determination 
(26) (Figure 1B). To control for pre-existing mutations, 
we also determined the HSV-tk mutant frequencies 
(MF) for each ssDNA used to construct the GD mol-
ecules. The DNA sequences within the target region of 
independent mutants isolated from 2 to 3 polymerase re-
actions per template were determined (24). </p>

<p>Determination of polymerase error frequencies </p>

<p>Pol and Pol produced multiple mutational events per 
target sequence, while Pol 4 normally created only 1 mu-
tational event per target. In order to properly compare 
error rates among these three polymerases, we identified 
those mutational events that were detectable as single mu-
tational events, and adjusted the HSV-tk MF to reflect 
multiple errors per target. First, polymerase error 
frequencies (Pol EFs) were determined by the following 
equation: Pol EF = (Observed MF)-(ssDNA background 
MF)-(Outside target MF) where outside target MF is the 
frequency of errors occurring outside the gap target, either 
through background errors in the GD molecule, polymer-
ase displacement synthesis or polymerase exonuclease 
activity (Pol 4). Next, the Pol EF was adjusted by per-
forming calculations as described (27) with a few modifi-
cations. Each mutational event was scored as detectable or 
undetectable. All frameshifts and those base substitutions 
that changed an amino acid were considered detectable. 
Each mutational event was also scored as tandem or 
non-tandem. Tandem events were those adjacent to one 
another, whereas non-tandem were errors &gt;1 nt apart. To 
fully represent all of the mutational events created by the 
human polymerases, both detectable and undetectable 
events within the HSV-tk gene are depicted in 
Supplementary Figure S2. However, only those that 
were detectable were used for determining Pol EF est . Pol 
EFs were then corrected for the existence of multiple mu-
tations according to the following formula: </p>

<p>Pol EF est ¼ Pol EF= 
X 4 </p>

<p>n¼1 </p>

<p>ð1=nÞðmutants with n errors= </p>

<p>total analyzed mutants) </p>

<p>where n is the number of detectable non-tandem errors. 
The Pol EF est of a specific type of mutational event was 
calculated from the proportion of the specific mutational 
event (among the total analyzed) multiplied by Pol EF est . </p>

<p>Pol d4 and Pol j primer extension competition analyses </p>

<p>In a common buffer (25 mM potassium phosphate buffer 
pH 7.2, 5 mM MgCl 2 , 2.5 mM DTT, 200 mg/ml 
non-acetylated BSA and 250 mM dNTPs), Pol is 4-to 
5-fold more active than Pol 4 in the absence or presence 
of PCNA, using circular ssDNA as the template 
(Supplementary Figure S3, panel B). Primer extension </p>

<p>analyses were performed to determine termination within 
a [GT] 10 microsatellite for Pol 4 and Pol individually 
and together in a competition assay. Primer IHTW02, a 
15-mer oligonucleotide that initiates synthesis at HSV-tk 
position 132 was radioactively 5 
0 end-labeled and 
hybridized to [GT] 10 -containing ssDNA as described 
(28). Reactions containing 100 fmol of primed substrate 
and the common buffer in a final volume of 20 ml were 
preincubated at 37 
C for 3 min. Synthesis was initiated 
upon addition of Pol or equivalent activity of Pol 4. 
Aliquots were removed at 5, 15 and 30 min and quenched 
as described (28). Reaction products were separated on an 
8% denaturing polyacrylamide gel and quantitated using 
a Molecular Dynamics Phosphoimager. The number of 
DNA molecules within three regions (5 
0 to the [GT] 10 
microsatellite, the [GT] 10 microsatellite, and 3 
0 to the 
[GT] 10 microsatellite) were determined by <rs type="software">ImageQuant</rs> 
software and corrected for background and loading dif-
ferences. [GT] 10 termination probability is defined as the 
number of molecules within the [GT] 10 microsatellite 
divided by the number of molecules within the [GT] 10 
microsatellite and 3 
0 to the [GT] 10 microsatellite. 
Polymerase competition assays were performed similarly 
with 400 fmol of Pol 4 ± 500 fmol PCNA, initiating syn-
thesis in either moving (with 250 mM dNTPs) or stalled 
(-dATP) conditions. After 5 min, 40 fmol of Pol or an 
equivalent activity of Pol 4 (200 fmol; thus, 600 fmol Pol 
4 final) was added (along with a final concentration of 
250 mM dATP in the stalled reactions). Quantitation of 
reaction products was performed as above. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>To measure the frequency and types of mutational events 
within repetitive DNA, we engineered the 5 
0 -region of the 
HSV-tk gene to contain a variety of in-frame, short micro-
satellite (MS) sequences (Figure 1A). Gapped DNA 
heteroduplex molecules were constructed, and an in vitro 
DNA polymerase gap-filling assay was used to measure 
polymerase error rates within the MluI to StuI target (24). 
Forward mutations that inactivate the HSV-tk protein 
were scored after transfection of E. coli with the reaction 
products and selective plating (Figure 1B). An HSV-tk 
mutant phenotype can be generated either by mutations 
arising within the microsatellite motifs (that are not a 
multiple of three), or by mutations arising within the sur-
rounding HSV-tk target coding sequence (Figure 1A). 
This experimental approach allows us to directly 
measure mutations in microsatellite alleles of varying 
sequence composition, and compare such events to muta-
tions in the HSV-tk-coding sequence. </p>

<p>Replicative DNA polymerase fidelity within 
microsatellite alleles </p>

<p>We measured the fidelity of the recombinant 4-subunit 
holoenzyme form of human DNA polymerase (Pol 4). 
Polymerase reactions were performed using gapped DNA 
substrates containing [GT] 10 , [TC] 11 or [T] 8 microsatellite 
reporter cassettes. The observed HSV-tk mutant 
frequencies for Pol 4 were 8-to 44-fold higher than the </p>



<p>ssDNA background frequency (Table 1). The observed 
HSV-tk mutant frequencies were adjusted for background 
and multiple mutational events after DNA sequence 
analyses to obtain the overall estimated polymerase 
error frequencies (overall Pol EF est ; Table 1). This 
overall PolEF est is a result of polymerase errors within 
both the HSV-tk coding and microsatellite sequences of 
the target (Figure 1A). Polymerase error frequencies solely 
within the HSV-tk coding or the microsatellite sequences 
were calculated based on the proportion of mutational 
events within each of these regions. The majority 
(76-94%) of human Pol 4 errors were produced within 
the microsatellite sequences for all three substrates 
(Table 1). The Pol EF est for Pol 4 errors was high 
within the [GT] 10 (2.3 Â 10 </p>

<p>À3 </p>

<p>), [TC] 11 (2.4 Â 10 
À3 ), and 
[T] 8 (3.1 Â 10 </p>

<p>À3 </p>

<p>) alleles. We examined whether the 
PCNA/RFC complex could specifically increase Pol 4 
fidelity at microsatellite sequences. Pol 4 fidelity within 
either the HSV-tk-coding sequences or the [GT] 10 and 
[TC] 11 microsatellites was not altered by the addition of 
PCNA and RFC (Table 1). An earlier study showed that 
these accessory proteins lower yeast Pol fidelity for base 
substitution errors (29). </p>

<p>Y-family DNA polymerase fidelity within microsatellites </p>

<p>We tested our hypothesis that microsatellite mutagenesis 
may vary with respect to DNA polymerase families, using 
human Y-family polymerases. Under our experimental 
buffer and template conditions, Pol and Pol display 
similar or better DNA synthesis efficiencies to that of Pol 
4 (Supplementary Figure S3 and data not shown). The 
observed HSV-tk mutant frequencies for Pol and Pol 
reactions were 3-to 16-fold higher than Pol 4 for each 
template (Table 2). As a control, we compared the relative 
accuracy of the three polymerases during synthesis of the 
HSV-tk-coding sequences. The average coding Pol EF est </p>

<p>was 4.5 Â 10 
À4 for Pol 4, 120 Â 10 
À4 for Pol , and 
380 Â 10 
À4 for Pol (Supplementary Table S1). Thus, 
Pol and Pol are, on average, 27-and 84-fold less 
accurate than Pol 4 at coding sequences, respectively. 
These data are in complete agreement with published 
results using the lacZ target and purified proteins from 
other sources (30-32). 
When comparing polymerase fidelity at microsatellite 
sequences, we observed a low Pol error rate for muta-
tions arising within the [GT] 10 and [TC] 11 dinucleotide se-
quences (Table 2). Remarkably, the Pol error frequency 
measured within dinucleotide alleles is 4-to 8-fold lower 
than the frequency of errors within the HSV-tk-coding 
region. Moreover, within these two microsatellite alleles, 
Pol does not display an error-prone phenotype, as the 
Pol EF est for Pol is not higher than that for Pol 4 
(Tables 1 and 2). This selective accuracy is specific for 
Pol and not a general feature of Y-family polymerases, 
since the Pol EF est for dinucleotide errors produced by Pol 
is high for both microsatellite alleles (Table 2). </p>

<p>The creation of microsatellite interruptions by human 
DNA polymerases </p>

<p>Various types of errors can be produced by polymerases 
within dinucleotide microsatellite alleles (33), and can be 
broadly classified into either unit-based insertion/deletion 
(indel) errors (where 2 nt is the unit size for dinucleotide 
repeats), or interruption errors (Figure 2A). Microsatellite 
unit-based indel errors characterize the mutational 
behavior of microsatellites observed in numerous model 
systems. If left uncorrected, such errors will result in allele 
length changes that can be a source of genomic instability 
(3). Interruption errors are any error that disrupts the 
tandem repeat sequence, converting the repetitive tract 
from one that is pure to one that is impure. Such 
errors in dinucleotide alleles can occur via multiple </p>

<p>Table 1. Replicative DNA polymerase holoenzyme error rates within microsatellite and HSV-tk coding DNA sequences </p>

<p>Polymerase 
Observed HSV-tk 
frequency 
a Â10 
À4 (± SD) 
Pol EF est Â 10 
À4 b (No. mutational events observed) </p>

<p>Overall 
HSV-tk coding </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Microsatellite </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>pSStu2 / [GT] 10 template 
None </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>4.1 
0.26 (3) 
&lt;0.087 (0) 
0.26 (3) 
Pol d4 
32 ± 5.2 
27 (67) 
4.0 (10) 
23 (57) 
Pol d4+PCNA/RFC 
41 
31 (33) 
5.6 (6) 
25 (27) 
pSStu4 / [TC]11 template 
None 
3.5 
2.0 (26) 
&lt;0.078 (0) 
2.0 (26) 
Pol d4 
43 ± 22 
31 (62) 
7.5 (15) 
24 (47) 
Pol d4+PCNA/RFC 
28 
20 (24) 
6.7 (8) 
13 (16) 
pSStu10/ [T]8 template 
None 
0.89 
ND 
ND 
ND 
Pol d4 
39 ± 8.2 
33 (32) 
2.1 (2) 
31 (30) </p>

<p>a Observed mutant frequencies are mean of two, or mean ± SD of 3-6 independent reactions. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Polymerase error frequency (Pol EF) was calculated using the equation: Pol EF = (Observed MF) -(ssDNA Background MF) -(Outside Target 
MF). 
Pol EFs were adjusted for those mutants that had 2 or more mutational events in the target (see Methods). Mutants analyzed for DNA sequence 
changes were isolated from 2-3 independent polymerase reactions. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Coding and microsatellite PolEF est were calculated by multiplying the proportion of mutational events at either site by the overall PolEF est . </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Mutant frequency measured by electroporation of the ssDNA used to create the gapped DNA substrates. The corresponding overall Pol EF value is 
the frequency of mutations within the gapped target. 
ND not determined. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 4 1639 </p>

<p>mechanisms, including single base indel or base substitu-
tion errors (Figure 2A). Although interruptions are poly-
merase errors, such errors are expected to be less 
detrimental genetically than unit-based indel errors. 
First, interruptions are known to stabilize expanded </p>

<p>microsatellites (6). Second, microsatellite interruptions 
can divide the sequence into two smaller alleles with 
lengths below the threshold (34), thereby lowering mut-
ability and initiating microsatellite degeneration. 
We compared the propensity for the three polymerases 
to create interruption errors in vitro. The replicative Pol 4 
enzyme created very few interruptions within the alleles 
examined (Figure 2B). In stark contrast, Pol produced 
many interruption errors (up to 81%) within the GT 10 and 
TC 11 alleles, which is significantly different from Pol 4 
(P 0.0001 and P = 0.002, respectively, Fisher's exact 
test, Figure 2B). Thus, the Pol error frequency within 
the dinucleotide alleles is low (Table 2), and the few errors 
that are made by Pol are often interruptions, which may 
have beneficial consequences. </p>

<p>Distinct polymerase fidelity of unit-based indels within 
microsatellites </p>

<p>Both unit-based microsatellite allele length changes and 
traditional frameshift errors within coding sequences 
arise by a strand misalignment mechanism. Therefore, to 
directly compare the likelihood of the two types of poly-
merase misaligment errors, we calculated the Pol EF est for 
indel errors within the HSV-tk coding region versus 
unit-based indel errors within the microsatellite alleles. 
The HSV-tk target sequence includes 23 'monitor' sites 
of short tandem repeats (19 mononucleotide and four 
dinucleotide repeats of 2-3 units in length) that provide 
a good portrayal of polymerase indel errors occurring 
within coding sequences (34; underlined sequences in 
Supplementary Figure S2). As the HSV-tk coding region 
Pol EF est for each polymerase did not vary substantially 
between the different templates examined, a composite 
spectrum of coding region errors was created for each 
polymerase (Supplementary Figure S2). Strikingly, Pol 
produced primarily indel errors within monitor tandem 
repeats, as well as at non-repeated sequences. The Pol 
EF est for Pol or Pol indel errors within the HSV-tk 
coding region is $100-fold higher than the Pol EF est for 
Pol 4 (Figure 3A and Supplementary Table S1). These 
data establish that the hierarchy of polymerase accuracy 
for indel errors within short tandem repeats of coding se-
quences follows the order: Pol 4 &gt;&gt; Pol or Pol . A </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Single 
Base 
Insertion </p>

<p>Single 
Base 
Deletion </p>

<p>Base 
Subst. 
Unit-
Based 
Indel </p>

<p>[GT] 10 
[GT] n </p>

<p>[GT] 10 
[GT] 5 T[GT] 4 </p>

<p>[GT] 10 
[GT] 8 T[GT] 2 </p>

<p>[GT] 10 
[GT] 6 GA[GT] 3 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Specialized Y-family polymerases Pol and Pol create 
more interruptions in dinucleotide microsatellites than does Pol 4. 
(A) Types of mutations arising within dinucleotide microsatellites. 
Mutations within the dinucleotide microsatellite can occur via 
unit-based indel events (gray area) or by interruption events (white 
areas). Examples of interruption events by single base insertion, 
single base deletion, and base substitution mechanisms are shown for 
the [GT] 10 allele. (B) Graphs depict the proportion of microsatellite 
interruptions among the total number of microsatellite mutational 
events at the [GT] 10 and [TC] 11 alleles for Pol 4 (solid bars), Pol 
(hatched bars) and Pol (gray bars). </p>

<p>Table 2. Y Family DNA polymerase error rates within microsatellite and HSV-tk coding DNA sequences </p>

<p>Polymerase 
Observed HSV-tk 
frequency 
a Â 10 
À4 (± SD) 
Pol EF est Â 10 
À4b (No. mutational events observed) </p>

<p>Overall 
HSV-tk coding </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Microsatellite </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>pSStu2 / [GT] 10 template 
Pol 
140 ± 67 
160 (160) 
140 (144) 
16 (16) 
Pol 
460 ± 52 
410 (100) 
320 (79) 
86 (21) 
pSStu4 / [TC] 11 template 
Pol 
120 ± 39 
100 (75) 
80 (60) 
20 (15) 
Pol 
680 ± 120 
710 (130) 
430 (78) 
280 (52) 
pSStu10 / [T] 8 template 
Pol 
430 ± 85 
460 (49) 
140 (15) 
320 (34) 
Pol 
430 ± 140 
440 (35) 
210 (17) 
230 (18) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mutant frequencies are mean ± standard deviation of 3-6 independent reactions. 
b,c See legend to Table I for derivation of values. 
Bold values indicate a low Pol error frequency for mutations arising within the [GT] 
10 and [TC] 
11 sequences. </p>



<p>similar result was observed for the relative accuracy of 
Pols 4, and during synthesis of the [T] 8 
mononucleotide microsatellite allele. Specifically, Pols 
and displayed a 10-fold higher Pol EF est for unit-based 
errors within the allele than did Pol 4 (Figure 3B). 
A very different hierarchy of polymerase fidelity was 
observed for unit-based indel errors within both dinucleo-
tide alleles. Pol 4 produced almost exclusively (89-95%) 
unit-based indel errors (and correspondingly few interrup-
tions; Figure 2B), resulting in a high unit-based indel error 
frequency (Figure 3C and D). In contrast, few unit-based 
indel errors were observed in the Pol error spectra, 
because Pol creates many interruptions (Figure 2B). 
Thus, the resulting Pol EF est for unit-based indel errors </p>

<p>produced by Pol was lower than that produced by Pol 4 
in both dinucleotide alleles (Figure 3C and D). 
To compare polymerase indel error rates among targets 
of differing repeat lengths, we calculated the Pol EF/unit, 
where the unit size is one for mononucleotide and two for 
dinucleotide repeats (Table 3). For Pol 4, the GT micro-
satellite indel error rate is 100-fold higher than 
HSV-tk-coding indel error rate, demonstrating the 
inherent inaccuracy of Pol 4 at microsatellites (Table 3). 
Quite the opposite is true for Pol , as the ratio of the indel 
error rate within the GT microsatellite versus the 
HSV-tk-coding sequence is 0.17 (Table 3). Within the 
TC allele, the Pol 4 indel error rate/unit is 22 Â 10 
À5 , 
and the Pol indel error rate/unit is 11 Â 10 
À5 . Thus, </p>

<p>Figure 3. Comparison of DNA polymerase unit-based indel accuracy. (A) HSV-tk-coding sequence monitors. For each polymerase, the coding 
region polymerase error frequencies (from Tables 1 and 2) were averaged among all templates, and the combined proportion of indel errors at the 
23 monitor sites versus all detectable mutational events was calculated. This proportion was multiplied by the average coding PolEF est and the result 
graphed. One example of the type of mutations included in the analysis is depicted: the loss of one C residue within a short mononucleotide tandem 
repeat at HSV-tk positions 167-168. See Supplementary Figure S2 for complete representation of indel mutations at the 23 monitor sites. No 
mutational events were found at the coding region monitors among the mutants sequenced for the ssDNA background, and the error frequency is 
estimated to be &lt;0.08 Â 10 
À4 . (B) [T] 8 mononucleotide repeat. Indels at [T] 8 are defined as any gain or loss of T units that change the length of 
the [T] 8 tract to [T] n . The PolEF est for [T] 8 indels was calculated by multiplying the proportion of MS unit indel errors by the MS PolEF est (Tables 1 
and 2) for each polymerase. Background mutants from [T] 8 ssDNA were not sequenced; therefore, the indel error frequency is 0.89 Â 10 
À4 . 
(C) [GT] 10 microsatellite; and (D) [TC] 11 microsatellite sequences. Indels at [GT] 10 or [TC] 11 are defined as any gain or loss of dinucleotide units 
that change the length of the tract. The PolEF est for [GT] 10 and [TC] 11 indels was calculated by multiplying the proportion of MS indel errors by the 
MS PolEF est (Tables 1 and 2) for each template and polymerase. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 4 1641 </p>

<p>the ratio of polymerase error rates within the TC micro-
satellite/coding sequence is 130 for Pol 4, but only 0.7 for 
Pol . The similarity in rank order of polymerase fidelity 
for GT and TC motifs suggests that Pol accuracy may be 
similar to or greater than that of replicative polymerases 
at other dinucleotide alleles. Our data demonstrate that 
the hierarchy of DNA polymerase fidelity is dependent 
upon DNA substrate sequence, and for dinucleotide 
microsatellites, follows the alternative order: Pol ! Pol 
4 &gt; Pol . </p>

<p>Cooperativity between Pol d4 and Pol j at dinucleotide 
microsatellites </p>

<p>Using an E. coli model, Indiani et al. demonstrated that 
E. coli Pol IV can freely exchange with a moving replica-
tive Pol III holoenzyme during DNA replication (35). In 
another model, an exchange between Saccharomyces 
cerevisiae Pol and Pol was observed only upon 
stalling of the replicative polymerase (36). In both of 
these models, the polymerase exchange was monitored 
as a change in DNA synthesis rates and/or length of the 
DNA reaction products. Keeping these studies in mind, 
we ascertained whether Pol 4 and Pol displayed 
polymerase-specific termination profiles within the GT 10 
microsatellite that could be used to monitor polymerase 
exchange. The termination probability of Pol 4 within 
the GT allele was determined at three different 
polymerase:DNA template ratios (Figure 4). Under 
limiting enzyme conditions (2.5:1, Pol 4:DNA ratio), we 
observed a high termination probability (0.76-0.84) within 
the [GT] 10 sequence at all time points (Figure 4B, top 
panel). With higher amounts of enzyme, the termination 
probability decreased with increasing reaction time 
(Figure 4B, bottom panel), suggesting the product accu-
mulation observed within the [GT] 10 sequence is due to </p>

<p>slowing of Pol 4 synthesis rather than an absolute inhib-
ition. To directly compare polymerase synthesis profiles, 
we determined the specific activities of our preparations of 
Pol 4 and Pol using both primer extension (ssDNA 
template containing a [GT] 10 sequence) and dTTP incorp-
oration 
(poly 
dA/oligo 
dT 
primer-template) 
(Supplementary Figure S3). Under identical buffer condi-
tions, Pol is 4-to 5-fold more active than Pol 4. 
Therefore, we examined Pol termination probability 
within the [GT] 10 sequence using 4-5-fold lower molar 
amounts of enzyme, relative to Pol 4 (i.e. we compared 
equal activity). Under enzyme-limiting conditions (0.5:1, 
enzyme to DNA ratio), the Pol termination probability 
within the [GT] 10 sequence was 0.56-0.60, lower than Pol 
4 at all time points (Figure 4B, top panel). With 
increasing Pol amounts, termination probability again 
decreased with reaction time. More importantly, however, 
the Pol termination probability was significantly lower 
than the Pol 4 termination probability for every time 
point examined (P = 0.003, 5 and 15 min; P = 0.05, 
30 min; unpaired student t-test) (Figure 4B, middle panel). 
The differential termination observed above within the 
GT allele allowed us to test whether Pol could alleviate 
microsatellite-specific Pol 4 termination. In preliminary 
experiments, we observed a significant decrease in GT 10  termination when the synthesis reactions contained both 
Pol 4 and Pol in similar molar amounts (0.5 pmol Pol 4 
and 0.25 pmol Pol ), relative to reactions containing 
0.75 pmol of Pol 4 alone (Supplementary Figure S4). 
However, we also observed an appreciable increase in 
total primer-template extension in the dual polymerase 
reactions, relative to reactions with Pol 4 alone. 
Because we also noted a difference in the specific activity 
of our two enzyme preparations (Supplementary Figure 
S3), we were concerned that using near equimolar poly-
merase amounts would give an unfair advantage to the 
more active polymerase preparation, in this case, Pol . 
Thus, we examined whether Pol could compete with Pol 
4 during microsatellite DNA synthesis using submolar 
amounts of Pol to control for specific activity differ-
ences. We examined two different experimental scenarios. 
In the first set of experiments, we allowed Pol 4 to begin 
synthesis without any impediments, and then added either 
a 10-fold submolar amount of Pol , relative to Pol 4, or 
an equal activity of additional Pol 4 (as a control). After 
quantitating the resultant termination probability within 
the [GT] 10 sequence, we observed that the amount of 
microsatellite-specific termination decreased when Pol 
was added to the reaction, relative to the Pol 4 only 
reaction (Figure 5A). These results demonstrate that Pol 
can effectively compete with a moving Pol 4 for 
primer-extension synthesis, even when Pol 4 is present 
in a 10-fold molar excess over Pol . In the second set of 
experiments, we loaded Pol 4 onto the DNA template in 
the presence of only three dNTP substrates in order to 
force Pol 4 to stall prior to encountering the microsatel-
lite sequence. Again, we added either Pol or an equal 
activity of additional Pol 4, along with dATP, 
and analyzed DNA synthesis progression through the 
microsatellite. We observed a decrease of the 
microsatellite-specific Pol 4 pause with addition of as </p>

<p>Table 3. The hierarchy of DNA polymerase accuracy for indel errors 
is substrate-dependent </p>

<p>Polymerase 
Pol 
family </p>

<p>Indel polymerase 
error rate Â10 </p>

<p>À5 </p>

<p>Ratio GT 10 / 
HSV-tk </p>

<p>HSV-tk 
coding </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>[GT] 10 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>ypole </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>B 
0.033 
9.0 
270 
hpol 
B 
0.17 
22 
130 
ypol </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>B 
0.23 
25 
110 
calf thymus pol </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>B 
1.9 
19 
10 
rat pol </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>X 
3.3 
8.4 
2.5 
hpol 
Y 
13 
62 
4.8 
hpol 
Y 
18 
3.0 
0.17 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Coding indel monitor polymerase error rates are reported per unit and 
were determined by dividing the coding indel PolEF est by the total 
number of mono-and dinucleotide units included in all monitor sites 
(total from target sequence is 48). </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>[GT] 10 indel polymerase error rates are reported per unit and were 
determined by dividing the microsatellite indel PolEF est by the total 
number of GT units. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Data from (22). </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Unpublished data. </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>Data from (24,34). </p>



<p>little as 40 fmol Pol (Figure 5B). The presence of PCNA 
did not affect the results in either set of experiments, 
indicating that PCNA does not inhibit the competition 
between Pols 4 and (Figure 5). These biochemical 
results suggest that Pols 4 and can act cooperatively 
to reduce polymerase stalling within microsatellite 
sequences. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Intrinsic DNA features have been established as the 
primary determinants of microsatellite allele length vari-
ation (33). While the strand-slippage mechanism can 
readily account for the effects of microsatellite length 
(number of repeat units) on mutability, the mechanisms 
by which motif size and sequence composition affect 
microsatellite variation are less well established. In this 
study, we report that the human Y-family polymerase, 
Pol , displays a high accuracy during dinucleotide micro-
satellite DNA synthesis. Surprisingly, we observed that </p>

<p>the relative DNA polymerase accuracy for unit-based 
indel errors during dinucleotide microsatellite DNA syn-
thesis is: Pol ! Pol 4 &gt; Pol (Figure 3C, D). This hier-
archy is in distinct contrast to the one we observed within 
the HSV-tk-coding sequence control: Pol 4 &gt;&gt; Pol or 
Pol . Although Pol generated many strand-slippage 
errors within mononucleotide repeats, it is unusually 
accurate for unit-based indel events at the dinucleotide 
microsatellites (Figure 3). This behavior contrasts not 
only with human Pol 4, but also with yeast Pol and 
Pol e holoenzymes, and calf-thymus Pola-primase 
(Table 3). We measured a significantly higher termination 
probability for Pol 4 than for Pol within the [GT] 10 
microsatellite (Figure 4), and used this differential termin-
ation to demonstrate that Pol can compete with a 
moving Pol 4 enzyme during microsatellite DNA synthe-
sis (Figure 5). These results demonstrate that Pol 4 and 
Pol can cooperate enzymatically during dinucleotide 
microsatellite DNA synthesis. Our study conceptually 
extends the role of Pol beyond accurate translesion </p>

<p>Figure 4. Differential termination of Pol 4 and Pol DNA synthesis within the [GT] 10 microsatellite. (A) Representative phosphoimager scan of 
primer extension reaction products. The enzyme:DNA ratios for Pol (middle panel) and equivalent activity of Pol 4 (right panel) are indicated. 
Triangles represent increasing reaction times (5, 15, 30 min). Reactions were run alongside a DNA sequencing ladder (left panel). (B) Quantitation of 
the reaction products. Termination probability was calculated by determining the number of molecules within the [GT] 10 microsatellite divided by the 
number of molecules within and 3 
0 to the [GT] 10 microsatellite. Graphs compare results from equal activities of Pol and Pol 4. Data points are the 
mean of 2-6 independent reactions; error bars represent the standard deviation determined from 3 or more reactions. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 4 1643 </p>

<p>synthesis to include accurate synthesis of dinucleotide re-
petitive elements. As other studies (refs. 15-18) also have 
indicated a more widespread functional role of Y-family 
polymerases, we propose that the terminology 'specialized 
polymerases' to describe the Y-family polymerases may be 
more appropriate than the term TLS polymerases. Our 
data also demonstrate that the broad characterization of 
Y-family polymerases as error prone is not appropriate 
when considering the entire genome. 
Pol could potentially promote microsatellite stability 
in two ways. First, this polymerase has an inherently high 
fidelity for unit-based indel errors within dinucleotide 
microsatellites (Figure 3C, D), and may act to limit micro-
satellite allele length variation. Second, when Pol does </p>

<p>make errors within the microsatellites, it frequently creates 
interruption errors (Figure 2) within the long tandem 
repeat. We reported previously that a threshold length 
of 5 units exists for the mutability of GT/CA microsatel-
lites in vitro and in human populations (34). Below the 
threshold length, the rate of mutation within the tandem 
repeat is not higher than the rate of indel mutations in 
coding sequences. Above the threshold, the mutability of 
the tandem repeat increases exponentially as the number 
of repeats increases. Therefore, the interruption errors 
made by Pol effectively break the long dinucleotide 
repeat arrays into two, shorter arrays that will mutate at 
a lower frequency. The in vitro results we report here are 
entirely consistent with the in vivo phenotype of Pol null </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Figure 5. Pol and Pol 4 act cooperatively to alleviate pausing within the [GT] 10 microsatellite. (A) Analyses performed under moving Pol 4 
conditions. Left panel: Schematic of the experimental design. Middle panel: Phosphoimager scan of reaction products obtained in either the absence 
(-PCNA) or presence (+PCNA) of 500 fmol PCNA. Lanes 1 and 4 of each reaction set show products after the 5 min incubation with 400 fmol Pol 4 
alone. Lanes 2 and 3 are products after addition of 40 fmol of Pol . The reactions were terminated after an additional 20 or 35 min. Lanes 5 and 6 
are products after second addition of Pol 4 (200 fmol for a total of 600 fmol) and termination after an additional 20 or 35 min. Polymerase 
conditions were chosen so that 100% of the available primer-template was extended by 20 min whether we added Pol or additional Pol 4. 
Right panel: Termination probability within the [GT] 10 sequence at 35 min under each polymerase condition. (B) Analyses performed under stalled 
Pol 4 conditions. Pol 4 stalling was created by excluding dATP during the first 5 min of the reaction. Reactions conditions are otherwise the same 
as in (A). </p>



<p>mice. The spontaneous germline mutation rate within 
two expanded short tandem repeat (ESTR) alleles for 
Pol -deficient mice is significantly higher than within 
isogenic Pol wild-type mice (18). 
All cells contain multiple DNA polymerases, and a 
widely held belief is that individual polymerases serve 
specialized functions that are necessary to maintain 
genome stability (19). The original paradigm for the func-
tions of TLS polymerases posited that these enzymes 
promote the bypass of DNA lesions representing severe 
obstacles to replicative DNA polymerases, albeit at the 
cost of introducing mutations (37). This paradigm has 
shifted, as additional evidence has demonstrated that 
TLS polymerases can carry out error free bypass of 
specific DNA lesions in vivo, suggesting that this group 
of polymerases are structurally adapted for cognate 
lesions (38,39). Specifically, Pol has been implicated in 
efficient and error-free bypass in vivo of exocyclic N 
2 -
guanine lesions, such as benzo(a)pyrene diol epoxide 
formed by polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAH) 
(13,40). 
The studies we report here extend this growing 
paradigm shift, with the novel finding that Pol is 
accurate when processing dinucleotide repetitive 
elements. The number of dinucleotide microsatellite 
alleles in the human reference genome (hg 18) is 
$227 000 for [GT/CA] alleles alone, and $500 000 for di-
nucleotide alleles of all sequence motifs (Supplementary 
Table S2). In comparison, the number of PAH adducts 
present in the genomes of mothers and newborns (41) or 
non-smokers (42) is 78-1080 adducts/cell, and rises to a 
high of 2040 adducts/cell in the lung epithelium of 
smokers (42). Clearly, the potential mutational load 
from polymerase errors during synthesis of microsatellites 
sequences in the human genome is much higher than that 
expected from PAH lesions. The exact role of Pol in 
genome replication will need to be investigated by add-
itional in vivo studies. 
The proposal that specialized polymerases, such as Pol 
, participate in chromosomal replication to maintain 
genomic integrity implies that genome-wide replication 
involves the cooperation of multiple DNA polymerases 
in addition to the classical replicative polymerases. In eu-
karyotes, a direct interaction has been shown between 
Rev1 and the Pol Pol32 subunit (43) as well as 
between Rev1 and Pol (44), consistent with models 
proposing that TLS polymerases may be an integral com-
ponent of the replication fork. Indeed, human Pol can be 
found localized to PCNA-containing replication foci in 
undamaged cells (45). Current models of E. coli replica-
tion also propose the presence of multiple DNA polymer-
ases at the replication fork. The active E. coli replisome 
has been shown by direct microscopy in living cells to 
contain three molecules of the replicative polymerase 
(46). In a biochemical study investigating the roles of 
Pol II and Pol IV outside of TLS, both polymerases 
were shown to have access to the DNA replication fork, 
and to freely exchange with Pol III in a moving replisome 
(35). The suggestion has been made that the third poly-
merase of the E. coli replisome may act as a reserve poly-
merase to assist during replication fork stalling, and that </p>

<p>Pol II and Pol IV occupy the replisome to some extent 
during normal cellular growth (47). Thus, there exists the 
potential that specialized polymerases may encompass a 
role in replication at specific DNA structural elements. 
Our biochemical study (Figure 5) is similar to the 
previous analyses of replicative and Y-family DNA poly-
merase exchange (35,36,48), and extends this phenomenon 
to now include human Pol 4 in addition to replica-
tive polymerases of E. coli, T4 bacteriophage, and 
S. cerevisiae. Additionally, we are the first to provide 
evidence that Pol participates in an exchange reaction 
with Pol at an undamaged DNA sequence. We observed 
this exchange in the presence of a moving Pol 4 enzyme, 
similar to what was observed for the E. coli Pol IV/Pol III 
system. Recently, Pol was shown to be present in a 
complex with Pol in human cells, and participate in 
DNA repair synthesis associated with nucleotide excision 
repair (17). 
We presume that the differential accuracy of Pol and 
Pol 4 within mononucleotide and dinucleotide repeats 
(Figure 3) reflects structural differences between the 
enzymes that affect utilization of bulged (misaligned) 
primer templates. Structural information is available for 
Pols and in complex with DNA and dNTP substrates 
(49,50), with the caveat that none of the structures to date 
correspond to the full length, wild-type (and for Pol , 
multisubunit) enzymes we have used in this study. The 
unique N-clasp interaction of Pol locks the polymerase 
around the DNA substrate, creating a restrictive active 
site (50). We found that Pol is accurate during synthesis 
of dinucleotide repeats, but inaccurate for mononucleotide 
repeats. Possibly, the intimate Pol interactions with the 
nascent basepair and unpaired nucleotides 5 
0 to the 
templating base may disfavor utilization of bulges 
greater than one nucleotide. Alternatively, the N-clasp 
may cause Pol to have a novel interaction with the 
templating strand, such that the enzyme does not sense 
the entirety of the long tandem dinucleotide repeat 
during DNA synthesis, but instead only reads the 
template one base at a time. This model would account 
for the unique pattern of interruption mutations (primar-
ily, single base insertions or deletions) produced by Pol 
within the dinucleotide repeats. Pol , which primarily 
creates unit-based (two nucleotide) indels within the 
microsatellite, has a much larger protein footprint along 
the template strand through interactions of the N-terminal 
domain and the exonuclease domain (49). Such inter-
actions of Pol may provide stabilizing contacts for 
looped out/bulged bases in the template strand, analogous 
to the stabilizing protein-extrahelical base interactions 
observed in the Dbh4 and Dpo4 polymerase-strand mis-
alignment structures (51,52). 
Microsatellite allele length variation, or microsatellite 
instability, is associated with 10-15% of colorectal, endo-
metrial and gastric cancers, and has long been used as a 
diagnostic tool for Lynch Syndrome cancers. Alterations 
within microsatellites are generally accepted to be a con-
sequence of strand slippage events during DNA replica-
tion that are left uncorrected by a defective mismatch 
repair system. Tumors of this type are characterized as 
MSI-High, with mononucleotide microsatellite markers </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 4 1645 </p>

<p>proving to be more sensitive and predictive for Lynch 
Syndrome than dinucleotide markers (53). In addition, a 
group of sporadic colorectal carcinomas have been con-
sistently identified, termed MSI-Low. The underlying 
cause of the MSI-Low phenotype is controversial, and it 
is unknown whether MSI-Low represents random muta-
tions arising during clonal tumor cell evolution, or repre-
sents a mild mutator phenotype resulting from loss of a 
genome stability factor distinct from MMR (54-56). 
However, over-or under-expression of repair factors, 
such as alkyladenine DNA glycosylase (57) and 
methylguanine DNA methyltransferase (58), can contrib-
ute to an MSI-Low phenotype. Intriguingly, decreased Pol 
expression has been reported in colorectal tumors 
(59,60), relative to adjacent normal tissue. Results from 
our study and others may help to uncover unknown sus-
ceptibility factors in cancers exhibiting microsatellite 
instability. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Mr. Guruprasad Ananda (Penn State 
University, Center for Comparative Genomics and 
Bioinformatics) for providing us with the human 
genome microsatellite enumeration data. We thank Drs. 
Joann Sweasy and Laura Carrel, and members of the 
Eckert laboratory for critical discussions and reading of 
the manuscript. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>National Institutes of Health (grant numbers GM31973, 
ES014737 to M.Y.W.T.L., and CA100060, GM87472 to 
K.A.E.), and by generous contributions to the Gittlen 
Cancer Research Foundation of Penn State University. 
Funding for open access charge: National Institutes of 
Health (grant number GM87472 to K.A.E.) </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>







<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 4 1647 </p>

</text></tei>