<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3569919" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>There are a number of gas ionization sensors using carbon nanotubes as cathode or anode. Unfortunately, 
their applications are greatly limited by their multi-valued sensitivity, one output value corresponding to 
several measured concentration values. Here we describe a triple-electrode structure featuring two electric 
fields with opposite directions, which enable us to overcome the multi-valued sensitivity problem at 1 atm in 
a wide range of gas concentrations. We used a carbon nanotube array as the first electrode, and the two 
electric fields between the upper and the lower interelectrode gaps were designed to extract positive ions 
generated in the upper gap, hence significantly reduced positive ion bombardment on the nanotube 
electrode, which allowed us to maintain a high electric field near the nanotube tips, leading to a single-valued 
sensitivity and a long nanotube life. We have demonstrated detection of various gases and simultaneously 
monitoring temperature, and a potential for applications. </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>n 2001, carbon nanotube film was used to fabricate a double-electrode discharge gas sensor in our lab 1 , which 
triggered an explosion of research on carbon nanotube based gas sensors 1-13 . Unfortunately, these gas sensors 
exhibited multi-valued sensitivity of breakdown voltage or discharge current in response to targeted gas 
component at 1 atm total operating pressure, therefore their applications are limited because a single-valued 
sensitivity 14-20 to detection target is required for gas sensors. Additionally, the sensors in this configuration of 
double-electrode operated in self-sustaining discharge states, in which positive ions heavily bombard the cathode 
comprised of either nanotubes or a metal plate. In case of either a carbon nanotube cathode or a nanotube anode is 
used, current density can rise to a considerably large value around 100 A/m 2 , resulting in nanotube film damage 21 
and a short operating life 1-11 . 
A tripolar electrode configuration has been reported 7 , however, it still showed multi-valued sensitivity to 
acetone and ethanol because the second electrode collected most positive ions, resulting in current passing the 
first electrode of nanotube anode larger than that passing through the third electrode (sampling electrode) by ,2 
orders and also causing quick damage of the nanotube electrode. Here we report a triple-electrode structure with 
single-valued sensitivity and longer electrode life. The structure used a carbon nanotube array as the first 
electrode, featuring two electric fields with directions opposite each other, and is highly sensitive to various gases 
and capable of the detection directly from gas mixtures without separation in a wide range of the concentrations 
from 0 to 100%, as well as capable of monitoring temperature in a range of 17-120uC at the same time. In 
comparison to other existing sensors 22-28 , our design integrated gas and temperature detection into several 
tripolar electrode structures, featuring distinct interelectrode separations, capable of the operation at low power. 
Potentially, this could lead to a miniaturized gas ionization sensor with capability of multi-functional detections. </p>

<p>Results 
A triple-electrode structure is designed for gas detection at 1 atm, which is comprised of a carbon nanotube array 
cathode, an extracting electrode and a collecting electrode (Fig. 1a and Supplementary Fig. S1). The multiwalled 
nanotube (MWNT) film (Fig. 1b) was grown by thermal chemical vapor deposition 29,30 (TCVD) on one side of the 
Si cathode covered by a Ti/Ni/Au film. Nanotubes in the film are ,50 nm in diameter, and ,5-6 mm in length. 
The distance between nanotubes is ,50-100 nm. Ti/Ni/Au film was also sputtered on both sides of the extracting 
electrode (Fig. 1a, c) and the inner side of the collecting electrode for increasing initial discharge current. The 
sensor array was placed in a detection chamber with an electrical input and output interface, and air was pumped </p>

<p>SUBJECT AREAS: </p>

<p>ENVIRONMENTAL, 
HEALTH AND SAFETY 
ISSUES </p>

<p>ELECTRONIC DEVICES </p>

<p>APPLIED PHYSICS </p>

<p>NANOBIOTECHNOLOGY </p>

<p>out of the chamber to establish a low vacuum with a gas pressure of 
5 kPa. The gas to be detected was then introduced in a controlled 
fashion into the chamber until pressure is increased to 1 atm. The 
sensor displays very fast response within around the order of 10 26 s 31 
in comparison to other sensors 2,31,32 due to its non-self-sustaining 
discharge state. 
During operation, suitable d.c. voltages of U e and U c are applied 
between the cathode and the extracting electrode, and between the 
cathode and the collecting electrode (Fig. 1c), respectively. U e is 
higher than U c , which generates two electric fields E 1 and E 2 in 
reversed field direction. The field near the nanotube tips is much 
higher than that in the other region. Consequently, ionization takes 
place near the tips in around 1 mm range (reference). Through col-
lision and diffusion, significant amount of positive ions overcome the 
weak field near the extracting electrode and move into the region 
between the extracting and the collecting electrodes, then they are 
accelerated by E 2 towards the collecting electrode (Fig. 1d and 
Supplementary Fig. S2A). Therefore bombardment of the positive 
ions on nanotubes is considerably reduced, which hindered occur-
rence of self-sustaining discharge, resulting in a significantly longer 
life-span of nanotube electrode, and consequently a single-valued 
sensitivity. 
The structure enables a non-self-sustaining discharge near the 
nanotube tips at lower voltage U e of less than 150 V. Non-self-sus-
taining discharge current I is mainly determined by gas partial pres-
sure, electrode separation and gas temperature; and the gas partial </p>

<p>pressure is proportional to gas concentration. Therefore, at a given 
electrode separation, I is direct measurements of gas concentration 
and temperature. We found that distances between electrodes had a 
distinct effect on the detection. By varying the distances between 
electrodes, we were able to identify different gas species in a gas 
mixture without component separation and measure temperature 
at the same time. Single-valued sensitivity to several gases and mix-
tures were obtained under electric field above a critical value by 
control of electrode separation and applied voltages on electrodes. 
Single-valued sensitivity to gas temperature was also observed. We 
also found that temperature has a great effect on gas detection sens-
itivity, the higher gas temperature, the higher sensitivity. </p>

<p>Discussion 
For all our tests, gases probed were mixed with N 2 . The gases with 
first ionization energies higher than 10.3 eV are harder to ionize than 
nitrogen 31 , but they affect energy and charge transformation 33 during 
gas discharge in a mixture with N 2 . Since the first ionization energies 
of the gases probed are greater than 10.3 eV, the ionization process 
will depend mainly on the ionization of N 2 from its two metastable 
states, N 2 (A 3 P </p>

<p>u </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>) and N 2 (a 91 P </p>

<p>u </p>

<p>2 ) with lower excitation ener-
gies 33-37 of ,6.2 and ,8.4 eV, respectively. The first ionization coef-
ficient 32 of N 2 , a, reflects ionization ability of gas from collision with 
electrons, and is determined by the applied electric field E and the 
partial pressure P of N 2 (Supplementary Fig. S3), </p>

<p>a~Ape {BP=E 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>where A and B are constants related to gas species and temperature. 
When the electric field rises up to a critical value, a increases with 
increasing N 2 partial pressure from 0 to 1 atm, displaying single-
valued a2P curves. As collecting ionic current I c is a part of total 
discharge current I, it increases with a in a non-self-sustaining dis-
charge state 32 , 
I c ~I 0 e ad 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>where I 0 is initial current, d is electrode separation between nanotube 
cathode and extracting electrode. When the concentration of gas 
probed is increased in a gas mixture with N 2 , it reduces N 2 concen-
tration at the same time, therefore single-valued decrease of collect-
ing current with increasing concentration of the gas probed can be 
observed at given electric field up to a critical value. 
Gas ionization properties of the triple-electrode structure were 
tested for new insights of the mechanism of the detection. First, we 
measured the current I e flowing through the nanotube cathode in 
C 2 H 2 at 80 V U e with 200 mm electrode separations (between cath-
ode and extracting electrode and between extracting electrode and 
collecting electrode, in general we kept two separations the same). 
We found that I e 5 ,2I c (Supplementary Fig. S4). Current density j e 
passing the nanotubes can be calculated by dividing I e with the cross-
sectional area of all nanotubes. To understand the effect of gas con-
centration and electric field on gas conductivity, we tested NO in a 
concentration range of 0-690 ppm at various extracting voltages of 
U e and 120 mm electrode separations. Gas conductivity of NO, cal-
culated by dividing j e with the average electric field between the 
cathode and the extracting electrode 38 , was observed that it remained 
constant with rising average electric field and monotonically de-
creased with increasing NO concentration (Supplementary Fig. 
S5A). The results indicate a single-valued sensitivity mechanism of 
our structure for NO detection. Furthermore we evaluate the effect of 
gas temperature and electric field on gas ionization. Current density 
j e was found exponentially dependent on gas temperature and line-
arly dependent on average electric field in pure N 2 at 200 mm separa-
tions (Supplementary Fig. S6A, C), which follows the field-assisted 
thermal emission law 38 . It showed a potential of the structure for 
detecting gas temperature. To study the effect of gas concentration 
on electron emission ability of carbon nanotubes which greatly </p>

<p>Figure 1 | The triple-electrode sensor device. (a) Exploded view of triple-</p>

<p>electrode showing MWNT film used as the cathode. (b) SEM micrograph 
of a TCVD-grown, vertically aligned MWNT film. (c) Schematic diagram 
of the test system. U e is higher than U c , which offers two electric fields E 1 
and E 2 in reversed field direction. (d) Calculated potential schematic and 
its effect on ion diffusion and migration. Positive ions, generated by 
discharge (a process) between the cathode and the extracting electrode, 
diffuse to the extracting electrode and then move to the collecting electrode 
due to acceleration by the electric field E 2 , and thereby form the positive 
ionic current I c . </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1267 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01267 </p>

<p>
contributed to gas discharge current, we conducted tests using two 
sensors with 100 mm and 120 mm electrode separations at 80 V U e 
with NO concentrations from 0 to 700 ppm and at gas temperatures 
from 30 to 80uC (Supplementary Fig. S7A, B). Schottky barrier w was 
calculated according to Eq. 3. We observed that slightly barrier 
increasing with NO concentration (Supplementary Fig. S7C, D) 
could induce large change of collecting current. The result showed 
the effect of gas concentration on emission ability of nanotubes and 
also sensing potential of our structure. </p>

<p>j Schottky ~A : T 2 : exp {w=K : T 
ð 
Þ 
ð 3Þ </p>

<p>where A denotes the Richardson constant, A 5 1.20173 3 
10 6 A?m 22 ?K 22 , K denotes the Boltzmann constant, K 5 1.38065 
3 10 223 J?K 21 , and w denotes the Schottky barrier. In contrast, dou-
ble-electrode device displayed ruleless change of conductivity with 
both average electric field and NO concentration (Supplementary 
Fig. S5B), current density was also higher and up to 10 2 A/m 2 order 
(Supplementary Fig. S6D). This arises from the secondary electron 
emission induced by heavy bombardment of the positive ions on the 
nanotube cathode. Higher current density resulted in shorter life-
span of nanotubes and multi-valued sensitivity of double-electrode 
structure 2-11 . 
To study single-valued sensitivity, we chose hydrogen (H 2 ) as the 
test gas, and controlled electric field strength by varying voltage and 
distance between electrodes. To find the critical field needed for 
single-valued sensitivity, we kept the distances between the cathode 
and the extracting electrode, and between the extracting and the 
colleting electrodes constant at 200 mm, fixed U c constant at 10 V 
(0 V at the cathode and 10 V at the collecting electrode), changed U e 
from 40 to 80 V, and carried out hydrogen detection at 1 atm cham-
ber pressure. When U e increased, current characteristics changed 
from non-monotonic to monotonic at 80 V (Fig. 2a). Therefore, 
for H 2 , the threshold value of U e was found to be around 80 V at 
200 mm separations. We also found threshold voltages and electrode 
separations to obtain single-valued sensitivities for other gases and 
mixtures, including C 2 H 2 , O 2 , C 2 H 4 , SO 2 , SO 2 /NO and H 2 /C 2 H 2 / 
C 2 H 4 mixtures. 
Single-valued sensitivities were found to be distinct to different 
gases. This is because different gases have distinct physical and chem-
ical properties. A sensor with 200 mm electrode separations exhibited 
the sensitivities of 28 pA/ppm to 151 ppm (1 ppm 5 1 mL/L) for 
H 2 (Fig. 2a), and of 2533 pA/ppm to 1 ppm for C 2 H 2 (Fig. 2b) at 
80 V of U e . Fig. 2b also shows current vs. concentration change for 
O 2 . And the sensitivity was 2327 pA/10000 ppm (20.03 pA/ppm) 
to 6% O 2 within a wide range of concentration from 0 to 100% (at </p>

<p>1 atm chamber pressure). Distinct sensitivities were also found for 
gases of C 2 H 4 , NO, NO 2 , and SO 2 (Supplementary Fig. S8). Fig. 2c 
displays two adjacent sensitivity curves for C 2 H 2 , exhibiting our 
finding on the reproducible characteristic of the sensors in C 2 H 2 . 
Based on these results, we anticipated that our sensor might have 
the potential to detect a gas component in a mixture. 
To evaluate the potential of our sensor for detecting gas com-
ponents in a gas mixture, we tested the effect of the electrode 
distance on sensitivity of the sensors to mixed gases at 150 V of 
U e (Fig. 3a). For these tests, we also kept the distances between the 
cathode and the extracting electrode and between the extracting 
and the collecting electrodes the same. For a sensor with 75 mm 
electrode separations, we measured output currents larger than 
12 nA and observed the largest change of 4.8 nA corresponding 
to four gas mixtures; but for a sensor with 120 mm separations, the 
output currents were lower than 4.2 nA with a change of 1.4 nA 
corresponding to the same gas mixtures, displaying smaller sens-
itivity. Therefore, we can choose different electrode separations 
and make the sensors having various distinct sensitivities to dif-
ferent gas components, exploiting identification and detection of 
gas component in a mixture. 
We chose two electrode separations for fabricating two sensors 
(Fig. 3b), and conducted tests for detecting two components of SO 2 
and NO in a mixture with N 2 without component separation. One 
sensor with 100 mm separations detected NO in a 0-1128 ppm 
range, and the other with 150 mm separations detected SO 2 in a 0-
738 ppm range. Collecting currents as single-valued functions of 
two-component concentrations were measured when U e was 
increased to 100 V (Fig. 3c, d). Fig. 3c shows that the collecting 
current of the NO sensor decreased from 0.71 to 0.47 nA when 
maintaining constant NO concentration and increasing SO 2 concen-
tration from 141 to 738 ppm, showing interference from SO 2 com-
ponent. Similarly, Fig. 3d shows interference from NO component to 
the SO 2 detection. 
Equations (1) and (2) show that collecting current I c is an expo-
nential function of electrode separation d and component partial 
pressure 32 . When detection chamber volume is given, partial pres-
sure is proportional to component concentration. Therefore the col-
lecting current I c in Fig. 3c and d is determined mainly by three 
factors of electrode separation, NO concentration Q NO and SO 2 con-
centration Q SO2 , which can be described as follows: </p>

<p>I 1 ~a 0 f 0 d 1 
ð Þza 1 f 1 Q NO 
ð 
Þza 2 f 2 Q SO2 
ð 
Þ 
ð4Þ </p>

<p>I 2 ~b 0 g 0 d 2 
ð Þzb 1 g 1 Q NO 
ð 
Þzb 2 g 2 Q SO2 
ð 
Þ 
ð5Þ </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Effect of gas concentration on positive ionic current. (a) Single-valued decrease of positive ionic current namely collecting current with </p>

<p>increasing H 2 concentration at 200 mm separations and 80 V of U e (black). Multi-valued sensitivities to hydrogen at 200 mm separations with U e as 40 V 
(purple) and 60 V (red), respectively. (b) Single-valued decrease of collecting current with increasing C 2 H 2 concentration at 200 mm separations and 
80 V of U e (black). Single-valued decrease of collecting current with increasing O 2 concentration at 90 V of U e (red), at 200 mm separation between the 
cathode and the extracting electrode and 100 mm separation between the extracting and the collecting electrodes. (c) Sensitivity curves Nos. 1 and 2 of 
200 mm separation sensors to C 2 H 2 at 80 V of U e , exhibiting our finding on the reproducible single-valued characteristic of the sensors in C 2 H 2 . </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1267 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01267 </p>

<p>
where d 1 5 100 mm, d 2 5 150 mm, I 1 and I 2 are collecting current of 
the 100 mm and 150 mm separation sensors, respectively. The func-
tions of f 0 , f 1 and f 2 in Eq. (4) describe the effect of d 1 , Q NO and Q SO2 
on I 1 , respectively; g 0 , g 1 and g 2 in Eq. (5) describe the effect of d 2 , Q NO 
and Q SO2 on I 2 , respectively. a 0 , a 1 , and a 2 are the coefficients of f 0 , 
f 1 and f 2 , respectively; b 0 , b 1 and b 2 are the coefficients of g 0 , g 1 and g 2 , 
respectively. From the equations (4) and (5), values of Q NO and Q SO2 
can be solved. Therefore, by careful study of gas component inter-
action mechanism with electrodes and design of the sensor config-
uration, sensors capable for multi-component detection may be 
designed, and concentrations of the two components could be 
obtained through detection followed by data processing according 
to the equations (4) and (5). Fig. 4 shows that this technique is also 
valid for direct detection of H 2 , C 2 H 2 , and C 2 H 4 in a mixture by using 
three sensors with different electrode separations (Fig. 4). To C 2 H 2 , 
detection was sensitive down to 1 ppm. The results suggested that the 
sensor array with different electrode separations has potential for use 
in trace gas and gas component detections. 
Two sensors with different electrode separations were fabricated 
to simultaneously detect 0-700 ppm NO and gas temperature at 
80 V of U e , respectively (Fig. 5a, b and Supplementary Fig. S7A, 
B). Tests were conducted while NO concentration increased from 
0 to 700 ppm at various given temperature values in a range of 30-
80uC. The sensor with 100 mm electrode separation detected NO in a 
range of 0-700 ppm, and exhibits the highest sensitivity of 223 pA/ 
ppm to 335 ppm NO (Supplementary Table S1). The other sensor 
with 120 mm separation detected gas temperature in a range of 30-
80uC, and exhibits the highest sensitivity of 1 nA/uC to 70uC 
(Supplementary Table S2). Fig. 5a and b also show the effect of gas 
temperature on NO detection and that of NO concentration on 
temperature detection, respectively. The highest cross sensitivity of </p>

<p>the NO sensor to temperature is 2.0 3 10 22 /uC (Supplementary 
Table S1), two orders higher than that of the temperature sensor to 
NO, 23.1 3 10 24 ppm 21 (Supplementary Table S2), indicating a 
stronger effect of temperature on NO detection than that of NO on 
temperature detection. 
Analysis on simultaneously detecting NO and gas temperature 
follows: Since collecting current I c is an exponential function of 
electrode separation d, component partial pressure P, gas temper-
ature T and electric field intensity E (Eqs. (1) and (2)), we can obtain 
an equation for I c in dependent of d, Q and T at given voltages applied 
on three electrodes. In this case, the collecting current I c is deter-
mined by the three factors of electrode separation d, NO concentra-
tion Q NO and gas temperature T, which can be described as follows: 
I 1 ~a 0 f 0 d 1 
ð Þza 1 f 1 Q NO 
ð 
Þza 2 f 2 T 
ð Þ 
ð6Þ </p>

<p>I 2 ~b 0 g 0 d 2 
ð Þzb 1 g 1 Q NO 
ð 
Þzb 2 g 2 T 
ð Þ 
ð7Þ </p>

<p>where d 1 5 100 mm, d 2 5 120 mm, I 1 and I 2 are collecting current of 
the sensors with 100 mm and 120 mm electrode separation, respect-
ively. The functions of f 0 , f 1 and f 2 in Eq. (6) is dependent of d 1 , Q NO 
and T, respectively; g 0 , g 1 and g 2 in Eq. (7) is dependent of d 2 , Q NO and 
T, respectively. a 0 , a 1 , and a 2 in Eq. (6) are the coefficients of f 0 , f 1 and 
f 2 , respectively; b 0 , b 1 , and b 2 in Eq. (7) are the coefficients of g 0 , g 1 and 
g 2 , respectively. These coefficients can be determined experimentally 
(Fig. 5a, b and Supplementary Fig. S7A, B). The values of Q NO and T 
can be obtained by solving Eqs. (6) and (7). Similarly, a proper data 
processing of the data shown on Fig. 5a and b could be conducted, 
resulting in detection of NO concentration and gas temperature at 
the same time. Moreover, three sensors with various distinct elec-
trode separations were fabricated and used to simultaneously detect a 
SO 2 -NO mixture and gas temperature (Fig. 6). The sensor with a </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Effect of electrode separation on ionic current and detection of gas mixture. (a) Various separations are given as 75 mm, 80 mm, 100 mm and </p>

<p>120 mm, respectively. Case 1 denotes a concentration in gas mixture of SO 2 (280 ppm)/NO (1115 ppm)/NO 2 (195 ppm), 2 of SO 2 (736 ppm)/NO 
(1115 ppm)/NO 2 (195 ppm), 3 of SO 2 (280 ppm)/NO (296 ppm)/NO 2 (218 ppm), and 4 of SO 2 (280 ppm)/NO (818 ppm)/NO 2 (218 ppm). Four 
cases are all mixed with 208798 ppm O 2 in N 2 ambient with 150 V U e . It shows that various separations enable different collecting currents. (b) Two 
sensors with different separations constitute a sensor array for detecting two components of SO 2 and NO in a mixture at 100 V U e , with one sensor with 
100 mm separations for NO detection and the other with 150 mm separations for SO 2 detection. (c) Collecting current of the NO sensor decreases with 
increasing NO concentration at different constant SO 2 concentrations at 100 mm separations, showing interference from SO 2 component. (d) Collecting 
current of the SO 2 sensor decreases with increasing SO 2 concentration at different constant NO concentrations at 150 mm separations, showing 
interference from NO component to SO 2 detection. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1267 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01267 </p>

<p>
100 mm electrode separation showed a highest sensitivity of 
27.7 nA/ppm to 298 ppm NO (Supplementary Table S3), the sensor 
with a 75 mm electrode separation showed a highest sensitivity of 
23.8 nA/ppm to 280 ppm SO 2 (Supplemen-
tary Table S4), and the sensor with a 120 mm electrode separation 
showed a highest sensitivity of 83.2 nA/uC to 120uC (Supplementary 
Table S5). The highest cross sensitivity to temperature is one order 
higher than that to NO and SO 2 (Supplementary Tables S3-5), 
respectively, indicating a greater effect of temperature on NO and 
SO 2 detection than that of NO or SO 2 concentration on temperature 
detection. A proper data processing of the data presented in Fig. 6 
could also be conducted and could simultaneously detect the two 
components and gas temperature. Sensitivity of the sensor to gas 
temperature in pure N 2 was also tested (Fig. 6d), and displayed a 
highest sensitivity value of 14.9 mA/uC to 100uC (Supplementary 
Table S6), considerably higher than that to gas concentration by 
,three orders and higher than that of existing temperature measure-
ment technology by ,one order 26 . The results further suggested that 
our sensor with distinct gaps can work as gas sensor and temperature 
sensor at the same time, leading to the development of integrated 
sensing devices with capability for temperature monitoring and con-
centration detection at the same time. Additionally, our sensor is 
superior to the existing temperature measurement technology 26-28 . 
Our study overcame a key barrier of double-electrode and tripolar 
electrode ionic gas sensors, that is multi-valued sensitivity 2-11 to gas 
concentration at 1 atm operating pressure. Through design of the 
triple-electrode gas sensor and careful control of the distances from 
the extracting electrode to the cathode and the collecting electrode as </p>

<p>Figure 4 | (a) Detection of a H 2 /C 2 H 2 /C 2 H 4 mixture by using three sensors at 70uC, 150 V U e and 1 V U c . (b) the first sensor with 75 mm separations for </p>

<p>C 2 H 2 test, showing detection ability of the sensor down to 1 ppm trace gas, (c) the second with 100 mm separations for H 2 test and (d) the third with 
120 mm separations for C 2 H 4 test. The sensitivities of the three sensors are obviously different, and collecting current monotonically decreases with 
increasing H 2 , C 2 H 2 and C 2 H 4 concentrations in the preset concentration ranges. </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Simultaneous detection of NO and gas temperature. </p>

<p>(a) Collecting current I c dependence on NO concentration at 60uC, 70uC, 
and 80uC, respectively, showing a greater effect of gas temperature T on 
NO detection, at 100 mm electrode separations and 80 V U e . (b) Collecting 
current I c dependence on gas temperature T at 119 mL/L, 335 mL/L, and 
700 mL/L of NO, respectively, showing a slight effect of NO on gas 
temperature detection, at 120 mm electrode separations and 80 V U e . </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1267 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01267 </p>

<p>
well as the field direction and the voltages between them, we were 
able to significantly reduce ion bombardment on the carbon nano-
tube cathode, hence increase field strength at lower voltage near the 
tips without quick tip damaging, which leads to a single-valued sens-
itivity in a wide range. We have demonstrated multi-gas detection as 
well as simultaneously gas and temperature detection capability, and 
that our design is superior to existing commercial gas and temper-
ature sensors 22-28 . With further development, we believe this work 
could lead to miniaturized, multi-functional sensing devices. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Sensor fabrication. The triple-electrode sensor using carbon nanotube array was 
fabricated by using Microelectro Mechanical Systems (MEMS) technology. The silicon 
slices (500 mm thick, 27 mm in length, 8 mm in width) were cut as the substrates of 
cathode, extracting electrode and collecting electrode, respectively. They were 
processed through photolithography and dry etching, resulting in the cathode with 
two round holes, the extracting electrode with one round hole, and the collecting 
electrode with a 200 mm deep square blind hole. 50 nm thick Ti film, 400 nm thick Ni 
film and 125 nm thick Au film were deposited in sequence by magnetron sputtering 
on both sides of extracting electrode (Fig. 1a, c) and the inner side of cathode and 
collecting electrode. Then the three electrodes were rapidly annealed (Supplementary 
Fig. S1A-C) in a low vacuum of ,3.0 Pa at 450uC for 50 seconds to alloy the Ti/Ni/ 
Au film. On the annealed Ti/Ni/Au film of cathode, vertically aligned multiwalled 
nanotube (MWNT) array (Supplementary Fig. S1D) was grown by thermal chemical 
vapor deposition (TCVD) method. Polyester film was cut as the insulating strips 
between electrodes with 2-mm width and various given thickness which corresponds 
to various electrode separation of the device. In the final step golden wires were 
bonded on the edge of electrodes and the three electrodes were bonded together with 
insulating glue, and finally, the sensor device (Supplementary Fig. S1E) was fabricated. </p>

<p>Gas mixture preparation and temperature control system. An automatic gas 
mixing system was consisted of an operation platform based on a computer, a gas </p>

<p>mixing chamber, and a gas and temperature detection chamber. There were five gas 
cylinders containing high purity gas with concentration accuracy of 2%. One of them 
supplied the environment gas N 2 and the others supplied the measured gas. Five mass 
flow controllers (MFC, Line Tech M3030V with 1% accuracy) were used to 
continuously regulate gas flux for preparing mixed gas concentrations. The full scales 
of the five MFCs were two with 50 mL/min, one with 100 mL/min, one with 500 mL/ 
min and one with 1000 mL/min. 2.5% accuracy of the gas concentration in two/three/ 
four component mixtures was obtained through calculation on the basis of 1% 
accuracy of MFC and 2% accuracy of source gas. After well mixed in a gas mixing 
chamber, gas mixture flowed into a sealable stainless steel detection chamber with a 
pressure meter to detect gas pressure. A temperature control device was used to 
control gas temperature and the temperature can be increased to the set value within 
1 minute. A vacuum pump was equipped for pumping gas out of the detection 
chamber and quick gas exchange. </p>

<p>Electrical test system. A PXI bus test system was constructed to provide high stable 
powers for the sensors and to precisely measure the collecting currents from pA to nA. 
The test system based on PXI bus was consisted of a 14-Slot Chassis (NI PXI-1044), a 
controller module (NI PXI-ExpressCard8360), five digital multimeter modules (NI 
PXI-4071), and three power modules (NI PXI-4132). The three power modules 
provided voltages needed for the electrodes (Fig. 1c). Two of the power modules were 
connected in series to provide 0-150 V voltage for extracting electrodes of the 
sensors, and the other power module provided 0-100 V voltage for collecting 
electrodes. The digital multimeter modules with shielded cables are capable of 
acquiring the collecting currents from pA to nA for five sensors at the same time. All 
acquired data were recorded to a computer through a <rs type="software">LabVIEW</rs> program linked to 
MXI interface. </p>

<p>Sensor measurements. The sensor array was placed in a detection chamber and wires 
bonded to electrodes were extended outside through an interface. Sensors with 
distinct gaps in the array simultaneously detected different physical parameters such 
as concentration of different gas species and gas temperature. Measurements were 
conducted with increasing gas concentration in a preset range at various temperatures 
from 17 to 120uC. Before the measurements, temperature was controlled at a set value, </p>

<p>Figure 6 | Simultaneous detection of a NO2SO 2 mixture and gas temperature by using three sensors at 150 V U e and 10 V U c , and temperature </p>

<p>sensitivity test. (a) The first sensor with 75 mm separations for SO 2 test, (b) the second with 100 mm separations for NO test and (c) the third with 120 mm 
separations for gas temperature test. The sensitivities of the three sensors are distinctly different. Collecting currents I 1 and I 2 of the sensors in (a) and (b) 
monotonically decrease with increasing SO 2 and NO concentration, respectively; nevertheless I 3 in (c) increases with gas temperature in the preset range, 
showing a considerably higher sensitivity of the sensor to gas temperature. (d) Temperature sensitivity of our sensor at 200 mm separation between the 
cathode and the extracting electrode, 220 mm separation between the extracting and the collecting electrodes, and at 100 V U e in pure N 2 . </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1267 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01267 </p>

<p>
and then air was pumped out of the chamber to establish a low vacuum with a gas 
pressure of 5 kPa, later the measured gases and the environment gas N 2 were 
introduced in a controlled fashion until chamber pressure is increased to 1 atm. One 
minute after voltages were applied on three electrodes, collecting currents were 
measured and recorded to the computer through the MXI interface at various gas 
concentration and temperature conditions. </p>



<p>u </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>) found to be responsible for 
nitrogen oxides conversion in nonthermal nitrogen plasma. Ind. Eng. Chem. Res. 
43, 5077-5088 (2004). 
34. Fresnet, F. et al. Influence of water on NO removal by pulsed discharge in N 2 / 
H 2 O/NO mixtures. Plasma Sources Sci. Technol. 11, 152-160 (2002). 
35. Guerra, V., Sa, P. A. &amp; Loureiro, J. Role played by the N 2 (A 3 P </p>

<p>u </p>

<p>1 ) metastable in 
stationary N 2 and N 2 -O 2 discharges. J. Phys. D: Appl. Phys. 34, 1745-1755 (2001). 
36. Brunet, H. &amp; Rocca, S. J. Model for a glow discharge in flowing nitrogen. J. Appl. 
Phys. 57, 1574-1581 (1985). 
37. Ono, R., Tobaru, C., Teramoto, Y. &amp; Oda, T. Observation of N 2 (A 3 P </p>

<p>u </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>) 
metastable in pulsed positive corona discharge using laser-induced fluorescence. 
Proc. IEEE Ind. Appl. Soc. Annu. Meeting CANADA, 434-437 (2008). 
38. Kasap, S. O. Principles of Electronic Materials and Devices. 2nd edn, (McGraw-
Hill, Boston, 2002). </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank X. H. Song, W. H. Jiang, J. X. Cao, J. Song, S. Yang and J. Wang for contributions 
to the experiments. Y.Z. was supported by grants from the National Science Foundation of 
China (50877056), the 863 plan of China (2009AA04Z131), the Interdiscipline Project of 
Xi9an Jiaotong University (2009xjtujc31) and the Independent Research project 
(EIPE11117) from the State Key Lab of Electrical Institute and Power Equipment of Xi'an 
Jiaotong University. S.T.L. was supported by the National Science Foundation for 
Outstanding Youth of China (50625721), and the 973 Program of China (2011CB209404). </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>Y.Z. designed the project, supervised the experiments and wrote the manuscript. S.T.L. 
performed the ionization mechanism analysis and modified the manuscript. J.Y.Z. did 
experiments on gas and mixture sensitivity. Z.G.P. performed temperature effect 
experiment. D.M.M. did current dependence experiment on electric field. J.Y.Z., Z.G.P. and 
D.M.M. analyzed the data. X.L. grew nanotube films. X.P.S. and J.H.L. supervised the 
experiments. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>License: This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this 
license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Zhang, Y. et al. High-performance gas sensors with temperature 
measurement. Sci. Rep. 3, 1267; DOI:10.1038/srep01267 (2013). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1267 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01267 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>