<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3020393" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>56 </p>

<p>I 
In nt te er rn na at ti io on na al l J 
Jo ou ur rn na al l o 
of f M 
Me ed di ic ca al l S 
Sc ci ie en nc ce es s </p>

<p>2011; 8(1):56-67 
Abstract </p>

<p>To investigate the role of ROS in the helicobacter pylori (Hp) induced mtDNA mutations, 
AGS cells were treated by extracts of Hp11638 or Hp11638M. The ROS levels, cytochrome 
C reductions, and intracellular ATP levels were measured. The coding region and the D-Loop 
region were amplified and sequenced. Results showed the ROS levels, cytochrome C re-
duction and mtDNA mutations were markedly increased and cell viability decreased after 
treatment with both Hp extracts, and 616 mutations were detected in D-Loop region and 3 
heteroplasmic point mutations in the Cytb gene. No mutations were found in the coding 
region. The mutation rates of mtDNA D-Loop region were positively correlated with the 
ROS levels and negatively to the ATP levels. </p>

<p>Helicobacter pylori (Hp) are Gram-negative mi-
croaerophilic bacteria. Hp infection represents a key 
factor in the etiology of various gastrointestinal dis-
eases, ranging from chronic active gastritis without 
clinical symptoms to peptic ulceration, gastric ade-
nocarcinoma, and gastric mucosa-associated lym-
phoid tissue lymphoma. H. pylori-positive patients 
have a 10 to 20% lifetime risk of developing ulcer 
disease and a 1 to 2% risk of developing distal gastric 
cancer [1]. The cytotoxin-associated gene A (CagA) 
protein and vacuolating cytotoxin (VacA) protein are 
the main virulence factors of Hp and closely relevant 
with the occurrence of gastric ulcer and carcinoma [2]. 
Most H. pylori strains secrete VacA into the extracel-
lular space. After exposure of VacA to acidic or basic </p>

<p>pH, re-oligomerized VacA (mainly 6 monomeric 
units) at neutral pH is more toxic [3]. CagA (120-145 
kDa protein) is a highly anti-genic protein that is as-
sociated with a prominent inflammatory response. It 
has a pathogenic effect on gastric and duodenal mu-
cosa leading to the development of peptic ulcers [4]. 
Studies have shown that Hp can induce reactive 
oxygen species (ROS) production and programmed 
cell death in human gastric epithelial cells [5,6]. ROS 
are produced as a normal product of cellular meta-
bolism and include superoxide anion (O 2 •ˉ), hydro-
gen peroxide (H 2 O 2 ), hydroxyl radical (HO•), nitric 
oxide (NO•), etc. They are highly reactive due to the 
presence of unpaired valence shell electrons and can 
diffuse only an extremely short distance before they </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2011, 8 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>dissipate. Elevated levels of ROS have been impli-
cated in cellular physiological and pathological 
processes such as cell proliferation, apoptosis, diffe-
rentiation, carcinogenesis, etc [7]. Mitochondria are 
the centre of energy metabolism in the cell and a ma-
jor source of ROS. The proportion of oxygen con-
verted into O 2 •ˉaccounts for about 1-2 % of the overall 
oxygen consumption [8]. Mitochondrial DNA 
(mtDNA) is an extranuclear genetic material. mtDNA 
is particularly susceptible to ROS generated by the 
respiratory chain due to its close proximity and lack of 
protective histones, and inefficient DNA repair sys-
tems [9]. 
Evidence shows Hp VacA can activate the 
p38/activating transcription factor 2-mediated sig-
naling pathway resulting in decrease in mitochondrial 
membrane potential [10] and can induce suppression 
of energy metabolism followed by mitochondrial 
damage, leading to impairment of the cell cycle in 
gastric epithelial cells [11]. Recent studies suggest Hp 
can increase the mtDNA mutation in AGS cells and 
mtDNA mutations have been found in Hp infected 
gastric ulcer and carcinoma tissues [12,13]. However, 
the role of ROS in the Hp induced mtDNA mutations 
is still unknown and the impacts of VacA and CagA 
on the ROS production and mtDNA mutations are 
poorly understood. 
To investigate the ROS production and mtDNA 
mutations in the Hp infected cells, AGS cells were 
stimulated by the extract of NCTC Hp11638 (CagA+, 
VacA+) or the mutant Hp11638M (CagA+, VacA-). 
The relationships between ROS and mtDNA muta-
tions as well as mutations in D-loop were evaluated. 
Our results demonstrated the ROS levels and the 
amount of mtDNA mutations in cells treated by the 
extract of Hp11638 were markedly higher than those 
in cells treated by Hp11638 mutant strain. Several 
mutations in D-Loop region were also detected, but 
Cox-I, Cox-II, Cox-III, ATPase6 and ATPase8 genes 
had no mutations. Furthermore, 3 heteroplasmic point 
mutations were identified in Cytb gene and Hp in-
duced mutations in D-Loop region were closely re-
lated to the bacterial virulence and the endogenous 
ROS level. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Cells and Hp Strains </p>

<p>AGS cells were purchased from Shanghai Insti-
tute of Cell. NCTC Hp 11638, NCTC Hp11638M and 
E.coli ATCC 25922 were kindly provided by the De-
partment of Medical Microbiology and Parasitology, 
Shanghai Jiaotong University School of Medicine. </p>

<p>Reagents </p>

<p>F12 culture medium (Hangzhou Jino Biology 
Co., Ltd. China), fetal bovine serum (FBS), ampicillin, 
penicillin 
and 
streptomycin 
(Shanghai 
Bio-engineering Co., Ltd. China), brain heart infusion 
agar and liquid medium (OXOID Co., Ltd. UK), LB 
medium (Beijing Solarbio Co., Ltd. China), gas mix-
ture (5% O 2 , 85% N 2 , 10% CO 2 ) (Shanghai Shenkai Gas 
Co., Ltd. China), anti-CagA and anti-VacA polyclonal 
antibodies (Santa Cruz, USA), AP conjugated sec-
ondary antibody, CellTiter-Glo luminescent cell via-
bility assay kit (Cat.#G7570, Promega Co. USA), Di-
hydrorhdamine-123 (DHR-123) and oxidized cytoch-
rome c (Sigma, USA) and AGS mtDNA extraction kit 
GenMed Scientifics Co., Ltd USA) were used in the 
present study. </p>

<p>Cells and Hp Culture </p>

<p>AGS cells were grown in the F12 culture me-
dium containing 10% FBS, 100 U/ml penicillin and 
100 µg/ml streptomycin in a humidified atmosphere 
of 5% CO 2 and 95% air at 37°C. 
Hp was grown in the brain heart infusion agar 
containing 7% defibered sheep blood and Hp selective 
antibiotic V.C.A. for 72 h. Colonies were identified by 
Gram-stained smear and biochemical reactions, and 
the washed with 5 ml of brain heart infusion liquid 
medium. The eluate was incubated with brain heart 
infusion liquid medium containing 10% FBS and Hp 
selector. The bacteria were cultivated at 37°C for 48 h 
under a microaerophilic condition (5% O 2 , 85% N 2 , 
10% CO 2 ) with continuous shaking. 
E. coli were maintained in the LB liquid medium 
(containing 100 µg/ml ampicillin) at 37°C for 12 h 
with continuous shaking. </p>

<p>Preparation of Hp and E.coli extract </p>

<p>The Hp and E. coli were harvested, centrifuged 
at 12000 g for 10 min, washed 3 times with PBS, and 
then re-suspended in 5 ml of sterile double-distilled 
water. The suspension was vigorously oscillated for 
10 min and kept at room temperature overnight. On 
the next day, the supernatant was obtained and vi-
gorously oscillated for 10 min followed by centrifu-
gation at 12000 g for 10 min. The supernatant was 
collected and the sediment was re-suspended in 5 ml 
of sterile double-distilled water, and kept on the ice 
followed by sonication 3 times (30 sec per time with 
an interval of 45 sec). Then, centrifugation was per-
formed at 12000 g for 10 min and the supernatant was 
collected. All the supernatants were finally mixed and 
freeze-dried. The dry powder was dissolved in 1 ml of 
sterile double-distilled water and stored at -40℃ for 
use. Immediately before use, the solution was centri-</p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2011, 8 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>fuged at 18000 g for 10 min and the supernatant was 
filtered through a 0.22 μm filter to remove bacteria 
and macromolecular complex (membranes containing 
lipopolysaccharide and flagella) [14]. The protein 
concentration was determined with a DNA/Protein 
Analyzer (Beckman Du 800). The protein concentra-
tion in the Hp11638 extract, Hp11638M extract and 
E.coli ATCC25922 extract was 20 mg/ml, 30 mg/ml 
and 28 mg/ml, respectively. Then, the protein con-
centrations of Hp11638M extract and E. coli extract 
were adjusted to 20 mg/ml. </p>

<p>Detection of CagA and VacA protein using 
SDS-PAGE and Western Blot </p>

<p>Five microliters of extracts were mixed tho-
roughly with 20 μl of loading buffer, which were then 
boiled for 5 min. Ten microliters of the mixture were 
subjected to SDS-PAGE, and bands were captured. </p>

<p>Treatments of AGS cells </p>

<p>AGS cells in the logarithmic phase were divided 
into two groups. Cells in one group were grown in the 
medium containing 1 μmol/L DHR-123 and 60 
μg/ml, 120 μg/ml, 240 μg/ml, 480 μg/ml or 960 
μg/ml Hp extract for 24 h and those in the other 
group maintained in the medium containing 480 
μg/ml Hp extract and 1 μmol/L of DHR-123 for 3 h, 6 
h, 9 h, 12 h and 24 h. Cells in the blank control were 
grown in the culture medium alone. In the negative 
control group, Hp extract was replaced with E.coli 
extract. Cells in the positive control group were in-
cubated in the medium containing 1 µmol/L 
DHR-123 and 50 µmol/L H 2 O 2 for 24 h. </p>

<p>Detection of ROS using Flow cytometry </p>

<p>Cells were washed with PBS once. After trypsin 
digestion, AGS cells were re-suspended in PBS and 
1×10 4 viable cells were measured in each sample by 
FACScalibur (BD Bioscience). Histogram analysis was 
performed to analyze the mean fluorescence intensity 
of rhodamine 123 and ROS level can be expressed as 
the intensity of fluorescence [15]. All experiments 
were repeated for three times and data were expresses 
as  ± SD. </p>

<p>Analysis of Cytochrome c reduction </p>

<p>Cytochrome c reduction directly reflects the 
generation of O 2 •ˉ in cells. To further confirm the ROS 
levels, cytochrome c reduction was determined. After 
trypsin digestion, AGS cells were re-suspended in 
culture medium and cell density was adjusted to 
3×10 6 /ml. Then, cells were incubated with cytoch-</p>

<p>rome C (50 μmol/l) for 15 min and centrifuged at 200 
g for 10 min at 4℃. The absorbance of supernatant 
was measured using a spectrophotometer at 550 nm. 
The absorbance can be converted into the reduction of 
cytochrome c by the extinction coefficient for cytoch-
rome c (2.1×10 4 M -1 cm -1 ). The results were expressed 
as unit nmol/3×10 6 AGS cells/15 min [16]. The me-
dium containing 50 μmol/l reduced cytochrome C 
alone served as a blank control in the detection of 
absorbance. The experiment was repeated 3 times and 
data were expressed as  ± SD. </p>

<p>Detection of cell viability </p>

<p>Mitochondria play a major role in cellular func-
tion such as the productions of ATP and ROS. Ele-
vated ROS level can cause oxidative damage directly 
to mtDNA resulting in abnormality in ATP produc-
tion. Therefore, the amount of ATP was further de-
termined aiming to indirectly detect the cell viability 
and the mitochondrial activity and function [17]. After 
trypsin digestion, cell concentration was adjusted to 
3×10 5 /ml with medium and the ATP level was tested 
according to the manufacturer's instruction. The in-
tensity of the Luminescence (RLU) signals represents 
the cell viability. </p>

<p>Extraction of mtDNA of AGS cells </p>

<p>After trypsin digestion, AGS cells were then 
suspended in PBS and AGS mtDNA extraction was 
performed according to the manufacturer's instruc-
tions. </p>

<p>PCR amplification, sequencing and comparison 
of various mtDNA segments </p>

<p>The primers for mtDNA D-Loop region were 
synthesized by Shanghai Sangong Co., Ltd. (Table 1) 
and a total of 50 μl of mixture used for amplification. 
The products were sequenced by Shanghai Sangong 
Co., Ltd. immediately after purification. The primers 
for sequencing were those for amplification. 
Using the <rs type="software">DNA Star</rs> software, mtDNA se-
quences of AGS cells after Hp extract treatment were 
compared with those in the blank control (AGS cells). 
mtDNA mutation is defined as both sequences are 
different from the those in controls. If two peaks at a 
particular point are observed in the sequence, only 
when the lower-intensity peak accounted for more 
than 20% of the specific peak, a mixture of signals 
from two bases can be determined, and hence hete-
rogeneous mutation that occurs at this locus can be 
identified [18]. </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2011, 8 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Table 1 Primers sequence of mtDNA genes </p>

<p>Sequence 
Forward primer (5'→3') 
Reverse primer (5'→3') 
Anticipated length (bp) 
D-Loop 
ATTCTAACCTGAATCGGAGG 
GATGCTTGCATGTGTAATCT 
1528 
ATPase8 
CCCGGACGTCTAAACCAAACC 
GGGGATCAATAGAGGGGGAAATA 
512 
ATPase6 
AATTACCCCCATACTCCTTACACT 
GGGTCATGGGCTGGGTTTTACTAT 
857 
COX-I 
CCTCGGAGCTGGTAAAAA 
GGGGGTTCGATTCCTTC 
1654 
COX-II 
ACTACCCCGATGCATACACCACA 
GGGCAATGAATGAAGCGAACAG 
1333 
COX-III 
GCCGTACGCCTAACCGCTAACA 
TCGTAAGGGGTGGTTTTTCTATG 
1177 
Cyt b 
CGCACGGACTACAACCACGAC 
GGACAGGCCCATTTGAGTATTTTG 
1212 </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Data were analyzed with <rs id="software-2" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 11.0</rs> sta-
tistical software. Comparisons between multiple 
groups were performed with one way analysis of va-
riance. Differences among groups were evaluated by 
Newman-Keuls' Q-test. Differences between two 
groups were evaluated with t or t' test. The mtDNA 
mutation rates were assessed with the chi-square test. 
The relationship between ROS and mtDNA mutation 
rate was assessed using a linear correlation test. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>CagA and VacA proteins </p>

<p>As shown in Fig. 1a and b, the CagA protein (120 
kDa) and VacA protein (95 kDa) were expressed in the 
wide type Hp11638, whereas only the CagA protein 
was identified in the mutant Hp11638M. </p>

<p>Fig.1 Detection of CagA and VacA protein by Western 
Blot. a: CagA protein (arrow) b: VacA protein (arrow). Lane 
1: Marker; Lane 2: Hp 11638M; Lane 3: Hp11638. </p>

<p>ROS levels in the AGS cells </p>

<p>Compared with the blank control, the ROS levels 
of the negative control were no obvious change at all 
stimulated concentration and duration. (The ROS le-
vels were not significantly changed in the blank con-
trols and negative controls) 
When compared with the negative control, the 
ROS levels in the AGS cells were markedly increased </p>

<p>after stimulation with Hp11638M extract or Hp11638 
extract (Fig. 2). Moreover, the ROS levels in AGS cells 
treated with 480 µg/ml and 960 µg/ml Hp11638M 
extract and with 240 µg/ml, 480 µg/ml and 960 
µg/ml Hp11638 extract were remarkably higher than 
those in the positive control (310.67±24.01, P&lt;0.01) 
(Fig. 3b-g). Furthermore, the ROS levels in AGS cells 
stimulated by Hp11638 extract of difference concen-
trations were significantly higher than those in cells 
treated by Hp11638M extract of corresponding con-
centrations (P&lt;0.05) (Fig. 3c and f, other illustrations 
were not listed). As shown in Fig. 4, a similar trend 
was observed in the cytochrome c reduction. 
As shown in Table 2, the ROS levels in the AGS 
cells stimulated by Hp11638M extract and Hp11638 
extract were dramatically higher than those in the 
negative control (P&lt;0.01), and the ROS level elevated 
with the prolongation of stimulation (P&lt;0.01). After 
treatment with Hp11638M for 12 h and 24 h and with 
Hp11638 for 6 h, 9 h, 12 h and 24 h, the ROS levels 
were significantly higher than in the positive controls 
(P&lt;0.01). In addition, the ROS levels after stimulation 
by Hp11638 extract were remarkably higher than after 
stimulation by Hp11638M extract at the same time 
point (P&lt;0.05). Similar trend was also observed in the 
cytochrome c reduction (Fig. 5). </p>

<p>0 120 240 360 480 600 720 840 960 1080 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>2500 </p>

<p>Hp11638M </p>

<p>Hp11638 </p>

<p>Concentration of Hp extracts (g/ml) </p>

<p>ROS </p>

<p>levels </p>

<p>Fig.2 The ROS levels in the AGS cells after treatment with 
different Hp extracts of various concentrations. The ROS 
levels increased with the increase in the concentration of 
Hp extracts. The ROS levels after Hp11638 treatment were 
markedly higher than after mutant Hp11638M treatment at 
each concentration (P&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2011, 8 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Fig.3 ROS levels in the AGS cells after24 h of stimulation by Hp extracts of various concentrations. a: Negative control. 
Cells were stimulated by 960 µg/ml E. coli extract and the ROS level was 3; b: Positive control. Cells were incubated with 
culture medium containing 1 µmol/l DHR-123 and 50 µmol/l H 2 O 2 and the ROS level was 188; c: Cells were stimulated by 
480 µg/ml Hp11638M extract and the ROS level was 874; d: Cells were stimulated by 960 µg/ml Hp11638M extract and the 
ROS level was 1334; e: Cells were stimulated by 240 µg/ml Hp11638 extract and the ROS level was 835; f: Cells were 
stimulated by 480 µg/ml Hp11638 extract and the ROS level was 1395; g: Cells were stimulated by 960 µg/ml Hp11638 
extract and the ROS. </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2011, 8 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Table 2 the ROS level in AGS cells with various duration of stimulation by Hp extracts (  ± SD) </p>

<p>Group 
Duration of stimulation (h) 
3 
6 
9 
12 
24 
Blank Control 
2.33±0.47 
2.00±0 
2.67±0.47 
2.67±0.47 
2.67±0.47 
Negative Control 
3.03±0.51 
3.03±0.51 
3.03±0.51 
3.37±0.59 
3.37±0.59 
Positive Control 
260.67±18.70 
272.00±11.86 
284.67±17.42 
300.67±23.79 
310.67±24.01 
Hp11638M 
52.00±16.09 
166.00±39.59 
316.67±49.60 
475.33±59.01 j 
880.33±80.69 k 
Hp11638 
148.67±33.50 a 
473.00±63.51 b,f 
796.67±71.53 c,g 
1149.00±161.28 d,h 
1409.33±182.92 e,i </p>

<p>Note: a: P&lt;0.05, b; P&lt;0.01, c: P&lt;0.01, d: P&lt;0.01, e:P&lt;0.01 vs Hp11638M. f: P&lt;0.01, g: P&lt;0.01, h: P&lt;0.01, i: P&lt;0.01 vs positive controls. </p>

<p>0 120 240 360 480 600 720 840 960 1080 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>Hp11638M </p>

<p>Hp11638 </p>

<p>Concentration of Hp extracts (g/ml) </p>

<p>Cytochrome </p>

<p>C 
reduction </p>

<p>Fig.4 The cytochrome c reduction in the AGS cells after 
treatment with Hp extracts of various correlations. The 
cytochrome c reduction increased with the increase in the 
concentration of Hp extracts. The cytochrome c reduction 
after Hp11638 treatment were markedly higher than after 
mutant Hp11638M treatment at each concentration 
(P&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 
9 12 15 18 21 24 27 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>Hp11638M </p>

<p>Hp11638 </p>

<p>Duration of stimulation by Hp extracts(h) </p>

<p>Cytochrome </p>

<p>C 
reduction </p>

<p>Fig.5. Cytochrome c reduction in the AGS cells after sti-
mulation with Hp extracts for various durations. The cy-
tochrome c reduction increased with the increase in the 
duration of Hp extract stimulation. The cytochrome c 
reduction after Hp11638 treatment were markedly higher 
than after mutant Hp11638M treatment at each duration 
(P&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>As shown in Table 3 and 4, the Luminescence 
levels were not markedly changed in the blank con-
trol, and negative control. </p>

<p>When compared with the negative control, the 
Luminescence levels in the AGS cells stimulated by 
Hp11638M extract or Hp11638 extracts of various 
concentration or for different durations were signifi-
cantly lower (P&lt;0.01), and the decrease in the Lumi-
nescence level was in a concentration and time de-
pendent manner in both groups. Furthermore, the 
RLU levels in the AGS cells after stimulation by 
Hp11638 extract were dramatically lower than those 
after Hp11638M stimulation at corresponding con-
centration (P&lt;0.05), and the RLU levels after stimula-
tion by Hp11638 extract for 6 h, 9 h, 12 h and 24 h were 
also markedly decreased when compared with those 
after Hp11638M stimulation for corresponding dura-
tion (P&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>Table 3 RLU levels in the AGS cells after stimulation by Hp 
extracts of various concentrations ( 
 ± SD) </p>

<p>Group 
concentration of Hp extracts (μg/ml) 
60 
120 
240 
480 
960 
Blank control 1421±159 1439±171 1398±143 1592±178 1347±128 
Negative 
control 
1379±156 1452±167 1368±123 1676±185 1383±149 </p>

<p>Positive 
control 
815±88 
758±79 
818±85 
692±69 
795±71 </p>

<p>Hp11638M 658±62 
586±54 
415±37 
303±35 
186±21 
Hp11638 
503±54 a 350±42 b 282±31 c 153±17 d 102±12 e </p>

<p>Note: P&lt;0.01: negative control vs Hp11638M or Hp11638; a: P&lt;0.05; 
b: P&lt;0.01; c: P&lt;0.01;d: P&lt;0.01; e: P&lt;0.01 vs Hp11638M. </p>

<p>Table 4 RLU levels in the AGS cells after stimulation by Hp 
extracts for various durations ( 
 ± SD) </p>

<p>Group 
Duration (h) 
3 
6 
9 
12 
24 
Blank control 1415±147 1482±153 1427±162 1564±164 1474±139 
Negative con-
trol 
1484±166 1571±172 1378±148 1623±175 1568±151 </p>

<p>Positive con-
trol 
773±82 
816±93 848±80 759±73 754±71 </p>

<p>11638M 
807±86 
703±72 485±53 322±41 302±39 
11638 
750±82 a 
415±37 b 359±45 c 214±24 d 153±17 e </p>

<p>Note: P&lt;0.01: negative control vs Hp11638M or Hp11638; 
a:P&gt;0.05;b: P&lt;0.01; c: P&lt;0.05;d: P&lt;0.05; e: P&lt;0.01 vs Hp11638M </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2011, 8 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Mutations of mtDNA D-loop region and Cytb 
gene in the AGS cells </p>

<p>PCR products were verified by electrophoresis 
and then sequenced. Products of the expected size 
(Fig. 6a-b) showed that mtDNA D-loop region and 
Cytb genes were successfully amplified. </p>

<p>Fig.6 PCR products of mtDNA. a: products of mtDNA 
D-Loop region after 1% TAE agarose gel electrophoresis 
(1528 bp); b: products of Cytb gene after 1% TAE agarose 
gel electrophoresis (1212 bp). </p>

<p>When compared with the sequence of mtDNA 
D-Loop region of the AGS cells, no mutations in the 
mtDNA genes were found in the negative control. 
As shown in Table 5, the mutation rates in the 
mtDNA D-loop region after stimulation by Hp11638 
extract of 120 µg/ml, 240 µg/ml, 480 µg/ml and 960 
µg/ml were remarkably higher than those after sti-
mulation by Hp11638M extract of corresponding 
concentration (χ 2 =8.21, P&lt;0.01; χ 2 =6.19, P&lt;0.05; 
χ 2 =6.06, P&lt;0.05; χ 2 =8.44, P&lt;0.01, respectively). How-
ever, there was no significant difference between two 
groups when the concentrations of Hp extracts were 
60 µg/ml (χ 2 =2.93, P&gt;0.05). Furthermore, the muta-
tion rates in the mtDNA D-loop region elevated with 
the increase in the extract concentration (Fig.7). </p>

<p>Table 5 Mutation rates in the mtDNA D-loop region of 
the AGS cells </p>

<p>Group 
Concentration (µg/ml) 
Durations (h) 
60 120 240 480 960 3 
6 
9 
12 24 
Hp11638M 
(%) 
0.46 0.72 1.70 2.95 4.52 0.20 0.65 1.44 2.03 2.95 </p>

<p>Hp11638 
(%) 
0.98 a 1.90 b 3.08 c 4.65 d 7.00 e 0.33 f 1.70 g 2.49 h 3.53 i 4.65 j </p>

<p>Note: a: P&gt;0.05; b: P&lt;0.01; c: P&lt;0.05;d: P&lt;0.05; e: P&lt;0.01; f: P&gt;0.05;g: 
P&lt;0.01; h: P&lt;0.05;i: P&lt;0.05; j: P&lt;0.05. vs Hp11638M </p>

<p>When compared with the mtDNA of AGS cells 
without treatment, only three heteroplasmic muta-
tions in the Cytb gene were found in the mtDNA of 
AGS cells treated with 960 μg/ml Hp11638 extract for 
24 h (Fig.8), while no mutation in the mtDNA genes 
was found in the AGS cells after stimulation by Hp 
extracts of other concentrations. </p>

<p>0 120 240 360 480 600 720 840 960 1080 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Hp11638 </p>

<p>Hp11638M </p>

<p>Concentration of Hp extracts(g/ml) </p>

<p>Ra </p>

<p>te </p>

<p>of </p>

<p>mutation </p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>Fig.7 mutation rates in the mtDNA D-loop region of the 
AGS cells after stimulation by Hp extracts of various con-
centrations. The mutation rates increased with the increase 
in the concentration of Hp extracts. After stimulation by Hp 
extracts of 120 µg/ml, 240 µg/ml, 480 µg/ml and 960 µg/ml, 
the mutation rates in the Hp11638 group were remarkably 
higher than those in the Hp11638M group (P&lt;0.01). </p>

<p>Fig.8 Mutations in the mtDNA Cytb gene. a: Sequence of 
mtDNA of AGS cells without treatment. the section under 
the black line represents the normal sequence; b: Sequence 
of mtDNA of AGS cells stimulated by 960 µg/ml of 
Hp11638 extract for 24 h. The section under the black line 
represents the mutant sequence. The sequencing was car-
ried out from both directions and twice. </p>

<p>When compared with the D-Loop region of 
mtDNA of AGS cells without treatment, the mutation 
rates in the mtDNA D-loop region in AGS cells after 
stimulation by Hp11638 extract for 6, 9, 12 and 24 h 
were significantly higher than those after stimulation 
by Hp11638M extract for corresponding duration 
(χ 2 =7.2, P&lt;0.01; χ 2 =4.35, P&lt;0.05; χ 2 =6.40, P&lt;0.05; 
χ 2 =6.06, P&lt;0.05, respectively). There was no signifi-</p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2011, 8 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>cant difference between two groups after 3 h of sti-
mulation (χ 2 =0.5, P&gt;0.05). Furthermore, the mutation 
rates in the mtDNA D-loop region were positively 
correlated with Hp extract simulation duration 
(Fig.9). Furthermore, the mutation rates in the 
mtDNA D-loop region increased with the prolonga-
tion of Hp extract simulation. When compared with 
AGS mtDNA, no mutation was detected in all 
mtDNA genes in cells stimulated by two strains for 
the same period of time. </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 
9 12 15 18 21 24 27 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Hp11638 </p>

<p>Hp11638M </p>

<p>Duration of stimulation by Hp extracts(h) </p>

<p>Ra </p>

<p>te </p>

<p>of </p>

<p>mutation(%) </p>

<p>Fig.9 Mutation rates of mtDNA D-loop region after Hp 
extract simulation for different durations. The mutation 
rates increased with the prolongation of stimulation by Hp 
extracts. After 6 h, 9 h, 12 h and 24 h of stimulation, the 
mutation rates of mtDNA D-loop region in the Hp11638 
group were significantly higher than those in the Hp11638M 
group (P&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>Types of mutation </p>

<p>A total of 616 mutations were identified in the 
mtDNA D-Loop region including 489 point muta-
tions, 81 insertions and 46 deletions. In addition, 
89.4% of the point mutations (437/489) were G → A; 
C→T or A → G; T→C transition. 
Except in cells treated with 60 μg/ml Hp11638M 
extract for 24 h and those treated with 480 μg/ml both 
extracts for 3 h, micro-satellite mutations were found 
in the D-Loop region after Hp stimulation under the 
rest conditions. The sequences of 303PolyC, 
16184PolyC and 514CA repeats in the mtDNA 
D-Loop region of AGS cells were 8CT6C, 7CT4C and 
(CA) 5 , whereas the sequences were 7CT6C, 12C, and 
(CA) 4 after Hp induced mutation (Fig.10-12) . </p>

<p>Correlation between mtDNA mutation rate and 
ROS level </p>

<p>The results above suggested the mutation rate of 
mtDNA D-loop region and the mean ROS level were 
elevated and the ATP level was decreased with the 
increase in the concentration of both Hp extracts and 
with the prolongation of Hp extract stimulation. Cor-
relation analysis (Fig.13) showed the mutation rates of 
the mtDNA D-Loop region were positively correlated </p>

<p>with the mean ROS levels (r=0.982, P&lt;0.01), and ne-
gatively related to the mean ATP levels (r=0.909, 
P&lt;0.01) (Fig.14). </p>

<p>Fig.10 Mutation of 303PolyC in the mtDNA D-loop region. 
a: Sequence of 303PolyC in the mtDNA D-loop region of 
AGS cells, the section of black line is the normal sequence; 
b: Sequence of 303PolyC in the mtDNA D-loop region of 
AGS cells stimulated by Hp extracts, and the section of 
black line is the mutant sequence. The sequencing was 
carried out from both directions and repeated, and the 
sequence was assayed from 5' to 3'. </p>

<p>Fig.11 The mutation analysis of 16184PolyC in mtDNA 
D-loop region. a: Sequence of 16184PolyC in mtDNA 
D-loop region of AGS cells, the section of black line is the </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2011, 8 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>normal sequence; b: Sequence of 16184PolyC in mtDNA 
D-loop region of AGS cells stimulated by Hp extracts, and 
the section of black line is the mutant sequence. Sequencing 
was carried out from both directions and repeated once, 
and the sequence was assayed from 3' to 5'. </p>

<p>Fig.12 The mutation analysis of 514CA repeats in mtDNA 
D-loop region. a: Sequence of 514CA repeats in mtDNA 
D-loop region of AGS cells, the section of black line is the 
normal sequence; b: Sequence of 514CA repeats in mtDNA 
D-loop region of AGS cells stimulated by Hp extracts, and 
the section of black line is the mutant sequence. Sequencing 
was carried out from both directions and twice, and the 
sequence was assayed from 3' to 5'. </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>Rate of mtDNA mutation(%) </p>

<p>ROS </p>

<p>level </p>

<p>Fig.13 Correlation between the mtDNA mutation rate and 
ROS level. The mutation rates of mtDNA D-loop region 
were positively correlated with the mean ROS levels and 
the equation was Y=284.2X-12.7 (r=0.982, P&lt;0.01). </p>

<p>Fig.14 Correlation between the mtDNA mutation rate and 
the ATP level. The mean ATP levels were negatively cor-
related with the mutation rates of mtDNA D-loop region 
and the equation was Y=-106.1X+656.7 (r=0.909, P&lt;0.01). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Hp has been shown to be an important pathogen 
of gastric and duodenal inflammation. In various de-
veloping countries, more than 80% of the population 
is Hp positive, even at young ages. The prevalence of 
Hp infection in industrialized countries generally 
remains under 40% and is considerably lower in 
children and adolescents than in adults and elderly 
people [1]. To date, the pathogenic mechanisms have 
not been well defined. 
Studies have shown Hp can cause damage to 
mitochondria leading to the impairment of cell cycle 
[10,11]. In the study of Machado et al [12], they spe-
culate, following Hp infection, the activity and ex-
pression of base excision repair and mismatch repair 
are down-regulated both in vitro and in vivo. Moreo-
ver, Hp induces genomic instability in nuclear CA 
repeats in mice and in mtDNA of AGS cells and 
chronic gastritis tissue, and this effect in mtDNA is 
associated with bacterial virulence. Furthermore, the 
DNA damage induced genetic exchange may facilitate 
spread of antibiotic resistance and selection of fitter 
variants through re-assortment of preexisting alleles 
in this important human pathogen [19]. In a letter to 
the editor, Lee et al [13] reveal the mtDNA mutations 
in peptic ulcer tissues associated with Hp infection 
occur in both the mtDNA control and coding regions. 
Approximately half of the patients had heteroplasmic 
mtDNA mutations. 
The human mtDNA is a double stranded circular 
molecule of 16569 bp and contains 37 genes coding for 
two rRNAs, 22 tRNAs and 13 polypeptides. The 
mtDNA is present in high copy numbers (10 3~1 0 4 
copies per cell) in virtually all cells and the vast ma-
jority of copies are identical at birth. Furthermore, </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2011, 8 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>mtDNA is known for having high acquired mutation 
rates which are 10 times higher than that of nuclear 
genomic DNA. It is generally accepted that high mu-
tation rates of mtDNA are contributed to the lack of 
protective histones, inefficient DNA repair systems 
and continuous exposure to ROS generated by oxida-
tive phosphorylation in the mitochondria [9]. 
The D-loop, which is 1124 bp in size (positions 
16024-576), is a non-coding region, and acts as a 
promoter for both the heavy and light strands of the 
mtDNA, and contains essential transcription and rep-
lication elements. The D-loop region is a hot spot for 
mtDNA alterations and the nucleotide positions 
16024±16 324 and 63±322 located in the D-Loop are 
termed first hypervariable region (HV1) and second 
hypervariable region (HV2), respectively [20]. The 
sequence analysis of these two regions is used not 
only in forensic analysis, but also in medical diagnosis 
[21]. 
Obst et al have shown that Hp extract could in-
duce the synthesis of ROS, diminish the levels of re-
duced glutathione (GSH), induce DNA fragmentation 
and increase DNA synthesis in gastric cells [22]. Da-
vies et al also revealed Hp could stimulate the pro-
duction of reactive oxygen metabolite in the antral 
mucosa in vivo [23]. Hp can induce the production of 
pro-inflammatory cytokines from gastric epithelial 
cells resulting in the increased generation of ROS in 
gastric epithelial cells [24]. It has been shown that Hp 
infection can increase the expression and activity of 
spermine oxidase, which oxidizes polyamines that are 
abundant in epithelial cells to release hydrogen pe-
roxide [25]. In addition, study also demonstrates that 
Hp itself also generates ROS [26], and administration 
of antioxidase or antioxidant may be protective [14]. 
In the present study, extract was obtained from 
VacA positive and VacA negative HP. The stimulation 
of ROS production by VacA, an important virulence 
factor of Hp, has been demonstrated in numerous 
studies. Kimura et al revealed VacA purified from Hp 
could cause mitochondrial damage (impair mito-
chondrial membrane potential followed by a decrease 
in energy metabolism) [11], which may be a cause of 
excessive production of ROS. This effect was con-
firmed by Kim et al [27]. Furthermore, VacA from Hp 
could also impaired glutathione metabolism which 
alleviates the anti-oxidative potency [28]. These effects 
result in excessive generation of ROS and compro-
mised anti-oxidative potency. These effects may also 
explain why the ROS levels in AGS cells stimulated by 
Hp11638 extract were significantly higher than those 
in cells treated by Hp11638M extract at the corres-
ponding concentrations. </p>

<p>Therefore, Hp infection may involve in many 
gastrointestinal diseases through excessive ROS pro-
duction in the mucosa, the pronounced membrane 
damage, and the depletion of gastric anti-oxidants 
[29]. The ROS not only causes damage to nuclear and 
mitochondrial DNA, but compromises the DNA re-
pair. The mismatch repair (MMR) pathway is an im-
portant mechanism involving in the DNA repair. 
Studies have shown Hp infection can down-regulate 
the expressions of MMR in vivo and in vitro [30] [12]. 
ROS cause damage to not only nuclear DNA, but 
mtDNA. mtDNA mutations have been detected in 
Hp-infected chronic gastritis and peptic ulcer tissues, 
suggesting that Hp infection contributes to the accu-
mulation of mutations in mtDNA at early steps of 
gastric cancer development [31]. In the study of Ma-
chado et al., their results showed Hp infection re-
sulted in increased mutations in the non-coding 
D-loop as well as the coding genes ND1 and COI of 
mtDNA of gastric cells [12]. The increase in the num-
ber of mutations was mainly attributed to a rise of 
transitions, possibly a consequence of oxidative 
damage. The increase in mtDNA mutations was de-
pendent on the bacterial virulence factors. The 
changes in mtDNA in peptic ulcer tissues may further 
impair the ATP synthesis and increase the mtDNA 
copy number to compensate for the deficiency in ATP. 
During this perturbation, mitochondria might pro-
duce a large amount of ROS, causing the vicious cycle 
in peptic ulcer disease [13]. 
In the present study, the ROS levels and the 
mutations in the mtDNA of AGS cells were deter-
mined after Hp extract stimulation. Our results 
demonstrated the ROS levels and the frequency of 
mutations in the mtDNA increased and the cell via-
bility decreased in a concentration and time depen-
dent manner. In addition, the ROS levels and Lumi-
nescence levels were not markedly changed in the 
blank control and the negative control accompanied 
by absence of any mutation in the mtDNA. These 
findings further confirmed that the increased ROS 
levels and the elevated mutation rates as well as the 
decreased cell viability were caused by the Hp ex-
tracts. Furthermore, correlation analysis showed the 
ROS level was positively correlated with the mutation 
rates. Therefore, our findings support the hypothesis 
that Hp induced ROS was the main cause of mtDNA 
mutations. 
However, the mutation rate of mtDNA in our 
results (7% highest) is significantly lower than that 
reported by Machado et al [12] which may be ex-
plained the following reasons. First, Machado et al 
applied live bacteria to stimulate AGS cells and the 
duration of stimulation was as long as 5 d, whereas </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2011, 8 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>stimulation by the Hp extract was conducted for only 
up to 24 h in the present study. Second, Machado et al 
compared the mtDNA sequence post-stimulation 
with that from database, while, in the present study, 
the mtDNA sequence of AGS cells after stimulation 
was compared with that at baseline which avoids the 
false increase in the mutation rate due to variance in 
certain loci of mtDNA between AGS cells and normal 
human cells. Although the mutation rate in the 
present study was lower than that reported by Ma-
chado et al, we still postulated there is an accumula-
tion in the Hp extract induced mtDNA mutation. 
Our results also showed that no mutations were 
found in the coding regions of Cox-I, Cox-II, Cox-III, 
ATPase6 and ATPase8 in the mtDNA. Only 3 hete-
roplasmic mutations in the Cytb gene loci were iden-
tified in the mtDNA of AGS cells after stimulation 
with 960 μg/ml Hp11638 extract, which suggested 
that the D-Loop region is the main location where Hp 
induced mtDNA mutations occur and that the 
mtDNA mutation seldom takes place in the gene 
coding region of mtDNA [32]. 
MtDNA contains several mono-and dinucleo-
tide repeats. The ones most frequently used to test 
mtGI are a (CA)n microsatellite starting at 514 bp po-
sition of the D-loop [33] and a homopolymeric C tract 
extending from 16,184 to 16,193 bp of the D-loop, 
which is interrupted by a T at 16,189 bp position [34]. 
In human populations, the mtCA microsatellite shows 
seven different alleles varying in size by one repeat. 
On the other hand, the (16184)C homopolymer exhi-
bits two forms: the stable one in which all mt-genomes 
of an individual have equal-length tracts (usually 10 
bp long) and the unstable one in which the 
mt-genomes of a given individual are a mosaic of C 
tracts varying in length from 8 to 14 nucleotides. 
Moreover, a detailed analysis of the mechanism of 
length variation shows that a T→C transition in the T 
nucleotide at 16189 bp position is the primary cause of 
instability [34]. In our study, mutations were found in 
17 out of 20 samples after stimulation by Hp extracts 
and included C deletion in the 303PolyC region, CA 
deletion in the D514CA repeats and T→C replacement 
at the 16189 bp position of 16184PolyC. Previous stu-
dies have found that most of mtDNA mutations are 
T→C; G→A replacement [32,35]. In this study, 616 
mutations were identified in the D-Loop region of 
mtDNA, including 489 point mutations, 81 insertions 
and 46 deletions, and 89.4% of point mutations 
(437/489) were G → A; C→T and A → G; T→C con-
version. 
In conclusion, our study demonstrates that Hp 
extracts can induce the production of intracellular 
ROS, which may be the primary cause of mtDNA </p>

<p>mutations. In addition, mtDNA mutation results in 
the reduction of ATP synthesized in mitochondria 
and affect cell viability. Both the pathogenic factors of 
Hp (VacA and CagA), especially the VacA, play an 
important role in the Hp induced mtDNA mutation. 
We speculate that the accumulation of Hp induced 
mtDNA mutation is likely to be one of critical me-
chanisms underlying the carcinogenic effects of Hp. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>This study was funded by Shanghai Science and 
Technology Commission (No. 08411968100). </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>The authors have declared that no conflict of in-
terest exists. </p>



<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2011, 8 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>





</text></tei>