<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3531733" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Lipoglycans modulate the initiation of immune responses by interacting with TLR2. 
Results: A hypermannosylated lipomannan variant, once recognized by the immune system, enhances both innate responses 
and Th17 differentiation. 
Conclusion: Altered lipoglycan structures are differently recognized by innate immune cells with an impact on the adaptive 
immune response. 
Significance: Specific lipoglycan structures may be useful to modulate immune responses. </p>

<p>Toll-like receptors (TLRs) recognize pathogens by interacting 
with pathogen-associated molecular patterns, such as the 
phosphatidylinositol-based lipoglycans, lipomannan (LM) and 
lipoarabinomannan (LAM). Such structures are present in sev-
eral pathogens, including Mycobacterium tuberculosis, being 
important for the initiation of immune responses. It is well 
established that the interaction of LM and LAM with TLR2 is a 
process dependent on the structure of the ligands. However, the 
implications of structural variations on TLR2 ligands for the 
development of T helper (Th) cell responses or in the context of 
in vivo responses are less studied. Herein, we used Corynebacte-
rium glutamicum as a source of lipoglycan intermediates for 
host interaction studies. In this study, we have deleted a putative 
glycosyltransferase, NCgl2096, from C. glutamicum and found 
that it encodes for a novel ␣(132)arabinofuranosyltransferase, 
AftE. Biochemical analysis of the lipoglycans obtained in the 
presence (wild type) or absence of NCgl2096 showed that AftE is 
involved in the biosynthesis of singular arabinans of LAM. In its 
absence, the resulting molecule is a hypermannosylated (hLM) 
form of LAM. Both LAM and hLM were recognized by dendritic </p>

<p>cells, mainly via TLR2, and triggered the production of several 
cytokines. hLM was a stronger stimulus for in vitro cytokine 
production and, as a result, a more potent inducer of Th17 
responses. In vivo data confirmed hLM as a stronger inducer 
of cytokine responses and suggested the involvement of pat-
tern recognition receptors other than TLR2 as sensors for 
lipoglycans. </p>

<p>The immune system has evolved several mechanisms of 
defense against pathogens, favoring pathogen clearance while 
ensuring host integrity. The innate immune system is the first 
line of host defense against invading pathogens, being mediated 
by phagocytes including macrophages and dendritic cells (DC) </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>(1). These cells express host germ line-encoded pattern recog-
nition receptors (PRRs) that recognize specific pathogen-asso-
ciated molecular patterns present in microorganisms, resulting 
in the initiation of innate immune responses (2). To date, the 
best studied PRRs are toll-like receptors (TLRs) that sense com-
ponents of bacteria, fungi, protozoa and viruses, thus playing a 
major role in innate immunity (2). 
TLR2 binds a wider range of ligands than other members of 
the TLR family. TLR2 in association with TLR1 or TLR6 is 
essential for recognizing bacterial lipoproteins and lipopeptides 
as well as a variety of compounds, including lipoteichoic acids, 
lipoarabinomannan (LAM), and zymosan (2). Structural stud-
ies have revealed that the recognition of lipopeptide ligands by 
TLR2 induces the formation of TLR2-TLR1 or TLR2-TLR6 </p>

<p>□ S This article contains supplemental Table 1 and Figs. 1-7. 
Author's Choice-Final version full access. 
1 Supported by Fundação para a Ciência e Tecnologia (FCT), Portugal, Per-
sonal Grant PTDC/SAU-MII/101977/2008. 
2 Supported by FCT, Portugal, Project Grant PTDC/SAU-MII/101977/2008. 
3 Supported by the Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research (NWO) 
through a VENI research grant (016.101.001). 
4 Supported by FCT, Portugal, Project Grant PTDC/BIA-BCM/102776/2008. A 
Ciência 2007 fellow. To whom correspondence may be addressed. Tel.: 
351-253-604-906; Fax: 351-253-604-847; E-mail: msaraiva@ecsaude. 
uminho.pt. 
5 Supported by a Personal Research Chair from James Bardrick, a Royal Soci-
ety Wolfson Research Merit Award, a Lister Institute-Jenner research fel-
lowship, the Medical Research Council, and Wellcome Trust Grant 081569/ 
Z/06/Z. To whom correspondence may be addressed. Tel.: 44-121-415-
8125; Fax: 44-121-414-5925; E-mail: g.besra@bham.ac.uk. </p>

<p>6 The abbreviations used are: DC, dendritic cells; LM, lipomannan; hLM, hyper-
mannosylated lipomannan; LAM, lipoarabinomannan; PRR, pattern recog-
nition receptor; Th, T helper; TLR, Toll-like receptor; PEC, peritoneal exu-
date cell; BL/6, C57BL/6; ANOVA, analysis of variance; Ara, arabinose; Man, 
mannose. </p>

<p>THE JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY VOL. 287, NO. 53, pp. 44173-44183, December 28, 2012 </p>

<p>Author's Choice </p>

<p>© 2012 by The American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Inc. Published in the U.S.A. </p>

<p>DECEMBER 28, 2012 • VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 53 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 44173 </p>

<p>dimers, bringing together the intracellular domains of these 
TLRs, which is needed to initiate signaling cascades (3, 4). How-
ever, the structure-function relationship between TLR2 and 
ligands other than lipoproteins, particularly LAMs, is not so 
well understood. This issue is relevant in the field of mycobac-
teria, because pathogens of the Mycobacterium genus are well 
known for their unique and complex cell wall, composed by 
several molecules, including lipoglycans, able to activate TLR2 
(5). Lipoglycans are surface-exposed macromolecules (6) and 
can be found as lipomannan (LM) and LAM. In mycobacteria, 
LM is a linear 20 -25-sugar residue oligopolymer of ␣(136) 
mannose units decorated with 7-10 singular ␣(132) mannose 
units. This mature LM is proposed to be further glycosylated by 
a large arabinan domain (ϳ70 arabinose units) and capped by 
2-3 mannose residues, resulting in mannose-capped LAM 
(Man-LAM) (7, 8). The structure of LM and LAM differs 
between virulent and non-virulent species of mycobacteria 
(7-10), suggesting that these molecules play a key role in the 
outcome of host-pathogen interactions. Importantly, recent 
evidence points to the fact that subtle structural variations on 
LM and LAM determine their biological activity and affect 
immunological responses (10 -14). It has been suggested that 
LM is a stronger inducer of TLR2 responses than LAM (15), and 
the ability of LM to activate TLR2 is determined by the mannan 
chain length (14). Furthermore, truncation of the arabinan 
domain of LAM increases its ability to activate TLR2 (13). In 
addition, truncated LAM leads to altered phagocytosis of 
mycobacteria (16), and, more recently, LM from avirulent 
mycobacteria were shown to be less branched and to have 
shorter mannose domains, being more efficiently presented to 
T cells in the context of CD1b (10). The acylation state of myco-
bacterial LM was also shown to modulate TLR2 responses (12). 
The study of TLR2 in infection and immunity has been well 
addressed (17). In the case of Mycobacterium tuberculosis, its in 
vitro recognition by macrophages and DC strongly depends on 
TLR2, with decreased expression of several cytokines in its 
absence (18 -21). In vivo, lack of TLR2 did not compromise 
bacterial control (18, 19, 22-24) but impacted the maintenance 
of T helper (Th) 17 cells in the lungs of infected animals (25) and 
granuloma formation (18, 19, 25). Finally, in humans, the asso-
ciation of tlr2 polymorphisms with susceptibility to tuberculo-
sis remains controversial (26) and appears to greatly depend on 
the genetics of the host/bacteria interplay (27). 
In this study, we sought to further understand the impact of 
the arabinan branching in the phenotype of Th cell responses 
generated in vitro. Because most of the genetic loci encoding for 
cell wall biogenesis are essential in the context of M. tuberculo-
sis, we have used Corynebacterium glutamicum as a model to 
obtain LAM variants (8, 28, 29). We have generated a C. glu-
tamicum mutant deficient in a putative glycosyltransferase 
(NCgl2096), which resulted in abrogation of LAM and led to 
the accumulation of a novel form of hypermannosylated lipo-
mannan (hLM). Both LAM and hLM were recognized by DC, 
mainly via TLR2, and triggered the production of both pro-and 
anti-inflammatory cytokines. hLM was a stronger stimulus for 
in vitro cytokine production and also a more potent inducer of 
Th17 responses. In vivo responses were also increased upon 
hLM recognition. Importantly, our in vivo data point to the </p>

<p>involvement of PRRs other than TLR2 as sensors for 
lipoglycans. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>Bacterial Strains and Growth Conditions-C. glutamicum 
and Escherichia coli DH5␣mcr were grown in BHI, CGXII, and 
LB at 30 and 37°C with kanamycin and ampicillin (50 g/ml), 
wherever appropriate. All chemicals were of reagent grade and 
obtained from Sigma-Aldrich. 
Construction of Plasmids, Mutant, and Complemented Strain-
To delete aftE, the deletion vector pK19mobsacB⌬-aftE was 
made, and crossover PCR was used with genomic DNA of 
C. glutamicum as template and two different PCRs with primer 
pairs AB and CD (supplemental Table 1). The resulting PCR 
product served as template for primer pairs AD. The PCR prod-
uct contained 18 nucleotides of the 3Ј-end of the respective 
gene together with genomic upstream sequences and 36 nucle-
otides of the 5Ј-end together with genomic downstream 
sequences. All plasmids used in this work were confirmed 
by sequencing. AftE was deleted by electroporating 
pK19mobsacB⌬-aftE into C. glutamicum and then selecting for 
sucrose resistance (30). Chromosomal deletions were con-
firmed using primer pairs AD as well as the additional new 
primer pairs EF (overhangs required for hybridization are given 
in italics in supplemental Table 1) hybridizing outside of the 
regions used for plasmid constructions. To construct pEKEx2-
Cg-aftE, Cg-aftE was amplified using primer pairs AD, with the 
former providing the sequence CTGCAG as a ribosome bind-
ing site. The amplified product was ligated between PstI and 
EcoRI in pEKEx2. Plasmid pEKEx2-Cg-aftE was electroporated 
in C. glutamicum ⌬aftE, resulting in C. glutamicum ⌬aftE 
pEKEx2-Cg-aftE. 
Extraction and Biochemical Characterization of Lipoglycans-
Lipoglycans were extracted from delipidated cells as described 
previously (31, 32) and treated with H 2 O 2 before immunologi-
cal assays to remove any endotoxin contamination (13) and to 
yield a negative Limulus amebocyte lysate test using E-TOXA-
TE 
TM (Sigma-Aldrich). For MALDI-TOF-MS, 2,5-dihydroxy-
benzoic acid was used as a matrix, and samples (0.5 l; 10 
g/l) were analyzed on a Voyager DE-STR MALDI-TOF 
instrument (PerSeptive Biosystems) using linear mode detec-
tion. Furthermore, lipoglycans were derivatized for glycosyl 
and linkage analysis as described previously (31). All of the data 
were collected and analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Xcaliber</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 1.2</rs>). 
HEK293 Cell Culture and Stimulation Assay-Human 
HEK293 cells transfected with TLR2 (33) were cultured as 
described previously (13). For stimulation assays, trypsine-re-
leased HEK293 cells were washed with and resuspended in cul-
ture medium at 5.55 ϫ 10 
5 cells/ml, after which 90 l of cell 
suspension (5 ϫ 10 
4 cells) was transferred to a 96-well U-bot-
tom plate (Greiner) and left for 2 h to let the cells re-adhere. 
After this, cells were stimulated (in triplicate) with 50 g/ml 
LAM or hLM in a final stimulation volume of 100 l. Non-
stimulated cells and cells stimulated with 50 ng/ml Pam3CSK4 
served as negative and positive controls, respectively. Culture 
supernatants were harvested after 24 h by centrifugation and 
analyzed for IL-8 content using ELISA (Invitrogen). </p>

<p>Lipoarabinomannan Branching and Th Cell Differentiation </p>



<p>VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 53 • DECEMBER 28, 2012 </p>

<p>Animals-Eight-week-old female C57BL/6 (BL/6) and 
BALB/c mice were obtained from Charles River (Barcelona, 
Spain); TLR2 
Ϫ/Ϫ mice in a C57BL/6 background and DO11.10 
mice in a BALB/c background were maintained at the Life and 
Health and Sciences Research Institute. All protocols were per-
formed according to the European Union Directive 86/609/ 
EEC and previously approved by the Portuguese authority 
Direção Geral de Veterinária. 
Culture of Bone Marrow-derived DC-5 ϫ 10 
6 bone marrow 
cells were seeded per well in 6-well plates in DMEM supple-
mented with 10% FBS, 1% HEPES, 1% sodium pyruvate (Invit-
rogen), and 20% of GM-CSF and incubated at 37°C in 5% CO 2 . 
On days 2 and 4, the medium was renewed. On day 6, non-
adherent cells were collected and resuspended in fresh medium 
with 20% GM-CSF, and 2.5 ϫ 10 
6 cells/well were cultured over-
night. On day 7, cultures were stimulated with different doses of 
LAM or hLM (0 -100 g/ml), with LPS (25 ng/ml) or left 
unstimulated as controls, and RNA and supernatants were har-
vested 6 and 24 h thereafter, respectively. EC 50 was calculated 
using a non-linear fit regression in the dose-response curves. 
Co-cultures of CD4 
ϩ T Cells and DC-Naive CD4 
ϩ T cells 
were purified from spleens of OVA(323-339)-TCR transgenic 
DO.11.10 mice using magnetic CD4 
ϩ beads (GK1.5, Miltenyi 
Biotec). These cells (1 ϫ 10 
6 cells/ml) were co-cultured with 
BALB/c DC (5 ϫ 10 
5 cells/ml) in the presence of LAM or hLM 
(10 g/ml) and peptide OVA(323-339) (2.5 M) for 7 days at 
37°C in 5% CO 2 . CD4 
ϩ T cells (1 ϫ 10 
6 cells/ml) were recov-
ered on day 7 and co-cultured with DC for an additional round 
of differentiation with fresh BALB/c DC (5 ϫ 10 
5 cells/ml) and 
LAM or hLM for an additional 3 days at 37°C in 5% CO 2 . At the 
end of the culture, CD4 
ϩ T cells were recovered and restimu-
lated in the presence of PMA (50 ng/ml) and ionomycin (500 
ng/ml) for 4 h and in the presence of brefeldin A (40 g/ml) for 
the last 2 h. The frequency of OVA(323-339)-specific, IFN-␥-
or IL-17-producing CD4 
ϩ T cells was determined by flow 
cytometry. 
In Vivo Model of Peritoneal Challenge-Groups of five mice 
were injected intraperitoneally with 50 or 400 g/mouse of 
LAM or hLM and sacrificed at specific time points postchal-
lenge. Peritoneal cells were harvested with cold PBS, counted, 
and processed for flow cytometry or RNA extraction and real-
time PCR analysis. Resident PECs were harvested from 
unstimulated BL/6 or TLR2 
Ϫ/Ϫ mice and stimulated in vitro for 
3 or 6 h with LAM and hLM (10 g/ml). Cytokine mRNA quan-
tification was performed by real-time PCR. 
Real-time PCR Analysis-Total RNA was extracted with 
TRIzol (Invitrogen), and reverse transcription was performed 
using the ReverteAid 
TM H Minus First Strand cDNA synthesis 
kit (Fermentas). The cDNA was then subjected to real-time 
PCR for quantification of IL-12p40, IL-12p35, IL23p19, TNF-␣, 
IL-6, IL-10, CXCL2, and ubiquitin (supplemental Table 1) with 
SYBR Green supermix (Bio-Rad) in a CFX 96 real-time (Bio-
Rad) system. The quantification of the target genes was ana-
lyzed using the CFX 96 real-time software and normalized 
against mouse ubiquitin mRNA. 
Flow Cytometry Analysis-Cell surface markers were ana-
lyzed using specific antibodies against Ly6G (APC, 1A8; Bio-
Legend), GR1 (PercP-Cy5.5, RB6 -8C5; BioLegend), and </p>

<p>CD11b (phycoerythrin, M1/70; eBioscience) for identification 
of neutrophils or against CD4 (eFluor450, RM4 -5; eBiosci-
ence) for identification of CD4 
ϩ T cells. For intracellular detec-
tion of cytokines, specific antibodies for IL-17 (phycoerythrin, 
eBio17B7; eBioscience) and IFN-␥ (FITC, XMG1.2; eBiosci-
ence) or isotype control antibodies (BioLegend) were used. Flu-
orescence was analyzed using an LSRII flow cytometer and 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">FACSDiva</rs> Software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">BD Bioscience</rs>) and data with <rs id="software-2" type="software">FlowJo</rs> soft-
ware (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">TreeStar</rs>). 
ELISA-Supernatants from LAM-or hLM-stimulated DC 
were screened for IL-12p40, IL-23, TNF-␣, IL-6, IL-12p70, and 
IL-10 by Ready Set-Go ELISA kits (eBioscience). 
Statistical Analysis-One-way ANOVA post hoc Tukey's t 
test was used with a confidence interval of 95% when multiple 
comparisons were evaluated. Two-way ANOVA was used in 
kinetic evaluations. Data were expressed as means Ϯ S.E.; p Ͻ 
0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Construction and Growth of C. glutamicum ⌬aftE-In 
Corynebacterineae, like M. tuberculosis and C. glutamicum, 
␣(136) mannosyltransferases MptA (Rv2174/NCgl2093) and 
MptB (Rv1459c/NCgl1505) catalyze the ␣(136)-Manp trans-
fer to distal and proximal parts of the LM backbone (32, 34), and 
MptC (Rv2181/NCgl2100) adds singular ␣(132)-Manp on lin-
ear LM (35, 36). In C. glutamicum, two other glycosyltrans-
ferases are present in tandem with MptC; whereas the role of 
MptD (NCgl2097) has been established as a second ␣(132) 
mannopyranosyltransferase involved in mannan branching of 
LM and LAM (35), the role of the third glycosyltransferase, 
NCgl2096, remains to be identified (supplemental Fig. 1a). The 
NCgl2096-encoded protein (referred to as AftE hereafter) con-
sists of eight transmembrane helices and two negatively 
charged loops (6 Asp, 2 Glu) (37), probably required for glyco-
syltransferase activity as observed for the arabinosyltransferase 
Emb (supplemental Fig. 1b) (38). Furthermore, BLAST analysis 
suggests close similarity to mycobacterial mannopyranosyl-
transferases MptC and PimE and arabinosyltransferases EmbA, 
EmbB, and EmbC, suggesting it to be a glycosyltransferase. 
To further understand the function of AftE, a non-replicative 
plasmid pK19mobsacB⌬aftE was constructed consisting of 13 
nucleotides of the 3Ј-end of aftE together with genomic 
upstream sequences and 36 nucleotides of the 5Ј-end together 
with genomic downstream sequences. This vector was used to 
transform C. glutamicum to kanamycin resistance (Kan 
r ), indi-
cating chromosomal integration. Subsequently, sucrose resist-
ance (Suc 
r ) clones were selected in a second round of positive 
selection, indicating loss of the vector-bound sacB function 
(30). From 12 Kan 
s and Suc 
r clones analyzed via PCR, seven had 
lost aftE, whereas in the remaining five, the wild type phenotype 
was restored. One of the representative clones with deleted aftE 
was selected and is referred to here as C. glutamicum ⌬aftE 
(supplemental Fig. 2a). In addition, aftE was cloned in a shuttle 
vector pEKEx2 and electroporated into C. glutamicum ⌬aftE to 
achieve the complemented strain, C. glutamicum ⌬aftE 
pEKEx2-Cg-aftE. C. glutamicum ⌬aftE was grown in liquid 
CGXII and BHI media, and its growth pattern was studied. 
C. glutamicum ⌬aftE had a slightly reduced growth rate of </p>

<p>Lipoarabinomannan Branching and Th Cell Differentiation </p>

<p>DECEMBER 28, 2012 • VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 53 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 44175 </p>

<p>0.32 Ϯ 0.01 h 
Ϫ1 in comparison with 0.39 Ϯ 0.02 h 
Ϫ1 of wild type 
C. glutamicum on CGXII (supplemental Fig. 2b). A similar 
trend was seen on BHI medium, suggesting that AftE is not vital 
for C. glutamicum but nevertheless is required to ensure opti-
mal growth. Such trends have been observed previously for 
other glycosyltransferases involved in cell wall synthesis like 
Emb, MptA, and AftA (32, 39, 40). 
Purification and General Features of Lipoglycans-Lipogly-
cans from C. glutamicum, C. glutamicum ⌬aftE, and C. glu-
tamicum ⌬aftE pEKEx2-Cg-aftE were extracted from delipi-
dated cells as described previously (31, 35). The crude 
lipoglycan extract was subjected to hydrophobic interaction 
chromatography followed by gel permeation chromatography 
for separation of LM and LAM, which were examined on 15% 
SDS-PAGE (Fig. 1a and supplemental Fig. 3a). Crude extracts 
from C. glutamicum showed the presence of LM (a mixture of 
phosphate-myo-inositol-anchored Cg-LM-A and glucouronic 
acid-anchored Cg-LM-B with identical mannan backbone (34, 
41)) and LAM, whereas lipoglycans from C. glutamicum ⌬aftE 
showed subtle differences in their migration on SDS-PAGE 
(Fig. 1a). The lipoglycan fraction from C. glutamicum ⌬aftE 
consisted of two species, one with higher molecular weight 
lipoglycan migrating faster than LAM from wild type and 
another lower molecular weight lipoglycan migrating similar to 
LM from wild type (Fig. 1a). Furthermore, MALDI-TOF-MS of </p>

<p>the lipoglycans showed that LAM from wild type C. glutami-
cum exhibited a broad unresolved peak centered at m/z 15,000, 
indicating a molecular mass of ϳ15 kDa with major molecular 
species consisting of 87 sugar units (based on the molecular 
mass of Ac 1 PIM 2 with three sugar units, m/z 1398). The 
MALDI-TOF-MS of higher molecular weight lipoglycan from 
C. glutamicum ⌬aftE showed an unresolved peak that centered 
around m/z 13,000, suggesting the loss of ϳ13 sugar units (Fig. 
1b). However, there were no major differences between LM 
from C. glutamicum and smaller molecular weight lipoglycan 
from C. glutamicum ⌬aftE (data not shown). The presence of a 
smaller molecular weight lipoglycan, which is similar to LM, 
and a higher molecular weight lipoglycan, which is shorter than 
the wild type LAM in C. glutamicum ⌬aftE, suggested that AftE 
is involved in the biosynthesis of LAM and not LM. Comple-
mentation of C. glutamicum ⌬aftE by transformation with 
plasmid pEKEx2-Cg-aftE restored the wild type phenotype 
(Fig. 1a). 
Molecular Composition and Linkage Analysis of Lipoglycans-
Purified lipoglycans were processed and converted into alditol 
acetates, and their glycosyl composition was determined by gas 
chromatography (GC). Based on 1 inositol per molecule of 
LAM, the molecular composition of LAM from wild type 
C. glutamicum was determined. It yielded a ratio of 1 inositol, 
20 arabinose, and 65 mannose residues, which is in accordance 
with our previous studies (Fig. 2a) (31, 35). In addition, LM 
from wild type C. glutamicum consists of 28 sugars with a 
molecular ratio of 1 inositol (for Cg-LM-A) or 1 glucouronic 
acid (for Cg-LM-B) over 27 mannose units (32, 41). This obser-
vation, which was overlooked in previous studies, suggests that 
in comparison with LM, LAM has a larger mannan domain 
made up of ϳ65 mannose residues, which might be due to 
extended activities of MptA, MptC, and MptD (35). Surpris-
ingly, higher molecular weight lipoglycan from C. glutamicum 
⌬aftE showed a complete absence of the arabinan peak and a 
ratio of 1 inositol to 74 mannoses, a reduction of 13 sugar units 
in comparison with LAM from wild type C. glutamicum (Fig. 
2a). The complete absence of the arabinan peak should have 
resulted in the loss of 20 arabinose units instead of 13 units, 
suggesting that the loss of arabinan units was compensated by 
some additional mannosylation of LAM intermediate, probably 
by MptC and MptD. This may be due to a greater availability of 
branching sites generated due to deletion of aftE. Due to the 
absence of arabinose and hypermannosylation, this molecule is 
here referred to as hypermannosylated lipomannan (hLM). 
The glycosyl linkages present in each species of lipoglycans 
were analyzed by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry 
(GC-MS) by per-O-methylated alditol acetate derivatives pre-
pared from purified lipoglycans. LAM from wild type C. glu-
tamicum indicated a normal profile of glycosidic linkages cor-
responding to t-Ara (34%), t-Man (15%), 6-Man (10%), 2-Man 
(17%), and 2,6-Man (24%). However, mutant hLM from C. glu-
tamicum ⌬aftE was found to be completely devoid of t-Ara 
branching residues and possessed a significant increase in the 
amount of t-Man (39%), 6-Man (5%), 2-Man (18%), and 2,6-
Man (38%) (Fig. 2b). Linkage analysis of LM from C. glutami-
cum ⌬aftE suggested a slightly increased branching degree, </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Lipoglycan profiles of C. glutamicum, C. glutamicum ⌬aftE, and 
C. glutamicum ⌬aftE pEKEx2-aftE. a, lipoglycans were extracted as 
described under "Experimental Procedures," analyzed using SDS-PAGE, and 
visualized by Pro-Q emerald glycoprotein stain (Invitrogen). Lipoglycan pro-
files are represented with standard molecular mass markers of glycoproteins 
of 180, 82, 42, and 18 kDa. b, MALDI-TOF-MS spectra of LAM from C. glutami-
cum and hLM from C. glutamicum ⌬aftE. For this, 2,5-dihydrobenzoic acid was 
used as a matrix, and the spectra were acquired in the linear negative mode 
with delayed extraction. Lipoglycans were extracted from delipidated cells as 
described previously (31, 32) and treated with H 2 O 2 before immunological 
assays to remove any endotoxin contamination (13) and to yield a negative 
Limulus amebocyte lysate test using E-TOXATE 
TM (Sigma-Aldrich). </p>

<p>Lipoarabinomannan Branching and Th Cell Differentiation </p>



<p>VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 53 • DECEMBER 28, 2012 </p>

<p>ϳ87% in comparison with 75% of LM from wild type C. glu-
tamicum (data not shown). 
In conclusion, by deleting AftE, we obtained a hypermanno-
sylated intermediate of lipoglycans, devoid of singular arabinan 
(supplemental Fig. 3b). Next we investigated whether the bio-
logical activity of this structure is different from that of LAM 
from wild type C. glutamicum, particularly in what concerns 
the modulation of immune responses via TLR2. We focused 
our study on wild type LAM versus hLM, because these two 
molecules differ in arabinan branching and degree of manno-
sylation. Furthermore, the LM from wild type C. glutamicum is 
dominated by monoacylated glucouronic acid-anchored LM 
(Ͼ90%) and has a poor TLR2 activity and therefore has not been 
included in this study (data not shown). 
Arabinose Branching of LM Impacts T Helper Cell 
Differentiation-Several factors determine the polarization of 
Th cell differentiation, including the engagement of specific 
TLRs (42). The impact of structural variations of LAMs in 
CD4 
ϩ Th cell differentiation has not been addressed before. 
Taking advantage of the purified wild type LAM and hLM from </p>

<p>C. glutamicum and C. glutamicum ⌬aftE, respectively, we 
addressed this issue. For this, primary mouse bone marrow-
derived DC were co-cultured with purified CD4 
ϩ T cells, from 
OVA TCR transgenic DO11.10 mice (BALB/c background), in 
the presence of LAM or hLM and of OVA peptide (OVA(323-
339), the antigen recognized by the transgenic TCR in DO11.10 
CD4 
ϩ T cells). The intracellular cytokine profile of the differ-
entiated CD4 
ϩ T cells obtained at the end of the co-culture was 
evaluated by flow cytometry. Because both Th1 and Th17 have 
been described in infections with mycobacteria, we focused our 
analysis on IFN-␥-and IL-17-producing T cells. Both LAM and 
hLM stimulated CD4 
ϩ T cell differentiation into IL-17-pro-
ducing cells, although in the presence of hLM the percentage of 
IL-17-producing CD4 
ϩ T cells reached significantly higher val-
ues (Fig. 3a). Also, hLM, but not LAM, increased the percentage 
of CD4 
ϩ T cells differentiating into Th1 cells producing IFN-␥, 
although this was a modest effect (Fig. 3a). The differences 
observed were most likely not due to different proliferation 
rates of Th cells, because the number of cells recovered at the 
end of culture was similar to all conditions (supplemental Fig. 
4). 
The differentiation of Th cells is controlled in part by the 
cytokine environment generated by the antigen-presenting cell. 
Indeed, the presence of IL-12 (composed of p40 and p35 mono-
mers) is essential for the development of Th1 responses (43), 
whereas IL-6 together with TGF-␤ in the microenvironment 
promotes Th17 differentiation (44). Th17 cells also require as a 
survival factor IL-23, a heterodimer of p40 and p19 (44). Fol-
lowing our previous findings (Fig. 3a), we sought to understand 
whether the differential impact of LAM and hLM in Th1 and 
Th17 cell differentiation was due to the cytokine profile 
induced by these molecules in DC. To test our hypothesis, we 
stimulated mouse bone marrow-derived DC (of BALB/c origin) 
with LAM or hLM and measured the production of IL-12, 
IL-23, and IL-6 24 h poststimulation. As shown in Fig. 3b, hLM 
is a stronger inducer of each of these cytokines, which is in line 
with its effect on Th cell differentiation. Of note, the same pat-
tern was observed for the induction of TNF and IL-10 (Fig. 3b). 
As expected, unstimulated DC produced only negligible to 
non-detected cytokine amounts (Fig. 3b). Our findings are in 
agreement with previously published results, reinforcing the 
idea that branching of LM and the addition of arabinose resi-
dues contribute to a more controlled cellular response in terms 
of cytokine production (13-15). However, we now additionally 
implicate variations on lipoglycan structures on the outcome of 
Th immune responses. 
Activation of DC by LAM and hLM Is TLR2-mediated-Next 
we investigated if TLR2 activation was implicated on the differ-
ential response of DC to LAM and hLM depended on TLR2 
activation. For that, we started by measuring the response of 
human HEK cells transfected with TLR2 to LAM and hLM. We 
observed that hLM, as compared with LAM, induced a signifi-
cantly increased activation of TLR2, as demonstrated by the 
enhanced TLR2-dependent IL-8 production by the HEK cells 
(Fig. 4a). Of note, hLM was also more potent in inducing IL-8 
than the TLR2 agonist Pam3CSK4 (Fig. 4a). We then stimu-
lated bone marrow-derived DC, generated from WT (BL6) or 
TLR2-deficient mice, with LAM or hLM and at different time </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Glycosyl composition and linkage analysis of lipoglycans from 
C. glutamicum and C. glutamicum ⌬aftE. a, for glycosyl compositional anal-
ysis, purified lipoglycans were hydrolyzed, reduced, and per-O-acetylated as 
described under "Experimental Procedures." Resulting alditol acetates were 
subjected for GC analysis. b, for determining the sugar linkages present in 
these lipoglycans species, lipoglycans were per-O-methylated, hydrolyzed, 
reduced, and per-O-acetylated. The resulting partially per-O-methylated, per-
O-acetylated alditol acetates were analyzed using GC-MS. The partially per-
O-methylated, per-O-acetylated alditol acetates were identified based on 
their characteristic alditol cleavage acetal profiles: t-Ara (m/z 118, 161), t-Man 
(m/z 118, 102, 145, 161, 162, 205), 2-Man (m/z 129, 130, 161, 190), 6-Man (m/z 
118, 129, 162, 189, 233), and 2,6-Man (m/z 129, 130, 189, 190). </p>

<p>Lipoarabinomannan Branching and Th Cell Differentiation </p>

<p>DECEMBER 28, 2012 • VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 53 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 44177 </p>

<p>points measured the transcription and production of IL-12p40, 
p35, p19, and IL-6 as well as of TNF and IL-10. Both transcrip-
tion and secretion of all cytokines tested were higher upon hLM 
stimulation of DC than upon LAM stimulation (Fig. 4, b and c). 
As expected, DC responded to LPS stimulation with the pro-
duction of several cytokines (Fig. 4c). Furthermore, TLR2 medi-
ated the recognition of both LAM and hLM, because cytokine 
expression and secretion by stimulated DC was clearly de-
creased in its absence (Fig. 4, b and c). Of note, PRRs other than 
TLR2 must also be involved in the recognition of LAM and 
hLM, because, in the absence of TLR2, cytokine expression was 
not fully abrogated (Fig. 4, b and c). Interestingly, the increased </p>

<p>potency of hLM to activate DC was not only reflected in the 
expression of proinflammatory cytokines, but also in the 
expression and production of the anti-inflammatory molecule 
IL-10 (Fig. 4, b and c). For both IL-6 and TNF, we also deter-
mined the response of WT DC to increasing doses of LAM or 
hLM. For each dose tested, the stimulatory activity of hLM was 
higher than that of LAM (supplemental Fig. 5). Moreover, a 
clear difference in the EC 50 of the two molecules was observed 
(285.1 Ϯ 2.0 g/ml versus 10.7 Ϯ 1.2 g/ml in the case of TNF 
and 114.3 Ϯ 1.4 g/ml versus 15.6 Ϯ 1.1 g/ml in the case of 
IL-6, for LAM versus hLM, respectively). These findings suggest 
that changes on LAMs are discriminated by TLR2, with the </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. hLM is a stronger inducer of Th17 cells than LAM. Naive CD4 
ϩ T cells from DO11.10 mice were co-cultured with BALB/c DC in the presence of 2.5 
M peptide OVA(323-339) and/or 10 g of C. glutamicum LAM or hLM for 10 days. a, graphs and dot plots of FACS data of IL-17 and IFN-␥ production by 
differentiated CD4 
ϩ T cells restimulated with PMA and ionomycin in the presence of brefeldin A. Each dot plot and column represents the mean of three wells. 
b, cytokine production by DC generated from BALB/c mice and stimulated for 24 h with LAM or hLM (10 g/ml) or left unstimulated (Medium) was evaluated 
by ELISA. In all cases, results are from one representative of two independent experiments. Each column represents the mean Ϯ S.E. (error bars) of three wells. 
Statistical significance was calculated with one-way ANOVA post hoc Tukey's t test (*, p Ͻ 0.05; **, p Ͻ 0.01; ***, p Ͻ 0.001). bld, below detection level. </p>

<p>Lipoarabinomannan Branching and Th Cell Differentiation </p>



<p>VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 53 • DECEMBER 28, 2012 </p>

<p>stronger induction of TLR2 via hLM impacting the various sig-
naling pathways triggered by this receptor and not only on 
those leading to proinflammatory cytokines. 
hLM Is a Stronger Inducer of in Vivo Immune Responses-
Considering our in vitro data showing that hLM is a stronger </p>

<p>inducer of DC responses, with an impact on Th cell differenti-
ation, we next investigated the effect of LAM versus hLM dur-
ing in vivo immune responses. For this, we injected mice (WT 
versus TLR2 
Ϫ/Ϫ ) intraperitoneally with purified LAM or hLM 
and measured, at different times postinjection, cytokine pro-</p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Cytokine production induced by LAM or hLM in vitro is TLR2-mediated. a, human HEK293 cells transfected with TLR2 were stimulated with 50 
g/ml LAM or hLM. Non-stimulated cells (Medium) or cells stimulated with 50 ng/ml Pam3CSK4 served as a controls. After 24 h at 37°C, supernatants were 
harvested and analyzed for IL-8 using ELISA. b, -fold induction of mRNA expression of IL-12p40, IL-12p35, IL-23p19, IL-6, TNF-␣, and IL-10 was evaluated by 
real-time PCR after 6 h of LAM or hLM stimulation (10 g/ml) of 1 ϫ 10 
6 BL/6 or TLR2 
Ϫ/Ϫ DC, relative to non-stimulated cells. Results are from one representative 
of two independent experiments. c, production of IL-6, TNF-␣, and IL-10 was evaluated by ELISA after 24 h of LAM, hLM (both at 10 g/ml), or LPS stimulation 
(25 ng/ml) of 1 ϫ 10 
6 BL/6 and TLR2 
Ϫ/Ϫ DC. Unstimulated DC (Medium) were included as a control. In all cases, results are from one representative of two 
independent experiments. Each column represents the mean Ϯ S.E. of three wells. Statistical significance was calculated with one-way ANOVA post hoc Tukey's 
t test (*, p Ͻ 0.05; **, p Ͻ 0.01; ***, p Ͻ 0.001). bld, below detection level. </p>

<p>Lipoarabinomannan Branching and Th Cell Differentiation </p>

<p>DECEMBER 28, 2012 • VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 53 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 44179 </p>

<p>duction at the site of stimulation. Total peritoneal cells were 
harvested, their RNA was extracted, and the relative mRNA 
expression of several cytokines was quantified by real-time 
PCR. In contrast to what was observed in vitro upon DC stim-
ulation with LAM or hLM, in vivo the majority of the molecules 
tested were induced in a TLR2-independent way. In fact, the </p>

<p>absence of TLR2 did not compromise TNF, IL-6, or CXCL2 
(the mouse homologue of human IL-8) expression induced by 
LAM or hLM (Fig. 5a). Lack of TLR2 did, however, contribute 
to a significant decrease in IL-10 induced in vivo by LAM or 
hLM (Fig. 5a). Of note, as compared with LAM, hLM induced a 
higher expression of the tested proinflammatory cytokines and </p>

<p>FIGURE 5. In vivo cytokine production induced in the peritoneal cavity by LAM and hLM injections requires recognition by PRRs other than TLR2. LAM 
and hLM (50 g in 100 l) were intraperitoneally injected into BL/6 WT or TLR2 
Ϫ/Ϫ mice, and PECs were collected 0, 4, and 8 h postinjection. a, mRNA was 
extracted from 5 ϫ 10 
5 PECs/animal, and IL-6, TNF-␣, IL-10, and CXCL2 mRNA expression was evaluated by RT-PCR. The data points represent the mean Ϯ S.E. 
(error bars) of five animals. b, the number of neutrophils was calculated by taking into account the percentage of neutrophils determined by flow cytometry 
(Ly6G 
ϩ GR1 
ϩ CD11b 
ϩ ) and the total number of cells collected. The data points represent the mean Ϯ S.E. of five animals. Results are from one representative 
of two independent experiments. Statistical significance was calculated with a two-way ANOVA test with 95% confidence (*, p Ͻ 0.05). </p>

<p>Lipoarabinomannan Branching and Th Cell Differentiation </p>



<p>VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 53 • DECEMBER 28, 2012 </p>

<p>also of the anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10 and the chemo-
kine CXCL2 (supplemental Fig. 6a). To investigate if the profile 
of TLR2-independent in vivo responses observed for LAM ver-
sus hLM was mainly due to the recruitment of new cells or was 
a feature of the resident PECs, we collected peritoneal cells 
from non-stimulated mice, activated them in vitro for 3 or 6 h 
with LAM or hLM, and analyzed the expression of cytokines in 
response to this acute stimulation. We found that hLM induced 
stronger responses than LAM by resident PECs and that, with 
the exception of IL-10, these responses were TLR2-independ-
ent (supplemental Fig. 7). 
Considering that we had detected high IL-8 production by 
HEK cells stimulated with hLM (Fig. 4a) and also high CXCL2 
in our in vivo model upon hLM administration (supplemental 
Fig. 6a), and because IL-8 is a molecule involved in neutrophil 
recruitment, we investigated changes in the numbers of neutro-
phils recruited upon LAM or hLM injection. Although both 
LAM and hLM induced an increase in the total number of 
recruited neutrophils throughout time, this increase was signif-
icantly more pronounced (ϳ50% more) in the case of hLM 
(supplemental Fig. 6b). Furthermore, this increase in neutro-
phil recruitment was independent of TLR2 (Fig. 5b). Of note, 
increasing the dose of administered LAM or hLM did not affect 
the differences observed (i.e. hLM was still a higher inducer of 
neutrophil recruitment than LAM) (supplemental Fig. 6c). The 
intraperitoneal injections of either LAM or hLM in BL/6 mice 
did not influence the total number of cells collected from the 
peritoneum at any of the time points tested (supplemental Fig. 
6d), suggesting that another cellular population was decreased 
as the influx of neutrophils happened. 
Collectively, our data suggest that hLM is a stronger inducer 
of in vivo and in vitro immune responses than LAM. Although 
in DC cultures, the effect of both LAM and hLM is mainly 
mediated by TLR2, additional PRRs to TLR2 must differentially 
recognize these structures in an in vivo setting. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>TLRs are among the best studied PRRs, with a recognized 
role in protecting the host against infection but also in contrib-
uting to acute and chronic inflammation, as well as to cancer, if 
inappropriately activated (45). The need for an appropriate reg-
ulation of TLR responses calls for a deep understanding of the 
structural interaction of TLRs with their ligands. We are par-
ticularly interested in understanding the structure-function 
relationship between TLR2 and lipoglycans, such as LM and 
LAM. A growing body of evidence strongly suggests that the 
structure of LM and LAM affects their interaction with TLR2, 
thus modulating the outcome of the innate immune response 
(11-15). Understanding the details of these interactions is 
essential in the context of various infections, including those by 
M. tuberculosis that represent the second most common infec-
tious cause of mortality and morbidity (46). Importantly, 
although still controversial, a role for TLR2 has been described 
during primary and secondary M. tuberculosis infection (18, 19, 
22, 23, 25, 47), and polymorphisms in the tlr2 gene have been 
associated with susceptibility to tuberculosis (48). 
Although the structural interactions of TLR2 with lipopro-
tein ligands have been addressed before by x-ray crystallogra-</p>

<p>phy (3, 4), those mediating the interaction of TLR2 with lipo-
glycans are less studied. The detailed study of structural-
functional interactions of lipoglycans and TLR2 requires the 
availability of different structural variants and mimics of lipo-
glycans. In M. tuberculosis, most of the genetic loci encoding 
for cell wall biogenesis are essential, which limits the availability 
of these molecules with variable structures. For this reason, we 
have in the past successfully used C. glutamicum as a "proof of 
principle" to understand the biosynthesis of LM and LAM in 
mycobacteria (8, 32, 34, 35, 49). The biosynthetic pathway of 
LAM is complex, involving a series of enzymes that coordi-
nately add complexity to the growing lipoglycan (8). Herein, we 
identified a novel putative glycosyltransferase, AftE, from 
C. glutamicum, which adds singular arabinose branches on 
LAM intermediate, resulting in a complete structure of LAM. 
Biochemical analysis of higher molecular weight lipoglycan 
from C. glutamicum ⌬aftE produced a shorter mutant lipogly-
can, hLM, in comparison with LAM from wild type. The glyco-
syl composition and linkage analysis of hLM suggested com-
plete absence of arabinan or t-Ara. Further biochemical 
analysis suggested that hLM is a novel lipoglycan with an 
extended mannose backbone with higher ␣(132)-Man units 
probably due to the hyperaction of MptC and MptD on branch-
ing sites created due to the absence of t-Ara residues in C. glu-
tamicum ⌬aftE. Cumulatively, our study sheds light on the syn-
thesis of an additional lipomannan-like lipoglycan, hLM, which 
may be either an aberrant LM accumulating as a result of lack of 
arabinosylation or a precursor of LAM before arabinosylation. 
Presumably, mature LM with mannophosphatidylinositol 
anchor undergoes further mannosylation in the ␣(136) direc-
tion to yield branching sites for ␣(132)-Man and ␣(132)-Ara. 
There is high probability that one or both of the ␣(136) man-
nopyranosyltransferases, MptA and MptB, add further 
␣(136)-Man units to the mature LM (32, 34), providing further 
branching sites for arabinose and mannose units for LAM (35). 
We therefore generated two different structural variants of 
LAM, useful for studying the structural-functional relationship 
between this class of pathogen-associated molecular pattern 
and TLR2. Our findings show that, independently of the dose 
tested, hLM significantly induced higher cytokine secretion by 
DC cultures than LAM. Moreover, hLM was also more efficient 
than LAM in activating DC, as reflected by its lower values of 
EC 50 . 
Furthermore, hLM was also a more potent inducer of in vivo 
responses than LAM, in a model of intraperitoneal injection. 
Our findings clearly implicate TLR2 as the main PRR involved 
in in vitro DC recognition of both LAM and hLM, thus suggest-
ing that the structure of lipoglycans, in particular the extent of 
arabinan branching, influences their interaction with TLR2 and 
modulates DC responses. These findings are in agreement with 
previously published studies (13-15). We also provide evidence 
that, as a result of differential DC activation by LAM and hLM, 
a Th17-biased T cell response was generated in response to a 
microenvironment rich in hLM. It will be important in the 
future to investigate the mechanistic basis for the stronger 
hLM-induced TLR2-mediated response observed in DC. It is 
possible that hLM interacts with TLR2 with a higher affinity 
than LAM or that it induces the recruitment of more intracel-</p>

<p>Lipoarabinomannan Branching and Th Cell Differentiation </p>

<p>DECEMBER 28, 2012 • VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 53 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 44181 </p>

<p>lular signaling adaptors. It will be interesting to pursue these 
studies to further understand how TLR2 ligands other than 
lipoproteins interact with TLR2 and initiate TLR2-mediated 
immune responses. Interestingly, our data suggest that DC may 
respond to LAM in a stronger way than HEK cells transfected 
with TLR2. This finding may provide some hints about the way 
lipoglycans interact with TLR2. It is tempting to speculate that 
LAM may preferentially interact with TLR2-TLR1 or TLR2-
TLR6 heterodimers (absent in HEK cells expressing TLR2 but 
existing in DC), whereas hLM may have the ability to trigger 
cellular responses via TLR2 homodimers. 
Our findings show that, similarly to what was observed in 
vitro, in vivo, lack of arabinose branching correlates with 
enhanced immune responses. However, in contrast to what was 
observed for DC cultures, in vivo, other PRRs in addition to 
TLR2 are certainly involved in the differential recognition of 
lipoglycans. It is possible that in our in vivo model, cells other 
than DC are the major sensors for LAM and hLM, thus explain-
ing the difference observed in DC cultures and in the peritoneal 
cavity. This issue remains to be investigated, with cells express-
ing DC-SIGN and mannose receptors being good candidates 
for the recognition of LAM and hLM (50, 51). Further studies 
will be of interest and important to clarify both of these issues: 
which cells and which PRRs recognize and differentiate lipogly-
can structural variants. Of note, acute stimulation of resident 
PECs with LAM or hLM induced cytokine expression inde-
pendently of TLR2, suggesting that at least peritoneal macro-
phages differ from DC in their way of recognizing and respond-
ing to lipoglycans. Neutrophils are also good candidate cells, 
because we observed an influx of neutrophils to the peritoneal 
cavity upon LAM or hLM administration. Our data open ave-
nues for the modulation of innate and acquired immune 
responses by taking advantage of different LAM structures. 
This is particularly important in the context of infections by 
M. tuberculosis, where an appropriate balance of Th1 versus 
Th17 cell responses is critical for bacterial control both in pri-
mary infection and vaccination and for pathology prevention 
(52, 53). It is possible that, by modulating TLR2 signals, a faster 
and more potent Th17 response is achieved, which has been 
shown to be fundamental for efficient vaccination (53). </p>

<p>Acknowledgments-We acknowledge scientific discussions with Drs. 
Anne O'Garra, Luke Alderwick, and Apoorva Bhatt. </p>



<p>Lipoarabinomannan Branching and Th Cell Differentiation </p>



<p>VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 53 • DECEMBER 28, 2012 </p>



<p>Lipoarabinomannan Branching and Th Cell Differentiation </p>

<p>DECEMBER 28, 2012 • VOLUME 287 • NUMBER 53 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 44183 </p>

</text></tei>