<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3693422" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective: To comprehensively examine pathology </p>

<p>test utilisation of 25-hydroxyvitamin D (25(OH)D) 
testing in each state of Australia to determine the cost 
impact and value and to add evidence to enable the 
development of vitamin D testing guidelines. </p>

<p>Design: Longitudinal analysis of all 25(OH)D </p>

<p>pathology tests in Australia. </p>

<p>Setting: Primary and Tertiary Care. 
Measurements: The frequency of 25(OH)D testing </p>

<p>between 1 April 2006 and 30 October 2010 coded for 
each individual by provider, state and month between 
2006 and 2010. Rate of tests per 100 000 individuals 
and benefit for 25(OH)D, full blood count (FBC) and 
bone densitometry by state and quarter between 2000 
and 2010. </p>

<p>Results: 4.5 million tests were performed between </p>

<p>1 April 2006 and 30 October 2010. 42.9% of 
individuals had more than one test with some 
individuals having up to 79 tests in that period. Of 
these tests, 80% were ordered by general practitioners 
and 20% by specialists. The rate of 25(OH)D testing 
increased 94-fold from 2000 to 2010. Rate varied by 
state whereby the most southern state represented the 
highest increase and northern state the lowest increase. 
In contrast, the rate of a universal pathology test such 
as FBC remained relatively stable increasing 2.5-fold. 
Of concern, a 0.5-fold (50%) increase in bone 
densitometry was seen. </p>

<p>Conclusions: The marked variation in the frequency of </p>

<p>testing for vitamin D deficiency indicates that large sums 
of potentially unnecessary funds are being expended. The 
rate of 25(OH)D testing increased exponentially at an 
unsustainable rate. Consequences of such findings are 
widespread in terms of cost and effectiveness. Further 
research is required to determine the drivers and cost 
benefit of such expenditure. Our data indicate that 
adoption of specific guidelines may improve efficiency 
and effectiveness of 25(OH)D testing. </p>

<p>for conditions that would never cause symp-
toms, resulting in unnecessary labelling and 
overtreatment of healthy individuals. </p>

<p>1   Testing and diagnosis for 25-hydroxyvitamin 
D deficiency (25(OH)D) are good examples. 
Testing and diagnosis has reached levels that 
raise serious questions as to the true preva-
lence of the disorder, the accuracy of testing 
methods, the cost benefit of diagnosis and 
treatment and whether this is being translated 
into improved health outcomes. In accord-
ance with other Australian studies, 
2 we 
recently reported that the prevalence 25 
(OH)D deficiency in an Australian popula-
tion was greater than expected, ranging from 
33% in summer months to 58% in late winter 
and spring months. 
3 In a separate study, we 
reported a massive increase in the frequency 
of testing for serum 25(OH)D levels over an 
11-year period in Australia. 
4 The rate of 
testing had increased from 40.6 (tests/ </p>

<p>ARTICLE SUMMARY </p>

<p>Article focus </p>

<p>▪ Overscreening and overdiagnosis for conditions 
that would never cause symptoms have the 
potential to lead to unnecessary labelling and 
overtreatment. 
▪ A dramatic increase in 25-hydroxyvitamin D 
testing is apparent in many developed nations. </p>

<p>Key messages </p>

<p>▪ There is a dramatic increase in testing across 
each quarter of the year and for individuals 
having up to four tests. 
▪ Many tests are potentially being ordered 
unnecessarily. 
▪ A review of testing guidelines is warranted. </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ Strengths of this study include the ability to 
include all vitamin D tests and diagnostic test for 
breast cancer in Australia over a 4.5-year period. 
▪ Limitations include the inability to obtain infor-
mation on the precise reason for vitamin D 
testing in individuals. </p>

<p>Bilinski K, Boyages S. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002955. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-002955 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>100 000 people) in the year 2000 to 3472.2 (tests/100 000 
people) in 2011. As a result, the cost of testing for 25 
(OH)D in Australia had increased from $1.0M in the year 
2000 to $95.6M in the year 2010, or on average 59% each 
year. 
4 Small reports from the USA and Canada have also 
indicated rising test trends and costs for 25(OH)D 
testing. 
5 Similarly, the UK has seen a sixfold increase in 
25(OH)D tests between 2007 and 2010. </p>

<p>6   The consequences of these findings are widespread in 
terms of better quantifying the magnitude of risk of 25 
(OH)D deficiency for a given population as well as 
gaining a better understanding as to the best way of 
testing for the disorder to avoid unnecessary cost and the 
potential for overdiagnosis and overtesting. The aim of 
this study was to examine the pattern of 25(OH)D testing 
in individual patients over a 4.5-year period in Australia 
so as to inform the development of testing guidelines. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Medicare is Australia's publically funded universal health 
insurance scheme. A comprehensive range of services, 
diagnostic procedures and tests is itemised as the Medicare 
Benefits Schedule (MBS). Every public or private patient 
in the ambulatory setting receives a reimbursement via 
Medicare for services provided by General Practitioners 
(GPs) or specialists. Analysis of MBS data provides informa-
tion on patterns and trends in healthcare utilisation. 
The MBS was analysed by using specific item numbers 
for 25(OH)D testing, bone densitometry (dual energy 
x-ray absorptiometry) and a commonly requested refer-
ence test, full blood count (FBC). The latter was used as 
a control for pathology test utilisation as it is unlikely to 
have been influenced by topical health trends. For indi-
viduals who had one to five tests, we used analysis of vari-
ance adjusting for multiple comparisons using 
Bonferroni post hoc tests to determine whether there 
was a significant difference in the mean number of indi-
viduals being tested each year by quarter (not including 
duplicate tests) for each test frequency. All analyses were 
performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> V.<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">19.0.1</rs> ( <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-date">July 2010</rs>). </p>

<p>Medicare provider data from 2006 to 2010 
To test the hypothesis that overtesting could explain the 
increased number of tests, we investigated the frequency 
of 25(OH)D testing (item number 66 608), 25(OH)D 
test data between 1 April 2006 and 30 October 2010. 
These data were obtained from the Information Strategy 
&amp; Delivery Section of Medicare Australia by personal 
request. Each individual was coded then de-identified by 
Medicare prior to the release of data. Date of test, pro-
vider (GP or Specialist) and location of test by state or 
territory: New South Wales (NSW), Victoria (VIC), 
Queensland (QLD), South Australia (SA); Western 
Australia (WA), Tasmania (TAS), Northern Territory 
(NT) was provided for each participant. Ethics approval 
was not required as Medicare data are freely available to 
the general public. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Frequency of testing 
Approximately 4.5 million 25(OH)D tests were con-
ducted in 2.4 million individuals between 1 April 2006 
and 30 October 2010. Of the individuals tested, 57.1% 
of individual cases had one test in that period and 
42.9% of cases had subsequent testing (table 1A). The 
frequency of tests for each individual varied between 1 
and 79 in that period (table 1B). Of the total number of 
tests, 54% of tests were initial tests and the remaining 
46% of tests were subsequent tests, 25% of which were 
for the second test, 11% the third test and 6% the forth 
test. The remaining 6% of 25(OH)D tests were for 
between 5 and 79 tests in that period. Although we were 
able to distinguish between GP versus specialist, the data 
were not specific enough to determine if the same pro-
vider was performing each test. 
The number of tests for each quarter increased each 
year from 2006 to 2010 for individuals who had between 
one and four tests whereby the most rapid increase was 
for individuals who had one test. When investigated 
according to quarter, the number of individuals having 
2-4 tests also increased from 2006 to 2010 for all quar-
ters. However, the highest number of tests was consist-
ently performed in the second quarter of each year </p>

<p>Table 1 Number of individuals according to the 
frequency of tests for each individual between 2006 and 
2010 </p>

<p>Number </p>

<p>Per 
cent </p>

<p>(A) Number of cases 
Cases (no repeated test) 
1365369 
57.1 
Case (with repeated 
testing) </p>

<p>1026483 
42.9 </p>

<p>Total cases 
2391852 
100 </p>

<p>Frequency of testing per 
individual </p>

<p>Number of 
individuals </p>

<p>Per 
cent </p>

<p>(B) Frequency of repeated testing 
1 
2391852 
54 
2 
1026483 
23 
3 
496225 
11 
4 
251306 
6 
5 
132173 
3 
6 
71534 
2 
7 
39857 
1 
8 
22717 
1 
9 
13165 
0 
10 
7790 
0 
11-20 
13007 
0 
21-30 
255 
0 
31-40 
219 
0 
41-50 
77 
0 
51-60 
28 
0 
61-70 
20 
0 
71-80 
11 
0 
Total duplicate tests 
4466719 
100 </p>



<p>Bilinski K, Boyages S. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002955. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-002955 </p>

<p>Evidence of overtesting for vitamin D in Australia </p>

<p>whereby the number of individuals who had one test 
exceeded 40 000 (figure 1A). Interestingly, the number 
of individuals who had one test in the third quarter was 
the lowest, yet the number of individuals who had two 
tests in that quarter was the highest, resembling the 
second quarter. When plotted as a whole, the seasonal 
periodicity showed that the highest number of tests was 
consistently performed in the third quarter ( June-
August) and lowest number in the fourth quarter 
(September-November), which are in the winter and 
spring months, respectively (figure 1B). 
For the first quarter of each year, the proportion of 
individuals who had two tests increased approximately 
linearly from 2% in 2006 to 9% in 2010 (table 2). 
Similarly, for individuals tested in the second quarter, 
who had two tests, the proportion increased linearly 
from 9% to 22%; those tested in the third quarter 
increased from 20% to 39%; while those tested in the 
fourth quarter remained relatively stable from 2006 to 
2010. For individuals who had three tests, the propor-
tion was the highest in each year for the third quarter, 
increasing from 3% in 2006 to 8% in 2009. </p>

<p>Provider 
The proportion of 25(OH)D tests ordered by GPs 
between 2006 and 2010 varied from 71% to 85% by state 
whereas specialists ordered between 15% and 27% of 
tests (figure 2A). The proportion of specialists who 
ordered tests relative to GPs was highest in the more 
northerly Australian states and territories (mean 
24.25%; QLD, NT, NSW and WA) declining to whereas 
the proportion of specialists who ordered tests in the 
southern states and territories decreased to less than 
20% (mean 17.25%; ACT, SA, VIC, TAS; figure 2A). The 
number of tests ordered per quarter between Q2, 2006 
and Q3, 2010 by GPs increased approximately linearly 
by 10.5-fold, whereas the number of tests ordered by spe-
cialists increased 5.6-fold (figure 2B). </p>

<p>Rise in testing over the past decade 
The national rate of services for 25(OH)D tests has 
been growing exponentially each year 37/100 000 indivi-
duals in 2000-3648/100 000 individuals in 2011 
(table 2). In comparison, the rate for a widespread 
routine pathology test such as a FBC, increased approxi-
mately 2.5-fold (3057-10 780/100 000) and testing for 
bone health, using bone densitometry approximately 
0.5-fold (50%) from 60 to 91/100 000 population; 
table 3. 
When investigating the relative increase in rate by 
states and territories, the rate of testing varied, whereby 
the biggest increase in testing rate occurred in the most 
southern state of TAS (424-fold; table 3). Among other 
southern states, the rate of testing increased 196-fold in 
SA, whereas in VIC, also at similar latitude, the rate 
increased only 79-fold, although baseline values were 
lower in VIC and TAS. Of interest, the relative increase 
in the rate of testing in other states varied between 32 
(ACT) and 81 (NT). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
The primary source of 25(OH)D for the majority of indi-
viduals is exposure of the skin to ultraviolet B radiation in 
the wavelength 290-315 nm. 
7 A serum test for 25(OH)D 
is the most accurate marker for assessing vitamin D 
status. 
8 Although there is contention as to the accuracy of 
various assays of 25(OH)D, 
9 these assays have become 
widely available to primary and specialised health practi-
tioners. This improved access to testing alone has led to 
an increase in testing and subsequently, increased detec-
tion of vitamin D deficiency (25(OH)D &lt;50 nmol/L). 
Hence, there has been an increasing number of studies 
which have been published showing a higher than 
expected prevalence of 25(OH)D deficiency. </p>

<p>2 10 11   The common definition of vitamin D deficiency is a 
serum 25(OH)D concentration less than 50 nmol/L, </p>

<p>12   where the risk of adverse bone effects is well established. </p>

<p>13   A growing body of research suggests that 25(OH)D defi-
ciency may also be involved in the development of numer-
ous chronic conditions including cancer, 
14 autoimmune </p>

<p>Figure 1 Mean number of individuals who had one test each 
by quarter and year. </p>

<p>Bilinski K, Boyages S. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002955. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-002955 </p>



<p>Evidence of overtesting for vitamin D in Australia </p>

<p>disease, 
15 cardiovascular disease 
16 17 and diabetes, 
18 as 
well as overall mortality 
19 and adverse pregnancy out-
comes, 
20 other than its role in maintaining adequate bone 
density. However, most of these findings are from observa-
tional studies, for which the evidence is considered inad-
equate in comparison to randomised controlled trials, and 
therefore have not been formally accepted by review 
bodies. Conclusions from a 2011 consensus conference 
aimed at defining the term 'evidence-based nutrition,' sug-
gests that when examining the effect of nutritional consti-
tuents on health outcomes, the totality of evidence be 
taken into account and it should be subject to it's own 
nutritional methodologies, as opposed to randomised 
trials which are required for pharmaceutical drugs. </p>

<p>21   Nevertheless, because of the new disease associations of 25 
(OH)D deficiency, some have proposed raising the diag-
nostic threshold for 25(OH)D sufficiency to a level greater 
than 75 nmol/L. 
The present study demonstrates that there has been 
an unsustainable growth in 25(OH)D testing across 
Australia over the last 11 years which reflects other 
nations. 
5 6 22 The consequences of our findings are 
widespread in terms of unnecessary cost and potential 
overdiagnosis. </p>

<p>Improved access to health services is unlikely to 
explain the rise in 25(OH)D testing as a testing for a 
common pathology test remained stable. 
4 It is more 
likely that the dramatic increase seen is a consequence 
of preventative testing linked to increased awareness of 
the health benefits of achieving sufficient 25(OH)D 
status. The greater rise in the rate of testing in states 
such as TAS suggests that awareness of the risk and 
implications of 25(OH)D deficiency is higher in these 
states as a consequence of TAS's high latitude relative to 
other Australian states and territories. The hypothesis 
that community awareness of the risk of 25(OH)D defi-
ciency is driving the rate of 25(OH)D testing in should 
be formally evaluated. 
As expected, due to the relatively higher proportion of 
GPs in comparison to specialists, a higher proportion of 
tests were conducted by GPs (figure 2). The over-
representation of tests in NSW and VIC is likely to be 
due to the larger proportion of physicians practicing in 
these states as well as their higher latitude relative to 
other states. 
Is the amount of money spent on 25(OH)D testing value 
for money? In order to answer this question, a better 
understanding of the drivers of 25(OH)D testing as well as </p>

<p>Figure 2 Vitamin D testing by provider between quarter 2, 2006 and quarter 3, 2010. </p>

<p>Table 2 Proportion of individuals having two, three or four tests number of initial tests for each year and quarter in 
comparison to individuals who had one test </p>

<p>Year and quarter (%) 
2006 
2007 
2008 
2009 
2010 
Number of tests 
1 
2 
3 
4 
1 
2 
3 
4 
1 
2 
3 
4 
1 
2 
3 
4 
1 </p>

<p>2 
2 
9 
20 
2 
8 
19 
27 
1 
8 
20 
31 
1 
9 
22 
35 
2 
10 
3 
0 
1 
3 
0 
1 
3 
6 
0 
1 
3 
7 
0 
1 
3 
8 
0 
1 
4 
0 
0 
1 
0 
0 
0 
1 
0 
0 
0 
2 
0 
0 
0 
2 
0 
0 </p>



<p>Bilinski K, Boyages S. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002955. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-002955 </p>

<p>Evidence of overtesting for vitamin D in Australia </p>

<p>what the optimal level of 25(OH)D is, is necessary. Drivers 
that may be relevant to the increase in 25(OH)D testing 
include the shifting threshold for adequate 25(OH)D 
levels, incidental diagnosis, failure to recognise normal 
fluctuations and poor timing of testing. 
1 It has also been 
reported that industries that benefit from expanded 
markets or physicians wanting to increase their patient 
pool are major influencers on the rate of testing. 
1 On the 
other hand, the increased rate of testing suggests that there 
may be value as a result of a greater awareness of the preva-
lence of 25(OH)D deficiency. 
Further studies are required to determine whether 
this increased testing translates into improved 25(OH)D 
status of the population and subsequent health out-
comes. A worrying trend, however, is that despite the 
magnitude of the rise in 25(OH)D testing this did not 
translate into increased testing for physiological end-
points associated with 25(OH)D deficiency, such as 
osteoporosis. 
23 24 over the long term. </p>

<p>25   Our data showing marked variation in the frequency of 
testing in individuals further support calls for the adoption 
of more specific 25(OH)D testing guidelines internation-
ally and in Australia. Implementation of clinical guidelines 
has been shown to improve the quality of healthcare by 
reducing morbidity, mortality and by increasing cost-
effectiveness. 
26 27 A recent position statement advises 
against retesting before 3 months because it may take 
2-5 months for serum levels of 25(OH)D to plateau. </p>

<p>28   Vitamin D supplementation has been shown to increase 
25(OH)D levels by approximately 17 nmol/L for each 
1000 IU each day, reaching a plateau around 8 weeks. </p>

<p>29   Simply advising against routine screening, as is the 
policy in Australia, is evidently inadequate in preventing 
excess testing. To illustrate by example, imposing guide-
lines to limit testing to three per annum: the first test to 
establish the diagnosis, the second to be performed 3 
months after supplementation, and the third test 6 
months after supplementation, to ensure that appropri-
ate 25(OH)D concentrations are being maintained. If 
this approach was adopted, based on the current data, 
552 509 tests would have not been undertaken at a saving 
of more than $20 million over the 4.5-year period. Still, 
others question the necessity of testing at all, and suggest 
that supplementation without testing in high-risk indivi-
duals is safe and effective. 
30 This is also reflected in the 
endocrine society's recommendations to supplement the 
general population with 1000-2000 IU 25(OH)D. </p>

<p>12   Although, serum 25(OH)D has been shown to vary con-
siderably among individuals following vitamin D supple-
mentation, whereby one study has shown that 6100 IU 
vitamin D supplementation would be required to bring 
97.5% of the population up to a serum 25(OH)D level of 
74 nmol/L without evidence of toxicity. </p>

<p>31   Supplementation without 25(OH)D testing is linked 
to varying viewpoints; for instance, it has been postulated 
that blanket supplementation would result in substantial </p>

<p>Table 3 Rate of services and relative increase in rate for 25-hydroxyvitamin D tests subsidised by Medicare between 2000 
and 2011 </p>

<p>Year 
2000 2001 2002 2003 2004 2005 2006 2007 
2008 
2009 
2010 
2011 </p>

<p>(A) Vitamin D services/100 000 by state 
NSW 
58 
120 
120 
157 
219 
294 
544 
967 
1766 
2684 
3735 
4233 
VIC 
69 
144 
144 
200 
345 
480 
891 
1632 
2804 
4070 
5195 
5530 
QLD 
23 
44 
44 
51 
74 
97 
174 
296 
581 
956 
1435 
1770 
SA 
19 
84 
84 
143 
224 
321 
521 
871 
1624 
2383 
3503 
3769 
WA 
66 
153 
153 
194 
241 
294 
462 
672 
1082 
1799 
2702 
3016 
TAS 
10 
34 
34 
48 
129 
163 
279 
488 
1048 
2216 
3576 
4058 
ACT 
160 
277 
277 
407 
551 
842 
1446 2317 
3178 
4155 
4798 
5316 
NT 
18 
26 
26 
49 
51 
79 
115 
175 
329 
734 
1226 
1520 
Australia 
37 
59 
80 
109 
171 
251 
397 
730 
1348 
2128 
3003 
3468 
FBC 
3057 8459 8735 8782 9044 9517 9939 10 212 10 382 10 480 10 496 10 781 
Bone densitometry 60 
72 
84 
83 
86 
101 
100 
99 
91 
89 
89 
91 
(B) Relative increase in services since 2000 
NSW 
0.0 
1.1 
1.1 
1.7 
2.8 
4.1 
8.4 
15.7 
29.5 
45.3 
63.4 
72.0 
VIC 
0.0 
1.1 
1.1 
1.9 
4.0 
6.0 
11.9 
22.7 
39.7 
58.0 
74.3 
79.2 
QLD 
0.0 
0.9 
0.9 
1.2 
2.2 
3.2 
6.6 
12.0 
24.4 
40.8 
61.7 
76.4 
SA 
0.0 
3.4 
3.4 
6.5 
10.7 
15.8 
26.3 
44.6 
84.0 
123.7 
182.3 
196.2 
WA 
0.0 
1.3 
1.3 
2.0 
2.7 
3.5 
6.0 
9.2 
15.4 
26.3 
40.0 
44.8 
TAS 
0.0 
2.6 
2.6 
4.1 
12.5 
16.1 
28.3 
50.1 
108.8 
231.0 
373.5 
423.9 
ACT 
0.0 
0.7 
0.7 
1.5 
2.4 
4.3 
8.0 
13.5 
18.8 
24.9 
28.9 
32.2 
NT 
0.0 
0.4 
0.4 
1.7 
1.8 
3.3 
5.3 
8.5 
16.9 
38.8 
65.4 
81.4 
Australia 
0.0 
0.6 
1.2 
2.0 
3.7 
5.9 
9.9 
19.0 
35.9 
57.3 
81.3 
94.0 
FBC 
0.0 
1.8 
1.9 
1.9 
2.0 
2.1 
2.3 
2.3 
2.4 
2.4 
2.4 
2.5 
Bone densitometry 0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.4 
0.4 
0.7 
0.7 
0.6 
0.5 
0.5 
0.5 
0.5 </p>

<p>FBC, full blood count; NSW, New South Wales; NT, Northern Territory; QLD, Queensland; SA, South Australia; TAS, Tasmania; VIC, Victoria; 
WA, Western Australia. </p>

<p>Bilinski K, Boyages S. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002955. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-002955 </p>



<p>Evidence of overtesting for vitamin D in Australia </p>

<p>reduction in global healthcare costs, 
32-34 whereas others 
have shown that 25(OH)D deficiency, combined with 
lack of monitoring, predicted increased inpatient health-
care costs. </p>

<p>35   CONCLUSION 
This study demonstrates an unsustainable rate of 
increase in 25(OH)D testing which is likely to reflect a 
growing awareness of the consequences of 25(OH)D 
deficiency on human health. However, our study also 
indicates that the lack of guidelines for testing leads to 
inappropriate testing. 
At present, there is no agreement as to the appropriate 
timing and frequency of testing for the diagnosis of 25 
(OH)D deficiency. Current recommendations are to test 
individuals at high risk of deficiency such as the elderly or 
dark skinned individuals, 
8 although routine testing is cur-
rently not recommended by the Australian Bone and 
Mineral Society 
36 or the American Endocrine Society. 
Additionally, repeated testing 3 months after a loading 
dose of 25(OH)D supplementation has been recom-
mended </p>

<p>37 38   ; however, there are no formal guidelines for 
subsequent monitoring of adequacy of replacement 
therapy for 25(OH)D deficiency in Australia or elsewhere. 
Further research is required to better determine the 
drivers of 25(OH)D testing and cost benefit of such 
expenditure, although our data indicate that the adoption 
of specific guidelines are warranted to improve the effi-
ciency of 25(OH)D testing. Such guidelines would neces-
sarily specify criteria for testing, such as diagnosis of 25 
(OH)D deficiency disease or other indication of likely 
having low 25(OH)D levels, including many types of 
cancer, cardiovascular disease, diabetes mellitus, dental 
caries, erectile dysfunction, obesity, osteoporosis, periodon-
tal disease, respiratory infections, pregnant women and 
those admitted to the hospital for any reason. 
15 As an alter-
native, current Australian vitamin D intake recommenda-
tions, which range from 200 to 800 IU, 
28 39 could be 
increased in order to increase the number of people with 
serum 25(OH)D concentrations aimed at optimal health. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements We would like to thank Medicare Australia for providing 
testing data by patient and specialist. </p>

<p>Contributors KB and SB were intimately associated with generating the 
research concept resulting in this publication. KB was primarily responsible 
for researching the literature context as presented in the introduction. KB was 
responsible for data extraction and analysis. KB and SB had full access to the 
data and were responsible for interpreting and presenting the results. SB 
contributed to preparing the publication manuscript by generating the first 
draft and KB by coordinating and editing further contributions and comments. 
KB and SB were responsible for preparing responses to journal comments 
and criticisms. All authors have read and approved the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding This project was internally funded by Westmead Breast Cancer 
Institute. </p>

<p>Competing interests KB and SB have support from Westmead Breast Cancer 
Institute and the eHealth NSW Initiative. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>





<p>Bilinski K, Boyages S. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002955. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-002955 </p>

<p>Evidence of overtesting for vitamin D in Australia </p>



<p>Bilinski K, Boyages S. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002955. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-002955 </p>



<p>Evidence of overtesting for vitamin D in Australia </p>

</text></tei>