<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3268728" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT Ribosomal S6 kinase 1 (RSK1) belongs to a family of proteins with two kinase 
domains. Following activation in the cytoplasm by extracellular signal-regulated kinases 
(ERK1/2), it mediates the cell-proliferative, cell-growth, and survival-promoting actions of a 
number of growth factors and other agonists. These diverse biological actions of RSK1 in-
volve regulation of both cytoplasmic and nuclear events. However, the mechanisms that per-
mit nuclear accumulation of RSK1 remain unknown. Here, we show that phosphorylation of 
RSK1 on S221 is important for its dissociation from the type Iα regulatory subunit of protein 
kinase A (PKA) in the cytoplasm and that RSK1 contains a bipartite nuclear localization se-
quence that is necessary for its nuclear entry. Once inside, the active RSK1 is retained in the 
nucleus via its interactions with PKA catalytic subunit and AKAP95. Mutations of RSK1 that 
do not affect its activity but disrupt its entry into the nucleus or expression of AKAP95 forms 
that do not enter the nucleus inhibit the ability of active RSK1 to stimulate DNA synthesis. 
Our findings identify novel mechanisms by which active RSK1 accumulates in the nucleus and 
also provide new insights into how AKAP95 orchestrates cell cycle progression. </p>

<p>Ribosomal S6 kinase 1 (RSK1) is a member of a family of proteins 
with two kinase domains (Frodin and Gammeltoft, 1999; Anjum and 
Blenis, 2008). Among the four isoforms of RSKs that are products of 
different genes, RSK1, RSK2, and RSK3 share significant sequence 
similarity; RSK4 is longer than the other isoforms and may also be 
functionally different (Frodin and Gammeltoft, 1999; Dummler et al., 
2005; Anjum and Blenis, 2008). Despite their similarity, RSK1, RSK2, 
and RSK3 are not functionally redundant. Thus, although RSK1 and 
RSK3 show normal overlapping expression patterns with RSK2 in </p>

<p>brains of patients with Coffin-Lowry syndrome, in which RSK2 is mu-
tated, the functions of the mutant RSK2 are not replaced by the 
other isoforms (Jacquot et al., 1998). Likewise, whereas RSK1 can 
differentiate PC12 cells, RSK2 is not effective (Silverman et al., 2004), 
and RSK1, but not the other isoforms, regulates lung cancer cell 
motility and metastasis (Lara et al., 2011). 
The RSKs are the immediate downstream effectors of extracel-
lular signal-regulated kinases 1/2 (ERK1/2) and mediate the growth-
promoting, proliferative, and antiapoptotic actions of growth factors 
and agonists that activate this pathway (Frodin and Gammeltoft, 
1999; Anjum and Blenis, 2008; Cargnello and Roux, 2011). In keep-
ing with their role as positive modulators of cell proliferation and 
growth, RSK1 and RSK2 levels are elevated in ductal and lobular 
human breast cancer tissues, as well as in 50% of prostate tumors, 
and inhibition of RSK1 and RSK2 activities results in decreased cell 
growth (Clark et al., 2005; Smith et al., 2005). RSK1 also plays a pro-
found role in neuronal differentiation, as demonstrated by the find-
ing that constitutively active RSK1 is sufficient to elicit neuronal dif-
ferentiation of PC12 cells (Silverman et al., 2004). This observation 
also suggests that the prolonged ERK1/2 activation that is necessary 
for PC12 cell differentiation (Vaudry et al., 2002) is mediated by ac-
tivating the downstream kinase RSK1. The role of RSK1 in promoting 
cell survival has been demonstrated using dominant-negative forms </p>

<p>Monitoring Editor 
J. Silvio Gutkind 
National Institutes of Health </p>

<p>Received: Jul 29, 2011 
Revised: Oct 24, 2011 
Accepted: Nov 22, 2011 </p>

<p>This article was published online ahead of print in MBoC in Press (http://www 
.molbiolcell.org/cgi/doi/10.1091/mbc.E11-07-0658) on November 30, 2011. 
Address correspondence to: Tarun B. Patel (tpatel7@lumc.edu). </p>

<p>© 2012 Gao et al. This article is distributed by The American Society for Cell Biol-
ogy under license from the author(s). Two months after publication it is available 
to the public under an Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported 
Creative Commons License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0). 
"ASCB ® ," "The American Society for Cell Biology ® ," and "Molecular Biology of 
the Cell ® " are registered trademarks of The American Society of Cell Biology. </p>

<p>Abbreviations used: AKAP, PKA-anchoring proteins; BrdU, bromodeoxyuridine; 
CTK, C-terminal kinase domain; EGF, epidermal growth factor; ERK, extracellular 
signal-regulated kinase; GFP, green fluorescent protein; HA, hemagglutinin; LMB, 
leptomycin B; NLS, nuclear localization sequence; NTK, N-terminal kinase do-
main; PDK1, phosphoinositide-dependent kinase-1; PKA, protein kinase A; PKAc, 
catalytic subunit of PKA; PKARIα, type Iα regulatory subunit of PKA; RSK, p90 
ribosomal S6 kinase; siRNA, small interfering RNA. </p>

<p>504 | X. Gao et al. </p>

<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>sequence (RKXXS/T) and is autophosphory-
lated by the NTK with a resultant dissocia-
tion of ERK (Roux et al., 2003). On activation 
of RSK1 in the cytoplasm and at the plasma 
membrane, the fully active RSK1 localizes to 
the nucleus (Richards et al., 2001). 
In recent studies from our laboratory, we 
showed that RSK1 forms a complex with the 
type I cAMP-dependent protein kinase 
(PKA). By binding the pseudosubstrate site 
on the type Iα regulatory subunit of PKA 
(PKARIα), the inactive RSK1 competes with 
the catalytic subunit of PKA (PKAc) for inter-
actions with PKARIα, and, thereby, inactive 
RSK1 can activate PKA in a cAMP-indepen-
dent manner (Chaturvedi et al., 2006; Gao 
et al., 2010). On the other hand, active 
RSK1, via its C-terminal 13 residues, binds 
to PKAc, increasing the interactions of PKAc 
with PKARIα and decreasing the ability of 
cAMP to activate PKA (Chaturvedi et al., 
2006; Gao and Patel, 2009). This latter inter-
action requires phosphorylation of Ser-732 
on RSK1 (Gao and Patel, 2009). The phos-
phorylation of Ser 732 on RSK1 also results 
in the dissociation of ERK1/2 (Roux et al., 
2003; Gao and Patel, 2009). By associating 
with the subunits of PKA, the inactive and 
active RSK1 ensure their indirect interactions 
with A-kinase-anchoring proteins (AKAPs) 
such as D-AKAP1 (dual-specificity AKAP1; 
Chaturvedi et al., 2006, 2009). Of interest, 
dissociation of the RSK1 from its complex 
with AKAPs by different approaches, includ-
ing silencing of PKARIα or use of cell-per-
meable peptides that interfere with PKARIα/ 
AKAP interactions, decreases the nuclear 
content of active RSK1 and increases its 
amounts in the cytosol, with a resultant in-
crease in phosphorylation of its cytosolic 
substrates, such as Bcl-xL/Bcl-2-associated 
death promoter, and augmenting of its anti-
apoptotic actions (Chaturvedi et al., 2006, 
2009; Gao et al., 2010). However, the mech-
anisms that regulate the nuclear localization of RSK1, and for that 
matter, its other isoforms, remain unknown. 
Therefore the aims of this study were 1) to elucidate the mecha-
nisms by which active RSK1 enters the nucleus, 2) to identify the 
AKAP(s) that retain active RSK1 in the nucleus, and 3) to understand 
the functional consequences of impeding active RSK1 entry or re-
tention in the nucleus. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Phosphorylation of Ser-221 on RSK1 is necessary to 
dissociate it from PKARIα and permit its nuclear localization </p>

<p>Because previous reports suggested that the fully active RSK1 is lo-
calized to the nucleus, initially, we determined whether the last 
phosphorylation (Ser-221 in the NTK; Figure 1A) that fully activates 
RSK1 is necessary for its nuclear localization. Ser-221 is phosphory-
lated by PDK1 (Jensen et al., 1999). Therefore, as the first approach, 
we determined whether inhibition of PDK1 attenuated phosphoryla-
tion of S221 and altered the nuclear localization of RSK1. As shown </p>

<p>of RSK1 to antagonize the cell survival that was promoted by active 
forms of mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase alleles (Bonni et al., 
1999; Shimamura et al., 2000), as well as some of our recent studies 
(Chaturvedi et al., 2006, 2009; Gao et al., 2010). 
The activation of RSK1 depends on the docking of ERK1/2 to the 
C-terminus (Gavin and Nebreda, 1999; Smith et al., 1999; Figure 1A). 
Following docking onto RSK1, ERK1/2 phosphorylates T573 in the 
activation loop of the C-terminal kinase (CTK), as well as T359 and 
S363 in the linker region that joins the N-terminal kinase (NTK) and 
CTK (Frodin and Gammeltoft, 1999). Phosphorylation of T573 acti-
vates the CTK, and this domain can then phosphorylate S380 in the 
linker region (Frodin and Gammeltoft, 1999). Phosphorylation of 
S380 provides a docking site for phosphoinositide-dependent kinase 
1 (PDK1) (Frodin et al., 2000, 2002), which can then phosphorylate 
S221 in the activation loop of the NTK (Jensen et al., 1999; Richards 
et al., 1999) and permits RSK1 to phosphorylate its downstream sub-
strates (Frodin and Gammeltoft, 1999). Serine 732 (S749 in avian 
RSK1) in the ERK1/2 docking site also represents a RSK1 consensus </p>

<p>FIGuRE 1: RSK1 phosphorylation by PDK1 is required for its nuclear translocation. 
(A) Schematic of phosphorylation sites on rat RSK1. (B) Top two rows, serum-starved HeLa cells 
were treated with and without EGF (100 nM) for 10 min and the localization of total RSK1 was 
monitored with anti-RSK1 antibody; 4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole staining shows nuclei. Bottom 
four rows, the PDK1 inhibitor BX795 inhibits nuclear translocation of RSK1. HeLa cells were 
treated as described above with and without overnight preincubation with 0.5 μM BX795. The 
localization of active RSK1 was monitored with anti-phospho-T573-RSK antibody. (C) BX795 
inhibits phosphorylation of RSK1 on S221 and S732. Cells were treated as in B. After 
immunoprecipitation with anti-RSK1 antibody, Western analyses of the immune complexes were 
performed with anti-phospho RSK antibodies. Scale bar, 10 μm. Representative data from three 
independent experiments are shown. </p>

<p>Volume 23 February 1, 2012 </p>

<p>Nuclear localization and retention of RSK1 | 505 </p>

<p>in Figure 1B (top two rows), in the absence 
of epidermal growth factor (EGF), endoge-
nous RSK1, detected by the anti-RSK1 anti-
body, was localized mainly in the cytoplasm, 
with very little being present in the nucleus. 
However, after EGF treatment, considerable 
increase in the nuclear localization of the en-
dogenous RSK1 was observed (Figure 1B, 
top two rows). Similarly, use of anti-phos-
pho-Thr-573 antibody showed that there is 
very little active phospho-Thr-573 RSK1 in 
serum-starved HeLa cells (Figure 1B, third 
row). On stimulation with EGF, the endoge-
nous phospho-RSK1 in HeLa cells was local-
ized mainly in the nucleus, as reported be-
fore (Richards et al., 2001), and exposure of 
cells to the PDK1 inhibitor BX795 decreased 
the EGF-mediated nuclear localization of 
RSK1 (Figure 1B, bottom three rows). Of 
note, the PDK1 inhibitor did not affect RSK1 
phosphorylation in the activation loop (Thr-
573) of the C-terminal kinase, the linker re-
gion (Thr-359/Ser-363), and Ser-380, which 
forms the PDK1-binding site (Figure 1C). 
However, consistent with its role as PDK1 
inhibitor, BX795 inhibited the phosphoryla-
tion of Ser-221 (the PDK1 site) and Ser-732, 
the site on RSK1 that is autophosphorylated 
by its NTK (Roux et al., 2003; Figure 1C). 
These data suggest that Ser-221 phosphory-
lation is necessary for nuclear localization of 
RSK1. To more carefully examine the role of 
Ser-221 in nuclear localization of RSK1, we 
expressed hemagglutinin (HA)-tagged wild-
type RSK1 and HA-RSK1 harboring substitu-
tions of Ser-221 with either Ala (S221A), 
which cannot be phosphorylated, or Asp 
(S221D) to mimic phosphorylation at this 
site. As shown in Figure 2, A and B, upon 
EGF treatment of HeLa cells, the wild-type 
RSK1 localized to the nucleus. However, 
EGF did not enhance nuclear accumulation 
of the S221A mutant of RSK1. On the other 
hand, like its wild-type counterpart, the 
S221D form of RSK1 was localized to the 
nucleus after EGF treatment of HeLa cells 
(Figure 2, A and B). Consistent with the role 
of S221 phosphorylation in the activation of 
RSK1, in in vitro kinase assays, the S221A 
form of RSK1 was inactive and did not ex-
hibit any kinase activity (Figure 2C). In con-
trast, the S221D form of RSK1 was activated 
upon EGF addition but was not active with-
out EGF treatment of HeLa cells (Figure 2C). 
This is consistent with the findings that in 
addition to phosphorylation of S221 (or a 
negative charge at this position) in the NTK, 
the phosphorylation of other sites in the 
linker region on RSK1 is necessary for acti-
vation of the NTK (Dalby et al., 1998; Gross 
et al., 2001). Of note, by immunocytochem-
istry, the active endogenous RSK1 (detected </p>

<p>FIGuRE 2: Phosphorylation of RSK1 on S221 dissociates it from PKARIα to permit its 
nuclear translocation. (A, B) Wild-type and S221D mutant, but not the S221A form, of 
RSK1 translocate to nuclei after EGF treatment as shown by immunocytochemistry 
(A) and cellular fractionation (B). HeLa cells were transfected to express HA-RSK1 or its 
mutants. After serum starvation, cells were treated with or without 100 nM EGF for 
10 min. The HA-RSK1 localization was monitored with anti-HA antibody (A). In B, the 
amounts of HA-RSK1 or its mutants in cytosolic fraction (C) or nuclear fraction (N) were 
analyzed by Western blotting. PLCγ, cytosol marker; histone 1, nuclear marker. (C) Kinase 
activities of HA-RSK1 or its mutants. HA-tagged wild-type and its mutant RSK1 forms were 
immunoprecipitated with anti-HA antibody from HeLa cells treated with or without EGF 
for 10 min and then were subjected to the in vitro kinase assays. (D) Cell-permeable 
peptide PS, corresponding to the pseudosubstrate region of PKARIα, dissociates wild-
type and S221A mutant of RSK1 from their association with PKARIα. Serum-starved HeLa 
cells were preincubated with or without 2 μM peptide PS for 10 min and then treated with 
or without EGF for 10 min. PKARIα in the lysates was pulled down with cAMP-agarose, 
and presence of HA-RSK1 or its mutant was monitored. (E) Peptide PS allows RSK1 S221A 
to translocate to the nuclei in the presence of EGF. HeLa cells were treated as in D. 
HA-RSK1 localization was monitored with anti-HA antibody. All data presented are 
representatives from three independent experiments. Values in B and C are the 
mean ± SE (n = 3). Statistical significance was determined by Student's t test analyses. 
Scale bar, 10 μm. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>phorylation of Ser-221 on RSK1 is necessary 
for its dissociation from PKARIα and that, 
once released from this interaction, RSK1 
can enter the nucleus. </p>

<p>Nuclear localization of RSK1 requires 
importin-mediated transport </p>

<p>Because a number of large proteins translo-
cate to the nucleus via importin α/β-mediated 
transport, we determined whether this 
mechanism was involved in the nuclear lo-
calization of endogenous, active RSK1 in 
HeLa cells. For this purpose, we used the 
recently described cell-permeable peptide 
Bimax1 (sequence, RRRRPRKRPLEWDEEP-
PRKRKRLW), which binds with importin α 
and inhibits nuclear localization of proteins 
via an importin α/β-mediated pathway 
(Kosugi et al., 2008). Pretreatment of HeLa 
cells with Bimax1 for 20 min abrogated the 
nuclear localization of RSK1 (Figure 3A). The 
lack of endogenous RSK1 localization to the 
nucleus in the presence of Bimax1 was not 
due to changes in the ability of EGF to phos-
phorylate RSK1 on its various sites and acti-
vate it (Figure 3B). These data suggested 
that nuclear localization of RSK1 requires im-
portin α/β-mediated nuclear transport. </p>

<p>RSK1 contains a bipartite nuclear localization sequence </p>

<p>Importin α/β-mediated transport of proteins requires a nuclear lo-
calization sequence (NLS). A close examination of the RSK1 se-
quence revealed the presence of a 17-residue-long "putative" bi-
partite NLS (K 316 RHIFYSTIDWNKLYRR 332 ) at the interface of the 
NTK and linker region on RSK1 (Figure 4A). Because the basic resi-
dues on the N-and C-termini of the bipartite NLS are functionally 
important, we made substitutions of the N-terminal basic residues 
K316/R317 with Ala (NM) or the C-terminal basic residues K328/ 
R331/R332 with Ala (CM), as well as substitutions of all basic resi-
dues in both the N-and C-terminals in the "putative" NLS with Ala 
(NM/CM; Figure 4A). In response to EGF treatment of cells, the 
phosphorylation of T573, T359/S363, or S380 on the various mutant 
forms of RSK1 was not altered (Figure 4B). However, the NM/CM 
form of RSK1 was not phosphorylated on S221 (Figure 4B). Consis-
tent with the requirement for S221 phosphorylation being important 
for activation of RSK1, the NM/CM form of RSK1 that was immuno-
precipitated from cells treated with EGF did not exhibit elevation in 
kinase activity (Figure 4C). On the other hand, although the NM 
mutant of RSK1 was phosphorylated on S221, it was devoid of ki-
nase activity (Figure 4C), suggesting that the substitution of K316/ 
R317 with Ala in the extreme C-terminus of NTK (Figure 4A) dis-
rupted the structure of this kinase domain, rendering it inactive. The 
kinase activity of the CM mutant of RSK1 was enhanced by EGF 
treatment (Figure 4C). Another interesting finding in these experi-
ments is the observation that EGF increased phosphorylation of 
S732 on the NM/CM mutant of RSK1 that is not phosphorylated on 
S221 and is also not activated by the growth factor (Figure 4, B and 
C). This suggests that phosphorylation of S732 on RSK1 can occur 
in-trans and, in the case of the NM/CM RSK1, possibly via activation 
by EGF of the endogenous RSK1. 
Next, by confocal microscopy, we tested the ability of the HA-
tagged wild-type or mutant forms of RSK1 harboring substitutions </p>

<p>by anti-phospho-Thr-573 antibody) is localized mainly in the nu-
cleus, whereas significant amounts of total endogenous or ex-
pressed RSK1 are still observed in the cytoplasm after EGF treat-
ment (Figure 1B, top two rows, and Figure 2A). This is because the 
amount of active RSK1 is only a fraction of the total RSK1 and its 
translocation to the nucleus creates a higher concentration in the 
nucleus than the larger cytoplasmic compartment. Because of this 
concentration difference, it is difficult to clearly see the cytoplasmic 
active RSK1 by immunocytochemistry with anti-phospho-T573 an-
tibody. However, by cell fractionation (see Figure 6C later in this 
paper) and ImageJ analyses (see Figure 5 later in this paper), active 
endogenous RSK1 is detectable in the cytoplasm. 
Although, at first sight, the data in Figure 1, as well as in Figure 2, 
A-C, suggest that phosphorylation of S221 on RSK1 is necessary for 
its nuclear localization, we recently showed that S221 phosphoryla-
tion or substitution of Ser-221 with Asp on RSK1 also dissociates 
RSK1 from its interactions with the pseudosubstrate region of PKARIα 
(Gao et al., 2010). Thus it is possible that phosphorylation of Ser-221 
on RSK1 is required to release the enzyme from its interactions with 
PKARIα in the cytoplasm to then permit its entry into the nucleus. To 
address this possibility, we took advantage of our previously pub-
lished findings that a cell-permeable, palmitoylated peptide corre-
sponding to the pseudosubstrate region of PKARIα (peptide PS) dis-
sociates it from RSK1 (Gao et al., 2010). Essentially, we determined 
whether the cell permeable peptide PS that interferes with RSK1/ 
PKARIα interactions dissociates the S221A form of RSK1 from PKARIα 
and permits its entry into the nucleus. As shown in Figure 2D, prein-
cubation of HeLa cells with peptide PS decreased the association of 
RSK1 with both wild-type and S221A forms of RSK1. Moreover, 
whereas EGF treatment of cells did not result in nuclear localization 
of S221A RSK1, pretreatment of cells expressing this form of RSK1 
with peptide PS permitted its nuclear localization upon EGF addition 
(Figure 2E). Collectively, the data in Figure 2 demonstrate that phos-</p>

<p>FIGuRE 3: Nuclear translocation of RSK1 requires importin-mediated transport. (A) The 
importin inhibitor peptide Bimax1 decreases nuclear localization of RSK1. After overnight serum 
starvation, HeLa cells were incubated with or without 20 μM Bimax1 for 20 min prior to 
treatment with 100 nM EGF for 10 min. (B) Bimax1 does not alter EGF-mediated 
phosphorylation of RSK1 on the various sites. RSK1 from lysates of cells treated as in A was 
immunoprecipitated with anti-RSK1 antibody, and the immune complexes were probed with 
anti-phospho-RSK antibodies. Scale bar, 10 μm. Representative data from three independent 
experiments are shown. </p>

<p>Volume 23 February 1, 2012 </p>

<p>Nuclear localization and retention of RSK1 | 507 </p>

<p>FIGuRE 4: Nuclear translocation of RSK1 requires its intact NLS sequence. (A) Schematic of the NLS sequences of RSK1 
and its mutants. (B) Phosphorylation of wild-type and NLS mutants of RSK1 on the various sites. HeLa cells were 
transfected to express HA-RSK1 or its mutants and then treated with or without EGF (100 nM) for 10 min. Cell lysates 
were immunoprecipitated with anti-HA antibody, and then the IP complex was probed with anti-phospho-RSK 
antibodies. Representative data from three similar experiments are shown. (C) Kinase activity of the wild-type and NLS 
mutants of RSK1. After treatment of cells as in B, and following immunoprecipitation of HA-tagged RSK1 forms, the 
RSK1 kinase activity was determined in in vitro kinase activity assays. The blot below shows the amounts of HA-RSK1 or 
its mutants in the immune complex. The results shown are representative of three experiments performed in duplicates. 
(D) Mutations in the NLS of RSK1 abolish its nuclear translocation. HeLa cells were transfected to express HA-RSK1 or 
its mutant forms harboring substitutions in its NLS. After starvation, cells were treated with or without EGF (100 nM) for 
10 min. The localization of HA-RSK1 was monitored with anti-HA antibody. Lower panel, the quantification of the 
amount of HA-RSK1 in the nucleus as a function of that in the cytoplasm (mean ± SE) from 30-36 cells per each 
condition from three independent experiments. (E) Cellular fractionation of HeLa cells treated as in D shows that 
mutations in the NLS of RSK1 decrease its amounts in the nuclei. C, cytosolic; N, nuclear. PLCγ, cytosol marker; histone 
1, nuclear marker. Right, the quantitative data shown are the mean ± SE (n = 3) Statistical significance was determined 
by Student's t test analyses. Scale bar, 10 μm. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>in the putative NLS sequence to localize in the nucleus upon EGF 
treatment. As shown in Figure 4D, treatment of HeLa cells with EGF 
resulted in the nuclear localization of the wild-type RSK1 but none 
of the forms of RSK1 harboring mutations in the putative NLS. The 
findings in Figure 4D were also confirmed by monitoring the cyto-
plasmic and nuclear fractions of HeLa cells expressing either the 
wild-type or the NLS mutant forms of RSK1 (Figure 4E). The inability 
of the CM mutant of RSK1 to localize to the nucleus in response to 
EGF is not due to the lack of either its kinase activity or its phospho-
rylation on S221 (Figure 4, B and C), strongly suggesting that neither 
the phosphorylation of S221 nor kinase activity of RSK1 by itself is 
sufficient for nuclear localization. Moreover, these data (Figure 4, D 
and E) strongly suggest that residues K328/R331/R332 form part of 
the NLS on RSK1. </p>

<p>Retention of active RSK1 in the nucleus requires 
its association with AKAP(s) </p>

<p>We previously showed that active RSK1 interacts with PKAc, which 
binds to its regulatory subunit PKARIα, which in turn associates with 
AKAPs, and that disruption of the indirect (via PKA subunit) interac-
tion of RSK1 with AKAPs by different approaches disrupts the nu-
clear localization of active RSK1 (Chaturvedi et al., 2006, 2009; Gao 
et al., 2010). Therefore we asked whether, once localized to the nu-
cleus, RSK1 requires its indirect interactions with AKAPs to be re-
tained in the nucleus. To address this question, we first treated HeLa 
cells with EGF for 10 min and then added stearated-Ht31, a cell-
permeable peptide that disrupts the interactions of PKA regulatory 
subunits with AKAPs (Carr et al., 1991; Vijayaraghavan et al., 1997). 
At different times thereafter, we examined the localization of the 
endogenous active RSK1 in HeLa cells. As shown in Figure 5A (right 
panel), EGF treatment resulted in the nuclear localization of RSK1 
over the time span (20 min) of the experiment. However, when Ht31 
was added after pretreatment with EGF, the amount of the nuclear 
RSK1 decreased over time, such that 5 min after Ht31 addition, the 
amount of active RSK1 in the cytoplasm was markedly increased. 
These data (Figure 5A) show that the retention of the active RSK1 in 
the nucleus requires its association in a complex with AKAP(s). Of 
interest, exposure of HeLa cells to the nuclear export inhibitor lep-
tomycin B (LMB) abolished the Ht31-mediated decrease in nuclear 
accumulation of active RSK1 (Figure 5B), suggesting that RSK1 may 
also contain a nuclear export sequence (see Discussion). The data in 
Figure 5B also confirm that the loss of active RSK1 in the nucleus 
after Ht31 treatment was due to efflux of RSK1 from the nucleus. </p>

<p>AKAP95 retains RSK1 in the nucleus </p>

<p>To identify the AKAP(s) that retain active RSK1 in the nucleus, we 
treated B82L cells with cell-permeable, stearated Ht31 or control 
Ht31P that does not dissociate PKA regulatory subunits from AKAPs 
(Carr et al., 1991; Vijayaraghavan et al., 1997) for 20 min and then 
treated cells with EGF for 10 min. Following immunoprecipitation of 
RSK1, we analyzed the associated proteins by SDS-PAGE and gel 
code blue staining. Ht31 decreased a few protein bands associated 
with RSK1 (Supplemental Figure S1A). Liquid chromatography-mass 
spectrometer/mass spectrometer analyses of the ∼100-kDa band in 
control and Ht31P yielded peptides corresponding to several pro-
teins, including AKAP95 (Supplemental Figure S1B). AKAP95 was 
shown to be a nuclear protein (Coghlan et al., 1994; Eide et al., 
1998; Akileswaran et al., 2001). Therefore we investigated whether 
RSK1 and AKAP95 existed in the same complex. As shown in Figure 
6A, immunoprecipitation of AKAP95 from HeLa cells treated with 
EGF resulted in the coimmunoprecipitation of RSK1. In controls with 
NIH3T3 cells that do not express endogenous RSK1 but do express </p>

<p>RSK2 and RSK3 (Supplemental Figure S2), this interaction was not 
observed (Figure 6A). Of note, silencing of AKAP95 did not alter the 
ability of EGF to activate RSK1 in HeLa cells (Figure 6B). Moreover, 
as assessed by cell fractionation and fluorescence microscopy, si-
lencing of AKAP95 in HeLa cells, respectively, resulted in a decrease 
in the nuclear content of active RSK1 and increase in its cytosolic 
amounts (Figure 6, C and D). Similar results (not shown) were also 
found in B82L mouse lung fibroblasts, in which RSK1 interacts with 
PKA subunits as shown here with HeLa cells (Chaturvedi et al., 2006, 
2009; Gao et al., 2010). Thus the inability of phospho-RSK1 to local-
ize to the nucleus is not due to altered RSK1 activation. Together 
these data suggest that AKAP95 is one of the AKAPs that retain ac-
tive RSK1 in the nucleus. 
To further confirm the notion that AKAP95 retains active RSK1 in 
the nucleus, we expressed either the green fluorescent protein 
(GFP)-tagged wild-type AKAP95 or its mutant forms that contain 
substitutions of one (1M; R290S), two (2M; K304S/R305S), or three 
(3M; R290S/K304S/R305S) residues in its NLS and, therefore, do 
not affect (1M), attenuate (2M), or abolish (3M) the nuclear localiza-
tion of AKAP95 (Kamada et al., 2005). Consistent with the original 
report with these forms of AKAP95 (Kamada et al., 2005), as moni-
tored by immunocytochemistry in HEK293 cells, the wild-type and 
1M forms were mainly nuclear, the 2M form was distributed in both 
the nucleus and cytoplasm, and the 3M mutant was cytoplasmic 
(Supplemental Figure S3, A-D). In addition, after expressing wild-
type and mutant forms of GFP-AKAP95 in HEK 293 cells and treat-
ing them with EGF, we determined by cell fractionation studies the 
localization of the endogenous RSK1 in the nucleus and cytosolic 
fractions of the cells. As shown in Figure 7A, in the presence of EGF, 
more phospho-RSK1 was present in the nuclear fractions than in the 
cytosolic fractions from cells transfected with the wild-type and 1M 
mutant forms of AKAP95. The distribution of phospho-RSK1 was 
approximately similar in the cytosolic and nuclear fractions from 
cells transfected with GFP-AKAP95 2M and mostly cytosolic in cells 
expressing GFP-AKAP95 3M (Figure 7A). Similarly, in HeLa cells, the 
expressed wild-type GFP-AKAP95 was localized to the nucleus to-
gether with active (phospo-380) RSK1, whereas expression of the 
3M mutant of GFP-AKAP95 resulted in colocalization of the active 
RSK1 with the 3M mutant in the cytoplasm (Figure 7B). These find-
ings were also corroborated by immunolocalization of the wild-type 
AKAP95 or its 3M mutant and RSK1 (Figure 7C). Of note, mutations 
of the NLS in AKAP95 did not alter its ability to be coimmunopre-
cipitated with RSK1 (Supplemental Figure S3E). Together, the data 
in Figure 7 demonstrate that active RSK1 interacts with AKAP95 in 
cells and the 3M mutant of AKAP95, which cannot be localized to 
the nucleus, sequesters active RSK1 in the cytoplasm. In this latter 
respect, the overexpressed 3M mutant of AKAP95 acts as a "trap" 
for RSK1 and precludes its localization into the nucleus. </p>

<p>Nuclear localization of RSK1 is required for stimulation 
of DNA synthesis </p>

<p>Because RSK1 was shown to play an important role in cell prolif-
eration by promoting G1 → S progression (Fujita et al., 2003; 
Cargnello and Roux, 2011), using two different approaches we in-
vestigated whether its translocation to the nucleus is important to 
initiate DNA synthesis. In the first approach, we investigated 
whether the nuclear function of the CM mutant form of RSK1 that 
is activated by EGF but does not localize to the nucleus (Figure 4) 
is different from its wild-type counterpart. For this purpose, we 
monitored bromodeoxyuridine (BrdU) incorporation in NIH3T3 
cells, which express RSK2 and RSK3 but do not express any detect-
able amounts of endogenous RSK1 (Supplemental Figure S2). To </p>

<p>Volume 23 February 1, 2012 </p>

<p>Nuclear localization and retention of RSK1 | 509 </p>

<p>FIGuRE 5: Retention of active RSK1 in the nucleus requires its indirect (via PKA) interactions with AKAPs. (A) Ht31 
decreases the nuclear retention of active RSK1 in the nucleus. After serum starvation, HeLa cells were treated with or 
without 100 nM EGF for 10 min, followed by incubation with 20 μM Ht31 for the indicated times to dissociate PKA from 
AKAP(s). Immunocytochemical analyses were performed with anti-phospho-T573 RSK antibody. Right, controls with 
Ht31 or EGF alone for 20 min. The bar graph shows quantification (mean ± SE) of the nuclear phospho-T573 RSK as a 
ratio of that in the cytoplasm from 45-51 cells per each condition from three separate experiments. (B) LMB abolishes 
Ht31-mediated efflux of RSK1 from the nucleus. After serum starvation, HeLa cells were incubated with or without LMB 
(20 ng/ml) for 2 h, followed by treatment with or without 20 μM Ht31 for 15 min. Subsequently, cells were stimulated 
with or without 100 nM EGF for 10 min. RSK1 translocation was monitored with anti-pRSK T573 antibody. Scale 
bar,10 μm. Data from 41-44 cells per each condition from three experiments were quantified as in A. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>FIGuRE 6: RSK1 is present in a complex with AKAP95, and silencing of AKAP95 decreases phospho-RSK1 in the 
nucleus. (A) Immunoprecipitates of AKAP95 from HeLa cells, but not NIH3T3 cells, contain RSK1. NIH3T3 cells used as 
controls do not express any detectable amounts of RSK1. AKAP95 was immunoprecipitated from HeLa and NIH3T3 
cells, and the presence of endogenous RSK1 in the immunocomplex was monitored using anti-RSK1 antibody. WCL, 
whole-cell lysate. (B) Silencing of AKAP95 in HeLa cells does not alter activation of RSK1. The phosphorylation of RSK1 
was detected after immunoprecipitation with anti-RSK1 specific antibody from control and AKAP95-specific small 
interfering RNA (siRNA)-treated cells. (C) Silencing of AKAP95 in HeLa cells alters the distribution of phospho-RSK in 
cytoplasmic and nuclear fractions. After transfection with AKAP95 siRNA for 48 h and overnight serum starvation, HeLa 
cells were stimulated with EGF and processed for the isolation of cytosolic and nuclear fractions. Western analyses of the 
fractions was performed with anti-phospho-S380 RSK and AKAP95 antibodies. PLCγ, cytoplasmic marker; Histone H1, 
nuclear marker. (D) Silencing of AKAP95 decreases nuclear localization of phosphorylated endogenous RSK. HeLa cells 
were treated with or without EGF after transfection with AKAP95 siRNA for 48 h as in C. Immunocytochemical analyses 
with anti-AKAP95 and anti-phospho-Thr573 RSK antibodies were performed. Quantification of nuclear fluorescence of 
AKAP95 and phospho-RSK (mean ± SEM) from 41-49 cells per condition from three independent experiments is shown 
in the lower panel. Scale bar, 10 μm. The data in A-C are representatives of three independent experiments. </p>

<p>facilitate interpretation, the data were quantified to reflect BrdU-
positive cells as a ratio of the total number of cells that expressed 
the desired wild-type or mutant forms of either RSK1 or AKAP95. </p>

<p>The BrdU staining of untransfected cells in the same fields served 
as internal controls. As shown in Figure 8A, in NIH3T3 cells, EGF 
activated both the wild-type and CM forms of RSK1 to similar </p>

<p>Volume 23 February 1, 2012 </p>

<p>Nuclear localization and retention of RSK1 | 511 </p>

<p>FIGuRE 7: Overexpression of wild-type and NLS mutant forms of GFP-AKAP95 alter the cellular localization of 
endogenous RSK1. (A) HEK293T cells transfected with wild-type AKAP95 or its 1M, 2M, or 3M mutants were serum 
starved and treated with EGF. The cytosolic and nuclear fractions were isolated for Western blotting. Phospho-RSK1 
was detected with anti-pRSK S380 antibody. C, cytosolic; N, nuclear. Histone H1, nuclear marker; PLCγ, cytosolic marker. 
(B) HeLa cells were transfected with the wild-type and 3M mutant of AKAP95 and treated as in (A). Following cell 
fractionation, the active RSK1 and AKAP95 were monitored. (C) More of the endogenous RSK1 is present in the nuclei 
of HeLa cells expressing wild-type GFP-AKAP95 than those expressing the 3M form of GFP-AKAP95. After 48 h of 
transfection, cells were serum starved overnight and stimulated with EGF. RSK1 was visualized with anti-RSK1 specific 
antibody. Data shown are representative of three independent experiments. </p>

<p>extents. However, the wild-type RSK1 enhanced BrdU incorpora-
tion, but the CM mutant did not (Figure 8B). As a second approach, 
we expressed either wild-type or 3M mutant of AKAP95 in HeLa 
cells to determine whether permitting (with wild-type AKAP95) or 
restricting (with 3M-AKAP95) the nuclear localization of endoge-
nous RSK1 altered BrdU incorporation into cells. Whereas the ex-
pression of wild-type AKAP95 did not alter BrdU incorporation, the 
3M mutant of AKAP95, which sequesters active RSK1 in the cyto-
plasm, decreased BrdU incorporation (Figure 8C). These data 
demonstrate that disruption of the nuclear localization of active 
RSK1 by either mutation of its NLS or "trapping" of endogenous 
RSK1 in the cytoplasm by the nuclear localization-deficient 3M 
mutant of AKAP95 attenuates the nuclear functions of RSK1. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Besides elucidating how active RSK1 is localized and retained in the 
nucleus, we unraveled some additional salient features concerning 
how this enzyme is regulated. First, as previously suggested (Gao 
et al., 2010), although the phosphorylation of Ser-221 is necessary 
for nuclear localization of RSK1, we demonstrated that this phos-</p>

<p>phorylation is required to dissociate the active RSK1 from PKARIα in 
the cytoplasm. Hence the S221A mutant of RSK1, which does not 
localize to the nucleus upon EGF treatment of cells, can localize to 
the nucleus if its interaction with PKARIα is disrupted by low concen-
trations of a cell-permeable peptide (peptide PS) corresponding to 
the pseudosubstrate region of PKARIα, the inactive RSK1-binding 
site (Gao et al., 2010). At the low concentrations of peptide PS used 
in this study, PKAc and PKARIα interactions are not affected (Gao 
et al., 2010). Because the S221A mutant of RSK1 is not active, our 
findings with peptide PS also demonstrate that the inactive RSK1 
can enter the nucleus. However, because nuclear localization of the 
S221A mutant of RSK1 is EGF dependent, our findings suggest that 
the other sites on RSK1 have to be phosphorylated for its nuclear 
entry. Overall, therefore, although phosphorylation of S221 is re-
quired to release RSK1 from PKARIα and permit its nuclear localiza-
tion, the activity of the NTK is not necessary for its nuclear transloca-
tion. Second, supporting the notion that phosphorylation of sites in 
the linker region of RSK1 are necessary for its activity (Dalby et al., 
1998; Gross et al., 2001), we showed that the S221D mutant of RSK1 
also requires EGF for activation of the NTK and that a negative </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>2007), are important for activity, and their 
substitution perhaps alters the conforma-
tion of the NTK to abrogate its activity. 
We also demonstrated that RSK1 con-
tains a bipartite NLS, and substitution of ba-
sic residues in its N-or C-terminus abrogates 
its translocation to the nucleus after EGF ad-
dition. Because substitution of both the N-
terminal (K316/R317) and C-terminal (K328/ 
R331/R332) basic residues in the NLS with 
Ala (RSK1-NM/CM) also disrupts its phos-
phorylation on S221, this form of RSK1 most 
likely does not translocate to the nucleus 
because it cannot dissociate from PKARIα. 
However, substitutions of basic residues in 
only the N-terminal (K316/R317, RSK1-NM) 
or C-terminal (K328/R331/R332, RSK1-CM) 
regions of the NLS that permit the phospho-
rylation of S221 on these mutant forms also 
do not translocate to the nucleus irrespec-
tive of whether the activity of the NTK can 
be augmented by EGF (RSK1-CM) or not 
(RSK1-NM). These findings, coupled with 
the observations that phosphorylation of 
S221 or a negative charge at this position, 
but not the activity of the NTK, is required 
for nuclear translocation of RSK1 demon-
strate that the 17-residue-long region com-
prising K316-R332 is the NLS. This region is 
encompassed by the αI-αJ loop as well as 
the αJ helix at the surface of the large heli-
cal lobe of the NTK (Ikuta et al., 2007) and 
is conserved in RSK1 in different species 
such as mouse, rat, and human. In addition, 
cognate regions comprising residues K313-
K329 and K322-R338 on RSK2 and RSK3, 
respectively, also have significant similarity 
to the NLS on RSK1. Thus it is possible that 
these regions on RSK2 and RSK3 are also 
their respective NLSs. However, in one 
study, the expression of the N-terminal half 
of RSK2, which included residues K313-
K329, did not localize to the nucleus, and 
that study suggested that the C-terminal 
half of RSK2 is important for its nuclear lo-
calization (Eisinger-Mathason et al., 2008), 
raising the possibility that the NLS contain-
ing K313-329 is functional in the context of 
the full-length RSK2 when the autophos-
phorylation sites on the linker region are 
phosphorylated. 
We previously showed that the active 
RSK1 via its extreme C-terminal 13 residues, 
which include Ser-732, associates with PKAc, 
and this interaction requires the phosphory-
lation of Ser-732 (Gao and Patel, 2009). This 
interaction permits the indirect (via the reg-
ulatory subunit of PKA) association of the active RSK1 with AKAPs, 
and disruption of the RSK/PKA complex from AKAPs results in de-
creased nuclear localization of RSK1. The decreased nuclear local-
ization could result from either export of the RSK1 from the nucleus 
or the lack of RSK1 entry into the nucleus. Here we showed that </p>

<p>charge at this position by itself is not sufficient to activate the en-
zyme. A third interesting aspect is that the substitution of K316/ 
R317 with Ala abrogated the activity of the NTK without altering its 
phosphorylation on Ser-221. Thus these two basic residues in the 
extreme C-terminus of the NTK, which lie on its surface (Ikuta et al., </p>

<p>FIGuRE 8: Nuclear translocation of RSK1 is required to stimulate DNA synthesis. (A) HA-RSK1 
and its CM mutant form demonstrate similar kinase activities. NIH3T3 cells were transfected to 
express HA-RSK1 or its CM mutant. After serum starvation, cells were treated with or without 
100 nM EGF for 10 min. HA-RSK1 and HA-RSK1 CM were immunoprecipitated with anti-HA 
antibody, and the IP complex was subjected to the in vitro kinase assays. The amounts of 
HA-RSK1 in the IP were monitored with Western blotting (bottom). Data are mean ± SE (n = 3 
independent experiments). (B) HA-RSK1, but not its CM mutant, stimulate BrdU incorporation. 
NIH3T3 cells were transfected to express HA-RSK1 or HA-RSK1 CM. After serum starvation, 
cells were incubated with 10% serum/DMEM for 18 h, followed by the addition of BrdU for 4 h. 
(C) Overexpression of GFP-AKAP95 3M, but not wild-type GFP-AKAP95, decreases BrdU 
incorporation in HeLa cells. After transfection to express wild-type GFP-AKAP95 or its 3M 
mutant in HeLa cells, experiments were performed as in B. The quantified data in B and C reflect 
the number of BrdU-positive cells as a ratio of the total number of cells that expressed the 
different transfected constructs. The BrdU-positive staining in untransfected cells within the 
same fields provided the control ratios. The data are mean ± SE from at least 102 cells from four 
separate experiments (B) and at least 181 cells from three experiments (C). Statistical 
significance was determined by Student's t test analyses. Scale bar, 10 μm. </p>

<p>Volume 23 February 1, 2012 </p>

<p>Nuclear localization and retention of RSK1 | 513 </p>

<p>is exported out of the nucleus while it is still 
attached to PKAc and the regulatory sub-
unit of PKA (Figure 9). Because leptomycin 
B blocked the Ht31-mediated efflux of RSK1 
from the nucleus (Figure 5B), it is possible 
that RSK1 contains a nuclear export signal. 
However, a nuclear export signal for RSK1 
has not been identified. From its primary 
structure, it appears that residues Leu-173 
to Ser-180 on RSK1 qualify as a putative 
nuclear export sequence. These residues in 
the αE helix are adjacent to the NLS on the 
surface of the large helical loop of the NTK 
on RSK1 (Ikuta et al., 2007). Because substi-
tutions of K316 and R317 that are adjacent 
to the putative nuclear export signal (L173-
S180) on the surface of the NTK disrupt its 
activity, we have not endeavored to mutate 
the putative RSK1 nuclear export signal. 
In NIH3T3 cells, which do not express 
appreciable amounts of RSK1, expression of 
wild-type RSK1, but not its NLS-deficient 
CM mutant, increased DNA synthesis as 
monitored by BrdU staining. These data are 
consistent with the role of RSK1 as a pro-
moter of cell proliferation (Smith et al., 2005) 
and also demonstrate that the NLS mutant 
of RSK1 loses its nuclear function. Similarly, 
overexpression of GFP-AKAP 3M, which 
traps endogenous RSK1 in the cytoplasm, 
also diminished incorporation of BrdU, fur-
ther demonstrating the necessity for nuclear 
RSK1 in this process. 
Overall, our findings demonstrate that RSK1 contains an NLS 
(K316-R332) that is necessary for its import into the nucleus and that 
phosphorylation of Ser-221 in the NTK is required to dissociate it 
from PKARIα/AKAP complex in the cytoplasm. The activation of the 
NTK is not necessary for nuclear translocation of RSK1, and besides 
S221, other phospho sites on RSK1 are also important for both its 
activity and nuclear import. Once inside the nucleus, RSK1 requires 
indirect (via PKA) interactions with AKAP95 to be retained in the 
nucleus. Moreover, mutations of the NLS on RSK1 that do not affect 
its kinase activity but interfere with its nuclear localization or trap-
ping of RSK1 in the cytoplasm by an NLS-deficient mutant of 
AKAP95 diminishes BrdU incorporation in cells. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Reagents </p>

<p>Anti-RSK1 antibody was purchased from Santa Cruz Biotechnol-
ogy (Santa Cruz, CA). Anti-phospho-RSK1/2 (S221) from R&amp;D Sys-
tems (Minneapolis, MN), anti-phospho-RSK (T359/S363) from Cell 
Signaling (Beverly, MA), anti-phospho-RSK (S380) from Epitomics 
(Burlingame, CA), anti-phospho-RSK (T573) from Cell Signaling, 
and anti-phospho-RSK S732 raised by Rockland (Gilbertsville, PA) 
were used. Anti-PKARIα was from BD Biosciences (Palo Alto, CA). 
Anti-Erk1/2 was from Upstate Biotechnology (Lake Placid, NY). 
Anti-HA-horseradish peroxidase was from Roche Applied Science 
(Indianapolis, IN), and the anti-HA polyclonal antibody was from 
Covance (Berkeley, CA). Anti-BrdU was from Calbiochem (La Jolla, 
CA). N-terminally palmitoylated PKARIα peptide (PS), correspond-
ing to PKARIα pseudosubstrate region (amino acids 91-99), was 
synthesized by New England Peptide (Gardner, MA). N-terminally </p>

<p>once the active RSK1 is in the nucleus, the addition of Ht31, which 
disrupts PKA interactions with AKAPs, results in a time-dependent 
export of the active RSK1 from the nucleus. Hence the interaction of 
active RSK1 with PKAc and, therefore, AKAP(s) is necessary for its 
retention in the nucleus. The need for RSK1 interactions with PKA 
subunits and AKAP(s) for nuclear retention is akin to the nuclear 
retention of RSK2 via its interactions with TIA-1 (Eisinger-Mathason 
et al., 2008). 
Our studies also identified AKAP95 as one of the AKAPs that is 
necessary for the retention of RSK1 in the nucleus. Of interest, 
AKAP95 associates with the RII subunits of PKA (Herberg et al., 2000). 
Previously, we demonstrated that the inactive RSK1 interacts with RI 
but not RII subunits (unpublished data). However, since the active 
RSK1 interacts with PKAc, it is possible that in the nucleus the RSK1, 
via PKAc and PKARII, is tethered to AKAP95 (see schematic in Figure 
9). This would be consistent with the notion that PKARIα is cytosolic 
in its localization whereas nuclear PKARII is responsible for associa-
tion of PKAc with nuclear AKAPs (Day et al., 2011). Also interesting 
are the previous findings that AKAP95 is important in G1 → S phase 
transition and is associated with proteins that regulate this process 
(Arsenijevic et al., 2004, 2006). In addition, AKAP95 is involved in 
chromosome condensation at mitosis (Collas et al., 1999). Similarly, 
RSK1 is also important for G1 → S progression (Fujita et al., 2003; 
Cargnello and Roux, 2011). Thus, it appears that AKAP95, by associ-
ating with RSK1 and the other proteins, facilitates G1 → S pro-
gression, DNA synthesis, chromosome condensation, mitosis, 
and orchestrating of overall cell cycle progression. 
The disruption of the RSK1 interactions with AKAPs results in its 
export from the nucleus (Figure 5). It is not clear whether the RSK1 </p>

<p>FIGuRE 9: Schematic representing the mechanisms of nuclear localization and retention of 
RSK1 following its activation. Inactive RSK1 is associated with PKARIα (RI) in the cytoplasm. 
Activation of RSK1 dissociates it from PKARIα and permits its entry into the nucleus, where, via 
interactions with catalytic subunit of PKA (PKAc) and AKAP95, it is retained in the nucleus. 
Disruption of the PKA/AKAP95 interactions with Ht31 result in decreased RSK1 retention in the 
nucleus, an event that is LMB sensitive. Whether the RSK1 is exported from the nucleus in 
complex with PKAc or by itself is not currently known and is depicted by a question mark. 
D-AKAP, dual-specificity AKAPI known to be present in the RSK1/PKARIα complex (see the text). </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>palmitoylated Bimax1 peptide, which inhibits the importin α/β 
nuclear import pathway (Kosugi et al., 2008), was synthesized by 
Neo Peptide (Cambridge, MA). Kemptide was from Sigma-Aldrich 
(St Louis, MO). BX795 was from Axon Medchem (Groningen, 
Netherlands). </p>

<p>Plasmids </p>

<p>pHM6-RSK1 (rat) wild-type or S221 mutants expressing HA-tagged 
RSK1 were described previously (Gao et al., 2010). Mutations in the 
nuclear localization signal sequence of RSK1 were inserted using 
mutagenic primers and universal PCR of pHM6-RSK1. GFP-tagged 
AKAP95 and its mutant forms (1M, 2M, and 3M) harboring muta-
tions in its nuclear localization sequence (Kamada et al., 2005) were 
obtained from Shinji Kamada and Tony Hunter (Salk Institute, San 
Diego, CA). </p>

<p>Cell culture and transfection </p>

<p>Both HeLa cells and NIH3T3 cells were maintained in DMEM sup-
plemented with 10% fetal bovine serum, 2 mM l-glutamine, and 
penicillin/streptomycin. HeLa cells were plated in 60-mm dishes 
at 4 × 10 5 /dish and transfected with plasmids using a TransIT 
HeLaMONSTER-Transfection Kit (Mirus Bio, Madison, WI) follow-
ing the manufacturer's protocol. NIH3T3 cells were plated in 
60-mm dishes at 2 × 10 5 /dish and transfected with Transit 2020 
Transfection Reagent (Mirus Bio). </p>

<p>Immunoprecipitation </p>

<p>HeLa cells were serum starved overnight and then were treated with 
or without 100 nM EGF for 10 min. Cells were washed twice with 
cold phosphate-buffered saline and scraped into lysis buffer con-
taining 50 mM 4-(2-hydroxyethyl)-1-piperazineethanesulfonic acid 
(HEPES), pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 1.5 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM ethylene 
glycol tetraacetic acid, 50 mM NaF, 1% Triton X-100, 0.1% (vol/vol) 
β-mercaptoethanol, and protease inhibitor mixture (Roche Diagnos-
tics). A total of 500 μg of cleared cell lysates was incubated for 2 h 
at 4°C with 0.8 μg of anti-RSK1 antibody or anti-HA monoclonal 
antibody (1:250) together with 15 μl of protein G-conjugated aga-
rose beads. After three washes with lysis buffer, the immunoprecipi-
tates were eluted with Laemmli sample buffer and subjected to 
Western analyses. </p>

<p>Pulldown of PKARIα with cAMP-agarose </p>

<p>Serum-starved HeLa cells were preincubated with or without 2 μM 
PKARIα peptide PS for 10 min and then treated with or without 
EGF for 10 min. Cleared cell lysates (500 μg of protein) were mixed 
with cAMP-agarose (Sigma-Aldrich) for 2 h at 4°C. The beads were 
then washed twice with high-salt buffer (10 mM HEPES, pH 7.4, 
1.5 mM MgCl2, 10 mM KCl, 0.5 M NaCl, 0.1% Igepal CA-630, 
1 mM dithiothreitol, and proteinase inhibitor mixture) followed 
by two washes with no-salt buffer (same as high-salt buffer but with-
out NaCl). Proteins in the complex were resuspended in Laemmli 
buffer and subjected to Western analyses using anti-PKARIα and 
anti-HA horseradish peroxidase. </p>

<p>In vitro kinase activity assays </p>

<p>The assays were performed as described previously (Gao et al., 
2010). Essentially, HeLa cells were transfected to express HA-RSK1 
or its mutants. After overnight serum starvation, cells were treated 
with or without 100 nM EGF for 10 min. HA-RSK1 or its mutants 
were immunoprecipitated as described, and then the immunopre-
cipitate (IP) complex was resuspended in 20 mM HEPES, pH 7.5, 
0.1% mercaptoethanol, 1 mM sodium orthovanadate, 1 mM NaF, </p>

<p>25 mM glycerophosphate, and 5 mM MgSO4. The reaction was 
started with addition of 200 μM Kemptide, 125 μM ATP, and 2.5 μCi 
of [γ-32 P]ATP and stopped after 15 min of incubation at room tem-
perature. One parallel set of IP complex was resuspended in Laem-
mli sample buffer for Western blotting to monitor the amounts of 
HA-RSK1 or its mutants in the complex. </p>

<p>Immunocytochemistry </p>

<p>HeLa cells were plated in eight-chamber slides at 10,000 cells/well. 
After serum starvation, cells underwent different treatments as indi-
cated in the figure legends. After fixation with 4% formaldehyde in 
phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) for 10 min, cells were permeabi-
lized with 0.3% Triton X-100 in PBS for 10 min, followed by 1 h of 
blocking with 5% bovine serum albumin in PBS. Cells were stained 
with primary antibodies, rabbit anti-RSK1, rabbit anti-phospho-
T573 RSK, rabbit anti-AKAP95, or mouse anti-HA antibody over-
night at 4°C. Fluorescence staining was performed using Alexa 
488-conjugated goat anti-rabbit or anti-mouse antibody (green) or 
Alexa 594-conjugated goat anti-rabbit antibody (red). Confocal 
microscopy was performed using a multiphoton Zeiss LSM-510 
laser scanning microscope (Carl Zeiss, Jena, Germany) equipped 
with a C-Apo 40×/1.2 water lens. Confocal images were acquired 
with <rs type="software">LSM 510</rs> software. Nonconfocal images were acquired with an 
Olympus IX81 microscope (Olympus, Center Valley, PA) equipped 
with 40×/0.60 lens and Retiga EXi digital camera (QImaging, Surrey, 
Canada). For quantification, the fluorescence densities in the nu-
cleus or cytoplasm were analyzed with ImageJ (National Institutes of 
Health, Bethesda, MD). </p>

<p>Cell fractionation </p>

<p>Cells were homogenized after incubation in hypotonic buffer from 
the nuclear extraction kit (Active Motif, Carlsbad, CA) on ice for 
15 min. The cell homogenates were centrifuged at 200 × g to re-
move intact cells and cell debris. The supernatant was centrifuged 
at 1000 × g for 10 min to pellet cell nuclei. The nuclear pellet was 
washed and centrifuged again. The 1000 × g supernatants were 
then centrifuged at 100,000 × g to generate the cytosolic fraction. 
The proteins in nuclear and cytosolic fractions were subjected to 
Western analysis. </p>

<p>Brdu incorporation </p>

<p>NIH3T3 cells were plated in eight-chamber slides at 10,000 cells/ 
well. Cells were transfected with plasmids expressing HA-RSK1 or its 
mutant using Metafectene Pro transfection reagent (Biontex Labora-
tories GmbH, Martinsried, Germany). Similarly, HeLa cells were 
transfected with GFP-AKAP95 or its 3M mutant, which does not 
localize inside the nucleus, using TransIT-HeLaMONSTER Transfec-
tion Kit. One day after transfection, cells were serum starved for 24 h 
and then replaced with DMEM containing 10% fetal bovine serum 
for 18 h, followed by addition of 10 μM BrdU and 4 h of incubation. 
The cells were fixed with 4% formaldehyde/PBS for 10 min at room 
temperature and then were permeabilized with 0.3% Triton X-100/ 
PBS for 10 min. To denature DNA, cells were incubated with 2 N HCl 
at room temperature for 30 min. After extensive washes with PBS 
and 5% bovine serum albumin/PBS blocking, cells were incubated 
with anti-BrdU antibody (mouse monoclonal) and anti-HA antibody 
(rabbit polyclonal) at 4°C overnight. The secondary antibodies were 
Alexa 594-conjugated goat anti-mouse antibody or Alexa 488-con-
jugated goat anti-rabbit antibody. The images were obtained by a 
multiphoton Zeiss LSM-510 laser-scanning microscope as described. 
The results are expressed as the percentage of cells showing nuclear 
staining with BrdU. </p>

<p>Volume 23 February 1, 2012 </p>

<p>Nuclear localization and retention of RSK1 | 515 </p>



<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Warner Greene (University of California, San Francisco, 
San Francisco, CA) for the rat RSK1 cDNA. We are also grateful to 
Shinji Kamada and Tony Hunter (Salk Institute, San Diego, CA) for 
the GFP-AKAP (wild-type and NLS mutant) constructs. We thank 
Kuldeep Patel for help with some of the immunocytochemistry 
experiments. This research was supported by grants GM079226 
(to T.B.P.) from the National Institutes of Health and a Scientist 
Development Grant (to D.C.) from the American Heart Association, 
Midwest Affiliate. </p>



</text></tei>