<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3018006" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:38+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: We report development of a continuous scanning procedure and 
the use of a time delay integration (TDI) line scan camera for a light-sheet 
based microscope called a thin-sheet laser imaging microscope (TSLIM). 
TSLIM is an optimized version of a light-sheet fluorescent microscope that 
previously used a start/stop scanning procedure to move the specimen 
through the thinnest portion of a light-sheet and stitched the image columns 
together to produce a well-focused composite image. In this paper, 
hardware and software enhancements to TSLIM are described that allow for 
dual sided, dual illumination lasers, and continuous scanning of the 
specimen using either a full-frame CCD camera and a TDI line scan 
camera. These enhancements provided a ~70% reduction in the time 
required for composite image generation and a ~63% reduction in 
photobleaching of the specimen compared to the start/stop procedure. </p>

<p>A thin-sheet laser imaging microscope (TSLIM) is a device for nondestructive optical 
sectioning of organisms and thick tissues such as the mouse cochlea, zebrafish brain/inner ear 
and rat brain [1]. TSLIM is a modular device that can image transparent tissues such as 
zebrafish embryos or fixed and cleared transparent tissues that have been labeled with a 
fluorochrome. It is similar to other light sheet based microscopes in which specimens are </p>

<p>#131581 -$15.00 USD Received 15 Jul 2010; revised 6 Aug 2010; accepted 11 Aug 2010; published 13 Aug 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2010 OSA 
1 September 2010 / Vol. 1, No. 2 / BIOMEDICAL OPTICS EXPRESS 598 </p>

<p>illuminated by a light-sheet, and fluorescent tissue planes are recorded by a camera that is 
mounted orthogonal to the light-sheet. By moving in the z-axis, serial optical sections are 
obtained and three-dimensional (3D) reconstructions of structures can be generated for 
visualization and morphometry. However, since the light sheet is thinnest only in a narrow 
region (i.e., the beam waist) an x-axis scanning procedure was used to produce a well-focused 
composite image across the full width of the specimen. The original description of TSLIM [1] 
used a single green laser and a full-frame CCD camera in which the center 40 lines of the 
CCD array were collected using a start/stop procedure and an x-axis composite image was 
produced by stitching these image columns together. The present report describes hardware 
and software solutions that increase image quality and speed of optical sectioning, which also 
reduces photobleaching of the specimen. The use of a TDI line scan camera and our software 
and hardware features can also be used for other light-sheet based microscopes to reduce 
scanning times and specimen photobleaching. 
Light-sheet microscopy was introduced into the current literature by Voie and colleagues 
[2,3] who used it to image ear tissues but were unaware of a much earlier publication in 1903 
[4] describing light-sheet microscopy. It is technologically a relatively simple procedure 
whereby a thin sheet of light illuminates a plane in a transparent volume and that plane, or 
optical section, is observed orthogonal to the light-sheet. It has been used to image organisms 
in a plane of water [5] but its most common application is to optically section thick tissues 
that have been labeled with a fluorochrome and made chemically transparent. Light-sheet 
microscopes have been developed by a number of different investigators [1-8] and this 
technology is rapidly evolving. TSLIM [1] was developed by optimizing components of 
previous light-sheet microscopes and this report describes software and hardware 
enhancements to TSLIM that significantly improve its capabilities. Specifically, TSLIM now 
features a line scan camera in addition to the full-frame CCD camera, hardware triggering of 
the cameras, and software that allows for continuous scanning of the image in the x-axis. </p>

<p>2. Methods and results </p>

<p>The preferred way to produce a sheet of light is by using a cylindrical lens. In the present 
version of TSLIM a green solid-state laser with a wavelength of 532-nm (Optotronics, 
VAI50532) is used to produce a light-sheet and their light path is shown in Fig. 1. The laser 
beam is expanded and collimated using a 10X Galilean beam expander (Edmund Optics, 
NT55-579) and passed through, an f = 50.8 mm cylindrical lens (Newport CKX525-C). The 
light-sheet is rotated 90 degrees by passing through the image side of an NA = 0.14 EO 
infinity-corrected long working distance 5X Plan Apochromat microscopic objective 
(Edmund Optics, NT59-876). The light-sheet is projected through the side of an open top, 
glass or quartz specimen chamber (Starna, 3G20; DLC300Q20). The specimen is attached to a 
Delrin® (DuPont) rod that is suspended in the center of the chamber which contains either a 
clearing solution for fixed and cleared specimens or an aqueous solution for live specimen 
imaging. The illuminated plane within the tissue specimen is observed perpendicular to the 
light-sheet using either a 1X or 2X objective lens (NA = 0.25, NA = 0.50) on a horizontally 
mounted, Olympus micro MVX10 microscope. Images are captured using either a full-frame 
CCD digital camera (Retiga 2000R) or a TDI line scan camera (Dalsa, Piranha HS-40-
04K40). </p>

<p>#131581 -$15.00 USD Received 15 Jul 2010; revised 6 Aug 2010; accepted 11 Aug 2010; published 13 Aug 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2010 OSA 
1 September 2010 / Vol. 1, No. 2 / BIOMEDICAL OPTICS EXPRESS 599 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Top-view and side-view of TSLIM's light-sheet pathway. A solid state laser beam is 
converted in an optical assembly (beam expander, cylindrical lens and microscope objective) 
and passes through the specimen chamber containing the tissue. The thinnest portion of the 
light-sheet is at focal point of the microscope objective. The illuminated plane in the tissue is 
collected by a microscope objective and recorded using a digital camera. Upper left panel: the 
specimen is moved through the beam waist to produce a well-focused imaged across the width 
of the specimen. </p>

<p>As can be seen in Fig. 1, the light-sheet is thinnest in only a small x-dimension at the focal 
point of the microscope objective. The thinnest region of a focused light-sheet is called the 
beam waist w 0 . The width of the area in which w 0 increases to √2·w 0 is called the Rayleigh 
range x R . Twice the Rayleigh range is called the confocal parameter b, an area of the beam 
where its thickness remains approximately constant. However, calculations pertaining to the 
parameters of the light-sheet were provided in a previous publication describing TSLIM [1]. 
A thicker light-sheet has a longer confocal parameter but a thicker light sheet decreases 
the ability to resolve fine structures due to light scattering. Thus, producing thinner light-
sheets is desirable, but comes at the cost of a shorter confocal parameter and focal point [1]. If 
the width of the tissue fits within the confocal parameter, then a well-focused image is 
observed. However, if the width of the tissue is greater than the confocal parameter, then it 
does not appear to be well focused across its width. The region of the confocal parameter can 
also be referred to as the region of interest (ROI) within the tissue. </p>

<p>2.1 Start stop procedure (SSP) </p>

<p>Since the thinnest portion of the light-sheet covers only a small region of a large tissue to be 
imaged, either the specimen or the beam needs to be moved to produce a well-focused image 
across the width of the specimen. For simplicity we fixed the light-sheet and its beam waist at </p>

<p>#131581 -$15.00 USD Received 15 Jul 2010; revised 6 Aug 2010; accepted 11 Aug 2010; published 13 Aug 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2010 OSA </p>

<p>
the focal plane of the Olympus microscope and moved the specimen in the x,y,z-axes through 
the light-sheet using Newport 423 linear stages and three Newport motors. This was similar to 
a procedure developed by Buytaert and Dirckx [8]. Figure 1 shows (in the upper left panel) 
TSLIM's original start/stop procedure that was used to move the specimen in the x-direction 
and to collect columns of image data whose width are less than or equal to the confocal 
parameter of the light-sheet. 
Since great accuracy and speed is not necessary in the y-axis, this direction is manually 
controlled by a Newport NSC200, which drives an open-loop Newport CMA-25PP motor 
with a bi-directional repeatability of 4 µm and velocity of 0.4 mm/s. However, in the x-and z-
axes, Newport's computer guided ESP301 motion controller in combination with Newport's 
LTA-HS closed loop servomotors (with a typical bi-directional repeatability of 0.6 µm and 
velocity of 5 mm/s) are used to position the specimen. A <rs type="software">LabVIEW</rs> program coordinates 
image acquisition and motor positioning simultaneously. The image acquisition routine 
consists of grabbing a column of image data from the camera and moving the specimen the 
width of that column and then collecting another column. These columns are stitched together 
to form a composite image across the full width of the specimen. 
Figure 2(a) shows the ROI (i.e., the confocal paramater) in an image of the mouse cochlea. 
The Rayleigh range x R was calculated [1] with the 5X Plan Apo microscopic objective to 
approximately 34 µm and thus the confocal parameter b is 68 µm. To the left and the right of 
the ROI, the image appears out-of-focus due to greater beam thickness and light scattering. In 
addition, a blur is present in the lower left of the image, which is due to the presence of a high 
density structure (i.e. bone) in the cochlea that lies between the optical section and collecting 
lens of the Olympus microscope. However, Fig. 2(b) shows that stitching of multiple ROIs 
across the width of the specimen, results in improved focus of specimen across its width. 
Higher magnification of these stitched image columns [Fig. 2(c)] reveals some stitching 
artifacts due to image column misalignments. </p>

<p>#131581 -$15.00 USD Received 15 Jul 2010; revised 6 Aug 2010; accepted 11 Aug 2010; published 13 Aug 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2010 OSA </p>

<p>
Fig. 2. Optical section of a mouse cochlea before and after stitching. (a). Double white lines 
indicate the confocal region of the light-sheet where the specimen is in focus. Note that to the 
left and right of this region the tissue appears to be out-of-focus due to a thicker beam. (b). 
After stitching of image columns focus appears improved across the width of the specimen. 
Bar = 250 µm for panels a,b. (c). A higher magnification of 2b (above scale bar) showing a 
stitching artifact (arrowhead) and two less noticeable artifacts to the left of the arrowhead. 
Insert in upper left is a 3X magnification of the region outlined in main Fig. and shows the 
stitching artifact in detail. Bar = 50 µm. </p>

<p>#131581 -$15.00 USD Received 15 Jul 2010; revised 6 Aug 2010; accepted 11 Aug 2010; published 13 Aug 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2010 OSA 
1 September 2010 / Vol. 1, No. 2 / BIOMEDICAL OPTICS EXPRESS 602 </p>

<p>In order to produce a stitched image without columns artifacts like shown in Fig. 2(c), it is 
crucial to find a relationship between the moved distance m (µm) and the strip width w ROI 
(pixel). Since the magnification M of the microscope is the factor between its image and the 
original, it is also the major parameter in the relationship between m and w ROI . But because m 
is defined in µm and w ROI in pixels, the correction factor p, defined as the pixel size of the 
camera, is also included in Eq. (1). </p>

<p>ROI </p>

<p>p 
m w 
M </p>

<p>= 
(1) </p>

<p>To ensure that the stitched photos consist of completely focused strips, m is chosen 
smaller than the confocal parameter of 68 µm. Thus, a typical w ROI is 40 pixels or 59.2 µm 
with a 5X zoom and the Retiga 2000R camera (pixel size p 2000R = 7.4 µm). To produce a 
picture of 1200 pixels with 40 pixels per column, it takes ~60 seconds and 30 cycles of 
starting/stopping the servomotor to produce a composite image using a 15mW green laser. To 
optically section a whole mouse cochlea with approximate dimensions of 2 x 1.5 mm it took 
up to 5 hrs and 350 images with a 5 µm z-step size (distance between the pictures in z-
direction). A consequence of this prolonged light exposure is a loss of fluorescence intensity 
in the specimen, i.e, photobleaching. This effect is increased by subsequent sections of the 
specimen that are exposed to the beam before being collected since the unfocused area of the 
beam is significantly larger than the z-step size. Our previous measurements indicated a loss 
of approximately 8.85% in fluorescence intensity to complete one composite image [1]. 
Although the effect is much less than wide-field or confocal microscopy it is detrimental and 
decreases the signal to noise ratio, contrast, and picture quality. 
In addition, artifacts occur in the image due to misalignment of the pixel array of the 
camera to the direction of movement by the servomotors as well as position deviations. The 
latter is due to a difference between the acquired slice width of 40 pixels (59.2 µm) and the 
distance moved by the motor, which exceeds the size of one pixel. Hence the ROI needs to 
include overlapping pixels to minimize the stitching artifacts. However, that procedure 
requires a significant image processing and the overlapping pixels are still visible in the final 
image. That is why the strip width w ROI has to be reduced in order to reduce the influence of 
that distance and improve the image acquisition. This strategy will also reduce the effect of 
the misalignment of the pixel array of the camera chip to the moving direction, which makes 
it even more crucial to consider this requirement for an improvement of the image acquisition. 
A similar optimization strategy for improving the image quality by reducing the strip width 
w ROI was previously described by Buytaert and Dirckx [8]. </p>

<p>2.2 Hardware mastered scan procedure (HMSP) </p>

<p>Since the specimen was already being moved, we decreased the image collection time by 
implementing a continuous x-axis scanning procedure. A slice could be acquired "on the fly" 
without starting and stopping the mechanics, resulting in a significant time savings and 
reducing photobleaching of the specimen. However, such a procedure required accurate 
timing between the motor position and the image acquisition. A TTL trigger pulse was 
generated for the camera by converting and dividing the encoder signals from the Newport 
LTA-HS servomotor. A bypass card was used to break the appropriate signal lines of the 
encoder out of the servo-controller connection. The RS 422 signal was then converted to a 
TTL signal using a Microbotics Inc SLC10422-TTL converter. TTL signal data were then 
acquired by a National Instruments PCI-6221 DAQmx board with an SCB-68 connector 
block. The board is equipped with two counters, which can be armed with different counting, 
timing or generating tasks. One counter is used to count the incoming encoder signals and 
output a TTL impulse after a certain amount of encoder ticks. 
The relationship i between the input and output of ticks depends on the zoom M, the 
resolution of the encoder s i , the pixel size of the camera p and the strip width w ROI by Eq. (2). </p>

<p>#131581 -$15.00 USD Received 15 Jul 2010; revised 6 Aug 2010; accepted 11 Aug 2010; published 13 Aug 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2010 OSA 
1 September 2010 / Vol. 1, No. 2 / BIOMEDICAL OPTICS EXPRESS 603 </p>

<p>ROI </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>p w 
i 
M s </p>

<p>⋅ 
= 
⋅ 
(2) </p>

<p>The resolution of the encoder s i was determined by moving the motor 1 mm and counting 
the encoder signals. One encoder impulse for the Newport LTA-HS is equivalent to s i = 0.14 
µm which is important for the calculation of the relationship i. For example, the Retiga 2000R 
at 5x magnification p/M = 1.48 µm/pixel and when w ROI = 9 lines, an output signal has to be 
generated after every 94 input ticks of the encoder. This signal goes directly over the digital 
output via the SCB-68 connector block into the optic-coupled input of the camera where it 
initiates an exposure of the chip. The pictures are picked up on demand by a loop in the 
controlling <rs type="software">LabVIEW</rs> program. The whole concept for a hardware triggered system is 
summarized in Fig. 3. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Hardware triggering and scanning with both, the Retiga 2000R and the Dalsa HS-40-
04K40 camera. The encoder signal of Newport's LTA-HS servomotor in x-direction of the 
ESP 301 motion controller is bypassed over a custom made card and an RS422-to-TTL 
converter and goes to a National Instrument NI PCIe -6321 Counter/Timer/Trigger Card. This 
card is programmed to divide the rising edge of the received signal by a constant factor and the 
result is an output signal. The signal triggers the Retiga 2000R and the Dalsa HS-40-04K40 by 
a connection to the camera's trigger input channel. </p>

<p>With this system, acquisition is triggered by a hardware signal generated by the motor 
position. That means that there is a constant time gap between the arrival of the specimen at 
the desired position and the exposure of the camera, which makes the system real-time 
capable. This prevents artifacts from being produced by asynchronies between the software 
acquisition loop and the hardware motor position during the scan. One significant 
improvement of this system was that the produced composite images were almost completely 
free from the previous stitching artifacts using the start/stop procedure. Only very rarely did 
an artifact line appear due to a slight movement of the specimen in-between two strips. These 
artifacts were rare and minimal as long as the slice width was small (roughly under 10 lines). </p>

<p>#131581 -$15.00 USD Received 15 Jul 2010; revised 6 Aug 2010; accepted 11 Aug 2010; published 13 Aug 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2010 OSA </p>

<p>
However, since Eq. (2) usually does not return an integer result for the relationship i between 
the input and output of ticks, any result has to be rounded, which can lead to significant 
deviations with respect to the entire image since this deviation is compounded over the whole 
size of the image. Since a 3D reconstruction is used to measure volumes, areas and lengths of 
certain parts of the specimen, we did not want to exceed a ± 1% limit regarding the accuracy 
of the images. 
To compensate for the integer problem of the parameter i, the abilities of the NI PCIe -
6321 data acquisition card were used. The resolution was raised by increasing the number of 
steps per slice i, to minimize the rounding error over the whole image. Since the counters on 
the card can use either the rising or the falling edge, the signal contains more information than 
only the rising edge that is used for dividing the signal. 
This information can be used to increase the resolution of i by leading the incoming signal 
from the encoders to a digital input, which created an event on both the falling and the rising 
edges. A counter generates on each event a signal of two periods with a frequency that is four 
times higher than the one that comes from the encoder (because it is triggered on the falling 
and rising edge of the encoder). This frequency can be calculated over the speed that is given 
on the motor. The signal is counted on the rising edge by the second counter to create an 
output signal that is used to trigger the camera. The resolution was then four times higher than 
before and this increased the accuracy and created a pattern that does not exceed the ± 1% 
limit over the whole magnification range. 
The scanning speed is now only limited by the frame rate of the camera and the motion 
blur, which is caused by an exposure time that exceeds the time of the specimen's movement 
of one pixel. The Retiga 2000R is capable of 100 frames per second (10 ms per picture for 5 
ms exposure time) but for the calculation of the speed, only 80 fps are used (20 fps 
conservatively). It can be converted into a speed limit by using the magnification M and the 
number of lines w ROI , according to Eq. (3). </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>80 
1000 </p>

<p>ROI 
CAM </p>

<p>p 
Hz w 
V 
M </p>

<p>⋅ 
⋅ 
= 
⋅ 
(3) </p>

<p>Furthermore the motion blur time limit depends on exposure time t E itself, the 
magnification M, and the pixel size p, according to Eq. (4). </p>

<p>max EXP 
E </p>

<p>p 
V 
M t 
= ⋅ 
(4) </p>

<p>Since pixel size p is a constant parameter given by the camera, Eq. (3) and (4) show, that 
the maximum speed is either limited by the number of lines per slice or the exposure time for 
certain magnification configurations. That is why both have to be considered to realize an 
optimized scan speed. The acquisition of one strip, with a width of 5 pixels and an exposure 
time of 5 ms, was accomplished in 30 to 40 ms. This procedure allowed us to scan 1200 
pixels in 7.2 sec according to Eq. (5). </p>

<p>30 
1200 
1200 
7.2 
5 </p>

<p>Strip 
pic 
ROI </p>

<p>t 
ms 
t 
s 
w </p>

<p>= 
⋅ 
= 
⋅ 
= 
(5) </p>

<p>To allow time for building the image, the acquisition was only feasible in one direction. 
That is why the total scan time with stitching was about 15 sec per image, which is faster than 
the scan time reported by Buytaert and Dirckx [8] using 200 pixel lines. This procedure 
reduced total stack collection time from 3.5 to 5 hr for the start/stop method to 1.5 hr for the 
continuous scanning method, which was a significant improvement. 
The speed and resolution is only limited by the camera frame rate and exposure time and 
the system has the ability to trigger the camera at an appropriate speed without requiring 
properties that cannot be fulfilled by a line scan camera. Thus, that system is now suitable to </p>

<p>#131581 -$15.00 USD Received 15 Jul 2010; revised 6 Aug 2010; accepted 11 Aug 2010; published 13 Aug 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2010 OSA </p>

<p>
be combined with a line scan camera with a comparable pixel size to the one of the Retiga 
2000R. </p>

<p>2.3 Implementation of a Dalsa TDI line scan camera </p>

<p>With HMSP and its hardware solution, the system had the ability to supply a line scan camera 
with an appropriate trigger signal to achieve a fast and reliable scan. There were only two 
questions that had to be addressed with regard to using a line scan camera over a full-frame 
CCD camera; 1) could the confocal parameter be localized within the optical section and 
adjusted without a full-frame image, and 2), was the line scan camera sensitive enough for 
low light, fluorescent imaging? 
To solve the first problem, that was already identified as crucial in the Buytaert and 
Dirckx [8] paper, we selected a line scan camera with a high resolution in one dimension and 
more than one line in the other. The best solution was Dalsa with its High Sensitivity TDI 
Line Scan Cameras because of its Area and TDI Modes. Area Mode (reading out the entire 
chip in one exposure) was important for stack alignment and localization of the confocal 
parameter within the optical section because it allows the user to view a 96 x 4096 pixel 
picture. TDI Mode solved the second problem of low-light imaging. 
Instead of exposing the chip only once to the object as in a regular line scan camera, the 
TDI Mode allows for the integration of multiple exposures of the same, moving object. That 
means the entire chip of 16 to 96 lines is exposed to the object but only the last line of the 
camera is read out. The other ones are waiting to be accumulated with their following lines 
after the next exposure. The effect is that the integration time is spread out over several 
(depending on the available number of lines) short exposures, which increases the speed 
significantly for low light applications. 
A TDI line scan camera has several requirements. First, high accuracy is required for the 
trigger signal, since the object has to be exactly one pixel size shifted for the next exposure 
compared to the last one. An altering trigger signal would cause an exposure at the wrong 
position of the specimen, which would lead to a blurry image. Second, the trigger signal has 
to be provided with a higher frequency because the integration time is spread out over 16 to 
96 exposures. But with the HMSP we are able to provide both, an accurate trigger signal and a 
high frequency, which made this camera very suitable for TSLIM. 
A third consideration is that the confocal parameter cannot be reduced to the width of one 
pixel as with a regular line scan camera, since at least 16 lines are involved in the picture 
acquisition. However, the combination of the wide field of 4096 pixels and a 10X 
magnification of the Olympus microscope results in a wider field of the specimen that is 
available in a single frame from the line scan camera [Fig. 4(c)] compared to the Retiga 
2000R. But the advantage of more pixels can also be used to increase the magnification by a 
factor of ~2.5 X compared to the Retiga 2000R image. The resolution with the Dalsa camera 
increases while maintaining the same field of view as the Retiga 2000R. This is demonstrated 
in Fig. 4ab using a raw, unprocessed image of Claudius cells/basilar membrane taken from a 
low power image of the entire cochlea at a 5X magnification with the Retiga 2000R in 
Fig. 4(a) compared with a 10X magnification and the Dalsa in Fig. 4(b) (magnification 
increased by the factor of 2 leads to a comparable picture size). According to Eq. (1) we 
achieved a higher resolution and a lower confocal parameter limit of 11.2 µm with that 
system, compared to 59.2 µm for the Retiga, including a pixel size p = 7 µm for the Dalsa 
camera. Thus the confocal parameter limit was reduced to a significantly smaller confocal 
parameter than with a regular CCD camera while not only retaining but increasing the 
scanning speed. </p>

<p>#131581 -$15.00 USD Received 15 Jul 2010; revised 6 Aug 2010; accepted 11 Aug 2010; published 13 Aug 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2010 OSA </p>

<p>
Fig. 4. Comparison between full frame (a) and line scan camera (b) with a higher 
magnification. Due to increased resolution by the line scan camera the image can be enlarged 
more without showing pixelation. Bar = 20µm. (c) Comparison between size of a Retiga CCD 
image in the center panel with the image using the Dalsa camera (full image) at the same 
magnification. The Dalsa camera allows for collection of a larger view of the specimen. The 
dashed lines indicate that the width of the image is not limited because it can be scanned in that 
dimension. Bar = 150µm. </p>

<p>We chose the HS-40-04K40 model for TSLIM because it balances a high vertical 
resolution of 4096 pixels with a sensitive 7 µm pixel size in a chip size that is still compatible 
with the MVX10 Microscope. Since the pixel size is different from the Retiga 2000R camera, 
the accuracy had to be recalculated, but remains close to the ± 1% limit. The Dalsa camera is 
a medium configuration Camera Link camera with 36 kHz readout speed connected to a NI 
PCIe-1427 Camera Link card, as shown in Fig. 3. This card only allowed us to run the camera 
in base configuration with 18 kHz readout speed, which was adequate given our low light 
conditions. 
Since a line scan camera exposes the frame over the entire time between two trigger 
signals, rather than only exposing it over the exposure time, no time is lost between 
acquisitions. Combined with the technology of the TDI mode, it takes approximately 5 sec to 
scan a full-frame, high resolution image (4096x3000 pixels) of the entire cochlea with a 10x 
zoom and 32 integrations without any blur adjustments. That is not only significantly faster 
than the HROPFOS [8] scan but it also allows for greater enlargement of the image without 
pixelation. 
Due to a decrease in the time that it takes to collect a composite image by continuous 
scanning, photobleaching of the fluorochrome within a specimen should also be reduced. To 
test that hypothesis, three 100 pixel square, similar homogenous regions (i.e., compact bone) 
within the mouse cochlea (prepared as described in previous publication [1]) at three different 
z-stack locations were imaged repeatedly for 50 times and the intensity measured after each </p>

<p>#131581 -$15.00 USD Received 15 Jul 2010; revised 6 Aug 2010; accepted 11 Aug 2010; published 13 Aug 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2010 OSA </p>

<p>
composite was produced by the three methods described in this paper (start/stop, continuous 
CCD scan, and continuous line scan). Figure 5 shows that generation of 50 composite images 
that took 1550, 750, and 475 sec for each method respectively and fluorescence intensity was 
retained by 65, 80, 87% respectively. Thus, the line scan camera provided a ~70% reduction 
in the time required for composite image generation and a ~63% reduction (35%-13%/35%). 
in photobleaching of the specimen. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Photobleaching of a specimen following 50 repeated imaging of the same plane of an 
optical section. The start/stop procedure using the CCD camera takes 1550 sec to image 50 
sections and retains 65% of the fluorescence. A continuous scan using the CCD takes only 750 
sec and retains 80% of the fluorescence. A continuous scan with the line scan camera takes 
only 475 sec and retains 87% of the fluorescence making it the best choice for TSLIM 
imaging. </p>

<p>4. Conclusions </p>

<p>As far as we know this is the first description of the implementation of a line scan camera 
with the TDI technology for light-sheet microscopy. The Dalsa camera is well suited for 
imaging fluorescent specimens using scanned, thin-sheet laser microscopy. The TDI mode of 
the camera offers high sensitivity and sophisticated imaging technology to not only provide 
high resolution and low noise images, but also a fast scanning speed. This leads to a more 
efficient collection of the fluorescence and less photobleaching of the specimen. In the area 
mode, it also allows for alignment of the specimen and localization of the confocal region 
within the optical section. TSLIM has been enhanced with hardware and software additions 
that provide for high quality, rapid scans of large tissues such as the mouse cochlea. Due to 
the increased number of pixels in the line scan camera it is possible to image larger specimens 
within a single frame and to discriminate fine details in smaller specimens thanks to higher 
pixel density. This is important when one wants to contain the full height and width of a tissue 
or specimen within one picture of an image stack. In addition, TSLIM also allows us to 
decrease the beam waist and confocal parameter (above a limit of 11.2µm) and thus reveal </p>

<p>#131581 -$15.00 USD Received 15 Jul 2010; revised 6 Aug 2010; accepted 11 Aug 2010; published 13 Aug 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2010 OSA 
1 September 2010 / Vol. 1, No. 2 / BIOMEDICAL OPTICS EXPRESS 608 </p>

<p>finer subcellular structures. These enhancements to TSLIM makes it well suited for producing 
high resolution, optical sections of large tissues. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work was supported by the National Institutes of Deafness and Communication 
Disorders (NIDCD) grant (RO1DC007588-04) and American Recovery and Reinvestment 
funds (RO1DC007588-03S1) and by the Capita Foundation (La Mesa, CA). This research 
was conducted while Peter Schacht was a visiting fellow at the University of Minnesota. He 
performed the engineering aspects of the project and wrote the manuscript. He is currently an 
engineering graduate student at the Technische Universität Ilmenau and received a grant to 
study at the University of Minnesota. Shane B. Johnson is a junior scientist in the Santi 
laboratory and performed the histological aspects of this study and wrote the manuscript. 
Peter A. Santi is a professor of Otolaryngology and Neuroscience at the University of 
Minnesota. He wrote grants that funded this research, proposed and supervised the work, and 
wrote the manuscript. The authors would like to thank Matthias Hillenbrand for critically 
reading of the manuscript and for his useful comments. The animal care and use for this study 
was approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) of the 
University of Minnesota. </p>

<p>#131581 -$15.00 USD Received 15 Jul 2010; revised 6 Aug 2010; accepted 11 Aug 2010; published 13 Aug 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2010 OSA 
1 September 2010 / Vol. 1, No. 2 / BIOMEDICAL OPTICS EXPRESS 609 </p>

</text></tei>