<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3501353" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Millions of platelets are produced each hour by bone marrow (BM) megakaryocytes 
(MKs). MKs extend transendothelial proplatelet (PP) extensions into BM sinusoids and 
shed new platelets into the blood. The mechanisms that control platelet generation 
remain incompletely understood. Using conditional mutants and intravital multiphoton 
microscopy, we show here that the lipid mediator sphingosine 1-phosphate (S1P) serves 
as a critical directional cue guiding the elongation of megakaryocytic PP extensions 
from the interstitium into BM sinusoids and triggering the subsequent shedding of PPs 
into the blood. Correspondingly, mice lacking the S1P receptor S1pr1 develop severe 
thrombocytopenia caused by both formation of aberrant extravascular PPs and defec-
tive intravascular PP shedding. In contrast, activation of S1pr1 signaling leads to the 
prompt release of new platelets into the circulating blood. Collectively, our findings 
uncover a novel function of the S1P-S1pr1 axis as master regulator of efficient throm-
bopoiesis and might raise new therapeutic options for patients with thrombocytopenia. </p>

<p>2166 </p>

<p>S1pr1 controls bone marrow thrombopoiesis | Zhang et al. </p>

<p>CMK, each express the S1P receptor subtypes 1, 2, and 4 
(encoded by S1pr1 and S1PR1, S1pr2 and S1PR2, and S1pr4 
and S1PR4 in mice and humans, respectively; Fig. 1, A-E; and 
Table S1). To directly test whether S1P receptors play a role 
for megakaryo-or thrombopoiesis, we determined platelet 
counts in peripheral blood of WT mice and mice lacking the 
S1P receptors expressed by MKs. Loss of S1pr2 or S1pr4 on 
hematopoietic cells had no significant effects on peripheral 
platelet counts or platelet size (Fig. 1 F, Table S2, and not de-
picted). In contrast, ablation of the S1pr1 gene was associated 
with dramatically reduced platelet numbers. Loss of one S1pr1 
allele (S1pr1 +/ mutants) already resulted in a significant 
reduction in the number of circulating platelets (Fig. 1 G and 
Table S3). Loss of both alleles (S1pr1 / mice) was embryoni-
cally lethal (Liu et al., 2000); thus, to circumvent embryonic 
lethality, we generated chimaeras by transferring fetal liver 
(FL) cells from S1pr1 / , S1pr1 +/ , or S1pr1 +/+ donors into 
irradiated WT mice. 6-8 wk after reconstitution, BM cells 
from S1pr1 / , S1pr1 +/ , or S1pr1 +/+ FL chimaeras were 
isolated and further transplanted into irradiated secondary 
recipient mice. Platelet counts in S1pr1 +/ and S1pr1 / 
chimaeras were reduced by &gt;50% and 70% compared with 
S1pr1 +/+ chimaeras, respectively (Fig. 1 G and Table S2). Col-
lectively, these results indicate that S1pr1 on hematopoietic 
cells controls blood platelet homeostasis, whereas S1pr2 and 
S1pr4 are dispensable for this process. 
Next we evaluated whether S1pr1 expressed by MKs or 
by other hematopoietic lineages regulates the number of 
blood platelets. To this end, we reconstituted irradiated mice 
with BM cells carrying two floxed S1pr1 alleles (S1pr1 fl/fl ) 
and transduced with a lentivirus expressing Cre recombinase 
under the MK-specific GpIIb promoter (GpIIb-Cre S1pr1 fl/fl ) 
to delete S1pr1 in the MK/platelet progeny (Fig. 1 H; 
Allende et al., 2003). Importantly, platelet counts became sig-
nificantly reduced in GpIIb-Cre S1pr1 fl/fl BM recipients as 
compared with S1pr1 fl/fl control chimaeras (Fig. 1 H). More-
over, lentiviral reexpression of S1pr1 under the MK-specific 
GpIb promoter rescued S1pr1 / FL cells to reconstitute 
the blood platelet compartment in lethally irradiated mice 
(Fig. 1 I). These findings demonstrate that S1pr1 expressed by 
the MK lineage intrinsically controls platelet homeostasis. </p>

<p>Normal MK development, platelet life span, 
and serum TPO levels in S1pr1-deficient mice 
What could be the reason for the severe thrombocyto-
penia in the absence of S1pr1? First we showed that the 
life spans of platelets from S1pr1 +/+ , S1pr1 +/ , or S1pr1 / 
chimaeras and between WT and S1pr1 +/ mutant mice 
was similar, excluding a reduced life span as cause for the 
reduced platelet counts (Fig. 2 A). We also excluded a defect 
in the release of TPO, the principle regulator of thrombo-
poiesis (Kaushansky, 2005a), as cause for the thrombocy-
topenia in S1pr1-null mutants (Fig. 2 B). Finally, we also 
could not find evidence for a gross defect in MK develop-
ment, as we found similar numbers of megakaryocytic 
progenitor cells in WT and S1pr1 / FL cells populations </p>

<p>the perivascular niche, where they interact with sinusoidal BM 
endothelial cells (Avecilla et al., 2004; Patel et al., 2005a). Once 
they have settled in the perivascular microenvironment, mature 
MKs form dynamic transendothelial pseudopods, which ex-
tend into the lumen of BM sinusoids. These intravascular pseu-
dopodial extensions, termed proplatelets (PPs), continue to 
elongate and become tapered into multiple platelet-size beads 
connected to each other and with their maternal MKs by thin 
cytoplasmic bridges (Italiano et al., 1999; Patel et al., 2005a). 
The release of platelets, the final step of platelet formation, then 
occurs within the blood, where new platelets are shed as frag-
ments from the tips of intravascular PPs (Stenberg and Levin, 
1989; Choi et al., 1995; Italiano et al., 1999; Junt et al., 2007). 
MKs are a rare cell population, constituting &lt;0.01% of all 
BM cells. This contrasts with the high demand of platelet pro-
duction, implying that the differentiation of MKs (termed 
megakaryocytopoiesis) and the subsequent assembly and re-
lease of platelets by MKs (termed thrombopoiesis) are highly 
efficient and tightly controlled processes. Among the factors 
that modulate megakaryocytopoiesis, thrombopoietin (TPO) 
is the major regulator of MK expansion from hematopoietic 
stem and progenitor cells, whereas chemokines, including 
stromal-derived factor-1 (SDF-1), primarily initiate the relo-
cation of maturing MKs to the perivascular microenviron-
ment (Avecilla et al., 2004). In contrast, the molecular pathways 
that control the final steps of thrombopoiesis, particularly the 
guidance signals that direct megakaryocytic pseudopodial ex-
tensions into the vascular lumen and trigger the intravascular 
release of new platelets, are entirely unknown. 
The bioactive sphingolipid sphingosine 1-phosphate (S1P) 
and the receptors responsive to this mediator regulate impor-
tant biological functions of various hematopoietic cell types 
(Spiegel and Milstien, 2003, 2011; Schwab et al., 2005; 
Massberg et al., 2007), including cell migration in the BM 
compartment (Ishii et al., 2009; Allende et al., 2010). Here we 
report that S1P and the MK S1P receptor S1pr1 receptor are 
indispensable for normal BM thrombopoiesis. Using mouse 
mutants and by multiphoton intravital microscopy (MP-IVM), 
we demonstrate that a transendothelial S1P gradient navigates 
megakaryocytic PP extensions into the lumen of BM sinu-
soids. In the blood, PP extensions are exposed to high S1P 
concentrations, which initiate the subsequent shedding of 
platelets into the circulation. Both processes involve the S1P 
receptor S1pr1, triggering activation of the Gi/Rac GTPase 
signaling. Correspondingly, lack of S1pr1 on MKs, but not of 
other S1P receptors, results in severe thrombocytopenia. Thus, 
we have identified the S1P-S1pr1 pathway as a key nodal 
point integrating guidance cues that navigate directional PP 
elongation and enabling the final step of thrombopoiesis, the 
shedding of new platelets into the blood stream. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
S1pr1 expression in MKs intrinsically regulates 
platelet homeostasis 
We observed here that cultured mouse and human MKs, 
as well as the human megakaryocytic cell lines Meg01 and </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 12 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>

<p>2167 </p>

<p>Figure 1. MKs express S1pr1, and S1pr1-deficient mice display severe thrombocytopenia. (A) Relative expression of S1P receptor mRNA by 
FL-derived mature and immature MKs. (B) Relative expression of S1P receptor mRNA in human megakaryocytic cell lines. (A and B) Data are representative of 
three independent experiments with triplication. (C) Representative immunostaining of S1pr1 in immature and mature FL-derived MKs. WT MKs stained </p>

<p>2168 </p>

<p>S1pr1 controls bone marrow thrombopoiesis | Zhang et al. </p>

<p>in vitro PPF was reduced by &gt;70% in S1pr1 / MKs, as &lt;2 
out of 100 S1pr1 / MKs formed PPs (Fig. 4 A). Importantly, 
lentiviral reexpression of GpIb promoter-driven S1pr1 in 
S1pr1 / MKs corrected PPF in vitro (Fig. 4 B). These results 
clearly indicate that S1pr1 plays a critical and intrinsic role for 
PPF by MKs. 
When we examined how S1pr1 might control PPF, 
we could exclude a primary lack of the invaginated demarca-
tion membrane system (DMS), the predominant reservoir 
for PP membranes (Radley and Haller, 1982; Schulze et al., 
2006), in S1pr1 / MKs, as electron microscopy of S1pr1 / 
BM MKs did not reveal abnormalities of the DMS when 
compared with S1pr1 +/+ BM MKs (Fig. 4 C). Next we tested 
whether S1P serves as a chemoattractant for polarizing MKs 
and for inducing the formation of PP protrusions. Within the 
normal BM compartment, S1P is rapidly degraded by lyases 
and phosphatases expressed by most hematopoietic cells. Thus, 
the local S1P concentrations in the BM (with its densely 
packed hematopoietic cells) are exceedingly low (unpublished 
data), reflecting similar concentrations reported for other tis-
sues such as lymph nodes (Schwab et al., 2005; Pappu et al., 
2007). In contrast, high S1P concentrations exist in the blood 
stream (Caligan et al., 2000; Berdyshev et al., 2005; Pappu 
et al., 2007). Because of their positioning at the vascular inter-
face, MKs are therefore exposed to a steep transendothelial 
S1P gradient. To mimic the situation in the BM, we exposed 
cultured MKs to a gradient of S1P in vitro. Notably, PP 
extensions developed preferentially toward increasing con-
centrations of S1P but not of vehicle (Fig. 4 D). A similar 
result was also obtained with S1pr2 / and S1pr4 / MKs 
(Fig. 4 D). VPC23019, a previously described S1pr1 and S1pr3 
antagonist (Davis et al., 2005), was used in our study to selec-
tively block megakaryocytic S1pr1 signaling because MKs do 
not express S1pr3 (Fig. 1 A). Inhibition of the megakaryo-
cytic S1pr1 using VPC23019 abolished this directionality of 
PPF; MKs projected PP extensions into random directions 
(Fig. 4 D). These findings suggest that S1P-S1pr1 signaling 
is essential for PPF by providing a chemoattractant stimulus 
that controls the polarization of PP processes generated by 
MKs in culture. 
Next we defined the signaling downstream of S1pr1 
involved in the regulation of PPF and polarization. Be-
cause Rac GTPase activity controls actin dynamics leading 
to membrane protrusion/extensions (Aspenström et al., 
2004), we tested whether activation of Rac GTPases via </p>

<p>(Fig. 2 C) and a normal differentiation of WT and S1pr1 / 
precursor cells into MKs both in vitro (Fig. 2 D) and in vivo 
(Fig. 2, E and F). </p>

<p>Loss of S1pr1 increases MK size but has no effect 
on positioning and motility of MKs in vivo 
Next we examined whether S1pr1 controls platelet biogenesis 
for example by modulating MK motility or their positioning 
within the BM compartment. To address this question, we 
performed MP-IVM of calvarian BM (Junt et al., 2007) of 
two different sets of S1pr1 +/+ or S1pr1 / chimaeras, in which 
MKs and their progeny were genetically marked: (a) S1pr1 +/+ 
or S1pr1 / CD41-YFP ki/+ FL chimaeras, in which MKs and 
platelets express the YFP driven from the endogenous CD41 
gene locus (Zhang et al., 2007) and (b) S1pr1 +/+ or S1pr1 / 
lenti-GpIb-enhanced GFP (EGFP) BM chimaeras, in which 
MKs and platelets express EGFP under the transcriptional con-
trol of the murine GpIb promoter (Lavenu-Bombled et al., 
2007). The experiments revealed neither differences in MK 
size nor in their positioning or motility when we compared 
S1pr1 +/+ CD41-YFP ki/+ or S1pr1 +/+ lenti-GpIb-EGFP chi-
maeras and naive (nontransplanted) S1pr1 +/+ CD41-YFP ki/+ 
or platelet factor 4 (Pf4)-EYFP transgenic mice, in which 
EYFP is driven by the MK-specific Pf4 promoter, which 
allowed excluding a major influence of irradiation and BM 
transplantation (Fig. 3, A-D). As reported previously (Junt et al., 
2007), S1pr1 +/+ MKs were large, mostly sessile cells always lo-
cated in close proximity to BM sinusoids (Fig. 3, A and D-G). 
In S1pr1 / chimaeras and S1pr1 +/ mice, MKs were signifi-
cantly larger compared with S1pr1 +/+ chimaeras, whereas the 
position and motility of MKs was similar among all genotypes 
(Fig. 3, E-G). The aforementioned results suggest that in con-
trast to other cells in the BM (Ishii et al., 2009), neither posi-
tioning nor migration of MKs or their committed progenitors 
in marrow spaces is controlled by S1pr1. </p>

<p>S1pr1 is essential for intravascular PP formation (PPF) 
During thrombopoiesis, mature MKs extend transendothelial 
protrusions, termed PPs, into BM microvessels (Junt et al., 
2007). To test whether S1P/S1P receptor signaling plays a role 
during PPF, we cultured MKs in vitro (Lecine et al., 1998) 
and found that on average, 9 out of 100 WT MKs spontane-
ously formed PPs as assessed by phase-contrast microscopy. 
MKs isolated from S1pr2 / and S1pr4 / mice generated 
similar number of PPs (unpublished data). In sharp contrast, </p>

<p>with irrelevant control IgG or anti-S1pr1-stained S1pr1-null MKs served as controls. (D and E) Expression of S1pr1 in murine BM (D) and S1PR1 in human 
BM sections (E). Arrowheads indicate MKs. CD42c is the marker for MKs. All MKs examined stained positive for S1pr1 or S1PR1. Bars, 10 µm. (F) Platelet 
counts in peripheral blood. n = 15 for WT BM chimaeras; n = 5 for S1pr2 / BM chimaeras; n = 3 for S1pr4 / BM chimaeras. (G) Platelet counts in 
peripheral blood. n = 8 for WT; n = 6 for S1pr1 +/ ; n = 15 for WT BM chimaeras; n = 9 for S1pr1 +/ BM chimaeras; n = 14 for S1pr1 / BM chimaeras. 
(H) Platelet counts in chimaeras after transferring S1pr1 fl/fl BM cells transduced with lenti-GPIIb-cre or empty control vectors into irradiated recipient 
mice (left). Expression of S1pr1 in platelets in chimaeras after transferring S1pr1 fl/fl BM cells transduced with lenti-GPIIb-cre or empty control vectors. 
-Actin served as loading control (right). n = 3 per genotype. (I) Percentage of EGFP  platelets in chimaeras after hematopoietic reconstitution of lethally 
irradiated mice with EGFP + S1pr1 +/+ BM cells and EGFP  S1pr1 / FL cells at a ratio of 20:1. The EGFP  S1pr1 / FL cells were transduced with lenti-
GpIb-S1pr1 or empty control vectors before transplantation. n = 3 per genotype. All error bars indicate SEM. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 12 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>indicating that activation of Rac GTPases downstream of 
S1pr1 is required for PPF. 
To evaluate the in vivo relevance of S1P and its receptors 
for PPF, we examined CD41-YFP ki/+ mice by MP-IVM. In 
CD41-YFP ki/+ mice, 59% of all MKs extended plump or long 
PP protrusions into BM sinusoids (Fig. S1 A and Video 1), indi-
cating active participation in platelet biogenesis. PP protrusions </p>

<p>S1pr1 in MKs controls PPF. As reported previously for en-
dothelial cells (Paik et al., 2004), we found that S1P, and 
also the S1pr1-specific agonist SEW2871, enhances Rac 
GTPase activity via S1pr1 in megakaryocytic cell lines 
(Fig. 4, E and F). Conversely, we observed that pharmaco-
logical inhibition of Rac GTPases by NSC23766 com-
pletely abolished PPF in response to S1P in vitro (Fig. 4 G), </p>

<p>Figure 2. Loss of S1pr1 does not change 
platelet life span, serum TPO levels, and 
MK development. (A) Platelet life span as-
says in the indicated genotypes. n = 3-5 per 
genotype. (B) Serum TPO levels. n = 3-5 per 
genotype. (C) Quantification of CFU-MK num-
bers in FL cells. Data are representative of 
three independent experiments with triplica-
tion. (D) Number of mature MKs in cultured FL 
cells. Data are representative of four indepen-
dent experiments with triplication. (E) Repre-
sentative immunostaining of MKs in mouse 
femoral BM. MKs were detected by the MK-
specific marker CD41 (green). DAPI is stained 
blue. Bars, 10 µm. (F) Quantification of MK 
numbers per 20× high-power field in femoral 
BM. n = 3 mice per genotype. All error bars 
represent SEM. </p>



<p>S1pr1 controls bone marrow thrombopoiesis | Zhang et al. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Loss of S1pr1 increases the size but has no effect on the positioning and motility of MKs in vivo. (A) Representative MP-IVM images 
of YFP + or EGFP + MKs (green) in BM. BM microvasculature was visualized by intravenous injection of TRITC-dextran (red). Left, naive (nontransplanted) 
S1pr1 +/+ CD41-YFP ki/+ ; middle left, S1pr1 +/+ ;Pf4-EYFP; middle right, S1pr1 +/+ ;lenti-GPIb-EGFP BM chimaeras; right, S1pr1 +/+ ;CD41-YFP ki/+ FL chimaeras. 
Bars, 20 µm. (B-D) Volumes (B), distances from sinusoids (C), and the instantaneous lateral (x-y) velocity (D) of MKs in the indicated groups. Red lines in 
C indicate medians; red lines in D indicate means. Error bars represent SEM. n = 13-46 MKs per genotype. Data are pooled from three mice each group. 
P-values among the different groups in B-D are &gt;0.05. (E) Surface area of MKs in BM. (F) Distance of MKs from BM sinusoids. (E and F) Red lines indicate 
medians. (G) Instantaneous lateral (x-y) velocity of MKs. Red lines indicate means. (E-G) Data are pooled from three mice each group. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 12 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>

<p>2171 </p>

<p>Figure 4. S1P regulates PPF. (A) The percentage of MKs displaying PPF. PPF is expressed as the percentage of MKs carrying PPs (8,000-10,000 MKs per 
experiment, five independent experiments with triplications). (B) The percentage of MKs displaying PPF in S1pr1 +/+ or S1pr1 / MKs transduced with 
lenti-GpIb-S1pr1 or empty control vectors (3,000-8,000 MKs per experiment, two independent experiments with triplications). (C) Representative elec-
tron micrographs of WT and S1pr1 / MKs in BM. Arrowheads indicate the DMS. Red color highlights the DMS. N, nucleus. (D) The percentage of MKs 
with polarized PPF in the presence or absence of S1P and the S1pr1-specific inhibitor VPC23019 (VPC). n = 127-265 MKs per group. Data are pooled from 
three to five independent experiments. (E) Y10/L8057 cells were incubated with 10 µM S1P or vehicle for 2 min. The activities of Rac-GTP were quantified 
by pull-down assay (n = 5 independent experiments). (F) Y10/L8057 cells were incubated with 1 µM S1pr1 agonist, SEW2871, or vehicle for 5 min. The 
activities of Rac-GTP were quantified by pull-down assay (n = 3 independent experiments). (G) The percentage of MKs displaying PPF in the presence or </p>



<p>S1pr1 controls bone marrow thrombopoiesis | Zhang et al. </p>

<p>fragmentation at high S1P concentrations, mimicking S1P 
plasma levels but not at low concentrations prevailing in the 
BM interstitium (Fig. 5, C and D). 
In vivo, blood flow-induced shear stress might facilitate 
the separation of intravascular cell fragments from MKs (Junt 
et al., 2007). We therefore evaluated whether S1P also plays 
a role for PP fragmentation under flow conditions. Cultured 
MKs exposed to the physiological shear stress of BM sinu-
soids (4 dynes/cm 2 ; Junt et al., 2007) in the absence of S1P 
(serum-free buffer) rarely shed PPs from their MK stems. In 
contrast, in the presence of 5 µM S1P, PPs were rapidly re-
leased (Fig. 5, E and F; and Video 5), indicating that S1P is 
required for PP shedding under static as well as flow condi-
tions. Loss of S1pr2 or S1pr4 did not affect S1P-induced PP 
shedding (Fig. 5 B, Fig. S1 B, and Video 6). However, lack 
of the megakaryocytic S1pr1 receptor completely abolished 
S1P-induced release of PPs (Fig. 5 B, Fig. S1 B, and Video 6). 
This indicates that S1pr1, but not S1pr2 or S1pr4, plays the 
predominant role for S1P-driven PP shedding. To further 
clarify the involved signaling pathway, we used pertussis toxin 
and NSC23766 to inhibit Gi and Rac GTPase activity, re-
spectively. Both inhibitors blocked S1P-induced fragmenta-
tion of PPs (Fig. 5 B and Fig. S1 B). The observation that 
S1P activates Rac GTPase in MKs via S1pr1 (Fig. 4, E and F) 
together with the aforementioned findings suggests that 
S1P-induced PP fragmentation depends on S1pr1/Gi/Rac 
GTPase signaling. </p>

<p>S1P controls PP shedding into blood via S1pr1 in vivo 
To address whether S1P-S1pr1 signaling is also essential for 
PP fragmentation in vivo, we examined PP shedding in live 
mice by MP-IVM. PP shedding from MKs was a frequent 
event in naive (nontransplanted) S1pr1 +/+ CD41-YFP ki/+ 
transgenic mice (Junt et al., 2007) but also in S1pr1 +/+ CD41-
YFP ki/+ BM chimaeras (Video 7). Most MKs shed PP frag-
ments that consist of beaded platelet-like structures (Fig. 6, 
A and B; and Video 7), which generate mature platelets by 
undergoing consecutive fragmentation steps (Behnke and 
Forer, 1998; Junt et al., 2007). More than 60% of the S1pr1 +/+ 
MKs carrying intravascular PP processes showed fragmenta-
tion within 1 h (Fig. 6, A and B; and Video 7). We did not find 
any defect in PP fragmentation in S1pr2 / or S1pr4 / 
mice (Fig. 6 A), whereas this process was severely impaired in 
S1pr1 mutants. In S1pr1 / chimaeras, we barely observed 
intravascular PP processes because of the aberrant interstitial 
PPF reported above (Fig. 4, H and I). However, 70-100% of 
the PP processes that had eventually made their way into BM </p>

<p>extended almost exclusively into marrow sinusoids of CD41-
YFP ki/+ mice, whereas we rarely detected extravascular PP 
processes (Fig. 4, H and I; and Video 2). To determine whether 
the S1P receptors expressed by MKs provide the guidance 
information necessary to direct PP processes into BM 
sinusoids, we examined S1pr1 +/ CD41-YFP ki/+ , S1pr2 / 
CD41-YFP ki/+ , and S1pr4 / CD41-YFP ki/+ mice as well as 
lenti-GpIb-EGFP BM chimaeras. Consistent with our in 
vitro findings (Fig. 4 D), loss of S1pr2 or S1pr4 did not affect 
the formation or polarization of PPs in vivo (Fig. 4, H and I). 
In contrast, loss of S1pr1 disrupted PPF and polarization; cor-
respondingly, S1pr1 +/ or S1pr1 / MKs projected PP ex-
tensions in random directions (Fig. 4, H and I; and Video 2). 
As a consequence, we found aberrant PP processes in the mar-
row interstitial space, whereas intrasinusoidal PPs were rarely 
detected in S1pr1-deficient chimaeras (Fig. 4, H and I; and 
Video 2). Likewise, when we treated S1pr1 +/+ CD41-YFP ki/+ 
mice with the S1pr1-specific antagonist W146 for 24 h, the 
physiological directionality of PPF was entirely disrupted. We 
frequently observed long cytoplasmic extensions outside si-
nusoids in mice treated with W146 but not in vehicle-treated 
animals (Fig. 4, H and I; and Video 3). In addition, inhibition 
of S1pr1 also retarded PP growth in vivo, resembling the re-
duced PPF of cultured S1pr1 / MKs in vitro (Fig. 4, A and J). 
These results indicate that S1pr1 signaling supports PPF and 
elongation along the physiological S1P gradient between BM 
interstitium and BM sinusoids and controls the entry of PPs 
into the marrow blood stream in vivo. </p>

<p>S1P enhances PP fragmentation via S1pr1 in vitro 
Once MK PP processes have entered the blood, they are ex-
posed to significantly higher S1P concentrations compared 
with the BM interstitium (unpublished data). To our surprise, 
when we mimicked the situation in the blood by incubating 
cultured MKs to allow PPF and then adding a high concen-
tration of S1P (instead of exposing MKs to an S1P gradient), 
we found a significant reduction in the number of MKs dis-
playing PP extensions (Fig. 5 A). Using differential interfer-
ence contrast (DIC) microscopy of cultured MKs, we observed 
that exposure of MKs to a high, homogenous concentration 
of S1P results in almost immediate shedding of platelet-like 
particles from PPs (Fig. S1 B and Video 4). Within 1 h, platelet-
like particles were shed from 26% of PPs in response to 
S1P but only from 3% of PPs treated with vehicle (Fig. 5 B). 
To further quantify the effect of S1P on PP shedding in vitro, 
we determined the number of fragmentation events by 
flow cytometry (Fig. 5 C). S1P, but not vehicle, increased PP </p>

<p>absence of 50 µM NSC23766, a Rac GTPase inhibitor (4,000-7,000 MKs per experiment; three independent experiments with triplications). (H) Representa-
tive MP-IVM images of MKs with YFP + or EGFP + PPs. Green indicates MKs and PPs; red indicates sinusoids. Arrowheads indicate extravascular YFP + or 
EGFP + PPs; arrows indicate interstitial YFP + or EGFP + PPs. The inset shows magnification for the dotted box. The arrow in the inset indicates the connec-
tion between extravascular YFP + PPs. Bars: (C) 2 µm; (H) 20 µm. (I) MKs displaying intrasinusoidal PPF in vivo presented as a percentage of all MKs carry-
ing PPs (20-30 MKs per group; five independent experiments for WT; three independent experiments for other genotypes). (J) The lateral (x-y) speed of PP 
elongation was measured in naive (nontransplanted) S1pr1 +/+ CD41-YFP ki/+ mice, S1pr1 +/ CD41-YFP ki/+ mice, and S1pr1 +/+ CD41-YFP ki/+ mice treated with 
W146. Red lines indicate means. Data are pooled from three mice each group. All error bars indicate SEM. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 12 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>

<p>2173 </p>

<p>Figure 5. The effect of S1P on PP fragmentation in vitro. (A) The number of MKs displaying PPF in the absence or presence of 10 µM S1P (230-590 
MKs per experiment; three independent experiments with triplications). (B) The number of PPs with or without fragmentation observed by DIC microscopy 
in vitro over 1 h in the indicated groups. Data are pooled from 4-10 independent experiments for each group (n = 30-60 per group). (C) Representative 
dot plots show flow cytometric analyses of PP fragmentation. The first two panels show the gates for PPs. The CD41 + CD61 + population was analyzed for 
the distribution of PPs according to FSC and SSC. MKs are G3; PPs with higher and lower FSC values are G2 and G1, respectively. The three representative 
microphotographs in the right show a representative brightfield image, as well as tubulin and CD41 stainings of fragments sorted using the gating strat-
egy illustrated in the two plots. (D) Flow cytometric analyses of the PP fragmentation index in the presence or absence of various concentrations of S1P. 
The PP fragmentation index was calculated as described in Materials and methods. Data are representative of six independent experiments with triplica-
tion. (E) PP fragmentation by MKs exposed to shear stress. The efficiency of dynamic PP fragmentation was calculated as described in Materials and 
methods. Data are pooled from five independent experiments for each group. (F) Representative time-lapse video microscopy of PPs in the presence or 
absence of 5 µM S1P under shear stress (4 dynes/cm 2 ). Arrows indicate direction of flow; arrowheads indicate PP shedding events. All error bars indicate 
SEM. Bars: (C) 10 µm; (F) 20 µm. </p>



<p>S1pr1 controls bone marrow thrombopoiesis | Zhang et al. </p>

<p>Figure 6. The effect of S1P on PP fragmentation in vivo. (A) Percentage of PP fragmentation events observed by MP-IVM over 1 h in the indicated 
groups. n = 13-33 per group. Data are pooled from three to seven independent experiments. (B) Role of S1pr1 for PP shedding in vivo visualized by MP-IVM. 
Representative MP-IVM sequences show that WT MKs frequently shed PPs as shown in the first and the third rows. The inset shows a magnification 
of a shed PP particle. Asterisks show embedded platelet-like particles. Inhibition or loss of S1pr1 abolishes PP shedding (second and fourth rows). Arrow-
heads indicate intrasinusoidal PPs, and arrows show extrasinusoidal PPs in S1pr1 / chimaeras. The dashed lines highlight the sinusoids. Green or yellow </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 12 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>

<p>2175 </p>

<p>S1pr1 agonists enhance platelet production 
Modulation of S1P receptors by FTY720 (fingolimod) has 
become a promising strategy for the treatment of patients 
with multiple sclerosis (Kappos et al., 2006). Here, we show 
that treatment of mice with a single dose of FTY720 leads 
to a prompt and transient increase in circulating platelets 
(Fig. 7 A). When we used MP-IVM to examine MKs before 
and after treatment with a single dose of FTY720, we found 
that FTY720 accelerates the shedding of intravascular PP ex-
tensions into the blood stream. As a consequence, the number 
of MKs carrying intravascular PPs significantly decreased 
immediately after a single dose of FTY720 compared with 
vehicle (Fig. 7, B and C). This suggests that FTY720 repre-
sents an agonist for megakaryocytic S1pr1 receptors and has 
the potential to rapidly mobilize PPs into the blood, most 
likely by supporting fragmentation of intravascular PPs (Fig. 7, 
B and C). Treatment with the S1pr1-specific agonist SEW2871 
also caused an increase in circulating blood platelets (Fig. 7 D), 
further supporting that activation of S1P-S1pr1 receptor sig-
naling enhances thrombopoiesis. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Our results assign a new role for S1P and its receptor S1pr1 
as master regulators of thrombopoiesis. In a dose-dependent 
and sequential manner, S1P controls two key steps in the 
cascade of thrombopoiesis by BM MKs: (1) the polarized 
development of PP extensions into the blood stream and 
(2) the subsequent shedding of PPs from their transendothe-
lial stems. As a consequence, loss of S1pr1 is not compatible 
with normal thrombopoiesis. Collectively, our findings 
uncover the molecular pathway that enables the final steps 
of thrombopoiesis. </p>

<p>S1P navigates PP extensions into BM sinusoids 
and initiates platelet release 
Mature MKs form intravascular PP extensions that grow from 
the MK cell body at a mean speed of 10 µm/min under shear 
conditions in vivo (Fig. 4 J), with the DMS functioning as the 
membrane reservoir for PP elongation (Schulze et al., 2006). 
During elongation, PPs are equipped with specific proteins 
associated with platelets, including von Willebrand factor 
(vWF) and fibrinogen receptors. Microtubules, assembled 
from /-tubulin dimers, are the primary structural compo-
nent of the engine that drives the elongation of PPs. Corre-
spondingly, PPs fail to form when cultured MKs are exposed 
to agents that inhibit microtubule assembly (Italiano et al., 1999) 
or sliding (Patel et al., 2005b), and mice lacking 1-tubulin, </p>

<p>sinusoids remained firmly attached to their MK stems; only in 
rare instances did MKs release PP fragments (Fig. 6, A and B; 
and Video 7). Together, these data indicate that S1pr1 is criti-
cal for both directional PPF and for proper intravascular PP 
fragmentation. Defective PP shedding is likely to explain the 
increase in size of S1pr1 / MKs (Fig. 3 E). Interestingly, the 
frequency of intravascular PP shedding was only moderately 
reduced in CD41-YFP ki/+ S1pr1 +/ mice (Fig. 6 A), suggest-
ing that a single S1pr1 allele is sufficient to maintain intra-
vascular PP shedding and that the mild thrombocytopenia 
observed in S1pr1 +/ mice is mostly caused by a defect in 
navigating PP processes into BM sinusoids (Fig. 4, H and I). 
To examine whether S1pr1 regulates the dynamic process 
of PP shedding independently from its effects on PP invasion 
into BM sinusoids, we next tested the consequences of short-
term pharmacological inhibition of S1pr1. We treated naive 
(nontransplanted) S1pr1 +/+ CD41-YFP ki/+ mice with a single 
dose of the selective S1pr1 antagonist W146 and visualized PP 
shedding immediately thereafter. In contrast to protracted inhi-
bition or genetic ablation of S1pr1 (Fig. 4, H and I), this did not 
affect the overall number of MKs with intravascular PP protru-
sions. However, &lt;20% of MKs with established intravascular 
protrusions managed to release PP fragments into the blood 
stream within 6 h after administration of W146; the vast ma-
jority of the intrasinusoidal processes remained attached to their 
MK stems (Fig. 6, A and B; and Video 8). Repetitive treatment 
of mice with W146 for 24 h resulted in a significant reduction 
in circulating young reticulated platelets with an elevated RNA 
content (Fig. 6 C), consistent with a central role of the S1P-
S1pr1 pathway for PP fragmentation and release of platelets. 
Short-term treatment with W146 also reduced platelet counts 
in CD1 mice (Fig. 6 D), suggesting that S1pr1 controls throm-
bopoiesis across different strains of mice. W146 maintains an 
adequate in vivo receptor blockade for only 5-6 h (Sanna et al., 
2006), and shedding reoccurred 6 h after a single dose of W146, 
suggesting that S1pr1 inhibition does not affect the viability of 
MKs (Fig. 6 A and Video 8). In rare instances, where PP shed-
ding occurred in the presence of the S1pr1 inhibitor W146, the 
time required until an intravascular fragment dissociated from 
its MKs stem was significantly prolonged (Fig. 6 E). The failure 
to properly shed PPs resulted in the formation of abnormal, 
thick intravascular PP processes (Video 8). In line with this 
observation, the few PP fragments that were released despite 
the presence of W146 were significantly bigger compared with 
those in vehicle-treated control mice (Fig. 6 F), reminiscent of 
the large platelets observed in S1pr1-null chimaeras (Fig. 6 G 
and Table S2). </p>

<p>indicates MKs and PPs; red indicates sinusoids. Bars, 20 µm. (C) Circulating reticulated (young) platelets in mice treated with W146, an S1pr1-specific 
antagonist, or vehicle as assessed by flow cytometry. n = 3 mice each group. (D) Circulating platelet counts in CD1 mice treated with W146 or vehicle. n = 4 
mice each group. (E) The time point of fragmentation detected by MP-IVM in mice treated with W146 (&lt;6 h) or vehicle. Data are pooled from three 
independent experiments each group. (F) Volumes of PP fragments in mice treated with W146 (within 6 h) or vehicle. Red lines indicate means. Data are 
pooled from three independent experiments each group. (G) Mean platelet volume in the indicated genotypes. n = 8 for WT; n = 6 for S1pr1 +/ ; n = 15 
for WT BM chimaeras; n = 9 for S1pr1 +/ BM chimaeras; n = 14 for S1pr1 / BM chimaeras. All values are mean and SEM. </p>



<p>S1pr1 controls bone marrow thrombopoiesis | Zhang et al. </p>

<p>fragments break down further in the circulation giving rise to 
mature platelets of 2-3-µm diameter within the circulation 
(Stenberg and Levin, 1989). Blood shear stress contributes to 
the shedding of PPs (Junt et al., 2007; Dunois-Lardé et al., 
2009; Thon et al., 2010); however, whether additional signals 
are required for efficient PP shedding was completely un-
known. In this study, we show that hydrodynamic forces alone 
are not sufficient to allow the release of new platelets from 
MK PP extensions. Instead, we found that high concentra-
tions of the bioactive lipid S1P prevailing in the sinusoidal 
blood, but not in the BM interstitium, are mandatory for the 
release of new platelets from MKs. 
From a teleological point of view, the S1P-dependent 
sequential guidance of thrombopoiesis comprising (a) di-
rectional PPF along a transendothelial S1P gradient and 
(b) subsequent S1P-dependent intravascular PP shedding 
leads to the introduction of naive platelets into the circulating 
blood and prevents aberrant platelet production within the 
BM interstitium. S1P guidance of intravascular PPF, elonga-
tion, and shedding therefore provides grounds for efficient 
thrombopoiesis, which seems instrumental given the relative 
paucity of MKs. </p>

<p>S1P controls thrombopoiesis via megakaryocytic 
S1pr1 receptors 
Our study shows that MKs robustly express three different 
S1P receptors, S1pr1, S1pr2, and S1pr4. Loss of S1pr1 on he-
matopoietic cells and also conditional deficiency of S1pr1 in 
MKs were associated with severe thrombocytopenia. More-
over, gain of S1pr1 function in S1pr1 / MKs rescued their </p>

<p>the most abundant -tubulin in platelets, develop thrombo-
cytopenia (Schwer et al., 2001). 
Cultured MKs form PPs that elongate into random direc-
tions (Italiano et al., 1999; Dunois-Lardé et al., 2009). In con-
trast, we show here by MP-IVM that PPF occurs in a highly 
polarized fashion in the BM in vivo. This suggests that PPs 
integrate a previously unknown guidance signal, which navi-
gates them into the intravascular compartment and avoids the 
interstitial BM compartment. Our study has uncovered this 
guidance signal and shows that a transendothelial S1P gradi-
ent in the BM controls the directionality of PPF and elonga-
tion. We observed that the interstitial S1P concentrations in 
the BM are low, whereas the S1P blood concentration is 
orders of magnitude higher. Residing at the vascular interface, 
mature MKs are located in a particularly strategic position for 
integrating the guidance cues provided by the transendothe-
lial S1P gradient. Equipped with S1pr1, they sense the steep 
vascular S1P gradient and extend dynamic PP protrusions 
into microvessels along increasing concentrations of this lipid 
mediator. A similar S1P gradient also exists in the lymph node 
between lymph node interstitium and the lymph fluid, where 
it drives the migration of T cells into efferent lymph vessels 
(Matloubian et al., 2004). Recent observations showing that 
the S1P pathway controls the egress of lymphocytes from the 
BM into the blood stream emphasize the biological relevance 
of the transendothelial S1P gradient for BM homeostasis 
(Allende et al., 2010). 
Once MKs have successfully extended their PPs into the 
blood, they release fragments from the tips of their intravas-
cular projections (Video 7; Junt et al., 2007). These new PP </p>

<p>Figure 7. The S1P analogue FTY720 and 
SEW2871 trigger rapid release of platelets. 
(A) Mice were treated with a single dose of 
FTY720 (3 mg/kg i.p.) or DMSO (vehicle). Open 
bars indicate baseline of platelet counts assessed 
before drug administration; closed bars indicate 
platelet counts measured 12 h after drug admin-
istration. n = 9 mice each group. (B) Representa-
tive MP-IVM images of MKs with YFP + PPs from 
CD41-YFP ki/+ mice before and 8 h after a single 
injection of FTY720 (3 mg/kg i.p.) or DMSO 
(vehicle). Green indicates MKs and PPs; 
red indicates sinusoids. Arrowheads indicate 
intravascular PPs. Dashed lines indicate BM 
sinusoidal vessels. Bars, 20 µm. (C) Fold change 
of MKs displaying PPF 8 h after a single injection 
of FTY720 (3 mg/kg i.p.) or DMSO (vehicle) com-
pared with numbers recorded before treatment. 
n = 120-140 MKs per group. Data are pooled 
from three independent experiments. (D) Mice 
were treated with a single dose of SEW2871 
(20 mg/kg i.p.) or dimethyl formamide (DMF; 
vehicle). Open bars indicate baseline of platelet 
counts assessed before drug administration; 
closed bars indicate platelet counts measured 
12 h after drug administration. n = 3 mice each 
group. All error bars indicate SEM. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 12 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>

<p>2177 </p>

<p>strategy and is currently being used in patients with relapsing 
multiple sclerosis (Kappos et al., 2006). After administration, 
FTY720 is metabolized to phosphorylated FTY720 (FTY720P), 
an agonist for four of the five S1P receptors including S1pr1. 
FTY720 limits effector lymphocyte egress from lymph nodes 
(Matloubian et al., 2004), contributing to its immunosuppres-
sive actions. However, FTY720 has not been examined for its 
potential effects on megakaryo-and thrombopoiesis. In this 
study, we show that treatment of mice with a single dose of 
FTY720 leads to shedding of intravascular PP extensions into 
the blood stream, paralleled by a prompt, but transient in-
crease in circulating platelets. This suggests that FTY720 acts 
as an agonist on megakaryocytic S1pr1 receptors and has the 
potential to rapidly mobilize PPs into the blood, most likely 
by supporting fragmentation of intravascular PPs. Whereas 
lymphocyte S1pr1 engagement by phosphorylated FTY720 
within secondary lymphoid organs triggers down-modula-
tion of the receptor, resulting in functional antagonism of the 
S1pr1 pathway, an agonistic effect of FTY720 similar to the 
one observed here for MK has recently been reported to pro-
mote the recirculation of BM osteoclast precursor monocytes 
from the bone surface (Ishii et al., 2009). This indicates that 
FTY720 predominantly exerts agonist effects in cells of the 
myeloid lineage. Because activation of S1P-S1pr1 receptor 
signaling enhances thrombopoiesis in mice, future studies will 
have to evaluate potential clinical implications of S1pr1 ago-
nists, in particular in the treatment of thrombocytopenia. 
Collectively, the present study reveals that S1P, a signaling 
lipid circulating in the blood, regulates dynamic intravascular 
PP elaboration and PP shedding without affecting MK matu-
ration and positioning. Tonic S1P-S1pr1 signaling is critical 
for normal thrombopoiesis in mice. Although the exact role 
of S1P-S1pr1 signaling for human thrombopoiesis still needs 
to be defined, our findings could have clinical implications 
and provide new approaches to treat thrombocytopenia. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Mice. C57BL6/J (CD45.2), B6.SJL-Ptprc a Pep3 b /BoyCrl (CD45.1), and CD1 
mice were purchased from Charles River. -Actin-EGFP mice were pro-
vided by A. Wagers (Harvard Medical School, Boson, MA). S1pr1 +/ and 
S1pr2 / mice were generated as described previously (Liu et al., 2000; Kono 
et al., 2004). S1pr4 / mice were provided by D. Guerini (Novartis Institutes 
for BioMedical Research, Basel, Switzerland). CD41-YFP ki/+ mice were 
generated as described previously (Zhang et al., 2007). Pf4-cre and ROSA26-
flox-stop-flox-EYFP mice were obtained from the Jackson Laboratory and 
crossed to get Pf4-EYFP transgenic mice, in which EYFP is driven by the 
MK-specific Pf4 promoter. FL chimaeras and BM chimaeras were generated 
as described previously (Massberg et al., 2007). Cytometric analysis showed 
that &gt;95% of the blood cells were derived from donors in all the BM chi-
maeras. S1pr1 fl/fl mice were obtained from R.L. Proia. Age-and gender-
matched mice in a C57BL/6 background were used in all experiments. All 
experimental procedures performed on animals met the requirements of the 
German legislation on the protection of animals. </p>

<p>Blood cells and serum TPO measurements. We measured blood cell 
counts in the mice before and 12 h after a single injection of FTY720 
(3 mg/kg i.p.; Cayman) or DMSO (Sigma-Aldrich) as vehicle. Platelet counts 
were assessed in the mice before and 12 h after a single injection of SEW2871 
(20 mg/kg i.p.; Cayman) or dimethyl formamide (Sigma-Aldrich). Serum 
TPO was measured using the Quantikine murine TPO Immunoassay kit </p>

<p>defect in platelet production. These results clearly demon-
strate that S1pr1 expressed by the MK lineage intrinsically 
controls platelet homeostasis. It has been shown previously 
that signaling via S1pr1 activates Rac GTPases in multiple 
hematopoietic lineages, including T cells (Matsuyuki et al., 
2006; Gérard et al., 2009). Consistent with this, we observed 
here that Rac activation is triggered in MKs by S1pr1 ago-
nists. Rac GTPases are known to regulate actin dynamics and 
induce the formation of membrane extensions (Aspenström 
et al., 2004). In MKs, the turnover of actin filaments is known 
to control platelet formation (Bender et al., 2010). Corre-
spondingly, we found here that Rac GTPase activation 
leading to cytoskeletal reorganization is indispensable for 
S1P-S1pr1-driven PPF and fragmentation. Although we 
observed that simultaneous pharmacological inhibition of all 
Rac GTPases by NSC23766 virtually abolishes S1P-driven 
thrombopoiesis in vitro, loss of Rac1 alone does not lead to 
thrombocytopenia in vivo (McCarty et al., 2005), suggesting 
that other Rac GTPase family members, including Rac2, 
Rac3, and RhoG, may have redundant functions in thrombo-
poiesis and its control by S1P. In addition, we cannot rule out 
that other small Rho GTPases, including cdc42 and RhoA 
(Pleines et al., 2010; Pleines et al., 2012), also contribute to 
S1P-driven platelet generation by MKs. 
Unlike the loss of S1pr1, genetic disruption of S1pr2 
or S1pr4 on hematopoietic cells was not associated with 
thrombocytopenia. Moreover, loss of S1pr2 or S1pr4 did not 
result in any gross defect of MK development, directional 
PPF or PP fragmentation in vitro or in vivo. In line with this 
finding, one recent study demonstrated that S1pr4-deficient 
mice have normal numbers of BM MKs and normal platelet 
counts under physiological conditions (Golfier et al., 2010). 
Despite its irrelevance for maintenance of physiological blood 
platelet counts, S1pr4 was reported to play a subtle role in the 
terminal differentiation of MKs and PPF (Golfier et al., 2010), 
an effect which we did not observe here in several sets of 
in vitro and in vivo assays, most likely because of the different 
experimental conditions. Collectively, our present study and 
the previous study (Golfier et al., 2010) suggest that S1pr1, 
but not S1pr2 or S1pr4, plays a primary role in the control of 
thrombopoiesis under physiological conditions. 
In contrast to other cells within the BM compartment, 
including osteoclast precursors (Ishii et al., 2009) and lympho-
cytes (Allende et al., 2010), MKs clearly do not require S1pr1 
signaling for migration and positioning. This corroborates 
previous studies showing that these processes are predomi-
nantly orchestrated by fibroblast growth factor-4 (FGF-4) and 
SDF-1 (Majka et al., 2000; Avecilla et al., 2004). Likewise, loss 
of S1pr1 does not affect proliferation and maturation of mega-
karyocytic progenitor cells into platelet-producing MKs. This 
is consistent with the concept that megakaryopoiesis is regu-
lated predominantly by TPO (Kaushansky, 2005b). </p>

<p>S1P receptor agonist increases blood platelet counts 
Recently, modulation of S1P receptor signaling by FTY720 
(fingolimod) has emerged as a promising immunosuppressive </p>



<p>S1pr1 controls bone marrow thrombopoiesis | Zhang et al. </p>

<p>Lentiviral infection of FL or BM cells. The different lentiviral con-
structs were derived from the pTRIP U3 EF1-EGFP vector (a gift from 
P. Charneau, Institut Pasteur, Paris, France). The EF1 promoter was replaced 
by a 541-bp core promoter fragment (254 to 287) of the murine GPIb 
promoter to obtain the vector pTRIP U3 mGPIb-EGFP. The GFP open 
reading frame was removed, and the coding region for murine S1pr1 was in-
serted to obtain the vector pTRIP U3 mGIb-mS1pr1. A subcloned DNA 
fragment containing a 921-bp fragment of the human GPII promoter (889 
to 32), and the Cre coding sequence was directly cloned into the vector 
pTRIP U3 EF1-EGFP to obtain the vector pTRIP U3 hGPIIb-Cre. 
BM or FL cells were incubated with lentiviral particles in the presence 
of 8 µg/ml polybrene (Sigma-Aldrich) at 37°C for 12 h in serum-free me-
dium supplemented with 1% BSA, 100 ng/ml Flt3-ligand, 100 ng/ml stem 
cell factor (Sigma-Aldrich), 20 ng/ml TPO (ImmunoTools). After transduc-
tion with lentiviral vectors, BM and FL cells were injected into irradiated 
mice (two doses of 6.5 Gy). For reexpression of S1pr1 in S1pr1 / MKs, 
S1pr1 / FL cells were transduced with lenti-GPIb-S1pr1 viral vectors to 
express S1pr1 under the control of MK promoter GPIb. 10 5 S1pr1 / FL 
cells transduced with lenti-GPIb-S1pr1 or empty lentiviral vector and 2 × 
10 6 BM cells from -actin-EGFP mice were coinjected into irradiated 
CD45.1 mice. The percentage of EGFP-positive platelets was determined by 
flow cytometry. Because the donor chimaerism in peripheral whole blood of 
all generated chimaeras was &gt;99% and 100% of platelets from -actin-EGFP 
mice were EGFP positive, almost all EGFP-negative platelets were from 
S1pr1 / FL donor cells. For conditional deletion of S1pr1 in MKs, S1pr1 fl/fl 
BM cells were transduced with lenti-GPIIb-cre viral vectors to express 
Cre recombinase under the control of MK promoter GPIIb and transferred 
into irradiated mice. S1pr1 floxed allele was excised in MKs in S1pr1 fl/fl 
BM chimaeras. </p>

<p>Flow cytometry. We analyzed the mean platelet sizes as described previ-
ously (Gramaglia et al., 2005). We performed platelet life span assays as 
described previously (Robinson et al., 2000). We used Thiazole orange 
(Molecular Probes) to stain residual RNA in juvenile, reticulated platelets 
and detected them by flow cytometry as described previously (Matic et al., 
1998). For analysis of PP fragmentation, FL-derived MK cultures were treated 
with various concentrations of S1P or vehicle for 4 h and then stained with 
CD41-FITC and CD61-PE (BD) antibodies. The PP fragmentation index is 
determined by the percentage of G1 in the PP population (G1 + G2; Fig. 5 C). 
We collected the PP fraction according to the gate in Fig. 5 C using a FAC-
SAria cell sorter and then observed the sorted PPs using brightfield micro-
scopy (Fig. 5 C). </p>

<p>Western blot analyses. Y10/L8057 mouse megakaryocytic cells were 
cultured in IMDM supplemented with 10% FCS and 25 ng/ml TPO for 1 d 
and then starved overnight on 100-mm dishes coated with 0.5% fatty acid-free 
BSA (Sigma-Aldrich). The starved Y10/L8057 cells were simulated with 
10 µM S1P or vehicle for 2 min or 1 µM SEW2871 or vehicle for 5 min. Rac-
GTP activities were measured using Rac assay kit (Cell Biolabs). Platelet ly-
sates were subjected to SDS-PAGE and then immunoblotted with antibodies 
recognizing murine S1pr1 (Imgenex) or -actin (Abcam) as loading controls. </p>

<p>Multiphoton intravital imaging of the BM. We prepared the mouse cal-
varian BM as described previously (Junt et al., 2007). We used a BioTech 
TriMScope system (LaVision BioTec) and Ti: Sa laser (MaiTai) to capture 
images through a 20× water immersion objective lens (NA = 0.95; Olym-
pus). Images were acquired with ImSpectorPro (LaVision BioTec). For 
three-dimensional (3D) acquisition, the stacks were acquired at a 920-nm 
wavelength at vertical spacing of 2-3 µm to cover an axial depth of 30-100 µm 
(for YFP or EGFP). Subsequently, the same stacks were acquired at a wave-
length of 800 nm (for TRITC-dextran). The distances between MKs and 
vasculatures were measured in the reconstructed 3D structure using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Volocity</rs> 
software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">PerkinElmer</rs>). If MKs were outside the vessels, the closest distance 
from MKs to vessels was measured and represented as negative values. If MKs 
were in direct physical contact with the vessels, the distance was regarded as </p>

<p>(R&amp;D Systems). To block S1pr1 in vivo, we treated C57BL6/J or CD1 
mice with W146 (3 mg/kg body weight i.p.) or vehicle every 6 h and mea-
sured platelet counts in these mice 24 h later. </p>

<p>Immunostaining. Anti-mouse S1pr1 (Zytomed), anti-human S1PR1 
(ABR), anti-S1pr2 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.), anti-S1pr4 (Santa Cruz 
Biotechnology, Inc.), antitubulin (Cell Signaling Technology), anti-mouse 
CD41 (BD), and anti-CD42c (Emfret Analytics) antibodies were used for 
immunostaining. The samples were examined using Leica microscopy 
equipped with 40× objective lens (NA = 0.7) or 20× objective lens (NA = 0.5) 
and commercial charge-coupled device camera (AxioCam; Carl Zeiss). 
Images were acquired by <rs id="software-3" type="software">AxioVision</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Carl Zeiss</rs>). For quantification 
of MK number and size in BM, we counted the total number of MKs in five 
randomly selected 20× microscopic fields, and the area of MK cell body was 
analyzed by <rs id="software-1" type="software">ImageJ</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">National Institutes of Health</rs>). </p>

<p>S1P level measurement. Levels of S1P were determined by high-
performance liquid chromatography with mass detection as described previously 
(Berdyshev et al., 2005). </p>

<p>Transmission electron microscopy. BM samples were fixed in 2.5% 
glutaraldehyde, embedded in epon, and analyzed using an electron micro-
scope (EM 902; Carl Zeiss). </p>

<p>Quantitative RT-PCR. Quantitative real-time PCR was performed using 
the MaximaTM SYBR Green PCR Master mix (Thermo Fisher Scientific) 
and an ABI PRISM 7700 Sequence Detection System (Applied Biosystems) 
according to the manufacturers' instructions. The data were normalized to 
the mRNA level of glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (Gapdh or 
GAPDH). Primers are listed in Table S1. </p>

<p>MK culture. Mouse embryonic day (E) 12.5-14.5 FL cells were cultivated 
in TPO-containing medium for differentiation into MKs (Lecine et al., 
1998). In brief, mouse FLs were isolated from E12.5-14.5 embryos and kept 
in DMEM (Invitrogen) supplemented with 10% charcoal-treated FBS 
(PAN) in the presence of hTPO (ImmunoTools) in a humidified 5% 
CO 2 /95% air incubator at 37°C. For isolation of immature MKs, E12.5-
14.5 FL cells were cultured in medium for 12 h and then incubated with 
FITC-CD41 (BD) and PE-CD34 (BioLegend) antibodies. Immature MKs 
were identified as a CD41/CD34 double-positive population and enriched 
by using a FACSAria cell sorter (BD). Mature MKs were enriched by BSA 
gradient, as described previously (Pang et al., 2006). In brief, the BSA step 
gradient was prepared by placing PBS containing 1.5% BSA on top of PBS 
with 3% BSA (PAA). Cells were loaded on top of the gradient, and MKs 
were settled to the bottom within 30 min at 1× gravity at room temperature. 
Mature MKs formed a pellet at the bottom of the tube. We distinguished 
and scored PPs according to the criteria mentioned previously (Chen et al., 
2007). To inhibit the activity of Rac GTPases, we cultured MKs in the pres-
ence of 50 µM NSC23766 (Tocris Bioscience) for 3 d and then scored MKs 
carrying PPs. To establish a stable gradient during the slow process of PPF, 
we applied chemotaxis -slides (ibidi), which consist of two large reservoirs 
with different chemoattractant concentrations and a thin (1 mm) slit be-
tween these two reservoirs. A linear and stable chemoattractant gradient is 
established in the slit by diffusion (Zengel et al., 2011). MKs were resus-
pended in serum-free medium in the presence or absence of 1 µM VPC23019 
(Avanti Polar Lipids, Inc.) and loaded onto chemotaxis -slides coated with 
poly-l-lysine between two large reservoirs. 10 µM S1P or vehicle was 
applied into one of the reservoirs of the -slides. MKs were cultivated for 
10 h at 37°C, and polarization of PPF was evaluated based on the images 
captured using an Axiovert microscope (Carl Zeiss) equipped with 20× 
objective lens (Nikon) and <rs type="software">AxioVision</rs> software. </p>

<p>CFU-MK assay. We seeded 10,000 isolated BM or FL mononuclear cells 
into Megacult-C medium (STEMCELL Technologies) and scored CFU-
MKs on day 5 according to the manufacturer's instructions. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 12 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>

<p>2179 </p>

<p>S.-S. Bolz, and A. Billich performed MP-IVM, generated chimaeras, generated 
lentiviral constructs, performed in vitro MK assays, generated FL-derived MKs, 
and performed S1P measurements; R.L. Proia and T. Graf generated and provided 
mutant mice and helped with data interpretation; M. Prinz and A. Müller performed 
electron microscopy; E. Montanez and M. Sixt performed in vitro shedding assay 
and examined S1pr1 downstream signaling; L. von Baumbarten, R. Fässler, M. Sixt, 
U.H. von Andrian, and T. Junt helped with MP-IVM, data interpretation, and discussion. </p>

<p>Submitted: 22 May 2012 
Accepted: 5 October 2012 </p>



<p>zero. For analysis of PP shedding, four-dimensional acquisitions were per-
formed at 920 nm by capturing 3D image stacks at an interval of 
60 s for 60 min. Videos were generated as maximum intensity projections 
representing a ''top'' (x-y) view of the volume using Volocity. The centroid 
positions (x-y) of MKs or PP tips from a series of top-view (x-y) images were 
measured using ImageJ, and instantaneous lateral (x-y) velocity, a measure 
of cell motility was determined by dividing the change in cell displacement 
between each frame by the time interval between frames and was quantified 
by the Chemotaxis and Migration Tool plugin (ibidi). All mice were treated 
with 8 µg/kg/d mTPO (ImmunoTools) for 3 d before imaging as de-
scribed previously (Junt et al., 2007). W146 (Avanti Polar Lipids, Inc.) or 
vehicle was injected (i.p.) 3 mg/kg body weight every 8 h for 24 h before 
imaging. To evaluate PP shedding, the mice were injected (i.p.) with W146 
(3 mg/kg body weight) or vehicle and immediately visualized using MP-
IVM. For FTY720 experiments, the same MKs were visualized in mice be-
fore and 8 h after a single injection of FTY720 (3 mg/kg i.p.) or DMSO 
using MP-IVM. </p>

<p>PP shedding under shear stress. MKs from -actin-EGFP mice were 
seeded in -slides VI coated with 100 µg/ml human fibrinogen (Sigma-
Aldrich). The slides were then connected to a pump system (ibidi). A laminar 
shear stress of 4 dynes/cm 2 was applied to the cells in the presence of 5 µM 
S1P or vehicle. Image stacks were acquired at 2 µm in z to cover a 20-µm 
vertical distance at 60-s intervals for 20 min. The efficiency of PP fragmenta-
tion was determined by (L 0min  L 20min )/L 0min × 100%. L 0min and L 20min 
represent the length of PPs at 0 min and 20 min, respectively. </p>

<p>Live cell imaging. Mature MKs were starved in serum-free medium in 
custom-made Petri dishes coated with 100 µg/ml of human fibrinogen 
(Sigma-Aldrich) for 4 h before incubation with S1P or vehicle. We treated 
MKs with 10 µM S1P together with 25 µM NSC23766 (Tocris Bioscience) 
to inhibit Rac GTPases. We incubated MKs with 500 ng/ml pertussis toxin 
(Sigma-Aldrich) to inhibit Gi signaling 1 h before the addition of 10 µM S1P. 
Live cell imaging was performed as described previously (Lämmermann 
et al., 2008). In brief, MKs were kept on a heated micro-incubator to keep the 
temperature at 37°C and monitored using a DIC microscope system (Carl 
Zeiss), equipped with a 40× oil objective lens with NA = 0.7 (Carl Zeiss). </p>

<p>Statistics. We used two-tailed type 2 Student's t test and Kolmogorov-
Smirnov test to calculate p-values. We considered p-values of &lt;0.05 as 
statistically significant. </p>

<p>Online supplemental material. Fig. S1 shows intravascular PPF and DIC 
microscopy of PP fragmentation. Videos 1 and 2 show intravital visualization 
of PPF and shedding in WT or S1pr1 mutants. Video 3 shows intravital vi-
sualization of PPs in WT mice treated with S1pr1 inhibitor, W146, or its ve-
hicle. Videos 4 and 5 show the effect of S1P on PP shedding in vitro. Video 6 
shows the effect of S1P on PP shedding in S1pr2 / or S1pr4 / MKs or 
S1pr1 / MKs. Videos 7 and 8 show intravital visualization of PP shedding 
in WT or S1pr1 mutants or WT mice treated with W146. Table S1 shows 
the sequences of primers used for qRT-PCR. Table S2 shows the blood cell 
counts in BM chimaeras. Table S3 shows the blood cell counts in nontrans-
planted mice. Online supplemental material is available at http://www.jem 
.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20121090/DC1. </p>

<p>We thank Dr. Timothy Hla (Cornell University, Ithaca, NY) for helpful discussions 
and suggestions. 
This study was supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft and by the 
Intramural Research Program of the National Institutes of Health, National Institute 
of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases. 
A. Billich and T. Junt are employees of Novartis. The authors have no further 
conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>Author contributions: L. Zhang and S. Massberg came up with the conception and 
study design and wrote the manuscript; L. Zhang, M. Orban, M. Lorenz, 
V. Barocke, D. Braun, N. Urtz, C. Schulz, M.-L. von Brühl, A. Tirniceriu, F. Gaertner, </p>





</text></tei>