<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3429821" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>IMR is useful for assessing the microvascular dysfunction after primary percutaneous 
coronary intervention (PCI). It remains unknown whether index of microcirculatory 
resistance (IMR) reflects the functional outcome in patients with anterior myocardial 
infarction (AMI) with or without microvascular obstruction (MO).This study was performed 
to evaluate the clinical value of the IMR for assessing myocardial injury and predicting 
microvascular functional recovery in patients with AMI undergoing primary PCI. We 
enrolled 34 patients with first anterior AMI. After successful primary PCI, the mean distal 
coronary artery pressure (Pa), coronary wedge pressure (Pcw), mean aortic pressure (Pa), 
mean transit time (Tmn), and IMR (Pd * hyperemic Tmn) were measured. The presence and 
extent of MO were measured using cardiac magnetic resonance image (MRI). All patients 
underwent follow-up echocardiography after 6 months. We divided the patients into two 
groups according to the existence of MO (present; n = 16, absent; n = 18) on MRI. The 
extent of MO correlated with IMR (r = 0.754; P &lt; 0.001), Pcw (r = 0.404; P = 0.031), and 
Pcw/Pd of infarct-related arteries (r = 0.502; P = 0.016). The IMR was significantly 
correlated with the ΔRegional wall motion score index (r = -0.61, P &lt; 0.01) and ΔLeft 
ventricular ejection fraction (r = -0.52, P &lt; 0.01), implying a higher IMR is associated with 
worse functional improvement. Therefore, Intracoronary wedge pressures and IMR, as 
parameters for specific and quantitative assessment of coronary microvascular dysfunction, 
are reliable on-site predictors of short-term myocardial viability and Left ventricle 
functional recovery in patients undergoing primary PCI for AMI. </p>

<p>Early restoration of epicardial coronary blood flow reduces in-
farct size in patients with acute myocardial infarctions (AMI) 
and has a beneficial effect on healing of the myocardium and 
left ventricular (LV) remodeling. However, successful restora-
tion of epicardial flow does not induce optimal reperfusion of 
myocardial tissue and microvascular function, LV remodeling, 
and improved clinical outcome (1). As a consequence, complete 
restoration of infarct-related arterial patency and microvascular 
integrity has important prognostic significance in patients after 
an AMI (2). Microvascular obstruction (MO), or no reflow phe-
nomenon, defines an area within an AMI that has undergone 
cardiomyocyte necrosis, as well as severe and irreversible micro-
circulation damage (3). Microvascular obstruction is associated 
with poor prognosis and worse LV remodeling. Infarct extent 
and MO can reliably be detected by magnetic resonance imag-</p>

<p>ing (MRI) (4). However, this information is not readily available 
in clinical practice, and other prognostic measures have been 
proposed to meet such limitations. The thrombolysis in myocar-
dial infarction (TIMI) flow grade, the TIMI blush grade, the cor-
rected TIMI frame count, and the coronary flow reserve (CFR) 
have all been investigated and known to be related to outcome 
of AMI patients (5, 6). With recent technological advances, it is 
now possible to measure pressure and estimate coronary artery 
flow simultaneously with a single pressure-temperature sensor-
tipped coronary wire (7, 8). The single pressure-temperature 
sensor-tipped coronary wire has additional advantage of allow-
ing assessment of several potentially useful clinical indices. It has 
been reported that IMR was a predictor of microvascular dam-
age after myocardial infarction and predictor of left ventricular 
functional recovery after 3 months (9, 10). However, our study 
periods are 6 months, thereby more reliable results can be derived 
from our study. Out study can be more reliable for 6 months pe-</p>

<p>Yoo S-H, et al. • IMR for Microvascular Functional Recovery with AMI </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2012.27.9.1044 </p>

<p>riod of study more than 3 months. It also has been reported that 
IMR was a predictor of myocardial viability and left ventricular 
functional recovery in acute myocardial infarction (11). Past study 
used 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography to 
quantify the myocardial variability, and few IMR study using 
MRI has been done (12). We quantified myocardial viability by 
MRI and it has relatively free methods-limitation. Studies with 
animal models have shown that an index of microcirculatory 
resistance (IMR) correlates with true microvascular resistance, 
and unlike CFR, it is independent of the epicardial arteries (7, 8,  12, 13). Therefore, a relationship between the perfusion and in-
farct size can be assumed, but whether or not the microvascu-
lar hemodynamic parameter can reliably represent the extent 
of necrosis in the infarct territory remains unknown. Further-
more, previous studies have not focused on the indices which 
specifically represent cardiac microvascular status and can thus 
accurately predict the extent of myocardial injury during the 
acute phase of an AMI. We assessed the clinical value of the IMR 
to assess the micro-vascular dysfunction and predicting micro-
vascular functional recovery in patients with AMI who under-
went primary percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI). </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study population 
We prospectively studied 34 consecutive patients who were re-
ferred for PCI following a first AMI. All patients were treated by 
successful primary PCI, defined as TIMI flow grade &gt; 2 and 
subsequent stent implantation with residual stenosis of &lt; 25%. 
Inclusion criteria were as follows: 1) an episode of chest pain 
&gt; 30 min, 2) an ECG showing ST-elevation ≥ 2 mm on a pre-
cordial lead, and 3) a 3-fold increase in cardiac enzymes above 
the normal range, and 4) a regional wall motion abnormalities 
in ≥ 3 segments on resting echcardiography. The exclusion cri-
teria were as follows: 1) cardiogenic shock, 2) left main disease 
or 3-vessel disease, 3) old MI, 4) visible collateral circulation on 
coronary artery angiography (after successful PCI, we used pres-
sure-temperature sensor-tipped coronary wire), and 5) patients 
with contraindications for MRI. Patients were treated with aspi-
rin, heparin, abciximab, clopidogrel, statins, beta-blockade, and 
angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors. 
All patients underwent primary PCI with catheterization for 
monitoring IMR between 1 and 5 hr after symptoms onset, then 
underwent cardiac MRI at least 72 hr, but within 7 days after pri-
mary PCI. All cardiac MRI were supervised and analyzed by one 
operator who was blinded to IMR and vice versa. </p>

<p>MRI protocol 
The MRI was performed on a 1.5-T scanner (Siemens Sonata; 
Erlangen, Germany) utilizing a 12-channel body array surface 
coil. All patients were examined in the supine position, and con-</p>

<p>trast material was injected via cephalic vein. Scout images were 
obtained, and typical imaging parameters were a 380 * 320 mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>field of view (FOV), a 256 * 159 matrix, an 8-mm slice thickness, 
a 2-mm slice gap, a 70º flip angle, a 1.51-ms echo time, and a 
45.15-ms repetition time. Six short-axis slices were chosen at 
equal distances along the LV long axis for first-pass perfusion 
imaging with an electrocardiographically-triggered saturation 
recovery ultra-fast gradient echo (turbo-flash) sequence (repe-
tition time/echo time/inversion time, 188 ms/0.96 ms/100 ms; 
flip angle, 15º). A 96 * 128 matrix, an 8-mm slice thickness, and 
a 309 * 380 mm 
2 FOV were used. A bolus of gadopentetate dime-
glumine in a dose of 0.1 mM/kg of body weight was injected in-
travenously at 3 mL/s, followed by 20 mL of normal saline using 
a MRI-compatible power injector. A second bolus of Gd-DTPA 
(0.1 mM/kg of body weight) was administered, and late gadolin-
ium enhancement (LGE) images were obtained 12 to 15 min after 
the second contrast administration. With a flip angle of 45º, de-
layed contrast-enhanced images covering the left ventricle from 
the base to the apex in the short axis view (slice thickness, 8 mm; 
gap, 2 mm) were obtained 15 min after perfusion imaging with 
breath-hold and a phase-sensitive inversion recovery steady 
state-free precision sequence with repetition and echo times of 
680 ms and 1.26 ms, respectively. The typical imaging parame-
ters were a 308 * 340 mm 
2 FOV and a 184 * 256 matrix. </p>

<p>MRI data analysis and definitions 
All MRI data was obtained on the cine images using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">MASS</rs> 
software package (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Medis</rs>, Leiden, The Netherlands). On all the 
short-axis cine slices, the endocardial and epicardial borders 
were outlined manually on the end-diastolic and -systolic im-
ages. We divided the short axis into 12 equiangular segments to 
measure the LV segmental function, and the LV volumes and LV 
ejection fractions (LVEF) were calculated. We assessed delayed 
enhancement images and infarct size as previously described 
(14). The total infarct size was calculated as the percentage of 
the LV mass, and transmural extent of infarction was calculated 
by dividing the hyper-enhanced area by the total area of the pre-
defined segment (%). A transmurality score was calculated in 
each patient, which was expressed as the sum of segments with 
&gt; 75% infarcted myocardium as a percentage of the total num-
ber of segments scored. On the delayed enhancement images, 
the MO was defined as any region of hypo-enhancement with-
in the hyper-enhanced infarcted area, and was included in the 
calculation of the total infarct size. The extent of MO was calcu-
lated in each patient, and measured percent by dividing num-
ber of MO segment by number of total segment. All MRI mea-
surements of the LVEF and extent of MO and infarct size were 
reviewed by two independent blinded observers. The intra-class 
correlation coefficients for the intra-and inter-observer agree-
ment for these parameters were all &gt; 0.9. </p>

<p>Yoo S-H, et al. • IMR for Microvascular Functional Recovery with AMI </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2012.27.9.1044 </p>

<p>Intracoronary pressure parameters measurement 
Intracoronary pressure parameters were measured in each pa-
tient after PCI using previously described principles (7). With 
commercially available software (Radi Medical Systems, Upps-
lae, Sweden), the shaft of the pressure wire can act as a proximal 
thermistor, sensor near the tip of the wire simultaneously mea-
sured the pressure and temperature acting as a distal thermis-
tor. Thermodilution technique was used to check the the transit 
time of room temperature when saline was injected down to cor-
onary arteries (8). 3 mL aliquots of room temperature saline was 
administered to the coronary artery, and the resting mean transit 
time (baseline mean transit time [bTmn]) was measured. Steady 
state of maximal hyperemia was induced by intravenous infusion 
of adenosine (140 µg/kg/min). Three additional 3 mL aliquots 
of room temperature saline was injected, and the hyperemic 
mean transit time (hTmn) was measured. The simultaneous mea-
surements of mean aortic pressure (Pa, by guiding catheter) and 
mean distal coronary pressure (Pd, by pressure wire) were also 
obtained during the resting state and maximal hyperemic state. 
The CFR thermo was calculated, dividing the resting hTmn by the 
bTmn. The IMR was defined as the simultaneously measured dis-
tal coronary pressure divided by the inverse of the hTmn (12, 13). </p>

<p>Evaluation of LV functional recovery by echocardiography 
Echocardiographic images were obtained in the standard para-
sternal long, short axes and apical 4-and 2-chamber views uti-
lizing digital Vivid 7 ultrasound equipment with a combined tis-
sue imaging 2.5-4.0 MHz transducer (GE, Milwaukee, WI, USA). 
At least three cardiac cycles were monitored at the LV base, mid-
papillary muscle level, and apex for wall motion assessment. No 
intravenous contrast agent was used. After 6 months, an blinded 
expert reader obtained measurements off-line from the para-
sternal and apical windows. Two-dimensional (2D) ventricular 
volumes and LVEF were measured from the 4-and 2-chamber 
areas using the modified Simpson's rule. The left ventricle was 
divided into 16 segments. The myocardial motion of each seg-
ment was evaluated according to the American Society of Echo-
cardiography wall motion scoring system and the regional wall 
motion score index (RWMSI) was calculated. The two observers 
were blinded to the echocardiographic investigations, The LVEF 
was calculated by substracting the baseline LVEF from the fol-
low-up LVEF, and ΔRWMSI was calculated by substracting the 
baseline LVEF from the follow-up RWMSI. </p>

<p>Statistics 
The values are reported as the mean ± SD or median (25th-75th 
percentiles) for continuous variables and as frequency for cate-
gorical variables. The correlations between the extent of MO and 
coronary physiologic parameters were calculated by using sim-
ple linear regression analysis to identify parameters which are 
independently associated with the extent of MO, being deter-</p>

<p>mined by cardiac MRI. Multivariate logistic regression analysis 
was used to assess the relationship between coronary hemody-
namic pressure parameters and the presence of MO. A P value 
&lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. All calculations 
were generated by <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">12.0</rs> for Windows. </p>

<p>Ethics statement 
The study protocol was approved by the Ethics Committee of 
our hospital (IRB approval No. 12-054), and written informed 
consent was obtained from all patients before cardiac catheter-
ization by one of the investigators. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Baseline characteristics 
Of the 34 patients included in the study (mean age, 57 ± 4 yr), 
20 were men, 9 had hypercholesterolemia, 8 had diabetes mel-
litus, 8 had a history of hypertension, and 14 were smokers. The 
mean time from the onset of symptoms to reperfusion was 194 
min, and standard deviation was 123 min. The patients were di-
vided into the following two groups: no MO group (MRI with 
homogeneous enhancement of the myocardium; n = 16); and </p>

<p>Table 1. Clinical, angiographic characteristics </p>

<p>Parameters 
No MO (n = 16) 
MO (n = 18) 
P </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
52 ± 10 
59 ± 21 
0.091 
Male 
9 (56%) 
11 (61%) 
0.642 
Risk factors 
DM, No. (%) 
Hypertension, No. (%) 
Dyslipidemia, No. (%) 
Smoking, No. (%) </p>

<p>2 (12%) 
3 (19%) 
4 (25%) 
5 (31%) </p>

<p>6 (33%) 
5 (28%) 
5 (28%) 
9 (50%) </p>

<p>0.214 
0.693 
0.585 
0.729 
Result of reperfusion 
Peak CK (IU) 
Time to reperfusion (min) </p>

<p>2,229 ± 1,834 
100 ± 17 </p>

<p>3,080 ± 2,104 
123 ± 32 </p>

<p>0.306 
0.065 
Infarct-related artery 
Location of occlusion 
Proximal 
Mid 
Disital 
Reference vessel size (mm) </p>

<p>9 
6 
1 
3.47 ± 0.37 </p>

<p>11 
6 
1 
3.32 ± 0.21 </p>

<p>0.360 
0.237 </p>

<p>0.243 
Pre PCI 
MLD (mm) 
DS (%) </p>

<p>0.22 ± 0.33 
93 ± 9.8 </p>

<p>0.43 ± 0.26 
85.5 ± 8.5 </p>

<p>0.654 
0.382 
Post-PCI 
MLD (mm) 
DS (%) </p>

<p>3.1 ± 0.4 
9.7 ± 6.7 </p>

<p>3.0 ± 0.3 
10.3 ± 7.0 </p>

<p>0.329 
0.830 
TIMI flow after PCI 
Grade 0 
Grade 1 
Grade 2 
Grade 3 </p>

<p>0 
1 
5 
10 </p>

<p>2 
4 
6 
6 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>Infarct size, % of left ventricle 
9.6 ± 5.2 
26.4 ± 6.7 
0.01 
Extent of transmural 
necrosis, % segments </p>

<p>6.9 ± 8.7 
24.9 ± 10.7 
0.01 </p>

<p>Values are expressed as mean ± SD or No. (%). DS, diameter stenosis; MLD, mini-
mal lumen diameter; CK, creatine kinase; PCI, percutaneous coronary intervention; 
TIMI, thrombolysis in myocardial infarctio; DM, diabetes mellitus; IU, international unit. </p>

<p>Yoo S-H, et al. • IMR for Microvascular Functional Recovery with AMI </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2012.27.9.1044 </p>

<p>the MO group (MRI with hypo-enhanced region; n = 18; Table 1), 
according to the presence of MO on MRI. An MRI was performed 
6 ± 4 days after the acute event. There were no differences in the 
baseline characteristics and hemodynamic variables between 
the two groups. </p>

<p>Relations between Intracoronary pressure parameters 
and MO 
Intracoronary pressure parameters data showed that the increas-</p>

<p>ing extent of MO was associated with higher hyperemic mean 
transient time and decreased CFR. The IMR was significantly 
higher in the MO group than the no MO group. Although the Pa 
and Pd values were comparable between the two groups, the mean 
Pcw was significantly higher in the MO group. Thus, the elevation 
of the mean Pcw appears, in part, to explain an increase in Pcw/Pa 
in the MO patients (Table 2). Stepwise multivariate linear regres-
sion analysis was performed to identify the factors that were 
closely related to IMR, and the presence of MO was proven to 
be related to IMR (T = 3.4; P &lt; 0.01), and no MO had the stron-
gest relationship to IMR. The extent of MO was correlated with 
IMR (r = 0.754; P &lt; 0.001), Pcw (r = 0.404; P = 0.031), and Pcw/Pa 
of the infarct-related artery (r = 0.502; P = 0.016). An inverse re-
lationship was observed between the extent of MO and CFR 
(r = -0.368; P = 0.029; Fig. 1). </p>

<p>IMR and functional recovery 
All hospitalized patients were evaluated with echocardiography, 
and follow-up echocardiography was additionally performed 
after average 6.3 months. The values for the LVEF at the 6-month 
follow-up was significantly higher in the no MO group than in 
the MO group, and no MO group presented higher ΔLVEF and </p>

<p>Table 2. Intracoronary pressure measurements </p>

<p>Parameters 
No MO (n = 16) 
MO (n = 18) 
P </p>

<p>CFR 
2.7 ± 1.1 
2.0 ± 0.8 
0.043 
Pa (mmHg) 
95 ± 9 
92 ± 11 
0.521 
Pd (mmHg) 
89 ± 12 
85 ± 13 
0.345 
Tmn (s) 
0.18 ± 0.1 
0.43 ± 0.2 
0.001 
Pcw (mmHg) 
26.5 ± 9.6 
35.4 ± 10.0 
0.012 
Pcw/Pa 
0.27 ± 0.83 
0.33 ± 0.17 
0.003 
IMR (U) 
16.7 ± 12.4 
38.1 ± 16.7 
0.001 </p>

<p>Values are expressed as mean ± SD or n (%). CFRthermo, thermodilution coronary flow 
reserve; IMR, index of microcirculatory resistance; Pa, mean aortic pressure; Pcw, cor-
onary wedge pressure; Pcw/Pa, coronary wedge pressure to mean aortic pressure ratio; 
Pd, mean distal coronary attery pressure; Tmn, mean transit time; MO, microvascular 
obstruction. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Correlation between intracoronary pressure parameters, index of microcirculatory resistance (IMR) and extent of microvascualr obstruction (MO). There was significant 
correlation between IMR, intracoronary pressure parameters and extent of MO. Open circles represent patients with MO as measured by cardiac MRI. CFR, coronary flow re-
serve; Pa, mean aortic pressure; Pcw, coronary wedge pressure. </p>

<p>CFR 
Pcw </p>

<p>Extent of MO (%) </p>

<p>r = -0.368 </p>

<p>P = 0.029 </p>

<p>r = 0.404 </p>

<p>P = 0.031 </p>

<p>Extent of MO (%) </p>

<p>0.0 
10.0 
20.0 
30.0 
40.0 
50.0 
0.0 
10.0 
20.0 
30.0 
40.0 
50.0 </p>

<p>2.40 </p>

<p>2.20 </p>

<p>2.00 </p>

<p>1.80 </p>

<p>1.60 </p>

<p>1.40 </p>

<p>40.0 </p>

<p>35.0 </p>

<p>30.0 </p>

<p>25.0 </p>

<p>20.0 </p>

<p>Pcw/Pa 
IMR </p>

<p>r = 0.502 </p>

<p>P = 0.016 </p>

<p>r = 0.754 </p>

<p>P = &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Extent of MO (%) 
Extent of MO (%) </p>

<p>0.0 
10.0 
20.0 
30.0 
40.0 
50.0 
0.0 
10.0 
20.0 
30.0 
40.0 
50.0 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>35.0 </p>

<p>30.0 </p>

<p>25.0 </p>

<p>20.0 </p>

<p>15.0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>Yoo S-H, et al. • IMR for Microvascular Functional Recovery with AMI </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2012.27.9.1044 </p>

<p>ΔRWMSI than the MO group. We compared the relationship 
between IMR and the magnitude of LV functional improvement. 
The IMR was significantly correlated with ΔRWMSI (r = -0.61, 
P &lt; 0.01; Fig. 2A) and ΔLVEF (r = -0.52, P &lt; 0.01), implying a 
higher IMR is associated with worse functional improvement. 
When the ΔRWMSI was compared in patients with TIMI-3 flow, 
there was no relationship among the patients with TIMI-3 flow 
(r = 0.32, P &gt; 0.05). So close correlation existed between the IMR 
and ΔRWMSI in the AMI patients, we could derive an intracor-
onary wedge pressure index (Pcw/Pa). The parameter was signif-
icantly lower in the no MO group than the MO group (0.27 ± 0.83 
vs 0.33 ± 0.17, P &lt; 0.01). There was a close inverse relationship 
between Pcw/Pa, IMR, and ΔRWMSI (Fig. 2). On multivariate 
analysis including infarct size and TIMI grade, IMR was the stron-
gest independent predictor of ΔRWMSI (r = -0.61, P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our study examined the predictive ability of microcirculatory 
resistance (IMR) in MI patients treated with PCI for recovery at 
6 months. Patients who had PCI were studied by using Gd-en-
hanced MR to evaluate infarct size and enhancement which re-
flects MO. Echocardiography was performed after MI and then 
6 months later. Our study showed that hemodynamic indices 
(IMR, Pcw, and Pcw/Pa) reflected the extent of MO and functional 
recovery at 6 months after MI. Recovery of function and devel-
opment of remodeling after MI are strongly related to perfusion 
at the microcirculatory level. Recent MRI investigations have 
shown that MO, irrespective of infarct size, is a strong predictor 
of cardiovascular events after infarction (15). The no-reflow phe-
nomenon is thus an important prognostic factor (16), but its de-
tection requires additional investigations, such as MRI or myo-</p>

<p>cardial contrast echocardiography. The findings of this study 
suggest that microcirculatory reactivity assessed with a coronary 
guide wire indicates the amount of microvascular injury and 
clarifies why coronary hemodynamic parameters can be used 
as a prognostic parameter for myocardial functional recovery. 
The CFR has been reported that the increased flow velocity dur-
ing the acute phase of an AMI limits the accurate evaluation of 
the extent of microvascular injury (8, 17). Although the role of 
Pcw in protecting the myocardium and in reflecting myocardial 
injury is fraught with controversy, a recent study reported that 
the rise of coronary wedge pressure reflects the level of micro-
vascular injury, and that the coronary zero flow pressure (Pzf) in 
AMI patients who underwent PCI within 24 hr of the onset of 
chest pain is correlated with the microvascular dysfunction in-
duced by myocardial injury (18, 19). The results of our study sup-
port the findings of previous studies by demonstrating the cor-
onary artery wedge pressure and correction of coronary artery 
wedge pressure to coronary perfusion pressure (Pcw/Pa) as use-
ful indicators for ischemic microvascular dysfunction. The IMR 
is a novel index that represents microvascular integrity; the IMR 
is a better predictive parameter of myocardial damage than other 
parameters for evaluating the microvasculature after primary 
PCI (12, 13). The indices of various coronary artery microvascu-
lar abnormalities were measured by intra-coronary pressure 
wires within the coronary arteries and then compared to MR 
images, the current standard method of evaluation for myocar-
dial injury. The present study has shown that the intracoronary 
hemodynamic indices (Pcw and Pcw/Pa), measured by the intra-
coronary pressure, adequately represent myocardial injury. In 
the presence of detectable significant myonecrosis, we presumed 
that increasing IMR indicates microvascular dysfunction after 
PCI. The results of our study also support IMR as a useful indi-</p>

<p>Fig. 2. Correlation between ΔRWMSI and IMR (A) and Pcw/Pa (B). There was significant inverse correlation between ΔRWMSI and IMR. Thus, higher IMR is associated with the 
lower ΔRWMSI, implying the worse functional outcomes. Significant correlation was also found between ΔRWMSI and Pcw/Pa. Triangles indicate patients with MO, and circles 
represent patients with no MO. Δ (delta), the difference of the values at Follow up day minus at baseline day; RWMSI, regional wall motion score index; IMR, index of microcir-
culatory resistance; Pcw/Pa, coronary wedge pressure to mean aortic pressure ratio. </p>

<p>ΔRWMSI 
ΔRWMSI </p>

<p>IMR 
Pcw/Pa </p>

<p>0.00 
10.00 
20.00 
30.00 
40.00 
50.00 
60.00 
0.20 
0.25 
0.30 
0.35 
0.40 </p>

<p>0.60 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.700 </p>

<p>0.600 </p>

<p>0.500 </p>

<p>0.400 </p>

<p>0.300 </p>

<p>0.200 </p>

<p>0.100 </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>r = 0.61, P &lt; 0.01 
r = 0.58, P &lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>Yoo S-H, et al. • IMR for Microvascular Functional Recovery with AMI </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2012.27.9.1044 </p>

<p>cator for assessing microvascular dysfunction after PCI during 
the acute phase of myocardial ischemia. As an invasive indica-
tor, IMR is expected to play an important role in assessing micro-
vascular injury and prognosis, and in planning treatment pro-
cedures at earlier stages of disease. Also, Pcw/Pa and CFR thermo 
can be obtained simultaneously by an intracoronary pressure 
wire, providing additional information about the degree of mi-
crovascular dysfunction and myocardial injury. Furthermore, 
simultaneous measurement of intracoronary pressure parame-
ters and IMR may provide a simple means for comprehensive 
and specific assessment of intracoronary hemodynamics at both 
the epicardial and microvascular levels, respectively. MO with a 
subsequent high impedance results in the inability to squeeze 
blood forward into the venous circulation during systole, and 
consequently the blood will be pushed back into the epicardial 
coronary arteries (20). 
We acknowledge limitations of the study. First, the hemody-
namic characteristics of coronary arteries and their clinical sig-
nificance and outcome can vary according to the different in-
farct-related arteries and the location of the lesion. In light of 
such a fact, the study had excluded patients with anatomic vari-
ations and whose lesions were located at the distal portion. Sec-
ondly, there is a controversy about the effect of epicardial artery 
occlusion when measuring the microvascular resistance using 
IMR. When the occlusion is severe, the simplified equation of 
this study does not take collateral circulations into consideration, 
resulting overestimation of microvascular resistance. However, 
in our study, the measurements were obtained after successful 
removal of epicardial occlusion through intervention, thus the 
effect of epicardial artery occlusion is thought to be minimal. 
Moreover, transient vasospasm and distal microemboli during 
the acute phase of an MI can increase microvascular resistance, 
but it does not always result in irreversible necrosis of the myo-
cardium. Third limitation is that there is no TIMI frame count, 
myocardial blush score, TIMI flow, and specific follow up wall 
motion score. Such a fact can serve as a limitation in the evalu-
ation of myocardial dysfunction using the IMR as a measure of 
microvascular resistance during the acute phase of an AMI. 
A close correlation between the size of the anatomic MO and 
necrosis was already proved to be related to ischemic cardiac 
injury. In the present study, we showed that the extent of MO (% 
of microvascular damage) assessed by cardiac MRI correlated 
well with intracoronary pressure parameters, such as IMR and 
Pcw/Pa. Furthermore, after adjusting the extent of MO, IMR and 
Pcw/Pa were able to predict myocardial injury during the acute 
phase of an AMI. 
In conlusion, intracoronary wedge pressures and IMR, as pa-
rameters for specific and quantitative assessment of coronary 
microvascular dysfunction, are reliable on-site predictors of 
short-term myocardial viability and LV functional recovery in 
patients undergoing primary PCI for AMI. </p>



<p>Yoo S-H, et al. • IMR for Microvascular Functional Recovery with AMI </p>





</text></tei>