<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3524325" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:28+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Extubation is associated with the risk of complications such as accumulated secretion above the endotracheal 
tube cuff, eventual atelectasia following a reduction in pulmonary volumes because of a lack of physiological positive end 
expiratory pressure, and intra-tracheal suction. In order to reduce these complications, and, based on basic physiological 
principles, a new practical extubation method is presented in this article. 
Methods: The study was designed as a six-month prospective cross-sectional clinical trial. Two hundred fifty-seven patients 
undergoing coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG) were divided into two groups based on their scheduled surgery time. The 
first group underwent the conventional extubation method, while the other group was extubated according to a new described 
method. Arterial blood gas (ABG) analysis results before and after extubation were compared between the two groups to find 
the effect of the extubation method on the ABG parameters and the oxygenation profile. 
Results: In all time intervals, the partial pressure of oxygen in arterial blood / fraction of inspired oxygen (PaO 2 / FiO 2 ) 
ratio in the new method group patients was improved compared to that in the conventional method; some differences, like 
PaO 2 / FiO 2 four hours after extubation, were statistically significant, however (p value = 0.0063). 
Conclusion: The new extubation method improved some respiratory parameters and thus attenuated oxygenation 
complications and amplified oxygenation after extubation. </p>

<p>J Teh Univ Heart Ctr 2012;7(3):121-127 </p>

<p>This paper should be cited as: Yousefshahi F, Barkhordari K, Movafegh A, Tavakoli V, Paknejad O, Bina P, Yousefshahi H, Sheikh </p>

<p>Fathollahi M. A New Method for Extubation: Comparison between Conventional and New Methods. J Teh Univ Heart Ctr 2012;7(3):121-127. </p>

<p>Keywords: Airway extubation • Cardiac surgical procedures • Blood gas analysis </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>For all the painstaking attention granted to tracheal </p>

<p>intubation, especially with regard to the management of 
the difficult airway, precious little heed has thus far been </p>

<p>paid to tracheal extubation. 
1 Compared to 4.6% respiratory 
complications in the intubation of elective cases, extubation-
related complications arise in 12% in the same group. </p>

<p>2   In some studies, researchers have tried to, along with 
other extubation criteria, indicate the application of oxy-</p>



<p>The Journal of Tehran University Heart Center </p>

<p>hemoglobin as a guide to extubation decision. </p>

<p>3, 4   During the extubation process, vital signs and oxy-
hemoglobin saturation percentage should be monitored. </p>

<p>2, 5   Given that the period immediately after extubation is the most 
critical and vulnerable time for the patient, it is necessary for 
the medical staff to be alert and look for any sign or symptom 
of respiratory disturbance and hypoxia. </p>

<p>5   The pulmonary effects of systemic inflammatory 
reaction after cardiac surgery are often modest and include 
decreased lung compliance, pulmonary edema, increased 
intrapulmonary shunt fraction, and decreased functional 
residual capacity and their resultant hypoxemia. Few patients 
(2%) undergoing cardiac surgery develop full-blown acute 
respiratory distress syndrome. 
6 However, it is reported that 
up to 40% of cardiac surgery patients are readmitted to the 
intensive care unit (ICU) because of respiratory failure. </p>

<p>7, 8   During the last decade, many researchers have tried to address 
different strategies like the Open Lung Concept (OLC), </p>

<p>9,   10 Recruitment Maneuver, 
11 and Positive End Expiratory 
Pressure (PEEP) 
12, 13 as well as some other measures 
14, 15 in 
order to attenuate hypoxemia after cardiac surgery. 
Considering that there are no practical standards for 
extubation techniques and an increasing number of patients 
experience extubation-related complications, 
16 we devised a 
novel extubation method and compared its results with those 
of the conventional method. The principal goals were: (1)  to augment oxygenation by reducing the aspiration of the 
respiratory secretion and (2) to decrease intra-pulmonary 
shunting and its effects on the ICU stay. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>The present study was a six-month prospective cross-
sectional clinical trial. A pilot study was initially devised so 
as to determine the sample size, there being no similar study 
available in the existing literature. The results of the pilot 
study determined the number at 90 per study group with a 
confidence coefficient of 90%. Data were gathered by trained 
staff, matching was performed both for the patients and the 
methods, anesthesia techniques and drugs were coordinated 
and equalized by three experienced anesthesiologists, and 
randomization was done on a time basis: the new method 
was utilized in the first three months, followed by the 
conventional method in the ensuing three months. 
The inclusion criterion was elective on-pump coronary 
artery bypass grafting surgery (CABG), and the exclusion 
criteria were comprised of severe lung disease, intubation 
before surgery, severe hemodynamic disturbance requiring 
balloon pumps, and need for operation before extubation. 
These data were comprised of the mean of Partial Pressure 
of Oxygen in Arterial Blood (PaO 2 ) = 87.7 mmHg with a 
standard deviation of 16.6 for the new method group and 
95.31 mmHg with a standard deviation of 14.56 for the </p>

<p>conventional method group. 
Arterial blood gas (ABG) parameters constituted the main 
variables, particularly PaO 2 and PaO 2 / FiO 2 (Fraction of 
Inspired Oxygen), at one and four hours after extubation. 
The time periods considered for the purposes of the present 
study were: 1) one hour after ICU admission; 2) just before 
extubation; 3) one hour after extubation; 4) four hours after 
extubation; 5) twelve hours after extubation; and 6) forty-
eight hours after extubation. 
The study population comprised post on-pump CABG 
patients who were under care in the ICU during a six-month 
period in 2008. Confounding factors were cardiopulmonary 
bypass (CPB) time, aortic cross-clamp time, body mass index 
(BMI), and underlying diseases such as chronic obstructive 
pulmonary disease, diabetes mellitus, smoking, reoperation, 
and dialysis. 
The inclusion criteria were composed of CABG without 
any co-surgery, intubation in the operating room, and 
consent for participation in the study. The exclusion criteria 
were comprised of valvular disease requiring surgery, 
pneumonia, hemodynamic disturbance, intra-aortic balloon 
pump (because it induces inflammation), respiratory 
distress, urgent or elective intubation, carbon dioxide 
pressure (PCO 2 ) &gt; 45mmHg, oxygen pressure (PO 2 ) &lt; 60 
mmHg, forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV 1 ) &lt; 
60% or FEV 1 / FVC (forced vital capacity) &lt; 60% and vital 
capacity (VC) &lt; 50%, ejection fraction (EF) &lt; 30%, need for 
reoperation before extubation, neurological complications, 
consciousness disorder, significant neurological defect, and 
BMI &gt; 40. 
Immediately after ICU admission, the cuff pressure was 
controlled and was thereafter monitored every eight hours. 
Next, the ventilator machine was set on SIMV-PSV (SIMV: 
synchronized intermittent mechanical ventilation, PSV: 
pressure support ventilation): Vt (tidal volume) = 8 cc/kg 
of ideal body weight, frequency of intermittent mandatory 
ventilation (F) (IMV) = 10/min; F (IMV + PSV) = 15/min, I/E 
(inspiratory-expiratory time ratio) = 1/2, PEEP = 5 cmH 2 O, 
PSV = 5 cmH 2 O above total inspiratory pressure support, 
(PEEP) = 10 cmH 2 O), pressure support = 10 cmH 2 O, oxygen 
flow = 60 lit/min, and FiO 2 &lt; 50%. Subsequently, FiO 2 was 
adjusted based on PaO 2 . 
The rapid shallow breathing index (RSBI), which is the 
proportion of respiratory rate/ tidal volume, was considered 
a criterion for extubation: if this proportion was &gt; 105, the 
patient was regarded as not being able to stand extubation 
(Crawford J, Otero R, Donnino M, Garcia J, Khazal R, 
Lenoir T. Rapid shallow breathing index-a key predictor for 
noninvasive ventilation. Critical Care 2007;11:169). Before 
extubation, the Recruitment Maneuver was done for all the 
patients. 
In the conventional extubation method, the patient's mouth 
was washed and suctioned using normal saline (10 cc). Next, 
separation from the machine was done. In aseptic condition, </p>

<p>Fardin Yousefshahi et al. </p>

<p>TEHRAN HEART CENTER </p>

<p>The Journal of Tehran University Heart Center123 </p>

<p>A New Method for Extubation: Comparison between Conventional and New Methods </p>

<p>the patient's tracheal tube was thereafter suctioned using a 
suction tube with a caliber ≤ 1/3 the caliber of the patient's 
tracheal tube. Then, the tracheal tube cuff was evacuated and 
patient was asked to take a deep breath. In the climax of the 
inspiration, the patient was extubated. 
In the new method, the patient's mouth was suctioned dry 
(without liquid). Then, only if it was necessary, intra-tracheal 
suction was done. Afterward and before evacuating the 
tracheal tube cuff, the system's PEEP was set to 15 cmH 2 O 
and PSV to 20 cmH 2 O. Next, immediately after evacuating 
the cuff with a syringe, the patient's mouth and pharynx 
were suctioned cautiously. And finally, the tracheal tube was 
removed along its curve. 
Extubation in both methods was done by trained nurses. 
If there was secretion in the pharynx, it was suctioned again 
and the patient was encouraged to cough or swallow the 
secretion and to breathe deeply. The patient was set in a 
semi-sitting posture (30-45 degrees) and oxygenation was 
done with nasal oxygen, and if necessary, by using a face 
mask with an oxygen reservoir bag. 
Based on ethical rules, in the fifth and sixth time periods, 
ABG analysis (as an invasive procedure) was conducted in 
accordance with the rules of our ICU or the clinical judgment 
of the anesthesiologist. 
The results are reported as mean ± standard deviation (SD) 
for the quantitative variables and are summarized by absolute 
frequencies and percentages for the categorical variables. 
Differences in the distribution of the characteristics in the 
patients were examined using the chi-square test for the 
discrete variables, while the t-test was employed to examine 
differences between the two groups for the continuous 
variables. Logistic regression analysis was utilized to 
eliminate the effect of the confounders. For the statistical 
analyses, the statistical software <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">16.0</rs> for 
Windows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL) and the statistical 
package <rs id="software-1" type="software">SAS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">9.1</rs> for windows (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc</rs>., 
Cary, NC, USA) were used. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>This study initially recruited 257 patients, and after 5 
patients were eliminated because their intubation time 
exceeded 36 hours as a result of decreased consciousness 
level, hemodynamic instability, or the other underlying 
diseases, the study population was divided into the 
conventional group (n = 154) and the new method group 
(n = 98).Totally, 74.2% of the cases were male and 25.8% 
female:73.4% male and 26.6% female in the control group 
and 75.5% male and 24.5% female in the case group (p value 
= 0.7). According to the Chi-Square statistical method, there 
was no significant difference between the two groups. The 
distribution of the independent quantitative variables, in all 
the patients in the study and differentially in the two groups </p>

<p>is shown in Table 1. 
As regards the underlying diseases and risk factors, 
cigarette smoking was seen in 37.8% of all the patients, 
followed by diabetes mellitus (31.9%). There was no 
significant difference between the two groups in the 
percentage of the diabetic patients (p value = 0.98), chronic 
obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) patients (p value 
= 0.08), cigarette smoking (p value = 0.84), and opium 
consumption (p value = 0.23). In terms of admission in 
the ICU (p value = 0.95), inotrope requirement (p value = 
0.71) and balloon pump before extubation (p value = 0.71) 
and balloon pump two hours after ICU admission (p value 
= 1), there was no significant difference between the two 
groups. There was, however, a significant difference in the 
percentage of inotrope usage two hours after ICU admission: 
the control group 26% and the case group 12% (p value = 
0.01). There was a significant difference between the two 
groups in the age average: 61.84 ± 8.86 years in the control 
group and 59.07 ± 10.05 years in case group (p value = 0.02), 
but the difference was not significant, clinically. There was 
no significant difference in the other variables like BMI (p 
value = 0.2), graft number (p value = 0.77), cardiopulmonary 
bypass (CPB) time (p value = 0.16), cross-clamp time (p 
value = 0.15), ejection fraction (EF) % (p value = 0.44), and 
FEV 1 / FVC (p value = 0.28) between the new method and 
control groups. Based on our findings, recorded in Table 2, 
some of the ABG parameters such as PaO 2 , pH, and oxygen 
saturation (SpO 2 ) showed significant differences between the 
two groups, before extubation. 
After extubation, all the patients were oxygenated by 
nasal cannulae unless there was 1) respiratory distress, 2) 
tachypnea &gt; 35/min, or 3) PO 2 decrease &lt; 60 mmHg, in 
which case, nasal cannulae were replaced with reservoir 
masks. The patients were, accordingly, assigned into two 
groups according to the usage of the nasal cannulae or 
reservoir mask: 9 (5.9%) patients in the control group and 
none of the patients in the case group required reservoir 
masks. (The assumption was that the reservoir mask 
provides 80% oxygenation and the nasal cannula 40 %.) 
One hour after extubation, the difference was significant 
(p value = 0.02). Four hours after extubation, 8 patients in 
the control group and none in the case group needed the 
reservoir mask and breathing via the nasal cannula was 
adequate to prepare desired oxygenation; nevertheless, the 
difference was not significant (p value = 0.08). With respect 
to inotrope or balloon pump requirement at one, four, and 
twelve hours after extubation, there were no significant 
differences between the patients of the conventional and new 
method groups. In the hours mentioned, p values were 0.8, 
0.66, and 0.29, respectively, for inotrope demand and 0.59, 
0.54, and 0.08 for balloon pump requirement. A comparison 
of the dependent variables between the two groups revealed 
no significant difference in the ICU length of stay (LOS) 
between the two groups (Table 3). </p>



<p>The Journal of Tehran University Heart Center </p>

<p>Table 1. Independent quantitative variables in the two groups of study </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Total 
Conventional Method 
New Method 
P value </p>

<p>Age (y) 
60.8±9.4 
61.8±8.9 
59.1±10.1 
0.02 </p>

<p>Graft Number 
3.4±0.8 
3.4±0.9 
3.4±0.8 
0.77 </p>

<p>CPB time (min) 
68.0±23.9 
69.5±25.8 
64.5±18.1 
0.16 </p>

<p>Cross-clamp time (min) 
41.3±14.8 
42.2±15.5 
38.7±12.5 
0.15 </p>

<p>BMI (Kg/m 
2 ) 
27.3±4.1 
27.6±4.3 
26.9±3.8 
0.20 </p>

<p>EF (%) 
47.9±9.4 
48.3±9.9 
47.4±8.5 
0.44 </p>

<p>FEV 1 /FVC 
86.2±13.6 
86.9±12.6 
84.9±15.2 
0.28 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Data are presented as mean±SD 
CPB, Cardiopulmonary bypass; BMI, Body mass index; EF, Ejection fraction; FEV 1 /FVC, Forced expiratory volume in 1 second/forced vital capacity </p>

<p>Table 2. Arterial blood gas parameters before extubation in the two groups of study </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Conventional Method 
New Method 
P value </p>

<p>One hour after ICU Admission </p>

<p>pH 
7.4±0.1 
7.4±0.1 
0.89 </p>

<p>PaO 2 (mmHg) 
128.4±33.8 
138.7±46.2 
0.06 </p>

<p>BE (mmol/L) 
-4.9±3.2 
-4.8 ± 2.9 
0.76 </p>

<p>SpO 2 (%) 
97.9±1.5 
98.0±1.4 
0.74 </p>

<p>Just before extubation </p>

<p>pH 
7.3±0.1 
7.3±0.1 
&lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>PaO 2 (mmHg) 
110.8±25.0 
119.3±28.9 
&lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>BE (mm/L) 
-4.8±2.9 
-4.9±3.2 
0.66 </p>

<p>SpO 2 (%) 
96.9±1.6 
97.7±1.3 
&lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Data are presented as mean±SD 
pH, Hydrogen ion concentration; PaO 2 , Alveolar oxygen partial pressure; BE, Base excess; SpO 2 , Oxygen saturation </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Table 3. Length of stay in the ICU and arterial blood gas parameters after extubation in two groups of study </p>

<p>Conventional Method 
New Method 
P value </p>

<p>LOS 
40.6±31.4 
42.7±30.5 
0.61 </p>

<p>One hour after extubation </p>

<p>PaO 2 (mmHg) 
96.4±23.7 
100.3±22.4 
0.21 </p>

<p>SpO 2 (%) 
96.2±1.9 
96.6±1.9 
0.06 </p>

<p>pH 
7.3±0.1 
7.3±0.1 
0.51 </p>

<p>PaCO 2 (mmHg) 
36.2±4.7 
37.6±4.1 
0.02 </p>

<p>BE (mmol/L) 
-4.5±2.8 
-4.0±3.2 
0.23 </p>

<p>Four hours after extubation </p>

<p>PaO 2 (mmHg) 
94.5±24.7 
96.1±18.8 
0.64 </p>

<p>SpO 2 (%) 
96.1±1.9 
96.7±1.5 
0.03 </p>

<p>pH 
7.4±0.1 
7.4±0.1 
0.29 </p>

<p>PaCO 2 (mmHg) 
35.8±4.9 
36.5±4.1 
0.32 </p>

<p>BE (mmol/L) 
-3.7±2.7 
-3.7±3.9 
0.98 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Data are presented as mean±SD 
ICU, Intensive care unit; LOS, Length of stay; PaO 2 , Alveolar oxygen partial pressure; SpO 2 , Oxygen saturation; pH, Hydrogen ion concentration; PaCO 2 , 
Partial pressure of carbon dioxide in arterial blood; BE, Base excess </p>

<p>Fardin Yousefshahi et al. </p>

<p>TEHRAN HEART CENTER </p>

<p>The Journal of Tehran University Heart Center125 </p>

<p>As it has been mentioned above, after weaning the patient 
from the respiratory machine, FiO 2 was estimated based 
on the patient's oxygenation way: 0.4 (40%) for the nasal 
cannula and 0.8 (80%) for the reservoir mask. 
Among the independent variables, significant differences 
were seen in the variables of age (p value = 0.02), inotrope (p 
value = 0.01), and ABG factors (Table 2) like PaO 2 (p value 
= 0.02), pH (p value = 0.01), and SpO 2 (p value = 0.001) 
when using the "t-test". Nonetheless, PaO 2 / FiO 2 was not 
different between the two groups statistically. Ultimately, the 
"regression" statistical method was utilized to consider the 
confounding effect(s) of these factors. 
Among the ABG factors, one hour after extubation, 
partial pressure of carbon dioxide in arterial blood (PaCO 2 ) 
in the control group was lower than that in the case group, 
significantly (Table 3). A comparison of PaCO 2 , four hours 
after extubation, between the two groups demonstrated 
recovery in PaCO 2 reduction, with the difference not 
constituting a significant difference anymore. Four hours 
after extubation, SpO 2 exhibited improvement in the case 
group by comparison with that in the control group; their 
difference was statistically significant (p value = 0.03) 
(Table 3). 
Finally, PaO 2 / FiO 2 = 225 (approximately the average 
level), at which the new extubation method had the most 
efficiency, was considered as the cut point. A comparison of 
this proportion between the two groups showed that PaO2 
/ FiO 2 &lt; 225 (PaO 2 / FiO 2 less than 225) was about 51.3% 
and 37.3% in the conventional and new method groups, 
respectively, at one hour after extubation, and also, 54.2% 
and 32.7% in the control and case groups, respectively, at 
four hours after extubation; their differences were statistically 
significant. The other ABG variables such as pH, BE (base 
excess), and PaO 2 did not show significant statistical 
differences between the two study groups, although almost 
all of them exhibited improvement in the new method group. 
Furthermore, twelve hours after extubation, most of the 
patients who required ABG, and all of them, forty-eight hours 
after that, were in the control group. There was a higher rate 
of requirement to the reservoir mask than the nasal cannula 
in the control group than that in the case group at one hour 
after extubation, with the difference being significant. Also, </p>

<p>at four hours after extubation, there was no requirement to 
the reservoir mask in the case group but 8 patients in the 
control group required the usage of the reservoir mask; as 
a result, breathing via the nasal cannula seemed appropriate 
for providing proper oxygenation in the case group. The 
percentages of the patients with Po 2 / Fio 2 &lt; 200 (PaO 2 / FiO 2 
less than 200) at one and four hours after extubation were 
smaller in the case group than in the control group, but their 
differences were not significant (Table 4). 
At one hour after extubation, 7 (4.6%) patients in the 
control group showed PO 2 / FiO 2 &lt; 150, whereas none of the 
patients in the case group developed this complication; their 
difference was significant. Also, in the control group, at four 
and twelve hours after extubation, 9 and 10 patients showed 
PO 2 / FiO 2 &lt; 150 (PaO 2 / FiO 2 less than 150), respectively, 
while no patient experienced a similar situation in the new 
method group. At forty-eight hours after extubation, in the 
open method group, 8 patients (of 20), who required ABG, 
had respiratory parameters within the range of PO 2 / FiO 2 &lt; 
150. In contrast, no patient required ABG forty-eight hours 
after extubation in the other group (Table 5). 
As is mentioned in the results, variables that might 
affect the findings were regarded as confounding variables. 
Considering the variables of age, gender, BMI, EF, 
intubation time, FEV 1 / FVC, and PaO 2 / FiO 2 in the "logistic 
regression" test demonstrated that the new method decreased 
the extubation complications in PaO 2 / FiO 2 &lt; 225 at one 
and four hours after extubation, and PO 2 / FiO 2 &lt; 200 at one, 
four, and twelve hours after extubation. However, only the 
difference in PaO 2 / FiO 2 &lt; 225 at four hours after extubation 
was statistically significant between the two groups (Table 
6). 
Additionally, the multivariable linear regression test, <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">16</rs>, showed a higher range of PaO 2 / FiO 2 at one hour after 
extubation and PaO 2 / FiO 2 at four hours after extubation 
in the patients with the new extubation method than that in 
those with the conventional extubation method (8.888 mmHg 
and 8.248 mmHg, respectively); there were, however, no 
significant differences. </p>

<p>Table 4. Oxygenation in range of PaO 2 / FiO 2 &lt; 200 in the two groups of study </p>

<p>Conventional Method 
New Method 
P value </p>

<p>One hour after ICU admission 
35 (23.0) 
26 (29.5) 
0.25 </p>

<p>Just before extubation 
29 (19.0) 
14 (18.2) 
0.80 </p>

<p>One hour after extubation 
45 (29.6) 
15 (18.1) 
0.05 </p>

<p>Four hours after extubation 
49 (34.5) 
14 (26.9) 
0.31 </p>

<p>Twelve hours after extubation 
58 (56.9) 
8 (42.1) 
0.23 </p>

<p>Forty-eight hours after extubation 
16 (80.0) 
-
-</p>

<p>* Date are presented as n (%) 
PaO 2 /FiO 2 , Alveolar oxygen partial pressure / fraction of inspired oxygen; ICU, Intensive care unit </p>

<p>A New Method for Extubation: Comparison between Conventional and New Methods </p>



<p>The Journal of Tehran University Heart Center </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Tracheal extubation has captured precious little attention 
compared with intubation. 
1 We sought to present the details 
of a new extubation method to prevent atelectasis and 
hypoxia and to augment PaO 2 / FiO 2 in the ICU for first time. 
Although we found no comprehensive report of a similar 
method to compare our results with, our new method and 
its goals, mechanically, bears considerable similarities with 
the open lung concept (OLC) recruitment maneuver and use 
of PEEP and continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) 
during and after surgery. The application of the OLC results 
in fewer episodes of hypoxemia, 
9, 10 and the use of PEEP as 
well as that of CPAP prevents the formation of atelectasis. </p>

<p>12, 13,   17 In all the above-mentioned methods, preventing atelectasis 
and its unavoidable profound and catastrophic consequences 
in highly inflame lung parenchyma after on-pump CABG are 
the main target. Our study would be deemed a new aspect of 
the OLC, which has been previously ignored. In comparison 
with the existing literature on the OLC, we placed greater 
emphasis on a very significant, albeit temporary, intervention 
which can significantly improve the patient's condition 
and could be considered a routine in other populations of 
ICU patients. Based on our results, even a short period 
of atelectasia plays an important role in the production of 
hypoxemia in latter phases; consequently, considering the 
OLC strategy, even at definite special times, can have a 
significant preventive effect for hypoxemia. 
Among the ABG factors, one hour after extubation, PaCO 2 
in the control group was significantly lower than that in the </p>

<p>case group (Table 3). It is noteworthy that agitation, pain, 
and hypoxia can cause PaCO 2 reduction after extubation. 
Four hours after extubation, SpO 2 was better in the case 
group than in the control group, with the difference 
constituting statistical significance (p value = 0.03) (Table 
3). Based on these differences and given the importance of 
oxygen saturation, the new extubation method seems more 
appropriate than the old one. 
Finally, considering the cut point of 225 for PaO 2 / FiO 2 , 
we found PaO 2 / FiO 2 &lt; 225 in about 51.3% and 37.3% in the 
conventional and new method groups, respectively, at one 
hour after extubation and also 54.2% and 32.7% in the control 
and case groups, respectively, at four hours after extubation; 
the differences were statistically significant. Therefore, the 
efficiency of the new method for enhancing PaO 2 / FiO 2 and 
oxygenation rate was apparent in the level &lt; 225. Regarding 
the other ABG variables such as pH, BE (base excess), and 
PaO 2 , their differences were not significant statistically; be 
that as it may, almost all of them enjoyed improvement in 
the new method group. Furthermore, with respect to rough 
parameters, clinical need to perform ABG analysis, and 
use of reservoir masks or nasal cannulae, there were fewer 
patients with Po 2 / Fio 2 &lt; 200 and PO 2 / FiO 2 &lt; 300 at one 
and four hours after extubation in the case group. Although 
these differences are not statistically significant, they seem 
to further underscore the efficiency of the new method. 
At forty-eight hours after extubation, in the conventional 
method group, 8 patients (of 20), who required ABG, had 
respiratory parameters within the range of PO 2 / FiO 2 &lt; 150, 
while none of the new method group patients needed ABG </p>

<p>Table 5. Oxygenation in range of PaO 2 / FiO 2 &lt; 150 in the two groups of study </p>

<p>Conventional Method 
New Method 
P value </p>

<p>One hour after ICU admission 
9 (5.9) 
3 (3.4) 
0.39 </p>

<p>Just before extubation 
3 (2.0) 
1 (1.3) 
1.00 </p>

<p>One hour after extubation 
7 (4.6) 
0 (0) 
0.04 </p>

<p>Four hours after extubation 
9 (6.3) 
0 (0) 
0.06 </p>

<p>Twelve hours after extubation 
10 (9.8) 
2 (10.5) 
1.00 </p>

<p>Forty-eight hours after extubation 
8 (40) 
-
-</p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Date are presented as n (%) 
PaO 2 /FiO 2 , Alveolar oxygen partial pressure / Fraction of inspired oxygen; ICU, Intensive care unit </p>

<p>Table 6. Results of multivariable linear regression tests </p>

<p>OR 
95% CI 
P value </p>

<p>PaO 2 /FiO 2 &lt; 225 </p>

<p>One hour after extubation 
0.62 
0.30-1.29 
0.20 </p>

<p>Four hours after extubation 
0.29 
0.12-0.71 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>PaO 2 /FiO 2 &lt; 200 </p>

<p>One hour after extubation 
0.53 
0.21-1.28 
0.15 </p>

<p>Four hours after extubation 
0.63 
0.25-1.57 
0.32 </p>

<p>Twelve hours after extubation 
0.30 
0.07-1.37 
0.12 </p>

<p>OR, Odds ratio; CI, Confidence interval; PaO 2 /FiO 2 , Partial pressure of oxygen in arterial blood / Fraction of inspired oxygen </p>

<p>Fardin Yousefshahi et al. </p>

<p>TEHRAN HEART CENTER </p>

<p>The Journal of Tehran University Heart Center127 </p>

<p>forty-eight hours after extubation. Given the high rate of 
mortality and morbidity in such patients, these percentages 
should be regarded as a very important clinical parameter to 
compare the two groups and to introduce the new method as 
an effective and safe extubation method. 
Considering confounding variables in the logistic 
regression test using <rs id="software-3" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">9.1</rs> software, we found that in 
almost all the time periods, PaO 2 / FiO 2 was higher in the 
new extubation method group; however, only PaO 2 / FiO 2 
four hours after extubation &lt; 225 between the two groups 
was statistically significant (Table 6). 
These findings suggest that our new method of extubation 
enjoys an acceptable oxygenation profile after CABG by 
comparison with the conventional method. 
One of the most important restrictions in this study was 
ethical limitations in redundant blood sampling for ABG. 
When the patients were discharged from the ICU, their 
catheters were off, usually. Therefore, afterward, blood 
sampling for ABG was limited for the patients who required 
it based on medical indications. In addition, after extubating 
and weaning the patients from the respiratory machine, FiO 2 
was estimated based on the nasal mask or the reservoir mask, 
40% or 80%, respectively. 
We believe that accurate monitoring of all patients with 
PO 2 / FiO 2 &lt; 200 and PO 2 / FiO 2 &lt; 300, at least for forty-eight 
hours after extubation (when atelectasia, pneumonia, or the 
other extubation complications may have appeared), could 
indicate the differences between the two methods. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Considering all of the findings in the present study, we 
believe that our new extubation method could improve some 
respiratory parameters and thus lessen the complications 
and augment oxygenation after extubation. However, future 
studies are required to further confirm our results and 
improve our new extubation method. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank the personnel of the 
Cardiac Surgery Intensive Care Unit of Tehran Heart 
Center for their co-operation. This study was approved and 
supported by Tehran University of Medical Sciences. </p>



<p>A New Method for Extubation: Comparison between Conventional and New Methods </p>

</text></tei>