<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3796294" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: The aim of this study was to evaluate changes of anger 
scores in female karate athletes during 18 months, and to compare anger 
scores in adolescents who continue or stop training karate. 
Method: The sample consisted of 18 female elite karate athletes, 
practicing modern style of karate. To measure anger and its subscales, 
participants were asked to complete "Adolescent Anger Rating Scale" 
(AARS) questionnaire in both stages of the study. Athletes were divided in 
to two groups of "stayer" (n=12) and "quitter" (n=6) if they continued 
practicing karate or stopped it, respectively. In order to study the changes 
of anger score with time, paired T test was used. 
Results: In analysis of changes in anger scores with time, there was a 
statistically significant increase in instrumental anger (p=0.001) and non-
significant increase in other anger scores among 14-year-old girls who 
continued practicing karate. 
Conclusion : Increased instrumental anger in female karate athletes 
could be due to the impact of participation in a combative sport. However, 
the results should be interpreted cautiously due to limitations of the study. </p>

<p>Anger changes in adolescent karate athletes </p>

<p> 
Iranian J Psychiatry 8:2, Jun 2013 ijps.tums.ac.ir </p>

<p>study 
outlines, 
participants 
completed 
the 
questionnaire. Karateka completed the questionnaires 
before the start of their training session. 
To follow up the athletes, all participants were given a 
unique code in the first stage which was repeated in the 
second stage. Informed consent was obtained from the 
adolescents and their caregivers. This study was 
approved by the Research Ethics Committee of Tehran 
University of Medical Sciences. 
More than one year of practice is necessary to assess 
meaningful changes, the athletes were followed for 18 
months (11). In the second stage, participants were 
asked to complete the questionnaire and data sheet 
including demographic data, practice status changes in 
previous 18 months, and the reasons for quitting karate 
if it was the case. At the end of this stage, 18 
adolescents completed the study. Two participants 
were no longer available for assessment. 
Measures 
The "Adolescent Anger Rating Scale" (AARS) 
questionnaire, designed by DM Burney, was applied in 
both stages of the study. The validity and reliability of 
the AARS tool has been reported as satisfactory by 
Burney and Kromrey (12-13). The AARS is a 41-item, 
4-point Likert-type scale which measures adolescents' 
total, and its subscales include reactive anger, 
instrumental anger and anger control. Participants were 
asked to answer the items ranging from "hardly ever" 
to "very often". Reactive anger is an immediate angry 
response to a perceived negative, threatening, or fear-
provoking event. Instrumental anger is defined as a 
negative emotion that triggers a delayed response 
resulting in a desired and planned goal of revenge 
and/or retaliation. Reactive anger score ranges from 8 
to 32 and instrumental anger score range is 20 to 80. 
Higher scores of reactive or instrumental anger show 
greater reactive or instrumental anger. Anger control is 
a method used to respond to reactive and/or 
instrumental stimulations. Anger control score ranges </p>

<p>from 13 to 52 and higher scores show better anger 
control (12). 
Analysis 
The participants were divided in to two groups of 
"stayer" (n=12) and "quitter" (n=6). "Stayers" were 
athletes who have practiced karate throughout the 
previous 18 months for three or more days a week. 
"Quitters" were adolescents who stopped exercising 
karate for at least 6 months and were not willing to 
start again. The "quitter" group was questioned about 
the reason of quitting karate. There were four choices: 
parental prohibition i.e., "My parents don't allow me to 
take karate classes anymore." personal motivation, i.e., 
"I am not interested in karate anymore." injury, i.e., "I 
was injured during training or competition"; and for 
other details, the adolescents were allowed to write 
their own reasons. 
In order to compare anger scores of "stayer" and 
"quitter" groups at the start or end of the study, 
independent t-test was used, and paired t-test was used 
to study the changes of anger score with time. <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> 
software (version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13</rs>) was used for data analysis; and p 
values of less than 0.05 were considered statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>Result </p>

<p>The mean age of adolescents was 14.6 (SD=2.2) at the 
beginning of the study. Furthermore, we divided the 
adolescents into two groups of "stayers" and "quitters". 
In comparison of stayers and quitters' age, which were 
14.1 (SD=2.2) and 15.8 (SD=1.7) respectively, the 
difference was not significant (p=0.11). As shown in 
table 1, no significant differences were observed 
between the two groups of stayers and quitters in anger 
scores (total anger, reactive anger, instrumental anger 
and anger control) neither at the beginning nor at the 
end of the study. </p>

<p>Table 1: Comparison of anger scores in "stayer" and "quitter" groups at the beginning (stage 1) and after 18 
months (stage 2) </p>

<p>Stage 1 
Stage 2 
Stayer 
Quitter 
t </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Stayer 
Quitter 
t 
P value 
Reactive anger 
48.33 (8.06) </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>44.3 (7.0) 
1.025 
0.320 
49.67 (5.53) 
53.00 (9.96) 
-0.92 
0.396 
Instrumental anger 
47.92 (4.12) 
49.6 (13.05) 
-0.43 
0.670 
55.17 (4.91) 
54.83 (3.19) 
0.15 
0.883 
Anger control 
52.00 (7.16) 
50.00 (8.20) 
0.53 
0.601 
52.08 (6.53) 
52.50 (6.25) 
-0.12 
0.899 
Total anger 
48.58 (6.93) 
48.00 (4.64) 
0.13 
0.893 
51.33 (5.05) 
52.00 (5.40) 
-0.25 
0.800 
* P value and t value stands for independent t-test analysis between stayers and quitters in each stage. 
mean (standard deviation) </p>

<p>Table 2: Changes of anger scores in 18 months </p>

<p>Stayer 
Quitter 
Total </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P 
value </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>95% 
confidence 
interval 
t </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P 
value </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>95% confidence 
interval 
t </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P 
value </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>95% 
confidence 
interval 
lower 
upper 
lower 
upper 
lower 
upper 
Reactive 
anger </p>

<p>-0.464 
0.652 
-7.65 
4.99 
0.146 
0.146 
-21.63 
4.30 
-1.454 
0.164 
-9.26 
1.71 </p>

<p>Instrumental 
anger </p>

<p>-4.699 
0.001 
-10.65 
-3.85 
-1.080 
0.330 
17.47 
7.13 
-3.593 
0.002 
-10.40 
-2.71 </p>

<p>Anger control 
-0.035 
0.973 
-5.39 
5.23 
-0.677 
0.529 
-12.00 
7.00 
-0.449 
0.659 
-5.07 
3.29 
Total anger 
-0.947 
0.364 
-9.14 
3.64 
-0.862 
0.428 
-15.93 
7.93 
-1.319 
0.205 
-8.23 
1.90 
* p value and t value stands for paired t-test analysis. </p>

<p>Ziaee, Lotfian, Memari </p>

<p> 
Iranian J Psychiatry 8:2, Jun 2013 ijps.tums.ac.ir </p>

<p>However, in examining longitudinal changes in anger 
scores, paired t-test analysis showed a significant 
increase in instrumental anger after 18 months. Further 
analysis in each group revealed that instrumental anger 
significantly increased in stayers, but not in quitters as 
it is shown in Table 2. 
Furthermore, when quitters were asked about the 
reason of quitting karate, 5 of 6 (~ 83%) indicated the 
personal motivation, though one participant did not 
state any reason. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Previous studies have shown that girls are generally 
less aggressive than boys, although there are some 
reports of no sex difference in anger (14-15). It was 
reported that 14-year-old girls used aggression as a 
problem-solving strategy more than 17-year-old girls. 
In other words, in late adolescence (17 years of age) 
aggression decreases to the lowest level, which seems 
to be different from behavioral maturation in boys(15- 16).Overall, it seems necessary to investigate how 
martial arts influence girls' performance instead of 
generalizing the anger and aggressiveness findings in 
boys to their female counterparts (17). Therefore, the 
main purpose of this study was to observe the changes 
in anger scores of a group of female elite karate 
athletes. 
Investigating karate, wrestling and boxing, Bjorkqvist 
and Varhama reported positive effects of karate 
training on males and negative effects on females in 
violent conflict resolution compared with other groups 
(18). Wargo examined personality characteristics of 
martial athletes, and found two main differences 
among expert and novice female players and novice 
and expert male players. Expert female karateka 
received significantly higher scores on paranoia and 
anger, as well as lower measures in social discomfort 
(19). Accordingly, our results revealed a statistically 
significant increase in instrumental anger and non-
significant increase in other anger scores among 14-
year-old girls across a period of 18 months. A possible 
explanation may be that participation in martial arts 
training and competition sessions can suppress or 
reverse the developmental decrease of anger and 
aggressiveness in girls. 
Another possible explanation for observed increase of 
anger scores is the style of training. Karate could be 
practiced in a traditional or modern style; each of 
which may have a distinct influence on adolescents' 
aggressiveness and anger. Those athletes who attended 
a modern program with more emphasis on combat and 
goal orientation as the athletes in the present study, 
showed higher aggressiveness score, which was 
assumed to be the result of the training style (10). 
Although previous studies showed that Judo and Karate 
training decreases aggressiveness, our results in 
accordance with Reynes &amp; Lorant study, did not 
support these early findings. Authors also proposed a </p>

<p>correlation between kata, meditation and self-control 
(9). According to a review by Vertonghen and 
Theeboom, there is an inconstancy in the findings of 
studies after mid 90s compared with earlier studies that 
reported positive impact of martial arts training on 
personality traits. This discrepancy may be due to 
increase in popularity of modern style of martial arts 
(20). Another potential source of difference, which was 
reported by Maxwell and colleagues, is culture. They 
addressed the differences in anger and aggressiveness 
between British and Hong Kong Chinese athletes, and 
reported lower aggressive responses or more frequent 
disapproval of aggressive behaviors in eastern male 
athletes, although the difference was not observed in 
anger (21-22). Consequently, the differences between 
our data and results from East Asian athletes could be 
explained in a sociocultural context . </p>

<p>Limitation </p>

<p>The study findings should be interpreted with caution 
due to small sample size and lack of a control group. 
The other limitation is the application of only one 
measure for presenting anger. Although examining 
other psychosocial factors underlying anger in athletes 
is beyond the scope of the current study, further 
investigation on possible associated factors will be 
warranted. Despite the limitations, there seems to be 
some strong points in the study. To our knowledge, this 
is the first longitudinal study investigating anger in 
female karate athletes. Moreover, we followed quitters 
and stayers in parallel to ensure a real comparison. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Although a developmental decrease was presumed, 
young girls training karate showed a small increase in 
anger scores. Increased instrumental anger in female 
karate athletes could be due to the impact of 
participation in a combative sport. However, the results 
should be interpreted cautiously due to limitations of 
the study. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This study was funded by Sports Medicine Research 
Center and Vice-Chancellor for Research of Tehran 
University of Medical Sciences. The authors would 
like to acknowledge to the athletes and their trainers for 
their cooperation during this period of time. </p>



<p>Anger changes in adolescent karate athletes </p>

<p> 
Iranian J Psychiatry 8:2, Jun 2013 ijps.tums.ac.ir </p>



</text></tei>