<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3886109" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Objectives: The purpose of this study was to evaluate the oral health-related quality of life of patients treated with implant-
supported mandibular overdentures and to compare the attachment systems used. 
Material and Methods: Altogether 112 patients treated with implant-supported mandibular overdentures in 1985 -2004 were 
invited to the follow-up; 58 of them attended and replied to the Oral Health Impact Profile (OHIP-14) -questionnaire. There 
were 48 overdentures with a bar connection and 10 with a ball connection, the total number of implants installed and still in 
use was 197. The mean follow-up time was 13.7 years. The associations between the OHIP-14 variables and the patient's age, 
gender as well as the number of implants supporting the overdenture and the type of attachment used were assessed. 
Results: The results showed that patients with implant-supported mandibular overdentures were satisfied with their oral 
health-related quality of life (OHRQoL). Older patients were more satisfied than younger ones in both genders. Neither the 
implant connection type nor the number of supporting implants seemed to have a significant influence on the OHRQoL. 
Conclusions: Especially older patients with mandibular implant-supported overdentures were satisfied with their oral health-
related quality of life. Attachment type or the number of supporting implants did not have a significant influence on the oral 
health-related quality of life. </p>

<p>Dental implants have been used in edentulous jaws 
to improve the retention and stability of complete 
dentures. Attachment to the implants improves the 
stability and function of the prostheses and increases 
patient satisfaction [1-4]. The implant connection also 
improves neuromuscular activity and adaptation and 
thereby substantially improves masticatory function 
in edentulous patients [5-12]. Implant treatment nearly 
doubles maximum bite forces compared with those 
achieved with conventional complete dentures, and jaw 
muscles are used in a more efficient way [1,13]. 
Quality of life is affected in some way by oral health 
in the majority of people [14-16]. The type and quality 
of prosthetic constructions, and nowadays more often 
implant-supported prostheses, can be considered one 
aspect of oral health in elderly patients. The oral health 
impact profile index (OHIP-14) [17] has been used as a 
shortened 14-item questionnaire to evaluate the impact 
of oral health on the quality of life. The index measures 
people's perception of the social impact of oral 
disorders on their well-being. The OHIP-14 captures 
only negative impacts, whereas some other oral health-
dependent quality of life instruments capture both 
positive and negative impacts. However, the OHIP is the 
most frequently used and best-documented instrument 
nowadays [18]. 
The aim of our retrospective study was to gather 
information about the outcome of treatment with 
implant-supported mandibular overdentures from the 
patients' perceptions by using the oral health impact 
profile index (OHIP-14) and to compare the attachment 
systems used. The research hypothesis was that implant 
connection in complete dentures results in a favourable 
assessment of patients' oral health-related quality of 
life. </p>

<p>MATERIAL AND METHODS </p>

<p>Altogether 112 patients treated with implant-supported 
mandibular overdentures between 1985 and 2004 were 
invited to the follow-up [2]. Patients were referred 
to specialist care to the Department of Oral and 
Maxillofacial Surgery in Oulu University Hospital 
being very demanding cases. Main indications for 
implant treatment of these patients were severe retention 
problems of conventional prostheses, recurrent mucosal 
pain and sore spots and problems with chewing related 
to advanced alveolar bone resorption. 
The number of patients who took no contact and did 
not attend was 22. Fourteen patients had no possibility </p>

<p>to come or said they didn't want to come and 18 patients 
had died. In all, 58 (51.8%) of the invited patients 
(46 female and 12 male) attended the examination; 
33/58 of the patients were treated during 1985 -1994 
and 25/58 during 1995 -2004. Fifty participants out of 
58 gave answers to all the OHIP-14 items [18]. There 
were 6 persons with 1 missing answer and 2 persons 
with more than 2 missing answers. 
The mean age of the patients examined was 55.2 
years (range 37 to 78) at the time of the implantation 
procedure and 69 years (range 56 to 90) at the time of 
the follow-up, the mean follow-up time was 13.7 years 
(range 3.3 to 21.9). 
The total number of implants installed and still in use 
was 197 (average number 3 implants/ overdenture, range 
2 to 4), mean length 12 mm (range 8 to 21 mm). There 
were altogether 48 overdentures with a bar connection 
and 10 with a ball connection. Fifty-three patients had 
a conventional complete denture in the opposite jaw, 2 
patients had an implant-retained overdenture, 1 patient 
had an implant-supported fixed partial denture, 1 patient 
had a removable partial denture and 1 patient had his 
own teeth. The questionnaire (OHIP-14) was filled in 
by the patients before the clinical examination [17]. 
Every 7 dimension includes two items, yielding 
altogether 14 (OHIP 1-14). The seven dimensions are 
functional limitation, physical pain, psychological 
discomfort, physical disability, psychological disability, 
social disability and handicap. The five categories of 
response for each item are never (= 0), hardly ever 
(= 1), occasionally (= 2), fairly often (= 3) and very 
often (= 4). Higher OHIP scores indicate worse, and 
lower OHIP scores indicate better oral health-related 
quality of life. 
This study of 58 patients was approved by the Ethical 
Committee of the Northern Ostrobothnia Hospital 
District. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The average values for the OHIP-14 were calculated 
using non-missing score values and the results were 
analyzed using ANOVA and Student's T-test. <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> 
software (SPSS, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 16.0</rs>, SPSS, Chicago, IL, 
USA) was used to perform the statistical analyses of the 
data. A significant level of P &lt; 0.05 was used. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The frequencies of the seven different OHIP dimensions 
are presented in Figure 1A -G. The distribution of the 
patient's responses was uniform in all seven OHIP-14 
dimensions except in the dimension of 'physical pain', </p>

<p>Figure 1. Patients' perceptions of the social impact of oral disorders 
on their well-being according to the questionnaire (OHIP-14). 
The five categories of response for each item are never (= 0), hardly 
ever (= 1), occasionally (= 2), fairly often (= 3) and very often (= 4). 
A = Functional limitation ('trouble pronouncing words because of 
problems with teeth, mouth or dentures' (OHIP 1) and 'sense of taste 
has worsened because of problems with teeth, mouth or dentures' 
(OHIP 2)). 
B = Physical pain ('painful aching in the mouth' (OHIP 3) and 
'uncomfortable to eat any foods because of problems with teeth, 
mouth or dentures' (OHIP 4)). 
C = Psychological discomfort ('have been self-conscious because of 
teeth, mouth or dentures' (OHIP 5) and 'have felt tense because of 
problems with teeth, mouth or dentures' (OHIP 6)). 
D = Physical disability ('diet has been unsatisfactory because of 
problems with teeth, mouth or dentures' (OHIP 7) and 'have had to 
interrupt meals because of problems with teeth, mouth or dentures' 
(OHIP 8)). 
E = Psychological disability ('difficult to relax because of problems 
with teeth, mouth or dentures' (OHIP 9) and 'have been a bit 
embarrassed because of problems with teeth, mouth or dentures' 
(OHIP 10)). </p>

<p>http://www.ejomr.org/JOMR/archives/2013/2/e4/v4n2e4ht.htm 
J Oral Maxillofac Res 2013 (Apr-Jun) | vol. 4 | No 2 | e4 | p.3 
(page number not for citation purposes) </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF ORAL &amp; MAXILLOFACIAL RESEARCH 
Kuoppala et al. </p>

<p>F = Social disability ('have been a bit irritable with other people because of problems with teeth, mouth or dentures' (OHIP 11) and 'have 
had difficulty doing usual jobs because of problems with teeth, mouth or dentures' (OHIP 12)). 
G = Handicap ('have felt that life in general is less satisfying because of problems with teeth, mouth or dentures' (OHIP 13) and 'have been 
totally unable to function because of problems with teeth, mouth or dentures' (OHIP 14)). </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 
cannot 
say 
never 
hardly 
ever 
occasionally fairly 
often 
very 
often </p>

<p>Number of patients </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 
cannot 
say 
never 
hardly 
ever occasionally 
fairly 
often 
very 
often </p>

<p>Number of patients </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 
cannot 
say 
never 
hardly 
ever 
occasionally fairly 
often 
very 
often </p>

<p>Number of patients </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 
never 
hardly 
ever 
occasionally 
fairly 
often 
very 
often </p>

<p>Number of patients </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 
cannot 
say 
never 
hardly 
ever 
occasionally 
fairly 
often 
very 
often </p>

<p>Number of patients </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 
cannot 
say 
never 
hardly 
ever 
occasionally 
fairly 
often 
very 
often </p>

<p>Number of patients </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 
never 
hardly 
ever 
occasionally 
fairly 
often 
very 
often </p>

<p>Number of patients </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>OHIP 3 </p>

<p>OHIP 4 
OHIP 9 </p>

<p>OHIP 10 </p>

<p>OHIP 11 </p>

<p>OHIP 12 </p>

<p>OHIP 13 </p>

<p>OHIP 14 </p>

<p>OHIP 7 </p>

<p>OHIP 8 </p>

<p>OHIP 3 </p>

<p>OHIP 4 </p>

<p>OHIP 5 </p>

<p>OHIP 6 </p>

<p>http://www.ejomr.org/JOMR/archives/2013/2/e4/v4n2e4ht.htm </p>

<p>J Oral Maxillofac Res 2013 (Apr-Jun) | vol. 4 | No 2 | e4 | p.4 
(page number not for citation purposes) </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF ORAL &amp; MAXILLOFACIAL RESEARCH 
Kuoppala et al. </p>

<p>where fewer 'never' answers i.e. more complaints were 
reported by the patients (Figure 1B). 
According to the questionnaire, it was seen that most 
of the patients were satisfied with their oral health and 
prostheses and there were no statistically significant 
differences between women and men (P &gt; 0.05). 
The youngest age group (patients under 65 years 
of age) seemed to differ from the older ones, who 
usually had fewer complaints in the dimensions of 
the OHIP-14 (Figure 2). The older patients reported 
'never' answers more often than the patients under 65 
years of age, whereas the patients under 65 years of age 
more often reported 'very often' or 'fairly often' answers 
in the OHIP-14 questionnaire. The subjects under 65 
years of age seemed to be more dissatisfied with their </p>

<p>quality of life, especially in terms of psychological 
discomfort and disability. They had been self-conscious 
and had felt tense because of their dentures and more 
often had had difficulty relaxing and more often had 
been embarrassed because of problems with their teeth, 
mouth or dentures. For example, 87% of the subjects in 
the older age groups, reported never having difficulty 
relaxing. 
The number of implants supporting the overdenture 
as well as the connection type (bar or ball connection) 
did not have a statistically significant influence on 
the OHIP-14 values (P &gt; 0.05) (Figure 3). It can be 
seen, however, that patients with two implants and 
an overdenture reported higher OHIP-14 values, but 
not significantly, which means more dissatisfaction 
with OHRQoL compared with patients with four 
implants and an overdenture. Slightly higher OHIP-14 
values, but not significantly, i.e. more dissatisfaction, 
were also noted with a ball connection than with bars 
(Figure 4). When comparing the patient groups 
according to the time elapsed since completion of 
the prosthetic treatment (follow-up time 3 to 12 years 
and 13 to 22 years), no statistical differences were found 
in the OHIP-14 values. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>According to the results of the present study, it can 
be seen that patients treated with implant-supported 
mandibular overdentures were satisfied with the 
outcome of the treatment when evaluated using the 
OHIP-14 questionnaire. The clinical situation recorded 
to be good, the prostheses functioned well and only few 
breakages were recorded in the prosthetic constructions </p>

<p>Figure 2. Mean OHIP-14 sum scores in three different age groups 
(P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Figure 3. Mean OHIP-14 scores and number of implants per 
overdenture. No statistically significant difference was found 
between the groups (P &gt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Figure 4. Mean OHIP-14 scores and attachment type in overdentures. 
No statistically significant difference was found between the groups 
(P &gt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Mean OHIP-14 sum score </p>

<p>Age group </p>

<p>Mean OHIP-14 score 
Mean OHIP-14 score </p>

<p>Number of implants/overdenture 
Attachment type </p>

<p>Ball attachment 
Bar attachment </p>

<p>≥ 70 
65 -69 
&lt; 65 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>4 
3 
2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>http://www.ejomr.org/JOMR/archives/2013/2/e4/v4n2e4ht.htm </p>

<p>J Oral Maxillofac Res 2013 (Apr-Jun) | vol. 4 | No 2 | e4 | p.5 
(page number not for citation purposes) </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF ORAL &amp; MAXILLOFACIAL RESEARCH 
Kuoppala et al. </p>

<p>as reported earlier [2]. It must be noted that in some 
cases the follow-up time was over 20 years, and 
67% of the patients examined still had their original 
overdenture in use [2]. In five cases long implants had 
been used in mandible, one patient having even 21 mm 
long implants, which was common in the 80' to achieve 
bicortical anchorage to implants. 
No statistically significant difference was foundbetween 
the number of implants supporting an overdenture 
or the attachment system used when evaluated with 
the OHIP-14 [19]. Contrary to the study by Siadat 
et al. [16], gender did not correlate here with patient 
satisfaction. 
Older patients were even more satisfied in the aspects of 
psychological discomfort and disability when compared 
with patients under 65 years of age. The people in 
the youngest age group were usually still involved 
in working life and had to cope with different social 
situations, and the demands of oral status might have 
been higher than in the older age groups. 
It has been confirmed that older people often lack 
the facility to adapt to changes in edentulousness. 
The degree of adaptive capacity can be expected to 
influence the quality of life [1,2]. On the other hand, it 
has been noted that older people are even satisfied with 
less than ideal oral health and they have less unrealistic 
expectations of the treatment than younger patients. 
Less complaints about oral conditions among the 
elderly have been noted in several studies, for instance 
in the UK and the USA, with lower impact rankings 
in QoL reports, that is to say the impact of oral health </p>

<p>problems on the quality of life decreases with increasing 
age [14,16]. 
This study was retrospective and information given by 
the patients concerning their oral health-related quality 
of life with the aid of OHIP-14 questionnaire was not 
available before implant treatment. Every patient, 
however, had a history of severe problems related to 
use of conventional mandibular dentures. According 
to the present study, treatment outcome with implant-
supported mandibular overdentures was found to be 
good and successful when evaluated with the oral health 
impact profile (OHIP-14). </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>The results of this retrospective study show that patients 
treated with implant-supported mandibular overdentures 
were satisfied with their oral health-related quality of 
life. Differences in age groups show that older patients 
were even more satisfied than younger ones. Gender as 
well as attachment type or the amount of connecting 
implants did not seem to be especially significant in this 
study. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS AND DISCLOSURE 
STATEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest related to this 
study. </p>



<p>To cite this article: 
Kuoppala R, Näpänkangas R, Raustia A. Quality of Life of Patients Treated With Implant-Supported Mandibular Overdentures 
Evaluated With the Oral Health Impact Profile (OHIP-14): a Survey of 58 Patients. 
J Oral Maxillofac Res 2013;4(2):e4 
URL: http://www.ejomr.org/JOMR/archives/2013/2/e4/v4n2e4ht.pdf 
doi: 10.5037/jomr.2013.4204 </p>

<p>Copyright © Kuoppala R, Näpänkangas R, Raustia A. Accepted for publication in the JOURNAL OF ORAL &amp; </p>

<p>MAXILLOFACIAL RESEARCH (http://www.ejomr.org), 19 June 2013. </p>

<p>This is an open-access article, first published in the JOURNAL OF ORAL &amp; MAXILLOFACIAL RESEARCH, distributed 
under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivative Works 3.0 Unported License, which 
permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work and is 
properly cited. The copyright, license information and link to the original publication on (http://www.ejomr.org) must be 
included. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF ORAL &amp; MAXILLOFACIAL RESEARCH 
Kuoppala et al. </p>

</text></tei>