<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3013714" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Large numbers of long RNAs with little or no 
protein-coding potential [long noncoding RNAs 
(lncRNAs)] are being identified in eukaryotes. In 
parallel, increasing data describing the expression 
profiles, molecular features and functions of indi-
vidual lncRNAs in a variety of systems are 
accumulating. To enable the systematic compilation 
and updating of this information, we have developed 
a database (lncRNAdb) containing a comprehensive 
list of lncRNAs that have been shown to have, or to 
be associated with, biological functions in eukary-
otes, as well as messenger RNAs that have regu-
latory roles. Each entry contains referenced 
information about the RNA, including sequences, 
structural information, genomic context, expres-
sion, subcellular localization, conservation, func-
tional evidence and other relevant information. 
lncRNAdb can be searched by querying published 
RNA names and aliases, sequences, species and 
associated protein-coding genes, as well as terms 
contained in the annotations, such as the tissues in 
which the transcripts are expressed and associated 
diseases. In addition, lncRNAdb is linked to the 
UCSC Genome Browser for visualization and 
Noncoding RNA Expression Database (NRED) for 
expression information from a variety of sources. 
lncRNAdb provides a platform for the ongoing col-
lation of the literature pertaining to lncRNAs and 
their association with other genomic elements. 
lncRNAdb can be accessed at: http://www 
.lncrnadb.org/. </p>

<p>The eukaryotic transcriptome is enormous, and com-
prises not only a large set of protein-coding messenger 
RNAs, but also large numbers of non-protein coding 
transcripts that have structural, regulatory or unknown 
functions (1). Noncoding RNAs include intergenic 
transcripts as well as a complex array of RNAs that 
overlap protein-coding loci on both strands (2-4), 
including promoter-associated RNAs (4), intronic RNAs 
(5), convergent and bi-directional transcripts (3), 
noncoding alternatively spliced isoforms of protein-coding 
genes (6) and mRNAs that also have regulatory roles 
as untranslated RNAs (7,8). While some of these RNAs 
are processed to form small RNA species such as 
microRNAs (miRNAs) and small nucleolar RNAs 
(snoRNAs), many can have diverse roles as primary or 
spliced long noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs) (9). In struc-
tural terms, lncRNAs range in size from approximately 
100 to 100 000 bases, can be spliced or unspliced, 
polyadenylated or non-polyadenylated, nuclear or cyto-
plasmic, and are usually transcribed by RNA polymerase 
II and/or III (10). 
The 
combination 
of 
different 
experimental 
methodologies to study the transcriptome of several 
species has resulted in a continuous discovery of novel 
transcripts (11), with the FANTOM project alone 
cataloguing more than 30 000 putative lncRNA tran-
scripts in mouse tissues by full-length cDNA cloning (2). 
This provides a challenge for their molecular and func-
tional characterization, as well as for their cataloguing. 
Although the subset of lncRNAs characterized to date 
corresponds to a small fraction of the long noncoding 
transcripts in multicellular organisms, growing interest in 
the field has resulted in a rapid increase in the character-
ization of individual lncRNAs in a variety of systems. </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +61 7 3346 2079; Fax: +61 7 3346 2101; Email: m.dinger@imb.uq.edu.au 
Correspondence may also be addressed to John S. Mattick. Tel: +61 7 3346 2079; Fax: +61 7 3346 2101; Email: j.mattick@uq.edu.au </p>

<p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first three authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. </p>

<p>D146-D151 Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, Database issue 
Published online 25 November 2010 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkq1138 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>A decade ago less than a dozen lncRNAs were 
recognized and catalogued in all eukaryotes (12), but fol-
lowing the dramatic increase in their numbers, a recent 
catalogue 
listed 
approximately 
40 
functionally 
characterized lncRNAs in mammals alone (13). This list 
contained lncRNAs whose functions had been assessed 
either by loss-or gain-of-function experiments, and did 
not include many that have other types of evidence for 
functionality. For example, several studies have docu-
mented the cell type-specific and/or dynamic expression 
of hundreds of long ncRNAs in various developmental 
systems, such as embryonic stem cell differentiation (14) 
and oligodendrogenesis (15), finding in each case different 
subsets of differentially expressed lncRNAs. 
These studies have indicated that lncRNAs comprise a 
class of bona fide gene products that have been largely 
unaccounted for in public databases such as RefSeq 
(16), UniGene (17) and the Mammalian Gene Collection 
(18). While there are databases cataloguing ncRNAs, 
these have been predominantly focused on well-validated 
classes of small RNAs and contain limited data pertaining 
to lncRNAs. Recently, a database with diverse informa-
tion on imprinted RNAs was made available, which is 
largely comprised of small RNAs, such as piRNAs 
(piwi-interacting RNAs), but also contains imprinted 
lncRNAs, and is restricted to mammals (19). Our 
previous database of noncoding RNAs, RNAdb (20), 
was also limited to mammals, and included all classes of 
regulatory RNAs, such as snoRNAs, piRNAs and 
miRNAs. Due to the rapid expansion in each of these 
classes, they are now independently curated in dedicated 
databases, including miRbase (21), piRNAbank (22) and 
Sno/scaRNAbase (23). Consequently, there is a need for a 
dedicated database of lncRNAs that includes not only 
mammalian lncRNAs, but detailed annotations of 
lncRNAs from all eukaryotic species. </p>

<p>AIMS OF THE DATABASE </p>

<p>lncRNAdb provides a central repository of known 
lncRNAs in eukaryotic cells (including those derived 
from viruses), their aliases and published characteristics. 
A well-collated library will greatly facilitate research of 
these poorly annotated genes. It also aims to decrease in-
stances of replication and unknown identity by the inclu-
sion of aliases such as p15AS, which was reported as a 
novel antisense RNA (24), but appears to be an unspliced 
isoform of a previously described ncRNA called ANRIL 
(25), and Gomafu (26), which is also known as MIAT (27) 
and RNCR2 (28). 
The centralization of lncRNAdb enables integration 
with other resources including the UCSC Genome 
Browser (29) and the Noncoding RNA Expression 
Database (NRED) (30), which provide insight into 
genomic context and expression data. This ensures that 
researchers interested in lncRNAs can conveniently find 
a wide range of information regarding genes of interest 
from a single location. 
Currently, the characteristics and functions of most 
lncRNAs are still unexplored, but it is expected that the </p>

<p>number of studied RNAs will rapidly increase by in silico, 
in vitro and in vivo characterization. By providing a simple 
interface accessible to public users, we aim to provide a 
tool for the scientific community that will allow existing 
entries to be updated, modified to improve accuracy, and 
new entries to be added by users. Following verification of 
new published data by the curators, the information will 
become available in lncRNAdb. </p>

<p>DATABASE STRUCTURE </p>

<p>lncRNAdb is available online at: http://www.lncrnadb 
.org. Users can search the database by lncRNA name, 
nucleotide sequence string, species, annotation status or 
through a full-text search with results being displayed 
for online perusal and available as a tab delimited file 
download. 
Annotated entries include one or more literature refer-
ences, annotations across a series of categories and a list of 
species in which the lncRNA is observed. Literature ref-
erences and genomic coordinates are hyperlinked to 
PubMed and the UCSC Genome Browser, respectively. 
Other biological components related to the annotated 
lncRNAs, such as genomically-associated genes or inter-
acting proteins, are also listed and briefly described in a 
separate table that provides links to the PubMed 
reference. 
The lncRNAdb database also links to NRED, our 
online expression analysis application for ncRNAs in 
mouse and human (30). This extends the database 
through access to relative expression levels of both the 
lncRNAs and their contextually related transcripts in 
various public microarray experiments, such as NCode 
data and the GNF atlas (31), as well as the Allen Brain 
Atlas (32), which includes mouse brain in situ expression 
data for over 800 expressed lncRNAs (33). 
The application architecture consists of a <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Microsoft</rs> 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">asp.NET</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3.5</rs> presentation layer (c#), c# 4.0 data model 
and application layer, and <rs type="software">MySQL</rs> persistent storage. </p>

<p>QUERYING THE DATABASE </p>

<p>Querying the database is a matter of entering one or more 
search criteria (Figure 1A); a full or partial lncRNA name 
(or alias), a search string to interrogate each ncRNA's 
annotations or a species in which the lncRNA is known, 
or any combination of those. lncRNAdb will return a list 
of matching entries whose full detail can be viewed by 
clicking on the lncRNA name. 
To download the database values for the entire list as a 
file of tab delimited text, users can click on the 'Export 
Results' button under the search results. </p>

<p>lncRNAdb CONTENT </p>

<p>Although lncRNAs have been defined previously as tran-
scripts &gt;200 nt (9), this was an arbitrary definition largely 
based on a convenient biochemical cutoff in RNA isola-
tion protocols and the fact that it excluded most known 
small RNAs. In an effort to make a clear distinction to </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, Database issue D147 </p>

<p>small RNA species and to create a more biologically 
meaningful definition of lncRNAs, we consider lncRNAs 
as noncoding RNAs that may have a function as either 
primary or spliced transcripts, which is independent of 
processing into known classes of small RNAs, such as 
miRNAs, piRNAs and snoRNAs, while also excluding 
structural RNAs from classical housekeeping families 
(tRNAs, snoRNAs, spliceosomal RNAs, etc). Existing 
databases and archives, including Sno/scaRNAbase (23), 
miRBase (21), tRNAdb-CE (34) and piRNAbank (22), 
already represent such ncRNAs. However, some 
lncRNAs that are host genes for small RNA species 
(35,36), but may also have roles as regulatory lncRNAs, 
have been included in the annotations. An example is 
the GAS5 lncRNA, which is a repressor of the gluco-
corticoid receptor but also encodes several intronic 
snoRNAs (37). </p>

<p>The database currently contains over 150 lncRNAs 
identified from the literature in around 60 different 
species. Each entry contains a comprehensive range of 
available information about the RNA, including se-
quences, structural information, genomic context, expres-
sion, subcellular localization, conservation, functional 
evidence and relevant 'miscellaneous' information (see 
e.g. in Figure 1B). As expected, most (75%) of 
catalogued lncRNAs are from mammals, for which more 
transcriptomic data is available and which have been more 
intensively studied, but lncRNAs from vertebrates to 
single-celled eukaryotes have been included. 
Among the entries in lncRNAdb, approximately 100 
have functions directly tested by in vitro and/or in vivo 
experiments. For quick reference, these have been listed 
in Supplementary Table S1, highlighting the wide array of 
functional mechanisms and processes affected by </p>

<p>Figure 1. Representative screenshots of lncRNAdb showing (A) the search bar and (B) a lncRNA catalogued in lncRNAdb. Figure 1A shows the 
search fields available for querying the database and some of the pre-made descriptors available. Figure 1B depicts part of the annotation and 
references for the Neat1 transcript. </p>



<p>lncRNAs. This list is not exhaustive, but it catalogues 
functional lncRNAs found not only in mammals but 
also lncRNAs tested in diverse eukaryotic species, such 
as meiRNA (38) in yeast, frq antisense RNAs in 
Neurospora crassa (39), rncs-1 in Caenorhabditis elegans 
(40), IPS1 (41) in plants, Xlsirts in frogs (42) and bereft 
in Drosophila (43). In addition to RNAs expressed in 
normal physiological states, the database contains infor-
mation about RNAs expressed in disease, and even 
lncRNAs derived from viruses and expressed in eukaryot-
ic cells during infection (see below). Examples of lncRNA 
categories that can be used to limit queries are listed 
below. </p>

<p>Imprinted lncRNAs </p>

<p>LncRNAs are prevalent in imprinted regions where they 
can function to control imprinting and the expression of 
other genes from the locus, such as Air (44) and Kncq1ot1 
(45). Some imprinted lncRNAs are host genes for small 
RNAs, such as Bsr (46), where the lncRNA host has no 
known function; or has an independent function, e.g. the 
putative tumour suppressor Meg3/Gtl2 (47). </p>

<p>Disease associated lncRNAs </p>

<p>Underscoring their importance in cellular functions, a 
growing number of lncRNAs have been implicated in a 
variety of diseases, including cancer. These are described 
in the database and include putative or confirmed 
cancer-associated lncRNAs, such as NDM29 (48), 
HOTAIR, which regulates metastatic progression (49), 
and H19, which has been described as both an oncogene 
(50) and a tumour suppressor (51). We also include 
lncRNAs that have been implicated in neurological func-
tions and diseases, including BACE1AS (52) that shows 
increased expression in Alzheimer's disease, and the 
Drosophila hsr-o gene, which is induced by a variety of 
stresses and which has been shown to greatly increase 
protein polyglutamine-induced toxicity and neuro-
degeneration (53). 
In addition, the observation that a substantial fraction 
of the genotypic variation underlying complex phenotypic 
traits occurs in noncoding regions, many of which are 
transcribed into discrete lncRNAs, has led to the appreci-
ation that lncRNAs may play a central role in the molecu-
lar etiology of complex diseases (13). We have catalogued 
RNAs associated with these loci in lncRNAdb, such as 
ANRIL, a well-characterized lncRNA located in the 
complex genetic susceptibility locus INK4b/ARF/INK4a 
implicated in coronary artery disease, type 2 diabetes, 
periodontitis and cancer (24,54,55). We opted to also 
include uncharacterized lncRNAs linked to disease-
susceptibility loci, as cataloguing these transcripts may 
facilitate their recognition as candidates for functional 
studies in normal and pathological conditions. Examples 
include AK023948, which is located in a susceptibility 
locus to papillary thyroid tumour (56), and LOC285194, 
which is located in a copy number alteration and 
loss-of-heterozygosity region in osteosarcoma (57). </p>

<p>Pathogen-induced or derived lncRNAs </p>

<p>Some lncRNAs are produced and modulated by patho-
gens or host cells during infection. These have been mostly 
omitted from other noncoding RNA catalogues, but 
incorporated in lncRNAdb. These include eukaryotic 
parasite transcripts such as the Pinci1 ncRNA family in 
the fungal plant-pathogen Phytophthora infestans, which 
are specifically upregulated during infection (58), and 
mammalian lncRNAs that are induced during viral infec-
tion (59), such as Neat1/VINC in the mouse brain (60), 
or produced in infected cells by oncogenic viruses, such 
as human herpesviruses (61). Indeed, the accumulating 
examples of lncRNAs encoded by viruses and expressed 
in eukaryotic cells have been annotated in lncRNAdb, 
because they can regulate cell function and are relevant 
to disease etiology. For instance, b2.7 is a 2.7 kb ncRNA 
encoded in the herpesvirus HCMV genome that is rapidly 
accumulated upon infection and has a fundamental role in 
preventing metabolic dysfunction and apoptosis of the 
host cell (62). </p>

<p>Bifunctional RNAs </p>

<p>An emerging class of genes is those encoding bifunctional 
RNAs, which can have multiple independent roles, such as 
acting as a regulatory lncRNA or being translated into a 
protein. Examples include well-known lncRNAs such as 
the co-activator SRA transcript, isoforms of which also 
encode a protein (8,63), and known protein coding 
genes, such as p53, whose transcripts also act as regulatory 
RNAs (7). In some cases, splicing isoforms are known to 
encode a protein, whereas specific splicing isoforms 
encode regulatory lncRNAs, such as the LXRB/ 
LXRBSV isoform pair (6). </p>

<p>lncRNAs of unknown function </p>

<p>lncRNAdb includes RNAs that are well described in the 
literature but whose functions have yet to be identified. 
These regions are transcribed into lncRNAs that have 
been characterized to some extent at the structural and/ 
or expression level, including dozens of lncRNAs that 
show tissue specificity and dynamic expression during de-
velopment (64), as well as cellular localization, suggestive 
of undiscovered functionality. Likewise, the database also 
includes transcripts such as PHO5 antisense lncRNA in 
yeast (65) where it is not yet established whether the func-
tional role is conveyed by the lncRNA or its transcription. </p>

<p>FUTURE DIRECTIONS </p>

<p>The data in lncRNAdb will be extended through manual 
curation by the authors and submissions to the site by 
other researchers on an ongoing basis. The lowering cost 
and improved depths of RNA-sequencing methodologies 
is already enabling transcriptomics studies for alternative 
model-and non-model species, and it is expected that the 
identification and characterization of lncRNAs will 
follow, which may substantially increase the representa-
tion of non-mammalian species in the database. New func-
tionality will be included with integration of the publicly </p>



<p>available successor to NRED (NRED2) early in 2011, 
giving access to not only additional microarray expression 
data but also transcriptomic RNA-seq data for context-
ually related long noncoding and coding genes, tools for 
visualization of the lncRNA and cross-referencing of ex-
perimental expression profiles. Finally, the absence of a 
centralized database of lncRNAs is reflected by the ad 
hoc naming of newly identified members, which are 
often not self-consistent and potentially confusing. With 
the number of functional lncRNAs likely to be very large, 
it will be important to establish a standardized nomencla-
ture to minimize confusion and allow this emerging field 
to be as accessible as possible to all biologists. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Australian Research Council/University of Queensland 
co-sponsored Federation Fellowship (FF0561986; to 
J.S.M.); National Health and Medical Research Council 
of Australia Career Development Award (CDA631542; to 
M.E.D.); Queensland Government Department of 
Employment, Economic Development and Innovation 
Smart Futures Fellowship (to M.E.D.); Australian 
Research Council Postgraduate Awards (to P.P.A., 
M.B.C. and D.G.A). Funding for open access charge: 
The University of Queensland. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>







<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, Database issue D151 </p>

</text></tei>