<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3890344" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT For correct functioning of the nervous system, the appropriate number and com-
plement of neuronal cell types must be produced during development. However, the mole-
cular mechanisms that regulate the production of individual classes of neurons are poorly un-
derstood. In this study, we investigate the function of the thrombospondin-1-like glycoprotein, 
Nel (neural epidermal growth factor [EGF]-like), in the generation of retinal ganglion cells 
(RGCs) in chicks. During eye development, Nel is strongly expressed in the presumptive retinal 
pigment epithelium and RGCs. Nel overexpression in the developing retina by in ovo elec-
troporation increases the number of RGCs, whereas the number of displaced amacrine cells 
decreases. Conversely, knockdown of Nel expression by transposon-mediated introduction of 
RNA interference constructs results in decrease in RGC number and increase in the number of 
displaced amacrine cells. Modifications of Nel expression levels do not appear to affect prolif-
eration of retinal progenitor cells, but they significantly alter the progression rate of RGC dif-
ferentiation from the central retina to the periphery. Furthermore, Nel protects RGCs from 
apoptosis during retinal development. These results indicate that Nel positively regulates 
RGC production by promoting their differentiation and survival during development. </p>

<p>The vertebrate CNS is composed of a diverse range of morphologi-
cally and functionally distinct types of cells, and the correct function-
ing of the nervous system is critically dependent on the production 
of a sufficient and balanced number of each cell type. This cellular 
diversity arises from multipotent progenitor cells by complex </p>

<p>developmental mechanisms, including cell proliferation, fate deter-
mination, differentiation, and survival. Identification of the molecules 
and mechanisms that generate the proper number of neuronal cell 
types is one of the major goals of developmental biology. 
The retina has served as an excellent model system for study-
ing the mechanisms of cell production in the vertebrate CNS. 
During development, progenitor cells in the presumptive neural 
retina give rise to six major classes of neurons and one glial cell 
class in an evolutionally conserved order, which follows a histoge-
netic sequence in the retina (Price et al., 1987; Holt et al., 1988; 
Wetts and Fraser, 1988). The first cells that emerge from the retinal 
progenitor cells are retinal ganglion cells (RGCs), which are the 
sole output neurons in the retina and locate in the innermost layer 
(the ganglion cell layer [GCL]) of the mature retina (Prada et al., 
1991). Whereas cell-intrinsic mechanisms play crucial roles in reti-
nal cell diversification (Cayouette et al., 2006), several extrinsic 
signals derived from various sources in the eye influence RGC de-
velopment (Isenmann et al., 2003; Agathocleous and Harris, 2009), 
including fibroblast growth factors (FGFs; McCabe et al., 1999, </p>

<p>Monitoring Editor 
Marianne Bronner 
California Institute of 
Technology </p>

<p>Received: Aug 8, 2013 
Revised: Nov 8, 2013 
Accepted: Nov 8, 2013 </p>

<p>This article was published online ahead of print in MBoC in Press (http://www 
.molbiolcell.org/cgi/doi/10.1091/mbc.E13-08-0453) on November 20, 2013. 
Address correspondence to: Masaru Nakamoto (m.nakamoto@abdn.ac.uk). </p>

<p>© 2014 Nakamoto et al. This article is distributed by The American Society for Cell 
Biology under license from the author(s). Two months after publication it is avail-
able to the public under an Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported 
Creative Commons License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0). 
"ASCB </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>," "The American Society for Cell Biology </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>," and "Molecular Biology of 
the Cell 
® " are registered trademarks of The American Society of Cell Biology. </p>

<p>Abbreviations used: BDNF, brain-derived neurotrophic factor; EGFP, enhanced 
green fluorescent protein; EmGFP, emerald green fluorescent protein; FGF, fibro-
blast growth factor; GCL, ganglion cell layer; HH, Hamburger Hamilton stage; 
INL, inner nuclear layer; miRNA, microRNA; PEDF, pigment epithelium-derived 
factor; PH3, phosphohistone H3; RGC, retinal ganglion cell; RNAi, RNA interfer-
ence; RPE, retinal pigment epithelium; Shh, sonic hedgehog; VEGF, vascular en-
dothelial growth factor. </p>

<p>Volume 25 January 15, 2014 </p>

<p>Retinal ganglion cell development | 235 </p>

<p>During development, Nel is expressed in 
many different regions of the developing 
nervous system, including the retina, cere-
bral cortex, hippocampus, amygdala, and 
spinal cord (Matsuhashi et al., 1995; Oyasu 
et al., 2000; Nelson et al., 2002, 2004). Previ-
ous studies showed that Nel stimulates dif-
ferentiation of neuronal progenitor cells in 
the spinal cord and mitogenesis in dorsal 
root ganglia in chicks (Nelson et al., 2004). In 
addition, we previously demonstrated that 
Nel inhibits outgrowth of RGC axons and in-
duces growth cone collapse and axon re-
traction, and suggested that Nel acts as an 
inhibitory axon guidance molecule in estab-
lishment of the layer specificity in the visual 
projection (Jiang et al., 2009; Nakamura 
et al., 2012). It was also shown that Nel pro-
motes survival of cortical and hippocampal 
neurons in vitro (Aihara et al., 2003) and of 
RGCs after optic nerve injury in vivo (Mune-
masa et al., 2012). In adults, targeted disrup-
tion of the Nel gene results in significant 
enhancement of long-term potentiation in 
the dentate gyrus (Matsuyama et al., 2004). 
Moreover, Nel-deficient mice show impair-
ment of spatial learning, further suggesting 
its functions in regulation of synaptic plastic-
ity in the hippocampus (Matsuyama et al., 
2005). These results indicate that Nel plays 
crucial and diverse functions in the develop-
ing and adult nervous system. The cell sur-
face receptor(s) for Nel remains to be 
identified. 
In the developing retina, Nel is strongly 
expressed in RGCs (Nelson et al., 2002). 
However, its functions in retinal develop-
ment remain elusive. In this study, we inves-
tigate the functions of Nel in development 
of RGCs in the chick retina. Our results indi-
cate that Nel positively regulates RGC pro-
duction by both stimulating RGC differentiation and inhibiting pro-
grammed cell death. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Nel is expressed in retinal pigment epithelium and RGCs 
in the developing chick eye </p>

<p>To explore potential functions of Nel in retinal development, we 
first examined its spatial and temporal expression patterns in the 
developing chick eye by RNA in situ hybridization. In chicks, in-
vagination of the primary optic vesicle starts at Hamburger Hamil-
ton stage (HH) 14 (embryonic day [E] 2.5), and the double-layered 
optic cup is formed at HH15 (E2.5). At those stages, Nel RNA ex-
pression was detected in the outer layer of the optic cup, the pre-
sumptive retinal pigment epithelium (RPE; Figure 1A). At HH20 
(E3.5), Nel expression in the RPE increased, and, in addition, sig-
nificant expression of Nel RNA was detected in cells that occupy 
the inner surface of the central retina (Figure 1B), where newly dif-
ferentiated RGCs reside. Nel RNA expression in RGCs increased 
between E4 and E6 (Figure 1C). Expression of Nel persisted and 
continued to be restricted to the RPE and RGCs at least until E18 
(Figure 1, C′, D, and D′). The observed strong expression of Nel in </p>

<p>2006; Martinez-Morales et al., 2005), Sonic hedgehog (Shh; Zhang 
and Yang, 2001a; Masai et al., 2005), vascular endothelial growth 
factor (VEGF; Hashimoto et al., 2006), and Delta-Notch signaling 
(Austin et al., 1995). Considering the complexity of cellular and 
molecular interactions that mediate retinal development, however, 
it seems likely that additional extracellular signals are involved in 
regulation of RGC development. 
Nel (neural epidermal growth factor [EGF]-like) is an extracellular 
glycoprotein that was initially identified in chickens (Matsuhashi 
et al., 1995, 1996). In mammals, two related genes were subse-
quently identified and termed Nel-like 1 (Nell1) and 2 (Watanabe 
et al., 1996; Kuroda et al., 1999). Based on sequence similarities, 
Nell2 appeared to be the mammalian orthologue of chicken Nel. In 
this article, we refer to both Nel and Nell2 as Nel. The Nel/Nell pro-
teins have significant structural similarities with thrombospondin-1, 
which plays important roles in a wide range of physiological and 
pathological conditions, such as tumor growth and metastasis, an-
giogenesis, wound healing, inflammation, and synaptogenesis 
(Adams and Lawler, 2011). The Nel protein contains an N-terminal 
thrombospondin-1 domain, five chordin-like/von Willebrand factor 
C domains, and six EGF-like domains (Matsuhashi et al., 1995, 1996). </p>

<p>FIGURE 1: RNA and protein expression of Nel in the developing chick retina. (A-D) Nel 
expression detected by RNA in situ hybridization. Retinal sections prepared from different 
stages of chick embryos were hybridized with an RNA probe for Nel (violet). (A) HH14-15 (E2.5), 
(B) HH20 (E3.5), (C, C′) E6, and (D, D′) E18. RNA expression of Nel is initially restricted to the 
presumptive RPE (pe; A) but is also detected in RGCs (gc) at later stages (B-D). Nel RNA 
expression in the RPE and RGCs persists until at least E18 (D). In C and D, higher-magnification 
views of the RPE (areas indicated by small rectangles) are shown in insets (C′ and D′, 
respectively). In B and C, the sections are counterstained with methyl green (light blue). 
(E-G) Nel protein distribution detected by immunohistochemistry. Sections of HH17 (E3), E6 (F), 
or E18 (G) retina were treated with anti-Nel antibody (red). The Nel protein is mostly localized in 
the RPE and RGC layer. le, lens; nr, neural retina. Scale bars, 50 μm. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>Nel overexpression increases RGC 
number in vivo </p>

<p>The expression patterns of Nel in early 
retinal development raised the possibility 
that Nel may be involved in retinal neuro-
genesis, particularly in development of 
RGCs. To test this possibility directly in 
vivo, we constructed a replication-compe-
tent retroviral vector that drives bicistronic 
expression of Nel and an enhanced green 
fluorescent protein (EGFP) marker (RCAS-
Nel-IRES-EGFP). As a negative control, we 
used the RCAS-IRES-EGFP vector, which 
expresses only EGFP. The expression vec-
tors were transfected into the optic vesicle 
at HH9-11 (E1.5) by in ovo electropora-
tion, and expression of the transgenes was 
assessed at later stages by fluorescence 
of EGFP and immunohistochemistry using 
anti-Nel antibody (Jiang et al., 2009; 
Figure 2, A-F). 
To examine effects of Nel overexpres-
sion on RGC development, we incubated 
embryos transfected with the RCAS-Nel-
IRES-EGFP vector until E8, when produc-
tion of RGCs is mostly complete (Prada 
et al., 1991). Retinal sections were then 
prepared and stained for Brn3a, a specific 
marker for RGCs in the retina (Xiang et al., 
1995). Retinal neurogenesis occurs in a 
central-to-peripheral gradient (Snow and 
Robson, 1995; McCabe et al., 1999) and 
also shows slight temporal-to-nasal and 
dorsal-to-ventral gradients (Prada et al., 
1991). We therefore compared the num-
bers of Brn3a-positive cells between 
equivalent areas (e.g., central-temporal 
area) of transfected and untransfected 
(contralateral) retinas. We found that the 
number of Brn3a-positive cells increased 
by approximately 40% in regions trans-
fected with RCAS-Nel-IRES-EGFP (Figure 
2, G-L). Transfection of the control vector 
that expresses only EGFP did not affect 
the production of Brn3a-positive cells in 
the retina (Figure 2L). 
During vertebrate retinal development, significant numbers 
of amacrine cells, which are mainly located in the superficial part 
of the inner nuclear layer (INL), migrate to the GCL. In chicks, 
those "displaced" amacrine cells are produced between E5.5 
and E6.5 and comprise 20-35% of the total number of cells in 
the GCL (Galvez et al., 1977; Ehrlich and Morgan, 1980; Layer 
and Vollmer, 1982). Therefore next we examined whether Nel 
overexpression affects the number of displaced amacrine cells 
by using the amacrine cell marker syntaxin. We found that in the 
retinal regions where Nel is overexpressed, the number of dis-
placed amacrine cells in the GCL significantly decreases. The to-
tal cell numbers in the GCL showed a slight increase after Nel 
overexpression, although this difference was not statistically sig-
nificant (Figure 2L). These results indicate that Nel overexpres-
sion promotes the genesis of RGCs and decreases the number of 
displaced amacrine cells in the GCL. </p>

<p>RGCs is consistent with previous reports (Nelson et al., 2002; 
Wang et al., 2007). 
Because Nel is a secreted protein, it could in principle diffuse 
distances to be distributed in neighboring layers and tissues. We 
therefore examined the Nel protein distribution in the developing 
retina by immunohistochemistry using anti-Nel antibody (Jiang 
et al., 2009). The distribution of the Nel protein showed a very simi-
lar pattern to that of Nel RNA expression (Figure 1, E-G), indicating 
that most of the secreted Nel protein remains in the layers of its ori-
gin. This result is consistent with our previous observation that Nel 
RNA and protein show similar layer-specific distributions in the de-
veloping chick optic tectum (Jiang et al., 2009). This limited diffu-
sion of the Nel protein may be due to its heparin-binding activity 
(Kuroda et al., 1999; Nakamura et al., 2012), and the Nel protein 
may be trapped by heparin sulfate proteoglycans in situ soon after 
secretion from Nel-expressing cells. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2: Nel overexpression results in increase in RGC number. (A-F) Overexpression of Nel 
by using RCAS-Nel-IRES-EGFP. The retrovirus construct was electroporated into the optic vesicle 
of HH9-11 (E1.5) chick embryos, and retinal sections were prepared at E5. An area of Nel 
overexpression (A-C) and a corresponding area transfected with the control RCAS-IRES-EGFP 
(D-F) are shown. Nel expression was detected by anti-Nel antibody (red), and transfection 
domains are marked by the EGFP reporter (green). (C, F) Merged images of the left two images. 
(A′, D') Higher-magnification views of the RPE (areas indicated by small rectangles in A and D, 
respectively). In Nel/EGFP transfection domains, ectopic expression of Nel in progenitor cells 
(pc) of the neural retina is detected. In addition, staining for the Nel protein in RGCs (gc) and 
RPE (pe) is stronger compared to that in control areas. (G-L) Effects of Nel overexpression on 
RGC production. Retinal sections were prepared at E8 from embryos transfected with RCAS-
Nel-IRES-EGFP, and the production of RGCs was evaluated by immunohistochemistry for Brn3a 
(red). The transgene was introduced into half of the retina (overexpression [OE] side), which is 
marked by the EGFP reporter (green). (I) Merged image of G and H. (J, K) Higher-magnification 
views of Nel-overexpressing and corresponding untransfected areas in G (indicated by small 
rectangles), respectively. The number of Brn3a-positive cells significantly increased in Nel 
ectopic domains. on, optic nerve head. Scale bars, 50 μm. (L) Quantification of cell numbers in 
the GCL. The numbers of Brn3a-positive RGCs, syntaxin-positive displaced amacrine cells, and 
total cells in the GCL (4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole) in areas transfected with Nel and EGFP 
(Nel/EGFP) or EGFP only (EGFP) were compared with those in equivalent areas of the 
contralateral (untransfected) eye (Control) and indicated as mean ± SEM. *p &lt; 0.001, 
**p &lt; 0.0005. n = 6 embryos. ANOVA test. </p>

<p>Volume 25 January 15, 2014 </p>

<p>Retinal ganglion cell development | 237 </p>

<p>Tol2 transposable element (Koga et al., 
1996). We made a Tol2 transposon construct 
(pT2K-CAGGS-Nel miRNA482/2461-emer-
ald GFP [EmGFP]) that expresses Nel-spe-
cific miRNA and an EmGFP marker under 
the CAGGS promoter. As a negative con-
trol, we used a transposon vector carrying 
nonspecific miRNA sequences with the 
EmGFP marker gene (pT2K-CAGGS-Control 
miRNA-EmGFP). When introduced into cells 
with a transposase activity, the expression 
cassette would be excised from the plasmid 
and integrated into the host genome, allow-
ing stable expression of the miRNA and the 
EmGFP marker (Figure 3A). We electropo-
rated the transposon vector of Nel miRNA 
with the transposase expression vector 
pCAGGS-T2TP into the optic vesicle at 
HH9-11 (E1.5). Electroporation efficiency 
was monitored by expression of EmGFP, 
and effects of RNA interference (RNAi) on 
Nel expression was evaluated by immuno-
histochemistry using anti-Nel antibody. At 
E4.5, endogenous expression of Nel was 
found to be significantly reduced in EmGFP-
expressing cells in the RPE (Figure 3, B-D). 
At E8, reduction of Nel expression was also 
obvious in RGCs (Figure 3, E-I). 
Then we examined whether RNAi 
knockdown of Nel affects the numbers of 
RGCs and displaced amacrine cells. 
Whereas transfection of the control vector 
did not cause any changes in the RGC or 
displaced amacrine cell numbers, intro-
duction of the Nel miRNA construct with 
the transposase expression vector resulted 
in an approximately 40% reduction in the 
number of Brn3a-positive cells and to a 
lesser extent, an increase in the number of 
displaced amacrine cells (Figure 4). Taken 
together, these results indicate that Nel 
regulates the number of RGCs positively 
and that of displaced amacrine cells nega-
tively and is essential for the generation of 
the proper numbers of retinal neurons 
during development. </p>

<p>Effects of Nel on other types 
of retinal cells </p>

<p>Next we tested whether Nel overexpres-
sion or knockdown affects the production 
of other types of retinal cells. To this end, we examined the num-
bers of different types of retinal cells at E18 by using AP2α as 
a bipolar cell marker, Pax6 as a horizontal cell marker, rhodopsin 
as a marker for rods, visinin as a marker for cones, and vimentin 
as a Müller glia marker. As shown in Figure 5, neither over-
expression nor RNAi knockdown caused significant changes in 
the numbers of those retinal cells. In addition, the amacrine 
cell numbers in the INL were not significantly altered by the 
modulations of Nel expression levels. These results indicate that 
the effects of Nel expression are confined to the GCL of the 
retina. </p>

<p>Decrease of RGC number by RNA interference knockdown 
of Nel </p>

<p>Next we examined whether Nel is essential for the production of the 
proper number of RGCs in vivo. To test this, we designed artificial 
microRNAs (miRNAs) to target Nel expression and introduced them 
into the developing eye by in ovo electroporation. Because RGC 
production continues over at least 5-6 d, it was necessary that the 
production of the artificial miRNA be maintained throughout the 
period of RGC generation without significant reduction in expres-
sion. To achieve stable expression of transgenes, we used a transpo-
son-mediated gene transfer system (Sato et al., 2007) that uses the </p>

<p>FIGURE 3: Knockdown of Nel expression by transposon-mediated transfer of artificial miRNA. 
(A) A scheme showing transposition of a Tol2-flanked expression cassette for artificial Nel 
miRNA and EmGFP by transposase. When a Tol2 transposon construct (pT2K-CAGGS-Nel 
miRNA482/2461-EmGFP) is introduced into cells with a transposase expression construct 
(pCAGGS-T2TP), the Tol2-flanked cassette is excised from the vector and integrated into the 
host genome by the transposase activity (modified from Sato et al., 2007). (B-I) RNAi 
knockdown of Nel expression in the developing eye. A transposon construct containing an 
expression cassette of Nel miRNA and EmGFP was cotransfected with a transposase expression 
vector into the optic vesicle by in ovo electroporation at HH9-11 (E1.5). Retinal sections were 
prepared at E4.5 (B-D) or E8 (E-I), and expression of Nel was examined by 
immunohistochemistry using anti-Nel antibody (red). Half of the retina was transfected with the 
transposon constructs and marked by EmGFP (knockdown [KD] side, green). The boundary 
between transfected and untransfected (Control) sides is indicated by a dotted line in C and F. 
(D, G) Merged images of the left two images. (B-D) At E4.5, Nel expression is significantly 
reduced in the RPE (pe) cells that express EmGFP. Note the complementary pattern of Nel 
immunostaining and EmGFP expression. (E-I) At E8, Nel expression in the RPE and RGCs (gc) is 
decreased on the knockdown side (left side of the section). (H, I) Higher-magnification views of 
knockdown and corresponding untransfected areas in E (indicated by small rectangles), 
respectively. Scale bars, 50 μm. nr, neural retina; of, optic fissure. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>antibody. Neither overexpression nor RNAi 
knockdown of Nel caused any significant 
change in the number of PH3-positive cells 
(Figure 6, E-J). These results suggest that 
Nel does not serve as a mitogen during 
early retinal development. </p>

<p>Nel accelerates the progression 
of RGC differentiation wave </p>

<p>Next we examined the effects of Nel on 
RGC differentiation. During development, 
RGC differentiation occurs in a central-to-
peripheral gradient, such that RGCs are ini-
tially produced in the central retina and then 
the wave of differentiation proceeds from 
the central to peripheral retina, much like an 
expanding circle (Snow and Robson, 1995; 
McCabe et al., 1999). In addition, it was re-
ported that neurogenesis in the chick retina 
shows slight temporal-to-nasal and dorsal-
to-ventral gradients (Prada et al., 1991). To 
test whether Nel affects the progression of 
the RGC differentiation wave, we overex-
pressed Nel in half (nasal or temporal) of the 
retina at HH9-11 (E1.5), and examined the 
progression of RGC differentiation by immu-
nohistochemistry for the RGC marker Islet-1 (Austin et al., 1995) at 
E4.5, when RGCs are still actively produced. Equal numbers of na-
sally and temporally transfected retinas were examined. We found 
that the overexpressing side of the retina contained significantly 
larger numbers of Islet-1-positive cells than the control side (Figure 7, 
A, B, and E). Furthermore, compared to the control side, the periph-
eral edge or front of RGC differentiation reached farther from the 
central toward peripheral retina (Figure 7, A, B, and F), indicating 
that Nel overexpression accelerates the movement of the RGC dif-
ferentiation wave. Conversely, when expression of Nel was knocked 
down by RNAi in half of the retina, the knockdown side of the retina 
not only contained fewer Islet-1-positive cells, but also showed 
slower progression of the RGC differentiation wave (Figure 7, C-F). 
These results indicate that Nel enhances the rate of RGC differentia-
tion and its progression from the central to peripheral retina. </p>

<p>Nel protects retinal cells from 
developmental cell death </p>

<p>In retinal development, the period of RGC 
production partly overlaps with the earlier 
peak phase of developmental cell death 
(Frade et al., 1997). Therefore next we ex-
amined whether manipulations of Nel ex-
pression levels affect programmed cell 
death during retinal development. Consis-
tent with previous reports (Zhang and Yang, 
2001a,b), only a few apoptotic cells were 
detected by terminal deoxynucleotidyl 
transferase dUTP nick end labeling (TUNEL) 
assay in central regions of the normal E6 
retina. Overexpression of Nel resulted in a 
decrease in the number of TUNEL-positive 
cells in transfected areas (Figure 8, A, B, and 
E). Conversely, when Nel expression was 
knocked down by RNAi, a marked increase 
in the number of TUNEL-positive cells was </p>

<p>Nel does not significantly affect proliferation of retinal 
progenitor cells </p>

<p>The potential mechanisms by which Nel positively regulates RGC 
production include stimulation of retinal progenitor proliferation, 
promotion of RGC differentiation, and inhibition of apoptosis. First, 
we tested whether Nel can enhance proliferation of progenitor cells 
in the developing retina. We electroporated RCAS-Nel-IRES-EGFP 
into the optic vesicle at HH9-11 (E1.5) and counted the number of 
bromodeoxyuridine (BrdU)-positive cells after 3 h of in vivo labeling 
at E6. No significant difference in the number of BrdU-positive cells 
was observed between Nel-overexpressing and control areas (Figure 
6, A, B, and I). In addition, RNAi knockdown of Nel expression did 
not affect the number of BrdU-positive cells (Figure 6, C, D, and J). 
In a separate set of experiments, retinal sections were examined 
by immunohistochemistry using anti-phosphohistone H3 (PH3) </p>

<p>FIGURE 4: Reduction of the RGC number by RNAi knockdown of Nel expression. A transposon 
construct of artificial Nel miRNA and EmGFP (pT2K-CAGGS-Nel miRNA482/2461-EmGFP) was 
cotransfected with a transposase expression vector (pCAGGS-T2TP) into the optic vesicle by in 
ovo electroporation at HH9-11 (E1.5). Retinal sections were prepared at E8 and stained for 
Brn3a (red). (A-C) Representative section through the optic nerve head (on). The transgenes 
were introduced into half (knockdown [KD] side, green) of the retina. Compared to the control 
side, the number of Brn3a-positive cells is significantly reduced on the knockdown side. 
(D, E) Higher-magnification views of RNAi knockdown (D) and corresponding untransfected 
(E) areas in A (indicated by small rectangles). Scale bars, 50 μm. (F) Quantification of cell 
numbers in the GCL. The numbers of Brn3a-positive RGCs, syntaxin-positive displaced amacrine 
cells, and total cells in the GCL (4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole) in areas transfected with Nel 
miRNA or control miRNA were compared with those in equivalent areas in the contralateral 
(untransfected) eye (Control) and plotted as mean ± SEM. *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.0005. n = 6 
embryos. ANOVA test. </p>

<p>FIGURE 5: Effects of Nel on production of different retinal cell types. Expression constructs for 
Nel cDNA (A) or artificial miRNA (B) were transfected into the optic vesicle by in ovo 
electroporation at HH9-11 (E1.5). The numbers of different types of retinal cells in transfected 
areas were compared with those in corresponding areas transfected with control vectors (EGFP 
in A, control RNAi in B) at E18. No significant differences were detected in the numbers of 
AP2α-positive bipolar cells, Pax6-positive horizontal cells, rhodopsin-positive rods, visinin-
positive cones, or vimentin-positive Müller glia. In addition, the amacrine cell numbers in the INL 
were not significantly altered. n = 6 embryos. ANOVA test. </p>

<p>Volume 25 January 15, 2014 </p>

<p>Retinal ganglion cell development | 239 </p>

<p>Xenopus embryos, overexpression of FGF2 
in retinal progenitor cells results in a 35% 
increase of RGCs without affecting retinal 
cell proliferation (Patel and McFarlane, 
2000). Whereas both Nel and FGF1 acceler-
ate the progression of RGC differentiation 
wave, the central-to-peripheral gradient of 
RGC differentiation is preserved in the pres-
ence of excess Nel or FGF1. Given that the 
cells at the wave front are more mature than 
those in the peripheral retina, these results 
may suggest that Nel and FGF1 act to stim-
ulate further differentiation of nascent RGCs 
in final stages of RGC development (Jiang 
et al., 2013). 
Programmed cell death plays crucial 
roles in regulation of cell numbers during 
neural development, and a significant por-
tion of newly generated RGCs undergo pro-
grammed cell death during development. 
The present study shows that whereas Nel 
overexpression decreases number of apop-
totic cells in the developing retina, RNAi 
knockdown of Nel dramatically increases it. 
These results suggest that in addition to ac-
celeration of RGC differentiation, suppres-
sion of developmental cell death contrib-
utes to promotion of RGC production by 
Nel. Importance of developmental cell 
death in regulation of RGC numbers has 
also been shown by studies on brain-derived neurotrophic factor 
(BDNF). Application of BDNF to chick embryos in ovo significantly 
inhibits the earlier peak phase of developmental cell death in the 
retina and results in a 60-90% increase in RGC number (Frade et al., 
1997). Nel was shown to promote survival of cortical and hippocam-
pal neurons in primary culture (Aihara et al., 2003). More recently, it 
was reported that overexpression of Nel in the retina promotes RGC 
survival in vivo after optic nerve transection (Munemasa et al., 2012). 
These results indicate that Nel can act as a survival factor for multi-
ple types of neurons. 
We found that the number of displaced amacrine cells in the 
GCL is negatively affected by Nel expression. Given that amacrine 
cells are among the early-born neurons in the retina and are gener-
ated at approximately the same time as RGCs (Cepko et al., 1996), 
Nel may act to cause a cell fate shift from amacrine cells to RGCs, 
although the change in amacrine cell number is restricted in the 
GCL, and no significant effects were observed on amacrine cell 
number in the INL by Nel overexpression or RNAi knockdown. Alter-
natively, the displacement of amacrine cells in the GCL may be 
negatively controlled by the number of RGCs in the layer, and thus 
the observed effects on the number of displaced amacrine cells may 
represent secondary effects due to the change of RGC number 
caused by modulation of Nel expression. </p>

<p>Nel in molecular interaction network during retinal 
development </p>

<p>During retinal development, Nel is produced by two different 
sources in the eye (Figure 9). First, at early stages of retinal develop-
ment before the first RGCs emerge in the GCL, the presumptive 
RPE acts as the sole source of Nel in the developing eye. Through-
out eye development, the neural retina and the RPE are kept in 
close apposition, and development of the two tissues occurs in </p>

<p>observed (Figure 8, C-E). Transfection of control vectors did not 
change the number of TUNEL-positive cells (Supplemental Figure 
S1). These results indicate that Nel acts to protect RGCs from pro-
grammed cell death during retinal development. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Functions of Nel in RGC development </p>

<p>Several lines of evidence obtained in this study indicate that Nel 
positively regulates the production of RGCs during development. 
First, Nel is strongly expressed in RGCs (Nelson et al., 2002; Wang 
et al., 2007) and the RPE in the developing eye. Second, gain-of-
function studies show that retroviral overexpression of Nel in the 
developing retina increases RGC number. Third, loss-of-function ex-
periments using RNAi knockdown demonstrate that reduction of 
Nel expression levels results in decreased number of RGCs. We also 
showed that alterations of Nel expression levels do not exert obvi-
ous effects on cell proliferation but significantly affect the rate of 
RGC differentiation and developmental cell death, suggesting that 
Nel enhances the production of RGCs by promoting their differen-
tiation and survival. 
During retinal development, RGC differentiation initially occurs 
in the central retina, and the wave of differentiation proceeds to-
ward the periphery of retina. Our results show that overexpression 
of Nel accelerates the progression of the RGC differentiation wave, 
whereas RNAi knockdown of Nel expression retards the movement 
of the wave front. This effect of Nel appears similar to that previously 
reported for FGF signaling. During the initial stage of chick retino-
genesis, FGF1 is expressed at high levels in the peripheral part of 
the developing retina (de Iongh and McAvoy, 1992). In a retinal 
explant culture system, FGF1 promotes the progression of RGC 
differentiation wave, and inhibition of the FGF receptor signaling 
inhibits the movement of the wave front (McCabe et al., 1999). In </p>

<p>FIGURE 6: Effects of Nel on proliferation of retinal progenitor cells. Expression constructs for 
Nel cDNA (A, E) or artificial miRNA (C, G) were transfected into the optic vesicle by in ovo 
electroporation at HH9-11 (E1.5), and effects on cell proliferation were examined by comparing 
with corresponding areas transfected with control vectors (EGFP in B, F, I; control RNAi in D, H, 
J). Areas in the central retina are shown. (A-D) Embryos were labeled with BrdU in ovo for 3 h at 
E6, and retinal sections were prepared and stained with anti-BrdU antibody. (E-H) Retinal 
sections of E4.5 chicks were stained for PH3. Scale bars, 50 μm. nr, neural retina; pe, pigment 
epithelium. (I, J) Quantifications of BrdU-and PH3-positive cells. The numbers of stained cells 
are shown as percentage control in mean ± SEM. No significant differences were detected 
between Nel overexpression, RNAi knockdown, and their controls. n = 6 embryos. ANOVA test. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>from the RPE, including VEGF, FGF, and pig-
ment epithelium-derived factor (PEDF; 
Strauss, 2005). In Xenopus, PEDF supports 
normal development of photoreceptor neu-
rons and Müller cells after removal of the 
RPE, demonstrating that RPE-derived PEDF 
plays important roles in the final stages of 
retinal development (Jablonski et al., 2000, 
2001). Although the Nel protein appears to 
localize mostly in the presumptive RPE at 
this stage, our results raise the possibility 
that RPE-derived Nel functions as a part of 
the molecular network between the RPE 
and neural retina and acts to increase, di-
rectly or indirectly, RGC production in early 
stages of retinal neurogenesis. 
Second, strong Nel expression was de-
tected in RGCs that had migrated into the 
GCL. Previous studies showed that differen-
tiated RGCs secrete several factors that af-
fect RGC production. For example, Shh is 
produced by newly differentiated RGCs and 
required for the propagation of the neuro-
genic wave toward the peripheral retina 
(Masai et al., 2005). Shh also suppresses the 
generation of additional RGCs behind the 
neurogenic wave front (Zhang and Yang, 
2001a). In addition, VEGF produced by dif-
ferentiated RGCs increases proliferation of 
retinal progenitors and decreases produc-
tion of RGCs (Hashimoto et al., 2006). The 
present study suggests that Nel is a novel 
RGC-derived factor that positively regulates 
RGC production. 
The relative contributions and respective 
functions of RPE-and RGC-derived Nel in 
RGC production remain elusive. In addition, 
it is not clear whether RPE-derived Nel 
affects expression of RGC-derived Nel, or 
expressions of RPE-and RGC-derived Nel 
are independently regulated. We plan to 
address those issues in future studies by cre-
ating and analyzing conditional (RPE-and 
RGC-specific) knockout mice of Nel. </p>

<p>Gene silencing in chick embryos by 
transposon-mediated integration of 
artificial miRNA transgenes </p>

<p>Although chick embryos have long been 
used as a favorite model organism in the 
field of developmental biology, robust and 
efficient loss-of-function approaches had 
not been available for the chick until re-
cently. In the past decade, RNAi has been 
successfully used in chick embryos by electroporating small interfer-
ing RNAs (siRNAs; Hu et al., 2002) or expression vectors for short 
hairpin RNA (Katahira and Nakamura, 2003) in ovo. More recently, 
an RCAS retrovirus-based siRNA delivery system was shown to effi-
ciently knock down gene expression in chick embryos (Harpavat and 
Cepko, 2006). 
In loss-of-function analysis of this study, we introduced artificial 
miRNA transgenes into the developing chick retina by using a </p>

<p>concert (Strauss, 2005). Ablation of the RPE severely disrupts devel-
opment of the neural retina (Stiemke et al., 1994; Raymond and 
Jackson, 1995). Interestingly, compared to pigmented wild-type 
mice, more RGCs are produced during the initial period of retinal 
neurogenesis in albino mice, which lack pigmentation in the RPE. 
Furthermore, pharmacological inhibition of pigment production in-
creases the number of RGCs in eyecups isolated from pigmented 
mice (Rachel et al., 2002). A variety of growth factors are secreted </p>

<p>FIGURE 7: Enhancement of the progression of RGC differentiation wave by Nel. (A-D) Nel was 
either overexpressed (A, B) or knocked down (C, D) in half (left side) of the developing retina by 
in ovo electroporation at HH9-11 (E1.5). Retinal sections were prepared at E4.5, and RGCs were 
detected by immunohistochemistry using anti-Islet-1 antibody (red). The areas of transgene 
expression are marked by expression of a GFP reporter (transfection side, green). Compared to 
the control side, Nel overexpression increased the number of RGCs and accelerated the 
progression of RGC differentiation wave. Conversely, RNAi knockdown of Nel decreased the 
RGC number and slowed down the rate of their differentiation. The white lines indicate the 
midline of the retina, and the arrows show the peripheral edge of RGC differentiation wave. le, 
lens. (E) Quantification of RGC numbers. The number of Islet-1-positive cells is shown as 
percentage control in mean ± SEM. (F) Quantification of progression of the RGC differentiation 
wave. The angles subtended by the arcs of RGC cells were measured on the transfection (θt) 
and control sides (θc), as indicated. Effects on wave progression were quantified as θt/θc × 100 
and plotted as mean ± SEM. Equal numbers of nasally and temporally transfected retinas were 
examined. *p &lt; 0.005, **p &lt; 0.001. n = 6 embryos each for temporal and nasal transfection. 
Paired Student's t test. </p>

<p>Volume 25 January 15, 2014 </p>

<p>Retinal ganglion cell development | 241 </p>

<p>Diverse functions of Nel in visual 
system development </p>

<p>In the chick visual system, Nel is expressed 
not only in RGCs (projecting neurons), but 
also in the optic tectum (the main target of 
RGC axons in nonmammalian vertebrates). 
Nel expression in the chick tectum is de-
tected as early as E5. Expression levels of 
Nel significantly increase between E8 and 
E12, and the high expression is maintained 
at least until E18. First RGC axons reach the 
tectum by E6, and RGC axons project to the 
specific layers ("retinorecipient laminae") in 
the superficial part of the tectum between 
E12 and E18. During this period, Nel ex-
pression in the tectum is confined to deeper 
layers of the tectum, which RGC axons do 
not normally innervate ("nonretinorecipient 
laminae"). Because Nel inhibits outgrowth 
of RGC axons and induces growth cone col-
lapse and axon retraction in vitro, these re-
sults suggest that Nel may act as an inhibi-
tory axon guidance cue that prevents RGC 
axons from invading inappropriate layers in 
the deeper part of the tectum and thus con-
tribute to the establishment of the layer 
specificity in the visual projection (Jiang 
et al., 2009; Nakamura et al., 2012). In addi-
tion, in view of the functions of Nel in RGC 
production revealed in this study, it seems 
plausible that Nel could also have roles in 
differentiation and survival of tectal neurons 
in nonretinorecipient laminae. 
It is intriguing that Nel exerts both posi-
tive (promotion of differentiation and sur-
vival) and negative (inhibitory effects on ax-
ons) effects on RGCs. Several other axon 
guidance molecules were also reported to exert both positive and 
negative effects on neurons. Such examples include ephrins, Wnt 
(Flanagan, 2006), and netrins (Moore et al., 2007). Because the Nel 
protein consists of different domains, it seems likely that different 
domains interact with distinct receptors and exert different func-
tions, as is the case for thrombospondin-1 (Adams and Lawler, 2011). 
Interestingly, Nel exerts neuroprotective effects on cultured neurons 
at concentrations lower than those required for inhibitory effects on 
RGC axons (Aihara et al., 2003). This may suggest that Nel exerts 
inhibitory axon guidance functions and neuroprotective effects 
through distinct receptors that have different affinities for the ligand. 
Alternatively, the same receptor(s) may mediate both positive and 
negative signals in response to different concentrations of the li-
gand, as shown for Eph receptor-ephrin interactions (Hansen et al., 
2004; Matsuoka et al., 2005). Further studies, including identifica-
tion of its receptors, would be required to fully understand the 
molecular mechanisms of Nel functions. Nonetheless, it has become 
increasingly apparent that Nel is a multifunctional molecule that 
plays crucial roles in development of the vertebrate nervous system 
and its functions. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Chick embryos </p>

<p>Fertilized White Leghorn chicken eggs were purchased from Henry 
Stewart (Louth, United Kingdom) and incubated at 38°C until use. </p>

<p>transposon-mediated gene transfer system (Sato et al., 2007). This 
method offers several distinct advantages. First, it supports stable 
expression of the transgene and thus persistent production of 
miRNA. Electroporation of conventional expression vectors permits 
only transient expression of the transgene, usually lasting only for 
several days in embryonic cells, because of the inability of the elec-
troporated plasmid to be integrated into chromosomes. In contrast, 
the present method involves chromosomal integration of the ex-
pression cassette by activity of coelectroporated transposase and 
therefore can achieve stable expression of the transgenes. Second, 
the cells that express the transgene can be easily traced because 
each of the transfected cells is clearly marked by the EmGFP marker. 
Third, because expression of miRNA and EmGFP is driven by the 
same CAGGS promoter, the risk of promoter interference is avoided, 
which is one of the common problems with retroviral vectors con-
taining an additional promoter to attain dual gene expression (e.g., 
Yee et al., 1987)). Finally, the areas of transfection can be controlled 
by properly choosing the type and positions of electrodes. Because 
this method does not use replication-competent retroviral vectors, 
there is no transmission of the transgene to neighboring cells after 
the electroporation. Within the transfected retinas, areas that do not 
express the transgene serve as a good internal control. Therefore 
this system provides a stable and efficient loss-of-function option 
and can contribute to the analysis of gene functions during chick 
development. </p>

<p>FIGURE 8: Nel promotes survival of retinal cells during development. (A-D) Nel was either 
overexpressed (A, B) or knocked down (C, D) in half (left side) of the developing retina by in ovo 
electroporation at HH9-11 (E1.5). Retinal sections were prepared at E6, and apoptotic cells 
were detected by TUNEL assay (red). The areas of transgene expression are marked by 
expression of a GFP reporter (transfection side, green). A subset of TUNEL-positive cells is 
indicated by arrows. Compared to the control side, Nel overexpression decreased the number 
of TUNEL-positive cells, whereas RNAi knockdown of Nel drastically increased it. nr, neural 
retina; on, optic nerve. Scale bars, 100 μm. (E) Quantification of apoptotic cells. The number of 
TUNEL-positive cells on the transfected side was compared with that on the control side and 
plotted as mean ± SEM. *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.0005. n = 6 embryos. ANOVA test. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>potent target sequences were selected (corresponding to nucle-
otide numbers 482-502 and 2461-2481, respectively) and tan-
demly cloned into the pcDNA6.2-GW/EmGFP-miRNA vector 
(pcDNA6.2-GW-Nel miRNA482/2461-EmGFP) according to the 
manufacturer's instructions. To construct the pT2K-CAGGS-Nel 
miRNA482/2461-EmGFP vector, cDNA sequences encoding the 
two pre-miRNA and EmGFP of the pcDNA6.2-GW/Nel miRNA 
482/2461-EmGFP vector were amplified by PCR with an artificial 
EcoRI site on both ends (5′-GGGAATTCTCTGGCTAACTAGA-
GAAC-3′ and 5′-CCG AATTCCCTCTAGATCAACCACT-3′) and 
cloned into the pT2K-CAGGS vector. The control pT2K-CAGGS-
Control miRNA-EmGFP vector was constructed by cloning the cor-
responding region of the pcDNA6.2-GW/EmGFP-miRNA negative 
control plasmid (Invitrogen) into the pT2K-CAGGS vector using the 
same set of PCR primers and restriction enzyme sites as mentioned. 
The pT2K-CAGGS and pCAGGS-T2TP vectors were kindly pro-
vided by Yoshiko Takahashi (Kyoto University, Kyoto, Japan) and 
Koichi Kawakami (National Institute of Genetics, Mishima, Japan), 
respectively. </p>

<p>In ovo electroporation </p>

<p>In ovo electroporation was performed as described previously 
(Harada et al., 2008). Briefly, a small amount of plasmid DNA solu-
tion (5 μg/μl each) mixed with fast green (dye tracer) was injected 
into the lumen of the optic vesicle of HH9-11 (E1.5) chick embryos 
in windowed eggs. Parallel platinum-coated electrodes spaced at 
3 mm were placed perpendicular to the long axis of the embryo, 
one electrode being on the anterior (nasal) side and the other elec-
trode on the posterior (temporal) side of the optic vesicle. Five 
square pulses (25 V, 50 ms/s) were applied by a CUY21 electropora-
tor (Nepa Gene, Ichikawa, Japan). The levels of ectopic expression 
varied in different embryos. Only the embryos that showed signifi-
cant levels of expression were used for analysis. Equal numbers of 
nasally and temporally transfected retinas were analyzed. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry and TUNEL assay </p>

<p>For immunohistochemistry, embryonic retinas were fixed with 4% 
paraformaldehyde, cryoprotected with 30% sucrose in phosphate-
buffered saline (PBS), embedded in OCT compound, frozen, and 
sectioned at 12-30 μm. Immunohistochemistry for Nel protein was 
performed as described previously (Jiang et al., 2009), except that 
Alexa Fluor 594-conjugated anti-rabbit immunoglobulin G (IgG; 
1:1000; Invitrogen) was used as secondary antibody. For immuno-
staining of Brn3a, Islet-1, PH3, Pax6, and AP2α, sections were pro-
cessed for antigen retrieval in a citrate buffer solution (10 mM triso-
dium citrate, 0.05% Tween-20) at 95°C for 3 min, blocked in a 
blocking solution (10% donkey serum, 0.3% Triton X-100 in PBS) for 
1 h at room temperature, and treated with primary and secondary 
antibodies in an antibody dilution solution (0.3% Triton X-100, 1% 
bovine serum albumin in PBS). The following antibodies were used: 
anti-Brn3a (1:100, clone 5A3.2; Millipore, Billerica, MA), anti-Islet-1 
(1:50, clone 39.4D5; Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank 
[DSHB], University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA), anti-PH3 (1:100; Millipore), 
anti-syntaxin (1:2000; Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO), anti-Pax6 
(1:200; DSHB), anti-PKCα (1:2000; Sigma-Aldrich), anti-vimentin 
(1:2000; DSHB), anti-rhodopsin (1:200; Sigma-Aldrich), anti-visinin 
(1:100; DSHB); anti-AP2-α (1:200; DSHB), Alexa Fluor 594-conju-
gated anti-mouse IgG (1:1,000; Invitrogen), and Alexa Fluor 
488-conjugated anti-rabbit IgG (1:400; Invitrogen). The TUNEL as-
say was performed by using the In Situ Cell Death Detection Kit, 
TMR red (Roche Applied Science, Indianapolis, IN), according to 
the manufacturer's instructions. For quantification, the number of </p>

<p>In situ RNA hybridization </p>

<p>In situ RNA hybridization was performed using digoxigenin-labeled 
probes for Nel as previously described (Jiang et al., 2009), using 
12-to 30-μm frozen sections of the embryonic retina. </p>

<p>Plasmid constructs </p>

<p>For construction of the RCAS-IRES-EGFP plasmid, cDNA sequences 
containing IRES-EGFP (nucleotide numbers 666-1973) of the 
pIRES2-EGFP vector (Clontech, Mountain View, CA) were amplified 
by PCR. Both the 5′ and 3′ PCR primers contain an artificial ClaI site, 
and the 3′ ClaI site was protected by a 5′ guanine, thus preventing 
ClaI cleavage when methylated, as previously described (McLaugh-
lin et al., 2003). The PCR product was cloned into the ClaI site of the 
replication-competent avian retroviral vector RCAS (Fekete and 
Cepko, 1993). The RCAS-Nel-IRES-EGFP vector was constructed by 
inserting the protein-coding region of Nel cDNA (GenBank acces-
sion number NM_001030740.1, nucleotide numbers 118-2565) into 
the RCAS-IRES-EGFP vector upstream of the IRES at the functional 
ClaI site. 
For RNAi knockdown, we designed pairs of single-stranded 
DNA oligonucleotides (one encoding target pre-miRNA and 
the other corresponding its complement) for 10 potential target 
sequences by using <rs id="software-0" type="software">RNAi Designer</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Invitrogen</rs>, Carlsbad, CA; 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">https://rnaidesigner.invitrogen.com/rnaiexpress/)</rs>/). After annealing, 
the double-stranded oligonucleotides were individually cloned 
into the pcDNA6.2-GW/EmGFP-miRNA vector (Invitrogen). Knock-
down effects of each construct were evaluated by cotransfection 
with a Nel-AP expression vector into HEK293T cells, followed by 
measurement of AP activity in the culture media. The two most </p>

<p>FIGURE 9: Expression and potential modes of actions of Nel in 
retinal neurogenesis. (A) During retinal development, Nel is secreted 
from two different types of cells. Left, at early stages of retinal 
neurogenesis before RGCs are produced, Nel is expressed exclusively 
in the presumptive retinal pigment epithelium. Right, at later stages, 
newly differentiated RGCs also secrete Nel, whereas Nel expression 
in the RPE is maintained. (B) Nel accelerates the rate of differentiation 
of retinal progenitor cells into RGCs and inhibits apoptosis of retinal 
cells. Sources of Nel are indicated in red. nr, neural retina; pe, retinal 
pigment epithelium; rgc, retinal ganglion cells; rp, retinal progenitor 
cells. </p>

<p>Volume 25 January 15, 2014 </p>

<p>Retinal ganglion cell development | 243 </p>

<p>positive cells in transfected retinal regions was scored in a high-
power optic field and compared with that in equivalent regions of 
the contralateral (untransfected) retinas or corresponding control 
areas. At least three fields were examined for each retina, and at 
least six retinas were analyzed for each type of treatment. Equal 
numbers of nasally and temporally transfected retinas were 
analyzed. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Statistical significance of the data was determined using analysis of 
variance (ANOVA) or Student's t test. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank John Flanagan and Lynda Erskine for discussions and criti-
cal reading of the manuscript; Lynda Erskine, Neil Vargesson, Bing 
Lang, and Freyja Bruce for help and advice on immunostaining and 
the TUNEL assay; and Yvonne Turnbull for technical assistance in the 
purchase and maintenance of chicken eggs. The pCAGGS-T2TP 
and pT2K-CAGGS vectors were generous gifts from Koichi Kawakami 
and Yoshiko Takahashi, respectively. The anti-Pax6 antibody (devel-
oped by A. Kawakami), anti-Islet-1 (39.4D5; by T. M. Jessell and S. 
Brenner-Morton), anti-vimentin (H5; by J. R. Sanes), anti-visinin (7G4; 
by C. Cepko), and anti-AP-2 alpha (3B5; by T. Williams) were ob-
tained from the Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank developed 
under the auspices of the National Institute of Child Health and 
Human Development and maintained by the Department of Biol-
ogy, University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA. This work was supported by 
grants from the Royal Society and Biotechnology and Biological 
Sciences Research Council to M.N. </p>





<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>



</text></tei>