<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3469014" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Amputation causes a variety of physical and psy-
chosocial challenges including alterations in body 
image and lifestyle, changes in self-concept, 
impairments in physical functioning, using 
prosthesis, and feeling pain (1, 2, 3). 
It is well documented that stressors which are as-
sociated with amputation may challenge the indi-
vidual's ability to maintain emotional well-being 
and, in some instances, may promote maladaptive 
reactions leading to poor psychosocial adjustment 
(4,5). Furthermore, the well-being of amputee 
should be considered as the main goal of rehabil-
itation rather than biomechanical or physiological 
factor. We can consider quality of life as an um-
brella, covering all aspect of medical services that 
is presented to an amputee. The concept of quality 
of life extends beyond traditional symptoms to </p>

<p>include patients' subjective well-being, satisfaction, 
functioning, and impairments (6). 
The quality of life contains several determinant 
factors such as health, personal development, 
physical environment, natural resource, and secu-
rity (7). In health care services, quality of life is 
considered as an endpoint in clinical trials and in 
intervention studies (8). Additionally, quality of 
life is often viewed negatively as the person's abil-
ity to perform activities of daily living (8). It seems 
important to balance this view by focusing on 
people's own view of quality of life. Quality of life 
is an interaction between the external conditions 
of an individual's life and the internal perception 
of those conditions (9). It is considered as a main 
goal for medical care and may be an equally 
important goal as health and welfare (6). </p>

<p>Abstract 
Background: Assessment of quality of life can promote health services. The purpose of this study was evaluation of 
health related quality of life in lower limbs amputee veterans of Iran. 
Methods: In the present cross sectional study, we compared 38 lower limbs amputee veterans with 50 normal healthy 
subjects with SF36 questioner in face-to-face interview. 
Results: Amputees had significantly lower grade than normal subject did in role physical (P &lt; 0.01) and were better 
than normal subjects in vitality (P &lt; 0.001) and mental health (P &lt; 0.01). As a whole, amputees have higher in mental 
summary component of quality of life (P &lt; 0.05) and lower in physical component of quality of life (P &lt; 0.01). 
Conclusion: Diminishing the demand and improving social support of amputee veterans might be considered as high 
grade in mental summary component of their quality of life. </p>

<p>Keywords: Health, Quality of Life, Lower Limb Amputee, Veterans </p>

<p>*Corresponding Author: E-mail: Kh_Ahmady@yahoo.com </p>

<p>Available at http://ijph.tums.ac.ir </p>

<p>Karami et al.: Better Mental Component of Quality of Life … </p>

<p>54 
Available at http://ijph.tums.ac.ir </p>

<p>The term Health Related Quality of Life 
(HRQOL), refers the value assigned to duration 
of life as modified by the impairments, functional 
states, perceptions and social opportunities influ-
enced by disease, injury, treatment or policy (7). 
Recently, there has been a growing interest in the 
research literature to assess quality of life impair-
ments in many psychiatric disorders. The main 
issue in treatment and medical care of this kind of 
patients is shifting away from a focus on symptom 
severity to include the broader impact of psychia-
tric disorders on patients' lives and their percep-
tions of their quality of life (10). In other hand, 
quality of life concept is a controversial issue (10), 
so that some researchers assess quality of life in 
relation to functional impairment (11) and others 
consider it as subjective perception of their lives 
(12). 
In this study, it seems that the subjective expe-
rience of quality of life is more determinative than 
objective factors are (13). Measuring quality of life 
in terms of functional impairment provides little 
more than a health status rating (14). Quality of 
life is set apart from other indicators of mental 
health precisely, because it takes into account an 
individual's perception of their own well-being, 
rather than solely relying on an objective assess-
ment. Subjective measures of quality of life offer a 
rich alternative to traditional mental health assess-
ments by allowing individuals to express their own 
insights and values regarding their lives. Indeed, 
the multidimensional nature of the quality of life 
concept makes it appropriate to be considered in 
evaluations of comprehensive programs involving 
people with serious and persistent mental illness 
(15). In other hand, if mental health services wish 
to strive to be consumer-oriented and holistic in 
their deliverance of treatment and resources, qual-
ity of life assessment provides a means of so do-
ing. Accurate assessment of the needs and views 
of consumer simplicity requires consumer in-
volvement, and quality of life assessments can 
provide a complex and differentiated way of carry-
ing out that evaluation. Quality of life assessment 
can provide important information about individ-
ual priorities concerning domains of personal </p>

<p>functioning in addition to self-assessment of cur-
rent life circumstances (16). This information can 
be vital to allocate resources within service sys-
tems in a way that is based on patients' priorities. 
In the present study, we assessed quality of life of 
Iranian veterans with lower limbs amputations. 
The purpose of this study was determining the 
aspects of their life that should be promoted. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>This was a cross-sectional study for evaluating 
health related quality of life in lower limbs 
amputation veterans of Iran. In the present study, 
data collected from 38 lower limbs amputation 
veterans and 50 normal healthy controls that live 
in all provinces of Iran with face-to-face interview. 
The control group is matched in gender, 
education, and age with amputee group. All 
participants were male. Mean age for amputee 
group were 43.91 (± 6.21) and for normal healthy 
subjects were 43.66 (± 6.07). The duration of 
amputation was 24.55 (± 2.61) years. 
HRQOL was assessed by means of the Medical 
Outcomes Research 36-item Short-Form Health 
Survey (SF-36), which has been validated in the 
Iranian population (17). The SF-36 consists of 36 
questions integrating eight multi item scales: 
physical functioning (PF); role limitations caused 
by physical problems (RP); bodily pain (BP); gen-
eral health perceptions (GH); vitality, energy, or 
fatigue (VT); social functioning (SF); role limita-
tions caused by emotional problems (RE), and 
general mental health (MH). Based on these 
scales, component summary scores were calcu-
lated to provide a global measure of physical and 
mental functioning; the Physical Component 
Summary (PCS) and the Mental Component 
Summary (MCS) were derived from the eight 
multi-item scales. The scales and summary com-
ponents ranged from 0 to 100, where higher val-
ues denote better functioning and fewer limita-
tions. For each question basis on number of item 
in Lickert scale, each item pointed from 0 to 100. 
The SF-36 derived scores did not have a cutoff 
point to differentiate between good or poor </p>

<p>Iranian J Publ Health, Vol. 41, No.7, July 2012, pp.53-58 </p>

<p> 
Available at http://ijph.tums.ac.ir </p>

<p>HRQOL. This questionnaire had been translated 
to Persian and validated for Iranian population. 
The internal consistency (to test reliability) 
showed that all eight SF-36 scales met the mini-
mum reliability standard, the Cronbach's alpha 
coefficients ranging from 0.77 to 0.90 with the 
exception of the vitality scale (alpha = 0.65) (18). 
Inclusion criteria were amputation of lower limbs 
veterans based on observation. Veterans were ex-
cluded, as were severely mentally handicapped and 
subjects unable to understand Persian language. 
The soft ware of <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">18</rs> was used for performing 
the data analysis. Descriptive statistics were used 
to analyze data. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The socio demographic characteristics of partici-
pants are shown in Table 1. 
The means of SF-36 by groups are presented in 
table 2. Mean score of quality of life for dimen-
sion of quality of life in orderly RP, PF, BP, VT, 
MH, RE, SF, GH for amputee were 32.57, 45.86, 
40.74, 67.05, 68.24, 50, 59.12 and 50.32 and for 
normal healthy subjects were 58.23, 55.32, 58.72, 
43.55, 41.29, 41.29, 60.30 and 58.71. Only role 
physical and physical functioning were lower than 
mean Likert score in amputee group and vitality 
and mental health were lower than mean Likert 
score in matched healthy subjects. </p>

<p>Table 1: Some demographic characteristics of 
lower limbs amputation veterans of Iran </p>

<p>Amputee 
number 
Healthy 
number 
Age group 
20-29 years 
1 
2 
30-30 years 
2 
3 
40-49 years 
32 
40 
50-59 years 
2 
3 
60-69 years 
1 
2 
Marital Status 
Married 
34 
43 
Single 
0 
4 
Divorced 
1 
1 
Widowed 
0 
2 
Educational Level 
Illiterate 
0 
2 
Primary school 
0 
1 
Secondary school 
6 
7 
High school 
13 
47 
University 
15 
1 </p>

<p>Amputees were significantly lower grade than 
normal subject in role physical was (P &lt; 0.01) and 
were better than normal subjects in vitality (P &lt; 
0.001) and mental health (P &lt; 0.01). As a whole 
amputees were higher in mental summary compo-
nent of quality of life (P &lt; 0.05) and lower in 
physical component of quality of life (P &lt; 0.01). </p>

<p>Table 2: Scores of dimensions of quality of life in study groups </p>

<p>Score 
Amputee 
Mean(SD) (n=38) 
Healthy Control 
Mean(SD) (n=50) 
T 
Ratio </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>Value 
Role Physical (RP) 
32.57 (35.62) 
58.23 (25.30) 
3.64 
0.000 
Physical Functioning (PF) 
45.86 (23.94) 
55.32 (26.13) 
1.52 
0.133 
Bodily Pain (BP) 
40.74 (22.12) 
58.72 (25.52) 
3.33 
0.001 
Energy/ Fatigue/Vitality (VT) 
67.05 (14.09) 
43.55 (13.60) 
7.24 
0.000 
Mental Health (MH) 
68.24 (11.77) 
41.29 (16.23) 
7.75 
0.000 
Role Emotional (RE) 
50.00 (38.79) 
60.30 (27.50) 
1.33 
0.185 
Social Functioning (SF) 
59.12 (22.37) 
58.71 (26.04) 
0.07 
0.944 
General Health (GH) 
50.32 (13.71) 
53.80 (19.21) 
0.07 
0.400 
Physical Component Summary (PCS) 
44.40 (13.56) 
55.65 (17.85) 
0.84 
0.012 
Mental Component Summary (MCS) 
61.21 (14.76) 
50.49 (12.25) 
2.59 
0.004 </p>

<p>Karami et al.: Better Mental Component of Quality of Life … </p>

<p> 
Available at http://ijph.tums.ac.ir </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The aim of our study was comparing quality of life 
in lower limbs amputee veterans with age and 
gender matched healthy normal population. Re-
sults show that amputees have significantly lower 
grade than normal subject does in role physical. 
So physical functioning is lower in amputees than 
normal healthy subjects are but role physical is 
better in amputees. We can consider these find-
ings as paucity of physical role and demand of pa-
tient from his body during the period of amputa-
tion. 
Quality of life could be defined as "the gap be-
tween a person's expectations and achievements". 
This gap can be kept small in two ways: living up 
to one's expectations or lowering these expecta-
tions. Lowering one's expectations is an adapta-
tion psychological process (19). we can conclude 
that long time period of life with amputation 
(more than 20 years) caused our subjects expect 
lower physical role for their bodies and this factor 
reflected in results as higher physical role perfor-
mance than normal healthy subjects. 
Results show that amputees were significantly bet-
ter than normal subjects in vitality and mental 
health were. As a whole, amputees have higher 
grade in mental summary component of quality of 
life. 
The first cause of this finding is psychosocial 
adaptation to lower limb amputation in our 
population. Living with amputee lower limb more 
than two decade has adapted them with new situa-
tions. The extent to which this occurs may be partly de-
pendent on the coping strategies or styles indi-
viduals adopt to manage experiences associated 
with their illness or injury (4, 20). Investigation of 
the role of coping strategies in adjustment to 
lower limb amputation, consistent with the wider 
coping literature, suggests that active/task-
oriented strategies such as problem solving and 
perceiving control over the disability are condu-
cive to positive psychosocial adjustment (21). In 
contrast, emotion-focused and passive strategies 
such as cognitive disengagement, avoidance, and 
catastrophic situations have been associated with </p>

<p>poor psychosocial outcomes (21). For example, 
Researches show that greater active problem solv-
ing was negatively associated with depression and 
internalized anger and positively associated with 
adjustment and acceptance of disability. In con-
trast, emotion-focused coping and cognitive dis-
engagement were positively associated with de-
pression, externalized hostility, and lack of accep-
tance of disability. 
In other hand, it is well documented that quality 
of life is deteriorated by mental illness rather than 
physical dysfunction. Lowlife satisfaction is one 
finding in a wide range of psychiatric disorders 
(22). Lower everyday functioning capacity and 
greater severity of positive, negative, and depres-
sive symptoms have been associated with lower 
grade of QOL (23-26). 
Another factor that should be considered as 
determinant criteria in increasing quality of life in 
our population is social support of them. Our 
population have extended network in whole coun-
try that is supported by veteran affair organization 
and this organization has financial support for 
them. We can consider this factor as one determi-
nant factor that prevent sever fallacy in quality of 
life in double lower limb amputee veteran. 
Previous studies have demonstrate significant as-
sociations between greater social support and bet-
ter functioning (27), higher quality of life (28), and 
lower rates of depressive symptomatology (21) in 
a variety of patient groups, consistent with most 
cross-sectional studies (29). Research showed that 
poor social networks are associated with worse 
physical health and mental well-being. Other fac-
tors such as living in poor housing, inadequate 
finances, and inadequate social relationships were 
also important factors leading to deterioration of 
quality of life in late life (30). So, good health, 
good social relationship, having social activities, 
good financial circumstances, and being inde-
pendent significantly would increase quality of life. 
Some other researches show that older adults with 
greater emotional support from their network of 
social relationships tend to have better cognitive </p>

<p>Iranian J Publ Health, Vol. 41, No.7, July 2012, pp.53-58 </p>

<p> 
Available at http://ijph.tums.ac.ir </p>

<p>functioning (31) and better health (32), although 
the correlated nature of such findings suggests 
that social support may be both a cause and a re-
sult of social connection. 
Evidence for the health benefits of social support 
may be clearer. Social support has been associated, 
for example, with better blood pressure regulation 
in patients with hypertension (33) and with better 
immune functioning (34). A pathway connecting 
social support to perceptions of stress through 
physiological functioning (e.g., cardiovascular, 
immune) and ending in physical health outcomes 
has been suggested (33). Low-income patients 
have twice the rate of functional limitations, and 
are less than half as likely to report good or very 
good health status compared with those of higher 
income (35). Low income, and difficulties meeting 
basic needs such as paying for food and medical 
bills, have been shown to be most consistently 
associated with increased mortality (35). 
Mental component of quality of life is distinct 
from physical component so that some individuals 
with sever handicap and physical impairment can 
achieve acceptable grade in mental component of 
quality of life. We can conclude that for physical 
handicaps mental health improvement may be en-
hanced quality of life of them. </p>

<p>Ethical considerations </p>

<p>Ethical issues (Including plagiarism, Informed Con-
sent, misconduct, data fabrication and/or falsification, 
double publication and/or submission, redundancy, 
etc) have been completely observed by the authors. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>This work was supported by Behavioural Research 
Center of Baghiyattallah Medical Science Univer-
sity. The authors declare that there is no conflict 
of interests. </p>



<p>Karami et al.: Better Mental Component of Quality of Life … </p>

<p> </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>