<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3123123" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The histone H3 variant CENP-A is the most favored candidate 
for an epigenetic mark that specifies the centromere. In fission 
yeast, adjacent heterochromatin can direct CENP-A Cnp1 chro-
matin establishment, but the underlying features governing 
where CENP-A Cnp1 chromatin assembles are unknown. We 
show that, in addition to centromeric regions, a low level of 
CENP-A Cnp1 associates with gene promoters where histone 
H3 is depleted by the activity of the Hrp1 Chd1 chromatin-
remodeling factor. Moreover, we demonstrate that noncod-
ing RNAs are transcribed by RNA polymerase II (RNAPII) 
from CENP-A Cnp1 chromatin at centromeres. These analyses 
reveal a similarity between centromeres and a subset of RNA-
PII genes and suggest a role for remodeling at RNAPII pro-
moters within centromeres that influences the replacement 
of histone H3 with CENP-A Cnp1 . </p>

<p>of chromatin extract. Hrp1 Chd1 binding data and histone H3 
density maps are from a previous study (16). 
Raw data from Affymetrix (.CEL format) were analyzed 
with <rs id="software-3" type="software">Affymetrix TAS</rs> (tiling analysis) <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">version 1.1</rs> software 
and visualized with <rs type="software">Affymetrix IGB</rs> (integrated genome 
browser). The data were normalized using quantile normal-
ization plus scaling and run with a bandwidth of 20. p values 
were calculated using hypergeometric probability distribu-
tion in R version 2.12.0. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Hrp1 Chd1 has previously been implicated in CENP-A Cnp1 
deposition but is not essential for cell viability (12). Expression 
of RNAPII-transcribed marker genes such as arg3 is repressed 
when placed within the central domain, and silencing of cen1: 
arg3 is highly sensitive to defective CENP-A Cnp1 deposition 
(17); however, this silencing is only partially impaired in hrp1 
cells (Fig. 1A). This suggests that redundant mechanisms oper-
ate to ensure CENP-A Cnp1 deposition in the absence of 
Hrp1 Chd1 . In agreement with this and previous analyses (12), 
when hrp1 was combined with the mis6-302 temperature-
sensitive mutation (defective in CENP-A Cnp1 deposition), it 
reduced the restrictive temperature of mis6-302. Furthermore, 
hrp1 also reduced the restrictive temperature of cnp1-87, a 
weak temperature-sensitive allele (Fig. 1B) (18). Consistent 
with this, the levels of CENP-A Cnp1 associated with the central 
domain were further reduced in hrp1 cnp1-87 double mutants 
compared with either single mutant (Fig. 1C). We conclude that 
Hrp1 facilitates the assembly of CENP-A Cnp1 chromatin, and it 
becomes essential when Mis6 or CENP-A Cnp1 function is 
impaired. 
Genome-wide analyses of CENP-A Cnp1 and histone H3 
localization by ChIP on tiling arrays with anti-CENP-A Cnp1 
and anti-H3 antibodies confirmed that Hrp1 Chd1 is required 
to maintain normal levels of CENP-A Cnp1 and that, in hrp1 
cells, H3 levels increase across the central domain (Fig. 1D 
and supplemental Fig. S1). Previously, we have shown that 
Hrp1 Chd1 acts at a subset of gene promoters to disassemble 
histone H3-containing nucleosomes close to the transcrip-
tion start sites (16). Further examination of the genome-
wide analyses revealed that low but detectable levels of 
CENP-A Cnp1 associate with a significant proportion of pro-
moters in wild-type cells at which Hrp1 Chd1 acts to disassem-
ble H3-containing nucleosomes (Fig. 2A). CENP-A Cnp1 asso-
ciation is significantly reduced at some, but not all, of these 
promoters in hrp1 cells, and in agreement with this, we saw 
an increase in H3 (p 2.7e 4 , hypergeometric probability) 
(Fig. 2, B and C). Some promoters show an increase in CENP-
A Cnp1 association and a decrease in H3 in hrp1 cells; how-
ever, this is less significant (Fig. 2D). These analyses imply 
that Hrp1 Chd1 directly participates in a remodeling process 
that evicts H3 and allows CENP-A Cnp1 deposition at the pro-
moters of some genes. However, additional factors, such as 
Scm3, must also contribute to the replacement of H3 with 
CENP-A Cnp1 and/or CENP-A Cnp1 maintenance at centrom-
eres (19, 20). This bears resemblance to the transcription-
coupled replacement of H3.1 with H3.3 in metazoa (21) and 
suggests that remodeling at some promoters of RNAPII </p>

<p>genes is intimately associated with the destabilization of 
H3-containing nucleosomes to encourage the assembly of 
CENP-A Cnp1 chromatin. Nucleosome replacement in 
S. cerevisiae is more prominent at promoters than within 
coding regions (22), and the genome-wide effects of 
Hrp1 Chd1 on H3 eviction in fission yeast are more pro-
nounced at promoters compared with coding regions and 
3-intergenic regions (16), accounting for the preferential 
association of CENP-A Cnp1 with the promoters of genes at 
which Hrp1 Chd1 functions. 
The close correlation between CENP-A Cnp1 association 
and Hrp1 Chd1 function at gene promoters as well as at cen-
tromeres raises the possibility that centromeric DNA may 
contain promoters for hitherto unidentified transcription 
elements. It is well established that transcripts are produced 
from the heterochromatic outer repeats of fission yeast cen-
tromeres and processed by the RNAi pathway (23, 24). To 
determine whether the central kinetochore domain is also 
transcribed, RT-PCR was performed with primer pairs 
(PP1-PP10) complementary to centromere 1 (cen1) (Fig. 
3A). PP1-PP3 detect part of the outer repeat heterochro-
matic transcript. PP4 flanks the tRNA Ala /tRNA Glu genes, 
whereas PP5-PP10 lie within the central subkinetochore 
domain. In wild-type cells, heterochromatic transcripts were 
detected in a region immediately adjacent to the outer 
repeats (PP1 and PP2), but transcripts were not apparent in 
the central domain (Fig. 3B). Outer repeat transcripts are 
known to accumulate in mutants defective in RNAi or het-
erochromatin integrity (23, 24). Several studies in S. cerevi-
siae indicate that aberrant or cryptic transcripts are 
degraded by 5-3-and/or 3-5-exoribonucleases; 3-end 
processing can contribute to RNA stability (25). Indeed, in 
fission yeast, outer repeat heterochromatin transcript levels 
are also regulated by the exosome (26 -28). We therefore 
tested whether conditional mutations in Pfs2 (pfs2-11 tem-
perature-sensitive; polyadenylation factor I subunit 2) (29), 
Dhp1 (dhp1-1 temperature-sensitive; 5-3-exoribonu-
clease orthologous to Xrn2/Rat1) (30), or Dis3 (dis3-54 cold-
sensitive; 3-5-exoribonuclease component of the exo-
some) (27) allow accumulation of RNA homologous to the 
central domain. Transcripts from the central domain were 
clearly detected with PP5, PP6, PP7, PP9, and PP10 in 
dhp1-1, pfs2-11, and dis3-54 cells, but not in wild-type cells, 
under restrictive conditions (36 or 18 °C) (Fig. 3B). We con-
clude that a large proportion of the central domain is tran-
scribed but that the resulting transcripts are normally unde-
tectable due to their rapid turnover. RT-PCR also detected 
transcripts homologous to the central domains of cen2 and 
cen3 in dis3-54 cells (Fig. 3C). Thus, transcription of subkin-
etochore chromatin is a general property of the three cen-
tromeres, and these transcripts from under kinetochores 
(TUKs) are normally degraded by the exosome. 
Northern analyses with an RNA probe specific for the cen1 
central domain confirmed the presence of TUKs; no obvious 
signal was observed in wild-type cells, but a smear of transcripts 
was detected in RNA-processing mutants (pfs2-11, dhp1-1, and 
dis3-54) (Fig. 4A and supplemental Fig. S2). We also examined 
the temperature-sensitive mutants mis6-302 and cnp1-1, </p>

<p>CENP-A Chromatin Transcription in Fission Yeast </p>

<p>JULY 1, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 26 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 23601 </p>

<p>which have reduced levels of CENP-A Cnp1 chromatin over 
the central domain (31, 32). Surprisingly, transcripts with 
discrete sizes (0.5 kb) were identified in both mutants (Fig. 
4A); these discrete transcripts (discrete TUKs) were highly 
enriched in poly(A)-selected RNA (Fig. 4B). A lower level of 
these specific transcripts was also enriched in the poly(A) 
fraction from dis3-54 (Fig. 4B, arrowhead). Dis3 is the key 
catalytic subunit of the exosome required to degrade aber-
rant transcripts, whereas Pfs2 and Dhp1 are required for </p>

<p>normal 3-end formation/termination (27, 29, 30). pfs2-11 
and dhp1-1 may generate transcripts with extended 3-ends 
due to transcriptional read-through into downstream 
regions, resulting in the observed heterogeneous smear of 
transcripts (Fig. 4, A and B). The specific increase in discrete 
TUKs observed in mis6-302 and cnp1-1 cells could be inter-
preted to mean that intact CENP-A Cnp1 chromatin prevents 
expression of these transcripts; however, our analyses sug-
gest that TUKs are constitutively produced and turned over </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Chromatin-remodeling factor Hrp1 Chd1 contributes to CENP-A Cnp1 chromatin formation. A, silencing of cen1:arg3 in WT, cnp1-169, and hrp1 
cells. The growth assay was performed on non-selective (N/S) or arginine-depleted (Arg) plates at 25, 32, and 36 °C. B, viability of cells bearing hrp1 
combined with mis6-302 (upper panels) or with cnp1-87 (lower panels) compared with wild-type and single mutants grown at 25, 32, or 36 °C. C, CENP-A Cnp1 ChIP 
analyses in WT, hrp1, cnp1-87, and hrp1 cnp1-87 cells grown at 36 °C. The enrichment of the cnt1 product was compared with input DNA relative to the act1 
control by quantitative PCR. D, genome browser view of cen1 showing ChIP-chip binding profiles for CENP-A Cnp1 (purple) and H3 (green) in WT and hrp1 cells 
(as indicated) at 30 °C. The relative ratios of CENP-A Cnp1 and H3 (hrp1/WT) are indicated (black). Data on the y axis are presented in log 2 scale, and the x axis 
shows genome positions in base pairs. </p>

<p>CENP-A Chromatin Transcription in Fission Yeast </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 26 • JULY 1, 2011 </p>

<p>by the exosome in wild-type cells. The chromatin context in 
mis6-302 and cnp1-1 cells is dramatically altered from 
CENP-A Cnp1 to H3 chromatin; CENP-A Cnp1 chromatin may 
interfere with events required for the formation of specific 
transcripts, such as accurate 3-termination, ensuring their 
turnover. Using RNA probes complementary to either 
reverse or forward strands of the cen1 central core (cc1/tm1) 
(supplemental Fig. S2), we detected other discrete tran-
scripts in distinct central domain regions in poly(A) RNA 
from cnp1-1 cells (Fig. 4, C and D). To identify the 5-ends of 
these central domain noncoding transcripts, we employed 
5-rapid amplification of cDNA ends (RACE)/PCR on 
5-capped poly(A) RNA extracted from wild-type and cnp1-1 
cells. This demonstrated that these novel/unusual tran-
scripts are produced from within the central domain and do 
not arise by read-through from outer repeat transcripts (Fig. 
4E and supplemental Fig. S3). The high sensitivity of 
5-RACE/PCR allowed the detection of transcripts in wild-
type cells with some primers (Fig. 4E, black arrows, and sup-
plemental Fig. S3). The transcription start sites for these 
transcripts were identical in wild-type and cnp1-1 cells, sug-
gesting that they are indeed produced from wild-type cen-
tromeres, albeit at a lower level. The fact that these tran-
scripts are 5-capped and polyadenylated indicates that 
TUKs are produced by RNAPII. Consistent with alterations </p>

<p>in central domain chromatin affecting transcription (lower 
CENP-A Cnp1 and higher H3 deposition) (Fig. 1D), increased 
levels of the central domain transcript were also detectable 
in hrp1 cells (supplemental Fig. S4). 
On the basis of the 5-RACE analyses above, we designed 
improved probes for Northern analyses to detect the forward 
and reverse strands of the cen1 central core (cc1/tm1) (sup-
plemental Fig. S2) in additional mutants known to affect 
kinetochore integrity (mis12-537, mis16-53, and mis18-262 
in addition to mis6-302 and cnp1-1) (6). At 36 °C, transcripts 
were detected in all mutants apart from mis12-537 with this 
TM-forward 5 probe (Fig. 4F). Some transcripts were even 
detectable in mis6-302, cnp1-1, and mis16-53 at 25 °C, the 
permissive temperature. In all mutants, including mis12-
537, this TM-reverse probe allowed detection of other tran-
scripts (Fig. 4G) in addition to those observed with the orig-
inal probe (Fig. 4D). Together, these analyses indicate that 
cryptic transcription is prevalent in the central kinetochore 
domain of fission yeast centromeres and revealed only in 
cells defective in RNA turnover or formation of subkineto-
chore chromatin. In support of this, low levels of H3K4 </p>

<p>5 TM represents a 3.3-kb element shared between the central domains of 
cen2 and cen3. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Genome-wide CENP-A Cnp1 localization correlates with Hrp1 Chd1 occupancy and H3 density changes in hrp1 cells. A, Venn diagram 
illustrating the overlap of CENP-A Cnp1 enrichment with Hrp1 Chd1 occupancy and H3 density increase in hrp1 cells (16). A cutoff of 1.5 was used for 
CENP-A Cnp1 enrichment. The p values indicate the probability of overlap generated by a hypergeometric probability test using R. B, genome browser 
view of gene SPBC839.06 with reduced CENP-A Cnp1 (purple) and increased H3 (green) levels at its promoter in hrp1 cells. The arrow indicates the 
direction of transcription. The relative ratios of CENP-A Cnp1 and H3 are indicated (black). Data on the y axis are presented in log 2 scale, and the x axis 
shows genome positions in base pairs. C, Venn diagram showing the overlap between promoters where CENP-A Cnp1 is reduced, promoters where H3 is 
increased, and promoters where H3 is reduced in hrp1 cells. A cutoff of 1.2 was used for CENP-A Cnp1 reduction. D, Venn diagram showing the overlap 
between promoters where CENP-A Cnp1 is increased, promoters where H3 is increased, and promoters where H3 is reduced in hrp1 cells. A cutoff of 1.2 
was used for the CENP-A Cnp1 increase. </p>

<p>CENP-A Chromatin Transcription in Fission Yeast </p>

<p>JULY 1, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 26 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 23603 </p>

<p>methylation, a modification associated with active transcrip-
tion, have been shown to be enriched in the small amount of 
histone H3 that remains within subkinetochore chromatin 
in wild-type cells (33). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Centromere-associated DNA has been shown to be tran-
scribed in plants and vertebrates (7, 10). 30 years ago, EM 
studies demonstrated the presence of RNase-sensitive mate-
rial at the base of kinetochore microtubules in newt lung 
cells (34). Since then, centromeric transcripts have been 
found to associate with kinetochore proteins (9, 10). In this 
study, we demonstrated an analogy between the central 
domain-associated CENP-A Cnp1 chromatin of centromeres 
and genes whose promoters are associated with Hrp1 Chd1 in 
fission yeast. The fact that Hrp1 Chd1 promotes eviction of 
histone H3 at a set of promoters suggests that similar remod-
eling processes may occur at RNAPII promoters within cen-
tromeres and may contribute to exchange of canonical 
H3-containing nucleosomes for CENP-A Cnp1 -containing 
nucleosomes (summarized in Fig. 5). 
It is possible that transcription within centromeres occurs 
merely as a consequence of having RNAPII promoters whose 
presence or activation is critical to act as a seed for remod-
eling events that promote CENP-A Cnp1 deposition. The 
resulting TUK transcripts are degraded by the exosome and 
thus may represent just nonfunctional by-products of tran-</p>

<p>scription. However, we cannot rule out the possibility that 
these unstable transcripts might also have a dedicated func-
tion in guiding some components of the CENP-A Cnp1 depo-
sition machineries and/or kinetochore complex to their cog-
nate DNA sequences (10). Alternatively, the production of 
TUKs might influence chromatin modification within cen-
tromeric chromatin by processes analogous to those associ-
ated with cryptic or antisense noncoding RNA production in 
S. cerevisiae (35, 36). However, we found that the accumula-
tion of TUKs in pfs2-11, dhp1-1, or dis3-54 cells had no 
obvious effect on CENP-A Cnp1 chromatin formation. 6 It is 
also conceivable that these transcripts are processed into a 
specific class of small RNAs that have a role in CENP-A Cnp1 
chromatin formation and/or kinetochore assembly analo-
gous to how siRNAs derived from outer repeat transcripts 
induce heterochromatin formation. However, with our 
detection methods, we did not find evidence for the presence 
of small RNAs corresponding to the central domain of 
centromeres. 5 
Intriguingly, it has recently been reported that S. cerevi-
siae CENP-A Cse4 also tends to associate with a number of 
RNAPII promoters where RNAPII binding is high (37); how-
ever, it is not known if these promoters share any structural 
or mechanistically related features with S. cerevisiae centro-</p>

<p>6 E. S. Choi and R. C. Allshire, unpublished data. </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Accumulation of central domain transcripts in RNA-processing mutants. A, schematic of fission yeast cen1, indicating the central core 
(cnt), innermost repeat (imr), and outer repeats (otr/dg-dh). Regions amplified by primer pairs (PP1-PP10) used in RT-PCR are indicated below (black 
bars). B, RT-PCR analysis of transcripts from cen1 and the act1 control. Wild-type, dhp1-1, and pfs2-11 cells were grown at 25 °C and then shifted to 36 °C 
for 6 h before RNA extraction. Wild-type and dis3-54 cells were grown at 36 °C and shifted to 18 °C for 9 h before RNA extraction. RT, negative control 
performed without reverse transcriptase; *, unspecific products. PCR with a chromosomal DNA (chr. DNA) template was included as a positive control. 
C, RT-PCR analysis of transcripts from cnt2, cnt3, and the act1 control. PP-cnt2 and PP-cnt3 are specific for the central domain of cen2 and cen3, 
respectively. </p>

<p>CENP-A Chromatin Transcription in Fission Yeast </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 26 • JULY 1, 2011 </p>

<p>meres that contribute to CENP-A Cse4 deposition. Interest-
ingly, the S. cerevisiae centromeric protein Cbf1, which 
binds centromere DNA element I, functions as a transcrip-
tion factor at the MET16 promoter (38). In this regard, it is 
possible that RNAPII transcription might also occur within 
or close to centromeres of S. cerevisiae. In fact, cryptic tran-
scription was detected close to CEN3 in S. cerevisiae exo-
some mutants (39); it is not known if this is a general feature </p>

<p>of all S. cerevisiae centromeres. Recently, the human chro-
matin-remodeling factor FACT (facilitates chromatin tran-
scription), whose function is implicated in transcription, was 
found to associate with affinity-purified CENP-A chromatin 
(40, 41) Moreover, depletion of FACT was found to impair 
incorporation of newly synthesized CENP-A in chicken cells 
(42). CHD1 was also found at centromeres in chicken cells 
and is required for centromeric localization of CENP-A in </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Northern and 5-RACE/PCR analyses of central domain transcripts. A, Northern analysis of total RNAs in RNA-processing and kinetochore 
mutants. An RNA probe complementary to cnt1 was used. Cells grown at the permissive temperature (25 °C for WT, pfs2-11, dhp1-1, mis6-302, and cnp1-1 
cells and 36 °C for WT and dis3-54 cells) were shifted to the restrictive temperature (6 h at 36 °C for WT, pfs2-11, dhp1-1, mis6-302, and cnp1-1 cells and 
9 h at 18 °C for WT and dis3-54 cells) before RNA extraction. act1 was used as a loading control. *, rRNA interference with hybridization. For additional 
EtBr images, see supplemental Fig. S5A. B, the same cnt1 probe used on poly(A) RNA. For additional EtBr images, see supplemental Fig. S5B. C and D, 
Northern analysis of total or poly(A) RNAs from WT and cnp1-1 cells with an RNA probe complementary to the reverse strand (forward probe; C) or the 
forward strand (reverse probe; D) of the cc1/tm1 sequence, which is shared by cnt1 and cnt3. *, nonspecific band. For additional EtBr images, see 
supplemental Fig. S5 (C and D). E, schematic representation of transcription start sites determined by 5-RACE/PCR in WT and cnp1-1 cells. Black arrows, 
transcription start sites identified in WT and cnp1-1 cells; gray arrows, transcription start sites identified only in cnp1-1 cells. F and G, Northern blots 
showing transcripts complementary to the TM-forward (F) or TM-reverse (G) probes in WT, mis6-302, cnp1-1, mis12-537, mis16-53, and mis18-262 cells 
grown at permissive (25 °C) and restrictive (36 °C) temperatures. *, nonspecific band. EtBr staining confirmed equal loading. </p>

<p>CENP-A Chromatin Transcription in Fission Yeast </p>

<p>JULY 1, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 26 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 23605 </p>

<p>human cells (42). These observations, together with the anal-
yses presented here, implicate RNAPII transcription and the 
associated remodeling activities in the replacement of his-
tone H3 with CENP-A. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments-We thank A. Pidoux, A. Buscaino, L. Harrington, 
and J. Houseley for comments on the manuscript. We are grateful to 
the following colleagues for advice, strains; and reagents: K. Taka-
hashi and M. Yanagida. </p>



<p>CENP-A Chromatin Transcription in Fission Yeast </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 26 • JULY 1, 2011 </p>



<p>CENP-A Chromatin Transcription in Fission Yeast </p>

<p>JULY 1, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 26 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 23607 </p>

</text></tei>