<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3129971" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>INTRODUCTION: PXR polymorphisms have been implicated in modulating CYP3A4 and PXR expression, potentially 
accounting for interindividual differences in drug metabolism. The prevalence of PXR polymorphisms varies among 
ethnic groups and data on the allelic distribution in the highly mixed Brazilian population is lacking. The aim of this 
study was to analyze genetic variations in the PXR gene in Brazilians and to compare the results to other ethnic 
groups. </p>

<p>METHODS: DNA samples from 117 healthy Brazilians underwent PCR amplification and sequencing. </p>

<p>RESULTS: Eleven polymorphisms were identified, 3 of which are highly associated with differences in CYP3A4 expression. 
We also identified 1 new synonymous variant in 1.3% of the alleles. Among the functional polymorphisms, -25913 C.T 
and -6994T.C occurred at a higher frequency compared to the African alleles (p , 0.05) but at a lower frequency 
compared to Caucasian alleles. The 8055 C.T allele was found at a similar frequency to those described in Caucasians and 
Africans (p . 0.05). </p>

<p>CONCLUSION: We observed that functional variants of the PXR were frequent in our sample of 
the Brazilian population. Our results suggest that PXR gene variants may be of interest in pharmacogenetic 
studies involving Brazilians. </p>

<p>The interindividual variability in human drug metabo-
lism may be genetically determined by allelic variance in 
genes encoding P450 proteins and nuclear receptors. </p>

<p>1-4 </p>

<p>Cytochrome P450s metabolize approximately 80% of clinical 
drugs and polymorphisms in the CYP3A4 gene have been 
previously investigated due to its involvement in the 
metabolism of more than 50% of drugs. Despite the large 
interindividual differences in CYP3A4 expression, poly-
morphisms that impair enzyme activity seem to be rare. </p>

<p>5-7 </p>

<p>CYP3A4 expression is mainly induced by the pregnane X 
receptor (PXR), 
8-10 a member of the orphan nuclear receptor 
subfamily and the main transcriptional regulator of cyto-
chrome P4503A enzymes. 
8,9 The activation of PXR initiates 
in the cytoplasm. After exposure to ligands, PXR dimerizes 
with the retinoic acid receptor (RXR) and binds to nuclear 
receptor response elements in the upstream regulatory </p>

<p>regions of target genes. These genes encode drug-metabo-
lizing enzymes such as CYP3A4 and drug transporters, </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>which are the main regulators in the uptake and transfor-
mation of many prescribed medicines. 
Several PXR (also known as NR1I2) polymorphisms have 
been identified that influence the level of PXR expression and, 
therefore, indirectly regulate its target genes. 
4,12 These poly-
morphisms account for the wide variability of CYP3A4 levels in 
the population. 
4,13 The functional effects of these polymorph-
isms include aberrant DNA binding and alterations in the 
transactivation and expression of downstream target genes. </p>

<p>4,12 </p>

<p>While the allelic distribution of the PXR gene varies 
widely among different ethnic groups, 
13-17 it has yet to be 
studied in the highly mixed Brazilian population. Here we 
analyze the frequency of PXR variants in a sample of 
healthy Brazilian subjects. We also compare the frequencies 
of PXR polymorphisms to those described in Asians, 
Caucasians, and Africans in order to determine whether 
PXR variants should be evaluated in pharmacogenetic 
studies involving Brazilian subjects. </p>

<p>Subjects </p>

<p>The study protocol was approved by the Ethical 
Committee of Sã o Paulo University. Written consent was </p>

<p>Copyright ß 2011 CLINICS -This is an Open Access article distributed under 
the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits unrestricted non-
commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the 
original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2011;66(6):1041-1044 
DOI:10.1590/S1807-59322011000600020 </p>



<p>obtained from all subjects. Healthy volunteers consisted of 
76 females and 41 males with a mean age 25.8 ¡ 11.8 years. 
The self-reported ethnicity of this cohort was 87.2% 
Caucasian and 12.8% African. In addition, 88% were from 
the southeast, 8.5% from the northeast, and 3.5% from the 
southern region of Brazil. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>DNA samples from all subjects were obtained from 
peripheral blood leukocytes using a salting out procedure. 
All coding regions of the PXR gene were analyzed in addition 
to three variants in non-coding regions that had a minor allele 
frequency of at least $ 0.10 in other ethnic groups. We also 
looked for three variants, which modified the PXR and/or 
CYP3A4 expression, previously described in non-coding 
regions with a minor allele frequency $ 0.10 in other ethnic 
groups. 
4,17 The PXR gene was amplified as previously 
described. 
4,18 The amplified products were sequenced using </p>

<p>the Big Dye Terminator Sequencing Kit 
TM (Applied 
Biosystem, Inc., Foster City, CA, USA) and capillary electro-
phoresis was conducted on an ABI PRISM 3100 sequencer 
(Applied Biosystem, Inc.). Sequence traces were analyzed 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Sequencher</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 4.5 build 1416</rs>) and assembled to 
the reference (NCBI accession number AF364606). </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>When appropriate, identified allele frequencies were 
compared to the expected normal distribution in a popula-
tion (Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium) by using a goodness-of-
fit x 
2 test. 
Differences in allele frequencies between ethnic groups 
were analyzed using the x 
2 test. Values of p , 0.05 were 
considered to be significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The allelic frequencies of PXR polymorphisms that we 
identified in this study are shown in Table 1 along with 
previously published data from Asian, Caucasian, and African 
populations. The genotypic frequencies that we found are 
listed in Table 2. All polymorphisms were in Hardy-Weinberg 
equilibrium. We identified 11 polymorphisms (Tables 1 and 2), 
one of which is a new synonymous variant located in exon 4 </p>

<p>(4306 C.G) that was present in 1.3 % of Brazilian alleles. Eight 
polymorphisms were identified in the coding regions of the 
PXR gene and 3 polymorphisms in non-coding regions. Of the 
variants identified, 8055 C.T, -25913 C.T, and -6994 C.T are 
known to be associated with functionality. 
The 8055 C.T (rs2276707) variant was found in 12.5% of 
alleles, which is similar to its frequencies in Caucasian and 
African alleles of 15% and 18% (p . 0.05), 
12 respectively, but 
lower than its frequency in Chinese alleles of 45% (p , 
0.05). 
19 The -25913 C.T (rs1523130) variant occurred in 50% 
of the Brazilian alleles, which is less frequent than in 
Caucasians (70%, p = 0.003, 95% CI: 0.66-0.76) but more 
frequent than in Africans (28%, p , 0.001, 95% CI: 0.49-0.61). 
The -6994 C.T (rs2472677) polymorphism was found in 
46% of the Brazilian alleles, which is a higher frequency 
than in Africans (38.1%, p = 0.03, 95% CI: 0.80-0.85) but a 
lower frequency than in Caucasians (62%, p = 0.01, 95% CI: 
0.70-0.79). 
The 79 C.T (rs12727613) polymorphism was found in 
2.1% of Brazilian alleles. This variant is significantly more 
frequent in African alleles (20%, p , 0.001) and not present 
in Caucasians or Asians. The 106 G.A (rs12721607) 
polymorphism, which is absent in Asians, was found in 
1.3% of alleles in this population, similar to its frequencies in 
Caucasians and Africans of 5% and 4%, respectively (p , 
0.05). The 4321 G.A (rs12721608) polymorphism is absent 
in Africans but present in Brazilians at a similarly low 
frequency as that found in Caucasians (p , 0.05). The other 
five polymorphisms were detected at a frequency lower 
than 1% [4447 T.C (rs12721611), 4499 C.T (rs12721600), 
4773 G.A (rs12721612), and 8528 G.A (rs59152710)]. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>PXR polymorphisms have been implicated in modulating 
CYP3A4 and PXR expression, potentially accounting for 
interindividual differences in drug metabolism. 
20 These 
variants impact drug response and some types of drug 
interactions by affecting serum levels of the medicines and 
endogenous compounds, which can include PXR ligands 
and substrates of enzymes and drug transporters. 
13 The 
distribution of allelic variants in the PXR gene varies widely 
among different ethnic groups, 
12,14 which helps to explain 
variations in the pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics 
of drugs that are PXR ligands. </p>

<p>Table 1 -Allelic frequency of polymorphisms in the PXR gene in Brazilians compared to Asians, Caucasians, and Africans. </p>

<p>Location 
dbSNP </p>

<p>*Position in 
AF364606 </p>

<p>Amino Acid 
Change 
Asians 
Caucasians 
Africans </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>This study </p>

<p>n˚Frequency 
n˚Frequency 
n˚Frequency 
n˚Frequency </p>

<p>59UTR 
rs1523130 
-25913 C.T 
-
8 0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.67 
80 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.70 
80 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.28 
234 
0.50 
Intron 1 
rs2472677 
-6994 C.T 
-
9 2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0.62 
714 </p>

<p># </p>

<p>0.381 
234 
0.457 
Exon 2 
rs12727613 
79 C.T 
Pro27Ser 
80 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
300 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 
6 6 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>0.20 
234 
0.021 
Exon 2 
rs12721607 
106 G.A 
Gly36Arg 
80 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
8 0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.05 
80 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.04 
234 
0.013 
Exon 4 
-
4306 C.G 
Arg156Arg 
234 
0.013 
Exon 4 
rs12721608 
4321 G.A 
Gln122Arg 
144 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>0.01 
714 </p>

<p># </p>

<p>0 
234 
0.012 
Exon 4 
rs12721611 
4447 T.C 
Thr164Thr 
80 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
8 0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
8 0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.03 
234 
0.008 
Exon 5 
rs12721600 
4499 C.T 
Gly220Gly 
234 
0.008 
Exon 6 
rs12721612 
4773 G.A 
Gly317Gly 
234 
0.004 
Intron 6 
rs2276707 
8055 C.T 
-
8 0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.51 
150 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0.15 
22 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0.18 
234 
0.125 
Exon 8 
rs59152710 
8528 G.A 
Ala370Thr 
312 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 
6 4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.016 
234 
0.004 </p>

<p>a African-American population. n˚: number of alleles. Data from Asians, Caucasians, and Africans was obtained from 
1 King et al. 2007, 
2 Hustert et al. 2001, 
3 Wang et al. 2008, 
4 Lamba et al. 2008, and </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Zhang et al. 2008. 
# Data from sub-Saharan Africans (Svard et al. 2010). Italics: new variant. *Position in 
relation to translation start site of PXR (NR1I2): GenBank Accession AF364606. </p>

<p>Genetic polymorphisms of PXR in Brazilians 
Moreira RPP et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2011;66(6):1041-1044 </p>



<p>This study was carried out in order to determine the 
frequency of variants of the PXR gene in a sample of the 
Brazilian population. We found 11 polymorphisms in the 
PXR gene, including the 4306 C.G substitution in exon 4 
that has not been previously described. This variant is not 
predicted to alter the splice site in exon 4 of the PXR gene 
and is unlikely to alter protein function. 
The Brazilian population is highly heterogeneous, result-
ing from centuries of interbreeding among peoples from 
three continents: European colonizers (mostly Portuguese), 
African slaves, and native Indians. 
21 Although Brazilians 
contain approximately 28% of African alleles, we found that 
the variant C79T (rs12727613), which occurs in 20% of alleles 
Africans, occurred at a much lower than expected frequency 
in our sample (2.1%). On the other hand, the -25913 C.T 
(rs1523130) polymorphism that is present in 28% of African 
alleles was present at a significantly higher frequency in our 
population (50%, p = 0.003). We also found that the -
6994T.C (rs2472677), which is present in 38% of African 
alleles, was significantly more frequent in the Brazilian 
alleles (46%, p = 0.03). Finally, the -25913 C.T and -
6994T.C polymorphisms were not as frequent in the 
Brazilian alleles as in Caucasian alleles (p , 0.05). 
Our results are distinctly clustered. This could represent 
the unique admixture of the regional subpopulation from 
the southeast region of Brazil, which has similar ancestral </p>

<p>contributions from African (34%), European (31%), and 
Native American (33%) alleles, in contrast to the higher 
proportion of African lineages observed in the northeast 
region. </p>

<p>21-23 </p>

<p>Our study emphasizes the population-dependent fre-
quency of PXR polymorphisms. The polymorphism fre-
quencies found in our sample differ greatly from those 
previously described in Caucasians and Africans. Our 
results suggest that variants in the PXR gene should be 
considered in pharmacogenetic studies involving Brazilians 
from the southeast region, since the miscegenation varies 
from region to region. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors gratefully acknowledge Mr. Ricardo de Paula for language 
editing. 
This research was supported by grants from FAPESP # 05/04726-0 and 
09/54238-2, RPP Moreira by FAPESP # 08/50959-4 and 09/54394-4, 
and Bachega TASS, Jorge AA, and Mendonca BB by CNPq #305117/ 
2009-2, #301477/2009-4, and #301339/2008-9, respectively. </p>



<p>Table 2 -Genotypic frequency of polymorphisms in the 
PXR gene in Brazilians. </p>

<p>Location 
dbSNP 
*Position in AF364606 
Frequency </p>

<p>59UTR 
rs1523130 
-25913 C.T 
CC 
0.325 
CT 
0.35 
TT 
0.325 
Intron 1 
rs2472677 
-6994 C.T 
CC 
0.368 
CT 
0.352 
TT 
0.282 
Exon 2 
rs12727613 
79 C.T 
CC 
0.957 
CT 
0.043 
TT 
0 
Exon 2 
rs12721607 
106 G.A 
GG 
0.974 
GA 
0.026 
AA 
0 
Exon 4 
-
4306 C.G 
CC 
0.974 
CG 
0.026 
GG 
0 
Exon 4 
rs12721608 
4321 G.A 
GG 
0.974 
GA 
0.026 
AA 
0 
Exon 4 
rs12721611 
4447 T.C 
TT 
0.983 
TC 
0.017 
CC 
0 
Exon 5 
rs12721600 
4499 C.T 
CC 
0.983 
CT 
0.017 
TT 
0 
Exon 6 
rs12721612 
4773 G.A 
GG 
0.992 
GA 
0.08 
AA 
0 
Intron 6 
rs2276707 
8055 C.T 
CC 
0.769 
CT 
0.214 
TT 
0.017 
Exon 8 
rs59152710 
8528 G.A 
GG 
0.992 
GA 
0.08 
AA 
0 </p>

<p>Italics: new variant, *Position in relation to translation start site of PXR 
(NR1I2): GenBank Accession AF364606. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2011;66(6):1041-1044 
Genetic polymorphisms of PXR in Brazilians 
Moreira RPP et al. </p>





<p>Genetic polymorphisms of PXR in Brazilians 
Moreira RPP et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2011;66(6):1041-1044 </p>



</text></tei>