<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3608489" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT Multiple Rabs are associated with secretory granules/vesicles, but how these 
GTPases are coordinated to promote regulated exocytosis is not well understood. In bladder 
umbrella cells a subapical pool of discoidal/fusiform-shaped vesicles (DFVs) undergoes 
Rab11a-dependent regulated exocytosis in response to bladder filling. We show that Rab11a-
associated vesicles are enmeshed in an apical cytokeratin meshwork and that Rab11a likely 
acts upstream of Rab8a to promote exocytosis. Surprisingly, expression of Rabin8, a previ-
ously described Rab11a effector and guanine nucleotide exchange factor for Rab8, stimu-
lates stretch-induced exocytosis in a manner that is independent of its catalytic activity. Ad-
ditional studies demonstrate that the unconventional motor protein myosin5B motor (Myo5B) 
works in association with the Rab8a-Rab11a module to promote exocytosis, possibly by 
ensuring transit of DFVs through a subapical, cortical actin cytoskeleton before fusion. Our 
results indicate that Rab11a, Rab8a, and Myo5B function as part of a network to promote 
stretch-induced exocytosis, and we predict that similarly organized Rab networks will be 
common to other regulated secretory pathways. </p>

<p>Rabs are a large family of small GTPases (44 subfamilies in humans) 
that regulate multiple steps in membrane traffic, including the un-
coating, movement, maturation, tethering, and fusion of vesicles 
with their target membranes (Diekmann et al., 2011; Hutagalung  and Novick, 2011). Of the Rabs identified, Rab3 (a-d isoforms), 
Rab26, Rab27 (a and b isoforms), and Rab37 are referred to as 
"secretory" Rabs because of their association in neuroendocrine 
cells with regulated secretion (Fukuda, 2008); that is, those pathways </p>

<p>in which a storage pool of secretory vesicles/granules fuses with the 
plasma membrane in response to extracellular stimuli. The role of 
other "nonsecretory" Rabs in regulated secretion is not well under-
stood or documented, despite the association of many of these 
Rabs with purified secretory granules (Brunner et al., 2007; Casey  et al., 2007; Rindler et al., 2007) and observations that they can pro-
mote regulated secretion in different cell types (Duman et al., 1999;  Khvotchev et al., 2003). Furthermore, regulated secretory pathways 
often depend on multiple Rabs (Fukuda, 2008; Pavlos and Jahn,  2011), but the hierarchy of these Rabs and their relationships to one 
another remain to be defined. 
In bladder umbrella cells, Rab11a, a well-known regulator of en-
docytic recycling in other cell systems (Ullrich et al., 1996; Casanova  et al., 1999; Lapierre et al., 2001; Knodler et al., 2010), is associated 
with an abundant subapical pool of discoidal/fusiform-shaped vesi-
cles (DFVs), which are enriched in the apical membrane protein uro-
plakin 3a (UP3a; Khandelwal et al., 2008; Hudoklin et al., 2012), one 
of four major UP species that make up the asymmetric unit mem-
brane of the umbrella cell (Wu et al., 2009). DFVs are distinct from </p>

<p>Monitoring Editor 
Keith E. Mostov 
University of California, 
San Francisco </p>

<p>Received: Aug 2, 2012 
Revised: Jan 29, 2013 
Accepted: Jan 30, 2013 </p>

<p>This article was published online ahead of print in MBoC in Press (http://www 
.molbiolcell.org/cgi/doi/10.1091/mbc.E12-08-0568) on February 6, 2013. 
Address correspondence to: Gerard Apodaca (gla6@pitt.edu). </p>

<p>© 2013 Khandelwal et al. This article is distributed by The American Society for Cell 
Biology under license from the author(s). Two months after publication it is avail-
able to the public under an Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported 
Creative Commons License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0). 
"ASCB </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>," "The American Society for Cell Biology </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>," and "Molecular Biology of 
the Cell 
® " are registered trademarks of The American Society of Cell Biology. </p>

<p>Abbreviations used: DFV, discoidal/fusiform-shaped vesicle; GAP, GTPase-
activating protein; GEF, guanine nucleotide exchange factor; Myo5B, myosin5B 
motor; UP, uroplakin. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>Veranic and Jezernik, 2002). Thus an actin-based motor is likely to 
be required at late steps in the exocytic pathway, after DFV move-
ment through the cytokeratin network and before access to the api-
cal plasma membrane. </p>

<p>the endocytic system and instead form de novo from the trans-Golgi 
network (TGN; Khandelwal et al., 2008, 2010; Hudoklin et al., 2009). 
On exit from this compartment, DFVs mature and move toward the 
subapical region of the cell, where they are enmeshed in a cytokera-
tin network (Veranic and Jezernik, 2002; Guo et al., 2009; Hudoklin  et al., 2012). In response to increased apical membrane tension 
(i.e., as a result of bladder filling) and an attendant rise in Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>, they 
undergo an actin-and Rab11a-dependent exocytosis, dramatically 
increasing apical plasma membrane surface area (Lewis and de  Moura, 1982; Wang et al., 2003; Khandelwal et al., 2008; Yu et al.,  2009). The proteins that are modulated by and act downstream of 
Rab11a to promote stretch-induced DFV exocytosis are unknown, 
although the cytoskeletal motor protein myosin 5B (Myo5B) is a 
known Rab11a effector, as well as Rab8a and Rab10 effector, in 
other cellular events (Lapierre et al., 2001; Volpicelli et al., 2002;  Wakabayashi et al., 2005; Varthakavi et al., 2006; Nedvetsky et al.,  2007; Swiatecka-Urban et al., 2007; Provance et al., 2008; Chu et al.,  2009; Roland et al., 2011; Schuh, 2011; Xu et al., 2011). 
To better understand the dependence of DFV exocytosis on 
Rab11a, we turned to an analogous, albeit constitutive secretory 
pathway that has been carefully dissected in the budding yeast 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae. In this organism, newly synthesized se-
cretory vesicles emerge from the late Golgi under the control of 
Ypt31p/32p, paralogues of Rab11 (Benli et al., 1996). GTP-bound 
Ypt31p/32p recruits Sec2p, a guanine nucleotide exchange factor 
(GEF) for Sec4p. The Sec4p GTPase is homologous to Rab8 and 
associates with vesicles before their fusion with the emerging bud 
(Ortiz et al., 2002). An important effector in this system is Myo2p, a 
Myo5-like protein that interacts with both Ypt31p/32p and Sec4p 
and is responsible for actin-dependent delivery of the vesicles from 
the Golgi to the plasma membrane (Lipatova et al., 2008; Jin et al.,  2011). Furthermore, Myo2p associates with Sec15p, a component 
of the octameric exocyst complex that tethers secretory vesicles to 
the plasma membrane before fusion (Jin et al., 2011). Sec15p also 
serves as an effector of Sec4p (Jin et al., 2011), and by its reported 
binding to Sec2p it may aid in the recruitment of Sec4p (Medkova  et al., 2006). We now show that an evolutionarily conserved 
Rab11a-Rab8a module along with Myo5B functions in umbrella 
cells to modulate stretch-induced DFV exocytosis. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
DFV exocytosis is dependent on the Myo5B motor protein </p>

<p>We previously identified Rab11a as a modulator of DFV exocytosis 
(Khandelwal et al., 2008), and hence our initial goal was to identify 
molecules that acted downstream of this GTPase to promote DFV 
fusion. A well-known effector of Rab11a is the Myo5 motor protein, 
which promotes long-range as well as local actin-based movements 
(Lapierre et al., 2001; Volpicelli et al., 2002; Wakabayashi et al.,  2005; Varthakavi et al., 2006; Nedvetsky et al., 2007; Swiatecka- Urban et al., 2007; Provance et al., 2008; Chu et al., 2009; Roland  et al., 2011; Schuh, 2011; Xu et al., 2011). Despite the actin depen-
dence of apical exocytosis and apical endocytosis in umbrella cells 
(Lewis and de Moura, 1982; Yu et al., 2009; Khandelwal et al., 2010), 
a cortical actin cytoskeleton is reported to be absent from the apical 
pole of the umbrella cell (Romih et al., 1999; Wang et al., 2008). In 
our studies we observed that the amount of actin staining is variable 
at this surface (Acharya et al., 2004), prompting us to explore differ-
ent fixation protocols. We found that a critical factor was fixation at 
37°C, and at this temperature a meshwork of actin was found at the 
apical surface (Figure 1A). The cortical actin cytoskeleton was more 
apical than, and distinct from, an apical meshwork of cytokeratins, 
which was previously shown to encase clusters of DFVs (Figure 1A; </p>

<p>FIGURE 1: Presence of a subapical actin cytoskeleton in umbrella 
cells and expression of Myo5B in rat uroepithelium. (A) Distribution of 
cytokeratin 20 (CK20), the phalloidin-labeled actin cytoskeleton, and 
ToPro3-labeled nuclei (Nu) in cross-sectioned uroepithelium. Middle, 
arrows indicate the position of the umbrella cell apical membrane, and 
intermediate cells are marked with filled circles. (B) RT-PCR detection 
of Rab8a, Rab8b, Myo5A, and Myo5B message in rat uroepithelium. 
(C) Distribution of endogenous Myo5B in uroepithelium. Arrows point 
to the apical surface of the umbrella cell layer, and the first layer of 
intermediate cells is marked with filled circles. Right, inset, a 
magnified view of the boxed region in the parent image file. In some 
sections, Myo5B expression was also detected in cells within the 
lamina propria, examples of which are marked with an asterisk. 
(D, E) Colocalization of Myo5B with UP3a (D) or Rab11a (E). The 
epithelium in D and E more stretched than that in C. </p>

<p>Volume 24 April 1, 2013 </p>

<p>Rab network in umbrella cell exocytosis | 1009 </p>

<p>Marker </p>

<p>M X colocalization 
coefficient </p>

<p>M Y colocalization 
coefficient </p>

<p>Myo5B (X) + 
UP3a (Y) </p>

<p>0.70 ± 0.02 
0.74 ± 0.02 </p>

<p>Myo5B (X) + 
Rab11a (Y) </p>

<p>0.52 ± 0.02 
0.50 ± 0.02 </p>

<p>Myo5B-tail (X) + 
Rab11a (Y) </p>

<p>0.84 ± 0.01 
0.76 ± 0.01 </p>

<p>Myo5B-tail (X) + 
UP3a (Y) </p>

<p>0.96 ± 0.01 
0.84 ± 0.01 </p>

<p>Myo5B-tail (X) + 
TGN-38 (Y) </p>

<p>0.21 ± 0.02 
0.40 ± 0.06 </p>

<p>Myo5B-tail (X) 
and Rab8 (Y) </p>

<p>0.04 ± 0.01 
0.23 ± 0.07 </p>

<p>Myo5B-tail (X) 
and Rabin8 (Y) </p>

<p>0.06 ± 0.03 
0.38 ± 0.14 </p>

<p>Rab11a (X) + 
Rab8 (Y) </p>

<p>0.57 ± 0.02 
0.43 ± 0.03 </p>

<p>AUM (X) + 
Rab8 (Y) </p>

<p>0.54 ± 0.02 
0.53 ± 0.03 </p>

<p>Rab8 (X) + 
Rabin8 (Y) </p>

<p>0.70 ± 0.02 
0.75 ± 0.02 </p>

<p>Rab11 (X) + 
Rabin8 (Y) </p>

<p>0.64 ± 0.06 
0.89 ± 0.07 </p>

<p>Myo5b (X) 
and nuclei (Y) </p>

<p>0.07 ± 0.02 
0.05 ± 0.01 </p>

<p>As a negative control we performed colocalization of Myo5B and nuclei, which 
showed only a limited degree of colocalization. Data are mean ± SEM; n ≥ 6 
random sections. AUM, asymmetric unit membrane. </p>

<p>TABLE 1: Manders' colocalization coefficients M X and M Y for the 
indicated pair of markers. </p>

<p>transduction efficiency was &gt;80%. When expressed exogenously, 
the cargo-binding domains of myosin motors generate a domi-
nant-negative phenotype that is marked by clustering of the mo-
tor and its select cargoes within the cell cytoplasm (Lapierre et al.,  2001; Volpicelli et al., 2002; Wakabayashi et al., 2005; Chu et al.,  2009; Roland et al., 2011; Xu et al., 2011). These characteristics 
were apparent when the size and distribution of endogenous 
UP3a, Rab11a, and TGN-38 in umbrella cells were compared with 
cells expressing GFP-tagged Myo5B-tail (compare Figure 2A to 
Figure 2, B-D). The transduced samples contained large, vesicu-
lar-appearing, Myo5B-tail-positive clusters that showed extensive 
colocalization with UP3a or Rab11a (Table 1). In contrast to Rab11a 
and UP3a, the non-Myo5B cargo protein TGN-38 showed signifi-
cantly less colocalization with the Myo5B-tail (p &lt; 0.5; Figure 2D 
and Table 1). Furthermore, when cross sections of GFP-(control) 
or GFP-Myo5B-expressing cells were examined by transmission 
electron microscopy, only the latter showed clusters of DFVs, 
which appeared smaller than vesicles observed in control cells 
(Figure 2E). Stacks of Golgi appeared in proximity to, but distinct 
from, the clustered DFVs when cells were examined by electron 
microscopy (Figure 2E). 
To determine whether Myo5B modulated stretch-induced exo-
cytosis, we transduced umbrella cells with GFP-(control) or Myo5B-
tail-encoding adenoviruses and exposed the isolated bladders to 
experimental filling (i.e., stretch). As a measure of exocytosis, we 
monitored changes in capacitance (C T ; where 1 μF ≈ 1 cm 
2 of sur-
face area), which increase in response to stretch and show good 
concordance with other measures of exocytosis (Truschel et al.,  2002; Khandelwal et al., 2008; Yu et al., 2009). Myo5B-tail caused a 
significant decrease in stretch-induced changes in C T compared 
with control tissues (Figure 3A). The importance of Myo5B was also 
shown by experiments in which umbrella cells were transduced with 
both Myo5B-tail and human growth hormone, which is packaged 
into DFV and secreted in response to bladder filling (Kerr et al.,  1998; Khandelwal et al., 2008). In these studies, Myo5B-tail caused 
a significant ∼70% decrease in growth hormone release after 2 h of 
filling the bladders (Figure 3B). </p>

<p>Rab8a acts with Rab11a to regulate DFV exocytosis </p>

<p>Our next goal was to examine whether Rab11a worked in 
conjunction with Rab8 to promote DFV exocytosis. Reverse tran-
scription (RT)-PCR confirmed the expression of Rab8a/b in the 
uroepithelium (Figure 1B). Because we could not find an Rab8a-
or Rab8b-selective antibody for use in our studies, we used an 
antibody that recognizes both isoforms of this GTPase. Thus, 
when describing the localization of Rab8, we do not make a dis-
tinction between its two isoforms. Rab8 was associated with 
punctate vesicular structures at the apical pole of the cell that 
colocalized with UPs (Figure 4, A and B, and Table 1). We also 
observed Rab8-positive vesicles that were localized in the bottom 
half of the umbrella cell (Figures 4A and 5F). These likely repre-
sent Rab8-positive vesicular intermediates involved in other traf-
ficking events such as transport of newly synthesized proteins to 
the basolateral cell surface (Huber et al., 1993). When umbrella 
cells were transduced with the GFP-tagged, dominant-negative 
mutant Rab8aT 22 N (DN-Rab8a), there was a significant decrease 
in stretch-induced changes in C T (Figure 4C). We previously re-
ported that changes in C T were not observed in quiescent tissues 
not exposed to stretch (Truschel et al., 2002). However, expres-
sion of dominant-active RFP-tagged Rab8a-Q 67 L (DA-Rab8a) 
caused a significant increase in C T above stretched or unstretched 
control tissues (Figure 4D). This last phenotype was similarly </p>

<p>Both Myo5A and Myo5B mRNA expression were detected in the 
uroepithelium (Figure 1B). Because Myo5B is a well-known effector 
of Rab11a (Lapierre et al., 2001; Volpicelli et al., 2002; Wakabayashi  et al., 2005; Varthakavi et al., 2006; Nedvetsky et al., 2007; Swiatecka- Urban et al., 2007; Provance et al., 2008; Chu et al., 2009; Roland  et al., 2011; Schuh, 2011; Xu et al., 2011), we focused on this iso-
form. Its expression was confirmed by immunofluorescence analysis, 
which showed that endogenous Myo5B localized to punctate vesic-
ular elements, reminiscent of DFV, just underneath the apical do-
main of the umbrella cells. Myo5B was also observed in the upper 
cytoplasm of the first layer of intermediate cells (Figure 1C), which 
also have DFVs (Apodaca, 2004), and in cells in the underlying lam-
ina propria (examples are marked with an asterisk in Figure 1C). The 
association of Myo5B with DFV was confirmed by showing that 
Myo5B colocalized with the DFV cargo molecule UP3a (Figure 1D; 
see Table 1 for colocalization coefficients). Myo5B also colocalized, 
but to a somewhat lesser extent, with the DFV marker protein Rab11a 
(Figure 1E and Table 1). 
As further evidence of an interaction between Myo5B and 
DFV, we transduced umbrella cells in situ using an adenovirus ex-
pressing the C-terminal cargo-binding domain of Myo5B fused to 
green fluorescent protein (GFP; Myo5B-tail; Lapierre et al., 2001). 
In situ transduction primarily targets the umbrella cell layer 
(Khandelwal et al., 2008), and in the present experiments the </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>observed when dominant-active, GFP-tagged Rab11a-S 20 V 
(DA-Rab11a) was expressed (Figure 5A; Khandelwal et al., 2008). 
Whereas this increase was measured in excised tissue, voiding in 
vivo is accompanied by a rapid and complete recovery of all 
added membrane (Khandelwal et al., 2010). Thus any DA-Rab8a 
(or Rab11a)-induced increase in umbrella cell surface area would 
likely be counteracted at each cycle of voiding. 
Next we determined whether Rab11a and Rab8a acted in the 
same network to regulate stretch-induced exocytosis. If true, we 
reasoned that DN-Rab11a should impair DA-Rab8a-stimulated 
exocytic events and that DN-Rab8a should inhibit DA-Rab11a-
dependent increases. Indeed, this is what we observed (Figure 5A). 
We were unable to evaluate the effects of expressing both 
DN-Rab8a and DN-Rab11a on exocytosis, as this caused severe 
defects in transepithelial resistance. Because these experiments do 
not resolve which GTPase acts upstream of the other, we performed 
the following analysis. First, we observed that expression of GFP-
tagged DN-Rab11a resulted in a reduction in the subapical accu-
mulation and apparent intensity of Rab8-positive vesicles (Figure 
5B). In contrast, expression of DN-Rab8a did not appear to impair 
the apical localization or apparent intensity of Rab11a-positive 
DFVs (Figure 5C). These results are consistent with the possibility 
that Rab11a functions upstream of Rab8, possibly by recruiting </p>

<p>FIGURE 2: Expression of Myo5B-tail clusters DFVs. (A) Localization of endogenous UP3a, Rab11a, or TGN-38 in 
uroepithelial tissues. (B-D) Rat bladders were transduced with an adenovirus encoding GFP-tagged Myo5B-tail, the 
bladder tissues were excised and stained, and the localization of the MyoVb-tail and endogenous UP3a (B), Rab11a (C), 
or TGN-38 (D) was assessed. (E) Ultrastructure of umbrella cells transduced with GFP (left) or GFP-tagged Myo5B-tail 
(middle and right). The boxed region in the middle is magnified in the image to the right. The positions of DFVs and 
Golgi stacks are indicated. </p>

<p>FIGURE 3: Expression of Myo5B-tail impairs stretch-induced 
exocytosis. (A) Umbrella cells were transduced in situ with 
adenoviruses expressing GFP (control) or GFP-tagged Myo5B-tail. 
The excised bladders were mounted in Ussing stretch chambers 
and either left in a quiescent state (no stretch) or subjected to 
stretch at t = 0. Changes in capacitance (C T ), normalized to the 
starting value, were recorded. Data are mean ± SEM (n ≥ 6). Values 
significantly different from control are indicated with an asterisk. 
(B) Umbrella cells were transduced with adenoviruses encoding 
human growth hormone (hGH) alone, hGH and GFP, or hGH and 
Myo5B-tail. The bladders were then filled, and the release of hGH 
into the bladder lumen was quantified as described in Materials and 
Methods. Data are mean ± SEM (n ≥ 6). Values significantly different 
from control are indicated with an asterisk. </p>

<p>Volume 24 April 1, 2013 </p>

<p>Rab network in umbrella cell exocytosis | 1011 </p>

<p>possibility that Rabin8 was recruited to DFVs by Rab11a. This effect 
was not observed in cells expressing DN-Rab8a (Figure 6E). Expres-
sion of GFP alone did not alter the distribution of Rabin8 (Figure 6F). 
Next we examined the effects of expressing wild-type GFP-tagged 
Rabin8, which we predicted would activate Rab8a and like DA-
Rab8a would stimulate exocytosis. Expression of GFP-tagged wild-
type Rabin8 had no significant effect in the absence of stretch but 
significantly increased exocytosis in stretched tissues (Figure 6G). 
We also expressed a mutant GFP-tagged Rabin8 (Rabin8-L 196 A/ 
F 201 A; Rabin8-AA), which lacks Rab8 GEF activity and is believed to 
act in a dominant-negative manner to suppress Rab8 activation 
(Park et al., 1997; Bossu et al., 2000). Expression of Rabin8-AA had 
no effect on the distribution of Rab8, or for that matter of Rab11a or 
Myo5b (Figure 6, H-J), but like wild-type Rabin8 caused a significant 
stimulation of stretch-induced exocytosis (Figure 6K). This stimula-
tion was reversed at later time points if Rabin8-AA was coexpressed 
with DN-Rab8a (Figure 6K), indicating that the Rabin8-AA-mediated 
increase in exocytosis was at least partially the result of Rab8a-
dependent exocytosis. We were unable to assess the effect of co-
expressing DN-Rab11a and Rabin8-AA, as this combination caused 
a large decrease in transepithelial resistance. Taken together, these 
results indicate that Rabin8 is recruited to DFVs by Rab11a, where it 
apparently modulates stretch-induced exocytosis in a manner that is 
independent of its GEF activity. </p>

<p>Relationship between Myo5B and Rab8a-and Rab11a-
dependent DFV exocytosis </p>

<p>To determine the relationship of Myo5B to the Rab11a-Rab8 net-
work, we first examined the effects of coexpressing the Myo5B-tail </p>

<p>Rab8 to DFVs or by modulating Rab8-positive DFV accumulation at 
the apical pole of the umbrella cell. Expression of GFP alone did not 
affect the localization of either Rab8 or Rab11a (Figure 5, B and C). 
To further examine the relationship between the Rab8-and 
Rab11a-positive vesicles and the apical membrane, we performed 
additional localization studies. In addition to finding Rab8-positive 
DFVs that were also Rab11a positive (Figure 5D and Table 1), we 
also observed a pool of Rab8-positive vesicles that appeared to be 
closer to the apical pole of the cell and thus nearer to the apical 
plasma membrane. This was more apparent when we compared the 
distribution of Rab11a and Rab8 to the cytokeratin meshwork. 
Whereas Rab11a-positive DFVs were mostly found within the net-
work (Figure 5E), those subapical DFVs that were only Rab8 positive 
were observed outside the cytokeratin meshwork and thus in closer 
proximity to the apical plasma membrane than Rab11a-positive 
DFVs (Figure 5F). Unfortunately, we could not find an antibody com-
bination that allowed us to examine the position of Rab8/Rab11a-
positive vesicles relative to the cytokeratin meshwork. The proximity 
of Rab8-positive DFVs to the apical membrane is further evidence 
that Rab8 may function downstream of Rab11a. 
Ciliogenesis and apical lumen formation are both dependent on 
the Rab11a-dependent recruitment of Rabin8, a GEF that promotes 
activation and recruitment of Rab8a to Rab11a-positive vesicles 
(Hattula et al., 2002; Bryant et al., 2010; Knodler et al., 2010). In um-
brella cells, Rabin8 appeared in a subapical, punctate distribution 
(Figure 6A) and colocalized with Rab11a-or Rab8-positive DFVs 
(Figure 6, B and C, and Table 1). Furthermore, we observed that 
expression of DN-Rab11a caused endogenous Rabin8 to appear 
scattered throughout the cytoplasm (Figure 6D), consistent with the </p>

<p>FIGURE 4: Rab8 is associated with DFVs and modulates their exocytosis. (A) Endogenous Rab8 expression in the 
uroepithelium. Actin was labeled with phalloidin, and nuclei were labeled with ToPro-3. (B) Colocalization of Rab8 and 
UPs. The latter were labeled with an antiserum that recognize multiple UP species. (C, D) C T was measured in umbrella 
cells transduced with GFP (control), GFP-labeled DN-Rab8a, or RFP-labeled DA-Rab8a in the absence or presence of 
stretch. Data are mean ± SEM (n ≥ 4). Values significantly different from control are indicated with an asterisk. Control 
data are reproduced from Figure 3A. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>FIGURE 5: Rab8a acts downstream of Rab11a to modulate DFV exocytosis. (A) Umbrella cells were transduced with 
GFP (control) or with the indicated constructs. The percentage change in C T was monitored in unstretched, quiescent 
bladders and recorded. Data are mean ± SEM (n ≥ 4). Values significantly different from control are indicated with an 
asterisk. The control, no-stretch data in Figure 3A are reproduced in A. (B) Effect of expressing GFP-tagged DN-Rab11a 
(top) or GFP alone (bottom) on Rab8 localization in umbrella cells. (C) Umbrella cells were transduced with GFP-tagged 
DN-Rab8a (top) or GFP alone (bottom), and the localization of Rab11a was examined in cross sections of bladder tissue. 
(D) Colocalization of endogenous Rab8 and Rab11a in the uroepithelium. (E, F) Distribution of Rab11a (E) or Rab8 (F) 
and the apical cytokeratin network labeled with an antibody to CK20. Nuclei were labeled with an anti-lamin B receptor 
antibody. </p>

<p>Volume 24 April 1, 2013 </p>

<p>Rab network in umbrella cell exocytosis | 1013 </p>

<p>FIGURE 6: Localization of Rabin8 and effects of expressing wild-type (WT), GFP-tagged Rabin8, or Rabin8-AA on 
exocytosis. (A) Localization of endogenous Rabin8, actin, and nuclei in the rat uroepithelium. (B, C) Colocalization of 
endogenous Rabin8 with Rab11a (B) or Rab8 (C). The tissue in B and C is more stretched than that in A. (D-F) Bladders 
were transduced in situ with adenoviruses encoding GFP-tagged DN-Rab11 (D), GFP-tagged DN-Rab8a (E), or GFP 
alone (F) and the endogenous distribution of Rabin8 assessed. (G) Bladders transduced in situ with GFP alone (control) 
or GFP-tagged Rabin8 were mounted in Ussing chambers and then left in a quiescent state (no stretch) or stretched. 
The percentage change in C T is reported. Data are mean ± SEM (n ≥ 4). Values significantly different from control are 
indicated with an asterisk. Control data are reproduced from Figure 3A. (H-J) Localization of endogenous Rab8 (H), 
Rab11a (I), or Myo5B (J) in issue transduced with GFP-tagged Rabin8-AA. (K) Umbrella cells were transduced with 
viruses encoding GFP, GFP-tagged Rabin8-AA, or both GFP-tagged Rabin8-AA and DN-Rab8a. The bladders were 
stretched at t = 0. The percentage change in C T is reported. Data are mean ± SEM (n ≥ 4). Values significantly different 
from control are indicated with an asterisk. The control, stretch data are reproduced from Figure 3A. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>with Rab10, also impaired exocytosis (Figure 7B). In contrast, the 
Myo5B-tail-QLYC, which cannot interact with Rab8a, failed to block 
stretch-induced exocytosis (Figure 7B), indicating that Myo5B may 
be acting downstream of this GTPase. Consistent with the latter 
possibility, we measured some overlap between Myo5B and Rab8 
(Figure 7C and Table 1) and also noted that, like Rab8, a population 
of Myo5B-positive vesicles extended beyond the cytokeratin matrix 
and were in close apposition to the plasma membrane (Figure 7D). 
However, other studies indicated that the interplay between 
Myo5B and Rab8a was more complex than a simple one-on-one 
interaction. First, as noted previously, there was a population of 
Rab11a-positive DFVs that were also positive for Myo5B (Figure 1E). 
Furthermore, expression of the Myo5B-tail caused Rab11a-positive 
vesicles to cluster (Figure 2C). Second, the subapical distribution of 
Myo5B was not obviously affected by expression of DN-Rab8a </p>

<p>with either DA-Rab8a or DA-Rab11a. We observed that Myo5B-tail 
impaired the ability of these mutants to stimulate increases in DFV 
exocytosis (Figure 7A), indicating that Myo5B acted within the same 
network as Rab11a and Rab8a. Next we sought to determine which 
GTPase acted upstream of Myo5B to promote DFV exocytosis. We 
expressed mutant Myo5B cargo-binding domains that cannot form 
interactions with either Rab8a, or Rab10, or Rab11a (Figure 7B; 
Roland et al., 2011). Myo5B does not interact with Rab8b (Roland  et al., 2007). In the simplest case, for example, when Myo5B acts 
solely downstream of Rab11a, we expected that wild-type Myo5B-
tail (or mutants lacking the Rab8a or Rab10 interaction sites) would 
inhibit exocytosis, whereas a mutant lacking the Rab11a interaction 
site (Myo5B-tail-YEQR) would not. Surprisingly, Myo5B-tail-YEQR 
inhibited these trafficking events (Figure 7B). Likewise, Myo5B-tail-
∆D exon , which lacks the D exon of the protein and does not interact </p>

<p>FIGURE 7: Rab11a and Rab8a act together with Myo5B to regulate DFV exocytosis. (A) Umbrella cells were transduced 
with GFP alone (control) or GFP-tagged DA-Rab8a or DA-Rab11a in the presence or absence of GFP-tagged Myo5B-
tail. The percentage change in C T was monitored in isolated quiescent bladders. Data are mean ± SEM (n ≥ 4). Values 
significantly different from control are indicated with an asterisk. DA-Rab8a, no stretch, DA-Rab11a, no stretch, and 
control, no stretch are reproduced from Figures 4D, 5A, and 3A, respectively. (B) Umbrella cells were transduced with 
GFP (control) or the indicated GFP-tagged Myo5B-tail mutant. The percentage change in C T was recorded for bladder 
tissue mounted in Ussing stretch chambers and subjected to stretch. To aid comparisons, the control, stretch data from 
Figure 3A are reproduced. Data are mean ± SEM (n ≥ 5). Values significantly different from control are indicated with an 
asterisk. (C, D) Colocalization of endogenous Myo5B with Rab8 (C) or CK20 (D). (E) Effect of expressing GFP-tagged 
DN-Rab8a on the distribution of Myo5B. (F) Umbrella cells were transduced with virus encoding GFP-tagged Myo5B-
tail. The distributions of Rab8 and GFP-tagged Myo5B-tail are shown. </p>

<p>Volume 24 April 1, 2013 </p>

<p>Rab network in umbrella cell exocytosis | 1015 </p>

<p>2002; Veranic and Jezernik, 2002). DFVs must then move through 
the subapical actin cytoskeleton, which we describe in this study, 
before soluble N-ethylmaleimide-sensitive factor attachment pro-
tein receptor (SNARE)-dependent fusion with the apical membrane 
(Born et al., 2003). 
Because Rab11a does not colocalize with the umbrella cell TGN 
(Khandelwal et al., 2008) and Rab11a-positive DFVs are generally 
encased within the subapical cytokeratin cytoskeleton, we hypoth-
esize that Rab11a acts subsequent to DFV release from the TGN 
and may be important in modulating vesicle transit through the cy-
tokeratin meshwork and the initial aspects of the subapical actin 
network (Figure 8). In addition, Rab11a likely fosters DFV maturation 
by recruiting the downstream Rab8a GTPase. The mechanism by 
which Rab11a recruits Rab8a in umbrella cells is unknown. Whereas 
Rabin8 is apparently recruited to DFVs downstream of Rab11a, it is 
unlikely to be the relevant Rab8 GEF because its overexpression 
stimulates exocytosis irrespective of its GEF activity. How it does so 
is unclear, but it is possible that the amount of Rabin8 is normally 
limiting and overexpression potentiates interactions with binding 
partners, which positively regulate the Rab11a-Rab8a pathway in 
umbrella cells (independent of Rabin8's GEF activity). Alternatively, 
the Rabin8-interacting proteins may act as negative regulators of 
exocytosis, and binding to Rabin8 relieves this inhibition. Although 
the target of Rabin8 in DFV exocytosis is unknown, studies reported 
interactions between Rabin8 and Rab3a, Rheb, SSX2, ad Sec15 
(Brondyk et al., 1995; de Bruijn et al., 2002; Parkhitko et al., 2011;  Feng et al., 2012). Finally, if we assume a Rab cascade is operative, 
then after its recruitment, Rab8a is likely to enlist a Rab11a GAP, the 
identity of which is unknown but may include putative Rab11a GAPs 
described in other studies (Fukuda, 2011). Although a Rab cascade </p>

<p>(Figure 7E). Furthermore, Rab8-positive vesicles showed only a 
small degree of colocalization with Myo5B-tail-induced clusters 
(Figure 7F; Manders' coefficient M Y = 0.23 ± 0.07), and almost no 
colocalization was measured when the intensities of the Myo5B-tail 
clusters were compared with those for Rab8 (M X = 0.04 ± 0.01; 
Table 1). However, we did note that Rab8-positive DFVs appeared 
dispersed and fragmented under these conditions. Similar results 
were obtained for Rabin8 (Table 1). In sum, the data indicate a role 
for Myo5B within the Rab8a/Rab11a network; however, the inter-
action is likely to be more complex than a simple recruitment of 
Myo5B by one or the other GTPase in this module. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our studies show that Rab11a, which we previously implicated in 
DFV exocytosis (Khandelwal et al., 2008), acts as a partner in a con-
nected network of proteins that also likely includes Rab8a and 
Myo5B. A Rab11-Rab8-Myo5B network has been described for the 
biogenesis of cilia and apical lumen formation (Bryant et al., 2010;  Knodler et al., 2010), and a homologous Ypt31/32p-Sec4p-Myo2p 
yeast pathway has been implicated in yeast exocytosis (Ortiz et al.,  2002; Medkova et al., 2006; Jin et al., 2011). However, the connec-
tion of these conserved pathways to regulated secretion was not 
previously appreciated. 
In ciliogenesis, in lumen formation, and in the yeast secretory 
system, the Rab11-Rab8 network is believed to be arranged as a 
"cascade" that promotes a process termed Rab conversion or matu-
ration (Rink et al., 2005; Hutagalung and Novick, 2011). During this 
conversion, Rab11 present on an upstream compartment engages a 
GEF for Rab8 (e.g., Rabin8), stimulating Rab8's conversion from an 
inactive, GDP-bound state to an active, GTP-bound state and re-
cruitment to the membrane (Knodler et al., 2010). In its GTP-bound 
state, active Rab8 recruits effector proteins to the compartment, 
modifying its membrane and further promoting vesicular move-
ments and fusion (Barr and Lambright, 2010). Effectors include spe-
cific GTPase-activating proteins (GAPs), which, when recruited by 
Rab8, promote the transformation of GTP-bound Rab11 to its GDP-
bound state, preserving compartmental identity by inactivation of 
the upstream Rab (Rivera-Molina and Novick, 2009; Barr and  Lambright, 2010; Bryant et al., 2010). Rab cascades have been de-
scribed for pathways that involve endosomes (Eitzen et al., 2000;  Rink et al., 2005; Zhu et al., 2009; Bryant et al., 2010; Poteryaev  et al., 2010), in addition to those described for the constitutive se-
cretory pathway (Ortiz et al., 2002; Morozova et al., 2006; Rivera- Molina and Novick, 2009; Starr et al., 2010; Grigoriev et al., 2011). 
Although we have not identified the relevant GAPs and GEFS in 
DFV exocytosis, the ability of DN-Rab11a to effect the distribution 
of Rab8a, but not vice versa, the differential proximity of Rab11a 
versus Rab8 vesicles to the apical plasma membrane, and the ho-
mology to similarly organized pathways are consistent with the pos-
sibility that DFV exocytosis may also be regulated by a Rab cascade. 
Additional support for this possibility is the finding that DFVs 
undergo a maturation process as they exit from the TGN and their 
lumens become increasingly acidic (Guo et al., 2009), and in rodents 
(but not humans or rabbits), a shape change occurs as DFVs transi-
tion from discoidal shaped to one that is fusiform in appearance as 
they move toward the apical pole of the cell (Hudoklin et al., 2009,  2012). Superimposed on this maturation is DFV transport to the sur-
face, which depends, in part, on a dense subapical cytokeratin net-
work, which encases the DFVs and in response to filling moves the 
enmeshed vesicles toward the apical pole of the cell as the cytok-
eratins are "pulled" from a random orientation to one that aligns 
parallel to the apical surface of the umbrella cell (Truschel et al.,   FIGURE 8: Model for hypothesized role of the Rab11a-Rab8a-Myo5B 
network in regulating DFV exocytosis. Newly synthesized DFVs exit 
the TGN, where they associate with Rab11a, which may facilitate DFV 
passage through the cytokeratin meshwork. In one scenario, Rab11a 
may promote early recruitment of the Myo5B motor. In addition, 
Rab11a stimulates DFV maturation by recruiting Rab8a to the vesicles. 
The GEF is unknown but is apparently not Rabin8, which is recruited to 
DFVs by Rab11a and may modulate exocytosis through other effector 
proteins (not shown). In turn, Rab8a recruits an unknown Rab11a GAP, 
which would terminate the Rab11a-dependent steps and maintain 
compartment identity. Myo5B may also be recruited by Rab8a, but the 
interaction is likely to be ephemeral and may be stabilized by other 
proteins, including the exocyst subunit Sec15 and SNARE proteins 
(not shown). An important function of Myo5B is to promote DFV 
transit through the subapical actin cytoskeleton before fusion. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>relationship of Myo5B to Rab11a/Rab8a-dependent DFV exocyto-
sis. Finally, Myo5A can also form interactions with Rab8, Rab11, and 
Rab27 (Roland et al., 2007; Rudolf et al., 2011), so this motor may 
also play an important role in DFV exocytosis. 
In addition to Rab11a and Rab8a, Rab27b is also reported to in-
teract with a subset of DFVs (Chen et al., 2003). Technically, Rab27b 
could act upstream or downstream of this Rab11a/8a network; how-
ever, we previously reported that there are at least two populations 
of DFVs: a preexisting pool that undergoes rapid exocytosis, and 
one that requires new protein synthesis and only slowly fuses with 
the apical membrane (Balestreire and Apodaca, 2007; Yu et al.,  2009). Therefore it is possible that Rab27b associates with one of 
these vesicle pools and Rab11a/8a with the other. This could also 
explain why none of the dominant-negative constructs we used 
gave an all-or-none response and may also speak to possible Rab 
targets of Rabin8 that may modulate the Rab11a/8a pathway. 
An important prediction of our work is that Rab/myosin motor 
networks and possibly cascades will be common to other regulated 
secretory system. Support for this proposition includes the following: 
1) Purified synaptic vesicles, insulin secretory granules, and zymogen 
granules contain 10-30 Rabs (Takamori et al., 2006; Brunner et al.,  2007; Rindler et al., 2007). Putting aside the possibility that contami-
nation with other organelles contributes to this tally, multiple, se-
quentially acting Rabs would ensure that the complex process of 
secretory granule maturation occurs in an orderly and vectorial man-
ner and that exocytosis is properly timed and of the correct duration. 
2) Exocytosis in neuroendocrine cells requires Rab3 isoforms (Fukuda,  2008; Pavlos and Jahn, 2011). However, neurons lacking expression 
of all four Rab3 isoforms only show a 30% loss of stimulated neu-
rotransmitter release (Schluter et al., 2004). Thus other Rabs, most 
likely Rab27 isoforms, are likely to be involved (Fukuda, 2008; Pavlos  and Jahn, 2011). Of interest, Rab3 and Rab27 share effectors and 
GEFs, and both act at late stages in the regulated exocytic response 
(Tsuboi and Fukuda, 2006; Handley et al., 2007; Pavlos et al., 2010;  Pavlos and Jahn, 2011). 3) Myosin motors, particularly Myo5A, are 
common requirements for regulated secretion (Rudolf et al., 2011), 
and, as noted, can promote vesicle motility as well as vesicle tether-
ing and fusion. Based on our insights into umbrella cell exocytosis, it 
is likely that Rab3 and Rab27 also form a Rab cascade or network, 
and their sequential functions will be important in modulating the 
broad array of regulated secretory pathways that depend on these 
proteins for their function (Fukuda, 2008). </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Reagents and antibodies </p>

<p>Unless specified otherwise, all chemicals were obtained from 
Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO). Polyclonal antibodies and mouse 
monoclonal 8H10 antibody to Rab11a have been described 
(Lapierre et al., 2003). Other antibodies included rabbit anti-
human growth hormone (hGH; National Hormone and Peptide 
Program, Torrance, CA) or mouse monoclonal anti-hGH (BD 
Biosciences, San Jose, CA), mouse monoclonal K8B12 antibody 
against UP3a (Truschel et al., 2002), rabbit anti-TGN-38 (Sigma-
Aldrich), rabbit anti-Myo5B (a kind gift from Irwin Arias and John 
Hammer, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD), mouse 
monoclonal anti-Rab8 (BD Biosciences), mouse anti-cytokeratin 
20 (Dako, Carpinteria, CA), goat anti-lamin B receptor (Acris, San 
Diego, CA), or rabbit anti-asymmetric unit membrane antibody 
(kindly provided by T. T. Sun, New York University, New York, NY). 
A rabbit polyclonal Rabin8/Rab3a-interacting protein antibody 
was produced as described previously (Hattula et al., 2002) or 
purchased from LifeSpan Biosciences (Seattle, WA; LS-C120290). </p>

<p>is attractive, we cannot rule out the possibility that the Rab11a-
Rab8a network we describe here may be organized in a manner 
more complex than a cascade of sequential events. 
The other player in DFV exocytosis we identified is Myo5B, which 
our studies indicate may work in conjunction with Rab8a and possi-
bly Rab11a to ensure DFV passage through the subapical cortical 
actin cytoskeleton (Figure 8). However, it is possible that Myo5B 
may function at other actin-dependent steps that precede delivery 
to the apical membrane (see later discussion). Myo5B is a well-
known effector of Rab11a (Lapierre et al., 2001; Volpicelli et al.,  2002; Wakabayashi et al., 2005; Varthakavi et al., 2006; Nedvetsky  et al., 2007; Swiatecka-Urban et al., 2007; Provance et al., 2008; Chu  et al., 2009; Roland et al., 2011; Schuh, 2011; Xu et al., 2011), but 
more recent data indicate that it can also interact with Rab8a (but 
not Rab8b) and Rab10 (Roland et al., 2007, 2011). Indeed, we 
observed colocalization between Rab11a and Myo5B, as well as 
colocalization between Myo5B and Rab8. Furthermore, Myo5B was 
associated with vesicles that were in close proximity to the plasma 
membrane. We also noted that a Myo5B-tail mutant lacking an 
Rab11a-interacting motif (Myo5B-tail-YEQR) impaired exocytosis. In 
contrast, a mutant Myo5B-tail that lacked an Rab8a-interacting 
motif (Myo5B-tail-QLYC) failed to inhibit exocytosis. In the simplest 
scenario, in which MyoVb forms an interaction with only the Rab8 
GTPase, these results would indicate that a Rab8a-Myo5B interac-
tion was critical for this process. However, interactions between 
Myo5 family motors and both Rab8 and Rab11 homologues have 
been reported in both yeast and mammalian cells (Lipatova et al.,  2008; Jin et al., 2011). Thus an additional scenario, which may better 
fit our data, is that Myo5B forms interactions with both GTPases 
(Figure 8). This would explain why a fraction of Rab11a colocalizes 
with Myo5B and why Myo5B-tail clusters Rab11a-positive DFVs. In 
this second scenario, Myo5B-tail-YEQR would inhibit DFV exocyto-
sis by perturbing the interaction between Myo5B and the down-
stream Rab8a GTPase. In contrast, expression of Myo5B-tail-QLYC, 
which retains its Rab11a-interacting motif, would primarily affect the 
upstream, Rab11a-dependent reaction, and not the downstream 
Rab8a one. On the assumption that sufficient Rab8a-positive DFVs 
were available under these conditions, their exocytosis would pro-
ceed, apparently unimpeded by expression of this mutant. 
We also observed that Rab8-positive vesicles were not efficiently 
recruited into Myo5B-induced clusters and that expression of DN-
Rab8a failed to affect the distribution of Myo5B. At first take, these 
observations appear to be inconsistent with a role for Rab8a in re-
cruiting Myo5B. However, some provisos are worth noting. First, 
expression of Myo5B-tail was not without effect, as the Rab8-posi-
tive vesicles appeared smaller and dispersed in their distribution. 
Second, in cells expressing Myo5B-tail the affinity of Rab8a for 
Myo5B may be less than that of Rab8a for other interacting proteins 
such as Myo5A (Roland et al., 2007), which is also expressed in um-
brella cells. If so, Myo5A (or other interacting partners) may "pull" 
Rab8 out of the Myo5B-induced clusters or prevent Rab8a-positive 
vesicles from being incorporated into these clusters. Additional 
Rab8a-interacting proteins include Rab11a. Furthermore, the yeast 
Myo2p motor interacts with the Sec15 subunit of the exocyst, an 
octomeric complex that may promote vesicle tethering before fu-
sion with the plasma membrane (Jin et al., 2011), and other Myo5 
motors interact with SNARE components, including syntaxins and 
vesicle-associated membrane proteins (Prekeris and Terrian, 1997;  Watanabe et al., 2005; Bond et al., 2011). Any one or combination 
of these proteins could act to effect Myo5B localization in the 
absence of Rab8a. Although our studies support an important role 
for Myo5B in DFV, additional studies are needed to understand the </p>

<p>Volume 24 April 1, 2013 </p>

<p>Rab network in umbrella cell exocytosis | 1017 </p>

<p>further stimulate DFV exocytosis and fusion. Changes in the um-
brella cell surface area were monitored by measuring C T as previ-
ously described (Khandelwal et al., 2008). </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence labeling, image acquisition, and 
measurement of colocalization </p>

<p>Bladder tissue was fixed and processed as described (Khandelwal  et al., 2008); however, the Rab8 antibody only reacted if the follow-
ing procedure was followed. After the frozen tissue was cross-
sectioned and rehydrated with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), we 
performed antigen retrieval by incubating the tissue for 7 min with 
quench buffer (20 mM glycine, pH 8.0, and 75 mM NH 4 Cl dissolved 
in PBS) containing 0.1% Triton X-100. This was followed by a 3-min 
incubation in quench buffer containing 0.05% SDS and 0.1% Triton 
X-100. The tissue was then quickly rinsed three times with PBS and 
then three times for 5 min in the same buffer. When mounting the 
tissues, we found that enhanced image quality could be obtained if 
postfixation the tissues were rinsed with 100 mM Tris, pH 8.0, and 
then treated for 1-2 min each with ascending concentrations of 
thiodiethanol (50, 75, and 97% [vol/vol]) dissolved in the same buf-
fer (Staudt et al., 2007). The samples were then mounted in 97% 
thiodiethanol/Tris buffer containing 0.01% (wt/vol) phenylenedi-
amine and stored at −20°C. The 97% thiodiethanol has the same 
refractive index as our immersion oil (1.1518). Although this solution 
worked well for proteins labeled with secondary antibodies, tetram-
ethylrhodamine isothiocyanate-phalloidin and To-Pro3 were quickly 
leached out the samples, necessitating the use of our standard 
glycerol-based mounting medium for these markers (Acharya et al.,  2004). Images were captured using an HCX PL APO 63×/numerical 
aperture (NA) 1.3 glycerol objective (Leica, Wetzlar, Germany) or a 
Leica STED 100×/NA 1.4 oil objective and the appropriate laser 
lines of a Leica TCS SP5 CW-STED confocal microscope (in normal 
confocal mode). The photomultipliers were set at 900-1200, and 
8-bit images were collected using four to eight line averages com-
bined with four to eight frame averages. Serial 0.25-μm z-sections 
were acquired. The images were imported into <rs id="software-0" type="software">Volocity 4D</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">PerkinElmer</rs>, Waltham, MA) and, after image reconstruction, 
exported as TIFF files. The contrast of the latter was corrected in 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">Photoshop</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version">CS5</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Adobe</rs>, San Jose, CA), and the composite images 
were prepared in <rs id="software-2" type="software">Adobe Illustrator</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version">CS5</rs>. 
Measures of colocalization were performed using <rs type="software">Volocity</rs> soft-
ware, and Manders' colocalization coefficients were calculated as 
previously described (Khandelwal et al., 2008). Briefly, stacks of 
dual-labeled confocal sections were imported into <rs type="software">Volocity</rs>, back-
ground noise was removed using the fine (3 × 3) median noise re-
duction filter, and a scatter plot of green and red pixel intensities 
(associated with each of the two markers in question) was generated 
using the colocalization function. A constant threshold of 40 was 
applied to both channels of the image stack, and Manders' colocal-
ization coefficients for each of two markers (M X and M Y , respec-
tively) were calculated for the entire three-dimensional image stack 
using the following equations (Manders et al., 1993): </p>

<p>M X = 
X i,colocalized </p>

<p>colocalized 
i </p>

<p>X i </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>and M Y = 
Y i, </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>Y i </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>∑ </p>

<p>∑ 
∑ </p>

<p>∑ </p>

<p>where X i is equal to the intensity of marker X at a given voxel and 
X i,colocalized = X i if the associated intensity of the other marker (Y i ) is 
above the threshold value (i.e., it colocalizes). However, X i,colocalized 
= 0 if Y i is below the threshold value (i.e., does not colocalize). Y i is 
equal to the intensity of marker Y at a given voxel and Y i,colocalized 
= Y i if X i is above the threshold value and Y i,colocalized = 0 if X i is </p>

<p>Fluorophore-or horseradish peroxidase-labeled, affinity-purified 
and minimal cross-reacting goat or donkey secondary antibodies 
were purchased from Jackson ImmunoResearch (West Grove, PA). 
Rhodamine phalloidin and TO-PRO3 were obtained from Mole-
cular Probes-Invitrogen (Grand Island, NY). </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>Urinary bladders were obtained from female Sprague Dawley 
rats (250-300 g). Rats were killed by inhalation of 100% CO 2 , fol-
lowed by a thoracotomy. All animal studies were approved by 
the University of Pittsburgh Institutional Animal Care and Use 
Committee. </p>

<p>RT-PCR </p>

<p>The uroepithelium was recovered by gentle scraping as described 
(Balestreire and Apodaca, 2007), the cells were lysed, and RNA was 
purified using the RNAqueous Micro Kit (Life Technologies, Carls-
bad, CA). RNA was treated with DNase I and cDNA generated using 
the RETROscript First Strand Synthesis Kit (Life Technologies). PCR 
was performed using Taq polymerase (Life Technologies). The prim-
ers used were as follows: Myo5A, GTG GGG CAA AAG AGA C and 
TCA GAC CCT TGC AAT GAA GCC; Myo5B, GCA GCC CAA CTC 
CTT CAG and TCA GAC TTC ATT GAG GAA CTC; Rab8a, ATG 
GCG AAG ACC TAC GAT TAC C and TCA CAG GAG ACT GCA 
CCG G; and Rab8b, ATG GCG AAG ACG TAC GAT TAT CTG and 
TCA AAG CAG AGA ACA CCG GAA G. Sequencing was used to 
confirm the identity of the PCR reaction products. </p>

<p>Preparation of adenoviruses and in situ transduction of 
umbrella cells </p>

<p>Adenoviruses expressing GFP, GFP-tagged DN-Rab11aS 25 N, DA-
Rab11aS 20 V, and hGH were described previously (Khandelwal et al.,  2008). GFP-tagged Myo5B-tail mutants showing reduced affinity 
for Rab8a (Myo5B-QLYC), Rab10 (Myo5B-∆D exon ), or Rab11a 
(Myo5B-YEQR) were described previously (Roland et al., 2011). 
Adenoviruses were made by cloning the appropriate cDNAs into 
the plasmid pAdlox. Rab8a was cloned into pAdlox, and adenovi-
ruses expressing RFP-tagged DA-Rab8aQ 67 L and GFP-tagged 
DN-Rab8aT 22 N were made by mutating Glu 67 to Lys and Ser 22 to 
Val in Rab8a-pAdlox using the QuikChange Site-Directed Mutagen-
esis Kit (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA). cDNA for human Rabin8a was 
obtained from Addgene (Cambridge, MA) and subcloned into 
pAdlox. The QuikChange Kit was then used to generate the 
Rabin8a-F 201 A/L 196 A mutant. Adenoviruses were prepared and 
purified, and bladders were transduced in situ using our previously 
described methods (Khandelwal et al., 2008). </p>

<p>Estimation of hGH secretion </p>

<p>Rat bladders were transduced in situ with adenoviruses expressing 
hGH alone or in combination with Myo5B-tail or GFP. The bladders 
were filled, and hGH released into the bladder lumen was collected 
and Western blots quantified as described (Khandelwal et al.,  2008). </p>

<p>Mounting rat bladder in Ussing stretch chambers 
and measuring C T </p>

<p>Rats were killed, and bladders were excised, cut open, and then 
mounted in a Ussing stretch chamber with the mucosal surface fac-
ing an enclosed stretch hemichamber (Khandelwal et al., 2008). 
After a 1-h period of equilibration, bladder filling was simulated by 
slowly adding Krebs buffer to the mucosal hemichamber. The cham-
ber was then sealed, and an additional solution was added to </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>below the threshold value. An M X (or M Y ) value of 1.0 indicates that 
the ratio for all X intensity values that have a corresponding Y in-
tensity (i.e., are colocalized), divided by the sum of all X intensity 
values is 100%. In contrast, a value of 0.0 indicates that there is no 
colocalization. We previously reported combinations of markers 
that had minimal colocalization (Khandelwal et al., 2008, 2010), 
and for this study we colocalized MyoVb and nuclei, which had 
minimal overlap and resulted in a coefficient that approached zero 
(see Table 1). The values for M X and M Y can be similar or not, as the 
values are intensity weighted, and in addition one marker may 
have a broader distribution than the other in the sampled region of 
the tissue. </p>

<p>Electron microscopy </p>

<p>Bladder tissue was isolated and then fixed with 2.0% (vol/vol) glu-
taraldehyde and 2% (wt/vol) paraformaldehyde in 100 mM sodium 
cacodylate buffer, pH 7.4, containing 0.5 mM MgCl 2 and 1 mM 
CaCl 2 for 60 min. The tissue was then cut into small pieces, washed 
with 100 mM sodium cacodylate, pH 7.4, cut into small blocks 
(2-5 mm in size), and then postfixed in 1.0% (wt/vol) OsO 4 and 
1.0% (wt/vol) K 4 Fe(CN) 6 , in 100 mM sodium cacodylate, pH 7.4. 
After a wash with water, the samples were en bloc stained over-
night in 0.5% (wt/vol) uranyl acetate. The tissues were then dehy-
drated in a graded series of ethanol, and after incubation in pro-
pylene oxide, embedded in the epoxy resin LX-112 (Ladd, 
Burlington, VT) and cured 2 d at 60°C. Embedded tissue was 
sectioned with a diamond knife (Diatome, Fort Washington, PA), 
and sections, silver to pale gold in color, were mounted on Butvar-
coated nickel grids, contrasted with uranyl acetate and lead cit-
rate, and viewed at 80 kV in a 100 CX electron microscope (JEOL, 
Tokyo, Japan). Images were captured using an L9C Peltier-cooled 
transmission electron microscopy camera system (Scientific Instru-
ments and Applications, Duluth, GA). Digital images were im-
ported into <rs type="software">Adobe Lightroom</rs>, and the images were processed by 
using the brightness, contrast, and clarity controls. When contrast 
was too low, adjustments to the tone curve were made to the 
whole image. Images were sharpened using a radius of 0.5, and 
luminance noise reduction was performed. The composite images 
were assembled using <rs id="software-6" type="software">Adobe Illustrator</rs> <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version">CS5</rs>. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data are reported as mean ± SEM. Statistically significant differences 
between means were determined using a two-tailed Student's t test; 
p &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. One-way analysis 
of variance, with Bonferonni's correction, was used when making 
multiple comparisons. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank T. T. Sun, Irwin Arias, and John Hammer for their kind 
gifts of antibodies. This work was supported by an American 
Heart Association Scientist Development Grant (to P.K.), National 
Institutes of Health Grants R37-DK54425, R01-DK077777, and 
P30-DK079307 (to G.A.) and R01-DK048370 and R01-DK070856 
(to J.G.), and the Cellular Physiology and Kidney Imaging Cores 
of the Pittsburgh Center for Kidney Research (P30-DK079307). </p>



<p>Volume 24 April 1, 2013 </p>

<p>Rab network in umbrella cell exocytosis | 1019 </p>



</text></tei>