<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3881473" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. [Purpose] The aim of this study was to investigate the changes in mechanical energy due to continuous 
use of a plantar flexion resistive ankle-foot orthosis (AFO) of subjects with chronic hemiplegia. [Subjects and Meth-
ods] The subjects were 5 hemiplegic patients using AFOs without a plantar flexion resistive function in their daily 
lives. We analyzed the gait of the subjects using a 3D motion capture system under three conditions: patients' use of 
their own AFOs; after being fitted with a plantar flexion resistive AFO; and after continuous use of the device. The 
gait efficiency was determined by calculating the mutual exchange of kinetic and potential energy of the center of 
mass. [Results] An increased exchange rate of the kinetic and potential energy was found for all subjects. A larger 
increase of energy exchange was shown on the non-paralyzed side, and after continuous use of the plantar flexion 
resistive AFO. [Conclusion] We found that continuous use of a plantar flexion resistive AFO increased the rate of 
mutual exchange between kinetic energy and potential energy. The change in the rate was closely related to the role 
of the non-paretic side, showing that the subjects needed a certain amount of time to adapt to the plantar flexion 
resistive AFO. 
Walking is an action with an extremely low energy cost. 
From the perspective of energy conversion of the center of 
mass (COM), the trajectory of the COM in the sagittal plane 
is similar to the motion of a pendulum, and this movement 
in known as the inverted pendulum model 1, 2) . In this model, 
kinetic energy in the direction of progress reaches its peak 
at the time of heel strike, and gradually decreases in the 
first half of the stance phase as kinetic energy is converted 
to potential energy of the COM. The potential energy shows 
its peak at the midpoint of the stance phase. During the lat-
ter half of the stance phase, when the COM goes down, po-
tential energy gradually decreases, as it is converted into 
kinetic energy. In order to achieve an efficient gait, energy </p>

<p>conversion through the efficient use of gravity is important. 
This has been shown by passive walking robots 3) achieving 
ambulation with relatively low energy cost. Although the 
free gait speed of hemiplegic patients is less than half of that 
of healthy individuals, their oxygen consumption cost is 
about 25% larger 4) . The cause of the increased energy cost 
of hemiplegic gait is closely related to the increase of ex-
ternal work by the muscles involved in moving the COM 5) . 
Furthermore, it is thought that inefficiency in the energy 
conversion described above is one of the characteristics of 
hemiplegic gait 6) . 
The rocker function proposed by Perry 7) is said to play 
an important role in reproducing the inverted pendulum 
model and achieving efficient energy conversion. A plantar 
flexion resistive ankle-foot orthosis (PF-AFO) is an AFO 
which assists the rocker function 8-10) . The PF-AFO directly 
assists the initial turnover period, and wearers also show an 
improvement in the second turnover period after continu-
ous use of the PF-AFO 11, 12) . The objective of this study was 
to investigate the change in mechanical energy of the COM 
in hemiplegic gait after continuous use of a PF-AFO. </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. 
25: 1437-1443, 2013 </p>

<p>*Corresponding author. Hirokazu Haruna (e-mail: haruna@ 
hit.ac.jp) </p>

<p>©2013 The Society of Physical Therapy Science </p>

<p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Cre-</p>

<p>ative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-</p>

<p>nd) License &lt;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/&gt;. </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. Vol. 25, No. 11, 2013 </p>

<p>
SUBJECTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>The subjects were 5 maintenance-phase hemiplegics 
who used AFOs without a plantar flexion-resistive func-
tion in their daily lives (Table 1). The participation crite-
ria for the study were: cerebrovascular disease hemiplegia 
with unilateral pathology at onset; no rehabilitation treat-
ment during the experimental period; no marked higher 
brain dysfunction or difficulty understanding commands; 
no marked limitation in joint mobility of the lower limbs or 
trunk; being able to walk unassisted; and being able to walk 
forward by means of a heel strike. The subjects received a 
thorough explanation about the study content and methods 
both orally and in writing, and their written consent to par-
ticipation was received. The study content conformed to the 
principles of the Declaration of Helsinki and received ap-
proval from the Hokkaido Institute of Technology Graduate 
School Research Ethics Committee. 
The experimental schedule was as follows. On the first 
day, a 3D-motion analysis device was used to measure the 
gait of the patients' while wearing their own AFO, and their 
gait after the first fitting of the PF-AFO. After subjects had 
consented to continuous use of the PF-AFO, the same gait 
measurements were performed after 3-4 weeks of PF-AFO 
use. Each PF-AFO was manufactured from a cast of the foot 
of each subject. 
At the first fitting, the plantar flexion movement of the 
ankle joint of the PF-AFO was confirmed in stance. After 
subjects had consented to use the PF-AFO, the amount of 
resistive moment and the initial ankle joint angle of the PF-
AFO were adjusted for each subject's condition. 
Subjects were orally instructed to "touch the ground 
with the heel of the side with paralysis first." In the mea-
surement of PF-AFO gait on the first day, sufficient walking 
practice time was provided to familiarize subjects with the 
new orthosis. Then, 3D-motion analysis was performed on 
a flat walking pathway 7.5 m in length, and 6 one-way trial </p>

<p>walks were performed under two conditions, with subjects' 
own AFOs and with the PF-AFO. Data after the fourth step 
from the start of ambulation was used in order to extract 
a steady state. The apparatus used for measurement was a 
3D-motion analysis device (VICON-Nexus, Vicon Motion 
System Inc., Ltd., Oxford, United Kingdom). Six infrared 
cameras were placed around the walking pathway. Sixteen 
reflective markers were placed on the subjects: on the left 
and right sides of the acromion, one-third of the distance 
from the greater trochanter and the anterior superior iliac 
spine, the lateral center of the knee joint cleft, the exter-
nal malleolus, the head of the fifth metatarsal, the calcaneal 
region, the anterior superior iliac spine, and the posterior 
superior iliac spine. The sampling frequency was 120 Hz. A 
seven-link segmental model was used to calculate the COM 
using the anthropometric data of typical Japanese men and 
women. 
The conversion efficiency of COM potential energy to 
kinetic energy was calculated using the method of Cavana 
et al 
13-23) . In the present study, the mechanical energy was 
calculated as described below based on the COM informa-</p>

<p>Table 1. Subject characteristics </p>

<p>Case 1 
Case 2 
Case 3 
Case 4 
Case 5 </p>

<p>Sex 
Female 
Male 
Female 
Male 
Male 
Age (years) 
33 
37 
50 
67 
65 </p>

<p>Diagnosis 
Cerebral 
Infarction </p>

<p>Cerebral 
Hemorrhage </p>

<p>Cerebral 
Hemorrhage </p>

<p>Cerebral 
Infarction </p>

<p>Cerebral 
Infarction 
Paretic Side 
Left 
Right 
Left 
Right 
Right 
Period from Onset 
(Months) 
20 
28 
124 
202 
44 </p>

<p>Lower Limb BRS 
III 
IV 
III 
III 
III 
Lower Limb FMA 
9 (41%) 
20 (91%) 
15 (68%) 
15 (68%) 
17 (77%) 
Ankle Joint MAS 
2 
1 
2 
1+ 
2 
Independence 
Supervision required 
Independent 
Independent 
Independent 
Independent 
Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>AFO with metal 
uprights </p>

<p>Plastic Leaf 
Spring </p>

<p>Plastic Leaf 
Spring </p>

<p>Plastic Leaf 
Spring </p>

<p>Plastic Leaf 
Spring 
Height (cm) 
160 
175 
151 
164 
163 
Weight (kg) 
57 
75 
51 
68 
65 </p>

<p>BRS: Brunnstrom recovery stage; FMA: Fugl-meyer assessment; MAS: Modified Ashworth scale </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Separate phases of the mechanical energy of COM </p>



<p>tion measured and calculated from the 3D-motion analysis 
data. 
In this study, mechanical energy was analyzed as four 
kinds. Thus, there were four kinds of power: the power used </p>

<p>to accelerate in the travel direction of the COM (Power-y), 
the power for lifting the COM in the vertical direction COM 
(Power-z), the power generated by muscles (Power-ext), and 
the rate of exchange of kinetic energy to potential energy </p>

<p>Table 2. Changes in gait speed </p>

<p>[m/sec] Mean (SD) 
(1)Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>(2)Before continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(3)After continuous 
use of PF-AFO 
(1)vs.(2) 
(1)vs.(3) 
(2)vs.(3) </p>

<p>Case 1 
0.39 (0.03) 
0.41 (0.05) 
0.50 (0.02) 
* 
** 
Case 2 
0.75 (0.03) 
0.76 (0.02) 
0.85 (0.04) 
** 
** 
Case 3 
0.62 (0.04) 
0.55 (0.04) 
0.69 (0.02) 
** 
** 
Case 4 
0.28 (0.02) 
0.28 (0.01) 
0.29 (0.02) 
Case 5 
0.21 (0.01) 
0.21 (0.02) 
0.25 (0.02) 
** 
** </p>

<p>*p&lt;0.05; **p&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>Table 3. Changes in Power-y </p>

<p>[W/kg] Mean (SD) 
Paretic side Elevation </p>

<p>(1)Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>(2)Before continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(3)After continuous 
use of PF-AFO 
(1)vs.(2) 
(1)vs.(3) 
(2)vs.(3) </p>

<p>Case 1 
1.4 (0.4) 
-0.2 (1.6) 
-1.8 (0.8) 
* 
Case 2 
-7.0 (3.3) 
-6.5 (2.7) 
-9.5 (2.9) 
* 
Case 3 
-0.2 (1.6) 
-2.2 (1.4) 
-2.3 (0.7) 
* 
* 
Case 4 
-0.4 (0.3) 
-0.5 (0.3) 
-0.5 (0.1) 
Case 5 
0.4 (0.2) 
0.2 (0.2) 
-0.1 (0.2) 
** 
* 
Paretic side Drop 
(1)Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>(2)Before continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(3)After continuous 
use of PF-AFO 
(1)vs.(2) 
(1)vs.(3) 
(2)vs.(3) </p>

<p>Case 1 
0.4 (0.9) 
0.9 (0.5) 
1.0 (0.6) 
Case 2 
4.3 (1.0) 
5.5 (1.6) 
6.4 (2.4) 
Case 3 
3.6 (2.7) 
3.7 (1.2) 
5.5 (1.5) 
Case 4 
-0.3 (0.1) 
0.8 (0.3) 
0.8 (0.2) 
** 
** 
Case 5 
1.1 (0.3) 
1.6 (0.5) 
1.5 (0.2) 
* 
** 
Non-paretic side Elevation 
(1)Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>(2)Before continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(3)After continuous 
use of PF-AFO 
(1)vs.(2) 
(1)vs.(3) 
(2)vs.(3) </p>

<p>Case 1 
-3.5 (0.6) 
-3.2 (0.6) 
-4.5 (0.6) 
* 
Case 2 
-7.6 (1.5) 
-9.3 (1.7) 
-13.0 (5.6) 
* 
Case 3 
-7.7 (2.6) 
-6.1 (1.2) 
-8.3 (1.2) 
* 
Case 4 
-1.1 (0.2) 
-1.1 (0.2) 
-1.5 (0.2) 
* 
* 
Case 5 
-2.0 (0.4) 
-2.1 (0.5) 
-2.1 (0.3) 
Non-paretic side Drop 
(1)Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>(2)Before continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(3)After continuous 
use of PF-AFO 
(1)vs.(2) 
(1)vs.(3) 
(2)vs.(3) </p>

<p>Case 1 
2.9 (0.3) 
3.9 (1.2) 
5.5 (0.8) 
* 
Case 2 
10.2 (1.6) 
9.3 (1.9) 
12.8 (2.1) 
* 
** 
Case 3 
6.2 (1.3) 
5.5 (1.5) 
8.1 (0.9) 
** 
** 
Case 4 
1.5 (0.1) 
1.4 (0.2) 
1.7 (0.1) 
* 
* 
Case 5 
0.4 (0.1) 
0.4 (0.1) 
0.7 (0.1) 
** 
** </p>

<p>*p&lt;0.05; **p&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. Vol. 25, No. 11, 2013 </p>

<p>
(% recovery). 
To calculate the COM energy changes during ambula-
tion, it is necessary to have information about the peak 
value of the vertical COM position (COM-Z). The motion 
of COM-Z is described by a sinusoidal curve (Fig. 1). In 
order to know the rise and fall of the inverted pendulum 
on both the paretic and non-paretic sides, it is necessary to 
know the highest and lowest points of COM-Z during gait. 
Therefore, knowledge of the range between the peak values 
of COM-Z on the paretic side and non-paretic side is neces-
sary. To find this, gait data of more than one gait cycle was 
extracted, from the heel contact of the paralyzed limb to 
the foot contact of the ipsilateral limb, to have information 
about the highest and lowest positions of the COM. To calu-
late the kinetic energy and potential energy during ambula-
tion, the kinetic energy (Ek.y) in the direction of progress of 
the body COM was calculated using Formula 1, the kinetic 
energy (Ek.z) in the vertical direction by Formula 2, the </p>

<p>potential energy (Ep) by Formula 3, the total kinetic energy 
(Ek) by Formula 4, and the total energy (Etot) by Formula 5. </p>

<p>Ek.y=1/2mVy 2 (1) </p>

<p>Ek.z=1/2mVz 2 (2) </p>

<p>Ep=mgz (3) </p>

<p>Ek=Ek.y+Ek.z (4) </p>

<p>Etot=Ek+Ep (5) </p>

<p>Were, m is the body mass, g is the acceleration due to 
gravity (9.8 m/s 2 ), Vz is the vertical velocity of COM, 
and Vy is the velocity in the direction of COM progress. </p>

<p>The external work for accelerating the COM in the di-
rection of progress was calculated using Formula 6, the </p>

<p>Table 4. Changes in Power-z </p>

<p>[W/kg] Mean (SD) 
Paretic side Elevation 
(1)Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>(2)Before continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(3)After continuous 
use of PF-AFO 
(1)vs.(2) 
(1)vs.(3) 
(2)vs.(3) </p>

<p>Case 1 
12.4 (2.7) 
14.1 (2.2) 
16.9 (0.7) 
* 
* 
Case 2 
14.6 (1.8) 
14.2 (1.7) 
15.2 (3.9) 
Case 3 
5.8 (0.8) 
7.1 (1.5) 
7.9 (1.7) 
* 
Case 4 
10.5 (1.5) 
9.9 (1.6) 
9.3 (0.8) 
Case 5 
8.6 (2.8) 
10.1 (1.9) 
12.5 (1.3) 
* 
* 
Paretic side Drop 
(1)Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>(2)Before continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(3)After continuous 
use of PF-AFO 
(1)vs.(2) 
(1)vs.(3) 
(2)vs.(3) </p>

<p>Case 1 
-5.6 (0.3) 
-6.6 (1.3) 
-6.9 (1.3) 
Case 2 
-14.5 (1.6) 
-15.8 (1.9) 
-21.7 (4.8) 
** 
** 
Case 3 
-2.5 (1.1) 
-4.7 (1.3) 
-7.4 (1.0) 
* 
** 
* 
Case 4 
-10.1 (2.5) 
-12.6 (1.5) 
-10.3 (1.1) 
* 
Case 5 
-8.2 (1.5) 
-8.7 (1.8) 
-10.4 (1.1) 
* 
Non-paretic side Elevation 
(1)Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>(2)Before continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(3)After continuous 
use of PF-AFO 
(1)vs.(2) 
(1)vs.(3) 
(2)vs.(3) </p>

<p>Case 1 
11.3 (1.6) 
11.3 (1.3) 
12.2 (0.8) 
Case 2 
23.9 (0.8) 
24.8 (2.3) 
28.0 (4.0) 
* 
* 
Case 3 
27.3 (1.7) 
25.4 (0.9) 
21.5 (1.1) 
** 
** 
Case 4 
15.4 (2.1) 
16.4 (1.1) 
14.6 (0.8) 
* 
Case 5 
19.3 (2.4) 
17.1 (1.9) 
14.7 (1.2) 
** 
* 
Non-paretic side Drop 
(1)Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>(2)Before continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(3)After continuous 
use of PF-AFO 
(1)vs.(2) 
(1)vs.(3) 
(2)vs.(3) </p>

<p>Case 1 
-19.0 (2.3) 
-18.9 (2.4) 
-22.6 (1.2) 
* 
Case 2 
-23.6 (2.2) 
-22.2 (1.6) 
-25.0 (3.1) 
* 
Case 3 
-28.8 (1.5) 
-29.3 (2.3) 
-22.9 (1.6) 
** 
** 
Case 4 
-14.6 (0.7) 
-15.5 (0.5) 
-14.9 (1.4) 
Case 5 
-18.2 (1.3) 
-17.1 (1.3) 
-17.3 (2.4) </p>

<p>*p&lt;0.05; **p&lt;0.01 </p>



<p>external work of raising the COM in the vertical direction 
against gravity by Formula 7, and the external work gener-
ated by the muscles to move the COM was calculated using 
Formula 8. </p>

<p>Wy=ΣΔEk.y (6) </p>

<p>Wz=ΣΔ (Ek.z+Ep) (7) </p>

<p>Wext=ΣΔEtot (8) </p>

<p>Were, Δ is the amount of energy increase or decrease and 
∑ is the summation of the data of Δ. </p>

<p>By dividing the external work by time, it was possible 
to determine the external power (Power-y) use to accelerate 
the COM in the direction of progress, the external power 
(Power-z) for raising the COM, and the external power 
(Power-ext) generated by the muscles. External power was 
calculated for the four phases shown in Fig. 1. </p>

<p>Conversion efficiency (%recovery 16) ) was calculated us-
ing Formula 9. </p>

<p>%recovery= (│Wy│+│Wz│-Wext) ⁄ (│Wy│+│Wz│) × 100 (9) </p>

<p>%recovery is the rate of mutual exchange of the kinetic 
energy and potential energy of the COM in walking. 
Meaning the value of %recovery in walking with effi-
cient use of gravity is high. The %recovery value was 
calculated for each phase shown in Fig. 1, and the aver-
ages of one whole gait cycle, and the stance phases of 
the paretic and the non-paretic sides were calculated. 
The data of gait speed, Power-y, Power-z, Power-ext of 
each phase, and %recovery, were compared among the 
three conditions of: gait with patients' own AFOs, with 
the PF-AFO at the first fitting, with the PF-AFO after 
continuous use. <rs id="software-0" type="software">R</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">2.8.1</rs> software was used for statistical 
analysis, and the Steel-Dwass method was applied. The 
level of significance was chosen as less than 5%. </p>

<p>Table 5. Changes in Power-ext </p>

<p>[W/kg] 
Mean (SD) 
Paretic side Elevation 
(1)Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>(2)Before continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(3)After continuous 
use of PF-AFO 
(1)vs.(2) 
(1)vs.(3) 
(2)vs.(3) </p>

<p>Case 1 
13.9 (3.1) 
13.9 (3.8) 
15.1 (1.0) 
Case 2 
7.6 (2.9) 
7.7 (3.5) 
5.8 (3.5) 
Case 3 
5.5 (1.0) 
4.9 (1.9) 
5.6 (2.2) 
Case 4 
10.1 (1.6) 
9.4 (1.3) 
8.8 (0.7) 
Case 5 
9.0 (2.8) 
10.3 (1.9) 
12.4 (1.3) 
* 
* 
Paretic side Drop 
(1)Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>(2)Before continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(3)After continuous 
use of PF-AFO 
(1)vs.(2) 
(1)vs.(3) 
(2)vs.(3) </p>

<p>Case 1 
-5.3 (0.8) 
-5.7 (1.6) 
-5.8 (1.6) 
Case 2 
-10.3 (2.0) 
-10.4 (1.2) 
-15.3 (3.0) 
** 
** 
Case 3 
1.1 (14.9) 
-1.0 (1.2) 
-1.9 (1.4) 
Case 4 
-10.5 (2.5) 
-11.9 (1.6) 
-9.6 (1.0) 
* 
Case 5 
-7.1 (1.4) 
-7.1 (1.3) 
-8.9 (1.1) 
* 
* 
Non-paretic side Elevation 
(1)Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>(2)Before continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(3)After continuous 
use of PF-AFO 
(1)vs.(2) 
(1)vs.(3) 
(2)vs.(3) </p>

<p>Case 1 
7.8 (1.9) 
8.0 (1.1) 
7.7 (0.7) 
Case 2 
16.3 (1.2) 
15.5 (2.5) 
15.0 (2.9) 
Case 3 
19.6 (1.4) 
19.3 (1.6) 
13.2 (1.1) 
** 
** 
Case 4 
14.3 (1.9) 
15.3 (1.1) 
13.1 (0.8) 
* 
Case 5 
17.4 (2.2) 
15.0 (1.9) 
12.6 (1.2) 
** 
* 
Non-paretic side Drop 
(1)Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>(2)Before continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(3)After continuous 
use of PF-AFO 
(1)vs.(2) 
(1)vs.(3) 
(2)vs.(3) </p>

<p>Case 1 
-16.2 (2.6) 
-14.9 (2.2) 
-17.1 (1.4) 
Case 2 
-11.8 (1.8) 
-13.0 (1.2) 
-12.2 (4.0) 
Case 3 
-21.9 (1.4) 
-23.8 (2.4) 
-14.8 (0.9) 
** 
** 
Case 4 
-13.0 (0.7) 
-14.2 (0.5) 
-13.2 (1.3) 
* 
Case 5 
-17.8 (1.2) 
-16.7 (1.2) 
-16.6 (2.3) </p>

<p>*p&lt;0.05; **p&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. Vol. 25, No. 11, 2013 </p>

<p>
RESULTS </p>

<p>No significant changes were noted in gait speed for gait 
with the PF-AFO on the first day in all cases, but a signifi-
cant increase was seen in four cases after continuous use of 
the PF-AFO (Table 2). An increase was also seen in Power-y 
in all cases in the non-paretic side downward phase after 
continuous use of the PF-AFO (Table 3). Power-z showed 
a significant change in all phases of both the paretic and 
non-paretic sides after continuous use of the PF-AFO in 
3 cases (Table 4). The results of Power-ext showed some 
changes, but no clear trend was noted (Table 5). The aver-
age %recovery for one gait cycle after the continuous use 
of the PF-AFO increased in all cases. The comparison of 
the averages of the non-paretic and paretic stance phases, 
revealed increases in %recovery in the non-paretic stance 
phases of four cases, and in the paretic stance phases of two 
cases (Table 6). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The most interesting result of this study was the increase 
of %recovery in one gait cycle gait after the continuous use 
of the PF-AFO. Since the PF-AFO was worn only on the 
paretic side, it had no direct effect on the non-paretic side. 
However, comparing the averages of the non-paretic stance 
and paretic stance, four out of five subjects showed large 
increases in the stance phase of the non-paretic side. Fur-</p>

<p>thermore, only small changes were found just after PF-AFO 
adaptation, but many changes were found after its continu-
ous use. 
The present results happened because loading on the par-
alyzed limb became smooth due to the use of the PF-AFO, 
eliminating the need for excessive control of the non-paret-
ic side 24) . The increase of Power-y in the downward phase 
on the non-paretic side of all cases, indicates that subjects 
made steps without decreasing the speed of the COM in the 
late stance phase of the non-paretic side. Furthermore, the 
results suggest that the immediate effects at the time of first 
use of the PF-AFO were few, but many changes were found 
after its continuous use, indicating that time was necessary 
to learn to control the non-paretic side in order to adapt to 
the PF-AFO 11, 12, 24) . 
Taken together, the use of the PF-AFO increased COM 
energy conversion efficiency. This change was seen not 
only on the paretic side with the AFO, but also on the non-
paretic side, and a certain amount of time was needed to 
adapt the PF-AFO. 
A limitation of this study was that the time series of me-
chanical energy was not investigated in detail. Also, some 
parameters increased after 3-4 weeks use of the PF-AFO, 
but of the exact timing of these changes was not investi-
gated. A detailed study of the time series of the adaptation 
to the PF-AFO, and the development of an exercise program 
to facilitate early adaptation of the PF-AFO will be neces-
sary in a future study. </p>

<p>Table 6. Changes in %recovery </p>

<p>[%] 
Mean (SD) 
Average of the one cycle gait 
(1)Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>(2)Before continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(3)After continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(1)vs.(2) 
(1)vs.(3) (2)vs.(3) </p>

<p>Case 1 
22.3 (5.7) 
28.1 (7.1) 
34.8 (2.5) 
* 
Case 2 
55.1 (6.9) 
56.0 (4.9) 
62.3 (3.9) 
* 
* 
Case 3 
43.8 (14.5) 
49.5 (5.4) 
59.5 (6.9) 
* 
* 
Case 4 
10.2 (0.3) 
12.5 (1.1) 
15.5 (1.1) 
* 
** 
** 
Case 5 
11.6 (1.3) 
14.2 (2.3) 
15.0 (1.3) 
** 
Average of the paretic stance phase 
(1)Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>(2)Before continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(3)After continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(1)vs.(2) 
(1)vs.(3) (2)vs.(3) </p>

<p>Case 1 
7.7 (9.5) 
17.1 (15.8) 
22.6 (7.5) 
Case 2 
53.2 (14.6) 
55.8 (9.9) 
60.4 (7.4) 
Case 3 
43.2 (21.9) 
64.1 (12.0) 
65.1 (13.6) 
Case 4 
3.6 (2.2) 
10.5 (2.3) 
12.0 (1.5) 
** 
** 
Case 5 
11.5 (2.2) 
15.5 (1.8) 
13.8 (1.6) 
** 
Average of the non-paretic stance phase 
(1)Subject's own 
Orthosis </p>

<p>(2)Before continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(3)After continuous 
use of PF-AFO </p>

<p>(1)vs.(2) 
(1)vs.(3) (2)vs.(3) </p>

<p>Case 1 
37.0 (5.8) 
39.1 (4.2) 
46.5 (4.5) 
Case 2 
57.0 (3.0) 
56.3 (3.3) 
64.2 (6.3) 
** 
** 
Case 3 
44.4 (11.3) 
35.0 (3.0) 
54.0 (2.5) 
** 
Case 4 
16.9 (1.1) 
14.5 (1.7) 
19.1 (1.3) 
* 
** 
Case 5 
11.6 (1.4) 
12.9 (3.0) 
16.2 (1.8) 
** 
* </p>

<p>*p&lt;0.05; **p&lt;0.01 </p>





</text></tei>