<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3955898" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Background and aims Current creatine-based 
criteria for defining acute kidney injury (AKI) are 
validated in general hospitalised patients but 
their application to cirrhotics (who are younger 
and have reduced muscle mass) is less certain. 
We aimed to evaluate current definitions of AKI 
(acute kidney injury network (AKIN) criteria) in a 
population of cirrhotic patients and correlate this 
with outcomes. 
Methods We prospectively identified patients 
with AKI and clinical, radiological or histological 
evidence of cirrhosis. We compared them with 
a control group with evidence of cirrhosis and 
no AKI. 
Results 162 cirrhotic patients were studied 
with a mean age of 56.8±14 years. They were 
predominantly male (65.4%) with alcoholic liver 
disease (78.4%). 110 patients had AKI: 44 stage 
1, 32 stage 2 and 34 stage 3. They were well 
matched in age, sex and liver disease severity 
with 52 cirrhotics without AKI. AKI was 
associated with increased mortality (31.8% vs 
3.8%, p&lt;0.001). Mortality increased with each 
AKI stage; 3.8% in cirrhotics without AKI, 
13.5% stage 1, 37.8% stage 2 and 43.2% stage 
3 ( p&lt;0.001 for trend). Worsening liver disease 
(Child-Pugh class) correlated with increased 
mortality: 3.1% class A, 23.6% class B and 
32.8% class C ( p=0.006 for trend). AKI was 
associated with increased length of stay: 
median 6.0 days (IQR 4.0-8.75) versus 
16.0 days (IQR 6.0-27.5), p&lt;0.001. Multivariate 
analysis identified AKI and Child-Pugh classes B 
and C as independent factors associated with 
mortality. 
Conclusions The utility of AKIN criteria is 
maintained in cirrhotic patients. 
Decompensated liver disease and AKI appear to 
be independent variables predicting death in 
cirrhotics. </p>

<p>INTRODUCTION 
Mortality from liver disease is increasing. </p>

<p>1   Key drivers of this increase are the rising 
prevalence of alcoholic liver disease, viral 
hepatitis and fatty liver disease. 
2 Liver 
disease is now the fifth highest cause of 
death in the UK, with a 25% increase in 
mortality between 2001 and 2009. 
3 Renal 
dysfunction is a common complication of 
cirrhosis and confers a poor prognosis. </p>

<p>4   Renal dysfunction occurs in 20% of 
patients with cirrhosis admitted to hos-
pital, often linked with other complica-
tions of cirrhosis such as variceal bleeding 
and spontaneous bacterial peritonitis. 
5 In 
a systematic review of 118 studies, the 
presence of renal dysfunction was a 
powerful predictor of death in decompen-
sated cirrhosis. 
6 Hepatorenal syndrome 
(HRS) has an extremely poor prognosis 
with a median survival time of 3 months, </p>

<p>7   falling to just 1 month in those with 
untreated Type 1 HRS. 
8 Serum creatine is 
one of three variables comprising the 
model of end-stage liver disease score 
which is widely used in predicting short 
term mortality in allocating priority for 
orthotopic liver transplantation. </p>

<p>9   Many definitions of renal dysfunction in 
liver disease are based on creatine thresh-
olds, such as those used in HRS classifica-
tion. 
10 This approach does not account for 
individual variation in baseline renal func-
tion or that a significant decline in renal 
function can occur with much smaller 
changes in creatine. There has also been a 
lack of standardisation in defining these 
thresholds. 
10-13 A more evolved approach 
to defining acute renal dysfunction has 
come with the widespread acceptance of 
consensus criteria for acute kidney injury </p>

<p>LIVER </p>

<p>Scott RA, et al. Frontline Gastroenterology 2013;4:191-197. doi:10.1136/flgastro-2012-100291 </p>



<p>(AKI) that provide a method of diagnosing and describing 
the severity of renal dysfunction based on individualised 
changes in serum creatine and urine output. The Kidney 
Disease: Improving Global Outcomes (KDIGO) diagnos-
tic criteria are the most current, 
14 combining the earlier 
acute kidney injury network (AKIN) 
15 and Risk of renal 
dysfunction; Injury to the kidney; Failure of kidney func-
tion; Loss of kidney function; and End-stage kidney 
disease (RIFLE) classifications. 
16 The use of these criteria 
has been validated in a variety of settings including the 
critically ill and general hospitalised patients. </p>

<p>17-21   Importantly, these criteria recognise that even a small 
decline in renal function is associated with poor out-
comes. 
22 AKI therefore encompasses a wide spectrum of 
illness in a large number of patients from an abrupt rise in 
serum creatine of only 26.4 mmol/l (0.3 mg/dl) to critic-
ally unwell patients requiring renal replacement therapy. 
However, there are several reasons why creatine-based 
definitions of AKI may perform differently in patients 
with liver disease. Cirrhotics are younger and have 
reduced muscle mass compared with other hospitalised 
patients. 
23 Severe hyperbilirubinaemia gives a falsely 
low value of serum creatine with chemical rather than 
the enzymatic measurement techniques. 
24 These factors 
may result in lower than expected baseline creatine 
values in this patient group relative to glomerular filtra-
tion rate. 
25 A small number of studies have begun to 
evaluate the current AKI criteria in cirrhotics. Some 
have focused on specific groups, such as those in inten-
sive care or decompensated patients with ascites, which 
may limit their generalisability. 
26-28 The only prospect-
ive trial using robust AKIN definitions in a cirrhotic 
population was performed in four tertiary centres in the 
USA, but did not include a control group. 
29 These data 
may differ from European experience with a low pro-
portion of compensated cirrhosis (only 2% had Child-
Pugh class A disease), high incidence of hepatitis C 
(44%) and high rates of inpatient dialysis (24%). We 
therefore sought to add to these studies by further 
evaluating the utility of current diagnostic criteria for 
AKI in patients with cirrhosis and examine their associ-
ation with patient outcomes. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Setting </p>

<p>The Royal Derby Hospital is a 1139-bed teaching hos-
pital that provides all major medical and surgical spe-
cialities (excepting neuro-and cardiothoracic surgery). </p>

<p>The liver unit is a tertiary referral centre, serving a 
population of 700 000. There is a central chemical 
pathology laboratory for all inpatient and outpatient 
samples. A compensated kinetic Jaffe method with an 
inter-assay coefficient of variance of 2.3% at 96 mmol/ 
l (Roche P-analyser, Roche Diagnostics, West Sussex, 
UK) was used to measure all serum creatine values 
throughout the study period (normal creatine range 
70-120 mmol/l). </p>

<p>Detection of AKI </p>

<p>We have devised and implemented a real-time elec-
tronic reporting system for AKI that identifies all cases 
of AKI across our hospital. This is based on the AKIN 
diagnostic criteria, which are summarised in table 1. </p>

<p>15   This system has been in clinical use since 2010 and 
its diagnostic accuracy has been established. A full 
description of the system is available elsewhere. </p>

<p>30   This system also allows prospective data collection for 
all cases of AKI at our centre. A daily electronic report of 
all AKI episodes is automatically generated that details 
patient location (community vs hospital-acquired), 
patient age and baseline creatine. These data are supple-
mented by the highest AKI stage, last serum creatine in 
stay (to assess renal recovery), length of hospital stay and 
whether the patient survived to hospital discharge. 
Comorbidity data (based on ICD-10) coding and 
Charlson score are also included. Approval to use anon-
ymised data in this way was obtained from the National 
Information Governance Board and a Local Research 
Ethics Committee waived requirement of individual 
patient consent. </p>

<p>Identification of patients with cirrhosis </p>

<p>All patients under the care of the Gastroenterology 
Department were selected from the prospectively 
identified hospital-wide population of those with AKI 
in the period 1 June 2010-31 October 2011. These 
patients were then manually screened to identify those 
with cirrhosis. Cirrhosis was diagnosed on the basis of 
any clinical (eg, decompensated chronic liver disease), 
radiological (eg, coarse liver, splenomegaly, presence 
of varices), or laboratory parameters (eg, prolonged 
international normalised ratio (INR) low platelets) 
and/or histological evidence from liver biopsy when 
available. </p>

<p>29 31   A control group of patients with cirrhosis without 
AKI were retrospectively identified from the </p>

<p>Table 1 Classification/staging system for AKI according to AKIN </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>AKI stage 
Serum creatine criteria 
Urine output criteria </p>

<p>AKI stage 1 
Increase in serum creatine ≥0.3 mg/dl or increase to ≥150%-200% from baseline 
Urine output&lt;0.5 ml/kg/h for &gt;6 h 
AKI stage 2 
Increase of serum creatine to &gt;200%-300% from baseline 
Urine output&lt;0.5 ml/kg/h for &gt;12 h 
AKI stage 3 
Increase of serum creatine to &gt;300% from baseline 
OR serum creatine ≥4.0 mg/dl after a rise of at least 0.5 mg/dl 
OR treatment with renal replacement therapy </p>

<p>Urine output&lt;0.3 ml/kg/h for 24 h 
OR anuria for 12 h </p>

<p>AKI, acute kidney injury; AKIN, acute kidney injury network. </p>

<p>LIVER </p>



<p>Scott RA, et al. Frontline Gastroenterology 2013;4:191-197. doi:10.1136/flgastro-2012-100291 </p>

<p>admission register to the liver unit over the same time 
period. Sequential patients were manually screened 
for evidence of cirrhosis in the same way as previously 
detailed. Patients were included only once in the 
control group regardless of the number of admissions 
during the 18-month period. Data were taken exclu-
sively from the initial admission. 
Child-Pugh score and class were retrospectively 
established for all cirrhotic patients included in the 
study. Where possible, this was calculated from elec-
tronic records within 3 months of the acute admis-
sion. If not possible, it was established from the 
results nearest to normal during the admission. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Parametric data are presented as mean±SD and non-
parametric data as median (inter-quartile range). χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Test was used to compare categorical data and t test 
or Mann-Whitney test to compare continuous data 
depending on whether data were parametric or non-
parametric. A Kaplan-Meier survival curve was calcu-
lated based on mortality data censored for admission. 
Binary logistic regression was used to test significant 
univariate associations with inhospital mortality. 
p Values of&lt;0.05 were considered significant. All ana-
lyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> V.<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">19</rs>. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Cirrhotic population </p>

<p>A total of 162 patients with cirrhosis were included, 
110 with AKI and 52 controls. Of the 110 patients 
with cirrhosis who sustained AKI, 44 patients (40%) 
had AKI stage 1, 32 patients stage 2 (29.1%) and 34 
(30.9%) stage 3. The mean age of the cirrhotic popula-
tion was 56.8±13.6 years. Patients were predomin-
antly male (65.4%) and 78.4% had liver disease caused 
by alcohol. The remainder of patients had fatty liver 
disease (6.2%), cryptogenic cirrhosis (5.5%), auto-
immune hepatitis (3.7%), Hepatitis C (HCV) (1.9%), 
primary biliary cirrhosis (PBC) (1.9%) and other 
causes (2.5%). A total of 50 patients (30.9%) had 
biopsy-proven cirrhosis; 6.2% were recorded as having 
pre-existing chronic kidney disease. The mean baseline 
creatine was 78.4±29.4 mmol/l. </p>

<p>AKI versus non-AKI in patients with cirrhosis </p>

<p>Patient characteristics were similar when comparing 
those with and without AKI, as summarised in table 2. 
There was no significant difference between ages of the 
groups (59.6±13.4 vs 50.9±12.2, p=0.842), sex 
(62.7% vs 71.2% male, p=0.292) or aetiology of liver 
disease (79.1% vs 76.9% alcohol, p=0.754). There 
was also comparable severity of liver disease ( p=0.135 
for trend) and similar comorbidities between the 
groups. The only differences were the prevalence of 
diabetes (29.1% in the AKI group vs 11.5% in the 
control group, p=0.014) and mean baseline creatine </p>

<p>value (85.5±28.8 mmol/l in the AKI group vs 
64.7±25.6 mmol/l in the control group, p=0.03). </p>

<p>Factors associated with outcomes </p>

<p>The presence of AKI in the cirrhotic population was 
associated with significantly increased mortality, 
31.8% versus 3.8% in the control group ( p&lt;0.001), 
summarised in figure 1. We also observed that mortal-
ity increased as AKI became more severe, as shown in 
figure 2. Inhospital mortality rates were 13.5% in AKI 
stage 1, 37.8% in AKI stage 2 and 43.2% in AKI stage 
3 (χ 
2 for trend, p&lt;0.001). A Kaplan-Meier survival 
curve shows inhospital mortality associated with each 
stage of AKI (figure 3). This difference was significant 
between AKI stages 1 and 2 ( p=0.001), but not 
between AKI stages 2 and 3 ( p=0.793). AKI was 
also associated with an increased length of stay: 
median 6.0 days (IQR 4.0-8.75) versus 16.0 days 
(IQR 6.0-27.5), p&lt;0.001. 
There was also an association between mortality 
and increasing severity of liver disease as measured by 
Child-Pugh class. Mortality rates were 3.1% in class 
A, 23.6% in class B and 32.8% in class C (χ 
2 for 
trend=0.006) (figure 4). </p>

<p>Table 2 Comparisons between cirrhotic groups: cirrhotics with 
acute kidney injury (AKI) and cirrhotic controls without AKI </p>

<p>Factor </p>

<p>Cirrhotics 
with AKI </p>

<p>Cirrhotic controls 
without AKI 
Significance </p>

<p>AKI stage 0 
AKI stage 1 
AKI stage 2 
AKI stage 3 </p>

<p>-
44 (40%) 
32 (29.1%) 
34 (30.9%) </p>

<p>52 (100%) 
-
-
-
Severity of liver disease 
Mean CPS 
8.87 
8.29 
p=0.364 
CP A 
17 (15.5%) 
15 (28.8%) 
p=0.135 
CP B 
52 (47.2%) 
21 (40.4%) 
CP C 
41 (37.1%) 
16 (30.8%) 
Comorbidities 
Diabetes 
32 (29.1%) 
6 (11.5%) 
p=0.014 
Lung disease 
9 (8.2%) 
7 (13.5%) 
p=0.293 
IHD 
5 (4.5%) 
0 (0%) 
p=0.118 
Acute MI 
5 (4.5%) 
0 (0%) 
p=0.118 
CCF 
5 (4.5%) 
1 (1.9%) 
p=0.409 
CKD 
8 (7.3%) 
2 (3.8%) 
p=0.398 
Stroke 
4 (3.6%) 
0 (0%) 
p=0.164 
Connective 
tissue disease </p>

<p>2 (1.8%) 
0 (0%) 
p=0.328 </p>

<p>Dementia 
0 (0%) 
1 (1.9%) 
p=0.145 
Peptic ulcer 
disease </p>

<p>3 (2.7%) 
1 (1.9%) 
p=0.758 </p>

<p>Peripheral 
vascular disease </p>

<p>3 (2.7%) 
1 (1.9%) 
p=0.758 </p>

<p>Cancer 
3 (2.7%) 
0 (0%) 
p=0.229 
Diabetic 
complications </p>

<p>0 (0%) 
1 (1.9%) 
p=0.145 </p>

<p>AKI, acute kidney injury; CPS, Child-Pugh score; CP A, Child-Pugh A, B 
and C etc; IHD, ischaemic heart disease; MI, myocardial infarction; 
CCF, congested cardiac failure; CKD, chronic kidney disease. </p>

<p>LIVER </p>

<p>Scott RA, et al. Frontline Gastroenterology 2013;4:191-197. doi:10.1136/flgastro-2012-100291 </p>



<p>We compared survivors and non-survivors to iden-
tify additional factors associated with inhospital mor-
tality. Previous myocardial infarction (1.6% vs 8.1%, 
p=0.044), peripheral vascular disease (0.8% vs 8.1%, 
p=0.012), connective tissue disease (0% vs 5.4%, 
p=0.009) and the presence of pre-existing chronic 
kidney disease (CKD) (4% vs 13.5%, p=0.035) were 
associated with increased mortality. Other comorbid 
conditions were not associated with death, including 
diabetes (21.6% vs 29.7%, p=0.305) and baseline 
creatine (median 77.8±31.4 vs 80.3±22.0 mmol/l, 
p=0.181). In our population, there was no difference 
in age between survivors and non-survivors (median 
55.9±13.9 vs 59.8±12.3 years, p=0.193). 
Binary logistic regression including all significant 
univariate associations revealed that the only factors 
independently associated with increased mortality 
were AKI, Child-Pugh class B and Child-Pugh class C 
(Nagelkerke r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=0.256, Hosmer and Lemeshow test 
for goodness of fit p=0.567). Table 3 shows this 
model in full. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION  This study demonstrates that current creatine-based 
definitions of AKI retain their utility in cirrhotic </p>

<p>patients, with the presence and increasing severity of 
AKI strongly associated with inhospital mortality. Our 
results add to the relatively small number of studies 
examining the use of such criteria in cirrhotic patients 
and provide an important comparison between those 
with and without AKI. 
Previous criteria for identifying renal dysfunction, 
such as the HRS definitions, 
10 use arbitrary creatine 
thresholds which fail to incorporate an individual's 
baseline renal function and exclude smaller changes in 
creatine values despite their impact on patient 
outcome. Newer AKI criteria, such as the AKIN or 
KDIGO classifications, have several advantages. Small 
but significant changes in an individual's baseline creat-
ine are included to improve sensitivity; these criteria 
also describe the severity of AKI depending on the 
magnitude of creatine rise (or degree of oliguria). 
These criteria are now widely accepted and have been 
validated in a variety of clinical scenarios, 
14 but the dif-
ferences in creatine profile seen in liver patients </p>

<p>Figure 4 Mortality with increasing severity of liver disease by 
Child-Pugh class. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Kaplan-Meier survival curve showing inhospital 
mortality in cirrhotics with and without acute kidney injury (AKI) 
(censored at 120 days). </p>

<p>Figure 1 Overall mortality of cirrhotics with and without 
(control group) acute kidney injury (AKI). </p>

<p>Figure 2 Mortality across acute kidney injury (AKI) stages. </p>

<p>LIVER </p>



<p>Scott RA, et al. Frontline Gastroenterology 2013;4:191-197. doi:10.1136/flgastro-2012-100291 </p>

<p>mandate that these criteria are examined specifically in 
this patient group. To date, there have been a small 
number of studies that have attempted this. Carvalho 
et al 
32 retrospectively studied 91 patients with cirrhosis 
and ascites identifying AKI within 48 h of hospital 
admission. The majority of patients had mild renal dys-
function (91% had stage 1 AKI). Patients with AKI had 
a hospital mortality rate of 52.7%. Presence of AKI 
conferred an OR of 2.6 for hospital mortality but 
quantifying the risk by stage was limited by the small 
numbers of patients with more severe AKI. Belcher 
et al 
29 prospectively studied 192 hospitalised cirrhotic 
patients with AKI in four centres in the USA. AKIN cri-
teria were used to identify AKI, with 50 (26%) patients 
with AKI stage 1, 47 (24%) stage 2 and 95 (49%) stage 
3. Baseline creatine was robustly defined as the most 
recent stable measurement prior to admission for the 
index hospitalisation within 1 year or if they had at 
least 5 days of stable values within the normal creatine 
range following admission. Overall mortality was 26% 
and severity of AKI was independently associated with 
mortality (adjusted OR=3.8, 95% CI 1.3 to 11.1), but 
the presence of AKI itself was not assessed as there was 
no control group without AKI. Tsient et al 
31 prospect-
ively studied a total of 91 patients with cirrhosis and 
ascites recruited from hepatology outpatient clinics. 
Patients had bloods performed at 4-6 weekly intervals 
and AKI was defined by AKIN criteria if two samples 
within 48 h were available or if a 50% increase in 
serum creatine from the baseline visit was observed. If 
identified, AKI was treated with volume expansion of 
albumin (1 g/kg) for two consecutive days. In all, 49 
patients suffered with 82 episodes of AKI, and again 
mortality was higher in those with AKI. 
Our results add to these studies and confirm that AKI 
(as per AKIN criteria) is associated with mortality in 
patients with cirrhosis, even after adjustment for severity 
of liver disease and comorbid conditions. Although com-
parisons between studies are difficult, mortality rates in cir-
rhotics with AKI do appear to be higher than other 
reports of generalised hospital patients with AKI, suggest-
ing that this patient group is particularly vulnerable when 
AKI develops. 
17 30 For contextual reference, the overall 
mortality of general hospitalised patients with AKI at our 
centre from September 2010 to August 2012 was 21.2% 
(stage 1, 15.2%; stage 2, 32.3%; stage 3, 33.5%). Despite 
potential differences between the demographics of USA 
and European cirrhotics, we observed mortality rates 
similar to those reported by Belcher et al. 
29 Although high 
(at over 30%), our observed mortality rates are lower than </p>

<p>some historic studies. 
26 27 This may reflect our inclusion 
of patients with less severe AKI, an effect of using current 
diagnostic criteria; mortality rose to above 40% in those 
with AKI stage 3. However, it is important to recognise 
that even small acute rises in serum creatine are significant, 
with mortality in our patients with AKI stage 1 substan-
tially elevated as compared with controls. The implications 
of relatively small changes in serum creatine often remain 
underappreciated in clinical practice, which may be partly 
addressed by wider usage of current AKI definitions. 
Our observed mortality rate in the control group 
was low (3.8%). It is, however, similar to that 
reported in other studies of cirrhotic patients with 
ascites who did not sustain AKI. 
31 This may reflect 
the relatively young age of patients with cirrhosis, the 
low prevalence of comorbidity or a less severe acute 
illness without factors that may precipitate AKI. 
Comparison between the groups with and without 
AKI showed they were well matched in terms of age, 
sex, cause and severity of liver disease. There were few 
differences in renal risk profile between the control 
group and those with cirrhosis and AKI, with the only 
differences in baseline creatine and diabetes. Although 
diabetes was not associated with increased mortality, it 
is possible that its presence may be a risk factor for 
developing AKI. The higher baseline creatine may 
reflect a gradual increase in creatine which may occur 
as a prodrome of renal dysfunction in patients with cir-
rhosis. 
33 Particular attention should therefore be paid 
defining baseline creatine in this group. In general 
patients, avoiding the use of results from the 7 days 
prior to hospital admission may avoid the use of falsely 
high reference creatine values, 
34 but in cirrhotic 
patients it is conceivable that this period should be 
extended due to the indolent increase sometimes in 
serum creatine prior to the acute presentation. 
The modified Child-Turcotte-Pugh score is widely 
used as a simple descriptive or prognostic indicator in 
patients with cirrhosis. 
35 36 Unlike the model of end-
stage liver disease score 
37 it does not include a marker 
of renal dysfunction, although it could be argued that 
the inclusion of bilirubin, ascites and encephalopathy 
are potential surrogate markers of renal injury. 
38 It is 
not surprising that increasing mortality was associated 
with increasing severity of liver disease in a stage-
dependent manner as measured by the Child-Pugh 
class. It does, however, support that the scores were 
credibly calculated with a valid methodology. 
Our study does have some potential weaknesses. The 
methodology for electronic identification of AKI 
employed by this study has been previously validated in a 
generalised hospital population with a false negative rate 
of 0.2%. 
30 However, in a population of patients with cir-
rhosis who are younger with lower than average baseline 
serum creatine values, it is possible that the initial step, 
which depends on a comparison with an estimated creat-
ine value, may miss a small number of cases of AKI stage 
1. In addition, the data presented are limited to </p>

<p>Table 3 Multivariate analysis of factors independently 
associated with mortality </p>

<p>Factor 
Significance 
HR 
95% CIs </p>

<p>Acute kidney injury 
0.02 
10.6 
2.4 to 47.0 
Child-Pugh B 
0.04 
8.1 
1.0 to 65.4 
Child-Pugh C 
0.016 
13.1 
1.6 to 106.0 </p>

<p>LIVER </p>

<p>Scott RA, et al. Frontline Gastroenterology 2013;4:191-197. doi:10.1136/flgastro-2012-100291 </p>



<p>information collected routinely as standard of care either 
in patient notes or on electronic record. Comorbidity 
data are based upon International Classification of 
Diseases -version 2010 (ICD-10) coding and therefore 
limited to these definitions. Thus, we are unable to 
report the impact of other variables, such as circulatory 
dysfunction, infection or inflammation. Further studies 
could evaluate whether changing AKIN creatine thresh-
olds would be of added benefit in cirrhotics. 
In conclusion, this study shows that AKI, as defined 
by the AKIN diagnostic criteria, is associated with 
increased mortality in patients with cirrhosis in a stage-
dependent manner. Severe liver disease and AKI appear 
to be independent variables in predicting death in cir-
rhotic patients. The current methods for defining AKI 
appear to have clinical utility in patients with cirrhosis, 
and their wider use may help with improved recognition 
and earlier intervention for AKI, which has particular 
relevance in this vulnerable group. </p>

<p>What is already known about this subject </p>

<p>▸ Renal dysfunction in cirrhosis is common and confers 
a poor prognosis. 
▸ Previous definitions of renal dysfunction in patients 
with cirrhosis (eg, HRS definitions) have relied on cre-
atinine thresholds. 
▸ AKIN criteria recognise that a small decline in renal 
function is associated with poor outcomes in general 
hospitalised patients. </p>

<p>What this study adds </p>

<p>▸ AKI, as defined by the AKIN diagnostic criteria, is 
associated with increased mortality in patients with 
cirrhosis in a stage-dependent manner. 
▸ Mortality rates in cirrhotics with AKI appear to be 
higher than other reports of generalised hospital 
patients with AKI. 
▸ Severe liver disease and AKI appear to be independ-
ent variables in predicting death in cirrhotic patients. </p>

<p>How might it impact on clinical practice in the fore-
seeable future </p>

<p>▸ AKIN criteria appear to have clinical utility in patients 
with cirrhosis. 
▸ Their wider use may help with improved recognition 
and earlier intervention for AKI which should improve 
patient outcomes. 
▸ Further work is needed to understand the mechanism 
and risk factors in developing renal dysfunction in 
patients with cirrhosis. </p>

<p>Contributors NS and AA conceived the study and overall 
supervised conduct of the study. RS and NS contributed to 
study design, data collection, analysis and interpretation. NK 
contributed to data collection. CM contributed to data 
interpretation. All authors contributed to the drafting, revising 
of the article and approved the final version of the manuscript. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Ethics approval National Information Governance Board. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally 
peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in 
accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non 
Commercial (CC BY-NC 3.0) license, which permits others to 
distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, 
and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-
commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/ </p>



<p>LIVER </p>



<p>Scott RA, et al. Frontline Gastroenterology 2013;4:191-197. doi:10.1136/flgastro-2012-100291 </p>



<p>LIVER </p>

<p>Scott RA, et al. Frontline Gastroenterology 2013;4:191-197. doi:10.1136/flgastro-2012-100291 </p>



</text></tei>