<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3500846" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:32+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Plant viral expression vectors are advantageous for high-throughput functional characterization studies of 
genes due to their capability for rapid, high-level transient expression of proteins. We have constructed a 
series of tobacco mosaic virus (TMV) based vectors that are compatible with Gateway technology to enable 
rapid assembly of expression constructs and exploitation of ORFeome collections. In addition to the 
potential of producing recombinant protein at grams per kilogram FW of leaf tissue, these vectors facilitate 
either N-or C-terminal fusions to a broad series of epitope tag(s) and fluorescent proteins. We demonstrate 
the utility of these vectors in affinity purification, immunodetection and subcellular localisation studies. We 
also apply the vectors to characterize protein-protein interactions and demonstrate their utility in screening 
plant pathogen effectors. Given its broad utility in defining protein properties, this vector series will serve as 
a useful resource to expedite gene characterization efforts. </p>

<p>Thus, TRBO vector has great potential for use in high-throughput 
plant proteomic studies. A major drawback, however, is that it relies 
on traditional restriction digestion and ligation based cloning for 
target gene insertion, hampering rapid gene cloning for high 
throughput functional analysis of proteins. Additionally, the cur-
tailed polylinker region of TRBO vector with only three unique 
restriction enzyme sites (PacI, NotI, and AvrII) poses another hurdle </p>

<p>in devising cloning strategies for large cDNAs, genomic DNA inserts 
or inserts carrying translational fusions. To overcome the limitations 
of restriction and ligation-based cloning, a modified version of the 
TRBO vector was developed 12 to exploit ligation-independent clon-
ing (LIC) 13 ; however, an obvious downside of the LIC strategy is that 
sub-cloning or re-cloning is not efficient due to the inherent need for 
PCR re-amplification and, thus, sequencing of the inserts after each 
procedure 14 . A strict requirement for correct T4 DNA polymerase 
treatment of the insert and vector is another disadvantage of the LIC 
method. 
The time requirements and limitations of traditional cloning pro-
cedures have been significantly reduced through development of the 
Gateway cloning system 15 which employs site-specific recombina-
tion to enable inter-molecular transfer of DNA fragments between 
plasmid vectors. Gateway 'entry' clones of full-length ORFs for sev-
eral organisms are currently available through public repositories 
and commercial suppliers. Alternatively, they can be assembled by 
topoisomerase-mediated cloning 16 or conventional cloning proce-
dures, both technically amenable due to the generally small size of 
entry vectors. To complement application of ORFs, the genomic 
coding regions of genes, encompassing the complete repertoire of 
potential splice variants thereby enabling broader analysis of gene 
function than possible using an ORF, can also be rapidly incorpo-
rated into the Gateway system using a bacteriophage-based homo-
logous recombination system (recombineering) 17 . The Gateway 
vector system has been employed in large-scale plant genomic pro-
jects and compatible vectors have been developed for many applica-
tions, including ectopic overexpression, promoter-reporter fusions, 
RNA interference, complementation analysis, gene stacking, and 
affinity purification using epitope tags 17-21 . Epitope tagging has 
proved to be an indispensable way for analyzing protein func-
tions 22-24 by enabling specific detection of recombinant proteins 
using commercially available antibodies, thereby eliminating the 
need for generating antibodies for each protein to be studied. 
While several non-viral Gateway compatible binary expression vec-
tors incorporating epitope tags have been described in the literat-
ure 18,20 , they are limited by lacking the autonomous replication and 
high transient expression capability of viral expression vectors. 
Examples of incorporating Gateway recombination sites into 
TMV, potato virus X and tobacco rattle virus based expression vec-
tors have been reported 25-27 ; however, with the single exception of an 
N-terminal GFP fusion variant 26 , the design of these vectors do not 
support fusion of target proteins with epitope tags or multiple fluor-
escent proteins, thus limiting their utility in comprehensive func-
tional analysis studies. 
Here we describe construction and functional validation of a 
unique set of viral expression vectors that combine the favourable 
attributes of the TRBO vector with Gateway technology, epitope-
tagging and fluorescent protein-fusion systems to enable rapid and 
efficient cloning of gene inserts and production of native or recom-
binant proteins at very high yields within a short time frame. We 
further demonstrate the utility of these vectors for protein produc-
tion, affinity purification, immunodetection, subcellular localisation 
and analysis of protein-protein interactions as well as plant patho-
genic effector screening. </p>

<p>Results 
Vector design and features. A major caveat with currently available 
viral expression vectors which depend on traditional in vitro cloning 
procedures is the inefficiency and laboriousness of cloning ORFs 
of gene candidates in multiple formats (e.g. epitope-tag variants). 
To enable rapid cloning of gene inserts and achievement of high 
level protein expression in a short time, we constructed a set of 
TMV-based Gateway compatible (TMV-Gate) expression vectors 
that facilitate production of native as well as epitope-or fluore-
scent protein-tagged variants (Figure 1). The backbone of these </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Schematic illustration of the TMV-Gate vectors. (A) </p>

<p>Expression vectors facilitating N-terminal tagging of target protein with 
various epitope tags, including single-or triple-repeats of HA, FLAG or c-
myc, as well as 2xStrep-tag II-6xHis-Xpress epitope. (B) Expression vector 
facilitating C-terminal tagging of target protein with 2xStrep-tag II-6xHis 
epitope tags. (C)Expression vectors facilitating C-terminal tagging of 
target protein with epitope tagged fluorescent proteins, including YFP-
3xFLAG or CFP-3xHA. The illustrated vector features include: LB, T-DNA 
left border; RB, T-DNA right border; 35S Prom, CaMV 35S promoter; 35S 
term, CaMV 35S terminator; RdRP, RNA-dependent RNA polymerase; 
MP, movement protein; bent arrow, coat protein promoter; attR1 and 
attR2, Gateway recombination sites; Cm R , chloramphenicol resistance 
marker; ccdB, E. coli DNA gyrase inhibitor; asterisk in pTK251, 
enterokinase protease recognition site; asterisk in pMW399, 3C protease 
recognition site; YFP, yellow fluorescent protein; CFP, cyan fluorescent 
protein. The epitope tag regions in the map are enlarged 1:20 for 
readability. DNA sequences for the vectors have been deposited at 
GenBank with accession numbers as follows: pMW388, JX971627; 
pSK101, JX971619; pSK102, JX971620; pSK103, JX971621; pSK104, 
JX971622; pSK105, JX971623; pSK106, JX971624; pTK251, JX971625; 
pMW399, JX971626; pMW390, JX971628; and pMW391, JX971629. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 874 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00874 </p>

<p>
Destination vectors is derived from TRBO vector 11 which includes a 
full-length cDNA clone of TMV U1 strain modified to lack the coat 
protein (CP) coding sequence and which is placed adjacent to the 
cauliflower mosaic virus (CaMV) 35S promoter in a T-DNA binary 
vector. All of the Destination vectors described in this study use the 
attR1/R2 RfA Gateway cassette which is linked in-frame to various 
epitope tags and/or fluorescent proteins and is cloned adjacent to the 
coat protein promoter of the TRBO vector. These assemblies were 
confirmed by restriction digests (data not shown) followed by DNA 
sequencing of the junctions between the TRBO vector, RfA cassette 
and epitope tag/fluorescent proteins. 
The structure of the T-DNA region of various TMV-Gate express-
ion vectors is illustrated in Figure 1. In planta expression of the viral 
replicons in all eleven TMV-Gate vectors is driven by the CaMV 35S 
promoter (Figure 1). The TMV-Gate vector that allows expression of 
native proteins is designated as pMW388. TMV-Gate vectors that 
allow addition of N-terminal epitope tags, such as HA, 3xHA, FLAG, 
3xFLAG, c-myc, 3xc-myc and 2xStrep-tag II-6xHis-Xpress epitope 
tag are designated as pSK101-pSK106 and pTK251, respectively. The 
TMV-Gate vector that allows addition of a C-terminal 2xStrep-tag 
II-6xHis epitope tag is designated as pMW399. pTK251 and 
pMW399 further encode an enterokinase cleavage site or 3C protease 
site, respectively, that permits proteolytic removal of the epitope tags 
from the recombinant protein. Another set of TMV-Gate vectors, 
designated as pMW390 and pMW391, allow generation of C-ter-
minal fusions of target proteins to YFP with a 3xFLAG tag or CFP 
with 3xHA tag, respectively. All TMV-Gate vectors encode a kana-
mycin-resistance (Km R ) bacterial selectable marker. Conventional 
pENTR Gateway vectors also utilise a Km R marker which may inter-
fere in selection of recombinant clones following the 'LR' Gateway 
insert transfer reaction. To overcome this problem, the entry clone 
encoding the gene of interest needs to be linearized by a restriction 
enzyme that uniquely cleaves the backbone of the vector outside the 
attL sites prior to performing LR recombination reactions. 
Alternatively, a derivative of the Gateway Entry vector carrying a </p>

<p>different bacterial selectable marker may be used. We have prev-
iously described a pENTR2B derivative vector, pJM1 (GenBank: 
FJ391469) and a pENTR1A derivative, pTK172 (GenBank: 
FJ410920) in which the Km R marker is inactivated by insertion of 
functional tetracycline and zeocin resistance genes, respectively 17 . </p>

<p>In planta evaluation and utility of TMV-Gate vectors for func-
tional analysis of proteins. TRBO vector from which TMV-Gate 
vectors are derived has several favourable attributes, including high 
agroinfection rates, high protein expression levels, ease of scale-up 
and bio-containment 11 . TMV-Gate vectors should perform very 
similarly to the TRBO vector since none of the TRBO features 
have been modified during vector assembly. Functionality of 
TMV-Gate vectors was evaluated for transient expression of native 
and epitope-tagged proteins, affinity purification, immunodetection, 
analysis of protein-protein interaction, subcellular localisation and 
pathogen effector screening. Additionally, the agroinfectivity and 
expression capability of a subset of the TMV-Gate vectors were 
analyzed and compared with that of the TRBO vector. To enable 
these analyses, entry clones encoding ORFs of reporter genes such 
as mGFP5 28 , GusPlus and NLS-mCherry as well as AtDMC1 
(Arabidopsis thaliana disrupted meiotic cDNA 1), an orthologue 
of a RecA-like protein in yeast that facilitates meiotic homologous 
recombination 29 , and XopD (a type III effector protein from Xantho-
monas campestris) 30 were recombined into various TMV-Gate 
vectors as listed in Table 1. </p>

<p>Agroinfectivity of TMV-Gate vectors. To test the agroinfectivity of 
TMV-Gate vectors A. tumefaciens cells carrying a subset of expres-
sion constructs encoding native or epitope-tagged mGFP5 (pSK133 
and pSK143-149; Table I) or 2xStrep-tag II-6xHis-GusPlus (pSK154; 
Table I) were infiltrated into N. benthamiana leaves and expression 
of mGFP5 and GusPlus was monitored for 6 days post infiltration 
(DPI). Expression of these reporter genes was detected at 3 DPI and 
increased gradually over the next 2-3 days reaching a maximum at </p>

<p>Table 1 | Recombinant expression constructs generated using TMV-Gate vectors to evaluate their functionality and utility </p>

<p>LR recombination 
Recombinant clone 
Recombinant protein </p>

<p>TMV-Gate vector 
Entry clone </p>

<p>For ectopic expression 
pMW388 
pMW350 
pSK133 
mGFP5 
pTK251 
pSK6 
pSK154 
2xStrep-tag II-6xHis-GusPlus 
For ectopic expression, affinity purification and analysis of protein-protein interactions 
pSK101 
pMW350 
pSK143 
HA-mGFP5 
pSK102 
pMW350 
pSK144 
3xHA-mGFP5 
pSK103 
pMW350 
pSK145 
FLAG-mGFP5 
pSK104 
pMW350 
pSK146 
3xFLAG-mGFP5 
pSK105 
pMW350 
pSK147 
c-myc-mGFP5 
pSK106 
pMW350 
pSK148 
3xc-myc-mGFP5 
pTK251 
pMW350 
pSK149 
2xStrep-tag II-6xHis-mGFP5 
pSK104 
pSW45 
pSK84 
3xFLAG-GusPlus 
pSK101 
pTK135 
pSK109 
HA-AtDMC1 G138D 
pSK102 
pTK135 
pSK110 
3xHA-AtDMC1 G138D 
pSK103 
pTK135 
pSK111 
FLAG-AtDMC1 G138D 
pSK104 
pTK135 
pSK112 
3xFLAG-AtDMC1 G138D 
pSK105 
pTK135 
pSK113 
c-myc-AtDMC1 G138D 
pSK106 
pTK135 
pSK114 
3xc-myc-AtDMC1 G138D 
pTK251 
pTK135 
pTK255 
2xStrep-tag II-6xHis-AtDMC1 G138D 
pMW399 
pMW389 
pMW403 
AtDMC1 G138D -2xStrep-tag II-6xHis 
For analysis of subcellular localisation 
pMW388 
pMK6 
pMW412 
NLS-mCherry 
pMW390 
pSK212 
pSK215 
NLS-mCherry-YFP-3xFLAG 
pMW391 
pSK212 
pSK216 
NLS-mCherry-CFP-3xHA 
For pathogen effector screening 
pSK103 
pSU73 
pSU101 
FLAG-XopD </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 874 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00874 </p>

<p>
5-6 DPI. At 5 DPI, most of the cells in the infiltrated leaf area were 
found to be expressing mGFP5 (Figure 2A) as well as GusPlus 
(Figure 2B), thus confirming the high agroinfection capability and 
expression potential of TMV-Gate vectors. 
The CP gene is required for systemic movement of virus part-
icles 31,32 . Thus, TMV CP deletion vectors, such as TRBO 11 and those 
developed by ICON Genetics 3 , cannot form virions and are unable to 
move systemically in plants, desirable attributes for bio-contain-
ment. TMV-Gate replicons share the feature of non-systemic move-
ment as evident from the infiltration zone-restricted expression of 
mGFP5 and GusPlus (Figure 2). This feature of TMV-Gate vectors 
thus possesses the desirable attribute of bio-containment by reducing 
plant to plant transmission and persistence in the environment. 
Lindbo 11 demonstrated that N. benthamiana leaves can be effi-
ciently agroinoculated with TRBO-GFP replicon over a wide range 
of A. tumefaciens cell densities (upto 1:300 dilution from a starting 
optical density at 600 nm (OD 600 ) of 1.0). To determine whether 
dilute suspensions of TMV-Gate vectors also can be used to effi-
ciently inoculate N. benthamiana leaves, we evaluated various dilute 
suspensions (upto 1:500 dilution from a starting OD 600 of 1.0; 
Figure 1C) of A. tumefaciens carrying pSK133 (pMW388 encoding 
mGFP5; Table I) and the expression of mGFP5 was monitored over 
the next five days. Expression of mGFP5 in all treatments began to be 
visible at 3 DPI and nearly all cells in the leaf zone infiltrated with A. 
tumefaciens cell suspension diluted upto 1:400 expressed mGFP5 at 
5 DPI, suggesting that, similar to the TRBO vector, the agroinfectiv-
ity of TMV-Gate vectors remains high at a wide range of cell densities 
of inoculum. A low density of A. tumefaciens cells [dilution of 1: 
500 (Figure 2C) and beyond (data not shown)] resulted in re-
duced mGFP5 expression, while higher A. tumefaciens cell density 
(OD 600 .1.0) occasionally resulted in yellowing and necrotic spots in 
the infiltration zone (data not shown), probably due to host cell death 
triggered as a defence mechanism in response to the high titre of 
inoculum. These results illustrate the inoculum cell density and the 
length of infection by A. tumefaciens cells carrying TMV-Gate-based 
expression constructs may be varied to achieve optimal levels of 
recombinant protein production for different applications. </p>

<p>Expression of native and fusion proteins using TMV-Gate vectors. 
To determine the protein production efficiency of TMV-Gate vec-
tors, mGFP5 accumulation in N. benthamiana leaves infiltrated with 
A. tumefaciens cells carrying empty vector (pMW388), TRBO-
GFP 11 , pSK133 (pMW388 encoding mGFP5) and pSK143 (pSK101 
encoding HA-tagged mGFP5) was quantified using an Experion TM 
automated electrophoresis system. Functionality of the constructs 
was first confirmed by assessing GFP fluorescence in agroinfil-
trated N. benthamiana leaves (Figure 3A). Protein extracts from 
infiltrated leaf sectors were prepared at 5 DPI and were resolved 
using an Experion Pro260 protein chip. A virtual gel image of the 
proteins detectable in each extract is shown in Figure 3B. As 
expected, the sample from the empty viral replicon extract did not 
possess a protein representing GFP, whereas distinct bands for GFP 
(,27 kDa) and HA-GFP (,30 kDa) were seen in protein extracts 
from N. benthamiana leaves agroinfected with TRBO-GFP or 
pSK133 and pSK143, respectively. Quantification of resolved pro-
teins indicated that TRBO-GFP, pSK133 and pSK143 produced 4.7, 
2.5 and 2.8 mg of GFP g 21 FW, respectively (Figure 3C). This GFP 
production by TRBO-GFP is in agreement with values (3.3 to 5.5 mg 
GFP g 21 FW) reported earlier 11 . It has been previously demonstrated 
that the level of recombinant protein production increases propor-
tionately with the proximity of the corresponding gene insert to the 
viral 39 terminus 10,11 . Thus, the relatively lower levels of protein 
produced by TMV-Gate replicons (pSK133 and pSK143) may be 
due to the incorporation of ,70 bp attR sequence between the 
GFP coding region and the 39 terminus of the TMV RNA genome. 
Nevertheless, the levels of protein produced by the TMV-Gate </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Transient expression of mGFP5 and GusPlus in N. 
benthamiana leaves by using TMV-Gate vectors. (A) N. benthamiana leaf 
infiltrated with A. tumefaciens carrying empty vector or viral expression 
vector encoding mGFP5 with or without translational fusion to either HA, 
3xHA, FLAG, 3xFLAG, c-myc, 3xc-myc or 2xStrep-tag II-6xHis-Xpress 
epitope tag(s) was illuminated under UV light at 5 DPI and photographed. 
Inset shows immunoblot detection of 2xStrep-tag II-6xHis-Xpress 
epitope-tagged mGFP5 (in silico predicted size of 37.8 kDa) in crude 
extract using anti-6xHis antibody. (B) N. benthamiana leaf discs from the 
area infiltrated with A. tumefaciens carrying empty vector (pTK251) or 
viral expression vector encoding 2xStrep-tag II-6xHis-GusPlus (pSK154) 
were excised 5 DPI and stained for GUS activity. Inset in right panel shows 
immunoblot detection of 2xStrep-tag II-6xHis-Xpress epitope-tagged 
GusPlus (in silico predicted size of 81.5 kDa) in crude leaf extract using 
anti-6xHis antibody. (C) N. benthamiana leaf infiltrated with various 
dilutions of a cell suspension of A. tumefaciens at OD 600 of 1.0 carrying 
pSK133 (pMW388 encoding mGFP5) and photographed with UV 
illumination at 5 DPI. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 874 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00874 </p>

<p>
replicons is much higher than the amount of GFP reported 11 to be 
produced by conventional non-TMV based agroinfiltration vectors 
(0.03-0.04 mg GFP g 21 FW), full-length TMV genome based 
vectors (1.5-1.7 mg GFP g 21 FW) or pEAQ series of Cowpea 
mosaic virus-derived binary vectors (0.7-1.25 mg GFP g 21 FW) 33 . </p>

<p>Affinity purification and immunodetection of epitope-tagged 
proteins expressed using TMV-Gate vectors. TMV-Gate vectors 
designed to express epitope-tagged proteins allow addition of sin-
gle or triple-repeats of several commonly used epitope tags, such as 
HA, FLAG, c-myc, Strep-tag II, 6xHis, and Xpress epitope, to either 
the N-or C-terminus of target proteins (Figure 1). To demonstrate 
the utility of these vectors in expression, detection and purification of 
recombinant proteins, the ORF of an AtDMC1 variant with a defect 
in its ATPase motif (AtDMC1 G138D ; see below) was recombined into 
TMV-Gate vectors, including pSK101-106, pTK251 and pMW399, 
resulting in expression constructs pSK109-114, pTK255 and pMW403, 
respectively (Table I). Leaf tissues encompassing zones agroinfil-
trated with these constructs were collected at 5 DPI, total protein 
extracted and the epitope tagged proteins affinity purified by using 
either agarose resins possessing epitope tag-specific antibody or Strep-
Tactin matrix columns. Immunodetection of various epitope-tagged 
versions of AtDMC1 G138D expressed from TMV-Gate vectors is shown 
in Figure 4. The anti-HA, -FLAG, -c-myc, -Strep-tag II and -6xHis 
antibodies effectively recognised both the single-(molecular mass of 
,42 kDa) and triple-repeat (molecular mass of ,44 kDa) epitope 
tagged AtDMC1 G138D fusion proteins from the input as well as affi-
nity purified fractions. These results demonstrate the functionality 
of the epitope and affinity purification modules of the TMV-Gate 
vectors. 
Epitope tagged proteins are most commonly eluted from affinity 
matrices using SDS-PAGE sample buffer. This elution method typ-
ically results in denaturation and loss of activity of the purified pro-
teins. Proteins can be eluted under native conditions by competitive 
elution using epitope tag-specific synthetic peptides or counter 
ligands. To test this possibility, the single or triple-repeat FLAG-
tagged AtDMC1 G138D expressed using TMV-Gate vectors and immo-
bilized on anti-FLAG agarose affinity resin was eluted using 3xFLAG 
peptide. As shown in Figure 4B, the 3xFLAG peptide efficiently 
eluted the triple-repeat FLAG-tagged AtDMC1 G138D ; however, as 
suggested by the peptide manufacturer, it failed to elute the single-
repeat FLAG-tagged AtDMC1 G138D . Similarly, the 2xStrep-tag II-
6xHis-Xpress epitope-tagged AtDMC1 G138D immobilized on Strep-
Tactin matrix was eluted using desthiobiotin as a counter ligand. 
Experion-based analysis of the purified AtDMC1 G138D revealed the 
presence of a single band at ,50 KDa (Figure 4F), the predicted size 
of the fusion protein, indicating high purity of the product. 
Subsequently, the epitope tags from the purified fusion protein were 
cleaved off by treatment with enterokinase and the resultant 
AtDMC1 G138D was successfully used for raising antibody in a rabbit 
(data not shown). Taken together, the results of these experiments 
establish the suitability of TMV-Gate vectors for expression of re-
combinant proteins, their immunodetection and affinity purification 
to obtain native proteins of high purity. </p>

<p>Utility of TMV-Gate vectors for analysis of protein-protein in-
teraction. Protein-protein interactions play a central role in the 
maintenance and control of cellular and organismal processes. The 
study of protein-protein interactions has been greatly enhanced by 
epitope-tagging technology facilitating 'pull-down' experiments that 
can be used to detect and validate protein interactions. In order to 
establish the utility of epitope-tagging TMV-Gate vectors for anal-
ysing protein-protein interactions we employed AtDMC1. The yeast 
and human DMC1 orthologues have been shown to physically in-
teract homotypically by yeast two-hybrid (Y2H) analysis and, in the 
case of human DMC1, by immunoprecipitation 34 . DMC1 DNA 
strand exchange activity in vitro is dependent upon ATP binding </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Quantitative analysis of transient GFP production in N. 
benthamiana using TRBO or TMV-Gate vectors. (A) Fluorescence 
emitted from GFP transiently produced in a N. benthamiana leaf by 
infiltration with A. tumefaciens carrying TRBO-GFP (Lindbo, 2007b) or 
TMV-Gate constructs pSK133 encoding mGFP5, pSK143 encoding HA-
mGFP5 or pMW388 (empty vector) and photographed with UV 
illumination at 5 DPI. (B) Assessment of GFP accumulation by automated 
capillary electrophoresis analysis. N. benthamiana leaf discs from the area 
outlined in (A) were excised at 5 DPI and corresponding protein extracts 
were resolved and GFP identified using the Experion capillary 
electrophoresis system. Position of the GFP band in each sample is 
indicated by downward pointing triangles in the simulated gel view 
produced by the <rs type="software">Experion</rs> software. The shift in the molecular weight of 
GFP in pSK143 is due to the presence of an HA tag at the N-terminus. (C) 
Quantification of GFP resolved by automated capillary electrophoresis 
analysis using the Experion system. Error bars represent standard 
deviation. FW, fresh weight. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 874 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00874 </p>

<p>
and hydrolysis mediated by an ATPase motif highly conserved 
between prokaryote and eukaryote RecA-like proteins 35 , including 
AtDMC1. Notably, mutating the ATP-binding motif in yeast DMC1 
(yDMC1 G126D ) results in defective meiotic homologous recombina-
tion; however, homotypic interactions of yDMC1 G126D have not been 
demonstrated because of instability of the Y2H plasmid expressing 
this protein 34 . In characterising AtDMC1 we created a variant 
(AtDMC1 G138D ) analogous to yDMC1 G126D and sought to assess if it 
could interact homotypically. Self-interaction of AtDMC1 G138D was 
initially analysed by Y2H assay wherein interaction of the bait and 
prey fusion proteins results in expression of a HIS3 reporter gene 
enabling growth of his3 auxotrophic yeast cells on a selective medium 
lacking histidine. When the AtDMC1 G138D bait was expressed with 
the non-interacting empty prey vector no growth of yeast cells was 
detected in histidine-deficient plates containing 15 mM 3-amino-
1,2,4-triazole (3-AT) which was added to suppress autoactivation 
of the reporter gene by the AtDMC1 G138D bait. In contrast, co-
expression of AtDMC1 G138D as bait and prey enabled growth of </p>

<p>yeast cells, indicating that AtDMC1 G138D can interact homotypi-
cally (Figure 5A) and, as proposed for yDMC1 G126D 34 , given the 
substitution of glycine by the relatively bulky and negatively 
charged aspartate likely does so independently of ATP binding. 
To validate the results of the Y2H assay, we performed pull-down 
experiments with various versions of epitope tagged-AtDMC1 G138D 
expressed using TMV-Gate vectors. FLAG-tagged AtDMC1 G138D was 
first immobilized on anti-FLAG agarose beads and then incubated 
with crude protein extracts containing c-myc-tagged AtDMC1 G138D 
or c-myc-tagged mGFP5 to allow protein complex formation. 
Western blot analysis of the proteins eluted off the anti-FLAG beads 
after thorough washing revealed the presence of c-myc-tagged 
AtDMC1 G138D , with expected molecular mass of 42 kDa, but not 
the c-myc-tagged mGFP5 (Figure 5B, left panel), demonstrating 
that FLAG-tagged AtDMC1 G138D interacted with c-myc-tagged 
AtDMC1 G138D but not with c-myc-tagged mGFP5. In a similar man-
ner, 3xHA-tagged AtDMC1 G138D was immobilised on anti-HA anti-
body conjugated beads and incubated with crude protein extract of </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Affinity purification and detection of epitope-tagged AtDMC1 G138D transiently expressed in N. benthamiana leaves by using TMV-Gate </p>

<p>vectors. Epitope-tagged recombinant AtDMC1 G138D immobilized on anti-HA, anti-FLAG or anti-c-myc antibody-conjugated agarose beads were eluted 
either by boiling the beads in SDS-PAGE sample buffer (SDS eluate) or by incubating the beads with 3xFLAG peptide (peptide eluate). The Strep-tag II-
tagged AtDMC1 G138D immobilized on Strep-Tactin matrix was eluted using desthiobiotin. Equal volume aliquots of the input protein extract and eluted 
AtDMC1 G138D proteins were subjected to SDS-PAGE, transferred onto PVDF membrane then subjected to immunoblot analysis. WB, western blot. (A) 
Immunoblot detection of HA-or 3xHA-tagged AtDMC1 G138D protein affinity captured using anti-HA agarose affinity gel. (B) Immunoblot detection of 
FLAG-or 3xFLAG-tagged AtDMC1 G138D protein affinity captured using anti-FLAG agarose affinity gel. (C) Immunoblot detection of c-myc-or 3xmyc-
tagged AtDMC1 G138D protein affinity captured using anti-c-myc conjugated agarose beads. (D) Immunoblot detection of 2xStrep-tag II-6xHis-Xpress 
epitope-tagged AtDMC1 G138D in crude extract using anti-Strep-tag II antibody. (E) Immunoblot detection of 2xStrep-tag II-6xHis-Xpress epitope-tagged 
AtDMC1 G138D in crude extract using anti-6xHis antibody. (F) Capillary electrophoresis analysis using the Experion system of 2xStrep-tag II-6xHis-Xpress 
epitope-tagged AtDMC1 G138D protein affinity purified by using Strep-Tactin matrix. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 874 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00874 </p>

<p>
3xFLAG-tagged AtDMC1 G138D or 3xFLAG-tagged GusPlus then 
eluted proteins were probed with anti-FLAG antibody. As predicted, 
3xHA-tagged AtDMC1 G138D interacted with 3xFLAG-tagged 
AtDMC1 G138D but not with 3xFLAG-tagged GusPlus (negative con-
trol; Figure 5B, right panel). These results, apart from confirming the 
ability of AtDMC1 G138D to interact homotypically and validating the 
results of the Y2H assay, demonstrate the applicability of TMV-Gate 
vectors for the analysis of protein-protein interactions. </p>

<p>Utility of TMV-Gate vectors for analysis of subcellular localisa-
tion of proteins. In recent years, translational fusion of candidate 
proteins to a fluorescent protein combined with microscopy has 
become a powerful tool for defining protein function through deter-
mining its subcellular localisation. TMV-Gate vectors designed to 
express C-terminal YFP or CFP fusion proteins include an in-frame 
3xFLAG or 3xHA epitope tag, respectively (Figure 1), and thus 
enable simultaneous analyses, including (i) in planta evaluation of 
subcellular localisation of fluorescent protein fusions and (ii) immu-
nodetection, affinity purification and analysis of protein-protein 
interaction by virtue of the epitope tags attached at the C-terminal 
ends of the fusion proteins. To test the suitability of these vectors 
for studying subcellular localisation of proteins, the mCherry red 
fluorescent protein linked to a nuclear localisation signal derived 
from the SV40 large T-antigen (NLS-mCherry) was recombined 
with pMW388; additionally, a variant lacking the stop codon 
(NLS-mCherry DSTOP ) was recombined with the TMV-Gate vectors 
pMW390 or pMW391 to generate in-frame fusions with YFP-
3xFLAG or CFP-3xHA, respectively (Figure 6A). The resultant con-
structs, designated as pMW412, pSK215 and pSK216, respectively 
(Table I), were agroinfiltrated into N. benthamiana leaves and sub-
cellular localisation of the fusion proteins assessed by fluorescent 
microscopy. The subcellular fluorescence signal emitted by NLS-
mCherry overlapped with the DAPI (49,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole; 
a nuclear stain) signal (Figure 6B), demonstrating that NLS-
mCherry localizes to the nucleus and can be utilized as a positive </p>

<p>control in nuclear localisation experiments. As expected, both NLS-
mCherry-YFP-3xFLAG and NLS-mCherry-CFP-3xHA fusion proteins 
localized to the nucleus, as deduced by comparing the fluorescence 
signal with the DAPI signal (Figure 6B). These results demon-
strate pMW390 and pMW391 TMV-Gate vectors can be utilized 
for detection of subcellular localisation of proteins in planta. </p>

<p>Utility of TMV-Gate vectors in pathogen effector protein screen-
ing. Effectors are pathogen-derived molecules that manipulate host 
cell structure and function, thereby facilitating infection and/or trig-
gering disease resistance, culminating in a hypersensitive response 
(HR)-based programmed cell death 36,37 . In recent years, the combi-
nation of genome sequencing of plant pathogens with computational 
data mining has dramatically accelerated the identification of effec-
tor candidates. Developing high-throughput vector platforms for 
functional screening of candidate effectors thus would provide an 
important complement to the bioinformatics approach of identifying 
effectors. Ectopic expression of effector proteins in plant cells often 
leads to phenotypic effects, such as induction of HR-like necrosis 38 . 
To test the suitability of TMV-Gate vectors for the expression and 
functional screening of effector proteins we selected XopD which has 
been shown to elicit HR-like tissue chlorosis and necrosis symptoms 
in N. benthamiana 39 . The ORF of XopD was recombined in-frame 
with the FLAG epitope tag of pSK103, resulting in pSU101. This and 
pSK145 encoding mGFP were agroinfiltrated into N. benthamiana 
leaves at 1:5 dilution from the initial OD 600 of 1.0 (optimised to 
overcome the necrosis potentially induced by A. tumefaciens). Tran-
sient expression of FLAG-XopD resulted in localized tissue chlorosis 
by 5-6 DPI and necrosis by 9-10 DPI (Figure 7). In contrast, tran-
sient expression of FLAG-mGFP5 did not elicit such symptoms. 
These data, in agreement with a previous report by Kim et al. 39 , 
illustrate that XopD is capable of eliciting an HR response in N. 
benthamiana and also confirm the suitability of TMV-Gate vectors 
for effector screening. </p>

<p>Discussion 
In this study, we describe construction and validation of a viral vector 
system for expedited production and characterisation of recombin-
ant proteins via transient expression in plant leaves. The vectors are 
derived from the TRBO variant of TMV previously reported 11 as 
enabling high-level production of recombinant proteins but which 
is severely constrained in practical applications by requiring reliance 
on traditional DNA cloning procedures. The vectors described in this 
study are unique from other plant virus vectors integrating Gateway 
technology 25-27 by further incorporating a very broad series of epi-
tope, affinity purification and fluorescent protein tags to more read-
ily exploit the attributes of TMV for rapid production and analysis of 
protein attributes regarding their biochemical and cell biology prop-
erties. The compatibility of this expression system with Gateway 
technology enhances its suitability for high-throughput functional 
analysis studies. Gateway technology has been widely adapted by the 
research community to facilitate high-throughput proteomic 
research. We anticipate that this vector system will complement 
the on-going and future efforts to clone and functionally characterize 
ORFeomes using Gateway pENTR vectors 40 . 
We demonstrate the utility of the vector system through examples 
of protein-protein interaction analysis and protein sub-cellular loca-
lisation. Effective protein expression using the system was demon-
strated by immunoblot analysis of AtDMC1 and GFP with eight 
different tags or GusPlus with 2xStrep-tag II-6xHis tag revealing 
no truncated recombinant proteins; furthermore, in all of these cases 
the proteins were extracted without a denaturation step, collectively 
supporting their accumulation as intact soluble cellular constituents 
and not as truncated proteins or insoluble aggregates. Because of the 
capability to generate grams of recombinant protein per kg of fresh 
weight biomass within a short time frame, this vector set has great </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Protein-protein interaction of AtDMC1 G138D expressed using </p>

<p>TMV-Gate vectors. (A) Yeast two-hybrid analysis demonstrating self-
interaction of AtDMC1 G138D . (B) Confirmation of AtDMC1 G138D self-
interaction by pull-down experiment. The FLAG-tagged AtDMC1 G138D 
and 3xHA-tagged AtDMC1 G138D immobilized on anti-FLAG and anti-HA 
agarose beads, respectively, were incubated with total protein extract of N. 
benthamiana leaf discs transiently expressing c-myc-tagged AtDMC1 G138D 
or c-myc-tagged mGFP5 (negative control) and 3xFLAG-tagged 
AtDMC1 G138D or 3xFLAG-tagged GusPlus (negative control), respectively; 
corresponding TMV-Gate vectors and recombinant plasmids are listed in 
Table I. After washing the affinity matrices, proteins were eluted using 
SDS-PAGE sample buffer, resolved by SDS-PAGE and visualized by 
immunoblotting with antibodies as indicated. WB, western blot. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 874 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00874 </p>

<p>
potential to be utilized in large scale protein production applications. 
Additionally, the mid-to high-level of protein production inherent 
to TMV-Gate vectors combined with the flexibility of modulating 
protein accumulation through altering A. tumefaciens cell density 
and length of infection has utility in experiments involving toxic 
proteins which when expressed at very high levels may confer det-
rimental effects on host cells. Recombinant proteins produced using 
this system can be easily separated from cellular material using anti-
epitope tag affinity matrices and be readily detected by either using 
anti-epitope tag antibodies or by fluorescence microscopy. Such cap-
abilities can be useful for functional genomic studies by defining 
protein properties, including analysis of protein-protein interactions 
and subcellular localisation. Functionality of the system for subcel-
lular localisation studies was illustrated using NLS-mCherry which 
maintained its ability to localise to the nucleus when expressed in 
fusion with fluorescent proteins. Similarly, AtSAP18 (At2g45640), 
an established corepressor involved in chromatin remodelling and 
previously demonstrated to localize to the nucleus 41 , when expressed 
in fusion with CFP using pMW391 reproducibly localised to the 
nucleus (Supplementary Figure S1), thereby further validating the 
utility of the TMV-Gate vectors in cell biology applications. It is 
evident from these results that TMV-Gate driven high-level expres-</p>

<p>sion of proteins does not affect their integrity, solubility or localisa-
tion. To-date, this system has been used to successfully express 45 
native or fusion proteins, including: fluorescent protein, GusPlus, 
AtDMC1 and XopD variants as listed in Table I (with insert sizes 
ranging from 741-2358 bp); four transcriptional regulators (654-
939 bp; data not shown); a corepressor involved in chromatin 
remodelling (1422 bp; data not shown); and 17 pathogen effectors 
(234-1335 bps; data not shown) from Albugo candida 42 . In the past, 
several viral-based expression vector systems have been utilized for 
functional screening of effector proteins 43-45 ; however, TMV-Gate 
vectors, by virtue of their ability to produce native as well as various 
epitope-or fluorescent protein-tagged recombinant proteins, pro-
vide a more complete and integrated platform for functional evalu-
ation of effector candidates in N. benthamiana. Collectively, this 
illustrates the robustness and broad utility of the system. 
In summary, the vector system described here allows rapid and 
versatile assembly of expression constructs for production of intact, 
soluble and functionally active recombinant proteins at a very high 
yield within a short time-frame and overcomes some limitations of </p>

<p>Figure 6 | Nuclear localizsation of NLS-mCherry expressed using TMV-</p>

<p>Gate vectors. (A) Schematic diagram showing constructs used for analysis 
of subcellular localisation of NLS-mCherry. mCherry carrying a nuclear 
localization signal (NLS) was introduced unmodified into pMW388. A 
NLS-mCherry variant without translational stop codon was linked in-
frame with the coding sequence of YFP-3xFLAG or CFP-3xHA in 
pMW390 and pMW391, respectively. Annotated features as per Figure 1. 
(B) Epifluorescent microscopy images showing nuclear localisation of 
NLS-mCherry (upper panel), NLS-mCherry linked to YFP-3xFLAG 
(middle panel) or NLS-mCherry linked to CFP-3xHA in cells of N. 
benthamiana leaves infiltrated with A. tumefaciens carrying the constructs 
described in (A) and imaged 3 DPI. The nucleus was detected by staining 
cells with DAPI. Images were taken using YFP, CFP, mCherry or DAPI 
filter sets as indicated. Scale bar, 20 mM. DIC, differential interference 
contrast. </p>

<p>Figure 7 | TMV-Gate vector based expression of XopD effector protein in 
N. benthamiana leaves. N. benthamiana leaves were infiltrated with A. 
tumefaciens strains expressing FLAG-tagged XopD (pSU101) or mGFP5 
(negative control; pSK145) and the phenotypes were photographed at 2, 4, 
6, 8, 10 and 12 DPI. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 874 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00874 </p>

<p>
prokaryotic expression systems, thereby providing an invaluable tool 
to expedite plant functional genomics and proteomics research. 
While this study employs plant proteins as examples, it is expected 
the vector system will be attractive for applications with proteins 
from animal or other species given the combination of tags incorpo-
rated and the potential for rapid, high-level production of heterolog-
ous proteins. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Plant material. N. benthamiana plants were grown for 4-6 weeks in a greenhouse at 
,25uC on a 16 h light and 8 h dark cycle before infiltration with A. tumefaciens 
cultures carrying various expression constructs. </p>

<p>Construction of Destination vectors. Cloning techniques were performed using 
standard protocols 46 . Nucleotide sequences of the primers (Integrated DNA 
Technologies) used in this study are listed in Supplementary Table S1. Resynthesised 
DNA cassettes were obtained from the National Research Council (Saskatoon, SK). 
Gateway reagents and vectors were obtained from Invitrogen. PCR amplifications 
were performed using PicoMaxx polymerase (Stratagene). All destination vector 
assemblies as described below were transformed into One Shot ccdB Survival 2 T1 
Phage-Resistant Escherichia coli cells (Invitrogen), and positive transformants were 
selected in the presence of kanamycin (50 mg/L) and chloramphenicol (30 mg/L). </p>

<p>Vectors encoding RfA-cassette with or without N-terminal epitope tag(s). The 
RfA-cassette encoding a chloramphenicol resistance marker and ccdB flanked by 
attR1 and attR2 was amplified by PCR using primers Dest-59-SnaMfePac and Dest-
39-SphPspAvr. Coding sequences for the RfA-cassette linked to the HA 
(YPYDVPDYA) or 3xHA (YPYDVPDYAGYPYDVPDYAGSYPYDVPDYA) 
epitope tags were amplified by PCR from pEarleyGate201 20 using sense primers 
pEG201-59-BspPac or pEG201-59-BspPac12xHA, respectively, and a common 
antisense primer DEST-39AvrPsm. Similarly, the FLAG (DYKDDDDK) or 3xFLAG 
(DYKDDDDKGDYKDDDDKGDYKDDDDK) tags linked to the RfA-cassette were 
amplified from pEarleyGate202 20 using the primers pEG202-59-BspPac or pEG202-
59-BspPac12xFLAG, respectively, as sense primers and the common antisense 
primer DEST-39AvrPsm. To amplify c-myc (EQKLISEEDLN) or 3xc-myc 
(EQKLISEEDLNGEQKLISEEDLNGEQKLISEEDL) tags linked to the RfA-cassette, 
pEarleyGate203 20 was used as template and the primers pEG203-59-BspPac or 
pEG203-59-BspPac12xMyc, respectively, were used as sense primers along with the 
common antisense primer DEST-39AvrPsm. The 2xStrep-tag II-6xHis-Xpress 
epitope-linked RfA-cassette was amplified using as template pTK249, a pEXP1-Dest 
(Invtirogen) derivative encoding a 2xStrep-tag II-6xHis-Xpress epitope-linked RfA-
cassette (see Supplementary Methods), and primers Strep-59-PciNdePac and Exp1-
Dest-39-PspAvr. The PCR amplicons (,1.8 kb) encoding the RfA-cassettes with or 
without epitope tags from the above PCR reactions were digested with PacI and AvrII 
then ligated into the TRBO vector digested with the same enzymes resulting in the 
respective TMV-Gate vectors pMW388, pSK101, pSK102, pSK103, pSK104, pSK105, 
pSK106 and pTK251, as depicted in Figure 1. </p>

<p>Vector encoding RfA-cassette with C-terminal epitope tag. The 2xStrep-tag II-
6xHis epitope assembly at the 39 end of the RfA cassette in pMW394, a pEXP2-Dest 
(Invitrogen) derivative (see Supplementary Methods), was amplified by PCR using 
the primers EXP2-Dest-59-XhoSnaPac and EXP2-Dest-39-SacPspAvr. The 1.95 kb 
amplicon was digested with PacI and AvrII then ligated into the TRBO vector 
digested with the same enzymes, resulting in pMW399 (Figure 1). </p>

<p>Vectors encoding RfA-cassette with C-terminal epitope-tagged fluorescent 
protein. Plasmids pMW397 and pMW396 encoding assemblies of the RfA-cassette 
linked to C-terminal YFP or CFP and 3x concatamers of the FLAG or HA tag, 
respectively, were derived from pEarleyGate101 and pEarleyGate102 20 (see 
Supplementary Methods). The RfA-YFP-3xFLAG and RfA-CFP-3xHA cassettes 
were isolated by digestion of pMW397 and pMW396 (Supplementary Methods), 
respectively, with PacI and AvrII then ligated into the TRBO vector digested with the 
same enzymes, resulting in pMW390 and pMW391 (Figure 1). </p>

<p>Gateway Entry clones. The Gateway Entry clones pMK6, pMW350, pSK6, pSW45, 
pSU73 and pTK135 (Table I) were assembled as described in the Supporting 
Information (see Supplementary Methods). These plasmids were digested with PvuI, 
uniquely cutting the Km R gene, gel-purified and recombined with Destination vectors 
pSK101-106, pTK251, pMW388, pMW390-391, or pMW399 (Table I) using LR 
clonase II Invitrogen. </p>

<p>Agroinfection. Expression constructs (Table I) encoding mGFP5, GusPlus, 
AtDMC1 G138D , NLS-mCherry and XopD were introduced into A. tumefaciens 
GV3101::pMP90 47 by electroporation. Agroinfection of N. benthamiana leaves was 
carried out as described previously 11 and summarised in the Supporting Information 
(see Supplementary Methods). </p>

<p>Visualization of mGFP5 and GusPlus activity. Five days after infiltration of N. 
benthamiana leaves with A. tumefaciens carrying various TMV-Gate expression 
vectors encoding GFP and GusPlus reporter genes, leaf material encompassing the </p>

<p>infiltrated area was excised. Leaves expressing GFP were photographed under UV 
illumination generated by a transilluminator (VWR Scientific). GusPlus activity was 
visualized by histochemical staining 48 with overnight incubation at 37uC. </p>

<p>Yeast two-hybrid assay. The GAL4-based ProQuest (Invitrogen) Y2H system was 
used. To assemble the bait and prey constructs, the ORF encoding AtDMC1 G138D was 
transferred from pTK135 to pDEST32 (bait vector) and pDEST22 (prey vector) using 
the LR clonase reaction, resulting in pTK149 and pTK145, respectively. Yeast strain 
MaV203 (Invitrogen) was transformed with plasmid combinations listed in 
Figure 5A according to the method of Gietz and Woods 49 . Assays were conducted on 
plates containing minimal medium lacking leucine, tryptophan and histidine 
supplemented with 15 mM 3-AT (Sigma-Aldrich). </p>

<p>Extraction of leaf proteins. Proteins from agroinfected N. benthamiana leaves were 
extracted by grinding tissue in the presence of liquid nitrogen then suspending in 4-5 
volumes of extraction buffer [50 mM Tris HCl, pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 
1% Triton-X-100, 1 mM PMSF and 1x plant protease inhibitor mix (Sigma-
Aldrich)]. The homogenate was centrifuged twice at 14,000 rpm for 15 min at 4 uC. 
Protein concentration was determined by the Bradford method 50 (BioRad). </p>

<p>Experion automated electrophoresis analysis. Samples for Experion Pro260 
(BioRad) analysis were prepared by mixing 2 ml of sample buffer with 4 ml samples of 
protein extracts then loaded onto chips as recommended by the manufacturer. 
Electrophoresis runs were analyzed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Experion</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">BioRad</rs>) as 
summarised in Supporting Information (Supplementary Methods). </p>

<p>Affinity purification and pull-down experiment. Protein extracts prepared as 
described above were either incubated with 50 mL (bed volume) of pre-washed 
EZview red agarose beads (Sigma-Aldrich) conjugated with anti-HA, anti-FLAG or 
anti-c-myc antibodies, or passed through Strep-Tactin matrix (IBA GmbH). Bound 
protein was then washed three times with extraction buffer. Tagged proteins affinity 
captured on the beads were eluted either by boiling the beads in SDS-PAGE sample 
buffer or, in the case of FLAG-based purification, by mixing with antibody-specific 
peptide (3xFLAG peptide; Sigma-Aldrich) or for the Strep-Tactin matrix eluted by 
addition of 2.5 mM desthiobiotin. Eluted proteins were analysed by SDS-PAGE 
followed by immunoblotting using antibodies specific to each of the epitope tags (see 
Supplementary Methods). 
For pull-down experiments, FLAG or 3xHA-tagged AtDMC1 G138D fusions 
immobilized on anti-FLAG or anti-HA-antibody-conjugated agarose beads, 
respectively, were washed three times with 500 mL of extraction buffer, then incubated 
for ,90 min with total protein extract prepared from N. benthamiana leaves 
expressing c-myc-or 3xFLAG-tagged AtDMC1 G138D , mGFP5 (negative control) or 
GusPlus (negative control). The beads were then washed three times with 500 mL of 
extraction buffer. Proteins retained on the beads were eluted using SDS-PAGE sample 
buffer and analyzed by SDS-PAGE followed by immunoblotting with anti-c-myc or 
anti-FLAG antibodies (see Supplementary Methods). </p>

<p>Epifluorescence microscopy. Epifluorescent images of leaf discs expressing NLS-
mCherry, NLS-mCherry-YFP-3xFLAG and NLS-mCherry-CFP-3xHA were 
obtained by using a Zeiss Axio Imager.Z1 microscope equipped with an EC Plan-
Neofluar 20X/0.50 M27 objective and an AxioCam HRm camera and using 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">AxioVision</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Carl Zeiss Canada Ltd.</rs>.). The light source was a broad spectrum 
X-cite 120 series mercury bulb (Lumen Dynamics Group Inc.). Nuclei were detected 
by staining with 49,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI). Filter sets (Carl Zeiss 
Canada Ltd.) include HE DsRed (excitation: 538-562; emission: 570-640), YFP 
(excitation: 490-510; emission: 520-550), HE Cyan (excitation: 424-448; emission: 
460-500) and DAPI (excitation: 335-383; emission: 420-470). Exposure times were 
between 0.2 to 0.9 seconds. </p>

<p> </p>



<p>
Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank J. Lindbo for providing the TRBO vector and TRBO-GFP construct and R. Tsien 
for providing mCherry. We also thank Hyun-hye Kim for technical assistance. Milosz 
Kaczmarek and Song Wang contributed to assembly of NLS-mCherry and the GusPlus 
ORF, respectively. GusPlus was provided by CAMBIA. pEarleyGate vectors were obtained 
from the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Centre. This work was supported by funding 
from the Canadian Crop Genomics Initiative of Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada 
provided to K.R. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>KR conceived the study. KR and SK designed and coordinated the study, and wrote the 
manuscript. SK developed and established protocols, and assembled constructs in concert 
with MW and TB. SK performed transient expression, purification and characterization of 
recombinant protein experiments. WY performed Y2H experiments. SU and MHB 
designed and performed pathogen effector screening experiments. All authors read and 
approved the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>License: This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this 
license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Kagale, S. et al. TMV-Gate vectors: Gateway compatible tobacco 
mosaic virus based expression vectors for functional analysis of proteins. Sci. Rep. 2, 874; 
DOI:10.1038/srep00874 (2012). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 874 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00874 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>