<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3768479" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Actinomyces strain A01 was isolated from soil of a vegetable field in the suburb of Beijing, China. According 
to the morphological, cultural, physiological and biochemical characteristics, and 16S rDNA sequence analysis, 
strain A01 was identified as Streptomyces lydicus. In the antimicrobial spectrum test strain A01 presented a 
stable and strong inhibitory activity against several plant pathogenic fungi such as Fusarium oxysporum, 
Botrytis cinerea, Monilinia laxa, etc. However, no antibacterial activity was found. In pot experiments in 
greenhouse, the development of tomato gray mold was markedly suppressed by treatment with the fermentation 
broth of the strain A01, and the control efficacy was higher than those of Pyrimethanil and Polyoxin. A main 
antifungal compound (purity 99.503%) was obtained from the fermentation broth of strain A01 using column 
chromatography and HPLC. The chemical structural analysis with UV, IR, MS, and NMR confirmed that the 
compound produced by the strain A01 is natamycin, a polyene antibiotic produced by S. chattanovgensis, S. 
natalensis, and S. gilvosporeus, widely used as a natural biological preservative for food according to 
previous reports. The present study revealed a new producing strain of natamycin and its potential application 
as a biological control agent for fungal plant diseases. </p>

<p>Plant diseases caused by fungi are one of the major reasons 
for causing agricultural losses (8). Gray mold disease, caused 
by the fungus Botrytis cinerea, has now become a limiting 
factor in the vegetable production in many areas of China. 
The disease used to be and is still being mainly controlled by 
chemical fungicides, such as aminobenzimidazoles, 
phthalimide, and carbamates (28,29). However, resistance has 
been found in B. cinerea to several of these chemicals (24). 
Furthermore, long term application of chemicals have caused 
serious food and environment pollutions, and brought 
attention to the search for alternative measures in controlling 
plant fungal diseases. </p>

<p>The development and application of microbial agents is one 
of the alternative measures. Several Streptomyces strains that 
suppressed the growth of B. cinerea were shown to produce 
antibiotic compounds such as phosphazomyzin, albopeptin B, 
tautomycin, tautomycein, and ezomycin S (18). The diverse 
chemical structures of these metabolites would reduce the 
chance for pathogens to develop resistance (26). In addition, 
the searching for antimicrobial metabolites has also been spurred 
on by the possibilities that they could be developed into new 
classes fungicides (5,10). In the present study, we report a study 
on the extraction and identification of the metabolic substance 
of actinomyces strain A01 and its antifungal spectrum and the 
control efficacy to tomato gray mold under greenhouse 
conditions. </p>



<p>Lu, G.C. et al. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Strains 
Actinomyces strain A01 was isolated from the soil of 
vegetable field in Beijing suburb by the Institute of Plant and 
Environment Protection, Beijing Academy of Agriculture and 
Forestry Sciences (IPEP-BAAFS), and has been deposited in 
the Chinese General Microbiological Collection Centre (Beijing, 
China) as strain CGMCC No.1653. Fungal pathogens, Fusarium 
oxysporum f.sp. vasinfectum, F. oxysporum f.sp. niveu, F. 
oxysporum f.sp. conglutinans. B.cinerea, Magnaporthe oryzae, 
Cladosporium fulvum, Exserohilum turcicum, Alternaria 
solani, Alternaria mali, Monilinia laxa and Colletotrichum 
capsici were provided by IPEP-BAAFS. The bacterial strains, 
Agrobacterium rhizogenes, Pseudomonas syringae pv. 
lachrymans, Bacillus cereus, Xanthomonas vesicatoria and 
Ralstonia solanacearum, were obtained from Department of 
Plant Pathology, China Agricultural University. And the yeast 
strain Saccharomyces cerevisiae (ACCC No. A20063) was 
obtained from Agricultural Culture Collection of China. </p>

<p>Preparation of the antibiotic fermentation broth of strain A01 
Strain A01 was cultured on GAOs no. 1 agar slant (17) at 
28ºC for 2-wk. The mature spores were washed from the slant 
with sterilized distilled water and diluted into the suspension in 
the concentration of 10 
6 spores mL </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>. Two mL of this suspension 
was then inoculated into a 500 mL Erlenmeyer flask containing 
100mL fermentation medium (dextrose 2 g, soybean meal 2 g, 
soluble starch 0.5 g, peptone 0.5 g, corn steep liquor 0.25 g, 
(NH 4 ) 2 SO 4 0.25 g, MgSO 4 . 7H 2 O 0.025 g, K 2 HPO 4 0.002 g, NaCl 
0.4 g, CaCO 3 0.2 g, tap water 100 mL) and incubated at 28ºC on a 
rotary shaker at 180 rpm for 96 h. The fermented broth was 
centrifuged at 5,000 g, 4ºC for 15 min, and the supernatant was 
filtered using a 0.45-μm-pore-size membrane filter (Millipore). 
The filtrate was collected as the antibiotic sample. </p>

<p>Bioassay of the antimicrobial activity 
For determining the antimicrobial spectrum, spore 
suspensions from pathogenic fungi were prepared according 
to the method described by Soares et al. (22) as follows. Plant 
pathogenic fungi were cultured on PDA slants (17) at 25-28ºC 
for 5-7 d. The fungal spores were harvested by washing with 5 
mL sterilized distilled water and diluted into the suspension in 
the concentration of 10 
6 spores mL </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>. About 200 μl of the spore 
suspension was then inoculated onto a PDA plate (9 cm in 
diameter). The plant pathogenic bacteria inoculated on beef 
peptone agar slants (17), S. cerevisiae on PDA, were cultured 
at 28ºC for 2 d, and then washed up and diluted into the 
suspension in the concentration of 10 
4 CFU mL 
-1 with sterile 
physiological salt solution (0.85% NaCl) and 5 mL of the 
suspension was mixed into 100 mL molten PDA at 45ºC. 30 mL 
of the mixture was poured into a Petri dish (9 cm in diameter) to </p>

<p>give a solid plate. Three wells (7 mm in diameter) were prepared 
in each seeded agar plate and each well was filled with 100 μl of 
the antibiotic fermentation broth of strain A01. The plates were 
incubated at 25ºC for 2 d. The diameter of the inhibition zones 
were measured with a vernier caliper. Each treatment had three 
replications. 
For estimating the antifungal activity of the bioactive extracts 
dissolved in organic solvents, the paper disc agar diffusion 
bioassay modified from the method of Valgas et al. (25) was 
used. The sterile filter paper disk (10 mm in diameter) was 
saturated with the bioactive extract solution, and then dried up. 
Repeat this three times. The paper disk treated with bioactive 
solution was placed on the surface of a seeded agar plate 
prepared as described above. The clear inhibition zone around 
the paper disk was measured after incubation for 2 d at 25ºC. </p>

<p>Evaluation of the control effect in greenhouse 
Autoclaved soil (121ºC for 2 h) was mixed with peat moss 
(1:1) and placed into 5 × 9 × 12 cm plastic pots. Two germinated 
tomato seeds (Lycopersicon esculentum Mill. cv. Zhongshu 
No.6) were planted into each pot and grown in a greenhouse at 
25 ± 2ºC under natural light. The experiment included four 
treatments: 1) 1:5 dilution of the filtrate from fermented broth of 
strain A01; 2) chemical fungicide Pyrimethanil (Qinggyuanbao 
Biotech Ltd., Inner Mongolia, China) in the concentration of 
500 μg mL </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>; 3) wettable powder of the fungicide Polymyxin 
(Yanbian Chunlei Biopharmcieuticals Ltd., China) in the 
concentration of 30 μg mL </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>; and 4) water as the negative control. 
45 tomato plants for each treatment and three replicates were 
performed. 
Each of the solutions was sprayed on the surface of tomato 
plants at the first bloom stage. While the surface of the leaves 
become dry, the plants were sprayed with the spore suspension 
(10 
6 spores mL </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) of B. cinerea, and then were placed in an 
enclosed plastic chamber in which the humidity was kept at 
100% for 48 h. Plants were then incubated at 22ºC in the 
greenhouse until symptoms appeared on leaves of the control 
plants. The disease rate and disease index was surveyed based 
on the criteria given by Bioassay Division of Institute for the 
Control of Agrochemicals, Ministry of Agriculture, China (6). </p>

<p>Taxonomic determination of strain A01 
For the morphological characterization, strain A01 was 
cultured on GYM agar (15) and oatmeal agar (13) at 28ºC for 7 d, 
and observed using a microscope (Nikon ECLIPSE TE2000-U, 
Japan). Cultural characteristics were determined by growing 
the strain on 6 media namely GAOs no.1 agar, starch agar (13), 
GYM agar, oatmeal agar, Bennett's agar, and nutrient agar (17) 
plates at 28ºC for 2 wk to observe mycelia color and diffusible 
pigments. The physiological and biochemical characteristics 
were tested using the media and methods described by Ruan 
(17) and Shirling &amp; Gottlieb (19). </p>

<p>Antifungal metabolite of Actinomyces </p>



<p>The 16S rDNA sequence of strain A01 was analyzed using 
the method of Hopwood et al. (12). The PCR was carried out 
using the universal bacterial 16S rDNA primers and the PCR 
product was sequenced directly with the Taq DyeDeoxy 
Terminator Cycle Sequencing Kit (Biosystem, INC, USA). 
Electrophoresis and data collection was performed with an 
automated DNA Sequencer (model 377, Applied Biosystems, 
USA). The 16S rDNA sequence was assembled and blasted 
against sequences in the GenBank database to determine the 
identity. </p>

<p>Purification and chemical characterization of the bioactive 
substance 
The fermented broth of strain A01 was mixed with 100% 
ethanol (1:1, v/v) and placed at 4ºC for 2 h. The mixture was then 
stirred up and centrifuged at 5,000 g for 20 min. The supernatant 
was concentrated at 45ºC under vacuum. The concentrate was 
adsorbed into macroporous resin D4006 (Chemical factory of 
Nankai University, Tianjin, China) and then eluted seriatim with 
deionized water, 50% methanol and 80% ethanol at a rate of 0.5 
mL min </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>. The eluent were collected into tubes in fractions of 5 
mL with a BSZ-100 automatic fraction collector (Shanghai Huxi 
Analytical Instrumentation Factory, Shanghai). After being bio-
assayed using the paper disc agar diffusion method with B. 
cinerea as the indicator, the active fractions were combined 
and concentrated under vacuum at 45ºC, then diluted with twice 
volume of methanol:water (7:3, v/v) and separated again by 
using a 26.0 mm × 400 mm chromatography column of 200 mesh 
silica gel (Beijing Chemical Reagent Co., Beijing, China) with 
the mobile phase consisting of chloroform-methanol-water 
(2:3:1, v/v/v). The eluent was collected, concentrated and bio-
assayed again. The active fractions were finally separated by a 
cycled preparative HPLC (Japan Analytical Industry Co., Ltd., 
Japan) with C18 reverse phase column (LC-9101-JAIGEL-ODS, 
Japan), using the mobile phase of 70% methanol (Fisher, USA) 
at a rate of 3 mL min </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>, and monitored at 305 nm with a UV 
detector (JAI UV 3702, Japan). The fractions corresponding to 
each absorption peak were collected separately with a fraction 
collector (JAI FC-206, Japan) and bio-assayed. The main active 
fraction was picked out as the terminal sample and concentrated 
with a SpeedVac centrifuging concentrator (Thermo SPD1010, 
USA). The purity of the concentrate was examined using 
analytical HPLC (LC-10AT, Shimadzu Corporation, Japan) with 
analytical C18 reverse phase column. 
The chemical structure of the terminal antimicrobial 
compound was determined with spectroscopy methods. The 
nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) analysis was performed 
using a Bruker AVANCE DRX-500 NMR spectrometer (Bruker 
Instruments Inc., Germany) with N, N-dimethylformamide (d-
DMF) as a solvent. High resolution FT-mass spectrometry was 
conducted using a 9.4T Apex Q-FT-MS spectrometer (Bruker 
Instruments Inc., Germany) under the following conditions: </p>

<p>capillary 4000 v, dry gas 4.0 L/s, ion source temperature 180ºC, 
scan range 300-2000 amu, syringe pump 1.5 mL min </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>. The infrared 
spectrum within 4000 cm </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>-400 cm 
-1 was measured using a 
Tensor 27 Nicolet spectrometer (Bruker Instruments Inc., 
Germany), and the ultra-violet spectrum within 190-400 nm using 
a UV-VIS 3010 spectrophotometer (Hitachi Ltd., Japan). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
The experiment data of the antimicrobial activities in vitro 
and control efficacies to tomato gray mold in greenhouses were 
analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13.0</rs> for Windows. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The antimicrobial spectrum of A01 
The result of mycelial growth inhibition assay showed that 
the fermented broth of strain A01 presented a strong inhibitory 
activity against all of the 14 plant pathogenic fungi and one 
yeast S. cervisiae tested in the experiment (Table 1). The average 
diameter of inhibition zones for the pathogens (about 4.0 cm) 
was greater than that for the yeast (about 3.0 cm). Especially 
the inhibition zone for the pathogens M. laxa and E. turcicum 
reached respectively up to 4.8 cm and 4.7 cm. However, no 
antibacterial activity was found against the tested bacteria. </p>

<p>The control effect in greenhouse 
Five days after being inoculated with B. cinerea, the plants 
treated with Pyrimethanil and water were wilted, some leaves 
were chlorotic, covered with gray mold in some surface areas, 
and fall off. While the negative control plants were severely </p>

<p>Table 1. Antifungal activities of fermentation broth of strain 
A01. </p>

<p>Pathogens 
Average inhibition 
diameter (cm) </p>

<p>Fusarium oxysporum f. sp. vasinfectum 
4.30± 0.00 
Fusarium oxysporum f. sp. niveum 
4.13± 0.07 
Fusarium oxysporum. f. sp. conglutinans 4.47± 0.03 
Botrytis cinerea (on grape) 
4.30± 0.00 
Botrytis cinerea (on tomato) 
4.03± 0.03 
Botrytis cinerea (on eggplant) 
4.50± 0.00 
Pyricularia oryzae 
4.00± 0.00 
Cladosporium fulvum 
4.40± 0.00 
Exerphilum turcicum 
4.63± 0.03 
Alternaria solani 
4.50± 0.00 
Monilinia laxa 
4.77± 0.03 
Alternaria mali 
4.07± 0.07 
Colletotrichum capsici 
4.10± 0.00 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae 
2.97± 0.09 </p>



<p>Lu, G.C. et al. </p>

<p>diseased, there was a reduction in the level of severity in the 
plants treated with this fungicide (about 80 vs 45 disease index, 
Table 2). However, all plants died 10 days after treatment in 
both cases. In contrast plants sprayed with Polyoxin and the 
fermented broth of strain A01 had much lower levels of disease 
incidence than control plants (about 100 vs 35, respectively) 
and lower disease severities (about 80 vs 15). Both the fungicide 
and the filtrate provided about 85% disease reduction. </p>

<p>Taxonomic classification of strain A01 
The cultural, biochemical and physiological characteristics 
of strain A01 are typical properties of genus Streptomyces (Table 
3 and Table 4). A 1,270 bp 16S rDNA partial sequence of strain 
A01 was determined. The DNA sequence was deposited in 
GenBank under accession no.EF532323. A standard nucleotide-
nucleotide BLAST search (1) against the GenBank database 
using this sequence showed that there is the highest homology 
in the 16S rDNA sequence between strain A01 and S. lydicus 
Y15507.1. According to the polyphasic studies, strain A01 was 
identified as S. lydicus. </p>

<p>Purification and structure elucidation of the antifungal 
compound 
The results of the bioassay showed that the active 
constituents were mainly collected from the mobile phase of 
80% ethanol in the case of the macroporous resin separation 
and the adjacent fractions of the eluate of chloroform-methanol-
water (2:3:1, v/v/v) from the silica gel column. The active 
fractions resulted in 6 peaks on the first HPLC separation 
spectrum, and the fraction corresponding to the peak appearing 
at the elution time of 57.399 min was identified as the active one. 
The active fraction was separated again by second HPLC. A 
fraction with higher activity was obtained as the terminal 
constituent, which corresponded to the peak at the elution time 
of 38.399 min on the last HPLC spectrum. Only one peak was </p>

<p>Table 2. Biocontrol effects of fermentation broth of strain A01 against tomato gray mold in greenhouse. </p>

<p>Treatment 
Days after 
Disease 
Disease 
Control 
treatment 
rate* 
index* 
efficacy </p>

<p>Water 
5 
99.4± 0.31 a 
78.5± 0.33 a 
10 
99.7± 0.12 a 
82.4± 0.82 a 
Pyrimethanil (500 μg mL </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) 
5 
91.9± 0.71 b 
43.1± 0.65 b 
45.1 
10 
92.9± 0.20 a 
45.7± 0.46 b 
44.5 
Polyoxin (30 μg mL </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) 
5 
29.5± 0.27 e 
13.3± 0.38 c 
83.1 
10 
37.9±1.70 c 
14.5± 0.58 c 
82.4 
Fermentation broth 
5 
35.1± 0.57 d 
8.1± 0.52 d 
89.7 
10 
33.7± 0.26 c 
14.0± 0.87 c 
83.0 </p>

<p>* The data are the average of three replicates ± SE. Data in the same column followed by the same letter are not significantly different (P &lt;0.05) 
according to analysis of variance. </p>

<p>Table 3. Cultural characteristics of strain A01 on different 
media. </p>

<p>Agar media Growth 
Aerial 
Substrate 
Soluble 
mycelium mycelium 
pigments </p>

<p>GAOs no.1 ++ 
white/gray 
yellow 
light yellow 
Bennett's 
++ 
light gray 
brown 
light yellow 
Nutrient 
+++ 
gray 
light brown 
none 
GYM 
+++ 
light gray 
brown 
yellow 
Oatmeal 
++ 
gray 
light brown light brown 
Starch 
++ white /gray 
brown 
light yellow </p>

<p>Note: +++, very well; ++, well. </p>

<p>detected for the terminal constituent by analytical HPLC, which 
revealed that the constituent contained a single compound. 
The relative area of the peak suggested a purity up to 99.503% 
for the compound, sufficiently meeting the requirement for 
structural analysis. The terminal active constituent was dried in 
a vacuum into white powder that was partially soluble in N, N-
dimethylformamide (DMF), dimethyl sulphoxide (DMSO), 
pyridine, acetic acid with water, methanol or ethanol with water, 
but insoluble in acetone, chloroform, diethyl ether, ethyl acetate, 
and water. 
The UV spectrum showed that the active compound 
dissolved in methanol-water presented four typical absorbance 
peaks at wavelengths 281 nm, 291 nm, 305 nm and 319 nm, 
which is the typical characteristic of conjugated polyene 
chemicals. In the IR spectrum, the peaks at ν&gt;3000 cm 
-1 indicated 
that there is a typical carboxyl-structure; the ν=1716 cm 
-1 peak 
revealed a conjugated ester; the ν=1570 cm 
-1 peak corresponded 
to a primary amine; and the ν=1270-1150 cm 
-1 peaks showed the 
existence of different C-O-. The molecular weight 665 and the 
molecular formula C33H47NO13 of the antibiotic compound of </p>

<p>Antifungal metabolite of Actinomyces </p>



<p>strain A01 were deduced by high resolution FT -mass 
spectroscopy (M+Na, m/z 688.2938, calculated 688.2940) (Fig. 
1). In the </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>H-NMR spectrum (Fig. 2), the hydrogen on the 
carboxyl-was neutralized in the solvent DMF, causing the 
disappearance of peak δ=12and the presence of two solvent 
peaks of δ=3 and 8 at the same time; the group of peaks next to 
δ=6 represented the hydrogen bonded on the conjugated ester, 
and the group of peaks around δ=5 presented a -OH. In the 
13 C-
NMR spectrum (Fig. 3), the peaks of δ=180 and 165 are indicative 
of the existence of carboxyl and ester groups, the peak of δ=130 
was produced by polyethylene, and the most intensive peak 
was given by the solvent DMF. In addition, COSY, TOCSY, 
DEPT, NOE, HMBC and HMQC spectrometry were also 
conducted on the compound. Based on the analysis of NMR 
data and other chemical characteristics, the antibiotic compound 
of A01 turned out to have the same structure as natamycin as 
shown in Fig. 4. </p>

<p>Table 4. Physiological and biochemical characteristics of strain 
A01. </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Results </p>

<p>Gram stain 
+ 
Nitrate reduction 
-
Melanin production 
-
H2S production 
-
Citrate acidolysis 
-
Degradation of : 
Gelatin 
+ 
Starch 
+ 
Urea 
+ 
Cellulose 
-
Esculin 
+ 
Growth on sole carbon sources: 
Fructose 
+ 
Mannose 
+ 
Glucose 
+ 
Maltose 
+ 
Sucrose 
+ 
Lactose 
+ 
Rhamnose 
-
Xylose 
-
Arabinose 
-
Sorbose 
-
Growth at: 
1% NaCl 
+ 
3% NaCl 
+ 
5% NaCl 
+ 
7% NaCl 
-</p>

<p>Note: +, positive reaction; -, negative reaction. </p>

<p>Figure 1. High resolution FT -mass spectrum of the bioactive 
compound of strain A01. </p>

<p>Figure 3. 
13 C NMR spectrum of the bioactive compound of 
strain A01 recorded at 
13 C-500MHz and 25º. </p>

<p>Figure 2. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>H NMR spectrum of the bioactive compound of strain 
A01 recorded at </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>H-500MHz and 25º. </p>



<p>Lu, G.C. et al. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Actinomycetes are major producer of pharmaceuticals and 
agricultural pesticides due to its ability to produce antibiotics. 
Among the 10,000 antimicrobial active compounds produced 
by microorganisms, over 50% were from Actinomycete (2). Many 
S. lydicus strains have been reported to produce different types 
of secondary metabolites, such as Chandramycin (21), 
Lydicamycin (11), Ganefromycin (7), and Streptolydigin (20). S. 
lydicus WYEC108 has been studied extensively for agricultural 
applications in recent years (16). It is produced commercially to 
control soil-borne and leaf surface diseases in turf and 
greenhouse crops (27). WYEC108 produces chitinase (14), which 
functions synergistically with several antibiotics (9,23) to kill 
other fungi. 
In this study, strain A01 presented a strong antifungal effect 
in vitro and effectiveness in controlling tomato gray mold in 
pot experiments in greenhouse. On the basis of morphological, 
cultural, physiological and biochemical characteristics, and 16S 
rDNA sequence analysis, the strain was identified to be S. 
lydicus. It could produce high antifungal substance by liquid 
fermentation. The chemical structural analysis with UV, IR, MS, 
and NMR confirmed that the main antifungal compound 
produced by A01 is natamycin. 
Natamycin is a macrolide polyene antifungal drug, which is 
widely used for the treatment of fungal keratitis and also in the 
food industry to prevent mold contamination of cheese and 
other nonsterile foods (3). Now, it has been used as a natural 
biological preservative and anti-microbial additive for food in 
more than 30 countries (4). Up to now, the antibiotic was reported 
to be produced by S. chattanovgensis, S. natalensis, and S. 
gilvosporeus. To the best of our knowledge, no documented 
record indicated that the antibiotic natamycin was produced by 
S. lydicus, and there is no systematic report on the use of 
natamycin to control plant fungal diseases. </p>

<p>Our research results revealed that the antibiotic natamycin 
can be produced by S. lydicus. This provided a new producing 
microorganism resource for natamycin. Furthermore, the 
bioactive compound was proved having a broad antifungal 
spectrum to plant pathogenic fungi. The findings from this study 
suggest the potential of using natamycin as a biocontrol agent 
for plant fungal diseases. Further evaluations are needed for 
the biocontrol efficiency to plant diseases in the fields. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This research was jointly supported by the National Natural 
Scientific Foundation of China (No.30671346), Beijing Natural 
Scientific Foundation (No.6072010), and Beijing Municipal 
Science &amp; Technology Program (D0706005000091 and 
D0706005040231). </p>

<p>RESUMO </p>

<p>Identificação de um metabólito antifúngico produzido 
pela cepa Actinomyces A01 </p>

<p>A cepa Actinomyces A01 foi isolada do solo de um campo 
agrícola no subúrbio de Beijing, China. De acordo com as 
características morfológicas, culturais, fisiológicas e 
bioquímicas, e análise da sequência 16S rDNA , a cepa A01 foi 
identificada como Streptomyces lydicus. Nos testes de espectro 
antimicrobiano, a cepa A01 apresentou atividade inibitória 
intensa e estável contra vários fungos patogênicos para plantas, 
como Fusarium oxysporum, Botrytis cinerea, Monilia laxa, 
etc. Entretanto, não foi encontrada atividade antibacteriana. 
Em experimentos em estufas, o desenvolvimento do fungo cinza 
do tomate foi fortemente inibido pelo tratamento com o caldo 
de fermentação da cepa A01, com eficiência superior à do 
pyremethanil e polyoxin. Por cromatografia em coluna e HPLC, 
obteve-se um composto fúngico (pureza 99,503%), cuja análise 
estrutural por UV, IR, MS e NMR revelou ser natamicina, um 
antibiótico polienico produzido por S. chattanovgensis, S. 
natalensis e S.gilvosporeus, empregado como conservador 
biológico natural em alimentos. O presente estudo relata a 
detecção de uma nova cepa produtora de natamicina e sua 
aplicação potencial como um agente de controle biológico de 
doenças fúngicas em plantas. </p>

<p>Palavras-chave: Streptomyces lydicus, natamicina, doenças 
fúngicas em plantas, controle biológico </p>



<p>Figure 4. The structure of the bioactive compound of strain 
A01. </p>

<p>Antifungal metabolite of Actinomyces </p>





</text></tei>