<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3793542" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Objective The pelvic fl oor is an integrated 
structure; dysfunctions may lead to a wide range 
of symptoms, involving voiding, defecation and 
sexual functioning (SF). Functional symptoms 
such as constipation and lower abdominal pain 
are often caused by pelvic fl oor dysfunction 
(PFD), and they highly impact the quality of life. 
Multiple specialists are responsible for a specifi c 
part of the pelvic fl oor, but its treatment asks 
for a holistic approach. The authors are still 
unaware of gastroenterologists' knowledge 
on PFD or whether they are addressing pelvic 
fl oor complaints in their daily practice. 
Design A 42-itemed anonymous 
questionnaire was mailed to all 402 members 
of the Dutch Society of Gastroenterology 
(gastroenterologists and residents-in-training). 
Results 169 (42%) questionnaires were 
analysed. Most gastroenterologists address 
lower urinary tract symptoms in their history-
taking, 92% in female patients and 84% in male 
patients. When patients indicate irritable bowel 
syndrome-like complaints, more than 60% of 
the physicians inquire about SF to their female 
patients, compared with 38% inquiries to male 
patients (p&lt;0.001). A reason not to inquire about 
SF is a lack of knowledge about female and male 
sexuality (19% and 23%, respectively). Forty-
six per cent of the respondents regard it rather 
important to receive more training on PFD in 
male patients versus 61% in female patients. 
Conclusion Awareness of PFD is not 
yet routinely integrated into the history 
taken by gastroenterologists. </p>

<p>of the pelvic floor may lead to a wide range 
of symptoms, involving voiding, sexual, 
genital and defecatory functions. 
1 2 For 
example, vaginism is related to dyssynergic 
defecation and vesicourethral dyssynergia. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Because the pelvic floor is an integrated 
functional unit, unsuspected pathology 
may lie outside the focus of a given spe-
cialty. Therefore, urologists, gynaecolo-
gists, gastroenterologists and colorectal 
surgeons should share their knowledge and 
be aware of the pathologies of neighbour-
ing specialties. Depending on the chief pre-
senting complaint, the pelvic floor patient 
will find his way to the specialist responsi-
ble for that specific area. In the majority of 
cases, patients do not mention complaints 
in other areas if they are not specifically 
asked about them. 
4 Gynaecologists are 
alert to pelvic floor tissue-stretching and 
pudendal nerve damage during vaginal 
delivery, and are aware that traumatic dam-
age can cause faecal and urinary inconti-
nence. 
5 6 Many urologists screen for sexual 
dysfunction as well. 
7 Gastroenterologists 
are confronted with the posterior pelvic 
floor compartment disorders. Results of 
reports suggest that they could be a feature 
in patients with irritable bowel syndrome 
(IBS). 
8-10 In many cases these posterior pel-
vic floor compartment disorders are non-
specific and associated with structural, 
neuromuscular and functional defects, 
giving rise to symptoms such as prolapse, 
lower abdominal pain, dyssynergic defeca-
tion, faecal incontinence, stool trapping 
and constipation. 
11 12 Patients consulting 
the gastroenterologist with those symp-
toms are very likely to have dysfunction 
of the pelvic floor and may need to be 
referred to a pelvic floor physiotherapist, 
sexologist, urologist or a psychologist to 
treat his or her complaints in total. </p>

<p>▶ Additional tables are 
published online only. To view 
the fi les please visit the journal 
online (http://fg.bmj.com/ 
content/3/3.toc). </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Urology, Leiden 
University Medical Center, 
Leiden, The Netherlands </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of 
Gastroenterology, Utrecht 
University Medical Center, 
Utrecht, The Netherlands </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of Surgery, 
Haaglanden Medical Center, 
the Hague, The Netherlands </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Department of Medical 
Statistics, Leiden University 
Medical Center, Leiden, 
The Netherlands </p>

<p>Correspondence to 
Dr H W Elzevier, Department of 
Urology, LUMC, Albinusdreef 
2, Leiden, The Netherlands; 
H.W.Elzevier@lumc.nl </p>

<p>Received 27 January 2012 
Accepted 28 February 2012 
Published Online First 
24 April 2012 </p>

<p>RESEARCH </p>

<p>Pelvic fl oor complaints in 
gastroenterology practice: results of 
a survey in The Netherlands </p>

<p>Melianthe P J Nicolai, 
1 Herma H Fidder, 
2 Milou D Bekker, 
3 Hein Putter, </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Rob C M Pelger, 
1 Henk W Elzevier </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Frontline Gastroenterology 2012;3:166-171. doi:10.1136/fl gastro-2012-100133 </p>

<p>PROFESSIONAL MATTERS </p>



<p>demographic questions were unanswered); their mean 
age was 42.3 (SD±9.8) years; 60.4% of the respond-
ents were men. The respondents were equally divided 
between university hospitals, teaching hospitals and 
district general hospitals (table 1). </p>

<p>Lower urinary tract symptoms </p>

<p>The majority of the respondents asked each patient 
with abdominal pain or defecation problems about 
lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS) when patients 
indicated to have specific complaints (table 2). Most 
doctors (91.7%) asked female patients about micturi-
tion, 83.8% asked male patients. Female physicians 
asked significantly more often about LUTS in female 
patients (98.3%), compared with male physicians 
(89.3%; p=0.034). </p>

<p>Gastroenterologists have not yet been surveyed 
regarding patient assessment of pelvic floor complaints, 
nor is there any information about their perspectives 
regarding subjects such as sexual dysfunction. We 
hypothesise that most gastroenterologists are aware of 
pelvic floor-related problems, but they do not consist-
ently inquire about pelvic floor complaints, probably 
due to a lack of experience in this field or a lack of 
time in their daily practices. </p>

<p>Methods 
In the autumn of 2010, an online questionnaire was 
emailed to all the Dutch gastroenterologists (n=262) 
and residents-in-training (n=140), followed by two 
reminder emails. Eight months later, a postal mailing 
was sent to the non-responders. 
The 42-itemed questionnaire (see online supple-
mentary appendix), which was designed by a urolo-
gist (HWE) and a gastroenterologist (HHF), addressed 
pelvic floor-related complaints and the gastroenter-
ologists' beliefs and overall perceptions of pelvic floor 
complaints in relation to sexual functioning. The 
results obtained by the questions about sexual abuse 
will be published separately. 
We carried out a small pilot survey with eight gastro-
enterologists to evaluate the questionnaire and adjusted 
it accordingly. Validation of the questionnaire was not 
performed. The survey was accompanied by a letter 
explaining the objectives of the study. All data were 
collected anonymously. Demographic data included 
type of practice, medical degree (resident or gastroen-
terologist), gender and age. 
Data analysis was performed with the help of the 
medical statistics department in our centre (HP), mak-
ing use of <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> release V.<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">18.0</rs> . Frequencies were used 
to estimate the prevalence of inquiring about the differ-
ent domains of the pelvic floor. Bivariate associations 
between the groups and the types of answers were cal-
culated using the Pearson χ2 procedure; two-sided p 
values &lt;0.05 were considered statistically significant. 
Some questions with more than one possible answer, 
and with open answers, were grouped together for 
analysis. In The Netherlands, ethical approval is not 
required for questionnaires of this kind. </p>

<p>Results 
Of the 402 mailed questionnaires, 243 questionnaires 
were returned. Sixty contained refusal notes or a noti-
fication of unavailability to complete the questionnaire 
due to a lack of time or interest. Of the 183 (response 
rate, 45.2%) filled in, 14 were incomplete. We only 
used questionnaires in which at least 90% of all appli-
cable questions were answered. This means that 169 
questionnaires were analysed (42%). 
In these questionnaires, 0.6-3.6% of the questions 
about the pelvic floor and 5.3% of the sociodemo-
graphic questions were not answered. 
The majority of respondents were gastroenterolo-
gists (66.3%); 28.4% were residents (5.3% of the </p>

<p>Table 1 Demographic characteristics of respondents 
(n=169) </p>

<p>Age (years) 
n (%) </p>

<p>Median 43.2 (SD 9.7) 
169 (100) 
Gender 
Male 
102 (60.4) 
Female 
58 (34.3) 
Unknown 
9 (5.3) 
Medical degree 
Gastroenterologist 
112 (66.3) 
Resident gastroenterology 
48 (28.4) 
Unknown 
9 (5.3) 
Type of clinic/practice 
Tertiary referral centre (or university hospital) 
51 (30.2) 
District general teaching hospital 
66 (39.1) 
District general hospital 
43 (25.4) 
Unknown 
9 (5.3) </p>

<p>Table 2 Micturition function evaluation </p>

<p>Do you ask each 
patient about 
LUTS symptoms? </p>

<p>Female 
patient </p>

<p>Male patient 
p Value* </p>

<p>n=169 
n=169 
n (%) 
n (%) 
Yes 
118 (69.8) 
79 (46.7) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Do you ask about 
LUTS when a 
patient presents 
with specifi c 
gastrointestinal 
complaints? </p>

<p>Female 
Male </p>

<p>n=169 
n=167 </p>

<p>n (%) 
n (%) </p>

<p>Yes 
155 (91.7) 
140 (83.8) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>*Pearson χ2 (two sided) test. 
LUTS, lower urinary tract symptoms. </p>

<p>Frontline Gastroenterology 2012;3:166-171. doi:10.1136/fl gastro-2012-100133 </p>

<p>PROFESSIONAL MATTERS </p>



<p>male patients this percentage lies considerably lower 
(2.5%; p&lt;0.01). However, when female patients 
reported specific symptoms such as lower abdominal 
pain, 60% of the doctors asked them about SF. Male 
patients are asked considerably less often about SF 
(only 37.9%; p&lt;0.001). Table 3 shows an overview of 
the specific complaints that seem to evoke a gastroen-
terologist's inquiry about SF. 
Doctors gave a variety of reasons for not asking 
their patients about SF. Many reported that they did 
not see the importance of it in their practice, 30.3% 
in male patients and 11.5% in females (p&lt;0.001). A 
gender difference seemed to exist between the phy-
sicians, since male doctors stated significantly more 
often that they did not see the importance of inquiring 
about male SF (37.3%), compared with their female 
colleagues (20.7%) (p=0.03). 
Other reasons not to inquire about male SF were a 
lack of knowledge about the topic (23.3%), the dif-
ficulty of raising the topic (8.6%), and 8.0% did not 
know what to do when patients stated to be with sex-
ual dysfunction. 
In female patients, the reasons not to ask were simi-
lar: 18.8% stated a lack of knowledge about the topic 
as a main reason, 6.1% a difficulty of raising the topic, 
and 7.3% a lack of knowledge about the implications 
in case of a positive answer. Only a few physicians 
referred to a lack of time as the reason not to ask about 
female SF (7.9%) (table 4). 
To the question: 'Do you think it is important to 
pay more attention to sexuality related abdominal 
complaints during your training?' Concerning male 
patients, 46.3% answered 'rather' and 12.5% answered 
'very important'. Concerning female patients, 61.3% 
answered 'rather important' and 16.9% answered 
'very important'. A significant difference was seen </p>

<p>Less than 4% of the physicians mentioned lack of 
time as a reason not to inquire about LUTS. Three per 
cent stated that they did not know what to do when 
a female patient presents with LUTS, compared with 
5.4% in male patients (p&lt;0.01). There were no sig-
nificant differences between specialists and residents 
concerning the inquiry of LUTS. 
Gastroenterologists and residents estimated that a 
mean of 30.5% (SD±20.2) of the female patients in 
their patient population has LUTS; for male patients a 
mean of 12.6% (SD±10.9) was estimated </p>

<p>Sexual function </p>

<p>One of the primary goals of the survey was to assess 
whether gastroenterologists and residents address 
patients' sexual function (SF) as a part of history-tak-
ing. A small percentage of the physicians asked their 
female patients regularly about SF (13.3%), while for </p>

<p>Table 4 Reasons not to inquire about sexual 
dysfunction </p>

<p>Reasons not to 
inquire about 
sexual function </p>

<p>Female patient Male patient </p>

<p>p Value* </p>

<p>n=165 
n=163 </p>

<p>n(%) 
n (%) </p>

<p>I do not see the 
importance of it in 
my practice </p>

<p>19 (11.5) 
50 (30.7) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Lack of knowledge 
on the topic </p>

<p>31 (18.8) 
38 (23.3) 
NS </p>

<p>Diffi culty raising the 
topic </p>

<p>10 (6.1) 
14 (8.6) 
NS </p>

<p>Lack of knowledge 
about the 
implications in case 
of a positive answer </p>

<p>12 (7.3) 
13 (8.0) 
NS </p>

<p>Lack of time 
13 (7.9) 
12 (7.4) 
NS </p>

<p>*Pearson χ2 (two sided) test. 
NS, not signifi cant. </p>

<p>Table 3 Sexual function (SF) evaluation </p>

<p>Do you ask each 
patient about SF? </p>

<p>Female 
patient 
Male patient 
p Value* </p>

<p>n=165 
n=163 
n (%) 
n (%) 
Yes 
22 (13.3) 
4 (2.5) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Do you ask 
about SF when a 
patient presents 
with specifi c 
gastrointestinal 
complaints? </p>

<p>Female 
patient 
Male patient </p>

<p>n=161 
n=161 
n(%) 
n(%) 
Yes 
102 (63.4) 
61 (37.9) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Which complaints? 
(multiple answers 
possible) </p>

<p>Female 
patient 
Male patient </p>

<p>n=102 
n=58 
n (%) 
n (%) 
Lower abdominal pain 39 (38.2) 
8 (13.8) 
&lt;0.001 
Constipation 
25 (24.5) 
7 (12.1) 
NS 
Faecal incontinence 
13 (12.7) 
12 (20.7) 
NS 
Suspicion of 
infl ammatory bowel 
disease </p>

<p>15 (14.7) 
9 (15.5) 
NS </p>

<p>Dyssynergic defecation 10 (9.8) 
1 (1.7) 
NS 
Suspicion of pelvic 
fl oor dysfunction </p>

<p>15 (14.7) 
1 (1.7) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Suspicion of sexual 
abuse </p>

<p>5 (4.9) 
1 (1.7) 
NS </p>

<p>Perianal problems 
(fi steling) </p>

<p>11 (10.7) 
9 (15.5) 
NS </p>

<p>Other 
14 (13.7) † 
21 (36.2)  ‡ 
NA </p>

<p>*Pearson χ2 (two sided) test. 
 †Mostly dyspareunia. 
 ‡Mostly 'on indication' 
NA, not applicable; NS, not signifi cant. </p>

<p>Frontline Gastroenterology 2012;3:166-171. doi:10.1136/fl gastro-2012-100133 </p>

<p>PROFESSIONAL MATTERS </p>



<p>their female patients for sexual dysfunction. Similarly, 
in a recent survey among urologists, 6% stated they ask 
each female patient about SF. Yet, a much larger group 
(87%) stated that they ask about SF if a patient presents 
with specific complaints, such as lower abdominal 
pain, urinary or faecal incontinence, urgency or fre-
quency. 
7 Comparable studies carried out by mem-
bers of the British Society of Urogynaecology and 
the American Urogynaecologic Society, with respect 
to female sexual dysfunction, showed that 50% of 
the British urologists and gynaecologists screened for 
female sexual dysfunction compared with 77% of the 
American members. 
6 7 21 These percentages are in con-
cordance with our results. 
To our knowledge, these data are unique because 
this is the first survey carried out on gastroenterolo-
gists regarding their views on pelvic floor function. 
However, this study has some limitations. We used a 
non-validated questionnaire in which cultural com-
ponents were not taken into account. Unfortunately, 
validated instruments that evaluate doctors' practices 
and beliefs do not exist. However, after analysing the 
results of the first reminder by email (111 respond-
ents) the results were very similar to the results as they 
are now (169 questionnaires), this points to a good 
validity of our results. Furthermore, as in most ques-
tionnaire studies, there may be a bias in reporting. The 
respondents may have overestimated the frequency 
of their inquiry about pelvic floor function, or they 
overestimate to give more 'socially accepted' answers. 
Attempts were made to reduce such a bias by making 
the survey anonymous. We analysed only 42% of the 
questionnaires, less than half of the Dutch gastroenter-
ologists. Although the response rate in postal question-
naires is mostly around 40%, 
22 the non-respondents 
may have different beliefs, attitudes and practice pat-
terns than the respondents; this may have caused a 
selection bias. Therefore, a higher return may provide 
a different set of answers and values. However, the 
demographic data of the respondents suggested a very 
representative group with a normal distribution com-
pared with the total population of gastroenterologists 
and residents. 
In this study, a significant difference is observed 
between male and female physicians. Male physicians 
state significantly more often that they did not see the 
importance of inquiring about SF in their patients. To 
explain these findings, we hypothesise that this is due 
to sex-role differences among physicians, since it is 
unlikely that professional socialisation processes would 
completely counteract normal sex-role differences 
among physicians. To the extent that female physicians 
have been socialised in the traditional female sex-role, 
they may be more nurturing and expressive and have 
stronger interpersonal orientations than male physi-
cians. 
23 In addition, a difference is observed between 
male and female patients, since female patients are asked 
about PFD significantly more often, and the majority of </p>

<p>between male and female patients, as 34.4% of the 
physicians stated that it would be 'slightly' important 
to have more training on sexuality regarding male 
patients; on the other hand, only 18.1% found it to 
be just 'slightly' important when it concerned female 
patients (p&lt;0.01). 
The estimated prevalence of sexual dysfunction in 
the gastroenterology practice was 20.5% (SD±15.37) 
in female patients and 10.5% (SD±10.3) in male 
patients. 
Because the issue of sexual abuse history is signifi-
cant in pelvic floor function, and it is important how 
gastroenterologists approach this issue, we published 
the data on sexual abuse separately in Journal of Sexual 
Medicine. </p>

<p>Discussion 
This study was performed to assess the approach of 
gastroenterologists and their residents regarding pel-
vic floor complaints in their daily practices. It appears 
that most of them address LUTS in their anamnesis 
(&gt;80%). More than 60% asked about SF when a 
female patient presented with specific gastrointesti-
nal complaints. An implicit assumption of our survey 
is that Dutch gastroenterologists seem to be aware of 
the value that inquiry about female SF has in assess-
ing female patients with gastrointestinal complaints. 
However, significantly less physicians ask male patients 
about SF (38%, p&lt;0.001); many state they did not see 
the purpose of this in their practice. We hypothesised 
that lack of time might be an important reason why 
gastroenterologists do not ask about pelvic floor dys-
function (PFD), but this does not seem to be the most 
important factor (&lt;8%). The main reason appears to 
be a lack of knowledge about the subject. Many doc-
tors stated more training is needed on PFD in relation 
to abdominal and defecatory complaints, especially 
female physicians who were interested in additional 
training. 
Mounting literature has described the connection 
between PFD and faecal incontinence, 
12-14 constipa-
tion 
15 16 and IBS. 
17 18 However, our results show that 
gastroenterologists are not consistent in inquiring 
about pelvic floor complaints, although most of them 
seem to be aware of the integrated function of the pel-
vic floor. Gastroenterologists believe that an average 
of 20% of their female patients are with a sexual dys-
function. The percentage of sexual dysfunction in male 
patients is estimated even lower. Yet, the prevalence 
of female sexual dysfunction has been shown to be as 
high as 43% in the general population; 
19 the preva-
lence of female sexual dysfunction in sexually active 
women attending a urogynaecology outpatient clinic 
ranges from 48% to 64%. </p>

<p>20 21 </p>

<p>Other surveys regarding the perspectives of gastro-
enterologists on pelvic floor patients have not been 
done before. A couple of surveys among urologists and 
gynaecologists, regarding the subject of female sexual 
dysfunction, showed that only a minority screen all </p>

<p>Frontline Gastroenterology 2012;3:166-171. doi:10.1136/fl gastro-2012-100133 </p>

<p>PROFESSIONAL MATTERS </p>



<p>survey, cleaned and analysed the data, drafted 
and revised the paper, and is the guarantor. HHF 
designed the questionnaire, contributed to the data 
collection, monitored data collection for the whole 
trial, and revised the draft paper. MDB revised the 
draft paper. HP wrote the statistical analysis plan 
and supervised data analysis. RCMP revised the 
draft paper. HWE designed the protocol, designed 
the questionnaire, monitored data collection 
for the whole survey, revised and approved the 
paper, and is the supervisor of the study. </p>

<p>Competing interests None </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not 
commissioned; externally peer reviewed </p>

<p>Data sharing statement The authors state that 
additional unpublished data from the study will be 
shared with Frontline Gastroenterology if necessary. </p>

<p>the respondents regard it to be more important to pay 
attention to female than to male SF during their train-
ing. This may be attributed to the fact that much more 
is known about female PFD, since most studies on pel-
vic floor symptoms were performed on female patients 
only. We acknowledge that the benefits of the disclo-
sure and discussion of SF in male patients have not 
been fully studied. However, PFD is often indicated in 
male gastroenterology patients as well, suggesting that 
PFD is equally important in both sexes. </p>

<p>24 25 </p>

<p>PFD is very prevalent in gastroenterology practice, 
and it can have a major impact on patients' quality of 
life. 
26 Although less than half the Dutch gastroenter-
ologists responded, this study indicates that gastro-
enterologists should receive training about PFD and 
especially about SF. This training should be based on 
patients' attitudes regarding their expectations of the 
physician. Patients expect from their physician to take 
the initiative in raising the issue of sexual health and to 
ask the questions about subjects which the patient can-
not directly relate to the complaint he/she is presenting 
with. 
27 28 For example Gordon et al showed that of 283 
patients visiting a urogynaecological clinic, only 0.7% 
disclosed their lower gastrointestinal symptoms with-
out being directly asked. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Knowledge about the pelvic floor, and when to 
inquire about its functioning, is an obligation for all 
gastroenterologists. Consequently, when a PFD of any 
kind is present, it is necessary to know how to provide 
care. Besides helping the patient in his or her own area 
of expertise, it may be necessary to refer the patient 
to a pelvic floor physiotherapist, a sexologist, a urolo-
gist or a psychologist to be able to treat the complaints 
comprehensively. Further research is needed to evalu-
ate the experiences of patients regarding the discussion 
of sexuality with their specialist. Another interesting 
question would be what the doctor actually does or 
would do when faced with patients who admit a sex-
ual or pelvic floor-related problem. Would he refer the 
patient or would he just ignore it? </p>

<p>Conclusion 
The results of this survey show that inquiry of PFD, 
and especially of sexual dysfunction, is not yet routine 
in the history taken by gastroenterologists. Because 
PFD is very prevalent in the gastroenterology practice 
and it can have a major impact on patients' quality of 
life, awareness and knowledge about the role of the 
pelvic floor in gastroenterology should be increased. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements This study was initiated by 
the Pelvic Floor and Sexuality Research Group, 
Leiden. The authors wish to thank Roger de Bats, 
for helping in creating and understanding the 
online questionnaire, and Charlotte Nouwens for 
the revisions. The authors also thank Tramedico 
for supporting this study with a limited grant. </p>

<p>Contributors MPJN designed the questionnaire, 
was responsible for data collection for the whole </p>

<p>What is already know on this subject </p>

<p>▶ Dysfunction of the pelvic fl oor may lead to a wide range of 
functional symptoms including sexual function, micturition and 
defecation. 
▶ Most patients do not disclose intimate complaints such as 
urinary or faecal incontinence without being directly asked. 
▶ Dysfunction of the pelvic fl oor is responsible for a high 
percentage of lower urinary tract symptoms and sexual 
problems in patients visiting a gastroenterologist. 
▶ Treatment of pelvic fl oor dysfunction (PFD) asks for a 
multidisciplinary, holistic approach. </p>

<p>What this study adds </p>

<p>▶ Gastroenterologists inquire regularly about lower urinary tract 
symptoms in their patients. 
▶ On indication, a majority of gastroenterologists inquire about 
sexual function in their female patients; in male patients 
inquiries about sexual function are exceptional. 
▶ The main reason not to inquire about sexual function is a lack 
of knowledge on the subject. 
▶ Signifi cant differences between male and female physicians 
exist concerning their views on PFD. </p>

<p>How might it impact on clinical practice in the 
future </p>

<p>▶ Our results demonstrate that the knowledge about PFD is not 
yet intergraded in gastroenterologists' daily practice patterns. 
Raising the awareness on PFD will improve holistic patient care. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in 
accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non 
Commercial (CC BY-NC 3.0) license, which permits others to 
distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different 
terms, provided the original work is properly cited and the use 
is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-
nc/3.0/ </p>

<p>Frontline Gastroenterology 2012;3:166-171. doi:10.1136/fl gastro-2012-100133 </p>

<p>PROFESSIONAL MATTERS </p>





</text></tei>