<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3789839" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Carotid intima-media thickness (CIMT) and plaque formation have been used 
as surrogate end-points for evaluating the regression and/or progression of atherosclerotic 
cardiovascular disease, but their predictive value for stable coronary artery disease (CAD) is 
inconclusive. 
Methods: Carotid ultrasonography was performed in patients who underwent noninvasive 
multislice computed tomography (MSCT) angiography for CAD suspected, due to chest pain. 
CIMT and plaque formation on the left and right common carotid arteries (CCAs), carotid bulb 
(CB), and proximal internal carotid arteries (ICAs) were evaluated, and the relationship between 
angiographic CAD, CIMT, and plaque formation was determined. 
Results: 120 patients (95 male; 25 female), with a mean age ± standard deviation of 61 ± 11 years 
(range: 35-89 years) were recruited. Because age had a significant impact on CAD (r = 0.191; 
P = 0.036), CCA plaques (r = 0.368; P = 0.001), ICA plaques (r = 0.334; P = 0.004), and 
mean CIMT (r = 0.436; P = 0.001), patients were divided into two groups aged ,60 years 
and $60 years. In the ,60 years group, CIMT-CB was significantly higher in patients with 
CAD (P = 0.041), while in the $60 years group, mean CIMT, CIMT-CCA, and CIMT-CB 
were significantly higher in patients with CAD (P , 0.05, for each). In both groups, the occur-
rence of carotid plaques was significantly higher in patients with CAD than in those without 
CAD (P , 0.007, for each). After controlling for other risk factors, carotid plaques were an 
independent predictor of CAD in both groups (P , 0.05, for each), while CIMT-CB could 
independently predict CAD only in patients $60 years old (P = 0.031). 
Conclusion: Our findings suggest that carotid plaques are a strong predictor of stable CAD. 
However, CIMT-CB could predict stable CAD only in patients over 60 years of age. 
Coronary artery disease (CAD) is a common and disabling disorder. It remains the 
leading cause of mortality worldwide, resulting in the deaths of 3.8 million men and 
3.4 million women annually. 
1 Most individuals with stable CAD show no symptoms 
and signs for decades, until the sudden onset of coronary events, such as myocardial 
infarction. Therefore, it is desirable to identify patients at an early stage of CAD, to 
enable preventive interventions and to promote lifestyle modifications as early as 
possible. 
Traditional risk factors for CAD, such as family history of CAD, age, smoking, 
hypertension, diabetes mellitus, hyperlipidemia, and obesity have been used to 
identify asymptomatic individuals who are at higher risk of cardiovascular events. </p>

<p>2,3 </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Clinical Interventions in Aging 
24 September 2013 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2013:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1284 </p>

<p>Chang et al </p>

<p>However, these risk factors can only identify approximately 
50% of patients at risk of CAD. 
4 Carotid ultrasonography 
has become a prominent focus of clinical research in the 
last two decades, and the relationship between cardiovas-
cular events, and carotid intima-media thickness (CIMT) 
and plaque formation, has been studied widely. Many large 
epidemiological studies have shown a strong relationship 
between cardiovascular events, and CIMT and plaques. </p>

<p>5-8   Overall, evidence for the predictive value of carotid plaques 
for CAD seems consistent, 
9-13 but evidence for the use of 
CIMT in clinical practice is incomplete, because the predic-
tive value of CIMT for CAD is inconsistent, especially in 
patients with stable CAD. Some studies have suggested that 
CIMT could be used as a predictive marker for cardiovas-
cular events, 
14-16 while others have reported that CIMT was 
not an independent predictor for CAD, after adjustment for 
traditional risk factors. 
17,18 Such conflicting results may be 
due to considerable variation between studies in relation to 
measurement methods and cut-off values for CIMT. In addi-
tion, most studies have used severe cardiovascular events, 
such as myocardial infarction, CAD death, or coronary 
revascularization, as study end-points. However, it is not 
suitable to apply the results derived from these studies to 
patients with asymptomatic CAD. A genome-wide study also 
showed a strong genetic effect on CIMT. 
19 Unfortunately, very 
few studies are available regarding the age-related predictive 
value of CIMT and plaques for stable CAD in the Chinese 
population. Thus, the purpose of this prospective study was 
to investigate the predictive value of CIMT and plaques for 
the occurrence of stable CAD. </p>

<p>Material and methods 
Patients </p>

<p>Patients who were referred to Cathay General Hospital, 
Taipei, Taiwan with suspected CAD due to chest pain were 
consecutively recruited from January 2008-January 2010. 
Exclusion criteria included a history of myocardial infarction, 
unstable angina, coronary-artery bypass surgery, stroke, ven-
tricular and supraventricular arrhythmias, contraindications 
for the use of iodinated contrast medium, history of cervical 
spine injuries, wounds on the neck, and poor echo imaging. 
All participants underwent physical examination, noninva-
sive multislice computed tomography (MSCT) coronary 
angiography for the diagnosis of CAD, and ultrasonography 
for the assessment of CIMT and plaques. Hypertension 
was defined as a blood pressure .140/90 mmHg, or treat-
ment with any antihypertensive agent. Hyperlipidemia was 
defined as a total cholesterol level .5.0 mmol/L, or the </p>

<p>use of any antihyperlipidemic agent. Diabetes mellitus was 
defined as a fasting plasma blood glucose level .7.0 mmol/L 
on two different days, a postprandial blood glucose 
level .11.1 mmol/L, or the use of antidiabetic medications. 
All participants provided informed, written consent. 
The study was conducted in accordance with the Helsinki II 
Declaration and approved by the Scientific Ethics Committee 
of Cathay General Hospital. </p>

<p>MsCT coronary angiography </p>

<p>MSCT coronary angiography was performed with a 
64-slice MSCT scanner (Aquilion 64, Toshiba Medical 
Systems, Otawara-shi, Japan). A nonenhanced prospective 
electrocardiographically-gated scan was performed first, to 
determine the start and end position of the following helical 
scan, through which coronary angiography was performed. 
The presence of coronary atherosclerosis was visually evalu-
ated based on axial images and curved multiplanar recon-
structions in two orthogonal planes. Obstructive coronary 
atherosclerosis was defined as a luminal narrowing .50% 
in one or more coronary arteries. </p>

<p>Carotid ultrasonography </p>

<p>Carotid ultrasonography was performed within 24 hours 
following MSCT coronary angiography. The carotid arteries 
were evaluated using a high resolution B-mode color Dop-
pler and pulse Doppler ultrasound system (iE33 xMATRIX, 
Philips Healthcare, Andover, MA, USA) with a transducer 
frequency of 11-13 MHz, by an examiner who was blind to 
the subjects' characteristics. The near and far wall of the right 
and left common carotid arteries (CCAs) (at least 1.5 cm 
proximal to the origin of the carotid bulb [CB], bifurcations 
at the CB), and proximal internal carotid arteries (ICAs) were 
scanned. Using an automated edge detection algorithm, the 
maximum IMT was determined as the distance between the 
lumen-intima interface and the media-adventitia interface 
at a plaque-free segment in end-diastole. The maximum IMT 
of the CCA, ICA, and CB was recorded. Mean CIMT was 
defined as the average of IMT values at the right and left sides 
of the CCA, ICA, and CB. A carotid plaque in the CCA, CB, 
or ICA was defined either as (1) a thickening of the focal 
wall that was at least 50% greater than the thickening of the 
surrounding vessel wall (relative plaque), or (2) a focal region 
with an IMT of .1.5 mm (absolute plaque). </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was conducted using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software ver-
sion <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">19.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corporation</rs>, Armonk, NY, USA). Continuous </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2013:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1285 </p>

<p>Carotid atherosclerosis and CAD </p>

<p>variables were expressed as mean ± standard deviation, and 
categorical variables were expressed as number (%). The 
Student's t-test or Mann-Whitney U test was performed 
for between-group comparisons of continuous variables 
(according to distribution characteristics), while the chi-
square test was used to perform between-group comparisons 
of categorical variables. Partial correlation analysis was 
performed to test the correlation between CAD and CIMT 
or plaques, controlling for age, diabetes mellitus, hyperlipi-
demia, hypertension, smoking, and family history of CAD. 
Multivariate logistic regression analysis (with CAD as the 
outcome variable) was performed to determine the indepen-
dent predictors of CAD. Two-tailed tests were performed, and 
a value of P , 0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results 
Patient characteristics </p>

<p>A total of 120 patients were recruited into the study, including 
95 males and 25 females, with a mean age of 61 ± 11 years 
(range: 35-89 years). Age had a significant impact on CAD 
(r = 0.191; P = 0.036), CCA plaques (r = 0.368; P = 0.001), 
ICA plaques (r = 0.334; P = 0.004), and CIMT (r = 0.436; 
P = 0.001). As most Chinese retire at the age of 60 years, and 
their lifestyles may change dramatically after retirement, we 
separated patients into two groups (,60 years and $60 years) 
for further analysis. As shown in Table 1, compared with 
patients ,60 years old, patients $60 years old had a higher 
incidence of hypertension (P = 0.018), and more severe CAD 
(involving three coronary arteries; P = 0.015). No difference 
was found between the two groups in terms of sex or CAD 
risk factors, such as family history of CAD, smoking, diabetes 
mellitus, and hyperlipidemia (P . 0.05, for each). </p>

<p>CIMT and its correlation with CAD </p>

<p>In the ,60 year group, only IMT-CB was significantly higher 
in patients with CAD, as compared to those without CAD 
(P = 0.041), while in the $60 years group, mean CIMT, 
IMT-CCA, and IMT-CB were significantly higher in patients 
with CAD than in those without CAD (P , 0.05, for each). 
Comparing the two age groups, mean CIMT and IMT-CCA 
were significantly higher in the $60 years group than those 
in the ,60 years group (P , 0.0001, for each) (Table 2). 
After controlling for other CAD risk factors (age, family 
history of CAD, smoking, diabetes mellitus, hypertension, 
and hyperlipidemia), partial correlation analysis showed that 
only IMT-CB was correlated with CAD in the ,60 years 
group (P = 0.041), but that mean CIMT, IMT-CCA, and 
IMT-CB were all correlated with CAD in the $60 years 
group (P , 0.05, for each) (Table 3). These results suggest 
that IMT-CB was more specific for predicting the rela-
tionship between CIMT and CAD in both age groups, 
while mean CIMT and IMT-CCA were only valuable in 
patients $60 years old. </p>

<p>Carotid plaques and correlation 
with CAD </p>

<p>Of the 120 patients, 27 (22.5%) had no carotid plaques, 
and 93 (77.5%) had plaques, of whom 16 (13.3%) had 
plaques at one site, 40 (33.3%) had plaques at two sites, 
and 37 (30.8%) had plaques at three sites. As shown in 
Table 4, the proportion of patients with plaques at all sites 
(CCA, ICA, and CB) was significantly higher in patients 
with CAD than in those without CAD, in both age groups 
(P , 0.007, for each). However, the proportion was higher </p>

<p>Table 1 Patient characteristics </p>

<p>Total 
,60 years 
(n = 61) </p>

<p>$60 years 
(n = 59) </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>Age (years) 
61 ± 11 
52 ± 5 
71 ± 7 
0.000 
Males 
95 (79.2) 51 (83.6) 
44 (74.6) 
ns 
CAD risk factors 
Family CAD history 21 (17.5) 10 (16.4) 
11 (18.6) 
ns 
smoking 
65 (54.2) 35 (57.4) 
30 (50.8) 
ns 
Diabetes 
46 (38.3) 20 (33.3) 
26 (44.1) 
ns 
hypertension 
88 (73.3) 39 (63.9) 
49 (83.1) 
0.018 
hyperlipidemia 
57 (47.5) 32 (52.5) 
25 (42.4) 
ns 
number of diseased coronary arteries 
0 
32 (26.7) 19 (31.1) 
13 (22.0) 
ns 
1 
19 (15.8) 12 (19.7) 
7 (11.9) 
ns 
2 
20 (16.7) 12 (19.7) 
8 (13.6) 
ns 
3 
49 (40.8) 18 (29.5) 
31 (52.5) 
0.015 </p>

<p>Note: Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation, or number (percentage). 
Abbreviations: CAD, coronary artery disease; NS, not significant. </p>

<p>Table 2 Difference in carotid intima-media thickness between 
the two age groups of patients, with and without coronary artery 
disease </p>

<p>,60 years (n = 61) 
$60 years (n = 59) 
P </p>

<p>Mean CIMT (mm) 
non-CAD 
0.65 ± 0.02 
0.72 ± 0.04 
ns 
CAD 
0.68 ± 0.02 
0.81 ± 0.02 
0.000 
P 
ns 
0.028 
IMT-CCA (mm) 
non-CAD 
0.84 ± 0.02 
0.88 ± 0.04 
ns 
CAD 
0.85 ± 0.02 
0.97 ± 0.02 
0.000 
P 
ns 
0.036 
IMT-CB (mm) 
non-CAD 
0.87 ± 0.02 
0.85 ± 0.03 
ns 
CAD 
0.93 ± 0.02 
0.98 ± 0.02 
ns 
P 
0.041 
0.001 </p>

<p>Note: Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation. 
Abbreviations: CIMT, carotid intima-media thickness; CCA, common carotid 
artery; CB, carotid bulb; CAD, coronary artery disease; NS, not significant. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2013:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1286 </p>

<p>Chang et al </p>

<p>in patients aged $60 years, compared against those aged 
,60 years (P , 0.05, for each). After controlling for other 
CAD risk factors (age, family history of CAD, smoking, 
diabetes mellitus, hypertension, and hyperlipidemia), partial 
correlation analysis showed that carotid plaques in the CCA 
and CB were significantly correlated with CAD in patients 
aged ,60 years (P , 0.05, for each), whereas plaques in 
all sites were correlated with CAD in those aged $60 years 
(P , 0.05, for each) (Table 3). </p>

<p>CAD risk prediction </p>

<p>By controlling for other CAD risk factors, multivariate 
logistic regression analysis (with CAD as the outcome 
variable) showed that only IMT-CB was an independent 
predictor of CAD in patients $60 years old (P = 0.031), 
but not in patients ,60 years old. However, carotid plaques 
were an independent predictor of CAD in patients ,60 
and $60 years old (P = 0.006 and P = 0.045, respectively) 
(Table 5). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present study analyzed the relationship between carotid 
atherosclerosis and stable angiographic CAD. We found 
that CIMT was not an independent predictor of CAD in 
patients ,60 years old, but that IMT-CB could predict CAD 
in patients $60 years old, after adjustment for traditional risk 
factors. Carotid plaques in the CCA or CB were strongly 
correlated with CAD in all patients, and multivariate logis-
tic regression analysis showed that this was an independent 
predictor of CAD in all patients. 
Our findings regarding the predictive value of CIMT 
differ from those of previous studies. Kablak-Ziembicka 
et al 
18 examined IMT at the CCA, ICA, and CB in 558 con-
secutive patients referred for coronary angiography. They 
reported that CIMT was strongly correlated with the pres-
ence and severity of CAD, particularly in women. However, 
there were some significant limitations to that study. First, 
the CIMT maximum included plaque, which would signifi-
cantly increase the predictive value of CIMT. Second, the 
mean CIMT values among patients with no disease and 1-, 
2-and 3-vessel disease overlapped substantially. Moreover, 
many patients had a history of myocardial infarction, which 
places them in a high-risk group. In another study, Timoteo 
et al 
21 measured maximum IMT and plaques at the CCA in 
300 patients with suspected stable CAD, and found that the 
maximum IMT at the CCA was an independent predictor 
of CAD, together with age, sex, and diabetes mellitus. The 
Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) study, 
22 which 
recruited subjects between 45-64 years old, also found that 
CIMT and plaque information can be used to improve CAD 
risk prediction, and was equal or superior to other contem-
porary markers. 
Debate remains active as to which carotid segment should 
be used to measure IMT. The ARIC study examined whether 
IMT-CCA was as good as all-segment IMT for the prediction 
of vascular events, when added to traditional risk factor and 
plaque information. No difference between the two measures </p>

<p>Table 3 The correlation between carotid IMT and plaque with 
the incidence of CAD, after controlling for other risk factors </p>

<p>,60 years 
$60 years </p>

<p>r 
P 
r 
P </p>

<p>Mean CIMT 
0.125 
0.336 
0.286 
0.028 
IMT-CCA 
0.028 
0.829 
0.274 
0.036 
IMT-CB 
0.263 
0.041 
0.424 
0.001 
CCA plaque 
0.319 
0.012 
0.347 
0.007 
ICA plaque 
0.168 
0.195 
0.288 
0.027 
CB plaque 
0.255 
0.047 
0.481 
0.000 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: r, correlation coefficient; IMT, intima-media thickness; CIMT, 
common carotid intima-media thickness; CAD, coronary artery disease; CCA, 
common carotid artery; CB, carotid bulb; ICA, internal carotid artery. </p>

<p>Table 4 Difference of carotid plaque occurrence between the 
two age groups of patients, with and without coronary artery 
disease </p>

<p>,60 years (n = 61) 
$60 years (n = 59) 
P </p>

<p>CCA plaque 
non-CAD 
2 (3.3) 
6 (10.2) 
0.028 
CAD 
18 (28.7) 
38 (64.4) 
0.000 
P 
0.000 
0.000 
ICA plaque 
non-CAD 
4 (6.6) 
5 (8.5) 
ns 
CAD 
16 (25.4) 
33 (55.9) 
0.002 
P 
0.007 
0.000 
CB plaque 
non-CAD 
8 (13.2) 
6 (10.2) 
ns 
CAD 
29 (47.5) 
42 (71.2) 
0.014 
P 
0.000 
0.000 </p>

<p>Note: Data are presented as number (percentage). 
Abbreviations: CAD, coronary artery disease; CCA, common carotid artery; ICA, 
internal carotid artery; CB, carotid bulb; NS, not significant. </p>

<p>Table 5 Prediction of coronary artery disease by carotid IMT 
and plaque </p>

<p>,60 years 
$60 years </p>

<p>OR (95% CI) 
P 
OR (95% CI) 
P </p>

<p>Mean CIMT 1.42 (0.46-4.34) 
0.540 1.79 (0.45-7.06) 
0.408 
IMT-CCA 
2.23 (0.70-7.09) 
0.174 0.92 (0.24-3.61) 
0.905 
IMT-CB 
0.73 (0.25-2.13) 
0.560 3.86 (1.13-13.23) 
0.031 
Carotid 
plaque </p>

<p>5.36 (1.63-17.63) 0.006 14.91 (1.06-209.84) 0.045 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval; CIMT, carotid intima-
media thickness; CCA, common carotid artery; CB, carotid bulb. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2013:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1287 </p>

<p>Carotid atherosclerosis and CAD </p>

<p>was found, suggesting that IMT-CCA was sufficient for use 
in clinical risk assessment. 
22 However, in the Three-City 
Study, 
23 IMT was examined at the CCA in 5,895 CAD-free 
adults aged 65-85, and the results indicated that CIMT at 
a plaque-free site failed to predict CAD events, such as 
hospitalization for angina pectoris, myocardial infarction, 
CAD death, or a revascularization procedure (percutaneous 
intervention or coronary artery bypass or grafting). Although 
the measurement of IMT at the CCA is more reproducible 
than that measured at the ICA or bifurcation, 
24 disease 
progression is more obvious in the ICA and bifurcation. </p>

<p>5   Therefore, measuring only IMT-CCA may underestimate 
carotid atherosclerosis. In the present study, we measured 
IMT at the CCA, ICA, and CB, and found that CIMT mea-
sured at all sites could not predict CAD in patients ,60 years 
old, while in patients $60 years old, IMT-CB could weakly 
predict CAD. These results suggest that CIMT should be 
assessed in all carotid segments in order to avoid underesti-
mation of carotid atherosclerosis. 
In the present study, CIMT was assessed in the carotid seg-
ments free of plaques because, although correlated, increased 
CIMT and the presence of plaques represent different stages 
and aspects of atherosclerosis. Diffuse adaptive thickening 
of the carotid wall reflects arteriosclerosis, responding to 
aging and hypertension, while plaque formation is a focal 
process, and is more related to atherosclerotic processes, such 
as inflammation, oxidation, and endothelial dysfunction, </p>

<p>25,26   which may be more strongly associated with the pathology 
of CAD. A recent meta-analysis of eleven population-based 
studies by Inaba et al 
27 showed that carotid plaques, compared 
against CIMT, had a significantly higher diagnostic accuracy 
for prediction of future coronary events. In the present study, 
we found also that correlation between carotid plaques and 
the severity of CAD was consistent in patients below and 
above 60 years old. 
We separated patients into two groups at 60 years of age 
because we had found, along with others, 
6 that age has a sig-
nificant impact on CIMT and plaque formation. In addition, 
in the People's Republic of China, most people have dramatic 
lifestyle changes following retirement at the age of 60, which 
can affect their health condition. We found that the predictive 
value of CIMT for CAD was different in patients under and 
over 60 years of age, suggesting that age plays an extremely 
important role in CAD and plaque formation. This may help 
to explain why the predictive value of CIMT for CAD is 
inconsistent in previous studies, as they included different age 
groups of patients. We believe the present findings, based on 
the comparison between these two age groups, will be more </p>

<p>useful for clinical decision making. The American Heart 
Association's Prevention Conference V recommended CIMT 
scanning for patients who are older than 45, and requiring 
further clarification of their CAD risks. 
28 Although carotid 
ultrasonography is easy and quick to perform, it requires 
expensive equipment and specific operator training. To 
perform carotid scanning for a target population older than 
45 years would have an enormous cost. We think it may be 
more efficient and useful to target those aged over 60 years, 
with CAD risk factor assessment. 
There are certain limitations to the present study. Firstly, 
the study sample is relatively small for multivariate logis-
tic regression analysis, which may affect the significance 
of the results. For example, the ARIC Study 
22 recruited 
a population-based cohort of 15,792 subjects; the 25th 
and 75th percentile CIMT values were only 0.65 mm and 
0.84 mm, for men, and 0.58 mm and 0.74 mm, for women, 
respectively, which are much lower than our measurements. 
However, our results still suggest that CIMT and plaque 
information can be used to improve CAD risk prediction, 
and may be equivalent or superior to other contemporary 
markers. Secondly, in our study, the proportion of women 
was small. It has been reported that patients with chest 
pain and normal coronary angiographies are predominantly 
women. 
29 However, age-and sex-related differences in the 
prevalence of CAD are well recognized: male patients tend 
to have earlier onset of CAD; 
30 therefore, male patients 
predominate. Finally, the incidence of plaques was relatively 
high in our study. This may reflect a true patient population 
in the People's Republic of China, because only patients who 
are considered to be at high risk of CAD will be referred 
for CT angiography. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Our findings suggest that carotid plaque formation is a strong 
predictor of stable CAD. However, CIMT-CB could predict 
stable CAD only in patients aged over 60. Further study with 
a larger sample size is warranted. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests 
in this work. </p>



<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/clinical-interventions-in-aging-journal </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging is an international, peer-reviewed journal 
focusing on evidence-based reports on the value or lack thereof of treat-
ments intended to prevent or delay the onset of maladaptive correlates 
of aging in human beings. This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, 
MedLine, the American Chemical Society's 'Chemical Abstracts </p>

<p>Service' (CAS), Scopus and the Elsevier Bibliographic databases. The 
manuscript management system is completely online and includes a 
very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2013:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Chang et al </p>



</text></tei>