<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3426798" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:32+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objectives. To determine the extent to which demographic characteristics, clinical measurements and bio-
markers were associated with poor self-reported health (SRH) among Inuit adults in the Canadian Arctic. 
Study design. Cross-sectional survey was adopted as the study design. 
Methods. The International Polar Year Inuit Health Survey carried out in 36 Canadian Arctic communities in 
2007 and 2008 included Inuit men and women, aged 18 years or older, recruited from randomly selected 
households. The main outcome measure was SRH, which was dichotomized into good health (excellent, very 
good and good responses) and poor health (fair and poor responses). 
Results. Of the 2,796 eligible households, 1,901 (68%) households and 2,595 participants took part in the 
survey. The weighted prevalence of poor SRH was 27.8%. Increasing age was significantly associated with 
poor SRH. The relative risk ratios for poor SRH was 2.0 (95% confidence interval [CI] 1.3Á3.1) for men aged 
50 years or older and 2.3 (95% CI 1.7Á3.0) for women aged 50 years or older, compared with men and women 
aged 29 years or younger. After adjusting for age, gender and body mass index, poor SRH was significantly 
associated with smoking status (odds ratio [OR]01.5; CI 1.1Á2.0), at-risk fasting glucose levels (]6.1 mmol/L) 
(OR02.5; 95%; CI 1.5Á4.2) and elevated hs C-reactive protein levels (!3Á 510 mg/L) (OR02.1; 95% CI 
1.4Á3.1). Poor SRH was also significantly associated with a hypertriglyceridemic waist phenotype (high-risk 
waist circumference ]102 cm for men and ]88 cm for women with high triglyceride levels, ]1.7 mmol/L), 
adjusted for age and gender, OR01.6; 95% CI 1.1Á2.3. 
Conclusions. Clinically relevant indicators of chronic disease risk were related to subjective assessment of 
SRH among Inuit. </p>

<p>The objective of this article is to investigate the 
association between demographic characteristics, clinical 
measurements and biomarkers with poor SRH and thus 
add to the understanding of how biological processes 
may play a part in the assessment of SRH. Further, 
by studying this relationship among Inuit, we can also 
examine if SRH has wider cross-cultural implications 
beyond the North American and European populations 
on which most previous research on SRH has been based. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>Study design 
The International Polar Year Inuit Health Survey (IPY-
IHS) is a multifaceted, cross-sectional health survey 
conducted in the late summer and fall of 2007 and 2008 
in 33 coastal and 3 inland communities in the Inuvialuit 
Settlement Region (ISR) of the Northwest Territories, 
Nunavut and the Nunatsiavut region of Labrador in 
Canada. All coastal communities were visited by the 
Canadian Coast Guard Ship (CCGS) Amundsen, which 
was equipped with research and laboratory facilities. 
The inland communities were visited by air by separate 
research crews. Communities provided the researchers 
with numbered housing lists from which a random 
sample of households was selected using a random 
numbers table or computer-generated random digits. 
All Inuit adults, aged 18 years or older, within the 
selected households were eligible to participate. Three 
attempts were made to contact the selected households. 
Households were visited by locally trained research 
assistants and survey team members, who explained the 
study protocol, obtained written consent from individuals 
and booked clinic appointments on the ship. </p>

<p>Participatory process 
The IPY-IHS was developed using a participatory health 
research approach (22,23). Memoranda of Agreements 
were developed with steering committees in each of the 
3 regions, consisting of representatives of Inuit commu-
nities and regional health officials, outlining responsibil-
ities and processes to be followed. Similarly, separate 
communityÁuniversity agreements were signed by all 36 
local community councils, inviting the IPY-IHS teams 
into their communities. </p>

<p>Informed consent 
In recognition of the strong oral traditions of the Inuit, 
a ''visual'' consent form, which duplicated the written 
informed consent form word-for-word and depicted all 
clinical and laboratory procedures, was created as a DVD 
in the appropriate Inuit languages. After watching the 
DVD, participants who consented to participating in the 
study signed the bilingual written consent form. </p>

<p>Questionnaires 
Trained interviewers, who were bilingual in English and 
Inuit dialects, administered the questionnaires. One adult 
from each household completed a questionnaire concern-
ing the environment at home, living conditions, access to 
country food and other questions about the household. 
All other eligible adults in the household then completed 
an individual questionnaire on current and past health, 
health-related behaviours, such as smoking, and socio-
demographic information. Diet was assessed using both 
multiple-pass 24-hour food recalls and food frequency 
questionnaires. SRH was dichotomized by grouping ex-
cellent, very good and good responses into the ''good'' 
category, and fair and poor responses into the ''poor'' 
category. </p>

<p>Clinical measurements 
Standing height was measured to the nearest 0.1 cm using 
a portable stadiometer (Road Rod 214 Portable Stadio-
meter, Seca, MD). Body weight was measured to the 
nearest 0.1 kg using the Tanita scale (Tanita TBF-300GS, 
Tanita Corporation of America, Inc., Arlington Heights, 
IL). Standard body type was assumed for all participants 
and 0.4 kg was subtracted for light clothing. Participants 
who had a pacemaker had their body weight measured 
with a Seca scale (Medical Scale Model 214, Seca Corp., 
Ontario, Canada). Body mass index (BMI) was calcu-
lated (kg/m 
2 ) and classified into 3 categories: normal </p>

<p>B25.0, overweight 25.0Á29.9 and obese ]30. Waist 
circumference was measured to the nearest 0.1 cm using 
a cloth retractable tape measure (ERP, Laval, Quebec, 
Canada) at the natural waist midway between the lowest 
rib margin and the lateral iliac crest. Waist circumference 
was dichotomized into ''normal'' (B102 cm for males 
and B88 cm for females) and ''at risk'' (]102 cm for 
males and ]88 cm for females) (24). 
Blood pressure was measured, at rest, to the nearest 
1 mm Hg using a BpTRU 
TM Vital Signs Monitor (VSM 
MedTech Ltd., Coquitlam, BC, Canada). Three readings, 
with a 2-minute rest period between readings, were 
recorded for each participant and the mean of the 3 
readings was used in the analysis, and blood pressure 
was categorized as low-risk without diabetes, as at-risk 
with or without diabetes or on medication. Diabetes was 
characterized as having a fasting blood glucose level 
]7.0 mmol/L or OGTT ]11.1 mmol/L or taking anti-
diabetic medication. </p>

<p>Blood sampling 
Participants were asked to fast (water was allowed) for 
at least 8 hours. Nurses carried out venipuncture and a 
maximum of 45 ml of blood was centrifuged on-site and 
decanted into appropriate tubes and stored at (808C 
before being transported to the Center for Indigenous 
Peoples Nutrition and Environment (CINE) for labora-
tory analyses. </p>

<p>Helga Saudny et al. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>Citation: Int J Circumpolar Health 2012, 71: 18589 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/ijch.v71i0.18589 </p>

<p>Fasting plasma and serum were used for the analyses of 
glucose, lipids and high sensitivity C-reactive protein 
(hsCRP), respectively. Analyses were carried out at Nu-
trasource Diagnostics, Guelph, ON (Life Labs/Gamma 
Dynacare and the Montreal General Hospital, Canada). 
Fasting glucose results were classified into normal, 
B6.1 mmol/L; or at-risk, ]6.1 mmol/L; or taking 
anti-diabetic medication. Blood lipid concentrations 
were categorized according to the Canadian Heart and 
Stroke Foundation's cut-off values (24). HDL-cholesterol, 
normal!1.0 for males and !1.3 for females, abnormal 
51.0 mmol/L for males and 51.3 mmol/L for females; 
at-risk cholesterol, normal LDL-cholesterol B5.0 or 
total cholesterol/HDL-cholesterol B6.0; and at-risk: 
LDL-cholesterol ]5.0 or ratio of total cholesterol/ 
HDL-cholesterol ]6.0 mmol/L; triglycerides, normal 
B1.7 and abnormal ]1.7 mmol/L. hsCRP concentra-
tions were classified into 3 groups, low risk (B1.0 mg/L), 
average risk (]1.0 Á 53.0 mg/L) and high risk (!3.0Á 
510 mg/L), excluding 149 (6.75%) participants with 
values indicating an acute infection (!10 mg/L) (25). 
The hypertriglyceridemic waist phenotype was classified 
into 4 categories*normal waist with normal triglyceride 
levels, normal waist with high triglyceride levels, at-risk 
waist with normal triglyceride levels and at-risk waist 
with high triglyceride levels (26). </p>

<p>Statistical analyses 
Data were analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 9.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, 
Cary, NC). Weighted data were used in all analyses. 
Weight 1 was based on the total number of households in 
each community and the number of participating house-
holds per community; weight 2 was based on the total 
number of people in each household and the number 
of people sampled per household; weight 3 was used to 
correct for differences in the sex distribution between our 
sample and it's population distribution. Risk ratios and 
95% confidence intervals (CI) predicting poor SRH by 
age and gender were calculated and multivariate logistic 
regression was used to evaluate the relationship between 
demographic characteristics, clinical measurements and </p>

<p>biomarkers with poor SRH, adjusting for age, gender 
and BMI. Odds ratios (OR) and 95% CI were calculated. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The logistics of the survey and the movement of the 
ship (depending on tide tables) varied across the Arctic. 
Generally, very small communities were overrepresented 
as the ship could handle approximately 40 participants 
per day. A total of 2,796 Inuit households were ap-
proached from which 1,901 households participated 
(68%), with an average of 1.38 participants per household 
(n02,595 participants, aged 18 years or older, 998 
[38.5%] men and 1,597 [61.5%] women). The median 
number of participating households per community was 
41, with a minimum of 17 and a maximum of 143. For 
individuals, the median was 54, with a minimum of 
22 and a maximum of 172 individuals per community 
participating. The mean age of the survey population was 
43 years (SD 015) and the weighted prevalence of poor 
SRH was 27.8%. Poor SRH increased with advancing 
age, with a 2-fold higher risk for those aged ]50 years 
compared to the 18Á29 age group (Table I). The 
prevalence of poor SRH by categories of demographic 
characteristics and chronic disease risk factors identified 
no significant relationships with gender, primary lan-
guage spoken in the home or in traditional food 
consumption, but identified a protective relationship for 
married individuals. In analyses adjusted for age and 
gender, poor SRH was related to a hypertriglyceridemic-
waist phenotype. When further adjustments for age, 
gender and BMI were made, significant relationships 
persisted between chronic disease risk factors and poor 
SRH, where the prevalence of poor SRH was sig-
nificantly higher among participants who had at-risk 
fasting blood glucose levels and high-risk hsCRP levels 
(Table II). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present study adds to the limited literature available 
on biomarkers as they relate to SRH and represents the 
first investigation, to our knowledge, among Inuit adults 
in the Canadian Arctic. The most notable findings </p>

<p>Table I. Weighted risk ratios (RR and 95% confidence intervals (CI) predicting self-rated poor health by age and gender; International 
Polar Year Inuit Health Survey, 2007Á2008 </p>

<p>Men 
Women </p>

<p>Age group (years) 
(%) 
95% CI 
RR (95% CI) 
(%) 
95% CI 
RR (95% CI) </p>

<p>18Á29 
19.7 
11.8Á27.5 
1.0 
19.3 
14.5Á24.0 
1.0 
30Á39 
20.4 
13.7Á27.1 
1.0 (0.6Á1.7) 
24.0 
18.7Á29.3 
1.2 (0.9Á1.7) </p>

<p>40Á49 
25.0 
17.4Á32.5 
1.3 (0.8Á2.1) 
19.8 
14.7Á24.9 
1.0 (0.7Á1.5) </p>

<p>]50 
39.0 
31.4Á46.7 
2.0** (1.3Á3.1) 
43.7 
37.6Á49.9 
2.3*** (1.7Á3.0) </p>

<p>**p B0.01; ***p B0.001. </p>

<p>Poor health &amp; associated biomarkers in Canadian Inuit </p>

<p>Citation: Int J Circumpolar Health 2012, 71: 18589 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/ijch.v71i0.18589 </p>



<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>include the significantly higher OR of poor SRH as-
sociated with at-risk fasting glucose levels, at-risk waist 
circumference with high triglyceride levels and elevated 
hsCRP levels. Our results contribute to the limited data 
suggesting that a physiologic basis may be attributed to 
SRH, as suggested by others (14,17,27). 
This is the first study to report on a relationship 
between at-risk fasting blood glucose levels and poor 
SRH, where those with elevated fasting blood glucose 
levels were 2.5 times more likely to perceive their health 
as poor compared with normoglycemic individuals. 
The poorer assessment of health that was associated 
with elevated levels of fasting glucose may be the result of </p>

<p>physical sensations associated with disease progression, 
such as fatigue and poor sleep patterns, and important 
covariates, such as obesity. Further work is needed to 
explore the intuitive assessment of SRH and its relation 
to glucose homeostasis, especially in light of recently 
published results that suggest that Inuit ethnicity no 
longer prevents the development of diabetes, and the 
hypertriglyceridemic-waist phenotype is related to risk 
of fasting glycemia and type 2 diabetes (26). Our results 
of poorer SRH with a hypertriglyceridemic-waist pheno-
type provide additional information on the usefulness 
of SRH, beyond the more traditional objective health 
indicators. </p>

<p>Table II. Weighted prevalence and adjusted odds ratios 
a (OR) and 95% confidence intervals (CI) of self-reported poor health by 
demographic and health indicators; International Polar Year Inuit Health Survey, 2007Á2008 </p>

<p>Variable 
% Poor health (95% CI) 
OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>Marital status </p>

<p>Single (single, separated, divorced, widowed) 
29.8 (25.5Á34.1) 
1.0 </p>

<p>Married (married, common law partner) 
26.9 (23.9Á30.0) 
0.8* (0.6Á1.0) </p>

<p>Smoking at time of interview </p>

<p>No 
29.7 (25.2Á34.2) 
1.0 
Yes 
27.0 (24.0Á30.0) 
1.5* (1.1Á2.0) </p>

<p>Hypertension (mm Hg) </p>

<p>Low risk without diabetes 
24.2 (21.6Á26.9) 
1.0 </p>

<p>At risk with or without diabetes or taking </p>

<p>antihypertensive medication </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>36.0 (30.2Á41.7) 
1.0 (0.8Á1.4) </p>

<p>Body mass index (BMI) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Normal weight 
22.8 (19.0Á26.7) 
1.0 </p>

<p>Overweight (25.0Á29.9) 
25.8 (21.1Á30.4) 
1.1 (0.8Á1.5) </p>

<p>Obese ( ]30) 
32.5 (28.1Á36.9) 
1.4* (1.0Á1.9) </p>

<p>At-risk cholesterol (mmol/L) </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Normal 
26.8 (24.2Á29.4) 
1.0 </p>

<p>At-risk LDL ]5.0 or total/HDL ]6.0 
36.9 (29.2Á44.6) 
1.1 (0.7Á1.6) </p>

<p>At-risk fasting glucose (mmol/L) </p>

<p>Normal 
25.4 (22.8Á27.9) 
1.0 </p>

<p>At-risk ]6.1 or taking anti-diabetic medication 
57.2 (46.4Á68.0) 
2.5* (1.5Á4.2) </p>

<p>Hypertriglyceridemic-waist phenotype </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Normal waist with normal triglycerides B1.7 
23.8 (20.0Á27.6) 
1.0 </p>

<p>Normal waist with high triglycerides ]1.7 
26.0 (16.2Á35.7) 
1.0 (0.6Á1.7) </p>

<p>At-risk waist 
e with normal triglycerides B1.7 
26.8 (22.5Á31.1) 
1.0 (0.7Á1.4) </p>

<p>At-risk waist 
e with high triglycerides ]1.7 
36.7 (29.3Á44.1) 
1.6* (1.1Á2.3) </p>

<p>hsC-reactive protein (mg/L) </p>

<p>Low risk 
19.1 (15.7Á22.4) 
1.0 </p>

<p>Average risk 1.0Á 53.0 
28.0 (23.9Á32.2) 
1.3 (0.9Á1.7) </p>

<p>High risk !3.0Á 510 
40.4 (34.1Á46.8) 
2.1* (1.4Á3.1) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Adjusted for age (years), gender and BMI. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>At risk: non-diabetics, SBP ]140, DBP ]90 mm Hg; diabetics, SBP ]130, DBP ]80 mm Hg. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Adjusted for age (years) and gender. </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Or taking cholesterol lowering agents. </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>At-risk waist was defined as ]102 cm for men and ]88 cm for women. 
*pB0.05. </p>

<p>Helga Saudny et al. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>Citation: Int J Circumpolar Health 2012, 71: 18589 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/ijch.v71i0.18589 </p>

<p>Another interesting finding is the strong associa-
tion between higher levels of hsCRP and poorer SRH, 
which is in agreement with other reports, indicating that 
increasing circulating levels of inflammatory intermedi-
aries can influence health perception and relate to poorer 
health assessment (17Á19). Worth citing is a recent study 
among relatively healthy older adults that demonstrated 
that poorer self-rated health was significantly associated 
with higher levels of C-reactive protein. These associa-
tions remained after controlling for age, BMI, gender, 
objective health conditions, depressive symptoms and 
other health behaviours (20). Similarly, our results sup-
port the aforementioned findings as individuals with 
high-risk hsCRP levels are twice more likely to report 
poor health than individuals with low or average risk 
levels, adjusted for age, gender and BMI. CRP levels have 
been related to obesity and smoking status (28). Though 
these associations warrant further investigation, they are 
beyond the scope of this paper. 
Our results, like others, suggest that biochemical 
changes occurring at the cellular level, when the immune 
system is challenged, or covariates, such as obesity, result 
in associations with poorer SRH. Jylhä and colleagues 
have reached a similar conclusion based on results from 
a large community-based sample, where white blood cell 
count was significantly associated with poorer SRH, 
which remained after adjusting for a number of diseases, 
clinical measures, and socio-demographic conditions. The 
researchers concluded that SRH acted as a surrogate for 
disease and reflected subclinical physiological conditions 
(17). Likewise, a recent study of healthy Japanese men 
and women concluded that poor SRH was positively 
correlated with circulating immune markers even after 
adjusting for confounders (29). 
Very few studies have investigated the relationship 
between blood lipid levels and SRH. The Oslo Health 
Study suggested that increasing levels of HDL-cholesterol 
increased the odds of reporting good health in most 
age groups and both sexes (21). In our study, at-risk 
cholesterol levels were not associated with poor SRH. 
The view that older people are preoccupied with poor 
health may be exaggerated. While poor SRH and old age 
are clearly associated with mortality, (14) when overall 
health and not mortality is the outcome, the literature is 
not as convincing. Older subjects have been noted to 
report better health than younger subjects (30Á32), but 
the literature provides contradictory results (33,34). Also, 
women have been noted to report poorer health than men 
(35), which is not supported by our study as both men 
and women in the ]50 age group were 2 times more 
likely to rate their health as poor than their younger 
counterparts. The SRH response among those ]50 years 
could reflect underlying subclinical or clinical diseases 
and/or disabilities that relate to the lower life expectancy </p>

<p>among Inuit, which is 67 years compared with 80 years 
for the general Canadian population (36). </p>

<p>Strengths 
This study is the first to relate objectively measured 
biomarkers and clinical measurements to SRH in a large 
representative sample of Inuit adults from 3 regions 
across a vast geographic area in the Canadian Arctic. 
Nearly 20% of the adult Inuit population of the 3 regions 
participated in the survey (2,595 individuals) with 68% 
of households participating. A further strength of the 
study is its contribution of new evidence to the emerging 
body of research linking endocrine and immune-activated 
responses to SRH and the study's corroboration of 
existing information on clinical measurements and bio-
markers. Furthermore, this study provides additional 
evidence of the transcultural nature of SRH and its 
validity among Inuit and possibly other Indigenous 
populations (37). </p>

<p>Limitations 
The study is not without its limitations. The absolute 
value of the adjusted OR should be interpreted with 
caution as they tend to exaggerate the true relative risk 
for highly prevalent outcomes. Also, access to medical 
chart data was not available at the time of analyses, but 
nurses visually inspected and recorded medications taken 
and those taking medications for diabetes or dyslipidemia 
were excluded from analyses of fasting blood glucose and 
lipid-related biomarkers. Furthermore, we excluded indi-
viduals with hsCRP levels exceeding 10 mg/L from the 
hsCRP analysis, evidence of acute inflammation or other 
organic disease states that could have influenced SRH. 
However, only 1 marker of inflammation was available 
for analyses. Another limitation is that study participants 
received their anthropometric results during their clinic 
visit and prior to being interviewed, and knowledge of 
their obesity status may have influenced their responses 
to the SRH questions. 
Finally, an inherent weakness is, of course, the sub-
jective nature of SRH assessment, which is likely influ-
enced by multiple and complex dimensions of health and 
perceptions, cultural conventions, willingness to present 
a positive or negative self-image, past and present health 
experiences and knowledge and, last but not least, an 
optimistic or pessimistic temperament (14). However, 
given these inherent complexities in SHR, the current 
findings are all the more notable. </p>

<p>Future research 
More research linking endocrine and immune-activated 
response measures to SRH is needed. Also, more needs to 
be learned about the process that goes into the evaluation 
of self-perceived health. More studies linking SRH to 
biological processes and to self-reported and diagnosed </p>

<p>Poor health &amp; associated biomarkers in Canadian Inuit </p>

<p>Citation: Int J Circumpolar Health 2012, 71: 18589 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/ijch.v71i0.18589 </p>



<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>diseases will improve our understanding of the relation-
ship between biological processes and SRH. </p>

<p>Conclusion and policy implications 
The findings provide evidence of the trans-cultural 
validity of SRH for population-based health research. 
Further, the findings provide health care professionals 
with greater confidence in the usefulness of incorporating 
one simple question on SRH in their patient contacts. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We graciously thank all those who participated in the Canadian 
IPY-IHS. We acknowledge all the dedicated community research 
assistants, nurses and staff who made the survey possible. We also 
extend our warmest gratitude to the 3 steering committees repre-
senting 3 Inuit land claim regions who guided the survey from its 
inception to results dissemination. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest and funding </p>

<p>Funding was provided by the Government of Canada 
Federal Program for International Polar Year, Canadian 
Institutes of Health Research, Health Canada, Indian and 
Northern Affairs Canada, Government of Nunavut, Arctic-
Net, Canada Research Chair Program and the Canadian 
Foundation for Innovation. </p>

<p>Ethical approval: Ethical approval for the research was 
obtained from Faculty of Medicine, Institutional Review 
Board, McGill University. Research licences were obtained 
from the Nunavut Research Institute and the Aurora 
Research Institute, regulatory agencies for scientific research 
in Canada's territories. </p>





<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

</text></tei>