<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3283851" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Photodynamic therapy (PDT) using topical 
aminolevulinic acid (ALA) has increasingly been used for the 
treatment of acne vulgaris and several studies have shown its 
clinical efficacy. However, ALA-PDT needs a relatively long 
incubation period and is frequently associated with adverse 
effects. Indole-3-acetic acid (IAA) has been introduced as a 
new photosensitizer for the treatment of acne in recent study. 
IAA-PDT requires only a short incubation period and the 
procedure is relatively painless in contrast to ALA-PDT. 
Objective: To investigate the efficacy and safety of IAA-PDT 
in the treatment of acne. Methods: Twenty-five patients with 
facial acne lesions were enrolled in this study. IAA-PDT was 
performed for five sessions at 1-week intervals (week 0∼4). 
IAA was treated with 15 minute occlusion, and green light 
was given for 15 minutes. Clinical efficacy was determined 
by evaluating acne lesion counts, severity grading, and the 
Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI) at week 0, 2, 4, and 
5. Sebum secretion and erythema index was measured by 
Sebumeter and Mexameter, respectively, at baseline and one 
week after each treatment session (week 1∼5). Histopatho-
logical examination was performed at baseline and week 5. 
Adverse effects were recorded throughout the study. Results: 
All the patients completed the study. Numbers of both in-
flammatory and non-inflammatory acne lesions were sig-</p>

<p>nificantly decreased. Acne severity grade and the DLQI 
showed significant reduction. Sebum secretion and ery-
thema were also reduced. Histopathological examination 
showed a reduction in inflammatory reactions. No adverse 
effects were observed except for transient pruritus in one 
patient. Conclusion: PDT using IAA and green light was an 
effective, simple and safe treatment for acne. (Ann Dermatol 
24(1) 56∼60, 2012) </p>

<p>Acne vulgaris is a common skin disorder causing chronic 
inflammation of the pilosebaceous units. Increased sebum 
production, abnormal keratinization of keratinocytes, col-
onization by Propionibacterium acnes and inflammation 
are thought to be the major pathogenic factors. The stan-
dard treatments for acne vulgaris include topical anti-
microbials, topical retinoids, oral antibiotics, and oral 
isotretinoin. However, the effects of conventional thera-
pies are limited due to antibiotic resistance and adverse 
effects such as irritation and teratogenicity of isotre-
tinoin 
1,2 . Therefore, there is a need for the development of </p>

<p>alternative treatments for acne. 
Currently, several authors have reported on the efficacy of 
photodynamic therapy (PDT) for acne 
3-5 . PDT uses a pho-</p>

<p>tosensitizing drug activated by light, and causes cell 
destruction by the generation of reactive oxygen species 
3 . </p>

<p>5-aminolevulinic acid (ALA) is commonly used and ALA-
induced protoporphyrin IX has been shown to accumulate 
not only in the epidermal cells but also in the pilose-
baceous units 
6,7 . Although its specific mechanism invol-</p>

<p>The Effect of Indole-3-Acetic Acid and Green Light on Acne Vulgaris </p>

<p>Vol. 24, No. 1, 2012 57 </p>

<p>ved has not been fully identified, it has been postulated 
that ALA-PDT causes phototoxic injury of sebaceous 
glands and inhibits sebum production, photodynamic 
killing of P. acnes, and reduction of follicular obstruc-
tion 
3-7 . However, adverse effects such as pain, burning, </p>

<p>stinging, erythema, exfoliation, and post-inflammatory hy-
perpigmentation are commonly observed in ALA-PDT 
3-5 . </p>

<p>Moreover, topical ALA has to be applied for a relatively 
long period under occlusion, since ALA requires time to 
convert into protoporphyrin IX and penetrate into the skin. 
In addition, strict photoprotection is required after the 
treatment procedure to avoid phototoxicity 
8 . </p>

<p>Recently, indole-3-acetic acid (IAA) has been introduced 
as a new photosensitizer for PDT of acne 
9 . IAA is a </p>

<p>member of the group of phytohormones called auxins 
10 . </p>

<p>IAA alone is non-toxic in humans, however it can be 
activated after oxidative decarboxylation by horseradish 
peroxidase (HRP) and becomes cytotoxic 
11,12 . IAA can be </p>

<p>activated not only by HRP but also by visible and 
ultraviolet light 
9,13 . Among various wavelengths of visible </p>

<p>light, green light (520 nm) activated IAA most effectively 
9 . </p>

<p>The pilot study of IAA-PDT using green light has been 
shown to be painless and does not require long incu-
bation periods or photoprotection after the procedure in 
contrast to ALA-PDT 
9 . </p>

<p>The purpose of this study was to evaluate the efficacy and 
tolerability of PDT using IAA and green light in the 
treatment of acne. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study design and patients </p>

<p>This study was performed between January 2010 and May 
2010. The study was approved by the Institutional Review 
Board at our hospital and informed consent was obtained 
from all patients. Patients older than 16 years with acne 
lesions on the face were included. Patients were excluded 
if they had used any acne treatment during the previous 4 
weeks or had any other skin diseases on the face. Preg-
nant and lactating women were also excluded. Twenty-
five patients with facial acne lesions were enrolled. 
The patients were treated once a week for five consecutive 
weeks. Before application of IAA (0.015%), the skin was 
gently cleansed and IAA was applied for 15 minutes under 
occlusion. Then, green light (520 nm, 9 J/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) was illu-
minated for 15 minutes. </p>

<p>Efficacy and safety evaluations </p>

<p>All patients were evaluated at baseline (week 0) and one 
week after each treatment session (week 1∼5). During 
each visit, standardized frontal and bilateral 45° side </p>

<p>photographs were taken. The numbers of inflammatory 
(papules, pustules, nodules and cysts) and non-inflam-
matory (comedones) acne lesions were counted and se-
verity was assessed based on the Korean Acne Grading 
System 
14 at week 0, 2, 4, and 5. The severity score (gra-</p>

<p>des 1∼6) was as follows: grade 1, ＜10 papules; grade 2, 
11∼30 papules; grade 3, ＞31 papules and ＜10 nodules; 
grade 4, 11∼20 nodules; grade 5, 21∼30 nodules; and 
grade 6, ＞31 nodules 
14 . </p>

<p>Patients were asked to complete the Dermatology Life 
Quality Index (DLQI) questionnaire 
15 at week 0, 2, 4, and </p>

<p>5. The DLQI is one of the most widely used instruments 
for assessing skin-related quality of life (QoL). It consists of 
10 questions, and each item is scored on a four-point 
scale (0∼3 points). Higher scores indicate greater im-
pairment of the patient's QoL. 
Objective skin measurements were performed at each 
follow-up visit. Erythema index of the acne lesions on 
both cheeks and forehead was measured with a Mexa-
meter (MX-18; Courage &amp; Khazaka Electronic GmbH, 
Cologne, Germany). Sebum secretion on both cheeks and 
forehead was also measured with a Sebumeter 
Ⓡ (SM 815; 
Courage &amp; Khazaka) in a room with constant temperature 
(22∼23°C) and humidity (relative humidity 40∼45%). 
The mean values of erythema index and sebum secretion 
were calculated by averaging the values obtained from 
both cheeks and forehead. 
At baseline and 1 week after the final treatment session 
(week 5), a 2 mm punch biopsy was performed from most 
acne lesions in 8 patients. Specimens were sectioned and 
stained with hematoxylin and eosin. Severity of inflam-
mation was graded using a 0∼3 scale (grade 0: ＜5%, 1: 
5∼30%, 2: 31∼70%, 3: ＞70%). 
Adverse effects were recorded throughout the study. The 
investigator graded the degree of erythema, scaling, 
hyperpigmentation, pruritus and pain at each visit, using a 
0∼3 scale (0, none; 1, mild; 2, moderate; 3, severe). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Treatment effects were compared from each follow-up 
visit to the baseline scores using paired t-tests. Data were 
analyzed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">15.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chi-
cago, IL, USA). p-values of ＜0.05 were considered stati-
stically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>Twenty-five acne patients were enrolled in the study. All 
patients were Korean women, and their mean age was 
25.68±0.88 years (age range: 18∼34 years). All the </p>

<p>SY Huh, et al </p>



<p>Fig. 3. Sebum secretion at baseline and follow-up visits. *p 
＜0.05 vs. baseline. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Erythema index at baseline and follow-up visits. *p＜0.05 
vs. baseline. </p>

<p>patients completed the study. </p>

<p>Clinical assessment </p>

<p>Median reduction in numbers of inflammatory and 
non-inflammatory acne lesions from baseline to week 2, 
4, and 5 are shown in Fig. 1A, B. There was a significant 
reduction in inflammatory acne lesion counts from week 
2. Non-inflammatory lesion counts also showed signi-
ficant reductions at week 2 and 5. The representative pho-
tographs showing the improvement observed on treated 
patient are shown in Fig. 1C. Acne severity assessed by 
the Korean Acne Grading System also showed significant 
reduction from 1.4 at baseline and 1.16 and 1.08 at week 
2 and 5 (p=0.011 and 0.008, respectively). The mean </p>

<p>DLQI score at baseline was 7.00 and significantly 
decreased to 5.92, 4.64, and 4.56 at week 2, 4 and 5, 
respectively. No significant adverse effects were reported. 
Only one subject had mild pruritus, which was self-
limiting. </p>

<p>Objective assessment </p>

<p>The mean value of erythema index of the acne lesions 
showed a significant reduction throughout the study 
period from week 2 (Fig. 2). Sebum secretion showed 
significant reduction at week 5 (Fig. 3). Histopathological 
examination showed a significant reduction in inflam-
mation at week 5 compared to baseline (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>Fig. 1. (A) The number of inflammatory acne lesions at week 
0, 2, 4 and 5. *p＜0.05 vs. baseline. (B) Numbers of non-
inflammatory acne lesions at week 0, 2, 4 and 5. *p＜0.05 vs. 
baseline. (C) Clinical photographs of acne patient treated with 
IAA PDT (indole-3-acetic acid photodynamic therapy). </p>

<p>The Effect of Indole-3-Acetic Acid and Green Light on Acne Vulgaris </p>

<p>Vol. 24, No. 1, 2012 59 </p>

<p>Fig. 4. (A) Histopathological inflammation intensities at baseline 
and week 5. *p＜0.05 vs. baseline. (B) Histopathological chan-
ges of acne patients treated with IAA PDT (indole-3-acetic acid 
photodynamic therapy) at baseline and week 5 (H&amp;E, ×40). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>IAA is a plant growth hormone and plays an important 
role in plant cell division, elongation and differentia-
tion 
10 . IAA alone is a non-toxic substance, but can pro-</p>

<p>duce reactive oxygen species and a variety of free radicals 
when oxidized by HRP 
11 . Recent reports suggest that an </p>

<p>IAA/HRP combination is cytotoxic to mammalian cells, 
and can be used as novel cancer therapy 
11,12,16,17 . Further-</p>

<p>more, light activated IAA has shown its anti-cancer activity 
in several studies 
13,18,19 . In addition to its potential as an </p>

<p>anticancer drug, a recent study by Na et al. 
9 showed that </p>

<p>IAA could be used as a novel photosensitizer for PDT of 
acne. Green light was chosen for the light source, since it 
activated IAA most effectively. Even low fluence (9 J/cm 
2 ) </p>

<p>of green light was sufficient to activate IAA. The com-
bination of IAA and green light significantly decreased the 
colony count of P. acnes and S. aureus. Histological ex-
amination in mice back skin revealed that the com-
bination of IAA and green light destroyed follicular epi-
thelial cells. Fourteen patients were treated with a com-
bination of IAA and green light 3 times at 2-week intervals </p>

<p>and inflammatory lesion counts and sebum excretion 
significantly reduced 
9 . </p>

<p>In the present study, we conducted IAA-PDT using green 
light 5 times at 1-week intervals, which was different from 
a previous study 
9 . We observed significant improvement </p>

<p>through multidisciplinary approaches. Both inflammatory 
and non-inflammatory acne lesions were significantly 
decreased. The patients showed rapid improvement from 
week 2. Erythema index and sebum secretion were also 
significantly reduced after 5 treatment sessions. Addition-
ally, histopathological examination was performed in 8 
patients and the intensity of inflammation significantly 
decreased. Clinical and histological improvement shown 
in our study may be the effect of IAA itself or the result of 
antimicrobial activities on P. acnes 
9 . </p>

<p>The strength of IAA-PDT is that it could be done very 
easily with only a short incubation period and does not 
require photoprotection. Furthermore, we experienced 
that the procedure was completely painless in contrast to 
ALA-PDT. 
One limitation of our study is that there were no control 
subjects. The lack of long-term follow-up data was another 
limitation. Therefore, further controlled studies are re-
quired to determine an effective regimen to ensure a 
long-lasting result. In conclusion, the combination of IAA 
and green light was shown to be a very simple, safe and 
effective treatment option for acne. </p>



<p>SY Huh, et al </p>





</text></tei>