<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3875508" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Objectives: The purpose of this study was to determine the influence of platform switch-
ing on stress distribution of two different implant systems using three-dimensional (3D) 
finite element models. 
Materials and Methods: Six 3D finite element models were created to replicate two dif-
ferent implant systems with peri-implant bone tissue, in which six different implant-
abutment configurations were represented: model XiVE-a: 3.8-mm-diameter implant and 
3.8-mm-diameter abutment; model XiVE-b (platform-switching model): 4.5-mm-diameter 
implant and 3.8-mm-diameter abutment; model XiVE-c: 4.5-mm-diameter implant and 
4.5-mm-diameter abutment; model 3i-a: 4.0-mm-diameter implant and 4.1-mm-diameter 
abutment; model 3i-b (platform-switching model): 5.0-mm-diameter implant and 4.1-mm-
diameter abutment; model 3i-c: 5.0-mm-diameter implant and 5.0-mm-diameter abutment. 
vertical and oblique loads of 100 were applied to all models. 
Results: While the pattern of stress distribution was similar for both loading situations, 
oblique loading resulted in higher intensity and greater distribution of stress than axial 
loading in both cortical bone and implant-abutment-interface. Stress distribution at peri-
implant bone was almost identical with similar magnitudes for all six models. In both im-
plant systems, platform-switching models demonstrated lower maximum von Mises stress 
in cortical bone than conventional models. However, in both implant systems and under 
both loading situations, platform-switching models showed higher stresses at the implant-
abutment interface than conventional models. 
Conclusion: In both implant systems, platform switching design reduced the stress con-
centration in the crestal bone and shifted it towards the area of implant-abutment interface. 
In recent years, several investigations have 
been carried out in order to explain the 
changes observed in crestal bone height. Loca-
tion of the implant-abutment junction (IAJ) in </p>



<p>Journal of Dentistry, Tehran University of Medical Sciences </p>

<p>Sahabi et. al </p>

<p>www.jdt.tums.ac.ir July 2013; Vol. 10, No. 4 </p>



<p>relation to crestal bone [6-8], the bacterial co-
lonization of the micro-gap at the IAJ [9], the 
establishment of a biological width or mucosal 
barrier around dental implants [1, 10-12] and 
the stress-strain concentration due to occlusal 
loading [13-17] are among factors that have 
been suggested as the most likely causes of 
these crestal bone-level changes. Although 
this 1.5-2.0 mm of bone resorption is still clin-
ically acceptable [18], the ability to reduce this 
crestal bone loss may have several advantages 
such as improved esthetics, higher bone to im-
plant contact and better primary stability. 
[1,2,19]. In order to minimize this crestal bone 
resorption, several techniques and procedures 
such as non-submerged technique [20,21], uti-
lizing micro-roughness on implant neck sur-
face [22] and platform switching [23] have 
recently been developed. 
The concept of platform switching was intro-
duced by Lazzara and Porter, and refers to the 
use of a smaller-diameter abutment on a larg-
er-diameter implant collar [23]. Through 
placement of the smaller prosthetic compo-
nents on the implant platform, IAJ is moved 
inward from the implant shoulder and further 
away from the crestal bone [19,23,24]. Hypo-
thetically, platform switching may increase the 
distance between the inflammatory cell infil-
trate and the adjacent alveolar crest that can 
limit crestal bone resorption around the res-
tored two-piece implants [25]. The results of 
several histomorphometric studies showed that 
platform switching can significantly help to 
maintain the peri-implant soft and hard tissue 
and may be especially beneficial in esthetical-
ly demanding locations that require strong soft 
tissue support [25-29]. 
In the past two decades, finite element analy-
sis (FEA) has become an increasingly useful 
tool for prediction of the effects of stress on 
the implant and its surrounding bone, and has 
been used extensively in describing biome-
chanical performance of dental implant sys-
tems [30]. However, excessive simplifications 
of geometry will result in considerable inaccu-</p>

<p>racy in FEA results. To produce more accurate 
geometries, some methods starting from com-
puted tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance 
data of actual human bones have been pro-
posed [11]. 
Several studies on platform switching, using 
three-dimensional (3D) finite element models, 
reported the biomechanical advantage of shift-
ing stress concentration area away from the 
cervical bone implant interface [31-34]. Some 
FEA studies, on the other hand, showed that 
platform switching may have a minimal effect 
on von-Mises stress in the crestal region of the 
cortical bone [35]. Interestingly, a new FEA 
investigation about platform switching dem-
onstrated that the reduction in bone strain was 
mostly caused by increasing the diameter of 
the implant, instead of using the platform 
switching technique [36]. </p>

<p>Reviewing the dental literature revealed 
that there are still some controversies 
about the biomechanical advantages 
of platform switching. Therefore, the ob-
jectives of this three-dimensional FEA 
study were to compare and analyze the 
biomechanical effects of platform switch-
ing on the crestal bone around the two dif-
ferent dental implant systems. </p>

<p>MATHERIALS AND METHODS 
FE model design 
Computerized tomographic (CT) images of a 
human edentulous mandibular first molar area 
were acquired. The distance between adjacent 
CT images was 2.0 mm. The mandible was 
approximately 8.5 mm in width buccolingual-
ly and 24 mm in height inferosuperiorly. The 
cross-sectional image was extruded to create a 
3D section of the mandible and then 3D finite 
element models were constructed. Models 
were prepared with two implant systems: 
XiVE S Plus (DENTSPLY Friadent, GmbH, 
Germany) and 3i Certain (Biomet 3i, Florida, 
USA). 
These implant systems were assembled on the 
mandible creating six different models: model </p>



<p>Sahabi et. al </p>

<p>Biomechanical Effects of Platform Switching in Two Different Implant Systems </p>

<p>www.jdt.tums.ac.ir July 2013; Vol. 10, No. 4 </p>



<p>XiVE-a: 3.8×11 mm implant and 3.8-mm-
diameter Esthetic Base abutment, model 
XiVE-b: 4.5×11 mm implant and 3.8-mm-
diameter Esthetic Base abutment, model 
XiVE-c: 4.5×11 mm implant and 4.5-mm-
diameter Esthetic Base abutment, model 3i-a: 
4.0×11.5 mm implant and 4.1-mm-diameter 
Certain abutment, model 3i-b: 5.0×11.5 mm 
implant and 4.1-mm-diameter Certain abut-
ment, model 3i-c: 5.0×11.5 mm implant and 
5.0-mm-diameter Certain abutment. Platform-
switching configuration was only assumed for 
groups XiVE-b and 3i-b (Fig 1). 
The optical digitizing system ATOS II (GOM, 
Braunschweig, Germany) was used to digitize 
the implants and abutments with high accura-
cy. </p>

<p>The measured data were imported to <rs id="software-0" type="software">Solid- Works</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-date">2008</rs> environment (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Solidworks Crop</rs>., 
Concord, MA, USA) to construct the solid 
models that were analyzed by a three dimen-
sional FE analysis package (<rs id="software-1" type="software">ABAQUS</rs> V<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">6.7- 1</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Simulia Corp</rs>., Providence, USA). Models 
were meshed with four-node tetrahedral solid 
elements, and were meshed between 90,765 
and 102,795 nodes, and between 457,151 and 
519,456 contact elements. </p>

<p>Material Properties 
The implants and bone used in the models 
were considered to be isotropic, homogeneous 
and linearly elastic. The elastic properties 
were adopted from the literature as shown in 
Table 1 [37, 38]. </p>

<p>Table 1. Material Properties of Bone and Finite Element Models </p>

<p>Material 
Young (Elastic)'s Modulus(MPa) 
Poisson's Ratio </p>

<p>Cortical Bone 
13,700 
0.30 </p>

<p>[37] </p>

<p>Cancellous Bone 
1,370 
0.30 </p>

<p>[37] </p>

<p>Titanium 
110,000 
0.33 </p>

<p>[38] </p>

<p>Fig 1. Three dimensional models of implants and abutments. From left to right: model XiVE a, model 
XiVE b, model XiVE c, model 3i a, model 3i b, and model 3i c. </p>



<p>Journal of Dentistry, Tehran University of Medical Sciences </p>

<p>Sahabi et. al </p>

<p>www.jdt.tums.ac.ir July 2013; Vol. 10, No. 4 </p>



<p>Interface Conditions 
Connectivity between the bone and implants 
were assumed to simulate 100% osseointegra-
tion and the abutments and implants were as 
sumed to be completely bonded without any 
movement. </p>

<p>Loading and Boundary Conditions 
As the boundary condition, the nodes at the 
mesial and distal surfaces of the mandibular 
bone were fixed in all directions. In order to 
evaluate the stress distribution in peri-implant 
bone tissue and on implants and abutments, a </p>

<p>Fig 2. Von Mises stress distribution in the peri-implant bone tissue for all six models induced by 100 N 
oblique load (a) and 100 N vertical load (b). </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>



<p>Sahabi et. al </p>

<p>Biomechanical Effects of Platform Switching in Two Different Implant Systems </p>

<p>www.jdt.tums.ac.ir July 2013; Vol. 10, No. 4 </p>



<p>linear static analysis was performed on the 
prepared 3D solid models. Loading was simu-
lated by applying either axial or an oblique 
load (in a buccolingual direction with 15 de-
grees of inclination to the alveolar longitudinal 
axis) of 100 N on the top of the abutments in 
their central region [39, 40]. 
Finally, the finite element models were used to 
calculate von Mises stresses in the crestal bone 
(both compact and cancellous bone) surround-
ing implants and in the implant-abutment in-
terface area. Moreover, stress distribution in 
the FE models were illustrated to compare the 
biomechanical differences between conven-
tional and platform-switching models in two 
different implant systems. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Stress distribution in the implants and peri-
implant bone tissue: 
The results from FEA are demonstrated in 
stress maps with a color scale that makes it 
possible to compare the stress distribution in 
different structures (implants and peri-implant 
bone tissues) of all six models (Fig 2). In order 
to compare stress distribution among the struc-
tures in different models more quantitatively, 
stress values are presented for equivalent 
stresses (von Mises) (Table 2). 
Moreover, the maximum (the first) and mini-
mum (the third) principal stresses at crestal 
bone are demonstrated in Figs 4 and 5. 
The maximum and minimum principal stress </p>

<p>Fig3. Von Mises stress distribution at the implant-abutment interfaces of all six models induced by 100 N 
oblique load (a) and 100 N vertical load (b). </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>



<p>Journal of Dentistry, Tehran University of Medical Sciences </p>

<p>Sahabi et. al </p>

<p>www.jdt.tums.ac.ir July 2013; Vol. 10, No. 4 </p>



<p>indicates maximum tensile and compressive 
stress, respectively. 
The positive values show tensile stress and the 
negatives demonstrate compressive stress.The 
pattern of stress distribution was almost simi-
lar under both loading situations and for both 
two implant systems. However, oblique loads 
produced more stress among the models than 
axial loads. 
In all models and under both loading situa-
tions, stress values were higher for the cortical 
bone than the cancellous bone (Table 2). 
Under 100 N oblique load, the maximum von 
Mises stress in the cortical bone was from 
15.06 MPa in model XiVE -b (platform-
switching model) to 32.11 MPa in model 3i-a. 
Moreover, the maximum von Mises stress in 
the cancellous bone was from 2.49 MPa in 
model 3i-b (platform switching model) to 6.28 
MPa in model XiVE-a. 
The results clearly showed that platform-
switching reduced von Mises stress values at 
the crestal bone in both implant systems (Fig 
2). 
In both 3i and XiVE implant systems, wide 
platform implants (models 3i-c and XiVE-c) 
presented lower stress values and more favor-
able patterns of stress distribution compared to 
regular platform implants (models 3i-a and 
XiVE-a). </p>

<p>For maximum principal stress, the tensile 
stress concentration was located on the buccal 
side of the cortical bone tissue that was on the 
opposite side of load application. For mini-
mum principal stress, the location of compres-
sive stress concentration was under the ap-
plied-load side of the models. In almost all 
models, tensile stress was less than compres-
sive stress. In both implant systems and for 
both loading conditions, the platform switch-
ing models presented obvious decreases in 
tension and compression values in the third 
principal stress. However, for the first princip-
al stress, wide platform models showed lower 
tension values, while platform-switching mod-
els showed lower compression values (Figs 4 
and 5). </p>

<p>Stress distribution at the implant-abutment 
interface 
Analyzing implant-abutment interface demon-
strated that the stress concentration was 
around the periphery of the uppermost surface 
of the implant in the conventional models 
(models a, c) (Fig 3), while this high stress 
area shifted toward the center of the implant in 
the platform-switching models. In both im-
plant systems and for both loading conditions, 
the platform switching increased the stress 
value in the implant-abutment interface. </p>

<p>Cortical Bone 
(MPa) </p>

<p>Cancellous Bone 
(MPa) </p>

<p>Abutment-Implant 
Interface (MPa) </p>

<p>Load 
Oblique 
Vertical 
Oblique 
Vertical 
Oblique 
Vertical </p>

<p>Model 3i-a 
32.11 
18.16 
3.13 
3,26 
60.27 
17.01 
Model 3i-b 
16.25 
13.4 
2.49 
3.84 
70.76 
21.3 </p>

<p>Model 3i-c 
20.36 
14.87 
2.69 
5.52 
34.60 
16.82 
Model XiVE-a 
23.31 
11.81 
6.28 
7.06 
65.70 
23.57 
Model XiVE-b 
15.06 
7.96 
3.28 
3.68 
80.20 
33.84 
Model XiVE-c 
20.94 
10.52 
2.83 
3.09 
54.70 
23.22 </p>

<p>Table 2. Maximum von Mises Stress Values (MPa) in the Models induced by 100 N Oblique and Vertical Loading </p>



<p>Sahabi et. al </p>

<p>Biomechanical Effects of Platform Switching in Two Different Implant Systems </p>

<p>www.jdt.tums.ac.ir July 2013; Vol. 10, No. 4 </p>



<p>Fig 4. Peri-implant principal stresses (MPa) in crestal bone for 3i implant models (a) and XiVE implant 
models (b) induced by 100 N oblique load </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>



<p>Journal of Dentistry, Tehran University of Medical Sciences </p>

<p>Sahabi et. al </p>

<p>www.jdt.tums.ac.ir July 2013; Vol. 10, No. 4 </p>



<p>Fig 5. Implant principal stresses (MPa) in crestal bone for 3i implant models (a) and XiVE implant models 
(b) induced by 100 N vertical loading </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>



<p>Sahabi et. al </p>

<p>Biomechanical Effects of Platform Switching in Two Different Implant Systems </p>

<p>www.jdt.tums.ac.ir July 2013; Vol. 10, No. 4 </p>



<p>Moreover, wide platform implants (models 3i-
c and XiVE-c) showed lower von Mises 
stresses than implants with regular platforms 
(models 3i-a and XiVE-a) (Table 2). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Bone resorption close to the first thread of the 
two-piece implants is frequently observed dur-
ing initial loading [2, 5]. To achieve and main-
tain stable osseointegration for implants in 
function, high stress concentration in the bone 
should be avoided. Some studies showed that 
using abutments with a smaller diameter than 
the implant neck or platform-switching tech-
nique helps in reducing crestal bone resorption 
[4, 23-25]. The possible reasons for bone pre-
servation with the platform switching tech-
nique include inward shifting of the location 
of the IAJ or the stress concentration area be-
tween the abutment and implant [23, 26]. 
The result of the present study revealed that 
the platform switching reduced von Mises 
stress values at the crestal bone in both im-
plant systems. It has been reported in the lite-
rature that crestal bone resorption is related to 
excessive load and damage of the supporting 
interfacial bone [41]. Stress concentration can 
lead to bone loss due to bone micro-damage 
and creation of crater-like bone defects around 
the implant [32, 42]. Tabata et al. [32] re-
ported that von Mises, maximum and mini-
mum principal stress were reduced in peri-
implant bone tissue and implant when the plat-
form-switching concept was used. In studies 
conducted by Hsu et al.[36] and Schrotenboer 
et al.[33], their FE analyses showed that when 
the abutment diameter was reduced, less stress 
was transferred to the crestal bone. However, 
the results of the present study are in contrast 
to the results previously reported by Pessoa et 
al. [35] The possible reasons may be attributed 
to the fact that in their FE models, platform 
switching was defined as the circumferential 
horizontal mismatch of 0.5 mm between im-
plant and abutment, while in the present study, </p>

<p>this horizontal mismatch was 1 mm for 3i im-
plants and 0.7 mm for XiVE implants. In 
another study, Canay and Akca [43] revealed 
that the platform-switching concept is an ef-
fective factor on mechanical properties of im-
plant-abutment complex rather than the load-
induced stresses developed at the marginal 
bone around implants. However, those results 
were obtained in very simplified models that 
did not consider the internal geometry of im-
plant-abutment junction in detail. 
In agreement with previous studies [32, 44,  45], it was confirmed that wide platform im-
plants show a lower stress value and more fa-
vorable stress distribution compared to regular 
platform implants. It seems that increasing the 
implant diameter enhances the contact be-
tween the implant and the bone that dramati-
cally reduced stress concentration [44]. Inte-
restingly, the platform-switching models of 
both implant systems still showed lower stress 
values than wide platform configurations. In 
other words, stress distribution was influenced 
more by the platform switching concept than 
the implant diameter. 
Hsu et al. [36] in a strain gauge analysis of 
immediately loaded implants concluded that 
bone strain was reduced more by increasing 
the diameter of the implant than by using plat-
form switching. However, one should keep in 
mind that in the present study, similar to most 
of the previous FEA studies, models of delay-
loaded implants were used, in which there was 
an ideal osseointegration between the surface 
of the implant and the bone. In addition, some 
studies reported that the concentration of 
stress is greater around immediately loaded 
implants than around delay-loaded implants 
[26, 27]. 
The present study also indicated that in both 
implant systems, the compressive and tensile 
stresses were lower in platform-switching 
models than conventional models at the com-
pact bone in the vicinity of the implant neck. 
Extensive compressive stress may increase the </p>



<p>Journal of Dentistry, Tehran University of Medical Sciences </p>

<p>Sahabi et. al </p>

<p>www.jdt.tums.ac.ir July 2013; Vol. 10, No. 4 </p>



<p>risk of bone resorption, since it can compro-
mise the periosteal blood supply and may re-
sult in bone necrosis [46]. High tensile stress 
has also been reported to cause bone loss [47]. 
Thus, the platform-switched design of both 
systems can reduce the risk of bone resorption 
and loss of osseointegration. Similarly, Chang 
et al. [34] showed higher compressive and ten-
sile stresses in the conventional model than in 
the platform-switching model at the crestal 
bone around implants. 
In agreement with recently published studies 
[32, 45], the present investigation demonstrat-
ed that platform switching increased the stress 
concentration in the implant-abutment inter-
face. It was suggested that the increased stress 
concentration at the implant-abutment inter-
face in platform switching models can lead to 
mechanical problems such as screw loosening 
or fracture [48]. 
However, according to a study performed by 
Maeda et al. [31], such complications happen 
only if the stresses exceed the elastic limit. 
These increases in stress values may not result 
in any major complication, since the yield 
strength of titanium alloy (620 to 725 MPa) 
[37] and cobalt-chromium alloy (552 to 1,034 
MPa) [38] is more than the stress values re-
ported in the implant-abutment interface of 
both systems [32] (Table 2). To construct a 
finite element model, it is usually necessary to 
simplify the system by making some assump-
tions. The implants and bone used in the mod-
els were considered to be isotropic, homoge-
neous and linearly elastic and the occlusal 
forces were static. Furthermore, in the present 
study, the bone-implant contact was 100%, but 
in vivo, bone-implant contact percentages 
usually range from 30% to 70%. Thus, the fi-
nal models represented an average clinical sit-
uation, and generalization of its results should 
be done with care. Therefore, because the fi-
nite element models used in this study do not 
identically reproduce all clinical situations, the 
application of the results should be tempered 
with sound clinical judgment. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION 
Within the limitation of this 3D finite element 
analysis study, the following conclusions were 
drawn: 
1-In both implant systems,platform-switching 
design reduced the stress concentration at the 
crestal bone and shifted it towards the area of 
implant-abutment interface. 
2-In the present study, this stress reduction 
was not related to increasing Implant diameter. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS 
This article was based on a post-graduate the-
sis and financially supported by Dental Re-
search Center, Research Institute of Dental 
Sciences of Shahid Beheshti University of 
Medical Sciences (grant No. 5416 ). There 
was no conflict of interest in this article. </p>

<p>REFERENCES 
1-Hermann F, Lerner H, Palti A. Factors in-
fluencing the preservation of the periimplant 
marginal bone. Implant Dent. 2007 
Jun;16(2):165-75. 
2-Cardaropoli G, Lekholm U, Wennstrom JL. 
Tissue alterations at implant-supported single 
tooth replacements: A 1-year prospective clin-
ical study. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2006 
Apr;17(2):165-71. 
3-Oh TJ, Yoon J, Misch CE, Wang HL. The 
causes of early implant bone loss: myth or 
science? J Periodontol. 2002 Mar;73(3):322-
33. 
4-Fickl S, Zuhr O, Stein JM, Hurzeler MB. 
Peri-implant bone level around implants with 
platform-switched abutments. Int J Oral Max-
illofac Implants. 2010 May-Jun;25(3):577-81. 
5-de Almeida FD, Carvalho AC, Fontes M, 
Pedrosa A, Costa R, Noleto JW et al. Radio-
graphic evaluation of marginal bone level 
around internal-hex implants with switched 
platform: a clinical case report series. Int J 
Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2011 May-
Jun;26(3):587-92. 
6-Hermann JS, Cochran DL, Nummikoski 
PV, Buser D. Crestal bone changes around </p>



<p>Sahabi et. al </p>

<p>Biomechanical Effects of Platform Switching in Two Different Implant Systems </p>





<p>Journal of Dentistry, Tehran University of Medical Sciences </p>

<p>Sahabi et. al </p>

<p>www.jdt.tums.ac.ir July 2013; Vol. 10, No. 4 </p>







<p>Sahabi et. al </p>

<p>Biomechanical Effects of Platform Switching in Two Different Implant Systems </p>

<p>www.jdt.tums.ac.ir July 2013; Vol. 10, No. 4 </p>







</text></tei>