<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3664807" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The DNase I accessibility and chromatin organiza-
tion of genes within the nucleus do correlate to their 
transcriptional activity. Here, we show that both 
serum starvation and overexpression of Tip5, a key 
regulator of ribosomal RNA gene (rDNA) repression, 
dictate DNase I accessibility, facilitate the associ-
ation of rDNA with the nuclear matrix and thus 
regulate large-scale rDNA chromatin organization. 
Tip5 contains four AT-hooks and a TAM (Tip5/ 
ARBP/MBD) domain, which were proposed to bind 
matrix-attachment regions (MARs) of the genome. 
Remarkably, the TAM domain of Tip5 functions as 
nucleolar localization and nuclear matrix targeting 
module, whereas AT-hooks do not mediate associ-
ation with the nuclear matrix, but they are required 
for nucleolar targeting. These findings suggest a 
dual role for Tip5's AT-hooks and TAM domain, tar-
geting the nucleolus and anchoring to the nuclear 
matrix, and suggest a function for Tip5 in the regu-
lation of higher-order rDNA chromatin structure. </p>

<p>Mammalian cells synthesize the 47S precursor for riboso-
mal RNA (rRNA) from multicopy genes. During recent 
years, several chromatin-dependent regulators of rRNA 
transcription were discovered, which take part in the 
balancing of this highly energy-demanding metabolic 
activity of the cell [reviewed in (1)]. Compared with 
promoter-specific actions of these chromatin regulators, 
little is known about their role in large-scale spatial organ-
ization and distribution of actively transcribed versus 
inactive rRNA gene copies in the nucleus. The synthesis </p>

<p>of 47S pre-rRNA from active rDNA takes place at the 
fibrillar center/dense fibrillar component (FC/DFC 
border) of the mammalian nucleolus, whereas inactive 
rDNA is localized within the FC or outside of nucleoli 
[for a recent review see (2)]. It has been demonstrated 
earlier that changes in the ribosome synthesis activity 
result in alterations of nucleolar architecture when cells 
are treated with different inhibitors of ribosome biogenesis 
or serum starved (3-5). Part of the morphological alter-
ations in nucleolar structure may be correlated to rDNA 
chromatin movements, which accompany changes in the 
transcriptional activity of rRNA genes. 
In addition to the visual inspection of nuclear mor-
phology, nuclear matrix isolation enables a simple 
biochemical characterization of large-scale chromatin or-
ganization. The nuclear matrix was originally defined as a 
component of nuclei that resists extensive DNase I diges-
tion and salt extraction (6). It contains mainly intermedi-
ate filament proteins like lamins, heterogeneous nuclear 
ribonucleoprotein particles, specific non-histone chroma-
tin proteins and associated DNA, which represents the 
matrix-attachment regions (MARs) of the genome. 
MARs, which are supposed to anchor chromatin loops 
to the nuclear matrix constitutively or transiently, have 
been implicated in the regulation of gene expression and 
replication [for a review see (7)]. Importantly, specific en-
richment of rDNA in nuclear matrix preparations has 
been demonstrated by using biochemical (8) and cell 
biology methods (9). 
Previous studies on rDNA chromatin regulation 
revealed the role of the nucleolar remodeling complex 
(NoRC) in nucleosome positioning, transcriptional repres-
sion, epigenetic silencing and replication timing (10-14). 
NoRC consists of two subunits, the ATPase subunit Snf2h 
and the large, regulatory subunit Tip5 (15). More recently, 
the association of these two proteins with the transcrip-
tional co-repressor CtBP (C-terminal-binding protein) </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +49 9419 432 846; Fax: +49 9419 432 474; Email: attila.nemeth@vkl.uni-regensburg.de 
Correspondence may also be addressed to Gernot La¨ngst. Tel: +49 9419 432 849; Fax: +49 9419 432 474; Email: gernot.laengst@ 
vkl.uni-regensburg.de </p>

<p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. </p>

<p>Published online 10 April 2013 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 10 5251-5262 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkt218 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0/), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>was also reported, and a non-nucleolar chromatin regula-
tory function of this tripartite complex has been described 
(16). The role of Tip5 in the inactivation of rRNA tran-
scription has been demonstrated to involve cooperation 
with proteins, such as TTF-I, HDACs and Dnmts 
(12,14,17). Tip5 not only has numerous protein interacting 
domains but also has several predicted AT-hooks and the 
TAM domain. AT-hooks are small peptide motifs, which 
mediate binding to the minor groove and thereby alter the 
architecture of DNA (18-20). The TAM domain shows 
sequence homology to the methyl-CpG-binding domain 
(MBD) found in transcriptional repressor proteins that 
selectively bind methylated DNA (18,21). However, the 
TAM domain of Tip5 has been shown to bind to DNA 
irrespective of its DNA methylation status (15) and also 
associates with the structured rDNA promoter RNA (22). 
As the TAM domain and AT-hooks are predicted MAR 
binders (18), we hypothesized that Tip5 could mediate the 
anchoring of rDNA to the nuclear matrix and, thus, 
separate silenced rDNA repeats from active ones. To elu-
cidate the contribution of transcriptional repression, and 
particularly that of Tip5, to the control of large-scale or-
ganization of rDNA chromatin, the association of rDNA 
with the nuclear matrix was analyzed after serum starva-
tion and overexpression of Tip5. In subsequent experi-
ments, the DNA-binding activities of single AT-hook 
domains of the Tip5 protein were characterized in vitro, 
and the role of AT-hooks and the TAM domain in sub-
nuclear localization and nuclear matrix association of 
Tip5 was investigated in vivo. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Cell culture </p>

<p>IMR90 human lung embryonic fibroblasts, HeLa human 
cervix carcinoma cells and HEK293 human embryonic 
kidney cells were maintained in Dulbecco's modified 
Eagle's medium with 10% fetal calf serum, 100 U/ml of 
penicillin and 100 mg/ml of streptomycin and incubated at 
37 C in 5% CO 2 . IMR90 cells were cultured for 1 week in 
serum-free medium in serum starvation experiments. 
HeLa and HEK293 cells were used in transfection experi-
ments, and DNA was delivered with the FuGENE HD 
(Roche) transfection reagent according to the manufac-
turer's instructions. Tip5 sequences were derived from 
mouse Tip5 cDNA (GenBank Acc. No AJ309544). </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence </p>

<p>Cells were rinsed twice in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) 
at 37 C. Fixation was performed in 4% paraformaldehyde 
in PBS for 10 min at room temperature. During the last 
minute, few drops of 0.5% Triton X-100 in PBS were 
added to the cells. Afterwards cells were washed three 
times in PBS with 0.01% Triton X-100 for 3 min at 
room temperature, followed by 5 min in PBS with 0.5% 
Triton X-100. Finally, cells were washed with PBS-T (PBS 
with 0.1% Tween20) twice for 5 min at room temperature 
and stored at 4 C. All the subsequent steps were carried 
out at 37 C. Cells were washed in PBS-T three times for 
5 min before antibody staining. Afterwards they were </p>

<p>incubated with the primary antibody in 4% bovine 
serum albumin (BSA) in PBS-T for 1 h in a humidified 
chamber. Cells were then again washed in PBS-T three 
times for 3 min and incubated with the suitable secondary 
antibody in 4% BSA in PBS-T for 1 h. After washing with 
PBS-T twice for 5 min, the DNA was counterstained with 
50 ng/ml of DAPI in PBS-T for 5 min. Slides were rinsed 
again in PBS-T and mounted in Vectashield mounting 
medium (Vector). For detection of Tip5, cells were fixed 
in methanol and acetone as previously described (15) and 
then processed as described earlier in the text. Images were 
taken on a Zeiss Axiovert 200 inverted fluorescence micro-
scope using the <rs type="software">Axio Vision</rs> software. </p>

<p>Nuclear matrix isolation </p>

<p>The isolation of nuclear matrix was carried out essentially 
as described (6,23,24). A total of 2.5-5 Â 10 6 cells were 
washed in 1 ml of PBS, pH 7.4, (5 min, 1000g centrifuga-
tion), and cells were extracted in 200 ml of cytoskeleton 
buffer (10 mM PIPES, pH 6.8, 100 mM NaCl, 300 mM 
sucrose, 3 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM EGTA, supplemented with 
Protease Inhibitor Cocktail (Roche), 1 mM TCEP and 
0.5% Triton X-100). After 5 min incubation at 4 C, 
soluble cytoplasmic proteins were separated by centrifu-
gation at 5000g for 3 min (supernatant = 'CP' cytoplasmic 
fraction). Chromatin was solubilized by DNA digestion 
with 400 U of RNase-free DNase I (Roche) in 110 ml of 
CSK buffer plus protease inhibitors for 90 min at 37 C 
with shaking at 300 g. In particular experiments, RNase 
A at 0.3 mg/ml final concentration was also added at this 
step. Then 50 ml of ammonium sulfate was added from a 
1 M stock solution in CSK buffer to a final concentration 
of 0.25 M, and, after 5 min incubation at 4 C on rotating 
wheel, samples were pelleted again by centrifugation at 
5000 g for 3 min (supernatant = 'CHR' chromatin 
fraction). The pellet was further extracted with 100 ml of 
2 M NaCl in CSK buffer for 10 min at 4 C on rotating 
wheel and then centrifuged at 5000g for 3 min. This treat-
ment removes all accessible DNA and histones from the 
nucleus (supernatant = '2M' 2 M salt wash fraction, 
which was diluted 1:2 with water before SDS-PAGE). 
The remaining pellet was solubilized in 200 ml of 8 M 
urea buffer (10 mM Tris-HCl, 100 mM NaH 2 PO 4 Â H 2 O, 
8 M urea; pH 8.0) and was considered the nuclear matrix-
containing fraction ('NM'). Hundred microliters of each 
fraction was dialyzed against 1Â TE buffer and subse-
quently digested with RNaseA (37 C, 1 h) and proteinase 
K (50 C o/n), precipitated, dissolved in 50 ml of ddH 2 O 
and controlled on 1% agarose gel (10 ml), and the 'NM' 
fraction was subjected to qPCR analysis. In all, 25 ml of 
5Â La¨mmli buffer was added to the remaining 100 ml of 
the fractions, and 20 ml each was subjected to western blot 
analysis or Coomassie staining after boiling the probes at 
95 C, 10 min and separating on denaturing SDS-poly-
acrylamide gels. </p>

<p>Nuclear matrix preparations in situ </p>

<p>In situ preparations of nuclear matrix for immunofluores-
cence analysis was done essentially as described (25). For 
protease inhibition, the complete EDTA-free tablets </p>



<p>(Roche) were used. Chromatin digestion was performed 
using 500 U/ml of recombinant DNase I, RNase-free 
(Roche) at 30 C for 30 min. After matrix preparation, 
cells were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde in PBS at room 
temperature for 15 min. Immunofluorescence detection 
was carried out as described earlier in the text. </p>

<p>Quantitative PCR </p>

<p>To measure the quantities of rDNA fragments in the 
nuclear matrix fractions from different experiments, ap-
proximately equal amounts of the isolated nuclear 
matrix-associated DNA were used as templates from 
control versus treated cells. The interferon b (IFNb) 
promoter MAR, which is not bound by Tip5, served as 
normalization control, and the amount of rDNA 
promoter, 28S and intergenic spacer (IGS) MAR se-
quences were quantified in the isolated DNA fractions. 
The oligonucleotides were as follows: IFNbF 5 0 -TGC 
TCT CCT GTT GTG CTT CTC CAC, IFNbR 5 0 -ATA 
GAT GGT CAA TGC GGC GTC C, Hr42857F 5 0 -ATG 
GTG GCG TTT TTG GGG AC, Hr42964R 5 0 -CGA 
AAG ATA TAC CTC CCC CG, Hr9661F 5 0 -CGA 
ATG ATT AGA GGT CTT GGG GC, Hr9860R 
5 0 -TGG GGT CTG ATG AGC GTC GG, Hr36189F 5 0 -
TCG CCG ACT CTC TCT TGA CTT G, Hr36399R 5 0 -
TGG AGC ACA GTG ACA CAA CTA TGG. The 
numbers of human rDNA oligos (Hr) indicate the position 
relative to the transcription start site (+1) in the repeat 
unit (GenBank Acc. No. U13369). </p>

<p>Antibodies </p>

<p>To detect proteins on western blots or by immunofluores-
cence 
rabbit 
polyclonal 
a-Upstream 
Binding 
Transcription Factor, RNA Polymerase I (UBF) (sc-
9131, Santa Cruz Biotechnology), a-lamin A/C (sc-
20681, Santa Cruz Biotechnology), a-RPA194 (sc-28714, 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology), a-Tip5 (15), a-Snf2h, a-
RPA116 (26), a-Brg1, a-Mi-2 (both were a kind gift of 
A. Brehm) and mouse monoclonal a-fibrillarin (38F3, 
Novus Biologicals) and a-tubulin (ab7291, Abcam) 
antibodies were used at appropriate dilutions. </p>

<p>Expression and purification of recombinant proteins </p>

<p>GST-AT-hook constructs were prepared by inserting 
oligonucleotides containing the coding region for the 
peptides listed in Figure 4A and flanking BamHI/SalI re-
striction sites into pGEX4T3. The fusion proteins were ex-
pressed in the Escherichia coli Rosetta strain as follows: the 
transformed bacteria were induced at OD 600 = 0.6 by 
adding IPTG at 0.5 mM final concentration and incubated 
for 3-4 h at 37 C. Cells were then harvested and affinity 
purified on Glutathione Sepharose 4B beads (Pharmacia) 
in batch according to the manufacturer's protocol. Protein 
concentration of the elution fractions was estimated by 
using the Bradford assay (Bio-Rad). </p>

<p>Gel retardation assays </p>

<p>To analyze the DNA-binding activity of recombinant 
AT-hooks, gel retardation assays were performed as </p>

<p>follows: 34 bp, double-stranded synthetic oligonucleotides 
(sense strand sequences: rDNA En: 5 0 -TGG ATC TTT 
TTT TTT TTT TTT CTT TTT TCC TCC A, rDNA 
IGS: 5 0 -AAG TCG TGC CTA AAA TAA ATA TTT 
TTC TGG CCA A, IFNb: 5 0 -GGA GAA GTG AAA 
GTG GGA AAT TCC TCT GAA TAG A, GC ctrl: 5 0 -
CAC GCG CTC GCG CAC GCG CTC GCG CAC GCG 
CTC) were incubated with recombinant AT-hook proteins 
in 180 mM NaCl, 1 mM MgCl 2 , 0.01% (w/v) BSA, 10 mM 
Tris, pH 8.1, and 5% glycerol. Ten-microliter reactions 
were incubated for 10 min on ice, and protein-DNA 
complexes were separated on 6% native polyacrylamide 
gels in 0.4Â TBE buffer at 4 C applying the constant 
voltage of 100 V. The gels were stained with SybrSafe, 
and DNA was visualized on a transilluminator. </p>

<p>Microscale thermophoresis </p>

<p>All microscale thermophoresis measurements were per-
formed at room temperature using Monolith NT TM 
Hydrophobic Capillaries and the Monolith NT.015T 
device by NanoTemper technologies with the laser being 
on for 40 s resulting in a temperature increase of 6 K (27). 
Binding reactions took place in a solution containing 
100 mM NaCl, 50 mM HEPES, pH 7.4, 0.05% (v/v) NP-
40 and 5 mM MgCl 2 in final concentration, as well as one 
type of double-stranded, fluorescently labeled oligonucleo-
tide as template (rDNA En: 5 0 -TCT TTT TTT TTT TTT 
TTC TTT TTT CCT CC, Cy5-labeled; GC ctrl: 5 0 -CAC 
GCG CTC GCG CAC GCG CTC GCG CAC GCG 
CTC, Cy3-labeled) with a constant concentration of 
50 nM. For each binding analysis, a titration series was 
prepared with varying concentrations of the respective 
peptide as indicated in the plots. All curves were plotted 
with the <rs type="software">KaleidaGraph</rs> software, and the thermophoresis 
signals were fitted with the Hill equation corrected for the 
minimum (Min) and maximum (Max) values of the 
binding curve: Y(c) = Min+(Max À Min)/(1+EC 50 / 
c </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>pep ) n , with Y (c) being the thermophoresis signal, c </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>pep </p>

<p>the variable concentration of the respective peptide, 
EC 50 the concentration where half of the oligonucleotide 
is bound and n being the Hill-coefficient. Thermophoresis 
signals were normalized to fraction bound (X) by 
X = [Y(c) À Min]/(Max À Min), error bars (std) were 
normalized by std norm = std(c)/(Max À Min), and both 
were plotted and fitted as described earlier in the text. 
K D values were not determined, as the gel retardation ex-
periments showed that multiple protein-DNA complexes 
appear at higher peptide concentrations (Figure 3B). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Serum starvation induces global changes in nucleolar 
architecture and enrichment of rDNA in the nuclear 
matrix </p>

<p>To monitor changes in nucleolar structure, which correl-
ate to repression of rRNA synthesis, immunofluorescence 
experiments were performed and the distributions of 
UBF, fibrillarin and Pol I were compared in serum-
starved and normally proliferating IMR90 human embry-
onic lung fibroblasts (Figure 1A and Supplementary </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 10 5253 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Serum starvation induces global changes in nucleolar architecture and enrichment of rDNA in the nuclear matrix. (A) Immunofluorescence 
detection of the nucleolar proteins UBF and fibrillarin in control and serum starved IMR90 human embryonic fibroblasts. The nuclei were coun-
terstained with DAPI. The lower panel shows the enlargements of the selected cells that are indicated with an arrow on the merged image of the 
upper panel. Bars indicate 5 mm. (B) Real-time qPCR analysis of serum starvation-induced changes in the nuclear matrix association of rDNA. The 
scheme of the rDNA repeat is shown at the top, 18S, 5.8S, 28S and IGS mark the coding regions and the intergenic spacer of the human rDNA 
(GenBank Acc. No. U13369). Brackets and abbreviations indicate the location of rDNA regions analyzed in qPCR reactions (Prom, promoter; 28S, 
rRNA coding region). Predicted MARs are labeled with hexagons. Similar amounts of purified nuclear matrix template DNA were subjected real-
time qPCR from normally growing and serum-starved cells. C t differences between serum-starved and control cells were determined at the three 
different human rDNA regions and normalized to the C t differences of the IFNb promoter. The results of three biological replicate experiments are 
shown in different colors. </p>



<p>Figure S1). Serum starvation led to reduction of nucleolar 
size and focal compactions of UBF and Pol I signals 
within the nucleolus. Based on these results and similar 
observations in previous reports (28-30), we assumed that 
the spatial organization of rDNA chromatin in the nucle-
olus is changed after repression of rRNA synthesis. To test 
this hypothesis, the relative amounts of various rDNA 
fragments in isolated nuclear matrix fractions of control 
and serum-starved cells were quantified and compared 
with the level of the IFNb promoter, which is a bona 
fide MAR (31), stably associated with the nuclear 
matrix, and contains a well-characterized binding site for 
the AT-hook protein HMGA1 (19). We assumed that al-
terations in the relative amount of selected rDNA regions 
compared with this specific MAR reflect the changes in the 
association of rDNA with the nuclear matrix. First, the 
putative MARs of the human rDNA were determined in 
silico by using a formerly developed web tool (32). 
Predicted MARs localize to the IGS of rDNA as shown 
in Figure 1B. Real-time qPCR reactions were established 
to quantify the amount of one selected rDNA IGS 
sequence (IGS) that is localized between two predicted 
neighboring MAR, as well as two additional rDNA 
regions, which are not predicted MARs (Figure 1B). 
One of these sites, the rDNA promoter (Prom), is a 
binding site of Tip5. Tip5 possesses four AT-hooks and 
a TAM domain and, therefore, potentially targets its 
binding sites to the nuclear matrix. Another sequence 
was selected from the rDNA coding region (28S) where 
no Tip5 binding occurs (12). Thus, our experimental 
system allows the monitoring of MAR-and Tip5-depend-
ent and -independent associations of rDNA sequences 
with the nuclear matrix. Similar amounts of purified 
nuclear matrix template DNA were analyzed from 
normally growing and serum-starved cells in quantitative 
real-time PCR reactions. Threshold cycle (C t ) differences 
between serum-starved and control cells were determined 
at each of the three different regions of the human rDNA 
and normalized to the C t differences of the IFNb 
promoter (Figure 1B). The results of three biological rep-
licates are shown and demonstrate that the three tested 
rDNA regions are accumulating in the nuclear matrix 
on serum starvation. They are sequestered to different 
extent: the IGS sequence is enriched $1.5-to 2-fold in 
the matrix fraction compared with the IFNb promoter, 
the coding region 2-to 5-fold, whereas the promoter 
region is enriched 5-to 10-fold. </p>

<p>Tip5 is associated with the nuclear matrix and targets the 
rDNA to the nuclear matrix </p>

<p>Because the NoRC subunit Tip5 contains several pre-
dicted MAR-binding domains (18), we tested its potential 
to target rDNA to the nuclear matrix. First, the sub-
cellular localization of Tip5 was investigated by immuno-
fluorescence. The result showed that Tip5 predominantly, 
but not exclusively, localizes to nucleoli, which were 
marked by B23 immunostaining (Figure 2A). Next, we 
monitored the distribution of Tip5 in the fractions of 
nuclear matrix preparations. Whole-cell extracts of 
HEK293 human embryonic kidney cells were </p>

<p>fractionated, and the resulting cytoplasmic, chromatin, 
high-salt wash and nuclear matrix fractions were 
analyzed by immunoblotting (Figure 2B). The localization 
of lamin A/C in the matrix fraction, a-tubulin in the cyto-
plasmic fraction and large and small amounts of histone 
proteins in the chromatin fraction and wash fraction, re-
spectively, served as controls for the nuclear matrix prep-
arations. The results showed that two pools of Tip5 co-
exist in the cell. These pools were found in the chromatin 
and nuclear matrix fractions, where the majority of the 
protein is located. In contrast, other chromatin re-
modeling complex subunits, i.e. Brg1, Snf2h and Mi-2, 
appeared preferentially in the chromatin fraction. 
Moreover, the distribution of Pol I in the different frac-
tions demonstrated that not all nucleolar transcription 
factors are concentrated in the nuclear matrix. As the 
RNA-binding activity of Tip5 was recently reported 
(22), we also performed the nuclear matrix assay in the 
presence of RNaseA to test for RNA-dependent binding. 
Our results show that the matrix-bound fraction of Tip5 is 
not sensitive to digestion with RNaseA, but chromatin-
bound Tip5 requires RNA for its stable chromatin asso-
ciation (Supplementary Figure S2). In addition to cell 
fractionation, the association of Tip5 with the nuclear 
matrix was investigated by immunofluorescence experi-
ments in HeLa cervix carcinoma cells (Figure 2C). 
Similar to lamin A/C, Tip5 was clearly detectable in situ 
in the nuclear matrix after extensive DNase I digestion 
and chromatin extraction. To test whether there is a 
serum starvation-dependent change in the association of 
Tip5 with the nuclear matrix, immunoblot experiments 
were performed. The results illustrate that there is no de-
tectable loss of Tip5 in the nuclear matrix, the vast 
majority of the protein remains in this fraction 
(Supplementary Figure S3). 
The fact that Tip5 contains a number of DNA-binding 
domains that potentially bind to MAR sequences, and 
that the majority of the protein is present in the nuclear 
matrix fraction suggested that Tip5 could be involved in 
the nuclear matrix targeting of rDNA. To test this hypoth-
esis, we measured the relative amounts of rDNA in the 
nuclear matrix fraction of Tip5-and mock-transfected 
HEK293 cells as described earlier in the text. The 
immunoblot results show that Tip5 was strongly over-
expressed 72 h post-transfection (Figure 2D). DNA quan-
tification revealed that all three regions of the rDNA 
repeat were enriched in the nuclear matrix fraction, thus 
indicating that Tip5 targets rDNA to the nuclear matrix. 
The amount of IGS, coding region and promoter se-
quences increased $2-to 8-fold in the matrix fraction 
compared with the IFNb MAR control. There was only 
a minor difference between the matrix association levels of 
different rDNA regions within the individual biological 
replicate experiments (Figure 2E). </p>

<p>DNA-binding features of potential MAR-binding domains 
of Tip5 </p>

<p>Tip5, the large subunit of NoRC, contains a tandem 
PHD-bromodomain, which is involved in protein-
protein interactions, furthermore a variety of nucleic </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 10 5255 </p>

<p>acid-binding domains, e.g. AT-hooks and the TAM 
domain (Figure 3A), which were proposed to bind 
MARs (18). To begin with the functional characterization 
of Tip5's potential MAR-binding domains, DNA-binding 
assays were performed. The DNA-binding properties of 
the TAM domain have been analyzed in our previous 
study (15); however, the four AT-hooks remained to be 
investigated. Thus, the four individual AT-hooks and the 
combination of the first two AT-hooks of Tip5 were </p>

<p>expressed and purified as GST-tagged recombinant pro-
teins and subjected to gel retardation assays. The well-
characterized second AT-hook of the HMGA1 protein 
(19) served as a control in the DNA-binding assays 
(abbreviated as HMGA1 later in the text). Two AT-rich 
sites from the rDNA IGS were selected in addition to 
the previously characterized HMGA1-binding site of the 
IFNb promoter, and the DNA-binding properties of the 
purified AT-hooks were tested. The gel retardation </p>

<p>Figure 2. Tip5 is associated with the nuclear matrix and targets the rDNA to the nuclear matrix. (A) Immunofluorescence experiments show the 
predominantly nucleolar localization of endogenous Tip5 in HeLa cells. Tip5 was stained with a rabbit polyclonal antibody, the nucleoli with a 
mouse monoclonal B23 antibody and the nuclear DNA with DAPI. Bars indicate 5 mm. (B) Tip5 is associated with the nuclear matrix. Western blot 
and Coomassie gel pictures of nuclear matrix preparations from human HEK293 cells. CP, CHR, 2 M and NM indicate cytoplasmic, soluble 
chromatin, high-salt wash and nuclear matrix fractions, respectively. Tubulin, core histones and lamin A/C served as controls for the CP, CHR/ 
2 M and NM fractions, respectively. Immunoblot detections of Tip5, Snf2h, Brg1, Mi-2 and RPA116, the second largest subunit of RNA polymerase 
I, are shown. (C) Immunofluorescence detection of the association of Tip5 with the nuclear matrix. Nuclear matrix of HeLa cells was prepared in situ 
and analyzed by immunofluorescence. Lamin A/C served as control. The bar indicates 5 mm. (D) Immunoblot detection of Tip5 overexpression. 
HEK293 cells were transfected with full-length, Flag-tagged Tip5 for 72 h, and cellular extracts were prepared and analyzed by immunoblotting. 
Lamin A/C served to normalize for differences in loading. (E) Real-time qPCR analysis of Tip5 overexpression-induced changes in the nuclear matrix 
association of rDNA. For details about the experimental set-up see Figure 1B and the text. The results of three biological replicates are shown. </p>



<p>experiments showed that (i) all AT-hook domains are 
bona fide DNA-binding elements; (ii) the individual AT-
hooks bound the different sequences with similar affinity; 
(iii) more than one AT-hook molecule bound to one DNA 
molecule in the case of the individual AT-hooks, as 
indicated by the supershifts; (iv) there was only one 
protein-DNA complex in the case of the larger, double 
AT-hook AT1+2 protein. This suggests that in the double 
AT-hook construct, both AT-hooks contact the short, 34-
bp DNA fragments, not leaving space for an additional 
AT-hook to bind this DNA (Figure 3B). To monitor the 
sequence preference of the AT-hook binding, gel retard-
ation assays were performed in parallel using AT-and 
GC-rich sequences. The results showed that the GC-rich 
template was less efficiently bound under identical experi-
mental conditions (Supplementary Figure S4A). </p>

<p>The double AT-hook acts as a nucleolar targeting domain </p>

<p>To continue with the characterization of Tip5's potential 
MAR-binding domains and to determine the MAR binder 
with highest affinity, AT-hook-DNA interactions were 
quantified in microscale thermophoresis experiments. This 
novel method enables the measurement of molecular inter-
actions in solution based on the monitoring of molecular 
movement in a thermal gradient (27). We have measured 
thermally induced kinetics of a fluorescently labeled AT-
rich site from the rDNA incubated with a serial dilution 
of the different AT-hooks. The analysis of the normalized 
thermophoresis curves provided us with the equilibrium 
constant concentration values for each AT-hook, when 
50% of the DNA was bound by the protein (EC50). The </p>

<p>binding constants exhibit clear differences between the in-
dividual AT-hooks, displaying slightly weaker affinities 
than the HMGA1 control. The EC50 value of the double 
AT-hook AT1+2 is higher than the EC50 of the individual 
AT-hooks, suggesting that both domains contact DNA 
simultaneously and reveal a binding affinity similar to 
HMGA1 (Figure 4A). To examine the sequence preference 
of AT-hook binding in a quantitative manner, the Cy5-
labeled AT-rich rDNA sequence was mixed with equimolar 
amounts of a Cy3-labeled GC-rich DNA fragment, and the 
EC50 values were determined for AT2 and AT1+2 in a 
competitive-binding assay. The results reinforced the obser-
vations of the gel retardation experiments in that the AT-
rich sequence was bound with higher affinity 
(Supplementary Figure S4B). 
After identifying the double AT-hook as the strongest 
putative MAR binder, the nuclear matrix association of 
this protein domain was investigated in transient transfec-
tion experiments (Figure 4B-D). A wild-type and a mutant 
version of the double AT-hook domain was fused to GFP 
resulting in the GFP-AT1+2 wt and GFP-AT1+2mut 
constructs. In the latter one, the RGR core motifs of 
both AT-hooks were mutated to the DGD tripeptide that 
was previously shown to loose DNA-binding activity (33). 
First, the sub-cellular localization was analyzed in immuno-
fluorescence experiments, which showed that GFP-
AT1+2 wt predominantly localizes to nucleoli. In 
contrast, GFP-AT1+2mut was evenly distributed in the 
nucleus (Figure 4B). The results clearly demonstrate that 
the first two AT-hooks serve as nucleolar targeting module. 
Surprisingly, nuclear matrix analyses of cellular fractions </p>

<p>Figure 3. DNA-binding features of Tip5's AT-hook domains. (A) Domain structure of Tip5, the large subunit of the NoRC complex. TAM domain; 
ATx, AT-hook; DDT, domain in different transcription and chromosome remodeling factors; PHD, plant homeodomain zinc-finger; bromo, 
bromodomain. The numbers below the scheme indicate amino acids. (B) Gel retardation assays. Lane 1 shows in the upper panel an rDNA 
enhancer (rDNA En) probe, in the middle panel an rDNA intergenic spacer (rDNA IGS) probe and in the lower panel an IFNb promoter 
(IFNb) probe alone. Increasing amounts (18, 36, 72 and 144 pmol) of the different Tip5 AT-hook peptides AT1+2 (lanes 2-5), the negative 
control GST (lanes 6-9), AT1 (lanes 10-13), AT2 (lanes 14-17), AT3 (lanes 18-21), AT4 (lanes 22-25) and the positive control second AT-hook 
of HMGA1 ('HMGA1', lanes 26-29) were analyzed for DNA binding on 1.25 pmol DNA. Different protein-DNA complexes are indicated with 
arrows and labeled with C1 and C2. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 10 5257 </p>

<p>(Figure 4C) and fixed cells (Figure 4D) showed that despite 
the in vitro MAR-binding activity and nucleolar targeting, 
the double AT-hook domain is not sufficient to mediate 
association with the nuclear matrix. </p>

<p>The TAM domain mediates nuclear matrix association 
and nucleolar targeting </p>

<p>To test whether the other putative MAR-binding domain, 
the TAM domain, is required to mediate association 
with the nuclear matrix, the GFP-AT1+2 wt and </p>

<p>GFP-AT1+2mut constructs were extended with this 
domain resulting in the GFP-TAM-AT1+2 wt and 
GFP-TAM-AT1+2mut constructs. Again, the sub-
cellular localization of these two GFP-tagged Tip5 
proteins was analyzed first. Immunofluorescence experi-
ments showed slightly different sub-nuclear distributions 
of the proteins. GFP-TAM-AT1+2mut was predomin-
antly localized in nucleoli, suggesting that the TAM 
domain is sufficient for nucleolar targeting, similar to 
the first two AT-hooks. In contrast, the GFP-TAM-
AT1+2 wt protein was rather enriched in perinucleolar </p>

<p>Figure 4. Analyses of Tip5's AT-hook domains in microscale thermophoresis, immunofluorescence and nuclear matrix isolation experiments. (A) 
Microscale thermophoresis experiments. The scheme of a measurement is shown on the left side. The curves represent individual reactions, in which 
the DNA concentration was kept constant and the AT-hook concentration varied. Thermophoresis was induced by heating the reaction with an 
infrared (IR) laser. Fluorescence intensity changes are plotted as a function of time. C cold and C hot indicate the time points where fluorescence 
measurements were carried out. The curves representing full binding and no binding are labeled in red and blue, respectively, whereas the gray curves 
represent partial binding. For a detailed description of the assay please refer to Baaske et al. (27). The results of the measurements are shown on the 
right side. The indicated amounts of the different Tip5 AT-hook peptides were analyzed for DNA binding at constant, 50 nM concentration of a 
29 bp, Cy5-labeled rDNA IGS oligonucleotide. The amount of bound DNA was plotted against the peptide concentration, and the concentrations 
where half of the oligonucleotide is bound, the EC50 values, were determined. The data points of the plot represent mean ± standard deviation 
values of four measurements. The list of the analyzed AT-hooks is shown below the diagrams. GRP core motifs of the peptides are indicated in red. 
The classification of AT-hooks according to Aravind and Landsman (18) is shown. The numerical EC50 values for each peptide are shown on the 
right side. (B) Immunofluorescence experiments show the sub-nuclear localization of the wild-type and mutated versions of the first two AT-hooks. 
The GFP-tagged proteins were stained with a rabbit polyclonal GFP antibody, the nucleoli with a mouse monoclonal B23 antibody and the nuclear 
DNA with DAPI. Bars indicate 5 mm. (C) Immunoblot and Coomassie gel pictures of nuclear matrix preparations. HEK293 cells were transfected 
with the indicated GFP-Tip5 protein-encoding plasmid DNA for 72 h, and nuclear matrices were prepared. CP, CHR, 2 M and NM indicate 
cytoplasmic, soluble chromatin, high-salt wash and nuclear matrix fractions, respectively. Core histones and lamin A/C served as controls for the 
CHR/2 M and NM fractions, respectively. (D) The double AT-hook domain of Tip5 does not mediate nuclear matrix association. HeLa cells were 
transfected with the indicated GFP-Tip5 protein-encoding plasmid DNA for 48 h; nuclear matrices were prepared in situ and analyzed by 
immunofluorescence. The names of the peptides are shown on the left. Lamin A/C detection served as control for nuclear matrix preparations. 
Bars indicate 5 mm. </p>

<p>5258 Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 10 </p>

<p>chromatin and entered only to lesser extent the nucleolus, 
with higher protein levels detected in the nucleoplasma 
(Figure 5A). Interestingly, nuclear matrix analyses of 
fixed cells (Figure 5B) and cellular fractions (Figure 5C) 
revealed that the TAM domain is necessary and sufficient 
to mediate the association of the GFP-TAM-AT proteins 
with the nuclear matrix. 
Even though the nucleolar matrix targeting domain 
could be assigned to the TAM domain, the sequestering 
of the rDNA to the nuclear matrix fraction requires a 
functional Tip5 molecule. DNA quantification after 
expressing similar levels of the double AT and TAM-AT 
hook constructs did not exhibit an increase of rDNA in 
the matrix, as shown for the Tip5 protein, showing 
that the TAM domain is required for nucleolar matrix 
targeting; however, additional DNA-binding domains in </p>

<p>Tip5 are required for rDNA binding (Supplementary 
Figure S5). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Targeting rRNA genes to the nuclear matrix </p>

<p>rRNA gene repression either by serum starvation or Tip5 
overexpression results in a significant enrichment of 
rDNA in the nuclear matrix. The chromatin remodeling 
complex NoRC is a key factor required for repression of 
the gene by repositioning the promoter bound nucleosome 
and initiates heterochromatin formation by its interaction 
with HDACs and Dnmts (10,12,14). Here, we show that 
NoRC regulates higher-order rDNA chromatin organiza-
tion, in that it is part of the nuclear matrix and induces the </p>

<p>Figure 5. The TAM domain mediates nuclear matrix association and nucleolar targeting. (A) Immunofluorescence experiments show the sub-nuclear 
localization of the TAM domain fused to either wild-type or mutated versions of the first two AT-hooks. The GFP-tagged proteins were stained with 
a rabbit polyclonal GFP antibody, the nucleoli with a mouse monoclonal B23 antibody and the nuclear DNA with DAPI. Bars indicate 5 mm. (B) 
Immunofluorescence detection of the association of Tip5 proteins with the nuclear matrix. HeLa cells were transfected with GFP or the indicated 
GFP-Tip5 protein-encoding plasmid DNA for 48 h; nuclear matrices were prepared in situ and analyzed by immunofluorescence. The names of the 
peptides are shown on the left. Lamin A/C served as control for nuclear matrix preparations. Bars indicate 5 mm. (C) Immunoblot and Coomassie gel 
pictures of nuclear matrix preparations. HEK293 cells were transfected with GFP or the indicated GFP-Tip5 protein-encoding plasmid DNA for 
72 h, and nuclear matrices were prepared. CP, CHR, 2 M and NM indicate cytoplasmic, soluble chromatin, high-salt wash and nuclear matrix 
fractions, respectively. Core histones and lamin A/C served as controls for the CHR/2 M and NM fractions, respectively. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 10 5259 </p>

<p>recruitment of rDNA to the matrix. Our results suggest 
that in addition to its well-defined role in regulating local 
chromatin structures at the rDNA promoter, NoRC is 
involved also in large-scale chromatin domain organiza-
tion of the rDNA locus. 
The association of mammalian rDNA with the nuclear 
matrix was shown earlier by several independent labora-
tories. Genome-scale biochemical (8) and cell biology ex-
periments (9) unambiguously demonstrated the specific 
enrichment of rDNA in the nuclear matrix. However, 
neither the transcriptional activity of the nuclear matrix-
associated rDNA nor the sequences within the rDNA 
repeat unit, which mediate the association with the 
nuclear matrix, were identified in these studies. 
Regarding these questions, seemingly contradictory 
models were proposed: Keppel suggested that the entire 
rDNA repeat unit is associated with the nuclear matrix 
(34), whereas others found that the coding sequence 
itself (35) or non-transcribed regions flanking the 47S 
rRNA coding sequence are predominantly enriched in 
the nuclear or nucleolar matrix (36-38). With regard to 
the transcriptional activity of nuclear matrix-associated 
DNA, it was suggested on one side that active rDNA is 
associated with the nuclear matrix (34,36), and on the 
other side that the nuclear matrix contains transcription-
ally inactive rDNA (38), which could also represent se-
quences that are being replicated (39). These 
discrepancies can be explained largely by differently used 
terminology and differences in the experimental proced-
ures. The nuclear matrix (6), nuclear scaffold (40) and 
nuclear skeleton (41) are operational definitions, which 
are based on biochemical fractionation approaches. The 
experimental procedures include different endonuclease 
digestions followed by high-salt or low-salt extractions, 
or the fractionation is carried out at physiological salt 
concentration. Remarkably, the concentration of DNase 
I and the incubation time of the endonuclease digestion 
vary frequently between the protocols of different 
laboratories, which may affect the observed association 
of the rDNA with the nuclear matrix as shown in an 
initial study (8). The addition of nucleolus isolation 
steps to the nuclear matrix isolation procedure in particu-
lar studies (37,38) further complicates the comparability of 
the published data about the nuclear matrix association of 
rDNA. Here, we prepared the nuclear matrix by applying 
extensive DNase I digestion and high-salt extractions es-
sentially as described in former publications (6,23,24) and 
named the last insoluble fraction as nuclear matrix, ac-
cording to the nomenclature of the initial publication 
(6). It is important to note here that this nuclear matrix 
does not represent an identifiable sub-nuclear structure 
(42,43). However, its protein content largely overlaps 
with that of the nucleoskeleton, a well-defined, intermedi-
ate filament-based protein network of the nucleus (44). 
Moreover, the DNA content of the nuclear matrix repre-
sents a fraction of the genome, which is resistant to exten-
sive DNase I digestion, and specific sequences that are 
enriched in this fraction possess gene regulatory functions 
(7,45). As active, open chromatin structures are highly 
accessible to nucleases (46) and active rDNA is 
largely nucleosome-depleted (47), we suppose that </p>

<p>predominantly inactive rDNA repeats are associated 
with the nuclear matrix. Our results suggest that the 
entire rDNA repeat can be associated with the nuclear 
matrix. The relatively moderate effects on the rDNA 
IGS MAR indicate that this region was probably 
associated with the nuclear matrix already before the 
serum starvation; thus, it could represent a nucleation 
site for the association. </p>

<p>Tip5 is a nuclear matrix-associated protein and targets 
rDNA to the nuclear matrix </p>

<p>In addition to DNase I inaccessible genomic regions, the 
nuclear matrix consists of various proteins and RNA mol-
ecules. In this study, we demonstrated that the large pro-
portion of the protein resides in the nuclear matrix 
fraction, and thus identified Tip5 as a nuclear matrix-
associated protein. Next, the role of RNA in mediating 
the association of Tip5 with chromatin was investigated in 
the nuclear matrix assay. The finding that chromatin-
associated Tip5 was sensitive to RNaseA treatment 
suggests co-existence of two functionally different Tip5 
populations in the cell. It is tempting to speculate 
whether the binding of Tip5 to this mobile chromatin 
fraction is mediated by the regulatory pRNA, which is 
transcribed from the rDNA promoter (22), and/or by 
other RNA species. Tip5, the large, regulatory subunit 
of the NoRC complex, is a key regulator of rDNA repres-
sion (1). Our data on Tip5-dependent nuclear matrix tar-
geting of rDNA indicate that besides its other functions, 
Tip5 also regulates the DNase I accessibility of rDNA in 
the nucleus, i.e. nucleolar topology. To our surprise, not 
only the IGS MAR, but also the Tip5-binding site at the 
promoter, further a 28S rRNA coding region, where no 
Tip5 binding occurs, were enriched in the nuclear matrix 
fraction after overexpression of Tip5. This suggests that in 
addition to a possible direct nuclear matrix targeting, 
NoRC-mediated silencing also augments the association 
of rDNA with the nuclear matrix. We propose a model in 
which Tip5 plays a key role in recruiting the rDNA to the 
nuclear matrix and NoRC-mediated heterochromatin for-
mation and chromatin compaction leads to limited DNase 
I accessibility and the accumulation of large rDNA chro-
matin domains in the nuclear matrix. Taken together, our 
results provide insights into the activity-dependent large-
scale organization of nucleolar rDNA chromatin and 
reveal a novel function of Tip5 in this process. </p>

<p>A role for TAM and AT-hook domains in nucleolar 
targeting and association of Tip5 with the nuclear matrix </p>

<p>Tip5 contains the TAM domain and four minor groove 
binder AT-hooks, which are supposed to bind MARs and 
mediate nuclear matrix association (18). To identify Tip5's 
protein domain, which shows the highest affinity to a 
MAR and could thus mediate association with the 
nuclear matrix, the DNA-binding features of the AT-
hooks were investigated in gel retardation and microscale 
thermophoresis experiments. It was already shown that 
the TAM domain binds considerably less efficiently to 
DNA than the AT-hooks (15). Similar DNA-binding </p>



<p>affinities were detected for three AT-hooks, whereas one 
of them bound less efficiently to all three DNA fragments 
tested. In summary, the comparison of experimentally 
observed DNA-binding activities of the AT-hooks 
showed the following order: AT1 &lt; AT2 &amp; AT3 &amp; AT4 
&lt; HMGA1 in contrast to the expected AT1 &amp; AT3 &lt; 
AT2 &lt; AT4 &amp; HMGA1, which is based on the classifica-
tion described previously (18). Quantification of the 
DNA-binding efficiencies also revealed that the combin-
ation of the first two AT-hooks bound most efficiently to 
DNA. Thus, this double AT-hook domain along with its 
mutant was tested for nuclear matrix-binding activity. To 
our surprise, the result was negative and, therefore, this 
domain and its mutant were extended with the TAM 
domain and tested again for nuclear matrix-binding 
activity. The results revealed that the TAM domain is a 
nuclear matrix targeting domain, which is in agreement 
with its proposed role (18). In addition, both the TAM 
domain and the double AT-hook domain of Tip5 were 
identified as nucleolar targeting sequences. Finally, the 
targeting of rDNA to the nuclear matrix by these Tip5 
domains was investigated, where we could not detect sig-
nificant changes in the matrix association of rDNA on 
overexpression of the different proteins. This result indi-
cates that additional parts of Tip5 are required for the 
specific enrichment of rDNA in the nuclear matrix. We 
speculate that overexpression of these domains could 
result in genome-wide MAR binding, which prevents de-
tectable rDNA-specific targeting effects. In contrast, 
overexpression of the full-length Tip5 clearly showed 
such an effect. In summary, our findings suggest a dual 
role for Tip5's double AT-hook and TAM domain, tar-
geting the nucleolus and anchoring to the nuclear matrix, 
and a function for Tip5 in regulating large-scale rDNA 
chromatin organization. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online: 
Supplementary Figures 1-5. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank Alexander Brehm and Ingrid 
Grummt for antibodies against Mi-2, Brg1 and RPA116 
and Katharina Filarsky and Philipp Baaske for technical 
help. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft [SFB960]; Bayerische 
Genomforschungsnetzwerk [BayGene] (to G.L.); Elite 
Network of Bavaria (to K.Z.). Funding for open access 
charge: German Research Foundation (DFG) within the 
funding programme Open Access Publishing. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>5262 Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, No. 10 </p>

</text></tei>