<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3010901" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs type="software">Spectrum</rs><rs type="software">EPP</rs><rs type="software">EPP</rs><rs corresp="#software-15" type="version-date">2009</rs><rs id="software-15" type="software">EPP</rs><rs type="software">EPP</rs><rs type="software">EPP</rs><rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-date">2009</rs><rs id="software-5" type="software">EPP</rs><rs type="software">Spectrum</rs>described, together with the estimation methods for the number 
of adults and children that are in need of ART. 8 </p>

<p>TRENDS IN THE HIV PANDEMIC </p>

<p>The quality of serosurveillance in low-and middle-income 
countries is described in an updated assessment building on 
similar exercises. 9 Broadly, the quality of serosurveillance has 
remained constant with an increased number of antenatal clinic 
sites and nationally representative population samples, but with 
an increase in the number of countries with poorly functioning 
surveillance. 
A paper from Jamaica explains how the <rs corresp="#software-11" type="version-date">2009</rs> versions of the 
<rs type="software">EPP</rs> and <rs id="software-11" type="software">Spectrum</rs> tools have been applied in Jamaica, together 
with the country-specific data and assumptions, to assess the 
course of the epidemic and to set programme targets. 10 
Analytical papers based on new estimates explore various 
topics. A paper on the prevention of mother-to-child trans-
mission (PMTCT) quantifies the effect of epidemic trends and 
PMTCT programmes on the annual number of new child 
infections. 11 In addition, the paper explores which efforts are 
needed to virtually eliminate new child infections through 
mother-to-child transmission by 2015. An updated analysis of 
the contribution of HIV to under-five mortality shows 
a decrease in recent years. 12 The effect of changing global 
guidelines of the starting criteria for the initiation of ART on the 
number of people estimated to be eligible for ART is assessed. 13 
A second paper, focused on ART, estimates the impact of ART on 
mortality and estimates how many life-years have been gained 
through ARTamong adults. 14 A final analytical paper uses recent 
biological and behavioural surveillance data from young people 
aged 15e24 years in the most affected countries to assess trends 
in HIV prevalence and sexual behaviour. The analysis shows 
that, among the countries with sufficient data for the analysis, 
in 10 countries there is evidence of significant declines in HIV 
prevalence of at least 25% since 2000, while an additional six 
countries have non-significant declining trends, and another five 
do not show declining trends. 15 </p>

<p>FUTURE DEVELOPMENTS </p>

<p>Looking towards the future, we expect several new develop-
ments in estimation tools. First, it is desirable that <rs type="software">EPP</rs> and 
<rs type="software">Spectrum</rs> be integrated, thereby allowing streamlining of the 
handling of demographic and ART data, and in doing so avoiding 
errors. Second, a more flexible epidemic model should be 
included in <rs type="software">EPP</rs> to improve on the current phi-shift feature, 
building on the proposals by Hogan 16 and Bao. 17 Many countries 
now have seen a decline in prevalence and these would be 
expected to show an increase in prevalence in future years as 
a result of either increased survival due to ART of a large 
proportion of all people living with HIV or of increased trans-
mission, or both. Third, with ART programmes expanding and 
maturing, improvements in modelling epidemics should be 
expected from the tracking of HIV-infected individuals by their 
CD4 level. Fourth, for mother-to-child transmission, the new 
WHO guidelines should be incorporated in <rs type="software">Spectrum</rs>. 
While <rs type="software">EPP</rs> and <rs type="software">Spectrum</rs> work well for countries where 
survey-derived data constitute the bulk of the surveillance data, 
they are not well adapted for countries that rely mostly on HIV 
and AIDS case reporting for HIV surveillance. Many European 
countries rely on such data and a new initiative coordinated by 
the European Centre for Disease Control hopes to develop 
estimation tools appropriate in such settings. </p>

<p>In conclusion, the 2009 estimation tools described in this 
supplement contain several important improvements over 
previous versions. The resulting estimates have already allowed 
several insightful multicountry and global analyses. We trust 
that these estimates also serve programme planners, scientists, 
policy makers and the wider public. We are committed to 
continue to improve estimation methods and assumptions in 
future years as the epidemics and the data availability continue 
to evolve, and to communicate these changes in a transparent 
way. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; not externally peer reviewed. </p>



<p> 
Sex Transm Infect 2010;86(Suppl 2):ii1eii2. doi:10.1136/sti.2010.047852 </p>

<p>Supplement </p>

</text></tei>