<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3425424" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The developmental origins hypothesis proposes that undernutrition 
during early development is associated with an increased type 2 
diabetes risk in adulthood. We investigated the association between 
undernutrition during childhood and young adulthood and type 2 
diabetes in adulthood. We studied 7,837 women from Prospect-
EPIC (European Prospective Investigation Into Cancer and Nutri-
tion) who were exposed to the 1944-1945 Dutch famine when they 
were between age 0 and 21 years. We used Cox proportional haz-
ards regression models to explore the effect of famine on the risk of 
subsequent type 2 diabetes in adulthood. We adjusted for potential 
confounders, including age at famine exposure, smoking, and level 
of education. Self-reported famine exposure during childhood and 
young adulthood was associated with an increased type 2 diabetes 
risk in a dose-dependent manner. In those who reported moderate 
famine exposure, the age-adjusted type 2 diabetes hazard ratio 
(HR) was 1.36 (95% CI [1.09-1.70]); in those who reported severe 
famine exposure, the age-adjusted HR was 1.64 (1.26-2.14) relative 
to unexposed women. These effects did not change after adjust-
ment for confounders. This study provides the first direct evi-
dence, using individual famine exposure data, that a short period 
of moderate or severe undernutrition during postnatal develop-
ment increases type 2 diabetes risk in adulthood. Diabetes 
countries. The rationale and design of both EPIC and Prospect-EPIC have been 
described in detail elsewhere (18,19). In brief, women residing in Utrecht or its 
surroundings were recruited between 1993 and 1997 through a breast cancer 
screening program. All participants signed informed consent before study in-
clusion. The study complies with the Declaration of Helsinki and was approved 
by the institutional review board of the University Medical Center Utrecht. 
At enrollment, participants were asked to fill in two questionnaires: a general 
questionnaire to gather information on demographic and lifestyle factors and 
past and current morbidity and an extensive food frequency questionnaire to 
determine regular dietary intake in the year prior to enrollment. All participants 
underwent physical examination. Trained assistants measured height, weight, 
waist and hip circumference, and systolic and diastolic blood pressure and 
checked the questionnaires for missing information. 
Famine exposure 
The Dutch famine. The Dutch famine was an ;6-month period of severe 
starvation occurring in the urban western part of the Netherlands at the end of 
World War II. The famine evolved from a number of cascading events. While 
the southern part of the Netherlands was already liberated by the Allied 
forces, liberation of the northern part came to a halt when the attack to 
capture the Rhine bridge at Arnhem (Operation Market Garden) failed. To 
support the Allied offensive, the Dutch government in exile arranged a strike 
of the national railways to thwart German transport of troops and ammunition. 
As a reprisal, the German occupier put an embargo on all food transports. At 
the height of the famine, from December 1944 to April 1945, the official daily 
rations varied between 400 and 800 kcal (20). The relative amount of proteins, 
fats, and carbohydrates remained essentially unchanged during this period 
(21). After ;6 months of starvation, the Netherlands was liberated, which 
ended the famine abruptly. 
Famine exposure assessment. The self-administered general questionnaire 
that had been completed at enrolment contained questions about place of 
residence and experiences of hunger and weight loss during the 1944-1945 
Dutch famine. Women could respond to these last two questions using one of 
three answer categories: "hardly," "little," or "very much." Women who had 
answered "not applicable" or "I don't know" to one or both famine questions 
were excluded from the analysis. We combined the answers into a three-point 
subjective hunger score: women who reported having been very much ex-
posed to both hunger and weight loss were categorized as "severely exposed"; 
women who reported having been hardly exposed to either hunger or weight 
loss were categorized as "unexposed"; and all others were categorized as 
"moderately exposed." Where we use the terms severely exposed, moderately 
exposed, and unexposed, we mean self-reported exposure to famine. With 
these individual self-reports of famine exposure, we believe to have captured 
real undernutrition as the determinant of later life outcome. However, as with 
all retrospective studies on wartime famine exposure, we cannot exclude that 
these measures are proxies of other phenomena, such as psychological stress. 
Exposure age categories. Age at famine exposure was assessed taking 1 
October 1944, the start of the famine, as reference. Exposure age was classified 
into three categories: childhood (age 0-9 years), adolescence (age 10-17 
years), and young adulthood (age $18 years), according to the seven stages in 
the postnatal human life cycle as defined by Bogin (22). We defined pre-
adolescent childhood, a period of rapid growth with many developmental 
milestones in physiology, behavior, and cognition, as the period between age 
0 and 9 years, just before the growth spurt in women (22,23). From the start of 
the growth spurt, at approximately age 10 years, through age 17 was called 
adolescence (22,23); this period is characterized by the growth spurt, in-
cluding sexual development (22,23). From 18 years of age, we considered 
persons as young adults gradually reaching homeostasis in physiology. 
Subject selection. For the present analysis, we excluded women born after 
the famine (n = 2,559) and those who resided outside occupied Netherlands 
during the famine (n = 1,732). For 8,091 of the remaining 13,066 women, the 
hunger score could be calculated (62%). Women not permitting data retrieval 
from the municipal administration registries, the National Medical Registry, or 
Statistics Netherlands (n = 246) and women who had been diagnosed with 
type 1 diabetes (n = 8) were also excluded, which left 7,837 women for our 
analyses. Data were complete for 7,557 women (96%). 
Outcome assessment. The process of ascertainment and verification of the 
type 2 diabetic case subjects has been described in detail elsewhere (24). In 
short, type 2 diabetic case subjects were ascertained retrospectively by means 
of self-report at baseline and prospectively in three ways: by means of 1) two 
follow-up questionnaires with 3-to-5 year intervals; 2) a urinary glucose strip 
test, sent out with the first follow-up questionnaire, for detection of glucosuria; 
and 3) linkage with the standardized computerized register of hospital dis-
charge diagnosis from the National Medical Registry. Follow-up was complete 
on 1 January 2006. 
All potential type 2 diabetic case subjects ascertained by any of these methods 
were verified by information from either the participant's general practitioner 
(GP) or the participant's pharmacist through mailed questionnaires. We classified </p>

<p>participants as type 2 diabetic case subjects if 1) the GP or pharmacist confirmed 
the diagnosis of type 2 diabetes in this ascertained participant or 2) information 
from both the GP and pharmacist was absent but two or more ascertainment 
sources indicated that the participant had been diagnosed with type 2 diabetes. 
Data analysis. First, we tabulated characteristics at enrollment, including 
demographics, anthropometry, and lifestyle, against severity of famine expo-
sure to identify potential confounders. We used Cox proportional hazards 
regression models to explore the effect of famine exposure on the risk of type 2 
diabetes. Follow-up time was defined as the time from date of birth to type 2 
diabetes diagnosis or censoring. The time to type 2 diabetes was considered 
censored at the date of death, the date of loss to follow-up, or 1 January 2006, 
whichever came first. 
We used trend tests to explore dose-response relations by introducing the 
hunger score as an ordinal variable (1 for unexposed, 2 for moderately exposed, 
and 3 for severely exposed). First we analyzed the association between famine 
exposure and type 2 diabetes adjusted for age at start of the famine (years). In 
the first model, we additionally adjusted for potential confounders, including 
smoking (pack years) and education (low/intermediate/high; socioeconomic 
status proxy). In subsequent models, we additionally included waist circum-
ference (cm), waist-to-hip ratio (WHR), and BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) separately, since 
visceral adiposity is a risk factor for type 2 diabetes. To assess sensitive 
growth periods during female development in which undernutrition has the 
largest effect on later type 2 diabetes risk, we tested for interaction by in-
troducing the cross products of famine exposure and age at famine exposure 
into the model. We evaluated the proportionality of the hazards over time with 
log-minus-log plots. Results are reported as hazard ratios (HRs) with 95% CIs. 
Continuous variables were introduced as such in the different models; for 
categorical variables, we created indicator variables. We performed all sta-
tistical analyses with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 17.0</rs> (SPSS, Chicago, IL). P values were 
based on two-sided tests with a cutoff level for statistical significance of 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>At the end of follow-up on 1 January 2006, 7,284 (93%) 
women were still alive, 497 (6%) had died, and 56 (1%) were 
lost to follow-up. In total, 407 (5%) women had been di-
agnosed with type 2 diabetes (543,019 observation-years). 
Table 1 shows baseline characteristics of the study group at 
recruitment. Of the total of 7,837 women, 3,572 (46%) re-
ported no exposure, 2,975 (38%) reported moderate expo-
sure, and 1,290 (16%) reported severe exposure to famine. 
On average, severely famine-exposed women were older at 
the time of the famine, had a higher BMI and waist cir-
cumference, and smoked more than unexposed women. 
Figure 1 shows the relation between famine exposure 
and subsequent type 2 diabetes risk, adjusted for age at 
start of the famine and additionally adjusted for the poten-
tial confounders smoking and education (as a proxy for 
socioeconomic status). Of the total of 407 women who had 
been diagnosed with type 2 diabetes, 144 reported to be 
unexposed to famine, 172 reported to be moderately famine 
exposed, and 91 reported to be severely famine exposed. 
In moderately famine-exposed women, the age-adjusted 
type 2 diabetes HR was 1.36 (95% CI 1.09-1.70), significantly 
higher than in unexposed women. In severely famine-exposed 
women, the age-adjusted type 2 diabetes HR was 1.64 
(1.26-2.14), also significantly higher compared with un-
exposed women (P for trend , 0.001). After additional 
adjustment for the potential confounders, these HRs were 
1.33 (1.06-1.67) and 1.51 (1.16-1.98), respectively. In addi-
tion, including waist circumference, WHR, or BMI slightly 
attenuated the risk estimates (all P for trend , 0.05) 
(Table 2). Additional adjustment for family history of di-
abetes, energy intake, or physical exercise separately did 
not affect the results. Adjustment for all these variables 
together (age at start of the famine, smoking, education, 
waist circumference, WHR, BMI, family history of diabetes, 
energy intake, and physical exercise) still showed a statis-
tical significantly increased, albeit attenuated, risk of type 2 
diabetes (moderate exposure HR 1.21 [0.95-1.54]; severe 
exposure HR 1.35 [1.01-1.81]). Analyzing the data by </p>

<p>FAMINE EXPOSURE AND RISK OF TYPE 2 DIABETES </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, SEPTEMBER 2012 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>choosing the date of enrollment in the study as the be-
ginning of follow-up and excluding the type 2 diabetic case 
subjects who had been diagnosed before enrollment did 
not change the risk estimates (data not shown). Also, ex-
clusion of 134 women who had been partly prenatally and 
partly postnatally exposed to famine did not change our 
results (data not shown). </p>

<p>There was no statistically significant interaction between 
the effects of famine exposure and age at start of the famine 
(P for interaction = 0.50). Table 3 shows the relation be-
tween famine exposure and subsequent type 2 diabetes risk 
within the exposure age categories, adjusted for age at start 
of the famine and additionally adjusted for the potential 
confounders, including smoking and education (as a proxy 
for socioeconomic status). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This study demonstrates for the first time, by using in-
dividual famine exposure data, that a short period of severe 
undernutrition during childhood or young adolescence is 
associated with an increased risk of type 2 diabetes in adult 
life, in a dose-dependent manner. 
Before further discussion, some aspects of our study re-
quire consideration. The Dutch famine of 1944-1945 is a 
"natural experiment" in history, which gave us the unique 
possibility to study the long-term effects of acute under-
nutrition during childhood and young adulthood in other-
wise well-nourished girls and women. A strength of our 
study is the fact that we verified the ascertained type 2 di-
abetic case subjects through medical information from GP 
or pharmacy records (24), minimizing the presence of false-
positive cases of type 2 diabetes and, hence, reducing di-
lution of associations. On the other hand, the presence of 
diabetes often goes undetected and may be preclinical up to 
9 to 12 years (25). Individuals with undetected diabetes may 
have been misclassified as nondiabetic individuals, resulting 
in attenuated associations. 
The approximate cumulative incidence of type 2 diabetes 
in our study population was 40 per 1,000 women among 
those who reported to be unexposed to famine and 52 per </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Baseline characteristics of the Prospect-EPIC study population according to self-reported level of famine exposure (none, moderate, 
or severe) </p>

<p>Self-reported level of famine exposure 
None 
Moderate 
Severe </p>

<p>n (%) 
3,572 (46) 
2,975 (38) 
1,290 (16) 
General characteristics, median (range) 
Age at start of the famine (years) 
8.3 (0-21) 
9.5 (0-21) 
10.1 (0-21) 
Age at recruitment (years) 
59.0 (49-70) 
60.4 (49-70) 
60.8 (49-70) 
Body size, mean (SD) 
Height (cm) 
164.5 (5.9) 
164.1 (6.0) 
163.8 (6.2) 
Weight (kg) 
70.3 (11.1) 
70.8 (11.5) 
70.7 (11.9) 
BMI (kg/m 
2 ) 
26.0 (4.0) 
26.3 (4.1) 
26.4 (4.2) 
Waist (cm) 
83.7 (9.8) 
84.7 (10.0) 
85.0 (10.5) 
Hip (cm) 
105.9 (8.2) 
106.1 (8.5) 
105.9 (8.6) 
WHR 
0.79 (0.06) 
0.80 (0.06) 
0.80 (0.06) 
Lifestyle 
Level of education, n (%) 
Low 
1,797 (50) 
1,359 (46) 
651 (50) 
Intermediate 
1,293 (36) 
1,151 (39) 
486 (38) 
High 
477 (13) 
463 (16) 
153 (12) 
Smoking (pack years), mean (SD) 
5.6 (9.2) 
6.7 (10.1) 
8.0 (11.0) 
Smoking, n (%) 
Ever (current or past) 
1,822 (51) 
1,648 (56) 
755 (59) 
Never 
1,745 (49) 
1,318 (44) 
526 (41) 
Energy intake (kcal), mean (SD) 
1,791 (430) 
1,777 (418) 
1,743 (447) 
Family history of diabetes, n (%) 
Father 
261 (7) 
230 (8) 
113 (9) 
Mother 
535 (15) 
483 (16) 
212 (16) 
Both parents 
41 (1) 
54 (2) 
15 (1) </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Self-reported famine exposure and the risk of type 2 diabetes. 
Results are adjusted HRs with 95% CIs for women who reported to be 
moderately or severely exposed to famine compared with those who 
reported to be unexposed to famine. •, model adjusted for age at start 
of the famine; □, multivariable model 1 (adjusted for the potential 
confounders age at start of the famine, smoking, and education [as 
a proxy for socioeconomic status]). </p>

<p>A.F.M. VAN ABEELEN AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, SEPTEMBER 2012 </p>

<p>
1,000 women in the total cohort. Although there may be 
cohort effects, this corresponds closely to an estimate from 
general practices in the Netherlands, showing an incidence 
in 2007 of 41 per 1,000 women of all ages (26). 
In this study, we used individual self-reported data on 
famine exposure instead of classifying populations accord-
ing to place of residence or time (15,16), aiming at obtaining 
more precise exposure assessment. The drawback of in-
dividual self-reported data may be its subjective nature. 
However, our exposure classification data agree with ra-
tioning practices at that time. The allocated individual 
amount of calories was based on age, with young children 
being relatively protected; children between age 1 and 3 
years received ;50% of the distributed amount of calories 
at the start of the famine, whereas those age .18 years 
received ;25% (20). Furthermore, children were relatively 
protected within families and by special committees, such 
as the Interchurch Organization (20,27). Our data reflect 
these historical facts, showing that the older women were at 
the start of the famine, the higher the proportion that 
reported to have been exposed to famine. Furthermore, the 
famine was worst in large cities in the western part of the 
Netherlands, which is also reflected in our data. The per-
centage of women who reported to be severely exposed to 
the famine was 12% in the western part of the Netherlands, 
whereas it was 4% in the eastern part of the Netherlands. 
This may be considered in support of the quality of our </p>

<p>exposure data. Nevertheless, our individual self-reported 
famine score is still susceptible to misclassification since it 
was based on recollection. This may be true especially for 
the youngest age-group, although it is conceivable that these 
women have learned about their famine experiences from 
their parents and family. Nevertheless, if recall in the 
youngest age-group during the famine is not as good as in 
the older age-group of women, this would lead to larger 
exposure misclassification in that age-group. This mis-
classification is, however, unlikely to be related to the 
outcome in our study and would therefore lead to an 
underestimation of the true relation. 
We studied only women recruited through a breast can-
cer screening program. Since there is a rising body of evi-
dence showing sex-specific differences in programming, the 
generalizability of these results to men is unknown (28). 
We found a significant dose-dependent increased risk of 
type 2 diabetes in adult life among women who reported 
to be moderately and severely famine exposed compared 
with women who reported to be unexposed. Important risk 
factors for type 2 diabetes, including age at enrollment in 
the study and smoking, were higher among severely famine-
exposed women compared with unexposed women. Ad-
justment for such risk factors yielded slightly attenuated 
risk estimates. Including possible intermediate variables 
linking childhood undernutrition to later type 2 diabetes in 
the models, such as BMI, waist circumference, and WHR, </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
Self-reported exposure to famine and risk of type 2 diabetes in later life: Cox regression analysis </p>

<p>Level of self-reported famine exposure 
Case subject (n) </p>

<p>Multivariable 
model 2* </p>

<p>Multivariable 
model 3 † </p>

<p>Multivariable 
model 4 ‡ 
HR 
95% CI 
HR 
95% CI 
HR 
95% CI </p>

<p>Unexposed 
144 
1.00 
Reference 
1.00 
Reference 
1.00 
Reference 
Moderately exposed 
172 
1.25 
1.00-1.57 
1.21 
0.96-1.52 
1.28 
1.02-1.60 
Severely exposed 
91 
1.47 
1.12-1.93 
1.37 
1.05-1.80 
1.52 
1.16-1.99 </p>

<p>Adjusted HRs and 95% CIs for the risk of type 2 diabetes for women who reported to be moderately or severely exposed to famine compared 
with those who reported to be unexposed to famine. Multivariable model 1 is displayed in Fig. 1. *Adjusted for age at start of the famine 
(1 October 1944), smoking (pack years), education (low/intermediate/high), and waist circumference (cm). P for trend 0.004.  †Adjusted for 
age at start of the famine (1 October 1944), smoking (pack years), education (low/intermediate/high), and WHR. P for trend 0.02.  ‡Adjusted for 
age at start of the famine (1 October 1944), smoking (pack years), education (low/intermediate/high), and BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). P for trend 0.002. </p>

<p>TABLE 3 
Self-reported exposure to famine and risk of type 2 diabetes in later life: Cox regression analysis </p>

<p>Age at self-reported 
famine categories </p>

<p>Age at recruitment 
(years), mean (SD) </p>

<p>Case 
subject (n) </p>

<p>Model adjusted for age at start 
of the famine 
Multivariable model 1 
HR 
95% CI 
P for trend 
HR 
95% CI 
P for trend </p>

<p>0-9 years 
0.001 
0.01 
Unexposed 
55.2 (3.2) 
58 
1.00 
Reference 
1.00 
Reference 
Moderately exposed 
55.4 (3.2) 
56 
1.25 
0.86-1.80 
1.20 
0.83-1.74 
Severely exposed 
55.8 (3.3) 
39 
2.06 
1.37-3.10 
1.72 
1.13-2.62 
10-17 years 
0.04 
0.04 
Unexposed 
64.5 (2.5) 
75 
1.00 
Reference 
1.00 
Reference 
Moderately exposed 
64.7 (2.5) 
94 
1.37 
1.01-1.86 
1.39 
1.02-1.90 
Severely exposed 
64.2 (2.5) 
45 
1.41 
0.97-2.04 
1.40 
0.96-2.04 
$18 years 
0.33 
0.54 
Unexposed 
68.8 (0.7) 
11 
1.00 
Reference 
1.00 
Reference 
Moderately exposed 
69.0 (0.5) 
22 
1.72 
0.83-3.56 
1.57 
0.74-3.33 
Severely exposed 
69.0 (0.6) 
7 
1.42 
0.55-3.67 
1.25 
0.47-3.33 </p>

<p>Adjusted HRs and 95% CIs for the risk of type 2 diabetes for women within each of the exposure age categories who reported to be moderately 
or severely exposed to famine compared with those who reported to be unexposed to famine. Multivariable model 1: adjusted for age at start 
of the famine (1 October 1944), smoking (pack years), and education (low/intermediate/high). </p>

<p>FAMINE EXPOSURE AND RISK OF TYPE 2 DIABETES </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, SEPTEMBER 2012 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>also yielded slightly lower risk estimates. Because body 
size does play a causal role in type 2 diabetes occurrence, 
the increased type 2 diabetes risk among famine-exposed 
women seems to be partly explained by effects on BMI, 
waist circumference, or WHR. Furthermore, the baseline 
data of our cohort show that famine exposure may be re-
lated to increased body fatness and waist circumference, 
and the attenuation, albeit small, of the type 2 diabetes risk 
estimates after adjustment for BMI, waist circumference, 
or WHR that we report here corroborates that observation. 
We could not demonstrate a statistically significant inter-
action between the effects of age at start of the famine and 
famine exposure. However, analyzing the effects of famine 
exposure on the risk of type 2 diabetes in the three expo-
sure age categories revealed a statistically significant dose-
response relationship within the exposure age categories of 
0-9 and 10-17 years, while there was no significant dose-
response relation in the $18-year exposure age category. 
However, the risk of type 2 diabetes was also higher among 
famine-exposed women in the $18-year exposure age cat-
egory, although not statistically significant. Nevertheless, 
the number of case subjects in the $18-year exposure age 
category was very small. Therefore, further research is 
needed to confirm these findings. 
We were not able to distinguish the effects of under-
nutrition from war-and famine-related stress because we 
do not have information about the experience of stress dur-
ing the famine. A Finnish study reports higher hypothalamic-
pituitary-adrenocortical axis reactivity to a psychosocial 
stress test in childhood war evacuees (29). This study also 
shows that experiences of wartime evacuation during 
childhood were associated with a 1.4-fold increased risk of 
a later type 2 diabetes diagnosis (30). The authors suggested 
that early life stress may influence hypothalamic-pituitary-
adrenocortical axis function, which in turn can modulate 
inflammation processes in adulthood, thereby increasing 
the risk of type 2 diabetes in adult life (30). 
Many studies show an association between lower birth 
weight, as a marker of prenatal undernutrition, and in-
creased insulin resistance, higher fasting insulin concen-
trations, and increased incidence of type 2 diabetes in adult 
life (31). More recent studies show that not only body size 
at birth but also early postnatal growth rates affect the risk 
of type 2 diabetes in adult life (11-13,32,33). Those who 
were most likely to develop type 2 diabetes in adult life had 
low weight at birth and underwent rapid postnatal weight 
gain (11-13,32,33). The current study agrees with and adds 
to the existing literature that shows that undernutrition 
during childhood is associated with an increased risk of 
type 2 diabetes in adult life (15,16). In these previous 
studies, famine exposure was defined by classifying pop-
ulations according to place of residence. In contrast, our 
study relies on individual self-reported hunger scores to 
define the severity of famine exposure. 
Relevance. Our findings support the idea that moderate or 
severe undernutrition may program glucose-insulin me-
tabolism, resulting in an increased risk of type 2 diabetes 
in adult life. Famine and undernutrition are still a major 
problem worldwide; the first of the Millennium Development 
Goals is to eradicate extreme hunger (34). Moreover, since 
the formulation of the Millennium Development Goals, the 
number of hungry people worldwide has increased (35). 
Never before in history has the number of people suffering 
from hunger been larger: one in every six human beings 
suffers from undernutrition, and every 4 s, someone dies 
of the consequences of hunger (35). Since the incidence of </p>

<p>chronic diseases, including cardiovascular disease and type 
2 diabetes, is rising in many parts of the world (36), further 
research into the long-term health effects of undernutrition 
is warranted. 
Conclusions. This study provides the first direct evidence, 
using individual self-reported famine exposure data, that 
a short period of moderate or severe undernutrition during 
postnatal development increases the risk of type 2 di-
abetes in adult life. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The Prospect-EPIC study was supported by the Europe 
Against Cancer Program of the European Commission, the 
Dutch Ministry of Health, the Dutch Cancer Society, 
ZonMw, the Netherlands Organization for Health Research 
and Development, and the World Cancer Research Fund. 
No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article 
were reported. 
The funders played no role in the design and conduct of the 
study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of 
data; or preparation, review, and approval of the manuscript. 
A.F.M.v.A. performed statistical analysis, analyzed and 
interpreted data, and wrote the manuscript. S.G.E., P.M.M.B., 
T.J.R., and C.S.P.M.U. analyzed and interpreted data, super-
vised the study, and critically revised the manuscript for 
important intellectual content. D.E.G. contributed to study 
concept and design, obtained funding, analyzed and inter-
preted data, supervised the study, and critically revised the 
manuscript for important intellectual content. Y.T.v.d.S. 
contributed to study concept and design, obtained funding, 
analyzed and interpreted data, and critically revised the 
manuscript for important intellectual content. All authors 
approved the final version of the manuscript. A.F.M.v.A. is 
the guarantor of this work and, as such, had full access to all 
the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity 
of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. 
Parts of this study were presented in abstract form at the 
World Diabetes Congress of the International Diabetes 
Federation, Dubai, United Arab Emirates, 4-8 December 
2011. 
The authors thank the PHARMO Institute, GPs, and 
pharmacists for follow-up data on type 2 diabetes. </p>

<p> </p>



<p>
FAMINE EXPOSURE AND RISK OF TYPE 2 DIABETES </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, SEPTEMBER 2012 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

</text></tei>