<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3349032" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Guinea pigs were fed a hypercholesterolemic diet (0.25 g/100 g cholesterol) and randomly allocated either to a Control group (n = 9) or to a 
Lutein (0.1 g/100 g) group (n = 10) for 12 weeks to evaluate oxidative stress and inflammation in both liver and eyes. Malondialdehyde (MDA) 
concentrations and inflammatory cytokines were measured as well as hepatic nuclear factor-kappaB (NF-κB) binding. Lutein concentrations were 
greater in eyes (P &lt; 0.01) and liver (P &lt; 0.001) in the Lutein group. All guinea pigs had high concentrations of hepatic cholesterol as well as high 
plasma ALT and AST levels indicative of liver injury. However, the Lutein group had 43% lower hepatic free cholesterol than the Controls (P 
&lt; 0.05). Hepatic MDA and MDA in the eye were lower in the Lutein compared to the Control group (P &lt; 0.05). Hepatic tumor necrosis factor-α 
was 32% lower in the Lutein group (P &lt; 0.05). Lastly, the Lutein group presented lower NF-κB DNA binding activity than the Control group (P 
&lt; 0.001). These results suggest that in the presence of high cholesterol, lutein exerts both antioxidant and anti-inflammatory effects, which can be 
explained by attenuated NF-κB DNA binding activity. Furthermore, results also suggest that lutein accumulates in the eyes of guinea pigs to protect 
against oxidative stress. </p>

<p>The carotenoid lutein is preferentially accumulated in the 
macular region of the human retina where it is known to protect 
the eyes against light damage [1], preventing the development 
of degenerative conditions in the eye including age-related 
macular degeneration (AMD) [2]. Retinal inflammatory reaction 
is suggested as a pathogenic factor in most retinal diseases 
including AMD [3,4]. Furthermore, oxidative stress is known to 
contribute to retinal inflammatory reactions. In an experimental 
animal model, oxidative damage in the outer retina and induction 
of inflammation contribute to the development of AMD [4]. 
However, whether the administration of lutein reduces the level 
of reactive oxygen species (ROS) in eyes and has a protective 
effect during inflammatory states remains to be elucidated. 
Recent studies have also suggested that lutein can reduce 
atherosclerosis and exert cardiac protection [5,6]. However, there 
are not sufficient reports on the effects of lutein on other 
degenerative conditions, such as liver injury, and its underlying 
mechanisms. A small number of in vivo studies have suggested 
that this carotenoid may protect the liver against oxidation [7,8]. 
In the aspect of anti-inflammatory effects, previous studies have 
shown that lutein inhibited lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-induced 
systemic inflammation in animal models and in RAW 264.7 </p>

<p>macrophages [9,10]. A recent study also reported that dietary 
lutein decreased interleukin (IL)-1β mRNA levels in the liver 
of F-line turkeys challenged with LPS injection [11]. The 
mechanism by which lutein down-regulates inflammatory 
responses in the liver has not been fully investigated. However, 
several studies have suggested an association between nuclear 
factor-kappaB (NF-κB) signaling pathway and a wide variety of 
pathological conditions in the liver [12-14]. Based on these 
observations, it is possible that the mechanism by which lutein 
attenuates the inflammatory state in the liver may be mediated 
through NF-κB pathways. 
The guinea pig is a suitable animal model to study hepatic 
cholesterol and lipoprotein metabolism because of similar 
responses to humans in regards to dietary interventions [15]. High 
cholesterol diets (0.25%) have been shown to increase hepatic 
cholesterol and triglyceride accumulation compared to low 
cholesterol diets (0.04%) [16,17]. This excess lipid accumulation 
in the liver may lead to the development of non-alcoholic fatty 
liver disease (NAFLD) [18]. We have previously demonstrated 
that lutein decreases cholesterol accumulation, oxidative damage 
and inflammation in aortas of guinea pigs [19]. Therefore, we 
hypothesized that lutein accumulation in the eyes of guinea pigs 
could protect against oxidative stress and inflammation. Further 
we tested the hypothesis that lutein could prevent degenerative </p>

<p> § Corresponding Author: Maria Luz Fernandez, Tel. 1-860-486-5547, Fax. 1-860-486-3674, Email. maria-luz.fernandez@uconn.edu 
Received: October 19, 2011, Revised: January 27, 2012, Accepted: February 3, 2012 
ⓒ2012 The Korean Nutrition Society and the Korean Society of Community Nutrition 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>



<p>Lutein and hepatic inflammation </p>

<p>conditions in the liver of guinea pigs fed with high cholesterol 
diet by reducing lipid peroxidation and attenuating pro-inflammatory 
cytokine production. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>Nineteen male Hartley guinea pigs (Charles River Breeding 
Laboratories, Wilmington MA) were randomly assigned into 
either the Lutein group or the Control group. All animals were 
fed a high cholesterol diet (0.25 g/100 g) for 12 weeks, while 
the Lutein group was also given lutein supplementation (0.1 
g/100 g) (FloraGLO 
® Lutein, Kemin Industries, Inc., USA). The </p>

<p>percent energy distribution of the diet was 42:35:22 for carbohy-
drate: fat:protein and the micronutrient composition was formulated 
to meet the National Research Council requirements for guinea 
pigs [20]. Animal protocols were approved by the Institutional 
Animal Care and Use Committee of the University of Connecticut 
protocol number A08-070. After 12 hours of food depravation, 
guinea pigs were killed and the livers and eyes were harvested. 
The tissues samples were promptly frozen in liquid nitrogen and 
then stored in -80℃ until analyses. </p>

<p>Plasma and liver lutein concentration </p>

<p>Approximately 0.5g of liver or 500 uL of plasma were prepared 
for carotenoid analysis by saponification and extraction with 
hexane and ethyl ether. Samples were prepared as previously 
reported [21]. </p>

<p>Eye lutein concentration </p>

<p>Two whole eyes were pooled for each animal and homogenized 
in 1mL PBS with a tissue tearor (Model 985370-07, BioSpec 
Products, Inc., Bartlesville, OK). An equal volume of tetrahydro-
furan (THF) was added to the homogenate and vortexed then, 
5 mL of ethyl ether were added and the mixture was vortexed 
and sonicated for 3 min at 3 watts RMS. After centrifugation 
at 1,000 × g for 10 min, the top organic layer was transferred 
to a second glass vial. The bottom phase was extracted again 
with 5 mL of ethyl ether and the organic phases of two extractions 
were combined. Solvents in the extract were evaporated under 
nitrogen gas. In preparation for high performance liquid 
chromatography (HPLC) analysis, the samples were re-dissolved 
with 1 mL of ethanol and analyzed as previously reported [21]. </p>

<p>Liver lipids </p>

<p>After total lipids extraction with chloroform-methanol (2:1), 
hepatic total cholesterol (Roche-Diagnostics, Indianapolis, IN), 
free cholesterol (Wako Chemicals USA, Inc., Richmond, VA) </p>

<p>and triglyceride (Roche-Diagnostics, Indianapolis, IN) were 
determined according to Carr et al. [22] by using enzymatic 
reagents. Hepatic esterified cholesterol concentrations were 
calculated by subtracting free cholesterol from total cholesterol. </p>

<p>Liver enzymes </p>

<p>Photometric measurements were used to measure plasma 
aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase 
(ALT) by using Cobas c 111 analyzer (Roche-Diagnostics, 
Indianapolis, IN). </p>

<p>Malondialdehyde (MDA) concentrations </p>

<p>Liver and eye MDA concentrations were measured by 
thiobarbituric acid reactive substances (TBARS) assay using a 
commercially available assay kit (Cayman Chemical, Ann Arbor, 
MI). In brief, 100 μL of homogenized liver and eye tissues 
suspended in RIPA buffer or 100 μL standards were added to 
100 μL of SDS solution and 4 mL of color reagent. Vials were 
placed into vigorously boiling water for one hour and 
immediately removed and placed in ice for 10 min to stop the 
reaction. Samples were centrifuged for 10 min at 1,600 × g at 
4℃ and incubated at room temperature for 30 min. Samples (150 
μL) and standards were read by fluorescence at an excitation 
wavelength of 530 nm and an emission wavelength of 550 nm. 
Detected MDA were normalized to protein concentrations, which 
were measured using a commercially available Bradford assay 
(Bio-Rad Laboratories; Hercules, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Protein levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines in the liver and eye </p>

<p>Protein levels of TNF-α, IL-1β and monocyte chemotactic 
protein-1 (MCP-1) were evaluated from homogenates of liver and 
eye using the MILLIPLEX MAP Mouse Cytokine PREMIXED 
Immunoassay kit (Millipore coorporation, Charles, MO, USA) 
and Luminex system (Luminex 200 System, Austin, TX) as 
previously reported [19]. </p>

<p>Nuclear fraction extraction </p>

<p>The nuclear fraction was extracted using Nuclear Extract kit 
(Active Motif, Carlsbad, CA). In brief, 100 mg of frozen liver 
tissue were ground using a cold mortar and pestle. The ground 
tissue samples were suspended in 300 µL of 1X stock hypotonic 
buffer and then transferred to a dounce homogenizer and dounced 
on ice approximately 20 strokes. Homogenized tissues were 
incubated on ice 15 minutes and then centrifuged at 850 × g for 
10 minutes at 4℃. The pellet containing nuclei was re-suspended 
in 50 µL 1X stock hypotonic solution and after 15 minutes 
incubation on ice, 2.5 µL detergents were added to disrupt nuclear 
membrane. Samples were centrifuged at 14,000 × g for 30 sec 
at 4℃ and then the nuclear pellet was re-suspended in 50 µl </p>

<p>Jung Eun Kim et al. </p>



<p>Control (n = 9) 
Lutein (n = 10) </p>

<p>Triglyceride (μmol/g liver) 
56.5 ± 6.8 
52.6 ± 11.9 </p>

<p>Total Cholesterol (μmol/g liver) 
71.0 ± 14.5 
76.2 ± 14.0 </p>

<p>Free Cholesterol (%) 
57.5 ± 20.7 
31.5 ± 25.5* </p>

<p>Esterified Cholesterol (%) 
42.5 ± 20.7 
68.5 ± 25.5* </p>

<p>ALT (U/L) 
233.6 ± 108.9 
233.7 ± 100.9 </p>

<p>AST (U/L) 
795.0 ± 513.3 
777.4 ± 410.9 </p>

<p>1) Values are expressed as mean ± SD for the number of guinea pigs indicated in 
parentheses. </p>

<p>* P &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>Table 1. Hepatic lipids and plasma concentrations of Alanine Transferase (ALT) 
and Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) of guinea pigs from Lutein or Control 
groups </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>(B) </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Correlations between AST and free cholesterol (r = 0.57, P &lt; 0.025) 
(Panel A) and ALT and free cholesterol (r = 0.66, P &lt; 0.001) for 19 guinea pigs 
(n = 9, control and n = 10 for the lutein group). ALT and AST were determined 
by use of a COBAS C-111 analyzer. </p>

<p>complete lysis buffer (5 µL 10 mM DTT, 45 µL lysis buffer 
AM1, 0.5 µL protease inhibitor cocktail). To extract the nuclear 
proteins, samples were incubated on ice for 30 minutes, after 
vortexing, they were centrifuged at 14,000 × g for 10 minutes 
at 4℃ to remove insoluble material. </p>

<p>NF-κB DNA binding activity </p>

<p>DNA-binding activity of p65 was assessed using an NF-κB 
p65 EZ-TFA transcription factor assay colorimetric kit 
(Millipore, Danvers, MA). Briefly, 50 μL of transcription factor 
assay (TFA) buffer containing 12.5 μg of nuclear extract and 
2 μL of NF-κB capture probe were added to a well and incubated 
for 2 h. Primary NF-κB antibody was added and incubated for 
1 h, after which wells were washed 3 times with an enhanced 
TFA buffer. IgG-HRP conjugated secondary antibody was added 
and after 30 minutes incubation, wells were washed 4 times with 
a TFA buffer. To develop color, the TMB/E substrate was added 
and after 10 min incubation, the plate was read by a spectro-
photometric microplate reader (Bio-Tek, Winooski, VT) at 450 
nm. Positive and negative controls were also analyzed to validate 
this assay. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Independent t-tests were used for comparisons between groups 
and bivariate correlations were used when appropriate. Statistical 
analyses were conducted by using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">17.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS, Chicago, IL</rs>) and the values reported as mean ± standard deviation (SD). 
Values with P &lt; 0.05 were considered to be significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Eye and Hepatic lutein concentrations </p>

<p>Eye lutein concentrations of guinea pigs from the Lutein group 
were 2.87 ± 0.98 ng/eye and this value was significantly higher 
than the Control group (1.03 ± 0.69 ng/eye) (P &lt; 0.01) Hepatic 
lutein concentrations were 23.8 ± 5.6 nmol/g in the Lutein group 
while the concentrations was &lt; 1 nmol/g in the Control group. 
Plasma lutein concentrations in the Lutein group were 75.1 ± 
17.1 nmol/L compared to &lt; 5 nmol/L in the Control group. </p>

<p>Hepatic lipids and enzymes </p>

<p>There were no significant differences in liver weight between 
the Lutein and the Control group (data not shown). Similarly, 
hepatic total cholesterol and triglyceride concentrations were not 
different between groups (Table 1). However, the percent 
distribution of free cholesterol in hepatic total cholesterol was 
significantly lower whereas the percent distribution of cholesterol 
ester was significantly higher in the Lutein group (31.5 ± 25.5% </p>

<p>and 68.5 ± 25.5%) compared to those of the Control group (57.5 
± 20.7% and 42.5 ± 20.7%) (P &lt; 0.05). Plasma values for ALT 
and AST were not different between groups. However, both ALT 
and AST levels were positively correlated with percent distribu-
tion of free cholesterol in the liver (r = 0.57; P &lt; 0.025 and r 
= 0.66; P &lt; 0.001, respectively) (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>Liver and eye MDA concentrations </p>

<p>Guinea pigs from the Lutein group had lower hepatic MDA 
concentrations (6.0 ± 1.0 nmol/mg protein) than the Control 
group (7.0 ± 1.0 nmol/mg protein) (P &lt; 0.05) (Fig. 2). Hepatic </p>



<p>Lutein and hepatic inflammation </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Malonaldehyde concentrations in liver and in eye of guinea pigs fed 
control (n = 9) or lutein (n = 10) diets. MDA concentrations were measured by 
thiobarbituric acid reactive substances (TBARS) * indicates P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>(B) </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Concentrations of TNF-α, MCP-1 and IL-1β of liver and eye of guinea 
pigs fed control (n = 9) or lutein (n = 10) diets. Protein levels of cytokines were 
evaluated from homogenates of liver and eye using the MILLIPLEX MAP Mouse 
Cytokine PREMIXED Immunoassay kit * indicates P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. NF-kB p65 DNA binding activity of control and lutein treated guinea pigs. 
** P &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>lutein concentration was negatively correlated with hepatic MDA 
concentration (r = -0.47, P &lt; 0.05). The eyes from the Lutein 
group also presented significantly lower MDA concentration 
(3.08 ± 1.43 nmol/mg protein) than those from the Control group 
(6.20 ± 3.80 nmol/mg protein) (P &lt; 0.05). In addition, eye lutein 
concentrations were negatively associated with eye MDA 
concentration (r = -0.63, P &lt; 0.05) (data now shown). </p>

<p>Hepatic and eye pro-inflammatory cytokine concentrations </p>

<p>Guinea pigs from the Lutein group had significantly lower 
hepatic concentrations of TNF-α (338.9 ± 100.7 pg/mg protein) 
than the Control guinea pigs (499.9 ± 182.5 pg/mg protein, P 
&lt; 0.05) (Fig. 3A). There were no significant differences in 
MCP-1 (509.4 ± 100.2 pg/mg protein vs 623.3 ± 152.8 pg/mg 
protein, P = 0.069) or IL-1β (614.5 ± 125.5 pg/mg protein vs 
668.1 ± 173.1 pg/mg protein) concentrations in the liver between 
groups. 
In the eye, the Lutein group showed significantly lower TNF-α 
(125.5 ± 14.1 pg/mg protein vs 138.9 ± 9.6 pg/mg protein, P &lt; 
0.05) and IL-1β (323.6 ± 41.4 pg/mg protein vs 413.8 ± 128.0 
pg/mg protein P &lt; 0.05) (Fig. 3B) concentrations than the Control 
group. However, there were no significant differences in MCP-1 
concentration (P = 0.321) between groups. </p>

<p>NF-κB p65 DNA binding activity </p>

<p>Along with lower TNF-α concentrations in the liver, the Lutein 
group also presented 18.3% lower NF-κB p65 DNA binding 
activity than the Control group (P &lt; 0.0001) (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present study demonstrates that guinea pigs with lutein 
treatment successfully accumulate this carotenoid in both liver 
and eyes. In addition, lutein exerts antioxidant and anti-infla-
mmatory effects. Furthermore, lutein treatment protects against 
degenerative conditions in the liver of guinea pigs fed with high 
cholesterol diet by reducing hepatic free cholesterol, decreasing 
lipid peroxidation and attenuating the inflammatory responses 
known to contribute to the development of NAFLD. Data also 
indicate that the attenuated inflammatory response with lutein 
treatment was due to the decreased NF-κB p65 DNA binding 
activity. However, interestingly, there were no differences in 
ALT and AST concentrations between groups, two major </p>

<p>Jung Eun Kim et al. </p>



<p>indicators of liver injury. 
A previous study conducted with guinea pigs identified lutein 
in both eyes and liver after feeding the animals lutein at the 
supplemental level of 7.97 mg/kg diet [23]. Based on this result, 
we decided to use 0.1 g/100 g lutein to ensure not only the 
presence of this carotenoid in eye and liver but also to prove 
its protective effects on these tissues. Consistent with this study 
[24], we successfully detected lutein in both eyes and liver. 
Hepatic lipid overloading has been considered the first hit in 
NAFLD development [18] and high cholesterol diet treated guinea 
pigs present greater hepatic total cholesterol and triglyceride 
accumulation than those fed a low cholesterol diet [17]. In this 
study, we observed greater lipid accumulation in guinea pig liver 
compared to those treated with low concentrations of dietary 
cholesterol [24]. It is important to note that there were no 
differences in hepatic total cholesterol and triglyceride concent-
rations between the two groups in the present study. Consistent 
with these results, it is reported that fat content of liver was 
independent of amounts of dietary lutein in Japanese quail [25]. 
However the Lutein group presented significantly lower percent 
distribution of free cholesterol in hepatic total cholesterol 
compared to the Control group. Additionally, percent distribution 
of free cholesterol presented strong positive correlations with 
both plasma ALT and AST levels. Therefore, the larger portion 
of free cholesterol in the Control group may increase the risk 
of liver injury. Lipid composition of human liver demonstrated 
almost 2-fold increase in free cholesterol content in subjects with 
NAFLD or nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH) compared to 
normal subjects [26]. It is suggested that several abnormalities 
that can be observed in NAFLD including mitochondrial abnor-
malities and impaired adenosine triphosphate synthesis may 
potentially contribute to the increase in hepatic free cholesterol 
contents [27,28]. 
Oxidative stress also has been considered as an important 
etiological factor in many progressive liver diseases [29]. The 
excessive lipid peroxidation caused by free radicals leads to 
oxidative stress, which results in the accumulation of MDA. 
MDA is one of the end products of lipid peroxidation and 
oxidative stress [30]. It is well known that lutein is a beneficial 
antioxidant due to its structural characteristics consisting in 
centrally localized conjugated C = C double bonds, which can 
readily quench reactive oxygen species [31]. Additionally, 
hydroxyl groups attached to each of the 2 terminal β, ε-ionone 
rings make lutein scavenge free radicals more efficiently than 
other carotenoids [32]. Collectively, the antioxidant effects of 
lutein may attenuate the oxidative stress and the production of 
MDA. In the present study, the lutein treated guinea pigs 
presented lower MDA production in liver compared to the control 
guinea pigs. In addition, hepatic lutein concentrations were 
negatively correlated with hepatic MDA concentrations, which 
clearly indicates that lutein may inhibit lipid peroxidation. 
Liver injury by pro-inflammatory cytokines is another major 
factor to induce liver disease [18]. In particular, NF-κB, a major </p>

<p>transcriptional factor involved in cell survival, immunity and 
inflammation, is activated during liver injury [12]. NF-κB 
signaling pathway and subsequent pro-inflammatory cytokine 
production regulate the maintenance of liver homoeostasis as well 
as the pathogenesis of a wide variety of liver diseases, including 
viral hepatitis, steatohepatitis, cirrhosis and hepatocellular 
carcinoma [14]. It has been shown that lutein directly decreases 
NF-κB activation and suppresses both mRNA and protein levels 
of cyclooxygenase (COX)-2, inducible nitric oxide synthase 
(iNOS), TNF-α, and IL-1β. Peroxisome proliferator X receptor 
(PPAR) and retinoic acid X receptor (RXR) are members of 
nuclear hormone receptors and they regulate NF-κB signaling 
pathway and inflammatory cytokine production [33]. One recent 
study suggested that LPS-induced PPARα and RXRα 
down-regulation was partially reversed by increasing the dietary 
lutein content to 50 mg/kg in chickens [34]. Therefore, based 
on these studies, an anti-inflammatory effect of lutein may be 
explained by direct inhibition of NF-κB activation or PPARα 
/RXRα-mediated regulation. Consistent to these studies, we 
found that guinea pigs from the Lutein group presented signifi-
cantly lower hepatic TNF-α concentration than guinea pigs from 
the Control group. In agreement with our study, mice with 
D-galactose-induced liver injury also showed that 40 mg/kg/day 
of lutein treatment lowers iNOS content in the liver [35]. 
Although lutein treatment inhibited lipid peroxidation and the 
inflammatory state in guinea pigs fed a high cholesterol diet, 
there were no differences on liver enzyme concentrations in the 
plasma between two groups. Serum ALT concentrations have 
been associated with decreased serum antioxidant concentrations, 
particularly carotenoids [36]. Additionally, Several animal studies 
suggest that lutein lowers ALT and AST concentrations due to 
scavenging of reactive oxygen radicals in rats with paracetamol-, 
carbon tetrachloride-and ethanol-induced hepatic injury [7,37]. 
However, these studies used higher amount of lutein (50, 100, 
250 mg/day) than in the current investigation (30 mg/day). 
The retina in the eyes is extremely rich in membranes with 
polyunsaturated fatty acids and this characteristic makes the eye 
susceptible to lipid peroxidation [38]. Not only by filtering the 
blue light, which is the most damaging wavelength of light that 
reaches the retina [39] but also by readily quenching singlet 
oxygen species [40], lutein protects the eye from oxidative stress. 
In the current study, lutein was successfully detected in the eyes 
of guinea pigs with lutein treatment and they presented lower 
concentrations of MDA compared to guinea pigs without lutein 
treatment. We also observed lower pro-inflammatory cytokine 
productions with lutein treatment in the eye and consistent with 
our study, pro-inflammatory cytokine productions in the aqueous 
humor of rats with endotoxin-induced uveitis were reduced with 
100 mg/kg lutein administration [9]. This result was explained 
by suppression of NF-κB activation with lutein, therefore lutein 
might be involved in the regulation NF-κB signaling pathway 
in the eye as well. 
In summary, our findings suggest that lutein might have </p>



<p>Lutein and hepatic inflammation </p>

<p>antioxidant and anti-inflammatory functions in the eye. Additionally, 
this carotenoid could prevent degenerative conditions of the liver 
by reducing the free cholesterol pool and attenuating lipid 
peroxidation and pro-inflammatory cytokine production. Further, 
attenuated inflammatory state in the liver could be explained by 
decreased NF-κB p65 binding activity. </p>



<p>Jung Eun Kim et al. </p>





</text></tei>