<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3663311" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Objective: Acute accidental poisoning in children is still an important public health problem. The 
epidemiological investigation specific for each country is necessary to determine the extent and 
characteristics of the problem. The aim of our study was to elucidate the current pattern of acute poisoning 
among children. </p>

<p>Methods: The present retrospective study describes the epidemiology of acute accidental poisoning in 
children (less than 10 years old) admitted to the Emergency Department of two teaching hospitals during a 
period of two years. </p>

<p>Findings: Three hundred and forty four children under 10 years old were admitted to emergency department 
of two teaching hospitals due to acute accidental poisoning. Drugs were the most common agents causing the 
poisoning (58.1%), followed by Hydrocarbons (13.1%), and opioids (9.3%). Common signs were neurological 
(42.6%) with lethargy being the most common (39.1%). 50.6% of cases were discharged from hospital within 
6-12 hours, 91.6% of them without any complication. </p>

<p>Conclusion: Accidental poisonings are still a significant cause of morbidity among children in developing 
countries. Regarding the high prevalence of pharmaceutical drug poisoning and because lethargic was the 
most frequent neurological sign, comprehensive toxicology screen tests should be included as part of the 
routine evaluation of children presenting to an ED with an apparent life-threatening event. </p>

<p>Despite various preventive measures, poisoning in 
children still remains an important public health 
matter worldwide, resulting in a large number of 
hospitalizations in emergency units. Poisoning 
accounts for about 7% of all accidents in children 
under 5 years and is implicated in about 2% of all </p>

<p>childhood deaths in the developed world, and over 
5% in the developing countries [1] . 
Substantial differences in socioeconomic and 
cultural situations in different countries cause 
various patterns of poisoning with different 
poisonous agents. These differences vary from 
country to country and between geographical 
areas within the same country. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Iran J Pediatr 
Apr 2013; Vol 23 (No 2), Pp: 189-193 </p>



<p>Acute Accidental Poisoning in Children </p>

<p>Iran J Pediatr; Vol 23 (No 2), Apr 2013 
Published by: Tehran University of Medical Sciences (http://ijp.tums.ac.ir) </p>

<p>Previous researches indicated that a variety of 
social and demographic factors influence the acute 
accidental poisoning in children [2,3] . Factors such 
as family size, socioeconomic condition, child care 
and place of storing poison are important. 
There is a lot of data and research about acute 
accidental childhood poisoning from developed 
and developing countries [4-6] . However, there is a 
scarcity of data from Iran because there is neither 
a national database nor any authority in charge, 
but individual local studies have been carried out 
in cities in the past [7-12] . 
The main objective of our study was to 
determine the agents of poisoning, demographic 
distribution, clinical manifestations of poisoned 
children and to investigate the various risk factors 
associated with it. </p>

<p>Subjects and Methods </p>

<p>This hospital based, retrospective and non-
interventional case series study was carried out at 
Department of Pediatrics, Alzahra University 
Hospital, a referral children's hospital, and referral 
clinical toxicology emergency department of the 
Noor Hospital, both in the region of Isfahan, 
located in central Iran, with a population of 
4,815,000. The cases were included from April 1, 
2008 to March 31, 2010. 
The inclusion criteria were patients less than 10 
years of age admitted to the two mentioned 
hospitals with a main diagnosis of acute poisoning 
based on history, practitioner's judgment or 
laboratory findings. All suspected poisonings were 
initially included, but patients were excluded from 
the study if the initial diagnosis of poisoning was 
rejected clinically or otherwise. 
The information about each case was recorded 
in standardized forms. The occurrence of 
childhood poisoning was described according to 
time trends, age and gender of the child, route of 
exposure, symptoms at presentation to the 
emergency room, role of the child or others, and 
substance involved in the poisoning, duration 
between exposure and admission, duration of stay 
in the hospital, measures carried out by parents 
before admission, and outcome. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis of the data was performed 
using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences 
(SPSS</rs>), <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 15.0</rs> (SPSS, Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). 
All quantitative variables were expressed as the 
median and standard deviation, while qualitative 
variables were expressed as frequencies and 
percentages. All treatment was given according to 
standard protocols, and in accordance with the 
Helsinki declaration. </p>

<p>Findings </p>

<p>Three hundred and forty-four patients under 10 
years old were admitted to ED of two teaching 
hospitals due to accidental poisoning during 
period of two years. Complete clinical data were 
obtained for all of the children. </p>

<p>Age and sex 
Of 344 intoxicated patients 174 (50.6%) were 
males and 170 (49.4%) females. The mean age of 
all these children was 3.07±1.43 years. Most 
(89.5%) of the children were under 6 years and 
10.5% were between 6 and 10 years. Children 
between 1 and 3 years of age accounted for 44.7% 
of poisonings (Table 1). </p>

<p>Table 1: Total number of children with accidental 
poisoning according to age groups </p>

<p>Age (year) 
n (%) 
&lt;1 
56 (16.3) </p>

<p>1-3 
154 (44.6) </p>

<p>4-6 
98 (28.6) </p>

<p>7-10 
36 (10.5) </p>

<p>Total 
344 (100) </p>

<p>Route of exposure and monthly distribution 
Ingestion in 95.1% (327 cases) was the main route 
of exposure and then transdermal in 9 (2.6%), 
inhalation in 6 (1.7%) and ingestion with 
inhalation together in 2 (0.6%). 
Autumn had the most number of poisonings 
with peak of 10.8% (37 cases) in august and 
lowest rate (5.2%) of poisoning was observed in 
November. </p>



<p>Gheshlaghi F, et al </p>

<p>Iran J Pediatr; Vol 23 (No 2), Apr 2013 
Published by: Tehran University of Medical Sciences (http://ijp.tums.ac.ir) </p>

<p>Fig. 1: Clinical manifestations of poisoning in children under 10 years </p>

<p>Time elapsed before admission 
The mean (standard deviation) time interval to 
reach hospital was 6.9±3.1 hours. About one half 
(46.2%, n=159) of the children reached hospital 
within 4 hours following poisoning and 3.2% (11 
cases) of patients arrived after 24 hours. 
Neurological signs were the most common 
(42.6%, n=203) complaints of children at 
admission, among these lethargy was the most 
frequent (39.1%,n=90) neurological sign while 
extrapyramidal sign had the lowest rate 
(1.7%,n=4). Gastrointestinal symptoms (vomiting 
or abdominal pain) were noted in 106 (22.2%) 
children. 71 (14.9%) patients were asymptomatic 
(Fig 1). In one half of the cases parents had not 
done any appropriate action and 44% had brought 
their child to a local hospital before admission to 
the referral hospitals. Just in 8 (2.3%) cases 
parents had undertaken an appropriate 
performance before arriving to the hospital. </p>

<p>Agents Involved 
Drugs were the most common agents causing 
poisoning 
(58.1%, 
n=200), 
followed 
by 
hydrocarbons, opioids, pesticides, plants, insect 
stings and cleansing products (Table 2). </p>

<p>Duration of hospitalization and outcome 
One hundred and seven (31.1%) patients were 
discharged within 6 hours and 170 (50.6%) cases 
were discharged between 6 to 24 hours. Only 63 
children remained in hospital after 24 hours. 
Three hundred and fifteen (91.6%) patients 
were discharged with full recovery, 6.7% (23 </p>

<p>cases) were discharged with few complications 
and 5 (1.5%) patients died as a result of poisoning. 
Two of deceased children were intoxicated with 
drugs, two intoxicated with hydrocarbons and one 
with opioids. </p>

<p>Table 2: Agents causing acute poisoning </p>

<p>Agent 
n (%) 
Drugs 
200 (58.1) </p>

<p>Hydrocarbons 
45 (13.1) </p>

<p>Opioids 
32 (9.3) </p>

<p>Pesticides 
22 (6.4) </p>

<p>Plants 
12 (3.5) </p>

<p>Insect stings 
10 (2.9) </p>

<p>Cleansing products 
10 (2.9) </p>

<p>Drug-opioid 
1 (0.3) </p>

<p>Drug-toxin 
1 (0.3) </p>

<p>Unknown 
11 (3.2) </p>

<p>Total 
344 (100) </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Intoxication represents one of the most frequent 
emergencies in childhood. Its epidemiological 
characteristics differ from country to country, so 
special epidemiological studies in each country 
and each region is necessary to determine how 
this health problem can be prevented. Many 
studies have revealed that children under 5 years 
are particularly at risk for accidental poisoning [1-3] . 
The results of our study showed that children 
below 5 years of age included about 84% of </p>



<p>Acute Accidental Poisoning in Children </p>

<p>Iran J Pediatr; Vol 23 (No 2), Apr 2013 
Published by: Tehran University of Medical Sciences (http://ijp.tums.ac.ir) </p>

<p>poisonings in children under 10 years. Similar to 
the findings in USA about 60% of children were 
under three years of age and slightly more than 
one half (50.6%) were boys [2,3] . 
Consistent with reports published by Toxic 
Exposure Surveillance Systems of the American 
Association of Poison Control Centers (TESS) 
database and National Health Interview Survey 
(NHIS) the most common route of poisoning in 
children was by the way of ingestion [13] . It seems 
that higher prevalence of ingestion in this age 
group is related to their attitude in putting small 
foreign objects into the mouth. 
Poisonous agents show geographical variations 
influenced by economical status. In developed 
countries, poisoning mostly happens because of 
drugs, cosmetics and beauty products, household 
cleansing products and alcohol, while for 
developing countries, where the economy is based 
on agriculture, common causes of poisoning are 
hydrocarbons, pesticides, traditional medicines 
and mushrooms [14-17] . As reported by previous 
studies, drugs are the most poisonous agents in 
children [2,3,18] . Similar to other studies in EMR 
region approximately 58.1% of the poisonings in 
our surveillance involved medications [10,19] . 
Acetaminophen, vitamins, benzodiazepine and 
antibiotics which are the most accessible drugs in 
homes, were the most common causes of drug-
related poisonings. The other common agents 
involved 
in 
accidental 
poisoning 
were 
hydrocarbons and opioids. According to a study in 
north Iran, opium was the most frequent cause of 
poisoning in children under 4 years of age and 
medications were more common in patients older 
than 4 years [19] . Moreover other studies in Iran 
show higher prevalence of opioid poisoning in 
comparison with other countries [12,19] . In contrast 
to other studies household products were not 
common among children in the present study. 
According to our retrospective search in 
emergency unit the most admissions due to child 
poisoning were in August, in which children in 
Iran spend more time in closed places and their 
home. 
Although gastrointestinal symptoms and 
psychological signs have been reported as the 
most frequent complaints of children poisoning in 
other studies, our study revealed that neurological 
signs including lethargy and unconsciousness are 
the main causes of children's arrival to ED [10,12] . </p>

<p>About one half of the patients presented within 
four hours following poisoning and about 81 
percent of the patients have been discharged in 
the first 24 hours. 
The rate of mortality in our surveillance was 
1.5% which in comparison to similar studies is 
relatively high [20] . Maybe the higher mortality rate 
in our study is related to the fact that our study 
population consisted of hospitalized patients and 
poisonings not requiring hospitalization were not 
accounted. The mortality rate concluded from our 
study is almost similar to the rate reported by 
Abdollahi et al about acute poisoning in Tehran, 
Iran [17] . 
Considering that most of children had no life-
threatening symptom and could be discharged by 
short term observation, it seems that it is not 
necessary to refer all cases of poisoning to the 
pediatrics or clinical toxicology center. 
Our study has some limitations. It was done 
retrospectively. So, it is possible that the exact 
types of drugs have not been noted in patients' 
records. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Frequency of accidental poisoning and mortality 
rate is relatively high in Isfahan. Regarding to high 
prevalence of pharmaceutical drugs poisoning and 
because lethargy was the most frequent 
neurological sign, comprehensive toxicology 
screen tests should be included as part of the 
routine evaluation of children presenting to an ED 
with an apparent life-threatening event. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>Authors thank the nurses of Department of Pediatrics, 
Alzahra University Hospital, and referral Clinical 
Toxicology Emergency department of the Noor Hospital 
for their help in management of the patients. Approval 
of The Data Inspectorate and the Local Ethics 
Committee was obtained. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: The authors declare that they have 
no competing interests. </p>



<p>Gheshlaghi F, et al </p>

<p>Iran J Pediatr; Vol 23 (No 2), Apr 2013 
Published by: Tehran University of Medical Sciences (http://ijp.tums.ac.ir) </p>



</text></tei>