<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3446116" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:43+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Objective: Congenital heart disease (CHD) is the most common form of cardiovascular diseases in 
children. This study was performed from September 2006 to August 2007 in Ardebil, 
Westnorthern Iran. The aim was to determine the prevalence of heart murmur in newborns and its 
correlation with CHD. </p>

<p>Methods: In a 1-year cross sectional descriptive-analytic study, 2928 newborns were screened for 
heart murmur during routine neonatal physical examination. All babies with murmur underwent 
echocardiography. </p>

<p>Findings: Murmur was detected in 91 (3.1%) neonates, of whom 47 (51.6%) had a congenital 
heart disease. The most common (17.6%) abnormality was ventricular septal defect. Patent ductus 
arteriosus was found in 10 (11%) patients. </p>

<p>Conclusion: Remarkable high (round 50 %) rate of CDH in newborns presenting with heart 
murmur, urges to observe these neonates closely to establish the diagnosis of congenital heart 
disease and early referral to pediatric cardiologist. </p>

<p>Congenital heart disease (CHD) is defined as a 
structural abnormality of the heart or 
intrathoracic great vessels that is actually or </p>

<p>potentially of functional significance [1] . This is 
themost common form of cardiovascular diseases 
in children. Cardiovascular malformations affect 6 
to 8 infants per 1000 live births [2] . The incidence </p>

<p>Short Communication </p>

<p>Iran J Pediatr 
Mar 2011; Vol 21 (No 1), Pp: 103-106 </p>



<p>Heart Murmur in Neonates; M Mirzarahimi, et al </p>

<p>of structural congenital heart disease is estimated 
to be less than 1% of all live births [3] . 
Heart murmurs are a common finding in infants 
and children and mostly originate from normal 
flow patterns with no structural or anatomic 
abnormalities of the heart or vessels and are 
referred to as innocent, physiological or normal 
murmurs; conversely, murmur may be created by 
abnormal flow patterns in the heart and vessels 
resulting from congenital heart abnormalities [4] . 
According to one study two-thirds of normal 
newborns have innocent murmurs for several 
days after birth [5] . Another study found heart 
murmur within the first week of life in 7.38/1,000 
live births [6] . 
The present study was conducted to evaluate 
incidence of heart murmur in neonates and its 
association with congenital heart disease. </p>

<p>Subjects and Methods </p>

<p>Two thousand nine hundred twenty eight 
newborns admitted to the nursery of Imam 
Khomeini and Alavi Hospitals, Ardabil, Iran were 
examined from September 1, 2006 to September 
1, 2007. The clinical examination was carried out 
by a pediatrician within 24 h of delivery. </p>

<p>All neonates with heart murmur underwent 
echocardiography by cardiologist to explain the 
nature of the abnormality. The results of 
echocardiography were categorized as a) 
structural heart malformation, b) physical 
variance and c) completely normal. 
Birth weight, gestational age and gender in all 
infants were noted. Maternal age at delivery and 
folic acid use were recorded in the questionnaire. 
The Spearman's Rho and Chi 2 tests were used to 
define correlation and association between 
variables. Significance level of P&gt;0.05 was used in 
the analysis. All statistical analyses were 
performed using <rs type="software">SPSS</rs> software. </p>

<p>Findings </p>

<p>Out of 2928 live-born infants 91 had heart 
murmur (prevalence: 31 cases per 1000 live 
births). 
Cardiovascular malformations were present in 
16 of 1000 infants, 9.9 (61.7%) in female infants 
and 6.4 (38.3%) cases in male infants. The most 
common cardiac defect was ventricular septal 
defect (VSD), and the second most common was 
patent ductus arteriosus (PDA) (Table 1). </p>

<p>Table 1: Distribution of various causes of heart murmur in neonates </p>

<p>N (%) 
Results of echocardiography </p>

<p>44 (48.4) 
normal </p>

<p>16 (17.6) 
Ventricular septal defect (VSD) </p>

<p>10 (11) 
Patent ductus arteriosus (PDA) </p>

<p>5 (5.5) 
Pulmonary stenosis (PS) </p>

<p>4 (4.4) 
Atrial septal defect (ASD) </p>

<p>4 (4.4) 
Left ventricular hypertrophy (LVH) </p>

<p>2 (2.2) 
Transposition of the great arteries (TGA) </p>

<p>2 (2.2) 
ASD, VSD </p>

<p>1 (1.1) 
VSD, PS </p>

<p>1 (1.1) 
VSD, PS, PDA </p>

<p>1 (1.1) 
Right ventricular hypertrophy, Right atrial 
hypertrophy </p>

<p>1 (1.1) 
ASD, VSD, Pulmonary arterial hypertension </p>

<p>91 (100) 
Total </p>



<p>Iran J Pediatr; Vol 21 (No 1); Mar 2011 </p>

<p>Of 91 neonates 16 had ventricular septal defect, 
a prevalence of 5.5 per 1000 live births [11 
(68.8%) females; 5 (31.3%) males]. None of the 
patients had a family history of congenital heart 
disease in first degree relatives. 
Birth weight ranged from 1000 to 5000 g. 
Congenital heart disease was seen more (42.6%) 
in infants with birth weight between 2500-3499g 
and there was no significant relation between 
birth weight and congenital heart disease (P=0.4). 
Congenital heart disease was present in 24 
(51.1%) infants born at &gt;39 weeks of gestation. 
Altogether, 10 (21.3%) infants were born at 30-34 
weeks, 9 (19.1%) at &lt;29 weeks and the others 
(8.5%) at 35-39 weeks. No significant relation 
between gestational age and congenital heart 
disease was detected in our data (P=0.8). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Congenital heart diseases comprise the most 
common group of congenital malformations. 
Despite recent developments in interventional and 
surgical techniques, heart disease in children 
continues to be an important cause of morbidity 
and mortality [1] . Neonatal heart murmur is the 
most common reason for pediatric cardiologist 
consultation in neonatal intensive care units and 
nurseries [7] . 
Tanner et al observed innocent murmur in 44 
(48.4%) and congenital structural heart defects in 
47 (51.6%) newborns [8] . Rein et al found that 24% 
of heart murmur in neonates was innocent [9] . 
Another study has shown the prevalence of heart 
murmur in 13.7 per 1000 neonates. If a murmur is 
heard, there is a 42.5% chance of being an 
underlying cardiac malformation [10] . Yet another 
study stated that 84% of heart murmur in 
neonates was caused by heart diseases and only 
16% were innocent and urged echocardiography 
with a clinically diagnosed or possible heart 
disease [11] . Many types of congenital heart disease 
may be associated with an asymptomatic murmur, 
the most common being ventricular septal defect 
(VSD) [3,9,11-16] . 
As a limitation to the study we did not measure 
the quality, grading and location of murmur. </p>

<p>Because of the high prevalence of VSD in our 
study, it might be advantageous to create a 
longitudinal study that would allow subgroup 
analysis of patients with specific forms of CHD 
(e.g. VSD). </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Approximately 51.6% of neonates with heart 
murmur had congenital heart disease and only in 
48.4% the murmur was innocent. Although clinical 
evaluation could determine the presence or 
absence of heart diseases in most neonates, the 
lesion-specific diagnoses were not quite 
satisfactory. Echocardiography is necessary for 
neonates with a clinically diagnosed or possible 
heart disease. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>The authors thank the Office of Vice Chancellor for 
Research and education of Ardebil University of 
Medical Sciences for financial support and all 
colleagues in the Hospital who helped us in 
organizing the project. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: None </p>





<p>Heart Murmur in Neonates; M Mirzarahimi, et al </p>



</text></tei>