<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3025493" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background information. CDC25 (cell division cycle 25) phosphatases function as activators of CDK (cyclin-
dependent kinase)−cyclin complexes to regulate progression through the CDC. We have recently identified a pool 
of CDC25B at the centrosome of interphase cells that plays a role in regulating centrosome numbers. </p>

<p>Results. In the present study, we demonstrate that CDC25B forms a close association with Ctn (centrin) pro-
teins at the centrosome. This interaction involves both N-and C-terminal regions of CDC25B and requires 
CDC25B binding to its CDK−cyclin substrates. However, the interaction is not dependent on the enzyme activ-
ity of CDC25B. Although CDC25B appears to bind indirectly to Ctn2, this association is pertinent to CDC25B 
localization at the centrosome. We further demonstrate that CDC25B plays a role in maintaining the overall in-
tegrity of the centrosome, by regulating the centrosome levels of multiple centrosome proteins, including that of 
Ctn2. </p>

<p>Conclusions. Our results therefore suggest that CDC25B associates with a Ctn2-containing multiprotein complex 
in the cytoplasm, which targets it to the centrosome, where it plays a role in maintaining the centrosome levels of 
Ctn2 and a number of other centrosome components. </p>

<p>1 Correspondence may be addressed to either of these authors at Centre Pierre 
Potier, ITAV − UMS3039 CRT-CIV, 141 route d'Espagne, BP 50624, 31106 
Toulouse Cedex 1, France and Children's Medical Research Institute, The 
University of Sydney, 214 Hawkesbury Road, Westmead, NSW 2145, Australia 
(email bernard.ducommun@itav-recherche.fr or rboutros@cmri.org.au). 
Key words: CDC25B, centrin (Ctn), centrosome, cyclin-dependent kinase 
(CDK), fluorescence lifetime imaging microscopy (FLIM). 
Abbreviations used: CaM, calmodulin; CCD, charge-coupled device; CDC25, 
cell division cycle 25; CDK, cyclin-dependent kinase; Ctn1, centrin 1; DMEM, 
Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium; FLIM, fluorescence lifetime imaging 
microscopy; FRET, fluorescence resonance energy transfer; GFP, green 
fluorescent protein; GST, glutathione transferase; MCP-PMT, microchannel 
plate-photomultiplier tube; NER, nucleotide excision repair; PCM, 
pericentriolar material; siRNA, small interfering RNA; WT, wild-type; XPC, 
xeroderma pigmentosa group C. </p>

<p>and timely activation of their CDK (cyclin-dependent 
kinase)−cyclin substrates. Although we have some 
knowledge of the contributions of nuclear and cyto-
plasmic pools of CDC25 proteins, in terms of their 
upstream regulators and downstream targets, much 
less is known about their collaborators at the centro-
some. 
The primary role of the centrosome in non-dividing 
mammalian cells is to assemble and organize micro-
tubules in order to maintain the shape and polarity of 
the cell. In the dividing cell, the centrosome takes on 
a more dynamic role as it transforms into the bipolar 
mitotic spindle required for accurate segregation of 
duplicated chromosomes between the two daughter 
cells (Doxsey, 2001). For this, the G 1 phase centro-
some, consisting of a mother and daughter centriole </p>

<p>www.biolcell.org | Volume 103 (2) | Pages 55-68 
55 </p>

<p>Biology of the Cell www.biolcell.org </p>

<p>© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>R. Boutros and others </p>

<p>pair surrounded by a dense network of proteins, 
known as the PCM (pericentriolar material) must 
duplicate itself once before mitotic entry. This pro-
cess begins in the early S phase and usually occurs in 
a semi-conservative manner, in that a new centriole 
(or procentriole) forms perpendicular to each existing 
mother or daughter centriole. It then elongates by 
recruiting essential components from the surround-
ing PCM (Doxsey, 2001; Azimzadeh and Bornens, 
2007). 
We have recently demonstrated that a centrosomal 
pool of CDC25B participates in the regulation of 
two important processes during interphase: (i) nuc-
leation of microtubules and (ii) assembly of centro-
somes (Boutros et al., 2007b). Further, cells depleted 
of CDC25B and consequently arrested in the G 2 
phase of the cell cycle have a reduced number of Ctn 
(centrin)-positive centrioles within each centrosome 
(Boutros and Ducommun, 2008). This loss of centri-
oles and/or Ctn protein following CDC25B depletion 
is not the result of premature centrosome separation 
(Boutros and Ducommun, 2008). Thus, it is most 
likely caused either by a defect in centriole duplica-
tion or a defect in the incorporation of Ctn itself into 
replicating centrioles. 
Ctns are small calcium-binding proteins, and al-
though more than 90% of the protein is partitioned 
between the cytoplasm and nucleus in human cells, 
the remaining pool is concentrated at the centro-
some (Baron et al., 1994; Paoletti et al., 1996). Ctns 
are localized within multiple regions of the centro-
some, including the distal lumen of the centriole 
core structure, the interconnecting bridge between 
the mother and daughter centriole pair, and in the 
PCM (Paoletti et al., 1996; Salisbury, 2007). In addi-
tion to making up an important structural compon-
ent of the centrosome, Ctns have been reported to be 
involved in either centriole assembly or centriole se-
gregation, depending on the organism in question. In 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae, the Ctn homologue CDC31p 
has been found to be essential for initiating spindle 
pole body duplication (Baum et al., 1986; Paoletti 
et al., 2003), whereas two Ctn orthologues found in 
Paramecium were reported to be involved in centriole 
positioning (Ruiz et al., 2005). In mammalian cells, 
determining the role(s) of Ctns in centriole biogen-
esis has proven to be more complicated. Four Ctn 
isoforms are known to exist, which are differentially 
expressed. Ctn1 and Ctn4 appear to be restricted to </p>

<p>terminally differentiate ciliated cells, whereas Ctn2 
and Ctn3 are expressed in all somatic cells (Salis-
bury, 2007). The role of Ctn2 in centriole duplication 
in human cells remains unclear. Although siRNA 
(small interfering RNA) depletion of Ctn2 was first 
reported to cause a failure in centriole duplication in 
HeLa cells (Salisbury et al., 2002), these results were 
challenged by the finding that centrioles can con-
tinue to duplicate normally in the absence of both 
Ctn2 and Ctn3 in PLK4-overexpressing U2OS cells 
(Kleylein-Sohn et al., 2007). However, other evidence 
exists that suggests Ctn2 can contribute to centro-
some duplication, through interactions with CaM 
(calmodulin) and CP110 (Tsang et al., 2006), hSfi1 
(Kilmartin, 2003; Martinez-Sanz et al., 2006) and 
hPOC5 (Azimzadeh et al., 2009). Thus, it appears 
that the involvement of Ctns in the centrosome as-
sembly pathway in mammalian cells is most likely 
exerted through their association(s) with other pro-
teins and protein complexes. 
In the present study, we have investigated the re-
lationship between CDC25B and Ctn at the centro-
some. We found that CDC25B can associate with 
multiple Ctn isoforms, expressed either endogenously 
or exogenously in HeLa and U2OS cells, although 
this association appears to occur indirectly. Nonethe-
less, we found that Ctn2 depletion results in a loss of 
CDC25B from the centrosome. Similarly, CDC25B 
depletion causes a loss of centrosomal Ctn2, in ad-
dition to γ -tubulin, Nedd1, and the pericentriolar 
matrix protein PCM1. Together, our results suggest 
that CDC25B forms a complex with Ctn2, which is 
necessary for its localization to the centrosome, where 
it is involved in regulating the local levels of multiple 
centrosome proteins. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>CDC25B localization to the centrosome is 
dependent on both N-and C-terminal domains </p>

<p>We have demonstrated using fixed human cell lines 
that CDC25B localizes to the centrosome through-
out the cell cycle (Schmitt et al., 2006; Boutros et al., 
2007b; Boutros and Ducommun, 2008). In live cells, 
however, in which cytoplasmic CDC25B protein can-
not be pre-extracted, the detection of the centro-
somal pool of CDC25B against a strong cytoplasmic 
background has proven technically challenging, and 
CDC25B was almost never discernible in cells tran-
siently expressing fluorescently tagged CDC25B. To </p>

<p>56 
C The Authors Journal compilation C 2011 Portland Press Limited </p>

<p>© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>A CDC25B−centrin association </p>

<p>Research article </p>

<p>overcome this, we attempted to transiently express 
low levels of an mCherry-tagged CDC25B in a HeLa 
cell line that stably expresses human GFP (green 
fluorescent protein)-Ctn1 (HeLa-Ctn1, generously 
given by Dr Michel Bornens, Curie Institute, Paris, 
France), as a centrosome marker. Surprisingly, we ob-
served that the visibility of CDC25B at the centro-
some was enhanced in cells overexpressing Ctn (Fig-
ure 1A). In fact, when transfected into HeLa-Ctn1 
cells, mCherry-CDC25B was readily detectable at 
the centrosome(s) in approx. 25% of interphase cells, 
in comparison with less than 1% when expressed in 
parental HeLa cells [Figure 1A; WT (wild-type) and 
results not shown]. 
This permitted us to use live cell imaging of 
various mutant forms of CDC25B to try to gain some 
insight into which region(s) of the protein may be 
important for its centrosomal localization. As illus-
trated in Figure 1(B), a series of CDC25B mutants 
were generated that lack a specific region of the gene 
and/or have mutations in specific residues required 
for the catalytic activity of CDC25B (C487S and 
Cter C487S) (Gabrielli et al., 1996) or CDK−cyclin 
substrate-binding capacity (R506L and Cter R506L) 
(Sohn et al., 2004). These CDC25B mutants were 
transiently expressed as mCherry fusion proteins 
in HeLa-Ctn1 cells and assessed for their abilities 
to localize to centrosomes in live cells. As sum-
marized in Figure 1, full-length CDC25B forms 
localized to the centrosome, even when either the 
critical catalytic residue Cys 
487 or substrate-binding 
residue Arg 
506 were mutated. Furthermore, both 
Nter (regulatory region only) and Cter (catalytic 
domain only) mutants were capable of localizing to 
the centrosome (Figure 1). However, when the cata-
lytic site Cys 
487 residue was mutated (Cter C487S), 
the Cter domain alone was no longer sufficient for 
CDC25B localization to the centrosome. As the 
levels of CDC25B expressed showed significant 
cell-to-cell variations for all mutants examined, 
we were unable to determine with any certainty 
whether any of the various CDC25B mutants 
examined preferentially localize to the centrosome 
in comparison with the WT protein. 
Together, these results indicate that CDC25B loc-
alization to the centrosome may be mediated by either 
N-or C-terminal residues and involves the catalytic 
site, but not the CDK−cyclin-binding domain of 
CDC25B. </p>

<p>Centrosomal CDC25B protein levels are regulated 
by Ctn </p>

<p>Since Ctn1 overexpression enhances the detection 
of CDC25B at the centrosome in live cells (Fig-
ure 1), we next investigated the effect of its de-
pletion on centrosomal CDC25B levels. As Ctn1 
(which shares 85% sequence homology with Ctn2) 
is restricted to differentiated cells, we targeted Ctn2, 
which is ubiquitously expressed at the centrioles of 
all somatic cells (Salisbury et al., 2002; Salisbury, 
2007). To detect the centrosomal pool of CDC25B, 
immunofluorescence analyses were performed using 
an antibody that specifically detects CDC25B phos-
phorylated on Ser 
230 (CDC25B-S230P), which is me-
diated by Chk1 throughout the cell cycle (Schmitt 
et al., 2006; Boutros et al., 2007b), as this is cur-
rently the only reliable antibody available for the 
reproducible detection of endogenous CDC25B at 
the centrosome in all cells. We observed a significant 
loss in the centrosomal pool of CDC25B in approx. 
50% of HeLa (Figure 2) and 40% of U2OS (Sup-
plementary Figure S1 at http://www.biolcell.org/ 
boc/103/boc1030055add.htm) cells, in which Ctn2 
was efficiently depleted by 48 h siRNA treatment 
(Figure 2C). However, Western-blot analyses showed 
no effect of Ctn2 siRNA depletion on either total 
or S230-phosphorylated pools of CDC25B protein 
(Figure 2C). 
To ensure that observed effects of Ctn2 depletion on 
centrosomal CDC25B were not an indirect effect 
on centrosomal Chk1 levels (as a loss of Chk1 
would also cause a loss of CDC25B-S230P signal; 
Schmitt et al., 2006), co-immunofluorescence ana-
lyses of Chk1 and Ctn were performed. We observed 
no significant effect on centrosomal Chk1 levels 
in Ctn2-depleted cells (Supplementary Figure S2 
at http://www.biolcell.org/boc/103/boc1030055add. 
htm). These results therefore suggest that Ctn2 con-
trols either the localization or the levels of CDC25B 
at the centrosome. </p>

<p>CDC25B can associate with Ctns at the 
centrosome and in the cytoplasm </p>

<p>The observation that CDC25B levels at the centro-
some can be regulated by Ctn led us to question 
whether CDC25B and Ctn proteins physically 
associate. We first addressed this question using a 
FRET (fluorescence resonance energy transfer)-based 
approach in HeLa-Ctn1 cells, in which GFP-Ctn1 </p>

<p>www.biolcell.org | Volume 103 (2) | Pages 55-68 </p>

<p>
© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>R. Boutros and others </p>

<p>Figure 1 Both N-and C-terminal domains of CDC25B are involved in its centrosome targeting 
Various mutant forms of mCherry-CDC25B were derived, transfected into HeLa-Ctn1 cells and analysed for their ability to localize 
to the centrosome. (A) Examples of HeLa-Ctn1 cell transfected with mCherry-WT, -R506L, -Nter or -Cter CDC25B constructs. 
(B) Schematic diagram representing various N-(regulatory, yellow) and C-(catalytic, blue) domain mutant forms of CDC25B, in 
addition to mutations of specific amino acids within the catalytic domain (red stars), representing the mutation of Cys 
487 [critical </p>

<p>for CDC25B catalytic activity (Gabrielli et al., 1996)] to serine (C487S), or Arg 
506 [critical for substrate binding (Sohn et al., 2004)] </p>

<p>to leucine (R506L). The right-hand column indicates the presence (+) or absence ( − ) of each mutant at the centrosome 24 h 
post-transfection in HeLa-Ctn1 cells. </p>

<p>acted as the donor and mOrange-CDC25B as 
the acceptor fluorophore. In the case of an interaction 
between the two proteins, the fluorescence t1 / 2 of </p>

<p>GFP is shortened in proportion with the intensity 
of energy transfer to the mOrange fluorophore, 
directly reflecting the strength of the interaction </p>

<p>58 
C The Authors Journal compilation C 2011 Portland Press Limited </p>

<p>© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>A CDC25B−centrin association </p>

<p>Research article </p>

<p>Figure 2 Ctn2 depletion causes loss of CDC25B from the centrosome 
HeLa cells were treated with scrambled control or Ctn2 siRNA duplexes for 48 h before immunofluorescence detection of 
Ctn (green) and CDC25B (CDC25B-S230P, red). (A) Examples of Ctn2-depleted cells also demonstrating a detectable loss 
of centrosomal CDC25B (arrows) in comparison with cells treated with control siRNA duplexes. (B) Percentage of HeLa cells 
in which CDC25B-S230P and Ctn2 (Ctn2 siRNA only) were not detectable or substantially diminished from the centrosomes. 
In Ctn2 siRNA-treated cells, only the cells displaying a loss of centrosomal Ctn2 were scored for the presence or significant 
loss of centrosomal CDC25B-S230P signal. Bars represent mean results for at least 200 cells counted from three independent 
experiments + − S.D. (C) Western blots of lysates from control (Cont), Ctn2 and CDC25B siRNA-depleted cells immunoblotted for 
Ctn2, total CDC25B (using the C20 antibody from Santa Cruz), CDC25B-S230P and α-tubulin (α-tub) as loading control. </p>

<p>www.biolcell.org | Volume 103 (2) | Pages 55-68 </p>

<p>
© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>R. Boutros and others </p>

<p>Figure 3 WT CDC25B interacts with Ctn1 at the centrosome in live cells 
FRET−FLIM analyses of HeLa-Ctn1 cells co-expressing mOrange-CDC25B. (A) Example of a HeLa-Ctn1 cell co-transfected with 
mOrange (mOr)-CDC25B WT, demonstrating co-localization with GFP-Ctn1. (B) GFP fluorescent lifetime values in HeLa-Ctn1 
cells that were either mock-transfected (GFP-Ctn) or co-transfected with mOrange vector control, WT CDC25B (mOr-CDC25B 
WT), the catalytically inactive mutant mOr-CDC25B C487S, or the substrate-binding mutant mOr-CDC25B R506L. Fluorescence 
lifetime measurements are in nanoseconds (ns) and n represents the total number of cells analysed from three to five independent 
experiments. </p>

<p>between GFP-Ctn1 and mOrange-CDC25B. We 
used multiphoton FLIM (fluorescence lifetime 
imaging microscopy) analyses to characterize 
the spatial organization and the kinetics of the 
interaction. Co-localization of Ctn1 and CDC25B 
proteins were detected at the centrosomes of 
live HeLa-Ctn1 cells transiently transfected with 
mOrange-CDC25B WT, C487S and R506L (Fig-
ure 3A and results not shown). The lifetime of 
GFP fluorescence was found to be 2.463 ns for un-
transfected HeLa-Ctn1 cells (Figure 3B). However, 
when co-transfected with mOrange-CDC25B-WT 
or mOrange-CDC25B C487S mutant, this value </p>

<p>was reduced to 2.101 and 2.086 ns respect-
ively (representing 14.7 and 15.3% variations 
in fluorescence lifetime). However, no variation in 
GFP fluorescence lifetime was observed in cells 
co-transfected with the mOrange-CDC25B R506L 
mutant, or mOrange vector alone (Figure 3B and 
Supplementary Figure S3 at http://www.biolcell.org/ 
boc/103/boc1030055add.htm). These results indi-
cate that CDC25B interacts with Ctn1 at the 
centrosome, and that this interaction is de-
pendent on CDC25B substrate-binding capacity, 
but not its catalytic activity. The interaction 
between Ctn1 and CDC25B was confirmed using </p>

<p> 
C The Authors Journal compilation C 2011 Portland Press Limited </p>

<p>© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>A CDC25B−centrin association </p>

<p>Research article </p>

<p>Figure 4 Endogenous Ctn2 can be pulled down with 
GST−CDC25B 
GST−CDC25B fusion proteins produced in bacteria were 
bound to GST beads and incubated with protein extracts from 
HeLa cells. Proteins attached to the GST beads were dena-
tured and separated by SDS/PAGE. (Upper panel) Ponceau 
stain of nitrocellulose showing levels of GST or the various 
GST−CDC25B fusion proteins in each reaction. (Lower panel) 
Western-blot analysis of the same nitrocellulose membrane, 
immunostained for Ctn2. </p>

<p>co-immunoprecipitation analyses of endogenous 
CDC25B and GFP-Ctn1 from soluble/cytoplasmic 
extracts of HeLa-Ctn1 cells and was found to be inde-
pendent of cell-cycle phase (Supplementary Figure S4 
at http://www.biolcell.org/boc/103/boc1030055add. 
htm). 
We next addressed whether endogenous Ctn2 could 
associate with CDC25B using GST (glutathione 
transferase)-tagged recombinant CDC25B incubated 
with HeLa or U2OS cell protein extracts. As shown 
in Figure 4, both WT and the catalytically inact-
ive (C487S) full-length GST-tagged CDC25B pulled 
down endogenous Ctn2, whereas GST alone did not. 
Finally, to determine whether CDC25B could bind 
Ctn1, Ctn2 or Ctn3 directly, we incubated the full-
length GST−CDC25B WT or C487S fusion pro-
teins with in vitro translated 
35 S-labelled Ctn1, Ctn2 
or Ctn3. However, we failed to pull down any Ctn 
isoform with CDC25B (Supplementary Figure S5 </p>

<p>at http://www.biolcell.org/boc/103/boc1030055add. 
htm; results not shown). In agreement with this res-
ult, small peptides encoding putative Ctn-binding 
domains (Charbonnier et al., 2006; Yang et al., 2006; 
Azimzadeh et al., 2009) from within CDC25B failed 
to bind Ctn2 (S. Miron, personal communication). 
Together, these results indicate that CDC25B and 
Ctn proteins are within very close proximity at the 
centrosome (Figure 3 and Supplementary Figure S3) 
and can be found in the same protein complex (Fig-
ure 4 and Supplementary Figures S4 and S5), they are 
likely to associate via an indirect mechanism. </p>

<p>CDC25B is required for centrosome integrity </p>

<p>Since Ctns and CDC25B proteins co-localized and 
associated at the centrosome (Figures 1, 3 and 
4), and the centrosomal localization of CDC25B 
appeared to be dependent on Ctn protein levels (Fig-
ures 1 and 2), we questioned whether the local-
ization of Ctn2 to the centrosome might be sim-
ilarly dependent on CDC25B. We therefore de-
pleted CDC25B from HeLa and U2OS cells by 
siRNA, and examined the centrosomal levels of 
Ctn2. We observed that CDC25B-depleted cells dis-
played a significant loss of Ctn2 from the centro-
some in approx. 30−40% of both HeLa (Figure 5) 
and U2OS (Supplementary Figure S6 at http://www. 
biolcell.org/boc/103/boc1030055add.htm) cells, al-
though no effect on total Ctn2 protein levels were 
detected by Western-blot analyses (Figure 2C). These 
results are consistent with our previous observation 
that CDC25B depletion in HeLa cells results in a 
significant proportion of cells in the G 2 phase dis-
playing only one detectable (or barely detectable) 
Ctn-positive centriole, rather than two (Boutros and 
Ducommun, 2008). 
Since we had previously observed a similar ef-
fect of CDC25B depletion on centrosomal γ -tubulin 
levels (Boutros et al., 2007b), we questioned whether 
CDC25B may have a role in maintaining the over-
all integrity of the centrosome, or the PCM cloud, 
perhaps by controlling the centrosome levels of mul-
tiple centrosome proteins. CDC25B siRNA and sub-
sequent immunofluorescence analyses revealed that 
depletion of CDC25B caused a visible reduction in, or 
a dispersal of, centrosomally localized γ -tubulin [in 
agreement with our previous finding (Boutros et al., 
2007b)], in addition to Nedd1, ninein and PCM1 
proteins, but had no effect on pericentrin (Figure 6). </p>

<p>www.biolcell.org | Volume 103 (2) | Pages 55-68 </p>

<p>
© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>R. Boutros and others </p>

<p>Figure 5 CDC25B and Ctn2 centrosomal localizations are interdependent 
HeLa cells were treated with scrambled control or CDC25B siRNA duplexes for 48 h before immunofluorescence detection of 
CDC25B (CDC25B-S230P) and Ctn. (A) Examples of siRNA-treated cells from which CDC25B was successfully depleted which 
also show a loss of centrosomal Ctn2 (arrows). (B) Percentage of HeLa cells displaying loss of both CDC25B-S230P (CDC25B 
siRNA only) and Ctn2 from the centrosomes. Bars represent means for at least 200 cells counted from three independent 
experiments + − S.D. </p>

<p>In contrast, Ctn2 depletion had no significant effect 
on any of the centrosome proteins examined (Fig-
ure 6). 
Together, these results demonstrate that CDC25B 
forms a tight association with a Ctn2-containing 
complex that is required for CDC25B localization 
to the centrosome. Here, CDC25B plays a role in 
maintaining overall centrosome integrity, probably </p>

<p>by controlling the local levels of key centrosome com-
ponents. </p>

<p>Discussion 
The centrosome duplication cycle must be tightly 
regulated and synchronized with the CDC to ensure 
the accurate segregation of chromosomes among </p>

<p>62 
C The Authors Journal compilation C 2011 Portland Press Limited </p>

<p>© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>A CDC25B−centrin association </p>

<p>Research article </p>

<p>Figure 6 CDC25B depletion causes a loss of centrosome integrity in HeLa cells 
HeLa cells were treated with scrambled control, CDC25B or Ctn2 siRNA duplexes, and co-stained for γ-tubulin (red) and 
4 , 6-diamino-2-phenylindole (DAPI, blue), along with (A) CDC25B (CDC25B-S230P), (B) Ctn2, (C) Nedd1, (D) PCM1, (E) peri-
centrin or (F) ninein (green). </p>

<p>dividing cells. In recent years, a small subset of 
centrosome proteins have been identified as being 
essential for centriole duplication, including PLK4 
(Bettencourt-Dias et al., 2005; Kleylein-Sohn et al., </p>

<p>2007), hSAS-6 (Rodrigues-Martins et al., 2007a, 
2007b), CPAP (Rodrigues-Martins et al., 2007b), 
CP110 (Chen et al., 2002; Kleylein-Sohn et al., 
2007) and Cep135 (Kleylein-Sohn et al., 2007), </p>

<p>www.biolcell.org | Volume 103 (2) | Pages 55-68 </p>

<p>
© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>R. Boutros and others </p>

<p>in addition to CDK2 (Hinchcliffe et al., 1999; 
Meraldi et al., 1999) and γ -tubulin (Ruiz et al., 
1999; Kleylein-Sohn et al., 2007). However, many 
other proteins that are present at the centrosome 
also contribute to centrosome biogenesis. One such 
protein is Ctn, a member of the EF-hand superfamily 
of calcium-binding proteins that is recruited to the 
site of centriole assembly from the very early S phase 
(Klink and Wolniak, 2001; Koblenz et al., 2003; 
Stemm-Wolf et al., 2005; Kleylein-Sohn et al., 
2007), but whose exact role in centriole assembly 
in mammalian cells remains unclear. A number of 
Ctn2-binding partners have been identified to date 
which together suggest that it functions primarily 
through modifying the activities of its binding 
partners. 
At the centrosome, Ctn2 has been shown to asso-
ciate with its highly related EF-hand family member 
CaM, which simultaneously associates with CP110, 
in a high-molecular-mass multiprotein complex, in-
volved in centriole duplication and cytokinesis (Chen 
et al., 2002; Tsang et al., 2006). Two other known 
direct-binding partners for human Ctn2 are involved 
in centrosome duplication. The human homologue of 
the Sfi1 protein, identified in the yeast S. cerevisiae, 
is an essential component of centrosome duplica-
tion and the G 2 −M transition (Kilmartin, 2003; 
Martinez-Sanz et al., 2006). The recently identi-
fied centriole protein hPOC5, which contains Ctn-
binding repeats similar to those found in Sfi1p and 
is recruited to the distal ends of centrioles in the G 2 
phase of the cell cycle, to regulate centriole elongation 
(Azimzadeh et al., 2009). In the nucleus, Ctn2 inter-
acts with the XPC (xeroderma pigmentosa group C 
gene product), which is involved in the early steps 
of NER (nucleotide excision repair) of DNA lesions 
(Araki et al., 2001; Nishi et al., 2005), and enhances 
the XPC-stabilizing activity of a second NER com-
plex protein HR23B via an indirect association (Araki 
et al., 2001). The nuclear pool of Ctn2 is modified by 
the SUMO (small ubiquitin-related modifier) ma-
chinery to regulate its nuclear localization and its 
interaction with XPC (Klein and Nigg, 2009). Nuc-
lear Ctn2 has also been shown to play a role in mRNA 
export, through its interaction with the nucleo-
porin Nup107−160 complex (Resendes et al., 2008). 
Thus, in a fashion similar to CaM, with which it 
shares at least 50% amino acid sequence homology 
(Friedberg, 2006), Ctn2 appears to exert its effect on </p>

<p>centrosome duplication and other cellular processes 
through interactions with other proteins. 
Here, we have investigated the relationship 
between Ctn and the CDC25B phosphatase at the 
centrosome, and found that the depletion of one 
results in the loss of the other protein from the 
centrosome. This appears to be due to a common 
association with an as yet unidentified protein or 
protein complex. The formation of this CDC25B/ 
Ctn-containing complex controls centrosomal con-
centrations of both CDC25B and Ctn2, albeit 
through different mechanisms. CDC25B appears to 
associate with a Ctn-containing complex for target-
ing to the centrosome, where it is involved in reg-
ulating centrosome numbers and microtubule nuc-
leation (Boutros et al., 2007b). Notably, we had ob-
served that CDC25B depletion disrupts the micro-
tubule network by reducing the level of γ -tubulin 
at the centrosome (Boutros et al., 2007b). We now 
observe a loss of other centrosomal components fol-
lowing CDC25B depletion, including Ctn2 itself, 
and a more dispersed organization of PCM1, which is 
required for microtubule anchoring (Dammermann 
and Merdes, 2002). Together, these results suggest 
that the overall integrity of the centrosome is com-
promised in the absence of CDC25B and that the 
associated abnormalities in the microtubule network 
are probably caused by the combined loss or dispersal 
of multiple centrosome proteins required for anchor-
ing and assembling tubulin polymers. 
We have previously observed that CDC25B, along 
with a number of other cell cycle regulators that 
localize to the centrosome, are found predominantly 
around the mother centriole during S and early G 2 
phases of the cell cycle (Boutros and Ducommun, 
2008). Moreover, it has been suggested that the PCM 
promotes the formation of daughter centrioles by 
concentrating γ -tubulin around the mother centriole 
(Dammermann et al., 2004). It is therefore tempting 
to postulate that overexpression of CDC25B, which 
is common in many human cancers (Boutros et al., 
2007a), contributes to a local increase in centrosomal 
levels of Ctn, γ -tubulin, and perhaps other PCM 
components, to promote the assembly of excess cent-
rioles. Indeed, CDC25B overexpression alone is suffi-
cient to cause centrosome overduplication during the 
S phase (Boutros et al., 2007b). 
Our combined results from live cell imagin-
ing and FRET analyses suggest that it may be a </p>

<p> 
C The Authors Journal compilation C 2011 Portland Press Limited </p>

<p>© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>A CDC25B−centrin association </p>

<p>Research article </p>

<p>CDK-cyclin substrate that mediates an indirect as-
sociation between CDC25B and Ctn. The R506L 
substrate-binding mutant of CDC25B failed to in-
teract with Ctn at the centrosome in FRET ana-
lyses, whereas the catalytically inactive C487S form 
of CDC25B could interact with Ctn1. This inter-
action was also true for GST−CDC25B C487S and 
endogenous Ctn2 protein from both HeLa and U2OS 
cells, in pull-down analyses. Our results suggest that 
once at the centrosome, CDC25B must also be cap-
able of binding to its CDK-cyclin substrates to re-
main in close proximity to Ctn. One possibility is 
that CDC25B controls the centrosomal levels of Ctn 
through a CDK-cyclin-mediated phosphorylation of 
Ctn, which protects the protein from recognition by 
the proteasome machinery. Indeed, Ctn2 has been 
shown in vitro to be a CDK substrate (Lutz et al., 
2001). This model would be analogous to CDK2-
cyclin E phosphorylation of centrosomal Mps1 (Kas-
bek et al., 2007). 
Finally, it is possible that the association between 
CDC25B and Ctn requires prior phosphorylation of 
Ctn, since endogenous Ctn was found within the same 
protein complex as CDC25B in both FRET and pull-
down analyses, whereas in vitro translated Ctn could 
not associate with recombinant CDC25B. This is a 
possibility that will require further exploration. 
In the present study, we have identified an as-
sociation between Ctn and a CDC25B-containing 
complex that is involved in maintaining centrosome 
integrity. We propose that CDC25B and Ctn are tar-
geted to the centrosome together in a multiprotein 
complex, where the levels of Ctn and other PCM com-
ponents are regulated at least in part, by CDC25B. 
Excess quantities of these PCM components, includ-
ing Ctn and γ -tubulin, around the mother centri-
ole appear to be sufficient for the formation of ex-
cess daughter centrioles (Dammermann et al., 2004; 
Prosser et al., 2009). Thus, this may be a common 
mechanism by which CDC25B, through its CDK-
cyclin substrates, controls the local concentrations 
of several centrosome proteins to control centrosome 
numbers. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Cell culture </p>

<p>U2OS and HeLa cells obtained from the American Type Cul-
ture Collection were maintained at 37 
• C/5% CO 2 in DMEM 
(Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium) containing 10% fetal calf </p>

<p>serum or serum supreme respectively. HeLa cells stably express-
ing GFP-Ctn1 (HeLa-Ctn1) were kindly given by Dr Michel 
Bornens (Curie Institute) and were maintained in DMEM media 
with 10% fetal calf serum. </p>

<p>Plasmids </p>

<p>For the derivation of mCherry-and mOrange-tagged CDC25B 
variants, single-base mutations C487S and R506L were per-
formed using site-directed mutagenesis (Stratagene). N-and 
C-terminal deletions were created by PCR amplification of the 
region of interest, flanked by HindIII (N-terminal) and BamHI 
(C-terminal) restriction sites. mCherry-and mOrange-tagged 
CDC25B WT, C487S and R506L variants were all cloned as 
HindIII−BamHI inserts into pmCherry-C1 and pmOrange-C1 
vectors respectively. GST and GST-tagged CDC25B variants 
were expressed from pGEX-2T vectors as described previously 
(Gabrielli et al., 1996; Forrest and Gabrielli, 2001). </p>

<p>DNA transfection </p>

<p>For transient transfections of HeLa-Ctn1 cells with mCherry or 
mOrange plasmids for live cell imaging, cells were seeded in two-
well chamber slides 24 h before transfection with 1 μg of DNA 
using JetPEI 
TM reagent (Polyplus-Transfection Inc.), according 
to the manufacturer's instructions, and cells were imaged 20 h 
later. </p>

<p>RNA silencing </p>

<p>siRNA duplexes were transfected into HeLa or U2OS cells us-
ing Lipofectamine 
TM 2000 (Invitrogen), according to the manu-
facturer's instructions. Briefly, cells were seeded into 60-mm-
diameter culture dishes at a density of 300 000 cells per 
plate, and grown for 16 h before transfection with 60 pmol 
of siRNA/0.5 ml for 48 h. Control T12N scramble (Invitro-
gen), CDC25B (Kramer et al., 2004) and Ctn2 (Salisbury et al., 
2002) siRNA duplexes were purchased from Invitrogen, and 
Ctn2 Smart-pool siRNA duplexes were purchased from Dhar-
macon. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence microscopy </p>

<p>For immunofluorescence studies, HeLa or U2OS cells seeded 
on to glass coverslips and treated as indicated in the text were 
fixed either in ice-cold methanol for 5 min, or in 4% (w/v) 
paraformaldehyde at room temperature (21 
• C) for 20 min and 
then permeabilized for 5 min in 0.5% Triton X-100. Cells were 
blocked in 5% serum for 1 h at room temperature before anti-
body incubations. Centrosomal CDC25B was detected using 
the antibody against CDC25B-S230P that has already been de-
scribed (Schmitt et al., 2006). Anti-γ -tubulin (GTU-88) and 
-Chk1 (DCS-310) monoclonal antibodies were purchased from 
Sigma−Aldrich, anti-Ctn2 (N-17) from Santa Cruz Biotechno-
logy and anti-pericentrin from Abcam. The monoclonal antibody 
against Ctn2 and Ctn3 (20H5) was a gift from Dr Jeffrey Salis-
bury (Mayo Clinic, Rochester, NY, U.S.A.), rabbit polyclonal 
antibodies against Nedd1 and PCM1 were gifts from Dr An-
dreas Merdes (CNRS, Toulouse, France) and anti-ninein was a 
gift from Dr Michel Bornens (Curie Institute, Paris, France). Sec-
ondary antibodies labelled with Alexa Fluor 
® 488, 555 or 647 
were purchased from Invitrogen. DNA was visualized using 4 ,6-
diamino-2-phenylindole staining. Images were acquired using </p>

<p>www.biolcell.org | Volume 103 (2) | Pages 55-68 </p>

<p>
© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>R. Boutros and others </p>

<p>an Apotome microscope (Carl Zeiss), and subsequently processed 
using AxioVision or Photoshop software packages. </p>

<p>FRET−FLIM </p>

<p>The light source used in the FRET experiments was a mode-
locked Ti:sapphire laser (Tsunami, model 3941, Spectra-Physics) 
pumped by a 10 W diode laser (Millennia Pro, Spectra-Physics) 
and delivering ultrafast femtosecond pulses of light with a fun-
damental frequency of 80 MHz. A pulsepicker (model 3980, 
Spectra-Physics) was used to reduce the repetition rate to 2 MHz 
to satisfy the requirements of the triggering unit working at 2 
MHz. The experiments were performed at λ = 880 nm, the 
optimal wavelength to excite GFP in multiphoton mode (Chen 
and Periasamy, 2004). The power delivered at the entrance of 
the FLIM optics was 14 mW. 
All images were acquired with a ×60 oil-immersion lens 
(Plan Apo 1.4 NA, IR) mounted on an inverted microscope (Ec-
lipse TE2000E; Nikon) coupled to the FLIM system. In this 
set-up the femtosecond-pulsed laser light is scanned into the 
left camera port of the microscope through the FLIM optics. 
The fluorescence emission is directed back into the detection 
unit through the same camera port and a short-pass filter (λ &lt; 
750 nm). The FLIM unit was composed of two galvano mirrors, 
scanning along the x and y axes, a relay lens to focus the laser 
beam on to the dichroic (with a cut-off at 750 nm), and the streak 
camera (Streakscope C4334, Hamamatsu Photonics) coupled to 
a fast and high-sensitivity CCD (charge-coupled device) camera 
(model C8800-53C, Hamamatsu Photonics). The streak cam-
era consisted of a photocathode surface, a sweep electrode to 
deflect the photoelectrons according to their arrival time, an 
MCP-PMT (microchannel plate-photomultiplier tube) to amp-
lify photoelectrons and a phosphor screen to detect the amplified 
photoelectrons. The images on the phosphor screen were read-
out by the CCD camera (for a comprehensive description of the 
streak-FLIM system, see Krishnan et al., 2003). The images were 
acquired with a lateral resolution of 0.246 nm. For each y posi-
tion in the object, an (x,t) image was produced by recording the 
fluorescence decay during a given time interval (full timescale of 
10 ns with a temporal resolution of 60 ps). Scanning the entire 
optical image in the y-direction results in a stack of (x,t) images 
from which fluorescence decays at each (x,y) position can be ex-
tracted. The intensity image of the object plane was obtained by 
integrating fluorescence intensities over time. The CCD camera 
gain was set to 0 to minimize electronic noise. The MCP-PMT 
gain (6−8) and the exposure time of the CCD (100 ms) were 
adjusted to avoid overexposure of the CCD (max value of 4096 
grey levels). Frame accumulation (up to 20 frames) was used to 
increase the signal/noise ratio. The total acquisition time per 
image ranged from 60 to 80 s (imaging field of 15 μm). 
For each image, average fluorescence decay profiles were calcu-
lated in the region of interest corresponding to the centrosome (4 
or 6 pixels). Then, lifetimes were estimated by fitting these res-
ults with a mono-exponential function using a non-linear least-
squares estimation procedure with <rs id="software-2" type="software">Origin</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">7.5</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Origin- Lab, Northampton, MA, U.S.A</rs>.) or the profile fitting function 
of the Hamamatsu FLIM analysis software. </p>

<p>Statistical and image analyses </p>

<p>All statistical analyses were performed using paired Student's 
t tests and <rs type="software">Microsoft Excel</rs> or <rs type="software">Prism</rs> software packages. Image </p>

<p>analyses were performed using the <rs type="software">Image J</rs> imaging software 
package, as outlined in the Figure legends. </p>

<p>Recombinant protein expression </p>

<p>PGEX-2T and PGEX-2T-CDC25B constructs were transformed 
into Escherichia coli BL21 cells, and protein expression induced by 
0.5 mM IPTG (isopropyl β-D-thiogalactoside) for 4 h at 37 
• C. 
Fusion proteins were extracted by Sarkosyl lysis and affinity-
purified on glutathione-agarose, as described by Gabrielli et al. 
(1996). </p>

<p>In vitro transcription/translation </p>

<p>Ctn1, Ctn2 and Ctn3 ORFs (open reading frames; clones 11074, 
11076 and 11043 respectively) were obtained from the Or-
feome1.1 human DNA library (Open Biosystems). Coupled in 
vitro transcription/translation was performed using the TNT T7 
rabbit reticulocyte lysate system (Promega), following the man-
ufacturer's instructions, and proteins were radiolabelled with 
[ 
35 S]methionine (PerkinElmer). </p>

<p>Pull-down assays </p>

<p>For pull-down assays performed on endogenous Ctn2 protein 
from HeLa or U2OS cell extracts, cells were lysed into NETN 
buffer containing 0.1% SDS, 30 mM NaCl, phosphatase in-
hibitors and protease inhibitors and 5 mg of soluble protein 
extracts incubated with approx. 50 μg of purified GST or 
GST−CDC25B fusion proteins bound to glutathione beads for 
2 h at 4 
• C. Beads were washed five times in lysis buffer and bound 
protein complexes separated on SDS/15% PAGE gels and trans-
ferred to nitrocellulose membranes. For comparison of GST and 
GST−CDC25B fusion protein quantities used in each reaction, 
membranes were stained with Ponceau S before Western-blot 
analyses. 
For pull-down assays performed using in vitro translated 
Ctn proteins, 40 μl (80% of the reaction) in vitro trans-
lated protein was incubated with approx. 50 μg purified GST 
or GST−CDC25B recombinant proteins bound to glutathione 
beads, in NETN lysis buffer on a rotor at 4 
• C for 6 h. Beads were 
washed five times in NETN buffer and once in PBS. Bound pro-
tein complexes were separated on SDS/12.5% PAGE gels. The 
gels were Coomassie Brilliant Blue-stained, dried and exposed 
to a phosphorimager. </p>

<p>Co-immunoprecipitation assays </p>

<p>Soluble protein extracts were prepared by lysing cell pellets in 
1 mM Tris (pH 6.8) containing 0.1% saponin, in the presence 
of phosphatase and protease inhibitors. A 5 mg portion of pro-
tein extract was pre-cleared by incubation with Protein G or A 
Sepharose beads for 2 h on a rotary mixer. A 5 mg portion of 
GFP or CDC25B antibodies were incubated on ice for 30 min 
with Protein G or A Sepharose respectively before the addition 
of pre-cleared protein extracts. Immunoprecipitation reactions 
were performed overnight at 4 
• C. Beads were washed four times 
with lysis buffer and immunoprecipitated proteins eluted, separ-
ated on SDS/12.5% PAGE gels and transferred to nitrocellulose 
membranes for Western-blot analyses. </p>

<p> 
C The Authors Journal compilation C 2011 Portland Press Limited </p>

<p>© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>A CDC25B−centrin association </p>

<p>Research article </p>

<p>Western-blot analyses </p>

<p>Cell pellets were resuspended into lysis buffer containing 50 mM 
Tris (pH 7.5), 150 mM sodium chloride, 1% deoxycholic acid, 
1% SDS, 1% NP40 (Nonidet P40), 1 mM dithiothreitol and 
phosphatase and protease inhibitors, and sonicated. Proteins 
were separated on SDS/12.5−15% PAGE gels and transferred 
on to nitrocellulose membranes. Western-blot analyses were 
performed with antibodies against phosphorylated CDC25B 
(CDC25B-S230P; Schmitt et al., 2006), total CDC25B (C-20) 
from Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Ctn2 (N-17) from Santa Cruz 
Biotechnology, α-tubulin (B-5-1-2) and γ -tubulin (GTU-88) 
from Sigma−Aldrich, and GFP from Roche. Secondary anti-
bodies conjugated with horseradish peroxidase were purchased 
from Zymed. </p>

<p>Author contribution 
Rose Boutros, Bernard Ducommun, Corinne 
Lorenzo and Brian Gabrielli designed and con-
ceived the experiments. Odile Mondesert and 
Christine Dozier cloned the CDC25B mutants. 
Odile Mondesert performed live-cell imaging 
on these, and, together with Corinne Lorenzo 
and Alain Jauneau, performed the FRET ana-
lyses. Vanessa Oakes assisted Rose Boutros with 
in vitro translation of Ctn proteins. Rose Boutros per-
formed all other experiments and wrote the first draft 
of the manuscript. All other authors contributed to 
the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements 
We are sincerely grateful to Dr Megan Chircop for 
critical reading of this manuscript prior to submis-
sion. We thank Dr Michel Bornens (Curie Insti-
tute) for the HeLa-Ctn1 cell line and the ninein 
polyclonal antibody, Dr Andreas Merdes (CNRS, 
Toulouse, France) for the Nedd1 and PCM1 poly-
clonal antibodies and Dr Jeffrey Salisbury (Mayo 
Clinic, Rochester NY, U.S.A.) for the Ctn 20H5 
monoclonal antibody. </p>

<p>Funding 
Work in the Ducommun laboratory was supported 
by Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, 
l'Université Paul Sabatier, la région Midi-Pyrénées, 
le Cancéropôle Grand-Sud-Ouest and la Ligue Na-
tionale Contre le Cancer (Equipe labellisée 2005 and 
2008). Work in the Gabrielli laboratory was suppor-
ted by the National Health and Medical Research 
Council (NHMRC) Australia. R.B. is a recipient of a 
CJ Martin post-doctoral training fellowship from the 
NHMRC Australia. </p>



<p>www.biolcell.org | Volume 103 (2) | Pages 55-68 </p>

<p>
© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>R. Boutros and others </p>



<p>Received 9 September 2010/19 November 2010; accepted 23 November 2010 </p>

<p>Published as Immediate Publication 23 November 2010, doi:10.1042/BC20100111 </p>

<p> 
C The Authors Journal compilation C 2011 Portland Press Limited </p>

<p>© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Biol. Cell (2011) 103, 55-68 (Printed in Great Britain) doi:10.1042/BC20100111 </p>

<p>Supplementary online data </p>

<p>CDC25B associates with a centrin 2-containing complex and 
is involved in maintaining centrosome integrity </p>

<p>Rose Boutros* † 
1 , Corinne Lorenzo † ‡, Odile Mondesert † ‡, Alain Jauneau , Vanessa Oakes*, Christine Dozier † ‡, </p>

<p>Brian Gabrielli* and Bernard Ducommun † ‡ § </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>*Diamantina Institute, Princess Alexandra Hospital, The University of Queensland, Brisbane, Australia,  †Université de Toulouse, LBCMCP, </p>

<p>118 route de Narbonne, F-31062 Toulouse, France,  ‡Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (CNRS), LBCMCP-UMR5088, F-31062 </p>

<p>Toulouse, France, CNRS, Plateforme Imagerie, Pôle de Biotechnologie Végétale, F-31320 Castanet Tolosan, France, and  §CHU Purpan, </p>

<p>Service d'Hématologie, TSA 40031, F-31059 Toulouse, France </p>

<p>See the pages that follow for Supplementary Figures S1-S6. </p>

<p>1 Correspondence may be addressed to either of these authors at Centre Pierre 
Potier, ITAV − UMS3039 CRT-CIV, 141 route d'Espagne, BP 50624, 31106 
Toulouse Cedex 1, France and Children's Medical Research Institute, The 
University of Sydney, 214 Hawkesbury Road, Westmead, NSW 2145, Australia 
(email bernard.ducommun@itav-recherche.fr or rboutros@cmri.org.au). </p>

<p>www.biolcell.org | Volume 103 (2) | Pages 55-68 </p>

<p>© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>R. Boutros and others </p>

<p>Figure S1 Ctn depletion causes loss of CDC25B from the centrosome in U2OS cells 
U2OS cells were treated with control or Ctn2 siRNA duplexes for 48 h before immunofluorescence detection of Ctn (green) 
and CDC25B (CDC25B-S230P, red) as in Figure 2(A). Examples of Ctn2-depleted cells demonstrating a loss of centrosomal 
CDC25B in some cells (arrows), in comparison with cells treated with control siRNA duplexes. (B) Percentage of U2OS cells in 
which CDC25B-S230P and Ctn2 (Ctn2 siRNA only) were not detectable or substantially diminished from the centrosomes. Bars 
represent means for at least 200 cells counted from three independent experiments + − S.D. </p>

<p>C The Authors Journal compilation C 2011 Portland Press Limited </p>

<p>© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>A CDC25B−centrin association </p>

<p>Figure S2 Ctn depletion does not affect the centrosomal 
localization of Chk1 
HeLa cells were treated with control or Ctn2 siRNA duplexes 
as in Figure 2 of the main paper before immunofluorescence 
detection of Ctn and Chk1. Percentages of HeLa cells in which 
Chk1 was not detectable or substantially diminished at the 
centrosomes are shown. Bars represent means for at least 
200 cells counted from six independent experiments, per-
formed using either Smartpool (Dharmacon) or custom (11) 
Ctn2 siRNA duplexes (+ − S.D.). </p>

<p>www.biolcell.org | Volume 103 (2) | Pages 55-68 </p>

<p>© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>R. Boutros and others </p>

<p>Figure S3 Raw FRET-FLIM data showing reduced GFP-Ctn1 fluorescence lifetime when co-expressed with WT but not 
R506L mutant mOrange-CDC25B 
(A) Lifetime distributions of GFP-Ctn with or without co-expression of mOrange constructs, comparing the fluorescence lifetime 
distributions of control HeLa-Ctn1 cells (GFP-Ctn1 fluorescence) with cells expressing the various mOrange control and fusion 
proteins. Each histogram represents the total number of cells displaying each fluorescence lifetime value, with the fluorescence 
mean lifetime shift due to FRET being clearly evident with co-expression of the mOrange-CDC25B. (B) Fluorescence decay 
curve for GFP-Ctn corresponding to the centrosome region, without (orange line) or with co-expression of mOrange (yellow 
triangles), mOrange-CDC25B (green line) or mOrange-CDC25BR506L (blue line) fusion proteins. </p>

<p>C The Authors Journal compilation C 2011 Portland Press Limited </p>

<p>© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>A CDC25B−centrin association </p>

<p>Figure S4 CDC25B and Ctn1 co-immunoprecipitate 
Endogenous CDC25B was immunoprecipitated (IP) from soluble protein extracts from asynchronous, G 1 , S and G 2 /M cell 
populations, using Protein G Sepharose in the presence (+) or absence ( − ) of IgG. Western blots (WB) were performed using 
anti-CDC25B and -GFP antibodies. </p>

<p>www.biolcell.org | Volume 103 (2) | Pages 55-68 </p>

<p>© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>R. Boutros and others </p>

<p>Figure S5 CDC25B does not interact directly with Ctn1, Ctn2 or Ctn3 
GST or GST-full-length WT CDC25B (WT FL 25B) fusion proteins produced in bacteria were bound to GST beads and incubated 
with recombinant in vitro translated [ 
35 S]methionine-incorporated Ctn1, Ctn2, Ctn3 or luciferase (Lucif.) proteins prepared using </p>

<p>rabbit reticulocyte extracts. Luciferase was used as positive control and a no DNA ( − DNA) reaction was included as a negative 
control. Proteins attached to the GST beads were denatured and separated by SDS/PAGE. Gels were Coomassie Brilliant 
Blue-stained (Coomassie, lower gel) and then dried on to blotting paper and exposed to a phosphorimaging screen for a 
maximum of 2 weeks ( 
35 S signal, upper gel). </p>

<p>C The Authors Journal compilation C 2011 Portland Press Limited </p>

<p>© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>A CDC25B−centrin association </p>

<p>Figure S6 CDC25B depletion causes loss of Ctn from the centrosome in U2OS cells 
U2OS cells were treated with scrambled control or CDC25B siRNA duplexes as in Figure 5 of the main text. (A) Examples 
of siRNA-treated cells from which CDC25B was successfully depleted, which also show a loss of centrosomal Ctn2 (arrows). 
(B) Percentage of HeLa cells displaying loss of both CDC25B-S230P (CDC25B siRNA only) and Ctn2 from the centrosomes. 
Bars represent means for at least 200 cells counted from three independent experiments + − S.D. </p>

<p>Received 9 September 2010/19 November 2010; accepted 23 November 2010 </p>

<p>Published as Immediate Publication 23 November 2010, doi:10.1042/BC20100111 </p>

<p>www.biolcell.org | Volume 103 (2) | Pages 55-68 </p>

<p>© 2010 The Author(s) </p>

<p>The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

</text></tei>