<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3825938" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective To investigate compliance with a viscosity-modified diet among Korean dysphagic patients and to 
determine which factors are associated with compliance. 
Methods We retrospectively reviewed medical records of patients who had been recommended to use thickeners 
in the previous videofluoroscopic swallowing study (VFSS). Among 68 patients, 6 were excluded because tube 
feeding was required due to deterioration in their medical condition. Finally, 62 patients were included in the 
study. Patient compliance was assessed using their medical records by checking whether he or she had maintained 
thickener use until the next VFSS. To determine which factors affect compliance, the relationship between 
thickener use and patient characteristics, such as sex, age, inpatient/outpatient status, severity of dysphagia, 
aspiration symptoms, follow-up interval of VFSS, and current swallowing therapy status were assessed. For non-
compliers, reasons for not using thickeners were investigated by telephone interview. 
Results Among 62 patients, 35 (56.5%) were compliers, and 27 (43.5%) were noncompliers. Eighteen (90%) of 20 
inpatients had followed previous recommendations; however, only 17 (40.5%) of 42 outpatients had been using 
thickeners. Of patient characteristics, only admission status was significantly correlated with compliance. When 
asked about the reason why they had not used thickeners, noncompliers complained about dissatisfaction with 
texture and taste, greater difficulty in swallowing, and inconvenience of preparing meals. 
Conclusion Among Korean dysphagic patients, compliance with a viscosity-modified liquid diet was only about 
50%. Betterments of texture and taste along with patient education might be necessary to improve compliance 
with thickener use. </p>

<p>The term "dysphagia" is applied to all kinds of swallow-
ing difficulties. The condition is clinically common and 
can be attributed to various diseases including disorders 
of the central nervous system, such as stroke and trau-
matic brain injury, neurodegenerative diseases, such as 
Parkinson disease and Alzheimer disease, disorders of </p>

<p>Received April 9, 2013; Accepted May 28, 2013 
Corresponding author: Tai Ryoon Han 
Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Seoul National University 
College of Medicine, 103 Daehak-ro, Jongno-gu, Seoul 110-799, Korea 
Tel: +82-2-2072-2925, Fax: +82-2-743-7473, E-mail: tairyoon@snu.ac.kr </p>

<p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons. 
org/licenses/by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted noncommercial use, 
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is 
properly cited. </p>

<p>Copyright © 2013 by Korean Academy of Rehabilitation Medicine </p>

<p>Compliance With Viscosity-Modified Diet </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>the peripheral nervous system, neuromuscular junction 
disorders, myopathies, and local anatomical lesions [1]. 
Major complications of dysphagia are pneumonia, mal-
nutrition, dehydration, and increased mortality. These 
complications bring about the increased need of medical 
resources in terms of the length of hospital stay, rehabili-
tation time, the need for long-term care assistance, and 
health care cost [2]. 
Altering the characteristics of food is one of the com-
mon approaches used to treat and compensate dyspha-
gia [3]. Size, color, shape, taste, viscosity, and texture are 
components of the characteristics of food. In general, 
thin fluid, such as water, soup, or juice is more likely to be 
aspirated [4]; therefore, thickening fluid using thickeners 
is the mainstay of dysphagia diet [5]. One study of 66 dys-
phagic patients documented that thickened fluid and soft 
mechanical diet reduced the incidence of pneumonia by 
80% compared with a regular diet [6]. 
Despite these advantages, many patients and caregiv-
ers are reluctant to make modifications to the diet. It has 
been demonstrated that 75% of the patients who were 
recommended to modify diet with thickeners did not 
prefer using them [7]. According to a study in the United 
States, there was a disjunction between the expecta-
tions of medical staffs and what patients are really doing. 
Speech-language pathologists expected a higher compli-
ance of 72%; however, only 36% patients followed their 
instructions on thickener use [8]. </p>

<p>No study has documented, however, the level of com-
pliance with a viscosity-modified diet in Korea. The pur-
poses of the present study were to examine compliance 
with a viscosity-modified diet among Korean dysphagic 
patients and to evaluate relevant factors affecting compli-
ance. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Subjects 
A retrospective chart review was performed in Seoul 
National University Hospital, a university-affiliated ter-
tiary care hospital. From June 1 to September 30, 2011, a 
total of 349 patients underwent a videofluoroscopic swal-
lowing study (VFSS). We included only those who had 
been recommended thickener use in fluids in the previ-
ous VFSS within 6 months (Fig. 1). Among 349 patients, 
modified diet including thickened liquids was prescribed </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic and clinical data of study partici-
pants (n=62) 
Characteristic 
Value 
Age (mean) 
64.1 
Sex 
Male 
38 (61.3) 
Female 
24 (38.7) 
Follow-up interval (day) 
55.7 
Duration of dysphagia 
&lt;3 mo 
21 
3 mo to 1 yr 
28 
&gt;1 yr 
13 
Diagnosis 
Brain lesion 
31 (50.0) 
Ischemic lesion 
12 
Hemorrhagic lesion 
11 
Brain tumor 
8 
Deconditioning 
8 (12.9) 
Neuromuscular disease 
6 (9.7) 
Neurodegenerative disease 
5 (8.1) 
Local structural lesion 
4 (6.5) 
Others 
8 (12.9) 
Compliance 
Compliant 
35 (56.5) 
Noncompliant 
27 (43.5) 
Values are presented as number (%). 
Fig. 1. Flow chart of the study design. </p>

<p>Jae Seong Shim, et al. </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>in 68 patients. Among those, 6 required nasogastric tube 
feeding due to the development or deterioration of their 
medical condition. Finally, 62 dysphagic subjects were 
included in the analysis. 
Demographic and clinical data of study subjects are 
shown in Table 1. The mean age at VFSS was 64.1 years. 
The mean interval time between the studies was 55.7 
days on average, and half of the patients had dysphagia 
secondary to brain lesion, such as stroke or brain tumor. </p>

<p>Medical chart review and interview 
Through medical chart review, data on age, sex, diag-
nosis, admission status (outpatient or inpatient), current 
diet, recommended diet regimen in the previous VFSS, 
videofluoroscopic dysphagia scale (VDS) [9], symptoms 
of aspiration, and current status in swallowing therapy 
were identified. At our institution, just before the VFSS, 
all patients or caregivers are routinely asked about the 
current diet and whether they have maintained the use 
of thickeners or not. Compliance was defined as using 
thickeners in liquids, such as water and juice. Accord-
ingly, patients were categorized into two groups: compli-
ant and noncompliant. Furthermore, we analyzed factors 
affecting compliance among the clinical characteristics 
of study subjects including sex, age, admission status, 
prescribed viscosity level, interval between swallowing 
studies, presence of aspiration symptoms, severity of dys-
phagia in VDS, and current status of swallowing therapy. 
For patients in the noncompliant group, the reasons 
for cessation of thickener use and, if any, his or her own 
compensatory maneuvers were assessed by phone inter-</p>

<p>view. For each question, multiple answers were allowed. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
All statistical analyses were performed with the <rs id="software-0" type="software">PASW</rs> 
Statistics ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">18</rs> for Windows software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chica-
go, IL, USA). To decide which factors are associated with 
compliance among patient characteristics, chi-square 
tests and univariate logistic regression analyses were 
used for categorical variables and continuous variables, 
respectively. In multiple logistic regression analysis, 
variables showing p&lt;0.2 in the univariate analysis were 
included. For multiple analysis, the stepwise forward 
procedure was used for variable entry. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Among 62 patients, 35 (56.5%) had been using thicken-
ers in liquids; however, 27 (43.5%) had been drinking 
thin fluids. Consequently, the overall compliance rate for 
viscosity modification was 56.5%. Twenty subjects were 
inpatients at the time of follow-up VFSS, and 18 (90%) of 
20 were compliant. On the contrary, among a total of 42 
outpatients, 17 (40.5%) were following the recommenda-
tions. Thus, the admission status (inpatient or outpatient) 
proved to be significantly associated with compliance 
(p=0.001) (Fig. 2). However, compliance was not shown 
to be significantly correlated with following factors: sex, 
age, prescribed viscosity level, interval between swal-
lowing studies, presence of aspiration symptoms, and 
severity of dysphagia in VDS. A trend toward higher com-
pliance in those currently receiving swallowing therapy 
was observed; however, the difference was insignificant 
(p=0.108; odds ratio, 2.86). Finally, admission status and 
current swallowing therapy status were included in the 
multiple logistic regression model. In the analysis, com-
pliance was shown to be significantly associated with </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Compliance difference between outpatients and 
inpatients. Outpatients showed lower compliance than 
inpatients (n=62). </p>

<p>Table 2. Reason for noncompliance (total 10 patients) </p>

<p>Reason for noncompliance 
Number of 
response 
Dissatisfaction with texture 
4 
Dissatisfaction with taste 
4 
Difficulty in preparation 
2 
Difficulty in swallowing 
2 
Dyspepsia 
1 
Doubt in effect 
1 </p>

<p>Compliance With Viscosity-Modified Diet </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>admission status (p=0.004); however, no correlation was 
found between compliance and current application of 
swallowing therapy (p=0.532). 
Among the noncompliant, ten patients responded to 
the interview regarding the reasons for not using thick-
eners, whereas the others were not available as a result 
of phone connection failure, no answer, death, etc. Re-
sponses included dissatisfaction with texture (4 patients), 
dissatisfaction with taste (4 patients), difficulty in prepa-
ration (2 patients), and greater difficulty in swallowing 
(2 patients) (Table 2). Concerning compensatory ma-
neuvers, 2 patients answered that they swallow fluids by 
splitting in small amounts using a straw or a spoon. One 
patient said, "I eat in the chin-tuck position." Another 
patient said, "I use glutinous rice flour to thicken fluids 
rather than commercialized thickeners." </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This is the first study demonstrating compliance with a 
viscosity-modified diet in Korean dysphagic patients. The 
overall compliance for fluid-thickening was 56.5%, and 
this finding is in close agreement with those of previous 
studies from other countries documenting compliance 
with a dysphagia diet [8,10,11]. According to one study 
in New Zealand [10], 18 (21%) out of 86 patients with 
dysphagia were never compliant with fluid-thickeners, 
whereas the other 68 patients (79%) sometimes or always 
followed the prescribed dietary regimen. Even though 
compliance in their study is higher than that of the pres-
ent study, the difference may arise from the distinct 
definition of compliance in each study. Another study in 
the United Kingdom found that 48% of the patients com-
plied with the recommendations of speech and language 
therapists [11]. In another study in the United States, 
only 36% maintained thickener use [8]. Compliance in 
these studies was lower compared to that in the present 
study. However, these studies were conducted among 
outpatients. Among outpatients of the present study, we 
observed markedly similar compliance. 
Admission status was the only factor which was proven 
to be associated with compliance. Other variables in-
cluding age, sex, aspiration symptoms, and even current 
swallowing therapy status did not significantly affect 
compliance. According to the previous studies, however, 
younger and institutionalized patients were more likely </p>

<p>to be noncompliant. In the study, the authors comment-
ed that such an unexpected age difference appears to be 
caused by a survival effect which reflects higher mortal-
ity among noncompliant older people. Furthermore, 
persons who live in community facilities usually do not 
prepare their meals by themselves, thus leading to higher 
levels of compliance due to passivity [10]. The results of 
the present study which demonstrated inpatients' higher 
compliance correspond with this finding. We expected 
that patients who maintained swallowing therapy until 
the follow-up VFSS would be more compliant, and the re-
sults were in close agreement with this prediction; how-
ever, the difference did not reach statistical significance. 
This warrants a further study with a larger sample size. 
Regarding the reasons for not using thickeners, many 
patients complained of dissatisfaction with texture and 
taste (4 patients each). Some patients reported that pre-
paring a dysphagia diet is inconvenient, or reported ag-
gravation of swallowing difficulty with thickener use. Ac-
cording to a previous study concerning noncompliance 
with swallowing recommendations, dissatisfaction with 
diet modifications was reported by all participants, fol-
lowed by open denial, calculated risk, and minimization, 
in order of frequency [12]. 
The most commonly used methods to deal with patient 
noncompliance with diet modifications are education 
and involvement of others [12]. One intervention study 
demonstrated a significant improvement in compliance 
with thickener use (48% to 64%) after having the partici-
pants undergo a program based on an in-house training 
scheme and pre-thickened drinks [11]. In the present 
study, clinical dietitians provided a structured education-</p>

<p>Table 3. Structured educational program for dysphagic 
patients and caregivers 
Educational 
item 
Detail </p>

<p>Subject 
Patient and caregiver 
Educator 
Clinical dietitian 
Operation place Bedside 
Duration 
10-15 minutes 
Content 
Definition and need for modified diet 
How to use thickener 
Lists of allowed and prohibited food 
Chin tuck maneuver </p>

<p>Jae Seong Shim, et al. </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>al program for all the inpatients and some outpatients 
(Table 3, Fig. 3). Therefore this may be the reason for the 
difference in compliance between outpatients and inpa-
tients. The result opens the possibility of further investi-
gations concerning the effects of educational programs 
on compliance. 
This study has important limitations that mostly stem 
from its small sample size and retrospective design. First, 
the evaluation of compliance depended on the patients' 
recollection. Even though we should acknowledge the ef-
ficiency of this design since we cannot practically moni-
tor all the patients, there exist possibilities of recall bias, 
lie and false response. Second, compliance was assessed 
dichotomously only. In further research, it can be sub-
divided into many grades. Additionally, utilization of a 
prospective design in future studies may increase the re-
sponse rate for the reasons of noncompliance and com-
pensatory maneuvers. 
In conclusion, among Korean dysphagic patients, com-
pliance with a viscosity-modified liquid diet was found to 
be only about 50%. Betterments of texture and taste along 
with patient education might be necessary to improve 
compliance with thickener use. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article 
was reported. </p>



<p>Fig. 3. Examples of modified diet. 
(A) Liquids with honey-like vis-
cosity and mechanically altered 
solids. (B) Liquids with nectar-like 
viscosity and pureed solids. </p>

</text></tei>