<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3664701" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T14:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Phosphatidylinositol-4,5-bisphosphate (PIP 2 ), which constitutes 1% of the plasma membrane phospholipid, 
plays a key role in membrane-delimited signaling. PIP 2 regulates structurally and functionally diverse membrane 
proteins, including voltage-and ligand-gated ion channels, inwardly rectifying ion channels, transporters, and re-
ceptors. In some cases, the regulation is known to involve specific lipid-protein interactions, but the mechanisms 
by which PIP 2 regulates many of its various targets remain to be fully elucidated. Because many PIP 2 targets are 
membrane-spanning proteins, we explored whether the phosphoinositides might alter bilayer physical properties 
such as curvature and elasticity, which would alter the equilibrium between membrane protein conformational 
states-and thereby protein function. Taking advantage of the gramicidin A (gA) channels' sensitivity to changes 
in lipid bilayer properties, we used gA-based fluorescence quenching and single-channel assays to examine the 
effects of long-chain PIP 2 s (brain PIP 2 , which is predominantly 1-stearyl-2-arachidonyl-PIP 2 , and dioleoyl-PIP 2 ) on 
bilayer properties. When premixed with dioleoyl-phosphocholine at 2 mol %, both long-chain PIP 2 s produced 
similar changes in gA channel function (bilayer properties); when applied through the aqueous solution, however, 
brain PIP 2 was a more potent modifier than dioleoyl-PIP 2 . Given the widespread use of short-chain dioctanoyl-
phosphoinositides, we also examined the effects of diC 8 -phosphoinositol (PI), PI(4,5)P 2 , PI(3,5)P 2 , PI(3,4)P 2 , and 
PI(3,4,5)P 3 . The diC 8 phosphoinositides, except for PI(3,5)P 2 , altered bilayer properties with potencies that de-
creased with increasing head group charge. Nonphosphoinositide diC 8 phospholipids generally were more potent 
bilayer modifiers than the polyphosphoinositides. These results show that physiological increases or decreases in 
plasma membrane PIP 2 levels, as a result of activation of PI kinases or phosphatases, are likely to alter lipid bilayer 
properties, in addition to any other effects they may have. The results further show that exogenous PIP 2 , as well as 
structural analogues that differ in acyl chain length or phosphorylation state, alters lipid bilayer properties at the 
concentrations used in many cell physiological experiments . </p>



<p>Phosphoinositides alter lipid bilayer properties </p>

<p>analogues alter bilayer properties and, if so, to parse out 
which bilayer properties are affected. 
Many different probes have been used to character-
ize the changes in bilayer properties that are caused by 
drugs and other amphiphiles (Seddon et al., 2009). For 
the present studies, we used gramicidin A (gA) channels 
as probes that serve as prototypical bilayer-spanning 
proteins, which experience minimal interference from 
specific lipid-protein interactions. gA channels form by 
the transmembrane dimerization of nonconducting mo-
nomeric subunits residing in apposing bilayer leaflets 
(O'Connell et al., 1990). Channel formation is associated 
with a local bilayer compression (Elliott et al., 1983;  Huang, 1986; Harroun et al., 1999), which makes gA 
channels sensitive to changes in bilayer properties 
(Andersen et al., 2007; Lundbaek et al., 2010a,b). 
Using gA channels as probes, we have explored the 
effects of phosphoinositides on lipid bilayers while vary-
ing the method by which membrane PIP 2 was manipu-
lated, the acyl chain composition, and the number and 
posi tions of phosphate groups on the inositol ring (Fig. 1). 
For comparison, we also examined the bilayer-perturbing 
effects of other related short-chain phospholipids. 
Our results show that increasing or decreasing the 
mole percentage of long-chain PIP 2 in the plasma mem-
brane results in altered lipid bilayer properties. Both 
long-and short-chain phosphoinositides, as well as non-
phosphoinositide short-chain phospholipids, are bilay er-
modifying agents. </p>

<p>M A T E R I A L S A N D M E T H O D S </p>

<p>Materials 
All phospholipids were purchased from Avanti Polar Lipids, Inc., ex-
cept for diC 8 PI (1,2-dioctanoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphoinositol), which 
was purchased from Echelon Biosciences (Fig. 1). The diC 8 phospho-
lipid stock solutions were 5 mM in water, except for the diC 8 PE 
stock solution, which was 5 mM in ethanol (Pharmco-AAPER). 
The long-chain PIP 2 s were 1,2-dioleoyl-sn-glycero-3-phospho-
(1-myo-inositol-4,5-bisphosphate) and the porcine brain extract 
of PIP 2 , which is 80% C 18/20:4 PIP 2 . To make aqueous "solutions" 
of diC 18:1 and brain PIP 2 , the powder was suspended in H 2 O. The 
suspension was sonicated in an ultrasonic homogenizer (model 
300 V/T; Biologics Inc.) for 30 min on ice at 90% power and 90% 
duty cycle using 1-s pulses. The resuspended long-chain phos-
phoinositides were flash frozen and stored at 40°C in a glass vial. 
To make DC 18:1 PC (1,2-dioleoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine)/ 
PIP 2 lipid mixtures, the long-chain PIP 2 was dissolved in chloro-
form (Honeywell Burdick and Jackson) and mixed with DC 18:1 PC 
in chloroform at the appropriate mole percentage. Chloroform was 
evaporated under N 2 , and the mixture was suspended in n-decane 
(Sigma-Aldrich). 8-Aminonaphthalene-1,3,6-trisulfonate (ANTS) 
was purchased from Invitrogen. For the single-channel experi-
ments, we used a 15-amino acid analogue, [Ala </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>]gA (AgA(15)), a 
chain-shortened 13-amino acid gA analogue of opposite helix 
sense, des-d-Val-Gly-gA 
 (gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13)), and a 15-amino acid analogue 
in which the NH groups on the four Trp residues are methylated, 
[Val  1 ,N-Me-Trp  9,11,13,15 ]gA (N-Me-gA(15)); they were synthesized 
and purified as described previously (Greathouse et al., 1999). For 
the fluorescence assay, we used the natural mixture of gramicidins </p>

<p>2007)-and local PIP 2 concentrations may be even higher 
(Wang and Richards, 2012). Given the lack of a clear 
mechanism for many of the PIP 2 -mediated effects, it thus 
becomes important to explore whether changes in ex-
tant, or exogenously applied, PIP 2 s alter bilayer properties 
at relevant concentrations, in which case some of PIP 2 's 
effects may be caused by nonspecific bilayer-mediated 
mechanisms, as recently was proposed in the case of inver-
tebrate phototransduction (Hardie and Franze, 2012). 
Bilayer-spanning proteins are energetically coupled 
to the host lipid bilayer through hydrophobic interac-
tions between the transmembrane domains and the lipid 
bilayer hydrophobic core, which can influence the lipid 
packing around the protein (Killian et al., 1989, 1996)  or the protein conformation (Keller et al., 1993; Brown,  1994; Greathouse et al., 1994). This lipid reorganization 
(bilayer deformation) has an associated energetic cost, 
the bilayer deformation energy (G def ). If protein con-
formational changes (e.g., from state I to state II) alter 
the local lipid bilayer deformations, the resulting differ-
ence in the bilayer deformation energy, </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆ </p>

<p>I II 
bilayer </p>

<p>G 
, be-
comes the bilayer contribution to the total free energy 
of the conformational transition </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆ </p>

<p>I II 
total </p>

<p>( 
) 
G 
(Nielsen and  Andersen, 2000; Andersen and Koeppe, 2007; Lundbaek  et al., 2010a): </p>

<p>→ 
→ </p>

<p>→ 
→ </p>

<p>⎧ 
⎫ 
∆ 
= 
= 
− 
= 
⎨ 
⎬ 
⎩ 
⎭ </p>

<p>⎧ 
⎫ 
∆ 
+ ∆ 
⎪ 
⎪ 
− 
⎨ 
⎬ 
⎪ 
⎪ 
⎩ 
⎭ </p>

<p>I II 
I II 
total 
II </p>

<p>I 
B </p>

<p>I II 
I II 
protein 
bilayer </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>exp </p>

<p>exp 
, </p>

<p>G 
n 
K 
n 
k T </p>

<p>G 
G </p>

<p>k T </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>where n I and n II denote the surface densities of the pro-
tein in states I and II, </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆ </p>

<p>I II 
protein </p>

<p>G 
and </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆ </p>

<p>I II 
bilayer </p>

<p>G 
denote the 
protein and bilayer contributions to </p>

<p>2 of 22 
Phosphoinositides alter lipid bilayer properties </p>

<p>conformational equilibrium of membrane proteins. (It 
is given that G def will change, but the changes may or 
may not be sufficient to cause measurable changes in 
protein function.) We therefore set out to determine 
whether PIP 2 and its structural analogues alter bilayer 
properties and, if so, to parse out which bilayer proper-
ties are affected. 
Many different probes have been used to characterize 
the changes in bilayer properties that are caused by 
drugs and other amphiphiles (Seddon et al., 2009). For 
the present studies, we used gramicidin A (gA) chan-
nels as probes that serve as prototypical bilayer-span-
ning proteins, which experience minimal interference 
from specific lipid-protein interactions. gA channels 
form by the transmembrane dimerization of noncon-
ducting monomeric subunits residing in apposing bi-
layer leaflets (O'Connell et al., 1990). Channel 
formation is associated with a local bilayer compression 
(Elliott et al., 1983; Huang, 1986; Harroun et al., 1999), 
which makes gA channels sensitive to changes in bilayer 
properties (Andersen et al., 2007; Lundbaek et al.,  2010a,b). 
Using gA channels as probes, we have explored the 
effects of phosphoinositides on lipid bilayers while vary-
ing the method by which membrane PIP 2 was manipu-
lated, the acyl chain composition, and the number and 
positions of phosphate groups on the inositol ring (Fig. 
1). For comparison, we also examined the bilayer-per-
turbing effects of other related short-chain 
phospholipids. 
Our results show that increasing or decreasing the 
mole percentage of long-chain PIP 2 in the plasma mem-
brane results in altered lipid bilayer properties. Both 
long-and short-chain phosphoinositides, as well as non-
phosphoinositide short-chain phospholipids, are bi-
layer-modifying agents. </p>

<p>M A T E R I A L S A N D M E T H O D S </p>

<p>Materials 
All phospholipids were purchased from Avanti Polar Lipids, Inc., 
except for diC 8 PI (1,2-dioctanoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphoinositol), 
which was purchased from Echelon Biosciences (Fig. 1). The diC 8 
phospholipid stock solutions were 5 mM in water, except for the 
diC 8 PE stock solution, which was 5 mM in ethanol (Pharmco-
AAPER). The long-chain PIP 2 s were 1,2-dioleoyl-sn-glycero-3-
phospho-(1-myo-inositol-4,5-bisphosphate) and the porcine 
brain extract of PIP 2 , which is 80% C 18/20:4 PIP 2 . To make aque-
ous "solutions" of diC 18:1 and brain PIP 2 , the powder was sus-
pended in H 2 O. The suspension was sonicated in an ultrasonic 
homogenizer (model 300 V/T; Biologics Inc.) for 30 min on ice 
at 90% power and 90% duty cycle using 1-s pulses. The resus-
pended long-chain phosphoinositides were flash frozen and 
stored at 40°C in a glass vial. To make DC 18:1 PC (1,2-dioleoyl-sn-
glycero-3-phosphocholine)/PIP 2 lipid mixtures, the long-chain 
PIP 2 was dissolved in chloroform (Honeywell Burdick and Jack-
son) and mixed with DC 18:1 PC in chloroform at the appropriate 
mole percentage. Chloroform was evaporated under N 2 , and the </p>

<p>percentage of PIP 2 in the plasma membrane is likely to 
be &gt;1% (Hilgemann, 2007)-and local PIP 2 concentra-
tions may be even higher (Wang and Richards, 2012). 
Given the lack of a clear mechanism for many of the 
PIP 2 -mediated effects, it thus becomes important to ex-
plore whether changes in extant, or exogenously ap-
plied, PIP 2 s alter bilayer properties at relevant 
concentrations, in which case some of PIP 2 's effects may 
be caused by nonspecific bilayer-mediated mechanisms, 
as recently was proposed in the case of invertebrate 
phototransduction (Hardie and Franze, 2012). 
Bilayer-spanning proteins are energetically coupled 
to the host lipid bilayer through hydrophobic interac-
tions between the transmembrane domains and the 
lipid bilayer hydrophobic core, which can influence the 
lipid packing around the protein (Killian et al., 1989,  1996) or the protein conformation (Keller et al., 1993;  Brown, 1994; Greathouse et al., 1994). This lipid reor-
ganization (bilayer deformation) has an associated en-
ergetic cost, the bilayer deformation energy (G def ). If 
protein conformational changes (e.g., from state I to 
state II) alter the local lipid bilayer deformations, the 
resulting difference in the bilayer deformation energy, 
∆G bilayer </p>

<p>I II 
→ </p>

<p>, becomes the bilayer contribution to the total 
free energy of the conformational transition ( 
) </p>

<p>total </p>

<p>I II </p>

<p>∆G </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>(Nielsen and Andersen, 2000; Andersen and Koeppe, 
2007; Lundbaek et al., 2010a): </p>

<p>n 
n 
K 
G 
k T </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>II </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>I II 
total </p>

<p>I II </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>protein </p>

<p>I II </p>

<p>= 
= 
− 
 
 
 </p>

<p>  </p>

<p> 
 
 </p>

<p>  </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>exp </p>

<p>exp </p>

<p>∆ </p>

<p>∆ 
+ + 
 
 
 </p>

<p>  </p>

<p> 
 
 </p>

<p>  </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆G </p>

<p>k T </p>

<p>bilayer </p>

<p>I II </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>where n I and n II denote the surface densities of the pro-
tein in states I and II, ∆G protein </p>

<p>I II 
→ </p>

<p>and ∆G bilayer </p>

<p>I II 
→ </p>

<p>denote the 
protein and bilayer contributions to ∆G total 
I II , </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>and k B T 
consists of Boltzmann's constant and the temperature 
in Kelvin. Changes in lipid bilayer physical properties, 
which are expressed as changes in ∆G bilayer 
I II , </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>thus will 
alter the protein conformational equilibrium and 
function. 
Amphiphiles modulate lipid bilayer properties by ad-
sorbing to the bilayer-solution interface (Lundbaek et  al., 2010a; Rusinova et al., 2011; Bruno et al., 2013), 
thereby altering the bilayer response to a deformation 
(changing G def and thus G bilayer ). Key bilayer proper-
ties that may be affected by amphiphile adsorption in-
clude the intrinsic curvature, as a result of the altered 
profile of intermolecular interactions along the bilayer 
normal (Seddon, 1990; Cantor, 1997; Andersen and Ko- eppe, 2007; Marsh, 2007), bilayer elasticity (Evans et al.,  1995), lipid disorder, and possibly lipid demixing (Zhe- lev, 1998; Heerklotz, 2002). These amphiphile-medi-
ated changes in bilayer properties in turn may shift the </p>

<p>ROUGH GALLEY PROOF </p>

<p>and k B T con-
sists of Boltzmann's constant and the temperature in 
Kelvin. Changes in lipid bilayer physical properties, which 
are expressed as changes in </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆ </p>

<p>I II </p>

<p>bilayer , 
G 
thus will alter the 
protein conformational equilibrium and function. 
Amphiphiles modulate lipid bilayer properties by ad-
sorbing to the bilayer-solution interface (Lundbaek et al.,  2010a; Rusinova et al., 2011; Bruno et al., 2013), thereby 
altering the bilayer response to a deformation (changing 
G def and thus G bilayer ). Key bilayer properties that may 
be affected by amphiphile adsorption include the intrin-
sic curvature, as a result of the altered profile of intermo-
lecular interactions along the bilayer normal (Seddon,  1990; Cantor, 1997; Andersen and Koeppe, 2007; Marsh,  2007), bilayer elasticity (Evans et al., 1995), lipid disorder, 
and possibly lipid demixing (Zhelev, 1998; Heerklotz,  2002). These amphiphile-mediated changes in bilayer 
properties in turn may shift the conformational equilib-
rium of membrane proteins. (It is given that G def will 
change, but the changes may or may not be sufficient to 
cause measurable changes in protein function.) We there-
fore set out to determine whether PIP 2 and its structural </p>

<p>Rusinova et al. </p>



<p>with the compound to the appearance frequency from a record-
ing right before compound addition. Only recordings lasting 
≥300 s were used to evaluate changes in relative channel appear-
ance frequencies. </p>

<p>Energetics of gA channel formation 
gA in lipid bilayers exists in equilibrium between nonconducting 
monomers and conducting dimeric channels: </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>⎯⎯→ 
+ ←⎯⎯ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>M M 
D, </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>where k 1 and k 1 are the association and dissociation rate con-
stants, respectively. The dimer dissociation rate constant can be 
estimated as 1/, and changes in the association rate constant can 
be estimated from changes in the channel appearance frequency 
because k 1 = f/[M] 
2 . 
The channel's hydrophobic length (l), 2.2 nm for a 15-amino 
acid analogue (Elliott et al., 1983; Huang, 1986), is less than the 
lipid bilayer's unperturbed hydrophobic thickness (d 0 ), 3-4 nm 
(Benz et al., 1975; Lewis and Engelman, 1983; Lundbaek et al.,  2010b), and gA channel formation is associated with a local bi-
layer compression with an associated deformation energy, G def . 
Using the theory of elastic bilayer deformations (Huang, 1986;  Helfrich and Jakobsson, 1990; Dan et al., 1994; Nielsen et al., 1998;  Nielsen and Andersen, 2000; Partenskii and Jordan, 2002; Rusinova  et al., 2011), G def can be expressed as </p>

<p>( 
) 
( 
) </p>

<p>∆ 
= 
× − 
+ 
× − 
× + 
× </p>

<p>2 
2 
def 
B 
0 
X 
0 
0 
C </p>

<p>0 , 
G 
H 
l d 
H 
l d 
c H 
c 
(2) </p>

<p>where c 0 is the intrinsic monolayer curvature and H B , H X , and H C 
are phenomenological elastic coefficients determined by the bilayer 
elastic moduli, the channel radius, and d 0 . The bilayer responds to 
the compression by imposing a disjoining force (F dis ) on the channel, </p>

<p>( 
) 
( 
) </p>

<p>∂∆ 
= − 
= × 
× 
− − 
× 
∂ − </p>

<p>def 
dis 
B 
0 
X 
0 
0 </p>

<p>2 
, 
G 
F 
H 
d l H 
c 
l d </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>from Bacillus brevis (Sigma-Aldrich), which is 80% [Val </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>]gA (Abo- Riziq et al., 2006); the mixture is denoted as gD (for R. Dubos, who 
discovered the gramicidins; Dubos, 1939). </p>

<p>Electrophysiology 
Planar lipid bilayers were formed across a 1.5-mm-diameter aper-
ture in a Teflon partition using DC 18:1 PC or DC 18:1 PC-long-chain 
PIP 2 suspensions in n-decane. The total phospholipid concentra-
tion was the same (15 mg/ml) in the pure and mixed lipid suspen-
sions. The aqueous solution was a 1 M NaCl and 10 mM HEPES, 
pH 7.0, solution; the temperature was 25 ± 1°C. Single-channel 
measurements were performed at 200 mV using a patch clamp am-
plifier (model 3900A; Dagan Corp.) and the bilayer punch method 
(Andersen, 1983). The current signal was filtered at 5 kHz, sam-
pled at 20 kHz, and digitally filtered at 500 Hz. After the bilayer was 
formed, gA analogues of different lengths and helix senses were 
added to both sides of the bilayer, and the solutions were stirred 
for 5 min (in a few experiments, only N-Me-gA(15) was added). 
After 30 min, to allow for gA incorporation, control current 
traces were recorded. In the experiments in which the lipids were 
added through the aqueous phase, short-or long-chain phospho-
lipids were added to both sides of the bilayer. The solutions were 
stirred for 1 min and equilibrated for 10 min before recording. 
Single-channel current transitions were identified using the al-
gorithm described previously (Andersen, 1983), implemented in 
software written in <rs id="software-0" type="software">Visual Basic</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Microsoft Corp</rs>.). Single-channel 
lifetimes () were determined by fitting single exponential distribu-
tions to survivor histograms of the lifetime distributions using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Origin</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version">6.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">OriginLab</rs>). At least 300 channels were collected in each ex-
periment. Changes in appearance frequency ( f ), the number of 
channels (opening followed by closing events) per unit of time, were 
determined only in experiments in which the bilayer remained in-
tact after adding the phospholipid. The results were reported as 
means ± SD; in case there were only two observations, the results 
were reported as means ± range. Relative changes in appearance 
frequency were determined by normalizing the appearance fre-
quency in the first two recordings right after the 10-min incubation </p>

<p>Figure 1. Structures of the phospholipids used in this study; brain PIP 2 is predominantly 1-C 18:0 -2-C 20:4 -PI(4,5)P 2 , which is shown in 
the figure. </p>



<p>Phosphoinositides alter lipid bilayer properties </p>

<p>Additional information can be obtained through simultaneous 
measurements on two gA channels of different lengths (with dif-
ferent hydrophobic mismatch and helix sense, to prevent the for-
mation of heterodimers), which allows for distinguishing between 
effects on bilayer curvature and elasticity. This is possible because, 
according to Eqs. 2 and 3, if the bilayer elasticity (expressed as 
changes in H B ) is altered, the effects will be hydrophobic mismatch 
dependent, with greater changes in the shorter channel's appear-
ance frequency and lifetime (Lundbaek et al., 2005; Rusinova et al.,  2011). If the relative changes in lifetime are similar for the longer 
and shorter channels, curvature effects dominate (Artigas et al.,  2006; Ashrafuzzaman et al., 2006). </p>

<p>Fluorescence-based gA assay 
To assay for the phosphoinositides' bilayer-modifying effects, we 
used a gramicidin-based fluorescence quench assay (Ingólfsson  and Andersen, 2010; Ingólfsson et al., 2010; Rusinova et al., 2011)  in which fluorophore-loaded lipid vesicles were mixed with a 
gramicidin-permeable fluorescence quencher (Tl 
+ ) such that 
changes in gramicidin channel activity (the number of channels 
in the large unilamellar vesicle [LUV] membrane) were moni-
tored as changes in the rate of fluorescence quenching. In brief, 
after solvent evaporation, DC 22:1 PC (1,2-dierucoyl-sn-glycero-3-
phosphocholine) was rehydrated in 100 mM NaNO 3 , 25 mM ANTS, 
and 10 mM HEPES, pH 7. After vesicle extrusion and desalting 
to remove excess ANTS, the ANTS-loaded LUVs were prepared 
for fluorescent experiments by diluting 1:20 in 140 mM NaNO 3 
and 10 mM HEPES, pH 7. ANTS-loaded LUVs were doped with 
gD; after incubation for 24 h at 12.5°C to allow for bilayer incor-
poration of gD, the LUVs were incubated at 25°C with or with-
out (control) the test phospholipid for 10 min (unless otherwise 
noted). The LUVs and the Tl 
+ -containing quench buffer were 
mixed in a stopped-flow spectrometer (SX.20; Applied Photo-
physics) with a dead time of &lt;2 ms, and the time course of the 
ANTS fluorescence signal was recorded (see Figs. 8 A and 9 A). 
The resulting fluorescence quench curves were fit with a stretched 
exponential (Berberan-Santos et al., 2005) in Figs. 8 B and 9 B to </p>

<p>acting to dissociate the dimer. Changes in bilayer physical properties 
will alter the phenomenological elastic coefficients and thus G def , 
f, and  (Lundbaek et al., 2010b; Greisen et al., 2011), which make 
the gA channels suitable as probes of changes in bilayer properties. 
The energetics of the gA monomer↔dimer equilibrium is de-
scribed by </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>→ 
→ 
→ 
→ </p>

<p>⎧ 
⎫ 
∆ 
+ ∆ 
⎧ 
⎫ 
∆ 
⎪ 
⎪ 
= 
= 
− 
= 
− 
⎨ 
⎬ 
⎨ 
⎬ 
⎩ 
⎭ 
⎪ 
⎪ 
⎩ 
⎭ </p>

<p>M D 
M D 
M D 
prot 
bil 
M D 
tot 
2 
B 
B </p>

<p>[D] 
exp 
exp 
, 
[M] </p>

<p>G 
G 
G 
K 
k T 
k T </p>

<p>where [M] and [D] denote the surface concentrations of gA mono-
mers and dimers, </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆ </p>

<p>M D 
bil </p>

<p>G 
is the change in G def upon dimer for-
mation, and </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆ </p>

<p>M D 
tot </p>

<p>G 
is the free energy contribution from protein 
interactions. We are interested in the amphiphile-induced changes 
in bilayer properties, and the associated </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆∆ </p>

<p>M D 
bil </p>

<p>G 
is determined 
by the changes in the time-averaged gA activity in the presence 
relative to that in the absence of amphiphiles. From Eq. 4: </p>

<p>→ 
→ 
→ </p>

<p>⎧ 
⎫ 
⎪ 
⎪ 
∆∆ 
= − 
⎨ 
⎬ 
⎪ 
⎪ 
⎩ 
⎭ </p>

<p>M D 
amph 
M D 
tot 
B 
M D 
cntrl </p>

<p>ln 
, 
K 
G 
k T 
K </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>where the subscripts denote the presence or absence of amphi-
phile and </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆∆ </p>

<p>M D 
tot </p>

<p>G 
can be estimated as </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>→ 
→ </p>

<p>× τ 
∆∆ 
≈ − 
× 
= − 
× 
≈ ∆∆ 
× τ </p>

<p>⎧ 
⎫ 
⎧ 
⎫ 
⎨ 
⎬ 
⎨ 
⎬ 
⎩ 
⎭ 
⎩ 
⎭ </p>

<p>amph 
amph 
amph 
M D 
M D 
tot 
B 
B 
bil 
cntrl 
cntrl 
cntrl </p>

<p>[D] 
ln 
ln 
. 
[D] </p>

<p>f 
G 
k T 
k T 
G 
f </p>

<p>The first approximation holds as long as [M] is in excess and 
does not vary after the amphiphiles have been added-as long 
as [M] amph  [M] cntrl /[M] cntrl ≈ 0. The second approximation holds 
when the subunit-subunit interactions do not vary-as long as </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆∆ 
≈ </p>

<p>M D 
prot </p>

<p>0. 
G </p>

<p>Figure 2. Effects of increasing the mole percentage 
of long-chain PIP 2 on gA channel activity in mixed 
DC 18:1 PC/long-chain PIP 2 bilayers. Single-channel 
current traces recorded in DC 18:1 PC planar lipid bi-
layers containing 0 (control), 0.2, 0.6, and 2 mol % 
brain PIP 2 or 2 mol % diC 18:1 PIP 2 . </p>

<p>Rusinova et al. </p>



<p>PIP 2 , as well as short-chain phosphoinositides with vary-
ing numbers (and positions) of phosphate groups in the 
inositol ring-through the aqueous solution; finally, we 
compare the effects of short-chain (diC 8 ) phosphoinositi-
des with those of other diC 8 phospholipids. </p>

<p>Endogenous versus exogenous addition of PIP 2 </p>

<p>To explore the mechanisms by which phosphoinositides 
alter lipid bilayer properties and to estimate the changes 
in energetic cost of protein-imposed bilayer deforma-
tions, we used single-channel electrophysiology to mon-
itor the changes in gA channel lifetimes and appearance 
frequencies. These experiments were performed using 
gA analogues of different chirality and length, gA 
 (13) 
and AgA(15), which allows for detailed information 
about the phosphoinositide effects on bilayer properties 
(Lundbaek et al., 2005). </p>

<p>Effects of endogenous long-chain PIP 2 s. Figs. 2 and 3 show 
results obtained in mixed brain PIP 2 /DC 18:1 PC or 
diC 18:1 PIP 2 /DC 18:1 PC bilayers (Fig. 2); in each case, the 
PIP 2 was added at up to 2 mol %. 
Using either mixture, the lifetimes of both gA 
 (13) 
and AgA(15) channels were longer than in pure DC 18:1 PC </p>

<p>determine the fluorescence quench rate at 2 ms, which reports 
on the time-averaged number of gramicidin channels in the 
LUV membrane. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
All data plots and statistical analyses were performed in <rs id="software-2" type="software">Origin</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version">6.1</rs>. One population Student's t test was used to establish whether 
means were significantly different from 1 as indicated by asterisks 
(P ≤ 0.05). Two population, two-tailed, independent Student's 
t tests were used to establish whether two means were significantly 
different (P ≤ 0.05). A one-way ANOVA test performed on all 
compared means indicated significant differences (P ≤ 0.05). </p>

<p>Online supplemental materials 
Fig. S1 shows the diC 8 PIP 2 effect on the single-channel lifetimes, 
ap pearance frequencies, as well as the channel </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆∆ </p>

<p>M D 
bil </p>

<p>G 
for 
N-Me-gA(15) channels. Online supplemental material is available 
at http://www.jgp.org/cgi/content/full/jgp.201310960/DC1. </p>

<p>R E S U L T S </p>

<p>We first examine the effects of endogenous long-chain 
PIP 2 , in which the PIP 2 was added to the lipid suspensions 
used to form mixed PIP 2 /DC 18:1 PC bilayers; we then ex-
amine the changes in bilayer properties produced by the 
addition of exogenous phosphoinositides-long-chain </p>

<p>Figure 3. Effects of increasing the mole per-
centage of long-chain PIP 2 on single-channel 
lifetimes in DC 18:1 PC/long-chain PIP 2 bilayers. 
(A and C) Lifetime distributions of gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) 
(red lines) and AgA(15) (blue lines) channels, 
which are fit with single exponential distri-
butions (dashed gray lines) in DC 18:1 PC and 
in bilayers with 2 mol % brain PIP 2 (A) and 
DC 18:1 PC and in bilayers with 2 mol % 
diC 18:1 PIP2 (B). The s from the fits are noted 
in the plots. (B and D) Changes in  for gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) 
(red bars) and AgA(15) (blue bars) channels in 
control and mixed bilayers with either 2 mol 
% brain PIP 2 (n = 5; C) or 2 mol % diC 18:1 PIP 2 
(n = 2; D). The  values in control and mixed 
bilayers were normalized to the mean  in 
three separate experiments in control bilay-
ers. Error bars represent SD. </p>



<p>Phosphoinositides alter lipid bilayer properties </p>

<p>function as hydrogen bond acceptors (Sun et al., 2008). 
These transitions were not examined further, but the 
overall behavior is similar for gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) and AgA(15) chan-
nels and is reminiscent of the behavior induced by the 
green tea catechins (Ingólfsson et al., 2011). </p>

<p>Exogenous addition of PIP 2 s. Because experiments with 
phosphoinositides often are done using exogenous ad-
dition, we examined the effect of brain PIP 2 and diC 18:1 
PIP 2 as well as diC 8 PIP 2 when added through the aque-
ous solution. None of the PIP 2 s altered the single-channel 
current amplitudes of gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) or AgA(15) channels, in-
dicating that they do not interact directly with, or accumu-
late in the vicinity of, the channels (Figs. 5 and 6, A and B). 
(The small differences in the gA </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>(13) and gA(15) cur-
rent amplitudes in the presence of the PIP 2 s relative to </p>

<p>(control) bilayers (Fig. 3, A and C). Both long-chain 
PIP 2 s thus alter lipid bilayer properties at physiologically 
relevant mole percentages. 
In addition to altering the single-channel lifetimes, the 
long-chain PIP 2 s caused flickering channel appearances 
(Fig. 2), with no change in the current through the fully 
conducting state. The flickers appear as rapid transi-
tions into and out of one or more subconductance states, 
meaning that they reflect partial pore block rather than 
gA dimer dissociation. We do not understand how the 
long-chain PIP 2 s cause these conductance transitions, but 
they are unlikely to result from interactions between the 
indole NH groups and phosphate oxygens in the inositol 
bisphosphate head groups (Kim et al., 2012), as 2 mol % 
brain PIP 2 produced similar effects in N-Me-gA(15) chan-
nels (Fig. 4, A and B), where the indole residues cannot </p>

<p>Figure 4. Effects of brain PIP 2 on N-Me-gA(15) channel function. (A) Current traces of N-Me-gA in mixed bilayers with 2 mol % brain 
PI(4.5)P 2 . (B) The relative changes in  in bilayers containing 2 mol % brain PIP 2 relative to DC 18:1 PC bilayers without brain PIP 2 . Error 
bars represent SD; n = 2-5. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Testing for bilayer-modifying effects of long-and short-chain PIP 2 s using a gA-based single-channel assay. (A) gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) and 
AgA(15) single-channel current traces without (top) and with (bottom) 50 µM diC 18:1 PIP 2 . (B) AgA(15) and gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) single-channel cur-
rent traces without (top) and with (bottom) 10 µM brain PIP 2 . The current amplitudes of gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) and AgA(15) channels are indicated 
by red and blue dotted lines, respectively. </p>

<p>Rusinova et al. </p>



<p> can be understood by noting that the bilayer needs to 
thin by &gt;1 nm to reach the transition state for channel 
formation, whereas the two subunits need to move apart 
by only a small distance to reach the transition state for 
channel dissociation (Greisen et al., 2011). 
The changes in </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆ </p>

<p>M D 
bilayer </p>

<p>G 
are modest (Fig. 7 C) but of 
sufficient magnitude to alter gA channel function. We 
also evaluated the changes in </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆ </p>

<p>M D 
bilayer </p>

<p>G 
for N-Me-gA(15) 
channels, where </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆∆ </p>

<p>M D 
bilayer </p>

<p>G 
was 2.3 kJ/mol at 50 µM 
diC 8 PI(4,5)P 2 (1,2-dioctanoyl-sn-glycero-3-phospho-(1-
myo-inositol-4,5-bisphosphate; Fig. S1). 
As was observed previously with other amphiphiles 
(Lundbaek et al., 2010b), the changes in the gA 
-(13) 
single-channel lifetimes (expressed as 
τ 
τ </p>

<p>13 
13,cntrl </p>

<p>ln{ / 
}) 
vary as a linear function of the changes in the AgA(15) 
single-channel lifetimes (expressed as 
τ 
τ </p>

<p>15 
15,cntrl </p>

<p>ln{ / 
}; 
Fig. 7 D). The slope is 1.30 ± 0.08 (R = 0.996) and not 
significantly different from a slope of 1. Thus, though </p>

<p>controls are variable and not statistically significant.) Nor 
do the long-chain PIP 2 s produce the flickering behavior 
that was observed in the mixed PIP 2 /DC 18:1 PC bilayers 
(Fig. 5). Surprisingly, given the results in Figs. 2 and 3, 
diC 18:1 PIP 2 had no effect on f or  for either channel type 
(Figs. 5; 6, A and C; and 7, A and B). 
Both diC 8 and brain PIP 2 increased the single-channel 
lifetimes, and, when added at the same nominal concen-
trations, the lifetime increases relative to control were 
similar for diC 8 and brain PIP 2 (Fig. 7 A). diC 8 PIP 2 pro-
duced no changes in the appearance frequencies of 
gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) channels and only small changes in AgA(15) 
channels, whereas brain PIP 2 increased f for both chan-
nel types (Fig. 7 B), with the larger changes in f being 
observed for the longer AgA(15) channels. It is surpris-
ing that both brain PIP 2 and diC 8 PIP 2 produce larger 
changes in f for gA(15) as compared with gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) chan-
nels, but the greater effect of brain PIP 2 on f than on </p>

<p>Figure 6. Effects of long-and short-chain PIP 2 s on gA single-channel function. (A and B) Single-channel current transition amplitude 
distributions of gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) and AgA(15) channels before and after additions of 50 µM diC 18:1 PIP 2 (A) and 50 µM brain PIP 2 (B). The 
vertical red and blue lines denote the mean current transition amplitudes in the absence of PIP 2 . (C and D) Lifetime distributions of 
gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) (red lines) and AgA(15) (blue lines) channels in the presence of increasing concentrations of diC 18:1 PIP 2 (C) and brain PIP 2 
(D); the lifetime distributions are fit with single exponential distributions, N(t)/N(0) = exp{t/} (dashed gray lines) where N(t) is the 
number of channels with lifetimes longer than time t and  is the gA single-channel lifetime. The s from the fits are noted in the plots. </p>



<p>Phosphoinositides alter lipid bilayer properties </p>

<p>quench rate reflect changes in the Tl 
+ influx and channel 
activity (Ingólfsson and Andersen, 2010; Ingólfsson et al.,  2010). The gA dimerization constant varies with changes 
in lipid bilayer properties (Andersen and Koeppe, 2007;  Lundbaek et al., 2010a), meaning that one can attribute 
the changes in quench rate after amphiphile addition 
to modulation of bilayer properties, which in turn gov-
ern the gramicidin monomer↔dimer equilibrium and 
thus the number of channels in the LUV membrane 
(Ingólfsson and Andersen, 2010; Rusinova et al., 2011). 
Brain PIP 2 and diC 8 PIP 2 increased the fluorescence 
quench rates, whereas diC 18:1 PIP 2 did not alter the quench 
rates at the tested concentrations (Fig. 8). The results 
in Fig. 8 are consistent with the electrophysiological </p>

<p>the relative changes in single-channel appearance fre-
quencies, f, and lifetimes, , elicited by either PIP 2 spe-
cies were not significantly different for the longer AgA(15) 
and the shorter gA 
 (13) channels, which would suggest 
that they primarily alter intrinsic curvature, the aggre-
gate results suggest that they also increase bilayer elas-
ticity (Lundbaek et al., 2010b; Rusinova et al., 2011). </p>

<p>Fluorescence quench studies. We also explored the long-
chain PIP 2 s' and diC 8 PIP 2 's bilayer-modifying effects 
using a gramicidin-based fluorescence assay that takes 
advantage of the gramicidin channels' permeability to 
Tl 
+ , a heavy-ion quencher of the water-soluble ANTS 
fluorophore. In this assay, changes in the fluorescence </p>

<p>Figure 7. Effects of long-and short-chain PIP 2 s on 
gA single-channel function. (A and B) Normalized 
changes in  (A) and f (B) of gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) (red bars) and 
AgA(15) (blue bars) channels produced by diC 8 PIP 2 , 
brain PIP 2 , and diC 18:1 PIP 2 . (A)  †, in the presence of 
30 µM diC 8 or 50 µM brain PIP 2 , / cntrl is significantly 
&gt;50 µM diC 18:1 PIP 2 (P ≤ 0.05) for gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) as well as 
gA(15);  ‡, gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) / cntrl in the presence of 10 µM 
diC 8 PIP 2 is significantly &gt;10 µM brain PIP 2 . (B)  †, 
gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) f/f cntrl in the presence of 10 µM diC 8 is signifi-
cantly &gt;10 µM brain PIP 2 . (C) The resulting </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆∆ </p>

<p>M D 
bil </p>

<p>G 
values are calculated from the changes in  and f as 
described in Materials and methods (Eq. 6). We could 
not determine the changes in f at 50 µM brain PIP 2 
because of bilayer instability. (A-C) All values are plot-
ted as means ± SD or range; n = 2-6. *, means are 
significantly different from 1 (P ≤ 0.05). Dotted lines 
indicate the level where there is no change relative to 
control (y = 1). (D) Plot of the natural logarithm of 
/ cntrl of gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) as a function of / cntrl of gA(15) 
channels in the presence of different concentrations 
of diC 8 and brain PIP 2 (square). The 95% confidence 
intervals (green lines) indicate that the slope is not 
significantly different from the slope of 1 (dashed 
line), suggesting that both short-and long-chain PIP 2 s 
produce larger increases in the lifetimes of gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) 
channels than of gA(15) channels. </p>

<p>Rusinova et al. </p>



<p>diC 18:1 PIP 2 , they were 1.0 ± 0.1 vs. 1.05 ± 0.03 after 10 
and 30 min, respectively). Moreover, although the lon-
ger acyl chain lengths would suggest greater partition-
ing of diC 18:1 or brain PIP 2 into the bilayer, as compared 
with the shorter diC 8 PIP 2 , the dose-response curves for 
diC 18:1 or brain PIP 2 were right shifted compared with 
those of their diC 8 counterpart. </p>

<p>Short-chain phosphoinositides </p>

<p>The short-chain (diC 8 ) phosphoinositides are relatively 
water soluble, with critical micelle concentrations (CMCs) 
in the high micromolar range (Table 1), which makes 
them easy to handle in functional assays. We therefore 
examined the bilayer-modifying effects of diC 8 phos-
phoinositides with different numbers and positions of 
the phosphate groups on the inositol ring using the fluo-
rescence quench method. 
All of the diC 8 phosphoinositides increased gramicidin 
channel activity, as reflected by the increased quench </p>

<p>results (Figs. 5-7), yet the different bilayer-modifying 
potencies of diC 18:1 PIP 2 and brain PIP 2 are surprising 
because bilayer partition coefficients of fatty acids in-
crease with increasing acyl chain saturation (Yokoyama  and Nakagaki, 1993; Richieri et al., 1999). One would 
expect that the same would apply for diC 18:1 PIP 2 , com-
pared with its polyunsaturated counterpart brain PIP 2 that 
mostly is C 18:0/20:4 PIP 2 . It is not clear, however, whether 
this reasoning should apply to situations in which the 
PIP 2 s are micellar because the free energy of transfer be-
tween micelles and bilayers is likely to be modest (Bullock  and Cohen, 1986; Heerklotz and Seelig, 2000). The obser-
vation that brain PIP 2 was more effective than diC 18:1 PIP 2 
thus suggests that the exchange between micelles and 
the bilayer is slower for diC 18:1 PIP 2 than for brain PIP 2 . 
Nevertheless, longer incubation times of vesicles with 
either long-chain PIP 2 did not alter the quench rates. 
(The relative changes in quench rates observed with 
50 µM brain PIP 2 were 2.7 ± 1 vs. 3.1 ± 1.0; with 50 µM </p>

<p>Figure 8. Testing for bilayer-modifying 
effects of long-chain PIP 2 s and diC 8 PIP 2 
using a gramicidin-based fluorescence 
assay. (A) Time course of Tl 
+ quenching 
of the ANTS fluorescence in the absence 
(top trace) and presence (bottom three 
traces) of gD and in the absence or pres-
ence of different PIP 2 s. The trace for each 
condition shows data points from all 
mixing trials (gray points) and the cor-
responding mean (black lines, controls; 
cyan line, 50 µM diC 18:1 PIP 2 ; navy blue 
line, 50 µM brain PI(4,5)P 2 ). (B) Fluores-
cence quench traces from a single mixing 
trial for each condition in A. The points 
are colored like the corresponding mean 
traces in A; the solid lines denote fits 
of a stretched exponential to the data, </p>

<p>Rusinova et al. 
9 of 22 </p>

<p>because bilayer partition coefficients of fatty acids in-
crease with increasing acyl chain saturation (Yokoyama  and Nakagaki, 1993; Richieri et al., 1999). One would 
expect that the same would apply for diC 18:1 PIP 2 , com-
pared with its polyunsaturated counterpart brain PIP 2 
that mostly is C 18:0/20:4 PIP 2 . It is not clear, however, 
whether this reasoning should apply to situations in 
which the PIP 2 s are micellar because the free energy of 
transfer between micelles and bilayers is likely to be 
modest (Bullock and Cohen, 1986; Heerklotz and  Seelig, 2000). The observation that brain PIP 2 was more 
effective than diC 18:1 PIP 2 thus suggests that the ex-
change between micelles and the bilayer is slower for 
diC 18:1 PIP 2 than for brain PIP 2 . Nevertheless, longer in-
cubation times of vesicles with either long-chain PIP 2 
did not alter the quench rates. (The relative changes in 
quench rates observed with 50 µM brain PIP 2 were 2.7 ± </p>

<p>quench rate reflect changes in the Tl 
+ influx and chan-
nel activity (Ingólfsson and Andersen, 2010; Ingólfsson  et al., 2010). The gA dimerization constant varies with 
changes in lipid bilayer properties (Andersen and Ko- eppe, 2007; Lundbaek et al., 2010a), meaning that one 
can attribute the changes in quench rate after amphi-
phile addition to modulation of bilayer properties, 
which in turn govern the gramicidin monomer↔dimer 
equilibrium and thus the number of channels in the 
LUV membrane (Ingólfsson and Andersen, 2010;  Rusinova et al., 2011). 
Brain PIP 2 and diC 8 PIP 2 increased the fluorescence 
quench rates, whereas diC 18:1 PIP 2 did not alter the 
quench rates at the tested concentrations (Fig. 8). The 
results in Fig. 8 are consistent with the electrophysiolog-
ical results (Figs. 5-7), yet the different bilayer-modify-
ing potencies of diC 18:1 PIP 2 and brain PIP 2 are surprising </p>

<p>Figure 8. Testing for bilayer-modifying 
effects of long-chain PIP 2 s and diC 8 PIP 2 
using a gramicidin-based fluorescence 
assay. (A) Time course of Tl 
+ quenching 
of the ANTS fluorescence in the absence 
(top trace) and presence (bottom three 
traces) of gD and in the absence or pres-
ence of different PIP 2 s. The trace for 
each condition shows data points from 
all mixing trials (gray points) and the 
corresponding mean (black lines, con-
trols; cyan line, 50 µM diC 18:1 PIP 2 ; navy 
blue line, 50 µM brain PI(4,5)P 2 ). (B) 
Fluorescence quench traces from a sin-
gle mixing trial for each condition in A. 
The points are colored like the corre-
sponding mean traces in A; the solid 
lines denote fits of a stretched exponen-
tial 
to 
the 
data, </p>

<p>F t 
F 
F 
F 
t 
( ) 
( ) 
( ) 
( ) exp ( / ) 
= ∞ + 
− ∞ × 
− </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>{ 
} </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>β , </p>

<p>where F(t) is fluorescence intensity at 
time t,  is a measure of sample disper-
sity (0 &lt;  ≤ 1), and  0 is a parameter with 
units of time (Berberan-Santos et al.,  2005). (C) Normalized fluorescence 
quench rates in gD-doped vesicles in the 
presence of diC 18:1 (cyan) and brain 
(navy blue) PI(4,5)P 2 (means ± SD; n = 
3-6). Data for diC 8 PI(4,5)P 2 (gray) from 
Fig. 9 C is included for comparison. 
Quench rates for each mixing reaction 
was 
evaluated 
at 
2 
ms 
as 
k t 
t 
( ) 
/ 
/ </p>

<p>= ( 
) × ( 
) </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>β τ 
τ </p>

<p>β 
0 
0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>(Berberan- Santos et al., 2005). The mean quench 
rate for each set of mixing reactions in 
the presence of the PIP 2 s was normalized 
to that in the absence of phosphoinosit-
ide, and the resulting normalized 
quench rates are plotted. *, statistically 
significant difference between diC 8 PIP 2 
and both diC 18:1 and brain PI(4,5)P 2 ;  ‡, statistically significant difference between diC 18:1 and brain PI(4,5)P 2 . Statistical analysis was done 
by two-tailed, independent t test (P &lt; 0.05). (B and C) Dotted lines indicate the level where there is no change relative to control (y = 1). </p>

<p>ROUGH GALLEY PROOF </p>

<p>where F(t) is fluorescence intensity at 
time t,  is a measure of sample dispersity 
(0 &lt;  ≤ 1), and  0 is a parameter with units 
of time (Berberan-Santos et al., 2005). 
(C) Normalized fluorescence quench 
rates in gD-doped vesicles in the pres-
ence of diC 18:1 (cyan) and brain (navy 
blue) PI(4,5)P 2 (means ± SD; n = 3-6). 
Data for diC 8 PI(4,5)P 2 (gray) from Fig. 9 C 
is included for comparison. Quench 
rates for each mixing reaction was evalu-
ated at 2 ms as </p>

<p>Rusinova et al. 
9 of 22 </p>

<p>because bilayer partition coefficients of fatty acids in-
crease with increasing acyl chain saturation (Yokoyama  and Nakagaki, 1993; Richieri et al., 1999). One would 
expect that the same would apply for diC 18:1 PIP 2 , com-
pared with its polyunsaturated counterpart brain PIP 2 
that mostly is C 18:0/20:4 PIP 2 . It is not clear, however, 
whether this reasoning should apply to situations in 
which the PIP 2 s are micellar because the free energy of 
transfer between micelles and bilayers is likely to be 
modest (Bullock and Cohen, 1986; Heerklotz and  Seelig, 2000). The observation that brain PIP 2 was more 
effective than diC 18:1 PIP 2 thus suggests that the ex-
change between micelles and the bilayer is slower for 
diC 18:1 PIP 2 than for brain PIP 2 . Nevertheless, longer in-
cubation times of vesicles with either long-chain PIP 2 
did not alter the quench rates. (The relative changes in 
quench rates observed with 50 µM brain PIP 2 were 2.7 ± </p>

<p>quench rate reflect changes in the Tl 
+ influx and chan-
nel activity (Ingólfsson and Andersen, 2010; Ingólfsson  et al., 2010). The gA dimerization constant varies with 
changes in lipid bilayer properties (Andersen and Ko- eppe, 2007; Lundbaek et al., 2010a), meaning that one 
can attribute the changes in quench rate after amphi-
phile addition to modulation of bilayer properties, 
which in turn govern the gramicidin monomer↔dimer 
equilibrium and thus the number of channels in the 
LUV membrane (Ingólfsson and Andersen, 2010;  Rusinova et al., 2011). 
Brain PIP 2 and diC 8 PIP 2 increased the fluorescence 
quench rates, whereas diC 18:1 PIP 2 did not alter the 
quench rates at the tested concentrations (Fig. 8). The 
results in Fig. 8 are consistent with the electrophysiolog-
ical results (Figs. 5-7), yet the different bilayer-modify-
ing potencies of diC 18:1 PIP 2 and brain PIP 2 are surprising </p>

<p>Figure 8. Testing for bilayer-modifying 
effects of long-chain PIP 2 s and diC 8 PIP 2 
using a gramicidin-based fluorescence 
assay. (A) Time course of Tl 
+ quenching 
of the ANTS fluorescence in the absence 
(top trace) and presence (bottom three 
traces) of gD and in the absence or pres-
ence of different PIP 2 s. The trace for 
each condition shows data points from 
all mixing trials (gray points) and the 
corresponding mean (black lines, con-
trols; cyan line, 50 µM diC 18:1 PIP 2 ; navy 
blue line, 50 µM brain PI(4,5)P 2 ). (B) 
Fluorescence quench traces from a sin-
gle mixing trial for each condition in A. 
The points are colored like the corre-
sponding mean traces in A; the solid 
lines denote fits of a stretched exponen-
tial 
to 
the 
data, </p>

<p>F t 
F 
F 
F 
t 
( ) 
( ) 
( ) 
( ) exp ( / ) 
= ∞ + 
− ∞ × 
− </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>{ 
} </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>β , </p>

<p>where F(t) is fluorescence intensity at 
time t,  is a measure of sample disper-
sity (0 &lt;  ≤ 1), and  0 is a parameter with 
units of time (Berberan-Santos et al.,  2005). (C) Normalized fluorescence 
quench rates in gD-doped vesicles in the 
presence of diC 18:1 (cyan) and brain 
(navy blue) PI(4,5)P 2 (means ± SD; n = 
3-6). Data for diC 8 PI(4,5)P 2 (gray) from 
Fig. 9 C is included for comparison. 
Quench rates for each mixing reaction 
was 
evaluated 
at 
2 
ms 
as 
k t 
t 
( ) 
/ 
/ </p>

<p>= ( 
) × ( 
) </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>β τ 
τ </p>

<p>β 
0 
0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>(Berberan- Santos et al., 2005). The mean quench 
rate for each set of mixing reactions in 
the presence of the PIP 2 s was normalized 
to that in the absence of phosphoinosit-
ide, and the resulting normalized 
quench rates are plotted. *, statistically 
significant difference between diC 8 PIP 2 
and both diC 18:1 and brain PI(4,5)P 2 ;  ‡, statistically significant difference between diC 18:1 and brain PI(4,5)P 2 . Statistical analysis was done 
by two-tailed, independent t test (P &lt; 0.05). (B and C) Dotted lines indicate the level where there is no change relative to control (y = 1). </p>

<p>ROUGH GALLEY PROOF </p>

<p>(Berberan-Santos et al., 2005). The 
mean quench rate for each set of mixing 
reactions in the presence of the PIP 2 s 
was normalized to that in the absence of 
phosphoinositide, and the resulting nor-
malized quench rates are plotted. *, sta-
tistically significant difference between 
diC 8 PIP 2 and both diC 18:1 and brain 
PI(4,5)P 2 ;  ‡, statistically significant dif-
ference between diC 18:1 and brain PI(4,5)P 2 . Statistical analysis was done by two-tailed, independent t test (P &lt; 0.05). (B and C) Dotted 
lines indicate the level where there is no change relative to control (y = 1). </p>



<p>Phosphoinositides alter lipid bilayer properties </p>

<p>Schwarzenbach, 1995; Avdeef, 2001; Seydel and Wiese,  2002). Based on the estimated mole percentage of each 
phospholipid in the LUV membranes (Table 1) and the 
dose-response curves (Fig. 10), the zwitterionic diC 8 PC 
and -PE have similar bilayer-modifying potencies, whereas 
the anionic diC 8 PI and -PS are more potent. </p>

<p>Single-channel electrophysiology. The short-chain diC 8 PC 
(1,2-dioctanoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine), -PE, -PS, 
and -PI vary also in their effects on planar bilayers, with 
diC 8 PS and diC 8 PE eliciting the largest channel life-
time increases, and diC 8 PC causing the least change 
(Fig. 11 A). 
Although the changes are small, the linear relation-
ship between the natural logarithm of the AgA(15) and 
gA 
 (13) single-channel lifetimes, in the presence of 
diC 8 phospholipids, has a slope of 1.16 ± 0.05, R = 0.994 
(Fig. 11 D), suggesting that they do increase bilayer 
elasticity (Lundbaek et al., 2010b), in addition to chang-
ing the curvature (Rusinova et al., 2011). Except for 
the effects of diC 8 PS on AgA(15) channels, the relative 
changes in f (Fig. 11 B) were larger than the changes in 
. At the highest concentration tested, none of the 
phospholipids (whether anionic or zwitterionic) altered 
the gA single-channel current transition amplitudes. 
That the anionic phospholipids do not alter the single-
channel current transition amplitudes is in striking con-
trast to the results obtained with free fatty acids (Bruno  et al., 2007, 2013). </p>

<p>D I S C U S S I O N </p>

<p>The mechanisms by which phosphoinositides alter mem-
brane protein function remain enigmatic in the sense 
that, for many proteins, it is unclear to what extent the </p>

<p>rate, with PI being the most active and PI(3,4,5)P 3 and 
PI(3,5)P 2 the least bilayer active: PI &gt; PI(4,5)P 2 = PI(3,4) 
P 2 &gt; PI(3,4,5)P 3 ≥ PI(3,5)P 2 (Fig. 9). 
The concentrations at which we observed changes in 
bilayer properties varied from 10 µM for PI, PI(3,4)P 2 , 
and PI(4,5)P 2 to 150 µM for PI(3,5)P 2 and PI(3,4,5)P 2 . 
Overall, the potency decreased with increasing head 
group charge (compare with Fig. 1), as would be expected 
if the short-chain phosphoinositides' bilayer-modifying 
potencies depended on their ability to partition into the 
bilayer-solution interface. Though the formal charge on 
PI(3,5)P 2 is the same as that on PI(4,5)P 2 and PI(3,4)P 2 , 
its bilayer-modifying potency was less than that of 
PI(3,4,5)P 3 , suggesting that the phosphate configura-
tion around the inositol ring modulates the interac-
tion with the bilayer. Unlike the adjacent phosphates in 
PI(3,4)P 2 or PI(4,5)P 2 , the distant phosphates in 
PI(3,5)P 2 may prevent the phosphoinositol ring from 
inserting as far into the bilayer (Redfern and Gericke,  2005), resulting in weaker bilayer effects. </p>

<p>Other short-chain phospholipids </p>

<p>Fluorescence quench studies. For comparison with the 
short-chain phosphoinositides, we examined other short-
chain phospholipids-diC 8 PS (1,2-dioctanoyl-sn-glycero-
3-phospho-l-serine), -PE, and -PC. All three alter lipid 
bilayer properties with similar dose-response curves 
(Fig. 10); they have similar bilayer-modifying potencies 
even though their head groups vary in size and charge. 
The bilayer partition coefficients of surfactants can be 
estimated from their CMCs (Bullock and Cohen, 1986;  Heerklotz and Seelig, 2000). (In case CMCs are not avail-
able, the partition coefficient of a neutral amphiphile 
can be estimated from the logarithms of the calculated 
water/octanol partitioning ratio (clogP; Escher and </p>

<p>T A B l E 1 </p>

<p>Phospholipid distribution in the membrane single-channel experiments </p>

<p>Compound 
CMC 
Nominal [PL] 
[PL] a 
{PL} m 
Mole % PL </p>

<p>LUV 
Planar bilayer 
LUV 
Planar bilayer 
LUV 
Planar bilayer 
LUV 
Planar bilayer </p>

<p>M 
M 
M 
M 
M 
moles/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>moles/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>mole % 
mole % </p>

<p>diC 8 PC 
270 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>30 
3 
15 
1 
2 × 10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>1 × 10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>6 
0.4 </p>

<p>diC 8 PE 
230 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>30 
3 
10 
1 
2 × 10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>1 × 10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>8 
0.4 </p>

<p>diC 8 PI 
500 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>30 
3 
20 
1.5 
1 × 10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>7 × 10 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>4 
0.3 </p>

<p>diC 8 PS 
500 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>30 
3 
20 
1.5 
1 × 10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>7 × 10 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>4 
0.3 </p>

<p>brain PIP 2 
30 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>50 
50 
5 
3 
4 × 10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>2 × 10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>15 
9.0 </p>

<p>The aqueous phospholipid concentrations and their surface densities and mole percentage in the membrane ([PL] a , {PL} m , and mole % PL , respectively) 
were calculated according to Bruno et al. (2007) and Rusinova et al. (2011) using 1.2/CMC as an estimate for the (dimensionless) partition coefficient 
into the membrane (Bullock and Cohen, 1986); the total phospholipid concentration in the membrane was taken to be 1.2 M. This may overestimate the 
partition coefficient and mole % PL , as Heerklotz and Seelig (2000) found the partition coefficient for diC 7 PC to be threefold less than predicted using the 
above estimator. (The difference between the mole fractions in the LUVs vs. the planar bilayer is a result of the different amount of lipids in the different 
systems.) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Zhou et al., 1997.   b   Estimated from the CMC for diC 6 PE, 12 mM (Zhou et al., 1997), and scaling by the ratio of the CMC for diC 8 PC over the CMC for diC 6 PC. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Wang et al., 2008.   d   Palmer, 1981; Huang and Huang, 1991; Moens and Bagatolli, 2007. </p>

<p>Rusinova et al. </p>



<p>The PIP 2 modulation of bilayer properties occurs 
at relevant concentrations </p>

<p>The PIP 2 concentrations tested here are comparable 
with those used in cell physiological experiments. Fol-
lowing Rusinova et al. (2011), we analyzed the bilayer 
contribution to the free energy of gA channel formation 
(Fig. 7 C) when the PIP 2 analogues are applied through 
the aqueous phase and found that the changes are mod-
est: </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆∆ 
≤ </p>

<p>M D 
bil 
B </p>

<p>G 
k T (= 2.5 kJ mol 
1 at 25°C). (This esti-
mate pertains to gA channels in a relatively soft bilayer; </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆∆ </p>

<p>I II 
bil </p>

<p>G 
for an integral membrane protein may be larger 
or smaller, depending on the protein radius, shape, and 
the host bilayer material properties.) Both long-and short-
chain polyphosphoinositides have little effect on bilayer 
properties at 3 µM (nominal concentration; Figs. 7 and 9), 
meaning that functional effects of long-chain polyphos-
phoinositides that occur at or below the micromolar 
range are unlikely to be bilayer mediated. In contrast, </p>

<p>phosphoinositides act through direct binding to their 
membrane protein effectors, as opposed to altering lipid 
bilayer properties or some other indirect mechanism that 
in turn will alter the energetics of protein conforma-
tional transitions. We used gramicidin-based fluores-
cence quenching and single-channel assays to determine 
whether various polyphosphoinositide isoforms alter 
lipid bilayer properties and found that they do so at 
physiologically relevant concentrations (mole fractions 
in the membrane). 
First, we highlight that bilayer modulation by PIP 2 oc-
curs at "relevant" concentrations and consider what bi-
layer properties are affected. Next, we discuss implications 
of our findings in view of what is known about PIP 2 and 
its mechanism of action. Finally, we discuss and com-
pare the bilayer-modifying effects of PIP 2 to those of 
isoforms with different phosphate group organizations 
as well as acyl chain variants and other phospholipids. </p>

<p>Figure 9. Testing for bilayer-modi-
fying effects of short-chain phospho-
inositides using a gA-based fluorescence 
quench assay. (A) Time course of Tl </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>quenching of the ANTS fluorescence 
in the absence (top four traces) and 
presence (bottom four traces) of gA 
and in the absence or presence of dif-
ferent short-chain phosphoinositides. 
The trace for each condition shows 
data points from all mixing trials (gray 
points) and the corresponding mean 
(black lines, controls; red lines, 30 µM 
diC 8 PI; orange lines, 30 µM diC 8 PI(4,5) 
P 2 ; green lines, 30 µM diC 8 PI(3,4,5)P 3 ). 
(B) Fluorescence quench traces from a 
single mixing trial for each condition 
in A. The points are colored like the 
corresponding mean traces in A; the 
solid lines denote fits of a stretched ex-
ponential to the data. (C) Normalized 
fluorescence quench rates, evaluated 
at 2 ms, in gD-doped vesicles in the 
presence of phosphoinositides. The 
mean quench rate for each set of mix-
ing reactions in the presence of phos-
phoinositides was normalized to that in 
the absence of phosphoinositide, and 
the resulting normalized quench rates 
are plotted (means ± SD; n = 3-6). 
*, statistically significant difference be-
tween diC 8 PI or diC 8 PI(3,4,5)P 2 and 
both diC 8 PI(4,5)P 2 and diC 8 PI(3,4) 
P 2 at 30 µM;  ‡, statistically significant 
difference between diC 8 PI(4,5)P 2 and 
diC 8 PI(3,4)P 2 at 30 µM. diC 8 PI(3,4,5) 
P 2 and diC 8 PI(3,5)P 2 are not signifi-
cantly different at 30 µM. (B and C) 
Dotted lines indicate the level where 
there is no change relative to control 
(y = 1). Statistical analysis was done by 
two-tailed, independent t test (P &lt; 0.05). </p>



<p>Phosphoinositides alter lipid bilayer properties </p>

<p>2005; Li et al., 2005; Hilgemann, 2007), and PIP 2 alters 
gramicidin channel stability at 2 mol % (Fig. 2). Thus, 
physiological depletion or enrichment of PIP 2 in the inner 
leaflet of the plasma membrane (Nasuhoglu et al., 2002;  Xu et al., 2003; Horowitz et al., 2005; Li et al., 2005; Suh  and Hille, 2005), whether global or local, is likely to be 
associated with changes in lipid bilayer properties. 
Local PIP 2 enrichment may be considerable, as there 
are 70-80 phospholipids in the first two lipid shells around 
a bilayer-spanning protein of 3-nm radius. If one PIP 2 
molecule is required to alter protein function, the local 
PIP 2 mole percentage would be 1; if four PIP 2 s were 
needed, the mole percentage would be ≥5! PIP 2 bind-
ing to its target proteins thus may alter the local bilayer 
environment (the bilayer material properties), and the 
question becomes, what are the relative energetic con-
tributions of specific binding and nonspecific bilayer-
mediated effects on protein function? 
Whether bilayer-mediated effects become important 
will depend on the affinity of PIP 2 (or other ligands) for 
the protein. Some ion channels are regulated at very 
low PIP 2 concentrations, whereas other PIP 2 targets re-
quire higher concentrations, as reflected in their regu-
lation by physiological stimulation of PIP 2 hydrolysis 
(Huang et al., 1998; Kobrinsky et al., 2000; Runnels et al.,  2002; Lopes et al., 2002; Zhang et al., 2003; Rohács et al.,  2005; Rohács, 2007). In the case of Kir channels, the PIP 2 
affinity is inversely correlated with the channels' suscep-
tibility to regulation by PIP 2 isomers and other mole-
cules (Zhang et al., 1999; Schulze et al., 2003; Lee et al.,  2005; Rosenhouse-Dantsker and Logothetis, 2007). Thus, 
channels with lower affinity for PIP 2 are likely to be more 
sensitive to their environment, in which case dynamic 
changes in the environment (including PIP 2 -induced 
changes in bilayer properties) may be important for 
function. These features may be tested by exposing the 
channels to short-chain nonphosphoinositide phospho-
lipids, which modify the bilayer (Fig. 11 C) and thus allow 
for a positive control of sensitivity to changes in lipid 
bilayer properties. </p>

<p>Bilayer-modifying effects of different polyphosphoinositide 
isoforms and short-chain phospholipids </p>

<p>Results obtained using the gramicidin-based fluores-
cence assay show that all compounds tested increase the 
ANTS fluorescence quench rates because they shift the 
gA monomer↔dimer equilibrium toward the conduct-
ing dimers, indicating that each of them alters lipid bi-
layer properties, albeit with different potencies. 
A compound's apparent bilayer-modifying potency re-
flects several factors: its affinity for the bilayer (its partition 
coefficient), which relates the concentration of mono-
disperse molecules in solution to the surface density or 
volume concentration in the bilayer; the state of the com-
pound in solution, where micelle or other aggregate 
formation will influence the number of monomeric </p>

<p>effects that are observed only at concentrations ≥10 µM 
may, at least in part, be caused by altered bilayer proper-
ties. Many studies have used much higher [diC 8 PIP 2 ] 
(Runnels et al., 2002; Zhang et al., 2003; Lopes et al.,  2005; Rohács et al., 2005; Hernandez et al., 2008), in 
which case it becomes important to consider the possi-
bility of membrane effects. </p>

<p>Implications for PIP 2 targets </p>

<p>PIP 2 -sensitive channels vary considerably in their phos-
phate isomer specificity (Fan and Makielski, 1997; Rohács  et al., 2003; Zhang et al., 2003; Rohács, 2007), and the 
binding pockets in PIP 2 -binding membrane-spanning 
proteins vary greatly, meaning that the definition of bind-
ing sites for PIP 2 becomes ambiguous (Suh and Hille,  2008). Other than requirements for positive and aro-
matic residues, the binding sites are not clearly defined 
(Rosenhouse-Dantsker and Logothetis, 2007; Suh and  Hille, 2008), however, and mutations of specific residues, 
or even entire polybasic regions, may modulate but not 
eliminate the PIP 2 effects (Rohács et al., 2003; Zhang  et al., 2003; Rohács, 2007; Vaithianathan et al., 2008). 
These ambiguities suggest that some PIP 2 effects may be 
the result of less specific interactions, such as altered en-
ergetic coupling between the target protein and the host 
bilayer. Indeed, nonphosphoinositide phospholipids can 
alter channel function if applied at high concentrations 
from 0.01 to 1 mM (Fan and Makielski, 1997; Kim and  Bang, 1999; Hilgemann et al., 2001; Zhang et al., 2003;  Vaithianathan et al., 2008). Importantly, the PIP 2 abun-
dance percentage in the inner leaflet of the plasma mem-
brane is on the order of 1%, perhaps higher (Ferrell and  Huestis, 1984; Balla and Várnai, 2002; Nasuhoglu et al.,  2002; Wenk et al., 2003; Xu et al., 2003; Horowitz et al.,   Figure 10. Testing for bilayer-modifying effects of short-chain 
phospholipids using the gA-based fluorescence assay. Normalized 
changes in quench rates produced by the diC 8 phospholipids 
(means ± SD; n = 3-5). Data for diC 8 PI (gray line) from Fig. 2 C is 
included for comparison. Means of different diC 8 phospholipids 
were not significantly different, with the exception of diC 8 PC and 
diC 8 PE at 30 µM. The dotted line indicates the level where there 
is no change relative to control (y = 1). </p>

<p>Rusinova et al. </p>



<p>bilayer-modifying potency (Lundbaek et al., 1997; see 
also Lundbaek and Andersen, 1994; Bruno et al., 2013). 
In the case of the polyphosphoinositides, the decreased 
potencies, relative to diC 8 PI (compare Fig. 9 with Fig. 10), 
may be the result of a dominant effect of the charge-
dependent decrease in the partition coefficient. 
Using isothermal titration calorimetry, we explored 
the partitioning of diC 8 PI, diC 8 PIP 2 , and diC 8 PI(3,4,5) 
P 3 into lipid vesicles but did not observe heats of parti-
tioning (unpublished data), either because the partition 
coefficients are too low to be measured, as suggested 
from the CMCs (Table 1 legend), or because the parti-
tioning is primarily entropy driven. In any case, although 
the head group charges make it challenging to estimate 
the mole fractions of PI, PIP 2 , and PIP 3 in the bilayer (they 
preclude using clogP for the estimate), the decreasing 
bilayer-modifying potency with increasing charge on the </p>

<p>molecules available to partition into the bilayer (see last 
paragraph of Discussion); and the ability of a molecule 
in the bilayer to alter bilayer properties. The apparent 
potencies of the short-chain phosphoinositides decrease 
with increasing charge, consistent with the expected in-
fluence of charge to lower the partition coefficient into 
lipid bilayers (Peitzsch and McLaughlin, 1993). In the 
LUV experiments, the short-chain nonphosphoinosit-
ide phospholipids and diC 8 PI have similar potencies. 
The similar effects of the charged and zwitterionic phos-
pholipids could be caused by the combined effect of a 
decreased partition coefficient (Marsh and King, 1986;  Peitzsch and McLaughlin, 1993; Marsh, 2012a) and a 
larger effective head group size (Israelachvili et al., 1980;  Kleinschmidt and Tamm, 2002) for the charged phos-
pholipids. Thus, molecule per molecule, the charged 
phospholipids would be expected to have increased </p>

<p>Figure 11. Effects of short-chain phospholipids on 
gA single-channel activity. (A and B) Normalized 
changes in  (A) and f (B) for gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) (red bars) 
and gA(15) (blue bars) channels in the presence 
of diC 8 PC, diC 8 PI, diC 8 PE, and diC 8 PS at the indi-
cated concentrations. (A) #, not significantly differ-
ent from 1. (C) The resulting </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>∆∆ </p>

<p>M D 
bil </p>

<p>G 
values are 
calculated from the changes in  and f as described 
in Materials and methods (Eq. 6). (A-C) All values 
are plotted as means ± SD or range (n = 2-4). 
*,  †, and  ‡ denote statistically significant differences 
between means (P &lt; 0.05). There is no significant 
difference between diC 8 PE and diC 8 PS. (D) Plot of 
the natural logarithm of / cntrl of gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) as a func-
tion of / cntrl of gA(15) channels in the presence 
of different concentrations of diC 8 phospholip-
ids (squares). The 95% confidence intervals (green 
lines) indicate that the slope is significantly different 
from 1.0 (dashed line), indicating that both of the 
short-chain phospholipids produce relatively larger 
increases in the lifetimes of the gA </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(13) channels as 
compared with the gA(15) channels. </p>



<p>Phosphoinositides alter lipid bilayer properties </p>

<p>In contrast to the LUV experiments, in which the short-
chain phospholipids had similar potencies, the bilayer-
modifying rank-order potency in the planar bilayer 
experiments was PS ≥ PE &gt; PI ≥ PC, which cannot be ac-
counted for simply by different partitioning (Table 1). 
The different rank-order potencies in the LUVs and pla-
nar bilayers, as well as the differences observed for short-
chain phospholipids described here and long-chain 
lysophospholipids from a previous study (Lundbaek and  Andersen, 1994), reflect the compounds' detailed mo-
lecular properties, including the effective cross-sectional 
areas of the acyl chains relative to the head groups-as 
well as the lengths of their acyl chains relative to those 
of the bilayer-forming lipids in the host bilayer (Aagaard  et al., 2006; Ingólfsson and Andersen, 2011). Ingólfsson  and Andersen (2011), in particular, found that the sign 
of the effect of an n-alkyl alcohol on lipid bilayer prop-
erties varied with the n-alkyl length (short-chain alcohols 
increased gA channel dimerization; long-chain alcohols 
decreased dimerization). The chain length at which the 
transition occurred furthermore varied with the host 
bilayer phospholipid acyl chain length. The relative dif-
ferences in bilayer-modifying potency observed in the 
stopped-flow and single-channel experiments thus may 
differ (see also Ingólfsson and Andersen, 2010). 
The different rank-order potencies of the short-and 
long-chain PIP 2 s in single-channel versus fluorescence 
assays again are likely to reflect different perturbations of 
the membrane acyl chains. The hydrophobic and electro-
static contributions to the free energy of adsorption at the 
bilayer-solution interface tend to be additive (Zaslavsky  et al., 1978; Israelachvili et al., 1980; Tanford, 1980; King  and Marsh, 1987; Buser et al., 1994), meaning that the dif-
ference in ionic strength between the fluorescence and 
single-channel experiments should have similar effects 
on the adsorption of the long-and short-chain PIP 2 s. 
The lack of effect of diC 18:1 PIP 2 in the fluorescence 
and electrophysiological assays, when added through the 
aqueous phase, is in striking contrast to the effects ob-
served when the compound is added through the lipid 
phase (compare Figs. 3, 6, and 7). The key difference 
between these experiments is the elimination of the 
micelle→water and water→bilayer partitioning steps, 
which also may have implications for the design and inter-
pretation of cell physiological experiments. For example, 
the negative correlation between the PIP 2 concentra-
tion needed to elicit an effect and the length of the PIP 2 
acyl chain (Rohács et al., 1999; Jin et al., 2002; Zhang et al.,  2003; Vaithianathan et al., 2008) is often attributed to 
higher partitioning of PIP 2 s with longer acyl chains. Yet, 
the modest differences between the dose-response curves 
for diC 8 -and brain PIP 2 , which cannot be accounted for 
by the difference in hydrophobicity of their acyl chains, 
show that the correlation between CMC and bilayer par-
titioning is complicated-at least in systems contain-
ing both micelles and bilayers (see beginning of this </p>

<p>inositol ring suggests that the differences in potency are 
caused mainly by differences in bilayer partitioning. 
The bilayer-modifying potencies of the long-chain 
PIP 2 and the short-chain phosphoinositides and other 
phospholipids varied with the experimental system, 
but there was overall concordance between the results 
obtained in planar bilayers and LUVs, indicating that 
bilayer-modifying effects are little affected by changes in 
ionic strength (and the associated changes in ionization) 
or the presence of decane. The key difference we observed 
was with the long-chain PIP 2 s. When added through the 
aqueous solution, brain PIP 2 altered bilayer properties, 
whereas diC 18:1 PIP 2 did not-and diC 18:1 PIP 2 remained 
inactive after prolonged (30 min) incubation. This dif-
ference may be important for the design and interpre-
tation of experiments in biological membranes. To gain 
further insight into these observations, we attempted to 
determine the partition coefficients of the long-chain 
PIP 2 s by separating LUV-partitioned PIP 2 from micellar 
PIP 2 using ultracentrifugation and assessing the PIP 2 
concentrations by phosphorus assay (Chen et al., 1956). 
The density of PIP 2 micelles, however, allows them to sedi-
ment with LUVs (unpublished data), precluding sepa-
ration of LUVs from PIP 2 micelles by centrifugation. 
To determine how the short-and long-chain phospho-
lipids alter lipid bilayer properties, we sought to use gA 
single-channel recordings to explore whether the effects 
could be ascribed to changes in bilayer elasticity or cur-
vature. (Long-chain PIP 2 s also may alter the bilayer lat-
eral organization [Wang and Richards, 2012], but we 
have discovered no evidence for lipid de-mixing.) Both 
long-and short-chain PIP 2 s produce modest relative 
changes in f and . Even when comparing the lifetime 
changes observed with the gA 
-(13) and AgA(15) chan-
nels (Figs. 7 D and 11 D), we cannot unambiguously 
distinguish between PIP 2 effects on curvature and elas-
ticity. Furthermore, it remains unclear to what extent the 
electrostatic interactions among the PIP 2 head groups, 
which would tend to increase the effective head group 
size (Kleinschmidt and Tamm, 2002), would influence 
the intrinsic curvature (Lundbaek et al., 1997) and maybe 
also the head group hydration. Importantly, the PIP 2 s 
had no effect on the gA single-channel current ampli-
tudes, indicating that their mole percentage in the first 
lipid shell around the channel was low (compare the con-
trasting results obtained with other anionic compounds; 
Lundbaek et al., 1997; Bruno et al., 2007). Though not 
con clusive evidence, this suggests that electrostatic effects 
are likely to be of minor importance at physiological 
mole percentages. 
In contrast, diC 8 PC, -PI, -PS, and -PE produce greater 
increases in f and  for the short, as compared with 
the long, gA channels, indicating that short-chain non-
polyphosphoinositide phospholipids increase bilayer 
elasticity. The results, nevertheless, do not rule out fur-
ther effects of lipid curvature (Lundbaek et al., 2010a,b). </p>

<p>Rusinova et al. </p>





<p>section). The apparent differences in bilayer partition-
ing of the diC 18:1 and brain PIP 2 analogues in our assays 
also may manifest themselves in cell physiological stud-
ies, as apparent differences in potency that may not, in 
fact, have a functional basis. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>Both long-and short-chain phosphoinositides are bilayer-
modifying molecules in that they can alter their target 
protein function by a combination of direct (protein bind-
ing) and indirect (bilayer mediated) effects. The changes 
in bilayer properties occur at physiologically relevant 
concentrations (mole percentage of membrane lipids), 
in the case of the long-chain PIP 2 s, and at pharmaco-
logically relevant concentrations, in the case of short-
chain compounds. It thus becomes important to consider 
the changes in membrane properties resulting from 
local PIP 2 depletion or enrichment, which may be a con-
tributing mechanism through which PIP 2 alters protein 
function. Our results suggest a strategy for identifying, 
or excluding, such nonspecific bilayer effects. Effects at 
low micromolar concentrations of (long or short chain) 
PIP 2 s are likely to reflect specific interactions with the 
target protein, whereas effects observed only at 10 µM 
or higher concentrations are likely to reflect, at least in 
part, altered bilayer properties. It is furthermore possi-
ble to test for nonspecific bilayer effects using not only 
short-chain phosphoinositides but also other short-
chain phospholipids. </p>

<p>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health (NIH) 
grant GM021342 and American Recovery and Reinvestment Act 
of 2009 Supplement GM021342-35S1. The peptide facility is sup-
ported by NIH grants GM103429 and GM103450. 
We thank Denise V. Greathouse for the purified gA analogues 
and Donald W. Hilgemann, Helgi I. Ingólfsson, Ruchi Kapoor, 
Jens A. Lundbaek, R. Lea Sanford, and Sidney A. Simon for help-
ful discussions. </p>

<p>Donald W. Hilgemann served as guest editor. </p>

<p>Submitted: 8 January 2013 
Accepted: 6 May 2013 </p>

<p>R E F E R E N C E S </p>





<p>Phosphoinositides alter lipid bilayer properties </p>



<p>Rusinova et al. </p>







<p>Phosphoinositides alter lipid bilayer properties </p>



</text></tei>