<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3650246" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>MicroRNA-29b (miR-29b) expression has been shown to be reduced in non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC) tissues. Here, 
we have identified the oncogene cyclin-dependent protein kinase 6 (CDK6) as a direct target of miR-29b in lung cancer. We 
hypothesized that in vivo restoration of miR-29b and thus targeting of genes important to tumor initiation and progression may 
represent an option for lung cancer treatment. We developed a cationic lipoplexes (LPs)-based carrier that efficiently delivered 
miR-29b both in vitro and in vivo. LPs containing miR-29b (LP-miR-29b) efficiently delivered miR-29b to NSCLC A549 cells, 
reduced the expression of key targets CDK6, DNMT3B, and myeloid cell leukemia sequence 1 (MCL1), as well as cell growth 
and clonogenicity of A549 cells. In addition, the IC 50 for cisplatin in the miR-29b-treated cells was effectively reduced. In a 
xenograft murine model, LPs efficiently accumulated at tumor sites. Systemic delivery of LP-miR-29b increased the tumor miR-
29b expression by approximately fivefold, downregulated the tumor mRNA expression of CDK6, DNMT3B, and MCL1 by ~57.4, 
~40.5, and ~52.4%, respectively, and significantly inhibited tumor growth by ~60% compared with LP-miR-NC (negative control). 
Our results demonstrate that cationic LPs represent an efficient delivery system that holds great potential in the development 
of miRNA-based therapeutics for lung cancer treatment. 
Lung cancer is the leading cause of cancer deaths in the 
United States with a disappointing 15% overall 5-year survival 
rate. 1,2 It is estimated that in 2012, there will be approximately 
226,000 new cases and 160,000 deaths from lung cancer 
(non-small cell and small cell combined). 2 The overall 5-year 
mortality has changed very little since the 1970s. 3 Much of 
this may be attributed to the lack of adequate screening, the 
lack of clarity in what constitutes "high risk" for the develop-
ment of disease, heterogeneity of disease and the limited 
number of novel therapies. 
MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are small (~22 nucleotide) endog-
enous non-coding RNAs that regulate gene expression at 
the posttranscriptional level through RNA interference. 4,5 
MiRNAs are actively involved in many biological processes 
and have an impact on many diseases including cancer. 
Differential expression of miRNAs has been demonstrated 
in many types of cancer. These miRNAs carry both diag-
nostic and prognostic information and have been shown to 
alter cancer cell phenotype by targeting biological pathways 
critical to tumorigenesis. 6-8 For example, recent studies 
have suggested that members of miR-29 family may play 
an important role in cancer by regulating cell proliferation, 
differentiation, apoptosis, migration, and invasion. 9,10 Down-
regulation of miR-29 family members has been observed 
in leukemia, 11-14 melanoma, 15 liver, 16 colon, 17 cervical, 18 
and lung cancer. 19-21 In lung cancer, Fabbri et al. recently </p>

<p>determined that miR-29 members functionally targeted DNA 
methytransferases (DNMT) 3A and 3B, two key enzymes 
involved in DNA methylation and often related to the survival 
of patients with lung cancer. 20 Re-expression of miR-29 in 
lung cancer cells restored normal DNA methylation patterns 
and thus induced re-expression of methylation-silenced 
tumor suppressor genes, such as FHIT and WWOX, and 
inhibited tumorigenicity in vitro and in vivo. Rothschild et al. 
determined that miR-29b was involved in the Src-ID1 sig-
naling pathway thus regulating lung cancer cell migration 
and invasion. 21 As a result, miR-29 has become an attrac-
tive candidate for miRNA-based therapeutics. 
The development of miRNA-based therapeutics represents 
a new strategy in cancer treatment. However, targeted in vivo 
delivery of miRNAs faces many challenges including limited 
stability in serum, rapid blood clearance, off-target effects, and 
poor cellular uptake. 22 Chemical modifications (locked nucleic 
acid, 2′-O-methylation, etc.), and nanoparticle delivery sys-
tems have been developed to overcome these challenges. 
Alternatively, miRNAs can be delivered as a precursor shRNA 
encoded by a plasmid via viral vectors. Delivery by nanopar-
ticles has the advantages of being more cost-effective, less 
immunogenic, less toxic and less oncogenic. 23 However, only 
three groups have published results on the development of 
nanoparticle delivery systems to systemically deliver miRNAs 
for lung cancer treatment. Chen et al. established a liposome-
polycation-hyaluronicacid-based nanoparticle to effectively 
deliver siRNA and miR-34a in a syngeneic model of B16F10 </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy-Nucleic Acids </p>

<p>Therapeutic Delivery of MicroRNA-29b 
Wu et al. </p>



<p>lung metastases. 24 Wiggins et al. and Trang et al. used a 
neutral lipid emulsion, Max Suppressor in vivo RNA LancerII 
(BIOO Scientific) to deliver both miR-34a and let-7 to inhibit 
tumor growth in lung cancer mouse models. 25,26 Our group </p>

<p>developed a cationic lipoplexes (LPs)-based carrier system 
for miR-133b delivery. 27 In the current study, we used a cat-
ionic LPs-based delivery system to efficiently deliver miR-29b 
to suppress tumorigenicity in vitro and in vivo by downregu-
lating multiple oncogenes, including cyclin-dependent pro-
tein kinase 6 (CDK6), DNMT3B, and myeloid cell leukemia 
sequence 1 (MCL1). </p>

<p>Results 
Efficient cellular uptake of LPs 
LPs containing miR-29b (LP-miR-29b) were prepared by 
mixing synthetic miR-29b with empty liposomes at a lipids/ 
miR-29b mass ratio of 12.5 (Figure 1a). As a positive con-
trol, siPORT NeoFX transfection reagent was used to pre-
pare complexes containing miR-29b (NeoFX-miR-29b) by 
following the protocol recommended by the manufacturer. As 
shown in Figure 1b, the resulting LP-miR-29b had a mean 
diameter weighted by volume of 84.0 ± 10.9 nm and zeta 
potential of 17.26 ± 3.15 mV. The resulting NeoFX-miR-29b 
had a mean diameter by volume of 1,276.0 ± 120.8 nm and 
zeta potential of −7.57 ± 2.34 mV. 
To demonstrate more efficient cellular uptake of LPs, A549 
cells were transfected with LPs containing FAM-labeled miR-
Negative Control (LP-FAM-miR-NC) and NeoFX complexes 
containing FAM-labeled miR-NC (NeoFX-FAM-miR-NC) at 
FAM-miR-NC concentration of 100 nmol/l. Cellular uptake 
was evaluated at 4, 24, and 48 hours after transfection by flow </p>

<p>Figure 1 Efficient cellular uptake of lipoplexes. (a) Preparation 
of lipoplexes containing miRNAs. (b) Typical size distributions of 
LP-miR-29b (left) and NeoFX-miR-29b (right). (c) Flow cytometry 
analysis of A549 cellular uptake of LP-FAM-miR-NC and NeoFX-
FAM-miR-NC at FAM-miR-NC concentration of 100 nmol/l. A 
typical flow cytometry dataset at 4 hours after transfection (left). 
Mean fluorescence intensity of FAM averaged on three replicates 
4, 24, and 48 hours after transfection (right, n = 3). (d) Confocal 
microscopy analysis of cellular uptake of LP-FAM-miR-NC and 
NeoFX-FAM-miR-NC 4 hours after transfection at FAM-miR-NC 
concentration of 100 nmol/l. </p>

<p>miRNA </p>

<p>Empty liposome </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>RT </p>

<p>15 minutes </p>

<p>Lipoplexes 
containing miRNA </p>

<p>30,000 </p>

<p>Untreated </p>

<p>Lipoplexes FAM-miR-NC </p>

<p>NeoFX FAM-miR-NC </p>

<p>Untreated </p>

<p>Lipoplexes 
FAM-miR-NC </p>

<p>NeoFX 
FAM-miR-NC </p>

<p>Untreated </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 
Count </p>

<p>80 
4 hours </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>10 2 10 3 </p>

<p>FAM </p>

<p>10 4 10 5 </p>

<p>Lipoplexes FAM-miR-NC 
NeoFX FAM-miR-NC </p>

<p>25,000 </p>

<p>20,000 </p>

<p>Mean fluorescence intensity </p>

<p>15,000 </p>

<p>10,000 </p>

<p>5,000 </p>

<p>0 
4 hours 
24 hours 
48 hours </p>

<p>100 
Lipoplexes miR-29b 
80 </p>

<p>60 
Volume </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>4 
2 
3 
5 6 
8 
7 9 
4 
4 
2 
2 
2 
6 
6 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 
NeoFX miR-29b 
80 </p>

<p>60 
Volume </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Diameter (nm) 
Diameter (nm) </p>

<p>DAPI </p>

<p>20 µm 
20 µm 
2 0 µm 
2 0 µm </p>

<p>20 µm 
20 µm 
2 0 µm 
2 0 µm </p>

<p>20 µm 
20 µm 
2 0 µm 
2 0 µm </p>

<p>FAM-miR-NC 
Phase contrast 
Merged </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>miR-29b expression </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Normal tissue </p>

<p>Tumor tissue </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
0.01 nmol/l 
0.05 nmol/l 
miRNA concentration </p>

<p>0.10 nmol/l </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>CDK6 3′UTR luciferase activity </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>miR-NC </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>miR-29b 
Untreated </p>

<p>N 1 
T 1 N 2 
T 2 N 3 
T 3 N 4 
T 4 N 5 
T 5 N 6 
T 6 N 7 
T 7 N 8 
T 8 N 9 
T 9 
N 1 0 
T 1 0 </p>

<p>Untreated </p>

<p>Figure 2 MiR-29b dysregulation and target expression. 
(a) Expression of miR-29b was significantly down regulated in 7 out 
of 10 NSCLC tumor tissue samples compared with normal tissue 
samples. (b) CDK6 was a direct target of miR-29b. Three CDK6 
complementary sites were cloned into the 3′-UTR of the firefly 
luciferase gene and transfected with miR-29b in CHO cells. MiR-
29b significantly reduced the luciferase activity with respect to the 
scrambled miR-NC sequences (n = 3, *P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>www.moleculartherapy.org/mtna </p>

<p>Therapeutic Delivery of MicroRNA-29b 
Wu et al. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>cytometry (Figure 1c). At 4 hours after transfection the mean 
fluorescence intensity of FAM in A549 cells treated by LP-FAM-
miR-NC was much higher than that of NeoFX-FAM-miR-NC. 
In addition, LP-FAM-miR-NC transfected cells demonstrated 
a narrower FAM fluorescence distribution than NeoFX-FAM-
miR-NC. Confocal microscopy images also showed stronger 
and more uniform cellular uptake of LP-FAM-miR-NC than 
NeoFX-FAM-miR-NC (Figure 1d). These results demon-
strate that LPs are a more efficient delivery system in vitro 
than NeoFX complexes. At 24 and 48 hours after transfection, 
the mean fluorescence intensity of FAM was progressively 
decreased in A549 cells transfected by both LPs and NeoFX 
complexes, which was due to the degradation of FAM-labeled 
miR-NC and the "dilution" effect by the cell growth. On the 
basis of the observation, delivery of miR-29b every 48 hours 
might represent a reasonable frequency if repeated delivery </p>

<p>is desired. Therefore, LP-miR-29b was delivered every other 
day in the subsequent in vivo studies. </p>

<p>MiR-29b expression is reduced in human non-small-cell 
lung cancer 
We analyzed the expression of miR-29b and CDK6 in 10 
pairs of human non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) tumor 
tissue samples and adjacent normal tissue samples by quan-
titative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR). As shown in Figure 2a, 
the expression of miR-29b was significantly downregulated 
in 7 out of 10 NSCLC tumor tissue samples compared with 
normal tissue samples (P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>MiR-29b directly targets CDK6 
Next, we sought to determine whether CDK6 was a direct target 
of miR-29b in lung cancer. Three CDK6 complementary sites </p>

<p>1,400 </p>

<p>1,200 </p>

<p>1,000 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>Mature miR-29b expression </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 
Untreat 
miR-29b 
lipoplexes </p>

<p>miR-NC 
lipoplexes </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>miR-29b 
NeoFX </p>

<p>miR-NC 
NeoFX </p>

<p>Untreat </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>CDK6 expression </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>miR-29b 
lipoplexes </p>

<p>miR-NC 
lipoplexes </p>

<p>miR-29b 
NeoFX </p>

<p>miR-NC 
NeoFX </p>

<p>** 
* </p>

<p>Untreat </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>DNMT3B expression </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>miR-29b 
lipoplexes </p>

<p>miR-NC 
lipoplexes </p>

<p>miR-29b 
NeoFX </p>

<p>miR-NC 
NeoFX </p>

<p>** 
* </p>

<p>Untreat </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>MCL-1 expression </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>miR-29b 
lipoplexes </p>

<p>Lipoplexes 
Untreated </p>

<p>Untreated </p>

<p>CDK6 
(36 K) </p>

<p>DNMT3B 
(96 K) </p>

<p>β-tubulin 
(50 K) </p>

<p>MCL1 
(40 K) </p>

<p>β-tubulin 
(50 K) </p>

<p>miR-29b miR-NC </p>

<p>NeoFX </p>

<p>miR-29b miR-NC </p>

<p>miR-NC 
lipoplexes </p>

<p>miR-29b 
NeoFX </p>

<p>miR-NC 
NeoFX </p>

<p>miR-29b 
Lipoplexes NeoFX </p>

<p>miR-NC 
Lipoplexes NeoFX </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Figure 3 LP-miR-29b downregulates target gene expression in vitro. (a) Expression of mature miR-29b and downregulation of CDK6, 
DNMT3B, and MCL1 expression at (b-d) mRNA level and (e) protein level 48 hours after A549 cells were transfected with LP-miR-29b, 
NeoFX-miR-29b, LP-miR-NC, and NeoFX-miR-NC at microRNA concentration of 100 nmol/l (*P &lt; 0.05 and **P &lt; 0.01) (n = 3). </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy-Nucleic Acids </p>

<p>Therapeutic Delivery of MicroRNA-29b 
Wu et al. </p>



<p>were cloned into the 3′-UTR (untranslated region) of the firefly 
luciferase gene and transfected with miR-29b in CHO cells. As 
shown in Figure 2b, miR-29b significantly reduced the lucifer-
ase activity compared with the scrambled sequences (P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Downregulation of CDK6, DNMT3B, and MCL1 expression 
by LP-miR-29b 
A549 cells were transfected with LP-miR-29b, NeoFX-miR-
29b, LP-miR-NC, or NeoFX-miR-NC at miRNA concentration 
of 100 nmol/l. At 48 hours after transfection, compared with 
untreated control, mature miR-29b expression was increased 
~1,230-folds in cells transfected with LP-miR-29b, and ~98-
fold in those transfected by NeoFX-miR-29b, demonstrating 
that LPs were a more efficient carrier system than NeoFX 
complexes (Figure 3a). The expression of target genes, 
CDK6, DNMT3B, and MCL1, was more efficiently downregu-
lated at both mRNA and protein levels in cells transfected 
with LP-miR-29b compared with NeoFX-miR-29b (Figure 
3b-e). LP-miR-NC and NeoFX-miR-NC did not cause a non-
specific effect on the expression of mature miR-29b or three 
target genes. </p>

<p>Inhibition of A549 tumorigenicity by LP-miR-29b in vitro 
A549 cells were transfected with LP-miR-29b, NeoFX-miR-
29b, LP-miR-NC, or NeoFX-miR-NC at microRNA concen-
tration of 100 nmol/l. After transfection, the tumorigenicity of 
A549 cells was evaluated by measuring cell growth, clono-
genic survival and IC 50 following treatment with cisplatin. As 
shown in Figure 4a, LP-miR-29b significantly inhibited the 
growth of A549 cells compared with NeoFX-miR-29b, LP-
miR-NC, NeoFX-miR-NC, and untreated control. In the clo-
nogenic survival assay, the number of colonies was reduced 
by ~50% in the cells transfected with LP-miR-29b compared 
with untreated control (Figure 4b). No significant difference 
was found between untreated cells and cells transfected 
by NeoFX-miR-29b, LP-miR-NC, and NeoFX-miR-NC. LP-
based transfection also increased the sensitivity of A549 
cells to chemotherapeutic agent cisplatin. The IC 50 of cis-
platin was reduced from ~11.77 µmol/l in untreated cells to 
~7.90 µmol/l in cells transfected by LP-miR-29b (Figure 4c). </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
0 
5 
10 </p>

<p>Cisplatin concentration (µmol/l) </p>

<p>20 
30 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 
Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 
Colony number </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Day 0 </p>

<p>Untreated 
Lipoplexes miR-29b Lipoplexes miR-NC </p>

<p>NeoFX miR-29b 
NeoFX miR-NC </p>

<p>Untreated </p>

<p>Untreated, IC 50 = 11.77 ± 1.82 µmol/l 
Lipoplexes miR-29b, IC 50 = 7.90 ± 0.95 µmol/l * </p>

<p>Lipoplexes miR-NC, IC 50 = 11.92 ± 1.56 µmol/l </p>

<p>NeoFX miRNC, IC 50 = 12.62 ± 1.63 µmol/l </p>

<p>NeoFX miR-29b, IC 50 = 12.94 ± 2.14 µmol/l </p>

<p>Lipoplexes 
miR-29b </p>

<p>Lipoplexes 
miR-NC </p>

<p>NeoFX 
miR-29b </p>

<p>NeoFX 
miR-NC </p>

<p>Day 1 </p>

<p>*P &lt; 0.05 
**P &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>*P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>*P &lt; 0.005 </p>

<p>Day 2 
D ay 3 
D ay 4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Total cell number (e5) </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Untreated </p>

<p>Lipoplexes miR-29b </p>

<p>NeoFX miR-29b </p>

<p>Lipoplexes miR-NC </p>

<p>NeoFX miR-NC </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Figure 4 LP-miR-29b inhibit tumorigenicity of A549 cells in 
vitro. (a) Growth curve, (b) colonogenic survival, and (c) IC 50 
of cisplatin for A549 cells after transfection with LP-miR-29b, 
NeoFX-miR-29b, LP-miR-NC, and NeoFX-miR-NC at microRNA 
concentration of 100 nmol/l (*P &lt; 0.05 and **P &lt; 0.005) (n = 3). </p>

<p>Untreated </p>

<p>Untreated Lipoplexes 
Cy5-ODN </p>

<p>10 µm 
10 µm </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>400 
× 10 6 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>10 µm 
10 µm </p>

<p>10 µm 
10 µm 
10 µm 
10 µm </p>

<p>Lipoplexes 
Cy5-ODN </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Figure 5 Accumulation of LPs at tumor sites. A549 cells were 
implanted into the flanks of 6-week-old, nude mice and tumors 
were allowed to develop to ~100 mm 3 without treatment. LP-
Cy5-ODN was injected through tail vein at 1.5 mg Cy5-ODN/kg 
mouse weight. After 4 hours, mice were killed and tumor tissues 
were analyzed using (a) IVIS imaging system and (b) confocal 
microscopy. The Cy5 fluorescence from the tumor tissues indicated 
the accumulation of LPs in the tumor sites (n = 6). </p>

<p>www.moleculartherapy.org/mtna </p>

<p>Therapeutic Delivery of MicroRNA-29b 
Wu et al. </p>



<p>NeoFX-miR-29b, LP-miR-NC, and NeoFX-miR-NC did not 
affect the sensitivity of A549 cells to cisplatin treatment. </p>

<p>Inhibition of A549 tumorigenicity by LP-miR-29b in vivo 
The antitumor effects of LP-miR-29b were evaluated in a 
xenograft murine model using A549 cells. A549 cells were 
implanted into the flanks of 6-week-old, female athymic mice. 
Tumors were allowed to develop to ~100 mm 3 before treat-
ment. To demonstrate the delivery of LPs to the tumor site, LPs 
containing Cy5-labeled oligodeoxynucleotide (LP-Cy5-ODN) </p>

<p>were injected into mice through tail vein at a dosage of 1.5 
mg Cy5-ODN/kg mouse weight. Four hours later, the mice 
were killed and tumor tissues were collected for IVIS imaging 
(Figure 5a) and confocal microscopy analysis (Figure 5b). 
Results showed that the LPs successfully delivered Cy5-
ODN to the flank tumor sites demonstrating that they were 
an effective carrier system to systemically deliver miRNAs 
in vivo. Next, at 22 days following implantation, mice with 
established tumors (tumor volume ~100 mm 3 ) were randomly 
assigned to four groups (n = 6). LP-miR-29b, LP-miR-NC, at </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>Gene expression </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>2 
CDK6 
DNMT3B 
MCL1 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Mature miR-29b 
expression in tumor </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>22 
24 </p>

<p>*P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>26 
28 
30 
32 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>34 
36 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 
Tumor volume (mm 3 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>700 </p>

<p>800 
Untreated (n = 6) </p>

<p>Untreated 
Lipoplexes 
miR-29b </p>

<p>Lipoplexes 
miR-NC </p>

<p>Empty 
liposomes </p>

<p>Untreated 
Lipoplexes 
miR-29b </p>

<p>Lipoplexes 
miR-NC </p>

<p>Untreated </p>

<p>TUNEL </p>

<p>Ki67 </p>

<p>Lipoplexes miR-29b 
Lipoplexes miR-NC </p>

<p>Empty 
liposome </p>

<p>Untreated 
Lipoplexes 
miR-29b </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Lipoplexes 
miR-NC </p>

<p>Empty 
liposome </p>

<p>Lipoplexes miR-29b (n = 6) 
Lipoplexes miR-NC (n = 6) 
Empty liposome (n = 6) </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>c 
d </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>Figure 6 LP-miR-29b inhibit tumorigenicity of A549 cells in vivo. (a,b) Tumor growth. A549 cells were implanted into the flanks of 
6-week-old, nude mice and tumors were allowed to develop ~100 mm 3 without treatment. At 22 days after implantation, mice were treated 
with LP-miR-29b, LP-miR-NC, and empty liposomes by intravenous injection at 1.5 mg miR/kg mouse weight every other day for seven 
injections. Tumors were measured using a digital caliper and tumor volumes were calculated (n = 6,*P &lt; 0.001). (c) Expression of mature 
miR29b in tumors (n = 6, *P &lt; 0.005). (d) Expression of CDK6, DNMT3B, and MCL1 was significantly downregulated in the tumors of mice 
treated with LP-miR-29b than those treated with LP-miR-NC (n = 6, *P &lt; 0.01). (e) Ki-67 staining and TUNEL staining of tumor tissues of 
untreated mice and mice treated with LP-miR-29b and LP-miR-NC. </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy-Nucleic Acids </p>

<p>Therapeutic Delivery of MicroRNA-29b 
Wu et al. </p>



<p>dosages of 1.5 mg microRNA/kg mouse weight, or match-
ing lipid dose of empty liposomes were given via intrave-
nous injection every other day for a total of seven injections 
(Q2Dx7). Mice were killed 2 days after the last injection. As 
shown in Figure 6a,b, at the conclusion of the experiment, 
the mice treated with LP-miR-29b had significantly smaller 
tumors compared with LP-miR-NC (60.8% inhibition, n = 6, 
P &lt; 0.001), empty liposomes (69.3% inhibition, n = 6, P &lt; 
0.001), and untreated control group (72.5% inhibition, n = 6, 
P &lt; 0.001). Tumor tissues were collected and evaluated for 
the expression of mature miR-29b (Figure 6c) and three tar-
get genes (Figure 6d) using qRT-PCR. In the tumors of mice 
treated with LP-miR-29b, the expression of mature miR-29b 
was increased ~4.7-fold and the mRNA expression of CDK6, 
DNMT3B, and MCL1 was downregulated by ~57.4, ~40.5, 
and ~52.4%, respectively compared with mice treated with 
LP-miR-NC. No significant difference in the expression of 
mature miR-29b and three target genes were found between 
untreated control group and the two groups treated with 
LP-miR-NC or empty liposomes (P &lt; 0.05). Tumor tissues 
from LP-miR-29b-treated mice showed reduced expression 
of Ki-67 and increased number of apoptotic cells (TUNEL) </p>

<p>(Figure 6e), indicating LP-miR-29b actively inhibit cell prolif-
eration and stimulated the apoptosis process. </p>

<p>Cytotoxicity evaluation of LP-miR-29b in vivo 
The cytotoxicity effect of LP-miR-29b in the major mouse 
organs including heart, liver, and kidney was evaluated 
by H&amp;E and TUNEL staining and compared with those of 
untreated control mice and LP-miR-NC-treated mice. We 
have previously demonstrated that our nanoparticles did not 
induce toxicity in the lung tissues. 27 As shown in Figure 7a,b, 
no significant pathology was observed among untreated 
control, LP-miR-29b-treated mice and LP-miR-NC-treated 
mice, suggesting that LP-miR-29b did not induce significant 
cytotoxicity to major organs. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>MiRNAs can serve as tumor suppressors or oncogenes 
by regulating processes essential to cancer development 
including proliferation, survival, apoptosis, and metasta-
sis. 6-8 Through the simultaneous regulation of multiple bio-
logical pathways, miRNA mimics may represent a powerful 
therapeutic strategy in cancer treatment. 7,8 However, there 
are several obstacles to reaching the in vivo application of 
miRNAs as therapy. Here, we present a cationic LPs-based 
carrier system that efficiently delivered miR-29b to A549 
NSCLC cells demonstrating an in vitro and in vivo reduction 
in tumorigenicity by targeting multiple oncogenes including 
CDK6, DNMT3B, and MCL1. 
In our LPs formulation, 1,2-di-O-octadecenyl-3-trimethyl-
ammonium propane (DOTMA, chloride salt), a cationic lipid 
previously used in nonviral vectors of gene therapy, was 
selected as the building block of our miRNA delivery system. 
DOTMA has shown high transfection activities in vitro and 
in vivo. 28 DOTMA also confers a positive surface charge to 
the LPs which in turn facilitates the interaction between LPs 
and the negatively charged cell membrane providing more 
efficient and uniform cellular uptake. Cholesterol, a neutral 
lipid, was chosen as a helper lipid because it can improve 
transfection efficiency in vivo, protecting oligonucleotides 
from degradation, and facilitating the interaction between LPs 
and the cell membranes. 29 d-α-Tocopheryl polyethylenegly-
col 1,000 succinate (vitamin E TPGS), a short poly(ethylene 
glycol) (PEG) molecule linked to vitamin E, was added to 
increase the stability and circulation time of LPs in vivo. In 
addition, confocal microscopy images showed that the LPs 
were able to deliver miR-29b to the nucleus of A549 cells, 
which is important because endogenous miR-29b is signifi-
cantly enriched in the cell nucleus. 9 
MiR-29b, a potential prognostic marker, targets oncogenes 
and antiapoptotic genes, and is usually silenced or downregu-
lated in many cancers. In acute myeloid leukemia and mantle 
cell lymphoma, CDK6 has been validated as a direct target of 
miR-29b. 13,30 In HPV-mediated cervical cancer, restoration of 
miR-29b expression was shown to prevent malignant trans-
formation of cervical cells by targeting CDK6. 18 In NSCLC, 
miR-29b directly targets DNMT3A and 3B. The expression of 
miR-29b is inversely correlated to DNMT3A and 3B expres-
sion. 20 In acute myeloid leukemia, cholangiocarcinoma, and </p>

<p>Figure 7 Cytotoxicity evaluation of LP-miR-29b in major 
organs. (a) H&amp;E staining of liver, heart, and kidney. (b) TUNEL 
staining for liver, heart, and kidney. </p>

<p>Untreated </p>

<p>Liver </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Heart </p>

<p>Kidney </p>

<p>Liver </p>

<p>Heart </p>

<p>Kidney </p>

<p>Lipoplexes miR-29b 
Lipoplexes miR-NC </p>

<p>Untreated 
Lipoplexes miR-29b 
Lipoplexes miR-NC </p>

<p>www.moleculartherapy.org/mtna </p>

<p>Therapeutic Delivery of MicroRNA-29b 
Wu et al. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>hepatocellular carcinoma, miR-29b has been shown to target 
the expression of MCL1 protein, which affects malignant cell 
survival. 13,16,31 To the best of our best knowledge, no stud-
ies have shown the relationship between miR-29b expres-
sion and CDK6 expression in NSCLC tumor tissue samples; 
therefore, we evaluated the expression of miR-29b in 10 pairs 
of human NSCLC tumor tissue samples and adjacent nor-
mal tissue samples. We found that the expression of miR-
29b was downregulated in the majority of NSCLC tissue 
samples compared with normal tissue samples (Figure 2a). 
We then demonstrated that CDK6 was a direct target of miR-
29b (Figure 2b), which was further validated by the down-
regulation of CDK6 gene expression by LP-miR-29b in vitro 
(Figure 3) and in vivo (Figure 6). 
The antitumorigenic properties of LP-miR-29b were first 
evaluated in A549 cells. Because the delivery efficiency 
of LPs was superior to that of NeoFX complexes, mature 
miR-29b expression in A549 cells transfected by LPs was 
~12.5 times higher, and all three targets genes (CDK6, 
DNMT3B, and MCL1) were successfully downregulated 
at both mRNA and protein levels (Figure 3). LP-miR-29b 
also showed greater biological activity than NeoFX-miR-
29b in A549 cells. Compared with untreated control, ~62 
and ~18% inhibition in A549 cell growth was observed in 
cells treated by LP-miR-29b and NeoFX-miR-29b respec-
tively. The clonogenic survival of A549 cells was reduced 
by ~53%, and the IC 50 of cisplatin was decreased by ~33% 
after treatment with LP-miR-29b compared with untreated 
control (Figure 4). No significant effects were observed in 
the cells transfected by NeoFX-miR-29b. In the xenograft 
mouse model, we observed that LPs successfully accumu-
lated at the tumor sites (Figure 5). Following seven intra-
venous injections of LP-miR-29b at a dosage of 1.5 mg 
miR-29b/kg mouse weight, tumor growth was significantly 
inhibited (Figure 6a,b). Systemic miR-29b delivery by LPs 
increased tumor miR-29b expression by ~4.7-fold compared 
with mice treated with LP-miR-NC (Figure 6c). The tumor 
expression of CDK6, DNMT3B, and MCL1 was signifi-
cantly downregulated compared with the other three control 
groups (Figure 6d). Results of Ki-67 and TUNEL staining 
showed that tumor tissues from LP-miR-29b-treated mice 
had lower expression of Ki-67 and more apoptotic cells 
which was in agreement with the observed downregulation 
of CDK6 and MCL1 expression (Figure 6e). In addition, we 
did not observe significant cytotoxicity effects of LP-miR-
29b on the vital organs of mice, suggesting the off-target 
effects of miR-29b were minimal (Figure 7a,b). 
In summary, we have developed a novel cationic LPs-based 
delivery system that efficiently delivered miR-29b and thus 
inhibited the tumorigenicity of NSCLC in vitro and in vivo. Our 
results demonstrate a potential for LPs in the development 
of miRNA-based therapeutics for lung cancer treatment. In 
the future, chemotherapeutic drugs, such as cisplatin, might 
be combined with miRNA-based therapeutic strategies to 
enhance therapeutic efficacy. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Materials. 1,2-Di-O-octadecenyl-3-trimethylammonium pro-
pane (DOTMA, chloride salt) was purchased from Avanti </p>

<p>Polar Lipids (Alabaster, AL). Cholesterol was purchased 
from Sigma-Aldrich (St Louis, MO). d-α-Tocopheryl poly-
ethyleneglycol 1,000 succinate (vitamin E TPGS) was pur-
chased from Eastman (Kingsport, TN). MiRIDIAN mimic 
hsa-miR-29b (C-300521-05, mature miR sequence: 
5′-UAGCACCAUUUGAAAUCAGUGUU-3′) and miRIDIAN 
mimic NC#1 (CN-001000-01, mature miR sequence: 5′-UCAC 
AACCUCCUAGAAAGAGUAGA-3′) were purchased from 
Dharmacon RNAi Technologies (Lafayette, CO). FAM dye-
labeled pre-miR negative control #1 (FAM-miR-NC, Ambion, 
AM17121) was purchased from Ambion (Austin, TX). Cy5 
dye-labeled oligodeoxynucleotides (Cy5-ODN, 5′-Cy5-TCT 
CCC AGC GTG CGC CAT-3′) was custom synthesized by 
Alpha DNA (Montreal, Quebec, Canada). </p>

<p>Experimental animals. Female athymic nude mice of age 4-6 
weeks (weight 18-20 g) were purchased from Charles River 
Laboratories International (strain code 490; Wilmington, MA). 
All work performed on animals was in accordance with a pro-
tocol approved by the IACUC at the Ohio State University. </p>

<p>Human tissues. Ten pairs of human non-small cell lung ade-
nocarcinomas tissue samples and adjacent uninvolved tissue 
samples were obtained the Cooperative Human Tissue Net-
work through an IRB approved protocol. qRT-PCR was then 
performed for miR-29b (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA; 
assay ID 002247) and presented as 2 −ΔC </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>. Statistical signifi-
cance was based on a Student's t-test. </p>

<p>Cell culture. A549 cells and CHO cells were obtained from 
the American Type Culture Collection (Manassas, VA). A549 
cells were routinely cultured in a 75 cm 2 T flask containing 
15 ml of RPMI 1640 media supplemented with 10% heat-
inactivated fetal bovine serum (16,000; Invitrogen, Carlsbad, 
CA). CHO cells were maintained in Dulbecco's modified 
Eagle's medium (Invitrogen) supplemented with 10% fetal 
bovine serum (Atlanta Biologicals, Lawrenceville, GA), 1× 
antibiotic-antimycotic (Invitrogen), and 0.0175 mg/ml l-pro-
line (Sigma-Aldrich). The cells were seeded into T flasks at a 
concentration of 1 × 10 5 viable cells/ml and incubated at 37 
°C in a humidified atmosphere containing 5% CO 2 . The cells 
were subcultured every 2 days. </p>

<p>Preparation of LP-miR-29b. Empty liposomes were 
prepared first by injecting a lipid mixture in ethanol 
(DOTMA:cholesterol:TPGS at 49.5:49.5:1 molar ratio) into 
20 mmol/l HEPES buffer (pH = 7.4) to achieve 10% ethanol 
and 90% aqueous in the final mixture. LP-miR-29b was pre-
pared by adding miR-29b to empty liposomes at the lipids to 
miR-29b mass ratio of 12.5. The mixture was incubated at 
room temperature for 15 minutes and used immediately. </p>

<p>Particle size and surface charge measurement. The size 
distributions of LP-miR-29b were measured by dynamic 
light scattering (Brookhaven Instruments, Holtsville, NY; BI 
200SM). The wavelength of the laser was 632.8 nm, and 
the detection angle was 90°. The size distributions of three 
batches of LP-miR-29b prepared independently were mea-
sured at 20 °C, and the mean diameter by volume ± SD was 
reported. The surface charges of LP-miR-29b were mea-
sured using ZetaPALS zeta potential analyzer (Brookhaven 
Instruments, Holtsville, NY). Three batches of independently </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy-Nucleic Acids </p>

<p>Therapeutic Delivery of MicroRNA-29b 
Wu et al. </p>



<p>prepared LPs were diluted in 20 mmol/l HEPES buffer. Three 
measurements, each consisting of five runs, were performed 
at 20 °C. The Smoluchowski model was used to calculate the 
zeta potential, and the mean ± SD was reported. </p>

<p>Luciferase reporter constructs. A 1,271-bp fragment of the 
human CDK6 3′-UTR (NM_001259, transcript variant 1, 
mRNA) that encompassed three putative miR-29 binding sites 
(http://www.targetscan.org, TargetScan 6.2, release date 
June, 2012) was PCR-amplified using the following sense 
(5′-ATACTCGAGTTCCCTGCTACCATCCTGGCTTGTCC-3′) 
and antisense (5′-ATAGCGGCCGCCATCATCTGACAATA-
AATACCTAC-3′) primers using standard procedures, a proof-
reading polymerase (Platinum Pfu; Invitrogen) and human 
genomic DNA as template. The XhoI and NotI restriction 
endonuclease sites incorporated into the sense and anti-
sense primers above are shown in boldface. After PCR 
amplification, the amplicon was double digested with XhoI/ 
NotI for 2 hours following the manufacturer's protocol. The 
PCR product was subsequently subcloned into the XhoI/NotI 
sites downstream of the Renilla luciferase (r-luc) reporter 
gene (psiCHECK-2; Promega). The authenticity and orienta-
tion of the inserts relative to the Renilla luciferase gene were 
confirmed by dideoxy sequencing. The resulting recombinant 
plasmids were designated psiCHECK/CDK6-UTR. Finally, 
transformed bacterial cultures were grown and each reporter 
construct was purified using the PureLink Hipure Plasmid 
Maxiprep kit (Invitrogen). </p>

<p>Transfection and luciferase assay. MiR-29b and negative 
control mimics (partially double-stranded RNAs that mimic 
the Dicer cleavage product and are subsequently processed 
into their respective mature miRNAs) were obtained from 
Dharmacon (Lafayette, CO). Transfection of CHO cells were 
transfected with psiCHECK/CDK6-UTR construct (10 ng per 
well) using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen) and the appropri-
ate miRNA precursor as indicated. After 24 hours, CHO cells 
were washed and lysed with Passive Lysis Buffer (Promega), 
and firefly and Renilla luciferase activities were determined 
using the Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay System (Pro-
mega) and a luminometer. Renilla luciferase expression in 
the psiCHECK vector is generated via an SV40 promoter. 
In addition, the psiCHECK-2 vector possesses a secondary 
firefly reporter expression cassette which is under the con-
trol of the HSV-TK promoter. This firefly reporter cassette has 
been specifically designed to be an intraplasmid transfection 
normalization reporter; thus when using the psiCHECK-2 
vector, the Renilla luciferase signal is normalized to the firefly 
luciferase signal. </p>

<p>Transfection of A549 cells with LP-miR-29b. A549 cells were 
seeded at 2 × 10 5 viable cells/well in six-well plates contain-
ing 2 ml of culture medium supplemented with 10% fetal 
bovine serum. The cells were incubated at 37 °C in a humidi-
fied atmosphere containing 5% CO 2 overnight. The culture 
medium was then replaced with medium containing no fetal 
bovine serum. LP-miR-29b was then added to the cells at 
miR-29b concentration of 100 nmol/l. The cells were incu-
bated at 37 °C for 4 hours, and then transferred into 2 ml fresh 
culture medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum. 
All transfection experiments were performed in triplicate. </p>

<p>NeoFX-miR-29b was used as the positive control. The trans-
fection of miR-29b via siPORT NeoFX transfection reagent 
(Invitrogen; AM4511) was performed by following the manu-
facturer's protocol. Briefly, 5 µl of NeoFX was mixed with 95 
µl OptiMEM (Invitrogen; 11058021) and the mixture was 
incubated at room temperature for 10 minutes. MiR-29b was 
diluted in OptiMEM and then added into the NeoFX trans-
fection agent. The final mixture was incubated at room tem-
perature for another 10 minutes and used for transfection by 
following the same transfection procedure as for transfection 
of LPs. Untreated cells and cells transfected by scrambled 
microRNA mimic with no target, miR-NC, which were delivered 
by both LPs and NeoFX, were negative controls in our work. </p>

<p>Cellular uptake of LP-FAM-miR-NC. A549 cellular uptake of 
LP-FAM-miR-NC was studied by flow cytometry (BD LSR II, 
San Jose, CA, USA) and laser scanning confocal microscopy 
(Olympus FV1000, Center Valley, PA). A549 cells were trans-
fected with LP-FAM-miR-NC or NeoFX-FAM-miR-NC. The 
cells were harvested 0, 24, and 48 hours after transfection. 
Briefly, the cells were first detached from culture plates using 
0.25% trypsin, washed with PBS twice and fixed using 4% 
paraformaldehyde. In the flow cytometry experiments, the flu-
orescence signals of FAM were observed in the FITC chan-
nel. For each sample, 10,000 events were collected, and the 
average results of three replicates were reported. In confo-
cal microscopy experiments, A549 cells were counterstained 
with DAPI and mounted on glass slides. The fluorescence 
signals of DAPI and FAM were observed in the DAPI (dichroic 
mirror 430-470 nm) and FAM (dichroic mirror 505-605 nm) 
channels respectively. </p>

<p>Expression of mature miR-29b, CDK6, DNMT3B, and MCL1 
mRNAs in A549 cells by qRT-PCR. Total RNA was extracted 
using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen; 15596-018) and chloroform, 
further purified by isopropanol precipitation and washed by 
70% ethanol. To measure mature miR-29b expression, the 
total RNA was first reverse transcribed into cDNA using the 
TaqMan MicroRNA reverse transcription kit (Applied Biosys-
tems; 4366596). The qRT-PCR amplification of cDNA was 
then performed using TaqMan MicroRNA assay (Applied 
Biosystems; assay ID 002247). The mature miR-29b expres-
sion was determined by the ΔΔC t method and normalized to 
RNU48 (Applied Biosystems; assay ID 001006), which was 
the endogenous control in the corresponding samples, and 
relative to the untreated control cells. 
To measure the expression of CDK6, DNMT3B, and 
MCL1 mRNAs, the total RNA was transcribed into cDNA 
using the High Capacity cDNA Reverse Transcription Kit 
(Applied Biosystems; 4368814). The resulting cDNA was 
amplified by qRT-PCR (Applied Biosystems; CDK6 assay ID: 
Hs01026371_m1, DNMT3B assay ID: Hs00171876_m1, and 
MCL1 assay IDHs03043899_m1). Relative gene expression 
values were determined by the ΔΔC t method. The expression 
of CDK6, DNMT3B, and MCL1 mRNAs was normalized to 
GAPDH (Applied Biosystems; assay ID: Hs02758991_g1), 
which was the endogenous reference in the corresponding 
samples, and relative to the untreated control cells. </p>

<p>Expression of CDK6, DNMT3B, and MCL1 protein in A549 
cells by western blotting. Protein from A549 cells was extracted </p>

<p>www.moleculartherapy.org/mtna </p>

<p>Therapeutic Delivery of MicroRNA-29b 
Wu et al. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>using RIPA lysis buffer (Sigma-Aldrich; R0278) containing a 
protease inhibitor cocktail (Sigma-Aldrich; P8340) on ice for 
15 minutes. The cell lysate was centrifuged for 15 minutes 
at 12,000g at 4 °C. The protein concentration of the super-
natant was measured by bicinchoninic acid (BCA) assay 
(Biorad, Hercules, CA; 500-0006), and 50µg of protein from 
each sample was loaded in a 4-15% Ready Gel Tris-HCl 
polyacrylamide gel (BioRad), and then transferred to a PVDF 
membrane (GE). After blocking with 5% nonfat milk in Tris-
buffered saline/Tween-20 for 1 hour, the membranes were 
incubated with mouse antihuman CDK6 antibody (1:2,000; 
Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, MA; 3136S), rabbit anti-
human DNMT3B antibody (1:1,000; Cell Signaling Technol-
ogy; 2161S), rabbit antihuman MCL1 antibody (1:500; Cell 
Signaling Technology; 4572S), or mouse antihuman β-tubulin 
antibody (1:10,000; Sigma; T8328) at 4 °C overnight, followed 
by incubation with horseradish peroxidase-conjugated goat 
antirabbit IgG (1:2,000; Santa Cruz Biotechnology; SC2004) 
and horseradish peroxidase-conjugated goat antimouse IgG 
(1:2,000; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Dallas, TX; SC2005) for 
1 hour at room temperature. The membrane was then devel-
oped with Pierce SuperSignal West Pico or Dura Extended 
DurationSubstrate (Pierce, Rockford, IL) and imaged with 
KodakX-OMAT film (Kodak, Rochester, NY). </p>

<p>Growth curve of A549 cells. At 1, 2, 3, and 4 days after trans-
fection, the A549 cells were stained with Trypan Blue (0.4%) 
(Invitrogen; 15250-061) and viable cells were counted using 
Hemocytometer. Each sample had three replicates and the 
mean ± SD was reported. </p>

<p>Clonogenic assay. At 24 hours after transfection, A549 cells 
were harvested and resuspended in the culture medium. In 
six-well plates, 2,000 cells/well were seeded and allowed to 
grow until visible colonies formed (6 days). Cell colonies were 
fixed using 4% paraformaldehyde and stained with 0.5% 
crystal violet in water at room temperature for 2 hours. Cell 
colonies were then washed three times with tap water and 
air-dried. Colonies with &gt;50 cells were counted under micro-
scope. Each sample had three replicates and the mean ± SD 
was reported. </p>

<p>LP-Cy5-ODN accumulation at tumor sites. Three million 
A549 cells were resuspended in PBS and implanted into 
the flanks of 6-week-old, female athymic nude mice. Tumors 
were allowed to develop to ~100 mm 3 without any treat-
ment. LP-Cy5-ODN was injected through tail vein at dosage 
of 1.5 mg Cy5-ODN/kg mouse weight. After 4 hours, mice 
were euthanized and tumor tissues were collected and fixed 
in 10% formalin for 24 hours. The tumor tissues were then 
soaked in 30% sucrose solution for another 24 hours. The 
fluorescence signals of Cy5 emitted by the whole tumor tis-
sues were measured using Xenogen IVIS-200 Optical In Vivo 
Imaging System (Caliper Life Sciences, Hopkinton, MA). All 
tumor tissues were then cryopreserved in optimal cutting 
temperature (OCT) compound. The cross sections of tumor 
tissues were counterstained with Hoechst and mounted on 
glass slides for confocal microscopy analysis. The fluores-
cence signals of Hoechst and Cy5 were observed in the 
DAPI (dichroic mirror 430-470 nm) and Cy5 (dichroic mirror 
655-755 nm) channels, respectively. </p>

<p>In vivo delivery of LP-miR-29b. Three million A549 cells were 
resuspended in PBS and implanted into the flanks of 6-week-
old, nude mice. Tumors were allowed to develop to ~100 
mm 3 without any treatment till day 22. LP-miR-29b, LP-miR-
NC and empty liposomes were administered to nude mice 
by intravenous injection at a dosage level of 1.5 mg miR/kg 
mouse weight every other day for total seven injections (n 
= 6). Tumors were measured using a digital caliper. Tumor 
volumes were calculated using the equation V (in mm 3 ) = A 
× B 2 /2, where A is the largest diameter and B is the per-
pendicular diameter. At 48 hours after the last administra-
tion, mice were euthanized and tumor tissues were collected 
and quickly frozen in liquid nitrogen. The frozen tumor tissues 
were grounded to powders. The total RNA was extracted 
using TRIzol and chloroform further purified by isopropanol 
precipitation and washed by 70% ethanol. The total RNA 
was then reverse transcribed into cDNA using the TaqMan 
MicroRNA reverse transcription kit. The qRT-PCR amplifica-
tion of cDNA was then performed using TaqMan MicroRNA 
assay (Applied Biosystems; assay ID 002247). The mature 
miR-29b expression was determined by the ΔΔC t method 
and normalized to sno135 (Applied Biosystems; assay ID 
001230), which was the endogenous control in the corre-
sponding samples, and relative to the untreated control tis-
sue samples. To measure the expression of CDK6, DNMT3B, 
and MCL1 mRNAs in the tumors, the total RNA was tran-
scribed into cDNA using the High Capacity cDNA Reverse 
Transcription Kit (Applied Biosystems; 4368814). The result-
ing cDNA was amplified by qRT-PCR (Applied Biosystems; 
CDK6 assay ID: Mm01311342_m1, DNMT3B assay ID: 
Mm01240113_m1, and MCL1 assay ID Mm0725832_s1). 
Relative gene expression values were determined by the 
ΔΔC t method. The expression of CDK6, DNMT3B, and MCL1 
mRNAs was normalized to GAPDH (Applied Biosystems; 
assay ID: Mm99999915_g1), which was the endogenous 
reference in the corresponding samples, and relative to the 
untreated control cells. </p>

<p>Tumor histology. Tissues were fixed in formalin and embed-
ded in paraffin. Sections (4 µm) were cut and stained with 
H&amp;E. Representative sections of liver, heart, and kidney were 
scanned with a Scanscope CS slide scanner (Aperio Tech-
nologies, Vista, CA), visualized with <rs id="software-11" type="software">ImageScope</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-11" type="creator">Aperio Technologies</rs>), and composed in <rs type="software">Adobe Photoshop</rs> 
(San Jose, CA). Images were adjusted in brightness, con-
trast, and color balance for a more uniform appearance of the 
H&amp;E stain. These adjustments do not obscure, eliminate, or 
misrepresent any information presented in the original slides. 
Original objective lens magnification was 20×. All images 
were reviewed by a veterinary pathologist. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry. Paraffin embedded tissues were 
cut at 4 µm and placed on positively charged slides. Slides 
were then placed in a 60 °C oven for 1 hour, cooled, and 
deparaffinized and rehydrated through xylenes and graded 
ethanol solutions to water. For Ki-67 staining, all slides were 
quenched for 5 minutes in a 3% hydrogen peroxide solu-
tion in water to block for endogenous peroxidase. The slides 
were antigen retrieved in Dako's Target Retrieval Solution 
(pH6.0) in a vegetable steamer. The slides were incubated </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy-Nucleic Acids </p>

<p>Therapeutic Delivery of MicroRNA-29b 
Wu et al. </p>



<p>with the rat antimouse Ki-67 primary antibody (DakoM7249, 
clone TEC-3) at the dilution of 1:500 for 1 hour at room tem-
perature. Endogenous biotin was blocked using the Avidin/ 
Biotin Blocking Kit (Dako, X0590; 20 minutes for the avidin 
block, 20 minutes for the biotin block). The slides were then 
incubated with the rabbit antirat secondary antibody (Vec-
tor Labs, BA-4001) at the dilution of 1:200 and incubated for 
20 minutes. The detection system used was Vectastain Elite 
(Vector Labs, PK-6100) for 30 minutes. The substrate chro-
mogen used was DAB+ (Dako K3468). The slides were then 
counterstained with Richard Allen hematoxylin, dehydrated 
through graded ethanol solutions and sealed with cover slips. 
For TUNEL staining, the slides were pretreated with Dako 
RTU Proteinase K (S3020) for 5 minutes at room temper-
ature, and then quenched in 3% H 2 O 2 for 5 minutes. Next, 
the slides were incubated with RTU equibibration buffer for 
10 seconds at room temperature, and then incubated with 
Tdt enzyme in hybridizer at 37 °C. The reaction was stopped 
by rinsing with stop/wash buffer and PBS. The slides were 
incubated with RTU anti-Digoxigenin-Peroxidase conjugate 
for 30 minutes and then rinsed with PBS. The slides were 
incubated with peroxidase substrate (DAB) for 5 minutes and 
rinsed with diH 2 O. The slides were counterstained with Rich-
ard Allen hematoxylin, dehydrate in alcohols, clear in xylene 
and sealed with cover slips. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Data are presented as the mean ± SD. 
The statistical significance was determined using JMP Pro 
9 software. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments. This work was supported in part by the 
National Science Foundation grant EC-425625 to LJ LEE 
and National Cancer Institute grant CA150297 to S.P. Nana-
Sinkam. The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>



<p>Molecular Therapy-Nucleic Acids is an open-access 
journal published by Nature Publishing Group. This work 
is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
NoDerivative Works 3.0 License. To view a copy of this license, visit 
http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

</text></tei>