<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3366639" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">


<p>For organic semiconductors to find ubiquitous electronics applications, the development of 
new materials with high mobility and air stability is critical. Despite the versatility of carbon, 
exploratory chemical synthesis in the vast chemical space can be hindered by synthetic and 
characterization difficulties. Here we show that in silico screening of novel derivatives of the 
dinaphtho[2,3-b:2′,3′-f]thieno[3,2-b]thiophene semiconductor with high hole mobility and air 
stability can lead to the discovery of a new high-performance semiconductor. on the basis of 
estimates from the marcus theory of charge transfer rates, we identified a novel compound 
expected to demonstrate a theoretic twofold improvement in mobility over the parent molecule. 
synthetic and electrical characterization of the compound is reported with single-crystal field-
effect transistors, showing a remarkable saturation and linear mobility of 12.3 and 16 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>, 
respectively. This is one of the very few organic semiconductors with mobility greater than 
10 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s 
− 1 reported to date. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1451 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 2:437 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1451 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>he field of organic electronics has gained tremendous interest 
in the last decade, motivated by flexible display </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, photovoltaic </p>

<p>2,3 </p>

<p>and sensor 
4-7 applications. New materials are typically dis-
covered experimentally, with theoretical characterization providing 
only post-facto justification of the observed device performance. 
In a few recent cases, however, theory in particular computational 
chemistry methods together with rational design techniques guided 
the synthesis of successful organic electronic materials for solar cell 
applications 
8 and liquid crystals </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>. A priori screening of new materi-
als and the prediction of the device performance would open vast 
opportunities for new materials design </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>. 
Theoretical prediction of high-performance novel organic semi-
conductor materials is hindered by the large number of factors 
influencing charge carrier mobility in thin-film devices; for exam-
ple, synthetic methods, device geometry, contacts, device interfaces, 
thin-film growth, and molecular packing of the solid </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>. The challenge 
one faces is the choice of the 'right' molecule for synthesis. Although, 
π-extended compounds such as oligoacenes and oligothiophenes are 
known to be suitable as organic semiconductors, many factors on the 
molecular level, such as molecular reorganization energy, electronic 
structure and air stability must be optimized </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>. Moreover, the control 
of molecular properties is not sufficient for successful semiconductor 
design, as bulk properties (for example, orbital overlap, packing), and 
thus the delocalization of charges depend on the crystal structure. 
Therefore, accurate prediction of the molecular packing within the 
solid is crucial for computation of the magnitude 
11 and anisotropy 
13 of 
charge transport. Despite the recent advances in the crystal-structure 
prediction </p>

<p>14-16 </p>

<p>, de novo prediction of organic crystal structures 
remains a challenging task </p>

<p>17-20 </p>

<p>, but the related problem of optimizing 
the unit cell parameters is more tractable </p>

<p>17,21 </p>

<p>. The difficulty arises from 
the fact that the sum of weak intermolecular forces such as van der 
Waals, H-bonding and π-π interactions determine the final packing 
structure. Although, there has been some recent success for the 
de novo prediction of crystal structures of small organic rigid 
molecules when the contents of the asymmetric unit is known </p>

<p>17,21 </p>

<p>, 
the success of such predictions rely on highly accurate dispersion-
corrected Density Functional Theory (DFT) methods that are 
precluded for the large extended π-conjugated heteroacenes. 
The theory of charge transport in organic semiconductors relies 
on two contributions. The first is the magnitude of the electronic 
coupling (transfer integral), which depends on the relative arrange-
ment of the molecules in the crystal, whereas the second is the geo-
metric relaxation of the molecule and its surroundings (reorganiza-
tion energy) on movement of the charge carriers </p>

<p>11,22 </p>

<p>. The former can 
be approximated as nearest-neighbour contributions, as the elec-
tronic couplings fall off rapidly with distance. The latter is mostly 
the energy change of a single molecule on charge addition/removal 
(intramolecular reorganization energy), because contributions from 
polarization of surrounding molecules is significantly smaller </p>

<p>23,24 </p>

<p>. 
Previous calculations indicate that the high charge mobilities of 
pentacene and dinaphtho[2,3-b:2′,3′-f]thieno[3,2-b]thiophene (1) 
can be partially attributed to both strong electronic coupling inter-
actions among neighbouring molecules and to a decrease of the 
hole intramolecular reorganization energy (λ + ) </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>, suggesting that 
quantum-chemical calculations of these properties can be used to 
identify novel semiconductors. 
The present work was stimulated by the report of Yamamoto and 
Takimiya on a facile synthesis of 1, with high hole mobility (2.9-
3.1 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>) and stability in air </p>

<p>26,27 </p>

<p>. Subsequent measurements 
on single-crystals of 1 yielded hole mobility of µ + = 8.3 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>(ref. 28) whereas Hall effect measurements by the same group pro-
vided an intrinsic hole mobility of 1.2 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s 
− 1 (ref. 29). The sta-
bility of 1 in air, attributed to the deeper highest occupied molecular 
orbital (HOMO) level due to thienothiophene core </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>, is a significant 
improvement over pentacene, which readily undergoes many types 
of disproportionation reactions to generate impurities that decrease </p>

<p>the mobility </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>. Compared with oligothiophenes, for example, the 
limited number of sulfur atoms in 1 results in smaller reorganiza-
tion energies and thereby higher mobilities. Taken together, these 
factors have motivated previous work substituting different molec-
ular fragments, such as thiophene and acene, to develop organic 
semiconductors with superior charge transport properties and air 
stability </p>

<p>12,30 </p>

<p>. Molecule 1 is also a good model system for computa-
tional discovery of new materials. A computational search can use 
databases to limit possible candidates to commercially available 
or previously reported precursor candidates. Quantum chemical 
calculations are then performed to identify molecular derivatives 
exhibiting lower reorganization energies and higher transfer inte-
grals than those of the parent compound. 
In this study, a computational screening procedure followed by 
synthesis and characterization led to single-crystal-based organic 
field-effect transistors (OFETs) of the new compound 2 that dem-
onstrated a saturation region hole mobility of µ + = 12.3 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>and a linear region mobility of 16 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>. This is one of the very 
few organic semiconductors that has exhibited mobility greater than 
10 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>. The study suggests that a computational screening 
approach can lead to the informed synthesis and characterization of 
novel organic materials for electronics applications. </p>

<p>Results 
Screening procedure. The screening procedure involved the 
following steps: design of potential derivatives of compound 1 from 
fused aromatics; computational screening for low reorganization 
energy candidates; crystal structure optimization; charge transport 
calculation to establish relative mobilities; selection of the most 
promising candidates with the highest mobility; synthesis; and 
finally, device fabrication and characterization. This approach was 
applied by theoretically screening seven new heteroacenes (2-8, 
Fig. 1) to identify the most promising charge-transport materials, 2 
and 7. On the basis of the computational results, 2 was given priority 
over 7 because of higher transfer integral. It was subsequently 
synthesized, and single-crystal transistors were fabricated for charge 
transport characterization. </p>

<p>Theoretical calculations. We used a combined quantum-mechani-
cal and molecular mechanics approach for the computational stud-
ies here, the details of which are presented in the Supplementary 
Methods. Here we first discuss results for 1, to directly compare 
against known experimental values </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>. As shown in Table 1, the calcu-
lated HOMO energy of 1 with the 6-311 + G(d,p) basis is in reason-
able agreement with the electrochemical cyclic voltametry measure-
ment value of 5.44 eV (ref. 27). The calculated HOMO-LUMO (lowest 
unoccupied molecular orbital) gap, ∆ε, is also in reasonable agreement 
with the optically observed absorption edge of 3.0 eV, given that our 
calculation considers an isolated molecule in vacuum, whereas the 
experiment was performed on a crystal. The time-dependent density 
functional theory (TD-DFT) optical gap of 3.0 eV (Supplementary 
Information) is in excellent agreement with the experimental absorp-
tion spectrum. Use of the larger 6-311 + G(d,p), basis set improves 
the orbital energies, but the reorganization energies are practically 
same for both basis sets. To obtain a numerical estimate of the hole 
mobility for 1, we used its experimental 
27 as well as the predicted 
crystal structures (Supplementary Table S1) to calculate the transfer 
integrals </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>, V + , the data are listed in Table 2. In general, V + calculated 
for 1 is comparable to those of pentacene. However, the lower mobil-
ity for 1 results from the higher λ + (λ + = 0.128 eV for 1, as compared 
with λ + = 0.099 eV for pentacene </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>) due to the exponential depend-
ence of the hopping rate on this parameter, whereas quadratic power 
law dependence on the transfer integral, V + (Supplementary Infor-
mation, equation (1)). We also note that optimized crystal structures 
with charges calculated at the levels of Perdew-Burke-Ernzerhof </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>parametrization with the double numeric plus polarization basis </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1451 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 2:437 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1451 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>(PBE/DNP) -denoted 'DNP' and Becke three-parameter Lee-Yang-
Parr functional 
35,36 with the Gaussian basis (B3LYP/6-311 + G(d,p)) </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>-denoted 'G' have slightly larger unit cells and lower predicted mobili-
ties (1.64 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s 
− 1 (DNP), 1.69 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s 
− 1 (G)) compared with that 
of the experimental structure (1.90 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s 
− 1 (xtal)). 
Having established this approach with 1, we next examined 
whether larger ring structures, such as 2-8, could have better sta-
bility (that is, greater ∆ε, comparable or lower ε HOMO ) and lower 
λ + than 1, and therefore yield higher performance OFET devices. 
Increasing the length of polyacenes leads to a decreasing ∆ε and λ + , 
so that a decrease in stability cancels any benefit from reduced λ + . 
However, as shown in Table 1, structures 3, 4, 5, and 7 all have larger 
∆ε than 1. Given the inaccuracies of the gaps calculated by DFT in 
general and B3LYP in particular </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>, 6, which is only 53 meV lower, 
may also be considered comparable to 1. In addition, all of 3-7 have 
lower ε HOMO than 1, adding support for their environmental stability. 
In contrast, both 2 and 8 have gaps that are lower than 1 by ~0.5 eV, 
with calculated HOMO-LUMO gaps between those of tetracene 
(∆ε = 2.737 eV) and pentacene (∆ε = 2.176 eV), and with ε HOMO com-
parable to tetracene (ε HOMO = 5.199) </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>. As 2 has a similar HOMO 
energy to tetracene, but with dramatically higher hole mobility 
(vide infra), it may be utilized to improve the hole-mobility limited </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>performance of tetracene/C 60 planar heterojunction photovoltaics. </p>

<p>At the B3LYP/6-311 + G(d,p) level of theory, 3-5 have λ + 
~50 meV greater than 1, comparable to that of naphthalene 
(λ + = 0.183 eV) </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>. Therefore, we conclude that these will have infe-
rior carrier mobilities to 1. In contrast, 6 has λ + comparable to 1, 
while 2 and 7 have λ + that are 44 and 53 meV lower (respectively) 
than 1, and moreover, lower than pentacene (λ + = 0.099 eV). 
Having identified 2 and 7 as the most promising candidates, in 
Table 2 columns, labelled '2(G)' and '7(G)' , we show hole mobil-
ity results based on calculated crystal structures. As with pentacene 
and 1, both show anisotropic mobility, with the strongest couplings 
for the T 1 dimer (see Fig. 2). In the case of 2, the nearest-neigh-
bour distances are comparable, and the transverse couplings slightly 
stronger than 1, leading to a predicted µ + of 3.34 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>, twice 
that of 1. In the case of 7, however, despite the much lower λ + , the 
transverse dimer couplings are weakened, leading to µ + slightly 
smaller than (but comparable to) 1 and pentacene (between 2.20 to 
1.45 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>). This prediction of increased mobility and poten-
tial stability in air motivated the synthetic and device studies of 2. </p>

<p>Synthesis and characterization. The synthesis of 2 was carried out 
using a similar strategy as used for synthesis of 1 and its derivatives, 
Supplementary Figure S1 (refs 27,41). 2-Hydroxymethylanthracene 
(S1) was first synthesized from anthraquinone-2-carboxylic acid </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Table 1 | Calculated energies of the target compounds. </p>

<p>B3LYP/6-31G(d,p)(eV) 
B3LYP/6-311 + G(d,p)(eV) </p>

<p>ε HOMO 
ε LUMO 
∆ε 
λ + 
ε HOMO 
ε LUMO 
∆ε 
λ + </p>

<p>1 
− 5.197 
− 1.823 
3.374 
0.130 
− 5.479 
− 2.173 
3.306 
0.128 
2 
− 4.898 
− 2.231 
2.667 
0.085 
− 5.174 
− 2.567 
2.608 
0.084 
3 
− 5.442 
− 1.551 
3.891 
0.181 
− 5.746 
− 1.911 
3.834 
0.188 
4 
− 5.306 
− 1.633 
3.673 
0.182 
− 5.628 
− 1.980 
3.648 
0.188 
5 
− 5.333 
− 1.660 
3.673 
0.180 
− 5.634 
− 2.007 
3.627 
0.181 
6 
− 5.170 
− 1.878 
3.292 
0.122 
− 5.482 
− 2.228 
3.253 
0.121 
7 
− 5.224 
− 1.741 
3.483 
0.077 
− 5.512 
− 2.078 
3.434 
0.075 
8 
− 4.925 
− 2.122 
2.803 
0.141 
− 5.224 
− 2.460 
2.764 
0.138 </p>

<p>Energies of frontier molecular orbitals, ε Homo and ε Lumo , Homo-Lumo gap, ∆ε=ε Lumo -ε Homo and the intramolecular hole reorganization energies, λ + , calculated at the B3LYP/6-31G(d,p) and B3LYP/6-
311 + G(d,p) levels of theory. </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>4 
5 
6 </p>

<p>7 
8 </p>

<p>Figure 1 | The molecular structures of the targeted compounds. The structures of seven extra heteroacenes (2-8) derived from the parent 
dinaphtho[2,3-b:2′,3′-f]thieno[3,2-b]thiophene (1) computationally characterized as potential high-performance organic semiconductors. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1451 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 2:437 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1451 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>S1 was then oxidized to the corresponding aldehyde, 2-anthralde-
hyde (S2), using PCC in dichloromethane. The aldehyde S2 is pho-
tochemically unstable in solution; thus, the reaction involving this 
had to be carried out in dark. The thiomethyl group was selectively 
introduced to the 3-position of anthracene to yield 3-methylthio-
2-anthraldehyde (S3) using excess n-butyllithuim and dimethyl-
disulfide in presence of N,N,N′,N′-tetramethylethylenediamine. 
The olefin compound, trans-1,2-bis(3-methylthio-2-anthracen-
yl)ethene (S4), was synthesized using McMurry coupling. Owing 
to the poor solubility of these anthracene derivatives, purification of 
the S1-S4 was achieved mainly via selective precipitation. The final 
ring closing reaction, to yield dianthracen-[2,3-b:2′,3′-f]thieno[3,2-
b]thiophene (2), was carried out in chloroform in presence of excess 
iodine. As the crude product was directly subjected to sublimation 
and a significant amount of product seemed to decompose in pres-
ence of reaction impurities at high temperature (~300 °C), the exact 
yield could not be determined. The subsequent sublimations and 
crystal growth experiments did not show material degradation. 
The UV-vis absorption spectrum of a thin film of 2 was collected 
(Supplementary Fig. S2). The optical HOMO-LUMO gap is 2.2 eV 
as estimated from the onset of the absorption edge, which is 0.9 eV 
red-shifted from 1 (ref. 27). This is consistent with the calculated 
HOMO-LUMO gap, which predicts a 0.7 eV red-shift of 2 relative 
to 1 (Table 1), and TD-DFT calculations which predict a 0.7 eV red-
shift of the first excitation. The material was not soluble enough 
in organic solvents to allow for solution NMR or solution optical 
characterization. The HOMO of single crystals of 2 was estimated 
to be 5.2 eV from the ionization potential measured by photoelec-
tron spectroscopy (Supplementary Fig. S3) that is in excellent agree-
ment with the calculated value of − 5.2 eV at the level of B3LYP/6-
311 + G(d,p) theory. </p>

<p>An X-ray diffraction pattern from crystals of compound 2 
was collected at the Stanford Syncrotron Radiation Lightsource, 
at beamline 11-3 (Supplementary Fig. S4). The unit cell structure 
was obtained by a least-square fitting method (homemade software 
employing a modified Levenberg-Marquardt algorithm) using the 
positions of 15 clearly measurable, overlap-free peaks in powder 
spectrum. The unit cell dimension is slightly smaller than the pre-
dicted one, similar as the case for compound 1 noted earlier. Using 
the experimental crystal structure, we re-calculated the transfer 
integrals and found much stronger coupling along the a-axis; V P 
increased from 0.0415 to 0.0687 eV whereas V T1 and V T2 are the 
same. Thus, the transfer integrals suggest that mobility along a-axis 
would be highest; we expect only a moderate anisotropy in the 
mobility in the ab-plane as all three transfer integrals are reasonably 
high. Ensuing calculated mobility of 3.36 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s 
− 1 for the crystal 
is only slightly higher than the predicted value of 3.34 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Thin-film devices. Before studying the intrinsic transport char-
acteristics of 2 through single-crystal devices, thin-film devices 
were fabricated for comparison. Because the yield of sublima-
tion was low, performing more than two sublimation purifica-
tion steps was not possible. Despite that, we are aware extra 
sublimation steps can significantly improve the performance of 
the device 
43 . Nonetheless, thin-film transistors were fabricated 
by evaporation of a 40 nm layer of 2 on octadecylsilane-treated 
substrates at 95 °C, after which Au source and drain electrodes 
(40 nm) were deposited through a shadow mask. Atomic force 
microscopy demonstrated large two-dimensional growth of 2, 
which is favourable for charge transport (Supplementary Fig. S5). 
The transistors were measured in a glove box with N 2 atmosphere. 
The average mobility (µ) measured was 0.51 ± 0.06 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s 
− 1 with 
a threshold voltage (V T ) of 37.9 ± 1.3 V (Supplementary Fig. S6). 
The on/off ratio was around 4×10 
6 . The mobility of the evaporated 
thin films was lower than a comparable mobility for pentacene </p>

<p>44 </p>

<p>or 1 (ref. 27) evaporated under the same conditions. We attributed 
the relatively low mobility value of 0.51 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s 
− 1 to insufficient 
purification of the material. Additionally, the use of the crude, 
unpurified material resulted in an order of magnitude decrease 
in the mobility. There was no change in the thin-film transistor 
device performance following a six-month storage period in air, 
demonstrating the stability of 2, even in the presence of thin-
film impurities. </p>

<p>Single-crystal devices. To determine the charge carrier mobility 
in 2, vapour-grown crystals were used to construct single-crystal 
field-effect transistors (SC-FETs). The use of vapour growth for the 
formation of single crystals was required due to the insolubility 
of 2. An extra benefit of the use of crystal is the purification dur-
ing crystal growth. We fabricated low-voltage SC-FETs utilizing the </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>T 2 </p>

<p>T 1 </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Dimer type neighbours in the crystal structure of 2. The 
projections on the ab-(on the left) and bc-plane (on the right) of predicted 
crystal structure of 2 are shown. unique transfer integrals are computed 
only for the transverse (T 1 and T 2 ), parallel (P), and longitudinal (L) nearest 
neighbour pairs. </p>

<p>Table 2 | Calculated structural and hole transport properties of selected molecules. </p>

<p>Pentacene 
1(xtal) 
1(DNP) 
1(G) 
2 (G) 
2 (xtal) 
7(G) </p>

<p>d T1 (Å) 
4.734 
4.886 
5.025 
4.953 
4.984 
4.877 
5.617 
V T1 (eV) 
0.0967 
0.0940 
0.0975 
0.0967 
0.1020 
0.1023 
0.0536 
d T2 (Å) 
5.199 
5.148 
5.284 
5.219 
5.273 
5.202 
5.644 
V T2 (eV) 
0.0640 
0.0290 
0.0545 
0.0553 
0.0589 
0.0597 
0.0390 
d P (Å) 
6.275 
6.187 
6.401 
6.356 
6.444 
6.225 
7.198 
V P (eV) 
0.0417 
0.081 
0.0552 
0.0690 
0.0415 
0.0687 
0.00118 
d L (Å) 
14.10 
16.210 
16.499 
16.227 
21.203 
20.824 
19.601 
V L (eV) 
0.0008 
0.0013 
0.00026 
0.00025 
0.00018 
0.00027 
0.00021 
µ + (cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>) 
2.20 
1.90 
1.64 
1.69 
3.34 
3.36 
1.45 </p>

<p>The hole mobility, µ + , calculated at 300 K based on the B3LYP/6-311 + G(d,p) reorganization energies (Table 1) and B3LYP/6-31G(d,p) transfer integrals, V. The distances, d, are the monomer 
centre-of-mass distances for each dimer. Results for 1 include the experimental crystal structure from Yamamoto and Takimiya ('xtal'), and the calculated results using PBE/DnP charges ('DnP') and 
B3LYP/6-311 + G(d,p) charges ('G'). Results for 2 include the powder X-ray diffraction-calculated structure (xtal) (this work) and B3LYP/6-311 + G(d,p) charges ('G'). Results for 7 are calculated using 
B3LYP/6-311 + G(d,p) charges. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1451 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 2:437 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1451 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>bottom-contact, bottom-gate geometry, with a novel cross-linked 
polymer dielectric recently reported by our group; namely PVP-
HDA (Supplementary Information) </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>. The polymer allows for the 
use of low voltages and exhibits low dielectric leakage for device 
operation </p>

<p>46 </p>

<p>. The polymer layer was formed according to our previ-
ously reported procedures, and Au bottom contacts were deposited 
through a shadow mask. The crystals were manually laminated onto 
the devices and individually screened for transistor behaviour. It 
should be noted that the formation of SC-FETs critically depends 
on the single-crystal morphology. In the case of 2, the single crys-
tals grew as ultra-thin plates; however, on average, the plates were 
limited in the lateral dimensions to ~100-400 µm. Additionally, 
owing to the thin nature of the plates, the larger crystals agglom-
erated together, making the selection of single-crystal candidates 
from the growth tube difficult. Nonetheless, the placement of the 
single crystals on the patterned electrodes usually resulted in the 
observation of transistor behaviour with high mobility. Indeed, 
from the twelve single crystals tested, seven exhibited mobilities of 
at or above 5 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>. The mobilities measured in these devices 
that are made by hand-picking the crystals are, of course, expected 
to show a much larger variation in performance, because of crys-
tal placement, contacts and crystal orientation. Additionally, the 
mobility of the crystal has been shown to be significantly improved 
with decreasing crystal thickness, thus, only thin, small plates were 
used </p>

<p>47 </p>

<p>. Each crystal was subsequently examined under a cross-
polarized microscope to ensure the crystal is not twinned or with 
multiple crystals (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>Discussion 
The best performance obtained for a laminated SC-FET was observed 
for the crystal shown in Figure 3. The facets of the crystal are clearly 
visible and crystal is oriented such that the long-axis is along the 
electric field between source and drain electrode. Indexing of the 
crystal facets (Fig. 3) confirms that the long axis of the crystal is the 
a-axis, consistent with the predicted high transfer integral direction. 
Thus, this crystal is aligned to exhibit the maximum device per-
formance. Under cross-polarized light, no cracks or any other limit-
ing factors for charge transport are visible (Fig. 3c). The near-perfect 
alignment with electric field and proper contact to the electrodes is 
likely the main reason why this particular device performs better 
compared with most other single-crystal devices. The transfer and 
output characteristics of the device are shown in Figure 4, below. 
The maximum mobility reached was 12.3 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s 
− 1 in the satura-
tion regime and 16.0 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s 
− 1 in the linear regime using − 0.1 V 
as the drain-source (V DS ) bias (Fig. 4c). The on/off current ratio was 
6.4×10 
3 with a threshold voltage V T of 0.44 V. To ensure accuracy in 
the measurement, the capacitance of the dielectric was measured 
directly next to the placed single crystal as 68 nF cm </p>

<p>− 2 </p>

<p>. The chan-
nel width/length (W/L) parameter (0.5) was extracted by measuring 
the single crystal under a digital microscope and taking the aver-
age of the two sides of the crystal in contact with the electrodes. 
The gate leakage for the device was on the order of 0.1 nA (Sup-
plementary Fig. S7). Both transfer and output characteristics show 
excellent scaling with the gate voltage, indicating there is no severe 
contact issues. It should be noted that the devices experienced less </p>

<p>(1 1 0) </p>

<p>(-1 1 0) </p>

<p>(1 0 0) </p>

<p>(0 1 0) </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Single-crystal optical and X-ray characterization. shown here are the (a) optical micrograph and the (c) cross-polarized counterpart (under 
an angle of 45°) of the best performing device (µ sat = 12.3 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s 
− 1 and µ linear = 16 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>) based on a single crystal of compound 2. It is noted that we 
used an average of the length of each side of the crystal in contact with the electrodes as the channel width (W) for mobility calculation. The scale bar 
shown in pane (c) is 10 µm. (b) Crystal structure of 2 with labelled crystal planes used for facet identification, showing the molecular arrangement along 
the a-axis (0 1 0) plane, (blue). The angles of the facets as measured from the single crystal were matched to those calculated from the X-ray structure. 
The calculated and measured angles for the intersection of the (1 1 0) (red) and (0 1 0) (blue) planes were both 130.2°. The calculated and measured 
angles for the intersection of the (1 1 0) (red) and ( − 1 1 0) (purple) planes were 99.6° and 100.5°, respectively. </p>

<p>1E-6 
6E-8 </p>

<p>5E-8 </p>

<p>4E-8 </p>

<p>3E-8 </p>

<p>1E-8 </p>

<p>2E-8 </p>

<p>6E-4 </p>

<p>-1E-7 </p>

<p>-2E-7 </p>

<p>-3E-7 </p>

<p>-4E-7 </p>

<p>-5E-7 
-0.9 
-0.6 
-0.3 
0.0 </p>

<p>+0.9 V 
+0.7 V 
+0.5 V 
+0.3 V 
+0.1 V 
-0.1 V 
-0.3 V 
-0.5 V 
-0.7 V 
-0.9 V </p>

<p>0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5E-4 </p>

<p>4E-4 </p>

<p>3E-4 </p>

<p>2E-4 </p>

<p>1E-4 </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>ds 
1/2 </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>1/2 </p>

<p>I 
ds (A) 
I 
ds (A) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>1E-7 </p>

<p>1E-8 </p>

<p>1E-9 </p>

<p>1E-10 </p>

<p>-1.0 
-0.8 
-0.6 
-0.4 
-0.2 </p>

<p>V g (V) 
V ds (V) 
V g (V) </p>

<p>0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>I 
ds (A) </p>

<p>-1.0 
-0.8 
-0.6 
-0.4 
-0.2 </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Single-crystal device characterization. (a) Transfer characteristics in the saturation regime and (b) output curve of the single-crystal field-
effect transistor of 2 with a field-effect mobility of 12.3 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>. The drain-source bias (V Ds ) was − 1.0 V, the threshold voltage (V T ) was 0.44 V, and 
the on/off ratio was 6.4×10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>. (c) Transfer characteristics in the linear regime of the single-crystal field-effect transistor with a field-effect mobility of 
16.0 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>. The V Ds was − 0.1 V. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1451 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 2:437 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1451 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>than 10% degradation in mobility after a period of six months stor-
age in the ambient environment, attesting to the air stability of the 
compound. Moreover, during the submission of this manuscript, an 
independent study by the Takimiya group reported the synthesis 
and thin-film transistor characterization of 2 </p>

<p>48 </p>

<p>. This paper demon-
strated similar stability for thin-film devices with a lower observed 
mobility of 3.0 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>. Previously, our group proposed a similar 
synthetic route within a published US patent </p>

<p>49 </p>

<p>. 
To establish an accurate comparison of the single-crystal result 
of 2 to that of the parent compound 1, we fabricated several single-
crystal devices utilizing the same device architecture described 
within the paper. This is necessary as variations in device fabrica-
tion could result in changes in device performance. To this end, 
within our studies, 1.19 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s 
− 1 was the highest value of mobil-
ity for a single crystal of 1 (Supplementary Fig. S8). This number 
agrees well with a recent report of the Hall mobility measured for 1 
(ref. 29) Whereas this is approximately a factor of 10 lower than that 
obtained for 2, the intrinsic value for the mobility of 2 needs to be 
evaluated by similar Hall effect studies. 
In summary, we have demonstrated a theoretical screening 
approach for the discovery of novel organic semiconductor cores 
before chemical synthesis. On DFT calculation of eight semicon-
ductor cores, 2 was found to have lower hole reorganization energies 
than both 1 and pentacene. Charge transport modelling indicated 
that 2 would have a higher hole mobility than that predicted for 1. 
On the basis of these calculation results, 2 was selected as a promis-
ing high mobility candidate. It was synthesized and characterized 
in single-crystal OFET devices. Single-crystal transistors demon-
strated saturation region hole mobilities as high as 12.3 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>and a linear region mobility of 16 cm 
2 V 
− 1 s </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>. This high mobility 
combined with high air stability (less than 10% degradation in SC-
FET performance after a six-month period of storage in air), makes 
2 a promising candidate for high-performance OFET applications. 
Future synthetic work will focus on the improvement of synthetic 
yield of 2, and the introduction of pendant side chains and the syn-
thesis and experimental characterization of 7 that is predicted to 
have similar performance to the molecule 1. 
The development of more sophisticated theoretical models 
that go beyond the semiclassical regime, with the goal of bridg-
ing the gap between the predicted hopping-mechanism calcula-
tions and the measured mobility, is underway. This study sug-
gests that computational screening is a viable approach for finding 
novel organic materials for electronics and photovoltaic appli-
cations. A high-throughput version of this screening of materi-
als, by means of IBM's World Community Grid and the Clean 
Energy Project (http://www.worldcommunitygrid.org and http:// 
cleanenergy.harvard.edu) is in progress (Olivares-Amaya R. et al., 
unpublished work and Hachmann J. et al., unpublished work). 
Strategies for predicting the carrier type based on single-molecular 
calculations can be used to screen for n-channel and ambipolar 
materials in addition to the p-channel materials studied here </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Computational methodology. Geometries of the neutral ground state and 
radical cations were calculated at the B3LYP/6-31G(d,p) level of theory, followed 
by single-point calculations employing the valence-triple-ζ 6-311 + G(d,p) basis 
set 
35,36,51,52 for faster convergence as implemented in the Q-Chem software 
package 
37 . The reorganization energies, shown in Table 1, are calculated based on 
the usual four-point scheme 
22 neglecting the outer sphere contributions to the total 
reorganization energy. </p>

<p>Crystal structure prediction. We performed crystal structure prediction only for 
the molecules 1, 2 and 7, because 2 and 7 are identified as promising candidates 
for OFET applications based on the isolated molecule properties. Because of the 
structural similarities of 2 and 7 to 1, we hypothesized that the most probable 
packing motif would be a herringbone type with P2 1 similar to 1. We modified 
the initial guesses of the unit cell parameters from 1 in accordance with the sizes 
of the molecules 2 and 7, then performed rigid body optimization of the unit 
cell dimensions constructed from the calculated gas phase molecular structures. </p>

<p>We employed the Dreiding 
53 force field with ab initio point charges fit to the 
electrostatic potential, and optimized the unit cell using a combination of steepest 
descent, Newton-Raphson and quasi-Newton methods </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>. The long-range periodic 
electrostatic interactions were evaluated by Ewald sums. The results presented here 
are based on a lattice energy minimization of motionless molecules (that is, finite 
temperature effects are totally neglected). To validate this approach, we attempted 
to reproduce the experimental crystal structure of 1. For 1, the initial guess for the 
optimization was the experimentally determined unit cell. The effect of charges 
calculated by PBE/DNP 
34 and B3LYP/6-311 + G(d,p) levels of theory on the unit 
cell parameters of 1 are shown in Supplementary Table S1, indicated by (DNP) and 
(G), respectively. Both yield comparable structure parameters to the experimentally 
determined unit cell, although B3LYP/6-311 + G(d,p) charges have slightly better 
agreement with the experimental unit cell parameters and density. Consequently, 
the latter was used for the computations on 2 and 7. All crystal prediction calcula-
tions were carried out with the <rs type="software">Materials Studio Modules</rs>, <rs type="software">Forcite</rs> and <rs type="software">DMol </p>

<p>34</rs> </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Mobility calculations. The mobility calculations were performed assuming diffu-
sion of charges in the absence of an electric field, with charge carrier transfer rates 
obtained from the semiclassical Marcus theory 
32 . Although this approach neglects 
tunnelling contributions to the mobility, which can significantly increase the hole 
mobility of highly purified polyacenes 
43 , especially at low temperatures </p>

<p>54 </p>

<p>, our 
present goal is to obtain a lower bound estimate of the performance for these mate-
rials in the presence of impurities, polymorphism, and temperature effects leading 
to carrier localization best described by a hopping model. Further description of 
the mobility calculations is provided in the Supplementary Information. </p>

<p>Synthesis of compound 2. The complete synthetic route for compound 2 is 
included in the Supplementary Information. Dianthra[2,3-b:2′,3′-f]thieno[3,2-b] 
thiophene (2). A solution of S4 (0.18 g, 0.38 mmol) and iodine (4 g, 15.8 mmol) 
in chloroform (25 ml) was refluxed for 21 h. After cooling to room temperature, 
saturated aqueous sodium hydrogen sulfite solution (40 ml) was added, and the 
resulting precipitate was collected by filtration and was washed with water and 
chloroform. The crude product was purified by vacuum sublimation to provide a 
bright pink product. MS (MALDI) m/z = 440.17 (M + H 
+ ), calcd m/z = 440.0693. </p>

<p>Purification of materials. Before use in thin-films or single-crystal growth both 1 
and 2 were purified twice by sublimation using a three-temperature zone furnace 
(Lindberg/BlueThermo Electron) at a reduced pressure of 1×10 
− 4 Torr or less. 
Surface modification and thin-film device preparation is reported in the 
Supplementary information. </p>

<p>Single-crystal device characterization. The devices were tested in bottom contact 
geometry with crystals laminated across thermally evaporated gold contacts on the 
polymer dielectric. Previous studies on SC-FETs have established that to achieve 
maximum performance conformal elastomeric 
55 or free-space dielectrics 
56 should 
be employed. In this fashion, the dielectric acts as a passivated surface to the criti-
cal crystal interface as well as providing a conformal contact to the crystal. This 
lamination typically helps create an efficient contact with the bottom electrodes, 
and allows for efficient charge injection. The gold contacts were thermally evapo-
rated in high vacuum at a rate of 1 Å s 
− 1 while rotating the substrate holder. The 
electrode dimensions were defined by a shadow mask with a 50 µm channel length 
(L), and a W/L ratio of approximately 20. The W/L used in the mobility calcula-
tion for SC-FETs was determined from the individual crystals used. The SC-FET 
transistors were characterized using a Keithley 4200SCS and standard probe station 
setup in air. The thin-film transistors were characterized using the same probe 
setup in N 2 . Overall no significant difference between the performance in 
N 2 and in air was observed. 
Devices were tested in the saturation regimes and linear regimes with the device 
parameters extracted using the standard calculation techniques. The saturated field-effect 
mobility was calculated by plotting the square root of the source-drain current (I DS ) 
versus gate voltage (V GS ) and using the mobility equation from the saturated regime: </p>

<p>I 
WC L 
V 
V </p>

<p>i 
DS 
FET GS 
T </p>

<p>= 
− 
( 
/ ) 
( 
) 
2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>The linear field-effect mobility was calculated by plotting the source-drain cur-
rent (I DS ) versus gate voltage (V GS ) and calculating the slope m linear . The mobility was 
calculated according to the equation for the linear regime: </p>

<p>m = m 
L W 
V 
C i </p>

<p>linear 
DS </p>

<p>( / )( / 
)( / ) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>The capacitance value of the polymer dielectric was evaluated using an Agilent 
E4980 precision LCR meter operating at 1 V and 1 kHz frequency. The capacitance 
was evaluated directly on the bottom contact electrodes that were used in the 
placement of the single crystal, to avoid discrepancies with polymer thickness. 
Electrodes of different dimensions on the polymer substrate were evaluated and the 
capacitance was confirmed to remain constant across the device. </p>

<p>Crystal growth. Single crystals of 2 were grown by the physical vapour transport 
method 
57 at atmospheric pressure in semiconductor-grade argon at ~80 ccm; the 
details of this setup are described elsewhere </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>. The material formed two-dimensional 
platelets of varying quality. All platelets were pink/red, depending on crystal thickness. </p>

<p>(1) (1) </p>

<p>(2) (2) </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1451 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 2:437 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1451 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>The single crystals of 1 were grown according to previously published literature 
procedures </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Surface characterization. Atomic force microscopy was performed using a Digital 
Instruments Nanoscope IV operated in tapping mode (~320 kHz frequency, Si tip). </p>

<p>Cross-linked poly(4-vinylphenol). (x-PVP) (refs 45,46). Poly(4-vinylphenol) 
(PVP, Aldrich, MW 25,000) was dissolved in propylene glycol monomethyl ether 
acetate (PGMEA) with ratio of 40 mg ml 
− 1 . Separately, the cross-linker with 4,4′-
(hexafluoroisopropylidene) diphthalic anhydride (HDA, Aldrich) was dissolved in 
PGMEA at a ratio of 4 mg ml 
− 1 . Into a 2 ml solution of PVP, 2 µl of triethylamine 
was added, and the solution was shaken for a period of 30 s to ensure complete 
mixture. To this mixture, 2 ml of HDA solution was added, and the solution 
shaken to ensure complete mixture. Before spin coating, the blank silicon sub-
strates were exposed to gentle UV-ozone treatment (Jelight Model 42) for 3 min 
to promote polymer adhesion. To form the thin dielectric film, a filtered (0.2 µm 
PTFE filter) dielectric solution (~200 µl) was deposited onto the desired substrate, 
and allowed to settle for a period of 30 s. The substrate was subsequently spun 
coated (using Headway Research spin coater) at 7,000 RPM for 1 min and then 
cured on a hot plate at 100 °C for 1 h. A second UV ozone treatment of the x-PVP 
layer (3 min) was followed by the spin-coated deposition of an extra x-PVP layer 
following the above procedure. The device was subsequently cured on a 100 °C 
hot plate for 4 h. </p>



<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1451 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 2:437 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1451 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>



<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank E. Verploegen and A. Ayzner for help with collection of the PXRD structure 
of 2, Y. Jiang for help with the photoelectron spectroscopy measurement, and S. Saikin 
for helpful discussions. We acknowledge support from the following institutions: The 
Mary-Fieser Postdoctoral Fellowship at Harvard University (R.S.S.-C.), The Netherlands 
Organisation for Scientific Research (NWO) (H.B.A. and A.P.Z.), The Stanford Global 
Climate and Energy Program (GCEP) (Z.B., S. A. E. and A.A.-G.), NSF-DMR-Solid 
State Chemistry (DMR-0705687-002) (Z.B.), the Center for Advanced Molecular 
Photovoltaics (Award No KUS-C1-015-21, made by King Abdullah University of 
Science and Technology) (KAUST) (Z.B), and Air Force Office of Scientific Research 
(FA9550-09-1-0256) (Z.B.), The Harvard Materials Research Science and Engineering 
Center (DMR-0820484) (S.A.E. and A.A.-G.), and The Camille and Henry Dreyfus and 
Sloan Foundations (A.A.-G.). Portions of this research were carried out at the Stanford 
Synchrotron Radiation Lightsource, a national user facility operated by Stanford 
University on behalf of the U.S. Department of Energy, Office of Basic Energy Sciences. </p>

<p>This work used the resources of the National Energy Research Scientific Computing 
Center, which is supported by the Office of Science of the U.S. Department of Energy 
under Contract No. DE-AC02-05CH11231. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>A.N.S., S.A.-E., R.M., J.S., Z.B. and A.A.-G. conceptualised the work. S.A.-E., R.S.S.-C., 
and J.S. carried out the theoretical portion of the work. R.M., S.G.-F., and A.P.Z. carried 
out the synthetic portion of the work. A.N.S. and H.B.A carried out thin film and single-
crystal device portion of the work. S.C.B.M refined the powder X-Ray data. A.N.S., 
S.A.-E., R.M., H.B.A., J.S., S.G.-F., Z.B. and A.A.-G. co-wrote the paper. All authors 
discussed the results and commented on the manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
naturecommunications </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Reprints and permission information is available online at http://npg.nature.com/ 
reprintsandpermissions/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Sokolov, A.N. et al. From computational discovery to 
experimental characterization of a high hole mobility organic crystal. Nat. Commun. 
2:437 doi: 10.1038/ncomms1451 (2011). </p>

<p>License: This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
NoDerivative Works 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

</text></tei>