<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3481138" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Blocks in genetic programs required for terminal myeloid differentiation and aberrant proliferation characterize acute myeloid 
leukemia (AML) cells. 1,25-Dihydroxy-vitamin D3 (VitD3) arrests proliferation of AML cells and induces their differentiation into 
mature monocytes. In a previous study, we showed that miR-26a was induced upon VitD3-mediated monocytic differentiation. 
Here, we identify E2F7 as a novel target of miR-26a. We show that E2F7 significantly promotes cell cycle progression and inhibits 
monocytic differentiation of AML cells. We also demonstrate that E2F7 binds the cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor p21 </p>

<p>CIP1/WAF1 </p>

<p>(cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor 1A) promoter repressing its expression. Moreover, interfering with E2F7 expression results in 
inhibition of c-Myc (v-myc myelocytomatosis viral oncogene homolog) transcriptional activity. This leads to the downregulation 
of c-Myc transcriptional target miR-17-92 cluster, whose expression has a well-defined role in contributing to block monocytic 
differentiation and sustain AML cell proliferation. Finally, we show that the expression of E2F7 is upregulated in primary blasts 
from AML patients. Thus, these findings indicate that the newly identified miR-26a target E2F7 might have an important role in 
monocytic differentiation and leukemogenesis. 
essential roles in cell growth and proliferation through their 
ability to both positively and negatively regulate the expres-
sion of coding and noncoding genes. 
13,14 C-Myc (v-myc 
myelocytomatosis viral oncogene homolog) is frequently 
activated in AML and has an important role in the induction 
of leukemogenesis. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Notably, c-Myc transcriptionally 
represses p21 
CIP1/WAF1 expression, thereby sustaining AML 
cell proliferation. Conversely, p21 
CIP1/WAF1 represses Myc 
transcriptional activity by interfering with its dimerization with 
Max protein. 
15 Repression of tumor-suppressing miRNAs is a 
fundamental component of the Myc tumorigenic program. 
One of the relevant miRNAs repressed by c-Myc in 
hematopoietic malignancies is miR-26a, 
16,17 which was 
shown to act as a tumor suppressor in different types of 
cancer. </p>

<p>18-22 </p>

<p>In a previous study, we showed that miR-26a was induced 
upon VitD3-mediated monocytic differentiation of AML cell 
lines. 
17 In addition, we have shown that miR-26a was 
downregulated in primary AML blasts and, if reconstituted in 
AML cell lines, was able to decrease proliferation and induce 
myeloid differentiation. 
17 However, the mechanism under-
lying this effect was not fully understood. Here, we identify the 
transcriptional repressor E2F7 as a novel target for miR-26a 
function in AML. We show that E2F7 promotes cell cycle 
progression and inhibits monocytic differentiation of AML 
cells. The repression of E2F7 by miR-26a contributes to the 
increased expression of p21 
CIP1/WAF1 observed during VitD3-
induced monocytic differentiation of AML cells. In addition, 
interfering with E2F7 expression results in inhibition of c-Myc 
activity and downregulation of the oncogenic miR-17-92 
cluster. Finally, we further show that, conversely to miR-
26a, the expression of E2F7 is upregulated in AML blasts. 
Therefore, we identified a new regulatory network that might 
have a relevant role in leukemogenesis. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>E2F7 is a direct target of miR-26a and is upregulated in 
AML. We previously showed that miR-26a negatively regulates 
cell proliferation and stimulates myeloid differentiation of AML 
cells. 
17 Notably, miR-26a negatively regulates G 1 /S transition 
in different tumors and this has been attributed, at least in 
part, to the direct regulation of EZH2 by miR-26a. </p>

<p>16,17,19,21 </p>

<p>However, we showed that EZH2 is not a direct target of 
miR-26a in AML cells. 
17 Thus, we decided to investigate 
novel relevant targets for miR-26a function in AML. Between 
the putative targets of miR-26a, we noticed the E2F7 trans-
cription factor (data from <rs id="software-0" type="software">TargetScan</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">www.targetscan.org</rs>) 
and Pictar (pictar.mdc-berlin.de)), an important regulator 
of the G 1 /S-phase transition. 
23 The 3'-untranslated region 
(3 
0 -UTR) of E2F7 contained two highly conserved putative 
binding sites for miR-26a (Figure 1a). To show the direct 
targeting of E2F7 by miR-26a, we constructed luciferase 
reporters containing the wild type (WT) 3 
0 -UTR of E2F7 (WT), 
the E2F7 3 
0 -UTR mutated at the miR-26a binding site I (Mut1), 
the E2F7 3 
0 -UTR mutated at the miR-26a binding site II (Mut2) 
or the E2F7 3 
0 -UTR mutated at both miR-26a binding sites 
(Mut1-2). Luciferase reporters were individually co-transfected 
in HeLa cells with a plasmid expressing miR-26a or control </p>

<p>(Figure 1b). The expression of WT reporter was significantly 
decreased by miR-26a compared with control. Reporter Mut1 
behaved similarly to WT, while deletion of Mut2 partially 
relieved translational repression. On the other hand, expres-
sion of the reporter construct mutated at both miR-26a 
binding sites of E2F7 3 
0 -UTR (Mut1-2) was not sensitive to 
miR-26a translational repression. This may be explained by 
the fact that the binding of miR-26a on site II increases the 
accessibility to site I or, alternatively, binding of one 
repressive complex on site II may serve as scaffold for 
attracting cofactors necessary for repression on site I. These 
results demonstrated that miR-26a regulated E2F7 expres-
sion through direct binding of the 3 
0 -UTR. 
To further demonstrate that miR-26a represses E2F7 
expression in AML, U937 cells were infected with a lentivirus 
containing an miR-26a expression cassette (Lenti-26a) or 
control (Mock inf.). Enforced expression by lentiviral transduc-
tion significantly increased miR-26a levels with a concomitant 
decrease in E2F7 protein levels (Figure 2a). Similar results 
were obtained with the HL-60 cell line (Supplementary 
Figure 1). Altogether, these data indicated that E2F7 is a 
direct target of miR-26a in AML. 
We also examined the expression levels of E2F7 protein 
and miR-26a during monocytic differentiation of U937 induced 
by VitD3 (Figure 2b). As expected, E2F7 protein levels 
decreased upon monocytic differentiation and are inversely 
correlated to miR-26a levels (Figure 2b). Similar results were 
obtained during monocytic differentiation of HL-60 cells 
(Supplementary Figure 1). We previously showed that miR-
26a is downregulated in primary AML samples. 
15 Thus, we 
analyzed E2F7 expression levels in human monocytes 
isolated from healthy donors and diagnostic samples of AML 
patients by real-time RT-PCR (Figure 2c). We have restricted 
the analysis to M2, M4 and M5 FAB subtypes because they 
can respond to monocytic differentiation in vitro. 
3,4 High 
expression levels of E2F7 were detected in all AML samples 
compared with mature monocytes. These data indicated that 
E2F7 is upregulated in primary AML samples and that its 
expression is inversely correlated with miR-26a. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>Mut1-2 </p>

<p>RLuc </p>

<p>E2F7 wt: </p>

<p>hsa-miR26a: </p>

<p>E2F7 Mut1: </p>

<p>541-562 </p>

<p>Site 1 
Site 2 </p>

<p>2419-2441 </p>

<p>mock 
+miR-26a 
Normalized </p>

<p>luciferase activity </p>

<p>AAAAAA </p>

<p>Mut2: " </p>

<p>P&lt; 0.005 
P= 0.04 
P&lt; 0.005 </p>

<p>WT 
Mut1 Mut2 </p>

<p>Figure 1 E2F7 is a direct target of miR-26a. (a) Schematic representation of the 
constructs used in the luciferase assays. Positions and sequences of predicted miR-
26a binding sites are shown. (b) Luciferase assays in HeLa cells transfected with 
the constructs indicated in panel a with an expression plasmid for miR-26a ( þ miR-
26a) or control plasmid (mock). P-values are indicated </p>

<p>The miR-26a target E2F7 counteracts monocytic differentiation 
B Salvatori et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Decreased E2F7 levels stimulate monocytic differentiation 
and inhibit proliferation of AML cells. It has been 
previously demonstrated that miR-26a induced the expres-
sion of p21 
CIP1/WAF1 (Figure 2a) and, concomitantly, mono-
cytic differentiation of AML cell lines. 
17 Thus, we next 
investigated the role of E2F7 in monocytic cell differentiation. 
We selected U937 cells for further experiments because 
they have been extensively used as suitable model systems to 
study monocytic differentiation. These cells differentiate into 
mature monocytes by treatment with VitD3, a process mainly 
mediated by p21 
CIP1/WAF1 expression and subsequent G 0 /G 1 
cell cycle arrest. 
6,7 Cells were infected with lentiviral vectors 
expressing short hairpin RNAs (shRNAs) against E2F7 
(L-shE2F7) or scramble shRNA (L-shSCR) and differentiation 
was evaluated by analyzing the morphology, immunopheno-
type and induction of specific molecular markers. Cells 
infected with Lenti-shE2F7 exhibited almost a complete 
depletion of E2F7 protein level (Figure 3a). Strikingly, the 
depletion of E2F7 induced drastic changes in the morphology </p>

<p>of transduced cells. A nuclear condensation and more 
abundant cytoplasm were observed, indicating an induction 
of myeloid differentiation (Figure 3b). Notably, cells interfering 
with E2F7 presented a more pronounced differentiation upon 
VitD3 treatment with a feature of matured monocytes/ 
macrophages, such us indented nuclei, increased cytoplas-
mic processes and granules. Immunophenotype was ana-
lyzed to further examine differentiation. A strong increase in 
cells expressing the surface markers, cluster of differentiation 
14 (CD14) and cluster of differentiation 11b (CD11b), which 
are upregulated during myelomonocytic differentiation, was 
observed upon depletion of E2F7 and treatment with VitD3 
(Figures 3c and d). We also measured mRNA expression 
levels for marker of monocytic differentiation such as M-CSF, 
M-CSFr and MafB (Figure 3e). We detected a strong increase 
in monocytic markers upon inhibition of E2F7 expression by 
RNAi, even in the absence of any inducer, indicating that the 
depletion of E2F7 is sufficient to commit U937 toward 
monocytic differentiation. Similar results were obtained with </p>

<p>-1.5 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>-1.5 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>miR-26a </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
VitD3 (hrs) </p>

<p>E2F7 </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>p21 CIP1/WAF1 </p>

<p>Log10 Relative Expression to 
U6 snRNA </p>

<p>M2 
(n=11) </p>

<p>M4 
(n=4) </p>

<p>M5 
(n=10) </p>

<p>Mon. 
(n=5) 
Log10 Relative Expression to 
U6 snRNA 
* 
** 
** </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 
* 
P&lt;0.005 
** </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 
* 
P&lt;0.005 
** </p>

<p>M2 
(n=11) </p>

<p>M4 
(n=4) </p>

<p>M5 
(n=10) </p>

<p>Mon. 
(n=5) </p>

<p>E2F7 
miR-26a </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>miR-26a </p>

<p>E2F7 </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>p21 CIP1/WAF1 </p>

<p>VitD3 (hrs) 
96 
72 
48 
24 </p>

<p>96 
72 
48 
24 </p>

<p>Figure 2 Expression analysis of miR-26a and E2F7. (a, left panel) qPCR analysis of miR-26a levels in HL-60 and U937 cells infected with a lentivirus for ectopic 
expression of miR-26a (Lenti-26a) or control (Mock inf.). Values were normalized for U6 expression. The histograms represent the means±S.E.M. from triplicates. (Right 
panel) Western blot analysis of E2F7 and p21 protein levels from cells transduced with control lentivirus (Mock inf.) or Lenti-26a. GAPDH was utilized as the loading control. 
(c) qPCR analysis of miR-26a levels during VitD3-induced monocytic differentiation of U937 cell line. Values were normalized for U6 expression. The histograms represent the 
means±S.E.M. from triplicates. (c) Western blot analysis of E2F7 and p21 
CIP1/WAF1 protein levels during VitD3-induced monocytic differentiation of U937 cell line. GAPDH 
was utilized as the loading control. (c) qPCR analysis of E2F7 and miR-26a levels in primary leukemia cells derived from patients with M2, M4 and M5 AML subtypes (n ¼ 19) 
and monocytes (Mon.) isolated from healthy donors (n ¼ 5). Box plots graphically represent numerical data and the average of expression levels is indicated. Values were 
normalized with U6 snRNA. P-values are indicated </p>

<p>The miR-26a target E2F7 counteracts monocytic differentiation 
B Salvatori et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>HL-60 cells (Supplementary Figure 2). Altogether, these 
results indicate that decreased E2F7 levels stimulated 
monocytic/macrophage differentiation of AML cells. 
In AML, the terminal differentiation block is strictly related to 
aberrant proliferation. 
2 Thus, to better understand the activity 
of E2F7 in leukemic cells, we analyzed the effect of E2F7 on 
cellular proliferation and cell cycle. U937 cells infected with 
L-shE2F7 showed lower proliferation rate than control 
L-shSCR cells (Figure 4a). In addition, cell cycle analysis 
showed that silencing of E2F7 expression increased the 
percentage of cells in G 1 arrest and decreased the number of 
cells in the S phase (Figures 4b and c). Expression analysis of 
relevant cell cycle regulators by real-time PCR (qPCR) 
indicated that E2F7 silencing reduced the levels of several 
positive regulators of the G1 phase, including CDK2, CDK4 
and CDK6 (Figure 4d). Similar results were obtained with HL-
60 cells (Supplementary Figure 3). These data indicated that 
endogenous E2F7 could be essential for maintaining cellular 
proliferation of AML cells. </p>

<p>Increased E2F7 levels counteract monocytic differentia-
tion and stimulate proliferation of AML cells. We next 
evaluated whether enforced expression of E2F7 affected the </p>

<p>differentiation status and proliferation of AML cells. Thus, we 
cloned an E2F7 derivative with a 3 
0 -UTR devoid of miRNA 
target sites in a stable and Tet-on inducible system derived 
from the enhanced PiggyBac (ePiggyBac) transposon (EBP-
PURO) giving rise to the EBP-PURO-E2F7 construct. 
Doxycycline (Dox) treatment of U937 cells transformed with 
EBP-PURO-E2F7 increased the levels of E2F7 as compared 
with those transformed with the empty vector EBP-PURO 
(Figure 5a). Moreover, E2F7 overexpression is retained after 
VitD3 treatment, when endogenous E2F7 protein levels 
decreased (Figure 5a). High levels of E2F7 resulted in a 
reduction of VitD3-induced monocytic differentiation 
assessed by morphological changes and percentage of 
CD11-and CD14-positive cells compared to cells transfected 
with the empty vector (Figures 5c-e). Moreover, enforced 
E2F7 expression resulted in increased proliferation rate and 
percentage of cells in the S phase, while decreased the 
number of cells arrested in the G1 phase (Figures 5b, f and g). 
Notably, this effect is maintained even after VitD3 treatment 
(Figures 5f and g). Altogether, these data indicated that 
increased levels of E2F7 stimulated proliferation and 
counteracted monocytic differentiation of AML cells; there-
fore, suggesting that one of the pathways by which miR-26a </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>E2F7 </p>

<p>L-shSCR 
L-shE2F7 </p>

<p>VitD3 </p>

<p>Ctr </p>

<p>CD14 </p>

<p>GeoMean 
CD11b/CD14 </p>

<p>M-CSF 
M-CSFr </p>

<p>Relative expression 
Relative expression </p>

<p>CD11b </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>63.25% 
36.52% </p>

<p>0.22% 
0.01% 
0.00% 
0.10% </p>

<p>80.49% 
19.42% </p>

<p>L-shSCR 
L-shE2F7 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>2500 </p>

<p>L-shSCR L-shE2F7 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>VitD3 </p>

<p>Ctr </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>MafB </p>

<p>10 4 
10 3 
10 2 
10 1 
10 0 
10 4 
10 3 
10 2 
10 1 
10 0 </p>

<p>L-shSCR 
L-shE2F7 
L-shSCR 
L-shE2F7 
L-shSCR L-shE2F7 </p>

<p>Figure 3 E2F7 counteracts monocytic differentiation of AML cells. (a) Western blot analysis of E2F7 levels from U937 cells infected with L-shE2F7 or L-shSCR. GAPDH 
was utilized as the loading control. (b) Morphological analysis of L-shE2F7-and L-shSCR-infected cells treated without (Ctr) or with 250 ng/ml of VitD3 for 72 h. 
(c) Representative FACS analysis of CD11b-and CD14-positive cells after VitD3 treatment. (d) The histogram represents the geometric mean ± S.E.M. of CD11b/CD14-
positive cells after VitD3 treatment and indicates the average intensity of CD11b/CD14 in a population. (e) qPCR analysis of monocytic specific markers. Data were normalized 
for GAPDH mRNA. The histograms represent the means±S.E.M. from three independent experiments </p>

<p>The miR-26a target E2F7 counteracts monocytic differentiation 
B Salvatori et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>promotes monocytopoiesis of AML cells is through E2F7 
repression. </p>

<p>E2F7 represses p21 
CIP1/WAF1 expression. To explain the 
effect of E2F7 on AML cells, we investigated the level of the 
cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor p21 </p>

<p>CIP1/WAF1 </p>

<p>, which has a 
crucial role in inducing cell cycle arrest and monocytic dif-
ferentiation of AML cells 
6 and whose levels are increased 
upon VitD3 treatment (Figure 2b). In addition, E2F repres-
sors, including E2F7, have been recently identified has 
negative regulators of p21 
CIP1/WAF1 transcription. 
23,24 Sup-</p>

<p>pression of E2F7 by RNAi was sufficient to produce a 
drastic increase of p21 
CIP1/WAF1 protein levels in AML cells 
(Figure 6a). Notably, a p21 
CIP1/WAF1 increase was also 
observed by overexpressing miR-26a (Figure 2a). 
17 Immu-
nofluorescence analysis also indicated that p21 </p>

<p>CIP1/WAF1 </p>

<p>protein accumulated in both nuclear and cytoplasmic 
compartments (Figure 6b). To clarify whether E2F7 binds 
the p21 
CIP1/WAF1 promoter in vivo, we carried out chromatin 
immunoprecipitation (ChIP) assays with an E2F7 antibody. 
To assess the specific binding of E2F7, ChIP experiments 
were performed on cells treated with VitD3 (Figure 5c) or </p>

<p>L-shSCR 
L-shE2F7 </p>

<p>DNA content </p>

<p>Events </p>

<p>DNA content </p>

<p>Events </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>20.0 </p>

<p>30.0 </p>

<p>40.0 </p>

<p>50.0 </p>

<p>60.0 </p>

<p>70.0 </p>

<p>Percent of cells </p>

<p>G 1 
S 
G 2 /M </p>

<p>U937 </p>

<p>L-shSCR </p>

<p>L-shE2F7 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>Cell no. (10 3 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>days </p>

<p>L-shSCR </p>

<p>L-shE2F7 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>L-shE2F7 
L-shSCR </p>

<p>CDK2 
CDK4 </p>

<p>L-shE2F7 
L-shSCR 
Relative expression 
Relative expression 
Relative expression </p>

<p>CDK6 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
8 </p>

<p>G1= 43.3% 
S = 36.5% 
G2/M = 20.2% </p>

<p>G1= 62.2% 
S = 12.5% 
G2/M = 25.3% </p>

<p>L-shE2F7 
L-shSCR </p>

<p>Figure 4 Interference against E2F7 inhibits AML cell proliferation. (a) Effect of L-shE2F7 and L-shSCR on cell proliferation. (b) Cell cycle distribution of cells transduced 
with L-shE2F7 and L-shSCR. The histograms represent the means±S.E.M. from three independent experiments. (c) Representative cell cycle analysis of cells transduced 
with L-shE2F7 and L-shSCR. (d) qPCR analysis of positive cell cycle regulators. Data were normalized for GAPDH mRNA. The histograms represent the means±S.E.M. from 
three independent experiments </p>

<p>The miR-26a target E2F7 counteracts monocytic differentiation 
B Salvatori et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>upon repression of E2F7 expression by shRNAs (Figure 6d). 
A specific enrichment of the p21 
CIP1/WAF1 promoter regions in 
E2F7-immunoprecipitated samples from untreated cells was 
observed. Notably, the immunoprecipitations were strongly 
reduced after VitD3 treatment or RNAi for E2F7, in 
accordance with the decreased E2F7 protein levels 
(Figures 2b and 6a). These data indicate that E2F7 
contributes to repress p21 
CIP1/WAF1 expression in AML cells. </p>

<p>E2F7 sustains miR-17-92 cluster expression. Previous 
work demonstrated a relevant contribution for the miR-17-92 
cluster in blocking monocyte/macrophage differentiation and 
leukemogenesis. 
25,26 More importantly, inhibition of miR-17-
92 expression cluster has been associated to monocyte/ 
macrophage differentiation of both normal progenitors and 
AML cells. 
25,26 Thus, we analyzed the expression levels of 
miR-17-92 upon silencing of E2F7 in U937. All cluster </p>

<p>G1= 62.5% 
S = 32.2% 
G2/M = 5.3% </p>

<p>G1= 49.3% 
S = 44.1% 
G2/M = 6.6% </p>

<p>ePB-PURO 
ePB-PURO-E2F7 </p>

<p>Ctr+ 
Dox </p>

<p>VitD3+ 
Dox </p>

<p>G1= 81.9% 
S = 12.9% 
G2/M = 5.1% </p>

<p>G1= 76% 
S = 18.8% 
G2/M = 5.2% </p>

<p>DNA content </p>

<p>Events </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>4000 </p>

<p>6000 </p>

<p>8000 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>ePB-PURO-E2F7 +Dox </p>

<p>ePB-PURO+Dox </p>

<p>Cell no. (10 3 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>days </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>150% </p>

<p>Percent of cells </p>

<p>G2/M </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>G1 </p>

<p>Ctr 
+Dox </p>

<p>VitD3 
+Dox </p>

<p>ePB-PURO ePB-PURO-E2F7 </p>

<p>Ctr 
+Dox </p>

<p>VitD3 
+Dox </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>E2F7 </p>

<p>ePB-PURO : 
ePB-PURO-E2F7 : 
Dox : 
VitD3 : </p>

<p>CD14 </p>

<p>CD11b </p>

<p>67.05% 
32.92% </p>

<p>0.02% 
0.00% </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>55.11% 
44.82% </p>

<p>0.07% 
0.00% </p>

<p>ePB-PURO 
ePB-PURO-E2F7 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>3000 </p>

<p>4000 </p>

<p>GeoMean 
CD11b/CD14 </p>

<p>ePB-
PURO </p>

<p>ePB-
PURO-E2F7 </p>

<p>ePB-PURO 
ePB-PURO-E2F7 </p>

<p>Ctr+ 
Dox </p>

<p>VitD3+ 
Dox </p>

<p>10 4 
10 3 
10 2 
10 1 
10 0 
10 4 
10 3 
10 2 
10 1 
10 0 </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
-
-
-
-</p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>Figure 5 Enforced E2F7 expression stimulates AML cell proliferation and counteracts monocytic differentiation of AML cells. (a) Western blot analysis of E2F7 protein 
levels in U937 cells transformed with EPB-PURO and EPB-PURO-E2F7. Data were normalized for GAPDH. (b) Effect of EPB-PURO and EPB-PURO-E2F7 on U937 
proliferation upon Dox treatment (200 ng/ml). (c) Morphological analysis of EPB-PURO and EPB-PURO-E2F7 cells treated with Dox alone or in combination with VitD3 for 
72 h. (d) Representative FACS analysis of CD11b-and CD14-positive cells after Dox and VitD3 treatment. (e) The histogram represents the geometric mean ± S.E.M. of 
CD11b/CD14-positive cells after Dox and VitD3 treatment and indicates the average intensity of CD11b/CD14 in a population. (f) Cell cycle distribution of cells transduced with 
EPB-PURO and EPB-PURO-E2F7 and treated with Dox alone or in combination with VitD3 for 72 h. (g) Representative cell cycle analysis of (f) </p>

<p>The miR-26a target E2F7 counteracts monocytic differentiation 
B Salvatori et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>miRNAs were significantly downregulated, and miR-17 and 
miR-20 levels are shown (Figure 7a). Interestingly, a 
decrease in miR-17 and miR-20 levels was also obtained 
upon enforced expression of miR-26a (Figure 7b). ChIP 
experiments showed that the binding of c-Myc on miR-17-92 
promoter region is strongly reduced after VitD3 treatment 
and downregulation of E2F7 levels (Figure 7c). These results 
suggested that E2F7 could contribute to maintain c-Myc 
activity and high level of the miR-17-92 cluster, therein 
sustaining the differentiation block and aberrant proliferation 
of AML cells. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>AML cells are characterized by increased proliferation, block 
of differentiation programs and enhanced self-renewal. 
Insights into the molecular networks that control all these 
processes are critical to fully understand the leukemogenic 
process and develop effective therapies. 
MiRNAs are critical regulators of gene programs that 
control blood cell homeostasis. 
9 For this reason, it is not 
surprising that hematological malignancies are characterized 
by miRNA misregulation. 
9 A critical aspect for understanding 
miRNA function is to link specific miRNAs to their relevant 
targets. A preliminary study showed that miR-26a was </p>

<p>downregulated in AML by the oncogene c-Myc and that 
reconstitution of miR-26a in AML cell lines induced prolifera-
tion arrest and stimulated monocytic differentiation. 
17 This 
study identified as a novel target for miR-26a function in AML 
the transcriptional repressor E2F7. E2F7 belongs to the 
atypical E2F members, which were initially identified as a 
negative regulator of cell cycle progression. 
27 However, 
different studies revealed that atypical E2Fs might also act 
as a positive regulator of cellular proliferation. 
28-31 Here, for 
the first time, we showed that E2F7 expression was 
upregulated in AML primary blasts. Recently, E2F7 was 
found upregulated in rhabdomyosarcoma, indicating that 
E2F7 misregulation might have significant role in tumorigen-
esis. 
32 Herein, we demonstrated that E2F7 silencing in AML 
cell lines inhibited the cellular growth and induced monocytic 
differentiation. Conversely, enforced E2F7 expression stimu-
lated proliferation and counteracted monocytic differentiation. 
The E2F7 knockdown in AML cells delayed cell cycle 
progression and in particular G1/S transition, which was not 
consistent with previous data obtained in fibroblast. 
33 Notably, 
similar results have been described for the other atypical E2F 
factor E2F8 in hepatocellular carcinoma. 
28,34 This suggests 
that E2F7, like E2F8, could act as a positive or negative 
regulator of cell cycle progression in a cellular context-
dependent manner. Therefore, much more work will be </p>

<p>p21 </p>

<p>CIP1/WAf1 </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>Fold enrichment </p>

<p>Ab-E2F7 </p>

<p>VitD3 </p>

<p>Ctr </p>

<p>p21 
CIP1/WAf1 Prom </p>

<p>p21 CIP1/WAf1 
TO-PRO-3 </p>

<p>L-shSCR </p>

<p>L-shE2F7 </p>

<p>merge </p>

<p>L-shE2F7 </p>

<p>L-shSCR </p>

<p>Ab-E2F7 </p>

<p>Fold enrichment </p>

<p>E2F7 </p>

<p>P&lt; 0.005 
P&lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>p21 
CIP1/WAf1 Prom </p>

<p>Figure 6 E2F7 represses the expression of p21 
CIP1/WAF1 in AML cells. (a) Western blot analysis of p21 
CIP1/WAF1 protein levels in cells transduced with L-shE2F7 and 
L-shSCR. Data were normalized for GAPDH. (b) Localization of endogenous p21 
CIP1/WAF1 protein in cells transduced with L-shE2F7 and L-shSCR. DNA staining with 
TO-PRO-3 and a merged view of green and blue channels of the same field is shown (merge). (c) ChIP analysis with anti-E2F7 antibody on p21 
CIP1/WAF1 promoter in U937 
cells before and after VitD3 treatment. (d) ChIP analysis with anti-E2F7 antibody on p21 
CIP1/WAF1 promoter in U937 cells transduced with L-shE2F7 and L-shSCR. The 
recovered DNA in ChIP experiments was quantified by real-time PCR. Results are expressed as the relative level over control cells after correcting for differences in the 
amount of starting (input) chromatin materials. Experiments were performed in triplicate. P-values are indicated </p>

<p>The miR-26a target E2F7 counteracts monocytic differentiation 
B Salvatori et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>necessary to identify E2F7 interacting proteins and assign 
specific functions to E2F7 in different cell lineages. 
Importantly, both miR-26a overexpression and E2F7 
inhibition produces p21 
CIP1/WAF1 accumulation, a factor that 
has a crucial role in the proliferation arrest and monocytic 
differentiation of AML cells. 
6,8 We showed that the transcrip-
tional repressor E2F7 is able to bind to p21 
CIP1/WAF1 promoter 
region in proliferating AML cells; thus, sustaining the 
differentiation block of AML cells by inhibiting p21 </p>

<p>CIP1/WAF1 </p>

<p>expression. In summary, we propose a model in which the 
translational repression of E2F7 by miR-26a could contribute 
to a detachment of E2F7 from p21 
CIP1/WAF1 promoter and, in 
turn, to the induction of p21 
CIP1/WAF1 expression during VitD3-
mediated differentiation of AML cell lines. It is worth noting that 
just as E2F7 is just one of the hundreds of potential targets of 
miR-26a, p21 
CIP1/WAF1 is just one of the downstream effectors </p>

<p>of E2F7. Further studies will be needed to understand the 
relevance of this model in normal monocytopoiesis and AML. 
Previous studies have shown that the transcriptional activity 
of c-Myc is inhibited by p21 
CIP1/WAF1 protein. 
15 c-Myc 
transcriptionally activates the oncogenic miR-17-92 cluster, </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>containing miRNAs known to inhibit monocytic/macrophage 
differentiation of both normal myeloid progenitors and AML 
cells. 
25,26 Moreover, increased expression of miR-17-92 has 
been reported in AML patients where it helps to maintain self-
renewal of leukemic cells. 
26,35 Our studies showed that, in our 
cellular system, E2F7 contributed to control miR-17-92 
expression. Indeed, E2F7 inhibition is sufficient to produce a 
decrease of miR-17-92. This suggests a model in which E2F7 
could control miR-17-92 expression through the inhibition of 
c-Myc activity by p21 </p>

<p>CIP1/WAF1 </p>

<p>. However, further experiments 
will be needed to clarify the relation between p21 
CIP1/WAF1 , 
c-Myc and miR-17-92 expression. Notably, the p21 </p>

<p>CIP1/WAF1 </p>

<p>mRNA is also a target of the miR-17 family. 
26,35,36 Conse-
quently, the decreased expression of miR-17-92 might 
contribute to enforce p21 
CIP1/WAF1 expression during AML 
cell differentiation. This indicates that upregulation of E2F7 
could contribute to oncogenesis in AML by maintaining high 
levels of miR-17-92. 
In conclusion, this study identified a novel aspect of VitD3 
action in regulating proliferation and differentiation of AML 
cells through the miR-26a/E2F7/p21 
CIP1/WAF1 network. How-
ever, it should be considered that the level of complexity of 
gene regulation during these processes is such that no single 
circuitry operates in isolation and they are very likely part of 
fully integrated networks within the cells. Therein, the 
biological effect of a specific miRNA strongly depends on 
the cellular context. In particular, miR-26a has been shown to 
induce proliferation arrest in different tumor model systems, 
such as lymphomas and liver, breast and nasopharyngeal 
carcinomas. 
16,17,21,22,37 Conversely, it has been shown to act 
as an oncogene in glioblastoma. 
38 An important aspect to 
consider in using miR-26a as an antitumor molecule in AML is 
that p21 
CIP1/WAF1 not only has a relevant role in the 
proliferation arrest during differentiation of normal and 
pathological hematopoietic progenitors 
6-8 but also prevents 
excess DNA-damage accumulation and exhaustion of cancer 
stem cells. 
39 Thus, consideration should be given to the 
design of antitumor therapies based on miR-26a. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods 
Cell cultures and reagents. HL-60 and U937 cell lines were maintained in 
RPMI 1640 medium supplemented with 1 Â penicillin/streptomycin solution, 1 Â 
L-glutamine and 10% fetal bovine serum. VitD3 and Dox were purchased from 
Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA) and utilized at a concentration of 250 and 
200 ng/ml, respectively, unless differently specified. 
Mononuclear cells (MCs) were isolated from the peripheral blood (PB) of 
informed healthy donors as reported. 
17 Monocytes were isolated from MCs by 
adherence. Percentage of monocytes after the isolation was assessed using 
morphology and FACS analysis and was higher than 80%. PB/BM cells were 
obtained from 21 informed, newly diagnosed AML patients (Supplementary 
Table 1). Cases were classified according to the FAB classification and showed an 
initial percentage of circulating blasts more than 80%. </p>

<p>RNA interference and miR-26a overexpression. E2F7 knockdown 
was obtained by Mission Lentiviral shRNA clones targeting E2F7 
TRCN0000017455 and TRCN000017453 (Sigma-Aldrich). Mission Lentiviral 
Non-Targeting shRNA clone SHC002 (Sigma-Aldrich) was utilized as control. </p>

<p>miR-17 
miR-20a </p>

<p>Relative expression 
Relative expression </p>

<p>miR-17 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>miR-20a </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>Fold enrichment </p>

<p>Ab-Myc </p>

<p>L-shE2F7 </p>

<p>L-shSCR </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>miR-17-92 
Fold enrichment </p>

<p>Ab-Myc </p>

<p>VitD3 </p>

<p>Ctr </p>

<p>P&lt; 0.05 
P&lt; 0.005 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1.50 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Prom 
miR-17-92 Prom </p>

<p>Figure 7 (a) qPCR analysis of miR-17 and miR-20a in cells transduced with 
L-shE2F7 and L-shSCR. (b) qPCR analysis of miR-17 and miR-20a in cells 
transduced with Lenti-26a and mock. (c) ChIP analysis with anti-c-Myc antibody on 
miR-17-92 cluster promoter in cells treated with VitD3 for 72 h or transduced with 
L-shE2F7 and L-shSCR. The recovered DNA in ChIP experiments was quantified 
by real-time PCR. Results are expressed as the relative level over control cells after 
correcting for differences in the amount of starting (input) chromatin materials. 
Experiments were performed in triplicate. P-values are indicated </p>

<p>The miR-26a target E2F7 counteracts monocytic differentiation 
B Salvatori et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Lentiviral particles were prepared according to the manufacturer's specifications. 
Lentiviral vectors for miR-26a expression and control were described previously. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>Infection of AML cell lines was performed as described previously. </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Cell proliferation and differentiation. For cell cycle analysis, 2 Â 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>cells were resuspended in PBS/50% FCS, fixed in 70% ethanol for 24 h, incubated 
with 50 Ag/ml propidium iodide (Sigma-Aldrich) and 50 U/ml DNase-free RNase A 
(Sigma-Aldrich), and analyzed after 3 h (10 000 events) using an Epics XL 
Cytometer (Beckman Coulter, Brea, CA, USA). Morphology was evaluated after 
7 days from lentiviral transduction in conventional light-field microscopy of 
Wright-Giemsa-stained cytospins. Differentiation was assessed by direct immuno-
fluorescence staining of cells using an allophycocyanin anti-human CD11b (Becton 
Dickinson, San Jose, CA, USA), PerCP anti-human CD14 (Becton Dickinson) 
and PE-IgG1 isotype control (eBiosciences, San Diego, CA, USA) as described 
previously. 
17 A minimum of 10 000 events were collected for each sample with 
flow cytometer (CyAN ADP; Dako Italia S.p.a., Milan, Italy) by using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">Summit</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">4.3</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Beckman Coulter</rs>) for data acquisition and analysis. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence. A total of 2 Â 10 
5 cells were spotted onto the slide 
by cytospin, fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde in PBS for 15 min at room 
temperature (RT) and then washed with PBS for 10 min at RT. The cells were 
incubated with p21 antibody (Cell Signaling Technology, Beverly, MA, USA) and 
diluted in 1% PBS/BSA for 1 h at RT. The slides were then washed with PBS for 
10 min at RT and subsequently incubated with Alexa Fluor 488 (rabbit)-conjugated 
secondary antibody (Molecular Probes Inc., Eugene, OR, USA) for 1 h at RT. 
After washing with PBS, slides were counterstained with TO-PRO-3 for 10 min 
and mounted with Vectashield (Vector Labs, Burlingame, CA, USA). Cells were 
examined under a Leica TCS SP2 fluorescence confocal microscope (Leica 
Microsystems, Wetzlar, Germany) (argon 488 nm laser). Photomicrographs were 
acquired with <rs id="software-2" type="software">LAS AF</rs> Software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Leica Microsystems</rs>). </p>

<p>RNA extraction and analysis. Total RNA was prepared using Qiazol 
reagent and miRNAeasy kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). Hsa-miR-26a analysis 
by real-time PCR was performed using miRScript System (Qiagen) and E2F7 
analysis was performed with QuantiTect Primer Assay QT00059115 (Qiagen). 
Delta-delta Ct values were normalized with those obtained from the amplification 
of the endogenous U6 snRNA (Qiagen). P-values between primary AML samples 
and monocytes data were obtained with t-test. cDNAs for p21, CDK2, CDK4 and 
CDK6 analysis were generated with miRScript RT Kit (Qiagen). Oligonucleotides 
are described in the primers list (shown below). M-CSF, M-CSFr and MafB 
were detected with TaqMan oligonucleotides Hs00166144_m1, Hs00234622_m1 
and Hs00534343_s1, respectively, and normalized by the amplification of 
glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) Hs99999905_m1 (Applied 
Biosystems, Life Technologies Italia, Monza MB, Italy). MiR-17 and miR-20a 
were detected with TaqMan microRNA assay TM-393 and TM-580 (Applied 
Biosystems), respectively. Delta-delta Ct values were normalized with those 
obtained from the amplification of the endogenous U6 snRNA, TaqMan probe 
TM-1093 (Applied Biosystems). All reactions were performed in triplicate. 
Primers list: </p>

<p>Name 
Sequence </p>

<p>CDK2 fw 
5 
0 -CTCCACCGAGACCTTAAAC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>CDK2 rev 
5 
0 -AAGTAACTCCTGGCCACACC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>CDK4 fw 
5 
0 -TTCGTGAGGTGGCTTTACTG-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>CDK4 rev 
5 
0 -GATATGTCCTTAGGTCCTGGTCT-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>CDK6 fw 
5 
0 -CTCCGAGGTCTGGACTTTTCT-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>CDK6 rev 
5 
0 -TGCTCTGTACCACAGCGTGA-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>INTERGENIC fw 
5 
0 -AAACCACCCATCCAGAAGGG-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>INTERGENIC rev 
5 
0 -CGTGGCAGCACTCGTAAGACT-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>P21 PROM fw 
5 
0 -GCGCTCTGTTACGTGCACACATTT-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>P21PROM rev 
5 
0 -AAGAGCTTGTTCCAGAGCCAGGAT-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>MIR-17 PROM fw 
5 
0 -AAAGGCAGGCTCGTCGTTG-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>MIR-17 PROM rev 
5 
0 -CGGGATAAAGAGTTGTTTCTCCAA-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>P21 fw 
5 
0 -GGCAGACCAGCATGACAGATT-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>P21 rev 
5 
0 -GCGGATTAGGGCTTCCTCTT-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Immunoblot analysis. In all, 40 mg of whole cell extract was separated by 
10% SDS-PAGE and electroblotted to nitrocellulose membrane (Protran S&amp;S, </p>

<p>Drammen, Norway). Immunoblots were incubated with antibodies to p21 (sc-817; 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Cruz, CA, USA), E2F7 (BCN4776, AntibodyBCN) 
and GAPDH (sc-25778; Santa Cruz Biotechnology). </p>

<p>ChIP assay. DNA/protein crosslinking and ChIP with anti-E2F7 (BCN4776; 
AntibodyBCN) and anti-c-Myc (sc-764; Santa Cruz Biotechnology) antibodies were 
performed as described previously. 
17 Immuoprecipitation without specific antibody 
was performed as negative control. Negative control amplifications were 
performed on intergenic region. 
17 The relative occupancy of the immunoprecipi-
tated factor at a locus was estimated by using the comparative threshold 
method. 
17 Oligonucleotides for promoters and intergenic region detection are 
described in the primers list. P-values were obtained with t-test. </p>

<p>E2F7 overexpression. The E2F7 cDNA clone was purchased from Open 
Biosystems (Thermo Scientific, Rockford, IL, USA) (clone 9020354) and subcloned in 
the ePiggyBac (EPB) vector EPB-PURO 
41 generating the EPB-PURO-E2F7 plasmid. 
This plasmid contains a TET-on system for inducible transgene expression. Helper 
and transposon plasmids were electroporated in U937 with the Neon Transfection 
System (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer's instruction. 
Selection with puromycin was initiated 2 days after transfection and maintained until 
resistant colonies became visible. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest 
The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements. We thank Professor L Naldini for lentiviral plasmids, 
Dr. A Rosa and Dr. A Brivanlou for the ePiggyBac inducible transposon system, 
O Sthandier, M Marchioni and M Arceci for technical assistance. BS is a recipient of 
a fellowship from the Italian Foundation for Cancer Research (FIRC). This work was 
supported by grants from: Italian Association for Cancer Research (AIRC), Italian 
Institute of Technology (IIT) 'SEED' project, MIUR-FIRB and 'Centro di eccellenza 
BEMM' -Sapienza University of Rome. </p>



<p>The miR-26a target E2F7 counteracts monocytic differentiation 
B Salvatori et al </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease is an open-access journal 
published by Nature Publishing Group. This work is 
licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-No 
Derivative Works 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, 
visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies the paper on Cell Death and Disease website (http://www.nature.com/cddis) </p>

<p>The miR-26a target E2F7 counteracts monocytic differentiation 
B Salvatori et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

</text></tei>