<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3245946" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>b-D-3 0 -Azido-2 0 ,3 0 -dideoxyguanosine (3 0 -azido-ddG) 
is a potent inhibitor of HIV-1 replication with a 
superior resistance profile to zidovudine. Recently, 
we identified five novel 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddG 
analogs that exhibit similar or superior anti-HIV-1 
activity compared to 3 0 -azido-ddG in primary cells. 
To gain insight into their structure-activity-resist-
ance relationships, we synthesized their triphos-
phate (TP) forms and assessed their ability to 
inhibit HIV-1 reverse transcriptase (RT). Steady-
state and pre-steady-state kinetic experiments 
show that the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP analogs 
act as adenosine rather than guanosine mimetics 
in DNA synthesis reactions. The order of potency 
of the TP analogs against wild-type RT was: 
3 0 -azido-2,6-diaminopurine &gt;3 0 -azido-6-chloropurine; 
3 0 -azido-6-N-allylaminopurine &gt; 2-amino-6-N,N-
dimethylaminopurine; 
2-amino-6-methoxypurine. 
Molecular 
modeling 
studies 
reveal 
unique 
hydrogen-bonding interactions between the nucleo-
tide analogs and the template thymine base in the 
active site of RT. Surprisingly, the structure-activity 
relationship of the analogs differed in HIV-1 RT 
ATP-mediated excision assays of their monophos-
phate forms, suggesting that it may be possible to 
rationally design a modified base analog that is 
efficiently incorporated by RT but serves as a poor </p>

<p>substrate for ATP-mediated excision reactions. 
Overall, these studies identify a promising strategy 
to design novel nucleoside analogs that exert pro-
found antiviral activity against both WT and drug-
resistant HIV-1. </p>

<p>Most combination therapies used to treat antiretroviral-
naı¨ve and -experienced HIV-1 infected patients include at 
least two nucleoside reverse transcriptase (RT) inhibitors 
(NRTIs). NRTIs are analogs of 2 0 -deoxyribonucleosides 
that lack a 3 0 -OH group on the ribose sugar/pseudosugar. 
Once metabolized by host cell kinases to their active tri-
phosphate (TP) forms, they inhibit viral reverse transcrip-
tion by acting as chain terminators of HIV-1 RT DNA 
synthesis (1). Although combination therapies that contain 
two or more NRTIs have substantially reduced mortality 
from HIV-1 associated disease, the approved NRTIs have 
significant limitations that include acute and chronic tox-
icity, and the selection of drug-resistant variants of HIV-1 
that exhibit cross-resistance to other NRTIs. Accordingly, 
there is a need to develop potent and safe NRTIs that 
demonstrate activity against a broad-range of drug-
resistant HIV-1. 
To date, most NRTIs were discovered by an empirical 
approach in which novel sugar modified nucleoside ana-
logs were synthesized without a priori knowledge of their 
activity against wild-type (WT) or drug-resistant HIV-1. 
To specifically identify NRTIs that retain activity </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 412 648 8457; Fax: +1 412 648 8521; Email: nps2@pitt.edu </p>

<p>Published online 13 September 2011 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 1 381-390 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkr756 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>against a broad spectrum of drug-resistant HIV-1, our 
group adopted a rational discovery approach that util-
ized structure-activity-resistance relationships to identify 
NRTI base and sugar moieties that retain potent ac-
tivity against drug-resistant HIV-1 (2,3). Importantly, 
this approach identified 3 0 -azido-2 0 ,3 0 -dideoxyguanosine 
(3 0 -azido-ddG) as a lead compound (4) that exhibits 
potent activity against HIV-1 variants that contain the 
discrimination mutations K65R, L74V or M184V and 
against HIV-1 that contains multiple thymidine analog 
mutations (TAMs) that enhance nucleotide excision. 
Furthermore, 3 0 -azido-ddG does not exhibit cytotoxicity 
in primary lymphocytes or epithelial and T-cell lines, and 
does not decrease the mitochondrial DNA content of 
HepG2 cells (4). 
To further improve the antiviral activity of 3 0 -azido-
ddG, we recently synthesized and characterized a series 
of novel base modified 3 0 -azido-2 0 ,3 0 -dideoxypurine 
analogs (5). Of the 26 analogs studied, five [namely, 
3 0 -azido-2 0 ,3 0 -dideoxy-2,6-diaminopurine 
(3 0 -azido-2, 
6-DA-P), 3 0 -azido-2 0 ,3 0 -dideoxy-2-amino-6-chloropurine 
(3 0 -azido-6-Cl-P), 3 0 -azido-2 0 ,3 0 -dideoxy -2-amino-6-N, 
N-dimethylaminopurine (3 0 -azido-6-DM-P), 3 0 -azido-2 0 , 
3 0 -dideoxy-2-amino-6-methoxypurine (3 0 -azido-6-MX-P) 
and 3 0 -azido-2 0 ,3 0 -dideoxy-2-amino-6-N-allylaminopurine 
(3 0 -azido-6-AA-P)] exhibited superior or equivalent activ-
ity to 3 0 -azido-ddG in primary lymphocytes (Figure 1). To 
gain additional insight into the structure-activity-resist-
ance relationships of these compounds, we have now 
synthesized their TP forms and have assessed their 
ability to inhibit DNA synthesis by recombinant purified 
HIV-1 RT. Importantly, we show for the first time that 
HIV-1 RT recognizes and incorporates these 6-modified-
3 0 -azido-ddGTP nucleotides as adenosine analogs. These 
findings reveal new avenues for developing novel ambigu-
ous nucleoside analogs that could be used to treat HIV-1 
infection. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Reagents </p>

<p>The WT, K65R, L74V, M184V, A62V/V75I/F77L/ 
F116Y/Q151M, M41L/L210W/T215Y (TAM41) and 
D67N/K70R/T215F/K219Q (TAM67) HIV-1 RTs were 
purified as described previously (6,7). The protein concen-
tration of the purified enzymes was determined spectro-
photometrically at 280 nm using an extinction coefficient 
(e 280 ) of 260 450 M À1 cm À1 , and by Bradford protein assays 
(Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA). The RNA-and 
DNA-dependent DNA polymerase activities of the puri-
fied WT and mutant enzymes were similar (data not 
shown). The triphosphate (TP) forms of each of the 
6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddG analogs were synthesized and 
purified using the methods of Ludwig and Eckstein (8). 
3 0 -Azido-ddGTP, 3 0 -azido-ddATP, 3 0 -azido-ddCTP and 
zidovudine-TP (ZDV-TP) were purchased from TriLink 
Biotechnologies, Inc. (San Diego, CA, USA). [g-32 P]ATP 
was obtained from PerkinElmer Life Sciences (Boston, 
MA, USA). All DNA oligonucleotides were synthesized 
by Integrated DNA Technologies (Coralville, IA, USA). </p>

<p>Inhibition of HIV-1 RT DNA synthesis under steady-state 
conditions by the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP analogs </p>

<p>The ability of the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP analogs to 
inhibit HIV-1 RT DNA-or RNA-dependent DNA syn-
thesis was determined using two different template/primer 
(T/P) substrates, as described below: </p>

<p>(i) RT DNA synthesis was evaluated using a 214-nt 
RNA or DNA template that corresponds to the 
HIV-1 sequence used for (À) strong stop DNA syn-
thesis (Figure 2). The RNA and DNA templates were 
prepared as described previously (3). Both the RNA-
and DNA-dependent DNA synthesis reactions were 
primed with the same 5 0 -end-32 P-labeled 18-nt DNA </p>

<p>Figure 1. Structures of zidovudine (ZDV), 3 0 -azido-2 0 ,3 0 -dideoxyadenosine (3 0 -azido-ddA), 3 0 -azido-2 0 ,3 0 -dideoxyguanosine (3 0 -azido-ddG), 
3 0 -azido-2 0 ,3 0 -dideoxy-2,6-diaminopurine 
(3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P), 
3 0 -azido-2 0 ,3 0 -dideoxy-2-amino-6-chloropurine 
(3 0 -azido-6-Cl-P), 
3 0 -azido-2-
,3 0 -dideoxy-2-amino-6-N,N-dimethylaminopurine (3 0 -azido-6-DM-P), 3 0 -azido-2 0 ,3 0 -dideoxy-2-amino-6-methoxypurine (3 0 -azido-6-MX-P) and 
3 0 -azido-2 0 ,3 0 -dideoxy-2-amino-6-N-allylaminopurine (3 0 -azido-6-AA-P). The EC 50 values, adapted from Zhang et al. (5), are for WT HIV-1 and 
were determined in peripheral blood mononuclear (PBM) cells. </p>

<p>382 Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 1 </p>

<p>primer (5 0 -GTCCCTGTTCGGGCGCCA-3 0 ) that cor-
responds to the HIV-1 primer binding site. DNA syn-
thesis reactions (20 ml) were carried out in a 50-mM 
Tris-HCl (pH 7.5) buffer that contained 50 mM KCl, 
10 mM MgCl 2 , 20 nM T/P, 0.5 mM of each dNTP and 
varying concentrations of the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-
ddGTP analogs. Reactions were initiated by the 
addition of 200 nM WT HIV-1 RT, incubated at 
37 C for 30 min (DNA-dependent DNA synthesis) or 
60 min (RNA-dependent DNA synthesis) and then 
quenched by addition of 20 ml of gel loading buffer 
(98% deionized formamide containing 1 mg/ml each </p>

<p>of bromophenol blue and xylene cyanol). Samples 
were then denatured at 95 C for 10 min and polymer-
ization products were separated from substrates by 
denaturing gel electrophoresis using 14% acryl-
amide gels containing 7 M urea. DNA synthesis was 
analyzed by phosphorimaging using a GS-525 
Molecular Imager and Quantity One Software 
(Bio-Rad Laboratories, Inc., Hercules, CA, USA). 
(ii) Inhibition of HIV-1 RT DNA synthesis was also 
evaluated to determine IC 50 values using a 
5 0 -end-32 P-labeled 19-nt DNA primer (5 0 -TTGTAG 
CACCATCCAAAGG-3 0 ) that was annealed to one </p>

<p>Figure 2. 6-Modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTPs are recognized and incorporated by WT HIV-1 as adenosine analogs. (A) Representative denaturing poly-
acrylamide gel showing chain-termination of HIV-1 RT DNA synthesis by each of the 3 0 -azido-ddGTPs on a heteropolymeric DNA/DNA T/P under 
steady-state assay conditions. (B) Representative denaturing polyacrylamide gel showing chain termination of WT HIV-1 RT DNA synthesis by each 
of the 3 0 -azido-ddGTPs on a heteropolymeric RNA/DNA T/P under steady-state assay conditions. Reaction conditions are described in the 
'Materials and Methods' section. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 1 383 </p>

<p>of three 36-nt DNA templates that contained five 
consecutive thymine, cytosine or adenosine bases. 
In this regard, inhibition of HIV-1 RT DNA syn-
thesis by analogs with adenine, guanine or thymine 
bases were evaluated using the templates (T1, 5 0 -CA 
GACTTTTTCAGACCTTTGGATGGTGCTACA 
AGCT-3 0 ), (T2, 5 0 -CAGAGCCCCCGAGACCTTT 
GGATGGTGCTACAAGCT-3 0 ), or (T3, 5 0 -CTGC 
TAAAAACTGCCCTTTGGATGGTGCTACAAG 
CT-3 0 ), respectively. The T1 template was used for 
inhibition of WT and mutant HIV-1 RT DNA syn-
thesis by each of the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP 
analogs. Reaction conditions and gel electrophoresis 
were identical to those described above except 
100 nM of WT or mutant HIV-1 RT was used to 
initiate the reaction. Reactions were quenched fol-
lowing incubation at 37 C for 10 min. The amount 
of final product on the denaturing polyacrylamide 
gel electrophoresis (PAGE) gels was quantified by 
densiometric analysis using <rs type="software">Quantity One</rs> Software. 
The concentration of each 6-modified-3 0 -azido-
ddGTP analog required to inhibit the formation of 
final product by 50% was calculated using non-
linear regression analyses (<rs id="software-6" type="software">SigmaPlot Software</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">Version 11</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">Systat Software, Inc., San Jose, CA, USA.</rs>) from at least three independent experiments. 
Two-tailed homoscedastic t-tests were used to calcu-
late the reported P-values. </p>

<p>Pre-steady-state incorporation of 
6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP analogs </p>

<p>A rapid quench instrument (Kintek RQF-3 instrument, 
Kintek Corporation, Clarence, PA, USA) was used for 
pre-steady-state experiments. The typical experiment was 
performed at 37 C in 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5) contain-
ing 50 mM KCl, 10 mM MgCl 2 and varying concentra-
tions of nucleotide. All concentrations reported refer to 
the final concentrations after mixing. HIV-1 RT 
(200 nM) was pre-incubated with 20 nM T/P substrate, 
prior to rapid mixing with nucleotide and divalent metal 
ions to initiate the reaction that was quenched with 50 mM 
EDTA. The sequences of the template and 5 0 -radiolabeled 
primer are shown in Table 1. The quenched samples were 
then mixed with an equal volume of gel loading buffer and 
products were separated from substrates as described 
above. The disappearance of substrate (20mer) and the 
formation of product (21-mer) were quantified using a 
Bio-Rad GS525 Molecular Imager (Bio-Rad Laboratories, 
Inc., Hercules, CA, USA). Data were fitted by nonlinear 
regression with <rs id="software-4" type="software">Sigma Plot software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Systat Software, Inc., San Jose, CA, USA.</rs>) using the appropriate equa-
tions (9). The apparent burst rate constant (k obs ) for 
each particular concentration of dNTP was determined 
by fitting the time courses for the formation of prod-
uct (21mer) using the following equation: [21mer] = 
A[1 À exp(Àk obs t)], where A represents the burst ampli-
tude. The turnover number (k pol ) and apparent dissoci-
ation constant for dNTP (K d ) were then obtained by 
plotting the apparent catalytic rates (k obs ) against dNTP </p>

<p>concentrations and fitting the data with the following 
hyperbolic equation: k obs = (k pol [dNTP])/([dNTP]+K d ). 
Catalytic efficiency was calculated as the ratio of turnover 
number over dissociation constant ([k pol /K d ]). Selectivity 
for natural dNTP versus 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP 
analog was calculated as the ratio of catalytic efficiency 
of dNTP over that of the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP 
analog ([(k pol /K d ) dNTP /(k pol /K d ) Analog ]). </p>

<p>Excision of the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddG monophosphate 
analogs by WT or TAM-containing HIV-1 RTs </p>

<p>The ability of WT or TAM-containing HIV-1 RT to fa-
cilitate ATP-mediated excision of the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-
ddG-MP analogs from a DNA/DNA chain-terminated 
T/P was assessed as described previously (3). For 
excision of 3 0 -azido-ddAMP and each 6-modified-3 0 -
azido-ddGMP analog the T/P pair was T1/pr23A 
(pr23A: 
5 0 -TTGTAGCACCATCCAAAGGTCTG-3 0 ). 
The 23-nt DNA primer was 5 0 -radiolabeled with 
[g-32 P]ATP, annealed to T1, and then chain-terminated 
with the appropriate nucleotide analog. Reactions were 
carried out in a 50-mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5) buffer that 
contained 50 mM KCl, 10 mM MgCl 2 , 3 mM ATP and </p>

<p>Table 1. Pre-steady-state kinetic values for incorporation of 
6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP analogs by WT HIV-1 RT </p>

<p>Incorporation as an 'A' analog a </p>

<p>Nucleotide analog 
k pol (s À1 ) K d (mM) 
k pol /K d 
(mM À1 s À1 ) </p>

<p>Selectivity b 
versus 
dATP </p>

<p>dATP 
17.0 AE 2.1 c 0.33 AE 0.05 52 
-
3 0 -azido-ddATP 
14.0 AE 5.6 0.32 AE 0.13 44 
1.2 
3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-TP 14.0 AE 4.9 0.29 AE 0.05 48 
1.1 
3 0 -azido-6-Cl-P-TP 
2.7 AE 0.5 
1.8 AE 1.0 
1.5 
35 
3 0 -azido-6-AA-P-TP 
2.1 AE 0.2 
4.8 AE 2.3 
0.44 
118 
3 0 -azido-6-MX-P-TP 
2.8 AE 0.2 12.0 AE 1.2 
0.23 
226 </p>

<p>Incorporation as a 'G' analog d </p>

<p>Nucleotide analog 
k pol (s À1 ) K d (mM) 
k pol /K d 
(mM À1 s À1 ) </p>

<p>Selectivity 
versus 
dGTP </p>

<p>dGTP 
17.3 AE 1.4 0.17 AE 0.05 102 
-
3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-TP 0.16 AE 0.02 
34 AE 14 
0.005 
20 400 
3 0 -azido-6-Cl-P-TP 
0.37 AE 0.04 0.92 AE 0.02 0.402 
254 
3 0 -azido-6-AA-P-TP 
n.m. e 
&gt;50 
n.m. 
n.m. 
3 0 -azido-6-MX-P-TP 0.22 AE 0.09 16.3 AE 4.3 0.013 
7846 </p>

<p>a 3 0 -ACAGGGACAAGCCCGCGGTGACGATCTCTTAAAGGTAA-
GACTGATTTTCCCAGACTC-5 0 ; 5 0 -TCGGGCGCCACTGCTAGAG 
A: Sequence of the T/P substrate used to assess the 6-modified-
3 0 -azido-ddGTP nucleotides as 'A' analogs. 
b Selectivity is (k pol /K d ) dNTP /(k pol /K d ) 3 0 -azido-ddNTP </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Values represent the mean AE standard deviation of three to four inde-
pendent experiments </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>3 0 -ACAGGGACAAGCCCGCGGTGACGATCTCTCAAAGGTAA-
GACTGATTTTCCCAGACTC-5 0 ; 5 0 -TCGGGCGCCACTGCTAGA 
GA: Sequence of the T/P substrate used to assess the 6-modified-
3 0 -azido-ddGTP nucleotides as 'G' analogs </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>n.m. Not measurable. 
The rate of incorporation was so inefficient that accurate kinetic par-
ameters could not be determined. </p>

<p>384 Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 1 </p>

<p>1 mM dATP/10 mM ddGTP. Reactions were initiated by 
the addition of 200 nM WT or mutant RT. Aliquots 
(5 ml) were removed at defined times, quenched with gel 
loading buffer, denatured at 95 C for 10 min, and product 
was then resolved from substrate by denaturing PAGE 
and analyzed, as described above. </p>

<p>Molecular modeling </p>

<p>Molecular models of incorporation were constructed using 
the X-ray crystallographic coordinates (PDB entry 1 
RTD) for the RT-T/P-TTP ternary complex (10). The 
3 0 -OH of the primer strand as well as the 6-modified-
3 0 -azido-2 0 ,3-ddGTP analogs and complementary bases 
in the template strand were built into the model to 
generate a pre-initiation complex, as described previously 
(11). Tautomerization and protonation potential of the 
entire system was calculated using the Generalized 
Born/Volume Integral (GB/VI) electrostatics method of 
Labute (12). Energy gradient minimization was carried 
out using MMFF94x force field in the Molecular 
Operating Environment (MOE 2008.02; Chemical 
Computing Group, Montreal, Quebec, Canada). Ligand 
interactions were quantified and images generated using 
the LigX interaction function in MOE. Structural 
models comparing incorporation and excision of specific 
nucleotide analogs used the PDB co-ordinates 3KLF and 
3KLE that contain the excision product AZT adenosine 
dinucleoside tetraphosphate (AZTppppA) (13). To elimin-
ate the potential force field bias from alignment of bases, 
empirically derived angle relations were used for all analogs 
tested. 3KLF and 3KLE were fit to the p66 subunit of 
1RTD using the Matchmaker function in <rs id="software-1" type="software">Chimera</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 1.51</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">UCSF Chimera, Resource for Biocomputing, Visualization, and Informatics at the University of California, San Francisco.</rs>). Aligned structures 
were opened in MOE and dihedral angles were measured 
from bases relative to the ribose ring O and C1 of both 
template and bound nucleotides for each complex. 
MOE's builder function was used to modify each 
template/bound nucleotide base pair retaining the experi-
mental dihedrals. Hydrogen-bonding potential between the 
aligned base pairs was quantified using the 'FindHBond' 
function in <rs type="software">Chimera</rs> with default settings. Parts of 
modeling workflow was automated using <rs id="software-3" type="software">Pipeline Pilot</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">7.5</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Accelrys Corporation, San Diego, CA, USA.</rs>) </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Steady-state incorporation of 6-modified 3 0 -azido-ddGTP 
nucleotides by HIV-1 RT </p>

<p>To characterize the ability of the WT HIV-1 RT to incorp-
orate the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP analogs we first 
conducted steady-state DNA synthesis reactions using 
heteropolymeric DNA/DNA and RNA/DNA T/P sub-
strates (Figure 2). The sequences of the RNA and DNA 
templates correspond to the HIV-1 sequence used for (À) 
strong stop DNA synthesis, and both reactions were 
primed with the same 18-nt DNA primer that was com-
plementary to the HIV-1 primer binding site (3). 3 0 -Azido-
ddGTP, 3 0 -azido-ddATP, 3 0 -azido-ddCTP and ZDV-TP </p>

<p>were included as controls in these experiments. 
Unexpectedly, we found that HIV-1 RT recognized all of 
the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP nucleotides as adenosine 
analogs and incorporated them opposite thymine in DNA 
(Figure 2A) or uracil in RNA (Figure 2B). As anticipated, 
their incorporation resulted in chain-termination of DNA 
synthesis. Under the assay conditions described in 
Figure 2, the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP nucleotides were 
not incorporated into the nascent DNA opposite cytosine. 
However, if the dNTP concentration was lowered to 
0.1 mM, chain termination opposite cytosine was observed 
(data not shown). We also determined the concentration 
of 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP analog required to inhibit 
DNA synthesis (i.e. IC 50 ) using a different hetero-
polymeric DNA/DNA T/P substrate, as described in the 
'Materials and Methods' section (Table 2). Their order of 
potency against WT RT was determined to be: 3 0 -azido-
ddATP, 
3 0 -azido-ddGTP 
&gt;3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-TP &gt; 
3 0 -azido-6-Cl-P-TP, 
3 0 -azido-6-AA-P-TP &gt; 3 0 -azido-6-
DM-P-TP, 3 0 -azido-6-MX-P-TP. </p>

<p>Pre-steady-state incorporation of 6-modified 3 0 -azido-
ddGTP nucleotides by HIV-1 RT </p>

<p>Pre-steady-state kinetic analyses were carried out to eluci-
date, in detail, the interactions between the 6-modified-
3 0 -azido-ddGTP analogs and the polymerase active site 
of WT HIV-1 RT (Table 1). Because the 6-modified-3 0 -
azido-ddGTP analogs behave as adenine nucleotide 
analogs, we included 3 0 -azido-ddATP as a control. The 
results (Table 1) show that the catalytic efficiency of in-
corporation (k pol /K d ) of 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-TP was similar 
to that of dATP and 3 0 -azido-ddATP. Consistent with the 
steady-state kinetic experiments, 3 0 -azido-6-Cl-P-TP, 
3 0 -azido-6-AA-P-TP and 3 0 -azido-6-MX-P-TP were all 
less efficiently incorporated by WT HIV-1 compared to 
dATP. The observed decreases in catalytic efficiency for 
each of these substrates was driven by both a decrease in 
the rate of nucleotide incorporation (i.e. k pol ) and a 
decrease in the affinity of the nucleotide for the polymer-
ase active site (i.e. K d ). Due to limited quantities of the 
3 0 -azido-6-DM-P-TP, we were unable to obtain 
pre-steady-state kinetic data for this analog. We also 
assessed the ability of the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP 
analogs to be incorporated opposite cytosine (Table 1). 
The data show that, in comparison to dGTP, the 
6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP analogs were inefficiently 
incorporated by HIV-1 RT. The only compound with rea-
sonable activity as a G-analog was 3 0 -azido-6-Cl-P-TP; 
however, its selectivity value versus dGTP (254) was 
$7-fold less than its selectivity value versus dATP (35). </p>

<p>Activity of the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP analogs against 
HIV-1 RT containing NRTI discrimination mutations </p>

<p>The amino acid substitutions K65R, L74V, Q151M (in 
complex with A62V, V75I, F77L and F116Y) or M184V 
in HIV-1 RT improve the enzyme's ability to discriminate 
between the natural dNTP substrate and an NRTI-TP. 
These substitutions are typically referred to as NRTI dis-
crimination mutations. To determine whether NRTI dis-
crimination mutations impacted RTs' ability to recognize </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 1 385 </p>

<p>and incorporate the 6-modified-ddGTP analogs, we deter-
mined the concentration of nucleotide analog required to 
inhibit 50% of the DNA polymerase activity (i.e. IC 50 ) 
under steady-state assay conditions using the heteropoly-
meric DNA/DNA T/P substrates as described in the 
'Materials and Methods' section (Table 2). 3 0 -Azido-
ddATP, 3 0 -azido-ddGTP and ZDV-TP were again in-
cluded as controls. The 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP 
analogs were also incorporated as adenosine analogs by 
the mutant HIV-1 RTs (data not shown). In general, the 
mutant HIV-1 RTs exhibited fold-resistance values to 
each of the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP analogs that 
were similar (i.e. &lt;2-fold) to the fold change in resistance 
values determined for 3 0 -azido-ddATP. The only statistic-
ally significant exceptions (P &lt; 0.05) included 3 0 -azido-
6-AA-P-TP and 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-TP which exhibited 
better activity against K65R HIV-1 RT and M184V 
HIV-1 RT, respectively. Of interest, the fold-resistance 
values for all of the 3 0 -azido-dideoxypurines against 
HIV-1 RT containing A62V/V75I/F77L/Y116F/Q151M 
were significantly less than the fold-resistance value that 
was determined for ZDV-TP. </p>

<p>Excision of 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddG-5 0 -MP analogs by 
WT and TAM containing HIV-1 RT </p>

<p>HIV-1 RT has the intrinsic ability to rescue DNA synthe-
sis from an NRTI-MP blocked primer, using ATP as a 
phosphate donor (14). This ATP-mediated excision activ-
ity of HIV-1 RT is selectively increased by TAMs (15). 
Accordingly, we investigated the ability of WT and 
TAM-containing RT to excise the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-
ddGMP analogs from a DNA chain-terminated T/P. 
Two RT enzymes that contained different patterns of 
TAMs [e.g. D67N/K70R/T215F/K219Q (TAM67) and 
M41L/L210W/T215Y (TAM41)] were studied. Our 
results (Figure 3) showed that the WT, TAM67, and 
TAM41 RTs could unblock T/Ps chain-terminated with 
3 0 -azido-ddAMP, 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-MP and 3 0 -azido-6-
AA-P-MP, although TAM41 RT and TAM67 RT were 
more efficient in this regard than was the WT enzyme. By 
contrast, both the WT and TAM-containing RTs could 
not efficiently unblock T/P substrates chain-terminated 
with 3 0 -azido-6-MX-P-MP, 3 0 -azido-6-Cl-P-MP or 
3 0 -azido-6-DM-P-MP. </p>

<p>Table 2. Inhibition of steady-state WT and mutant HIV-1 RT DNA synthesis by 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP analogs </p>

<p>Nucleotide analog 
HIV-1 RT </p>

<p>WT 
K65R 
L74V 
M184V 
Q151M a </p>

<p>ZDV-TP 
IC 50 (mM) b 
0.13 AE 0.04 
0.66 AE 0.20 
0.18 AE 0.10 
0.12 AE 0.03 
2.7 AE 1.0 
Fold-R c 
-
5.2 
1.4 
0.9 
21.0 
3 0 -azido-ddGTP 
IC 50 (mM) 
0.15 AE 0.01 
0.36 AE 0.02 
0.25 AE 0.10 
0.06 AE 0.02 
0.30 AE 0.20 
Fold-R 
-
2.5 
1.7 
0.4 
2.1 
3 0 -azido-ddATP 
IC 50 (mM) 
0.16 AE 0.10 
0.70 AE 0.10 
0.42 AE 0.10 
0.19 AE 0.10 
1.44 AE 1.00 
Fold-R 
-
4.3 
2.5 
1.2 
8.8 
3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-TP 
IC 50 (mM) 
0.80 AE 0.10 
2.5 AE 1.6 
1.3 AE 0.4 
0.34 AE 0.10 
4.2 AE 3.6 
Fold-R 
-
3.1 
1.6 
0.4 
5.3 
P-value d 
-
0.36 
0.08 
0.02 
0.45 
3 0 -azido-6-Cl-P-TP 
IC 50 (mM) 
3.2 AE 0.8 
9.1 AE 3.8 
11.8 AE 3.9 
2.5 AE 1.0 
30.8 AE 6.1 
Fold-R 
-
2.9 
3.7 
0.8 
9.7 
P-value 
-
0.12 
0.15 
0.22 
0.81 
3 0 -azido-6-AA-P-TP 
IC 50 (mM) 
4.10 AE 0.8 
8.8 AE 0.8 
10.3 AE 1.9 
4.8 AE 0.6 
21.8 AE 12.0 
Fold-R 
-
2.2 
2.5 
1.2 
5.3 
P-value 
-
0.0006 
0.97 
0.94 
0.43 
3 0 -azido-6-DM-P-TP 
IC 50 (mM) 
23.4 AE 13.0 
&gt;50 
&gt;50 
N.D. e 
&gt;50 
Fold-R 
-
&gt;2.0 
&gt;2.0 
&gt;2.0 
P-value 
-
-
-
-
-
3 0 -azido-6-MX-P-TP 
IC 50 (mM) 
24.4 AE 7.0 
80.1 AE 6.1 
&gt;100 
32.9 AE 23.0 
78.0 AE 34.0 
Fold-R 
-
3.3 
&gt;4.0 
1.3 
3.2 
P-value 
-
0.10 
-
0.71 
0.31 </p>

<p>a The Q151M RT contained the A62V, V75I, F77L, F116Y and Q151M mutations. 
b IC 50 values are the concentration of drug required to inhibit 50% of DNA synthesis under steady-state assay conditions. 
Data are shown as the mean AE standard deviation of at least three independent experiments. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Fold-resistance (Fold-R) values are calculated by IC 50 
mutant RT /IC 50 </p>

<p>WT RT </p>

<p>. 
d P-value compares the Fold-R values determined for the 6-modified 3 0 -azido-ddGTP analogs to the Fold-R value determined for 
3 0 -azido-ddATP. </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>Not determined. </p>

<p>386 Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 1 </p>

<p>Molecular models of 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-TP and 
3 0 -azido-6-Cl-P-TP in the active site of HIV-1 RT </p>

<p>We used molecular modeling to gain structural insight 
into the binding interaction between the 6-modified-3 0 -
azido-ddGTP analogs and the thymine base in the DNA 
template in the active site of HIV-1 RT. Specifically we 
modeled 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-TP and 3 0 -azido-6-Cl-P-TP 
into the active site of HIV-1 RT using the co-ordinates 
(1RTD) from the RT-T/P-TTP complex (10). Both 
3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-TP and 3 0 -azido-6-Cl-P-TP were found 
to fit comfortably into the active site of HIV-1 RT and 
formed hydrogen-bond interactions with the thymine base 
in the DNA template (Figure 4). However, the base 
hydrogen-bonding characteristics differed for each analog. 
The base of 3 0 -azido-6-Cl-P-TP forms two hydrogen-bond 
interactions through the nitrogen (NH) at position 1 and 
the amine (NH 2 ) at position 2 with the template thymine 
(Figure 4B). In addition to these two hydrogen-bonding 
interactions, 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-TP can form an add-
itional hydrogen bond via the amino group (NH 2 ) at 
the 6-position of the purine base (Figure 4D). Therefore, 
the 2,6-diaminopurine:thymine base-pairing interaction </p>

<p>mimics the canonical Watson-Crick guanine:cytidine 
interaction. </p>

<p>Molecular models for ATP-mediated excision of the 
6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddG-5 0 -MP analogs </p>

<p>To gain structural insight into why the 6-modified-3 0 -
azido-ddG analogs are differentially excised by HIV-1 
RT containing TAMs, we modeled their excision products 
(6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddG adenosine dinucleoside tetra-
phosphate) in the enzyme's active site. These models 
reveal a hydrogen-bonding network that is different from 
those observed for the TP forms. 3 0 -Azido-ddA forms 
hydrogen bonds from the 1 and 6 atoms to the 3 and 4 
atoms of the complementary thymine template in both the 
incorporation (Figure 4C) and excision (Figure 5A) 
models. By contrast, the hydrogen bond observed between 
the 2-amino substitution and the 2-carbonyl of the thymine 
template observed for the nucleotide triphosphate analogs 
(Figure 4B and D) is lost in all related excision complexes 
(Figure 5B-D). 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P (Figure 5B) and 
3 0 -azido-6-AA-P (Figure 5C) retain an H-bond from the 
6 atom position of the purine ring and the 4 atom position </p>

<p>Figure 3. ATP-mediated excision of 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGMP analogs by WT (A), TAM67 (B) or TAM41 (C) HIV-1 RT. Data are the 
mean AE standard deviation from at least three independent experiments. Reaction conditions are described in the 'Materials and Methods' section. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 1 387 </p>

<p>on the template thymine, whereas this interaction is not 
maintained for 3 0 -azido-6-Cl-P (Figure 5D), 3 0 -azido-6-
DM-P and 3 0 -azido-6-MX-P (data not shown). Taken 
together, these different hydrogen-bonding patterns may 
explain why 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P and 3 0 -azido-6-AA-P are 
more efficiently excised by HIV-1 RT than are 3 0 -azido-
6-Cl-P, 3 0 -azido-6-DM-P and 3 0 -azido-6-MX-P. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, we demonstrated that 6-modified-3 0 -azido-
ddGTP nucleotides act as adenosine mimetics for DNA 
synthesis carried out by HIV-1 RT. Of the five analogs 
studied, 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-TP, which has a 2,6-diamino-
purine base, was found to be the most efficient substrate 
for incorporation by HIV-1 RT. In pre-steady-state 
kinetic experiments, 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-TP was recognized 
and incorporated by WT HIV-1 RT as efficiently as dATP 
and 3 0 -azido-ddATP. The analogs that contain the 
2-amino-6-N,N-dimethylaminopurine (3 0 -azido-6-DM-P-
TP) or 2-amino-6-methoxypurine (3 0 -azido-6-MX-P-TP) </p>

<p>bases, however, were poor substrates for incorporation 
by HIV-1 RT. Our molecular modeling studies suggest 
that 6-modifications with a branched side-chain (e.g. 
3 0 -azido-6-DM-P-TP) or one with electronic incompatibil-
ity (e.g. 3 0 -azido-6-MX-P-TP) may alter the alignment of 
the bases and move their a-phosphate away from the 
primer 3 0 -OH, thus impairing nucleotide incorporation. 
In contrast, 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-TP, 3 0 -azido-6-CL-P-TP 
and 3 0 -azido-6-AA-P-TP form relatively planar base-
pairing interactions with the template thymine that en-
hance their a-phosphate interaction with the 3 0 -OH of 
the primer. Compared to the canonical A:T base pair, 
the additional hydrogen bond achieved by the 3 0 -azido-
2,6-DA-P:thymine base pair may further stabilize the 
a-phosphate, facilitating the favorable catalytic efficiency 
observed in pre-steady-state assays. In contrast, the 
6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP nucleotide analogs are ineffi-
ciently incorporated by HIV-1 RT opposite cytosine bases. 
Taken together, these findings are consistent with those of 
Cheong et al. who reported that oligodeoxyribonucleotide 
duplexes containing 2,6-diaminopurine formed more 
stable base pairs opposite thymine than cytosine (16). </p>

<p>Figure 4. Molecular models of 3 0 -azido-ddGTP (A), 3 0 -azido-6-Cl-P-TP (B), 3 0 -azido-ddATP (C) and 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-TP (D) in the DNA poly-
merase active site of HIV-1 RT. Each of the analogs was modeled into the ternary RT-T/P-TTP complex (pdb co-ordinates 1RTD). A schematic 
representation of the hydrogen-bonding patterns between the incoming nucleotide analog and the template base is depicted below each model. </p>



<p>The mutations K65R, L74V, Q151M (in complex with 
A62V, V75I, F77L and F116Y) or M184V in HIV-1 RT 
allow the enzyme to discriminate between the natural 
dNTP substrate and modified nucleotide analogs. In 
Table 2, we show that the K65R, L74V and Q151M mu-
tations confer low levels of resistance to both 3 0 -azido-
ddATP and 3 0 -azido-ddGTP at the enzyme level. 
Modification at the 6-position of the purine base does 
not appear to enhance this discrimination phenotype: 
the K65R, L74V or A62V/V75I/F77L/F116Y/Q151M 
HIV-1 RTs all exhibited fold-resistance changes to each 
of the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGTP analogs that were 
largely similar (i.e. &lt;2-fold) to the fold change in resist-
ance values determined for 3 0 -azido-ddATP. Interestingly, 
the structure-activity relationship for the ATP-mediated 
excision of the 6-modified-3 0 -azido-ddGMP analogs by 
WT or TAM-containing HIV-1 RT differed from the 
structure-activity relationship for their incorporation. </p>

<p>For example, whereas 3 0 -azido-6-CL-P-TP is a relatively 
good substrate for incorporation, it is not efficiently 
excised by either WT or TAM-containing HIV-1 RT. In 
this regard, our modeling data show that the hydrogen-
bonding patterns observed for this analog differs 
from that of 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P and 3 0 -azido-6-AA-P 
(Figure 5). As such, it is possible that the change in tran-
sition state geometry required for excision is not suffi-
ciently stabilized by the 6-Cl substituted guanine analog 
base-paired with thymine. Taken together, these data 
suggest that the optimal conformation of the HIV-1 RT 
active site differs for incorporation and excision and 
further suggests that 6-position modifications differen-
tially effect these two reactions. This finding provides 
'proof of concept' that modified base analogs can be 
identified that are efficiently incorporated by HIV-1 RT 
but serve as a poor substrate for HIV-1 ATP-mediated 
excision reactions. Further optimization of these </p>

<p>Figure 5. Molecular models of the excision products of 3 0 -azido-ddA (A), 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P (B), 3 0 -azido-6-AA-P (C) and 3 0 -azido-6-Cl-P (D) in the 
DNA polymerase active site of HIV-1 RT containing TAMs. Each of the analogs was modeled into the ternary RT-T/P-AZTppppA complex (pdb 
co-ordinates 3KLE). A schematic representation of the hydrogen-bonding patterns between the excised nucleotide analog and the template base is 
depicted below each model. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 1 389 </p>

<p>divergent but favorable properties of purine analogs is in 
progress. 
We previously demonstrated that 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P, 
3 0 -azido-6-CL-P, 3 0 -azido-6-DM-P, 3 0 -azido-6-MX-P and 
3 0 -azido-6-AA-P showed comparable or superior antiviral 
activities to 3 0 -azido-ddG in primary human cells 
(5, Figure 1). Intracellular pharmacology analyses, 
however, revealed that each of these compounds was 
efficiently metabolized by adenosine deaminase to 
3 0 -azido-ddG in cells (5). Therefore, the observed 
anti-HIV-1 activity of each of these nucleoside analogs 
was not primarily due to incorporation of the ambiguous 
purine nucleotides described in this study. However, we 
recently identified RS-788, a 5 0 -monophosphate prodrug 
of 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P, as a potent and selective inhibitor of 
HIV-1 replication (Schinazi et al., 16th Conference on 
Retroviruses and Opportunistic Infections (2009) 
Abstract 557). In peripheral blood mononuclear cells, 
RS-788 is metabolized $1:1 to both 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-
TP and 3 0 -azido-ddGTP. Consequently, RS-788 delivers 
two chemically distinct metabolites each of which are 
potent HIV-1 RT chain terminators that are incorporated 
opposite different complementary bases (cytosine for 
3 0 -azido-ddGTP and thymine for 3 0 -azido-2,6-DA-P-TP). 
Therefore, our studies provide a promising new approach 
for the design and development of novel ambiguous NRTI 
that exert profound antiviral activity against WT and 
drug-resistant HIV-1. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>J.H.N. thanks Sun Microsystems and Accelrys 
Corporation for Academic Achievement awards of 
modeling hardware and software. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>The National Institutes of Health (R01-AI-071846 to 
J.W.M., 5P30-AI-050409 to R.F.S., 5R37-AI-041980 to 
R.F.S., 5R37-AI-025899 to R.F.S.) and the Department 
of Veterans Affairs (R.F.S.). Funding for open access 
charge: National Institutes of Health (grant R01 -AI -
071846). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. Professor R.F.S. is a founder 
and major shareholder of RFS Pharma LLC. J.W.M. is a 
consultant to RFS Pharma and owns options in RFS 
Pharma. </p>



<p>390 Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 1 </p>

</text></tei>