<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3017597" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Genome organization into transcriptionally active 
domains denotes one of the first levels of gene ex-
pression regulation. Although the chromatin domain 
concept is generally accepted, only little is known 
on how domain organization impacts the regulation 
of differential gene expression. Insulators might 
hold answers to address this issue as they delimit 
and organize chromatin domains. We have previ-
ously identified a CTCF-dependent insulator with 
enhancer-blocking activity embedded in the 5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>non-coding region of the chicken a-globin domain. 
Here, we demonstrate that this element, called the 
aEHS-1.4 insulator, protects a transgene against 
chromosomal position effects in stably transfected 
cell lines and transgenic mice. We found that this 
insulator can create a regulated chromatin environ-
ment that coincides with the onset of adult a-globin 
gene expression. Furthermore, such activity is in 
part dependent on the in vivo regulated occupancy 
of CTCF at the aEHS-1.4 element. Insulator function 
is also regulated by CTCF poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation. 
Our results suggest that the aEHS-1.4 insulator con-
tributes in organizing the chromatin structure of the 
a-globin gene domain and prevents activation of 
adult a-globin gene expression at the erythroblast 
stage via CTCF. </p>

<p>Differential gene expression in genomic domains is 
regulated at multiple levels. Not only does it require </p>

<p>chromatin structure remodeling at local regulatory 
elements, but also the establishment of a chromatin archi-
tecture defining the domain itself. Consequently, more 
than proximal and distal regulatory elements are 
required for a gene's coordinated transcription in order 
to first demarcate the genomic region in which it is 
located. Once the chromatin domain is delimited and 
organized, local regulatory actions take place to achieve 
expression of specific genes (1). 
Insulators have been considered as regulatory elements 
that act as boundaries to the action of external enhancers 
and repressive chromatin and participate in the forma-
tion and maintenance of chromatin domains (1,2). 
Accumulated evidence suggests that insulators, particu-
larly CTCF-linked insulators, do not act exclusively as 
boundary elements (3). For example, CTCF in coordin-
ation with cohesins, mediate the formation of chromatin 
loops favoring optimal spatial organization of gene 
domains (4,5). This vision is further supported by the 
presence of insulator bodies that are important for 
domain formation at the nuclear periphery of Drosophila 
cells. Insulator bodies are formed of polymorphic protein 
complexes including dCTCF, Su(Hw) and CP190, besides 
other proteins (6). Interestingly, such insulator-mediated 
topological organization of the genome is dynamic. For 
instance, CTCF and cohesin mediate chromosomal cis 
contacts in a regulated manner in several loci. Such loci 
include the Igf2/H19 imprinted locus (7,8), the cytokine 
locus including IL4, IL5, IL13 and IFNG (9), the mouse 
b-globin locus, in which the spatial organization of regu-
latory components to form an active chromatin hub is 
facilitated by CTCF during tissue-specific activation of 
globin genes (10), the MHC class II genes (11) and more 
recently, the b-globin locus, which interacts with flanking 
olfactory receptor genes on the human chromosome 11 </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +52 55 56 22 56 74; Fax: +52 55 56 22 56 30; Email: frecilla@ifc.unam.mx </p>

<p>Published online 2 September 2010 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 1 89-103 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkq740 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>(5). Notoriously, such interactions are not exclusively 
intrachromosomal, CTCF also mediates interchromo-
somal contacts between one allele of the Igf2/H19 imprint-
ing control region on chromosome 7 and one allele of the 
Wsb1/Nf1 imprinted locus on chromosome 11 (12). 
Insulator action through CTCF enhancer blocking 
activity can also be regulated by other mechanisms as by 
thyroid hormone (13) and post-translational modifications 
as poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation (14) among others. Thus, 
CTCF is implicated in diverse regulatory and structural 
functions (3). 
We previously described a regulatory element located in 
the 5 
0 non-coding region of the chicken a-globin domain, 
$14-kb upstream of the embryonic p gene (Figure 1A) 
(15). This element, named aEHS-1.4, which corresponds 
to a DNA fragment of 1.4 kb is an insulator with 
CTCF-dependent enhancer-blocking activity (15). This in-
sulator is located within an intron of the C16orf35 gene 
antisense transcript (16,17), between the distal locus 
control region known as the a-major regulatory element 
(a-MRE), and the a-globin genes (Figure 1A). Since the 
aEHS-1.4 is located 3 
0 from the a-MRE it seemed unlikely 
that the aEHS-1.4 insulator element acts as a boundary 
for the 5 
0 -side of the a-globin domain, shielding it from 
silent chromatin expansion or from the action of enhan-
cers outside the domain. Consequently, we addressed the 
contribution of this element to the chromatin configur-
ation of the a-globin domain and for regulated gene ex-
pression during erythropoiesis and development. 
Here, we demonstrate that the aEHS-1.4 element 
shields a transgene from chromosomal position effects 
(CPE) and gene silencing in stably transfected cell lines 
and transgenic mice. In contrast to the chicken 5 
0 cHS4 
b-globin insulator (18), the protective function of the 
aEHS-1.4 insulator is CTCF-dependent. Moreover, this 
element mediates the chromatin conformation of the 5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>non-coding region of the domain during developmentally 
regulated gene expression. Subsequently, we demonstrate 
that prior to erythroid differentiation, the aEHS-1.4 insu-
lator is bound by CTCF and prevents adult a-globin gene 
expression, and, as differentiation proceeds, CTCF is 
deployed and the blockage is released allowing the activa-
tion of the adult a-globin genes in fully developed eryth-
roid cells. Our results provide insight into the function of 
insulators as organizers of chromatin domains and regu-
lators of differential gene expression during cell differen-
tiation and development. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Culture of stable cell lines </p>

<p>Avian arrested cell lines were maintained at 37 
C, 5% 
CO 2 with the following corresponding media: 6C2 
(pre-eritroblasts) cells with a-MEM (GIBCO) supple-
mented with 10% (v/v) fetal bovine serum (FBS) 
(Multicell), 2% (v/v) chicken serum (CS), 1 mM HEPES 
(pH 7.2) (SIGMA) and 50 mM b-mercaptoethanol. The 
avian erythroblastosis virus-transformed chicken erythro-
blast cell line HD3 and the chicken lymphoid cell-line 
DT40 were cultured in DMEM (GIBCO) supplemented </p>

<p>with 8% FBS and 2% CS (19,20). All media contain peni-
cillin/streptomycin (500 U/ml) (GIBCO). To differentiate 
HD3 cells they were cultured with the same media with 
2% anemic CS at 42 
C for 7-15 days, as described (21,22). </p>

<p>Protection against chromosomal position effects assay </p>

<p>The protection against CPE assay was performed as pre-
viously described (18,23). Stable transfection of the differ-
ent plasmids was performed with Lipofectamine 
(Invitrogen) following manufacturer instructions. The 
transfected plasmids were pGa </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>, containing the EGFP 
under the chicken 
D gene promoter, pGa 
D HS4 (contain-
ing the b-globin 5 
0 cHS4 insulator on each side of the 
D -
EGFP) and pGa </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>1.4 (containing the aEHS-1.4 insulator 
on each side of the 
D -EGFP). Individual integrants were 
obtained by using a semisolid media (Methocel Fluka, 
Buchs, Switzerland) with neomycin at 0.9 mg/ml (18). 
After 10-14 days of selection, individual clones were 
isolated and their expression was determined by FACS 
(at Day 0). Copy number and transgene integrity was 
evaluated by Southern blot analysis using a DNA 
fragment of the EGFP as a probe. Transgene expression 
was evaluated twice a month until completion of at least 
100 days of continuous cell culture without neomycin. The 
mutant aEHS1.4ÁÁ construct was obtained by nested 
PCR using primers containing the ÁCAG and ÁCTAG 
base changes at the CTCF-binding site defined previously 
(15) and then using primers to amplify the complete 1.4-kb 
DNA fragment (all primers are available upon request). </p>

<p>Generation of transgenic mice </p>

<p>The plasmid pTYR5-1.4 containing the aEHS-1.4 element 
was cloned in a standard 5 
0 -3 
0 orientation, at the 5 
0 end in 
the unique Xba I site of the Tyr (tyrosinase)-reporter con-
struct ptrTYR5 (24); it was digested with Ecl XI and Sal I 
enzymes, thereby releasing the 13-kb DNA band with the 
insert that was purified following described standard pro-
cedures (25). In parallel, the corresponding Ecl XI-Sal I 
11.6-kb DNA band from ptrTYR5, without the insulator 
element, was also purified and used as the reference 
control for transgenesis. The resulting DNA fragments 
and transgenes were named as: TYR5 and TYR5-
aEHS-1.4, respectively. For the generation of transgenic 
mice, suitable DNA solutions from each of the two trans-
genes were microinjected into the pronucleus of albino 
outbreed NMRI/Hsd fertilized mouse oocytes (Harlan 
Interfauna Iberica SL, Barcelona, Spain) using standard 
procedures (25) . Transgenic founder mice were detected 
at birth due to obvious pigmentation (24) and confirmed 
by PCR analysis, using tyrosinase minigene-specific 
primers, as described before (24) and also by Southern 
blot analysis, using the pmTyrE5 tyrosinase probe that 
reveals polymorphic Hind III DNA bands between the 
transgene (3.4 kb) and the endogenous tyrosinase locus 
(2.2 kb), as reported (26). Transgenic mouse lines were 
established and maintained, as hemizygous, in the albino 
outbreed NMRI/Hsd genetic background. Transgene 
copy-number was determined from the DNA of F 1 indi-
viduals by Southern blot analysis, as reported before (26). 
For the TYR5-aEHS-1.4 construct, 289 fertilized oocytes </p>



<p>were microinjected, 192 embryos were transferred to 
pseudopregnant females and resulted in the birth of 17 
pups, out of which five independent transgenic mouse 
lines were established. For the TYR5 transgene, 581 
fertilized oocytes were microinjected, 284 embryos were 
transferred and gave rise to 17 newborns, out of which 
three were transgenic. Subsequently, two of these mouse 
lines were found to carry multiple transgene insertions 
that could be segregated in the F1 generation, thus 
finally resulting in a total of six independent transgenic </p>

<p>mouse lines with the TYR5 construct. Representative F 1 
individuals from each transgenic mouse line were briefly 
anesthetized with 1 ml/100 g of a mixture of Ketamine 
(10 mg/ml) and Xylazine (2 mg/ml) for obtaining the 
arranged pictures (Figure 2A). All the procedures that 
required the use of animals complied with Spanish and 
European legislation concerning vivisection and the use 
of genetically modified organisms, and the protocols 
were approved by the local ethics committees on animal 
experimentation. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B 
C </p>

<p>D 
E </p>

<p>Figure 1. Protection against position effects by the aEHS-1.4 insulator. (A) Scheme of the a-globin gene domain. The a-MRE constitutes the 
putative locus control region of the domain. The aEHS-1.4 insulator is located $14-kb upstream of the embryonic p globin gene. CpG, represents a 
CpG-island located $4-kb upstream of the embryonic p globin gene which represents the first CTCF-binding site identified in vivo, that corresponds 
to the promoter of the antisense transcript C16orf35 (47). Vertical arrows indicate the position of DNase I hypersensitive sites and the 3 
0 -side 
enhancer (21). (B) Flow cytometry histograms (FACS) showing the GFP fluorescence level of five representative and independent stably transfected 
cell lines containing the control vector without insulators at days 0, 30 and 100 of continuous cell culture. (C) Fluorescence of independent cell lines 
incorporating the insulated plasmid with the chicken 5 
0 cHS4 insulator of the b-globin gene locus. (D) Fluorescence of independent cell lines 
containing the plasmid flanked on each side of the transgene by the aEHS-1.4 insulator. (E) Chart showing the mean percentage of GFP expressing 
cells (±SD) at different time points during culture for the three different transgenes (pG 
D 3 n = 15, pG 
D 5 
0 cHS4 n = 10 and pG 
D EHS-1.4 
n = 10). sc = single-copy and mc = multi-copy integrants. ***P 0.001 with respect to the pG 
D 3 (100 days) control (ANOVA). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 1 91 </p>

<p>Analysis of transgenic mice </p>

<p>Total RNA was prepared from whole brain, dorsal skin 
and eyes from at least three adult F 1 or F 2 individuals </p>

<p>from each of the transgenic mouse lines carrying the 
TYR5 and TYR5-aEHS-1.4 constructs, using the 
RNeasy Kit (Qiagen). Tyrosinase (Tyr) expression was 
assessed by quantitative RT-PCR using specific mouse </p>

<p>Figure 2. Analysis of TYR5 versusTYR5-aEHS-1.4 transgenic mice. (A) Coat color of transgenic mice. Representative F1 individuals from TYR5 
(left) and TYR5-aEHS-1.4 (right) transgenic mice are shown alongside non-transgenic albino NMRI littermates (wt, for wild-type), used as the 
recipient mouse strain for transgenesis. The number of the independent transgenic line and number of integrated transgene copies (in brackets) are 
shown on the top. (B) Retinas of TYR5 and TYR5-aEHS-1.4 transgenic mice. Whole-mount retinas showing pigmentation levels due to the retinal 
pigment epithelium and the overlaying choroid with melanocytes, from adult TYR5 (panels A to F: A, line #2222; B, line #2332; C, line #2122; D, 
line #2028; E, line #2231; F, line #2131) and TYR5-aEHS1.4 (panels G to K: G, line #2004; H, line #2017; I, line #2016; J, line #2009; K, line 
#2005) transgenic mice. A retina from a non-transgenic albino NMRI littermate is included for reference (panel L). (C) Analysis of tyrosinase gene 
expression. Tyrosinase (Tyr) gene expression was measured by quantitative RT-PCR using specific TaqMan and reference (Tbp) probes in all 
transgenic mouse lines carrying the TYR5 (grey bars) and the TYR5-aEHS-1.4 (solid black bars) construct in total RNA isolated from three 
different tissues: eyes (top chart), dorsal skin (middle), and whole brain (bottom). Two F1 or F2 adult representative animals from each transgenic 
mouse line were used for measurements. Results are shown as averages ± SD. The number of each of the transgenic mouse lines and their corres-
ponding transgene copy-number (in brackets) is indicated below each bar. A non-transgenic albino NMRI littermate (white bar) was used as a 
control for all tissues. </p>



<p>TaqMan (Applied Biosystems) Tyr (Mm00495817_m1) 
and Tbp (Mm00446973_m1, included as a reference) 
probes, on an ABI-Prism 7000 (Applied Biosystems), 
using TaqMan Universal PCR Master Mix (Applied 
Biosystems), as described before (27). Whole-mount 
retinas from adult F 1 or F 2 individuals from each of the 
transgenic mouse lines carrying the TYR5 and TYR5-
aEHS-1.4 constructs were prepared according to previous-
ly described methods (27,28). Quantification of the total 
melanin contents from eye and skin extracts was carried 
out from at least two adult F 1 or F 2 individuals from each 
of the transgenic mouse lines carrying the TYR5 and 
TYR5-aEHS-1.4 constructs, according to reported proto-
cols (28). </p>

<p>Chromatin immunoprecipitation </p>

<p>Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) analysis were 
performed and analyzed as described (29). Duplex PCR 
was used for evaluating histone marks and CTCF enrich-
ment at different points in the aEHS-1.4 insulator region 
covering the CTCF-binding site (see scheme in Figure 4), 
the aEHS-1.4 CTCF-binding site in the transgene and a 
DNA fragment of EGFP. As controls we used regions in 
which the analyzed histone covalent modification or 
nuclear factor is absent; for permissive chromatin 
histone marks and CTCF we used two heterochromatin-
associated sequences located 5 
0 of the chicken b-globin 
gene domain (30), for the repressive histone marks we 
used the b-globin 5 
0 cHS4 insulator sequence that is 
enriched with permissive marks in all cell types used 
(30). Enrichment was calculated by using the following 
equation: Ab test (test region/control region)/IgG (test 
region/control region). The antibodies employed were 
the following: antibodies against acetylated histone H3 
and acetylated histone H4 (06-599 and 06-866) were 
obtained from Upstate Biotechnology (Lake Placid, 
NY). The antibody against H3K4me2 (ab7766) was 
purchased from Abcam (Cambridge, MA). The antibody 
against H3K79me2 was kindly provided by Fred van 
Leeuwen (Nederland Kanker Instituut-Antoni van 
Leeuwenhoek 
Ziekenhuis, 
Amsterdam, 
The 
Netherlands). Antibodies against the trimethylated 
versions of histone 3 on K9 and histone 4 on K20 were 
kindly provided by Thomas Jenuwein (Max Planck 
Institute of Immunology, Freiburg, Germany). The 
antibody against chicken CTCF [anti-cCTCF(86-233)] 
was previously obtained as described (15). </p>

<p>CTCF knock down and 3-aminobenzamide treatment </p>

<p>For the CTCF knock down series of experiments, three 
different sets of small hairpin RNA interference (shRNAi) 
sequences against CTCF were tested with overall similar 
results. To generate the CTCF knock down cells we used a 
collection of four plasmids containing different sequences 
to generate shRNAi against the 5 
0 region of chicken 
CTCF mRNA. Three of them were designed from the 
reported sequences in (31) (pSiLefevre1, 2 and 3) and 
one was kindly provided by Ishihara (pCTI). Even 
though the pCT1 shRNAi was designed against human 
CTCF (32), it reduced CTCF levels in the chicken </p>

<p>cell lines. Plasmids containing the hairpin DNAs 
were stably transfected as described previously, and 
integrants were selected with 1 mg/ml puromicin 
(SIGMA) for 7-15 days. CTCF reduction was assessed 
by western blot analysis (Supplementary Figure S4A). 
For 3-aminobenzamide (3-ABA) treatment, 8 mM 
3-ABA was added to the culture media for 3-6 days 
prior to evaluation by western blotting and ChIP 
analysis, as described (14). The CTCF antibody used to 
perform the western blot (15) recognizes both the 130-and 
180-kDa forms of CTCF as shown in Supplementary 
Figure S4A. </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>Two-tailed analysis of variance (ANOVA) or multivariate 
analysis of variance (MANOVA) statistical analyses 
were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> program (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 18</rs>) con-
sidering as significant: *P 0.05, **P 0.01 and 
***P 0.001. Scheffe or Games-Howell post hoc tests 
were used when appropriate to distinguish which compo-
nents analyzed are causing the significant variance 
between conditions. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The aEHS-1.4 insulator protects against chromosomal 
position effects in stably transfected cell lines </p>

<p>To test if the aEHS-1.4 insulator located 14-kb upstream 
of the embryonic p gene of the a-globin locus protects a 
trangene against chromosomal position effects, we 
generated stably transfected HD3 erythroblasts expressing 
a GFP reporter driven by the chicken 
D gene promoter 
( 
D -GFP) (Figure 1B) (29), or 
D -GFP flanked on 
each side by the aEHS-1.4 insulator (Figure 1D). The </p>

<p>D -GFP flanked on each side by the 5 
0 cHS4 core insulator 
of the b-globin locus was used as control (18). Transgene 
integrity and copy number (single-or multi-copy) was 
determined by Southern blot for a selected set of stable 
lines (data not shown). We measured GFP fluorescence 
by flow cytometry at different time points to assess 
transgene expression (18,23). As expected, the </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>-GFP 
plasmid (without insulators) showed sensitivity to 
CPE, as transgene expression was extinct even before 
day 100 of continuous cell culture (Figure 1B). In 
contrast, the aEHS-1.4 insulator robustly protected 
against CPE even after 100 days of continuous cell 
culture (Figure 1D). This protective activity was compar-
able to that exerted by the chicken b-globin 5 
0 cHS4 insu-
lator (Figure 1C-E). Next, we examined the profile 
of histone post-translational modifications present over 
the GFP transgene in distinct cell lines by ChIP. 
Modifications corresponding to a permissive chromatin 
environment were present only in insulated transgenes 
(Supplementary Figure S1). Thus, the aEHS-1.4 insulator 
efficiently protects against CPE in chicken HD3 erythro-
blasts cells thereby favoring a transcriptionally permissive 
chromatin environment. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 1 93 </p>

<p>The aEHS-1.4 insulator protects against chromosomal 
position effects in transgenic mice </p>

<p>To test the functionality of the aEHS-1.4 element in vivo 
we addressed its role in preventing chromosomal position 
effects in transgenic mice. We used a reporter system in 
which the albino phenotype is rescued in transgenic mice 
expressing a functional tyrosinase gene (Tyr) (24), and 
which has been useful to validate the effect of the 
chicken 5 
0 cHS4 b-globin insulator in protecting trans-
genes from CPE (33). The aEHS-1.4 insulator was 
cloned as a single copy at the 5 
0 end of Tyr in the 
ptrTYR5 construct (TYR5-aEHS-1.4). We cloned the 
aEHS-1.4 sequence only at the 5 
0 end of the vector since 
constructs usually integrate as multi-copy tandem arrays; 
therefore, most transgene copies would end up shielded by 
aEHS-1.4 elements (25). The parental plasmid, ptrTYR5, 
here called TYR5, was used as a reference. 
Five independent transgenic mouse lines carrying the 
insulated TYR5-aEHS-1.4 construct (lines #2004, 
#2017, #2016, #2009 and #2005), and six carrying the 
control TYR5 construct (lines #2222, #2331, #2122, 
#2028, #2231 and #2131) where generated in the albino 
outbreed strain NMRI/Hsd (Figure 2A). Transgene integ-
rity and copy number was assessed by Southern blot 
analysis (data not shown). As anticipated, insertion of 
either construct rendered pigmented transgenic mice 
(Figure 2A). In all cases, pigmentation was uniform, 
without obvious signs of mosaicism [that were obvious 
in similar transgenic mice reported by Potts et al. (33)]. 
Mouse lines with higher number of TYR5 copies [i.e. 
#2131 (10 copies)] showed increased pigmentation, as 
compared to lines with fewer transgene copies [i.e. #2222 
(one copy)]. However, there was little coat color variation 
in the remaining TYR5 transgenic lines with intermediate 
transgene copy-number (Figure 2A, lines #2331, #2122, 
#2028 and #2231). In contrast, the five transgenic mouse 
lines generated with the TYR5-aEHS-1.4 transgene, 
produced individuals with progressively darker pigmenta-
tion, mostly correlating with the corresponding transgene 
copy-numbers. Only one line, #2004 (one copy), showed 
no detectable pigmentation in skin and/or eyes 
(Figure 2A). 
To better assess Tyr expression in transgenic mice we 
carried out three additional experiments. First, we 
prepared whole-mount retinas from representative F1 in-
dividuals from TYR5 and TYR5-aEHS-1.4 transgenic 
lines to directly visualize the retinal pigment epithelium 
cells and melanocytes present in the choroid. Pigment sat-
uration was readily observed in retinas from TYR5 trans-
genic lines, without any obvious correlation with 
transgene copy number (Figure 2B and A-F). In 
contrast, progressively higher pigmentation correlated 
with transgene copy number in retinas from TYR5-
aEHS-1.4 transgenic lines similar to coat color pigmenta-
tion (Figure 2B and G-K). 
Second, we measured the Tyr gene expression by quan-
titative RT-PCR. Tyr expression was assessed in eyes and 
skin, where Tyr is normally expressed; and brain, where 
Tyr is not expressed (27). Tyr expression in TYR5 trans-
genic mouse lines was relatively uniform in the eye, erratic </p>

<p>in the skin, and absent in the brain (Figure 2C), and did 
not correlate with transgene copy number. In contrast, 
Tyr expression in TYR5-aEHS-1.4 transgenic lines was 
relatively proportional to transgene copy number in the 
eye, while it fully correlated with transgene copy number 
in the skin and, surprisingly, in the brain. 
Finally, we quantified the total melanin contents in 
the eyes and skin of all transgenic lines (Supplementary 
Figure S2). Eye melanin contents of TYR5 transgenic 
mice were relatively uniform whereas in TYR5-
aEHS-1.4 mice melanin contents correlated with trans-
gene copy number. Likewise, melanin contents in 
the skin of TYR5 transgenic individuals were highly 
variable. In contrast, melanin contents in the dorsal skin 
of TYR5-aEHS-1.4 transgenic mice clearly correlated 
with transgene copy number. In conclusion, the 
aEHS-1.4 insulator protects a transgene against chromo-
somal position effects and progressive silencing not only in 
stable cell lines but also in transgenic mice. </p>

<p>CTCF-binding site is indispensable for aEHS-1.4 
insulator activity </p>

<p>In order to address whether CTCF contributes to the pro-
tection against CPE by the aEHS-1.4 insulator, we 
introduced two point mutations that abolish CTCF 
binding to this element (15) to generate the aEHS-
1.4ÁÁ insulator and assessed its protective function 
against CPE in stably transfected HD3 cells by flow 
cytometry. A very high proportion of cells from lines in 
which GFP was flanked on each side by the aEHS-1.4 
insulator showed high levels of fluorescence even after 
70 days of continuous culture. In contrast, fluorescence 
levels decreased in an important proportion of cells 
carrying the mutant insulator aEHS-1.4ÁÁ after 70 
days (Figure 3A). These results are reflected in the per-
centages of GFP-expressing cells in selected stably trans-
fected lines (Figure 3A). Interestingly, the protection 
against CPE by a single copy of the intact, or the 
mutant aEHS-1.4, was less efficient than by multiple 
copies, suggesting that optimal insulation is reached only 
when the aEHS-1.4 sequence flanks the transgene on each 
side (Figure 3A, compare single-and multi-copy cell 
lines). Thus, the mutant aEHS-1.4ÁÁ insulator protects 
against CPE less efficiently than the aEHS-1.4 insulator, 
suggesting that, unlike the chicken 5 
0 cHS4 b-globin insu-
lator (18), CTCF binding is required for the insulator 
function of aEHS-1.4. </p>

<p>The activity of the aEHS-1.4 insulator correlates with 
CTCF occupancy during erythroid differentiation </p>

<p>Since the a-MRE is located further upstream of the 
aEHS-1.4 in the a-globin locus, it seems unlikely that 
the aEHS-1.4 acts as the 5 
0 boundary limiting the 
a-globin chromatin domain (Figure 1A). Therefore, we 
asked if the aEHS-1.4 element regulates a-globin gene ex-
pression and if it does so via CTCF. For these purpose we 
first addressed the CTCF binding to the endogenous 
aEHS-1.4 during erythroid differentiation and chicken de-
velopment by semi-quantitative ChIP. Interestingly, the 
occupancy of the aEHS-1.4 insulator by CTCF varied </p>



<p>depending on the differentiation stage analyzed. CTCF 
abundance peaked at the pre-erythroblasts stage, repre-
sented by HD3 cells, and, it drastically diminished as 
differentiation proceeds into a mature erythrocyte, repre-
sented by red blood cells from 10-day-old chicken 
embryos (10dRBCs), or differentiated HD3 cells 
(Figure 3B). Western blots showed similar CTCF total 
protein levels in undifferentiated and differentiated HD3 </p>

<p>cells (Supplementary Figure S4A, right panel), suggesting 
regulated binding of CTCF to the aEHS-1.4 element. In 
contrast to the aEHS-1.4 insulator, the CTCF's highest 
enrichment on the chicken 5 
0 cHS4 b-globin insulator 
was detected in 10dRBCs (Supplementary Figure S3), sug-
gesting a different mode of action of CTCF for each of 
these elements. Next, we analyzed the protective function 
of the aEHS-1.4 insulator against CPE in undifferentiated </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Figure 3. CTCF is necessary for aEHS-1.4 insulator function and its in vivo occupancy varies during erythroid differentiation. (A) Transgene 
expression analysis by FACS at day 0 (red) and 70 (grey) in cultured cell lines with the respective transgene integrated in multi-copy (aEHS-1.4 
and mutant aEHS-1.4ÁÁ insulator were placed only at the 5 
0 -side of the transgene). Quantification of the average (±standard error) of GFP 
+ cells 
at day 0 and 70 of culture of the set of single-and multi-copy clones. aEHS-1.4 (sc) n = 16; aEHS-1.4ÁÁ (sc) n = 22; aEHS-1.4 (mc) n = 18 and 
aEHS-1.4ÁÁ (mc) n = 22. *P 0.05 with respect to the aEHS-1.4 (ANOVA). (B) CTCF in vivo binding at the aEHS-1.4 insulator sequence was 
estimated by semi-quantitative ChIP assays (29). We observed an enrichment peak of CTCF in HD3 cells (erythroblasts), and as differentiation 
proceeds (dif-HD3), CTCF dissociates from the insulator. *P 0.05. The number of independent ChIP assays per cell line is: DT40 n = 3, 6C2 n = 5, 
HD3 n = 4, 5dRBC n = 3, 10dRBC n = 3 and dif-HD3 n = 4. (C) Protection against CPE in two representative differentiated HD3 cell lines 
containing the plasmid insulated with the aEHS-1.4 element (the same experiment was performed using the b-globin 5 
0 cHS4 insulator, see 
Supplementary Figure S3B). (D) ChIP using an antibody against CTCF and primers recognizing the transgene. CTCF binds to the transgene in 
HD3 cells and is dissociated in differentiated HD3 cells mimicking what happens at the endogenous context (see B), consistent with a loss of 
insulator function in the differentiated clones. A representative gel of the radioactive duplex-PCR is shown. Results are shown as averages 
(±standard error). *P 0.05 with respect to the lines 506 or 528 (ANOVA). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 1 95 </p>

<p>cells (HD3) and terminally differentiated erythroblasts 
(dif-HD3). Two HD3 cell lines carrying the </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>-GFP 
transgene shielded by the aEHS-1.4 (lines 506 and 528) 
were differentiated for 15 days (21), and GFP fluores-
cence was measured by flow cytometry. GFP fluores-
cence of the differentiated cells reproducibly decreased 
as compared to their undifferentiated counterpart 
(Figure 3C). This correlates with decreased occupancy 
of the endogenous aEHS-1.4 insulator by CTCF in 
10dRBCs (Figure 3B), and of the transgene 
incorporated in differentiated HD3 cells (Figure 3D). In 
contrast, differentiated HD3 lines carrying the 5 
0 cHS4 
b-globin insulator did not show a significant fluores-
cence decrease (Supplementary Figure S3B). Therefore, 
the decreased protective effect of the aEHS-1.4 
against CPE might be due to decreased CTCF binding. </p>

<p>Reduction of CTCF protein levels and inhibition of 
PARP-1 affects insulator function </p>

<p>Based on the data supporting dynamic CTCF binding at 
the aEHS-1.4 insulator during differentiation, we decided 
to knock down CTCF expression and inhibit its potential 
poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation (Supplementary Figure S4). First, 
we generated a series of cell lines in which CTCF 
was stably knocked down by transfection of three differ-
ent sets of small hairpin RNAs. Decreased CTCF protein 
was confirmed by western blot (Supplementary 
Figure S4A, left panel). The reduction of CTCF decreased 
the protective effect of the aEHS-1.4 insulator against 
CPE (Supplementary Figure S4B, left panel). ChIP 
assays confirmed decreased CTCF at the aEHS-1.4 insu-
lator upon CTCF knock down (Supplementary 
Figure S4C). Poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation has been shown to 
be needed for CTCF insulator function (14,34-37), there-
fore we addressed whether inactivation of CTCF by inhib-
ition of the poly(ADP) ribose polymerase-1 (PARP-1) 
impacts on the protection against CPE conferred by the 
aEHS-1.4 insulator. PARP-1 post-translationally modifies 
CTCF by adding ADP polymers to its N-terminal 
domain, resulting in two electrophoretic forms, one 
migrating at 130 kDa, which contains few ADP-ribose 
residues, and the other one migrating at 180 kDa, which 
contains more than 20 ADP-ribose residues (36). 
Treatment of the HD3 transgenic cell lines 506 and 528, 
which carry GFP flanked on each side by the aEHS-1.4 
insulator, with 3-ABA, an inhibitor of PARP-1 (36), 
resulted in a diminishment of transgene protection 
against CPE along with a decrease of the 180 kDa form 
of CTCF (Supplementary Figure S4A, right panel). 
Interestingly, inhibition of poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation did 
not affect CTCF binding to the aEHS-1.4 insulator, as 
shown by ChIP (Figure 6A), implying that, while affecting 
its function on the aEHS-1.4 insulator, inhibition of 
CTCF PARylation does not affect its DNA-binding 
properties. 
Taken together, these results further support the notion 
that activity of the aEHS-1.4 insulator is CTCF-
dependent and that such activity can be, at least in part, 
modulated by post-translational modification. </p>

<p>The genomic region encompassing the aEHS-1.4 insulator 
progressively structures as transcriptionally permissive 
chromatin during erythroid differentiation </p>

<p>As a first approach to understand the function of 
aEHS-1.4 element on the chromatin organization of the 
a-globin domain, we characterized the chromatin struc-
ture of a 6.6-kb genomic region encompassing the 
aEHS-1.4 element during erythroid differentiation and de-
velopment (Figure 4A). We performed ChIP assays for 
several histone post-translational modifications corres-
ponding to transcriptionally permissive (acH3, acH4, 
H3K4me2 and H3K79me2) and repressive (H3K9me3 
and H4K20me3) chromatin conformations. We found 
that the enrichment in histone modifications along the 
targeted genomic region varies during adult erythroid 
differentiation (Figure 4A). In 6C2 cells, which represent 
a pre-erythroblast differentiation stage, a modest enrich-
ment in acetylated histones, as well as H3K4me2 
and H3K79me2 was observed over the aEHS-1.4 
insulator (Figure 4A). As differentiation proceeds into 
an erythroblast stage represented by HD3 cells, there 
was a notorious peak of permissive histone marks 
overlapping with the CTCF-binding sequence at the 
aEHS-1.4 element (Figure 4A). Importantly, a-globin 
genes are not transcribed in 6C2 or HD3 cells (21). 
Thus, these results suggest that the aEHS-1.4 element 
may contribute to the establishment of an open configur-
ation of the domain prior to adult a-globin gene expres-
sion. Such hypothesis is further supported by notorious 
enrichment of transcriptionally permissive histone modifi-
cations on the same genomic region in 5dRBC [Figure 4B, 
CTCF(P2)], in which the embryonic p gene is transcribed 
(21). Then, the 6.6-kb genomic region encompassing 
the aEHS-1.4 insulator structures as transcriptionally 
permissive chromatin after globin gene expression 
switching, i.e. in 10dRBCs, when the adult a-globin 
genes ( 
D and </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>) are robustly expressed, while the em-
bryonic gene is silenced (21). The DT40 lymphoid 
cell line, in which the a-globin gene domain is inactive, 
was used as a control (21,38). Thus, the progressive 
arrangement of the 6.6-kb genomic region containing 
the aEHS-1.4 insulator into transcriptionally permissive 
chromatin correlates with a-globin locus activation 
and the onset of adult a-globin gene expression. 
These results are in contrast to the timing of aEHS-1.4 
insulator function and CTCF occupancy, which rise in 
erythroblasts, and decrease in mature erythrocytes 
(Figure 3B). 
Taken together, our results support a model in 
which the aEHS-1.4 insulator, located between the 
domain's putative a-MRE and the a-globin genes 
might act by blocking the transcriptional influence of 
the a-MRE over the a-globin adult genes at the erythro-
blast stage. Then, as differentiation proceeds towards 
mature erythrocytes, CTCF dissociates from the 
aEHS-1.4 insulator, releasing its blocking activity over 
the a-MRE and allowing the establishment of transcrip-
tionally active chromatin and trans-activation of the adult 
genes. </p>



<p>Figure 4. Distribution of histone post-translational modifications over the 6.6-kb genomic region containing the aEHS-1.4 insulator. (A) Histone 
covalent modifications were evaluated semi-quantitatively using duplex-PCR with primers P1-P5 (primers locations are shown in the bottom scheme) 
in DT40 (lymphoid), 6C2 (pre-erythroblasts) and HD3 (erythroblasts) cells. (B) ChIP assays as in (A) using 5d and 10dRBCs. (C) Representative gel 
of the duplex-PCR amplification using primers P2 located over the CTCF-binding site with its corresponding control (Ctrl). The ChIP was performed 
on 10-day-old embryonic erythrocytes (10dRBC). All the histone modification enrichments are statistically significant (ANOVA with P 0.001) with 
respect to the control IgG except for the acH3 enrichment. Results are shown as averages (±standard error). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 1 97 </p>

<p>Loss of aEHS-1.4 insulator function results in active 
chromatin configuration and precocious adult a-globin 
gene expression </p>

<p>To start testing the proposed model in which the 
aEHS-1.4 insulator blocks the a-MRE over a-globin 
gene expression in erythroblasts, we addressed the chro-
matin configuration as well as a-globin gene expression in 
cells with decreased or inactive CTCF. Open chromatin 
histone modifications at the aEHS-1.4 insulator region 
were increased in undifferentiated HD3 cells with 
knocked-down CTCF (Figure 5A). As expected, 
a-globin gene expression was not detected in untreated 
HD3 cells (Figure 5B) (21). No changes were observed 
in undifferentiated HD3 cells with decreased CTCF 
(Figure 5B, left panel). In contrast, in differentiated 
HD3 cells with decreased CTCF the adult 
D and </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>globin genes did not get fully activated (Figure 5B, right 
panel). 
A similar set of experiments was performed in cells 
treated with 3-ABA inhibitor of PARP-1 enzyme. Open 
chromatin histone modifications at the aEHS-1.4 insula-
tor region were generally increased in undifferentiated </p>

<p>HD3 cells in which CTCF function was inactivated by 
3-ABA, as compared to untreated cells (Figure 6A). 
Accordingly, HD3-treated cells showed premature activa-
tion of the adult 
D and 
A globin genes in contrast with 
CTCF knock-down cells (Figure 6B). No significant dif-
ferences in histone modifications or a-globin gene expres-
sion were found in treated differentiated HD3 cells. Two 
main conclusions emerge from this set of experiments. 
First, inhibition of CTCF poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation in 
HD3 erythroblasts mimics, at least in part, the chromatin 
structure and the expression of the adult 
D and 
A globin 
genes in 10dRBCs (Figures 4B and 6). Second, knock 
down of CTCF perturbs more dramatically the chromatin 
structure of the a-globin domain, as compared to inhib-
ition of CTCF poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation, while impeding 
full globin gene activation (Figure 5B, right panel). 
Thus, it is possible that poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation regulates 
the activity of CTCF on the aEHS-1.4 insulator at its 
natural context. Together, these results support a model 
in which the aEHS-1.4 promotes optimal chromatin con-
figuration and prevents a-MRE-mediated adult a-globin 
genes trans-activation at the erythroblast stage. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Reduction of CTCF alters the profile of histone covalent modifications at the aEHS-1.4 insulator region and a-globin genes expression. 
(A) ChIP analysis of histone modifications in HD3 cells (HD3) and HD3 cells knocked down for CTCF (HD3+CTCF-kd). Each ChIP assay was 
performed in triplicate. Representative radioactive duplex PCR gels of the HD3-scramble (HD3-scr) and HD3 cells knocked down for CTCF 
(HD3+CTCF-kd) are shown. (B) Evaluation of a-globin gene expression in HD3 cells (HD3) and HD3 cells knocked down for CTCF in normal 
conditions (undifferentiated, HD3+CTCF-kd) and differentiated HD3 cells (dif-HD3). The results are representative of nine independent PCR 
reactions from two independent total RNA purifications and reverse transcriptase reactions. There is a premature chromatin opening of the insulator 
region in the CTCF knock down cells, and the adult genes are unable to be expressed in the HD3 differentiated cells. *P 0.05 (MANOVA) and 
***P 0.001 (MANOVA) with respect to the corresponding histone covalent modification or expressed gene in HD3 or dif-HD3 scramble controls, 
respectively. </p>



<p>a-MRE trans-activation potentiation by CTCF release 
from the aEHS-1.4 insulator during differentiation </p>

<p>In an attempt to validate the proposed model we 
generated pools of stable HD3 cell lines comparing the 
activity of the 
D gene promoter alone, the same 
promoter with the a-MRE element and a construct with 
the aMRE, the a-EHS-1.4 and the 
D gene promoter 
mimicking their endogenous organization (Figure 7). 
Based on our previous observations we propose that 
CTCF dissociation from the aEHS-1.4 insulator in 
mature erythrocytes (differentiated HD3 cells) increase 
a-MRE trans-activation potential. Indeed, we found that 
under non-differentiated conditions the majority of the 
reporter gene activity is not trans-activated, instead 
when HD3 cells are differentiated into mature erythro-
cytes we detected a robust trans-activation of the 
reporter gene (Figure 7) consistent with the dissociation 
of CTCF over the insulator in the transgene (Figure 3B 
and C). 
These results further support the model in which the 
aEHS-1.4 insulator regulates the a-MRE trans-activating 
function over the adult a-globin genes during adult eryth-
roid differentiation. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Genomic organization into chromatin domains represents 
an important level of gene expression regulation achieved 
by regulatory elements located mainly at intergenic regions 
(2,3). Here we studied the function of the aEHS-1.4 insu-
lator in the chromatin organization and gene expression 
regulation of the a-globin gene domain. We previously 
demonstrated that the aEHS-1.4 insulator, embedded in 
the 5 
0 non-coding region of the a-globin domain, posses 
enhancer blocking activity (15). With the aim to better 
understand the insulator properties of the aEHS-1.4 
element and its role in the chicken a-globin domain, we 
first demonstrate that the aEHS-1.4 element is able to 
shield a transgene from CPE in stably transfected cell 
lines and in mice in a CTCF-dependent manner. This 
differs from the 5 
0 cHS4 insulator in which only enhancer 
blocking function is CTCF-dependent, whereas protection 
against CPE needs binding of USF1 and USF2 factors 
(18,39). Since no USF1/USF2 factors are present at the 
aEHS-1.4 (data not shown), a different protein complex 
most likely regulates aEHS-1.4 insulator activity. 
Importantly, CTCF occupancy of the aEHS-1.4 insula-
tor varies during erythroid differentiation. This raises the </p>

<p>Figure 6. Poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase-1 inhibitor affects histone modifications associated with the aEHS-1.4 insulator and a-globin genes expres-
sion. (A) ChIP analysis of histone covalent modifications in HD3 cells (HD3) and cells incubated with the PARP-1 inhibitor (HD3+3-ABA) using P2 
primers (Figure 4). Each ChIP was performed in triplicate. Representative radioactive duplex PCR gels for HD3 cells and HD3 cells incubated with 
the 3-ABA inhibitor are shown. (B) Semi-quantitative duplex RT-PCR of a-globin genes expression in HD3 cells and HD3 cells treated with 8 mM 
of 3-ABA (left graph). The same experiment was performed in differentiated HD3 cells (dif-HD3) and differentiated HD3 cells incubated with 
3-ABA (dif-HD3+3-ABA, right panel). The results are representative of nine independent PCR reactions from two independent total RNA puri-
fication and reverse transcriptase reactions. *P 0.05 (MANOVA), **P 0.01 (MANOVA) and ***P 0.001 (MANOVA), with respect to the 
corresponding histone covalent modification or expressed gene in HD3 cells. Results are shown as averages (±standard error). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 1 99 </p>

<p>possibility that the aEHS-1.4 acts as a stage-specific insu-
lator probably influencing the activity of the a-MRE on 
the expression of adult 
D and 
A genes. Indeed, the 
activity of aEHS-1.4 is regulated, and peaks during the 
switching from early to late adult erythroid differenti-
ation, when an erythroid-specific signal might favor 
CTCF dissociation. We propose that the function of the 
aEHS-1.4 insulator is to block the activity of the a-MRE 
distal element during early adult erythroid differentiation. 
Once differentiation takes place, CTCF dissociates and 
open chromatin propagates 3 
0 towards the gene cluster 
(Figure 8A). Possibly the aEHS-1.4 element regulates 
the poised state of the RNA polymerase II and 
pre-initiation complex components found at the a-MRE </p>

<p>(40). The RNA polymerase II blockage by CTCF has been 
described in other loci (41,42). In such a hypothetical 
scenario, CTCF release from the aEHS-1.4 insulator 
may favor the chromosomal conformation changes and 
the signal spreading needed for the interaction between 
the a-MRE and the adult 
D and 
A gene promoter 
regions and their transcriptional activation (Figure 8B). 
This model represents a novel regulatory role for a 
CTCF-dependent chromatin insulator involved in a differ-
entiation pathway. In summary, at the endogenous 
context the aEHS-1.4 insulator may have enhancer 
blocking activity (presumably over the a-MRE) and 
barrier function to contribute to chromatin structure 
changes at the domain scale. Such dual activity is thus 
in part CTCF-dependent, and probably can also be 
driven by different stage-specific nuclear factors. 
A possible mechanism for CTCF release regulation 
could come from the presence of intergenic transcripts at 
the a-globin domain (43 and unpublished results). It has 
been recently demonstrated that for lysozyme gene activa-
tion by pro-inflammatory stimuli there is a CTCF-cohesin 
complex eviction by the transient stimulation of a 
non-coding RNA (31). 
Additionally, we demonstrated that poly(ADP-ribosyl)-
ation is modulating CTCF activity at the aEHS-1.4 insu-
lator (Supplementary Figure S4 and Figure 6). When 
PARP-1 is inhibited at the erythroblast stage we are able 
to mimic the effect of CTCF release during differentiation, 
i.e. an increase in histone open marks and the activation of 
the adult 
D and 
A globin genes (Figure 6). In contrast, 
CTCF knock down do not cause the activation of any 
a-globin gene in erythroblasts (Figure 5B) and impedes 
a-globin gene trans-activation at the differentiated 
stage. From these results several interpretations emerged. 
One predicts that CTCF poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation does 
not occur in all the CTCFs bound in vivo along the 
domain and that the CTCF located at the aEHS-1.4 insu-
lator is modified post-translationally by PARP-1 (36). 
Furthermore, it is possible that not all CTCF associated 
complexes located along the domain possess the same 
peptidic composition and activity. This is an aspect that 
is currently under investigation. We predict that some 
CTCF-associated complexes are more structural and 
others, like the one linked to the aEHS-1.4, should have 
a regulatory function. Based on such predictions, it is now 
attractive to look for CTCF partners at different locations 
in the domain, including PARP-1. For example, CHD8, 
cohesins, lamin or CTCF itself among others (3,32) which 
would further support the proposal that poly(ADP-
ribosyl)ation could form a docking site for multiple 
protein interactions with regulatory and chromatin func-
tions (44). 
A different interpretation, that does not exclude the 
previous one, has to do with the spatial organization of 
the chicken a-globin domain. We propose that CTCF is 
possibly contributing to this 3D organization of the 
domain, and therefore when it is knocked down, there is 
a generalized reduction of the protein levels affecting the 
active chromatin hub formation and consequently the ac-
tivation of the adult a-globin genes (Figure 5). This is not 
surprising since it has previously been demonstrated that </p>

<p>Figure 7. aMRE element is able to trans-activate the a 
D promoter 
upon differentiation to the mature erythrocyte stage. Flow cytometry 
histograms (FACS) showing the GFP fluorescence level of pools of 
stably transfected HD3 cells with three different constructs, </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>, 
aMRE-
D and aMRE-aEHS-1.4-
D (showed underneath each graph). 
The full red graph corresponds the erythroblast stage (HD3 cells) and 
the black empty graph corresponds to the same pool subjected to dif-
ferentiation (HD3-dif). </p>



<p>CTCF can mediate long-distance chromatin loop forma-
tion in the mouse b-globin locus (10). We predict that 
CTCF is not the only factor participating as it has been 
shown that LCR long-distance contacts can also be de-
pendent on EKLF and GATA-1/FOG-1 (45,46), factors 
that also bind different regions of the a-globin gene 
domain (21). 
In this regard, the 3D structuring of the a-globin 
domain was recently suggested by a chromatin conform-
ation capture approach, which showed the formation of 
an active chromatin hub by the interaction between the </p>

<p>a-MRE, a DNase I hypersensitive site of unknown 
function located À9-kb upstream of the gene (-9-kb 
DHS), the CpG-island corresponding to the promoter of 
the C16orf35 gene and the promoter region of the adult </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>gene (Figure 1) (38). Interestingly, the aEHS-1.4 element, 
located around À14-kb upstream the embryonic p gene, is 
contained in the loop formed by contacts between the 
a-MRE and the À9-kb DHS, thus the aEHS-1.4 element 
appears not to contribute directly to hub formation in 
this context. Whether alternative CTCF sites along 
the a-globin domain, which we recently identified </p>

<p>Figure 8. Summary and model for the aEHS-1.4 insulator role at the chicken a-globin locus. (A) Summary of histone post-translational modifica-
tions and CTCF in vivo enrichment over the 6.6-kb genomic region containing the aEHS-1.4 insulator. As adult erythroid differentiation proceeds 
there is an increment in histone modifications corresponding to a permissive chromatin environment over the aEHS-1.4 insulator and the CTCF site 
(see P2 primer location) that expands and further increases over the entire region in 10dRBC when the adult genes 
D and 
A are switched on. CTCF 
is present during differentiation with a peak at the erythroblast stage (HD3 cells) and then released at the mature 10dRBC when the adult 
D and </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>genes are being expressed (see right side green graph bar). P1-P5 represent the primers covering the 6.6-kb genomic region used for ChIP assays and 
P2 are the primers located over the CTCF-binding site. (B) Model suggesting a mechanism of action for the aEHS-1.4 insulator at the level of the 
chromatin structure at the domain scale and adult a-globin gene expression. Vertical arrows represent DNase I hypersensitive sites. We propose that 
at the erythroblast stage the aEHS-1.4 insulator blocks the effects coming from the a-MRE concomitant with the fact that the adult 
D and </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>globin genes remain silenced. At the late erythrocyte stage CTCF dissociation from the insulator facilitates a-MRE activity allowing trans-activation 
of a-globin adult genes. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 1 101 </p>

<p>(unpublished observations), contribute to domain organ-
ization via interaction of CTCF and its co-factors, would 
require further investigation. 
In summary, we propose that the aEHS-1.4 insulator 
contributes to regulate the chromatin structure and differ-
ential gene expression of the chicken a-globin gene 
domain throughout erythroid differentiation. We suggest 
that the regulated interaction of CTCF with its binding 
site could represent a way to control the function of the 
aEHS-1.4 element over a-globin genes expression, 
together with post-translational modifications like the 
poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation that modulate CTCF activity. In 
terms of the chromatin configuration of the locus, multiple 
CTCF-binding sites and their associated factors may fa-
cilitate the formation of a chromatin hub in a regulated 
manner. Our results suggest that the intergenic regulatory 
and structural components of a chromatin domain are 
critical to achieve regulated gene expression. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank Paul Delgado-Olguı´n, Catherine 
Farrell and Gary Felsenfeld for invaluable suggestions 
on the manuscript. The authors also thank Martı´n 
Escamilla-del-Arenal, He´ctor Rinco´n-Arano and all 
members of Fe´lix Recillas-Targa laboratory for constant 
scientific discussions. The authors thank Fabian Flores 
Jasso for his help generating the shRNA used against 
CTCF. The authors thank L. Ongay, G. Codiz and M. 
Mora from the Unidad de Biologı´a Molecular, 
IFC-UNAM, for the DNA sequencing and FACS 
facility. The CNB Transgenic Facility is acknowledged 
for producing the transgenic mice reported in this 
article. The authors are most grateful to Almudena 
Tello, Diego Mun˜oz, Zahira Corrales, and Esther Zurita 
for technical assistance. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Direccio´n 
General 
de 
Asuntos 
del 
Personal 
Acade´mico-Universidad Nacional Auto´noma de Me´xico 
(IN209403 and IN214407); Consejo Nacional de Ciencia 
y Tecnologı´a (CONACyT: 42653-Q and 58767); PhD fel-
lowship from CONACyT (170087 and 207989) and 
Direccio´n General de estudios de Posgrado-Universidad 
Nacional Auto´noma de Me´xico (DGEP) (to M.F.-M. 
and E.G.-B.); PhD Graduate Program of Doctorado en 
Ciencias Biome´dicas, UNAM; Spanish Ministry of 
Education and Science (BFU2006-12185); Spanish 
Ministry of Science and Innovation (BIO2009-12697) (to 
L.M.). Funding for open access charge: Universidad 
Nacional Auto´noma de Me´xico (UNAM), Instituto de 
Fisiologia Celular. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>







<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 1 103 </p>

</text></tei>