<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3406768" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Fertile plants undergoing male gametogenesis can be treated with nitrous oxide (N 2 O) gas to obtain 2n male 
gametes. N 2 O treatment is also expected to restore the fertility of interspecific hybrids through meiotic 
restitution or mitotic amphidiploidization. However, this technique has few applications to date, and it is un-
known how N 2 O treatment restores fertility in sterile hybrids. To establish optimal N 2 O treatment conditions 
and determine its cytological mechanism of action, we treated various sized floral buds with N 2 O gas at dif-
ferent anther developmental stages from fertile and sterile hybrid lilies. N 2 O treatment using the optimal 1-
4 mm floral buds induced mitotic polyploidization of male archesporial cells to produce 2n pollen in fertile 
hybrid lilies. In sterile hybrid lilies, N 2 O treatment doubled the chromosome number in male archesporial 
cells followed by homologous chromosome pairing and normal meiosis in pollen mother cells (PMC), result-
ing in restoration of pollen fertility. Backcrossing the resultant fertile pollen to Lilium × formolongi produced 
many triploid BC 1 plants. Thus N 2 O treatment at the archesporial cell proliferating stage effectively overcame 
pollen sterility in hybrid lilies, resulting in fertile, 2n pollen grains that could produce progeny. The procedure 
presented here will promote interspecific or interploidy hybridization of lilies. </p>

<p>Interspecific hybridization is useful for increasing genetic 
diversity. In ornamental flower breeding, interspecific hy-
bridization is an essential technique that produces novel cul-
tivars, as driven by consumer demand. Many such cultivars 
are used as ornamental crops (Fukai and Tsuji 2004, Okazaki 
et al. 1992, 1994, 1995, Saruwatri et al. 2008), whereas hy-
brids obtained from remote interspecific crosses are mostly 
sterile and cannot be used in cross breeding (Choudhary et 
al. 2000, Gangadevi et al. 1985, Poysa 1990). The traditional 
method of overcoming hybrid sterility is to double chromo-
some number using polyploidizing agents such as colchicine 
to produce allopolyploids that may be fertile (Asano 1982, </p>

<p>Nimura et al. 2006). 
Nitrous oxide (N 2 O) has been applied to zygotes and 
seedlings in many crops as a polyploidizing agent in lieu of 
colchicine treatment (Berdahl and Barker 1991, Dvorak et 
al. 1973, Kato 2002, Kato and Birchler 2006, Nygren 1955, 
Östergren 1954, 1957, Taylor et al. 1976, Zeilinga and 
Schouten 1968). Meiotic metaphase stage anthers of male-
fertile cultivars in tulips and lilies are optimal for N 2 O treat-
ment to produce fertile 2n pollen grains (Akutsu et al. 2007, 
Okazaki et al. 2001, 2005). Compared to other chemicals 
that mostly induce mitotic polyploidization by arresting cell 
division, N 2 O is not damaging and leads to first division 
restitution (FDR) or second division restitution (SDR) in 
meiosis in male-fertile plants, producing 2n gametes that are 
functional and available for crossing. Some polyploid plants 
have been produced using 2n gametes obtained by N 2 O 
treatment (Akutsu et al. 2007, Okazaki et al. 2005). 
Lilies (Lilium spp., 2n = 2x = 24) are one of the most 
important horticultural crops, with about 100 species </p>

<p>Communicated by M. Hirai 
Received January 28, 2011. Accepted August 2, 2011. 
*Corresponding author (e-mail: okazaki@agr.niigata-u.ac.jp) 
 † These two authors contributed equally to this work </p>

<p>Nukui, Kitamura, Hioki, Ootsuka, Miyoshi, Satou, Takatori, Oomiya and Okazaki </p>

<p>
widespread in the northern hemisphere (Nishikawa et al. 
1999). The most important modern commercial lilies mainly 
belong to the Asiatic, Oriental, and Longiflorum hybrid 
groups, and over 10,000 cultivars, including many sterile in-
terspecific hybrids, are registered (Matthews 2007). Barba-
Gonzalez et al. (2006) obtained fertile 2n pollen from sterile 
lily hybrids by using N 2 O treatment. Postulating that N 2 O 
treatment could bring about meiotic restitution in sterile as 
well as fertile lily cultivars, they concluded from cytological 
analyses of progeny that N 2 O had induced FDR gametes in 
most cases. However, the particular FDR mechanism by 
which hybrid sterility can be overcome does not explain the 
finding of Kitamura et al. (2009). In their histological study 
on pollen meiosis in fertile plants treated with N 2 O gas for 
24 h, microtubules were effectively depolymerized, which 
prevented chromosomes from moving to the poles and re-
sulted in chromosome retention in the center of N 2 O-treated 
cells. Cell plate formation took place without delay, how-
ever, yielding one daughter cell with a diploid genome and 
another daughter cell without chromosomes. As a result, a 
2n male gamete was produced during meiotic metaphase. In 
sterile interspecific hybrids where chromosomes are scat-
tered in the cytoplasm owing to non-homologous parental 
genomes, the cell plate divides the chromosomes unequally 
to make aneuploid daughter cells with or without N 2 O treat-
ment (Kitamura et al. 2009). This suggests that N 2 O treat-
ment during meiotic division does not lead to chromosome 
doubling in a daughter cell through the FDR mechanism in 
sterile hybrids. The cytological mechanism of action of N 2 O 
treatment for overcoming hybrid sterility remains to be de-
termined. 
Therefore, this study investigated how N 2 O gas leads to 
the development of fertile gametes in sterile interspecific hy-
brid lilies and determined the optimal PMC developmental 
stage for overcoming hybrid sterility. In addition, to verify 
whether the resulting fertile pollen could produce progeny, </p>

<p>we attempted to produce BC 1 progeny using the fertile pol-
len obtained from completely sterile interspecific hybrids. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Plant materials 
The cultivars used in this study were collected from 
Yamaki Noen Co., Ltd. (Niigata, Japan). The cultivars used 
are listed in Table 1: four fertile cultivars belonging to Lilium 
spp. Asiatic hybrid lilies, a fertile Oriental hybrid lily, two 
LA hybrids, an OT hybrid, and an LO hybrid. Two cultivars 
of L. × formolongi were crossed with pollen from N 2 O-
treated hybrids. Single bulbs of each cultivar were planted in 
10-cm pots in October or November and grown in an unheat-
ed greenhouse at Niigata University, Niigata, Japan. </p>

<p>N 2 O treatment 
N 2 O treatment (modified from Akutsu et al. 2007) was 
performed at room temperature for 48 h in a pressure-
tolerant cylinder, with N 2 O gas applied at 6 atm without 
oxygen. Prophase I and meiotic metaphase I in Asiatic hy-
brid lilies occur in 15-or 20-mm floral buds, respectively 
(Akutsu et al. 2007). In L. longiflorum, premeiotic mitosis 
occurs in 10-mm floral buds (Taylor and McMaster 1954), 
and N 2 O treatment during prophase I does not produce 2n 
pollen grains at flowering (Akutsu et al. 2007). Based on 
these results, we treated hybrid lilies with attached 1-10 mm 
floral buds, which presumably contained the archesporial 
cell proliferating stage. Buds were small at the time of treat-
ment, making direct length measurements difficult. Hence, 
longitudinal lengths of detached floral buds from plants 
grown under similar conditions were measured with a 
caliper or ruler to estimate the floral bud sizes of treated 
plants at the time of N 2 O treatment. The treated plants were 
grown in a greenhouse. N 2 O treatments were conducted 
for Asiatic hybrid lilies, Oriental hybrid lilies and LA </p>

<p>Table 1. Ploidy level, pollen fertility and origin of cultivars used in the study </p>

<p>Cultivars 
Horticultural 
groups </p>

<p>Ploidy 
level </p>

<p>Chromosome 
number 
Pollen fertility 
Origin </p>

<p>Regata 
Asiatic hybrids 
2× 
24 
fertile 
Intra-sectional hybrid (Sinomartagon) 
Mona 
Asiatic hybrids 
2× 
24 
fertile 
Intra-sectional hybrid (Sinomartagon) 
Gran Paradiso 
Asiatic hybrids 
4× 
48 
fertile 
Intra-sectional hybrid (Sinomartagon) 
Loreto 
Asiatic hybrids 
4× 
48 
fertile 
Intra-sectional hybrid (Sinomartagon) 
Willeke Alberti 
Oriental hybrids 
2× 
24 
fertile 
Intra-sectional hybrid (Archelirion) 
Serrada 
LA hybrids 
3× 
36 
almost sterile 
Inter-sectional hybrid; 
L. longiflorum (Leucolirion) × Asiatic hybrids (Sinomartagon) 
Royal Trinity 
LA hybrids 
3× 
36 
low fertile 
Inter-sectional hybrid; 
L. longiflorum (Leucolirion) × Asiatic hybrids (Sinomartagon) 
Yelloween 
OT hybrids 
2× 
24 
completely sterile Unknown 
Otome no Sugata LO hybrids 
2× 
24 
completely sterile Inter-sectional hybrid; 
L. × formolongi (Leucolirion) × L. rubellum (Archelirion) 
Katsuki 
L. × formolongi 
2× 
24 
fertile 
Intra-sectional hybrid (Leucolirion); 
L. formosanum × L. longiflorum 
Original Ougo 
L. × formolongi 
2× 
24 
fertile 
Intra-sectional hybrid (Leucolirion); 
L. formosanum × L. longiflorum </p>

<p>N 2 O-induced mitotic polyploidization in anther somatic cells </p>



<p>hybrids in 2007, 'Yelloween' in 2007 and 2008 and 'Otome 
no Sugata' in 2008. </p>

<p>Pollen assessments and statistical analysis 
At flowering time, a small amount of pollen was collect-
ed from six anthers of each bud, mixed, and then stained 
with 1% (w/v) acetocarmine solution. Lengths of short axes 
of pollen grains (100-400) were microscopically measured 
using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Image-Pro PLUS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Media Cybernetics Co., Ltd.</rs>., 
Bethesda, MD, USA). In the control and N 2 O-treated plants 
of 'Yelloween', microspore tetrad sizes were measured from 
young anthers of 30-35 mm floral buds. Pollen fertility was 
determined using the acetocarmine method, whereby 
acetocarmine-stained pollen was regarded as fertile pollen. 
Before pollination, the germinability of the pollen obtained 
by N 2 O treatment was assessed after culture for 24 h at 25°C 
in agar medium containing 10% (w/v) sucrose, 0.7% (w/v) 
agar, 0.3 g/L calcium nitrate and 10 mg/L boric acid. 
For data analysis, a non-parametric multiple comparison 
method (Steel-Dwass test) was performed using <rs type="software">Microsoft 
Excel 2003</rs> and statistical add-in software (<rs id="software-1" type="software">Excel Toukei 
2010</rs> for Windows, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Social Survey Research Information Co., Ltd., Tokyo, Japan</rs>). </p>

<p>Crossing and hybrid embryo rescue 
For intraspecific hybridization of Asiatic hybrid lilies, 
control crosses were made as follows: 2x × 2x; 4x × 2x; and 
4x × 4x. Tetraploid 'Gran Paradiso' was pollinated with pol-
len masses including putative 2n grains. Before flowering, 
flowers were emasculated in each cross. Capsules were har-
vested 2 months after pollination, and the seed number was 
counted for each cross. 
For interspecific hybridization using fertile pollen re-
stored from the sterile hybrid lilies, the capsules were col-
lected about 40 d after pollination and embryo culture was 
performed as described by Okazaki et al. (1994). </p>

<p>Histological observation 
PMC developmental stages of the Asiatic hybrid lily 
'Regata' were observed. Floral buds of different sizes were 
collected and fixed for 24 h in Carnoy's fluid, dehydrated 
in an alcohol gradient series, and embedded in paraffin. 
Paraffin-embedded samples were cut into 6-µm sections, 
stained with 0.05% (w/v) toluidine blue, mounted in balsam 
jelly, and observed by light microscopy (BX-60; Olympus, 
Tokyo, Japan). </p>

<p>Determination of ploidy and hybridity 
Ploidy of seedlings and pollen grains was measured using 
flow cytometry as described previously (Akutsu et al. 2007, 
Okazaki et al. 2005). To verify the hybridity of the progeny 
from the cross between L. × formolongi and the N 2 O-treated 
'Otome no Sugata', genomic DNA was extracted from the 
leaves using the CTAB method (Murray and Thompson 
1980), and the internal transcribed spacer (ITS) region of 
rDNA was amplified according to the methods of Nishikawa </p>

<p>et al. (1999, 2001). The amplified fragments were digested 
by MspI and analyzed on polyacrylamide gels (Nagaoka et 
al. 2010). </p>

<p>Genomic in situ hybridization (GISH) 
For mitotic metaphase chromosome analysis, the root tips 
were collected early in the morning. The root tips were incu-
bated in 0.05% (w/v) colchicine solution for 2-3 h and then 
fixed in ethanol-acetic acid (3 : 1) solution for 24 h and 
stored at 4°C until use. The root tips were washed in distilled 
water and incubated in a pectolytic enzyme mixture contain-
ing 2% (w/v) cellulose Onozuka-RS (Yakult Pharmaceutical 
Industry Co. Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) and 1% (w/v) pectolyase 
Y-23 (Kanto Chemical Co., Inc.) in 10 mM citrate buffer 
(pH 4.5) at 37°C for 1-2 h. Squash preparations were made 
in a drop of 45% (v/v) acetic acid and frozen using liquid 
nitrogen. The cover slips were removed using a razor blade. 
Genomic DNA of L. × formolongi was used as a probe 
and labeled with digoxigenin-11-dUTP by a standard nick 
translation protocol (Roche, Basel, Switzerland). GISH was 
performed as described by Marasek et al. (2006). The probe 
was detected with fluorescein-conjugated anti-digoxigenin. 
The preparations were analyzed with a microscope (BX60, 
Olympus) and photographed with a digital camera (DP70, 
Olympus). For each plant, the total number of chromosomes 
and the number of crossover points were determined. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Mitotic polyploidization of archesporial cells in fertile 
hybrid lilies 
Control pollen grain diameters ranged 51-71 µm 
(59 ± 4 µm, mean ± SD) in diploid Asiatic hybrid lily 
'Regata' (Fig. 1A, 1B) and 50-84 µm (60 ± 6 µm) in diploid 
Oriental hybrid lily 'Willeke Alberti' (Fig. 1D, 1E). Plants 
with small (1-10 mm) floral buds treated with N 2 O produced 
giant pollen in 'Regata' (Fig. 1C) and in 'Willeke Alberti' 
(Fig. 1F), whereas treated pollen shape was the same as the 
oval-shaped control pollen. For example, a 3-mm floral bud 
of 'Regata' and a 4-mm 'Willeke Alberti' bud treated with 
N 2 O gas resulted in a pollen size distribution of 59-119 µm 
(79 ± 15 µm) and 53-110 µm (81 ± 12 µm), respectively 
(Fig. 1A, 1D). 
Flow cytometric analysis of untreated pollen of 'Regata' 
revealed two peaks corresponding to 1C and 2C DNA 
content because the binucleate-type lily pollen contains one 
2C generative and one 1C vegetative cell (Fig. 1G). In con-
trast, the N 2 O-induced pollen gave rise to peaks at 1C, 2C 
and additional 4C levels, indicating both n and 2n pollen 
(Fig. 1H). These results indicated that N 2 O treatment was 
able to induce chromosome doubling in male gametes. 
Based on the difference in pollen size distribution between 
the control and N 2 O-induced pollen, we considered grains 
with a diameter of &gt;75 or 85 µm diameter as putative 2n 
pollen grains in 'Regata' or 'Willeke Alberti', respectively. 
To determine the most suitable floral bud stage for </p>

<p>Nukui, Kitamura, Hioki, Ootsuka, Miyoshi, Satou, Takatori, Oomiya and Okazaki </p>

<p>
mitotic chromosome doubling of male archesporial cells, 1-
10 mm floral buds were treated with N 2 O. Mean production 
rates of giant pollen in a treated flower were classified into 
five categories (Fig. 2). The efficacy of giant pollen forma-
tion fluctuated among treated flowers of 'Regata', with up to 
83% (n = 128) of flowers having more than 3% giant pollen 
among the 155 treated flowers (Fig. 2). Flowers producing </p>

<p>giant pollen grains with a frequency of higher than 50% oc-
curred in 1.0-1.9 mm and 2.0-3.9 mm floral buds. The aver-
age rate of giant pollen production in the 1.0-1.9 mm cate-
gory was significantly higher than in the other categories. 
N 2 O treatment using smaller floral buds tended to produce 
more giant pollen grains. 
Similarly, in Oriental hybrid lily 'Willeke Alberti', N 2 O </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Size distribution, appearance, and flow cytometry histograms of pollen grains in diploid cultivars. Pollen size distributions were obtained 
from control pollen (shaded bars) and pollen obtained from plants treated with N 2 O gas for 48 h (open bars) in 'Regata' (A) and 'Willeke Alberti' 
(D). The appearance of untreated (B, E) and N 2 O-induced (C, F) pollen grains are shown for 'Regata' (B, C) and 'Willeke Alberti' (E, F). The his-
tograms show pollen samples for untreated (G) and N 2 O-induced (H) pollen grains in 'Regata'. Bars = 50 μm (B, C, E, F). </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Frequency (%) of giant pollen production classes in floral buds of fertile hybrid lilies after 48 h of N 2 O treatment of floral buds of different 
lengths. Ave., mean percentage of giant pollen grains produced in each floral bud size, with number of N 2 O-treated floral buds in parentheses. 
Different letters between cultivars represent significant differences at P = 0.05, as determined by the Steel-Dwass test. </p>

<p>N 2 O-induced mitotic polyploidization in anther somatic cells </p>



<p>treatment induced giant pollen in flower buds ranging from 
1-7.9 mm (Fig. 2). The average rate of giant pollen produc-
tion in the 4.0-5.9 mm category was significantly higher 
than in the 1.0-1.9 mm category. Although there were no 
significant differences on giant pollen production rate 
among the 2.0-3.9 mm, 4.0-5.9 mm and 6.0-7.9 mm cate-
gories, we found flowers producing giant pollen with a fre-
quency of higher than 30% in the 4.0-5.9 mm category. 
Therefore, floral buds ca. 5 mm long at the time of N 2 O 
treatment were likely to be suitable for induction of giant 
pollen. Thus, the optimal bud size of 'Willeke Alberti' was 
larger than that of 'Regata. The efficacy of giant pollen for-
mation fluctuated among the treated flowers, as well as 
among the anthers within a given flower, in 'Willeke Alberti' 
and 'Regata' (data not shown). </p>

<p>Restoration of fertility in sterile and partially sterile hybrid 
lilies 
OT hybrid 'Yelloween' was completely pollen sterile 
(Fig. 3A). LA hybrid 'Serrada' displayed low pollen fertility 
ranging from 0-20% (10 ± 9.7%) (Fig. 3C). To examine 
whether N 2 O treatment could restore pollen fertility in ster-
ile interspecific hybrid lilies, 'Yelloween' and 'Serrada' 
plants were treated with N 2 O in 2007. A partially sterile LA 
hybrid 'Royal Torinity' also was included. N 2 O treatment 
restored pollen fertility in both sterile hybrid lilies (Fig. 3B, 
3D). Although acetocarmine-stained pollen is not always 
fertile, 76% of pollen on average was stained in the untreat-
ed plants of LA hybrid 'Royal Trinity' (Fig. 3E), whereas 
N 2 O-treated plants produced larger, positively stained pollen 
(Fig. 3F). The smaller-sized, positively stained pollen likely 
came from normal meiosis. 
To determine the optimal growth stage for overcoming 
pollen sterility, the aforementioned sterile and partially ster-
ile cultivars were treated at various stages (1-7.9 mm) of flo-
ral buds in 2007. N 2 O treatment of 1-3.9 mm floral buds of 
'Yelloween' produced more fertile pollen grains, with the 
highest pollen fertility (50%) achieved from 2-mm floral 
buds (Fig. 4). In 'Serrada', fertile pollen grains were most 
effectively produced using 1.0-3.9 mm floral buds, with the 
most fertile pollen (71%) obtained from 4-mm floral buds 
(Fig. 4). Untreated plants of LA hybrid 'Royal Trinity' 
showed normal meiosis, with the diameter of pollen grain 
ranging between 57-97 µm (83 ± 10 µm). Based on this 
control data for pollen grain diameter in 'Royal Trinity', to 
examine the effectiveness of N 2 O treatment, we scored the 
frequency of giant pollen grains as that of pollen grains with 
a diameter of &gt;100 µm in the N 2 O-treated plants. Although 
there were no significant differences among the 2.0-3.9 mm, 
4.0-5.9 mm and 6.0-7.9 mm categories, the 2.0-5.9 mm flo-
ral buds produced more giant pollen (&gt;100 µm) in 'Royal 
Trinity' (Fig. 4). 
To confirm the reproducibility and reliability of these re-
sults, we repeated the experiments to overcome hybrid steril-
ity using 'Yelloween' and a completely sterile LO hybrid 
'Otome no Sugata' in 2008. 'Otome no Sugata' produced </p>

<p>highly fertile pollen upon N 2 O treatment (Fig. 3G, 3H). In 
'Yelloween', the efficacy of recovery of fertile pollen varied 
among the treated flowers (Fig. 4) and ranged 1-67% (23% 
average in the 1.0-1.9 mm floral buds; 11% average in the 
2.0-3.9 mm floral buds). The efficacy of fertile pollen for-
mation fluctuated among the six anthers within a flower. For 
example, four of six anthers of 'Yelloween' had &lt;10% re-
covery of fertile pollen, whereas the remaining two anthers </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Overcoming hybrid sterility by treating sterile or partially ster-
ile hybrid lilies with N 2 O for 48 h. Appearance of control pollen (left 
side) and N 2 O-induced pollen (right side) in 'Yelloween' (A, B), 
'Serrada' (C, D), 'Royal Trinity' (E, F) and 'Otome no Sugata' (G, H) 
is shown. Bars = 100 μm. </p>

<p>Nukui, Kitamura, Hioki, Ootsuka, Miyoshi, Satou, Takatori, Oomiya and Okazaki </p>

<p>
had 55% and 50% recovery. 'Otome no Sugata' also had 
variable efficacy of fertile pollen recovery among the N 2 O-
treated flowers (21-90% range; 72% average in 1.0-1.9 mm 
floral buds; 76% average in 2.0-3.9 mm floral buds). </p>

<p>Histological observations of archesporial cells in anther 
primordia 
We observed cell development in anther primordia at the 
optimal floral bud developmental stage (1-4 mm) after N 2 O 
treatment in 'Regata'. Transverse sections of the 1-3 mm flo-
ral buds showed actively dividing archesporial cells inside 
the peripheral layers of the stamen (Fig. 5A, 5B). As a result 
of the cell proliferation along the longitudinal axis of anther 
locules, the oblong locules were filled with archesporial 
cells in 3-5 mm floral buds (Fig. 5C). Cell division in an-
ther primordia was almost finished at the 7-mm floral bud 
stage, with 0.6% mitotic index of the archesporial cells 
(Fig. 5D). In 10-mm floral buds, tapetum cells surrounded 
PMCs, and no mitotic divisions were observed (data not 
shown). In the 32-mm floral buds of 'Yelloween' undergo-
ing meiotic division, untreated control microspore tetrads 
had 20-29 µm (25 ± 1.8 µm) diameters, whereas floral buds 
treated with N 2 O had some larger microspore tetrads with 
19-41 µm (29 ± 4.2 µm) diameters (Fig. 6). Among them, 
29% were &gt;30 µm in diameter, which was similar to the re-
covery percentage of fertile pollen at anthesis. These results 
suggest that N 2 O treatment overcame hybrid sterility in the 
interspecific hybrid lilies owing to chromosome doubling of 
archesporial cells of PMCs. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Frequency (%) of floral buds in each fertile or giant pollen pro-
duction class in the sterile or partially sterile hybrid lily floral buds 
treated with N 2 O for 48 h. Ave., mean percentage of fertile or giant 
pollen grains in each floral bud size, with number of floral buds treated 
with N 2 O in parentheses. The fertile pollen production rate at flower-
ing ('Yelloween', 'Serrada' and 'Otome no Sugata') and the giant pol-
len production rate ('Royal Trinity') were measured. Different letters 
between cultivars represent significant differences at P = 0.05, as de-
termined by the Steel-Dwass test. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Transverse sections of young anthers of 'Regata'. The floral 
buds were sampled at lengths of 1 mm (A), 3 mm (B), 5 mm (C) and 
7 mm (D). Ep, epidermis; En, endothecium; T, tapetum; PMC, pollen 
mother cell. The archesporial cell undergoing mitotic division is 
marked with arrowheads. Bars = 50 μm. </p>

<p>N 2 O-induced mitotic polyploidization in anther somatic cells </p>



<p>Crosses with putative 2n pollen obtained from the N 2 O-
treated plants 
In the 2x-level control cross (between 2x Asiatic hybrid 
lilies 'Mona' and 'Regata'), all capsules set normally with 
about 120 normal seeds per capsule (Table 1). In the 4x-
level control cross (between 4x Asiatic hybrid lilies 'Gran 
Paradiso' and 'Loreto'), normal seeds were obtained with 34 
seeds per capsule. The ploidy levels of embryos excised 
from the resulting seeds were determined using flow cyto-
metry (Table 2). All seeds obtained from the 2x × 2x and 
4x × 4x crosses were diploid and tetraploid, respectively. 
These data indicate that the diploids and tetraploids used 
have normal fertility in male and female gametes. Neverthe-
less, no seeds were obtained in the interploidy cross between </p>

<p>the tetraploid 'Gran Paradiso' and the diploid 'Regata', ow-
ing to triploid block. This phenomenon can act as a selective 
barrier against triploids in crosses of tetraploid cultivars with 
mixed n and 2n pollen (Akutsu et al. 2007). In such crosses, 
the resulting progeny seeds will be tetraploids. In fact, when 
the tetraploid cultivar 'Gran Paradiso' was crossed with 2n 
grain including pollen from N 2 O-treated plants of the diploid 
cultivar 'Regata', 59% of the flowers pollinated set capsule 
and the resulting embryos were tetraploid. In the crosses 
using the 2n grain including pollen from N 2 O-treated 3x LA 
hybrid 'Royal Torinity', the examined embryos were penta-
ploid. When L. × formolongi was pollinated with pollen ob-
tained from the N 2 O-treated 'Yelloween' (OT hybrid) and 
'Otome no Sugata' (LO hybrid), some hybrid embryos were 
obtained. These were diploid, triploid or tetraploid (Table 3). 
However, no embryos were obtained using the control pol-
len that contained no viable grains. </p>

<p>Verification of hybridity 
'Otome no Sugata' was the diploid hybrid developed by 
crossing L. × formolongi with L. rubellum (Okazaki et al. 
1992). Crossing L. × formolongi with 2n grain including pol-
len of 'Otome no Sugata' produced in this study was regard-
ed as a backcross, which would lead to production of 
triploids having the diploid genomes of L. × formolongi and 
a haploid genome of L. rubellum. When genomic DNA of 
L. × formolongi was used as a probe, 24 chromosomes were 
detected in the triploid progeny (Fig. 7A), indicating that 
these 24 chromosomes came from L. × formolongi and the 
remaining 12 from L. rubellum. The GISH analysis revealed 
that no chromosome recombination occurred between the 
genomes of L. × formolongi and L. rubellum in either of the 
three hybrid plants examined. 
The ITS regions of rDNA in L. × formolongi, L. rubellum, 
'Otome no Sugata', and the backcrossed progeny were 
amplified by PCR, and the resulting PCR products were </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Size distribution and appearance of microspore tetrads in con-
trol and N 2 O-treated plants of 'Yelloween'. The plants were untreated 
(black bar) or treated (open bar) with N 2 O for 48 h (A). The appear-
ance of microspore tetrads of untreated (B) and N 2 O-treated (C) plants 
is indicated. Large microspore tetrads derived from chromosome dou-
bling by N 2 O treatment are marked with arrowheads. Bars = 50 μm. </p>

<p>Table 2. Results of interploidy crosses between diploid and tetraploid lily varieties and crosses between tetraploids and N 2 O-treated plants </p>

<p>Female parent 
Male parent 
No. of flowers 
pollinated </p>

<p>No. of ovaries 
developed </p>

<p>No. of seeds obtained per 
capsule (mean ± SD) </p>

<p>Ploidy level of seeds (%) </p>

<p>2× a 
4× 
5× </p>

<p>Diploid × diploid 
Mona (2×) 
Regata (2×) 
5 
5 
1 2 5 . 8 ± 18.2 
100 
n = 20 </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>Tetraploid × tetraploid 
Gran Paradiso (4×) 
L o r e t o ( 4 ×) 
9 
9 
3 3 . 7 ± 16.7 
0 
100 
n = 45 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Tetraploid × diploid 
Gran Paradiso (4×) 
Regata (2×) 
1 0 
0 
-
-
-
-</p>

<p>Tetraploid × N 2 O-treated plants 
Gran Paradiso (4×) 
Regata (2×) 
7 1 
4 2 
3 . 1 ± 2.7 
0 
100 
n = 41 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Gran Paradiso (4×) 
Royal Torinity (3×) 
11 
8 
5.5 
0 
0 
100 
n = 41 </p>

<p>a Ploidy of mature seeds was determined by flow cytometry (n = the number of seeds examined). </p>

<p>Nukui, Kitamura, Hioki, Ootsuka, Miyoshi, Satou, Takatori, Oomiya and Okazaki </p>

<p>
&lt;700 bp in size, and were cleaved by MspI (Fig. 7B). The ca. 
160 bp restriction fragment, specific to L. rubellum genome, 
was transmitted to the backcrossed triploid and tetraploid 
progeny, indicating that the triploid and tetraploid plants 
derived from crossing L. × formolongi with N 2 O-treated 
'Otome no Sugata' were true hybrids, whereas the diploids 
were false hybrids (data not shown). The two triploid plants 
derived from the cross of L. × formolongi and 'Yelloween' 
died after transplant. Appearance of diploids and tetraploids 
was an unexpected result; the tetraploid BC1 plants were 
arisen from the fusion of spontaneous 2n female gametes 
and the N 2 O-induced 2n pollen. The diploids might be de-
veloped by spontaneous 2n female gamete formation, fol-
lowed by pseudogamy. </p>

<p>Characteristics of hybrids 
Four plants from the cross of L. × formolongi with N 2 O-
treated 'Otome no Sugata' flowered in the 2 years after pol-
lination. L. × formolongi has white, trumpet-shaped, upright 
flowers with yellow pollen (Fig. 7C). 'Otome no Sugata' has 
pink, trumpet-shaped flowers that are slightly drooping with 
brownish anthers (Fig. 7D). The hybrid floral sizes were in-
termediate between both parents, whereas flower color and 
anther color were similar to 'Otome no Sugata' (Fig. 7E-
7H). The appearance of flowers varied among hybrids, with 
upright positioned (Fig. 7E), slightly drooping flower posi-
tions and trumpet-shaped (Fig. 7F, 7H) or bowl-shaped 
(Fig. 7G) pink flowers. The appearance of the trumpet-
shaped flowers of the hybrids was more like L. × formolongi 
than 'Otome no Sugata'. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The mechanism of action of N 2 O for overcoming hybrid ste-
rility 
Barba-Gonzalez et al. (2006) reported that N 2 O treatment 
overcame pollen sterility through the FDR mechanism in 5-
10 mm floral buds. At this developmental stage, however, 
the archesporial cells in anthers are thought to undergo 
premeiotic mitosis. In general, microspore developmental 
stages correlate with floral bud lengths (Goldberg et al. 
1993). In L. longiflorum, floral buds &lt;10 mm or 10-22 mm </p>

<p>have the proliferating stage of archesporial cells or meiotic 
prophase I PMCs, respectively (Taylor and McMaster 
1954). Our histological study confirmed a similar correla-
tion between microspore developmental stage and floral bud 
length in Asiatic hybrids, although these lilies have smaller 
floral buds than L. longiflorum. Therefore, in the 5-10 mm 
floral buds used for N 2 O treatment by Barba-Gonzalez et al. </p>

<p>Table 3. Results of interspecific crosses between L. × formolongi and 
interspecific hybrids </p>

<p>Male parent </p>

<p>No. of 
flowers 
pollinated </p>

<p>No. of 
capsules 
set </p>

<p>No. of 
plantlets 
obtained </p>

<p>Ploidy level of 
progeny </p>

<p>2× a 3× 4× </p>

<p>Untreated control 
'Otome no Sugata' (2×) 
14 
5 
0 
-
--
'Yelloween' (2×) 
3 7 
7 
0 
-
--
Pollinated with N 2 O-treated plants 
'Otome no Sugata' (2×) 
3 2 
2 1 
2 4 
9 1 4 1 
'Yelloween' (2×) 
3 9 
2 2 
1 7 
1 5 
2 0 </p>

<p>a Ploidy of progeny was determined by flow cytometry. </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Hybridity and appearance of the parents and their hybrids (BC 1 
plants). GISH analysis of a triploid progeny with 24 L. × formolongi 
(green) and 12 L. rubellum (dark blue) chromosomes (A). CAPS 
analysis of MspI-digestion of the rDNA ITS region (B): 1, HincII-
digested ϕX174 markers; 2, L. × formolongi; 3, 'Otome no Sugata'; 
4, L. rubellum; and 5, a hybrid. The appearance of a female parent 
(L. × formolongi) (C), male parent ('Otome no Sugata') (D) and BC 1 
shoots (E-H). Bars = 10 μm (A) or 10 cm (C-H). </p>

<p>N 2 O-induced mitotic polyploidization in anther somatic cells </p>



<p>(2006), archesporial cells should undergo mitosis, indicating 
that production of 2n gametes in 5-10 mm floral buds does 
not occur via FDR during meiosis. Furthermore, if fertile 
pollen was produced in sterile hybrid lilies through the FDR 
mechanism, the resulting meiotic products should be dyads 
(unreduced microspores) having the same size as tetrads. In 
our study, however, larger microspore tetrads were observed 
in plants treated with N 2 O. Therefore, our results suggest 
that the FDR mechanism is not involved in restoration of 
pollen fertility, and chromosome doubling in archesporial 
cells followed by formation of amphidiploid PMCs 
(2n = 4x) is the mechanism for the recovery of hybrid fertil-
ity. 
Kato (2002) obtained doubled haploid lines by treating 
haploid maize floral primordia with N 2 O, suggesting that ap-
plying N 2 O to the floral primordial stage might overcome 
hybrid sterility. Unlike the treatment of floral primordia by 
Kato (2002), we treated anther archesporial cells. Thus, the 
use of floral tissues at different developmental stages may 
overcome interspecific sterility through mitotic polyploidiza-
tion. </p>

<p>Application of N 2 O treatment 
The proportion of 2n pollen varied in each anther within 
a bud for cultivars treated with N 2 O gas. This may be due to 
incomplete synchronized mitotic division of archesporial 
cells in the different anthers within a flower. Nevertheless, 
the developmental stages of archesporial cells correlated to 
some extent with floral bud lengths. As a result, the mea-
surement of floral bud length could be used to determine the 
optimal timing for N 2 O treatment: 1-4 mm for Asiatic hy-
brid lilies; 2-6 mm for Oriental hybrid lilies and LA hybrid 
lilies; and 1-4 mm for completely sterile OT hybrid 
'Yelloween' and LO hybrid 'Otome no Sugata'. This size-
based criterion is not absolute because the developmental 
stages of floral buds and archesporial cells are affected by 
environmental and/or culture conditions. 
Treatment using smaller floral buds tended to produce 
greater numbers of giant pollen grains. This indicates that if 
some archesporial cells undergo chromosome doubling at an 
early developmental stage with N 2 O treatment, the resulting 
4x archesporial cells could predominate, with preferential 
cell proliferation of the archesporial cell lineage. Additional-
ly, in contrast to the colchicine-induced chimeric somatic tis-
sues where 2x cells proliferate better than 4x cells, the N 2 O-
induced 4x archesporial cells effectively proliferated along 
the oblong anther locules (Fig. 5) because this narrow ob-
long locule allowed a certain space for 4x archesporial cells 
to outcompete 2x archesporial cells with 2n ploidy levels. 
Chromosome doubling in archesporial cells with N 2 O can 
shorten the period of polyploidy breeding in lilies compared 
to the traditional method of soaking bulb scales in colchi-
cine, which requires a long duration to flowering. Taken to-
gether, compared to soaking in colchicine, chromosome 
doubling in archesporial cells treated with N 2 O can save 
time and enhance production of polyploids. </p>

<p>Two methods for obtaining 2n pollen in fertile cultivars 
Okazaki et al. (2005) and Akutsu et al. (2007) reported 
that N 2 O treatment at metaphase I produces 2n pollen in 
Tulipa and Lilium, respectively. In the present study, N 2 O 
treatment at the archesporial cell proliferating stage allowed 
mitotic diploidization of male gametes of fertile cultivars. 
Thus, to obtain 2n pollen in fertile cultivars, chromosome 
doubling by N 2 O treatment has two optimal stages-the 
meiotic division stage and the archesporial cell proliferating 
stage. N 2 O treatment during the short duration of meiotic 
metaphase I stage requires skillful techniques for optimizing 
timing during meiotic divisions. However, it can produce 
more 2n pollen than in the archesporial cell proliferating 
stage because PMCs at meiotic metaphase I have more syn-
chronized cell divisions at the time of N 2 O treatment than 
archesporial cells. On the other hand, treatment is easier at 
the archesporial cell proliferating stage because plants in 
premeiotic stage are smaller and easier to handle. Moreover, 
the duration applicable for N 2 O treatment at the archesporial 
cell proliferating stage is longer than for the meiotic stage. </p>

<p>Characteristics of the BC 1 plants 
In the backcrosses using the resultant fertile pollen, pro-
duction of progeny is evidence of functional pollen obtained 
by overcoming pollen sterility. Although the resultant pollen 
is functional, only a limited number of the BC 1 plants were 
obtained due to interspecific incongruity in the BC 1 progeny. 
We did not find any chromosome recombination between 
the genomes of L. × formolongi and L. rubellum, probably 
because of the preferential homologous chromosome pairing 
in the amphidiploid PMCs formed by N 2 O treatment. This 
result is consistent with previous studies by Barba-Gonzalez 
et al. (2004) and Lim et al. (2000), who reported that fewer 
chromosomal recombinations occur in progenies obtained 
from crosses using fertile pollen of amphidiploids restored 
by somatic chromosome doubling compared to crosses using 
fertile pollen obtained from meiotic polyploidization. In this 
study, we found some phenotypic variations in the BC 1 
progeny, such as in the flower direction, an important trait 
for lily breeding (Fig. 7E-7H). This probably resulted from 
genetic variation between the parental plants of 
L. × formolongi because chromosome recombinations which 
would be a potential source of phenotypic variation in the 
progeny did not occur between the genomes of 
L. × formolongi and L. rubellum. </p>

<p>Overcoming hybrid sterility 
Hybrid sterility derived from remote hybridization be-
tween two different species is a common phenomenon in 
plants and is a key problem in interspecific breeding. The se-
lection of 2n gamete producers has contributed to overcom-
ing hybrid sterility in crop breeding (Hanneman and Peloquin 
1968, Khan et al. 2009, Marasek et al. 2006, Ramanna et 
al. 2003). The diploid LA hybrid lilies derived from the 
cross of L. longiflorum and Asiatic hybrid lilies showed 
intermediate morphology between the parental species. This </p>

<p>Nukui, Kitamura, Hioki, Ootsuka, Miyoshi, Satou, Takatori, Oomiya and Okazaki </p>

<p>
intermediate morphology is esthetically undesirable. To im-
prove this undesirable trait, 2n gamete producers were se-
lected for further backcrossing of diploid LA hybrids with 
Asiatic hybrid lilies because diploid LA hybrids were basi-
cally pollen sterile. As a result, triploid LA hybrids have 
been developed for commercial distribution. Similarly, other 
hybrid lilies such as OT, OA and LO have been derived from 
more remote interspecific hybridization than LA hybrids, 
and hence, they have serious hybrid sterility problems that 
require breeding involving selection of 2n gamete produc-
ers. However, 2n gametes may not be widely applicable in 
breeding because their occurrence is not always predictable 
(Asano 1984, Barba-Gonzalez et al. 2004, Lim et al. 2001). 
Thus, techniques that can overcome hybrid sterility of lilies 
and perhaps other crops are eagerly awaited. N 2 O treatment 
would be a useful technique in this regard, and the procedure 
presented here will promote interspecific or interploidy hy-
bridization of lilies and other crops. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Dr. K. Shinoda (National Agricultural Research 
Center for Hokkaido Region, Japan) for his invaluable com-
ments on this study and two anonymous reviewers for valu-
able comments. This work was supported in part by grants 
from the Ministry of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries, 
Japan, and a grant from Japan Society for the Promotion of 
Science (Grant in Aid for Scientific Research No. 
19580024). </p>



<p>N 2 O-induced mitotic polyploidization in anther somatic cells </p>





</text></tei>