<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3857483" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition (EMT), whereby epi-
thelial cells become individual mesenchymal cells, is a common 
feature of embryonic development (Nieto, 2011) and is reiterated 
during tumor metastasis in adults (Thiery et al., 2009). During 
this process, profound changes occur in cell morphology such 
that tightly adherent and polarized epithelial cells are transformed 
into loosely organized, nonpolarized, and often migratory mesen-
chymal cells. The cell biological processes underlying EMT have 
been best studied in cancer cells grown in vitro, and several tran-
scription factors, including Snail, Twist, and Sip1/Zeb2/ZFHX1B 
(here referred to as Sip1), have been identified as important me-
diators of EMT in metastasis (Kang and Massagué, 2004; Thiery 
et al., 2009; Kerosuo and Bronner-Fraser, 2012). 
The neural crest (NC) provides a good model system for 
studying the molecular mechanisms underlying EMT in a non-
malignant environment. Neural crest progenitors first express de-
finitive specification markers, including EMT genes like Snail2, 
in the dorsal midline of the neural tube before initiating emigra-
tion in amniotes (Nieto et al., 1994). Shortly thereafter, NC cells </p>

<p>commence EMT and subsequently migrate to distant sites where 
they differentiate into numerous derivatives. Despite the similari-
ties in morphology and gene expression between embryonic and 
cancer cells undergoing EMT, little is known about the functional 
conservation of the underlying molecular pathways. 
During the process of neural crest EMT, the expression 
and cellular localization of adhesion molecules such as cad-
herin 6B (Cad6B) and neural cadherin (Ncad) are highly reg-
ulated (Kerosuo and Bronner-Fraser, 2012). Ncad is expressed 
throughout the apical portion of the neuroepithelium (Akitaya 
and Bronner-Fraser, 1992) but is down-regulated in trunk dorsal 
neural tube cells by the NC specifier gene FoxD3, allowing 
EMT to occur (Cheung et al., 2005; Dady et al., 2012). In can-
cer cells, the process of EMT is highly regulated by a switch 
between the expression of epithelial cadherin (Ecad) and Ncad, 
which is up-regulated in migratory mesenchymal cells (Kuphal 
and Bosserhoff, 2006) and is a common marker of the mesen-
chymal phenotype (Theveneau et al., 2010). Intriguingly, ex-
pression of Ecad recently has been reported in the neural tube 
and early emigrating NC cells in developing embryos, suggest-
ing that it may play a previously unrecognized role in neural </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>he neural crest, an embryonic stem cell population, 
initially resides within the dorsal neural tube but sub-
sequently undergoes an epithelial-to-mesenchymal 
transition (EMT) to commence migration. Although neural 
crest and cancer EMTs are morphologically similar, little is 
known regarding conservation of their underlying molec-
ular mechanisms. We report that Sip1, which is involved 
in cancer EMT, plays a critical role in promoting the neu-
ral crest cell transition to a mesenchymal state. Sip1 tran-
scripts are expressed in premigratory/migrating crest 
cells. After Sip1 loss, the neural crest specifier gene FoxD3 </p>

<p>was abnormally retained in the dorsal neuroepithelium, 
whereas Sox10, which is normally required for emigra-
tion, was diminished. Subsequently, clumps of adherent 
neural crest cells remained adjacent to the neural tube and 
aberrantly expressed E-cadherin while lacking N-cadherin. 
These findings demonstrate two distinct phases of neural 
crest EMT, detachment and mesenchymalization, with the 
latter involving a novel requirement for Sip1 in regula-
tion of cadherin expression during completion of neural 
crest EMT. </p>

<p>Sip1 mediates an E-cadherin-to-N-cadherin switch 
during cranial neural crest EMT </p>

<p>Crystal D. Rogers, Ankur Saxena, and Marianne E. Bronner </p>

<p>Division of Biology 139-74, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA 91125 </p>

<p>© 2013 Rogers et al. This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution-
Noncommercial-Share Alike-No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the pub-
lication date (see http://www.rupress.org/terms). After six months it is available under a 
Creative Commons License (Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, 
as described at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). </p>

<p>T H E J O U R N A L O F C E L L B I O L O G Y </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 203 • NUMBER 5 • 2013 
836 </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Sip1 expression during neurulation and 
neural crest development </p>

<p>To determine the spatiotemporal pattern of Sip1 expression dur-
ing early chick development, we performed whole-mount in situ 
hybridization. Sip1 transcripts are barely detectable in the pre-
sumptive neural plate at Hamburger Hamilton stage 4 (HH4; 
Fig. 1 A) but become strongly expressed in this region by HH5 
(Fig. 1 B). As neurulation begins, Sip1 is expressed throughout 
the neural plate at HH7 (Fig. 1, C and c). Expression increases 
at HH8 and HH8, just before neural crest EMT (Fig. 1, D 
and E). As NC cells begin to emigrate at HH9, Sip1 expression is 
maintained in the neural tube and also is present in the newly mi-
gratory NC cells (Fig. 1, F and f). By HH12, Sip1 is observed in 
the migratory cranial crest and in the rhombomere 4 migratory 
stream (Fig. 1, G and g; arrow), as evidenced by its overlap with 
the HNK-1 epitope, characteristic of migratory NC cells (Fig. 1 g, 
bottom). Sip1 transcripts are maintained throughout the develop-
ing central nervous system and migratory crest at HH12 and 
HH16 (Fig. 1, G and H), analogous to Sip1 protein expression 
(Fig. 1 g). Taken together, these results show that Sip1 is 
expressed throughout early stages of NC development. </p>

<p>Sip1 is required for the acquisition of </p>

<p>mesenchymal morphology and completion of </p>

<p>cranial neural crest EMT </p>

<p>We tested the functional role of Sip1 in NC development by 
electroporating a translation-blocking morpholino into the neu-
ral plate border region of gastrulating (HH4) embryos, corre-
sponding to the onset of endogenous Sip1 expression, and 
examined subsequent effects on neural crest development at 
HH8-13, corresponding with the expression of neural crest 
specifier genes and the end of migration in the cranial regions. 
At HH8, we examined the effects on expression of the 
early neural crest specifier gene, FoxD3, as well as neural genes, 
to determine whether the loss of Sip1 affected either neural 
or neural crest specification. Mulitplex NanoString analysis as 
well as in situ hybridization at HH8 revealed an early down-
regulation of FoxD3 expression after Sip1MO loss, but this 
decrease appeared to be very transient, recovering by HH9 
(Fig. S1, A-D). Similarly, the loss of Sip1 had little or no effect 
on neural specification, except for a slight change in ERNI at 
HH8 (Fig. S1, E-I). 
Because there appeared to be no prolonged effect on spec-
ification, we next examined whether the loss of Sip1 might in-
fluence neural crest EMT, which begins at HH9, by examining 
expression of FoxD3 and Sox10. In embryos lacking Sip1, FoxD3 
expression was abnormally maintained in the dorsal neural tube 
(Fig. 2, A and a; n = 19/33). At stages when NC cells should be 
undergoing EMT and leaving the neural tube, the loss of Sip1 
also resulted in a decrease in Sox10 expression (Fig. 2 B; n = 
25/29), normally required for migration to commence. Dem-
onstrating specificity, we found that co-electroporation of 
Sip1MO plus mRNA encoding human Zeb2/Sip1 DNA (Ellis 
et al., 2010) could partially rescue the loss of Sox10 expres-
sion (Fig. 2 C; n = 10/21). </p>

<p>crest EMT (Kuphal and Bosserhoff, 2006; Dady et al., 2012). At 
midbrain levels, Snail2 directly represses Cad6B, which is a 
prerequisite for EMT progression (Coles et al., 2007). Snail2 
functions in a complex with the adaptor protein PHD12 to re-
cruit HDAC to the Cad6B promoter (Strobl-Mazzulla and 
Bronner, 2012). Surprisingly, however, mice that are double 
mutant for Snail1 and Snail2 in the NC do not have an obvious 
neural crest phenotype (Murray et al., 2007). This result sug-
gests that at least in mice, other EMT mediators may be able to 
compensate for the lack of Snail genes. 
One candidate that may compensate for the loss of Snail2 
is the basic helix-loop-helix transcription factor, Twist, which is 
known to have functional redundancy with Snail2 during meso-
derm development in Drosophila and mesoderm and NC induc-
tion in Xenopus (Zhang and Klymkowsky, 2009). In frog, Twist 
physically interacts with Snail1/2 during NC development 
(Lander et al., 2013). Twist is post-transcriptionally regulated by 
an F-box protein, Partner of Paired, which also regulates the 
levels of other EMT factors, suggesting that there is a con-
served mechanism regulating the proteins that control the pro-
cess of EMT (Lander et al., 2011). In addition, Twist has been 
demonstrated as one of the major factors involved in cancer cell 
EMT due to its ability to repress the expression of Ecad (Kang 
and Massagué, 2004). However, Twist is not highly expressed in 
the premigratory or migrating NC of amniotes (Bothe et al., 
2007) or lamprey embryos (Sauka-Spengler et al., 2007). More-
over, the NC defects observed in Twist1-null mice (Chen et al., 
2007) appear to be secondarily caused by the loss of Twist in the 
adjacent mesoderm (Chen and Behringer, 1995; Bildsoe et al., 
2013). These findings suggest that, in amniotes at least, EMT fac-
tors other than Snail and Twist must be playing an important 
role in the regulation of NC development. 
Another factor implicated in cancer progression and metas-
tasis is Smad-interacting protein 1 (Sip1), which is a two-handed 
zinc finger transcriptional repressor (Verschueren et al., 1999; 
Brabletz and Brabletz, 2010). Sip1 has been postulated to play an 
important role in the transition of epithelial tumors to metastatic 
cancers (Brabletz and Brabletz, 2010). Similar to the Snail pro-
teins, Sip1 has been shown to directly bind to and repress Ecad 
expression in cancer cells, thus facilitating EMT (Comijn et al., 
2001). During embryonic development, Sip1 can function down-
stream of the BMP signaling pathway as a co-regulator with 
R-Smad proteins and CtBP, or it can function independent of 
BMP signaling to repress transcription of its targets (van Grunsven 
et al., 2007). Although there have been several studies regarding its 
role in early development (van Grunsven et al., 2000; Sheng et al., 
2003; Nitta et al., 2007; Delalande et al., 2008; Lander et al., 2011), 
little is known about the function of Sip1 during neural crest EMT. 
Here, we examine the role of Sip1 in the transition of neuro-
epithelial cells to mesenchymal NC cells in avian embryos. The data 
suggest that neural crest EMT is a two-step process in which cells 
first detach from the neural tube and then subsequently disassociate 
from each other to become migratory mesenchymal cells. Our data 
reveal that, while not required for NC cells to exit the neural tube, 
Sip1 is required for cells to become fully mesenchymal, and that their 
inability to complete EMT in Sip1's absence appears to involve the 
dysregulation of the adhesion molecules Ecad and Ncad. </p>

<p> 
Sip1 regulates cadherin switch in neural crest EMT • Rogers et al. </p>

<p>ContMO-injected side of the same embryo, with the latter ap-
pearing to have advanced much farther (Fig. 2, D and d; n = 
9/10). HNK1 staining confirmed that Sip1MO-injected cells 
were indeed able to delaminate from the neural tube but were 
unable to progress and migrate; instead, they remained attached 
to each other and/or to the ectoderm (not depicted). Similar </p>

<p>To further explore this phenotype, we examined the ex-
pression of Pax7 protein as a nuclear marker for premigratory 
and early migrating NC cells, and HNK1 as a cell surface 
marker for migrating NC cells. At HH10, migratory Pax7+ neural 
crest cells appeared clustered a short distance from the neural 
tube on the morpholino-injected side compared with the </p>

<p>Figure 1. Sip1 is expressed in the developing neural and neural crest cells. (A-H) Whole-mount in situ hybridization of chick embryos at various stages 
using an antisense probe to Sip1 reveals expression in the developing neural plate (A-C), neural tube (D-H), and premigratory and migratory NC cells 
(F-H) at stages HH4-HH16. Sections of embryos at indicated axial level are marked by dashed lines (c, f, and g). Sip1 is expressed throughout the 
neural plate, neural tube, and in migratory NC cells (arrow). (g) Top panel is Sip1 expression and bottom panel is HNK1 expression in same section 
showing overlap with migratory cells (arrow). (g) Whole-mount immunohistochemistry showing that Sip1 protein is localized to the same tissues as Sip1 
transcript. Bars: (A-H) 200 µm; (c-g)100 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 203 • NUMBER 5 • 2013 </p>

<p>
To examine this process in the absence of other cell types, 
cranial neural tubes that were treated with either ContMO or 
Sip1MO were dissected from HH8 embryos and cultured on 
fibronectin-coated tissue culture dishes. Immunostaining with 
the HNK1 antibody demonstrated that the Sip1MO-electroporated 
neural crest cells were able to separate from the neural tube 
tissue (Fig. 3 G; n = 8/8; halo of migrating neural crest cells in-
dicated by dotted line) and up-regulate the HNK1 epitope, but 
unable to individualize and instead remained closely adherent 
to each other (Fig. 3, compare G-g with H-h). In contrast, 
NC cells from ContMO explants were highly migratory and dis-
played mesenchymal cell morphology. Similar to the in vivo 
findings, these results lend further support to the idea that Sip1 
is required for NC cells to complete the process of EMT. </p>

<p>Live imaging of the dorsal neural </p>

<p>tube after Sip1 knockdown </p>

<p>To identify the morphological changes that occur in NC cells lack-
ing Sip1 during EMT, we performed live imaging (Videos 1-6). 
HH4 embryos were electroporated with either FITC-tagged 
Sip1MO (Video 1) or ContMO (Video 4) along with membrane-
localized mem-RFP DNA to better visualize cell shapes and move-
ment. At HH9-10, these embryos were visualized via time-lapse 
confocal microscopy in order to examine the behavior of cells lack-
ing Sip1 as they exited the neural tube and began migrating. </p>

<p>phenotypes were observed for electroporations performed at 
HH4-HH7 (Fig. S2, A and B), though the phenotype was less 
marked when Sip1 was knocked down at HH7 (Fig. S2 C). 
Taken together, these data suggest that Sip1-depleted NC cells 
are able to delaminate from the neural tube but then fail to com-
plete the process of EMT and become mesenchymal cells, as 
defined by their migratory characteristics. 
Embryos were then analyzed by in situ hybridization at 
stages of active neural crest migration (HH10) for expression 
of Sox10 and FoxD3, both of which are expressed in migrating 
neural crest cells. In contrast to control morpholino (ContMO)-
injected embryos (Fig. 3, A and C) or the uninjected contra-
lateral side, Sip1 morpholino (Sip1MO)-treated embryos had 
diminished Sox10 expression indicative of a reduction in mi-
grating neural crest cells (Fig. 3, B and b; n = 11/13), while 
aberrantly maintaining expression of FoxD3 in the dorsal neural 
tube (Fig. 3, D and d; n = 7/10). This suggests an important role 
for Sip1 in progression of the normal neural crest program. To 
analyze whether this phenotype persists, embryos were allowed 
to develop until HH13, by which time cranial NC emigration 
from the neural tube is complete. Even at these late stages, NC 
cells remained closely adherent to the dorsal neural tube and 
ectoderm after Sip1 knockdown (Fig. 3 E; n = 4/5, arrow). The 
efficiency of Sip1 protein knockdown by the morpholino was 
verified by Western blot analysis (Fig. 3 F). </p>

<p>Figure 2. Loss of Sip1 affects neural crest gene expression. (A) Whole-mount in situ hybridization with a probe for FoxD3 in embryos electroporated with 
Sip1 morpholino (MO) on the right side and analyzed at HH9. A section of an embryo in A showing FoxD3 expression (a) after Sip1MO injection marked 
by FITC (a). FoxD3 is up-regulated on the Sip1MO side (n = 19/33). (B and C) Whole-mount in situ hybridization with a probe for Sox10 in embryos 
electroporated with (B) ContMO (left side) and Sip1MO (right side) showing loss of Sox10 expression (n = 25/29), or (C) Sip1MO (left side) and Sip1MO + 
Zeb2 DNA showing rescue of that loss (C; n = 10/21). (D) Immunohistochemistry for Pax7 in embryos with ContMO on the left side and Sip1 MO on the 
right side (green is FITC from ContMO on left and Sip1MO on right). (d) A section from embryo, in D as indicated by dashed line, showing maintenance 
of Pax7 expression in premigratory cells but fewer migratory cells (n = 9/10). Right panel is overlay with ContMO and Sip1MO FITC. Bars: (A-d) 200 µm. 
The data shown here are from a single representative experiment out of at least three repeats. </p>

<p> 
Sip1 regulates cadherin switch in neural crest EMT • Rogers et al. </p>

<p>neural tube. This is further evident in a transverse section of an 
HH9 embryo injected on both sides with membrane plus nuclear 
RFP and on one side with Sip1MO (Fig. 4, I and J). Whereas NC 
cells on the control side are spread out (Fig. 4, I and J; left), those 
on the morpholino-injected side appear stuck together such that it 
is difficult to distinguish individual cell bodies (Fig. 4, I and J; right, 
arrows). The inability of the Sip1-depleted cells to detach from 
each other despite their ability to delaminate and exit from the neu-
ral tube suggests that the loss of Sip1 may alter NC cell-cell adhe-
sive behavior in a manner that perturbs their mesenchymalization. </p>

<p>Loss of Sip1 increases E-cadherin levels </p>

<p>in the ectoderm and migratory NC </p>

<p>Under normal conditions, expression of adhesion molecules is 
tightly regulated during EMT. Thus, the observation that 
Sip1MO-electroporated cells failed to disaggregate raised the </p>

<p>The results show that Sip1MO-electroporated cells are able 
to leave the neural tube and migrate laterally but then tend to ag-
gregate near the midline, likely due to increased cell-cell adhesion 
(Video 2, asterisks). In comparison to control embryos, these cells 
maintain more of their cell-cell connections, lose directionality, 
and fail to migrate far (Videos 1-3; n = 5). The cells exhibit a lead-
ing edge (LE), but the LE does not move consistently away from 
the midline as in ContMO-electroporated cells (Videos 4-6), 
which are able to separate from the midline, separate from each 
other, and migrate directionally (Video 4 and Video 5; n = 4). Cell 
tracking indicated that the cells lacking Sip1 travel a short distance 
and without proper directionality (Fig. 4 C) when compared with 
ContMO-injected cells (Fig. 4 G), which migrate linearly and gen-
erally laterally away from the embryonic midline. Ultimately, 
Sip1-depleted NC cells remain adherent to each other (compare 
Video 3 with Video 6), forming clumps of cells adjacent to the </p>

<p>Figure 3. Loss of Sip1 prevents the completion of neural crest EMT. Whole-mount in situ hybridization of embryos electroporated with ContMO (A and C) 
or Sip1MO (B and D) at HH4 and collected at HH10. A and B, Sox10 expression; C and D, FoxD3 expression. While ContMO-electroporated embryos 
have normal expression of both genes, Sip1-electroporated embryos exhibit decreased expression of (B) Sox10 in the migratory crest (n = 11/13) and 
aberrantly maintain (D) FoxD3 in the dorsal neural tube (n = 7/10). (b-d) Sections from levels indicated by dotted lines in B and D. (E) In situ hybrid-
ization for Sox10 on an HH13 embryo electroporated at HH4 with Sip1MO showing a maintenance of neural crest near the midline at the level of the 
midbrain (asterisk; n = 4/5). (F) Western blot analysis of Sip1 protein expression in HH9-10 embryos after injection of 1 mM ContMO, 1 mM Sip1MO, 
and 2 mM Sip1MO showing that Sip1 protein expression is greatly reduced after Sip1MO electroporation. The data shown here are representative of one 
experiment out of three repeats. In this experiment, protein was pooled from 8-10 chicken whole embryos. (G and H) Whole-mount immunohistochemistry 
for HNK1 (magnification of 10) comparing neural tube explants from embryos electroporated with either (G) Sip1MO (n = 8/8) or (H) ContMO (n = 6/6) 
showing lack of migration and clumping phenotype. Dashed lines indicate distance migrated by furthest cells from the explant. Explants are overlaid 
with bright-field images. (g and h) A 40× image from dashed box in explants (G and H, respectively) demonstrating HNK1-positive cells that are either 
clumped outside of the neural tube in Sip1MO-injected explants (g) or that have migrated away from the ContMO-injected explant (h). (g and h) High 
magnification image of explants showing HNK1 expression and Sip1MO or ContMO alone showing that HNK1-positive cells are clumped next to the 
explant (g, white arrows) or have migrated away from the explant (h, white arrowhead). Bars: (A-E) 200 µm; (b-d) 150 µm; (G and H) 100 µm; and 
(g and h) 30 µm. The data shown here are from a single representative experiment out of at least three repeats. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 203 • NUMBER 5 • 2013 </p>

<p>
To analyze the effect of Sip1 knockdown on Ecad protein 
expression, we performed Western blot analysis of heads dis-
sected from embryos that were either injected with ContMO or 
Sip1MO (Fig. 5 C). Consistent with our qPCR results, Ecad pro-
tein levels were increased in Sip1MO-injected embryos com-
pared with ContMO embryos. To verify that the Ecad transcript 
levels were up-regulated in the neural tube, we performed whole-
mount in situ hybridization using an Ecad probe. Embryos in-
jected with Sip1MO exhibited a strong up-regulation of Ecad 
expression in the neural tube compared with the contralateral 
side (Fig. 5 D; n = 8/10). Next, we performed immunohisto-
chemistry to localize Ecad protein after Sip1MO knockdown. To 
this end, ContMO was electroporated into the left side of HH4 
embryos, concurrent with the electroporation of Sip1MO into the 
right side of the same embryo. There was a marked up-regulation 
of Ecad protein expression in both the ectoderm and the migratory </p>

<p>possibility that loss of Sip1 may affect expression of one or 
more adhesion molecule(s). To test this, we quantitated the 
effects of Sip1 knockdown on various transcripts, including 
adhesion molecules, known to be involved in NC develop-
ment, using the NanoString nCounter system (Fig. 5 A). The 
results show that the expression of three adhesion molecules 
was significantly altered by loss of Sip1 (Fig. 5 A; n = 3). 
Whereas Ecad expression was up-regulated in cells lacking 
Sip1, Ncad and cadherin 7 (Cad7) were down-regulated. To 
further verify the effect of Sip1 knockdown on the expression of 
Ecad, we performed quantitative RT-PCR on dissected neural 
tubes plus adjacent neural crest cells, comparing the Con-
tMO-and Sip1MO-injected sides of the same embryos. The re-
sults show that the Sip1MO-injected side expressed Ecad at a 
twofold higher level than the ContMO-injected side (Fig. 5 B; 
n = 4, P &lt; 0.036). </p>

<p>Figure 4. Neural crest cells lacking Sip1 exhibit reductions in detachment, directional migration, and overall displacement. Time-lapse imaging of the 
midbrain regions of living embryos starting at HH10. (A and B) Snapshots of embryos electroporated with Sip1MO-FITC + pCS2-memRFP show electropor-
ated cells that are able to delaminate from the neural tube (NT) and migrate laterally (LE, leading edge). However, they remain connected to each other 
(asterisks) near the midline and form clumps of cells relative to ContMO-injected cells (E and F). (C and D) Cell tracking and net displacement over time 
(t = 295 min) shows that Sip1MO-injected cells are unable to migrate long distances away from the midline and in a directional manner as is seen in Con-
tMO embryos (G and H; t = 245 min). (H) Displacement of ContMO-injected cells demonstrates that NC cells near the LE actively migrate away from the 
midline while the NT appears to move away from the NC cells due to growth and movement. (I and J) Confocal imaging of a histological section from an 
embryo electroporated on the left side with memRFP + nucRFP and on the right side with Sip1MO + memRFP + nucRFP reveals that Sip1MO-treated cells remain 
clumped next to the midline (arrows). NT, neural tube; LE, leading edge. (C and G) white dots represent final time points for each track. (A and B) z = 8 µm; 
(E and F) z = 10 µm; (I and J) z = 6 µm. Bars, 30 µm. See also Videos 1-6. The data shown are representative of multiple repeats (experiment was repeated 
five [Sip1MO] and four [ContMO] times). </p>

<p> 
Sip1 regulates cadherin switch in neural crest EMT • Rogers et al. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Sip1 knockdown leads to maintenance of Ecad protein in migratory NC cells. (A) Multiplex NanoString analysis of transcripts from neural tubes 
dissected from HH9 embryos, comparing the Sip1MO electroporated side to the control side of the same embryo. The results show that Ecad mRNA levels 
are up-regulated while Ncad and Cad7 are reduced (n = 3). The data shown here are representative of three separate experiments with the changes in 
transcript data pooled. (B) Quantitative RT-PCR analysis of neural tubes plus migratory crest cells dissected from HH9 embryos that were electroporated on 
the left side with ContMO (C) and on the right side with Sip1MO (S) at HH4. Ecad gene expression was compared with GAPDH expression. Error bars 
are standard deviation between samples and P &lt; 0.036 (asterisk indicates statistical significance; n = 4). The data shown here are one representative 
experiment with expression data from four embryos, and this was repeated four times. (C) Western blot analysis of Ecad protein expression after the injec-
tion of 1 mM ContMO and 1 mM Sip1MO showing that Ecad protein expression is increased after Sip1MO electroporation. The data shown here are 
representative of one experiment out of three repeats. In this experiment, protein was pooled from 8-10 chicken whole embryos. -Tubulin was used as a 
loading control. (D) In situ hybridization using a probe for Ecad shows that it is ectopically expressed in the neural tube after Sip1 knockdown (asterisk). 
Embryo injected on right side as indicated by asterisk. (E and F) Whole-mount immunohistochemistry for Ecad in midbrain sections at 40× in HH9 (E) and 
HH15 (F) embryos demonstrates increased sequestration of Ecad protein on the cell membranes on the Sip1MO side compared with the control side (white 
arrowheads). (G and H) To visualize the change in Ecad protein expression in vitro, neural tubes were dissected from HH8 embryos electroporated with 
ContMO on the left side and Sip1MO on the right side at HH4. Explants were cultured for 12-24 h and examined for expression of Ecad and HNK1. 
(G) ContMO-injected migratory neural crest cells express HNK1 (green) but lack Ecad expression (g, white arrows), whereas cells lacking Sip1 (H) emi-
grate from the neural tube explants (marked by white dashed line) but fail to detach from each other or migrate far from the explant (n = 6/8). Additionally, 
the Sip1MO-injected cells co-express HNK1 (green) and Ecad protein (h, white asterisk), suggesting that delamination from the neural tube explant does 
not require Ecad down-regulation, whereas subsequent detachment and migration does. (I and J) Whole-mount immunohistochemistry using an antibody for 
Pax7 in embryos electroporated with (I) ContMO on the left and Sip1 on the right (less migration on right) and (J) Sip1MO + Ecadcatenin on the right 
(recovered migration). Red dashed lines indicate midline and level of section. (i) A section through the embryo in panel I demonstrating clumped Pax7-
positive cells on the Sip1MO-injected side. (i) An overlay of Pax7 and FITC from ContMO and Sip1MO. (j) A section of the embryo from J demonstrating 
recovered Pax7-positive cells on the Sip1MO + Ecad-catenin-injected side. (j) An overlay of Pax7 and FITC Sip1MO. Bars: (D-J) 100 µm; (g-h) 30 µm; 
(i-j) 50 µm. The whole-mount and section data shown here are from a single representative experiment out of at least three repeats. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 203 • NUMBER 5 • 2013 </p>

<p>
migration as analyzed by Snail2 expression (Fig. 6, E-e; 
n = 12/14), Sip1MO + Ncad led to a partial rescue of NC migra-
tory ability, demonstrated by similar numbers and migratory abil-
ity of Snail2+ cells on experimental and control sides (Fig. 6, 
F-f). However, the addition of exogenous Ncad failed to com-
pletely restore the mesenchymal morphology of NC cells, and 
the Snail2+ migratory NC cells remained clumped together on 
the injected but not the uninjected side (Fig. 6, f and f; n = 10/14). 
Co-expression of Ncad appears to decrease the levels of Ecad 
protein in the Sip1MO-injected cells, thus partially restoring nor-
mal Ecad protein levels in the premigratory cells (Fig. 6, G and H; 
n = 8/11), perhaps explaining its ability to rescue the phenotype. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Numerous EMT factors have been implicated in cell transfor-
mation and metastasis in various types of cancer (Kang and 
Massagué, 2004; Thiery et al., 2009; Kerosuo and Bronner-
Fraser, 2012). For example, the Sip1/Zeb, Snail, and Twist 
transcription factor families are highly linked to tumor metasta-
sis (Sánchez-Tilló et al., 2012). However, much less is known 
about the role of these EMT factors in vivo during embryonic 
EMTs. Moreover, the same transcription factors appear to have 
divergent functions in different vertebrates, highlighting the 
need for better clarification of the molecular pathways driving 
developmental EMT. 
During embryogenesis, Sip1 functions at multiple time 
points and in varied processes that are seemingly unrelated to 
EMT. The N terminus zinc-finger domain is required for neural 
induction in frog embryos (Eisaki et al., 2000; van Grunsven et al., 
2000; Sheng et al., 2003), whereas the C terminus zinc finger do-
main is required for repression of Xenopus brachyury (Xbra/ 
Tbx6) to maintain the separation of neural and mesodermal tis-
sues (Sheng et al., 2003; Nitta et al., 2007). Sip1 is also required 
for normal anterior-posterior patterning in zebrafish (Delalande 
et al., 2008). It has also been linked to the regulation of adhesion 
molecules during EMT in the heart, and appears to be regulated 
by olfactomedin-1 for cell invasion (Lencinas et al., 2013). At 
later stages, dysregulated Sip1 has been associated with the vagal 
neurocristopathies, Mowat-Wilson syndrome and Hirschsprung's 
disease (Wakamatsu et al., 2001). 
Adding to its developmental functions, the present study 
shows that Sip1 is required for cranial NC cells to complete 
the process of EMT. Our results also highlight that there are 
at least two discrete steps required for the process of cranial 
neural crest EMT: detachment from the neural tube and sub-
sequent separation of NC cells from the epidermis and each 
other. After loss of Sip1, NC cells are able to complete the first 
step but not the second. Although they exit the neural tube, 
they remain rounded and clumped together outside of the neu-
ral tube and are unable to detach from each other, preventing 
the rearrangements that are required to navigate through the 
ECM. This phenotype is likely due to increased expression of 
Ecad in the epidermis and migratory NC cells and the con-
comitant decrease in Ncad in the neural tube and therefore in 
the migratory crest cells (Fig. 7). These data suggest that the </p>

<p>NC cells on the Sip1MO side compared with the control side of 
the same embryo (Fig. 5 E; n = 26/30). Cells lacking Sip1 ap-
peared to maintain expression of Ecad on all surfaces, consistent 
with the observed increase in cell-cell adhesion and rounded 
cellular morphology. This phenotype was observed in older em-
bryos as well (Fig. 5 F; n = 4/5). As late as HH12-13, these cells 
maintained high levels of Ecad protein and remained con-
nected to one another. In neural tube explants (Fig. 5, G and H), 
ContMO NC cells emigrated out of the neural tube explant 
and down-regulated Ecad protein in migratory cells that ex-
pressed the HNK1 epitope (Fig. 5 g). However, cells lacking Sip1 
remained close to the neural tube, failed to become mesenchy-
mal (Fig. 5, H and h), and maintained Ecad protein expression 
while expressing HNK1 (Fig. 5 h). 
Because of the observed reciprocal relationship between 
Sip1 and Ecad, we predicted that simultaneous knockdown of 
both Sip1 and Ecad might rescue the phenotype. To test this pos-
sibility, we co-electroporated Sip1MO while blocking Ecad func-
tion via a dominant-negative form of human Ecad that lacks the 
-catenin binding domain (Ecad-cat) (Gottardi et al., 2001). 
Embryos were injected with (1) ContMO on the left side and 
Sip1MO on the right side (Fig. 5 I) or (2) Sip1MO + Ecad-
cat on the right side (Fig. 5 J). The resultant phenotypes were 
characterized using antibodies against Pax7 (Fig. 5, I and J) and 
Snail2 (not depicted), which are expressed in the nuclei of premi-
gratory and migrating cranial NC cells. As expected, Sip1 knock-
down resulted in a failure of NC cells to move far from the neural 
tube (Fig. 5, I and i; n = 13/17, right side) when compared with 
the ContMO-injected side. In contrast, co-electroporation of 
Sip1MO + Ecad-cat was able to partially rescue the Sip1MO 
phenotype (Fig. 5, J and j; n = 10/13), with the Pax7-positive migra-
tory cells emigrating earlier and farther from the neural tube. These 
findings support an epistatic relationship between Sip1 and Ecad. </p>

<p>Sip1 knockdown reduces </p>

<p>N-cadherin expression </p>

<p>In addition to Ecad, several other cadherins are expressed at the 
time of NC emigration, including Cad6B and Ncad (Akitaya 
and Bronner-Fraser, 1992; Nakagawa and Takeichi, 1998; 
Coles et al., 2007; Shoval et al., 2007; Dady et al., 2012; Strobl-
Mazzulla and Bronner, 2012). Interestingly, we observed a sig-
nificant decrease in Ncad transcript and protein expression in 
the dorsal neural tube after Sip1 knockdown. This reduction was 
confirmed by qPCR (Fig. 6 A; n = 4, P = 0.046), Western blot 
analysis (Fig. 6 B), whole-mount in situ hybridization (Fig. 6 C, 
inset; n = 16/19) and immunohistochemistry (Fig. 6 D; n = 21/23). 
Each assay revealed a decrease in Ncad expression on the 
Sip1MO-injected side compared with the ContMO or uninjected 
side of the same embryo. In contrast, loss of Sip1 protein did not 
increase Cad6B gene or protein expression at midbrain levels, but 
did somewhat delay the expression of Cad6B transcript without 
significantly affecting protein levels (Fig. S3). 
Finally, we tested if concurrently knocking down Sip1 and 
overexpressing full-length chicken Ncad (Shiau and Bronner-
Fraser, 2009) at HH4 would rescue the loss-of-function pheno-
type. Whereas Sip1MO alone caused a decrease in neural crest </p>

<p> 
Sip1 regulates cadherin switch in neural crest EMT • Rogers et al. </p>

<p>Cells lacking Sip1 are able to delaminate from the neural 
tube but cannot detach from each other, due to an increase in their 
cell-cell adhesion (Figs. 3 and 4). Our data suggest that Sip1 me-
diates adhesive changes by regulating Ecad transcript expression 
and perhaps protein localization in early migratory avian NC 
cells. Knockdown of Sip1 leads to the up-regulation or main-
tenance of Ecad transcripts and protein in the epidermis, neu-
ral tube, and migratory NC cells in vivo (Fig. 5, A-F). In vitro, 
Ecad is absent from HNK1+ migrating NC cells in control ex-
plants but highly and aberrantly expressed on the cell surface of 
migrating crest cells after the loss of Sip1 (Fig. 5, G and H). The 
latter fail to disassociate from each other, preventing the comple-
tion of EMT. Sip1 is a well-characterized direct repressor of 
Ecad expression in cancer metastasis and during embryonic de-
velopment (Comijn et al., 2001; Wakamatsu et al., 2001). How-
ever, in early avian development, Sip1 and Ecad transcripts 
overlap in expression (Dady et al., 2012). Thus, the ability of 
Sip1 to act as a repressor of Ecad expression may be stage-
dependent and related to the availability of cofactors that may 
differ as a function of time. In the mouse, expression of Sip1 
and Ecad appear to be mutually exclusive (Wakamatsu et al., 
2001). However, in chicken embryos the expression of endogenous </p>

<p>switch between Ecad and Ncad in NC cells likely plays a criti-
cal role in completing EMT and creating functionally motile, 
mesenchymal NC cells. </p>

<p>Sip1 is required to reduce Ecad 
in migratory NC cells </p>

<p>The expression of adhesion molecules undergoes a well-
documented transition that appears to be tightly regulated to 
allow for normal neural crest EMT (Kerosuo and Bronner-
Fraser, 2012). It was previously thought that Ncad and Cad6B 
were the two most critical adhesion molecules involved in neu-
ral crest EMT; both are expressed at the onset of EMT and are 
down-regulated in the dorsal neural tube, facilitating cranial 
neural crest detachment from the neural tube (Nakagawa and 
Takeichi, 1998). Furthermore, maintenance of Cad6B in the 
dorsal neural tube leads to EMT defects (Coles et al., 2007; 
Strobl-Mazzulla and Bronner, 2012). In the present study, how-
ever, we find that Cad6B is unaffected after Sip1 knockdown 
(Fig. S3). Instead, Ecad, which is expressed on the apical side of the 
neural tube epithelium as well as in the early migratory NC (Dady 
et al., 2012), appears to play a critical role, paralleling the situa-
tion in many types of cancer cells (Sivertsen et al., 2006). </p>

<p>Figure 6. Ncad expression is reduced in cells lacking Sip1. (A) Quantitative PCR analysis of neural tubes and migratory crest cells dissected from HH9 
embryos that were electroporated on the left side with ContMO and on the right side with Sip1MO at HH4. Ncad expression was compared with GAPDH 
expression. Error bars are standard deviation between samples and P &lt; 0.046 (n = 4). The data shown here are one representative experiment with 
expression data from four embryos, and this was repeated four times. Asterisk indicates statistical significance. (B) Western blot analysis of Ncad protein 
expression after the injection of 1 mM ContMO and 1 mM Sip1MO showing that Ncad protein expression is decreased after Sip1MO electroporation. 
-Tubulin was used as a loading control. The data shown here are representative of one experiment out of two repeats. In this experiment, protein was 
pooled from 8-10 chicken whole embryos. (C) Whole-mount in situ hybridization for Ncad expression in embryos lacking Sip1 on the right side shows a 
decrease in Ncad. (D) Confocal image of a section from an embryo, electroporated with ContMO on the left side and Sip1MO (green) on the right side, 
showing decrease in Ncad protein (red) expression (Z = 8 µm). (E and F) Whole-mount immunohistochemistry using an antibody for Snail2 of an embryo 
electroporated with (E) Sip1MO on the right side or (F) Sip1MO + Ncad-GFP DNA on the right side. Snail2 expression is reduced in the Sip1MO-injected 
cells, and this effect is rescued by co-electroporation of Sip1MO + Ncad-GFP cells. (e) A section from the embryo in E showing loss of Snail2 protein. 
(e) Overlay of Snail2 and Sip1MO. (f) A section from the embryo in F at the level indicated by dashed white line shows that although Snail2 appears 
reduced in whole mount, Snail2 expression and numbers of migratory NC cells are partially rescued. (G) Whole-mount immunohistochemistry using an 
antibody to Ecad on an embryo electroporated with Sip1MO + Ncad-GFP DNA on the right side shows that although Ecad protein is still increased on the 
injected side, it is at a lower level in the cells injected with high levels of Ncad-GFP and Sip1MO (indicated by dashed circle and white arrow) than with 
Sip1MO alone. Bars: (C and D) 30 µm; (E and F) 200 µm; (e and f) 100 µm; and (G and H) 50 µm. The whole-mount and section data shown here are 
from a single representative experiment out of at least three repeats. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 203 • NUMBER 5 • 2013 </p>

<p>
Several possible mechanisms may account for the indirect 
down-regulation of Ncad after Sip1 loss of function. In addition 
to its transcriptional role, Sip1 has been shown to inhibit BMP 
signaling (van Grunsven et al., 2007). In turn, BMP in the dorsal 
neural tube has been reported to down-regulate Ncad protein 
(Shoval et al., 2007). Thus, after loss of Sip1, BMP signaling may 
continue in dorsal neural tube cells, thereby inhibiting Ncad pro-
duction. Consistent with this possibility, our NanoString data 
show that BMP4 transcripts are slightly up-regulated in the dorsal 
neural tube (Fig. 5 A). A second possibility is that up-regulation 
of both membrane-bound and cytoplasmic Ecad may lead to a 
decrease in Ncad expression, as has been reported in melanoma 
cells lines (Kuphal and Bosserhoff, 2006). Finally, the observed 
maintenance of FoxD3 expression in the cranial dorsal neural 
tube (Figs. 2 D and 3 A) may lead to aberrant repression of 
Ncad gene expression. In the trunk NC, which differs from cra-
nial crest in its EMT program, FoxD3 has been shown to inhibit 
expression of Ncad while up-regulating integrin 1, laminin, 
and Cad7 (Cheung et al., 2005). Although these observations 
were made at a different axial level, our finding that Sip1 up-
regulates FoxD3 but down-regulates Ncad is consistent with 
these previous findings and may suggest that Sip1 indirectly 
regulates Ncad via FoxD3. 
In summary, we show that Sip1, one of the best-characterized 
cancer EMT-related proteins, is also required for progression of 
the normal program that regulates neural crest EMT. We find 
that NC EMT is a two-step process requiring: (1) detachment 
from the neural tube and (2) a subsequent ability to separate 
from other NC cells. Sip1 plays a role in the second phase of 
NC EMT by inversely regulating adhesion molecules Ecad 
and Ncad in the migratory NC. This switch in cadherins is criti-
cal for NC cell EMT and strikingly similar to that observed dur-
ing cancer metastasis as well as other EMTs such as those 
during cardiac development (Lencinas et al., 2013). Thus, the 
key role of Sip1 in regulating transcriptional and potential 
post-translational events is likely to have significant implica-
tions for understanding EMT in both developmental and onco-
logical contexts. </p>

<p>Ecad transcript and protein is maintained in the apical neural tube 
cells and early migratory crest until approximately HH10-HH11, 
well after the onset of cranial NC EMT (Dady et al., 2012). 
Our results show that NC cells lacking Sip1 maintain a high 
level of Ecad protein and therefore are unable to migrate nor-
mally. However, it is interesting to note that emigrating neural 
crest cells do normally express some Ecad protein as they leave 
the neural tube, suggesting a requirement for cell-cell adhesion 
in the early migrating neural crest cells. During studies of cancer 
EMT, there is conflicting evidence about the requirement for the 
down-regulation of adhesion molecules during EMT and metas-
tasis. Recent work by Chui (2013) has suggested that the mesen-
chymal phenotype of cells does not necessarily confer metastasis; 
i.e., cancer cells do not need to undergo full EMT to detach from 
tumors, migrate, and invade other tissues. Our live-imaging stud-
ies (compare Video 1 with Video 2) have shown that even in con-
trol cells that migrate normally, NC cells appear to migrate as a 
transient group that is intermittently, but consistently, in contact 
with the cells that surround them. However, normal neural crest 
migration requires cell rearrangement to navigate through the 
ECM and tissues. Our data show that without Sip1, the cells are 
unable to detach from one another, leading to an inability to com-
plete EMT and navigate through the ECM. </p>

<p>Sip1 is required for Ncad expression </p>

<p>In addition to influencing Ecad levels and distribution, our re-
sults suggest that Sip1 influences Ncad expression. Ncad is nor-
mally expressed throughout the apical portion of the developing 
neural tube before NC EMT (Akitaya and Bronner-Fraser, 1992; 
Nakagawa and Takeichi, 1998). As EMT commences, Ncad is 
down-regulated in the dorsal neural tube. In addition to the full-
length version in the neural tube, there also is a proteolytically 
cleaved variant of Ncad that is expressed in migratory NC and 
functions as an EMT activator (Shoval et al., 2007). After loss of 
Sip1, both Ncad transcript and protein expression are decreased 
(Fig. 6). Despite the excess of Ecad protein that keeps NC cells 
clumped, it is possible that the observed concomitant excess loss 
of Ncad allows for their delamination after Sip1 knockdown. </p>

<p>Figure 7. Diagram showing the effect of Sip1 
knockdown on neural crest EMT. Our results 
show that NC cells undergoing the process 
of EMT go through two separate steps to be-
come fully mesenchymal: (1) detachment from 
the neural tube and (2) separation from the 
ectoderm and dissociation from the other mi-
gratory NC cells. Compared with ContMO 
or untreated NC cells (left side), loss of Sip1 
(right side) has no effect on step 1, but blocks 
step 2 due to the increased cell-cell adhesion 
caused by increased Ecad in the neural tube, 
epidermis, and migratory NC cells (red) and 
the loss of Ncad expression in the neural tube 
and migratory NC cells (orange). These data 
support a critical role for Sip1 in regulation 
of multiple adhesion molecules during neural 
crest EMT. </p>

<p> 
Sip1 regulates cadherin switch in neural crest EMT • Rogers et al. </p>

<p>a MeOH/PTW series at room temperature before being stored at 20°C in 
100% MeOH. Chick in situ hybridization was performed as follows: On 
day 1 embryos were rehydrated in a stepwise manner from 100% MeOH 
to 100% PBS with 0.1% Tween 20. They were then prehybridized in hybrid-
ization buffer (Acloque et al., 2008) for 1 h. The embryos were then hybrid-
ized with the digoxigenin-labeled antisense probes overnight at 65-70°C. 
On day 2 embryos were washed two times for 30 min in 2× SSC buffer, two 
times for 30 min in 0.2× SSC buffer, and two times for 10 min in 1× MAB 
buffer with 0.1% Tween 20 (MABT). Next, embryos were blocked in a solu-
tion of 10% BBR and 10% sheep serum in MABT for 1-3 h. The embryos 
were then incubated with an anti-digoxigenin AP Fab fragments (Roche) in 
blocking solution for either 3 h at room temperature or overnight at 4°C. Em-
bryos were washed three times for 30 min in MABT and signal was visual-
ized using NBT and BCIP stock solutions (Roche) diluted in alkaline 
phosphatase buffer and subsequently fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for 
30 min. The linearized plasmid DNA templates that were used for digoxi-
genin-and fluorescein-labeled RNA probes were Sip1, FoxD3, Sox10, 
Ncad, Ecad, N-Myc, and Sox2. The embryos were imaged in whole mount 
and after were transverse sectioned at 10-25 µm in a cryostat. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry 
Immunohistochemistry for Pax7 (Pax7; Developmental Studies Hybridoma 
Bank [DSHB]), HNK1 (3H5; DSHB), Ncad (MNCD2; DSHB), Cad6B 
(CCD6B-1; DSHB), Sip1 (ARP39141_P050; Aviva Systems Biology), and 
Ecad (610181; BD) was performed as follows: embryos were fixed in 4% 
paraformaldehyde in phosphate buffer for &lt;20 min at room temperature. All 
washes were performed in TBST + Ca 
2+ + 0.5% Triton X-100. Blocking was 
performed with 10% donkey serum in the same buffer. The primary antibodies 
(1:10 for all hybridoma antibodies and 1:1,000 for all others) were incubated 
in the TBST buffer from overnight to 2 d at 4°C and secondary antibodies 
(1:500 to 1:1,000) were applied in the same buffer for either 3 h at room 
temperature or overnight at 4°C. </p>

<p>Live confocal imaging 
Embryos were electroporated with 0.75 mM ContMO or Sip1MO (FITC la-
beled) + 1.5 mg/ml membrane RFP and/or nuclear RFP. They were imaged 
in the Lab-Tek chambered 1.0 borosilicate coverage glass system (Thermo 
Fisher Scientific) coated with &lt;0.5 ml 0.6% low-melt agarose mixed with 
Ringer's solution. Embryos were maintained at 37°C during imaging. A con-
focal microscope (LSM 510 Meta or LSM 710; Carl Zeiss) was used with an 
LD C-Apochromat 40×/1.1 W Corr objective (Carl Zeiss). Time lapses were 
done with a z total = 31 µm to leave space for z-drift. Time points were col-
lected at 5-min intervals. Subsets in the z-plane containing the cells of interest 
were selected for clarity. Collected time-lapse data were registered using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Imaris</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Bitplane</rs>) to account for embryo drift and exported as TIF im-
ages and MOV videos. The registration correction (processed with <rs type="software">Imaris</rs> 
software) for embryo drift results in the changes in movie shapes seen here. 
Cell tracking in <rs type="software">Imaris</rs> was done in the FITC (green) channel. Parameters 
used included a spot diameter of 5.19 µm and the "Connected Compo-
nents" algorithm for tracking. </p>

<p>Neural tube explant assays 
Neural tube explant assays were performed as follows: embryos were elec-
troporated with 0.75 mM ContMO plus PCI carrier DNA on the left side and 
0.75 mM Sip1MO plus PCI carrier DNA on the right side of the same em-
bryo at HH4. Embryos were cultured until HH8 as described previously 
(Sauka-Spengler and Barembaum, 2008). At HH8, the neural tubes were 
dissected out of the embryo in Ringer's solution and subsequently placed in 
in 8-well chamber slides (Sigma-Aldrich) that were coated with 1% fibronec-
tin. The explants were cultured in DMEM with 10% FBS, 2 mM l-glutamine, 
and 100 units of penicillin with 0.1 mg/ml streptomycin and cultured at 
37°C with 0.5% CO 2 from 12-24 h. </p>

<p>Online supplemental material 
Fig. S1 shows transcript analyses using NanoString, qPCR, and in situ hy-
bridization; although Sip1MO slightly delays NC specification, the NC 
cells recover and that neural specification is not affected. Fig. S2 shows 
whole-mount in situ hybridization for Sox10 after Sip1MO electroporation 
at stages HH5, HH6, and HH7 to demonstrate that the loss of Sip1 affects 
NC development when knocked down as late as HH7. Fig. S3 shows in situ 
hybridization and whole-mount immunohistochemistry of Cad6B protein to 
demonstrate that Sip1 knockdown does not affect Cad6B protein expres-
sion. Videos 1-3 are live-imaging confocal movies of a chicken midbrain at 
HH10 after Sip1MO electroporation. Video 1 is Sip1MO-FITC and Video 2 
is memRFP. Video 3 shows a 2.3× image of Video 1 to visualize the cell </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Embryos 
Fertilized chicken eggs were obtained from local commercial sources 
(McIntyre Farms, San Diego, CA) and incubated at 37°C to the desired 
stages according to the criteria of Hamburger and Hamilton (HH). </p>

<p>RNA preparation and qPCR 
RNA was prepared from individual embryos (n = 3-5) using the RNAqueous-
Micro isolation kit (Ambion) following the manufacturer's instructions. The 
obtained RNA was treated with DNaseI amplification grade (Invitrogen) and 
then reverse transcribed to cDNA with SuperScript II (Invitrogen) using ran-
dom hexamers. qPCR was performed using a 96-well plate qPCR machine 
(ABI 7000; Applied Biosystems) with SYBR Green iTaq Supermix with ROX 
(Invitrogen), 150-450 nM of each primer, and 200-500 ng of cDNA in a 
25-µl reaction volume. During the exponential phase of the qPCR reaction, a 
threshold cycle (CT) and baseline was set according to the protocols of Ap-
plied Biosystems. The results for different samples were then analyzed using 
the Livak/CT method, and the Student's t test was used to determine sig-
nificance. There were three replicates for every sample and GAPDH was 
used as a control. </p>

<p>Electroporation of antisense morpholinos and vectors 
A translation blocking antisense morpholino to Sip1 (Sip1MO) was designed 
(5-CATCCGCCATGATCTGCTGCTTCAT-3), and one control morpholino 
(ContMO) was used (5-CCTCTTACCTCAGTTACAATTTATA-3). Injections of 
the fluorescein-tagged morpholinos (0.75-1 mM plus 0.5-1.5 mg/ml of PCI 
carrier plasmid DNA; Voiculescu et al., 2008) were performed by air pres-
sure using a glass micropipette targeted to the presumptive NC region at HH 
stages 4-5. Rescue experiments were performed in the same manner as 
Sip1MO electroporations except that the pCDNA-4/HisMax-hZeb2 (Ellis 
et al., 2010), pCS2-Ncad-GFP (Shiau and Bronner-Fraser, 2009), and 
pcDNA3-Ecad--catenin (Gottardi et al., 2001) plasmids were used 
(1 mg/ml) instead of the PCI carrier plasmid. Stage 4-5 electroporations 
were conducted on whole chick embryo explants placed ventral side up on 
filter paper rings. The Sip1 morpholino and vectors were injected on the right 
side of the embryo and the controls were injected on the left side when co-
injected, and platinum electrodes were placed vertically across the chick em-
bryos and electroporated with five pulses of 6.3 V in 50 ms at 100-ms 
intervals. The embryos were cultured in 1.0 ml of albumen in tissue culture 
dishes until they reached the desired stages. The embryos were then re-
moved and fixed for 20 min to overnight in 4% PFA at room temperature 
or 4°C, respectively. The embryos were placed in PTW (1× PBS + 0.1% 
Tween 20), viewed, and photographed as whole mounts using a fluores-
cence stereomicroscope to show the electroporation efficiency. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis 
Western blots were performed to assess whether Sip1 knockdown affected 
the expression of Sip1, Ncad, and Ecad protein levels. Stage 8-10 chicken 
embryos were homogenized in a lysis buffer. Protein levels were mea-
sured using a Bradford assay and an equal amount of protein was boiled for 
10 min and loaded in each lane of an 8% SDS-PAGE gel. The proteins were 
fractionated by SDS-PAGE and transferred onto nitrocellulose membranes 
(EMD Millipore). Western blot analysis was performed by using an ECL che-
miluminescence blotting kit (GE Healthcare, Boehringer Ingelheim). In brief, 
after blocking in PBS containing 0.2% Tween and 5% low-fat dry milk for 1 h 
at room temperature, the membrane was incubated in Sip1, Ncad, Ecad, or 
-tubulin antibody, followed by development using ECL chemilumines-
cence reagents and visualization by x-ray autoradiography. </p>

<p>NanoString nCounter 
Individual halves of embryo neural tubes treated with Sip1-MO were disag-
gregated in lysis buffer (Ambion) and stored at 80°C. The total RNA from the 
lysates was then allowed to hybridize with the capture and reporter probes in-
cubating overnight at 65°C according to the nCounter gene expression assay 
manual. After the washes, the purified target-probe complexes were eluted off 
and immobilized in the cartridge for data collection performed in the nCounter 
digital analyzer. Results from three separate embryos were grouped and 
regression analysis was used to determine differences. Only genes that were 
altered by 25% or more were considered significant. </p>

<p>In situ hybridization 
For whole-mount in situ hybridization, embryos were fixed for 1 h to over-
night in 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) at room temperature or 4°C, respec-
tively, washed in PBS containing 0.1% Tween 20 (PTW), and dehydrated in </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 203 • NUMBER 5 • 2013 </p>



<p>
We would like to thank Tatjana Sauka-Spengler and the Bronner laboratory for 
helpful discussions. We would also like to thank the Caltech Biological Imaging 
center where we performed the live-imaging experiments and the Mertz Lab at 
the University of Wisconsin at Madison for the gift of human Zeb2 DNA. 
This work was supported by National Institutes of Health grant HD037105 
(to M.E. Bronner) and a National Institutes of Health minority supplement P01 
HD037105 (to C.D. Rogers). </p>

<p>Submitted: 9 May 2013 
Accepted: 4 November 2013 </p>



<p> </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>