<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3730412" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Microglia are the resident immune cells in the central nervous system and key players against pathogens and injury. However, 
persistent microglial activation often exacerbates pathological damage and has been implicated in many neurological diseases. 
Despite their pivotal physiological and pathophysiological roles, how the survival and death of activated microglia is regulated 
remains poorly understood. We report here that microglia activated through Toll-like receptors (TLRs) undergo RIP1/RIP3-
dependent programmed necrosis (necroptosis) when exposed to the pan caspase inhibitor zVAD-fmk. Although zVAD-fmk and 
the caspase-8 inhibitor IETD-fmk had no effect on unstimulated primary microglia, they markedly sensitized microglia to TLR1/ 
2,3,4,7/8 ligands or TNF treatment, triggering programmed necrosis that was completely blocked by R1P1 kinase inhibitor 
necrostatin-1. Interestingly, necroptosis induced by TLR ligands and zVAD was restricted to microglial cells and was not 
observed in astrocytes, neurons or oligodendrocytes even though they are known to express certain TLRs. Deletion of genes 
encoding TNF or TNFR1 failed to prevent lipopolysaccharide-and poly(I:C)-induced microglial necroptosis, unveiling a TNF-
independent programmed necrosis pathway in TLR3-and TLR4-activated microglia. Microglia from mice lacking functional TRIF 
were fully protected against TLR3/4 activation and zVAD-fmk-induced necrosis, and genetic deletion of rip3 also prevented 
microglia necroptosis. Activation of c-jun N-terminal kinase and generation of specific reactive oxygen species were 
downstream signaling events required for microglial cell death execution. Taken together, this study reveals a robust 
RIP3-dependent necroptosis signaling pathway in TLR-activated microglia upon caspase blockade and suggests that TLR 
signaling and programmed cell death pathways are closely linked in microglia, which could contribute to neuropathology and 
neuroinflammation when dysregulated. 
prevented. Activation of the kinase domain of receptor 
interacting protein 1 (RIP1) and assembly of RIP1/RIP3-
containing signaling complex have been shown to trigger 
programmed necrosis in some cells, a process also termed 
necroptosis. 
13 Necrostatin-1 (Nec-1), a small tryptophan-
based molecule that allosterically inhibits RIP1 kinase 
activity, 
14,15 prevents death receptor-induced necrosis 
16 and 
blocks oxidative oligodendroglial cell death. 
17 Administration of 
necrostatin-1 ameliorates neural injury in animal models of 
ischemia, 
15,18 traumatic brain injury, 
19 and Huntington's 
disease. 
20 Although the underlying mechanism of the in vivo 
protective effect of necrostatin-1 remains to be fully estab-
lished, necrostatin-1 administration in mice subjected to 
controlled cortical impact was associated with reduced micro-
glial activation. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Multiple lines of evidence have demonstrated that caspase-8, 
the initiator caspase of the death receptor-induced pathway 
of apoptosis, and its adaptor protein Fas-associated death 
domain (FADD) negatively regulate RIP1/RIP3-dependent 
programmed necrosis by cleaving and inactivating RIP1. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>Suppression of caspase-8 activity with the pan caspase 
inhibitor zVAD-fmk facilitates TNFa-induced necroptosis in 
cells expressing RIP3. 
22 Unlike TNF death receptor-induced 
necrosis, the details of pathogen-induced necrosis in innate 
immune cells have just started to emerge. Several studies 
have shown that when caspase-8 activity is suppressed by 
IETD-fmk, zVAD-fmk, or the viral caspase inhibitor CrmA, 
ligation of TLR3 or TLR4 results in programmed necrosis in 
human macrophages 
23 and mouse peritoneal macrophages 
via RIP3. 
22,24 However, whether activated microglia, the 
innate immune cells in the CNS, undergo programmed 
necrosis remains unanswered. 
In this study, we report that primary microglia activated by 
TLR ligations undergo apoptotic as well as necrotic cell death. 
Blockade of caspase-8 with zVAD-fmk or IETD-fmk markedly 
sensitized microglia to TNF and TLR1/2, TLR3, TLR4, and 
TLR7/8 ligation. Necroptosis of TLR3-and TLR4-activated 
microglia was further determined to be mediated by TRIF, 
RIP3, and downstream c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK) and 
reactive oxygen species (ROS). As necrotic cell death could 
elicit secondary inflammatory responses, unfolding the 
molecular mechanisms underlying the demise of activated 
microglia may hold important clues for future therapeutic 
intervention of CNS diseases. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Distinct microglial responses to different magnitudes of 
TLR4 activation. LPS elicits robust immune responses in 
microglia via TLR4. To examine the relationship between the 
extent of microglial activation and microglial cell fate, we 
challenged primary rat microglia with increasing concentra-
tions of LPS. Although activation of microglia with very low 
dose of LPS (0.1 ng/ml) promoted cell survival (Figures 1a 
and b) and TNF production (Figure 1d), higher concentra-
tions of LPS (10-100 ng/ml) caused microglial cell death in a 
dose-dependent manner (Figures 1a-c). Production of TNF 
by activated microglia was dependent on the extent of 
microglia activation and appeared to reach the peak with 
10 ng/ml LPS (Figure 1d), a concentration that also induced </p>

<p>significant DNA fragmentation as determined by increased 
number of TUNEL 
þ cells (Figure 1c). These data are in line 
with a previous study 
25 and suggest that programmed cell 
death is an intrinsic, self-eliminating mechanism that 
prevents over-activation. 
Next, we asked whether LPS over-activated microglia 
employ the classic apoptotic pathway for self-elimination. 
Activation of the executioner caspase-3 was evident in 
microglia treated with higher but not low dose of LPS 
(Figure 1e) and preceded apoptotic cell death 
(Supplementary Figure S1). As caspase-8 is an initiator 
caspase required for extrinsic pathways of apoptosis, we 
examined caspase-8 activation in live microglia after LPS 
stimulation with fluorescein-tagged FAM-LETD-fmk that 
affinity-labels activated caspase-8. 
26 Two distinct patterns of 
caspase-8 activation were observed (Figure 1e): diffuse 
cytosolic activation (C-Casp-8) and localized subcellular 
activation of caspase-8 (L-Casp-8). Although L-Casp-8 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>microglia were negative for TUNEL or activated caspase-3, 
many C-Casp-8 
þ microglia were also positive for TUNEL and 
activated caspase-3, suggesting that diffuse caspase-8 
activation in cytosol leads to apoptosis (Figures 1e and f). 
Localized caspase-8 activation was previously also found in 
T lymphocytes upon antigen receptor activation and was 
associated with cell proliferation. 
26 Together, these findings 
suggest that focally activated caspase-8 may function as a 
signaling molecule in complexes, while higher degree of 
activation in the cytoplasm initiates apoptotic cell death 
programme. </p>

<p>Microglia activated by low dose of LPS become necrotic 
when caspase-8 is suppressed. To examine the possible 
function of localized caspase-8 activation in LPS-activated 
microglia, we activated primary rat microglia with 0.1 ng/ml of 
LPS in the presence of specific caspase inhibitors. Although 
the pan caspase inhibitor zVAD-fmk (zVAD) had no effect on 
unstimulated, 'resting' microglia, it triggered rapid and 
massive cell death in LPS-activated microglia (Figures 2a-c). 
Furthermore, zVAD was similarly effective in inducing 
microglial cell death when added to microglia that were 
pre-activated with LPS and washed extensively 
(Supplementary Figure S2). LPS-activated microglia were 
also sensitive to caspase-8 inhibitor IETD-fmk (IETD) 
(Figures 2a and b). In contrast, caspase-3/7 inhibitor 
DEVD-fmk, caspase-1 inhibitor YVAD-fmk or their combina-
tion did not cause any cell death (Figures 2a and b). Microglia 
underwent necrotic cell death when treated with LPS/zVAD, 
as evidenced by increased DNA fragmentation (Figures 2d 
and e) and loss of plasma membrane integrity (Figures 2b-c). 
As in situ detection of fragmented DNA by TUNEL does not 
necessarily distinguish between apoptosis and necrosis, we 
then employed electron microscopic analyses. Consistent 
with our finding that higher magnitude of LPS/TLR4 activa-
tion induces caspase-dependent apoptosis (Figure 1e, 
Supplementary Figure S1), microglia activated with higher 
dose of LPS alone exhibited morphological characteristics of 
typical apoptosis, including decreased cellular volume, 
condensation of chromatin and intact cytoplasmic membrane 
(Figure 2f, middle). In contrast, zVAD greatly sensitized 
microglia to low level of LPS activation, leading to necrosis </p>

<p>RIP3 mediates programmed necrosis in activated microglia 
SJ Kim and J Li </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>that was characterized by translucent cytoplasm, organelle 
swelling, increased cell volume and disruption of the plasma 
membrane (Figure 2f). It should be mentioned that, in 
contrast to LPS-activated primary microglia where caspase-8 
inhibitors triggered necrosis without suppressing TNF 
(Supplementary Figure S3), LPS/zVAD failed to cause cell 
death in BV-2 microglial cell line and only moderately 
suppressed TNF secretion (Supplementary Figure S4). </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>Taken together, our results demonstrate that LPS-activated </p>

<p>primary microglia possess at least two distinct cell death 
pathways depending on the extent of their activation and the 
presence of caspase suppressors. </p>

<p>Programmed necrosis induced by TLR ligands/zVAD 
occurs only in microglia, not in neurons, astrocytes or 
oligodendrocytes. As microglia express multiple TLRs, we 
next examined whether zVAD also causes necrosis of 
microglia activated by other TLR ligands such as double </p>

<p>Figure 1 Microglial responses to different doses of LPS. (a) Low dose of LPS increased microglia viability whereas higher doses triggered cell death. Primary rat microglia 
were stimulated with increasing concentrations of LPS (0.1, 10, 100 ng/ml) for 20-24 h, and the number of microglial cells were counted. Data are a representative of three 
independent experiments with similar results. (b) Representative phase-contrast images of microglia treated with indicated concentrations of LPS. Scale bar, 50 mm. 
(c) Significant increase of TUNEL-positive microglia after LPS stimulation for 6 h. Data represent the percentage of TUNEL-positive cells of the total cells. (d) Dose-dependent 
increase of TNF production upon LPS treatment for 6 h. Data are a representative of three independent experiments with similar results. (e, f) LPS-activated microglia 
exhibited two distinct casaspe-8 activation patterns. Localized caspase-8 activation (L-Casp-8) was not associated with caspase-3 activation or cell death (upper panel, e), 
whereas profound cytoplasmic activation of caspase-8 (C-Casp-8) induced caspase-3 activation, DNA fragmentation (TUNEL-positive) and cell death (lower panel, e). 
Rat microglia were treated with 0.1-100 ng/ml LPS as above and in situ detection of caspase-8 activation in live cells was carried out as described in Methods section. Cells 
were then fixed and subjected to TUNEL labeling or immunostaining for cleaved/activated caspase-3 (act. Casp-3). Results are shown as percentage of Casp-8-positive cells 
of total cells. NS, not significant; *Po0.05; **Po0.01; ***Po0.001 </p>

<p>RIP3 mediates programmed necrosis in activated microglia 
SJ Kim and J Li </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>strained RNA mimic poly (I:C) (TLR3 ligand), Pam3CSK4 
(TLR1/2), and R848 (TLR7/8). Indeed, all other TLR ligands 
tested induced microglial necrosis (Figure 3a). In contrast, 
activation of microglia with ATP (up to 1 mM) or IL-13 
(100 ng/ml) plus zVAD did not cause cell death 
(Supplementary Figure S5), suggesting microglial necrosis 
specificity to death receptor and TLR activation. Interestingly, 
although neurons, astrocytes, and oligodendrocytes 
are known to express functional TNF receptor and certain 
TLRs, for example, TLR2/TLR3 in oligodendrocytes and </p>

<p>astrocytes 
28-31 and TLR3/TLR8 in neurons, 
32,33 they were 
not sensitive to TNF/zVAD or TLR ligand/zVAD treatment 
(Figures 3b-d). These results demonstrate that TNF/zVAD 
or TLR ligand/zVAD induces necrosis specifically in primary 
microglia but not in other CNS cells. </p>

<p>Blockade of RIP1 kinase with necrostatin-1 completely 
abolishes microglia necrosis. To investigate the molecular 
mechanism underlying TLR activation and zVAD-induced 
necrosis, we first tested the effect of Nec-1, which inhibits </p>

<p>Figure 2 Microglia activated by low dose of LPS undergo rapid necrotic cell death upon caspase-8 blockade. (a-c) Inhibition of caspase-8 in LPS-activated microglia triggered a 
marked loss of cell viability. Primary rat microglia were stimulated with or without LPS (0.1 ng/ml) in the presence or absence of the pan caspase inhibitor, z-VAD-fmk, caspase-8 
specific inhibitor IETD-fmk, caspase-3/7 inhibitor DEVD-fmk, caspase-1 inhibitor YVAD-fmk, or the combination of DEVD-fmk and YVAD-fmk (25 mM each) for 20-24 h. Cell viability 
was determined by Alamar Blue assay that measures metabolic activity, and it was confirmed by live/dead cell analysis using propidium iodide (PI) and Calcein AM as described. 
Representative phase contrast and PI/Calcein AM staining images of microglia treated as indicated were shown. Data are representative of at least three independent experiments. 
Scale bar, 50 mm. **Po0.01; ***Po0.001. (d, e) LPS plus zVAD-fmk induced microglial cell death in rat mixed glial cultures that were treated with LPS (1 mg/ml) and zVAD-fmk for 
24 h. The percentage of TUNEL 
þ Iba1 
þ microglia was determined. (f) Transmission electron microscopy of microglia treated with vehicle DMSO (left), 10 ng/ml of LPS alone 
(middle) or 0.1 ng/ml of LPS plus zVAD-fmk (10 mM) (right) for 6 h. Microglia treated with vehicle and 10 ng/ml of LPS had intact cytoplasmic membrane, whereas many LPS/zVAD 
treated microglia exhibited translucent cytoplasm, swelling mitochondria (insert), and membrane breakdown. Scale bars, 2 mm, 0.1 mm (insert) </p>

<p>RIP3 mediates programmed necrosis in activated microglia 
SJ Kim and J Li </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>RIP1 kinase activity 
14 and RIP1/RIP3 association. </p>

<p>34,35 </p>

<p>Cotreatment with Nec-1 completely abolished LPS/zVAD-
induced microglial cell death (Figures 4a and b). Furthermore, 
although RIP1 and RIP3 were endogenously expressed 
in unstimulated microglia, they were markedly upregulated 
in LPS-primed microglia at both transcription and protein 
levels (Figures 4c and d). This increased expression of 
RIP1 and RIP3 in LPS-activated microglia may account for 
their enhanced vulnerability to programmed necrosis. 
Consistently, Nec-1 was equally effective in protecting 
microglia against zVAD and other TLR ligand-induced cell 
death (Figure 4e). </p>

<p>TLR3 and TLR4 activation induced microglial necroptosis 
is independent of TNF/TNFR1 but dependent on TRIF 
and RIP3. Given our finding that TNF/zVAD is capable of 
triggering programmed necrosis in primary microglia 
(Figure 3a) and the fact that TNF is produced by activated 
microglia, we next investigated the possible involvement of 
autocrine TNF signaling in microglial necrosis induced by 
LPS/zVAD and poly(I:C)/zVAD. First, we confirmed that 
LPS/zVAD-induced necrosis was indeed mediated through 
the LPS receptor TLR4, as LPS-but not poly(I:C)-induced 
necroptosis was completely abrogated in tlr4-mutant 
microglia (Figure 5a). Next, we prepared mixed glial cultures 
from tnf 
þ / þ and tnf 
À / À mouse brains, and examined 
microglial survival after overnight stimulation with LPS/zVAD. 
Although tnf 
À / À microglia were incapable of producing 
TNF, 
36 they were equally susceptible as wild type to </p>

<p>LPS/zVAD-induced cell death (Figure 5b), suggesting that 
autocrine production of TNF was not necessary for LPS/ 
zVAD-induced necrosis. In line with this, LPS/zVAD-induced 
loss of microglia was also independent of the TNF receptor 
TNFR1 (Figure 5b). Similarly, poly(I:C)/zVAD caused signifi-
cant level of toxicity in both wild-type and tnf-deficient 
microglia (Supplementary Figure S6). Together, these results 
demonstrate the existence of alternative necrosis-initiating 
pathways other than the TNF/TNFR1 pathway in TLR4-and 
TLR3-activated microglia. 
Activation of TLR3 and TLR4 is known to initiate a series of 
signaling cascades through various adaptors. As TRIF is a 
common adaptor molecule for both TLR3 and TLR4 signaling, 
the role of TRIF in microglial necroptosis was examined. 
Whereas LPS/zVAD and poly(I:C)/zVAD induced significant 
loss of wild-type microglia, trif-mutant microglia were com-
pletely protected, demonstrating a critical role for TRIF in 
TLR3/TLR4-activated microglial cell death (Figure 5c). To 
verify that TRIF indeed specifically mediated the signaling 
events following TLR3 ligation, TNF secretion in culture 
supernatants was analyzed. As expected, poly(I:C)-induced 
TNF production was abolished in trif-mutant microglia 
whereas LPS-induced TNF production was only transiently 
blocked (Figure 5d). This is consistent with the concept that 
TLR4 recruits adaptor molecules MyD88 and TRIF, whereas 
TRIF is the sole adaptor molecule for TLR3. 
3 One potential 
mechanistic link between TLR3/TLR4 activation and necrop-
tosis is that TRIF physically interacts with RIP1 and RIP3 via 
receptor-interacting protein homotypic interaction motif </p>

<p>Figure 3 TLR agonists and TNF plus zVAD induce necrotic cell death only in microglia, but not in astrocytes, oligodendrocytes or neurons. (a) Primary rat microglia were 
treated with vehicle, TLR agonists poly(I:C) (PIC, 10 mg/ml), Pam3CSK4 (0.1 mg/ml), R848 (1 mg/ml) or TNFa (10 ng/ml ) in the presence or absence of zVAD-fmk (25 mM) as 
indicated. Cell viability was determined 20-24 h later as described. Data represent mean ± S.E.M. of three independent experiments. ***Po0.0001. (b-d) Enriched primary 
astrocytes, oligodendrocytes, and neurons were treated with vehicle, LPS (20 ng/ml), poly(I:C) (50 mg/ml), Pam3CSK4 (0.5 mg/ml), R848 (5 mg/ml) or TNFa (30 ng/ml) in the 
presence or absence of zVAD-fmk (50 mM), and cell viability was determined 20-24 h later. No loss of cell viability was observed in astrocytes, oligodendrocytes, or neurons. 
Data are representative of three independent experiments </p>

<p>RIP3 mediates programmed necrosis in activated microglia 
SJ Kim and J Li </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>(RHIM). 
24,37 In support of this idea, rip3 deficiency com-
pletely prevented microglia from LPS/zVAD-as well as 
poly(I:C)/zVAD-induced necrosis (Figure 5e), and had no 
effect on LPS-induced TNF production (not shown). Interest-
ingly, rip3 
þ / À heterozygous microglia exhibited about 50% of 
the sensitivity toward LPS/zVAD or poly(I:C)/zVAD as 
compared with rip3 
þ / þ microglia (Figure 5e). Therefore, in 
addition to RIP3 activation being a key regulatory point for 
necroptosis, our data also indicate that the protein expression 
level of RIP3 is important for effective induction of necroptosis. </p>

<p>Activation of JNK and production of reactive oxygen 
species orchestrate microglial cell demise. Previously 
we have shown that arachidonic acid triggers programmed 
necrosis in oligodendroglia through RIP1 and downstream 
c-jun N-terminal kinase (JNK). 
17 To determine whether JNK 
activation is required for LPS/zVAD-induced microglial 
necroptosis, we examined the effect of the JNK specific </p>

<p>inhibitor SP600125 on microglial survival. Cotreatment with 
SP600125 significantly but not completely prevented 
LPS/zVAD-induced cell death (Figure 6a), whereas blockade 
of p38 kinase or ERK1/2 had no protective effect 
(Supplementary Figure S7). Consistent with the role of JNK 
in microglial necrosis, robust JNK activation was observed 
3 h post LPS/zVAD treatment, and was inhibited significantly 
by SP600125 and completely by Nec-1 (Figure 6b), indicat-
ing that JNK activation occurs downstream of RIP1. 
Reactive oxygen species (ROS) production, lipid peroxida-
tion, and lysosomal leakage have been suggested to be 
pivotal steps for necrosis execution in certain cell lines. 
13 As 
LPS-activated microglia are capable of producing reactive 
oxygen/nitrogen species, </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>we reasoned that ROS 
scavenger butylated hydroxyanisole (BHA) may prevent 
LPS/zVAD-induced necrosis. Indeed, LPS/zVAD-induced 
microglial necrosis was almost completely mitigated by BHA 
(Figure 6a). In contrast and to our surprise, we did not observe </p>

<p>Figure 4 Blockade of RIP1 kinase activity abrogates TLR-activation-induced microglial necrosis. (a) Blockade of RIP1 kinase activity with necrostatin-1 (Nec-1) completely 
prevented LPS/zVAD-induced necrosis. Primary rat microglia were treated as indicated with LPS (0.1 ng/ml), zVAD (25 mM) or Nec-1 (20 mM), and cell survival was evaluated 
by cell counting. ***Po0.001. (b) Representative PI/Calcein AM (upper panel) and phase contrast (lower panel) images of microglia treated as above showing that microglial 
cell death induced by LPS/zVAD were abrogated by Nec-1. Data represent at least three independent experiments. Scale bars, 50 mm. (c) LPS significantly upregulated RIP1 
and RIP3 expression in microglia as determined by western blot analysis. Rat microglia were preactivated overnight with low dose of LPS, washed extensively and exposed 
subsequently to zVAD or zVAD/Nec-1 for 3 h. Cell lysates were then prepared and subjected to western blot analysis. A representative western blot with shorter exposure time 
was shown. Quantification of relative RIP1 and RIP3 expression was carried out by densitometry analyses of western blots from 3 to 7 independent experiments. *Po0.05; 
two-tailed student t test. (d) RT-PCR analysis of microglia treated as above, showing that LPS transcriptionally increases RIP1 and RIP3 expression. Actin and Iba1 were used 
as internal controls, and TNF as an indicator for microglial activation. RT, reverse transcriptase. Experiments were repeated three times with similar results. (e) Nec-1 
effectively abrogated microglial necrosis induced by other TLR ligands. Microglia were treated as indicated with zVAD, Nec-1 and various TLR agonists: TLR1/2 agonist 
Pam3CSK4 (0.1 mg/ml), TLR3 agonist poly(I:C) (PIC, 10 mg/ml), or TLR7/8 agonist R848 (1 mg/ml). Cell survival was determined by cell counting. Data represent 
mean±S.E.M. of two independent experiments. ***Po0.001 </p>

<p>RIP3 mediates programmed necrosis in activated microglia 
SJ Kim and J Li </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Figure 5 LPS/zVAD-induced microglial cell death is independent of TNF/TNFR1 but dependent on TRIF and RIP3. (a) LPS receptor TLR4 was required for LPS/zVAD-induced 
but not poly(I:C)/zVAD-induced mi microglial cell death. Mixed glial cultures from individual dissection of tlr4 wild-type (WT) (n ¼ 2-5) and knockout (KO) (n ¼ 3) littermate pups were 
treated with vehicle, LPS (1 mg/ml), LPS/zVAD (50 mM), poly(I:C) (50 mg/ml) or poly(I:C)/zVAD for 20-24 h. Microglia survival was determined by counting Iba1 
þ cells. ***Po0.001; 
NS, not significant. (b) TNF and TNFR1 were dispensable for LPS/zVAD-induced microglial necrosis. Mixed glial cultures prepared from WT and tnf-, tnfr1-deficient mice were 
treated with vehicle, LPS or LPS/zVAD as indicated for 20-24 h. Microglial survival was determined by counting Iba1 
þ cells. Microglia susceptibility to LPS/zVAD was the same in 
WT, tnf-and tnfr1-KO mixed glial cultures. Data represent three to four independent experiments. ***Po0.001; NS, not significant. (c) TRIF was essential for LPS/zVAD-and 
poly(I:C)/zVAD-induced microglial necrosis. Mixed glial cultures from WT and trif-mutant mice were treated with LPS/zVAD or poly (I:C)/zVAD as indicated, and microglia survival was 
evaluated as above. Data represent mean±S.E.M. of at least three independent experiments. LPS/zVAD-and poly(I:C)/zVAD-induced microglial cell death was completely 
abrogated in trif-mutant cultures. Insert, western blot analysis of TRIF protein expression in trif-WT and mutant microglia. ***Po0.001. (d), TRIF mediated poly(I:C)-induced TNF 
production by microglia. Mixed glia from wild-type and trif-mutant mice were stimulated with vehicles, LPS and poly(I:C) as specified. TNF secretion was determined by ELISA of 
culture supernatants from each condition at time indicated. Data represent two independent experiments with similar results. (e) RIP3 mediated LPS/zVAD-and poly(I:C)/zVAD-
induced programmed necrosis in microglia. Mixed glial cultures derived from rip3 
þ / þ , rip3 
þ / À , and rip3 
À / À littermates were challenged with LPS, poly(I:C), and zVAD for 24 h, 
and microglial survival was determined by counting Iba1 
þ cells. Data represent mean ± S.E.M. of three independent experiments. ***Po0.001 </p>

<p>Figure 6 Reactive oxygen species (ROS) and JNK phosphorylation are required for programmed necrosis of microglia. (a) Abrogation of LPS/zVAD-induced microglial 
cell death by SP600125 (10 mM) and BHA (150 mM). Pure rat microglia were treated as indicated and cell survival was determined by counting Calcein AM 
þ /PI 
-cells 20-24 h 
later. Vitamin K1 (1 mM) and K2 (1 mM, Menaquinone-4) had a moderate effect but not statistically significant. AA861 (10 mM) had no protective effect. Data represent 
mean ± S.E.M. of three to five independent experiments. ***Po0.001; NS, not significant as compared with LPS/zVAD-treated cells. (b) Increased JNK phosphorylation in 
LPS/zVAD-treated microglia and complete inhibition by Nec-1. Rat microglia were pre-treated with vehicle, Nec-1 (20 mM), BHA (150 mM), or SP600125 (10 mM) for 1 h 
followed by stimulation with or without LPS (0.1 ng/ml) and zVAD (10 mM) for 3 h. Microglial lysates were then prepared and subjected to western blot analyses as described. 
Data represent mean ± S.E.M. of densitometry analyses of three independent experiments. *Po0.05; **Po0.01; ***Po0.001; two-tailed Student's t test </p>

<p>RIP3 mediates programmed necrosis in activated microglia 
SJ Kim and J Li </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>any protection by 12-lipoxygenase inhibitor AA861, and only 
minor but not statistically significant protection by vitamin K1 
and K2 (Figure 6a), reagents that were all highly effective in 
ameliorating glutathione depletion-induced oxidative injury in 
oligodendrocytes and neurons 
38 as well as arachidonic acid-
induced necroptosis in oligodendrocytes. 
39 Moreover, other 
classic antioxidants such as hydrophilic Trolox and lipophilic 
vitamin E (a-tocopherol) did not confer significant protection 
(Supplementary Figure S8), nor did we observe significant 
protection by nitric oxide synthase inhibitor L-NMMA, super-
oxide dismutase mimic MnTMPyP, NADPH oxidase inhibitor 
diphenyleneiodonium, peroxynitrite decomposition catalyst </p>

<p>FeTMPyP or glutathione peroxidase mimic Ebselen 
(Supplementary Figure S7). 
To further determine the role of ROS in microglial necrosis, 
intracellular ROS production was assessed. Unlike previous 
studies, we did not detect significant fluorescence signal in 
LPS/zVAD-treated microglia using H 2 DCF-DA, a widely used 
general cellular oxidative stress/ROS indicator, 
40 likely due to 
the low activation state of microglia. However, a significant 
increase of fluorescence signal from superoxide indicator 
hydroethidine (HE) 
41 was detected in microglia treated with 
LPS/zVAD for 3 h as compared with those treated with LPS 
alone (Figure 7a). Consistent with their effects on survival, </p>

<p>Figure 7 Elevated production of superoxide anion orchestrates microglial demise and proceeds plasma membrane permeabilization. (a) Increased superoxide anion 
production by LPS/zVAD-activated microglia and complete suppression by Nec-1 and BHA. Microglia were pre-treated with Nec-1 (20 mM), BHA (150 mM), vitamin E (10 mM), 
vitamin K2 (10 mM), or SP600125 (10 mM) for 1 h prior to stimulation with low concentration of LPS (0.1 ng/ml) or LPS (0.1 ng/ml)/zVAD (25 mM) for 3 h. Reactive oxygen 
species were then evaluated by the superoxide anion indicator hydroethidine (HE, 1 mM) and flow cytometry as described. Data represent mean ± s.e.m. of three independent 
experiments. **Po0.01; NS, not significant. (b) Representative live fluorescence and phase contrast images of microglia stimulated with LPS/zVAD for 3 h and incubated with 
HE (1 mM) and Sytox (10 nM) for 20 min, showing increased oxidized HE signal preceding microglial cell death (arrows). Bisbenzimide was used to visualize all nuclei. Scale 
bar, 50 mm. (c, d) Representative microglia cells in (b) at higher magnification, showing elevated oxidized HE signal in subpopulation of microglia (arrow in c, arrow head in d) 
preceding plasma membrane permeabilization in the dying cell (arrow in c). Stealth arrow in (d) indicates a microglia cell with minimum oxidized HE signal. (e) Time-lapse 
imaging analysis of microglia loaded with HE and Sytox and treated with LPS/zVAD reveals that oxidized HE signal precedes cell death. Right, graphic representation of the 
mean intensities of HE and Sytox signal of the representative cell over time. Scale bars, 15 mm </p>

<p>RIP3 mediates programmed necrosis in activated microglia 
SJ Kim and J Li </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Nec-1 and BHA efficiently abrogated LPS/zVAD-induced HE 
signal whereas vitamin E and K2 did not (Figure 7a). The JNK 
inhibitor SP600125, although significantly and partially sup-
pressed LPS/zVAD-induced cell death, had only limited effect 
on LPS/zVAD-induced increased of HE signal, suggesting 
that JNK activation is at the level or downstream of ROS 
production. This is in agreement with the observation that 
BHA prevented ROS production, and significantly and 
partially blocked LPS/zVAD-induced JNK activation 
(Figure 6b). Further fluorescence microscopy analyses at 
single cell levels revealed that LPS/zVAD-triggered super-
oxide production proceeded plasma membrane permeabiliza-
tion and cell death (Figures 7b-e). Together, these results 
support the idea that excess superoxide or related species is a 
main source of ROS in LPS/zVAD-treated microglia. In 
summary, our data demonstrate that TLR4-induced microglial 
necroptosis is orchestrated by a series of events mediated by 
TRIF, RIP1/RIP3 signaling, JNK activation and specific ROS 
production. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Programmed cell death is a fundamental cellular process with 
critical functions in development, homeostasis, and immunity. 
Caspase-dependent apoptosis and the recently identified 
programmed necrosis, also termed necroptosis, are two 
programmed cell death pathways that have been shown to 
have pivotal roles in the peripheral immune system, such as 
elimination of reactive T cells and innate control of viral 
infections. 
42-44 Microglia are the immune cells in the CNS and 
regulate both innate and adaptive immune responses; 
however, to date, to our knowledge little information is 
available on a necroptosis programme in microglia. In this 
study, we demonstrated an operation of two interconnected 
programmed cell death pathways in TLR-activated primary 
microglia: (1) caspase-dependent apoptosis in overactivated 
microglia, and (2) RIP3-mediated necroptosis as unmasked 
by caspase blockade. TLR-receptor agonists as well as TNF 
were capable of initiating primary microglia necrosis when 
caspase-8 was suppressed by zVAD-fmk or IETD-fmk, 
phenomena not observed in other cells of the CNS including 
primary neurons, astrocytes, and oligodendrocytes. The 
specific RIP1 kinase inhibitor, necrostatin-1, was highly 
effective in rescuing microglia against necroptosis. We further 
found that necrosis induced by ligation of microglial TLR4 or 
TLR3 with LPS and poly(I:C), respectively, and zVAD was 
independent of autocrine TNF/TNFR1 signaling and was 
transduced through the adaptor molecule TRIF, as LPS/zVAD 
and poly(I:C)/zVAD failed to cause microglial necroptosis in 
trif-mutant cells. TRIF, RIP1 and RIP3 are known RHIM 
motif-containing adaptor proteins capable of interacting with 
each other via RHIM, 
37,45 and activation of TLR3 and 
TLR4 in the presence of zVAD induces the formation of 
TRIF/RIP3 complex. </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Consistent with this, genetic 
ablation of rip3 completely abrogated necroptosis in microglia, 
demonstrating an absolute requirement for RIP3 signaling in 
initiating necrotic death of activated microglia. Finally, activa-
tion of JNK and generation of specific ROS appear to execute 
the cell death program and result in disintegration of activated 
microglia. </p>

<p>Microglia act as a first line of defense in the CNS and can be 
activated through TLRs in diverse situations, not only by 
microbial PAMPs but also by host-derived molecules liberated 
from damaged cells. However, the regulation of the home-
ostasis of activated microglia remains poorly understood. 
Excessive activation of microglia with LPS was associated 
with increased apoptotic cell death. Intriguingly, although low 
dose of LPS activated microglia without inducing cell death, 
blockade of caspase-8 triggered a robust RIP1-dependent 
necrosis programme. One possibility is that caspase-8 
inactivates RIP1 through proteolytic cleavage, 
21 and its 
suppression enhances RIP1 stability, thereby sensitizing cells 
to RIP1-mediated necrosis. In fact, caspase-8 has been 
shown to possess prosurvival activities as it is required for 
T-lymphocyte activation, 
46,47 monocyte differentiation </p>

<p>48,49 </p>

<p>as well as suppression of TNF-induced necroptosis. </p>

<p>13,21 </p>

<p>Caspase-8 and -3/7 recently have also been implicated in 
microglial activation, as their blockade with IETD-fmk and 
DEVD-fmk suppressed LPS-induced upregulation of iNOS 
and certain cytokines in BV-2 microglia without triggering cell 
death. 
27 We also found that caspase inhibitors did not cause 
BV-2 cell death and only moderately suppressed LPS-
induced TNF production. In contrast, caspase blockade did 
not prevent LPS-induced TNF secretion in primary rat 
microglia, but rather markedly sensitized the cells to LPS 
challenge. It is noteworthy that primary rat microglia are more 
vulnerable than mouse microglia to TLR3/4 stimulation and 
caspase blockade. As caspase-8 can interact and form 
signaling complexes with, for example, cFLIP, FADD, RIP1/3, 
and TRIF under different contexts, 
50 further investigation is 
required to delineate the exact function of caspase-8 in 
regulating microglial activation, survival and cell death using 
genetic approaches. Another interesting finding of this study is 
that overnight stimulation of microglia with LPS results in 
enhanced RIP1/RIP3 expression that predisposes the cells to 
necroptosis induction. The mechanism underlying LPS-
induced upregulation of RIP3 remains to be defined. 
ROS production has been shown to be required for 
necroptosis in some cell types but not others. 
35,50,51 It is 
interesting to note that only the lipophilic antioxidant BHA 
prevented TLR3/4-mediated necroptosis and was actually the 
antioxidant used in most of previous studies on necroptosis. 
Other lipophilic antioxidants, such as a-tocopherol, antiox-
idant enzyme mimics and lipoxygenase inhibitors, although 
effective in preventing arachidonic acid-induced necroptosis in 
oligodendrocytes, 
17 did not efficiently block TLR-mediated 
microglial necrosis. Zhang et al. 
22 also noted that only BHA 
prevented TNF-induced necrosis in N cells. In line with our 
findings, elevated levels of superoxide production in LPS/zVAD-
treated microglia were found to precede cell death and was 
completely abolished by Nec-1 and BHA. Although we cannot 
exclude the possibility that BHA may have effects other than 
preventing superoxide production, overall our data strongly 
suggest that specific ROS at specific subcellular locations is 
required for TLR-activation-induced necroptosis in microglia. 
Microglia are specified macrophages in the CNS. Recent 
studies have shown that microglia have a distinct embryonic 
origin from that of bone marrow-derived monocytes, colonize 
the CNS during early embryonic development, and exhibit 
unique features such as ramification that distinguishes them </p>

<p>RIP3 mediates programmed necrosis in activated microglia 
SJ Kim and J Li </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>from macrophages. 
52 However, our identification of a TLR/ 
zVAD-induced necroptosis pathway, similar to that of macro-
phages, 
24,35 in microglia raises the question whether protec-
tion against necrotic microglial cell death might be beneficial in 
the CNS given that necrotic cell death often results in 
inflammation. On the other hand, it is conceivable that 
necroptosis is a backup strategy of innate immune cells 
against pathogens to stimulate the immune system when 
apoptosis is blocked by, for example, viruses. 
13,34 Pathologi-
cal microglial cell death or degeneration has indeed been 
observed in mouse models of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, </p>

<p>53 </p>

<p>multiple sclerosis 
54 and neurodegenerative diseases. 
55 How-
ever, the trigger and consequences of microglial cell death 
remain largely unexplored and warrant further investigation. 
In summary, our data revealed that microglia activated 
through TLRs can undergo apoptosis for self-elimination or 
RIP3-mediated programmed necrosis when sensitized with 
zVAD or under certain conditions. It thus appears that 
microglial TLR activation not only initiates CNS immune 
responses against pathogens and tissue damage, but may 
also be exploited to regulate the cell fate of activated 
microglia. Indeed, during the review process of our manu-
script, a recent study reported that zVAD induces necrosis of 
LPS-activated microglia in mixed neuronal/glial cultures, 
thereby protecting neurons indirectly from LPS toxicity. 
56 As 
microglia have critical physiological and pathological roles in 
many neurological disorders, detailed understanding of the 
mechanism that regulates the survival and death of activated 
microglia may provide novel strategies for targeting neurode-
generation and neuroinflammation. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods 
Animals and reagents. Wild-type B6.129SF2/J and C57BL/6J mice, TNFa 
(wild-type control B6.129SF2/J, # 003008) and TNFR1 (wild-type control C57BL/6J, 
#003242) knockout (KO) mice, and TRIF (Ticam1, background C57BL/6J, #005037) 
mutant mice were obtained from the Jackson Laboratory (Bar Harbor, ME, USA). 
Rip3-deficient mice were generous gift from Dr. Xiaodong Wang (National Institute of 
Biological Sciences, China) and Dr. Astar Winoto (University of California, Berkeley). 
BV-2 microglial cells were kindly provided by Dr. Monica Carson (University of 
California, Riverside). DMEM, HBSS, propidium iodide, Calcein AM, Alamar blue, 
and hydroethidine were purchased from Invitrogen (Carlsbad, CA, USA). Antibody 
against Iba1 was from Wako chemicals (Richmond, VA, USA). Recombinant TNF, 
zVAD-fmk, IETD-fmk, DEVD-fmk, YVAD-fmk, and antibody against RIP1 were 
obtained from R&amp;D Systems (Minneapolis, MN, USA). Rabbit anti-RIP3 and TRIF 
antibodies were from IMGENEX (San Diego, CA, USA). JNK, pJNK and active 
caspase-3 antibodies were obtained from Cell Signaling Technology (Danvers, MA, 
USA). Pam3CSK4 and R848 were obtained from InvivoGen (San Diego, CA, USA). 
JNK inhibitor II (SP600125) was from Merck (Darmstadt, Germany). MnTMPyP, 
0FeTMPyP, L-NMMA and Ebselen were obtained from Cayman Chemical (Ann 
Arbor, MI, UA). HRP-conjugated secondary antibodies were obtained from Jackson 
ImmunoResearch (West Grove, PA, USA). Unless specified otherwise, all other 
reagents were from Sigma (St. Louis, MO, USA). </p>

<p>Primary glial cell cultures. Primary microglia, oligodendrocytes, astro-
cytes, and mixed glial cultures were prepared from forebrains of 1-to 2-day-old 
Sprague-Dawley rat pups as described previously. 
8,36 Briefly, dissociated cells 
were plated onto poly-D-lysine (PDL)-coated T75 flasks or 96 well culture plates 
and were fed every other day with D10S (DMEM with 10% FBS) for 7-10 days. 
Microglia were isolated by shaking mixed glia-containing flasks for 1 h at 200 r.p.m. 
The purity of microglia at this stage was consistently 495%. For highly purified 
microglia monocultures (499%), the cells were plated onto regular petri dishes for 
1 h, detached from the plates with ice cold EBSS, and plated at final density of 
3 Â 10 
4 cells per well in 96-well plates. Following 1-h pre-shaking, the flasks were 
shaken overnight at 200 r.p.m. to separate OL precursors (preOLs) from the </p>

<p>astrocyte layer. The cell suspension was then plated onto uncoated Petri dishes 
for 1 h to remove residual contaminating microglia, and the resulting preOLs were 
plated into poly-L-ornithine-coated culture plates and maintained in a serum-free 
basal defined medium (0.1% bovine serum albumin, 50 mg/ml human 
apo-transferrin, 50 mg/ml insulin, 30 nM sodium selenite, 10 nM D-biotin and 
10 nM hydrocortisone in DMEM) supplemented with PDGF 10 ng/ml and bFGF 
10 ng/ml for 5-9 days at 37 1C in a humid atmosphere of 5% CO2 and 95% air. 
Astrocytes (495%) were purified from the remaining astrocyte layer in the flask 
after being exposed to a specific microglia toxin L-leucine methyl ester (1 mM) for 
1 h and were subcultured one to two times. Mouse mixed glial cultures were 
prepared with similar methods as described above from B6.129SF2/J, C57BL/6J, 
TRIF mutant, TNF KO, TNFR1 KO, and rip3 KO mice and were seeded in 
PDL-coated 96-well plates. Mixed glial cultures at DIV6-7 were used in this study. </p>

<p>Cell treatment and survival determination. Microglia monocultures 
were washed two times with D1S (DMEM containing 1% FBS) and treated in 
triplicate with vehicle, LPS, Pam3CSK4, R848, poly(I:C), or TNFa in the presence 
or absence of zVAD-fmk or IETD-fmk as specified. For mixed glial cultures, cells 
were treated in serum-free basal defined medium. 
30 As microglia in mixed glial 
cultures were not as sensitive as in isolated pure cultures to LPS/zVAD-induced 
necroptosis, higher concentrations of LPS and poly(I:C) were used. Microglial 
survival was determined by counting Iba1 
þ cells with normal nuclei in mixed glia 
cultures or Calcein AM 
þ /propidium iodide (PI) 
À cells in pure microglia cultures. 
Total number of cells was revealed by staining all nuclei with Hoechst 33342. Five 
to ten random consecutive fields were counted in each well under 100 Â or 
200 Â magnification, with a total of 41000 cells counted in the control condition. 
In some cases, cell viability in monocultures was determined by measuring cell 
metabolic activity using Alamar Blue, a tetrazolium dye that is reduced by living 
cells to a colored product as previously described. </p>

<p>38,57 </p>

<p>For experiments involving RNA and protein isolation, primary microglia were 
seeded into six-well plates at a density of 1.5-2 Â 10 
6 cells/well in D10S. After 
attachment, the cells were washed twice with D1S, and pre-treated with LPS 
(0.1 ng/ml) for 12-16 h. At the end of LPS treatment, microglia were washed twice 
with D1S and incubated with Nec-1, butylated hydroxyanisole (BHA), SP600125, or 
corresponding vehicle for 1 h before the induction of necrosis with zVAD-fmk 
addition. Microglia were then collected with ice-cold PBS at 1 h (RNA extraction) and 
3 h (protein preparation) post zVAD-fmk treatment. Vehicles used were PBS for LPS, 
DMSO for zVAD-fmk, Nec-1, and SP600125, and ethanol for BHA, and these were 
used at the same final concentration volume (o0.1%) as the corresponding reagent. </p>

<p>In situ caspase-8 activity assay. To detect caspase-8 activity in situ in 
living microglia, a caspase-8 detection kit containing a specific and fluorescent 
FAM-LETD-fmk that covalently labels active caspase-8 was used according to the 
manufacturer's instruction (Image-iTs LIVE Green Caspase-8 Detection Kit, 
Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). After live labeling of active caspase-8, microglia 
were fixed and subjected to immunocytochemistry as specified in the Figure 1 
legend. Images were captured using a fluorescence microscope equipped with an 
Olympus DP70 digital camera. On the basis of the intracellular location of active 
caspase-8, the percentage of microglia with cytoplasmic diffuse caspase-8 signal 
(C-casp-8) and localized active caspase-8 (L-casp-8) was counted and analyzed 
across treatment conditions. </p>

<p>Detection of intracellular ROS. Intracellular ROS production was 
evaluated by flow cytometry using the superoxide indicator hydroethidine 
(HE) 
41,58,59 and visualized by fluorescence microscopy. Briefly, freshly isolated 
primary rat microglia were treated in suspension as specified in Figure 7 legend. At 
the end of the treatment, cells were incubated with 1mM HE and 10 nM Sytox 
green nucleic acid stain for 20 min at 37 1C, centrifuged at 100 Â g, resuspended 
in 100 ml of PBS containing 2% FBS and analyzed immediately using a flow 
cytometer equipped with 488 nm laser for excitation (Accuri C6, BD Biosciences, 
San Diego, CA, USA). Data were collected using FL1 for Sytox green nucleic acid 
stain (530±15 nm) or FL2 channel for HE (585±20 nm). A minimum of 10 000 
cells were analyzed per condition. For time lapse microscopy, microglia seeded in 
slide chambers were loaded with 1 mM HE and 10 nM Sytox for 20 min, washed 
and subjected to LPS (0.1 ng/ml)/ zVAD-fmk (25 mM) stimulation. Images were 
manually acquired from the same chamber field at specified time points. To 
minimize photobleaching, cells were imaged with o0.5 s of exposure time for 
each filter. Fluorescence intensity of representative cells was analyzed with 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Image J</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">National Institutes of Health</rs>, Bethesda, MD, USA). </p>

<p>RIP3 mediates programmed necrosis in activated microglia 
SJ Kim and J Li </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Reverse transcription -PCR. Transcriptional expression levels of RIP1, 
RIP3, Iba1, TNFa, and b-actin in microglia upon stimulation with LPS and zVAD-
fmk were examined as described previously. 
57 Using Tri reagent, total RNA was 
extracted according to the manufacturer's instructions. Residual DNA was 
digested by incubating RNA samples with DNase I for 15 min at room temperature 
followed by DNase inactivation at 65 1C for 10 min according to the manufacturer's 
instructions (Invitrogen). The samples were reverse transcribed to cDNA using the 
reverse transcription system kit (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) as described 
previously. 
57 Primers specific for b-actin were used as a loading control. 
All products were amplified by PCR using 50 ng of cDNA and the following 
specific primers: RIP1, forward 5 
0 -GCACCAGCTGTCAGGGCCAG-3 
0 , reverse 
5 
0 -GCCCAGCTTTCGGGCACAGT-3 
0 ; RIP3, forward 5 
0 -ACCTTGGCTGGCACTC 
CCCA-3 
0 , reverse 5 
0 -CCCCTGCCGAACTGTGCTGG-3 
0 ; TNFa, forward 5 
0 -GCC 
CACGTCGTAGCAAAC-3 
0 , reverse 5 
0 -GCAGCCTTGTCCCTTGAA-3 
0 ; Iba1, for-
ward 5 
0 -CTTTTGGACTGCTGAAAGCC-3 
0 , reverse 5 
0 -GTTTCTCCAGCATTC 
GCTTC-3 
0 ; and b-actin, forward 5 
0 -AGACTTCGAGCAGGAGATGG-3 
0 , reverse 
5 
0 -CCATCATGAAGTGTGACGTTG-3 
0 . After the PCR reaction, products were 
electrophoresed on 2% agarose gels and visualized under UV light using a 
Bio-Rad Chemidoc XRS gel documentation system and <rs type="software">Quantity-one</rs> software. </p>

<p>TNFa ELISA. TNFa levels in culture supernatants were determined using a 
commercially available ELISA kit according to the manufacturer's instruction 
(eBioScience). Absorption at 450 nm was determined with a microplate reader 
(Fluostar Optima, BMG Labtech, Cary, NC, USA). The detection limits of the TNF 
ELISA were 8 pg/ml for mouse TNFa and 16 pg/ml for rat TNFa. </p>

<p>Transmission electron microscopy. After a quick wash with PBS, 
microglia were fixed in 1% glutaraldehyde and 4% paraformaldehyde (Electron 
Microscopy 225 Sciences, Hatflield, PA, USA) in 0.1 M, pH 7.4 phosphate buffer 
overnight at 4 1C. Following three washes with 8% sucrose in 0.1 M phosphate 
buffer, the cells were washed again in 0.1 M sodium cacodylate buffer 
and stained with 1% osmium tetroxide and 0.5% potassium ferrocyanide in 
0.5% sucrose for 1.5 h. The cells were then dehydrated in ascending 
alcohol series and embedded in epoxy resin. Ultrathin sections of microglia 
were examined using an FEI Morgagni 268 transmission electron microscope 
at an accelerating voltage of 80 kV. Digital images were acquired with a 
MegaViewIII camera operated with <rs id="software-2" type="software">iTEM</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Olympus Soft Imaging Systems</rs>, Germany). </p>

<p>Immunostaining, TUNEL and immunofluorescence microscopy. 
After the treatment, microglia were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde at room 
temperature for 10 min. Cells were rinsed three times with TBS, and blocked with 
TBS-T (0.1% Triton X-100) containing 5% goat serum for 1 h at room temperature. 
Primary antibody against Iba1 (1 : 2000) was used for detecting microglia. 
Antibody against cleaved, active casaspe-3 (1 : 1000) was used to evaluate 
caspase-3 activation. After overnight incubation at 4 1C, secondary antibodies 
conjugated with Alexa Fluor 488 or Alexa Fluor 594 (1 : 1000; Invitrogen) were 
used. Nuclei were stained with Hoechst 33342. To label fragmented DNA, 
TUNEL was performed using an in situ cell death detection kit (Roche, 
Indianapolis, IN, USA). All images were captured with an inverted fluorescence 
microscope equipped with an Olympus DP70 digital camera (model IX71; 
Olympus, Tokyo, Japan). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. All cell culture treatments were performed in at least 
triplicate samples. <rs type="software">GraphPad prism</rs> software (San Diego, CA, USA) was used for 
data analyses. Data were expressed as mean ± S.E.M. and analyzed by one-way 
ANOVA followed by Bonferroni's post hoc test unless stated otherwise. 
Differences were considered to be statistically significant when Po0.05. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest 
The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements. We are grateful to Dr. Xiaodong Wang and Dr. Astar 
Winoto for providing the RIP3-deficient mice; Dr. Monica Carson for the BV-2 cells, 
and Dr. Beiyan Zhou for allowing us to use her flow cytometer. We thank Dr. Ross 
Payne for his excellent technical support in TEM and Li lab members for technical 
assistance and discussions. This study was funded by research grants NS060017 </p>

<p>from the National Institutes of Health and RG3975 from the National Multiple 
Sclerosis Society. </p>



<p> 
SJ Kim and J Li </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>





<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

</text></tei>