<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3604266" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Endoscopic sinus surgery (ESS) is now a well-established strate-
gy for the treatment of chronic rhinosinusitis that has not re-
sponded to medical treatment [1]. Increased visualization, supe-
rior cosmesis, and decreased postoperative recovery time justify 
the use of ESS in almost all diseases of the paranasal sinuses [2]. </p>

<p>As the orbit and sinuses are in close proximity, orbital damage 
can sometimes occur during sinus surgery. Diplopia is one of the 
major orbital complications, and diplopia after ESS is usually 
caused by extraocular muscle (EOM) damage due to direct mus-
cle injury [3]. The most commonly injured EOM is the medial 
rectus muscle (MR), followed by the inferior rectus muscle (IR) 
and superior oblique muscle (SO) [4]. In addition, there is a re-
ported case of SO palsy that developed after frontal sinus mini-
trephine [5]. 
A navigation system for sinus surgery allows a relatively safe 
operation but has the disadvantages of high cost and a longer 
preparation time [3]. Failure to calibrate the instruments, com-
bined with overreliance on the given information, may result in 
misleading information, with a subsequent error in anatomic lo-
calization and a new list of complications. It should be noted </p>

<p>Objectives. This study aimed to investigate the anatomy of the intraorbital structures regarding to endoscopic sinus surgery 
and external frontal sinus surgery analyzing computer tomography (CT) scans. </p>

<p>Methods. The CT scans of 100 patients were retrospectively evaluated. The anatomic relationships between the intraorbital 
structures and paranasal structures were measured using multiplanar reconstruction of the CT scan. </p>

<p>Results. The mean distances from the medial orbital floor (MOF) to the intraorbital structures were measured at the depth 
of the anterior ethmoid (AE), basal lamella (BL), and midportion of posterior ethmoid (PE) in the coronal planes re-
spectively. The mean distances from the MOF to the medial rectus muscle and inferior rectus muscle at the depth of 
AE were approximately 8 mm and those distances in the BL and PE decreased rapidly. The mean distances from the 
MOF to the infraorbital nerve at the depth of the AE and BL were approximately more than 10 mm. The mean dis-
tances from the vertical axis, which passed through the MOF, to the superior oblique muscle and optic nerve at the 
depth of the PE were approximately 5 mm medially and 1 mm laterally. In addition, the mean distance from the mid-
line to the trochlea of the superior oblique muscle was approximately 15 mm. </p>

<p>Conclusions. Those measurements provide spatial information on the placements of the extraocular muscles within the or-
bit. The measurements will contribute to the avoidance of orbital complications during sinus surgery. </p>

<p>Keywords. Anatomy, Orbit, Endoscopy, Computer tomography, Landmark </p>

<p>• Received April 7, 2012 
Revision June 14, 2012 
Accepted June 26, 2012 </p>

<p>• Corresponding author: Jun Myung Kang 
Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Bucheon 
St. Mary's Hospital, The Catholic University of Korea College of Medicine, 
Sosa-ro 327 beon-gil, Wonmi-gu, Bucheon 420-717, Korea 
Tel: +82-32-340-7051, Fax: +82-32-340-2674 
E-mail: entkjm@catholic.ac.kr </p>

<p>pISSN 1976-8710 eISSN 2005-0720 </p>



<p>that despite technological advancements, a thorough knowledge 
of the complex endoscopic paranasal sinus and orbital anatomy 
gained through laboratory dissections and surgical experience 
remains the single most important factor for decreasing opera-
tive morbidity [6]. 
High resolution computed tomography (HRCT) of the orbit 
provides detailed information about the anatomy and location 
of a muscle relative to other structures [7]. Multiplanar imaging 
studies provide valuable information about the spatial relation-
ship and distance of the muscle [8]. However, although normal 
anatomy of the orbital structures as seen on CT is described in 
several studies [7,9,10], in a review of the literature we could 
not find reliable anatomic CT data on the anatomic relationship 
between the structures in the orbit and those in the paranasal si-
nuses, which may be important in helping to avoid orbital com-
plications such as diplopia during sinus surgery. This study aimed 
to investigate the anatomy of intraorbital structures, including 
the trochlea of the SO, with reference to ESS using multiplanar 
reconstruction of the CT scan. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Records from patients who had undergone diagnostic paranasal 
HRCT scans at our clinic between March 2010 and March 2011 
were examined retrospectively for this study. Patients with trau-
matic, neoplastic, or inflammatory lesions that destroyed the 
wall of the orbit were excluded. One hundred patients (38 males 
and 62 females, 200 sides) were involved in our study. The ages 
of the patients were between 19 and 78 years, with an average 
of 48 years. This study was approved by the Institutional Review 
Board of the Catholic Medical Center Clinical Research Coordi-
nating Center. 
HRCT scans were performed in 0.69 mm slices with a CT scan-
ner (Sensation 16, Siemens Medical Systems, Munich, Germa-
ny). After the imaging data were stored in a Digital Imaging and 
Communication in Medicine (<rs type="software">DICOM</rs>) file, they were imported 
to a personal computer. All scanning was performed at constant 
window level and width settings of 300 and 330 H, because ev-
ery change in the window level and width settings resulted in 
deviating values with respect to the muscle size on CT scan. The 
coronal reconstructions were modified using 3D-DOCTOR soft-
ware (Able Software Co., Lexington, MA, USA), so that the na-
sal floor in the coronal and sagittal planes was horizontal. Se-
quential coronal planes were observed using 3D-DOCTOR soft-
ware and simultaneous multiplanar reconstructions in bone al-
gorithm format were reconstructed in the axial and sagittal planes. 
The positions of the coronal plane on which the measurements 
were taken were defined as the AE (anterior wall of bulla eth-
moidalis that was removed first during anterior ethmoidecto-
my), BL (the basal lamella through which posterior ethmoidec-
tomy was performed), and PE (the midportion of the posterior </p>

<p>ethmoid sinus in the sagittal plane) in order to evaluate the in-
traorbital structures in view of the ethmoidectomy [11]. Through 
multiplanar reconstructions, the coronal planes that were equiv-
alent to the positions of the AE, BL, and PE were identified ex-
actly. 
To evaluate the relationship between the intraorbital struc-
tures and medial orbital floor (MOF), the distances from the 
MOF to the MR, IR, and infraorbital nerve (ION) were mea-
sured in separate coronal planes, which were equivalent to the 
position of the AE (Fig. 1), BL (Fig. 2), and PE (Fig. 3). In addi-
tion, the distances from the vertical line, which passed through 
the MOF, to the medial margin of the optic nerve (ON) were 
measured in each coronal plane at the depth of the AE, BL, and 
PE. The distances from the MOF to the SO and distances from 
the vertical line to the medial margin of the SO were measured 
at the depth of the BL and PE except the AE because the SO in 
coronal plane at the depth of the AE was tiny and ill-defined. 
The distances from the lamina papyracea (LP) to the MR and 
distance from the orbital floor to the IR were measured in the 
coronal planes at the depth of the AE because of increased width </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Multiplanar reconstruction of the computed tomography scan 
and measurements regarding the intraorbital structures at the depth 
of the AE. The AE (yellow line) was identified in the axial plane (A) 
and sagittal plane (B). The red line in the axial plane meant the posi­ 
tion of the sagittal plane and the blue line in the sagittal plane meant 
the level of the axial plane. The relationship between the intraorbital 
structures and the references points at the depth of the AE were mea­ 
sured in the coronal plane (C). (a) vertical distance from the MOF to 
the inferior margin of the MR; (b) vertical diameter of the MR; (c) hor­ 
izontal distances from the MOF to the medial margin of the IR; (d) 
horizontal distances from the vertical axis of MOF to the ION; (e) hor­ 
izontal distance from the vertical axis of the MOF to the orbit ball; (f) 
shortest horizontal distance from the lamina papyracea to the MR; 
(g) shortest vertical distance from the orbital floor to the IR. AE, ante­ 
rior wall of the ethmoid bulla; MOF, medial orbital floor (red point); 
MR, medial rectus muscle; IR, inferior rectus muscle; ION, infraorbit­ 
al nerve; dashed vertical line, the vertical axis of the MOF. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>f b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>g 
d </p>

<p>MR </p>

<p>IR 
ION </p>

<p>Hwang SH et al.: Anatomical Analysis of Intraorbital Structures Regarding Sinus Surgery 25 </p>

<p>of the extraconal fat pad between the EOM and orbital wall ad-
jacent to the AE (Fig. 1). 
To evaluate the position of the trochlea of the SO, the rela-
tionship between the trochlea and the opening of the frontal si-
nus (FO) was assessed in the parasagittal plane. The imaginary 
point, which was equivalent to the position of the trochlea coro-
nally and axially, was drawn in the parasagittal plane, which was 
equivalent to the midportion of the FO. The vertical distance 
from the frontal beak to imaginary point, anteroposterior dis-
tance from the anterior wall of the frontal sinus to imaginary 
point, and anteroposterior distance from the frontal beak to 
imaginary point were measured in the parasagittal plane. In ad-
dition, the horizontal distance from the midline to the trochlea 
was measured in the coronal plane, where the trochlea was iden-
tified (Fig. 4). Statistical analysis was done using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 18</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). Statistical comparisons between 
genders and laterality were performed using t-test. Pearson's 
correlations were applied to define the relationship of the mea-
surements with aging. A P-value of less than 0.05 was consid-
ered significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The mean vertical distances from the MOF to the MR at the 
depth of the AE, BL, and PE in the coronal scans were 7.3±1.4 
mm, 4.1±1.2 mm, and 2.9±0.9 mm, respectively. The mean 
horizontal distances from the MOF to the IR at the depth of the 
AE, BL, and PE were 9.0±1.4 mm, 2.5±1.5 mm, and -0.9±1.0 
mm, respectively. The mean horizontal distances from the MOF 
to the ION at the depth of AE, BL, and PE were 13.6±1.6 mm, 
12.0±1.1 mm, and 9.6±1.2 mm, respectively. The mean verti-
cal diameters of the MR at the depth of the AE, BL, and PE were 
8.5±0.8 mm, 8.8±0.8 mm, and 7.2±0.8 mm, respectively. The 
mean horizontal distances from the vertical axis, which passed 
through the MOF at the depth of the AE, BL, and PE, to the me-
dial margin of the ON were 5.6±1.3 mm, 4.8±1.5 mm, and 
1.0±1.2 mm, respectively. The mean vertical distances from the 
MOF to the SO at the depth of the BL and PE were 13.0±1.6 
mm and 9.3±1.4 mm, respectively. The mean horizontal dis-
tances from the vertical axis, which passed through the MOF at 
the depth of the BL and PE, to the medial margin of the SO were 
5.1±1.2 mm and 5.2±1.1 mm, respectively. The shortest hori-
zontal distance from the LP to the MR and the shortest vertical 
distance from the orbit floor to the IR at the depth of the AE 
were 3.0±0.6 mm and 3.8±1.1 mm, respectively. Those mea-
surements did not significantly vary according to gender, with </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Multiplanar reconstruction of the computed tomography scan 
and measurements regarding the intraorbital structures at the depth 
of the PE. The PE (yellow line) was identified in the axial plane (A) 
and sagittal plane (B). The red line in the axial plane meant the posi­ 
tion of the sagittal plane and the blue line in the sagittal plane meant 
the level of the axial plane. The relationship between intraorbital struc­ 
tures and the reference points at the depth of the PE were measured 
in the coronal plane (C). The distances (a­g) were measured at the 
depth of the PE using identical landmarks to the distances in Fig. 2. 
PE, midportion of posterior ethmoid; red point, medial orbital floor 
(MOF); dashed vertical line, the vertical axis of the MOF. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>e 
b </p>

<p>a 
c 
d </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Multiplanar reconstruction of the computed tomography scan 
and measurements regarding the intraorbital structures at the depth 
of the BL. The BL (yellow line) was identified in the axial plane (A) 
and sagittal plane (B). The red line in the axial plane meant the posi­ 
tion of the sagittal plane and the blue line in the sagittal plane meant 
the level of the axial plane. The relationship between intraorbital 
structures and the reference points at the depth of the BL were mea­ 
sured in the coronal plane (C). The distances (a­d) were measured 
at the depth of BL using identical landmarks to the distances in Fig. 
1. The distance (e) was the horizontal distance from the vertical axis 
of the MOF to the ON. The distance (f) was the horizontal distance 
from the vertical axis of the MOF to the medial margin of the SO and 
the distance (g) was the vertical distance from the MOF to the inferi­ 
or margin of the SO. BL, basal lamella; MOF, medial orbital floor, red 
point; SO, superior oblique muscle; ON, optic nerve; dash ed vertical 
line, the vertical axis of the MOF. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>g 
c </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>SO </p>

<p>ON 
b 
a </p>



<p>the exception of the vertical diameter of the MR, horizontal dis-
tance from the vertical axis to the ON at the depth of the AE, 
and vertical diameter of the MR at the depth of the PE (Table 1). 
In addition, those measurements did not significantly vary ac-
cording to laterality, with the exception of the distance from the 
orbit floor to the IR at the depth of the AE. 
The horizontal distance from the midline to the trochlea, ver-
tical distance from the frontal beak to imaginary point, antero-
posterior distance from the anterior frontal sinus wall to imagi-
nary point, and anteroposterior distance from the frontal beak 
to imaginary point were 16.1±1.4 mm, 8.9±2.1 mm, 5.0±1.3 
mm, and 2.1±1.7 mm, respectively. There was a significant dif-
ference between genders in the lateral distance from the midline 
to the trochlea and anteroposterior distance from the frontal 
beak to imaginary point (Table 2), while there was no significant 
difference between laterality in measurements regarding to the </p>

<p>trochlea. 
Aging had a positive correlation with the shortest horizontal 
distance from the LP to the MR and the shortest vertical dis-
tance from the orbit floor to the IR at the depth of the AE and 
horizontal distances from the MOF to the IR at the depth of BL. 
However, aging had a negative correlation with the anteroposte-
rior distance from the anterior frontal sinus wall to imaginary 
point (P&lt;0.05) (Table 3). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Orbital complications related to sinonasal surgery can be poten-
tially disastrous when they occur during ESS and are the com-
mon cause for medicolegal action in otolaryngology [4]. The com-
monly seen orbital complications include retrobulbar hemato-
ma, EOM injury or entrapment, ocular dysmotility, orbital em-
physema, nasolacrimal duct injury, and direct optic nerve dam-
age [10]. Complications associated with ESS have been attribut-
ed to multiple factors, including anatomic variations of "high 
risk" areas, surgeon inexperience, intraoperative disorientation, 
poor intraoperative visualization, and revision surgery. 
Several studies, including radiological anatomical studies, in 
relation to the anatomy of intraorbital structures have been pub-
lished [7,9,12,13]. However, the measurements in those studies 
are not sufficient to understand the anatomy of the EOM in view 
of sinus surgery because those were conducted for the diagnosis 
of the disease or the neurosurgical approach in the intraorbital 
tumor. In this study, the measurements of the EOM were con-
ducted in coronal computed tomography (CT) planes, which were 
simultaneously reconstructed in the axial and sagittal planes 
through multiplanar reconstructions in order to identify the ex-
act position in the coronal planes. 
The MOF is easily identifiable after the antrostomy without 
the additional procedures and consistent anatomic landmark 
which is not affected by the presence of significant inflammatory 
disease or previous surgery. These characteristics could provide 
even the most inexperienced surgeon with reliable information 
to find all of the paranasal sinuses and orbital structures. Be-
cause the MOF is a safe distance from the optic nerve, orbital 
roof, and sphenoid sinus roof, the surgeon can determine the 
surgeon's approximate location within the ethmoid sinus and 
operate in a zone of confidence [6]. In this study, the MOF was 
used as an anatomic reference point, and the relationships be-
tween intraorbital structures and the MOF were evaluated in the 
coronal plane. The distances from the MOF to the MR and IR at 
the depth of the AE were approximately 8 mm, and those dis-
tances at the depth of the BL and PE decreased markedly. In ad-
dition, the shortest mean distance from the orbital wall to the 
MR and IR at the depth of the AE was approximately 3 or 4 mm, 
and those structures were attached to the orbital wall behind 
the BL. During anterior ethmoidectomy and widening of the </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Multiplanar reconstruction of the computed tomography scan 
and measurements regarding the trochlea of the SO. To evaluate the 
relationship between the surrounding structures and the trochlea, 
the coronal, axial, and parasagittal planes were observed. The red 
line and yellow line in the axial plane meant the position of the sagit­ 
tal plane and coronal plane separately and the blue line in the coro­ 
nal plane meant the level of the axial plane. The distance (a) was 
the horizontal distance between the midline and trochlea and well 
identified in axial (A) and coronal (B) planes. In the parasagittal plane 
(C) that was located at the midpoint of the frontal sinus opening, an 
imaginary point (P) that was parallel to the trochlea in position and 
level was drawn. The distance (b) was the vertical distance from P 
to the frontal beak. The distances (c) and (d) were the anteroposteri­ 
or distances from P to the anterior frontal sinus wall and frontal beak, 
separately. SO, superior oblique muscle; T, trochlea. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>a T 
T </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>c b </p>

<p>Hwang SH et al.: Anatomical Analysis of Intraorbital Structures Regarding Sinus Surgery 27 </p>

<p>antrostomy, the EOM would be difficult to injure with penetra-
tion of the LP or orbital floor with a sickle knife or cutting for-
ceps, because there is some distance from the orbital wall to the 
EOM at the depth of AE. However, the distance between the 
MOF and EOM in BL and PE decreased rapidly. In particular, 
the mean horizontal distance from the MOF to the IR was ap-
proximately -1 mm, which meant that the medial margin of the 
IR passed over the vertical axis of MOF medially. Considering </p>

<p>these results, the injury of the LP at the depth of the PE can cause 
injury of the EOM, and posterior ethmoidectomy must be cau-
tiously performed even in the inferior portion of the posterior 
ethmoid sinus [3]. 
During ethmoidectomy, failure to correctly identify the LP 
can misdirect the surgeon with disastrous consequences for the 
patient, and the recognition of the medial bulging of the LP in 
the ethmoid sinus is important to prevent injury of the LP. In </p>

<p>Table 1. Linear measurements in relation to the extraocular muscles and optic nerve and globe </p>

<p>Measurements (mm) 
Total (sides=200) 
Male (sides=76) 
Female (sides=124) 
Unpaired t­test (P­value) </p>

<p>Anterior ethmoid 
MR­MOF 
7.3±1.4 (4.0­10.0) 
7.3±1.5 
7.3±1.4 
0.865 
MR­LP 
3.0±0.6 (1.5­4.9) 
3.0± 0.5 
3.0±0.6 
0.993 
MR VD 
8.5±0.8 (6.5­11.0) 
8.7±0.8 
8.4±0.9 
0.017* 
IR­MOF 
9.0±1.4 (4.3­12.4) 
9.1±1.6 
9.0±1.3 
0.821 
IR­OF 
3.8±1.1 (1.5­8.1) 
3.8±1.3 
3.8±1.1 
0.854 
ION­MOF 
13.6±1.6 (9.9­18.0) 
14.0±1.8 
13.5±1.6 
0.06 
Vertical axis­ON 
5.6±1.3 (2.2­9.8) 
6.0±1.5 
5.4±1.3 
0.008* 
Basal lamella 
MR­MOF 
4.1±1.2 (1.0­7.0) 
3.9±1.3 
4.2±1.2 
0.157 
MR VD 
8.8±0.8 (6.7­11.1) 
8.9±0.9 
8.7±0.8 
0.143 
IR­MOF 
2.5±1.5 (0.0­6.0) 
2.8±1.8 
2.6±1.8 
0.326 
ION­MOF 
12.0±1.1 (9.3­16) 
12.1±1.0 
11.9±1.2 
0.271 
SO­MOF 
13.0±1.6 (9.7­17.7) 
13.3±1.7 
12.8±1.5 
0.067 
Vertical axis­SO 
5.1±1.2 (2.8­8.0) 
5.0±1.2 
5.1±1.3 
0.807 
Vertical axis­ON 
4.8±1.5 (1.5­8.4) 
4.9±1.4 
4.7±1.6 
0.542 
Posterior ethmoid 
MR­MOF 
2.9±0.9 (1.0­5.5) 
2.9±1.0 
3.0±0.8 
0.422 
MR VD 
7.2±0.8 (5.2­9.5) 
7.4±1.0 
7.0±0.8 
0.007* 
IR­MOF 
­0.9±1.0 (­4.2­1.4) 
­0.8±1.0 
­0.9±1.0 
0.258 
ION­MOF 
9.6±1.2 (7.0­13.0) 
9.5±1.3 
9.6±1.1 
0.867 
SO­MOF 
9.3±1.4 (6.4­14.6) 
9.5±1.8 
9.2±1.3 
0.214 
Vertical axis­SO 
5.2±1.1 (2.5­7.3) 
5.3±0.9 
5.1±1.1 
0.169 
Vertical axis­ON 
1.0±1.2 (­2.0­3.9) 
1.2±1.1 
0.8±1.2 
0.063 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±SD (range). 
MR­MOF, the vertical distance from the inferior margin of the medical rectus muscle to the medial orbital floor; MR­LP, the shortest horizontal distance from 
the lamina papyracea to the medial rectus muscle; MR VD, the vertical diameter of the medical rectus muscle; IR­MOF, the horizontal distance from the 
medial margin of the inferior rectus muscle to the medial orbital floor; IR­OF, the shortest vertical distance from the orbital floor to the inferior rectus muscle; 
ION­MOF, the horizontal distance from the infraorbital nerve to the medial orbital floor; SO­MOF, the vertical distance from the inferior margin of the superior 
oblique muscle to the medial orbital floor; vertical axis­SO, the horizontal distance from vertical axis of the medial orbital floor to the medial margin of the 
superior oblique muscle; vertical axis­ON, the horizontal distance from vertical axis of the medial orbital floor to the medial margin of the optic nerve. 
*P &lt;0.05. </p>

<p>Table 2. Linear measurements in relation to the surrounding structures and trochlea of the superior oblique muscle </p>

<p>Measurements (mm) 
Total (sides=200) 
Male (sides=76) 
Female (sides=124) 
Unpaired t­test </p>

<p>Trochlea­midline 
16.1±1.4 (13.0­20.0) 
16.5±1.5 
15.8±1.3 
&lt;0.001* 
Trochlea­FB height 
8.9±2.1 (4.0­14.0) 
9.0±2.1 
8.8±2.1 
0.692 
Trochlea­FB AP 
2.1±1.7 (­1.9­6.1) 
2.5±1.9 
1.9±1.5 
0.014* 
Trochlea­AW 
5.0±1.3 (2.0­8.3) 
5.2±1.4 
4.8±1.2 
0.065 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±SD. 
Trochlea­midline, the horizontal distance from the midline to the trochlea; trochlea­FB height, the vertical distance from the frontal beak to the imaginary 
point; trochlea­FB AP, the anteroposterior distance from the frontal beak to the imaginary point; trochlea­AW, the anteroposterior distance from the anterior 
frontal sinus wall to the imaginary point. 
*P &lt;0.05. </p>



<p>Table 3. Correlation of the aging with anatomic measurements </p>

<p>Coefficient 
P­value* </p>

<p>MR­LP (anterior ethmoid) 
0.165 
0.03 
IR­OF (anterior ethmoid) 
0.249 
0.001 
IR­MOF (basal lamella) 
0.163 
0.032 
Trochlea­AW 
­0.243 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>MR­LP, the shortest horizontal distance from the lamina papyracea to the 
medial rectus muscle; IR­OF, the shortest vertical distance from the orbital 
floor to the inferior rectus muscle; IR­MOF, the horizontal distance from the 
medial margin of the inferior rectus muscle to the medial orbital floor; tro­ 
chlea­AW, the anteroposterior distance from the anterior frontal sinus wall 
to the imaginary point. 
*P &lt;0.05. </p>

<p>our study, the horizontal distance from the vertical axis, which 
passed the MOF to the SO, which runs along the superolateral 
portion of the LP, was measured in order to evaluate the degree 
of medial bulging of the LP. The mean horizontal distances from 
the vertical axis to the SO at the depth of the BL and PE were 
approximately 5.1 mm. The mean horizontal distances from the 
vertical axis to the ON at the depth of the AE and BL area were 
similar (5.6 mm and 4.8 mm), but the mean horizontal distance 
from the vertical axis to the ON at the depth of the PE was 1.0 
mm. The range of this measurement at the depth of the PE was 
from -2.0 mm to 3.9 mm. These results meant that the ON at 
the depth of the PE was located near the MOF or, even, medial 
to the vertical axis of the MOF. Considering the distances from 
the vertical axis of the MOF to the SO and ON, we assumed 
that posterior ethmoidectomy should be performed more medi-
ally, relative to the vertical axis of the MOF; otherwise, penetra-
tion of the LP could occur and lead to injury of the ON as well 
as the EOM. 
The ION is a branch of the trigeminal nerve, continues along 
the orbital floor from the pterygopalatine fossa to the anterior 
wall of the maxilla, and appears on the face through the infraor-
bital foramen [14]. The ION is used as the landmark for endo-
scopic orbital decompression and endoscopic approach of the 
pterygopalatine fossa [15,16]. In our study, the horizontal dis-
tances from the MOF to the ION at the depth of the AE and BL 
were approximately more than 10 mm. Those results could sup-
port the concept that it would be difficult to injure the ION by 
orbital floor removal in endoscopic orbital decompression [15]. 
The SO takes a circuitous route, beginning at the orbital apex, 
passing anterosuperiorly along the orbital roof and into the tro-
chlear fossa at the superomedial aspect of the anterior orbit. 
There it passes through the trochlea, a U-shaped cartilaginous 
structure, at which point the SO tendon turns at an acute angle 
toward its insertion on the superolateral aspect of the globe [17]. 
Comparing the height of the inferior margin of the SO to the 
height of the superior margin of the MR (the sum of the vertical 
diameter of the MR and the vertical distance between the MOF 
and MR), the difference between the two measurements was ap-
proximately less than 1 mm in the BL and PE. Considering the </p>

<p>neurovascular bundles that run medially between the SO and 
MR [18], injury of the superior aspect of the MR would cause 
injury of the neurovascular structures as well as the SO. 
Frontal sinus disease, which was typically managed with ex-
ternal procedures, is now usually managed endoscopically. De-
spite endoscopic advances, an external procedure or combined 
internal-external approach may still be required. Although the 
position of the trochlea is not usually considered when design-
ing an incision or entering the frontal sinus during an external 
procedure such as a frontal sinus mini-trephine or an osteoplas-
tic flap, the location of the skin incision and tearing of the un-
derlying periosteum are critical to the trochlea damage causing 
the SO palsy [5]. It was known that the damage to the trochlea 
could occur as the periosteum is elevated from bone or prolong-
ed traction on soft tissue near the trochlea. The position of troch-
lea is located in close proximity to the supraorbital rim and the 
soft tissue thickness overlying the supraorbital rim is approxi-
mately 6 mm [19]. A highly vascular sheath which meets the need 
for repair of "wear and tear" surrounds the trochlea and the 
tendon of SO. The skin incision which may be located in more 
laterally than the periosteal incision would cause prolonged or 
inappropriate traction on soft tissue and direct injury of the tro-
chlea and vascular sheath. However, there is little description 
regarding the position of the trochlea in frontal sinus surgery. 
Based on the fact that the trochlea lie on the superior wall of 
the orbit, which is surrounded by the frontal sinus, the relation-
ships between the trochlea and frontal sinus were evaluated on 
coronal, axial, and sagittal plane. Considering that placing the 
skin incision more medially reduces the risk of potential damage 
[5], our results showed that the surgeon could perform the skin 
incision safely within approximately 1.5 cm from the midline 
during external frontal sinus surgery. In addition, the frontal beak 
which could be identified in the internal approach could supple-
ment the limitation of the facial midline which is likely to be af-
fected by the anatomy of the nasal bones and cartilage and vary 
considerably among ethnicities and individuals [20]. These mea-
surements, which located the exact position of the trochlea in 
the frontal sinus using the midline and frontal beak, could help 
predict the position and avoid injury of the trochlear due to in-
advertent tearing of the underlying periosteum during an exter-
nal procedure [5]. 
The comparisons of the measurements between genders show-
ed that some measurements statistically vary according to gen-
ders. However, there would be clinically no differences in the 
measurements according to the gender because of within 1 mm 
differences. In the anatomical studies regarding aging changes of 
orbital fat, the volume of total orbital fat and fat anterior to the 
inferior orbital rim increased with age [21]. Considering these 
results, anatomic changes of the aging orbital fat could affect the 
relationship between the intraorbital structures and anatomic 
landmarks. In this study, the distance from the EOM to the or-
bital wall at the depth of the AE increased with age and the oth-</p>

<p>Hwang SH et al.: Anatomical Analysis of Intraorbital Structures Regarding Sinus Surgery 29 </p>

<p>er measurements showed no correlation with age. Since the or-
bital cavity is filled with orbital fat and is surrounded by orbital 
bone except the anterior portion, the globe and ON would be 
pushed anteriorly and move superiorly and laterally from the 
orbital wall. Those characteristics of the orbital cavity could in-
fluence on the distances from the EOM to the orbital wall at the 
depth of the AE. The size of the frontal sinus had a tendency to 
decrease with aging [22]. We showed that aging had a negative 
correlation with the anteroposterior distance from the anterior 
frontal sinus wall to imaginary point. 
To our knowledge, this study is the first to describe the rela-
tionship of the paranasal structures and intraorbital structures 
has been described in this manner. The anatomical knowledge 
regarding the intraorbital structures allows the surgeon to be in-
dependent of intuition and to learn the anatomically based pro-
cedures and notices for sinus surgery. Our results may be used 
as a reference to avoid orbital complications. 
In conclusions, We have described the relationships between 
the intraorbital structures and paranasal sinus structures using 
the analysis of CT scans. In view of sinus surgery, the measure-
ments of extraocular structures can reliably serve as a guide to 
safely advance in the ethmoid sinus and frontal sinus, and our 
results will allow surgeons to avoid orbital complications during 
ESS and external frontal sinus surgery. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was re-
ported. </p>



</text></tei>