<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3661168" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase (IDO) is a cytosolic protein that 
catalyzes the rate-limiting step of human tryptophan (Trp) 
metabolism. Trp depletion induces effector T cells to undergo 
a G 1 cell cycle arrest 1 and triggers an integrated stress response 
pathway that involves general control nonrepressed 2 (GCN2) 
signaling and eukaryotic initiation factor 2α (eIF2α) phosphory-
lation. 2,3 IDO also causes systemic anergy by inducing naive </p>

<p>Indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase (IDO) has recently been proposed to account for tumor-induced immunosuppression 
by influencing the conversion of tryptophan (Trp) into kynurenine (Kyn). The objective of our study was to correlate 
IDO activity with disease outcome in non-small cell lung cancer (NscLc) patients treated with multimodal combination 
therapy. In a single-arm phase II trial involving induction gemcitabine and carboplatin followed by concurrent paclitaxel, 
carboplatin and 74 Gy thoracic radiation in stage III NscLc patients, plasma was drawn at baseline, post-induction, 
and post-concurrent therapy. The mean plasma Kyn/Trp ratio was used as a surrogate indicator of IDO activity. The 33 
participants were distributed as follows: 15 females, 18 males; median age = 62; median overall survival (Os) = 22.4 (95% 
cI 19.3-25.1) months; median progression-free survival (pFs) = 11.5 (95% cI 6.7-16.3) months. The mean Kyn/Trp ratio at 
baseline (4.5 ± 2.8) was higher than that of healthy controls (2.9 ± 1.9, p = 0.03) and increased after induction therapy (5.2 
± 3.2, p = 0.08) and chemoradiation (5.8 ± 3.9, p = 0.01). The post-treatment Kyn/Trp ratio and radiologic responses were 
not significantly associated at any time point. No significant correlation was found between baseline Kyn/Trp ratios and 
Os (hR = 1.1, 95% cI 0.45-2.5) or pFs (hR = 0.74, 95% cI 0.30-1.82). a post-induction chemotherapy increase in IDO activity 
portended worse Os (hR = 0.43, 95% cI 0.19-0.95, p = 0.037) and pFs (hR = 0.47, 95% cI 0.22-1.0, p = 0.055). This observed 
increase in IDO transcription may be a means for tumors to evade immunosurveillance. </p>

<p>Indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase activity and clinical 
outcome following induction chemotherapy 
and concurrent chemoradiation in Stage III 
non-small cell lung cancer </p>

<p>Ben c. creelan, 1, * scott antonia, 2 Gerold Bepler, 3 Timothy J. Garrett, 4 George R. simon 5 and hatem h. soliman 2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>University of south Florida; Tampa, FL Usa; 2 h. Lee Moffitt cancer center; Tampa, FL Usa; 3 Karmanos cancer Institute; Wayne state University; Detroit, MI Usa; 
4 University of Florida; Gainesville, FL Usa; 5 MD anderson cancer center; houston, TX Usa </p>

<p>Keywords: indoleamine 2,3 dioxygenase, innate immunity, kynurenine, non-small cell lung cancer, tryptophan </p>

<p>Abbreviations: AJCC, American joint committee on cancer; AUC, area under the curve; BIN1, bridging integrator 1; 
CI, confidence interval; CT, computed tomography; CTLA-4, cytotoxic T-lymphocyte antigen 4; 
D-1MT, 1-methyl-D-tryptophan; ECOG, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group; GCN-2, general control nonrepressed 2; 
HPLC, high performance liquid chromatography; HR, hazard ratio; IDO, indoleamine 2,3 dioxygenase; IFN, interferon; 
IHC, immunohistochemistry; ILT, immunoglobulin-like transcript; IPMN, intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasm; 
Kyn, kynurenine; MS, mass spectrometry; mTOR, mammalian target of rapamycin; NCT, national clinical trial; 
NSCLC, non-small cell lung cancer; OS, overall survival; PET, positron emission tomography; PFS, progression-free survival; 
PKCΘ, protein kinase C Θ; RECIST, response evaluation criteria in solid tumors; STAT1, signal transducer and activator of 
transcription 1; TGF, transforming growth factor; TIL, tumor-infiltrating lymphocyte; Trp, tryptophan </p>

<p>T cells to differentiate into CD4 + CD25 + FOXP3 + regulatory 
T cells. 4 Dendritic cells respond to low Trp levels by upregulat-
ing inhibitory factors such as immunoglobulin-like transcript 3 
(ILT3), ILT4 and transforming growth factor β1 (TGF-β1), thus 
becoming immunosuppressive. 5 Moreover, Trp metabolites such 
as kynurenine (Kyn), quinolinic acid, and picolinic acid exert 
cytotoxic effects on CD8 + tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes (TILs) 
and CD4 + T H 1 cells. 6,7 The IDO-mediated deprivation of Trp 
also inhibits the immunomodulatory kinases mammalian target </p>

<p>e23428-2 </p>

<p>OncoImmunology 
Volume 2 Issue 3 </p>

<p>anticancer vaccines. 11,12 Cancer cells bearing mutations in the 
oncosuppressor gene BIN1 are stimulated by interferon γ (IFNγ) 
to overexpress IDO, leading to increased intracellular levels of 
signal transducer and activator of transcription 1 (STAT1) and 
nuclear factor κB (NFκB). 13 Thus, IDO may be an important 
stimulator of immune tolerance in human cancer. 
Non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) is an aggressive epithe-
lial malignancy that often overexpresses the mRNA coding for 
IDO. 14 NSCLC has an annual incidence of 1.61 million people 
worldwide, 15,16 and 83 percent of NSCLC patients will even-
tually die of their cancer. 16 Locoregionally-advanced NSCLC 
comprises more than one-third of cases at presentation and is 
classified as Stage III. 17 Over three quarters of Stage III NSCLC 
patients are technically or medically inoperable. 18 Chemotherapy 
and concurrent radiation is the standard therapy for inoper-
able Stage III NSCLC, but the five year overall survival (OS) 
remains poor, that is, 20% and 8% for IIIA and IIIB disease, 
respectively. 19 Such an aggressive malignant phenotype has been 
hypothesized to stem from an innate resistance of NSCLC to 
chemotherapy 20,21 and to its ability to evade immunosurveil-
lance. 22,23 However, the role of IDO in mediating immune toler-
ance in NSCLC is unclear. 
Trp catabolism in lung cancer patients is associated with 
advanced disease stage. 24,25 This said, how IDO activity changes </p>

<p>of rapamycin (mTOR) and protein kinase C Θ (PKCΘ), thereby 
inhibiting autophagy. 8 In fact, IDO is overexpressed by many 
human cancers 9 and may serve as an escape mechanism from host 
immunity. 10 For example, in humans and animals, the induc-
tion of IDO limits the immune response to dendritic cell-based </p>

<p>Figure 1. Trial flow diagram. Induction chemotherapy: gemcitabine and 
carboplatin. Thoracic radiation: 74 Gy conformal. concurrent chemo-
therapy: paclitaxel and carboplatin. </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographics and baseline measurements </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Patients n (%) 
Kyn (μM) Mean ± SD 
Trp (μM) Mean ± SD 
Kyn/Trp (μM/μM) Mean ± SD </p>

<p>Total 
33 
1.6 ± 0.8 
37.9 ± 8.5 
4.5 ± 2.8 </p>

<p>Age in years (Median ± sD) 
62.4 ± 7.9 </p>

<p>age &lt; 65 y 
19 (58) 
1.6 ± 0.9 
40.3 ± 8.2 
4.0 ± 2.3 </p>

<p>age 65 y 
14 (42) 
1.6 ± 0.7 
34.7 ± 8.1 
5.1 ± 3.3 </p>

<p>Race </p>

<p>caucasian 
31 (94) 
1.6 ± 0.8 
37.9 ± 8.8 
4.6 ± 2.8 </p>

<p>asian 
1 (3) 
0.9 
36.5 
2.5 </p>

<p>Black 
1 (3) 
1.1 
37.9 
2.9 </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Female 
15 (45) 
1.6 ± 0.8 
36.3 ± 8.0 
4.9 ± 2.3 </p>

<p>Male 
18 (55) 
1.5 ± 0.8 
38.9 ± 8.9 
4.2 ± 1.9 </p>

<p>ECOG* performance status </p>

<p>ps 0 
11 (33) 
1.5 ± 1.0 
37.4 ± 10.7 
5.5 ± 2.3 </p>

<p>ps 1 
22 (66) 
1.6 ± 0.7 
38.0 ± 8.0 
4.6 ± 1.6 </p>

<p>Smoking status </p>

<p>active smoker 
12 (36) 
1.7 ± 0.8 
38.6 ± 7.7 
4.5 ± 3.1 </p>

<p>Former smoker 
21 (64) 
1.5 ± 0.8 
37.4 ± 9.3 
4.4 ± 2.3 </p>

<p>AJCC  § clinical stage </p>

<p>IIIa 
16 (48) 
1.6 ± 0.9 
38.2 ± 9.2 
4.7 ± 2.7 </p>

<p>IIIB 
17 (52) 
1.6 ± 0.7 
37.5 ± 8.0 
4.3 ± 2.2 </p>

<p>Histotype of NSCLC </p>

<p>adenocarcinoma 
11 (33) 
1.5 ± 0.7 
37.4 ± 7.2 
4.0 ± 1.3 </p>

<p>squamous cell 
10 (30) 
1.4 ± 0.8 
39.7 ± 7.4 
3.8 ± 3.3 </p>

<p>Other  ‡ 
12 (36) 
1.8 ± 0.8 
36.9 ± 10.7 
5.3 ± 2.3 </p>

<p>*eastern cooperative Oncology Group.  § american Joint committee on cancer.  ‡ Includes bronchoalveolar, large cell and "not otherwise specified." No 
statistically significant mean difference was detected for any comparison of the groups presented (p &lt; 0.05, Wilcoxon rank-sum test). </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>OncoImmunology 
e23428-3 </p>

<p>ratios at Time 2, with p = 0.19 (Fig. 4B). To index the shift in 
IDO activity after chemotherapy, the differences in Kyn/Trp 
ratios between Time 0 and Time 1 (ΔIDO 1 ) and between Time 1 
and Time 2 (ΔIDO 2 ) were calculated. Participants were subdi-
vided into two groups based on the median ΔIDO value. Using 
RECIST to define the percentage of response, a non-significant 
trend was observed between radiologic responses at Time 1 and 
ΔIDO 1 (Fig. 5). 
Median OS was 22.4 mo (95% CI 19.3-25.1) and median pro-
gression-free survival (PFS) 11.5 mo (95% CI 6.7-16.3) (Table 2). </p>

<p>after chemotherapy or radiation in NSCLC patients is unclear. 
The abrogation of BIN1 causes IDO overexpression and promotes 
NSCLC in animals. 26 NSCLC-infiltrating lymphocytes are often 
anergic and hypoproliferative, 27 and the overexpression of IDO 
in the NSCLC peritumoral stroma is associated with poor prog-
nosis. 28 Based on the these observations, we hypothesized that 
IDO activity may increase in Stage III NSCLC patients undergo-
ing conventional multimodal therapy. Since Kyn is the primary 
metabolite of Trp metabolism, the plasma Kyn/Trp ratio has been 
used as a surrogate indicator of IDO activity. 29,30 Our objective 
was to prospectively correlate serial changes in IDO activity, as 
measured by the plasma Kyn/Trp ratio, with radiologic response 
and survival in NSCLC patients treated with multimodal therapy. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Forty-three participants were enrolled from December 2003 to 
February 2006. Of 39 participants initiated on treatment, 33 had 
plasma drawn at Time 0 evaluable for mass spectrometry (Fig. 1). 
We observed no trends between baseline plasma metabolites and 
demographic features such as age, race, gender, and performance 
status (Table 1). Moreover, we observed no correlations between 
baseline plasma markers and tumor characteristics such as his-
tology or clinical stage. However, these correlative studies were 
limited by a relatively low statistical power. To assess the presence 
of outliers, we used a formal outlier test, the extreme studentized 
deviate (ESD) method with p &lt; 0.05, which identified one out-
lier at time 0 (14.5 with z = 3.6) and no outliers at Time 1 and 
Time 2. To further assess the influence of outliers, we examined 
the clinicopathologic features of the six participants displaying 
the highest Kyn/Trp ratio at Time 0 and Time 1 compared with 
the rest the cohort. No statistically significant differences in age, 
survival, tumor burden, chemotherapy response, white blood 
count and serum albumin was observed. 
Compared with a sample of 24 healthy controls (2.9 ± 1.9), 
participants had higher mean Kyn/Trp ratio at baseline (4.5 ± 2.8, 
p = 0.03) (Fig. 2). Mean plasma Kyn/Trp ratios increased after 
induction chemotherapy (Time 0 to Time 1, 5.2 ± 3.2, p = 0.08), 
and after concurrent definitive chemoradiation (Time 1 to 
Time 2, 5.8 ± 3.9, p = 0.01). No correlation was observed 
between baseline plasma Kyn/Trp ratios and primary tumor 
cross-sectional area (r = 0.10, 95% CI −0.27-0.43) or total cross-
sectional area of all target lesions on CT (CT) (r = 0.02, 95% 
CI −0.33-0.37) (Fig. 3A). Likewise, no appreciable correlation 
was observed between changes in plasma Kyn/Trp ratios from 
Time 0 to Time 1 (ΔIDO 1 ) and changes in primary tumor cross-
sectional area (r = -0.25, 95% CI −0.56-0.12) or changes in total 
cross-sectional area of all target lesions on CT (r = −0.17, 95% 
CI −0.50-0.20) (Fig. 3B). 
After induction chemotherapy, we observed one complete 
response, 11 partial responses and 21 patients with stable disease. 
Using response evaluation criteria in solid tumors (RECIST), 
a non-statistically significant association was observed between 
improved radiologic responses and plasma Kyn/Trp ratios at 
Time 1, with p = 0.34 (Fig. 4A). A similar non-significant trend 
was observed between radiologic responses and plasma Kyn/Trp </p>

<p>Figure 2. plasma metabolites in stage III non-small cell lung can-
cer patients. (A) plasma kynurenine (Kyn) concentration. (B) plasma 
tryptophan (Trp) concentration. (C) plasma Kyn/Trp ratios, a surrogate 
for indoleamine 2,3 dioxygenase (IDO) activity. plasma IDO activity 
was higher in non-small cell lung cancer (NscLc) patients at baseline 
(Time 0) than in healthy individuals. plasma IDO activity increased 
after induction carboplatin/gemcitabine (Time 1) and after concurrent 
carboplatin/paclitaxel with thoracic radiation (Time 2). Bars: Median 
with interquartile range. For healthy individuals vs. Time 0: Wilcoxon 
rank-sum test. For Time 0 vs. Time 1 and Time 1 vs. Time 2: Wilcoxon 
signed-rank test.  ‡ p &lt; 0.10; *p &lt; 0.05;  † † p &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>e23428-4 </p>

<p>OncoImmunology 
Volume 2 Issue 3 </p>

<p>carcinoma, melanoma, 32 colorectal carcinoma, 33 esophageal 
cancer, 34,35 thyroid carcinoma, 36 acute myelogenous leukemia, 37 
breast cancer 38 and gynecologic cancer 29 patients. This observa-
tion lends credence to the hypothesis that cancer cells may stimu-
late dendritic cells to express IDO or may directly overexpress 
the enzyme. Indeed, NSCLCs exhibit high Trp metabolism as 
monitored by α-methyl-tryptophan positron emission tomogra-
phy (PET) imaging as compared with normal tissues. 39 We could 
not observe a strong correlation between baseline tumor sizes and 
Kyn/Trp ratios, or a strong correlation between changes in tumor 
size and changes in Kyn/Trp ratios. This suggests that Kyn/Trp 
ratios are unlikely to be determined by the tumor burden alone. 
Consistent with previous observations in NSCLC patients, 24 
we did not find a correlation between baseline IDO activity and 
survival. Several authors have examined the relationship between 
IDO activity and survival in other cancers (Table 3). Of inter-
est, studies based on the immunohistochemical detection of IDO 
more often reported an unfavorable role for IDO than stud-
ies based on the detection of IDO mRNA levels (16:1 vs 1:6, </p>

<p>Baseline Kyn/Trp ratios were not significantly associated with OS 
(HR = 0.88, 95% CI 0.41-1.35). After induction chemotherapy 
at Time 1, patients with high ΔIDO 1 had worse OS (p = 0.037) 
and a trend toward worse PFS (p = 0.055) as compared with indi-
viduals with low ΔIDO 1 (Fig. 6). However, no association was 
found after chemoradiation between ΔIDO 2 and OS (HR = 1.1, 
95% CI 0.45-2.5) or PFS (HR = 0.74, 95% CI 0.30-1.82). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>To our knowledge, this is the first report to serially explore 
changes in plasma IDO activity during the treatment of Stage III 
NSCLC patients, as measured by Kyn/Trp ratios. We found 
that IDO activity was higher in cancer patients than in healthy 
individuals, consistent with previous observations in lung can-
cer, 24,25,31 bladder cancer, hepatocellular carcinoma, renal cell </p>

<p>Figure 3. correlation between tumor burden and indoleamine 2,3 dioxygenase activity. (A) correlation between cross-sectional tumor burden and 
plasma kynurenine/tryptophan (Kyn/Trp) ratio. n = 33, r = 0.02 (95% cI −0.33-0.37). (B) correlation between changes in cross-sectional tumor burden 
and changes in plasma Kyn/Trp ratios after induction carboplatin/gemcitabine (Time 1 − Time 0). n = 32, r = −0.17 (95% cI −0.50-0.20). Total burden 
represents the sum of cross-sectional areas for primary tumor and all target lymph nodes. cross-sectional area represents the product of the longest 
tumor diameter and its perpendicular axis. r = spearman's rank correlation coefficient. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Radiologic response and plasma kynurenine/tryptophan 
ratio after induction therapy (Time 1) and after concurrent carboplatin/ 
paclitaxel therapy coupled to thoracic radiation (Time 2). Bars: median, 
interquartile range. n.s. = non significant (Wilcoxon rank-sum). cR, 
complete response; pD, progressive disease; pR, partial response; sD, 
stable disease. </p>

<p>Table 2. summary of results </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Time 0 
Time 1 
Time 2 </p>

<p>N 
33 
32 
27 </p>

<p>Analytes (mean ± sD) </p>

<p>Kyn (μM) 
1.59 ± 0.77 
1.58 ± 0.73 
2.05 ± 1.25 </p>

<p>Trp (μM) 
37.9 ± 8.5 
34.1 ± 8.7 
35.2 ± 6.7 </p>

<p>Kyn/Trp (μM/μM) 
4.5 ± 2.8 
5.15 ± 3.12 
6.11 ± 4.02 </p>

<p>Radiology </p>

<p>primary tumor area (cm 2 ) 
18.7 ± 17.9 
11.0 ± 10.4 
5.5 ± 4.7 </p>

<p>Total tumor area (cm 2 ) 
27.6 ± 19.2 
16.1 ± 12.0 
7.4 ± 5.5 </p>

<p>Survival 
Median 
95% CI 
Events </p>

<p>pFs (mo) 
11.5 
(6.7-16.3) 
29/33 </p>

<p>Os (mo) 
22.2 
(19.2-25.1) 
27/33 </p>

<p>pFs, progression-free survival; Os, overall survival; cI, confidence inter-
val; sD, standard deviation; Mo, months. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>OncoImmunology 
e23428-5 </p>

<p>Fischer's exact p = 0.0003). This difference may reflect a post-
transcriptional regulation of IDO. Our study also examined the 
relationship between changes in IDO activity and disease out-
come. Our results suggest that a high increase in IDO activity 
after chemotherapy is associated with a higher risk of mortal-
ity. A possible explanation for our findings is that the expression 
of IDO by tumor cells may mediate-at least in part-resis-
tance to chemotherapy. 40 Along these lines, it has recently been 
reported that a subset of NSCLC patients with favorable radio-
logic responses after chemotherapy exhibit a significant decrease 
in IDO activity within monocytes as compared with baseline 
conditions. 41 Tumors may generate a hostile microenvironment 
that impedes host antitumor immune response. Interestingly, no 
changes in the expression of IDO by tumor cells was observed in 
melanoma biopsies at baseline and during regression in response </p>

<p>Figure 5. Waterfall plot of response after induction chemotherapy. partici-
pants with reduced surges in indoleamine 2,3 dioxygenase (IDO) activity 
after induction chemotherapy (ΔIDO 1 ) had non-significant trend toward 
improved radiologic responses. The median difference in the kynurenine/ 
tryptophan (Kyn/Trp) ratio was taken as pre-specified cut-point. evaluable 
patients, n = 32; non-evaluable patients, n = 1. </p>

<p>to tremelimumab treatment, 42 suggesting that IDO activity 
may not be influenced by cytotoxic T-lymphocyte antigen 4 
(CTLA-4) inhibition. 
Several aspects of our report necessitate a more detailed 
investigation before firm conclusions can be drawn. Due to 
a small sample size, our trial was statistically underpowered 
to detect any significant association between Kyn/Trp ratios 
and demographic characteristics. Likewise, our patient sample 
was too small to establish a stepwise dose-effect relationship 
between IDO activity and clinical outcome. Next, tissues 
were not available for the immunohistochemical detection 
of IDO, so we used plasma Kyn/Trp ratios as a convenient 
surrogate marker for IDO activity. Other studies have used 
plasma Kyn/Trp ratios as an indirect measure for IDO activ-
ity (Table 3) and these correlate well with immunohisto-
chemical data. 43 However, plasma Kyn/Trp ratios are not 
a direct measure of IDO activity. In particular, other Trp 
catabolizing enzymes, including tryptophan 2,3-dioxygen-
ase and the IDO splice variant known as IDO2 contribute to 
Kyn production as well. Moreover, our study did not mandate 
uniform timing for blood draws. Since plasma Trp levels may 
vary by as much as 20% in the same subject depending on the 
distance of the last meal and the diurnal cycle, 44 we acknowl-
edge this as a potential confounder. Nonetheless, plasma Kyn 
has only minor diurnal variation, 43 and the changes that we 
observed in Kyn/Trp ratios appeared predominantly attribut-
able to Kyn (Fig. 2). Another drawback of the present study is 
that correlative immunologic markers, such as FOXP3 expres-
sion, CD3 activity, and IFN production were not measured. 
Additional markers may help to substantiate the putative role 
of IDO in this patient population. Moreover, conclusions 
cannot be drawn about the effect of individual chemotherapy 
agents, which are known to have specific immunomodulatory 
properties. 45,46 Finally, our calculations were performed with-
out multiple comparison rules. 47 Thus, the possibility exists 
that the observed associations could stem from family-wise 
errors. In view of all these limitations, our results should be 
strictly viewed as exploratory. 
In summary, our findings may serve as a rationale for 
larger studies correlating changes in the Kyn/Trp ratio with 
clinical parameters during standard multimodal therapy 
against NSCLC. As IDO may contribute to the resistance of 
NSCLC to therapy, this clinical setting may be a fertile area for 
the investigation of the antineoplastic effects of IDO inhibitors, 
such as1-methyl-D-tryptophan (D-1MT). 48 </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Patients. The design of the clinical trial has been previously 
described. 49 Briefly, our single-arm trial used induction gem-
citabine (1 g/m 2 ) on day 1 and day 8 and carboplatin (AUC = 5) 
on day 1 given at 4-week intervals for two cycles. This was fol-
lowed by weekly carboplatin (AUC = 2) and paclitaxel (50 mg/m 2 ) 
with concurrent conformal radiation (dose = 74 Gy ± 5%) 
administered over 40 daily fractions. Plasma was collected at 
baseline (Time 0), after induction at week 9 (Time 1), and after </p>

<p>Figure 6. Relationship between changes in indoleamine 2,3 dioxygenase 
activity and non-small cell lung cancer patients survival. participants with a 
consistent increase in indoleamine 2,3 dioxygenase (IDO) activity from base-
line (Time 0) to induction chemotherapy (Time 1) had shorter overall survival 
(Os) and a trend toward shortened progression-free survival (pFs). Median 
Os = 24.6 vs. 18.0 mo, hR = 0.43 (95% cI 0.19-0.95), *p = 0.037 (Log-rank test) 
Median pFs: 15.2 vs. 9.4 mo, hR = 0.47 (95% cI 0.22-1.02), *p = 0.055 (Log-rank 
test). Median difference in kynurenine/tryptophan (Kyn/Trp) (ΔIDO 1 ) was 
taken as pre-specified cut-point. </p>

<p>e23428-6 </p>

<p>OncoImmunology 
Volume 2 Issue 3 </p>

<p>concurrent therapy at week 25-26 (Time 2). All participants 
enrolled had previously untreated clinical Stage IIIA or "dry" 
IIIB NSCLC, as determined by American Joint Committee on 
Cancer (AJCC) criteria v. 6. None of these patients had received 
previous chemotherapy or radiation. </p>

<p>All participants had measurable disease by RECIST v. 1.0 cri-
teria. Both CT and PET scans were performed at Time 0, Time 1 
and Time 2. Radiographic responses were quantified by the per-
centage of changes in the sum of all greatest tumor diameters 
between post-and pre-treatment scans. Institutional radiologists </p>

<p>Table 3. select studies of indoleamine 2,3 dioxygenase IDO in human cancers </p>

<p>Neoplasm type 
Stage 
Tissue source 
Sample size (n) for survival 
Prognostic for survival 
Reference </p>

<p>Lung 
all 
serum kyn/trp 
123 
Null 
24 </p>

<p>Breast 
I-III 
serum kyn/trp 
33 
n/a 
38 </p>

<p>Ovarian, serous 
III-IV 
Tumor Ihc 
24 
Unfavorable 
40 </p>

<p>Ovarian, epithelial 
Ic-IV 
Tumor Ihc 
60 
Unfavorable 
51 </p>

<p>Renal cell 
IV 
Tumor mRNa 
107 
Favorable 
52 </p>

<p>hepatocellular 
all 
Tumor Ihc 
138 
Unfavorable 
53 </p>

<p>Ovarian </p>

<p>all 
serum kyn/trp </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>n/a 
29 
endometrial 
41 </p>

<p>Vulvar 
40 </p>

<p>Ovarian 
III-IV 
Tumor Ihc 
122 
Unfavorable 
54 </p>

<p>Lung 
all 
Tumor Ihc 
28 
n/a 
14 </p>

<p>Breast 
all 
Tumor mRNa 
1059 
Null 
55 
Breast, basal-like 
209 
Favorable </p>

<p>Oral squamous 
all 
Tumor Ihc 
88 
Unfavorable 
56 </p>

<p>Breast 
all 
Tumor mRNa 
30 
Null 
57 </p>

<p>colorectal 
all 
Tumor Ihc 
143 
Unfavorable 
58 </p>

<p>colorectal 
all 
Tumor Ihc 
265 
Unfavorable 
59 </p>

<p>endometrial 
all 
Tumor Ihc 
80 
Unfavorable 
60 </p>

<p>pancreatic 
all 
Tumor Ihc 
17 
n/a 
61 </p>

<p>colorectal 
II-IV 
Tumor Ihc 
69 
n/a 
62 </p>

<p>Osteosarcoma 
all 
Tumor Ihc 
47 
Unfavorable 
63 </p>

<p>esophageal, squamous 
I-III 
Tumor Ihc 
45 
n/a 
34 </p>

<p>acute myelogenous leukemia 
all 
Tumor mRNa 
262 
Unfavorable 
37 </p>

<p>Melanoma, uveal 
-
Tumor Ihc 
7 
n/a 
64 </p>

<p>pancreatic IpMNs* 
-
Tumor Ihc 
39 
n/a 
65 </p>

<p>endometrial 
all 
Tumor Ihc 
355 
Unfavorable 
66 </p>

<p>Vulvar 
all 
Tumor Ihc 
286 
Null 
67 </p>

<p>Melanoma 
III 
Tumor Ihc 
25 
Unfavorable 
68 </p>

<p>Melanoma 
I-III 
Tumor Ihc 
26 
n/a 
69 </p>

<p>cervical 
n/a 
Tumor Ihc 
17 
n/a 
70 </p>

<p>hepatocellular 
all 
Tumor mRNa 
21 
Favorable 
71 </p>

<p>colorectal 
all 
Tumor Ihc 
71 
Unfavorable 
72 </p>

<p>Lymphoma 
all 
Tumor Ihc 
119 
Unfavorable 
73 </p>

<p>Melanoma 
all 
serum kyn/trp 
87 
Unfavorable 
32 </p>

<p>endometrial 
all 
Tumor Ihc 
65 
Unfavorable 
74 </p>

<p>esophageal, squamous 
all 
Tumor mRNa 
30 
Unfavorable 
35 </p>

<p>cervical 
IB-IIB 
Tumor Ihc 
112 
Unfavorable 
75 </p>

<p>Thyroid 
all 
Tumor mRNa 
20 
Null 
36 </p>

<p>Melanoma 
all 
Tumor Ihc 
116 
Unfavorable 
76 </p>

<p>Lung, Non-small cell 
n/a 
serum kyn/trp 
36 
n/a 
25 </p>

<p>Favorable, improved survival with higher IDO; unfavorable, worse survival with higher IDO; null, no difference observed; n/a, not tested; Ihc, Immuno-
histochemistry. *Intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasm. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>OncoImmunology 
e23428-7 </p>



<p>individual mean concentrations were recorded. The intraassay 
and day-to-day analytic coefficients of variation were less than 
5% for each analyte (Table S1). 
Statistics. The plasma concentrations of Kyn and Trp, as 
well as Kyn/Trp ratios approximated a parametric distribution. 
Therefore, data were presented as means ± SD. Due to the small 
sample size, the associations between serum biomarker levels and 
clinicopathologic variables were evaluated with Wilcoxon rank-
sum and Kruskal-Wallis tests. Wilcoxon signed rank was used to 
compare between time points. Correlation was estimated using 
Spearman's rho. Survival curves were calculated according to the 
Kaplan-Meier method. To address the experimental hypothesis, 
the statistical population was equally divided into "hig" and 
"low" patients using the median Kyn/Trp value as pre-specified 
cut-point. The effects of biomarkers on PFS and OS were evalu-
ated using log-rank (Mantel-Cox) test and Cox proportional-
hazards regression models. All tests performed were two-tailed. 
Statistical analysis was performed using the <rs type="software">SAS</rs> software (version 
8.0). Figures and survival plots were generated using <rs id="software-1" type="software">GraphPad 
Prism</rs> ® (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 5.04</rs>). </p>

<p>Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was funded by NCI R01-CA102726 and 
P50-CA119997, and supported in part by the NIH/NCATS 
Clinical and Translational Science Award to the University of 
Florida UL1 TR000064. The content is solely the responsibility of 
the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of 
the National Cancer Institute or the National Institutes of Health. </p>

<p>Supplemental Material </p>

<p>Supplemental materials may be found here: 
http://www.landesbioscience.com/journals/oncoimmunology/ 
article/23428/ </p>

<p>evaluated all scans. OS was defined as the interval between the 
date of treatment and the date of death. PFS was defined as the 
interval between the date of treatment and the date of progres-
sion or death from any cause. Participants without an event were 
censored as of the date of last follow-up, which occurred between 
August and September 2009. 
All procedures were approved by the Institution Review Board 
(IRB) from the University of South Florida (FWA00001669) 
and were in accordance with the Helsinki Declaration of 1975. 
Participants prospectively provided informed consent for the use 
of their tissue in research. 
Measurement of plasma markers. Heparinized blood 
samples were drawn and centrifuged at 800 g for 10 min to 
extract plasma and then stored at −80°C. HPLC/MS/MS was 
performed with gradient elution on a C18 column (Thermo 
Betabasic, 150 mm × 2.1 mm, 5 μm particles) with matching 
guard column at a flow rate of 500 μL/min using heated elec-
trospray ionization in the positive ion mode. 50 Gradient solvents 
were 0.1% formic acid in water and acetonitrile with 0.1% for-
mic acid (HPLC grade, Fisher-Scientific). The mass spectrometer 
(TSQ Quantum Ultra, Thermo) was operated in selected reac-
tion monitoring mode (SRM). Calibration standards for Trp and 
Kyn (Fisher-Scientific) were prepared in albumin (Sigma) in the 
ranges of 10-2,000 ng/mL for Kyn and 100-20,000 ng/mL for 
Trp. Quality control samples were prepared in albumin at 10, 
100, 1000 ng/mL for Kyn and 100, 1,000, 10,000 ng/mL for 
Trp. 150 μL of internal standard solution containing Trp-d3 at 
4,000 ng/mL and Kyn-d6 at 400 ng/mL (Cambridge Isotopes) 
were added and mixed to 150 μL of calibration standard, quality 
control, and clinical specimens. For protein precipitation, 30 μL 
of 2.4 M perchloric acid (Fisher-Scientific) were added, samples 
were vortexed and cooled for 5 min, then centrifuged at 20,400 
g for 20 min. The supernatant was transferred to a filter tube 
(0.44 μm) and re-centrifuged. The filtered sample was trans-
ferred to a glass vial with 400 μL insert and 10 μL was injected 
onto the column. Each sample was performed in triplicate, and </p>





<p>OncoImmunology 
Volume 2 Issue 3 </p>



<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>OncoImmunology 
e23428-9 </p>



</text></tei>