<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3994435" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Rheumatic heart disease (RHD) remains a serious cardiovascular disorder across the world. Tumor necrosis 
factor alpha (TNF-a) codifies a potent immunomodulator and pro-inflammatory cytokine that mediates 
diverse pathological processes. A promoter 308G.A polymorphism in TNF-a has been implicated in RHD 
risk. However, the results remain controversial. Therefore, to evaluate more precise estimations of the 
relationship, a meta-analysis was performed. A total of 7 studies including 735 RHD cases and 926 controls 
were involved in this meta-analysis. Overall, our results revealed that there was a significant association with 
RHD risk in three genetic models (homozygous model: OR 5 3.06, 95%CI 5 1.22-10.60, P 5 0.020; 
dominant model, OR 5 2.03, 95%CI 5 1.01-4.07, P 5 0.048; and recessive model, OR 5 4.26, 95%CI 5 
2.41-7.55, P , 0.001). Further ethnic population analysis found a significantly increased risk of RHD 
among Asians and Europeans. Interestingly, similar results were found among hospital-based studies. 
Begg's funnel plot and Egger's test did not reveal any publication bias. Taken together, this meta-analysis 
demonstrates that the TNF-a 308G.A polymorphism is associated with RHD susceptibility, and it 
contributes to the increased risk of RHD. However, additional well-designed studies with larger samples are 
warranted to confirm these findings. </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>heumatic heart disease (RHD) is an inflammatory disease of the heart tissue, which seriously affects the 
quality of life of patients, and causes a large economic burden on the national healthcare system </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>. After 
recovery from the acute stage of carditis, patients developed RHD 
3 . This makes RHD the major acquired 
heart disease in many developing countries. As a complex disease, the precise molecular mechanism of RHD is 
still unknown. However, it was widely accepted that the occurrence of RHD relied on the interaction of gene and 
environment </p>

<p>4,5 </p>

<p>. 
Although the pathophysiology has not been fully understood, several lines of evidence suggest that inflam-
matory response is an essential part of the pathogenesis of RHD </p>

<p>6,7 </p>

<p>. Tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-a) is a 
cytokine that mediates diverse pathological processes, such as shock during infection and inflammation during 
autoimmunity </p>

<p>8,9 </p>

<p>. Blood mononuclear cell from RHD patients produced more TNF-a than healthy controls </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>. A 
common 308G.A polymorphism (rs1800629) in the promoter region of TNF-a has been identified to elicit a 
regulatory effect on the TNF-a gene. The A allele is associated with increased levels of TNF in plasma compared 
with the G allele </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>. Moreover, the 308G.A polymorphism has been shown to contribute to the susceptibility of 
several autoimmune diseases </p>

<p>12-14 </p>

<p>. 
Although many studies on the relationship between TNF-a gene 308G.A polymorphism and RHD have been 
performed so far, the results were still inconsistent </p>

<p>15-21 </p>

<p>. These disparate findings may be partly due to limited 
sample size, false positive finding and publication bias. In addition, a previous meta-analysis on this issue also 
generated conflicting results, which had insufficient power in the meta-analysis </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>. In the present study, a meta-
analysis on all published studies was performed to estimate the overall TNF-a gene 308G.A promoter poly-
morphism with RHD susceptibility. </p>

<p>Results 
Characteristics of Studies. As shown in Figure 1, we identified 89 related articles, of which 7 studies were 
potentially appropriate. According to the inclusion criteria, a total of 735 cases and 926 controls were 
available for this analysis. Study characteristics are described in Table 1. Two main genotyping approaches 
were used, including polymerase chain reaction-restriction fragment length polymorphism (PCR-RFLP) and 
PCR-sequence-specific primers (PCR-SSP). Population-based and hospital-based controls were involved in </p>

<p>OPEN </p>

<p>SUBJECT AREAS: </p>

<p>DIAGNOSTIC MARKERS </p>

<p>BIOMARKER RESEARCH </p>

<p>different studies. We also assessed deviation from HWE in controls, 
and the results demonstrated that most genotype distributions 
among controls were well goodness of fit except for one study </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>. Of 
these case-control studies, five reported on Europeans, while two 
reports were on Asians. </p>

<p>Quantitative synthesis. The A allele frequency of the TNF-a 
308G.A polymorphism in Asians and Europeans were 0.055 and 
0.156, respectively. The pooled analysis showed that the TNF-a 
308G.A polymorphism was significantly associated with RHD 
risk (homozygous model: OR 5 3.06, 95%CI 5 1.22-10.60; 
dominant model, OR 5 2.03, 95%CI 5 1.01-4.07, Figure 2; and 
recessive model, OR 5 4.26, 95%CI 5 2.41-7.55). In the ethnicity-
stratified analysis, the significant risk was observed to be associated </p>

<p>with recessive model among Asians and Europeans (OR 5 7.11, 
95%CI 5 1.26-40.07 for Asians, and OR 5 3.92, 95%CI 5 2.13-
7.21 for Europeans). Moreover, in the stratification of source of 
controls, significant main effects were found in the hospital-based 
studies (homozygous model: OR 5 6.34, 95%CI 5 2.91-31.84; 
heterozygous model, OR 5 1.79, 95%CI 5 1.37-2.34; dominant 
model, OR 5 2.29, 95%CI 5 1.66-3.16; and recessive model, OR 
5 4.49, 95%CI 5 2.29-10.44) (Table 2). </p>

<p>Test of Heterogeneity, publication bias and sensitivity analysis. 
There was moderate heterogeneity among all the genetic models 
except the recessive model (P 5 0.626, and I2 5 0.0% in the 
recessive model). We used funnel plot and Egger's test to access 
the publication bias of literatures. As shown in Figure 3, the shape </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Study identification, inclusion, and exclusion for the meta-analysis. </p>

<p>Table 1 | Main characteristics of included studies in the meta-analysis </p>

<p>Author </p>

<p>Publication 
year 
Country 
Ethnicity </p>

<p>Sample size 
(cases/controls) </p>

<p>Quality 
scores 
Source of controls </p>

<p>Genotyping 
menthod 
P </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Hernandez-Pacheco 
2003 
Mexico 
Caucasian 
82/101 
8 
Population-based 
PCR-RFLP 
0.880 
Sallakci 
2005 
Turkey 
Caucasian 
63/89 
7 
NA 
PCR-RFLP 
0.615 
Chou 
2006 
China 
Asian 
115/103 
6 
Population-based 
PCR-RFLP 
0.459 
Settin 
2007 
Egypt 
Caucasian 
46/98 
5 
NA 
PCR-SSP 
,0.001 
Ramasawmy 
2007 
Brazil 
Caucasian 
199/281 
7 
Hospital-based 
PCR-RFLP 
0.295 
Mohamed 
2010 
Egypt 
Caucasian 
80/50 
6 
Hospital-based 
PCR-RFLP 
0.649 
Rehman 
2013 
Pakistan 
Asian 
150/204 
7 
Hospital-based 
PCR-SSP 
0.444 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P value of Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium. 
PCR-RFLP, PCR-restriction fragment length polymorphism; PCR-SSP, PCR-sequence-specific primers; NA, not available. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4731 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04731 </p>

<p>
of the funnel plots did not show asymmetrical in the dominant 
model, suggesting absence of publication bias. Moreover, we did 
not find significant publication bias in the Egger's test (t 5 0.07, P 
5 0.945 in the dominant model). Sensitivity analysis was carried out 
by removing each study. The pooled ORs were not materially altered 
(data not shown), implying that the results were robust. </p>

<p>Discussion 
TNF-a is produced by macrophages, monocytes, neutrophils, T-cells 
and NK-cells after stimulation. In turn, TNF-a can stimulate cyto-
kine secretion, increase the expression of adhesion molecules as well 
as activate neutrophils </p>

<p>23,24 </p>

<p>. TNF-a has been shown to be relevant for 
the physiopathology of various inflammatory conditions like rheum-
atic fever, rheumatoid arthritis, and RHD </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>. Furthermore, the TNF-a 
308G.A promoter polymorphism has been reported to be assoc-
iated with high TNF production and this has been associated with 
increased susceptibility for many inflation diseases </p>

<p>26,27 </p>

<p>. Therefore, it 
is biologically plausible that the TNF-a 308G.A polymorphism is 
associated with RHD risk. Compared with the literature by Shen et 
al. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>, we also performed a stratification of ethnic and source of con-
trols in our study, which could explain the difference results among 
Asians and Europeans. As a result, in the stratified analysis, we found 
that the main association was pronounced among Asians and Euro-
peans, suggesting that there was no different genetic background </p>

<p>contributing to the risk of RHD. However, there was no reported 
study on African populations. Therefore, additional studies are 
needed to elucidate the possible ethnic differences in the effect of 
TNF-a 308G.A polymorphism on RHD risk. Importantly, when 
stratifying by source of controls, a significantly elevated risk was 
observed among hospital-based studies but not among population-
based studies. This may be due to that the hospital-based case-con-
trol studies have some selection biases because such controls might 
not be a representative of the general population </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>. Thus, the selec-
tion bias and matching criteria should be considered in the design of 
case-control study. 
Some limitations of this meta-analysis should be addressed. First, 
the ORs extracted from each eligible study were based on unadjusted 
estimates, because not all studies reported adjusted ORs. Second, the 
number of each ethnic subgroup was relatively small, which limited 
the statistical power to detect the association between the TNF-a 
308G.A polymorphism and RHD risk among Asians and Euro-
peans. Third, there was significant between-study heterogeneity 
from studies of the TNF-a 308G.A polymorphism, and the geno-
type distribution also showed deviation from HWE in one study </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>. 
In summary, this meta-analysis of seven case-control studies indi-
cated that the TNF-a 308G.A polymorphism was associated with a 
significantly increased risk of RHD. These results provided the im-
portant role of the TNF-a polymorphisms in the RHD susceptibility, </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Forest plot of RHD risk associated with the TNF-a 308G.A (GA/AA vs. GG) among Asians and Europeans. The squares and horizontal lines </p>

<p>correspond to the study-specific OR and 95% CI. </p>

<p>Table 2 | Main results of pooled ORs of the TNF-a 308G.A polymorphism on RHD risk </p>

<p>Variable 
n </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>AA vs. GG 
GA vs. GG 
GA/AA vs. GG (dominant) 
AA vs. GG/GA (recessive) </p>

<p>OR (95% CI) 
P h </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>OR (95% CI) 
P h </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>OR (95% CI) 
P h </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>OR (95% CI) 
P h </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Overall 
7 3.60 (1.22-10.60) 0.045 1.73 (0.87-3.44) 
,0.001 2.03 (1.01-4.07) 
,0.001 4.26 (2.41-7.55) 0.626 
Ethnicities 
Asian 
5 7.52 (1.34-42.34) 0.469 1.43 (0.87-2.36) 
0.079 1.54 (0.55-4.34) 
0.039 7.11 (1.26-40.07) 0.506 
European 
3 3.10 (0.79-12.08) 0.021 1.93 (0.71-5.25) 
,0.001 2.29 (0.84-6.27) 
,0.001 3.92 (2.13-7.21) 0.479 
Case-control 
Population-based 2 4.89 (0.55-43.34) 0.624 2.75 (0.23-33.71) ,0.001 3.01 (0.24-37.98) 
0.001 4.35 (0.49-38.81) 0.708 
Hospital-based 
3 6.34 (2.91-13.84) 0.071 1.79 (1.37-2.34) 
0.549 2.29 (1.66-3.16) 
0.079 4.89 (2.29-10.44) 0.140 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Number of reports. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>P value of Q-test for heterogeneity test. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4731 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04731 </p>

<p>
and our findings need to be validated by future well-designed large 
studies. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Search stagey. A comprehensive literature search was performed using the PubMed 
database for relevant articles published. The following terms were used in this search: 
'TNF-a or tumor necrosis factor-alpha' and 'rheumatic heart disease or RHD' and 
'polymorphism or polymorphisms'. Additional studies on this topic were identified 
by contacting the corresponding authors or a hand search of references of related 
articles. Studies included in the current meta-analysis should meet the following 
requests: (a) only the case-control studies were considered; (b) evaluated the TNF-a 
gene 308G.A promoter polymorphism and RHD risk; and (c) had usable reported 
data on the genotypes among cases and controls. </p>

<p>Data extraction. Information was carefully extracted from all eligible studies 
independently by two investigators according to the inclusion criteria listed above </p>

<p>and the result was reviewed by a third investigator. The following information was 
extracted from each study: the first author, publication year, country, ethnicity, 
number of cases and controls, source of controls, genotyping methods, and evidence 
of Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE). Different ethnicity descents were 
categorized as European and Asian. Quality of studies was assessed according to the 
predefined criteria based on previous observational studies 
29,30 (Table 3). </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis. Odds ratios (ORs) were used as a measure of the association 
between the TNF-a 308G.A polymorphism and RHD risk. We evaluated the risk of 
the AA or GA genotype on RHD compared with the GG genotypes, and then 
calculated the ORs of GA/AA versus GG and AA versus GG/GA, using dominant and 
recessive genetic models of the A allele, respectively. Pooled estimates of the OR were 
obtained by calculating a weighted average of OR from eligible study. The between-
study heterogeneity I 
2 was assessed with the Q-test </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>. Heterogeneity was considered 
significant if the P , 0.05 among studies. The pooled OR was calculated using the 
fixed-effects model. Otherwise, the random-effects model was used. The HWE was 
assessed by Fisher's exact test with significance set at P , 0.05 level. The potential 
publication bias was constructed by a funnel plot. The funnel plot symmetry was 
evaluated by using Egger's linear regression test on the natural logarithm scale of the 
OR and significance was set at P , 0.05 level. All analyses were performed using the 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 10.0</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">StataCorp LP</rs>, College Station, TX). </p>



<p>Figure 3 | Publication bias on the TNF-a 308G.A polymorphism (GA/AA vs. GG) and RHD risk. </p>

<p>Table 3 | Methodological quality of included studies </p>

<p>Criteria 
Score </p>

<p>A. Representativeness of cases 
Selected from population or hospital 
2 
Selected from any cardiovascular diseases service 
1 
Selected without clearly defined inclusion/exclusion criteria 
0 
B. Credibility of controls 
Population-based 
3 
Blood donors or volunteers 
2 
Hospital-based 
1 
Not described 
0 
C. Ascertainment of rheumatic heart disease 
Two doctors confirmed 
2 
Diagnosis of rheumatic heart disease by patient medical record 1 
Not described 
0 
D. Genotyping examination 
Genotyping done under blinded condition 
1 
Not mentioned 
0 
E. Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium 
Equilibrium in controls 
2 
Disequilibrium in controls 
1 
No checked 
0 
F. Association assessment 
Assess association between genotypes and rheumatic heart 
disease with appropriate statistics </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Assess association between genotypes and rheumatic heart 
disease with logistic regression </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Inappropriate statistics used 
0 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4731 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04731 </p>



<p>
Author contributions </p>

<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: J.W., Z.R. Performed the experiments: J.W., Z.H., 
Z.R. Analyzed the data: J.W., Z.H. Contributed reagents/material/analysis tools: J.W., Z.H., 
Z.R. Wrote the main manuscript text: J.W., Z.H., and Z.R. Reference collection and data 
management: J.W., Z.R. Statistical analyses and paper writing: Z.R., J.W. Study design: J.W. 
J.W., Z.H. Prepared figures 1-3: Z.R. All authors reviewed the manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Zheng, R.-L., Zhang, H. &amp; Jiang, W.-L. Tumor necrosis factor-alpha 
308G.A polymorphism and risk of rheumatic heart disease: a meta-analysis. Sci. Rep. 4, 
4731; DOI:10.1038/srep04731 (2014). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License. The images in this article are included in the 
article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the image credit; 
if the image is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to 
obtain permission from the license holder in order to reproduce the image. To view 
a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4731 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04731 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>