<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3447890" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>cytokine response included 66 subjects (35 females and 31 males; average age 
21.4 6 13.5 years, range 4-53), with one or more islet autoantibodies. Twenty 
subjects were included in the group aged ,11 years (average 9.0 6 1.4), 21 in 
the group aged from 11 to ,21 years (average 15.3 6 2.8), and 25 in the group 
aged $21 years (average 36.5 6 9.4). Of these, 44 subjects were positive for 
one autoantibody, 20 were positive for two autoantibodies, and 2 were posi-
tive for three autoantibodies. The median HbA 1c value in the autoantibody-
positive group was 5.2 (range 4.5-6.2). The control group included 53 
autoantibody-negative individuals (29 females and 24 males; average age 
13.0 6 8.3 years, range 6-54); 24 subjects were included in the group aged ,11 
years (average 8.3 6 1.4), 24 in the group aged from 11 to ,21 years (average 
13.0 6 1.4), and 5 were included in the group aged $21 years (average 37.5 6 14.4). 
The study cohort used for our serum cytokine measurement studies in-
cluded 40 subjects (26 females and 14 males; average age 22.5 6 15.6 years, 
range 5-53), with one or more islet autoantibodies. The median HbA 1c value in 
the autoantibody-positive group was 5.3 (range 4.5-6). Of these, 30 were 
positive for one autoantibody, 8 were positive for two autoantibodies, and 2 
were positive for three autoantibodies. The control group included 40 auto-
antibody-negative individuals (21 females and 19 males) who were an average 
age of 14.0 6 9.2 years (range 5-43). 
PBMNC isolation. PBMNCs were freshly isolated by Ficoll-Hypaque Plus 
density centrifugation (GE Healthcare, Uppsala, Sweden) of freshly drawn 
heparinized blood from autoantibody-positive and autoantibody-negative sub-
jects. PBMNCs were washed twice with PBS (Invitrogen Life Technologies) 
and resuspended in endotoxin-free high-glucose Dulbecco's modified Eagle's 
medium (DMEM) containing 2 mmol/L L-glutamine and 100 units/mL penicillin/ 
streptomycin (both from Invitrogen Life Technologies), and 10% human AB 
serum (PAA Laboratories, New Bedford, MA). For flow cytometry analyses, 
PBMNCs were washed and resuspended in fluorescence-activated cell sorter 
buffer consisting of PBS (Invitrogen Life Technologies) plus 1% BSA and 0.05% 
sodium azide (both from Sigma-Aldrich). 
Analysis of DC and monocyte frequencies in the peripheral blood. 
PBMNCs were isolated from freshly drawn blood as described above. For 
mDC enumeration, we used APC-conjugated anti-cluster of differentiation 1 
(CD1) C (mouse IgG2a, clone AD5-8E7, Miltenyi Biotech) plus APC-Alexa Fluor 
750-conjugated anti-CD19 (mouse IgG1, clone HIB19, eBioscience, San Diego, 
CA). Staining with anti-CD19 was performed to exclude B cells expressing 
CD1C. For monocyte staining, we used pacific blue-conjugated anti-CD14 
monoclonal antibody (mAb; mouse IgG2a, clone M5E2, BioLegend, San Diego, 
CA). For plasmacytoid dendritic cell (pDC) subset staining, cells were surface 
stained with phycoerythrin-conjugated mAb directed against CD304 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>(mouse IgG1, clone AD5-17F6, Miltenyi Biotech, Auburn, CA). 
Activation of PBMNCs with TLR ligands and intracellular cytokine and 
chemokine staining. PBMNCs were added to a 96-well round-bottom 
microtiter plates at a concentration of 1 3 10 
6 /well in a total volume of 100 mL. 
For intracellular cytokine analysis, PBMNCs were incubated in the presence 
or absence of various purified TLR ligands and 1 mL/mL brefeldin A (BD 
Biosciences, San Diego, CA) for 4 h, followed by staining for surface markers 
and intracellular cytokines. For intracellular cytokine staining, PBMNCs were 
cultured in the presence or absence of 100 ng/mL ultrapurified lipopolysac-
charide (LPS; O111:B4; InvivoGen, San Diego, CA), 50 mg/mL polyinosinic: 
polycytidylic acid (Poly[I:C]; Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO), and 10 mg/mL 
R848 (Axxora, San Diego, CA) for 4 h, followed by staining for DC and 
monocyte surface markers, followed by staining for IL-1b and IL-6, as pre-
viously published (11). All TLR ligands were dissolved in Dulbecco's PBS and 
stored in aliquots at -20°C until used. 
Serum cytokine expression levels. Twenty-five microliters of serum were 
used for measuring levels of IL-1 receptor antagonist (IL-1RA), interferon (IFN)-a, 
IFN-g, IL-1a, IL-1b, IL-6, IL-17A, chemokine (C-X-C motif) ligand (CXCL-10), 
and monocyte chemoattractant protein (MCP)-1 using the Meso Scale Dis-
covery (MSD) cytokine multiplex kit according to the manufacturer's in-
struction (MSD, Gaithersburg, MD). The detection sensitivity of the MSD 
method is considered to be greater than other systems (14,15). The diluent 
included in the kit contains blockers for the neutralization of heterophilic 
antibodies present in human serum. We measured levels of IL-1 receptor an-
tagonist (IL-1RA), IL-1a, IL-1b, IFN-a2, IFN-g, IL-6, IL-17A, CXCL-10, and 
MCP-1. The detection sensitivity limits for these cytokines are 120, 0.12, 0.3, 
0.7, 1, 0.7, 0.4, and 3.5 pg/mL, respectively. The diluent MSD plates were read 
using the MSD SECTOR Imager 2400. 
Statistical analyses. Statistical differences in frequencies of freshly drawn 
mDCs, pDCs, and monocytes, as well as frequencies of monocytes and mDCs-
expressing cytokines after TLR ligation in positive versus negative subjects, 
frequencies of monocytes and mDCs expressing cytokines in at-risk subjects 
positive for one versus more than one autoantibodies, cytokine responses 
based on age group, cytokine expression levels, and serum cytokine levels in 
subjects with one versus more than one autoantibodies were evaluated using 
the nonparametric Mann-Whitney U test. Associations between cell frequencies </p>

<p>or cytokine levels and age were evaluated using Pearson correlation analysis. 
Age correction and ANOVA were applied when a significant association was 
observed. For statistical differences in serum cytokine levels between sero-
positive and seronegative subjects and to correct for the effect of age, cyto-
kine concentrations were log-transformed to obtain approximately normally 
distributed measures and then analyzed using ANOVA. Values of P , 0.05 
were considered to be statistically significant. Analyses were performed in 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.2</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, NC). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>DC and monocyte proportions in the peripheral 
blood. We tested the possibility that altered frequencies 
of DC subsets and monocytes in the peripheral blood may 
be involved in the early course of T1D in seropositive ver-
sus seronegative subjects before disease onset. PBMNCs 
were isolated from blood samples drawn as described in 
RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS. The percentages of mDCs, 
pDCs, and monocytes from subjects positive for autoanti-
bodies were slightly elevated compared with individuals 
negative for autoantibodies (Fig. 1A and B); however, this 
difference did not reach a statistically significant level. The 
data imply that the frequency of peripheral monocytes and 
DC subsets is not altered in seropositive subjects at risk 
for T1D. 
TLR-induced IL-1b-expressing monocytes and mDCs. 
The IL-1 pathway has previously been implicated in humans 
with T1D (16-19) as well as in animal models of the disease 
(20). We recently reported that monocytes and mDCs from 
newly diagnosed patients with T1D have an altered TLR-
induced IL-1 pathway (11). We tested the hypothesis that 
this alteration is detectable in peripheral monocytes and 
mDCs from nondiabetic individuals positive for one or 
more anti-islet autoantibodies. To test this, we used flow 
cytometry to determine the proportion of IL-1b-producing 
monocytes and mDCs after TLR ligation in vitro. Results 
show that 13.9 6 19.6% of monocytes from autoantibody-
positive subjects produced IL-1b ex vivo compared with 
only 4.3 6 5.0% in autoantibody-negative control individuals 
(P = 0.003; Fig. 2A and Supplementary Fig. 1). Stimulation 
of PBMNCs with LPS led to IL-1b expression in 87.1 6 
11.9% of total monocytes in autoantibody-positive, com-
pared with 79.5 6 11.8% in autoantibody-negative subjects 
(P , 0.01; Fig. 2A and Supplementary Fig. 1). Similarly, 
activation of the TLR3 and TLR7/8 pathways resulted in an 
increase of ;10% in the proportion of IL-1b-expressing 
monocytes from autoantibody-positive individuals versus 
those without autoantibodies (P 5 0.008 and P 5 0.002, 
respectively; Fig. 2A and Supplementary Fig. 1). 
Next, we assessed whether mDCs from autoantibody-
positive individuals also have dysregulated IL-1b responses. 
We found that TLR7/8 ligation led to a moderate increase 
of 7% in the proportion of IL-1b-expressing mDCs from 
autoantibody-positive subjects versus the control indi-
viduals (P = 0.01; Fig. 2B and Supplementary Fig. 1). We 
further evaluated whether the magnitude of the TLR re-
sponsiveness in seropositive subjects is associated with 
the number of autoantibodies. Similar frequencies of cells 
expressing IL-1b in monocytes and mDCs were detectable 
in individuals positive for one versus two and three auto-
antibodies (data not shown, P . 0.05). Taken together, our 
observations indicate that alterations in TLR-induced IL-1b 
pathways are detectable in monocytes and mDCs from 
seropositive subjects before disease onset. 
Correlation between TLR-induced IL-1b responses 
and age. We checked whether the altered IL-1b responses 
observed in monocytes from seropositive subjects corre-
spond to any specific age groups. To test this, we analyzed </p>

<p>TLR RESPONSES IN SUBJECTS AT RISK FOR T1D </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, OCTOBER 2012 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>IL-1b responses in subjects stratified into three age 
groups: ,11 years (young children), from 11 to ,20 
years (adolescents), and $21 years (adults). The data 
shown in the upper panel of Fig. 3A demonstrate that the 
presence of monocytes expressing IL-1b ex vivo was more 
substantial in individuals aged $21 years. Data presented in 
Fig. 3A also show that increased frequencies of monocytes 
expressing IL-1b after LPS activation were more readily 
detectable in seropositive subjects from the group aged 
,11 years, as evident by a difference of ;12% in the pro-
portion of IL-1b-expressing monocytes from autoantibody-
positive compared with autoantibody-negative subjects 
(P = 0.005). Similar findings were seen in TLR3 and TLR7/8 
activated monocytes from seropositive individuals aged 
,11 years. Increased IL-1b responses were also more 
readily detectable in mDCs from children aged ,11 years 
after TLR4 and TLR7/8 activation (Fig. 3B and data not 
shown). These data may indicate that altered IL-1b </p>

<p>responses are more prevalent in monocytes and mDCs from 
seropositive young children aged ,11 years. 
TLR-induced IL-6-expressing monocytes and mDCs. 
We next assessed whether alterations in the TLR-induced 
IL-6 pathway are involved in the early course of T1D be-
fore hyperglycemia, as observed in new-onset patients 
with T1D (11). We observed that PBMNC activation with 
TLR3, TLR4, and TLR7/8 ligands resulted in a modest re-
duction in the percentage of IL-6-expressing monocytes 
from autoantibody-positive versus seronegative individu-
als (Fig. 4A and Supplementary Fig. 2). A reduction of 
;11% was observed in PBMNCs activated with Poly(I:C) 
and R848 (P = 0.02 and P = 0.004, respectively; Fig. 4A and 
Supplementary Fig. 2). No statistically significant differ-
ences in the frequency of IL-6-expressing mDCs were 
observed between seropositive and seronegative individ-
uals (Fig. 4B). We further checked whether the level of 
TLR-induced IL-6-expressing monocytes and mDCs in </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Frequencies of monocytes and DC subsets in the peripheral blood. PBMNCs isolated from the blood of autoantibody-positive subjects 
enrolled in the Type 1 Diabetes TrialNet and DAISY studies and autoantibody-negative control subjects stained for surface markers characteristic 
of monocytes, mDCs, pDCs, or the appropriate isotype control. A: Representative flow images show stained monocytes and DCs from autoantibody-
negative vs. autoantibody-positive subjects. B: Frequencies are shown of monocytes and DC subsets from seronegative vs. seropositive subjects. 
The results are expressed as percentages of cell subtypes from the total PBMNCs. The bars indicate the mean values. (A high-quality color 
representation of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>A.K. ALKANANI AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, OCTOBER 2012 </p>

<p>
seropositive subjects is influenced by the number of auto-
antibodies. The frequencies of IL-6-expressing cells did 
not correspond with the number of autoantibodies (data 
not shown, P . 0.05). Taken together, the data indicate 
that alterations in the IL-6 pathway may occur in sero-
positive subjects before disease onset. 
Correlation between TLR-induced IL-6 and age. We 
next checked whether the TLR-induced IL-6 response in 
monocytes is linked with a specific age group. Analysis of 
the IL-6 response demonstrated that altered IL-6 responses 
were more readily detectable in monocytes from autoanti-
body-positive subjects aged from 11 to ,21 years after liga-
tion of TLR7/8, as evident by a difference of 20% between 
seropositive versus seronegative individuals (P = 0.008; 
Fig. 5A). Similar observations were made in Poly(I:C)-
activated monocytes from seropositive individuals at 
age 11 to ,20 years (data not shown). Results presented 
in Fig. 5B demonstrate that reduced frequencies of mDCs 
expressing IL-6 were more readily detectable in the group 
aged from 11 to ,20 years after TLR7/8 ligation, similar 
to the results observed in monocytes. On the basis of 
our data, we hypothesize that reduced TLR-induced IL-6 
responses may be more prevalent in monocytes and 
mDCs from 11-to ,20-year-old seropositive adolescents. 
Serum cytokine and chemokine levels. We used the 
MSD approach to analyze the level of IL-1RA, IFN-a, IFN-g, 
IL-1a, IL-1b, IL-6, IL-17A, CXCL-10, and MCP-1 in sera from 
seropositive versus seronegative subjects. These cytokines 
and chemokines have previously been implicated in the 
course of T1D in humans and animal models (11). IL-6, 
MCP-1, and CXCL-10 were detected in sera from all subjects, </p>

<p>IFN-g and IL-17A were detected in most of the samples, 
and the other cytokines were not detectable in most of the 
samples. Interestingly, we found that the level of none of 
the cytokines and chemokines tested was increased in 
seropositive versus seronegative subjects (Fig. 6A and data 
not shown). Moreover, a reduction of more than twofold in 
the level of CXCL-10 was observed in sera from autoanti-
body-positive versus autoantibody-negative individuals 
(P = 0.01; Fig. 6A). The level of CXCL-10 did not correlate 
with any specific age group (data not shown). 
We further assessed whether serum cytokine and che-
mokine levels correspond to the number of autoantibodies 
present. Subjects were stratified by the expression of one 
or more than one autoantibody. Results presented in Fig. 6B 
indicate that individuals with more than one autoanti-
body had significantly lower amounts of CXCL-10 than 
subjects with only one autoantibody (P = 0.01). These data 
imply that altered CXCL-10 serum level could be involved 
in the early course of T1D in seropositive individuals and 
that this may be associated with the number of anti-islet 
antibodies present in the peripheral blood. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION   We analyzed TLR responsiveness in PBMNCs from sero-
positive individuals and compared it with seronegative 
subjects. We document for the first time that freshly iso-
lated monocytes and mDCs from autoantibody-positive 
subjects have dysregulated TLR-induced IL-1b and IL-6 
pathways compared with autoantibody-negative individu-
als via mechanisms that may be linked with age but not </p>

<p>FIG. 2. TLR-induced IL-1b expression in monocytes and mDCs. PBMNCs were unactivated or activated with purified LPS, Poly(I:C), and R848 in 
the presence of brefeldin A, followed by staining with fluorochrome-conjugated mAbs directed against surface markers for monocytes (CD14 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) and 
mDCs (CD1C </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>CD19 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). The cells were fixed, permeabilized, and labeled with fluorochrome-conjugated mAbs against IL-1b or the appropriate 
isotype controls. Each symbol represents an individual percentage of monocytes (A), or mDCs (B) expressing IL-1b from the total monocytes and 
mDCs, respectively. The bars indicate mean values. P values were evaluated using the nonparametric Mann-Whitney U test. </p>

<p>TLR RESPONSES IN SUBJECTS AT RISK FOR T1D </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, OCTOBER 2012 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>with altered proportions of peripheral monocytes and DCs, 
aberrant levels of HbA 1c , or the presence of one versus 
more than one autoantibody. We also document that au-
toantibody-positive subjects have lower levels of CXCL-10 </p>

<p>in their blood. The observation that altered innate immu-
nity is detectable in at-risk subjects before disease onset 
supports the hypothesis that this alteration may be linked 
with early disease mechanisms. </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Correlation between TLR-induced IL-1b in monocytes and mDCs and age. IL-1b responses were evaluated in subjects stratified into three 
age groups: &lt;11 years (young children), from 11 to &lt;21 years (adolescents), and  ‡21 years (adults). Each symbol represents an individual fre-
quency of IL-1b-expressing monocytes (A) and mDCs (B) after activation with LPS. The bars represent the mean values. P values were evaluated 
using the nonparametric Mann-Whitney U test. </p>

<p>A.K. ALKANANI AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, OCTOBER 2012 </p>

<p>
Our findings that seropositive subjects have altered IL-
1b and IL-6 pathways are compatible with our recent 
finding that newly diagnosed patients with T1D have 
higher proportions of ex vivo monocytes secreting IL-1b 
and elevated numbers of TLR-induced IL-1b2expressing 
monocytes compared with healthy subjects (11). Our data 
lend support to the hypothesis that changes in TLR re-
sponsiveness are detectable in monocytes and mDCs from 
humans with ongoing autoimmunity before and after dis-
ease onset. In addition, our results are also in accordance 
with a previous report that patients with T1D have higher 
frequencies of ex vivo IL-1b-expressing monocytes de-
termined using ELISPOT (21). It was proposed that mono-
cytes could be involved in T1D onset by inducing an IL-17 
response (21). 
Observations from a number of experimental systems 
have suggested the potential involvement of the IL-1 path-
way in islet destruction. We recently demonstrated that the 
IL-1 pathway is involved in the proinflammatory response 
leading to virus-induced T1D (20,22). IL-1, alone or com-
bined with other proinflammatory cytokines such as IFN-b, 
can cause b-cell destruction in islets from humans and 
animals and perfused pancreas via pathways involving 
mitogen-activated protein kinase and nuclear factor (NF)-
kB (23-25). Blocking the IL-1 pathway protected from 
T1D in animal models and treating non-diabetes-prone 
animals with IL-1 caused transient insulinopenic diabetes 
(25). Finally, earlier reports have linked IL-1 cytokine 
family members, including IL-1b, IL-1R1, and IL-1R2, with 
human T1D (26). 
Our finding that subjects at risk for T1D have reduced 
TLR-induced monocyte expression of IL-6 is reminiscent of 
our previous observation that PBMNCs from new-onset </p>

<p>patients activated with LPS contain lower frequencies of 
IL-6-expressing mDCs (11). Others have also reported 
a reduced IL-6 response in monocytes from patients with 
T1D (27). IL-6 promotes inflammation (28) and adaptive 
immune responses (29); however, it also suppresses the 
functions of various cell subsets, including macrophages 
and synovial fibroblasts. IL-6 induces anti-inflammatory 
factors, such as IL-1 receptor antagonist and glucocorti-
coids, inhibits the production of proinflammatory cyto-
kines, such as IL-1, tumor necrosis factor, and IL-12, 
and downregulates the expression of adhesion molecules 
(30). Thus, reduced IL-6 responses in seropositive indi-
viduals could potentially be part of early mechanisms 
leading to loss of immune regulation and consequently 
T1D. 
It is currently unclear how dysregulated TLR-induced IL-
1b and IL-6 responses in monocytes and mDCs are in-
volved in mechanisms leading to islet destruction. There is 
also uncertainty regarding the mechanism underlying this 
alteration. The data demonstrating that subjects with more 
than one autoantibody have similar TLR-induced IL-1b and 
IL-6 responses as subjects with only one autoantibody is 
interesting given the large difference in the risk for T1D 
between these groups (5). One potential explanation is 
that the increased TLR responses seen in seropositive 
subjects may be linked with mechanisms triggering anti-
islet autoimmunity rather than progression to T1D. The 
interpretation of these data should be constrained by the 
caveat that most of the seropositive subjects included in 
this study expressed only one or two autoantibodies. It 
remains to be determined whether monocytes and mDCs 
from individuals with three autoantibodies react differ-
ently to TLR ligation compared with subjects with one and </p>

<p>FIG. 4. TLR-induced IL-6 in monocytes and mDCs. PBMNCs were unactivated or stimulated with purified TLR agonists, followed by staining 
for intracellular IL-6. Each symbol represents an individual percentage of monocytes (A) or mDCs (B) expressing IL-6 of the total monocytes 
and mDCs, respectively. The bars indicate the mean values. Significant differences were evaluated using the nonparametric Mann-Whitney 
U test. </p>

<p>TLR RESPONSES IN SUBJECTS AT RISK FOR T1D </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, OCTOBER 2012 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>two autoantibodies. Also intriguing is the observation that 
altered IL-1b responses are more prevalent in young chil-
dren (,11 years) compared with IL-6 responses that 
appeared to be more readily detectable in adolescents. It 
is tempting to speculate that the altered innate immune </p>

<p>pathways detectable in seropositive individuals could be 
occurring at different ages or disease stages. 
The altered ability of monocytes and mDCs to respond 
to TLR ligation could be involved in disease mechanisms 
by altering the balance between proinflammatory and </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Correlation between TLR-induced IL-6 in monocytes and mDCs vs. age. IL-6 responses were evaluated in subjects grouped by age: &lt;11 
years (young children), from 11 to &lt;21 years (adolescents), and  ‡21 years (adults). Each symbol represents an individual frequency of IL-6-
expressing monocytes (upper panel) and mDCs (lower panel) after stimulation with R848. The bars represent the mean values. P values were 
evaluated using the nonparametric Mann-Whitney U test. </p>

<p>A.K. ALKANANI AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, OCTOBER 2012 </p>

<p>
regulatory mechanisms in the periphery and/or the pan-
creatic islets. This could result in greater islet inflammation 
and anti-islets T-cell upregulation (31). Dysregulated 
TLR-induced cytokine and chemokine responses could be 
induced, at least in part, by genes linked with mediating 
innate immune functions or innate regulatory mechanisms. 
Our data suggest that the mechanism of altered TLR-
induced IL-1b and IL-6 responses in seropositive subjects 
does not involve altered TLR-induced NF-kB phosphory-
lation or TLR expression (data not shown). It is important 
to note, however, that although all study participants were 
free of hyperglycemia, we are unable to exclude the pos-
sibility that the altered innate immunity we observed in 
these subjects is in fact a result of subtle changes in glu-
cose metabolism triggered by ongoing proinflammatory 
responses in pancreatic islets (32,33). 
In contrast to our previously published data document-
ing elevated levels of IFN-g, IL-1b, and CXCL-10 in sera 
from new-onset patients (11), we observed that serum 
expression levels of CXCL-10 were lower in seropositive 
compared with seronegative subjects, whereas the amount 
of IFN-g was similar in these subject groups. Why sero-
positive individuals have reduced amounts of CXCL-10 in 
their blood is unknown. This reduction could be a conse-
quence of recruitment of chemokine-secreting monocytes, 
DCs, or B lymphocytes from the peripheral blood to in-
flamed tissues. The observation that the level of serum 
CXCL-10 is reduced in subjects with more than one versus 
only one autoantibody is compatible with this hypothesis, 
as it would be reasonable to hypothesize that individuals 
with more than one autoantibody may have a higher de-
gree of inflammation, resulting in the recruitment of 
greater numbers of CXCL-10-producing cells to inflamed 
islets. The possibility that CXCL-10 is directly involved in 
the inflammation leading to T1D is supported by a number 
of reports. CXCL-10 is detectable in human pancreatic 
islets from patients with new-onset T1D (34) and can also 
be found in pancreatic lymph nodes and islets from animal 
models of virus-induced T1D (35; our unpublished data). </p>

<p>Our opposing observations indicating an increase versus 
no change or a decrease in proinflammatory cytokine and 
chemokine levels in new-onset patients versus prediabetic 
individuals, respectively (current report; 11), could imply 
that alterations detected in subjects with new-onset T1D 
may be at least partly linked with late stages of T1D or 
hyperglycemia and inflammation previously documented 
in patients with T1D (32). 
In summary, our data demonstrate that individuals with 
active anti-islet autoimmunity have altered TLR-induced 
IL-1b-and IL-6-signaling pathways before disease onset. 
Future longitudinal studies in prediabetic individuals pro-
gressing to T1D will be required to evaluate the potential 
link between the innate immune system and disease onset. 
Studies to identify early immune pathways involved in T1D 
are critical not only for designing anti-inflammatory ther-
apeutic interventions but also for identifying biomarkers 
that could be used for monitoring inflammation and dis-
ease progression. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by grants 1-2006-745, 1-2007-584, 
5-2008-224, and 5-2011-41 from the Juvenile Diabetes Re-
search Foundation (JDRF) and a Diabetes and Endocrinol-
ogy Research Center (DERC) Pilot and Feasibility Award 
(to D.Z.), grants R01-DK32493 from National Institute of 
Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK) and 
33-2008-396 from JDRF (to M.R.), DERC National Institutes 
of Health Grant P30 DK-57516, and U01 DK-0855509 from 
NIDDK (to P.G.). 
No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article 
were reported. 
A.K.A. performed the experiments involving in vitro TLR 
activation, flow cytometry analyses, serum cytokine mea-
surements, and the Type 1 Diabetes TrialNet Natural History 
demographic data analysis. M.R. provided the DAISY 
samples, reviewed the data, and participated in writing the 
manuscript. F.D. performed statistical analyses. K.W. </p>

<p>FIG. 6. Serum cytokine and chemokine expression levels and correlation with autoantibody number. A: Each symbol represents an individual level 
of the indicated cytokine or chemokine. B: The serum expression level of the indicated cytokine or chemokine was stratified into two groups based 
on the expression of one and more than one anti-islet autoantibodies. The bars indicate mean values. For statistical comparisons, cytokine 
concentrations were log-transformed to obtain approximately normally distributed measures and then analyzed using ANOVA. </p>

<p>TLR RESPONSES IN SUBJECTS AT RISK FOR T1D </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, OCTOBER 2012 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>handled the DAISY blood samples. P.A.G. provided the Type 
1 Diabetes TrialNet Natural History blood samples, 
reviewed the data, and participated in writing the manu-
script. D.Z. reviewed and analyzed the data and wrote the 
manuscript. D.Z. is the guarantor of this work and, as such, 
had full access to all the data in the study and takes 
responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy 
of the data analysis. 
Parts of this study were presented in abstract form at the 
12th International Conference on the Immunology of Di-
abetes, Victoria, British Columbia, Canada, 15-19 June 2012. 
The authors thank Katherine Barriga, from the Barbara 
Davis Center for Childhood Diabetes, for her assistance 
with the DAISY demographic data. </p>



<p>A.K. ALKANANI AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 61, OCTOBER 2012 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>