<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3891859" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: The aim of this study was to explore root shape abnormalities, to investigate the influence of root form abnormali-
ties on periodontal attachment loss, and to gather basic data to assist in the diagnosis and treatment of aggressive periodonti-
tis. 
Methods: From January 2010 to June 2012, a survey was conducted of all 3,284 periodontitis patients who visited the Depart-
ment of Periodontology, Daejeon Dental Hospital, Wonkwang University School of Dentistry. Clinical parameters (probing 
depth, periodontal attachment loss, missing teeth) were measured and a radiographic examination was performed at the base-
line. We classified the root shape abnormality of bicuspids and molars based on Meng classification. 
Results: The periodontal attachment loss was the highest at the maxillary first molar (6.03 mm). The loss of the second molar 
was prominent. Type V deformity was shown to be the most common in the second maxillary and mandibular molars (P&lt; 0.05). 
Type V root shape was associated with the highest attachment loss (P = 0.01). 
Conclusions: Considering the small population and limited design of this study, definitive conclusions cannot be drawn. We 
suggest larger scale, methodologically more sophisticated studies that include normal controls and chronic periodontitis pa-
tients to clarify whether root form abnormalities are a potential risk factor for aggressive periodontitis. </p>

<p>Aggressive periodontitis is characterized by a rapid loss of 
periodontal attachment and alveolar bone. It commonly af-
fects young adults [1-3]. As opposed to chronic periodontitis, 
the amount of biofilm and calculus accumulation in aggres-
sive periodontitis is inconsistent with the severity and rate of 
progression of the periodontal destruction. These infections 
are subdivided into localized and generalized forms, accord-
ing to the extent of the periodontal destruction [4]. The strin-
gent age requirement used previously for diagnosis of early-
onset periodontitis is no longer considered to be essential [5]. 
Even though there have been attempts to analyze aggressive 
periodontitis biochemically and microbiologically, there is </p>

<p>no specific way to screen for the disease. Currently, early de-
tection depends primarily on clinical and radiographic ex-
amination [1,5]. 
Many reports have discussed host susceptibility factors, in-
cluding family aggregation, single nucleotide polymorphisms, 
polymorphonuclear neutrophils, antibodies to bacteria, smok-
ing, stress, a local contributing factor (root morphology), and 
herpes virus infections [6]. Anatomic variations in teeth, such 
as cervical enamel projections, enamel pearls, intermediate 
bifurcation ridges, and root grooves have been regarded as 
etiologic cofactors in this destructive periodontal disease 
process [7]. It has been shown that molars are more vulnera-
ble to attachment loss and are more frequently extracted [8-
10]. Anatomical variations in molar root form may favor plaque </p>

<p>Received: Jun. 10, 2013; Accepted: Nov. 25, 2013 
*Correspondence: Seong-Nyum Jeong 
Department of Periodontology, Daejeon Dental Hospital, Wonkwang University School of Dentistry, 77 Dunsan-ro, Seo-gu, Daejeon 302-120, Korea 
E-mail: seongnyum@wonkwang.ac.kr, Tel: +82-42-366-1141, Fax: +82-42-366-1115 </p>

<p>Journal of Periodontal 
&amp; Implant Science </p>

<p>JPIS </p>

<p>Young-Mi Chung and Seong-Nyum Jeong 277 </p>

<p>retention in these teeth and may contribute to an unfavorable 
crown-root ratio, resulting in increased susceptibility to loos-
ening when they are subjected to heavy occlusal force [11]. 
Meng et al. [6] indicated that root shape abnormalities can be 
a susceptibility factor in the development of aggressive peri-
odontitis and suggested root shape classification. Kim [12] 
reported that the ratio of root abnormalities was 1.76 times 
higher in aggressive periodontitis patients than in normal 
patients. 
The aim of this study was to explore root shape abnormali-
ties based on Meng classification, to investigate the influence 
of root form abnormalities on periodontal attachment loss 
and to gather basic data to assist in the diagnosis and treat-
ment of aggressive periodontitis. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Subjects 
From January 2010 to June 2012, a survey was conducted of 
all 3,284 periodontitis patients who visited the Department of 
Periodontology, Daejeon Dental Hospital, Wonkwang Uni-
versity School of Dentistry. To qualify for inclusion in the 
survey, patients were required to display clinical and radio-
graphic signs of aggressive periodontitis (based on the crite-
ria of the American Academy of Periodontology Internation-
al Classification of 1999) (Table 1). The patients were also re-
quired to be less than 35 years old at the time of the survey. </p>

<p>Patients aged 35-40 years old who had suffered from peri-
odontal disease since age twenty were also included. Of the 
3,284 patients surveyed, 66 patients were selected as subjects 
for this study. The average age was 34.32 ( ± 4.04). The num-
bers of males and females were 50 (2.2%) and 16 (1.6%), re-
spectively, (P &gt; 0.05) (Table 2). Of the 66 subjects, 37 (56.1%) 
were smokers. To participate in the study, each subject was 
required to have a family history of destructive periodontitis 
back at least one generation. All of the subjects were thorough-
ly informed about the procedure and gave written consent 
for inclusion in the study. This study was approved by the In-
stitutional Review Board of Wonkwang University Dental 
Hospital (IRB No. WKD IRB 20110201). </p>

<p>Clinical examinations 
Before clinical periodontal assessment, complete medical 
and dental histories were taken. The workup included clini-
cal assessment and examination by a single examiner, includ-
ing the probing depths, gingival recession (data not shown) 
at six points per tooth, and Löe's plaque index [13]. The prob-
ing pocket depth was measured from the free gingiva to the 
pocket base using a periodontal probe (PW, Hu-Friedy Man-
ufacturing Co., Chicago, IL, USA). We measured the gingival 
recession from the cemento-enamel junction to the free gin-
giva with the same tool. We expressed periodontal attachment 
loss, defined as the length from the cemento-enamel junc-
tion to the depth of the pocket base, as the sum of the depth 
of the pocket and the gingival recession. 
We classified roots according to the system published by 
Meng et al. [6]: cone root (type I), slender root (type II), curved 
root (type III), poor crown-root ratio (type IV), and syncretic 
root (type V) (Table 3, Fig. 1). We included the first and second </p>

<p>Table 1. Diagnostic criteria based on the 1999 AAP classification of 
periodontal diseases. </p>

<p>Localized aggressive periodontitis 
Rapid attachment and bone loss in otherwise healthy patients 
First molar-incisor presentation with no more than two other teeth affected 
At least two permanent teeth affected where at least 1 is a first molar 
Lifetime cumulative attachment loss ≥ 4 mm at the affected sites 
Generalized aggressive periodontitis 
Rapid attachment and bone loss in otherwise healthy patients 
Generalized interproximal attachment loss affecting at least three teeth other 
than the first molars and incisors 
Lifetime cumulative attachment loss ≥ 4 mm at the affected sites </p>

<p>AAP: American Academy of Periodontology. </p>

<p>Table 2. Number of patients by gender. </p>

<p>Gender 
Periodontitis patients 
Subjects </p>

<p>Female 
1,032 
16 
Male 
2,252 
50 
Total 
3,284 
66 </p>

<p>Values are presented as number. P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. 
No statistically significant difference by gender (P = 0.108). </p>

<p>Table 3. The classification of root form by Meng [12]. </p>

<p>Type 
Type of root 
Description </p>

<p>I 
Cone root 
Normal root 
II 
Slender root 
Root morphology is too thin 
III 
Curved root 
Root form is curved 
IV 
Maladjusted proportion of crown 
and root </p>

<p>Root form is abnormally short or 
long 
V 
Syncretic root 
Two-or three-root fusion </p>

<p>Figure 1. Root form of Meng classification [12]. </p>

<p>I 
II 
III 
IV 
V </p>

<p>Journal of Periodontal 
&amp; Implant Science </p>

<p>JPIS </p>

<p>Attachment loss and root form abnormalities </p>

<p>
premolars and the first and second molars of each arch in 
this root shape analysis study. 
Tooth mortality was defined as the value obtained by add-
ing the numbers of hopeless and missing teeth. The evalua-
tion criterion for the hopeless category was an insufficient 
attachment level to maintain health, convenience, and func-
tion [14,15]. Following the clinical examination, full-mouth 
periapical radiographs were taken and analyzed for bone lev-
el, root deformity, or missing teeth using <rs id="software-0" type="software">PiView STAR</rs> soft-
ware (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Infinitt Co.</rs>., Seoul, Korea). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Data management procedures employed <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">ver. 14.0</rs>. 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). The tooth mortality and root 
form distribution were analyzed using the chi-square test. 
Periodontal probing depth and clinical attachment loss by 
root form was analyzed using one-way analysis of variance 
with Tukey or Dunnett T3 post hoc test. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>There was no significant difference in prevalence of disease 
among smokers and nonsmokers (P &gt; 0.05) (Table 4). The 
plaque index averaged 1.7 (data was not shown). 
The probing pocket depth was the deepest at the maxillary 
first molar and at the mandibular second molar (Table 5). The 
periodontal attachment loss was the highest at the first mo-
lar in both the maxilla and mandible (Table 6). The average 
number of missing teeth was 1.35 per subject. The tooth 
mortality was the highest among the maxillary first molars 
and the mandibular second molars (Table 7). 
The results of root shape deformity analysis of bicuspids 
and molars showed type V deformity to be the highest in the 
second maxillary and mandibular molars. Type IV was the 
most common in the first mandibular molar (P &lt; 0.05). All 
five types of root shape deformity were seen in the maxillary 
second premolar only (Table 8). In a comparison of frequency 
of root form abnormalities, the maxillary incidence (16.7%) 
was higher than the mandibular incidence (10.9%), showing 
a significant difference (P = 0.008) (Table 9). We analyzed the 
periodontal attachment loss of each tooth according to root 
form. In the second maxillary and mandibular molars, the 
type V root anomaly correlated with the highest periodontal 
attachment loss, 6.2 mm and 6.0 mm, respectively, among 
the deformity types, but not to a significant extent. There were </p>

<p>Table 6. Periodontal attachment loss of representative teeth. </p>

<p>First 
premolar </p>

<p>Second 
premolar 
First molar 
Second 
molar 
P-value </p>

<p>Maxilla 
4.37 ± 1.84 4.68 ± 1.80 </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>6.03 ± 2.71 
a,c) 5.40 ± 2.36 0.000 </p>

<p>Mandible 4.11 ± 1.58 4.16 ± 1.59 </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>5.14 ± 1.86 
b,c) 5.02 ± 2.08 0.000 </p>

<p>P-value 
0.266 
0.028 
0.005 
0.594 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation (mm). P &lt; 0.05 was considered 
statistically significant. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Statistically significant difference in the maxillary group. </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Statistically significant 
difference in the mandible group. </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>Statistically significant difference between 
the maxilla group and mandible group. </p>

<p>Table 7. Tooth mortality rate by tooth type. </p>

<p>Missing teeth 
Hopeless 
Tooth mortality </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Maxilla 
Central incisor 
10 (7.56) 
3 
13 (9.85) 
Lateral incisor 
6 (4.55) 
0 
6 (4.55) 
Canine 
4 (3.03) 
1 
5 (3.79) 
First premolar 
9 (6.82) 
9 
18 (13.64) 
Second premolar 
3 (2.27) 
11 
14 (10.61) 
First molar 
12 (9.09) 
16 
28 (21.21) 
Second molar 
10 (7.56) 
16 
26 (19.67) 
Total 
54 (5.84) 
56 
110 (11.90) 
Mandible 
Central incisor 
5 (3.79) 
7 
12 (9.09) 
Lateral incisor 
2 (1.52) 
5 
7 (5.30) 
Canine 
0 (0) 
0 
0 (0) 
First premolar 
3 (2.27) 
3 
6 (4.55) 
Second premolar 
6 (4.55) 
4 
10 (7.56) 
First molar 
8 (6.06) 
6 
14 (10.61) 
Second molar 
11 (8.33) 
9 
20 (15.15) 
Total 
35 (3.79) 
34 
69 (7.47) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%). P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Statistically significant difference in the maxilla and mandible group. </p>

<p>Table 5. Periodontal pocket depth of representative teeth. </p>

<p>First 
premolar </p>

<p>Second 
premolar 
First molar 
Second 
molar 
P-value </p>

<p>Maxilla 
4.0 ± 1.61 4.38 ± 1.54 </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>5.16 ± 2.26 
a) 5.06 ± 2.20 
0.000 
Mandible 3.83 ± 1.45 3.92 ± 1.49 </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>4.8 ± 1.63 5.02 ± 2.08 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>0.000 
P-value 
0.433 
0.029 
0.183 
0.875 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation (mm). P &lt; 0.05 was considered 
statistically significant. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Statistically significant difference in the maxilla group. </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Statistically significant 
difference in the mandible group. </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>Statistically significant difference between 
the maxilla group and mandible group. </p>

<p>Table 4. Smoking status of subjects. </p>

<p>Smoker, n (%) 
Nonsmoker, n (%) 
P-value </p>

<p>37 (56.1) 
29 (43.9) 
0.325 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Nonsmoker means previous smoker and never-smoker. P &lt; 0.05 was considered 
statistically significant. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>No statistically significant difference by smoking status. </p>

<p>Journal of Periodontal 
&amp; Implant Science </p>

<p>JPIS </p>

<p>Young-Mi Chung and Seong-Nyum Jeong 279 </p>

<p>no significant differences in attachment loss between the 
different deformities detected in the first and second premo-
lars and first molars (Table 10). In the comparison between 
root shape abnormality and periodontal attachment loss re-
gardless of tooth type, the type V root shape was associated </p>

<p>with the highest periodontal attachment loss at 6.09 ± 2.11 (P = 
0.01) (Table 11). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Although we did our best to identify aggressive periodonti-
tis patients based on clinical and radiographic evidence, we 
could not confirm the subjects of this study to be aggressive 
periodontitis patients. Classification of periodontal disease 
and the criteria for distinction between the two major forms 
of periodontitis are listed in the Consensus Reports of the 
1999 International Workshop. However, distinguishing be-
tween the two forms in clinical practice remains problematic. 
For example, we looked for the primary criteria of rapid at-
tachment and bone loss to diagnose aggressive periodontitis. 
However, any evaluation of disease progression requires some 
inference of the condition's severity with respect to patient 
age. According to current classification principles, age should </p>

<p>Table 8. Analysis of root form deformity by tooth. </p>

<p>Type I 
Type II 
Type III 
Type IV 
Type V 
Total 
P-value </p>

<p>Maxilla 
First premolar 
90 (89.1) 
2 (2.0) 
6 (5.9) 
3 (3.0) 
0 (0) 
101 (100) 
0.000 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Second premolar 
90 (85.7) 
2 (1.9) 
3 (5.7) 
5 (4.8) 
2 (1.9) 
105 (100) 
0.000 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>First molar 
89 (91.8) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
3 (3.1) 
5 (1.0) 
97 (100) 
0.000 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Second molar 
65 (66.3) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
5 (5.1) 
28 (28.6) 
98 (100) 
0.000 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Mandible 
First premolar 
101 (98.1) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
2 (0.4) 
0 (0) 
103 (100) 
0.000 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Second premolar 
94 (94.0) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
1 (1.0) 
0 (0) 
100 (100) 
0.000 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>First molar 
95 (94.1) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
6 (5.9) 
0 (0) 
101 (100) 
0.000 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Second molar 
68 (69.4) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
12 (12.2) 
18 (18.4) 
98 (100) 
0.000 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Values are presented as frequency (%). P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Statistically significant difference between each tooth of the maxilla. </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Statistically significant difference between each tooth of the mandible. </p>

<p>Table 9. Composition of root form by jaw type. </p>

<p>Type I 
Type II 
Type III 
Type IV 
Type V 
Total 
P-value </p>

<p>Maxilla 
334 (83.3) 
4 (1.0) 
12 (3.0) 
16 (4.0) 
35 (8.7) 
401 (100) 
0.000 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Mandible 
358 (89.1) 
0 (0) 
5 (1.2) 
21 (5.2) 
18 (4.5) 
402 (100) 
0.000 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Total 
692 (81.6) 
4 (0.5) 
17 (2.0) 
37 (4.6) 
53 (6.6) 
803 (100) </p>

<p>Values are presented as frequency (%). P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Statistically significant difference in the maxilla. </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Statistically significant difference in the mandible. </p>

<p>Table 10. Periodontal attachment loss of each tooth by root form. </p>

<p>Root type 
First premolar 
Second 
premolar 
First molar Second molar </p>

<p>Maxilla 
I 
4.5 ± 1.49 
4.8 ± 1.78 
7.0 ± 2.04 
5.7 ± 1.89 
II 
3.6 ± 0.35 
3.5 ± 0.28 
-
-
III 
5.7 ± 3.46 
4.5 ± 1.98 
-
-
IV 
3.4 ± 0.96 
5.7 ± 0.60 
7.1 ± 0.74 
5.7 ± 2.11 
V 
-
2.8 ± 0.07 
8.1 ± 2.90 
6.2 ± 1.98 
P-value 
0.177 
0.256 
0.245 
0.583 
Mandible 
I 
4.2 ± 1.49 
4.4 ± 1.28 
5.5 ± 1.46 
5.5 ± 1.58 
II 
-
-
-
-
III 
-
4.3 ± 0.78 
-
-
IV 
2.3 ± 0.00 
4.3 ± 0.00 
4.5 ± 1.96 
5.8 ± 2.19 
V 
-
-
-
6.0 ± 1.68 
P-value 
0.073 
0.961 
0.119 
0.499 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation (mm). P &lt; 0.05 was considered 
statistically significant. There was no statistically significant difference in 
periodontal attachment loss of any of the types of teeth by root form. </p>

<p>Table 11. Analysis of periodontal attachment loss by root form. </p>

<p>Type I 
Type II 
Type III 
Type IV 
Type V 
P-value </p>

<p>5.07 ± 1.05 3.53 ± 0.26 5.05 ± 2.30 5.35 ± 2.15 6.09 ± 2.11 
0.01 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation (mm). P &lt; 0.05 was considered 
statistically significant. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Statistically significant difference in periodontal attachment loss between each 
deformity group. </p>

<p>Journal of Periodontal 
&amp; Implant Science </p>

<p>JPIS </p>

<p>Attachment loss and root form abnormalities </p>

<p>
no longer constitute a primary determinant of diagnosis. Fa-
milial aggregation is also largely unhelpful [16]. A recent sys-
tematic review of the literature concluded that there is no 
evidence that the subgingival etiological factors in chronic 
periodontitis are substantially different from those of corre-
sponding lesions in aggressive periodontitis [17]. Instead, it is 
generally accepted that the variation in susceptibility to peri-
odontitis and types of disease are largely due to host factors 
[18]. In treating patients with aggressive periodontitis, there-
fore, early and aggressive treatment measures are more im-
portant than an investigation of etiology. 
A review of the published literature suggests that the preva-
lence of aggressive periodontitis may vary significantly among 
countries and ethnicities. Albandar and Tinoco [19] reported 
that the prevalence of aggressive periodontitis was 10% in 
African-Americans, 5% in Hispanics, and 1.3% in white Unit-
ed States adolescents between 13 and 17 years of age. Low 
prevalence rates ranging between 0.1% and 0.2% have been 
reported in Europe [20]. In Japan, Kowashi [21] reported a 0.47% 
prevalence of aggressive periodontal disease in subjects be-
tween 19 and 28 years of age. The data from China showed 
the prevalence of aggressive periodontitis to vary between 
0.12% and 0.47% in different areas of the country [22]. Of the 
surveyed initial 3,284 patients, 66 patients were provisionally 
assumed to have aggressive periodontitis (2.01% prevalence) 
with a mean age of 34.32, which was somewhat higher than 
that found in previous clinical studies [23]. It seems that this 
is because the subjects were patients who presented to the 
hospital rather than youths without symptoms. Considering 
an asymptomatic progression period and delay in patients 
visiting the hospital, we applied less strict criteria for age, es-
pecially since age is not a critical diagnostic criterion for ag-
gressive periodontitis. 
The gender ratio was male:female 3.13:1, but this was not a 
statistically significant difference. Studies are contradictory 
as to the predilection of periodontal disease according to 
gender. Differences in periodontal disease risk by sex have 
not been clearly demonstrated [24]. Baer [25] estimated a 
female:male ratio of about 3:1. Hormand and Frandsen [26] 
concluded that the disease affects females more often than 
males with a ratio of 2.5:1. Albandar and Rams [27] denied the 
existence of a relationship between aggressive periodontitis 
and gender. More studies are required to determine the gen-
der ratio in aggressive periodontitis prevalence in Koreans. 
In the present study, marked attachment loss over 5 mm 
was observed at the first molars. This result is consistent with 
our previous study [23]. It is assumed that the first molars 
might be affected earlier by periodontitis. Aggressive peri-
odontitis developed as a localized form may progress into a 
generalized form with the involvement of more teeth with </p>

<p>advancing age. 
The average number of missing teeth was 1.35 at the first 
visit, but if we include the teeth diagnosed as hopeless, it 
doubled to 2.71. The most frequently missing teeth in the 
current study were the maxillary first molars (21.21%) and the 
mandibular second molars (15.15%). In the evaluation of 
tooth mortality, a high attachment loss of molars seems to 
lead to high tooth loss. We can assume that the high percent-
age of molar tooth loss might be because the molars had ad-
ditional susceptibility factors such as occlusal interference, 
hygienic difficulty, and abnormal root form. Further epide-
miologic studies of larger populations, comparing them with 
normal and chronic periodontitis subjects, are needed to as-
sess the exact prevalence and pattern of aggressive periodon-
titis in Korea. 
The shape, length, and spread of molar roots are important 
factors in tooth prognosis, as they can affect the anchorage 
and stability of molars. Molar root fusion is one of the most 
common anomalies in root morphological development [8,11]. 
Root fusion (type V) was the commonest anomaly in both the 
maxilla and mandible, and showed the highest prevalence in 
the second molars in this study. Ross and Evanchik [11] re-
ported that a relatively high proportion of Europeans (70%) 
had one or more maxillary molars and 54% had one or more 
mandibular molars with fused roots. In the studies of Choi et 
al. [28] and Ryu et al. [29], root fusion demonstrated higher 
prevalence in the maxilla than mandible, and was the highest 
in the second maxillary molar. When we analyzed the degree 
of periodontal tissue destruction according to root shape, the 
second molars with root fusion (type V) had a greater risk of 
increased probing depth and periodontal attachment loss. In 
the correlation of root fusion and local inflammation, Choi 
et al. [28] reported a significance increase in clinical index-
probing depth, gingival index, and tooth mobility in both the 
maxilla and mandible. Likewise, Hou and Tsai [8,30] described 
the correlation between root fusion and periodontal disease 
in a Chinese population. Negative characteristics of molars 
with root fusion, such as an unfavorable crown-to-root ratio, 
short root length, and a taper-shaped root, may offer less re-
sistance to heavy occlusal loads and/or torque forces. This 
evidence suggests that molar root fusion may ultimately ac-
celerate periodontal tissue destruction. However, Hou and 
Tsai's study was not conducted in patients with aggressive 
periodontitis. Given the similar results of the present study, 
we can cautiously infer that a fused root can be a contribut-
ing factor in disease progression of aggressive periodontitis 
as well as of chronic periodontitis. 
In summary, periodontal attachment loss was the highest 
at the first molar in both the maxilla and mandible. Root fu-
sion (type V) was the most prevalent among root abnormality </p>

<p>Journal of Periodontal 
&amp; Implant Science </p>

<p>JPIS </p>

<p>Young-Mi Chung and Seong-Nyum Jeong 281 </p>

<p>types in both the maxilla and mandible, demonstrating the 
highest prevalence in the second molars. In the comparison 
between root shape abnormality and periodontal attachment 
loss regardless of tooth type, the type V root shape was asso-
ciated with the highest attachment loss. Studies on the impact 
of root shape in patients with aggressive and chronic peri-
odontitis are rare. Considering the small population and lim-
ited design of this study, definitive conclusions cannot be 
drawn. We suggest more large-scale, methodologically so-
phisticated studies that include normal controls and chronic 
periodontitis patients to clarify whether root form abnormal-
ities are a potential risk factor for aggressive periodontitis. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was 
reported. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by a 2012 Grant from Wonkwang 
University. </p>



<p>Journal of Periodontal 
&amp; Implant Science </p>

<p>JPIS </p>



</text></tei>