<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3378868" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor c 
(PPARc) is a key transcription factor in mamma-
lian adipogenesis. Genome-wide approaches 
have identified thousands of PPARc binding sites 
in mouse adipocytes and PPARc upregulates 
hundreds of protein-coding genes during adipo-
genesis. However, no microRNA (miRNA) genes 
have been identified as primary PPARc-targets. By 
integration of four separate datasets of genome-
wide PPARc binding sites in 3T3-L1 adipocytes we 
identified 98 miRNA clusters with PPARc binding 
within 50 kb from miRNA transcription start sites. 
Nineteen mature miRNAs were upregulated !2-fold 
during adipogenesis and for six of these miRNA loci 
the PPARc binding sites were confirmed by at least 
three datasets. The upregulation of five miRNA 
genes miR-103-1 (host gene Pank3), miR-148b 
(Copz1), miR-182/96/183, miR-205 and miR-378 
(Ppargc1b) followed that of Pparg. The PPARc-
dependence of four of these miRNA loci was 
demonstrated by PPARc knock-down and the loci 
of miR-103-1 (Pank3), miR-205 and miR-378 
(Ppargc1b) were also responsive to the PPARc 
ligand rosiglitazone. Finally, chromatin immunopre-
cipitation analysis validated in silico predicted 
PPARc binding sites at all three loci and H3K27 
acetylation was analyzed to confirm the activity of 
these enhancers. In conclusion, we identified 22 
putative PPARc target miRNA genes, showed the 
PPARc dependence of four of these genes and 
demonstrated three as direct PPARc target genes 
in mouse adipogenesis. </p>

<p>The need for understanding of the mechanisms controlling 
the differentiation of fibroblast-like pre-adipocytes to 
lipid-loaded adipocytes is due to the worldwide epidemic 
of obesity of high medical relevance (1). Adipogenesis is 
regulated by a network of transcription factors. The most 
prominent transcription factor in adipocytes is the nuclear 
receptor peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor g 
(PPARg) (2). During mouse adipogenesis the number of 
genomic binding sites for PPARg increases from a few 
to thousands (3-7) implicating that PPARg regulates 
hundreds of genes during adipogenesis. Therefore, the 
synthetic PPARg ligand rosiglitazone (RGZ) has been 
used in many countries in the therapy of type 2 diabetes 
mainly acting via its effects on gene regulation in adipo-
cytes (8). 
The prerequisite for the direct transcriptional regula-
tion of a given gene by PPARg is the presence of at 
least one specific PPARg binding site, referred to 
as PPAR response element (PPRE), in the regulatory 
regions flanking the gene's transcription start site (TSS) 
[reviewed in (9)]. Direct DNA binding of PPARg takes 
place as a heterodimeric complex with another nuclear 
receptor, the retinoid X receptor (RXR), and PPREs 
are formed as a direct repeat of hexameric core binding 
motifs with one intervening nucleotide (DR1-type 
PPREs) (10,11). To promote the expression of its target 
genes, PPARg must overcome the transcriptionally 
repressive dense packaging of genomic DNA within 
chromatin. PPARg is also capable of repressing some of 
its target genes in a ligand-dependent manner either 
directly via recruitment of co-repressors upon agonist 
binding or via a mechanism called trans-repression 
(12,13). However, in adipocytes PPARg has been mainly 
linked to transcriptional activation of its target genes 
(3-5). </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +352 4666446839; Fax: +352 4666446949; Email: lasse.sinkkonen@uni.lu </p>

<p>4446-4460 Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 10 
Published online 7 February 2012 
doi:10.1093/nar/gks025 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>In addition to transcription factors and their co-factors, 
several new groups of small RNA molecules have been 
described in recent years as capable of controlling gene 
expression [reviewed in (14)]. One of the most important 
of these groups consists of small RNA molecules called 
microRNAs (miRNAs), which are endogenous non-
coding transcripts transcribed mainly by RNA polymerase 
II (RNA Pol II) as their own primary transcripts 
(pri-miRNAs) or together with their host genes 
[reviewed in (15)]. The miRNA precursor (pre-miRNA) 
is cropped from the primary transcript by a complex 
known as Microprocessor that consists of two proteins, 
namely DROSHA and DGCR8. This pre-miRNA hairpin 
is then further processed into the mature miRNA duplex 
by an RNase III enzyme DICER. The mature miRNAs 
can identify their target mRNAs by base pairing to the 
partially complementary regions within the target mRNAs 
(16). miRNAs function by serving as guides to the 
proteins of the Argonaute family and other associated 
proteins, which together induce inhibition of translation 
as well as degradation of the targeted mRNAs (17,18). 
Currently, there are more than 700 known mature 
miRNAs in mouse (miRBase v18.0) and most of them 
can potentially target hundreds of mRNAs (19,20). 
In this way they show very comparable functions to tran-
scription factors. Thus miRNAs can remarkably influence 
the transcriptomes of most eukaryotic cells. Still, fairly 
little is known about the transcriptional regulation of 
miRNA genes. Until recently, the progress was 
hampered by limited knowledge about the structure of 
miRNA genes, especially the location of their TSSs 
(21,22). Many miRNAs are transcribed together as 
clusters of several mature miRNAs. Considering this 
feature and the fact that each of these miRNAs can 
have a potential to regulate a vast number of target 
mRNAs, the transcriptional control of these miRNA 
genes needs to be both accurate and robust. And import-
antly, miRNAs have been shown to play key roles in the 
development and differentiation of most tissues and cell 
types (23). Also the formation of white adipose tissue 
in vivo and the differentiation of the mouse pre-adipocyte 
cell line 3T3-L1 depend on expression of miRNAs (24,25). 
Moreover, some miRNAs, such as miR-103, are regula-
tors of adipogenesis in mouse (26). 
Several recent datasets of chromatin immunopre-
cipitation (ChIP)-based monitoring of genome-wide 
binding of PPARg during differentiation of 3T3-L1 cells 
identified thousands of genomic PPARg-bound sites sug-
gesting hundreds of PPARg target genes (3-7). However, 
none of these are miRNA genes. Therefore, in this study 
we integrated four of the above mentioned datasets of 
genome-wide PPARg binding sites and mouse miRNA 
TSS annotations (3-6,21) and identified 98 miRNA 
clusters with PPARg binding within 50 kb from 
miRNA gene TSSs. Nineteen of these miRNAs (corres-
ponding to 22 miRNA genes) are upregulated during 
adipogenesis and are putative PPARg targets. Further 
filtering resulted in the five miRNA genes miR-103-1 
(host gene Pank3), miR-148b (Copz1), miR-182/96/183, 
miR-205 and miR-378 (Ppargc1b) that followed the 
upregulation of the Pparg gene during mouse </p>

<p>adipogenesis. The transcription of all except miR-148b 
(Copz1) depends on PPARg in adipocytes and the loci 
of miR-103-1, miR-205 and miR-378 were also responsive 
to RGZ. Finally, ChIP assays validated three in silico pre-
dicted PPREs at the miR-103-1 locus, two at the miR-378 
locus, and one at the miR-205 locus. In conclusion, we 
have identified a number of PPARg-regulated miRNA 
genes in mouse adipogenesis, which will serve the future 
integration of miRNAs to the core regulatory network of 
adipocyte differentiation and further characterize the 
extensive role of PPARg during this process. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Integration of the genome-wide PPARc binding data 
and miRNA TSS annotation </p>

<p>The different publically available datasets used in this 
study were unified on a common genome build on the 
basis of the coordinates from TSS annotation data for 
miRNA genes from Marson et al. (21), namely NCBI36/ 
mm8. Accordingly, the coordinates of the PPARg-bound 
sites from Nielsen et al. (4) and Lefterova et al. (6) were 
lifted over from mm9 to mm8 using the UCSC lift-over 
tool, while the coordinates from the datasets of Lefterova 
et al. (3) and Hamza et al. (5) were already based on mm8. 
For all datasets we used only published pre-analyzed data 
and the provided coordinates for PPARg-bound sites were 
used. First, miRNA gene TSSs within 50 kb of a PPARg 
binding site (Supplementary Table S1A-D) were 
identified. This was followed by checking whether an 
identified PPARg binding site overlaps with an in silico 
predicted PPRE (10) (Supplementary Table S2A-D). 
A third step detects, whether an identified PPARg 
binding site co-localizes with a CEBPa (CCAAT/ 
enhancer binding protein) binding site. As input data for 
the last step, PPARg-and CEBPa-bound sites provided 
by Lefterova et al. (3) were used and a threshold of 1 kb 
was applied to define a co-localized region. Further details 
can be provided upon request. </p>

<p>Cell culture </p>

<p>The 3T3-L1 mouse pre-adipocyte cell line was used for all 
experiments. The cells were maintained in Dulbecco's 
modified Eagle's medium supplemented with 10% fetal 
calf serum, 1% penicillin-streptomycin and 1% L-glutam-
ine. The cells were kept at 37 C and 5% CO 2 . In order to 
differentiate pre-adipocytes to adipocytes, the cells were 
seeded 4 days before differentiation (D-4), grown 2 days 
to reach confluency (D-2) and maintained 2 days 
post-confluency before starting the differentiation (D0) 
by adding differentiation medium I (500 mM 3-isobutyl-
1-methylxanthine, 250 nM dexamethasone and 5 mg/ml 
insulin in normal growth medium). From D2 on differen-
tiation medium II (5 mg/ml insulin and 100 nM RGZ in 
normal growth medium) was used and renewed every 2 
days (D4, D6). For treatments with RGZ and 
5,6-Dichlorobenzimidazole 1-b-D-ribofuranoside (DRB) 
the cells were seeded and grown in the same way as 
described above. Two or six days differentiated 3T3-L1 
mouse cells were treated either with 100 nM RGZ </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 10 4447 </p>

<p>or 100 mM of DRB and with an equal volume of a vehicle 
control [dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO)] and total RNA was 
collected after 4, 8, 12, 24 and 48 h. </p>

<p>siRNA silencing </p>

<p>Six days differentiated 3T3-L1 cells were transfected with 
Nucleofector II Device (Lonza, Basel, Switzerland) by 
using Cell Line Nucleofector Kit V and program A-033. 
The transfection procedure was done according to the 
manufacturer's instructions using a 100 nM mixture of 
three double-stranded siRNA sequences against Pparg 
(siPparg, Eurogentec, Liege, Belgium) or 100 nM of a 
scrambled double-stranded siRNA sequence as a control 
(siControl, Eurogentec). The cells were collected 48 h 
post-transfection. The siRNA sequences are provided in 
Supplementary Table S3. </p>

<p>RNA extraction and cDNA synthesis </p>

<p>Total RNA was isolated from the 3T3-L1 cells by using 
TRIsure (Bioline, London, UK). Medium was removed 
and 1 ml of TRIsure per 6-well plates was added to lyse 
the cells. RNA was extracted with 200 ml chloroform 
and precipitated from the aqueous phase with 400 ml isopro-
panol by incubating at À20 C overnight. cDNA 
was synthesized by using 1 mg of total RNA, 0.5 mM 
dNTPs, 2.5 mM oligo-dT primer (for mature mRNAs) or 
0.2 mg random hexamer primers (for pri-miRNAs), 1 U/ml 
RiboLock RNase Inhibitor (Fermentas, Vilnius, Lithuania) 
and 10 U/ml M-MuLV Reverse Transcriptase (Fermentas). 
The cDNA synthesis was performed for 1 h at 37 C and 
the reaction was stopped by 10 min incubation at 70 C. </p>

<p>Quantitative PCR </p>

<p>Real-time quantitative PCR (qPCR) was performed in an 
Applied Biosystems 7500 Fast Real-Time PCR System 
using Absolute Blue qPCR SYBR Green Low ROX Mix 
(Thermo Fisher Scientific, Surrey, UK). For each reaction 
5 ml of cDNA template or 4 ml of ChIP template, 1 ml of 
primer pairs (10 mM) and 10 ml of the qPCR SYBR 
mixture to a final reaction volume of 20 ml were used. 
The PCR reaction started with 15 min at 95 C to 
activate the polymerase. The PCR cycling conditions 
were: 40 cycles, of which each was composed of 15 s at 
95 C, 15 s at 55 C and 30 s at 72 C. Relative expression 
levels at the tested experimental conditions were calculated 
within each independent experiment using the formula 
2 À(ÁÁCt) , where ÁÁCt is (Ct (target gene) À Ct (Rpl13a) ) tested </p>

<p>condition À (Ct (target gene) À Ct (Rpl13a) ) control condition and the 
Ct is the cycle, at which the threshold is crossed. 
Depending on the experiment either vehicle control, 
siCtrl or D0 served as the control condition. The quality 
of the PCR product was monitored using post-PCR melt 
curve analysis. The sequences of the primer pairs are listed 
in Supplementary Table S4 and a schematic depiction of 
their locations is provided in Supplementary Figure S1. </p>

<p>miRNA assays </p>

<p>The detection of the miRNAs was done by using TaqMan 
MicroRNA Reverse Transcription Kit together with </p>

<p>TaqMan MicroRNA Assays (Applied Biosystems). The 
miRNA cDNA synthesis and miRNA detection was 
done by following the manufacturers instructions and by 
using an Applied Biosystems 7500 Fast Real-Time PCR 
System. Relative expression levels at the tested experimen-
tal conditions were calculated within each independent 
experiment using the formula 2 À(ÁÁCt) , where ÁÁCt 
is (Ct (target miRNA) À Ct (U6) ) tested condition À (Ct (target </p>

<p>miRNA) À Ct (U6) ) control condition and the Ct is the cycle, at 
which the threshold is crossed. Depending on the experi-
ment either vehicle control, siCtrl or D0 served as the 
control condition. </p>

<p>ChIP </p>

<p>ChIP was performed using confluent 3T3-L1 pre-
adipocytes (D0) or 3T3-L1 adipocytes (D6) grown on 
10 cm 2 dishes. Chromatin was cross-linked by adding for-
maldehyde at Enal concentration of 1% to the culture 
media for 8 min. The cross-linking reaction was stopped 
with 150 mM glycine for 5 min. The cells were washed 
twice with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and lysed in 
650 ml SDS lysis buffer (1% SDS, 10 mM EDTA, 50 mM 
Tris-HCl, pH 8.1) containing a protease inhibitor cocktail 
(Roche Diagnostics, Mannheim, Germany). In order to 
reduce the DNA to average length of 500 bp, the lysates 
were sonicated (Bioruptor, Diagenode, Liege, Belgium) 
with 15 Â 30 s pulses. Cellular debris were removed by cen-
trifugation and the lysates were diluted 1:10 in ChIP 
dilution buffer (0.01% SDS, 1.1% Triton X-100, 1.2 mM 
EDTA, 167 mM NaCl, protease inhibitors and 16.7 mM 
Tris-HCl, pH 8.1). A quantity of 1500 ml of diluted lysate 
were incubated with the respective antibody [3.5 ml 
anti-PPARg (101 700, Cayman, Ann Arbor, MI USA), 
5 ml anti-PPARg (sc-7196, Santa Cruz Biotechnologies, 
Santa Cruz, CA, USA) or 2.5 ml IgG (sc-2027)] overnight 
at 4 C. The immuno-complexes were collected with 60 ml 
of BSA-coated protein A agarose beads slurry (Millipore, 
Billerica, MA, USA) for 2 h at 4 C with rotation. The 
beads, containing the immuno-complexes, were washed 
sequentially with 1 ml of the following buffers: low salt 
wash buffer (0.1% SDS, 1% Triton X-100, 2 mM 
EDTA, 150 mM NaCl, 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.1), high 
salt wash buffer (0.1% SDS, 1% Triton X-100, 2 mM 
EDTA, 500 mM NaCl, 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.1), LiCl 
wash buffer (0.25 mM LiCl, 1% Nonidet P-40, 1% 
sodium deoxycholate, 1 mM EDTA, 10 mM Tris-HCl, 
pH 8.1) and twice with TE buffer (1 mM EDTA, 10 mM 
Tris-HCl, pH 8.0). After the washing steps the 
immuno-complexes were eluted with 500 ml elution buffer 
(1% SDS, 100 mM NaHCO 3 ). The cross-linking was 
reversed with proteinase K (40 mg/ml, Fermentas) over-
night at 65 C. The DNA was recovered by 
phenol-chloroform extraction or by ChIP DNA Clean 
Kit (Zymo Research, Irvine, CA, USA), ethanol 
precipitated and dissolved in 60 ml of water. Sample of 
4 ml were used as template for qPCR using specific 
primers listed in Supplementary Table S4. Relative enrich-
ment was calculated using the formula 2 À(ÁÁCt) where 
ÁÁC t 
is 
(Ct (PPARg) À Ct (input) ) À (Ct (IgG) À Ct (input) ), 
PPARg and IgG are the respective immunoprecipitated </p>

<p>4448 Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 10 </p>

<p>DNA samples and input is 1:100 diluted purified genomic 
DNA from the starting material of the respective 
immunoprecipitation. </p>

<p>Western blot </p>

<p>Cells, seeded in 6-well plates, were first washed with PBS, 
trypsinized for 5 min at 37 C and centrifuged. The remain-
ing pellet was lysed in 200 ml ice-cold protein lysis buffer 
(150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 1% Triton-X, 20 mM Tris-
HCl, pH 7.4) containing protease inhibitors (Roche 
Diagnostics). Then the lysate was sonicated at low fre-
quency with 10 repeats of 8 s pulses followed by 30 s 
pauses. Sonicated lysates were centrifuged for 30 min at 
maximum speed to separate the fat from the proteins and 
the cell debris. The protein concentrations were measured 
by Bradford assay and comparable amounts were loaded 
on a gel. The proteins were separated with SDS-PAGE, 
probed with the corresponding primary (anti-PPARg, 
1:200 dilution (101 700 Cayman), anti-b-actin, 1:10,000 
dilution (MAB1501, Millipore) and horseradish pero-
xidase-coupled secondary antibodies (anti-mouse IgG, 
1:500 dilution (P0447, Dako, Glostrup, Denmark) and 
anti-rabbit IgG, 1:500 dilution (P0448, Dako)) and dete-
cted via ECL (GE Healthcare, Buckinghamshire, UK). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>PPARc localization at miRNA loci in mouse adipocytes </p>

<p>In order to identify miRNA genes regulated by PPARg in 
mouse adipogenesis, we integrated the genome-wide 
binding site coordinate information from four available 
datasets (3-6) with the recent TSS annotation of mouse 
miRNA genes (21) (Table 1). The considered binding sites 
were selected according to the analysis in the original pub-
lications (3-6). The total number of PPARg-bound sites in 
the differentiated 3T3-L1 adipocytes varied for each 
dataset from approximately 2600 to almost 7000. We 
screened each of the four datasets for miRNA genes that 
had at least one PPARg-bound site within ±50 kb from 
their TSS (Supplementary Table S1). Under these criteria 
for each dataset between 22 and 70 miRNA clusters (cor-
responding to 31-113 miRNA precursors) were identified. 
Combining the information from all four datasets resulted 
in 98 different miRNA clusters (corresponding to 149 in-
dividual miRNA precursors and 140 different mature 
miRNAs, Table 1). Within these 98 genomic loci 61 
miRNA genes had at least one of their observed </p>

<p>PPARg-bound sites overlapping with a putative PPRE 
identified in silico by RESearch algorithm (10) 
(summarized in Table 1, details are in Supplementary 
Table S2). This suggests that in majority of the loci the 
PPARg enrichment corresponds to direct DNA binding. 
In summary, we integrated genome-wide datasets for 
PPARg binding with the location of miRNA gene 
TSSs and identified 149 pre-miRNAs corresponding to 
140 mature miRNAs in 98 genomic loci with at least 
one PPARg binding site within 50 kb distance to their 
TSS. </p>

<p>Identification of putative PPARc target miRNA genes </p>

<p>To better distinguish, which of the miRNA genes with 
PPARg binding in their vicinity could be direct targets 
of PPARg, we compared the list of 140 mature miRNAs 
combined from all four datasets (originating from 149 
precursors; Table 1) to the existing miRNA expression 
profiling from 3T3-L1 adipocytes (26) (Figure 1A). 
Applying a 2-fold cut-off, a similar number of miRNAs 
were up-and downregulated (26 and 19, respectively) 
during 9 days of adipogenesis. Comparing these miRNA 
lists with the combined list of 140 mature miRNAs 
(Table 1) showed that a total of 19 different mature 
miRNAs associated with PPARg binding in at least one 
of the datasets were also upregulated above 2-fold during 
3T3-L1 adipogenesis (Figure 1A). Nine different miRNAs 
showed similar extent of downregulation. Interestingly, 
the miRNA genes with PPARg-bound sites were signifi-
cantly enriched for upregulated miRNAs (calculated using 
hypergeometric probability, P = 1.03 Â 10 À5 ). This en-
richment of upregulated miRNAs fits well with the role 
of PPARg as a transcriptional activator of its target genes 
(3-5) and implies that many of these miRNAs could be 
real targets of PPARg-mediated regulation. 
Since many mature miRNAs can be transcribed from 
more than one locus, but cannot be distinguished by 
sequence in miRNA microarray analysis, the number of 
miRNA genes that are putative primary PPARg targets is 
22, i.e. it exceeds that of the identified mature miRNAs. In 
addition, many of these putative PPARg target miRNA 
genes give rise to more than one mature miRNA. This 
opens the possibility that also the other miRNAs that 
are transcribed from these clusters are regulated by 
PPARg, although they did not change above 2-fold in 
the array analysis. </p>

<p>Table 1. Genome-wide PPARg occupancy close to miRNA gene TSSs </p>

<p>Dataset 
Total # of PPARg 
peaks </p>

<p># of miRNA precur-
sors with PPARg peak 
(±50 kb) </p>

<p># of miRNA clusters with 
PPARg peak (±50 kb) </p>

<p># of miRNA clusters 
with PPARg peaks 
overlapping PPREs </p>

<p>Lefterova et al. (3) (ChIP-chip) 
5299 
77 
52 
36 
Nielsen et al. (4) (ChIP-Seq) 
6946 
113 
70 
45 
Hamza et al. (5) (ChIP-PET) 
2953 
49 
35 
1 
Lefterova et al. (6) (ChIP-Seq) 
2611 
31 
22 
12 
All combined 
-
149 
98 
61 </p>

<p>The annotation of miRNA TSS is based on Marson et al. (21). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 10 4449 </p>

<p>In order to more stringently identify the true targets of 
PPARg among the putative target miRNAs, we analyzed 
how many of all of the miRNA genes are implicated as 
PPARg targets in at least three of the four used genome-
wide binding profile datasets. The direct overlapping of 
the exact PPARg binding site genomic coordinates from 
the four different datasets rarely show direct matches, 
although the same antibody has been used in all four 
studies (data not shown). These differences are likely to 
be explained by the rather different methodology and 
varying data analysis strategies. In order to overcome 
this issue, we checked how many of the PPARg-associated 
miRNAs (Supplementary Table S1) were common 
between the different datasets. Ten miRNAs were 
located in loci bound by PPARg in all four genomic 
PPARg binding site datasets and another 19 in at least 
three of the four datasets (Supplementary Figure S2). 
From these 29 miRNAs, 27 were mature miRNAs with 
different sequences and could be distinguished in miRNA 
microarray analysis. Overlapping the list of these mature 
miRNAs with the miRNAs downregulated in adipocytes 
yielded only one mature miRNA (Figure 1B). However, 
five mature miRNAs miR-103, miR-148b, miR-183, </p>

<p>miR-205 and miR-378, originating from six separate 
miRNAs genes, were upregulated above 2-fold in adipo-
cytes. These constitute the high confidence PPARg target 
miRNA genes in mouse adipocytes and are referred to as 
the candidate PPARg target miRNAs from here on. 
Taken together, further filtering of miRNA genes with 
PPARg-bound sites that were both confirmed in at least 
three genome-wide datasets and upregulated at least 
2-fold during adipogenesis reduced the list to the five 
miRNAs miR-103, miR-148b, miR-183, miR-205 and 
miR-378. </p>

<p>Dynamic expression profiles of the candidate 
PPARc-target miRNAs and their host genes during 
adipocyte differentiation </p>

<p>The five candidate PPARg target miRNAs originate from 
six different miRNA loci, since miR-103 is transcribed 
from two different loci, miR-103-1 and miR-103-2, as 
two identical mature miRNAs. miR-103-1, miR-103-2, 
miR-148b and miR-378 are transcribed within their re-
spective host genes Pank3, Pank2, Copz1 and Ppargc1b. 
None of these host genes have so far been described as </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>miRNAs with PPARγ binding 
within 50 kb from TSS (140) </p>

<p>miRNAs down-regulated 
≥ 2.0-fold during 3T3-L1 
differentiation (19) </p>

<p>miRNAs up-regulated 
≥ 2.0-fold during 
3T3-L1 differentiation (26) </p>

<p>High confidence PPARg target miRNA genes (6): </p>

<p>mmu-miR-103-1 </p>

<p>mmu-miR-103-2 </p>

<p>mmu-miR-148b </p>

<p>mmu-miR-182/miR-96/miR-183 </p>

<p>mmu-miR-205 </p>

<p>mmu-miR-378 </p>

<p>miRNAs with PPARγ binding within 50 kb 
from TSS in ≥ 3 datasets (27) </p>

<p>miRNAs down-regulated 
≥ 2.0-fold during 3T3-L1 
differentiation (19) </p>

<p>miRNAs up-regulated 
≥ 2.0-fold during 
3T3-L1 differentiation (26) </p>

<p>Putative PPARg target miRNA genes (22): </p>

<p>mmu-let7a-1/let-7f-1/let-7d 
mmu-miR-182/miR-96/miR-183 </p>

<p>2 
-
5 
6 
3 
/ 
3 
9 
1 
-
R 
i 
m 
-
u 
m 
m 
g 
7 
-
t 
e 
l 
-
u 
m 
m </p>

<p>mmu-miR-101b 
mmu-miR-193b/miR-365-1 </p>

<p>mmu-miR-103-1 
mmu-miR-194-1/miR-215 </p>

<p>mmu-miR-103-2 
mmu-miR-194-2/miR-192 </p>

<p>mmu-miR-107 
mmu-miR-205 </p>

<p>mmu-miR-10b 
mmu-miR-210 </p>

<p>mmu-miR-146b 
mmu-miR-30a </p>

<p>mmu-miR-148a 
mmu-miR-30c-1/miR-30e </p>

<p>mmu-miR-148b 
mmu-miR-30c-2 </p>

<p>mmu-miR-15a/miR-16-1 
mmu-miR-378 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Dataset integration to identify the putative PPARg target miRNAs. (A) A Venn diagram depicting the overlapping of the list of all 
individual mature miRNAs (140) with PPARg binding within 50 kb from their TSS (Supplementary Table S1) together with &gt;2-fold up or 
downregulated miRNAs based on available miRNA expression profiling during 3T3-L1 differentiation (26). This analysis yields 19 upregulated 
mature miRNAs that are putative PPARg targets. The 22 putative PPARg target miRNA genes corresponding to the 19 mature miRNAs (in bold) 
are listed on the right side. (B) A Venn diagram depicting the overlapping of the list of all individual mature miRNAs (27) with PPARg binding 
within 50 kb from their TSS (Supplementary Figure S2) in at least three of the used datasets together with &gt;2-fold up or downregulated miRNAs 
based on available miRNA expression profiling during 3T3-L1 differentiation. This analysis yields five upregulated mature miRNAs that are high 
confidence PPARg targets. The six putative PPARg target miRNA genes corresponding to the five mature miRNAs (in bold) are listed on the 
right side. </p>

<p>4450 Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 10 </p>

<p>primary PPARg targets. miR-183 and miR-205 are 
transcribed from intergenic regions, most likely as inde-
pendent miRNA genes. In addition, miR-183 is part of a 
cluster of three mature miRNAs and is transcribed 
together with the two other members of the cluster, 
miR-182 and miR-96. 
Due to the very short sequence of the mature miRNAs, 
the arrays used to measure miRNA expression profiles are 
often prone to false positive results. In order to validate 
the upregulation and to analyze the expression dynamics 
of the six candidate PPARg target miRNAs as well as 
their host genes, we profiled their expression and 
compared them with the positive control genes Pparg, 
Cebpa and Angptl4 during mouse adipogenesis. To do 
this we took every 24 h RNA samples from the 8-day dif-
ferentiation process of 3T3-L1 cells and determined by 
qPCR the relative expression of the transcripts of 
interest (Figure 2A). For each miRNA we measured the 
levels of the mature miRNA as well as the pri-miRNA. 
While the exact fold changes between independent differ-
entiation experiments vary, the overall expression profiles 
of individual transcripts were generally reproducible 
(Figure 2B-G). This was confirmed by ANOVA analysis 
for significant changes during the time course, which con-
firmed the changes for all tested mRNAs and most of the 
microRNAs as statistically significant (Figure 2). 
The robust upregulation of the Pparg gene was visible 
already on D2 and confirmed the successful differentiation 
of the adipocytes (Figure 2B). The expression profiles of 
the two known primary PPARg target genes, Cebpa and 
Angptl4 (27,28), followed closely that of Pparg. All three 
genes were clearly induced by D4 and remained at induced 
levels through the remaining time course (Figure 2B). 
Mature miR-103-1 and miR-103-2 are produced from 
intron 5 of two separate but related host genes encoding 
the pantothenate kinases PANK3 and PANK2, respect-
ively. These enzymes are important for co-enzyme 
A synthesis and thereby for lipid metabolism (29). The 
level of mature miR-103 continuously increased through 
the differentiation starting from D2 to &gt;5-fold on D8 
(Figure 2C). Consistent with previous reports, the Pank2 
gene showed no or only weak upregulation during 
adipogenesis when compared with the level of Pank3 
mRNA that robustly increased with an expression 
profile similar to that of the known PPARg target gene 
Cebpa (Figure 2C) (26). This indicates that the observed 
increase in miR-103 is mainly due to increased production 
of miR-103-1 from the Pank3 gene locus. This observation 
is further supported by the fact that pri-miR-103-1 is 
clearly induced during adipogenesis while pri-miR-103-2 
remained non-induced in most experiments. Interestingly, 
the upregulation of the mature miR-103 showed a delay in 
relation to its host gene Pank3. This might reflect the 
different processing and stability of the miRNA 
compared with the mRNA as well as the fact that tran-
scription at the Pank3 locus has to triple in order to lead 
to doubling in the mature miR-103 production due to very 
similar basal expression levels of the two miR-103 loci 
(data not shown, see also 'Discussion' section). 
Unlike for miR-103, the initial induction of miR-148b 
slightly preceded that of its host gene Copz1 and showed a </p>

<p>peak after D6 of differentiation (Figure 2D). Both 
miR-148b and its host gene Copz1 were upregulated 
more moderately than the other tested PPARg target 
genes and for Copz1 (and the pri-miR-148b) the fold 
change never exceeded 3-fold. The upregulation of 
miR-96 was fairly robust reaching maximum induction 
around D8 of differentiation and resembling the delayed 
induction of miR-103 (Figure 2E). However, the expres-
sion profile of pri-miR-96 suggests that the locus is tran-
scriptionally activated already at earlier stages of 
differentiation. 
By far the most induced of all the tested miRNAs was 
miR-205 that had strongly increased already on D3 of 
differentiation and reached several hundred-fold induc-
tion by the end of the differentiation (Figure 2F). The 
extent of the induction can be explained by the very low 
basal expression of miR-205 in pre-adipocytes (data not 
shown). Similarly to the mature miRNA, also pri-miR-205 
was upregulated during the time course, although with 
lower fold change. This argues that increased transcrip-
tional activity at the miR-205 locus is contributing to the 
robust observed induction of the mature miRNA, while 
specific regulation of the miRNA biogenesis pathway 
might also play a role. 
The upregulation of miR-378 was the second highest of 
all the miRNAs tested (Figure 2G). The host gene of 
miR-378, Ppargc1b, encodes for PGC-1b, which is an 
important transcriptional co-activator of PPARg as well 
as other transcription factors (30,31). Ppargc1b expression 
was induced already early on with a very similar profile to 
known PPARg target genes, followed by strong increase in 
pri-miR-378. The mature miR-378 followed the expression 
of the host gene and the primary transcript, leading again 
to slightly delayed response by the mature miRNA. 
In general, the pri-miRNAs showed quite different 
dynamics from their respective mature miRNAs, and 
especially for miR-205, these inductions were clearly 
weaker. These differences may be explained by the rela-
tively low stability of the transient pri-miRNA transcripts 
that are processed into pre-miRNAs co-transcriptionally 
(32,33). To address this possibility in more detail we 
specifically inhibited RNA Pol II-mediated transcriptional 
elongation in D6 adipocytes by treating the cells 
with DRB for a time course of 12, 24 and 48 h (Supple-
mentary Figure S3A). As expected, all tested mRNAs had 
decreased by around 50% or more already after 12 h and 
remained at lowered levels throughout the treatment 
(Supplementary Figure S3B-G). Cebpa and Pparg were 
the least stable mRNAs with only 5-20% of the tran-
scripts remaining after DRB treatment when compared 
with cells similarly treated with the DMSO vehicle 
(Supplementary Figure S3B). Similarly to mRNAs, the 
pri-miRNA transcripts were all reduced up to 10-fold 
after 12 h of transcription inhibition and for all except 
pri-miR-103-2 remained below the control levels 
(Supplementary Figure S3B-G). Curiously, all pri-
miRNA transcripts exhibited some increase in their 
levels towards the end of the treatment. This might to be 
explained by decreased processing of the primary tran-
scripts upon prolonged inhibition of RNA Pol II. In 
contrast to the unstable pri-miRNA transcripts, most of </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 10 4451 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>Figure 2. Expression profiles of the candidate PPARg target miRNAs and host genes during 8 days of 3T3-L1 mouse pre-adipocyte differentiation. qPCR with gene-specific primers for miRNA 
host genes and the pri-miRNAs or TaqMan probes for the mature miRNAs were used to measure the expression profiles of the different transcripts during 8 days of 3T3-L1 mouse pre-adipocyte 
differentiation. Schematic depictions of the locations of qPCR primers are provided in Supplementary Figure S1 (A) Schematic representation of the differentiation procedure and the collection </p>

<p>time points. (B-G) Individual panels depict the relative expression profiles during adipogenesis in three independent differentiation experiments (Differentiation 1-3) for (B) Pparg, Angptl4 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>Cebpa; 
(C) Pank2, Pank3, 
pri-miR-103-1, pri-miR-103-2 and the mature miR-103; (D) Copz1, 
pri-miR-148b and miR-148b; (E) pri-miR-96 and miR-96; (F) pri-miR-205 and miR-205 and (G) </p>

<p>Ppargc1b, 
pri-miR-378 and miR-378. The measured expression values were normalized to Rpl13a 
mRNA (for mRNAs and pri-miRNAs) or U6 small nuclear RNA (snRNA) (for miRNAs) and </p>

<p>are shown relative to D0. The results from three independent differentiation experiments are shown. The statistical significance of the changes for each transcript during the time course of the 
three independent differentiations was tested using ANOVA. All tested mRNAs, all mature miRNAs except miR-148b and pri-miR transcripts for miR-103-1, miR-205 and miR-378 were 
significantly affected during differentiation (P &lt; </p>

<p>0.05; for pri-miR-96 the P-value </p>

<p>was 0.078). </p>



<p>the mature miRNAs remained unaffected throughout the 
experiments and only miRNAs miR-205 and miR-378 
decreased clearly below the DMSO-control levels after 
48 h of DRB treatment (Supplementary Figure S3F and 
G). These results are consistent with previous studies sug-
gesting high stability of mature miRNA transcripts (34,35) 
and readily explain the observed differences in the expres-
sion profiles of the pri-miRNAs and their mature 
counterparts. 
Taken together, five candidate PPARg target miRNAs 
were dynamically upregulated during 3T3-L1 differenti-
ation, most likely due to increased transcription at their 
genomic loci as indicated by the induced levels of the re-
spective pri-miRNA transcripts. With the exception of 
miR-103-2, the expression of all tested genes followed 
that of Pparg, implicating them as possible primary 
PPARg target genes. </p>

<p>PPARc-dependence of the candidate PPARc-target 
miRNAs and their host genes </p>

<p>To test the PPARg-dependence of the candidate PPARg 
target miRNA genes, we performed siRNA silencing of 
PPARg on D6 of 3T3-L1 differentiation (Figure 3A). At 
48 h post-transfection the expression of both PPARg 
variants had strongly decreased on the protein level 
(Supplementary Figure S4) and the Pparg mRNA level 
was reduced below 30% of that in cells transfected with 
an unspecific control siRNA (Figure 3B). The expression 
levels of the two primary PPARg target genes, Cebpa and 
Angptl4, were also decreased, confirming a reduced tran-
scriptional activation by PPARg. 
Comparison of the two miR-103 loci showed that 
pri-miR-103-1 and especially its host gene Pank3 were 
downregulated by PPARg silencing, while pri-miR-103-2 
and its host gene Pank2 were not affected (Figure 3C). 
This also further confirms miR-103-1 as the main source 
of miR-103 upregulation during adipogenesis. However, 
reduction in the levels of mature miR-103 could not be 
detected yet at this point, most likely due to remarkably 
high stability of the mature miRNA (Supplementary 
Figure S3). Consistent with their moderate induction in 
adipogenesis, mature miR-148b and pri-miR-148b 
remained mainly unaffected by PPARg silencing, and 
their host gene Copz1 was only modestly, although signifi-
cantly, downregulated (Figure 3D). Pri-miR-96 was 
decreased to same extent as the mature miR-96 
(Figure 3E). Similarly, both pri-miR-205 and miR-205, 
which were the two most strongly affected miRNA tran-
scripts tested, showed a drastic reduction down to 20-30% 
of their expression level (Figure 3F). Finally, pri-miR-378, 
mature miR-378 and their host gene Ppargc1b were all 
significantly downregulated by PPARg silencing 
(Figure 3G). 
In summary, all candidate PPARg-targeted miRNA 
loci except miR-148b and miR-103-2 depend on PPARg 
for their expression in mouse adipocytes. Moreover, this 
dependence can be attributed to their transcriptional regu-
lation as demonstrated by the reduced levels of the 
respective pri-miRNA transcripts and host genes. </p>

<p>Effects of RGZ on candidate PPARc target miRNAs 
and their host genes </p>

<p>One classical approach to identify primary target genes of 
ligand-dependent nuclear receptors includes short-time 
treatments with agonists. Therefore, we tested treatments 
of differentiating 3T3-L1 cells at D2, D4 and D6 with the 
PPARg agonist RGZ and observed highest upregulation 
of the known primary PPARg target genes Cebpa and 
Angptl4 at D2 (Figure 4A and B and data not shown). 
This is an obvious time point for RGZ treatment, since 
on D2 the levels of PPARg expression have already 
increased but the cells have not yet been exposed to 
RGZ or high levels of endogenous ligands. To test the 
RGZ response of the candidate genes we performed a 
time series of RGZ treatments and collected RNA 4, 8, 
12, 24 and 48 h after the treatment (Figure 4A). In agree-
ment with around 24-h delay in the upregulation of 
mature miRNAs observed during the differentiation 
time course (Figure 2), the mature miR-378 was not 
induced until after 12 h of RGZ treatment and the more 
stable miR-103 became induced only after 48 h 
(Figures 4C-G). In contrast miR-205 was significantly 
induced already 4 h after RGZ treatment, reached 
almost 3-fold induction by 8 h and continued to accumu-
late up to 10-fold by 48 h (Figure 4F). Consistently, also 
pri-miR-205 showed a clear response to the agonist treat-
ment, although with a weaker fold change. Likewise, 
pri-miR-103-1 and pri-miR-378 were both significantly 
induced upon PPARg activation and continued to accu-
mulate throughout the time course (Figure 4C and G), 
while inductions of pri-miR-148b and pri-miR-96 as well 
as their mature counterparts were either very weak or not 
significant (Figure 4D and E). Similarly to the 
pri-miRNAs, the host genes of miR-103-1 and miR-378, 
Pank3 and Pparg1b, were also significantly upregulated 
already after first time points of RGZ treatment, arguing 
that these genes are indeed primary PPARg targets. 
Taken together, from the six candidate PPARg target 
miRNA genes three, namely miR-103-1, miR-205 and 
miR-378, and the two host genes Pank3 and Ppargc1b 
could be confirmed as PPARg targets also by upregulation 
upon treatment with the PPARg ligand RGZ. </p>

<p>Validation of the PPARc association with PPREs on 
the Pank3, Ppargc1b and miR-205 loci </p>

<p>In order to validate direct binding of PPARg to the regu-
latory regions of our newly identified PPARg target genes, 
we performed regular ChIP assays followed by qPCR with 
chromatin extracted from 3T3-L1 cells at D0 and D6 ex-
pressing either low or high levels of PPARg (Figure 5, 
Supplementary Figure S4). In order to confirm that the 
observed enrichments are specific for PPARg, we used two 
different PPARg antibodies in separate immunopreci-
pitations (one used in the previous genome-wide studies 
and another independent antibody from a different 
provider, see 'Materials and Methods' section). For this 
validation we focused our efforts on the three miRNA loci 
that were most responsive to RGZ, namely miR-103-1, 
miR-205 and miR-378. As positive control we used the 
known PPARg target gene Angptl4 and as negative </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 10 4453 </p>

<p>control the Pou5f1 gene, which is not significantly 
expressed in adipocytes (data not shown). Examination 
of the genomic regions ±100 kb from the TSS of 
Angptl4 (Figure 5A), Pou5f1 (Figure 5B), Pank3 </p>

<p>(miR-103-1) (Figure 5C) and Ppargc1b (miR-378) 
(Figure 5D), and ±120 kb from the TSS of miR-205 
(Figure 5E) identified 8, 2, 10, 13 and 5 independent 
PPARg-bound sites on each locus, respectively, when </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B 
C </p>

<p>D 
E </p>

<p>F 
G </p>

<p>Figure 3. Effects of PPARg downregulation in mature mouse 3T3-L1 adipocytes on the candidate miRNAs and their host genes. (A) Schematic 
representation of the experimental procedure for silencing PPARg in differentiated 3T3-L1 adipocytes. Six days differentiated 3T3-L1 cells were 
transfected with siRNA specific for Pparg (siPparg) or with unspecific control siRNA (siControl). Forty-eight hours post-transfection the cells were 
collected and the total RNA was extracted. (B-G) qPCR analysis of the relative expression values in siPparg transfected cells compared with 
siControl transfection for (B) Pparg, Cebpa and Angptl4; (C) Pank2, Pank3, pri-miR-103-1, pri-miR-103-2 and miR-103; (D) Copz1, pri-miR-148b 
and miR-148b; (E) pri-miR-96 and miR-96; (F) pri-miR-205 and miR-205 and (G) Ppargc1b, pri-miR-378 and miR-378. The measured expression 
values were normalized to Rpl13a mRNA (for mRNAs and pri-miRNAs) or U6 snRNA (for miRNAs) and are shown relative to siControl, value of 
which was set to 1 (indicated by dashed line). Data points indicate the mean expression values of four independent experiments and the error bars 
represent SEM. One sample t-test was performed to determine the significance of downregulation upon siPparg transfection (*P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; 
for Cebpa, Pank3, pri-miR-96, miR-96 and miR-205 the P-values of downregulation were 0.096, 0.078, 0.097, 0.139 and 0.052, respectively). </p>

<p>4454 Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 10 </p>

<p>looking at all four genome-wide datasets. To identify the 
PPARg-bound sites that could correspond to direct DNA 
binding of PPARg to a PPRE, we aligned the ChIP-
identified binding sites with PPREs predicted by the </p>

<p>REsearch algorithm (10). Predictions by REsearch are 
based on PPARg binding in gel shift analysis and, in 
addition to the PPRE location, provide information 
about the strength of the PPARg-PPRE interaction </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B 
C </p>

<p>D 
E </p>

<p>F 
G </p>

<p>Figure 4. Effects of RGZ treatment of 2 days differentiated 3T3-L1 cells on the candidate miRNAs and their host genes. (A) Experimental pro-
cedure for RGZ treatment of 2 days differentiated 3T3-L1 cells. (B-G) qPCR analysis of the relative expression values in RGZ-treated cells 
compared with DMSO-treated controls for (B) Pparg, Cebpa and Angptl4; (C) Pank2, Pank3, pri-miR-103-1, pri-miR-103-2 and miR-103; 
(D) Copz1, pri-miR-148b and miR-148b; (E) pri-miR-96 and miR-96; (F) pri-miR-205 and miR-205 and (G) Ppargc1b, pri-miR-378 and 
miR-378. The measured expression values were normalized to Rpl13a mRNA (for mRNAs and pri-miRNAs) or U6 snRNA (for miRNAs) and 
are shown relative to DMSO treatment, value of which was set to 1 (indicated by dashed line). Data points indicate the mean expression values of at 
least three independent experiments and the error bars represent SEM. One sample t-test was performed to determine the significance of upregulation 
upon RGZ treatment (*P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; ***P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 10 4455 </p>

<p>in vitro. This filtering approach reduced the number of 
genomic regions to two for Angptl4, none for Pou5f1, 
three for Pank3 and five for both Ppargc1b and 
miR-205. For the Angptl4 gene we selected RE1 Angptl4 con-
taining three predicted PPREs, one of which is a known 
functional PPRE in adipocytes (28). For the Pou5f1 gene 
we used its TSS region (TSS Pou5f1 ). The three PPREs, 
RE1 Pank3 , RE2 Pank3 and RE3 Pank3 , are located $19, 31 
and 37 kb upstream from the Pank3 TSS, respectively. 
RE3 Pank3 in fact contains two separate PPREs located 
within 200 bp from each other. All three REs contain 
PPREs with good in vitro binding strength for PPARg. 
From the five PPARg-bound sites of the Ppargc1b locus 
four contain at least two adjacent PPREs each. Two of 
them, RE1 Ppargc1b and RE2 Ppargc1b , located $38 and 90 kb 
upstream from Ppargc1b TSS, were selected for </p>

<p>validation. RE2 Ppargc1b contains two strong PPREs and 
one weak PPRE while RE1 Ppargc1b has only two 
weak PPREs. Finally, from the five PPARg-bound sites 
at miR-205 locus we chose two, RE1 miR-205 and 
RE2 miR-205 , to be validated. The sites are located at 37 
and 118 kb upstream from the miR-205 TSS with one 
PPRE in each. The sequences and the exact locations of 
the PPREs are provided in Supplementary Table S5. 
In ChIP assays PPARg showed low association with 
RE1 Angptl4 in pre-adipocytes (D0) but in differentiated adi-
pocytes (D6) a significant increase in enrichment to 
$15-fold over IgG could be observed at this genomic 
region with both PPARg antibodies (Figure 5A), reflecting 
the specific binding by PPARg during differentiation. The 
enrichment of the control TSS Pou5f1 remained at the back-
ground level in both conditions (Figure 5B). Importantly, </p>

<p>A 
B 
C 
D 
E </p>

<p>Figure 5. Identification of active PPREs responsible for direct PPARg-DNA interaction and validation of the PPARg binding at the PPREs on the 
Pank3, Ppargc1b and miR-205 loci by ChIP analysis. (A-E, top panel) Levels of H3K27 acetylation determined by ChIP-Seq (7) at D0, D2 and D7 
of 3T3-L1 differentiation and (A-E, middle panel) PPARg-binding sites determined by ChIP-chip (3), ChIP-Seq (4,6) and ChIP-PET (5) ±100 kb 
around the TSS of (A) the Angptl4 positive control locus, (B) the Pou5f1 negative control locus, (C) Pank3 (miR-103-1), (D) Ppargc1b (miR-378) and 
(E) ±120 kb around the TSS of miR-205. In silico predicted PPREs overlapping with the ChIP binding sites are marked in red. The PPREs selected 
for validation are highlighted and the primers used to amplify regions overlapping these PPREs are indicated as arrows. (A-E, lower panel) ChIP 
analysis using two different PPARg antibodies from independent providers [a-PPARg (Cayman) or a-PPARg (Santa-Cruz)] and IgG as a control. 
qPCR was performed with DNA immunoprecipitated from pre-adipocytes (D0) or adipocytes (D6) and using primers specific for (A) a known PPRE 
on the Angptl4 locus, (B) an unrelated control region on the Pou5f1 locus, (C) three putative PPREs (RE1 Pank3 , RE2 Pank3 and RE3 Pank3 ) on the 
Pank3 locus, (D) two clusters of putative PPREs (RE1 Ppargc1b and RE2 Ppargc1b ) on the Ppargc1b locus and two putative PPREs (RE1 miR205 and RE2 </p>

<p>miR205 ) on the miR-205 locus. The measured enrichment values were normalized to 1:100 diluted input DNA. The enrichment of PPARg is shown 
relative to the enrichment of IgG (indicated by dashed line). Data points indicate the mean enrichment values of at least three independent 
experiments and the error bars represent SEM. One sample t-test was performed to determine the significance of PPARg enrichment at D6 
compared with D0 (*P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; ***P &lt; 0.001). </p>



<p>the enrichments of the three REs at the Pank3 locus 
(Figure 5C), the two tested REs at the Ppargc1b locus 
(Figure 5D) as well as RE2 miR-205 (Figure 5E) all exhibited 
strong and mostly significant increases in their enrich-
ments between pre-adipocytes and adipocytes. Finally, 
all enrichments were consistent between the two 
antibodies, arguing that we are monitoring specific 
binding of PPARg at these regions. 
Since the interaction of PPARg with the selected REs 
could be validated by regular ChIP assays, we were inter-
ested to see whether these regions could indeed be active 
enhancers contributing to regulation of expression of the 
confirmed target genes. To address this possibility, we 
took advantage of the recent identification of acetylation 
of lysine 27 of histone H3 (H3K27ac) as a histone modi-
fication specifically marking active enhancer regions 
(36,37). Analysis of the published ChIP-Seq data from 
Mikkelsen et al. (7) for the level of H3K27ac at our loci 
of interest during 3T3-L1 differentiation confirmed 
that all of our tested REs, except RE3 Pank3 , are 
accumulating H3K27 acetylation during adipogenesis 
(Figure 5, top panel). These data argue that the identified 
PPREs can serve as specific binding sites for PPARg 
during adipogenesis and contribute as active enhancers 
to the regulation of the identified primary PPARg target 
miRNA genes. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This study was performed with the aim to identify miRNA 
genes that are primary nuclear receptor targets. Since 
miRNA genes often serve as critical developmental 
switches and are regulated in differentiation processes 
(23), we have chosen adipogenesis as an experimental 
system, where a dominant role is played by the nuclear 
receptor PPARg (2). We selected the mouse 3T3-L1 cells 
as a cellular model, for which far more public data are 
available than for any comparable human system (3-6,26). 
Our approach for the identification of miRNA genes that 
are primary PPARg targets was to integrate genome-wide 
data about PPARg binding with recent information on 
TSS locations of miRNA genes. 
Although the genome-wide PPARg location data were 
obtained with the same cellular model and the same 
antibody, we realized that only the minority of the 
PPARg-bound sites are confirmed in at least three of the 
four datasets. The integration of the four datasets sug-
gested that for 140 miRNAs a PPARg-bound site is 
located within 50-kb distance from their TSS in at least 
one of the datasets. Since PPARg is significantly 
upregulated during adipogenesis, a filtering of the 140 
miRNAs for those that are more than 2-fold upregulated 
during 3T3-L1 differentiation, reduced the number to 19 
miRNAs encoded by 22 miRNA genes that form the list 
of putative PPARg targets. However, the condition that 
PPARg binding at the genomic region had to be confirmed 
in at least three of the four datasets, reduced the list to six 
miRNA genes miR-103-1, miR-103-2, miR-148b, 
miR-183/96/182, miR-205 and miR-378. Both a detailed 
time course analysis of the upregulation of these miRNAs </p>

<p>as well as PPARg silencing in differentiated adipocytes 
excluded only miR-103-2 and miR-148b from this list of 
putative primary PPARg target genes. Still, PPARg might 
influence also the transcription of miR-103-2 and 
miR-148b loci, although not as potently as for the other 
tested loci, or for example in a different cellular context. 
Importantly, the genes encoding miR-103-1, miR-205 and 
miR-378 could be confirmed as classical PPARg targets 
also by RGZ treatments. Interestingly, the host genes of 
these miRNAs, Pank3 and Ppargc1b, are also primary 
PPARg target genes, which have not yet been reported 
as such. For Pank3 (miR-103-1) we validated three 
genomic PPARg binding sites that overlap with in silico 
predicted PPREs 19, 31 and 37 kb upstream from the 
Pank3 TSS, for the Ppargc1b (miR-378) locus two 
PPARg locations with adjacent PPREs 90 and 38kb 
upstream of the TSS, and for the miR-205 locus one 
PPARg binding site with PPRE at 118-kb upstream of 
the TSS. The future work to identify the exact PPRE 
sequences responsible for target gene regulation, especially 
for REs containing multiple PPREs, will require detailed 
experiments applying reporter gene assays or optimally 
zinc-finger nuclease-mediated targeting of individual en-
dogenous PPREs. However, by applying the genome-wide 
mapping of H3K27ac, a histone modification specifically 
marking the active enhancer regions, we have already 
shown that most of the validated PPARg-bound sites 
are accumulating increased levels of H3K27ac, suggesting 
that these enhancers are actively contributing to the regu-
lation of the identified target genes. 
Since Lefterova et al. (3) have shown PPARg to 
co-localize with the transcription factor CEBPa in 
differentiated 3T3-L1 cells, we took advantage of this 
dataset and compared CEBPa-bound sites with the 
PPARg-bound sites at miRNA loci. In most of them (29 
of the 52) CEBPa was found in &lt;1 kb distance from the 
respective PPARg-bound sites (data not shown). 
Moreover, all of the six candidate miRNA loci except 
miR-205 had their regulatory regions co-occupied by 
PPARg and CEBPa, suggesting that the two transcription 
factors might induce different miRNA genes in a com-
binatorial manner, similarly to protein coding genes 
(data not shown) (3). 
Although most of our candidate miRNA genes depend 
on PPARg for their expression in adipocytes, we found 
that the dynamics of their expression changes, and those 
of their host genes, varied during adipogenesis. This is 
perhaps most evident for miR-103, which exhibits a 
delay in its upregulation when compared with the host 
gene Pank3. While this observation might be mainly 
explained by different processing of the two mature tran-
scripts, the usage of alternative TSSs or differential stabil-
ity of the two mature transcripts could also play a role. 
Histone H3 lysine 4 trimethylation (H3K4me3) is an epi-
genetic modification known to mark active TSSs. Based 
on genome-wide mapping of H3K4me3 in mouse 3T3-L1 
cells, only one TSS exists at the Pank3 locus during 
adipogenesis (7). This argues that the differences 
observed in the expression dynamics are more likely to 
be explained by the dissimilar stabilities of the mature 
transcripts, rather than alternative TSS usage. Indeed, </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 10 4457 </p>

<p>consistently with our observations (Supplementary 
Figure S3), miRNAs were recently estimated to possess 
an average half-life of almost 5 days (35). This is 12 
times longer than the median half-life of mRNAs, which 
is 10 h (38). When a mature transcript exhibits a low turn-
over, it accumulates higher basal expression levels, even 
upon low levels of basal transcription. Consequently, 
upon increased expression such transcript can exhibit rela-
tively low fold inductions with slower accumulation rate 
although the extent of transcriptional output is compar-
able with that of a lower stability transcript. Therefore, it 
is likely that the different dynamics of miR-103 (and other 
miRNAs) are explained by its higher stability compared 
with the mature Pank3 mRNA (Supplementary 
Figure S3). Consistently, we found that 48 h knock-down 
of PPARg had no significant effects on mature miR-103 
and its response to treatments with RGZ occurred only 
after 48 h, while the host gene Pank3 clearly responded 
already after 4 h. 
Transcriptional regulation by PPARg is both necessary 
and sufficient for adipogenesis and therefore its primary 
target genes, including the miRNA genes described here, 
might play a critical role or at least contribute to success-
ful adipogenesis. Indeed, miR-103 has already been 
described as highly induced in primary mouse adipocytes 
and as capable of accelerating adipogenesis (26). miR-103 
belongs to a family of three miRNAs, miR-103-1, 
miR-103-2 and miR-107, that have almost identical 
sequences and are transcribed together with their host 
genes Pank3, Pank2 and Pank1, respectively (22,29). 
Interestingly, in addition to the two miR-103 loci also 
miR-107 was identified as a putative PPARg target gene 
in our initial analysis (Figure 1A) and its host gene Pank1 
has been described as a primary PPARa target in human 
liver (39). Importantly, recent data from Trajkovski et al. 
(40) demonstrated that silencing of miR-103 and miR-107 
in the adipose tissue of mice leads to reduced fat levels, 
but in contradiction to previous in vitro data, not via in-
hibition of adipogenesis. Instead, lowered levels of 
the miRNAs increased the insulin sensitivity of the adipo-
cytes, a phenomenon linked to increased number of 
smaller sized adipocytes. Therefore, our data, together 
with abovementioned findings, create direct links 
between PPARs, miR-103/107 family miRNAs and 
insulin sensitivity. 
Unlike miR-103, the miR-183/96/182 cluster has 
not been functionally connected to adipogenesis so far. 
However, based on the very robust induction that we 
observed during 3T3-L1 adipogenesis, the members of 
this cluster are likely to contribute to the biology of 
mature adipocytes. Treatment with insulin alone was 
recently shown to downregulate miR-183 levels in 
3T3-L1 adipocytes (41). However, during adipogenesis 
the cluster becomes upregulated in a PPARg-dependent 
manner, despite the presence of insulin in the differenti-
ation medium. Therefore, it is probable that the expres-
sion of the miR-183/96/182 cluster is under combinatorial 
regulation of several transcription factors and pathways 
that together lead to the clusters increased expression in 
adipocytes. </p>

<p>By far the highest induced miRNA tested in our 
analysis was miR-205. The exact significance of this induc-
tion for adipogenesis remains unclear for now. However, 
the list of predicted target mRNAs for miR-205 includes, 
for example, Runx2 (<rs id="software-3" type="software">TargetScan</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">5.2</rs>), a transcript 
encoding a transcription factor with an important role in 
favoring osteoblastogenesis over adipogenesis during mes-
enchymal stem cell differentiation (42). High levels of 
PPARg are known to suppress RUNX2 protein expres-
sion and induction of miR-205 might serve as a mechan-
ism to achieve this suppression. Indeed, Zhang et al. (43) 
recently showed that miR-205 can attenuate RUNX2 
protein accumulation together with nine other miRNAs 
in mouse osteoblasts. However, our preliminary experi-
ments have so far failed to demonstrate reduction in 
Runx2 mRNA levels upon miR-205 overexpression in 
pre-adipocytes (data not shown), suggesting that a com-
binatorial function of multiple miRNAs might be required 
for robust regulation of Runx2 at the mRNA level. 
Consistently, we were so far unable to demonstrate any 
significant impact of miR-205 overexpression on early 
adipogenesis in general, as measured by the expression 
levels of the known adipocyte marker genes such 
as Pparg and Cebpa (data not shown). Proteome-
or transcriptome-wide analysis upon gain-or loss-of-
function of miR-205 would be needed to reveal the 
primary targets mRNAs and pathways regulated by the 
robust induction of miR-205 during adipogenesis. 
Interestingly, we also found miR-378 and its host gene 
Ppargc1b as primary PPARg targets in adipocytes. 
miR-378 can induce lipogenesis and expression of lipogen-
ic genes, when overexpressed during adipogenesis of ST2 
mesenchymal precursors (44). Moreover, Ppargc1b is a 
known transcriptional co-activator responsible for 
inducing the target genes of numerous transcription 
factors (for example, sterol response element binding 
proteins, liver X receptors and PPARs) that are involved 
in regulation of lipogenesis and related processes (31). 
This suggests that PPARg may induce both miR-378 
and Ppargc1b, in order to allow both to function syner-
gistically in the regulation of lipid metabolism. Impor-
tantly, this induction is not limited to mouse 3T3-L1 
cells as miR-378 was recently identified as the most 
highly upregulated miRNA during the differentiation of 
both mouse and human primary adipocytes (26,45). 
In addition to miRNAs discussed above, a more 
detailed analysis of our initial list of putative PPARg 
target miRNA genes will lead to a more complete list of 
the true PPARg target miRNAs. Revealing the role of 
these miRNAs in adipogenesis and identification of 
their primary target mRNAs will be important for their 
integration to the regulatory networks governing 
adipogenesis. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online: 
Supplementary Tables S1-S5 and Supplementary Figures 
S1-S4. </p>

<p>4458 Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 10 </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>University of Luxembourg, National Research Fund 
(FNR, Luxembourg), Televie (FNRS, Belgium, to C.C.); 
fellowships from the National Research Fund (FNR, Lux-
embourg to E.J. and M.L.). Funding for open access 
charge: University of Luxembourg. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>4460 Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 10 </p>

</text></tei>