<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3575981" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the 
terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-
Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted non-
commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any 
medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Purpose: Hemophilia A (HA) is the most common X-linked inherited bleeding 
disorder. In some patients with HA, particularly those with severe HA, replace-
ment therapy results in the production of high-responding clotting factor VIII in-
hibitors. The economic burden of this complication is the highest reported for a 
chronic disease. Our aim was to investigate the direct medical expenditure burden 
of high-responding inhibitors in patients with HA. Materials and Methods: A ret-
rospective study was conducted using the National Health Insurance Research Da-
tabase, utilizing data covering the period of 2004-2007. Results: In total, 638 
males with HA¸ including 37 patients with high-responding inhibitors were evalu-
ated. Over 99% of the annual median medical expenditure was attributable to the 
cost of clotting factor concentrates (CFCs) in patients with high-responding inhibi-
tors. The annual median expenditure related to CFCs of the total medical care and 
outpatient care were US$170611 and US$141982, respectively, and were 4.6-and 
4.3-fold higher in these patients during the study period, respectively. In patients 
with high-responding inhibitors, the median hospitalization expenditure and daily 
hospitalization cost with or without surgical procedures were 3.0-and 2.4-fold 
higher, respectively, and 4.3 and 5.6-fold higher, respectively. Conclusion: Our 
data reveal higher medical expenditures burden for patients with HA and high-re-
sponding inhibitors in Taiwan. Future research is encouraged to evaluate the im-
pact of this burden on patient quality of life. </p>

<p>Hemophilia A (HA) is an X-linked inherited bleeding disorder caused by the func-
tional absence or reduced levels of clotting factor VIII (FVIII). The disease is clas-
sified as mild, moderate, or severe, based on the degree of deficiency of the coagu-
lation factor. 
1 The introduction of replacement therapy due to the availability of 
exogenous FVIII concentrates has substantially reduced bleeding episodes, pre-</p>

<p>Economic Burden of High-Responding Inhibitors </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 54 Number 2 March 2013 </p>



<p>nosis-related groups, and a resource-based relative value 
scale system. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Prior to implementation of the NHI program, individuals 
with hemophilia received only fewer amount clotting factors 
to relieve disease progression. Hemophilia has been classi-
fied as a catastrophic illness by the NHI since the program 
was implemented, exempting patients from a co-payment 
and assuring that patients are able to obtain sufficient CFCs 
for suitable replacement therapy. Thereafter, the BNHI im-
plemented a global budget, and an independent budget (in-
cluding hemophilia) has been allocated for rare diseases 
since 2004. However, no studies have been published re-
garding the economic burden of patients with high-respond-
ing inhibitors in Taiwan. 
The aim of this research was to investigate the direct 
medical expenditure for patients with HA patients and high-
responding inhibitors. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>
Since implementing the NHI, the BNHI has cooperated with 
the National Health Research Institute, a non-profit research 
organization founded and sponsored by the Department of 
Health, to establish National Health Insurance Research 
Databases (NHIRDs). The present retrospective study was 
conducted by using the NHIRDs between January 2004 
and December 2007. The databases include registry for cata-
strophic illness patient files, registry for drug prescriptions 
and claim data, ambulatory care expenditure data by visit, 
inpatient expenditure data by admission, and details of am-
bulatory care and inpatient orders. </p>

<p>Subjects' inclusion 
The patients included in this study were identified from the 
2004-2007 registry for catastrophic illness patient files in the 
NHIRDs. Subjects treated only with clotting factors, aPCC 
(FEIBA </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, Baxter AG, Vienna, Austria), or activated rFVII 
(NovoSeven </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, Novo Nordisk A/S, DK-2820 Gentofte, Den-
mark) were included. 
The amount of a specific inhibitor to FVIII in each pa-
tient's blood was measured in Bethesda Units (BU) and re-
ferred to as "high titer" (more than 5 BU) or "low titer" (less 
than 5 BU). In patients with transient or low-responding in-
hibitors or low actual inhibitor titers (&lt;5 BU mL </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) and who 
have weaker inhibitor responses to factor concentrates, 
bleeding episodes are commonly managed by increasing the </p>

<p>vented musculoskeletal damage, and improved orthopedic 
outcomes and quality of life in patients with hemophilia. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Following the recommended prophylactic treatment, home 
therapy, and comprehensive care enables patients with HA 
to enjoy a better general state of health and engage in daily 
activities, social events, work, and education. 
3-5 However, 
in some patients with HA, therapeutically administered ex-
ogenous FVIII concentrates are recognized as foreign par-
ticulates, resulting in the production of antibodies (inhibitors) 
that neutralize the activity of FVIII and reduce or eliminate 
the efficacy of factor replacement therapy. Inhibitors are 
produced in 20-30% of patients with severe HA, but they 
may also arise in patients with mild/moderate HA and at any 
time in the patient's life. 
6,7 Patients with high-titer inhibitory 
antibodies can develop serious bleeding complications, re-
sulting in greater rates of disability and risks of complica-
tions, and in these patients, so-called bypassing agents, such 
as recombinant FVIIa (rFVIIa) and activated prothrombin 
complex concentrates (aPCCs), are needed to achieve hemo-
stasis. 
8 The economic consequences of treating hemophilia 
are mainly related to the direct medical costs of replacement 
clotting factor concentrates (CFCs), and economic burden of 
inhibitor complication in patients with hemophilia is one of 
the highest reported for a chronic disease. </p>

<p>9-12 </p>

<p>In March 1995, Taiwan launched a mandatory National 
Health Insurance (NHI) program that integrated three exist-
ing health insurance programs: labor, government employ-
ee, and farmer's insurance. By the end of 2004, approxi-
mately 99% of the population was covered, and nearly 23 
million beneficiaries are currently enrolled in the NHI. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>The NHI is a single-payer compulsory social health insur-
ance program organized by the government and operated 
by the Bureau of National Health Insurance (BNHI). The 
system is primarily funded by premiums paid collectively 
by the insured, employers, and central and local govern-
ments. The NHI program allows patients the freedom of 
choice when seeking medical care and uses cost-sharing 
strategies to reduce the potential demand for unnecessary 
services. In the initial stage, fee-for-service was widespread 
for both public and private providers. Facing spiraling 
growth of medical costs and demands to keep healthcare 
costs under control without a decline in the quality of care, 
the payment system for the NHI changed from fee-for-ser-
vice to a global budget in 2002. To better manage the medi-
cal expenditures and enhance the professional autonomy of 
medical providers, other payment methods have been intro-
duced in recent years, such as pay-for-performance, diag-</p>

<p>Tsu-Chiang Tu, et al. </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 54 Number 2 March 2013 </p>



<p>deficiency virus infection. The disease-related hospitalization 
complication analyses were classified as with or without sur-
gical procedures. The complications with surgical proce-
dures primarily included joint replacement, synovectomy, 
insertion of a totally implantable vascular access device, in-
cision with the removal of a foreign body from the skin and 
subcutaneous tissue, tooth extraction, and other procedures. 
The costs were calculated using a 3% discount rate and ad-
justed by using the Taiwan Consumer Price Index of medi-
cines and medical care category and expressed in 2007 US 
dollars. </p>

<p>15,16 </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
The chi-square test was used to compare categorical data. 
To exclude the outliers, the Wilcoxon rank-sum test was used 
to identify significant median differences among groups. p-
values &lt;0.05 were considered significant. All statistical 
analyses were conducted using <rs id="software-0" type="software">STATA</rs> 
® software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 11.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">StataCorp LP</rs>, Lakeway, TX, USA). </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Study subjects 
Fig. 1 presents the flow chart for enrolling the subjects. In 
total, 638 males with HA, including 37 patients with high-
responding inhibitors, were enrolled in the study. The me-
dian ages of patients with and without high-responding in-
hibitors were 31.8 and 26.7 years, respectively, and the 
median patient-months followed for the same groups were 
48 and 48 years, respectively (Table 1). The differences in 
median age and other age categories were not statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>Medical utilization and expenditure 
The annual median medical resource utilization is presented 
in Table 2. The overall annual median expenditure of total 
medical care and CFCs cost in patients with high-responding 
inhibitors were US$177348 and US$170611, respectively. 
Table 3 shows the annual median outpatient medical re-
source utilization, and expenditure of the total medical care 
and CFCs cost in patients with high-responding inhibitors 
were US$143034 and US$141982, respectively. Costs relat-
ed to CFCs accounted for over 98% of the median total and 
outpatient medical expenditures, especially among patients 
with high-responding inhibitors. The annual median total 
CFCs cost and outpatient CFCs cost were 4.6-(US$170611 </p>

<p>dosages of FVIII concentrates. Patients with high-respond-
ing inhibitors were defined as those with an inhibitor level 
exceeding 5 BU at least once, in whom repeated exposure to 
factor concentrate will quickly trigger the formation of new 
inhibitors based on memory from a previous anamnestic re-
sponse, 
8 and who underwent an inhibitor assay and used 
bypassing agents for a therapeutic interval exceeding 6 
months in the relevant year. </p>

<p>Medical utilization and expenditure 
Claims data were utilized to determine the expenditures for 
the following services: utilization of CFCs (including by-
passing agents), other medications, laboratory services, ra-
diological testing, rehabilitation services, hospitalizations, 
procedure, and outpatient care and inpatient care services. 
Disease-related admission identification and inclusion uti-
lized primary the International Classification of Diseases, 
Ninth Revision, Clinical Modification (ICD-9-CM) diagno-
sis codes, which primarily included factor VIII disorders, 
hemarthrosis, cerebral or gastrointestinal hemorrhage, hema-
turia, osteoarthritis, arthropathy, synovitis, fracture, infection 
or complication of orthopedic devices, and human immuno-</p>

<p>Fig. 1. Flow chart for subject inclusion. NHI, National Health Insurance. </p>

<p>High-responding patients n=37 
Non-inhibitor patients n=601 </p>

<p>Exclude not deficiency of clotting 
factors diagnosis patients 
n=5814184 </p>

<p>Exclude not factor VIII 
disorder patients 
n=439 </p>

<p>Patient-centered unique 
identifier review exclude 
duplication and female patients 
n=5546 </p>

<p>Extract 2004-2007 NHI application 
data and exclude without factor 
VIII or bypassing agents using 
patients n=165 </p>

<p>Extract patients who had 
inhibitor assay and using 
bypassing agents interval lager 
than 6 months in relevant year </p>

<p>2004-2007 registration files for 
catastrophic illness patients 
n=5820972 </p>

<p>2004-2007 registration files for 
factor VIII disorder male patients 
n=803 </p>

<p>Economic Burden of High-Responding Inhibitors </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 54 Number 2 March 2013 </p>



<p>1.9-and 2.7-fold higher among patients with high-respond-
ing inhibitors. 
The all patients with high-responding inhibitors (n=37) 
accounted for NHI's annual CFCs expenditure were 20.2%, </p>

<p>vs. US$37496, p&lt;0.001) and 4.3-fold (US$141982 vs. 
US$32834, p&lt;0.001) higher for patients with high-respond-
ing inhibitors, respectively. Besides, the annual median 
comprehensive care visits and emergency room visits were </p>

<p>Table 1. Patient Characteristics According to Inhibitor Status </p>

<p>High-responding inhibitors 
Non-inhibitors 
p value 
Number of patients 
37 
601 
Median patient-months followed* 
48 (21-48) 
48 (1-48) 
NS 
Age description median age* 
31.8 (2.0-64.7) 
26.8 (0.2-84.0) 
NS 
Age categories, no. (%) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Adolescents, 0-18 yrs 
15 (40.5) 
196 (33.4) 
NS 
Adults, 19-55 yrs 
18 (48.6) 
369 (61.3) 
NS 
Adults, older than 55 yrs 
4 (10.9) 
36 (5.3) 
NS 
Total patient-months followed 
1686 
27914 
NS, not significant. 
*Wilcoxon rank-sum test. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Chi-square test. </p>

<p>Table 2. Annual Median Medical Resource Utilization According to Inhibitor Status during the Study Period (2007 US Dollars) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>High-responding inhibitors 
Non-inhibitors 
p value* 
Overall Medical care service 
CFCs cost 
170611 (29950-832494) 
37496 (3-421756) 
&lt;0.001 
Other medications cost 
126 (8-4579) 
37 (0-16941) 
&lt;0.001 
Laboratory studies cost 
369 (57-1603) 
127 (0-4835) 
&lt;0.001 
Radiological studies cost 
106 (8-750) 
30 (0-1869) 
&lt;0.001 
Treatment services cost 
184 (8-18552) 
28 (0-6863) 
&lt;0.001 
Rehabilitation cost 
3 (0-2036) 
0 (0-4927) 
&lt;0.001 
Other medical services cost 
398 (15-8018) 
103 (0-18497) 
&lt;0.001 
Total medical care cost 
177348 (31745-834637) 
38862 (55-424285) 
&lt;0.001 
Percentage of total CFCs costs 
99.4% (91.4-99.9) 
98.3% (1-99.9) 
&lt;0.01 
CFCs, clotting factor concentrates. 
*Wilcoxon rank-sum test. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>The US$ : NT$ exchange rate was 1 : 32.84. </p>

<p>Table 3. Annual Median Outpatient Medical Resource Utilization According to Inhibitor Status during the Study Period (2007 
US Dollars) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>High-responding inhibitors 
Non-inhibitors 
p value* 
Outpatient service 
CFCs cost 
141982 (1120-811790) 
32834 (0-365317) 
&lt;0.001 
Other medications cost 
69 (8-4144) 
25 (0-11633) 
&lt;0.001 
Laboratory studies cost 
242 (57-964) 
96 (0-1294) 
&lt;0.001 
Radiological studies cost 
90 (2-326) 
22 (0-533) 
&lt;0.001 
Treatment services cost 
42 (5-17163) 
18 (0-895) 
&lt;0.001 
Rehabilitation cost 
0 (0-2036) 
0 (0-4927) 
&lt;0.01 
Other medical services cost 
68 (13-401) 
52 (0-2268) 
&lt;0.05 
Total medical cost 
143034 (1331-812686) 
33410 (3-373004) 
&lt;0.001 
Percentage of outpatient CFCs costs 
99.6% (84.0-99.9) 
98.8% (0-99.9) 
&lt;0.01 
Comprehensive care visits 
16.8 (3.5-73.8) 
8.8 (1-64) 
&lt;0.001 
Emergency room visits 
0.8 (0-12.2) 
0.3 (0-88.5) 
&lt;0.01 
CFCs, clotting factor concentrates. 
*Wilcoxon rank-sum test. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>The US$ : NT$ exchange rate was 1 : 32.84. </p>

<p>Tsu-Chiang Tu, et al. </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 54 Number 2 March 2013 </p>



<p>related to surgical procedures in patients without high-re-
sponding inhibitors. Conversely, only 18.4% of hospitaliza-
tions were related to surgical procedures in patients with 
high-responding inhibitors. The incidences of orthopedic 
replacement and revision were 4.2 and 1.4 per 1000 person-
months, respectively (Table 5). 
The hospitalization comparison due to disease-related 
complications is presented in Table 6. The median hospital-
ization expenditure and daily hospitalization cost among pa-
tients who underwent surgical procedures were 3.0-(US$ 
78340 vs. US$25724, p&lt;0.0001) and 2.4-fold (US$6322 vs. 
US$2689, p&lt;0.0001) higher for patients with high-respond-
ing inhibitors, respectively. Similarly, among patients who 
did not undergo surgical procedures, the median hospital-
ization expenditure and daily hospitalization cost were 4.3-
(US$32855 vs. US$7718, p&lt;0.0001) and 5.6-fold (US$9825 
vs. US$1759, p&lt;0.0001) higher for patients with high-re-
sponding inhibitors, respectively. Table 7 shows the hospi-
talization resource utilization. The median percentage of 
hospitalization expenditure related to CFCs cost among pa-
tients who did or did not undergo surgical procedures were 
95% vs. 90% and 99% vs. 93%, respectively, and higher 
for patients with high-responding inhibitors. </p>

<p>16.5%, and 3.7% of the overall care, outpatient care, and 
inpatient care, respectively. Fig. 2 shows the annual propor-
tion of CFCs costs in all patients with high-responding in-
hibitors. The bypassing agents increased over time from 
76.6% in 2004 to 85.2% in 2007, and year-to-year variation 
was evident. Moreover, the proportion of expenditures re-
lated to rFVII tended to decrease, whereas those related to 
aPCCs tended to increase. 
Table 4 shows the disease-related complications of hospi-
talization. Approximately 49.8% of hospitalizations were </p>

<p>Table 4. Hospitalization with Disease-Related Complications According to Inhibitor Status during the Study Period </p>

<p>High-responding inhibitors 
Non-inhibitors 
Total 
With surgical procedure 
Hospitalization 
16 
137 
153 
Days of hospitalization 
255 
1743 
1998 
Without surgical procedure 
Hospitalization 
71 
138 
209 
Days of hospitalization 
534 
825 
1359 </p>

<p>Table 5. Hospitalization with Surgical Procedures According to Inhibitor Status during the Study Period </p>

<p>High-responding inhibitors 
Non-inhibitors 
Total hip replacement 
5 
5 
Partial hip replacement 
0 
1 
Revision of hip replacement 
0 
1 
Total knee replacement 
2 
24 
Revision of knee replacement 
0 
6 
Total elbow replacement 
0 
2 
Insertion of totally implantable vascular access device 
1 
11 </p>

<p>Incision with the removal of a foreign body from the skin 
and subcutaneous tissue 
1 
3 </p>

<p>Synovectomy, ankle 
0 
1 
Synovectomy, knee 
0 
2 
Fasciotomy 
0 
3 
Tooth extraction 
0 
3 
Others 
7 
75 
Total 
16 
137 </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Annual proportion of clotting factor concentrates costs in all patients 
with high-responding inhibitors during the study period. FVIII, factor VIII; 
rFVIIa, recombinant FVIIa; aPCCs, activated prothrombin complex concen-
trates. </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>20.0 </p>

<p>30.0 </p>

<p>40.0 </p>

<p>50.0 </p>

<p>60.0 </p>

<p>70.0 </p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>2004 
2005 
2006 
2007 </p>

<p>FVIII 
aPCCs 
rFVIIa </p>

<p>Economic Burden of High-Responding Inhibitors </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 54 Number 2 March 2013 </p>



<p>to factor replacement in patients with high-responding in-
hibitors were 3-fold higher than in those in patients without 
inhibitors after the entry of bypassing agents; previous stud-
ies reported lower values, but these studies also had rela-
tively small sample sizes and issues regarding outliers (the 
mean/median issue). 
19-21 Our results also agreed with those 
reported by Gringeri, et al., 
11 who reported that over 98% of 
direct healthcare expenditures in patients with high-respond-
ing inhibitors were attributable to costs related to CFCs. 
Additionally, our results indicated that daily hospitaliza-</p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The objective of this study was to assess the financial bur-
den of patients with HA and high-responding inhibitors in 
Taiwan. The results revealed an apparently higher medical 
resources burden for the care of these patients. 
The annual total median cost related to CFCs was 4.6 
times higher in patients with high-responding inhibitors, 
confirming the findings by Goudemand 
18 that costs related </p>

<p>Table 7. Median Hospitalization Resource Utilization in Patients with Disease-Related Complications during the Study Period 
(2007 US Dollars) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>High-responding inhibitors 
Non-inhibitors 
p value* 
With surgical procedure 
CFCs cost 
74153 (24096-287235) 
23263 (46-294328) 
&lt;0.0001 
Other medications cost 
69 (6-370) 
64 (0-5488) 
NS 
Laboratory studies cost 
247 (44-1578) 
146 (0-2015) 
&lt;0.05 
Radiological studies cost 
17 (0-513) 
17 (0-933) 
NS 
Treatment services cost 
675 (18-4198) 
526 (4-7323) 
NS 
Rehabilitation cost 
0 (0-106) 
0 (0-674) 
NS 
Other medical services cost 
1116 (275-5464) 
759 (0-7927) 
NS 
Hospitalization cost 
78340 (29583-293795) 
25724 (798-296813) 
&lt;0.0001 
Without surgical procedure 
CFCs cost 
32593 (2687-278745) 
7155 (202-167659) 
&lt;0.0001 
Other medications cost 
14 (0-2897) 
8 (0-3239) 
&lt;0.05 
Laboratory studies cost 
54 (0-1527) 
31 (0-572) 
&lt;0.05 
Radiological studies cost 
0 (0-772) 
0 (0-671) 
NS 
Treatment services cost 
34 (0-7361) 
7 (0-10484) 
&lt;0.001 
Rehabilitation cost 
0 (0-10) 
0 (0-60) 
NS 
Other medical services cost 
272 (47-7808) 
194 (28-3976) 
&lt;0.05 
Hospitalization cost 
32855 (2764-282678) 
7718 (428-170737) 
&lt;0.0001 
CFCs, clotting factor concentrates; NS, not significant. 
*Wilcoxon rank-sum test. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>The US$ : NT$ exchange rate was 1 : 32.84. </p>

<p>Table 6. Median Hospitalization Comparison in Patients with Disease-Related Complications during the Study Period (2007 
US Dollars) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>High-responding inhibitors 
Non-inhibitors 
p value* 
With surgical procedure 
Length of hospitalization 
16 (3-29) 
10 (1-57) 
NS 
Age of hospitalization 
34.6 (0.4-63.6) 
32.0 (0.5-83.1) 
NS 
Hospitalization cost 
78340 (29583-293795) 
25724 (798-296813) 
&lt;0.0001 
Daily cost 
6322 (1286-33123) 
2689 (80-26976) 
&lt;0.001 
Without surgical procedure 
Length of hospitalization 
5 (1-56) 
3 (1-53) 
NS 
Age of hospitalization 
4.6 (0.3-63.0) 
14.7 (0.5-76.6) 
NS 
Hospitalization cost 
32855 (2764-282678) 
7718 (428-170737) 
&lt;0.0001 
Daily cost 
9825 (302-64580) 
1759 (101-20409) 
&lt;0.0001 
NS, not significant. 
*Wilcoxon rank-sum test. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>The US$ : NT$ exchange rate was 1 : 32.84. </p>

<p>Tsu-Chiang Tu, et al. </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 54 Number 2 March 2013 </p>



<p>more severe degrees of arthropathy and greater difficulties 
with mobility and daily activities than patients without in-
hibitors. 
24,25 Gringeri, et al. 
11 reported that quality of life and 
joint scores were significantly improved by the allocation of 
large amounts of resources to patients with high-responding 
inhibitors in Italy. In particular, the physical quality of life in 
these patients was similar to that in patients with severe 
chronic diseases such as diabetes and dialysis-dependent 
chronic renal failure, whereas their mental quality of life 
was comparable to that of the general population. Approxi-
mately 4.6% (37/803) of patients with high-responding in-
hibitors consume approximately 20% of NHI's CFC-related 
resources annually, suggesting that continued optimization 
of strategic planning and management with the care net-
work is needed to improve patient quality of care and quali-
ty of life. Future studies are encouraged in Taiwan to in-
clude the impact on quality of life excluding economic 
consequences. 
The use of the Taiwanese NHI dataset provides the first 
major evidence of economic burden among an Asian popu-
lation of patients with high-responding inhibitors. The man-
datory NHI program insures &gt;99% of the Taiwanese popula-
tion, with all geographic regions and populations represented. 
However, some limitations in the present study should be 
mentioned. First, we identified patients with high-respond-
ing inhibitors via an inhibitor assay and according to the use 
of rFVIIa and aPCCs in the study. Unfortunately, this meth-
odology may have missed some patients with high-respond-
ing inhibitors, particularly children who were treated only 
with ITI therapy after diagnosis, which usually involves the 
daily infusion of large doses of FVIII over many months or 
years. Consequently, the proportion of patients with high-re-
sponding inhibitors may have been underestimated. Second, 
as patients with severe hemophilia patients have been dem-
onstrated to use more CFCs than those with mild and mod-
erate hemophilia, patients with high-responding inhibitors, 
who generally have severe disease, can potentially account 
for the increased cost of CFC. Further assessment of the 
comparing with patients characterized was severe hemophil-
ia in non high-responding inhibitors (412/601, 68.5%). The 
annual median expenditure related to total medical care and 
total CFCs costs showed a reduction to 3.0-amd 2.9-fold 
higher among patients with high-responding inhibitors, re-
spectively. Therefore, it is unlikely that it would materially 
affect the high economic burden results of our study. Third, 
CFCs, comprising the most costly component of hemophil-
ia treatment, are administered on the basis of weight. Un-</p>

<p>tion costs depend primarily on the inhibitor status of the pa-
tient. The median daily hospitalization costs in patients who 
did or did not undergo surgical procedures were 2.4-and 
5.6-fold higher, respectively, in patients with high-respond-
ing inhibitors. Gautier, et al. 
22 reported that the daily cost 
was 2-5-fold higher in French patients with HA and high-
responding inhibitors during hospitalization. Costs related 
to bypassing agents accounted for more than 90% of the to-
tal inpatient costs related to CFCs among patients with high-
responding inhibitors. The difference in hospitalization costs 
may be closely related to the duration of hospitalization and, 
to a lesser extent, to the possible reason for bypassing agent 
administration. 
The proportion of expenditures (rFVII vs. aPCCs) changed 
dramatically after 2004, and a slightly higher proportion of 
expenditures was related to aPCCs (53% vs. 47%) in 2007. 
The NHI has reimbursement criteria for the clinical manage-
ment of inhibitory antibodies in patients, although on-de-
mand treatment is most common. However, CFC replace-
ment therapy and drug utilization patterns are critically 
influenced by multiple variables, such as clinical circum-
stances, patient profiles, individual responses, dose regimen 
protocol, reimbursement policy, and healthcare service type. 
Other cost-contributing concerns include the use of immune 
tolerance induction (ITI) for inhibitor eradication and/or 
prophylaxis to decrease the frequency of bleeding episodes. 
Owing to the wide clinical variability and responsiveness to 
current therapeutic approaches and the scarcity of studies 
providing high-level evidence for therapeutic guidelines at 
the present time, 
11,23 we believe that current strategies for 
managing these patients are rather heterogeneous, and in our 
clinical experience, patients do not respond equally well to 
the various types of bypassing agents in Taiwan. Further 
studies are encouraged to clarify this issue. 
During the 48-month study period, 7 of 37 patients un-
derwent arthroplasty to treat the orthopedic consequences 
of high-responding inhibitors, corresponding to an inci-
dence rate of 4.2 per 1000 person-months. The incidence 
rate was 3-fold higher in patients with high-responding in-
hibitors, which may be attributable to the increasing need 
for surgery in previous years because of difficulties in per-
forming these interventions. Additionally, aPCCs have been 
available only since 2004. If this explanation is valid, the 
estimates from our study are representative of short-and 
middle-term phenomena, and are likely to decrease in size 
and importance in the long term. 
Furthermore, patients with high-responding inhibitors have </p>

<p>Economic Burden of High-Responding Inhibitors </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 54 Number 2 March 2013 </p>





<p>fortunately, weight data are not available in NHIRDs. The 
effect of this limitation on our results is unknown. 
In summary, this retrospective study confirmed higher 
economic burden related to patients with HA and high-re-
sponding inhibitors in Taiwan. To best of our knowledge, 
this is the first major evidence of the economic burden of 
patients with high-responding inhibitors in Asia, and its find-
ings are consistent with those in Western countries. More-
over, future research is encouraged to include the impact on 
quality of life excluding economic consequences. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This study was sponsored by the Hemophilia Care and Re-
search Center in Tri-Service General Hospital, Taipei, Tai-
wan, which was also supported by a Baxter Education Fund. </p>



</text></tei>