<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3692048" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs id="software-7" type="software">DIANA-microT</rs><rs corresp="#software-7" type="version-number">v5.0</rs>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are small endogenous RNA 
<rs id="software-5" type="software">DIANA-microT</rs><rs corresp="#software-5" type="url">http://www.microrna.gr/webServer</rs><rs id="software-6" type="software">DIANA-microT</rs><rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">v5.0</rs><rs corresp="#software-8" type="creator">Taverna</rs><rs id="software-8" type="software">Workflow 
Management System</rs>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are small non-coding RNAs 
($21-23 nt in length) that post-transcriptionally regulate 
gene expression by blocking translation or inducing deg-
radation of the targeted mRNA (1). Since their first iden-
tification in Caenorhabditis elegans in 1993 (2), the number 
of annotated miRNAs and miRNA-related publications 
increase in a super linear rate, clearly depicting their 
central position in the RNA revolution (3). 
In silico miRNA target identification is a crucial step in 
most miRNA experiments, as the miRNA interactome has 
not yet been adequately mapped, even for the most 
studied model organisms. Early miRNA-related research 
efforts have highlighted the necessity of computational 
analyses in order to assist the experimental identification 
of miRNA targets. This has resulted to the development of 
numerous miRNA target prediction algorithms (4), which 
are now considered indispensable for the design of 
relevant experiments. These algorithms identify in silico 
miRNA targets as candidates for further experimentation 
or for computational processing, such as target enrich-
ment analyses. Predictions of the available computational 
algorithms can be acquired from relevant interaction data-
bases or web servers (4,5). </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +30 210 9656310 (ext. 190); Fax: +30 210 9653934; Email: hatzigeorgiou@fleming.gr 
Correspondence may also be addressed to Maria D. Paraskevopoulou. Tel: +30 210 9656310 (ext. 190); Fax: +30 210 9653934; 
Email: paraskevopoulou@fleming.gr </p>

<p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors </p>

<p>Published online 16 May 2013 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, Web Server issue W169-W173 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkt393 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial 
re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>The <rs id="software-11" type="software">DIANA-microT</rs> web server <rs corresp="#software-11" type="version-number">v4.0</rs> (6) is focused on 
providing in silico predictions of miRNA-mRNA inter-
actions. It is characterized by a user-friendly interface 
and provides extensive information for predicted 
miRNA-target gene interactions such as a global score 
for each interaction, as well as detailed information for 
all predicted target sites. Each target site can be visualized, 
and the user can examine its local prediction score, target 
site conservation and miRNA-mRNA binding structure. 
The server also provides connectivity to online biological 
databases and offers links to nomenclature, sequence and 
protein databases. 
Here, we present <rs id="software-12" type="software">DIANA-microT</rs> web server <rs corresp="#software-12" type="version-number">v5.0</rs>, a 
significantly updated version, which hosts the state-of-
the-art target prediction algorithm, DIANA-microT-
CDS (7). microT-CDS is the only algorithm available 
online, specifically designed to identify miRNA targets 
both in 3 
0 untranslated region (3 
0 UTR) and in coding 
sequences (CDS). The new server detects miRNA targets 
in mRNA sequences of Homo sapiens, Mus musculus, 
Drosophila melanogaster and C.elegans. Furthermore, it 
has been updated to miRBase v18 (8) and <rs id="software-13" type="software">Ensembl</rs> <rs corresp="#software-13" type="version-number">v69</rs> 
(9). Specific attention has been paid to the web server 
interface, which follows the DIANA design framework, 
to be instantly familiar to users of previous versions, or 
other DIANA tools (Figure 1). On the other hand, online 
help, informative tooltips and easy-to-use menus minimize 
the learning curve of new users. The fifth version of the 
DIANA-microT web server focuses also on advanced 
users and laboratories requiring support for sophisticated 
pipelines. The server provides programmatic access to 
services of multiple DIANA algorithms and a complete 
integration with the <rs type="software">Taverna Workflow Management 
System</rs> (WMS) (10), using the in-house developed 
DIANA-Taverna Plug-in. Furthermore, a new section of 
the web interface hosts ready-made advanced workflows 
that can perform extensive miRNA-related analyses on 
results derived from high-throughput techniques, such as 
microarrays or Next-Generation Sequencing (NGS). </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Integration of DIANA-microT-CDS </p>

<p>Initial research efforts have unveiled that miRNAs 
regulated gene expression through their binding on 
the 3 
0 UTR of protein-coding genes (2). However, 
accumulated experimental evidence has revealed that 
miRNA-binding sites within coding sequences are also 
functional in controlling gene expression (11). The new 
algorithm microT-CDS (7) can identify miRNA targets 
in 3 
0 UTR, as well as in CDS regions. Further details on 
the microT-CDS algorithm and the utilized training sets 
can be found in the relevant publication by Reczko et al. 
(7). DIANA-microT-CDS provides increased accuracy 
and the highest sensitivity at any level of specificity over 
other available state-of-the-art implementations, when 
tested against pulsed stable isotope labeling by amino 
acids in cell culture (pSILAC) proteomics data sets (12). 
The selection of DIANA-microT-CDS as its core algo-
rithm renders the new web server the only available online </p>

<p>resource capable of incorporating miRNA targets in 
3 
0 UTR as well as in CDS. The new web server enables 
users to attain high quality predicted miRNA-gene inter-
actions in all relevant in silico pipelines. </p>

<p>Web server update and extension </p>

<p><rs type="software">DIANA-microT</rs> server has been updated to miRBase v18 
and <rs id="software-18" type="software">Ensembl</rs> <rs corresp="#software-18" type="version-number">v69</rs>. The server is compatible with the new 
miRNA nomenclature (3p/5p) introduced in miRBase 
v18, as well as with previous miRNA naming conventions. 
It currently supports 7.3 Â 10 
6 H.sapiens, 3.5 Â 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>M.musculus, 4.4 Â 10 
5 D.melanogaster and 2.5 Â 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>C.elegans interactions between 3876 miRNAs and 64 750 
protein-coding genes. Gene (9) and miRNA (13) expres-
sion annotation has been incorporated into the web server, 
enabling the user to perform advanced result filtering 
based on tissue expression. Furthermore, users can also 
restrict predictions between uploaded lists of expressed 
genes and/or miRNAs. For example, this feature can be 
used to identify interactions between a list of repressed (or 
overexpressed) genes and overexpressed (or repressed) 
miRNAs, in the case of a differential expression analysis 
pipeline. 
Moreover, the web server hosts an updated version of 
the KEGG database providing a relevant search module 
based on KEGG pathway descriptions (14). A redesigned 
optional user space has also been implemented, which 
provides personalized features and facilitates the 
interconnectivity between the web server and the available 
<rs type="software">DIANA</rs> software and databases (Figure 1). </p>

<p>Web server support of advanced pipelines </p>

<p>As high-throughput data have become the new backbone 
of biological research, there is an increasing need to 
support advanced high-throughput analysis pipelines. 
The new <rs type="software">DIANA-microT</rs> web server aims to facilitate 
users, not having access to extensive computational 
infrastructures and support, to perform ready-to-use 
sophisticated pipelines. 
<rs id="software-24" type="software">DIANA-microT</rs> web server <rs corresp="#software-24" type="version-number">v5.0</rs> hosts numerous 
integrated analyses in the form of ready-made advanced 
pipelines, covering a wide range of inquiries regarding pre-
dicted or validated miRNA-gene interactions and their 
impact on metabolic and signalling pathways. These pipe-
lines can be used to analyse user data derived from small 
scale and high-throughput experiments directly from the 
<rs type="software">DIANA-microT</rs> web server interface, without the neces-
sity to install or implement any kind of software. 
For instance, one of the available workflows (Figure 2) 
can analyse mRNA and miRNA expression data (expres-
sion and fold change). Suppressed genes are automatically 
matched with overexpressed miRNAs (and vice versa). 
The workflow performs enrichment analysis of experimen-
tally validated targets derived from DIANA-TarBase v6.0 
(3) or/and predicted interactions from microT-CDS. This 
step is considered crucial to identify miRNAs that signifi-
cantly regulate the differentially expressed genes. 
The prediction score threshold can significantly affect 
the analysis steps that follow. In the case of predicted 
interactions, the pipeline can be optimized by automatic </p>



<p>repetitions of different prediction thresholds (from sensi-
tive to more stringent), to minimize the effect of the 
selected settings to the result. By using meta-analysis stat-
istics, the server combines the P-values from each repeti-
tion into a total P-value for each miRNA, signifying its 
effect on the selected genes for all used thresholds (15,16). 
In the last step of the pipeline, the identified miRNAs are 
subjected to a functional analysis, where pathways 
controlled by the combined action of these miRNAs are 
detected using <rs id="software-27" type="software">DIANA-miRPath</rs> <rs corresp="#software-27" type="version-number">v2.1</rs> (16). 
Other available pipelines can handle miRNA and gene 
lists, to perform the enrichment analysis, or even select the 
type of used interactions (predicted or experimentally 
validated). In the latter workflow, the algorithm 'personal-
izes' the target identification module for each miRNA. It 
initially identifies the number of available interactions in 
DIANA-TarBase and DIANA-microT-CDS (validated 
versus predicted) and automatically selects to use validated 
targets only in the cases of well-annotated miRNAs. 
Computationally identified interactions are used otherwise. 
The new <rs type="software">DIANA-microT</rs> web server enables users to 
perform such analyses directly from the on-line user inter-
face, or create even more extensive pipelines programmat-
ically or by using visual tools (<rs type="software">Taverna WMS</rs>). </p>

<p>Web server integration with Taverna WMS </p>

<p><rs id="software-30" type="software">DIANA-microT</rs> web server <rs corresp="#software-30" type="version-number">v5.0</rs> was completely re-
designed to provide the necessary building blocks for </p>

<p>easily incorporating miRNA functional analysis in 
complex pipelines. The new <rs type="software">DIANA-microT</rs> web server 
aims to facilitate advanced users in creating novel or 
enhancing existing pipelines with miRNA target identifi-
cation and functional analysis tools. To this end, <rs id="software-32" type="software">DIANA-
microT</rs> web server <rs corresp="#software-32" type="version-number">v5.0</rs> provides a complete integration 
with the <rs type="software">Taverna WMS</rs>, using our in-house developed 
DIANA-Taverna Plug-in. 
DIANA-<rs type="software">Taverna</rs> Plug-in enables the user to directly 
access our target prediction server (microT-CDS) from 
the graphic interface of Taverna and incorporate 
advanced miRNA analysis functionalities into custom 
pipelines. Furthermore, the plug-in enables the extension 
of such pipelines through the use of other DIANA tools 
and databases, providing access to the most extensive col-
lection of validated miRNA targets (DIANA-TarBase 
v6.0) and to <rs id="software-37" type="software">DIANA-miRPath</rs> <rs corresp="#software-37" type="version-number">v2.1</rs>, a tool designed for 
the identification of miRNA targeted pathways. 
Furthermore, the web server also supports direct pro-
grammatic access to all aforementioned utilities in the 
form of services, to facilitate users having already imple-
mented pipelines using scripting or programming 
languages. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>High-throughput techniques have significantly increased 
the number of users requiring in-depth analysis of </p>

<p>Figure 1. Example of a submitted query in the DIANA-microT web server v5.0. The interface presents information regarding the specified predicted 
miRNA-mRNA interactions. miRNA and gene-related information, as well as the advanced search options have been expanded. Links to external 
databases, graphical representation of the binding sites, as well as miRNA-recognition elements (MREs) conservation and prediction scores are 
displayed in the relevant sections. The left side of the page is devoted to personal user space, reporting latest searches and bookmarks. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, Web Server issue W171 </p>

<p>miRNA-mRNA interactions. These techniques provide 
great numbers of differentially expressed miRNAs and 
genes, which have to be analysed in sophisticated pipe-
lines. The new <rs type="software">DIANA-microT</rs> web server aims to 
further increase the target prediction accuracy and usabil-
ity of the server interface, while facilitating users aiming to 
perform complex miRNA-related analyses. 
Compared with the previous version, the new web 
server has received a major upgrade and is currently up 
to date with key miRNA/gene repositories, such as 
<rs id="software-40" type="software">Ensembl</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-40" type="version-number">v69</rs>) and miRBase (v18). The Taverna Plug-in 
and the integration of cutting-edge workflows in the web 
interface provide the missing link between experimental 
results and state-of-the-art functional meta-analyses. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>The project [09 SYN-13-1055] 'MIKRORNA' by the 
Greek General Secretariat for Research and Technology 
and the project 'TOM' which is implemented under 
the 'ARISTEIA' Action of the 'OPERATIONAL 
PROGRAMME EDUCATION AND LIFELONG 
LEARNING' and is co-funded by the European Social </p>

<p>Fund (ESF) and National Resources. Funding for open 
access charge: Projects TOM and MIKRORNA. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Figure 2. Flowchart depicting an analysis pipeline directly available from the web server interface. Interactions between user-defined miRNA and 
gene sets are in silico identified in 3 
0 UTR and CDS regions using DIANA-microT-CDS. A subsequent miRNA target enrichment analysis identifies 
miRNAs controlling significantly the sets of differentially expressed genes. The pipeline is automatically repeated for different prediction thresholds 
(from more sensitive, to more stringent). By using meta-analysis statistics, the server combines the P-values from each repetition into a total P-value 
for each miRNA, signifying its effect on the selected genes for all used thresholds. In the last step of the pipeline, miRNA-targeted pathway analysis 
is implemented with <rs id="software-38" type="software">DIANA-miRPath</rs> <rs corresp="#software-38" type="version-number">v2</rs>. </p>





<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2013, Vol. 41, Web Server issue W173 </p>

</text></tei>