<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3817086" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Mixed lineage kinase domain-like protein (MLKL) was initially identified as 
a key receptor interacting protein 3 downstream component of tumor-necrosis-factor-induced 
necrosis. In this study, we characterized the expression of MLKL in ovarian carcinomas and 
evaluated the prognostic value of MLKL in patients with ovarian cancer. 
Materials and methods: The ovarian cancer tissue specimens were collected from 153 patients 
diagnosed as primary ovarian cancer after operation at The Second Xiangya Hospital from 
January 2005 to December 2008. Immunohistochemistry was performed for MLKL and the 
protein expression score was quantified using an established scoring system. Kaplan-Meier 
survival curves were generated for disease-free survival (DFS) and overall survival (OS) for 
all patients. MLKL expression levels were correlated with DFS and OS using univariate and 
multivariate Cox regression analysis. 
Results: Seventy-five patients (49%) were defined as having high MLKL expression and 
67 patients (43.7%) had .80% of cells staining for MLKL. Remarkably, low MLKL expression 
was significantly associated with decreased DFS (median 40 months versus 25 months, P=0.0282) 
and OS (median 43 months versus 28 months, P=0.0032). In multivariate analysis, retained 
significance was also observed. 
Conclusion: Low MLKL expression was significantly associated with both decreased DFS 
and OS in patients with primary ovarian cancer. MLKL expression may serve as a potential 
prognostic marker in patients with ovarian cancer. 
Ovarian cancer is the fifth leading cause of cancer deaths in women, and it is the third 
most common gynecological cancer. 
1 In the People's Republic of China, the age-stan-
dardized incidence and mortality rates of ovarian cancer are 3.4 and 1.6 per 100,000, 
respectively. 
2 Despite advances in surgical resections and systemic chemotherapies, the 
prognosis of ovarian cancer remains poor and the 5-year survival rate is only approxi-
mately 30% after the initial diagnosis. 
3 The main reason for the poor rate of survival 
is that early symptoms of malignant ovarian tumors are silent and most of the patients 
have an advanced stage of the disease at diagnosis. In addition, primary or secondary 
multidrug resistances also account for failure in treatment of ovarian cancer. 
4 Thus, 
identifying novel molecular markers with prognostic value is important for improving 
therapeutic methods and extending survival of ovarian cancer patients. 
Necrosis is a type of cell death and is morphologically characterized by a gain in 
cell volume, swelling of organelles, plasma membrane rupture, and subsequent loss </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
29 October 2013 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1540 </p>

<p>he et al </p>

<p>of intracellular contents. 
5 Necrosis is often observed in solid 
tumors with overgrowth and many cancer treatments can 
induce necrotic cell death. 
6,7 Necrosis can occur in a con-
trolled and regulated manner, which is called necroptosis. </p>

<p>8   The initiation of necroptosis can be induced through death 
receptors including tumor necrosis factor (TNF) receptor 1, 
TNF receptor 2, and cluster of differentiation 95 (FasR). 
The serine/threonine kinases, receptor-interacting protein 1 
(RIP1), and receptor-interacting protein 3 (RIP3) are key 
regulators of necrotic signaling. 
8 The mixed lineage kinase 
domain-like protein (MLKL) has been recently identified as 
a key RIP3 downstream component of TNF-induced necro-
sis. 
9,10 MLKL is phosphorylated by RIP3 and is recruited to 
the necrosome through its interaction with RIP3. In addition, 
it has been shown that prolonged c-Jun N terminal kinase 
activation contributes to TNF-induced necrosis. 
11 Several 
studies demonstrated that the activation of c-Jun N terminal 
kinase is associated with poor prognosis in cancer patients. </p>

<p>12,13   However, the prognostic values of RIP1 and RIP3, the key 
components of the necroptosis pathway, have not been evalu-
ated in cancer patients. Interestingly, a recent study suggested 
that MLKL expression can serve as a potential prognostic 
biomarker for patients with early-stage resected pancreatic 
cancer. 
14 However, the prognostic value of MLKL in other 
types of cancers and the role of MLKL in cancer necroptosis 
is unknown. In this study, we investigate the expression and 
prognostic value of MLKL in patients with ovarian cancer. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
patients </p>

<p>This study was approved by the Research Ethics Committee 
of The Second Xiangya Hospital, Hunan, People's Republic 
of China. Informed consent was obtained from all of the 
patients. The ovarian cancer tissue samples were collected 
from 153 patients diagnosed with primary ovarian can-
cer after operation at The Second Xiangya Hospital from 
January 2005 to December 2008. All of the ovarian cancer 
patients received cisplatin-based adjuvant chemotherapies 
following cytoreduction. Briefly, the patients were treated 
with paclitaxel (135 mg/m 
2 , intravenous [IV] for 3 hours) 
plus cisplatin (70 mg/m 
2 , IV for 1 hour) and repeated every 
21 days for six cycles. Surgical staging was established 
according to the International Federation of Gynecology and 
Obstetrics (FIGO) system. Histopathological classification, 
including the stage, grade, and tumor type, was performed 
by an experienced pathologist (Table 1). Disease-free sur-
vival (DFS) was calculated from the date of the first cycle 
of first-line chemotherapy to the first radiological evidence </p>

<p>of recurrence. Overall survival (OS) was calculated from the 
date of histological diagnosis to the date of cancer-caused 
death or to the date of the last follow-up examination. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Paraffin-embedded tissues were stained with anti-MLKL 
antibody (1:60 dilution, ab118348; Abcam, Cambridge, 
MA, USA) at 4°C overnight. Rabbit immunoglobulin G 
was used as a negative control. After washing three times 
with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), the slides were incu-
bated with biotinylated secondary antibody (1:200 dilution; 
Vector Laboratories Inc, Burlingame, CA, USA) at room 
temperature for 30 minutes. After washing three times with 
PBS, the slides were stained with the ABC Elite kit (Vector 
Laboratories Inc). Finally, the slides were counterstained 
with hematoxylin, dehydrated, cleared, and then mounted 
with Permount mounting medium (Thermo Fisher Scientific, 
Waltham, MA, USA). Histological images were captured 
from the microscope (Carl Zeiss AX10; Carl Zeiss Meditec 
AG, Jena, Germany) with an objective magnification of X40, 
and high-resolution digital images were acquired and pro-
cessed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">Axionvision</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Carl Zeiss Meditec AG</rs>). 
MLKL staining was scored independently by two patholo-
gists and was calculated using a previously defined scoring 
system. 
15,16 Briefly, the proportion of positive tumor cells was 
scored as: 0= less than 5%; 1+=5%-20%; 2+=21%-50%; and 
3+.50%. The intensity was arbitrarily scored as 0= weak 
(no color or light blue), 1= moderate (light yellow), 2= 
strong (yellow brown), and 3= very strong (brown). The </p>

<p>Table 1 Clinic pathological characteristics and results of MLKL 
immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Number 
of patients </p>

<p>MLKL expression 
P-value 
Low or no 
High </p>

<p>Ages 
0.1412 
#60 
62 
27 
35 </p>

<p>.60 
91 
51 
40 
histologic type 
0.0782 
Serous 
93 
42 
51 </p>

<p>Mucinous 
42 
28 
14 </p>

<p>endometrioid 
12 
5 
7 </p>

<p>Clear cell 
6 
3 
3 
pathological grade 
0.1353 
1 
25 
17 
8 </p>

<p>2 
44 
19 
25 </p>

<p>3 
84 
42 
42 
FIGO stage 
0.0906 
I-II 
57 
24 
33 </p>

<p>III-IV 
96 
54 
42 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: FIGO, International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics; 
MLKL, mixed lineage kinase domain-like protein. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1541 </p>

<p>prognostic value of MLKL in ovarian cancer </p>

<p>overall score was calculated by multiplying the two scores 
obtained from each sample. A score of $4 was defined as 
high MLKL expression and a score of ,4 was defined low 
MLKL expression. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The relationship between the expression of MLKL and 
patient's age, histological type, pathologic grade, and FIGO 
stage were analyzed using the χ 
2 test or Fisher's exact test, as 
appropriate. OS curves and DFS curves were generated using 
the Kaplan-Meier method and compared using a log-rank 
test. Univariate and multivariate analyses were performed 
using Cox regression models. P-values less than 0.05 were 
regarded as statistically significant. Data were analyzed using 
the <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> (version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version">20.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM Corporation</rs>, Armonk, NY, 
USA) software program. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>In this study, we collected a total of 153 ovarian cancer sam-
ples from patients with a median age of 66 years. Patient char-
acteristics of the population are summarized in Table 1. A total 
of 60.7% of the cases had a serous histology (93/153); 27.4% 
of the cases had a mucinous histology (42/153); whereas 
endometrioid and clear cell histotypes were less represented. 
The median follow-up for survivors was 37 months (range, 
3-102 months). At the time of the last follow-up, 71.8% of the 
patients had died and 15.4% had no evidence of disease. All 
of the patients in this study were treated with cisplatin-based 
first-line chemotherapy after surgery. 
We examined the expression of MLKL in ovarian tumor 
samples by immunohistochemical analysis. As shown in 
Figure 1, MLKL positive staining was localized to the 
cytoplasm in tumor cells. According to established criteria 
for high-expression and low-expression groups, 75 patients 
(49%) were defined as having high MLKL expression 
(Table 1) and 67 patients (43.7%) had .80% of cells staining 
for MLKL. We further analyzed the association of MLKL 
expression with clinic pathological characteristics in the 
patients. We found no statistical associations between the 
expression of MLKL and patient age, histological type, 
pathologic grade, or FIGO stage (Table 1). 
We then evaluated the prognostic signif icance of 
MLKL expression in ovarian cancer patients. Interestingly, 
we found that high MLKL expression was significantly 
associated with increased DFS (median 40 months versus 
25 months, P=0.0282) and showed a trend towards longer 
OS (median 43 months versus 28 months, P=0.0032) 
(Figure 2A and B). Furthermore, a multivariate Cox regres-</p>

<p>sion analysis was applied to all of the clinicopathologic 
characteristics with MLKL expression levels. As shown in 
Table 2, low MLKL expression levels were independently 
associated with the poor prognosis of patients with ovar-
ian cancer. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>MLKL was initially identified as a key mediator in TNF-
induced necroptosis. In cancer cells, RIP3 interacts with and 
phosphorylates MLKL to promote necroptosis. 
9,10 Interest-
ingly, one recent study suggested that MLKL expression 
can be served as a prognostic biomarker in patients with 
early-stage resected pancreatic adenocarcinoma. 
14 In this 
study, Colbert et al identified that low MLKL expression was 
significantly associated with both decreased DFS and OS in 
the patients receiving adjuvant therapy. This study provides 
the first evidence that a necroptosis protein has prognostic 
value in cancer patients. In our current study, by using a 
relatively large cohort of ovarian carcinoma specimens, 
we identified that ovarian cancer patients with low MLKL 
expression showed a worse DFS and OS, which is similar 
to the pattern described by Colbert et al. 
14 It has been shown </p>

<p>Figure 1 representative images of MLKL immunohistochemical staining in ovarian 
cancer tissues. 
Notes: (A) high MLKL expression in serous ovarian cancer tissue. (B) Low MLKL 
expression in serous ovarian cancer tissue. (C) high MLKL expression in mucinous 
ovarian cancer tissue. (D) Low MLKL expression in mucinous ovarian cancer tissue. 
(E) high MLKL expression in endometrioid ovarian cancer tissue. (F) Low MLKL 
expression in endometrioid ovarian cancer tissue. Magnification, ×400. 
Abbreviation: MLKL, mixed lineage kinase domain-like protein. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1542 </p>

<p>he et al </p>

<p>phosphorylation level of MLKL in cancer patients in order to 
validate the role of MLKL in necroptosis in cancer patients 
with chemotherapy. 
As all of the patients in our study received cisplatin-based 
chemotherapy, our study provides a potential biomarker 
for clinicians to better select chemotherapies based on 
MLKL expression. Patients with low MLKL expression in 
tumor tissues may be less likely to benefit from the regular 
cisplatin-based chemotherapy. However, these patients may 
benefit from combination chemotherapy or participation in 
clinical trials. Thus, future studies should examine the role 
of MLKL in predicting response to different therapies for 
better treatment selection. Recently, there have been reports 
of several other proteins that may serve as a prognosis 
biomarker for ovarian cancer patients such as steroid recep-
tor coactivator-3, high-mobility group AT-hook 2, c-Abl, 
and centromere protein A. 
16,19-21 These proteins have been 
shown to be involved in cell cycle regulation, apoptosis, 
invasion, and metastasis in cancer. Our study demonstrated 
that expression of a protein involved in necroptosis exhibits 
prognostic value in ovarian cancer patients, suggesting that 
necroptosis may play an important role in determining cancer 
cell death and patient outcome with chemotherapy. Future 
studies need to evaluate the association between MLKL and 
other prognostic biomarkers and may identify a prognostic 
panel including multiple prognostic biomarkers in ovarian 
cancer patients. 
In conclusion, our study first explored the expression of 
MLKL in the context of ovarian cancer and suggests that low 
MLKL expression is associated with decreased DFS and OS 
in patients with ovarian cancer. This study suggests that MLKL 
may serve as a potential therapeutic target in ovarian cancer 
patients. However, since relatively little is known about the 
detailed role of MLKL in necroptosis or in other signaling 
pathways, future studies need to elucidate the molecular mech-
anisms of MLKL in cancer cell death with chemotherapy. </p>

<p>Percent survival </p>

<p>Percent survival </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 </p>

<p>Months </p>

<p>80 
100 </p>

<p>High MLKL 
(n=75) </p>

<p>Low MLKL 
(n=78) </p>

<p>P=0.0282 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Disease-free survival </p>

<p>Months </p>

<p>High MLKL 
(n=75) </p>

<p>Low MLKL 
(n=78) </p>

<p>P=0.0032 </p>

<p>0 
2 0 
4 0 
6 0 
8 0 
1 00 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Overall survival </p>

<p>Figure 2 Kaplan-Meier log-rank survival analysis for (A) disease-free survival and 
(B) overall survival of ovarian cancer patients according to MLKL expression. 
Abbreviations: MLKL, mixed lineage kinase domain-like protein; n, number. </p>

<p>Table 2 Multivariate analyses for all patients (n=153) </p>

<p>Characteristics 
DFS 
OS </p>

<p>HR (95% CI) 
P-value 
HR (95% CI) 
P-value </p>

<p>Ages (#60 years vs .60 years) 
1.2 (0.8-2.1) 
0.1281 
1.3 (0.9-1.8) 
0.4586 
histologic type (serous vs mucinous vs 
endometrioid vs clear cell) </p>

<p>1.5 (0.4-1.5) 
0.0926 
0.8 (0.2-1.7) 
0.8192 </p>

<p>pathological grade (grade 1 vs grade 2 vs grade 3) 
1.3 (0.9-2.0) 
0.2565 
1.0 (0.8-1.4) 
0.1328 
FIGO stage (I-II vs III-IV) 
0.8 (0.6-1.9) 
0.2734 
0.6 (0.2-1.7) 
0.0937 
Level of MLKL expression (high vs low) 
3.5 (0.5-7.1) 
0.0211 
4.2 (1.3-11.5) 
0.0038 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; DFS, disease-free survival; FIGO, International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics; hr, hazard ratio; MLKL, mixed lineage 
kinase domain-like protein; OS, overall survival; vs, versus. </p>

<p>that cisplatin can induce both apoptosis and necrosis in cancer 
cells, which is dependent on the profile of proteins involved 
in cell death and cell cycle. 
17,18 Because MLKL was a key 
mediator in necroptosis signaling, low expression of MLKL 
may suggest decreased necroptosis signaling in patients with 
chemotherapy. Thus, one possible underlying mechanism for 
the association of low MLKL expression with poor progno-
sis in ovarian cancer patients may be a result of decreased 
necroptosis signaling in these patients. In the future, it 
would be interesting to examine the necroptosis-specific </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargets-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open access 
journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1543 </p>

<p>prognostic value of MLKL in ovarian cancer </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>This research was supported by the Hunan Provincial Natural 
Science Foundation of China (number 2013SK3045). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



</text></tei>