<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3782730" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVE: To understand the relationships between brain structures and function (behavior and cognition) in 
healthy aging. 
METHOD: The study group was composed of 56 healthy elderly subjects who underwent neuropsychological 
assessment and quantitative magnetic resonance imaging. Cluster analysis classified the cohort into two 
groups, one (cluster 1) in which the magnetic resonance imaging metrics were more preserved (mean age: 66.4 
years) and another (cluster 2) with less preserved markers of healthy brain tissue (mean age: 75.4 years). 
RESULTS: The subjects in cluster 2 (older group) had worse indices of interference in the Stroop test compared 
with the subjects in cluster 1 (younger group). Therefore, a simple test such as the Stroop test could 
differentiate groups of younger and older subjects based on magnetic resonance imaging metrics. 
CONCLUSION: These results are in agreement with the inhibitory control hypotheses regarding cognitive aging 
and may also be important in the interpretation of studies with other clinical groups, such as patients with 
dementia and mild cognitive impairment. </p>

<p>findings regarding the evidence that age-related changes in 
the volume of specific brain structures have direct con-
sequences for cognitive function. Therefore, the relation-
ships between structure (brain) and function (behavior and 
cognition) in healthy aging remain controversial. 
Another area of interest is the age at which the greatest loss 
in cognition occurs. There is no consensus regarding whether 
it begins after age 70, after age 80, or even between these ages 
(8-11). Because of this lack of consensus, another of our 
objectives was to compare MRI markers of neuropsycholo-
gical performance in a group of younger healthy elderly (12)  with those in an older healthy elderly group (13) to 
understand the differences between these groups. 
Regarding brain structure, the MRI analysis included 
volumetric quantitative techniques; relaxometry (quantita-
tive T2), which is a marker of the presence of changes in the 
concentration of intra-and extracellular water in tissues; 
and evaluation of the magnetization transfer ratio (MTR), 
which is used to infer demyelination and axonal damage. In 
the neuropsychological assessment, techniques and tests 
that were sensitive to disorders associated with aging were 
applied and were translated into Portuguese. 
Therefore, the objective of this study was to compare 
structural changes (both global and lobar gyri changes) on 
MRI with patterns of functional performance on neuropsy-
chological tests to identify a connection between structure 
and function in the spectrum of normal aging. </p>

<p>&amp; PATIENTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study design </p>

<p>This was a prospective case-control study with normal 
elderly subjects submitted to an extensive medical evalua-
tion to exclude both dementia and mild cognitive impair-
ment (MCI). Both subgroups were studied with an 
extensive MRI protocol that included regular sequences 
and quantitative measurements of the cortical surface 
segmentation, brain parenchymal fraction (BPF), white 
matter (WM) and gray matter (GM) volume, magnetiza-
tion transfer ratio (MTR), and quantitative T2 (qT2) of WM 
and GM. We extracted the values from maps of each 
group, and changes were evaluated based on these 
physical characteristics. The patients, based on their MRI 
characteristics, were divided into two subsets of indivi-
duals that exhibited higher (cluster 1) and lower (cluster 2) 
performance. </p>

<p>Participants </p>

<p>The study group consisted of 56 elderly subjects, aged 
58 to 83 years (mean¡SD: 68.2¡6.22 years), who had 
completed 1 to 15 years of schooling (7.4¡4.37 years). All 
subjects were diagnosed as healthy, with the exclusion of 
any abnormality that may interfere with cognitive and 
cerebral functioning. The study was approved by the 
Research Ethics Committee, and all subjects provided 
written informed consent to participate in the study. </p>

<p>Procedures </p>

<p>One expert geriatrician evaluated all participants to 
exclude medical conditions that may interfere with 
cognitive and cerebral functioning, such as diseases of 
the central nervous system that compromised cognitive 
function; sensorineural deficits (meaningful hearing loss, 
visual or color recognition deficit) or sensorimotor </p>

<p>incapacitation that would impair the execution of the 
proposed tests; psychiatric disorder; history of chronic 
alcoholism (.3 drinks per day); clinical delirium; oxygen-
dependent pulmonary conditions (partial pressure of 
oxygen less than 60 mmHg); pulmonary diseases or severe 
refractory asthma; endocrine-metabolic and nutritional 
conditions determined by laboratory tests, such as the 
venereal disease research laboratory (VDRL), calcium, 
fasting blood glucose, HMG, and TSH tests (i.e., diabetes 
mellitus, hypo/hyperthyroidism, hypercalcemia, growth 
hormone deficiency, conditions of hypo-or hypercortiso-
lism, vitamin B12 or folic acid and niacin deficiency, and 
anemia with hemoglobin levels below 10 mg/dl); and 
cardiovascular disorders, including a diagnosis of severe 
or end-stage heart disease, a history of acute myocardial 
infarction or documented coronary disease, moderate 
to severe hypertension, and advanced atherosclerosis. 
Additionally, participants taking any of the following 
medications were also excluded: neuroleptics, tricyclic 
antidepressants, anticonvulsants, methyldopa, clonidine or 
similar drugs, corticoids (.5 mg of prednisone or equiva-
lent), and benzodiazepines (for less than 6 months or at a 
dose of more than 10 mg of diazepam per day, or 
equivalent). 
The instruments used to test study-eligible patients 
included the Brazilian version of the MINI International 
Neuropsychiatric Interview, which is a short, structured 
diagnostic interview used to diagnose psychiatric condi-
tions, such as mood disorders and psychosis (14), and the 
Brazilian version of the Mini Mental State Exam (Folstein  et al., 1975), adopting the criteria of 2 standard deviations 
above the mean for normal seniors with the same education 
level of this study group for exclusion of the diagnosis of 
dementia (3). The participants had to have scored 26-30 
points on the Mini-Mental State Exam and passed the 
screening procedure in the short structured diagnostic 
interview (Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview -
Brazilian version). In addition, the subjects underwent 
activities of daily living assessment using the Katz scale, 
which must show preserved indices (scores: 0), i.e., 
independent activities of daily living scale (15) and 
Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR) scale, which includes 
indices of 0 and 0.5 (16). After this screening procedure, 
the participants proceeded to the MRI scan and neuropsy-
chological assessment. </p>

<p>MRI protocol </p>

<p>MRI images were acquired in a 1.5-Tesla MR machine 
(Magnetom Vision; Siemens, Erlangen, Germany). The 
image protocol included two identical axial gradient-echo 
sequences (TR = 34 ms; TE = 11 ms; slice thickness = 5 mm; 
and number of slices = 34), with and without a magnetiza-
tion transfer pulse, used to generate the MTR map; one 
axial SE multi-echo sequence (TR = 3000 ms; TE = 22/60/ 
120 ms; and 20 slices, 5-mm thickness), used to generate 
the T2 relaxometry map; and one sagittal volumetric 
3DT1 MPRAGE sequence (TR = 9.7 ms; TE = 4 ms, and 
160 slices 1-mm thick), used for volumetry and tissue 
classification. </p>

<p>MRI analysis </p>

<p>Segmentation of regions. The automated procedures for 
obtaining volumetric measurements of the different brain 
structures were described by Fischl et al. (17). This </p>

<p>Spectrum of Normal Aging 
Foss MP et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2013;68(9):1197-1205 </p>



<p>procedure was accomplished using the Freesurfer package 
version 4.5 (Martinos Center for Biomedical Imaging, 
Charlestown, Massachusetts, USA). This software classifies 
each voxel with a neuroanatomical label based on 
probabilistic information automatically estimated from 
a manually labeled training set. Initially, an optimal linear 
transform was computed to maximize the likelihood of 
the input image based on an atlas constructed from 
manually labeled images. Next, a nonlinear transform 
was initialized with the transformation of the previous 
step, and the image was deformed until a better match of 
the atlas was obtained. Finally, a Bayesian segmentation 
procedure was applied, and the maximum a posteriori 
estimate of the labeling was computed. The technique has 
been previously shown to be comparable in accuracy to 
manual labeling (17). The <rs type="software">Freesurfer</rs> system provides the 
volumes of the classified structures and cortical thickness 
values. 
MTR map. The MTR map is a percent-difference image 
calculated voxel-by-voxel from one pair of identical 
sequences, except for the presence or absence of the MT 
pulse, using the following formula (18): </p>

<p>MTR~M 
0 -M S 
M 0 
|100 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>where (MO) is the signal intensity of the pixel with no MT 
pulse, Ms is the signal intensity of the pixel with the MT 
pulse, and MTR is the magnetization transfer ratio. We used 
the <rs type="software">Mincmath</rs> tool (19) to construct the MTR map for each 
exam. 
Relaxometry map. A natural logarithm (ln) was applied 
in the multi-echo images. A linear equation results from this 
procedure: </p>

<p>ln Sr r,TE 
ð 
Þ 
½ 
ln S 0r r 
ð Þ 
½ 
{ 
1 
T2r r 
ð Þ 
|TE 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>where Sr r,TE 
ð 
Þand S 0r r 
ð Þ represent the pixel intensity at the 
positionr r in the image obtained at the TE echo time and 
''ideal'' 0 echo time, respectively. Therefore, a linear least 
squares method can be used to estimate the T2 pixel value 
(T2r r 
ð Þ) from the obtained TE images. The in-house script 
"Relaxon" was implemented for this purpose using <rs type="software">MINC</rs> 
tools. 
Estimation of global measures and cluster analysis. After 
the segmentation, the global measures were computed. The 
following parameters were calculated: </p>

<p>Brain parenchyma fraction (%). </p>

<p>BPF~W 
MVzGMV 
ð 
Þ 
ICV 
|100 
ð3Þ </p>

<p>where WMV is the white matter volume, GMV is the gray 
matter volume, and ICV is the intracranial volume. </p>

<p>Percentage of white matter (%). </p>

<p>PWM~L 
WMVCerebralzRWMVCerebralzLWMVCerebellumzRWMVCerebellum 
ð 
Þ 
ICV 
|100 ð4Þ </p>

<p>where LWMV is the white matter volume of the left 
hemisphere, RWMV is the white matter volume of the 
right hemisphere, and ICV is the intracranial volume. </p>

<p>Percentage of gray matter (%). </p>

<p>PGM~L 
GMVCerebralzRGMVCerebralzLGMVCerebellumzRGMVCerebellum 
ð 
Þ 
ICV 
|100 ð5Þ </p>

<p>where LGMV is the gray matter volume of the left 
hemisphere, RGMV is the gray matter volume of the right 
hemisphere, and ICV is the intracranial volume. </p>

<p>MTR of white matter (%): </p>

<p>MTRWM~LMTRWM Cerebral zRMTRWM Cerebral </p>

<p>zLMTRWM Cerebellum zRMTRWM Cerebellum 
ð6Þ </p>

<p>where LMTRWM is the white matter MTR of the left 
hemisphere and RMTRWM is the white matter MTR of the 
right hemisphere. </p>

<p>MTR of Gray matter (%): </p>

<p>MTRGM~LMTRGM Cerebral zRMTRGM Cerebral </p>

<p>zLMTRGM Cerebellum zRMTRGM Cerebellum 
ð7Þ </p>

<p>where LMTRGM is the white matter MTR of the left 
hemisphere and RMTRGM is the white matter MTR of the 
right hemisphere. </p>

<p>Relaxometry of white matter (ms): </p>

<p>RXWM~LRXWM Cerebral zRRXWM Cerebral </p>

<p>zLRXWM Cerebellum zRRXWM Cerebellum 
ð8Þ </p>

<p>where LRXWM is the white matter relaxometry of the left 
hemisphere and RRXWM is the white matter relaxometry of 
the right hemisphere. </p>

<p>Relaxometry of gray matter (ms): </p>

<p>RXGM~LRXGM Cerebral zRRXGM Cerebral </p>

<p>zLRXGM Cerebellum zRRXGM Cerebellum 
ð9Þ </p>

<p>where LRXWM is the white matter relaxometry of the left 
hemisphere and RRXWM is the white matter relaxometry of 
the right hemisphere. 
The patients, based on their MRI characteristics, were 
divided using k-means cluster analyses implemented in 
<rs type="software">Minitab</rs> software, and two groups were formed: cluster 1, 
which had the best results with respect to quantitative MRI 
measures (high volumes and MTRs), and cluster 2, which 
had the worst results (low volumes and MTR values and 
high T2 values). The k-means cluster analysis is used to 
cluster observations into groups when the groups are 
initially unknown. This procedure uses non-hierarchical 
clustering of observations. 
Cluster analysis and comparison. Using the MTR, 
relaxometry, volumes of cortical and subcortical structures, 
white matter areas, and cortical thickness values, we 
compared the clusters with the goal of identifying the 
specific localization of lesions. For this comparison, we 
used the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test to analyze the normality </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>CLINICS 2013;68(9):1197-1205 
Spectrum of Normal Aging 
Foss MP et al. </p>



<p>of the samples and the two-tailed t-test for independent 
samples. </p>

<p>Characterization of neuropsychological indexes </p>

<p>Healthy individuals were submitted to the neuropsycho-
logical evaluation using the Mattis Dementia Rating Scale 
(MDRS) (20), Stroop Test (21,22), Verbal Fluency test (23), 
Wisconsin Card Sorting Test (WCST) (24), Rey Complex 
Figure test (25), Vocabulary -Wais -III (26), Logical 
Memory (WMS-R) test (27), Visual Reproduction (WMS-R) 
(27) and Rey Auditory-Verbal Learning Test (RAVLT) (28), 
conducted by a neuropsychologist with experience in 
cognitive assessment of elderly individuals. Other demo-
graphic variables were collected by informal questionnaires 
with the patient such as schooling, occupation, socio-
economic level and handedness. </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>The performance of each participant during the neurop-
sychological evaluation was standardized in z-scores 
according to the mean and standard deviation of this study 
group and the signs were inverted for the measures for 
which a higher score indicated a poorer performance, as 
was the case for the measures of processing time. 
These neuropsychological results were divided according 
to the quantitative MRI measures, and a comparison 
between the groups was performed by the Mann-Whitney 
nonparametric test of the <rs id="software-6" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version">13.0</rs> for Windows including 
the variables age and schooling. </p>

<p>&amp; RESULTS </p>

<p>The cluster analysis identified one group in which the 
brain MRI markers were more preserved and another in 
which the brain MRIs showed less preserved markers. The 
cluster 1 had the best results with respect to quantitative 
MRI measures (high volumes and MTRs) and cluster 2 had 
the worst results (low volumes and MTR values and high 
T2 values). With regard to volume, cluster 1 had higher 
significant values than the second cluster at global (brain 
parenchyma fraction (p = 0.02) and local levels (left brain 
white matter (p = 0.02), left cerebral cortex (p = 0.03), right 
brain white matter (p = 0.004), and right cerebral cortex 
(p = 0.02)) (Figure 1). The cortical regions had a greater 
number of distinct regions compared with WM and 
subcortical structures. There was also an increased involve-
ment of the left cerebral cortex compared with the right 
cerebral cortex, for both gray and white matter. The frontal 
and temporal lobes were more affected than the other 
regions in the two groups. 
The MTR showed predominant changes in WM and 
subcortical structures, with more conserved values in 
cluster 1 (p,0.05) (Figure 1). The qT2 showed more 
extensive abnormalities than MTR, especially in the right 
cerebral cortex (Figure 1). The MTR and qT2 demonstrated 
more preserved indices for cluster 1 in the pars triangularis, 
medial temporal regions (including entorhinal regions), the 
pre-motor frontal lobe of the left cerebral cortex, and the 
right cortical regions of the frontal lobe. Volume analysis of 
subcortical structures revealed more preserved values for 
cluster 1 in the hippocampus, amygdala, and ventral 
diencephalon bilaterally, as well as in the left thalamus, 
brain stem, left accumbens area, and right cerebellum. The 
middle posterior corpus callosum, anterior middle corpus </p>

<p>callosum, and central corpus callosum (Figure 1) also 
demonstrated differences between groups. The differences 
in magnetization transfer between the clusters were 
significant in the left ventral diencephalon, optic chiasm, 
mid-anterior corpus callosum, and bilaterally in the 
amygdale. The qT2 revealed better indices for cluster 1 in 
the left thalamus proper, left and right hippocampus, and 
central corpus callosum. 
The participants in cluster 1 had a mean age of 66.4¡5.2 
years and 7.3¡4.2 years of schooling, while those in cluster 
2 had a mean age of 75.4¡4.8 years and 7.8¡5.2 years of 
schooling. Occupations varied in clusters 1 and 2, with half 
of the participants being retired (51-54%), 26-18% being 
housewives, and 22-27% being employed. The right-hand 
preference was prevalent for clusters 1 and 2. In both 
clusters, 55-54% of the participants were of low socio-
economic status, while 44-45% were of middle socio-
economic status. There were no significant differences 
(p,0.05) between the clusters with regard to education, 
occupation, handedness, and socioeconomic level, but 
significant differences in age were found. 
Due to the differences in neuropsychological performance 
between cluster 1 (mean age of 66.4 years) and cluster 2 
(mean age of 75.4 years), we encountered significant 
differences in the interference indices of the Stroop test 
(p = 0.024) (Figure 2). In addition, cluster 1 had better 
weighted scores (z-score: +0.142) than cluster 2 (z-score: -
0.650). There were also significant differences in age 
between the clusters (p,0.0001, Figure 3), whereas no 
significant difference was noted in years of schooling 
(p = 0.536). Therefore, the older group, which had worse 
indices of interference in the Stroop test, also had inferior 
results in MRI than the younger group. </p>

<p>&amp; DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Controversy remains regarding the relationship between 
brain volumes and cognition in healthy elderly, yet changes 
in the aging brain structure are shown by MRI and described 
as an increase in size of the cerebral ventricles and reduction 
in volume of the cerebral cortex, hippocampus, and 
parahippocampal gyrus related to aging (29). However, 
cognitive declines in aging involve mechanisms other than 
those that are purely structural, such as alterations in the 
production of neurotransmitters (dopaminergic explanation), 
dysfunction of some cognitive domains (inhibitory control 
hypothesis, hypothesis of slow mental processing, and 
frontal hypothesis), and sensory losses, among others. 
These theories are not mutually exclusive, and a theory that 
unifies and explains the interrelated mechanisms of cognitive 
aging in these different levels is still missing (1). 
Previous studies in this area seem to consider only one 
side of the equation between brain and behavior, without 
explaining their relationships; therefore, the present study 
is important because it compared MRI results with 
neuropsychological performance in two groups of healthy 
elderly, one in the sixth decade of life and another in the 
seventh decade of life. This study began with the analyses of 
biological markers associated with MRI findings in two 
clusters, namely cluster 1 (mean 66.4 years), consisting of 
participants who had less volumetric change in MTR and 
qT2, and cluster 2 (mean 75.4 years), consisting of 
participants who had global atrophy, a low MTR, and a 
prolonged T2 time. Such findings are in accordance with </p>

<p>Spectrum of Normal Aging 
Foss MP et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2013;68(9):1197-1205 </p>



<p>studies that indicate a more rapid decline in cognition after 
70 years of age (8,9). These results did not show differences 
with respect to other variables such as educational level, 
occupation, socioeconomic level, and handedness, which 
could explain such discrepancies. 
The MRI results showed that cortical regions were more 
affected than white matter and subcortical structures in the 
older cluster. Other studies demonstrated that cortical gray 
matter atrophy predicted cognitive decline regardless of 
whether lacunes were present; neither lacunes nor white 
matter hyperintensity independently predicted decline (30). </p>

<p>Although many histological studies have demonstrated that 
white matter changes are more prominent than cortical 
changes with aging (31-37), other authors indicated a 
greater loss of gray matter in mild cognitive impairment 
(MCI), with a greater risk of conversion to dementia than in 
stable MCI (38). Another study using a cross-sectional, 
population-based VBM also revealed an accelerated gray 
matter loss exclusively in men, involving the temporal 
neocortex, prefrontal neocortex, and medial temporal 
regions (39). Even though our study included more women 
than men, it did not reveal differences related to gender. </p>

<p>Figure 1 -Brain Volumetric Changes. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2013;68(9):1197-1205 
Spectrum of Normal Aging 
Foss MP et al. </p>



<p>Subcortical structures were less affected by age than 
cortical structures, but significant differences (p,0.05) were 
found in the volume of the left thalamus proper, brain stem, 
left acumens area, and right cerebellum white matter, as well </p>

<p>as bilaterally in the hippocampus, amygdale, and ventral 
diencephalon. These findings are comparable to those of 
other studies indicating that the greatest shrinkage across the 
lifespan occurs in the caudate, cerebellum, hippocampus, </p>

<p>Figure 2 -Stroop test (z-scores) and MRI. </p>

<p>Figure 3 -Relationship between Age and RMI. </p>

<p>Spectrum of Normal Aging 
Foss MP et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2013;68(9):1197-1205 </p>



<p>and prefrontal areas (6). Previous studies also argued that 
subcortical structures, such as the striatum, have not been 
extensively studied in aging, and similarly little is known 
about changes in the volume of the cerebellum (5,40,41). 
According to the present study, the subcortical structures do 
not seem to change significantly with age, as we verified 
more involvement of the cortical regions. 
The MTR provides an indication of the quantity of 
protons bound to macromolecules in a given tissue, and 
our study revealed WM impairment in addition to volume 
loss. The MTR is reduced in many pathological processes, 
particularly those associated with demyelination and axonal 
damage (42). Decreases in the MTR have been reported in 
experimental models of Wallerian degeneration after optic 
nerve lesions (43). 
Clinical studies have reported that MTR measurements 
show major reductions in processes related to demyelina-
tion, axonal loss, and tissue destruction (44). The MTR has 
been extensively used for the assessment of central nervous 
system WM lesions in different diseases, especially in MS, in 
which the MTR is used to predict disease progression (45- 48). Although brain atrophy may be associated with the 
MTR decrease, pathological correlations have demonstrated 
that the main cause of the MTR decrease is demyelination. 
In addition, in normal-appearing WM, the MTR decrease 
correlates with axonal attenuation. Therefore, we speculate 
that the MTR decrease in our cohort may be explained by a 
combination of neuronal and axonal damage and demyeli-
nation related to aging. 
The qT2 showed abnormalities in cortical structures 
related to the right cerebral cortex, as well as the MTR. 
Both of these MRI metrics revealed changes in cortical 
structures that were most severe in the second cluster in the 
left cortex associated with the temporal-frontal cortex and 
right cerebral cortex of the frontal lobe. 
Therefore, our data demonstrated that the frontal and 
temporal lobes were preferentially affected (Figure 1). Many 
studies also concluded that the prefrontal cortices were the 
most affected by aging compared with other neocortical 
regions, followed by losses in parietal, temporal, and 
occipital cortices (1,5,8). 
As already cited, the cortical areas were more affected 
than the other areas, and the relationship between gray 
matter loss and executive functions probably indicates 
processes that affect the frontal cortex by direct neuronal 
loss, loss of neocortical association ascending pathways, or 
damage to fronto-subcortical circuits (49). Executive func-
tioning was impaired with the increase in white matter 
hyperintensities and the loss in volume of the prefrontal 
cortex (50). The analysis of the MTR in this study indicated 
lower values in the anterior regions of the brain in cluster 2, 
suggesting that this group of older elderly individuals with 
less preserved brain volume and worse neuropsychological 
scores possesses smaller areas of myelination than cluster 1. 
Thus, decreased myelination of nerve fibers appears to 
influence the biological and neuropsychological measures of 
aging (inhibitory control) even in a healthy aging group. 
The decrease in MTR and the increase in relaxation time 
of the brain MRI is a sign of healthy tissue loss that may be 
observed more in the left cerebral hemisphere, mainly in the 
temporal and frontal areas, whereas these occurrences were 
confined to the frontal lobe in the right hemisphere cortical 
areas. This finding suggests greater tissue integrity loss in 
anterior areas of the brain, especially in the frontal cortex. </p>

<p>The vulnerability of the frontal lobes to cognitive aging is 
the basis of one of the most accepted theories of cognitive 
aging known as the Frontal Lobe Hypothesis of Aging. This 
hypothesis postulates that the decline in frontal efficiency 
can account for many of the cognitive deficits associated 
with cognitive aging, such as impared executive functions 
(1). 
The Stroop test, Color and Trail-Making Test, Word 
Fluency tests, and Wisconsin Card Sorting Test (WCST) 
were administered to evaluate executive functions. The 
Stroop test (interference index) was the only test that 
indicated differences between clusters 1 and 2, with worse 
MRI measures found in the older elderly (cluster 2) 
compared with the younger elderly cluster (cluster 1). The 
effect of age on the Stroop interference paradigm could be 
attributable to the slowness in mental processing time; 
however, this slowness would lead to a decrease in the 
reading speed for incongruent words, leading to the Stroop 
interference effect (41). In the current study, the rate of 
interference was measured by dividing the time (in seconds) 
necessary to name colored dots by the time required to 
name the colors of words written with the names of 
different colors. 
Changes in inhibitory control constitute one of the 
hypotheses about cognitive aging that may relate it to a 
healthy process of human development. However, other 
authors pointed out that errors in the color incongruent trials, 
in a computerized version of the Stroop test, along with 
differences between congruent and incongruent trials (inter-
ference index), were the strongest predictors of conversion to 
Alzheimer's disease (AD) (51). Accordingly, deficits in the 
Stroop test could be an incipient symptom of the develop-
ment of pathological states that are not exclusively related to 
cognitive aging and deserve other follow-up. 
According to our results, signs of neuronal loss were 
more frequent in the frontal lobe in both clusters but could 
also be observed in the left temporal lobe. Other authors 
showed greater gray matter loss in the hippocampus and 
hippocampal structures and less loss in the posterior 
cingulate cortex, inferior temporal gyrus and middle fusi-
form gyrus, precuneus, tempoparietal junction, and frontal 
cortex in the pre-clinical stages of dementia, which diverges 
from the results in our study group and seems to place them 
at a higher risk for dementia (38). 
In general, different authors have linked memory decline 
with hippocampal volume loss in elderly individuals 
(5,30,40,49,50). However, our results did not reveal such a 
correlation, probably because this series was restricted to 
healthy elderly participants, which may not be representative 
of the normal aging group as a whole. Moreover, it was not 
possible to compare these results with population normative 
data that could explain the lack of significant differences 
between groups in measures of memory. Indeed, it must be 
considered that the assessment of cognitive decline was 
beyond the scope of this work because it was not a 
longitudinal study. 
In conclusion, our data allow the inference that the 
heterogeneity of normal aging can be expressed functionally 
and structurally, which may explain the overlap between 
normal and pathological groups in studies comparing mild 
cognitive impairment and early dementia. From a functional 
point of view, these results are in accordance with the inhibitory 
control hypotheses regarding cognitive aging. Investigations of 
the normal spectrum of aging are essential for the study of the </p>

<p>CLINICS 2013;68(9):1197-1205 
Spectrum of Normal Aging 
Foss MP et al. </p>



<p>pre-clinical stages of all degenerative processes associated with 
aging and can highlight some biological and neuropsycholo-
gical markers of incipient cases of dementia. </p>

<p>&amp; AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS </p>

<p>Foss MP recruited patients, performed neuropsychological testing, 
conceived and conducted the analyses of neuropsychological assessment 
data, performed statistical analysis, and served as the main author of the 
article. Diniz PR developed the parameters, analyzed the magnetic 
resonance imaging (MRI) data, performed the statistical analysis, generated 
the MRI data, and revised the manuscript. Formighieri PF examined the 
patients for inclusion in the study and reviewed the manuscript. Salmon 
CE created the software to analyze the RMI, contributed to the article, 
performed MRI data analysis, and revised the manuscript. Speciali JG 
served as the post-graduate supervisor of the project and revised the 
manuscript. Santos AC served as the second post-graduate supervisor of 
the project, analyzed the MRI data, and revised the manuscript. </p>

<p>&amp; REFERENCES </p>



<p>Spectrum of Normal Aging 
Foss MP et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2013;68(9):1197-1205 </p>





<p>CLINICS 2013;68(9):1197-1205 
Spectrum of Normal Aging 
Foss MP et al. </p>



</text></tei>