<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3018578" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:42+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Recently, emerging waterborne protozoa, such as microsporidia, Cyclospora, and Cryptosporidium, have become 
a challenge to human health worldwide. Rapid, simple, and economical detection methods for these major waterborne 
protozoa in environmental and clinical samples are necessary to control infection and improve public health. In the pre-
sent study, we developed a multiplex PCR test that is able to detect all these 3 major waterborne protozoa at the same 
time. Detection limits of the multiplex PCR method ranged from 10 
1 to 10 
2 oocysts or spores. The primers for microsporidia 
or Cryptosporidium used in this study can detect both Enterocytozoon bieneusi and Encephalitozoon intestinalis, or both 
Cryptosporidium hominis and Cryptosporidium parvum, respectively. Restriction enzyme digestion of PCR products with 
BsaBI or BsiEI makes it possible to distinguish the 2 species of microsporidia or Cryptosporidium, respectively. This sim-
ple, rapid, and cost-effective multiplex PCR method will be useful for detecting outbreaks or sporadic cases of waterborne 
protozoa infections. </p>

<p>vitro culture using BS-C-1 cells (African green monkey kidney 
cells; Korean Cell Line Bank, Seoul, Korea) following the man-
ufacturer's instructions. Briefly, Eagle's minimum essential me-
dium (Sigma, St. Louis, Missouri, USA) with 2 mM L-gluta-
mine, 1.5 g/L sodium bicarbonate, 0.1 mM non-essential amino 
acid, and 1.0 mM sodium pyruvate supplemented with 3% fetal 
bovine serum (GIBCO, Invitrogen, Carlsbad, California, USA) 
was used for maintenance of infection, and cells were incubat-
ed at 37℃ with 5% CO2. Oocysts of Cryptosporidium parvum 
(KKU isolate) were obtained from laboratory mice (C57BL6/J) 
that were infected and maintained as described [10]. The study 
was approved by the Animal Care and Use Committee of Kon-
kuk University (Seoul, Republic of Korea). 
For DNA extraction from fecal specimens, QIAquick stool 
mini kit (QIAGEN Inc., Valencia, California, USA) was used. 
For E. intestinalis and C. parvum DNA, each number of isolated 
spores or oocysts from 1 × 10 
4 to 1 × 10 
0 were spiked into 
500 mg of uninfected human stool and mixed with 10 ml dis-
tilled water (DW). After washing with DW twice by centrifuga-
tion at 100 g, pellets were resuspended in ASL lysis buffer includ-
ed in the kit. The samples were incubated at 70℃ for 30 min. 
The procedure was executed in accordance with the manufac-
turer's recommendations. The extracted DNA was used as a 
template for PCR. DNA of Cyclospora cayetanensis was extracted 
from the stool of an infected patient who was the subject of a 
published case study in 2003 [11]. We cloned the 18S rRNA gene 
of Cyclospora using pGEM-T easy vector (Promega, Madison, 
Wisconsin, USA) and used it as a template DNA after diluted it 
equivalent to each number of parasite. 
All of the PCR primers used in this study were designed using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Primer-BLAST</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</rs>) and are shown 
in Table 1. The first-round multiplex PCR amplification was </p>

<p>performed in a 70-ml volume containing 5 ml of template DNA, 
10 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.3), 2 mM MgCl2, 200 mM each of dATP, 
dCTP, dGTP, and dTTP, 0.7-1 mM of each primer (0.7 mM for 
microsporidia and 1 mM for Cyclospora and Cryptosporidium), 
and 5 U Taq DNA polymerase (Promega). The second-round 
multiplex PCR amplification was performed under the same 
conditions, except 2 ml of template DNA (product of the first-
round PCR) was used in a 30-ml final volume. Both amplifica-
tions were performed using a C-1000 DNA thermal cycler (Bio-
Rad, Hercules, California, USA) with initial denaturation at 94 
℃ for 5 min, followed by 35 cycles at 94℃ for 30 sec, 53℃ 
for 30 sec, and 72℃ for 90 sec and a final extension at 72℃ 
for 10 min. The second-round PCR cycling conditions were 
identical to the first-round PCR except for the annealing tem-
perature (55℃). Amplified DNA was analyzed by electrophore-
sis in a 2% (w/v) agarose gel stained with ethidium bromide 
(0.5 mg/ml) and visualized under ImageQuant300 (GE Health-
care, Giles, UK). 
An aliquot (5 ml) of the second-round PCR product of E. in-
testinalsis or C. parvum was used for enzyme digestion with BsaBI 
or BsiEI (New England BioLabs, Massachusetts, USA) at 60℃ 
for 2 hr. DNA fragments were analyzed by electrophoresis in a 
2% (w/v) agarose gel as described above. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>From the first-round PCR amplification, we obtained the fol-
lowing products with the predicted sizes: 644-657 bp, 636 bp, 
and 415-427 bp for microsporidia, C. cayetanensis, and Cryp-
tosporidium, respectively (data not shown). From the second-
round PCR, the following predicted PCR products were ampli-
fied: 410-420 bp, 294 bp, and 171-183 bp for microsporidia, </p>

<p>298 Korean J Parasitol. Vol. 48, No. 4: 297-301, December 2010 </p>

<p>Parasite 
PCR 
Primer name 
Sequence 
PCR product size </p>

<p>Microsporidia 
1st 
Mic A 
5′ -GGAGCCTGAGAGATGGCT-3′ 
644-657 bp 
Mic E 
5′ -AACGGCCATGCACCAC-3′ 
2nd 
Mic C 
5′ -GGTGCCAGCAGCCGCGG-3′ 
410-420 bp 
Mic D 
5′ -GCACAATCCACTCCT-3′ 
Cyclospora cayetanensis 
1st 
CYCF1E 
5′ -TACCCAATGAAAACAGTTT-3′ 
636 bp 
CYCR2B 
5′ -CAGGAGAAGCCAAGGTAGG-3′ 
2nd 
CYCF3E 
5′ -CCTTCCGCGCTTCGCTGCGT-3′ 
294 bp 
CYCR4B 
5′ -CGTCTTCAAACCCCCTACTG-3′ 
Cryptosporidium spp. 
1st 
cp2415F 
5′ -CCCACGCGAAGTTGAAGTAAC-3′ 
415-427 bp 
cp2415R 
5′ -CTTAGGTTGCTTGCTTGGAGTTGG-3′ 
2nd 
cp2171F 
5′ -CAACCCAGAAGTTGAGGTT-3′ 
171-183 bp 
cp2171R 
5′ -CTAGTATGCTTCAGACCATGAG-3′ </p>

<p>Table 1. Primer sets used for multiplex PCR </p>

<p>C. cayetanensis, and Cryptosporidium, respectively (Fig. 1). The 
lower detection limit of nested PCR amplification that was per-
formed with template DNA from each individual protozoa was 
10 
2 spores for microsporidia, 10 
0 oocysts for Cyclospora, and 10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>oocysts for Cryptosporidium (Fig. 1). The lower detection limit 
of multiplex PCR amplification that was performed with mixed 
DNA from each protozoan was 10 
2 for microsporidia and Cyclo-
spora and 10 
1 for Cryptosporidium (Fig. 2). 
The primers for microsporidia and Cryptosporidium used in 
the present study are capable of detecting both E. bieneusi and 
E. intestinalis, and C. parvum and C. hominis, respectively. Restric-
tion enzyme digestion of the resulting nested PCR products can 
distinguish the 2 kinds of microsporidia and Cryptosporidium 
spp. Restriction enzyme digestion with BsaBI showed 2 frag-</p>

<p>mented bands of 167 and 253 bp in E. intestinalis (Fig. 3A), 
and with BsiEI showed no fragmented bands in C. parvum (Fig. 
3B). Whereas it was confirmed with <rs id="software-2" type="software">Clone Manager</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version">6</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Sci-Ed</rs>, 
North Carolina, USA) that there will be no fragmented bands 
in E. bieneusi with BsaBI digestion and 2 fragmented bands of 
48 and 137 bp in C. hominis with BsiEI digestion. Each primer 
set for microsporidia, C. cayetanensis, and Cryptosporidium used 
in the present study showed no cross-reactivity with each of the 
other parasite DNA (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>There are various detection methods currently available for 
microsporidia, Cyclospora, and Cryptosporidium. These include </p>

<p>Lee et al.: Multiplex PCR for waterborne protozoa 299 </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>420 bp </p>

<p>294 bp </p>

<p>171 bp </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>M 
1 0 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Sensitivity of nested PCR primer sets for microsporidia (A), 
Cyclospora cayetanensis (B), and Cryptosporidium (C). M, DNA 
marker; N, negative control (DW). </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Sensitivity of multiplex nested PCR for microsporidia, Cyclo-
spora cayetanensis, and Cryptosporidium. Serially diluted template 
DNA from each type of protozoan was mixed, and 3 kinds of primer 
sets for each type were included in 1 reaction tube. M, DNA mark-
er; N, negative control (DW). </p>

<p>420 bp </p>

<p>M 
1 0 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>294 bp </p>

<p>171 bp </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Restriction enzyme digestion of nested PCR products of mi-
crosporidia digested with BsaBI (A) and Cryptosporidium parvum 
digested with BsiEI (B). M, DNA marker; Ei, E. intestinalis; Cp, C. 
parvum. </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>253 bp 
167 bp 
171 bp </p>

<p>Ei 
M 
Cp </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>morphological examination after specific staining, fluorescence 
microscopy after specific antibody labeling, and molecular diag-
nosis with such methods as PCR [2,12,13]. Although it is inex-
pensive and fast, the classical staining method depends on high-
ly trained experts for accurate diagnosis. Immunofluorescence-
based antibody-labeling methods depend on the sensitivity 
and specificity of antibodies against parasites for the accurate 
diagnosis, and cross-reactivity or nonspecific labeling can be a 
challenge. Multiplex PCR would eliminate the need for a high-
ly trained expert and would reduce the diagnostic time by being 
able to catch 3 kinds of protozoa at the same time. If well-de-
signed multiplex PCR having a high sensitivity and specificity 
is available, it would be an excellent diagnostic method for these 
waterborne protozoa. 
The primers used for Cyclospora in this study were designed 
by Relman et al. [14]. Orlandi and Lampel [9] reported a sensi-
tivity level for Cyclospora that was as low as 3 oocysts using nest-
ed PCR with the same primer set, which is similar to the level 
of sensitivity in our study. In addition, Orlandi and Lampel [9]  described a detection sensitivity of C. parvum and E. intestinalis 
of as few as 10 oocysts from singleplex PCRs with each parasite 
DNA [9]. Their detection sensitivity for E. intestinalis is 10-fold 
higher than our results; however, they did not report the sensi-
tivity of multiplex PCR using mixed DNA of each protozoan. 
Furthermore, agarose gel electrophoresis analysis of PCR prod-
ucts from both the first and second rounds of PCR is necessary 
to confirm the detection results with the method described by 
Olandi and Lampel [9], because that method amplified the C. </p>

<p>parvum target only during the first round of PCR. 
Generally the sensitivity of multiplex PCR is not exactly the 
same with individual PCR done with each parasite DNA. Multi-
plex PCR developed in the present study showed the same detec-
tion sensitivity with that of individual PCR in case of micro-
sporidia and Cryptosporidium. Agarose gel electrophoresis of the 
second-round PCR products could provide all of the detection 
results, when the multiplex PCR tests reported here were applied. 
Another advantage of the multiplex PCR test developed in 
the present study is that the 2 species of microsporidia, such as 
E. bieneusi and E. intestinalis, and the 2 species of Cryptosporidium, 
such as C. parvum and C. hominis, can be differentiated after 
PCR by restriction enzyme digestion. We did not show restric-
tion enzyme-digested PCR products of E. bieneusi and C. hominis 
in the present study as we did not secure DNAs of these 2 organ-
isms. Instead, we confirmed the results of restriction enzyme 
digestion of these 2 organisms after PCR using a restriction enzy-
me cutting software program (<rs id="software-3" type="software">Clone Manager</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version">6</rs>). 
Although there is a well-established genomic database for 
Cryptosporidium (http://cryptodb.org) that was established thro-
ugh the efforts of many devoted and excellent scientists, there 
are still only limited genomic data available for Cyclospora and 
microsporidia. Therefore it is quite difficult to develop specific 
primers for these 2 protozoa. The difficulty is especially chal-
lenging for Cyclospora because PCR detection of the 18S rRNA 
gene could be confused with that of Eimeria spp., which show 
98% similarity with the 18S rRNA gene sequence of Cyclospora. 
Thus sequence analysis after multiplex PCR should be perform-
ed for the accurate differential diagnosis of Cyclospora and Eime-
ria spp. 
In conclusion, the multiplex PCR test developed in the pre-
sent study can detect microsporidia, Cyclospora, and Cryptospori-
dium, all of which cause severe waterborne diarrheal disease. 
The test is very simple and rapid and offers high sensitivity and 
specificity. This test could help improve detection of diarrheal 
outbreaks or sporadic diarrheal disease that is due to infection 
with these major waterborne protozoa which have been con-
sidered as unknown etiology for the difficulty in detection pre-
viously. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This research was supported by the Basic Science Research 
Program through the National Research Foundation of Korea 
(RF) funded by the Ministry of Education, Science, and Tech-</p>



<p>M 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>600 bp </p>

<p>DNA of Encephalitozoon intesinalis 
+ 
-
-
-</p>

<p>DNA of Cyclospora cayetanensis 
-
+ 
-
-</p>

<p>DNA of Cryptosporidium parvum 
-
-
+ 
-
Primers for E. intestinalis 
-
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>Primers for C. cayetanensis 
+ 
-
+ 
+ </p>

<p>Primers for C. parvum 
+ 
+ 
-
+ </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Specificity of multiplex nested PCR primers. No cross-react-
ed PCR bands were detected when the 3 primer sets were paired 
with DNA from the different protozoa. Lane 4, negative control (DW). </p>

<p>nology (2010-0017321). </p>



<p>Lee et al.: Multiplex PCR for waterborne protozoa 301 </p>

</text></tei>