<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3797259" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:37+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Fludarabine-based regimens and CHOP (doxorubicin, cyclophosphamide, vincristine, 
prednisone)-like regimens with or without rituximab are the most common treatment modalities 
for indolent lymphoma. However, there is no clear evidence to date about which chemotherapy 
regimen should be the proper initial treatment of indolent lymphoma. More recently, the use of 
fludarabine has raised concerns due to its high number of toxicities, especially hematological 
toxicity and infectious complications. The present study aimed to retrospectively evaluate both the 
efficacy and the potential toxicities of the two main regimens (fludarabine-based and CHOP-like 
regimens) in patients with previously untreated indolent lymphoma. Among a total of 107 patients 
assessed, 54 patients received fludarabine-based regimens (FLU arm) and 53 received CHOP or 
CHOPE (doxorubicin, cyclophosphamide, vincristine, prednisone, or plus etoposide) regimens 
(CHOP arm). The results demonstrated that fludarabine-based regimens could induce significantly 
improved progression-free survival (PFS) compared with CHOP-like regimens. However, the 
FLU arm showed overall survival, complete response, and overall response rates similar to those 
of the CHOP arm. Grade 3-4 neutropenia occurred in 42.6% of the FLU arm and 7.5% of the 
CHOP arm (P , 0.000). Moreover, the FLU arm also had a higher occurrence of infection than 
the CHOP arm (27.8% vs 8.5%; P = 0.034). Multi-factor regression of infection revealed that 
only age (.60 years) and presentation of grade 3-4 myelosuppression were the independent 
factors to infection, and the FLU arm had significantly higher myelosuppression. In conclusion, 
the present study revealed that the use of fludarabine-based regimens could induce high rates of 
myelosuppression over CHOP-like regimens, in spite of significant increases in PFS. 
Per World Health Organization (WHO), indolent lymphomas account for nearly one-
third of non-Hodgkin lymphoma (NHL). These mainly include follicular lymphoma 
(FL), small lymphocytic lymphoma/chronic lymphocytic leukemia (SCL/CLL), and 
marginal zone B-cell lymphoma. 
1 Their natural history is characterized by a high initial 
response rate to both chemotherapy and radiotherapy, often with transformation to a 
more aggressive histology, and followed invariably by disease recurrence. Finally, the 
patients usually die due to disease progression or treatment-induced toxicity. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Addition of rituximab to chemotherapy is associated with higher response, 
progression-free survival (PFS), and overall survival (OS) rates; 
3-5 but there is no clear 
evidence about which chemotherapy regimen should be the proper initial treatment </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
7 October 2013 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>Table 1 Dosage information and time schedule of chemotherapy regimens </p>

<p>Arms 
Regimen 
Drug 
Dose 
Route 
Days </p>

<p>chOP arm (every 21 days) 
chOP* 
Doxorubicin 
cyclophosphamide 
Vincristine 
Prednisone </p>

<p>50 mg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>750 mg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1.4 mg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>100 mg/d </p>

<p>iV 
iV 
iV 
PO </p>

<p>1 
1 
1 
1-5 
chOPe* 
Doxorubicin 
cyclophosphamide 
Vincristine 
Prednisone 
etoposide </p>

<p>50 mg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>750 mg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1.4 mg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>100 mg/d 
100 mg/d </p>

<p>iV 
iV 
iV 
PO 
iV </p>

<p>1 
1 
1 
1-5 
3-5 
FlU arm (every 28 days) 
Fc* 
Fludarabine 
cyclophosphamide </p>

<p>25 mg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>250 mg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>iV 
iV </p>

<p>1-3 
1-3 
FnD* 
Fludarabine 
Mitoxantrone 
Dexamethasone </p>

<p>25 mg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 mg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>20 mg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>iV 
iV 
PO </p>

<p>1-3 
1 
1-5 </p>

<p>Notes: *With or without rituximab 375 mg/m 
2 as an iV infusion on day 0. The chOP arm consisted of "chOP" (doxorubicin, cyclophosphamide, vincristine, and prednisone), 
or "CHOPE" (CHOP plus etoposide). The FLU arm consisted of "FC" (fludarabine plus cyclophosphamide), or "FND" (fludarabine, mitoxantrone, and dexamethasone). 
Abbreviations: iV, intravenous; PO, oral. </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1386 </p>

<p>Xu et al </p>

<p>of indolent lymphoma. In the late 1980s, the approval of 
nucleoside analogs such as fludarabine for the treatment 
of low-grade lymphomas brought significantly increased 
outcomes, 
6-9 but the benefit with regards to PFS and OS 
is still under debate, as few trials compared the efficacy 
of a fludarabine-based regimen with the classical CHOP 
(doxorubicin, cyclophosphamide, vincristine, prednisone) 
regimen for NHL. 
10-13 More recently, the use of fludarabine 
has also raised concerns due to its high toxicities, especially 
hematological toxicity and infectious complications. </p>

<p>14,15 </p>

<p>The present study aimed to evaluate retrospectively both the 
efficacy and the potential toxicities of the two main regimens 
(fludarabine-based and CHOP-like regimens) in patients with 
previously untreated indolent lymphoma. </p>

<p>Methods 
Patients and criteria for eligibility </p>

<p>Data from patients with previously untreated indolent 
lymphoma (n = 107) were retrospectively included in 
the study. All these patients received chemotherapy 
consecutively at the Tianjin Medical University Cancer 
Institute and Hospital and the First Affiliated Hospital of 
Chinese PLA General Hospital between January 2007 and 
August 2012. All patients underwent the following routine 
staging procedures: complete physical examination; labora-
tory tests, including serum lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) 
and serum beta-2 microglobulin; type-B ultrasonic check; 
computed tomography (CT) scan of the chest, abdomen, and 
pelvis (or positron emission tomography-CT); bone marrow 
aspiration; and biopsy. Their disease condition was diagnosed 
by biopsy and immunophenotypical analysis per the WHO </p>

<p>criteria for indolent lymphoma, 
16 and the Ann Arbor staging 
system was used to define the stage of lymphoma. 
17 No 
patients had severe damage to their heart, liver, kidney, or 
other important organs; and the mean neutrophil count at 
baseline was .3.0 × 10 
9 /L. </p>

<p>Treatment schedule </p>

<p>Patients received four to eight cycles of chemotherapy, 
either with CHOP-like or fludarabine-based regimens with 
or without rituximab. The treatment protocol and schedule 
followed the recommendations laid down by the National 
Comprehensive Cancer Network, USA. Dosage informa-
tion and drug administration schedule are listed in Table 1. 
Additionally, patients with stage I-II cancer received 
radiotherapy. Also, the granulocyte colony-stimulating 
factor was administered only to patients who had more 
advanced grades of neutropenia (grade 3-4). However, 
no patients received any antibiotic prophylaxis. Response 
to therapy was assessed at the end of every two cycles of 
chemotherapy. </p>

<p>safety analysis </p>

<p>Patient-and physician-reported adverse events were recorded 
per the Common Toxicity Criteria (version 2.0) of National 
Cancer Institute, USA for all cycles of chemotherapy. 
Hematotoxicity was assessed for treatment-specific nadir 
windows per the WHO grades for hematotoxicity. </p>

<p>statistical methods </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">17.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). Survival curves were calculated </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>Table 2 Patient demographic and clinical characteristics by 
treatment arm </p>

<p>Characteristics No of assessable patients Two-sided 
P-value </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CHOP arm 
n = 53 
[n (%)] </p>

<p>FLU arm 
n = 54 
[n (%)] </p>

<p>sex 
0.390 
0.740 
Male 
Female </p>

<p>28 (47.5) 
31 (52.5) </p>

<p>30 (55.6) 
24 (44.4) 
age (years) 
0.816 
0.054 
#60 
.60 
Mean (range) </p>

<p>37 (62.7) 
22 (37.3) 
53 (18-80) </p>

<p>35 (64.8) 
19 (35.2) 
53 (20-79) 
ann arbor 
staging </p>

<p>0.209 
1.577 </p>

<p>i-ii 
iii-iV </p>

<p>31 (52.5) 
28 (47.4) </p>

<p>22 (40.8) 
32 (59.2) 
B-symptoms 
0.610 
0.260 
no 
Yes </p>

<p>43 (72.9) 
16 (27.1) </p>

<p>37 (68.5) 
17 (31.5) 
exnodal 
involvement </p>

<p>0.707 
0.141 </p>

<p>Present 
absent </p>

<p>37 (62.7) 
22 (37.3) </p>

<p>32 (59.3) 
22 (40.7) 
serum lDh level 
0.089 
2.887 
normal 
abnormal </p>

<p>36 (61.0) 
23 (39.0) </p>

<p>41 (75.9) 
13 (24.1) 
ecOg 
performance 
status </p>

<p>0.871 
0.026 </p>

<p>#1 
$2 </p>

<p>53 (89.8) 
6 (10.29) </p>

<p>48 (88.9) 
6 (11.1) 
histological 
subtype </p>

<p>0.092 
4.774 </p>

<p>Fl 
cll/sll 
MalT </p>

<p>20 (33.9) 
14 (23.7) 
25 (42.4) </p>

<p>18 (33.3) 
22 (40.7) 
14 (25.9) 
Treatment 
0.209 
1.577 
With r 
Without r </p>

<p>31 (52.5) 
28 (47.5) </p>

<p>22 (40.7) 
32 (59.3) </p>

<p>Notes: The chOP arm consisted of "chOP" (doxorubicin, cyclophosphamide, 
vincristine, and prednisone), or "chOPe" (chOP plus etoposide). The FlU arm 
consisted of "FC" (fludarabine plus cyclophosphamide), or "FND" (fludarabine, 
mitoxantrone, and dexamethasone). 
Abbreviations: lDh, lactate dehydrogenase; Fl, follicular lymphoma; cll/ 
sll, chronic lymphocytic lymphoma/small lymphocytic leukemia; MalT, mucosa-
associated lymphoid tissue lymphoma; ecOg, eastern cooperative Oncology 
group; r, rituximab. </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1387 </p>

<p>Fludarabine versus chOP in indolent lymphoma </p>

<p>using Kaplan-Meier estimates, and statistical comparisons 
between curves were made using the log-rank test. The chi-
square test and Fisher's exact text were used to compare 
variables. Two-sided P-values were used throughout. 
Variables associated with myelosuppression and infec-
tion in cases and controls were com pared using odds ratios 
and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) from univariate logistic 
regression models. Multivariable logistic regression was 
performed; the covariates identified in the univariate analy-
sis were used to adjust the multivariate logistic regression 
model. </p>

<p>Results 
Patient characteristics </p>

<p>Of the 107 patients, the condition of 37 patients was 
diagnosed as FL, 33 had SLL/CLL, and 37 had mucosa-
associated lymphoid tissue lymphoma. The two treatment 
groups were comparable in terms of age, sex distribution, 
stage, extra-nodal site involvement, B symptoms (fever, 
weight loss, or night sweats), performance status, serum 
LDH levels, histological subtype, and combination of 
rituximab (Table 2). Patients with stage I and II disease 
accounted for nearly 50% of the study population, which 
was higher than previous reports. This distribution could 
mainly be attributed to the presence of B symptoms, pres-
ence of progressive bulky disease (especially superficial 
lymph nodes), and patients' desire to receive treatment. </p>

<p>response and survival analysis </p>

<p>At the end of induction, the FLU arm had a similar com-
plete response (CR) rate (68.5% vs 67.9%; P = 0.947) but 
a higher overall response rate (ORR) (96.3% vs 86.8%; 
P = 0.093) than the CHOP arm. After median follow-up 
of 26 months (range 2-66 months), overall 3-year PFS 
and 3-year OS were 68.0% and 78.8%, respectively 
(Figure 1). The FLU arm had a significantly better 3-year 
PFS (75.8% vs 61.0%; P = 0.011), but no differences were 
observed in the 3-year OS between the two arms (82.1% vs 
74.8%; P = 0.209). </p>

<p>safety evaluation </p>

<p>The most common adverse effects are hematologic toxicity 
and infection. Safety data were available for all 107 patients 
for a median follow-up of 25 months (range 7-66 months). No 
instance of grade 3-4 anemia or thrombocytopenia was evalu-
ated, but significant difference in neutropenia was observed 
between the two treatment arms. Frequency of grade 3-4 neu-
tropenia in the FLU arm was much larger than that in CHOP </p>

<p>arm (42.6% [23 in 54] vs 7.5% [4 in 53]; P , 0.001). Patients 
in the FLU arm had an increased rate of infections (15 in 54 
patients [27.8%] vs 3 in 53 patients [5.7%]; P = 0.002). 
In univariate regression analysis, the following variables 
were found to be significantly associated with infection: 
age over 60 years, III-IV Ann Arbor staging, presence of 
grade 3-4 myelosuppression, and combination of rituximab 
(Table 3). More myelosuppression occurred in patients 
receiving the fludarabine-based regimen and patients with 
B symptoms than in those who received the CHOP-like </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1388 </p>

<p>Xu et al </p>

<p>chemotherapy (Table 4). Multi-factor regression was used 
to find the potential predictive factors of infection and 
myelosuppression. Factors identified in the multivariable 
logistic regression as being independently associated with 
infection included the following: age over 60 years and 
presence of grade 3-4 myelosuppression (Table 3). In the 
multivariable logistic regression analysis, patients who 
received a fludarabine-based regimen and patients with 
B symptoms had variables significantly related to myelosup-
pression (Table 4). 
During the follow-up, two secondary malignancies were 
reported in the FLU arm: one myelodysplastic syndrome and 
one meningioma. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The results of the present study demonstrated that the 
fludarabine-based regimen could induce significantly improved 
PFS compared with the CHOP-like regimen in patients with 
previously untreated indolent lymphoma. However, the FLU 
arm showed similar rates of OS, CR, and ORR rates as the 
CHOP arm. In spite of the improved PFS, the FLU arm was 
associated with a higher incidence of hematological toxicity, 
infections, and late events than the CHOP arm. 
Potential risk of toxicities is one of the major concerns 
with the concurrent use of purine analogs, even though they 
possess superior response or survival rates. It was found that 
the myelosuppression was mainly presented as neutropenia. 
No instance of grade 3-4 anemia or thrombocytopenia was 
recorded among the two treatment arms. In terms of neutrope-
nia, the findings were comparable to those of the randomized </p>

<p>FOLL05 trial comparing rituximab, cyclophosphamide, 
vincristine, and prednisolone (R-CVP), rituximab plus 
CHOP (R-CHOP), and rituximab plus fludarabine, and 
mitoxantrone for the initial treatment of advanced-stage 
FL. 
13 However, Zinzani et al 
10 and Leporrier et al 
12 reported 
no difference in hematologic toxicity between the various 
treatment groups. 
10,12 These differences could partly result 
from the different treatment regimens, histological subtypes, 
and patient characteristics. Karmali et al 
18 hinted that the bone 
marrow involvement at presentation could also influence the 
pathogenesis of prolonged cytopenia in follicular or marginal 
zone lymphoma with rituximab, fludarabine, mitoxantrone, 
dexamethasone (R-FND) followed by radioimmunotherapy 
consolidation, but the researchers did not give any detailed 
evidence. In the present study, the multi-factor regression 
showed no correlation between bone marrow involvement 
and myelosuppression, although the bone marrow involve-
ment was higher in the FLU arm than the CHOP arm (19/54 
[35.2%] vs 6/53 [11.9%]; P = 0.004). 
Another variable associated with myelosuppression 
was the presence of B symptoms, which was in accordance 
with the outcomes by Sharma et al. 
19 B symptoms were 
regarded as the independent predictors of myelosuppres-
sion from chemotherapy in patients with NHL. The cor-
relation between disease stage and myelosuppression in 
univariate analysis has been reported previously, although 
the staging was not identified as an independent factor to 
myelosuppression in the multivariate regression. 
19,20 Such 
association was not identified in the present study. Potential 
reasons for these differences could be related to the sup-
portive care practices or heterogeneity in chemotherapy. 
In addition, a small sample size could have some influence 
on the results. 
The occurrence of infection was significantly higher 
in the FLU arm than in the CHOP arm. The predictors of 
infection during fludarabine-based chemotherapy included 
the following: .60 years of age, low serum immunoglobulin 
G, previous fludarabine exposure, .3 years from diagnosis 
to treatment, performance score of $2, and baseline neutro-
phil count of ,2.0 × 10 
9 /L. 
21,22 In the present study, logistic 
regression showed that both the presentation of myelosup-
pression and age (.60 years) were independent factors to 
infection. This indicated that the proper control of myelo-
suppression could benefit patients by avoiding unwanted 
adverse events. 
The addition of rituximab to standard chemotherapy 
in patients with cluster of differentiation (CD)-20 positive 
malignant lymphomas could increase the frequency of </p>

<p>70 
60 
50 
40 </p>

<p>Time (months) </p>

<p>Survival (%) </p>

<p>30 
20 
10 
0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Overall survival </p>

<p>Progession-free survival </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Figure 1 The overall survival and progression-free survival of 107 patients with 
indolent lymphoma. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1389 </p>

<p>Fludarabine versus chOP in indolent lymphoma </p>

<p>myelosuppression and infectious complications. 
5,23,24 A meta-
analysis conducted on the risk of infection with lymphoma 
with or without rituximab concluded that the addition of 
rituximab to standard chemotherapy could increase the 
risk of severe leukopenia (relative risk [RR] = 1.24; 95% 
CI 1.12-1.37) and granulocytopenia (RR = 1.07; 95% CI 
1.02-1.12), but no increase in the overall risk of severe 
infections (RR = 1.00; 95% CI 0.87-1.14) was reported. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>No association between combination of rituximab and 
infection was observed in this study. 
It is unknown whether or not prophylaxis is needed to 
avoid side effects. However, no difference in safety profile 
was reported between the patients who had received early pro-
phylaxis (including antibiotics, immunoglobulin, and low-dose 
interleukin-2) and patients without these prophylactics. </p>

<p>6,26,27 </p>

<p>Nevertheless, the addition of granulocyte colony-stimulating </p>

<p>Table 3 association between potential predictive factors and infection </p>

<p>Observation 
Infection 
Univariate 
logistic analysis </p>

<p>Forward stepwise 
logistic analysis </p>

<p>n 
n (%) 
OR (95% CI) 
P-value 
OR (95% CI) 
P-value </p>

<p>age (years) 
0.176 (0.037-0.847) 
0.030 
0.205 (0.059-0.719) 
0.013 
#60 
.60 </p>

<p>35 
72 </p>

<p>7 (9.7) 
11 (31.4) 
sex 
1.041 (0.223-4.866) 
0.959 
Male 
Female </p>

<p>57 
50 </p>

<p>10 (17.5) 
8 (16) 
ann arbor-cotswolds staging 
13.762 (1.428-132.665) 
0.023 
i-ii 
iii-iV </p>

<p>52 
55 </p>

<p>8 (15.4) 
10 (18.2) 
grade 3-4 myelosuppression 
0.055 (0.009-0.339) 
0.002 
0.066 (0.019-0.233) 
,0.001 
Present 
absent </p>

<p>80 
27 </p>

<p>5 (6.3) 
13 (48.1) 
Bone marrow involvement 
0.235 (0.018-3.086) 
0.270 
Yes 
no </p>

<p>82 
25 </p>

<p>7 (28.0) 
11 (13.4) 
B-symptoms 
0.759 (0.143-4.013) 
0.745 
no 
Yes </p>

<p>80 
27 </p>

<p>10 (12.5) 
8 (29.6) 
exnodal involvement 
1.456 (0.197-10.776) 
0.713 
Present 
absent </p>

<p>66 
41 </p>

<p>11 (16.7) 
7 (17.1) 
serum lDh level 
0.241 (0.38-1.518) 
0.129 
normal 
abnormal </p>

<p>77 
30 </p>

<p>10 (13.3) 
8 (25.0) 
Performance status (ecOg) 
0.268 (0.37-1.943) 
0.193 
#1 
$2 </p>

<p>96 
11 </p>

<p>14 (14.6) 
4 (36.4) 
histological subtype 
Fl 
cll/sll 
MalT </p>

<p>37 
33 
37 </p>

<p>7 (18.9) 
6 (18.2) 
5 (13.5) </p>

<p>2.364 (0.215-26.004) 
3.016 (0.353-25.785) </p>

<p>0.605 </p>

<p>Treatment 
0.199 (0.043-0.932) 
0.040 
With r 
Without r </p>

<p>50 
57 </p>

<p>11 (22.0) 
7 (12.3) 
regimen* 
0.195 (0.027-1.428) 
0.108 
FlU arm 
chOP arm </p>

<p>54 
53 </p>

<p>15 (27.8) 
3 (5.7) 
cycles of chemotherapy 
1.228 (0.219-6.891) 
0.816 
#4 
.4 </p>

<p>49 
58 </p>

<p>8 (16.3) 
10 (17.2) </p>

<p>Notes: *combined with or without rituximab. The chOP arm consisted of "chOP" (doxorubicin, cyclophosphamide, vincristine, and prednisone), or "chOPe" (chOP 
plus etoposide). The FLU arm consisted of "FC" (fludarabine plus cyclophosphamide), or "FND" (fludarabine, mitoxantrone, and dexamethasone). 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; CLL/SLL, chronic lymphocytic lymphoma/small lymphocytic leukemia; ECOG, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group; FL, follicular 
lymphoma; lDh, lactate dehydrogenase; MalT, mucosa-associated lymphoid tissue lymphoma; Or, odds ratio; r, rituximab. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1390 </p>

<p>Xu et al </p>

<p>factor during chemotherapy was reported to have beneficial 
effects on infection-related morbidity and mortality. 
28,29 Further 
multicenter prospective studies with large sample sizes are rec-
ommended to understand the safety profile of these regimens 
and to achieve desired efficacy outcomes. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Fludarabine-based regimens improve PFS in patients with 
previously untreated indolent lymphoma to a greater extent 
than that of a CHOP-like regimen. However, the use of </p>

<p>fludarabine induces myelosuppression and contributes to 
a higher degree of infection. Based on the safety analysis, 
it can be concluded that a CHOP-like regimen has a better 
therapeutic index with fewer adverse effects. Being a ret-
rospective study with a very small sample size, the authors 
recommend further prospective studies to evaluate a proper 
front-line treatment for indolent lymphoma. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>

<p>Table 4 association between potential predictive factors and myelosuppression </p>

<p>Observation 
Grade 3-4 
myelosuppression </p>

<p>Univariate 
logistic analysis </p>

<p>Forward stepwise 
logistic analysis </p>

<p>n 
n (%) 
OR (95% CI) 
P-value 
OR (95% CI) 
P-value </p>

<p>age (years) 
#60 
.60 </p>

<p>72 
35 </p>

<p>16 (22.2) 
11 (31.4) </p>

<p>0.689 (0.206-2.303) 
0.545 </p>

<p>sex 
Male 
Female </p>

<p>57 
50 </p>

<p>15 (26.3) 
12 (24.0) </p>

<p>1.250 (0.391-3.996) 
0.707 </p>

<p>ann arbor-cotswolds staging 
i-ii 
iii-iV </p>

<p>52 
55 </p>

<p>8 (15.4) 
19 (34.5) </p>

<p>0.723 (0.175-2.983) 
0.654 </p>

<p>Bone marrow involvement 
Yes 
no </p>

<p>82 
25 </p>

<p>16 (19.5) 
11 (44.0) </p>

<p>0.965 (0.147-6.316) 
0.970 </p>

<p>B-symptoms 
no 
Yes </p>

<p>80 
27 </p>

<p>15 (18.8) 
12 (44.4) </p>

<p>0.289 (0.081-1.037) 
0.057 
0.298 (0.102-0.870) 
0.027 </p>

<p>exnodal involvement 
Present 
absent </p>

<p>41 
66 </p>

<p>10 (24.4) 
17 (25.8) </p>

<p>0.619 (0.113-3.387) 
0.619 </p>

<p>serum lDh level 
normal 
abnormal </p>

<p>75 
32 </p>

<p>18 (24.0) 
9 (28.1) </p>

<p>1.207 (0.311-4.686) 
1.207 </p>

<p>Performance status (ecOg) 
#1 
$2 </p>

<p>96 
11 </p>

<p>23 (24.0) 
4 (36.4) </p>

<p>1.606 (0.219-11.771) 
0.641 </p>

<p>histological subtype 
Fl 
cll/sll 
MalT </p>

<p>37 
33 
37 </p>

<p>12 (32.4) 
7 (21.2) 
8 (21.6) </p>

<p>1.770 (0.344-9.102) 
0.397 (0.081-1.941) </p>

<p>0.178 </p>

<p>Treatment 
With r 
Without r </p>

<p>57 
50 </p>

<p>13 (22.8) 
14 (28.0) </p>

<p>0.522 (0.170-1.604) 
0.257 </p>

<p>regimen* 
FlU arm 
chOP arm </p>

<p>53 
54 </p>

<p>4 (7.5) 
23 (42.6) </p>

<p>0.073 (0.018-0.302) 
,0.001 
0.098 (0.029-0.334) 
,0.001 </p>

<p>cycles of chemotherapy 
#4 
.4 </p>

<p>49 
58 </p>

<p>9 (18.4) 
18 (31.0) </p>

<p>0.404 (0.118-1.380) 
0.148 
-</p>

<p>Notes: *combined with or without rituximab. The chOP arm consisted of "chOP" (doxorubicin, cyclophosphamide, vincristine, and prednisone), or "chOPe" (chOP 
plus etoposide). The FLU arm consisted of "FC" (fludarabine plus cyclophosphamide), or "FND" (fludarabine, mitoxantrone, and dexamethasone). 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; CLL/SLL, chronic lymphocytic lymphoma/small lymphocytic leukemia; ECOG, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group; FL, follicular 
lymphoma; lDh, lactate dehydrogenase; MalT, mucosa-associated lymphoid tissue lymphoma; Or, odds ratio; r, rituximab. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Fludarabine versus chOP in indolent lymphoma </p>



<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargets-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open access 
journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Xu et al </p>

</text></tei>