<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3386209" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:46+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT How cell cycle machinery regulates extracellular matrix (ECM) remodeling during 
cytokinesis remains poorly understood. In the budding yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae, the 
primary septum (PS), a functional equivalent of animal ECM, is synthesized during cytokinesis 
by the chitin synthase Chs2. Here, we report that Dbf2, a conserved mitotic exit kinase, local-
izes to the division site after Chs2 and directly phosphorylates Chs2 on several residues, includ-
ing Ser-217. Both phosphodeficient (chs2-S217A) and phosphomimic (chs2-S217D) mutations 
cause defects in cytokinesis, suggesting that dynamic phosphorylation-dephosphorylation of 
Ser-217 is critical for Chs2 function. It is striking that Chs2-S217A constricts asymmetrically with 
the actomyosin ring (AMR), whereas Chs2-S217D displays little or no constriction and remains 
highly mobile at the division site. These data suggest that Chs2 phosphorylation by Dbf2 trig-
gers its dissociation from the AMR during the late stage of cytokinesis. Of interest, both 
chs2-S217A and chs2-S217D mutants are robustly suppressed by increased dosage of Cyk3, a 
cytokinesis protein that displays Dbf2-dependent localization and also stimulates Chs2-medi-
ated chitin synthesis. Thus Dbf2 regulates PS formation through at least two independent 
pathways: direct phosphorylation and Cyk3-mediated activation of Chs2. Our study establishes 
a mechanism for direct cell cycle control of ECM remodeling during cytokinesis. </p>

<p>Cytokinesis in animal and fungal cells requires spatiotemporally co-
ordinated functions of a contractile actomyosin ring (AMR) and tar-
geted membrane deposition. The AMR is believed to power the 
ingression of the plasma membrane (PM) at the division site and 
guide membrane deposition (Balasubramanian et al., 2004; Fang 
et al., 2010; Pollard, 2010), whereas membrane deposition is be-</p>

<p>lieved to increase surface area, as well as deliver enzymatic cargoes 
for localized extracellular matrix (ECM) remodeling during cytokine-
sis (Strickland and Burgess, 2004; Barr and Gruneberg, 2007; Fang 
et al., 2010). The core components of the AMR and the mem-
brane-trafficking machine are conserved from yeast to human 
(Balasubramanian et al., 2004; Pollard, 2010). Thus the budding 
yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae has served as an effective model for 
elucidating the general mechanisms of cytokinesis. 
ECM remodeling appears to play a critical role in animal cytokine-
sis, as evidenced by the cytokinesis failure caused by a defect in 
chondroitin synthesis in Caenorhabditis elegans and mice (Mizuguchi 
et al., 2003; Izumikawa et al., 2010). However, it remains unknown 
how ECM is remodeled specifically at the division site and how this 
process is regulated by the cell cycle machinery. In budding yeast, 
the primary septum (PS), a specialized cell wall structure that is syn-
thesized by the chitin synthase Chs2 during cytokinesis (Sburlati and 
Cabib, 1986), is conceptually similar to animal ECM. Deletion of </p>

<p>Monitoring Editor 
Fred Chang 
Columbia University </p>

<p>Received: Jan 17, 2012 
Revised: Apr 20, 2012 
Accepted: May 3, 2012 </p>

<p>This article was published online ahead of print in MBoC in Press (http://www 
.molbiolcell.org/cgi/doi/10.1091/mbc.E12-01-0033) on May 9, 2012. 
Address correspondence to: Erfei Bi (ebi@mail.med.upenn.edu). </p>

<p>© 2012 Oh et al. This article is distributed by The American Society for Cell Biol-
ogy under license from the author(s). Two months after publication it is available 
to the public under an Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported 
Creative Commons License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0). 
"ASCB ® ," "The American Society for Cell Biology ® ," and "Molecular Biology of 
the Cell ® " are registered trademarks of The American Society of Cell Biology. </p>

<p>Abbreviations used: AMR, actomyosin ring; ECM, extracellular matrix; PS, primary 
septum. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>division site during cytokinesis, although their precise timing of ar-
rival has not been determined (Chuang and Schekman, 1996; Frenz 
et al., 2000). Second, Chs2 is essential for PS formation (Sburlati and 
Cabib, 1986; Shaw et al., 1991), whereas Dbf2 has also been impli-
cated in the process (Hwa Lim et al., 2003; Meitinger et al., 2010). 
Finally, deletion analyses and in vitro chitin synthase assays suggest 
that an N-terminal region, especially residues 197-230, of Chs2, 
which is located outside the catalytic domains (con1 and con2), plays 
an ill-defined regulatory role in its activation (Figure 1A; Uchida et al., 
1996), and this region contains two consensus sequences (RXXS) for 
Dbf2 (Mah et al., 2005), with serines 217 and 225 as the potential 
phosphorylation sites (Figure 1A). To determine whether Dbf2 can 
phosphorylate Chs2 directly, we fused the N-terminal region (resi-
dues 1-286) of Chs2 to glutathione S-transferase (GST), and sub-
jected the fusion protein to in vitro kinase assay using recombinant 
Dbf2-Mob1 kinase (Mob1 is the regulatory subunit for Dbf2), which 
was preactivated by Cdc15 (Mah et al., 2001). Chs2 was robustly 
phosphorylated by preactivated Dbf2 but not by Cdc15 alone or its 
combination with an inactive Dbf2 (Figure 1B, left). Change of Ser-
217 to alanine (S217A) decreased the phosphorylation to 73% of the 
wild-type level (Figure 1, B and C). Additional change of Ser-225 to 
alanine (S217A, S225A) further reduced the phosphorylation to 43% 
(Figure 1, B and C). These data indicate that Chs2 is a direct sub-
strate of Dbf2 in vitro and that both Ser-217 and Ser-225 are phos-
phorylated by Dbf2. Of importance, the same two sites were also 
found to be phosphorylated in vivo in studies aimed at global map-
ping of phosphoproteins in budding yeast, but the responsible ki-
nase was not known (Chi et al., 2007; Dephoure and Gygi, 2011). </p>

<p>Chs2 localizes to the division site before Dbf2 
during cytokinesis </p>

<p>To determine when and where Dbf2 might phosphorylate Chs2 dur-
ing cytokinesis, we performed live-cell imaging on cells carrying 
both Chs2-GFP and Dbf2-mCherry. As expected, Chs2 was local-
ized to the mother-bud neck of cells at the onset of cytokinesis (Fig-
ure 1D and Supplemental Video S1; Schmidt et al., 2002; Fang 
et al., 2010). Consistent with a previous observation (Frenz et al., 
2000), Dbf2 was first localized to the spindle pole bodies (Figure 1D, 
arrows) and then translocated to the bud neck during cytokinesis. Of 
importance, we found that the bulk of Dbf2 arrived at the neck 4 min 
after Chs2 (Figure 1D and Supplemental Video S1). Chs2 was gener-
ally removed from the neck region by endocytosis within 10 min af-
ter its arrival, whereas Dbf2 remained at the neck for longer time 
(Figure 1D). On the basis of our previous (Fang et al., 2010; Wloka 
et al., 2011) and present (see Figure 4D later in the paper) studies, 
during the first 4 min of Chs2 localization, the AMR would have 
constricted &gt;50% of its initial size. Thus Dbf2 likely phosphorylates 
Chs2 at the neck region during late stage of cytokinesis. Of interest, 
the bulk accumulation and maintenance of Dbf2 at the neck appear 
to correlate with the onset of Chs2 endocytosis, which is marked by 
the appearance of Chs2-green fluorescent protein (GFP) "puncta" 
near the neck region. </p>

<p>Both phosphorylation and dephosphorylation of Ser-217 
are important for cytokinesis </p>

<p>To determine the functional consequence of Ser-217 and Ser-225 
phosphorylation, C-terminally GFP-tagged, wild-type, phosphode-
ficient (chs2-S217A, chs2-S225A, chs2-AA [S217A S225A]) and 
phosphomimic (chs2-S217D, chs2-S225D, chs2-DD [S217D S225D]) 
alleles of CHS2, expressed from the native CHS2 promoter, were 
integrated onto the chromosome of chs2Δ cells, respectively. None 
of the chs2 phosphomutants displayed obvious defects in cell </p>

<p>CHS2 causes severe defects in cytokinesis, including rapid and asym-
metric AMR constriction, which underscores the importance of ECM 
remodeling during yeast cytokinesis (Bi, 2001; Schmidt et al., 2002; 
VerPlank and Li, 2005). Deletion of MYO1, which encodes the sole 
myosin-II in budding yeast, also causes defects in cytokinesis and cell 
separation, including misoriented PS formation (Fang et al., 2010). 
Thus PS formation and AMR constriction are mutually dependent 
(Bi, 2001; Schmidt et al., 2002; VerPlank and Li, 2005), suggesting 
that these processes are normally coordinated to ensure efficient 
cytokinesis. 
How PS formation is regulated by cell cycle signals remains poorly 
understood. During mitosis, Chs2 is synthesized and held at the en-
doplasmic reticulum (ER) through phosphorylation by CDK1 (Chuang 
and Schekman, 1996; Zhang et al., 2006; Teh et al., 2009). At the 
onset of cytokinesis, Chs2 is triggered to exit the ER by the mitotic 
exit network (MEN; Zhang et al., 2006; Teh et al., 2009; Chin et al., 
2011) and is then delivered to the division site (or the bud neck) via 
the secretory pathway (Chuang and Schekman, 1996; VerPlank and 
Li, 2005). MEN consists of a Ras-related small GTPase (Tem1), pro-
tein kinases (Cdc15, Dbf2, and its homologue Dbf20), a protein 
phosphatase (Cdc14), and a few regulatory proteins (Balasubrama-
nian et al., 2004; Stegmeier and Amon, 2004). GTP-bound Tem1 
binds and recruits Cdc15 to the spindle pole bodies (SPBs; equiva-
lent of centrosomes in animal cells), which, in turn, recruits and acti-
vates Dbf2, resulting in the release of Cdc14 from the nucleolus to 
the entire cell. Cdc14 then acts on a few key substrates to down-reg-
ulate CDK1/mitotic cyclin activity, resulting in mitotic exit. Cdc14 
also directly acts on Chs2 to remove the phosphorylation by CDK1, 
which enables Chs2 exit from the ER for subsequent transport to the 
division site (Chin et al., 2011). MEN may also regulate cytokinesis 
directly at the division site, as several MEN components, including 
the Cdc15 and Dbf2 kinases, localize to the division site during cy-
tokinesis (Frenz et al., 2000; Xu et al., 2000). However, the cytokine-
sis targets of these kinases are largely unknown. In this study, we 
demonstrate that Dbf2 regulates PS formation directly by phospho-
rylating Chs2 at a single residue, resulting in its dissociation from the 
AMR during late stage of cytokinesis, and that timed phosphoryla-
tion of this residue is important for PS formation during cytokinesis. 
Several proteins, including Iqg1 (the sole IQGAP in budding 
yeast), Inn1, Hof1 (a F-BAR protein), and Cyk3 have been implicated 
in PS formation (Korinek et al., 2000; Vallen et al., 2000; Nishihama 
et al., 2009; Meitinger et al., 2010), but the underlying mechanism 
remains unknown. Iqg1 is also required for actin ring assembly (Epp 
and Chant, 1997; Lippincott and Li, 1998). Of interest, overexpres-
sion of Cyk3 suppresses the lethality and cytokinesis defects of 
iqg1Δ cells without restoring actin ring assembly, suggesting that 
Cyk3 functions in an AMR-independent process-most likely sep-
tum formation-to promote cytokinesis (Korinek et al., 2000). Over-
expression of Cyk3 also suppresses the cytokinesis and PS defects 
of inn1Δ cells (Nishihama et al., 2009) and causes the formation of 
ectopic PS-like structures in wild-type cells (Meitinger et al., 2010). 
These observations suggest that Cyk3 may be an activator of Chs2. 
In this study, we show that overexpression of Cyk3 robustly sup-
presses the growth and cytokinesis defects of the chs2 phosphomu-
tants, further supporting the "activator" hypothesis. We also dem-
onstrate that Cyk3 and Dbf2 phosphorylation define distinct 
mechanisms in regulating Chs2 function during cytokinesis. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Chs2 is a direct substrate of Dbf2 kinase in vitro </p>

<p>The following observations suggest that Chs2 may be a substrate of 
Dbf2 during cytokinesis. First, both Chs2 and Dbf2 localize to the </p>

<p>Volume 23 July 1, 2012 </p>

<p>Dbf2 regulation of Chs2 during cytokinesis | 2447 </p>

<p>defect. In comparison, none of the wild-type cells and 66% of the 
chs2Δ cells formed cell clusters. Neither chs2-S225A nor chs2-S225D 
mutation caused any obvious defects in cell growth and cytokinesis 
even in rich media (unpublished data). In addition, the chs2-S225 
mutations only slightly enhanced the phenotypes of the chs2-S217 
mutations (Figure 2, A, right, and B, right). Together these data indi-
cate that both phosphorylation and dephosphorylation of Ser-217 
are important for cytokinesis. 
It is not clear why the chs2-S217 mutants displayed media-de-
pendent behavior. However, media influence on the phenotypes of </p>

<p>growth or cytokinesis when cultured in minimal media (Figure 2, A, 
left, and B, left). However, both chs2-S217A and chs2-S217D mu-
tants displayed clear defects in cell growth and cytokinesis when 
grown in rich media (Figure 2, A, right, and B, right). Forty-four per-
cent of chs2-S217A and 53% chs2-S217D cells formed cell clusters 
containing three or more cell bodies, indicative of a cytokinesis </p>

<p>FIGURE 1: Mitotic exit kinase Dbf2 directly phosphorylates Chs2. 
(A) Schematic diagram of Chs2. con1 and con2, conserved regions of 
typical chitin synthases; TM, predicted transmembrane domains. 
Demonstrated and putative phosphorylation sites for CDK1 and Dbf2 
kinases in the N-terminal region of Chs2 are indicated. (B) In vitro 
phosphorylation of the N-terminal region of Chs2 by Dbf2. Asterisk, 
degradation product of GST-Chs2 (1-286). (C) Quantification of 
Dbf2-mediated phosphorylation of Chs2. (D) Time-lapse analysis of a 
yeast cell coexpressing Chs2-GFP and Dbf2-mCherry (YO1182). Cells 
were grown in SC-HIS media to exponential phase at 25°C and then 
processed for time-lapse microscopy. Arrows, spindle pole bodies. 
Scale bar, 2 μm. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2: Both phosphorylation and dephosphorylation of Ser-217 
are important for cell growth and division. (A) Tenfold serial dilutions 
of different strains (YO1338, YO1339, YO1359, YO1360, YO1450, and 
YO1451) containing pRS305 (Vector) or its derivatives carrying 
different Chs2*-GFP alleles integrated at the leu2 locus of a parent 
strain (chs2Δ CDC3-mCherry) were spotted onto plates containing 
either minimal medium (SC-LEU) or rich medium (YPD) and grown for 
2-3 d at 25°C. (B) Strains indicated in A were grown to exponential 
phase in liquid SC-LEU or rich (YM-1) media at 25°C. Percentages of 
cell clusters (counted &gt;200 cells for each strain under each growth 
condition) were analyzed as indicated. (C) Representative 
morphologies of strains (YO1338, YO1339, YO1450, and YO1451) 
were visualized by DIC microscopy after grown exponentially in 
SC-LEU and YM-1 media at 25°C. Scale bar, 5 μm. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>yeast cytokinesis mutants has been observed (Bulawa and Osmond, 
1990; Nishihama et al., 2009). It is possible that the chs2-S217 muta-
tions have compromised the functionality of Chs2 at the division site 
to the extent that is still sufficient to support cytokinesis in slow-grow-
ing minimal media but not in fast-growing rich media. Because of 
the media influence, only cells grown in rich media were used for 
functional assays on Chs2 hereafter, unless stated otherwise. </p>

<p>Phosphoregulation of Chs2 is important for chitin synthesis 
at the division site </p>

<p>To explore the underlying mechanism for the cytokinesis defect 
caused by the chs2-S217 mutations, we first monitored the chitin 
level at the division site in different strains by Calcofluor staining 
(Pringle, 1991). C-terminally GFP-tagged alleles of CHS2 (wild-type, 
S217A, and S217D) under control of the native promoter and carry-
ing a centromere-based plasmid were introduced into a chs1Δ 
chs2Δ chs3Δ strain in which all chitin synthase genes in budding 
yeast had been deleted. The viability of the triple mutant relied 
solely on the introduced chs2 allele. The chitin levels at the division 
site of the chs2-S217A and chs2-S217D cells were both reduced to 
∼71% of the wild-type level (Figure 3, A and B). To ensure fair com-
parisons, only cells with a similar size of Chs2*-GFP ring from differ-
ent strains (Figure 3A), which is indicative of a similar cell cycle stage, 
were included in our quantitation. These data suggest that phos-
phoregulation of Chs2 at Ser-217 is important for chitin synthesis at 
the division site, which may account for the cytokinesis defects 
caused by these mutations. 
The decreased chitin synthesis at the division site could ensue as 
a result of decreased catalytic activity and/or altered protein expres-
sion, localization, or dynamics. To distinguish these possibilities, we 
first measured the chitin synthase activity of the Chs2 variants in 
strains lacking chitin synthase I and chitin synthase III activity. Chitin 
synthase II assays were done using membranes from chs1Δ chs3Δ 
rather than chs1Δ chs2Δ chs3Δ cells because the former are much 
healthier in growth and division (Shaw et al., 1991). Furthermore, the 
activity of chromosomally encoded Chs2 in membranes from chs1Δ 
chs3Δ cells grown in minimal medium is negligible (Nagahashi et al., 
1995), regardless of pretreatment with trypsin, which is known to 
stimulate Chs2 activity in vitro (Sburlati and Cabib, 1986; Uchida 
et al., 1996). High-copy plasmids expressing HA3-Chs2, HA3-Chs2-
S217A, or HA3-Chs2-S217D from the inducible GAL1 promoter 
were introduced into chs1Δ chs3Δ cells, which were then grown in 
minimal medium and induced by the addition of galactose. Mem-
branes from each strain were assayed for chitin synthase activity with 
or without prior treatment by trypsin and proved to have high activ-
ity (Figure 3C), whereas membranes from chs1Δ chs3Δ cells assayed 
in parallel incorporated background levels of radioactivity regard-
less of trypsin treatment (unpublished data). Trypsin treatment stim-
ulated chitin synthase activities of all Chs2 variants to a similar extent 
(1.5-to 2-fold). Specific activities of membranes expressing Chs2 
and Chs2-S217A were comparable, whereas the specific activity of </p>

<p>FIGURE 3: Phosphorylation and dephosphorylation of Ser-217 affect 
chitin synthesis at the division site. (A) Cells (YO1320, YO1324, and 
YO1325; chs1Δ chs2Δ chs3Δ with YCp111-Chs2*-GFP plasmids) were 
grown in SC-LEU medium to exponential phase at 25°C and then 
diluted into rich media (YM-1) and grown for additional 3 h at 25°C. 
Chs2*-GFP and cellular chitin (stained with 10 mg/ml Calcofluor) were 
visualized by fluorescence microscopy. (B) Quantification of chitin 
synthesis in vivo. The ratio of Calcofluor staining intensity divided by </p>

<p>Chs2*-GFP signal intensity was plotted for each indicated strain (WT, 
n = 21; S217A, n = 21; S217D, n = 26). The error bar represents SEM. 
*p &lt; 0.001 in comparison to WT. (C) Cells (YO1535, YO1536, and 
YO1537; chs1Δ chs3Δ with YEp-pGAL1-HA3-Chs2* plasmid [2 μ, 
TRP1]) were grown in inducing medium (yeast nitrogen base 
containing 2% galactose and 1% raffinose) for 18 h at 25°C. In vitro 
chitin synthase II activity was measured with and without prior 
treatment of portions of membranes with 0, 100, and 200 μg of 
trypsin. Scale bar, 2 μm. </p>

<p>Volume 23 July 1, 2012 </p>

<p>Dbf2 regulation of Chs2 during cytokinesis | 2449 </p>

<p>Chs2-GFP. It is striking that Chs2-S217A-
GFP constricted asymmetrically in 79% 
of cells (Figure 4, B and C, and Supple-
mental Video S2, middle), in comparison to 
100% symmetric constriction for wild-type 
Chs2-GFP (Supplemental Video S2, left); in 
contrast, Chs2-S217D-GFP showed little or 
no constriction before its disappearance 
from the division site in 80% of cells (Sup-
plemental Video S2, right). As expected, the 
AMR (marked by the mCherry-tagged sole 
myosin-II, Myo1, in budding yeast) and 
Chs2-GFP always constricted together and 
symmetrically in wild-type cells (Figure 4D 
and Supplemental Video S3, left; Fang et al., 
2010). Similarly, the AMR and Chs2-AA-GFP 
always constricted together but in an asym-
metric manner (Supplemental Video S3, 
middle). In contrast, Chs2-DD-GFP failed to 
follow the constriction of the AMR (Supple-
mental Video S3, right), suggesting the un-
coupling of this mutant Chs2 from the AMR. 
AMR constriction and disassembly appeared 
to be slightly longer in both Ser-217 mu-
tants, especially in the chs2-AA mutant, than 
in wild-type cells (Figure 4E). 
The uncoupling of Chs2-S217D from the 
AMR is further supported by the following 
observations. First, despite similar profiles in 
protein expression (unpublished data) and 
the timing and duration of their localiza-
tions, Chs2-S217D-GFP always appeared as 
a broad and nonconstricting band, whereas 
the wild-type Chs2-GFP or Chs2-S217A-GFP 
appeared as a sharply focused and con-
stricting band between the septin rings. 
Second, fluorescence recovery after photo-
bleaching (FRAP) analysis indicates that 
wild-type Chs2-GFP at the division site re-
covers quickly after bleaching during the first ∼3 min of its localiza-
tion, presumably reflecting a continuous recruitment to the division 
site. Chs2-GFP is then immobilized in a myosin II-dependent man-
ner for the rest of cytokinesis, ∼6-7 min. Using this analysis on cells 
with already localized Chs2 and photobleaching only a portion of 
the Chs2*-GFP ring, we found that Chs2-S217D-GFP displayed full 
recovery throughout cytokinesis (Supplemental Video S4, right); in 
contrast, wild-type Chs2-GFP (Supplemental Video S4, left) and the 
majority of Chs2-S217A-GFP (Supplemental Video S4, middle) dis-
played no or little recovery (Figure 5, A and B). Taken together, these 
data suggest that phosphorylation of Chs2 by Dbf2 may trigger its 
dissociation from the AMR during the late stage of cytokinesis. </p>

<p>Inactivation of Dbf2 causes delayed endocytic removal 
of Chs2 from the division site </p>

<p>If Chs2 were indeed a physiological substrate of Dbf2 at the division 
site, Chs2 would be expected to display asymmetric constriction, 
essentially phenocopying the chs2-S217A mutant, when Dbf2 is in-
activated. To test this hypothesis, we monitored at the nonpermis-
sive temperature Chs2-GFP localization in a wild-type strain and a 
dbf2-Ts (temperature-sensitive) mutant carrying a GAL1 promoter-
controlled allele of SIC1 s (T5V, T33V, S76A) that encodes a stable 
version of the CDK1 inhibitor (Meitinger et al., 2010). Because Dbf2 </p>

<p>the membranes expressing Chs2-S217D was on average ∼80% of 
that expressing Chs2. Similar results were obtained when cells were 
grown in rich medium (unpublished data). These data suggest that 
the defect in cytokinesis or chitin synthesis at the division site caused 
by the chs2-S217 mutations may not be fully explained by the mildly 
decreased catalytic activity of the mutant proteins assayed at 2 mM 
UDP-GlcNAc. </p>

<p>Phosphorylation of Ser-217 regulates Chs2 dynamics 
at the division site </p>

<p>To further explore the underlying mechanism for the cytokinesis de-
fect, we monitored the dynamics of Chs2-S217A and Chs2-S217D 
proteins at the division site. Yeast strains carrying Cdc3-mCherry 
and different GFP-tagged alleles of CHS2 (CHS2, chs2-S217A, and 
chs2-S217D as the sole source of Chs2 in the cell) were grown in rich 
media and imaged by three-dimensional spin-disk time-lapse mi-
croscopy. Like wild-type Chs2-GFP, both Chs2-S217A-GFP and 
Chs2-S217D-GFP were localized to the bud neck around the onset 
of cytokinesis (Fang et al., 2010), which is marked by the splitting of 
the septin hourglass into two cortical rings (Cdc3-mCherry; Figure 
4A; Lippincott et al., 2001). The duration of Chs2-S217A-GFP and 
Chs2-S217D-GFP at the division is 12.8 ± 2.4 and 11.5 ± 2.0 min, 
respectively, slightly longer than the 10.3 ± 1.0 min for wild-type </p>

<p>FIGURE 4: Chs2-S217A and Chs2-S217D display distinct dynamic behaviors during cytokinesis. 
(A) Localization patterns of Chs2-S217A and Chs2-S217D during the cell cycle. Cells of different 
strains (YO1339, YO1359, and YO1360; chs2Δ CDC3-mCherry with integrated Chs2*-GFP in at 
the leu2 locus) were grown in SC-LEU medium to exponential phase at 25°C and then diluted 
into rich media (YM-1) and grown for additional 1-2 h at 25°C before being subjected to 
time-lapse analysis. (B) Three-dimensional reconstruction of selected time points for the cells 
shown in A. Both the side view (top) and the en face view (bottom) of the cells are presented. 
The blue arrow and dashed line indicate the direction of rotation. White arrow indicates the 
position of Chs2*-GFP near the end of its constriction. Scale bar, 1 μm. (C) Data acquired in A 
were quantified for the constriction patterns of Chs2-S217A and Chs2-S217D (WT, n = 22; 
S217A, n = 29; S217D, n = 41). (D) Spatial relationship between Chs2-S217A or Chs2-S217D and 
the actomyosin ring during cytokinesis. Cells of different strains (YO1454, YO1453, and YO1455; 
chs2Δ Chs2*-GFP::LEU2 with pRS314-MYO1-C-mCherry) were cultured and imaged as in A. 
Arrowhead indicates the onset of AMR constriction. (E) Quantification of the durations of 
Chs2*-GFP, AMR contraction, and AMR disassembly during cytokinesis (WT, n = 16; S217A 
S225A, n = 17; S217D S225D, n = 29). </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>Cyk3 is a robust dosage suppressor of 
chs2 phosphomutants </p>

<p>Cyk3, a cytokinesis protein that localizes to 
the division site in a Dbf2-dependent man-
ner (Meitinger et al., 2010), has been impli-
cated in PS formation, but the underlying 
mechanism remains unknown (Korinek et al., 
2000; Nishihama et al., 2009; Meitinger 
et al., 2010). It is striking that high-copy 
CYK3 robustly suppressed the growth and 
cytokinesis defects of both chs2-AA and 
chs2-DD cells (Figure 7, A and B). In con-
trast, high-copy CYK3 failed to rescue chs2Δ 
cells (Figure 7B), suggesting that the sup-
pression is Chs2 dependent. Of importance, 
high-copy CYK3 strongly stimulated chitin 
synthesis at the division site of chs1Δ chs3Δ 
cells in which Chs2 is the sole chitin synthase 
(Figure 7C). Reciprocally, deletion of CYK3 
exacerbated the defects of the chs2-AA and 
chs2-DD mutants even when the mutant 
cells were grown in minimal media (Figure 
7D). Consistent with the notion of Cyk3 act-
ing through Chs2, cyk3Δ and chs2Δ did not 
produce any additive or synergistic defect in 
growth or cytokinesis (Figure 7D). Together 
these data strongly suggest that Cyk3 is an activator of Chs2 in vivo 
and that Cyk3 and Ser-217 phosphorylation regulate Chs2 function 
independently during cytokinesis. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Dbf2 directly phosphorylates Chs2 to regulate its dynamics 
and chitin synthesis at the division site during cytokinesis </p>

<p>Our study demonstrated, for the first time, that Chs2 is a direct sub-
strate of the conserved mitotic exit kinase Dbf2. Chs2 contains six 
putative Dbf2-consensus sites (RXXS; Ser-21, Ser-150, Ser-217, Ser-
225, Ser-256, and Ser-326; Mah et al., 2005) at its N-terminal region 
and two catalytically important as well as seven predicted trans-
membrane domains in its C-terminal region (Figure 1A). In this study, 
we showed that both Ser-217 and Ser-225 are phosphorylated by 
Dbf2 in vitro. Of importance, the same two sites were also found to 
be phosphorylated in vivo in global studies of phosphoproteins in 
budding yeast (Chi et al., 2007; Dephoure and Gygi, 2011). Other 
putative Dbf2 sites and/or additional serines or threonines in the 
N-terminal region of Chs2 may also be phosphorylated by Dbf2, as 
∼43% of phosphorylation still remained when GST-Chs2 (1-286, 
S217A S225A) was used as the substrate. However, because of the 
clear phenotypes displayed by the chs2-S217 mutations, our func-
tional analysis has thus far focused on phosphorylation at this resi-
due. These results, together with the observations that Chs2 and 
Dbf2 colocalize at the division site during cytokinesis and that Dbf2 
is also implicated in PS formation (Meitinger et al., 2010), make 
Chs2 a highly likely substrate of Dbf2 in vivo. 
Our study suggests that Ser-217 phosphorylation regulates 
Chs2 dynamics and chitin synthesis at the division site during cy-
tokinesis. Both the phosphodeficient and the phosphomimic mu-
tations of Ser-217 caused little defect in the catalytic activity of 
Chs2 in the bulk chitin synthase assay in vitro but clearly caused a 
30% reduction in chitin synthesis at the division site in vivo. Be-
cause the amount and duration of the Chs2-S217A and Chs2-S217D 
variants at the bud neck are similar to those of the wild-type pro-
tein, these data suggest that Ser-217 is involved in fine-tuning the </p>

<p>inactivation simultaneously blocks both mitotic exit and cytokine-
sis, Sic1 overexpression was induced by adding galactose to the 
growth medium (see Materials and Methods for details) to force 
mitotic exit and trigger Chs2 translocation from the ER to the bud 
neck in the dbf2-mutant cells. This strategy provides the opportu-
nity for assessing the specific effect of Dbf2 inactivation on Chs2 
behavior at the division site. As expected, in wild-type cells, 
Chs2-GFP localized, constricted, and disappeared at or from the 
division site within 12 min (Figure 6, A and B, and Supplemental 
Video S5, left). In contrast, Chs2-GFP accumulated at the division 
site more slowly in the dbf2-mutant than in wild-type cells, perhaps 
reflecting an imperfect mitotic exit forced by Sic1 overexpression 
(Figure 6, A and B, and Supplemental Video S5, right). More im-
portant, Chs2-GFP was retained at the division site of the mutant 
cells for &gt;40 min with little constriction, and its signal intensity de-
creased gradually over time (Figure 6, A and B, and Supplemental 
Video S5, right). The weak signal of Chs2-GFP at the end of our 
imaging, coupled with its nearly nonconstrictive behavior, pre-
vented a clear assessment of its constriction symmetry. However, a 
previous EM study indicates that 81% of the dbf2 mutant cells form 
an asymmetric PS (Meitinger et al., 2010), suggesting that Chs2 
distribution is eventually asymmetric, which lends strong support 
to our hypothesis. 
Similar to wild-type Chs2, Chs2-S217A and Chs2-S217D accu-
mulated at and then disappeared from the division site more slowly 
in the dbf2-mutant than in wild-type cells, although Chs2-S217D 
consistently seemed to disappear more quickly (Figure 6B). To-
gether these data suggest that the endocytic removal of Chs2 is 
delayed in the dbf2 mutant, which is largely independent of Chs2 
phosphorylation by Dbf2. This conclusion is supported by the pre-
vious observation that accumulation of actin patches at the divi-
sion site, which are required for endocytosis in budding yeast, is 
significantly decreased in the dbf2 mutant (Corbett et al., 2006). 
Thus the MEN may also regulate the endocytic removal of Chs2 
during cytokinesis by regulating actin-patch polarization at the di-
vision site. </p>

<p>FIGURE 5: Phosphomimic Chs2-S217D is highly mobile during cytokinesis. (A) FRAP analysis of 
Chs2-S217A and Chs2-S217D. Cells of different strains (YO1339, YO1359, and YO1360; chs2Δ 
CDC3-mCherry with integrated Chs2*-GFP at the leu2 locus) were grown in SC-LEU to 
exponential phase at 23°C and then diluted into rich YM-1 medium and grown for at least 
3 additional hours before being subjected to FRAP analysis. (B) Data acquired in A were 
quantified for the recovery patterns of Chs2*-GFP (WT, n = 12; S217A, n = 28; S217D, n = 18). 
Arrows indicate the points of photobleaching. </p>

<p>Volume 23 July 1, 2012 </p>

<p>Dbf2 regulation of Chs2 during cytokinesis | 2451 </p>

<p>displayed strikingly different behaviors at the division site, which 
may also partly account for their defects in cytokinesis. Chs2-S217A 
is associated with the AMR throughout cytokinesis. In contrast, 
Chs2-S217D is largely uncoupled from the AMR upon its arrival at 
the division site. These observations suggest a simple model for 
the function of Ser-217 phosphorylation (Figure 8A). In wild-type 
cells, "unphosphorylated" Chs2 is delivered to the division site at 
the onset of cytokinesis. Approximately halfway through AMR con-
striction, Dbf2 level reaches its peak at the bud neck, causing 
phosphorylation of Chs2 at Ser-217, resulting in Chs2 dissociation 
from the AMR. This dissociation may facilitate Chs2 inactivation 
and/or its endocytic removal from the division site. Persistent as-
sociation of Chs2 with the AMR, as shown by Chs2-S217A, some-
how causes asymmetric distribution of the AMR components, re-
sulting in asymmetric constriction. On the other hand, premature 
uncoupling of Chs2 from the AMR, as shown by Chs2-S217D, re-
sults in broad and dynamic distribution of Chs2-S217D between 
the septin rings, which presumably would lead to inefficient PS 
formation due to inaccurate placement of chitin. Thus timed phos-
phorylation of Ser-217 is important for proper PS formation and 
cytokinesis. </p>

<p>Dbf2 regulates primary septum formation through 
multiple pathways </p>

<p>Dbf2 appears to regulate PS formation at multiple levels via distinct 
mechanisms (Figure 8B). First, during mitosis, Chs2 is phosphory-
lated by CDK1 at four residues (Ser-14, Ser-60, Ser-69, and Ser-100), 
and this phosphorylation prevents Chs2 from prematurely exiting 
the ER before cytokinesis (Teh et al., 2009). During mitotic exit, 
Dbf2, as a part of the MEN, activates the phosphatase Cdc14, which 
removes the CDK1 phosphorylation from Chs2, thus promoting its 
exit from the ER (Chin et al., 2011). Second, we show here that Dbf2 
phosphorylates Chs2 directly at the division site to regulate its chitin 
synthase activity and also its dissociation from the AMR. This regula-
tory mechanism plays an important role in cytokinesis. Third, Dbf2 
regulates PS formation indirectly by controlling Cyk3 localization to 
the division site (Meitinger et al., 2010). We show here that increased 
dosage of Cyk3 stimulates Chs2-mediated chitin synthesis and ro-
bustly suppresses chs2-AA and chs2-DD mutants, whereas deletion 
of CYK3 exacerbates the phenotypes of the chs2 mutants. These 
data suggest that Cyk3 is a potent activator of Chs2 in vivo and that 
Cyk3 and Dbf2-mediated phosphorylation regulate Chs2 function 
independently during cytokinesis. Fourth, Dbf2 may regulate the 
endocytic removal of Chs2 from the division site by regulating ac-
tin-patch polarization at the division site. Finally, Dbf2 is also known 
to phosphorylate the F-BAR protein Hof1 (Meitinger et al., 2011), 
which has been implicated in PS formation and/or its coordination 
with the AMR during cytokinesis (Vallen et al., 2000; Meitinger et al., 
2010, 2011). 
It becomes increasingly clear that ECM remodeling is impor-
tant for animal cytokinesis (Mizuguchi et al., 2003; Izumikawa 
et al., 2010). However, how the ECM is locally remodeled at the 
division site and how this remodeling is coupled to AMR constric-
tion and controlled by the cell cycle machinery remain largely un-
known in animal cells. In this study, we established a mechanism 
by which the conserved mitotic exit kinase Dbf2 directly phospho-
rylates Chs2 to regulate PS formation (or ECM remodeling) during 
cytokinesis in budding yeast. On the basis of the overall conserva-
tion in the core mechanisms of cell cycle control and cytokinesis 
between yeast and animal cells, we speculate that similar cell cycle 
regulation of ECM remodeling during cytokinesis likely exists in 
animal cells. </p>

<p>FIGURE 6: Inactivation of Dbf2 prolongs Chs2 localization at the 
division site. (A) Chs2 disappears from the division site slowly in a 
dbf2 mutant. Wild-type (WT, CHS2-GFP CDC3-mCherry; YEF6653) 
and the dbf2-Ts mutant (dbf2-1 dbf20Δ CDC3-mCherry, CHS2-GFP, 
pGAL1-SIC1 s ; YO1399) cells were grown under conditions to 
inactivate Dbf2 and also overexpress Sic1 to force mitotic exit in the 
mutant cells (see Materials and Methods for details) and then 
analyzed by time-lapse microscopy. (B) Endocytic removal of Chs2 is 
delayed in the dbf2 mutant. Quantification of Chs2*-GFP 
disappearance from the division site was performed on the time-lapse 
data acquired in A, as well as those acquired from strains YO1410 
(dbf2-1 dbf20Δ CDC3-mCherry, chs2-S217A-GFP, pGAL1-SIC1 s ) and 
YO1411 (dbf2-1 dbf20Δ CDC3-mCherry, chs2-S217D-GFP, 
pGAL1-SIC1 s ). The average of the peak fluorescence of Chs2*-GFP for 
each strain was set at 100. The error bar represents SEM. </p>

<p>chitin synthase activity of Chs2. This is consistent with previous 
reports that the N-terminal noncatalytic region of Chs2, including 
the Ser-217 residue (Figure 1A), is involved in the regulation of 
Chs2 activity based on in vitro chitin assays (Uchida et al., 1996; 
Martinez-Rucobo et al., 2009). The underlying mechanism for the 
involvement of Ser-217 in this regulation remains unknown. One 
possibility is that Ser-217 might affect the putative proteolysis of 
Chs2 that is believed to be required for its activation in vivo 
(Sburlati and Cabib, 1986; Uchida et al., 1996; Martinez-Rucobo 
et al., 2009). However, we note that in our experiments, the chs2-
S217A and chs2-S217D mutations did not significantly affect the 
degree to which the in vitro Chs2 activity was stimulated by trypsin. 
The moderate decrease in chitin synthesis caused by both the 
chs2-S217A and the chs2-S217D mutations in vivo likely explains, 
at least in part, their medium-dependent defects in cytokinesis. 
Presumably, cells demand more robust chitin synthesis at the divi-
sion site to ensure efficient cytokinesis in the fast-growing rich me-
dia than in the slow-growing minimal media. 
Despite their similar defects in chitin synthesis in vivo, the phos-
phodeficient and the phosphomimic variants of Chs2 at Ser-217 </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Strains and growth media </p>

<p>Yeast strains used in this study are listed in Table 1. Standard culture 
media and genetic techniques were used (Guthrie and Fink, 1991). 
Escherichia coli strains DH12S (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) and BL21 
(DE3) (Invitrogen) were used as hosts for plasmid manipulation and 
recombinant protein expression, respectively. Yeast strains were 
grown routinely at 25°C in synthetic complete (SC) minimal medium 
lacking specific amino acid(s) and/or uracil or in rich medium YM-1 
(Lillie and Pringle, 1980) or yeast extract/peptone/dextrose (YPD). </p>

<p>Constructions of plasmids and yeast strains </p>

<p>Common plasmid vectors used in this study include YCplac111 
(CEN, LEU2), pRS314 (CEN, TRP1), pRS316 (CEN, URA3), pRS305 
(integrative, LEU2), and YIplac204 (integrative, TRP1). Plasmids 
p414ADH (CEN, TRP1; Mumberg et al., 1995) and pBK42 (2μ, CYK3, 
TRP1; Korinek et al., 2000) were described previously. Plasmid YI-
plac211-GAL1-SIC1 s (T5V, T33V, S76A)-HA (integrative, URA3; Meit-
inger et al., 2010; kindly supplied by Gislene Pereira, German Can-
cer Research Center, Heidelberg, Germany), carrying a GAL1 
promoter-controlled allele of SIC1 s that encodes a stabilized pro-
tein, was cut with EcoRV and integrated at the ura3 locus of the re-
cipient strain. Plasmids YIplac128-CDC3-mCherry (integrative, 
LEU2; Gao et al., 2007), YIplac211-CDC3-mCherry (integrative, 
URA3; Fang et al., 2010), and YIplac204-CDC3-mCherry (integra-
tive, TRP1; Wloka et al., 2011), carrying mCherry-tagged CDC3, 
were digested with BglII and integrated at the CDC3 locus of the 
recipient strains. Plasmid pGEX5X-CHS2-N was constructed by 
cloning a BamHI-and SalI-digested (both sites were introduced in 
PCR primers) CHS2 fragment encoding amino acids 1-286 into the 
corresponding sites of pGEX5X-1 (GE Healthcare, Pittsburgh, PA). 
YEp-pGAL1-HA3-CHS2 was constructed by inserting a 1.7-kb PCR 
fragment carrying TRP1-pGAL1-HA3 (Longtine et al., 1998) in front 
of CHS2 on plasmid pEC2 (2 μ, CHS2, URA3; Ford et al., 1996). The 
QuikChange Multi Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit (Agilent Technolo-
gies, Santa Clara, CA) was used to generate phosphodeficient mu-
tations (S217A and/or S225A) or phosphomimic mutations (S217D 
and/or S225D) in CHS2 using plasmid YCp111-CHS2-GFP-KanMX6 
as the template (Wloka et al., 2011). Wild-type and the phosphomu-
tant alleles of CHS2 were then subcloned into the integrative vector 
pRS305 (LEU2), as described previously (Wloka et al., 2011). The 
resulting plasmid pRS305-CHS2*-GFP was digested with AflII and 
integrated at the leu2 locus of the recipient strains. Plasmid 
pAG24-CYK3 was constructed by transferring CYK3 from the tiling 
library plasmid pGP564-CYK3 (2 μ, LEU2; Open Biosystems, Lafay-
ette, CO) onto the Gateway vector pAG24 (2 μ, URA3) using Gate-
way LR Clonase II (Invitrogen, Grand Island, NY). </p>

<p>Microscopy </p>

<p>A computer-controlled Eclipse 800 microscope (Nikon, Tokyo, 
Japan) and a high-resolution charge-coupled device camera (model 
C4742-95; Hamamatsu Photonics, Bridgewater, NJ) were used to </p>

<p>FIGURE 7: Increased dosage of Cyk3 stimulates Chs2-dependent 
chitin synthesis and robustly suppresses the growth and cytokinesis 
defects of both chs2-AA and chs2-DD mutants. (A) Multicopy CYK3 
suppresses the growth defects of chs2-AA and chs2-DD. Strains 
(YO1543 and YO1544, top half of the plate; YO1550 and YO1551, 
bottom half of the plate; chs2Δ Chs2*-GFP::LEU2 CDC3-mCherry cells 
transformed with either an empty vector [pAG426, 2 μ, URA3] or a 
high-copy CYK3 plasmid [pAG426-CYK3]) were streaked onto plates 
containing minimal (SC-URA) or rich (YM-1) media and grown at 25°C 
for 3-4 d. (B) Multicopy CYK3 suppresses the cytokinesis defects of 
chs2-AA and chs2-DD. Cells of different strains (top, YO1245, 
YO1246, YO1247, and YO1248; bottom, YO1213, YO1214, YO1215, 
and YO1216; chs2Δ leu2::LEU2 [pRS305, vector] or chs2Δ Chs2* (WT, 
chs2-AA, or chs2-DD)-GFP::LEU2 cells transformed with either an 
empty vector [pRS314] or a high-copy CYK3 plasmid [pBK42]) were 
grown to exponential phase in rich medium (YM-1) at 25°C and then 
visualized by DIC microscopy. (C) Increased Cyk3 stimulates 
Chs2-dependent chitin synthesis at the division site. Cells (YO1129, 
YO1130; chs1Δ chs3Δ cells transformed with either an empty vector 
[p414ADH] or a high-copy CYK3 plasmid [pBK42]) were grown 
overnight at 30°C on an SC-TRP plate and then stained for cellular 
chitin using Calcofluor. The relative amounts of chitin in both strains 
(Vector, n = 14; CYK3, n = 22) were quantified and presented in the 
plot. The average intensity for the strain containing the "Vector" was </p>

<p>arbitrarily set at 100. The error bar represents SEM. Scale bar, 2 μm. 
(D) chs2-AA and chs2-DD mutations display synthetically enhanced 
defects with cyk3Δ. Different strains (top, YO1338, YO1339, YO1450, 
and YO1451; chs2Δ leu2::LEU2 [pRS305, vector] and chs2Δ Chs2* 
(WT, chs2-AA, or chs2-DD)-GFP::LEU2; bottom, YO1209, YO1210, 
YO1211, and YO1212; chs2Δ cyk3Δ leu2::LEU2 [pRS305, vector] and 
chs2Δ cyk3Δ Chs2* (WT, chs2-AA, or chs2-DD)-GFP::LEU2) were 
grown to exponential phase in SC-LEU medium at 25°C and then 
visualized by DIC microscopy. Scale bar, 5 μm. </p>

<p>Volume 23 July 1, 2012 </p>

<p>Dbf2 regulation of Chs2 during cytokinesis | 2453 </p>

<p>FIGURE 8: Roles of CDK1 and MEN in the control of Chs2 localization, dynamics, and activation 
during cytokinesis. (A) Role of Dbf2 in regulating Chs2-AMR association during cytokinesis. 
(B) Multipronged regulation of Chs2 function by MEN. MEN regulates Chs2 exit from the ER by 
antagonizing CDK1 phosphorylation, regulates Chs2 dynamics by direct phosphorylation, and 
stimulates Chs2 activity through Cyk3 by a yet-to-be-defined mechanism. See the text for details. </p>

<p>visualize cell morphology, Calcofluor-stained chitin (Pringle, 1991), 
and CHS2*-GFP (wild-type [WT] or phosphomutant alleles of CHS2) 
by differential interference contrast (DIC) and fluorescence micros-
copy, respectively. The images were acquired using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Image-Pro Plus</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 7.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Media Cybernetics</rs>, Bethesda, MD). 
For live-cell imaging of yeast strains carrying a plasmid, cells 
were grown at 25°C in SC media lacking a specific amino acid to 
select for the presence of a plasmid. For imaging yeast strains car-
rying a chs2 phosphomutation, cells were first grown in SC-LEU me-
dium to keep them healthy and then washed twice with rich me-
dium YM-1 without carbon source. Cells were then incubated 
further for 1-3 h at 25°C before being concentrated by centrifuga-
tion and spotted on a slab of YM-1 medium containing 2% agarose 
for live-cell imaging. For live-cell imaging at 37°C (Figure 6), the 
wild-type and the dbf2-1 dbf20Δ strains were grown in liquid YM-1 
media containing 2% raffinose at 25°C to the exponential phase 
and then shifted to 37°C for additional 3 h. A 2.0-ml culture was 
then transferred to a 3.5-mm dish coated with polylysine (MatTek, 
Ashland, MA), which was incubated in the 37°C chamber of the 
microscope for 20 min to let the cells settle down. A 1.5-ml culture </p>

<p>was then removed from the dish, which was 
followed by the addition of a 1.5-ml pre-
warmed YM-1 medium containing 2% 
raffinose, 3% galactose, and 1.5% low-melt-
ing agarose. Images were acquired at 25 or 
37°C on a spinning disk confocal micro-
scope equipped with a Yokogawa CSU 10 
scan head combined with an Olympus IX 71 
microscope (Olympus, Tokyo, Japan) and 
an Olympus 100× objective (1.4 numerical 
aperture, Plan S-Apo oil immersion). Acqui-
sition and hardware were controlled by 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">MetaMorph</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 7.7</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Molecular Devices</rs>, 
Downingtown, PA). A Hamamatsu ImagEM 
EMCCD camera (model C9100-13, Bridge-
water, NJ) was used for capture. Diode la-
sers for excitation (488 nm for GFP and 561 
nm for mCherry/RFP) were housed in a 
launch constructed by Spectral Applied Re-
search (Richmond Hill, Canada). Images 
were taken every minute with z-stacks rang-
ing from 11 × 0.3 to 12 × 0.5 μm. A maxi-
mum projection was generated with Meta-
Morph, version 7.7, or <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> (1.45b; 
National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, 
MD). For quantification of relative chitin lev-
els in different chs2 phosphomutants (Figure 
3), the ratio between Calcofluor signal in-
tensity at the bud neck was divided by 
Chs2-GFP signal intensity at the bud neck. 
For the experiments involving FRAP, 
cells were grown to exponential phase in 
SC-HIS media at 23°C. Cells were then cen-
trifuged and resuspended in 10 ml YM-1 
medium and grown for at least another 3 h 
in a 50-ml flask at 25°C in a water-bath 
shaker. One milliliter of this culture was 
taken to concentrate the cells by centrifuga-
tion. Cells were then spotted on YM-1 me-
dium containing 2% agarose for FRAP and 
imaging analysis. FRAP was performed us-
ing a Micro Point computer-controlled abla-
tion system (Photonic Instruments, St. Charles, IL) consisting of 
a nitrogen-pumped dye laser (wavelength, 435 nm) controlled by 
<rs type="software">MetaMorph</rs>. In some cases, sequential photobleaching was ap-
plied (Figure 5A, S217D). Images were captured and processed us-
ing the same microscope, camera, and software as described ear-
lier. Images were taken every 20 s with a z-stack consisting of 12 × 
0.4 μm steps. </p>

<p>Kinase assay </p>

<p>GST-Chs2(1-286; WT, S217A, or S217D) fusion proteins were ex-
pressed in the E. coli strain BL21 (DE3) and purified as described 
previously (Fang et al., 2010). Dbf2-dependent phosphorylation of 
GST-Chs2(1-286) was performed as described previously (Mohl 
et al., 2009). </p>

<p>In vitro assay for Chs2 activity </p>

<p>Cells (YO1528, YO1535, YO1536, and YO1537) were grown for 24 h 
at 30°C in 30 ml of SC medium supplemented with tryptophan and 
lysine. Cells were sedimented by centrifugation and then resus-
pended in 250 ml 0.67% (wt/vol) yeast nitrogen base containing </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>Strain 
Genotype 
Source </p>

<p>J230-2D 
a dbf2-1 dbf20Δ::TRP1 ade1 leu2 trp1 ura3 
Toyn and Johnston (1994) </p>

<p>YEF473 
a/α his3/his3 leu2/leu2 lys2/lys2 trp1/trp1 ura3/ura3 
Bi and Pringle (1996) </p>

<p>YEF473A 
a his3 leu2 lys2 trp1 ura3 
Bi and Pringle (1996) </p>

<p>YEF473B 
α his3 leu2 lys2 trp1 ura3 
Bi and Pringle (1996) </p>

<p>YEF2845 
As YEF473 except chs2Δ::His3MX6/CHS2 
This study a </p>

<p>YEF6653 
a CHS2-GFP::His3MX6 CDC3-mCherry::URA3 
This study </p>

<p>YO790 
a chs1Δ::KanMX6 chs3Δ::His3MX6 
This study a </p>

<p>YO1111 
a chs1Δ::NatMX6 chs3Δ::His3MX6 
This study </p>

<p>YO1172 
a/α chs2Δ::His3MX6/CHS2 chs3Δ::KanMX6/CHS3 [pEC2, 2 μ, CHS2, URA3] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1182 
a CHS2-GFP::KanMX6 DBF2-mCherry::His3MX6 
This study </p>

<p>YO1194 
α chs2Δ::His3MX6 [pEC2, 2 μ, CHS2, URA3] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1209 
a chs2Δ::His3MX6 cyk3Δ::TRP1 leu2::LEU2-pRS305 
This study </p>

<p>YO1210 
a chs2Δ::His3MX6 cyk3Δ::TRP1 CHS2-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 
This study </p>

<p>YO1211 
a chs2Δ::His3MX6 cyk3Δ::TRP1 chs2-S217A S225A-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 
This study </p>

<p>YO1212 
a chs2Δ::His3MX6 cyk3Δ::TRP1 chs2-S217D S225D-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 
This study </p>

<p>YO1213 
a chs2Δ::His3MX6 leu2::LEU2-pRS305 [pBK42, 2 μ, CYK3, TRP1] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1214 
a chs2Δ::His3MX6 CHS2-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 [pBK42, 2 μ, CYK3, TRP1] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1215 
a chs2Δ::His3MX6 chs2-S217A S225A-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 [pBK42, 2 μ, CYK3, TRP1] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1216 
a chs2Δ::His3MX6 chs2-S217D S225D-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 [pBK42, 2 μ, CYK3, TRP1] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1129 
a chs1Δ::KanMX6 chs3Δ::His3MX6 [p414ADH, CEN, TRP1] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1130 
a chs1Δ::KanMX6 chs3Δ::His3MX6 [pBK42, 2 μ, CYK3, TRP1] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1244 
a chs1Δ::TRP1 chs2Δ::His3MX6 chs3Δ::KanMX6 [pEC2, 2 μ, CHS2, URA3] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1245 
a chs2Δ::His3MX6 leu2::LEU2-pRS305 [pRS314, CEN, TRP1] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1246 
a chs2Δ::His3MX6 CHS2-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 [pRS314, CEN, TRP1] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1247 
a chs2Δ::His3MX6 chs2-S217A S225A-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 [pRS314, CEN, TRP1] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1248 
a chs2Δ::His3MX6 chs2-S217D S225D-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 [pRS314, CEN, TRP1] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1320 
a chs1Δ::TRP1 chs2Δ::His3MX6 chs3Δ::KanMX6 [YCp111-CHS2-GFP::KanMX6, CEN, LEU2] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1324 
a chs1Δ::TRP1 chs2Δ::His3MX6 chs3Δ::KanMX6 [YCp111-CHS2-S217A-GFP::KanMX6, 
CEN, LEU2] </p>

<p>This study </p>

<p>YO1325 
a chs1Δ::TRP1 chs2Δ::His3MX6 chs3Δ::KanMX6 [YCp111-CHS2-S217D-GFP::KanMX6, 
CEN, LEU2] </p>

<p>This study </p>

<p>YO1338 
α chs2Δ::His3MX6 CDC3-mCherry::TRP1 leu2::LEU2-pRS305 
This study </p>

<p>YO1339 
α chs2Δ::His3MX6 CDC3-mCherry::TRP1 CHS2-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 
This study </p>

<p>YO1359 
α chs2Δ::His3MX6 CDC3-mCherry::TRP1 chs2-S217A-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 
This study </p>

<p>YO1360 
α chs2Δ::His3MX6 CDC3-mCherry::TRP1 chs2-S217D-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 
This study </p>

<p>YO1398 
a dbf2-1 dbf20Δ::TRP1 CDC3-mCherry::LEU2 
This study b </p>

<p>YO1399 
a dbf2-1 dbf20Δ::TRP1 CDC3-mCherry::LEU2 pGAL1-SIC1 s (T5V, T33V, S76A)-HA::URA3 
[YCp111-CHS2-GFP::KanMX6, CEN, LEU2] </p>

<p>This study </p>

<p>YO1400 
a dbf2-1 dbf20Δ::TRP1 CDC3-mCherry::LEU2 pGAL1-SIC1 s (T5V, T33V, S76A)-HA::URA3 
This study </p>

<p>YO1410 
a dbf2-1 dbf20Δ::TRP1 CDC3-mCherry::LEU2 pGAL1-SIC1 s (T5V, T33V, S76A)-HA::URA3 
[YCp111-CHS2-S217A-GFP::KanMX6, CEN, LEU2] </p>

<p>This study </p>

<p>YO1411 
a dbf2-1 dbf20Δ::TRP1 CDC3-mCherry::LEU2 pGAL1-SIC1 s (T5V, T33V, S76A)-HA::URA3 
[YCp111-CHS2-S217D-GFP::KanMX6, CEN, LEU2] </p>

<p>This study </p>

<p>YO1450 
α chs2Δ::HIS3 CDC3-mCherry::TRP1 chs2-S217A S225A-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 
This study </p>

<p>YO1451 
α chs2Δ::HIS3 CDC3-mCherry::TRP1 chs2-S217D S225D-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 
This study </p>

<p>TABLE 1: Yeast strains used in this study. </p>

<p>Continues </p>

<p>Volume 23 July 1, 2012 </p>

<p>Dbf2 regulation of Chs2 during cytokinesis | 2455 </p>



<p>Strain 
Genotype 
Source </p>

<p>YO1454 
α chs2Δ::His3MX6 CHS2-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 [pRS314-MYO1-C-mCherry, CEN, TRP1] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1453 
α chs2Δ::His3MX6 chs2-S217A S225A-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 [pRS314-MYO1-C-mCherry, 
CEN, TRP1] </p>

<p>This study </p>

<p>YO1455 
α chs2Δ::His3MX6 chs2-S217D S225D-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 [pRS314-MYO1-C-mCherry, 
CEN, TRP1] </p>

<p>This study </p>

<p>YO1528 
a chs1Δ::NatMX6 chs3Δ::His3MX6 [pRS314, CEN, TRP1] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1535 
a chs1Δ::NatMX6 chs3Δ::His3MX6 [YEp-TRP1-pGAL1-HA3-CHS2, 2 μ, URA3] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1536 
a chs1Δ::NatMX6 chs3Δ::His3MX6 [YEp-TRP1-pGAL1-HA3-CHS2-S217A, 2 μ, URA3] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1537 
a chs1Δ::NatMX6 chs3Δ::His3MX6 [YEp-TRP1-pGAL1-HA3-CHS2-S217D, 2 μ, URA3] 
This study </p>

<p>YO1543 
α chs2Δ::HIS3 CDC3-mCherry::TRP1 chs2-S217A S225A-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 [pAG426, 
2 μ, URA3] </p>

<p>This study </p>

<p>YO1544 
α chs2Δ::HIS3 CDC3-mCherry::TRP1 chs2-S217A S225A-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 [pAG426-
CYK3, 2 μ, URA3] </p>

<p>This study </p>

<p>YO1550 
α chs2Δ::HIS3 CDC3-mCherry::TRP1 chs2-S217D S225D-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 [pAG426, 
2 μ, URA3] </p>

<p>This study </p>

<p>YO1551 
α chs2Δ::HIS3 CDC3-mCherry::TRP1 chs2-S217D S225D-GFP::KanMX6::LEU2 [pAG426-
CYK3, 2 μ, URA3] </p>

<p>This study </p>

<p>a All YEF and YO strains except YO1398-1411 are derived from YEF473, YEF473A, or YEF473B. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Derived from J230-2D. </p>

<p>TABLE 1: Yeast strains used in this study. Continued </p>



<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Aaron Gitler and Gislene Pereira for providing plasmids 
and the members of the Bi, Deshaies, and Orlean laboratories for 
discussions. This work was supported by National Institutes of 
Health Grants GM59216 and GM87365 (to E.B.), a fellowship from 
the Boehringer Ingelheim Fonds (to C.W.), and Taiwan Merit Schol-
arship TMS-094-1-A-026 (to K.J.C.). R.D. is an Investigator of the 
Howard Hughes Medical Institute. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>



</text></tei>