<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3031013" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>We evaluated the effects of previous pulmonary tuberculosis (TB) on the risk of obstructive 
lung disease. We analyzed population-based, the Second Korea National Health and 
Nutrition Examination Survey 2001. Participants underwent chest X-rays (CXR) and 
spirometry, and qualified radiologists interpreted the presence of TB lesion independently. 
A total of 3,687 underwent acceptable spirometry and CXR. Two hundreds and ninty four 
subjects had evidence of previous TB on CXR with no subjects having evidence of active 
disease. Evidence of previous TB on CXR were independently associated with airflow 
obstruction (adjusted odds ratios [OR] = 2.56 [95% CI 1.84-3.56]) after adjustment for 
sex, age and smoking history. Previous TB was still a risk factor (adjusted OR = 3.13 [95% 
CI 1.86-5.29]) with exclusion of ever smokers or subjects with advanced lesion on CXR. 
Among never-smokers, the proportion of subjects with previous TB on CXR increased as 
obstructive lung disease became more severe. Previous TB is an independent risk factor for 
obstructive lung disease, even if the lesion is minimal and TB can be an important cause of 
obstructive lung disease in never-smokers. Effort on prevention and control of TB is crucial 
in reduction of obstructive lung disease, especially in countries with more than 
intermediate burden of TB. </p>

<p>Tuberculosis (TB) and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease 
(COPD) are major public health problems worldwide. Despite 
intensive global efforts, the total number of new TB cases is still 
increasing, with 9.27 million new cases and 1.78 million deaths 
in 2006 (1). The mortality rate of COPD is also increasing, and 
more than three million people worldwide were estimated to die 
from COPD in 2005 (2). About 80 million people worldwide are 
estimated to have moderate-to-severe COPD. Several previous 
reports have suggested an association between these two diseas-
es. There is a high and increasing prevalence of obstructive lung 
disease in patients who are being treated for pulmonary TB (3). 
A previous epidemiological study found that the prevalence of 
COPD may be different in subjects with and those without a 
history of TB (4). Another population-based study found that a 
history of TB is closely associated with airflow obstruction (5). 
Although some previous studies have shown an association 
of TB and obstructive lung disease, most of these studies had </p>

<p>small sample sizes and did not totally exclude the effect of smok-
ing, a potential and strong confounding factor. Smoking is a ma-
jor cause of COPD (6) and also increases the risk of developing 
TB (7). In most studies, a medical history of TB is based on self-
reporting, a method limited by recall bias. Patients with sponta-
neously healed TB will not report a history of TB, and that can be 
the cause of underestimation on the presence of TB (8). There-
fore, a previous TB should be also evaluated by chest imaging. 
In the present study, we evaluated the risk attributable to pul-
monary TB on the development of obstructive lung disease. We 
performed nationwide representative sampling in Korea, a coun-
try with an intermediate TB burden. We also evaluated the risk 
in patients with minimal TB lesions, and in patients who have 
never smoked. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Data collection 
We analyzed the Second Korea National Health and Nutrition </p>

<p>Lee SW, et al. • Tuberculosis and Obstructive Lung Disease </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>DOI: 10.3346/jkms.2011.26.2.268 </p>

<p>Examination Survey (KNHANES II) 2001 data that were prospec-
tively collected in 2001 by the Korea Institute for Health and So-
cial Affairs. Based on the 2000 Population Census of the Nation-
al Statistical Office of Korea, a stratified, multi-stage, clustered, 
probability design was used to select a representative sample of 
civilian, non-institutionalized Korean adults aged 18 yr and old-
er. Trained interviewers visited subjects' homes and adminis-
tered standardized questionnaires to determine health status. </p>

<p>Pulmonary function test 
Spirometry was conducted by trained pulmonary technicians 
according to the 1994 American Thoracic Society (ATS) recom-
mendations (9), using Dry Rolling-seal spirometry (Vmax-2130, 
Sensor-Medics, Yorba Linda, CA, USA). The electronically gen-
erated spirometric data were transferred via the internet to the 
review center on the same day. Two trained nurses reviewed the 
test results and provided quality control feedback to the techni-
cians. All data were saved for further analysis. Even though the 
ATS recommendations require three or more acceptable curves 
for an adequate test, this is not practical for a large-scale exami-
nation survey, so we analyzed only the data of subjects with two 
or more acceptable spirometry performances (10). The predict-
ed forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) and forced 
vital capacity (FVC) were derived from the survey data of life-
time nonsmoking subjects with normal chest radiographs and 
no history of respiratory disease or symptoms (11). Airflow ob-
struction was defined as FEV1/FVC less than 70% (6) or lower 
limit of normal (LLN) (12). </p>

<p>Chest radiograph (CXR) 
CXR images were taken in specially-equipped mobile exami-
nation cars at the time of spirometry. Two qualified radiologists 
evaluated CXRs independently using standard criteria for report-
ing of radiological abnormalities (13). If there was disagreement 
about interpretation of a CXR, the two radiologists discussed 
this with a third radiologist and reached a consensus. TB lesion </p>

<p>on CXR was defined as the presence of discrete linear or reticu-
lar fibrotic scars, or dense nodules with distinct margins, with 
or without calcification, within the upper lobes. Based on CXR 
findings, we categorized the TB lesion of each subject as mini-
mal, moderately advanced, or far-advanced, based on the clas-
sification of the National Tuberculosis and Respiratory Disease 
Association of the USA (14). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Comparisons between variables were tested using the chi-square 
test or Student's t-test. We constructed a logistic regression mod-
el with obstructive lung disease as the dependent variable and 
age, sex, smoking history (more than 2 weeks), and TB lesions 
on CXR as independent variables. A forward selection method 
was used to exclude multi-colinearity of each variable. Odds ra-
tios (ORs) were calculated with <rs id="software-0" type="software">PASW</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">17.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, 
IL, USA). </p>

<p>Ethics statement 
The institutional review board of the Asan Medical Center (Seoul, 
Korea) approved this analysis of the Korean population, which 
was prospectively collected. Informed consent was obtained 
from all subjects during the initial data collection. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Characteristics of enrolled subjects 
Among 9,243 subjects (&gt; 18 yr old), 8,209 (88.8%) responded to 
the questionnaires, 4,479 (48.5%) completed spirometry and 
CXR; and 3,687 (39.9%) subjects underwent at least two spirom-
etry measurements acceptable by ATS criteria with chest radio-
graph data (we analyzed these subjects). Although there was 
significant difference in age distribution between subjects en-
rolled and excluded, the pattern of sex, smoking status, respira-
tory symptoms, physician based diagnosis of COPD and asth-
ma, and mean age (43.4 yr in enrolled vs 43.1 yr in excluded, P = 
0.33) were similar, suggesting the data were representative (Table 
1). Among 3,687 enrolled for analysis, radiologists concluded 
that 294 (8.0%) subjects were classified as having TB lesion on 
CXR. All TB lesions were classified as inactive and there was no 
subject with lesion indicative of active TB on CXR. Two hundreds </p>

<p>Table 1. General characteristics of the subjects </p>

<p>Parameters 
Subjects enrolled 
(n = 3,687) </p>

<p>Subjects excluded 
(n = 4,522) 
P value </p>

<p>Age (yr): No. (%) 
18-34 
35-54 
55-74 
≥ 75 </p>

<p>1,098 (29.8) 
1,693 (45.9) 
838 (22.7) 
58 (1.2) </p>

<p>1,672 (37.0) 
1,740 (38.5) 
866 (19.2) 
244 (5.4) 
&lt; 0.001 
Male: No. (%) 
1,694 (45.9) 
2,055 (45.4) 
0.66 
Smoking status 
Never: No. (%) 
Ever: No. (%) 
≥ 20 pack-year: No. (%) </p>

<p>2,270 (62.4) 
1,385 (37.6) 
463 (12.7) </p>

<p>2,279 (61.2) 
1,750 (38.8) 
565 (12.6) </p>

<p>0.28 
0.95 
Cough: No. (%) 
46 (1.3) 
47 (1.1) 
0.40 
Sputum: No. (%) 
92 (2.6) 
85 (1.9) 
0.06 
Dx of COPD or asthma 
128 (3.5) 
156 (3.5) 
0.98 </p>

<p>Dx, physician diagnosis; COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. </p>

<p>Table 2. Pulmonary function of subjects with or without TB lesion on CXR </p>

<p>Parameters 
Subjects with 
TB lesion (n = 294) </p>

<p>Subjects without 
TB lesion (n = 3,393) 
P value </p>

<p>FVC (L) 
3.81 ± 0.95 
3.88 ± 0.94 
0.22 
FVC (%pred) 
94.9 ± 13.5 
98.3 ± 12.0 
&lt; 0.001 
FEV1 (L) 
2.83 ± 0.83 
3.16 ± 0.80 
&lt; 0.001 
FEV1 (%pred) 
89.5 ± 17.0 
97.2 ± 13.1 
&lt; 0.001 
FEV1/FVC (%) 
74.3 ± 10.8 
81.6 ± 7.8 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>CXR, chest X-rays; TB, tuberculosis; %pred, % of predicted value; FVC, forced vital 
capacity; FEV1, forced expiratory volume in one second. </p>

<p>Lee SW, et al. • Tuberculosis and Obstructive Lung Disease </p>



<p>DOI: 10.3346/jkms.2011.26.2.268 </p>

<p>and ninty subjects had minimal lesions and four subjects had 
moderately or far-advanced lesions. Initial interpretation be-
tween two radiologists about the presence of TB lesion showed 
almost perfect agreement (κ = 0.95, P &lt; 0.001) with 99.3% of agree-
ment rate. There were characteristic differences in sex, age and 
number of smokers between subjects with and without TB lesion 
on CXR. Group with TB lesion on CXR had higher mean age 
(53.3 ± 14.0 yr vs 42.5 ± 14.0 yr, P &lt; 0.001), more male sex (184/ 
294 [62.6%] vs 1,510/3,393 [44.5%], P &lt; 0.001) and more smok-
ers (156/294 [53.1%] vs 1,229/3,393 [36.2%], P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Pulmonary function as the presence of TB lesion on CXR 
Subjects with TB lesion had relatively lower FVC per predicted 
value (94.9 ± 13.5% vs 98.3 ± 12.0%, P &lt; 0.001), FEV1 (2.83 ± 0.83L 
vs 3.16 ± 0.80, P &lt; 0.001), FEV1 per predicted value (89.5 ± 17.0% 
vs 97.2 ± 13.1, P &lt; 0.001) and FEV1/FVC (74.3 ± 10.8% vs 81.6 ± 
7.8, P &lt; 0.001), compared with those without TB lesion on CXR. 
FVC did not show significant difference between two groups 
(Table 2). </p>

<p>The risk of airflow obstruction by TB lesions on CXR 
Based on univariate analysis, male sex, age, smoking history, 
and TB lesions were associated with airflow obstruction. After 
adjustment for sex, age, smoking history, TB lesions on CXR were 
still associated with airflow obstruction. Adjusted ORs were 2.56 
(95% CI = 1.84-3.56) by the definition of airflow obstruction FEV1/ </p>

<p>FVC &lt; 0.70 and 2.64 (95% CI = 1.97-3.52) by FEV1/FVC &lt; LLN. 
After excluding subjects with smoking histories and subjects 
with moderate or far-advanced TB lesions (n = 2,298), minimal 
TB lesions on CXR remained associated with airflow obstruc-
tion, with adjusted ORs of 3.13 (95% CI = 1.86-5.29) by the defi-
nition of airflow obstruction FEV1/FVC &lt; 0.70 and 4.02 (95% CI 
= 2.54-6.36) by FEV1/FVC &lt; LLN (Table 3). </p>

<p>Table 3. Risks of airflow obstruction by previous TB. Odd Ratios are analyzed in all enrolled subjects and in never smokers with exclusion of subjects with advanced TB lesion, 
separately </p>

<p>Parameters </p>

<p>Airflow obstruction defined as FEV1/FVC &lt; 0.70 
Airflow obstruction defined as FEV1/FVC &lt; LLN </p>

<p>No. (%) 
with airflow 
obstruction </p>

<p>Crude OR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Adjusted* OR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>No. (%) 
with airflow 
obstruction </p>

<p>Crude OR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Adjusted* OR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>All enrolled subjects 
3,687 
3,668 (100) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>TB lesion 
No previous TB 
Previous TB </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>3,393 
294 </p>

<p>219 (6.5) 
82 (27.9) 
5.61 (4.20-7.49) 
2.56 (1.84-3.56) </p>

<p>376 (11.1) 
89 (30.3) 
3.46 (2.64-4.54) 
2.64 (1.97-3.52) 
Smoking 
Never 
Ever </p>

<p>2,300 
1,387 </p>

<p>109 (4.7) 
192 (13.8) 
3.23 (2.53-4.13) 
1.88 (1.31-2.72) </p>

<p>175 (7.7) 
290 (21.0) 
3.21 (2.62-3.92) 
2.18 (1.62-2.94) 
Sex 
Female 
Male </p>

<p>1,993 
1,694 </p>

<p>87 (4.4) 
214 (12.6) 
3.17 (2.45-4.10) 
2.12 (1.44-3.11) </p>

<p>146 (7.4) 
319 (18.9) 
2.94 (2.38-3.61) 
1.56 (1.15-2.13) 
Age </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>2.34 (2.12-2.58) 
2.30 (2.07-2.54) 
1.19 (1.11-1.27) 
1.12 (1.04-1.20) 
Never smokers with exclusion 
of subjects with advanced 
TB lesion </p>

<p>2,300 
2,287 (100) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>TB lesion 
No previous TB 
Previous TB </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>2,162 
138 </p>

<p>84 (3.9) 
25 (18.1) 
5.47 (3.37-8.89) 
3.13 (1.86-5.29) </p>

<p>146 (6.8) 
29 (21.0) 
3.65 (2.35-5.68) 
4.02 (2.54-6.36) 
Sex 
Female 
Male </p>

<p>1,894 
406 </p>

<p>79 (4.2) 
30 (7.4) 
1.83 (1.19-2.83) 
1.73 (1.09-2.76) </p>

<p>135 (7.2) 
40 (9.9) 
1.42 (0.98-2.06) 
1.36 (0.94-1.98) 
Age </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>2.15 (1.85-2.50) 
2.05 (1.75-2.39) 
0.95 (0.85-1.05) 
0.89 (0.80-1.00) </p>

<p>*Adjusted for TB lesion on CXR, smoking history, sex and age; 
 † Subjects without data of height and weight were excluded in analysis; 
 ‡ Previous TB was defined by TB lesions 
on chest X-ray; 
 § Odds ratio as age increased by 10 yr. TB, tuberculosis; LLN, lower limit of normal; FVC, forced vital capacity; FEV1, forced expiratory volume in one second; OR, 
odds ratio; CI, confidence interval. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Proportion of subjects with TB lesion as the severity of airflow obstruction. % 
Pred, % of predicted value; TB, tuberculosis; FVC, forced vital capacity; FEV1, forced 
expiratory volume in one second. </p>

<p>Proportion of subjects with previous 
lesion (%) </p>

<p>FEV1/FVC &lt; 0.7 </p>

<p>5.2% </p>

<p>14.3% </p>

<p>P for trend &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P = 0.002 </p>

<p>P = 0.01 </p>

<p>34.0% </p>

<p>FEV1/FVC ≥ 0.7 
FEV1 ≥ 80%Pred 
FEV1 &lt; 80%Pred </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Lee SW, et al. • Tuberculosis and Obstructive Lung Disease </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>DOI: 10.3346/jkms.2011.26.2.268 </p>

<p>Subjects with TB lesions as severity of airflow obstruction 
among never smokers 
Among never smokers, the proportion of subjects with TB lesions 
increased as the severity of obstructive lung disease increased 
(P for trend &lt; 0.001). A total of 113 (5.2%) of 2,190 subjects with-
out airflow obstruction (FEV1/FVC &gt; 0.7) had TB lesions. Among 
subjects with airflow obstruction, 9 (14.3%) of 63 subjects with 
FEV1 ≥ 80% of predicted values, 16 (34.0%) of 47 with FEV1 &lt; 80% 
of predicted values had TB lesions (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, based on a nationwide representative sampling of 
Korean subjects, we found that previous TB was a risk factor for 
obstructive lung disease and even a minimal TB lesion was an 
also strong risk factor in never smokers. The proportions of sub-
jects with previous TB lesion increased as the severity of obstruc-
tive lung disease, suggesting previous TB is an important contrib-
uting factor for obstructive lung disease among never smokers. 
Previous studies have suggested that pulmonary TB is associ-
ated with obstructive lung disease. Patients with previous pul-
monary TB were more likely to suffer from acute exacerbation 
of COPD than those who did not have pulmonary TB (15). In 
silicosis patients, history of TB is an independent predictor of 
airflow obstruction (16). The bronchodilator response of pa-
tients with a tuberculous-destroyed lung is lower than that of 
patients with COPD (17). Airflow impairment is related to the 
radiological extent of TB (3) and to the number of TB episodes. 
However, most of these studies had small sample sizes, were 
not population-based, or did not fully adjust for smoking histo-
ry. A smoking history could potentially have biased the estimat-
ed effect of TB on loss of lung function. A previous study found 
that smoking history is associated with an increased risk of TB 
for a cohort of white gold miners, and smoking is known to in-
crease lung function loss (18). Recently, a population-based 
study of Latin American middle-aged and older adults found 
that previous medical diagnosis of TB was associated with air-
flow obstruction (5). A cohort study showed that radiologic evi-
dence of inactive TB was associated with increased risk of air-
flow obstruction, although it was not population-based (8). 
A history of TB may affect lung function by pleural change, 
bronchial stenosis, or parenchymal scarring. TB increases the 
activity of the matrix metalloproteinases, thus contributing to 
pulmonary damage (19). Extensive TB lesions may produce re-
strictive changes, with reduced transfer of carbon monoxide in 
the lung (20). However, we found that the presence of minimal 
lesions was also an independent risk factor for airflow obstruc-
tion. In these patients, airway fibrosis and inflammation may 
play important roles. TB infection is associated with airway fibro-
sis and the immune response to mycobacteria could cause air-
way inflammation, a characteristic of obstructive lung disease </p>

<p>(21). 
Smoking is a well-established major risk factor for COPD (22) 
and much COPD research has focused on smokers (23). How-
ever, recent evidence suggests that other risk factors are also im-
portant in causing obstructive lung disease, especially in devel-
oping countries. These factors include air pollutants, dust and 
fumes, history of repeated lower respiratory tract infections dur-
ing childhood, chronic asthma, intrauterine growth retardation, 
poor nourishment, and poor socioeconomic status. Several ques-
tionnaire studies have also suggested that a history of TB is a risk 
factor for airflow obstruction (24, 25). In our study, 22.7% (25/ 
110) of never smokers with airflow obstruction had TB lesions, 
and the proportion increased for subjects with FEV1 &lt; 80% of 
predicted value. This suggests that previous TB can be an impor-
tant cause of obstructive lung disease among never smokers. 
In this study, we defined airflow obstruction as FEV1/FVC 
less than 0.70 or LLN. Although a fixed ratio of 0.70 is simple and 
widely used, it is criticized due to over-diagnosis of both the pres-
ence and severity of COPD in the elderly (26). TB lesion on CXR 
was still associated with airflow obstruction (adjusted OR = 2.66, 
95% CI 1.99-3.55, P &lt; 0.001) and it is consistent in never smok-
ers (adjusted OR = 4.02, 95% CI 2.54-6.36, P &lt; 0.001), when we 
defined obstructive lung disease by LLN. We enrolled subjects 
with two or more acceptable spirometry performances for prac-
tical consideration of a large-scale examination survey. ATS and 
European Respiratory Society (ERS) recommendations was pub-
lished after this survey, requiring three or more acceptable cur-
ves for an adequate test with the differance in the two largest 
values of FVC or FEV1 &lt; 0.150 L (27). When we adopted this rec-
ommendation (n = 2,533), TB lesion on CXR was still associated 
with airflow obstruction (FEV1/FVC &lt; 0.70) with adjusted OR = 
2.20, 95% CI 1.44-3.35, P &lt; 0.001) and it was also consistent in 
never smokers (adjusted OR = 3.38, 95% CI 1.75-6.55, P = 0.001). 
This study has some limitations. First, airflow obstruction was 
defined by FEV1/FVC rather than post-bronchodilator FEV1/FVC. 
This might lead to an overestimate of the prevalence of obstruc-
tive lung disease. However, our estimates are similar to those of 
previous studies. Second, previous TB was only evaluated by 
CXR and clinical history was not examined. From a specificity 
point of view, a lesion that seems to be TB-related on CXR could 
be a sequela of other diseases such as pneumonia. From a view 
of sensitivity, CXR could miss some parenchymal TB lesions, 
which can only be identified by computed tomography (CT) 
analysis (28, 29). In addition, some TB patients might have had 
complete healing without any evidence on the CXR. Although 
CXR has limitations in confirming previous TB, in the present 
study 3 qualified radiologists interpreted the CXRs to reduce this 
limitation and interpretation on CXRs of radiologists showed 
almost perfect agreement. Third, there was relatively large num-
ber of subjects with TB lesion on CXR (8.0%), compared with 
the number of TB reports in Korea (30). In other study, the prev-</p>

<p>Lee SW, et al. • Tuberculosis and Obstructive Lung Disease </p>



<p>DOI: 10.3346/jkms.2011.26.2.268 </p>

<p>alence of prior TB based on self-reports (2.9%) was also signifi-
cantly lower than that defined by CXR (24.2%) (8). Considering 
this discrepancy between radiologic evidence and self-report of 
TB and continuously decreasing annual incidence in Korea, our 
interpretations of TB lesion on CXR do not seem to go beyond 
reasonable level. Fourth, there were only four subjects with ad-
vanced TB lesion. In this survey, subjects should visit a car with 
special equipment to undergo spirometry. Therefore, the possi-
bility of selection bias, to enroll relatively healthy subjects main-
ly, cannot be excluded. 
In conclusion, previous TB was an independent risk factor 
for obstructive lung disease, even if the lesions are minimal. TB 
could be also an important cause of airflow obstruction in sub-
jects who had never smoked. The results of this population-based 
study indicated that appropriate management and control of 
TB is as important as smoking quitting for reducing obstructive 
lung disease. </p>



<p>Lee SW, et al. • Tuberculosis and Obstructive Lung Disease </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>





<p>AUTHOR SUMMARY </p>

<p>The Risk of Obstructive Lung Disease by Previous Pulmonary Tuberculosis in a 
Country with Intermediate Burden of Tuberculosis </p>

<p>Sei Won Lee, Young Sam Kim, Dong-Soon Kim, Yeon-Mok Oh, and Sang-Do Lee </p>

<p>We evaluated the effects of previous pulmonary tuberculosis (TB) on the risk of obstructive lung disease. We analyzed population-
based, the Second Korea National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey 2001. Participants underwent chest X-rays (CXR) and 
spirometry, and qualified radiologists interpreted the presence of TB lesion independently. Among 3,687 participants, 294 subjects 
had evidence of previous TB on CXR. Evidence of previous TB on CXR were independently associated with airflow obstruction (odds 
ratios = 2.56, 95% CI 1.84-3.56) after adjustment for sex, age and smoking history. Previous TB was still a risk factor with 
exclusion of ever smokers or subjects with advanced lesion on CXR. Previous TB is an independent risk factor for obstructive lung 
disease, even if the lesion is minimal and TB can be an important cause of obstructive lung disease in never smokers. </p>

</text></tei>