<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3863651" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Study Design: Prospective study. 
Purpose: The main purpose of this study was to clarify the range of magnification errors on digital plain radiographs and to deter-
mine if there is a correlation between the body mass index (BMI) of a patient and the magnification error. 
Overview of Literature: Most clinicians currently use digital plain radiography. This new method allows one to access images and 
measure lengths and angles more easily than with the past technologies. In addition, conventional plain radiography has magnifica-
tion errors. Although few articles mention magnification errors in regards to digital radiographs, they are known to have the same 
errors. 
Methods: We used plain digital radiography and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) to acquire images of the cervical spine with the 
goal of evaluating magnification errors by measuring the anteroposterior vertebral body lengths of C2 and C5. The magnification error 
(ME) was then calculated: ME=(length on radiograph-length on MRI)/length on MRI ×100 (%). The correlation coefficient between the 
magnification error and BMI was obtained using Pearson's correlation analysis. 
Results: Average magnification errors in C2 and C5 were approximately 18.5%±5.4% (range, 0%-30%) and 20.7%±6.3% (range, 
1%-32%). There was no positive correlation between BMI and the magnification error. 
Conclusions: There were magnification errors on the digital plain radiographs, and they were different in each case. Maximum mag-
nification error differences were 30% (C2) and 31% (C5). Based on these finding, clinicians must pay attention to magnification errors 
when measuring lengths using digital plain radiography. </p>

<p>Clinical Study </p>

<p>Asian Spine J 2013;7(4):267-272 • http://dx.In the past, conventional hard-copy radiography images 
have been used. Currently, most clinicians (including 
ourselves) use digital plain radiography. This new method 
allows one to access images and measure lengths and </p>

<p>angles more easily than with past technologies. The com-
puter systems and programs used for this purpose are ge-
nerically known as picture archiving and communication 
systems (PACSs). 
Conventional plain radiographs have been reported to 
have some magnification errors [1]. Although few articles </p>

<p>Hideki Shigematsu et al. 
 
Asian Spine J 2013;7(4):267-272 </p>

<p>have mentioned magnification errors in regard to digital 
radiographs, they too exhibit these errors because digital 
radiography uses the same method to acquire photo-
graphs as conventional radiography. Clinicians may be-
lieve that digital radiography calculates the magnification 
error after uploading because of its simplicity, but this is 
not correct. When clinicians do not recognize this point, 
they may misjudge what is normal or abnormal. Spine 
surgeons frequently treat cervical spine diseases, such 
as dislocation and subluxation as well as spine trauma 
including fractures. As a guide, surgeons will use criteria 
based on distances measured on the radiograph. Because 
the cervical spine is comprised of a small proportion of 
bone tissue, a magnification error is an important consid-
eration when making medical decisions. 
The primary aim of this study was to assess the range 
of the magnification error on digital cervical plain radio-
graphs. The secondary aim was to evaluate whether there 
was a correlation between the body mass index (BMI) of 
a patient and the degree of magnification error on digital 
plain radiographs. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>We used <rs id="software-0" type="software">PACS software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Centricity SEJ, GE Healthcare, Milwaukee, WI, USA</rs>) to access cervical digital radio-</p>

<p>graphs (FCR Velocity, Fujifilm, Tokyo, Japan) and mag-
netic resonance imaging (MRI) scans (1.5T, SignaHDxt, 
GE Healthcare) of our outpatients to calculate the magni-
fication error. 
We recruited 54 patients (26 men, 28 women). We in-
cluded only patients with cervical radiculopathy, cervical 
myelopathy, or mechanical neck pain who had under-
went both digital radiography and MRI at the cervical 
level from January 2009 to August 2009 in our outpatient 
department. Our exclusion criteria included the presence 
of tumors, fractures, or infection in the cervical spine. 
We chose C2 and C5 for assessment and measured 
the anteroposterior vertebral body length on the lateral 
cervical radiographs (Fig. 1A) [2]. In two of the patients, 
we were unable to confirm the presence of C5 clearly be-
cause of a short neck. The source beam was positioned a 
standard 150 cm away from the X-ray plate (Fig. 2). The 
midline T2-weighted sagittal images were used to assess 
the length (Fig. 1B). We were able to analyze C2 in 54 
cases and C5 in 52 cases with digital plain radiography, 
and corresponding MRI was performed in these cases. 
All measurements of length were conducted by the 
same researcher and were performed on two occasions on 
different days. Intraobserver agreement was calculated, 
and an average of the two measured values was obtained. 
To determine interobserver agreement, another doctor, </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Fig. 1. (A) Measurements on the digital plain radiograph. (B) Measurements on magnetic resonance imaging. </p>

<p>Magnification error in cervical spine </p>

<p>Asian Spine Journal 
Asian Spine Journal </p>



<p>who was blinded to the patients' information, measured 
the same radiographs and MRI scans. The intraobserver 
and interobserver agreement for measurements were 
found to be excellent. 
The interobserver error was as follows: radiography at 
C2: 0.967 (95% confidence interval [CI], 0.943-0.981); 
radiography at C5: 0.970 (95% CI, 0.948-0.983); MRI at 
C2: 0.958 (95% CI, 0.928-0.976), MRI at C5: 0.928 (95% 
CI, 0.874-0.959). 
The intraobserver error was as follows: radiography 
at C2: 0.937 (95% CI, 0.892-0.963), radiography at C5: 
0.947 (95% CI, 0.909-0.983); MRI at C2: 0.828 (95% CI, 
0.705-0.900), MRI at C5: 0.862 (95% CI, 0.761-0.921). 
The magnification error (ME) was calculated as follows: </p>

<p>ME= (length on radiograph-length on MRI)/length on 
MRI×100 (%). </p>

<p>Based on the BMI, we divided these patients into an 
underweight group (&lt;18.5 kg/m 
2 ) and an overweight </p>

<p>group (&gt;25 kg/m 
2 ) for further assessment. The correla-</p>

<p>tion coefficient between the magnification error and BMI 
was obtained using Pearson's correlation analysis. The 
Mann-Whitney's U-test was used to evaluate the differ-
ence between the underweight and overweight groups. 
p&lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. 
Our institutional review board approved this study. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The demographic data are as follows and are expressed </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Positioning the patient for photography. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Correlation between the magnification error and the patients' 
body mass index (BMI) values at C2. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Correlation between the magnification error and the patients' 
body mass index (BMI) at C5. </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographics of the subjects used in this study </p>

<p>Characteristic 
C2 
C5 </p>

<p>Sex (cases) </p>

<p>Male 
26 
25 </p>

<p>Female 
28 
27 </p>

<p>Age (yr) </p>

<p>Male 
61.1±13.3 
60.8±13.5 </p>

<p>Female 
55.6±15.7 
54.7±15.5 </p>

<p>Height (cm) </p>

<p>Male 
165.3± 5.6 
165.6±5.6 </p>

<p>Female 
156.7± 8.2 
157.1±8.1 </p>

<p>Weight (kg) </p>

<p>Male 
65.0±9.7 
65.2±9.9 </p>

<p>Female 
54.7±8.2 
54.5±8.4 </p>

<p>Body mass index (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Male 
23.8±3.3 
23.8±3.4 </p>

<p>Female 
22.2±2.8 
22.1±2.7 </p>

<p>Hideki Shigematsu et al. 
 
Asian Spine J 2013;7(4):267-272 </p>

<p>as the averages±standard deviation (Table 1). 1) C2: 54 
patients (26 men; age, 61.1±13.3 years; BMI, 23.8±3.3 kg/ 
m 
2 ; 28 women; age; 55.6±15.7 years; BMI, 22.2±2.8 kg/ </p>

<p>m 
2 ). 2) C5: 52 patients (25 men; age, 60.8±13.5 years; </p>

<p>BMI, 23.8±3.4 kg/m 
2 ; 27 women; age, 54.7±15.5 years; </p>

<p>BMI, 22.1±2.7 kg/m 
2 ). </p>

<p>The ages of the patients ranged from 25 to 86 years (av-
erage, 58.2±14.8 years). 
The overall radiography measurements were 19.2±1.9 
mm (range, 15.1-24.3 mm) at C2 and 21.6±3.3 mm 
(range, 14.8-32.4 mm) at C5. The overall MRI measure-
ments were 16.2±1.5 mm (range, 13.4-22.0 mm) at C2 
and 17.8±2.4 mm (range, 13.1-25.9 mm) at C5. 
The magnification results are summarized in Table 
2. The average magnification errors in C2 and C5 were 
approximately 18.5%±5.4% (range, 0%-30%) and 
20.7%±6.3% (range, 1%-32%). There was no significant 
difference between the magnification errors in C2 and C5 
(p=0.08, Mann-Whitney U-test), and there was no sig-
nificant correlation between BMI and the magnification 
error (C2: r=0.07, p=0.60; C5: r=0.23, p=0.11) (Figs. 3, 4). 
We analyzed the data for the sexes but found no signifi-
cant correlation between BMI and magnification error. 
We divided the cases based on our definition of the 
BMI values (kg/m 
2 ): &lt;18.5, underweight group; &gt;25.0, </p>

<p>overweight group). The underweight group was com-
prised of five patients examined at C2 and five at C5. The </p>

<p>overweight group was comprised of 14 patients exam-
ined at C2 and 13 at C5. In the underweight group, the 
magnification error at C2 and C5 was 21.0%±3.8% and 
21.2%±6.5%, respectively. In the overweight group, the 
magnification error at C2 and C5 was 19.8%±4.8% and 
21.2%±5.6%. There was no significant difference in the 
magnification errors between the two groups (Table 3). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, we evaluated the magnification errors on 
digital plain radiographs. The errors varied among the 
different cases (0%-32%) (Figs. 3, 4); however, a signifi-
cant correlation between the patients' BMIs and the de-
gree of the magnification errors was not observed. Also, 
there was no significant difference in the magnification 
errors between the underweight and overweight groups. 
A number of previous studies have examined the mag-
nification error on pelvic radiographs [3-6]. For accurate 
preoperative planning of total hip replacement, it is im-
portant to know and take into account the magnification 
error. Few studies have examined the magnification error 
on digital films at the cervical spine. Spine surgeons usu-
ally use radiographs for diagnosis and/or assessment. For 
example, atlantoaxial subluxation is diagnosed in patients 
with an atlantodental interval &gt;3 mm [7], and subaxial 
subluxation is diagnosed when there is &gt;2 mm displace-</p>

<p>Table 2. Effect of the subjects' body mass index on the magnification error </p>

<p>Level 
Body mass index 
% Magnification error 
p-value </p>

<p>C2 </p>

<p>All (n=54) 
23.0±3.1 
18.5±5.4 
0.60 </p>

<p>Male (n=26) 
23.8±3.3 
19.4±6.0 
0.75 </p>

<p>Female (n=28) 
22.2±2.8 
17.5±4.8 
0.40 </p>

<p>C5 </p>

<p>All (n=52) 
22.9±3.1 
20.7±6.3 
0.11 </p>

<p>Male (n=25) 
23.8±3.4 
23.0±5.5 
0.70 </p>

<p>Female (n=27) 
22.1±2.7 
18.6±6.4 
0.28 </p>

<p>Table 3. Effect of being underweight or overweight on the magnification error </p>

<p>Level 
Underweight group (BMI&lt;18.5) 
Overweight group (BMI&gt;25) 
p-value </p>

<p>C2 
21.0±3.8 
19.8±4.8 
0.60 </p>

<p>C5 
21.2±6.5 
21.2±5.6 
0.99 </p>

<p>BMI, body mass index. </p>

<p>Magnification error in cervical spine </p>

<p>Asian Spine Journal 
Asian Spine Journal </p>



<p>ment [8]. Because it is important that we still use the unit 
of length, not a ratio, when addressing the cervical spine, 
we thought that it would be meaningful to know the de-
gree of magnification error that occurs. 
Theoretically, the magnification error is determined 
based on the distance between the film and the spine [6], 
which depends on maintaining the distance from the film 
and not altering the focus. That is, if the object moves 
away from the film, the magnification error increases. 
Ravi and Rampersaud [2] reported that the magnifica-
tion error was correlated with the patient's BMI. Based on 
their study, the distance between the film and the spine 
might increase as the BMI increases. 
We did not find a significant correlation between the 
patients' BMIs and the magnification errors. There are 
some possible reasons for this lack of correlation. First, 
the BMIs of our patients ranged between 16.0 kg/m 
2 and </p>

<p>33.3 kg/m 
2 , and within this range there might not be sig-</p>

<p>nificant differences in the distance between the film and 
the cervical spine. Second, although we determined that 
the distance of the film to the source of the beam was 150 
cm without exception for the cervical spine, clinically 
there was a possibility that the distance was different for 
each patient because the radiology technician usually 
obtained numerous radiographs in the outpatient de-
partment and might not have been able to maintain the 
precise distance. Although we cannot determine precisely 
why these individual differences occurred, we believe the 
important consideration is that digital plain radiography 
always has a magnification error, which is similar to hard-
copy radiography, and there is great variability among 
patients. 
Routine use of computed tomography (CT) and MRI 
for diagnostic purposes has resulted in more widespread 
radiation exposure. It has also put a greater demand on 
the radiology department, with increased costs. Plain 
radiography is inexpensive, and we can evaluate dynamic 
factors from flexion and/or extension views-points that 
are advantageous when compared with CT or MRI. Con-
sequently, measurements from plain radiographs cannot 
be completely eliminated by assessing cervical spine dis-
orders. 
Our study has some limitations. First, we did not in-
clude patients with a high BMI (e.g., BMI, 40-50 kg/m 
2 ), </p>

<p>so we could not evaluate magnification errors of high-
BMI patients. Second, we did not directly evaluate the 
correlation between BMI and the distance from the film </p>

<p>to the spine. Third, we used MRI for the alternative mea-
surement. Although measurements taken from CT im-
ages are accurate to within 1 mm of the actual size [9], a 
previous study showed that MRI is as accurate as CT [2]. 
Even with these limitations, we clarified the difference 
in magnification errors among patients. Again, we believe 
that the most important point is that there are magnifica-
tion errors to consider when using digital plain radiog-
raphy and that these errors vary widely among patients. 
Although there are many clinical scenarios where linear 
measurements from plain radiographs are used to assist 
in diagnostic and/or clinical decision-making, clinicians 
need to consider and compensate for magnification er-
ror. We also recommend evaluating cervical spine digital 
radiographs using an angle or a ratio (e.g., percent slip in 
the lumbar spine), neither of which is influenced by the 
magnification error. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>In this study, we identified magnification errors when 
using digital plain radiography, and their degree varied 
among patients. There was no significant correlation 
between BMI and the magnification error. Finally, when 
using digital plain radiography for measurements, the 
magnification error should be measured and taken into 
consideration. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article 
was reported. </p>



<p>Hideki Shigematsu et al. 
 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>