<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3624981" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: The aim of this study was to evaluate short-term clinical outcomes by comparing hand-assisted laparoscopic sur-
gery (HALS) with open surgery for sigmoid colon cancer. 
Methods: Twenty-six patients who underwent a hand-assisted laparoscopic anterior resection (HAL-AR group) and 52 pa-
tients who underwent a conventional open anterior resection during the same period were enrolled (open group) in this 
study with a case-controlled design. 
Results: Pathologic parameters were similar between the two groups. The incidences of immediate postoperative leukocytosis 
were 38.5% in the HAL-AR group and 69.2% in the open group (P = 0.009). There were no significant differences between 
the two groups as to leukocyte count, hemoglobin, and hematocrits (P = 0.758, P = 0.383, and P = 0.285, respectively). Of 
the postoperative recovery indicators, first flatus, sips of water and soft diet started on postoperative days 3, 5, 7 in the HALS 
group and on days 4, 5, 6 in the open group showed statistical significance (P = 0.021, P = 0.259, and P = 0.174, respectively). 
Administration of additional pain killers was needed for 1.2 days in the HAL-AR group and 2.4 days in the open group (P = 
0.002). No significant differences in the durations of hospital stay and the rates of postoperative complications were noted, 
and no postoperative mortality was encountered in either group. 
Conclusion: The patients with sigmoid colon cancer who underwent a HAL-AR had a lower incidence of postoperative 
leukocytosis, less administration of pain killers, and faster first flatus than those who underwent open surgery. Clinical 
outcomes for patients' recovery and pathology status were similar between the two groups. Therefore, a HAL-AR for sig-
moid colon cancer is feasible and has the same benefit as minimally invasive surgery. </p>

<p>extended with the development of new instruments [1-4]. Lapa-
roscopic surgery has many advantages, such as smaller incision, 
less pain, faster postoperative recovery, and shorter hospital stay; 
however, limitations, such as its complexity, long operation time, 
long learning curve and lack of tactile feedback, still exist [1]. 
Hand-assisted laparoscopic surgery (HALS) originated from us-
ing a mini-laparotomy for specimen retrieval or an extracorporeal 
procedure in pure laparoscopic surgery [2]. This procedure is a 
kind of minimally invasive surgery, but has the features of open 
surgery [2]. The most remarkable factor of HALS is that the oper-
ator's hand can be placed into the intra-abdominal cavity. The op-
erator's hand can palpate organs or tumors, retract structures gen-
tly, identify vessels, and provide finger pressure to bleeding points. 
In other words, HALS is a kind of hybrid procedure between pure 
laparoscopic surgery and conventional open surgery [2]. Although 
many studies related to the use of HALS for treating colorectal dis-</p>

<p>Since laparoscopic colorectal surgery was introduced in the early 
1990s, minimally invasive surgery for colorectal diseases has been </p>

<p>Received: January 31, 2013 • Accepted: February 15, 2013 
Correspondence to: Dae-Yong Hwang, M.D. 
Department of Surgery, Colorectal Cancer Center, Konkuk University Medical 
Center, Konkuk University School of Medicine, 120 Neungdong-ro, 
Gwangjin-gu, Seoul 143-729, Korea 
Tel: +82-2-2030-5111, Fax: +82-2-2030-5112 
E-mail: hwangcrc@kuh.ac.kr </p>

<p>This was presented at 64th Annual Congress of the Korean Surgical Society. </p>

<p>© 2013 The Korean Society of Coloproctology </p>

<p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-
Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted non-
commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Annals of </p>

<p>Coloproctology </p>

<p>www.coloproctol.org 
18 </p>

<p>Feasibility of Hand-Assisted Laparoscopic Surgery as Compared to Open Surgery for 
Sigmoid Colon Cancer: A Case-Controlled Study </p>

<p>Sang Eun Nam, et al. </p>

<p>ease have been performed, few reports comparing HALS to open 
surgery in patients with sigmoid colon cancer have been published. 
Therefore, the aim of this study was to assess the clinico-patho-
logic parameters and the short-term clinical outcomes of a hand-
assisted laparoscopic anterior resection (HAL-AR) in patients with 
sigmoid colon cancer by comparing them to those of a conven-
tional open anterior resection. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Using the prospectively collected colorectal cancer database at our 
institute, we designed a case-controlled study. Between January 
2009 and October 2011, of the patients with an adenocarcinoma 
on the sigmoid colon, 26 who underwent a HAL-AR (HAL-AR 
group) and 52 who underwent a conventional open anterior re-
section (open group) were enrolled as the study and the control 
groups, respectively. Patients in the control group were selected so 
as to be case-matched with those in the HAL-AR group in the as-
pects of age, sex, and tumor-node-metastasis (TNM) stage. All 
patients underwent a curative resection by one experienced sur-
geon. Patients with cancer obstruction or perforation were ex-
cluded, as were patients who underwent emergent surgery. 
In postoperative care, patient-controlled analgesia (PCA) was 
applied for all patients, and additional intravenous analgesia was 
administrated when required. Sips of water began when patients 
had no discomfort in the abdomen after first flatus, and soft diet 
was started one day after. Patients were discharged when soft diet 
was tolerable and they agreed. Regular laboratory tests were per-
formed on postoperative days 1, 2, 4, and 7; especially, a postoper-</p>

<p>ative white blood cell count in analysis was done on postoperative 
day 1. Between the HAL-AR group and the open group, clinico-
pathologic, intraoperative and postoperative parameters were an-
alyzed statistically. </p>

<p>Surgical techniques 
Under endotracheal intubation, the patient was positioned on the 
surgical table in a modified lithotomy position by using Allen's 
stirrups, and a pneumatic compression device was applied to the 
patient's legs. The operative field was prepared in the usual man-
ner and draped. The operating room setup for the HAL-AR is 
shown in Fig. 1. 
First, a Pfannenstiel incision with a 7-cm length was made on the 
lower abdomen, and a Gelport (Applied Medical Resources Co., 
Rancho Santa Margarita, CA, USA) was applied to the skin at the 
incision. A Gelport is a kind of hand-port that can maintain the 
pneumoperitoneum while the surgeon's hand is in the abdominal 
cavity. On the right and the left sides of the abdomen at the level 
of the umbilicus, outside the rectus abdominis muscle, a 12-mm 
trocar was inserted, and a pneumoperitoneum was made with 
CO2 gas. 
Then, the surgeon, who was located between the patient's legs, 
inserted the laparoscopic camera via the right-side port. The sur-
geon's left hand was inserted into the hand-port, and the inferior 
mesenteric artery was isolated and ligated with clips by using a 
laparoscopic device inserted via the left-side port. Then, the sig-
moid colon mesentery was dissected using the medial-to-lateral 
approach. After complete dissection of the sigmoid colon, the 
Gelport was removed, and next steps were conducted as in open 
surgery. The sigmoid colon was resected, and a specimen was de-
livered. Anastomosis was performed using the hand-sewn or dou-
ble-stapled method. After warm saline irrigation and meticulous 
hemostasis, the Gelport was reapplied, and a pneumoperitoneum 
was made to check the anastomosis alignment and the dissection 
plane for bleeding. A Jackson-Pratt drain was inserted into the 
pelvic cavity via the left port. The right port and the Pfannenstiel 
incision were closed layer by layer after the Gelport had again been 
removed. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Data analysis was performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 14.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., 
Chicago, IL, USA). Summary statistics using the chi-squared test, 
the two-sample t-test with Welch's correction, and Fisher's exact 
test were used to compare the HAL-AR group with the open group. 
Statistical significance was associated with P-values less than 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The total 78 cases consisted of 26 in the HAL-AR group and 52 in 
the open group. As to the patients' characteristics, the gender ratio 
(male : female) was 1.9 :1 (17 vs. 9) in the HAL-AR group and 1.9: 
1 (34 vs. 18) in the open group (P = 0.596). The mean age was 60 </p>

<p>M 
O 
N 
I 
T 
O 
R </p>

<p>M 
O 
N 
I 
T 
O 
R </p>

<p>Camera/ 
assistant 
Assistant </p>

<p>Surgeon </p>

<p>Anesthesiologist </p>

<p>Hand port ( 7 cm) </p>

<p>12-mm 
12-mm </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Operating-room setup for hand-assisted laparoscopic ante-
rior resection. </p>

<p>Annals of </p>

<p>Coloproctology </p>

<p>www.coloproctol.org 
19 </p>

<p>Volume 29, Number 1, 2013 </p>

<p>Ann Coloproctol 2013;29(1):17-21 </p>

<p>years in the HAL-AR group and 61 years in the open group (P = 
0.465). No significant differences existed between the groups in </p>

<p>terms of gender, age, comorbidity, body mass index, obstruction, 
or tumor markers (Table 1). 
The mean operation time was 224 minutes in the HAL-AR group 
and 195 minutes in the open group (P = 0.162). The operation 
time in the open group was slightly, but not significantly, shorter 
than it was in the HAL-AR group. No conversion to open surgery 
was needed in the HAL-AR group, and no intraoperative compli-</p>

<p>Table 1. Patients' characteristics </p>

<p>Characteristic 
HAL-AR group (n=26) 
Open group (n=52) 
P-value </p>

<p>Gender (M:F) 
17:9 
34:18 
0.596 </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
60.0 ± 12.6 
61.3 ± 9.9 
0.465 </p>

<p>Body mass index (kg/m 
2 ) 
24.6 ± 3.2 
23.6 ± 4.6 
0.769 </p>

<p>Preoperative comorbidities 
11 (42.3) 
36 (69.2) </p>

<p>Hypertension 
3 (11.4) 
8 (15.4) 
0.067 </p>

<p>Diabetes mellitus 
5 (19.2) 
18 (34.6) 
0.126 </p>

<p>Pulmonary tuberculosis 
2 (7.7) 
2 (3.8) 
0.407 </p>

<p>Others </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1 (3.8) 
8 (15.4) 
0.127 </p>

<p>Obstruction </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>3 (11.5) 
3 (5.8) 
0.315 </p>

<p>Incidence of preoperative carcinoembryonal antigen elevation 
2 (7.7) 
10 (19.2) 
0.159 </p>

<p>Incidence of preoperative carbohydrate antigen 19-9 elevation 
0 (0) 
3 (5.8) 
0.290 </p>

<p>Level of preoperative carcinoembryonal antigen (ng/mL) 
5.6 ± 14.0 
4.7 ± 7.5 
0.448 </p>

<p>Level of preoperative carbohydrate antigen 19-9 (ng/mL) 
10.7 ± 8.1 
12.0 ± 16.7 
0.054 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation or number (%). 
HAL-AR, hand-assisted laparoscopic anterior resection. 
a HAL-AR group, cerebral infarction; open group, stomach cancer, atrial septal defect, valvular heart disease, cerebral infarction, congestive heart failure, chronic renal fail-
ure, and chronic liver disease. 
b Preoperative colonic stent was inserted. </p>

<p>Table 2. Operative and pathologic parameters in the HAL-AR and 
the open groups </p>

<p>Parameter 
HAL-AR group 
(n=26) </p>

<p>Open group 
(n=52) 
P-value </p>

<p>Operation time (min) 
224.4 ± 31.7 
( 192-256 ) </p>

<p>195.2 ± 66.4 
(129-261) </p>

<p>0.162 </p>

<p>Conversion case 
0 (0) </p>

<p>Intraoperative complication 
0 (0) 
0 (0) </p>

<p>Anastomosis method 
0.070 </p>

<p>Double stapled 
23 
51 </p>

<p>Hand-sewn 
3 
1 </p>

<p>TNM stage 
0.688 </p>

<p>0 
2 
5 </p>

<p>I 
11 
16 </p>

<p>II 
4 
13 </p>

<p>III 
9 
18 </p>

<p>Tumor size (cm) 
3.1 ± 2.2 
3.7 ± 4.1 
0.338 </p>

<p>No. of retrieved lymph node 
17.5 ± 9.2 
15.3 ± 7.8 
0.211 </p>

<p>Lymphatic invasion 
3 (11.5) 
13 (25.0) 
0.137 </p>

<p>Perineural invasion 
1 (3.8) 
3 (5.8) 
0.593 </p>

<p>Venous invasion 
1 (3.8) 
1 (1.9) 
0.558 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation (range) or number (%). 
HAL-AR, hand-assisted laparoscopic anterior resection; TNM, tumor-node-metas-
tasis. </p>

<p>Table 3. Postoperative laboratory data and recovery parameters </p>

<p>HAL-AR group 
(n=26) </p>

<p>Open group 
(n=52) 
P-value </p>

<p>Leukocytosis 
10 (38.5) 
36 (69.2) 
0.009 </p>

<p>WBC count difference (/µL) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>5,600 ± 3,500 4,300 ± 2,800 
0.758 </p>

<p>Extra-pain killer use 
22 (84.6) 
48 (92.3) 
0.249 </p>

<p>Day of pain killer administration 
1.2 ± 0.8 
2.4 ± 3.0 
0.002 </p>

<p>Day to flatus (day) 
3.2 ± 1.8 
3.8 ± 1.1 
0.021 </p>

<p>Day to sips of water (day) 
4.9 ± 1.8 
4.5 ± 1.3 
0.259 </p>

<p>Day to soft diet (day) 
6.8 ± 2.1 
6.2 ± 1.5 
0.174 </p>

<p>Day to discharge (day) 
11.7 ± 3.8 
11.5 ± 4.0 
0.923 </p>

<p>Postoperative complication 
0 (0) 
1 (1.9) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.667 </p>

<p>Readmission 
0 (0) 
0 (0) </p>

<p>Reoperation 
0 (0) 
0 (0) </p>

<p>Mortality 
0 (0) 
0 (0) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%) or mean ± standard deviation. 
HAL-AR, hand-assisted laparoscopic anterior resection; WBC, white blood cell. 
a Postoperative WBC count-preoperative WBC count. 
b Postoperative ileus problem. </p>

<p>Annals of </p>

<p>Coloproctology </p>

<p>www.coloproctol.org 
20 </p>

<p>Feasibility of Hand-Assisted Laparoscopic Surgery as Compared to Open Surgery for 
Sigmoid Colon Cancer: A Case-Controlled Study </p>

<p>Sang Eun Nam, et al. </p>

<p>cations were encountered in either group. In most cases, the co-
lonic anastomosis was performed mainly using the double-stapled 
method. Between the two groups, no significant differences were 
noted in either the distribution of TNM stages or pathologic fac-
tors, such as tumor size, number of retrieved lymph nodes, and 
lymphovascular or neural invasion (Table 2). 
The postoperative parameters for the two groups are shown in 
Table 3. The incidence of immediate postoperative leukocytosis in 
the HAL-AR group (38.5%) was significantly lower than it was in 
the open group (69.2%) (P = 0.009). No significant differences 
were noted between the two groups in regard to leukocyte count, 
hemoglobin and hematocrits (P = 0.758, P = 0.383, and P = 0.285, 
respectively). Compared to patients in the open group, those in 
the HAL-AR group used significantly fewer pain killers and expe-
rienced earlier passage of flatus after surgery. Administration of 
additional pain killers was needed for 1.2 days in the HAL-AR 
group and 2.4 days in the open group (P = 0.002). No significant 
differences in hospital stay (11.7 days vs. 11.5 days, P = 0.923) and 
postoperative complications (0 vs. 1, P = 0.667) were noted. The 
one complication in the open surgery group was postoperative il-
eus, and that patient recovered after conservative management. No 
postoperative mortality or reoperation occurred in either group. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>According to our data, compared to the patients in the conven-
tional open anterior resection group, those who received a HAL-
AR for sigmoid colon cancer experienced the following advan-
tages: a lower incidence of postoperative leukocytosis, less admin-
istration of pain killers and faster recovery of gastrointestinal func-
tion. These factors mean less surgical trauma, less pain and faster 
recovery, which are also the advantages of minimally invasive sur-
gery. 
According to some studies comparing open surgery with HALS 
for treating colorectal diseases, a common conclusion was that 
HALS had a smaller incision, a faster postoperative recovery and 
a shorter hospital stay [5-9]. Our data showed similar results: small 
incisions, reductions in the amounts of additional pain killers re-
quired, and fast recovery of bowel movement. In addition, the 
complication rates, as well as the incidences of reoperations, read-
missions and mortalities, were comparable between the two groups. 
However, the duration of hospital stay was similar, about 11 days, 
in both groups, which was probably because the patients tended 
to stay a few days longer even though they were on a tolerable diet 
and in a general condition acceptable for discharge. 
Our data also demonstrated similar operation times between 
the two groups. Most previous studies had demonstrated that the 
operation time was significantly longer in the HALS group than 
in the open surgery group [7,9,10]. In those studies, the surgeon's 
experience was not mentioned; neither did those studies address 
whether multiple surgeons had performed various types opera-
tions, e.g., anterior resections, right or left hemicolectomies, low </p>

<p>anterior resections or total colectomies. In contrast, this study en-
rolled only those patients who underwent an anterior resection 
performed by one surgeon with sufficient experience with open 
colorectal surgery [3,7,9,11-15]. Kang et al. [6] also reported simi-
lar operation times for both the HALS and the open surgery 
groups when the surgery was conducted by one surgeon, which 
implies that the longer operation time in the HALS group is most 
likely due to the surgeon's lack of experience, not the type of oper-
ation. 
In other studies comparing HALS with conventional laparoscopic 
surgery for treating colorectal diseases [3,4,16-18], the postopera-
tive clinical outcomes were similar between the two groups; in 
addition, the rate of conversion to open surgery was lower in the 
HALS group than in the conventional laparoscopic surgery group 
[4,16,17,19,20]. On the other hand, HALS patients had a rather 
long incision length and more severe surgical trauma than laparo-
scopic-surgery patients [4,16,17,19,20]. Nevertheless, the benefits 
of HALS countervail the demerits; that is, HALS had a reduced 
open conversion rate, the surgeon's hand maintained tactile sensa-
tion [2,17,20-22]. Also, when an unexpected or serious situation 
occurred during surgery, the surgeon could approach the opera-
tive field directly and solve the problem quickly when using HALS 
technique [2,17,20-22]. 
Minimally invasive surgery for treating colorectal diseases has 
already been reported to be safe and technically feasible [5,16,19]. 
However, most studies included diverse categories of colorectal 
diseases, including diverticulitis, inflammatory bowel diseases, 
sigmoid volvulus, colorectal cancer and so on [8,9,12,13]. In the 
case of malignant disease, not only the feasibility of surgery, but 
also oncologic safety should be considered and evaluated. Thus, 
the number of retrieved lymph nodes should be one parameter 
describing the extent of lymph-node dissection. Our data demon-
strated that the numbers of retrieved lymph nodes were 17.5 in 
the HAL-AR group and 15.3 in the open group, being more than 
12 in both group [23]. Sheng et al. [8] reported no significant dif-
ference in the numbers of retrieved lymph nodes between patients 
who underwent a hand-assisted laparoscopic right hemicolectomy 
for the treatment of right colon cancer and those who underwent 
an open right hemicolectomy. However, there are few reports on 
the use of an anterior resection for the treatment of sigmoid colon 
cancer. 
As described in the introduction, hand-assisted laparoscopic 
colorectal surgery is a hybrid technique, which has the merits of 
both laparoscopic and conventional open surgery for the treat-
ment of sigmoid colon cancer, even though some surgeons con-
sidered HALS to be a bridge from open surgery to laparoscopic 
surgery. 
In conclusion, patients with sigmoid colon cancer who under-
went a HAL-AR had not only a lower incidence of postoperative 
leukocytosis, less administration of pain killers, and faster recov-
ery of the gastrointestinal tract, but also a radicality of lymph-node 
dissection similar to that in open cases. Therefore, the use of a </p>

<p>Annals of </p>

<p>Coloproctology </p>

<p>www.coloproctol.org 
21 </p>

<p>Volume 29, Number 1, 2013 </p>

<p>Ann Coloproctol 2013;29(1):17-21 </p>

<p>HAL-AR for the treatment of sigmoid colon cancer is feasible and 
safe and can be considered as an alternative procedure to open 
surgery. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported. </p>



</text></tei>