<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3835501" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Several lines of evidence indicate that prehypertension is more atherogenic than normal 
blood pressure. Serum γ-glutamyltransferase (GGT) is known to be positively associated 
with prehypertensive status and the progression of hypertension. However, there have 
been no prospective studies of serum GGT level as a predictor of prehypertension. 
Apparently 13,435 healthy men (mean age 42.0 ± 6.6 yr) with normal blood pressure were 
included in a prospective cohort study in 2005 and were followed up to 2010 with the 
endpoint being incident of prehypertension. During the follow up period (median 2.80 ± 
1.44 yr; actual follow-up 37,679.1 person-year), prehypertension was developed in 7,867 
(58.6%) participants. Risk estimations for incident prehypertension were analyzed based 
on quartiles of serum GGT levels using multivariate adjusted Cox proportional hazards 
model. In unadjusted model, the hazard ratio for incident prehypertension for the highest 
3 quartiles of baseline serum GGT level was 1.21 (1.13-1.29), 1.29 (1.21-1.38), and 1.57 
(1.47-1.67) compared the lowest quartile of serum GGT level, respectively (P for trend &lt; 
0.001). These associations still remained statistically significant, even after adjusting for 
multiple covariates. These findings indicate that increased serum GGT level is independently 
associated with incident prehypertension in Korean men. </p>

<p>Serum γ-glutamyltransferase (GGT), a plasma membrane-
bound enzyme, has been used as a biological marker for alco-
hol intake or liver cell damage (1-3). However, recent studies 
have shown that serum GGT might be related to oxidative stress 
and might have a role in the pathogenesis of cardiovascular dis-
ease, diabetes mellitus, strokes and metabolic syndrome (4-6). 
In the seventh Joint national committee (JNC-7), National 
Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI) of United States pre-
sented a new diagnostic classification for blood pressure (BP) 
where systolic BP (SBP) is between 120-139 mmHg or diastolic 
BP (DBP) is between 80-89 mmHg, previously categorized as 
normotensive and borderline BP in the JNC-6, is now catego-
rized as prehypertension. This is based on the study results that 
the risk of cerebral infarction and coronary artery disease in-
creases in patients with SBP/DBP above 115/75 mmHg, and 
the risk is doubled as BP increases by 20/10 mmHg (7). In Strong 
Heart Study, the incidence rate of hypertension within 4 yr in 
prehypertensive group was 38%, and in Framingham Heart-
Study, the risk of hypertension was doubled in prehypertensive </p>

<p>group compared with normotensive group (8, 9). Additionally, 
the risk of cardiovascular disease in prehypertensive group has 
1.8 times higher than that of normotensive group (10). 
Recent cross-sectional studies have reported the association 
between serum GGT and hypertension and prehypertension 
prevalence (11-15). However, there was no prospective cohort 
study on the association between serum GGT and incident pre-
hypertension. In this study, we examined the clinical associa-
tion between baseline serum GGT level and incident prehyper-
tension in Korean men. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study populations 
The present study was a prospective cohort study to examine 
the association between serum GGT level and incident prehy-
pertension in Korean men participating in a medical health 
check-up program at the Total Healthcare Center of Kangbuk 
Samsung Hospital, Sungkyunkwan University, Seoul, Korea. 
We included in the present study only men who were normo-
tensive at baseline. Initially, participants who had abnormal </p>

<p>Chun H, et al. • γ-Glutamyltransferase and Prehypertension </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2013.28.11.1603 </p>

<p>blood pressure and participants with prehypertension and hy-
pertension were excluded from this study. In 2005, 46,728 men 
who had participated in a medical health check-up program 
were recruited in this study. Among the 46,728 participants, 
29,233 men were excluded due to the following reasons: 238 
had a history of a malignancy; 323 had a history of cardiovascu-
lar disease; 3,241 were receiving antidyslipidemic medications; 
19,793 and 9,591 had a baseline prehypertension and hyper-
tension. Because some participants had more than one exclu-
sion criteria, the total number of men who were eligible for the 
study was 17,495. We further excluded 4,060 participants who 
did not attend any follow-up visit between 2006 and 2010. Ac-
cordingly, 13,435 participants were included in the final analy-
sis and were observed for incident prehypertension. The total 
follow-up period was 37,679.1 person-year and average follow-
up period was 2.80 ± 1.44 person-years. </p>

<p>Clinical and Laboratory measurements 
Study data included a medical history, a physical examination, 
information provided by a questionnaire, anthropometric mea-
surements and laboratory measurements. The medical history 
was assessed by the examining physicians. All the participants 
were asked about health-related behavior including alcohol in-
take, cigarette smoking and physical activity. Questions about 
alcohol intake included the frequency of alcohol intake per week 
and the usual amount of alcohol intake per day. We considered 
participants as current smoker who reported to smoke at that 
time of the study. In addition, the participants were asked about 
the frequency of physical activity, such as jogging, bicycling, 
and swimming that lasted long enough to produce perspiration 
(≥ 1 time/week). Body mass index (BMI) was calculated as the 
weight (kilograms) divided by height (meters) squared. 
After a 5-min rest, BP was measured on the right upper arm 
in the sitting position using a standardized mercury sphygmo-
manometer. SBP and DBP were recorded as the first and fifth 
Korotkoff phases, respectively. According to the JNC-7 guide-
lines, the measured BP was classified as normal (SBP &lt; 120 
mmHg and a DBP &lt; 80 mmHg), prehypertension (SBP 120 to 
139 mmHg or DBP 80 to 90 mmHg) and hypertension (SBP ≥ 
140 mmHg or DBP ≥ 90 mmHg, or current use of medication 
for hypertension). Diabetes mellitus was defined as fasting se-
rum glucose more than 126 mg/dL, or current use of medica-
tion for diabetes. 
After fasting for at least 12 hr, peripheral venous samples were 
collected. Total cholesterol, triglyceride, low-density lipopro-
tein (LDL) cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein (HDL) choles-
terol, creatinine, high-sensitivity C-reactive protein (hs-CRP), 
fasting blood glucose, insulin, aspartate aminotransferase (AST), 
alanine aminotransferase (ALT), and GGT were measured. Serum 
GGT was measured using Bayer Reagent Packs (Bayer Health-
Care, Tarrytown, NY, USA) on an automated chemistry analyzer </p>

<p>(ADVIA 1650 Autoanalyzer; Bayer Diagnostics, Leverkusen, 
Germany). Insulin levels were measured with immunoradio-
metric assays (Biosource, Nivelles, Belgium). Insulin resistance 
was calculated with the homeostasis model assessment of in-
sulin resistance (HOMA-IR): fasting serum insulin (μU/mL) × 
FBG (mg/dL)/22.5 (16). The clinical laboratory has been ac-
credited and participates annually in inspections and surveys 
by the Korean Association of Quality Assurance for Clinical La-
boratories. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Data in the text and tables were expressed as the mean ± stan-
dard deviation (SD) or medians (interquartile range) for con-
tinuous variables and percentages of the number for categori-
cal variables. Participants were divided into quartiles on the ba-
sis of serum GGT level as follows: quartile 1, GGT &lt; 17 IU/L; 
quartile 2, GGT 17 to 25 IU/L; quartile 3, 25 to 40 IU/L GGT; 
and quartile 4, GGT ≥ 40 IU/L. The one-way ANOVA and chi-
square-test were used to analyze the statistical differences among 
the characteristics of the participants at the baseline visit ac-
cording to the quartile groups of serum GGT level. The distribu-
tions of continuous variables were evaluated, and log transfor-
mations were used in the analysis as required. For cases with 
incident prehypertension, the time spent at incident prehyper-
tension was assumed to be the midpoint between the baseline 
visit and the visit at which prehypertension was first diagnosed. 
The person years were calculated as the sum of follow-up times 
from the baseline until the assumed time prehypertension was 
diagnosed or until the final examination of each individual. 
Compared to the lowest quartile of serum GGT, the hazards ra-
tios (HRs) of the highest 3 quartiles of serum GGT was calculat-
ed by the Cox proportional hazard model after adjustment for 
baseline characteristics such as age, log (hsCRP), total choles-
terol, creatinine, recent smoking status, alcohol intake, regular 
exercise and diabetes mellitus. For the linear trends of risk, the 
number of quartiles was used as a continuous variable and test-
ed on each model. To use the Cox proportional hazards models, 
we checked the validity of the proportional hazards assump-
tion. Two approaches were used to assess the validity of the 
proportional hazards assumption. First, the assumption was 
assessed by log-minus-log-survival function and found to graph-
ically hold. Second, to confirm the validity of the proportional 
hazards assumption, time-dependent covariate analysis was 
used. The time-dependent covariate was not statistically signifi-
cant, suggesting that the proportional hazards assumption is 
not violated (P = 0.055). P values less than 0.05 were considered 
to be statistically significant. Statistical analyses were performed 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">PASW Statistics</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">18</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>Ethics statement 
This cohort study was approved by the institutional review board </p>

<p>Chun H, et al. • γ-Glutamyltransferase and Prehypertension </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2013.28.11.1603 </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline characteristics of participants according to quartile groups of serum GGT level (n=13,435) </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Overall 
GGT (IU/L) </p>

<p>Quartile 1 ( &lt; 17) Quartile 2 ( ≥ 17, &lt; 25) Quartile 3 ( ≥ 25, &lt; 40) Quartile 4 ( ≥ 40) 
P for trend* </p>

<p>Person-year (total) 
37,679.1 
10,005.4 
9,773.2 
9,093.4 
8,807.1 
Person-year (average) 
2.80 ± 1.44 
3.00 ± 1.45 
2.85 ± 1.45 
2.77 ± 1.44 
2.59 ± 1.41 
&lt; 0.001 
Age (yr) 
42.0 ± 6.6 
41.1 ± 6.9 
41.7 ± 6.5 
42.4 ± 6.6 
42.8 ± 6.3 
&lt; 0.001 
BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
23.6 ± 2.6 
22.4 ± 2.3 
23.2 ± 2.4 
24.0 ± 2.5 
24.9 ± 2.5 
&lt; 0.001 
Systolic BP (mmHg) 
103.4 ± 7.1 
102.5 ± 7.5 
103.5 ± 7.1 
103.7 ± 7.0 
104.0 ± 6.7 
&lt; 0.001 
Diastolic BP (mmHg) 
69.1 ± 4.4 
68.4 ± 4.7 
69.0 ± 4.3 
69.3 ± 4.2 
69.6 ± 4.2 
&lt; 0.001 
Total cholesterol (mg/dL) 
189.1 ± 30.9 
177.0 ± 27.3 
186.2 ± 28.9 
193.0 ± 30.2 
200.2 ± 32.2 
&lt; 0.001 
Triglyceride (mg/dL) 
113 (83-158) 
88 (68-116) 
104 (79-140) 
123 (91-167) 
150 (111-202) 
&lt; 0.001 
HDL-cholesterol (mg/dL) 
50.3 ± 10.3 
51.6 ± 10.2 
50.4 ± 10.3 
49.7 ± 10.3 
49.6 ± 10.3 
&lt; 0.001 
LDL-cholesterol (mg/dL) 
111.5 ± 26.2 
103.0 ± 23.5 
110.4 ± 25.0 
114.5 ± 25.8 
117.8 ± 28.0 
&lt; 0.001 
Fasting blood glucose (mg/dL) 
95.3 ± 13.7 
93.1 ± 12.5 
94.3 ± 11.8 
95.5 ± 12.2 
98.4 ± 17.2 
&lt; 0.001 
HOMA-IR 
1.81 (1.41-2.38) 
1.59 (1.28-2.00) 
1.73 (1.36-2.21) 
1.87 (1.45-2.46) 
2.17 (1.65-2.81) 
&lt; 0.001 
Insulin (µU/dL) 
8.4 ± 3.1 
7.4 ± 2.4 
8.0 ± 2.7 
8.6 ± 3.3 
9.6 ± 3.5 
&lt; 0.001 
Creatinine (mg/dL) 
1.12 ± 0.12 
1.11 ± 0.10 
1.12 ± 0.15 
1.13 ± 0.10 
1.13 ± 0.11 
&lt; 0.001 
hsCRP (mg/L) 
0.05 (0.02-0.10) 
0.03 (0.02-0.07) 
0.04 (0.02-0.09) 
0.05 (0.03-0.11) 
0.07 (0.04-0.14) 
&lt; 0.001 
AST (U/L) 
23 (19-27) 
21 (18-24) 
22 (18-25) 
24 (20-28) 
27 (23-33) 
&lt; 0.001 
ALT (U/L) 
24 (18-33) 
18 (15-23) 
21 (17-27) 
26 (20-33) 
35 (26-49) 
&lt; 0.001 
Current smoker (%) 
45.9 
36.7 
42.3 
47.4 
56.8 
&lt; 0.001 
Alcohol intake (%) 
9.2 
4.1 
6.1 
9.6 
16.8 
&lt; 0.001 
Regular exercise (%) 
13.4 
15.1 
13.6 
13.4 
11.4 
&lt; 0.001 
Diabetes mellitus (%) 
2.3 
1.1 
1.5 
2.5 
3.9 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Data are means (standard deviation), medians (interquartile range), or percentages. *P value by ANOVA for continuous variables and chi square test for categorical variables. </p>

<p>Table 2. Incident prehypertension according to quartile groups of serum GGT level </p>

<p>GGT (IU/L) 
Incident of prehypertension (%) </p>

<p>Quartile 1 ( &lt; 17) 
51.0 
Quartile 2 ( ≥ 17, &lt; 25) 
57.8 
Quartile 3 ( ≥ 25, &lt; 40) 
59.6 
Quartile 4 ( ≥ 40) 
65.7 
P for trend* 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>*P value by chi square test for categorical variables. </p>

<p>of Kangbuk Samsung Hospital (Seoul, Korea) (IRB number: 
KBC12134). Informed consent was obtained from all partici-
pants. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The demographic and biochemical characteristics of the study 
participants according to the quartile groups of serum GGT lev-
el are presented in Table 1. During 37,679.1 person-years of fol-
low-up, 7,867 (58.6%) cases of prehypertension were diagnosed 
between 2006 and 2010. At the baseline visit, the mean age and 
BMI of study participants were 42.0 ± 6.6 yr and 23.6 ± 2.6 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, 
respectively. There were significant linear trends across the quar-
tiles of serum GGT level with respect to all of the listed variables. 
Age, BMI, SBP, DBP, total cholesterol, triglyceride, LDL-choles-
terol, fasting blood glucose, insulin, HOMA-IR, hsCRP, AST and 
ALT tended to increased as the serum GGT quartile increased. 
The percentages of current smoker, alcohol intake participant 
and diabetes mellitus have a tendency to increase along with 
the increase of the serum GGT quartile. However, HDL-choles-
terol and the percentages of regular exercise participants tend-
ed to decrease along with the increase in the serum GGT quar-
tile, respectively. Table 2 shows the incident prehypertension 
have a tendency to increase according to the quartile groups of 
serum GGT level. 
The baseline characteristics of participants with or without in-
cident prehypertension are shown in Table 3. Participants who 
were diagnosed prehypertension during the follow-up period </p>

<p>had higher serum GGT level at baseline compared with those 
who did not develop prehypertension. In contrast to participants 
without incident prehypertension, those with incident prehy-
pertension were slightly older (42.6 vs 41.2 yr) and more likely to 
have a less favorable metabolic profiles at baseline. As expected, 
all clinical variables showed statistically significant differences 
between two groups except for recent smoking status. 
Table 4 presented the results of Cox proportional HRs and 
95% confidence interval (CI) for prehypertension according to 
the quartile groups of serum GGT levels. In unadjusted model, 
the HRs and 95% CI for incident prehypertension for the high-
est 3 quartiles of baseline serum GGT level 1.21 (95% CI, 1.13-
1.29), 1.29 (95% CI, 1.21-1.38) and 1.57 (95% CI, 1.47-1.67) com-
pared to the lowest quartile of serum GGT, respectively (P for 
trend &lt; 0.001). The age adjusted HRs was 1.19 (95% CI, 1.12-
1.27), 1.26 (95% CI, 1.18-1.34) and 1.51 (95% CI, 1.42-1.61) com-
pared to the lowest quartile of serum GGT, respectively (P for 
trend &lt; 0.001). These associations still maintained statistically 
significant, even after further adjustments for explanatory vari-</p>

<p>Chun H, et al. • γ-Glutamyltransferase and Prehypertension </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2013.28.11.1603 </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparison between participants with and without incident of prehypertension </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Without incident of prehypertension (n = 5,568) 
With incident of prehypertension (n = 7,867) 
P value* </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
41.2 ± 6.6 
42.6 ± 6.5 
&lt; 0.001 
BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
23.2 ± 2.5 
23.9 ± 2.6 
&lt; 0.001 
Systolic BP (mmHg) 
102.2 ± 7.3 
104.3 ± 6.8 
&lt; 0.001 
Diastolic BP (mmHg) 
68.3 ± 4.7 
69.6 ± 4.1 
&lt; 0.001 
Total cholesterol (mg/dL) 
187.0 ± 30.8 
190.7 ± 30.9 
&lt; 0.001 
Triglyceride (mg/dL) 
123.5 ± 69.3 
135.3 ± 73.5 
&lt; 0.001 
HDL-cholesterol (mg/dL) 
50.7 ± 10.4 
50.0 ± 10.2 
&lt; 0.001 
LDL-cholesterol (mg/dL) 
110.0 ± 26.3 
112.6 ± 26.1 
&lt; 0.001 
Fasting blood glucose (mg/dL) 
94.3 ± 12.3 
96.1 ± 14.6 
&lt; 0.001 
HOMA-IR 
1.90 ± 0.80 
2.04 ± 0.87 
&lt; 0.001 
Insulin (µU/dL) 
8.1 ± 3.0 
8.6 ± 3.2 
&lt; 0.001 
Creatinine (mg/dL) 
1.12 ± 0.1 
1.13 ± 0.1 
&lt; 0.001 
hsCRP (mg/L) 
0.11 ± 0.3 
0.13 ± 0.4 
&lt; 0.001 
AST (U/L) 
24.1 ± 14.6 
25.4 ± 15.1 
&lt; 0.001 
ALT (U/L) 
26.9 ± 23.7 
29.7 ± 24.3 
&lt; 0.001 
GGT (IU/L) 
31.4 ± 28.2 
37.1 ± 34.6 
&lt; 0.001 
Current smoker (%) 
46.0 
45.8 
0.855 
Alcohol intake (%) 
8.1 
9.9 
&lt; 0.001 
Regular exercise (%) 
12.1 
14.3 
&lt; 0.001 
Diabetes mellitus (%) 
1.9 
2.5 
0.019 </p>

<p>Data are expressed as means (standard deviation) or percentages. *P value by t-test for continuous variables and chi square test for categorical variables. </p>

<p>Table 4. Hazard ratios (HRs) and 95% confidence intervals (CI) for incident of prehypertension according to quartile groups of serum GGT level </p>

<p>Variables 
Hazard ratios (95% Confidence Interval) </p>

<p>Unadjusted 
Age-adjusted 
Model 1 
Model 2 </p>

<p>GGT 
Quartile 1 
Quartile 2 
Quartile 3 
Quartile 4 
P for trend </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) 
1.21 (1.13-1.29) 
1.29 (1.21-1.38) 
1.57 (1.47-1.67) 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) 
1.19 (1.12-1.27) 
1.26 (1.18-1.34) 
1.51 (1.42-1.61) 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) 
1.19 (1.10-1.28) 
1.18 (1.09-1.27) 
1.35 (1.24-1.46) 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) 
1.17 (1.08-1.26) 
1.16 (1.07-1.26) 
1.32 (1.21-1.43) 
&lt; 0.001 
Age 
1.03 (1.02-1.03) 
1.03 (1.02-1.03) 
1.03 (1.02-1.03) 
HOMA-IR 
1.12 (1.09-1.15) 
1.12 (1.09-1.16) 
Triglyceride 
1.00 (1.00-1.00) 
1.00 (1.00-1.00) 
HDL-cholesterol 
1.00 (0.99-1.00) 
1.00 (0.99-1.00) 
Total cholesterol 
1.00 (1.00-1.00) 
1.00 (1.00-1.00) 
Log (hsCRP) 
1.06 (1.03-1.09) 
1.06 (1.03-1.09) 
Creatinine 
1.33 (1.04-1.72) 
1.29 (1.00-1.67) 
Current smoker 
1.01 (0.96-1.06) 
Alcohol intake 
1.12 (1.03-1.23) 
Regular exercise 
0.90 (0.83-0.97) 
Diabetes mellitus 
1.10 (0.93-1.31) </p>

<p>Model 1 was adjusted for age, HOMA-IR, triglyceride, HDL-cholesterol, total cholesterol, log (hsCRP) and creatinine. Model 2 was adjusted for model 1 plus recent smoking sta-
tus, alcohol intake, regular exercise and diabetes mellitus. </p>

<p>ables (age, total cholesterol, log [hsCRP], creatinine, recent smok-
ing status, alcohol intake, regular exercise and diabetes melli-
tus) in model 1 and 2. In model 1, the adjusted HRs (95% CI) for 
incident of prehypertension were 1.21 (1.12-1.30), 1.23 (1.13-
1.32) and 1.48 (1.37-1.60), respectively (P for trend &lt; 0.001). In 
model 2, the adjusted HRs (95% CI) for incident prehyperten-
sion were 1.19 (1.11-1.29), 1.21 (1.12-1.31) and 1.44 (1.33-1.56), 
respectively (P for trend &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Serum GGT level was found to be positively associated with the 
incident prehypertension in Korean men, free of baseline pre-
hypertension, hypertension and many other diseases. The HR 
of prehypertension was increased with in a dose-dependent 
manner by increasing quartiles of serum GGT. Theses associa-
tion persisted after adjusting for age, total cholesterol, log (hsCRP), 
creatinine, current smoking status, alcohol intake, regular exer-</p>

<p>Chun H, et al. • γ-Glutamyltransferase and Prehypertension </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2013.28.11.1603 </p>

<p>cise, and diabetes mellitus. 
In our study, 17,495 eligible male participants were selected 
because of sex differences in serum GGT level. Serum GGT was 
significantly higher in men compared to women due to the grea-
ter consumption of alcohol and higher prevalence of liver dis-
ease in men (17). Another reason was the difference in distribu-
tion of excess fat in men and women. Serum GGT in women 
with BMI above 32 kg/m 
2 was comparable to the serum GGT in 
men with BMI in the range of 20-24 kg/m 
2 (18, 19). 
To the best of our knowledge, our study was the first prospec-
tive cohort study demonstrating a positive association between 
baseline serum GGT level and incident prehypertension; there-
fore we were unable to compare our results with those of oth-
ers. Only several previous cross-sectional studies showed that 
serum GGT is associated with prevalence of prehypertension. 
Higher serum GGT levels were associated with prehyperten-
sion in nationally representative sample of the US adults, with 
the multivariate odds ratio (OR) (95% CI) of 1.84 (1.37-2.46) 
comparing quartile 4 of serum GGT (&gt; 29 U/L) to quartile 1 
(&lt; 13 U/L). Their results were consistent in subgroup analyses 
of race-ethnicity, age, smoking, alcohol intake, BMI, waist cir-
cumference and diabetes (13). Similar results were found in a 
community-based cross-sectional study from Japan and Tur-
key. The multivariate OR (95% CI) for prehypertension was 1.73 
(1.06-3.18) for the middle tertile (29-53 IU/L) and 2.37 (1.31-
4.31) for the highest tertile (&gt; 53 IU/L), compared to the lowest 
tertile of serum GGT (&lt; 29 IU/L) in Japanese men (14). And the 
mean serum GGT level was higher in the prehypertension group 
than in the control group (24.33 and 18.85 U/L, respectively; 
P &lt; 0.001) in Turkish men and women (15). These findings were 
consistent with previous reports related to hypertension (16,  20). However, we further suggest that serum GGT level is also 
related to incident prehypertension, a stage with higher risk of 
progressing to hypertension. Therefore, if people who have 
higher serum GGT level change their life-style with the healthy 
behavior such as a combination of increased physical activity, 
moderation in alcohol intake, and consumption of a diet that is 
lower in sodium content and higher in fruit, vegetables, and 
low-fat dairy products, then risk of progressing to hypertension 
will be decreased (21, 22). Prehypertension was one of the main 
contributors to hypertension, and possibly to the future devel-
opment of cardiovascular disease, although there were differ-
ences in the progression rate prehypertension to hypertension 
(9, 23). Thus, we consistently suggest that higher serum GGT 
level within physiologically normal range may be useful to pre-
dict the risk of prehypertension. 
GGT is an enzyme expressed in serum and most cell surfac-
es; however the function of GGT on these cells is uncertain. 
Emerging evidence has been shown that serum GGT might be 
an important enzyme in the pathogenesis of cardiovascular 
diseases. However, the mechanisms by which the serum GGT </p>

<p>level increases the risk of prehypertension are not fully under-
stood. In our study, the serum GGT predicted the incident pre-
hypertension independently of the alcohol intake. Therefore, 
the association between serum GGT and prehypertension is 
not mediated by alcohol intake. Several lines of recent evidence 
suggest that an association between serum GGT and incident 
prehypertension is plausible. First, serum GGT has been inter-
preted as a reliable marker of oxidative stress (3, 6). Serum GGT 
has a critical role in the maintenance of intracellular defense 
mechanism by initiating extracellular catabolism of glutathi-
one, the main antioxidant in mammalian cells (1, 2, 24). These 
associations suggest that GGT may be a marker of oxidative 
stress. Oxidative stress caused increase of BP by direct vasocon-
striction and sodium retention in the vascular smooth muscle 
and endothelial cells (3). Second, insulin resistance could play 
a major role in the association between serum GGT and inci-
dent prehypertension, because GGT might be interpreted as a 
marker for hepatic steatosis and hepatic insulin resistance (3,  5). More recent studies suggest that leptin may stimulate sym-
pathetic outflow from the hypothalamus which will increase 
the heart rate and BP (25). In this study, HOMA-IR increased in 
dose-response manner with increasing quartiles of serum GGT. 
Serum GGT might be a reliable predictor of diabetes and hy-
pertension, even within a physiologically normal range in the 
CARDIA study (6). Third, serum GGT activity probably reflect-
ed chronic inflammation associated with low levels of anti-in-
flammatory hormones or cytokines. Serum GGT was strongly 
associated with C-reactive protein, the widely recognized mark-
er of chronic inflammation (5, 26). These results strongly sug-
gest that GGT is involved in the pathway of inflammation. How-
ever to clarify the mechanisms of prehypertension, further in-
terventional studies that target serum GGT are needed. 
Several limitations of this study must be considered. First, 
participants were self-selected and approximately 23% of par-
ticipants were excluded because they were unattended any fol-
low up visit. Therefore this study might posses some selection 
bias. Moreover, a single reading of BP on only 1 visit may have 
served as a drawback because of large random fluctuations in a 
casual reading. 
In conclusion, serum GGT was an early predictor for pro-
gression of prehypertension in healthy Korean men. Therefore 
increased serum GGT level is implicated in increased BP and 
the progression of prehypertension. In addition, it is needed to 
determine whether a more aggressive intervention, such as nu-
tritional or lifestyle modifications that decrease serum GGT lev-
el, will decrease the risk of prehypertension. </p>

<p>DISCLOSURE </p>

<p>The authors have no potential conflicts of interest to disclose. </p>

<p>Chun H, et al. • γ-Glutamyltransferase and Prehypertension </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2013.28.11.1603 </p>



</text></tei>