<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3964559" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Tropical cyclones (TC) are one of the most threatening natural hazards to human beings. Although significant 
improvements have been made in the track prediction of TCs during the past several decades, considerable 
uncertainties still exist, especially for recurving tracks. In this study, we explore the physical mechanisms that 
drove the large recurvature of super typhoon Megi through numerical sensitivity experiments using a 
regional atmospheric model. The results indicate that the cold air intrusion from the northwest to the 
southeast of China is the main cause of the sharp turning of Megi. This finding suggests that a cold air 
intrusion could be taken as an indicator for predicting the recurvature of a tropical cyclone in the future. </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>ue to the disastrous effect of tropical cyclones, an accurate prediction of their tracks is very important to 
protecting human lives and property </p>

<p>1,2   . Because of a number of diverse and complex factors that influence 
the movement of a tropical cyclone, considerable uncertainties still exist in track prediction using state-of-
the-art numerical models or empirical methods. In particular, the prediction of the recurving track of a tropical 
cyclone is extremely difficult and remains a big challenge to forecasters </p>

<p>3-5   , because a recurving track of a TC 
involves more complex processes than an un-recurving one 
4 . 
Previous studies have shown that the recurvature of a TC could be caused or influenced by a number of factors, 
including the steering flows 
6 , subtropical high </p>

<p>3,7-9   , monsoon system </p>

<p>7,10-12   , midlatitude westerly trough </p>

<p>3,5,8,9,13,14   , 
zonal winds in the middle and upper troposphere </p>

<p>15,16   , vorticity advection </p>

<p>17   , momentum exchange </p>

<p>3,8   , and beta 
effect together with the basic current asymmetries </p>

<p>18   . In particular, it is found that recurving tracks are closely 
associated with retreat of a subtropical ridge and approach of a midlatitude westerly trough 
3,5,7-9,13,14 . Several 
studies on modeling TC recurvature have also been carried out for both idealized conditions and real cases </p>

<p>3,5,19,20   . 
However, because state-of-the-art numerical models generally fall short in capturing the intricacies of the 
underlying mechanisms of TC recurvature, large errors still exist in the prediction of recurving TC tracks </p>

<p>3,4,8,13   . 
Although high-quality initial conditions by data assimilation 
20 or by the improved initialization technique 
21,22 are 
beneficial to improve the forecasting accuracy of recurving TC tracks, there is not yet a reliable method to predict 
a TC recurving track in operational practice. 
Recently, when we investigated the big recurvature of super typhoon Megi (2010), we noticed that there was a 
cold air intrusion (CAI) from the northwest to the southeast of China before the sharp turn of Megi, accompanied 
by a northeast-southwest-oriented cold front located on the eastern coast of China (Fig. 1). In the fields of 925-
hPa and 500-hPa temperature and geopotential height, the CAI presented as a cold tongue and a midlatitude 
westerly trough aloft with strong cold advection from northwest, respectively, which extended as south as to the 
southeastern China and located on the north of Megi within a distance of 15u latitude (see Supplementary Figs. 
S8q and S9q online). We thus speculate that the CAI may be the primary reason for the recurvature of Megi. 
To see the generality of this relationship between a CAI and a TC's recurvature, we conduct a census on all TCs 
of the northwestern Pacific and the SCS that first moved westward/northwestward/southwestward and then made 
a clockwise recurvature with turning angle larger than 45u during 1975-2012. Here the TC recurvature is confined 
to that occurring at the tropical regions (with latitude , 23u), thus it is somehow different with that occurring at 
the extratropical regions which is associated with the extratropical transition of a TC </p>

<p>23   . To be as objective as 
possible, here we define a CAI as that it should satisfy the following criteria: 1) in the field of 925-hPa temperature, </p>

<p>there is an apparent cold tongue defined as 296 K isotherm for June 
to September and 294 K isotherm for October and November, loc-
ating on the north of the TC and within a box of 10u (longitude, east-
west) 3 15u (latitude, south-north) centered at the TC center; 2) in 
the fields of 500-hPa temperature and geopotential height, there is an 
apparent midlatitude westerly trough with a cold advection from the 
northwestern upstream (i.e., there is a southeastward temperature 
gradient and the temperature trough should be out of phase with 
trough of geopotential height). The results are given in Table 1. 
Among the 21 TCs with the recurvature angle larger than 45u, 17 
TCs are apparently associated to the CAI, counting 81% of the total 
number (see more details in Supplementary Figs. S8-S11 online). 
To test the hypothesis that a CAI may induce a TC's recurvature, 
we conduct a set of sensitivity experiments using a mesoscale atmo-
spheric model with full physics while taking the super typhoon Megi 
(2010) as our experimental case. </p>

<p>Case description and experimental setup 
Megi was the strongest tropical cyclone in all ocean basins during 
2010, with a maximum wind speed of 80 ms 
21 and a lowest sea level </p>

<p>pressure of 895 hPa (see a detailed description in Supplementary 
Information online). It caused a direct damage of 2.8 billion RMB 
and affected a population of over half a million in southeastern 
China. The most noticeable feature of Megi's movement is its sharp 
turn from westward to northward at 0000 UTC 20 Oct. after it swept 
over the North Philippines and entered the SCS. As shown in the 
Fig. 2, this sharp turn was approximately predicted by the Global 
Forecast System (GFS) maintained by the National Centers for 
Environmental Prediction (NCEP) and a real-time air-sea-wave 
forecasting system called the Experimental Platform of Marine 
Environment Forecasting (EPMEF, see a briefly introduction in 
Supplementary Information online) as early as at 0000 UTC 18 
Oct., i.e., 48-h ahead of the recurvature, whereas most other opera-
tional forecast agencies failed until 5-h ahead of the recurvature. An 
analysis of the forecast outputs indicates that the GFS and EPMEF 
well predicted the CAI. It should be aware that the forecasts from 
most operational agencies are usually based on combined results 
from a number of guidance models (including multi-layer dynamical 
models, single-layer trajectory models, consensus models, statistical 
models and so on). Since forecasts from multi-layer dynamical </p>

<p>Figure 1 | The synoptic situation associated with a cold air intrusion and Megi (2010) at the initial time (0000 UTC 18 Oct. 2010). (a), Surface </p>

<p>wind (barb, m s 
21 ), sea level pressure (contour with interval of 5 hPa) and 900-hPa temperature anomalies relative to zonal mean (shaded, K). 
(b), Infrared image from Multi-functional Transport Satellite-1R (MTSAT-1R) of Japan Meteorological Agency (obtained with permission from 
http://agora.ex.nii.ac.jp/digital-typhoon/globe/color/2010/2048x2048/MTS110101800.globe.1.jpg). (c), 500-hPa geopotential height (contour with 
interval of 40 m) and 850-hPa equivalent potential temperature anomalies relative to zonal mean (shaded, K). Data for plotting (a) and (c) are from 
NCEP GFS data (1u 3 1u) which were interpolated into model grids. The blue 'H' in (a) denotes the surface high pressure system, and the thick blue lines 
in both (a) and (b) indicate the cold front. Figures (a) and (c) were drawn using <rs type="software">GrADS</rs> and <rs type="software">NCL</rs> (doi:10.5065/D6WD3XH5) respectively. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4451 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04451 </p>

<p>
models (such as the GFS) are not available to forecasters until about 
4-h after the starting time of a forecast cycle (generally called ''late 
models''), a technique is usually adopted in operational forecast 
agencies to adjust the most recent available run of a late model to </p>

<p>the current synoptic time and initial conditions (the adjusted version 
of a late model is thus known, mostly for historical reasons, as ''inter-
polated model''. see more details in Supplementary Information 
online regarding the definition of ''late model'' and ''interpolated 
model''). Therefore, it is hard for us to know exactly the causes in a 
Numerical Weather Prediction (NWP) point of view that most 
operational forecast agencies failed to predict the sharp turn of 
Megi timely, and exploring the specific causes of failure for each 
operational forecast agency is beyond the scope of this paper which 
focuses on investigating whether CAI could cause TC recurvature. 
Given that Megi was the strongest tropical cyclone in all ocean basins 
during 2010 with a near-90u sharp turn, and that most of the locally 
operational forecast agencies did not well predict the sharp turn 
timely, Megi was particularly a difficult case of prediction and could 
be a representative one of TC recurvature for studying. 
To further investigate the impact of the CAI on the recurvature of 
Megi, we design a set of sensitivity experiments in which the CAI is 
enhanced or suppressed in varying degrees by adding different tem-
perature increments into the initial temperature fields of the Weather 
Research and Forecasts (WRF) model (see Method for details). We 
denote the control run with the CAI (i.e., the same as the atmospheric 
component run of EPMEF) as CTRL and the sensitivity experiments 
as sen_21.5, sen_21.0, sen_1.0, and sen_1.5 corresponding to dif-
ferent amplitudes (A) of temperature increment 21.5, 21.0, 1.0, and 
1.5 K, respectively, where a negative (positive) amplitude (A) indi-
cates an enhancement (suppressing) of the CAI (see Supplementary 
Figs. S2-S7 online for the change of temperature or equivalent poten-
tial temperature at low atmosphere at different times). </p>

<p>Experimental results and analysis 
The model starts at 0000 UTC 18 Oct. and makes a 72-h forecast of 
the track and intensity of Megi. Results show that, when there is a 
CAI from the northwest of China (CTRL), Megi first moves west-
ward, and then makes a sharp turn around 0000 UTC 20 Oct (Fig. 3). 
When the CAI is enhanced, Megi appears to make an earlier and </p>

<p>Table 1 | A census on the CAI associated the TC recurvature occurred on the western Pacific and the SCS during 1975-2012. These TCs 
originally moved westward/northwestward/southwestward and then made a clockwise recurvature with turning angle larger than 45u. A 
CAI is confirmed only when the following two criteria are satisfied (indicated by 3): 1) there is a cold tongue on the north of the TC and within 
a box of 10u (longitude, east-west) 3 15u (latitude, south-north) centered at the TC center, which is defined as 296 k isotherm for June to 
September and 294 k isotherm for October and November in the 925-hPa temperature field; 2) there is a midlatitude westerly trough with a 
cold advection from the northwestern upstream in the fields of 500-hPa temperature and geopotential height </p>

<p>TC Name (No.) 
Category 
925-hPa Cold Tongue </p>

<p>500-hPa Midlatitude Westerly 
Trough with Cold Advection Cold Air Intrusion (CAI) </p>

<p>1 
Thelma (197704) 
Severe Typhoon 
3 
3 
3 
2 
Babe (197709) 
Super Typhoon 
3 
3 
3 
3 
Rose (197804) 
Severe Tropical Storm 
3 
3 
3 
4 
Faye (197907) 
Severe Tropical Storm 
3 
3 
3 
5 
Mac (197914) 
Severe Tropical Storm 
3 
3 
3 
6 
Joe (198314) 
Severe Tropical Storm 
3 
3 
3 
7 
Thelma (198705) 
Super Typhoon 
3 
3 
3 
8 
Nathan (199004) 
Severe Tropical Storm 
3 
3 
3 
9 
Mike (199025) 
Super Typhoon 
3 
3 
3 
10 
Faye (199206) 
Severe Tropical Storm 
3 
3 
3 
11 
Dot (199318) 
Typhoon 
3 
3 
3 
12 
Joel (199422) 
Severe Tropical Storm 
3 
3 
3 
13 
Helen (199505) 
Severe Tropical Storm 
3 
3 
3 
14 
Herb (199609) 
Super Typhoon 
7 
3 
7 
15 
Maggie (199903) 
Typhoon 
3 
3 
3 
16 
Rananim (200413) 
Severe Typhoon 
3 
3 
3 
17 
Sepat (200708) 
Super Typhoon 
3 
3 
3 
18 
Parma (200917) 
Severe Typhoon 
7 
3 
7 
19 
Chanthu (201003) 
Typhoon 
7 
7 
7 
20 
Megi (201013) 
Super Typhoon 
3 
3 
3 
21 
Vicente (201208) 
Typhoon 
7 
7 
7 </p>

<p>Figure 2 | The ''best'' track (denoted by OBS) and the 72-h predicted </p>

<p>tracks by different agencies for Megi (2010) started at 0000 UTC 18 Oct. 
2010. The positions of the typhoon center are shown at an interval of 
24 hours. Here JTWC represents the US navy Joint Typhoon Warning 
Center, NMCC the National Meteorological Center of China, JMA the 
Japan Meteorological Administration, CWBT the Central Weather Bureau 
of Taiwan, GFS the Global Forecast System, and EPMEF the experimental 
platform of marine environment forecasting. This figure was drawn using 
<rs type="software">GrADS</rs>. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4451 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04451 </p>

<p>
shaper turn than in CTRL; when the CAI is suppressed, Megi tends to 
move westward straightforward. The more intensively the CAI is 
enhanced or suppressed (with larger increment amplitudes A), the 
sharper turn or the more straightforward movement Megi makes. 
Therefore, the CAI from the north of Megi could be the primary 
reason for the sharp turn of Megi from westward to northward. 
Why and how did the CAI cause the recurvature of Megi? Since TC 
movement is generally affected by environmental flows 
24-27 from the 
lower to upper atmosphere, we speculate that the cold air may have 
changed the large scale circulation of the upper troposphere through 
the thermodynamic interactions. The change of large scale circula-
tion can be examined in terms of the geostrophic winds, the subtrop-
ical high and the midlatitude upper-level westerly trough (MUWT). 
According to Holton   28   , the thermal wind relation can be expressed as: </p>

<p>u t~{ 
Lu g 
Lp~{ </p>

<p>R 
pf </p>

<p>LT 
Ly </p>



<p>p </p>

<p>v t~{ 
Lv g 
Lp~R pf </p>

<p>LT 
Lx </p>



<p>p </p>

<p>8 
&gt; &gt; &gt; &lt; </p>

<p>&gt; &gt; &gt; : 
, 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>where the subscripts t and g stand for thermal winds and geostrophic 
winds respectively, f the Coriolis parameter, R the constant of dry air, 
p the pressure and T the temperature. This formula relates the ver-
tical variation of the zonal (meridional) geostrophic winds (i.e., ther-
mal winds) to the meridional (zonal) variation of air temperature. 
When there is a CAI from the north, there will be a north-to-south </p>

<p>temperature gradient ( 
LT 
Ly </p>



<p>p </p>

<p>, 0) and we have westerly thermal </p>

<p>winds ( 
LT 
Ly </p>



<p>p </p>

<p>, 0 R u t~{ 
R 
pf </p>

<p>LT 
Ly </p>



<p>p </p>

<p>. 0), and thus the westerly </p>

<p>zonal geostrophic winds tend to increase with height ({ 
Lu g 
Lp 
. 0). </p>

<p>As a result, the deep-layer mean steering flows (indicated by the black 
vectors in Fig. 3) would become more eastward and hence facilitate 
the sharp turn of Megi. As shown in (Fig. 4), when the CAI is </p>

<p>enhanced, the larger north-to-south temperature gradient ( 
LT 
Ly </p>



<p>p </p>

<p>, 0) leads to stronger westerly zonal geostrophic winds at high level 
of the atmosphere and thus intensified eastward steering flows, 
which helps Megi make a sharper turn anticyclonically (Fig. 4a-b); 
when the CAI is suppressed by adding an inverse (south-to-north) </p>

<p>temperature gradient ( 
LT 
Ly </p>



<p>p </p>

<p>. 0), there will be anomalous easterly </p>

<p>thermal winds enhanced with the increment amplitude A getting 
from 1.0 to 1.5 (Fig. 4c-d), leading to anomalous westward steering 
flows and thus a westward (straightforward) movement of Megi 
(Fig. 3). 
The CAI can also influence the position and strength of the sub-
tropical high. This can be explained using the hydrostatic relation-
ship: </p>

<p>{ 
LW 
Lp~R p 
T, 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>where W is the geopotential. From Eq. (2), we can see that the thick-
ness (2hW/hp) is proportional to the temperature, which implies 
that a CAI may lead to a reduced thickness and thus a weakened </p>

<p>Figure 3 | The ''best'' track (denoted by OBS) and the predicted tracks by </p>

<p>different experiments for Megi (2010) starting at 0000 UTC 18 Oct. 2010. 
Here the gray and red lines are the tracks from the observation (the ''best'' 
track) and the control run (CTRL), and the rests are from sensitive 
experiments in which the amplitudes of temperature increment are set to 
21.5, 21.0, 1.0 and 1.5 K, respectively. Black arrows denote the steering 
flow at the corresponding time and typhoon center locations around the 
recurvature. The time interval between circles (or dots) of each track is 
6 hours. This figure was drawn using Matlab. </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Temperature differences (shaded, K) between each sensitive experiment and the control run (the former minus the latter) and the </p>

<p>corresponding thermal winds (vector, m s 
21 Pa </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>) calculated using Eq. (1) at 900-hPa at initial time (0000UTC 18 Oct. 2010). (a), sen_21.5. (b), 
sen_21.0. (c), sen_1.0. (d), sen_1.5. Thermal wind larger than 2 3 10 
24 m s 
21 Pa 
21 are not shown since they are mostly attributed to the discontinuity of 
temperature modification. These figures were drawn using <rs type="software">GrADS</rs>. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4451 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04451 </p>

<p>
Figure 5 | 500-hPa geopotential height (contour with interval of 40 m) and 850-hPa equivalent potential temperature anomalies relative to zonal mean </p>

<p>(shaded, K) at 0000 UTC 19 Oct. 2010. (a), CTRL. (b), sen_21.5. (c), sen_21.0. (d), sen_1.0. (e), sen_1.5. These figures were drawn using <rs type="software">NCL</rs> 
(doi:10.5065/D6WD3XH5). </p>

<p>Figure 6 | Upper-layer (400-200 hPa) mean temperature advection (shaded in all panels, 10 </p>

<p>25 K s </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>) and 500 hPa geopotential height (contour in 
Panel a with interval of 50 m) or differences (contour in Panels b-d with interval of 20 m) between each sensitivity experiment and the control 
experiment (the former minus the latter) at 0000 UTC 20 Oct. 2010. (a), CTRL. (b), sen_21.5. (c), sen_21.0. (d), sen_1.0. (e), sen_1.5. These figures 
were drawn using <rs type="software">GrADS</rs>. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4451 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04451 </p>

<p>
subtropical high. A weakened and east-retreated subtropical high 
favors the northward movement of a tropical cyclone generated in 
the north western Pacific Ocean due to the northward flows of the 
western edge of the subtropical high. The 500-hPa geopotential 
height for different experiments indicate that the CAI or enhanced 
CAI do lead to a weakened and east-retreated subtropical high 
(Fig. 5a-c), and suppressing the CAI results in a stronger and 
west-extended subtropical high (Fig. 5d-e, also see Supplementary 
Figs. S5-S7 online), as depicted by the contour of 5920 m in Fig. 5. 
When the west-reached subtropical high may block Megi from mov-
ing northward and the westward flows of its southern edge may steer 
Megi to the west, the east-retreated subtropical high induced by the 
CAI seems to open a south-to-north passage for the northward 
movement of Megi. Studies have also shown that the MUWT can 
have significant influence on the tracks of tropical cyclones 
8 . Our 
experimental results further indicate that the upper-level cold advec-
tion from the high-mid-latitude regions can deepen the MUWT, and 
thus the northeastward flows ahead of the MUWT may steer Megi to 
move northward/northeastward (Fig. 6a-c). On the other hand, the 
weakened upper-level cold advection results in an increase of the 
geopotential height and therefore a weakening of the MUWT which 
in turn reduces the cold advection (Fig. 6c-d), leading to a westward 
(straightforward) movement of Megi. 
As discussed in the study of Wu et al. </p>

<p>29   , the positive PV advection 
from higher latitudes at upper troposphere may induce upper tro-
pospheric pumping and thus mid-low tropospheric ascent, which is 
in favor of TC development. Fig. 7 shows PV and horizontal winds on 
the 315-K isentropic surface at 0000 UTC 20 Oct. 2010 for different 
experiments. With CAI (CTRL), high PV associated with the west-
erly trough between 30-40u N is found, and a positive southeastward 
PV advection results in a high PV ridge north/northeast of Megi 
(Fig. 7a); the intensified CAI (sen_21.0, sen_21.5) leads to an </p>

<p>enhancement in the high PV of the westerly trough, the positive 
southeastward PV advection and the PV ridge northeast of Megi 
(Figs. 7b-c). Therefore, Megi tends to move northward/northeast-
ward where the atmospheric environment is favorable for TC 
development with high PV in the upper troposphere. In contrast, 
when the CAI is suppressed (sen_1.0, sen_1.5), the high PV of the 
westerly trough, the positive southeastward PV advection and the PV 
ridge northeast of Megi weaken, whereas a PV ridge northwest of 
Megi develops and enhances, leading to a westward/northwestward 
movement of the TC. </p>

<p>Discussion 
It should be noted that the factors causing the recurvature of a TC 
could be various and complex. In addition to the subtropical high 
and midlatitude westerly trough, the recurvature of a tropical cyclone 
may be also affected by a number of other factors 
3-18 as aforemen-
tioned. In particular, for a super typhoon like Megi, the thermal 
structure and its interaction with the environmental flow may be 
different from a moderate tropical cyclone, which may make the 
causes of its recurving more complex. Our experimental results, 
however, are the first attempt to numerically demonstrate that the 
CAI can lead to the sharp turn of a super typhoon through the 
thermodynamic adjustment of the large scale circulation of the upper 
troposphere. The results may also have potential value in guiding 
forecasters for predicting the recurving track of a TC in the future. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>We employed a regional weather forecasting model, called the Weather Research and 
Forecasts (WRF) model, for our numerical experiments. The WRF is a next-gen-
eration meso-scale numerical weather prediction system that was designed to serve 
both operational forecasting and atmospheric research needs 
30 and was developed by 
the National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR) and the National Centers for 
Environmental Prediction (NCEP) in the U. S. A dynamical downscaling technique is </p>

<p>Figure 7 | Potential vorticity (shading, PVU 5 10 </p>

<p>26 m 
2 s </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>K kg </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>) and horizontal wind (vector, m s 
21 ) at the 315-K isentropic surface at 0000 UTC 20 
Oct. 2010. (a), CTRL. (b), sen_21.5. (c), sen_21.0. (d), sen_1.0. (e), sen_1.5. Only the potential vorticity with value larger than 0.35 PVU is 
shaded. These figures were drawn using NCL (doi:10.5065/D6WD3XH5). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4451 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04451 </p>

<p>
employed for the regional atmospheric model to obtain higher-resolution output with 
small-and meso-scale features from the lower-resolution output of a global atmo-
spheric model. To realize this, a two-domain-nested configuration with horizontal 
resolutions of 72 km and 24 km, respectively, is designed (see Supplementary Fig. S1 
online). Both domains have 27 layers in the vertical. The output from the Global 
Forecast System (GFS) maintained by NCEP with horizontal resolution of 1u 3 1u is 
used to provide initial conditions and lateral boundary conditions for the outer 
domain. The Ferrier microphysics scheme 
31 , Kain-Fritsch cumulus scheme 
32 , YSU 
PBL scheme 
33 , and Dudhia short wave and RRTM long wave radiation schemes </p>

<p>34,35   are chosen for both domains. 
To intensify or suppress the CAI while maintaining the stability of the model 
integration, we change the temperature field as follows by adding an increment to the 
original temperature value T 0 if and only if all the following three conditions are 
satisfied: 1) between 1000 hPa and 200 hPa; 2) those grid points with latitude 
$ 10uN; 3) Tƒ 
T{0:5 (where 
T denotes the zonal-averaged temperature), i.e.,: </p>

<p>T~T 0 zA : DT, 
ð3Þ </p>

<p>DT~Q 
{Q 0 
Q 0 
, 
ð4Þ </p>

<p>where Q is the latitude and Q 0 5 10uN the start latitude. A is the increment amplitude, 
that is, the larger the absolute value of A is, the more intensively the cold air intrusion 
is enhanced (for negative value) or suppressed (for positive value). In this study, A is 
set to 21.5, 21.0, 1.0 and 1.5 K in different sensitive experiments denoted as 
sen_21.5, sen_21.0, sen_1.0 and sen_1.5, respectively. Supplementary Figs. S2-S4 
online display the temperature fields at 900 hPa at different times. 
The steering flow is obtained following the traditional method 
9,36 , which is a height-
and area-averaged large-scale flow between 925 hPa and 300 hPa and over a 3 , 8u 
ring-area centered at the typhoon center. The isentropic potential vorticity is calcu-
lated as </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>P~{g f zk.+ h |v 
ð 
Þ = Lp=Lh 
ð 
Þ , 
ð5Þ </p>

<p>where f is the Coriolis parameter, k a unit vertical vector, + h the three dimensional 
gradient operators in x 2 y 2 h space, h the potential temperature, and v the 
horizontal wind vector. The equivalent potential temperature is computed by </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>h e &lt;h L exp 
r s T L 
ð ÞL v T L 
ð Þ 
c pd T L </p>



<p>, 
ð6Þ </p>

<p>where h L and T L are (dry) potential temperature and temperature at the lifted con-
densation level (LCL), r s (T L ) the saturation mixing ratio at temperature T L , L v (T L ) the 
latent heat of condensation at temperature T L , and c pd the specific heat of dry air at 
constant pressure respectively. 
The 6-hourly NCEP/NCAR Reanalysis 1 (for TCs before 1979) and Reanalysis 2 
(only available from 1979) data on 2.5u 3 2.5u latitude/longitude grids are used in the 
analysis of CAI associated to the TC recurvature during 1975-2012 (http://www.esrl. 
noaa.gov/psd/data/gridded/). The best tracks of the TCs are obtained from the U.S. 
Navy/Air Force Joint Typhoon Warning Center (JTWC). </p>



<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>S.P. designed the study. Z.L. performed the experiments, and Y.Q. and S.H. analyzed the 
results. S.C. and H.X. made the census on the relationship between TC recurvature and CAI </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4451 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04451 </p>



<p>
Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Peng, S.Q. et al. On the mechanisms of the recurvature of super 
typhoon Megi. Sci. Rep. 4, 4451; DOI:10.1038/srep04451 (2014). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported license. To view a copy of this license, 
visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4451 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04451 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>