<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3273808" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Compared to protein enzymes, our knowledge 
about how RNA accelerates chemical reactions is 
rather limited. The crystal structures of a ribozyme 
that catalyzes Diels-Alder reactions suggest a rich 
tertiary architecture responsible for catalysis. RNA can fold into 3D scaffolds that generate binding 
sites and catalytic centers. While natural ribozymes that 
catalyze the cleavage or ligation of RNA strands have 
been studied quite thoroughly, RNAs ability to accelerate 
chemically different reactions-and in particular those 
involving small molecules-received less attention. 
Consequently, the nature of RNA active sites evolved 
for such functions remains poorly understood (1-4). 
Carbon-carbon bond formation is a fundamental task 
in organic synthesis, biochemistry and prebiotic chemistry, 
and finding ribozymes that catalyze such processes has 
been a tremendous challenge (5,6). Our laboratory has 
previously reported the combinatorial selection of ribo-
zymes that catalyze C-C bond formation by Diels-
Alder reaction (5), an important reaction type in organic 
chemistry (7). The RNA molecules were selected to 
accelerate the cycloaddition reaction of an aromatic 
anthracene diene tethered to their 5 
0 -ends (in cis reaction) 
with a biotinylated maleimide dienophile. The majority 
of the active sequences was found to contain a small 
secondary structure motif consisting of three helices 
(shown in cyan, yellow and green, Figure 1a and 
Supplementary Figure S1), an asymmetric internal loop, 
and the formally single-stranded 5 
0 -end (shown in red), 
and a rationally re-designed 49-mer RNA containing 
these elements accelerated the in cis reaction about 
20 000-fold. These ribozymes were later found to cata-
lyze the cycloaddition reaction in a truly bimolecular 
fashion between dienes and dienophiles free in solution 
(in trans reaction). Other distinctive features are fast 
multiple-turnover catalysis and enantioselective bond 
formation (8). </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +49 6221 54 48 53; Fax: +49 6221 54 64 30; Email: jaeschke@uni-hd.de </p>

<p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. </p>

<p>1318-1330 Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 3 
Published online 5 October 2011 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkr812 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>A first insight into the principles of substrate recogni-
tion was obtained by studying the interactions of the 
ribozyme with a panel of systematically varied substrate 
analogs (9). These results suggested a major role for 
hydrophobic and van der Waals interactions, while 
hydrogen bonding and metal-ion coordination appeared 
to be less important for catalysis. Mutation analysis and 
chemical probing identified interactions between nucleo-
tides of the 5 
0 -terminus and the internal asymmetric 
bubble, and indicated a preformed catalytic pocket (10). 
These findings could be confirmed by the solution of the 
crystal structure of this ribozyme in the unbound state and 
in complex with the Diels-Alder reaction product (Figure 
1b and c) (11). The RNA was found to adopt a -shaped 
nested pseudoknot architecture, whose hydrophobic 
pocket shows precise shape complementarity (according 
to P1L21, P10L73, P11L9) to the reaction product 
(shown in dark blue). RNA folding and product binding 
are dictated by extensive stacking and hydrogen bonding, 
whereas stereoselection is governed by the shape of the 
catalytic pocket. The 5 
0 -terminal tetranucleotide segment 
plays a critical role in shaping both the RNA scaffold and </p>

<p>the catalytic pocket. All four residues align through 
Watson-Crick base pairing with residues on both sides 
of the asymmetric bubble segment (dotted black lines in 
Figure 1a), thereby forming the pseudoknot and zippering 
up the bubble (Figure 1b). The crystal structure suggests 
three hydrogen bonds between the ribozyme and the 
Diels-Alder product, involving amino and hydroxyl 
groups of the former and carbonyl and ether oxygen 
atoms of the latter (vide infra). 
These two crystallized complexes (11), however, repre-
sent only two points on the reaction coordinate (empty 
catalyst and catalyst-product complex), whereas other 
relevant intermediates (e.g. the ribozyme bound to 
the substrates or to a transition state analog) could not 
be crystallized. Therefore, alternative approaches are 
required for elucidating the principles that govern 
RNA-substrate interaction and catalytic rate acceleration. 
Considerable effort has been devoted recently to under-
standing the structural dynamics of the Diels-Alderase 
ribozyme. Single-molecule fluorescence resonance energy 
transfer (smFRET) and nuclear magnetic resonance 
(NMR) spectroscopy have revealed that the ribozyme is </p>

<p>Figure 1. Minimized Diels-Alderase ribozyme. (a) Ribozyme secondary structure with helices I, II and III (cyan, yellow, green), the asymmetric 
bubble and the conserved 5 
0 -end (both in red), and in-cis Diels-Alder reaction. (b) Tertiary fold and (c) 3D topology in the crystal structure of the 
ribozyme-product complex. One enantiomer of the Diels-Alder product (dark blue sticks with transparent spheres) is bound into the catalytic pocket 
of the ribozyme. This manuscript uses the original numbering scheme for this ribozyme (5). A translation map between the different schemes is 
provided as Supplementary Figure S1. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 3 1319 </p>

<p>highly dynamic in aqueous solution at room temperature 
(12,13). The concentration of divalent metal ions was es-
tablished as a major determinant of folding and dynamics 
(12-14). Recent molecular dynamics (MD) simulations 
revealed the existence of conformations with similar 
overall architecture but either closed or open catalytic 
pocket, resulting in either inactive or active catalysts (15). 
Based on this static and dynamic structural informa-
tion, we set out to elucidate the principles that govern 
RNA-substrate interaction and catalytic rate acceleration. 
The availability of high-resolution structural information 
allows to rationally design experiments that support or 
disprove the relevance of individual structural elements 
for the catalytic function of the ribozyme. 
In this study, we use the tool box of atomic mutagen-
esis. We add, delete or replace functional groups either in 
a rational site-directed or in a combinatorial fashion, and 
determine the enzymatic activity of the mutants. As these 
assays measure the rate of product formation, they can 
detect interference of the atomic mutation with any essen-
tial step that precedes or is concurrent with this event, 
from RNA folding to substrate binding to the chemical 
step of carbon-carbon bond formation. To identify inter-
acting positions, rescue experiments are carried out that 
involve compensatory double and triple mutations. These 
investigations are supplemented by chemical probing, in-
hibition and binding studies, and single-molecule fluores-
cence spectroscopy. In particular, we focus on the 
H-bonding network in the catalytic pocket. The results 
obtained present unprecedented insight into the strategies 
RNA utilizes to catalyze carbon-carbon bond formation. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Oligonucleotide synthesis and labeling </p>

<p>Oligonucleotides were synthesized by phosphoramidite 
chemistry (Expedite 8900 synthesizer, standard protecting 
groups, standard deprotection) or purchased from CSS 
Chemical Synthesis Services, Craigavon and IBA, 
Go¨ttingen. Phosphoramidites were from Proligo, 
Cruachem and ChemGenes. T7 transcription reactions 
were performed as described (16). a-Thio-modified nu-
cleoside triphosphate analogues were from Glen 
Research or IBA. Incorporation of hexa-ethylene glycol 
(HEG)-tethered anthracene was performed either chem-
ically by using the respective phosphoramidite, or by tran-
scription initiation (17). Oligonucleotides were purified by 
HPLC and/or PAGE. Oligonucleotides and conjugates 
were </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>P-labeled at their 3 
0 -end with T4 RNA ligase 
or Klenow fragment of DNA Polymerase I, or 5 
0 -end 
labeled with polynucleotide kinase, according to 
standard procedures (18). The 11-mer anthracene conju-
gates were always synthesized chemically, while RNA 
18-mers and 24-mers were either chemically synthesized, 
or prepared by run-off transcription. </p>

<p>Ribozyme activity assays </p>

<p>Two different gel electrophoretic assays were used. 
True initial rates of product formation were determined 
by monitoring the first 15% of conversion. For rapid </p>

<p>screening of mutants, semi-quantitative data were 
obtained by performing single-time point measurements 
with a standard reaction time of 30 min. A wild-type com-
bination of the unmutated strands was always run in 
parallel (typical yield: 65% conversion in 30 min) and 
used as reference. About 0.1 mg/ml dodecyl maltoside was 
added to avoid unspecific binding in the true initial rate 
assays. Other reaction conditions were as described (10). 
All assays were done in triplicate. 
The product inhibition kinetics were determined by 
UV/vis-spectroscopy in an in trans assay that employed 
the free (i.e. non-tethered) substrates anthracene-HEG 
(100 mM) and N-pentylmaleimide (500 mM) as well as 
28 mM double mutant ribozyme (G9Pu U17dU) in 
reaction buffer containing 10% ethanol in the presence 
of increasing concentrations of Diels-Alder products. 
Second-order rate constants of triple determinations 
were calculated over the first 5% conversion as k 
(M 
À1 h 
À1 ). All other conditions were as in reference (9). </p>

<p>Chemical probing </p>

<p>The 5 
0 -
32 P-labeled RNAs (fmol amounts, 50 000 cpm/sam-
ple) were supplemented with 0.15 mg/ml unlabeled tRNA. 
Reactions were performed in 0.75 mM freshly prepared 
lead acetate solution, in 40 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 
40 mM NaCl, 0-10 mM MgCl 2 , 5% ethanol, with or 
without 1 mM Diels-Alder product at 20 
C for 45 min 
and were terminated by 1:1 mixing with a 7 M urea, 
10 mM EDTA solution. Electrophoretic separation was 
performed on 15% denaturing polyacrylamide gels 
at 60 W for 3 h. Further reaction conditions were as in 
reference (10). </p>

<p>Nucleotide analog interference mapping </p>

<p>S P -a-thio modified nucleoside triphosphate analogues 
(NTPs) were statistically incorporated into in vitro 
transcribed RNAs using a modification of published 
protocols (19-21). Anthracene-HEG-GMP initiator 
nucleotides were incorporated at the 5 
0 -terminus (5). 
Transcriptions were performed in 40 mM Tris-HCl, pH 
8.0, 22 mM MgCl 2 , 4-7 mM spermidine, 10 mM DTT, 
2.4 mg/ml bovine serum albumine, 1 mM double-stranded 
DNA template, 1 mM initiator nucleotide A-HEG-GMP 
and 80 U T7-RNA polymerase. While most experiments 
were conducted with the wild-type sequence, investigation 
of the role of nucleotide G9 required (for incorporation of 
2-aminopurine, purine and 2,6-diaminopurine riboside) 
the use of a G9A mutant transcription template, while 
inosine was incorporated using the wild-type template. 
The two resulting transcript libraries showed largely dif-
ferent reactivities in Diels-Alder reactions and required 
different conditions (see below). Concentrations of S P -
aS-NTPs were adjusted according to the frequency of 
the respective nucleotide and the length of the ribozyme 
and had to be optimized for each analog. Transcription 
mixtures were ethanol precipitated and the re-dissolved 
pellets applied onto a C 18 -HPLC reversed phase column. 
Full length ribozyme conjugates were identified by their 
spectroscopic properties, isolated and 3 
0 -end-labeled 
using 5 
0 -
32 P-pCp and T4 RNA ligase. The resulting </p>



<p>Diels-Alderase-HEG-anthracene conjugate libraries con-
taining modified nucleosides (final concentrations 100 nM) 
were subjected to Diels-Alder reaction with 5 mM biotin 
maleimide, and the reaction time was adjusted to achieve a 
library conversion (Cr) of 25-33% (2 min for the wild-type 
sequence, 30 min for the less reactive G9A mutant). After 
electrophoretic separation on 20% polyacrylamide gels, 
(unreacted) substrate and (reacted) product bands were 
quantified by phosphorimaging, excised, eluted and sub-
jected to iodine cleavage in denaturing loading buffer 
(5.3 M urea, 34 mM EDTA pH 8.0) using 1/10 sample 
volume of ethanolic iodine solution (100 mM) for 3 min 
at room temperature and additionally for 1 min at 65 
C. 
Cleavage patterns were analyzed by phosphorimaging of 
denaturing 20% PAGE sequencing gels (0.4 mm) using 
alkaline hydrolysis and RNase T1 digest ladders for 
sequence assignments. Slight offsets of these reference 
lanes with respect to the phosphorothioate cleavage 
lanes are due to the different termini generated in the re-
actions. Analog interferences and phosphorothioate 
effects were identified by comparing the densities of sub-
strate and product bands of individual positions, which 
were also used for quantitative data calculation. Product 
band densities D p were multiplied with the respective 
library conversion values C r (vide supra), while substrate 
band densities D s were multiplied by the factor (1 À C r ). 
Reaction yields r = D p *C r /[D p *C r +D s *(1 À C r )] of indi-
vidual point mutants were calculated, taking into 
account the adjustment of the specific radioactivities of 
substrate and product lanes on the sequencing gels to 
equal levels. Relative activity values were calculated by 
comparison with the wild-type sequence. It should be 
noted that these values represent semi-quantitative 
activity data rather than true initial rates, as the samples 
were analyzed after 25-33% conversion, which was neces-
sary due to general practical requirements of the nucleo-
tide analog interference mapping (NAIM) methodology 
(19,22). </p>

<p>Single-molecule FRET experiments </p>

<p>Wild-type and U17isoC mutant ribozyme with a Cy3 dye 
attached to the 5 
0 -end, a Cy5 dye attached to position L2.2 
and a 3 
0 -biotin were synthesized by a chemoenzymatic 
approach as described in reference (23). The wild-type 
construct was found to have full activity (compared to a 
ribozyme without modifications), while the U17isoC 
mutant was found to be inactive (23). smFRET experi-
ments were carried out on a home-build confocal laser 
scanning microscope with single-molecule sensitivity, es-
sentially as described in reference (24,25). Briefly, probe 
solutions with freely diffusing RNA molecules at 
$100 pM concentration were placed in the sample cell. 
Excitation was done with 532 (green) and 633 nm (red) 
laser lines in alternating fashion at 10 kHz with 70% of 
duty cycle for the green laser. Detection of fluorescence 
light was performed synchronously with the excitation in 
two channels spectrally optimized for the donor (Cy3, 
550-610 nm) and acceptor (Cy5, 650-750 nm) emission. 
FRET efficiency histograms were compiled from selected 
fluorescent bursts with simultaneously photoactive donor </p>

<p>and acceptor, durations between 0.2 and 2 ms, and more 
than 30 photon counts. </p>

<p>Graphics </p>

<p>Figures were prepared from the PDB data set 1YLS, 
chains A and B, by using <rs type="software">PyMOL</rs> (26). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Individual site-specific atomic mutations </p>

<p>To assess the role of individual functional groups for 
catalysis, single mutations were introduced into the 
ribozyme by chemical synthesis, and the influence on the 
ribozyme-catalyzed reaction estimated using an earlier 
described tripartite Diels-Alderase assay (10). This 
ribozyme system of a 24-mer strand, an 18-mer and an 
anthracene-tether-11-mer spontaneously assembles after 
mixing, and reactions could be easily monitored by gel 
electrophoresis (see inset in Figure 2a). Important 
atomic positions were identified using a rapid screening 
assay, and only those mutants were selected for further 
characterization for which the amount of product 
formed within 30 min was reduced at least by half, 
compared to the wild-type. For these mutants, apparent 
rate constants k obs were determined by measuring the 
initial rate within the first 15% of conversion. Division 
by k obs, wild-type (0.12 min </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>) yielded k rel values. 
Site-specific 2 
0 -deoxy-substitutions introduced at all nu-
cleotides of the internal bubble and the 5 
0 -GGAG end 
revealed that not a single 2 
0 -hydroxyl group is absolutely 
required (Figure 2a). The strongest influence was observed 
at guanosine G9 (k obs = 0.005 min 
À1 , k rel = 4%), and 
slight activity reductions were seen at adenosines A15 
and A16, while for all other positions, the 2 
0 -OH group 
is apparently not critical. The high residual activity of 
the U17dU mutant (k obs = 0.04 min 
À1 , k rel = 34%) is 
noteworthy, as the 2 
0 -hydroxyl group of this nucleotide 
is proposed to be involved in the catalytic mechanism by 
hydrogen bonding to a maleimide carbonyl oxygen (11). 
For selected positions, 2 
0 -O-methyl substitutions were 
studied, too (red in Figure 2a). Nucleotide G9 tolerated 
this substitution even worse than the deoxy-modification 
(k rel = 1.5%). While A15 and A16 were insensitive to 2 
0 -O-
methylation, the U17 and A18 mutants showed reduced 
activities with k rel values of 11% and 2.5%, respectively. 
For the three uridine positions inside the internal 
bubble, the addition of a methyl group to the 5-position 
was additionally investigated by incorporating thymidine 
(blue in Figure 2a). This modification was found to be 
detrimental at U20 (k obs = 0.001 min 
À1 , k rel = 1%), 
while it has no significant influence at U8 and U17. </p>

<p>Combinatorial atomic mutations </p>

<p>Atomic mutagenesis can also be carried out in a combina-
torial fashion (NAIM) (19-21). While this technique was 
successfully applied to RNA-processing ribozymes for 
which the change in molecular size due to self-cleavage 
is a convenient selection marker, the investigation of the 
Diels-Alder reaction required the development of a </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 3 1321 </p>

<p>modified approach. This involved the preparation and 
purification of RNA-tether-anthracene conjugates (17) 
with statistically incorporated a-thio-nucleoside triphos-
phates (a-thio-NTPs), their 3 
0 -terminal 
32 P-labeling, 
reaction with biotin maleimide, and the separation of 
reacted and unreacted fractions by denaturing PAGE, 
followed by iodine cleavage at the thiophosphate group 
and gel analysis (Supplementary Figure S2). </p>

<p>The role of the non-bridging pro-R P -phosphate oxygen 
atoms was studied by using the parental a-thio-NTPs 
(i.e. those nucleotides that do not carry additional modi-
fications). While no phosphorothioate interferences 
were observed for the purine nucleotides, weak but signifi-
cant interferences were found in the pyrimidine series 
primarily at positions C10, C11, C19, U8, U17 and U20 
(Supplementary Figure S3). According to the crystal struc-
ture, all these positions are candidates for metal ion 
coordination (11). Using modified a-thio-NTPs, rather 
strong interferences were observed for inosine, pur-
ine riboside and 2-aminopurine riboside substitutions 
at position G9, a nucleotide proposed to make a 
mechanistically important H-bond to the transition state 
(Figure 2b). Another strong interference was seen at 
position A18, in particular for 7-deaza-adenosine, 
2-aminopurine riboside and purine riboside, while 
weaker interferences were seen for N6-methyl-adenosine 
and 2,6-diaminopurine riboside, suggesting an importance 
of the Hoogsteen face of this nucleotide. Weak interfer-
ences are also seen for nucleotide A/G 12 at the interface 
of helix III and the internal loop for 7-deaza-adenosine, 
2-aminopurine riboside, purine riboside and 2,6-diamino-
purine riboside (Figure 2b). </p>

<p>Site-specific double mutations </p>

<p>To quantitatively determine the contribution of the two 
proposed H-bonds between Diels-Alder transition state 
and ribozyme (2-NH 2 of G9 and 2 
0 -OH of U17, both 
with the same maleimide carbonyl oxygen), we combined 
individual RNA strands with chemical modifications at 
the G9 and U17 positions and determined initial rates in 
the tripartite assay. These measurements revealed k rel 
values of 10% (2-aminopurine), 12% (purine) and 22% 
(inosine) for the single-mutants in position 9 and 4-5% for 
the double mutants that carried the U17dU substitution 
(Figure 3a), thereby showing that both proposed H-bonds 
indeed contribute to catalytic rate acceleration in an 
additive manner. </p>

<p>Product inhibition studies </p>

<p>The Diels-Alderase is known to be strongly product-
inhibited (IC 50 $10-20 mM) (9), and these two above-
mentioned H-bonds are likely to contribute. To study 
their relevance in product binding, a 49-mer double 
mutant was synthesized that carries the U17dU and the 
G9Pu substitutions in one strand, and its catalytic activity 
towards the free (i.e. non-tethered) substrates determined 
in the presence of increasing amounts of two different 
Diels-Alder products. No effect on the reaction rate 
could be observed up to the solubility limits of these com-
pounds (200 and 500 mM, respectively, Figure 3b), sup-
porting the hypothesis that the product normally makes 
critical interactions with the 2-NH 2 of G9 and the 2 
0 -OH 
of U17. </p>

<p>Site-specific rescue experiments involving modified 
nucleotides </p>

<p>To probe the relevance for catalysis of other secondary 
and tertiary interactions observed in the crystal structure </p>

<p>Figure 2. Single mutation analysis. (a) Individual site-specific muta-
tions. Gray scale represents activity of 2 
0 -deoxy mutants: black-no 
effect, gray-slight reduction, white w. black hairline-strong effect. 
Red: 2 
0 -O-methyl substitutions. Blue: 5-methyl substitution. The inset 
shows a typical assay gel for determination of k obs in the tripartite 
ribozyme assay. S-substrate, P-product. (b) NAIM. PAGE gels 
showing interferences at positions 9 and 12. Bottom: summary of nu-
cleotide analog effects. Arrow size corresponds to the magnitude of the 
effects. </p>



<p>by activity restoration (rescues), site-specifically sub-
stituted double and triple mutants were chemically 
synthesized and assayed for catalytic activity. These 
chemically modified ribozyme variants involved 
2 
0 -deoxyguanosine, 2 
0 -methoxyguanosine, 7-deazaguan-
osine, 8-oxo-2 
0 -deoxyguanosine, isoguanosine and 
isocytidine substitutions. The results are summarized in 
Table 1 and discussed in a structural context below. 
The (putative) structures of modified base pairs and 
triples are shown in Supplementary Figure S4. One of 
the most interesting results is the dependence of catalytic 
activity on the presence of a single H-bond (4-NH 2 group 
of C10 versus carbonyl oxygen O 2 of U17). </p>

<p>Chemical probing </p>

<p>To elucidate the reason for the functional relevance of this 
interaction, lead probing experiments were carried out 
with the U17 wild-type, a 33% active U17C mutant and 
the completely inactive U17isoC mutant. Lead probing 
detects both, specific metal ion coordination and general 
accessibility of the phosphodiester bonds (27). While the 
overall probing patterns are very similar (indicating 
similar overall structures), the lower half of the asymmet-
ric bubble shows significant differences. Nucleotide A18 
(the direct neighbor of U17) is completely protected from 
lead cleavage in the wild-type and U17C mutants, while it 
is efficiently cleaved in the isoC mutant (Figure 3c). While 
wild-type and U17C mutant are stabilized against cleavage 
by increasing Mg 
2+ ion concentration, the probing pattern </p>

<p>of the U17isoC mutant is not influenced by divalent 
cations. Another striking difference is the alteration 
of the probing patterns upon addition of Diels-Alder 
product (Supplementary Figure S5). In contrast to 
wild-type and U17C mutant, the U17isoC mutant 
exhibits no changes at all, indicating a strongly reduced 
affinity for the reaction product. </p>

<p>smFRET spectroscopy </p>

<p>To further elucidate the role of this particular H-bond, 
variants of the wild-type and the U17isoC mutant were 
synthesized, labeled with a pair of dyes (Cy3 at the 5 
0 -end 
and Cy5 in the upper tetraloop) (Supplementary Figure 
S6) and investigated by smFRET spectroscopy on freely 
diffusing molecules in solution (24), probing conform-
ational states by varying the concentration of Mg 
2+ ions 
(Figure 4). For both constructs, a similar behavior was 
observed: Two conformations could be distinguished 
with nearly identical average FRET intensities E of 0.42 
and 0.74 (wild-type) and 0.44 and 0.75 (mutant). 
According to our previous work, these conformations 
can be assigned to intermediate (I) and folded (F) states 
(12). For both constructs, the fractional population of the 
F state increases with the Mg 
2+ ion concentration at the 
expense of the I state in a similar fashion with midpoints 
of 4.0 and 9.3 mM, respectively. The essentially identical 
E-values and the similar shapes of the distributions 
indicate that the distances between the dyes are the same 
and, thus, suggest similar 3D structures. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Investigation of mutations: (a) Relative catalytic activity of the differently combined modifications in positions 9 and 17. Gray column 
represents the wild-type. (b) Catalytic activity of the U17dU G9Pu double mutant in the presence of two different Diels-Alder products. (c) Lead 
probing PAGE gel of 5 
0 -
32 P-labeled wild-type, U17C and U17isoC mutant at different Mg 
2+ ion concentrations (0-10 mM). 'OH' and 'T1' corres-
pond to alkaline hydrolysis and RNase T1 ladder, 'Ctrl' to control incubation (absence of lead ions). For precise assignment of the bands, compare 
Figure 6 in reference (10). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 3 1323 </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Architectural principles: the 'spine' and the stabilization 
of the cross-strand junction </p>

<p>The data obtained in this study allow to more precisely 
define structural elements and to assign function. While 
X-ray crystallography showed that extensive stacking is an 
important principle of this ribozyme's structure formation 
(11), the atomic mutagenesis data presented here identify 
the extended cross-strand stack that runs through the 
whole molecule from the bottom of helix II through the 
catalytic pocket to the top of helix III (semi-transparent 
gray spheres in Figure 5a, for a stereo picture see 
Supplementary Figure S7) as arguably the single most im-
portant and most sensitive structural element. We call this 
element the 'spine', and it shapes and reinforces the overall 
architecture of the catalyst. The junction point of the 
cross-strand stack is located between nucleotides G9 and 
U17 (Figure 5b). Nucleotide G9 makes-according to the 
crystal structure-a number of non-standard interactions, 
one of them being a hydrogen bond proposed between its </p>

<p>2 
0 -OH group and ring nitrogen HN3 of nucleotide U17 
(11). This position is found to be sensitive to 2 
0 -deoxy 
substitution (Table 1 and Figure 2a, k rel = 4%), and 
placement of two H-bond acceptors opposite each other 
completely abolishes catalytic activity (G9-2 
0 OMeG 
versus U17C, k rel &lt; 0.1%), thereby strongly supporting 
the importance of this particular interaction. 
The crystallographic data localize a Mg 
2+ ion (#5) in the 
direct vicinity of the junction point. The analysis of the 
activity data indicates a stabilizing role of this metal ion. It 
is apparently coordinated to a 5 
0 -phosphate oxygen of 
U8 (as suggested by the phosphorothioate interference at 
U8) and carbonyl oxygen O6 of nucleobase G9 on one 
side of the junction point, as well as with carbonyl 
oxygen O4 of U17 on the other side. Replacement of 
either carbonyl oxygen atom by an amino group reduces </p>

<p>Figure 4. Histograms of smFRET efficiency values, E, measured on 
freely diffusing wild-type ribozyme (left) and U17isoC mutant (right) 
molecules in buffer solutions at five different Mg 
2+ concentrations. 
Dashed and solid thin lines represent best-fit model distributions for 
the I and F states, respectively; the solid thick line gives the sum of the 
distributions. It should be noted that, in comparison to our previous 
work (12), the dye positions were changed to ensure full catalytic 
activity of the wild-type construct. </p>

<p>Table 1. Catalytic activities of various single, double and triple 
mutants of the Diels-Alderase ribozyme </p>

<p>5 
0 -end 
Upper bulge 
Lower bulge 
k obs (min 
À1 ) </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>k rel (%) </p>

<p>U8-A18 reverse Hoogsteen base pair 
U8C 
0.0023 
1.9 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>U8iC 
0.001 
0.8 
A18G 
0 
0 
A18deazaG 
0 
0 
A18-8OxodG 
0.0029 
2.4 
U8C 
A18G 
0 
0 
U8C 
A18deazaG 
0 
0 
U8C 
A18-8OxodG 
0.0032 
2.6 
U8iC 
A18G 
0 
U8iC 
A18deazaG 
0 
U8iC 
A18-8OxodG 
0.0002 
0.2 </p>

<p>Pseudoknot base pairs G1-C11 and G2-C10 
G1iG 
$0.05 
$40 
C11iC 
0.0004 
0.3 
G1iG 
C11iC 
0.0037 
3.1 
G2iG 
0.01 
8 
C10iC 
0.001 
0.8 
G2iG 
C10iC 
0.0004 
0.3 </p>

<p>Base triple G2-C10-U17 
U17C 
0.04 
33 
U17iC 
0 
0 
G2iG 
C10iC 
U17iC 
0 
0 
G2iG 
C10iC 
U17C 
0 
0 </p>

<p>Spine junction G9-U17 
G9dG9 
0.005 
4 
G9-2 
0 OMeG 
0.0018 
1.5 
U17C 
0.04 
33 
G9dG9 
U17C 
0.0018 
1.5 
G9-2'OMeG 
U17C 
0 
0 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Initial rates were determined in the tripartite gel-shift assay over the 
first 15% of conversion. The initial rate of the wild-type sequence com-
bination was defined as 100%. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>'0' denotes a k obs &lt; 0.0001 min 
À1 and a k rel &lt; 0.1%. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>The U8 position was earlier referred to as 'absolutely conserved' (10). 
This assignment has to be changed into 'highly conserved', as the U8C 
mutant shows significant residual (1.9% wild-type) activity. </p>



<p>ribozyme activity by a factor of 3 (Table 1 and Figure 5a), 
presumably due to attenuated interaction with the 
hydrated Mg 
2+ ion. We interpret these data as indicating 
a synergistic stabilization of the cross-strand junction by 
the combined action of the G9-U17 H-bond and Mg #5. 
Interference with the H-bond apparently 'breaks the 
spine', thereby causing loss of function, while an 
attenuated interaction with the metal ion has a less 
dramatic effect. </p>

<p>The formation of the catalytic pocket: the 'roof' </p>

<p>The spine is involved in numerous critical interactions: In 
the central part, it holds the upper pseudoknot minihelix </p>

<p>G1-C11 and G2-C10, which-in the proper orientation-
can be viewed as the 'roof' of the catalytic pocket. This 
minihelix seen in the crystal had so far only been sup-
ported by indirect evidence from chemical probing, as all 
mutations in this part (including pair-wise complementary 
ones) resulted in inactive constructs (10). Here, a partial 
rescue observed with the isomeric G1isoG-C11isoC 
double mutant (3.1% activity versus 0.3% activity for 
the C11isoC single mutant, Table 1) provides some 
support for this interaction in solution, whereas no 
rescue was seen for the G2-C10 interaction (28). 
Attachment of the roof to the spine is apparently ac-
complished by a single hydrogen bond, namely between </p>

<p>Figure 5. Visualization of structural features of the Diels-Alderase ribozyme. (a) Overview of the structure. Nucleotides belonging to the 'spine' are 
represented as semi-transparent gray spheres through all panels of this figure. (b) Cross-strand junction stabilized by magnesium ion Mg5 and one 
H-bond. Inset: k rel values of selected atomic mutants. (c) Coordination of magnesium ion Mg3. (d) Importance of the U17-C10 H-bond with atomic 
mutagenesis data. (e) The reverse Hoogsteen base pair U8-A18 with supporting data. (f) Sharp turn involving nucleotides 18-21.4. The two arrows 
indicate positions where the addition of a CH 3 group interferes with activity. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 3 1325 </p>

<p>the exocyclic 4-NH 2 group of C10 (of the G2-C10 base 
pair) and carbonyl oxygen O2 of U17 (the nucleotide 
already found important for the stabilization of the 
cross-strand junction). In agreement with a critical role 
of this interaction, incorporation of isoC at position 17 
in which the critical carbonyl oxygen O 2 is replaced by a 
NH 2 group yields a completely inactive ribozyme 
(k rel &lt; 0.1%, Table 1, Figure 5d). A triple rescue experi-
ment for this tertiary interaction is conceivable but 
not trivial, as the interacting nucleotides constitute 
the active site and make direct contacts with the 
substrates. The inactivity of the isosteric triple mutant 
U17isoC-C10isoC-G2isoG (k rel &lt; 0.1%, Table 1 and 
Supplementary Figure S4) is, therefore, not surprising. 
Further insight into the role of this particular inter-
action was obtained by chemical probing (Figure 3c) 
and smFRET spectroscopy (Figure 4) of the U17isoC 
mutant. Both techniques indicate a global structure very 
similar to the wild-type ribozyme, but with a different 
state of the catalytic pocket. The lower half of the bulge 
becomes more accessible to lead ions, and both methods 
fail to detect any binding to the Diels-Alder product. 
Intriguingly, MD simulations recently established the 
existence of Diels-Alderase ribozyme conformations 
with a closed pocket (15). These species still contain the 
global nested pseudoknot fold, but the register of the 
upper pseudoknot minihelix is shifted (G2:C11 and 
G1:A12 instead of G2:C10 and G1:C11), the stabilizing 
interaction with U17 is missing, and nucleotide G2 stacks 
directly on A3, thereby closing the catalytic pocket. The 
U17isoC mutant might therefore be an RNA that exists in 
the closed pocket state only, is catalytically incompetent, 
and cannot bind the reaction product. 
In the wild-type ribozyme, the critical C10-U17 
hydrogen bond is apparently the only stabilizing 
inter-strand interaction in this section and needs precise 
positioning for fine-tuned interaction. If perturbed, 
the catalytic pocket may either collapse, or the upper 
minihelix may fall off the spine, thereby removing the 
roof and parts of the back wall from the catalytic 
pocket. The possibility to disassemble the catalytic 
pocket by breaking a single hydrogen bond may be im-
portant for the multiple-turnover behavior of this catalyst 
(8,9), and also for the possibility of a 'back door' reaction 
pathway that requires substrate passage through a narrow 
orifice (29). Such a frequent breakdown and re-formation 
of the tertiary structure would be consistent with the struc-
tural transitions between 'folded' and 'intermediate' con-
formations on the 100 ms timescale, which were observed 
by both single-molecule (12) and NMR spectroscopy (13). </p>

<p>The interface between catalytic pocket and helix III </p>

<p>Following the spine toward the top, the next structural 
element is the interface between catalytic pocket and 
helix III. According to the crystal structure (11), a mag-
nesium ion (#3) is localized in this region, where the 
sugar-phosphate backbone of the counter-strand shows 
deviations from a standard helical conformation. The 
observed phosphorothioate interferences are in agreement 
with metal ion binding to the 5 
0 -phosphate of C11, and </p>

<p>the weak nucleotide analog effects at position A12 
(7-deazaadenine, 2-aminopurine, purine) support the im-
portance of its Hoogsteen face, which points toward the 
bound ion (Figure 5c). Likely, metal ion coordination at 
this site helps positioning the upper pseudoknot minihelix 
for proper interaction with its partners. </p>

<p>The central scaffold element: helix II, the sharp turn 
and Mg ions #1 and 2 </p>

<p>From the cross-strand junction towards the bottom, the 
spine holds a very unusual element that is critical for 
aligning helices I and II in a special kind of three-way 
junction (Figure 5a). Neighboring nucleotides G7.4 and 
U8 form stacked base pairs; a standard Watson-Crick 
pair G7.4-C21.4 and a reverse Hoogsteen pair U8-A18, 
thereby formally extending helix II by one base pair. In a 
sharp turn of the counter-strand, the intervening nucleo-
tides C19 and U20 are pushed outwards and rotated, 
allowing them to form-with their Watson-Crick 
faces-the lower pseudoknot minihelix that stacks upon 
helix I and forms the bottom of the catalytic pocket. Thus, 
while the first and the last member of this four-nucleotide 
stretch form one helix, the second and third one are 
involved in another one. While the phosphate backbone 
of the counter-strand makes only a $180 
turn, bases 
A18 and C21.4 stack upon each other and enclose a full 
360 
segment (Figure 5f). The importance of the sharp 
turn is confirmed here by two findings: While a 
2 
0 -deoxy-substitution is tolerated well at nucleotide A18, 
incorporation of a 2 
0 -OMe group causes a rather large 
reduction in activity (Figure 2, k rel $ 2.5%). Strikingly, 
the addition of a methyl group to carbon atom C5 of nu-
cleotide U20 leads to inactivation of comparable magni-
tude (Figure 2, k rel = 1%). These two phenomena seem to 
be connected: in the crystal structure, the 2 
0 -O atom of 
A18 and C5 of U20 are only 3.3 Å apart and point 
(roughly) towards each other (see arrows in Figure 5f). 
Thus, the addition of a methyl group at either side of 
this hydrophobic compartment has a similarly detrimental 
effect. 
The U8-A18 reverse Hoogsteen base pair (Figure 5e) 
has been supported by independent data. Both nucleotides 
are highly conserved, and chemical probing indicated that 
the N1 position (Watson-Crick face) gets exposed on 
tertiary structure formation, while N7 (Hoogsteen side) 
becomes protected (10). An A18G substitution mutant is 
completely inactive, in agreement with the different 
Hoogsteen pairing schemes for the two purine nucleotides 
(10). The removal of the N7 ring nitrogen (deazaA) or the 
exocyclic amino group (2-aminopurine, purine) lead to 
reduced activities in NAIM experiments. The complete 
or near-complete inactivity of all double mutants 
designed to probe this interaction (Table 1) is likely due 
to direct interaction of this base pair with the substrates. 
In the crystal structure, two Mg 
2+ ions (#1 and #2) 
are observed right next to this sharp turn, bound central-
ly in the major grove of helix II, and at the same time 
coordinate to the opposed U19 and C20 of the pseudo-
knot minihelix (Figure 5a and f). A significant phosphor-
othioate interference was observed here for C19 </p>



<p>(Supplementary Figure S3), likely due to direct coordin-
ation of its pro-R P phosphate to magnesium ion #2. The 
pro-R P phosphate oxygen of nucleotide U20 is located 4.0-
4.5 Å away from both Mg1 and Mg2, which is a typical 
distance for outer sphere interactions and may explain the 
weaker interference. The dimeric metal ion site was also 
supported by EPR-spectroscopy that identified-by a 
distinct coupling pattern-two metal ions in close proxim-
ity ($7 Å distance) (14), and by MD simulations (15). </p>

<p>The hydrogen bonding network inside the catalytic pocket </p>

<p>The catalytic center is formed by the central spine section 
(including the junction), the roof, the bottom, and the 
reverse Hoogsteen adenosine, and a total of 8 nt make 
contact with the reaction product (Figure 6). The pocket 
is held together by an intricate hydrogen bonding network 
that looks like those seen in typical enzyme active sites. 
Conventional and atomic mutagenesis was used to probe 
the relevance of each interaction. The two Watson-Crick 
standard type interactions (gray dotted lines) are found 
important, but conservation levels differ. The bottom 
A-U pair tolerates pair-wise complementary substitutions 
(10), while for the roof G-C base pair the G2isoG 
(k rel = 8%) and the C10isoC exchanges (k rel = 0.8%) are 
the only mutations that do not completely abolish catalyt-
ic activity. This may be due to the different functions; the 
bottom apparently provides primarily a platform for diene 
stacking, while the roof has to interact with both sub-
strates. Several non-standard interactions are found to 
be critically important for function (blue dotted lines), in 
particular those involving either junction nucleotide U17 
or the reverse Hoogsteen pair U8-A18. Other interactions 
that are conceivable on the basis of the crystallographic 
information are found to be not essential for catalysis (red 
dotted lines). The hydrogen bond between ring nitrogen 
N3 of nucleotide A18 and the 2 
0 -OH group of U20 is not 
essential, since the U20dU mutant shows high catalytic 
activity (Figure 2a), and the interaction between ring 
nitrogen HN1 of G9 and the 5 
0 -phosphate group of A18 
is also not critically important, as G9 mutants with an 
unprotonated N1 (purine and diaminopurine, Figures 2 
and 3) are found to be active. </p>

<p>RNA-substrate interactions and mechanistic 
considerations </p>

<p>Two of the three hydrogen bonds between RNA and 
bound cycloaddition product observed in the crystal struc-
ture involve a carbonyl oxygen (arising from the 
maleimide substrate) of the reaction product and have 
the exocyclic 2-NH 2 group of guanosine G9 and the 
2 
0 -OH group of U17 as partners. Such hydrogen bonds 
could indeed be mechanistically meaningful, as a 
dienophile's reactivity in a Diels-Alder reaction is 
known to be enhanced by the withdrawal of electron 
density via hydrogen bonds (30), a strategy also 
observed in catalytic Diels-Alderase antibodies (31,32). 
The atomic mutagenesis data presented here support 
this view (Figure 3a). While removal of the 2 
0 -OH group 
of U17 causes only a 3-fold reduction in activity, destruc-
tion of the H-bond to the 2-NH 2 group of G9 by </p>

<p>incorporation of inosine and purine results in a 5-to 
8-fold decrease. The respective double mutants have 
residual activities of 4-5% of the wild-type, demonstrating 
an additive effect of the two interactions. This additivity 
suggests that the ribozyme combines the energy of two 
interactions of moderate strength to make a significant 
contribution to catalysis (33). The measured rates 
suggest that these two hydrogen bonds together contribute 
$7-8 kJ/mol to transition state stabilization. On the other 
hand, such a residual activity represents a $600-fold rate 
acceleration with respect to the uncatalyzed background 
(corresponding to a ÁÁG 
# of $16 kJ/mol). Thus, the 
larger part of the energetic contribution comes from 
other interactions. The crystal structures indicated an ex-
cellent shape complementarity between the catalytic 
pocket and both, the Diels-Alder product and the transi-
tion state of the reaction. The magnitude of the </p>

<p>Figure 6. Surface representation of the catalytic pocket. (a) Empty 
catalytic pocket with stick representations of the nucleotides. 
Standard Watson-Crick type interactions are indicated by gray 
dotted lines, blue indicates non-standard interaction and red highlights 
interactions for which no experimental evidence was found. (b) RNA-
product interactions. Only those nucleotides are shown that were 
proposed to interact with the Diels-Alder product (red dotted lines). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 3 1327 </p>

<p>equilibrium dissociation constant of the RNA-product 
complex (9,25) ($10 mM, corresponding to a ÁG of 
$30 kJ/mol) suggests that noncovalent interactions 
between the transition state and the catalytic pocket can 
easily provide the required amount of activation energy. 
Our finding that the point mutant U17isoC folds into the 
pseudoknot shape but cannot stabilize the appropriately 
shaped catalytic pocket and is completely inactive high-
lights the importance of shape complementarity. 
These two H-bonds between RNA and Diels-Alder 
product are also found to be responsible for the high 
affinity of this ribozyme for the Diels-Alder product and 
the associated strong product inhibition (9). In contrast to 
the wild-type ribozyme, the G9Pu U17dU double mutant 
was not even slightly inhibited by two different Diels-
Alder products up to their respective solubility limits. 
This finding is not surprising, considering the strong simi-
larity of reaction product and transition state. 
The third hydrogen bond proposed in the RNA-
product complex between the 6-NH 2 group of adenosine 
A3 and the first ether oxygen of the polyethylene glycol 
tether attached to the reaction product is not critical 
either, since both partners of this interaction were previ-
ously shown to be variable (9,10,29). </p>

<p>The T-loop motif and its role in the catalysis of 
Diels-Alder reactions </p>

<p>Careful analysis of the structural features of the Diels-
Alderase ribozyme revealed the presence of an important 
tertiary structure motif that is well known in a different 
context. The sharp 4 base-pair turn, with the bottom base 
pair being a Watson-Crick and the top base pair a reverse 
Hoogsteen, is known as the UA_handle which is, e.g. part 
of the T-loop signature found in tRNA (34). There, it 
directly interacts with the D-loop and thereby makes an 
essential contribution to the formation of the L-shaped 
tertiary structure. The nucleotides involved in its forma-
tion are among the most conserved ones in the whole 
tRNA structure, and the U54-A58 reverse Hoogsteen 
interaction was identified as one of the key structural 
aspects of tRNA functionality (35). The striking structural 
similarities between the respective sections of the Diels-
Alderase ribozyme and tRNA 
Phe (from yeast, PDB Data 
set 1EHZ) are highlighted in Figure 7 (for more details, 
see Supplementary Figure S8). Several occurrences of this 
T-loop motif and the UA_handle submotif have also been </p>

<p>reported in ribosomal and other large RNAs (34,36,37). 
Thus, rather than inventing a new structural solution for 
the problem of catalyzing a Diels-Alder reaction, in vitro 
evolution has recycled a motif that natural evolution has 
created a long time ago for completely different purposes, 
providing yet another example for the modular character 
of RNA architecture (38-40). 
The occurrence of the T-loop motif in the Diels-
Alderase ribozyme makes an interesting connection to a 
report about the catalysis of Diels-Alder reactions by 
native tRNA (tRNA 
Phe from yeast) under high pressure 
(41). In that study, a different set of substrates 
(6-furfuryl-adenine as diene and maleic anhydride as 
dienophile) was used. The authors concluded from 
pressure-dependent lead probing and CD spectroscopy 
that high pressure disrupts the T-loop-D-loop interaction, 
and proposed that this opened tRNA forms a scaffold to 
which the diene is docked by stacking interaction. 
Considering the structural parallels with the Diels-
Alderase ribozyme, this suggestion appears conceivable, 
as the left half of the catalytic center would already be 
in place. The adenine part of the diene substrate could 
furthermore be sandwiched between the G57 (yellow) 
and reverse Hoogsteen A58 (blue) in the space that is 
normally occupied by G18 from the D-loop, thereby 
placing the furfuryl ring roughly at the same position 
(relative to the T-loop motif) as the anthracene ring 
system in the Diels-Alderase ribozyme. How the 
dienophile substrate is positioned and how the catalytic 
site is formed remains unclear, however. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS AND OUTLOOK </p>

<p>While the X-ray crystal structures of the Diels-Alderase 
provided a first detailed glimpse at the structural prin-
ciples governing the architecture of this remarkable 
ribozyme, the atomic mutagenesis studies presented here 
allow the classification of structural elements and the as-
signment of function. The roles of several individual 
hydrogen bonds and of four magnesium ions for the sta-
bility and catalytic function of the ribozyme could be un-
raveled. The critical importance of the central hydrogen 
bonding network was established by experimental data. 
Moreover, new insight was obtained regarding the mech-
anistic role of hydrogen bonds between catalyst and sub-
strates, and the integrity of the catalytic pocket. The loss </p>

<p>Figure 7. Comparison of the structures of the Diels-Alderase sharp turn (panel a) and the T-loop of tRNA 
Phe (b). </p>



<p>of a single H-bond on the surface of the catalytic pocket 
leads to complete inactivation. The base triplet G2-C10-
U17 and, in particular, the acceptor-donor pair 2O-U17 
versus 4NH 2 -C10, are of extraordinary importance for the 
formation of the active fold. A sharp 360 
turn reminis-
cent of the T-loop motif observed in tRNA is found to be 
crucially important for catalytic function, although its 
precise role is not clear yet. Future work will address 
some of the open questions regarding the structure and 
mechanism of this ribozyme, such as the order of substrate 
binding and the role of conformational changes during the 
catalytic cycle, and the molecular details about how this 
ribozymes folds into its nested pseudoknot tertiary 
architecture. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online: 
Supplementary Figures S1-S8. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG Ja 794/3 and 
CFN); BioFuture program of the German Federal 
Government (BEO 0311861); Human Frontiers Science 
Program (RGP 76/2003); Fonds der Chemischen 
Industrie, and the Volkswagen Foundation (VW-I/ 
82549). Funding for open access charge: Institutional 
Budget. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 3 1329 </p>





</text></tei>