<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3184742" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: </p>

<p>Objective: The aim of this cross-sectional analytic study was to evaluate the diagnostic 
efficacy of panoramic-based indices of the mandible (Mental Index-MI, Mandibular Cor-
tical Index-MCI and Panoramic Mandibular Index-PMI) and to determine their correlation 
with bone mineral density (BMD) of the femoral neck and lumbar vertebrae (L2-L4) in 
order to assess the possibility of using these parameters as indicators of osteoporosis. 
Materials and Methods: The mandibular indices of 67 women over 35 years old were 
measured from panoramic radiographs, and bone densitometry was performed in the fe-
moral neck and lumbar vertebrae (L2-L4), using DXA (Dual Energy X-ray Absorptiome-
try) technique. The patients were divided into three categories of normal, osteopenic and 
osteoporotic in each skeletal region. One-way ANOVA and ROC curve analyses were ap-
plied. The results were considered statistically significant when the P-value was less than 
0.05. 
Results: Comparing the mean BMD in the femoral neck in women between C1 and C3 
subgroups of MCI, a significant difference was detected (P=0.04). The mean PMI in the 
three skeletal subgroups was not different according to the skeletal region (P&gt;0.05). We 
found a significant difference in mean MI between normal and osteopenic subgroups in 
the femoral neck (P=0.042). 
Conclusion: Using radiomorphometric indices of the mandible (MCI-MI) may be useful 
in determining the skeletal status of the patients, but is not sufficient for precise evalua-
tion. </p>

<p>and consequent morbidity for patients. Since 
the disease is preventable, diagnostic tech-
niques are of major importance. A considera-
ble effort has been made to identify methods 
of detecting individuals with osteoporosis at an 
early stage to limit the disease process. In 
much a number of studies, bone mineral densi-
ty (BMD) in the mandible has been described 
to be strongly correlated with that in the lum-</p>

<p>Marandi et al. </p>

<p>Relationship between Panoramic Indices and Bone Density </p>

<p>2010; Vol. 7, No. 2 </p>



<p>bar spine and femoral neck, the most suscepti-
ble osteoporotic areas [2]. 
It is essential to use the panoramic radiographs 
for routine dental examinations especially be-
fore prosthodontic and periodontal treatments 
and maxillofacial surgeries. In panoramic ra-
diographs, a number of mandibular indices 
have been made to do the quantitative measur-
ing of the mandibular bone mass and trabecu-
lar architecture in order to diagnose patients 
with osteoporosis. Mental index (MI), pano-
ramic mandibular index (PMI) and mandibular 
cortical index (MCI) are among these indices. 
Radiographs have shown that the decreased 
BMD affects the morphometric [3-5], densi-
tometric [6] and architectural characteristics 
[7, 8] of the mandibular bone on radiographs. 
The aim of this study was to evaluate the asso-
ciation between various oral signs and osteo-
porosis in women to determine whether these 
radiographic measurements have accuracy in 
predicting BMD in order to detect the disease 
in the early stage and prevent the consequent 
side effects. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
This cross-sectional descriptive analytic study 
was based on 67 women in the age range of 36 
to 92 years old who were referred to the Radi-
ology Department of Mashhad Dental School. 
All of them had a panoramic radiography in 
their orders and none of the participants was 
known to have any prior fracture and systemic 
disease that would affect bone metabolism 
(chronic renal osteodystrophy, hyperparathy-
roidism, hypoparathyroidism, gastrointestinal 
disease, paget's disease or rheumatoid arthri-</p>

<p>tis). They were not using specific drugs or 
hormones (corticosteroids, cyclosporine, hepa-
rin, estrogen, progesterone, androgen and 
excess thyroid hormone). The data regarding 
age and BMI (body mass index) was obtained 
by questionnaire. All the panoramic radio-
graphs were taken with PM 2002 CC appara-
tus (Planmeca Oy, Asentajankatu 6, 00880 
Helsinki, Finland) by a single operator (AB). 
The position of the head was standardized as 
much as possible and also the exposure factors 
(kVp, mA) were regulated for each patient. To 
have similar density and contrast in all radio-
graphs, we used both AGFA Dentus panoram-
ic film (Heraeus Kulzer, Belgium) and Kodak 
screens (Kodak Lanex Regular Screen, East-
man Kodak Company, USA). Processing of 
the films was automatically performed by <rs id="software-0" type="software">Pro- tec processor</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">PROTEC medical systems</rs>, 
Stuttgart, Germany). For examination of the 
bone mineral density, DXA (Dual Energy X-
ray Absorptiometry) scans were performed 
with Osteocore 2 (MEDILINK, France). This 
technique is widely accepted as the "gold 
standard" method of clinical bone mineral 
measurements [9,10]. DXA itself is subject to 
some minor inaccuracy in BMD measurement 
[6]. Precision of DXA ranges from 0.55 to 5% 
[11]. 
Sixty-seven panoramic radiographs were ana-
lyzed for MCI, MI and PMI. According to Jo-
witt et al [12], "MCI is classification of the 
appearance of the mandibular inferior cortex 
distal to the mental foramen, which includes 
the following criteria: 
C1: The endosteal margin of the cortex is even 
and sharp on both sides of the mandible. </p>

<p>Table 1. Correlation of PMI with BMD of the femoral neck and lumbar spine. </p>

<p>Variable 
Pearson Correlation Coefficient (R) 
P-Value 
femoral neck 
lumbar region 
femoral neck 
lumbar region 
BMD 
0.09840 
0.14388 
0.4283 
0.2454 
Z-Score 
0.08808 
0.11281 
0.4785 
0.3634 
T-Score 
0.14163 
0.16321 
0.2529 
0.1869 </p>

<p>BMD=Bone Mineral Density </p>

<p>Journal of Dentistry, Tehran University of Medical Sciences </p>

<p>Marandi et al. </p>

<p>2010; Vol. 7, No. 2 </p>



<p>C2: The endosteal margin has semilunar de-
fects (resorption cavities) with cortical resi-
dues one to three layers thick on one or both 
sides. 
C3: The endosteal margin consists of thick 
cortical residues and is clearly porous" [13] 
(Fig 1). 
According to Devlin [14] and Karayianni [15] 
MI is the height of the mandibular inferior cor-
tex. According to Wical and Swoope [16], h is 
the distance from the lower border of the 
mandible to the lower border of the mental fo-
ramen. PMI was calculated according to Ben-
son et al's method [17] as the ratio of MI/h. 
Since the mental foramen is not a region where 
masticatory muscles are attached, it is consi-
dered as the standard region for study in most </p>

<p>of the surveys [17] (Fig 2). 
All the measurements were made in millime-
ters (0.1 mm variation) with calipers by the 
same investigator (AB). The indices were 
measured bilaterally and the mean was record-
ed for each patient. When only one foramen 
was visible, the measurements were done only 
on that side [18]. The information on age and 
BMD statuses of the patients was blinded to 
the examiner in order to eliminate information 
bias. 
Afterwards we gave the patients their radio-
graphs and referred them to Toos Bone Densi-
tometry Center for BMD testing. Written in-
formed consent was obtained from the patients 
to carry out bone densitometry as a part of the 
study on osteoporosis. BMD testing was per-</p>

<p>Fig 1. Diagram illustrating the classification of the en-
dosteal inferior cortex on panoramic radiographs. </p>

<p>C1: The endosteal margin of the cortex is even and sharp on both 
sides of the mandible. 
C2: The endosteal margin has semilunar defects (resorption cavities) 
with cortical residues one to three layers thick on one or both sides. 
C3: The endosteal margin consists of thick cortical residues and is 
clearly porous. </p>

<p>Table 2. The ability of MCI to discriminate between normal and osteopenic-osteoporotic skeletal status. </p>

<p>MCI 
Sensitivity Specificity 
Positive 
Predictive Value </p>

<p>Negative 
Predictive Value 
Accuracy </p>

<p>C 2 &amp;C 3 
Femoral neck 
79.4% 
39.3% 
57% 
65% 
60% 
Lumbar region 
73.8% 
36.0% 
66% 
45% 
60% </p>

<p>MCI=Mandibular Cortical Index, C2&amp;C3=Subgroups of MCI </p>

<p>Fig 2. Measurements on the panoramic radiograph, 
made with Wical and Swoope technique. The inferior 
edge of the mental foramen was traced. </p>

<p>1: a line parallel to the long axis of the mandible and tangential to the 
inferior border of the mandible was drawn. 
2: A line perpendicular to this tangent intersecting the inferior border 
of the mental foramen was constructed. 
B: Distance from the lower border to the inferior edge of the mental 
foramen (h). 
C: thickness of the mandibular cortex (MI). </p>

<p>Marandi </p>

<p>2010; Vo </p>

<p>formed 
brae (L 
teocore 
determi 
individu 
populati 
T-score 
young p 
[19]. A 
patients 
score&gt;-
and oste 
Calcula 
as well 
perform 
(SPSS I 
died var 
son corr 
was per </p>

<p>Fig 3. Fre </p>

<p>Table 3. T </p>

<p>≤0.29 </p>

<p>≤0.32 </p>

<p>≤0.33 </p>

<p>≤0.46 </p>

<p>PMI=Panor </p>

<p>et al. </p>

<p>ol. 7, No. 2 </p>

<p>in the femo 
2-L4), usin 
2. BMD, 
ned in each 
ual's data 
ion with th 
compares t 
population 
ccording to 
s into thre 
1.0), osteo 
eoporotic (T 
ations of me 
as correla 
med using 
Inc., IL). T 
riables was 
relation coe 
rformed to </p>

<p>equency of va </p>

<p>The ability of PM </p>

<p>PMI </p>

<p>9 
Femor 
Lumba </p>

<p>2 
Femor 
Lumba </p>

<p>3 
Femor 
Lumba </p>

<p>6 
Femor 
Lumba </p>

<p>ramic Mandibular </p>

<p>oral neck a 
ng DXA tec 
Z-score an 
h site. Z-sco 
with the s 
he similar s 
the acquired 
according 
o T-score, w 
ee subgrou 
openic (-2 
T-score≤-2.5 
eans and sta 
ations and 
SPSS 11. 
The correlat 
s established 
efficient. O 
assess a s </p>

<p>arious skeletal </p>

<p>MI to discrimin </p>

<p>Se </p>

<p>ral neck 
ar region 
ral neck 
ar region 
ral neck 
ar region 
ral neck 
ar region </p>

<p>r Index </p>

<p>and lumbar 
chnique wit 
nd T-score 
ore compar 
same age 
sex and rac 
d results wi 
to sex and 
we classifie 
ups: norma 
2.5&lt;T-score≤ 
5) [20]. 
andard devi 
differences 
5 for Win 
tion betwee 
d using the 
ne-way AN 
significant d </p>

<p>l statuses. </p>

<p>nate between no </p>

<p>ensitivity S </p>

<p>20.5% 
16.6% 
29.4% 
26.1% 
29.4% 
28.5% 
91.1% 
95.2% </p>

<p>Relatio </p>

<p>verte-
th Os-
were 
res the 
group 
ce, but 
ith the 
d race 
ed the 
al (T-
≤-1.0) </p>

<p>ations 
were 
ndows 
n stu-
Pear-
NOVA 
differ-</p>

<p>en 
sk 
sp 
ne 
ria 
os 
dic 
Ch 
us 
of 
os 
co </p>

<p>RE 
In 
51 
me 
mm 
mo 
C2 
fou 
the 
rot 
ly 
sp 
fem 
the 
wo 
in 
Th 
dif 
fie 
in </p>

<p>ormal and osteo </p>

<p>Specificity </p>

<p>91.0% 
88.0% 
78.7% 
76.0% 
66.6% 
64.0% 
9.0% 
16.0% </p>

<p>onship betwee </p>

<p>nce in mean 
keletal statu 
ecificity, p 
egative pred 
ables in dia 
teoporotic s 
chotomous 
haracteristic 
ed to determ 
f PMI and M 
teoporosis. 
onsidered sta </p>

<p>ESULTS 
this study 
.37 years 
ean for MI 
m) and 0.3 
ost common 
2 (65.7%). 
und that of 
e number of 
tic patients 
in the femo 
ectively in 
moral neck 
e patients w 
omen in the 
the lumbar 
he results sh 
fference in 
ed as having 
the femor </p>

<p>openic-osteopor </p>

<p>Positive 
Predictive V 
70% 
70% 
59% 
65% 
48% 
57% 
51% 
65% </p>

<p>en Panoramic </p>

<p>MI and PM 
ses in each 
positive pr 
dictive valu 
agnosing no 
skeletal stat 
2×2 tables 
c (ROC) c 
mine the opt 
MI index fo 
A P-value 
atistically si </p>

<p>67 women 
(SD=9.95 
and PMI w 
32 (SD=0.0 
n type of M 
According 
f the total n 
f normal, os 
were 33, 3 
oral neck an 
the lumbar 
and the lum 
were osteopo 
e femoral ne 
region wer 
howed that t 
mean BMD 
g C1 and C 
al neck (P= </p>

<p>rotic skeletal sta </p>

<p>Value </p>

<p>N 
Pred </p>

<p>c Indices and B </p>

<p>MI between 
h site. The 
redictive v 
ues of man 
ormal and o 
tuses were 
s. Receiver 
curve anal 
timal cutoff 
or the ident 
e less than 
ignificant. </p>

<p>with the m 
years) atte 
was 5.08 mm 
05), respect 
MCI in all p 
g to the T 
number of 
steopenic an 
2 and two, 
nd 25, 33 an 
vertebrae. 
mbar spine 
orotic; i.e., 2 
eck and 13.4 
re osteoporo 
there was a 
D in the pati 
C3 cortical 
=0.04), but </p>

<p>atuses. </p>

<p>Negative 
ictive Value 
53% 
39% 
52% 
38% 
48% 
35% 
50% 
67% </p>

<p>Bone Density </p>

<p>101 </p>

<p>the various 
sensitivity, 
values, and 
dibular va-
osteopenic-
tested with 
r Operating 
lyses were 
f thresholds 
tification of 
n 0.05 was </p>

<p>mean age of 
ended. The 
m (SD=0.93 
tively. The 
patients was 
T-score we 
67 patients 
nd osteopo-
respective-
nd nine, re-
Both in the 
the least of 
2.9% of the 
4% of them 
otic (Fig 3). 
a significant 
ients classi-
appearance 
t the BMD </p>

<p>Accuracy </p>

<p>55.2% 
58.2% 
53.7% 
44.7% 
47.7% 
41.7% 
50.7% 
65.6% </p>

<p>y </p>

<p>s 
, 
d 
-
-
h 
g 
e 
s 
f 
s </p>

<p>f 
e </p>

<p>e 
s 
e 
s 
-
-
-
e 
f 
e 
m </p>

<p>t 
-
e 
D </p>

<p>Journal of Dentistry, Tehran University of Medical Sciences </p>

<p>Marandi et al. </p>

<p>2010; Vol. 7, No. 2 </p>



<p>values in C1-C3 groups did not differ signifi-
cantly in the lumbar region (P=0.11). PMI as-
sessments were not significantly correlated 
with BMD. Furthermore, the results of our 
study showed no significant correlation be-
tween PMI and bone densitometry variables 
(Table 1). The area under the ROC curve (AZ) 
for MI was 0.344 (95% CI, 0.214-0.475) in the 
lumbar vertebrae and 0.388 (95% CI, 0.249-
0.526) in the femoral neck and for PMI it was 
0.410 (95% CI, 0.272-0.548) in the lumbar 
vertebrae and 0.400 (95% CI, 0.253-0.548) in 
the femoral neck. Since the acquired AZ, sen-
sitivity, and specificity were low in each cutoff 
threshold, we used several cutoff points to de-
termine the sensitivity and specificity. 
To determine the sensitivity and specificity of 
MCI and PMI indices, we changed the catego-
ries of the patients into two groups of normal 
and osteopenic-osteoporotic, who were pre-
viously classified into three subgroups of nor-
mal, osteopenic and osteoporotic, then the 
measurements were performed (Tables 2 and 
3). 
According to Table 2, we may conclude that of 
the osteopenic-osteoporotic patients, 79.4% in 
the femoral neck and 73.8% in the lumbar re-
gion had C2 or C3 cortex (sensitivity). In the 
women with normal skeletal statuses, 39.3% in 
the femoral neck and 36% the lumbar region 
had C1 cortex (specificity). 57% and 66% of 
the patients with C2 or C3 cortex had osteope-
nia or osteoporosis in the femoral neck and the 
lumbar region, respectively (positive predic-</p>

<p>tive value) and 65% and 45% of the patients 
with C1 cortex had normal skeletal statuses in 
the femoral neck and the lumbar region, re-
spectively (negative predictive value). It is 
demonstrated in Table 3 that by increasing the 
PMI, sensitivity increases and specificity de-
creases. The maximum sensitivity and the 
minimum specificity are related to PMI≤0.46 
and the highest positive predictive value is ob-
served in PMI≤0.29. The maximum negative 
predictive value and accuracy in the femoral 
neck was in PMI≤0.29 and for the L2-L4 re-
gion, this value was detected in PMI≤0.46. 
Our results showed a negative correlation be-
tween MI and age (P=0.016). There was also a 
positive correlation between MI and BMD in 
the femoral neck (P=0.021), T-score in the fe-
moral neck (P=0.006), BMD in the lumbar re-
gion (P=0.013) and T-score in the L2-L4 re-
gion (P=0.008) (Table 4). One-way ANOVA 
was performed to assess a significant differ-
ence in mean MI between the skeletal statuses 
of normal, osteopenic and osteoporotic in the 
femoral neck and the lumbar region. A signifi-
cant difference was shown by Tukey test be-
tween normal and osteopenic subgroups 
(P=0.042) (Table 5). According to Table 5 
there was a significant difference in mean MI 
between various skeletal statuses of the femor-
al neck (P=0.046). As it is shown in Table 5, 
there was a significant difference in mean MI 
between various skeletal statuses of the lumbar 
region (P=0.022) and Tukey test showed a sig-
nificant difference between normal and osteo-</p>

<p>Table 4. The correlation of variables with MI in the patients. 
Variable 
Pearson Correlation Coefficient (R) 
P-Value 
Age 
-0.294 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.016 
BMI 
0.164 
0.184 
BMD in the femoral neck 
0.282 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.021 
Z-Score in the femoral neck 
0.211 
0.086 
T-Score in the femoral neck 
0.330 </p>

<p># </p>

<p>0.006 
BMD in the lumbar region 
0.304 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.013 
Z-Score in the lumbar region 
0.209 
0.089 
T-Score in the lumbar region 
0.320 </p>

<p># </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>* P&lt;0.05, 
# P&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>Marandi et al. </p>

<p>Relationship between Panoramic Indices and Bone Density </p>

<p>2010; Vol. 7, No. 2 </p>



<p>porotic (P=0.017) and also osteopenic and os-
teoporotic subgroups (P=0.050). 
In order to obtain the sensitivity and specifici-
ty of MI we used two skeletal statuses of nor-
mal and osteopenic-osteoporotic subgroups for 
the further measurements (Table 6). According 
to Table 6, only 11.7% of the osteopenic-
osteoporotic patients had MI≤3.69 mm in the 
femoral neck (sensitivity) but 100% of the pa-
tients with normal skeletal statuses had 
MI&gt;3.69 mm in the femoral neck and the lum-
bar region (specificity). In addition, 100% of 
the patients with MI≤3.69 mm were osteopen-
ic-osteoporotic in the femoral neck (positive 
predictive value) and 52% of the patients with 
MI&gt;3.69 mm had normal BMD in the femoral 
neck (negative predictive value). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
PMI, MCI and MI are the parameters eva-
luated in screening osteoporosis. Some of the 
investigators have reported that they could be 
used in screening osteoporosis [3,7,13,21], but 
others disagree [1,22]. In this study we did not 
observe a significant difference between mean 
PMI in the various skeletal subgroups in the 
femoral neck and the lumbar vertebrae (L2-
L4). Similarly, Watson et al [23] did not find 
any difference in the mean PMI between nor-
mal (0.38) and osteoporotic (0.37) females in 
the 54-71 years age group, which agrees with 
Drozdzowska et al [1], who performed BMD 
measurements of the hip using DXA tech-
nique. Our study reveals that PMI in women is 
not significantly correlated with bone density 
in the femoral neck and the lumbar region. </p>

<p>Similar results were reported by Drozdzowska 
et al [1]. Klemetti and Kolmakow [4] also re-
ported that the correlation between PMI and 
BMD of the femoral neck and spine measured 
in 355 British women were weak but signifi-
cant (r=0.20-0.24, P=0.001), contrary to Tagu-
chi et al [24]. One of the most commonly stu-
died parameters of the mandibular bone in re-
lation to osteoporosis is the porosity of mandi-
bular cortical bone (MCI). Some of the inves-
tigators have found an association between 
MCI and osteoporosis [4,16,25-26]. Dalili et al 
[27] reported the MCI frequency of 20.9%, 
71.3%, and 7.8% of C1, C2, and C3 cortices, 
respectively. In the present survey, these val-
ues were 29.9%, 65.7% and 4.4%, respective-
ly. The minor difference in the data between 
these two studies is due to the different age 
group of the women, number of the patients 
and also the variation in nutrition. 
The ability of mandible variables (MCI, PMI) 
to discriminate between normal and osteopen-
ic-osteoporotic subgroups was poor to mod-
erate. The specificity, sensitivity, positive pre-
dictive value, and negative predictive value in 
PMI≤0.33 in the femoral neck were 66.6%, 
29.4%, 48%, and 48%, respectively and in the 
lumbar vertebrae were 64%, 28.5%, 57%, and 
35%, respectively. In comparison with Drozd-
zowska et al's study [1], all the indices, espe-
cially the specificity were lower. If the cutoff 
threshold increases from 0.33 to 0.46, the sen-
sitivity increases noticeably (91.1% in the fe-
moral neck and 95.2% in the lumbar region). 
Drozdzowska et al [1] reported a 31% speci-
ficity, 93% sensitivity, 54% positive predictive </p>

<p>Table 5. Mean MI of various skeletal statuses in the femoral neck and the lumbar region </p>

<p>Skeletal 
Statuses </p>

<p>n 
Mean MI 
S.D 
95% CI 
Femoral 
neck </p>

<p>Lumbar 
region </p>

<p>Femoral 
neck </p>

<p>Lumbar 
region </p>

<p>Femoral 
neck </p>

<p>Lumbar 
region </p>

<p>Femoral 
neck </p>

<p>Lumbar 
region 
Normal 
33 
25 
5.37 
5.30 
0.95 
0.81 
(5.03-5.71) (4.96-5.63) 
Osteopenic 
32 
33 
4.8 
5.13 
0.86 
1.00 
(4.51-5.12 ) (4.77-5.48) 
Osteoporosis 
2 
9 
4.72 
4.32 
0.17 
0.61 
(3.13-6.31) (3.85-4.79) 
Total 
67 
67 
5.08 
5.08 
0.93 
0.93 
(4.85-5.31) (4.85-5.31) </p>

<p>MI=Mental Index, SD=Standard Deviation, CI=Confidence Interval </p>

<p>Journal of Dentistry, Tehran University of Medical Sciences </p>

<p>Marandi et al. </p>

<p>2010; Vol. 7, No. 2 </p>



<p>value and a 83% negative predictive value for 
MCI in the hip, but in our study these values 
amounted to 39.3%, 79.4%, 57% and 65%, 
respectively in the femoral neck and 36% 
73.8%, 66% and 45%, respectively in the lum-
bar region. The difference may be due to racial 
difference and number of cases. 
The current study indicates a significant dif-
ference in MI between normal and osteopenic 
subgroups in the femoral neck (P=0.042). Al-
so, in the lumbar region, normal and osteopo-
rotic (P=0.017) and osteopenic and osteoporot-
ic subgroups (P=0.050) showed significant dif-
ferences. However, Drozdzowska et al [1]  noted that there was a significant difference in 
MI between various skeletal statuses (4.5 mm, 
5.1 mm, 3.5 mm and P&lt;0.05). 
Bollen et al [18] reported that in patients with 
osteoporotic fractures, thickness of the mandi-
bular inferior cortex was 0.54 mm thinner than 
the control group, but Mohajery and Brooks 
[22] found no significant difference in MI be-
tween osteoporotic and normal post-
menopausal women; it should be considered 
that they used the cortical thickness in the 
mandibular angle instead of MI. We found a 
negative correlation between MI and age 
(P=0.016, r=-0.294), which is concordant with 
that of Ledgerton et al's study [9]. Arifin et al 
[28] used a digital system for MI measurement 
and noted that MI and BMD had significant 
correlation in the lumbar region and the fe-
moral neck (r=0.50, r=0.54, P&lt;0.001 and </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001, respectively). This agrees with the 
significant correlation which we found 
(r=0.30, r=0.28, P=0.013 and P=0.021, respec-
tively) but the lower correlation of our results 
may be due to the digital system, used in Ari-
fin et al [28] study and it's higher accuracy in 
measurements. 
The ability of MI to discriminate between 
normal and osteopenic-osteoporotic groups 
was poor to moderate. Drozdzowska et al [1]  reported the specificity, sensitivity, positive 
predictive and negative predictive value of 
81%, 21%, 50%, and 54% for MI≤4 mm in the 
hip. According to Table 6, these values for 
MI≤4 mm in the femoral neck were 94%, 
14.7%, 71% and 52%, respectively and 96%, 
14.2%, 86% and 40%, respectively in the lum-
bar region. Taguchi et al [29] also determined 
the specificity, sensitivity, positive predictive 
and negative predictive values of 42.1%, 
79.4%, 71%, and 53.3% in the lumbar verte-
brae, respectively for MI≤4.5 mm, which were 
84%, 26.2%, 73.3%, and 40% in the lumbar 
spine in our study. Since on time diagnosis of 
osteopenic-osteoporotic patients may prevent 
side effects of the disease, in comparison with 
high specificity, high sensitivity is more use-
ful. Compared with MI≤4.5 mm, increasing 
the mandibular cortical thickness by 0.5 mm 
(MI=5 mm), the sensitivity increases to 64.7% 
in the femoral neck and 64.2% in the L2-L4 
region, which has more considerable sensitivi-
ty than MI≤4.5 mm. </p>

<p>Table 6. Ability of MI to discriminate between normal and osteopenic-osteoporotic skeletal statuses with 95% CI. </p>

<p>MI (mm) 
Sensitivity 
Specificity 
Positive 
Predictive Value </p>

<p>Negative 
Predictive Value </p>

<p>≤3.69 
Femoral neck 
11.7 (0.9-22.5) 
100.0 
100.0 
52.0 (35.2-68.8) 
Lumbar region 
9.5 (0.6-18.3) 
100.0 
100.0 
40.0 (25.1-54.8) </p>

<p>≤4.00 
Femoral neck 
14.7(2.7-26.6) 
94.0 (86.0-100.0) 
71.0 (55.7-86.2) 
52.0 (35.2-68.8) 
Lumbar region 
14.2 (3.6-24.7) 
96.0 (90.0-100.0) 
86.0 (75.5-96.4) 
40.0 (25.1-54.8) </p>

<p>≤4.50 
Femoral neck 
29.4 (14.0-44.7) 
84.8 (72.7-96.8) 
66.6 (50.7-82.4) 
53.8 (37.0-70.5) 
Lumbar region 
26.2 (12.9-39.4) 
84.0 (72.9-95) 
73.3 (59.9-86.6) 
40.0 (25.1-54.8) </p>

<p>≤5.00 
Femoral neck 
64.7 (48.6-80.7) 
51.5 (34.7-68.3) 
58.0 (41.4-74.5) 
59.0 (42.4-75.5) 
Lumbar region 
64.2 (49.7-78.7) 
56.0 (41.0-71.0) 
71.0 (57.2-84.7) 
48.0 (32.9-63.1) </p>

<p>MI=Mental Index, CI=Confidence Interval </p>

<p>Marandi et al. </p>

<p>Relationship between Panoramic Indices and Bone Density </p>

<p>2010; Vol. 7, No. 2 </p>



<p>CONCLUSION 
Contrary to PMI, which needs recording of 
some measurements on panoramic radiographs 
and also some calculations, MCI is a simple 
three-graded classification of the changes in 
the cortex with higher sensitivity in detecting 
osteopenic and osteoporotic patients. In addi-
tion, according to the simplicity of using the 
MI index, these two indices privileged PMI to 
discriminate the skeletal status of the patients, 
which of course are not adequate for precise 
evaluation. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS 
This study was supported by the vice chancel-
lor for research of Mashhad University of 
Medical Sciences, Dr. Jalil Tavakol Afshari, as 
grant No. 83082 and the authors are very 
thankful. </p>



<p>Journal of Dentistry, Tehran University of Medical Sciences </p>

<p>Marandi et al. </p>

<p>2010; Vol. 7, No. 2 </p>





</text></tei>