<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3419515" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Citation Raghavan R, Sloan DB, Ochman H. 2012. Antisense transcription is pervasive but rarely conserved in enteric bacteria. mBio 3(4):e00156-12. associated with these transcripts show no evidence of purifying 
selection. The lack of evolutionary conservation between these 
two closely related enteric bacteria, combined with comparisons 
of strains within species, supports the view that many or even most 
of the asRNAs detected by deep-sequencing techniques are non-
functional transcripts originating from spurious promoter-like 
sequences that arise nonadaptively throughout the genome. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Pervasive antisense transcription in E. coli and Salmonella. We 
obtained approximately 30 million 35-nucleotide (nt) strand-
specific sequencing reads each from exponential-phase E. coli and 
Salmonella Typhimurium grown in LB medium, with approxi-
mately 90% of the reads mapping to the respective genomes (Ta-
ble 1). The read coverages for the two genomes are nearly identi-
cal, with 2% of the reads mapping to the antisense strands of 
protein-coding genes. After applying empirically derived cutoffs 
to recognize expressed sequences from both genomes (see Mate-
rials and Methods), we detected sense and antisense transcripts 
from 75% and 28% of protein-coding genes, including tran-
scripts from 14 of 17 previously annotated asRNAs in E. coli (see 
Table S1 in the supplemental material). 
Detection of transcription start sites and quantification of 
expression levels. The strand-specific coverage at each genomic 
position was visualized and manually inspected using the Artemis 
software tool (17). As observed in previous deep-sequencing stud-
ies (18-21), sequencing reads accumulated with a pronounced 
peak at the 5= end of each gene (Fig. 1). Although this bias pre-
cludes characterizing the read coverage across the whole tran-
script, it allows the relatively precise identification of transcription 
start sites (TSSs) based on the 5= end of mapped reads (Fig. 1). For 
a sample of 50 highly expressed protein-coding genes, 80% of the 
TSSs identified with RNA-seq data were within 2 bp of experimen-
tally determined positions (22) (see Table S2 in the supplemental 
material). 
To verify the relationship between mapping coverage and gene 
expression, we used a quantitative PCR (qPCR) assay with a set of 
4 mRNAs and 18 asRNAs whose maximum read depths spanned 
several orders of magnitude. We found that maximum read depth 
was an accurate measure of expression level as estimated by qPCR 
for both mRNAs (r 0.920; P 0.05) and asRNAs (r 0.814; P 
0.001; see Fig. S1 in the supplemental material). 
Highly expressed asRNAs from E. coli and Salmonella. To 
compare the most highly expressed asRNAs in E. coli and Salmo-
nella, we identified antisense TSSs within annotated protein-</p>

<p>coding genes with a maximum read depth of at least 200. We 
excluded antisense TSSs within prophage genes and those that 
were located at the extreme 5= end of a protein-coding gene and 
likely represented the TSSs for a divergently transcribed gene on 
the opposite strand. Based on these criteria, we identified 90 
asRNAs in E. coli and 91 in Salmonella. These corresponded to a 
total of 173 distinct genes, 120 of which have orthologs in both 
species (see Tables S3 and S4 in the supplemental material). 
asRNAs are enriched for 70 promoters. Consistent with pre-
vious findings (9), the antisense TSSs that we identified by deep 
sequencing were frequently associated with canonical promoter 
elements on the antisense strand, further validating the use of 
RNA-seq to identify TSSs and indicating that most of the identi-
fied asRNAs are expressed under the control of the 70 transcrip-
tion factor. In both E. coli and Salmonella, 70% of the antisense 
TSSs had an identifiable 10 promoter element (Fig. 2) (23). This 
represents a highly significant enrichment (P 0.001), since only 
15% of randomly chosen antisense positions have a 10 se-
quence that met these criteria (Fig. 2). In contrast, similar analyses 
for 28 , 32 , or 54 promoters did not yield significant enrich-
ments upstream of antisense TSSs in either species. 
Most asRNAs are not shared between species. Among the 120 
orthologous gene pairs with a highly expressed asRNA in either 
E. coli or Salmonella, only 8 (6.7%) showed high antisense expres-
sion in both species, and only 3 (2.5%) shared an identical anti-
sense TSS position. Applying relaxed criteria that included any 
asRNA with a maximum read depth of at least 20 and an antisense 
TSS within 10 bp, we found that only 17 (14.2%) of the 120 gene 
pairs shared antisense expression at homologous positions in 
E. coli and Salmonella (Table 2). 
For asRNAs that were expressed in one species but not detected 
in the orthologous gene in the other species, the species lacking the 
asRNA was less likely to have an antisense 10 promoter element. 
In such cases, only 26.9% of the homologous positions in E. coli 
and 31.5% in Salmonella had an identifiable 10 promoter ele-
ment. Although these values are greatly reduced relative to the 
frequencies of 70% observed for expressed asRNAs, they still 
significantly exceed the expectation based on randomly chosen </p>

<p>TABLE 1 Sequencing reads mapped to E. coli and Salmonella genomes </p>

<p>Characteristic </p>

<p>Value for genome </p>

<p>E. coli 
Salmonella a </p>

<p>Total no. of reads 
30,206,434 
29,275,111 
Total mapped reads (%) 
88 
87 
Protein-coding genes (%) 
Sense 
30 
27 
Antisense 
2 
2 
Intergenic regions (%) 
54 
55 
Plasmid (%) 
No plasmid 
0.4 </p>

<p>a Of 5,313 putative ORFs in the Salmonella Typhimurium 14028S genome, only 4,477 
with orthologs in Salmonella Typhimurium LT2 and/or in E. coli MG1655 were 
considered. </p>

<p>FIG 1 Location of an asRNA within the holE coding region of E. coli. Tran-</p>

<p>scripts identified by RNA-seq mapped onto the E. coli genome: reads corre-
sponding to holE mRNA transcripts are in red, and reads corresponding to the 
antisense transcript are in green. Locations of TSSs and the direction of tran-
scription are shown. Numbering is according to the E. coli MG1655 genome 
(NC_000913.2). </p>

<p>Raghavan et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
July/August 2012 Volume 3 Issue 4 e00156-12 </p>

<p>antisense positions (P 0.05) (Fig. 2). As expected, promoter 
elements were much less likely to be shared between E. coli and 
Salmonella if antisense expression was detected in only one of the </p>

<p>species (37%) than if it was detected in both (90%) (P 0.002, 
Fisher's exact test). 
Lack of purifying selection on antisense promoters. Patterns 
of DNA sequence divergence provide an effective tool for identi-
fying sequences of functional importance. Such sequences typi-
cally experience purifying selection, meaning that most new mu-
tations are deleterious and are therefore eliminated from the 
population. As a result, functional sequences show lower rates of 
sequence evolution than their nonfunctional counterparts. Pro-
moters are necessary for the precise control of gene expression, 
and their sequences are typically under purifying selection and 
enriched in the regulatory regions of bacterial genomes (23-25). 
Accordingly, we found that the promoter regions for mRNAs ex-
hibited reduced nucleotide divergence between E. coli and Salmo-
nella relative to third codon position sites within protein-coding 
sequences. In particular, mRNA promoters exhibited pronounced 
reductions in divergence around the 35 and 10 elements, im-
portant functional regions that are involved in factor binding 
(Fig. 3A). 
In contrast to the functional constraint acting on promoter 
regions of mRNAs, there was no evidence of purifying selection on 
antisense promoter regions in E. coli and Salmonella. This is con-
sistent with the observed differences between these species in an-
tisense expression patterns and in the presence/absence of anti-
sense promoter elements. The levels of sequence divergence in 
antisense promoter regions were indistinguishable from back-
ground levels in the surrounding gene, and unlike the situation for 
mRNA promoters, there was no indication of specific reductions 
in the rate of sequence evolution around the 10 and 35 posi-
tions (Fig. 3A). 
Repeating this analysis with E. coli and its congener Esche-
richia fergusonii yielded similar results, indicating that even on a 
more recent evolutionary time scale, there is no evidence of selec-
tion on antisense promoter regions (Fig. 3B). Furthermore, we 
found a similar pattern at the intraspecific level by analyzing 41 
completely sequenced E. coli genomes, revealing a reduced fre-
quency of polymorphic sites in promoter regions (particularly </p>

<p>FIG 2 Enrichment of promoter elements associated with antisense RNAs. </p>

<p>Distributions show null expectations for the percentage of randomly selected 
antisense sites associated with a 10 promoter element in the E. coli (black/ 
right) and Salmonella (gray/left) genomes. For each genome, arrows indicate 
the percentage of identified antisense TSSs associated with 10 promoter 
elements. </p>

<p>TABLE 2 Genes with asRNAs conserved on their noncoding strands in E. coli and Salmonella </p>

<p>Gene 
Product </p>

<p>asRNA expression a </p>

<p>Distance between TSS positions (bp) 
E. coli 
Salmonella </p>

<p>acrR 
DNA-binding transcriptional repressor 
495 
819 
0 
asd 
Aspartate-semialdehyde dehydrogenase, NAD(P) binding 
1,062 
57 
0 
erfK 
L,D-Transpeptidase linking Lpp to murein 
176 
680 
1 
gloB 
Hydroxyacylglutathione hydrolase 
110 
1,079 
1 
ispB 
Octaprenyl diphosphate synthase 
30 
637 
1 
mdtL (yidY) 
Multidrug efflux system protein 
447 
143 
0 
metB 
Cystathionine gamma-synthase, PLP dependent 
502 
40 
0 
mltC 
Membrane-bound lytic murein transglycosylase C 
178 
657 
0 
napA 
Nitrate reductase, periplasmic, large subunit 
419 
209 
10 
nudF 
ADP-ribose pyrophosphatase 
171 
346 
0 
pflB 
Pyruvate formate lyase I 
79 
214 
0 
treR 
DNA-binding transcriptional repressor 
321 
28 
0 
ybhA 
Pyridoxal phosphate (PLP) phosphatase 
270 
29 
0 
ycdX 
Predicted zinc-binding hydrolase 
204 
3,500 
10 
yhbE 
Predicted inner membrane permease 
90 
243 
1 
yjjX 
Inosine/xanthosine triphosphatase 
1,113 
419 
0 
ytfP 
Conserved protein, UPF0131 family 
432 
550 
0 </p>

<p>a Maximum depth of mapped reads near asRNA TSS. </p>

<p>Antisense RNAs in Enteric Bacteria </p>

<p>July/August 2012 Volume 3 Issue 4 e00156-12 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 3 </p>

<p>around the 35 and 10 positions) for mRNAs but not for 
asRNAs (Fig. 3C). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We detected widespread antisense transcription and strikingly 
similar numbers of asRNAs in E. coli and Salmonella but found 
that most individual asRNAs are not shared between these two 
closely related enteric bacteria. The lack of conservation in 
asRNAs between these species might be taken to indicate that 
asRNAs function largely in a species-specific manner; however, we 
found no evidence of conservation or functional constraint acting 
within the genus Escherichia or even among different strains of 
E. coli (Fig. 3). Therefore, we suggest the alternative interpretation 
that a large fraction of antisense expression in bacterial genomes is 
nonfunctional. 
Promoter-like sequences are expected to arise spontaneously 
by point mutations over short evolutionary time scales in bacterial 
genomes because of the low information content in 70 transcrip-
tion factor binding sites (16, 26). The underrepresentation of 
transcription factor binding motifs in bacterial genomes indicates 
that selection acts to purge spurious promoters (23, 24, 27). How-
ever, Hahn et al. (27) found that the average intensity of selection 
against such elements is weak, falling well within the range of 
"nearly neutral" mutations, where the effects of genetic drift begin 
to overwhelm the strength of selection (28, 29). Consequently, 
many spurious promoter-like sequences are expected to persist 
within populations and even reach fixation based purely on non-
adaptive mechanisms of mutation and drift. 
In the context of these observations, the lack of conservation in 
highly expressed bacterial asRNAs between E. coli and Salmonella 
and within E. coli suggests that many of these transcripts are the 
products of transcriptional misfiring resulting from the degener-</p>

<p>ate nature of the binding site motifs for the housekeeping factor. 
This conclusion parallels a recent examination of the Bacillus sub-
tilis transcriptome, which also found many asRNAs to be products 
of spurious transcriptional events from evolutionarily less con-
served promoter sequences (30). 
The recent analysis of transcription in B. subtilis (30) found 
that asRNAs were highly variable across environmental condi-
tions and originated preferentially with alternative promoters. In 
contrast to the situation in B. subtilis, we found asRNA expression 
in E. coli and Salmonella to be predominantly controlled by the 
housekeeping 70 factor, consistent with expectations given our 
sampling at log-phase growing conditions. It is possible that our 
analysis captured only a fraction of potential antisense expression, 
which could account for the limited overlap observed between the 
sets of asRNAs reported in different studies of E. coli (see Table S5 
in the supplemental material). The sensitivity of spurious tran-
scription events to minor environmental differences may also ex-
plain why antisense TSS positions are weakly but significantly en-
riched in promoter-like sequences, even in species for which we 
found no expression of the corresponding asRNA. 
Even if most asRNAs do not have a clear role in cellular pro-
cesses, there are undoubtedly some individual asRNAs that serve 
some biological function. Previous studies have described func-
tional asRNAs in both E. coli and Salmonella (12-15), and a recent 
analysis of the transcriptomes of a number of Gram-positive bac-
teria suggests a role for asRNAs in genome-wide mRNA process-
ing (31). Our findings, however, make it clear that the identifica-
tion of antisense expression does not, in and of itself, confirm an 
adaptive role. The future identification of functional asRNAs 
should ideally link expression data to a combination of genetic, 
biochemical, and evolutionary data to reject the null hypothesis </p>

<p>FIG 3 Comparisons of divergence/polymorphism in asRNA and mRNA promoter sequences. Plotted are averages from a 9-bp sliding window of the </p>

<p>interspecific sequence divergence between either E. coli and Salmonella (A) or E. coli and E. fergusonii (B) or for the proportion of segregating sites within E. coli 
(C). Black arrows on y axes indicate average divergence (or polymorphism) for the entire coding sequences of ORFs containing asRNAs. Note that levels of 
sequence divergence (or polymorphism) in the asRNA promoter regions are statistically indistinguishable from the corresponding levels in the surrounding ORF 
(P 0.5 for all three data sets; paired t tests). The 10 bp flanking the 10 and 35 regions have been highlighted. Each error bar represents 1 standard error 
of the proportion. </p>

<p>Raghavan et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
July/August 2012 Volume 3 Issue 4 e00156-12 </p>

<p>that expression is a consequence of transcription from spurious 
promoters. 
The existence of pervasive, antisense transcription may be of 
general consequence to the cell: antisense transcription itself may 
be metabolically costly or interfere with the expression of the cog-
nate protein-coding gene (32), and asRNA transcripts could po-
tentially serve as raw material for the evolution of new regulatory 
elements. Noncoding RNAs and regulatory sequences have been 
found to be involved in short-term evolutionary diversification 
and adaptation to local environments in both bacteria and eu-
karyotes (33-36), suggesting that strain-specific evolution of non-
coding transcripts has the potential to supply new functions. Per-
vasive antisense expression may also affect genome contents in 
that bacterial mutations are biased towards AT (37, 38) and 
selection pressure acting to purge AT-rich promoter-like se-
quences would have a counterbalancing effect on the genomic 
base composition. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Bacterial strains, RNA preparation, library construction, and sequenc-
ing. E. coli K-12 MG1655 (GenBank accession no. NC_000913.2) and 
Salmonella enterica subsp. enterica serovar Typhimurium strain 14028S 
(GenBank accession no. CP001363.1) were grown in LB medium to log 
phase (optical density at 600 nm [OD 600 ] of ~0.5). Cells were harvested by 
centrifugation at 4°C for 5 min, and total RNA was extracted from bacte-
rial pellets using Tri reagent (ABI) and cleaned using Qiagen RNeasy 
columns. Genomic DNA was removed by DNase treatment, and 16S and 
23S rRNAs were eliminated using the MICROBExpress kit (ABI). Direc-
tional (i.e., strand-specific) RNA-seq libraries were prepared to maintain 
strand information (39) and were assayed on a Bioanalyzer 2100 system 
(Agilent) for quality. Each library was loaded onto a single lane of a flow 
cell and sequenced using the Illumina GA II platform (35 cycles) at the 
Yale Center for Genome Analysis. Raw sequencing reads have been de-
posited in the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (accession no. SRA047329.1), 
and Artemis-ready files are available on request. 
Mapping of sequencing reads and quantitative PCR. Sequencing 
reads were mapped using the software program <rs type="software">MAQ</rs> (40) onto the pub-
lished E. coli (NC_000913.2) and Salmonella Typhimurium (CP001363.1) 
genomes, allowing up to two mismatches per read. The number of reads 
mapped to each nucleotide position on each strand was obtained by pars-
ing the <rs type="software">MAQ</rs> pileup file using a custom Perl script, as previously described 
(18). The expression levels of genes were estimated by identifying the 
maximum number of reads that mapped to the sense and antisense 
strands of annotated open reading frames (ORFs). Background expres-
sion levels were calculated for 53 genes (see Table S6 in the supplemental 
material) that were not expressed in a previous microarray-based study in 
exponential-phase E. coli in LB (41). Microarray data were downloaded 
from the Oklahoma University E. coli Gene Expression Database (http: 
//genexpdb.ou.edu/main/). Read depths for these genes ranged from 0 to 
19. Based on these, we used a cutoff of 20 reads to designate an asRNA as 
expressed. 
For qPCR validation of expression levels, E. coli was grown in LB 
medium, and RNA was extracted as described above. After DNase treat-
ment, cDNA was prepared from 1 g of RNA using an iScript kit (Bio-
Rad). Four loci (cdd, ldcC, napF, and ompA) were selected for qPCR, 
which was performed using SYBR green on a LightCycler instrument 
(Roche). To assess the similarity between expression estimates from Illu-
mina sequencing and qPCR, we calculated the Pearson correlation coef-
ficient between log-transformed maximum read depth and the qPCR cy-
cle threshold (C T ), applying a one-tailed test of significance (see Fig. S1 in 
the supplemental material). 
For qPCR validation of asRNAs, three independent E. coli samples 
were grown in LB and RNA was extracted, as described above. After 
DNase treatment, cDNA was prepared from 500 ng of RNA and asRNA-</p>

<p>specific primers using a SuperScript II reverse transcriptase kit (Invitro-
gen). Reaction mixtures were incubated at 50°C for 30 min, followed by 
enzyme inactivation at 70°C for 15 min. qPCR was performed on a Mas-
tercycler instrument (Eppendorf), and the intraclass correlation among 
the replicate C T values obtained for each sample was determined using the 
irr package in the software environment R v2.8.0 (see Fig. S2). 
Identification of antisense TSSs. After RNA-seq reads were mapped 
to the respective genome, the antisense strands of all protein coding genes 
were scanned using a custom Perl script to identify regions with a read 
depth of at least 200. These genes were then manually inspected in Artemis 
to determine the positions of upshifts in coverage to identify putative TSSs 
(30) (Fig. 1). Antisense TSSs that were located at the 5= ends of three 
protein-coding genes (ybaN and STM14_1994 in Salmonella, and yneJ in 
E. coli) were excluded from further analysis because they potentially rep-
resent the TSSs of the divergently transcribed adjacent genes. 
Identification of 10 promoter elements. DNA binding of the 70 
transcription factor is mediated by a promoter region that consists of two 
short motifs positioned approximately 10 and 35 bp upstream of the TSS 
(42). The 10 element is particularly indispensable and has a core se-
quence with the 6-bp consensus TATAAT (43, 44). This motif is highly 
degenerate, however, since promoter elements often have imperfect 
matches to the consensus and can be located anywhere in a window rang-
ing from approximately 4 to 18 bp upstream of the TSS (44). Therefore, to 
identify potential 10 elements associated with antisense TSSs, we 
searched this 15-bp window for any hexamers that matched at least 4 of 
the 6 bp in the consensus sequence including the two most highly con-
served positions, A2 and T6 (23). This approach could potentially miss 
some legitimate 10 elements because many documented promoters are 
too divergent to satisfy these criteria (45). 
To produce a null expectation for the observed frequency of 10 
elements, we generated 1,000,000 sets of randomly sampled antisense po-
sitions in each genome and determined the fraction of sites in each set that 
contained a 10 element satisfying the criteria described above. 
Analysis of nucleotide sequence divergence and polymorphism. 
Patterns of nucleotide divergence and polymorphism were analyzed to 
infer whether promoter regions regulating asRNA expression are subject 
to functional constraint. To calculate levels of nucleotide sequence diver-
gence, protein-coding gene sequences containing identified antisense 
TSSs were extracted from the genome sequence of either E. coli 
(NC_000913.2) or Salmonella (CP001363.1) and aligned with ortholo-
gous sequences from the other species. Codon-based nucleotide align-
ments were generated by aligning translated amino acid sequences using 
the software program <rs id="software-4" type="software">MUSCLE</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">v3.7</rs> and then converting them back to 
nucleotide sequences (46). Divergence values were calculated using third 
codon positions only, which are largely synonymous and thus less suscep-
tible to selection acting on the sense-strand-encoded amino acid se-
quence. Alignment gaps were excluded from divergence estimates. 
Average divergence levels between E. coli and Salmonella were calcu-
lated based on the distance to the antisense TSS. To test the hypothesis that 
purifying selection acts to constrain sequence evolution in antisense pro-
moter regions, the divergence data were partitioned into two categories: 
(i) an antisense promoter region consisting of the TSS along with 50 
upstream and 10 downstream nucleotides on the antisense strand and (ii) 
the rest of the surrounding protein-coding gene. A paired t test was im-
plemented in R v2.8.0 to compare levels of nucleotide divergence between 
these two partitions. In addition, divergence data within the antisense 
promoter region were visualized using a sliding-window analysis with a 
window size of 9 bp and a step size of 1 bp. 
The above comparison between E. coli and Salmonella was repeated 
using E. coli and its more closely related congener Escherichia fergusonii 
(NC_011740.1). In addition, a similar analysis was performed using the 
number of segregating sites in multiple alignments generated from com-
plete genome sequences of 41 strains of E. coli (see Table S7 in the supple-
mental material). Note that this set of genomes included some isolates 
that are taxonomically placed in the genus Shigella based on their patho-</p>

<p>Antisense RNAs in Enteric Bacteria </p>

<p>July/August 2012 Volume 3 Issue 4 e00156-12 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 5 </p>

<p>genic properties but are phylogenetically nested within E. coli (47). Only 
genes that were present in at least 10 of the strains were included in this 
polymorphism analysis. 
To provide a basis of comparison for the patterns of nucleotide diver-
gence and polymorphism observed in antisense promoter regions, we 
identified TSSs for a set of highly expressed protein-coding mRNAs (max-
imum read depth of at least 200) in E. coli and Salmonella (67 and 55 loci, 
respectively). For this set of control loci, we extracted gene sequences 
along with associated 5= regions extending 200 bp upstream of the iden-
tified TSS from the same sets of genomes described above. Nucleotide 
alignments were performed in <rs type="software">MUSCLE</rs>, and sequence divergence and 
polymorphism values were calculated as described above, except that 
there was no filtering based on codon position for upstream noncoding 
sequences. Genes with unalignable upstream regions were excluded from 
the analysis. 
For both interspecific and intraspecific comparisons, putative or-
thologs were identified as pairs of genes that returned top hits in reciprocal 
searches between a pair of genomes with <rs corresp="#software-8" type="creator">NCBI</rs> <rs id="software-8" type="software">tBLASTn</rs> <rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-number">v2.2.24</rs> (48). All 
analyses were conducted with custom Perl scripts utilizing BioPerl mod-
ules (49). </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIAL </p>

<p>Supplemental material for this article may be found at http://mbio.asm.org 
/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1128/mBio.00156-12/-/DCSupplemental. 
Figure S1, EPS file, 1.1 MB. 
Figure S2, EPS file, 0.7 MB. 
Table S1, DOCX file, 0.1 MB. 
Table S2, DOCX file, 0.1 MB. 
Table S3, DOCX file, 0.1 MB. 
Table S4, DOCX file, 0.1 MB. 
Table S5, DOCX file, 0.1 MB. 
Table S6, DOCX file, 0.1 MB. 
Table S7, DOCX file, 0.1 MB. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Cindy Barlan for technical help and Kim Hammond for assis-
tance with figures. 
This work was supported in part by NIH grant GM74738 to 
H.O. D.B.S. was supported by an NIH Ruth Kirschstein postdoctoral fel-
lowship (1F32GM099334-01). </p>





<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
July/August 2012 Volume 3 Issue 4 e00156-12 </p>



<p>Antisense RNAs in Enteric Bacteria </p>

<p>July/August 2012 Volume 3 Issue 4 e00156-12 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 7 </p>

</text></tei>