<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3590572" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Synopsis </p>

<p>The different steps of the human Top1 (topoisomerase I) catalytic cycle have been analysed in the presence of a 
pentacyclic-diquinoid synthetic compound. The experiments indicate that it efficiently inhibits the cleavage step of 
the enzyme reaction, fitting well into the catalytic site. Surprisingly the compound, when incubated with the binary 
topoisomerase-DNA cleaved complex, helps the enzyme to remove itself from the cleaved DNA and close the DNA gap, 
increasing the religation rate. The compound also induces the religation of the stalled enzyme-CPT (camptothecin)-
DNA ternary complex. Analysis of the molecule docked over the binary complex, together with its chemical properties, 
suggests that the religation enhancement is due to the presence on the compound of two oxygen atoms that act as 
hydrogen acceptors. This property facilitates the deprotonation of the 5 DNA end, suggesting that this is the limiting 
step in the topoisomerase religation mechanism. </p>

<p>DNA topoisomerases are key enzymes that modulate the topolo-
gical state of DNA through the breaking and rejoining of DNA 
strands. There are two classes of topoisomerases (types I and 
II), both characterized by a catalytic mechanism that involves a 
nucleophilic attack of a DNA phosphodiester bond by a tyrosyl 
residue from the enzyme, but type I cleaves a single DNA strand, 
whereas type II cleaves both strands. The human Top1 (topoi-
somerase I) enzyme is composed of 765 amino acids and has 
four distinct domains: the NH 2 -terminal domain (1-214), the 
core domain (215-635), the linker domain (636-712) 
and the COOH-terminal domain (713-765) [1,2]. The three-
dimensional (3D) structure of reconstituted N-terminal truncated 
version of human Top1 in complex with a 22 bp DNA molecule </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................ </p>

<p>Abbreviations used: CPT, camptothecin; Et-KuQ, 1-ethylKuQuinone; TBS, Tris-buffered saline; Top1, topoisomerase I. 
1 To whom correspondence should be addressed (email desideri@uniroma2.it). </p>

<p>shows the enzyme organized in multiple domains, which 'clamp 
on' the DNA molecule [3]. The active site tyrosine (Tyr 
723 ) starts 
the catalytic cycle of the enzyme through a nucleophilic attack 
on the DNA backbone, resulting in the breakage of one DNA 
strand with the enzyme covalently attached to the 3 -phosphate 
to form the cleavable complex. After changing the linking num-
ber a second nucleophilic attack, driven by the 5 -hydroxyl DNA 
end, restores an intact double-stranded DNA, and the enzyme is 
released. In both cases, to become a nucleophile the hydroxylic 
group belonging to the tyrosine or to the DNA end must donate a 
proton to a nearby group that has been proposed to be the lateral 
chain of Lys 
532 [2,4]. 
DNA Top IB can be inhibited by several compounds that 
act through different mechanisms, such as prevention of DNA-
topoisomerase binding, inhibition of DNA cleavage or stabiliz-
ation of the cleavable complex. Inhibitors of Top1 are divided </p>

<p>c 2013 The Author(s). This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>269 </p>

<p>Bioscience Reports www.bioscirep.org </p>

<p>B. Arnò and others </p>

<p>into two classes: poisons and catalytic inhibitors. Poisons in-
clude clinically used drugs, such as the derivatives of the natural 
compound CPT (camptothecin) that reversibly binds the covalent 
Top1-DNA complex slowing down the religation of the cleaved 
DNA strand, thus inducing cell death [5]. Two water-soluble 
CPT derivatives, topotecan and irinotecan have been approved 
by the FDA (Food and Drug Administration) for clinical use. 
The 3D structure of the topotecan-enzyme-DNA ternary com-
plex has shown that topotecan mimics a DNA base-pair and binds 
at the site of DNA cleavage by intercalating between the upstream 
( − 1) and downstream ( + 1) base-pairs [6] interacting also with 
the enzyme, acting as an interfacial uncompetitive inhibitor [5]. 
On the other hand, catalytic inhibitors act through inhibiting any 
other step of the Top1 enzymatic cycle. They include both natural 
and non-natural compounds [7] and they mainly act by inhibiting 
the cleavage [8-10] or the DNA binding [11,12], although some 
of them are able to inhibit both cleavage and religation [13,14]. 
The CPT derivatives are widely used in clinics; however, they 
have some intrinsic limits, the main one being linked to the 
equilibrium of the α-hydroxylactone E-ring of CPTs with 
the carboxylate form, which is inactive against Top1 and tightly 
binds to serum albumin. For this reason, other drugs are under de-
velopment, the most promising one being indolocarbazoles and 
the indenoisoquinolines [5]. 
It has been shown that the ADP-ribose polymers, that is rap-
idly synthesized by PARP [poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase], ac-
tivated by the occurrence of a DNA break, is also able to interact 
with human Topo I [15]. The interaction has been elegantly shown 
to produce two important effects, the first one being the cleav-
age inhibition, the second one consisting in the enhancement of 
the religation [16]. The second effect is quite astonishing and 
poly(ADP-ribose) has been up to now the only molecule able 
to induce this effect, although the molecular mechanism is still 
unclear. 
In this work, in the search for a new topoisomerase 
poison, we have investigated the interaction of the enzyme 
with Et-KuQ (1-ethylKuQuinone) (Figure 1), a pentacyclic-
diquinoid synthetic compound [17]. The results indicate that 
Et-KuQ inhibits cleavage and enhances religation in the pres-
ence of CPT. A mechanism for such a process is provided 
and it is proposed to also occur in the case of poly(ADP-
ribose). </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Chemicals and pH titration </p>

<p>The Et-KuQ was synthesized as previously described [17]. 
CPT (Sigma) and Et-KuQ were dissolved in DMSO to a final 
concentration of 4 and 0.5 mg/ml, respectively, and stored at 
− 20 
• C. Anti-FLAG M2 monoclonal affinity gel, FLAG peptide 
and anti-FLAG M2 monoclonal antibody were purchased from 
Sigma. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Structure of KuQ 
(A) Structure and dissociation equilibrium of Et-KuQ. (B) Spectrophoto-
metric titration curve for the ionization of Et-KuQ in aqueous solution. </p>

<p>Et-KuQ acid-base titration </p>

<p>The spectrophothometric titration of a 3.5×10 
− 5 mol/l aqueous 
solution of Et-KuQ was performed with a Shimadzu UV-2450 
spectrophotometer. The various pH values were obtained by di-
luting HCl or NaOH mother solutions and measuring the desired 
pH value through a pH metre (Amel 334-B) equipped with a glass 
electrode CRISON5203. The electrode was checked with com-
mercial standard buffer solutions at pH 4.01, 7.01 and 9.26. The 
titration curve for the acid ionization was obtained by recording 
the absorption value of Et-KuQ at 384 nm as a function of pH 
(Figure 1); a corresponding sigmoid fit of the data [18] provides 
the pKa value of 5.4. </p>

<p>Yeast strains and plasmids </p>

<p>The Saccharomyces cerevisiae strain EKY3 (ura3-52, his3 200, 
leu2 1, trp1 63, top1::TRP1, MATα) previously described 
[19], was used to express the human Top1 gene. Top1 is ex-
pressed in YCpGAL1-e-Top1 single copy plasmid [19,20]. The 
epitope-tagged construct, indicated as 'e' contains the N-terminal 
sequence DYKDDDY and is recognized by the M2 monoclonal 
antibody. </p>

<p>Top1 purification </p>

<p>Top1 was expressed under the galactose inducible promoter in 
a single copy plasmid, YCpGAL1-e-Top1, used for transforma-
tion of EKY3 cells, that were grown on SC-uracil plus 2 % (w/v) </p>

<p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>



<p>c 2013 The Author(s). This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>A novel organic compound enhances human topoisomerase I religation activity </p>

<p>dextrose and diluted 1:100 in SC-uracil plus 2 % (w/v) raffinose. 
At a D 595 = 1.0, the cells were induced with 2 % (w/v) galactose 
for 6 h. Cells were then centrifuged, washed with ice-cold wa-
ter and resuspended in 2 ml buffer/g of cells [50 mM Tris/HCl, 
pH 7.4, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM EGTA, 10 % (v/v) glycerol and pro-
tease inhibitors cocktail (Roche)], supplemented with 0.1 mg/ml 
sodium bisulfate, 0.8 mg/ml sodium fluoride, 1 mM PMSF and 
1 mM DTT (dithiothreitol). After an addition of 0.5 vol of 425-
600 mm diameter glass beads, the cells were disrupted by vor-
texing for 30 s alternating with 30 s on ice and then were cent-
rifuged. The column, containing 2 ml of anti-FLAG M2 affinity 
gel, was washed with 20 column volumes of TBS (Tris-buffered 
saline; 50 mM Tris/HCl pH 7.4 and 150 mM KCl), prior to load-
ing the lysate. Elution of FLAG-fusion-e-Top1, was performed 
by competition with five column volumes of a solution contain-
ing 100 mg/ml FLAG peptide in TBS. Fractions (500 μl) were 
collected and 40 % (v/v) glycerol was added in all preparations, 
which were stored at − 20 
• C [21]. Fractions were resolved by 
SDS/PAGE using the epitope-specific monoclonal antibody M2 
protein. The protein concentration has been estimated by dens-
itometry of the chosen fraction and compared with the purified 
Top I (purchased from Topogene). Our Top1 has a concentration 
of 10 ng/μl. </p>

<p>DNA relaxation assays </p>

<p>The activity of 1 μl of Top1 was assayed in 30 μl of reac-
tion volume containing 0.5 μg of negatively supercoiled pBlue-
Script KSII( + ) DNA, that is present in both dimeric and 
monomeric forms and reaction buffer (20 mM Tris/HCl pH 7.5, 
0.1 mM Na 2 EDTA, 10 mM MgCl 2 , 50 μg/ml acetylated BSA 
and 150 mM KCl). The effect of Et-KuQ on enzyme activity was 
measured by adding different concentrations of the compound; 
the dose-dependent analysis has been performed by simultan-
eously adding Top1 and the supercoiled plasmid in the presence 
of DMSO as control, or with different concentrations of Et-KuQ 
or pre-incubating the enzyme with various concentrations of Et-
KuQ for 10 min at 37 
• C before adding the DNA; the reactions 
were stopped after 60 min. The relaxation activity of Top1, pre-
incubated with 5 μM Et-KuQ, or with the same concentration 
of DMSO, before adding the supercoiled plasmid, was also ana-
lysed as a function of time at 37 
• C. Reactions were stopped with 
0.5 % SDS and the samples were resolved in a 1 % (w/v) agarose 
gel in 48 mM Tris, 45.5 mM boric acid, 1 mM EDTA. The gel 
was stained with ethidium bromide (0.5 μg/ml), destained with 
water and photographed under UV illumination. </p>

<p>Cleavage kinetics </p>

<p>Oligonucleotide substrate CL14 (5 -GAAAAAAGACTTAG-3 ) 
was radiolabelled with [γ -
32 P]ATP at the 5 end. The CP25 com-
plementary strand (5 -TAAAAATTTTTCTAAGTCTTTTTTC-
3 ) was 5 phosphorylated with unlabelled ATP. The two strands 
were annealed at 2-fold molar excess of CP25 over CL14, cre-
ating the partial duplex suicide substrate. The cleavage reactions 
were carried out in 20 mM Tris/HCl pH 7.5, 0.1 mM Na 2 EDTA, </p>

<p>10 mM MgCl 2 , 50 μg/ml acetylated BSA and 150 mM KCl at 
25 
• C, by incubating 20 nM CL14/CP25 and an excess of Top1 
with DMSO, as no-drug control, or 50 μM Et-KuQ, or pre-
incubating the enzyme and the compound for 10 min before 
adding the suicide substrate [22]. At various time points 5 μl 
aliquots were removed and the reaction stopped with 0.5 % (w/v) 
SDS. After ethanol precipitation samples were resuspended in 
5 μl of 1 mg/ml trypsin to degrade the protein and were ana-
lysed by denaturing 7 M urea/20 % (w/v) PAGE in 48 mM Tris, 
45.5 mM boric acid, 1 mM EDTA. However, a short trypsin-
resistant peptide is always left, explaining why the Cl1 migrates 
slower than the Cl14 oligonucleotide [23]. The percentage of 
cleavage, determined by PhosphorImager and <rs type="software">ImageQuant</rs> soft-
ware, was calculated in each lane as the ratio between the amount 
of cleavage product and the total amount of radioactivity. The 
percentage of cleavage product, corresponding to the plateau ob-
served for the experiment carried out with the substrate and the 
enzyme alone, was then considered as 100 % of cleavage product 
and all the other measurements were normalized to this value. </p>

<p>Religation kinetics </p>

<p>CL14/CP25 (20 nM) was incubated with an excess of Top1 for 
60 min at 25 
• C followed by 30 min at 37 
• C in 20 mM Tris/HCl 
pH 7.5, 0.1 mM Na 2 EDTA, 10 mM MgCl 2 , 50 μg/ml acetylated 
BSA and 150 mM KCl. After the formation of the cleavable 
complex (Cl1) a 5-μl aliquot was removed and used as the 
time 0 point, then DMSO or 50 μM Et-KuQ were added and 
the religation reaction was started by adding a 200-fold molar 
excess of R11 oligonucleotide (5 -AGAAAAATTTT-3 ) over 
the CL14/CP25 [21]. The KCl concentration was increased to 
350 mM when R11 was added, to avoid the religated product be-
ing recleaved by the protein [24]. Where indicated, the compound 
was pre-incubated with the cleavable complex for 10 min at 37 
• C, 
before adding the R11 oligonucleotide. At 37 
• C 5 μl aliquots 
were removed at various time points, and the reaction stopped 
with 0.5 % (w/v) SDS. After ethanol precipitation, samples were 
resuspended in 5 μl of 1 mg/ml trypsin and incubated at 37 
• C 
for 60 min. Samples were analysed by denaturing 7 M urea/20 % 
(w/v) PAGE in 48 mM Tris, 45.5 mM boric acid, 1 mM EDTA. 
The religation percentage, determined by <rs type="software">ImageQuant</rs> software, 
was plotted as a function of time and normalized to the plateau 
value. </p>

<p>Cleavage/religation equilibrium </p>

<p>Oligonucleotide CL25 (5 -GAAAAAAGACTTAGAAAAAT-
TTTTA-3 ) was 5 radiolabelled with [γ -
32 P]ATP. The CP25 com-
plementary strand (5 -TAAAAATTTTTCTAAGTCTTTTTTC-
3 ) was phosphorylated at its 5 end with unlabelled ATP. 
The two strands were annealed at a 2-fold molar excess of 
CP25 over CL25. The assay was done by adding 20 nM 
duplex CL25/CP25 to Top1 alone (DMSO), in the pres-
ence of 50 μM CPT, in the presence of 50 μM Et-KuQ or 
after incubating the reaction mixture with 50 μM CPT for 
1 min and then adding 50 μM Et-KuQ, or incubating with </p>

<p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>

<p>c 2013 The Author(s). This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>



<p>B. Arnò and others </p>

<p>50 μM Et-KuQ for 1 min and then adding 50 μM CPT. Re-
actions were performed at 25 
• C in 20 mM Tris/HCl pH 7.5, 
0.1 mM Na 2 EDTA, 10 mM MgCl 2 , 50 mg/ml acetylated 
BSA and 150 mM KCl and were stopped at two different times: 
1 and 2 min, by adding 0.5 % (w/v) SDS, precipitating with eth-
anol and digesting with trypsin [25]. Products were resolved in 
20 % (w/v) PAGE/7 M urea gel and quantified using <rs type="software">ImageQuant</rs> 
software. The values were calculated by the ratio between the 
cleavage amount and the total radioactivity of each lane, sub-
tracting the control background. </p>

<p>Molecular docking </p>

<p>The deprotonated Et-KuQ molecular geometry in the gas phase 
was obtained at the B3LYP/6-31 + G(d,p) level of theory us-
ing GAMESS-US-2011 ed. [26]. The molecular geometry of the 
Top1 non-covalent binary complex was obtained by modelling 
the 1A36 PDB entry; after removing the DNA, the same structure 
was used to obtain a model of the Top1 enzyme in the absence 
of DNA. The 1T8I PDB entry was used to obtain a model for 
the ternary complex. The <rs id="software-6" type="software">MGLTools</rs> <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">1.5.6 rc1</rs> was used to con-
vert the PDB into PDBQT format, to calculate the Gasteiger-
Marsilii charges and produce the input file. Grid was calcu-
lated using an in-house modified version of <rs id="software-7" type="software">AutoGrid</rs> <rs corresp="#software-7" type="version-number">4.2.2.1</rs> 
using a 256×256×256 grid with step of 0.5Å (1Å = 0.1 nm) 
enclosing the whole Top1. 250 runs of docking were gener-
ated using the standard GA algorithm with <rs id="software-8" type="software">AutoDock</rs> <rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-number">4.2.2.1</rs> 
[27] for Et-KuQ on each of the three systems. The complexes 
were clusterized on the basis of their RMSD (root-mean-square 
deviation), using a cut-off value of 2Å. Figures 6-8 were 
generated with <rs corresp="#software-9" type="creator">ucsf</rs> <rs id="software-9" type="software">Chimera</rs> <rs corresp="#software-9" type="version-number">1.9</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-9" type="url">http://www.cgl.ucsf.edu/chimera</rs>). </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Et-KuQ physical-chemical properties </p>

<p>KuQuinones are a new class of pentacyclic di-quinoid compounds 
that have recently been discovered and synthesized with a facile 
one-pot reaction [17]. The polycyclic system can be considered 
a naphthoquinone derivative and its name is due to the structural 
similarities with vitamin K. In this work the Et-KuQ has been re-
acted with the human Top1 enzyme. The main feature of its struc-
ture is the presence of a pentacyclic skeleton (similarly to CPT) 
with a double-quinone functional group; the five rings consist of 
two naphthalene units fused through a 5-membered moiety that 
contains an alkyl chain (Figure 1A). Extended electronic conjug-
ation is proved by the intense absorption spectrum with a broad 
band between 400 and 600 nm. These molecules were isolated as 
enol tautomers stabilized by the intramolecular hydrogen bond 
with the nearest carbonyl group, as shown in the crystal structure 
of the Et-KuQ derivative [17]. The strong hydrogen-bond inter-
action is evidenced by the very high value of the chemical shift 
(18 ppm) of the enolic hydrogen in the 
1 H NMR spectrum. On </p>

<p>the other hand, the shift of the relative tautomeric equilibrium to-
wards the keto form appears to be strongly sensitive to solvent po-
larity and hydrogen-bonding capacity. Therefore it can be reason-
ably assumed that the keto tautomer is favoured in aqueous media; 
a complete characterization of the equilibrium is under current 
investigation. 
The pH dependence of the spectrum permits us to evaluate a 
pK a of 5-6 for the equilibrium between a protonated and a depro-
tonated form (Figure 1B). The unusual acidity of the compound 
compares well with that reported for the hipposudoric acid [28], 
a natural structurally related compound. In fact, the conjugate 
base of Et-KuQ, i.e. the enolate species, is particularly stable 
because of the stabilization of the negative charge within the 
molecule. </p>

<p>Et-KuQ inhibits the relaxation activity of Top1 </p>

<p>The relaxation activity of native Top1 has been assessed by in-
cubating the enzyme in the presence of increasing concentration 
of Et-KuQ in a plasmid relaxation assay (Figure 2A). The sim-
ultaneous addition of enzyme, Et-KuQ and DNA never resulted 
in complete inhibition of the plasmid relaxation activity up to a 
concentration of 100 μM. The inhibitory effect is greater when 
the enzyme is pre-incubated with Et-KuQ before adding DNA 
and the compound fully inhibits the relaxation at a concentration 
of 12.5 μM (Figure 2A, lane 14). An additional control has been 
performed (C2 Figure 2A, lane 20) by adding the drug to the 
DNA plasmid, demonstrating that the Et-KuQ does not permit 
DNA migration and so does not bind to DNA. The relaxation as-
say carried out as function of time at an Et-KuQ concentration of 
5 μM indicated that the inhibitory effect is abolished after 15 min 
(Figure 2B, lane 16), demonstrating that the binding of the com-
pound is reversible. Since Et-KuQ is dissolved in DMSO, as a 
control, the reaction in presence of this solvent has been carried 
out and it shows that the enzyme, at the same DMSO concentra-
tion, maintains its activity over time (Figure 2B, lanes 1-9). </p>

<p>Cleavage and religation analysis </p>

<p>The time course of the cleavage of the wild-type enzyme in 
the presence and absence of Et-KuQ has been followed us-
ing a suicide cleavage substrate. In detail, a 5 end radiola-
belled oligonucleotide CL14 (5 -GAAAAAAGACTTAG-3 ) was 
annealed to the CP25 (5 -TAAAAATTTTTCTAAGTCTTTT-
TTC-3 ) complementary strand, to produce a duplex with an 
11-base 5 single-strand extension that is preferentially cut by the 
enzyme at the site indicated by the arrow (Figure 3A, top). The 
religation step is precluded, because the dinucleotide, generated 
during cleavage, is too short to be religated, leaving the enzyme 
covalently attached to the 3 end of the oligonucleotide. The data 
indicate that in the absence of the drug the wild-type protein 
shows a typical time-dependent cleavage of the fragment (Fig-
ure 3A, lanes 2-7), whereas pre-incubation of the enzyme with 
50 μM Et-KuQ fully inhibits the cleavage reaction (lanes 8-13). 
The inhibitory effect of the compound, after a simultaneous in-
cubation with both the enzyme and the suicide substrate, is also 
clear (lanes 14-19), although lower than that observed for the </p>

<p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>



<p>c 2013 The Author(s). This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>A novel organic compound enhances human topoisomerase I religation activity </p>

<p>Figure 2 
Relaxation of supercoiled DNA 
(A) Relaxation of negative supercoiled plasmid by Top1 incubated with increasing concentrations of Et-KuQ (lanes 2-9) or 
after pre-incubation for 10 min at 37 
• C with increasing concentrations of Et-KuQ (lanes 11-18). Lanes 1 and 10, no drug 
added; lane 19, no drug and protein added, lane 20, no protein added. (B) Relaxation of negative supercoiled plasmid 
in a time course experiment for DMSO (lanes 1-9), 5 μM Et-KuQ (lanes 10-18); lane 19, no protein added. The reaction 
products are resolved in an agarose gel and visualized with ethidium bromide. The two forms of the supercoiled plasmid 
DNA are indicated as 'Dimer' and 'Monomer'. </p>

<p>pre-incubation. These results can be well appreciated from the 
plot in Figure 3(B) where the percentage of cleavage is reported 
as a function of time. In detail in the absence of the drug (black 
line) the maximum of the cleaved product is observed after 4 min, 
while in the presence of the drug preincubated with enzyme (grey 
line with circles), no cleaved product is observed in the first 4 min 
and a small percentage is observed in the 8-15 min time window. 
This result unambiguously indicates that Et-KuQ is an inhibitor 
of cleavage and that its interaction with the enzyme is reversible 
due to the appearance of a small percentage of cleaved product 
at long times. 
In order to analyse the effect of Et-KuQ on the religation reac-
tion, Top1 was incubated with the suicide substrate, to allow the 
cleavage reaction (Figure 4A, lane 1). The religation is then fol-
lowed in the absence of the compound (Figure 4A, lanes 2-7), or 
by pre-incubating the cleavable suicide complex with 50 μM Et-
KuQ before adding 200-fold molar excess of the complementary 
R11 oligonucoleotide (Figure 4A, lanes 8-13) or adding Et-KuQ 
together with the religation substrate (Figure 4A, lanes 14-19). 
In all the experiments, the KCl concentration is maintained at 
350 mM when R11 is added to the samples, in order to avoid the 
religated product being cleaved again by the protein, since cleav-
age reaction is inhibited at high salt concentration [24]. Aliquots 
have been removed at different times, the reaction stopped by ad-
dition of SDS and the products analysed by PAGE (Figure 4A). 
The Figure clearly shows that Et-KuQ, when preincubated for 
10 min with the covalent complex, stimulates the rate of religation 
(lanes 8-13), the amount of product formed being much higher </p>

<p>than in the reaction carried out in the absence of Et-KuQ, or 
without preincubating it with the covalent complex. A quantitat-
ive analysis of this result is shown in the graph in Figure 4(B). This 
is to our knowledge the first time that a small organic compound 
acts as a stimulator of the Top1 religation reaction. The same 
experiment, performed using an excess of Et-KuQ (200 μM), 
shows that, at this high Et-KuQ concentration, an increase of the 
rate of religation is observed also when the compound is added 
together with the R11 substrate (see Supplementary Figure S1 at 
http://www.bioscirep.org/bsr/033/bsr033e025add.htm). </p>

<p>Cleavage/religation equilibrium assay </p>

<p>To understand the effect of Et-KuQ on the stability of the co-
valent DNA-Top1 complex, a cleavage/religation equilibrium 
experiment on the 25-mer full duplex oligonucleotide has also 
been performed (Figure 5A). The assay was done at two different 
times: 1 and 2 min, respectively, for the substrate and the enzyme 
alone (lanes 1 and 2), in the presence of 50 μM CPT (lanes 3 and 
4), or with 50 μM Et-KuQ (lanes 5 and 6), or after incubating 
the reaction mixture with 50 μM CPT and then adding 50 μM 
Et-KuQ and stopping the reaction after another minute (lane 7), 
or incubating with 50 μM Et-KuQ for 1 min and then adding 
50 μM CPT and stopping the reaction after another minute (lane 
8). The reactions were stopped with SDS, the samples digested 
with trypsin and the products analysed by PAGE (Figure 5A). 
In the presence of DMSO, the cleavage/religation equilibrium 
is shifted towards religation and a small level of cleavage of </p>

<p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>

<p>c 2013 The Author(s). This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>



<p>B. Arnò and others </p>

<p>Figure 3 Cleavage kinetics 
(A) Time course (0.5-15 min) of the cleavage experiment between the CL14/CP25 suicide substrate and the purified Top1 
alone (lanes 2-7), after 10 min pre-incubation with 50 μM Et-KuQ (lanes 8-13) or simultaneously incubated with 50 μM 
Et-KuQ (lanes 14-19). In lane 1 the protein has not been added. Cl1 represents the DNA substrate cleaved by Top1 at 
the preferred cleavage site, indicated by an arrow over the DNA sequence. (B) The percentage of cleavage, determined by 
PhosphorImager and <rs type="software">ImageQuant</rs> software, was normalized to the total amount of radioactivity in each lane. The DMSO 
(black line), simultaneous incubation with Et-KuQ (grey line with squares) and the experiment performed pre-incubating the 
Top1 with Et-KuQ (grey line with circles) are shown. </p>

<p>the labelled DNA strand is detected (Figure 5A, lanes 1 and 2). 
When the enzyme is in the presence of 50 μM CPT the cleav-
age/religation equilibrium is shifted towards cleavage, since CPT 
reversibly binds to the covalent DNA-enzyme intermediate, sta-
bilizing it and slowing down the religation rate, as indicated by 
the band indicated by the asterisk corresponding to the substrate 
cleaved at the preferred site (Figure 5A, lanes 3 and 4) [5,29,30]. 
The band of the cleavage complex is not observed when Et-KuQ 
is added to the enzyme together with the substrate (Figure 5A, 
lanes 5 and 6), confirming that the compound inhibits the cleav-
age step. In line with this, incubation for 1 min of the enzyme, the 
substrate and the Et-KuQ, followed by addition and incubation of 
CPT for another minute, shows a band (Figure 5A, lane 8) similar </p>

<p>to that observed in the presence of Et-KuQ alone, confirming that 
Et-KuQ is an inhibitor of cleavage. The most striking result is ob-
tained upon addition of Et-KuQ to the enzyme previously reacted 
with the substrate in the presence of CPT. The Et-KuQ addition 
brings to 50 % destabilization of the cleaved complex stabilized 
by CPT (Figure 5A, lane 7 compared with lane 4). This result 
indicates that Et-KuQ is able to stimulate the religation even in 
the presence of CPT, overcoming the poisoning effect of the drug 
on inhibiting the religation. A quantification of the cleaved com-
plex observed in the different assays is shown in the histogram 
of Figure 5(B), that indicates the ability of Et-KuQ to reduce the 
CPT stabilization of the cleaved complex (compare lane 4 with 
lanes 7 and 8). These data provide evidence that Et-KuQ has a </p>

<p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>



<p>c 2013 The Author(s). This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>A novel organic compound enhances human topoisomerase I religation activity </p>

<p>Figure 4 
Religation kinetics 
(A) Gel analysis of the religation kinetics (0.5-15 min) between the wild-type suicide covalent complex (Cl1) and the R11 
complementary oligonucleotide (shown at the top of the Figure) in the absence of Et-KuQ (lanes 2-7), after pre-incubation 
with 50 μM Et-KuQ (lanes 8-13), or incubated together with 50 μM Et-KuQ (lanes 14-19). In lane 1 the cleaved complex, 
which represents time 0, has been loaded. In lane 20 no protein was added. 'Cl1' represents the DNA fragment cleaved at 
the preferred enzyme site; 'Religation' is the restored fully duplex oligonucleotide that is the final product of the reaction. 
(B) Percentage of religation, determined by <rs type="software">ImageQuant</rs> software, was plotted as a function of time and normalized to 
the plateau value for the experiment with Top1 alone. Substrate and Top1 (black circles), substrate added to the enzyme 
pre-incubated with Et-KuQ (grey circles), simultaneous mixing of substrate, enzyme and drug (grey squares). </p>

<p>dual effect, inhibiting the cleavage and surprisingly promoting 
the religation, even in the presence of CPT. </p>

<p>Molecular docking </p>

<p>Three molecular docking experiments were performed 
on the Et-KuQ deprotonated form (Figure 1A), in order to study 
the molecular mechanism underlying the observed inhibition of 
cleavage and the enhancement of religation. The first-docking ex-
periment was performed using as a receptor the crystal structure </p>

<p>of the Top1-DNA non-covalent complex [3] after DNA removal. 
The complexes obtained have been subjected to clusterization 
and the largest cluster shows that Et-KuQ interacts with the Top1 
catalytic pentad with an energy of − 9.6 kcal/mol (1 kcal = 
4.184 kJ) (Figure 6). In this structure the Et-KuQ deprotonated 
oxygen molecules are at hydrogen bonding distance with the side-
chains of three residues of the catalytic pentad: Arg 
488 , Arg 
590 and 
Tyr 
723 . This conformation is consistent with the observed inhibi-
tion of the DNA cleavage, and with the increase of the inhibition 
in the case of pre-incubation (Figure 3). </p>

<p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>

<p>c 2013 The Author(s). This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>



<p>B. Arnò and others </p>

<p>Figure 5 Cleavage/religation equilibrium 
(A) Gel electrophoresis of the products from the incubation of Top1 with the [γ -
32 P] end-labelled duplex DNA (CL25/CP25), 
shown at the top of the Figure. The arrow indicates the preferred cleavage site. The duplex was incubated for 1 or 2 min 
with the enzyme (lanes 1 and 2), in presence of CPT (lanes 3 and 4), Et-KuQ (lanes 5 and 6), after a pre-incubation with 
CPT and then addition of Et-KuQ (lane 7) and after pre-incubation with Et-KuQ and then addition of CPT (lane 8). Lane 
9, no enzyme added. The band corresponding to the enzyme-substrate cleaved complex is indicated by an asterisk. (B) 
Percentage of the cleavable complex normalized to the total radioactivity of each lane. </p>

<p>The second docking experiment was performed on the Top1-
DNA covalent complex [3]. Owing to the presence of DNA co-
valently bound to the catalytic Tyr 
723 , Et-KuQ cannot bind in the 
position previously observed in Figure 6 for the docking with 
the protein alone. When the docking is made with the Top1-
DNA covalent complex, Et-KuQ has a binding site in prox-
imity of the catalytic pentad with energy of − 9.8 kcal/mole 
(Figure 7). In this complex the ethyl group of the drug and 
its aromatic scaffold show van der Waals interactions with the 
DNA major grove at the level of the bases in positions − 1 
and + 1, while the deprotonated oxygen molecules of Et-KuQ 
form an hydrogen bond with the lateral chain of Asn 
722 (Fig-
ure 7). This structure permits us to provide an interpretation </p>

<p>of the effect of the compound during the religation process. In 
fact, the deprotonated oxygen molecules of Et-KuQ that rep-
resent a strong hydrogen acceptor site [17] and that can then 
help the deprotonation process that the hydroxyl group of the 5 
DNA terminal must undergo to reseal the cleaved DNA strand, 
are at an average distance from the DNA O5 of 6.7Å (Fig-
ure 7). In the crystal structure of the covalent enzyme-DNA 
binary complex the distance between the DNA O5 and the Nζ 
Lys 
532 , that is considered the proton acceptor site, is 7.2Å [4,6]. 
The relatively short distance between the DNA O5 and a pro-
ton acceptor site provides an explanation for the increase of the 
religation rate observed in the presence of Et-KuQ, shown in 
Figure 4. </p>

<p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>



<p>c 2013 The Author(s). This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>A novel organic compound enhances human topoisomerase I religation activity </p>

<p>Figure 6 
Representative structure of Et-KuQ docked on Top1 in the absence of DNA 
The Et-KuQ (cyan) and the residues of the catalytic pentad are represented as sticks, while the rest of the protein appears 
as a ribbon. The lateral chains of the residues of the catalytic pentad are explicitly represented and labelled. </p>

<p>Figure 7 
Representative structure of Et-KuQ docked on the covalent Top1 + DNA binary complex 
The Et-KuQ is represented in cyan; the lateral chains of the residues of the catalytic pentad and of the Asn 
722 are 
represented as sticks and labelled, the rest of the protein is represented as ribbon. The base-pairs in position + 1 and 
− 1 are represented in black. A blue dashed line indicates the distance between the 5 DNA end, represented as a red 
sphere and the closest Et-KuQ oxygen acceptor. </p>

<p>In order to confirm that this mechanism can be involved in 
the displacement of CPT by Et-KuQ (Figure 5), a third docking 
experiment was performed on the CPT + TopoI + DNA ternary 
complex. In this complex the CPT interfacial inhibitor inter-
calates between the cleaved DNA bases, making the distance 
between the O5 DNA end and the Lys 
532 Nζ proton acceptor as 
long as 11.9Å [6]. Docking experiments indicate that Et-KuQ 
can bind in proximity of the Top1 catalytic pentad with an en-
ergy of − 10.7 kcal/mol (Figure 8), forming a complex where 
the Et-KuQ deprotonated oxygen molecules are at distance of 7.4 
A from the hydroxyl of the 5 DNA end, i.e. the same distance 
observed between the 5 end and the Lys 
532 in the X-ray cova-
lent binary complex [3]. In the docked complex, Et-KuQ makes </p>

<p>contacts with the DNA bases in positions + 1 and − 1 through 
its carbon scaffold and forms a hydrogen bond with the Lys </p>

<p>755 </p>

<p>of the CTD (C-terminal domain) of Top1 through the deproton-
ated oxygen molecules. The relatively short distance between the 
Et-KuQ deprotonated oxygen molecules and the cleaved DNA 
5 -terminal (about 7Å) makes possible the 5 deprotonation pro-
cess, permitting the release of the cleaved complex even in the 
presence of CPT as experimentally observed (Figure 5). 
The chemical properties of Et-KuQ, characterized by the pres-
ence of two deprotonated oxygen molecules that in solution dis-
play a pK a = 5.5 (Figure 1B), whose value can be modulated by 
the protein environment, together with the docking experiment, 
provide a molecular explanation for the facilitated religation in </p>

<p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>

<p>c 2013 The Author(s). This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>



<p>B. Arnò and others </p>

<p>Figure 8 Representative structure of Et-KuQ docked on the CPT + Top1 + DNA ternary complex 
The Et-KuQ is represented in cyan; the lateral chains of the residues of the catalytic pentad and the CPT are represented 
as sticks and labelled; the rest of the protein appears as a ribbon; the base-pairs in position + 1 and − 1 as black lines. 
A blue dashed line indicates the distance between the 5 DNA end, represented as a red sphere, and the closest Et-KuQ 
oxygen acceptor. </p>

<p>the presence of the compound. The Et-KuQ oxygen molecules 
may, in fact, act as hydrogen acceptors facilitating the religation 
process. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The planar pentacyclic structure of Et-KuQ permits a favourable 
interaction of the compound inside the human Top1 catalytic site 
as shown by the docking experiments with the enzyme alone 
(Figure 6), explaining the inhibition of the relaxation and of the 
cleavage displayed by the compound (Figures 2 and 3). 
On the other hand, the proximity between the oxydryl of the 
DNA 5 end and the two close oxygen atoms (Figure 7), acting as 
efficient hydrogen acceptors, explains the ability of the compound 
to act as an enhancer of the enzyme religation rate (Figure 4). The 
Et-KuQ pK a defining the equilibrium between the protonated and 
deprotonated form is 5.6 in solution (Figure 1) and this value can 
be slightly modulated by the protein environment, facilitating the 
acceptance of an hydrogen by the two oxygen molecules that are 
at an average distance of 6.7Å from the oxydryl group of the DNA 
5 end in the docked complex with the covalent enzyme-DNA 
structure (Figure 7). This distance is shorter than the one observed 
in the X-ray diffraction structure between the O5 and the lateral 
chain of Lys 
532 (3), that is supposed to be the proton acceptor in 
the reaction in the absence of any external compound [4]. This 
short distance, coupled with the hydrogen acceptor property of 
the two oxygen molecules, explains the increased religation rate 
promoted by Et-KuQ. 
The same characteristics can be proposed to explain the Et-
KuQ ability in displacing the stalled CPT-DNA-enzyme tern-
ary complex and promoting the religation (Figure 5). In this 
case the Et-KuQ oxygen molecules-O5 DNA distance, observed 
in the docked structure, is about 7Å (Figure 8), permitting the 
deprotonation of the DNA oxydryl group. In this latter case two </p>

<p>possible mechanisms can be envisaged. (1) The DNA oxydryl 
group releases its proton to the Et-KuQ oxygen molecules and 
the deprotonated 5 end forces the CPT displacement promoting 
the religation reaction. (2) The DNA hydroxyl group releases 
its proton to the Et-KuQ oxygen molecules and the reversible 
binding of CPT finds the deprotonated 5 ready to religate during 
the CPT off process. In both cases, the final result is that the 
religation occurs and CPT is displaced. 
Recently it has been proposed that poly(ADP-ribose) displays 
a similar effect: it inhibits the cleavage, but it also reverses the pre-
formed covalent Top-DNA complex, stimulating the religation 
activity of the enzyme [15,16]. It is probable that the same mech-
anism proposed for Et-KuQ can also work for the poly(ADP-
ribose) polymer. The complex structure of the poly(ADP-ribose), 
made by many phosphate groups, may facilitate the deprotona-
tion of the 5 DNA end, again facilitating the religation. It can 
then be concluded that facilitation of the deprotonation of the 5 
DNA end is the crucial process to promote religation. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTION </p>

<p>Barbara Arnò carried out the majority of the experimental part of the 
study, helped by Cinzia Tesauro and Laura Zuccaro. Sara Lentini, 
Pierluca Galloni, Valeria Conte and Barbara Floris performed the Et-
KuQ synthesis and the Et-KuQ acid-base titration. Andrea Coletta 
carried out all of the docking analysis. Paola Fiorani and Alessandro 
Desideri designed, co-ordinated the studies and co-wrote the paper. 
All authors read and approved the paper. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Associazione Italiana per la Ricerca 
sul Cancro (AIRC) [project 10121 (to A.D.)]. </p>

<p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>



<p>c 2013 The Author(s). This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>A novel organic compound enhances human topoisomerase I religation activity </p>



<p>Received 15 November 2012/6 December 2012; accepted 19 December 2012 </p>

<p>Published as Immediate Publication 31 January 2013, doi 10.1042/BSR20120118 </p>

<p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>

<p>c 2013 The Author(s). This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>



<p>Biosci. Rep. (2013) / 33 / art:e00025 / doi 10.1042/BSR20120118 </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>



<p>Supplementary Figure S1 is on the following page </p>

<p>1 To whom correspondence should be addressed (email desideri@uniroma2.it). </p>

<p>c 2013 The Author(s). This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>B. Arnò and others </p>

<p>Figure S1 Religation kinetics 
(A) Gel analysis of the religation kinetics (0.5-15 min) between the wild-type suicide covalent complex (Cl1) and the R11 
complementary oligonucleotide (shown at the top of the Figure) (lanes 2-7), after pre-incubation of the cleavage complex 
with 200 μM Et-KuQ (lanes 8-13), or added together with 50 μM Et-KuQ (lanes 14-19). In lane 1, the cleaved complex, 
which represents time 0, has been loaded. In lane 20, no protein was added. 'Cl1' represents the DNA fragment cleaved at 
the preferred enzyme site; 'Religation' is the restored fully duplex oligonucleotide that is the final product of the reaction. 
(B) Percentage of religation, determined by ImageQuant software, was plotted as function of time and normalized to the 
plateau value for the experiment with Top1 alone (black circles), substrate added to the enzyme pre-incubatied with Et-KuQ 
(grey circles), simultaneous mixing of substrate, enzyme and drug (grey squares). </p>

<p>Received 15 November 2012/6 December 2012; accepted 19 December 2012 </p>

<p>Published as Immediate Publication 31 January 2013, doi 10.1042/BSR20120118 </p>

<p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>

<p>c 2013 The Author(s). This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

</text></tei>