<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3030791" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Background: Size, location, and type of colonic polyps 
may prevent colonoscopic polypectomy. Laparoscopic 
colectomy may serve as an optimal alternative in these 
patients. We assessed the perioperative outcome and the 
risk for cancer in patients operated on laparoscopically for 
colonic polyps not amenable to colonoscopic resection. </p>

<p>Methods: An evaluation was conducted of our prospec-
tive accumulated data of a consecutive series of patients 
operated on for colonic polyps. </p>

<p>Results: Sixty-four patients underwent laparoscopic re-
section for colonic polyps during a 6-year period. This 
group comprised 18% of all our laparoscopic colorectal 
procedures. Forty-six percent were males, mean age was 
71. Most of the polyps (66%) were located on the right 
side. No deaths occurred. Conversion was necessary in 3 
patients (4.6%). Significant complications occurred in 3 
patients (4.6%). Nine patients (14%) were found to have 
malignancy. Three of them had lymph-node involvement. 
No difference existed in polyp size between malignant 
and nonmalignant lesions. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Laparoscopic colectomy for endoscopic 
nonresectable colonic polyps is a safe, simple procedure 
as reflected by the low rate of conversions and complica-
tions. However, invasive cancer may be found in the final 
pathology following surgery. This mandates a strict adher-
ence to surgical oncological principles. Polyp size cannot 
predict the risk of malignancy. </p>

<p>Key Words: Laparoscopy, Colorectal surgery, Polyps, 
Colorectal cancer. </p>

<p>INTRODUCTION </p>

<p>Endoscopic polypectomy is the standard treatment for 
colon and rectal polyps and is indicated to prevent future 
colorectal cancer. Some of these polyps cannot be re-
sected endoscopically due to technical factors and risk of 
complications. Factors related to polyp size (occupies 
more than one-third of bowel circumference or 2 haustral 
folds), type (flat/sessile), and location (ileocecal valve, 
flexures) might exclude the polyp from being excised 
endoscopically and expose the patient to the risk of bleed-
ing and perforation. 1-3   Polyps that are endoscopically nonresectable would need 
surgical removal. The laparoscopic approach with its as-
sociated advantages provides an optimal choice to the 
management of these polyps. Laparoscopic colorectal sur-
geries include a wide spectrum of procedures for a variety 
of different pathologies and have different levels of diffi-
culty and surgical considerations. The adoption of lapa-
roscopy for colorectal cancer has been slow to evolve due 
to concerns over its oncological safety. 4   In recent years, large multi-center prospective random-
ized studies 5,6 have demonstrated the oncological safety 
of these procedures in cancer patients. However, a pre-
requisite for a safe oncological operation is surgeon ex-
perience and adherence to surgical oncological princi-
ples. 7   Oncological factors are not involved in the laparoscopic 
approach for benign colorectal entities; however, the 
common benign entities, such as inflammatory bowel 
disease and diverticular disease, may be a hostile environ-
ment for the laparoscopic surgeon due to distorted anat-
omy and the need to handle friable and inflamed tissue. </p>

<p>Laparoscopic colectomy for nonresectable colonic polyps 
might be a simpler procedure both for the surgeon and 
patient, because no inflammatory process is involved and 
the entity is considered benign. However, a risk for ma-
lignancy exists, and this should be taken into consider-
ation. </p>

<p>The aim of this study was to address 2 aspects of laparo-
scopic resection of colonic polyps. The important one was 
to estimate the rate of invasive cancer in the final pathol-</p>

<p>Department of Surgery A, Tel Aviv Sourasky Medical Center, Tel Aviv, Israel (all 
authors). </p>

<p>Address correspondence to: Shmuel Avital, Department of Surgery A, Tel-Aviv 
Sourasky Medical Center, Ichilov Hospital, 6 Weizmann Street Tel-Aviv 64239. Tele-
phone: 972-3-6947289, Fax: 972-3-6974820, E-mail: shmuelavital@hotmail.com </p>

<p>DOI: 10.4293/108680809X12589998404407 </p>

<p>© 2009 by JSLS, Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons. Published by 
the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons, Inc. </p>

<p>JSLS (2009)13:555-559 </p>

<p>555 </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC PAPER </p>

<p>ogy results of the resected specimens of these benign-
appearing lesions. And the second one was to evaluate 
the perioperative outcome of these procedures as re-
flected in complications and conversions. </p>

<p>PATIENTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Operative data on patients who underwent laparoscopic 
colectomy for colonic polyps was retrieved from a pro-
spectively collected database of all consecutive patients 
who have undergone an elective laparoscopic colorectal 
procedure by our surgical team since September 2003. 
These data were collected in an <rs type="software">excel</rs> data sheet and 
include demographic data, preoperative diagnosis (endo-
scopic and pathology), perioperative parameters, and fi-
nal pathology results. </p>

<p>All patients who had an endoscopically nonresectable 
polyp with benign preoperative pathology were included 
in this study. Patients with endoscopic appearance of a 
tumoral mass but a benign pathology were excluded from 
this series, because they were considered to have cancer 
prior to surgery. Patients with colonic polyps with a pre-
operative biopsy of cancer were excluded as well. </p>

<p>The preoperative colonoscopies were performed by a 
large number of gastroenterologists. The decision to refer 
patients for laparoscopic colectomy due to endoscopically 
nonresectable polyps was done by the specific physician 
who performed the colonoscopy. </p>

<p>All operative procedures were performed or directed by 1 
of 2 surgeons. All polyps were marked with India ink 
before surgery, except for polyps located near the cecum. 
The size of the polyps was measured and recorded by the 
pathologists. </p>

<p>Our standard surgical approach used in most cases is 
based on a medial to lateral technique. For right colecto-
mies, we use a 3-port technique with a medial to lateral 
mesocolon dissection, lateral mobilization, colonic exteri-
orization, colonic transection, and extracorporal anasto-
mosis. Left-sided resections were performed with 4-ports 
with a medial to lateral dissection, lateral mobilization, 
intracorporeal distal transection, exteriorization of the 
proximal colon with proximal transection and intracorpo-
ral anastomosis using an endoluminal stapler. As a rule, 
we protect the extraction site in both right and left colec-
tomies. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Sixty-four elective laparoscopic colorectal operations for 
colorectal polyps with benign preoperative pathology </p>

<p>were performed during a 6-year period by our surgical 
team. This group comprised 18% of our laparoscopic 
colorectal procedures. Forty-six percent of the patients 
were males. Mean age was 71. The most frequent proce-
dure performed was right colectomy, performed in 42 
patients (66%), anterior resection in 7 (11%), sigmoidec-
tomy in 6 (9.3%), subtotal colectomy in 3 (4.6%), and 
transverse colectomy in 2 (3.1%). Mean operative time 
was 140 minutes (range, 60 to 265). </p>

<p>In 3 patients (4.6%), surgery had to be converted to open, 
one due to severe adhesions, one due to intraoperative 
bleeding, and in one patient the ink mark was not found. 
No mortalities occurred. Major complications occurred in 
3 patients; one underwent relaparotomy due to nonfunc-
tioning anastomosis, one due to small bowel injury, and 
one due to anastomotic leak that was reanastomosed. All 
3 patients recovered completely following the second 
operation. </p>

<p>Final pathology revealed 9 patients (14%) with adenocar-
cinoma. Cancer stage was T3N1 in 2 patients, T3N0 in 2 
patients, T2N1 in 1 patient, T2N0 in 2 patients, and T1N0 
in 2 patients. Mean number of harvested nodes for these 
patients was 13 (range, 4 to 29). There was no difference 
in average polyp size between cancer and noncancer 
patients (Table 1). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Laparoscopic colorectal surgery has grown in popularity 
for both benign and malignant indications. This approach 
generally offers decreased postoperative pain, improved 
pulmonary function, shorter hospital stay, and the benefits 
of improved cosmetics. 8   However, laparoscopic colorectal surgery is a technically 
demanding procedure with a long learning curve and 
mandates specific considerations based on the pathology 
involved. </p>

<p>In the common benign indications like inflammatory 
bowel or diverticular disease, the procedures are techni-
cally difficult due to distorted anatomy and inflammation 
leading to increased conversion and complication rates 
and require significant surgical experience. 9,10   On the other hand when approaching colorectal cancer, 
laparoscopic oncological factors should be taken into con-
sideration. The adoption of laparoscopy for colorectal 
cancer was slow to evolve due to early reports of postop-
erative port-site metastases, which raised concerns over its 
long-term oncological safety. 4 Large multicenter prospec-</p>

<p>Laparoscopic Surgery for Colorectal Polyps, Itah R et al. </p>

<p>JSLS (2009)13:555-559 </p>



<p>tive randomized trials 5-7 have since demonstrated the on-
cological safety of the laparoscopic approach in colorectal 
cancer patients, citing equivalent long-term outcomes to 
that of standard open resection and concluding the debate 
over the oncological safety of this approach. However, 
these operations should be carried out by experienced 
surgeons and with adherence to oncological principles 
including adequate lymph-node harvesting and wound 
precautions. </p>

<p>Laparoscopic colectomy for polyps appears to be a sim-
pler procedure for both patients and surgeons. Mobiliza-
tion of the colon and tissue dissection is generally simpler 
and easier during surgery for polyps because no inflam-
matory process is involved and no bulky tumors are 
present. Our perioperative results demonstrate a low con-
version rate of approximately 5%, low significant compli-
cation rate, and no mortality. These results are compara-
ble to results of other recent published reports 11,12 and are 
better compared with laparoscopy for other colorectal 
entities, such as malignant tumors or diverticular dis-
ease. 8,13   Strong emphasis should be placed on preoperative local-
ization of the polyps. Polyps located in the cecal area do 
not need to be marked. In these cases, a formal right 
colectomy is performed any way. For polyps at any other 
location, localization procedures are highly recom-
mended. We routinely perform endoscopic tattooing be-
fore surgery because lack of preoperative localization may 
lead to conversion. 14 Intraoperative colonoscopy may be 
performed as well; however, it may result in hyperinfla-
tion of the bowel, thus obscuring the laparoscopic view. 15  CO 2 colonoscopy may serve as a good alternative in these 
cases as the CO 2 is absorbed very rapidly from the colonic 
lumen. 16   The distribution of polyp location in our series revealed a 
majority of polyps (66%) located on the right side. This 
finding is in accordance with the findings in other series of 
laparoscopic colectomy for polyps, which report 76% to 
78% of patients with right-sided polyps. 11,12,17   This finding is interesting because most of polyps re-
moved endoscopically are located in the left colonic 
side. 18 The fact that most of the surgically removed polyps 
are right-sided may reflect the reluctance of the endosco-
pist to resect large and difficult to locate polyps in the right 
colon because of the fear of complications like perforation 
of the relatively thin right colonic wall. </p>

<p>In addition, this makes the laparoscopist's decision to 
recommend laparoscopic segmental resection even sim-
pler because laparoscopic right-sided colectomies are eas-
ier to perform. 19   However, we believe that the most important issue when 
approaching these patients is the high risk for cancer in 
these apparently benign polyps. In our series, 14% of the 
patients had malignancy in their final pathology despite 
the benign endoscopic appearance and pathology results 
before surgery. Moreover, most of the patients, 6 out of 9, 
who were found to have cancer, had advanced stage 
tumors (Stage II or more). Higher percentages of up to 
22% cancer identified in the final pathology and a high 
rate of advanced cancer have been reported in other 
recently published series 11,12,17 (Table 2). </p>

<p>Our series included only patients in whom both the en-
doscopic appearance, as evaluated by the physician, and 
the pathology were benign. This was different from other 
reported series that included all neoplasms with benign </p>

<p>Table 1. 
Comparison of Polyp Size </p>

<p>Benign Pathology 
Cancer 
P Value </p>

<p>No. of Patients 
55 
9 </p>

<p>Range of Polyp Size (cm) 
0.8-5 
07-4.5 </p>

<p>Mean Polyp Size Ϯ Standard Deviation (cm) 
2.63 Ϯ 1.11 
2.47 Ϯ 1.30 
NS </p>

<p>Table 2. 
Cancer Rate and Percentage of Advanced Tumor in Final 
Pathology </p>

<p>Author 
Carcinoma in 
Final Pathology </p>

<p>Percentage of 
Advanced Tumor 
(Stage II or More) </p>

<p>Pokala et al </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>20% 
NR </p>

<p>Brozovich et al </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>22% 
57% </p>

<p>Ross et al </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>18.2% 
60% </p>

<p>Present Study 
14% 
44% </p>

<p>JSLS (2009)13:555-559 </p>



<p>preoperative histology, regardless of the endoscopic ap-
pearance. 11 This may explain the higher rate of cancer 
found in other series 11,12,17 compared with our study. This 
difference emphasizes the fact that even polyps with a 
benign endoscopic appearance and benign pathology re-
ferred for surgery may harbor cancer that may be invasive. </p>

<p>It is difficult to reliably predict which patients would have 
invasive cancer verified in their final pathology. Associa-
tion between increasing polyp size and the possibility of 
harboring cancer is well known. 18,20   However, the size of a polyp in patients referred for 
surgery cannot reliably predict or negate the risk for can-
cer. In our series, 6 of 9 patients who had cancer (33%) 
had a polyp size Յ2cm, and the average size of these 
polyps was not different from the average size of the 
benign polyps as has been shown by others. 11   An interesting optional treatment modality for difficult 
colonic polyps is a combination of laparoscopy and en-
doscopy. 21,22 In this technique, the laparoscopic surgeon 
helps to manipulate the bowel to allow a simultaneous 
endoscopic resection and at the same time monitors the 
procedure for possible perforation. This technique may 
prevent unnecessary segmental resections; however, it 
mandates a specific surgical set up of different teams. In 
addition, all specimens should be evaluated intraopera-
tively for cancer so the surgeon can decide on formal 
resection. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Laparoscopic colectomy for endoscopic nonresectable co-
lonic polyps is generally a safe procedure associated with 
a low rate of conversions and complications. The inci-
dence of malignancy and specifically advanced staged 
tumors documented on final pathology may be high and 
cannot be ruled out before surgery. These study results 
emphasize the fact that colonic lesions with benign pa-
thology that have an endoscopic benign polypoid appear-
ance may also harbor an invasive cancer. We believe that 
this is a major consideration when operating on these 
patients, mandating strict adherence to surgical oncolog-
ical principles with adequate lymph node harvesting and 
wound precautions. Surgeons experienced with laparos-
copy for colorectal cancer should be involved in these 
procedures. </p>









</text></tei>