<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3361002" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:45+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Positive feedback is a common mechanism enabling biological systems to respond to stimuli in a 
switch-like manner. Such systems are often characterized by the requisite formation of a 
heterodimer where only one of the pair is subject to feedback. This ASymmetric Self-UpREgulation 
(ASSURE) motif is central to many biological systems, including cholesterol homeostasis (LXRa/ 
RXRa), adipocyte differentiation (PPARg/RXRa), development and differentiation (RAR/RXR), 
myogenesis (MyoD/E12) and cellular antiviral defense (IRF3/IRF7). To understand why this motif is 
so prevalent, we examined its properties in an evolutionarily conserved transcriptional regulatory 
network in yeast (Oaf1p/Pip2p). We demonstrate that the asymmetry in positive feedback confers a 
competitive advantage and allows the system to robustly increase its responsiveness while precisely 
tuning the response to a consistent level in the presence of varying stimuli. This study reveals 
evolutionary advantages for the ASSURE motif, and mechanisms for control, that are relevant to 
pharmacologic intervention and synthetic biology applications. 
Positive feedback systems are ubiquitous in biology. They play 
critical regulatory roles in signaling, transcription, metabolism 
and molecular assembly. In positive feedback systems, input 
signals trigger a chain of signaling or regulatory events, which 
loop back and amplify the system response. In biological 
networks they serve to transform environmental signals to all-
or-none switches (Ferrell and Machleder, 1998; Xiong and 
Ferrell, 2003) and can slow 'switch on' times (Maeda and 
Sano, 2006) and 'switch off' times (Siciliano et al, 2011). In 
combination, fast and slow positive feedback loops can buffer 
against a noisy input to produce a reliable response 
(Brandman et al, 2005). A common feature of biological 
positive feedback systems is that they contain an element 
where two factors combinatorially (e.g. as a heterodimeric 
complex) regulate the expression level or activity of their 
targets and only one factor is upregulated by the heterodimer 
(Figure 1). Several examples of networks with this feature are 
listed in Table I; we term this network motif ASSURE for 
ASymmetric Self-UpREgulation. As suggested for nuclear 
receptors, many ASSURE motifs appear to have evolved, 
through gene duplications followed by specialization, from 
regulators that previously acted as homodimers (Laudet et al, 
1992). </p>

<p>An additional, common feature of these network motifs is 
that one of the proteins of the heterodimeric regulatory 
complex is responsible for sensing the input signal. In such 
cases, there are two possible variations of the ASSURE 
network motif that are defined based on the direction of 
the feedback loop. In ASSURE I, the heterodimer upregulates 
the synthesis of the signal sensor partner; in ASSURE II, 
the heterodimer upregulates the synthesis of the signal 
sensor itself. The core of the fatty acid-responsive gene 
regulatory network in the budding yeast Saccharomyces 
cerevisiae is an example of ASSURE I. A heterodimer of 
Oaf1p and Pip2p (Phelps et al, 2006; Smith et al, 2007), is 
activated by the direct binding of fatty acid (oleate) to the 
Oaf1p ligand binding domain (Phelps et al, 2006). The active 
Oaf1p/Pip2p hetorodimer upregulates the expression of the 
PIP2 gene but not the OAF1 gene (Figure 1A) (Rottensteiner 
et al, 1997). 
Peroxisome proliferators in mammals exemplify the 
ASSURE II network motif. For example, the nuclear receptors 
peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor g (PPARg) and its 
partner protein retinoid X receptor a (RXRa) form a hetero-
dimer which is activated by ligand binding (e.g., certain 
arachidonic acid metabolites or oxidized fatty acids) to PPARg 
and the active PPARg/RXRa heterodimer upregulates the 
expression of the PPARg gene (Figure 1B) (Wakabayashi </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 8; Article number 577; doi:10.1038/msb.2012.10 
Citation: Molecular Systems Biology 8:577 </p>

<p>&amp; 2012 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited All rights reserved 1744-4292/12 </p>

<p>www.molecularsystemsbiology.com </p>

<p>&amp; 2012 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2012 1 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Peroxisome 
biogenesis 
Heterodimer </p>

<p>Oaf1p </p>

<p>Pip2p </p>

<p>Fatty 
acid </p>

<p>Heterodimer </p>

<p>Adipocyte 
differentiation </p>

<p>PPARγ </p>

<p>RXRα </p>

<p>Ligand </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Heterodimer </p>

<p>Myogenesis </p>

<p>MyoD </p>

<p>E12 </p>

<p>Signal </p>

<p>Figure 1 Schematic representations of three examples the ASSURE biomolecular regulatory systems composed of asymmetric positive feedback loops. (A) Fatty acid 
response and peroxisome biogenesis in budding yeast; (B) Adipocyte differentiation; (C) Myogenesis. Each system leads to the production of a heterodimer, which feeds 
back on one arm of the network conferring self-upregulation and control of the biological response. In each case a signal (represented by a filled circle) activates a 
transcription factor (oval). The factor forms a heterodimer with its partner (circle) and together this complex positively feeds back (dashed arrow) and activates genes 
involved in the biological response (dashed arrow). </p>

<p>Table I Examples of biomolecular systems with the asymmetric positive feedback network motif </p>

<p>System 
Asymmetric positive feedback 
Type 
References </p>

<p>Fatty acid response and peroxisome 
biogenesis in budding yeast </p>

<p>Fatty acid þ Oaf1p2Oaf1p* 
Oaf1p* þ Pip2p2heterodimer-PIP2 gene </p>

<p>I 
(Phelps et al, 2006; 
Rottensteiner et al, 1997; 
Smith et al, 2007) 
Adipocyte differentiation 
Agonist þ PPARg2 PPARg* 
Agonist þ RXRa2RXRa* 
PPARg* þ RXRa(RXRa*)2heterodimer-PPARg gene </p>

<p>I/II 
(Westin et al, 1998; 
Wakabayashi et al, 2009) </p>

<p>Cholesterol homeostasis in human 
macrophages </p>

<p>Agonist þ LXRa2LXRa* 
LXRa* þ RXRa2heterodimer-LXRa gene </p>

<p>I/II 
(Whitney et al, 2001) </p>

<p>Early development and 
differentiation (human) </p>

<p>Agonist þ RAR2RAR* 
RAR* þ RXR2heterodimer-RAR gene </p>

<p>I/II 
(de The et al, 1990) </p>

<p>Early development and 
differentiation (mice) </p>

<p>Agonist þ RAR2RAR* 
RAR* þ RXR2heterodimer-RAR gene </p>

<p>I/II 
(Hoffmann et al, 1990; 
Leroy et al, 1991a; 
Leroy et al, 1991b) 
Early development and 
differentiation (zebrafish) </p>

<p>Agonist þ RAR2RAR* 
RAR* þ RXR2heterodimer-RAR gene </p>

<p>I/II 
(Linville et al, 2009) </p>

<p>Cellular antiviral defense 
Signal þ IRF3-IRF3* 
Signal þ IRF7-IRF7* 
IRF3* þ IRF7*2heterodimer-IFNb gene-IFNb-STAT1, 
STAT2, IRF9-IRF7 gene </p>

<p>I/II 
(Honda and Taniguchi, 2006; 
Tamura et al, 2008) </p>

<p>Myogenesis 
Signal þ MyoD-MyoD* 
MyoD* þ E122heterodimer-MyoD gene </p>

<p>II 
(Benayoun et al, 1998) </p>

<p>Control of the synaptic 
plasticity in Drosophila </p>

<p>Signal þ Fos-Fos* 
Signal þ Jun-Jun* 
Fos* þ Jun*2heterodimer-CREB gene 
CREB-CREB and Fos genes </p>

<p>I/II 
(Sanyal et al, 2002; 
Sheng and Greenberg, 1990) </p>

<p>Filamentous growth 
regulation in yeast </p>

<p>Signal (low nitrogen, butanol, etc.) þ Tec1-Tec1* 
Signal þ Ste12-Ste12* 
Tec1* þ Ste12*-TEC1 </p>

<p>I/II 
(Madhani and Fink, 1997; 
Prinz et al, 2004; 
Zeitlinger et al, 2003) 
Cell proliferation and 
growth </p>

<p>c-Myc -| miRNA-22 -| MYCBP-c-Myc þ 
MAX-target genes </p>

<p>II 
(Xiong et al, 2010) </p>

<p>Antioxidant response 
(HepG2 cells) </p>

<p>ROS-KEAP1-Nrf2-Nrf2-Nrf2/small Maf-p62 
gene-p62-Nrf2 gene </p>

<p>II 
(Alam et al, 1999; 
Jain et al, 2010; 
Motohashi et al, 2002) 
Response to xenobiotics: 
reduction of arsenic-induced 
cytotoxicity (HeLa cells) </p>

<p>iAsIII-Nrf2 activation (KEAP1-Nrf2-Nrf2)-Nrf2/small 
Maf-HO-1 gene-HO-1-Nrf2 gene </p>

<p>II 
(Abiko et al, 2010; 
Alam et al, 1999; 
Motohashi et al, 2002) 
White-opaque phenotypic 
switching in Candida albicans </p>

<p>Signal (loss of the mating type locus heterozygosity)-Wor1 
Wor1 þ Mcm1-WOR1 </p>

<p>II 
(Morschhauser, 2010; 
Tuch et al, 2008; 
Zordan et al, 2007) 
Cell cycle (G 1 -S phase transition) 
and tumor suppression control </p>

<p>E2F1 þ DP12E2F1/DP1 
E2F1/DP1 þ pRB2pRB/E2F1/DP1 
Growth stimulatory signals-
pRB/E2F1/DP1-E2F1/DP1 þ pRB-E2F1 gene </p>

<p>II 
(Helin et al, 1993; 
Johnson et al, 1994; 
Krek et al, 1993) </p>

<p>CREB, cAMP response element-binding; DP, differentiation regulated transcription factor protein; E2F, E2 transcription factor; HO-1, heme oxigenase-1; IRF, interferon 
regulatory factor; iAsIII, inorganic arsenite; KEAP, Kelch-like ECH-associated protein; LXR, liver X receptor; MAX, c-Myc-associated factor X; MCM, minichromosome 
maintenance; MYCBP, c-Myc-binding protein; Nrf2 (NFE2L2), Nuclear factor (erythroid-derived 2)-like 2; OAF, oleate-activated transcription factor; PIP, peroxisome 
induction pathway; PPAR, peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor; pRB, retinoblastoma protein; RAR, retinoic acid receptor; ROS, reactive oxygen species; RXR, 
retinoid X receptor; STAT, signal transducer and activator of transcription; TEC, transposon enhancement control; WOR, White-Opaque Regulator; 2, dimerization; -, 
upregulation/activation; -|, downregulation. </p>

<p>ASSUREd network responses 
AV Ratushny et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2012 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>et al, 2009). Another example of an ASSURE II network motif is 
composed of myogenic transcription factors MyoD and E12. 
During myogenic differentiation, MyoD is activated by Mos 
kinase phosphorylation and forms a heterodimer with E12, 
and together they upregulate the expression of the gene 
encoding MyoD (Figure 1C) (Benayoun et al, 1998). 
Because of the prevalence and the wide range of systems in 
which the ASSURE network motif is found, we asked what 
features may be responsible for its presumed evolutionary 
advantages. Here, we studied both experimentally and using 
computational modeling, the behavior of systems controlled 
by the ASSURE I or II motif and systems in which both 
regulatory molecules in the pair are self-upregulated. We 
demonstrate that the asymmetry in positive feedback motifs 
provides the system with precise, tunable and robust control of 
responses to stimuli that allows the system to reliably execute 
its physiological program and that this motif leads to a fitness 
advantage. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>To investigate possible functional implications of the ASSURE 
network motif we developed mathematical models of four </p>

<p>different biomolecular regulatory systems where the network 
response to a stimulus involves homo-or heterodimerization of 
transcription factors (Figure 2A-D). In the first system, the 
sensor molecule P is activated by an extracellular or an 
intracellular signaling species (Signal) and forms a homodimer 
that upregulates its targets without feedback (Figure 2A). The 
second system is composed of the same players, but the 
homodimer feeds back in a positive manner to increase the 
synthesis of P (symmetric positive feedback (SPF)) (Figure 2B). 
The remaining two systems represent versions of the ASSURE 
network motif (Figure 2C and D). In ASSURE I, the sensor 
molecule (P 1 ) is activated by the Signal and forms a heterodimer 
with protein (P 2 ), which upregulates the synthesis of P 2 and 
additional targets (Figure 2C). In ASSURE II, the sensor 
molecule (P 1 ) is activated by the Signal and forms a heterodimer 
with protein (P 2 ), which positively upregulates the synthesis of 
P 1 and additional targets (Figure 2D). Constraints associated 
with the general machinery of gene expression and protein 
synthesis are accounted for in the models by representing the 
fractional activity of genes using a saturation function (see 
Materials and Methods). 
To investigate the effects of network topology on network 
function, models describing the four network classes were 
compared in a mathematically controlled fashion, i.e., using </p>

<p>0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1 </p>

<p>-0.5 
0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 
2 
3 
2.5 
Signal (a.u) </p>

<p>Time (h) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>-0.5 
0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 
2 
2.5 
3 
Level of response (a.u.) </p>

<p>Time (h) </p>

<p>SPF 
No feedback 
ASSURE I 
ASSUREII </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>-0.5 
0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 
2 
2.5 
3 
Level of response (a.u.) </p>

<p>Time (h) </p>

<p>Signal 
P </p>

<p>P* </p>

<p>Homodimer </p>

<p>Targets </p>

<p>Signal 
P 1 </p>

<p>P 1 * 
P 2 </p>

<p>Heterodimer </p>

<p>Targets </p>

<p>Signal </p>

<p>P 1 </p>

<p>P 1 * </p>

<p>P 2 </p>

<p>Heterodimer </p>

<p>Targets </p>

<p>Signal </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P* </p>

<p>Homodimer </p>

<p>Targets </p>

<p>Asymmetric positive 
feedback (ASSURE I) </p>

<p>Symmetric positive 
feedback (SPF) </p>

<p>Asymmetric positive 
feedback (ASSURE II) 
No feedback </p>

<p>K sp 
K sp 
K sp 
Ksp </p>

<p>K d 
K d 
K d 
K d </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>-0.5 
0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 
2 
2.5 
3 
Level of response (a.u.) </p>

<p>Time (h) </p>

<p>SPF, low K d 
SPF, high K d 
ASSURE, low K d </p>

<p>0 
0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
4 0 
5 0 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.08 </p>

<p>Probability density </p>

<p>τ 0.5 (min) </p>

<p>SPF 
ASSURE </p>

<p>A 
B 
C 
D 
E </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>G 
H 
I </p>

<p>ASSURE, high K d </p>

<p>10, 000 random parameter sets 
P &lt; 10 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>Figure 2 Theoretical prediction of the precisely tunable and robust response of the biomolecular network with the ASSURE network motif. (A) A network where a 
sensor molecule P activated by an extra-or intracellular signal (Signal) forms a homodimer that upregulates its targets (a network without feedback). (B) A network where 
a sensor molecule P activated by Signal forms a homodimer that upregulates its own synthesis and targets (dashed arrows). (C) A network where a sensor molecule (P 1 ) 
activated by Signal forms a heterodimer with a protein (P 2 ) that upregulates the synthesis of P 2 and targets (ASSURE I). (D) A network where a sensor molecule (P 1 ) 
activated by Signal forms a heterodimer with a protein (P 2 ) that upregulates the synthesis of P 1 and targets (ASSURE II). (E) Stimulus applied to each system. 
(F) Responses of each system to the stimulus. Responses of ASSURE I and II are equal when Signal4 4P 1 and/or the dissociation constant K sp is low, indicating the 
high affinity between Signal and P 1 . (G) Color coded variation of initial P 1 level in the ASSURE I system (inset) and corresponding responses of each system to the 
stimulus. (H) Effect of K d (the dissociation constant of homo-and heterodimerization) variation on the symmetric positive feedback and the ASSURE system responses 
to the stimulus. The difference between the low and high K d is five orders of magnitude (low K d ¼ 10 
À 5 a.u. and high K d ¼ 1 a.u.) (see also Supplementary Figures 2 
and 3). (I) Response time (t 0.5 ) probability density for the SPF and ASSURE models, respectively, calculated based on the model responses with 10 000 random 
parameter sets (Supplementary Table 1; Supplementary Figure 9). </p>

<p>ASSUREd network responses 
AV Ratushny et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2012 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2012 3 </p>

<p>equivalent parameters save for the specific parameter encod-
ing the difference in model topology (Henceforth, in the 
mathematical models, we will use a species's symbol (e.g., 
Signal) to represent its concentration.). Model simulations 
revealed that the kinetic characteristics of the responses from 
ASSURE I and ASSURE II network motifs are identical under 
typical physiological conditions (i.e. when Signal 4 4P 1 and/ 
or the dissociation constant for binding of P 1 by Signal (K sp ) 
is low (indicating a high affinity)) (Figures 2E and F). This 
assumption is based on the fact that activating ligands are 
typically in higher abundance than their targets (e.g., protein 
receptors) and affinities between ligands and receptors are also 
typically high (e.g., K d for oleate binding to Oaf1p is 
1.65 Â10 
À 8 M (Phelps et al, 2006); K d for nitrolinoleic acid 
binding to PPARg is 1.33 Â10 
À 7 M (Schopfer et al, 2005); K d 
for 22(R)-hydroxycholesterol binding to LXRa and is 2.5 Â 
10 
À 7 M (Bramlett et al, 2003)). In simulations where the ligand 
concentration is low (Signal o oP 1 ) and/or the affinity 
between the ligand and the sensor is low (high K sp ) the 
responses of ASSURE I and ASSURE II are distinct; ASSURE I is 
more responsive due to the relatively high concentration of the 
sensor protein P 1 (Supplementary Figure 1). 
Model simulations revealed several characteristics of the 
ASSURE network motif that would be expected to confer 
advantages over other motifs. The ASSURE motif has proper-
ties typical of other positive feedback networks (including 
symmetric positive feedback motifs), which confer sigmoidal 
all-or-none like responses to stimuli. The ASSURE motif is also 
tunable, like the motif with no feedback; the maximum level of 
the response is dictated by the abundance of one partner of the 
heterodimeric pair (i.e., the protein that is not subject to 
positive feedback, P 1 in ASSURE I and P 2 in ASSURE II) 
(Figures 2F and G; Supplementary Figure 2). In addition, in the 
ASSURE motifs, the member of the heterodimer that is not 
subject to positive feedback is assumed to be at higher 
constitutive levels than the inducible partner. This 'ready state' 
efficiently shifts the equilibrium for the reaction pair P 1 þ 
P 2 3P 1 P 2 toward the formation of heterodimer, increasing the 
responsiveness of the ASSURE network compared to the SPF 
network. The network controlled by the ASSURE motif 
therefore responds more rapidly and reaches a plateau earlier 
than a network controlled by symmetric positive feedback. 
To address whether the ASSURE system response time (t 0.5 ) 
would be robust to changes in the partner interaction strength, 
we investigated the response in the context of changes to the 
dissociation constant (K d ) of the heterodimer formed between 
P 1 and P 2 . A wide range of K d values have little effect on the 
response of the systems with the asymmetric positive feed-
back. By contrast, the response of the symmetric positive 
feedback motif is sensitive to changes in K d (Figure 2H; 
Supplementary Figures 3 and 4). In addition, the sensitivity of 
the ASSURE response time to changes in the affinity of 
dimerization is not significantly altered by changes in the 
number of molecules of the heterodimerizing partner (whose 
expression is not upregulated) (Supplementary Figure 5). In 
the ASSURE network, the lower sensitivity of the response 
time with respect to changes in K d is likely due to the 
imbalance in the abundance of P 1 and P 2 . The 'ready state' 
ensures that the system can operate efficiently at lower affinity 
between P 1 and P 2 , facilitating evolvability. </p>

<p>Exploration of the effects of changing multiple model 
parameters on the temporal responses of the SPF and ASSURE 
models revealed the same pattern of robust responses in the 
ASSURE system (Supplementary Figures 6 and 7). Interest-
ingly, for some parameter sets, the SPF model does not respond 
to the stimulus whereas the ASSURE model for the same 
parameter sets readily responds (see the high K d values in 
Supplementary Figures 6, 7 and 8). 
We next investigated, in the context of a model of 
evolutionary variations to pathway kinetic parameters, 
whether there is a difference between the ASSURE and SPF 
networks in terms of the frequencies with which network 
perturbations would lead to substantially slower network 
induction or inability to induce. Across randomly parameter-
ized SPF and ASSURE models, the distribution of response 
times of the ASSURE model is significantly different (Po10 
À 4 ) 
than the distribution of response times of the SPF model, with 
the ASSURE model's t 0.5 distribution having a much smaller 
right tail (Figure 2I; Supplementary Figures 9A and B; 
Supplementary Table 1). Thus, randomly parameterized SPF 
networks were more likely to be slow at inducing (t 0.5 415 
min) than were ASSURE networks. The coefficient of variation 
of the ASSURE t 0.5 distribution was 21.4% lower than the 
coefficient of variation of the SPF t 0.5 distribution. Further-
more, across random parameterizations, the frequency with 
which the SPF model failed to respond was higher than for the 
ASSURE model (Supplementary Figure 9C). 
Next, to gain insight into the 'evolvability' of the motifs, 
we studied how random single parameter changes would 
affect the response times for the SPF and ASSURE models 
with randomly generated parameter sets. For each model 
class, an ensemble of models was generated by randomly 
generating vectors of parameter values (Supplementary 
Table 1), and the response time of each model in the ensemble 
was calculated. Then, for each model, a single parameter, 
selected at random, was perturbed by a random amount, to 
simulate a single evolutionary change, and the resulting 
change Dt 0.5 was calculated. This analysis revealed that 
the distribution of the Dt 0.5 values for the SPF model class 
had a markedly longer tail than the distribution for the 
ASSURE model class (Po10 
À 4 ), indicating that the response 
times of models of the ASSURE class are, overall, less affected 
by single parameter perturbations than models of the SPF 
class (Supplementary Figure 10A). Moreover, single-para-
meter perturbations in models of the SPF class were more 
likely to cause a failure to respond, than were single-parameter 
perturbations in models of the ASSURE class (Supplementary 
Figure 10B). 
Steady-state bifurcation analysis of the SPF and ASSURE 
models revealed that both models have parameter ranges in 
which they have bistable responses (which would correspond 
to heterogeneous responses across a cell population (Acar 
et al, 2005)); however, the ASSURE system shows bistability 
over a significantly smaller range of k a and K d parameter 
values compared to the SPF model (Supplementary Figure 11). 
This property of the ASSURE system may be indicative of 
additional advantages for this motif, namely, preserving the 
system's monostability and controllability, over a wide range 
of heterodimer affinities (K d ) and activities (k a ) that are subject 
to change during evolution. </p>

<p>ASSUREd network responses 
AV Ratushny et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2012 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>To experimentally validate the ASSURE network motif role, 
we compared the responses of a wild-type (WT) ASSURE I 
network (Figure 3A) and an engineered version that 
mimics the symmetric feedback network (Figure 3B and 
Supplementary Figure 12). The WT ASSURE I network forms 
the core of the fatty acid-responsive gene regulatory network 
in S. cerevisiae. A heterodimer of Oaf1p/Pip2p, is activated by 
the direct binding of oleate to the Oaf1p ligand binding domain 
and the activated Oaf1p/Pip2p heterodimer upregulates the 
expression of the PIP2 gene (Rottensteiner et al, 1997). In 
the engineered strain the OAF1 gene is placed under control of 
the PIP2 promoter so that it is also positively upregulated 
by the activated Oaf1p/Pip2p heterodimer, forming a 'sym-
metric' positive feedback loop (Figures 3B and C). The 
symmetric positive feedback type I (SPF I) model, the analog 
of the engineered experimental system, reproduces exactly the 
SPF model when the degradation rates are equal (k u 
P1 ¼ k u 
P2 ). 
While the kinetics of the SPF I model change relative to the SPF 
model when k u 
P1 ak u 
P2 , the characteristics of the response 
remain the same (Supplementary Figure 12). Thus, in these </p>

<p>models homo-and heterodimers can be treated equivalently 
within a set of given parameters. Oaf1p half-life is 55 min 
(Beyer et al, 2004) slightly more than that of Pip2p (40 min) 
(Belle et al, 2007). This difference in protein degradation is 
compensated for by the opposite differences in the half-lives of 
corresponding mRNAs (15 min for OAF1 mRNA and 22 min for 
PIP2 mRNA (Holstege et al, 1998)). The comparable levels of 
Oaf1p and Pip2p make the engineered strain a reasonable 
system to explore the symmetric feedback network. 
The oleate response of the WT and engineered strains was 
measured at the protein level using flow cytometry, replicated 
6 times over a matrix of varying conditions (Figure 3D and 
Supplementary Figure 13). Despite the potential for additional 
control mechanisms operating in the context of the larger 
cellular network, for example the differences in response times 
between the early log phase and mid/late log phase cultures 
(Supplementary Figure 13), the in vivo responses measured 
here mirrored the predictions from the model simulations 
discussed above. While both the ASSURE I and engineered 
'symmetric' feedback motifs yielded switch-like responses, </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>OAF1 </p>

<p>P OAF1 </p>

<p>Wild-type </p>

<p>PIP2 </p>

<p>P PIP2 </p>

<p>Heterodimer </p>

<p>Targets 
(e.g. POT1) </p>

<p>Oaf1p </p>

<p>Pip2p </p>

<p>Fatty 
acid </p>

<p>Heterodimer </p>

<p>Targets 
(e.g. POT1) </p>

<p>Oaf1p </p>

<p>Pip2p </p>

<p>Fatty 
acid </p>

<p>PIP2 </p>

<p>OAF1 </p>

<p>P PIP2 </p>

<p>P PIP2 </p>

<p>Engineered 
strain </p>

<p>hph </p>

<p>Anti-Oaf1p-myc </p>

<p>Anti-Gsp1p </p>

<p>Oleate: + -+ -+ -+ -</p>

<p>0 h 
1 h 
4 h 
6 h </p>

<p>Oleate, 0.2% 
Glucose, 0.15% </p>

<p>Time (h) 
0 
7 2 
24 
48 
WT+Eng 
YPD </p>

<p>WT+Eng 
hygromycin </p>

<p>WT+Eng 
YPD </p>

<p>WT+Eng 
hygromycin </p>

<p>WT+Eng 
YPD </p>

<p>WT+Eng 
hygromycin </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>Wild-type 
Engineered strain </p>

<p>Pot1p-GFP fluorescence intensity (a.u.) </p>

<p>Induction time (h) </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>21 22 </p>

<p>Figure 3 Experimental validation of the ASSURE network motif role. (A) Wild-type Oaf1p-Pip2p ASSURE network motif. (B) Engineered strain where the OAF1 gene 
is under control of the PIP2 promoter. (C) Oaf1p under the control of the PIP2 promoter is induced in response to oleate incubation. Samples were grown in YPB low 
glucose (0.15%) over a 6 h time course. Those samples to which 0.2% oleate was added show an increase in the amount of Oaf1p-myc detected by Western blot 
analysis relative to the uninduced sample. Gsp1p is used as a load control. (D) Response of the wild-type (diamonds) and engineered (dashes) budding yeast cells to 
oleate induction. The time course of Pot1p protein level was measured in individual cells using flow cytometry in the wild-type strain with a Pot1p-GFP reporter and in the 
engineered strain with the same reporter under oleate growth conditions. Error bars represent standard error of means of Pot1p-GFP protein level from six independent 
replicates. (E) The presence of the ASSURE network motif enables a competitive fitness advantage. Cells from wild type and engineered strains were mixed 1:1 and 
grown under time varying oleate and glucose conditions. At the indicated times cells were transferred between YPBO (0.2% oleate) and YPBD (0.15% glucose). At 24, 
48 and 72 h, multiple replicates of equal volumes of dilutions were plated onto YPD and YPD with 400 ug/ml Hygromycin B (Sigma) medium, to select for the engineered 
strain (see Material and Methods). Source data is available for this figure in the Supplementary Information. </p>

<p>ASSUREd network responses 
AV Ratushny et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2012 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2012 5 </p>

<p>the ASSURE I motif yielded a response that was more rapid 
(t 0.2 B3 h) and controlled, whereas the engineered motif led to 
a slower response (t 0.2 B8 h) and to the overproduction of the 
target protein (Figure 3D). 
To address the role of the ASSURE motif in the context of a 
cellular phenotype we hypothesized that the altered kinetics of 
the transcriptional response would result in a decreased 
competitive advantage of the engineered strain. To test this 
hypothesis we performed fitness assays in which the wild type 
and engineered strains were co-cultured in conditions that 
alternated between oleate and glucose carbon sources 
(Figure 3E). An advantage of this experimental design is that 
it is internally controlled; both strains are co-subjected to the 
same experimental conditions (see Materials and Methods). 
The engineered strain was specifically disadvantaged under 
oleate growth conditions compared to the wild type strain 
(Figure 3E) while under glucose growth conditions no fitness 
disadvantage for the engineered strain was observed 
(Supplementary Figure 14). In an environment that is switch-
ing back and forth between oleic acid as the sole carbon source 
and glucose as sole carbon source, the organism has to 
repeatedly activate the peroxisome biogenesis gene regulatory 
network and induce peroxisomes. We interpret these data to 
indicate that the kinetics of the response conferred by the 
ASSURE motif endow the system with a fitness advantage, 
contributing to its use and evolutionary persistence in a wide 
range of organisms and regulatory networks. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Here, we theoretically and experimentally investigated dyna-
mical properties of the highly prevalent ASSURE network 
motif, which lies at the heart of numerous networks 
controlling many essential biological functions. In the ASSURE 
motif, a heterodimer forms in response to a signal to regulate 
the activity of downstream targets; one component of the 
heterodimer acts as a sensor of the signal, and one (and only 
one) component is also the target of feedback regulation by the 
heterodimer itself. This motif confers numerous fundamental 
properties including precise, tunable and robust control of 
responses to environmental stimuli and is central to many 
different biological processes (Table I). It seems likely that this 
is because of the properties we have exposed here. For 
example, RAR binding to retinoic acid induces formation of the 
nuclear receptor RAR/RXR heterodimer, which in turn 
regulates numerous aspects of vertebrate morphogenesis, 
growth, cellular differentiation, and tissue homeostasis 
(Mark et al, 2006). The regulatory circuit is predicted to be 
robust and controlled, ensuring the appropriate execution of 
developmental programs. 
In the immune system, the host innate response is often 
considered a double-edged sword (Kobayashi and Flavell, 
2004; Liew et al, 2005). A rapid host defense against harmful 
pathogens is essential, but at the same time, if the immune 
response is unregulated, the overproduction of proinflamma-
tory cytokines may result in inflammation-associated sequelae 
(Kobayashi and Flavell, 2004). IRF3 and IRF7 are central 
regulators of certain chemokine genes and type I interferon 
(INF) genes that are essential for host antiviral response </p>

<p>(Janeway and Medzhitov, 2002; Tamura et al, 2008); IRF3 and 
IRF7 form an ASSURE motif. IRF3 levels are constitutive, 
whereas IRF7 is expressed at a low level under normal 
conditions (Honda and Taniguchi, 2006; Tamura et al, 2008). 
When activated, an IRF3/IRF7 heterodimer forms leading to 
the upregulation of the type I interferons IFN-a and IFN-b, 
triggering a positive-feedback upregulation of IRF7, which in 
turn leads to the full induction of type I IFN genes during the 
host antiviral response (Tamura et al, 2008). While in this case 
the activation occurs through phosphorylation, and feedback 
on IRF7 occurs indirectly by interferons, the essential features 
of the motif remain. The system response is predicted to be 
reliably controlled, which is critical for balanced yet rapid, 
antiviral and inflammatory responses. 
Importantly, the ASSURE network motif 'buffers against' 
variations in the affinity between partners in the heterodimer. 
This buffering feature of the motif can enable the evolution of 
new activities and partners through gene duplication. In 
principle both proteins of a heterodimer in the ASSURE 
network motif can bind ligands, which could, in turn, alter the 
affinity of the heterodimer. For example, PPAR/RXR hetero-
dimers can be activated by PPAR or RXR ligands (Westin et al, 
1998) and even if different ligands alter the K d of the 
heterodimer (Yue et al, 2005) the ASSURE network behavior 
would remain essentially unchanged. 
On the other hand, the control and robustness of the 
ASSURE system are highly sensitive to the abundance of the 
protein that is not subject to feedback upregulation, with 
increased abundance leading to stronger responses. From an 
evolutionary standpoint there are many factors that can 
operate to control levels of the constitutive protein (synthesis, 
turnover, localization etc.). We expect that these factors 
contribute in combination to control and buffer systems that 
contain the ASSURE network motif. Indeed in our experi-
mental exploration of induction parameters by flow cytometry 
(Supplementary Figure 13), we identified conditions that 
change the response types within the predicted range of 
profiles (Figure 3 and Supplementary Figures 12). In addition, 
the ASSURE network motif properties discovered here are 
applicable to any combinatorial up or down regulatory event 
where two or more factors are involved, including cofactors/ 
coactivators, and at least one component is not subject to 
feedback, but feedback is dependent on that component. 
Investigation of the ASSURE network in the model system of 
yeast responding to oleate demonstrated that this network 
contributes to a fitness advantage, which at least partially 
explains its prevalence and reuse in many biological systems. 
Comparing the dynamics of transcription from the natural 
ASSURE network and the engineered SPF validated the 
predictions made from in silico studies. Specifically, a key 
difference between these motifs is the response times upon 
induction with oleate. These altered transcriptional rates likely 
result in a fitness disadvantage through a multitude of 
downstream effects such as delayed organelle biogenesis, 
potential increases in reactive oxygen species at early time 
points or a potential increase in the translational burden at 
later time points. Accordingly, delayed expression of targets of 
Oaf1p and Pip2p, conferred by, for example deletion of the 
histone variant Htz1 (Wan et al, 2009; Saleem et al, 2010) leads 
to a delay in biogenesis and reduced viability in oleate </p>

<p>ASSUREd network responses 
AV Ratushny et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2012 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>conditions (Smith et al, 2006; Lockshon et al, 2007). Another 
key difference between these motifs is the ability to control the 
level of the response. More of the reporter protein, Pot1p-GFP, 
was observed in the engineered strain at later stages of 
induction, which may also underlie the oleate specific 
competitive disadvantage of this strain. Regardless, the relative 
poor performance of cells in which the ASSURE network has 
been replaced is founded in differences in transcription, with 
the ASSURE motif contributing to fast response times and 
constraining the level of the system response. 
Understanding the dynamical properties of the ASSURE 
network motif also has value in rational drug design and 
development of optimal treatment procedures. For example, 
PPARg, a nuclear receptor which forms an ASSURE network 
motif in combination with RXR, has been implicated in the 
pathology of numerous diseases including atherosclerosis, 
diabetes and cancer and is a prominent and widely studied 
drug target (Varga and Nagy, 2008). We predict, based on this 
study, that PPARg/RXR-based responses would be relatively 
insensitive to drug concentration differences, and as concen-
trations of a drug or other xenobiotics increase, the core 
PPARg/RXR-based response would be similar. In addition, we 
expect that the core PPARg/RXR-based response would be 
tolerant to the introduction of a drug that affects the affinity 
between PPARg and RXR. 
The persistence of the ASSURE network motif through 
evolution and its central role in many diverse regulatory systems 
are evidence of the advantages conferred by the dynamical 
features we describe here. Moreover, as biological regulatory 
systems are increasingly harnessed in synthetic biology applica-
tions, the precise control and robustness of the ASSURE network 
motif make it an attractive tool for synthetic molecular 
regulatory systems with predetermined and tunable functions. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Strain construction </p>

<p>An engineered cassette consisting of the HPH gene amplified from the 
pFA6a-hphNT1 (Janke et al, 2004), and a 500 bp region upstream from 
the start of the PIP2 ORF, which herein is described as the PIP2 
promoter, was constructed by assembly PCR (Supplementary Table 2). 
This cassette contained 40 bp of homology facilitating integration of 
the construct into the OAF1 5 
0 UTR and OAF1 ORF. Correct integration 
of the engineered promoter was confirmed by both diagnostic PCR and 
DNA sequencing. 
Positive clones containing the OAF1 ORF under the control of the 
PIP2 promoter were then transformed with a PCR cassette which 
incorporates GFP at the 3 
0 end of the oleate responsive gene POT1. The 
functionality of this construct was tested by inducing the cells with 
oleate and observing the GFP signal by flow cytometry and the 
localization of Pot1p-GFP to peroxisomes by fluorescence microscopy. 
Construction of the wild-type Pot1p-GFP strain was described 
previously (Saleem et al, 2008). The wild type and engineered strains 
are genetically identical, with the exception of the insertion of the PIP2 
promoter at the 5 
0 end of the OAF1 ORF (and an HPH drug resistance 
gene upstream of the ectopic PIP2 promoter) in the engineered strain, 
which generates the SPF I topology (Supplementary Figure 12) with 
respect to the oleate responsive transcription factors, Oaf1p and Pip2p. 
OAF1 was genomically tagged by homologous recombination, using 
an integration cassette with OAF1 3 
0 ORF and 3 
0 UTR homology 
(Supplementary Table 2), amplified from the pFA6-13MYC plasmid 
(Wan et al, 2009). Correct integration of the myc tag was confirmed by 
both diagnostic PCR and DNA sequencing. </p>

<p>Cell culture, protein extraction and western blot 
analysis </p>

<p>Cells were grown overnight in YPBD (0.3% yeast extract, 0.5% 
peptone, 0.5% potassium phosphate buffer, pH 6.0, 2% glucose) to an 
OD 600 of approximately 1.0. For protein extractions, cells were 
transferred to YPB-low glucose (0.15%) and either grown in YPB-low 
glucose (0.15%) only or induced with 0.2% oleate, 0.5% Tween 40. 
Samples were collected at the indicated times (Figure 3C), the media 
removed and the cells resuspended in a lysis solution of 264 mM NaOH, 
152 mM 2-mercaptoethanol. After a 10 min incubation on ice, 
tricholoracetic acid was added to a final concentration of 6% and 
proteins precipitated for 10 additional minutes on ice. Precipitated 
proteins were pelleted by centrifugation and resuspended in a solution 
of 6.5% SDS, 0.5 M Tris base and 15% glycerol. The samples were 
heated at 95 1C and proteins resolved on 4-12% gradient gels. Myc-
tagged Oaf1p was detected by western blot analysis using an anti c-Myc 
9E10 mouse monoclonal antibody (Abcam). An anti Gsp1p rabbit 
polyclonal antibody was used to detect Gsp1p as a load control. </p>

<p>Flow cytometry </p>

<p>Six replicates of each strain were assayed over a matrix of experimental 
conditions, varying pre-culture conditions (2% glucose or 0.15% 
glucose), cell densities (OD 600 of 0.4, 0.8, or 1.6) and oleate 
concentrations (0.2% or 1%) (Supplementary Figure 13). At the 
indicated time points (Figure 3D and Supplementary Figure 13), 20 ml 
of induced cells were added to 100 ml of dH 2 O in a 96-well flat-
bottomed plate and analyzed by flow cytometry for total GFP 
fluorescence. Flow cytometry was done using a FACSCalibur (BD 
Biosciences) with the following parameters: forward scatter, E0 
haploid linear scale; side scatter, 520 V linear scale; fluorescence, 
490 V logarithmic scale. Cells were loaded onto the FACSCalibur using 
the high throughput sampler (BD Biosciences). The high throughput 
sampler was run in standard mode, sampling 10 ml at a rate of 2 ml/s for 
a total event count of 10 000 cells. </p>

<p>Competition assay </p>

<p>The competitive fitness of the wild type versus the engineered strains 
was investigated under time varying oleate and glucose conditions. 
Cells from wild type and engineered strains were mixed 1:1 and grown 
in YPD to an OD 600 of approximately 0.5. At the times indicated in 
Figure 3E, cells were transferred between YPBO and YPBD (0.15% 
glucose). At 0, 24, 48 and 72 h, the cultures were sampled and then 
reseeded at 1:5 to ensure they did not reach saturation. For sampling, 
10 technical and two biological replicates of equal volumes of dilutions 
were plated onto YPD, which is nonselective and allows both strains to 
grow equally, and YPD with 400 ug/ml Hygromycin B (HPH; Sigma) 
medium, to select for the engineered strain. Under conditions in which 
the engineered strain showed no advantage or disadvantage the 
expected number of colonies on the YPD-HPH plate would be half of 
the number of colonies on the YPD plate. </p>

<p>Mathematical modeling </p>

<p>The ordinary differential equations for the 'No feedback', symmetric 
and asymmetric feedback systems are as follows: 
'No feedback' model: </p>

<p>dg </p>

<p>dt ¼ k s f ðdðdðs; P; K sp Þ; dðs; P; K sp Þ; K d ÞÞ À k u g; 8g 2 Target 
f 
g </p>

<p>dP </p>

<p>dt ¼ 0 </p>

<p>( </p>

<p>; </p>

<p>SPF model: </p>

<p>dg 
dt 
¼ k s f ðdðdðs; P; K sp Þ; dðs; P; K sp Þ; K d ÞÞ À k u g; 8g 2 P; Target 
f 
g ; </p>

<p>ASSURE I model: </p>

<p>dg </p>

<p>dt ¼ k s f ðdðdðs; P 1 ; K sp Þ; P 2 ; K d ÞÞ À k u g; 8g 2 P 2 ; Target 
f 
g </p>

<p>dP1 </p>

<p>dt ¼ 0 </p>

<p>( </p>

<p>; </p>

<p>ASSUREd network responses 
AV Ratushny et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2012 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2012 7 </p>

<p>ASSURE II model: </p>

<p>dg </p>

<p>dt ¼ k s f ðdðdðs; P 1 ; K sp Þ; P 2 ; K d ÞÞ À k u g; 8g 2 P 1 ; Target 
f 
g </p>

<p>dP2 </p>

<p>dt ¼ 0 </p>

<p>( </p>

<p>; </p>

<p>SPF I model (see Supplementary Figure 12): </p>

<p>dg 
dt 
¼ k s f ðdðdðs; P 1 ; K sp Þ; P 2 ; K d ÞÞ À k u g; 8g 2 P 1 ; P 2 ; Target 
f 
g ; </p>

<p>where d(x, y, K) represents the quasi-steady-state concentration of the 
heterodimer between x and y with the dissociation constant K 
calculated using the following equation: </p>

<p>dðx; y; KÞ ¼ 
K 
2 
1 þ 
x þ y 
K 
À </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi </p>

<p>1 þ 
x þ y 
K </p>

<p>
2 
À 
4xy 
K 2 </p>

<p>r 
! </p>

<p>: </p>

<p>d(x, y, K) is a solution of the quadratic equation (x À d) (y À d) ¼ Kd 
that is derived from the steady-state assumption for the reversible 
biomolecular reaction x þ y , </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>d. In the case of a homodimer, x ¼ y. 
f(z) represents a fractional activity of the target gene which is a 
function of the activator z. f(z) is calculated using the following 
equation: </p>

<p>f ðzÞ ¼ </p>

<p>k 0 þ </p>

<p>z 
ka </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>1 þ </p>

<p>z 
ka </p>

<p>h : </p>

<p>For example, f(d(d(s,P 1 ,K sp ),P 2 ,K d )) represents the fractional activity 
of the ASSURE target gene that is a function of the concentration of the 
heterodimer between P 2 and another heterodimer between s and P 1 in 
the model with K d and K sp dissociation constants, respectively. 
Parameter values for results presented in Figure 2 are following: 
k s ¼ 10 min 
À 1 , k u ¼ 0.1 min 
À 1 , k 0 ¼ 0.1, k a ¼ 40 a.u., h ¼ 2, K sp ¼ 10 </p>

<p>À 3 </p>

<p>a.u., K d ¼ 10 
À 5 a.u., s ¼ 10 
3 a.u. The unregulated component of the 
heterodimer (P 1 in ASSURE I and P 2 in ASSURE II) is set to a 
corresponding constant value. The Equations were solved numerically 
with Matlab 7.9.0. The models are available in SBML format at 
BioModels database (http://www.ebi.ac.uk/biomodels-main/) (SPF 
ID: MODEL1203010000; ASSURE I ID: MODEL1203010001; ASSURE II 
ID: MODEL1203010002; 'No Feedback' ID: MODEL1203010003; SPF I 
ID: MODEL1203010004). </p>

<p>Computational analysis </p>

<p>The response time (t x ) was calculated as the time that the system takes 
to reach x portion of its response between the initial and steady-state 
levels. A P-value for the comparison of the distributions of t 0.5 values 
for the SPF and ASSURE models in Figure 2I was calculated based on 
the two-sample Kolmogorov-Smirnov test using the kstest2 <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> 
routine. The response time probability density in Figure 2I was 
estimated using the ksdensity <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> routine. </p>

<p>Supplementary information </p>

<p>Supplementary information is available at the Molecular Systems 
Biology website (www.nature.com/msb). </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank J Smith, V Litvak and I Shmulevich for helpful discussions 
and comments on the manuscript. This study was supported by NIH/ 
NIGMS (R01-GM075152, U54-2U54RR022220 and P50-GM076547). 
Author contributions: AVR and JDA designed the research. AVR 
developed mathematical models and performed numerical simula-
tions. AVR and SAR performed theoretical and computational analysis. 
RAS and KS built the engineered strain and performed experiments. 
AVR, RAS, SAR and JDA wrote the manuscript. </p>



<p>ASSUREd network responses 
AV Ratushny et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2012 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>



<p>ASSUREd network responses 
AV Ratushny et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2012 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2012 9 </p>

</text></tei>