<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3915115" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:42+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Older women have lower breast cancer surgery rates than younger women. UK policy states that differences in 
cancer treatment by age can only be justified by patient choice or poor health. </p>

<p>Methods: We investigate whether lack of surgery for older patients is explained by patient choice/poor health in a prospective 
cohort study of 800 women aged X70 years diagnosed with operable (stage 1-3a) breast cancer at 22 English breast cancer units 
in 2010-2013. Data collection: interviews and case note review. Outcome measure: surgery for operable (stage 1-3a) breast cancer 
o90 days of diagnosis. Logistic regression adjusts for age, health measures, tumour characteristics, socio-demographics and </p>

<p>patient's/surgeon's perceived responsibility for treatment decisions. </p>

<p>Results: In the univariable analyses, increasing age predicts not undergoing surgery from the age of 75 years, compared with 
70-74-year-olds. Adjusting for health measures and choice, only women aged X85 years have reduced odds of surgery (OR 0.18, 
95% CI: 0.07-0.44). Each point increase in Activities of Daily Living score (worsening functional status) reduced the odds of surgery 
by over a fifth (OR 0.23, 95% CI: 0.15-0.35). Patient's role in the treatment decisions made no difference to whether they received 
surgery or not; those who were active/collaborative were as likely to get surgery as those who were passive, that is, left the 
decision up to the surgeon. </p>

<p>Conclusion: Lower surgery rates, among older women with breast cancer, are unlikely to be due to patients actively opting out of 
having this treatment. However, poorer health explains the difference in surgery between 75-84-year-olds and younger women. 
Lack of surgery for women aged X85 years persists even when health and patient choice are adjusted for. </p>

<p>Older women experience higher incidence and worse survival for 
breast cancer compared with younger women. Incidence doubles 
from 202 out of 100 000 for women aged 45-49 to 409 out of 
100 000 for those aged X85 years (England 2009) (ONS, Office of 
National Statistics, 2011). Relative five year breast cancer survival 
decreases with age from 89% for 40-49-year-olds to 69% for </p>

<p>women aged X80 years, a drop not seen in the United States and 
Western European countries (Coleman et al, 2011; Cancer 
Research UK, 2012). The King's Fund indicates that improved 
management of older cancer patients could increase cancer survival 
in England (Foot and Harrison, 2011), and it has been estimated 
that more than 14 000 cancer deaths could be avoided each year in </p>

<p>*Correspondence: Dr K Lavelle; E-mail: katrina.j.lavelle@manchester.ac.uk </p>

<p>Received 25 September 2013; revised 23 October 2013; accepted 30 October 2013; 
published online 28 November 2013 </p>

<p>&amp; 2014 Cancer Research UK. All rights reserved 0007 -0920/14 </p>

<p>FULL PAPER </p>

<p>Keywords: breast cancer; older; patient choice; co-morbidity; health status </p>

<p>British Journal of Cancer (2014) 110, 573-583 | doi: 10.1038/bjc.2013.734 </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.734 
573 </p>

<p>the UK for people aged X75 years if our mortality rates matched 
those of the USA (Moller et al, 2011). 
Previous studies demonstrate significant and substantial 
differences in the management of older women with breast 
cancer compared with younger women (Bouchardy et al, 2007;  Louwman et al, 2007). Older women are less likely to be managed 
in line with the treatment guidelines. Specifically, they are less 
likely to undergo primary surgery and are also less likely to 
have follow-up adjuvant treatments such as radiotherapy and 
chemotherapy (Wyld et al, 2004; Giordano et al, 2005; Naeim  et al, 2006; Lavelle et al, 2007b). Around 60% of women aged 
X80 years in England do not have surgery for breast cancer 
compared with o10% of younger age groups (Lavelle et al,  2007a,b, 2012; Lawrence et al, 2011). 
There are many reasons why treatment could vary with age, but 
UK national cancer strategy has identified 'patient choice' and 
'poor health' as the only 'acceptable' reasons for older breast cancer 
patients not receiving clinically appropriate treatment (DH,  Department of Health, 2007, 2011). A systematic review comparing 
surgery plus endocrine therapy with endocrine alone in women 
aged X70 years concludes that surgery should only be omitted in 
women who are 'unfit for, or refuse, surgery' (Hind et al, 2007,  p 1029). A recent UK Parliamentary Inquiry into older age and 
breast cancer states that 'the pressing question is whether the 
reduced level of treatment observed in older breast cancer patients 
is justified' and highlights that adjusting for patients' co-
morbidities and frailty would help establish whether older people 
with breast cancer are being 'inappropriately undertreated' (APPGBC, 
All Party Parliamentary Group on Breast Cancer, 2013, p 17). 
Our previous studies suggest that older women in the UK are 
receiving non-standard treatment for breast cancer for reasons 
other than having poorer general health (Lavelle et al, 2007b,  2012), as defined by co-morbidity and increasing dependence in 
Activities of Daily Living (ADL) (functional status). Patients aged 
X80 years, attending breast cancer units in Greater Manchester 
between 2002-2003, had 44 times the odds of not receiving surgery 
for operable breast cancer compared with patients aged 65-79 
years, controlling for co-morbidity and functional status (Lavelle  et al, 2007a). Several national policies, guidelines (DH, Department  of Health, 2000, 2007, 2011) and initiatives (MacMillan Cancer 
Support, Age UK and the Department of Health, 2012) have 
specifically addressed the issue of access to treatment for older 
cancer patients. This may well have increased surgical rates among 
older cancer patients over the last decade. Using routine 
registration data we recently investigated over 23 000 women aged 
X65 years, registered with breast cancer in Northern Yorkshire 
and West Midlands, and showed surgery rates rose from 67.4% in  1997-1999 to 75.1% in 2003-2005 (Lavelle et al, 2012). After 
adjustment for co-morbidity, older age still predicted lack of 
surgery. Compared with 65-69-year-olds, the odds of surgery 
decreased from 0.74 (95% CI: 0.66-0.83) for 70-74-year-olds to 
0.13 (95% CI: 0.11-0.14) for women aged X85 years. However, co-
morbidity is likely to be underestimated as the routine data sources 
are limited to inpatient stays only. Moreover, no data on wider 
measures of health such as patient frailty or functional status are 
routinely collected in the UK, so could not be included. Functional 
status has been shown to vary independently from co-morbidity 
(Extermann et al, 1998) and has been found to account for some of 
the difference in surgical treatment between younger and older 
breast cancer patients (Lavelle et al, 2007a). 
One explanation for differences in the treatment is that older 
women may choose non-standard treatment (e.g., decline surgery). 
No measure of patient choice was adjusted for in these previous 
UK studies. Tang et al (2011) found that of women aged X70 
years, diagnosed with early stage breast cancer in Nottingham 
(England), who were offered a choice between surgery or treatment 
with hormone therapy, 58.9% did not have surgery. However, </p>

<p>no adjustment was made for age and health in multivariable analysis. 
The residual variation in access to surgery, not explained by choice 
and health, could therefore not be estimated. Taking account of 
patient preference in multivariate models has been attempted in 
two US studies (Silliman et al, 1997; Mandelblatt et al, 2000). Both 
adjusted for physical health status as measured by the Short Form-
36 (Ware et al, 2002) and whether treatment options had been 
offered/discussed. However, older age remained the strongest 
predictor of not receiving standard treatment, after adjusting for 
these measures of patient health and choice. The generalisability of 
these results to the UK is limited by differences between the health 
care systems and survival rates (Coleman et al, 2008). Moreover, 
even when a treatment choice is offered, the patient could defer to 
the doctor's advice. There is evidence that older women with breast 
cancer prefer (and are more likely) to do this (Degner et al, 1997), 
suggesting that non-standard management of older women is more 
likely to be the result of the doctor's rather than the patient's 
decision. This needs to be tested in a study in which perceptions of 
responsibility for the treatment decision for non-standard manage-
ment are also measured and adjusted for. 
The current study therefore investigates the extent to which the 
lack of surgery for older patients is justified by patient choice or 
poor health and, thereby, whether (and if so the extent to which) 
'inappropriate undertreatment' (as defined by national policy) 
occurs among older breast cancer patients in the UK. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study design. This is a prospective, cohort study of a consecutive 
series of women diagnosed with operable (stage 1-3a) breast 
cancer attending 22 breast cancer units predominantly in North-
west England, over a period of 33 months. Data on patient 
preferences, tumour characteristics, general health and treatment 
were collected by patient interviews and case note review. The 
primary outcome measure is primary surgery for operable (stage 
1-3a) breast cancer within 3 months of diagnosis. Explanatory 
variables adjusted for include age, measures of health, patient 
choice, tumour characteristics, demographics and hospital resources. </p>

<p>Measures of health. Reflecting WHO's definition of health as 
'a state of complete physical, mental and social well-being and not 
merely the absence of disease and infirmity' (WHO, 1948), a range 
of health measures, representing patient's functional/health status 
and Health Related Quality of Life (HRQoL) in addition to co-
morbidity and other clinical measures, were considered. Measures 
have primarily been selected based on ease of administration, 
validity, reliability, acceptability to older people (Sturgis et al, 2001;  Haywood et al, 2004), and prediction of non-standard manage-
ment (Lavelle et al, 2007a) and/or treatment outcomes (Audisio  et al, 2005). Measures include: Elderly Population Health Status 
Survey's (ELPHS) ADL (Sharples et al, 2000) functional status 
measure, Short Form-12 (SF-12) (Ware et al, 2002) health status 
measure, European Organisation for Research and Treatment of 
Cancer EORTC-C30 measure of HRQoL (Osoba et al, 1997), 
Eastern Co-operative Oncology Group-Performance Status (Oken  et al, 1982), 6 item Cognitive Impairment Test (6CIT) (Brooke and  Bullock, 1999), smoking status, body mass index (Bertin et al, 1998;  Sorensen et al, 2002) and Charlson Index of Co-morbidity 
(Charlson et al, 1987). </p>

<p>Patient choice. The Control Preferences Scale (CPS) has a 
component Perception Scale (Degner et al, 1997; Janz et al,  2004), which we used to examine the extent to which older patients 
were given and made the choice of whether or not to have surgery 
from the perspective of both the patients and their surgeons. The 
CPS Perception Scale measures perceptions of responsibility for the 
treatment decision (see Table 1), presenting the patient/surgeon </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Breast surgery and older patients' choice/health </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.734 </p>

<p>with five corresponding response alternatives along a continuum, 
from the patient to the doctor solely making the treatment 
decision. The Patient Perception Scale is used to elicit patients' 
perceptions of who made the decision of whether or not to have 
surgery. In a subgroup, we also use the Physician Perception Scale 
to investigate surgeons' perceptions of the same decision for the 
same consultations (Janz et al, 2004). The patient can then be 
classified as passive (i.e., surgeon made decision) vs collaborative/ 
active (i.e., patient shared in or made decision). The scale can only 
be applied to consultations where a treatment option has been 
considered. An additional category of 'not discussed' is therefore 
also included. </p>

<p>Tumour characteristics. Pre-treatment assessments of tumour 
characteristics, tumour size, stage, nodal and steroid receptor status 
were recorded based on clinical, imaging and fine needle/core 
biopsy assessments (cTNM (UICC, 2009)). </p>

<p>Socio-demographics. Socio-economic class is measured using the 
National Statistics Socio-Economic Classification (ONS, Office of 
National Statistics, 2013) and based on the main occupation pre-
retirement if retired and the highest classification if the participant 
was married or living with a partner. Ethnicity was recorded based 
on the census classification categories (ONS, Office of National 
Statistics, 2010). </p>

<p>Study population. Of the 22 breast cancer units in the study 19 
are based in the North West of England, 2 in London and 1 in the 
Midlands. Surgeons' views of the surgical treatment decisions were 
also collected after each relevant consultation in a subgroup of 12 
breast cancer units only, mainly based in Greater Manchester. The 
restriction of this subset was largely due to the feasibility of 
obtaining surgeons' views within a manageable geographical area. </p>

<p>Inclusion criteria </p>

<p>Women. Men were not included as o1% of all invasive breast 
cancer occurs in men (ONS, Office of National Statistics, 2011) and 
surgical management differs (SIGN, Scottish Intercollegiate  Guidelines Network, 2005; ABS at BASO, Association of Breast 
Surgeons at British Association of Surgical Oncologists, 2009; 
NICE, National Institute for Clinical Excellence, 2009). </p>

<p>Aged X70 years. Previous studies suggest that odds of not 
receiving surgery significantly increase from age 70 (Lavelle et al, 
2012). Women aged 70-74 years are included as a reference group. </p>

<p>Diagnosed with a new episode of operable invasive breast cancer 
(stage 1-3a). Carcinoma in situ, stage 3b, metastatic and recurrent 
breast cancers are not included as the standards for operable breast 
cancer do not apply (SIGN, Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines 
Network, 2005; ABS at BASO, Association of Breast Surgeons at 
British Association of Surgical Oncologists, 2009; NICE, National 
Institute for Clinical Excellence, 2009). </p>

<p>Screening and accrual. The study was phased in at 16 sites from 
July 2010 to October 2010 and 6 sites joined the study later. 
Recruitment ended in sites from October 2012 to April 2013. At 10 
sites we recruited patients from age 65 years to take part in a 
further study of diagnostic tests and follow-up treatments. Apart 
from the lower age limit, the studies are identical and we include 
patients aged X70 in this paper. During the recruitment period 
2631 patients were screened for eligibility, 1923 approached by the 
Trust staff to take part in the study and 1004 recruited (52%). 
Following initial recruitment, 200 patients were excluded 
(Figure 1). For a further four patients we were unable to obtain 
case notes for review, leaving 800 included patients aged X70 
years. </p>

<p>Data collection. Eligible patients were identified at diagnosis by 
Multi-Disciplinary Team meetings, clinic lists and hospital 
computer systems by research nurses. A patient information pack 
was given to patients in clinic and followed up by telephone call. 
Patients who agreed to take part were interviewed within 30 days of 
diagnosis and (if they were having surgery) before surgery took 
place. The interview comprised demographic variables and 
measures of health as detailed above. CPS cards elicited patients' 
perceived role in the surgical decision. In 12 of the 22 sites 
surgeons' perceptions (CPS) were also recorded. In these sites 
following a consultation, in which the decision for surgery or not 
was taken for each eligible patient, the surgeon completed the CPS 
scale (Table 1). The case notes of each patient were reviewed at 3 
months post-diagnosis, or later, using a proforma developed to 
collect data on tumour characteristics at diagnosis, treatments 
undertaken and co-morbidity. Inter-rater agreement levels for the 
proforma all satisfied kappa 40.6 indicating substantial to perfect 
agreement (Landis and Koch, 1977). Three per cent of case note 
review proformas and 8% of patient interviews were tested for data 
input errors. Error rates per data item inputted were o0.5% so no 
further data-checking was required. </p>

<p>Sample size. In order to test whether patients' health and role in 
the surgical treatment decision predicts surgery among women </p>

<p>Table 1. Control preferences scale </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Option 
Physician perception scale </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Patient perception scale </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>A 
The patient made the final decision about which treatment she would receive. I made the final decision about which treatment I would receive. </p>

<p>B 
The patient made the final decision about which treatment she would receive 
after seriously considering my opinion. </p>

<p>I made the final decision about 
d my treatment after seriously </p>

<p>considering my doctor's opinion. </p>

<p>C 
I shared responsibility with the patient for making the final decision about the 
treatment she would receive. </p>

<p>My doctor and I shared responsibility for deciding which 
treatment was best for me. </p>

<p>D 
I made the final decision about which treatment the patient would receive after 
seriously considering the patient's opinion. </p>

<p>My doctor made the final decision about which treatment would 
be used but seriously considered my opinion. </p>

<p>E 
I made the final decision about which treatment the patient would receive. 
My doctor made the final decision about which treatment I would 
receive 
e . </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Degner et al (1997). </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Janz et al (2004). </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Modified from Janz et al (2004). </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>'Selection of' changed to 'decision about' to correspond more closely with other responses and scales. </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>'All the decisions regarding my treatment' changed to ' the final decision about which treatment I would receive' to correspond more closely with Physicians Perception Scale and to avoid 
patient confusion, that is, referring to the treatment decision for surgery vs no surgery not the treatment decision for type of surgery. </p>

<p>Breast surgery and older patients' choice/health 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.734 </p>

<p>
aged X70 with operable breast cancer, the recommended sample 
size is determined by the number of explanatory variables included 
in the logistic regression model predicting surgery in order to avoid 
over-specification. For reliable modelling, logistic regression should 
have at least 10 cases for each explanatory variable for both 
categories of a binary dependant variable (Peduzzi et al, 1996;  Bland, 2005). The main limiting factor is therefore the number of 
patients not receiving primary surgery for operable breast cancer 
(17% in our previous study (Lavelle et al, 2007a) -a 1 : 4.9 ratio of 
no surgery to surgery). To have at least 10 times as many cases as 
variables for patients not receiving surgery, we therefore need 110 
patients not receiving surgery to allow a maximum of 11 
explanatory variables. This requires 539 patients receiving surgery 
and thus the rule-of-thumb recommends having at least 649 
patients in the final model. </p>

<p>Analyses. Explanatory variables were investigated in univariable 
analysis using Pearson's w 
2 test, Fisher's exact test, w 
2 test for trend 
and univariable logistic regression analyses to generate odds ratios 
(two tailed with a ¼ 0.05). The distribution of continuous variables 
was assessed for normality using the Shapiro-Wilk W-test. 
Associations between non-normal variables and surgery/age group 
were investigated using the non-parametric two-sample Wilcoxon 
rank sum (Mann-Whitney test) and Kruskal-Wallis equality-of-
populations rank test, respectively. Associations for parametric 
variables were investigated using the two-sample t-test. 
Indicators of standard management found to be significantly 
associated with surgery in univariable analyses were used as 
independent variables in the subsequent logistic regression 
(forward stepwise). The model was built in line with our Data 
Analyses Plan agreed a priori with the project's Independent Data 
Monitoring Committee modifying an approach suggested by 
Hosmer and Lemeshow (2000). A base model containing explanatory </p>

<p>variables of primary clinical importance to the study was 
constructed including age group, patient role in surgical decision 
and co-morbidity (as the only measure of pre-existing disease). 
The remaining explanatory variables were considered unless the 
significant effect was only in the 'missing' category of data. 
Variables were considered in three groups and added into the 
model in order of importance to the primary aim of the study, that 
is, health measures, tumour characteristics and then socio-
demographics. Within each group the order in which variables 
were added into the model was determined by Bayesian 
Information Criterion (BIC) values of each variable added into 
the model individually. Variables with lower BIC values were 
added in sequentially starting with the variable giving the lowest 
value. At each step an individual variable's contribution to the 
model was assessed using two criteria: (1) the difference between 
the model with the additional variable and the previous model 
using the Likelihood Ratio Test (a.k.a. analysis of deviance) and 
(2) producing a significant coefficient in the model (both at a 5% 
significance level). In order to reduce the likelihood of multi-
collinearity and to ensure the number of cases in the model could 
sustain the potentially high number of health measures, they were 
only retained in the model if they produced both a significant 
coefficient and likelihood ratio test. Tumour characteristics and 
socio-demographic variables were retained if they had a significant 
likelihood ratio test only. Once each group of variables had been 
added variance inflation factors were checked and variables 
exhibiting factors above 10 removed to prevent multicollinearity 
(Kutner et al, 2004). 
In order to retain sufficient number of cases to support the 
subgroup analysis, which includes surgeons' perceptions in a 
nested model, all variables with non-significant coefficients were 
removed from the final main model. In addition one health 
measure was selected and retained as representative of the 
remaining health measures. Both the main and nested models 
were tested for goodness of fit (Hosmer &amp; Lemeshow) and 
discrimination (area under receiver operating characteristic curve). 
Data were analysed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">STATA</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">12</rs>. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Sample characteristics. Eight hundred women were included, 
of whom 83.0% (664) had surgery (95% CI: 80.4-85.6%) and 48.0% 
had a Charleson co-morbidity score of X1 (95% CI: 44.5-51.5%). 
Ages ranged from 34% aged 70-74 years, 30% 75-80 years, 19% 
80-84 years to 17% aged X85 years (Table 2). The sample was 
predominantly of professional/intermediate social class and white 
ethnic group. Over half were treated at a district general hospital 
rather than a university teaching hospital. The majority of 
participants (62.4%) believed that the option of having surgery 
(vs not having surgery) was not discussed with them. Of the 35.2% 
who felt it was discussed, nearly twice as many identified 
themselves as active/collaborative vs passive in making this 
decision. Conversely, 62.2% of surgeons indicated that the option 
of no surgery vs surgery was discussed with the patient. More than 
double the proportion of surgeons identified patients as active/ 
collaborative in this decision (52.8%) than patients did themselves 
(22.9%). Of the 480 patients for whom the surgeon CPS was not 
missing, 473 had a corresponding patient CPS referring to 
the same index consultation (Table 3). Of these, in 249 cases the 
patient and the surgeon selected the same option regarding the 
patient's role in the surgical decision (52.6%) giving a kappa value 
of 0.261, indicating fair agreement (Landis and Koch, 1977). 
The majority of disagreement is due to the 123 cases (26.0%) in 
which the patient felt the option of surgery vs no surgery was not 
discussed but the surgeon felt that it was and that the patient was 
active/collaborative in this discussion. </p>

<p>Number of patients screened 
n=2631 </p>

<p>Number of patients approached 
n=1923 </p>

<p>Number of patients recruited 
n=1004 
52% response rate </p>

<p>Final sample 
n=800 </p>

<p>Excluded (204) 
-Metastatic disease (7) 
-Inoperable advanced (29) 
-Carcinoma in situ only (13) 
-Recurrent breast cancer (4) 
-Private treatment (2) 
-Died &lt;90 days of diagnosis and pre-surgery (1) 
-Aged 65-69 (n=144) 
-No case notes available for review (4) </p>

<p>Figure 1. Recruitment and retention of patients in the study. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Breast surgery and older patients' choice/health </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.734 </p>

<p>Just over 40% of the sample were recorded with stage I disease at 
diagnosis; 58.3% were stage II or IIIa and were hence regarded as 
having early operable breast cancer (SIGN, Scottish Intercollegiate  Guidelines Network, 1998) (Table 4). Over two thirds of the sample 
(70.1%) had no nodal involvement recorded at diagnosis and over 
half the sample had small tumours of p20 mm (53.9%). The vast 
majority of participants were steroid receptor positive for either 
oestrogen or progesterone receptors (85.5%). </p>

<p>Univariable analysis. Only 57.3% of patients aged X85 years 
underwent surgery for their operable breast cancer compared with 
93.5% of women aged 70-74 years (Po0.001) (Table 2). The 
proportion undergoing surgery was over 8% less among manual 
socio-economic classes compared with professional/intermediate </p>

<p>participants (P ¼ 0.030). Surgical rates ranged across the 22 sites 
from 67.7-96.4%, but this difference was not statistically significant 
(Fisher-Freeman-Halton Exact, P ¼ 0.139). There was a slight 
but significantly greater surgical rate in university/teaching hospitals 
(87.0%) compared with district general hospitals (80.2%) (P ¼ 0.012). 
Participants were less likely to get surgery if they presented with 
later stage (P ¼ 0.003) larger (P ¼ 0.003) breast tumours (Table 4). 
Mean difference in tumour size was 2.99 mm between patients 
having surgery (21.28 mm) vs not having surgery (24.27 mm) 
(two-sample t-test with equal variance P ¼ 0.011). Participants 
were more likely to have surgery if they were negative for oestrogen 
and/or progesterone steroid receptors. 
All of the self reported measures of health demonstrate significantly 
worsening health with increasing age (Table 5). Participants aged X85 </p>

<p>Table 2. Socio-demographics, and role in surgical decision, by surgery </p>

<p>Variable 
Category 
n 
Percent 
No. surgery 
Per cent surgery 
P </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Age group (years) 
70-74 
275 
34.4 
257 
93.5 
75-79 
236 
29.5 
201 
85.2 
80-84 
151 
18.9 
127 
84.1 
85 þ 
138 
17.3 
79 
57.3 
o0.001 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Socio-economic classification 
Professional 
421 
52.6 
358 
85.0 
Intermediate 
198 
24.8 
169 
85.4 
Manual 
171 
21.4 
131 
76.6 
0.030 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Missing 
10 
1.3 
6 
60.0 
0.015 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Ethnicity 
White 
769 
96.1 
643 
83.6 
Other 
18 
2.3 
14 
77.8 
0.519 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Missing 
13 
1.6 
7 
53.9 
0.020 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Hospital type 
Teaching/Uni 
330 
41.3 
287 
87.0 
District 
470 
58.8 
377 
80.2 
0.012 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Patient's view of their role in decision: 
Active/collab 
183 
22.9 
124 
67.8 
surgery vs no surgery CPS 
Passive 
98 
12.3 
64 
65.3 
Not discussed 
499 
62.4 
460 
92.2 
o0.001 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Missing 
20 
2.5 
16 
80.0 
o0.001 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Surgeon's view of patient's role in 
Active/collab 
292 
52.8 
224 
76.7 
decision: surgery vs no surgery CPS 
Passive 
52 
9.4 
41 
78.9 
(base for % n ¼ 553) </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Not discussed 
136 
24.6 
129 
94.9 
o0.001 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Missing 
73 
13.2 
59 
80.8 
o0.001 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Not included </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>247 
na 
na 
na </p>

<p>Total 
800 
100% </p>

<p>Abbreviation: CPS ¼ Control Preferences Scale. *P-values for each variable for complete data reported first followed by data including missings if relevant. 
P-values o0.05 are shown in bold. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>w 
2 squared test for trend. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>w 
2 squared Pearson. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Fisher's exact test. </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Surgeons' views only taken in the nested study. </p>

<p>Table 3. Patients' vs surgeons' views of patient's role in decision to have surgery or not </p>

<p>Surgeon's view of patient's role in surgical decision </p>

<p>Patient's view of their role in surgical decision 
Active/collaborative 
Passive 
Not discussed 
Total </p>

<p>Active/collaborative 
126 
8 
9 
143 </p>

<p>Passive 
37 
11 
15 
63 </p>

<p>Not discussed 
123 
32 
112 
267 </p>

<p>Total 
286 
51 
136 
473 </p>

<p>Agreement ¼ 52.6%, Kappa ¼ 0.261, Po0.001. Agreed values shown in bold italics. </p>

<p>Breast surgery and older patients' choice/health 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.734 </p>

<p>
years were more likely to have difficultly or need help with ADL 
(Po0.001) with over 50% of this age group, also having a ECOG 
performance status of 2 or more, compared with 21-37% of 
younger women (Po0.001). The proportion experiencing mild to 
moderate cognitive problems according to the <rs type="software">6CIT</rs> screening tool 
was over twice as large among women aged X85 years (30.1%) 
compared with younger age groups (p14%) (Po0.001). Body 
mass index reduced with age (Po0.001) and a greater proportion 
of those aged over 80 years were non-smokers compared with younger 
women (P ¼ 0.008). There was over a 10% increase in the proportion 
scoring 1 or more on the Charlson co-morbidity index: from 41.1% 
of 70-74-year-olds to 52.9% of X85-year-olds (P ¼ 0.016). 
All measures of health were significantly associated with receipt 
of surgery (Table 5), with poorer health decreasing the likelihood 
of undergoing surgery. Over two thirds of those not undergoing 
surgery had a co-morbidity score of 1 or more compared with 
44.0% of surgical patients. Those not receiving surgery were also 
more likely to need help with ADL (Po0.001) with 63.4% of these 
non-surgical patients having a ECOG performance status score of 2 
or more compared with 26.4% of women having surgery 
(Po0.001). Non-surgical patients also had a slightly lower body 
mass index (P ¼ 0.006) and were more likely to smoke (P ¼ 0.007). </p>

<p>Multivariable analysis. A logistic regression analysis was carried 
out to investigate whether age is a predictor of primary surgery for 
operable breast cancer. There was no significant difference between 
the observed and values predicted by the final model (goodness 
of fit test w 
2 (Hosmer-Lemeshow) ¼ 5.88: d.f. ¼ 8; P ¼ 0.661) 
and model discrimination (AUC ¼ 0.871) considered excellent 
(Hosmer and Lemeshow, 2000). The results of the univariable 
and main multivariable regression model are shown in Table 6. </p>

<p>In univariable analysis, the odds of receiving surgery diminished 
substantially with increasing age, for all age groups with women 
aged 75-79 years having 0.40 (95% CI: 0.22-0.73) the odds of 
surgery compared with women aged 70-74 years. After controlling 
for the effect of patient choice, health and tumour characteristics 
only the oldest age group had significantly reduced odds of surgery 
with women aged X85 years having just over one fifth of the odds 
of receiving surgery compared with 70-74-year-olds (OR 0.21, 95% 
CI: 0.10-4.46). Women perceiving themselves as passive in the 
decision of whether or not to have surgery had the same chance of 
having surgery as women adopting an active role. However, those 
reporting that the choice between surgery and no surgery was not 
discussed with them had over three and a half times the odds of 
having surgery compared with women who said this option was 
discussed (OR 3.54, 95% CI: 1.97-6.37). Although co-morbidity 
had a significant effect in the univariable analyses, once other 
health measures were adjusted for, the effect of co-morbidity lost 
significance. Conversely, EORTC quality of life measure, ELPHS 
ADL functional status measure and smoking status produced 
significant effects in the main model with poorer health predicting 
lack of surgery. For example, for each point increase on the 1-4 
ADL scale, indicating poorer functional status/decreasing inde-
pendence, the odds of surgery reduce by over a third (OR 0.36, 95% 
CI: 0.24-0.55). Also non-smokers have over two and a half times 
the odds of undergoing surgery compared with smokers (OR 2.60, 
95% CI: 1.18-5.73). The tumour characteristics of oestrogen/ 
progesterone steroid receptor positivity and tumour size showed a 
significant effect in the univariable analyses, but this did not 
remain once the other explanatory variables were adjusted for. 
Surgeon's perception of patient role in the decision of whether 
or not to have surgery was significant in the univariable analyses </p>

<p>Table 4. Tumour characteristics at diagnosis by surgery </p>

<p>Variable 
Category 
n 
Percent 
No. surgery 
Percent surgery 
P* </p>

<p>Stage 
I 
334 
41.8 
293 
87.7 
II and IIIa </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>466 
58.3 
371 
79.6 
0.003 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Nodes involved 
Yes 
239 
29.9 
197 
82.4 
No/NR 
561 
70.1 
467 
83.2 
0.778 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Tumour size 
p20 mm 
431 
53.9 
374 
86.8 
420p50 mm 
329 
41.1 
260 
79.0 
450 mm 
22 
2.8 
15 
68.2 
0.003 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Missing 
18 
2.3 
15 
83.3 
0.007 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Grade 
1 
138 
17.3 
112 
81.2 
2 
428 
53.5 
348 
81.3 
3 
168 
21.0 
145 
86.3 
0.213 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Missing 
66 
8.3 
59 
89.4 
0.220 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Oestrogen receptor ER status 
Positive 
667 
84.6 
549 
81.1 
Negative 
85 
10.6 
79 
92.9 
0.006 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Missing 
38 
4.8 
36 
94.7 
0.002 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Progesterone receptor PR status 
Positive 
523 
65.4 
417 
79.7 
Negative 
188 
23.5 
166 
88.3 
0.008 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Missing 
89 
11.1 
81 
91.0 
0.002 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>ER or PR positive 
Yes 
684 
85.5 
555 
81.1 
No 
72 
9.0 
68 
94.4 
0.003 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Missing 
44 
5.5 
41 
93.2 
0.002 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Total 
800 
100% </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ER ¼ oestrogen receptor; PR ¼ progesterone receptor; NR ¼ not reported. P-values o0.05 are shown in bold. *P-values for each variable for complete data reported first followed by 
data including missings if relevant. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Includes 17 patients with stage IIIa. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>w 
2 squared test for trend. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>w 
2 squared Pearson. </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Fisher's exact test. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Breast surgery and older patients' choice/health </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.734 </p>

<p>(Table 7). Similar to the patients' perception measure, if surgeons 
perceived that the option of surgery (vs no surgery) was not 
discussed, the patient had over five and a half times the odds of 
having surgery (OR 5.59, 95% CI: 2.49-12.55). However, after 
adjusting for the other explanatory variables, this effect failed to 
retain significance. Owing to the smaller sample size available to 
this subgroup analyses, all non-significant variables were dropped 
and, of the health measures, only ELPHS ADL was retained as this 
produced the strongest effect in the main model. The addition of 
surgeons' perceptions in this nested model does not alter much the 
effect of age on chance of surgery. After adjusting for patient 
choice, as well as functional health status, women aged X85 years 
still have around a fifth of the odds of surgery compared with 
70-74-year-olds (OR 0.18, 95% CI: 0.07-0.44). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this prospective cohort study of 800 women aged X70 years 
diagnosed with invasive operable breast cancer, women aged X85 </p>

<p>years were less likely to have surgery adjusting for the effects of 
patient health and choice. The reduction in surgical rates with 
increasing age demonstrated in this study is in broad agreement 
with previous studies both in the UK (Golledge et al, 2000; Wyld  et al, 2004; Lavelle et al, 2007a,b, 2012) and elsewhere (Hillner et al,  1996; Giordano et al, 2005; Naeim et al, 2006). However, previous 
studies reporting unadjusted surgical rates demonstrate reduced 
odds of surgery from the age of 70 years and older (Bastiaannet  et al, 2010; Lawrence et al, 2011; Tang et al, 2011); a pattern also 
demonstrated in our unadjusted odds reported here. Once patient 
health and choice were adjusted for, both the location and size of 
effect changed. Although the pattern of decreased odds of surgery 
with increasing age remained, only the oldest women aged X85 
years retained significantly reduced odds of surgery; around a fifth 
for adjusted odds compared with those aged 70-74-year-olds vs a 
tenth for unadjusted odds. However, neither patient health nor 
choice accounts for the lack of surgery for the oldest women aged 
X85 years. 
This reduction in effect size, to the point of non-significance, for 
75-84-year-olds appears to be largely driven by adjustment for 
measures of health rather than patient choice. In the main and </p>

<p>Table 5. Health measures by age and surgery </p>

<p>Measure 
Age (years) 
Scores 
P* 
Surgery 
Scores 
P* </p>

<p>ELPHS ADL self report 1-4 inc ¼ worse 
70-74 
1.44 (1.37-1.51) 
Yes 
1.57 (1.52-1.62) 
75-79 
1.72 (1.63-1.81) 
No 
2.42 (2.30-2.55) 
o0.001 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>80-84 
1.77 (1.66-1.87) 
85 þ 
2.20 (2.07-2.32) 
o0.001 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>SF12 PCS self report 1-100 inc ¼ better 
70-74 
46.83 (45.38-48.28) 
Yes 
45.02 (44.10-45.95) 
75-79 
42.59 (40.84-44.33) 
No 
32.43 (30.15-34.70) 
o0.001 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>80-84 
41.47 (39.53-43.40) 
85 þ 
37.88 (35.63-40.13) 
o0.001 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>EORTC QLQ self report 1-100 inc ¼ better 
70-74 
72.59 (70.12-75.05) 
Yes 
69.83 (68.13-71.52) 
75-79 
63.93 (60.41-67.44) 
No 
48.23 (43.67-52.79) 
o0.001 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>80-84 
63.41 (59.74-67.09) 
85 þ 
61.89 (57.75-66.04) 
o0.001 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>PS self report 0-4 categories, inc ¼ worse, %41 
70-74 
20.97 (16.06-25.89) 
Yes 
26.36 (22.95-29.77) 
75-79 
31.90 (25.85-37.94) 
No 
63.36 (55.00-71.72) 
o0.001 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>80-84 
36.99 (29.06-44.91) 
85 þ 
52.67 (44.01-61.34) 
o0.001 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>6CIT (0-28) inc ¼ worse, %47 i.e., mild/mod cog impair 
70-74 
10.89 (7.06-14.73) 
Yes 
12.79 (10.10-15.49) 
75-79 
12.02 (7.56-16.48) 
No 
25.00 (16.54-33.46) 
0.002 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>80-84 
13.85 (7.83-19.86) 
85 þ 
30.10 (21.09-39.11) 
o0.001 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Body mass index 
70-74 
28.46 (27.76-29.17) 
Yes 
27.90 (27.48-28.31) 
75-79 
28.25 (27.49-29.00) 
No 
26.60 (25.50-27.69) 
0.006 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>80-84 
27.29 (26.56-28.02) 
85 þ 
25.54 (24.70-26.38) 
o0.001 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Smoking status (% non-smokers) 
70-74 
87.96 (84.08-91.83) 
Yes 
92.15 (90.09-94.20) 
75-79 
88.94 (84.90-92.98) 
No 
84.09 (77.77-90.41) 
0.007 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>80-84 
96.67 (93.76-99.57) 
85 þ 
93.33 (89.07-97.60) 
0.008 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Charlson co-morbidity, %X1 
70-74 
41.09 (35.24-46.94) 
Yes 
43.98 (40.19-47.76) 
75-79 
51.27 (44.85-57.69) 
No 
67.65 (59.68-75.61) 
o0.001 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>80-84 
50.99 (42.93-59.06) 
85 þ 
52.90 (44.47-61.33) 
0.016 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Abbreviations: 6CIT ¼ 6-Item Cognitive Impairment Test (scale 0-28: increase indicates worse cognitive impairment, 0-7 indicates normal); ECOG-PS ¼ Eastern Co-operative Oncology Group -
Performance Status (0-5 categories indicate decreasing functional status); ELPHS ADL ¼ Elderly Population Health Status Survey's Activity of Daily Living (scale 1-4: increase indicates worse 
functional status); EORTC QLQ-C30 ¼ European Organization for Research on Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire (version 3) Global Quality of Life scale 1-100 (increase indicates 
better health related quality of life); SF-12 ¼ Short Form-12 Physical Component Summary (scale 1-100: increase indicates better health status). Values for scores are mean (95% confidence 
interval) unless indicated otherwise. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mann-Whitney. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Kruskal-Wallis w </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Fisher's exact. </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>w 
2 for trend. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>All P-values are o0.05. </p>

<p>Breast surgery and older patients' choice/health 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.734 </p>

<p>
nested models only whether or not the patient perceived the 
surgical treatment decision was discussed remained significant. 
Measuring and adjusting for patient choice in terms of responsi-
bility for treatment decisions builds on previous research, which 
either simply records whether a treatment option was offered or 
whether 'patient choice' is listed as a reason for lack of treatment in 
case notes. As Hamaker et al (2013), point out this latter approach 
is flawed because 'what is stated to be the patient's preference could 
in fact be a reflection of the physician's preference' (p550). In our 
prospective cohort we measure responsibility for the surgical 
treatment decision from both the surgeon's and the patient's 
perspective using the previously validated CPS (Degner et al, 1997). 
On the basis of responses to the CPS there is no evidence that there 
was active choice not to have surgery among those who did not 
have surgery. These findings suggest that the lack of surgery for the 
oldest patients is not due to them actively opting out of having this 
treatment. However, actually having the discussion about not 
having/having surgery is associated with reduced likelihood of 
receiving surgery. Tang et al (2011) also found that 58.9% (66 out 
of 112) breast cancer patients aged 470 years did not go on to 
have surgery after being offered a choice of this or treatment with 
hormone therapy. A likely explanation for this is that the option of 
not having surgery is only offered/discussed if there are concerns 
about the patient undergoing surgery. 
Among the measures of heath, the strongest predictor of 
undergoing surgery was the functional status measure of ADL. 
Activities of Daily Living has been shown in previous studies to </p>

<p>predict access to and outcomes from surgery in terms of 
complications and HRQoL (Extermann and Hurria, 2007;  Lavelle et al, 2007a; Audisio et al, 2008; Pal et al, 2010). ADL 
measures the ability to function independently in everyday life 
and is a consistent component of the Comprehensive Geriatric 
Assessment; a battery of varying health status and functional tests 
recommended by the International Society for Geriatric Oncology 
as an essential element of treatment decision making for older 
cancer patients (Biganzoli et al, 2012). The European Organisation 
for Research and Treatment of Cancer also states that 'main-
tenance of function and independence should be one of the major 
principles of cancer management in the elderly' (Pallis et al, 2010). 
The strength of ADL's prediction of having surgery, both in this 
and previous studies, suggest that maintenance of independence is 
a pivotal consideration for older patients contemplating surgery. 
The ECOG PS scale also measures functional status and has 
been shown to predict surgical outcomes for older cancer patients 
(Audisio et al, 2008). With the added attraction of brevity (5 items 
vs 18 in the ELPHS ADL), it is collected by some NHS breast care 
teams as part of the Cancer Outcomes and Services Dataset (NCIN,  National Cancer Intelligence Network, 2013). However, although 
ECOG PS was associated with surgery in the univariable analyses, 
its effect lost significance once ELPHS ADL along with other 
measures of health were adjusted for. Previous studies suggest that 
ECOG PS may lack sensitivity as although 70-80% of older adults 
with cancer present with an ECOG PS of 0-1 (indicating at least 
capable of all basic self-care), greater than half require assistance </p>

<p>Table 6. Multivariable (main) logistic regression of receiving primary surgery (vs not receiving primary surgery) (n ¼ 674) </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Unadjusted odds 
ratio 
95% CI 
P-value* </p>

<p>Adjusted odds 
ratio </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>95% CI 
P-value* </p>

<p>Age group </p>

<p>70-74 
(ref) 
-
-
(ref) 
-
-
75-79 
0.40 
0.22-0.73 
0.003 
0.69 
0.32-1.50 
0.354 
80-84 
0.37 
0.19-0.71 
0.003 
0.54 
0.24-1.20 
0.131 
85 þ 
0.09 
0.05-0.17 
o0.001 
0.21 
0.10-0.46 
o0.001 </p>

<p>Patient's views on role CPS </p>

<p>Active/collab 
(ref) 
-
-
(ref) 
-
-
Passive 
0.90 
0.53-1.50 
0.677 
0.89 
0.44-1.81 
0.750 
Not discussed 
5.61 
3.58-8.81 
o0.001 
3.54 
1.97-6.37 
o0.001 </p>

<p>Co-morbidity </p>

<p>0 
(ref) 
-
-
(ref) 
-
-
1 þ 
0.38 
0.25-0.55 
o0.001 
0.61 
0.36-1.05 
0.075 </p>

<p>EORTC QLQ 1-100 scale inc ¼ better 
1.04 
1.03-1.05 
o0.001 
1.02 
1.01-1.03 
0.005 </p>

<p>ELPHS ADL 1-4 scale inc ¼ worse 
0.20 
0.15-0.27 
o0.001 
0.36 
0.24-0.55 
o0.001 </p>

<p>Smoking </p>

<p>Smoker 
(ref) 
-
-
(ref) 
-
-
Non-smoker 
2.22 
1.29-3.83 
0.004 
2.60 
1.18-5.73 
0.018 </p>

<p>ER or PR </p>

<p>Positive 
(ref) 
-
-
(ref) 
-
-
Negative 
3.95 
1.42-11.03 
0.009 
2.82 
0.86-9.25 
0.086 </p>

<p>Tumour size (mm) 
0.98 
0.97-1.00 
0.013 
1.00 
0.98-1.02 
0.695 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI ¼ confidence interval; CPS ¼ Control Preferences Scale; ELPHS ADL ¼ Elderly Population Health Status Survey's Activity of Daily Living; EORTC QLQ ¼ European Organization 
for Research on Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire; ER ¼ oestrogen receptor; PR ¼ progesterone receptor. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Health measures 6CIT, BMI and ECOG performance status were not included as there was no significant effect in the initial multivariable model. SF12 PCS was removed as it produced 
VIFs410. Tumour stage, nodal status, socio-economic classification and type of hospital treated at were removed as they did not significantly improve the fit of the model. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Adjusted for all other variables in the table. All variance inflation factors o10. Goodness of fit test w 
2 Hosmer-Lemeshow ¼ 5.88: d.f. ¼ 8; P ¼ 0.661. Area under receiver operator characteristics </p>

<p>curve ¼ 0.871. *P-values o0.05 are shown in bold. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Breast surgery and older patients' choice/health </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.734 </p>

<p>with the more advanced/instrumental ADLs such as housework, 
meal preparation and shopping (Extermann, 2000; Pal et al, 2010). 
ADL therefore is more likely to have sufficient sensitivity 
to identify patients on the threshold of needing additional help 
to maintain independence. At the point of making the decision to 
have surgery or not, this may enable post-surgical-care packages to 
be put in place pre-operatively if necessary. 
Although co-morbidity was associated with surgery in univari-
able analyses, its effect lost significance in the main multivariable 
model adjusting for other measures of health. Co-morbidity has 
been found to predict lack of treatment in several previous studies 
of older women with breast cancer (Ballard-Barbash et al, 1996;  Hérbert-Croteau et al, 1999; Giordano et al, 2005; Naeim et al,  2006; Lavelle et al, 2012). However, this is by no means a universal 
finding (Hillner et al, 1996; Silliman et al, 1997; Mandelblatt et al,  2000; Lavelle et al, 2007a), particularly in studies, which also 
adjusted for measures of functional/health status (Silliman et al,  1997; Mandelblatt et al, 2000; Lavelle et al, 2007a). This suggests 
that measures of functional/health status may have a stronger 
bearing on treatment decision making than co-morbidity for older 
breast cancer patients. This may particularly be the case for long 
standing chronic co-morbidities, such as diabetes or asthma, which 
may be well managed and therefore have little impact on everyday 
function or indeed the decision to have surgery for breast cancer 
or not. 
There is some evidence that surgical rates are improving for 
older women with breast cancer in the UK. The overall surgical 
rate in the study reported here (83.0% in 2010-2013) would fall in 
line with the increase over time reported in our previous study 
based on cancer registry data, from 67.4% in 1997-1999 to 75.1%  in 2003-2005 (Lavelle et al, 2012). Although this may, in part, 
reflect improving completeness of treatment data, increasing 
surgical rates over time have also been reported in national audits 
(NCASP, National Clinical Audit Support Programme, 2009). 
It therefore seems likely that the improved surgical rates also 
demonstrate changes in practice, reflecting the guidelines that were 
published and the major reorganising of cancer services over the </p>

<p>last 15 years (DH, Department of Health, 2000, 2007; ABS at 
BASO, Association of Breast Surgeons at British Association of 
Surgical Oncologists, 2009; NICE, National Institute for Clinical 
Excellence, 2009; DH, Department of Health, 2011). 
Compared with all breast cancers registered in England in 2011 
our sample under represented women aged X85 years, that is, 
26.0% nationally (ONS, Office of National Statistics, 2011) 
compared with 17.3% (95% CI: 14.7-20.0%) in the study reported 
here. This may be due to the exclusion of advanced/inoperable 
breast cancer in our sample as older patients are more likely to 
present at a later stage at which the tumour is advanced/inoperable 
(Ramirez et al, 1999). However, the under-representation of older 
patients is also likely to be due in part to selection bias, as 
participants needed to be capable of consent and be interviewed in 
order to take part in the study. Nevertheless, the proportion of 
patients having a Charleson co-morbidity score of X1 (48.0%, 95% 
CI: 44.5-51.5%) is similar to that found in previous studies, which 
measure breast cancer patients co-morbidity prospectively (Ring  et al, 2011; Lavelle et al, 2012). For example, Ring et al found 44.5% 
(95% CI: 41.6-47.5%) of patients aged X70 years taking part in the 
ATAC trial had a Charleson score of X1. Similarly, our estimates 
of ADL are in line with our own (Lavelle et al, 2007a) and others 
(Sharples et al, 2000) estimates in studies of older adults living in 
the community. However, these previous studies are likely to be 
subject to the same influence of selection bias and it is probable 
that older women unable to consent/take part in an interview 
would have poorer health than younger ones who can. Selection 
bias towards younger and probably physically healthier women 
may have limited the generalisability of the study. Yet the results 
still clearly demonstrated a reduction in standard surgery for 
women aged X85 years. A larger sample including older less 
healthy women would have been expected to increase the 
association between increasing age and non-standard management 
of breast cancer. 
In this study the lack of surgery for 75-84-year-olds could be 
explained by differences in health status. However, once health 
measures as well as patient role in treatment decision were adjusted </p>

<p>Table 7. Multivariable (nested) logistic regression of receiving primary surgery (vs not receiving primary surgery) adjusting for surgeons' views on role of 
patient in surgical decision (n ¼ 473) </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Unadjusted odds 
ratio 
95% CI 
P-value* </p>

<p>Adjusted odds 
ratio </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>95% CI 
P-value* </p>

<p>Age group </p>

<p>70-74 
(ref) 
-
-
(ref) 
-
-
75-79 
0.40 
0.22-0.73 
0.003 
0.60 
0.25-1.48 
0.267 
80-84 
0.37 
0.19-0.71 
0.003 
0.48 
0.19-1.21 
0.118 
85 þ 
0.09 
0.05-0.17 
o0.001 
0.18 
0.07-0.44 
o0.001 </p>

<p>Patient's view of role CPS </p>

<p>Active/collab 
(ref) 
(ref) 
-
-
Passive 
0.90 
0.53-1.50 
0.677 
0.70 
0.30-1.62 
0.404 
Not discussed 
5.61 
3.58-8.81 
o0.001 
2.69 
1.34-5.39 
0.005 </p>

<p>Surgeon's view of role CPS </p>

<p>Active/collab 
(ref) 
-
-
(ref) 
-
-
Passive 
1.31 
0.55-2.32 
0.736 
0.64 
0.24-1.66 
0.355 
Not discussed 
5.59 
2.49-12.55 
o0.001 
2.37 
0.93-6.04 
0.072 </p>

<p>ELPHS ADL 1-4 scale inc ¼ worse 
0.20 
0.15-0.27 
o0.001 
0.23 
0.15-0.35 
o0.001 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI ¼ confidence interval; CPS ¼ Control Preferences Scale. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Co-morbidity, ER/PR and tumour size were not included as there was no significant effect in the main multivariable model. ELPHS ADL was retained as it showed the strongest effect among 
the health measures with significant effect in the main model. EORTC QLQ and smoking status were therefore not included. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Adjusted for all other variables in the table. All variance inflation factors o10. Goodness of fit test w 
2 Hosmer-Lemeshow ¼ 10.90: d.f. ¼ 8; P ¼ 0.208. Area under receiver operator characteristic </p>

<p>curve ¼ 0.869. *P-values o0.05 are shown in bold. </p>

<p>Breast surgery and older patients' choice/health 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.734 </p>

<p>
for, women aged X85 years were still less likely to have surgery. 
Although surgical rates for older breast cancer patients appear to 
be increasing, lack of surgery for women aged X85 years persists 
even when health and patient choice are adjusted for. These 
findings suggest that, as defined by national policy, 'inappropriate 
undertreatment' is still occurring for this oldest age group in 
the UK. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This study was funded by the Breast Cancer Campaign 
(2008NOVPR35), a National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) 
Programme Grant for Applied Research (RP-PG-0608-10168) and 
independent research arising from a Post Doctoral Fellowship 
supported by the NIHR (PDF/01/2008/027). The views expressed 
in this publication are those of the authors and not necessarily 
those of the NHS, the National Institute for Health Research or the 
Department of Health. We would like to thank the women who 
took part in this study and research assistants Noshaba Anwar, 
Lorie Dickinson, Kirsty Ewing, Nisha Patel, Emma Rhodes, 
Georgina Pennington-Smith, Bernhard Wagner and Rosie Perry. 
We are also grateful for the participation of the 22 breast clinics 
and the help of the co-ordinating sites (St Helens and Knowsley 
Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust and University Hospital of South 
Manchester NHS Foundation Trust). Ethical approval was granted 
by the National Research Ethics Service (10/H1014/32 &amp; 33). </p>



<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Breast surgery and older patients' choice/health </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.734 </p>



<p>Breast surgery and older patients' choice/health 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.734 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>