<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3255244" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:49+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>mutants, we developed a novel monoclonal 
antibody that recognizes the N-terminal cytoplasm region of 
CD20 molecule. We screened L26-negative cases with our 
antibody and found several mutations. A rituximab-binding 
analysis using the cryopreserved specimen that mutation was 
identified in CD20 molecules indicated that the C-terminal 
region of CD20 undertakes a critical role in presentation of the 
large loop in which the rituximab-binding site locates. Thus, 
combination of antibodies of two kinds of epitope permits the 
identification of C-terminal CD20 mutations associated with 
irreversible resistance to rituximab and may help the decision 
of the treatment strategy. 
Previously, we reported that gene mutations of CD20 were 
somehow involved in resistance to rituximab therapy, and we 
proposed that C-terminal deletion mutations of CD20 might be 
related to relapse/resistance after rituximab therapy. 
1 Many of 
these C-terminal truncated CD20 molecules were not recog-
nized by the L26 monoclonal antibody used routinely in most 
clinical laboratories. Therefore, expression of CD20 seemed to 
have been completely lost for these lymphomas. However, an 
immunohistochemical study using a polyclonal antibody 
showed that some kind of C-terminal truncated CD20 was 
present in cytoplasm, so it was possible that the epitope of L26 
was lost by gene mutations. 
1 L26 recognizes the cytoplasmic 
region of CD20 molecules, but no more detailed information 
about its epitope had been reported. 
2,3 In this study, we 
determine a recognition site of L26 by using a series of deletion 
mutants of CD20 molecules. In addition, to detect every one of 
the mutated CD20 molecules, we developed new antibodies </p>

<p>that recognize the N-terminal region of CD20 molecules. We 
used these antibodies to identify cells that have CD20 molecules 
with abnormalities in the C-terminal cytoplasmic region. We 
characterized these mutated CD20 molecules using living 
primary lymphoma cells. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Cells, viruses and DNA constructs </p>

<p>The coding region of the CD20 gene was amplified by reverse 
transcription PCR (RT-PCR) from RNA extracted from a Burkitt's 
lymphoma cell line, Raji, and was cloned into a pDON-AI 
retroviral vector (Takara, Ohtsu, Japan). A series of deletion 
mutants of CD20 in the C-terminal cytoplasmic region was 
constructed by inserting stop codons after nucleotides encoding 
E281, E263, E245, V228 and G210. Retroviruses carrying wild 
type and deletion mutants of CD20, together with mock 
construct, were produced with the transient retrovirus packaging 
cell line G3T-hi (Takara) according to the manufacturer's 
protocol. Packaged retrovirus vectors were then used to infect 
a myeloma cell line, KMS12PE, 
4 with subsequent selection 
using 500 mg/ml G418. 
For the transfection of mutant CD20 gene, whole coding 
region of CD20 complementary DNA (cDNA) prepared by 
RT-PCR of total RNA isolated from the patient cells was cloned 
into first cassette of a bicistronic retrovirus vector carrying a 
green fluorescent protein (Takara). Bicistronic expression of 
ZsGreen is facilitated by internal ribosomal entry site only when 
CD20 mutant gene was translated, enabling the efficient 
selection of transformed cells. </p>

<p>Generation of monoclonal antibody secreting 
hybridomas </p>

<p>A synthetic peptide corresponding to residues 23-36 of human 
CD20 with one additional cysteine at the N-terminus 
(CMQSGPKPLFRRMSS) was synthesized. The peptide was 
coupled with keyhole limpet hemocyanin. BALB/c mice were 
primed with a subcutaneous injection of the keyhole limpet 
hemocyanin-conjugated synthetic peptide emulsified in 
Freund's complete adjuvant. Mice were boosted four times at 
two-week intervals with the same antigen. Mice that developed 
antibodies as measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay 
with the immunizing peptide were boosted intravenously with 
the same peptide 4 days before splenocytes were harvested and 
fused to mouse myeloma cells. Hybridization and cloning were 
performed according to standard procedures. </p>

<p>5   CD20 gene sequencing </p>

<p>Pleural effusion mononuclear cells were obtained by density 
gradient centrifugation using Ficoll-Hypaque 1.077 (Sigma, </p>

<p>Received 28 October 2010; revised 7 January 2011; accepted 
1 February 2011 </p>

<p>Correspondence: Dr K Hatake, Department of Clinical Oncology and 
Hematology, Cancer Institute Hospital, Japanese Foundation for 
Cancer Research, 3-8-31, Ariake Koto-ku, Tokyo 135-8550, Japan. 
E-mail: khatake@jfcr.or.jp </p>

<p>Citation: Blood Cancer Journal (2011) 1, e15; doi:10.1038/bcj.2011.11 
&amp; 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited All rights reserved 2044-5385/11 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/bcj </p>

<p>St Louis, MO, USA). The isolated mononuclear cells then 
underwent negative immunomagnetic selection using a B Cell 
Isolation Kit II (Miltenyi Biotec, Bergisch Gladbach, Germany) 
for purifying B-linage cells. Total RNA was prepared using 
TRIzol reagent according to the instructions of the manufacturer 
(Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) and 1 mg was subjected to 
reverse transcription under MMLV reverse transcriptase 
(Takara). To prepare cDNA-containing whole coding region of 
CD20, PCR amplification was performed from 2 ml of cDNA 
using primers outside of the start and the stop codon: hCD20-5 
0 -
FW (5 
0 -GCAGCTAGCATCCAAATCAG-3 
0 ) and hCD20-3 
0 -RV 
(5 
0 -TGGTGCGTATGTGCAGAGTA-3 
0 ). To determine the se-
quence of the CD20, we performed cycle sequencing on a 
3130 DNA analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA), 
directly from PCR-purified products, in both directions using a 
BigDye Terminator Cycle Sequencing Kit v3.1 (Applied Biosystems). </p>

<p>Immunocytochemistry </p>

<p>Cells were stained by rituximab and L26 antibody (DAKO, 
Carpentaria, CA, USA) sequentially. Briefly, the cells were 
labeled by incubating in 10 mg/ml of rituximab conjugated with 
Alexa Fluor 647 (Invitrogen) according to previously described 
procedure 
6 and washed twice with phosphate-buffered saline. 
Rituximab-labeled cells were swelled by treatment with 75 mM 
KCl and then were made to adhere onto collagen I-coated cover 
glass by brief centrifugation. After fixing and permeabilization, 
the specimens were exposed to L26 antibody. Subsequently, the 
specimens were washed and were incubated in Alexa488-
conjugated goat anti-mouse IgG. Nuclear staining was per-
formed using 5 mg/ml of 4'-6-diamidino-2-phenylindole. The 
preparations were screened for fluorescence with a confocal 
microscope (FV1000, OLYMPUS, Tokyo, Japan) using excitation 
wavelengths of 405, 488 and 633 nm to detect emission by 
nuclear staining (4'-6-diamidino-2-phenylindole), rituximab or 
L26 staining, respectively. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>The tissues had been routinely fixed in 10% neutral formalin and 
embedded in paraffin. L26 antibody and monoclonal antibodies 
raised against the N-terminal cytoplasmic region of CD20 were 
used. The sections were deparaffinized and rehydrated in graded 
alcohol. For heat-induced epitope retrieval, the sections were 
subjected to Target Retrieval Solution, pH 9 (DAKO) at 97 1C for 
40 min. The sections then were brought to an automated stainer 
(DAKO) by following the vendor's protocol. EnVision Plus 
(DAKO) and peroxidase detection methods were used. </p>

<p>Rituximab-binding analysis </p>

<p>Rituximab-binding analysis was performed according to our 
previously developed imaging-based procedure, with some 
modifications. 
6 Briefly, approximately ten thousands cells of 
purified living lymphoma cells using a Dead cell removal kit 
(Miltenyi Biotec) were incubated with 10 mg/ml of anti-
CD19 mAb labeled with Alexa Fluor 488 (Invitrogen) and 
rituximab labeled with Alexa Fluor 647 (Invitrogen) for 30 min 
at 4 1C. The cells were washed with phosphate-buffered saline 
two times and were then suspended in 4 ml of RPMI1640 
medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum and 5 mg/ 
ml of Hoechist 33 342. The cell suspension was pipetted into a 
well made of silicon, 2.5 mm in diameter and 2 mm in depth, on 
a piece of cover glass. Images were collected by means of an 
OLYMPUS PlanApo Â 60 oil objective in an OLYMPUS 
FV-1000 confocal microscope (OLYMPUS). The fluorophore </p>

<p>was excited by laser at 405, 488 or 633 nm. The cells were 
optically sectioned along the z-axis, and the images were 
collected at 640 Â 640 pixel resolution in a sequential mode to 
minimize the crossover between channels. The step size in the 
z-axis was 0.5 mm. For three-dimensional reconstruction, two-
dimensional confocal stacks were saved in an Olympus.oib 
format and three-dimensional images were generated using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Fluoview</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">OLYMPUS</rs>). </p>

<p>Cell sorting and genetic analysis </p>

<p>The cryopreserved B-linage cells of the pleural effusion at 
relapse were further sorted into two fractions of the cells with 
high affinity to rituximab (R-high) and those of low (R-low) by 
using flow cytometry (FACSvantage, Becton Dickinson, Franklin 
Lakes, NJ, USA). The cells were labeled with rituximab 
conjugated with AlexaFluor488 (Invitrogen) and anti-CD19-PE 
(Becton Dickinson), then resuspended in phosphate-buffered 
saline containing 2 mg/ml of 7-AAD (Sigma) to exclude dead 
cells. The sorting gate used for 'R-high' was rituximab </p>

<p>high </p>

<p>/ 
CD19 
þ /7-AAD 
À , and for 'R-low' was rituximab 
low/ CD19 
þ /7-
AAD 
À . The sorted cells were immediately used for extraction of 
both genomic DNA and total RNA using QIAamp DNA micro 
kit and RNeasy micro kit, respectively, (QIAGEN, Hilden, 
Germany). For amplifying the DNA-containing exon 8 of CD20 
from genomic DNA, PCR was carried out using the forward 
primer (5 
0 -TTCTGTTTTZGAACATAGTTCTCCCTGTCCA-3 
0 ) and 
the reverse primer (5 
0 -CAGAAAACAGAAATCACTTAAGGAGAG-3 
0 ). 
RT-PCR to amplify the CD20 cDNA were performed according 
to the method described above. The PCR and RT-PCR products 
were used to determine the CD20 gene sequence by direct 
sequencing method. In addition, 1 ml of RT-PCR products were 
cloned into a TA-cloning vector (pCR2.1, Invitrogen) and CD20 
DNA sequences of 16 clones of each RT-PCR product were 
determined for estimating the ratio of different sequences. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>To confirm the epitope of L26, we made a series of constructs of 
the CD20 molecules with deletion mutations in the C-terminal 
cytoplasmic domain and introduced them into retrovirus vectors 
(Figure 1a). KMS12PE cells, in which expression of CD20 is not 
detected immunohistologically, were then transformed, and we 
established six kinds of sub-lines with the various C-terminal 
deletion mutations of CD20. A semi-quantitative RT-PCR 
analysis using a primer set designed to amplify the CD20 
N-terminal region indicated that no major difference was found 
in CD20 messenger RNA (mRNA) expression of the six cell lines 
(Figure 1b). We carried out immunocytochemical analysis using 
L26 and fluorescence-labeled rituximab against these six CD20-
expressing transfectants, along with a mock transfectant and Raji 
cells as negative and positive controls, respectively. The cells 
stained by L26 antibody were only those expressing wild type 
(amino acid 1-297) and DM1 mutant (amino acid 1-281). On 
the other hand, rituximab could bind to shorter CD20 
molecules, such as DM2, DM3 or DM4, as well as to the 
CD20 molecules recognized by L26 (Figure 1c). These results 
indicate that L26 antibody recognizes the C-terminal cytoplasm 
region of CD20 molecules and that its epitope is present in the 
amino-acid sequence of 264-281. The data suggest that 
immunohistochemistry using L26 antibody will exhibit a false 
negative if a deletion or a frame shift occurs upstream of this 
epitope. In addition, the shortest deletion mutant DM5 that 
lacked the C-terminal cytoplasmic region was detected by </p>

<p>CD20 mutations of rituximab-resistant lymphoma 
Y Mishima et al </p>



<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>

<p>neither L26 antibody nor rituximab. Possible reasons might 
include the low membrane localization of DM5 mutant and/or 
low stability of the post-translational product. To clarify this, we 
carried out western blot analysis using total cell lysate of the 
series of deletion mutants that were tagged by FLAG peptide at 
the N-terminal region of CD20 constructs. We found that the 
cellular protein level of the DM5 deletion mutant of CD20 was 
remarkably lower than that of others, suggesting that low post-
translational stability may be the reason for the low antigenicity 
of DM5 mutant (data not shown). 
To detect CD20 in the clinical specimens that acquired 
rituximab resistance mutations, we developed novel anti-CD20 
antibodies and screened them in paraffin sections. We isolated an 
antibody specific for the CD20 N-terminus and named it CD20N. 
Using this antibody, we carried out immunohistochemistry 
conducted on the CD20-negative cases by L26 antibody-based 
analysis and found several cases with mutations in the C-terminal 
cytoplasm region. Among them, a cell specimen, a part of which 
had been cryopreserved as living cells, was included. This was 
pleural effusion from a patient with relapsed diffuse large cell 
B-cell lymphoma after complete remission following rituximab 
containing chemotherapy (rituximab, cyclophosphamide, adria-
mycin, vincristine and prednisone). This patient did not respond to 
further treatment with salvage therapies containing rituximab. The 
results of immunochemical analysis of the fibrin clot of the pleural 
effusion at relapse, as well as the biopsy of lymph nodes at the first 
examination, are shown in Figure 2. The lymph node biopsy 
before rituximab treatment was stained in the same way by both 
L26 and CD20N antibodies. However, L26 antibody did not stain 
at the population having mutated CD20 in the pleural effusion. 
On the other hand, the CD20N antibody stained almost all of the 
B-cell population. It should be noted that most of the cells were 
stained at the region of plasma membrane by CD20N antibody. 
As a result of DNA sequencing of purified B cells, we found 
one nucleotide deletion mutation, which caused a frame 
shift after the amino-acid residue 251, in half of the DNA </p>

<p>(Figure 3a). We conducted a binding analysis of rituximab using the 
viable cells of B-lineage purified from cryopreserved mononuclear 
cells. Most of these cells were CD19 positive. However, these cells 
consisted of two kinds of cell populations that were quite different 
in their affinity for rituximab (Figure 3b). Furthermore, flow 
cytometry analysis revealed that the fluorescent intensity of 
fluoro-labeled monoclonal antibody of CD20 decreased to less 
than one-tenth in about half of the B-cell population (Figure 3c). 
These results indicate that the C-terminal mutation of the CD20 
gene in this case caused abnormality of extracellular-antigen 
presentation, even though the protein expression and the cell 
membrane localization seemed to be normal. 
To reveal the genetic mechanisms of the reduced antigenicity 
to rituximab, we conducted gene-sequencing analysis about 
both population of cells that differ in affinity to rituximab. The 
cryopreserved B lymphocytes of the pleural effusion at relapse 
were sorted into two fractions of cells of high affinity to 
rituximab (R-high) and those of low (R-low) by using flow 
cytometry (Figure 4a). Then genomic DNA and total RNA from 
each fraction were extracted. The results of DNA sequencing of 
exon 8 of CD20 in which the mutation was found demonstrated 
that, surprisingly, both cell populations had both normal and 
the monobasic deletion mutant CD20 genes. To determine 
the proportion of the genes, the PCR-amplified DNA fragments 
were inserted into a TA-cloning vector and 16 clones from both 
'R-high' and 'R-low' fractions were determined the sequence of 
CD20. As a result, the ratio of mutant DNA accounted for 
approximately half of genomic DNA of both 'R-high' (7 out of 16) 
and 'R-low' (9 out of 16). On the other hand, the results 
of sequence analysis about the cDNA revealed that the ratio of 
mutant mRNA in 'R-low' was remarkably increased (14 out of 16), 
whereas that of 'R-high' was as the same of the results 
of genomic DNA (8 out of 16; Figure 4b). We also carried out 
a sequence analysis about genomic DNA from a slice of paraffin 
-embedded tissue of lymph node at the first diagnosis of this 
patient, and found that approximately half of the genomic DNA </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>Cytoplasmic 
Cytoplasmic 
Cytoplasmic </p>

<p>297 </p>

<p>281 </p>

<p>263 </p>

<p>245 </p>

<p>228 </p>

<p>210 </p>

<p>TM TM 
TM 
TM 
Extracellular </p>

<p>Cytoplasmic 
Cytoplasmic 
Cytoplasmic 
TM TM 
TM 
TM 
Extracellular </p>

<p>Cytoplasmic 
Cytoplasmic 
Cytoplasmic 
TM TM 
TM 
TM 
Extracellular </p>

<p>Cytoplasmic 
Cytoplasmic 
TM TM 
TM 
TM 
Extracellular </p>

<p>Cytoplasmic 
Cytoplasmic 
TM TM 
TM 
TM 
Extracellular </p>

<p>Cytoplasmic 
Cytoplasmic 
TM TM 
TM 
TM 
Extracellular </p>

<p>DM1 </p>

<p>DM2 </p>

<p>DM3 </p>

<p>DM4 </p>

<p>DM5 </p>

<p>CD20 </p>

<p>M 
o c k 
C 
D 
2 0 W </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C 
D 
2 0 D </p>

<p>M 
1 </p>

<p>C 
D 
2 0 D </p>

<p>M 
2 </p>

<p>C 
D 
2 0 D </p>

<p>M 
3 </p>

<p>C 
D 
2 0 D </p>

<p>M 
4 </p>

<p>C 
D 
2 0 D </p>

<p>M 
5 </p>

<p>G3PDH </p>

<p>DIC </p>

<p>KMS12PE 
/mock </p>

<p>CD20 [WT] 
(aa 1-297) </p>

<p>CD20 [DM1] 
(aa 1-281) </p>

<p>CD20 [DM2] 
(aa 1-263) </p>

<p>CD20 [DM3] 
(aa 1-245) </p>

<p>CD20 [DM4] 
(aa 1-228) </p>

<p>CD20 [DM5] 
(aa 1-210) </p>

<p>Raji </p>

<p>DAPI Rituximab L26 
Merge </p>

<p>Figure 1 Search for epitopic site of L26 antibody and analysis of the extracellular exposure of CD20 molecules having C-terminal deletion 
mutation. (a) To explore the binding site of the L26 antibody, we constructed various lengths of the CD20 deletion mutant at their C-terminal 
cytoplasmic domains. TM: transmembrane domain. (b) KMS12PE cells retrovirally transduced with C-terminal truncated CD20 showed 
approximately similar levels of mRNA expression. (c) Immunocytochemical studies suggested that L26 recognizes amino-acid sequence between 
264 and 281. An objective lens of Â 60 was used with a Â 10 digital zoom, bar: 5 mm. DAPI, 4'-6-diamidino-2-phenylindole; DIC, differential 
interference contrast; G3PDH, glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase; WT, wild type. </p>

<p>CD20 mutations of rituximab-resistant lymphoma 
Y Mishima et al </p>



<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>

<p>included the mutant CD20 gene same as the cells at relapse 
(8 out of 16; Figure 4c). These results indicated that this patient 
had already carried the mutation in CD20 gene, as onset of </p>

<p>primary lymphoma, and that a transcriptional imbalance 
of wild-type CD20 and mutated CD20 have occurred by 
undetermined mechanisms in some cell populations. </p>

<p>5 ' -
5 ' -</p>

<p>3 ' -
3 ' -</p>

<p>Protein primary structure </p>

<p>CD19-Alexa488 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 1 
10 0 
10 0 
Mouse lgG1 PE </p>

<p>Mouse lgG1 FITC </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 1 
10 0 
10 0 </p>

<p>CD20 PE </p>

<p>CD19 FITC </p>

<p>rituximab-Alexa647 
Merged image </p>

<p>wild type 
1 </p>

<p>-3 ' </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>-3 ' </p>

<p>-5 ' 
-5 ' </p>

<p>mutated </p>

<p>Cytoplasmic 
Cytoplasmic </p>

<p>Cytoplasmic </p>

<p>Cytoplasmic </p>

<p>297 </p>

<p>290 
250 
1 </p>

<p>Cytoplasmic 
Cytoplasmic </p>

<p>TM TM </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>TM Extracellular </p>

<p>Extracellular 
TM </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>TM 
TM </p>

<p>Figure 3 The analysis of primary lymphoma cells derived from pleural effusion of a patient with rituximab-refractory, diffuse large-cell 
lymphoma. (a) A direct sequence analysis of the CD20-coding region revealed that an adenine residue ( þ 478) was deleted in about half of the 
cDNA. This gene mutation caused a frame shift after the amino-acid sequence of 250 and early denomination. The blue column in the protein 
schematic charts expresses an abnormal primary structure. *Single nucleotide deletion occurred at this position in approximately half of cDNA. 
(b) Rituximab-binding analysis based on three-dimensional imaging. Magnetically sorted living B-lineage cells were labeled with CD19 (green 
pseudo-color) and rituximab (red pseudo-color). Although the intensity varied, the CD19 antigen was expressed in most of the cells. Meanwhile, 
rituximab bound markedly to approximately half of the cells, but the binding to the rest of cells could not be detected. The blue pseudo-color 
indicates fluorescence of Hoechist22242 nuclear dye. Results shown here are representative of the 19 microscopic fields. (c) Flow cytometric 
analysis of mononuclear cells from the pleural effusion of this patient suggested that there were two populations of different CD20-expressing 
levels among CD19 positive cells. The mean fluorescence intensities (MFIs) of the higher (blue) and lower (red) CD20-expressing populations were 
calculated as 486.8 and 30.5, respectively. FITC, fluorescein isothiocyanate. </p>

<p>Pre-treatment 
(lymph node) </p>

<p>H/E </p>

<p>IHC (L26) </p>

<p>IHC (CD20N) </p>

<p>Relapse 
(PE lymphoma) </p>

<p>Figure 2 Immunohistochemistry (IHC) was performed on a biopsied specimen of a lymph node at the first examination (a, b and c) and on a fibrin 
clot from the B-cell population from pleural effusion at the relapse phase (d, e and f). Both L26 and CD20N antibodies uniformly stained the 
lymphoma cells in the lymph node biopsy specimen (b and c, respectively). However, L26 did not recognize about half of the B cells derived from 
pleural effusion (e), whereas CD20N stained almost all the cells (f). (a and d) indicates hematoxylin and eosin (H/E) stain. High-magnification 
images of the region boxed in (a-f) were shown in (a 
0 -f 
0 ), respectively. An objective lens of Â 60 was used, bar: 50 mm. PE lymphoma, lymphoma 
cell in pleural effusion. </p>

<p>CD20 mutations of rituximab-resistant lymphoma 
Y Mishima et al </p>



<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>

<p>As CD20 is thought to be present as a tetramer in cells, </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>mutated CD20 may affect also wild-type peptide in the same 
cell. To verify this possibility, we introduced the CD20 gene 
carrying the same mutation as this patient to CD20 
À cell line, 
KMS12PE and CD20 
þ Daudi using a retrovirus vector, then 
selected the cells expressing the exogeneous CD20 by a green 
fluorescent protein reporter promoted by an internal ribosome 
entry site (Figure 5a). As the result of evaluating the binding 
affinity to rituximab by flow cytometry, the exogeneous mutated 
CD20 exhibited remarkably attenuated antigenicity to rituximab 
as compared with the wild-type CD20 (Figure 5b). Next, 
we transformed Daudi cells with the mutant CD20 to examine 
the effect on expression of wild-type CD20 molecules. </p>

<p>In consideration of turnover of intrinsic CD20, we evaluated 
binding of rituximab to the transfectants 7 days after virus 
infection. As shown in Figure 5c, the expression of this mutated 
CD20 was found to have hardly affected the affinity for 
rituximab. These results suggested that at least the mutation 
found in this patient did not exert a dominant negative effect 
against normal CD20 molecules. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Previously, we reported that mutations in the CD20 gene were 
found with some frequency in patients treated with rituximab. </p>

<p>before sorting 
'R-high' fraction 
'R-low' fraction </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 2 
CD19 PE </p>

<p>Genomic DNA of 'R-high' cells at relapse 
(mt : wt = 7 : 9) </p>

<p>Genomic DNA of 'R-low' cells at relapse 
(mt : wt = 9 : 7) </p>

<p>mRNA of 'R-high' cells at relapse 
(mt : wt = 8 : 8) </p>

<p>Genomic DNA of 'R-high' cells of primary LN 
(mt : wt = 8 : 8) </p>

<p>mRNA of 'R-low' cells at relapse 
(mt : wt = 14 : 2) </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 0 
10 0 
10 4 
10 3 
10 2 
CD19 PE </p>

<p>10 1 
10 0 
10 4 
10 3 
10 2 
CD19 PE </p>

<p>10 1 
10 0 </p>

<p>Rituxmab-AF488 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>Rituxmab-AF488 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>Rituxmab-AF488 </p>

<p>Figure 4 The genetic analysis of patient's lymphoma cells. The cryopreserved B linage cells of the pleural effusion at relapse were further sorted 
into two fractions of cells with high affinity to rituximab (R-high) and those of low (R-low) by using flow cytometry. (a) Dot blot of the cells before 
and after sorting. (b) The results of CD20 sequence analysis of genomic DNA and cDNA of 'R-high' and 'R-low'. The diagrams of direct sequencing 
of CD20 exon 8 region are shown. The ratio of mutant and wild-type CD20 genes were determined by the sequencing of 16 clones of RT-PCR 
products. (c) The results of genomic DNA sequence of primary lymphoma. </p>

<p>CD20 mutations of rituximab-resistant lymphoma 
Y Mishima et al </p>



<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>

<p>These cases often have a diagnosis of CD20 negative by 
immunostaining, based on the commonly used L26 antibody, 
and are difficult to distinguish from the cases in which protein 
expression of CD20 is extremely low. So the mutation in the 
CD20 gene has been less noticed with regard to resistance to 
rituximab. In the present study, we roughly identified the 
epitope of L26, and it became clear that all of the C-terminal-
mutated CD20 that we had found earlier lost the epitope for 
L26, because the epitope was located near the C-terminal of 
CD20 molecule. To detect CD20 with these mutations 
comprehensively, we developed monoclonal antibodies that 
recognize a part of the amino-acid sequence of the N-terminal 
cytoplasmic region of CD20. One of these antibodies, CD20N, 
recognized CD20 proteins, including those having a mutation 
in the paraffin-embedded, formalin-fixed specimen. In this 
study, we showed that it could be applied to the primary </p>

<p>screening of the lymphoma cells that express mutated CD20 by 
selecting L26-negative and CD20N-positive cells. 
To date, there are not many reports that the mutation of the 
CD20 gene contributes to resistance to rituximab. 
1,8 A part of 
the reason for this may be that L26 cannot detect most of 
mutated CD20. In addition, Johnson et al. 
8 carried out a 
sequencing screening of exon 5 of the CD20 gene encompass-
ing the epitope of rituximab. They detected CD20 mutations 
involving the rituximab epitope in only 1/264 (0.4%) and 1/15 
(6%) of the biopsies taken at diagnosis and relapse, respectively. 
Similarly, in our previous screening, no mutation was found in 
the region of exon 5, whereas four cases with mutation (out of 
50) were found in the C-terminal cytoplasm region of CD20. </p>

<p>1   In the CD20 gene, a genetic mutation could be more likely to 
occur in the C-terminal region compared with around the region 
of rituximab epitope by uncertain mechanism(s). </p>

<p>LTR 
wt CD20 
IRES </p>

<p>IRES </p>

<p>ZsGreen 
LTR </p>

<p>LTR 
ZsGreen 
mt CD20 </p>

<p>KMS12PE cells transfected with wild-type CD20 </p>

<p>KMS12PE cells transfected with mutant CD20 </p>

<p>Daudi cells transfected with mutant CD20 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 2 
ZsGreen 
ZsGreen </p>

<p>ZsGreen 
ZsGreen </p>

<p>ZsGreen 
ZsGreen </p>

<p>control lgG PE </p>

<p>control lgG PE </p>

<p>control lgG PE </p>

<p>rituximab PE </p>

<p>rituximab PE </p>

<p>rituximab PE </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 0 
10 4 
10 3 
10 2 
10 1 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 4 
10 3 
10 2 
10 1 
10 0 
10 4 
10 3 
10 2 
10 1 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 4 
10 3 
10 2 
10 1 
10 0 
10 4 
10 3 
10 2 
10 1 
10 0 </p>

<p>LTR </p>

<p>Figure 5 The effect of mutant CD20 on wild-type CD20 with respect to rituximab binding. (a) The schematic diagram of retrovirus vectors used 
for transduction of wild-type and mutant CD20. (b) The transfectants were labeled with PE-conjugated. rituximab and analyzed by flow cytometry 
at seven days after viral infection. The contour plots of KMS12PE cells transfected with wild-type (upper panel) or mutated CD20 (lower panel) are 
shown. (c) Daudi cells were transfected with mutated CD20 and analyzed the rituximab-binding. The mutant CD20 introduced exogenously 
hardly affected the binding of rituximab to Daudi cells. IRES, internal ribosome entry site; LTR, long terminal repeat; wt, wild type; mt, mutant. </p>

<p>CD20 mutations of rituximab-resistant lymphoma 
Y Mishima et al </p>



<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>

<p>By using live cryopreserved cells, derived from a newly 
identified case with the mutation in the CD20 gene, we 
successfully analyzed in detail the phenotype of lymphoma 
cells having mutated CD20. In this case, a frame shift mutation 
occurred because of one base nucleotide deletion, resulting in 
the translation of peptide of another reading frame of 41 amino 
acids after the amino acid position 250 with a slight early 
termination. Immunohistochemical analysis using CD20N anti-
body revealed that the CD20 molecules with C-terminal 
mutations were indeed expressed in the lymphoma cells, and 
located at the cell membrane. However, the living cell binding 
evaluation showed that rituximab could scarcely bind to these 
cells. These results suggest that the C-terminal region of CD20 
undertakes a critical role in presentation of the large loop in 
which the rituximab-binding site locates. 
As a result of genetic analysis for lymphoma cells, it was 
suggested that this patient had a mutation in the CD20 gene as 
onset of primary lymphoma. Because normal and mutated 
CD20 gene were almost the same copy numbers and the most of 
cells in the lymph follicle were stained in L26 at the first 
diagnosis, it can be considered that the lymphoma cells of this 
patient had equal number of normal and mutated CD20 alleles 
rather than the mixture of the cells having only normal CD20 
allele(s) or only mutant allele(s). And at the relapse, two 
cell populations of the different affinity for rituximab has arose 
('R-high' and 'R-low'), and both had a genome of the same 
mutation status, however, the expression of the mutated mRNA 
has been predominant only in 'R-low'. As a result of semi-
quantitative RT-PCR analysis revealed that whole CD20 mRNA 
expression of 'R-low' slightly decreased as compared with that 
of 'R-high' (data not shown), the imbalanced mRNA expression 
in 'R-low' may be due to the suppression of CD20 mRNA 
expression from the wild-type allele at the transcription level. 
To summarize these data, the primary lymphoma cells of this 
patient expressed both wild-type and mutated CD20 equally. As 
the mutant CD20 in this case was found to have little effect on 
the antigenicity of wild-type CD20 molecules, these cells were 
still susceptible to rituximab plus CHOP and the patient has 
obtained complete remission. However, at the relapse, cells that 
predominantly expressed the mutant CD20 emerged. This 
mutant molecule expressed and localized at the plasma 
membrane, however, the large loop could not be oriented 
appropriately. So it was considered that rituximab-containing 
salvage treatments have failed perhaps because affinity for 
rituximab was not enough. 
It was noteworthy that the antibody that recognizes N-terminal 
region of CD20 has capability to detect the mutated CD20 before 
start of the salvage therapy. This indicated the possibility that we 
can predict the existence of lymphoma cells resistant to rituximab 
before start of therapy. In addition, this information may provide 
important criterion to judge whether it should switch to the 
treatment such as using second-generation CD20 antibody that is 
effective against fewer CD20-expressing cells 
9-12 or using anti-
body for the different target molecule such as CD22. </p>

<p>13,14   The resistance for a molecular target drug acquired by a 
mutation in the gene of the target molecule is commonly 
considered to be irreversible. 
15-19 We propose here that detecting 
a mutation in the gene by screening using antibodies of two kinds 
of epitope is useful in detection of irreversible resistant mutation for 
molecular targeted drug including rituximab. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Ms Sayuri Minowa, Ms Harumi Shibata and Ms Mariko 
Mikuniya for their assistance in specimen preparation. We also 
thank Dr Dovie Wylie of On-Site English, Inc. (Palo Alto, CA, 
USA) for English editing assistance. </p>





<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>



<p>CD20 mutations of rituximab-resistant lymphoma 
Y Mishima et al </p>



<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>

</text></tei>