<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3655304" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:48+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS) has been used to 
identify the characteristics of cancer cells and to evaluate </p>

<p>Application of </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MR Spectroscopy to the Brain Tumors </p>

<p>Dong-Ho Ha, MD </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Sunseob Choi, MD </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Jong Young Oh, MD </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Seong Kuk Yoon, MD </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, 
Myong Jin Kang, MD </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Ki-Uk Kim, MD </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Departments of </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Radiology and </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Neurosurgery, College of Medicine, Dong-A University, Busan 602-715, Korea </p>

<p>Objective: To evaluate the clinical feasibility and obtain useful parameters of </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS) 
study for making the differential diagnosis of brain tumors. 
Materials and Methods: Twenty-eight patients with brain tumorous lesions (22 cases of brain tumor and 6 cases of abscess) 
and 11 normal volunteers were included. The patients were classified into the astrocytoma group, lymphoma group, 
metastasis group and the abscess group. We obtained the intracellular pH and the metabolite ratios of phosphomonoesters/ 
phosophodiesters (PME/PDE), PME/inorganic phosphate (Pi), PDE/Pi, PME/adenosine triphosphate (ATP), PDE/ATP, PME/ 
phosphocreatine (PCr), PDE/PCr, PCr/ATP, PCr/Pi, and ATP/Pi, and evaluated the statistical significances. 
Results: The brain tumors had a tendency of alkalization (pH = 7.28 ± 0.27, p = 0.090), especially the pH of the lymphoma 
was significantly increased (pH = 7.45 ± 0.32, p = 0.013). The brain tumor group showed increased PME/PDE ratio compared 
with that in the normal control group (p = 0.012). The ratios of PME/PDE, PDE/Pi, PME/PCr and PDE/PCr showed 
statistically significant differences between each brain lesion groups (p &lt; 0.05). The astrocytoma showed an increased 
PME/PDE and PME/PCr ratio. The ratios of PDE/Pi, PME/PCr, and PDE/PCr in lymphoma group were lower than those in the 
control group and astrocytoma group. The metastasis group showed an increased PME/PDE ratio, compared with that in the 
normal control group. 
Conclusion: We have obtained the clinically applicable </p>

<p>31   P MRS, and the pH, PME/PDE, PDE/Pi, PME/PCr, and PDE/PCr ratios 
are helpful for differentiating among the different types of brain tumors. 
Index terms: Magnetic resonance imaging; MRS; Brain; Tumor </p>

<p>Received May 31, 2012; accepted after revision September 4, 2012. 
This study was supported by research funds from Dong-A University. 
Corresponding author: Sunseob Choi, MD, Department 
of Radiology, College of Medicine, Dong-A University, 26 
Daesingongwon-ro, Seo-gu, Busan 602-715, Korea. 
• Tel: (8251) 240-5344 • Fax: (8251) 253-4931 
• E-mail: sschoi317@yahoo.co.kr 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License 
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0) which permits 
unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in 
any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Original Article | Neuroimaging and Head and Neck </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 2013;14(3):477-486 </p>

<p>the response of cancer cells to the targeted treatment, 
noninvasively, by MR signal (1). The commonly utilized 
elements for MRS are </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>H, </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P, </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>C, </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>F, </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>NA and </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>H (2). 
The phosphorous metabolites detected by </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS, such 
as adenosine triphosphate (ATP), phosphocreatine (PCr), 
inorganic phosphate (Pi), phosphomonoesters (PME), and 
phosophodiesters (PDE), provide the information of the 
intracellular pH, the cellular energy metabolism, and the 
phospholipid metabolism (3, 4). 
In brain tumors, </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS showed variable changes of the 
phospholipid metabolism. The intracellular pH and some 
phosphorous metabolite ratios, such as PME/PDE, PME/ 
Pi, PDE/Pi, PME/ATP, PDE/ATP, PME/PCr and etc, were 
considered to be potential markers of tumors (3, 5-8). </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3348/kjr.2013.14.3.477 </p>

<p>pISSN 1229-6929 · eISSN 2005-8330 </p>



<p>Ha et al. </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 14(3), May/Jun 2013 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>However, there are several limitations. There have been 
reports that </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS has a limited role for diagnosing 
cancer, making the differential diagnosis of specific tumor 
types and assessing the degree of malignancy (3, 6, 8). 
Moreover, even though </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS showed good reproducibility 
among different institutions (9), many of the results did not 
match well with other results. The most useful metabolite 
ratios have not yet been agreed on. Furthermore, long scan 
time and the complexity of the post-processing procedure 
make other limitations to apply </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS to patients. 
We performed a localized </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS study on brain tumorous 
lesions with a relatively short scan time and evaluate the 
useful parameters of </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS study to differentiate the brain 
tumors. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patients 
From October 2006 to May 2010, we prospectively 
performed MRS study on 47 patients who had brain tumorous 
lesions detected on MRI. Forty five cases of brain tumor and 
abscess were confirmed by biopsy or open surgery. 
We excluded the brain lesion that had large hemorrhage 
on the T1 weighted MR images. We also excluded the other 
brain lesions for the following reasons by a consensus of 
two radiologists: 1) the size of brain lesions on MRI was 
too small to evaluate the MRS spectrum, lesser than 3 cm in 
diameter, 2) two post-radiation states, 3) local recurrence 
after chemotherapy or radiation therapy, 4) rare cases such 
as pineal meningioma and dural hemangioblastoma, 5) one 
case of pilocytic astrocytoma that had a large cyst, was </p>

<p>excluded from the cases of astocytoma, and 6) one case of 
purely cystic abscess that contained entirely cystic portion 
on the fluid-attenuated inversion recovery images. 
As a result, we included 22 cases of brain tumor and 6 
cases of abscess. The pathologically confirmed brain tumor 
and abscess were classified into the 13 cases of astrocytoma 
(age range: 16-74, mean age: 42.8, 7 males and 4 females, 
4 cases of low grade astrocytoma and 9 cases of high grade 
astrocytoma), 4 cases of lymphoma (age range: 56-69, mean 
age: 64.0, 3 males and 1 female), 5 cases of metastasis 
(age range: 60-80, mean age: 71.8, 1 male and 4 females) 
and 6 cases of abscess (age range: 30-73, mean age: 54.5, 
3 males and 3 females) (Fig. 1). All 4 cases of lymphoma 
were large B cell lymphoma. None of these patients received 
therapy before the MRS analysis. 
We also obtained the MRS spectra of 11 normal volunteers 
as the control group (age range: 23-40 years, mean age: 
30.2, 7 males and 4 females). They did not have any 
specific medical history, such as migraine, recent infarct or 
trauma. The MRS of normal volunteers was obtained at the 
thalamus area to avoid the artifact from subcutaneous fat 
and magnetic inhomogeneity due to a peripheral location. </p>

<p>MRS Protocol 
We performed </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS on a 1.5 T GE scanner (Signa; 
GE Medial System, Milwaukee, WI, USA) with a flexible </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P transmit/receive coil, operating at 25.85 MHz. This 
coil contained a blocking circuit to prevent the reception 
of signals at the hydrogen frequency (63.86 MHz). The 
patient's head was wrapped with the flexible surface 
phosphorus coil and placed in the hydrogen head coil for </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Flow chart of patient selection. On basis of histopathologic results, patients were classified into 22 cases of brain tumor and 6 cases </p>

<p>of abscess. Brain tumors were subdivided into 13 cases of astrocytoma group, 4 cases of lymphoma group, and 5 cases of metastasis group. MRS 
= magnetic resonance spectroscopy </p>

<p>Astrocytoma 
(n = 13) </p>

<p>Lymphoma 
(n = 4) </p>

<p>Metastasis 
(n = 5) </p>

<p>Excluded patients 
(n = 19) </p>

<p>Included patients 
(n = 28) </p>

<p>Brain tumor 
(n = 22) </p>

<p>Abscess 
(n = 6) </p>

<p>Presence of hemorrhage 
No histopathologic confirm 
Small size of lesions 
Post-radiation states 
Recurrences 
Rare cases 
A pilocytic astrocytoma 
A purely cystic abscess </p>

<p>Total 47 patients who had brain tumorous 
lesions detected on MRI, underwent MRS </p>



<p>Application of </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MR Spectroscopy to Brain Tumors </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 14(3), May/Jun 2013 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>localization. 
For localization of a region of interest (ROI), the T2 
weighted fast spin-echo sequences in two different slice 
orientations were performed. Then, automated </p>

<p>1   H shimming 
was done to obtain the homogeneity of the ROI by using 
the point resolved spectroscopy sequence pulse sequence. 
For </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P spectroscopy, the free induction decay (FID) 2 
dimensional (2D) chemical shift imaging (CSI) sequence was 
carried out in an axial plane. The field of view was 3 x 3 x 
3 cm, and the volume was 27 mL. The following parameters 
were used, Nex: 8, scan number: 128, spectral width: 2500 
Hz, and acquired data points: 2048. 
The </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P spectra were post-processed using an automated 
procedure developed in <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAGE</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GE Medical Systems</rs>, Fremont, 
CA, USA). The obtained FID signal was displayed as a 
spectrum, following 2D CSI reconstruction with a magnitude 
channel. After using the 6 Hz exponential line broadening, 
we obtained the MR spectra that were assigned on the basis 
of prior assignment, such as PME, Pi, PDE, PCr and ATP. 
The chemical shift in the </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS referred to the position 
of PCr (δ = 0.00 ppm). The intracelluar pH of the lesions 
was calculated by using the chemical shift of Pi relative 
to PCr, with the formula taken from Ng et al. (10) (Fig. 2). 
The integral of each of the phosphorous metabolites, such 
as ATP, PCr, Pi, PME and PDE, was measured. The following 
metabolite ratios of PME/PDE, PME/Pi, PDE/Pi, PME/ATP, 
PDE/ATP, PME/PCr, PDE/PCr, PCr/ATP, PCr/Pi and ATP/Pi </p>

<p>were calculated from the measured values (Figs. 3-5). </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis 
We compared the mean values of the intracellular pH and 
the metabolite ratios between the normal control group and 
the brain tumor group by using the Mann-Whitney U test. 
The Kruskal-Wallis test was used for obtaining the 
statistical significant parameter between the each brain 
lesion. Additionally, multiple comparisons of each brain 
lesions were also carried out using the Dunn test. 
For comparison between the low grade astrocytoma group 
and high grade astocytoma group, and between the brain 
tumor group and the abscess group, the mean values of 
the intracellular pH and the metabolite ratios were also 
compared by using the Mann-Whitney U test. 
A p value of less than 0.05 was considered significant. 
The statistical analysis was performed by using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences</rs> software (version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">19.0</rs>, 
Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The average scan time for </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS was 6 minutes 36 
seconds. Total scan time was 15 minutes, including the 
scanning for localization. All patients were tolerable to 
obtain the MR imaging and the MR spectrum in a study. The 
pattern of the spectrum or chemical shift frequency of each 
metabolite was very similar in each group. 
The intracellular pH in the normal control group was 
calculated as 7.07 ± 0.10 (Table 1). These values were 
slightly higher than those of the previous reported values 
in a healthy volunteer group (11, 12). The brain tumors had 
a tendency of alkalization at a pH = 7.28 ± 0.27 (p value, 
0.090) (Table 1). The PME/PDE ratio in the brain tumor 
group (0.57 ± 0.11) showed a significant increase compared 
to that in the control group (0.47 ± 0.07) (p value, 0.012). 
The intracellular pH between each brain lesion groups did 
not show a statistically significant difference by using the 
Kruskal-Wallis test (Table 2). We also obtained statistical 
significance of the intracellular pH between the normal 
control group and each brain lesions by using the Mann-
Whitney U test. The lymphoma had a mean pH of 7.45 ± 
0.32 and this represents significant alkalization, compared 
to the normal control group (p value, 0.013). The mean 
value of pH in the metastasis (7.48 ± 0.56) was markedly 
higher than in the normal brain, but the difference was 
statistically insignificant (p value, 0.112). The pH in the </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Measuring pH in lesion. Intracelluar pH of brain lesions is </p>

<p>calculated by using measured δ Pi (arrow), which is chemical shift, 
from PCr to Pi. PME = phosphomonoester, PDE = phosphodiester, PCr 
= phosphocreatine, ATP = adenosine triphosphate, Pi = inorganic 
phosphate </p>

<p>2.5 x 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2.0 x 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>1.5 x 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>1.0 x 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5.0 x 10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 
5 
0 
-5 
-10 
-15 
Frequency (ppm) </p>

<p>Magnitude </p>

<p>Low 
High </p>

<p>PME </p>

<p>PDE </p>

<p>PCr </p>

<p>α-ATP </p>

<p>β-ATP 
γ-ATP 
Pi </p>



<p>Ha et al. </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 14(3), May/Jun 2013 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Fig. 3. 44-year-old man with high grade astrocytoma of 
brain. </p>

<p>A. Localizer image for </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS shows huge mass in right 
frontal lobe without cyst or hemorrhage. B. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS shows 
high level of PME (303), low level of Pi (90) and relatively 
low level of PDE (433). Calculated PME/PDE ratio (0.70) 
is higher than its mean value in control group (0.47). 
PME = phosphomonoester, PDE = phosphodiester, PCr = 
phosphocreatine, MRS = magnetic resonance spectroscopy, Pi 
= inorganic phosphate </p>

<p>2500 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>10 
5 
0 
-5 
-10 
-15 
Frequency (ppm) </p>

<p>Magnitude </p>

<p>PCr 
541 </p>

<p>PDE 
433 
PME 
303 </p>

<p>Pi 
90 </p>



<p>Application of </p>



<p>P MR Spectroscopy to Brain Tumors </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 14(3), May/Jun 2013 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Fig. 4. 53-year-old man with large B cell lymphoma. </p>

<p>A. Localizer image for </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS shows large mass with marked 
surrounding edema in left basal ganglia area. B. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS 
shows high level of PME (305), high level of PCr (1222) and 
low level of PDE (373). Calculated ratio shows high PME/PDE 
ratio (0.81). Calculated PDE/Pi ratio (2.76) is lower than its 
mean value of control group (3.44) and astrocytoma group 
(3.27). Calculated PDE/PCr ratio (0.31) is also lower than 
that of astrocytoma group (0.77). PME = phosphomonoester, 
PDE = phosphodiester, PCr = phosphocreatine, MRS = magnetic 
resonance spectroscopy, Pi = inorganic phosphate </p>

<p>3 x 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 x 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>1 x 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 
5 
0 
-5 
-10 
-15 
Frequency (ppm) </p>

<p>Magnitude </p>

<p>PCr 
1222 </p>

<p>PDE 
373 
PME 
305 Pi 
135 </p>



<p>Ha et al. </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 14(3), May/Jun 2013 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>metastasis showed a wide standard deviation. Two cases 
of metastasis showed a lower pH value (below 6.90) than 
that in the normal brain. Three cases of metastasis showed 
marked alkalization. The pH in the brain abscess (7.56 ± 
0.64) also showed a wide standard deviation, compared to 
that in the control group (p value, 0.159). 
The ratios of PME/PDE, PDE/Pi, PME/PCr and PDE/PCr 
showed statistical significant differences between each 
brain lesion groups by using the Kruskal-Wallis test (Table 
2). We used the Dunn procedure for comparison of each 
group and a p value of less than 0.005 was considered 
significant. The PME/PDE ratio in the astrocyoma group (0.56 
± 0.10) was significantly higher than that in the control 
group (0.47 ± 0.07) (p value, 0.003). The PME/PDE ratio </p>

<p>in the lymphoma group (0.60 ± 0.15) was higher than that 
in the control group, but it had a wide standard deviation 
(p value, 0.117). The mean value of the PME/PDE ratio in 
metastasis (0.68 ± 0.19) was significantly higher than that 
in the control group (p value, 0.003). The abscess group 
showed a higher mean value of the PME/PDE ratio (0.65 ± 
0.32) with a wide standard deviation than that in control 
group, statistically insignificant (p value, 0.366). 
The PDE/Pi ratio in the lymphoma group (2.57 ± 0.60) 
was significantly lower than that in the control group (3.44 
± 0.49) (p value, 0.002). The PDE/Pi ratio in lymphoma 
was lower than that in astrocytoma (3.27 ± 0.62), but 
statistically insignificant (p value, 0.052). The PME/PCr 
ratio in the astrocyoma (0.43 ± 0.11) was significantly </p>

<p>A 
Fig. 5. 73-year-old man with brain abscess. </p>

<p>A. FID signal for </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS was obtained at left basal ganglia mass lesion. </p>



<p>Application of </p>



<p>P MR Spectroscopy to Brain Tumors </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 14(3), May/Jun 2013 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>higher than that in the control group (0.34 ± 0.07) and 
in the lymphoma group (0.30 ± 0.08) (p value, 0.004, 
0.003, respectively). The PME/PCr in lymphoma was also 
reduced compared to that of the control group, although 
the difference was statistically insignificant (p value, </p>

<p>0.151). The PDE/PCr ratio in lymphoma (0.51 ± 0.16) was 
significantly lower than that in the astrocytoma group (0.77 
± 0.18) (p value, 0.002). The PDE/PCr ratio in the lymphoma 
group was reduced compared to that of the control group 
(0.75 ± 0.20), but the statistically insignificant p value was 
observed (0.068). 
There was no significant parameter between the low grade 
astrocytoma and high grade astrocytoma (Table 3). All the 
parameters of the metabolite ratios did not show significant 
differences between the brain tumor and the abscess (Table 3). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P magnetic resonance spectroscopy can monitor the 
intracellular pH in living systems by using the chemical shifts 
of various phosphorous compounds (13). We obtained the 
intracellular pH by using the chemical shift of endogeneous 
Pi. The microenvironment within solid tumors displays acidic 
and hypoxic physiochemical alterations (14, 15). Contrary 
to the assumption that tumor cells have acidic metabolism, 
measurements of human and animal tumor pH using </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P 
MRS reported neutral-to-alkaline values (16). As reported 
in various studies, the pH of brain tumors was significantly 
higher than that of the normal brain tissue (17, 18). </p>

<p>B 
C </p>

<p>2.0 x 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>1.5 x 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>1.0 x 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5.0 x 10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 
5 
0 
-5 
-10 
-15 
Frequency (ppm) </p>

<p>Magnitude </p>

<p>PCr 
584 </p>

<p>PDE 
486 
PME 
284 
Pi 
189 </p>

<p>Fig. 5. 73-year-old man with brain abscess. </p>

<p>B. Fluid-attenuated inversion recovery image shows heterogeneous signal intensity mass with central low signal intensity in left basal ganglia. 
C. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS shows low level of PME (284), low level of PCr (584) and relatively high level of PDE (486). Calculated ratio of PME/PDE (0.58) 
is lower than its mean value of metastasis group (0.68). FID = free induction decay, PME = phosphomonoester, PDE = phosphodiester, PCr = 
phosphocreatine, MRS = magnetic resonance spectroscopy, Pi = inorganic phosphate </p>

<p>Table 1. Mean pH and Mean Metabolite Ratios (± SD) between 
Normal Control Group and Brain Tumor Group </p>

<p>Normal Control 
(n = 11) 
Mean ± SD </p>

<p>Brain Tumor 
(n = 22) 
Mean ± SD </p>

<p>P* </p>

<p>pH 
7.07 ± 0.10 
7.28 ± 0.27 
0.090 
PME/PDE 
0.47 ± 0.07 
0.57 ± 0.11 
0.012 
PME/Pi 
1.60 ± 0.19 
1.80 ± 0.51 
0.178 
PDE/Pi 
3.44 ± 0.49 
3.16 ± 0.74 
0.088 
PME/ATP 
0.21 ± 0.03 
0.24 ± 0.05 
0.261 
PDE/ATP 
0.45 ± 0.09 
0.43 ± 0.11 
0.559 
PME/PCr 
0.34 ± 0.07 
0.40 ± 0.12 
0.178 
PDE/PCr 
0.75 ± 0.20 
0.72 ± 0.21 
0.753 
PCr/ATP 
0.61 ± 0.07 
0.61 ± 0.14 
1.000 
PCr/Pi 
4.74 ± 0.74 
4.63 ± 1.42 
0.445 
ATP/Pi 
7.76 ± 0.64 
7.93 ± 2.81 
0.822 </p>

<p>Note.-*All p values were calculated by using Mann-Whitney 
U test. SD = standard deviation, PME = phosphomonoester, 
PDE = phosphodiester, PCr = phosphocreatine, ATP = adenosine 
triphosphate, Pi = inorganic phosphate </p>



<p>Ha et al. </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 14(3), May/Jun 2013 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>In our study, the brain tumor had a tendency of 
alkalization. The pH of astrocytoma was slightly higher 
than that of the normal brain. In lymphoma, the pH was 
significantly higher than that in the normal brain. The 
pH in the abscesses and metastatic lesions was clearly 
higher than that in the normal brain, but the pH was not 
statistically different due to the large scatter of data. We 
suspected that this was caused by the heterogenous nature 
of the lesions. </p>

<p>The phosphorous metabolites, detected by </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS, can 
be used for providing the information of the phospholipid 
metabolism. The measuring of the absolute concentration 
of phosphorous metabolites is the ultimate goal of the </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS study. However, there are various limitations. The 
obtained integral of each phosphorous metabolites (PME, 
PDE, PCr, Pi, ATP) on the spectrum were considered as the 
relative concentration of metabolites in the lesion (4). The 
difficulty of appropriate calibration, the sensitivity of the 
surface coils, J-coupling, low concentration of metabolites 
and variations from other various correction factors also 
contribute to the variations of quantification of phosphorus 
metabolites. The use of metabolite ratios could reduce these 
variations. A number of researchers have used various ratios 
of metabolic components, such as PME/ATP, PDE/ATP, PDE/ 
PME, PCr/ATP, PME/PCr PDE/PCr and etc (3, 8, 19). 
The PME and PDE indicated the significance of 
phospholipid precursors and catabolites as markers for 
tumor detection, malignancy, progression and the response 
to treatment (3, 5, 20). The major components of PME 
are phosphocholine (PCho) and phosphoethanolamine 
(PEtn) (19). These molecules are the intermediates in 
the biosynthesis of phosphoglycerides and indicate the 
presence of precursors of cytoplasmic membrane synthesis 
(21). The complete deacylation of phospholipids produce 
glycerophosphocholine and glycerophosphoethanolamine. 
These molecules are the major components of PDE, which 
indicates the presence of breakdown products of the 
membrane (21, 22). The ratio of PME/PDE can serve as 
an index of the metabolism of membrane phospholipid </p>

<p>Table 2. Mean pH and Mean Metabolite Ratios (± SD) in Normal Control Group, Astrocytoma Group, Lymphoma Group, Metastasis 
Group and Abscess Group </p>

<p>Normal Control 
(n = 11) 
Mean ± SD </p>

<p>Astrocytoma 
(n = 13) 
Mean ± SD </p>

<p>Lymphoma 
(n = 4) 
Mean ± SD </p>

<p>Metastasis 
(n = 5) 
Mean ± SD </p>

<p>Abscess 
(n = 6) 
Mean ± SD </p>

<p>P* </p>

<p>pH 
7.07 ± 0.10 
7.15 ± 0.20 
7.45 ± 0.32 
7.48 ± 0.56 
7.56 ± 0.64 
0.058 
PME/PDE 
0.47 ± 0.07 
0.56 ± 0.10 
0.60 ± 0.15 
0.68 ± 0.19 
0.65 ± 0.32 
0.034 
PME/Pi 
1.60 ± 0.19 
1.83 ± 0.50 
1.56 ± 0.61 
1.69 ± 0.35 
2.00 ± 1.01 
0.304 
PDE/Pi 
3.44 ± 0.49 
3.27 ± 0.62 
2.57 ± 0.60 
2.76 ± 1.27 
3.18 ± 0.78 
0.039 
PME/ATP 
0.21 ± 0.03 
0.24 ± 0.05 
0.20 ± 0.05 
0.23 ± 0.04 
0.28 ± 0.08 
0.152 
PDE/ATP 
0.45 ± 0.09 
0.44 ± 0.10 
0.35 ± 0.11 
0.37 ± 0.15 
0.48 ± 0.18 
0.340 
PME/PCr 
0.34 ± 0.07 
0.43 ± 0.11 
0.30 ± 0.08 
0.36 ± 0.10 
0.42 ± 0.09 
0.028 
PDE/PCr 
0.75 ± 0.20 
0.77 ± 0.18 
0.51 ± 0.16 
0.59 ± 0.28 
0.73 ± 0.27 
0.049 
PCr/ATP 
0.61 ± 0.07 
0.58 ± 0.15 
0.69 ± 0.12 
0.66 ± 0.11 
0.67 ± 0.13 
0.314 
PCr/Pi 
4.74 ± 0.74 
4.36 ± 0.95 
5.51 ± 2.52 
4.72 ± 0.48 
4.86 ± 2.18 
0.640 
ATP/Pi 
7.76 ± 0.64 
7.90 ± 2.51 
8.37 ± 4.34 
7.28 ± 1.39 
7.61 ± 4.12 
1.000 </p>

<p>Note.-*All p values were calculated by using Kruskal-Wallis test. SD = standard deviation, PME = phosphomonoester, PDE = 
phosphodiester, PCr = phosphocreatine, ATP = adenosine triphosphate, Pi = inorganic phosphate </p>

<p>Table 3. Significant Differences of pH and Metabolite Ratios 
between Low Grade Astrocytoma Group and High Grade 
Astrocytoma Group and between Brain Tumor Group and 
Abscess Group </p>

<p>Low Grade vs. 
High Grade 
Astrocytoma 
P* </p>

<p>Brain Tumor vs. 
Abscess </p>

<p>P* 
pH 
0.575 
0.419 
PME/PDE 
0.877 
0.947 
PME/Pi 
0.758 
0.689 
PDE/Pi 
0.165 
0.505 
PME/ATP 
0.280 
0.182 
PDE/ATP 
0.440 
0.386 
PME/PCr 
1.000 
0.594 
PDE/PCr 
0.758 
0.947 
PCr/ATP 
0.877 
0.317 
PCr/Pi 
0.537 
0.594 
ATP/Pi 
0.758 
0.463 </p>

<p>Note.-*All p values were calculated by using Mann-Whitney 
U test. PME = phosphomonoester, PDE = phosphodiester, PCr = 
phosphocreatine, ATP = adenosine triphosphate, Pi = inorganic 
phosphate </p>



<p>Application of </p>



<p>P MR Spectroscopy to Brain Tumors </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 14(3), May/Jun 2013 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>and reflect changes in the rate of membrane synthesis or 
metabolic turnover (5, 8). 
We observed significantly increased PME/PDE ratio in 
brain tumor as compared to that in the normal brain control 
group. We also observed a significantly increased PME/PDE 
ratio in astrocytoma as compared to that in the normal 
brain. In metastasis, the PME/PDE ratio was significantly 
higher than that in the normal brain. The PME/PDE ratio 
in lymphoma was higher than that in the normal brain and 
astrocytoma, but this was statistically insignificant. 
Unfortunately, these changes have variable limitations 
in application to the tumors, according to the previous 
studies. At first, both PME level and PDE level was increased 
in most tumors (8). It seems difficult to understand an 
accumulation of metabolic precursors with an accelerated 
formation of end products. Various pathways, enzymes 
and the roles of PCho and PEtn can affect this paradoxical 
phenomenon. Furthermore, other studies also showed 
increased PME levels with using cytostatic agents on the 
cancer cells, which inhibit proliferation (20, 23). Moreover, 
these alterations are not exclusive to malignancy (8). 
These changes may also occur in developing (embryo or 
fetal) organs, in proliferating tissues, such as regenerating 
liver, in benign tumors and even in some degenerative 
pathologies (8). 
Variability of peak intensities of the phosphorous 
metabolite on </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS was also demonstrated, according to 
the different origin of the tumors (24). In the present study, 
the PME/PCr and PDE/PCr ratios in lymphoma were also 
significantly lower than those in the astrocytoma group. 
The PDE/Pi ratio in the lymphoma group was lower than 
that in control group and the astrocytoma group. The ratio 
of PDE/PCr in lymphoma was significantly lower than that 
in astrocytoma. We suspected that this observation may 
be correlated with the reduced PDE level in lymphoma. 
The PME/PCr and PDE/PCr ratio in lymphoma were also 
significantly lower than those in the astrocytoma group. 
On comparison with the normal control group, the PME/ 
PCr and PDE/PCr ratios were also reduced, even thought 
it was statistically insignificant. We considered that this 
result could be correlated with the increased PCr level in 
lymphoma. We thought that these changes will be helpful 
to differentiate the brain tumors. 
There are reports of phosphorous metabolites as markers 
for the degree of malignancy (3, 6). In this study, there 
was no statistically significant parameter that would 
differentiate between low grade astrocytoma and high grade </p>

<p>astrocytoma. 
Another biologic application of </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS is studying the 
cellular energy metabolism. ATP, PCr and Pi play crucial 
roles in cellular energetic (25-27). In a study on brain 
tumor, the Pi/PCr ratio was significantly elevated and the 
PCr/ATP ratio was reduced (19). The PCr/ATP, PCr/Pi and 
ATP/Pi ratios in this study were not significantly different 
between the control group and the brain tumor group, and 
between each brain lesion. 
In the present study, the MRS signal was obtained by 
using the FID 2D CSI sequence, collecting FID signal using 
the CSI sequence. In a classical CSI sequences, the MRS 
obtains the signal by applying the phase-encoding gradients 
without a frequency-encoding gradient. Thus, the FID CSI 
sequence collects a FID, either from the entire sensitive 
volume of the receiver coil or a prescribed set of slices 
(28, 29). As a result, the MRS signals using the FID CSI 
sequences can be contaminated from normal parenchyma 
in the outside of the lesion. The MRS signal differences 
between the tumor and normal tissue can be reduced. For 
more conservative approach, we performed </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS on the 
relatively large sized brain tumor. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P magnetic resonance spectroscopy study to the patients 
with a low field strength equipment like a 1.5 T scanner 
usually require a long scan time and large voxel, due to 
low SNR caused by a low concentration of phosphorous 
metabolite in the lesion (3, 8). Recently, MRS apparatus has 
rapidly evolved to perform the study of a relatively small 
volume of voxel and in a reasonable scan time. We adapted 
a 27 mL voxel volume and a 6 minutes 36 seconds scan 
time, with a total scan time of 15 minutes, including the 
scanning for localization. We designed this study to obtain 
the MRS signal in vivo as soon as possible and to evaluate 
the clinical feasibility of </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS study. This scan time was 
tolerable for patients to obtain the MR imaging and the MR 
spectrum in a study. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P magnetic resonance spectroscopy study of human brain 
lesions has shown substantial variability. This variability 
reported in the literature seemed to have numerous causes. 
In another previous study (3), masses with a large portion 
of necrosis were excluded. They suspected that the amount 
of the necrosis or cystic portion in the brain tumor could 
create variability of the peak intensities of phosphorous 
metabolites in the same tumor group. Moreover, the 
peripheral located voxel and hemorrhage in a lesion may 
produce magnetic susceptibility artifact that causes a non-
diagnostic spectrum or distortion of spectrum. In order to </p>



<p>Ha et al. </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 14(3), May/Jun 2013 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>avoid the possibility of spectrum diversity by these causes, 
we excluded the brain lesions that have a large cyst, a large 
necrotic portion, hemorrhage, and were small peripheral 
located brain lesions, according to the routine brain MRI. </p>

<p>Conclusion 
The clinically applicable </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P MRS spectrum was obtained 
with a relatively short scan time and the pH, PME/PDE, 
PDE/Pi, PME/PCr, and PDE/PCr ratios seem to be useful 
parameters for the differentiation of the brain tumors. </p>



</text></tei>