<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3887290" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Carcinoma of unknown primary (CUP) is a clinical presentation with a poor prognosis. Inflammation-based 
prognostic systems are stage-independent prognostic predictors in various malignancies. We aimed to assess the accuracy of the 
modified Glasgow Prognostic Score (mGPS), neutrophil/lymphocyte ratio (NLR) and platelet/lymphocyte ratio (PLR) as objective 
prognostic models in CUP. </p>

<p>Methods: We derived inflammatory scores in 60 consecutive CUP referrals to the Imperial College oncology unit between 1996 
and 2011. Patient demographics, treatment and staging data and full blood profiles were collected. An independent cohort of 179 
patients presenting to the Taipei Veterens Hospital between 2000 and 2009 were used as a 'validation' data set. Uni-and 
multivariate survival analysis was used to predict the overall survival (OS). </p>

<p>Results: Sixty patients were included: median age 61 (range: 33-86); 51% men; median OS 5.9 months (0.7-42.9); 88% with distant 
metastases. On univariate analysis NLR 45 (P ¼ 0.04) and mGPS (score 1-2) (P ¼ 0.03) correlated with OS. Multivariate analysis 
demonstrated significant hazard ratios for NLR; 2.02 (CI 1.0-4.1) (P ¼ 0.04) and mGPS; 1.52 (CI 1.0-2.3) (P ¼ 0.03). These findings 
were reinforced by analysis of the validation data. </p>

<p>Conclusion: NLR and mGPS are independent, externally validated prognostic markers in CUP, with superior objectivity compared 
with performance status. </p>

<p><rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">11.5</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS</rs>Multivariate analysis identified both mGPS (HR 1.53 95% CI 
1.03-2.25, P ¼ 0.03) and NLR (HR 2.01 95% CI 1-4.09, P ¼ 0.04) 
as significant independent predictors of OS in CUP. </p>

<p>Validation of prognostic models. The NLR and GPS were further 
assessed for their prognostic power and discriminative ability in an 
independent and larger validation set. No significant differences </p>

<p>were observed on comparison of patients' clinico-pathological 
features across the two study population (Table 1). Both the NLR 
(median survival 11.1 vs 3.5 months; Po0.01) and mGPS (median 
survival 7.7 vs 3.0 vs 1.8 months for mGPS 0, 1 and 2, respectively; 
P o0.01) remained significant predictors of OS on univariate 
analysis, mGPS HR 2.16 (95% CI 1.52-3.08); Po0.01 and NLR HR 
2.46 (95% CI 1.66-3.66); Po0.01. A combined prognostic score 
using both NLR and mGPS was then derived using logistic 
regression to determine the predicted probability of death. A model 
for predicted probability of death was determined to be calculated 
by the equation 1/(1 þ exp( À f)), where f ¼ À 0.3357 þ (06043* 
mGPS) þ (0.6147*NLR). Subsequent ROC analysis resulted in a C 
statistic of 0.65 (95% CI 0.55-0.75). 
In addition, 66% of the validation population received palliative 
chemotherapy. Regimes were predominantly cisplatin-based 
(75.4%), with 43% receiving additional 5-fluorouracil (5-FU) and 
11% being taxane based. The treated cohort were significantly 
younger (mean age 65.5 vs 74.4 years, Po0.01) and had a better PS 
(Po0.01). The results suggest a survival benefit in those patients 
who received palliative chemotherapy compared with those who 
did not (9.2 months vs 1.6 months Po0.01). In addition to this, 
evaluation of mGPS (median survival mGPS 0; 23.3 vs 4.6 months, 
mGPS 1; 12.8 vs 2.1 months and mGPS 2; 2.9 vs 0.4 months 
Po0.01) and NLR (median survival NLR o5 10.2 vs 7 months and 
NLR 45 21.2 vs 3.5 months Po0.01) correlates with improved 
prognosis in the treated group (Table 4). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Primary peritoneal 
4 (7) 
0 (0) 
Adenocarcinoma of axillary glands 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
Squamous carcinoma of cervical glands 
1 (2) 
0 (0) 
Neuroendocrine 
2 (3) 
12 (1) 
CUP of single location 
1 (2) 
0 (0) </p>

<p>Non-specific subset </p>

<p>Favourable prognosis 
8 (13) 
42 (23) 
Poor prognosis 
33 (55) 
125 (70) </p>

<p>Site of metastatic disease </p>

<p>Liver 
Table 3. Inflammation-based prognostic scoring systems: training set univariate and multivariate survival analysis </p>

<p>Variable 
Univariate HR (95% CI) 
P-value 
Multivariate HR (95% CI) 
P-value </p>

<p>PLR o300/X300 (N ¼ 60) 
0.83 (0.39-1.72) 
0.6 
-
-</p>

<p>NLR o5/X5 (N ¼ 60) 
2.06 (1.04-4.08) 
0.04 
2.01 (1.0-4.09) 
0.04 </p>

<p>mGPS (N ¼ 46) 
1.55 (1.05-2.29) 
0.03 
1.53 (1.03-2.25) 
0.03 </p>

<p>PS (N ¼ 49) 
2.23 
o0.01 
-
-</p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI ¼ confidence interval; HR ¼ hazard ratio; mGPS ¼ modified Glasgow Prognostic Score; NLR ¼ neutrophillymphocyte ratio; PLR ¼ platelet lymphocyte ratio; PS ¼ performance 
status. Associations reaching statistical significance (Po0.05) are highlighted in bold. </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>NLR </p>

<p>NLR&gt;5 </p>

<p>NLR&lt;5 </p>

<p>NLR&lt;5-censored </p>

<p>NLR&gt;5-censored </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.00 10.00 20.00 30.00 40.00 50.00 
Time (months) </p>

<p>0.4 
Overall survival (proportion) </p>

<p>Figure 1. Kaplan-Meier curve demonstrating the relationship between 
NLR score and survival in CUP in the training data set. 
. </p>

<p>1.0 
mGPS 0 </p>

<p>mGPS </p>

<p>mGPS 1 </p>

<p>mGPS 2 </p>

<p>mGPS 0-censored </p>

<p>mGPS 1-censored </p>

<p>mGPS 2-censored </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.00 10.00 20.00 30.00 40.00 50.00 </p>

<p>Time (months) </p>

<p>0.4 
Overall survival (proportion) </p>

<p>Figure 2. Kaplan-Meier curve demonstrating the relationship between 
mGPS and survival in CUP in the training data set. 
. </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>Performance status </p>

<p>PS 2-3 </p>

<p>PS 0-1 </p>

<p>PS 0-1-censored </p>

<p>PS 2-3-censored </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.00 10.00 20.00 30.00 40.00 50.00 </p>

<p>Time (months) </p>

<p>0.4 
Overall survival (proportion) </p>

<p>Figure 3. Kaplan-Meier curve demonstrating the relationship between 
PS and survival in CUP in the training data set. 
. </p>

<p>Table 4. Comparison of deranged inflammatory score and overall survival 
in patients receiving and declined chemotherapy in the validation set </p>

<p>Median survival (months) </p>

<p>Inflammation-
based system </p>

<p>Chemotherapy 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>No 
chemotherapy 
(95% CI) 
P-value </p>

<p>NLR o5 (N ¼ 72) 
21.2 (14.8-27.4) 
7.0 (3.9-10.1) 
o0.01 </p>

<p>NLR 45 (N ¼ 117) 
10.2 (5.9-14.5) 
3.5 (1.0-6.0) </p>

<p>mGPS 0 (N ¼ 42) 
23.3 (11.7-35.3) 
4.6 (3.1-6.0) 
o0.01 </p>

<p>mGPS 1 (N ¼ 53) 
12.8 (4.5-21.1) 
2.1 (0.7-3.4) 
mGPS 2 (N ¼ 19) 
2.9 (2.1-3.8) 
0.4 (0.1-0.6) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI ¼ confidence interval; mGPS ¼ modified Glasgow Prognostic Score; 
NLR ¼ neutrophillymphocyte ratio. Associations reaching statistical significance (Po0.05) 
are highlighted in bold. </p>

<p>Inflammatory indices in CUP 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.683 </p>

<p>
groups prior to considering therapy. PSX2, hypoalbuminaemia, 
hypercalcaemia, raised LDH and number of metastatic sites have all 
been shown to be poor prognostic factors (Seve et al, 2006a,b;  Trivanovic et al, 2009; Kodaira et al, 2010; Chen et al, 2012). Although 
our study has demonstrated a negative trend with some of these 
factors no statistical significant associations with OS were observed. 
Variations between our results and those previously published maybe 
explained by the renown heterogeneity of CUP which may explain the 
variability in assessing prognostic traits. There is limited published 
literature to suggest the role of tumour markers as a prognostic 
marker in CUP (Milovic et al, 2002). However, in future studies it 
may be of interest to further evaluate the interplay between tumour 
marker burden and inflammatory scores. 
The relatively small sample size of the training set and the 
retrospective nature of our study should be acknowledged as 
potential limitations. In addition, although there is a postulated 
pathological inflammatory mechanism in carcinogenesis that 
forms the basis of both the NLR and mGPS, it must be recognised 
that infection and concomitant therapy with corticosteroids are 
also common causes for a measurable inflammatory response 
which may alter the prognostic utility of these parameters. 
Nonetheless, the number of deaths on which our survival analysis 
was powered, in conjunction with the process of external validation 
in a larger and independent case series leaves little doubt regarding 
the utility of mGPS and NLR as predictors of survival in patients 
with CUP. 
Although the number of studies supporting the clinical use of 
inflammation-based prognostic models is increasing, including a 
study of 25 000 patients showing the stage and histotype-
independence of the prognostic information produced by inflam-
matory scores in solid tumours, the molecular mechanisms 
sustaining cancer-related inflammation remains poorly understood 
(Ramsey et al, 2007; Sharma et al, 2008; Proctor et al, 2011). It has 
been postulated that tumour hypoxia and necrosis triggers a variety 
of host responses. These include an alteration in the metabolic, 
haematopoietic and neuroendocrine environment including 
inflammatory cytokines and haematopoietic growth factors. 
Numerous cytokines have been implicated in the pro-inflamma-
tory response associated with malignancy but no one cytokine has 
been found to be pathogenic and it is likely that a complex 
interplay of cytokines drive the inflammatory process. For 
example, a recent study in patients with advanced colorectal 
cancer failed to show any correlation between NLR and circulating 
levels of IL-6 or TNF-a suggesting that further research is required 
in this area in order to define the possible cytokine relationship 
with carcinogenesis, especially as this may yield a therapeutic 
strategy to modulate the inflammatory response (Chua et al, 2012). 
The NLR is associated with a derangement in CRP, correspond-
ing to a pathological inflammatory state in cancer (Chua et al,  2012). A neutrophilic environment, which corresponds to a 
deranged NLR, results in infiltration of tumour cells and is 
responsible for the transformation to a metastatic phenotype 
(Tazawa et al, 2003). This maybe a result of protease-mediated 
extracellular digestion of the tumour basement membrane 
(Engbring and Kleinman, 2003). This degradation leads to the 
release of growth factors and other pro-mitotic cytokines. Thus, 
derangement of the NLR reflects a pro-inflammatory milieu which 
may contribute to a poor prognosis. 
Hypoalbuminaemia is a recognised poor prognostic factor in 
CUP and represents a state of progressive malnutrition. The 
inflammatory response is a critical driver of cancer-related 
cachexia, where a hyper-catabolic state results in increased toxicity 
and reduced tolerance of chemotherapy (Esper and Harb, 2005). 
In summary, the present study supports the prognostic utility of 
systemic inflammation-based scores in CUP. The mGPS and NLR 
are easily deducible, universally available and inexpensive prognos-
ticators that can be routinely used in clinical practice and are both a </p>

<p>more objective measure of patients' prognosis when compared with 
PS. Thus, measurement of systemic inflammation should be 
considered in the routine assessment of patients with CUP. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors would like to acknowledge Dr Les Huson for his 
statistical support. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>



<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Inflammatory indices in CUP </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.683 </p>



<p>This work is published under the standard license to publish agree-
ment. After 12 months the work will become freely available and 
the license terms will switch to a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. </p>

<p>Inflammatory indices in CUP 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.683 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>