<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3514035" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Epithelial junction assembly and morphogenesis are driven by a 
complex set of cytoskeletal rearrangements that drive dynamic 
membrane remodeling and the necessary cell shape changes that 
underlie the formation of functional epithelial tissues (Nelson,  2009). Although there are variations among different epithelia, 
junction formation is generally induced by filopodia or lamelli-
podia initiating cell-cell contact followed by junction formation 
and maturation, leading to the establishment of mature tight and 
adherens junctions (Vasioukhin et al., 2000; Matter and Balda,  2003b; Miyoshi and Takai, 2008; Nelson, 2009). Actin remod-
eling underlies these morphological transitions and needs to 
be carefully controlled to allow the coordinated assembly of a 
functional apical junctional complex (Vasioukhin et al., 2000;  Redd et al., 2004; Chhabra and Higgs, 2007). 
RhoGTPases are central regulatory switches that guide 
actin organization, junction formation, and epithelial differentiation </p>

<p>(Braga and Yap, 2005; Jaffe and Hall, 2005; Ridley, 2006). 
They are regulated by factors that catalyze the switch between 
the active, GTP-bound state, and the inactive, GDP-bound state: 
activation is mediated by guanine nucleotide exchange factors 
(GEFs) and inactivation by GTPase-activating proteins (GAPs; 
Bos et al., 2007). The RhoGTPase Cdc42 is an evolutionarily 
conserved regulator of cell polarization and regulates differ-
ent steps of junction formation from filopodial extension to 
junctional maturation; hence, mechanisms must exist that ac-
tivate and inactivate Cdc42 in a temporally controlled manner 
at specific subcellular sites to permit progression of dynamic 
morphological processes (Matter and Balda, 2003b; Iden and  Collard, 2008). Although activation of Cdc42 is generally seen 
as the critical step, expression of dominant-negative and consti-
tutively active mutants of Cdc42 revealed that inhibition as well 
as overstimulation of Cdc42 signaling prevents normal junction 
formation and differentiation (Kroschewski et al., 1999; Rojas  et al., 2001; Bruewer et al., 2004). Hence, negative regulation 
of Cdc42 is important for the successful completion of com-
plex sequential Cdc42-driven processes. This is supported by </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>pithelial cell-cell adhesion and morphogenesis 
require dynamic control of actin-driven membrane 
remodeling. The Rho guanosine triphosphatase 
(GTPase) Cdc42 regulates sequential molecular processes 
during cell-cell junction formation; hence, mechanisms must 
exist that inactivate Cdc42 in a temporally and spatially 
controlled manner. In this paper, we identify SH3BP1, a 
GTPase-activating protein for Cdc42 and Rac, as a regu-
lator of junction assembly and epithelial morphogenesis 
using a functional small interfering ribonucleic acid screen. 
Depletion of SH3BP1 resulted in loss of spatial control of </p>

<p>Cdc42 activity, stalled membrane remodeling, and en-
hanced growth of filopodia. SH3BP1 formed a complex with 
JACOP/paracingulin, a junctional adaptor, and CD2AP, a 
scaffolding protein; both were required for normal Cdc42 
signaling and junction formation. The filamentous actin-
capping protein CapZ also associated with the SH3BP1 
complex and was required for control of actin remodel-
ing. Epithelial junction formation and morphogenesis thus 
require a dual activity complex, containing SH3BP1 and 
CapZ, that is recruited to sites of active membrane remod-
eling to guide Cdc42 signaling and cytoskeletal dynamics. </p>

<p>Epithelial junction formation requires confinement of 
Cdc42 activity by a novel SH3BP1 complex </p>

<p>Ahmed Elbediwy, 
1 Ceniz Zihni, 
1 Stephen J. Terry, 
1 Peter Clark, 
2 Karl Matter, 
1 and Maria S. Balda </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 Department of Cell Biology, Institute of Ophthalmology, University College London, EC1V 9EL London, England, UK 
2 National Heart and Lung Institute, Imperial College London, South Kensington Campus, SW7 2AZ London, England, UK </p>

<p>© 2012 Elbediwy et al. This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution-
Noncommercial-Share Alike-No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the pub-
lication date (see http://www.rupress.org/terms). After six months it is available under a 
Creative Commons License (Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, 
as described at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). </p>

<p>T H E J O U R N A L O F C E L L B I O L O G Y </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 198 • NUMBER 4 • 2012 
678 </p>

<p>Figure 1. SH3BP1 depletion disrupts epithelial cell-cell junctions. (A and B) Caco-2 cells were transfected with control and Cdc42-directed siRNAs (50 nM) 
and then analyzed by immunoblotting (A) and immunofluorescence (B). Shown are epifluorescence images. (C) Caco-2 cells were transfected with myc-
tagged Cdc42L61, a constitutively active mutant, and then stained for ZO-1 and the transfected protein. (D) Summary of RhoGTPases and GAPs identified 
in the functional siRNA screen (see also Table S1). (E-L) Caco-2 cells were transfected with siRNAs as indicated and then analyzed by immunofluorescence 
(E and G-L) or immunoblotting (F). Apart from F-actin, shown are images of markers for tight junctions (E and G), adherens junctions (H), and basolateral 
and apical cell surface domains (K). Shown are epifluorescence (D and F-K) and confocal (L, xy and z sections are provided) images. For F-actin, apical 
and basal focal planes are shown. Panel I shows a quantification of the effect on the subcellular distribution of F-actin (counting cells with strongly induced 
basal F-actin; mean basal actin intensity increased by &gt;60% in SH3BP1-depleted cells) and three junctional markers (counting cells with discontinuous, 
irregular junctional staining). Shown are means ± 1 SD, representing the cells in at least five different fields per condition (n ≥ 5). Note that assembly of 
tight and adherens junctions is affected, but different components are affected to different extents. (M-O) Complementation of SH3BP1 siRNA transfection 
with a siRNA-resistant cDNA. Caco-2 cells were first transfected with siRNAs as indicated and then, after 3 d, with a plasmid carrying the siRNA-resistant 
cDNA. Cells were then analyzed by immunoblotting (M) or immunofluorescence (N). Panel O shows a quantification of the ZO-1 staining (six fields for each 
condition). The arrowheads in N point to staining for myc-SH3BP1 along cell-cell contacts. Error bars show SDs. Bars, 10 µm. p, phosphorylated. </p>

<p> 
Spatial control of Cdc42 and junction formation • Elbediwy et al. </p>

<p>the finding that Rich1, a GAP for Cdc42, is required for full 
polarization of epithelial cells (Wells et al., 2006). However, 
Rich1 is thought to regulate polarization once junctions are as-
sembled, as it is not required for membrane dynamics and adhe-
rens junction assembly. Whether specific GAPs are required for 
junction assembly and are important to maintain actin dynamics 
and membrane remodeling is not known. Moreover, it is likely 
that GTPase regulation is tightly connected to other regulators 
of actin dynamics; however, little is known about specific mo-
lecular cross talk that would mediate such cooperative regula-
tory mechanisms. 
Here, we use a functional siRNA screen to identify GAPs 
important for epithelial morphogenesis that led to the identifica-
tion of SH3BP1 as a crucial regulator of epithelial junction for-
mation and morphogenesis. SH3BP1 is a GAP for Rac and Cdc42 
(Cicchetti et al., 1995; Parrini et al., 2011), and our data show that 
its depletion leads to spatial and temporal deregulation of Cdc42 
and, depending on the cell model, a modest effect on Rac activa-
tion. SH3BP1 forms a complex with two scaffolding proteins and 
the F-actin-capping protein CapZ, suggesting that this regulatory 
complex represents a dual activity module that links regulation of 
Cdc42 and actin dynamics during membrane remodeling and 
junction formation. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>SH3BP1 is required for epithelial junction </p>

<p>formation and morphogenesis </p>

<p>We used the intestinal epithelial cell line Caco-2 as a model 
system to screen for functionally relevant Rho GAPs, as these 
cells form polarized monolayers and can be efficiently trans-
fected with siRNAs (Terry et al., 2011). The siRNA-mediated 
depletion of Cdc42 was efficient and led to flatter cells with 
a disrupted distribution of ZO-1, a tight junction protein, and 
-catenin, a component of adherens junctions as well as re-
duced and disorganized expression of the apical marker DPPIV 
and the basolateral protein Na 
+ K </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-ATPase (Fig. 1, A and B). 
Similarly, overexpression of constitutively active Cdc42, myc-
Cdc42L61, disrupted the normal organization of cell junctions 
and the actin cytoskeleton in Caco-2 as well as in the epider-
mal carcinoma cell line A431 (Fig. 1 C and Fig. S1 A). Hence, 
inhibition as well as overstimulation of Cdc42 interferes with 
normal epithelial junction formation and differentiation as pre-
viously observed in other epithelial cell systems (Kroschewski  et al., 1999; Rojas et al., 2001; Bruewer et al., 2004). 
We next combined this morphological assay for junction 
assembly and polarization with an siRNA library targeting 
RhoGTPases and GAPs to identify RhoGTPase regulators im-
portant for junction formation. Potential candidates identified in 
the first round of screening using standard siRNAs were retested 
in a second round using siRNAs modified to enhance specificity 
(Tables S1, S2, and S3). 
Depletion of the two RhoGTPases RhoA and Cdc42 led 
to clearly the strongest phenotypes followed by the Cdc42 GAP 
SH3BP1 and two RhoA GAPs, OPHN1 and MYO9A (Fig. 1 D 
and Fig. S1 B). Regulation of RhoA is crucial during epithelial 
junction formation (Terry et al., 2011), and both identified RhoA </p>

<p>GAPs MYO9A (Abouhamed et al., 2009; Omelchenko and  Hall, 2012) and OPHN1 (Fig. S1, C-E) localize to the junctional 
complex. OPHN1 has also GAP activity for Rac and Cdc42 
in vitro; however, its main function in vivo seems to be regulation 
of RhoA (Billuart et al., 1998; Khelfaoui et al., 2009). 
Depletion of SH3BP1 caused the strongest phenotype of 
all GAPs tested. Subsequent analysis in Caco-2 cells using dif-
ferent siRNAs resulted in monolayers that failed to assemble a 
normal junctional actin belt and exhibited a strong induction of 
basal F-actin, often in an astral shape along cell borders (Fig. 1, 
E and F). Similar patterns of disorganized actin were observed 
when cells were stained with -actin antibodies instead of phal-
loidin (Fig. S2 A). Tight and adherens junctions were also af-
fected, as markers such as ZO-1, cingulin, E-cadherin, and p120 
catenin exhibited enhanced cytoplasmic staining and were less 
concentrated along cell-cell contacts (Fig. 1, G-I). Cells also 
failed to differentiate normally, as the distributions of DPPIV 
and Na </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-ATPase were disrupted, although expression levels 
were not affected (Fig. 1 K and Fig. S2 B). Depleted cells re-
mained flat and did not form columnar cells with distinct tight 
and adherens junctions and, hence, were less densely packed 
(Fig. 1 L). Similarly, in SH3BP1-depleted human corneal epi-
thelial (HCE) cells, a squamous epithelial cell type, ZO-1, did 
not form a continuous junctional belt, and the adherens junc-
tion marker -catenin accumulated in filopodia-like structures 
(Fig. S2 C). In the epidermal carcinoma cell line A431, deple-
tion also triggered a reorganization of F-actin, resulting in 
accumulation of filopodia (Fig. S2 D). SH3BP1 is thus required 
for normal junction formation in epithelial cell models originat-
ing from different tissues and representing different types of 
epithelia. The accumulation of filopodia suggests that depletion 
may lead to deregulation of Cdc42. 
We next introduced silent mutations into an SH3BP1 
cDNA to generate an siRNA-resistant construct. Immuno-
blotting demonstrated that the construct was efficiently ex-
pressed in cells transfected with control and SH3BP1-specific 
siRNAs (Fig. 1 M). Immunofluorescence revealed that the 
siRNA-resistant construct indeed counteracted the depletion-
induced phenotype (Fig. 1, N and O). Ectopically expressed 
SH3BP1 was enriched at cell-cell junctions, suggesting that 
the GAP may interact with junctional components. However, 
the overexpressed protein also accumulated in the cytosol, 
suggesting that its targeting is easily saturated or may be a 
dynamically regulated. 
We next asked whether Caco-2 cells were still able to 
form functional tight junctions upon depletion of SH3BP1. To 
monitor de novo junction formation, we performed Ca switch 
assays, in which cells are plated in low calcium and junction 
formation is then induced in a synchronized manner by the 
addition of calcium. Cells spread out normally after calcium 
addition, but conversion to a continuous peripheral actin belt 
did not occur, and junctional markers were not recruited effi-
ciently (Fig. 2, A-D; and Fig. S2, E and F). Consequently, the 
barrier properties of SH3BP1-depleted cells were strongly 
compromised (Fig. 2, E and F). 
During de novo junction formation in keratinocytes, filopo-
dia initiate cell-cell contacts followed by formation of a zipperlike </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 198 • NUMBER 4 • 2012 </p>

<p>
followed by formation of continuous adherens junctions over 
the course of a few hours (Fig. 2, G and H). In contrast, SH3BP1-
depleted cells formed contacts, but they did not progress beyond 
the stage of forming intercalating filopodia, indicating that 
SH3BP1 is required for the transition from early cell-cell contacts 
to cell junctions. </p>

<p>belt that precedes formation of mature junctions (Vasioukhin  et al., 2000). Therefore, the accumulation of filopodia in 
SH3BP1-depleted A431 may reflect a failure in the transition 
from filopodia to cell junctions. Addition of calcium to A431 
cells plated in low calcium resulted in the induction of filopo-
dia-based cell-cell contacts, enriched in F-actin and E-cadherin, </p>

<p>Figure 2. SH3BP1 regulates epithelial junction formation. (A-F) Caco-2 cells transfected with siRNAs were plated in low calcium medium before adding 
calcium to induce junction formation, which was followed by staining with fluorescent phalloidin (A), ZO-1 (B), E-cadherin (C), p120 catenin (D), or by 
measuring transepithelial electrical resistance (TER; E). (F) After 48 h, paracellular tracer diffusion was measured. E and F show means ± 1 SD; n = 3. 
(G and H) siRNA-transfected A431 cells were plated in low calcium medium and then stimulated for different periods of time with calcium to induce junc-
tion formation. Shown are images of cells stained phalloidin (G) or with anti-E-cadherin antibodies (H). Note that depletion of SH3BP1 leads to a strong 
induction of E-cadherin-positive filopodia. Bars, 10 µm. p, phosphorylated. </p>

<p> 
Spatial control of Cdc42 and junction formation • Elbediwy et al. </p>

<p>at cell junctions. Conversely, inhibition of EGF receptor signal-
ing with PD153035 led to a reduction of junctional SH3BP1 
(Fig. 4 F). Depending on the cellular context, EGF signaling 
can stimulate cell scattering and junctional remodeling as well 
as junction stabilization and enhanced barrier function (Van  Itallie et al., 1995; Singh and Harris, 2004; Brown et al., 2006;  Flores-Benítez et al., 2007; Terakado et al., 2011; Al Moustafa  et al., 2012). Hence, SH3BP1 may also support junction forma-
tion in response to EGF. A431 cells, in which SH3BP1 regulates 
calcium-induced junction assembly (Fig. 2), are well suited to 
address this question as their junctional integrity is EGF depen-
dent (Van Itallie et al., 1995). 
In serum-starved A431 cells, both SH3BP1 and ZO-1 
were mostly cytosolic. Addition of EGF led to the quick induc-
tion of dorsal ruffles to which ZO-1 and other junctional pro-
teins were recruited before appearing at cell junctions along 
with the formation of a junctional actin belt (Fig. 5 A). SH3BP1 
was quickly recruited to dorsal ruffles, indicating that the GAP 
associates with EGF-induced sites of actin remodeling. 
We next tested whether SH3BP1 is also required for EGF-
induced actin reorganization and junction formation. Indeed, 
depletion of the GAP inhibited dorsal ruffle formation, and the 
cells grew abundant and long filopodia (Fig. 5, B and C). Dorsal 
recruitment of junctional proteins was consequently also inhib-
ited (Fig. 6 A). Time-lapse microscopy with cells expressing 
GFP-actin further indicated that depletion of SH3BP1 strongly 
attenuated EGF-induced actin remodeling. Whereas control 
siRNA-transfected cells formed extensive and dynamic dorsal 
ruffles that exhibited the same morphology as in fixed cells, 
SH3BP1-depleted cells showed little signs of actin dynamics 
apart from the slow growth of filopodia (Fig. 6 B and Videos 1, 
2, 3, and 4). 
To determine whether SH3BP1 is generally required 
for EGF receptor trafficking and/or signaling, we stimulated </p>

<p>We next determined whether SH3BP1 is also important 
for epithelial morphogenesis in an organotypic 3D culture 
system. Fig. 3 A shows that depletion of the GAP resulted in 
generally smaller and poorly organized cysts. Actin staining 
demonstrated that SH3BP1 depletion led to cysts that often 
formed multiple instead of a single lumen (Fig. 3 B). Quanti-
fication of these experiments indeed supported the conclusion 
that SH3BP1 is essential for epithelial morphogenesis in a 3D 
culture system (Fig. 3 C). These experiments thus indicate that 
SH3BP1 is a critical regulator of junction formation and epi-
thelial morphogenesis in cell models derived from different 
epithelial tissues. </p>

<p>SH3BP1 colocalizes with the </p>

<p>junctional complex </p>

<p>As overexpressed SH3BP1 was recruited to cell junctions 
(Fig. 1 N), we tested whether endogenous SH3BP1 also as-
sociates with cell junctions. Fig. 4 A shows that staining for 
SH3BP1 was indeed enriched at the junctional complex. Junc-
tional SH3BP1 overlapped with -catenin and occludin. There 
was also staining in the nucleus and the cytosol; however, only 
the junctional staining completely disappeared when SH3BP1 
was depleted, suggesting that the nonjunctional staining might 
be partly nonspecific (Fig. 4 B). Confocal microscopy further 
supported the junctional association of SH3BP1 and suggested a 
closer association with adherens than tight junctions (Fig. 4 C). 
In mouse colon, SH3BP1 and ZO-1 also overlapped, suggesting 
that the GAP associates with cell junctions in vivo (Fig. 4 D). Dur-
ing de novo junction formation, SH3BP1 was recruited early to 
forming junctions along with E-cadherin, in agreement with a 
role in junction assembly (Fig. 4 E). 
During the localization experiments, we observed that 
serum-starved cells had lower levels of junctional SH3BP1 
(Fig. S3 A). Addition of EGF led to a rapid increase of the GAP </p>

<p>Figure 3. SH3BP1 regulates epithelial morphogenesis. (A-C) Caco-2 cells were transfected with siRNAs and then plated in a 3D matrix. After 5 d, the 
cells were fixed and first analyzed by phase-contrast microscopy (A) before staining with fluorescent phalloidin and Hoechst followed by confocal micros-
copy (B). Note that SH3BP1 depletion leads to smaller and often disorganized cysts. The effect of SH3BP1 depletion was quantified by counting normally 
organized cysts with a single lumen and disorganized cysts with no or multiple lumen (only cysts that had reached a minimal size of 30-µm diameter were 
considered for the morphological quantification to avoid a bias because of the smaller cysts). Shown are means ± 1 SD of three independent experiments 
(n = 3). Bars, 10 µm. p, phosphorylated. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 198 • NUMBER 4 • 2012 </p>

<p>
functional GAP domain could not (Fig. 6, C-F). Expression of 
the GAP mutant in control siRNA-transfected cells already 
stimulated filopodia, suggesting that it functioned as a dominant-
negative mutant (Fig. 6 F). The GAP activity of SH3BP1 is thus 
important for its role in junction formation. 
We next measured the effect of SH3BP1 depletion on the 
levels of active Cdc42 and Rac in A431 cell extracts. In serum-
starved cells, levels of Cdc42 were low and increased upon in-
duction of junction formation by EGF (Fig. 7 A). Depletion of 
SH3BP1 indeed strongly elevated levels of active Cdc42 during 
the entire EGF time course, which is in agreement with the ob-
served accumulation of filopodia (Fig. 5). The effect of EGF 
and SH3BP1 depletion on Rac was limited. A significant small 
increase in response to depletion of the GAP was only observed 
after 15 min of EGF stimulation. This indicates that SH3BP1 
plays a major role in the regulation of Cdc42 and a more modest 
role in guiding Rac signaling during junction formation. </p>

<p>siRNA-transfected cells with fluorescent EGF to monitor recep-
tor internalization. However, the ligand was still internalized 
in depleted cells, although apparently more slowly (Fig. S3 B). 
There was no inhibition of extracellular signal-regulated kinase 
(Erk) activation apparent (Fig. S3 C). Thus, SH3BP1 is not re-
quired for EGF receptor signaling per se but for normal actin 
dynamics and junction assembly. </p>

<p>SH3BP1 spatially restricts </p>

<p>Cdc42 signaling </p>

<p>SH3BP1 is a RhoGAP that stimulates GTP hydrolysis by Rac 
and Cdc42 in vitro and in vivo (Cicchetti et al., 1995; Parrini  et al., 2011). To test the importance of this GAP activity, we 
generated an siRNA-resistant construct carrying a substitution 
of a conserved arginine residue required for GAP activity (Bos  et al., 2007). Whereas the wild-type protein could rescue junc-
tion formation in siRNA-transfected cells, the protein lacking a </p>

<p>Figure 4. SH3BP1 associates with the epithelial junctional complex. (A-C) Caco-2 cells were processed for immunofluorescence with the indicated 
antibodies and then analyzed by epifluorescence (A and B) or confocal microscopy (C, xy and z sections are shown). For B, cells were transfected with 
siRNAs as indicated to determine the specificity of the SH3BP1 staining. (D) Frozen sections of mouse colon were stained with antibodies against SH3BP1 
and ZO-1. Shown are confocal sections. The overlay also includes a nuclear stain in blue. (E) Junction formation by Caco-2 cells plated in low calcium 
was stimulated with calcium for the indicated periods to time. The cells were then fixed and stained for SH3BP1 and E-cadherin. Arrowheads mark early 
E-cadherin-and SH3BP1-positive junctions. (F) Caco-2 cells were stained for SH3BP1 after an incubation with the EGF receptor inhibitor PD153035 or, 
as a solvent control, DMSO. Bars, 10 µm. </p>

<p> 
Spatial control of Cdc42 and junction formation • Elbediwy et al. </p>

<p>Figure 5. SH3BP1 regulates EGF-induced dorsal ruffling and junction formation. (A) A431 cells were serum starved and then stimulated with EGF as 
indicated. Cells were then fixed, stained, and analyzed by epifluorescence. For the last time point, images from apical and basal focal planes are shown. 
(B and C) Serum-starved and siRNA-transfected A431 cells were stimulated with EGF and then stained with fluorescent phalloidin and antibodies against 
SH3BP1. Shown are epifluorescence images. C shows images from the dorsal aspects of the cells. Bars, 10 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 198 • NUMBER 4 • 2012 </p>

<p>
Figure 6. The GAP activity of SH3BP1 is required for junction formation. (A) A431 cells were transfected with siRNAs, serum starved, and then stimulated 
with EGF for 5 min. After fixation, the cells were stained as indicated. Shown are epifluorescence images from the dorsal aspect of the cells. Note that A431 
dorsal ruffles are positive for SH3BP1, -catenin, and ZO-1, which are disrupted upon SH3BP1 depletion. (B) GFP-actin-expressing A431 cells were trans-
fected with siRNAs, serum starved, and then stimulated with EGF. Shown are images of time-lapse recordings taken from the dorsal aspect of the cells. See 
also Videos 1, 2, 3, and 4. (C-F) A431 cells were transfected with the indicated siRNAs and, after 3 d, with RNAi-resistant cDNAs encoding HA-tagged 
wild-type or GAP-deficient SH3BP1. The cells were serum depleted, stimulated with EGF, and then analyzed by immunoblotting (C) and immunofluores-
cence (D-F). E shows a quantification of cells with junctional ZO-1 staining. Shown are means ± 1 SD, representing the cells in at least seven different fields 
per condition (n ≥ 7). Note that mutant SH3BP1 has a strong dominant-negative effect on the actin organization. Bars: (A, D, and F) 10 µm; (B) 5 µm. </p>

<p> 
Spatial control of Cdc42 and junction formation • Elbediwy et al. </p>

<p>junctional Rac1 staining was not observed. As we did also not 
obtain clear phenotypes in response to Rac1 depletion or in-
hibition, Rac1 does not seem to be of importance for junction 
formation in Caco-2 cells. 
As depletion of SH3BP1 led to loss of spatial control of 
Cdc42 activity, partial depletion of the GTPase might be able to 
recover the phenotype; hence, we transfected Cdc42-specific 
siRNAs at suboptimal concentrations either together with non-
targeting or SH3BP1-targeting siRNAs. Fig. 8 A shows that 
20-and 30-nM Cdc42-specific siRNAs led to a partial depletion 
of the GTPase; depletion of the GAP was not affected by the 
cotransfection of different siRNAs. Partial depletion of Cdc42 
already interfered with normal junctional assembly but, as 
expected, not as efficiently as at optimal siRNA concentrations 
(Fig. 8, B and C). In SH3BP1-depleted cells, partial Cdc42 
depletion counteracted the phenotype, and cells formed more 
regular monolayers with assembled junctions, indicating that 
Cdc42 is a major functional target of SH3BP1. These data thus 
indicate that SH3BP1 is an important regulator of epithelial 
Cdc42 signaling by controlling the spatial organization of the 
active RhoGTPase, which is supported by the accumulation of 
SH3BP1 in areas enriched in active Cdc42 during EGF-and 
calcium-induced junction assembly (Fig. S4, G and H). </p>

<p>SH3BP1 is part of a multimeric, </p>

<p>dual activity complex </p>

<p>We next asked whether junctional signaling scaffolds are im-
portant for SH3BP1 localization and function. Coimmuno-
precipitation revealed that SH3BP1 formed complexes with 
JACOP/paracingulin, a junctional protein known to affect 
RhoGTPase signaling, and CD2AP, a scaffolding protein impli-
cated in actin remodeling, in Caco-2 and A431 cells (Fig. 8,  A and B; Ohnishi et al., 2004; Bruck et al., 2006; Guillemot  et al., 2008; van Duijn et al., 2010; Roldan et al., 2011). JACOP 
antibodies coprecipitated not only the GAP but also CD2AP, 
suggesting that the three proteins may exist in a triple com-
plex. Coprecipitation of JACOP with other proteins was not 
detected, possibly reflecting the low signal obtained in immuno-
blots of total cell extracts. Coprecipitation of SH3BP1 with 
several other major components of tight and adherens junc-
tions was not observed (Fig. S5, A and B). Nevertheless, 
there was coprecipitation of afadin/AF-6, a protein that as-
sociates with nectins (Takai et al., 2008), in Caco-2 but not 
A431 cells, suggesting that SH3BP1 and afadin do not exist 
in stable complexes in all epithelial cells (Fig. S5 C). 
SH3BP1, JACOP, and CD2AP not only form a stable 
complex but were also found to colocalize at established and 
forming cell junctions (Fig. 9, C and D) and in EGF-induced 
dorsal ruffles (Fig. 9 E). Complex formation did not require 
EGF stimulation (Fig. S5 D), and recruitment of JACOP and 
CD2AP to cell junctions was, like SH3BP1, attenuated when 
the EGF receptor was inhibited (Fig. 9 F). Expression levels of 
the GAP were affected by depletion of JACOP and CD2AP, 
suggesting that complex formation may be important for stabili-
zation of SH3BP1 (Fig. S5 E). Complex formation was further 
supported by the enhanced recruitment of CD2AP and SH3BP1 
to cell junctions upon overexpression of JACOP (Fig. S5 F). </p>

<p>The enhanced filopodial growth and the increased levels 
of active Cdc42 suggest that SH3BP1 confines Cdc42 signaling 
and, thereby, promotes actin remodeling and junction forma-
tion. Hence, we used a fluoresecence/Förster resonance energy 
transfer (FRET)-based biosensor for Cdc42 to test whether 
depletion of SH3BP1 led to a loss of spatial control of Cdc42 
activity (Yoshizaki et al., 2003). In control A431 cells, higher 
mean FRET activities were measured along the apical surface 
than along the base of the cells (Fig. 7, B and C). In depleted 
cells, mean FRET activity was decreased at cell-cell contacts 
and increased along the base of the cells, correlating with the 
inhibition of junction formation (Fig. 7 C). 
We next used recently developed antibodies specific for 
the active form of Cdc42 to monitor activation of endogenous 
GTPases (Fig. S4, A and B, positive controls using Cdc42-
specific GEFs; Daubon et al., 2011; Navarro et al., 2011). In 
serum-starved A431 cells, staining intensity was low, reflecting 
the low levels of active Cdc42 and indicating that the antibody 
background was low (Fig. S4 C and Fig. 7 A, Cdc42 levels). 
Stimulation with EGF resulted in staining of dorsal ruffles within 
5 min, in agreement with the previously reported quick and sus-
tained accumulation of active Cdc42 in ruffles (Kurokawa et al.,  2004; Kovacs et al., 2006; King et al., 2011). Active Rac1 also 
increased in response to EGF and was more prominent along 
the dorsal aspects of the cells; however, it did not accumulate 
in the large ruffles as active Cdc42 (Fig. S4 D). This is also in 
agreement with the biosensor experiments by Kurokawa et al.  (2004), demonstrating that Rac is transiently activated during 
ruffle initiation in A431 cells (Kovacs et al., 2006; King et al.,  2011). Hence, the results obtained with these antibodies are in 
agreement with previous work on Rac and Cdc42 activation in 
the same model system. 
In SH3BP1-depleted cells, Cdc42 levels were already 
higher before adding EGF and then accumulated throughout the 
cells as well as in filopodia, indicating that the normal spatial 
organization was lost (Fig. S4 C). Active Rac1 often accumu-
lated in perinuclear cuplike structures in depleted cells, indicat-
ing that the spatial organization of Rac1 signaling was also 
partially disturbed (Fig. S4 D). Deregulated RhoGTPase signal-
ing was also suggested by the increased phosphorylation of co-
filin upon SH3BP1 depletion (Fig. S4 E). These observations 
thus indicate that SH3BP1 regulates the spatial organization of 
Cdc42 and, in a more modest manner, Rac1 activity. 
In Caco-2 cells, the GAP activity of SH3BP1 was also 
found to be important as the GAP-defective mutant was also 
found to exert a dominant-negative effect by inducing actin-rich 
membrane protrusions upon transfection, whereas the wild-type 
protein did not, even at high expression levels that oversaturated 
junctional recruitment (Fig. 7 D). Analysis of the spatial distri-
bution of Cdc42 activity supported the importance of SH3BP1 
in the regulation of RhoGTPase signaling, as active Cdc42 was 
enriched apically in control cells but preferentially basal and 
reduced along cell-cell contacts in depleted cells (Fig. 7, E and F). 
Staining with the antibodies recognizing active Cdc42 led to 
the same conclusion, as the staining was enriched at junc-
tions in control cells and dispersed in depleted cells (Fig. 7, 
G and H; and Fig. S4 F, Cdc42 siRNA control). Lateral or </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 198 • NUMBER 4 • 2012 </p>

<p>
Figure 7. Spatial regulation of Cdc42 activity by SH3BP1. (A) Levels of active Cdc42 and Rac1 were measured after serum starvation and stimulation with 
EGF in total cell extracts after transfection of either control or SH3BP1-targeting siRNAs. Shown are means ± 1 SD (n = 3). (B and C) A431 cells were first 
transfected with siRNAs and then with a biosensor to measure Cdc42 activity. The cells were then serum starved before stimulating for 10 min with EGF. 
FRET efficiency was then measured by confocal microscopy. Shown are apical and basal sections. A FRET efficiency scale is shown for the color coding 
(high FRET efficiency reflects high Cdc42 activity). B shows a quantification of the FRET images, using apical sections to compare internal and cell-cell 
contact signals and ratios of apical versus basal mean FRET signals. Shown are means of different fields ± 1 SD (n = 11). (D) HA-tagged SH3BP1 constructs 
encoding the wild-type or a GAP-deficient mutant (R312A) were transfected, and effects on F-actin and -catenin were analyzed by immunofluorescence 
and epifluorescence microscopy. (E and F) Caco-2 cells were first transfected with siRNAs and then with the Cdc42 biosensor. FRET efficiency was then 
measured by confocal microscopy. Shown are apical and basal sections. FRET images were quantified as in C. Shown are means of different fields ± 1 SD 
(n = 12). (G and H) Caco-2 cells were transfected with siRNAs and then analyzed by immunofluorescence using antibodies against GTP-bound Cdc42 and 
ZO-1. H shows a quantification of the number of cells with a defined lateral Cdc42 staining as opposed to the diffuse lateral staining observed in SH3BP1-
depleted cells. Shown are means ± 1 SD from six different fields (n = 6). Bars, 10 µm. </p>

<p> 
Spatial control of Cdc42 and junction formation • Elbediwy et al. </p>

<p>We next used recombinant proteins to map the interacting 
domains in SH3BP1. Recombinant full-length SH3BP1 as well 
as a fusion protein containing the C-terminal domain, which in-
cludes the SH3-binding domain, pulled down CD2AP (Fig. 9 G). 
JACOP was only pulled down by the N-terminal domain, sug-
gesting that the recombinant full-length protein might be in a 
confirmation that does not allow efficient binding. These binding 
experiments suggest that SH3BP1 might serve as a bridge, link-
ing JACOP to CD2AP. Indeed, coprecipitation of CD2AP with 
JACOP required SH3BP1, whereas depletion of CD2AP did not 
affect the coprecipitation efficiency of SH3BP1 with JACOP 
(Fig. 9 H). The N-terminal domain of SH3BP1 has recently been 
shown to associate with the exocyst in cells overexpressing the 
GAP (Parrini et al., 2011); however, we could not detect specific 
coprecipitation of endogenous proteins. 
Similar to SH3BP1, depletion of JACOP or CD2AP also 
led to an inhibition of actin remodeling and junction formation 
in both A431 and Caco-2 cells (Fig. 10, A and B; and Fig. S5,  G and H). Depletion of JACOP had the strongest effect on the 
lateral localization of the other components, suggesting that it 
serves as the primary junctional linker of the complex (Fig. 10 C). 
Depletion of neither JACOP nor CD2AP led to the same dis-
organized F-actin appearance, suggesting that disruption of the 
complex does not stimulate Cdc42. Indeed, depletion of either 
of the two scaffolding proteins reduced Cdc42 activity (Fig. 10 D), 
indicating that loss of normal complex formation leads to un-
controlled Cdc42 inactivation. 
Previous work showed that CD2AP binds and modulates 
the activity of CapZ1, a subunit of an F-actin-capping pro-
tein that regulates filopodial growth (Mejillano et al., 2004;   Bruck et al., 2006). Therefore, we asked whether the SH3BP1-
JACOP-paracingulin complex contains two actin-modulating 
activities: a Rho GAP and an F-actin-capping activity. Indeed, 
CapZ1 was detected in precipitates of SH3BP1 and the two 
scaffolding proteins (Fig. 9 B). CapZ1 was recruited to dorsal 
ruffles along with SH3BP1 in EGF-stimulated A431 cells but 
remained diffusely distributed in SH3BP1-depleted cells (Fig. 10 E). 
CapZ1 depletion indeed disrupted formation of a junctional 
actin belt and induced filopodia (Fig. 10, F and G). Thus, the 
identified SH3BP1 complex contains two activities that regulate 
the actin cytoskeleton: a GAP and a capping activity. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Here, we have shown that regulation of actin-driven membrane 
remodeling and junction formation requires an SH3BP1-based 
complex that modulates the actin cytoskeleton. This complex 
can regulate two processes: Cdc42 and Rac signaling via the 
GAP activity of SH3BP1 and actin polymerization via the cap-
ping activity of CapZ. It also contains two scaffolding proteins: 
CD2AP, a protein that is part of the submembrane actin cyto-
skeleton and binds and regulates CapZ, and JACOP, a junc-
tional protein that mediates subcellular targeting of SH3BP1. 
Depletion of SH3BP1 did not only lead to deregulation of 
Cdc42, but the enhanced and spatially deregulated activity led 
to the accumulation of large filopodia and a strong reduction 
of actin dynamics. Hence, maintenance of actin dynamics and 
morphological transitions rely not simply on Cdc42 activation 
but require the full GTPase cycle. This is supported by results 
with dominant-negative and constitutively active Cdc42 that </p>

<p>Figure 8. Cdc42 is a functionally important target of SH3BP1. Caco-2 cells were transfected with control, SH3BP1-, and Cdc42-specific siRNAs. For 
Cdc42, two different suboptimal concentrations, 20 and 30 nM, were used. (A and B) Depletion of SH3BP1 and Cdc42 was then analyzed by immuno-
blotting (A), and the effect on cell morphology and junction assembly was analyzed by immunofluorescence (B). (C) The effect on the ZO-1 distribution was 
then quantified as in Fig. 1 C. Shown are means ± 1 SD from three independent experiments (n = 3). The indicated p-values for double knockdown data 
are for comparisons with single SH3BP1 and Cdc42 depletions. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 198 • NUMBER 4 • 2012 </p>

<p>
Figure 9. SH3BP1 forms a complex with CD2AP and the junctional scaffold JACOP. (A and B) Extracts from Caco-2 (A) and A431 (B) cells were subjected 
to immunoprecipitation with the indicated antibodies. An IgG control from the same species as each of the specific primary antibodies is shown. The JACOP 
antibody recognized only a weak band in total cell extracts, and coprecipitation of this protein could not be detected. (C) Caco-2 cells were fixed and 
processed for immunofluorescence using antibodies against SH3BP1, CD2AP, and JACOP. Shown are confocal xy and z sections. (D) Calcium was added 
to Caco-2 cells plated in low calcium for the indicated periods to time. The cells were then fixed and stained as indicated. (E) EGF-stimulated A431 cells 
were fixed and processed as indicated. Shown are epifluorescence images of the dorsal aspect of the cells. Note that CD2AP and JACOP colocalize with 
SH3BP1 in dorsal ruffles. (F) Caco-2 cells were stained for CD2AP or JACOP after an incubation with the EGF receptor inhibitor PD153035 or, as a solvent 
control, DMSO. (G) GST fusion proteins conjugated to glutathione beads were incubated with A431 lysate (NTD, N-terminal domain; CTD, C-terminal 
domain). Pull-down experiments were analyzed by immunoblotting. (H) A431 cells transfected with siRNAs as indicated were lysed, and coprecipitation of 
CD2AP and SH3BP1 with JACOP was analyzed. Note that depletion of SH3BP1 inhibits coprecipitation of CD2AP. Bars, 10 µm. </p>

<p> 
Spatial control of Cdc42 and junction formation • Elbediwy et al. </p>

<p>Figure 10. CD2AP, JACOP, and CapZ are functional components of the SH3BP1 complex. (A) siRNA-transfected A431 cells were stimulated with EGF and 
then stained with fluorescent phalloidin. Shown are epifluorescence images of the apical (0 and 5 min) and of the basal (30 min) side of the cells. Note 
that CD2AP-and JACOP-depleted cells form neither dorsal ruffles nor a cortical actin belt. (B) siRNA-transfected A431 cells were serum starved and then 
stimulated with EGF for different periods of time. The cells were then fixed and stained for ZO-1. Shown are epifluorescence images taken from the api-
cal part of the cells. Note that depletion of SH3PB1 and its associated proteins prevents the formation of ZO-1-positive ruffles and junctional recruitment. 
(C) Caco-2 cells transfected with siRNAs targeting SH3BP1, CD2AP, and JACOP were processed for immunofluorescence with antibodies against the three 
proteins. Shown are epifluorescence images of the junctional region. (D) Levels of active Cdc42 were measured after serum starvation and stimulation with 
EGF in extracts from cells transfected with either control, CD2AP-, or JACOP-targeting siRNAs. Shown are means ± 1 SD (n = 4). (E) A431 cells transfected 
with control and SH3BP1-targeting siRNAs and, after serum starvation, treated for 5 min with EGF. After fixation, the cells were stained as indicated. 
Shown are epifluorescence images representing dorsal focal planes. (F) A431 cells transfected with siRNAs targeting CapZ1 were then analyzed by 
immunoblotting as indicated. (G) A431 cells were siRNA transfected, serum starved, and then stimulated with EGF. The cells were then fixed and stained 
with fluorescent phalloidin. Shown are epifluorescence images. Note that depletion of CapZ1 leads to induction of filopodia and loss of the junctional 
actin belt. Bars, 10 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 198 • NUMBER 4 • 2012 </p>

<p>
both interfere with junction assembly and epithelial differentia-
tion (Fig. 1 and Fig. S1; Kroschewski et al., 1999; Rojas et al.,  2001; Bruewer et al., 2004). Inactivation of Cdc42 is mainly 
required to prevent excessive activation levels and maintain 
spatial control, as partial depletion of Cdc42 was sufficient to 
counteract the effect of SH3BP1 depletion. Similarly, depletion 
of the GAP corrected the phenotype caused by partial Cdc42 
depletion; hence, Cdc42 seems to be the main substrate of 
SH3BP1 during epithelial junction formation. Although GAPs 
are counteracting the function of GEFs and, hence, are often 
seen as inhibiting processes while GEFs promote them, our data 
show that GAPs, such as SH3BP1, are important to drive pro-
gression of complex processes that require sequential morpho-
logical steps and cytoskeletal dynamics. 
Epithelial junction formation is a complex process that 
involves sequential steps starting with cell shape changes, ini-
tiation of cell-cell contacts, and subsequent maturation to a 
fully differentiated apical junctional complex consisting of tight 
and adherens junctions (Vasioukhin et al., 2000; Miyoshi and  Takai, 2008; Nelson, 2009). This sequential process requires 
continuous membrane remodeling driven by the actin cyto-
skeleton. RhoGTPases play essential roles in these processes, 
and proper regulation of RhoGTPases is required for success-
ful junction assembly (Braga and Yap, 2005). Our data now 
show that SH3BP1 is a crucial negative regulator of RhoGTPase 
and, in particular, Cdc42 signaling, which is required for 
normal junction assembly and differentiation of epithelial cells 
from different tissues, and indicate that SH3BP1 is required 
for the morphological transition from early, immature cell-cell 
contacts to continuous cell-cell junctions. 
Epithelial differentiation seems to rely on different GAPs 
for Cdc42 that regulate different steps. The Cdc42 GAP Rich1 
associates with tight junctions via the Par3-6 complex and regu-
lates apical polarization, not junction assembly (Wells et al.,  2006). Thus, epithelial junctions recruit GAPs for Cdc42 with 
fundamentally different roles: SH3BP1 is recruited early during 
junction formation and regulates junction assembly, whereas 
Rich1 regulates polarization once junctions are assembled. 
Accordingly, we could not detect a defect in junction assembly 
upon transfection of Rich1-targeting siRNAs in the screen that 
has led to the identification of SH3BP1 (Table S1). 
Although membrane dynamics underlie the initiation of 
cell contacts in all epithelial models studied, different types of 
epithelia can make use of different mechanisms of actin-driven 
processes. Although keratinocytes use filopodia, the kidney 
epithelial cell line MDCK relies on lamellipodia (Vasioukhin  et al., 2000; Ehrlich et al., 2002). As filopodia are induced by 
Cdc42, whereas lamellipodia require Rac, different GTPases 
can initiate cell-cell contacts and, as they can both regulate 
polarity complexes, lead to successful epithelial differentiation 
(Matter and Balda, 2003b; Nelson, 2009). SH3BP1 was origi-
nally identified as a GAP with similar activities toward Cdc42 
and Rac1 in vitro (Cicchetti et al., 1995). This was recently con-
firmed using cell-based biosensor assays (Parrini et al., 2011). 
The latter paper also demonstrated that SH3BP1 regulates Rac 
at the front of migrating cells (Parrini et al., 2011). Together 
with our data, this indicates that SH3BP1 can stimulate GTP </p>

<p>hydrolysis by both Rac and Cdc42 in vitro and in vivo and that 
the activities toward both GTPases are relevant for specific bio-
logical processes. Moreover, it could be that SH3BP1 regulates 
junction formation not only in epithelia that rely on filopodia 
but also in those that use lamellipodia. 
The observations that the GAP activity of SH3BP1 toward 
Rac and Cdc42 is differentially used in specific cellular processes 
highlight the importance of the subcellular targeting of the GAP. 
Although during migration, SH3BP1 is targeted to the front of the 
cells and regulates Rac, which is active at the leading edge, it is 
targeted to cell-cell contacts during junction formation and regu-
lates Cdc42, which is active at cell junctions. Similarly, in dorsal 
ruffles, SH3BP1 strongly affects Cdc42 and, to a lesser extent, 
Rac1; both GTPases are stimulated during dorsal ruffle formation. 
Targeting to subcellular sites that are enriched in the active form of 
either Cdc42 or Rac thus seems to be a major determinant of the 
GTPase selectivity of the GAP, and its activity seems to prevent the 
diffusion of active GTPase away from specific sites. Complex for-
mation seems to play a fundamental role for junctional targeting of 
SH3BP1 and its function, as depletion of JACOP and, to lesser 
extent, CD2AP resulted in loss of junctional SH3BP1, deregulation 
of Cdc42, and inhibition of junction formation. 
The SH3BP1 complex contains molecules that have differ-
ent cellular roles. Two of these proteins, JACOP and CD2AP, are 
scaffolding proteins that are linked to each other by SH3BP1. 
JACOP, also called paracingulin, is a component of the apical junc-
tional complex and can bind different types of junctional proteins 
(Ohnishi et al., 2004; Pulimeno et al., 2011). Depletion of JACOP 
had a strong effect on the junctional recruitment of SH3BP1 and 
CD2AP and led to a strong reduction in Cdc42 activity, indicating 
that it is important for recruitment of the complex and the control 
of the GAP activity of SH3BP1. In MDCK cells, JACOP has 
been linked to the regulation of Rac and RhoA via two different 
GEFs (Guillemot et al., 2008); however, this is the first study that 
links JACOP to the regulation of a GAP and of Cdc42. 
CD2AP has been known to be recruited to cell junctions 
and is a cytoskeletal regulator that has been linked to renal dis-
ease and slit diaphragm function, a specialized cell junction 
formed by podocytes (Dustin et al., 1998; Asanuma and Mundel,  2003; Mustonen et al., 2005; Fukasawa et al., 2009). CD2AP is a 
regulator of actin dynamics and binds to the barbed-end binding 
protein CapZ (Mejillano et al., 2004; Bruck et al., 2006). CapZ 
is also part of the SH3BP1 complex, and its depletion induces 
filopodia, as has previously been demonstrated by genetic abla-
tion (Mejillano et al., 2004). CD2AP and CapZ thus provide the 
SH3BP1 complex with a second cellular activity that can guide 
actin reorganization and membrane remodeling. Given the link 
of CD2AP to renal disease, it will be important to determine 
whether and how SH3BP1 and JACOP contribute to normal 
renal physiology and, if deregulated, play a role in disease 
development. Because of its association with CapZ, we propose 
that the SH3BP1 complex represents a dual activity feedback 
complex required for the coordination of actin-driven morpho-
logical processes that is recruited to sites of active membrane 
remodeling by the scaffolding components JACOP and CD2AP 
to terminate individual steps, enabling activation of subsequent 
GTPase-activated processes and junctional maturation. </p>

<p> 
Spatial control of Cdc42 and junction formation • Elbediwy et al. </p>

<p>deflection induced by an alternating current square wave current (±20 µA 
at 12.5 Hz) using an epithelial voltohmmeter (EVOM; World Precision In-
struments) as previously described (Matter and Balda, 2003a). Paracellular 
permeability was determined using 4-kD FITC-conjugated dextran and 70-kD 
rhodamine B-conjugated dextran over a time of 3 h (Balda et al., 1996). 
Fluorescence was then determined with a microplate reader (FLUOstar 
OPTIMA; BMG Labtech). For 3D morphogenesis, siRNA-transfected Caco-2 
cells were plated on top of a layer of growth factor-reduced Matrigel (BD; 
Jaffe et al., 2008; Terry et al., 2011). In brief, coverslips in 48-well plates 
were covered with 90 µl Matrigel (9.3 mg/ml) and left to gel to 45 min. 
10,000 cells were then plated in 300 µl of low glucose medium containing 
2% Matrigel. After 48 h, the medium was replaced with fresh medium con-
taining 2% Matrigel and 0.1 µg/ml cholera toxin. After another 48 h, the 
medium was carefully replaced with the fresh medium/Matrigel/cholera 
toxin mix. The samples were then fixed 10 h later. </p>

<p>Immunostaining and microscopy 
Fixation with methanol or 3% PFA and permeabilization of cells were per-
formed as previously described (Balda et al., 1996; Matter and Balda,  2003a). For the antibodies against active Cdc42 and Rac1 (NewEast 
Biosciences), cells were fixed in 3% PFA for 20 min at room temperature 
or methanol for 5 min at 20°C followed by a 3-min incubation in 0.3% 
Triton X-100 in blocking buffer (PBS containing 0.5% BSA, 10 mM glycine, 
and 0.1% sodium azide). The samples were then washed and incubated 
for 1 h in blocking buffer. After blocking and incubation with primary 
antibodies, the samples were incubated with the appropriate fluorescent 
secondary antibodies conjugated to either FITC, Cy3, or Cy5 (Jackson 
ImmunoResearch Laboratories, Inc.) in blocking buffer. In some experiments, 
fluorescent phalloidin was used (FITC and TRITC [Sigma-Aldrich]; Alexa 
Fluor 647 [Molecular Probes]), and Hoechst 33258 was used to label 
DNA (Invitrogen). Matrigel-grown samples were fixed with PFA and then 
incubated with blocking buffer containing 0.5% Triton X-100 and 0.1% 
SDS for 1 h. Antibody incubations were then also performed with the same 
detergent-containing blocking buffer. For tissue sections, colons were dis-
sected from adult female MF1 mice that had been transcardially perfused 
with 4% PFA in PBS, in accordance with UK Home Office regulations, 
embedded in OCT compound (VWR International) and snap frozen. 5-µm 
sections were then taken using a cryostat. For immunofluorescence stain-
ing, the sections were permeabilized with acetone/methanol (33:67) 
for 10 min at 20°C and then transferred to methanol/DMSO (4:1) for 
20 h at 4°C. The samples were then rehydrated with sequential changes 
of methanol decreasing from 75 to 50 and 25 to 0% in PBS at room tem-
perature for 5-10 min each. Next, the samples were further permeabilized 
and blocked for 8-10 h at room temperature in a humidified chamber in BSA 
permeabilization buffer (3% BSA, 1% Triton X-100, 0.5% Na-deoxycholate, 
0.2% Na-dodecylsulfate, 150 mM NaCl, and 10 mM Hepes, pH 7.4) 
containing 5% donkey serum (Sigma-Aldrich). The samples were then in-
cubated with goat anti-SH3BP1 and rabbit anti-ZO-1 for 16 h at room 
temperature in BSA permeabilization buffer containing 5% donkey serum 
in a humidified chamber. Afterward, samples were washed with PBS and 
BSA permeabilization buffer sequentially for 10-15 min in two cycles. 
Incubation with fluorescently labeled secondary antibodies and Hoechst 
33258 in BSA permeabilization buffer was for 6 h at room temperature in 
BSA permeabilization buffer in a humidified chamber followed by washing 
with PBS and BSA permeabilization buffer for 10-15 min in two cycles 
and mounting with ProLong (Life Technologies). All fixed samples were 
embedded in ProLong Gold antifade reagent. All epifluorescent images 
of fixed specimens were acquired with a fluorescent microscope (DM IRB; 
Leica) using a 63×/1.4 NA oil immersion objective fitted with a camera 
(C4742-95; Hamamatsu Photonics) and <rs id="software-0" type="software">simplePCI</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Hamamatsu Photonics</rs>). Confocal images were acquired with a confocal laser-scanning 
microscope (LSM 700; Carl Zeiss) or a confocal microscope (SP2; Leica) 
using 63×/1.4 NA immersion oil objectives. Immersion oil (518 F; Carl 
Zeiss) was used for all objectives. Images were acquired at ambient 
temperature using <rs id="software-1" type="software">ZEN</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">2009</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Carl Zeiss</rs>) or <rs id="software-2" type="software">LCS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Leica</rs>). Images were 
adjusted for brightness and contrast with <rs id="software-3" type="software">Photoshop</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Adobe</rs>). For FRET 
experiments, siRNA-transfected cells were plated into eight multiwell cham-
ber slides (ibidi), transfected with pRaichu-Cdc42, and analyzed using a 
microscope (SP2; 63×/1.4 NA objective, 37°C, in medium with 10 mM 
Hepes, pH 7.4) and <rs type="software">LCS</rs> FRET software using the donor recovery after 
acceptor bleaching protocol (YFP was bleached to 30%; Yoshizaki et al.,  2003; Terry et al., 2011). The shown FRET efficiency maps were then gen-
erated using the <rs type="software">LCS</rs> software by calculating the FRET efficiency according 
to the formal [(D post  D pre )/D post ] × 100 (D represents donor intensity). For 
quantification, CFP images were subtracted, and mean FRET intensities were </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>RNAi, cDNAs, and transfection 
A full-length human SH3BP1 cDNA (NM018957.3) was used to generate 
HA-tagged constructs that were cloned into a pCDNA4/TO vector (Invitro-
gen). To generate a mutant allele defective in GAP activity, arginine-312 
was replaced by an alanine residue using the mutagenesis kit (QuikChange; 
Agilent Technologies). For SH3BP1 GST fusion protein constructs, the 
sequences encoding the indicated domains were cloned into pGEX-4T-3 
(GE Healthcare) to generate SH3BP1 full-length, N-terminal domain (containing 
the BAR [Bin-Amphiphysin-Rvs] domain), and C-terminal domain (containing 
the SH3-binding domain) fusion proteins. The HA-tagged JACOP cDNA was 
provided by M. Furuse (Kobe University, Kobe, Japan; Ohnishi et al., 2004), 
the HA-tagged OPHN1 was provided by P. Billuart (Institut Cochin, Paris, 
France; Billuart et al., 1998), and the Asef2 cDNA was obtained from 
D. Billadeau (Mayo Clinic, Rochester, NY; Hamann et al., 2007). The DBL 
isoform 1 was amplified by PCR and cloned into pcDNA-TO with an N-terminal 
myc tag (Komai et al., 2002). Sequences targeted in the siRNA screen are 
provided in Tables S2 and S3. siGENOME and ON-TARGETplus siRNAs 
were obtained from Thermo Fisher Scientific. For subsequent RNAi experi-
ments, cells were transfected with individual or pools of siGENOME siRNAs 
for SH3BP1, CGNL1 (JACOP), CD2AP, and CapZ1 as well as nontarget-
ing control siRNAs (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The following sequences were 
targeted: SH3BP1, 5-GAUGACAGCCACCCACUUC-3 and 5-UGGAGA-
UUCAGGCCGAUUA-3; CGNL1, 5-GCAGGGAGCUCGCAGAAAU-3, 
5-CGGAGUACCUGAUUGAAUU-3, 5-CGAGUAAAGUGCUGGAUGA-
3, and 5-GGGAGAAAUACGACAGUUA-3; CD2AP, 5-GGGCGAACUU-
AAUGGUAAA-3 and 5-GAGCAAAUGAAGUGUAAUA-3; CapZ1, 
5-GAUGGGCAACAGACUAUUA-3, 5-UGAAAGACCAUUAUUCCAA-3, 
5-CACUAACUGUUUCGAAUGA-3, and 5-UCUGUACUGUUUAUGC-
UAA-3; and Cdc42, 5-CGGAAUAUGUACCGACUGU-3' and 5-GAU-
GACCCCUCUACUAUUG-3. To generate a SH3BP1 cDNA resistant to 
siRNA2, the sequence 5-GATGACAGCCACCCACTTC-3 was changed 
to 5-AATGACAGCAACACACTTC-3. For siRNA transfections, transfec-
tion reagent (INTERFERin; Polyplus-transfection, Inc.) was used according 
to the manufacturer's instructions using a total final siRNA concentration 
of 20-80 nM (Terry et al., 2011). Samples were collected and processed 
3-4 d after transfection. For DNA transfections, 0.5 µg/ml plasmid DNA 
and transfection reagent (jetPEI; Polyplus-transfection, Inc.) was used ac-
cording to the manufacturer's instructions. Samples were collected and 
processed after 24 h. </p>

<p>Antibodies 
The following antibodies were used: goat anti-SH3BP1 (Everest Biotech); 
mouse anti-ZO-1 and mouse antioccludin (Invitrogen); mouse anti-CD2AP, 
rabbit anti-CGNL1/JACOP, mouse anti-CapZ, rabbit anticingulin, rabbit 
anti-OPHN1, and rabbit antiflag/OctA (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.); 
rabbit antimyc (MBL International); rabbit anti--catenin and --catenin 
and mouse anti--actin (Sigma-Aldrich); mouse anti-E-cadherin, mouse 
anti-p120 catenin, mouse antiafadin/AF-6, mouse anticofilin, and mouse 
anti-Cdc42 (BD); rat anti-HA (Roche); mouse anti-Cdc42-GTP and anti-
Rac1GTP (NewEast Biosciences); and mouse anti-p-cofilin, rabbit anti-Erk1/2, 
and mouse anti-p-Erk (Cell Signaling Technology). The following anti-
bodies were as previously described: rabbit anti-JACOP, rabbit anti-ZO-1, 
rabbit anti-ZO-2, rabbit anti-ZO-3, mouse anti--tubulin, mouse anti-DP-
PIV, mouse anti-Na </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-ATPase, and mouse and rabbit anti-HA tag epitope 
(Hauri et al., 1985; Kreis, 1987; Daro et al., 1996; Benais-Pont et al.,  2003; Ohnishi et al., 2004; Steed et al., 2009; Terry et al., 2011). </p>

<p>Cell culture, cell lines, 3D morphogenesis, calcium switch, 
and permeability assays 
Human adenocarcinoma colon cells (Caco-2), human epithelial carcinoma 
cell line (A431), and HCE cells were cultured in DME containing 20% 
(Caco-2) or 10% (A431 and HCE) heat-inactivated FCS with 100 µg/ml 
streptomycin and 100 µg/ml penicillin (PAA Laboratories) at 37°C in a 5% 
CO 2 atmosphere. Cells were cultured and plated for experiments as pre-
viously described (Matter et al., 1989; Steed et al., 2009; Terry et al.,  2011). EGF was used at a final concentration of 100 ng/ml (PeproTech), 
and PD153035 (Tocris Bioscience) was used for EGF inhibition. For cal-
cium switch and permeability assays, cells were cultured in 6-well plates 
for the siRNA transfections and were then replated in low calcium medium 
containing dialyzed FBS after 24 h (Balda et al., 1996; Terry et al., 2011). 
Junction formation was then induced by replacing the low calcium with 
normal medium after another 24 h. Trans-epithelial electrical resistance was 
measured with a silver/silver-chloride electrode to determine the voltage </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 198 • NUMBER 4 • 2012 </p>



<p>
quantified with ImageJ (National Institutes of Health). For each image, all 
cell-cell contacts were quantified and as many internal areas; means of all 
cell-cell contacts and all internal areas in a field then gave one value each 
per imaged field, and these values were used for the final statistical analy-
sis. Normalizations were performed by dividing mean values obtained 
for specific fields by the mean values obtained for the entire field imaged. 
Time-lapse videos of A431 cells expressing an EGFP-actin construct were 
recorded at 37°C using a microscope (Axiovert 200M; Carl Zeiss) with a 
40×/0.6 NA objective and a camera (C4742-95). Videos were acquired 
with <rs type="software">SimplePCI</rs> software, recording images every 5 s. </p>

<p>Immunoblotting, immunoprecipitations, GST pull-downs, and RhoGTPase 
activation assays 
Whole-cell lysates were collected after washing twice with PBS before add-
ing SDS-PAGE sample buffer and heating at 70°C for 10 min. Extracts 
were homogenized with a 23-gauge needle. Samples were processed 
using standard Western blotting techniques. For immunoprecipitations, 
Caco-2 cells were extracted at 4°C with 0.5% Triton X-100 in PBS and a 
cocktail of protease and phosphatase inhibitors (Terry et al., 2011). Ex-
tracts were preadsorbed with inactive Sepharose beads for 30 min before 
addition to antibodies conjugated to protein G-Sepharose beads for 2 h 
at 4°C. Samples were washed twice with 0.5% Triton X-100 in PBS and 
once with PBS before adding SDS-PAGE sample buffer. For GST pull-down 
experiments, cells were extracted with the same buffer at 4°C and pread-
sorbed with inactive beads as described for immunoprecipitations. Extracts 
were incubated with glutathione-agarose beads coated with fusion pro-
teins and incubated for 2 h at 4°C before washing as described for immuno-
precipitations. For RhoGTPase activation assays, cells were transfected 
with the appropriate siRNAs in 12-well plates, and after 72-96 h, the pro-
tein was harvested and analyzed for levels of active Cdc42 and Rac1 using 
the respective G-LISA assay kits (Cytoskeleton; Terry et al., 2011). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Means and SDs were calculated and provided in the graphs. Respective 
n values are provided in the figure legends. The indicated p-values were 
obtained with the two-tailed Student's t test. </p>

<p>Online supplemental material 
Fig. S1 shows identification of GAPs important for junction formation. Fig. S2 
shows the regulation of junction formation in Caco-2 cells by SH3BP1. 
Fig. S3 shows the association of SH3BP1 with cell-cell contacts and EGF 
receptor signaling. Fig. S4 shows regulation of Cdc42 and Rac signaling 
by SH3BP1. Fig. S5 shows SH3BP1 and complex formation with CD2AP 
and JACOP. Video 1 shows actin dynamics at the junctional level in control 
siRNA-transfected cells. Video 2 shows actin dynamics at the junctional 
level in SH3BP1 siRNA-transfected cells. Video 3 shows actin dynamics at 
the dorsal aspect of control siRNA-transfected cells. Video 4 shows actin 
dynamics at the dorsal aspect of SH3BP1 siRNA-transfected cells. Table S1 
shows a summary of the observed phenotypes in the siRNA screen. Tables 
S2 and S3 list the sequences of the siRNAs used in the primary and second-
ary screens, respectively. Online supplemental material is available at 
http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201202094/DC1. </p>

<p>We are grateful to Mikio Furuse for kindly providing JACOP antibodies and 
cDNAs, Pierre Billuart for the OPHN1 cDNA, and Daniel Billadeau for the 
Asef2 cDNA. 
A. Elbediwy received a Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research 
Council Studentship. This research was supported by the Wellcome Trust. </p>

<p>Submitted: 16 February 2012 
Accepted: 11 July 2012 </p>



</text></tei>