<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3494016" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>existence of new functional connections between Rb family of pro-
teins and p53 in this tissue 16 . These gene expression studies showed 
the underexpression of Pten in Rb F/F ;K14cre;p107 2/2 new born skin 
samples. Pten is a tumor suppressor gene, induced by several mecha-
nisms including p53 activation 17 , which regulates cell survival by 
PI3K/AKT pathway 18 . Inactivation of Pten gene is found in multiple 
tumors including human 19 and mouse 20 skin cancers. 
To explore the possible functional relationship between pRb, p53 
and Pten genes in vivo, we have generated a mouse model bearing the 
inducible Rb1 loss in stratified epithelia in the absence of p107 alleles 
(Rb F/F ;K14CreER TM ;p107 2/2 ) thus overcoming the early lethality of 
Rb F/F ;K14cre;p107 2/2 mice. Using this model we confirm the specific 
tumor suppressive roles for p107 in epidermis. Rb F/F ; K14CreER TM ; 
p107 2/2 mice develop squamous carcinoma and display impaired 
p53 transcriptional functions and reduced expression of Pten gene. 
Further, transcriptome analyses revealed striking similarities be-
tween the mouse tumors and human squamous cell carcinomas. 
Collectively our data support a novel previously unreported connec-
tion between pRb, p53 and Pten tumor suppressors of a particular 
relevance in the genesis of human squamous neoplasias. </p>

<p>Results 
Acute pRb loss in the absence of p107 leads to spontaneous tumors 
development. Compared with control or p107 2/2 mice (Supp Fig. 
S1a), the inducible loss of pRb in adult mice epidermis by tamoxi-
fen treatment (Rb F/F ;K14creER TM mice) produces skin hyperplasia 
(Supp. Fig. S1b), characterized by expansion of basal keratin 5 
(K5)-positive keratinocytes (Supp. Fig. S1e), interfollicular induc-
tion of K6 (Supp. Fig. S1h) and increased proliferation (Supp Fig. 
S1k, m, n), which is undistinguishable from that observed in mice 
bearing constitutive pRb loss in epidermis (Rb F/F ;K14cre mice) 6 . 
However, it is insufficient to allow spontaneous tumor develop-
ment over one year and half after pRb loss (n525) (Fig. 1n). On 
the contrary, p107 loss has no phenotypic consequences in epidermis 
(Fig. 1a; Supp. Fig. S1a) 6,14,21 . The inducible loss of Rb1 in a p107 null 
background (Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 ) avoided the early lethality 
observed in Rb F/F ;K14cre;p107 2/2 mice 6 and exacerbated the Rb F/F ; 
K14creER TM mouse phenotype, as demonstrated by increased hyper-
plasia (Supp Fig. S1c, o), increased proliferation (Supp Fig. S1l, m, n) 
and generalized expansion of the suprabasal expression of K5 and 
K6-expressing keratinocytes (Supp Fig. S1f, j). In addition, the </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Phenotypic characterization of Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice. a,b) Example of gross appearance of the Rb F/F ;p107 2/2 (a) and </p>

<p>Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 (b) mice 4 months after topical tamoxifen treatment. Macroscopic aspect of face, dewlap, snout and eyelid (c, c',c'' respectively). 
d-f) H&amp;E stained snout sections of Rb F/F ;p107 2/2 (d) Rb F/F ;K14creER TM (e) and Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 (f) showing massive hyperplasia, hyperkeratosis 
and epithelial downgrowths in Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 . g, g') Immunofluorescence showing the localization of Laminin in hyperplasic (g) and lesional 
areas (g') of Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mouse snouts. The reduced expression and disappearance of laminin in lesional areas support the invasive consition 
of squamous cell carcinomas. h-m) H&amp;E stained sections showing tumor samples of snout (h, i), neck (h'), eyelid (h''), lip (j), palate (k), oral epithelium (l) 
and ventral tongue (m) of Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice 4 months after tamoxifen treatment. n) Kaplan Meier plot showing the incidence of tumours in 
Rb F/F ;K14creER TM (open box; n525) and Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 (black box; n522) mice. p value was obtained by the log rank test. Bars5150 mm. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 828 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00828 </p>

<p>
Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice display a generalized hair loss and a 
very frail appearance (Fig. 1b). 
Although tamoxifen was topically applied in the lower back-skin 
area, PCR analysis reveals that Rb1 recombination occurs in 
untreated areas including untreated skin and oral tissues (Supp 
Fig. S2a). In spite of the observed recombination, no obvious pheno-
typic changes were observed between control (Supp Fig. S2c, d, e) and 
Rb F/F ;K14cre;p107 2/2 mice (Supp Fig. S2c', d', e') in stomach (Supp 
Fig. S2c, c'), esophagus (Supp Fig. S2d, d'), dorsal tongue (Supp Fig. 
S2e, e'), or other K14 expressing tissues (not shown) by four months 
after tamoxifen application. 
Prior to the degenerative phenotype, Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 
mice show the development of lesions in the cheek (Fig. 1c), neck 
(Fig. 1c' and Supp Fig. S3a), eyelids and snout (Fig. 1c''), and 
the overgrowth of nails (Supp Fig. S3b). Histology analyses of 
snout samples revealed that, compared to controls (Fig. 1d), Rb F/F ; 
K14creER TM mice display a moderate hyperplasia and mild hyper-
keratosis (Fig. 1e). However, in Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice a ge-
neralized hyperplasia, hyperkeratosis and downgrowths of epithelial 
cells suggestive of tumoral or pretumoral lesions were observed 
(Fig. 1f). Compared to the hyerplasic regions of Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ; 
p107 2/2 mouse snouts (Fig. 1g), the lesions showed areas of laminin 
loss (Fig. 1g') thus confirming that they correspond to invasive squa-
mous cell carcinoma (SCC). Similar types of tumors were found in 
all Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 in snout (Fig. 1h), neck (Fig. 1h') and 
eyelids (Fig. 1h''), in some cases associated to inflammatory processes 
(Fig. 1i). Histology also evidenced the presence of sporadic tumors 
affecting lips (Fig. 1j), palate (Fig. 1k), oral epithelia (Fig. 1l) and 
ventral tongue (Fig. 1m). The study of a cohort of Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ; 
p107 2/2 mice demonstrates that all mice (n522) developed tumors 
by two months after recombination induction (Fig. 1n). The analysis 
of pRb and p107 status in these tumors revealed that all of them 
display loss of p107 and generalized recombination of Rb F/F alleles 
after tamoxifen treatment (data not shown). </p>

<p>Reduced Pten expression and impaired p53-dependent tran-
scription in Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice. The phenotype dis-
played in face, snout, nails and epidermis (Supp Fig. 3a-c) by 
Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice is similar to that exhibited by mice 
expressing a constitutive active Akt 22,23 and those lacking Rb1 and 
Pten genes in stratified epithelia (Rb F/F ;Pten F/F ;K14cre mice; Supp Fig. 
S3a', b', c'). However, the Rb F/F ;Pten F/F ;K14cre mice also display early 
lethality (Segrelles et al, unpublished data) and all of them died by 1 
or 2 months after birth, precluding the analysis of adult mice. Despite 
this, comparative study of newborn skins from Rb F/F ;Pten F/F ;K14cre 
and Rb F/F ;K14cre;p107 2/2 mice transplanted onto immunodeficient 
mice (Supp Fig. S3e-e') revealed the development of massive epi-
dermal outgrowths corresponding to well differentiated squamous 
cell carcinomas in both cases. Remarkably, the tumors displayed 
almost identical histopathological characteristics regardless their 
origin (either Rb F/F ;Pten F/F ;K14cre or Rb F/F ;K14cre;p107 2/2 mouse 
newborn skin; Supp. Fig. S3f-h'). 
Tumor development in Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice suggested 
a possible deregulation of p53 functions, as p53 is a major player 
to suppress tumorigenesis in epidermis in the absence of pRb 7,24 . 
In agreement, previous gene expression analyses in Rb F/F ;K14cre; 
p107 2/2 newborn epidermis revealed the downregulation of a num-
ber of p53-induced genes, mainly involved in apoptosis 13 . Among 
these genes we observed the underexpression of Pten, which in cer-
tain tissues is transcriptionally induced by p53 17 . Consequently, the 
previous data and the extensive similarities between Rb F/F ;Pten F/F ; 
K14cre and Rb F/F ;K14cre;p107 2/2 mouse phenotypes, prompted us 
to study possible alterations in p53-and Pten-dependent signaling in 
Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice. 
Upon in vitro 4-hydroxytamoxifen treatment, primary keratino-
cytes from Rb F/F ;K14creER TM and Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice </p>

<p>displayed an almost complete recombination of Rb F/F alleles (Supp 
Fig. S2b), but only a partial loss of pRb (Fig. 2a). Nonetheless, this 
partial loss of pRb promoted the induction of p107 and a moderate 
increase in p130 (Fig. 2a). In addition, it also induced p53 expression 
and its bona fide target p21 CIP1 , which are both further induced in 
Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 keratinocytes (Fig. 2a). Among the other 
p53-family members, double deficient primary keratinocytes dis-
played a clear induction of DNp63a, without any significant increase 
in p73 or in DNp73. Similarly, Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 keratino-
cytes displayed increased levels of p53-Ser392 phosphorylated, 
-Lys373 Acetylated, and -Lys372 methylated (Fig. 2a), which in some 
cases corresponded to increased expression of the corresponding 
posttranscriptional effectors Tip60, SetD8 and Smyd2, without sig-
nificant variations in others such as Sirt1, Pcaf and CBP (Fig. 2a). In 
spite of the increased levels of p53 and its active forms, luciferase 
experiments revealed that the p53-depending response was not 
induced in these double deficient cells (Fig. 2b), but rather decreased 
when compared to Rb F/F ;K14creER TM cells. On the contrary, the 
induction of E2F-responding elements upon pRb reduction was fur-
ther increased in Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 keratinocytes (Fig. 2c). 
These data indicated that the p53-dependent transcription is 
impaired in Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 keratinocytes. 
The Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 keratinocytes also displayed a sig-
nificant reduction of Pten levels (Fig. 2a) associated to reduced Pten 
gene expression level, as demonstrated by qRTPCR (Fig. 2d) and by 
luciferase experiments using Pten gene promoter (Fig. 2e), but not 
due to promoter methylation dependent events (Supp Fig. S4). The 
reduction of Pten levels was in parallel with the increased c-jun 
expression, which represses Pten gene expression independently of 
p53 25 , and a concomitant increased phosphorylation of Akt at 
Thr308 and Ser473 (Fig. 2a). Of note, DNp63, which is also specif-
ically induced in double deficient cells (Fig. 2a), has been shown as a 
potential repressor of Pten gene expression in keratinocytes 26 . 
The comparative analysis of the expression of differentiation mar-
kers such as K5, K6, K10 and K15, or the rate of proliferation (ana-
lyzed by BrdU incorporation) in controls (Fig. 3a, b, c, d), Rb F/F ; 
K14creER TM (Fig. 3a', b', c', d') and Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ; p107 2/2 
(Fig. 3a'', b'', c'', d'') mice suggests that the lesions arising in 
Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice were predominantly well differen-
tiated squamous cell carcinomas similar to those arising upon Rb F/F ; 
K14cre;p107 2/2 skin transplantation experiments (Supp Fig. S3; see 
also 13 ), with a no evident signs of apoptosis (data not shown). A 
phosphoproteome analysis comparing skin and tumor protein 
extracts revealed increased p53 phosphorylation in different residues 
and overall increase in Akt/mTOR activity, as demonstrated not only 
by the augmented phosphorylation of Akt (in both Thr308 and 
Ser473) but also by the phosphorylation of specific Akt substrates 
such as GSK3b, p27 and p70S6K (Fig. 3e). Immunohistochemistry 
studies confirmed the increased phosphorylation of Akt (Fig. 3f) and 
almost no detectable amounts of Pten in tumor samples (Fig. 3f') 
which is accompanied with reduced Pten gene transcription (Fig. 3g). </p>

<p>Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 tumors resemblance with human 
tumors. The histology and biochemical characteristics of the spon-
taneous tumors of Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice are reminiscent 
of those human squamous carcinomas displaying increased Akt 
activity. In order to explore this possibility and to characterize the 
possible molecular events leading to tumor development in Rb F/F ; 
K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice, we performed a differential expression 
analysis between normal skin and carcinomas using microarrays. 
The selection of differentially expressed genes was performed by 
SAM test (see Materials and Methods), providing a gene signature 
of 2256-probesets (1128 overexpressed and 1128 underexpressed in 
tumors; hereafter 2256-gene signature) (Supplementary Tables 1 and 
2). Unsupervised hierarchical clustering analysis of the samples using 
this gene signature revealed a homogeneous expression pattern in </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 828 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00828 </p>

<p>
Figure 2 | Molecular alterations in primary keratinocytes of Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice. a) Western blot analysis of primary keratinocytes of the </p>

<p>quoted genotypes with or without 4OHTX treatment showing the expression of the indicated proteins. Actin was used as loading control. b, c) Luciferase 
activity of p53-(b) and E2F-responding elements (c) in primary keratinocytes of the quoted genotypes. d) Quantitative PCR for the relative expression 
analysis of Pten gene in epidermal extracts of the quoted genotypes. e) Relative luciferase activity of Pten promoter in primary keratinocytes of the quoted 
genotypes. Data in b, d, e come from three independent experiments and are shown as mean6S.E.M. Data in d) come from five different extracts 
normalized to GusB gene expression and are shown as mean6S.E.M. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 828 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00828 </p>

<p>
tumor samples (Fig. 4a). Consistent with the functional roles of the 
retinoblastoma family members, most of the overexpressed genes in 
the tumors were involved in cell cycle regulation, or DNA replication 
and repair, as evidenced by enrichment analysis of Gene Ontology 
biological processes (GOBP) terms (Fig. 4b). Additionally, we also 
found overexpression of genes involved in keratinization and 
epidermal cell differentiation, in agreement with the differentiated 
histology of the Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mouse carcinomas, and 
processes such as RNA transport and splicing or translation (Fig. 4b). 
In contrast, underexpressed genes were involved in muscle devel-
opment, which may be explained by the partial absence of dermal 
muscle layers in tumor samples, signaling, negative regulation of 
transcription and in cell adhesion (Fig. 4b), which is broadly asso-
ciated with carcinogenesis processes. 
To explore whether the mouse tumors resemble human squamous 
cell carcinoma samples, an exhaustive comparison of the mouse 
tumor 2256-gene signature with gene datasets of human SCC cancer 
samples arising in different organs (skin, head and neck, lung or 
cervix) was performed, using the Oncomine human cancer genomics </p>

<p>database (see Materials and Methods). This shows a very significant 
overlap between overexpressed genes (Supplementary Table 3, over-
lap n529 to 239 genes, p values from 6.7 x10 24 to 5.0310 280 , odds 
ratio from 2 to 4.7) or underexpressed genes (Supplementary Table 4, 
overlap n548 to 162 genes, p values from 5.5310 27 to 2.1310 222 , 
odds ratio from 2. to 3.2) in mouse samples with multiple studies. 
Such extremely relevant overlapping, may suggest that transcriptome 
data could be used to extract common genes significantly deregulated 
in the Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mouse and human SCC tumors. 
We found that 33 genes overexpressed and 12 genes underexpressed 
in mouse tumors were also found in at least 7 of the 15 studies of 
human tumors analyzed (Figure 4c), which might represent com-
mon biomarkers of human and mouse SCC. This meta-analysis of 
interspecies comparison corroborated the high degree of similarity 
between mouse and human SCC carcinomas at the molecular level. 
To further reinforce these findings, and to provide a wider analysis of 
the similarity between the changes in gene expression in the 
Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mouse and other gene signatures, we per-
formed a <rs type="software">Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA</rs>) study. This revealed </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Akt pathway is altered in Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 tumors. a-d'') Double immunofluorescence showing the expression of keratin 5 (red) </p>

<p>and keratin 10 (green) (a, a', a''), keratin 6 (red) and keratin 10 (green) (b, b',b''), keratin 15 (red) and keratin 10 (green) (c, c', c''), and keratin 5 (red) and 
BrdU incorporation (green)(d, d', d'') in Rb F/F p107 2/2 (a-d), Rb F/F ;K14creER TM (a'-d') and Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 (a''-d'') snout sections. 
Bars5150 mm. e) Phosphoproteome profiles of skin or tumor extracts of the quoted genotypes. At least four independent samples were pooled. f,f') 
Representative immunohistochemistry showing the expression of phosphorylated (Ser473) Akt (f) and Pten (f') in Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ; p107 2/2 mouse 
snout. Bars5150mm. g) Relative expression of Pten gene in skin and tumor samples; red bars denote mean6S.E.M. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 828 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00828 </p>

<p>
Figure 4 | Genomic analysis of Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 tumors. a) Unsupervised hierarchical clustering of carcinomas using the 2256 deregulated </p>

<p>probesets was done with Pearson distance metrics and complete linkage method. Columns represent samples, and rows are genes. Green samples are normal 
control skin from adult mice. Red samples are Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 carcinomas. Z-scores in log 2 scale were calculated for heatmap visualization. b) 
Enrichment analysis in Gene Ontology Biological Processes from the carcinoma signature of Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mouse. Red bars correspond to 
overexpressed genes and green bars correspond to downregulated genes p-val: significance of enrichment. c) Common gene signature between Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ; 
p107 2/2 mouse and at least 7 out of 15 different human SCC studies (from lung, head and neck, skin, esophagus, and cervix) obtained from ''Cancer vs. Normal'' 
comparisons in Oncomine (see Supp Table S3 and S4). Red boxes represent human genes overexpressed in SCC compared with normal tissue. Blue boxes 
represent human genes underexpressed in SCC compared with normal tissue. Bar plots represent the significance of the overlap, being the provided p-val for each 
specific gene the median-ranked p-val in each comparison. Genes are ordered by significance. Vertical red lines in bar plots represent p-val50.025. d) Significant 
GE overlapping between Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mouse and human HPV-infected carcinoma samples were found for both over-(in red) and under-
expressed (blue) genes in Oncomine. For Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 carcinoma genes (columns represent human samples, and rows are genes) the heatmap, the 
number of uninfected/infected human samples analyzed, the number of common genes, and the significance of overlapping (p-val) are provided. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 828 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00828 </p>

<p>
novel similarities between overexpressed and underexpressed genes 
in mouse tumors and specific signal transduction pathways, and 
human tumors (Table I). 
One of the studies observed in our GSEA analysis indicated the 
similarity between overexpressed genes in mouse tumors and human 
head and neck tumors associated with human papillomavirus (HPV) 
infection 27 (24 out of 59 genes in the signature, FDR q value5 
0.000033). The HPV are present in human carcinomas of the cervix 
and head and neck with a prevalence of 90% and 30%, respectively. 
As the E7 oncogene from different HPVs induces the degradation of 
retinoblastoma family proteins 28-30 , we hypothesize that SCC of 
Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice may also resemble HPV-infected 
human tumors. To confirm this, we compared the gene expression 
profiles between mouse and human HPV-infected carcinomas 31 
of the tongue, tonsil and cervix. The results of this comparison 
(Figure 4d) showed a very high similarities in these groups, thus 
indicating that the Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mouse SCCs could 
be a potential model to understand the E7-dependent molecular 
mechanisms of HPV oncogenesis. </p>

<p>Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mouse tumors display partial inhi-
bition of DNA damage p53-dependent regulatory network 
response. As commented above, the absence of pRb and p107 
leads to partial impairment of p53-dependent functions. To further 
confirm these findings, we analyzed the expression patterns of p53-
responsive genes in Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 compared with nor-
mal skin. To this, we used <rs type="software">GSEA</rs> of genes induced or repressed by 
DNA damage in a p53-dependent manner 32 . Our results indicated 
that although p53-activated genes are very significantly underex-
pressed in the tumors, the p53-repressed genes do not display over-
expression in tumors (Table II). Thus, Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 
carcinomas displayed partial inhibition of p53 function as transcrip-
tional regulator, corroborating the luciferase experiments (Fig. 2b). </p>

<p>In the same line of evidence, and in spite of showing a very different 
differentiation grade, we found strong similarities in the functional 
categories between the overexpressed (overlap 204, p value5 
3.25x10 2125 , odds ratio 16.1) and underexpressed (overlap 201, p 
value51.63x10 2153 , odds ratio 18.7) genes in Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ; 
p107 2/2 SCCs and those previously characterized by upregulation 
or downregulation in carcinomas generated by specific deletion of 
p53 in stratified epithelia (Trp53 F/F ;K14cre and Rb F/F ;Trp53 F/F ;K14cre 
genotypes) 33 . </p>

<p>Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mouse tumors are sensitive to PTEN/ 
AKT/mTOR inhibitors. As described above, the Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ; 
p107 2/2 mouse carcinomas display underexpression of Pten, leading 
to AKT/mTOR signaling activation. This indicates that targeted 
therapies inhibiting this signaling pathway would be of relevance 
in the treatment of these tumors. In order to explore this possi-
bility at the genome-wide level, we compared the 2256-gene signa-
ture with the gene expression profiles of human cancer cell lines 
showing differential sensitivities to these inhibitors. According to 
our hypothesis, the similarity of GE would indicate susceptibility 
to these agents. We found a significant overlap in gene expression 
between Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mouse carcinomas and cell lines 
sensitive to perifosine (AKT inhibitor) and temsirolimus (mTOR 
inhibitor) (Fig. 5a, b) 34 . 
To further substantiate the above commented observations, we 
performed a chemopreventive study. Mice were treated with tamox-
ifen, to induce the Rb1 recombination, and subsequently rapamycin 
was administered (10 mg/kg, thrice/week). After two months, we 
observed that Rapamicyn treatment produced an evident alleviation 
of the phenotype in snout, lips and eyelids (Fig. 6a-b'). Further, the 
histology study of these areas in the mouse cohorts (rapamycin treated 
n58, untreated n511) showed a reduced incidence of tumor develop-
ment in all the cases (Fig. 6c). As expected, rapamycin-treated mice </p>

<p>Table 1 | GSEA analysis of Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ; p107 2/2 mouse tumors </p>

<p>Gene Set Name (N) 1 
Number of enriched genes 
NES 
FDR q-val </p>

<p>KOBAYASHI_EGFR_SIGNALING_24HR_DN (210) 
153 
2.93 
, 0.00001 
BERENJENO_TRANSFORMED_BY_RHOA_UP (474) 
266 
2.75 
, 0.00001 
GRAHAM_NORMAL_QUIESCENT_VS_NORMAL_DIVIDING_DN (70) 
52 
2.62 
, 0.00001 
BENPORATH_PROLIFERATION (116) 
75 
2.57 
, 0.00001 
GRAHAM_CML_DIVIDING_VS_NORMAL_QUIESCENT_UP (152) 
87 
2.54 
, 0.00001 
REN_BOUND_BY_E2F (46) 
32 
2.44 
, 0.00001 
MARKEY_RB1_ACUTE_LOF_DN (213) 
111 
2.36 
, 0.00001 
LE_EGR2_TARGETS_UP (99) 
56 
2.35 
, 0.00001 
VERNELL_RETINOBLASTOMA_PATHWAY_UP (35) 
27 
2.32 
, 0.00001 
EGUCHI_CELL_CYCLE_RB1_TARGETS (18) 
17 
2.28 
, 0.00001 
YU_MYC_TARGETS_UP (37) 
27 
2.26 
, 0.00001 
TANG_SENESCENCE_TP53_TARGETS_DN (35) 
24 
2.17 
0.000014 
BENPORATH_CYCLING_GENES (487) 
214 
2.14 
0.000013 
DANG_MYC_TARGETS_UP (109) 
43 
2.11 
0.000012 
SLEBOS_HEAD_AND_NECK_CANCER_WITH_HPV_UP (59) 
24 
2.09 
0.000033 
SARRIO_EPITHELIAL_MESENCHYMAL_TRANSITION_UP (15) 
11 
2.08 
0.000042 
MOLENAAR_TARGETS_OF_CCND1_AND_CDK4_DN (38) 
25 
2.05 
0.000070 
SCIAN_CELL_CYCLE_TARGETS_OF_TP53_AND_TP73_DN (22) 
15 
2.03 
0.00015 
RICKMAN_HEAD_AND_NECK_CANCER_F (48) 
29 
22.72 
, 0.00001 
BERENJENO_TRANSFORMED_BY_RHOA_DN (352) 
191 
22.71 
, 0.00001 
KUNINGER_IGF1_VS_PDGFB_TARGETS_UP (41) 
7 
22.61 
, 0.00001 
GU_PDEF_TARGETS_UP (64) 
33 
22.26 
0.00006 
WANG_SMARCE1_TARGETS_UP (136) 
76 
22.15 
0.00022 
TSENG_IRS1_TARGETS_DN (117) 
46 
22.13 
0.00023 
DAIRKEE_TERT_TARGETS_DN (63) 
29 
22.11 
0.00036 
SENESE_HDAC2_TARGETS_DN (99) 
47 
22.11 
0.00037 
THUM_MIR21_TARGETS_HEART_DISEASE_UP (17) 
14 
22.06 
0.00054 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>N: number of genes from each gene set in mouse chip. 2) Shadowed rows represent overlapping of underexpressed genes in mouse tumors 
NES: normalized enrichment score. 
NES.0: enrichment in tumors; NES,0: enrichment in normal skin. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 828 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00828 </p>

<p>
display reduced phosphorylation of P-S6 (Fig. 6d, d', f) and Akt phos-
phorylation (Fig. 6e, e', f). Of note, in spite of the reduction in the 
tumor susceptibility, the overall frail appearance and alopecia were not 
affected by the preventive rapamycin treatment (data not shown). 
Similarly, rapamycin-treated mice displayed evident signs of hyper-
plasia and hyperkeratosis (Fig. 6g', h') compared to control mice 
(rapamycin-treated, tamoxifen-untreated; Fig. 6g, h), and no signifi-
cant reduction in epithelial proliferation compared with untreated 
mice (Fig. 6i, i', j). These results indicate that not all the physiological 
consequences of pRb and p107 loss in epithelia are attributable to the 
increased Akt/mTOR axis. However, mTOR inhibition significantly 
prevents tumor development. </p>

<p>Discussion 
The Rb1 gene product is functionally inactivated in most human 
tumors 2 . However, Rb1 gene mutations are only found in small sub-
sets of human tumors. This indicates that, as the functional inactiva-
tion of pRb probably also affects the other Rb family members p107 
and p130, the specific inactivation of Rb1 gene is only able to induce 
tumorigenesis in restricted tissues 35,36 . In epidermis, although Rb1 
loss promotes alterations in proliferation and differentiation, indi-
cating the existence of unique functions for this protein in this tissue, 
it is insufficient to allow tumor development 6 . Overlapping func-
tions between pRb and p107 in epidermis have been previously </p>

<p>demonstrated in epidermis 6 . Interestingly, although there are dra-
matic changes in gene expression, the phenotype of Rb F/F ;K14cre is 
not aggravated by p130 loss 14 . These overlapping functions between 
pRb and p107 have been also described in other tissues 37,38 , but are 
particularly highlighted in stratified epithelia where the complete loss 
of pRb and p107 led to death by pnd 10 6 . Moreover, double deficient 
epidermis leads to spontaneous tumor development in transplanted 
new born skin, indicating putative tumor suppressor functions of 
p107 in the absence of pRb 13 . Accordingly, double deficient kerati-
nocytes are highly susceptible to Ha-ras transformation and resistant 
to oncogene-induced premature senescence 13 . Here, using an indu-
cible mouse model for pRb loss in stratified epithelia to overcome the 
early lethality, we confirm such tumor suppressor functions of p107. 
Previous microarray data using newborn epidermis samples, also 
revealed that the absence of pRb and p107 promoted overexpression 
of multiple E2F-dependent genes 13 . In contrast, in spite of p53 induc-
tion, multiple p53-dependent genes, predominantly associated to 
apoptosis induction, were actually downregulated 13 . Our present 
data also reinforce these findings, as we observe that the DNA 
damage-induced p53-activated genes are underexpressed in the 
Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mouse carcinomas, and a significant 
overlap in gene expression was observed between tumors arising 
in Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice and spontaneous epidermal tu-
mors promoted by specific deletion of p53 in stratified epithelia </p>

<p>Table 2 | GSEA of p53-responding genes in Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ; p107 2/2 mouse tumors </p>

<p>Gene Set Name (N) 1 
Analysis 
Number of enriched genes 
NES 
FDR q-val </p>

<p>p53-induced (1653) 
ES vs DiffES 32 
425 
21.55 
, 0.0001* 
Rb;p107 tumors vs Normal skin 
599 
21.68 
, 0.0001* 
p53-repressed (1313) 
ES vs DiffES 32 
260 
1.41 
, 0.0001* 
Rb;p107 tumors vs Normal skin 
321 
21.01 
0.374 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>N: number of genes from each gene set in mouse chip. 
NES: normalized enrichment score. 
NES.0: enrichment in tumors or ES; NES,0: enrichment in normal skin or DiffES. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Significant enrichment. </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Genomic analysis of Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 tumors correspond to Akt and mTOR inhibition sensitivity. Sensitivity to AKT inhibitor (a, </p>

<p>perifosine) and mTOR (b, temsirolimus) was tested in a collection of human cancer cell lines. Transcriptome differences between sensitive versus resistant 
lines was compared with Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 carcinoma signature. Significant transcript overlapping was observed for over-(in red) and under-
expressed (in blue) genes in both the mouse signature and the sensitive cells. For each inhibitor, we show the number of sensitive/resistant cell lines tested 
(columns represent samples, and rows are genes), the number of common genes, and the significance of overlapping (p-val). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 828 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00828 </p>

<p>
(Trp53 F/F ;K14cre and Rb F/F ;Trp53 F/F ;K14cre genotypes) 33 . In addi-
tion, as p53-mediated repression acts through interfering with distal 
enhancer activity and p53-activated genes occurs at the promoter 
regions 32 , we may also suggest that somatic deletion of pRb and p107 
efficiently affect direct binding of p53 to the promoter regions of 
activated genes rather than distal enhancer binding. However, when 
we monitored possible defective signaling that may account for the 
decreased transcriptional activity of p53 observed over apoptotic 
genes 39 , and in particular focusing on p53 acetylation 40 , phosphor-
ylation and methylation 41 , we observed normal activation. This 
potentially discards that defects in these modifications may account 
for the observed effect. This aspect would deserve future investiga-
tion. 
Among the underexpressed genes in microarrays of Rb F/F ;K14cre; 
p107 2/2 skin, we found Pten gene. The expression of this gene is 
modulated by various transcription factors including p53, which 
enhances Pten transcription 17 . Our data showing decreased p53 tran-
scriptional activity and reduced Pten expression might support this 
observation. The specific upregulation of DNp63 and c-jun in double 
deficient keratinocytes can also contribute to the Pten gene down-
regulation, as these two transcription factors have been recently 
involved in Pten gene repression 25,26 . Nonetheless, the molecular </p>

<p>mechanisms by which pRb and p107 loss lead to such increased 
expression of p63 and and c-jun is presently unknown. 
The finding of tumor development specifically in the oral area 
concurs with the observed reduced expression of Pten. The express-
ion of a constitutive active Akt in stratified epithelia of transgenic 
mice led to preneoplasic lesions in the oral cavity and perioral 
regions 22,42 . Importantly, these lesions did not progress to overt 
squamous tumors due to the induction of premature senescence, 
which is overcome by specific ablation of p53, but not pRb 42 . 
Comparable incidence of tumors showing similar characteristics 
was found in mice bearing the specific elimination of Pten and p53 
genes in stratified epithelia 42 . The present data are in agreement and 
also reinforce these observations, as the absence of p107 can bypass 
the oncogene-induced senescence in pRb-deficient keratinocytes 13 . 
Our data are also in agreement with the recent report showing that 
the loss of pRb and p107 can predispose to oral tumors in mice 43 , 
although the authors do not report any spontaneous tumor develop-
ment 43 . This might be due to different experimental procedures and/ 
or to the different genetic background of the transgenic mice 43 . 
Gene expression profiles comparing normal and carcinoma sam-
ples provide information about genes that could display impor-
tant functions in the carcinoma maintenance or aggressiveness, </p>

<p>Figure 6 | Rapamycin treatment alleviates tumor development in Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice. a-b') External aspect of snout (a,a') and eyelid (b,b') </p>

<p>of untreated (a,b) or Rapamycin-treated (a',b') Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice after tamoxifen treatment. c) Summary of tumor incidence in the quoted 
anatomical localizations in untreated (grey bars; n511) or Rapamycin treated (black bars n58) Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice after tamoxifen 
treatment. d-e') Immunohistochemistry showing the expression of phosphorylated S6 (d, d') and Akt (e, e') in oral epithelium of untreated (d, e) or 
Rapamycin treated (d', e') Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ; p107 2/2 mice. f) Western blot analysis of protein extracts from snout of rapamycin-treated and untreated 
Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice, after tamoxifen application, showing the expression of the indicated proteins. Actin was used as loading control. g-h'') 
Representative examples of H&amp;E stained palate (g, g', g'') and snout (h, h', h'') sections of control mice (Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice without 
tamoxifen treatment (g, h) Rapamycin treated (g', h') or untreated (g'', h'') Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice. i, I') Immunohistochemistry showing the 
BrdU in snout epithelia of Rapamycin treated (i) or untreated (I') Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ; p107 2/2 mice. j) Quantitative analysis of BrdU incorporation in 
snout epithelia of the untreated/treated Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ; p107 2/2 mice. Data come from at least three mice per genotype scoring three different sections 
per mouse and are shown as mean 6 s.d. Bars5150 mm. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 828 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00828 </p>

<p>
and non-essential roles in the normal tissue. The therapeutic inhibi-
tion of these genes would not affect normal tissue homeostasis but 
may affect tumor growth or invasive properties, thus becoming 
potential molecular targets for therapy. In addition, interspecies 
comparison between human and mouse could also be useful to deter-
mine which genes display similar expression patterns so they can be 
considered candidate targets for therapy and/or biomarkers of 
human cancer 44 . The present data of comparative genomic analyses 
indicate that the Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 mice could represent a 
possible model for human squamous malignancies. This is of a par-
ticular relevance in the case of human cancers bearing HPV infec-
tion, which display a very significant gene expression overlap with 
mouse tumors. This observation, which is in agreement with the 
reported role of HPV E7 oncogene mediating the degradation of 
the retinoblastoma family members 28-30 , also reinforces the proposed 
role of HPV E7 oncogene in the genesis of this type of tumors 43 . Also 
in line with our observations, it has been reported that the expression 
of E7 oncogene is able to induce Akt activity in vitro in a manner 
dependent on pRb binding and inactivation, and similar increase was 
also reported in HPV-positive cervical high-grade squamous intrae-
pithelial lesions when compared with normal cervical tissue 45 . 
The HNSCC represents the sixth most common human cancer 
worldwide, with roughly half a million new cases each year 46 . Despite 
progress in surgery, radiation, and chemotherapy, the 5-year survival 
rate for oral cancer has not improved significantly over the past 
decades and remains at about 50-55% 46 . Numerous new targeted 
therapies have been proposed for this disease, in particular affecting 
Akt pathway (discussed in 47 ). Our present data showing that rapa-
mycin treatment significantly prevent the tumor development also 
reinforce these hypotheses and are in agreement with previous stud-
ies indicating that mTOR inhibition could be beneficial for the treat-
ment of this type of cancer 48-51 . Also in agreement, we observed that 
the deregulated genes in mouse tumors are differentially expressed in 
cell lines sensitive to Akt or mTOR inhibition. 
Collectively, our present data revealed a novel, previously unre-
ported, functional connection between the three major tumor sup-
pressor genes p53, Pten and pRb. Our results also highlight the 
relevance of these tumor suppressors in specific human malignancies 
and open new possible therapeutic avenues for the treatment of these 
diseases, and in particular those associated with HPV infection. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Mice. All animal experiments were approved by the Animal Ethical Committee 
(CEEA) and conducted in compliance with Centro de Investigaciones , 
Medioambientales y  (CIEMAT) guidelines. Rb F/F and p107 2/2 mouse 
models have been previously described 6,42 , Pten F/F mice were kindly provided by Dr. 
Anton Berns (NKI) and K14creER TM were purchased from Jackson laboratory (Jax 
005107). They were backcrossed for 10 generations to a pure FVB/N genetic 
background. Tamoxifen treatment (Sigma) was topically administered in the shaved 
backskin of the animals (2x2 cm) at 20 mg/per day dissolved in DMSO/acetone for 5 
consecutive days. Primary keratinocytes were cultured as described 6 . 1 mM 4-
hydroxitamoxifen (4OHTX) diluted in ethanol was added to primary keratinocytes 
for 72 hours in the culture medium. Rapamycin (LC Laboratories, R-5000) treatment 
was intraperitoneally administered three days per week for two months (10 mg/Kg) 
to mice treated previously with tamoxifen. Newborn skin transplants were performed 
as previously reported 8 . </p>

<p>Immunohistochemical methods. Immunohistochemistry or immunofluorescence 
analyses were performed in formalin or ethanol fixed paraffin embedded samples as 
previously reported 8,22 . Antibodies used were anti K5, anti K6 (Covance), anti K10 
(Dako), mouse monoclonal anti K15 (Neomarkers), anti Pten (Sta Cruz Biotech.), 
anti laminin (Sigma), anti Akt phospho-Ser473 (IHC Specific) and anti phospho-
Ser235/236 S6 ribosomal protein (Cell Signaling). Fluorochrome or Biotin-
conjugated secondary antibodies were purchased from Jackson ImmunoResearch. 
For immunohistochemistry, signal was amplified using avidin-peroxidase (ABC elite 
kit Vector) and peroxidase was visualized using diaminobenzidine as a substrate 
(DAB kit Vector). Control slides were obtained by replacing primary antibodies with 
PBS (data not shown). Mice were intraperitoneally (i.p.) injected with 
bromodeoxyuridine (BrdUrd; 0.1 mg/g weight in 0.9% NaCl; Roche) 1 hour before 
sacrifice. BrdUrd incorporation was monitored by immunofluorescence in ethanol-
fixed or in formalin-fixed sections using an anti BrdU antibody (Roche) as 
described 52 . </p>

<p>Western blot. Western blot was performed as described previously 6,8,22 . Secondary 
antibodies were purchased from Jackson ImmunoResearch. Super Signal West Pico 
Chemiluminscence Substrate (Pierce) was used according to the manufacturer's 
recommendations to visualize the bands. Antibodies used are anti pRb (Pharmigen), 
anti p107, anti p130, anti Pten, anti p63, anti CBP, anti c-jun, anti Akt (Sta. Cruz 
Biotechnology), anti Tip60, anti Pcaf, anti p21, anti p73, anti phospho-Ser392 p53, 
methyl K372 p53, acetyl K3731K382 p53, anti SetD8, anti smyd2 (AbCam), anti Sirt1 
(Sigma), anti DNp73 (Imgenex), anti Akt phosho S473 and phospho T308, anti 
phospho-Ser235/236 S6 ribosomal protein (Cell Signaling) and anti p53 
(Novocastra). Loading was controlled by using an anti Actin antibody (Sta.Cruz 
Biotechnology). 
The panel of phosphorylation profiles of kinases were analyzed following manu-
facter recomendations (Human Phospho-Kinase Array, ARY003, R&amp;D Systems, 
Minneapolis, MN). Membranes were incubated with 500 mg of protein extract from 
skin and tumor samples. This array screens for relative levels of phosphorylation of 39 
proteins. Quantification of the relative expression of specific phosphorylated protein 
was determined by <rs id="software-11" type="software">QuantityOne</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-11" type="creator">BioRad</rs>). </p>

<p>Methylation-specific PCR (MSP). Genomic DNA samples (1 mg) were modified by 
sodium bisulphite using the CpGenome DNA modification kit (Intergen) following 
the manufacturer's instructions. The DNA methylation status of the promoter region 
of Pten and cdkn1a genes was analyzed by methylation specific PCR (MSP) after 
sodium bisulphite modification of DNA. Mouse genomic DNA universally 
methylated for all genes (Zymo Research) was used as a positive control for 
methylated alleles. Water blanks were included with each assay. Following 
amplification, PCR products were subjected to gel electrophoresis through a 2.5% 
agarose gel and were visualized by ethidium bromide staining and UV transil-
lumination. For Pten-MSP, Pten-MD (59-TTTTCGGAGTATCGATTAAGGC-39) 
and Pten-MR (59-GAAAAAAACAAAAACGAAAAACG-39) primers were used in 
the methylated reactions, which amplify a 205bp product. For cdkn1a-MSP, cdkn1a-
MD (59-GTTAGCGAGTTTTCGGGATC-39) and cdkn1a-MR (59-
CTCGACTACTACAATTAACGTCGAA-39) primers were used for the methylated 
reaction, which amplify a 111bp product. The cdkn1a-UD (59-
GGTTAGTGAGTTTTTGGGATTG-39) and cdkn1a-UR (59-
TCAACTACTACAATTAACATCAAA-39) primers were used for the unmethylated 
reaction, which amplify a 111bp product. </p>

<p>Genome-wide transcriptome analysis of mouse Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 
carcinomas. RNA was obtained from 4 normal wild type control skin samples and 10 
carcinomas from Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 genotype, and purified from mice tissue 
as previously described 8 . Hybridization was done to Affymetrix Mouse GE MOE430 
2.0 array. Raw and processed data were deposited in the GEO database with the 
accession identifier GSE38257. Supervised analysis of differential expression between 
tumors and normal tissue was done using SAM test 53 available in the open source 
software <rs type="software">Multiexperiment Viewer</rs> (MeV) 54 , using 200 random permutations. For 
further analyses, a number of 1128 probesets (representing 2.5% of the array) were 
selected by fold change as overexpressed in the carcinomas or underexpressed (giving 
rise to 2256 deregulated probesets). Using this approach, all selected probesets display 
highly significant q-values (q-val50) and fold change values from 4.38 to 4.16 (for 
overexpressed) or from 24.38 to 24.10 (for underexpressed). MOE430 2.0 
Affymetrix chip probeset IDs were mapped to human using Ailun web utility 55 . 
Enrichment analysis of Gene Ontology (GO) terms was done upon uploading 
selected probesets identifiers into <rs type="software">DAVID Functional Annotation web tool</rs>, which 
computes enrichment of GO biological processes terms using EASE score 56,57 . </p>

<p>Enrichment analysis of p53-regulated genes. <rs type="software">Gene Set Enrichment Analysis 
(GSEA</rs>) 58,59 was used to <rs type="software">Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA</rs>) 58,59 was used to 
compare the gene expression pattern of the mouse Rb F/F ;K14creER TM ;p107 2/2 tumors 
with other gene signatures. In Table 1, we analyze the enrichment with a collection of 
2392 different gene sets (available at http://www.broadinstitute.org/gsea/msigdb/ 
collections.jsp) that represents gene expression signatures of genetic and chemical 
perturbations (subgroup c2.cgp). A selection of some relevant and highly statistically 
significant enriched gene sets was done. We permutated the gene set for 1000 times 
rather than permutating the phenotype because the sample number is small. In Table 
2, we analyze the enrichment of p53-activated and p53-repressed DNA damage 
response genes in mouse embryonic stem (mES) cells within the mouse tumors when 
compared to normal skin. Gene sets were downloaded from 32 , and fall into 2 groups: i) 
2070 genes activated and ii) 1627 genes repressed upon p53 activation with DNA 
damage agent adriamycin as determined by both ChIP-seq (with a pan-p53 antibody) 
and GE (GE) microarray data of mES cells 32 . ES and 14-d differentiated ES gene 
expression dataset was retrieved from the GEO database (GSE2972). </p>

<p>Overlapping analysis in human cancer GE studies. We used Oncomine GE 
Signatures database to search for overlapping 60 . Association of the mapped signatures 
with the database signatures was tested using Fisher's exact test, and was considered 
significant for Odds Ratio.1.5, and p-val,0.006. Genes overexpressed or 
underexpressed in the mouse carcinomas were mapped to human gene symbols and 
loaded into the Oncomine database. We have searched for overlaps using different 
filtering criteria, based on the type of human cancer comparison performed. These 
criteria were: i) ''Cancer vs. Normal'', to search for similarities with human squamous 
cell carcinomas of different tissue of origin; ii) ''Drug sensitivity'', to search for 
similarities with human cancer cell lines with differential sensitivities to specific </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 828 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00828 </p>

<p>
 </p>



<p>
Acknowledgements </p>

<p>Grant support: Ministerio de Ciencia e  (MICINN) grants 
SAF2011-26122-C02-01 and SAF2012-34378, Comunidad  de Madrid </p>

<p>Oncocycle Program Grants S2006/BIO-0232 and S2010/BMD-2470, Ministerio de Sanidad 
y Consumo grant ISCIII-RETIC RD06/0020/0029 and from  Sandra Ibarra to 
JMP. Grant AP99782012 from MMA Foundation (to MD) and RD06/0020/0111 (to FP) are 
also ackowledged. The excellent technical support by Pilar  in histology and the 
personnel of the CIEMAT Animal Facility are specially recognized. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>J.M.P. and M.S. directed all aspects of the Rbp107 project. M.S. and J.M.P. designed the 
experiments, M.S., C.C., R.G-E. and J.M.P. analyzed the data, and J.M.P. wrote the 
manuscript. C.C., C.S., C.L., M.D., M.F.L., X.A., F.P. and M.S. performed the experiments. 
R.G-E. and J.M.P. supervised the gene array data collection and analysis processing. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>License: This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this 
license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Costa, C. et al. A Novel Tumor suppressor network in squamous 
malignancies. Sci. Rep. 2, 828; DOI:10.1038/srep00828 (2012). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 828 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00828 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>