<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3822024" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Obstetric or non-obstetric surgery can be performed in pregnant women during the second trimester. We 
evaluated maximal sensory block level (MSBL), and other sensory block characteristics after spinal anesthesia in early 
and late second trimester pregnant women. 
Methods: Forty-four pregnant women scheduled for cervical cerclage under spinal anesthesia in the early second trimes-
ter (Group E) or in the late second trimester (Group L) were enrolled in this study. Spinal anesthesia was performed at 
the L3/4 and 7 mg of 0.5% hyperbaric bupivacaine was injected into the subarachnoid space. Hemodynamic variables, 
incidence of nausea/vomiting, ephedrine dose, and sensory block were recorded every 2.5 min during the first 15 min 
and 20 min after the injection. The MSBL, the time at which MSBL was achieved, and the time to the two-segment re-
gression of the sensory level were also recorded. 
Results: The maximum number of segments blocked was significantly greater in the Group L than in the Group E. The 
incidence of nausea/vomiting and hypotension, and dose of administrated ephedrine were significantly higher in the 
Group L than in the Group E. The mean arterial pressure during the 15 min after subarachnoid injection was significant-
ly lower compared to the baseline value in the Group L. 
Conclusions: The MSBL of spinal anesthesia with hyperbaric bupivacaine 7 mg were T9 in the early and T5 in the late 
second trimester groups. Pregnant women in the late second trimester exhibited increased incidence of hypotension and 
need for ephedrine than women in the early second trimester. (Korean J Anesthesiol 2013; 65: 322-326) </p>

<p>Spinal anesthesia is a preferred anesthetic technique in preg-
nant women in their second trimester due to minimal fetal drug 
exposure and reduced potential teratogenicity. In late stage of 
pregnant women, the volume of the lumbosacral subarachnoid 
space is reduced due to engorgement of epidural blood vessels 
resulting from compression of the inferior vena cava by the 
gravid uterus [1,2]. The enhanced spread of spinal anesthesia, 
comparable in magnitude with that observed in the term group, 
occurred in the second trimester group [1]. 
In a previous study, pregnant women in their second trimes-
ter exhibited a higher level of subarachnoid sensory block than 
that of non-pregnant women within 30 minutes of hyperbaric 
bupivacaine injection [3]. The maximum number of derma-
tomes blocked was greater by three dermatomes in the second 
trimester group compared to the non-pregnant group [3]. 
In a majority of the previous studies that evaluated the level 
of sensory block resulting from spinal anesthesia administered 
to pregnant women, grouping was done according to trimesters, 
a period of 13 weeks. Such groupings fell short of identifying the 
level of sensory block in the early and late periods of the second 
trimester. Moreover, there were a few studies on the spread of 
the subarachnoid sensory block in early and late second trimes-
ter pregnant women. 
Therefore, we evaluated the maximal sensory block level 
(MSBL) in pregnant women during early and late second tri-
mester undergoing spinal anesthesia with 7 mg of hyperbaric 
bupivacaine for cervical cerclage. In addition, we compared side 
effects such as hypotension and the requirement for ephedrine. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board 
of our hospital and registered at http://cris.nih.go.kr. Written 
informed consent was obtained from all the subjects and data 
collection was carried out from November 2011 to March 2012. 
Forty-four pregnant women scheduled for cervical cerclage 
under spinal anesthesia in the early second trimester (Group E) 
or in the late second trimester (Group L) were enrolled in this 
study. All the patients were American Society of Anesthesiolo-
gists physical status I or II. Patients with contraindications to 
spinal anesthesia, including coagulopathy, local skin infection, 
and uncorrected hypovolemia, body weight (&lt; 50 kg, or &gt; 100 
kg), multiple pregnancy and patients who could not assume 
the lateral position for spinal anesthesia due to risk of amnionic 
membrane rupture were excluded from our study. 
None of the patients received premedication. On arrival in 
the operating room, standard monitoring devices (Patient moni-
tor M1205A, Philips, USA or Micro O2, Siemens, Germany), </p>

<p>including an electrocardiogram, pulse oximetry and a noninva-
sive blood pressure cuff, were applied to the patients. Baseline 
systolic blood pressure (SBP), diastolic blood pressure (DBP), 
mean arterial pressure (MAP), and heart rate (HR) were record-
ed. Before spinal anesthesia, all patients intravenously received 
8-10 ml/kg of crystalloid solution. Patients were placed on their 
right side and the puncture site was disinfected. Local anesthetic 
was infiltrated into the subcutaneous tissue or muscle at the 
L3/4 interspinous space. A 25-gauge Whitacre spinal needle was 
inserted using the midline approach. When a free flow of cere-
brospinal fluid was confirmed, 7 mg of 0.5% hyperbaric bupiva-
caine (Marcaine </p>

<p>Ⓡ </p>

<p>, Astra Zeneca, Sweden) was injected into the 
subarachnoid space at 0.1 ml/sec. After performing spinal anes-
thesia, patients were placed in the supine position with a wedge 
under the right hip for five minutes and then in the lithotomy 
position for surgery. Since then cervical cerclage was started. 
In Group L, amniocentesis was performed add to cerclage for 
decompression of intrauterine pressure. The endpoint of the 
study was reached when the sensory block was below T10 in the 
recovery room, and the patients were transported to their room. 
The spinal anesthesia was performed by a second year resident. 
We recorded the SBP, DBP, MAP, HR, incidence of nausea/ 
vomiting, ephedrine dose, and sensory block every 2.5 min dur-
ing the first 15 min and 20 min after the injection. The sensory 
block level was assessed at the left midclavicular line using loss 
of light touch sensation with a alcohol swab. The MSBL, the time 
at which MSBL was achieved, and the time to the two-segment 
regression (TSR) of the sensory level were also recorded. Each 
dermatomal level was scored in sequence starting at L3 = 1 and 
T6 = 10 for statistical analyses. An intervention blood pressure 
was calculated as 80% of the baseline blood pressure. If SBP 
fell below an intervention blood pressure, or 90 mmHg, or if 
the patient complained of nausea and vomiting, ephedrine 4 
mg was injected intravenously. When the blood pressure drop 
continued, the same dose was repeatedly injected. Oxygen was 
supplied at the rate of 5 L/min through a facemask during the 
surgery. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The statistical analysis was performed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 9.2</rs>, 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Inc.</rs>., Cary, NC, USA). The data was expressed as the mean ± 
SD, median (range), or number of patients. The sample size was 
based on a previous study [3] which had a three-dermatome dif-
ference in maximal block height with an alpha error of 0.05 and 
a power of 90%. Twenty-two patients per group were necessary 
to demonstrate statistical significance. To compare variables be-
tween the two groups, the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test was used to 
identify the variables with a normal distribution. Variables with 
a normal distribution were compared by independent t-tests </p>



<p>www.ekja.org </p>

<p>Vol. 65, No. 4, October 2013 
Spinal anesthesia in second trimester </p>

<p>and those without a normal distribution were compared by the 
Mann-Whitney U-test. The number of patients was compared 
between the groups using the chi-square test. Value compari-
sons for each measurement were also conducted using repeated 
measures of ANOVA. All significant results were also analyzed 
with Tukey's post hoc test to determine whether time points 
produced values significantly different from baseline values. A P 
value less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Forty-four pregnant women were enrolled in this study and 
none were excluded or failed to inadequate anesthesia. 
The demographic data of the patients is presented in Table 1. 
The mean gestational age was 13.3 ± 0.6 in Group E vs 22.5 ± 
2 weeks in Group L and the fetal weight measured by ultraso-
nography was 89 ± 7.6 vs 616.6 ± 196 g in the Group E and L, 
respectively. The other characteristics of the patients were not 
significantly different between the groups. 
The number of dermatomes blocked at each time point is 
shown in Fig. 1. The number of dermatomes blocked was higher 
in the Group L 2.5 min after the subarachnoid injection. The 
maximum number of segments blocked was significantly greater </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Number of dermatomes blocked in the early (Group E) and late 
(Group L) second trimester of pregnant at 2.5, 5, 7.5, 10, 12.5, 15 and 20 
minutes after subarachnoid injection of 7 mg of 0.5% bupivacaine. *P &lt; 
0.05. Data represent mean ± SD. Dermatome 1 = L3; 4 = T12; 8 = T8; 12 
= T4 of sensory block level. </p>

<p>Table 1. Patients' Demographic Data in the Early (Group E) and Late 
(Group L) Second Trimester of Pregnant </p>

<p>Group E 
(n = 22) </p>

<p>Group L 
(n = 22) 
P value </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
Height (cm) 
Weight (kg) 
Gestational age (week) 
Weight of fetus (g) </p>

<p>33.0 ± 2.8 
162.5 ± 4.1 
62.2 ± 9.8 
13.3 ± 0.6 
89.0 ± 7.6 </p>

<p>32.3 ± 3.2 
161.4 ± 6.4 
63.0 ± 10.1 
22.5 ± 2.0 
616.6 ± 196.0 </p>

<p>0. 3961 
0.5044 
0.8098 
&lt; 0.0001 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Values are presented as the mean ± SD. </p>

<p>Table 2. Sensory Block Characteristics in the Early (Group E) and Late 
(Group L) Second Trimester of Pregnant </p>

<p>Group E 
(n = 22) </p>

<p>Group L 
(n = 22) 
P value </p>

<p>Nausea/Vomiting (n) 
Incidence of hypotension (n) 
Dose of ephedrine (mg) 
MSBL (dermatome) 
Time to MSBL (min) 
Time to TSR (min) </p>

<p>0 
0 
0 
7.3 ± 2.1 
11.7 ± 4.3 
58.9 ± 14.8 </p>

<p>5 
7 
4.7 ± 8.5 
11.0 ± 2.7 
10.8 ± 2.9 
55.0 ± 13.8 </p>

<p>0.0485 
0.0089 
0.0100 
&lt; 0.0001 
0.4186 
0.3755 </p>

<p>Values are presented as the mean ± SD or number of patients. 
Dermatome 1 = L3; 4 = T12; 8 = T8; 12 = T4 of sensory block level. 
MSBL: maximal sensory block level, TSR: two-segment regression. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Changes in mean arterial pressure (MAP, A) and heart rate (HR, B) after subarachnoid injection of 7 mg of 0.5% bupivacaine in the early (Group E) 
and late (Group L) second trimester of pregnant. Data represent mean ± SD. *P &lt; 0.05 compared with baseline value in each group. </p>

<p> 
www.ekja.org </p>

<p>Korean J Anesthesiol 
Lee et al. </p>

<p>in the Group L than in the Group E (11.0 ± 2.7 vs 7.3 ± 2.1, P &lt; 
0.0001). 
The characteristics of the sensory blocks are presented in 
Table 2. The incidence of nausea/vomiting and hypotension, and 
dose of administrated ephedrine were significantly higher in the 
Group L than in the Group E. However, the time at which MSBL 
was achieved, and the time to the TSR of the sensory level were 
not significantly different between the two groups. 
Fig. 2 shows the changes in MAP and HR after the subarach-
noid injection. The MAP and HR were not significantly different 
during the study period between the two groups. However, the 
MAP during the first 15 min after subarachnoid injection was 
significantly lower compared to the baseline value of the Group L. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In our study, the maximal sensory block levels of spinal an-
esthesia with hyperbaric bupivacaine 7 mg were T9 in the early 
and T5 in the late second trimester groups. Furthermore, preg-
nant women in the late second trimester exhibited a higher in-
cidence of hypotension and required more frequently ephedrine 
than that of the early second trimester. 
The mechanism for the enhanced spread of spinal anesthesia 
in pregnant women has not been clearly elucidated. A mechani-
cal factor that could be one possible explanation is the decreased 
CSF volume at lumbosacral area caused by the distension of the 
extradural veins due to obstruction of the inferior vena cava by 
the gravid uterus [4,5] and changes in the curvature of the spinal 
column [6]. Epidural venous distension develops in the first tri-
mester and remains throughout the third trimester [7]. Lee and 
colleagues [3] investigated the level of sensory block after spinal 
anesthesia in pregnant women in their second trimester (15.7 
weeks mean gestational age). In their study, the maximal block 
level with hyperbaric bupivacaine 7 mg was T7 in the second tri-
mester and it was greater by three dermatomes than in the non-
pregnant group. When considering the mean gestational age, 
this result was similar to our study in that patients in the early 
and late second trimester group had maximal sensory block 
levels of T9 and T5, respectively. Although compression of the 
vena cava by the enlarged uterus mechanically did not occur in 
the early second trimester, venous distension secondary to the 
increased blood volume associated with pregnancy did occur [8]. 
In our study, fetal weight measured by ultrasonography was 89.0 
± 7.6 vs 616.6 ± 196.0 gm in the Group E and L, respectively. In 
the late second trimester group (22.5 ± 2.0 weeks mean gesta-
tional age), the increased size of the fetus and the enlarged uterus 
might compress the vena cava similar to the third trimester. 
Another mechanical factor that could explain our findings 
is the change in the curvature of the spinal column. Lumbar 
lordosis exaggerated by the enlarged uterus at term pregnancy is </p>

<p>thought to influence the spread of spinal anesthesia [9]. Howev-
er, the effect from the mechanical factor on the difference in the 
spread of spinal anesthesia in the early and late second trimester 
does not seem to provide a sufficient explanation by itself. 
As a non-mechanical factor, plasma and CSF progesterone 
has been suggested as a reason for the enhanced spread of spinal 
anesthesia by altering the susceptibility of the nerves to local 
anesthetics [10-12]. Hirabayashi et al. [10] measured the proges-
terone concentration of the CSF in non-pregnant, first, second, 
third trimester, and term pregnant women. They observed that 
the progesterone concentration of the CSF in third trimester and 
term pregnant women was higher than in non-pregnant, first, 
and second trimester pregnant women. However, the maximal 
cephalad spread of spinal analgesia was higher in second, third 
trimester, and term pregnant women. Their study suggests that 
not only a minimum level of progesterone in the CSF but also a 
certain period of exposure may be necessary for the enhanced 
spread of spinal anesthesia. Bader et al. [13] investigated the 
effect of progesterone on neural blocks although the cellular 
mechanism of progesterone is unclear, and found that a devel-
opment period for increased sensitivity of the nerves to local 
anesthetics was needed. A certain period of exposure to elevated 
levels of progesterone resulting in increased sensitivity to local 
anesthetics is thought to be probable explanation for a more 
enhanced spread of spinal anesthesia in late second trimester 
pregnancy than in early second trimester pregnancy. 
Hemodynamic changes including blood pressure and HR 
are observed at the early and middle stages of pregnancy. SBP 
decreases by 6-8% at the middle stages of pregnancy and HR 
increases at the second trimesters by 20% [14,15]. In our study, 
although we could not compare the hemodynamic changes with 
non-pregnant women, we were able to investigate the cardiovas-
cular response to spinal anesthesia in the early and late second 
trimester. The incidence of nausea/vomiting and hypotension, 
and dose of administrated ephedrine were significantly higher in 
the Group L than in the Group E. Seven out of twenty-two pa-
tients in the late second trimester group had hypotension occur 
after spinal anesthesia with hyperbaric bupivacaine 7 mg. Our 
results possibly suggest that cardiovascular responses to spinal 
anesthesia are different between early and late second trimester 
pregnancy. The time at which MSBL was achieved, and the time 
to the TSR of the sensory level were faster in the Group L, but 
did not have any statistical difference. 
This study differentiates itself from previous studies in that it 
divides the second trimester into early and late spans. Previous 
studies were mostly designed to regard the second trimester as 
a sole unit. This study revealed that the level of sensory block of 
spinal anesthesia differs within the second trimester according 
to the number of gestation weeks. 
Our study has some limitations. First, after performing spinal </p>



<p>www.ekja.org </p>

<p>Vol. 65, No. 4, October 2013 
Spinal anesthesia in second trimester </p>

<p>anesthesia, patients were turned to the supine position for five 
minutes and then fixed in the lithotomy position during the 
operation. It is thought that the lithotomy position can limit the 
cephalad spread of local anesthetics because of the loss of the 
lumbosacral curvature. However, according to a study by Logan 
and Drummond [16], limiting hip flexion to 90 
o does not alter </p>

<p>the level of anesthetic sensory block. Second, our study was not 
blinded for the patients and observers because the amniocente-
sis was added to cervical cerclage in Group L for decompression. 
In conclusions, the MSBL of spinal anesthesia with hyper-</p>

<p>baric bupivacaine 7 mg were T9 in the early and T5 in the late 
second trimester groups. Pregnant women in the late second tri-
mester exhibited increased incidence of hypotension and need 
for ephedrine than women in the early second trimester. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Hye Sun Lee, Biostatistician, Department of Re-
search Affairs, Yonsei University College of Medicine, for statis-
tical analysis. </p>



</text></tei>