<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3977211" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Purpose: This study investigated the agreement of four anthropometric-based 
measurements including weight-for-height (WH), body mass index-for-age 
(BMI), mid-upper arm circumference-for-age (MUAC) and triceps skinfold 
thickness-for-age (TST) to identify underweight and overweight children and 
adolescents. </p>

<p>Methods: Two data sets were used in this research. The first one was a 
multistage random sample of 2397 healthy school children in pre-pubertal 
stage in Shiraz. The second data set consisted of 487 healthy students in 
pubertal stage and 558 students in post-pubertal stage. The parametric LMS 
method was used to construct reference centiles curves for each measure. The 
Kappa statistic was applied to examine the pairwise agreement of the four 
indices for detecting thinness and obesity. </p>

<p>Results: Generally, the pairwise agreement of adiposity measures was higher 
for identifying obesity than thinness. There was an excellent agreement 
between WH and BMI for detecting both thin and obese children in almost all 
subgroups (P&lt;0.001). MUAC had an excellent agreement with BMI in pre-
pubertal individuals (P&lt;0.001). However, TST had a weak agreement with the 
other three indices for detecting thinness and weak to good agreement for 
classification of obesity. </p>

<p>Conclusion: The performance of the four anthropometric-based measurements 
varied by sex and maturity level. MUAC as a simple and low-cost screening 
tool can also be used as an alternative to BMI for obesity assessment among 
pre-pubertal groups. </p>

<p>he worldwide growing pattern of childhood 
obesity has been identified as an important health 
problem over the past decades 
[1-5] . Obesity during </p>

<p>childhood has been established to be strongly 
associated with that in adulthood and also with several 
chronic diseases such as diabetes, some types of cancer 
and cardiovascular diseases 
[1-6] . In addition, being </p>

<p>underweight is an index of malnutrition and is also 
recognized as an underlying cause of some health 
disorders </p>

<p>[7-8] </p>

<p>. Therefore, proper assessment of the body </p>

<p>composition is a critical concern in public health 
evaluation and clinical screening. The reference 
methods such as dual-energy X-ray (DXA) or 
underwater weighting, which can analyze body 
composition accurately, are limited to the clinical 
research due to their complexity and cost 
[9-11] . Instead, </p>

<p>a variety of anthropometric-based measurements such 
as body mass index (BMI), weight-for-height (WH), 
triceps skinfold thickness (TST) and mid-upper arm 
circumference (MUAC) were introduced as simple, 
low cost and feasible methods </p>

<p>[9-11] </p>

<p>. Previous studies 
showed that different indices estimate different values </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>Agreement Analysis among Measures of Thinness and Obesity Assessment </p>

<p>273 </p>

<p>Published by: Tehran University of Medical Sciences (http://asjsm.tums.ac.ir) 
Asian J Sports Med; Vol 4 (No 4), Dec 2013 </p>

<p>for the prevalence of underweightness or 
overweightness which may lead to unnecessary and 
inappropriate clinical intervention 
[12] . Therefore, </p>

<p>selecting the most appropriate and feasible method 
among a variety of existing obesity indices is an 
important key to a successful clinical decision. The 
performance of the aforementioned anthropometric 
measurements has been evaluated by pioneer 
researchers, demonstrating that each method has its 
own advantages and disadvantages and behaves 
differently in different age and sex groups 
[6, 9-11, 13] . </p>

<p>However, a critical point which has not been 
comprehensively addressed is whether these body 
composition indices among various sex and maturation 
stage groups classify the same subjects as obese or thin 
which can be explored by agreement analysis. 
Although few studies have assessed the degree of 
pairwise agreement between a number of body 
composition indices in various age groups 
[10, 12, 14-16] , to </p>

<p>the best of our knowledge, no study has investigated 
the agreement of the all four obesity indices including 
BMI, WH, TST and MUAC simultaneously. 
Furthermore, most of the previously published studies 
have focused on just children or adolescents separately 
or have assessed children in a wide range of age 
altogether. 
Therefore, the present study aimed at examining the 
pairwise agreement of these four indices for identifying 
thin and obese individuals based on two representative 
samples of school children and adolescents in Shiraz, 
Southern Iran. We also made an attempt to investigate 
the agreement analysis separately in different age 
groups according to maturation levels (pre-pubertal, 
pubertal and post-pubertal groups), which has not yet 
been considered in other studies. </p>

<p>METHODS AND SUBJECTS </p>

<p>Two data sets were employed for this study. To 
conduct agreement analysis among prepubertal school 
children we used a data set collected in the academic 
year of 2002-2003. This cross-sectional study includes 
measurements of weight, height, mid-upper arm </p>

<p>circumference, triceps skinfold thickness and age of 
2397 healthy school children (1129 girls and 1268 
boys) in the age range of 6.5-11.5 years. The 
participants were randomly selected in a multistage 
method forming 2% of the school children from the 
four educational districts of Shiraz, one of the five 
main cities of Iran. The sample size was determined 
based on formula for each sex-age group 
(248 students), where is the variance of anthropometric 
measures estimated from previous study conducted in 
1988 
[17] and d is the precision. In each educational </p>

<p>district, a 10% systematic random sample of schools 
was selected and within each school, using tables of 
random numbers, a 1in 5 sample of students were 
chosen. Three trained auxologists measured the 
anthropometric measurements of students in morning 
and evening shifts. 
Height and weight were measured to the 0.1 cm and 
0.1 kg respectively, using a SECA marked stadiometer. 
A non-stretchable strip was used to measure the 
MUAC to the nearest 0.1 cm, based on the method 
proposed by Cameron </p>

<p>[18] </p>

<p>. Triceps skinfold thickness 
was measured using a graded caliper and recorded 
inmm. In addition, the subjects' ages were calculated 
exactly as the difference between the date of the 
interview and that of birth, which were recorded in 
their birth certificate accurately. To ensure that all 
children in this sample were in the pre-pubertal stage 
just some questions were asked from students and also 
their parents about the signs of puberty and individuals 
which were in pubertal stage were excluded from the 
study. 
The second data set consisted of a total of 487 
students including 217 boys and 270 girls in pubertal 
stage (aged 11.5-14.5 years) and 558 students including 
382 boys and 276 girls in postpuberal stage (aged 14.5-
18.5 years) which were randomly sampled by a multi-
stage random sampling procedure from guidance and 
high schools of the four educational districts of Shiraz 
in the Spring of 2011. Determination of sample size 
was conducted in a similar procedure as the former 
study described above. Two guidance schools and two 
high schools were selected randomly and in each grade 
of the schools a random sample of the students were 
selected. In this study, weight, height, MUAC, and age 
were measured using the same techniques and devices </p>

<p>Ayatollahi SMT, et al </p>



<p>Asian J Sports Med; Vol 4 (No 4), Dec 2013 
Published by: Tehran University of Medical Sciences (http://asjsm.tums.ac.ir) </p>

<p>as the former one by two trained auxologists, except 
TST which was measured to the nearest 0.5 mm. In this 
study, no exact criteria were used to classify 
participants in pubertal and post-pubertal categories. 
However, based on the mean and median age of girls 
and boys in different pubertal stages reported in the 
studies performed previously in Iran 
[19-20] , we </p>

<p>categorized students in guidance school to pubertal 
stage and those in high school to post-pubertal stage. 
The subjects' body mass index was obtained as weight 
divided by squared height in metric system (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). 
The LMS method 
[21] was applied to calculate sex-</p>

<p>specific weight-for-height, BMI-for-age, MUAC-for-
age, and also TST-for-age centiles in each of the three 
stages of maturity. The growth reference centile charts 
for prepubertal children were provided in the previous 
studies </p>

<p>[22-25] </p>

<p>. Although there is still no comprehensive 
consensus on how to define underweight and 
overweightness based on growth reference centiles, in 
this study the 5 
th and 95 
th centiles (according to a </p>

<p>number of references 
[22, 26-27] were selected as cut-off </p>

<p>points to identify underweight and obese children, 
respectively. Kappa statistic was used to assess the 
pairwise agreement of the WH, BMI, MUAC and TST 
for classifying underweight and obese children. A 
value of zero indicates no concordance and a value of 
unity indicates perfect concordance. Kappa coefficient 
greater than 0.75 represents excellent agreement, 
between 0.40 and 0.75 fair to good agreement, and 
smaller than 0.40 poor agreement </p>

<p>[28] </p>

<p>. In addition, 
Pearson correlation analysis was conducted to evaluate 
the linear association of anthropometric measures. Data 
analysis was performed using <rs type="software">LMSchartmaker</rs> and 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">11.5</rs> softwares. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Table 1 presents the descriptive statistics of height, 
weight, BMI, MUAC and TST of school children 
classified by age and sex. Based on independent 
sample t-test, no significant gender difference was 
observed in terms of their BMI in all age groups 
(P&gt;0.05) with the exception of the last age group in </p>

<p>17.5-18.49 </p>

<p>23 
11 
71.5(16.5) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>51.0(6.3) 
171.7(5.4) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>156.2(6.4) 
24.2(5.1) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>20.9(2.2) 
25.93(2.9) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>23.7(2.4) 
18.8(9.2) 
15.3(4.2) </p>

<p>Table 1: 
Number, mean and standard deviation of weight, height, BMI, MUAC and TST by age and sex </p>

<p>16.5-17.49 </p>

<p>86 
76 
63.4(10.7) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>54.1(8.5) 
171(5.6) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>159.1(5.7) 
21.5(3.1) 
21.4(3.1) 
24.3(2.9) 
24.7(3.2) 
14.5(6.5) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>17.8(6.2) </p>

<p>15.5-16.49 
127 
111 
63.5(15.7) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>54.9(11.2) 
170.3(7.9) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>158.9(4.8) 
21.8(4.6) 
21.7(4.1) 
23.8(6.4) 
25.0(3.5) 
18.6(9.4) 
18.2(6.3) </p>

<p>14.5-15.49 
163 
87 
61.2(14.7) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>55.2(10.9) 
166.5(7.2) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>158.3(4.6) 
21.9(4.6) 
21.9(3.9) 
23.7(4.5) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>25.3(3.5) 
19.5(9.2) 
17.8(5.9) </p>

<p>13.5-14.49 </p>

<p>76 
120 
53.3(12.5) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>49.55(8.1) 
160.6(7.6) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>156.6(6.7) 
20.5(3.8) 
20.2(2.8) 
21.9(3.4) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>24.3(3.6) 
14.0(6.5) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>16.8(5.7) </p>

<p>12.5-13.49 </p>

<p>46 
63 
46.6(14.2) 
49.1(12.7) 
152.3(9.4) 
154.6(6.7) 
19.7(4.4) 
20.4(4.4) 
21.4(4.3) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>23.9(3.8) 
14.2(6.4) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>18.1(7.8) </p>

<p>11.5-12.49 </p>

<p>76 
77 
42.9(13.1) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>48.1(12.5) 
146.0(6.8) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>152.0(6.7) 
19.9(4.6) 
20.7(4.6) 
20.8(4.1) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>23.9(4.0) 
14.9(7.7) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>19.48(7.9) </p>

<p>10.5-11.49 
284 
267 
33.8(7.4) 
34.9(7.9) 
139.9(6.5) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>141.5(7.4) 
17.2(2.7) 
17.3(2.9) 
19.8(2.7) 
20.2(2.7) 
9.4(5.6) 
10.5(5.2) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>9.5-10.49 
261 
245 
31.1(6.7) 
30.8(6.5) 
135.6(6.3) 
136.1(6.6) 
16.8(2.6) 
16.5(2.6) 
19.4(2.6) 
19.5(2.6) 
8.9(4.9) 
9.9(5.0) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>8.5-9.49 
249 
212 
28.1(5.9) 
27.7(5.7) 
130.7(6.3) 
130.4(6.5) 
16.4(2.4) 
16.2(2.3) 
18.6(2.4) 
18.7(2.3) 
8.5(4.7) 
8.9(4.4) </p>

<p>7.5-8.49 
237 
212 
25.1(5.3) 
24.6(4. 7) 
125.2(5.8) 
124.6(5.8) 
15.9(2.4) 
15.8(2.1) 
17.8(2.4) 
18.1(2.3) 
7.8(4.9) 
8.4(4.1) </p>

<p>6.5-7.49 
225 
184 
22.3(3.7) 
22.0(3.9) </p>

<p>119. 7(5.2) 
119.2(5.9) 
15.5(1.8) 
15.4(1.8) 
17.2(1.8) 
17.4(1.9) 
7.2(3.8) 
7.1(3.7) </p>

<p>Age (years) 
Boys 
Girls 
Boys 
Girls 
Boys 
Girls 
Boys 
Girls 
Boys 
Girls 
Boys 
Girls </p>

<p>number 
Weight 
Mean (SD) 
Height 
Mean (SD) 
BMI Mean 
(SD) 
MUAC 
Mean (SD) 
TST Mean 
(SD) </p>

<p>Agreement Analysis among Measures of Thinness and Obesity Assessment </p>



<p>Published by: Tehran University of Medical Sciences (http://asjsm.tums.ac.ir) 
Asian J Sports Med; Vol 4 (No 4), Dec 2013 </p>

<p>Table 2: Prevalence (%) of thinness (under 5 
th centile), and fatness (above 95 
th centile) by sex and puberty stages. </p>

<p>Underweight 
Obesity 
Pre-pubertal 
Pubertal 
Post-pubertal 
Pre-pubertal 
Pubertal 
Post-pubertal 
boys 
girls boys 
girls 
boys 
girls 
boys 
girls 
boys 
girls 
boys 
girls </p>

<p>BMI 
4.3 
4.1 
4.0 
4.6 
3.5 
6.3 
5.8 
5.8 
7.0 
5.0 
6.8 
4.9 
WH 
4.9 
4.4 
4.0 
5.0 
5.0 
5.6 
5.4 
5.2 
5.5 
5.8 
5.8 
5.2 
MUAC 
5.8 
4.3 
6.0 
5.4 
3.8 
5.2 
6.1 
5.2 
5.0 
4.2 
5.5 
3.5 
TST 
5.5 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>3.4 
6.5 
5.8 
4.8 
3.8 
5.1 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>4.5 
4.5 
4.2 
3.5 
6.3 </p>

<p>* Significant difference between boys and girls at 5% level; BMI: Body mass index; WH: weight-for-height; MUAC: mid-upper arm 
circumference-for-age; TST: triceps skinfold thickness-for-age </p>

<p>which the boys had a significantly greater BMI as 
compared to the girls. In addition, in younger children 
(less than 11.5 years), there was no significant 
difference between the two genders regarding their 
weight and height, though in older ones the weight and 
height of the boys was significantly higher than those 
of the girls. In terms of MUAC, just in the middle-aged 
children as well as the last age group significant 
differences were observed between boys and girls in 
which boys' MUAC was greater than that of girls. 
However, the girls' TST was thicker than that of the 
boys (p-value&lt;0.05) in the age groups of 9.5 to 14.49 
and 16.5-17.49 years, reflecting a reverse pattern 
between boys and girls compared to the other indices. 
The pubertal stage and sex-specific prevalence of 
thinness and obesity based on the four aforementioned 
growth reference centiles are presented in Table 2. 
Generally, obesity was more prevalent than thinness. 
Nevertheless, in the post-pubertal girls, the 
prevalence of thinness was more pronounced on the 
basis of BMI, WH, and MUAC, but not based on TST. 
Moreover using chi-square test, the prevalence of 
thinness and obesity did not differ significantly 
between boys and girls based on all indices (p-
value&gt;0.05) except for TST in pre-pubertal individuals. 
Moreover, we reported the percentage of normal </p>

<p>students based on the constructed reference centiles 
curve in Table 3. 
Tables 4 and 5 display the pairwise agreement of 
the four body composition indices for detecting 
underweight and overweight children according to the 
three maturity levels. As shown in Table 4, the level of 
agreement between WH and BMI was excellent for 
assessing thinness in both sexes and each pubertal 
stage except for the pubertal girls and post-pubertal 
boys, revealing a good agreement. Moreover, the level 
of agreement between MUAC and BMI was moderate 
in all classifications with the exception of the pubertal 
girls which was poor. MUAC and WH had moderate 
agreement in the post-pubertal girls and boys and poor 
agreement in the others levels of maturity. However, 
TST showed extremely poor agreement with any of the 
other measurements (Kappa ranges from 0.09 to 0.37). 
In general, the pairwise agreements of adiposity 
measures were higher for identifying obesity than 
thinness. As indicated in Table 5, for detecting obesity 
WH and BMI showed an excellent degree of agreement 
in each maturation level and gender with the exception 
of pre-pubertal and pubertal boys presenting 
reasonably good agreement. Furthermore, an excellent 
agreement between MUAC and BMI in the pre-
pubertal stage and a moderate one in the other maturity </p>

<p>Table 3: Percentage of normal children and adolescents by sex and puberty stages based on the reference centiles </p>

<p>Parameter 
Pre-pubertal 
Pubertal 
Post-pubertal 
boys 
girls 
boys 
girls 
boys 
girls 
Body mass index 
89.9 
90.1 
89.0 
90.4 
89.7 
88.8 
Weight-for-height 
89.7 
90.4 
90.5 
89.2 
89.2 
89.2 
MUAC 
88.1 
90.5 
89.0 
90.4 
90.7 
91.3 
TST 
89.4 
92.1 
89.0 
90.0 
91.7 
89.9 </p>

<p>MUAC: Mid-upper arm circumference-for-age; TST: triceps skinfold thickness-for-age </p>

<p>Ayatollahi SMT, et al </p>



<p>Asian J Sports Med; Vol 4 (No 4), Dec 2013 
Published by: Tehran University of Medical Sciences (http://asjsm.tums.ac.ir) </p>

<p>Mid-Upper Arm Circumference-for-Age </p>

<p>Postpubertal 
Girls 
-
-
-
0.33 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>* excellent concordance,  † moderate concordance,  ‡ poor concordance ; MUAC: Mid-upper </p>

<p>arm circumference-for </p>

<p>age </p>

<p>Table 4: 
Degree of agreement between four body composition indices for detecting thinness by sex and puberty stage </p>

<p>Boys 
-
-
-
0.26 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Pubertal 
Girls 
-
-
-
0.37 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Boys 
-
-
-
0.36 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Prepubertal 
Girls 
-
-
-
0.20 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Boys 
-
-
-
0.11 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Weight-for-Height </p>

<p>Postpubertal 
Girls 
-
-
0.48 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.19 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Boys 
-
-
0.43 
0.22 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Pubertal 
Girls 
-
-
0.34 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0.17 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Boys 
-
-
0.37 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Prepubertal 
Girls 
-
-
0.40 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Boys 
-
-
0.38 
0.15 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Body Mass Index </p>

<p>Postpubertal 
Girls 
-
0.75 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.52 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.31 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Boys 
-
0.57 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.61 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.27 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Pubertal 
Girls 
-
0.70 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.27 
0.18 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Boys 
-
0.75 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.58 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.24 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Prepubertal 
Girls 
-
0.87 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.09 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Boys 
-
0.78 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.41 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.12 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Parametr </p>

<p>Body Mass Index 
Weight-for-Height </p>

<p>MUAC 
TST </p>

<p>Mid-Upper Arm Circumference-for-Age </p>

<p>Postpubertal 
Girls 
-
-
-</p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>* excellent concordance,  † moderate concordance,  ‡ poor concordance ; MUAC: Mid-upper arm circumference-for </p>

<p>age </p>

<p>Table 5: 
Degree of agreement between four 
body composition indices for detecting </p>

<p>obesity by sex and puberty stage </p>

<p>Boys 
-
-
-</p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Pubertal 
Girls 
-
-
-</p>

<p>0.33 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Boys 
-
-
-</p>

<p>0.61 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Prepubertal 
Girls 
-
-
-</p>

<p>0.48 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Boys 
-
-
-</p>

<p>0.60 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Weight-for-Height </p>

<p>Postpubertal 
Girls 
-
-</p>

<p>0.54 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.58 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Boys 
-
-</p>

<p>0.41 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Pubertal 
Girls 
-
-</p>

<p>0.67 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.27 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Boys 
-
-</p>

<p>0.68 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.55 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Prepubertal 
Girls 
-
-</p>

<p>0.66 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.47 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Boys 
-</p>

<p>0.58 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.44 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Body Mass Index </p>

<p>Postpubertal 
Girls 
-
0.82 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.56 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.67 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Boys 
-
0.78 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Pubertal 
Girls 
-
0.84 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.56 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.21 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Boys 
-
0.70 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.58 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.64 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Prepubertal 
Girls 
-
0.85 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.76 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.46 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Boys 
-
0.71 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.83 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.57 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Parametr </p>

<p>Body Mass Index 
Weight-for-Height </p>

<p>MUAC 
TST </p>

<p>Agreement Analysis among Measures of Thinness and Obesity Assessment </p>



<p>Published by: Tehran University of Medical Sciences (http://asjsm.tums.ac.ir) 
Asian J Sports Med; Vol 4 (No 4), Dec 2013 </p>

<p>levels was observed. In addition, the level of agreement 
between MUAC and WH was reasonably good. 
Finally, TST had moderate agreement with the other 
three measurements in almost all cases, but in the 
pubertal girls and the post-pubertal boys had poor 
agreement. 
Table 6 shows bivariate correlations between 
anthropometric measurements classified by sex and 
maturity level. Height is not as highly correlated with 
the other indices as weight. Its correlation coefficient 
declined with the increase of maturity stage and it 
reached its minimum value in the post-pubertal group. 
The correlation coefficient between weight and the 
other indices decreased with increase of maturity level 
and its correlation was weaker with TST as compared 
with the other measurements. The highest correlation 
between weight and BMI was observed in post-
pubertal stage (0.93 for both genders). In addition, the 
correlation of BMI with MUAC was greater than with 
TST. The correlation of TST also reduced when the 
stage of puberty increased with the smallest values in 
the post-pubertal boys. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Based on our findings, different anthropometric-based 
measurements provide different prevalence rates of </p>

<p>obesity and thinness which is in the same line with the 
earlier research </p>

<p>[12] </p>

<p>. However, generally the prevalence 
of obesity was higher than that of thinness in almost all 
sex and pubertal stage groups; this might be due to the 
socioeconomic improvement as well as modernization 
process which occurred in Iran in the past decades 
[25] . </p>

<p>Nevertheless, based on the BMI, MUAC, and WH the 
prevalence of thinness is higher than that of obesity 
among post-pubertal girls. One possible reason is that 
in this stage girls are more likely to perceive 
themselves as overweight than boys, so they are likely 
to be engaged in weight control practice and lose their 
weight </p>

<p>[29] </p>

<p>. 
In most of previous studies, comparison of various 
body composition indices was carried out using 
correlation analysis 
[4,14,30-35] which cannot describe the </p>

<p>nature and extent of misclassifications, and when the 
purpose is to discriminate obesity from non obesity it is 
inappropriate to make recommendations based on 
correlations alone 
[6,37] . To our knowledge, few studies </p>

<p>have been conducted to examine the concordance of 
different measures to identify underweight and obese 
children and adolescents </p>

<p>[10,12,14-15] </p>

<p>. 
We performed both correlation and agreement 
analysis among the three maturation levels to achieve a 
more comprehensive insight about the performance of 
anthropometric indicators which rarely has been done 
in previous studies. Our results indicate an excellent 
agreement between WH and BMI for detecting both 
thin and obese children and adolescents. This coincides </p>

<p>Table 6: Bivariate correlation of anthropometric measures by sex and pubertal stage </p>

<p>Weight 
Height 
Body mass index 
MUAC 
TST 
boys 
girls 
boys 
girls 
boys 
girls 
boys 
girls 
boys 
girls </p>

<p>Pre-
pubertal </p>

<p>Weight 
1 
1 
0.81 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.82 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.86 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.84 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.90 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.87 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.68 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.62 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Height 
-
-
1 
1 
0.42 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.39 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.59 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.58 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.37 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>BMI 
-
-
-
-
1 
1 
0.90 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.88 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.74 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.69 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>MUAC 
-
-
-
-
-
-
1 
1 
0.77 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.72 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>pubertal </p>

<p>Weight 
1 
1 
0.71 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.52 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.91 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.91 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.89 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.81 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.74 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.64 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Height 
-
-
1 
1 
0.35 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.47 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.24 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.26 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.18 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>BMI 
-
-
-
-
1 
1 
0.92 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.84 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.83 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.65 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>MUAC 
-
-
-
-
-
-
1 
1 
0.82 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.61 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Post-
pubertal </p>

<p>Weight 
1 
1 
0.53 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.37 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.93 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.93 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.68 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.85 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.60 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.69 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Height 
-
-
1 
1 
0.19 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.03 
0.27 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.12 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.07 
BMI 
-
-
-
-
1 
1 
0.68 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.87 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.64 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.72 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>MUAC 
-
-
-
-
-
-
1 
1 
0.43 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.77 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* Significant difference between boys and girls at 5% level; MUAC: Mid-upper arm circumference-for-age; TST: triceps skinfold thickness-for-age </p>

<p>Ayatollahi SMT, et al </p>



<p>Asian J Sports Med; Vol 4 (No 4), Dec 2013 
Published by: Tehran University of Medical Sciences (http://asjsm.tums.ac.ir) </p>

<p>with a number of the previous research, though they 
had focused on different age groups </p>

<p>[12,36] </p>

<p>. However, 
other studies have detected a weak agreement between 
BMI and WH, reporting that the two indices cannot be 
used interchangeably 
[38] . </p>

<p>Although an excellent agreement between WH and 
MUAC was demonstrated by Anderson </p>

<p>[14] </p>

<p>, our results 
revealed a weak to moderate agreement for 
distinguishing underweight and overweight in all sex 
and age groups. In addition, there was a moderate 
agreement between TST and BMI in all subgroups 
except in pubertal girls and post-pubertal boys; this is 
consistent with a previous study indicating moderate 
agreement between TST and BMI for detecting obesity 
in the age range of 12-18 years </p>

<p>[15, 39] </p>

<p>. 
As shown in our results, the BMI was highly 
correlated with weight and less correlated with height 
which is a good characteristic of weight/height indices 
and is in agreement with previous results 
[31] . In </p>

<p>addition, the correlation between BMI and height 
decreased when levels of maturity increased. The same 
results were obtained in previous studies showing that 
BMI is independent of height in adults, but not in 
children </p>

<p>[31] </p>

<p>. In addition, the correlation of BMI with 
MUAC was stronger than that of TST which is not in 
accordance with the earlier studies indicating that BMI 
and TST are strongly correlated. Although previous 
research had demonstrated that BMI correlated less 
strongly with TST at younger age 
[31] , the correlation of </p>

<p>these two indicators was stronger in pre-pubertal 
individuals than that in pubertal and post-pubertal ones. 
Our results revealed that different anthropometric-
based indicators behaved differently in different 
genders and pubertal stage groups, which confirm the 
results of the previous studies 
[3, 9, 11, 31, 33] . The methods </p>

<p>we assessed have their own advantages and drawbacks. 
For instance, BMI is accepted as a standard method to 
evaluate nutritional status of individuals in almost all 
age ranges 
[6, 10, 12, 30, 32-35] , although it cannot present an </p>

<p>accurate evaluation of body fat particularly in children 
and adolescents </p>

<p>[38, 40] </p>

<p>. WH is identified as an 
appropriate screening tool which has the main 
advantage of being usefulwhen the child's age is 
unknown or unreliable, as is often the case in 
developing countries 
[25] . A number of previous studies </p>

<p>showed that BMI and WH can be used interchangeably </p>

<p>and they have the same performance 
[9] . We concluded </p>

<p>similarlyin our study, but another research focusing on 
2-5 years old children demonstrated that they cannot 
produce the same results </p>

<p>[6] </p>

<p>. 
Against WH and BMI, most of the previous 
research recommended TST as a more accurate method 
to reflect body fatn in children and adolescents and 
better a alternative for BMI for monitoring obesity in 
children </p>

<p>[3, 40] </p>

<p>. However, it has been shown that BMI 
and TST can be used as interchangeable methods in 
epidemiologic applications 
[33] and in children aged 5-</p>

<p>18 years they performed equally well for classifying 
obese individuals </p>

<p>[11] </p>

<p>. Also both indicators are 
dependent on sex during adolescence 
[3] . Despite </p>

<p>logical appealing of TST to reflect body fat, it has 
some methodological problems 
[33] , has low reliability </p>

<p>for obese persons 
[33] , and it does not provide additional </p>

<p>information for individuals whose BMI is greater than 
the 95 
th percentile 
[12] . </p>

<p>Although MUAC is introduced as another low cost 
screening method either for underweight or overweight 
classification in preschool children and assessing 
obesity at the end of childhood which can be performed 
quickly and only requires basic literacy level to be 
carried out, it should be applied with high accuracy and 
caution during maturity 
[23] . Since MUAC as well as </p>

<p>TST have an association with sexual development and 
they change with the onset of puberty. A prior study 
recommended 
that 
MUAC 
for 
identifying 
underweightness should be applied only when weight 
and height are not available, as the prevalence of 
malnutrition based on this index was underestimated as 
compared with weight-for-height. However, another 
study made a conclusion that BMI, TST, and MUAC 
have reasonable success for detecting obesity among 
children and adolescents 
[6] . </p>

<p>One limitation of our study is that since it is not 
clear which of the four measurement methods 
compared is a gold standard, we do not know which 
one represents true prevalence. Previous research 
revealed high correlation between BMI and Body Fat 
Mass (BFM) as an accurate index for assessing body 
fat among Iranian college students 
[41] . However, </p>

<p>further research is needed on Iranian children and 
adolescents to determine the most reliable and valid 
index representing accurate assessment of thinness and </p>

<p>Agreement Analysis among Measures of Thinness and Obesity Assessment </p>



<p>Published by: Tehran University of Medical Sciences (http://asjsm.tums.ac.ir) 
Asian J Sports Med; Vol 4 (No 4), Dec 2013 </p>

<p>obesity. Another limitation is that, no accurate criteria 
were applied for classification of participants in 
different stages of puberty; hence we recommended 
using more reliable and accurate methods than just 
considering the age of children for determination of 
puberty stage in future studies. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Based on our findings, the prevalence of obesity is 
more pronounced than that of thinness in school 
children and adolescents in Shiraz (Southern Iran). 
Therefore, preventive measures for controlling obesity 
are a must for public health promotion among school 
children in Iran. Another important finding is that WH 
and BMI can be used interchangeably in different 
pubertal stages and for detecting both underweight and </p>

<p>overweightness. In addition, in pre-pubertal stage BMI 
and MUAC can be used instead of each other for 
classifying obesity. Overall, our results are consistent 
with the pioneer research suggest that caution should 
be taken for selecting an appropriate index to classify 
children and adolescents as obese or thin in different 
sex and age groups. In addition, a single index may not 
produce satisfactory results and use of multiple 
indicators may lead to more trustworthy conclusions. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by the grant numbers 86-3723 and 
88-5039 from Shiraz University of Medical Sciences 
Research Council. We would like to thank Dr N. Shokrpoor 
for editing this manuscript. </p>

<p>Conflict of interests: None </p>



<p>Ayatollahi SMT, et al </p>



<p>Asian J Sports Med; Vol 4 (No 4), Dec 2013 
Published by: Tehran University of Medical Sciences (http://asjsm.tums.ac.ir) </p>



</text></tei>