<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3611748" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVE: Fetuin-A is a protein secreted from the liver that inhibits arterial calcification deposition and can 
contribute to insulin resistance. Hyperthyroidism is also associated with insulin resistance. It is not known 
whether hyperthyroidism has an effect on fetuin-A levels. 
METHODS: We measured fetuin-A levels and homeostasis model of assessment-insulin resistance before 
hyperthyroidism treatment was initiated and after euthyroidism was achieved. A total of 42 patients diagnosed 
with hyperthyroidism were enrolled in this study. Fetuin-A, insulin, high-sensitivity C-reactive protein, fasting 
blood glucose, free T3 (fT3), free T4 (fT4), and thyrotropin were measured before and after euthyroidism was 
established. 
RESULTS: Basal fasting blood glucose, high-sensitivity C-reactive protein, insulin, c-peptide, homeostasis model 
of assessment-insulin resistance, fT3, fT4 and fetuin-A levels were significantly decreased after euthyroidism 
was achieved (Table 1). Basal fasting blood glucose (r:0.407, p:0.008), high-sensitivity C-reactive protein (r:0.523, 
p,0.0001), insulin (r:0.479, p:0.001), homeostasis model of assessment-insulin resistance (r:0.541, p,0.0001), fT3 
(r:0.492, p:0.001) and fT4 (r:0.473, p:0.002) were positively correlated with basal fetuin-A levels. Basal 
thyrotropin levels were significantly negatively correlated (r:-0.553, p,0.0001) with basal fetuin-A levels. 
CONCLUSION: Our findings suggest that hyperthyroidism influences fetuin-A levels. </p>

<p>Mannheim, Germany). Free T3, free T4, TSH and insulin 
levels were measured with a chemiluminescence immuno-
metric assay using a UniCell DXI 800 analyzer (Beckman 
Coulter Inc., Fullerton, CA, USA). Serum hsCRP levels were 
determined using an ELISA according to the manufacturer's 
instructions (DRG International, Inc., USA). The intra-and 
inter-assay coefficients of variation were below 10%. Serum 
fetuin-A levels were measured with a human fetuin-A 
ELISA kit (BioVendor Laboratory Medicine, Brno, Czech 
Republic). The analytical sensitivity of the human fetuin-A 
ELISA kit was 0.35 ng/mL. The intra-and inter-assay 
coefficients of variation were below 6.5%. The exclusion 
criteria were previously known diabetes mellitus, athero-
sclerotic vascular disease, infections, malignancy, amyloi-
dosis, autoimmune diseases, alcohol consumption or 
smoking history, congestive heart failure, and liver or renal 
dysfunction. HOMA-IR was calculated using the following 
formula: 
HOMA-IR = fasting glucose (mmol/L)6fasting insulin 
(mU/mL)/22.5. 
The distribution of continuous variables was determined 
by the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. A paired-sample t test 
was performed to analyze initial and final values with a </p>

<p>normal distribution. A Wilcoxon signed rank test was used 
to analyze data with a skewed distribution. Pearson's and 
Spearman's analyses were used to identify correlations 
between study parameters. For all statistics, a two-sided p-
value ,0.05 was considered statistically significant. All 
analyses were performed with <rs type="software">SPSS 15.0 for Windows</rs>. </p>

<p>&amp; RESULTS </p>

<p>Of the 42 hyperthyroid patients (48.5¡15.0 years old), 27 
patients were female, and 15 were male. Among the causes 
of hyperthyroidism, 30 patients had Graves' disease, 11 
patients had toxic adenoma, and 1 patient had two toxic 
nodules. Euthyroidism was achieved in 3.0¡0.7 
(mean¡SD) months. Basal fasting blood glucose, hsCRP, 
insulin, HOMA-IR, fT3, fT4, calcium and fetuin-A levels 
were significantly decreased after euthyroidism was 
achieved (Table 1) (Figure 1). Basal fasting blood glucose 
(r:0.407, p:0.008), hsCRP (r:0.523, p,0.0001), insulin (r:0.479, 
p:0.001), HOMA-IR (r:0.541, p,0.0001), fT3 (r:0.492, p:0.001) 
and fT4 (r:0.473, p:0.002) were positively correlated with 
basal fetuin-A levels (Figures 2, 3). Basal TSH levels were 
significantly negatively correlated (r:-0.553, p,0.0001) with 
basal fetuin-A levels. The basal body mass index (before: </p>

<p>Table 1 -Biochemical results before and after euthyroidism was achieved (mean¡SD). </p>

<p>Parameter (reference values) 
Hyperthyroid 
Euthyroid 
p-value </p>

<p>Fetuin-A (ng/mL) 
468.7¡143.5 
234.5¡103.8 
,0.0001 
FT3 (pg/mL) (2.5-3.9) 
8.6¡2.3 
2.7¡0.3 
,0.0001 
FT4 (ng/dL) (0.61-1.06) 
4.7¡1.6 
1.2¡0.4 
,0.0001 
TSH (mIU/mL) (0.41-4.25) 
0.006¡0.014 
0.986¡0.467 
,0.0001 
Fasting blood glucose (mg/dL) (70-
110) </p>

<p>113.1¡15.6 
94.8¡22.2 
,0.0001 </p>

<p>Insulin (mU/mL) (1.9-23) 
13.1¡2.5 
8.5¡2.1 
,0.0001 
HOMA-IR 
3.69¡1.07 
2.00¡0.67 
,0.0001 
hsCRP (mg/L) (0.068-8.2) 
6.27¡2.65 
1.92¡0.79 
,0.0001 
Calcium (mg/dL) (8.6-10.2) 
10.1¡0.4 
9.4¡0.3 
,0.0001 </p>

<p>Figure 1 -The comparison of fetuin-A (ng/mL) levels during hyperthyroidism and euthyroidism. </p>

<p>Hyperthyroidism and fetuin-A 
Pamuk BO et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2013;68(3):379-383 </p>



<p>Figure 2 -The correlation between free FT4 (reference range: 0.61-1.06 ng/dL) and fetuin-A (ng/mL) levels. </p>

<p>Figure 3 -The correlation between TSH (uIU/mL) and fetuin-A (ng/mL) levels. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2013;68(3):379-383 
Hyperthyroidism and fetuin-A 
Pamuk BO et al. </p>



<p>27.1¡3.2, after: 28.2¡3.7, p,0.0001) increased significantly 
after euthyroidism was achieved. </p>

<p>&amp; DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, we found that fetuin-A levels decreased 
significantly with hyperthyroidism treatment. To our 
knowledge, this is the first study investigating the effect of 
hyperthyroidism on fetuin-A levels. In this study, hsCRP 
levels also decreased significantly with the normalization of 
thyroid hormones. Furthermore, fetuin-A levels were 
positively correlated with thyroid hormone, HOMA-IR 
and hsCRP levels. 
Fetuin-A is a liver-derived blood protein that acts as a 
potent inhibitor of ectopic mineralization. Monomeric 
fetuin-A protein binds to small clusters of calcium and 
phosphate. Therefore, fetuin-A is a mineral carrier protein 
and a systemic inhibitor of pathological mineralization that 
complements local inhibitors that act in a cell-restricted or 
tissue-restricted fashion (13). Fetuin-A deficiency is asso-
ciated with soft tissue calcification in mice and humans. 
Fetuin-A is a prominent serum glycoprotein as well as a 
major noncollagenous component of mineralized bone in 
mammals. In vitro, fetuin-A can inhibit or stimulate 
osteogenesis, depending on its concentrations (17). Rasul 
et al. previously found a positive correlation between fetuin-
A and bone alkaline phosphatase in type 2 diabetic males. In 
females, fetuin-A was significantly negatively associated 
with C-telopeptide levels (18). However, the researchers did 
not measure thyroid hormones in that study. Thyroid 
hormones increase bone turnover markers, and hyperthyr-
oidism increases bone turnover. Fetuin-A may be increased 
in hyperthyroidism through a mechanism related to bone 
metabolism. Fetuin-A has been studied in several metabolic 
derangements; however, its role has not been studied in 
hyperthyroidism. Therefore, we could not compare our 
results with previous studies. 
Sato et al. examined the effects of T3 on the expression of 
calcification-associated genes and found that a physiological 
concentration of T3 increased the mRNA level of matrix G1a 
protein (MGP), which is a potent inhibitor of vascular 
calcification in vivo (19). They also showed that hyperthyr-
oidism upregulated MGP mRNA 4.5 fold and reduced the 
calcium content of rat aortic smooth tissue by 11%. Fetuin-A 
also inhibits tissue calcification in a similar fashion; there-
fore, we hypothesize that there may be an interaction 
between fetuin-A synthesis and thyroid hormones because 
we found a positive correlation between these two 
parameters. To our knowledge, no experimental study in 
the literature has investigated the effect of thyroid hormones 
on the mRNA levels of fetuin-A. Hypercalcemia is a well-
known complication of hyperthyroidism, and stimulating 
fetuin-A synthesis may be an adaptation to prevent ectopic 
tissue calcification in hyperthyroidism. In a previous study 
of 32 thyrotoxic teenage girls, 21 (66%) showed some degree 
of calcification compared with 73 of 600 (12%) in the control 
group (22). Yamashita et al. previously observed that 
fibroblast growth factor (FGF)-23 levels (which are also 
related to soft tissue calcification) decreased significantly 
with hyperthyroidism treatment (23). However, they did 
not measure fetuin-A levels, and we therefore cannot 
compare our results with that study. 
Fetuin-A levels have been found to be higher in diabetes 
and inflammatory diseases, such as ankylosing spondylitis </p>

<p>(13). In addition to its functions as an inhibitor of tissue 
calcification, fetuin-A is an endogenous inhibitor of the 
insulin receptor tyrosine kinase (14), and fetuin-A-knockout 
mice exhibit increased insulin sensitivity (15). Recent 
studies have associated high levels of fetuin-A with an 
increased risk of type 2 diabetes incidence (16), insulin 
resistance, hepatosteatosis (8) and metabolic syndrome (7). 
Li et al. previously showed that fetuin-A plays a protective 
role in systemic inflammation by activating high-mobility 
group box 1 (HMGB1) synthesis (20). Hyperthyroidism may 
also initiate an inflammatory cascade and eventually 
stimulate fetuin-A synthesis. Insulin resistance in 
hyperthyroidism may also be related to the increased levels 
of fetuin-A. Yavuz et al. previously showed that levothyr-
oxine treatment of goiter patients significantly increased 
hsCRP at 16 weeks (21). In accordance with that study, 
we found a significant decrease in hsCRP levels with 
hyperthyroidism treatment. Fetuin-A also has strong anti-
inflammatory properties (13). In our study, fetuin-A levels 
decreased with hsCRP levels, which may also be related to 
the inflammation-fetuin-A interaction. In our study, insulin 
levels were significantly positively correlated with fetuin-A 
levels; furthermore, insulin levels and fetuin-A levels were 
decreased after euthyroidism was achieved. The relation-
ship between fetuin-A and insulin has been studied in both 
clinical and experimental studies. Fetuin-A binds to insulin 
receptors in adipose and muscular tissue and inhibits 
insulin receptor tyrosine kinase activity as well as insulin 
receptor autophosphorylation in vivo and in vitro (13). 
Fetuin-A has also been suggested to potentially cause 
insulin resistance and metabolic syndrome (13). 
In the present study, fasting glucose levels decreased 
significantly with hyperthyroidism treatment. Fasting glu-
cose levels were significantly positively correlated with 
fetuin-A levels. It was previously shown that higher fetuin-
A concentrations were associated with type 2 diabetes and 
insulin resistance (24). In another study, fetuin-A levels 
were significantly correlated with fasting plasma glucose 
and CRP (25). The present study is in accordance with these 
findings, as fetuin-A levels decreased significantly as the 
fasting glucose levels and insulin resistance decreased after 
hyperthyroidism treatment. Atherosclerosis has been shown 
to be enhanced in hypothyroidism (26). The anti-atherogenic 
effects of thyroid hormones may also be related to fetuin-A. 
Further clinical and experimental studies investigating the 
effect of hypothyroidism on fetuin-A levels may reveal its 
influence on atherosclerosis in hypothyroidism. 
In conclusion, this study showed that fetuin-A levels 
declined significantly after hyperthyroidism treatment. 
Fetuin-A levels were also correlated with thyroid hormones 
and insulin resistance. Further experimental studies are 
needed to elucidate the molecular link between the 
hormones regulating tissue calcification and thyroid hor-
mones. </p>

<p>&amp; AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS </p>

<p>Pamuk BO, Ertugrul DT conceived and designed the study, analyzed and 
interpreted the data, drafted the article, and critically revised the article for 
important intellectual content. Yılmaz H, Topcuoglu T, Bilgir O, Calan O, 
Pamuk G organized data in the tables, assisted the patients during the 
study, helped in the literature revision, drafted the manuscript, and 
critically revised the manuscript regarding important intellectual content. </p>

<p>Hyperthyroidism and fetuin-A 
Pamuk BO et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2013;68(3):379-383 </p>





<p>CLINICS 2013;68(3):379-383 
Hyperthyroidism and fetuin-A 
Pamuk BO et al. </p>



</text></tei>