<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3430911" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objectives: This study was designed to investigate whether long-term, low-level exposure to monocyclic aromatic hydrocarbons 
(MAHs) induced insulin resistance. 
Methods: The subjects were 110 male workers who were occupationally exposed to styrene, toluene, and xylene. One hundred 
and ten age-matched male workers who had never been occupationally exposed to organic solvents were selected as a control 
group. Cytokines, which have played a key role in the pathogenesis of insulin resistance, and oxidative stress indices were mea-
sured. Assessment of exposure to MAHs was performed by measuring their ambient levels and their urinary metabolites in ex-
posed workers, and the resulting parameters between the exposed group and non-exposed control groups were compared. 
Results: There was no significant difference in general characteristics and anthropometric parameters between the two groups; 
however, total cholesterol, fasting glucose, fasting insulin, and homeostasis model assessment of insulin resistance levels were 
significantly higher in the exposed group. Phenylglyoxylic acid levels showed significant association with tumor necrosis factor-α, 
total oxidative status, and oxidative stress index via multiple linear regression analysis. Further, there was a negative correlation 
between methylhippuric acid levels and total anti-oxidative capacity, and there was a significant relationship between MAHs ex-
posure and fasting glucose levels, as found by multiple logistic regression analysis (odds ratio = 3.95, 95% confidence interval = 
1.074-14.530). 
Conclusion: This study indicated that MAHs increase fasting glucose level and insulin resistance. Furthermore, these results sug-
gested that absorbing the organic solvent itself and active metabolic intermediates can increase oxidative stress and cytokine 
levels, resulting in the changes in glucose metabolism and the induction of insulin resistance. </p>

<p>Organic solvents are widely used at home as well as in work-</p>

<p>places, and their health hazards have been known for a long 
time. Diverse hazardous chemicals, including organic solvents 
that humans are occupationally or non-occupationally exposed 
to, have their own physicochemical characteristics with various 
absorption routes and target organs. They have been demon-
strated to cause toxicity in various organs [1] including the liver 
[2,3], hematopoietic organs [4], nervous system [5], immuno-
endocrinological system [6], kidney, cardiovascular system, 
skin, mucosa, and reproductive organs, and have been reported 
to decrease or damage the body homeostasis maintenance </p>

<p>Copyright © 2011 by Safety and Health at Work (SH@W) </p>

<p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), which permits unrestricted 
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Won YL et al. </p>

<p>Safety and Health at Work | Vol. 2, No. 4, Dec. 30, 2011 </p>

<p>366 </p>

<p>www.e-shaw.org </p>

<p>function [7]. 
Some studies have reported that exposure to organic 
solvents may be related to insulin resistance (IR) or associated 
metabolic syndrome (MetS). Kaukiainen et al. [8] reported that 
workers exposed to organic solvent mixtures had higher fasting 
glucose levels, and Hong et al. [9] mentioned that environmen-
tal contaminants including organic solvents may result in IR. 
Although the relationship between organic solvent exposure 
and IR has not been directly described, it has been reported 
that exposure to organic solvents increased cytokines includ-
ing tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-α) which are involved in 
inflammatory responses [6,10] and increased oxidative stress 
while reducing the activities of antioxidant enzymes [11,12]. It 
has also been reported that increased cytokines such as TNF-α, 
interleukin-6 (IL-6), and interleukin-1 beta (IL-1β) play a criti-
cal role in the development of IR as well as being involved in 
immunological reactions and signal transductions [13,14]; and 
that increased reactive oxygen species (ROS) are involved in 
blood glucose elevation and development of IR through activat-
ing c-Jun NH 2 -terminal kinase (JNK) and Iκβ kinase B (IKKβ), 
which are stress kinases, leading to accelerated phosphoryla-
tion of insulin receptor substrate-1 (IRS-1) serine [15,16]. How-
ever, studies on the relationship between exposure to low-level 
monocyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (MAHs) and IR and the 
pathogenesis of IR have been exceedingly insufficient in both 
Korea and other countries and thus, such studies are increas-
ingly needed. 
In this study, IL-1β, IL-6, and TNF-α, which are cyto-
kines playing key roles in the pathogenesis of IR, and oxida-
tive stress indices were measured in the subjects. Exposure to 
styrene, toluene, and xylene, which were representative MAHs, 
was assessed through measuring ambient levels and urinary 
metabolites in exposed workers. Finally, these parameters were 
compared between the exposed group and non-exposed control 
group to identify the effects of chronic exposure to low-level 
MAHs and IR in Korean workers. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>This paper was a cross-sectional study aimed at inspecting the 
effect of low-level organic solvent exposure on insulin resis-
tance. The subjects in the exposed group were workers who 
had been exposed to MAHs in paint manufacturing factories. 
Female subjects were excluded from this study as the number 
of female workers was not large enough to use in statistical 
calculations. The subjects in the control group were randomly 
selected among workers with a similar range in age as the 
subjects in the exposed group, in order to control the effects of </p>

<p>aging. The level of organic solvent in the air and urinary me-
tabolites in urine were set as exposure variables, and cytokines 
and oxidative stress levels were compared between the exposed 
and control groups. This study was reviewed and approved by 
the Institutional Review Board of the Occupational Safety and 
Health Research Institute, and informed consent was obtained 
from all the workers who volunteered to participate in the 
study. </p>

<p>Study subjects </p>

<p>One hundred and ten male workers (mean age of 38.9) who 
were occupationally exposed to mixed organic solvents includ-
ing styrene, toluene, and xylene in three paint manufacturing 
factories were selected as test subjects in the exposed group. 
The control group was composed of 110 age-matched (mean 
age of 38.6) male manufacturing workers and office workers at 
the same factories who had never been occupationally exposed 
to organic solvents. Workers with clinically diagnosed diabetes, 
those taking medication for a medical condition, and those 
with acute infections and/or diseases that may have suppressed 
their immune systems were excluded from the study. </p>

<p>Questionnaire survey </p>

<p>Self-administered questionnaires were distributed and in-person 
interviews were conducted to obtain information on the sub-
jects' general characteristics including age, smoking, drinking, 
physical activity, job characteristics including daily working 
hours and working duration, and eating habits. </p>

<p>Measuring ambient organic solvent levels and 
urinary metabolites </p>

<p>Ambient monitoring and biological monitoring was carried out 
for all the subjects. Ambient organic solvent levels were ana-
lyzed according to 'Method 1501 Aromatic Hydrocarbons' in 
National Institute of Occupational Safety and Health [17]. Or-
ganic solvents in the air at the workplace were sampled using 
low-flow active samplers (Low Flow Sampler 113 D, Gilian, 
USA) and analyzed using gas chromatography (CP-3800 GC/ 
FID, Varian Ltd., USA). The urine used to measure the levels 
of urinary metabolites was obtained at around 18:00-19:00 
after most workers had completed work. Urinary excretion of 
hippuric acid (HA) and methyl hippuric acid (mHA), which 
are metabolites of toluene and xylene, respectively, were ana-
lyzed using gas chromatography (CP-3800 GC/FID, Varian 
Ltd., USA), and the results were adjusted to urinary creatinine 
[18]. Phenylglyoxylic acid (PGA) and mandelic acid (MA), 
metabolites of styrene, were analyzed using gas chromatogra-
phy according to the method by Ogata and Taguchi [19], and </p>

<p>Exposure of MAHs and Insulin Resistance </p>

<p>Saf Health Work 2011;2:365-74 </p>



<p>www.e-shaw.org </p>

<p>the results were adjusted to urinary creatinine. </p>

<p>Blood collection and analysis </p>

<p>Venous blood was collected between 07:00 and 09:00 after the 
subjects had fasted for more than 10-hours, and centrifuged for 
15 minutes at 2,500 rpm within 30 minutes after sampling to 
separate plasma and serum. Separated plasma and serum were 
divided into 100 μL vials and frozen, and transported to the 
laboratory for analysis where biochemical tests were performed 
using a biochemistry analyzer (COBAS Integra 400, Roche 
Diagnostics Ltd., Switzerland). Fasting insulin levels were ana-
lyzed using a luminescence immunoassay system (ACCESS, 
Sanofi Diagnostics Pasteur, Inc., Minnesota, USA). IL-1β, IL-6 
and TNF-α were analyzed using a sandwich ELISA kit (R&amp;D 
systems, Minnesota, USA) by the method suggested by the 
manufacturer. All results are presented as mean values of dupli-
cate measurements. </p>

<p>Evaluation of oxidative stress </p>

<p>Total oxidative status (TOS) and total anti-oxidative capacity 
(TAC) were measured using a colorimetric test kit (Immunodi-
agnostik AG, Bensheim, Germany). For TOS, total lipid per-
oxides, which are directly correlated with oxygen radicals, were 
measured in the plasma and adjusted to reference material to 
calculate the concentration as a H 2 O 2 -equivalent (μmol/L). For 
TAC, H 2 O 2 remaining in the plasma after reaction with antioxi-
dants for a specific time was measured to identify the reactivity 
of antioxidants (presented as H 2 O 2 -equivalent [μmol/L]). The 
oxidative stress index (OSI) which was the TOS-to-TAC ratio 
was calculated using the equation, OSI (arbitrary unit) = TOS 
(μmol H 2 O 2 equivalent/L) / TAC (μmol H 2 O 2 equivalent/L). </p>

<p>Evaluation of insulin resistance </p>

<p>Insulin resistance was evaluated using a homeostasis model 
assessment of insulin resistance (HOMA-IR). The HOMA-IR 
was calculated using the equation, [HOMA-IR = fasting insu-
lin (μU/mL) × fasting glucose (mg/dL) / 405]. </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>The data was analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">12.0.1</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). T-tests were performed to 
compare the exposed and control groups, and multiple linear 
regression analysis and multiple logistic regression analysis was 
used to analyze the relationship between parameters. In the 
multiple logistic regression analysis, subjects with results in the 
upper 25% of HOMA-IR were considered part of the group 
having insulin resistance, and the lower 75% was considered 
part of normal group. Subjects with fasting plasma glucose lev-</p>

<p>els greater than or equal to 100 mg/dL were considered part of 
the high-glucose group and those with lower levels were consid-
ered part of the normal group [20]. All results were presented 
as mean ± standard deviation, and p-values less than 0.05 were 
considered significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Characteristics of the study subjects </p>

<p>The mean age of workers was 38.6 ± 8.5 and 38.9 ± 8.3 years 
in the control and exposed group, respectively. There were no 
significant differences in age, smoking and drinking rate, eating 
habits, and exercise habits between the two groups. TV viewing 
hours (1.4 ± 1.0 vs. 1.7 ± 0.9 hours per day) and department 
working duration (44.2 ± 56.9 vs. 114.8 ± 90.6 months) were 
significantly longer in the exposed group (p &lt; 0.05). The sub-
jects in the exposed group worked on average, 9.1 ± 1.4 hours, 
during which they were exposed to organic solvents while 
subjects in the control group worked for longer hours at an 
average of 9.9 ± 1.6 hours (p &lt; 0.001). Additionally, there was 
no significant difference with respect to any anthropometric 
parameters between the control and exposed groups (Table 1). </p>

<p>Level of exposure to MAHs and its correlation with 
metabolites in the exposed group </p>

<p>Workers in the exposed group were exposed to average sty-
rene levels of 0.10 ppm (range, 0.00-5.90) with mean levels of 
urinary PGA, a metabolite of styrene, of 0.02 g/g creatinine 
(range, 0.01-0.04). The correlation coefficient (r) between ambi-
ent styrene and urinary PGA level was 0.625 (p &lt; 0.05). Work-
ers in the exposed group were exposed to average toluene levels 
of 0.14 ppm (range, 0.00-2.02) while HA, a urinary metabolite 
of toluene, was 0.30 g/g creatinine (range, 0.01-1.34). There 
was no significant correlation between ambient toluene and 
urinary HA levels. Workers in the exposed group were exposed 
to average xylene levels of 8.83 ppm (range, 0.00-32.65) while 
mHA, a urinary metabolite of xylene, was 0.09 g/g creatinine 
(range, 0.00-0.48). The correlation coefficient between ambient 
xylene and urinary mHA level was 0.316 (p &lt; 0.01). Ambient 
exposure levels of styrene, toluene, and xylene and concentra-
tions of urinary excretion of their metabolites MA, PGA, HA, 
and mHA were all below the threshold limit value-time weight-
ed average (TLV-TWA) and biological exposure index (BEI) of 
Korea, respectively (Table 2). </p>

<p>Serum clinical parameters of the study subjects </p>

<p>Total cholesterol, fasting glucose, fasting insulin, and HOMA-
IR levels were statistically significantly higher in the exposed </p>

<p>Won YL et al. </p>

<p>Safety and Health at Work | Vol. 2, No. 4, Dec. 30, 2011 </p>



<p>www.e-shaw.org </p>

<p>group (p &lt; 0.05), while HDL-cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol, 
triglyceride were not significantly different between groups. 
Further, TNF-α levels in the exposed group were significantly 
higher compared to levels in the control group (4.785 ± 1.975 
pg/mL vs. 2.380 ± 1.635 pg/mL, p &lt; 0.001). IL-1β and IL-6 
levels were higher in the exposed group, although the difference 
compared to those in the control group was not statistically 
significant. TOS, TAC and OSI were measured to examine the 
changes in oxidative stress by exposure to MAHs. TAC, which 
indicates anti-oxidative capacity, was significantly lower in the 
exposed group compared to levels in control group, while TOS 
and OSI were not statistically different between groups (Table 
3). </p>

<p>Relationship between MAHs metabolites and 
cytokines or oxidative stress indices </p>

<p>The results from the multiple linear regression analysis for 
the 110 exposed workers have been provided in Table 4. Only 
the test items that had statistical significance have been listed. 
TNF-α was significantly affected by PGA (p &lt; 0.05), but other 
cytokines such as IL-6 and IL-1α were not significantly affected 
by independent variables (such as MA, PGA, HA and mHA). 
TOS (p &lt; 0.01) and OSI (p &lt; 0.01) were significantly affected 
by PGA positively, and TAC was negatively affected by mHA (p 
&lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Table 1. General and job characteristics of study subjects </p>

<p>Variables 
Control (n = 110) 
Mean ± SD </p>

<p>Exposed (n = 110) 
Mean ± SD 
p-value </p>

<p>Age (years) 
38.6 ± 8.5 
38.9 ± 8.3 
NS </p>

<p>TV viewing (hours/day) 
1.4 ± 1.0 
1.7 ± 0.9 
0.016 </p>

<p>Sleeping (hours/day) 
6.5 ± 1.0 
6.6 ± 0.8 
NS </p>

<p>Smokers, n (%) 
50 (45.5) 
66 (60.0) 
NS </p>

<p>Number of cigarettes/day 
8.9 ± 8.6 
10.6 ± 8.1 
NS </p>

<p>Alcohol drinking, n (%) 
93 (84.5) 
92 (83.6) 
NS </p>

<p>Alcohol consumption/week (g) 
75.3 ± 60.2 
83.5 ± 52.9 
NS </p>

<p>Regular exercise, n (%) 
64 (58) 
51 (56) 
NS </p>

<p>Eating habit 
20.59 ± 2.91 
20.78 ± 2.77 
NS </p>

<p>Workplace working duration (months) 
104.8 ± 87.1 
124.9 ± 91.5 
NS </p>

<p>Department working duration (months) 
44.2 ± 56.9 
114.8 ± 90.6 
0.000 </p>

<p>Working hours/day 
9.9 ± 1.6 
9.1 ± 1.4 
0.001 </p>

<p>Waist circumference (cm) 
83.04 ± 7.65 
84.35 ± 8.06 
NS </p>

<p>Hip circumference (cm) 
95.67 ± 5.03 
95.14 ± 5.46 
NS </p>

<p>Waist circumference/hip circumference ratio 
0.86 ± 0.08 
0.87 ± 0.07 
NS </p>

<p>Boby mass index (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
23.32 ± 2.63 
23.94 ± 2.75 
NS </p>

<p>Systolic blood pressure (mmHg) 
127.07 ± 12.60 
129.76 ± 15.65 
NS </p>

<p>Diastolic blood pressure (mmHg) 
75.78 ± 8.69 
76.17 ± 10.37 
NS </p>

<p>Weight (kg) 
69.24 ± 8.91 
70.39 ± 9.83 
NS </p>

<p>Subcutaneous fat thickness (cm) 
1.53 ± 0.50 
1.61 ± 0.62 
NS </p>

<p>Visceral fat thickness (cm) 
4.33 ± 1.35 
4.25 ± 1.35 
NS </p>

<p>Body fat percentage (%) 
20.04 ± 5.25 
20.94 ± 5.43 
NS </p>

<p>SD: standard deviation, NS: non significant. </p>

<p>Exposure of MAHs and Insulin Resistance </p>

<p>Saf Health Work 2011;2:365-74 </p>



<p>www.e-shaw.org </p>

<p>Relationship between exposure to MAHs and insulin 
resistance </p>

<p>After adjusting for the workers' age, smoking habits, drink-
ing habits, waist and hip circumference, weight, and regular 
exercise habits, a multiple logistic regression analysis was 
performed (with exposure levels of MAHs as the independent 
variable, and fasting glucose and HOMA-IR levels as the de-
pendent variable) in order to identify the relationship between 
exposure to MAHs and IR. The odds ratio (OR) between 
exposure levels of MAHs and fasting glucose was 3.951 (95% 
cofidence interval [CI] = 1.074-14.530, p = 0.039), indicating 
a significant relationship. The OR between exposure levels of 
MAHs and HOMA-IR was 1.713 (95% CI = 0.846-3.469, p = 
0.135), which did not indicate a significant relationship (Table 
5). Also, after adjusting for age, increase in working duration to 
MAHs was related to increased blood glucose levels (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>There have been many reports on the correlation between IR 
and lifestyle, but there are only a few studies regarding expo-
sure to hazardous chemicals, despite the fact that many have 
suggested the relationship between exposure to organic sol-
vents and IR. Therefore, we carried out this study to analyze 
the characteristics of working environments in manufacturing 
factories in Korea and analyzed their relationship with IR to </p>

<p>Table 2. Concentration of ambient MAHs and their urinary 
metabolites in 110 exposed workers </p>

<p>MAHs 
Mean (range) </p>

<p>Styrene </p>

<p>Ambient (ppm) 
0.10 (0.00-5.90) </p>

<p>Metabolites (g/g Cr) </p>

<p>Mandelic acid 
0.02 (0.00-0.14) </p>

<p>Phenylglyoxylic acid 
0.02 (0.01-0.04) </p>

<p>Toluene </p>

<p>Ambient (ppm) 
0.14 (0.00-2.02) </p>

<p>Metabolites (g/g Cr) </p>

<p>Hippuric acid 
0.30 (0.01-1.34) </p>

<p>Xylene </p>

<p>Ambient (ppm) 
8.83 (0.00-32.65) </p>

<p>Metabolites (g/g Cr) </p>

<p>Methylhippuric acid 
0.09 (0.00-0.48) </p>

<p>Exposure Coefficient of Mixture (&lt;1) 
0.07 (0.01-0.80) </p>

<p>Threshold limit value -time weighted average: Styrene: 20 ppm, 
Toluene: 50 ppm, Xylene: 100 ppm. 
Biological exposure index: Mandelic acid: 0.8 g/g creatinine, Phenyl-
glyoxylic acid: 0.24 g/g creatinine, Hippuric acid: 2.5 g/g creatinine, 
Methylhippuric acid: 1.5 g/g creatinine. 
MAHs: monocyclic aromatic hydrocarbons. </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparison of serum clinical parameters between control and exposed workers </p>

<p>Variables 
Control (n = 110) 
Mean ± SD </p>

<p>Exposed (n = 110) 
Mean ± SD 
p-value </p>

<p>Total cholesterol (mg/dL) 
184.19 ± 31.27 
194.29 ± 33.80 
0.024 </p>

<p>HDL-cholesterol (mg/dL) 
48.10 ± 12.56 
50.28 ± 10.35 
NS </p>

<p>LDL-cholesterol (mg/dL) 
112.47 ± 29.13 
112.22 ± 31.99 
NS </p>

<p>Triglyceride (mg/dL) 
164.68 ± 113.86 
189.88 ± 159.36 
NS </p>

<p>Fasting glucose (mg/dL) 
89.03 ± 11.81 
93.17 ± 15.36 
0.027 </p>

<p>Fasting insulin (μIU/mL) 
6.83 ± 5.49 
8.81 ± 6.89 
0.019 </p>

<p>HOMA-IR 
1.55 ± 1.36 
2.12 ± 1.89 
0.010 </p>

<p>IL-1β (pg/mL) 
0.254 ± 0.234 
0.333 ± 0.441 
NS </p>

<p>IL-6 (pg/mL) 
1.689 ± 1.006 
1.916 ± 1.908 
NS </p>

<p>TNF-α (pg/mL) 
2.380 ± 1.635 
4.785 ± 1.975 
0.001 </p>

<p>TOS (μmol H 2 O 2 equivalent/L) 
138.1 ± 63.4 
135.8 ± 71.7 
NS </p>

<p>TAC (μmol H 2 O 2 equivalent/L) 
316.1 ± 34.0 
297.7 ± 45.6 
0.001 </p>

<p>OSI 
0.444 ± 0.2 
0.482 ± 0.3 
NS </p>

<p>SD: standard deviation, NS: Non-significant, HOMA-IR: homeostasis model assessment of insulin resistance, IL-1β: interleukin-1 beta, IL-6: inter-
leukin-6, TNF-α: tumor necrosis factor-alpha, TOS: total oxidative status, TAC: total anti-oxidative capacity, OSI: oxidative stress index. </p>

<p>Won YL et al. </p>

<p>Safety and Health at Work | Vol. 2, No. 4, Dec. 30, 2011 </p>



<p>www.e-shaw.org </p>

<p>compare the results with those from other countries and clearly 
identify the relationship. 
We studied styrene, toluene, and xylene, which are MAHs 
widely used in industries in paint, plastic and rubber manu-
facturing as thinner, and attempted to understand the effect of 
exposure to these chemicals on the development of IR with a 
specific focus on cytokines and oxidative stress. With regard to 
lifestyle, Pardee et al. [21] reported that television viewing time 
was associated with hypertension and obesity, and that TV 
viewing time was reported to be positively correlated with BMI 
[22]. Mummery et al. [23] also reported that time spent sitting 
was positively correlated with BMI. In addition, De León et 
al. [24] reported that there were direct associations between a 
sedentary lifestyle and triglyceride, IR, and MetS. Thus, these </p>

<p>Table 4. Results of a multiple linear regression model for the association among MAHs metabolites, cytokines, and oxidative stress 
indices </p>

<p>Dependent 
variable 
TNF-α 
IL-6 
IL-1β </p>

<p>Independent 
variables 
B 
SE 
Beta 
t 
B 
SE 
Beta 
t 
B 
SE 
Beta 
t </p>

<p>(Constant) 
2.390 
0.888 
2.691* 
1.639 
0.893 
1.836 
0.175 0.078 
2.252 </p>

<p>MA 
69.708 
34.188 
0.382 2.039 
11.181 
15.789 
0.142 
0.708 
0.389 1.358 0.058 0.286 </p>

<p>PGA 
119.897 
43.492 
0.560 2.757* 
-14.141 
35.914 -0.085 
-0.394 
-0.138 2.935 -0.010 -0.047 </p>

<p>HA 
-1.846 
1.231 -0.256 -1.499 
-0.520 
1.610 -0.067 
-0.323 
0.226 0.151 0.323 1.499 </p>

<p>mHA 
-4.217 
2.336 -0.324 -1.805 
3.136 
3.421 
0.206 
-0.917 
-0.053 0.311 -0.040 -0.170 </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.614 
0.048 
0.102 </p>

<p>F 
5.559 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.305 
0.657 </p>

<p>Dependent 
variable 
TOS 
TAC 
OSI </p>

<p>Independent 
variables 
B 
SE 
Beta 
t 
B 
SE 
Beta 
t 
B 
SE 
Beta 
t </p>

<p>(Constant) 
76.432 
32.719 
2.336* 330.428 
19.453 
16.986 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0.186 0.123 
1.509 </p>

<p>MA 
-99.662 
596.064 -0.026 -0.167 
-111.632 354.395 -0.052 
-0.315 
-0.223 2.244 -0.015 -0.099 </p>

<p>PGA 
4,709.418 1,327.647 0.598 3.547 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>-584.676 
79.364 -0.131 
-0.741 
17.304 4.998 0.557 3.462 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>HA 
28.995 
61.090 0.078 0.475 
31.496 
36.322 
0.149 
0.867 
0.106 0.230 0.072 0.461 </p>

<p>mHA 
-1.654 
128.270 -0.002 -0.013 
-210.794 
76.264 -0.514 
-2.764* 
0.477 0.483 0.167 0.989 </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.369 
0.303 
0.426 </p>

<p>F 
3.803* 
2.830* 
4.814 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>MA: mandelic acid, PGA: phenylglyoxylic acid, HA: hippuric acid, mHA: methylhippuric acid, TNF-α: tumor necrosis factor-alpha, IL-6: interleu-
kin-6, IL-1β: interleukin-1 beta, TOS: total oxidative status, TAC: total anti-oxidative capacity, OSI: oxidative stress index. 
*p &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>p &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>p &lt; 0.001. </p>

<p>Table 5. Multiple logistic regression analysis for fasting glu-
cose and HOMA-IR </p>

<p>Variables 
β 
SE 
OR (95% CI) 
p-value </p>

<p>Fasting glucose 1.374 0.664 3.951 (1.074-14.530) 0.039 </p>

<p>HOMA-IR 
0.538 0.360 1.713 (0.846-3.469) 
0.135 </p>

<p>Independent variable: exposure levels of monocyclic aromatic hy-
drocarbons. 
Adjustment to age, smoking, drinking habit, waist and hip circum-
ference, weight and regular exercise. 
SE: standard error, OR: odds ratio, CI: confidence interval, HOMA-IR: 
homeostasis model assessment of insulin resistance. </p>

<p>Exposure of MAHs and Insulin Resistance </p>

<p>Saf Health Work 2011;2:365-74 </p>



<p>www.e-shaw.org </p>

<p>results suggest that induction of hypertension, obesity, IR, and 
MetS is associated with sedentary behaviors. However, in this 
study, a comparison of anthropometric results between the 
control and exposed groups showed no statistically significant 
difference. This result may be due to the lack of a significant 
difference in general characteristics that may have affected the 
anthropometric results between the groups. Therefore, we can 
induce that the effects of lifestyle and so on are ignorable in the 
various results of the analysis and in the the interpretation of 
the analysis in these two groups. 
Mokuda et al. [25] reported that liver damage induced 
by carbon tetrachloride increased glucose and insulin levels 
in blood, and Kaukiainen et al. [8] reported that fasting blood 
glucose levels were higher in those exposed to mixed organic 
solvents than in the control group who were not exposed to 
hazardous chemicals: organic solvent exposure was positively 
correlated with glucose, cholesterol and triglyceride though 
these were within reference ranges. In the present study, total 
cholesterol, fasting glucose, fasting insulin, and HOMA-IR 
were significantly higher in the exposed group. This result was 
comparable to other reports, and thought to be the effect of ex-
posure to MAHs. 
Styrene exposure has been reported to change the physi-
ological levels of serotonin and TNF-α which are neurotrans-
mitters [26], and TNF-α inhibits signaling by insulin through 
inhibiting IRS-1 function by serine phosphorylation [27]. 
TNF-α is known to have a biological action opposite to adipo-
nectin, even though its three-dimensional structure is very simi-
lar to that of adiponectin. These two are known to inhibit the 
production and action of each other [28]. TNF-α also elevates 
blood fatty acids by promoting lipolysis in adipocytes, which </p>

<p>may cause a decrease in insulin [29]. IL-1β may suppress IRS-1 
expression ERK-dependently during transcription and ERK-in-
dependently during post-transcription, which may damage in-
sulin signaling [14]. Among cytokines, IL-1β, IL-6 and TNF-α 
were measured and compared between the exposed and control 
groups in this study. Only TNF-α levels were significantly high-
er in the exposed group compared to controls, and IL-1β and 
IL-6 levels were not significantly different, though somewhat 
higher in the exposed group. Multiple linear regression analysis 
between these cytokines and organic solvents did not show any 
significance; however, cytokines and metabolites of organic 
solvents showed a significant relationship. Further, PGA, a 
metabolite of styrene, affected TNF-α positively, meaning that 
there was an increase in TNF-α levels in the exposed group, 
and positively correlated with PGA. It is likely that TNF-α in-
duced an initial immune reaction and diseases such as IR with 
a larger quantity than required for maintaining normal physi-
ological function. In this study, IL-6 was not significantly high; 
however, others have reported that it increases IR by increas-
ing free fatty acid levels in blood [30] and partly induces IR by 
stimulating the degradation of body fat, interrupting glucose 
metabolism, and decreasing the adiponectin [31]. 
With respect to oxidative stress, TOS and OSI were not 
significantly different between groups while TAC was signifi-
cantly lower in the exposed group. Multiple linear regression 
analysis between oxidative stress indices and ambient organic 
solvents or their metabolites showed significant positive asso-
ciation between PGA and TOS, or PGA and OSI, and showed 
a negative association between mHA and TAC. Like cytokines, 
oxidative stress indices were not associated with ambient or-
ganic solvents levels but were associated with urinary metabo-
lites. Absorbed dose seems to have stronger effect than ambient 
exposure level of organic solvents on the induction of physi-
ological changes. 
Most absorbed hazardous chemicals including MAHs are 
excreted from the body by the metabolic action of xenobiotics-
metabolizing enzymes. During this process, highly active and 
reactive metabolic intermediates and ROS are generated, and 
may induce in-vivo toxicity through covalent bonding with 
body macromolecules [32]. Such ROS toxicity in humans has 
been known to affect cell signaling as well as the endocrine 
and immune systems [33]. Karagözler et al. [34] reported that 
TNF-α was significantly increased in house painters, and the 
activities of superoxide dismutase and glutathione peroxidase, 
which are antioxidant enzymes, were significantly lower, and 
malondialdehyde, a measure of lipid peroxidation, was found 
to be significantly elevated. Styrene oxide, a metabolic interme-
diate of styrene, was found to decrease reduced glutathione lev-</p>

<p>Fig. 1. Scatter-plot graph between workplace working duration and 
fasting glucose. Adjustment to age, smoking, drinking habit, waist 
and hip circumference, weight and regular exercise (r = 0.242, p = 
0.014). </p>

<p>Won YL et al. </p>

<p>Safety and Health at Work | Vol. 2, No. 4, Dec. 30, 2011 </p>



<p>www.e-shaw.org </p>

<p>els, and ROS increases were observed in clara cells incubated 
with styrene and its metabolites [35]. In addition, styrene was 
reported to induce an inflammatory response by expressing glu-
tathione S-transferase, an oxidative stress index, and expressing 
monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 (MCP-1), a chemotactic 
cytokine, through NF-κB activation [10]. 
NF-κB is a redox-sensitive transcription factor which 
reacts to cytokines, hormones, and metabolites, and plays a 
central role in diverse responses associated with protection via 
rapid gene expression induction. TNF-α, IL-1β, mitogen, oxi-
dative stress, and inflammatory cytokines are related to its ac-
tivity [36]. While oxidative stress inducers including ROS have 
been known to result in insulin resistance by activating kinases 
such as JNK and IKKβ [37], hyperglycemia is known to result 
in oxidative stress through glucose auto-oxidation, formation of 
advanced glycation end products, arachidonic acid metabolism 
abnormality, and activation of protein kinase C [38], indicating 
that increases in blood glucose or oxidative stress by any reason 
affects reciprocally, possibly leading to a vicious circle. 
In this study, multiple logistic regression analysis (with 
fasting glucose and HOMA-IR levels as the dependent vari-</p>

<p>ables and MAHs exposure, cytokines, and oxidative stress 
as the independent variables) showed a relationship between 
MAHs exposure and fasting glucose. From the results above, 
we can confirm that MAHs exposure increases fasting glucose 
and IR. This high level of IR in the exposed group is thought 
to be due to the effect of oxidative stress and changes in physi-
ological levels of cytokines that are generated by unchanged or-
ganic solvents and the active metabolic intermediate produced 
during glucose metabolism and degradation (Fig. 2). 
In conclusion, the results of the current study demonstrat-
ed that exposure to organic solvents may induce IR, though the 
study population were exposed to organic solvents at as low as 
10% of exposure limit. Considering the recent increase of cere-
bro and cardiovascular diseases at workplaces and the high as-
sociation between IR and cardiovascular diseases, this relation-
ship between IR and exposure to chemical indicates that this 
study can be useful as basic data for the health management of 
workers exposed to chemicals. 
Despite its relevant findings, this study has several limita-
tions. First, the number of subjects for both the test and control 
group was insufficient to make clear conclusions. Second, the </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Possible mechanism of insulin 
resistance by MAHs. MAHs: monocyclic 
aromatic hydrocarbons, ROSs: reactive 
oxygen species. </p>

<p>Exposure of MAHs and Insulin Resistance </p>

<p>Saf Health Work 2011;2:365-74 </p>



<p>www.e-shaw.org </p>

<p>subjects were exposed to MAHs at low levels, and physiologi-
cal levels of cytokines and levels of oxidative stress could not 
be compared according to different exposure levels. Third, ac-
tive metabolic intermediates, transcription factors such as NF-
κB, and kinases that affect cytokines and oxidative stress were 
not measured but interpreted by citing the results from other 
researchers. Therefore, studies investigating clear mechanisms 
obtained via evaluating the levels of metabolic intermediates 
and transcription factors are needed in future research. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was re-
ported. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This study was supported by the intramural research fund 
of the Occupational Safety and Health Research Institute 
(OSHRI). </p>



<p>Won YL et al. </p>

<p>Safety and Health at Work | Vol. 2, No. 4, Dec. 30, 2011 </p>





</text></tei>