<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3537159" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The salient feature of liquid crystal elastomers and networks is strong coupling between orientational order 
and mechanical strain. Orientational order can be changed by a wide variety of stimuli, including the 
presence of moisture. Changes in the orientation of constituents give rise to stresses and strains, which result 
in changes in sample shape. We have utilized this effect to build soft cellulose-based motor driven by 
humidity. The motor consists of a circular loop of cellulose film, which passes over two wheels. When humid 
air is present near one of the wheels on one side of the film, with drier air elsewhere, rotation of the wheels 
results. As the wheels rotate, the humid film dries. The motor runs so long as the difference in humidity is 
maintained. Our cellulose liquid crystal motor thus extracts mechanical work from a difference in humidity. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>ellulose is the most common organic compound on earth. It is the structural component of the cell walls of 
green plants, constituting about a third of all plant matter. It is a polysaccharide, the linear polymer 
(C 6 H 10 O 5 ) n , where 10 2 vnv10 4 . Because of its ubiquity and importance, considerable attention has been 
given to its study and characterization 1 . In addition to paper products, it is used to produce cellophane, rayon and 
gunpowder, and well as adhesives, thickeners and stabilizers. It is also an additive to prevent caking of parmesan 
cheese powders. 
Hydroxypropylcellulose (HPC) is a commercially available derivative of cellulose in which some of the 
hydroxyl groups in the repeating glucose units have been hydroxypropylated. The structure is shown in 
Fig. 1a. Due to the presence of both hydrophobic and hydrophilic groups, it has a lower critical solution 
temperature than cellulose; below 45uC, it is water-soluble. It is biodegradable, biocompatible and electroneutral, 
well suited for pharmaceutical and food applications as thickeners, emulsifiers and encapsulators 2 . It is also used 
in artificial tears. 
Aqueous HPC solutions are isotropic at low polymer concentrations, typically consisting of separate polymer 
chains in the solvent. At higher concentrations, the hydrophobic hydroxypropyl groups promote the association 
of polymer chains to form rigid rod-like fragments 3 . The chains in the fragments are made rigid by intramolecular 
hydrogen bonding of the side chain hydroxylpropyl groups, and are held together by intermolecular hydrogen 
bonds and London dispersion forces. The molecules are packed into crystallites ,470 A ˚ long and ,34 A ˚ 
diameter 4 . These micro-fibrils, in turn, associate to form supermolecular rod-like fragments, resulting in a 
network of rigid rod-like fragments joined together by flexible polymer linkages. As the polymer concentration 
is increased, the increasingly densely packed rodlike fragments become parallel, and liquid crystal mesophases are 
formed 5 . 
Liquid crystals (LCs) are liquids with orientationally ordered constituents. Their broken continuous symmetry 
gives rise to low energy excitations -Goldstone modes. Consequently, LCs are exceptionally responsive to external 
stimuli, enabling LCD technology as well as other novel applications 6 . Simple nematic orientational order is </p>

<p>characterized by a tensor order parameter Q ab ~ 
1 
2 
3l a l b {d ab 
À 
Á 
( 
) 
, where l a is a component of a unit vector ^ l </p>

<p>along the symmetry axis of a mesogenic molecule or particle; the brackets denote ensemble average. Physical 
properties, such as the density, dielectric permittivity and magnetic permeability, are functions of Q ab . In a 
uniaxial system, the order parameter may be written as Q ab ~S 
1 
2 
n a n b {d ab 
À 
Á 
, where { 
1 
2 
ƒSƒ1 is a scalar 
order parameter, and ^ 
n is the nematic director, a unit vector along the direction of average alignment. </p>

<p>Elastomers are rubber-like solids characterized by an elastic 
modulus on the order of MPa which can accommodate strains 
.100%. In 1975, P.G. de Gennes proposed the concept of liquid 
crystal elastomers (LCEs), cross-linked polymer networks with 
orientationally ordered mesogenic units 7 . LCE materials were syn-
thesized and samples produced for the first time by H. Finkelmann 8 . 
The key aspect of these new 'solid' liquid crystals is coupling between 
mechanical strain, e ab and orientational order, Q ab . Due to the sym-
metry allowed scalar Q ab e ba which appears in the free energy, an 
applied strain will change orientational order, similarly to an applied 
electric field, and all physical properties which depend on it. More 
importantly for the work reported here, any change in orientational 
order will result in mechanical strain, similar to that resulting from 
external stress, causing a change in the shape of the elastomer sample. 
Due to their unusual behavior, LCEs have received considerable 
attention, their salient features are discussed in detail in Refs. 9,10. 
Changes in the order parameter caused by heating, illumination, 
exposure to electric fields or the presence of chemical solvents give 
rise to corresponding changes in sample shape 11-14 . The mesogenic 
units may be incorporated into the polymer main chain, or they can 
be attached via side-chains. In main chain LCEs, the increase of 
nematic order leads to an increase in sample length along the dir-
ector, and a contraction in the two perpendicular directions. A 
decrease in order has the converse effect. 
Polymer networks are structurally similar to elastomers, but due to 
higher cross-link density, their modulus is in the GPa range. Liquid 
crystal networks (LCNs) show similar behavior to LCEs in their 
response to excitations, except they are much stiffer. Although typ-
ically the orientationally ordered constituents of LCs are molecules, 
they may also be electron states 15 , or nano-16 or micro-17 particles. In 
the case of HPC, the orientationally ordered constituents are the 
mesogenic rigid fragments 18 . HPC films behave, as LCNs; their 
remarkable response to stimuli, discussed below, is the result of 
liquid crystallinity of the rod-like fragments, and the coupling of 
orientational order to mechanical strain. </p>

<p>Results 
Anisotropic HPC films are formed by the evaporation of water from 
liquid crystalline aqueous HPC solutions (60% w/w). In preparing 
samples, solutions are initially on a glass substrate, with a free surface 
exposed to air. When the cellulose concentration is sufficiently high 
for the formation of the liquid crystal phase, the mesogenic frag-
ments can be uniformly aligned in the sample by shear. Shear is 
applied via a calibrated Gardner knife moving at a controlled speed 
of 1.25 mm s 21 on the free surface, as shown in Fig. 1b.; the process 
produces a monodomain nematic sample. As indicated by X-ray 
studies 19 , the director aligns along the shear direction. As evaporation 
continues, the density of rod-like fragments increases near the free 
top surface, giving rise to increased orientational order. This in turn 
causes elongation at the top of the film in the direction parallel to the 
director, and since the dimensions of the bottom surface in contact 
with the glass substrate are fixed, the top surface buckles, forming a 
set of grooves 20 . This can also be seen in Fig. 1c. The final film 
thickness is ,40 mm microns. The grooves, whose wave vector is 
along the shear direction, are ,3 mm apart, with amplitude ,45 nm. 
The structure of the film near the glass surface is less well understood. 
Here, the solvent remains during shear, so less alignment is expected. 
The films, removed from the substrate, are large area, free-standing 
flexible macroscopic samples. 
The modulus of the cellulose network has been measured for strain 
along the director, as well as perpendicular to it. Results are shown 
in Fig. 2; for small strains, Young's modulus is 263+39 MPa </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Molecular structure and thin film preparation. (a) Idealized </p>

<p>chemical structure of hydroxypropylcellulose (HPC), R-
CH 2 CH(OR')CH 3 or -H (R9-H or -CH 2 CH(OH)CH 3 ), with an average 
degree of substitution of 3.5. (b) Schematic of apparatus used to produce 
HPC shear cast films from lyotropic liquid crystalline solutions, with 
different thicknesses (range 30-100 mm) depending on the Gardner knife 
gap and velocity. (c) 3D topographic image (23 3 23 mm 2 scan) of the free 
surface of a sheared HPC film. </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Stress-strain relations. Squares correspond to strain parallel to </p>

<p>the shear direction and the nematic director. Circles correspond to strain 
perpendicular to the shear direction and the nematic director. For this 
geometry, above a threshold, the stress is nearly independent of strain. This 
indicates 'semi-soft' elasticity, characteristic of nematic elastomers. The 
negative slope at higher strains corresponds to failure due to tearing of the 
films. </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Bending of free standing films. (a) The film free top surface and </p>

<p>(b) the film glass bottom surface exposed to water vapor. Sheared films 
were prepared from liquid crystalline HPC/water solution, the arrows 
indicate shear direction. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1028 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01028 </p>

<p>
for shear parallel and 140+9 MPa perpendicular to the director. 
Above a threshold of 4 MPa, the stress in the perpendicular direction 
is nearly independent of the strain. This 'semi-soft' elastic response is 
characteristic of liquid crystal elastomers 9 . When exposed to water 
vapor, free standing films prepared from a 60% w/w solution bend, as 
shown in Fig. 3. When water vapor penetrates the free surface of the 
film, the sample bends around an axis parallel to the shear direction, 
with the free surface on the outside (Fig. 3a.). This is consistent with 
expansion of the free surface of the film in the direction perpendic-
ular to the director. Such an expansion is expected, since the order 
parameter is reduced by the presence of the solvent water, and fur-
thermore the presence of water molecules between the cellulose 
chains in the rigid segments is expected to cause the thickness of 
the rod-like fragments to increase. 
The shear stress associated with such bend has been measured, as a 
function of time (Fig. 4), in a 20 mm 3 20 mm 3 32 mm planar 
sample at 24uC with free surface exposed to humidity. Measurements 
were taken with Mettler Toledo AG204 load sensor. The maximum 
stress measured was 383 Pa. 
When the film is allowed to dry, either by heating or by being 
placed in a low-humidity environment, the film unbends, reversibly 
assuming its original shape. The bending is relatively fast, on the scale 
of ,1 s. 
Interestingly, when the glass side of the film is exposed to water 
vapor, it bends around an axis perpendicular to the shear direction, 
with the glass side being convex (Fig. 3b.). This is consistent with a 
nearly isotropic expansion of the glass side surface due to the pres-
ence of moisture. Since corrugations on the free surface give rise to a 
smaller effective modulus for bend in this direction, as has been 
confirmed by independent measurements, bend occurs around an 
axis perpendicular to the shear direction. The bend produced by </p>

<p>exposing the glass side to water vapor is considerably smaller than 
that of the free surface. 
Water vapor induced bend has been demonstrated in DNA cov-
ered Si cantilevers 21 , as well as in a different LCN system with a 
different geometry by Broer et al. 14 . In this work, we have exploited 
such a bending phenomenon to produce a humidity driven rotary 
motor. 
There exist a wide variety of definitions of motors in the literature. 
We choose here to define a motor as a device, which uses energy, but 
not momentum, to produce motion. Engines may be defined as 
motors, which obtain energy from a fuel. 
Our humidity driven motor is shown below. A monodomain 
nematic HPC film was produced in the form of a circular loop, 
8.0 cm long, and 1.0 cm wide (Fig. 5). The alignment direction is in 
the plane of the film, perpendicular to the long edges. The loop was 
passed over two 14 mm diameter wheels with horizontal axes. When 
humid air was applied to the outer side of the film near one of the 
wheels, as shown in Fig. 5, the wheels began to rotate, and continued 
so long as humid air was present. The motion is caused by humidity-
induced bend of the liquid crystalline HPC film. A heuristic explana-
tion for the motion is as follows. If the tension in the film is assumed 
to be nearly uniform, the humidity induced bend shortens the lever 
arm on the side where the moist air is applied, resulting on a net 
torque on the wheel and causing rotation of the wheel as illustrated 
schematically in Fig. 6. We have estimated the tensile stress from the 
shape of the circular film loop to be 357 Pa, which is close to the shear 
stress produced by humidity. We conjecture that these two quantities 
need to be comparable for the engine to operate efficiently. 
As the motor rotates, the humid film dries. Key to the process is the 
spontaneous curvature of the film in the region near the wheel where 
the humidity is applied. The motor can be made to rotate faster if the 
ambient temperature is increased, or, equivalently, if the ambient 
humidity is reduced. A detailed model will be published elsewhere. </p>

<p>Discussion 
The energy to drive the motor comes from water vapor -from 
''steam''. In conventional steam engines, fuel is burned to heat the 
water, raising the chemical potential of the water vapor due to 
increase in the temperature. Free energy is converted into work by 
the engine. Our steam engine exploits the difference in chemical 
potential of water molecules in humid and in dry air; the LCN belt 
transports the water from regions of high chemical potential to low, 
gaining energy in the process. The difference in chemical potential m 
is given by 22 </p>

<p>m 2 {m 1 ~kT ln 
x 2 
x 1 </p>

<p>
ð1Þ </p>

<p>where k is Boltzmann's constant, T is the absolute temperature, and x 
is the relative humidity. If the relative humidities are 30% and 70%, as 
in our experiments, the amount of energy available for work at room 
temperature is 2.1 KJ/mole of water, or approximately 100 J/g. The 
underlying mechanism is similar to that of the collagen engine of 
Katchalsky 23 , which is driven by the chemical potential difference of </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Dynamics of stress evolution. Shear stress in a 20 mm 3 </p>

<p>20 mm 3 32 mm planar sample at 24uC with free surface exposed to 
humidity as function of time, measured with a Mettler Toledo AG204 load 
sensor. The maximum stress measured was 383 Pa. </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Moisture-driven liquid crystal cellulose engine. (a) Schematic of the motor, showing location of moist air and rotation direction. The </p>

<p>alignment direction is parallel to the axes of the wheels. The free surface of the film is on the outer side. (b) Series of video frames showing rotation. (Movie 
of the motor is available under supplementary materials.) The motor is housed in a dry environment. Momentum transfer from the moist air is small, and 
opposes the observed motion. Belt dimensions are: 1.0 cm 3 8.0 cm 3 30 mm; wheel dia. is 14 mm. The direction of rotation is indicated by a black arrow, 
and of moist air flow by a white arrow (a). In (b), t52 s/frame. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1028 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01028 </p>

<p>
NaCl in saline solutions and pure water. Whereas his collagen fibers 
contracted in the presence of salt, our LCN bends in the presence of 
humidity. Since our steam engine runs isothermally, it differs fun-
damentally from conventional steam engines in that it is not a heat 
engine. We call it therefore a steam engine of the second kind, and 
note that, consequently, its efficiency not limited by that of Carnot 
cycles. It appears, from Eq. (1), that considerable energy is available 
for work from reservoirs of high and low humidity; our engine pro-
vides a new method of obtaining work from a humidity difference. 
In summary, we have demonstrated a new type of soft motor, 
using a cellulose liquid crystal film, driven by a difference in humid-
ity. The motor is simple; it relies on the moisture-induced bend of the 
HPC, which arises from the coupling between the orientation order 
of the rigid rod-like fragments of the network and mechanical strain. 
Changes in orientational order are caused by the absorption of water 
molecules. As the engine rotates, the moist film dries in a dry air 
environment, and returns to its original shape, ready to perform 
work again when exposed to moist humidity. Since the transport 
of water is via directed diffusion along concentration gradients, it 
is expected that smaller motors will run faster. Micromotors oper-
ating on this principle, using the chemical potential of liquid water or 
moist air may be useful in reducing humidity or producing mech-
anical or electrical energy. Further studies are needed to determine 
the efficiency of the energy conversion process in such a steam engine 
of the second kind. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>(Hydroxypropyl)cellulose (HPC) was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (M W 
5100.000 g/mol; molar substitution, M S 5 3.5, as determined by 1 H NMR) and used 
as received. Solutions of HPC in distilled water with concentration of 60% (w/w) were 
prepared at room temperature. After the first week they were stirred every other day 
and kept, away from light, for at least 4 weeks, until used. 
Films were prepared from LC solutions, casted and sheared simultaneously by 
moving a calibrated Gardner knife from Braive Instruments at 1.25 mm s 21 . The films 
were allowed to dry at room temperature and were kept in a (20%) controlled 
humidity chamber until used. The thickness of the dried films was estimated by 
averaging 10 measurements with a Mitutoyo digital micrometer. 
To construct the motor, the cellulosic film was produced in the form of a circular 
loop, 8.0 cm long, 1.0 cm wide, which passes over two 14 mm diameter wheels. 
The water vapor was generated by an AirProject ultrasonic humidifier (Italy 
ARTSANA Group). 
Photographs and movie of the cellulosic film and motor were taken with a Casio 
EX-F1 Exilim Pro and Canon EOS 550D photo camera. <rs id="software-0" type="software">Blender</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 2.57b</rs>, was 
used to obtain the 3D draw of the shear-casting knife and motor. </p>



<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We acknowledge support from the Portuguese Science and Technology Foundation 
through grants SFRH/BD/63574/2009, SFRH/BPD/78430/2011 to Y. Geng and S.N. 
Fernandes respectively, projects PTDC/CTM/099595/2008, PTDC/FIS/110132/2009, 
PEst-C/CTM/LA0025/2011 (Strategic Project -LA 25 -2011-2012) and from the U.S. 
National Science Foundation IIP 1114332. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>Y.G., P.L.A. and S.N. prepared samples and worked on developing the motor. C.C. worked 
on optimizing the motor. P.P.-M. and M.H.G. conceived of and directed the project and 
wrote this paper; they contributed equally to this work. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>License: This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this 
license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Geng, Y. et al. A cellulose liquid crystal motor: a steam engine of the 
second kind. Sci. Rep. 3, 1028; DOI:10.1038/srep01028 (2013). </p>

<p>Figure 6 | Schematic of the humidity induced bending mechanism. </p>

<p>(a) The configuration is symmetric about a vertical axis. The lever arms 
(green) are of equal length, and the net torque on the top wheel due to 
tension in the film is zero. (b) Due to the humidity-induced bend, the 
configuration is no longer symmetric. Lever arm on the right in top wheel 
is shorter; net torque on top wheel due to tension in the film gives rise to 
CW rotation. (The humidity induced bend has been exaggerated to aid the 
illustration.) </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1028 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01028 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>