<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3589787" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>In order to manage phytosanitary risks in an ever growing and 
increasingly dynamic import and export market, the EU 7th </p>

<p>Framework Program funded the Quarantine Barcoding of Life 
project to develop a quick, reliable and accurate DNA barcode-</p>

<p>based diagnostic tool for selected species on the EPPO A1/A2 
lists and EU Council Directive 2000/29/EC (www.QBOL.org). 
There are currently almost 350 pest and quarantine organ-</p>

<p>isms, covering bacteria, phytoplasmas, fungi, parasitic plants, 
insects and mites, nematodes, virus and virus-like organisms 
on the EPPO A1 (currently absent from the EPPO region) and 
A2 (locally present but controlled in the EPPO region) lists of 
organisms that require standardised protocols against introduc-
tion into, and spread within, the EPPO region. Under QBOL, 
informative loci from the selected quarantine species and their 
taxonomically related species were subjected to DNA barcoding 
from voucher specimens in order to produce reliable DNA bar-
code sequences that are made publicly available through an 
online and searchable database called <rs id="software-32" type="software">Q-bank</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-32" type="url">www.q-bank.eu</rs>) (Bonants et al. 2010). Within the QBOL project, the CBS-
KNAW Fungal Biodiversity Centre (Utrecht, The Netherlands), </p>

<p>was tasked with barcoding the Mycosphaerella complex (order 
Capnodiales, class Dothideomycetes) on the EPPO A1/A2 lists 
and their taxonomically related closest sister species (Table 1). </p>

<p>A major problem with correctly identifying many of the EPPO 
A1/A2-listed fungi is the fact that individual species are often 
named for their particular morphs in separate publications. 
Dual nomenclature makes effective cooperation between 
scientists and the individual quarantine authorities very con-
fused and complicated. The dual nomenclatural system was 
recently abandoned at the International Botanical Congress in 
Melbourne (Hawksworth et al. 2011, Wingfield et al. 2012). In 
accordance with this decision, the concept 'one fungus = one 
name' will be applied in this paper. </p>

<p>The Mycosphaerella generic complex comprises one of the 
largest families within the phylum Ascomycota, whose spe-
cies have evolved as either endophytes, saprophytes and 
symbionts. Mostly, Mycosphaerella s.l. consists of foliicolous 
plant pathogens which are the cause of significant economical 
losses in both temperate and tropical crops worldwide (Crous 
et al. 2001). The Mycosphaerella teleomorph morphology is 
relatively conserved, but is linked to more than 30 anamorph 
genera (Crous 2009). Although originally assumed to be mono-
phyletic (Crous et al. 2001), phylogenetic analyses of numerous 
Mycosphaerella species and their anamorphs by Hunter et 
al. (2006) and Crous et al. (2007) have shown that the Myco­ 
sphaerella complex is in fact polyphyletic. This has since led 
to taxonomic redistribution of most of the phylogenetic clades 
within the complex, although several clades remain unresolved 
due to limited sampling (Crous 2009, Crous et al. 2009a, c). </p>

<p>During the 2011 Fungal DNA Barcoding Workshop in Amster-
dam, The Netherlands, it was decided that the internal tran-
scribed spacers region (ITS) of the nrDNA operon was to 
become the official primary fungal barcoding gene (Schoch et 
al. 2012). The ITS locus is easily amplified and gives a good 
species resolution in many fungal groups. Lack of sufficient ITS 
interspecies variation within some genera of Mycosphaerella-
like fungi (e.g. Septoria, Cercospora and Pseudocercospora) </p>

<p>DNA barcoding of Mycosphaerella species of quarantine 
importance to Europe </p>

<p>W. Quaedvlieg 1,2 , J.Z. Groenewald 1 , M. de Jesús Yáñez-Morales 3 , P.W. Crous 1,2,4 </p>

<p>1 CBS-KNAW Fungal Biodiversity Centre, Uppsalalaan 8, 3584 CT Utrecht, 
The Netherlands; 
corresponding author e-mail: w.quaedvlieg@cbs.knaw.nl. 
2 Microbiology, Department of Biology, Utrecht University, Padualaan 8, 3584 
CH Utrecht, The Netherlands. 
3 Colegio de Postgraduados, Km. 36.5 Carr, Mexico-Texcoco, Montecillo, 
Mpio. de Texcoco, Edo. de Mexico 56230, Mexico. 
4 Wageningen University and Research Centre (WUR), Laboratory of Phyto-
pathology, Droevendaalsesteeg 1, 6708 PB Wageningen, The Netherlands. </p>

<p>Key words </p>

<p>EPPO 
Lecanosticta 
Q-bank 
QBOL </p>

<p>Abstract The EU 7th Framework Program provided funds for Quarantine Barcoding of Life (QBOL) to develop a 
quick, reliable and accurate DNA barcode-based diagnostic tool for selected species on the European and Mediter-
ranean Plant Protection Organization (EPPO) A1/A2 quarantine lists. Seven nuclear genomic loci were evaluated </p>

<p>to determine those best suited for identifying species of Mycosphaerella and/or its associated anamorphs. These 
genes included β-tubulin (Btub), internal transcribed spacer regions of the nrDNA operon (ITS), 28S nrDNA (LSU), 
Actin (Act), Calmodulin (Cal), Translation elongation factor 1-alpha (EF-1α) and RNA polymerase II second larg-
est subunit (RPB2). Loci were tested on their Kimura-2-parameter-based inter- and intraspecific variation, PCR 
amplification success rate and ability to distinguish between quarantine species and closely related taxa. Results 
showed that none of these loci was solely suited as a reliable barcoding locus for the tested fungi. A combination of </p>

<p>a primary and secondary barcoding locus was found to compensate for individual weaknesses and provide reliable 
identification. A combination of ITS with either EF-1α or Btub was reliable as barcoding loci for EPPO A1/A2-listed </p>

<p>Mycosphaerella species. Furthermore, Lecanosticta acicola was shown to represent a species complex, revealing 
two novel species described here, namely L. brevispora sp. nov. on Pinus sp. from Mexico and L. guatemalensis sp. 
nov. on Pinus oocarpa from Guatemala. Epitypes were also designated for L. acicola and L. longispora to resolve 
the genetic application of these names. </p>

<p>Article info Received: 8 October 2012; Accepted: 2 November 2012; Published: 13 December 2012. </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 29, 2012 </p>

<p>Table 1   Isolates used during this study. Isolates marked with an asterisk (*) are type. Isolates marked in grey are quarantine species. Isolates used for the subset trees (Fig.1) are marked with a delta (Δ). </p>



<p>GenBank Accession no 2 </p>

<p>Species </p>

<p>Isolate no 1 </p>

<p>Host </p>

<p>Location </p>

<p>Collected by </p>

<p>ACT </p>

<p>CAL </p>

<p>EF-1α </p>

<p>Btub </p>

<p>RPB2 </p>

<p>ITS </p>

<p>LSU </p>

<p>Cercosporella virgaureae </p>

<p>CBS 113304 </p>

<p>Erigeron annueus </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>H.D. Shin 
JX902067 JX901506 JX901618 JX902189 JX901944 GU214658 JX901820 </p>

<p>Dothistroma pini </p>

<p>CBS 121011 </p>

<p>Pinus pallasiana </p>

<p>Russia </p>

<p>A.C. Usichenko 
JX902068 JX901507 JX901619 JX902190 JX901945 JX901734 JX901821 </p>

<p>CBS 116487 </p>

<p>Pinus nigra </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>G. Adams 
JX902069 JX901508 JX901620 JX902191 JX901946 GU214532 JX901822 </p>



<p>CBS 116486 </p>

<p>Pinus nigra </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>G. Adams 
JX902070 JX901509 JX901621 JX902192 JX901947 JX901735 JX901823 </p>



<p>CBS 116484 </p>

<p>Pinus nigra </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>G. Adams 
JX902071 JX901510 JX901622 JX902193 JX901948 JX901736 JX901824 </p>



<p>CBS 116483 </p>

<p>Pinus nigra </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>G. Adams </p>

<p>JX902072 JX901511 
JX901623 JX902194 JX901949 JX901737 JX901825 </p>



<p>CBS 117609 </p>

<p>Pinus pallasiana </p>

<p>Russia </p>

<p>A.C. Usichenko 
JX902073 JX901512 JX901624 JX902195 JX901950 JX901738 JX901826 </p>



<p>CBS 116485 </p>

<p>Pinus nigra </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>G. Adams 
JX902074 JX901513 JX901625 JX902196 JX901951 JX901739 JX901827 </p>



<p>CBS 121005 Δ </p>

<p>Pinus pallasiana </p>

<p>Russia </p>

<p>T.S. Bulgakov 
JX902075 JX901514 JX901626 JX902197 JX901952 JX901740 JX901828 </p>

<p>D. septosporum </p>

<p>CBS 128782 </p>

<p>Pinus mugo </p>

<p>The Netherlands </p>

<p>W. Quaedvlieg 
JX902076 JX901515 JX901627 JX902198 JX901953 JX901741 JX901829 </p>



<p>CPC 16799 </p>

<p>Pinus mugo </p>

<p>The Netherlands </p>

<p>W. Quaedvlieg 
JX902077 JX901516 JX901628 JX902199 JX901954 JX901742 JX901830 </p>



<p>CBS 543.74 </p>

<p>Pinus pinaster </p>

<p>Brazil </p>

<p>T. Namekata 
JX902078 JX901517 JX901629 JX902200 JX901955 JX901743 JX901831 </p>



<p>CBS 383.74 </p>

<p>Pinus coulteri </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>M. Morelet 
JX902079 JX901518 JX901630 JX902201 JX901956 EU167578 JX901832 </p>



<p>CBS 112498 Δ </p>

<p>Pinus radiata </p>

<p>Ecuador </p>

<p>P.W. Crous 
JX902080 JX901519 JX901631 JX902202 JX901957 JX901744 JX901833 </p>

<p>Lecanosticta acicola </p>

<p>LNPV241 </p>

<p>Pinus radiata </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>P. Chandelier 
JX902081 JX901520 JX901632 JX902203 JX901958 JX901745 JX901834 </p>

<p>LNPV242 </p>

<p>Pinus muricata </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>P. Chandelier 
JX902082 JX901521 JX901633 JX902204 JX901959 JX901746 JX901835 </p>



<p>WPF4.12 * </p>

<p>Pinus strobum </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>B. Ostrofsky 
KC013004 KC013010 KC013001 KC013007 KC013013 KC012998 KC013016 </p>



<p>CBS 133791 = WPF13.12 
Pinus strobum </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>B. Ostrofsky 
KC013005 KC013011 KC013002 KC013008 KC013014 KC012999 KC013017 </p>



<p>WPF73.12 </p>

<p>Pinus strobum </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>J. Weiner 
KC013006 KC013012 KC013003 KC013009 KC013015 KC013000 KC013018 </p>

<p>LNPV244 </p>

<p>P. attenuata </p>

<p>× radiata </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>P. Chandelier 
JX902083 JX901522 -
JX902205 JX901960 JX901747 JX901836 </p>

<p>LNPV245 </p>

<p>P. attenuata </p>

<p>× radiata </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>P. Chandelier 
JX902084 JX901523 -
JX902206 JX901961 JX901748 JX901837 </p>



<p>LNPV246 </p>

<p>P. attenuata </p>

<p>× radiata </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>P. Chandelier 
JX902085 JX901524 JX901634 JX902207 JX901962 JX901749 JX901838 </p>



<p>LNPV247 </p>

<p>P. radiata </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>P. Chandelier 
JX902086 JX901525 JX901635 JX902208 JX901963 JX901750 JX901839 </p>



<p>LNPV248 </p>

<p>P. attenuata </p>

<p>× radiata </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>P. Chandelier 
JX902087 JX901526 JX901636 JX902209 JX901964 JX901751 JX901840 </p>

<p>LNPV249 </p>

<p>P. attenuata </p>

<p>× radiata </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>P. Chandelier 
JX902088 JX901527 JX901637 JX902210 JX901965 JX901752 JX901841 </p>

<p>LNPV250 </p>

<p>Pinus sp. </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>P. Chandelier 
JX902089 JX901528 JX901638 JX902211 </p>

<p>JX901966 JX901753 JX901842 </p>

<p>LNPV251 </p>

<p>P. attenuata </p>

<p>× radiata </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>P. Chandelier 
JX902090 JX901529 -
JX902212 JX901967 JX901754 JX901843 </p>

<p>LNPV252 </p>

<p>P. attenuata </p>

<p>× radiata </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>P. Chandelier 
JX902091 JX901530 JX901639 JX902213 JX901968 JX901755 JX901844 </p>



<p>LNPV253 </p>

<p>P. palustris </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>C. Affeltranger 
JX902092 JX901531 JX901640 JX902214 JX901969 JX901756 JX901845 </p>

<p>LNPV254 </p>

<p>Pinus sp. </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>P. Chandelier 
JX902093 JX901532 JX901641 JX902215 JX901970 JX901757 JX901846 </p>

<p>LNPV255 </p>

<p>Pinus sp. </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>P. Chandelier 
JX902094 JX901533 JX901642 JX902216 JX901971 JX901758 JX901847 </p>



<p>LNPV256 </p>

<p>Pinus sp. </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>P. Chandelier 
JX902095 JX901534 JX901643 JX902217 JX901972 JX901759 JX901848 </p>



<p>LNPV257 </p>

<p>Pinus radiata </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>P. Chandelier 
JX902096 JX901535 JX901644 JX902218 JX901973 JX901760 JX901849 </p>



<p>CBS 133790 = LA773A </p>

<p>Pinus mugo </p>

<p>Lithuania 
S. Markovskaja, A. Kačergius JX902097 JX901536 JX901645 JX902219 JX901974 HM367708 JX901850 </p>









<p>&amp; A. Treigienė </p>



<p>LA773B </p>

<p>Pinus mugo </p>

<p>Lithuania 
S. Markovskaja, A. Kačergius JX902098 JX901537 JX901646 JX902220 JX901975 HM367707 JX901851 </p>









<p>&amp; A. Treigienė </p>



<p>LNPV243 Δ </p>

<p>P. pinaster </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>P. Chandelier 
JX902099 JX901538 JX901647 JX902221 JX901976 JX901761 JX901852 </p>



<p>CBS 871.95 Δ </p>

<p>Pinus radiata </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>M. Morelet </p>

<p>JX902100 JX901539 -
JX902222 JX901977 GU214663 JX901853 </p>



<p>CBS 133789 = CPC 17822 Δ </p>

<p>Pinus sp. </p>

<p>Mexico </p>

<p>J.Y. Morales 
JX902101 JX901540 JX901648 JX902223 JX901978 JX901762 JX901854 </p>

<p>L. brevispora </p>

<p>CBS 133601 = CPC 18092 * Δ Pinus sp. </p>

<p>Mexico </p>

<p>J.Y. Morales 
JX902102 JX901541 JX901649 JX902224 JX901979 JX901763 JX901855 </p>

<p>L. guatamalensis </p>

<p>IMI 281598 * Δ </p>

<p>Pinus oocarpa </p>

<p>Guatemala </p>

<p>H.C. Evans 
JX902103 JX901542 JX901650 JX902225 JX901980 JX901764 JX901856 </p>

<p>L. longispora </p>

<p>CPC 17940 Δ </p>

<p>Pinus sp. </p>

<p>Mexico </p>

<p>J.Y. Morales 
JX902104 JX901543 JX901652 JX902226 JX901981 JX901765 JX901857 </p>



<p>CBS 133602 = CPC 17941 * Δ Pinus sp. </p>

<p>Mexico </p>

<p>J.Y. Morales 
JX902105 JX901544 JX901651 JX902227 JX901982 JX901766 JX901858 </p>

<p>Mycosphaerella ellipsoidea </p>

<p>CBS 110843 * Δ </p>

<p>Eucalyptus cladocalyx </p>

<p>South Africa </p>

<p>P.W. Crous 
JX902106 JX901545 JX901653 JX902228 JX901983 AY725545 JX901859 </p>

<p>M. endophytica </p>

<p>CBS 114662 * </p>

<p>Eucalyptus sp. </p>

<p>South Africa </p>

<p>P.W. Crous 
JX902107 JX901546 JX901654 JX902229 JX901984 DQ302953 JX901860 </p>



<p>CBS 111519 * </p>

<p>Eucalyptus sp. </p>

<p>South Africa </p>

<p>P.W. Crous 
JX902108 JX901547 JX901655 JX902230 JX901985 DQ302952 JX901861 </p>

<p>M. laricis­leptolepidis </p>

<p>MAFF 410081 </p>

<p>Larix leptolepis </p>

<p>Japan </p>

<p>K. Ito 
JX902109 JX901548 JX901656 JX902231 JX901986 JX901767 JX901862 </p>



<p>MAFF 410632 </p>

<p>Larix leptolepis </p>

<p>Japan </p>

<p>T. Yokota </p>

<p>JX902110 
JX901549 JX901657 JX902232 JX901987 JX901768 JX901863 </p>



<p>MAFF 410633 </p>

<p>Larix leptolepis </p>

<p>Japan </p>

<p>T. Yokota </p>

<p>JX902111 
JX901550 JX901658 JX902233 JX901988 JX901769 JX901864 </p>



<p>MAFF 410234 Δ </p>

<p>Larix leptolepis </p>

<p>Japan </p>

<p>N. Ota </p>

<p>JX902112 
JX901551 JX901659 JX902234 JX901989 JX901770 JX901865 </p>



<p>W. Quaedvlieg et al.: DNA barcoding of Mycosphaerella </p>

<p>M. latebrosa </p>

<p>CBS 687.94 </p>

<p>Acer pseudoplatanus </p>

<p>The Netherlands </p>

<p>G. Verkley </p>

<p>JX902113 
JX901552 JX901660 JX902235 JX901990 JX901771 JX901866 </p>



<p>CBS 183.97 </p>

<p>Acer pseudoplatanus </p>

<p>The Netherlands </p>

<p>H.A. van der Aa </p>

<p>JX902114 
JX901553 JX901661 JX902236 JX901991 AF362051 JX901867 </p>



<p>CBS 652.85 </p>

<p>Acer pseudoplatanus </p>

<p>The Netherlands </p>

<p>H.A. van der Aa </p>

<p>JX902115 
JX901554 JX901662 JX902237 JX901992 AF362067 JX901868 </p>

<p>M. populicola </p>

<p>CBS 100042 Δ </p>

<p>Populus trichocarpa </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>G. Newcombe </p>

<p>JX902116 
JX901555 JX901663 JX902238 -</p>

<p>JX901772 JX901869 </p>

<p>Mycosphaerella sp. </p>

<p>CBS 111166 </p>

<p>Eucalyptus cladocalyx </p>

<p>South Africa </p>

<p>P.W. Crous </p>

<p>JX902117 
JX901556 JX901664 JX902239 JX901993 JX901773 JX901870 </p>



<p>CBS 110501 Δ </p>

<p>Eucalyptus globulus </p>

<p>Australia </p>

<p>A. Maxwell </p>

<p>JX902118 
JX901557 JX901665 JX902240 JX901994 EU167580 JX901871 </p>

<p>M. sumatrensis </p>

<p>CBS 118501 </p>

<p>Eucalyptus sp. </p>

<p>Indonesia </p>

<p>M.J. Wingfield </p>

<p>JX902119 
JX901558 -
JX902241 JX901995 JX901774 JX901872 </p>



<p>CBS 118502 </p>

<p>Eucalyptus sp. </p>

<p>Indonesia </p>

<p>M.J. Wingfield 
JX902120 JX901559 -
JX902242 JX901996 JX901775 JX901873 </p>



<p>CBS 118499 * Δ </p>

<p>Eucalyptus sp. </p>

<p>Indonesia </p>

<p>M.J. Wingfield 
JX902121 JX901560 -
JX902243 JX901997 JX901776 JX901874 </p>

<p>Phaeophleospora eugeniae </p>

<p>CPC 15143 </p>

<p>Eugenia uniflora </p>

<p>Brazil </p>

<p>Alfenas 
JX902122 JX901561 JX901666 JX902244 JX901998 FJ493188 </p>

<p>JX901875 </p>



<p>CPC 15159 Δ </p>

<p>Eugenia uniflora </p>

<p>Brazil </p>

<p>Alfenas 
JX902123 JX901562 JX901667 JX902245 JX901999 FJ493189 </p>

<p>JX901876 </p>

<p>Pseudocercospora angolensis </p>

<p>CBS 244.94 </p>

<p>Citrus sp. </p>

<p>Zimbabwe </p>

<p>P.W. Crous 
JX902124 JX901563 JX901668 JX902246 JX902000 JX901777 JX901877 </p>



<p>CBS 112748 </p>

<p>Citrus sp. </p>

<p>Zimbabwe </p>

<p>P.W. Crous 
JX902125 JX901564 JX901669 JX902247 JX902001 JX901778 JX901878 </p>



<p>CBS 112933 </p>

<p>Citrus sp. </p>

<p>Zimbabwe </p>

<p>M.C. Pretorius 
JX902126 JX901565 JX901670 JX902248 JX902002 AY260063 JX901879 </p>



<p>CBS 115645 </p>

<p>Citrus sp. </p>

<p>Zimbabwe </p>

<p>P.W. Crous 
JX902127 JX901566 JX901671 JX902249 JX902003 JX901779 JX901880 </p>



<p>CBS 149.53 * Δ </p>

<p>Citrus sinensis </p>

<p>Angola 
T. de Carvalho &amp; O. Mendes JX902128 JX901567 JX901672 JX902250 JX902004 JQ324941 JX901881 </p>

<p>P. assamensis </p>

<p>CBS 122467 </p>

<p>Musa sp. </p>

<p>India </p>

<p>I.W. Buddenhagen 
JX902129 JX901568 JX901673 JX902251 JX902005 EU514281 JX901882 </p>

<p>P. atromarginalis </p>

<p>CPC 11372 </p>

<p>Solanun nigrum </p>

<p>Republic of Korea H.D. Shin </p>

<p>JX902130 -
JX901674 JX902252 JX902006 JX901780 JX901883 </p>

<p>P. cercidis­chinensis </p>

<p>CPC 14481 </p>

<p>Cercis chinensis </p>

<p>Republic of Korea H.D. Shin </p>

<p>JX902131 -
JX901675 JX902253 JX902007 DQ267602 JX901884 </p>

<p>P. chiangmaiensis </p>

<p>CBS 123244 * </p>

<p>Eucalyptus camaldurensis </p>

<p>Thailand </p>

<p>R. Cheewangkoon </p>

<p>JX902132 -
JX901676 JX902254 JX902008 JX901781 JX901885 </p>

<p>P. clematidis </p>

<p>CPC 11657 Δ </p>

<p>Clematis sp. </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>M. Palm 
JX902133 JX901569 JX901677 JX902255 JX902009 DQ303072 JX901886 </p>

<p>P. flavomarginata </p>

<p>CBS 118824 * </p>

<p>Eucalyptus camaldulensis </p>

<p>China </p>

<p>M.J. Wingfield </p>

<p>JX902134 -
JX901678 JX902256 JX902010 JX901782 JX901887 </p>

<p>P. gracilis </p>

<p>CPC 11144 </p>

<p>Eucalyptus sp. </p>

<p>Indonesia </p>

<p>M.J. Wingfield 
JX902135 JX901570 JX901679 JX902257 JX902011 </p>

<p>DQ302961 JX901888 </p>



<p>CPC 11181 </p>

<p>Eucalyptus sp. </p>

<p>Indonesia </p>

<p>M.J. Wingfield 
JX902136 JX901571 JX901680 JX902258 JX902012 DQ302962 JX901889 </p>



<p>CBS 111189 </p>

<p>Eucalyptus urophylla </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>M.J. Wingfield 
JX902137 JX901572 JX901681 JX902259 JX902013 DQ302960 JX901890 </p>

<p>P. humuli­japonici </p>

<p>CPC 11315 </p>

<p>Humulus japonicus </p>

<p>Republic of Korea H.D. Shin 
JX902138 JX901573 JX901682 JX902260 JX902014 JX901783 JX901891 </p>



<p>CPC 11462 </p>

<p>Plectranthus </p>

<p>Republic of Korea H.D. Shin 
JX902139 JX901574 JX901682 JX902261 JX902015 JX901784 JX901892 </p>

<p>P. madagascariensis </p>

<p>CBS 124155 * </p>

<p>Eucalyptus camaldulensis </p>

<p>Madagascar </p>

<p>M.J. Wingfield </p>

<p>JX902140 -
JX901683 JX902262 JX902016 FJ790268 </p>

<p>JX901893 </p>

<p>P. norchiensis </p>

<p>CBS 120738 * </p>

<p>Eucalyptus sp. </p>

<p>Italy </p>

<p>W. Gams 
JX902141 JX901575 JX901684 JX902263 JX902017 JX901785 JX901894 </p>

<p>P. paraguayensis </p>

<p>CBS 111286 Δ </p>

<p>Eucalyptus nitens </p>

<p>Brazil </p>

<p>P.W. Crous </p>

<p>JX902142 -
JX901685 JX902264 JX902018 DQ267602 JX901895 </p>

<p>P. pini­densiflorae </p>

<p>CBS 125139 </p>

<p>Pinus thunbergii </p>

<p>Japan </p>

<p>Sung-Oui Suh </p>

<p>JX902143 -
JX901686 JX902265 JX902019 JX901786 JX901896 </p>

<p>CBS 125140 </p>

<p>Pinus kesiya </p>

<p>Japan </p>

<p>Sung-Oui Suh </p>

<p>JX902144 -
JX901687 JX902266 JX902020 JX901787 JX901897 </p>



<p>CBS 125138 Δ </p>

<p>Pinus sp. </p>

<p>Japan </p>

<p>Sung-Oui Suh </p>

<p>JX902145 -
JX901688 JX902267 JX902021 JX901788 JX901898 </p>

<p>P. pseudoeucalyptorum </p>

<p>CPC 12802 </p>

<p>Eucalyptus globulus </p>

<p>Portugal </p>

<p>A. Phillips 
JX902146 JX901576 JX901689 JX902268 JX902022 GQ852759 JX901899 </p>



<p>CPC 13769 </p>

<p>Eucalyptus punctata </p>

<p>South Africa </p>

<p>P.W. Crous 
JX902147 JX901577 JX901690 JX902269 JX902023 GQ852762 JX901900 </p>



<p>CPC 12568 </p>

<p>Eucalyptus nitens </p>

<p>Tasmania </p>

<p>C. Mohammed 
JX902148 JX901578 JX901691 JX902270 JX902024 GQ852758 JX901901 </p>

<p>P. pyracanthigena </p>

<p>CPC 10808 Δ </p>

<p>Pyracantha angustifolia </p>

<p>Republic of Korea H.D. Shin </p>

<p>JX902149 -
JX901692 JX902271 JX902025 JX901789 JX901902 </p>

<p>P. rhoina </p>

<p>CPC 11464 </p>

<p>Rhus chinensis </p>

<p>Republic of Korea H.D. Shin </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-
JX901693 JX902272 JX902026 JX901790 JX901903 </p>

<p>P. robusta </p>

<p>CBS 111175 * Δ </p>

<p>Eucalyptus robur </p>

<p>Malaysia </p>

<p>M.J. Wingfield 
JX902150 JX901579 JX901694 JX902273 JX902027 DQ303081 JX901904 </p>

<p>P. schizolobii </p>

<p>CBS 124990 </p>

<p>Eucalyptus camaldulensis </p>

<p>Thailand </p>

<p>W. Himaman </p>

<p>JX902151 -
JX901695 JX902274 JX902028 GQ852765 JX901905 </p>

<p>P. sphaerulinae </p>

<p>CBS 112621 * </p>

<p>Eucalyptus sp. </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>P.W. Crous </p>

<p>-
JX901580 JX901696 JX902275 JX902029 JX901791 JX901906 </p>

<p>P. subulata </p>

<p>CBS 118489 </p>

<p>Eucalyptus botryoides </p>

<p>New Zealand </p>

<p>M. Dick 
JX902152 JX901581 JX901697 JX902276 JX902030 JX901792 JX901907 </p>

<p>P. tereticornis </p>

<p>CPC 13008 </p>

<p>Eucalyptus tereticornus </p>

<p>Australia </p>

<p>A.J. Carnegie 
JX902153 JX901582 JX901698 JX902277 JX902031 GQ852769 JX901908 </p>



<p>CPC 13315 </p>

<p>Eucalyptus tereticornus </p>

<p>Australia </p>

<p>P.W. Crous 
JX902154 JX901583 JX901699 JX902278 JX902032 GQ852771 JX901909 </p>



<p>CBS 124996 Δ </p>

<p>Eucalyptus nitens </p>

<p>Australia </p>

<p>A.J. Carnegie 
JX902155 JX901584 JX901700 JX902279 JX902033 GQ852768 JX901910 </p>



<p>CPC 13299 * </p>

<p>Eucalyptus tereticornus </p>

<p>Australia </p>

<p>A.J. Carnegie 
JX902156 JX901585 JX901701 JX902280 JX902034 GQ852770 JX901911 </p>

<p>P. vitis </p>

<p>CPC 11595 </p>

<p>Vitis vinifera </p>

<p>Republic of Korea H.D. Shin 
JX902157 JX901586 JX901702 JX902281 JX902035 DQ073923 JX901912 </p>

<p>Septoria abeliceae </p>

<p>CBS 128591 </p>

<p>Zelkova serrata </p>

<p>Republic of Korea S.B. Hong 
JX902158 JX901587 JX901703 JX902282 JX902036 JX901793 JX901913 </p>

<p>S. cf. chrysanthemella </p>

<p>CBS 483.63 </p>

<p>Chrysanthemum sp. </p>

<p>The Netherlands </p>

<p>H.A. van der Aa 
JX902159 JX901588 JX901704 JX902283 JX902037 JX901794 JX901914 </p>



<p>CBS 351.58 </p>

<p>Chrysanthemum indicum </p>

<p>Germany </p>

<p>R. Schneider 
JX902160 JX901589 JX901705 JX902284 JX902038 JX901795 JX901915 </p>

<p>S. citri </p>

<p>CBS 315.37 Δ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>L.L. Huillier 
JX902161 JX901590 JX901706 JX902285 JX902039 DQ897650 JX901916 </p>

<p>S. cucurbitacearum </p>

<p>CBS 178.77 Δ </p>

<p>Cucurbita maxima </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>H.J. Boesewinkel 
JX902162 JX901591 JX901707 JX902286 JX902040 JX901796 JX901917 </p>

<p>S. lycopersici </p>

<p>CBS 353.49 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>S.P. Doolittle 
JX902163 JX901592 JX901708 JX902287 JX902041 DQ841155 JX901918 </p>



<p>CBS 128654 Δ </p>

<p>Lycopersicon esculentum </p>

<p>Republic of Korea S.B. Hong 
JX902164 JX901593 JX901709 JX902288 JX902042 JX901797 JX901919 </p>

<p>S. malagutii </p>

<p>CBS 106.80 Δ </p>

<p>Solanum sp. </p>

<p>Peru </p>

<p>L.J. Turkensteen 
JX902165 JX901594 JX901710 JX902289 JX902043 DQ841154 JX901920 </p>

<p>S. matricariae </p>

<p>CBS 109000 </p>

<p>Matricaria discoidea </p>

<p>The Netherlands </p>

<p>G. Verkley 
JX902166 JX901595 JX901711 
JX902290 JX902044 JX901798 JX901921 </p>

<p>CBS 109001 </p>

<p>Matricaria discoidea </p>

<p>The Netherlands </p>

<p>G. Verkley 
JX902167 JX901596 JX901712 JX902291 JX902045 JX901799 JX901922 </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 29, 2012 </p>

<p>might make this locus less than ideal for resolving some an-
amorph genera or cryptic species complexes within these 
genera (Verkley et al. 2004, Hunter et al. 2006, Schoch et al. 
2012). To compensate for this perceived lack of resolution within 
the ITS locus of Mycosphaerella-like species, seven loci were 
screened, which have individually or in combination been used 
in the past to successfully identify Mycosphaerella-like species. 
These include β-tubulin (Btub) (Feau et al. (2006)), internal tran-
scribed spacer (ITS), Actin (Act) (Schubert et al. 2007, Crous 
et al. In press), Translation elongation factor 1-alpha (EF-1α) 
(Schubert et al. 2007, Crous et al. In press) and 28S nrDNA 
(LSU) (Hunter et al. 2006), Calmodulin (Cal) (Groenewald et al. 
2005) and RNA polymerase II second largest subunit (RPB2) 
(Quaedvlieg et al. (2011)). </p>

<p>The aims of this study were to 1) identify the closest neighbours 
of seven Mycosphaerella-like species of quarantine importance 
using sequences of both the internal transcribed spacer regions 
and 5.8S nrRNA gene of the nrDNA operon (ITS). These isolates 
were then 2) screened with the seven previously mentioned test 
loci to determine the most optimal DNA barcode region(s) based 
on PCR efficiency, the size of the K2P barcode gaps and the 
molecular phylogenetic resolution of the individual loci. Based 
on the obtained results and existing literature, 3) the taxonomic 
status of these quarantine species was then revised employing 
the one fungus one name principle as stated by Hawksworth 
et al. (2011). </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Isolates and morphology 
Most of the DNA used during this study were isolated from pure 
cultures that were either available at, or were made available 
to, the CBS-KNAW Fungal Biodiversity Centre, Utrecht, the 
Netherlands (CBS). Reference strains were either maintained 
in the culture collection of CBS, the Ministry of Agriculture, For-
estry and Fisheries of Japan culture collection (MAFF) and/or 
at the LNPV - Mycologie, Malzéville, France (LNPV) (Table 1). 
Fresh collections were made from leaves of diverse hosts by 
placing material in damp chambers for 1-2 d. Single conidial 
colonies were established from sporulating conidiomata on Petri 
dishes containing 2 % malt extract agar (MEA) as described 
earlier by Crous et al. (1991). Colonies were sub-cultured onto 
potato-dextrose agar (PDA), oatmeal agar (OA), MEA (Crous 
et al. 2009b), and pine needle agar (PNA) (Lewis 1998), and 
incubated at 25 °C under continuous near-ultraviolet light to 
promote sporulation. Morphological descriptions are based on 
slide preparations mounted in clear lactic acid from colonies 
sporulating on PNA. Observations were made with a Zeiss V20 
Discovery stereo-microscope, and with a Zeiss Axio Imager 2 
light microscope using differential interference contrast (DIC) il-
lumination and an <rs corresp="#software-38" type="creator">AxioCam</rs> <rs id="software-38" type="software">MRc5</rs> camera and software. Colony 
characters and pigment production were noted after 1 mo of 
growth on MEA, PDA and OA (Crous et al. 2009b) incubated 
at 25 °C. Colony colours (surface and reverse) were rated 
according to the colour charts of Rayner (1970). Sequences 
derived in this study were lodged with <rs type="software">GenBank</rs>, the alignments 
in <rs id="software-29" type="software">TreeBASE</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-29" type="url">www.treebase.org</rs>), and taxonomic novelties in 
<rs id="software-35" type="software">MycoBank</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-35" type="url">www.MycoBank.org</rs>) (Crous et al. 2004a). </p>

<p>Multi-locus DNA screening 
Genomic DNA was extracted from mycelium growing on MEA 
(Table 1), using the UltraClean® Microbial DNA Isolation Kit (Mo 
Bio Laboratories, Inc., Solana Beach, CA, USA). These strains 
were screened for seven loci (ITS, LSU, Act, Cal, EF-1α, RPB2 
and Btub) using the primer sets and conditions listed in Table 
2. The PCR amplifications were performed in a total volume 
of 12.5 µL solution containing 10 -20 ng of template DNA, </p>



<p>GenBank Accession no 2 </p>

<p>Species </p>

<p>Isolate no 1 </p>

<p>Host </p>

<p>Location </p>

<p>Collected by </p>

<p>ACT </p>

<p>CAL </p>

<p>EF-1α </p>

<p>Btub </p>

<p>RPB2 </p>

<p>ITS </p>

<p>LSU </p>

<p>S. musiva </p>

<p>CBS 130559 </p>

<p>Hybrid poplar </p>

<p>Canada </p>

<p>J. LeBoldus 
JX902168 JX901597 JX901713 JX902292 JX902046 JX901800 JX901923 </p>



<p>D7L2 # </p>

<p>P. deltoides 
× P. balsamifera </p>

<p>Canada </p>

<p>J. LeBoldus 
JX902169 JX901598 JX901714 JX902293 JX902047 JX901801 JX901924 </p>



<p>CBS 130560 </p>

<p>Hybrid poplar </p>

<p>Canada </p>

<p>J. LeBoldus 
JX902170 JX901599 JX901715 JX902294 JX902048 JX901802 JX901925 </p>



<p>CBS 130561 </p>

<p>P. deltoides 
× P. balsamifera </p>

<p>Canada </p>

<p>J. LeBoldus 
JX902171 JX901600 JX901716 JX902295 JX902049 JX901803 JX901926 </p>



<p>CBS 130562 </p>

<p>Hybrid poplar </p>

<p>Canada </p>

<p>J. LeBoldus 
JX902172 JX901601 JX901717 JX902296 JX902050 JX901804 JX901927 </p>



<p>CBS 130563 </p>

<p>P. deltoides 
× P. balsamifera </p>

<p>Canada </p>

<p>J. LeBoldus 
JX902173 JX901602 JX901718 JX902297 JX902051 JX901805 JX901928 </p>



<p>CBS 130564 </p>

<p>Populus deltoides </p>

<p>Canada </p>

<p>J. LeBoldus 
JX902174 JX901603 JX901719 JX902298 JX902052 JX901806 JX901929 </p>



<p>CBS 130565 </p>

<p>Populus deltoides </p>

<p>Canada </p>

<p>J. LeBoldus 
JX902175 JX901604 JX901720 JX902299 JX902053 JX901807 JX901930 </p>



<p>CBS 130566 </p>

<p>Populus deltoides </p>

<p>Canada </p>

<p>J. LeBoldus 
JX902176 JX901605 JX901721 JX902300 JX902054 JX901808 JX901931 </p>



<p>CBS 130567 </p>

<p>Populus deltoides </p>

<p>Canada </p>

<p>J. LeBoldus 
JX902177 JX901606 JX901722 JX902301 JX902055 JX901809 JX901932 </p>



<p>CBS 130568 </p>

<p>Populus deltoides </p>

<p>Canada </p>

<p>J. LeBoldus 
JX902178 JX901607 JX901723 JX902302 JX902056 JX901810 JX901933 </p>



<p>CBS 130569 </p>

<p>Populus deltoides </p>

<p>Canada </p>

<p>J. LeBoldus 
JX902179 JX901608 JX901724 JX902303 JX902057 JX901811 </p>

<p>JX901934 </p>



<p>CBS 130570 </p>

<p>Populus deltoides </p>

<p>Canada </p>

<p>J. LeBoldus 
JX902180 JX901609 JX901725 JX902304 JX902058 JX901812 JX901935 </p>



<p>CBS 130571 </p>

<p>Populus deltoides </p>

<p>Canada </p>

<p>J. LeBoldus 
JX902181 JX901610 JX901726 JX902305 JX902059 JX901813 JX901936 </p>



<p>CBS 130558 Δ </p>

<p>P. deltoides 
× P. balsamifera </p>

<p>Canada </p>

<p>J. LeBoldus </p>

<p>JX902182 JX901611 
JX901727 JX902306 JX902060 JX901814 JX901937 </p>

<p>S. obesa </p>

<p>CBS 354.58 </p>

<p>Chrysanthemum indicum </p>

<p>Germany </p>

<p>R. Schneider 
JX902183 JX901612 JX901728 JX902307 JX902061 AY489285 JX901938 </p>



<p>CBS 128759 </p>

<p>Chrysanthemum morifolium 
Republic of Korea S.B. Hong 
JX902184 JX901613 JX901729 JX902308 JX902062 JX901815 JX901939 </p>



<p>CBS 128623 </p>

<p>Chrysanthemum indicum 
Republic of Korea H.D. Shin 
JX902185 JX901614 JX901730 JX902309 JX902063 JX901816 JX901940 </p>



<p>CBS 128588 </p>

<p>Artemisia lavandulaefolia </p>

<p>Republic of Korea S.B. Hong 
JX902186 JX901615 JX901731 JX902310 JX902064 JX901817 JX901941 </p>

<p>S. populi </p>

<p>CBS 391.59 Δ </p>

<p>Populus pyramidalis </p>

<p>Germany </p>

<p>R. Schneider 
JX902187 JX901616 JX901732 JX902311 </p>

<p>JX902065 JX901818 JX901942 </p>

<p>Teratosphaeria nubilosa </p>

<p>CPC 12243 Δ </p>

<p>Eucalyptus globulus </p>

<p>Portugal </p>

<p>A.J.L. Phillips 
JX902188 JX901617 JX901733 JX902312 JX902066 JX901819 JX901943 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CBS: Centraalbureau voor Schimmelcultures, Utrecht, The Netherlands; CPC: Pedro Crous working collection housed at CBS, LNPV: laboratoire national de la protection des végétaux, Angers, France. MAFF:Ministry of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries, Tokyo, Japan. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ACT = Actin, Btub = β-tubulin, CAL = Calmodulin, LSU = 28S large subunit of the nrRNA gene, RPB2= RNA polymerase II second largest subunit, ITS= Internal transcribed spacer and EF-1α = Translation elongation factor 1-alpha. # </p>

<p>isolate provided by J. LeBoldus. </p>

<p>Table 1   (cont.) </p>



<p>W. Quaedvlieg et al.: DNA barcoding of Mycosphaerella </p>

<p>1 × PCR buffer, 0.7 µL DMSO (99.9 %), 2 mM MgCl 2 , 0.4 µM 
of each primer, 25 µM of each dNTP and 1.0 U BioTaq DNA 
polymerase (Bioline GmbH, Luckenwalde, Germany). PCR 
amplification conditions were set as follows: an initial denatura-
tion temperature of 96 °C for 2 min, followed by 40 cycles of 
denaturation temperature of 96 °C for 45 s, primer annealing 
at the temperature stipulated in Table 3, primer extension at 
72 °C for 90 s and a final extension step at 72 °C for 2 min. The 
resulting fragments were sequenced using the PCR primers 
together with a BigDye Terminator Cycle Sequencing Kit v. 3.1 
(Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). Sequencing reactions </p>

<p>were performed as described by Cheewangkoon et al. (2008). </p>

<p>Phylogenetic analysis 
A basic alignment of the obtained sequence data was first done 
using <rs id="software-44" type="software">MAFFT</rs> <rs corresp="#software-44" type="version-number">v.6</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-44" type="url">http://mafft.cbrc.jp/alignment/server/index.html</rs> (Katoh et al. 2002) and if necessary, manually improved 
in <rs id="software-33" type="software">BioEdit</rs> v. <rs corresp="#software-33" type="version-number">7.0.5.2</rs> (Hall 1999). Bayesian analyses (critical 
value for the topological convergence diagnostic set to 0.01) 
were performed on the individual loci using <rs id="software-30" type="software">MrBayes</rs> v. <rs corresp="#software-30" type="version-number">3.2.1</rs> 
(Huelsenbeck &amp; Ronquist 2001) as described by Crous et al. 
(2006b). Suitable models were first selected using Models of </p>

<p>nucleotide substitution for each gene as determined using 
MrModeltest (Nylander 2004), and included for each gene 
partition. The substitution models for each locus are shown in 
Table 3. Teratosphaeria nubilosa (CPC 12243) was used as 
outgroup for all phylogenetic analyses. </p>

<p>Kimura-2-parameter values 
Inter-and intraspecific distances for each individual dataset 
were calculated using <rs id="software-28" type="software">MEGA</rs> v. <rs corresp="#software-28" type="version-number">4.0</rs> (Tamura et al. 2007) using 
the Kimura-2-parameter (pair-wise deletion) model. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Identification of the ideal DNA barcode </p>

<p>The dataset of the seven test loci was individually tested for 
three factors, namely amplification success, Kimura-2-parame-
ter values (barcode gap) and molecular phylogenetic resolution. </p>

<p>Amplification success 
The amplification success scores of the seven test loci on the 
118 strains varied from 100 % amplification success for both 
ITS and LSU to only 90 % for Cal. The other four test loci (EF-
1α, Act, RPB2 and Btub) gave amplification success scores of 
respectively 97, 98, 99 and 100 % (Table 3). The tested Cal 
primers failed to amplify the quarantine species Pseudocerco­ </p>

<p>spora pini­densiflorae and several other associated Pseudocer­ 
cospora species. Consequently, Cal is considered unsuitable 
as a barcoding locus for this quarantine dataset. </p>

<p>Although it had a very high overall amplification success rate 
(99 %), RPB2 failed to amplify in M. populicola. Although </p>

<p>M. populicola is not a quarantine species, it is very closely 
related and morphologically similar to the quarantine spe-</p>

<p>cies Septoria musiva. This deficit, combined with the fact that 
RPB2 amplification within the dataset was not robust (often 
multiple PCR and/or sequencing runs were needed to get 
good sequencing reads), makes RPB2 unsuitable to serve as a 
barcoding locus for the quarantine dataset. The remaining five 
test loci successfully amplified all quarantine species. </p>

<p>Molecular phylogenies 
General information per locus for the analysis, such as the </p>

<p>number of characters used per dataset and the selected model 
are displayed in Table 3. The trees resulting from the Bayesian </p>

<p>analyses of the seven individual loci showed that most loci have 
difficulty discriminating between closely related Septoria and </p>

<p>Pseudocercospora species. Deciding the sequence difference </p>

<p>Locus 
Primer 
Primer sequence 5' to 3': 
Annealing Orientation 
Reference 
temperature </p>



<p>(°C) </p>

<p>Actin 
ACT-512F 
ATGTGCAAGGCCGGTTTCGC 
52 
Forward 
Carbone &amp; Kohn (1999) 
Actin 
ACT2Rd 
ARRTCRCGDCCRGCCATGTC 
52 
Reverse 
Groenewald et al. (In press) 
Calmodulin 
CAL-235F 
TTCAAGGAGGCCTTCTCCCTCTT 
50 
Forward 
Present study 
Calmodulin 
CAL2Rd 
TGRTCNGCCTCDCGGATCATCTC 
50 
Reverse 
Groenewald et al. (In press) </p>

<p>Translation elongation factor-1α 
EF1-728F 
CAT CGA GAA GTT CGA GAA GG 
52 
Forward 
Carbone &amp; Kohn (1999) </p>

<p>Translation elongation factor-1α 
EF-2 
GGA RGT ACC AGT SAT CAT GTT 
52 
Reverse 
O'Donnell et al. (1998) 
β-tubulin 
T1 
AACATGCGTGAGATTGTAAGT 
52 
Forward 
O'Donnell &amp; Cigelnik (1997) 
β-tubulin 
β-Sandy-R 
GCRCGNGGVACRTACTTGTT 
52 
Reverse 
Stukenbrock et al. (2012) 
RNA polymerase II second largest subunit 
fRPB2-5F 
GAYGAYMGWGATCAYTTYGG 
49 
Forward 
Liu et al. (1999) 
RNA polymerase II second largest subunit 
fRPB2-414R 
ACMANNCCCCARTGNGWRTTRTG 
49 
Reverse 
Quaedvlieg et al. (2011) 
LSU 
LSU1Fd 
GRATCAGGTAGGRATACCCG 
52 
Forward 
Crous et al. (2009a) 
LSU 
LR5 
TCCTGAGGGAAACTTCG 
52 
Reverse 
Vilgalys &amp; Hester (1990) 
ITS 
ITS1 
GAAGTAAAAGTCGTAACAAGG 
52 
Forward 
White et al. (1990) 
ITS 
ITS4 
TCC TCC GCT TAT TGA TAT GC 
52 
Reverse 
White et al. (1990) </p>

<p>Table 2   Primers used in this study for generic amplification and sequencing. </p>

<p>Locus 
Act 
Cal 
EF1 
RPB2 
Btub 
ITS 
LSU </p>

<p>Amplification succes (%) 
98 
90 
97 
99 
100 
100 
100 
Q-amplification succes (%) 
100 
86 
100 
100 
100 
100 
100 
Number of characters 
615 
385 
800 
337 
430 
658 
751 
Unique site patterns 
235 
228 
551 
165 
290 
214 
120 
Sampled trees 
198 
686 
716 
148 
238 
728 
406 
Number of generations (×1000) 150 
642 
857 
123 
168 
433 
272 
Substitution model used 
GTR-I-gamma 
HKY-I-gamma 
HKY-I-gamma 
GTR-I-gamma 
HKY-I-gamma 
GTR-I-gamma 
GTR-I-gamma </p>

<p>Table 3   Amplification success, phylogenetic data and the substitution models used in the phylogenetic analysis, per locus. </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 29, 2012 </p>

<p>Fig. 1   Subset of Bayesian 50 % majority rule consensus trees of the individual test loci incorporating all Mycosphaerellaceae quarantine species (marked in 
grey) and their closest neighbour species as determined from the full-scale individual loci trees containing the complete dataset (available as supplementary 
data in <rs type="software">TreeBASE</rs>). The following abbreviations were used for the genera: T = Teratosphaeria, M = Mycosphaerella, Ph = Phaeophleospora, P = Pseudocer­ </p>

<p>cospora, D = Dothistroma and S = Septoria. A stop rule (set to 0.01) for the critical value for the topological convergence diagnostic was used for the Bayesian 
analyses. The trees were all rooted to Teratosphaeria nubilosa (CPC 12243). The scale bar indicates 0.1 expected changes per site. </p>

<p>TEF1 </p>

<p>0.97 </p>

<p>0.55 </p>

<p>0.78 </p>

<p>0.67 </p>

<p>0.93 </p>

<p>0.81 </p>

<p>0.72 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.99 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Teratosphaeria nubilosa CPC 12243 </p>

<p>L. guatemalensis IMI 281598 </p>

<p>Mycosphaerella sp. CBS 111166 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 871.95 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 133789 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV 243 </p>

<p>L. longispora CPC 17940 </p>

<p>L. longispora CBS 133602 </p>

<p>L. brevispora CBS 133601 </p>

<p>D. septosporum CPC 16798 </p>

<p>D. pini CBS 116484 </p>

<p>M. ellipsoidea CBS 110843 </p>

<p>M. laricis-leptolepidis MAFF 410633 </p>

<p>M. sumatrensis CBS 118501 </p>

<p>P. angolensis CBS 149.53 </p>

<p>P. sphaerulinae CBS 112621 </p>

<p>S. citri CBS 315.37 </p>

<p>S. malagutii CBS 106.80 </p>

<p>M. populicola CBS 100042 </p>

<p>S. musiva CBS 130558 </p>

<p>P. pini-densiflorae CBS 125138 </p>

<p>P. pyracanthigena CPC 10808 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>743/745 nt </p>

<p>744/745 nt </p>

<p>747/747 nt </p>

<p>747/747 nt </p>

<p>737/747 nt </p>

<p>LSU </p>

<p>0.78 </p>

<p>0.73 </p>

<p>0.58 </p>

<p>0.97 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.96 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.74 </p>

<p>0.83 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Teratosphaeria nubilosa CPC 12243 </p>

<p>P. angolensis CBS 149.53 </p>

<p>P. pini-densiflorae CBS 125139 </p>

<p>P. pyracanthigena CPC 10808 </p>

<p>M. endophytica CBS 111519 </p>

<p>M. ellipsoidea CBS 110843 </p>

<p>M. sumatrensis CBS 118501 </p>

<p>M. laricis-leptolepidis MAFF 410633 </p>

<p>P. clematidis CPC 11657 </p>

<p>L. brevispora CBS 133601 </p>

<p>D. pini CBS 116484 </p>

<p>D. septosporum CBS 383.74 </p>

<p>L. guatemalensis IMI 281598 </p>

<p>L. longispora CPC 17940 </p>

<p>L. longispora CBS 133602 </p>

<p>S. malagutii CBS 106.80 </p>

<p>S. cucurbitacearum CBS 178.77 </p>

<p>S. musiva CBS 130558 </p>

<p>M. populicola CBS 100042 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 133789 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 871.95 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV 243 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>488/495 nt </p>

<p>465/471 nt </p>

<p>411/436 nt </p>

<p>473/474 nt </p>

<p>462/466 nt </p>

<p>ITS </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.92 </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.95 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.98 </p>

<p>0.91 </p>

<p>0.99 </p>

<p>0.58 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>0.99 </p>

<p>0.96 1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Teratosphaeria nubilosa CPC 12243 </p>

<p>Ph. eugeniae CPC 15159 </p>

<p>L. brevispora CBS 133601 </p>

<p>P. angolensis CBS 149.53 </p>

<p>M. sumatrensis CBS 118502 </p>

<p>M. laricis-leptolepidis MAFF 410234 </p>

<p>M. ellipsoidea CBS 110843 </p>

<p>S. malagutii CBS 106.80 </p>

<p>S. lycopersici CBS 354.49 </p>

<p>S. musiva CBS 130556 </p>

<p>S. populi CBS 391.59 </p>

<p>P. clematidis CPC 11657 </p>

<p>D. septosporum CBS 543.74 </p>

<p>D. pini CBS 116484 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 871.95 </p>

<p>L. longispora CPC 17940 </p>

<p>P. pini-densiflorae CBS 125138 </p>

<p>P. pyracanthigena CPC 10808 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 133789 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV 243 </p>

<p>L. guatemalensis IMI 281598 </p>

<p>L. longispora CBS 133602 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>310/322 nt </p>

<p>336/337 nt </p>

<p>326/337 nt </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.99 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.73 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.77 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.71 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Teratosphaeria nubilosa CPC 12243 </p>

<p>M. laricis-leptolepidis MAFF 410234 </p>

<p>S. populi CBS 391.59 </p>

<p>S. citri CBS 315.37 </p>

<p>M. ellipsoidea CBS 110843 </p>

<p>P. clematidis CPC 11657 </p>

<p>P. angolensis CBS 149.53 </p>

<p>S. musiva CBS 130556 </p>

<p>M. populicola CBS 100042 </p>

<p>S. lycopersici CBS 354.49 </p>

<p>S. malagutii CBS 106.80 </p>

<p>D. septosporum CBS 383.74 </p>

<p>D. pini CBS 116484 </p>

<p>L. brevispora CBS 133601 </p>

<p>P. pyracanthigena CPC 10808 </p>

<p>P. pini-densiflorae CBS 125138 </p>

<p>L. guatemalensis IMI 281598 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 133789 </p>

<p>L. longispora CPC 17940 </p>

<p>L. longispora CBS 133602 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 871.95 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV 243 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>453/462 nt </p>

<p>371/387 nt </p>

<p>275/316 nt </p>

<p>RPB2 
-alpha </p>

<p>LSU 
ITS </p>

<p>RPB2 
TEF1-alpha </p>



<p>W. Quaedvlieg et al.: DNA barcoding of Mycosphaerella </p>

<p>that constitutes a positive discrimination threshold between spe-
cies is arbitrary. If a threshold value of at least five base pairs </p>

<p>difference is accepted as successfully discriminating between 
species, then only EF-1α discriminated between all tested 
Q-species (Fig. 1). If we set the threshold value to four base </p>

<p>pairs difference, then Cal, EF-1α and Btub successfully discrimi-
nated between all tested species (Fig. 1). The ITS, LSU, Act and </p>

<p>RPB2 loci were unable to discriminate among the various 
Q-species and closely related neighbours. </p>

<p>Kimura-2-parameter values 
The Kimura-2-parameter distribution graphs (Fig. 2) visualise 
the inter- and intraspecific distances per locus corresponding to 
the barcoding gap (Hebert et al. 2003). A good barcoding locus </p>

<p>301/317 nt </p>

<p>300/307 nt </p>

<p>307/315 nt </p>

<p>305/322 nt </p>

<p>307/311 nt </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.95 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.52 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.98 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Teratosphaeria nubilosa CPC 12243 </p>

<p>S. lycopersici CBS 354.49 </p>

<p>S. malagutii CBS 106.80 </p>

<p>M. populicola CBS 100042 </p>

<p>S. musiva CBS 130566 </p>

<p>Mycosphaerella sp. CBS 111166 </p>

<p>D. pini CBS 116484 </p>

<p>D. septosporum CBS 16798 </p>

<p>L. brevispora CBS 133601 </p>

<p>M. laricis-leptolepidis MAFF 410234 </p>

<p>M. sumatrensis CBS 118501 </p>

<p>P. angolensis CBS 149.53 </p>

<p>P. vitis CPC 11595 </p>

<p>L. guatemalensis IMI 281598 </p>

<p>L. longispora CPC 17940 </p>

<p>L. longispora CBS 133602 </p>

<p>P. pini-densiflorae CBS 125138 </p>

<p>P. paraguayensis CBS 111286 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 133789 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 871.95 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV 243 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.72 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.98 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.97 </p>

<p>0.65 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.76 </p>

<p>Teratosphaeria nubilosa CPC 12243 </p>

<p>S. lycopersici CBS 128654 </p>

<p>S. malagutii CBS 106.80 </p>

<p>L. guatemalensis IMI 281598 </p>

<p>L. brevispora CBS 133601 </p>

<p>M. laricis-leptolepidis MAFF 410234 </p>

<p>M. sumatrensis CPC 118501 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 133789 </p>

<p>P. angolensis CBS 149.53 </p>

<p>P. tereticornis CPC 13315 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 871.95 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV 243 </p>

<p>L. longispora CPC 17940 </p>

<p>L. longispora CBS 133602 </p>

<p>M. ellipsoidea CPC 110843 </p>

<p>M. populicola CPC 100042 </p>

<p>S. musiva CBS 130566 </p>

<p>D. pini CBS 116484 </p>

<p>D. septosporum CPC 16798 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>257/261 nt </p>

<p>282/303 nt </p>

<p>287/302 nt </p>

<p>294/304 nt </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.65 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.82 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.83 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.98 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Teratosphaeria nubilosa CPC 12243 </p>

<p>L. guatemalensis IMI 281598 </p>

<p>L. brevispora CBS 1336012 </p>

<p>M. laricis-leptolepidis MAFF 410234 </p>

<p>M. sumatrensis CPC 118501 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 871.95 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV 243 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 133789 </p>

<p>L. longispora CPC 17940 </p>

<p>L. longispora CBS 133602 </p>

<p>D. pini CBS 116484 </p>

<p>D. septosporum CPC 16798 </p>

<p>P. angolensis CBS 149.53 </p>

<p>P. clematidis CPC 11657 </p>

<p>P. pini-densiflorae CBS 125138 </p>

<p>P. paraguayensis CBS 111286 </p>

<p>S. musiva CBS 130566 </p>

<p>M. populicola CBS 100042 </p>

<p>S. malagutii CBS 106.80 </p>

<p>S. lycopersici CBS 354.49 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>535/537 nt </p>

<p>530/540 nt </p>

<p>536/545 nt </p>

<p>294/304 nt </p>

<p>
-tubuli </p>

<p>Calmoduli </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.98 </p>

<p>0.92 </p>

<p>0.99 </p>

<p>Teratosphaeria nubilosa CPC 12243 </p>

<p>L. guatemalensis IMI 281598 </p>

<p>L. brevispora CBS 133601 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV 241 </p>

<p>L. longispora CPC 17940 </p>

<p>L. longispora CBS 133602 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 133789 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV243 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV 242 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV 247 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV 250 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 871.95 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV 248 </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 133791 </p>

<p>L. acicola WPF 4.12 </p>

<p>L. acicola WFP 73.12 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV 246 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV 249 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV 252 </p>

<p>L. acicola LNPV 253 </p>

<p>L. acicola LA773B </p>

<p>L. acicola CBS 133790 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>2x </p>

<p>Lecanosticta guatemalensis </p>

<p>Lecanosticta acicola </p>

<p>Lecanosticta longispora </p>

<p>Lecanosticta brevispora </p>



<p>Fig. 1   (cont.) </p>

<p>β-tubulin 
Actin </p>

<p>Calmodulin </p>

<p>Lecanosticta 7x multigene </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 29, 2012 </p>

<p>should not overlap between inter-and intraspecific Kimura-
2-parameter distances. </p>

<p>The individual test loci showed varying degrees of overlap in 
their Kimura-2-parameter distribution graphs. For example, Act, 
ITS and LSU had much higher overlap than RPB2, EF-1α, Cal 
and Btub, which had minimal overlap. The primary cause for </p>

<p>the existing Kimura-2-parameter overlap within the test loci is 
the low interspecific variation between the Pseudocercospora 
species used in this dataset. Excluding the Pseudocercospora </p>

<p>species from the analyses (data not shown) removed the exist-
ing Kimura-2 overlap for RPB2, EF-1α and Btub, while reduc-
ing it significantly in Act. Excluding these Pseudocercospora </p>

<p>species had only negligible effect on the ITS and LSU Kimura-
2-parameter overlap (i.e. their lack of variation is more univer-
sal). Because Cal had a very low amplification success rate </p>

<p>within the negatively affecting Pseudocercospora species used 
in this dataset, its Kimura-2-parameter graph is subsequently 
much less negatively affected (i.e. no Kimura-2-parameter </p>

<p>Fig. 2   Frequency distribution of Kimura-2-parameter distances for the 
seven test loci. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Actin </p>

<p>Distance </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>0.01 
0.04 
0.07 
0.10 
0.13 
0.16 
0.19 
0.22 
0.25 
0.28 
0.31 
0.34 
0.37 
0.40 
0.43 </p>

<p>Calmodulin </p>

<p>intra </p>

<p>inter </p>

<p>Distance </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>TEF 1-alpha </p>

<p>intra </p>

<p>inter </p>

<p>Distance </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>0.01 
0.04 
0.07 
0.1 
0.13 
0.16 
0.19 
0.22 
0.25 
0.28 
0.31 
0.34 
0.37 
0.4 
0.43 
0.46 </p>

<p>β-tubulin </p>

<p>intra </p>

<p>inter </p>

<p>Distance </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>0.02 
0.06 
0.1 
0.14 
0.18 
0.22 
0.26 
0.3 
0.34 
0.38 
0.42 
0.46 
0.5 
0.54 
0.58 
0.62 </p>

<p>RPB2 </p>

<p>intra </p>

<p>inter </p>

<p>Distance </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>0.01 
0.02 
0.03 
0.04 
0.05 
0.06 
0.07 
0.08 
0.09 
0.10 
0.11 
0.12 
0.13 
0.14 
0.15 
0.16 
0.17 
0.18 
0.19 
0.20 </p>

<p>ITS </p>

<p>intra </p>

<p>inter </p>

<p>Distance </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0.00 
0.01 
0.01 
0.02 
0.02 
0.03 
0.03 
0.04 
0.04 
0.05 
0.05 
0.06 
0.06 
0.07 
0.07 
0.08 
0.08 
0.09 
0.09 
0.10 </p>

<p>LSU </p>

<p>intra </p>

<p>inter </p>

<p>Distance </p>

<p>50 
40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>intra </p>

<p>inter </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>Frequency 
Frequency </p>

<p>Frequency 
Frequency </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. </p>

<p>. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. 
. </p>

<p>β-tubulin </p>

<p>TEF1-alpha </p>

<p>Actin 
Calmodulin </p>

<p>ITS </p>

<p>RPB2 </p>

<p>LSU </p>



<p>W. Quaedvlieg et al.: DNA barcoding of Mycosphaerella </p>

<p>overlap) than the other four protein-coding test loci. The ITS </p>

<p>and LSU loci, either with or without the Pseudocercospora 
dataset, showed a generally large Kimura-2-parameter over-
lap. Based on Kimura-2-parameter values, the RPB2, Btub, </p>

<p>Act, Cal and EF-1α loci are not ideally suited for identifying 
Pseudocercospora species, but have a sufficient barcoding 
gap to successfully serve as the barcoding locus for the other 
species in this dataset. Both ITS and LSU are not suitable to 
serve as barcoding loci for this dataset. </p>

<p>Taxonomy </p>

<p>Dothistroma septosporum (Dorog.) M. Morelet (as 'septos­ 
pora'), Bull. Soc. Sci. Nat. Archéol. Toulon Var. 177: 9. 1968 </p>

<p>Basionym. Cytosporina septospora Dorog., Bull. Trimestriel Soc. Mycol. 
France 27: 106. 1911. 
≡ Septoriella septospora (Dorog.) Sacc. apud Trotter, Syll. Fung. 25: 480. 
1931. 
≡ Septoria septospora (Dorog.) Arx, Proc. Kon. Ned. Akad. Wetensch. C 
86, 1: 33. 1983. 
≡ Dothistroma septosporum var. keniense (M.H. Ivory) B. Sutton, in Sut-
ton, The coelomycetes. Fungi imperfecti with pycnidia acervuli and stromata 
(Kew): 174. 1980. </p>

<p>= Actinothyrium marginatum Sacc., Nuovo Giorn. Bot. Ital. 27: 83. 1920. 
= Dothistroma pini var. lineare Thyr &amp; C.G. Shaw, Mycologia 56: 107. 
1964. </p>

<p>= Dothistroma pini var. keniense M.H. Ivory (as 'keniensis'), Trans. Brit. 
Mycol. Soc. 50: 294. 1967. </p>

<p>= Mycosphaerella pini Rostr., in Munk, Dansk Bot. Ark. 17, 1: 312. 1957. 
≡ Eruptio pini (Rostr.) M.E. Barr, Mycotaxon 60: 438. 1996. </p>

<p>= Scirrhia pini A. Funk &amp; A.K. Parker, Canad. J. Bot. 44: 1171. 1966. 
≡ Mycosphaerella pini (A. Funk &amp; A.K. Parker) Arx, Proc. Kon. Ned. Akad. 
Wetensch. C 86, 1: 33. 1983 (nom. illegit., Art. 53). </p>

<p>Specimens examined. Brazil, São Paulo, Santo Antonio do Pinhal, on 
needles of Pinus pinaster, 1974, T. Namekata, CBS 543.74. -Ecuador, 
on needles of P. radiata, CPC 3779 = CBS 112498. - FrancE, Meurthe et 
Moselle, Arboretum d'Amance, on needles of P. coulteri, 27 Feb. 1970, CBS 
383.74. -ThE nEThErlands, Lunteren, Pinetum Dennenhorst, on needles </p>

<p>of Pinus mugo 'Rostrata', 1 June 2009, W. Quaedvlieg, CPC 16799, CPC 
16798 = CBS 128782. </p>

<p>Notes -Dothistroma septosporum is the causal agent of 
Dothistroma needle blight (Red band disease of pine). This </p>

<p>disease is endemic to virtually all continents and occurs on 
a small number of Pinus and Larix spp. where it can cause 
varying degrees of needle blight depending on humidity and 
temperature. Periods of higher humidity and temperature lead 
to more severe symptoms (Evans 1984, Barnes et al. 2004, 
EPPO 2012). Based on LSU data, isolates of M. pini cluster </p>

<p>with D. pini and M. africana (Crous et al. 2009c, 2011b) and 
a large number of Passalora-like species (Videira et al. un-
publ. data). Because the genus Mycosphaerella is linked to </p>

<p>Ramularia (Verkley et al. 2004, Crous et al. 2009c), the name 
Dothistroma should be used for this clade, and D. septosporum 
for this species. </p>

<p>Lecanosticta acicola (Thüm.) Syd., Ann. Mycol. 22: 400. 
1924. - Fig. 3 </p>

<p>Basionym. Cryptosporium acicola Thüm., Flora 178. 1878. 
≡ Septoria acicola (Thüm.) Sacc., Syll. Fung. 3: 507. 1884. 
≡ Dothistroma acicola (Thüm.) Schischkina &amp; Tzanava, Novosti Sist. 
Nizsh. Rast. 1967: 277. 1967. </p>

<p>= Lecanosticta pini Syd., Ann. Mycol. 20: 211. 1922. 
= Oligostroma acicola Dearn., Mycologia 18: 251. 1926. 
≡ Scirrhia acicola (Dearn.) Sigg., Phytopathology 29: 1076. 1939. </p>

<p>= Systremma acicola (Dearn.) F.A. Wolf &amp; Barbour, Phytopathology 31: 
70. 1941. </p>

<p>= Mycosphaerella dearnessii M.E. Barr, Contr. Univ. Michigan Herb. 9: 
587. 1972. </p>

<p>On PNA: Conidiomata acervular, erumpent, brown, up to 600 
µm diam, opening by means of longitudinal slit. Conidiophores </p>

<p>subcylindrical, densely aggregated, dark brown, verruculose, 
unbranched or branched at base, 1-3-septate, 20-60 × 4-6 
µm. Conidiogenous cells terminal, integrated, subcylindrical, 
brown, verruculose, 8 -20 × 3 -4.5 µm; proliferating sev-
eral times percurrently near apex. Conidia solitary, straight to </p>

<p>curved, subcylindrical with obtusely rounded apex, base trun-
cate, brown, guttulate, verruculose, (0-)3(-8)-septate, base 
2.5-3.5 µm diam, with minute marginal frill, (17-)30-45(-55) 
× (3-)4(-4.5) µm. 
Culture characteristics -Colonies erumpent, spreading, 
with sparse aerial mycelium, surface folded, with smooth, 
lobate margin; colonies reaching 7 mm diam after 2 wk at 
25 °C. On MEA surface olivaceous-grey to iron-grey, reverse 
olivaceous-grey. On PDA surface olivaceous-grey with diffuse 
umber pigment in agar, reverse pale olivaceous-grey. On OA 
surface olivaceous-grey with diffuse umber pigment. </p>

<p>Specimens examined. FrancE, Gironde, Le Teich, on needles of Pinus 
radiata, Apr. 1995, M. Morelet, CBS H-21114, culture CBS 871.95. - liThu-
ania, on needles of Pinus mugo, 2009, S. Markovskaja, A. Kačergius &amp; A. 
Treigienė, CBS H-21109, cultures LA773A &amp; LA773B = CBS 133790. -
MExico, on needles of a Pinus sp., 30 Nov. 2009, M. de Jesús Yáñez­Morales, 
CBS H-21112, cultures CPC 17822 = CBS 133789. - USA, South Carolina, </p>

<p>Aiken, needles of Pinus caribaea, 1876, H.W. Ravenel, IMI 91340, isotype of 
Cryptosporium acicula ex Padova No 1484; Arkansas, Pike City, alt. 700 ft, 
needles of Pinus (palustris or taeda), 24 Apr. 1918, coll. J.A. Hughes, det. 
Sydow, syntype of Lecanostricta pini, BPI 393329, BPI 393331; Florida, Silver 
Spring, needles of Pinus palustris, 27 Feb. 1919, coll. Geo G. Hedgcock, 
det. J. Dearness, type of Oligostroma acicola, BPI 643015; Maine, Bethel, </p>

<p>on needles of P. strobus, 14 June 2011, coll. B. Ostrofsky, det. K. Broders, 
WPF4.12; ibid., on needles of P. strobus, 15 June 2011, coll. B. Ostrofsky, 
det. K. Broders, WPF13.12; New Hampshire, Blackwater, on needles of </p>

<p>P. strobus, 25 June 2011, coll. J. Weimer, det. K. Broders, WPF13.12, epitype 
designated here CBS H-21113, culture ex-epitype CBS 133791. </p>

<p>Notes -Lecanosticta acicola is the causal agent of brown 
spot needle blight on Pinus spp. This disease is endemic 
to North and Central America, the central EPPO region and 
Eastern Asia where it causes yellowish, resin-soaked lesions 
with a prominent orange border on infected needles. As the </p>

<p>disease progresses, lesions coalesce and cause defoliation and 
dieback. Over several years this may lead to branch and tree 
death (Evans 1984, Barnes et al. 2004, EPPO 2012). Based </p>

<p>on LSU data, L. acicola clusters in a unique clade within the 
Mycosphaerellaceae, for which Crous et al. (2009c) chose the 
generic name Lecanosticta (based on L. acicola). The name 
Mycosphaerella dearnessii is no longer applicable, as Myco­ 
sphaerella s.str. is linked to the genus Ramularia (Verkley et 
al. 2004, Crous et al. 2009c). The correct name for this species </p>

<p>should therefore be Lecanosticta acicola. </p>

<p>Lecanosticta brevispora Quaedvlieg &amp; Crous, sp. nov. -
Myco Bank MB801940; Fig. 4 </p>

<p>Etymology. Named after its relatively short conidia. </p>

<p>On PNA: Conidiomata acervular, erumpent, brown, up to 500 
µm diam, opening by means of longitudinal slit. Conidiophores </p>

<p>subcylindrical, densely aggregated, dark brown, verruculose, 
unbranched or branched at base, 0-2-septate, 10-25 × 3-4 
µm. Conidiogenous cells terminal, integrated, subcylindrical, 
brown, verruculose, 5-8 × 2-3 µm; proliferating several times 
percurrently near apex. Conidia solitary, subcylindrical to nar-</p>

<p>rowly fusoid-ellipsoidal, with subobtusely rounded apex, base 
truncate, brown, verruculose, frequently with mucoid sheath, 
(0 -)1-septate, base 2 µm diam, with minute marginal frill, 
(11-)13 -15(-18) × 3(-4) µm. </p>

<p>Culture characteristics -Colonies flat to somewhat erum-
pent, spreading, with sparse aerial mycelium, surface folded, </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 29, 2012 </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Lecanosticta acicola. a -c. Needles with ascomata, asci and ascospores (BPI 643015); d -j. needles with acervuli, conidia and spermatia (BPI 39329); 
k. colony on PDA; l. colony on SNA; m -p. conidia formed on PNA (k -p = CPC 12822). - Scale bars = 10 µm. </p>

<p>c 
b </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>i 
j </p>

<p>k 
m </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>e 
f </p>

<p>o 
p </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Lecanosticta brevispora (CPC 18092). a, b. Conidiogenous cells giving rise to conidia; c -e. conidia (note mucoid sheath). - Scale bars = 10 µm. </p>

<p>c 
b 
d 
a 
e </p>



<p>W. Quaedvlieg et al.: DNA barcoding of Mycosphaerella </p>

<p>with smooth, lobate margin; colonies reaching 15 mm diam after 
2 wk at 25 °C. On MEA surface dirty white with patches of pale </p>

<p>olivaceous-grey, reverse olivaceous-grey in centre, luteous in 
outer region. On PDA surface dirty white in centre, isabelline 
in outer region, and isabelline in reverse. On OA surface dirty 
white with diffuse umber outer region. </p>

<p>Specimen examined. MExico, on needles of a Pinus sp., 24 Oct. 2009, 
M. de Jesús Yáñez­Morales, holotype CBS H-21110, cultures ex-type CPC 
18092 = CBS 133601. </p>

<p>Notes -Lecanosticta brevispora is distinguished from 
the other taxa within the genus by either Btub or EF-1α. Mor-
phologically it is distinct in having much smaller conidia than 
L. acicola; with narrower and less septate conidia than L. ci­ 
nereum (1-3-septate, (12 -)14 -18(-20) × (3.5 -)4 -5 µm, with 
obtuse apices), and L. gloeospora (1-3-septate, (9.5 -)10.5-
14.5(-17) × 3.5 -4.5 µm, with obtuse apices) (Evans 1984). </p>

<p>Lecanosticta guatemalensis Quaedvlieg &amp; Crous, sp. nov. -
MycoBank MB801941; Fig. 5 </p>

<p>Etymology. Named after the country where it was collected, Guatemala. </p>

<p>On PNA: Conidiomata acervular, erumpent, brown, up to 500 
µm diam, opening by means of longitudinal slit. Conidiophores </p>

<p>subcylindrical, densely aggregated, brown, verruculose, un-
branched or branched at base, 0-3-septate, 15-25 × 3-4 µm. </p>

<p>Conidiogenous cells terminal, integrated, pale brown, finely 
verruculose, subcylindrical to narrowly ampulliform, 6 -15 × 
2.5-3.5 µm; proliferating several times percurrently near apex. </p>

<p>Conidia solitary, straight to curved, subcylindrical with subob-
tusely rounded apex, tapering towards truncate base, pale 
brown, finely verruculose, (0 -)1(-2)-septate, base 2 -2.5 µm 
diam, with minute marginal frill, (12-)15-20(-23) × 3(-3.5) µm. </p>

<p>Culture characteristics -Colonies erumpent, spreading, 
with sparse aerial mycelium, surface folded, with smooth, lobate 
margin, except on PDA, where margin is feathery; colonies 
reaching 30 mm diam after 2 wk at 25 °C. On MEA surface dirty </p>

<p>white, reverse cinnamon with patches of isabelline, olivaceous-
grey to iron-grey, reverse olivaceous-grey. On PDA surface and 
reverse olivaceous-grey. On OA surface buff. </p>

<p>Specimen examined. GuaTEMala, on needles of Pinus oocarpa, 28 Apr. 
1983, H.C. Evans, holotype CBS H-21108, culture ex-type IMI 281598. </p>

<p>Notes -Lecanosticta guatemalensis can easily be distin-
guished from the other taxa presently known within the genus 
by either Btub or EF-1α. Morphologically it is distinguished by 
having conidia that are smaller than those of L. acicola, but 
larger than those of L. brevispora. </p>

<p>Lecanosticta longispora Marm., Mycotaxon 76: 395. 2000. -
Fig. 6 </p>

<p>On PNA: Conidiomata acervular, erumpent, brown, up to 600 
µm diam, opening by means of longitudinal slit. Conidiophores </p>

<p>subcylindrical, densely aggregated, brown, verruculose, un-
branched or branched at base, 0 -4-septate, 15 -55 × 3-4 
µm. Conidiogenous cells terminal, integrated, subcylindrical, </p>

<p>brown, verruculose, 10-15 × 2-3.5 µm; proliferating several 
times percurrently near apex. Conidia solitary, subcylindrical </p>

<p>with subobtusely rounded apex, base truncate, brown, gut-
tulate, verruculose, 1-3-septate, base 2 µm diam, with minute 
marginal frill, (16 -)30-45(-50) × 3(-4) µm. </p>

<p>Culture characteristics -Colonies flat, somewhat erum-
pent, spreading, with sparse aerial mycelium, surface folded, 
with smooth, lobate margin on MEA, but feathery on PDA and 
OA; colonies reaching 20 mm diam after 2 wk at 25 °C. On MEA 
surface pale olivaceous-grey with patches of olivaceous-grey. 
On PDA surface olivaceous-grey, reverse iron-grey. On OA </p>

<p>surface dirty white in centre, with patches of pale olivaceous-
grey and olivaceous-grey. </p>

<p>Specimens examined. MExico, Nuevo León, Galeana, Cerro del Potosí, 
on Pinus culminicola, J.G. Marmolejo, 6 June 1993, holotype CFNL; Mi-
choacan State, Zinapecuaro area, on needles of a Pinus sp., 24 Oct. 2009, 
M. de Jesús Yáñez-Morales &amp; C. Méndez-Inocencio, epitype designated here 
CBS H-21111, cultures ex-epitype CPC 17941, CPC 17940 = CBS 133602. </p>

<p>Notes -Lecanosticta longispora is distinguished from the 
other taxa within the genus by either Btub or EF-1α. Morpho-
logically it is similar to L. acicola in conidial length, but distinct 
in that conidia have 1-3 septa (Marmolejo 2000). </p>

<p>Mycosphaerella laricis-leptolepidis Kaz. Itô, K. Satô &amp; M. Ota 
(as 'larici­leptolepis'), Bull. Gov. Forest Exp. Sta. 96: 84. 1957 </p>

<p>Specimens examined. Japan, Yamagata, on needles of Larix leptolepis, 
1954 -1955, K. Itô, MAFF 410081; Hokkaidou, on needles of L. leptolepis, 
1954-1955, T. Yokota, MAFF 410632, MAFF 410633; Yamagata, on needles 
of L. leptolepis, May 1954, N. Ota, MAFF 410234. </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Lecanosticta guatemalensis (IMI 281598). a. Colony sporulating on PDA; b. colony sporulating on SNA; c -e. conidiogenous cells giving rise to conidia; 
f, g. conidia. - Scale bars = 10 µm. </p>

<p>c 
b </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>g 
e 
f </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 29, 2012 </p>

<p>Notes -Mycosphaerella laricis­leptolepidis is the causal 
agent of needle cast of Japanese larch. This disease is en-</p>

<p>demic to East Asia and Japan where it occurs on indigenous 
Larix species. It causes brown necrotic lesions on the needles 
that coalesce, leading to defoliation, stunted growth and even 
host plant death (Kobayashi 1980, EPPO 2012). Based on </p>

<p>LSU data, M. laricis­leptolepidis clusters in a clade described 
as 'Polythrincium' by Crous et al. (2009c). Although the genus 
Mycosphaerella s.str. is distinct from the 'Polythrincium' clade, 
the name M. laricis­leptolepidis is retained until more data 
becomes available. </p>

<p>Pseudocercospora angolensis (T. Carvalho &amp; O. Mendes) 
Crous &amp; U. Braun, Sydowia 55: 301. 2003 </p>

<p>Basionym. Cercospora angolensis T. Carvalho &amp; O. Mendes, Bol. Soc. 
Brot. 27: 201. 1953. 
≡ Phaeoramularia angolensis (T. Carvalho &amp; O. Mendes) P.M. Kirk, 
Mycopathologia 94: 177. 1986. 
≡ Pseudophaeoramularia angolensis (T. Carvalho &amp; O. Mendes) U. Braun, 
Cryptog. Mycol. 20: 171. 1999. </p>

<p>Specimens examined. anGola, Bié, from Citrus sinensis, Dec. 1953, T. de 
Carvalho &amp; O. Mendes, holotype IMI 56597, ex-type CBS 149.53. - ziMBaBwE, </p>

<p>from Citrus sp., March 1993, P.W. Crous, CPC 751 = CBS 244.94; ibid., from 
Citrus sp., 2002, P.W. Crous, CPC 4111 = CBS 112748; ibid., from Citrus 
sp., Sept. 2002, M.C. Pretorius, CBS H-20851, CPC 4118 = CBS 112933; </p>

<p>ibid., from Citrus sp., 2002, P.W. Crous, CPC 4117 = CBS 115645. </p>

<p>Notes -Pseudocercospora angolensis is the causal agent 
of Citrus leaf spot (Citrus fruit spot) and is endemic to sub-
Saharan Africa, where it occurs on all major Citrus species. It </p>

<p>causes greenish yellow lesions on leaves and fruit that coalesce 
and turn necrotic, leading to defoliation or abscission of young 
fruit (Timmer et al. 2000, Crous &amp; Braun 2003, EPPO 2012). </p>

<p>Based on LSU data, P. angolensis clusters within the Pseu­ 
docercospora clade (Pretorius et al. 2003, Crous et al. 2009c, 
In press). As the genus Pseudocercospora is taxonomically </p>

<p>correct and in current use, Pseudocercospora angolensis is 
the correct name for the causal agent of Citrus fruit leaf spot. </p>

<p>Pseudocercospora pini-densiflorae (Hori &amp; Nambu) Deigh-
ton, Trans. Brit. Mycol. Soc. 88: 390. 1987 </p>

<p>Basionym. Cercospora pini­densiflorae Hori &amp; Nambu, Tokyo J. Plant 
Protection 4: 353. 1917. 
≡ Cercoseptoria pini­densiflorae (Hori &amp; Nambu) Deighton, Mycol. Pap. 
140: 167. 1976. </p>

<p>= Mycosphaerella gibsonii H.C. Evans, Mycol. Pap. 153: 61. 1984. </p>

<p>Specimens examined. Japan, from needles of Pinus thunbergii, 1971, 
Sung­Oui Suh, CBS 125139; from needles of Pinus kesiya, 1971, Sung­Oui 
Suh, CBS 125140; from needles of a Pinus sp., 1971, Sung­Oui Suh, CBS 
125138. </p>

<p>Notes -Pseudocercospora pini­densiflorae is the causal 
agent of brown needle blight of pine (Cercospora pine blight). </p>

<p>This disease is mostly endemic to the tropics and subtropics 
in Brazil, sub-Saharan Africa, India, Southeast and East Asia, </p>

<p>where it may infect indigenous Pinus spp. It causes brown 
necrotic lesions on the needles leading to defoliation and is 
especially damaging on young saplings, on which defoliation 
leads to stunted growth and host plant death (Deighton 1987, 
Lewis 1998, EPPO 2012). Based on LSU data, isolates of </p>

<p>P. pini­densiflorae cluster within the Pseudocercospora clade 
(Crous et al. In press), confirming its generic placement as re-
ported by Deighton (1987). The generic name Mycosphaerella </p>

<p>is considered a synonym of the genus Ramularia (Verkley et al. 
2004, Crous et al. 2009c), and therefore Mycosphaerella should </p>

<p>not be used for the pathogen associated with brown needle 
blight of pine. The application of the name Pseudocercospora </p>

<p>pini­densiflorae is therefore correct. </p>

<p>Septoria malagutii E.T. Cline, Mycotaxon 98: 132. 2006 </p>

<p>= Septoria lycopersici var. malagutii Ciccar. &amp; Boerema, Phytopathol. 
Medit. 17: 87. 1978; nom. inval., Art. 37.1 </p>

<p>Specimen examined. pEru, Dep. Junin, Huasahuasi, from a Solanum 
spp., 1975, L.J. Turkensteen, holotype CBS H-18113, culture ex-type CBS 
106.80. </p>

<p>Notes -Septoria malagutii is the causal agent of Septoria 
leaf spot (angular leaf spot) of potato, and is endemic to Central </p>

<p>and South America, where it occurs on leaves of potato and 
other tuber-bearing Solanum species. It causes leaf lesions that 
coalesce until the leaves turn necrotic, leading to defoliation 
and severe losses in crop production (Stevenson 2001, EPPO 
2012). Based on LSU data, S. malagutii clusters within Septoria 
s.str. as defined by Quaedvlieg et al. (2011). The correct name </p>

<p>for this species is therefore Septoria malagutii (Cline &amp; Ross-
man 2006). </p>

<p>Septoria musiva Peck, Ann. Rep. New York State Mus. Nat. 
Hist. 35: 138. 1884 </p>

<p>= Mycosphaerella populorum G.E. Thomps., Phytopathology 31: 246. 1941. 
≡ Davidiella populorum (G.E. Thomps.) Aptroot, in Aptroot, Mycosphae-
rella and its anamorphs: 2. Conspectus of Mycosphaerella: 164. 2006. </p>

<p>Specimens examined. canada, Quebec City, from leaf of Populus del­ 
toides, J. LeBoldus, MAC = CBS 130564, LP3 = CBS 130565, PPP = CBS 
130566, PP = CBS 130567, LPR = CBS 130568, RCL = CBS 130569, SA = 
CBS 130570, RPN = CBS 130571, D2L2 = CBS 130558; Alberta, from leaves </p>

<p>of P. deltoides × P. balsamifera, J. LeBoldus, D2L2 = CBS 130558, NW3L1 = 
CBS 130563, NW2L2 = CBS 130561, D7L2; Alberta, from leaves of hybrid </p>

<p>Populus spp., J. LeBoldus, APC = CBS 130559, APH1 = CBS 130560, APH3 
= CBS 130562. </p>

<p>Fig. 6 Lecanosticta longispora (CPC 17940). a -d. Conidiogenous cells giving rise to conidia; e. conidia. - Scale bars = 10 µm </p>

<p>c 
b 
d 
a 
e </p>



<p>W. Quaedvlieg et al.: DNA barcoding of Mycosphaerella </p>

<p>Name on EPPO A1 and A2 lists 
Name in EU Council Directive 
Valid taxonomic name 
EPPO-listed identification 
Reference 
method </p>

<p>Mycosphaerella populorum / 
Mycosphaerella populorum 
Septoria musiva 
Fruiting body morphology 
Bier (1939), Peace (1962), 
Septoria musiva 
Waterman (1954) </p>

<p>Mycosphaerella gibsonii / 
Cercoseptoria pini­densiflorae 
Pseudocercospora pini­densiflorae 
Fruiting body morphology 
Deighton (1987) 
Cercoseptoria pini­densiflorae </p>

<p>Mycosphaerella laricis­leptolepidis / Mycosphaerella larici­leptolepis 
Mycosphaerella larici­leptolepis 
Fruiting body morphology 
Peace (1962) 
Phyllosticta laricis </p>

<p>Phaeoramularia angolensis 
Cercospora angolensis 
Pseudocercospora angolensis 
Fruiting body morphology 
Kirk (1986) </p>

<p>Septoria lycopersici / 
Septoria lycopersici / 
Septoria malagutii 
Fruiting body morphology 
Cline &amp; Rossman (2006) 
Spegazzini var. malagutii 
Spegazzini var. malagutii </p>

<p>Mycosphaerella dearnessii / 
Scirrhia acicola 
Lecanosticta acicola 
Fruiting body morphology / Barnes et al. (2004) 
Lecanosticta acicola 
ITS-RFLP </p>

<p>Mycosphaerella pini / 
Scirrhia pini 
Dothistroma septosporum 
Fruiting body morphology / 
Evans (1984), Barnes et al. 
Dothistroma septospora </p>

<p>
ITS-RFLP 
(2004) </p>

<p>Table 4   EPPO and EU Council Directive-listed Mycosphaerella species of quarantine importance, their currently advised identification method(s) and their 
valid taxonomic names. Taxonomic names marked in grey have yet to be resolved, therefore the Mycosphaerella name for this species should still be used. </p>

<p>Notes -Septoria musiva is the causal agent of Septoria 
canker of poplar and is endemic to North America and Argen-
tina, where it occurs on all native Populus spp. It causes severe 
cankering and die-back and is especially damaging to hybrid 
Populus species (Bier 1939, Waterman 1954, Ostry 1987, 
Dickmann 2001, EPPO 2012). Based on LSU data, S. musiva </p>

<p>clusters within Septoria s.str. as defined by Quaedvlieg et al. 
(2011). However, ongoing work by Quaedvlieg and Verkley 
(unpubl. data) revealed that S. musiva is located in a cryptic </p>

<p>phylogenetic lineage sister to Septoria s.str., and therefore the 
genus name of this clade might change in the future. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Current EPPO protocols for identifying A1/A2 listed Myco­ 
sphaerella species are based either on ITS-RFLP or fungal 
morphology (Table 4). These approaches each have limitations 
that make them ill-suited as identification tools for plant protec-
tion policy enforcement officers. </p>

<p>Morphology-based techniques are heavily dependent on high-</p>

<p>ly skilled personnel that need to perform time-consuming iden-
tifications of mature, sporulating cultures that often need to be 
grown on specific media and under specific conditions. The 
rapid advance of molecular techniques in recent years has 
underlined the limitations of identifications based solely on 
morphology and/or ITS sequencing. Examples of this are the </p>

<p>new Lecanosticta species that have been described during 
this study. These isolates had previously been identified as </p>

<p>Lecanosticta acicola based both on morphology and limited 
ITS sequencing. The sequencing of additional loci revealed that </p>

<p>L. acicola actually represented a species complex rather than a 
single species. This is yet another example of the tenet of Crous 
&amp; Groenewald (2005) which states "Show me a plant pathogen, 
and I will show you a species complex". Another example was </p>

<p>the Cercospora apii complex, which was considered to be a 
single species based on morphology (Crous &amp; Braun 2003), 
but which was found to represent several species when DNA 
sequencing techniques where employed (Crous et al. 2004b, 
2006a, In press, Groenewald et al. 2005, In press). This inability </p>

<p>to discriminate between cryptic species and their dependency 
on mature, sporulating cultures make morphology-based tech-
niques poorly suited for the rapid and reliable identification of </p>

<p>Mycosphaerella species on trade goods. 
PCR-RFLP-based methods work on a 'hit or miss' principle, </p>

<p>and work well for identifying small groups of well-characterised 
fungal species with little genetic variation. Unfortunately these </p>

<p>methods lack the inherent ability to cope with expanding natural 
variation. Point mutations, insertion or deletion events can lead 
to the loss of restriction sites, making isolates unrecognizable </p>

<p>for PCR-RFLP based methods (Majer et al. 1996). Species of </p>

<p>Mycosphaerella also co-colonize lesions, increasing the chance 
of having a mixed DNA sample if single-spored or hyphal-tipped 
colonies are not used in the assay (Crous &amp; Groenewald 2005). </p>

<p>The use of a DNA barcode or the combination of sequence data 
from two or more discriminatory loci (multi-locus sequence 
typing), for the recognition of species of quarantine importance 
has numerous advantages over previously used techniques. It 
does not require fruiting bodies or a mature life stage, it is fast, 
(relatively) cheap, and can be performed by moderately skilled </p>

<p>personnel and has a high probability of yielding a result, even 
with unknown species. But the single most important aspect 
of DNA barcoding is its ability to identify species (even cryptic 
species) with almost no margin of error, on condition that a large, 
validated, reference database library is available. </p>

<p>One of the main goals of this project was to determine the </p>

<p>most suitable barcoding locus/loci by which to identify Myco­ 
sphaerella-like spp. on the EPPO A1/A2 lists. Hebert et al. 
(2003) proposed that a good barcoding locus should show a </p>

<p>clear separation between the distributions of the mean intra-
and interspecific distances (the so-called 'Kimura-2-parameter 
barcoding gap'). The authors proposed that a locus should have 
a mean inter- / intraspecific distance ratio of at least 10, to be 
suitable as a barcoding locus. The loci tested in this study all 
had mean inter-, intraspecific distance ratios that were much 
higher than 10. Mean distribution ratios varied from 486 for 
LSU to 69 for ITS (Fig. 2). By these criteria alone, these loci 
should all be suitable barcoding loci. Almost all loci showed a </p>

<p>Kimura-2-parameter overlap between their absolute inter-and 
intraspecific distribution frequencies. When the Pseudocer­ </p>

<p>cospora isolates were included in the dataset, the size of this 
absolute inter- and intraspecific distribution frequencies data 
overlap varied from 12 % (LSU), 16 % (ITS), 3.4 % (Act), 
1.2 % (EF-1α), 0.6 % (RPB2), 0.5 % (Btub) and 0 % (Cal), 
respectively. Calmodulin did not overlap simply because this </p>

<p>locus failed to amplify most of the Pseudocercospora spp. that 
are mostly responsible for this Kimura-2-parameter inter-and 
intraspecific distribution overlap in the other loci. </p>

<p>The relatively high Kimura-2-parameter distribution overlap in 
the two nuclear ribosomal DNA loci (ITS and LSU) is caused </p>

<p>by the low natural variation that exists within these loci between 
species of certain genera (in this dataset Septoria spp. and </p>

<p>Pseudocercospora spp. had very low variability between spe-
cies). This difference within the natural variation present within </p>

<p>the different genera in the complete dataset can clearly be seen 
in the ITS and LSU Kimura-2-parameter distribution graphs 
(Fig. 2). These two graphs clearly show multiple 'peaks' that </p>

<p>represent the difference in natural variation within the varying 
genera used in this dataset. </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 29, 2012 </p>

<p>From the three independent barcode suitability tests we can 
conclude that, based on a threshold of at least five base pairs </p>

<p>difference, EF-1α is the best locus to use for DNA barcoding 
of the isolates within this dataset. If we use a threshold of four 
base pairs, then Btub is also suited to serve as DNA barcoding 
locus for this dataset. The other tested loci either have a clear 
amplification problem (Cal) or do not have sufficient resolution 
(Δ ≥ 4nt) (ITS, LSU, Act and RPB2) to discriminate between 
some of the quarantine species and their closest relative spe-
cies (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>Although the EF-1α and Btub loci have the highest species 
discrimination levels for the species used in this dataset, these 
loci have the disadvantage that there is not much reference data 
concerning these loci available in online databases which can 
help identify isolates not used in this dataset. To compensate </p>

<p>for this lack of reference data, we recommend using a combina-
tion of a primary and a secondary locus to give more reliable 
identification results. </p>

<p>The ITS locus is the prime candidate for the primary locus. </p>

<p>ITS has recently been proposed as one of the primary fungal 
barcoding loci (Schoch et al. 2012). ITS sequencing data is </p>

<p>easily obtained and a good starting point to rapidly identify 
genera and sometimes species. If an unknown genus or spe-</p>

<p>cies is not represented in a curated database such as <rs type="software">Q-bank</rs>, 
a <rs type="software">GenBank</rs> blast could be used to supplement these curated 
databases. Mycology has a long history of using ITS data to 
identify fungal species and <rs type="software">GenBank</rs> would thus be a good 
supplementary (although not completely curated) database. </p>

<p>The use of ITS as the primary locus, and if necessary using a 
secondary locus following a molecular decision protocol, would 
be the most stable approach for a reliable identification. This 
is also the identification protocol as it is currently implemented 
in <rs type="software">Q-bank</rs>. </p>

<p>As a secondary barcoding locus to supplement the ITS se-
quence data, either Btub or EF-1α would suffice for this dataset. 
Both loci are easily amplifiable and have a high amplification rate 
(100 % and 97 %, respectively), posses only minimal Kimura-
2-parameter inter- and intraspecific distribution overlap (0.5 % 
and 1.2 %, respectively) and both have 100 % species discri-
mination success rate within the tested dataset (Δ ≥ 4nt). The </p>

<p>use of either Btub or EF-1α may complement each other if 
amplification problems with either locus occur, thus leading 
to a successful identification of an unknown Mycosphaerella 
species of possible quarantine importance. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements We thank the technical staff, Arien van Iperen (cul-
tures) and Marjan Vermaas (photographic plates) for their invaluable assis-
tance. Special thanks go to Prof. Kirk D. Broders (Department of Biological 
Sciences, University of New Hampshire, USA), Dr. Isabelle Munck (USDA 
Forest Service, New Hampshire, USA), Jennifer Weimer (New Hampshire 
Division of Forests &amp; Lands Forest Protection, Blackwater, USA), Dr. Jared 
LeBoldus (Department of Plant Pathology, North Dakota State University, 
USA) and William Ostrofsky (Maine Forest Service, Bethel, USA) for collecting </p>

<p>and providing fresh material of Lecanosticta acicola. We would also like to 
thank Dr. Renaud Ioos (Laboratoire de la Santé des Végétaux, Anses, France) 
for providing DNA samples of Lecanosticta acicola and Dr. Sarah L. Boyer 
(Department of Biology, Macalester College, Saint Paul, USA) for providing 
support with the Kimura-2-parameter distribution graphs. The research lead-
ing to these results has received funding from the European Community's 
Seventh Framework Program (FP7/2007-2013)/grant agreement no. 226482 
(Project: QBOL - Development of a new diagnostic tool using DNA barcoding 
to identify quarantine organisms in support of plant health) by the European 
Commission under the theme 'Development of new diagnostic methods in 
support of Plant Health policy' (no. KBBE-2008-1-4-01). </p>





<p>W. Quaedvlieg et al.: DNA barcoding of Mycosphaerella </p>



</text></tei>