<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3442822" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Despite intense effort of prevention and education, diabetes is 
still rising throughout the world. There are currently no estab-
lished methods to non-invasively assess in vivo the mass and 
function of the native insulin-producing β cells, 
1 which form the 
bulk of the endocrine pancreatic islets, and are central to diabe-
tes pathogenesis. 
2 The non-invasive imaging of these cells, under 
either diabetic conditions or regeneration regimens, 
3,4 would be 
of great value in this context. To date, in vivo visualization of 
pancreatic islets has been demonstrated only after isolation and in 
vitro labeling with either iron-oxide nanoparticles 
5,6 or PET iso-
topes, 
7,8 prior to their transplantation into the liver or muscle. </p>

<p>5-9 </p>

<p>However, such methods will not be easily applicable to the imag-
ing of native islets in situ, due to the unavailability of a proper 
specific ligand that could act in vivo. 
10 One promising alternative 
is manganese-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging (MEMRI). 
Recent studies have shown that the intensity of the MRI pancreas 
signal can be enhanced by infusion of manganese, 
10-13 a cation 
which mimics the behavior of Ca 
2+ , an essential regulator of insu-
lin secretion. </p>

<p>14,15 </p>

<p>The main hypothesis of this study was that Mn 
2+ and Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>also compete during secretion of human insulin, enhancing 
the contrast of MR images in a way dependent on β cell func-
tion. Would that be the case, the MRI of β cells from nor-
moglycemic patients would be expected to be more enhanced </p>

<p>A non-invasive method to image the mass and/or function of human pancreatic islets is needed to monitor the 
progression of diabetes, and the effect of therapeutic interventions. As yet, no method is available for this purpose, 
which could be applied to in situ human islets. Animal and in vitro studies have documented that manganese infusion 
could improve the magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the endocrine pancreas. Here, we have tested whether a similar 
approach could discriminate diabetic and non-diabetic patients. In vitro, human isolated islets readily incorporated 
manganese. In vivo, 243 manganese-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging (MEMRI) examinations were reviewed, 
including 41 examinations which were run on 24 patients with type 2 diabetes and 202 examinations which were run 
on 119 normoglycemic patients. The results show that MEMRI discriminates type 2 diabetics from non-diabetic patients, 
based on the signal enhancement of pancreas. </p>

<p>Pancreatic magnetic resonance imaging after 
manganese injection distinguishes type 2 
diabetic and normoglycemic patients </p>

<p>Diomidis Botsikas, 
1 Sylvain Terraz, 
1 Laurent Vinet, 
2 Smaragda Lamprianou, 
2 Christoph D. Becker, 
1 Domenico Bosco, </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Paolo Meda 
2 and Xavier Montet </p>

<p>1, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Radiology; Geneva University Hospital; Geneva, Switzerland; 
2 Department of Cell Physiology and Metabolism; Geneva University; Geneva, Switzerland; 
3 Department of Surgery; Geneva University Hospital; Geneva, Switzerland </p>

<p>Keywords: diabetes, MRI, MEMRI, manganese, imaging </p>

<p>by manganese than that of β cells from patients with type 2 
diabetes. 
As yet, however, whether the MEMRI approach may be use-
ful to monitor the human endocrine pancreas in vivo has not yet 
been shown. To address this question, we evaluated the man-
ganese uptake by islets isolated from normoglycemic individu-
als. We then compared by MEMRI the in vivo enhancement of 
pancreas, liver, muscle and spleen signals in type 2 diabetic and 
normoglycemic patients. Using this approach, we further com-
pared subsets of patients with type 2 diabetes, differing by age, 
BMI and therapeutic requirement of insulin. Eventually, we 
investigated subsets of normoglycemic and diabetic patients that 
received gadolinium-DTPA, an extra-cellular contrast agent, 
which allows for evaluation of blood volume/perfusion 
16 in the 
pancreas. The data indicate that the MEMRI of pancreas non-
invasively distinguishes normoglycemic and type 2 diabetic 
patients, that this distinction is organ specific, and does not result 
from a different blood supply of the pancreas. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>In vitro experiments. To test whether manganese was uptaken 
by human islets, in sufficient amounts to enhance the MRI 
signal, we incubated islets isolated from normoglycemic organ 
donors in the absence or presence of Mn 
2+ , prior to MRI. MRI 
showed that the signal to noise ratio (SNR) increased by 159% </p>

<p>© 2012 Landes Bioscience. </p>

<p>Do not distribute. </p>

<p> 
Islets 
Volume 4 Issue 3 </p>

<p>evaluation of MR images of pancreas obtained after injection of 
gadolinium-DTPA, revealed a similar enhancement of pancreas 
in both normoglycemic and type 2 diabetic patients (42 ± 20% 
vs. 43 ± 15%, p = 0.87). 
To assess whether the MEMRI changes were specific to pan-
creas, we further evaluated the signals of different other insulin-
dependent and insulin-independent organs in the very same set of 
patients. Contrasting with the pancreas data, the Mn 
2+ -induced 
enhancement of the liver signal was similar (Fig. 4A) in normo-
glycemic (76.1 ± 2.2) and diabetic patients, whether requiring 
insulin therapy (53.6 ± 15.1) or not (82.8 ± 11; p = 0.16; Fig. 4A). 
This was also the case for the muscle (6.5 ± 9.0, 7.5 ± 9.1 and 7.5 ± 
9.1 in normoglycemic patients, type 2 diabetics with and without 
insulin therapy, respectively; p = 0.75) and spleen signals (18.4 ± 
7.0, 22.4 ± 6.7 and 21.0 ± 4.5 in normoglycemic patients, type 2 
diabetics with and without insulin therapy, respectively; p = 0.52) 
(Fig. 4B and C, respectively). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study provides evidence that manganese enhances the 
MRI signal of pancreas in both non-diabetic and type 2 dia-
betic patients. It further documents that this enhancement is 
significantly different in the two groups of patients, and in the 
latter group, correlates with their BMI but not their age or insu-
lin requirement. Given that the administration of gadolinium-
DTPA similarly enhanced the pancreas signal in non-diabetic 
and type 2 diabetic patients, the enhancement of the MEMRI 
signal is unlikely to be significantly affected by differences in 
the blood perfusion of pancreas of the two groups of patients. 
Furthermore, the enhancement of the MEMRI signal of liver, 
muscle and spleen enhancement was also similar in the three 
very same groups of individuals, stressing the pancreas specific-
ity of the observed changes. The findings indicate that MEMRI 
may be a helpful imaging strategy for investigating the evolution 
of diabetic alterations, and their potential modulation during 
therapy. </p>

<p>11-13 </p>

<p>The approach has several advantages compared with alterna-
tive methods 
10,18 in which isolated islets are loaded with either 
iron oxide nanoparticles (for MRI) or positron emitting radio-
isotopes (for PET/SPECT). 
18 First, MEMRI can be used for the 
repeated analysis of the same pancreas, which will be required 
for the prospective monitoring of patients. This repeated moni-
toring, which was performed in 25% of the cases studied here, 
is not presently possible with nanoparticles, and may be unsafe 
using the high energy positron-emitting radioisotopes that are 
required to obtain a PET labeling of the small pancreatic islets. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>While each labeling method has its own safety problems, 
10,18 the 
fact that manganese is handled by pancreatic islets like Ca 
2+ , </p>

<p>15,21 </p>

<p>disappears from the plasma in a few hours 
22 and from most tis-
sues within days, 
23 and is already frequently used in clinical 
MRI, makes its repeated use on the same patient more conceiv-
able. Second, in the absence of a β cell-or islet-specific probe 
suitable for targeted imaging, MEMRI may provide a higher 
and more specific enhancement of the pancreatic endocrine tis-
sue than of other pancreatic and non-pancreatic compartments. </p>

<p>(n = 3, p = 0.0003) after exposure to manganese (Fig. 1). An 
increase in SNR was also observed in the islets isolated from 
the single patient with type 2 diabetes we could access (data not 
shown). The data show that the MEMRI signal of pancreas is 
at least partly due to the uptake of manganese by the endocrine 
islets. 
In vivo study. To test whether the MEMRI of pancreas can 
distinguish normoglycemic and type 2 diabetic patients, we 
retrospectively analyzed the abdominal recording of MEMRI 
examinations, which had been performed in our institution for 
a variety of clinical conditions (Table 1). In most cases, these 
examinations were not purposely tailored for pancreas imaging. 
Based on the selection criteria which are given in the method 
section, including the obligatory requirement for each patient of 
a MRI before and after manganese infusion, we could include 
in the study 119 normoglycemic patients, who totalized 202 
MEMRI examinations and 24 patients with type 2 diabetes, who 
totalized 41 examinations (some of the patients underwent twice 
the imaging protocol). 
In all cases, the MRI signal of pancreas was enhanced after 
Mn-DPDP infusion (Fig. 2A-D). However, this enhancement 
was higher (p = 0.002) in normoglycemic controls (39.7 ± 1.5%) 
than in patients with type 2 diabetes (Fig. 2E). In the latter group 
there was no significant difference between the patients without 
insulin therapy (29.4 ± 3.7%) and those who required it (19.02 
± 6.0%) (Fig. 2E). The MEMRI enhancement of pancreas was 
similar whichever the age of the diabetic patients (Fig. 3B), and 
was inversely correlated with their BMI (Fig. 3A). The parallel </p>

<p>Figure 1. Manganese is uptaken by human islets. T1-weighted mag-
netic resonance images of pellets of human islets from non-diabetic 
multi-organ donors before (A) and after a 30 min exposure to MnCl 2 (B). 
(C) Manganese significantly enhanced the MRI signal to noise ratio (16.0 
± 1.3 vs. 41.6 ± 0.7, p = 0.0003). Data are mean + SEM signal-to-noise 
ratio. </p>

<p>© 2012 Landes Bioscience. </p>

<p>Do not distribute. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com 
Islets </p>

<p>
MRI conditions, which, for most patients were not optimized 
for pancreas imaging, is consistent with the changes in β cell 
mass that are anticipated from pathology studies in the European 
population. </p>

<p>28,29 </p>

<p>The retrospective nature of the study allowed for the analysis 
of only a limited number of patients, under conditions, which 
most likely, were not ideal for pancreas imaging, and prevented 
any functional assessment of β cell function. In spite of these 
limitations, and specifically the lack of direct data about the mass 
of β cells (some patients are still alive, and the pancreas was not 
sampled from those that passed away) and their function (beside 
the very indirect evaluation of blood glucose levels), the data 
document that MEMRI does non-invasively distinguish, under 
double blind conditions, the pancreas of diabetic and non-dia-
betic individuals. Further studies should now test whether the 
observed changes in the MRI signal specifically reflect an altera-
tion in the mass/function of β cells or are influenced by other </p>

<p>Thus, nanoparticles persist in the pancreas outside the endocrine 
islet cells, also when inflammation is present 
6,24,25 and radioiso-
topic PET labeling has a spatial resolution that largely exceeds 
the small islet sizes. Furthermore, both nanoparticles and PET 
ligands substantially label the exocrine pancreas as well as nearby 
organs 
18,26 due to the expression of the targeted molecules in 
multiple cell types. At least experimentally, MEMRI allows for 
the quantitative detection of individual islets, and their changes 
in a model of diabetes. 
13 Third, in the context of type 2 diabe-
tes, in which both the function and likely the mass of β cells is 
altered, MEMRI may provide information about both events, as 
manganese is uptaken by β cells as a function of their ability to 
release insulin in response to glucose. 
12-15 The inverse correlation 
observed between BMI and the MEMRI signal of pancreas is 
consistent with this view, given that BMI relates to residual β 
cell function. 
27 In this respect, the 15-30% loss of pancreas sig-
nal enhancement we evaluated in type 2 diabetic patients, under </p>

<p>Table 1. MRI indication </p>

<p>Targeted organ 
MRI indication 
No. of patients </p>

<p>Normoglycemic 
Type 2 diabetic </p>

<p>Liver </p>

<p>ear, nose and throat tumors 
2 
0 </p>

<p>melanoma 
2 
0 </p>

<p>small cell lung carcinoma 
1 
0 </p>

<p>non small cell lung carcinoma 
6 
0 </p>

<p>breast cancer 
7 
0 </p>

<p>hepatocellular carcinoma 
6 
0 </p>

<p>hepatic nodule 
0 
2 </p>

<p>hepatic abcess 
1 
0 </p>

<p>gallbladder carcinoma 
1 
0 </p>

<p>cholangiocarcinoma 
6 
1 </p>

<p>ampulloma 
2 
0 </p>

<p>esophagus tumor 
1 
0 </p>

<p>gastric adenocarcinoma 
4 
0 </p>

<p>gastrointestinal stromal tumor 
3 
0 </p>

<p>duodenal carcinoma 
1 
0 </p>

<p>terminal ileon carcinoid 
2 
0 </p>

<p>colorectal cancer 
45 
14 </p>

<p>pancreatic carcinoma 
4 
2 </p>

<p>retroperitoneal sarcoma 
1 
0 </p>

<p>nephroblastoma 
3 
0 </p>

<p>urothelial tumor 
3 
1 </p>

<p>ovarian cancer 
3 
0 </p>

<p>endometrial cancer 
1 
0 </p>

<p>testicular cancer 
1 
0 </p>

<p>diffuse non differentiated cancer 
0 
1 </p>

<p>diffuse neuroendocrine tumor 
1 
0 </p>

<p>multiple myeloma 
1 
0 </p>

<p>Biliary tract 
fistules, leaks, post-traumatic and post-surgery indications 
10 
2 </p>

<p>Pancreas 
carcinoma 
1 
1 </p>

<p>Total number of patients 
119 
24 </p>

<p>© 2012 Landes Bioscience. </p>

<p>Do not distribute. </p>

<p> 
Islets 
Volume 4 Issue 3 </p>

<p>ml, in the presence or absence of 12.5 μM manganese chloride. 
After three washings in RPMI-1640 medium without manga-
nese chloride, the islets were imaged in a clinical 1.5T Philips 
MR system (Philips Achieva, Philips Medical System), using a 
T1-weighted gradient echo sequence, with an inversion time of 
300 msec. The MRI signal to noise ratio (SNR) was defined as 
signal intensity (SI) of the islet pellet divided by the standard 
deviation of the noise. 
Patient study design. After obtaining the approval by the 
human ethic committee of our institution, we retrospectively 
analyzed the data from all patients who were addressed for 
MEMRI at our institution, for a variety of clinical conditions 
(Table 1). The cohort comprised 24 type 2 diabetics (who pro-
vided for 41 MEMRI) and 119 normoglycemic patients (who 
provided for 202 MEMRI). Patients were included in the dia-
betic group based on the filed medical history and clinical data 
(basal fed glycemia, HbA 1c levels). The 24 diabetic men were 
aged 51-85 y (mean 67 ± 7), and featured a mean BMI of 26 
± 6, an average basal fed glycemia of 8.3 ± 2.2 mmol/l, and an 
HbA 1c of 7.0 ± 0.8%. Of the 24 diabetic patients, seven were 
under insulin therapy, and were handled separately. The control 
group comprised 41 men and 78 women, aged 14-88 y (mean 
60 ± 14), who featured a mean BMI of 24 ± 5, and a basal fed 
glycemia of 6.0 ± 1.0 mmol/l. The HbA 1c levels of most of these 
normoglycemic patients were not available. </p>

<p>concurrent alterations. Nevertheless, the differential uptake of 
Mn 
2+ observed between non-diabetic and diabetic patients is in 
favor of imaging changes of mass/function of β cells. 
Moreover, our findings that the enhancement of the liver, 
spleen and muscle signal was similar in the two groups of 
patients reinforce the pancreatic specificity of the method. This 
is further supported by the observation that the non-specific 
extracellular gadolinium chelate, which also enhanced the pan-
creas signal, did not differentiate the pancreas signal of non-
diabetic and diabetic patients. Together, these findings indicate 
that MEMRI reveals changes that may be related to altered 
mass/function of the islet cells. Further developments of the 
technique, to specifically tailor it to the endocrine pancreas 
conditions, should now attempt at distinguish these two, likely 
coincidental β cell changes. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>In vitro islet testing. Human islets from multi-organ donors 
were obtained thanks to the European Consortium for 
Islet Transplantation (ECIT). Islets were isolated as per the 
Edmonton protocol. 
30 Three thousands islet equivalents isolated 
from control donors (n = 3) were imaged after a 30 min incu-
bation in RPMI-1640 medium supplemented with 10% fetal 
calf serum, 100 IU penicillin/ml and 100 μg streptomycin/ </p>

<p>Figure 2. The MRI signal enhancement of pancreas is enhanced by manganese. T1-weighted magnetic resonance imaging showing the pancreas (area 
limited by the dashed line) before (A and C) and 20 min after Mn-DPDP infusion (B and D) of a normoglycemic (A and B) and a type 2 diabetic patient 
(C and D). In both patients, the MRI signal of pancreas was enhanced by the manganese infusion. (E) This enhancement was significantly higher in 
normoglycemic than in type 2 diabetic patients. Data are mean + SEM signal enhancement, expressed as % of the signal evaluated prior to the manga-
nese infusion. </p>

<p>© 2012 Landes Bioscience. </p>

<p>Do not distribute. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com 
Islets </p>

<p>
We also analyzed the data from another group of 15 nor-
moglycemic and 15 type 2 diabetic patients, who were studied 
by MRI 1 min after injection of 0.1 mmol/kg gadolinium-
DTPA. 
MRI protocols. 243 MRI sessions involving a T1-weighted 
gradient echo sequence (GRE), acquired before and 20 min 
after a 2-3 ml/min infusion of 0.5 ml/kg b.w. manganese dipyr-
idoxal diphosphate (Mn-DPDP, Teslascan </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, GE-Amersham), 
were analyzed. All MRI sessions were realized at 1.5T, using 
either a Philips MR system (Philips Achieva, Philips Medical 
System) or a Siemens MR system (Siemens Magnetom Espree, 
Siemens AG). 
For imaging the isolated islets, we used a surface coil of 47 
mm diameter, and a 3D T1-weighted GRE with the following 
parameters: TR = 15.9 ms, TE = 9 ms, TI = 300 ms, flip angle = 
45°, number of averages = 4, field of view = 6 cm, matrix of 204 x 
204, slice thickness = 0.3 mm. 
For imaging of the patients, we used a body coil, and a 
T1-weighted GRE with the following parameters: TR = ~4 msec, 
TE = ~2 msec, flip angle = 10°, number of averages = 1, field of 
view = ~375 x 297 mm (depending on the size of the abdomen), 
matrix of 188 x 147, slice thickness = 4 mm. 
The analysis of the recorded images was performed by two 
readers (XM and DB), who were blinded to all clinical informa-
tion concerning the patients. To this end, a region of interest, 
which avoided major vessels, ducts, image inhomogeneities and 
artifacts, was defined in the pancreas, liver, spleen and muscle for </p>

<p>Figure 3. The MEMRI enhancement of pancreas correlated with the 
BMI of diabetic patients. The pancreas enhancement due to Mn 
2+ was 
inversely correlated with the BMI (A), but not the age of the diabetic 
patients (B), as assessed by Pearson's correlation. </p>

<p>Figure 4. The MEMRI signal of liver (A), muscle (B) and spleen 
(C) does not differentiate normoglycemic patients from diabetic 
patients. The signal enhancement of liver (A), muscle (B) and spleen 
(C) was not statistically different between normoglycemic and type 
2 diabetic patients. Data are mean + SEM signal enhancement, 
expressed as % of the signal evaluated prior to the manganese 
infusion. </p>

<p>evaluation of the MR signal. The signal enhancement (SI) was 
calculated as follows: SI = SI post -SI pre /SI pre , where SI pre and SI post 
are the signal intensities before and 20 min after the infusion of 
Mn-DPDP, respectively. </p>

<p>© 2012 Landes Bioscience. </p>

<p>Do not distribute. </p>

<p> 
Islets 
Volume 4 Issue 3 </p>

<p>Disclosure of PotentialConflicts of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest were disclosed. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Our teams are supported by grants from the Swiss National 
Science 
Foundation 
(310030-141162, 
310000-109402, 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Prism</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 5.0d</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-date">2010</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs><rs id="software-1" type="software">Statistica</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 8</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Statsoft Inc.</rs></p>

</text></tei>