<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3448160" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Citation Wiesner DL, et al. 2012. Cryptococcal genotype influences immunologic response and human clinical outcome after meningitis. mBio 3(5):e00196-12. biased immune responses to cryptococcal infections could be at 
higher risk for poor clinical outcomes. 
Numerous relationships between pathogen genotypes and vir-
ulence have been demonstrated in bacterial and viral pathogens 
(15-18) as well as between Cryptococcus gattii genotypes and vir-
ulence in the outbreak on Vancouver Island, British Columbia, 
Canada (19, 20), suggesting that cryptococcal strain variation 
could play a role in determining the clinical outcome. However, 
clinical outcomes in cryptococcosis are multifactorial-both the 
pathogen and the host contribute to disease. Epidemiological 
characteristics of Cryptococcus neoformans, virulence-associated 
phenotypic traits, and host immune responses have been studied 
as individual factors influencing the outcome of cryptococcosis, 
but none of these studies have found associations between cryp-
tococcal strain variation and human disease (21, 22). We propose 
that exogenous (pathogen) and endogenous (host) factors con-
tribute concurrently to the pathophysiology of cryptococcosis. 
Consequently, an integrated investigation of the cryptococcal 
strain and the host immune response could provide valuable in-
sight into cryptococcal pathogenesis and potentially lead to cus-
tom therapies that target the host-pathogen interface. Thus, we 
hypothesize that differences in strain genotype, as determined by 
multilocus sequence typing (MLST), and strain phenotype could 
be responsible for disease severity and clinical outcome in pa-
tients. To test these hypotheses, we analyzed cryptococcal strains 
and clinical data from a cohort of ART-naive Ugandans with AIDS 
and CM. We report that the genotype of the infecting strain is 
associated with the type of immune response and clinical out-
come. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Cohort demographic characteristics. A prospective cohort of 199 
HIV-infected, ART-naive Ugandans with their first episode of CM 
was recruited at Mulago Hospital, Kampala, Uganda, over a 26-
month enrollment period between 2006 and 2009 in order to 
study immune reconstitution inflammatory syndrome and other 
clinical outcomes after ART initiation (3). Of these patients, 111 
patients had culture-positive CSF samples stored for subsequent 
genotypic analysis. Detailed clinical and demographic informa-</p>

<p>tion from 98 of these patients were used for comparison of strain 
genotype to clinical outcome (Table 1). 
Cryptococcal strain genotypes. Cryptococcal strains were col-
ony purified from a total of 140 CSF specimens from the 111 
patients with their first episode of CM. Genotypes of the Ugandan 
clinical (UgCl) strains were determined by MLST according to a 
consensus scheme that included eight loci: CAP59, GPD1, IGS1, 
LAC1, PLB1, SOD1, URA5, and TEF1 (23). 
Eight isolates could not be fully genotyped, as some loci 
were recalcitrant to PCR amplification upon sequencing with 
either legacy (24) or consensus (23) MLST primers at 1 
MLST locus. The loci from these nongenotyped strains showed 
the highest similarity to Cryptococcus neoformans var. neofor-
mans (n 4) or var. grubii (n 4) (data not shown). None of 
the strains were Cryptococcus gattii based on sequencing or 
CGB agar screening. PCR serotyping showed combinations of 
both C. neoformans var. grubii and C. neoformans var. neofor-
mans gene alleles in the strains (data not shown). Taken to-
gether, these data suggest the eight strains are C. neoformans 
var. grubii/neoformans "hybrids." 
Colony purification allowed us to analyze the greatest number 
of clinical isolates from the broadest spectrum of patients, but 
coinfection of patients with multiple strains could confound this 
approach (25). Thus, multiple isolates were collected from 24 pa-
tients. In 20 of the 24 patients, no differences in MLST alleles 
between isolate pairs were observed; however, multiple genotypi-
cally distinct isolates were identified in 4 patients (17%), suggest-
ing coinfection with 2 strains. Subsequent analyses included sin-
gle isolates from clonally infected patients as well as both isolates 
from patients infected with two genotypes. 
Sequences for each MLST locus were compared and reduced to 
nonredundant clonal sets, and a maximum parsimony analysis of 
the sequences at individual loci was performed (see Fig. S1 in the 
supplemental material). Only one strain showed a polymorphism 
at the URA5 locus. The SOD1 locus was completely clonal in our 
population. Locus allele identifiers for each strain were combined 
to produce a strain sequence type (ST) that serves as a represen-
tation of the strain genotype. A total of 15 sequence types were 
identified (Table 2). The sequence types consisted of 4 clonal clus-</p>

<p>TABLE 1 Patient demographic characteristics and clinical parameters </p>

<p>Demographic characteristic 
or clinical parameter </p>

<p>Mean SD (n) a </p>

<p>P value c </p>

<p>Total 
subjects b </p>

<p>Patients in each burst group </p>

<p>Burst 1 
(78 isolates) </p>

<p>Burst 2 
(18 isolates) </p>

<p>Burst 3 
(10 isolates) </p>

<p>Hybrid 
(6 isolates) </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
35 8 (63) 
35 9 (43) 
37 8 (9) 
35 4 (9) 
33 4 (3) 
0.95 
Sex (no. of males/no. of females) 
51/32 (83) 
38/20 (58) 
7/7 (14) 
7/3 (10) 
1/2 (3) 
0.45 
Death (%) d 
78 (98) 
80 (71) 
80 (15) 
38 (8) 
100 (6) 
0.05 
CD4 count (no. of cells/l) 
26 24 (39) 
25 23 (29) 
29 31 (5) 
25 28 (6) 
NA 
0.94 
Viral load (log 10 no. copies/l) 
5.1 0.7 (34) 
5.0 0.8 (26 ) 
5.1 0.5 (3) 
5.3 0.4 (6) 
NA 
0.72 
CSF opening pressure (mm H 2 O) 
339 160 (56) 
364 174 (36) 
268 117 (11) 
360 134 (7) 
225 64 (2) 
0.25 
No. of CFU (log 10 CFU/ml) 
4.3 1.1 (64) 
4.4 1.0 (45) 
4.0 1.5 (10) 
4.0 0.9 (8) 
4.2 0.1 (3) 
0.53 
CRAG titer (log 2 titer) 
11.7 2.1 (56) 
11.8 1.9 (43) 
10.8 3.3 (8) 
12.1 0.8 (5) 
11.3 (1) 
0.61 </p>

<p>a Values indicated in the table are means SD for all demographic characteristics and clinical parameters except Sex, which indicates males/females, and Death, which shows the 
percentage of patients that died. n indicates the number of patients. NA, not available. 
b Complete data were not available for all patients. Total subjects indicates the mean SD of patients, indicated by n, for which data were available. 
c P values were calculated by one-way ANOVA or Fisher's exact test as appropriate. 
d Pairwise Fisher's exact test comparisons showed that patients infected with Burst group 3 isolates had significantly lower mortality than patients infected with Burst group 1 
isolates (P 0.02) or the hybrid isolates (P 0.03). </p>

<p>Wiesner et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
September/October 2012 Volume 3 Issue 5 e00196-12 </p>

<p>ters and 11 singleton sequence types (Fig. 1A). The largest clonal 
cluster (UgCl001) contained 74 isolates. The other clonal clusters 
contained 14, 5, and 3 isolates (represented in Table 2 by UgCl021, 
UgCl011, and UgCl057, respectively). 
A single representative strain for each sequence type was used 
to analyze evolutionary relationships between the UgCl strains 
and further stratify the isolates into distinct groups. Phylogenetic 
analyses, including maximum parsimony, maximum likelihood, 
and bootstrap analyses, were performed on the concatenated se-
quences of MLST loci for the 15 identified sequence types. Maxi-
mum parsimony analysis was performed with inclusion of refer-
ence strain sequences for the major C. neoformans var. grubii VNI, 
VNII, and VNB clades to place the resulting tree in the context of 
previously established evolutionary relationships (Fig. 1B). Max-
imum parsimony and maximum likelihood analyses produced 
comparable results (not shown). To further stratify the isolates, an 
MLST-specific Burst clustering analysis was performed (26). The 
Burst clustering hypothesized a division of the 15 sequence types 
into three nonredundant Burst groups and four more distant sin-
gleton strains (Fig. 1C). The more highly stratified three Burst 
groups were used in subsequent clinical and phenotypic analyses. 
For the 4 patients with multiple infections, 2 patients had infec-
tions with strains in the same Burst group, and thus the demo-
graphic and clinical comparisons were not repeated. Two of the 
patients had infections with strains in different Burst groups. In 
these instances, the clinical and geographic data from the two 
patients were included in the analysis of both respective Burst 
groups. 
Patient clinical outcome. Having identified three distinct 
Burst groups and a hybrid group, we next asked whether crypto-
coccal genotype could predict disease severity. Patient 1-year clin-
ical outcome data were available for 98 of the 111 culture-positive 
patients (Table 1). The overall 1-year mortality rate was 78%. 
Patients infected with Burst group 1 and 2 strains had higher mor-
tality than Burst group 3 strains (79% [68/86] versus 38% [3/8] 
[P 0.05 by the chi-square test]). Survival curves showed that 
patients infected with Burst group 3 strains lived longer than pa-
tients infected with the other genotypes (Fig. 2, P 0.007 by the 
log rank test). None of the six patients infected with hybrid strains 
survived the infection. No other clinical or demographic param-
eter monitored, including CD4 count and HIV-1 viral load, was 
associated with genotype. 
Environmental exposure to specific cryptococcal strains in 
particular geographic regions is a possible explanation for the as-
sociation between isolate genotype and patient death. The major-
ity of patients lived in parishes within the Kampala district in 
Uganda, but no geographic clusters of patients infected with sim-
ilar genotypes was observed (see Fig. S2 in the supplemental ma-
terial). 
Cryptococcal strain phenotypes. At least three major viru-
lence factors are important for cryptococcal pathogenesis: mating 
type, melanin, and polysaccharide capsule (21, 22). Mating type 
determination and in vitro assays of melanin and capsule produc-
tion were performed to identify any associations with genotype 
that could explain the differences in lethality. 
The mating type of the strain was determined by PCR using 
STE20 primers specific for mating type and serotype. The vast 
majority of the C. neoformans var. grubii strains were mating type 
(A); only two were mating type a (aA). Because only 2 out of 
132 C. neoformans var. grubii strains were mating type a, sufficient </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Ugandan clinical isolate sequences and sequence types </p>

<p>Burst </p>

<p>UgCl 
isolate b </p>

<p>Nucleotide a 
at the indicated position of the concatenated sequences in the UgCl isolate: </p>

<p>ST c </p>

<p>CAP59 GPD1 </p>

<p>IGS1 </p>

<p>LAC1 </p>

<p>PLB1 </p>

<p>TEF1 </p>

<p>URA5 </p>

<p>458 
527 563 576 683 778 915 956 1220 1303 1324 1388 1401 1459 1481 1482 1487 1548 1552 1688 1706 1708 1725 1826 1972 2014 2132 2273 2331 2355 2357 2422 2820 2832 3266 3430 3451 3933 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>001 </p>

<p>T 
T C T C G T C T </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>T 
T 93 </p>

<p>107 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. 
. T . </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>91 </p>

<p>036 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>94 </p>

<p>037 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C . </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>074 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>95 </p>

<p>122 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. 
. T </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>92 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>076 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C . </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>029 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C . </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>011 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C . </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>77 </p>

<p>040 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C . </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>78 </p>

<p>045 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C . </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>018 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C . </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>021 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C . </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. 
. A . </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>057 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>C . </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>63 </p>

<p>030 </p>

<p>C 
C T A . A . </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>69 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>The numbers are the locations of polymorphism relative to the start site of concatenated MLST loci. A dot indicates that the nucleotide was identical to that in UgCl001. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Clonal clusters indicated in bold type. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Sequence type (ST) designation based on BioloMICS.net database. </p>

<p>Cryptococcal Genotype Influences Clinical Outcome </p>

<p>September/October 2012 Volume 3 Issue 5 e00196-12 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 3 </p>

<p>variation was not present to allow for comparison of mating type 
to genotype, phenotype, or patient outcome. 
Melanin production by the clinical isolates was analyzed using 
media containing niger seeds or L-DOPA (L-3,4-dihydroxyphenyl-
alanine). These media provide biphenolic precursors for melanin 
production along distinct pathways (27). A relative scoring 
method based on similarity to reference strains with weak (JEC20) 
and strong (KN99) melanization was employed to analyze mel-
anin production over 48 h (see Fig. S3A in the supplemental ma-
terial). K-means clustering analysis for both types of media 
showed separation of the melanin production into 10 major clus-
ters on niger seed medium and 7 major clusters on L-DOPA me-
dium (Fig. S3B). The Burst and hybrid groups did not differ sig-
nificantly in their ability to produce melanin on niger seed </p>

<p>medium (Fig. 3A). In contrast, while 
no association between genotype and 
melanin production on L-DOPA was 
observed for the Burst groups, the hy-
brid group had significantly higher 
melanin production on L-DOPA me-
dium (P 0.001 by the Tukey-
adjusted t test) (Fig. 3B). 
Capsule production by the UgCl 
isolates was monitored in two ways for 
comparison to the genotype of the iso-
late. First, in vivo capsule release into 
patient CSF at the time of presentation 
with meningitis was measured using a 
qualitative cryptococcal antigen assay 
(CRAG) agglutination assay. No asso-
ciation between clinical CRAG titer 
and Burst genotype was observed (P 
0.32 by analysis of variance 
[ANOVA]). This result could be con-
founded by differences in the fungal 
burden in patients, resulting in inac-
curate measures of capsule produc-
tion. Consequently, an in vitro quanti-
tative CRAG assay was performed to 
more precisely determine the capacity 
of each strain to produce and shed 
capsule. Burst group 1 strains had the 
highest capacity to produce and se-
crete capsule (Fig. 3C). The hybrids 
produced significantly less capsule 
than the rest of the Burst groups (P 
0.005 by Tukey-adjusted t tests). Im-
portantly, Burst group 1 showed ele-
vated capsule release compared to 
Burst group 3 (P 0.02 by Tukey-
adjusted t test) and higher (but not sta-
tistically significant) capsule release 
compared to Burst group 2 strains. 
These data implicate elevated capsule 
production as one potential mecha-
nism by which Burst group 1 isolates 
could cause increased mortality in pa-
tients. 
Patient/host immune response. 
The observation that Burst group 1 
isolates were associated with higher mortality and shed more cap-
sule than the other Burst groups led us to hypothesize that the 
capsule from these strains could influence the type of immune 
response during infection. To directly test this hypothesis, we de-
veloped an ex vivo cytokine release assay to measure the responses 
to capsule and cell wall preparations obtained from representative 
Burst group 1 and 3 isolates. Blood samples from 18 healthy vol-
unteers were incubated with Burst group 1 and 3 antigens, cyto-
kine production was quantified by multiplex assay, and differ-
ences between each volunteer's response to the Burst group 1 and 
3 antigens was determined by a paired t test. 
Release of the Th 1 cytokine IFN-was similar between the 
Burst group 1 and 3 capsule antigens (P 0.08 by a paired t test) 
(Fig. 4A). In contrast, production of Th 2 cytokines IL-4 and IL-10 </p>

<p>FIG 1 Multilocus sequence typing of Ugandan clinical isolates. (A) Pseudocolor representation of the </p>

<p>allelic structure of the UgCl strain population. Alleles at the seven loci are indicated by different colors. Each 
row indicates a single strain. Vertical lines on the left represent Burst groups. (B) Consensus tree from 1,000 
bootstrapped replicates of a maximum parsimony analysis of the concatenated sequences of all informative 
loci. Bootstrap values over 50% are shown. (C) Analytical separation of UgCl strains into nonredundant 
evolutionary groups based on Burst analysis of the sequence types. The colors in the circles indicate the 3 
Burst groups. Outlier strains are not shaded. </p>

<p>Wiesner et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
September/October 2012 Volume 3 Issue 5 e00196-12 </p>

<p>was significantly higher in response to capsule antigens from Burst 
group 1 strains compared to Burst group 3 strains (P 0.02 and 
P 0.003 by a paired t test, respectively) (Fig. 4B and C). The 
amount of capsule antigen (measured by CRAG assay) was stan-
dardized in these assays, and both capsule antigens elicited equiv-
alent dose-dependent IL-8 chemokine responses (P 0.99 by a 
paired t test) (Fig. 4D; see Fig. S4B in the supplemental material). 
Thus, the observed differences in the immune responses to cap-
sule antigen were due to intrinsic properties of the capsule and not 
the quantity of capsule generated by the Burst group 1 and 3 iso-
lates. 
The cell wall antigen preparations did not elicit robust cytokine 
responses, but dose-dependent IL-8 chemokine responses equiv-
alent to those observed with the capsule antigens were still de-
tected (see Fig. S4 in the supplemental material). These data show 
that capsule, but not cell wall, from Burst group 1 isolates elicits a 
stronger Th 2 cytokine response than capsule from Burst group 3 
isolates. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We report the association between cryptococcal genotype and 
clinical outcome with further determination of the effect of viru-
lence potential on disease severity in a cohort of Ugandans with 
AIDS and culture-positive CM. Our investigation revealed that 
different genotypes are associated with differences in patient sur-
vival. Cryptococcal genotypes associated with high patient mor-
tality exhibited increased capsule (Burst group 1) or melanin (hy-
brid strains) production, which are two known virulence factors. 
We showed that capsule differences between genotypes also may 
have affected the host immune response, because capsule from 
genotypes associated with high mortality elicited a greater Th 2 
cytokine response. 
Previous studies noted genotypic diversity in clinical isolates 
from Southern Africa (e.g., Botswana, South Africa) predomi-
nantly in the VNI and VNB clades that show evidence of recom-
bination (24, 28, 29). In contrast, clinical isolates from other re-
gions of the world show significant clonality and are typically 
members of the VNI and VNII clades (29). The UgCl strains had 
the same SOD1 locus observed in other African cohorts (24, 29), 
but the Ugandan cohort had significant clonality, and the pre-</p>

<p>FIG 2 One-year survival of culture-positive patients presenting at Mulago </p>

<p>Hospital in Kampala, Uganda, based on strain genotype. Patients infected with 
Burst group 3 strains lived longer than patients infected with other genotypes 
(P 0.007 by log rank test). No patients infected with hybrid strains survived 
the infection. </p>

<p>FIG 3 Cryptococcal virulence factors and genotype. (A and B) Association </p>

<p>between Burst groups and temporal melanization as indicated by K-means 
cluster rank on niger seed (A) or L-DOPA (B) medium. (C) Association be-
tween Burst groups and shed capsule as measured by cryptococcal antigen 
titer. Each symbol represents the value for the individual strain. The short 
vertical bars represent the means for the different groups. Mean values that are 
statistically significantly different are indicated by bars and asterisks as follows: 
*, P 0.05; **, P 0.005; ***, P 0.0005. </p>

<p>Cryptococcal Genotype Influences Clinical Outcome </p>

<p>September/October 2012 Volume 3 Issue 5 e00196-12 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 5 </p>

<p>dominant clade has diverged from the VNI, VNII, and VNB ref-
erence alleles. These data suggest that cryptococcal populations in 
Uganda are isolated and highly clonal and that the unique Burst 
group 1 genotypes may be responsible for the unusually high mor-
tality rates observed in Ugandan patient cohorts. The study by 
Miglia et al. found several sequence types associated with specific 
geographic regions in South Africa (28). Our data showing no 
geographic distribution of the UgCl strains in the Ugandan pa-
tient population suggest that patient geographic location within 
Uganda cannot be used to predict infection with the different 
Ugandan genotypes. 
MLST has been used extensively to analyze both global and 
regional population structures in both C. neoformans and C. gattii 
(23-25). Yet, the ability of MLST to resolve clinically relevant 
differences between strains remained unclear. The data presented 
here show that MLST can be used to distinguish differences in 
clinical outcome and provide insight into factors affecting disease 
development. The Ugandan isolates were relatively homogenous 
with extensive clonality by MLST genotyping and with few poly-
morphisms between genotypes. Because of this homogeneity, 
most C. neoformans var. grubii isolates in the cohort could be 
stratified into one of three subpopulations based on Burst analysis. 
Each Burst group had multiple patients with identical MLST ge-
notypes that could be compared. This clustering of the data re-
vealed connections between genotype, clinical outcome, and vir-</p>

<p>ulence factor production that may not 
be readily apparent in more genotypi-
cally diverse populations. 
Coinfection with multiple strains 
of C. neoformans has been observed. 
Previous studies identified coinfec-
tions based on the phenotypic traits 
(30), mating types (25), or genotypes 
of serial isolates (31). Desnos-Ollivier 
estimated that coinfections could ac-
count for 20% of cryptococcal disease 
based on studies of a French cohort 
(25). Similarly, 17% of the Ugandan 
patients screened for coinfection were 
infected with multiple genotypes. The 
effect of coinfection on clinical presen-
tation and patient outcome remains to 
be determined. In this study, only 4 
patients had confirmed coinfections, 
and only two of the patients had infec-
tions with evolutionarily distinct 
strains in different Burst groups. Un-
fortunately, because the vast majority 
of the clinical isolates used here were 
colony purified before storage, coin-
fection could not be controlled in this 
study, and the effect of coinfection on 
clinical outcome remains unknown. If 
coinfection rates are almost 20%, as 
the available data suggest, then coin-
fection could lead to a 20% error rate 
in accurately predicting the host re-
sponse to infection. In this case, our 
results showing associations between 
genotype and clinical outcome could 
underestimate the differences between genotypes. The differences 
might be more pronounced if coinfections were identified and 
excluded from the analysis. Future studies in which coinfections 
and single infections are analyzed for their clinical outcome and 
host response will be necessary to define the effect coinfection has 
and whether the host response is cumulative, associated with the 
predominant strain, or associated with the most antigenic strain. 
However, the high prevalence of coinfection suggests that single 
colony-purified isolates may not accurately represent C. neofor-
mans infections. This has broad implications for many types of 
studies, including studies assessing antifungal susceptibility. 
The genotype of the cryptococcal strain was associated with 
differences in clinical outcome. Patients infected with Burst group 
1 or 2 isolates had higher mortality rates and shorter survival times 
than patients infected with Burst group 3 isolates (P 0.02); 
though, admittedly, there were few subjects with Burst group 3 
isolates. One possible explanation for the low prevalence of Burst 
group 3 isolates is that they may be poor pathogens and do not 
cause severe meningitis as frequently. This hypothesis is consistent 
with our results showing reduced capsule production and stimu-
lation of a protective immune response by Burst group 3 strains 
that would limit disease progression. 
To understand the connection between cryptococcal genotype 
and patient outcome, we analyzed virulence factor production by 
the different genotypes. We focused on three widely acknowl-</p>

<p>FIG 4 Immune response of healthy volunteers to ex vivo stimulation with capsule antigens from geneti-</p>

<p>cally distinct strains. (A to D) Production of IFN-(IFNg) (A), IL-4 (B), IL-10 (C), and IL-8 (D) cytokines 
in response to shed capsule antigen from a representative clonal cluster strain within each Burst group. 
Antigens were standardized to a physiologically relevant final assay CRAG titer of 1:1,024 as determined by 
cryptococcal antigen agglutination assay. Data are representative from assays of 6 independent strains. 
Mean values that are statistically different are indicated by bars and asterisks as follows: *, P 0.05; **, P 
0.005. Mean values that are not statistically different are indicated by bars labeled n.s. (for nonsignificant) 
with P 0.08 (A) and P 0.99 (D). </p>

<p>Wiesner et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
September/October 2012 Volume 3 Issue 5 e00196-12 </p>

<p>edged virulence factors of Cryptococcus: mating type, melanin, and 
capsule. While global populations of C. neoformans var. grubii are 
predominantly mating type, a high prevalence of a mating type 
strains were observed in strains from Botswana (32). Most of the 
Ugandan isolates were mating type, which is consistent with 
global populations, with only 2% a mating type in the Ugandan 
cohort. Thus, differences in mating type are unlikely to explain the 
higher lethality associated with Burst groups 1 and 2 relative to 
Burst group 3 strains. 
In assessing melanin production, we found no differences be-
tween genotypes when the strains were cultured on niger seed 
medium. However, the hybrid strains produced significantly 
more melanin when L-DOPA was provided as the biphenolic pre-
cursor. Although we found increased melanin production by 
hybrid strains when these isolates were grown on L-DOPA-
containing media in vitro, we cannot draw conclusions about mel-
anin production by these strains in human infections in vivo. 
L-DOPA, however, is prevalent in the central nervous system (21); 
thus, the increased melanin production of the hybrid strains in 
response to L-DOPA could potentially occur in vivo and promote 
virulence, leading to increased mortality. 
Capsule production was measured both in vivo and in vitro. 
The in vitro data proved superior for a number of reasons. First, 
the high degree of variability in the in vivo CRAG titers and small 
cohort made the statistical comparisons underpowered. Second, 
many uncontrolled factors, including duration of infection and 
amount of fungal proliferation, affect the amount of capsule pres-
ent in the in vivo samples. These factors likely resulted in the high 
variability of the in vivo CRAG titers. The number of cells and 
duration of culture were controlled more rigorously in the in vitro 
assay. Consequently, we were able to stratify the Burst groups and 
hybrids based on capsule shedding. Notably, the high-lethality 
Burst group 1/2 strains shed the greatest amount of capsule, 
whereas the less-lethal Burst group 3 strains shed significantly less 
capsule. The observation that capsule differences between geno-
types are statistically associated with differences in patient mortal-
ity suggests that genetic diversity of the cryptococcal capsule may 
directly influence clinical outcome and immune response in hu-
mans. 
Our findings suggested that Ugandan hybrid strains were asso-
ciated with increased mortality. Hybrid strains have attenuated 
virulence in mouse models of cryptococcal infection (33) and of-
ten produce less severe infections in humans (21). Thus, the 100% 
mortality observed with the Ugandan hybrid strains was surpris-
ing. A larger cohort of patients infected with hybrid strains com-
pared to C. neoformans var. grubii strains is needed to further 
explore differences between the infections. The hybrids exhibited 
high melanin production on L-DOPA medium but shed the least 
amount of capsule compared to the C. neoformans var. grubii iso-
lates. The genetic divergence of the hybrids relative to the nonhy-
brids, combined with the low number of hybrids analyzed, pre-
vents meaningful deduction in this regard. It is possible that the 
high lethality of the hybrids was a consequence of multiple factors, 
possibly unrelated to capsule or melanin production, and this will 
be the focus of future investigations. 
The current study demonstrates that strain genotype may be a 
significant factor in determining the immune response in patients 
with AIDS and CM. Protective immunity to Cryptococcus requires 
several elements. Innate cells such as macrophages, monocytes, 
and dendritic cells produce tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-), </p>

<p>chemokine (C-C motif) ligand 2 (CCL2) (monocyte chemotactic 
peptide 1 [MCP-1]), CCL3 (macrophage inflammatory protein 1 
[MIP-1]), and IL-12 to recruit and license additional leukocytes 
to the site of infection (34-36). The innate immune system alone 
is not sufficient to clear cryptococcal infections, as assistance is 
required from adaptive immunity with helper T cells. The priming 
and differentiation of CD4 T cells to the Th 1 lineage is crucial for 
a protective immune response to cryptococcal infection (37). 
IFN-produced by Th 1 cells not only acts in a positive-feedback 
loop to stimulate the production of more Th 1 cells but also classi-
cally activates macrophages to increase reactive oxygen produc-
tion and kill internalized cryptococcal cells (38-40). Conversely, 
an IL-4-driven Th 2 adaptive response generates alternatively acti-
vated macrophages, is nonprotective, results in greater fungal bur-
den, and allows dissemination (41). The Th 1 /Th 2 balance para-
digm used to define interactions between Mycobacterium 
tuberculosis and the human host may also apply to Cryptococcus 
(42, 43). The pathogen competes against the host to shift a pro-
tective Th 1 response to a pathogenic Th 2 response. How Crypto-
coccus affects this balance is an active area of research, and capsule 
production is one potential strategy that could be used by Crypto-
coccus. 
An ex vivo antigen stimulation assay was used to determine the 
effect of genetic diversity within the cryptococcal capsule on the 
Th 1 /Th 2 balance in humans. High-lethality Burst group 1 isolates 
stimulated greater IL-4 and IL-10 production compared to less-
lethal Burst group 3 isolates. IL-4 is a powerful inducer of Th 2 
development, serving as a positive-feedback signal for more IL-4 
production as well as a negative-feedback signal for Th 1 responses. 
Similarly, IL-10 is a suppressive cytokine that has antagonistic 
effects on Th 1 responses and development (13). These data suggest 
that the high-lethality Burst group 1 isolates shift the Th 1 /Th 2 
balance in favor of the pathogenic Th 2 response. In contrast, the 
less-lethal Burst group 3 isolates are unable to elicit a robust Th 2 
response, allowing the Th 1 /Th 2 balance to shift to the more pro-
tective Th 1 response. 
The capsule antigen preparations used in this study were a 
heterogeneous mix of microvesicles, proteins, immunogenic lip-
ids, and capsule polysaccharide. Therefore, it is likely that T cell 
antigens, mainly proteins, present in the preparation were pro-
cessed and presented by APCs to generate the Th 1 protective im-
mune response observed in all of the preparations. In contrast, 
capsule polysaccharide is widely implicated in host immune eva-
sion and can influence host responses in several ways. Capsule can 
directly inhibit opsonization, phagocytosis, and lysosomal degra-
dation within phagosomes (44-46). In addition, shed capsule can 
disrupt cytokine signaling and lymphocytes (6, 47, 48). The major 
component of capsule polysaccharide, glucuronoxylomannan 
(GXM), can also promote secretion of Th 2 cytokines by mono-
cytes (49). Burst group 1 strains produce more polysaccharide 
than Burst group 3 strains, yet the amount of polysaccharide used 
in the ex vivo assay was held constant. Thus, the differences in 
immune response to the capsule preparations observed in the ex 
vivo assay were due solely to genetic differences between the Burst 
group 1 and 3 strains that affect the structure, function, and/or 
composition of the capsule polysaccharide or other components 
of the preparation. The fact that Burst group 1 strains also produce 
more capsule polysaccharide suggests that the actual effect on the 
Th 1 /Th 2 balance is even greater than observed in the ex vivo anti-
gen stimulation assay. A shift in the Th 1 /Th 2 balance in favor of a </p>

<p>Cryptococcal Genotype Influences Clinical Outcome </p>

<p>September/October 2012 Volume 3 Issue 5 e00196-12 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 7 </p>

<p>pathogenic Th 2 response results in greater fungal burden, dissem-
ination, and ultimately death in mouse models of cryptococcosis 
(50, 51). Our data show strains capable of shifting the Th 1 /Th 2 
balance toward a Th 2 cytokine response in humans are also asso-
ciated with high mortality rates. 
The studies presented here were designed to analyze the effect 
of two parameters on the immune response and clinical outcome: 
capsule and cell wall. The capsule-both the amount of capsule 
and the type of capsule-differed between genotypes and affected 
the immune response. In contrast, while melanin pro-
duction was found to differ in the hybrids, no effect of cell wall 
components on the immune response was observed. Thus, the 
combination of the melanin and cell wall cytokine induction ex-
periments suggest that alterations in cell wall and melanin pro-
duction can differ between strains, but the role, if any, cell wall 
components play in disease outcome remains unclear. 
The high overall mortality rate in the Ugandan culture-positive 
cohort resulted in too few surviving patients to analyze the effect 
of strain genotype on subsequent development of immune recon-
stitution inflammatory syndrome (IRIS) following antiretroviral 
therapy. A larger cohort of culture-positive patients that initiate 
ART will be needed to examine associations between strain geno-
type and risk for IRIS. IRIS patients have an aberrant immune 
response following reconstitution of their CD4 T cell popula-
tion. Current theories suggest that this aberrant response is due to 
uncontrolled reconstitution of the immune system or continued 
prevalence of a highly reactive antigen (52). Our data show that 
Burst group 1 strains produce abundant, Th 2 -reactive, capsule 
antigen. Thus, Burst group 1 strains may also be more likely to 
elicit IRIS in patients who survive the initial infection compared to 
Burst group 3 strains with lower and less reactive antigen. 
Taken together, the data presented show that strain genotype is 
associated with disease outcome. The observation that strain ge-
notype affects the immune response to cryptococcal infections 
suggests that genotype can be clinically informative and leads to 
interesting possibilities for new treatment strategies in patients 
with AIDS and CM. Treatment regimens targeted at the unique 
combination of pathogen and host may improve clinical out-
comes. For example, new treatments such as IFN-(53) or other 
approaches that increase Th 1 cytokines in patients infected with 
those Cryptococcus strains that elicit predominant Th 2 responses 
may restore proper Th 1 /Th 2 balance and allow better control of 
the infection. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Ethical statement and data. Clinical samples were collected during an 
observational, prospective study of Ugandan AIDS patients with CM de-
signed to study immune reconstitution inflammatory syndrome follow-
ing ART initiation (3, 54, 55). Each patient had only one episode of CM. 
This study was reviewed and approved by the institutional review boards 
of the University of Minnesota, Makerere University, and the Uganda 
National Council of Science and Technology. Written informed consent 
was obtained from all subjects, and all data were deidentified. 
Strains and media. C. neoformans clinical isolates (Ugandan clinical 
[UgCl] isolates) from CSF samples were colony purified and stored as 
glycerol stocks. Cryptococcus and Candida albicans reference strains (56-
62; see Table S1 in the supplemental material) were also stored as glycerol 
stocks. All strains were grown on yeast peptone dextrose (YPD) medium 
prior to subsequent analysis. Complete Dulbecco's modified Eagle's me-
dium (DMEMC), niger seed, L-DOPA, canavanine glycine bromothy-
mol blue (CGB), and Christensen's urea media were used as previously 
described (63, 64). </p>

<p>MLST. Genomic DNA extraction was performed as described previ-
ously (65). Eight loci were amplified and sequenced-seven International 
Society for Human and Animal Mycology (ISHAM) consensus loci 
CAP59, GPD1, IGS1, LAC1, PLB1, SOD1, and URA5 (23) and the optional 
highly polymorphic TEF1 locus (24). An additional LAC1Ra primer was 
developed to replace the consensus primer, which was not sufficiently 
specific for LAC1 amplification in our samples. All primers are listed in 
Table S2 in the supplemental material. MLST PCR products were resolved 
by agarose gel electrophoresis, excised, purified, and sequenced. Sequence 
assembly was performed with Sequencher 4.9 software (Genecodes, Ann 
Arbor, MI). Exported sequences were truncated to the consensus MLST 
ends (23). Sequences for each locus were aligned using ClustalW software 
(66). All polymorphisms were verified using the sequence chromato-
grams, and alignments were manually edited to resolve ambiguities. Mul-
tiple alignments were processed with PAUP4.0b10 software (Sinauer As-
sociates, Sunderland, MA) to produce maximum parsimony trees using a 
heuristic algorithm with 1,000 random sequence additions and gaps 
treated as the fifth base. A total of 4,430 characters were analyzed: 4,315 
characters were constant, 71 variable characters were parsimony uninfor-
mative, and 44 characters were parsimony informative. Sequences for 
all loci for each UgCl sample were concatenated and subjected to maxi-
mum parsimony, maximum likelihood, and bootstrap analyses using 
PAUP4.0b10 software. Nonredundant allelic sets were compiled using 
the Non-redundant databases (NRDB) web tool (http://pubmlst.org). 
Novel allele sequences were deposited in MLST.net (http://www.MLST 
.net), BioloMICS.net, and BLAST public databases. Sequence types were 
identified as combinations of allelic types for individual loci based on 
NRDB data. Sequence types were subjected to Burst analysis (26) to pro-
duce a putative evolutionary relationship between clusters of closely re-
lated sequence types. A minimum spanning tree was produced from the 
sequence types with Prim's algorithm combined with Burst clustering. 
Phenotypic analyses. Cryptococcal yeasts were plated onto either 
Christensen's urea or CGB plates and incubated concurrently with con-
trol strains at room temperature for 24 to 48 h. Plates were visually in-
spected for color changes. C. gattii strains were used as positive controls 
for the CGB test, and C. neoformans KN99 was used as a positive control 
for Christensen's urea and a negative control for CGB test. Bright-field 
microscopy with a Zeiss Axioplan microscope with an attached AxioCam 
camera (Carl Zeiss, Germany) was used for analysis of cellular morphol-
ogy. 
Melanin production was measured by comparing pigmentation of 
UgCl strains grown on niger seed and L-DOPA media (67) to C. neofor-
mans reference strains with strong (KN99) and weak (JEC20) melaniza-
tion. Cell suspensions were adjusted to 10 6 and 10 7 yeasts/ml using a 
hemocytometer, plated onto YPD medium, grown at 25°C in the dark, 
and examined at 12, 18, 36, and 48 h. Melanin assays were performed in 
triplicate. The absolute production of melanin varied in the replicates, but 
the relative amounts of melanin were highly reproducible. Relative 
melanization scores of zero (no pigmentation), one (equal to JEC20), two 
(between JEC20 and KN99), three (equal to KN99), or four (more than 
KN99) were assigned to UgCl strains based on comparison with the 
reference strains grown on the same plate. C. albicans strain SC5314 was 
used as a negative melanization control. 
Cryptococcal antigen assay (CRAG) was performed at the time of 
diagnosis using the Murex Cryptococcus latex agglutination assay (Murex 
Diagnostics, Norcross, GA) according to the manufacturer's specifica-
tions or following in vitro culture with the Premier cryptococcal antigen 
kit (Meridian Bioscience, Cincinnati, OH) according to the manufactur-
er's specifications with a modified procedure for sample preparation. 
Briefly, DMEMC was inoculated and incubated at 30°C. Cultures with 
an optical density at 600 nm (OD 600 ) of 0.90 to 1.10 were centrifuged at 
10,000 rpm, and the supernatant was serially diluted from 1:10 to 1:6,250 
with the provided "DIL" solution to obtain an absorbance at 450 nm of 
0.14 to 1.50. The enzyme immunoassay value for each sample was calcu-
lated from the A 450 value according to the manufacturer's instructions </p>

<p>Wiesner et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
September/October 2012 Volume 3 Issue 5 e00196-12 </p>

<p>and normalized to an OD 600 of 1.0. PCR with differential PAK1, GPA1, 
and Ste20 primers was used for determination of serotype and mating type 
as previously described (68). 
Ex vivo antigen stimulation. Antigens were prepared from the cell 
wall and culture supernatants of six strains, including the control H99 
strain and five strains representative of the mean CRAG data points within 
each of the MLST clonal cluster genotypic groups. A capsule antigen prep-
aration was prepared from culture supernatant from each strain grown in 
DMEMC. The supernatant was decanted, frozen at 80°C, and lyoph-
ilized. The lyophilized sample was reconstituted in phosphate-buffered 
saline (PBS), and the CRAG titer was measured. A cell wall antigen prep-
aration was prepared from the yeasts. The cells were flash frozen in liquid 
nitrogen, combined with glass beads, and vortexed vigorously for 2 h at 
4°C to disrupt the cells. The insoluble fraction (i.e., cell wall) was analyzed 
for CRAG and for protein (BCA protein assay [BCA stands for bicin-
choninic acid]; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Rockford, IL) concentrations. 
Endotoxin levels in all antigen preparations were undetectable (0.06 U/ 
ml) by Limulus amebocyte lysate assay (Associates of Cape Cod, East 
Falmouth, MA). 
Whole-blood samples for the cryptococcal cytokine release assay were 
obtained from healthy individuals in North America. Peripheral blood 
samples from each subject were drawn into lithium heparin tubes, diluted 
2-fold with PBS, and dispensed into a tissue culture plate. Cell wall and 
capsule antigens were added to each well to yield a physiologically com-
parable glucuronoxylomannan (GXM) CRAG titer of 1:256. PBS was used 
as the negative control. The plates were incubated at 37°C in 5% CO 2 for 
20 h. After incubation, the plasma was separated from the cells and stored 
at 4°C until cytokine analysis. Cytokines were quantified in duplicate for 
interleukin 2 (IL-2), IL-4, IL-6, IL-8, IL-10, granulocyte-macrophage 
colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF), gamma interferon (IFN-), and tu-
mor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-) using a Luminex 100 instrument (Bio-
Rad, Hercules, CA). Negative controls incubated in PBS were subtracted 
from the raw data to determine the net response. 
Statistics. The means for groups of isolates were compared by analysis 
of variance (ANOVA) and t tests, and medians were compared using 
Kruskal-Wallis rank sum tests and Mann-Whitney U tests. The chi-square 
and Fisher's exact tests were used to evaluate the frequencies of categorical 
variables. Tukey adjustments were made to correct for multiple compar-
isons. The Mantel-Cox log rank test was used to compare survival data. All 
analyses were performed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>., Cary, NC). </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIAL </p>

<p>Supplemental material for this article may be found at http://mbio.asm.org 
/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1128/mBio.00196-12/-/DCSupplemental. 
Figure S1, PDF file, 1.5 MB. 
Figure S2, PDF file, 1.3 MB. 
Figure S3, PDF file, 1 MB. 
Figure S4, PDF file, 0.8 MB. 
Table S1, DOCX file, 0.1 MB. 
Table S2, PDF file, 0.1 MB. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by NIH grants AI070152, AI089244, AI073192, 
AI078750, and AI096925; the University of Minnesota (UMN) Office of 
International Programs; UMN Center for Infectious Diseases and Micro-
biology Translational Research; UMN Academic Health Center Collabor-
ative and Tibotec REACH initiative grants; and the Minnesota Medical 
Foundation Robert and Mabel Bohjanen Immune Reconstitution Re-
search Fund. </p>



<p>Cryptococcal Genotype Influences Clinical Outcome </p>

<p>September/October 2012 Volume 3 Issue 5 e00196-12 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 9 </p>





<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
September/October 2012 Volume 3 Issue 5 e00196-12 </p>

</text></tei>