<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3729991" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: Since laparoscopic appendectomy was first described, various modifi-</p>

<p>cations, such as single port incisionless-intracorporeal conventional equipment-
endoscopic surgery (SPICES), have been described for reducing pain and improving 
cosmetic results. In the retrocecal and retrocolic positions, attachments to the lateral 
peritoneum and cecum may lead to difficulties during SPICES, which is performed 
with only one port. Here, we present the effects of variations in the position of the 
vermiform appendix in treating acute appendicitis with SPICES. </p>

<p>Since the first successful laparoscopic appendectomy (LA) was performed by 
Semm [1] in Germany for a noninflamed appendix during gynecological surgery, 
numerous modifications of the procedure have been described for reducing pain and 
improving cosmetic results. The modifications have especially focused on reducing 
the number of ports [2-4]. As the need to minimize patient scars and maximize 
patient safety has increased, new devices such as the all-in-one laparoscope have 
continued to improve. These modifications and devices have led surgeons to use 
single port incisionless-intracorporeal conventional equipment-endoscopic surgery 
(SPICES) frequently [5]. This technique requires only an 11-mm conventional port, 
an all-in-one laparoscope and conventional working instruments. SPICES was first 
successfully used in appendectomy by Akgur et al. [5] in Turkey in 2010. 
Although preileal, postileal, pelvic, subcecal and ectopic positions of the appendix </p>

<p>Corresponding Author 
Huseyin Kilincaslan 
Department of Pediatric Surgery, Bezmialem Vakif 
University Faculty of Medicine, Adnan Menderes 
Bulvari, 34093 Fatih/Istanbul, Turkey 
Tel: +90-505-939-7834 
Fax: +90-212-534-6970 
E-mail: hkilincaslan@yahoo.com.tr </p>

<p>Key Words </p>

<p>Laparoscopy, Laparoscopic surgical procedure, 
Appendicitis, Appendectomy </p>

<p>Received December 24, 2012 
Revised April 8, 2013 
Accepted May 6, 2013 </p>

<p>J Korean Surg Soc 2013;85:80-83 
http://dx.doi.org/10.4174/jkss.2013.85.2.80 </p>

<p>Copyright © 2013, the Korean Surgical Society </p>

<p>cc Journal of the Korean Surgical Society is an Open Access 
Journal. All articles are distributed under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits 
unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction 
in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Suleyman Cuneyt Karakus, et al: SPICES and retrocecal appendicitis </p>

<p>Journal of the Korean Surgical Society 81 </p>

<p>vermiformis have been reported, the retrocecal and retrocolic 
positions are the most common [6,7]. In these positions, 
attachments to the lateral peritoneum and cecum may lead 
to difficulties during SPICES, which is performed with only 
one port. This technique also has limitations in handling, in 
contrast to 3-port LA and to the single incision laparoscopic 
surgery (SILS) with R-port or Triport. 
The aim of the present study is to evaluate the effect of 
varia tions in the position of the vermiform appendix in treat-
ing acute appendicitis with SPICES. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>We retrospectively reviewed 52 children who underwent 
SPICES for acute appendicitis between March 2010 and 
November 2011. The procedure was performed by the first 
author at Gaziantep Children's Hospital. The patients were 
divided into two groups according to the position of appendix. 
Group A consisted of 30 patients (12 females and 18 males; 
mean age, 10.5 ± 2.5 years; range, 5 to 15 years) with 
retrocecal appendix, while group B included 22 patients (9 
females and 13 males; mean age, 10.9 ± 2.3 years; range, 6 
to 15 years) with preileal, postileal, pelvic, sub cecal or ectopic 
appendix. 
The diagnosis of appendicitis was made based on clinical 
history and physical examination. We preferred open appen-
dectomy in cases of generalized peritonitis and firm right 
lower quadrant mass. 
Single dose cefuroxime and ornidazole were administered 
to all patients. SPICES was performed with patients in the 
Trendelenburg position with a gentle downward left tilt under 
general anesthesia. A single intraumbilical 1-cm vertical inci-
sion was made after stomach and bladder decompression, and 
an 11-mm port was inserted. We used the 0 degree all-in-
one laparoscope including a 6-mm operating channel and a 
parallel eyepiece (KARL STORZ GmbH &amp; Co. KG, Tuttlingen, 
Germany) in all cases. Initial diagnostic laparoscopy was 
routinely undertaken. Afterwards, the appendix was dissected 
from the retroperitoneal bands and grasped with a 5-mm 
atraumatic long grasper. A 16 G angiocath was percutaneously 
inserted in the peritoneal cavity. The needle was withdrawn, 
and a SWING suture, described by Akgur et al. [5], was passed 
through the sheath of the angiocath. The appendix was slung 
using this suture. The meso-appendix was dissected using 
ultrasonic shears (Harmonic Scalpel, Ethicon Endo-Surgery 
Inc., Cincinnati, OH, USA). The appendiceal base was then 
ligated intracorporeally with a 2-0 polyglactin suture using 
a fisherman's knot formed extracorporeally. The appendix 
was transected and the abdominal cavity was washed. 
Following the release of the SWING suture, the appendix was </p>

<p>removed inside the port to minimize the chance of wound 
contamination. 
The data collected included age, gender, operating time, 
length of hospital stay, second port insertion, conversion 
to open surgery and complications. The statistical analyses 
were performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 11.5</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, 
IL, USA). The data was expressed as the mean ± standard 
deviation. Mann-Whitney U and t-tests were used for the 
statistical analysis. P &lt; 0.05 was accepted as statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>There were no significant differences between the groups in 
terms of patient age (P = 0.549) and gender (P = 0.948) (Table 
1). 
SPICES was successfully performed in 27 patients (90%) 
and 21 patients (95.5%) in groups A and B, respectively. There 
were 2 conversions (6.7%) to open surgery and 1 (3.3%) second 
port insertion in group A, while a second port was inserted 
in 1 patient (4.5%) in group B. There were no significant 
differences between groups in the success rate of SPICES (P 
= 0.470). Although conversion rate looks higher in group A, 
there was no significant difference between the groups (P = 
0.221). 
The mean operating time for SPICES was 41.0 ± 9.0 
minutes (26 to 62 minutes) in group A and 36.5 ± 7.8 minutes 
(25 to 55 minutes) in group B, but the difference between 
the groups was not statistically significant (P = 0.088). No 
complications occurred during the operative period in either 
group. 
The mean postoperative hospitalization period was 2.2 ± 
0.5 days (1.5 to 3.5 days) in group A and 2.3 ± 0.6 days (1.5 to 
3 days) in group B. This difference was not statistically signi-
ficant (P = 0.460). 
The mean follow-up was 11.4 ± 6.1 months (range, 6 to 
28 months) in group A and 10.0 ± 6.5 months (range, 6 to 28 </p>

<p>Table 1. Summary of patients' characteristics and results </p>

<p>Variable 
Group A 
Group B </p>

<p>No. of patients 
30 
22 </p>

<p>Male/female 
18/12 
13/9 </p>

<p>Age (yr), mean ± SD 
10.5 ± 2.5 
10.9 ± 2.3 </p>

<p>Success rate (%) 
90 
95.5 </p>

<p>Operating time (min), mean ± SD 
41.0 ± 9.6 
36.6 ± 8.0 </p>

<p>Postoperative hospiatlization (day), mean ± SD 
2.2 ± 0.6 
2.3 ± 0.7 </p>

<p>Postoperative complications (%) 
3.3 
4.5 </p>

<p>SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>thesurgery.or.kr </p>



<p>JKSS </p>

<p>Suleyman Cuneyt Karakus, et al: SPICES and retrocecal appendicitis </p>

<p>months) in group B. Statistical analysis showed no differences 
between the two groups (P = 0.147). In group A, laparotomy 
was performed for adhesion-related intestinal obstruction 2 
months after SPICES. Transient seroma in the umbilical area 
developed in one patient in group B. The overall complication 
rates showed no statistically significant differences between 
the groups. SPICES has only one incision in the umbilical 
area, which has the advantage of hiding the scar, so the cos-
metic outcomes were sufficient with no residual scar formation 
at the angiocath insertion area. 
In group B, the appendix was located in the left lower 
quadrant in 2 patients. One of the patients had intestinal mal-
rotation, and the other had situs inversus totalis. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>LA is commonly used as an alternative to open surgery. 
In comparison with open surgery, the 3-port LA reduces 
postsurgical pain, shortens hospital stay, allows early food 
intake, and enhances cosmetic outcomes [8-10]. It reduces the 
irritation of the intestine and the incidence of postoperative 
adhesions. LA also allows the surgeon to assess associated 
abnormalities within the abdominal cavity. As laparoscopic 
mini mal invasive surgery has drawn greater attention and 
new equipment is developed, SILS has been increasingly 
widely used in appendectomy [11,12]. Performing SILS 
through the umbilicus, a congenital scar provides reliable 
cos metic results. Only one incision is made; thus, the risk 
of complications such as port site hernia, hematoma and 
infection are reduced. In the past decade, a number of SILS 
modifications for appendectomy have been described: 1) 
Extracorporeal laparoscopic-assisted appendectomy through a 
single umbilical port site is difficult to perform, causes wound 
contamination and usually requires a second port, 2) SILS 
with R-port or Triport requires a 2-cm incision that is larger 
than children's umbilical margins, and 3) SPICES is a feasible 
approach with excellent cosmetic results in children [5,13]. 
In 31% of cases, the tip of the appendix is in the pelvis, 
and in 65% of cases, it extends upwards behind the cecum. 
In 20% of cases of retrocecal appendix, the appendix rests 
freely, while in 5% of cases, it is truly extraperitoneal [6]. The 
remaining cases with retrocecal appendix have peritoneal 
adhesions. The overall conversion rate to open surgery from 
LA was reported as 4.1%, and retrocecal position of the 
appendix remains a common cause of conversion to open 
surgery [14]. Additionally, retrocecal appendix dissection 
presents challenges for extracorporeal laparoscopic-assisted 
ap pendectomy, and this localization may lead to parallel 
problems in SPICES. SPICES has limitations in handling 
compared to the 3-port LA and SILS with R-port or Triport, </p>

<p>which are performed using at least 2 conventional graspers. 
In the present study, the conversion rate of SPICES in pa-
tients with retrocecal appendicitis was not significantly dif-
ferent compared to other localizations of appendicitis. The 
SWING suture, a new homemade grasper that does not re-
quire a different stab incision, seems to have an important 
role in achieving such a low conversion rate. It replaces the 
second port and is capable of repositioning the appendix, 
like conventional graspers. The last stages of single-port 
LA, including the dissection of the meso-appendix, ligation 
of appendiceal base, and transection of the appendix can be 
performed intracorporeally using this suture. 
The most important part in SPICES is to sling the appendix 
with SWING suture. The truly extraperitoneal appendix needs 
the dissection and releasing of the appendix from attachments 
to the peritoneum before slinging of the appendix. It is dif-
ficult to dissect the truly extraperitoneal appendix by using 
only one grasper in SPICES. Therefore, in 2 cases in group 
A, we were not able to sling the appendix because of the 
truly extraperitoneal position, and open appendectomy was 
performed. The overall conversion rate to multitrocar surgery 
was also 3.8% in the present study. In one case in each group, 
the omentum covered the appendix firmly, and the second 
port was inserted. 
The success rates, mean operating times and mean hospital 
stay lengths in our study were not different from those of 
studies reporting extracorporeal laparoscopic-assisted ap-
pen dectomy and SILS with R-port or Triport [11,13,15]. 
Similarly low conversion rates to multitrocar surgery and 
open appendectomy have also been reported in appendicitis 
per formed with SPICES [5]. These results may encourage 
surgeons to perform the appendectomy with one port, but it is 
important not to be reluctant to insert a second or even a third 
port, especially in cases with truly extraperitoneal appendix 
and severe adhesions. Insistence can result in morbidity. 
The mean operating time was longer in the group with 
retrocecal appendix, but this difference was not statistically 
sig nificant. This may be because more time was spent on the 
dissection of peritoneal adhesions in group A. Additionally, 
one case of postoperative adhesion-related intestinal obstruc-
tion may be the result of extended dissection in group A. SILS 
with R-port or Triport requires at least a 2-cm incision, which 
is larger than the umbilical area, especially in children, and 
thus may result in a scar. In contrast, only a 1-cm incision is 
performed in SPICES. We suggest that care should be taken 
to keep the incision within the umbilical ring for the best 
cosmetic outcome. 
Situs inversus totalis, intestinal malrotation and an ex tre-
mely mobile cecum are the anatomic abnormalities that cause 
left-sided appendix [16,17]. The diagnosis of left-sided acute </p>

<p>Suleyman Cuneyt Karakus, et al: SPICES and retrocecal appendicitis </p>

<p>Journal of the Korean Surgical Society 83 </p>

<p>appendicitis may be difficult, and it is made based on physical 
examination, abdominal ultrasonography, and computed 
tomo graphy. In addition to being useful for appendectomy, 
laparoscopy can be diagnostic in patients with confusing 
cases [17]. In 2 cases, the malpositioned appendix lay free 
in the peritoneal cavity, and we performed SPICES without 
extended dissection. Approximately 100 cases of left-sided 
acute appendicitis have been reported in the literature [18]. To 
the best of our knowledge, these are the first reported cases of 
left-sided acute appendicitis performed with SPICES. 
In conclusion, SPICES is a feasible approach with sufficient 
cosmetic results in children with acute appendicitis. It can 
be performed easily and safely in patients with retrocecal 
acute appendicitis. Further prospective studies are needed to 
determine the validity of our data. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was 
reported. </p>



</text></tei>