<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3335898" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Opium use in diabetic populations is associated with major depressive disorder (MDD). This study was designed 
to investigate the relationship between opium use and severity of depression in Iranian diabetic patients. 
Methods: In this case-control study, 642 type 2 diabetic patients were recruited from those presenting at two outpatient clinics 
at the Akhavan Hospital in Kashan, Iran; of them, 600 diabetic patients were included in the study and divided into two groups: 
opium-abusers (150 patients) and non-opium-abusers (450 patients). Clinical and demographic information was obtained through 
a detailed questionnaire. Depression symptomalogy and severity were assessed with the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI), and a 
corresponding diagnosis was made based on the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-IV, Text Revision, 2000 
(DSM-IV TR) criteria. 
Results: The mean depression score was higher in the opium abuse group than in the non-abuser group (29.27±1.44 vs. 18.29± 
1.31, P&lt;0.001). In general, a significant association was found between opium abuse and depression among patients (odds ratio 
[OR], 4.54; 95% confidence interval [CI], 2.87 to 7.44; P=0.001). No significant relationship was found between dysthymia and 
opium abuse (OR, 0.68; 95% CI, 0.18 to 1.192; P=0.155), while MDD was significantly higher in the opium abuser group (OR, 
7.32; 95% CI, 5.20 to 12.01; P&lt;0.001). 
Conclusion: Depression is more frequent in opium-dependent diabetic patients, and its severity is also greater. Given these find-
ings, opium-dependent diabetic patients should be advised about the increased risks of depression and related comorbidities. </p>

<p>Diabetes mellitus is a chronic disease that can have many com-
plications, such as retinopathy, neuropathy, and nephropathy; 
it affects patients' quality of life, and it is often associated with 
depression [1-3]. Dietary restrictions, constant dependence on 
medicine, short-and long-term side effects, and the cost-bur-
den of the disease may help to explain the high prevalence of 
depression among these patients [4]. 
Opium has traditionally been consumed in Iran as a treat-</p>

<p>ment for pain, diarrhea, insomnia, and premature ejaculation. 
It is also used for enjoyment and elimination of tension [5,6]. 
Some Iranian patients consume opium for their diabetes, al-
though the reasons and prevalence are not clear. The pain re-
duction effects of opium and a lack of adequate knowledge may 
explain their opium usage to some extent, but research is need-
ed to gain a better understanding. However, it is known that 
opium abuse among diabetics is associated with an increased 
risk of severe depression [7]. Overall, about 90% of opioid-de-
pendent patients are recognized to have a psychiatric disorder, </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4093/dmj.2012.36.2.157 
pISSN 2233-6079 · eISSN 2233-6087 </p>



<p>Sepehrmanesh Z, et al. </p>

<p>Diabetes Metab J 2012;36:157-162 
http://e-dmj.org </p>

<p>which most typically include depression [8], antisocial charac-
ter, anxiety [9], and memory and psychosomatic disorders 
[10,11]. 
Depression is one of the most common psychiatric disorders 
[12]. Initial presenting symptoms tend to include an increas-
ingly reduced sense of self-efficacy, reduced self-care behav-
iors, mood swings, and in some cases increased suicidal ide-
ation [9,13]. These symptoms, although significant in and of 
themselves, can also exacerbate problems for patients with di-
abetes [3], such as poor medical adherence, functional impair-
ment, and high health care costs (up to 86% in primary care) 
[14]. 
Although opium abuse is known to have negative effects on 
diabetic patients [7], few studies have specifically assessed the 
impact of opium abuse on depression in this population. There-
fore, the current study is designed to investigate the association 
between opium abuse and severity of depression in Iranian di-
abetic patients. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>In this prospective case-control study, we recruited 642 type 2 
diabetic patients presenting at two outpatient clinics of the 
Akhavan Hospital in Kashan, Iran: 173 with a diagnosis of 
opium abuse (cases) and 469 without this diagnosis (controls). 
We obtained clinical and demographic information about all 
participants through a detailed questionnaire. Opium use sta-
tus was ascertained by self report; however, because of varia-
tion in opium quality and difficulty in uniform measurement 
across all study patients, the quantity of opium intake was not 
estimated. However, all opium abusers reported having regu-
larly used opium for at least 12 months prior to admission (as 
indicated by the question, "Has the client continued to use 
opium despite recurrent problems aggravated by the substance 
use within the last 12-month period?") [15]. Data on the fre-
quency and duration of opium intake was missing or incom-
plete in some cases. 
Depressive symptomalogy and severity were assessed through 
administration of the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI) [16], 
and patients scoring over 16 were considered to be depressed. 
A corresponding diagnosis was made based on the Diagnostic 
and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-IV, Text Revision, 
2000 (DSM-IV TR) criteria [17]. To distinguish opium-induced 
major depressive disorder (MDD) from independent MDD, 
patients with a history of depression before beginning opium </p>

<p>use, such as those who had used antidepressants or been hos-
pitalized due to depression, were excluded. Patients were con-
sidered to have hypertension if they were currently using anti-
hypertensive medications or if they had blood pressure read-
ings above 140/90 mm Hg on two different occasions. Hyper-
cholesterolemia was defined as having one or more serum 
cholesterol level readings above 6.2 mmol/L (240 mg/dL) [18]. 
Blood glucose control was assessed by measuring HbA1c lev-
els, and values above 7% were considered uncontrolled [19]. 
The study protocol was approved by the ethics committee of 
Kashan University of Medical Sciences (Kashan, Iran). In-
formed consent was obtained from the patients before enroll-
ment. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
In a case-control study, cases and controls ideally match on all 
characteristics except the variable of interest. In order to con-
sider the confounding effects of unmatched characteristics, we 
treated them as covariates in a multiple logistic regression 
analysis. Variables with P values less than 0.2 for differences 
between the two groups were considered to be covariates: these 
included age, marital status, literacy, hypertension, and hyper-
lipidemia. Results were reported as mean±standard deviation 
for quantitative variables and percentages for categorical vari-
ables. The groups were compared using the Student's t-test for 
continuous variables and the chi-square test (or Fisher's exact 
test as appropriate) for categorical variables. Odds ratios (OR) 
and 95% confidence intervals (CI) for OR were calculated. To 
decrease the effects of probable confounders, adjusted ORs 
were estimated when appropriate. Results for which P values 
were 0.05 or less were considered statistically significant. All 
the statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13.0</rs> 
for Windows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Of the 642 Iranian subjects with type 2 diabetes who satisfied 
the inclusion criteria, 600 (150 opium-abusers and 450 non-
opium-abusers) patients were selected for analysis in this study. 
Their demographic and clinical characteristics are summarized 
in Table 1. 
Depression and MDD were found to be more prevalent 
among opium-abusing diabetic patients than in non-abusers, 
and the mean depression score was higher in the opium abuse 
group. In contrast, dysthymia was diagnosed in 6.7% of abus-</p>



<p>Opium and severity of depression in diabetics </p>

<p>Diabetes Metab J 2012;36:157-162 
http://e-dmj.org </p>

<p>ers and 10.9% of non-abusers. Table 2 shows the prevalence of 
the different types of depression detected in the two groups. 
In general, depression was found to be over four times more 
likely among opium abusers than non-abusers (OR, 4.54; 95% 
CI, 2.87 to 7.44; P=0.001). No significant relationship was 
found between dysthymia and opium abuse (OR, 0.68; 95% CI, 
0.18 to 1.192; P=0.155). However, MDD was over seven times 
as likely in the opium abuse group (OR, 7.32; 95% CI, 5.20 to 
12.01; P&lt;0.001). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Depression is frequently comorbid in type 2 diabetic patients, 
with a prevalence of unipolar depression of about 10.9% and 
that of significant depressive symptoms of about 32.9% [20]. 
However, depression is under-recognized, and it is estimated 
to be untreated in approximately two-thirds of depressed dia-
betic patients. This is unfortunate, since the course of depres-
sion tends to be chronic and severe in patients with diabetes 
[21]. 
The association between diabetes and depression seems to 
be interactional, with some studies indicating that diabetes in-
creases the incidence of depression [1-3], and others reporting 
that depressed adults have an increased risk of developing type 
2 diabetes [22-24]. The latter might be explained by an in-
creased likelihood for depressed adults to have a sedentary 
lifestyle, obesity, and smoking [21]. Conversely, Golden et al. 
[25] described a reduced risk of depression in patients with </p>

<p>impaired fasting glucose levels and untreated type 2 diabetes. 
In addition, depression has been seen as a predictive factor for 
the severity and number of diabetic complications in some 
studies [26,27], while others have not found any such associa-
tions [28]. 
A surprising report states that up to 17.9% of Iranians have 
used opium at least once, and 8.8% are regular users [29]. Opi-
um contains as much as 12% morphine and is the crudest and 
least potent form of opiate. Opium abuse has propagated among 
youth and in various nations for reasons such as ample acces-
sibility and affordability of the drug, unemployment, and men-
tal health problems. 
From a physiopathological point of view, opiates act at the 
basomedial hypothalamus to inhibit the release of gonadotro-
pin releasing factor and thus decrease the circulating concen-
trations of luteizing hormone and follicular-stimulating hor-
mone. As a result of these decreased pituitary hormone con-
centrations, the testosterone plasma level declines [30]. Mc-
Intyre et al. [31] found that depressed men had lower mean 
bioavailable and total testosterone levels; likewise, several lines 
of evidence suggest that testosterone might be effective for the 
treatment of depression [32,33]. 
In several studies, it was established that opiate addicts were 
significantly more depressed than normal controls [8] and even 
slightly more depressed than psychiatric patients [34]. The rea-
son why opium abuse appears to worsen depression severity 
in diabetic patients has not been clarified. Although opium 
use was once recommended as a treatment for diabetes melli-
tus [35], studies have demonstrated that opium addiction ad-
versely affects some serum factors in diabetic patients by in-
creasing serum glucose, decreasing high density lipoprotein 
cholesterol, and thus adding to metabolic derangements [36]. 
Further, serum glucose elevation in diabetics appears to be </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic and clinical data of diabetic patients 
with and without opium dependence </p>

<p>Characteristic </p>

<p>Opium-
abuser 
(n=150) </p>

<p>Non-opium-
abuser 
(n=450) </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>Male gender 
32.0 
35.6 
0.425 </p>

<p>Age, yr 
45.1±4.6 
44.3±5.1 
0.089 </p>

<p>Married 
74.0 
59.8 
0.001 </p>

<p>Literacy 
84.0 
70.0 
0.008 </p>

<p>Family history of depression 51.3 
55.1 
0.419 </p>

<p>Hypertension 
51.3 
44.0 
0.12 </p>

<p>Hyperlipidemia 
70.7 
60.2 
0.021 </p>

<p>Diabetes duration, yr 
8.2±1.1 
8.3±2.3 
0.608 </p>

<p>Controlled diabetes 
47.3 
48.9 
0.734 </p>

<p>Data are presented as percent or mean±standard deviation. 
P&lt;0.05 significant. </p>

<p>Table 2. Prevalence of different types of depression seen in the 
two groups </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Opium-
addicted 
(n=31) </p>

<p>Non-opium-
addicted 
(n=165) </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>Depression symptoms 
80.6 
47.3 
0.001 </p>

<p>MDD 
74.3 
36.1 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Dysthymia 
6.7 
10.9 
0.15 </p>

<p>Depression score 
29.27±1.44 
18.29±1.31 &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Data are presented as percent or mean±standard deviation. 
MDD, major depressive disorder. </p>



<p>Sepehrmanesh Z, et al. </p>

<p>Diabetes Metab J 2012;36:157-162 
http://e-dmj.org </p>

<p>correlated with MDD [3]. 
Association between opium and depression or diabetes and 
depression has been discussed in several studies, and recent 
studies have found a significant association between opium 
abuse and depression in diabetic patients [7]. The current study 
also found this association to be significant, with 74.3% of opi-
um abusing diabetic patients diagnosed with MDD, compared 
to 36.1% of non-abusing diabetic patients. In contrast, Shiri et 
al. [7] detected MDD in only 22.8% of diabetic men which was 
1.7 times more than non-abuser diabetics. The reason for this 
considerable difference in results is not clear, but study design 
differences and confounders are likely contributors. In another 
study, Khamseh et al. [1] reported a 71.8% prevalence of MDD 
in all diabetic patients (abuser or non-abuser), just slightly less 
than the 74.3% in our study's abuser group. Their study includ-
ed both type 1 and type 2 diabetic patients, while only type 2 
diabetics were enrolled in our study. This appears to highlight 
the direct impact of opium consumption on diabetics' depres-
sive symptoms compared to the effects of diabetes alone. 
There is a fallacy among Iranian people that opium has fa-
vorable effects on diabetes mellitus. A previous study that ad-
dressed this possibility found that opium temporarily decreased 
blood glucose, but it had no distinct, long-lasting effects on 
blood glucose, as determined by HbA1c measurements [37]. 
Cerebral vascular involvement [38], vascular impairment fol-
lowing retinopathy, multiple hospital admissions, and sexual 
dysfunction seem to be worsened with comorbid depression 
among diabetic patients [39]. This may be related to the nega-
tive effects of psychiatric disorders on blood glucose control, 
which implies the importance of treatment for comorbid de-
pression [40]. 
In the present study, opium use was ascertained by self re-
port, and the quality of the opium intake was not quantified. It 
is possible that varying quality and frequency of opium use 
among abusing patients affected study outcomes. Additionally, 
while one of the exclusion criteria was a documented history 
of depression before beginning opium use, it is difficult to dis-
tinguish opium-induced major MDD from independent MDD, 
and there may have been pre-existing MDD that was not diag-
nosed. Group differences were adjusted for unmatched vari-
ables, but there are many possible confounders which were not 
measured or presented in this study. These include other as-
pects of physical health, mental health, and social support 
which might have modified the observed association between 
opium addiction and depression. Similarly, other possible con-</p>

<p>founders, such as thyroid function and folate levels, which may 
impact depression, were not matched between the groups. 
Findings could also have been enhanced by adding another 
control group consisting of non-diabetic opium abusers to as-
sess the direct effects of opium abuse on depression. 
We found that depression is both more frequent and more 
severe in diabetic patients who regularly use opium than in 
those who do not. Thus, our results suggest that opium-de-
pendent diabetic patients should be advised about the associ-
ated increased risks of depression and related comorbidities. 
Further research is indicated to assess whether consultation 
about opium abuse in diabetic patients with depression can 
reduce the severity of depressive symptoms. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was re-
ported. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank Dr. Siamak Mehdizadeh Seraj 
for language revision of the manuscript. </p>





<p>Opium and severity of depression in diabetics </p>





<p>Sepehrmanesh Z, et al. </p>



</text></tei>