<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3734831" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>effects of vorinostat in transformed BJ fibroblasts. Collectively, 
these data enhance our understanding of the molecular 
consequences of HDAC inhibition, and provide a mechanistic 
basis for the tumor-selective biological effects of these agents. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>HDAC inhibitors selectively kill tumor cells. Matched 
normal (BJ) and transformed (BJ LTSTERas) fibroblasts were 
treated with vorinostat over 72 h, and cell death was analyzed 
(Figures 1a and b). Following 24 h vorinostat treatment, there 
was a marginal increase in death of transformed BJ 
LTSTERas fibroblasts that increased substantially following 
extended drug exposure. BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts were 
significantly more sensitive to vorinostat than BJ cells (Figures 
1a and b). Vorinostat induced comparable time-dependent 
hyperacetylation of histone H3 (Figure 1c) and a-tubulin 
(Figure 1d) in both cell types, suggesting that the relative 
resistance of normal cells to vorinostat-mediated apoptosis 
was not due to a failure of vorinostat to inhibit HDACs in these 
cells. We next tested the sensitivity of BJ and BJ LTSTERas 
fibroblasts to romidepsin, an HDACi that selectively inhibits 
class I HDACs. 
20-22 BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts were more 
sensitive than BJ cells to romidepsin-induced apoptosis, even 
though there was equivalent acetylation of histone H3 in 
romidepsin-treated BJ and BJ LSTERas fibroblasts (Figures 
1e and f). As a-tubulin is deacetylated by HDAC6 that is not 
effectively inhibited by romidepsin, romidepsin did not induce 
hyperacetylation of a-tubulin. 
The sensitivity of donor-matched normal and transformed 
bone marrow endothelial cells (BMECs) to HDACi was also 
assessed. BMEC and BMEC LTSTERas were treated with 
vorinostat for 48 h and analyzed for annexin-V binding and 
propidium iodide uptake (Supplementary Figure 1A). Con-
sistent with observations in the BJ fibroblast system, 
transformed BMEC were comparatively hypersensitive to 
vorinostat-mediated death. 
Finally, we determined whether the mechanisms by which 
normal cells were transformed affected the relative sensitivity 
of cells to vorinostat-induced apoptosis. Transformed BJ 
fibroblasts in which SV40 large T antigen was functionally 
replaced with HPV16 E6 and E7, 
23 were tested for vorinostat-
sensitivity. BJ cells expressing hTERT, E6, E7, H-RAS </p>

<p>G12V   and ST (BJ E6E7 TRST) were sensitive to vorinostat relative 
to normal BJ fibroblasts when measured over a 72-h time </p>

<p>course (Supplementary Figure 1B). These data demonstrated 
that HDACis selectively killed transformed cells while mediat-
ing equivalent histone hyperacetylation in normal and 
transformed cells. </p>

<p>Vorinostat induces tumor-cell-selective gene expression 
changes. We hypothesized that tumor-cell-selective gene 
expression changes underpinned the differential sensitivity of 
isogenic tumor and normal cells to HDACi-induced apopto-
sis. To investigate whether de novo protein synthesis was 
required for HDACi-induced death, BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts 
were pre-treated for 1 h with cycloheximide (CHX) before the 
addition of vorinostat. CHX treatment significantly inhibited 
vorinostat-mediated apoptosis after 48 h of drug treatment 
(Figures 2a and b). Given the requirement of de novo protein 
expression for the induction of apoptosis by vorinostat, a 
time-course microarray study was conducted. An early (4 h) 
and intermediate (12 h) time point was selected for the 
microarray study on the basis of candidate quantitative real-
time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) analyses of 
CDKN1A (Figures 2c and d), a gene commonly induced by 
HDACi. 
20,24 CDKN1A mRNA was induced by vorinostat in BJ 
and BJ LTSTERas cells; however, the magnitude of 
induction was greater in transformed cells (Figures 2c and 
d). The abundance of CDKN1A mRNA in BJ and BJ 
LTSTERas cells after 24 h of vorinostat treatment was 
similar, as the threshold cycle (Ct) values relative to the 
control gene RPL32 were similar in both cell types (data not 
shown). The hyper-induction of CDKN1A in BJ LTSTERas 
fibroblasts over time reflects the lower basal expression in 
these cells (at time 0 h). </p>

<p>Vorinostat-induced changes in gene expression in 
BJ and BJLSTRas cells. Affimetrix microarray assays 
showed that the number of vorinostat-regulated probe sets 
increased in both cell types as a function of time; however, 
the overall response in BJ LTSTERas cells consistently 
exceeded that of BJ cells by B1000 probe sets at every 
time point (Figure 3a). At the time of onset of apoptosis 
(24 h), the number of vorinostat-regulated probe sets in BJ 
and BJ LTSTERas cells corresponded to 21.1 and 23.0% 
of the total number of probe sets represented on the 
arrays, respectively. Collectively, these data indicated that 
both BJ and BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts were capable of 
mounting a transcriptional response to vorinostat although </p>

<p>Figure 1 Matched normal and tumor cells are differentially sensitive to vorinostat-mediated apoptosis. (a, b) BJ and BJ LTSTERas cells were treated with 0, 2.5, 5, 10, 25 
or 50 mM doses of vorinostat for 24, 48 or 72 h. Following treatment, all cells were harvested and (a) stained for annexin-V-APC binding and propidium iodide uptake, and 
analyzed by flow cytometry; (b) fixed with 50% (v/v) ethanol in PBS, stained with propidium iodide and analyzed by flow cytometry. The percentage of annexin-V-APC, 
propidium iodide double positive cells or cells with sub-diploid DNA content is shown in panels (a, b), respectively. Data are presented as mean ± standard error of at least 
three independent experiments. P-values indicate statistical significance of cell type and dose response interactions as measured by two-way ANOVA, where Po0.05 is 
considered to be significant. (c, d) BJ (top panels) and BJ LTSTERas (bottom panels) cells were treated with 25 mM vorinostat or DMSO equivalent for 0-32 h. Protein extracts 
were analyzed by western blotting for: (c) acetylation of histone H3 with a pan-acetylated Histone H3 antibody, expression of a-Tubulin was used as a loading control; (d) 
acetylation of a-Tubulin with an anti-acetylated tubulin antibody, expression of b-Actin served as loading control. Western blots shown are representative of two independent 
experiments. (e) BJ and BJ LTSTERas were treated with 0, 2.5, 5, 10, 25 and 50 nM concentrations of romidepsin for 48 h. Following treatment, all cells were harvested and 
stained for annexin-V-APC binding and propidium iodide uptake (top panel) and analyzed by flow cytometry or fixed with 50% (v/v) ethanol in PBS, stained with propidium 
iodide (bottom panel) and analyzed by flow cytometry. The percentage of annexin-V-APC, propidium iodide double positive cells or cells with sub-diploid DNA content is 
shown. Data are presented as mean±standard error of at least five independent experiments. The difference in apoptotic sensitivity of BJ and BJ LTSTERas (interaction 
between cell type and romidepsin dose) was statistically significant (Po0.05), as determined by two-way ANOVA. (f) BJ and BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts were treated 
with 50 nM romidepsin for 0-24 h or with 25 mM vorinostat for 6 h (V). Immunoblots were probed with antibodies against acetylated histone H3 (AcH3), acetylated a-Tubulin 
(Ac-a-Tubulin) and total a-Tubulin to control for protein loading. Images are representative of two independent experiments </p>

<p>HDACi induce transcriptional responses 
JE Bolden et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>B1000 additional probe sets were significantly regulated by 
vorinostat in the transformed cells at every time point 
analyzed. 
The Connectivity Map (Cmap) tool 
25 was used to test 
whether the vorinostat signatures from BJ and BJ LTSTERas </p>

<p>fibroblasts were similar to other drug-induced expression 
profiles. The Cmap compound with highest connectivity to the 
BJ and BJ LTSTERas profiles generated in this study was 
vorinostat (Tables 1 and 2). Two hydroxamic-acid based 
HDACi, trichostatin A (TSA) and scriptaid, also demonstrated </p>

<p>% Annexin V, Propidium 
Iodide Positive </p>

<p>% Annexin V, Propidium 
Iodide Positive </p>

<p>% Annexin V, Propidium 
Iodide Positive </p>

<p>p=0.4687 </p>

<p>p&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>p&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>24 hr </p>

<p>48 hr </p>

<p>72 hr 
% Sub-Diploid DNA </p>

<p>Content </p>

<p>% Sub-Diploid DNA </p>

<p>Content </p>

<p>% Sub-Diploid DNA </p>

<p>Content </p>

<p>p=0.8590 </p>

<p>p=0.0021 </p>

<p>p=0.0001 </p>

<p>24 hr </p>

<p>48 hr </p>

<p>72 hr </p>

<p>Ac-H3 </p>

<p>Ac-H3 </p>

<p>DMSO </p>

<p>DMSO </p>

<p>α-Tubulin </p>

<p>25μM Vorinostat </p>

<p>25μM Vorinostat </p>

<p>Time (Hr) </p>

<p>p=0.0041 
0 2 4 8 16 24 0 2 4 8 16 24 V </p>

<p>Vehicle 
50nM Romidepsin </p>

<p>α-Tubulin </p>

<p>Ac α-Tubulin </p>

<p>Ac-H3 </p>

<p>0 2 4 8 16 24 0 2 4 8 16 24 V </p>

<p>Vehicle 
50nM Romidepsin </p>

<p>α-Tubulin </p>

<p>Ac α-Tubulin </p>

<p>Ac-H3 </p>

<p>Time (Hr) </p>

<p>Time (Hr) </p>

<p>BJ cells </p>

<p>BJ LTSTERas 
cells </p>

<p>HDACi induce transcriptional responses 
JE Bolden et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>high degrees of connectivity, which indicated that the probe 
sets regulated by vorinostat in BJ and BJ LTSTERas 
fibroblasts were similar to those regulated by different HDACi 
in diverse cell types. </p>

<p>Identification of genes that respond differently to 
vorinostat treatment in normal and transformed 
fibroblasts. We identified probe sets that responded differ-
ently to vorinostat treatment in matched normal and </p>

<p>Figure 2 Vorinostat-mediated apoptosis requires de novo protein synthesis. (a, b) BJ and BJ LTSTERas cells were pre-treated with 0, 5, 50, 250 and 500 ng/ml CHX to 
inhibit new protein synthesis and incubated with 25 mM vorinostat for 48 h. Cells were harvested and analyzed for cell death by flow cytometry. (a) Cells were stained with 
annexin-V-APC and propidium iodide. The percentages of cells staining positively for both markers are shown. (b) Cells were fixed with 50% (v/v) ethanol in PBS, stained with 
propidium iodide and analyzed for DNA content. The percentages of cells with sub-2N DNA content are shown. All data are presented as mean±S.E.M. of three independent 
experiments. *Po0.05, **Po0.01 as determined by a two-tailed Student's t-test, comparing 25 mM vorinostat treatments in the presence and absence of CHX. (c, d) BJ and 
BJ LTSTERas cells were treated with 25 mM vorinostat (red) or DMSO (black) for 0, 2, 4, 8, 16 and 24 h. Expression of CDKN1A in (c) BJ and (d) BJ LTSTERas cells was 
analyzed by qRT-PCR. Messenger RNA levels were calculated relative to that of transcripts from the non-HDACi-regulated control gene RPL32. Fold expression changes at 
each time point are plotted relative to time 0 h (untreated cells) </p>

<p>Figure 3 Regulation of gene expression in BJ and BJ LTSTERas by vorinostat. (a) The number of probe sets that were significantly altered in BJ and BJ LTSTERas cells in 
response to treatment with vorinostat. Probe sets that were induced and repressed by at least 1.5-fold at any of the 4, 12 and 24 h time points relative to time 0 h are shown. 
(b) Genes that responded differently to vorinostat treatment in matched normal and transformed cells (contrast genes) were analyzed using the <rs type="software">IPA</rs> tool. The associations of 
various molecular and cellular functions with contrast genes are plotted in decreasing order of statistical significance, according to À log2 (P-value). P-values were adjusted 
for multiple testing using the method of Benjamini and Hochberg. The orange line indicates the threshold for statistical significance (Po0.05) </p>

<p>HDACi induce transcriptional responses 
JE Bolden et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>transformed cells (contrast probe sets) at any of the three 
time points (relative to time 0 h), as we hypothesized that 
contrast gene expression might underpin the different 
biological responses of donor-matched cells to vorinostat 
treatment. In total, 5959 contrast probe sets were identified 
and these were differently regulated by vorinostat in terms of 
either the direction (induction or repression) or the magnitude 
(degree of induction or repression) of the vorinostat response 
in BJ and BJ LTSTERas cells. Of the 5959 contrast probe 
sets, 2945 were equally expressed in untreated normal and 
tumor cells. However, 6226 of the 9240 probe sets with basal 
expression differences did not respond differently to vorino-
stat in the two cell types. These data indicated that the basal 
gene expression levels did not determine the capacity of 
genes to differently respond to vorinostat treatment in BJ and 
BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts. GO and pathway analyses were 
performed on the contrast gene list using the <rs type="software">Ingenuity Pathways Analysis</rs> (IPA) tool (Figure 3b). 'Cell Death' was 
the most significantly represented molecular and cellular 
function associated with contrast genes (false discovery rate 
(FDR) ¼ 3 Â 10 
À 23 ) while genes involved 'cell-cycle' 
(FDR ¼ 5 Â 10 
À 21 ) and 'cellular growth and proliferation' 
(FDR ¼ 4 Â 10 
À 20 ) were also significantly represented on 
the contrast list. 
We further analyzed the contrast responses, in particular 
those genes that were selectively or hyper-induced in BJ 
LTSTERas cells compared with BJ cells, using GO analyses 
and the <rs type="software">Database for Annotation, Visualization and Integrated Discovery (DAVID</rs>) tool (Supplementary Tables 1-3). Genes 
involved in 'induction of programmed cell death' (P ¼ 0.0130) 
and 'apoptotic program' (P ¼ 0.0024) were over-represented 
in vorinostat-treated BJ LSTRas cells compared with BJ cells 
(Supplementary Tables 1-3). Many genes encoding compo-
nents of the intrinsic and extrinsic apoptotic pathway were </p>

<p>Table 1 Connectivity map for vorinostat-responding genes in treated BJ cells </p>

<p>Rank 
Cmap name 
Mean 
n 
Enrichment 
P-value 
Specificity 
% Non-null </p>

<p>1 
Vorinostat 
0.762 
12 
0.977 
0.00000 
0.0151 
100 
2 
Trichostatin A 
0.695 
182 
0.922 
0.00000 
0.0047 
96 
3 
Resveratrol 
0.342 
9 
0.873 
0.00000 
0.0049 
100 
4 
Valproic acid 
0.238 
57 
0.488 
0.00000 
0.0000 
68 
5 
Sirolimus 
0.102 
44 
0.439 
0.00000 
0.1024 
50 
6 
LY-294002 
0.194 
61 
0.421 
0.00000 
0.0940 
67 
7 
Scriptaid 
0.747 
3 
0.980 
0.00004 
0.0000 
100 
8 
Rifabutin 
0.695 
3 
0.973 
0.00004 
0.0000 
100 
9 
Prochlorperazine 
0.209 
16 
0.571 
0.00004 
0.0631 
81 
10 
Trifluoperazine 
0.204 
16 
0.549 
0.00006 
0.1442 
68 
11 
Thioridazine 
0.196 
20 
0.509 
0.00008 
0.2329 
80 
12 
Syrosingopine 
0.327 
4 
0.900 
0.00010 
0.0093 
100 
13 
CP-690334-01 
0.275 
8 
0.685 
0.00036 
0.0121 
75 
14 
Loperamide 
0.235 
6 
0.756 
0.00050 
0.0152 
100 
15 
Parbendazole 
À 0.365 
4 
À 0.874 
0.00054 
0.0000 
50 
16 
Tanespimycin 
0.115 
62 
0.248 
0.00064 
0.5285 
54 
17 
Mefloquine 
0.291 
5 
0.795 
0.00084 
0.0588 
100 
18 
Fluphenazine 
0.166 
18 
0.441 
0.00089 
0.1814 
66 
19 
Securinine 
À 0.582 
4 
À 0.852 
0.00092 
0.0127 
75 
20 
MS-275 
0.609 
2 
0.974 
0.00111 
0.0433 
100 </p>

<p>Table 2 Connectivity map for vorinostat-responding genes in treated BJ LTSTERas cells </p>

<p>Rank 
Cmap name 
Mean 
n 
Enrichment 
P-value 
Specificity 
% Non-null </p>

<p>1 
Vorinostat 
0.816 
12 
0.978 
0.00000 
0.0151 
100 
2 
Trichostatin A 
0.703 
182 
0.932 
0.00000 
0.0000 
96 
3 
Resveratrol 
0.243 
9 
0.861 
0.00000 
0.0098 
100 
4 
CP-690334-01 
0.358 
8 
0.802 
0.00000 
0.0121 
87 
5 
15-Delta prostaglandin J2 
0.202 
15 
0.696 
0.00000 
0.0447 
86 
6 
LY-294002 
0.168 
61 
0.577 
0.00000 
0.0134 
73 
7 
Valproic acid 
0.171 
57 
0.482 
0.00000 
0.0000 
61 
8 
Scriptaid 
0.777 
3 
0.978 
0.00004 
0.0000 
100 
9 
Rifabutin 
0.650 
3 
0.973 
0.00010 
0.0000 
100 
10 
5707885 
0.282 
4 
0.899 
0.00030 
0.0052 
100 
11 
Thiostrepton 
0.247 
4 
0.880 
0.00034 
0.0392 
100 
12 
Phenoxybenzamine 
0.261 
4 
0.876 
0.00046 
0.2030 
100 
13 
Ciclopirox 
0.196 
4 
0.864 
0.00101 
0.0338 
100 
14 
Isotretinoin 
0.197 
4 
0.842 
0.00050 
0.0000 
100 
15 
Bacitracin 
À 0.410 
3 
À 0.913 
0.00112 
0.0121 
100 
16 
Sertaconazole 
À 0.249 
4 
À 0.834 
0.00137 
0.0000 
75 
17 
Mycophenolic acid 
0.252 
3 
0.910 
0.00154 
0.0452 
100 
18 
Syrosingopine 
0.260 
4 
0.822 
0.00173 
0.0326 
100 
19 
MG-262 
0.314 
3 
0.902 
0.00184 
0.1676 
100 
20 
Fenoprofen 
À 0.187 
6 
À 0.683 
0.00266 
0.0255 
50 </p>

<p>HDACi induce transcriptional responses 
JE Bolden et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>selectively induced in BJ LTSTERas cells. A candidate 
approach was subsequently undertaken to more thoroughly 
investigate the transcriptional regulation of apoptotic pathway 
components by vorinostat using the IPA program. 
Vorinostat treatment resulted in decreased expression of 
TNFRSF6 (FAS), TNFRSF10A (DR4/TRAILR1) and 
TNFRSF1A (TNFa receptor) in both normal and transformed 
fibroblasts (Figures 4a and b). Only a mild tumor-selective 
induction of TNFRSF10B (DR5/TRAILR2) was observed. We 
did not observe any transcriptional modulation of genes 
encoding death receptor ligands in response to vorinostat in 
either cell type (Figures 4a and b). Moreover, the genes 
encoding FADD (FADD), caspase 8 (CASP8) and BID were 
downregulated in BJ and BJ LTSTERas, suggesting that 
death receptor signaling was transcriptionally repressed by 
vorinostat in BJ and BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts. Collectively, 
the downregulation of genes encoding receptors, adaptors 
and proteolytic intermediaries in the death receptor pathway 
suggested that the extrinsic apoptotic pathway was unlikely to </p>

<p>play a substantial role in promoting selective apoptosis of BJ 
LTSTERas fibroblasts. 
Vorinostat treatment caused the general transcriptional 
induction of the pro-apoptotic BH3-only protein encoding genes 
BAD, BCL2L11 (BIM), BIK, PMAIP1 (NOXA), the multi-domain 
pro-apoptotic gene BAK1 and genes encoding death effector 
components downstream of mitochondrial damage (DIABLO, 
APAF1, CASP9, HTRA2 and CYTC) in transformed fibroblasts. 
Moreover, the pro-survival genes BCL2A1, BCL2L1 (encoding 
BCL-XL) and BCL2L2 (encoding BCL-w) were concomitantly 
repressed in these cells (Figures 4c and d). Collectively, 
this transcriptional response is predicted to confer a strong 
pro-death signal in the tumor cells. 
Despite the downregulation of BCL2L1 and BCL2L2, 
normal BJ fibroblasts failed to mount a substantial pro-
apoptotic transcriptional response. BIK, PMAIP1 and BAK1 
probe sets were unchanged following vorinostat treatment, 
and BAX and BAD were repressed. Although the maximally 
responding probe set for BCL2L11 was induced in BJ and </p>

<p>Figure 4 Ingenuity pathways analysis. Interaction map of the death receptor pathway was created using the <rs type="software">ingenuity pathways analysis</rs> tool (a) BJ and (b) BJ LTSTERas 
fibroblasts. (c, d) An interaction map of the BCL-2 family of apoptotic regulators was created using the <rs type="software">ingenuity pathways analysis</rs> tool, and overlaid with transcriptional 
responses to vorinostat in (c) BJ and (d) BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts. For (a-d), the direction and magnitude of vorinostat-mediated expression changes following 24 h of 
treatment, relative to time 0 h are indicated by pseudo-coloring. Induced (red), repressed (green) and non-responding probe sets (white) are shown. Log2 expression values of 
the strongest responding probe sets for each vorinostat-responding pathway component are shown. Interactions between BH3-only and pro-survival proteins are based upon 
Biacore analyses described in reference 26. Interactions between multi-domain proteins BAX/BAK and other BCL-2 family members were based on ingenuity pathway 
information </p>

<p>HDACi induce transcriptional responses 
JE Bolden et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>BJ LTSTERas cells (therefore, BIM is pseudo-colored red in 
Figures 4c and d), three additional BCL2L11 probe sets were 
selectively induced in BJ LTSTERas cells (Supplementary 
Figure 2). Collectively, these data strongly support the 
hypothesis that the transformed cells were hypersensitive to 
vorinostat-mediated apoptosis due to acute transcriptional 
alterations in the balance of pro-death and pro-survival BCL2 
family genes, whose protein products functionally converge to 
govern the integrity of the mitochondrial outer membrane. </p>

<p>Validation of BCL2 family gene expression by 
qRT-PCR. Expression of selected BCL2 family genes 
following vorinostat and dimethyl sulphoxide (DMSO) treat-
ment was verified by qRT-PCR. qRT-PCR and microarray 
detection of vorinostat-induced transcriptional changes in 
BAD, BAK1, BIK, BCL2A1 were concordant (Figure 5a). 
BCL2L11 (encoding BIM) was transcriptionally induced in </p>

<p>normal and transformed BJ fibroblasts following vorinostat 
treatment, and BCL2L11 induction at the 4 h time point (by 
qRT-PCR) was consistently greater in the normal cells 
(Figure 5b). Seven Affymetrix probe sets map to BCL2L11. 
Interestingly, three of these probe sets responded to 
vorinostat in both cell types and three probe sets were 
selectively induced in BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts in a time-
dependent manner (Supplementary Figure 2). BMF was 
shown by us and others to be a primary HDACi response 
gene. 
27-29 In our microarray analyses, BMF was classified as 
a non-responding gene most likely due to the combined 
effects of low basal expression and the location of the sole 
probe set (226530_at) toward the 5 
0 end of the BMF 
transcripts. The expression of BMF using qRT-PCR demon-
strated that the gene was hyper-induced by vorinostat in BJ 
LTSTERas fibroblasts (Figure 5b). Taken together, the qRT-
PCR data supported the microarray-based observation of a </p>

<p>mRNA Expression 
(Relative to Time 0hr) </p>

<p>Affymetrix 
qRT-PCR </p>

<p>BJ 
BJ 
BJ LTSTERas 
BJ LTSTERas </p>

<p>BAK1 203728_at 
9 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>9 
2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
mRNA Expression 
(Relative to Time 0hr) </p>

<p>mRNA Expression 
(Relative to Time 0hr) </p>

<p>mRNA Expression 
(Relative to Time 0hr) </p>

<p>mRNA Expression 
(Relative to Time 0hr) </p>

<p>mRNA Expression 
(Relative to Time 0hr) </p>

<p>mRNA Expression 
(Relative to Time 0hr) 
mRNA Expression 
(Relative to Time 0hr) </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
30 
30 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
30 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
30 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
3 0 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
3 0 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0.5 
0.25 
0.125 
0.0625 
0.03125 
0.015625 </p>

<p>2 
1 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0.5 
0.25 
0.125 
0.0625 
0.03125 
0.015625 </p>

<p>2 
1 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>DMSO 
25μM Vorinostat </p>

<p>DMSO 
25μM Vorinostat </p>

<p>DMSO 
25μM Vorinostat </p>

<p>DMSO 
25μM Vorinostat </p>

<p>BAD 209364_at </p>

<p>BIK 205780_at 
BIK 205780_at </p>

<p>BCL2A1 205681_at 
BCL2A1 205681_at 
BCL2A1 
BCL2A1 </p>

<p>BIK 
BIK </p>

<p>BAD 209364_at 
BAD 
BAD </p>

<p>BAK1 203728_at 
BAK1 
BAK1 </p>

<p>Expression Value </p>

<p>(Arbitrary Units, Log </p>

<p>2 ) </p>

<p>Expression Value </p>

<p>(Arbitrary Units, Log </p>

<p>2 ) </p>

<p>Expression Value </p>

<p>(Arbitrary Units, Log </p>

<p>2 ) </p>

<p>Expression Value </p>

<p>(Arbitrary Units, Log </p>

<p>2 ) </p>

<p>Expression Value </p>

<p>(Arbitrary Units, Log </p>

<p>2 ) </p>

<p>Expression Value </p>

<p>(Arbitrary Units, Log </p>

<p>2 ) </p>

<p>Expression Value </p>

<p>(Arbitrary Units, Log </p>

<p>2 ) </p>

<p>Expression Value </p>

<p>(Arbitrary Units, Log </p>

<p>2 ) </p>

<p>Figure 5 Validation of vorinostat-induced transcriptional responses by qRT-PCR. Transcriptional responses of BJ and BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts following DMSO (black) 
and 25 mM vorinostat treatment (red) were validated by qRT-PCR using the same template RNA as that used in the microarray study. Log2 transformed expression intensities 
of HG U133 plus 2.0 probe sets corresponding to (a) BAK1, BAD, BIK and BCL2A1 and (b) BCL2L11 and BMF are shown. Gene names and probe set IDs are indicated in the 
title of each panel. Normalized probe set intensity values (Y-axis) are presented, which allows direct comparison of basal expression (time 0 h), and log2 transcriptional 
responses over time between cell types (BJ and BJ LTSTERas). Data represent the summarized probe set intensities from three independent microarray time course 
experiments. qRT-PCR verification of selected genes is shown. Transcript expression was calculated relative to the control gene RPL32 (that does not respond to vorinostat or 
DMSO treatment), and fold-change mRNA expression over time was calculated relative to the 0 h time point. Data are presented as the mean ± S.E.M. of three independent 
experiments. For both Affymetrix and qRT-PCR results, data sets for BJ cells are in the left panels while data sets for BJ LTSTERas are in the right panels. (c) Whole cell 
protein extracts from BJ and BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts treated with DMSO or 25 mM vorinostat for 0-48 h were separated by SDS-PAGE and analyzed for the expression of 
BMF, BIK and BIM by western blotting. The expression of a-Tubulin was analyzed to confirm equal protein loading in each lane. The asterisk (*) denotes a non-specific band in 
the BIK western blot, which acts as a positive control for activity of the BIK antibody. The arrow denotes the location of BIK. Images are representative of two independent 
experiments </p>

<p>HDACi induce transcriptional responses 
JE Bolden et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>tumor-cell-selective pro-apoptotic gene expression signa-
ture, which temporally preceded the onset of apoptosis in BJ 
LTSTERas cells. 
Western blotting was performed to confirm that the 
vorinostat-mediated transcriptional changes corresponded 
to alterated protein expression. BIK and BMF levels 
increased within 24 h of vorinostat treatment in BJ LTSTERas 
fibroblasts (Figure 5c). Despite the slight trans-
criptional induction of BMF and BIK mRNA in normal cells, 
changes in BIK and BMF protein levels were undetectable 
following vorinostat treatment in this cell type. BIM EL protein 
levels were increased in BJ and BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts 
within 4 h of vorinostat treatment (Figure 5c); however, the 
time to maximal BIM EL induction differed between the two cell </p>

<p>types (16 h in BJ fibroblasts versus 6 h in BJ LTSTERas 
fibroblasts). </p>

<p>Vorinostat-mediated 
expression 
changes 
are 
HDACi-specific. To 
investigate 
whether 
vorinostat-
mediated changes in expression of Bcl-2-family genes were 
HDACi-specific, BJ and BJ LTSTERas cells were treated 
with equipotent concentrations of romidepsin or the DNA 
damaging agent etoposide and the expression of BAK1, 
BCL2L11, BIK, BMF and BCL2A1 was analyzed by 
qRT-PCR (Figure 6). Similar to the response observed with 
vorinostat treatment, romidepsin induced BCL2L11 in 
normal and transformed fibroblasts and induced BAK1 in 
the transformed cells. Furthermore, romidepsin treatment </p>

<p>DMSO 
25μM Vorinostat </p>

<p>BJ 
BJ LTSTERas 
BJ 
BJ LTSTERas </p>

<p>Affymetrix 
qRT-PCR </p>

<p>BMF </p>

<p>BMF </p>

<p>0 
8 
4 
2 43 54 8 0 
8 
4 
2 43 54 8 </p>

<p>BJ 
BJ LTSTERas </p>

<p>0 
8 
4 
2 43 54 8 0 
8 
4 
2 43 54 8 </p>

<p>BJ 
BJ LTSTERas </p>

<p>Time (hr) </p>

<p>Time (hr) </p>

<p>DMSO </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
BIK </p>

<p>BIK </p>

<p>0 
4 
2 
8 24 32 0 
4 
2 
8 24 32 </p>

<p>BJ 
BJ LTSTERas </p>

<p>0 
4 
2 
8 24 32 0 
4 
2 
8 24 32 </p>

<p>BJ 
BJ LTSTERas </p>

<p>Time (hr) </p>

<p>Time (hr) </p>

<p>DMSO </p>

<p>24kDa </p>

<p>33kDa </p>

<p>24kDa </p>

<p>33kDa </p>

<p>0 2 4 6 8 16 24 
0 2 4 6 8 16 24 </p>

<p>0 2 4 6 8 16 24 
0 2 4 6 8 16 24 </p>

<p>BJ 
BJ LTSTERas </p>

<p>BJ 
BJ LTSTERas </p>

<p>Time (hr) </p>

<p>Time (hr) </p>

<p>DMSO </p>

<p>24kDa </p>

<p>24kDa </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>4.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>4.0 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
Time (hours) </p>

<p>DMSO 
25μM Vorinostat </p>

<p>BCL2L11 1555372_at </p>

<p>BMF 226530_at 
BMF 226530_at 
BMF 
BMF </p>

<p>BCL2L11 1555372_at 
BCL2L11 
BCL2L11 </p>

<p>Expression Value </p>

<p>(Arbitrary Units, Log </p>

<p>2 ) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Expression Value </p>

<p>(Arbitrary Units, Log </p>

<p>2 ) </p>

<p>mRNA Expression 
(Relative to Time 0hr) 
mRNA Expression 
(Relative to Time 0hr) </p>

<p>Expression Value </p>

<p>(Arbitrary Units, Log </p>

<p>2 ) </p>

<p>Expression Value </p>

<p>(Arbitrary Units, Log </p>

<p>2 ) </p>

<p>mRNA Expression 
(Relative to Time 0hr) 
mRNA Expression 
(Relative to Time 0hr) </p>

<p>α-Tubulin </p>

<p>α-Tubulin </p>

<p>α-Tubulin </p>

<p>α-Tubulin </p>

<p>α-Tubulin </p>

<p>α-Tubulin </p>

<p>25μM vorinostat </p>

<p>25μM vorinostat </p>

<p>BIM EL </p>

<p>BIM EL </p>

<p>25μM vorinostat </p>

<p>Figure 5 (Continued) </p>

<p>HDACi induce transcriptional responses 
JE Bolden et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>caused the hyper-induction of BIK and BMF, together with 
the marked repression of BCL2A1 selectively in transformed 
cells. By contrast, etoposide failed to substantially induce 
BMF or BIK. Furthermore, BCL2A1 was induced 22-fold 
(rather than repressed over time as observed with HDACi) 
in BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts by etoposide treatment. Etopo-
side was however clearly capable of modulating pro-
apoptotic gene expression in matched fibroblasts, and 
caused the hyper-induction of BAK1 in BJ LTSTERas cells 
with a considerably higher magnitude than the changes 
induced by vorinostat or romidepsin. Collectively, these data 
strongly suggested that vorinostat-mediated alterations in the </p>

<p>expression of BCL2 family genes such as BMF, BIK and 
BCL2A1 were HDACi-specific. </p>

<p>Forced expression of BCL2A1 protects BJ LTSTERas 
fibroblasts 
from 
vorinostat-mediated 
apoptosis. 
BCL2A1 was highly expressed in untreated BJ LTSTERas 
fibroblasts and demonstrated the strongest vorinostat 
response of all BCL2 family genes with the pro-survival gene 
being strongly repressed in a tumor-cell-selective manner 
following HDACi treatment (refer to Figure 5a). BCL2A1 
(encoding BFL-1) was over-expressed in BJ LTSTERas 
fibroblasts to ascertain whether restoration of BCL2A1 </p>

<p>Figure 6 Regulation of BCL2 family gene expression by the HDACi romidepsin and the DNA damaging agent etoposide. BJ (left panels) and BJ LTSTERas (right panels) 
fibroblasts were treated for 0, 4, 12 and 24 h with 50 nM romidepsin (red), 50 mM etoposide (blue) and analyzed for the expression of BAK1, BCL2L11, BIK, BMF and BCL2A1 
by qRT-PCR. Expression of each gene was calculated relative to the non-romidepsin-and non-etoposide-responding control gene RPL32 and fold-change expression over 
time was calculated relative to time 0 h. Gene expression changes resulting from vehicle treatment (black) are also shown. Data are presented as the mean expression fold 
change from two independent time course experiments </p>

<p>HDACi induce transcriptional responses 
JE Bolden et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>expression in BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts could protect 
cells from vorinostat-mediated death and to formally demon-
strate that vorinostat-induced BJ LTSTERas cell death 
proceeds through induction of the intrinsic apoptotic cas-
cade. BJ LTSTERas cells were transduced with an MSCV-
based retroviral construct encoding FLAG-tagged human 
BFL-1 (FLAG-BFL-1), and expression of the exogenous 
FLAG-BFL-1 protein in GFP-positive cells was confirmed by 
western blot (Figure 7a). 
The sensitivity of BJ LTSTERas cells transduced with 
MSCV empty vector or FLAG-BFL-1 to vorinostat-mediated 
apoptosis was evaluated alongside parental BJ LTSTERas 
and normal BJ fibroblasts. Expression of FLAG-BFL-1 
significantly protected BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts from vorino-
stat-mediated apoptosis at the 48 and 72 h time points, 
relative to parental and MSCV transduced BJ LTSTERas 
fibroblasts (Figure 7b, Po0.01, as measured by two-way 
ANOVA at 48 and 72 h). Collectively, these data showed that 
protection of cells at the level of mitochondrial integrity 
(through over-expression of a pro-survival BCL2 family gene) </p>

<p>significantly attenuated the induction of vorinostat-mediated 
apoptosis in transformed fibroblasts, and therefore formally 
demonstrated a role for the intrinsic apoptotic cascade in the 
death of BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>HDACi are being extensively used in the clinic as anti-cancer 
agents given their manageable toxicity profiles and broad anti-
tumor activities. 
30 While tumor-cell-selective killing by HDACi 
has been observed, 
13,31-34 exactly why transformed cells are 
selectively hypersensitive to HDACi remains unclear. We 
aimed to determine whether donor-matched normal and 
transformed cells demonstrate the same or different gene 
expression profiles following HDACi treatment. Time-course 
microarray expression profiling revealed that normal and 
transformed cells transcriptionally responded to HDACi 
treatment, and that vorinostat signatures resembled other 
HDACi signatures in the Cmap database. Therefore, it 
appears that diverse HDACi modulate the expression </p>

<p>Figure 7 Forced expression of BFL-1 protects BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts from vorinostat-mediated apoptosis. (a) Proteins were extracted from exponentially growing 
BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts, and MSCV and MSCV FLAG-BFL-1 transduced variants. Proteins were separated on 10% polyacrylamide gels by SDS-PAGE and analyzed for 
the expression of FLAG-BFL-1 by western blotting with an anti-FLAG antibody. The expression of a-Tubulin levels served as a control for protein loading. (b) BJ, BJ 
LTSTERas, BJ LTSTERas MSCV and BJ LTSTERas FLAG-BFL-1 cells were incubated with 0, 2.5, 5, 10, 25 and 50 mM vorinostat for 24, 48 and 72 h. Cells were harvested 
and stained with annexin-V-APC and propidium iodide as an apoptosis readout or stained for loss of mitochondrial outer membrane potential (MOMP, DCm) using the 
mitochondrial dye tetramethylrhodamine ethyl ester (TMRE). Cells were then analyzed by flow cytometry. The percentage of annexin-V-APC, propidium iodide double 
positive cells are shown in the left panels while cells that had lost the ability to bind TMRE (DCm) are in the right panels. Data are presented as mean±S.E.M. of three 
independent experiments </p>

<p>HDACi induce transcriptional responses 
JE Bolden et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>of a common set of genes, irrespective of cellular phenotype 
or the tissues from which cells were originally isolated, 
and that a restricted set of genes are particularly amenable 
to transcriptional modulation following HDACi treatment. 
Many genes responded differently to vorinostat treatment in 
normal and transformed cells and a tumor-cell-selective 
pro-apoptotic gene-expression signature was identified. 
A role for HDACi-mediated repression of BCL2A1 in the 
induction of tumor cell apoptosis was confirmed, and we 
formally demonstrated that the intrinsic apoptotic pathway 
was required for the cytotoxic activities of HDACi in 
transformed BJ fibroblasts. 
A link between tumor-cell-selective gene induction and cell 
death following HDACi treatment was previously pro-
posed. 
35,36 Kobayashi et al. analyzed romidepsin-mediated 
transcriptional responses in non-donor-matched normal 
melanocytes and melanoma cell lines and noted that RAP1A 
was selectively induced in melanoma cells, and was important 
for the cytotoxic effect of romidepsin in these cells. By 
contrast, we found RAP1A to be more highly induced in 
normal BJ fibroblasts than in BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts (data 
not shown), suggesting that any contribution of RAP1A 
towards HDACi-mediated cytotoxicity is likely to be cell-
type-dependent. Noh et al. 
36 investigated the transcriptional 
responses of non-donor-matched normal bronchial epithelium 
and lung cancer cells following TSA treatment. That study 
showed TSA mediated tumor-selective induction of CDKN1A 
and tumor-selective repression of ERBB2, 
36 both of which 
were also tumor-cell-selective events in our microarray study. 
Chiba et al. 
37 reported on the transcriptional responses of 
non-donor-matched hepatocytes and hepatocellular carci-
noma cells. In agreement with our study, an approximately 
equal number of genes were activated and repressed in 
normal cells following HDACi treatment, although in our study </p>

<p>a considerably higher percentage of total genes on the array 
were significantly modulated by vorinostat. </p>

<p>38   Previous studies had proposed that altered ROS production 
and differential expression of ROS scavengers governs the 
differential sensitivity of normal and transformed cells to 
HDACi-mediated apoptosis. 
31-33 We did not observe any 
vorinostat-mediated transcriptional alteration in thioredoxin 
gene (TXN) expression in normal or transformed cells. 
Moreover, the gene encoding TBP-2 (TXNIP) was equiva-
lently induced with vorinostat treatment in both cell types. 
Therefore, vorinostat-mediated transcriptional modulation of 
TXN and TXNIP was unlikely to be a direct determinant of 
normal BJ fibroblast resistance, or transformed BJ fibroblast 
sensitivity to vorinostat-mediated apoptosis. 
The most notable finding from our candidate and GO 
studies was the direction in which pro-and anti-apoptotic 
genes were transcriptionally altered in the normal and 
transformed cells. Vorinostat-treated BJ LTSTERas fibro-
blasts elicited a strong pro-apoptotic transcriptional response, 
consisting of the induction of pro-apoptotic BCL2-family genes 
and the concomitant repression of pro-survival genes. 
Although BCL2L1 and BCL2L2 were repressed in normal 
cells following vorinostat treatment, other pro-apoptotic genes 
such as BAX, BAD and BID were also downregulated. 
Collectively, these data supported a model in which a tumor-
cell-selective alteration in the balance between pro-and anti-
apoptotic molecules following HDACi treatment ultimately 
determines the apoptotic sensitivity of cells exposed to these 
agents (Figure 8). 
Previous studies have shown that HDACi can induce pro-
death transcriptional signatures in human tumor lines. </p>

<p>39-41   The regulation of BCL2 family genes by HDACi in normal 
cells has to our knowledge not previously been investi-
gated, making this study the first to characterize a </p>

<p>Normal </p>

<p>BCL2L11 </p>

<p>BCL2L1 </p>

<p>BCL2L2 
BAD </p>

<p>BAX </p>

<p>Tumour </p>

<p>BIK </p>

<p>BCL2L11 </p>

<p>BAD </p>

<p>BAK1 
BCL2A1 </p>

<p>BCL2L1 </p>

<p>BCL2L2 </p>

<p>BID </p>

<p>pro-survival BCL2 family </p>

<p>pro-apoptotic BCL2 family </p>

<p>pro-apoptotic BCL2 family </p>

<p>pro-survival BCL2 family </p>

<p>survival 
death 
survival 
death </p>

<p>MCL1 
BID </p>

<p>survival 
death </p>

<p>PMAIP1 </p>

<p>+ vorinostat </p>

<p>Figure 8 Model for the induction of tumor-selective apoptosis by vorinostat. The tumor-selective induction of apoptosis following vorinostat treatment may be due to acute 
alterations in the expression of pro-survival and pro-apoptotic BCL2 family genes. The vorinostat-mediated transcription changes observed in BJ LTSTERas cells are 
hypothesized to tip the balance of pro-survival and pro-apoptotic gene expression in a direction that favors cell death. Although pro-survival and pro-apoptotic expression 
changes were observed in normal cells, the net change of expression in terms of ability to 'tip the balance' is relatively neutral. Genes are pseudo-colored according to the 
direction of gene expression change at the 24-h time point, relative to time 0 h: induced (red) and repressed (green), and are placed on the balance according to whether the 
expression change is expected to confer a pro-death or pro-survival response </p>

<p>HDACi induce transcriptional responses 
JE Bolden et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>vorinostat-mediated BCL2 family transcriptional signature in 
donor-matched normal and transformed cells. The vorinostat-
regulated BCL2 family genes identified herein (e.g., BMF, 
BCL2L11, PMAIP1, BCL2L1) have also been shown in 
independent studies to impinge upon HDACi-mediated 
apoptosis in tumor cells, 
16,27,42-45 suggesting that tumor-
cell-selective regulation of pro-apoptotic genes might be a 
common mechanism employed by HDACi to exert their tumor-
selective cytotoxic effect. 
BCL2L11 and BMF were rapidly induced early by vorino-
stat, indicating that they may be primary HDACi-response 
genes as has been reported in the literature for BMF. </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>Despite the early transcriptional induction, an increase in BMF 
protein (selectively in tumor cells) was detected considerably 
later (24 h), and was consistent with BMF being a possible 
mediator of apoptosis in BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts. Previous 
reports suggested that elevated BIM expression alone 
(through deregulated E2F-1 activity) by HDACi was sufficient 
to induce apoptosis in E1A-expressing human fibroblasts. </p>

<p>43,44   Moreover, BIM was reportedly important for the induction of 
apoptosis by HDACi in leukemic cell lines and primary cells 
from patients with chronic lymphocytic leukemia. 
42 We did 
observe vorinostat-and romidepsin-mediated induction of 
BCL2L11 mRNA by microarray and qRT-PCR in normal and 
transformed cells. Moreover, BIM EL protein levels were 
elevated in both normal and transformed cells well before 
the onset of apoptosis (BIM induction was observed at 4 h). 
These data were, therefore, inconsistent with BIM being the 
critical mediator of tumor-cell-selective apoptosis in the BJ 
fibroblast system and support the notion that BIM might 
instead cooperate with the many other HDACi-induced BH3-
only proteins (such as BMF and BIK) to induce apoptosis in 
sensitive cells. 
Our data suggest that pro-death gene expression changes 
are likely to be important for the tumor-selective effects of 
HDACi; however, it is not yet known whether the HDACi 
signatures are driven by histone hyperacetylation in the 
promoters of specific loci and/or if gene modulation is due to 
the altered activities of transcription regulators. A recent 
report demonstrated a correlation between vorinotat-
mediated induction of BMF, NOXA and BCL2L11 and histone 
H4 hyperacetylation within the promoter regions of these 
genes following HDACi treatment. 
42 Whether such a correla-
tion between HDACi-mediated selective induction of gene 
expression and promoter histone acetylation occurs on a 
global scale and is the basis for the tumor cell-specific effects 
of these anti-cancer agents remains to be determined. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods 
Cell culture. BJ and BJ LTSTERas cells (kindly provided by Professor William 
Hahn, Dan Farber Cancer Institute, Boston, MA, USA) were grown in media 
containing four parts HEPES buffered DMEM, pH 7.4 (SAFC Biosciences, 
Brooklyn, Australia) to one part Medium 199 (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA), 
supplemented with 15% (v/v) fetal bovine serum (FBS; Commonwealth Serum 
Laboratories, Parkville, Australia), 1 Â GlutaMAX (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, 
USA), 100 U/ml penicillin and 100 mg/ml streptomycin (Life Technologies, Inc., 
Grand Island, NY, USA). BMECs were cultured in Medium 199 (Biowhittaker, 
Walkersville, MD, USA) supplemented with 20% FBS, 3% human serum, 20 mg/ml 
endothelial cell growth factor (Biomedical Technologies, Stroughton, MA, USA), 
90 mg/ml sodium heparin (Sigma), 2 mM L-Glutamine, 80 U/ml penicillin and 80 mg/ 
ml streptomycin. The establishment of transformed BMEC (previously referred to 
as BMSVhTERT-4Nras) was previously described. 
19 Transformed BMEC were </p>

<p>maintained in Iscove's Modified Dulbecco's Medium (IMDM; Life Technologies) 
with 20% FBS. All cells were maintained at 37 1C in a humidified incubator 
containing 5% CO 2 . </p>

<p>Chemical compounds. Vorinostat (100 mM) and CHX (5, 50, 500 mg/ml) 
stock solutions were made in DMSO (Sigma) and stored at À 20 1C. Romidepsin 
was dissolved in 80% (v/v) 1,2 propanediol, 20% (v/v) ethanol by the Peter 
MacCallum Cancer Centre Pharmacy, and diluted to a 1 mM stock concentration 
and stored at À 20 1C. Stocks were further diluted to working concentrations with 
growth media immediately before use. Cells were incubated with 0-50 mM 
vorinostat for 0 À 72 h, 0-50 nM romidepsin for 0-48 h and 50 mM etoposide for 
0-48 h to induce cell death and protein hyperacetylation. To inhibit new protein 
synthesis, cells were pre-treated (prior to the addition of HDACi) with 5, 50, 250 or 
500 ng/ml CHX for 1 h, and CHX was left in media throughout the HDACi 
treatment time course. </p>

<p>In vitro cell death analysis. BJ fibroblasts (5 Â 10 
4 cells) were seeded into 
wells of six-well plates (Greiner Bio-One, Stonehouse, UK). BMEC (1 Â 10 
5 cells) 
were seeded into 0.1% gelatin coated six-well plates. Cells were allowed to adhere 
overnight. Immediately prior to each experiment, spent media was replaced with 
fresh media and drugs/vehicles were added to working concentrations from stock 
solutions. At nominated time points, all floating and adherent cells (detached by 
trypsinization) were collected, washed with PBS, stained for viability markers and 
analyzed by flow cytometry. Mitochondrial outer-membrane permeability was 
measured with tetramethyl-rhodamine ethyl ester (TMRE-Molecular Probes, 
Eugene, OR, USA) 
46 and DNA content determined by propidium iodide staining as 
previously described. 
16,17 Cell viability was measured by propidium iodide uptake 
and Annexin-V-APC staining. Briefly, cells were resuspended in annexin-V binding 
buffer (10 mM Hepes pH 7.4, 140 mM NaCl, 5 mM CaCl 2 ) containing 1/200 dilution 
of annexin-V-APC (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA) and 1/100 dilution of PI 
citrate buffer. Cells were analyzed using LSRII and FACSCanto II flow cytometers 
(BD Biosciences). </p>

<p>Western blotting. Cells (1 Â 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) were seeded onto 10-cm plates and 
incubated in the presence of 25 mM vorinostat or DMSO. Cells were harvested by 
scraping into ice-cold PBS, washed once with PBS and lysed as described below. 
For analysis of BMF, BIK and BFL-1 cells were lysed in ice-cold whole-cell lysis 
buffer (150 mM NaCl, 50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 0.1 mM EDTA, 0.1 mM EGTA, 0.5% 
Triton X-100, 10% glycerol) supplemented with protease inhibitors (1 mg/ml 
Aprotinin, 1 mg/ml Leupeptin, 1 mg/ml Pepstatin and 2 mM PMSF) for 1 h, and the 
extracts cleared by centrifugation. For the analysis of acetylated proteins and BIM, 
cells were lysed on ice for 5 min with SDS lysis buffer (250 mM NaCl, 50 mM Tris-
HCl pH 7.5, 5 mM EDTA, 0.1% SDS, 1% Triton X-100, 1% sodium deoxycholate, 
20% glycerol, 1 mg/ml Aprotinin, 1 mg/ml Leupeptin, 1 mg/ml Pepstatin and 2 mM 
PMSF), sonicated twice for 15 s and extracts cleared by centrifugation. Proteins 
were separated on SDS-polyacrylamide gels and electroblotted onto Immobilon-P 
membranes (Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA). The following primary antibodies were 
used: anti-Acetylated tubulin (Clone 6-11 B-1, Sigma), anti-acetylated H3 (Upstate, 
Bellerica, MA, USA), anti-a-tubulin (Clone B-5-1-2, Sigma) anti-b-Actin (Clone 
AC-74, Sigma), anti-BMF (Abcam, Cambridge, UK), anti-BIM (Stressgen, 
Farmingdale, NY, USA), anti-BIK (Santa Cruz, Dallas, TX, USA) and anti-FLAG 
(M2, Sigma). Membranes were incubated overnight with primary antibodies at 4 1C, 
followed by short-term incubation with horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated 
secondary antibodies (DAKO) at room temperature. Immunoreactive bands were 
visualized by enhanced chemiluminescence (GE Healthcare, Little Chalfont, UK). </p>

<p>Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction. RNA was 
prepared from vehicle-and drug-treated cells (1 Â 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) using 1 ml TRIzol 
reagent according to the manufacturer's instructions (Invitrogen). RNA was 
resuspended in diethyl pyrocarbonate (DEPC)-treated, autoclaved MQH 2 O and 
first-strand cDNA was subsequently prepared using a random primer technique 
according to the manufacturer's instructions (Promega, Madison, WI, USA). 
Quantitative real-time PCR reactions were performed in triplicate using the SYBR 
green detection method in a 384-well plate format. Amplification and fluorescence 
detection was performed in a 7900 HT fast real-time PCR system with <rs id="software-8" type="software">SDS</rs> v<rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-number">2.3</rs> 
software (Applied Biosystems, Grand Island, NY, USA). Initial denaturation of 
template and enzyme activation was performed at 95 1C for 15 min followed by 40 
cycles of 95 1C for 30 s, 65 1C for 30 s. Dissociation protocols were always 
performed for each qRT-PCR reaction to ensure the presence of a single 'major' 
amplification product per well. An average Ct value for the three technical </p>

<p>HDACi induce transcriptional responses 
JE Bolden et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>replicates was calculated for each sample. Fold-change expression of 'test' mRNA 
was determined relative to RPL32 expression using the 2 
À DDCt method. 
Expression fold-change over time was plotted relative to mRNA expression at the 
0 h time point. </p>

<p>QRT-PCR primer sequences (5 
0 -3 
0 ) </p>

<p>RPL32. Forward TTCCTGGTCCACAACGTCAAG 
Reverse TTGTGAGCGATCTCGGCAC </p>

<p>CDKN1A. Forward GGCGGCAGACCAGCATGACAGATT 
Reverse GCAGGGGGCGGCCAGGGTAT </p>

<p>BCL2A1 (BFL-1). Forward CGTAGACACTGCCAGAACACTA 
Reverse GGGCAATTTGCTGTCGTAGA </p>

<p>BAK1. Forward ACACTTGCTCCCAACCCATTCA 
Reverse AACCAAGTCCTAAGCCCTGT </p>

<p>BIK. Forward ATCTTGATGGAGACCCTCCTGT 
Reverse TCACTGCCCTCCATGCATT </p>

<p>BMF. Forward ACCAGCCAGGAAGACAAAGCT 
Reverse CGATAGCCAGCATTGCCATAA </p>

<p>BAD. Forward AGTGACGAGTTTGTGGACTCCT 
Reverse AGCTTTGCCGCATCTGCGTT </p>

<p>BCL2L11 (BIM). Reverse GTTGCTTTGCCATTTGGTCT 
Forward CCACCACTTGATTCTTGCAG </p>

<p>Microarray hybridizations. Total RNA (2 mg) was prepared for hybridiza-
tion to Affymetrix GeneChip Human Genome U133 Plus 2.0 Arrays according to 
the manufacturer's recommendations. Poly-A RNA controls from Bacillus subtilis 
(lys, phe, thr and dap) were diluted in Poly-A control dilution buffer (serial dilutions 
of 1 : 20, 1 : 50 and 1 : 25) and 2 ml of the third serial dilution was spiked into each 
RNA sample prior to cDNA synthesis. RNA was reverse transcribed using a one-
cycle cDNA synthesis kit (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA, USA) and all annealing, 
amplification and incubation steps were performed in accordance with the 
manufacturer's instructions. Double-stranded cDNA was purified using a 
GeneChip sample cleanup module according to the manufacturer's instructions 
(Affymetrix) and cDNA was eluted from columns with 14 ml cDNA elution buffer. 
Biotin-labeled cRNA was synthesized from cDNA using a GeneChip IVT labeling 
kit (Affymetrix) in a total reaction volume of 40 ml. cRNA was purified and 
concentrated using the GeneChip sample cleanup module. Full-length cRNA 
(20 mg) was fragmented to 35-200 bp lengths by incubation with cRNA 
fragmentation reagent for 35 min at 94 1C. Fragmented cRNA (15 mg) was added 
to a hybridization mix according to Affymetrix instructions and hybridized to 
Affymetrix HG U133 plus 2.0 probe arrays at 45 1C in an Affymetrix Hybridization 
oven 640 with 60 r.p.m. rotation for 16 h. Array washes and three-stage 
streptavidin phycoerythrin (SAPE) staining was performed according to the 
manufacturer's instructions on a GeneChip fluidics station 450 (Affymetrix). HG 
U133 plus 2.0 arrays were individually scanned using an Affymetrix GeneChip 
3000 scanner with <rs id="software-9" type="software">GeneChip Operating Software</rs> (GCOS, <rs corresp="#software-9" type="creator">Affymetrix</rs>). </p>

<p>Microarray differential expression analyses. Intensities from the 
Affymetrix arrays were background corrected, normalized and summarized 
using the GC-Robust Multi-Array Analysis (GC-RMA) algorithm. 
47 Probe sets 
were defined by the default Affymetrix HG U133 plus 2.0 chip definition file. Box-
plots of expression intensities and RNA degradation plots confirmed good 
consistent quality of the samples and the hybridizations. Microarray data are 
available through the Gene Expression Omnibus, GEO accession number 
GSE43010. 
Differential expression analysis of the normalized log2-expression values was 
performed using the <rs corresp="#software-10" type="creator">Bioconductor</rs> software package <rs id="software-10" type="software">limma</rs>. 
48 All the arrays were 
analyzed together using a linear model. Empirical Bayes moderated t-tests were 
used to assess differential expression between the BJ and BJLTSTERas fibroblasts 
and between untreated and treated cells. 
48-50 Specifically, baseline differences 
between the cell lines were identified by comparing untreated BJ and to BJ 
LTSTERas fibroblasts at time 0 h. Probe sets responding to DMSO or vorinostat </p>

<p>were identified by comparing each of the 4, 12 or 24 h time points back to untreated 
cells, and this was done separately for BJ and BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts. For all 
comparisons, probe sets were considered to be significantly differentially expressed 
if the fold-change exceeded 1.5 (i.e., 50% difference in expression) and the FDR 
was o0.05. </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>Probe sets responding differently to vorinostat treatment in BJ LTSTERas 
fibroblasts as compared with BJ cells (i.e., contrast genes), were identified using 
empirical Bayes moderated F-tests. 
49,50 F-tests allowed us to combine information 
across the three treatment time points, looking for probe-sets with differing 
responses at any of the times. First we used an F-test to find probe sets whose gene 
expression changes (from 0 h to any of 4, 12 or 24 h vorinostat treatment) were 
different in BJ fibroblasts compared with BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts. This test is 
analogous to testing for interaction in a two-way ANOVA. Second, we subtracted 
from this list any probe set whose expression response to vorinostat could not be 
distinguished from that to DMSO (the vehicle control). To do this, we used an F-test 
to find probe sets whose response to vorinostat relative to DMSO was different 
between BJ fibroblasts and BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts at any of the paired time 
points. Only probe sets detected by both the above F-tests were retained in the 
contrast list. The final contrast list contained therefore only bona fide vorinostat-
responding genes. For all F-tests, probe sets were considered statistically significant 
if the FDR was o0.05 and at least one comparison involved in the test achieved a 
1.5-fold change. </p>

<p>GO analyses. Gene lists were tested for over-represented GO terms using the 
DAVID website. 
52 The Affymetrix HG U133 Plus 2.0 Array served as the 
background gene list. Only GO terms at specificity levels 4 or 5 within the directed 
acyclic graph hierarchy defined by the GO Consortium were included. 
53 The 
minimum hit threshold was set to 3. Over-represented GO terms were ordered by 
the EASE score P-value, a conservative modification of Fisher's Exact test 
designed to de-prioritise annotation terms containing very small numbers of 
genes. </p>

<p>54   Ingenuity pathway analyses. Gene lists and log2 expression fold-changes 
were uploaded into the <rs id="software-11" type="software">IPA</rs> tool (<rs corresp="#software-11" type="creator">Ingenuity Systems</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-11" type="url">www.ingenuity.com</rs>). 
When more than one probe set mapped to the same gene, the probe set 
with the largest fold-change was used. Pathways and interaction maps were 
constructed using the path designer function, with expression changes 
overlayed onto the pathways. Gene lists were also analyzed in <rs type="software">IPA</rs> for over-
represented cellular and molecular functions and for association with disease. 
P-values were adjusted by the Benjamini and Hochberg algorithm to control the 
FDR at o5%. </p>

<p>Connectivity map analyses. Probe sets with statistically significantly 
(F-test) responses to vorinostat at any time were ranked by their expression 
fold-change at 24 h versus 0 h, and this was performed separately for BJ and BJ 
LTSTERas cells. The 500 most induced and 500 most repressed probe sets were 
uploaded into the <rs id="software-18" type="software">Connectivity Map</rs> (Cmap) v<rs corresp="#software-18" type="version-number">02</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-18" type="url">http://www.broad.mit.edu/cmap</rs>). 
<rs type="software">Cmap</rs> ranked drug compounds with gene expression signatures similar to the 
uploaded gene lists on the basis of connectivity P-values and enrichment scores. </p>

<p>25   <rs type="software">Cmap</rs> required Affymetrix HG U133A probe set identifiers, so the identifiers from 
our HG U133 Plus 2.0 Arrays were mapped back to equivalent HG 133A probe 
sets using the <rs id="software-13" type="software">NetAffx analysis center</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-13" type="url">http://www.affymetrix.com/analysis/ index.affx</rs>). </p>

<p>Retroviral transduction of BJ LTSTERas fibroblasts. BFL-1 cDNA 
was cloned into the MSCV-IRES-GFP retroviral vector and transduction of BJ 
LSTERas cells was performed as previously described. </p>



<p>Conflict of Interest 
Dr. Johnstone's work has been funded by a research grant from Novartis. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements. We thank Ben Martin, Christopher Clarke and Richard 
Pearson for constructive criticism and helpful advice, and William Hahn for normal 
and transformed cell lines. RWJ is a Principal Research Fellow of the National 
Health and Medical Research Council of Australia (NHMRC) and supported by 
NHMRC Program and Project Grants, the Susan G Komen Breast Cancer 
Foundation, Cancer Council Victoria, The Victorian Cancer Agency, The Leukemia </p>

<p>HDACi induce transcriptional responses 
JE Bolden et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Foundation of Australia and the Victorian Breast Cancer Research Consortium. 
JEB was supported by The Cancer Research Institute Predoctoral Emphasis 
Pathway in Tumor Immunology. KLM was supported by funds from NHMRC, 
Cancer Institute NSW and NSW Cancer Council. GKS is a Senior Research 
Fellowship of the NHMRC. GKS and WS are supported by NHMRC Program Grant 
490037. </p>



<p>HDACi induce transcriptional responses 
JE Bolden et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>



<p>HDACi induce transcriptional responses 
JE Bolden et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

</text></tei>