<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3902401" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:48+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective: Prior studies have concentrated on the </p>

<p>acute short-term outcomes of sepsis, with little focus 
on its long-term consequences. The objective of this 
study was to characterise long-term mortality following 
a sepsis event. </p>

<p>Design: Population-based data from the 30 239 </p>

<p>community-dwelling individuals in the REasons for 
Geographic and Racial Differences in Stroke 
(REGARDS) cohort. </p>

<p>Setting: USA. 
Participants: Community-dwelling adults ≥45 years </p>

<p>of age. Sepsis was defined as hospitalisation or 
emergency department treatment for a serious 
infection with the presence of ≥2 systemic 
inflammatory response syndrome criteria. </p>

<p>Outcomes: 6-year all-cause mortality. The analysis </p>

<p>utilised a time-varying Cox model adjusted for 
participant's age, demographic factors, health 
behaviours and chronic medical conditions. </p>

<p>Results: The participants were observed for a median </p>

<p>of 6.1 years (IQR 4.5-7.1). During this period, 975 
individuals experienced a sepsis event. Sepsis hospital 
mortality was 8.9%. One-year, 2-year and 5-year all-
cause mortality among individuals with sepsis were 
23%, 28.8% and 43.8%, respectively, compared with 
death rates of 1%, 2.6% and 8.3% among those who 
never developed sepsis. On multivariable analysis, the 
association of sepsis with increased all-cause mortality 
persisted for up to 5 years, after adjustment for 
confounders; year 0.00-1.00, adjusted HR (aHR) 13.07 
(95% CI 10.admissions, 570 000 emergency department 
visits, 200 000 deaths and US$16.7 billion in 
medical expenditures annually in the USA. </p>

<p>1-3   While prior studies describe the acute care 
and course of individuals developing sepsis, 
relatively limited data characterise the long-
term consequences of a sepsis event. 
4 This 
gap in knowledge is important as the total 
public health impact of a disease encompasses 
not only the course of acute hospital care but 
also its downstream sequelae. Furthermore, 
compared with unaffected persons, an individ-
ual suffering from a disease-even after recov-
ery from the acute illness-may also 
experience a higher risk of long-term death. 
Prior studies describing mortality after 
sepsis have important limitations, including 
the lack of data describing health prior to 
the sepsis event, the use of hospital adminis-
trative data or data from single institutions or 
the focus on patients in intensive care 
units. 
4-8 Few studies have characterised the 
excess risk of long-term death attributable to 
a sepsis event or identified the independent 
predictors of early death after sepsis. 
The REasons for Geographic and Racial 
Differences in Stroke (REGARDS) study is 
one of the largest population-based longitu-
dinal cohorts of community-dwelling adults 
in the USA. In this study, we sought to char-
acterise long-term mortality after the hospital 
treatment for sepsis in the REGARDS cohort. </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ Study uses data from the 30 329 participants in 
the REasons for Geographic And Racial 
Differences in Stroke REGARDS cohort. 
▪ Participants were followed for over 6 years. 
▪ Study characterised long-term survival after a 
sepsis episode. 
▪ Robust analytic approach accounted for con-
founding effect for a wide range of participant 
characteristics. </p>

<p>Wang HE, Szychowski JM, Griffin R, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004283. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004283 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Study design 
This study utilised data from REGARDS, a national 
population-based longitudinal cohort. </p>

<p>Selection of participants 
Prior studies have described twofold increased stroke mor-
tality in the Southeastern US (the 'stroke belt') and three-
fold increased stroke mortality along the coastal plains of 
North Carolina, South Carolina and Georgia (the 'stroke 
buckle'). 
9 In addition, other studies highlight the 
increased stroke mortality among African-Americans. 
Being one of the largest ongoing national cohorts of 
community-dwelling individuals in the USA, REGARDS 
was designed to identify the reasons for the geographical 
and racial disparities. </p>

<p>9   REGARDS includes 30 239 community-dwelling adults 
≥45 years from all regions of the continental US. 
Participant 
representation 
oversampled 
the 
Southeastern US, with 21% of the cohort originating 
from the coastal plains of North Carolina, South 
Carolina and Georgia (the 'stroke buckle'), and 35% 
originating from the remainder of North Carolina, 
South Carolina and Georgia plus Tennessee, Mississippi, 
Alabama, Louisiana and Arkansas (the 'stroke belt'). 
The cohort is 42% African-American with 45% men and 
69% of individuals are &gt;60 years. The cohort does not 
include Hispanics where stroke mortality disparities are 
small to non-existent. The REGARDS cohort encom-
passes healthy community-dwelling adults-not just indi-
viduals with a history of stroke. 
REGARDS enrolled participants during 2003-2007. 
REGARDS obtained baseline data for each participant 
using the phone interview and in-person evaluations, 
including medical history, functional status, health beha-
viours, physical characteristics (height and weight), 
physiological measures (blood pressure, pulse and ECG) 
and an inventory of medications. Each participant pro-
vided blood and urine specimens. Self-administered 
questionnaires evaluated diet, family history of diseases, 
psychosocial factors and prior residences. The study con-
tacted participants at 6-month intervals by telephone, 
identifying the date, location and attributed reason for 
all emergency department visits and hospitalisations 
during the follow-up period. The study then retrieved 
medical records for specific health events. If the partici-
pant died, the study team reviewed death certificates 
and medical records and interviewed proxies to ascer-
tain the circumstances of the participant's death. </p>

<p>Identification of sepsis events 
Using the taxonomy of serious infections by Angus et al, </p>

<p>1   we identified all hospitalisations (emergency department 
visits and/or hospital admission) attributed by partici-
pants to a serious infection. Two trained abstractors 
independently reviewed all relevant medical records to 
identify clinical and laboratory information, confirm the 
presence of a serious infection on initial hospital </p>

<p>presentation and to verify the relevance of the serious 
infection as a major reason for hospitalisation. Initial 
review of 1349 hospital records indicated excellent inter-
rater agreement for the presence of a serious infection 
(κ=0.92) and the presence of sepsis (κ=0.90) on hospital 
presentation. 
Sepsis consisted of presentation to the hospital with an 
infection plus two or more systemic inflammatory 
response syndrome (SIRS) criteria, including (1) heart 
rate &gt;90 bpm, (2) fever (temperature &gt;38.3°C or &lt;36°C), 
(3) tachypnoea (&gt;20 breaths/min) or partial pressure of 
carbon dioxide &lt;32 mm Hg and (4) leukocytosis (white 
cell count &gt;12 000 or &lt;4000 cells/mm 
3 or &gt;10% band 
forms). 
10 We defined SIRS using any asynchronous com-
bination of the worst vital signs and laboratory test 
results for the initial 28 h of hospitalisation. We chose a 
28 h time frame to account for emergency department 
and up to one full day of inpatient treatment. Because 
our study focused on 'community-acquired' sepsis rather 
than 'hospital-acquired' sepsis, we did not utilise vital 
signs or laboratory findings from later points during hos-
pitalisation. The study follow-up period was from 5 
February 2003 to 30 July 2012. </p>

<p>Outcomes 
The primary outcome was all-cause mortality. The 
REGARDS study ascertained all-cause mortality through 
active follow-up with participants or proxies, plus 
searches of the Social Security Administration's Master 
Death File and the National Death Index. Observations 
were censored at the date of death or last follow-up. 
Available for a portion (74.5%) of deaths, cause of death 
was determined by dual-physician review and adjudica-
tion of death records, next-of-kin or proxy reports and 
hospitalisation records. </p>

<p>Covariates 
Demographic characteristics included age, sex, race, geo-
graphical region and self-reported annual household 
income and education (years of school). As conducted 
for the parent REGARDS cohort, geographical region 
consisted of participant's residence in the stroke 'buckle,' 
stroke 'belt' and elsewhere. 
9 Health behaviours included 
smoking status and alcohol use. Alcohol use categories 
included none, moderate (1 drink per day for women or 
2 drinks per day for men) and heavy (&gt;1 drink per day 
for women and &gt;2 drinks per day for men). 
11 To charac-
terise baseline health status, we used quintiles of the phys-
ical composite score and mental composite score of the 
Short Form-12 (SF-12) health survey. 
Chronic medical conditions included atrial fibrillation, 
cancer history, chronic lung disease, chronic kidney 
disease, coronary artery disease, deep vein thrombosis, 
diabetes, dyslipidaemia, hypertension, myocardial infarc-
tion, obesity, peripheral artery disease and stroke. We 
identified atrial fibrillation based on participants' self-
report or baseline ECG evidence. Chronic kidney 
disease included individuals with an estimated </p>



<p>Wang HE, Szychowski JM, Griffin R, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004283. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004283 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>glomerular filtration rate &lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m 
2 calcu-
lated using the Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology 
Collaboration CKD-EPIequation. </p>

<p>12   Coronary artery 
disease included a history of myocardial infarction or 
coronary intervention. Diabetes included a fasting 
glucose ≥126 mg/L (or a glucose ≥200 mg/L for those 
not fasting) or the use of insulin or oral hypoglycaemic 
agents. Dyslipidaemia included individuals with self-
reported high cholesterol or the use of lipid-lowering 
medications. Hypertension consisted of systolic blood 
pressure ≥140 mm Hg, diastolic blood pressure 
≥90 mm Hg or the self-reported use of antihypertensive 
agents. Myocardial infarction included individuals with a 
self-reported history of myocardial infarction or baseline 
ECG evidence of myocardial infarction. 
Obesity included those with a waist circumference 
&gt;102 cm for men or &gt;88 cm for women, or body mass 
index ≥30 mg/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. 
13 Participants self-reported the 
history of stroke (including transient ischaemic attacks) 
or deep vein thrombosis. Peripheral artery disease 
included a self-reported history of lower extremity arter-
ial bypass or leg amputation. Because REGARDS did not 
collect information on pulmonary conditions such as 
asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, we 
defined participants' use of pulmonary medications as a 
surrogate for chronic lung disease, including β agonists, 
leukotriene inhibitors, inhaled corticosteroids, combin-
ation inhalers, ipratropium, cromolyn, aminophylline 
and theophylline. 
For sepsis hospitalisations, we also identified organ 
dysfunctions using the Sequential Organ Failure 
Assessment (SOFA) based on the worst laboratory and 
physiological findings during the first 28 h of hospitalisa-
tion for respiratory, renal, hepatic, cardiovascular, haem-
atological and neurological systems. </p>

<p>14   Data analysis 
We sought to compare the adjusted risk of all-cause mor-
tality between sepsis and non-sepsis individuals as a func-
tion of follow-up time. Follow-up time consisted of (1) 
years after first sepsis event for individuals with sepsis, 
and (2) years after study enrolment for non-sepsis indivi-
duals. We assumed that non-sepsis participants were rep-
resentative of the general population, exhibited relative 
constant risk and entered the study relative to no par-
ticular health event. Therefore, the start of the follow-up 
period for non-sepsis individuals could be defined rela-
tive to any arbitrary event. 
Because of the non-proportional nature of the relative 
hazards of death, we fit a time-varying Cox regression 
model in a piecewise manner, calculating the hazards of 
death in 1-year intervals. 
15 To account for differing 
observation start times, we adjusted the model for age at 
the start of the follow-up period (age decile at sepsis 
event for individuals with sepsis, and age decile at 
REGARDS enrolment for non-sepsis participants). We 
adjusted the hazard estimates for participants' </p>

<p>demographic characteristics, baseline function, health 
behaviours and chronic medical conditions. 
To account for potential clustering of deaths within 
each stroke belt region (stroke belt, stroke buckle and 
non-belt), we repeated the analysis (1) using a robust 
variance estimator, and (2) modelling stroke belt region 
as a shared frailty, which are two common approaches to 
analysing clustered data in time-to-event analysis. Owing 
to the time lag in observations and medical record 
retrieval, we could not review medical records for a 
portion of participants with reported hospitalisations for 
a serious infection over the observation period. We 
therefore repeated the analysis excluding these indivi-
duals from the non-sepsis group. We also repeated the 
analysis stratifying by uncomplicated sepsis (infection 
+SIRS criteria only) versus severe sepsis (sepsis+organ 
dysfunction). 
To identify participant characteristics independently 
associated with early death after sepsis, among indivi-
duals with sepsis, only we fit a Cox model with age at 
sepsis, sex, race, tobacco and alcohol use, chronic 
medical conditions, infection type, admission to inten-
sive care unit and SOFA score on hospital presentation 
in the regression model. 
We conducted all analyses using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata</rs> V.<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">12.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Stata, Inc</rs>, College Station, Texas, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Valid follow-up data were available for 29 664 REGARDS 
participants, including 970 sepsis and 28 694 non-sepsis 
individuals. Median follow-up time was 6.1 years (IQR 
4.5-7.1). Sepsis incidence was 5.8/1000 person-years 
(95% CI 5.4 to 6.2). Median time to the first sepsis event 
was 1.9 years (IQR 3.5-5.0). The most common infection 
types associated with incident sepsis were pneumonia, </p>

<p>Table 1 Infection types associated with first 
hospitalisations for sepsis </p>

<p>Infection type </p>

<p>Number of first sepsis 
hospitalisations 
N (%) </p>

<p>Pneumonia 
412 (42.5) 
Kidney and urinary tract 
infections </p>

<p>155 (16.0) </p>

<p>Abdominal 
137 (14.1) 
Bronchitis, influenza and other 
lung infections </p>

<p>88 (9.1) </p>

<p>Skin and soft tissue 
74 (7.6) 
Sepsis 
58 (6.0) 
Fever of unknown origin 
15 (1.6) 
Catheter (intravenous/central/ 
dialysis) </p>

<p>5 (0.5) </p>

<p>Surgical wound 
7 (0.7) 
Meningitis 
3 (0.3) 
Unknown/other 
16 (16.5) </p>

<p>Total of 970 first-sepsis events. </p>

<p>Wang HE, Szychowski JM, Griffin R, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004283. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004283 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Table 2 Baseline patient characteristics </p>

<p>Characteristics </p>

<p>Sepsis (n=970) 
N (%) </p>

<p>Non-sepsis (n=28 694) 
N (%) 
p Value* </p>

<p>Demographics 
Age decile 
&lt;50 
14 (1.4) 
1460 (5.1) 
&lt;0.001 
50-59 
171 (17.6) 
7581 (26.4) 
60-69 
343 (35.4) 
10 835 (37.8) 
70-79 
311 (32.1) 
6839 (23.8) 
≥80 
131 (13.5) 
1979 (6.9) 
Gender 
Male 
508 (52.4) 
12 812 (44.7) 
&lt;0.001 
Female 
462 (47.6) 
15 882 (55.4) 
Race 
White 
662 (68.3) 
16 802 (58.6) 
&lt;0.001 
Black 
308 (31.8) 
11 892 (41.4) 
Education 
Less than high school 
153 (15.8) 
3547 (12.4) 
&lt;0.001 
High school graduate 
275 (28.4) 
7387 (25.7) 
Some college 
272 (28.0) 
7670 (26.7) 
College or higher 
268 (27.6) 
10 069 (35.1) 
Unknown 
2 (0.2) 
21 (0.01) 
Income 
&lt;US$20k 
238 (24.5) 
5102 (17.8) 
&lt;0.001 
US$20k-US$34k 
272 (28.0) 
6892 (24.0) 
US$35k-US$74k 
254 (26.2) 
8552 (29.8) 
≥US$75k 
103 (10.6) 
4587 (16.0) 
Unknown (refused) 
970 (10.6) 
3561 (12.4) 
Geographical region 
Stroke buckle 
209 (21.6) 
6003 (20.9) 
0.04 
Stroke belt 
367 (37.8) 
9910 (34.5) 
Non-belt/buckle 
394 (40.6) 
12 781 (44.5) 
Health status-physical composite score 
Quintile 1 (≤37.002) 
352 (36.3) 
5314 (18.5) 
&lt;0.001 
Quintile 2 (37.006-46.949) 
208 (21.4) 
5482 (19.1) 
Quintile 3 (46.951-52.111) 
145 (15.0) 
5545 (19.3) 
Quintile 4 (52.112-55.501) 
136 (14.0) 
6126 (21.4) 
Quintile 5 (≥55.502) 
76 (7.8) 
4945 (17.2) 
Missing 
53 (5.46) 
1282 (4.47) 
Health status-mental composite score 
Quintile 1 (≤49.591) 
224 (23.1) 
5442 (19.0) 
&lt;0.001 
Quintile 2 (49.592-55.282) 
188 (19.4) 
5481 (19.1) 
Quintile 3 (55.282-57.827) 
143 (14.9) 
5741 (20.0) 
Quintile 4 (57.828-59.872) 
144 (14.9) 
5459 (19.0) 
Quintile 5 (≥59.872) 
218 (22.5) 
5289 (18.4) 
Missing 
53 (5.5) 
1282 (4.5) 
Health behaviours 
Tobacco use 
Current 
173 (17.8) 
4106 (14.3) 
&lt;0.001 
Past 
471 (48.6) 
11 432 (39.8) 
Never 
323 (33.3) 
13 045 (45.5) 
Unknown 
3 (0.3) 
111 (0.4) 
Alcohol use 
Heavy 
39 (4.0) 
1136 (4.0) 
0.07 
Moderate 
279 (28.8) 
9406 (32.8) 
None 
631 (65.1) 
17 593 (61.3) 
Unknown 
21 (2.2) 
559 (2.0) 
Chronic medical conditions 
Atrial fibrillation 
128 (13.2) 
2418 (8.4) 
&lt;0.001 
Cancer history 
131 (13.5) 
3484 (8.7) 
&lt;0.001 
Continued </p>



<p>Wang HE, Szychowski JM, Griffin R, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004283. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004283 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>kidney and urinary tract infections and abdominal infec-
tions (table 1). Compared with non-sepsis participants, 
individuals with sepsis were older, more likely to be 
male, had lower income and education, were more likely 
to use alcohol or tobacco and were more likely to have 
chronic medical conditions (table 2). 
There were 324 deaths among 970 individuals with 
sepsis (33.4%) and 3155 deaths among 28 694 non-
sepsis individuals (11%). The incidence of death was 
141/1000 person-years for sepsis and 19.2/1000 person-
years for non-sepsis individuals (table 3). Adjudicated 
cause of death was available for 84.6% of sepsis and 
73.5% of non-sepsis deaths; the most common adjudi-
cated causes of death among individuals with sepsis were 
infection, lung disease and cancer (table 4). 
Among all first-sepsis events, 86 (8.9%) patients died 
in the hospital, with a median time to death of 7 days 
(IQR 3-15). One-year, 2-year and 5-year all-cause mortal-
ity among individuals with sepsis were 23%, 28.8% and 
43.8%, respectively (figure 1). One-year, 2-year and 
5-year all-cause mortality among non-sepsis individuals 
were 1%, 2.6% and 8.3%, respectively. Compared with 
non-sepsis persons, the rate of death was high among 
individuals with sepsis in the first year after the event </p>

<p>(adjusted HR 13.07; 95% CI 10.63 to 16.06; figure 2 and 
see online supplementary appendix 1). Among those 
who survived for at least 1 year, individuals with sepsis 
exhibited twofold increased rates of death for up to 
5 years after the sepsis event. 
To account for potential clustering of deaths within 
stroke belt region, we repeated the analysis using a 
robust variance estimator; we observed similar associa-
tions between sepsis and rates of long-term mortality; 
however, the higher rate of death among individuals 
with sepsis was statistically significant in the sixth year of 
follow-up. When repeating the analysis modelling stroke 
belt region as a shared frailty, we observed no major 
changes in the associations between sepsis and rates of 
all-cause mortality. When repeating the analysis exclud-
ing the 1310 non-sepsis individuals who had unadjudi-
cated possible sepsis events, we observed similar 
associations between sepsis and long-term mortality. 
We stratified the analysis by uncomplicated sepsis 
(n=257) versus severe sepsis (n=713). Compared with 
non-sepsis individuals, the adjusted rate of death was 
twofold higher for 1 year among those experiencing 
uncomplicated sepsis (see online supplementary appen-
dix 2). Among those who survived at least 1 year, the </p>

<p>Table 2 Continued </p>

<p>Characteristics </p>

<p>Sepsis (n=970) 
N (%) </p>

<p>Non-sepsis (n=28 694) 
N (%) 
p Value* </p>

<p>Chronic lung disease 
201 (20.7) 
2529 (8.8) 
&lt;0.001 
Chronic kidney disease 
210 (21.7) 
3034 (10.6) 
&lt;0.001 
Coronary artery disease 
277 (28.6) 
4948 (17.2) 
&lt;0.001 
Deep vein thrombosis 
89 (9.2) 
1464 (5.1) 
&lt;0.001 
Diabetes 
328 (33.8) 
6369 (22.2) 
&lt;0.001 
Dyslipidaemia 
618 (63.7) 
16 331 (56.9) 
&lt;0.001 
Hypertension 
666 (68.7) 
16 863 (58.8) 
&lt;0.001 
Myocardial infarction 
205 (21.1) 
3510 (12.2) 
&lt;0.001 
Obesity (elevated waist circumference or body 
mass index ≥30 kg/m 
2 ) </p>

<p>609 (62.8) 
15 328 (53.4) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Peripheral artery disease 
46 (4.7) 
615 (2.1) 
&lt;0.001 
Stroke 
107 (11.0) 
1786 (6.2) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>*From χ 
2 test. </p>

<p>Table 3 Incidence of death for sepsis and non-sepsis individuals </p>

<p>Activity 
Person-time (person-years) 
Deaths 
Incidence (deaths per 1000 person-years) </p>

<p>Non-sepsis 
163 520 
3140 
19.2 (18.5-19.9) 
Sepsis 
2241 
316 
141.0 (126.3-157.5) 
Lung infection 
1132 
176 
155.4 (134.1-180.2) 
Kidney infection 
366 
51 
139.4 (105.9-183.4) 
Abdominal infection 
388 
25 
64.4 (43.5-95.3) 
Skin infection 
168 
23 
137.1 (91.1-206.4) 
'Sepsis' NOS 
82 
25 
306.2 (206.9-453.2) 
Other infections 
105 
16 
152.2 (93.2-248.4) 
Overall 
165 761 
3456 
20.8 (20.2-21.6) </p>

<p>Sepsis incidence further stratified by infection type. 
NOS, not otherwise specified. </p>

<p>Wang HE, Szychowski JM, Griffin R, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004283. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004283 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>adjusted rates of death were twofold higher for up to 
5 years among those experiencing severe sepsis. 
In the sepsis subset, participant characteristics inde-
pendently associated with increased rates of death after 
the sepsis event included male sex, health status ( phys-
ical component score), cancer history, chronic kidney 
disease, deep vein thrombosis, diabetes, dyslipidaemia, 
hypertension and obesity (table 5 and see online supple-
mentary appendix 3). Among hospital course character-
istics, death rates were higher among participants with 
increased sequential organ failure scores or admission to 
the intensive care unit. Rates of long-term death were 
lower for sepsis due to abdominal infections. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
For almost a decade, the Surviving Sepsis Campaign 
guidelines have advocated best practices for sepsis care 
with the goal of reducing the mortality associated with 
this condition. 
16 Drawing on REGARDS, one of the 
nation's 
largest 
population-based 
cohorts 
of 
community-dwelling adults, our study highlights that 
excess long-term all-cause mortality persists among those 
suffering from sepsis. Compared with individuals who 
did not develop sepsis, rates of death among individuals 
experiencing sepsis were twofold higher for up to 
5 years after the sepsis event. Our analysis adjusted for a 
range of potential confounders and observed relatively 
small attenuation of risk, suggesting that comorbidities 
are not playing the major role in this extended risk. </p>

<p>Our findings add to the body of knowledge highlight-
ing the downstream consequences of sepsis. As high-
lighted in Winters et al's 
4 systematic review, most sepsis 
mortality studies have focused on shorter endpoints, </p>

<p>Table 4 Adjudicated causes of death. </p>

<p>Adjudicated cause of 
death </p>

<p>Sepsis 
(n=274) 
N (%) </p>

<p>Non-sepsis 
(n=2318) 
N (%) </p>

<p>Infection 
88 (32.1) 
187 (8.1) 
Chronic lung disease 
36 (13.1) 
92 (4.0) 
Cancer 
31 (11.3) 
647 (27.9) 
Sudden death 
23 (8.4) 
272 (11.7) 
Myocardial infarction 
18 (6.6) 
253 (10.9) 
Heart failure 
15 (5.5) 
147 (6.3) 
Cerebrovascular accident 11 (4.0) 
160 (6.9) 
End-stage renal disease 
8 (2.9) 
65 (2.8) 
Accident, injury, suicide or 
homicide </p>

<p>3 (1.1) 
92 (4.0) </p>

<p>Liver disease 
2 (0.7) 
30 (1.3) 
Dementia 
1 (0.4) 
55 (2.4) 
Pulmonary embolism 
0 (0.0) 
24 (1.0) 
Other cardiovascular 
condition </p>

<p>11 (4.0) 
93 (4.0) </p>

<p>Other non-cardiovascular 
condition </p>

<p>17 (6.2) 
129 (5.6) </p>

<p>Unclassifiable 
10 (3.7) 
72 (3.1) </p>

<p>Adjudicated cause of death not available for 274 of 324 (84.6%) 
deaths among individuals with sepsis and 2318 of 3155 (73.5%) 
deaths among non-sepsis individuals. 
Includes 274 deaths among sepsis individuals and 2318 deaths 
among non-sepsis individuals. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Kaplan-Meier curves and 95% CIs for long-term 
survival after sepsis. Sepsis versus non-sepsis. Includes 970 
sepsis and 28 694 non-sepsis individuals. Analysis censored 
at 6 years. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Adjusted HRs for association of sepsis with 
long-term survival. Time-dependent effects described using a 
Cox regression model with all sepsis defined as a 
time-varying covariate. Analysis censored at 6 years. Each 
bar reflects the HR for death among individuals alive at the 
beginning of that time segment. Graph depicts observation 
time ≥6 months only. Adjusted for age, sex, race, region, 
health status, smoking, alcohol use, obesity and chronic 
medical conditions, as reported at the beginning of the 
REasons for Geographic And Racial Differences in Stroke 
REGARDS study. </p>



<p>Wang HE, Szychowski JM, Griffin R, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004283. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004283 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>inadequately controlled for baseline comorbidities, and 
relied on population norms as matched controls. Other 
studies focused on intensive care unit patients with 
sepsis, used data from single or smaller groups of 
centres or utilised discharge diagnoses to identify sepsis 
events. 
6-8 Our contrasting study utilised a large (&gt;30 000 
persons) and diverse population-based sample of 
community-dwelling individuals in the USA and entailed 
follow-up of up to 6 years. Rather than relying on hos-
pital discharge diagnoses, a process that may underde-
tect sepsis cases, we identified sepsis through review of 
hospital records. 
1 17 We were able to account and adjust 
for baseline comorbidities that may affect the outcomes 
of sepsis and non-sepsis individuals. 
It is unclear whether increased sepsis mortality reflects 
the increased susceptibility of those with heightened </p>

<p>comorbid burden or whether sepsis triggers an inde-
pendent pathophysiological process leading to early 
death. 
18 Where adjudicated cause of death was available, 
70% of deaths following a sepsis event were attributed to 
a range of other conditions, including cardiovascular 
and pulmonary diseases. We also identified that select 
chronic medical conditions such as diabetes, chronic 
kidney disease and chronic lung disease were independ-
ent predictors of early death among individuals with 
sepsis. Other described sequelae of sepsis include acute 
kidney injury, atrial fibrillation, cognitive impairment, 
functional disability and impaired quality of life. </p>

<p>19-22   Additional study must confirm the mechanisms by which 
sepsis creates or complicates the management of these 
other conditions. For example, does sepsis increase long-
term mortality by causing acute kidney injury and subse-
quent chronic kidney disease? Another important ques-
tion is whether prevention or optimal management of 
these parallel conditions might reduce the long-term 
rates of sepsis death. For example, could optimal man-
agement of sepsis-triggered chronic kidney alter an indi-
vidual's risk of death? 
Some limitations of this analysis should be noted. The 
REGARDS cohort contains individuals over 45 years 
only, and thus we could not characterise sepsis in 
younger individuals, who would likely exhibit lower rates 
of long-term mortality after a sepsis event. We could not 
identify sepsis events not reported by participants. We 
did not examine the influence of repeat sepsis events, 
which could conceivably increase the risk of mortality. 
We identified individuals who presented to the hospital 
with sepsis, but did not include those who acquired 
sepsis during their hospitalisation; we would expect 
inclusion of the latter individuals to amplify the 
observed mortality differences. We did not evaluate cog-
nitive impairment, functional disability or impacts on 
quality of life. 
REGARDS was designed to study stroke, not sepsis. 
However, our novel study takes advantage of important 
features of REGARDS, including the large participant 
base, extensive baseline information and extended 
observation period. There have been no population-
based cohorts designed specifically to study sepsis, and 
few studies on sepsis have had access to comprehensive 
'baseline' information as is in our study. It would be 
logistically and financially difficult to replicate a cohort 
of this scale. 
By design, the REGARDS cohort includes only 
African-Americans and Caucasians, and thus these 
results may not generalise to other ethnic groups. Select 
medical conditions not identified by REGARDS may 
have exhibited associations with risk of sepsis as well as 
mortality; for example, a history of immunosuppression. 
As with all observational studies, residual confounding is 
always a concern. However, our risk adjustment strategy 
accounted for a comprehensive range of variables that 
were systematically identified for each participant at the 
beginning of the REGARDS study. While we accounted </p>

<p>Table 5 Participant characteristics associated with rates 
of mortality after first sepsis events </p>

<p>Characteristics 
HR (95% CI) </p>

<p>p 
Value </p>

<p>Demographics 
Sex (male vs female) 
1.37 (1.002 to 1.88) 0.048 
Health status-physical composite score 
Quintile 1 
Referent 
Quintile 2 
0.68 (0.46 to 1.01) 
0.06 
Quintile 3 
0.55 (0.36 to 0.84) 
0.006 
Quintile 4 
0.51 (0.33 to 0.79) 
0.002 
Quintile 5 
0.59 (0.35 to 0.99) 
0.045 
Chronic medical conditions 
Cancer history 
1.68 (1.24 to 2.27) 
0.001 
Chronic kidney disease 
1.43 (1.05 to 1.95) 
0.02 
Deep vein thrombosis 
0.63 (0.38 to 1.04) 
0.07 
Diabetes 
1.57 (1.17 to 2.11) 
0.003 
Dyslipidaemia 
0.73 (0.55 to 0.98) 
0.04 
Hypertension 
1.46 (1.07 to 2.00) 
0.02 
Obesity (elevated waist 
circumference or body 
mass index ≥30 kg/m 
2 ) </p>

<p>0.74 (0.56 to 0.99) 
0.04 </p>

<p>Hospital course 
Infection type 
Lung 
Referent 
Kidney 
0.80 (0.55 to 1.17) 
0.24 
Abdominal 
0.48 (0.29 to 0.78) 
0.004 
Skin 
0.79 (0.43 to 1.43) 
0.43 
Sepsis 
0.98 (0.58 to 1.67) 
0.96 
Other 
1.33 (0.72 to 2.46) 
0.37 
Admission to intensive 
care unit </p>

<p>2.02 (1.40 to 2.91) &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Sequential organ failure score 
0 
Referent 
1 
1.10 (0.71 to 1.71) 
0.68 
2 
1.25 (0.79 to 2.00) 
0.34 
3-4 
1.66 (1.06 to 2.58) 
0.03 
5+ 
3.62 (2.23 to 5.88) &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Hospital course data based on first sepsis episode only. Only 
variables associated with early death are listed-full model listed 
in online supplementary appendix 3. 
Includes individuals experiencing sepsis only. </p>

<p>Wang HE, Szychowski JM, Griffin R, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004283. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004283 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>for the presence of baseline participant characteristics 
and chronic medical conditions, we could not account 
for changes in these patterns over time. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION 
In the REGARDS cohort, individuals with sepsis exhib-
ited increased rates of long-term death, even after 
accounting for comorbidities. Sepsis is independently 
associated with increased mortality risk well after hos-
pital treatment. </p>

<p>Author affiliations </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Emergency Medicine, University of Alabama School of 
Medicine, Birmingham, Alabama, USA </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Biostatistics, School of Public Health, University of Alabama at 
Birmingham, Birmingham, Alabama, USA </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of Epidemiology, School of Public Health, University of Alabama 
at Birmingham, Birmingham, Alabama, USA </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Division of Preventive Medicine, Department of Medicine, University of 
Alabama School of Medicine, Birmingham, Alabama, USA </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Department of Emergency Medicine, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center, 
Boston, Massachusetts, USA </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors thank the other investigators, the staff, and 
the participants of the REGARDS (REasons for Geographic and Racial 
Differences in Stroke) study for their valuable contributions. A full list of 
participating REGARDS investigators and institutions can be found at http:// 
www.regardsstudy.org and http://www.regardssepsis.org </p>

<p>Contributors HEW, JMS and GH conceived the study. HEW and MMS 
organised and oversaw data collection. HEW, NIS, MMS and GH obtained 
funding for the study. HEW, JMS and RG conducted the analysis, and all 
authors contributed to review of results. HEW drafted the manuscript, and all 
authors contributed to its editorial review and revision. HEW assumes 
responsibility for the work as a whole. </p>

<p>Funding This study was supported by award R01-NR012726 from the 
National Institute for Nursing Research, UL1-RR025777 from the National 
Center for Research Resources, as well as by grants from the Center for 
Clinical and Translational Science and the Lister Hill Center for Health Policy 
of the University of Alabama at Birmingham. The parent REGARDS study was 
supported by cooperative agreement U01-NS041588 from the National 
Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke, National Institutes of Health, 
Department of Health and Human Service. </p>

<p>Competing interests MMS reports the following potential conflicts of interest: 
Amgen-salary support to study patterns of statin use in Medicare and other 
large databases; diaDexus-salary support for a research grant on lipids and 
coronary heart disease outcomes; diaDexus-consulting to help with Food 
and Drug Administration FDA application; National Institutes of Health, Agency 
for Healthcare Research and Quality-salary support for research grants. Dr 
Wang, Dr Szychowski, Dr Griffin, Dr Shapiro and Dr Howard do not report 
any related conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>Ethics approval The study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of 
the University of Alabama at Birmingham (Approval #X090531004). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 3.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided </p>

<p>the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/ </p>





<p>Wang HE, Szychowski JM, Griffin R, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004283. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004283 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>