<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3389425" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>BACKGROUND: Mesothelin is expressed in various types of malignant tumour, and we recently reported that expression of mesothelin 
was related to an unfavourable patient outcome in pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma. In this study, we examined the 
clinicopathological significance of the mesothelin expression in gastric cancer, especially in terms of its association with the staining 
pattern. 
METHODS: Tissue specimens from 110 gastric cancer patients were immunohistochemically examined. The staining proportion and 
intensity of mesothelin expression in tumour cells were analysed, and the localisation of mesothelin was classified into luminal 
membrane and/or cytoplasmic expression. 
RESULTS: Mesothelin was positive in 49 cases, and the incidence of mesothelin expression was correlated with lymph-node metastasis. 
Furthermore, luminal membrane staining of mesothelin was identified in 16 cases, and the incidence of luminal membrane expression 
was also correlated with pT factor, pStage, lymphatic permeation, blood vessel permeation, recurrence, and poor patient outcome. 
Multivariate analysis showed that luminal membrane expression of mesothelin was an independent predictor of overall patient 
survival. 
CONCLUSION: We described that the luminal membrane expression of mesothelin was a reliable prognostic factor in gastric cancer, 
suggesting the functional significance of membrane-localised mesothelin in the aggressive behaviour of gastric cancer cells. 
Keywords: mesothelin; luminal membrane expression; gastric cancer </p>



























































<p>Mesothelin is a 40-kDa cell surface glycoprotein and is expressed 
on normal mesothelial cells lining the pleura, pericardium, 
and peritoneum (Chang et al, 1992; Chang and Pastan, 1996). 
Moreover, mesothelin is overexpressed in various types of 
malignant tumour, including malignant mesothelioma, ovarian 
cancer, and pancreatic cancer (Argani et al, 2001; Ordonez, 2003a, b; 
Hassan et al, 2005a; Einama et al, 2011). The full length of human 
mesothelin gene codes the primary product being a 71-kDa 
precursor protein. It can be physiologically cleaved by some furin-
like proteases into a 40-kDa C-terminal fragment that remains 
membrane bound, and a 31-kDa N-terminal fragment, which is 
secreted into the blood (Chang and Pastan, 1996). The C-terminal 
40-kDa fragment is named mesothelin and is attached to the cell 
membrane through a glycosyl-phosphatidylinositol (GPI) anchor 
(Chang and Pastan, 1996; Hassan et al, 2004). 
The biological functions of mesothelin are not clearly under-
stood, although recent studies have suggested that overexpression 
of mesothelin increases cell proliferation and migration (Li et al, 
2008). In ovarian cancers, diffuse mesothelin staining correlated 
significantly with prolonged survival in patients who had 
advanced-stage disease (Yen et al, 2006), and another report </p>

<p>indicated that a higher mesothelin expression is associated with 
chemoresistance and shorter patient survival (Cheng et al, 2009). 
In pancreatic cancer, mesothelin expression was immunohisto-
chemically observed in all cases, while its absence was noted in 
non-cancerous pancreatic ductal epithelium, with or without 
pancreatitis (Argani et al, 2001; Swierczynski et al, 2004; Hassan 
et al, 2005b; Einama et al, 2011). Furthermore, we recently 
explored that the expression of mesothelin was related to an 
unfavourable patient outcome in pancreatic ductal adenocarci-
noma. However, in gastric cancer, which is one of the representa-
tive gastrointestinal cancers, mesothelin expression seems to 
correlate with prolonged patient survival (Baba et al, 2011); this 
is a paradoxical result for the other types of carcinomas. In this 
study, we investigated the immunohistochemical analysis of 
mesothelin in 110 primary gastric cancers, especially focussing 
in the localisation of mesothelin, that is, luminal membrane and/or 
cytoplasm, and its clinicopathological significance associated with 
patient's outcome. </p>

<p>PATIENTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patients' demography and tumour specimens </p>

<p>This study was performed with the approval of the Internal Review 
Board on ethical issues of Hokkaido University Hospital, Sapporo, </p>

<p>*Correspondence: Dr H Nishihara; E-mail: hnishihara@s5.dion.ne.jp 
Received 6 February 2012; revised 25 April 2012; accepted 29 April 
2012; published online 29 May 2012 </p>

<p>British Journal of Cancer (2012) 107, 137-142 
&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK All rights reserved 0007 -0920/12 </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com </p>

<p>Molecular Diagnostics </p>

<p>Japan. The subjects of this study were 110 patients who underwent 
radical surgery for primary gastric cancer between 2002 and 2004 
at the Department of General Surgery, Hokkaido University, 
Graduate School of Medicine, Sapporo, Japan. The clinicopatho-
logical characteristics of these cases are summarised in 
Supplementary Table 1. 
Mean patient age was 62.1 years (±2.4 standard deviation 
(s.d.)). Seventy patients (63.6%) were men, and the remaining 40 
(36.4%) were women. The location of the tumour was the upper 
third of the stomach in 38 (34.5%) patients and the middle and 
lower third in 72 (65.5%). Tumour stages comprising T factor, 
N factor, M factor, clinical stage were assigned according to the 
TNM classification of the Union Internationale Contre le Cancer 
(Sobin and Wittekind, 2002). Lymphatic permeation and blood 
vessel invasion were evaluated as either positive or negative. The 
median survival time of the patients was 54.8 months ( ± 5.2 s.d.). 
Formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded tissue blocks were prepared 
from patient's tumour specimens, and sections were cut and 
stained with haematoxylin and eosin (HE) for routine histo-
pathological examination. All specimens were diagnosed as 
gastric adenocarcinomas, and lymphatic permeation and blood 
vessel invasion were evaluated using Elastica van Gieson staining 
and immunostaining with anti-podoplanin (D2-40) antibody, 
if necessary, as a routine operation for pathological diagnosis. 
A representative tissue block including metastatic lymph node was 
selected from each case to perform immunohistochemical studies. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Four-micrometre-thick sections were mounted on charged glass 
slides, deparaffinised, and rehydrated through a graded ethanol 
series. For antigen retrieval, Dako Target Retrieval Solution pH 9.0 
(Catalogue number S2368) was used, and the slides were boiled in 
a pressure cooker (Pascal Pressure Cooker, Model: S2800; 
DAKO JAPAN, Tokyo, Japan) to a temperature of 125 1C for 
3 min. Endogeneous peroxidase was blocked with 0.3% hydrogen 
peroxidase. The slides were incubated with a 1 : 50 dilution of a 
mouse monoclonal antibody to mesothelin (clone 5B2 diluted 
1 : 50; Novocastra, Newcastle Upon Tyne, UK) at room temperature 
for 30 min and then reacted with a dextran polymer reagent 
combined with secondary antibodies and peroxidase (Envision/ 
HRP; Dako) for 30 min at room temperature. Specific antigen-
antibody reactions were visualised with 0.2% diaminobenzine 
tetrahydrochloride and hydrogen peroxide. Slides were counter-
stained with haematoxylin for 10 min, then rinsed gently in reagent 
quality water. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemical evaluation </p>

<p>All assessments were made on the tumour region of the specimen 
( Â 400). Each slide was evaluated independently by two 
pathologists (TE, KT) who did not know the clinical outcomes. 
Immunostaining for mesothelin was evaluated for both the 
proportion and staining intensity of tumour cells in each case. The 
proportion of mesothelin expression was assessed according to the 
percentage of mesothelin-positive cells as follows: þ 1, 1-10%; 
þ 2, 10-50%; and þ 3, 450%. The staining intensity of 
mesothelin was evaluated as weak ( þ 1), moderate to strong 
( þ 2) in addition to the staining localisation in the luminal 
membrane or in cytoplasm. The final evaluation of mesothelin 
expression was assessed using the following scoring system 
according to the previous study for the pancreas cancer (Einama 
et al, 2011): 'mesothelin positive' was defined as greater than or 
equal to þ 4 of proportion score and/or þ 2 of intensity score, 
while 'mesothelin negative' was given when the total score was less 
than þ 3 except in the cases of proportion score þ 1 and intensity 
score þ 2 (Supplementary Figure 1). </p>

<p>Furthermore, among the 'mesothelin-positive' cases, the staining 
localisation of mesothelin was evaluated as luminal membrane 
and/or cytoplasm. In cases in which the entire circumference of the 
luminal membrane was explicitly stained even in partial through-
out the section, 'luminal membrane positive' was given. When the 
luminal membrane was stained discontinuously and/or faintly, or 
in cases in which no membrane staining and only cytoplasmic 
staining was observed in any intensity level throughout the section, 
'luminal membrane negative' was given (Figure 1; Supplementary 
Figure 1). Meanwhile, the mesothelin cytoplasmic expression was </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>E 
F </p>

<p>G 
H </p>

<p>I 
J </p>

<p>Figure 1 The expression variations of mesothelin and its cellular 
localisation in gastric cancer. (A, C, E, G, and I) HE stain. (B, D, F, H, 
and J) Immunohistochemical stain for mesothelin. (A and B) A case of 
'mesothelin negative'. (C and D) A case of 'luminal membrane negative', 
although there was incomplete membrane staining in the cancer cells. 
(E and F) A case of 'luminal membrane positive'. The entire circumference 
staining of the cell membrane was stained. (G and H) A case 
of 'cytoplasmic positive' that represented the scant cytoplasmic staining 
of mesothelin. (I and J) A case of 'cytoplasmic positive' with granular 
staining in cancer cells. Scale bars: 100 mm. </p>

<p>Mesothelin in gastric cancer 
T Einama et al </p>



<p>British Journal of Cancer (2012) 107(1), 137 -142 
&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK </p>

<p>Molecular Diagnostics </p>

<p>evaluated as follows: in a case in which the cytoplasmic staining 
was clearly observed in the constituent cancer cells, including 
the cytoplasmic granular staining, we judged it as 'cytoplasmic 
positive' (Figure 1). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>We used w 
2 test or Fisher's exact test to determine the correlation 
between mesothelin and clinicopathological data. Survival curves 
of patients were drawn by the Kaplan-Meier method. Differences 
in survival curves were analysed by the log-rank test. Prognostic 
implications of mesothelin expression and clinicopathological </p>

<p>parameters were analysed by Cox univariate and multivariate 
proportional hazards models. All differences were considered 
significant at a P-value of o0.05. All statistical analyses were 
performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statview</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>., Cary, 
NC, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Clinicopathological analysis for mesothelin expression </p>

<p>In the 110 gastric cancers, mesothelin expression was detected 
in 49 cases (44.5%), and the luminal membrane expression of </p>

<p>Prognostic aspect depending on the expression pattern of 
mesothelin in gastric cancer </p>

<p>Mesothelin expression (n = 110) </p>

<p>Positive (n = 49) </p>

<p>Positive; greater than 50% of tumour cells (proportion score 
of +3) or moderate to strong staining ( the intensity score 
of 2+) </p>

<p>Luminal membrane 
expression (n = 7) </p>

<p>Cytoplasmic 
expression (n = 33) </p>

<p>Better prognosis </p>

<p>Membrane negative (n = 94) 
Membrane positive (n = 16) </p>

<p>Poor prognosis </p>

<p>Both expression 
(n = 9) </p>

<p>Negative (n = 61) </p>

<p>Figure 2 Flow chart of evaluation of mesothelin expression. </p>

<p>Table 1 Association between expression pattern of mesothelin and clinicopathological parameters </p>

<p>Mesothelin expression 
Luminal membrane expression 
Cytoplasmic expression </p>

<p>Parameter 
Total </p>

<p>Positive 
(n ¼ 49) </p>

<p>Negative 
(n ¼ 61) 
P-value </p>

<p>Positive 
(n ¼ 16) </p>

<p>Negative 
(n ¼ 94) 
P-value </p>

<p>Positive 
(n ¼ 42) </p>

<p>Negative 
(n ¼ 68) 
P-value </p>

<p>1. Histological classification 
por2-sig 
62 
25 
37 
40.99 
8 
54 
0.60 
22 
40 
0.56 
Others 
48 
24 
24 
8 
40 
20 
28 </p>

<p>2. pT factor 
pT1 
62 
23 
39 
0.085 
3 
59 
0.0019 
21 
41 
0.33 
pT2-4 
48 
26 
22 
13 
35 
21 
27 </p>

<p>3. pN factor 
Positive 
37 
22 
15 
0.028 
11 
26 
0.0029 
17 
20 
0.30 
Negative 
73 
27 
46 
5 
68 
25 
48 </p>

<p>4. pStage 
I, II 
80 
34 
46 
0.52 
5 
75 
0.0002 
35 
48 
0.66 
III, IV 
30 
15 
15 
11 
19 
10 
20 </p>

<p>5. Lymphatic permeation 
Positive 
48 
25 
23 
0.18 
13 
35 
0.0019 
20 
28 
0.56 
Negative 
62 
24 
38 
3 
59 
22 
40 </p>

<p>6. Blood vessel permeation 
Positive 
41 
21 
20 
0.32 
11 
30 
0.0098 
16 
25 
40.99 
Negative 
69 
28 
41 
5 
64 
26 
43 </p>

<p>7. Recurrence 
Yes 
26 
14 
12 
0.37 
11 
15 
o0.0001 
9 
17 
0.82 
No 
84 
35 
49 
5 
79 
33 
51 </p>

<p>Mesothelin in gastric cancer 
T Einama et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK 
British Journal of Cancer (2012) 107(1), 137 -142 </p>

<p>Molecular Diagnostics </p>

<p>mesothelin was observed in 16 cases, while the cytoplasmic 
expression was detected in 42 tumours, which included the 9 cases 
of 'positive for both luminal membrane and cytoplasm' (Figure 2). 
The detailed clinicopathological information of 16 cases with 
mesothelin luminal membrane expression was summarised 
in Supplementary Table 2. We never detected the mesothelin 
expression in the non-cancerous lesions (data not shown). The 
statistical analysis revealed that the incidence of mesothelin 
expression was only correlated with lymph-node metastasis 
(P ¼ 0.028), while the incidence of luminal membrane expression 
of mesothelin was correlated with pT factor (P ¼ 0.0019), lymph-
node metastasis (P ¼ 0.0029), clinical stage (P ¼ 0.0002), lymphatic 
permeation (P ¼ 0.0019), blood vessel invasion (P ¼ 0.0098), and 
recurrence (Po0.0001). There were no significant correlations 
between mesothelin cytoplasmic expression and clinicopathological 
parameters (Table 1). </p>

<p>Survival analysis associated with mesothelin expression </p>

<p>The analysis for patients' overall survival denoted that the group 
of 'luminal membrane positive' for mesothelin indicated a 
significantly unfavourable outcome compared with the group 
of 'luminal membrane negative' (Po0.001). On the other hand, 
the pure mesothelin expression regardless of the localisation, and 
also 'cytoplasmic expression' were not correlated with the overall 
survival of the patients (Figure 3). To confirm the mesothelin 
expression as an independent prognostic factor, we performed the 
univariate analysis of the 110 gastric cancers using the Cox 
proportional hazards model, and obtained the result that pT factor, 
pN factor, clinical stage, lymphatic permeation, blood vessel 
invasion, and mesothelin luminal membrane expression were 
significantly correlated with the risk of cancer death (Table 2). 
Furthermore, to exclude the possible interference of any other 
factors, the multivariate analysis was performed including pT 
factor, pN factor, clinical stage, lymphatic permeation, blood 
vessel invasion, and mesothelin luminal membrane expression. 
Interestingly, the luminal membrane expression of mesothelin was 
an independent predictor of overall survival for gastric cancer 
patients as well as clinical stage and lymphatic permeation 
(Table 3). </p>

<p>Mesothelin expression in metastatic lymph nodes </p>

<p>As shown above, luminal membrane expression of mesothelin was 
correlated with lymphatic permeation and lymph-node metastasis; 
thus, we analysed the expression pattern of mesothelin in 35 out of 
37 cases of lymph-node metastasis by immunohistochemistry, in 
which the tissue blocks of metastatic lymph node were available 
(Supplementary Figure 2). Interestingly, the incidence of luminal 
membrane positive including expression in both membrane 
and cytoplasm was increased in metastatic lymph nodes (51.4%; 
18 out of 35) compared with primary lesions (31.4%; 11 out of 35). 
Moreover, in 4 cases out of 14 mesothelin-negative cases in 
primary lesion, luminal membrane expression of mesothelin was 
observed. These results support our idea that luminal membrane 
expression of mesothelin is associated with the malignant 
behaviour of tumour cells. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, we demonstrated that the luminal membrane 
expression of mesothelin in gastric cancer was associated with 
unfavourable clinical outcome in patients after surgery. 
The univariate analysis indicated that the luminal membrane 
expression of mesothelin was also correlated with lymph-node 
metastasis, clinical stage, lymphatic permeation, blood vessel 
invasion, residual tumour, and recurrence, although a luminal </p>

<p>membrane expression of mesothelin remained a statistically 
independent factor for favourable patient outcome after the 
multivariate analysis. Our result that total mesothelin expression 
including the case of exclusive cytoplasmic expression did not 
correlate with patients' prognosis will explain the discrepant 
previous report in which mesothelin expression correlates with 
prolonged patient survival in gastric cancer (Baba et al, 2011). We 
therefore emphasise that membrane-localised mesothelin might 
have an important role in the development of gastric cancer. 
The full length of human mesothelin gene codes the primary 
product being a 71-kDa precursor protein. It can be </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Mesothelin negative N = 61 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 
Proportion alive 
Mesothelin positive N = 49 </p>

<p>P = 0.110 
(Logrank test) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
80 
100 </p>

<p>Time after surgery (month) </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 
Proportion alive </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
80 
100 
Time after surgery (month) </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 
Proportion alive </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
2 0 
4 0 
6 0 
8 0 
1 0 0 
Time after surgery (month) </p>

<p>Membrane negative N = 94 </p>

<p>Membrane positive N = 16 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 (Logrank test) </p>

<p>Cytoplasm positive N = 42 </p>

<p>Cytoplasm negative N = 68 </p>

<p>P = 0.985 (Logrank test) </p>

<p>Figure 3 Overall survival for patients with gastric cancer after surgical 
therapy stratified by the status of mesothelin expression (A), mesothelin 
luminal membrane expression (B), and mesothelin cytoplasmic expression 
(C), respectively. The group of 'luminal membrane positive' represented a 
statistically significantly unfavourable outcome compared with the group of 
'luminal membrane negative' (B: Po0.001). On the other hand, both total 
expression (A) and cytoplasmic expression of mesothelin (C) were not 
correlated with overall survival of the patients. </p>

<p>Mesothelin in gastric cancer 
T Einama et al </p>



<p>British Journal of Cancer (2012) 107(1), 137 -142 
&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK </p>

<p>Molecular Diagnostics </p>

<p>physiologically cleaved by some furin-like proteases into a 40-kDa 
C-terminal fragment that remains membrane bound, and a 31-kDa 
N-terminal fragment, which is secreted into the blood (Chang and 
Pastan, 1996). The C-terminal 40-kDa fragment is referred to as 
mesothelin, which is attached to the cell membrane by a GPI 
anchor (Chang and Pastan, 1996; Hassan et al, 2004). The 5B2 anti-
mesothelin antibody (Novocastra Laboratory Vision BioSystems, 
Boston, MA, USA), which we employed here for IHC, can detect 
the 71-kDa precursor protein and also the 40-kDa C-terminal 
fragment (Inami et al, 2008); therefore, we could not decide which 
form of mesothelin has a pivotal role in malignant behaviour of 
gastric cancer cells. Recent studies reported that mesothelin is not 
only associated with increased cell proliferation and with the 
migration of pancreatic cancer cells in vitro (Bharadwaj et al, 2008; 
Li et al, 2008), but also contributes to tumour progression in vivo 
(Li et al, 2008). Mesothelin inhibits paclitaxel-induced apoptosis 
through concomitant activation of phosphoinositide-3-kinase 
(PI3K) signalling in the regulation of Bcl-2 family expression 
(Chang et al, 2009), and induces the activation of signal transducer 
and activator of transcription (Stat) 3, which leads to increased 
expression of cyclin E and makes pancreatic cancer cells 
proliferate faster (Bharadwaj et al, 2008). In addition, meso-
thelin-activated nuclear factor-kappaB (NF-kB) induces elevated 
interleukin (IL)-6 expression, which acts as a growth factor 
to support pancreatic cancer cell survival/proliferation through 
a novel auto/paracrine IL-6/soluble IL-6R trans-signalling </p>

<p>(Bharadwaj et al, 2011a, b). Our study provided a new aspect that 
luminal membrane expression of mesothelin is associated with 
the malignant behaviour of tumour cells, such as depth of 
tumour invasion and vascular invasion, although it remains 
necessary to clarify the biological function of the 71-kDa 
mesothelin precursor and/or 40-kDa mesothelin protein in 
in-vitro and in-vivo studies, including the processing system by 
furin-like proteases. 
In terms of discovering the clinicopathological parameters for 
gastric cancer, there are many previous studies demonstrating the 
prognostic significance of various molecules, such as epidermal 
growth factor receptor and c-erB-2 (HER-2). These molecules also 
could be of unique significance as the indicators of eligibility 
to specific molecular targeting therapies, because most of them 
are located in the cell membrane as the useful targets for the 
molecular targeted drugs such as antibody drugs. We believe that 
the immunohistochemical evaluation for luminal membrane 
expression of mesothelin in gastric cancer would be of clinical 
benefit not only as a prognostic factor but also as a predictive 
factor for the eligibility to mesothelin-targeting therapies in the 
future (Hassan et al, 2004, 2007a, b, c, 2010; Hassan and Ho, 2008; 
Li et al, 2008; Inami et al, 2009). 
In conclusion, we demonstrated the clinicopathological sig-
nificance of the luminal membrane expression of mesothelin in 
gastric cancer as an independent prognostic factor, although 
additional studies to increase the number of the cases for luminal 
membrane expression (n ¼ 16) might be required for further 
confirmation. The immunohistochemical examination of mesothe-
lin expression in surgically resected tumour specimens should be 
clinically useful for prognostication and for decision making about 
further treatment procedures after surgical therapy in patients with 
gastric cancer. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported in part by a grant-in-aid from the 
foundation for the Department of General Surgery, Hokkaido 
University Alumni Association. </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies the paper on British 
Journal of Cancer website (http://www.nature.com/bjc) </p>

<p>Table 2 Univariate analysis for clinicopathological parameters and 
mesothelin expression on overall survival of patients with gastric carcinoma </p>

<p>Factor 
N 
P 
RR (95% CI) </p>

<p>1. Histological classification 
por2-sig 
62 
0.89 
1 
Others 
48 
0.954 (0.478-1.903) </p>

<p>2. pT factor 
pT1 
62 
o0.0001 
1 
pT2-4 
48 
13.354 (4.679-38.113) </p>

<p>3. pN factor 
Positive 
73 
o0.0001 
1 
Negative 
37 
9.301 (4.147-20.860) </p>

<p>4. pStage 
I, II 
80 
o0.0001 
1 
III, IV 
30 
18.837 (8.032-44.179) </p>

<p>5. Lymphatic permeation 
Positive 
62 
o0.0001 
1 
Negative 
48 
18.529 (5.637-60.534) </p>

<p>6. Blood vessel permeation 
Positive 
69 
o0.0001 
1 
Negative 
41 
11.493 (4.722-27.971) </p>

<p>7. Mesothelin expression 
No 
61 
o0.0001 
1 
Yes 
49 
1.749 (0.874-3.500) </p>

<p>8. Luminal membrane expression 
No 
94 
o0.0001 
1 
Yes 
16 
7.205 (3.489-14.877) </p>

<p>9. Cytoplasmic expression 
No 
68 
0.98 
1 
Yes 
42 
1.007 (0.493-2.055) </p>

<p>Abbreviation: CI ¼ confidence interval. RR indicates relative risk/hazard ratio. </p>

<p>Table 3 Multivariate analysis for clinicopathological parameters and 
mesothelin expression on overall survival of patients with gastric carcinoma </p>

<p>Factor 
P 
RR (95% CI) </p>

<p>1. pT factor 
pT1 vs pT2-4 
0.35 
2.497 (0.374-16.660) </p>

<p>2. pN factor 
Positive vs Negative 
0.060 
3.532 (0.946-13.181) </p>

<p>3. pStage 
I, II vs III, IV 
0.0003 
12.336 (2.533-60.069) </p>

<p>4. Lymphatic permeation 
Positive vs Negative 
0.0043 
11.996 (2.180-65.996) </p>

<p>5. Blood vessel permeation 
Positive vs Negative 
0.29 
2.091 (0.533-8.195) </p>

<p>6. Luminal membrane expression 
No vs Yes 
0.0073 
2.969 (1.341-6.573) </p>

<p>Abbreviation: CI ¼ confidence interval. RR indicates relative risk/hazard ratio. </p>

<p>Mesothelin in gastric cancer 
T Einama et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK 
British Journal of Cancer (2012) 107(1), 137 -142 </p>

<p>Molecular Diagnostics </p>



<p>This work is published under the standard license to publish agreement. After 12 months the work will become freely available and the 
license terms will switch to a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. </p>

<p>Mesothelin in gastric cancer 
T Einama et al </p>



<p>British Journal of Cancer (2012) 107(1), 137 -142 
&amp; 2012 Cancer Research UK </p>

<p>Molecular Diagnostics </p>

</text></tei>