<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3251324" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T03:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Diaporthe species (and their Phomopsis anamorphs) are endo-
phytes and pathogens on a wide range of hosts, and are respon-
sible for several diseases, some of which are of economic im-
portance. On soybean (Glycine max), Diaporthe species cause 
seed decay, stem blight and stem canker, resulting in significant 
yield and quality losses (Backman et al. 1985, Fernández et al. 
1999). For example, these diseases are responsible for yield 
losses of up to 62 % in the former Yugoslavia, depending on 
the pathogen involved (Vidić &amp; Jasnić 1998). Four Diaporthe 
taxa can be found on soybean: Diaporthe phaseolorum var. 
sojae, the causal agent of pod and stem blight; D. phaseolo-
rum var. caulivora and D. aspalathi (formerly referred to as 
D. phaseolorum var. meridionalis), causal agents of Northern 
and Southern stem cankers, respectively; and Phomopsis 
longicolla, primarily causing seed decay. Separation of D. pha-
seolorum into varieties was based on morphological characters 
including colony appearance, size of stromata, arrangement of 
perithecia, presence of an anamorph, presence of alpha-and 
beta-conidia (Morgan-Jones 1985), symptomology and viru-
lence on soybean (Sinclair &amp; Backman 1989). Because of the 
variability found in morphology, physiology and host relation-
ships in the D. phaseolorum complex, classification at varietal 
level is considered unsatisfactory (Morgan-Jones 1989). </p>

<p>Formerly, species in Diaporthe (and their Phomopsis ana-
morphs) were largely identified on host association. However, 
it is now recognised that the host is of minor importance in the 
taxonomy of these fungi (Rehner &amp; Uecker 1994, Mostert et 
al. 2001). On the other hand, morphological characters are not 
always suitable for species definition because of their inter-
and intra-species variability (van der Aa et al. 1990, Santos 
2008). Currently, species of Diaporthe are distinguished mainly 
based on their molecular phylogenies, especially those derived 
from sequences of the internal transcribed spacer (ITS) of the 
nuclear ribosomal DNA (nrDNA) (van Niekerk et al. 2005, van 
Rensburg et al. 2006, Santos &amp; Phillips 2009). Some authors 
have also used other genomic regions as molecular markers 
for phylogenetic analysis in Diaporthe and Phomopsis, such 
as the translation elongation factor 1-alpha (EF1-α) gene (e.g., 
van Rensburg et al. 2006, Santos et al. 2010). </p>

<p>The aim of this study was to determine the Diaporthe species 
that are found on soybean in Croatia, and to revise their taxo-
nomic status in terms of molecular and morphological data. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Isolates and morphology </p>

<p>Strains of Diaporthe and Phomopsis were isolated from stems 
and seeds of soybean as well as from stems of sunflower (Heli-
anthus annuus), Arctium lappa, Asclepias syriaca and Dipsacus 
lacinatus from several localities throughout Croatia (Table 1). 
Small tissue pieces (10-15 mm long) were excised from dis-
eased stems. These pieces, as well as symptomless soybean 
seeds, were washed with tap water, surface disinfected with 
96 % ethanol for 10 s and 1 % sodium hypochlorite (NaOCl) 
for 1 min, rinsed three times with sterile distilled water, dried 
on filter paper and then placed on potato-dextrose agar (PDA, 
Difco Laboratories, Detroit, MI, USA) plates. Some tissue pieces </p>

<p>Resolving the Diaporthe species occurring on soybean 
in Croatia </p>

<p>J.M. Santos 
1, 4, 5 , K. Vrandeč ić 
2, 4 , J. Ć osić 
2 , T. Duvnjak 
3 , A.J.L. Phillips </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 Centro de Recursos Microbiológicos, Departamento de Ciências da Vida, 
Faculdade de Ciências e Tecnologia, Universidade Nova de Lisboa, Quinta 
da Torre, 2829-516 Caparica, Portugal; 
corresponding author e-mail: jmsantos@fct.unl.pt. 
2 Department of Plant Protection, Faculty of Agriculture in Osijek, J.J. Univer-
sity of Osijek, Trg sv. Trojstva 3, 31000 Osijek, Croatia. 
3 Agriculture Institute Osijek, Juzno predgradje 17, 31000 Osijek, Croatia. 
4 These authors contributed equally to this work. 
5 Present address: Instituto de Medicina Molecular, Unidade de Parasitologia 
Molecular, Av. Prof. Egas Moniz, 1649-028 Lisboa, Portugal. </p>

<p>Key words </p>

<p>anamorph 
EF1-α 
ITS 
mating-types 
phylogeny 
systematics 
taxonomy 
teleomorph </p>

<p>Abstract Diaporthe (anamorph = Phomopsis) species are plant pathogens and endophytes on a wide range of 
hosts including economically important crops. At least four Diaporthe taxa occur on soybean and they are respon-
sible for serious diseases and significant yield losses. Although several studies have extensively described the 
culture and morphological characters of these pathogens, their taxonomy has not been fully resolved. Diaporthe 
and Phomopsis isolates were obtained from soybean and other plant hosts throughout Croatia. Phylogenetic rela-
tionships were determined through analyses of partial translation elongation factor 1-alpha (EF1-α) gene and ITS 
nrDNA sequence data. By combining morphological and molecular data, four species could be distinguished on 
soybeans in Croatia. Diaporthe phaseolorum is described in this study and its synonyms are discussed. Diaporthe 
phaseolorum var. caulivora is raised to species status and the name Diaporthe caulivora is introduced to accom-
modate it. A species previously known as Phomopsis sp. 9 from earlier studies on sunflower, grapevine, rooibos and 
hydrangea is reported for the first time on soybean, and is formally described as Diaporthe novem. The well-known 
soybean pathogen Phomopsis longicolla was also collected in the present study and was transferred to Diaporthe 
longicolla comb. nov. The presence of these species on herbaceous hosts raises once more the relevance of weeds 
as reservoirs for pathogens of economically important plants. </p>

<p>Article info Received: 4 January 2011; Accepted: 1 August 2011; Published: 26 September 2011. </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 27, 2011 </p>

<p>were placed on moist filter paper inside a Petri dish. Petri dishes 
were kept at 25 °C under a 12 h light /dark regime. Develop-
ing mycelium or spores (ascospores or conidia) exuding from 
fruiting bodies were transferred to fresh PDA plates. Isolates 
were established by transferring hyphal tips from the edge of 
the developing mycelium to fresh PDA plates. Morphological 
characters were studied and recorded as in Santos &amp; Phillips 
(2009). Reference isolates were deposited in the culture collec-
tion at Centraalbureau voor Schimmelcultures (CBS), Utrecht, 
The Netherlands, and nomenclatural novelties in MycoBank 
(Crous et al. 2004). Mean, standard deviation (S.D.) and 95 % 
confidence intervals were calculated for asci, ascospores, 
alpha-and beta-conidia. Minimum and maximum dimensions 
are given in parentheses. In the case of asci, these values were 
rounded to the closest half micron. </p>

<p>DNA extraction and amplification </p>

<p>Genomic DNA was extracted and part of the EF1-α gene was 
amplified for all isolates (Table 1) as described in Santos et al. 
(2010). The ITS-D1/D2 nrDNA region of a subset of isolates 
was amplified following the methods described by Santos &amp; 
Phillips (2009). PCR diagnosis of mating-types (MAT1-1 and 
MAT1-2) was done using primers MAT1-1-1FW, MAT1-1-1RV, 
MAT1-2-1FW and MAT1-2-1RV following the protocol of Santos 
et al. (2010). All PCR products were visualised under ultraviolet </p>

<p>light in agarose gels stained with GelRed 
TM Nucleic Acid Gel 
Stain (Biotium, Inc., Hayward, CA, USA) at a final concentra-
tion of 0.25×. </p>

<p>Sequence analysis </p>

<p>Amplicon purification and sequencing, sequence editing and 
dataset assembling followed the protocols of Santos et al. 
(2010). Phylogenetic trees were inferred in <rs id="software-3" type="software">MrBayes</rs> v. <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">3.0b4</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Ronquist &amp; Huelsenbeck</rs> 2003) by Bayesian analysis and 
in <rs id="software-2" type="software">PAUP</rs> (Phylogenetic Analysis Using Parsimony) v. <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">4.0b10</rs> 
(Swofford 2002) by Maximum Parsimony (MP) using the 
heuristic search option with random addition of sequences 
(1 000 replications), tree bisection-reconnection (TBR) and 
MULTREES options ON. Bayesian analysis was performed 
as described in Phillips et al. (2007), setting burn-in at 2 000 
generations. Bootstrap support values with 1 000 replications 
(Felsenstein 1985) were calculated for branches in the MP trees 
using MULTREES option OFF and 10 random sequence addi-
tions in each of 1 000 pseudoreplicates. Sequences obtained 
from GenBank are listed by their taxon names followed by ac-
cession numbers in the trees (Fig. 1, 2), while newly generated 
sequences are listed by their isolate number. Newly generated 
sequences have been deposited in GenBank (Table 1) and 
alignments and phylogenies in TreeBASE (Study S10556; 
Matrices M5715 / M5716 = EF1-α, M5718 / M5719 = ITS). </p>

<p>GenBank accession numbers </p>

<p>Species 
Isolate no. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Host 
Source of 
Origin 
Collector 
EF1-α </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ITS </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>MAT1-1-1 
MAT1-2-1 
isolation </p>

<p>D. caulivora 
Dip1 
Dipsacus lacinatus 
Stem 
Bosnjaci 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347687 
HM347703 
(-) 
(+) 
Dip2 
D. lacinatus 
Stem 
Bosnjaci 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347689 
n.d. 
(-) 
(+) 
Dpc1 
CBS 127268 Glycine max 
Stem 
Osijek 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347691 
HM347712 
(-) 
(+) 
Dpc4 
G. max 
Stem 
Klisa 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347690 
n.d. 
(-) 
(+) 
Dpc11 
G. max 
Stem 
Klisa 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347688 
HM347704 
(-) 
(+) </p>

<p>D. novem 
3/27-3-1 
G. max 
Seed 
Slavonija 
T. Duvnjak 
HM347697 
HM347706 
(-) 
(+) 
4-27/3-1 
CBS 127270 G. max 
Seed 
Slavonija 
T. Duvnjak 
HM347696 
HM347709 
(-) 
(+) 
4-27/3-2 
G. max 
Seed 
Slavonija 
T. Duvnjak 
HM347698 
n.d. 
n.d. 
n.d. 
5-27/3-1 
CBS 127269 G. max 
Seed 
Slavonija 
T. Duvnjak 
HM347693 
HM347708 
(+) 
(-) 
5/27/3-2 
G. max 
Seed 
Slavonija 
T. Duvnjak 
HM347694 
n.d. 
(-) 
(+) 
5/27/3-3 
CBS 127271 G. max 
Seed 
Slavonija 
T. Duvnjak 
HM347695 
HM347710 
(+) 
(-) 
AS1 
Asclepias syriaca 
Stem 
Slavonija 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347692 
n.d. 
(-) 
(+) </p>

<p>D. phaseolorum Ar2 
Arctium lappa 
Stem 
Osijek 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347679 
HM347705 
(+) 
(+) 
PS03 
G. max 
Stem 
Sopot 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347670 
HM347702 
(+) 
(+) 
PS06 
G. max 
Stem 
Osijek 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347669 
n.d. 
(+) 
(+) 
PS8 
G. max 
Stem 
Sopot 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347671 
HM347701 
(+) 
(+) 
PSu1 
CBS 127266 Helianthus annuus 
Stem 
Ostrovo 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347672 
HM347707 
(+) 
(+) 
PSu5 
H. annuus 
Stem 
Ostrovo 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347678 
n.d. 
(+) 
(+) 
PSuB9 
H. annuus 
Stem 
Bosnjaci 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347675 
n.d. 
(+) 
(+) 
PSuS3 
H. annuus 
Stem 
Sapci 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347676 
n.d. 
(+) 
(+) 
PSuS4 
H. annuus 
Stem 
Sapci 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347677 
n.d. 
(+) 
(+) 
Su9 
H. annuus 
Stem 
Opatovac 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347673 
GQ149763 
(+) 
(+) 
Su10 
H. annuus 
Stem 
Ilok 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347674 
GQ149764 
(+) 
(+) </p>

<p>D. longicolla 
1-2/4-1 
G. max 
Seed 
Slavonija 
T. Duvnjak 
HM347680 
n.d. 
(+) 
(+) 
1-2/4-2 
G. max 
Seed 
Slavonija 
T. Duvnjak 
HM347681 
n.d. 
n.d. 
n.d. 
1-2/4-3 
G. max 
Seed 
Slavonija 
T. Duvnjak 
HM347682 
HM347711 
(+) 
(+) 
3-27/3-2 
G. max 
Seed 
Slavonija 
T. Duvnjak 
HM347684 
n.d. 
(+) 
(+) 
Pl1a 
G. max 
Stem 
Sopot 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347686 
n.d. 
(+) 
(+) 
PL4 
CBS 127267 G. max 
Stem 
Sopot 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347685 
HM347700 
(+) 
(+) 
PL7 
G. max 
Stem 
Karanac 
K. Vrandečić 
HM347683 
HM347699 
(+) 
(+) </p>

<p>1 CBS: Centraalbureau voor Schimmelcultures, Utrecht, The Netherlands. All isolates are deposited in the culture collection housed at Centro de Recursos Microbiológicos, Caparica, Portugal. 
Ex-type cultures are listed in bold. 
2 EF1-α: translation elongation factor 1-alpha. 
3 ITS: internal transcribed spacer. 
(-): Negative PCR result; (+): Positive PCR result; n.d.: not determined. </p>

<p>Table 1 Croatian isolates of Diaporthe spp. used in this study. </p>



<p>J.M. Santos et al.: Diaporthe species on soybean </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>EF1-α phylogeny </p>

<p>Since Santos et al. (2010) suggested that EF1-α is a better 
phylogenetic marker in Diaporthe and Phomopsis than ITS, 
we started by sequencing part of the EF1-α gene, spanning 
an entire intron and partial sequence of the flanking exons, for 
all isolates under study. BLAST searches were done to select 
closely related sequences from GenBank. The sequence of 
Diaporthe phaseolorum isolate FAU458 was not available from 
GenBank and was retrieved from TreeBASE study S1506 (van 
Rensburg et al. 2006). The alignment consisted of 42 taxa (in-
cluding two outgroups) and 387 characters (including alignment 
gaps and indel coding). The phylogenetic analysis was done 
by Bayesian analysis and Maximum Parsimony (MP). Of the 
387 characters, 285 were parsimony informative and included 
in the MP analysis resulting in two equally parsimonious trees. 
The Bayesian analysis phylogram (Fig. 1) showed a similar 
topology and clades as the MP phylogenetic trees. Bayesian 
posterior probabilities followed by MP bootstrap values are 
shown at the nodes. </p>

<p>Five clades were formed, corresponding to four different species 
found mainly on soybean, but including other hosts (sunflower, 
Arctium lappa, Asclepias syriaca and Dipsacus lacinatus) and 
Diaporthe lusitanicae from Foeniculum vulgare (sequences 
retrieved from GenBank). The first four clades consist of D. pha-
seolorum, D. longicolla, D. novem and D. lusitanicae, respec-
tively. All these clades are supported by Bayesian posterior 
probabilities of 1.00. Diaporthe phaseolorum, D. longicolla and 
D. novem are supported by MP bootstrap values of 100 %, while 
D. lusitanicae is supported by a MP bootstrap value of 99 %. 
The fifth clade consists of D. caulivora with Bayesian poste-
rior probability of 1.00 and MP bootstrap support of 100 %. 
Although closely related to the taxa found on soybean, D. me-
lonis, represented by its ex-isotype isolate, is shown to be a 
distinct species. </p>

<p>ITS phylogeny </p>

<p>Since there are many Diaporthe species for which only ITS 
sequences are available, we decided to further confirm the 
identity of the species found on soybean by means of ITS 
sequencing. Therefore, representative isolates of each EF1-α </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>PSu5 </p>

<p>PS06 </p>

<p>PS03 </p>

<p>PS8 </p>

<p>PSu1 </p>

<p>Su9 </p>

<p>Su10 </p>

<p>PSuB9 </p>

<p>PSuS3 </p>

<p>PSuS4 </p>

<p>Ar2 </p>

<p>0.62/62 </p>

<p>D. phaseolorum FAU458 </p>

<p>D. phaseolorum AF398895 </p>

<p>0.94/61 </p>

<p>1.00/100 </p>

<p>D. melonis GQ250314 </p>

<p>0.52/* </p>

<p>1-2/4-1 </p>

<p>P. longicolla AF398900 </p>

<p>Pl1a </p>

<p>PL4 </p>

<p>3-27/3-2 </p>

<p>PL7 </p>

<p>1-2/4-3 </p>

<p>1-2/4-2 </p>

<p>0.91/94 </p>

<p>D. phaseolorum AF398894 </p>

<p>1.00/100 </p>

<p>1.00/100 </p>

<p>5-27/3-1 </p>

<p>Phomopsis sp. 9 DQ286259 </p>

<p>Phomopsis sp. 9 GQ250363 </p>

<p>5/27/3-3 </p>

<p>5/27/3-2 </p>

<p>0.93/63 </p>

<p>AS1 </p>

<p>3/27-3-1 </p>

<p>4-27/3-1 </p>

<p>4-27/3-2 </p>

<p>1.00/100 </p>

<p>D. lusitanicae GQ250311 </p>

<p>D. lusitanicae GQ250310 </p>

<p>1.00/99 </p>

<p>1.00/100 </p>

<p>0.91/98 </p>

<p>Dip1 </p>

<p>D. phaseolorum var. caulivora AF398889 </p>

<p>Dpc1 </p>

<p>Dpc4 </p>

<p>Dip2 </p>

<p>Dpc11 </p>

<p>1.00/100 </p>

<p>1.00/100 </p>

<p>Leucostoma niveum DQ862035 </p>

<p>Valsa ambiens DQ862041 </p>

<p>// </p>

<p>D. caulivora </p>

<p>D. lusitanicae </p>

<p>D. novem </p>

<p>D. longicolla </p>

<p>D. phaseolorum </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Phylogenetic tree resulting from a Bayesian analysis of 387 characters 
of EF1-α gene (including coded indels). Newly generated sequences are 
listed by their isolate number. Ex-type cultures are in bold. Bayesian posterior 
probabilities followed by MP bootstrap values with 1 000 replications are 
shown at the nodes. The tree was rooted to Leucostoma niveum (DQ862035) 
and Valsa ambiens (DQ862041). Scale bar represents 0.1 substitutions per 
site. Phylogeny deposited in TreeBASE (S10556, M5715/M5716). </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 27, 2011 </p>

<p>clade were selected for another phylogenetic analysis based 
on ITS sequences. The ITS nrDNA region of these isolates was 
sequenced and BLAST searches were done to select closely 
related sequences. An alignment comprising 27 taxa (includ-
ing two outgroups) and 443 characters (including alignment 
gaps and indel coding) and spanning ITS1 and ITS2 complete 
sequences as well as 18S and 28S partial sequences was in-
cluded in a phylogenetic analysis using Bayesian analysis and 
Maximum Parsimony (MP). The sequence of the 5.8S nrDNA 
gene of D. phaseolorum isolate FAU458 was not available and 
this region was excluded from all isolates in the analysis. Of the 
443 characters, 101 were parsimony informative and included 
in the MP analysis resulting in a single tree. The Bayesian 
analysis phylogram (Fig. 2) showed largely the same topology 
and clades as the MP analysis. Bayesian posterior probabilities 
followed by MP bootstrap values are shown at the nodes. </p>

<p>Although the phylogenetic relationships between D. novem, D. 
phaseolorum and D. longicolla are depicted differently in this 
tree, the same clades can be distinguished as in the EF1-α 
tree (Fig. 1). The first clade consists of D. phaseolorum with 
Bayesian posterior probability of 0.70 and MP bootstrap sup-
port of 89 %. The ex-type isolate of Phomopsis camptothecae 
clustered together with this species. The second clade consists </p>

<p>of D. lusitanicae (Bayesian posterior probability of 1.00 and 
MP bootstrap support of 99 %) and the third clade consists of 
D. novem. The separation between D. lusitanicae and D. novem 
is not completely evident in this tree, since a Bayesian posterior 
probability of 1.00 and a MP bootstrap value of 99 % support a 
single branch that includes both species. However, in the MP 
tree, a further dichotomic subdivision of this branch is observed, 
thus unambiguously separating them (not shown). Diaporthe 
lusitanicae and D. novem are, in this phylogenetic method, sup-
ported by bootstrap values of 99 and 64 %, respectively. The 
fourth clade consists of D. longicolla with Bayesian posterior 
probability of 0.99 and MP bootstrap support of 98 %. Finally, 
the fifth clade consists of D. caulivora (Bayesian posterior 
probability of 0.98 and MP bootstrap support of 99 %). As in 
Fig. 1, D. melonis clusters as a distinct species based on ITS 
sequences. </p>

<p>Mating-type diagnosis </p>

<p>Santos et al. (2010) developed degenerate primers for the 
mating-type diagnosis of Diaporthe and Phomopsis isolates by 
PCR. This approach was used in the present study to narrow 
down the number of crossings between isolates necessary to 
induce teleomorphs in culture. The PCR diagnosis revealed that </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>D. phaseolorum GQ149764 </p>

<p>PSu1 </p>

<p>0.97/62 </p>

<p>D. phaseolorum GQ149763 </p>

<p>PS03 </p>

<p>PS8 </p>

<p>Ar2 </p>

<p>P. camptothecae AY622996 </p>

<p>D. phaseolorum FAU458 U11323+U11373 </p>

<p>0.70/89 </p>

<p>D. lusitanicae EU814477 </p>

<p>D. lusitanicae GQ250190 </p>

<p>1.00/99 </p>

<p>Phomopsis sp. 9 DQ286285 </p>

<p>5-27/3-1 </p>

<p>5/27/3-3 </p>

<p>Phomopsis sp. 9 GQ250225 </p>

<p>3/27-3-1 </p>

<p>1.00/99 </p>

<p>0.98/83 </p>

<p>P. longicolla EU650789 </p>

<p>1-2/4-3 </p>

<p>PL4 </p>

<p>PL7 </p>

<p>0.99/98 </p>

<p>D. melonis FJ889447 </p>

<p>0.79/64 </p>

<p>1.00/99 </p>

<p>D. phaseolorum var. caulivora EU622854 </p>

<p>Dpc1 </p>

<p>Dpc11 </p>

<p>Dip1 </p>

<p>0.98/99 </p>

<p>D. phaseolorum AF001027 </p>

<p>0.77/94 </p>

<p>1.00/100 </p>

<p>Leucostoma persoonii DQ996042 </p>

<p>Valsa ceratosperma DQ241769 </p>

<p>D. caulivora </p>

<p>D. lusitanicae </p>

<p>D. novem </p>

<p>D. longicolla </p>

<p>D. phaseolorum </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Phylogenetic tree resulting from a Bayesian analysis of 443 characters of the ITS nrDNA region (including coded indels). Newly generated sequences 
are listed by their isolate number. Ex-type cultures are in bold. Bayesian posterior probabilities followed by MP bootstrap values with 1 000 replications are 
shown at the nodes. The tree was rooted to Leucostoma persoonii (DQ996042) and Valsa ceratosperma (DQ241769). Scale bar represents 0.1 substitutions 
per site. Phylogeny deposited in TreeBASE (S10556, M5718/M5719). </p>



<p>J.M. Santos et al.: Diaporthe species on soybean </p>

<p>all D. phaseolorum isolates under study have both MAT1-1-1 
and MAT1-2-1 genes (Kanematsu et al. 2007) and are therefore 
homothallic. This is in accordance with the observation that 
D. phaseolorum isolates are self-fertile. Diaporthe novem was 
also shown to have both mating-types but in separate isolates, 
thus indicating that this is a heterothallic species. This implied 
that the teleomorph of D. novem could only be observed when 
isolates of opposite mating-types were crossed in culture. 
Diaporthe caulivora is also shown to be self-fertile. However, 
only the MAT1-2 locus could be detected in all isolates. Finally, 
the PCRs revealed that the tested D. longicolla isolates possess 
both mating-types, as in the case of D. phaseolorum. </p>

<p>TAxONOMy </p>

<p>Diaporthe caulivora (Athow &amp; Caldwell) J.M. Santos, Vrandeč ić 
&amp; A.J.L. Phillips, comb. &amp; stat. nov. -MycoBank MB518520; 
Fig. 3 </p>

<p>Basionym. Diaporthe phaseolorum var. caulivora Athow &amp; Caldwell, 
Phytopathology 44: 323. 1954. </p>

<p>Perithecia on Foeniculum vulgare stems in culture, globose, 
230-310 μm in its widest diam, single or clustered in groups 
of 2-3 perithecia. Black, smooth, straight necks, 330-520 μm. 
Asci unitunicate, (24.0 -)29.5 -31.0(-35.0) × (6.5 -)8.0 -9.0 
(-10.5) μm, mean ± S.D. = 30.2 ± 2.1 × 8.3 ± 1.0 μm (n = 20), 
ellipsoid, widest at centre and rounded towards the apices, 
with conspicuous refractive apical ring, 8-spored. Ascospores 
barely biseriate, hyaline, smooth, (8.2 -)8.9 -9.2(-10.1) × 
(2.2-)2.4-2.5(-2.9) μm, mean ± S.D. = 9.0 ± 0.5 × 2.5 ± 0.1 μm 
(n = 50), ellipsoid to fusoid, medianly septate, non constricted, 
4-guttules, 2 in each cell, central ones widest, although normally 
this characteristic is not easily seen. Anamorph not seen. 
Sexuality -Homothallic. 
Known hosts -Abutilon theophrasti (Vrandeč ić et al. 2005), 
Dipsacus lacinatus and Glycine max (Dunleavey 1955, Hobbs 
et al. 1981, Jasnić &amp; Vidić 1981, Miller &amp; Roy 1982, Krausz &amp; 
Fortnum 1983, Grand 1985, Kulik &amp; Thomison 1985, Whitney 
&amp; Bowers 1985, Ginns 1986, Hirrel &amp; Kirkpatrick 1986, Black 
et al. 1996, Zhang et al. 1997, Pioli et al. 2001, Bradley &amp; Li 
2006, Costamilan et al. 2008). 
Distribution -Argentina (Pioli et al. 2001), Brazil (Costami-
lan et al. 2008), Canada (Ginns 1986), Croatia (Vrandeč ić et 
al. 2005), Italy (Zhang et al. 1997), USA -Arkansas (Hirrel &amp; 
Kirkpatrick 1986), Iowa (Dunleavey 1955), Louisiana (Black et 
al. 1996), Maryland (Kulik &amp; Thomison 1985), Michigan and 
Ohio (Hobbs et al. 1981), Mississippi (Miller &amp; Roy 1982), North 
Carolina (Grand 1985), North Dakota (Bradley &amp; Li 2006), South 
Carolina (Krausz &amp; Fortnum 1983) and Texas (Whitney &amp; Bow-
ers 1985) -and former Yugoslavia (Jasnić &amp; Vidić 1981). </p>

<p>Specimens examined. See Table 1 for isolates studied. Croatia, Osijek, 
on soybean stem, Sept. 2005, K. Vrandeč ić, NEOTYPE proposed herein 
CBS H-20461 (perithecia on Foeniculum vulgare stems in culture), culture 
ex-neotype Dpc1 = CBS 127268. </p>

<p>Notes -All attempts to induce anamorphic sporulation in 
culture were unsuccessful. Although only the MAT1-2 mating-
type could be detected by PCR in all isolates studied, fertile 
perithecia formed in pure cultures. Therefore, this species is 
considered to be homothallic. This species is similar to D. pha-
seolorum but differs in having slightly wider perithecia with 
longer necks and shorter asci. The most distinctive character 
that separates these species is the production of conidiomata: 
while D. phaseolorum regularly produces pycnidia with alpha-
and beta-conidia, this is reported to be extremely rare in D. cau-
livora. This pathogen is the cause of Northern stem canker 
of soybean. Kulik (1984) could not locate the type specimen 
of D. phaseolorum var. caulivora, and our search for the type 
was also unsuccessful. Therefore we propose CBS H-20461 
as neotype. </p>

<p>Diaporthe longicolla (Hobbs) J.M. Santos, Vrandeč ić &amp; A.J.L. 
Phillips, comb. nov. -MycoBank MB563213; Fig. 4 </p>

<p>Phomopsis longicolla Hobbs, Mycologia 77: 542. 1985. </p>

<p>Conidiomata on Foeniculum vulgare stems in culture pycnidial, 
cone-shaped, 390 -540 μm diam, mostly solitary. Pycnidial 
necks prominent, 290-790 μm long. Conidiophores subcylindri-
cal to cylindrical, hyaline, smooth, 1-3-celled, simple or most 
commonly branched, 6.8-12.3 × 2.1-5.2 μm. Conidiogenous 
cells phialidic, cylindrical, tapering towards the apex, periclinal 
thickening present but not conspicuous. Collarette not seen. 
Conidiogenous cells terminal, attached to the apex of conidio-
phores, 8.4-14.2 × 1.6-2.8 μm, and lateral, produced from the 
main axis of conidiophore but showing a lateral prolongation, 
3.7-5.6 × 1.1-1.5 μm. Alpha-conidia unicellular, ellipsoid to 
ovoid (5.9-)6.9-7.2(-8.1) × (1.8-)2.1-2.2(-2.4) μm, mean 
± S.D. = 7.1 ± 0.6 × 2.1 ± 0.1 μm (n = 50), hyaline, biguttulate, 
exuding from the pycnidial ostiole in a yellowish, translucent 
drop. Beta-conidia not seen. 
Sexuality -Asexual. 
Known hosts -Abutilon theophrasti (Vrandeč ić et al. 2004), 
Ambrosia trifida, Euphorbia maculata, Rumex crispus and Xan-
thium strumarium (Roy et al. 1997), Arachis hypogaea (Sanogo 
&amp; Etarock 2009), Aster exilis, Caperonia palustris, Desmanthus 
illinoensis, Eclipta prostrata, Euphorbia nutans, Ipomoea la-
cunose, Polygonum aviculare and Sida spinosa (Mengistu &amp; 
Reddy 2005), Chamaesyce nutans (Mengistu et al. 2007) and 
Glycine max (Hobbs et al. 1985, Vidić et al. 1996, Zhang et al. 
1997, Holevas et al. 2000, Ash et al. 2010). </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Diaporthe caulivora. a. Perithecia on F. vulgare stem in culture (CBS H-20461); b. ascus with 8 ascospores (Dpc1); c. ascospores (Dpc1). -Scale 
bars: a = 1 mm; b, c = 5 μm. Ex-type culture is in bold. </p>

<p>c 
b 
a </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 27, 2011 </p>

<p>Distribution -Australia (Ash et al. 2010), Croatia (Vrandeč ić 
et al. 2004), Greece (Holevas et al. 2000), New Mexico (Sanogo 
&amp; Etarock 2009), USA -Arkansas and Missouri (Zhang et al. 
1997) and Illinois, Iowa, Mississippi and Ohio (Hobbs et al. 
1985) -and former Yugoslavia (Vidić et al. 1996). </p>

<p>Specimens examined. See Table 1 for isolates studied. Croatia, Sopot, 
on soybean stem, Sept. 2005, K. Vrandeč ić, Herb. CBS H-20460 (pycnidia 
on Foeniculum vulgare stems in culture), isolate PL4 = CBS 127267. </p>

<p>Notes -Holotype on seed of Glycine max, Wooster, Ohio, 
USA (TWH P74 = BPI 358745). Ex-type culture deposited in 
ATCC (ATCC 60325) (Hobbs 1985). Although all of the isolates 
we studied possessed both mating-types, as determined by 
PCR diagnosis, no fertile perithecia formed under any condi-
tions. Therefore, this species is considered to be purely ana-
morphic. This species differs from D. novem mainly in having </p>

<p>solitary pycnidia producing only alpha-conidia. It differs from 
D. phaseolorum in having larger pycnidia and longer conidio-
phores and conidiogenous cells, as well as in producing only 
alpha-conidia. This pathogen is the main cause of seed decay 
of soybean. </p>

<p>Diaporthe novem J.M. Santos, Vrandeč ić &amp; A.J.L. Phillips, 
sp. nov. -MycoBank MB518521; Fig. 5 </p>

<p>Anamorph. Phomopsis sp. 9 (van Rensburg et al. 2006). </p>

<p>Peritheciis in agar cum Foeniculum vulgare stipes: globosis, 320 -440 μm 
diam, separatus, collo apicali erumpenti usque 2250 μm longo praeditis. Ascis 
unitunicatis, 38.5 -43 × 6.5 -10.5 μm, clavulatis, hyalinis, octosporis, cum 
annulis apicalibus distingentibus, refractis. Ascosporis 8.6-13.1 × 2.1-3.6 
μm, uniseriatis vel biseriatis, hyalinis, bicellularibus, cylindricis, ad septum 
constrictis, 4-guttulatis. Anamorphosis in agar cum Foeniculum vulgare </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Diaporthe longicolla. a. Pycnidia on F. vulgare stem in culture (CBS H-20460); b. conidiophores (PL4); c. alpha-conidia (PL4). -Scale bars: a = 1 mm; 
b, c = 5 μm. </p>

<p>c 
b 
a </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Diaporthe novem. a. Perithecia on F. vulgare stem in culture (CBS-H 20463); b. ascus with 8 ascospores (4-27/3-1 × 5/27/3-3); c. ascospores (4-27/3-1 
× 5/27/3-3); d. pycnidia on F. vulgare stem in culture (CBS H-20462); e. conidiophores (5-27/3-1); f. alpha-and beta-conidia (5-27/3-1). -Scale bars: a, d = 
1 mm; b, c, e, f = 5 μm. Ex-type cultures are in bold. </p>

<p>c 
b </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>e 
f </p>



<p>J.M. Santos et al.: Diaporthe species on soybean </p>

<p>stipes: conidiomata eustromatica, ad pycnidia, tubineus, 310-580 μm diam. 
Conidiophoris cylindricis, 5.3 -10.4 × 1.9 -3.2 μm. Cellulae conidiogenae 
hyalinae, phialidicae, enteroblasticae, terminus, 8.9 -16 × 1.7-2.7 μm, et 
lateralis, 4-7.3 × 1.2-1.7 μm. Alpha conidiis hyalinis, ovatis vel cylindricis, 
unicellularibus, 6.3 -8.9 × 1.9 -2.5 μm. Beta conidiis hyalinis, filiformis, 
unicellularibus, 26.4 -37.7 × 1-1.3 μm. </p>

<p>Etymology. Latin for nine, the name by which this species has been known 
since 2006 (van Rensburg et al. 2006), namely Phomopsis sp. 9. </p>

<p>Perithecia on Foeniculum vulgare stems in culture, globose, 
320-440 μm in its widest diam, scattered within black ectostro-
matic areas. Black, long necks, 1600 -2250 μm, hairy, filiform 
and frequently branched. Asci unitunicate, (38.5 -)40.5-41.5 
(-43.0) × (6.5 -)8.5 -9.0(-10.5) μm, mean ± S.D. = 40.8 ± 1.2 
× 8.8 ± 1.0 μm (n = 20), clavate, with visible refractive apical 
ring, 8-spored. Ascospores randomly arranged, from loosely 
uniseriate to biseriate, hyaline, smooth, (8.6-)10.6-11.1(-13.1) 
× (2.1-)2.8 -2.9(-3.6) μm, mean ± S.D. = 10.8 ± 0.9 × 2.8 
± 0.3 μm (n = 50), cylindrical, medianly septate, sometimes 
constricted at the septum, normally 4-guttulate, sometimes 
eguttulate, when 4-guttulate, the 2 central guttules, closer to 
the septum, are the largest. Conidiomata formed on Foenicu-
lum vulgare stems in culture pycnidial, cone-shaped, 310-580 
μm diam. Pycnidial necks hairy, 380 -710 μm long, arranged 
in clusters. Yellowish translucent conidial drop exuded from 
the ostiole. Conidiophores cylindrical, hyaline, smooth, uni-to 
bicellular, 5.3 -10.4 × 1.9 -3.2 μm. Conidiogenous cells phia-
lidic, clavate to filiform, tapering towards the apex, periclinal 
thickening present. Collarette not seen. Conidiogenous cells 
terminal, attached to the apex of conidiophores, 8.9 -16.0 × 
1.7-2.7 μm, and lateral, belonging to the main axis of conidio-
phore but showing a lateral prolongation, 4.0 -7.3 × 1.2-1.7 
μm. Alpha-conidia unicellular, oval to cylindrical, with obtuse 
ends, (6.3 -)7.3 -7.5(-8.9) × (1.9 -)2.1-2.2(-2.5) μm, mean 
± S.D. = 7.4 ± 0.6 × 2.2 ± 0.1 μm (n = 100), hyaline, biguttulate. 
Beta-conidia hyaline, aseptate, filiform, curved, eguttulate, with 
rounded ends, (26.4-)32.0-33.3(-37.7) × (1.0-)1.1(-1.3) μm, 
mean ± S.D. = 32.6 ± 2.4 × 1.1 ± 0.1 μm (n = 50). 
Sexuality -Heterothallic. 
Known hosts -Asclepias syriaca, Aspalathus linearis (van 
Rensburg et al. 2006), Glycine max, Helianthus annuus (Rekab 
et al. 2004), Hydrangea macrophylla (Santos et al. 2010) and 
Vitis vinifera (van Niekerk et al. 2005). 
Distribution -Croatia, Italy (Rekab et al. 2004), Portugal 
(Santos et al. 2010) and South Africa (van Niekerk et al. 2005, 
van Rensburg et al. 2006). </p>

<p>Specimens examined. See Table 1 for isolates studied. Croatia, Slavonija, 
on soybean seed, Sept. 2008, T. Duvnjak, holotype CBS H-20463 (pycnidia 
and perithecia on Foeniculum vulgare stems in culture obtained from cross 
between CBS 127270 and CBS 127271), cultures ex-type 4-27/3-1 = CBS 
127270 (MAT1-2) and 5/27/3-3 = CBS 127271 (MAT1-1); Herb. CBS H-20462 
(isolate 5-27/3-1 = CBS 127269). </p>

<p>Notes -Fertile perithecia formed in culture only after cross-
ing isolates with opposite mating-types, as diagnosed by PCR. 
Therefore, this species is heterothallic. This species is similar 
to D. chailletii but has much longer perithecial necks, shorter 
and wider asci, and cylindrical ascospores in contrast to the 
fusoid-ellipsoid ascospores of D. chailletii. </p>

<p>Diaporthe phaseolorum (Cooke &amp; Ellis) Sacc., Syll. Fung. 1: 
692. 1882 -Fig. 6 </p>

<p>Basionym. Sphaeria phaseolorum Cooke &amp; Ellis, Grevillea 6: 93. 1878. 
= Diaporthe phaseolorum var. phaseolorum (Cooke &amp; Ellis) Sacc., Syll. 
Fung. 1: 692. 1882. 
= Diaporthe phaseolorum var. sojae (Lehman) Wehm., The genus Dia-
porthe Nitschke and its segregates: 47. 1933. 
≡ Diaporthe sojae Lehman, Ann. Mo. Bot. Gdn. 10: 128. 1923. 
= Diaporthe phaseolorum var. batatae (Harter &amp; Field) Wehm., The genus 
Diaporthe Nitschke and its segregates: 48. 1933. </p>

<p>≡ Diaporthe batatas Harter &amp; E.C. Field, Phytopathology 2: 121. 1912. 
= Septomazzantia phaseolorum (Cooke &amp; Ellis) Lar.N. Vassiljeva, Nizshie 
Rasteniya, Griby i Mokhoobraznye Dalnego Vostoka Rossii 4: 44. 1998. </p>

<p>Anamorph. Phomopsis phaseoli (Desm.) Sacc., Nuovo Giorn. Bot. Ital., 
n.s. 22: 47. 1915. 
Basionym. Phoma phaseoli Desm., Ann. Sci. Nat., Ser. 3, 6: 247. 1836. 
= Phoma subcircinata Ellis &amp; Everh., Proc. Acad. Nat. Sci. Philadelphia 
45: 158. 1893. 
= Phomopsis batatas (Ellis &amp; Halst.) Harter &amp; E.C. Field, Phytopathology 
2: 121. 1912. 
≡ Phoma batatas Ellis &amp; Halst., New Jersey Agric. Coll. Exp. Sta. Bull. 
76: 25. 1890. 
= Phomopsis phaseoli var. phaseoli (Desm.) Sacc., Nuovo Giorn. Bot. 
Ital., n.s. 22: 47. 1915. 
≡ Phomopsis phaseoli (Desm.) Grove, Bull. Misc. Inform. Kew 60. 
1917. 
= Phomopsis phaseoli Petch, Ann. Roy. Bot. Gard. (Peradeniya) 7: 311. 
1922. 
= Phomopsis sojae Lehman, J. Elisha Mitchell Sci. Soc. 38: 13. 1922. 
= Phomopsis glycines Petr., Ann. Mycol. 34: 240. 1936. 
= Phomopsis camptothecae C.Q. Chang, Z.D. Jiang &amp; P.K. Chi, Myco-
systema 24: 145. 2005. </p>

<p>Perithecia on Foeniculum vulgare stems in culture, black, 
globose, 230 -270 μm in its widest diam, scattered in high 
numbers within black ectostromatic areas. Necks, 210-430 
μm long, filiform, with hairy and dilated tip. Asci unitunicate, 
(32.5 -)34.5 -36.0(-38.0) × (6.5 -)7.5 -8.5(-9.5) μm, mean 
± S.D. = 35.1 ± 1.8 × 8.0 ± 0.9 μm (n = 20), ellipsoid, with refrac-
tive apical ring, 8-spored. Ascospores randomly arranged within 
the ascus, rarely biseriate, hyaline, smooth, (8.0 -)9.3 -9.7 
(-11.3) × (2.0-)2.4-2.6(-3.0) μm, mean ± S.D. = 9.5 ± 0.7 × 2.5 
± 0.2 μm (n = 50), ellipsoid, medianly septate, not constricted, 
apical cell sometimes slightly wider, each cell biguttulate, the 
guttules closest to the septum being the largest. Conidiomata 
on Foeniculum vulgare stems in culture pycnidial, globose to 
subglobose, 140-170 × 150-340 μm. Conidiophores cylindri-
cal, hyaline, smooth, unicellular, 2.5-6.0 × 2.2-5.8 μm, bearing 
1-2 conidiogenous cells. Conidiogenous cells phialidic, clavate, 
tapering towards the apex, 6.0-8.8 × 2.0-3.8 μm. Collarette 
not seen. Alpha-conidia unicellular, ovoid, (5.4-)6.7-7.0(-8.9) 
× (1.8-)2.4(-3.1) μm, mean ± S.D. = 6.9 ± 0.7 × 2.4 ± 0.2 μm 
(n = 100), hyaline, biguttulate, conidiogenous scar sometimes 
visible. Beta-conidia hyaline, aseptate, filiform, bent, eguttulate, 
wider at the centre and thinner towards the ends, (13.3-)17.1-
17.8(-22.5) × (0.9-)1.2(-1.5) μm, mean ± S.D. = 17.4 ± 2.0 × 
1.2 ± 0.1 μm (n = 100). 
Sexuality -Homothallic. 
Known hosts -Abutilon theophrasti (Hepperly et al. 1980), 
Allium cepa, Allium sativum, Arachis hypogaea, Capsicum 
frutescens, Hibiscus esculentus, Lespedeza sp., Lupinus hir-
sutus, Lycopersicon esculentum, Phaseolus vulgaris, Stropho-
styles helvola and Vigna sinensis (Hanlin 1963), Amaranthus 
spinosus and Leonorus sibiricus (Cerkauskas et al. 1983), Arc-
tium lappa, Camptotheca acuminata (Chang et al. 2005), 
Capsicum annuum (Pennycook 1989), Glycine max (Petch 
1922, Preston 1945, Gilman 1949, Johnson &amp; Kilpatrick 1953, 
Gerdemann 1954, Peregrine &amp; Siddiqi 1972, Kmetz et al. 
1974, Gorter 1977, Ersek 1978, Ebbels &amp; Allen 1979, Bernaux 
1981, Kozireva et al. 1982, Alfieri et al. 1984, Jasnić &amp; Vidić 
1985, Richardson 1990, Dahal et al. 1992, Zhang et al. 1997), 
Helianthus annuus (Vrandeč ić et al. 2009), Ipomoea batatas, 
Phaseolus lunatus, Phaseolus sp., Solanum tuberosum and 
Zea mays (Wehmeyer 1933), Kandelia candel (Cheng et al. 
2008) and Stokesia laevis (Sogonov et al. 2008). 
Distribution -Argentina, Brazil, Canada, Italy, Puerto Rico, 
Senegal and Taiwan (Richardson 1990), Bermuda, China, 
Colombia, Cuba, Egypt, Guyana, India, Israel, Japan, New 
Zealand, Nigeria, Sierra Leone and Zaire (Punithalingam &amp; Hol-
liday 1972), Croatia (Vrandeč ić et al. 2009), France (Bernaux </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 27, 2011 </p>

<p>1981), Hungary (Ersek 1978), Korea (Zhang et al. 1997), Malawi 
(Peregrine &amp; Siddiqi 1972), Nepal (Dahal et al. 1992), Russia 
(Kozireva et al. 1982), South Africa (Gorter 1977), Sri Lanka 
(Petch 1922), Tanzania (Ebbels &amp; Allen 1979), USA -Arkansas 
(Zhang et al. 1997), Florida (Alfieri et al. 1984), Georgia (Hanlin 
1963), Illinois (Gerdemann 1954), Indiana, Louisiana, New 
Jersey and North Carolina (Wehmeyer 1933), Iowa (Gilman 
1949), Kentucky and Minnesota (Richardson 1990), Missis-
sippi (Johnson &amp; Kilpatrick 1953), Ohio (Kmetz et al. 1974) and 
Oklahoma (Preston 1945) -and former Yugoslavia (Jasnić &amp; 
Vidić 1985). </p>

<p>Specimens examined. See Table 1 for isolates studied. 
Sphaeria phaseolorum: USA, New Jersey, Newfield, on old bean stalks, 4 
Aug. 1877, J.B. Ellis, isotype Fungi of New Jersey 2651, NY00875162; on old 
bean vines, July 1888, J.B. Ellis, North American Fungi 188, NY00875150. 
Diaporthe phaseolorum: Croatia, Ostrovo, on Helianthus annuus stem, 
Aug. 2006, K. Vrandeč ić, Herb. CBS H-20459 (pycnidia and perithecia on 
Foeniculum vulgare stems in culture), isolate PSu1 = CBS 127266. -USA, 
New Jersey, Newfield, on old bean vines, July 1896, J.B. Ellis, Ellis &amp; Ever-
hart Fungi Columbiani 1044, CM1278 in NY; on old bean vines, Oct. 1890, 
J.B. Ellis, NY00875160; on dead stems of Phaseolus, Aug. 1890, J.B. Ellis, 
NY00875161; Baptist Hill, Conway, Massachusetts, on old stems of Solanum 
dulcamara, Mar. 1979, ME Barr, MEBB6539 in NY. -Venezuela, trail from 
El Rincon east along Rio Media to peak of Palo de Agua, Edo. Sucre, on 
unidentified wood, July 1972, KP Dumont, RF Cain, GJ Samuels, G. Morillo, 
det. ME Barr Biglow, Dumont-VE 5079 in NY; vicinity of El Arado, c. 12 km 
SW of Macarao, Edo. Miranda, on unidentified composite stem, July 1972, 
KP Dumont, RF Cain, GJ Samuels, G. Morillo, Dumont-VE 6319 in NY. </p>

<p>Notes -All isolates studied possessed both mating-types 
as determined by PCR diagnosis. Fertile perithecia formed in 
pure cultures and therefore this species is homothallic. Although </p>

<p>similar to D. caulivora, these species show some morphological 
differences (see above). Another similar species is D. aspalathi, 
as indicated by van Rensburg et al. (2006), which has wider 
perithecia, longer and cylindrical asci, longer ascospores and 
only produces fusoid alpha-conidia. This pathogen has a very 
wide host range, but on soybean it causes pod and stem 
blight. </p>

<p>Key to Diaporthe species on soybean </p>

<p>1. Self-infertile . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2 
1. Self-fertile . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3 </p>

<p>2. Teleomorph produced in crosses of opposite mating-types 
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . D. novem 
2. Both mating-types present but teleomorph never produced 
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . D. longicolla </p>

<p>3. Anamorph rarely seen in culture . . . . . . . . . . D. caulivora 
3. Anamorph and teleomorph form readily in culture . . . . . 4 </p>

<p>4. Asci 34.5-36 × 7.5-8.5 μm, ascospores 9.3-9.7 × 2.4-2.6 
μm . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . D. phaseolorum 
4. Asci 52-55 × 7-8 μm, ascospores 13 -15 × 3 μm . . . . . . 
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . D. aspalathi </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Phylogenetic analyses based on EF1-α and ITS sequence data 
revealed four species of Diaporthe on soybean in Croatia. Three 
of these (D. phaseolorum, D. caulivora and D. longicolla) are 
well-known from soybean, while D. novem has thus far never </p>

<p>Fig. 6 Diaporthe phaseolorum. a. Perithecia on F. vulgare stem in culture (CBS-H 20459); b. ascus with 8 ascospores (PSu1); c. ascospores (PSu1); 
d. pycnidia on F. vulgare stem in culture (PS03); e. conidiophores (PSu1); f. alpha-conidia (PS03); g. beta-conidia (PS03). -Scale bars: a, d = 1 mm; b, c, 
e, f, g = 5 μm. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>d 
a </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>g </p>



<p>J.M. Santos et al.: Diaporthe species on soybean </p>

<p>been recorded on this host. Not only were the species phylo-
genetically distinct, but they could also be distinguished based 
on their morphology, mating behaviour and on the disease that 
they cause. </p>

<p>The species of Diaporthe occurring on soybean has been the 
subject of a considerable amount of research and discussion. 
Much of the discussion has been aimed at the subdivision of 
D. phaseolorum into varieties or formae speciales. Although 
there have been arguments that classification at varietal 
level is not satisfactory (Morgan-Jones 1989), this system has 
persisted. The phylogenetic information that we supply here, 
together with the morphological differences and pathology of 
the varieties on soybean (Backman et al. 1985) adds further 
weight to the arguments against varietal separation, and we 
have proposed certain taxonomic changes. One of the varieties 
(D. phaseolorum var. meridionalis) has already been shown to 
be phylogenetically distinct and was elevated by van Rensburg 
et al. (2006) to species status. The name D. aspalathi was newly 
introduced since D. meridionalis was already occupied. </p>

<p>One factor that has hampered research on D. phaseolorum 
complex is the lack of isolates directly linked to the type speci-
mens. We followed the precedent set by van Rensburg et al. 
(2006) and regarded isolate FAU458 as a reference strain of 
D. phaseolorum. All of the isolates that we studied that clus-
tered phylogenetically with FAU458 correlated entirely with the 
morphology of the isotype of Sphaeria phaseolorum. Further-
more, all of these isolates were homothallic and readily formed 
the teleomorph in culture, which is a recognised feature of 
D. phaseolorum. For these reasons we are confident that these 
isolates represent D. phaseolorum. </p>

<p>In 1933, Wehmeyer noticed that D. phaseolorum var. phaseolo-
rum on Phaseolus spp., D. phaseolorum var. sojae on soybean 
and D. phaseolorum var. batatae on sweet potato were morpho-
logically highly similar and probably the same taxon. Later, for 
the same reason and after a thorough search of the literature, 
together with morphological studies of various specimens and 
isolates, Kulik (1984) placed all of these pathogens under the 
same name (D. phaseolorum), rejecting their separation into 
different varieties. Their anamorphs, Phomopsis phaseoli, 
P. sojae and P. batatas, respectively, were placed under P. pha-
seoli. In fact, the amount of variation in the size of perithecia, 
ascospores, pycnidia, alpha-and beta-conidia reported within 
each taxon at least equals the variation between them (Kulik 
1984). Almost at the same time, Hobbs et al. (1985) considered 
the type specimen of Phomopsis glycines to be morphologically 
the same as P. sojae, and included this binomial to the list of 
synonyms of D. phaseolorum. </p>

<p>The ITS sequence of the ex-type isolate of Phomopsis campto-
thecae clusters perfectly with D. phaseolorum in the ITS phylo-
gram (Fig. 2). According to Chang et al. (2005) the type speci-
men of this species is deposited in the Mycological Herbarium 
of South China Agricultural University (SCHM), Guangzhou. An 
extensive search for the herbarium specimens was done but un-
fortunately none could be found. However, the original descrip-
tion of this fungus corresponds in all ways with the anamorph 
of D. phaseolorum. Since P. camptothecae is morphologically 
and phylogenetically indistinguishable from the anamorph of 
D. phaseolorum it was considered to be a synonym. </p>

<p>Kulik (1984) was not sure about the differences between the 
stem canker pathogenic agent (D. phaseolorum var. caulivora) 
and all the other varieties of D. phaseolorum. Although he 
placed this variety as a synonym of D. phaseolorum, he sug-
gested that it should be called D. phaseolorum f. sp. caulivora 
until further studies confirm its true identity. In the present work, 
we have shown that D. phaseolorum var. caulivora is a distinct 
species (D. caulivora) that also occurs on soybean in Croatia. </p>

<p>We started the identification of the isolates of this species by 
studying their morphology. Since Kulik (1984) had reported an 
unfruitful search for the type specimen of D. phaseolorum var. 
caulivora, we based our preliminary identification on the original 
description given by Athow &amp; Caldwell (1954) and other authors 
(e.g., Kulik 1984). Our next approach was similar to the one 
followed by van Rensburg et al. (2006) to describe D. aspala-
thi. In that study, the ITS and EF1-α of isolates identified as 
D. phaseolorum var. meridionalis were sequenced and shown 
to be too distinct from the reference isolate of D. phaseolorum 
(FAU458) to consider them as a mere variety. In our work, we 
showed that both ITS and EF1-α support a clear separation of 
D. phaseolorum var. caulivora from the same reference isolate 
of D. phaseolorum, and thus named it D. caulivora. </p>

<p>Although several different media and incubation conditions were 
tried to induce anamorphic sporulation of D. caulivora, none of 
these attempts was successful. This taxon is renowned for the 
rarity of its conidial state (e.g., Welch &amp; Gilman 1948, Punitha-
lingam &amp; Holliday 1972, Kmetz 1975, Kulik 1984). Nevertheless, 
Kulik (1984) compiled and compared a series of anamorphic 
characters given by other authors and that work can thus be 
considered a good reference for the anamorphic morphology 
of D. caulivora. Only MAT1-2 mating-type could be detected in 
the isolates that we studied. Since this species is self-fertile, it 
is likely that the MAT1-1-1 primers simply failed to amplify this 
gene in this species. A similar situation was previously found 
for D. viticola isolates (Santos et al. 2010). </p>

<p>A third species found on soybean in Croatia was D. longicolla, 
which is another well-known soybean pathogen (Morgan-Jones 
1985, Sinclair &amp; Backman 1989). The holotype of this taxon 
(Phomopsis longicolla) is housed in BPI (TWH P74 = BPI 
358745) while the ex-type culture is deposited in ATCC (ATCC 
60325). Our isolates were phylogenetically identical to others 
identified as such. Moreover, the morphology of our isolates 
correlated entirely with the original description of this species 
as given by Hobbs et al. (1985). The absence of beta-conidia in 
the isolates used in the present study correlates with the scarcity 
of this type of spores as reported by Hobbs et al. (1985). Since 
this is clearly a species of Diaporthe, a new combination as 
D. longicolla was introduced. </p>

<p>The PCR mating-type diagnosis showed that both mating-types 
exist in D. longicolla and both are present in the genome of 
a single isolate. However, no teleomorph was seen in pure 
cultures. The inability for isolates to form their sexual state, 
together with the fact that the teleomorph of this species has 
never been found in nature indicates that this might be a purely 
anamorphic species. The existence of different mating-types in 
asexual ascomycetes is well documented (Coppin et al. 1997, 
Arie et al. 2000, Pöggeler 2001, Groenewald et al. 2006) and 
other asexual Phomopsis species are known to possess both 
mating-types, such as Phomopsis viticola (Santos et al. 2010). 
Nevertheless, in D. longicolla both mating-types are present in 
the same isolate, which is in contrast to P. viticola where the 
different mating-types are present in separate isolates (Santos 
et al. 2010). </p>

<p>The fourth species found on soybean in Croatia clustered in 
both phylogenetic trees with isolates identified as Phomopsis 
sp. 9. This is an unidentified species that was reported re-
cently on Aspalathus linearis (van Rensburg et al. 2006) and 
Hydrangea macrophylla (Santos et al. 2010). ITS sequence 
comparison revealed that this species has also been found 
on Helianthus annuus (Rekab et al. 2004) and Vitis vinifera 
(van Niekerk et al. 2005) under the name of D. helianthi. Van 
Rensburg et al. (2006) declined to apply a name to this spe-
cies because they had only one isolate that did not sporulate. 
In the present study, not only did our isolates produce fertile </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 27, 2011 </p>

<p>pycnidia but they also formed perithecia when isolates of op-
posite mating-types were crossed in culture. This is the first time 
that the teleomorph of this species has been observed and the 
name D. novem is applied to it. To our knowledge, this is also 
the first report of this species on soybean. Moreover, all of our 
isolates, except AS1, were from soybean seeds collected dur-
ing September 2008 in Slavonija County in Croatia. This can 
thus be considered a consistent isolation of this species from 
soybean in Croatia. Pathogenicity studies would help to clarify 
if this species represents a threat or if it is a weak pathogen 
on this host. It is important to note that this fungus was always 
isolated from symptomless seeds and never from diseased 
stems. Future isolations of Diaporthe and Phomopsis from 
soybean, especially in Croatia, will confirm whether this is an 
emergent pathogen on this host. </p>

<p>Besides the species described in this paper, D. aspalathi (for-
merly named D. phaseolorum var. meridionalis) has also been 
reported on soybean. This species was first described as caus-
ing soybean stem canker in the South-eastern USA (Fernández 
&amp; Hanlin 1996) and the disease was named Southern soybean 
stem canker. It was later established as the main causal agent 
of canker and die-back of rooibos (A. linearis) in South Africa 
(van Rensburg et al. 2006). Diaporthe aspalathi was not found 
on soybean in Croatia during the present study. Although this 
species seems to be geographically restricted, phytosanitary 
measures designed to control this pathogen should not be 
neglected. </p>

<p>It is important to note that the species found on soybean in 
Croatia are also present on several herbaceous hosts such as 
Arctium lappa, Asclepias syriaca and Dipsacus lacinatus (Table 
1). Diaporthe phaseolorum was also found on Helianthus an-
nuus, and this has already been reported in Croatia (Vrandeč ić 
et al. 2009). This observation raises once more the relevance 
of weeds as reservoir hosts for pathogens of economically 
important plants. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements This work was financed by the European Regional 
Development Fund and Fundação para a Ciência e a Tecnologia (FCT) under 
the project PTDC/AGR-AAM/67064/2006 and J. Santos was supported by a 
research grant within the project. A. Phillips was supported by grant number 
SFRH/BCC/15810/2006 from FCT. </p>





<p>J.M. Santos et al.: Diaporthe species on soybean </p>



</text></tei>