<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3794438" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>OBJECTIVES: The incidence of surgical site infection (SSI) after open vein harvesting in coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG) patients 
ranges in different studies between 2 and 20%. Triclosan is an antibacterial substance that reduces the growth of bacteria by inhibiting 
fatty acid synthesis. We hypothesized that wound closure with triclosan-coated sutures would reduce SSI after open vein harvesting. </p>

<p>METHODS: An investigator-initiated prospective randomized double-blind single-centre study was performed with 374 patients, rando-
mized to subcutaneous and intracutaneous leg-wound closure with either triclosan-coated sutures (Vicryl Plus ® and Monocryl Plus ® , 
Ethicon, Somerville, NJ, USA) (n = 184) or identical sutures without triclosan (n = 190) from the same manufacturer. All patients were 
followed up after 30 days (clinical visit) and 60 days (telephone interview). Primary endpoint was SSI within 60 days after surgery 
according to the definition of Center for Disease Control. Predefined secondary endpoints included culture-proven and antibiotic-
treated SSI. </p>

<p>RESULTS: The primary endpoint occurred in 23 patients (12.5%) with triclosan-coated sutures and in 38 patients (20.0%) in the group 
without triclosan (P = 0.0497, risk ratio 0.63, (95% confidence interval 0.39-1.00). Corresponding figures for culture-proven infections 
were 7.6 vs 12.1%, (P = 0.15), and for antibiotic-treated infections, 10.9 vs 18.4%, (P = 0.039). Staphylococcus aureus and coagulase-
negative staphylococci were the most common pathogens in both groups. Insulin-treated diabetes and vein-harvesting time were 
associated with SSI after vein harvesting. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS: Leg-wound closure with triclosan-coated sutures in CABG patients reduces SSIs after open vein harvesting. 
(ClinicalTrials.gov number NCT01212315). </p>

<p>Coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG) is the recommended 
treatment for coronary artery disease-patients with multivessel 
disease and/or left main stenosis [1]. Patients may receive a com-
bination of arterial and venous grafts. The venous graft is most 
often a segment of the great saphenous vein, harvested either 
with an open approach using longitudinal skin incision over the 
vein, or with an endoscopic technique. </p>

<p>Surgical site infections (SSI) after vein harvesting are among 
the most common complications in CABG patients, and these 
infections are troublesome for the patients and associated with 
high costs for the health-care system. The incidence of SSI after 
vein harvesting is usually in the 5-10% range, however, rates 
from 2 to 20% have been reported in different studies [2-4]. 
The large variation in incidence between studies can at least 
partly be explained by wide differences in the definition of SSI 
and the length of the observation period. 
A number of risk factors for SSI in cardiac-surgery patients 
have previously been reported, including advanced age, female 
gender, hypertension, diabetes, obesity and long operation time </p>

<p> † Presented at the 26th Annual Meeting of the European Association for </p>

<p>Cardio-Thoracic Surgery, Barcelona, Spain, 27-31 October 2012. </p>

<p>© The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of The European Association for Cardio-Thoracic Surgery. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), which 
permits non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact 
journals.permissions@oup.com. </p>

<p>ADULT CARDIAC </p>

<p>European Journal of Cardio-Thoracic Surgery 44 (2013) 931-938 </p>

<p>ORIGINAL ARTICLE </p>

<p>doi:10.1093/ejcts/ezt063 Advance Access publication 22 February 2013 </p>

<p>[3, 4]. Another factor that may influence the incidence of SSI in 
CABG patients is the suture used for closure of the wound, since 
bacteria may adhere to the suture material [5]. Sutures can 
be coated with antibacterial substances that may reduce the 
bacterial load in the wound. Triclosan (2,4,4-trichloro-2-hydroxy-
diphenylether) is an antibacterial substance that, in preclinical 
studies, has been shown to reduce the growth of bacteria by 
inhibiting fatty acid synthesis [6]. Triclosan has been used in 
topical preparations for antibacterial purposes. Furthermore, 
triclosan-coated sutures are commercially available and have 
been clinically tested in different surgical procedures with diver-
ging results [7-16]. One randomized controlled trial, comparing 
triclosan-coated sutures with identical sutures without coating in 
CABG patients, failed to demonstrate a difference in the inci-
dence of leg-wound SSI [13]. 
Based on previous clinical and preclinical studies, we hypothe-
sized that wound closure with sutures coated with triclosan 
would reduce SSI after open vein harvesting. We, therefore, con-
ducted a prospective randomized double-blind single-centre 
trial to test this hypothesis. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>Patients planned for CABG, CABG + aortic valve replacement (AVR) 
or CABG + mitral valve repair or replacement at Sahlgrenska 
University Hospital with the intended use of a saphenous vein 
graft, were included in the study between March 2009 and 
February 2012. All patients gave informed written consent before 
inclusion in the study. Exclusion criteria were on-going sepsis or 
septicaemia, on-going bacterial infections or antibiotic treatment, 
participation in other clinical studies, other severe disease that 
might influence wound healing, emergency surgery or known 
allergy to triclosan. The study was approved by the Research Ethics 
Committee at University of Gothenburg and externally monitored. 
Patient characteristics and perioperative data were prospect-
ively registered in an electronic database. Samples for preopera-
tive laboratory analyses (haemoglobin, white blood cell count, 
platelet count, serum-creatinine and plasma-glucose) were col-
lected the day before surgery and analysed with clinical standard 
methods. </p>

<p>Surgical procedure </p>

<p>All patients were operated on with the standard technique for 
CABG or CABG and valve surgery. All operations were performed 
on cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB) in normothermia (35-36°C) 
and with cold intermittent blood cardioplegia. All patients 
received antibacterial prophylaxis with four parenteral doses of 
cloxacillin 2 g. The first dose was administered 30 min before 
skin incision, the second 2 h after the first dose and the follow-
ing doses 6 and 24 h later. Patients with allergy to cloxacillin 
received clindamycin. 
The saphenous vein segment was harvested with an open sur-
gical approach. The great saphenous vein was identified via a in-
cision 1-2 cm above the medial malleolus, and then a single 
longitudinal skin incision was performed along the vein, the vein 
was dissected cautiously and all side branches were ligated or 
clipped. The wound was closed with one subcutaneous </p>

<p>continuous suture and one continuous intracutaneous suture. 
The wound was covered with drape, compresses and elastic ban-
dages. The drape was removed on the fourth postoperative day. </p>

<p>Randomization </p>

<p>The patients were randomized to wound closure with triclosan-
coated sutures or sutures without triclosan. In the triclosan group, 
the wound was closed subcutaneously with a 3.0 monofilament 
polyglactin suture coated with triclosan (Vicryl Plus ® , Ethicon, Inc.,) 
and intracutaneously with a 4.0 triclosan-coated monofilament 
polyglecaprone suture (Monocryl Plus ® , Ethicon, Inc.). In the 
no-triclosan group, identical sutures from the same manufacturer 
without triclosan were used (Vicryl ® and Monocryl ® ). The random-
ization sequence was performed with sealed envelopes. The 
patients were block randomized with 25 patients randomized to 
triclosan-coated sutures and 25 to no-triclosan sutures in each 
block. The randomization was stratified for diabetes. A research 
nurse who was not involved in the patients' follow-up opened the 
randomization envelope and delivered the sutures to the operat-
ing room. Both the coated and non-coated sutures that looked 
identical were taken from their packages and put on the assist 
table without any identification marks before the operating sur-
geons arrived at the operating room. </p>

<p>Follow-up </p>

<p>All wounds were inspected by a specially trained research nurse 
at 4 and 30 days after surgery and evaluated according to both 
the ASEPSIS score and the Centre for Disease Control (CDC) def-
inition of SSI (see below). At 60 days postoperatively, the patients 
were interviewed by telephone by the same research nurse, 
following a structured question form. All the research nurses 
involved in the follow-up of the patients were blinded to group 
allocation. If a patient reported any type of wound healing 
problems including dehiscence, swelling, redness or exudate, 
they were seen at the outpatient clinic, and the wounds were 
evaluated and patient records were collected. Bacterial cultures 
were only collected from patients with symptoms of infection, 
i.e. no surveillance cultures were collected. </p>

<p>Outcome variables </p>

<p>The primary endpoint was SSI in the vein-harvesting leg, accord-
ing to CDC's definition, within 60 days after surgery [17]. 
According to this definition, a superficial SSI must have at least 
one of the following features: (i) purulent drainage; (ii) positive 
culture; (iii) pain, tenderness, swelling, redness and deliberately 
opened incision by surgeon and culture proven or not cultured 
and (iv) Infection diagnosis by physician. Furthermore, a deep 
SSI had to involve fascia or muscle layers. 
Predefined secondary endpoints were (i) culture-proven SSI 
according to CDC's definition within 60 days after surgery; (ii) 
antibiotic-treated SSI according to CDC's definition within 60 
days after surgery; (iii) ASEPSIS score at Days 30 and 60 post-
operatively; (iv) non-infectious leg-wound dehiscence within 60 
days after surgery. 
When using the ASEPSIS score [18], the wound is evaluated in 
seven dimensions: A = additional treatment with antibiotics </p>

<p>L. Thimour-Bergström et al. / European Journal of Cardio-Thoracic Surgery </p>

<p>
(10 points), debridement (10 points) with purulent drainage 
(5 points); S = serous discharge (0-5 points); E = erythema 
(0-5 points); P = purulent exudates (0-10 points); S = separation 
of deep tissues (0-10 points); I = isolation of bacteria (10 points); 
S = stay in hospital &gt;14 days (5 points). A score 0-10 indicates no 
infection, 11-20 disturbance of healing, 21-30 minor infection, 
31-40 moderate infection and &gt;40 points severe infection [18]. 
Two independent observers (L.T.B. and A.J.) classified all 
wound problems according to the CDC's definition before the 
randomization code was broken. Disagreement in wound evalu-
ation was solved by consensus. </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation, median and 
range or number and percentage. A P-value of &lt;0.05 was consid-
ered statistically significant. The power analysis of developing a 
harvest-leg SSI was based on a pilot study performed at our insti-
tution (infection rate 20%) together with a literature review. Our 
analysis with 80% power and a P-value of 0.05 showed it was </p>

<p>necessary to include 180 patients in each group to demonstrate a 
50% reduction in a leg-wound infection according to the CDC 
definition ( primary endpoint) in one of the groups. Data were 
analysed according to the 'as treated' principle ( predefined). 
The groups were compared with unpaired t-test (continuous 
normally distributed data), Mann-Whitney test (continuous data 
not normally distributed) or χ 2 test (categorical variables). The 
effect of type of suture on SSI was evaluated with the χ 2 test and 
reported with risk ratio (RR) with 95% confidence interval (CI). 
The temporal distribution of the primary endpoint was com-
pared with the log-rank test, including 5 patients who were lost 
at the last follow-up. All calculations were performed on the 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistica</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">10</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">StatSoft</rs>, Tulsa, OK, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>Included in the study were 392 CABG patients with the intended 
use of a saphenous vein graft. A flow chart of the patients is </p>

<p>Figure 1: Flow chart of all patients in the study. </p>

<p>ADULT CARDIAC </p>

<p>L. Thimour-Bergström et al. / European Journal of Cardio-Thoracic Surgery </p>

<p>
shown in Fig. 1. The statistical analysis was based on 374 
patients, 304 males (81%) and 70 females (19%) with a mean age 
of 67 ± 8 years. Patient demographics are presented in Table 1 
and perioperative variables are given in Table 2. </p>

<p>Infections </p>

<p>SSI as defined by CDC ( primary endpoint) occurred in 23 
patients (12.5%) in the triclosan group and in 38 (20.0%) in the 
no-triclosan group, P = 0.0497. RR was 0.63 (95% CI 0.39-1.00), 
as given in Table 3. The temporal distribution of the primary 
endpoint is demonstrated in Fig. 2. The predefined secondary 
endpoint culture-verified SSI occurred in 14 of the patients in 
the triclosan group (7.6%) and in 23 of those (12.1%) in the 
no-triclosan group, P = 0.145 [RR 0.63 (95% CI 0.33-1.18)]. The 
predefined secondary endpoint antibiotic-treated SSI occurred 
in 20 (10.9%) vs 35 (18.4%) patients, P = 0.039 [RR 0.59 (95% CI 
0.35-0.98)]. ASEPSIS score tended to be lower in the triclosan 
group, both at 30 and 60 days after surgery, but the difference 
did not reach statistical significance, Table 3. </p>

<p>Patients with infection vs no-infection </p>

<p>Patient demographics for patients with and without harvest-leg 
SSI as defined by CDC are reported in Table 4. Insulin-treated 
diabetes mellitus was the only statistically different preoperative 
variable with a 2-fold-higher prevalence in the infection group 
(P = 0.029). Perioperative variables are reported in Table 5. 
Number of distal anastomoses was higher (P = 0.014) and vein-
harvesting time was longer in patients with SSI (P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Microbiological agents </p>

<p>In total, 45 wound cultures were obtained, 16 from patients in 
the triclosan group and 29 from the no-triclosan group. In the 
triclosan group, 88% of the cultures were positive and 79% in 
the no-triclosan group. The most common pathogen in both 
groups of patients was Staphylococcus aureus, followed by 
coagulase-negative staphylococci. A complete list of the cultured 
microorganisms is given in Supplementary Table 1. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The main finding of this prospective randomized double-blind 
study was that triclosan-coated sutures significantly reduced SSIs 
after open vein harvesting in CABG patients. 
Preclinical studies have shown that triclosan-coated sutures 
reduce the growth of Gram-positive bacteria, e.g. S. aureus and 
coagulase-negative staphylococci, and Gram-negative bacteria, 
e.g. Pseudomonas aeruginosa and Escherichia coli [19, 20]. These 
studies have been followed by both non-randomized retrospect-
ive studies and prospective controlled trials in different surgical 
populations to test if triclosan-coated sutures reduce SSIs. 
However, the results have been conflicting. Rozelle et al. [12] 
reported reduced incidence of infections with triclosan-coated 
sutures in wound closure for cerebrospinal fluid shunts in a pro-
spective randomized trial, and Justinger and co-workers reported 
similar results from two non-randomized studies after abdominal 
surgery [10, 11]. Furthermore, Galal et al. [8] reported a reduced 
infection rate in a prospective randomized study in mixed surgi-
cal patients. On the other hand, Baracs et al. [7] found no differ-
ence in infection incidence in a randomized controlled trial in 
abdominal surgery, and both Williams et al. [16] and Turtianien 
et al. [15] reported the same outcome after breast-cancer 
surgery and lower-limb vascular surgery, respectively. In cardiac-
surgery patients, Stadler et al. [14] found no difference in sternal 
wound infection in a retrospective study and in a randomized 
study, Isik et al. [9] found no difference in either sternal wound 
or leg-wound infections. In a recent systematic review and 
meta-analysis of randomized trials with triclosan-coated sutures, 
Chang et al. [21] concluded that triclosan-impregnated sutures 
do not decrease the rate of SSI, but also pointed out that the 
quality of the studies were moderate and further high-quality in-
dependent studies are required. 
In the only previously published prospective randomized trial 
with triclosan-coated sutures focussing on leg-wound infections 
after vein harvesting in CABG patients, Seim et al. [13] could not 
identify any difference in SSI rates. The different findings from 
our study could be related to several factors. Seim's study was 
not blinded and outcome measures were based on self-reports </p>

<p>Table 1: Patient demographics in the triclosan and 
no-triclosan group </p>

<p>Triclosan 
No triclosan 
P-value </p>

<p>N 
184 
190 
Mean age (year) 
67.6 ± 8.3 
66.9 ± 8.1 
0.45 
Female sex 
39 (21.1) 
31 (16.3) 
0.23 
BMI 
27.6 ± 4.1 
27.6 ± 4.1 
0.67 
Diabetes 
No 
138 (75.0) 
140 (73.7) 
0.77 
Insulin treatment 
22 (11.9) 
21 (11.1) 
0.78 
Oral treatment 
20 (10.8) 
22 (11.6) 
0.83 
Dietary treatment 
4 (2.2) 
7 (3.7) 
0.38 
Smoking 
Never 
70 (38.0) 
74 (38.9) 
0.86 
Previous (&gt;1 month ago) 
82 (44.5) 
82 (43.2) 
0.78 
On-going 
29 (15.8) 
31 (16.3) 
0.88 
Missing 
3 (1.6) 
3 (1.6) 
0.91 
Mean EuroSCORE 
4.0 ± 2.0 
3.7 ± 2.2 
0.15 
Angina type 
Unstable 
88 (47.8) 
95 (50.0) 
0.67 
Stable 
90 (48.9) 
93 (48.9) 
0.60 
No angina 
6 (3.3) 
2 (1.1) 
0.12 
Peripheral artery disease 
16 (8.7) 
16 (8.4) 
0.92 
Preoperative medication 
Acetylsalicylic acid 
172 (93.5) 
178 (93.7) 
0.98 
Clopidogrel 
70 (38.0) 
72 (37.8) 
0.92 
Beta-blocker 
160 (87.0) 
166 (87.4) 
0.97 
ACE-inhibitor 
106 (57.6) 
120 (63.1) 
0.24 
Corticosteroids 
8 (4.3) 
6 (3.2) 
0.54 
Preoperative laboratory analyses 
Haemoglobin (g/l) 
138 ± 13 
140 ± 14 
0.33 
White blood cell count 
(×10 9 /l) </p>

<p>7.6 ± 1.8 
7.6 ± 1.8 
0.87 </p>

<p>Platelet count (×10 9 /l) 
270 ± 80 
267 ± 71 
0.67 
Serum creatinine (µmol/l) 
85 ± 23 
86 ± 22 
0.48 
Plasma-glucose (mmol/l) 
7.1 ± 2.8 
7.0 ± 2.7 
0.99 </p>

<p>Mean ± standard deviation or number (%). 
ACE: angiotensin converting enzyme; BMI: body mass index. </p>

<p>L. Thimour-Bergström et al. / European Journal of Cardio-Thoracic Surgery </p>

<p>
from the patients, not on a structured follow-up with trained 
observers blinded to group assignment. Finally, and perhaps 
most importantly, the length of the follow-up differed in these 
two studies. In Seim et al.'s study, the follow-up was restricted to 
30 days while in the present study, the final follow-up occurred 
60 days after surgery. Our decision to follow the patients for 60 
days was based on a previous study from Swenne et al. [4] where 
27% of the leg-wound infections were diagnosed between 30 
and 60 days after surgery and a study from Jonkers et al. [22] </p>

<p>where 37% of leg-wound infections were diagnosed after 30 
days. These results were confirmed in the present study where 
19/61 of the leg-wound infections (31%) were diagnosed 
between postoperative days 30 and 60 (Fig. 2). 
Our extended follow-up may also, at least partially, explain the 
high incidence of leg-wound SSI in the present study. The inci-
dence of SSI ranges in different studies between 2 and 20% de-
pending on definition, the follow-up time, system of reporting 
infections and design of the study [2-4]. It is well known that the 
rate of complications is higher in prospective trials with manda-
tory follow-up than in retrospective studies. However, the high 
incidence of SSI is troublesome, and new methods and measures 
are warranted to reduce its incidence. One possibility is to use </p>

<p>Table 2: Perioperative characteristics in the triclosan and no-triclosan group </p>

<p>Triclosan 
No-triclosan 
P-value </p>

<p>Operation 
CABG 
164 (89.1) 
167 (87.9) 
0.71 
CABG + AVR 
17 (9.2) 
22 (11.6) 
0.46 
CABG + mitral repair 
3 (1.6) 
1 (0.5) 
0.30 
Number of bypasses 
3.0 ± 0.9 
3.2 ± 1.0 
0.008 
Operation time (min) 
Total 
181 ± 51 
185 ± 54 
0.41 
CPB 
80 ± 31 
84 ± 33 
0.30 
Aortic clamping 
52 ± 25 
55 ± 26 
0.33 
Vein harvesting 
52 ± 21 
51 ± 23 
0.83 
Length of leg incision (cm) 
43 ± 14 
44 ± 14 
0.62 
Person harvesting the vein 
Surgeon 
78 (42.4) 
92 (48.4) 
0.24 
Surgical trainee 
106 (57.6) 
98 (51.6) 
0.24 
Postoperative bleeding (ml/12 h) 
470 (95-1950) 
482 (110-4550) 
0.94 
Transfusions (units) 
Packed red cells 
0 (0-15) 
0 (0-20) 
0.73 
Plasma 
0 (0-9) 
0 (0-20) 
0.54 
Platelets 
0 (0-6) 
0 (0-13) 
0.25 
Haemoglobin at discharge (g/l) 
101 ± 11 
102 ± 11 
0.49 </p>

<p>Mean ± standard deviation, median and range, or number (%). 
AVR: aortic valve replacement; CABG: coronary artery bypass grafting; CPB: cardiopulmonary bypass. </p>

<p>Table 3: Efficacy endpoints in the triclosan and 
no-triclosan group </p>

<p>Triclosan, 
n = 184 </p>

<p>No triclosan, 
n = 190 </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Infection 
CDC criteria 
23 (12.5) 
38 (20.0) 
0.050 
Culture proven 
14 (7.6) 
23 (12.1) 
0.15 
Antibiotic-treated 
20 (10.9) 
35 (18.4) 
0.039 
Wound dehiscence 
(non-infectious) </p>

<p>11/161 (6.8) 
13/152 (8.5) 
0.57 </p>

<p>ASEPSIS score, day 4 
Mean and SD 
0.4 ± 1.2 
0.3 ± 0.8 
0.44 
Median and range 
0 (0-12) 
0 (0-5) 
0.78 
ASEPSIS score, day 30 
Mean and SD 
3.0 ± 7.6 
4.7 ± 9.4 
0.070 
Median and range 
0 (0-45) 
0 (0-43) 
0.20 
ASEPSIS score, day 60 
Mean and SD 
3.7 ± 8.7 
5.4 ± 10.0 
0.097 
Median and range 
0 (0-45) 
0 (0-43) 
0.46 </p>

<p>Mean ± standard deviation, median and range or number (%). 
CDC: Centre for Disease Control; SD: standard deviation. </p>

<p>Figure 2: Cumulative freedom from leg-wound SSI in the triclosan group and 
the no-triclosan group. T: triclosan, nT: No triclosan. Also patients lost at the 
last follow-up (n = 5) are included in the graph. </p>

<p>ADULT CARDIAC </p>

<p>L. Thimour-Bergström et al. / European Journal of Cardio-Thoracic Surgery </p>

<p>
endoscopic vein harvesting, as this has been shown to lower the 
risk of wound infections in comparison to open conventional 
techniques [23]. Of the known risk factors for SSI after vein har-
vesting, only insulin-treated diabetes mellitus was associated 
with SSI in the present study. In addition, vein-harvesting time 
emerged as a risk factor for SSI. The association between vein-
harvesting time and SSI remained after adjustment for the ex-
perience of the assisting surgeon (data not shown) and the 
length of the incision. This suggests that a more complicated 
vein-harvesting procedure increases the risk for SSI. The discrep-
ancy in risk factors between different studies indicates that risk 
factors for SSI in cardiac surgery may be local rather than 
general. 
Even though our results suggest the use of triclosan-coated 
sutures in order to lower the risk for SSIs, two important aspects 
of triclosan use in health care products should be discussed. 
First, it has been shown that there is a risk of antimicrobial resist-
ance to triclosan, including its use in topical products (e.g. cos-
metics) where resistance to populations of S. aureus has been 
reported [24]. This must be regarded as a major drawback in the 
use of triclosan as resistance to antibacterial substances repre-
sents a growing problem in modern medicine. On the other 
hand, if the use of conventional antibiotics in patients with SSI 
can be reduced by 40% with triclosan-coated sutures, as the 
results of the present study suggest, this may balance or out-
weigh the disadvantages. The second issue is the long degrad-
ation time of triclosan and the potential risk for bioaccumulation 
in the environment [25]. 
The primary endpoint in the study had a P-value of 0.0497 
when assessed with χ 2 test, but 0.0516 when the Fisher's exact 
test was used, a P-value just above the commonly used statistical 
threshold of 0.05. This difference between these tests is very 
small (0.00186) and not clinically significant; particularly as the 
cut-off P-value of 0.05 is arbitrary. Furthermore, the P-value for 
the somewhat stronger secondary endpoint (antibiotic-treated </p>

<p>Table 4: Patient demographics in patients with and 
without leg infection according to CDC's definition </p>

<p>Infection 
No infection 
P-value </p>

<p>n 
61 
313 
age (years) 
66.6 ± 7.7 
67.3 ± 8.3 
0.53 
Female sex 
11 (18.0) 
59 (18.9) 
0.88 
BMI 
28.3 ± 4.3 
27.4 ± 3.8 
0.081 
Diabetes 
No 
41 (67.2) 
237 (75.7) 
0.16 
Insulin treatment 
12 (19.7) 
31 (9.9) 
0.029 
Oral treatment 
5 (8.2) 
37 (11.8) 
0.41 
Dietary treatment 
3 (4.9) 
8 (2.6) 
0.32 
Smoking 
Never 
22 (36.0) 
122 (39.0) 
0.67 
Previous (&gt;1 month ago) 
27 (44.3) 
137 (43.8) 
0.94 
On-going 
12 (19.7) 
48 (15.3) 
0.40 
Missing data 
0 
6 (1.9) 
0.28 
EuroSCORE 
3.6 ± 1.9 
3.9 ± 2.2 
0.23 
Peripheral artery disease 
7 (11.5) 
25 (8.0) 
0.37 
Preoperative medication 
Acetylsalicylic acid 
59 (96.7) 
291 (93.0) 
0.27 
Clopidogrel 
24 (39.3) 
118 (37.7) 
0.82 
Beta-blockers 
56 (91.8) 
270 (86.3) 
0.24 
ACE-inhibitor 
39 (63.9) 
187 (59.7) 
0.56 
Corticosteroids 
1 (1.6) 
13 (4.2) 
0.34 
Preoperative laboratory analyses 
Haemoglobin (g/l) 
141 ± 11 
139 ± 14 
0.35 
White blood cell count 
(×10 9 /l) </p>

<p>7.5 ± 1.9 
7.6 ± 1.8 
0.60 </p>

<p>Platelet count (×10 9 /l) 
259 ± 66 
270 ± 77 
0.31 
Serum creatinine (µmol/l) 
87 ± 21 
85 ± 22 
0.58 
Plasma-glucose (mmol/l) 
7.1 ± 3.0 
7.0 ± 2.7 
0.82 </p>

<p>Mean ± standard deviation or number (%). 
ACE: angiotensin converting enzyme; BMI: body mass index; 
CDC: Centre for Disease Control. </p>

<p>Table 5: Operative characteristics in patients with and without leg infection according to CDC's definition </p>

<p>Leg infection, n = 61 
No leg infection, n = 313 
P-value </p>

<p>Operation 
CABG 
56 (91.8) 
275 (87.9) 
0.38 
CABG + AVR 
4 (6.6) 
35 (11.2) 
0.28 
CABG + mitral repair 
1(1.6) 
3 (1.0) 
0.64 
Number of bypasses 
3.4 ± 1.0 
3.1 ± 1.0 
0.014 
Operation time (min) 
Total 
184 ± 44 
183 ± 54 
0.76 
CPB 
81 ± 26 
82 ± 33 
0.95 
Aortic clamping 
53 ± 21 
53 ± 27 
0.92 
Vein harvesting 
61 ± 32 
48 ± 19 
&lt;0.001 
Incision length (cm) 
46 ± 12 
43 ± 14 
0.15 
Person harvesting the vein 
Surgeon 
28 (45.9) 
141 (45.0) 
0.90 
Trainee 
33 (54.1) 
172 (55.0) 
0.90 
Postoperative bleeding (ml/12 h) 
430 (95-1485) 
500 (140-4550) 
0.050 
Transfusions (units) 
Red blood cells 
0 (0-9) 
0 (0-20) 
0.072 
Plasma 
0 (0-8) 
0 (0-20) 
0.93 
Platelets 
0 (0-6) 
0 (0-13) 
0.68 
Haemoglobin at discharge (g/l) 
101 ± 10 
102 ± 11 
0.36 </p>

<p>Mean ± standard deviation, median and range or number (%). 
AVR: aortic valve replacement; CABG: coronary artery bypass grafting; CDC: Centre for Disease Control; CPB: cardiopulmonary bypass. </p>

<p>L. Thimour-Bergström et al. / European Journal of Cardio-Thoracic Surgery </p>

<p>
CDC infection) was &lt;0.05 both with the χ 2 test (0.039) and with 
Fisher's exact test (0.042). This supports the conclusion that the 
triclosan suture significantly reduces bacterial leg-wound 
complications. 
In conclusion, the results of the present study suggest that 
triclosan-coated sutures reduce the incidence of SSI after vein 
harvesting in CABG patients by 35%. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL </p>

<p>Supplementary material is available at EJCTS online. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This study was supported by the Västra Götaland Healthcare 
Region (ALF/LUA grant number 146281 to A.J.) and Ethicon, Inc., 
Somerville, NJ, USA. </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest: none declared. </p>



<p>APPENDIX. CONFERENCE DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Dr S. Collins (Lund, Sweden): I think this is a problem that usually, as surgeons, 
we don't want to see and we don't see because, of course, we don't do 
follow-up of more than 30 days. 
I was interested in the slide where you show there was no significance in 
the culture-proven infection. There was no significance between the triclosan 
and the no-triclosan while in the antibiotic there was. Have you got any idea 
why this can happen? 
Dr Jeppson: Both these diagrams showed the same pattern, about a 40% 
reduction, and we are actually balancing on the P value of 0.05. So I don't 
think you should draw any strong conclusions from just this slide. We saw, 
overall, a reduction in infections. 
I think the reduction in antibiotic-treated infections is interesting, because 
if triclosan is not good to use because of environmental reasons and because 
of the risk of antibiotic resistance, we had to balance that with a 40% reduc-
tion in the use of conventional antibiotics in these patients. I can't say if it 
ends up proving that triclosan sutures should be used, but, still, we have to 
take into account that triclosan-coated sutures may reduce the use of stand-
ard antibiotics. 
Dr Collins: Another question. What was your strategy when you had a leg 
wound infection? For how long do you treat these patients and with which 
preferred drug? 
Dr Jeppsson: We use a staphylococcus antibiotic like flucloxacillin as our 
first choice. I have not shown you the data today, but about 50% of all infec-
tions were caused by staphylococcus aureus and another 20% were caused by 
coagulase-negative staphylococcus. So some kind of staphylococcus antibio-
tics I think should be used in these patients. If the infection is not too exten-
sive we put the patient on antibiotics and tell them to come back three days 
later. 
Dr Collins: And then you look clinically to see whether or not they are 
improving. 
Dr Jeppsson: Yes. </p>

<p>ADULT CARDIAC </p>

<p>L. Thimour-Bergström et al. / European Journal of Cardio-Thoracic Surgery </p>

<p>
Dr Collins: And the last question is, when you do have to open the leg, 
what do you do? Do you put a VAC in it, a small VAC, or not? 
Dr Jeppsson: If it is extensive, a VAC. If it is not, no VAC. 
Dr Collins: So if it is beyond the knee then you place the VAC, but if it is 
just a little you don't? 
Dr Jeppsson: It depends on the extension of the infection. 
Dr V. Kurfirst (Ceske Budejovice, Czech Republic): Just one brief question. Do 
you use any type of minimally invasive harvesting techniques, which signifi-
cantly reduce the number of wound complications? </p>

<p>Dr Jeppsson: This was one of the questions that I expected. We don't use it 
today, but we are actually discussing starting it. I think that is a way to reduce 
infections. I think these figures in our study are scary. I mean, almost a 20% 
infection rate, we have to do something about this. I think that endoscopic 
vein harvesting would be one possibility. The problem is that it is expensive 
and you really have to show that you can get that cost back. Don't you agree? 
Dr Kurfirst: In my department we are doing about 70% with endoscopic 
and about 30% with the bridging technique. So we rarely see any infections. 
Dr Jeppsson: And you follow them for 60 days? 
Dr Kurfirst: Yes. </p>

<p>L. Thimour-Bergström et al. / European Journal of Cardio-Thoracic Surgery </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>