<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3138425" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>The fastest-evolving regions in the human and chimpanzee genomes show a remarkable excess of weak (A,T) to strong (G,C) 
nucleotide substitutions since divergence from their common ancestor. We investigated the phylogenetic extent and possible 
causes of this weak to strong (W/S) bias in divergent sequences (BDS) using recently sequenced genomes and 
recombination maps from eight trios of eukaryotic species. To quantify evidence for BDS, we inferred substitution histories 
using an efficient maximum likelihood approach with a context-dependent evolutionary model. We then annotated all 
lineage-specific substitutions in terms of W/S bias and density on the chromosomes. Finally, we used the inferred 
substitutions to calculate a BDS score-a log odds ratio between substitution type and density-and assessed its statistical 
significance with Fisher's exact test. Applying this approach, we found significant BDS in the coding and noncoding sequence 
of human, mouse, dog, stickleback, fruit fly, and worm. We also observed a significant lack of W/S BDS in chicken and 
yeast. The BDS score varies between species and across the chromosomes within each species. It is most strongly correlated 
with different genomic features in different species, but a strong correlation with recombination rates is found in several 
species. Our results demonstrate that a W/S substitution bias in fast-evolving sequences is a widespread phenomenon. The 
patterns of BDS observed suggest that a recombination-associated process, such as GC-biased gene conversion, is involved 
in the production of the bias in many species, but the strength of the BDS likely depends on many factors, including genome 
stability, variability in recombination rate over time and across the genome, the frequency of meiosis, and the amount of 
outcrossing in each species. </p>

<p>The recent sequencing of the genomes of many closely re-
lated species has created a powerful new paradigm for in-
vestigating the evolutionary processes that generate the 
diversity of life on Earth. Comparing the complete human 
genome sequence to that of a chimpanzee, our closest living 
relative, Dreszer et al. (2007) demonstrated that the most 
divergent regions of both genomes show a striking W/S 
substitution bias and that this association is correlated with 
recombination rates. This bias in divergent sequences (BDS) 
is not limited to neutrally evolving sequences and can signif-
icantly impact substitution patterns in conserved noncoding 
sequences (Pollard, Salama, King et al. 2006) and protein-
coding exons (Berglund et al. 2009; Ratnakumar et al. 
2010), suggesting the possibility of significant functional </p>

<p>consequences. These observations have profound implica-
tions regarding the interpretation of adaptive evolution in 
fast-evolving sequences of the human genome and our un-
derstanding of the evolutionary forces driving divergence 
between closely related species in general. 
In this paper, we explore two fundamental questions 
about BDS and what the phenomenon tells us about ge-
nome evolution and function. First, is BDS unique to the 
hominoids or a more widespread phenomenon? The recent 
sequencing of many closely related eukaryotic species ena-
bles us to investigate the phylogenetic extent of BDS. Sec-
ond, what evolutionary processes produce BDS? Based on 
the patterns of BDS found in human, Dreszer et al. 
(2007) argued that GC-based gene conversion (gBGC) 
(Duret and Galtier 2009) is the cause of BDS. gBGC is a non-
adaptive evolutionary process that favors the fixation of </p>

<p>ª The Author(s) 2011. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/ 
2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>



<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 3:516-527. doi:10.1093/gbe/evr051 Advance Access publication June 13, 2011 </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>weak alleles near the double-strand breaks that initiate re-
combination events. Episodes of gBGC in a genomic region 
could produce an association between W/S substitutions 
and substitution density (BDS) by driving W/S mutations to 
fixation in recombination hotspots. We investigate the ori-
gin of BDS by examining correlations between BDS and ge-
nomic variables, including recombination rates, in different 
species. 
To examine BDS in a broader phylogenetic context, we 
characterized recent substitutions in eight trios of eukaryotic 
organisms including: human (Homo sapiens), mouse (Mus 
musculus), dog (Canis familiaris), chicken (Gallus gallus), stick-
leback (Gasterosteus aculeatus), fruit fly (Drosophila mela-
nogaster), worm (Caenorhabditis elegans), and yeast 
(Saccharomyces cerevisiae). We selected these species based 
on availability of sequenced genomes for a closely related 
comparison taxon and an outgroup, quality of the genome 
assemblies, and (if possible) availability of recombination 
maps. 
To enable these genome-wide analyses, we inferred sub-
stitution histories using maximum likelihood and a context-
dependent model of evolution with the <rs id="software-6" type="software">PHAST</rs> package 
(<rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">Hubisz et al.</rs>. <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-date">2011</rs>). This approach accounts directly for 
CpG hypermutability and other context effects that can lead 
to incorrect inference of substitution type (e.g., W/S vs. 
not W/S) in parsimony-based analyses. Next, we analyzed 
substitution patterns using a new efficient statistical test for 
the association of nucleotide substitution types with substi-
tution rates and genome annotations. Most previous studies 
of substitution patterns in divergent regions have focused on 
discrete predefined elements across the genome; in contrast, 
our approach is more broad and allows a flexible continuous 
definition of ''divergent'' based on the density of substitution 
across the genome. Our work extends the approach of 
Dreszer et al. (2007) and provides a more rigorous statistical 
framework for measuring associations between substitution 
type and density. 
Using these tools, we confirm the previously observed 
pattern of BDS in the human genome and its association 
with elevated recombination rates. Our analysis of non-
primate clades shows that BDS is common outside of hu-
man, though not universal. When BDS is present, it exists 
in both coding and noncoding sequence and is often, but 
not always, correlated with high rates of recombination. 
This correlation, paired with the lack of W/S bias in 
within-species polymorphisms, argues that a recombina-
tion-driven fixation bias for strong nucleotides, such as 
that produced by gBGC, may be involved in the production 
of BDS, especially when there is variation in strength and 
location of gBGC over time. Overall, the strong evidence 
we find for BDS in many eukaryote genomes highlights the 
importance of understanding its causes and developing 
statistical models of DNA and protein evolution that incor-
porate these observations. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Data </p>

<p>Genome sequences and multiple sequence alignments of 
recent assemblies for all species (fig. 1) were downloaded 
from the University of California, Santa Cruz (UCSC) Ge-
nome Browser (Kent et al. 2002). The genome alignments 
were constructed from syntenic pairwise alignments which 
were then multiply aligned using the UCSC/MULTIZ align-
ment pipeline (Kent et al. 2003; Blanchette et al. 2004). 
When more than one precomputed alignment was available 
for a reference species, we chose the most phylogenetically 
restricted. For chicken, we did not consider the microchro-
mosomes (International Chicken Genome Sequencing Con-
sortium 2004) in our analysis. The following genome 
assemblies were used (UCSC identifiers): hg18, panTro2, 
rheMac2, mm9, rn4, cavPor2, canFam2, felCat3, bosTau4, </p>

<p>FIG. 1.-The patterns of BDS across eight eukaryotic lineages. 
Each trio of species contains a reference (red branch), comparison, and 
outgroup species. Substitutions occurring on the branch leading to the 
reference species from the last common ancestor with the comparison 
species were considered. The color of each box reflects the strength of 
the BDS in the associated species. Warm colors (reds) indicate W/S 
BDS, and cool colors (blues) indicate a preference against W/S 
substitutions in fast-evolving regions. Asterisks indicate a significant 
deviation from expected substitution patterns. BDS statistics for each 
species are given in table 1. </p>

<p>GC-Biased Substitutions in Divergent Sequences </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 3:516-527. doi:10.1093/gbe/evr051 Advance Access publication June 13, 2011 </p>



<p>galGal3, taeGut1, anoCar1, gasAcu1, oryLat1, fr2, dm3, 
droSim1, droYak2, ce6, caePb2, caeJap1, sacCer2, sacPar, 
sacMik. Conservation scores for each reference species were 
downloaded from the Genome Browser; phyloP (Pollard 
et al. 2010) scores were used when available, otherwise 
phastCons (Siepel et al. 2005; Hubisz et al. 2011) scores 
were used. Species trees and divergences were taken from 
the phastCons tree models estimated from 4-fold degener-
ate sites using <rs id="software-5" type="software">phyloFit</rs> (Siepel et al. 2005; <rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">Hubisz</rs> et al. 
2011). 
The raw single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) data for 
human and mouse come from dbSNP (Sherry et al. 2001) 
release 130 and 128, respectively. SNPs for chicken were 
identified by the Beijing Genomics Institute and downloaded 
from the UCSC Genome Browser bgiSNP track. 
Recombination rate data were obtained from a variety of 
sources. For human, we used the combined recombination 
map from the HapMap project (The International Hapmap 
Consortium 2007), as well as the deCODE genetics male 
and female maps which are based on 15,257 Icelandic 
parent-offspring pairs (Kong et al. 2010). Mouse recombi-
nation data were downloaded from the Mouse Map Con-
verter (Jackson Laboratories 2009), which is based on SNP 
analysis across 46 families (Shifman et al. 2006; Cox et al. 
2009). The chicken recombination map from Groenen et al. 
(2009) is based on SNPs across three mapping populations. 
For fruit fly, the Drosophila Recombination Rate Calculator 
(Fiston-Lavier et al. 2010), which compares genetic and 
physical maps of the genome to infer recombination rates, 
was used. </p>

<p>Analysis </p>

<p>Our BDS analysis pipeline consists of several steps. For each 
clade of interest, we started with an alignment of three spe-
cies: reference, comparison (sister taxon), and outgroup. 
Our analysis workflow is as follows (details below). First, 
the three-species alignments were filtered for alignment 
quality. Then substitution histories were computed using 
maximum likelihood and a context-dependent evolutionary 
model. Given the set of expected recent substitutions, the 
association between patterns of substitution and substitu-
tion density (BDS) was quantified. Finally, the strength of 
the BDS across the genome was correlated with several 
other genomic features. 
Data processing and analysis were performed using cus-
tom programs written in R (R Development Core Team 
2009) and Python with SciPy (Jones et al. 2001) and mat-
plotlib (Hunter 2007). </p>

<p>Alignment Filtering. In order to study patterns of substi-</p>

<p>tution between species, it is crucial that the data are not pol-
luted by false substitutions introduced by alignment errors. 
We filtered all alignments in a consistent manner across 
each set of species using several criteria that could be </p>

<p>applied in each clade considered. First, repetitive sequences 
as identified by the UCSC Genome Browser alignment pipe-
line were not considered. These regions were identified us-
ing the Tandem Repeats Finder and <rs id="software-12" type="software">RepeatMasker</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-12" type="creator">Smit and Hubley</rs> 2008-2010) and are indicated by lowercase letters in 
the alignments. (See the Genome Browser documentation for 
more details.) Next, the quality of the alignment around each 
position was considered. If there were any insertions or dele-
tions between the reference and comparison species within 
five base pairs (bp) of a position, then it was not considered. 
Finally, all positions in regions of the genome that had signif-
icant homology to another region of the genome were filtered 
out. These duplicated or repetitive regions are often difficult to 
align to other species due to their similarity. These regions 
were removed using the Genome Browser's chainSelf track 
of significant alignments of a genome with itself. </p>

<p>Identification of Recent Substitutions. We are inter-</p>

<p>ested in substitutions that occurred in the reference species 
since its divergence from the last common ancestor with 
the comparison species-for example, on the human lineage 
after its last common ancestor with chimpanzee. These 
branches of interest are indicated in red in figure 1. After fil-
tering the alignments as described above, we fit a context-
dependent dinucleotide phylogenetic model to the align-
ments for each chromosome using maximum likelihood. 
We used the general unrestricted dinucleotide model with 
strand symmetry (U2S) (Siepel and Haussler 2004). This phy-
logenetic model was fit to the alignments with <rs type="software">phyloFit</rs> from 
the <rs id="software-14" type="software">PHAST</rs> software package (<rs corresp="#software-14" type="creator">Hubisz et al.</rs>. <rs corresp="#software-14" type="version-date">2011</rs>). Using the 
model, we computed (also using <rs type="software">phyloFit</rs>) the posterior 
expectednumberof substitutionsof eachtypeon each branch 
of the tree for each site in the alignment. </p>

<p>Calculation of BDS. Given the inferred probabilities of </p>

<p>each type of substitution on the branch of interest at each 
site across each genome, we quantified the BDS with a log 
odds ratio that relates the density and pattern of substitu-
tions across a genomic region. The odds ratio is based on 
a two-by-two contingency table in which each possible sub-
stitution was classified as 1) W/S or not W/S and 2) in 
a divergent sequence or not. Any substitution from an A or T 
in the ancestor to G or C in the reference species was W/S, 
and all others were not. Each position was classified as di-
vergent/not divergent based on the substitution density in 
a genomic window of a given size around it. The expected 
number of substitutions of each type on the reference 
branch at this position was then added to the relevant cell 
of the contingency table. 
Given the resulting two-by-two contingency table for 
a genomic region of interest, we calculated the log odds ra-
tio and associated statistics in the standard manner after 
rounding the expected number of substitutions in each cell 
to the nearest whole number. This log odds ratio quantifies 
the strength of association between W/S bias and </p>

<p>Capra and Pollard </p>

<p>GBE </p>



<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 3:516-527. doi:10.1093/gbe/evr051 Advance Access publication June 13, 2011 </p>

<p>sequence divergence. If substitutions in divergent windows 
exhibit an excess of W/S changes, then the log odds ratio 
is greater than zero. It is less than zero if these divergent 
regions contain fewer W/S substitutions than expected. 
We refer to this log odds ratio as the BDS score and use 
the terms ''bias,'' ''BDS,'' and ''W/S BDS'' to refer to in-
creased W/S substitution in regions of high divergence. 
The genomic regions over which the BDS score was calcu-
lated may be small sequence blocks (as used in the correla-
tion analysis), a set of regions across the genome (as in the 
coding sequence analysis), or the entire genome. The signif-
icance of the BDS score was assessed with Fisher's exact test 
(FET). All reported P values are from the FET unless otherwise 
indicated. 
We explored a range of window sizes and density cut-
offs; figure 2 demonstrates the robustness of our results to 
any specific cutoff. When a single cutoff was required, we 
used window size of 1,000 bp and a substitution density 
such that as near to 5% of all substitutions as possible were 
assigned to the divergent group. Because the reference-
comparison species pairs we examined have different levels 
of sequence divergence, this threshold varies in absolute 
value across species (i.e., it is lower for species that are less 
diverged and higher for species that are more diverged). </p>

<p>Correlation of Genomic Features across the Genome. </p>

<p>To explore the correlation of data that vary across the genome, 
we selected an appropriate block size on which the features 
could be quantified. (This was often limited by the scale of the 
recombination maps available or the number of expected sub-
stitutions in a region.) Nonoverlapping blocks of 1 Mb were 
used for all species except for fly, worm, and yeast, where we 
used blocks of 10 and 100 kb due to their smaller genomes. 
We created a vector for each feature being compared, for 
example, BDS and recombination rate, across each corre-
sponding block of the genome and calculated the Spearman 
rank correlation across all blocks. We also calculated and plot-
ted the Spearman correlation of smoothed versions of the 
data. The data were smoothed by convolution with 
a seven-block Hanning window. To evaluate the significance 
of the difference in the correlation of a genomic feature with 
two other features, for example, in the comparison of BDS 
with male and female recombination rate, empirical P values 
were obtained by bootstrapping with 10,000 comparisons to 
random features. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>BDS Occurs in Vertebrates and Invertebrates </p>

<p>We calculated BDS scores and P values for eight diverse eu-
karyotic lineages (fig. 1). Figure 2A gives the BDS computed 
over substitutions on the human lineage since divergence 
from its last common ancestor with chimp for a range of 
window sizes and substitution density thresholds. For each </p>

<p>window size, there is significant BDS; that is, the fastest-
evolving regions show a significant enrichment for W/S 
nucleotide substitutions (increasing curves; all P % 0). This 
result is in agreement with that reported in Dreszer et al. 
(2007) using parsimony to infer substitutions and a different 
statistical test for association between substitution type and 
density. 
Extending the analysis to other lineages, we find signif-
icant BDS in mouse (P 5 5.2 Â 10 
À5 ), dog (P % 0), stickle-
back (P % 0), fruit fly (P % 0), and worm (P 5 5.1 Â 10 </p>

<p>À5 </p>

<p>) 
(fig. 1 and table 1). As in the human genome, the patterns of 
BDS in these species are not sensitive to the particular win-
dow size and density thresholds used (fig. 2 and supplemen-
tary fig S1, Supplementary Material online). However, we do 
observe interspecies differences in the magnitude of the 
BDS score. Dog exhibits the strongest bias, whereas mouse 
has the weakest statistically significant W/S BDS. 
Reversing the roles of the reference and comparison spe-
cies, we also find BDS in chimpanzee and several additional 
genomes (data not shown). However, inference of substitu-
tion histories is more difficult in comparison species, whose 
genome assemblies tend to be lower quality and often lack 
the resources for proper alignment quality filtering. 
We also calculated a variation of the BDS score that con-
siders only W/S and S/W substitutions. This resulted in 
slightly elevated scores compared with considering all sub-
stitution types. For example, in human, the bias increased 
from 0.12 to 0.14. </p>

<p>Chicken and Yeast Show a Significant Lack of 
W/S BDS </p>

<p>We do not observe W/S BDS in either chicken or yeast 
(table 1). In contrast to the other vertebrates analyzed, 
chicken shows a small but significant strong-to-weak 
(S/W) bias in fast-evolving regions (P 5 5.3 Â 10 </p>

<p>À6 </p>

<p>). Sim-
ilarly, yeast shows a significant excess of S/W nucleotide 
changes in divergent regions (P55:8Â10 
À7 , fig. 2D). This 
pattern in fixed substitutions is consistent with the S/W 
mutation bias observed in yeast (Lynch et al. 2008). In 
the next sections, we investigate several aspects of BDS 
that help us to interpret these observations. We consider 
possible explanations in the Discussion. </p>

<p>Variation in BDS between Species Is Not Due to 
Their Divergence </p>

<p>The species trios analyzed exhibit a range of evolutionary 
distances between the reference and comparison species 
(fig. 1; table 1). It is possible that the length of the branch 
considered might affect 1) our power to detect BDS and 2) 
the estimated strength of the BDS between the two species 
compared. Several observations argue against such biases, 
however. First, significant BDS patterns were observed in all 
comparisons. Hence, even though branch length likely </p>

<p>GC-Biased Substitutions in Divergent Sequences </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 3:516-527. doi:10.1093/gbe/evr051 Advance Access publication June 13, 2011 </p>



<p>influences the test's power, we are still able to detect a signal 
in each lineage. Additionally, the strength of the BDS ob-
served between two species is not well correlated with their 
divergence (table 1). We also calculated BDS in substitutions 
between human and a series of increasingly divergent spe-
cies that mirror the divergences of the other eukaryotic spe-
cies sets considered here. In three of the four comparisons 
(human with tarsier, tree shrew, and opossum), significant 
bias was still identifiable between human and the more dis-
tant comparison species (supplementary table S1, Supple-
mentary Material online). However, the fact that W/S 
BDS was not found in one of the comparisons (human with 
marmoset) suggests that the sources of BDS may not be 
constant over time or that our ability to detect BDS depends 
upon the quality of the comparison genome. We also tested </p>

<p>the use of increasingly divergent outgroup species and 
found no major influence on patterns of BDS. Thus, our 
method is able to detect bias within the range of divergence 
found in the species sets we analyzed, including those used 
to quantify BDS in chicken and yeast. We therefore conclude 
that factors other than evolutionary distance appear to drive 
the variation in BDS between lineages. </p>

<p>BDS Occurs in Both Coding and Noncoding Regions </p>

<p>Coding and noncoding sequences are often under very 
different patterns of evolutionary constraint. The protein-
coding fractions of the genomes we considered vary from 
around 2% in human to 73% in yeast (table 2). Thus, if sub-
stitution bias is different in coding and noncoding regions, 
this could influence our conclusions about the phylogenetic </p>

<p>FIG. 2.-Divergent sequences are significantly W/S biased in many, but not all, eukaryotes. Genomic regions with a high divergence show 
a significant enrichment for W/S substitutions (BDS) compared with regions with fewer substitutions. BDS is found in human (A), mouse, dog (B), 
stickleback, fly, and worm (C). In contrast, chicken and yeast (D) do not exhibit significant W/S BDS. These patterns are not sensitive to the size of the 
window (500-2000 bp) or the substitution density threshold. The gray bars indicate 95% confidence intervals for the BDS score. This figure includes 
substitution densities for which between 1% and 99% of substitutions are considered divergent. Table 1 gives BDS statistics for all species considered, 
and plots are provided for the other four species in supplementary figure S1 (Supplementary Material online). </p>

<p>Capra and Pollard </p>

<p>GBE </p>



<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 3:516-527. doi:10.1093/gbe/evr051 Advance Access publication June 13, 2011 </p>

<p>distribution of BDS. In particular, if BDS was absent or very 
weak in coding regions, we would have less power to detect 
genome-wide BDS in species with a high fraction of coding 
DNA, such as worm and yeast. 
To investigate this issue, we calculated BDS scores sep-
arately for coding regions in each species. Table 2 demon-
strates that in species with significant genome-wide BDS, 
significant bias is present in coding sequence considered 
alone. Interestingly, coding regions generally exhibit 
stronger BDS than noncoding sequence. Similarly, coding 
sequence in yeast and chicken show S/W BDS, in agree-
ment with the genome-wide evidence of S/W BDS in 
these species. The S/W bias in chicken coding regions 
is of similar magnitude to the genome-wide amount, 
but is not significant. This is not surprising given the weak 
signal in chicken genome wide. These results argue that 
patterns of bias in coding and noncoding sequences are 
usually in agreement and that the different fraction of 
coding sequence in different genomes is unlikely to be 
the source of their different bias patterns. </p>

<p>Intraspecies BDS Varies within and between 
Chromosomes </p>

<p>In the previous sections, a single BDS score was computed 
for each species to quantify genome-wide patterns of bias. </p>

<p>To profile variation in BDS within genomes, we computed 
BDS scores across the chromosomes of each species in win-
dows ranging in length from 10 kb to 1 Mb. 
The strength of BDS varies across the chromosomes of 
each species (fig. 3). Some sections of the chromosome have 
significant bias, whereas others do not exhibit any BDS. This 
variation was observed previously in human (Dreszer et al. 
2007), where a significant increase in BDS was found near 
the telomeres of most human and chimp chromosomes. Al-
though variance in the BDS score is universal, increased BDS 
near telomeres is not a general phenomenon in all species 
we considered. 
BDS strength also varies between chromosomes. To com-
pare the bias between chromosomes, we computed the BDS 
score for each chromosome in each species. In human, all 
chromosomes show peaks of significant BDS, but there is 
significant variation in the strength of the bias overall on dif-
ferent chromosomes (P , 2.2 Â 10 </p>

<p>À16 </p>

<p>., Woolf test). The 
overall GC content of a chromosome is strongly correlated 
with recombination rate and negatively correlated with 
chromosome length in many species, including human 
(Fullerton et al. 2001) and chicken (International Chicken 
Genome Sequencing Consortium 2004). To frame BDS pat-
terns in the context of these previous findings, we correlated 
its strength on each human chromosome with these fea-
tures. Chromosomal BDS was not significantly correlated 
with the chromosome's GC content (Spearman q50:04), re-
combination rate (q5 À 0:01), or length (q50:04). A similar 
lack of correlation of chromosomal BDS with GC content, 
recombination rate, and length was observed in all other 
species with significant BDS. </p>

<p>Local BDS Is Often Correlated with Recombination 
Rate </p>

<p>To investigate patterns of BDS at a finer scale, we calculated 
Spearman rank correlations of BDS in 1 Mb blocks with 
several genome features that vary across chromosomes: 
sex-averaged recombination rate, evolutionary conservation, </p>

<p>Table 1 
BDS Statistics in Eight Eukaryotic Species. </p>

<p>Divergent Regions 
Nondivergent Regions 
Branch 
Species 
W/S 
Not W/S 
W /S 
Not W/S 
Length 
BDS 
P value </p>

<p>Human 
0.445 
0.555 
0.425 
0.575 
0.01 
0.12 
%0 
Mouse 
0.419 
0.581 
0.415 
0.585 
0.17 
0.02 
5.2 Â 10 </p>

<p>À5 </p>

<p>Dog 
0.512 
0.488 
0.423 
0.577 
0.20 
0.52 
%0 
Chicken 
0.392 
0.608 
0.401 
0.599 
0.34 
À0.05 
5.3 Â 10 </p>

<p>À6 </p>

<p>Stickleback 
0.439 
0.561 
0.418 
0.582 
0.43 
0.13 
%0 
Fruit fly 
0.297 
0.703 
0.270 
0.730 
0.13 
0.19 
%0 
Worm 
0.311 
0.689 
0.295 
0.705 
0.81 
0.11 
5.1 Â 10 </p>

<p>À5 </p>

<p>Yeast 
0.426 
0.574 
0.442 
0.558 
0.25 
À0.10 
5.8 Â 10 </p>

<p>À7 </p>

<p>NOTE.-BDS is a log odds ratio quantifying the association between W/S substitution and the density of substitution. P values are computed using FET. Branch lengths are given 
in expected substitutions per site. All statistics are based on a cluster size of 1,000 bp and a density threshold that results in approximately 5% of substitutions being placed in the 
divergent class. </p>

<p>Table 2 
BDS Is Present in Coding Regions. </p>

<p>Species 
Percent Coding 
Coding BDS </p>

<p>Human 
2.4 
0.51 
Mouse 
2.3 
0.11 
Dog 
1.5 
0.83 
Chicken 
3.0 
À0.07 
Stickleback 
8.2 
0.14 
Fruit fly 
18.5 
0.51 
Worm 
27.9 
0.36 
Yeast 
72.9 
20.11 </p>

<p>NOTE.-Bold indicates significant BDS. </p>

<p>GC-Biased Substitutions in Divergent Sequences </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 3:516-527. doi:10.1093/gbe/evr051 Advance Access publication June 13, 2011 </p>



<p>GC content, and substitution rate (table 3). Stickleback, 
worm, and yeast were not included in the recombination cor-
relation analysis due to lack of appropriate recombination 
maps. Our findings support the previous result in human, ob-
tained using different methods, that recombination rate and 
BDS are correlated (Dreszer et al. 2007). This pattern occurs in 
other species as well; three of the four species (human, </p>

<p>mouse, and fly) that have significant genome-wide BDS 
and recombination rate data show a significant correlation 
between these variables. The one exception is dog, which 
has experienced a recent pseudogenization of the PRDM9 
gene (Oliver et al. 2009). This loss may explain the strong 
BDS in dog and the lack of correlation between BDS and re-
combination (see Discussion). BDS is not consistently </p>

<p>FIG. 3.-BDS is often correlated with recombination rate. The BDS varies in strength along chromosomes and is significantly correlated with sex-
averaged recombination rate in (A) human chromosome 6 (q50:36 smoothed, P 5 9 Â 10 
À7 ) and (B) mouse chromosome 16 (q50:36 smoothed, P 5 2 </p>

<p>Â 10 
À4 ). The smoothed data are plotted with solid lines, and the raw values are indicated with dashed lines. See table 3 for genome-wide correlation </p>

<p>statistics for these and other species on the raw data. For ease of visualization and comparison in this figure, the data have been scaled so that the 
minimum value is 0 and the maximum is 1. </p>

<p>Capra and Pollard </p>

<p>GBE </p>



<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 3:516-527. doi:10.1093/gbe/evr051 Advance Access publication June 13, 2011 </p>

<p>correlated with GC content, substitution density, or conser-
vation, although specific species do show modest significant 
correlations with some of these variables. Most notably, three 
out of the six species with genome-wide BDS have a positive 
correlation between BDS and evolutionary sequence conser-
vation. 
Overall, our analyses suggest that BDS and recombina-
tion rate are often but not always correlated. It also appears 
that fluctuations in BDS are not directly associated with GC 
percent, divergence, or conservation; however, factors that 
indirectly influence these features may be relevant to the 
production of BDS patterns in some species. </p>

<p>BDS and Recombination Are More Strongly Corre-
lated in Males </p>

<p>In the species for which we have sex-specific recombination 
data, we also considered the correlation of these rates with 
BDS separately for the two sexes. Previous studies of human 
Alu repeats (Webster et al. 2005) and substitution hotspots 
(Dreszer et al. 2007) indicate that biases associated with re-
combination may have a sex-specific impact. We find that 
BDS in human and mouse is more strongly associated with 
male recombination rate than with female (q50:152 vs. 
0:119 in human, P % 0:042; q50:093 vs. 0:014 in mouse, 
P % 0:001). In dog, BDS does not show a significant corre-
lation with sex-averaged recombination rate. However, 
when looking at male and female rates separately, the cor-
relation with the male rate is significantly greater than with 
female (q50:058 vs. À0:039, P % 0:001), and though it is 
small in magnitude, the correlation between male recombi-
nation rate and BDS is significant (P 5 0.018). 
In contrast, when looking sex-specific rates in chicken, 
a species that does not show significant BDS overall, neither 
male or female recombination rates are significantly associ-
ated with BDS across the genome (q5 À 0:079 and À0:074, 
respectively), and the difference between the sex-specific 
correlations is not significant. These results suggest that when </p>

<p>significant genome-wide BDS is present, the spatial correla-
tion of BDS and recombination along a species' chromosomes 
is consistently higher in males. Sex-specific recombination 
data from additional species would help to test and further 
explore this hypothesis. </p>

<p>BDS Is Not Present in SNPs </p>

<p>Our test can also be applied to SNP data to study bias in 
population-level sequence variation. Dreszer et al. (2007) 
found no W/S bias in regions of the human with a high 
density of SNPs, suggesting that a fixation bias rather than 
a mutation bias was likely responsible for the BDS. To ex-
plore the phylogenetic extent of this pattern, we considered 
SNPs in human, mouse, and chicken. SNPs for each species 
were downloaded from the UCSC Table Browser (Karolchik 
et al. 2004). The ancestral variant was identified by parsi-
mony using the alignment with the comparison species. 
Then, BDS scores were computed for SNPs using the same 
methods as used for fixed differences. SNPs for which 
no comparison species was present or with indeterminate 
ancestry were not considered in the analysis. 
SNPs in human, mouse, and chicken do not exhibit W/S 
BDS (supplementary fig. S4, Supplementary Material on-
line). This contrasts with the patterns in recent fixed substi-
tutions in human and mouse. In fact, there is a significant 
lack of W/S changes in regions with the highest SNP den-
sity; the BDS scores are À0:095 for human SNPs (P % 0), 
À0:018 for mouse (P 5 3.3 Â 10 </p>

<p>À5 </p>

<p>), and À0:177 for 
chicken (P 5 8.5 Â 10 </p>

<p>À6 </p>

<p>). Thus, just as the BDS in recent 
fixed substitutions is present in species other than human, 
the previously observed lack of BDS in human SNPs also ap-
pears to be a general pattern. This result suggests that BDS is 
unlikely to be driven by local variation in mutation rates and 
patterns. </p>

<p>BDS Patterns Are Robust to the Methodology Used 
to Infer Substitution Histories </p>

<p>The use of parsimony to infer substitution types can poten-
tially introduce biases into analyses of substitution patterns 
(Eyre-Walker 1998; Hernandez et al. 2007). CpG hypermu-
tability, which increases the probability of multiple substitu-
tions at a site and depends on the dinucleotide context, is 
a particular concern. To avoid these possible biases, our re-
sults are based on genome-wide substitution histories re-
constructed in a maximum likelihood framework using 
a context-dependent evolutionary model. For comparison, 
we also performed the analysis using 1) maximum likelihood 
with a noncontext-dependent strand-specific reversible 
model (SSREV) and 2) parsimony. 
Using maximum likelihood with the SSREV model produ-
ces very similar conclusions to those obtained with the U2S 
context-dependent model (supplementary fig. S2, Supple-
mentary Material online). This suggests that context-</p>

<p>Table 3 
Correlation of BDS with Other Genome Features. </p>

<p>Recombination 
GC 
Substitution 
Species 
Rate 
Percent 
Density 
Conservation </p>

<p>Human 
0.16 
0.05 
0.08 
À0.01 
Mouse 
0.08 
0.10 
À0.02 
0.09 
Dog 
0.02 
À0.09 
À0.04 
0.11 
Chicken 
À0.09 
À0.12 
À0.03 
0.06 
Stickleback 
N/A 
0.02 
0.08 
0.02 
Fruit Fly 
0.10 
0.15 
À0.05 
0.14 
Worm 
N/A 
0.03 
À0.02 
À0.11 
Yeast 
N/A 
0.07 
À0.06 
0.03 </p>

<p>NOTE.-Each value is the Spearman correlation of BDS with the specified feature 
across blocks of the genome. Bold indicates a significant correlation at the 0.01 level. 
Blocks of 1 Mb were used for all species, except for fly (100 kb), worm (10 kb), and 
yeast (10 kb). The raw values for each feature were used; the correlation coefficients 
generally increase if the data are smoothed before calculation (e.g., see fig. 3). </p>

<p>GC-Biased Substitutions in Divergent Sequences </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 3:516-527. doi:10.1093/gbe/evr051 Advance Access publication June 13, 2011 </p>



<p>dependent effects, such as CpG hypermutability, do influ-
ence the results slightly, but not significantly. The use of par-
simony also leads to qualitatively similar conclusions; 
however, worm and chicken change their BDS classification 
(supplementary fig. S3, Supplementary Material online). 
When comparing all three methods, the two maximum like-
lihood approaches agree most closely, suggesting that using 
parsimony may indeed have an impact on inferred substitu-
tion histories. This is likely the result of fairly long branches in 
several of the clades considered; these are more likely to 
have experienced multiple substitutions, which would be 
missed by parsimony. Within the maximum likelihood con-
text, our results are robust to the use of a context-depen-
dent model or not, indicating that CpG effects are not 
the driving force behind BDS. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We have demonstrated that divergent regions of several 
metazoan genomes from human to worm are associated 
with elevated rates of W/S substitution relative to the rest 
of the genome. In contrast, chicken and yeast do not exhibit 
significant BDS. </p>

<p>Episodic Biased Gene Conversion Is a Likely Cause 
of BDS </p>

<p>In human and several other species with significant BDS, we 
found consistent BDS in coding as well as noncoding 
sequences, correlations between BDS scores and recombi-
nation rates (especially in the male sex), and no significant 
BDS in SNPs. All of these observations are consistent with 
a recombination-associated, nonadaptive fixation bias as 
a cause of BDS. gBGC is a likely candidate. This bias occurs 
when there is a weak-strong polymorphism in a recombina-
tion heteroduplex, and the DNA mismatch is preferentially 
repaired to the strong base pair. These GC-biased conver-
sion blocks are thought to range between 200 bp and 
2 kb in length (Duret and Galtier 2009). gBGC has been 
directly observed in yeast (Mancera et al. 2008), but obtain-
ing experimental evidence for the action of gBGC is 
extremely challenging in other species. Nonetheless, gBGC 
has received considerable attention as a possible explana-
tion for many dominant and unexplained genomic attrib-
utes, such as the large-scale variation in GC content (the 
so-called isochore structure) of mammalian genomes 
(Eyre-Walker and Hurst 2001; Galtier et al. 2001; Meunier 
and Duret 2004; Romiguier et al. 2010). By driving strong 
alleles to higher frequencies and ultimately to fixation 
around recombination hotspots, bursts of gBGC could result 
in an increase in substitution rates and a W/S-biased sub-
stitution pattern (Berglund et al. 2009). These evolutionary 
events could produce the BDS pattern. 
Other evolutionary mechanisms, such as variation in mu-
tation rates across the genome or natural selection for GC </p>

<p>alleles (Eyre-Walker and Hurst 2001), could also produce 
BDS. However, the action of a biased mutation rate is not 
consistent with our observations. Specifically, the lack of 
W/S BDS in SNPs argues against mutation bias as a source 
of the BDS pattern. The relationship between BDS and se-
lection is less clear. If natural selection on GC content drives 
BDS, we would expect consistent differences in bias be-
tween regions of high and low conservation, such as coding 
and noncoding sequence. In most of the taxa we examined, 
significant BDS is present in both coding and noncoding se-
quence, and higher in coding regions. In addition, three spe-
cies (mouse, dog, and fly) show a significant correlation 
between genome-wide patterns of BDS and evolutionary 
conservation. But the three other species with significant 
BDS (human, stickleback, and worm) show no such corre-
lation. If selection has a role in BDS, we might additionally 
expect BDS to be stronger in species with large effective 
population sizes due to the increased efficiency of selection; 
however, this pattern is not observed. Thus, selective forces 
may be involved in the creation of BDS in some lineages, 
perhaps in concert with gBGC, but they are unlikely to 
be the sole cause of BDS. Together, these results suggest 
that there may multiple causes and paths to the creation 
of BDS in genomes. </p>

<p>Why Is BDS Stronger in Some Species than Others? </p>

<p>A recent study of the evolution of GC content across the 
mammalian phylogeny suggests that its dynamics are not 
constant across the tree and are influenced by many factors 
related to life history and genome organization (Romiguier 
et al. 2010). The variation we observe in BDS strength across 
the taxa considered here suggests a similarly dynamic pic-
ture for BDS with many possible factors influencing its 
strength. For example, the phylogenetic extent of gBGC, 
a likely source of BDS, across eukaryotes and its effect on 
genome evolution are currently unknown. There is strong 
sequence-based evidence for gBGC in mammals (Duret 
and Galtier 2009), and a recent comprehensive analysis 
of meiosis products in yeast provided direct experimental ev-
idence of gBGC (Mancera et al. 2008). There is also indirect 
evidence of gBGC in additional eukaryotic taxa, based on 
correlations between GC content and recombination rate 
or chromosome size found in birds (International Chicken 
Genome Sequencing Consortium 2004), turtles (Kuraku 
et al. 2006), flies (Marais et al. 2003), worms (Marais 
et al. 2001), and several other species (Glé min 2010). 
If gBGC is a cause of BDS, our identification of BDS in sev-
eral eukaryotic species adds to the mounting evidence for its 
importance in genome evolution. However, it also suggests 
that population characteristics and mating patterns can in-
fluence the strength of BDS. Generation time, effective pop-
ulation size, frequency of outcrossing, recombination 
pattern, and conversion bias will all influence the effective-
ness of gBGC (Duret and Arndt 2008), and many of these </p>

<p>Capra and Pollard </p>

<p>GBE </p>



<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 3:516-527. doi:10.1093/gbe/evr051 Advance Access publication June 13, 2011 </p>

<p>traits vary between species or within species over evolution-
ary time. These factors complicate cross-species comparison. 
For example, in light of the experimental evidence for 
gBGC in S. cerevisiae (Birdsell 2002; Mancera et al. 
2008), our finding of a significant lack of W/S BDS in yeast 
might seem to argue against gBGC as a cause of the bias. 
However, yeast differs from the other species we analyzed in 
a number of relevant genetic and physiological dimensions. 
Several aspects of sensu stricto yeast biology could act to 
limit gBGC's mutagenic impact. Most wild yeasts studied 
to date have very low frequencies of sex and outcrossing; 
recent work estimates that S. paradoxus undergoes meiosis 
only once in every 1,000 generations and only 1% of mat-
ings are outcrossed (Tsai et al. 2008). Since gBGC requires 
both meiosis and heterozygosity, its effect may be reduced 
in yeast by a factor of approximately 10 
5 compared with ob-
ligately outcrossed species (Marais et al. 2004; Glé min et al. 
2006; Tsai et al. 2010; Harrison and Charlesworth 2011). 
The resulting reduced mutagenic impact of gBGC has been 
proposed as an explanation for several differences in geno-
mic patterns between yeast and other eukaryotes, such as 
the conservation of recombination hotspots (Tsai et al. 
2010). Thus, the lack of detectable BDS in yeast is not incon-
sistent with the theory that gBGC is involved in creating BDS 
in other species. 
Several factors may contribute to the lower BDS observed 
in mouse than in human. For example, recombination rate is 
thought to be approximately two times higher on average in 
human than in mouse (Coop and Przeworski 2006), and it is 
also less variable across mouse chromosomes. Since BDS 
likely results from episodic gBGC (either in time or across 
the chromosome), this relative lack of variation would pro-
duce less difference between divergent and nondivergent 
sequences in mouse. In agreement with this interpretation, 
a very recent study found that substitution patterns are under 
different influences in primates and rodents with a weaker 
effect of gBGC in rodents (Clé ment and Arndt 2011). 
In dog, in contrast to other species with BDS, BDS and 
recombination rate do not show a significant correlation 
across the genome. The PRDM9 gene, which is thought 
to determine the location of about 40% of human recom-
bination hotspots, has been pseudogenized in dog (Oliver 
et al. 2009). This event likely dramatically influenced the re-
combination landscape of dog and thus may explain why 
current recombination patterns do not correlate well with 
historical patterns of bias over the entire branch to the an-
cestor of dog and cat. Further investigations are needed to 
determine exactly why BDS is so strong in the dog genome. 
The chicken genome lacks significant W/S BDS despite 
an estimated recombination rate, on both macro-and mi-
crochromosomes, considerably higher than in human (Inter-
national Chicken Genome Sequencing Consortium 2004). 
However, the chicken karyotype is thought to have been 
far more stable over time than that of most mammals and </p>

<p>may resemble that of the ancestral amniote (Webster et al. 
2006). Lack of chromosomal rearrangements removes a com-
mon source of variation in recombination rate across the ge-
nome over time. In addition, the cellular machinery for 
determining recombination hotspots may be different in birds 
because sauropsids lack PRDM9 as well (Oliver et al. 2009). 
Finally, the varying quality and availability of genome se-
quence data complicate cross-species comparisons of BDS. 
Low-coverage genome sequences are more likely to create 
noise from false substitutions inferred from sequencing er-
rors. Our sequence and alignment quality filters help correct 
for these differences. But in the end, some subsets of each 
genome may still be influenced by error. 
The phylogenetic patterns of BDS identified here point to 
the need for future work integrating all relevant variables in 
a consistent model for BDS. Unfortunately, this approach 
awaits further data generation as many of the important 
variables are not yet well-characterized across multiple taxa. </p>

<p>gBGC and Selection may Jointly Shape the Evolu-
tion of Functional Sequences </p>

<p>The dramatic enrichment for W/S substitutions in and 
around human accelerated regions (HARs) (Pollard, Salama, 
King, et al. 2006; Katzman et al. 2010) and the presence of 
possibly deleterious BDS in coding sequence (Berglund et al. 
2009; Ratnakumar et al. 2010) suggest a complex interac-
tion between BDS, selection, and the evolution of functional 
DNA elements. If the substitutions driving BDS in coding re-
gions are caused by gBGC, they may increase the suscepti-
bility of a gene to malfunction, as would be expected from 
the accumulation of mildly deleterious alleles (Charlesworth 
B and Charlesworth D 1998). 
The presence of BDS in many HARs prompted the sugges-
tion that gBGC, rather than positive selection, may have 
generated the acceleration (Galtier and Duret 2007). Thus, 
we might expect that HARs showing strong evidence of 
gBGC would be less likely to have obtained new functions 
in human. HAR1 and HAR2 (HACNS1), the two fastest 
evolving HARs, have strikingly biased substitution patterns. 
However, there is strong experimental evidence of function 
maintenance in HAR1 (Pollard, Salama, Lambert, et al. 
2006) and gain in HAR2 (Prabhakar et al. 2008)-a surpris-
ing result if the human-specific changes in these sequences 
were created by a purely neutral mutational process. There-
fore, we hypothesize that in some evolutionary scenarios, 
gBGC substitutions may themselves lead to novel functions 
or may set the stage for later adaptive changes, perhaps due 
to compensatory substitutions driven by selection. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>In this study, we used efficient statistical methods to high-
light phylogenetic patterns of a substitution bias. Our anal-
ysis of BDS in many eukaryotes suggests that it is common </p>

<p>GC-Biased Substitutions in Divergent Sequences </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 3:516-527. doi:10.1093/gbe/evr051 Advance Access publication June 13, 2011 </p>



<p>outside of human. Episodic gBGC driven by recombination is 
likely to play a major role in the production of BDS, but 
a number of evolutionary and organismal factors are likely 
to influence its occurrence. These conclusions underscore 
the importance of developing models of sequence evolution 
that incorporate the action of gBGC and other processes 
that interact with selection (Hurst 2009). Several promising 
preliminary steps have been made in the modeling of gBGC 
and selection (Duret and Arndt 2008; Berglund et al. 2009; 
Ratnakumar et al. 2010; Glé min 2010). As more genomes 
are assembled and richer recombination and polymorphism 
data become available for multiple species, we will be able 
to develop a deeper understanding of the causes and effects 
of BDS across the tree of life. </p>

<p>Supplementary Material </p>

<p>Supplementary figures S1-S4 and table S1 are available at 
Genome Biology and Evolution online http://www.gbe. 
oxfordjournals.org/. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Dennis Kostka for many helpful discussions and 
suggestions. This work was supported by the National 
Institute of General Medical Sciences at the National Insti-
tutes of Health [GM82901 to K.S.P.]; and the Alfred P. Sloan 
Foundation. </p>



<p>Capra and Pollard </p>

<p>GBE </p>



<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 3:516-527. doi:10.1093/gbe/evr051 Advance Access publication June 13, 2011 </p>



<p>Associate editor: Laurence Hurst </p>

<p>GC-Biased Substitutions in Divergent Sequences </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 3:516-527. doi:10.1093/gbe/evr051 Advance Access publication June 13, 2011 </p>



</text></tei>