<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3351152" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>It is estimated that 3-5% of all human proteins are 
localized to mitochondria (1), vital organelles that 
supply energy to the cell through the process of oxidative 
phosphorylation (OXPHOS). Approximately 90 proteins 
form the five enzyme complexes that perform OXPHOS 
and 13 of those are encoded in the mitochondrial genome 
(mtDNA). For this reason, mitochondria contain a 
separate translation apparatus, necessary for the synthesis 
of the mtDNA-encoded polypeptides of the OXPHOS 
system. The RNA components (2 rRNAs and 22 
tRNAs) of the mitochondrial translation machinery are 
encoded by mtDNA, while all protein components 
including the mitochondrial ribosomal subunits, transla-
tion factors, tRNA synthetases, tRNA-modifying 
enzymes, and other auxiliary factors are encoded by </p>

<p>nuclear genes and imported to mitochondria from the 
cytosol. Human mitoribosomes consist of a large 
(mt-LSU) and small subunit (mt-SSU) of 39S and 28S, 
respectively, and the entire ribosome has a sedimentation 
coefficient of 55S (2). 
Many genetic defects can lead to perturbations of the 
OXPHOS system and result in multi-system, often fatal, 
human diseases. These genetic defects can be located 
within nuclear DNA (nDNA) or mtDNA. Isolated 
OXPHOS deficiencies, that affect a specific biochemical 
activity of the OXPHOS system, are usually caused by 
mutations in structural genes (coding for a specific com-
ponent of the OXPHOS machinery) or in genes encoding 
proteins responsible for the assembly of a particular re-
spiratory complex. In contrast, inherited pathological 
mutations, affecting either mitochondrially or nuclearly 
encoded components of the mitochondrial translation 
machinery, are associated with combined OXPHOS 
deficiencies affecting multiple enzymes involved in 
cellular respiration. Many mutations in mtDNA-encoded 
genes for the RNA components of the mitochondrial 
translation apparatus (mt-rRNAs and mt-tRNAs) have 
been identified, and detection of yet uncharacterized 
mutations is relatively straightforward. On the contrary, 
a group of mutations in nuclear gene products involved in 
mitochondrial translation linked to human disease has 
emerged only in recent years (3). This group currently 
contains &lt;20 genes including those that encode: transla-
tion elongation factors, proteins of the mitoribosomal 
subunits, several tRNA synthetases, tRNA-modifying 
enzymes [for recent review see (4)] and also other transla-
tion auxiliary proteins, such as TACO1 (CCDC44) (5) or 
c12orf65 (6). Given the complexity of the mitochondrial 
translation system, this list is unlikely to be complete. 
By analogy to other translation systems one would, for 
example, anticipate that mitoribosome assembly factors 
would be present within the above inventory. However, 
to date only paraplegin, a conserved subunit of the 
ATP-dependent m-AAA protease, links the regulation of 
mitoribosome assembly with human mitochondrial 
disease based on studies of the paraplegin homologue in 
yeast mitochondria and a mouse model (7,8). Therefore, it </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +0044 1223 252750; Fax: +0044 1223 252715; Email: michal.minczuk@mrc-mbu.cam.ac.uk </p>

<p>Published online 11 January 2012 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 4097-4109 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkr1282 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>is vital to identify and characterize novel proteins involved 
in the regulation of mitochondrial translation, in particu-
lar those involved in the assembly of mitochondrial 
ribosomes. 
Systematic identification of genes that are found in 
organisms from several phylogenetic lineages, but remain 
largely uncharacterized ('conserved hypothetical' proteins) 
facilitates prediction of human homologues with import-
ant functions. In this context, we analysed a family of 
well-conserved proteins harbouring the YbeB/iojap 
domain (also known as DUF143). For two members of 
this family, YbeB from Escherichia coli (9) and iojap from 
Zea mays, a role in translation regulation has been sug-
gested (10,11). We identified a human protein that shares 
sequence homology with YbeB/iojap-C7orf30. Published 
proteomics data (12,13) and our in silico analysis predicted 
mitochondrial localization. Therefore, we hypothesized 
that C7orf30 is involved in translation in human 
mitochondria. Here we show that C7orf30 is indeed a 
mitochondrial protein that specifically associates with 
the large 39S subunit of the mitochondrial ribosome 
(mt-LSU). We depleted C7orf30 using RNAi and 
analysed the mitochondrial ribosomal subunits by 
sucrose gradient sedimentation and affinity purification 
methods. Inactivation of C7orf30 leads to instability of 
mt-LSU and a consequent loss of fully assembled ribo-
somes that is accompanied by reduced mitochondrial 
translation and respiratory deficiency. We propose that 
C7orf30 participates in the assembly and/or regulation 
of the stability of the large subunit of the mitochondrial 
ribosome. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Plasmids </p>

<p>In order to construct the pcDNA5-C7orf30.FLAG. 
STREP2 plasmid used to generate an inducible Flp-In 
T-Rex 
TM human embryonic kidney 293T (HEK293T) 
cell line, the cDNA encoding C7orf30 (cDNA clone 
MGC:20424, IMAGE:4646294) was modified by PCR to 
introduce unique KpnI (5 
0 ) and AgeI (3 
0 ) sites and the 
resulting fragment was cloned into pcDNA5-FST2 con-
structed as described in (14) using the above restriction 
sites. The D178A and H185A mutants were generated 
using PCR-based mutagenesis and the resulting cDNA 
was cloned into pcDNA5-FST2 as above. </p>

<p>Maintenance and transfection of mammalian cell lines </p>

<p>Human HeLa cells that are routinely used by us for im-
munofluorescence localization of mitochondrial proteins 
were cultured in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle's Medium 
(DMEM) containing 2 mM L-glutamine (Invitrogen) 
with 10% FCS (PAA Laboratories). For immunofluores-
cence experiments HeLa cells were transfected with 
pcDNA5-C7orf30.FLAG.STREP2 using Lipofectamine 
(Invitrogen) according to manufacturer's instructions. 
The Flp-In T-Rex 
TM human embryonic kidney 293T 
(HEK293T) cell line (Invitrogen), which allows for the 
generation of stable doxycycline-inducible expression of 
transgenes by FLP recombinase-mediated integration, </p>

<p>was used to express C7orf30.FLAG.STREP2 and the 
conserved residue mutants. HEK293T cells were grown 
in DMEM containing 2 mM L-glutamine (Invitrogen), 
10% tetracycline free FCS (Autogen Bioclear) and supple-
mented with 100 mg/ml Zeocin (Invitrogen) and 15 mg/ml 
Blasticidin (Invivogen). Cells were transfected using 
Lipofectamine according to the manufacturer's instruc-
tion. Twenty-four hours after transfection the selective 
antibiotics hygromycin (100 mg/ml, Invivogen) and 
blasticidin (15 mg/ml) were added with selective media 
replaced every 3-4 days. </p>

<p>Cell fractionation </p>

<p>Cell fractionation was performed as described in (14)  without the sucrose gradient step. </p>

<p>FLAG-tag affinity purification </p>

<p>Mitochondria were isolated from HEK293T cells 
overexpressing ICT1.FLAG, MRPS27.FLAG or PDE12. 
FLAG essentially as described in (15). Pelleted mito-
chondria were resuspended in lysis buffer and immunopre-
cipitation (IP) was performed with a FLAG M2 affinity 
gel (Sigma) following manufacturer's recommendations. 
Elution was effected with the FLAG peptide. </p>

<p>Immunodetection of proteins </p>

<p>The localization of proteins by immunofluorescence in 
fixed HeLa cells was performed as described previously 
(16). The following antibodies were used: mouse anti-
Flag IgG (Sigma, 1:200), FITC-conjugated anti-mouse 
IgG (Sigma, 1:200). Immunofluorescence images were 
captured using a Zeiss LSM 510 META confocal 
microscope. 
For immunoblot analysis equal amounts of protein cor-
responding to total cell lysates or protein fractions were 
subjected to SDS-PAGE, semi-dry transferred to nitrocel-
lulose membranes, blocked in 5% non-fat milk (Marvel) 
in PBS for 1 h and incubated with specific primary 
antibodies in 5% non-fat milk in PBS for 1 h or overnight. 
The blots were further incubated with HRP-conjugated 
secondary antibodies in 5% non-fat milk in PBS for 1 h 
and visualized using ECL+ (Amersham). 
The primary antibodies used were: rabbit anti-C7orf30 
(Sigma, 1:1000), mouse anti-FLAG IgG (Sigma, 1:5000), 
mouse anti-b-actin IgG (Sigma, 1:7000), mouse anti-CO2 
IgG (Abcam, 1:5000), rabbit anti-SSB1 IgG (kindly 
donated by Prof. D. Kang, 1:4000), mouse anti-GAPDH 
IgG (Abcam, 1:10 000), mouse anti-complex I subunit 
NDUFB8 (MitoSciences, 1:2000), mouse anti-complex II 
subunit 30 kDa (MitoSciences, 1:2000), mouse anti-
complex III subunit core 2 (MitoSciences, 1:2000), 
mouse anti-DAP3/MRPS29 IgG (Abcam, 1:1000) and 
goat anti-MRPL3 (Abcam, 1:1000), mouse anti-
MRPL12 (Abcam, 1:1000), rabbit anti-MRPS18B 
[Proteintech group (PTG), 1:1000]. 
Secondary antibodies were: anti-rabbit IgG-HRP 
(Promega, 1:2000), anti-mouse IgG-HRP (Promega, 
1:2000) and anti-goat IgG-HRP (Sigma, 1:1000) </p>



<p>siRNA gene silencing </p>

<p>Stealth 
TM siRNAs were obtained from Invitrogen and 
delivered to cells using Lipofectamine RNAiMAX. 
Stealth 
TM RNAi duplexes were generated using the fol-
lowing sequences: C7orf30 siRNA1: UCGAUAUGAUG 
GUUUCACUUCUGAG and C7orf30 siRNA2: CGACA 
CUUACAUGCCAUGGCCUUCU. </p>

<p>Measurement of mitochondrial respiration </p>

<p>HeLa cells transfected with siRNA against C7orf30 were 
seeded at 3 Â 10 
4 cells/well in 200 ml growth medium in XF 
24-well cell culture microplates (Seahorse Bioscience) and 
incubated at 37 
C in 5% CO 2 for 36-40 h. One hour 
before the assay growth medium was removed and 
replaced with assay medium (low buffered DMEM, 
10 mM L-glutamine, 1 mM sodium pyruvate, 2 mM 
glucose), with one wash of assay medium, and left to 
stabilize in a 37 
C non-CO 2 incubator. Analysis was 
performed in quadruplicate using a XF24 Extracellular 
Flux Analyzer (Seahorse Bioscience). The wells were 
sequentially injected with 20 mM 2-deoxyglucose (2-DG) 
to inhibit glycolysis, 100 nM oligomycin to inhibit 
ATP-synthase, 
500-1000 nM 
carbonylcyanide-4-
trifluorometho-xyphenylhydrazone (FCCP) to uncouple 
the respiratory chain, and 200 nM rotenone to inhibit 
complex I. Oxygen consumption rate (OCR) was 
measured for each well every 5 min. before and after 
each injection. Test compounds: 2-DG, oligomycin, 
FCCP and rotenone were all obtained from Sigma. </p>

<p>35 S-methionine metabolic labelling of mitochondrial 
proteins </p>

<p>HeLa cells transfected with siRNA against C7orf30 or 
stably transfected HEK293T cells expressing C7orf30. 
FLAG.STREP2 or mutants thereof were induced with 
doxycycline (50 ng/ml) for 3 days prior to 
35 S labelling. 
Growth medium was replaced with methionine/cysteine-
free DMEM (Sigma) supplemented with 2 mM L-glutam-
ine, 48 mg/ml cysteine and 50 mg/ml uridine. The cells 
were incubated for 2 Â 10 min in this medium, then 
transferred to methionine/cysteine-free DMEM medium 
containing 10% (v/v) dialysed FCS and emetine 
dihydrochloride (100 mg/ml). Cells were incubated for 
10 min before addition of 120 mCi/ml of [ 
35 S]-methionine. 
Labelling was performed for 15 min and the cells were 
washed twice with standard growth medium. Protein 
samples (30 mg) were separated on 4-12% SDS-PAGE 
gels, with products visualized and quantified using a 
PhosphorImager system in <rs id="software-0" type="software">ImageQuant</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Molecular Dynamics</rs>, GE Healthcare). </p>

<p>Analysis of mitochondrial ribosome profile on density 
gradients </p>

<p>Total cell lysates (0.7 mg) were loaded on a linear sucrose 
gradient [2 ml 10-30% (v/v)] in 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.2), 
10 mM Mg(OAc) 2 , 80 mM NH 4 Cl, 0.1 M KCl, 1 mM 
PMSF and centrifuged for 2 h 15 min at 100 000g max at 
4 
C (39 000 rpm, Beckman Coulter TLS-55 rotor). 
Twenty fractions (100 ml) were collected and 10-ml 
aliquots were analysed directly by western blotting. </p>

<p>RNA isolation and northern blotting </p>

<p>Total RNA from HeLa cells was isolated using Trizol 
(Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
For northern blots, RNA was resolved on 1% agarose gels 
containing 0.7 M formaldehyde in 1 Â MOPS buffer, trans-
ferred to a nylon membrane in 2Â SSC and hybridized 
with radioactively labelled PCR fragments corresponding 
to appropriate regions of mtDNA or 28S rDNA. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Identification of C7orf30 and in silico analysis of 
proteins containing the DUF143 domain </p>

<p>Analysis of the primary structure of C7orf30 by pairwise 
alignment revealed an evolutionarily well-conserved 
domain of unknown function named DUF143. 
The DUF143 domain of C7orf30 (residues 93-194) 
shares 33% sequence identity with YbeB of E. coli 
(residues 6-105), which has been reported to associate 
with the large subunit (50S) of the bacterial ribosome 
(9,17) and 29% sequence identity with iojap of Zea 
mays (residues 116-213), a protein which is involved in 
the regulation of chloroplast ribosome stability (10,11). 
Additionally, 24% of residues within the DUF143 
domain of C7orf30 are identical to the N-terminal 
domain of Saccharomyces cerevisiae ATP25 protein 
(residues 104-246), which is required for the expression 
and assembly of the Atp9p subunit of the mitochondrial 
ATPase (18) (Figure 1A and B). Bacterial YbeB and plant 
iojap share a similar domain architecture to C7orf30, with 
the DUF143 domain located at the C-terminus of these 
proteins. In ATP25, however, the DUF143 domain is 
located within the N-terminal portion of the protein and 
the C-terminus shares weak sequence homology with the 
metallo-beta-lactamase superfamily (Figure 1B). Three 
dimensional structures of two proteins containing the 
DUF143 domain have been solved: uncharacterized 
protein CV0518 from Chromobacterium violaceum (PDB: 
2id1) and uncharacterized protein BH1328 from Bacillus 
halodurans (PDB: 2o5a). On the basis of structural 
features, DUF143 has been assigned to the superfamily 
of nucleotidyltransferases (NTases) (19), enzymes that 
transfer nucleoside monophosphate (NMP) from nu-
cleoside triphosphate (NTP) to an acceptor hydroxyl 
group belonging to a protein, nucleic acid or small 
molecule. NTases are characterized by the presence of a 
common minimal core of a-b-a-b-a-b-a topology (19) 
(Figure 1). NTases contain the following common 
sequence motifs which include conserved active site 
residues involved in the coordination of divalent ions: 
(i) [DE]h[DE]h (h indicates a hydrophobic amino acid) 
located on the second core b-strand and (ii) h[DE]h 
placed on the third b-strand (Figure 1C and D, see 
hmtCCAse). Our 3D homology modelling of C7orf30 
based on the crystal structure of 2id1 indicated that 
none of the three active site aspartate/glutamate residues 
are conserved in C7orf30 suggesting that the protein is not 
an active NTase. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 4099 </p>

<p>C7orf30 is localized to human mitochondria </p>

<p>Several computer programmes that analyse the 
N-terminal region of proteins for the presence of a poten-
tial mitochondrial targeting sequence (MTS) indicated a 
high probability of a MTS in C7orf30 (MitoProt II 98%, 
MultiLoc 95%, TargetP 84%, Predotar 67%, PSORT 
(mitochondrial matrix) 50%, PSORT II 45%). 
Moreover, C7orf30 was reported to be present in the 
mitochondrial proteome of a motor neuron-like cell 
line, NSC34 (12). In order to study the cellular 
localization of C7orf30 we transiently expressed the 
corresponding cDNA with a FLAG tag in HeLa cells. 
Immunofluorescence analysis revealed that the recombin-
ant protein co-localizes with mitochondria (Figure 2A). </p>

<p>Cell fractionation experiments confirmed the mitochon-
drial localization of the protein, as endogenous 
C7orf30 co-fractionated with the well-characterized mito-
chondrial matrix protein, mtSSB1, and was resistant to 
proteinase K treatment. In similar conditions the outer 
membrane protein TOM22 was truncated by proteinase 
K (Figure 2B). These results suggest that C7orf30 is 
localized within the mitochondria of human cells. </p>

<p>C7orf30 associates with the large subunit of the 
mitochondrial ribosome </p>

<p>Since C7orf30 shares sequence homology with the YbeB 
protein that associates with the large subunit of the bac-
terial ribosome, we set out to determinate whether the </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>33 % </p>

<p>1 
105 </p>

<p>6 
1 0 4 
YbeB </p>

<p>612 </p>

<p>24 % </p>

<p>104 
246 
ATP25 
488 
581 
Lactamase_B 
1 </p>

<p>iojap </p>

<p>29 % </p>

<p>116 
213 </p>

<p>228 
1 </p>

<p>234 </p>

<p>93 
194 
C7orf30 
1 </p>

<p>CV0518 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>V86 
R36 </p>

<p>F34 </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>C7orf30 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>V176 </p>

<p>Y123 </p>

<p>T121 </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 
3 </p>

<p>1 
3 
2 </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>hmtCCase </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D77 </p>

<p>D79 </p>

<p>E121 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>C7orf30 
93 DIDMMVSLLRQENARDICVIQVPPEM---RYTDYFVIVSGTSTRHLHAMAFYVVKMYKHLKCKR( 3)VKIEGKDTDDWLCVD--FGSMVIHLMLPETREIYELEKLW 194 
YbeB 
1 LQDFVIDKIDDLKGQDIIALDVQGKS---SITDCMIICTGTSSRHVMSIADHVVQESRAAGLLP----LGVEGENSADWIVVD--LGDVIVHVMQEESRRLYELEKLW 104 
iojap 
116 FAVSLAKAASEIKATDIRVLCVRRLV---YWTRFFIILTAFSNAQIDAISS-KMRDIGEKQFSK----VASGDTKPNSWTLLD--FGDVVVHIFLPQQRAFYNLEEFY 213 
ATP25p 104 LRKIADLLTGKLGLDDFLVFDLRKKS(8)KLGDFMVICTARSTKHCHKSFLELNKFLKHEFCSS(34)CSAKDLNSEAWYMIDCRVDGIFVNILTQRRRNELNLEELY 246 
. 
*: .: : 
::* :. *. : 
: 
. .. * :* ...:.:::: . * 
:**::: </p>

<p>1 
3 
2 </p>

<p>hmtCCase 
CV0518 </p>

<p>C7orf30 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Properties of the NTase-like fold of C7orf30. (A) Multiple protein sequence alignment of the DUF143 domain. Protein sequence of the 
DUF143 domain (PFAM: PF02410) of E. coli YbeB (Genbank Accession No. NP_752658), Z. mays iojap (Genbank Accession No. NP_001105495), 
S. cerevisiae Atp25p (Genbank Accession No. NP_013816) and human C7orf30 (Genbank Accession No. NP_612455) were extracted from the 
PFAM database (42) and aligned using CustalW2. The boundaries of the sequence segment used in the alignment are indicated. Colons and dots 
denote chemical similarity between the sequences, whereas asterisks indicate identical residues. The secondary structure based on the resolved 
structure of the bacterial DUF143 protein CV0518 (pdb: 2id1) is indicated above the alignment [helix (cylinders), strand (arrow)]. Three b-sheets 
(numbered 1-3) and four a-helices of NTases a/b-fold are presented in red and yellow, respectively. (B) Domain architecture of proteins comprising 
the DUF143 domain. Functional domains of proteins containing DUF143 are schematically represented. The position of the DUF143 domain is 
indicated and represented in each protein by an orange box containing the percentage of identical residues between this domain and that of C7orf30. 
The green box represents a partial metallo-beta-lactamase domain (PFAM: PF00753) found in Atp25p using PSI-BLAST searches. (C) A comparison 
of C7orf30 NTase-like fold with that of a known NTase. Protein sequence alignment of the three core b-strands of the NTase fold (yellow) (43) of 
the human mitochondrial CCA tRNA nucleotidyltransferase 1 (hmtCCAse) (PDB: 2ou5), bacterial YbeB-type protein from C. violaceum (CV0518) 
(PDB: 2id1) and predicted core b-strands of the homology model of C7orf30 constructed with the reference to the crystal structure of CV0518. The 
two conserved aspartates (D) and a glutamate (E) involved in coordination of divalent ions by hmtCCAse are indicated in blue and cyan, respect-
ively. Corresponding residues in the CV0518 structure and the C7orf30 model are also coloured. (D-F) Ribbon diagrams indicating the key 
secondary structure elements of the NTase fold. The structures of hmtCCase (D), CV0518 (E) and the homology model of C7orf30 (F) are presented. 
The three-stranded, mixed b-sheets (yellow) and four a-helices (red) of the common core of the minimal fold are presented. The conserved aspartate/ 
glutamate residues and the corresponding residues in CV0518 and the C7orf30 model are shown as sticks and colour coded as presented in C. </p>



<p>human homologue might bind to the mitoribosome. To 
investigate this, we carried out sucrose gradient sedimen-
tation of human HeLa cell extracts followed by detection 
of C7orf30 and the components mt-SSU (28S) and 
mt-LSU (39S) by western blotting of gradient fractions. 
We used MRPS18B or DAP3/MRPS29 as markers 
for mt-SSU and MRPL3 or MRPL12 as markers 
for mt-LSU. Analyses of the sedimentation of mito-
ribosomal subunits revealed that C7orf30 is located in 
fractions positive for the mt-LSU markers (Figure 3A, </p>

<p>fractions 9-12) and low molecular weight fractions 
(Figure 3A, fractions 1-6). These results indicate that a 
part of the mitochondrial pool of C7orf30 associates with 
mt-LSU. A proportion of C7orf30 that is found at the top 
of the gradient likely represents free protein or protein in a 
low molecular weight complex, similarly to the MRPL12 
protein (Figure 3A, fractions 1-6). A very similar sedimen-
tation pattern has been obtained for YbeB, the bacterial 
homologue of C7orf30 (9). 
In order to gain further insights into the interaction of 
C7orf30 with the mitoribosome, we performed pull-down 
experiments in Flp-In T-Rex 
TM Human embryonic 
kidney (HEK293T) cell lines inducibly expressing 
either FLAG-tagged MRPS27, a component of mt-SSU, 
or FLAG-tagged ICT1, a component of mt-LSU (15). 
It has been reported previously that MRPS27.FLAG 
and ICT1.FLAG are able to pull-down components of 
mt-SSU or mt-LSU, respectively, with each of these 
proteins also capable of pulling down the entire 
monosome (15). We have performed IP with anti-FLAG 
antibodies after inducing MRPS27.FLAG or ICT1.FLAG 
for 3 days with 50 ng/ml doxycycline and analysed the 
eluates by western blotting. The C7orf30 protein 
co-purified with ICT1.FLAG (Figure 3B, lane 2) consist-
ent with the interaction of C7orf30 with mt-LSU. The lack 
of other highly abundant mitochondrial proteins, such as 
subunit 2 of complex IV (CO2), in the elution fraction 
implies specific interaction (Figure 3B). In contrast, 
C7orf30 was absent from the elution fraction of the 
MRPS27.FLAG IP suggesting that the C7orf30 protein 
does not interact with mt-SSU (Figure 3B, lane 4). 
Proteins of mt-LSU (MRPL3 and MRPL12) were 
present in the elution fraction of the MRPS27.FLAG 
IP, consistent with co-purification of the intact mitochon-
drial monosome (Figure 3B, lane 4). However, the lack of 
C7orf30 in this fraction suggests that the protein does 
not bind to the fully assembled mitoribosome. Finally, 
the specificity of C7orf30 association with mt-LSU was 
further confirmed in an IP experiment with a FLAG-
tagged version of the PDE12 protein (PDE12.FLAG) 
that according our previous studies is a mitochondrial 
RNase not associated with the mitoribosome (20). 
There was no C7orf30 nor any mitoribosomal pro-
teins readily detected in the IP experiment with 
PDE12.FLAG (Figure 3B, lane 5). Taken together, the 
results of sedimentation of C7orf30 on sucrose gradients 
and the IP experiments indicate that the C7orf30 protein 
associates exclusively with the large subunit of the mito-
chondrial ribosome. </p>

<p>C7orf30 is necessary for OXPHOS function </p>

<p>In order to assess the role of C7orf30 in OXPHOS, we 
silenced the expression of the gene by siRNA. We 
identified two siRNAs that depleted the protein in HeLa 
cells as verified by western analysis (Figure 4A), however, 
'siRNA 1' was more effective as compared to 'siRNA 2', 
which was particularly apparent after 3 days of siRNA 
treatment (Supplementary Figure S1). Upon inactivation 
of C7orf30 a reduction in the steady-state levels of the 
respiratory chain subunits was observed, which correlated </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>4 
3 </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>TOM22 </p>

<p>T 
D 
C Mitochondria 
Proteinase K </p>

<p>Fraction </p>

<p>Triton X </p>

<p>-
-
-
+ 
+ 
-
-
-
-
+ 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>C7orf30 </p>

<p>mtSSB1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>fl 
tr </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>Figure 2. Mitochondrial localization of C7orf30. (A) The intra-cellular 
localization of C7orf30 by immunofluorescence. The cDNA encoding 
the 
STREP2-
and 
FLAG-tagged 
variant 
of 
C7orf30 
(C7orf30.FLAG.STREP2) was transiently transfected into HeLa cells. 
Cell nuclei were stained with DAPI (blue, 1). C7orf30.FLAG.STREP 
was detected by anti-Flag antibody and visualised by secondary 
antibodies conjugated with FITC (green, 2). Mitochondria were 
stained with MitoTracker Red CMXRos (red, 3). Co-localization of 
the mitochondria-specific red signal and C7orf30-specific green signal 
appears yellow on digitally merged images (4). (B) Location of C7orf30 
in sub-cellular fractions. The HeLa cells were fractionated into debris 
(D, lane 2), cytosol (C, lane 3) and mitochondria (lanes 4-6). The 
mitochondrial fraction was treated with 25 mg/ml proteinase K in the 
absence (lane 5) or presence of 1% Triton X-100 (lane 6). 'T' indicates 
the total cell lysate. The fractions were analysed by western blotting 
using antibodies to C7orf30. The location of C7orf30 was compared 
with that of the following marker proteins: mtSSB1 (mitochondrial 
matrix side), TOM22 (mitochondrial outer membrane) and GAPDH 
(cytosol). 'fl' means TOM22 of full length, 'tr' means truncated 
TOM22. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 4101 </p>

<p>well with the effectiveness of the specific siRNA 
(Figure 4A). Although almost complete knockdown of 
C7orf30 was observed after 6 days for the two siRNAs 
(Figure 4A and Supplementary Figure S1), it is expected 
that differences in the reduction of steady-state levels of 
the OXPHOS components between the two siRNAs result 
from an unequal rate of gene inactivation. 
Inhibition of C7orf30 expression by 'siRNA 1' over 6 
days reduced the abundance of complexes I and IV 
subunits by 70 and 65%, respectively (Figure 4B). The 
steady-state levels of a component of complex III was 
also down-regulated, though to a lesser extent-by 30% 
after 6 days of siRNA treatment (Figure 4B). There was 
no marked reduction in the steady-state levels of complex </p>

<p>II, containing only nuclearly encoded subunits, suggesting 
that the C7orf30 depletion interferes only with mitochon-
drial gene expression. The observed decrease in respira-
tory chain components was accompanied by a reduced 
cellular OCR of &lt;50% (Figure 4C). Quantification of 
the steady-state levels of mitochondrial mRNAs and 
rRNAs in cells subjected to C7orf30 RNAi did not 
reveal any marked reductions (Figure 4D). These results 
indicate that C7orf30 plays an important role in mito-
chondrial energy production. Given its association with 
the mitoribosome, and lack of observed reduction in the 
steady-state levels of mitochondrial transcripts upon gene 
inactivation we hypothesized that this role is fulfilled via 
contributions to mitochondrial translation. </p>

<p>MRPS18B </p>

<p>MRPL3 </p>

<p>C7orf30 </p>

<p>TOP (10%) 
BOTTOM (30%) </p>

<p>MRPL12 </p>

<p>DAP3/MRPS29 </p>

<p>mt-LSU (39S) </p>

<p>mt-SSU (28S) </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 
protein level </p>

<p>[% of total signal] </p>

<p>C7orf30 </p>

<p>MRPL3 </p>

<p>MRPS18B </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C7orf30 </p>

<p>anti-FLAG </p>

<p>MRPL3 </p>

<p>MRPL12 </p>

<p>CO2 (Complex IV) </p>

<p>MRPS27.FLAG IP 
ICT.FLAG IP 
PDE12.FLAG IP </p>

<p>Input Eluate 
Input Eluate 
Eluate </p>

<p>MRPS18B </p>

<p>DAP3/MRPS29 </p>

<p>1 
5 
4 
3 
2 </p>

<p>mt-LSU (39S) </p>

<p>mt-SSU (28S) </p>

<p>Figure 3. Interaction of C7orf30 with the mitochondrial ribosome. (A) Endogenous C7orf30 co-sediments with the large subunit of the mitochon-
drial ribosome. Total lysate of HeLa cells was separated through a 10-30% (v:v) isokinetic sucrose gradient and fractionated. The fractions were 
analysed by western blotting with antibodies specific for C7orf30, components of mt-LSU (MRPL3 and MRPL12) and components of mt-SSU 
(DAP3/MRPS29 and MRPS18B). Western blot signal was quantified using <rs type="software">ImageQuant</rs> software and presented in the graph above. (B) IP of the 
endogenous C7orf30 with the mitochondrial ribosome. Cells expressing MRPS27.FLAG (a component of mt-SSU), ICT1.FLAG (a component of 
mt-LSU) or PDE12.FLAG (mitochondrial RNase that does not associate with the mitoribosome) were lysed and IP was performed using anti-FLAG 
antibodies. The lysates ('Input') and eluates were analysed by western blot with the antibodies as indicated in A. CO2-antibody against subunit 2 of 
mitochondrial complex IV. </p>



<p>C7orf30 gene silencing inhibits mitochondrial translation, 
alters the profile of mt-LSU and results is reduction of 
monosome formation </p>

<p>In order to establish whether OXPHOS defects observed 
upon inactivation of C7orf30 (Figure 4) were a result of 
impaired mitochondrial protein synthesis, we inhibited 
cytosolic translation and labelled de novo synthesized 
mitochondrially encoded subunits of the electron trans-
port chain with 
35 S-Met. The incorporation of radioactive 
35 S-Met into mitochondrial proteins was analysed 6 days 
after the HeLa cells were transfected with C7orf30 siRNA. 
Translation of all mitochondrially encoded respiratory </p>

<p>chain subunits was compromised upon C7orf30 gene 
silencing, with incorporation of 
35 S-Met reduced by 
&lt;60% (for the more potent C7orf30 siRNA oligo 1) as 
compared to controls transfected with an unrelated 
siRNA (Figure 5A). In order to investigate whether 
inactivation of C7orf30 has an effect on the integrity 
of the mitochondrial ribosome, we carried out gradi-
ent sedimentation analyses of lysates from HeLa cells 
transfected with C7orf30 siRNA for 6 days and control 
cells transfected with an unrelated siRNA (Figure 5B 
and Supplementary Figure S2). Analysis of the sedimen-
tation of mitoribosomal subunits upon silencing of 
C7orf30 revealed anomalous sedimentation of mt-LSU. </p>

<p>1 
Ctrl </p>

<p>siRNA 
C7orf30 </p>

<p>Complex I 
(NDUFB8) </p>

<p>Complex IV 
(CO2) </p>

<p>-actin </p>

<p>Complex III </p>

<p>Complex II </p>

<p>C7orf30 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>DAP3/MRPS29 </p>

<p>MRPL3 </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>1 
Ctrl </p>

<p>siRNA 
C7orf30 </p>

<p>12S </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>16S </p>

<p>ND1 </p>

<p>CO2 </p>

<p>28S </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>2-DG 
oligomycin 
FCCP 
rotenone </p>

<p>OCR (fmoles/min) </p>

<p>siRNA C7orf30 </p>

<p>Ctrl </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Complex I </p>

<p>(NDUFB8) </p>

<p>Complex IV </p>

<p>(CO2) </p>

<p>Complex III Complex II </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Relative protein abundance </p>

<p>Figure 4. Inactivation of C7orf30 perturbs OXPHOS function without affecting mitochondrial transcripts. (A) Steady-state level of the OXPHOS 
subunits in cells transfected with siRNA to C7orf30. Steady-state protein levels of the endogenous C7orf30 protein, subunits of respiratory chain 
complexes and components of the mitoribosome (DAP3/MRPS29 and MRPL3) were analysed by western blotting in control cells transected with an 
unrelated siRNA (Ctrl) or cells transfected with two siRNAs specific for C7orf30 for 6 days. b-actin was used as a loading control. (B) Quantification 
of steady-state levels of OXPHOS components in C7orf30-depleted cells. Western blot signals from the experiments as per (A) for 'siRNA 1' were 
quantified for C7orf30-depleted cells using <rs type="software">ImageQuant</rs> software. Relative abundance is presented as a percentage of the steady-state level for control 
cells transected with an unrelated siRNA. n = 3, **P &lt; 0.01, ***P &lt; 0.001; two-tailed unpaired Student's t-test error bars = 1 SD. (C) OCR in 
C7orf30-depleted cells. OCR measured in an extracellular flux Seahorse instrument in control cells transfected with an unrelated siRNA or cells 
treated with siRNA to C7orf30 for 6 days. The wells containing cells were sequentially injected with 20 mM 2-DG to inhibit glycolysis, 100 nM 
oligomycin to inhibit ATP-synthase, 1 mM FCCP to uncouple the respiratory chain and 200 nM rotenone to inhibit complex I. n = 6, error bars = 1 
SD. (D) Steady-state levels of mitochondrial transcripts upon inactivation of C7orf30. Total RNA from control cells (Ctrl) and cells transfected with 
two siRNAs specific for C7orf30 were analysed by northern blots using radioactive probes specific for the indicated mitochondrial transcripts. 
Nuclear-encoded 28S rRNA was used as a loading control. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 4103 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Coomassie 
gel stain </p>

<p>1 
Ctrl </p>

<p>siRNA 
C7orf30 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>siRNA 
C7orf30 </p>

<p>C7orf30 </p>

<p>BOTTOM (30%) </p>

<p>MRPL12 </p>

<p>MRPS18B </p>

<p>C7orf30 </p>

<p>MRPL12 </p>

<p>MRPS18B </p>

<p>MRPL3 </p>

<p>MRPL3 </p>

<p>protein level </p>

<p>[% of total signal] </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>siRNA C7orf30 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>C7orf30 </p>

<p>anti-FLAG </p>

<p>MRPL3 </p>

<p>MRPL12 </p>

<p>ICT.FLAG IP </p>

<p>Input </p>

<p>MRPS18B </p>

<p>DAP3/ 
MRPS29 </p>

<p>Eluate 
Input Eluate </p>

<p>siRNA 
C7orf30 + 
ICT.FLAG IP </p>

<p>1 
4 
3 
2 </p>

<p>mt-LSU 
(39S) </p>

<p>mt-SSU 
(28S) </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 
protein level </p>

<p>[% of total signal] </p>

<p>protein level </p>

<p>[% of total signal] </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>siRNA C7orf30 </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>siRNA C7orf30 </p>

<p>MRPL12 </p>

<p>MRPS18B </p>

<p>MRPL3 </p>

<p>MRPL12 </p>

<p>MRPS18B </p>

<p>MRPL3 </p>

<p>*** 
* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>siRNA C7orf30 </p>

<p>Ctrl </p>

<p>MRPL3 MRPL12 DAP3/ 
MRPS29 </p>

<p>MRPS18B 
Relative protein abundance </p>

<p>TOP (10%) </p>

<p>Figure 5. Mitochondrial translation and mitoribosome integrity upon inactivation of C7orf30. (A) Mitochondrial translation in cells treated with 
siRNA to C7orf30. Products of mitochondrial translation were labelled with 
35 S methionine in control cells transfected with an unrelated siRNA 
(Ctrl) or cells transfected for 6 days with two siRNAs specific for C7orf30. Mitochondrial proteins were separated by 4-12% gradient SDS-PAGE 
and visualized by autoradiography. To validate equal protein loading, a small section of the gel was stained with Coomassie dye. (B) The mito-
chondrial ribosome profile in C7orf30-depleted cells. Total cell lysates of control HeLa cells transfected with an unrelated siRNA or HeLa cells 
transfected with siRNA to C7orf30 were separated on a 10-30% (v:v) isokinetic sucrose gradient. Fractions obtained for control and RNAi-treated 
cells were analysed by western blotting with antibodies to C7orf30, mt-LSU (MRPL3, MRPL12) and mt-SSU (MRPS18B). (C-E) Quantification of 
the gradient distribution of mitoribosomal components upon C7orf30 silencing. Western blot signal for MRPL3 (C), MRPL12 (D) and MRPS18B 
(D) for control and C7orf30-depleted cells was quantified using <rs type="software">ImageQuant</rs> software. MRPL3 n = 3, MRPL12 n = 3, MRPS18B n = 4. All 
significant value changes are indicated as *P &lt; 0.05, ***P &lt; 0.001; two-tailed unpaired Student's t-test. Error bars = 1 SD. The remaining western 
blots used for quantification are shown in Supplementary Figure S2. (F) IP of the mitochondrial ribosome from C7orf30-depleted cells. Cells 
expressing ICT1.FLAG (a component of mt-LSU) transfected with an unrelated siRNA or siRNA to C7orf30 were lysed and IP was performed 
using anti-FLAG antibodies. The lysates ('Input') and eluates were analysed by western blotting with antibodies against the FLAG tag, C7orf30, 
components of mt-LSU (MRPL3 and MRPL12) and mt-SSU (DAP3/MRPS29 and MRPS18B). (G) The abundance of mitoribosomal components 
in IP fractions of C7orf30-depleted cells. Western blot signal from the experiments as per (F) were quantified for control and C7orf30-depleted cells 
using <rs type="software">ImageQuant</rs> software. Relative abundance is presented as a percentage of input, n = 2, Error bars = 1 SD. The remaining western blots used 
for quantification are shown in Supplementary Figure S3. </p>



<p>A significant proportion of the mt-LSU markers (MRPL3 
and MRPL12) relocated to less dense fractions as 
compared to control cells (Figure 5C and D, fraction 8). 
The profile of the mt-SSU marker MRPS18B was largely 
unchanged after C7orf30 depletion (Figure 5E). Of note, 
the steady-state levels of the component of mt-SSU and 
mt-LSU have not been altered upon silencing of C7orf30 
(Figure 4A). Next we examined whether the alterations in 
mt-LSU sucrose gradient profile observed in C7orf30-
depleted cells result in a concomitant reduction in the 
level of the intact monosome. We pulled-down mt-LSU 
and the entire monosome using a FLAG-tagged compo-
nent of the large subunit, ICT1.FLAG, from control cells 
and cells treated with siRNA to C7orf30 for 6 days, then 
analysed the eluates by western blotting (Figure 5F and 
Supplementary Figure S3). The components of mt-LSU 
were equally well pulled-down for control and C7orf30-
depleted cells (Figure 5F, lane 2 and Figure 5G). However, 
there was a 60% reduction in the levels of the 
mt-SSU proteins (DAP3/MRPS29 and MRPS18B) in 
the C7orf30-depleted cells (Figure 5F, lane 4 and 
Figure 5G), consistent with a decrease in monosome </p>

<p>formation, presumably due to alterations in mt-LSU in-
tegrity. These results, together with the observation that 
the steady-state levels of mitochondrial rRNAs were not 
changed (Figure 4D), suggest that the inhibition of mito-
chondrial translation upon inactivation of C7orf30 could 
be attributed mainly to instability and/or impaired 
assembly of the large mitoribosomal subunit, conse-
quently interfering with formation of the mitochondrial 
monosome. </p>

<p>Overexpression of C7orf30 mutant alters the 
profile of mt-LSU </p>

<p>In order to further investigate how C7orf30 contributes to 
regulation of the biogenesis of mt-LSU, we overexpressed 
mutants of the protein in human mitochondria. A FLAG-
and STREP2-tagged version of C7orf30 (C7orf30.FLAG. 
STREP2) was stably transfected into HEK293T cells. 
Similarly to the endogenous C7orf30, the recombinant 
protein was associated with mt-LSU as verified by 
sucrose gradient sedimentation of HEK293T cell ex-
tracts after induction of the transgene for 3 days with 
50 ng/ml of doxycycline (Figure 6). Overexpression of </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>CV0518 (2id1) 
EIQEISKLAIEALEDIKGKDIIELDTSKLTSLFQRMIVATGDSNRQVKALANSVQVK---LKEAGVDIVGSEGHESGEWVLVDAGDVVVHVMLPAVRDYYDIEALWG 
YbeB 
QGKALQDFVIDKIDDLKGQDIIALDVQGKSSITDCMIICTGTSSRHVMSIADHVVQE---SRAAGLLPLGVEGENSADWIVVDLGDVIVHVMQEESRRLYELEKLWS 
iojap 
ECLSFAVSLAKAASEIKATDIRVLCVRRLVYWTRFFIILTAFSNAQIDAISSKMRDI----GEKQFSKVASGDTKPNSWTLLDFGDVVVHIFLPQQRAFYNLEEFYG 
C7orf30 H.sapiens 
GPKFDIDMMVSLLRQENARDICVIQVPPEMRYTDYFVIVSGTSTRHLHAMAFYVVKMYKHLKCKRDPHVKIEGKDTDDWLCVDFGSMVIHLMLPETREIYELEKLWT 
C7orf30 G.gallus 
LPKFSIDFVVNLLRQENAKDICVIQVPPEIKYCHYFIVVSGSSTRHLHAMAQYMLKMYKHQKEESDPHTRIEGKETHDWLCIDFGSIVVHFMLPETRETYELEKLWT 
C7orf30 X.tropicalis 
LPSFDINTLVSLLRQENAKDLCVIRVPPQLKYTDYFVVVSGFSTRHVQAMAQYSVKVYKYLKREDEPHVQIEGEDTDDWMCIDFGNIVVHFMLPETREKYELEKLWT 
C7orf30 O.latipes 
SETFNLDVLVSLLRQENAVDLCVIKVPENIKYAEYFIVVSGISPRHLRAMALYAIKVYKFLRKDGDPNVKIEGKDAEDWMCIDFGKIVVHFMLPETREVYELEKLWI 
. 
: :. *: : . 
::: :. * :: ::: 
. .. .* :* *.:::*.: 
* *::* :: </p>

<p>1 
3 
2 </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>-C7orf30.FLAG.STREP2 </p>

<p>MRPS18B </p>

<p>MRPL3 </p>

<p>H185A </p>

<p>MRPS18B </p>

<p>MRPL3 </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>-C7orf30 </p>

<p>-C7orf30.FLAG.STREP2 </p>

<p>-C7orf30 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>WT 
H185A 
HEK293T </p>

<p>Coomassie 
gel stain </p>

<p>D178 
H185 </p>

<p>Figure 6. Effects of overexpression of C7orf30 mutants on mitochondrial translation and mitoribosome integrity. (A) Design of C7orf30 mutants. 
Protein sequence of C. violaceum CV0518, E. coli YbeB, Z. mays iojap and orthologues of C7orf30 were aligned using ClustalW2. Colons and dots 
denote chemical similarity between the sequences, whereas asterisks indicate identical residues. The secondary structure based on the resolved 
structure of CV0518 (pdb: 2id1) is indicated above the alignment [helix (cylinders), strand (arrow)]. Three b-sheets (numbered 1-3) and four 
a-helices of the NTase-type fold are presented in red and yellow, respectively. Two residues, D178 or H185 (numbering according to the human 
sequence) subjected to site directed mutagenesis are in bold. (B) Mitochondrial ribosome profile in cells overexpressing the H185A mutant of 
C7orf30. Cell lysates of HEK293T cells overexpressing wild-type C7orf30 or the H185A mutant for 3 days were separated on a 10-30% (v:v) 
isokinetic sucrose gradient. Gradient fractions were analysed by western blotting with antibodies to C7orf30, mt-LSU (MRPL3) and mt-SSU 
(MRPS18B). (C) Mitochondrial translation in cells overexpressing the H185A mutant of C7orf30. Products of mitochondrial translation were 
labelled with 
35 S methionine in control untransfected HEK293T cells, cells overexpressing wild-type C7orf30 (WT) or the H185A mutant for 3 
days. Mitochondrial proteins were separated by 4-12% gradient SDS-PAGE and visualized by autoradiography. To validate equal protein loading, a 
small section of the gel was stained with Coomassie dye. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 4105 </p>

<p>C7orf30.FLAG.STREP2 did not have any appreciable 
adverse effect on the mitoribosome profile (Figure 6). 
However, we reasoned that overexpressed mutants 
of C7orf30 might exhibit dominant-negative effects 
through, for example, outcompeting the endogenous 
protein for mitoribosome binding. We selected two 
residues conserved between C7orf30 orthologues, bacter-
ial DUF143-containing proteins and iojap: D178 and 
H185 (Figure 6A). These residues were replaced with 
alanines via site-directed mutagenesis and cDNAs 
encoding the D178A or H185A mutants with the 
FLAG.STREP2 tag were stably integrated into the gen-
ome of HEK293T cells. Overexpression of the H185A 
mutant, but not D178A (Supplementary Figure S4) for 3 
days with 50 ng/ml doxycycline resulted in a significant 
alteration to the profile of mt-LSU as assessed by 
sucrose gradient sedimentation and western blotting with 
specific antibodies. A significant proportion of the 
mt-LSU marker (MRPL3) migrated in less dense frac-
tions typical for low molecular weight complexes as 
compared with control cells expressing wild-type 
C7orf30 (Figure 6B, fractions 1-4). The sedimentation 
of the H185A mutant (Figure 6B, fractions 7 and 8) was 
different from wild-type C7orf30, suggesting an inter-
action with sub-ribosomal complex(es) rather than the 
fully assembled mt-LSU. The profile of the mt-SSU 
marker, MRPS18B, was essentially unchanged after 
overexpression of the H185A mutant. The changes in 
the mitoribosomal profile in cells overexpressing the 
H185A mutant were accompanied by reduced mitochon-
drial protein synthesis as measured by incorporation of 
radioactive 
35 S-Met into mtDNA-encoded proteins 
(Figure 6C). These results provide further evidence that 
C7orf30 is important for regulation of the stability and/or 
assembly of the large mitoribosomal subunit and suggest 
that b-sheet 3 of the conserved NTase-type fold is import-
ant for this process. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In all biological systems translation of the genetic infor-
mation into proteins is carried out by the ribosome. 
Complex regulatory pathways have evolved to modulate 
ribosomal function in response to various stimuli. Many 
protein factors regulate ribosome synthesis including 
those involved in rRNA processing and modification, 
trans-acting assembly factors, chaperones and a variety 
of stress response proteins. We propose that the novel 
human protein C7orf30 participates in the biogenesis of 
the mitochondrial ribosome, in particular the biosynthesis 
of the large 39S mitoribosomal subunit. </p>

<p>C7orf30 does not regulate mitochondrial 
translation at RNA level </p>

<p>In yeast mitochondria a group of regulatory proteins 
exists to optimize the translation of individual mRNAs. 
The regulatory role of these proteins can be exerted 
through regulation of the stability of specific transcripts 
or by binding to the 5 
0 -UTRs of mRNAs and assisting in 
translation initiation (21). Such translation regulatory </p>

<p>proteins have also been reported in mammalian 
mitochondria implying that, despite significant differences 
in mitochondrial mRNA architecture (for example: the 
length of UTRs or RNA polyadenylation), the require-
ment for precise regulation of the translation of individual 
transcripts is evolutionarily conserved. The TACO1 
protein (CCDC44) has been identified as a specific trans-
lational activator of CO1-lack of TACO1 results in sig-
nificantly reduced synthesis of the CO1 protein despite 
normal steady-state levels of the CO1 mRNA (5). 
Several human proteins of the pentatricopeptide (PPR) 
family have been proposed to play a regulatory role in 
mitochondrial translation. The PPR family of proteins is 
characterized by the presence of a tandemly repeated, 
35-amino acid motif. Most studies of plant PPR proteins 
thus far have indicated various roles in RNA turnover, 
processing or translational regulation in mitochondria or 
chloroplasts (22). Mutations in human leucine-rich 
PPR-motif containing protein, LRPPRC (or LRP130) 
cause the French Canadian variant of Leigh syndrome 
(LSFC) (23), with proposed functions in positive transla-
tional control of mitochondrially encoded subunits of 
COX (24,25). Other human mitochondrial PPR proteins 
involved in the regulation of specific events in RNA me-
tabolism or translational control include: (i) PTCD1, a 
negative regulator of translation acting by modulating 
the abundance of the leucine tRNAs (26), PTCD2, a regu-
lator of cytochrome B mRNA maturation (27) and 
PTCD3, which modulates mitochondrial protein synthesis 
via binding to 12S rRNA (28). 
Given the structural homology of C7orf30 to NTases, 
which are mostly nucleic acid modifying enzymes, one of 
our initial hypotheses for the function of the protein in 
mitochondria considered its involvement in translation 
regulation at the RNA level. This position was initially 
supported by the observation that C7orf30 shares 
sequence homology with the yeast mitochondrial ATP25 
protein (Figure 1), required for the processing and stabil-
ity of ATP9 mRNA (18). Zeng et al. showed that muta-
tions in ATP25 result in decreased levels of the ATP9 
mRNA and its translation product thereby precluding 
assembly of the functional F0 subunit of ATP synthase. 
However, the same study has shown that only the 
C-terminal fragment of Atp25p is sufficient to stabilize 
the ATP9 mRNA and restore synthesis of Atp9p (18). 
Our analysis revealed that the C-terminal section of 
Atp25p 
shares 
sequence 
homology 
with 
the 
metallo-beta-lactamase domain (Figure 1B), present in 
many RNA processing enzymes, such as mitochondrial 
RNAse Z (29). As an equivalent of the Atp25p 
C-terminal domain is absent from C7orf30, it is likely 
that the human protein is not involved in regulating 
RNA processing and/or stability. Consistent with this 
conclusion is the absence of key catalytic residues of the 
NTase fold (Figure 1) suggesting that C7orf30 is not an 
active nucleic acid modifying enzyme. Also, our results of 
downregulation and overexpression (Joanna Rorbach and 
Payam Gammage, unpublished work) of C7orf30 showed 
no appreciable changes in the steady-state levels of any of 
the mitochondrial RNAs analysed (Figure 4D). </p>



<p>C7orf30 as a mitoribosome assembly/stability factor </p>

<p>A complex, multi-step pathway precedes ribosome produc-
tion in all organisms studied thus far. In the yeast cyto-
plasm, approximately 200 proteins and 70 small nucleolar 
RNAs have been reported to participate in ribosome bio-
synthesis and at least half of these proteins are believed to 
function directly in the assembly and/or transport of 
pre-ribosomal complexes from the nucleolus to the cyto-
plasm (30). Trans-acting assembly factors are also involved 
in biosynthesis of the bacterial ribosome. However, owing 
to the lack of compartmentalization of ribosome synthesis 
steps fewer proteins are involved in this process. In 
contrast to the relatively well-studied ribosomal assembly 
pathway in bacteria and eukaryotic cytoplasm, assembly of 
the mammalian mitoribosome remains to be described. 
Only two proteins playing a role in the biogenesis of 
mammalian mt-SSU have been identified. A homologue 
of bacterial Era protein, ERAL1, a member of the 
conserved family of GTP-binding proteins with RNA-
binding activity, has been demonstrated to play a role in 
the formation mt-SSU (31,32). It has been suggested that 
ERAL1 functions as a mitochondrial RNA chaperone to 
protect 12S rRNA on mt-SSU during assembly (31). 
TFB1M (transcription factor B1, mitochondrial) is re-
sponsible for adenine dimethylation of 12S rRNA and 
its knock-out in mice causes impaired assembly of the 
mitochondrial ribosome (33). Trans-acting, non-ribosomal 
factors such as protein chaperones involved in the 
assembly of mt-SSU are yet to be found. 
The complement of proteins comprising mt-LSU has 
been described by Spremulli and co-workers a decade 
ago (34), however, there is very limited published data 
on protein factors involved in assembly of this subunit. 
Multiple GTPases participate in the assembly of LSU in 
bacteria and eukaryotes (30). The yeast Mtg1p protein, a 
homologue of bacterial YlqF GTPase (also known as 
RbgA) (35), has been suggested to function in the 
assembly of the ribosome in yeast mitochondria without 
a role in transcription or processing of mt-rRNAs (36). 
The evidence that a human orthologue of Mtg1p partici-
pates in an analogous process within mitochondria is cir-
cumstantial, though. Human Mtg1 is capable of partial 
rescue of respiratory deficiency in a yeast mtg1 mutant 
and it has been localized to mitochondria in human cells 
(36). Knock-out of NOA1 (c4orf14, mAtNOS1)-a 
member of the circularly permuted GTPase (cpGTPase) 
family-in mouse cells led to impaired protein synthesis 
without loss of mtDNA and/or transcription. It has been 
suggested NOA1 plays a role in the assembly of mt-LSU 
(37). hMTERF4, a member of the family of mitochondrial 
proteins involved in transcription regulation (38), forms a 
complex with a putative RNA m5C methyltransferase 
NSUN4. The hMTERF4-NSUN4 complex co-migrates 
with mt-LSU and participates in the assembly of the 
monosome (39). Lastly, another non-ribosomal protein 
involved mitoribosomal biogenesis is mitochondrial 
AAA (m-AAA) protease that processes MRPL32 at the 
late stages of the assembly (8). 
Our data indicate that C7orf30 is important for the 
assembly and/or stability of the mitochondrial ribosome, </p>

<p>in particular the large 39S subunit. Consistent with the 
role of the DUF143 domain in ribosome assembly and/ 
or stability is the phenotype of homozygous mutants of 
iojap in Zea mays; the plant homologue of C7orf30 
(Figure 1A and B). Maize iojap is localized to plastids, 
and mutations in the coding gene result in depletion of 
chloroplast ribosomes and defects in translation. It has 
been previously suggested that the iojap phenotype 
results from impaired plastid ribosome assembly (10,11). 
Our results clearly show that RNAi-mediated depletion of 
C7orf30 or overexpression of a mutant of the conserved 
H185 residue compromised the integrity of mt-LSU. Our 
data also suggest that C7orf30 participates in late stages of 
assembly as relatively high molecular weight assembles are 
still present after C7orf30 depletion. Consistent with this 
are the results of affinity purification of the large subunit 
using ICT1.FLAG. C7orf30 was clearly enriched with 
ICT1.FLAG, and recently published data confirmed that 
ICT1 is an important component of the complete mono-
some, not assembly intermediates. Also, the bacterial 
homologue of C7orf30, YbeB, purifies with the large ribo-
somal subunit (9), but not the 50S* particle (17), which 
constitutes a penultimate pre-ribosomal complex in the 
bacterial ribosome assembly pathway (40). Furthermore, 
in bacteria YbeB exists in an operon together with ORFs 
encoding proteins involved in late large subunit biogenesis 
(41). We could speculate that the DUF143 domain 
evolved to promote interactions between subunits of 
large complexes such as the ribosome or ATP synthase. 
The N-terminal fragment of Atp25p, the yeast homolog of 
C7orf30, contains the DUF143 domain. This N-terminal 
fragment plays a role in the oligomerization of Atp9p, a 
subunit of the F 0 portion of the yeast mitochondrial ATP 
synthase, into a correct size ring structure (18). An analo-
gous role could be played by C7orf30 in assembly of the 
mitoribosomal large subunit. 
In conclusion, C7orf30 is a novel human gene indispens-
able for mitochondrial translation, most probably via its 
contribution to the biogenesis of mt-LSU. The function of 
C7orf30 in mt-LSU is also supported by the study of 
Wanschers et al. (41). In this context C7orf30 could be 
prioritized for analysis as a candidate disease gene in 
patients with combined OXPHOS deficiencies. Further 
studies of this protein, for example by cross-link IP 
approach, should provide new insights into the largely 
unknown area of mitochondrial ribosome biogenesis 
pathway and could be helpful in identifying other 
protein factors involved in this process. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online: 
Supplementary Figures 1-4. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We are grateful to Robert Lightowlers and Zosia 
Chrzanowska-Lightowlers for providing the ICT1.FLAG 
and MRPS27.FLAG HEK293T cell lines. We would like 
to thank Prof. D. Kang for the mtSSB1 antibodies and </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 4107 </p>

<p>our colleagues from the Mitochondrial Biology Unit 
Mitochondrial Genetics group for help with the article. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Funding for open access charge: The Medical Research 
Council, UK. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>







<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 4109 </p>

</text></tei>