<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3646185" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives: Ascertain the extent of differences </p>

<p>between men and women in dispensed drugs since 
there is a lack of comprehensive overviews on sex 
differences in the use of prescription drugs. </p>

<p>Design: Cross-sectional population database analysis. 
Methods: Data on all dispensed drugs in 2010 to the </p>

<p>entire Swedish population (9.3 million inhabitants) 
were obtained from the Swedish Prescribed Drug 
Register. All pharmacological groups with ambulatory 
care prescribing accounting for &gt;75% of the total 
volume in Defined Daily Doses and a prevalence of 
&gt;1% were included in the analysis. Crude and age-
adjusted differences in prevalence and incidence were 
calculated as risk ratios (RRs) of women/men. </p>

<p>Results: In all, 2.8 million men (59%) and 3.6 </p>

<p>million women (76%) were dispensed at least one 
prescribed drug during 2010. Women were dispensed 
more drugs in all age groups except among children 
under the age of 10. The largest sex difference in 
prevalence in absolute numbers was found for 
antibiotics that were more common in women, 265.5 
patients (PAT)/1000 women and 191.3 PAT/1000 
men, respectively. This was followed by thyroid 
therapy (65.7 PAT/1000 women and 13.ARTICLE SUMMARY </p>

<p>Article focus </p>

<p>▪ To use drug dispensing data to analyse drug util-
isation in men and women in a whole country. 
▪ To identify areas of potential discrepancies in 
drugs dispensed to men and women. 
▪ To review the existing literature for explanations 
for differences in drug use between men and 
women. 
▪ To raise awareness about the differences in drug 
use between men and women which may not be 
rational. </p>

<p>Key messages </p>

<p>▪ Differences in men and women in the prevalence 
and incidence of dispensed drugs were found in 
Sweden overall, and in 48 of 50 pharmacological 
groups. 
▪ Many sex differences found in our study may be 
explained by sex differences in morbidity or biology. 
Other differences are hard to explain on medical 
grounds and may indicate unequal treatment. 
▪ There are few studies analysing the rationale of 
the observed sex differences. </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ A strength of this study is the complete coverage 
including all dispensed prescription drugs to the 
entire Swedish population regardless of patient 
co-payment. 
▪ Another strength is the data source using dis-
pensed drugs which is likely to provide a more 
accurate picture of actual drug consumption than 
data on prescriptions collected from medical 
records. 
▪ A limitation is that information on the diagnoses 
or conditions the drugs were prescribed for was 
not included. The study also lacked information 
on whether the patients actually used the dis-
pensed drugs or not, a problem shared with most 
clinical trials and studies on drug utilisation. </p>

<p>Loikas D, Wettermark B, von Euler M, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002378. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002378 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>the most important treatment options for most diseases 
and the majority of medical consultations result in a pre-
scription. 1 Furthermore, pharmaceuticals also constitute 
a significant proportion of healthcare spending, increas-
ing more rapidly than other healthcare components in 
many countries. 2 3 In Sweden, pharmaceuticals 
accounted for 12.6% of the total healthcare expenditure 
in 2010, 4 but the growth has been moderated after the 
implementation of major reforms. 5 
Rational drug use implies that 'patients receive medica-
tions appropriate to their clinical needs, in doses that 
meet their own individual requirements, for an adequate 
period of time, and at the lowest cost to them and the 
community'. 6 Individual requirements indicate that sever-
ity of disease, comorbidity, renal function and age should 
be considered in addition to sex and gender. While it is 
evident that biological differences, commonly referred to 
as 'sex differences', should be considered when prescrib-
ing medicines, it is unclear to what extent sociocultural dif-
ferences, commonly referred to as 'gender differences', 
should be considered by the prescribing physician. Sex dif-
ferences in drug use have been demonstrated in several 
therapeutic areas. 7-11 However, there is a lack of both com-
prehensive overviews on sex and gender differences of 
drug use in entire populations and especially studies ana-
lysing the rationale behind the observed differences. 
Variations in morbidity may explain some differences, 
whereas other differences may indicate inequities and 
underuse or overuse of certain drugs in men or women. 
WHO defines 'drug utilisation' as 'the marketing, dis-
tribution, prescription, and use of drugs in a society, 
with special emphasis on the medical, social, and eco-
nomic consequences'. 12 Drug utilisation data can be 
derived from different levels in the medication use 
process: sales data from the manufacturers to wholesa-
lers, the dispensing data at pharmacies or patient con-
sumption surveys. 13 14 The use of dispensed 
prescriptions as a measure of drug exposure has many 
advantages since it eliminates recall bias and improves 
the accuracy of the information on drug use. 13 15 In 
2005, a national registry on dispensed drugs to the 
entire Swedish population was established. 16 It contains 
complete data (&gt;99% coverage) with unique identifiers 
of all prescribed drugs dispensed to the entire Swedish 
population of 9.3 million inhabitants, and may offer a 
good opportunity to study sex differences in drug use. 
The aim of this study was to describe and analyse dif-
ferences in the prevalence and incidence between men 
and women of drugs dispensed to the Swedish popula-
tion. The findings may subsequently be used to plan 
future studies to address differences suggesting inequity 
in treatment approaches. </p>

<p>METHODS 
This was a cross-sectional study analysing sex differences 
in the prevalence and incidence of drugs dispensed in 
ambulatory care in Sweden in 2010, overall and within </p>

<p>different pharmacological groups. Data were collected 
from the Swedish Prescribed Drug Register. 16 
The period prevalence was defined as the proportion 
of the population in the country dispensed ≥1 prescrip-
tion in 2010 and measured by the number of patients 
exposed per 1000 inhabitants (PAT/TIN). Incidence was 
defined as the proportion of the population having at 
least one prescription dispensed in a pharmacy in 2010 
after a 1-year wash-out period with no drug dispensed 
and was measured by the number of patients per 1000 
person-years (PAT/1000 PYs). 
Pharmacological groups were selected by using the fol-
lowing procedure: 
1. All 89 Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) 
second level groups with drugs available on the 
Swedish market 17 18 were identified. 
2. In large ATC groups and ATC groups with drugs used 
for multiple heterogeneous indications, that is, 
cardiac therapy (C01), agents acting on the renin-
angiotensin system (C09), sex hormones (G03), uro-
logicals (G04), analgesics (N02), psycholeptics 
(N05), psychoanaleptics (N06), ophthalmologicals 
(S01), a subdivision was done to the ATC third or 
fourth level to attain a more clinically relevant 
description of the utilisation. 
3. ATC groups with less than 75% of the total sales 
volume in the country purchased on prescription 
were excluded since sex distribution was not possible 
to collect for those purchased over-the-counter or 
used in inpatient care. Volume was measured in the 
technical unit numbers of Defined Daily Doses 
(DDDs), except for eight pharmacological groups 
for which there were no DDDs assigned. 18 For these 
groups, packages were used as a volume measure. 
Calculations of the proportion of the total volume 
dispensed as prescriptions in ambulatory care were 
based on aggregated volume data from all Swedish 
pharmacies. 
4. For the identified ATC groups at various hierarchical 
levels, groups that were dispensed to less than 1% of 
the total Swedish population or to less than 0.4% of 
men or women, respectively, were excluded to avoid 
random variation due to small numbers. 
Crude and age-adjusted values were calculated. Age 
standardisation was performed by direct standardisation, 
where the Swedish population on 31 December 2009 
(4 649 014 men and 4 691 668 women 19 ) was used as the 
standard population. In the calculations, 5-year age 
groups were used. Differences between the sexes were 
calculated as a risk ratio (RR) of women/men with 95% 
CI. All analyses were performed in <rs id="software-1" type="software">Microsoft Excel</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">2007</rs> 
and <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.9.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, North Carolina, 
USA) using descriptive statistical methods. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
In 2010, the total volume of drugs dispensed in Sweden 
was 5.8 billion DDD, corresponding to 1715 DDD/1000 </p>



<p>Loikas D, Wettermark B, von Euler M, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002378. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002378 </p>

<p>Irrational differences in drug utilisation between men and women? </p>

<p>inhabitants daily. The total expenditures were 35.6 
billion Swedish Kronor (SEK; 100 SEK=8.96 GBP, 
September 2012). Drugs prescribed in ambulatory care, 
and thus included in the study, accounted for 88% of 
the total volume and 72% of the total expenditures on 
drugs in the country. 
In all, 2.8 million men (59%) and 3.6 million women 
(76%) were dispensed at least one prescribed drug 
during 2010. The older the patient, the higher the </p>

<p>likelihood was of being dispensed drugs. Women were in 
general dispensed more prescription drugs in all age 
groups except among children under the age of 10, 
even when hormonal contraceptives were excluded 
(table 1). 
Crude sex differences in prevalence were found in 
48 of the 50 pharmacological ATC groups included 
(figure 1, table 2). After age adjustment, sex differences 
remained in 48 ATC groups. Concerning drugs for 
glaucoma (S01E) and endocrine drugs (L02), the sex 
differences disappeared after age adjustment, while the 
opposite was seen for angiotensin receptor blockers 
(ARBs) (C09C+D) and calcium channel blockers (C08), 
which were more common in men after age adjustment. 
β blocking agents (C07) and cardiac glycosides (C01A) 
were more common in women before age adjustment, 
but were found to be more common in men after adjust-
ment. The large differences in drugs for treatment of 
bone diseases such as osteoporosis (M05), thyroid 
therapy (H03), mineral supplements (A12) and antide-
mentia drugs (N06D) diminished after age adjustment, 
even though they still were more common in women 
after adjustment (table 2). 
The pharmacological groups with the largest relative 
differences more commonly being dispensed to women 
were antimycotics for systemic use (RR 6.6), drugs for 
osteoporosis (RR 4.9) and thyroid therapy (RR 4.5), 
while a larger proportion of men were dispensed antig-
out preparations (RR 0.4), psychostimulants (0.6) and 
ACE-inhibitors (RR 0.7) (figure 2). 
The largest sex difference in absolute numbers was 
found for systemic antibacterials ( J01) that were more 
common in women, 265.5 PAT/1000 women and 191.3 
PAT/1000 men, respectively. This was followed by 
thyroid therapy (H03), 65.7 PAT/1000 women and 13.1 </p>

<p>Table 1 Proportions of the Swedish population dispensed 
at least one prescribed drug in 2010, by age and sex </p>

<p>Age 
group </p>

<p>Men 
(%) </p>

<p>Women 
(%) </p>

<p>Women, hormonal 
contraceptives (G03A) 
excluded (%) </p>

<p>0-4 
6 8 
6 4 
6 4 
5-9 
4 5 
4 3 
4 3 
10-14 
39 
45 
44 
15-19 
42 
77 
62 
20-24 
39 
77 
60 
25-29 
42 
74 
62 
30-34 
46 
73 
65 
35-39 
50 
73 
66 
40-44 
53 
73 
67 
45-49 
58 
74 
71 
50-54 
64 
78 
77 
55-59 
72 
82 
82 
60-64 
79 
85 
85 
65-69 
84 
88 
88 
70-74 
89 
92 
92 
75-79 
93 
94 
94 
80-84 
95 
96 
96 
85-89 
96 
96 
96 
90+ 
97 
99 
99 
Total 
59 
76 
71 </p>

<p>Figure 1 Flow chart showing the selection of pharmacological groups included in the specific analyses on sex and gender 
differences in different therapeutic areas. 1 Cardiac therapy (C01), agents acting on the renin-angiotensin system (C09), sex 
hormones (G03), urologicals (G04), analgesics (N02), psycholeptics (N05), psychoanaleptics (N06) and ophthalmologicals (S01). </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Volume was measured in Defined Daily Doses (DDDs), except for eight ATC groups without any assigned DDD values where 
packages were used instead. </p>

<p>Loikas D, Wettermark B, von Euler M, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002378. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002378 </p>



<p>Irrational differences in drug utilisation between men and women? </p>

<p>Table 2 Sex differences in prevalence of drug therapy in Sweden in 2010 by pharmacological group </p>

<p>ATC 
Pharmacological group </p>

<p>PAT/TIN 
RR (95% CI) </p>

<p>Age-adjusted 
RR (95% CI) 
Men 
Women Women/men 
Women/men </p>

<p>J02 
Antimycotics for systemic use 
2.75 18.90 6.87 (6.74 to 7.00) 
6.56 (6.44 to 6.68) 
M05 
Drugs for treatment of bone diseases 
3.19 19.28 6.04 (5.94 to 6.14) 
4.95 (4.87 to 5.03) 
H03 
Thyroid therapy 
13.12 65.67 5.00 (4.96 to 5.05) 
4.46 (4.42 to 4.50) 
N02C 
Antimigraine Preparations 
5.03 17.24 3.43 (3.38 to 3.48) 
3.44 (3.39 to 3.49) 
A12 
Mineral supplements 
16.19 57.29 3.54 (3.51 to 3.57) 
2.90 (2.88 to 2.92) 
A08 
Antiobesity preparations 
1.59 
4.13 2.60 (2.53 to 2.67) 
2.62 (2.55 to 2.69) 
J05 
Antivirals for systemic use 
7.85 14.79 1.88 (1.86 to 1.91) 
1.86 (1.84 to 1.89) 
P01 
Antiprotozoals 
11.00 20.55 1.87 (1.85 to 1.89) 
1.85 (1.83 to 1.87) 
N06A 
Antidepressants 
55.35 106.60 1.93 (1.92 to 1.93) 
1.79 (1.78 to 1.80) 
H01 
Pituitary and hypothalamic hormones and analogues 
2.46 
4.08 1.66 (1.62 to 1.70) 
1.66 (1.63 to 1.70) 
N05B 
Anxiolytics 
39.39 70.01 1.78 (1.77 to 1.79) 
1.60 (1.59 to 1.61) 
N05C 
Hypnotics and sedatives 
58.35 103.83 1.78 (1.77 to 1.79) 
1.56 (1.56 to 1.57) 
M03 
Muscle relaxants 
6.38 
9.98 1.56 (1.54 to 1.59) 
1.53 (1.51 to 1.56) 
B03 
Antianaemic preparations 
40.35 73.24 1.82 (1.81 to 1.83) 
1.48 (1.47 to 1.49) 
J01 
Antibacterials for systemic use 
191.26 265.58 1.39 (1.39 to 1.39) 
1.36 (1.36 to 1.36) 
L04 
Immunosuppressants 
7.32 10.05 1.37 (1.35 to 1.39) 
1.33 (1.31 to 1.35) 
G04BD Urinary antispasmodics 
6.12 
9.61 1.57 (1.55 to 1.60) 
1.33 (1.31 to 1.35) 
A02 
Drugs for acid related disorders 
70.08 101.87 1.45 (1.45 to 1.46) 
1.31 (1.31 to 1.32) 
H02 
Corticosteroids for systemic use 
37.17 51.98 1.40 (1.39 to 1.41) 
1.30 (1.30 to 1.31) 
S01B 
Anti-inflammatory agents 
12.72 18.95 1.49 (1.47 to 1.50) 
1.30 (1.29 to 1.31) 
A07 
Antidiarrhoeals, intestinal anti-inflammatory/ 
anti-infective agents </p>

<p>13.77 19.35 1.40 (1.39 to 1.42) 
1.29 (1.28 to 1.30) </p>

<p>N02A 
Opioids 
66.90 92.97 1.39 (1.38 to 1.40) 
1.27 (1.27 to 1.28) 
C03 
Diuretics 
59.48 92.83 1.56 (1.55 to 1.57) 
1.24 (1.24 to 1.25) 
S02 
Otologicals 
4.54 
5.71 1.26 (1.24 to 1.28) 
1.23 (1.21 to 1.25) 
R03 
Drugs for obstructive airway diseases 
71.79 88.80 1.24 (1.23 to 1.24) 
1.20 (1.20 to 1.21) 
S03 
Ophthalmological and otological preparations 
23.31 28.38 1.22 (1.21 to 1.23) 
1.18 (1.17 to 1.19) 
N03 
Antiepileptics 
18.22 22.08 1.21 (1.20 to 1.22) 
1.15 (1.14 to 1.16) 
N05A 
Antipsychotics 
13.59 16.51 1.21 (1.20 to 1.23) 
1.11 (1.09 to 1.12) 
N06D 
Antidementia drugs 
3.38 
5.41 1.60 (1.57 to 1.63) 
1.10 (1.07 to 1.12) 
N04 
Anti-Parkinson drugs 
6.83 
8.49 1.24 (1.22 to 1.26) 
1.06 (1.05 to 1.08) 
S01E 
Antiglaucoma preparations and miotics 
13.57 18.49 1.36 (1.35 to 1.38) 
1.02 (1.01 to 1.03) 
L02 
Endocrine therapy 
6.34 
7.60 1.20 (1.18 to 1.22) 
0.96 (0.95 to 0.97) 
C07 
β blocking agents 
97.82 107.57 1.10 (1.10 to 1.10) 
0.94 (0.93 to 0.94) 
C09C+D Angiotensin II antagonists and combinations 
45.16 46.56 1.03 (1.02 to 1.04) 
0.91 (0.91 to 0.92) 
C08 
Calcium channel blockers 
60.84 59.61 0.98 (0.97 to 0.98) 
0.84 (0.84 to 0.84) 
C01A 
Cardiac glycosides 
6.01 
6.83 1.14 (1.12 to 1.16) 
0.81 (0.79 to 0.82) 
C10 
Lipid modifying agents 
98.03 81.05 0.83 (0.82 to 0.83) 
0.74 (0.73 to 0.74) 
C01D 
Vasodilators used in cardiac diseases 
24.94 23.61 0.95 (0.94 to 0.95) 
0.73 (0.72 to 0.73) 
B01 
Antithrombotic agents 
109.81 97.68 0.89 (0.89 to 0.89) 
0.72 (0.72 to 0.73) 
A10 
Drugs used in diabetes 
45.27 34.48 0.76 (0.76 to 0.77) 
0.68 (0.68 to 0.69) 
C09A+B ACE-inhibitors and combinations 
78.14 60.90 0.78 (0.78 to 0.78) 
0.68 (0.67 to 0.68) 
N06B 
Psychostimulants 
6.94 
4.11 0.59 (0.58 to 0.60) 
0.62 (0.61 to 0.64) 
M04 
Antigout preparations 
12.24 
5.91 0.48 (0.48 to 0.49) 
0.38 (0.38 to 0.39) </p>

<p>Crude and age-adjusted relative differences for included ATC groups. The following pharmacological groups are not presented in the table 
due to sex-specific indications; G02 Other gynaecologicals (dispensed to 9.79 PAT/1000 women and 0.20 PAT/1000 men), G03A Hormonal 
contraceptives (dispensed to 132.05 PAT/1000 women and 0.08 PAT/1000 men), G03C Estrogens (dispensed to 69.62 PAT/1000 women 
and 0.08 PAT/1000 men), G03D Progestogens (dispensed to 15.90 PAT/1000 women and 0.03 PAT/1000 men), G03F Progestogens and 
Estrogens in combination (dispensed to 12.26 PAT/1000 women and 0.00 PAT/1000 men), G04C Drugs used in benign prostatic hypertrophy 
(dispensed to 0.25 PAT/1000 women and 26.23 PAT/1000 men) and G04BE Drugs used in erectile dysfunction (dispensed to 25.38 
PAT/1000 men and 0.07 PAT/1000 women). 
The relative differences were calculated with women as the numerator and men as the denominator. The table is sorted starting with the 
group with the largest age-adjusted sex difference. PAT/TIN=number of patients (men or women) per 1000 individuals. N=4 649 014 men and 
4 691 668 women. 
ATC, Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical; RR, risk ratio. </p>



<p>Loikas D, Wettermark B, von Euler M, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002378. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002378 </p>

<p>Irrational differences in drug utilisation between men and women? </p>

<p>PAT/1000 men, and antidepressants (N06A), 106.6 
PAT/1000 women and 55.4 PAT/1000 men. 
The incidence showed a similar pattern as the preva-
lence pattern (table 3). However, the sex differences 
were substantially higher for endocrine therapy (L02) 
and urinary antispasmodic agents (G04BD). Before age 
adjustment, 40 pharmacological groups were more fre-
quently dispensed to women and eight groups to men. 
After age adjustment, sex differences remained in 36 
and 11 ATC groups for women and men, respectively. In 
only one pharmacological group, drugs for treatment of 
bone diseases (M05), the sex difference diminished sub-
stantially after age adjustment. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
This study of all dispensed prescription drugs in Sweden 
shows substantial differences between men and women. 
It is obvious that some of these differences may be 
explained by variations in disease prevalence, severity of 
disease, pathophysiology, diagnostics and treatment 
response or by other biological differences such as those 
induced by pregnancy and/or lactation. However, it is 
also evident that other differences lack a rational 
medical explanation. 
Throughout their lifespan, women have more contact 
with the healthcare system, 20-22 which may provide them 
with an extra opportunity for detecting disease and 
receiving prescriptions. In the premenopausal years, a 
woman's need for contraceptives, pregnancy and child-
birth and, in the perimenopausal and postmenopausal 
period, screening programmes for breast and cervical 
cancers and gynaecological disorders require healthcare 
consultations. 22 Also, chronic disabling diseases asso-
ciated with a chronic need for medication, such as </p>

<p>musculoskeletal disorders, are more common in women 
than men. 20 From a gender perspective, studies have 
shown that men are less prone to seek preventive 
healthcare. 21 
Some differences between the sexes are expected. The 
higher proportion of women dispensed antimycotics 
could partly be explained by gynaecological infections 
such as vaginitis. Also, the 4.5 times higher proportion of 
dispensed thyroid therapy corresponds to a four times 
higher prevalence of impaired thyroid function in 
women. 23 The sex difference in the proportion of dis-
pensed drugs for migraine could be explained by a 2-3 
times higher prevalence of migraine among women. 24 
Men were dispensed more psychostimulants, correspond-
ing to a higher prevalence of attention deficit hyperactiv-
ity disorder 25 and autism. 26 
The largest sex difference in absolute numbers was 
observed for antibiotics, more commonly dispensed to 
women. A common reason for prescribing antibiotics in 
primary care is urinary tract infection, which is more 
prevalent in women. 27 An overdiagnosis of this condition 
in women has, however, been reported, which could 
potentially explain some of the higher number of women 
being dispensed these drugs. 28 Women were dispensed 
more antiobesity drugs than men in spite of obesity being 
more common in men. 29 30 Also, more women than men 
undergo obesity surgery. 31 There are reasons to believe 
that the sociocultural pressure to be slim is higher for 
women and studies have shown that women are more dis-
satisfied with their weight and their body than men. 32 33 
This could explain the prescription pattern. 
In the cardiovascular field, several differences in the 
dispensation of prescribed drugs were found. ACE inhi-
bitors, primarily used for the treatment of heart failure 
and hypertension, with the same prevalence in both </p>

<p>Figure 2 Pharmacological 
groups with the highest 
age-adjusted relative differences 
in prevalence in 2010. </p>

<p>Loikas D, Wettermark B, von Euler M, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002378. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002378 </p>



<p>Irrational differences in drug utilisation between men and women? </p>

<p>Table 3 Sex differences in incidence of drug therapy in Sweden in 2010 by pharmacological group </p>

<p>ATC 
Pharmacological group </p>

<p>PAT/1000 PYs RR (95% CI) </p>

<p>Age-adjusted RR 
(95% CI) 
Men 
Women Women/men 
Women/men </p>

<p>J02 
Antimycotics for systemic use 
2.28 13.23 5.80 (5.68 to 5.92) 
5.49 (5.38 to 5.60) 
H03 
Thyroid therapy 
1.55 
5.77 3.72 (3.62 to 3.81) 
3.49 (3.40 to 3.58) 
M05 
Drugs for treatment of bone diseases 
0.97 
3.98 4.11 (3.98 to 4.24) 
3.49 (3.38 to 3.60) 
N02C 
Antimigraine preparations 
1.89 
4.99 2.64 (2.57 to 2.70) 
2.67 (2.61 to 2.74) 
A08 
Antiobesity preparations 
0.55 
1.41 2.57 (2.45 to 2.69) 
2.60 (2.48 to 2.72) 
H01 
Pituitary and hypothalamic hormones and analogues 
0.99 
2.45 2.47 (2.38 to 2.55) 
2.48 (2.40 to 2.57) 
A12 
Mineral supplements 
5.82 14.85 2.55 (2.52 to 2.59) 
2.21 (2.18 to 2.24) 
J05 
Antivirals for systemic use 
4.60 
8.53 1.85 (1.82 to 1.89) 
1.80 (1.77 to 1.83) 
P01 
Antiprotozoals 
9.38 16.83 1.80 (1.77 to 1.82) 
1.79 (1.76 to 1.81) 
B03 
Antianaemic preparations 
12.28 23.72 1.93 (1.91 to 1.95) 
1.70 (1.68 to 1.72) 
N06A 
Antidepressants 
15.35 24.71 1.61 (1.59 to 1.62) 
1.52 (1.51 to 1.54) 
L02 
Endocrine therapy 
1.37 
2.43 1.78 (1.73 to 1.84) 
1.52 (1.48 to 1.56) 
N05B 
Anxiolytics 
17.90 28.41 1.59 (1.57 to 1.60) 
1.47 (1.46 to 1.48) 
M03 
Muscle relaxants 
4.50 
6.67 1.48 (1.46 to 1.51) 
1.46 (1.44 to 1.49) 
A07 
Antidiarrhoeals, intestinal anti-inflammatory/ 
antiinfective agents </p>

<p>6.68 10.27 1.39 (1.37 to 1.41) 
1.39 (1.37 to 1.41) </p>

<p>A02 
Drugs for acid related disorders 
25.47 37.35 1.47 (1.46 to 1.48) 
1.38 (1.37 to 1.39) 
N05C 
Hypnotics and sedatives 
18.90 26.94 1.43 (1.41 to 1.44) 
1.32 (1.31 to 1.34) 
S01B 
Anti-inflammatory agents 
9.27 13.71 1.48 (1.46 to 1.50) 
1.29 (1.27 to 1.31) 
H02 
Corticosteroids for systemic use 
21.36 28.28 1.32 (1.31 to 1.33) 
1.27 (1.26 to 1.28) 
N03 
Antiepileptics 
4.76 
6.29 1.32 (1.30 to 1.35) 
1.25 (1.22 to 1.27) 
L04 
Immunosuppressants 
1.43 
1.80 1.26 (1.22 to 1.30) 
1.23 (1.20 to 1.27) 
J01 
Antibacterials for systemic use 
126.14 153.73 1.22 (1.21 to 1.22) 
1.21 (1.20 to 1.21) 
R03 
Drugs for obstructive airway diseases 
27.19 32.11 1.18 (1.17 to 1.19) 
1.19 (1.18 to 1.20) 
N04 
Anti-Parkinson drugs 
1.67 
2.26 1.35 (1.31 to 1.39) 
1.19 (1.15 to 1.22) 
S02 
Otologicals 
3.39 
4.04 1.19 (1.17 to 1.22) 
1.17 (1.14 to 1.19) 
N02A 
Opioids 
39.55 48.30 1.22 (1.21 to 1.23) 
1.14 (1.14 to 1.15) 
C03 
Diuretics 
10.63 14.35 1.35 (1.33 to 1.37) 
1.14 (1.13 to 1.15) 
S03 
Ophthalmological and otological preparations 
18.43 21.41 1.16 (1.15 to 1.17) 
1.14 (1.13 to 1.15) 
G04BD Urinary antispasmodics 
2.63 
3.33 1.27 (1.24 to 1.30) 
1.10 (1.08 to 1.13) 
N05A 
Antipsychotics 
3.27 
4.03 1.23 (1.21 to 1.26) 
1.07 (1.05 to 1.10) 
N06D 
Antidementia drugs 
0.91 
1.38 1.52 (1.46 to 1.58) 
1.07 (1.03 to 1.11) 
B01 
Antithrombotic agents 
15.05 17.48 1.16. (1.15 to 1.7) 
1.05 (1.04 to 1.06) 
C07 
β blocking agents 
12.16 13.61 1.12 (1.11 to 1.13) 
1.02 (1.01 to 1.03) 
S01E 
Antiglaucoma preparations and miotics 
1.90 
2.15 1.13 (1.10 to 1.16) 
0.96 (0.93 to 0.98) 
C09C+D Angiotensin II antagonists and combinations 
6.18 
6.42 1.04 (1.02 to 1.05) 
0.95 (0.93 to 0.96) 
C08 
Calcium channel blockers 
10.35 10.72 1.04 (1.02 to 1.05) 
0.93 (0.92 to 0.94) 
C01A 
Cardiac glycosides 
1.09 
1.24 1.14 (1.10 to 1.18) 
0.86 (0.82 to 0.89) 
C09A+B ACE-inhibitors and combinations 
14.28 13.11 0.92 (0.91 to 0.93) 
0.83 (0.82 to 0.84) 
C10 
Lipid modifying agents 
13.01 11.28 0.87 (0.86 to 0.88) 
0.81 (0.80 to 0.82) 
A10 
Drugs used in diabetes 
4.83 
3.79 0.79 (0.77 to 0.80) 
0.73 (0.72 to 0.75) 
N06B 
Psychostimulants 
2.36 
1.57 0.67 (0.65 to 0.69) 
0.70 (0.68 to 0.72) 
C01D 
Vasodilators used in cardiac diseases 
8.34 
6.93 0.83 (0.82 to 0.84) 
0.69 (0.68 to 0.70) 
M04 
Antigout preparations 
2.71 
1.44 0.53 (0.51 to 0.55) 
0.44 (0.42 to 0.45) </p>

<p>Crude and age-adjusted relative differences for included ATC groups. The following pharmacological groups were excluded from the table due 
to sex-specific indications; G02 Other gynaecologicals (dispensed to 5.33 PAT/1000 PYs in women and 0.03 PAT/1000 PYs in men), G03A 
Hormonal contraceptives (dispensed to 42.09 PAT/1000 PYs in women and 0.04 PAT/1000 PYs in men), G03C Estrogens (dispensed to 
16.44 PAT/1000 PYs in women and 0.03 PAT/1000 PYs in men), G03D Progestogens (dispensed to 11.20 PAT/1000 PYs in women and 
0.01 PAT/1000 PYs in men), G03F Progestogens and estrogens in combination (dispensed to 2.56 PAT/1000 PYs in women and 0.00 PAT/ 
1000 PYs in men), G04C Drugs used in benign prostatic hypertrophy (dispensed to 0.20 PAT/1000 PYs in women and 7.34 PAT/1000 PYs in 
men) and G04BE Drugs used in erectile dysfunction (dispensed to 0.03 PAT/1000 PYs in women and 10.16 PAT/1000 PYs in men). 
The relative differences were calculated with women as the numerator and men as the denominator. The table is sorted starting with the 
group with the largest age-adjusted sex difference. PAT/1000 PYs=number of patients (men or women) per 1000 patient-years. N=4 649 014 
men and 4 691 668 women. 
ATC, Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical; RR, risk ratio. </p>



<p>Loikas D, Wettermark B, von Euler M, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002378. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002378 </p>

<p>Irrational differences in drug utilisation between men and women? </p>

<p>sexes, were more commonly dispensed to men. This may 
be due to the higher frequency of coughing as an 
adverse event in women. 34 However, the alternative treat-
ment ARB was dispensed to women and men to the 
same extent. Our findings may therefore indicate an 
underuse of renin-angiotensin agents in women. Lipid 
lowering drugs were also dispensed more frequently to 
men. The higher proportion in men may be explained 
by the higher prevalence of ischaemic heart disease. 
However, studies have shown that these drugs are under-
used for secondary prevention in women. 35-38 Reasons 
for this could be that women not only suffer more from 
myalgia as an adverse reaction 39 but also that women are 
older and have more comorbidity when suffering from 
cardiovascular disease, thus receiving less intensive sec-
ondary preventive medication. 
Men were dispensed more anticoagulants. The most 
common indication for anticoagulants is atrial fibrillation, 
a condition more commonly found in men but carrying a 
higher risk of fatal complications like embolic stroke for 
women. 40 Underuse of anticoagulants in women with atrial 
fibrillation has been shown in earlier studies. 37 38 41-44 Men 
were also dispensed antiarrhythmic drugs to a higher 
degree than women. This may be appropriate as women 
have a higher risk of the fatal arrhythmia 'torsade de 
pointe-ventricular tachycardia' induced by some antiar-
rhythmics like sotalol and quinidine. 45 
The main strength of this study is the complete cover-
age of all dispensed prescription drugs to the entire 
Swedish population. This provides a population-based 
overview of drug use difficult to acquire in many other 
health systems. 15 Although it is important to recognise 
that filling a prescription does not necessarily imply that 
the drugs are taken, we have no reason to believe that 
misclassification of drug use should be more prevalent 
in one sex. Furthermore, data on dispensed drugs are 
closer to the actual intake than data on prescribed 
drugs, and it is free from the recall bias common in 
patient reported data. 46 The most important limitation 
is the lack of information on patient characteristics and 
clinical data to assess the rationale behind the observed 
differences. Moreover, it is important to emphasise that 
gender differences may only be hypothesised from these 
data. 
In conclusion, in this large study we found substantial 
differences in drugs dispensed to men and women. In 
an attempt to explain these sex differences, we searched 
the literature. Some sex disparities could be explained 
by the differences in the prevalence of disease or fre-
quency of adverse reactions. Less medically justified 
explanations were also identified, such as overestimation 
of risk versus benefit in women compared with men. We 
also found suggestions that gender aspects such as soci-
etal acceptance of overweight in women compared with 
men may be involved. More research and a greater 
awareness of the influence of sex and gender in health 
and disease are needed to ensure rational drug use in 
both men and women. </p>

<p>Author affiliations 
1 Department of Medicine, Centre for Pharmacoepidemiology (CPE), Solna 
Clinical Epidemiology Unit, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden 
2 Department of Healthcare Development, Public Healthcare Services 
Committee, Stockholm County Council, Stockholm, Sweden 
3 Division of Clinical Pharmacology, Karolinska Institutet, Karolinska University 
Hospital, Stockholm, Sweden 
4 Department of Clinical Science and Education, Södersjukhuset, Karolinska 
Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden 
5 Department of Medicine, Cardiac Unit and Centre for Gender Medicine, 
Karolinska Institutet and Stockholm County Council, Stockholm, Sweden </p>

<p>Acknowledgements We thank Katarina Baatz, The Swedish National Board of 
Health and Welfare for extracting and processing data. We thank Dr Gunilla 
Ringbäck Weitoft, The Swedish National Board of Health and Welfare for 
valuable discussions about the study design. We thank Nina Johnston, Centre 
for Gender Medicine and Brian Godman, Clinical Pharmacology, both at 
Karolinska Institutet, for help in revising the manuscript. We also thank the 
expert groups of the regional Drug and Therapeutics Committee in Stockholm 
County Council for clinical comments on the study findings. </p>

<p>Contributors Everyone listed as an author fulfils all three of the ICMJE 
guidelines for authorship. KS-G conceived the idea of the study and was together 
with DL, BW and MvE responsible for the design of the study. DL and BW were 
responsible for undertaking data analysis and producing the tables and graphs. 
DL, BW, MvE, KS-G and UB provided input for the data analysis. The initial draft 
of the manuscript was prepared by DL and then circulated repeatedly among all 
authors for critical revision. DL was responsible for the acquisition of the data, 
and DL, BW, MvE, KSG and UB contributed to the interpretation of the results. 
All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding The study was funded by the Swedish Association of Local 
Authorities and Regions (SALAR) within the Sustainable Equality Project 
(HÅJ) no. SKL 08/2254, Stockholm County Council, and the Centre for 
Gender Medicine (Erica Lederhausen Foundation), Karolinska Institutet. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Ethics approval The study was approved by the regional Ethics Committee at 
Karolinska Institutet, Sweden. Ref. no. 2010/788-31/5. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement Proposals for data sharing should be sent to the 
corresponding author. </p>





<p>Irrational differences in drug utilisation between men and women? </p>





<p>Loikas D, Wettermark B, von Euler M, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002378. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002378 </p>

<p>Irrational differences in drug utilisation between men and women? </p>

</text></tei>