<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3259236" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: To describe the profile of chronic and aggressive periodontitis among Senegalese (West Africans) attending the In-
stitute of Dentistry of Dakar. 
Methods: A retrospective study was conducted with an inclusion period running from 2001 to 2008. The sample included 413 
chronic periodontitis and 151 aggressive periodontitis cases, among them 299 males and 265 females selected from 2,274 re-
cords. A Student's independent t-test or Pearson chi-squared test was used for data analysis. 
Results: The proportion of females with aggressive periodontitis was significantly higher than those with chronic periodon-
titis (64.9% vs. 40.4%, P &lt; 0.001). The aggressive periodontitis patients had an average age of 28.1 ± 8.9 years, and had lost less 
than 3 teeth. Less than a third of them reported using a toothbrush. Attachment loss was as high as 8 mm and severe lesions 
had spread to an average of 12 teeth with maximum alveolar bone loss up to 80%. The chronic periodontitis patients had an 
average age of 44.9 ± 14.0 and had lost on average less than 3 teeth. Nearly 75% used a toothbrush. Attachment loss was signifi-
cantly higher and lesions were more extensive in the aggressive periodontitis. Chronic periodontitis is associated with risk 
factors such as smoking or diabetes mellitus in 12.8% versus 0.7% in aggressive periodontitis (P &lt; 0.001). Differences between 
the two groups for most clinical and radiographic parameters were statistically significant. 
Conclusions: The profile of aggressive periodontist is characterized by more severe lesions than chronic periodontitis, where-
as tooth loss experience is similar in both forms. </p>

<p>Periodontitis is an inflammatory disease of the supporting 
tissues of the teeth caused by specific microorganisms or 
groups of specific microorganisms, resulting in progressive 
destruction of periodontal tissues [1]. The two main entities 
are chronic periodontitis (Fig. 1) and aggressive periodontitis 
(Figs. 2 and 3). In the last thirty years the role of plaque con-
trol has been reinforced as the only consistent determinant 
of periodontal disease. However, there have been several 
fundamental changes to the understanding of periodontal 
disease that have impacted this traditional concept. These </p>

<p>changes can be summarized as the differential susceptibili-
ties to the onset of disease, the prevalence of different severi-
ties of the disease, and the emerging links between periodon-
tal disease and other medical diseases or conditions [2]. The 
risk factors are environmental, behavioral, or biological fac-
tors that have been confirmed in longitudinal studies to have 
a punitive impact on the disease process [3-8]. Several factors 
are identified as increasing the risk of developing periodon-
tal disease [9,10]. The major risk factors for periodontitis are 
smoking, diabetes, and specific periodontal pathogens. Other 
potential factors, including the systemic diseases that impact 
host defenses, may play a role in the progression of the dis-</p>

<p>Received: Aug. 23, 2011; Accepted: Oct. 15, 2011 
*Correspondence: Henri Michel Benoist 
Service of Periodontology, Institute of Dentistry, Pharmacy and Odontostomatology, University of Dakar Faculty of Medicine, 
BP.16014 Dakar-Fann 12522 Dakar, Senegal 
E-mail: henri.benoist@ucad.edu.sn, Tel: +221-338249100, Fax: +221-338646573 </p>

<p>Journal of Periodontal 
&amp; Implant Science </p>

<p>JPIS </p>

<p>Profile of periodontitis in Senegalese 
280 </p>

<p>ease [11,12]. Although clinical attachment levels are consid-
ered the gold standard in periodontal diagnosis and outcome 
measurement, they do not reflect issues that may be impor-
tant to patients. Quality of life issues such as pain and dis-
comfort, changes in esthetics or function, costs of therapy, 
and tooth loss are seen by patients to be more relevant than 
attachment levels or probing depths [13,14]. Therefore, it 
must also be taken into consideration that functional impair-
ment and psychosocial impact of periodontal diseases may 
reduce quality of life. 
Chronic periodontitis is a common disease and can occur 
in most age groups but is more common in adults and elders 
worldwide [15]. Its prevalence and severity increase with age 
[3,4,16]. Aggressive periodontitis is characterized by severe 
and rapid loss of periodontal attachment and may be more 
common in children and adolescents. In young individuals, 
the onset of these diseases is often circumpubertal. The pri-</p>

<p>mary features of aggressive periodontitis include a history of 
rapid attachment and bone loss with familial aggregation [1]. 
Subsequent linkage studies of African-American and Cauca-
sian families suggest that there may be genetic and/or etio-
logic heterogeneity for aggressive periodontitis. Reported 
estimates of the prevalence of aggressive periodontitis forms 
in geographically diverse adolescent populations range from 
0.1 to 15% [15,17]. Most reports suggest a low prevalence (0.2%), 
which is markedly greater in African-American populations 
(2.5%) [15]. Albandar and Tinoco [18] reported on many stud-
ies on chronic/aggressive periodontitis in different ethnic 
and socio-economic level groups, concluding that a higher 
prevalence and severity could be found among individuals 
having a Hispanic-Black ethnic background or lower socio-
economic status. Also, as reported by Hirschfeld and Wasser-
man [19], McFall [20] and McLeod et al. [17], 78 to 84% of pa-
tients will experience at least minimal disease progression 
and tooth loss (average tooth loss, 0.5 to 1). No study has been 
conducted in Senegal to distinguish the clinical differences 
between the two main forms of periodontitis. 
The objective of this study was to describe the clinical pro-
file of aggressive and chronic periodontitis patients attend-
ing the Clinical Unit of Periodontics of the Institute of Den-
tistry at the University Cheikh Anta Diop of Dakar (University 
of Dakar, UCAD), Senegal (West Africa). </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>A retrospective study based on records of patients in the 
service of Periodontics, Institute of Dentistry at UCAD from 
2001 to 2008 was conducted. 
Included were the records of patients diagnosed with 
chronic periodontitis or aggressive periodontitis. The records 
of patients with gingival diseases and those insufficiently in-
formed or not incorporating panoramic radiograph were ex-</p>

<p>Figure 1. Buccal view of chronic periodontitis among male 45 years 
with no systemic disease or risk factors showing attachment loss and 
a significant amount of local factors. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Buccal view of an aggressive periodontitis case in a 21-year-
old female with no systemic disease or risk factors, showing discrete 
inflammation of the gingiva and very few local factors with the pres-
ence of diastema. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Panoramic radiograph of the same case in the previous 
figure (female, 21 years) showing alveolar bone levels, missing teeth, 
and the presence of alveolar bone defects. </p>

<p>Journal of Periodontal 
&amp; Implant Science </p>

<p>JPIS </p>

<p>Henri Michel Benoist et al. 281 </p>

<p>cluded. In all the cases, periodontitis diagnosis was based on 
the 1999 classification of the American Academy of Periodon-
tology (AAP) [1] and clinical and radiographic parameters. The 
localized or generalized type of periodontitis is not consid-
ered in this study but only the main form. 
The following chart entries were used in this study: gender, 
age, risk factors (like smoking or presence or absence of dia-
betes mellitus), use of a toothbrush for oral hygiene, attach-
ment loss, probing depth, number of teeth with a probing 
depth of 3 to 4 mm and ≥ 5 mm, number of teeth with an at-
tachment loss of 3 to 4 mm and ≥ 5 mm, tooth mobility, tooth 
loss, and maximum alveolar bone loss. William's periodontal 
probe (Michigan O probe, Hu-Friedy Mfg. Co., Chicago, IL, 
USA) was the main instrument used at the Clinic of Periodon-
tics of UCAD to assess attachment loss and probing depth. 
Assessment of the periodontal supporting tissues' status was 
based on clinical measurement of the distance from the ce-
mento-enamel junction or free gingival margin to the bot-
tom of pocket/sulcus at 4 or 6 sites per tooth (according to 
the charting sheet design at UCAD). Tooth mobility was as-
sessed using the Mühlemann index [21]. The alveolar bone 
loss was quantified on panoramic radiographs using the Bjorn 
technique for assessment of alveolar bone level as described 
by Albandar and Abbas [22]. In Bjorn's technique, the distance 
between the alveolar crest and the crown tip of the tooth was 
expressed as a proportion of the total length of the tooth. A 
lens displaying 2X magnification was fixed to a light screen 
and used to examine all radiographs. In this study, the alveo-
lar bone loss is expressed as a percentage by measurement 
on the proximal faces of the most affected tooth and corre-
sponded to the distance from the cemento-enamel junction 
to the bottom of the bone lesion reported to the distance be-
tween cemento-enamel junction and the apex. The measure-
ments were made by a single operator (S.Y.) using a transpar-
ent millimeter ruler and a dry-tipped compass. The reliability 
of measurements was tested on 50 images from randomly 
selected files, using the calculation of the intraclass correla-
tion coefficient. The threshold of 60% (95% confidence in-
terval) was considered sufficient in this study to conclude 
good agreement measures (usual threshold &gt; 70%) because 
of the non-uniform quality of the radiographs. The 3rd mo-
lars were excluded in this study. 
The records of 2,274 periodontal patients from the Service 
of Periodontics at UCAD were reviewed for this study. Only 
periodontitis patients were included (n = 637). Of these, 73 
(11.5%) were excluded because their charts were unusable or 
X-rays were absent or unreadable (conservation defects). Thus, 
564 records met the selection criteria including 413 chronic 
periodontitis (73.2%) and 151 aggressive periodontitis (26.8%). 
Statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">14.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). Descriptive statistics were calculated 
for all variables. Independent t-tests or chi-squared tests were 
performed to compare the clinical aggressive and chronic 
periodontitis group. The statistical significance was set at 
P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Comparative clinical parameters between chronic and ag-
gressive periodontitis are given in Table 1. The sample in-
cluded 299 males (53.0%) and 265 females (47.0%). The pro-
portion of females with aggressive periodontitis was signifi-
cantly higher than those with chronic periodontitis (64.9% 
vs. 40.4%, P &lt; 0.001). 
The age distribution showed two peaks around 25 and 45 
years (Fig. 4). The age ranged from 11 to 84 and the mean was 
40.4 ± 14.9 years. The median in the center of the box plot dia-
grams shows a symmetrical distribution of age in both 
groups (Fig. 4). The median was lower for patients with ag-
gressive periodontitis than those with chronic periodontitis. 
Higher variability of age among females with aggressive 
periodontitis and lower variability among males in the same 
group were observed. Several extreme values and outliers 
were noted in patients with aggressive periodontitis (Fig. 5). 
The toothbrush was used as a means of oral hygiene in 28.4% 
of patients with aggressive periodontitis and 71.6% of patients 
with chronic periodontitis (P = 0.030). 
Tooth loss experience was noted in 64.7% of the sample 
with a range of 1 to 22 teeth lost. The proportions were simi-
lar in both forms (65.4% vs. 62.9%, respectively, for chronic 
and aggressive forms) and no difference in mean tooth loss 
was seen (P = 0.658) (Table 1). Patients with chronic periodon-</p>

<p>Table 1. Comparison of clinical parameters from chronic periodon-
titis and aggressive periodontitis patients. </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Chronic 
periodontitis 
(n = 413) </p>

<p>Aggressive 
periodontitis 
(n = 151) </p>

<p>P-value 
(t-test) </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
44.9 ± 14.0 
28.1 ± 8.9 
&lt; 0.001 
Tooth loss 
2.9 ± 3.6 
2.5 ± 3.6 
0.283 
Tooth mobility 
1.8 ± 1.4 
2.6 ± 1.2 
&lt; 0.001 
Clinical attachment loss (mm) 
4.4 ± 1.4 
4.9 ± 1.4 
&lt; 0.001 
Probing depth (mm) 
6.4 ± 2.0 
8.2 ± 2.1 
&lt; 0.001 
Teeth with CAL 3-4 mm 
10.9 ± 6.5 
9.1 ± 5.4 
&lt; 0.001 
Teeth with PD 3-4 mm 
13.1 ± 6.1 
10.1 ± 5.2 
0.003 
Teeth with CAL ≥ 5 mm 
10.2 ± 6.9 
12.4 ± 6.2 
&lt; 0.001 
Teeth with PD ≥ 5 mm 
5.9 ± 5.7 
10.1 ± 6.2 
&lt; 0.001 
Alveolar bone loss (%) 
64.3 ± 26.9 
83.0 ± 20.5 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean ± SD. 
CAL: clinical attachment loss, PD: probing depth. </p>

<p>Journal of Periodontal 
&amp; Implant Science </p>

<p>JPIS </p>

<p>Profile of periodontitis in Senegalese </p>

<p>
titis were more likely to have risk factors (smoking, diabetes 
mellitus) than those who had aggressive periodontitis (12.8% 
vs. 0.7%, P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The objective of this study was to determine and compare 
the profile of the periodontitis patients consulted in the Peri-
odontic Clinic at the UCAD in Dakar. As with most retrospec-
tive studies, the one conducted here is subject to many bias-
es. The patients were probed by different undergraduate stu-
dents and their instructors, all of whom bring their own bi-
ases to the clinic. Diagnoses may not have been accurately 
recorded. Thus, the results of this study cannot be general-
ized beyond this particular group of patients. Smoking (con-
sumption, duration) and diabetes were insufficiently docu-
mented in the records of this study. The lack of a single med-
ical record for each patient and computerization may have 
led to inadvertent duplication. The non-homogeneous quali-
ty of radiographs did not allow for correctly measuring the 
real value of the bone loss and radiographic data should thus 
be analyzed as an approximation or a trend. The causes of 
tooth loss were not determined because they were insuffi-
ciently documented in the clinical records. The absence of 
necrotizing ulcerative periodontitis is not surprising, as it is 
shown in the literature that periodontal necrotizing disease 
reaches mainly young children in Africa and those living in 
disadvantaged areas in regard to necrotizing ulcerative gin-
givitis [23]. The clinical feature of necrotizing ulcerative peri-</p>

<p>odontitis occurs in most cases in young adults and the pro-
portion of males and females suffering from the disease is 
the same. However, it seems that white people are signifi-
cantly more likely to have this condition than blacks [24]. 
Necrotizing periodontal diseases occur with varying but low 
frequency (less than 1%) in North American and European 
children. It is seen with greater frequency (2 to 5%) in certain 
populations of children and adolescents from developing ar-
eas of Africa, Asia, and South America [25-27]. 
Although a predominance of males is noted, it is not repre-
sentative of the influence of gender on the occurrence of 
periodontitis but is probably due to hazard. Studies are con-
tradictory as to the predilection of periodontal disease ac-
cording to gender [28,29]. However, females are more likely 
to be affected than males [30]. Albandar and Rams [8] refute 
the association between gender and aggressive periodontitis. 
Those most exposed to aggressive periodontitis were young 
adults around 25 years, as described in past classifications of 
periodontitis [31,32]. However, in this study the presence of 
extreme values and outliers for age shows that it is possible 
that some are due to errors in data entry. The data otherwise 
would confirm that age is not a reliable criterion for the di-
agnosis of aggressive periodontitis that can evolve at a more 
advanced age. Eliminating the age criterion is probably one 
of the most important innovations of the AAP 1999 consen-</p>

<p>Figure 4. Histogram of age distribution among periodontitis pa-
tients showing two peaks. Std. Dev.: standard deviation. </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
0 
20 
40 
60 
80 
100 
Age (year) </p>

<p>Mean=40,41 
Std. Dev.=14,868 
N=564 </p>

<p>Figure 5. Box plot diagram of the age distribution by gender in pa-
tients with chronic periodontitis and aggressive periodontitis. A 
greater variability of age among females and several outliers were 
observed in the aggressive form. </p>

<p>Chronic periodontitis 
Aggressive periodontitis </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>Age (years) </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Male 
Female </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Diagnosis </p>

<p>Journal of Periodontal 
&amp; Implant Science </p>

<p>JPIS </p>

<p>Henri Michel Benoist et al. 283 </p>

<p>sus classification of periodontal diseases published by Armit-
age [1]. Initiation and progression of periodontal infections 
are clearly modified by local and systemic conditions called 
risk factors [9]. Significant risk factors known to be important 
today include diabetes mellitus (poor metabolic control) and 
cigarette smoking. These two risk factors markedly affect the 
initiation and progression of periodontitis, and attempts to 
manage these factors are now an important component of 
prevention and treatment of adult periodontitis. There are 
also background determinants associated with periodontal 
disease including gender, age and hereditary factors. Grossi 
et al. [3,4] showed the link between tobacco consumption 
(packages per year) and the severity of periodontitis. Also, Al-
pagot et al. [7] found a highly significant association between 
cigarette smoking, age, and attachment loss. A case-control 
study of 300 cases and 300 controls by Diallo et al. [23] in 
Senegal showed that the plaque index was significantly high-
er among smokers than nonsmokers with a very significant 
difference. 
In a longitudinal study of 20 years follow-up in a group of 
individuals aged 15 to 60 years reported by Hugoson and 
Laurell [16], it was noted that chronic periodontitis affects 
people of all ages. Also, the prevalence and extent of peri-
odontal destruction increases with age and inadequate oral 
hygiene. According to Albandar and Rams [8], the quality of 
oral hygiene and the presence of local factors such as calcu-
lus are not valid diagnostic criteria for aggressive periodonti-
tis. The severity of aggressive periodontitis seems to be more 
related to the virulence of bacteria such as Aggregatibacter ac-
tinomycetemcomitans, while systemic or genetic factors are 
associated with chronic forms. The presence of a history of 
periodontal disease in families may be a predisposing factor 
for aggressive periodontitis. According to Fourel [33], one of 
the constant parameters in early-onset-periodontitis cur-
rently classified as aggressive periodontitis is the existence of 
a familial factor. This was difficult to identify solely on the 
basis of this study because the characteristics of the siblings 
of the patients were not recorded. 
Goodson et al. [34] have presented evidence indicating that 
periodontal disease has dynamic states of exacerbation and 
remission and can be described in terms of patterns of pro-
gression and regression of the disease. Periodontitis can be 
distinguished by the rate of progression in different forms of 
the disease. In most patients, mean annual bone loss is less 
than 1 mm, while more susceptible people demonstrate rap-
id attachment loss and bone destruction [17]. Longitudinal 
studies on the progression of periodontitis indicate that the 
rate of periodontal tissue destruction is low and that advanced 
forms of the disease occur in comparatively few individuals 
and few tooth sites [16,35]. The periodontal lesions affect a </p>

<p>large number of sites and took generalized and severe forms 
among subjects of both groups in our study. However, sig-
nificantly greater amounts were found in aggressive peri-
odontitis. This finding is in concordance with the current 
understanding of the progression of periodontal attachment 
loss. 
There was no significant difference in tooth loss between 
aggressive periodontitis and chronic periodontitis in this 
study. Matthews et al. [14] showed in a study in Canada 
among 335 periodontitis patients that 20.6% had lost teeth. 
Periodontal disease accounted for 61.8% of the teeth lost, 
caries 24.8%, and all other causes accounted for 13.2%. Mat-
thews et al. [14] reported that patients with the aggressive 
form of periodontitis likely accounted for the majority of the 
tooth loss in their study. Albandar et al. [36] in a multiracial 
controlled study over 6 years showed that 46 to 50% of indi-
viduals with aggressive periodontitis had lost at least one 
tooth. According to Machtei et al. [37], a possible mechanism 
that might explain this greater tooth mortality in these sub-
jects is the likelihood that the dentist treating subjects with 
complex systemic conditions might prefer extraction over an 
elaborate treatment plan that might have preserved these 
teeth. Our findings show a high tooth loss experience among 
Senegalese, which may be due to poor economic status mak-
ing full access to dental care and treatment difficult. They 
otherwise show the importance of improvements that should 
be made to the processing of medical records such as com-
puterization in university dental institutes in developing 
countries like Senegal. 
Clinical characteristics in chronic and aggressive periodon-
titis are markedly extensive and severe. The profile of aggres-
sive periodontitis is characterized by more severe lesions 
than chronic periodontitis, whereas tooth loss experience is 
similar in both forms. Particular emphasis should be placed 
on the prevention and identification of patients at risk. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was 
reported. </p>



<p>Journal of Periodontal 
&amp; Implant Science </p>

<p>JPIS </p>

<p>Profile of periodontitis in Senegalese 
284 </p>



</text></tei>