<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3722356" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Psychopathy is a personality disorder associated with a profound lack of empathy. Neuroscientists have associated empathy and 
its interindividual variation with how strongly participants activate brain regions involved in their own actions, emotions and 
sensations while viewing those of others. Here we compared brain activity of 18 psychopathic offenders with 26 control subjects 
while viewing video clips of emotional hand interactions and while experiencing similar interactions. Brain regions involved in 
experiencing these interactions were not spontaneously activated as strongly in the patient group while viewing the video clips. 
However, this group difference was markedly reduced when we specifically instructed participants to feel with the actors in the 
videos. Our results suggest that psychopathy is not a simple incapacity for vicarious activations but rather reduced spontaneous 
vicarious activations co-existing with relatively normal deliberate counterparts. </p>

<p>Psychopathy is a personality disorder associated with a profound 
lack of empathy (Hare, 1991) and elevated reactive and instru-
mental aggression (Williamson et al., 1987; Serin, 1991; Cornell 
et al., 1996; Patrick and Zempolich, 1998; Blair, 2007). Dominant 
models of psychopathy focus on two processes. Some posit 
that deficits in instrumental learning are central to psychopathy, 
preventing individuals with psychopathy from associating their </p>

<p>antisocial behaviour with the negative affect that should be 
triggered by the distress of their victims (Blair, 2007). Others 
posit that deficits in attention might be central, with individuals 
with psychopathy having relatively preserved deliberate 'top-
down' attention, but abnormal automatic, 'bottom-up' attention 
(Moul et al., 2012). This imbalance would prevent subjects from 
adequately processing certain stimuli (e.g. distress cues) that are 
peripheral to their current goals (e.g. obtaining resources) 
(Patterson and Newman, 1993). </p>

<p>doi:10.1093/brain/awt190 </p>

<p>Brain 2013: 136; 2550-2562 | 2550 </p>

<p>Received December 19, 2012. Revised March 25, 2013. Accepted May 10, 2013 </p>

<p>ß The Author (2013). Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Guarantors of Brain. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), which permits 
non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>Here, we advocate considering a third, to date less explored 
process. Because vicariously experiencing (i.e. empathizing with) 
the negative emotional reactions of victims may normally inhibit 
aggression (Miller and Eisenberg, 1988), the increased instrumen-
tal aggression in psychopathy might be related to their reduced 
vicarious experience of the emotions of others (de Vignemont and 
Singer, 2006; Decety and Moriguchi, 2007). 
Functional MRI has shown that witnessing the emotions of 
others triggers neural activations in brain regions (insula and cin-
gulate cortex) normally associated with feeling similar emotions 
oneself (Bastiaansen et al., 2009; Lamm et al., 2011), and wit-
nessing what others do and sense recruits one's own motor and 
somatosensory cortices (Pineda, 2008; Keysers and Gazzola, 2009; 
Caspers et al., 2010; Keysers et al., 2010). The strength of these 
so called vicarious neural activations is predicted by interindividual 
differences in trait-empathy (Singer et al., 2004; Gazzola et al., 
2006; Jabbi et al., 2007) and they are therefore thought to rep-
resent a neural marker for empathy (Singer et al., 2004; Iacoboni, 
2006; Pineda, 2008; Bastiaansen et al., 2009; Keysers and 
Gazzola, 2009). 
These neural markers for empathy have been investigated in 
several psychiatric disorders, autism in particular (Dapretto et al., 
2006; Decety and Moriguchi, 2007; Dinstein et al., 2008; Minio-
Paluello et al., 2009), but surprisingly, not directly in psychopathy. 
However, a number of studies provide indirect evidence that 
warrants investigating vicarious activations directly in psychopathy. 
These studies show that psychopathic individuals display reduced 
physiological (Aniskiewicz, 1979; Blair et al., 1997; Perkins et al., 
2010), blood oxygen level-dependent (BOLD) signal (Mü ller et al., 
2003; but see Harenski et al., 2010) and electroencephalography 
(Cheng et al., 2012) responses to social emotional stimuli; recog-
nize emotions less accurately from voices or faces (Blair et al., 
2002, 2004; Kosson et al., 2002; Hastings et al., 2008); are less 
likely to attribute guilt to the protagonist in stories (Blair et al., 
1995), and have a weaker BOLD response in their premotor and 
primary somatosensory cortices while they observe faces in a 
gender discrimination task (Deeley et al., 2006; but see Dolan 
and Fullam, 2006). Reduced activations in insular, cingulate and 
secondary somatosensory cortices were also found during fear 
conditioning (Birbaumer et al., 2005), and in the cingulate 
cortex and inferior frontal gyrus while memorizing negative 
words (Kiehl et al., 2001), further pointing to functional deficits 
in brain regions that are known to be involved in vicarious re-
sponses. In addition, grey matter has also been found to be 
reduced in regions associated with vicarious responses (de 
Oliveira-Souza et al., 2008; but see Mü ller et al., 2008; 
Tiihonen et al., 2008; Yang et al., 2009; Schiffer et al., 2011). 
However, as these studies did not directly investigate whether 
regions involved in feeling one's own emotions are recruited ab-
normally in psychopathic individuals while viewing the emotions of 
others, it is impossible to conclude from this body of research that 
vicarious activations are reduced in individuals with psychopathy. 
To directly test this question, we developed short video clips 
of two hands interacting with each other in a loving, painful, 
neutral or rejecting way (Fig. 1A). Emotional interactions of 
hands involve goal-directed actions, sensations and emotions, 
and can thereby induce vicarious activations in motor, </p>

<p>somatosensory and emotional systems at once (Bastiaansen 
et al., 2009; Keysers and Gazzola, 2009). Different emotions 
were tested because psychopathic individuals may not be equally 
impaired at perceiving all types of emotions (Blair et al., 2002; 
Kosson et al., 2002; Blair et al., 2004; Marsh et al., 2008). Our 
main hypothesis was that the psychopathic group would show less 
vicarious activity than controls for at least one stimulus condition. 
Because previous studies have shown that performance and brain 
activity in tasks explicitly requiring social cognition are relatively 
preserved in psychopathy (Blair et al., 1996; Richell et al., 2003; 
Dolan and Fullam, 2004; Sommer et al., 2010), whereas abnorm-
alities in automatically orienting to salient information might gen-
erate the largest group differences in the absence of instruction to 
attend to specific, emotionally relevant aspects of the stimuli 
(Patterson and Newman, 1993; Newman et al., 2010; Moul 
et al., 2012), we further ventured to hypothesize that explicitly 
encouraging psychopathic individuals to empathize with the actors 
on the screen might reduce group differences in vicarious 
activations. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Participants </p>

<p>Twenty male offenders diagnosed with psychopathy (Psychopathy 
Checklist-Revised 5 26) (Hare et al., 2001; Hare, 2003) from Dutch 
Forensic Psychiatric Clinics, and 26 control subjects (matched at 
group-level for age, gender, IQ, handedness), without history of 
neuropsychiatric disorders, participated in the study. Subjects 
(age 18-60 years) had no previous diagnoses of schizophrenia, other 
psychotic disorders or autistic spectrum disorders. It was stressed that 
participation would not influence treatment. Two patients were 
excluded from analyses, one for technical difficulties and one for 
drug abuse on the day of scanning. The Research and Ethics 
Committee of the University Medical Centre Groningen approved 
the study. All participants signed an informed consent and received 
E7.50/h for participation. </p>

<p>General assessment </p>

<p>All subjects completed questionnaires about health, age, handedness, 
education and functional MRI suitability. IQ was measured with the 
Raven's Standard Progressive Matrices (RAVEN, Raven et al., 2003), 
and the abbreviated Groninger Intelligentie Test (GIT-2, Luteijn and 
Barelds, 2004). All subjects completed the Psychopathic Personality 
Inventory (Lilienfeld and Andrews, 1996), a 187-item self-report meas-
ure for criminal and non-criminal populations, the Autism Diagnostic 
Observation Schedule (ADOS, Lord et al., 1999) and a list of their 
medication, which was checked against their official record for the 
offender group and reviewed for psychoactive properties by J.d.B. 
(psychiatrist). </p>

<p>Experimental paradigm </p>

<p>Subjects performed three functional MRI experiments. </p>

<p>Observation </p>

<p>Subjects watched videos (2, 3 or 4 s) of hand interactions (Fig. 1A) 
during which an approaching hand entered the screen to interact </p>

<p>Vicarious representations in psychopathy </p>

<p>Brain 2013: 136; 2550-2562 | 2551 </p>

<p>with an already present receiving hand. The conditions were love 
(hands caressing), pain (one hand hitting the other), social exclusion 
(one hand pushing away the other friendly hand), and neutral videos 
(approaching hand touching the other and getting a non-emotional 
response). A duplicate of every video was left-right mirrored (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Adobe</rs> 
<rs id="software-4" type="software">Premiere</rs>) to ensure that hands entered equally often from both sides. 
Subjects were instructed to watch the videos as if they were watching 
one of their favourite videos. They were told that a question would be 
asked later and that they could answer it if they had watched (not 
memorized) the videos carefully. Two event-related runs ($8 min) con-
sisted of 36 videos (nine instances of each condition), separated by a </p>

<p>fixation cross for 8-12 s (Fig. 1C). Subjects' left eye-gaze was recorded 
by an infrared camera (SMI, iView; 50 Hz). </p>

<p>Empathy </p>

<p>Due to time constrains, only the love and pain conditions were pre-
sented in a block design (three videos from the same condition per 
block; 12 love and 12 pain blocks; $9 min total; Fig. 1C). Subjects 
were instructed to feel with the receiving (50%) or the approaching 
(50%) hand, indicated by a 1 s green cross on the left or right side of 
the screen. During the videos, a left or right red arrow at the bottom 
served as a reminder. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Love 
Neutral </p>

<p>Exclusion 
Pain </p>

<p>1. Observation 
2. Empathy 
3. Experience </p>

<p>8-12s </p>

<p>2-4s </p>

<p>1s </p>

<p>Block of 
3 movie 
clips </p>

<p>4-8s </p>

<p>3s </p>

<p>7s no response </p>

<p>Neutral 
Love 
Pain 
Exclusion </p>

<p>8-12s </p>

<p>8-12s </p>

<p>2-4s </p>

<p>2-4s </p>

<p>2-4s </p>

<p>Figure 1 Experimental paradigm. (A) Three still frames from example videos of each condition. Each video included a receiving (1) and an </p>

<p>approaching (2) hand. (B) Photo of hand interactions during the experience. (C) Design of the three experiments (always performed in this 
order). </p>



<p>H. Meffert et al. </p>

<p>Experience </p>

<p>Subjects participated in interactions similar to the ones presented 
during Observation. Subjects initiated the interaction after the appear-
ance of a green cross (Fig. 1C). The author (H.M.) responded (as 
instructed by a head-phone) by caressing, hitting, shaking or pushing 
away the subjects' hand. Subjects then rated the interaction with the 
unused hand operating a two-button response box on an 11-point 
scale (Fig. 1B). The 48 interactions (12 repetitions Â four conditions) 
were split in two runs. Subjects used the left hand in one, the right 
in the other run (order counterbalanced across subjects). Before 
the Experience run, every interaction was practiced until smoothly 
executed. 
After the functional MRI experiments, subjects rated all videos by 
means of an in-house questionnaire (Supplementary material). </p>

<p>Functional magnetic resonance imaging 
acquisition and analyses </p>

<p>Whole cerebrum activity was measured using a Philips Intera 3 T 
Quaser, eight-channel head coil, 32 axial gradient-echo slices, 3 mm 
thickness, no gap, single shot echo planar imaging, echo time: 30 ms, 
repetition time: 1.5 s. Slices were aligned to the anterior commissure-
posterior commissure line. The first five scans were discarded (T 1 equi-
libration). A T 1 -weighted image was also acquired (repetition time: 
7.55 ms, echo time: 3.5 ms, flip angle, field of view: 224; 160; 256, 
matrix 256 Â 229, voxel size: 1 Â 1 Â 1 mm). The total acquisition 
lasted $47 min. 
Images were analysed with <rs id="software-5" type="software">SPM5</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="url">http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm/software/spm5</rs>). For each subject, echo planar images were 
aligned to each other; the T 1 co-registered to the mean echo planar 
image and normalization parameters (obtained from T 1 segmentation) 
applied to all echo planar images (3 Â 3 Â 3 mm resolution), followed 
by smoothing (9 mm Gaussian kernel). Echo planar images were high-
pass filtered at 300 s. A separate general linear model was used for 
each experiment. 
At the subject level, observation was modelled with separate pre-
dictors for love, pain, exclusion, and neutral videos as boxcar functions 
convolved with the haemodynamic response function. The same was 
done for experience, with the addition of a fifth predictor modelling 
the rating epochs. For empathy, four separate regressors were used for 
empathizing with the receiving and approaching hand in the love and 
pain conditions. 
Summary volumes per condition, subject and experiment were then 
brought to the population analysis level to assess whether the groups 
differed for at least one condition (Pain, Love, Neutral, Exclusion for 
Experience and Observation; Pain-Receive, Pain-Approach, Love-
Receive, Love-Approach for Empathy). This was done in an ANOVA 
including two groups and four conditions, using the F contrast [1 0 0 0 
À1 0 0 0; 0 1 0 0 0 À 1 0 0; 0 0 1 0 0 0 À1 0; 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 À1] 
(first four columns represent conditions of the control group, last four 
those of the psychopathy group). We then explored the interaction 
Group Â Condition (F-contrast: [1 À 1 0 0 À 1 1 0 0; 0 1 À1 0 0 À1 
1 0; 0 0 1 À1 0 0 À 1 1]). Given that this interaction was not sig-
nificant in observation and empathy, we summed the four conditions 
to explore the main effect of group (F: [1 1 1 1 À1 À1 À1 À1]). We 
then performed T-tests to determine which group had stronger activa-
tions (T: [ À 1 À1 À1 À 1 1 1 1 1] and the reverse contrast). ANOVAs 
in SPM use a general linear model approach, which pools the error 
variance, and are valid for inferences across groups with different n. 
To assess whether the instructions to empathize significantly 
changed the group differences, we performed an interaction analysis </p>

<p>between Group (psychopathic versus control participants) and 
Experiment (observation and empathy). Only pain and love were 
tested in both experiments. Given that we found no interactions 
between Group and Condition during observation or empathy, we 
averaged parameter estimates for pain and love videos for observation 
and Pain-Receive, Pain-Approach, Love-Receive and Love-Approach 
videos for empathy. This resulted in one summary parameter estimate 
y per subject i for observation (y i,obs ) and one for ympathy (y i,emp ). 
We then performed a full-factorial repeated-measures ANOVA 
with factors Group (patient, control) and Experiment (observation, 
empathy) on Y. </p>

<p>Reporting of effects </p>

<p>All analyses were reported using a false-discovery correction at 
q fdr 5 0.05 to control the overall false positive rate. A minimum 
voxel-wise threshold was additionally imposed at P 5 0.001 (uncor-
rected). This means that the more stringent the T/F corresponding 
to q fdr 5 0.05 or P 5 0.001 was used. Only clusters of 410 voxels 
are reported. For null-findings, we indicate q fdr 4 0.05, and then the 
smallest T/F value at which there was no effect. All analyses were 
confined to the grey matter, as defined by averaging the normalized 
grey matter segment of all participants and thresholding at 40.3. The 
q fdr 5 0.05 threshold was determined for a search volume including 
the entire grey matter irrespective of whether results are restricted 
to the region of interest or not, i.e. we did not use a small volume 
correction for the region of interest. There is only one exception, 
the interaction analysis between Group Â Experiment, where a small 
volume correction was used to maximize sensitivity. </p>

<p>Region of interest </p>

<p>To explore if group differences were located in regions known to 
exhibit vicarious activations, we additionally inclusively masked the 
whole-brain results (thresholded at the whole-brain threshold deter-
mined above) with a region of interest defined as follows: </p>

<p>(i) We selected studies and meta-analyses that included an experi-
ence and an observation condition of actions, sensations or emo-
tions and selected the regions most consistently activated by 
experience and observation. Whenever possible we then used 
the <rs type="software">Anatomy ToolBox</rs> (Eickhoff et al., 2007) or the <rs corresp="#software-7" type="creator">AAL</rs> atlas 
of the <rs id="software-7" type="software">WFU Pickatlas</rs> (Maldjian et al., 2003) for regions not yet 
included in the Anatomy ToolBox and then combined them into a 
single composite anatomical region of interest using a logical 'OR' 
(Fig. 2, blue transparent regions). These anatomical regions, 
defined using <rs type="software">Anatomy ToolBox</rs> included the premotor cortices 
(Brodmann area 6 in Anatomy ToolBox) (Gazzola and Keysers, 
2009; Caspers et al., 2010), the primary and secondary somato-
sensory cortices (SI = BA3a + b + BA1 + BA2 and SII = OP1 + 
OP2 + OP3 + OP4) (Keysers et al., 2010). Those defined using 
the AAL included the insula and the anterior/mid cingulate 
(Wicker et al., 2003; Singer et al., 2004, 2006; Jabbi et al., 
2007; Bastiaansen et al., 2009; Lamm et al., 2011). 
(ii) We used the results from our localizer experiment (i.e. experi-
ence) to select voxels that were significantly activated by at least 
one of our stimuli by either one of the groups (Fig. 2, red 
transparent regions). Eight one-sample random effect t-tests, 
comparing the four summary volumes (love, pain, neutral, exclu-
sion) of the controls and those of the patients against zero 
(P unc 5 0.001), were combined by a logical 'OR' (<rs id="software-9" type="software">Marsbar</rs>; 
<rs corresp="#software-9" type="url">http://marsbar.sourceforge.net</rs>/) to generate a composite </p>

<p>Vicarious representations in psychopathy </p>

<p>Brain 2013: 136; 2550-2562 | 2553 </p>

<p>functional region of interest. We combined all hand interactions 
into a single region of interest, because empathic responses in 
the viewer are not always equal to the emotion in the actor; 
seeing pain can trigger tender feelings in addition to, or instead 
of, pain. Using a composite functional region of interest that 
included voxels triggered by any of the experiences (love, pain, 
exclusion or neutral), ensured an inclusive analysis that also 
captured empathic responses that are not equal to the viewed 
emotions: tender feelings triggered by a pain video would be 
captured by such a composite functional region of interest, 
because similar tender feelings will have been triggered by the 
love interactions also included in the region of interest definition. 
The same holds for pain triggered by the sight of exclusion etc. 
(iii) A logical 'AND' was used to combine the composite functional 
and anatomical regions of interest (Fig. 2, purple transparent 
regions) leading to our final region of interest. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Groups did not differ on age, IQ and handedness (Table 1). The 
patient group was significantly lower educated (Table 1 and 
Supplementary material). Mean Psychopathy Checklist-Revised 
score for the patient group was 32.3 (standard error 0.85; 
Supplementary Fig. 2). As expected, the control group scored 
lower (P 5 0.05) on the Psychopathic Personality Inventory. 
Diagnoses of the included patients are summarized in 
Supplementary Table 1 (see Supplementary material for assessment 
details). None of the participants scored above the cut-off for autistic 
spectrum disorder on the Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule. 
Two patients were taking psychoactive medication (citalopram 
20 mg/day; amitriptyline 175 mg/day). None of the control subjects 
reported using psychoactive medication. </p>

<p>RH 
LH </p>

<p>x = 38 
x = -38 </p>

<p>x = 6 </p>

<p>y = -26 </p>

<p>x = -6 </p>

<p>composite functional ROI </p>

<p>composite anatomical ROI </p>

<p>vicarious-experience mask </p>

<p>Figure 2 Region of interest definition. A voxel was included in the region of interest (ROI, purple) if and only if it was significantly </p>

<p>activated (P unc 5 0.001 and q fdr 5 0.05) during one of the interactions performed by subjects (controls or patients) during experience 
(blue) and if it belonged to anatomically defined brain regions the literature has associated with vicarious responses (red). LH = left 
hemisphere; RH = right hemisphere. </p>



<p>H. Meffert et al. </p>

<p>Experience </p>

<p>We tested the null hypothesis that for each condition, the two 
groups had the same BOLD signal using an ANOVA. No significant 
group differences were detected [q fdr 4 0.05; F(4,168) 5 9.17]. 
Except for a (14-voxel) cluster in the pars orbitalis of the inferior 
frontal gyrus [MNI: À 42, À 18, 14; q fdr 5 0.05; F(3,168) 4 8.24], 
there was no significant Group Â Experience interaction. </p>

<p>Observation </p>

<p>The ANOVA testing the null hypothesis that for each condition, 
the two groups had the same BOLD response revealed a large 
network of regions where this hypothesis was violated 
[P unc 5 0.001, F(3,168) = 4.85; q fdr 5 0.05]. A repeated measures 
ANOVA revealed no significant Group Â Video type interaction 
[q fdr 4 0.05, F(3,83,2) 5 8.58]. We therefore summed the activa-
tions of all videos to examine the main effect of Group. This 
revealed an extended network of brain regions with BOLD 
signal differing between the groups [P unc 5 0.001, F(1,168) = 
11.22; q fdr 5 0.05] (Fig. 3A and Supplementary Table 2). All of 
these regions showed higher BOLD for the control subjects. To 
explore if these group differences could include vicarious activa-
tions, we masked the analysis inclusively with our region of inter-
est (i.e. removed all significant voxels outside of the region of 
interest), at the same statistical threshold as the whole brain 
analysis. Group differences during observation indeed include a 
number of regions within this region of interest [P unc 5 0.001, 
F(1,168) = 11.22; q fdr 5 0.05] (Fig. 3B and Table 2), including 
the dorsal and ventral premotor cortex, primary and secondary 
somatosensory cortices, the anterior insula and the cingulate 
cortex. </p>

<p>Empathy </p>

<p>The null hypothesis that the two groups generated the same 
BOLD response for all four stimuli was rejected using an 
ANOVA [q fdr 5 0.05, F(3,168) = 4.89]. There was no 
Group Â Video type interaction [q fdr 4 0.05, F(1,168) 5 11.22, </p>

<p>P unc 4 0.001] and there was no Group Â Empathized hand inter-
action [q fdr 4 0.05, P unc 4 0.1, F(1,168) 5 2.74]. Accordingly, we 
examined the main effect of Group by summing over video type 
and empathized hand (Fig. 3C) [P unc 5 0.001 at F(1,168) 4 11.22; 
q fdr 5 0.05]. Some areas were more activated for the control sub-
jects, but fewer than during the observation experiment. 
Importantly, the instruction to feel with the hands in the videos 
led to a number of brain regions being more activated in the 
patients, including the medial and dorsolateral prefrontal cortex 
and the angular gyrus (Fig. 3C and Supplementary Table 3). 
Masking the analysis with the region of interest revealed very 
limited group differences in the region of interest; the control 
group only had higher BOLD in the primary somatosensory 
cortex; the patient group in the secondary somatosensory cortex 
(both P unc 5 0.001, T = 3.14; q fdr 5 0.05) (Fig. 3D and Table 3). </p>

<p>Effect of conditions </p>

<p>In all experiments, comparing the different stimulus categories 
recruited distinct and meaningful neural circuitries (Supplementary 
material). </p>

<p>Interaction analysis between Group and 
Experiment </p>

<p>To test if group differences were significantly reduced by the 
instruction to empathize, we examined the interaction between 
Experiment (observation, empathy) and Group, considering only 
the conditions common to both experiments (i.e. pain and love). 
We found the group differences to be smaller in the empathy 
compared to the observation experiment in a number of brain 
regions (P unc 5 0.001, T = 3.19, q fdr 5 0.05 for the entire brain), 
including the medial and anterior left insula, left hippocampus, 
bilateral thalamus, left caudate, left anterior cingulate cortex, 
and bilateral angular gyrus (Table 4). No regions showed the 
opposite effect. Within the region of interest, the left anterior 
insula showed reduced group differences under the instruction 
to empathize (Table 4, asterisk, small volume correction). A similar 
analysis with z-transformed data led to identical results </p>

<p>Table 1 Assessment data </p>

<p>Questionnaire 
Mean control 
Mean patient 
P-value t-test 
(n = 26) 
(n = 18) </p>

<p>Age 
36.96 (1.62) 
39.17 (2.41) 
P 2-tailed = 0.434 
GIT2-IQ (Groninger Intelligentie Test) 
98.77 (2.79) 
93.65 (4.00) 
P 2-tailed = 0.283 
Raven-IQ (Raven's Standard Progressive matrices) 
115.08 (2.05) 
106.62 (5.30) 
P 2-tailed = 0.101 
Handedness 
10.08 (0.38) 
9.67 (0.83) 
P 2-tailed = 0.623 
Years of education 
11.96 (0.34) 
7.39 (0.40) 
P 2-tailed 5 0.001 
Education level 
4.88 (0.54) 
2.00 (0.47) 
P 2-tailed 5 0.001 
PCL-R 
n/a 
32.3 (0.85) 
n/a 
F1 
n/a 
13.5 (0.62) 
n/a 
F1 
n/a 
14.9 (0.67) 
n/a 
Psychopathic Personality Inventory Total 
398.92 (7.61) 
422.39 (9.48) 
P 1-tailed = 0.023 </p>

<p>Numbers in brackets represent standard errors of the means. T-tests were used to compare the means of the groups; P-values are based on two-tailed testing except where 
directed hypotheses existed. Data for the Psychopathy Checklist-Revised (PCL-R) are not available for the control group. See Supplementary Fig. 1 for the histogram of the 
Psychopathy Checklist-Revised scores for the patient group and Supplementary Table 2 for a list of the clinical diagnosis for each patient. </p>

<p>Vicarious representations in psychopathy </p>

<p>Brain 2013: 136; 2550-2562 | 2555 </p>

<p>(Supplementary material). To graphically illustrate this interaction 
analysis containing pain and love only, we also calculated the 
group differences during observation, only considering pain and 
love trials (Supplementary Fig. 3), and plotted activation during 
empathy in regions showing group differences during observation 
(Supplementary Fig. 4). Results are very similar to those consider-
ing all conditions (see also Fig. 3A for the group differences using 
all four conditions). </p>

<p>Additional analyses to exclude 
confounds </p>

<p>Eye track data indicated no significant differences in spatial eye 
gaze pattern or in time spent looking at the videos (Supplementary 
material); baseline activation did not significantly differ between 
the groups during observation, empathy or experience, nor in the 
interaction of Group and Experiment (observation versus empathy) </p>

<p>Observation 
experiment </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>RH 
LH </p>

<p>Empathy 
experiment </p>

<p>x = -6 
x = 6 </p>

<p>x = -40 
x = 36 </p>

<p>x = -6 
x = 6 </p>

<p>x = -40 
x = 36 </p>

<p>x = -6 
x = 6 </p>

<p>x = -40 
x = 36 </p>

<p>x = -6 
x = 6 </p>

<p>x = -40 
x = 36 </p>

<p>t-values 
5 </p>

<p>0 
patients &gt; controls 
controls &gt; patients </p>

<p>RH 
LH </p>

<p>Figure 3 Observation and empathy results. (A and B) Group differences during observation (P unc 5 0.001,q fdr 5 0.05) (Supplementary </p>

<p>Table 3). (C and D) Group differences during empathy (P unc 5 0.001, q fdr 5 0.05) (Supplementary Table 4). (B and D) Same as A and C, 
but masked inclusively with the region of interest (Tables 2 and 3). Hot colours: BOLD response control 4 psychopaths; cold colours: 
psychopaths 4 controls. RH = right hemisphere; LH = left hemisphere; x = MNI coordinate of sagittal plane. Slices and renders are taken 
from the mean normalized anatomy of all subjects. </p>



<p>H. Meffert et al. </p>

<p>Table 2 Group differences in observation within the region of interest </p>

<p>Cluster 
size </p>

<p>T 
MNI coordinates 
Hemi-sphere 
Macro anatomical location 
of peak voxel </p>

<p>Overlap with 
cytoarchitectonic regions 
x 
y 
z </p>

<p>Controls larger than patients 
173 
6,26 
36 
À 33 
54 
R 
Postcentral gyrus 
BA2, BA3ab 
4,25 
51 
À 24 
42 
R 
Supramarginal gyrus 
3,87 
60 
À 15 
27 
R 
Supramarginal gyrus 
242 
6,20 
À33 
À 36 
45 
L 
Postcentral gyrus 
BA2, BA3ab 
4,68 
À 9 
À 18 
42 
L 
Midcingulate gyrus 
4,33 
À12 
À 42 
48 
L 
Precuneus 
35 
5,64 
21 
À3 
54 
R 
Superior frontal gyrus 
BA6 
4,80 
6 
18 
54 
R 
Pre-SMA 
4,04 
12 
6 
57 
R 
Pre-SMA 
84 
5,41 
60 
15 
18 
R 
Inferior frontal gyrus (p. oper.) 
BA44, BA45 
3,87 
48 
12 
24 
R 
Inferior frontal gyrus (p. oper.) 
85 
5,15 
À36 
À6 
À 12 
L 
Insula 
Insula (Id) 
3,89 
À36 
À3 
12 
L 
Insula 
72 
5,08 
27 
À 12 
48 
R 
Precentral gyrus (dPM) 
BA6 
20 
4,87 
À51 
15 
27 
L 
Inferior frontal gyrus (p. oper.) 
BA44 
45 
4,86 
30 
15 
À 18 
R 
Anterior insula 
4,72 
36 
18 
À 12 
R 
Anterior insula 
67 
4,80 
À27 
À 21 
51 
L 
Precentral gyrus (dPM) 
BA 6 
4,24 
À27 
À9 
54 
L 
Precentral gyrus (dPM) 
4,06 
À33 
À6 
60 
L 
Precentral gyrus (dPM) 
72 
4,38 
À33 
15 
3 
L 
Anterior insula 
4,07 
À27 
21 
6 
L 
Anterior insula 
35 
4,25 
9 
À 21 
39 
R 
Midcingulate gyrus 
30 
4,14 
42 
À 33 
15 
R 
Superior temporal gyrus 
4,00 
45 
À 24 
18 
R 
Rolandic operculum 
OP1, OP2 
49 
4,07 
45 
À3 
À 9 
R 
Superior temporal gyrus 
3,99 
42 
3 
0 
R 
Middle insula 
14 
4,03 
54 
30 
0 
R 
Inferior frontal gyrus (p. tri.) 
BA45 
27 
3,86 
À54 
À 15 
21 
L 
Postcentral gyrus 
OP1, OP4 
3,25 
À54 
À 15 
33 
L 
Postcentral gyrus 
BA3b 
16 
3,83 
9 
9 
27 
R 
Midcingulate gyrus 
3,52 
3 
15 
21 
R 
Midcingulate gyrus 
14 
3,82 
36 
30 
6 
R 
Anterior insula </p>

<p>Differences (P unc 5 0.001 and q fdr 5 0.05) in brain activity between the psychopathy and control group within the region of interest (see Supplementary Table 2 for the 
results outside the region of interest). No regions were more active for the psychopathy than the control group. The table specifies the size of each cluster, then, for its peak, 
the T-value, MNI coordinates, hemisphere and macro-anatomical location based on the groups' mean anatomy. Finally, the table specifies cytoarchitectonic brain regions 
that the cluster overlaps with according to the Anatomy Toolbox. 
BA = Brodmann area; SMA = supplementary motor area; dPM = dorsal premotor cortex; p.tri = pars triangularis; p.oper = pars opercularis. </p>

<p>Table 3 Group differences in empathy within the region of interest </p>

<p>Cluster 
size </p>

<p>T 
MNI coordinates 
Hemi-sphere 
Macro anatomical location 
of peak voxel </p>

<p>Overlap with 
cytoarchitectonic regions 
x 
y 
z </p>

<p>Controls larger than patients 
53 
6,64 
36 
À33 
51 
R 
Postcentral gyrus 
BA2, BA3 
48 
4,87 
À 33 
À36 
45 
L 
Postcentral gyrus 
BA2, BA3 
Patients larger than controls 
33 
4,63 
42 
À15 
18 
R 
Parietal operculum 
OP1-4 
48 
3,89 
À 57 
À12 
9 
L 
Parietal operculum 
OP1-4 </p>

<p>Table lists areas that were more activated (P unc 5 0.001 and q fdr 5 0.05) for the controls (positive effect of controls) and areas that were more activated for the patients 
(positive effect of patients) within the region of interest (see Supplementary Table 3 for differences between the two groups outside the region of interest). Conventions 
as in Table 2. 
BA = Brodmann area. </p>

<p>Vicarious representations in psychopathy </p>

<p>Brain 2013: 136; 2550-2562 | 2557 </p>

<p>(Supplementary material). Additionally, if empathy normalized 
after instructions to empathize, we would expect that both 
groups would report similar experiences while viewing the videos 
after the end of the experiment. A debriefing questionnaire 
confirmed this prediction (Supplementary material). Finally, 
group differences during observation could not be explained 
entirely by variance during experience (Supplementary material). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, we analysed vicarious activations in a group of 
incarcerated subjects with a diagnosis of psychopathy, by having 
them experience and observe emotional hand interactions, while 
being scanned. We compared these activations with those of age-
and IQ-matched healthy controls. During observation, individuals 
with psychopathy showed, compared to controls, a wide network 
with reduced activations, including regions of the temporal, insu-
lar, parietal and frontal lobe. In addition to agnostically reporting 
all brain regions showing group differences, we aimed to critically 
examine if these group differences provide robust evidence for 
reduced vicarious activations. To do so, we used a dual, conser-
vative approach, in which we excluded visually triggered group 
differences (i.e. during observation) as evidence of abnormal vicar-
ious activation if they occurred in regions (i) that were not acti-
vated by the experience of hand interactions (i.e. during 
experience); and (ii) that were not consistently associated with 
vicarious activations in the literature. Doing so, we show that 
areas associated with vicarious activations to hand actions (pre-
motor cortices), sensations (primary and secondary somatosensory </p>

<p>cortices), and emotions (anterior cingulate and insula cortices) 
were indeed hypo-activated in the psychopathy compared to the 
control group during observation. However, group differences 
attributable to vicarious activations were significantly reduced 
when specifically instructing participants to empathize with the 
actors in the videos. Despite the fact that the different types of 
hand actions induced different brain activations during experience 
and observation, including the expected recruitment of dorsal 
anterior cingulate cortex for painful and the ventromedial prefron-
tal cortex for loving interactions (Supplementary material), none of 
the experiments indicated that the patients were more different 
from the control subjects for a particular type of hand action. 
Our study has a number of limitations. First, because there was a 
security risk considered unacceptable associated with bringing non-
psychopathic incarcerated offenders to our scanning facility, we lack 
such a control group. Secondary factors linked to criminal lifestyle 
(e.g. lower level of education, history of drug abuse and length of 
incarceration) could thus contribute to our group differences. 
Unfortunately, as these variables were highly correlated with the 
factor Group [e.g. r(Group, Substance abuse) = 0.86], disentangling 
their contribution through inclusion of nuisance covariates in our 
analyses is impossible (Miller and Chapman, 2001). Secondly, 
although we included one of the largest group of psychopathic 
offenders ever scanned at 3 T, it is difficult to ascertain that our 
findings generalize to all incarcerated psychopathic offenders, 
making a replication study in a different country particularly impor-
tant. Third, incarcerated psychopaths are a subgroup of psycho-
paths. It is unclear whether those psychopaths that have never 
been incarcerated would show the same pattern of brain activity. </p>

<p>Table 4 Regions normalized after empathy instruction </p>

<p>Cluster 
size </p>

<p>T 
MNI coordinates 
Hemi-sphere 
Macro anatomical location of peak voxel 
Overlap with 
cytoarchitectonic regions 
x 
y 
z </p>

<p>59 
5.69 
À 21 
À 33 
À3 
L 
Thalamus, hippocampus 
Hipp (FD, SUB, CA) 
30 
5.19 
À 42 
42 
À 12 
L 
Inferior frontal gyrus (p. orb.) 
59 
4.91 
À 48 
0 
À 27 
L 
Middle temporal gyrus, temporal pole 
137 
4.53 
À 48 
À 54 
39 
L 
Inferior parietal lobe 
hIP1, IPC (PGa, PF, PFm) 
11 
4.49 
36 
39 
À 12 
R 
Inferior frontal gyrus, middle orbital gyrus 
207 
4.39 
33 
15 
45 
R 
Middle frontal gyrus 
49 
4.36 
9 
30 
48 
R 
Superior medial gyrus, anterior cingulate gyrus 
49 
4.33 
À9 
39 
33 
L 
Superior medial gyrus, anterior cingulate gyrus 
36 
4.24 
À 48 
21 
30 
L 
Inferior frontal gyrus 
BA44, BA45 
12 
4.16 
À 21 
57 
À3 
L 
Superior orbital gyrus 
31 
4.04 
À 30 
24 
45 
L 
Medial frontal gyrus 
63* 
3.99 
À 36 
3 
À6 
L 
Insula lobe 
45 
3.99 
45 
À 42 
24 
R 
Inferior parietal cortex 
IPC (PFm, PGa) 
16 
3.87 
À 21 
36 
33 
L 
Superior frontal gyrus 
13 
3.87 
À 15 
15 
0 
L 
Caudate 
13 
3.83 
21 
À 33 
3 
R 
Hippocampus 
Hipp (FD) 
12 
3.48 
À 33 
À 15 
À 24 
L 
Hippocampus 
Hipp (CA, SUB, EC) </p>

<p>Analysis is based on raw values. 
*The insula cluster, 31 voxels that are also significant when restricting the analysis to the region of interest (small volume correction, q 5 0.05 for the entire region 
of interest). 
Conventions as in Table 2. See Supplementary Table 4 for the results of the same analysis on z-transformed values. 
BA = Brodmann area; Hipp = hippocampus; p. orbitalis = pars hIP1 = Cytoarchitectonic subdivisions of the intraparietal sulcus according to Choi et al., 2006; Scheperjans, 
2008a,b; IPC = inferior parietal cortex; PGa., PF., PFm = Cytoarchitectonic subdivisions of the inferior parietal cortex according to Caspers et al., 2006, 2008; FD., SUB., 
CA., EC. = Cytoarchitectonic subdivisions of the hippocampus according to Amunts et al., 2005. </p>



<p>H. Meffert et al. </p>

<p>With these limitations in mind, our results shed new light on the 
neural basis of psychopathy in two ways. First, they point to 
reduced vicarious activity in regions involved in performing 
actions, feeling touch and experiencing emotions, that are consid-
ered functional markers of empathy, as a possible neural basis 
for the reduced empathy and antisocial behaviour, central to psy-
chopathy (Hare et al., 2001; Hare, 2003; Blair et al., 2006; Hare 
and Neumann, 2009). For most of us, seeing someone get hurt 
triggers vicarious activity in pain areas. This vicarious pain gives 
us an 'egoistic' reason to refrain from antisocial behaviour; do not 
hurt others because it (vicariously) hurts you (Miller and Eisenberg, 
1988). In psychopathy, reduced somatosensory, insula and 
anterior cingulate vicarious activations could disinhibit antisocial 
behaviour. Because we found these deficits to be independent 
of video type, they suggest reduced empathy even for the 
pleasure of others. 
Second, our results show that explicit instructions to empathize 
significantly reduced the group differences within regions asso-
ciated with vicarious activations. In particular, instructions led to 
a partial 'normalization' (i.e. significantly reduced quantitative 
group differences) of brain activity in the insula within our 
region of interest according to the Experiment Â Group interac-
tion. Because stimulation of the insula can inhibit aggression in 
monkeys (Caruana et al., 2011), this instruction-triggered increase 
of insular activations in psychopathy could have important vio-
lence-inhibiting behavioural effects. Future experiments should 
directly investigate the brain-behaviour link we propose, by creat-
ing conditions in which for instance psychopathic and control par-
ticipants are given a choice to harm a confederate to gain money, 
while measuring the participants' brain activity. Our data would 
predict that, particularly in participants with psychopathy, instruc-
tions to empathize with the confederate will increase vicarious 
pain activations in the insula and reduce the propensity to harm 
the confederate. The effect of instruction is also apparent in the 
brain activity in the psychopathy group outside the vicarious acti-
vation mask, where brain activity changed from never being more 
active compared to control subjects during the observation experi-
ment (Table 2 and Supplementary Table 3, and even when taking 
only love and pain into account Supplementary Fig. 3), to being 
more active in half the voxels during the empathy experiment 
(Table 3 and Supplementary Table 4). Altogether, combining the 
findings of the observation and empathy experiment, our data 
suggest a profound reconceptualization of psychopathy more as 
a reduced propensity, rather than an incapacity, to generate vicar-
ious activations. Indeed, in self-report measures of empathy, our 
psychopathy group reported normal levels of trait empathy (data 
not shown) and, after instructions to empathize, to have their own 
feelings affected as much by the different video types than our 
control group (Supplementary material), in line with our finding of 
relatively preserved capacity for empathy, at least under certain 
instructions. 
What mechanisms might mediate this effect of instruction? The 
interaction analysis revealed that normalization of brain activity in 
the region of interest following instructions to empathize was 
accompanied by increases relative to control subjects in regions 
(outside the region of interest), associated with conscious menta-
lizing (including the medial prefrontal cortex and the temporal </p>

<p>pole) (Amodio and Frith, 2006; Van Overwalle and Baetens, 
2009), and deliberate reappraisal (dorsolateral prefrontal cortex 
and angular gyrus, Ochsner et al., 2004). A recent functional 
MRI study in healthy volunteers showed that the anterior insula 
could be activated through the abovementioned mentalizing and 
reappraisal circuits while participants deliberately try to imagine 
what a character in a written story would feel (Jabbi et al., 
2008). Taken together, this suggests that under instructions to 
empathize, our psychopathic participants relied more than our 
control participants on deliberate mechanisms to boost the activa-
tion of their own actions, emotions and sensations. Accordingly, 
we do not find that the overall brain activity is 'normal' in psycho-
pathic individuals while deliberately empathizing with others, but 
rather, that they manage to recruit vicarious activations to a simi-
lar level. In the context of many residual group differences outside 
the vicarious activation region of interest, future research will need 
to use other methods (e.g. physiological recordings-galvanic skin 
response, pupillary dilation, heart rate, respiration or blood pres-
sure-or qualitative analyses of verbal reports) to further explore 
how the subjective experience of psychopathic individuals com-
pares with that of controls during deliberate empathy. This is 
particularly true because many qualitatively different emotions 
trigger quantitatively similar, overlapping patterns of activation 
(Jabbi et al., 2007), and quantitatively similar activations in the 
two groups within the vicarious activation region of interest could 
thus coexist with qualitative differences in the actual emotions 
triggered. 
So far, we focused on hypo-activations within our region of 
interest that indicate reduced vicarious activations during observa-
tion. However, in the main effect of Group during observation, 
we also measured reduced activations in the bilateral amygdala. 
Because the amygdala is central to learning (Blair, 2007) and 
attention (Patterson and Newman, 1993; Moul et al., 2012) 
centred theories of psychopathy, this reduced amygdala activation 
invites us to consider how our findings relate to these dominant 
theories of psychopathy. Our hypo-vicarious view of psychopathy 
integrates well with models of moral development emphasizing 
deficits in learning, where the amygdala of children normally 
helps them associate their instrumental aggressive behaviour, 
which is originally neutral, with negative emotions triggered by 
the distress of their victims (Blair, 2007). This is because our 
reduced spontaneous vicarious activations (within our region of 
interest) could lead to reduced personal distress while harming 
others and our reduced bilateral amygdala activity (outside the 
region of interest) may then lead to reduced associations between 
aggression and the (reduced) personal distress in psychopathic 
individuals. Our hypo-vicarious view of psychopathy, however, 
also overlaps with attention-based theories. As the amygdala is 
increasingly conceived as an automatic detector of salient 
features in the environment (Adolphs, 2010), our finding that 
deliberate attention can reduce vicarious activation deficits in psy-
chopathy dovetails with theories of psychopathy emphasizing 
abnormal amygdale-based attention (Moul et al., 2012), by sug-
gesting that reduced empathy is a downstream result of impaired 
stimulus driven, bottom-up attention to the emotions of others, 
which can under certain conditions (here through instructions) be 
compensated by deliberate, bottom-up attention. Hence, our work </p>

<p>Vicarious representations in psychopathy </p>

<p>Brain 2013: 136; 2550-2562 | 2559 </p>

<p>on vicarious activations is no alternative to work on instrumental 
learning or attention. Instead it complements these efforts by 
adding a third protagonist, vicarious activations, to a complex 
scenario in which abnormal bottom-up attention might fail to 
trigger normal empathy, which in turn prevents the instrumental 
learning so central to moral development. In this scenario, delib-
erate, top-down modulation of attention may restore vicarious 
activations. Understanding how the amygdala mechanistically 
interacts with regions involved in vicarious activations to direct 
this scenario remains to be understood. 
In many circumstances, empathy can be counterproductive: if 
you want to take the Rolex off an old man's arm, empathizing 
with the man will not serve your greed. Only if empathy is a 
spontaneous response, will you feel empathy in this circumstance, 
and reduce your violence (Miller and Eisenberg, 1988). 
Accordingly, the lack of spontaneous vicarious activation we mea-
sured in our observation experiment will have severe violence-
disinhibiting consequences even in the face of a preserved delib-
erate empathy. For therapists requesting a scientific understanding 
of psychopathy to tailor their therapies (Salekin et al., 2010), our 
finding that instructions to empathize can reduce group differ-
ences indicates that therapeutic efforts may actually not need to 
create a capacity for empathy, for such a capacity may already 
exist (at least in our sample of incarcerated psychopathic offen-
ders). Instead, therapies may need to focus on making the existing 
capacity more automatic, so that it will come into play even when 
inhibiting goal-directed behaviour. Such therapies could harvest 
the patients' potential to normalize vicarious activations through 
deliberately focusing attention on empathizing with others. The 
fact that psychopathic individuals often display low motivation 
for change and comply less with therapy than other criminals 
(Salekin et al., 2010) will certainly represent an unfortunate 
challenge in such efforts. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank A.J. Sibeijn-Kuiper for her help in setting up the specific 
safety protocol and scanning the subjects, R. Renken for his help 
with data analysis, S. Hwang for proofreading the manuscript. We 
also thank the participants for their cooperation. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>The work was supported by the Dutch Science Foundation (NWO) 
[grant number 452-04-305, 451-09-006]. The Forensic Psychiatric 
Clinic Dr. S van Mesdag paid for transport and security costs 
and partially funded H.M. None of the authors have conflicts of 
interest regarding this work. </p>

<p>Supplementary material </p>

<p>Supplementary material is available at Brain online. </p>





<p>H. Meffert et al. </p>



<p>Vicarious representations in psychopathy </p>

<p>Brain 2013: 136; 2550-2562 | 2561 </p>





<p>H. Meffert et al. </p>

</text></tei>