<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3078083" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT Fusion of mononucleated myoblasts to form multinucleated myofibers is an es-
sential phase of skeletal myogenesis, which occurs during muscle development as well as 
during postnatal life for muscle growth, turnover, and regeneration. Many cell adhesion pro-
teins, including integrins, have been shown to be important for myoblast fusion in verte-
brates, and recently focal adhesion kinase (FAK), has been proposed as a key mediator of 
myoblast fusion. Here we focused on the possible role of PKCθ, the PKC isoform predomi-
nantly expressed in skeletal muscle, in myoblast fusion. We found that the expression of PKCθ 
is strongly up-regulated following freeze injury-induced muscle regeneration, as well as dur-
ing in vitro differentiation of satellite cells (SCs; the muscle stem cells). Using both PKCθ 
knockout and muscle-specific PKCθ dominant-negative mutant mouse models, we observed 
delayed body and muscle fiber growth during the first weeks of postnatal life, when com-
pared with wild-type (WT) mice. We also found that myofiber formation, during muscle regen-
eration after freeze injury, was markedly impaired in PKCθ mutant mice, as compared with 
WT. This phenotype was associated with reduced expression of the myogenic differentiation 
program executor, myogenin, but not with that of the SC marker Pax7. Indeed in vitro dif-
ferentiation of primary muscle-derived SCs from PKCθ mutants resulted in the formation of 
thinner myotubes with reduced numbers of myonuclei and reduced fusion rate, when com-
pared with WT cells. These effects were associated to reduced expression of the profusion 
genes caveolin-3 and β1D integrin and to reduced activation/phosphorylation of their up-
stream regulator FAK. Indeed the exogenous expression of a constitutively active mutant 
form of PKCθ in muscle cells induced FAK phosphorylation. Moreover pharmacologically me-
diated full inhibition of FAK activity led to similar fusion defects in both WT and PKCθ-null 
myoblasts. We thus propose that PKCθ signaling regulates myoblast fusion by regulating, at 
least in part, FAK activity, essential for profusion gene expression. </p>

<p>Monitoring Editor 
During muscle development, myoblasts (the muscle-committed cell 
population) fuse together to form muscle fibers. When the muscle is 
built, postnatal muscle growth and regeneration are guaranteed by 
satellite cells (SCs), the muscle stem cells, recognized as located 
between the basal lamina and the sarcolemma, and expressing the 
SC marker Pax7; these cells are able to recapitulate myogenesis 
(Holterman and Rudnicki, 2005; Le and Rudnicki, 2007; Kuang and  Rudnicki, 2008). A large number of factors regulate muscle precur-
sor differentiation. Pax7-positive cells must escape from their stem 
cell program through the activation of myogenin and MRF4, which 
regulate the expression of muscle-specific protein to build the con-
tractile apparatus. An initial phase of myoblast fusion (primary fu-
sion) is required to form nascent myofibers. A secondary fusion </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>cells (Sun et al., 2000) and the mPKCθK/R transgenic model, in 
which a dominant-negative mutant form of PKCθ is expressed under 
the control of a muscle-specific promoter (Serra et al., 2003). </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Lack of PKCθ delays mouse growth </p>

<p>We initially observed that juvenile mice lacking PKCθ appeared 
smaller than age-and sex-matched WT mice. We thus systemati-
cally measured body weight of PKCθ 
−/-at different ages during 
postnatal growth, as compared with that of age-and sex-matched 
WT mice. As shown in Figure 1A, during the first 4-5 wk of age, 
the body weight of PKCθ 
−/-mice was significantly lower than that of 
WT mice, raising the level of WT body weight only by 5-8 wk. 
Because skeletal muscle is the tissue that contributes most to body 
weight, we aimed to verify whether the observed decrease in body 
weight was due to reduction in skeletal muscle mass. As first, lack of 
PKCθ expression in skeletal muscles (tibialis anterior [TA] and exten-
sor digitorum longus [EDL]) of the mutant mice was confirmed by 
Western blot analysis (Figure 1A). Indeed muscle mass, as well as 
muscle fiber size, of 2-mo-old PKCθ 
−/-hind limb was apparently re-
duced, as compared with that of WT (Figure 1B). In fact, morpho-
metric analysis of TA muscle showed that muscle fiber cross-sec-
tional area (CSA) was reduced in PKCθ 
−/-with respect to WT during 
the first weeks of postnatal life (Figure 1B), whereas no significant 
differences were observed in the total number of fibers (unpublished 
data). By 3 mo, however, muscle fiber CSA in PKCθ 
−/-was similar to 
that of WT mice (Figure 1B), suggesting that lack of PKCθ 
−/-delayed 
postnatal mouse growth, mostly by delaying postnatal skeletal 
muscle fiber growth. </p>

<p>Lack of PKCθ impairs muscle regeneration in vivo </p>

<p>It is well known that postnatal muscle growth is due to SC (muscle 
stem cell) differentiation and fusion to preexisting muscle fibers, as 
well as to each other, to form new fibers. Thus the reduction in 
muscle mass and myofiber CSA observed during the first weeks of 
postnatal growth in PKCθ 
−/-mice suggests that PKCθ may indeed 
be required for these processes. To verify this possibility, we first 
analyzed whether the expression and activation/phosphorylation of 
PKCθ was modulated in WT mice during muscle regeneration, a 
process which recapitulates muscle formation and growth. Muscle 
regeneration was induced by freeze injury in TA, and protein ex-
tracts from TA muscles, dissected at different periods of time (2, 4, 
and 7 d) after injury, were analyzed by Western blot. As shown in 
Figure 2A, PKCθ expression and phosphorylation peaked in regen-
erating muscle 4-7 d after injury, thus during the period of major 
fusion and growth of regenerating fibers. Muscle regeneration was 
then induced in age-and sex-matched PKCθ </p>

<p>−/-</p>

<p>. Muscle reorganiza-
tion was analyzed at morphological level, 4 d after injury when new 
myofibers started to form (unpublished data), and 7 d after injury, 
when most regenerating myofibers had formed but were still im-
mature, and compared with WT regenerating muscle (Figure 2B). 
Analysis of muscle sections revealed that muscle from mice in which 
PKCθ was deleted displayed, at both period of times, the character-
istics of delayed regeneration, such as smaller regenerating centro-
nucleated myofibers, heterogeneity in myofiber size, increased 
number of interstitial cells, and increased interstitial space between 
myofibers, as compared with time-matched regenerating WT mus-
cle (Figure 2B, a and b). In keeping with these observations at day 7, 
although the number of embryonic myosin heavy chain (eMyHC; 
used as a marker of regenerating myofibers) expressing myofibers in 
PKCθ 
−/-mice was similar to that in WT mice (Figure 2B, c and d), 
their median CSA was significantly smaller (Figure 2B, e). As a result, </p>

<p>wave (secondary fusion), involving recruitment of mononucleated 
cells to the nascent myofibers, then completes myofiber growth. 
Several molecules contribute to myoblast fusion, such as M-cad-
herin, neural cell adhesion molecule (NCAM), β1D integrin, and ca-
veolin 3. Among them, β1D integrin and caveolin 3 expression has 
been recently shown to be required for "secondary" myoblast 
fusion, because reduction of any of them dramatically impairs 
myoblast fusion; their expression appears to be regulated by focal 
adhesion kinase (FAK) signaling, which has thus been proposed as a 
key player in the fusion process (Quach et al., 2009). 
Many studies suggested that PKC is one of the key intermediates 
in integrin-mediated signaling in many cell types (Disatnik and  Rando, 1999; Mostafavi-Pour et al., 2003). Indeed inhibition of PKC 
activity results in the inhibition of cell attachment and spreading as 
well as of FAK phosphorylation. PKCs may also directly phosphory-
late focal adhesion proteins like talin and filamin (Tigges et al.,  2003), allowing the interactions of integrins with the actin cytoskel-
eton. Moreover activation of PKC can promote the cellular changes 
mediated by integrin/matrix interactions (Disatnik and Rando, 1999;  Disatnik et al., 2002; 2004; Connors et al., 2007; Tulla et al., 2008). 
These observations together demonstrate that PKC plays a specific 
role in integrin-mediated signal transduction. Because the PKC fam-
ily of serine/threonine protein kinases comprises at least 12 iso-
forms, it is still unclear whether different PKC isoforms may play 
distinct and specific role. PKCs can be subdivided in three sub-
groups, according to their structure and enzymatic activity: the 
"conventional" PKCs (PKCα, β1, β2, and γ), the enzymatic activity of 
which is calcium and phospholipid dependent, the "novel" PKCs (δ, 
ε, η, θ, and μ/PKD), the activity of which is calcium independent but 
phospholipid dependent, and the "atypical" PKCs (ζ, ι/λ, and τ), the 
activity of which is calcium and phospholipidindependent. In skele-
tal muscle, PKCθ is the PKC isoform predominantly expressed 
(Osada et al., 1992; Zappelli et al., 1996). In lymphocytes, it acts as 
a key regulator in their activation and proliferation (Pfeifhofer et al.,  2003; Manicassamy et al., 2006; Boschelli, 2009). We recently 
showed that it is also required for cardiomyocyte survival and car-
diac remodeling (Paoletti et al., 2010). Its role in skeletal muscle is 
not as clear yet, however. We and others have shown that PKCθ 
expression in skeletal muscle is developmentally and nerve regu-
lated, and that it mediates various cellular responses (Hilgenberg  et al., 1996; Zappelli et al., 1996; Serra et al., 2003; D'Andrea et al.,  2006; Gao et al., 2007; Tokugawa et al., 2009; Messina et al., 2010). 
It is noteworthy that PKCθ starts to be expressed during the fetal 
period of development, when muscle mass is built, and it peaks dur-
ing the first few weeks of postnatal life, when muscle mass needs to 
grow extensively (Hilgenberg et al., 1996; Zappelli et al., 1996;  Messina et al., 2010), suggesting that PKCθ may be involved in skel-
etal muscle growth and remodeling. To test this hypothesis, experi-
mentally induced muscle regeneration, which recapitulates most 
developmental and histogenetic events, may represent a reliable 
approach. Earlier studies have suggested that multiple PKC iso-
forms are implicated in muscle-regenerative process, acting differ-
ently in times and location and suggesting that individual isoform 
may fulfill distinct functions (Moraczewski et al., 2002). Indeed dur-
ing regeneration, an earlier expression of PKCθ than of the other 
members of PKC was observed in rats (Moraczewski et al., 2002). 
More recently, restriction of PKCθ immunoreactivity in SCs was de-
scribed in regenerating rat TA, suggesting a role in SC maintenance 
and/or activation (Tokugawa et al., 2009). We here aimed to investi-
gate the role of PKCθ in muscle regeneration in vivo and SC differ-
entiation in vitro, using two different models of PKCθ-null mice: a 
PKCθ knockout model, in which the PKCθ gene was inactivated in all </p>

<p>Volume 22 April 15, 2011 </p>

<p>PKCθ and myoblast fusion | 1411 </p>

<p>after injury, muscle morphology seemed 
similar in control and PKCθ 
−/-muscles, in 
terms of muscle fiber CSA and muscle orga-
nization (unpublished data), showing that 
there clearly are compensatory mechanisms 
that ultimately result in effective regenera-
tion even if significantly delayed compared 
with control muscle. </p>

<p>Lack of PKCθ impairs in vitro 
myogenesis </p>

<p>To test whether PKCθ may regulate myo-
blast fusion, the expression and activation of 
PKCθ were analyzed in in vitro differentiat-
ing primary myoblasts derived from WT 
mice. As shown in Figure 3A, PKCθ expres-
sion was strongly up-regulated within 8 h in 
differentiation medium (DM), and most of 
the protein was associated to the particulate 
fraction, as a feature of PKC activation. In 
vitro differentiation of primary myoblasts 
derived from PKCθ mutant mice was then 
compared with that of WT myoblasts. The 
cells were fixed after 48 h in DM and were 
either stained with Wright's solution or im-
munostained with the anti-sarcomeric myo-
sin heavy chain MF20 antibody. As shown in 
Figure 3B, by 48 h in DM, WT myoblasts had 
formed elongated myotubes containing a 
large number of nuclei; in contrast, PKCθ </p>

<p>−/-</p>

<p>myoblasts exhibited minimal fusion. To 
quantify these observations, fusion rate was 
evaluated by counting the number of nuclei 
included in myosin-positive myotubes (con-
taining ≥ 3 nuclei) divided by the total num-
ber of nuclei. As shown in Figure 3B, the fu-
sion rate in PKCθ 
−/-muscle cell cultures was 
almost 50% with respect to WT cells. To 
verify whether "secondary" myogenesis 
(addition of nuclei to already formed myo-
tubes) was actually impaired, the number of 
nuclei per myotube was evaluated; as shown 
in Figure 3B, the mean number of nuclei per 
myotube was significantly lower in PKCθ-
null cultures, as compared with WT. After culturing the cells for lon-
ger periods of time, the number of myotubes was approximately the 
same, as both cultures already reached the plateau stage by 48 h in 
DM. Fusion continued in both genotypes, but the fusion rate differ-
ences were still maintained (unpublished data). To verify whether 
similar defects may account for the reduced myofiber CSA observed 
in vivo, isolated myofibers were prepared from EDL muscle of 
2-mo-old mice, and nuclei were counted by means of TO-PRO-3 
staining. Nuclei included in myofiber-associated SCs were identified 
as located outside the sarcolemma. Indeed the number of nuclei 
in freshly isolated PKCθ 
−/-myofibers was significantly lower than 
that in WT ones, whereas the number of SCs per myofiber was not 
altered (Figures 3C and Supplemental Figure S1). 
To verify whether the in vitro observed defects might depend on 
different cell populations obtained from the two genotypes, the ex-
pression of alternative markers of muscle-specific resident precur-
sors, such as PW1 (Mitchell et al., 2010), as well as markers of early 
or middle stages of myogenesis, such as MyoD and desmin, was </p>

<p>the amount of eMyHC content in PKCθ 
−/-regenerating muscle was 
significantly lower than that in WT. In fact, Western blot analysis re-
vealed that, whereas in WT muscle eMyHC expression was increas-
ing by the time of regeneration, in PKCθ 
−/-its expression increased 
at 4 d after injury, but then it did not further increase (Figure 2C). To 
verify whether the observed alterations in muscle regeneration were 
due to impairment of SCs activation and/or differentiation, the ex-
pression of the SC marker Pax7 and of the myogenic differentiation 
executor myogenin was analyzed by Western blot. As shown in Fig-
ure 2C, Pax7 expression was highly increased in both mutant and 
WT mice at day 4 after injury, at a similar extent, and then decreased 
by day 7 similarly in both mutant and WT mice. In contrast, the 
strong up-regulation of myogenin expression in WT mice at day 4 
after injury was prevented in PKCθ 
−/-mice; moreover the following 
down-regulation observed in WT mice 7 d after injury, as an indica-
tor of the resolution of the differentiation process, was not observed 
in PKCθ </p>

<p>−/-</p>

<p>, where the level of expression of myogenin was only 
slightly lower than that observed at day 4 after injury. One month </p>

<p>FIGURE 1: Lack of PKCθ delays mice growth. (A) Mean body weight in WT and PKCθ 
−/-mice at 
different time points during postnatal growth (left panel) (n ≥ 5 per genotype/age). Right panel, 
Western blot analysis of PKCθ expression in EDL and TA muscle from 2-mo-old WT and 
PKCθ 
−/-mice. (B) H&amp;E staining of TA muscle sections from 2-mo-old WT (a) and PKCθ 
−/-mice 
(b) (bar = 100 μm); c: representative picture of hind limbs derived from 2-mo-old WT and 
PKCθ 
−/-mice, as indicated; d: mean myofiber CSA in PKCθ 
−/-(gray bars) TA muscles at different 
periods of time during postnatal growth, expressed as percentage of myofiber CSA in WT, 
assumed as 100% for each time point; n ≥ 3 per genotype/age ( </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>p &lt; 0.01, *p &lt; 0.05 vs. 
time-matched WT). </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>myoblasts, was comparable to that of WT cells (Figure 4A). Similar 
results were obtained when the medium was replaced with DM to 
induce differentiation (unpublished data). 
To verify whether the observed defects were, instead, the result 
of differences in growth rate, low-density cultures were assessed to 
obtain single-cell-derived clones. At first, the number of clones 
obtained per plated cell was evaluated, and the results were simi-
lar in both WT and PKCθ-null myoblasts (Figure 4B). Growth rate, </p>

<p>evaluated by immunofluorescence analysis in freshly isolated cell 
populations obtained from WT and PKCθ 
−/-muscle. As shown in 
Figure 4, the majority of the cells coexpressed all the markers ana-
lyzed, and no differences were detectable between the two geno-
types. Neither were the observed defects the result of differences in 
cell survival, because terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase dUTP 
nick end labeling (TUNEL) analysis revealed that the number of 
TUNEL-positive cells grown in growth medium (GM), among PKCθ </p>

<p>−/-</p>

<p>FIGURE 2: Lack of PKCθ impairs muscle regeneration in vivo. (A) Western blot analysis of total protein fractions from TA 
muscle at different periods of time after freeze injury in WT mice; the blot was incubated with the anti-phospho </p>

<p>Thr538 </p>

<p>PKCθ (p-PKCθ) and with the anti-PKCθ antibodies, as indicated; GAPDH level of expression was used for normalization. 
Representative experiment is shown (n = 3 per genotype). (B) Representative images of H&amp;E staining (a and b) of TA 
cryosections obtained from 2-mo-old WT (a) and PKCθ 
−/-(b) mice at day 7 after freeze injury (n ≥ 3 per genotype). 
Double immunofluorescence analysis (c and d) of TA muscle cryosections at day 7 after freeze injury for laminin (green) 
and eMyHC (red) expression in WT (c) and PKCθ 
−/-(d) (bar = 100 μm). Mean CSA of eMyHC-expressing (regenerating) 
myofibers in WT (black bar) and PKCθ 
−/-7 d after freeze injury (n = 3 per genotype; </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>p &lt; 0.001 vs. WT). (C) Western 
blot analysis of total protein fractions from WT and PKCθ 
−/-regenerating TA muscle 2, 4, and 7 d after freeze injury, as 
indicated. Representative blot from three independent experiments is shown (n = 3 per genotype at each time point); 
the blot was incubated with the α-Pax7, or -myogenin, or -eMyHC or -sarcomeric-MyHC (MyHC) antibodies, as 
indicated. GAPDH level of expression was used for normalization. Densitometric analysis is shown at the right. </p>

<p>Volume 22 April 15, 2011 </p>

<p>PKCθ and myoblast fusion | 1413 </p>

<p>evaluated in randomly selected clones (20 clones per genotype) as 
the number of cells per clone counted every 24 h during a 5-d 
culturing time period, also showed similar results in both geno-
types. Most of the clones derived from WT myoblasts, however, 
had formed elongated myotubes containing a large number of nu-
clei; in contrast, clones derived from PKCθ-null cells exhibited 
minimal fusion, similar to the nonclonally derived primary cultures 
(Figure 4B). </p>

<p>Lack of PKCθ prevents β1D integrin and caveolin-3 
up-regulation during myoblast differentiation </p>

<p>On the basis of these results, we thus analyzed the expression of 
factors regulating myogenesis, during in vitro differentiation of 
PKCθ-null myoblasts, as compared with WT. Similar to what was 
observed during regeneration in vivo, Western blot analysis re-
vealed that the expression of Pax7 was high in both PKCθ 
−/-and WT 
cells cultured in GM, as well as after 1 d in DM; after 2 d in DM, the 
expression of Pax7 was almost undetectable in both PKCθ 
−/-and 
WT cells (Figure 5A). In contrast, the expression of myogenin, fol-
lowing similar time-course kinetics in both genotypes, was lower in 
mutant cells with respect to WT cells, at all the time points consid-
ered (Figure 5A). Surprisingly, the expression level of muscle-specific 
genes, such as sarcomeric myosin, was similar in PKCθ 
−/-and WT 
differentiated cells (Figure 5A). In contrast, the expected up-regula-
tion of both β1D integrin and caveolin-3 expression, recently shown 
to be essential for myoblast fusion (Quach et al., 2009), observed in 
WT myoblasts after 1 d in DM, was significantly reduced in PKCθ </p>

<p>−/-</p>

<p>myoblasts To confirm the requirement of PKCθ for myoblast fusion 
using a different approach, primary myoblasts were prepared from a 
different mouse model, the mPKCθK/R mouse (Serra et al., 2003), in 
which the expression of a kinase dead mutant form of PKCθ cDNA 
is driven by the muscle-specific enhancer of the desmin promoter; 
thus the activity of PKCθ is selectively inhibited in differentiating 
myoblasts. mPKCθK/R myoblasts behaved similarly to the PKCθ </p>

<p>−/-</p>

<p>ones at the morphological level, giving rise to thin, oligonucleated 
myotubes in culture (unpublished data). Accordingly, the expression 
of β1D integrin and caveolin-3 was prevented at day 1 in DM, as 
compared with WT myoblasts (Figure 5B). At day 2 in DM, the ex-
pression level of β1D integrin and caveolin-3 in both PKCθ mutant 
cells was still reduced, although to a lesser extent, with respect to 
WT cells. </p>

<p>FIGURE 3: Lack of PKCθ inhibits myotube growth in vitro. 
(A) Western blot analysis of both cytosolic (Cy) and particulate 
(P) subcellular protein fractions of primary SCs derived from WT 
muscle cultured in GM or in DM for the indicated periods of time; the 
blot was incubated with the α-PKCθ antibody. Representative 
experiment is shown (n = 3 per genotype). Whole muscle protein 
lysate was used as positive control (+). Densitometric analysis is 
shown at the right. (B) Representative Wright staining (a and b) and 
immunofluorescence analysis of MyHC expression (c and d) of WT </p>

<p>(a and c)-and PKCθ 
−/-(b and d)-derived muscle SCs, cultured in DM 
for 48 h. Cells in c and d were counterstained with Hoechst; bar = 
100 μm. Bottom panel: fusion rate is shown at the left, determined as 
the percentage of nuclei included in myotubes (containing ≥ 3 nuclei), 
with respect to the total number of nuclei; the mean number of nuclei 
contained within each myotube is also shown at the right (WT = black 
bar; PKCθ 
−/-= gray bar). The data were collected from at least five 
independent experiments ( </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>p &lt; 0.001 vs. WT). (C) Representative 
z section images of immunofluorescence analysis of myofibers 
isolated from WT (a) or PKCθ 
−/-(b) EDL muscle, immunostained with 
the α-caveolin-3 antibody (red, used as sarcolemma marker). Nuclei 
were counterstained with TO-PRO-3; asterisks indicate myonuclei 
included within sarcolemma, arrows indicate nuclei of associated SCs, 
outside the sarcolemma. At least 10 myofibers per mouse were 
analyzed (n = 3 per genotype). Each myofiber was analyzed under 
confocal microscopy, and the number of myonuclei in each microfield 
was counted for the entire thickness of the myofiber, taking pictures 
every 5 μm z section (shown in Supplemental Figure S1). The mean 
number of nuclei and of SCs is shown at the bottom (WT, black bars; 
PKCθ </p>

<p>−/-</p>

<p>, gray bars). </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>FIGURE 4: Lack of PKCθ inhibits myoblast fusion. (A) Immunofluorescence analysis of freshly isolated cells derived from 
WT or PKCθ 
−/-hind limb muscle, as indicated. The cells were immunolabeled with the α-Pax7, -PW1, -MyoD, or -desmin 
antibodies, as indicated. (B) Representative microimages of TUNEL analysis in WT (a) and PKCθ 
−/-(b) muscle-derived 
cells cultured in GM. The number of TUNEL-positive nuclei divided by the total number of nuclei in WT (black bar) or 
PKCθ 
−/-(gray bar) is shown at the right (20 microfields per genotype, from three independent experiments). 
(C) Representative phase contrast images of clonally cultured muscle-derived SCs from WT (a) and PKCθ 
−/-(b) after 6 d 
in DM; c: cloning efficiency, expressed as the percentage of clones obtained divided by the total number of plated cells; 
d: growth rate, expressed as the mean fold increase in cell number within a single clone (15 clones per genotype); e: 
fusion index, expressed as the percentage of nuclei included in myotubes (containing ≥ 3 nuclei), with respect to the 
total number of nuclei, within a single clone cultured for 6 d in DM (20 clones per genotype); f: mean number of nuclei 
included in each myotube within a single clone cultured for 6 d in DM (20 clones per genotype). WT = black bar; 
PKCθ 
−/-= gray bar; </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>p &lt; 0.01 vs. WT. </p>

<p>PKCθ expression/activity is required for FAK 
phosphorylation </p>

<p>We then analyzed the expression and activation/phosphorylation 
level of FAK, an important nonreceptor protein tyrosine kinase in-</p>

<p>volved in integrin signaling, recently proposed as a key factor in 
myoblast fusion through its ability to regulate β1D integrin and ca-
veolin-3 expression (Quach et al., 2009). As shown in Figure 6A, 
Western blot and immunofluorescence analyses revealed that lack </p>

<p>Volume 22 April 15, 2011 </p>

<p>PKCθ and myoblast fusion | 1415 </p>

<p>of expression/activity of PKCθ significantly 
prevented FAK activation/phosphorylation 
during myoblast differentiation in vitro, as 
compared with WT myoblasts. To verify 
whether PKCθ signaling actually leads to 
FAK phosphorylation, a constitutively active 
mutant form of PKCθ (PKCθA/E; D'Andrea 
et al., 2006) was transfected in C2C12 cells 
(a mouse muscle cell line) cultured in GM. 
Parallel cultures were mock transfected. 
The ability of the exogenously expressed 
PKCθ mutant form to drive FAK phosphory-
lation was evaluated 16 h after transfection, 
by double immunofluorescence using the 
anti-phospho-FAK and the anti-PKCθ anti-
bodies. As shown in Figure 6B, a-d, whereas 
no p-FAK-positive or PKCθ-positive cells 
were detectable in mock-transfected cells, 
all the PKCθ-expressing cells, in PKCθA/E-
transfected cultures, coexpressed p-FAK. In 
parallel, another group of plates was pro-
cessed for immunoprecipitation using the 
anti-FAK antibody. The immunoprecipitate 
was then analyzed by Western blot for p-
FAK and for total FAK content. As shown in 
Figure 6B, increased FAK phosphorylation 
was observed in PKCθA/E-transfected cul-
tures compared with mock-transfected cul-
tures. To verify whether the observed de-
crease in FAK phosphorylation is the main 
event driving the phenotype, WT and 
PKCθ 
−/-primary muscle cells were cultured 
in the presence of the FAK inhibitor 14 
(Beierle et al., 2010), and both fusion rate 
and the number of nuclei per myotube 
were evaluated. As shown in Figure 6C, full 
FAK inhibition, by means of the inhibitor, 
strongly reduced fusion rate and number of 
nuclei per myotube in both WT and PKCθ </p>

<p>−/-</p>

<p>cultures to a similar extent. Moreover up-
regulation of both β1D integrin and caveo-
lin-3 was similarly prevented in both WT 
and PKCθ 
−/-treated cells (Figure 6D). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this article we demonstrate that the ex-
pression/activity of the θ isoform of PKCs 
is required for initial myoblast fusion events, 
but not for the induction of terminal </p>

<p>FIGURE 5: Lack of PKCθ expression or activity prevents up-regulation of caveolin-3 and 
β1D-integrin expression. (A) Western blot analysis of WT and PKCθ 
−/-muscle-derived SCs, 
cultured in GM, or for different periods of time in DM, as indicated. Representative experiment 
is shown of three independent experiments. The blot was incubated with the α-Pax7, 
α-myogenin, α-sarcomeric myosin heavy chain, α-caveolin-3, and α-β1D integrin antibodies. The 
level of expression of each protein in both genotypes, determined by densitometric analysis 
using the α-GAPDH antibody for normalization, is shown at the bottom; WT (♦), PKCθ 
−/-(). 
(B) Western blot analysis of WT and mPKCθK/R muscle-derived cells, cultured in GM, or for </p>

<p>different periods of time in DM, as indicated. 
The blot was incubated with the α-caveolin-3 
and α-β1D integrin antibodies. Densitometric 
analysis is shown at the bottom, WT (♦) 
and mPKCθK/R (), using the α-GAPDH 
antibody for normalization as in A ( </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>p &lt; 0.01, 
*p &lt; 0.05 vs. WT). When significant, 
reduction of expression in PKCθ 
−/-or in 
mPKCθK/R cells, expressed as percentage 
vs. WT (assumed as 100%) is also shown, 
resulting from at least three independent 
experiments. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>differentiation events. As first, lack of PKCθ 
in vivo resulted in reduced mice weight dur-
ing the first weeks of postnatal life. The ob-
served reduction was associated with reduc-
tion in both muscle mass and myofiber CSA. 
By 8-12 wk of postnatal life, both body 
weight and myofiber CSA in PKCθ 
−/-mice 
were similar to those in WT mice, suggest-
ing that lack of PKCθ delays the initial growth 
and building of the muscle mass. Indeed a 
reduction in lean muscle has previously 
been reported in PKCθ 
−/-mice with respect 
to WT (Gao et al., 2007). The fact that PKCθ 
is required for muscle growth is further sup-
ported by the observed delay in muscle re-
generation. Experimentally induced muscle 
regeneration is a valuable model to recapit-
ulate myofiber differentiation and growth. 
We show in this article that PKCθ expression 
was strongly up-regulated 4 d after injury, 
just during the phase of muscle rebuilding. 
This observation is consistent with a previ-
ously published study that showed that 
PKCθ activity increased significantly during 
the final phases of muscle regeneration in 
rat (Moraczewski et al., 2002). Indeed we 
show that lack of PKCθ delayed muscle re-
building after injury. The observed delay can 
be accounted for by impairment of the late 
phases of the growth/regeneration process. 
In fact, whereas no alteration in the expres-
sion of early markers of activated SCs, such 
as Pax7, was observed, full up-regulation of 
myogenin expression, an "executor" of 
myogenesis, was prevented, as well as the 
expression of the terminal differentiation 
marker of regenerating myofibers, eMyHC. 
More important, the size of regenerating 
myofibers, identified as eMyHC-positive 
myofibers, was significantly smaller in PKC </p>

<p>−/-</p>

<p>regenerating muscle than in time-matching 
regenerating WT muscle. Taken together, 
these observations demonstrate that, </p>

<p>FIGURE 6: PKCθ expression/activity is required for FAK phosphorylation. (A) Western blot 
analysis of WT, PKCθ </p>

<p>−/-</p>

<p>, and mPKCθK/R muscle-derived SCs, cultured in GM or for different 
periods of time in DM, as indicated. The blot was incubated with the α-FAK or with the 
α-phospho FAK antibodies. Representative experiment is shown of three independent 
experiments. Level of activation, determined by densitometric analysis as the phospho/total 
FAK ratio, is shown at the right. Representative immunofluorescence analysis of WT (a) or 
PKCθ 
−/-(b) muscle-derived cells cultured for 24 h in DM and incubated with the α-phospho FAK 
antibody is shown at the bottom. (B) Double immunofluorescence analysis of mock-transfected 
(a and b) or PKCθA/E-transfected (c and d) C2C12 cells using the α-PKCθ (red) and the α-pFAK 
(green) antibodies; e: Western blot analysis of mock-transfected or PKCθA/E-transfected C2C12 
cells immunoprecipitated with the α-FAK antibody and incubated with the α-pFAK or the α-FAK 
antibodies. Representative experiment is shown of three independent experiments. Level of 
activation was determined by densitometric analysis, as the phospho/total FAK ratio. </p>

<p>(C) Representative Wright staining of WT 
(a and c) or PKCθ 
−/-(b and d) muscle-derived 
primary cells cultured for 24 h in DM, in the 
absence (a and b) or presence (c and d) of the 
FAK inhibitor 14 (F14, 5 μM). Fusion rate, 
evaluated in each condition, is shown at the 
right, determined as the percentage of nuclei 
included in myotubes (containing ≥ 3 nuclei), 
with respect to the total number of nuclei; 
the mean number of nuclei contained within 
each myotube is also shown (WT = black 
bars; PKCθ 
−/-= gray bars). (D) Western blot 
analysis of the expression of caveolin-3 and 
β1D integrin in cells cultured as in C. 
Densitometric analysis is shown at the right; 
Red Ponceau staining of the membrane is 
shown to ensure equal loading. 
Representative experiment is shown of two 
independent experiments. </p>

<p>Volume 22 April 15, 2011 </p>

<p>PKCθ and myoblast fusion | 1417 </p>

<p>were analyzed. As we show here, PKCθ is poorly expressed in prolif-
erating myoblasts, but its expression is strongly up-regulated upon 
differentiation. Altogether, these observations suggest that, al-
though FAK activation is a common feature, different PKC isoforms 
can be involved in cell to extracellular matrix and in cell-to-cell inter-
actions, where different integrins are involved, and we show in the 
present study that activation of the θ isoform is indeed involved in 
FAK-mediated signaling leading to myoblast fusion. The fact that 
pharmacologically mediated full inhibition of FAK activity leads to 
similar fusion defects in both WT and PKCθ-null myoblasts further 
supports the hypothesis that the decreased FAK activation observed 
in PKCθ-null cells is sufficient to cause the phenotype. However, 
since no full FAK inhibition is observed in PKCθ-null myoblasts, other 
pathways might also contribute to FAK activation. 
Different from what was observed when FAK activity was inhibited 
(Quach et al., 2009), lack of PKCθ also prevented the full activation of 
myogenin. Indeed other pathways have been shown to be involved 
in "secondary fusion," such as calcineurin-dependent NFATc2 activa-
tion, leading to the production of IL-4 (Pavlath and Horsley, 2003), 
proposed as a profusion cytokine. It is worth noting that we and oth-
ers have shown that PKCθ is involved in many calcineurin-dependent 
signaling pathways, in both lymphocytes and myoblasts (Villunger  et al., 1999; Pfeifhofer et al., 2003; D'Andrea et al., 2006), suggest-
ing that it may be involved in multiple signaling pathways which 
ultimately lead to complete differentiation/fusion events. 
In conclusion, although the involvement of PKCθ in other path-
ways in regulating myoblast differentiation/fusion cannot be ruled 
out, we show in this article that it is indeed required for myoblast 
fusion, regulating FAK activation and, in turn, the expression of the 
profusion genes caveolin-3 and β1D integrin. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Animal models </p>

<p>PKCθ 
−/-mice were provided by Dan Littman (New York University, 
New York). In these mice, the gene encoding PKCθ was inactivated 
in all cells of the body, as previously described (Sun et al., 2000). 
mPKCθ-K/R transgenic mice express a PKCθ kinase dead mu-
tant form, which acts as dominant negative, specifically in muscle, as 
previously described (Serra et al., 2003). The animals were housed 
in the Histology Department-accredited animal facility. All the pro-
cedures were approved by the Italian Ministry for Health and were 
conducted according to the U.S. National Institutes of Health (NIH) 
guidelines. </p>

<p>Experimentally induced muscle regeneration </p>

<p>To induce freeze injury, a steel probe precooled in dry ice was ap-
plied to the TA muscle belly of anesthetized adult (8-12 wk old) 
male mice for 10 s. TA muscles were isolated at different time points 
after the injury, as specifically indicated. Uninjured, age-matched 
animals were used as controls. </p>

<p>Antibodies and reagents </p>

<p>The following primary antibodies were used: anti-PKCθ and anti-
phospho 
Thr538 PKCθ rabbit polyclonal antibodies, anti-caveolin-3 
and anti-MyoD mouse monoclonal antibodies (mAbs; BD Biosci-
ences, San Diego, CA); anti-desmin mouse mAb (Dako, Glostrup, 
Denmark); anti-myosin heavy chain MF20, anti-eMyHC F1.652, 
anti-Pax7, and anti-myogenin F5D mouse mAbs (Developmental 
Studies Hybridoma Bank, Iowa City, IA); rabbit polyclonal anti-PW1 
(provided by D.A. Sassoon; Mitchell et al., 2010); anti-β1D integrin 
(provided by G. Tarone; Belkin et al., 1996); and anti-FAK and 
anti-phospho 
Tyr397 FAK antibodies (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa </p>

<p>although SC activation and differentiation are not altered in PKCq </p>

<p>−/-</p>

<p>, 
further addition of fusing cells to regenerating myofibers (a process 
known as "secondary fusion") is, instead, prevented. Thus PKCθ ex-
pression/activity is required for the "resolution" of the SCs differen-
tiation program during the late phases of regeneration, when myo-
blast fusion is required. 
Accordingly, we show that PKCθ expression and activity were 
strongly induced in cultured muscle-derived cells within a few hours 
in DM, and inhibition of its expression (in PKCθ 
−/-muscle-derived 
cells) or activity (in mPKCθK/R muscle-derived cells) significantly re-
duced fusion index and myonuclei content, as compared with WT 
cells. This defect was actually dependent on a defect in the fusion 
process itself, because no differences in the nature of the cell popu-
lations obtained from the different genotypes were observed, and, 
when cells were clonally cultured, no differences in cell proliferation 
or in cell death were observed. Indeed single clones from PKCθ </p>

<p>−/-</p>

<p>muscle-derived cells still gave rise to thinner, oligonucleated myo-
tubes, as compared with clones derived from WT cells. Taken to-
gether, these results demonstrate that PKCθ plays a critical role in 
myoblast fusion and myofiber growth, which can be referred to as 
"secondary fusion." This conclusion is further strengthened by the 
observation that the number of nuclei in PKCθ 
−/-freshly isolated 
myofibers was lower than that in WT ones, suggesting that similar 
alterations are occurring in vivo as well. Many factors have been 
shown to be implicated in myoblast fusion, including components 
of the extracellular matrix remodeling, such as matrix metalloprotei-
nase (MMP)-2 and MMP-9 (Lluri and Jaworski, 2005; Lluri et al.,  2008); cell surface molecules, such as NCAM, N-and M-cadherins, 
a disintegrin and metalloproteinase 12, β1 integrins, and caveolin-3 
(Galbiati et al., 1999; Abmayr et al., 2003; Gullberg, 2003; Horsley  and Pavlath, 2004); or even cytokines, such as interleukin 4 (IL-4; 
Horsley et al., 2003). Whereas the activity of MMP-2 and -9 was not 
altered by ablation of PKCθ expression/activity (our unpublished ob-
servations), we show in this article that the up-regulation of β1D in-
tegrin and of caveolin-3 upon differentiation was significantly pre-
vented. Thus PKCθ activity appears to be involved in signaling 
pathways regulating the expression of molecules involved in myo-
blast fusion. To date, a clear picture of these pathways is not de-
picted yet; however, full activation of caveolin-3 and β1D integrin 
expression has been recently shown to be required for "secondary 
fusion" and dependent on FAK activation (Quach et al., 2009). In-
deed full FAK phosphorylation was prevented when PKCθ expres-
sion/activity was ablated in differentiating myoblasts, by either 
knocking the gene out or by expressing a dominant-negative mu-
tant form. Accordingly, when a constitutively active PKCθ mutant 
form was exogenously expressed in cultured muscle cells, FAK 
phosphorylation was induced, demonstrating that PKCθ, either di-
rectly or indirectly, is involved in FAK activation. Several studies have 
indicated that PKC activation is required for FAK phosphorylation in 
cell-to-extracellular-matrix adhesion events and that they colocalize 
at focal adhesion sites (Vuori and Ruoslahti, 1993; Haimovich et al.,  1996; Disatnik and Rando, 1999). The precise functional relationship 
between these two kinases, however, is not completely understood 
yet. It has been previously shown that, during muscle cell adhesion 
and spreading, integrin engagement leads to FAK phosphorylation 
via a PKC-dependent signaling pathway (Disatnik and Rando, 1999); 
among the PKC isoforms analyzed, sequential activation of PKCε, 
-α, and -δ has been shown to be necessary to promote muscle cell 
spreading (Disatnik et al., 2002). It is worth noting that in those stud-
ies no PKCθ expression was detected; thus its involvement in those 
events was ruled out. Indeed those studies were carried out using 
proliferating muscle cells, because cell adhesion and spreading </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank D.A. Littman, New York University, New York, for provid-
ing the mutant mice; G. Tarone, University of Turin, Italy, for the 
α-β1D integrin antibody; D.A. Sassoon, Myology Group, Université 
Paris VI/Pierre et Marie Curie, Paris, France, for the α-PW1 antibody; 
and G. Baier, University of Innsbruck, Innsbruck, Austria, for the </p>

<p>myotube was also determined. Approximately 100 myotubes were 
counted per dish. </p>

<p>Cell death assay </p>

<p>Cell apoptosis was determined by TUNEL reaction (Roche Ap-
plied Science, Indianapolis, IN). At the indicated time intervals, 
cells were fixed, incubated for 1 h at 37°C with the TUNEL mix-
ture, and processed following the manufacturer's instructions. 
Nuclei were counterstained with Hoechst 33342 (Fluka). Positive 
nuclei were detected under an epifluorescence Zeiss Axioskop 
2 Plus microscope. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis and immunoprecipitation </p>

<p>For the total protein extract preparation, tissue samples or cell pel-
lets were homogenized in ice-cold buffer (H-buffer) containing 
20 mM Tris (pH 7.5), 2 mM EDTA, 2 mM EGTA, 250 mM sucrose, 
5 mM dithiothreitol, leupeptin at 200 mg/ml, Aprotinin at 10 mg/ml, 
1 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride, and 0.1% Triton X-100 (all from 
Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO), as previously described 
(Zappelli et al., 1996). The obtained homogenate was disrupted by 
sonication, incubated for 30 min on ice with repeated vortexing, 
and then centrifuged at 15,000 × g for 15 min. The pellet was dis-
carded, and the supernatant was used for Western blot analysis. For 
the preparation of subcellular protein fractions, the cell pellet was 
homogenized in H-buffer lacking Triton X-100, and incubated 
30 min on ice. Samples were then spun at 100,000 × g for 30 min at 
4°C. The supernatant was saved as cytosolic fraction, and the re-
maining pellet was suspended in H-buffer containing 0.1% Triton 
X-100, and incubated for 30 min on ice. At the end, the samples 
were spun at 100,000 × g for 30 min at 4°C, and the remaining su-
pernatant was saved as the particulate fraction. An equal amount of 
protein from each sample was loaded onto 10% SDS-polyacrylam-
ide gels and transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane (Schleicher &amp;  Schuell, Dassel, Germany). The membranes were then incubated 
with the appropriate primary antibodies. Alkaline phosphatase 
(ALP)-conjugated goat anti-mouse IgG (Roche Applied Science) or 
ALP-conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG (Zymed Laboratories, South 
San Francisco, CA) were used as secondary antibodies, and immu-
noreactive bands were detected using CDP-STAR solution (Roche 
Applied Science), according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
Densitometric analysis was performed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Aida</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">2.1</rs> Image soft-
ware (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Raytest</rs>, Straubenhardt, Germany). 
For immunoprecipitation, cell lysate was incubated with the anti-
FAK antibody (1 μg/100 μl of lysate) overnight at 4°C. At the end of 
incubation, 20 μl of protein-A agarose (Santa Cruz Biotechnology) 
was added and incubated for an additional 3 h at 4°C. The immuno-
precipitate was then collected by centrifugation and washed three 
times with H-buffer, and the final pellet was used for Western blot 
analysis. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Quantitative data are presented as means ± SD of at least three ex-
periments. Statistical analysis to determine significance was per-
formed using paired Student's t tests. Differences were considered 
to be statistically significant at the p &lt; 0.05 level. </p>

<p>Cruz, CA). To pharmacologically inhibit FAK, FAK inhibitor 14 (Santa 
Cruz Biotechnology) was used. </p>

<p>Muscle cell culture and cell transfections </p>

<p>Primary cultures were prepared from total limb muscles of WT, 
PKCθ 
−/− , or mPKC-K/R mice, as previously described (Castaldi  et al., 2007). Muscle-derived cells were grown on collagen-coated 
dishes, in GM (DMEM containing 20% horse serum, HS, 3% chick 
embryo extract, EE, all from Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) in a hu-
midified 5% CO 2 atmosphere at 37°C. Differentiation was in-
duced by replacing the medium with medium containing lower 
serum and EE concentration, DM (DMEM containing 5% HS, 
0.75% EE). C2C12 cells, a mouse SC-derived cell line (D'Andrea  et al., 2006), were grown in DMEM supplemented with 10% fetal 
calf serum. For transient transfection assays, 10 
5 C2C12 cells were 
plated on 35-mm tissue culture dishes. After 24 h, proliferating 
myoblasts were transfected with a total of 1.5 μg of plasmid DNA/ 
dish, using the lipid-based Lipofectamine reagent (Invitrogen), 
according to the manufacturer's instructions. After an additional 
16 h, the cells were either fixed for immunofluorescence analysis 
or disrupted for immunoprecipitation and Western blot analysis. 
The expression plasmids encoding the constitutively active mu-
tant form of PKCθ cDNA, PKCθ A/E (provided by G. Baier) 
(Villunger et al., 1999), was used for transfections. The expression 
plasmid lacking cDNA was used for mock transfections. </p>

<p>Myofiber isolation </p>

<p>Two-month-old male WT and PKCθ 
−/-mice were killed by cervical 
dislocation, and the EDL muscles were carefully dissected. Muscles 
were digested in 0.2% collagenase type 1/DMEM (Sigma, St. Louis, 
MO); individual myofibers were dissociated by gently passing 
through Pasteur pipettes with different size apertures and then 
abundantly washed, as described (Aulino et al., 2010; White et al.,  2010). Intact myofibers with tapered/sculptured ends were se-
lected for fixation in 4% paraformaldehyde/phosphate-buffered 
saline (Sigma) for 6-10 min and processed for immunofluorescence 
analysis. </p>

<p>Histological and immunofluorescence analyses </p>

<p>Muscle cryosections were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde (Sigma-
Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) on ice, and cultured cells were fixed in etha-
nol/acetone (1:1 [vol/vol] ratio) at -20°C for 20 min. For histological 
analysis, muscle cryosections were stained with hematoxylin and eo-
sin (H&amp;E) solution (Sigma-Aldrich), and cultured cells with Wright's 
solution (Fluka, Milwaukee, WI). The muscle fiber mean CSA was 
determined by measuring the CSA of all fibers in the entire section, 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Scion Image</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4.0.3.2</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">NIH</rs>, Bethesda, MD). Immuno-
fluorescence analysis of cells, cryosections, or isolated myofibers 
was performed as previously described (Castaldi et al., 2007; Aulino  et al., 2010). Nuclei were counterstained with Hoechst 33342 (Fluka) 
or with TO-PRO-3 (Invitrogen), and the samples were analyzed un-
der an epifluorescence Zeiss Axioskop 2 Plus microscope (Carl Zeiss, 
Oberkochen, Germany) or a Leica Leitz DMRB microscope fitted 
with a DFC300FX camera (Leica, Wetzlar, Germany). </p>

<p>Fusion assay </p>

<p>After different periods of time in DM, cells were either stained with 
Wright's solution or immunostained with the anti-myosin heavy 
chain antibody MF20. Myotubes were defined as cells containing 
three or more nuclei. The fusion rate was determined as the per-
centage of nuclei in myotubes compared with the total number of 
nuclei in the field. The mean number of nuclei contained within each </p>

<p>Volume 22 April 15, 2011 </p>

<p>PKCθ and myoblast fusion | 1419 </p>



</text></tei>