<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3927753" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>One of the strategies to repair and regenerate damaged or 
diseased soft tissues is extracellular matrix (ECM)-induced 
in situ tissue formation that leads to the restoration and 
improvement of functions of affected tissues and organs. 
The pathway involves ECM preparation, implantation, host 
cell repopulation, revascularization, and remodeling of 
ECM scaffold. ECM scaffolds contain many structural pro-
teins with proper extracellular architecture, and signaling 
molecules such as fibronectin, integrins, laminin, and 
sequestered growth factors. The implanted ECM scaffold 
provides biomechanical support and can elicit new tissue 
formation by interacting with host cells to modulate cell 
behaviors such as adhesion, migration, proliferation, and </p>

<p>differentiation, as well as to modulate inflammatory 
responses and remodeling of ECM scaffolds. 1-6 Presently, 
about 30 tissue-derived scaffold products have received 
approval from United States and European regulatory </p>

<p>Process-induced extracellular matrix 
alterations affect the mechanisms of 
soft tissue repair and regeneration </p>

<p>Wendell Q Sun 1,2 , Hui Xu 2 , Maryellen Sandor 2 
and Jared Lombardi 2 </p>

<p>Abstract 
Extracellular matrices derived from animal tissues for human tissue repairs are processed by various methods of 
physical, chemical, or enzymatic decellularization, viral inactivation, and terminal sterilization. The mechanisms of action 
in tissue repair vary among bioscaffolds and are suggested to be associated with process-induced extracellular matrix 
modifications. We compared three non-cross-linked, commercially available extracellular matrix scaffolds (Strattice, 
Veritas, and XenMatrix), and correlated extracellular matrix alterations to in vivo biological responses upon implantation 
in non-human primates. Structural evaluation showed significant differences in retaining native tissue extracellular 
matrix histology and ultrastructural features among bioscaffolds. Tissue processing may cause both the condensation of 
collagen fibers and fragmentation or separation of collagen bundles. Calorimetric analysis showed significant differences 
in the stability of bioscaffolds. The intrinsic denaturation temperature was measured to be 51°C, 38°C, and 44°C for 
Strattice, Veritas, and XenMatrix, respectively, demonstrating more extracellular matrix modifications in the Veritas and 
XenMatrix scaffolds. Consequently, the susceptibility to collagenase degradation was increased in Veritas and XenMatrix 
when compared to their respective source tissues. Using a non-human primate model, three bioscaffolds were found 
to elicit different biological responses, have distinct mechanisms of action, and yield various outcomes of tissue repair. 
Strattice permitted cell repopulation and was remodeled over 6 months. Veritas was unstable at body temperature, 
resulting in rapid absorption with moderate inflammation. XenMatrix caused severe inflammation and sustained immune 
reactions. This study demonstrates that extracellular matrix alterations significantly affect biological responses in soft 
tissue repair and regeneration. The data offer useful insights into the rational design of extracellular matrix products and 
bioscaffolds of tissue engineering. </p>

<p>Keywords 
Biological scaffold, extracellular matrix, decellularization, matrix remodeling, soft tissue regeneration, bovine 
pericardium, porcine dermis, tissue engineering </p>

<p>1 Institute of Biomedical Technology, School of Medical Instruments and 
Food Engineering, University of Shanghai for Science and Technology, 
Shanghai, China 
2 LifeCell Corporation, Bridgewater, NJ, USA </p>

<p>Corresponding author: 
Wendell Q Sun, School of Medical Instruments and Food Engineering, 
University of Shanghai for Science and Technology, Shanghai 200093, China. 
Email: Wendell.q.sun@gmail.com </p>

<p>505305T EJ0010.1177/2041731413505305Journal of Tissue EngineeringSun et al. </p>

<p>2013 </p>

<p>Article </p>



<p>Journal of Tissue Engineering </p>

<p>authorities, and are marketed for various clinical applica-
tions in tissue repair and regeneration, 3,7-9 with 2011 US sales 
alone exceeding US$1 billion. 10 These scaffolds are derived 
from a variety of human and mammalian tissues, including 
blood vessel, heart valve, ligament, nerve, skin, small intesti-
nal submucosa, forestomach, pericardium, peritoneum, ten-
dons, and urinary bladder. ECM-based scaffolds are the first 
wave of commercially available products for tissue engineer-
ing and regenerative medicine, and have achieved considera-
ble success satisfying unmet clinical needs. This approach has 
been used to reconstruct and to repair increasingly more com-
plex tissues and organs in human patients, 11,12 and may be a 
promising platform for engineering whole functional organs 
by using in vitro recelluarization and matrix remodeling with 
autologous stem cells or differentiated cells. 13 
When an ECM scaffold is derived from donated human 
or other mammalian tissues, the native ECM is subjected to 
biochemical and structural alterations during processing 
that involves chemical, enzymatic, or physical decellulari-
zation, antigenicity reduction treatment, viral inactivation, 
and terminal sterilization. Different processing methods are 
known to yield ECM materials with different structural and 
biological properties. 9,14-18 Preclinical and clinical evi-
dences demonstrate that not all biologically derived scaf-
folds are equal and that host responses in tissue regeneration 
vary among scaffold products. 8,19-26 The variation of perfor-
mance in tissue repair and regeneration among scaffolds is 
presumably due to different tissue sources, the presence of 
undesirable cellular and matrix elements, and matrix dam-
age or modifications upon tissue processing. 2,7,9,15,20,22,23,26-28 
However, there are no generally accepted performance 
specifications for biological scaffolds, and little information 
is available about ECM modifications among commercially 
available scaffold products. How the process-induced ECM 
modifications affect the mechanisms of action in tissue 
repair remains poorly understood. 
To gain insight into the rational design of tissue engineer-
ing scaffolds, this study has examined ECM modifications 
in three non-cross-linked, commercially available scaffolds 
(Strattice ™ reconstructive tissue matrix, Veritas ® collagen 
matrix, and XenMatrix ™ surgical graft). It aims to correlate 
the comparative differences in ECM modifications among 
three scaffolds to biological responses in tissue repair and 
regeneration after implantation in a primate model. The 
comparative investigation of commercially available scaf-
folds may offer valuable biochemical and structural insights 
into the rational design of tissue engineering scaffolds. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>Ethics statements </p>

<p>A part of the research project involves the use of non-
human primate subjects. The non-human primate study 
was performed in strict compliance with the recommenda-
tions in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory </p>

<p>Animals of the National Institutes of Health, and all 
appropriate parts of the Animal Welfare Act of 1966 (P.L. 
89-544), as amended by the Animal Welfare Act of 1970 
(P.L. 91-579) and the 1976 amendments to the Animal 
Welfare Act (P.L. 94-279)-9 Code of Federal Regulations 
(CFR) Chapter I (1 January 1998 edition) as well as the 
International Guiding Principles for Biomedical Research 
Involving Animals developed by the Council for 
International Organizations of Medical Sciences and the 
following guidelines for animal welfare. The study proto-
col was reviewed and approved by the Institutional Animal 
Care and Use Committee (IACUC), the Behavioral 
Sciences Foundation (St Kitts, Eastern Caribbean). The 
research facility of the Behavioral Sciences Foundation is 
accredited by the Canadian Council for Animal Care and 
has a Public Health Service (PHS)-approved Animal 
Welfare Assurance (A5535-01) issued by the Office of 
Laboratory Animal Welfare (OLAW). </p>

<p>Tissue-based biological scaffolds </p>

<p>Strattice reconstructive tissue matrix (LifeCell Corporation, 
Branchburg, NJ) is derived from porcine dermis with a pro-
cess that removes cellular elements and reduces α-gal 
epitope in ECM via enzymatic cleavage. Viral reduction 
and e-beam irradiation are applied to yield a sterile scaffold 
that retains structural and biochemical integrity of porcine 
dermis ECM. 22,29 Veritas collagen matrix (Synovis Life 
Technologies, St Paul, MN) is derived from bovine pericar-
dium. Pericardium is decellularized and exposed to 1.0 N 
sodium hydroxide to eliminate bovine spongiform enceph-
alopathy (BSE) transmission. The decellularized pericar-
dium is then treated with propylene oxide for capping 
primary amine groups to reduce immunogenicity. Veritas is 
terminally sterilized by e-beam irradiation. 30-32 XenMatrix 
surgical graft (Davol, Inc., Warwick, RI) is also derived 
from porcine dermis, which is treated by a proprietary pro-
cessing technology to achieve an open matrix structure 
designed to encourage cell repopulation and minimize 
encapsulation by fibrotic tissue. 33 The XenMatrix process 
involves (a) freezing, thawing, and bleaching of porcine 
dermis to loosen the collagen matrix; (b) removing non-
collagenous elements; and (c) treating with sodium hydrox-
ide solution and hydrogen peroxide solution to improve 
biocompatibility. 34 XenMatrix graft is sterilized by e-beam 
irradiation. All three products are packaged in the hydrated 
state, and labeled as being non-cross-linked and stable for 
room temperature storage. These scaffolds are increasingly 
utilized to support soft tissue regeneration, including appli-
cations in hernia repairs, and urological, gynecological, and 
breast reconstruction surgeries. 8,35-37 </p>

<p>Minimally processed ECM materials </p>

<p>To evaluate the extent of ECM modifications in commercially 
available scaffolds, minimally processed porcine dermis </p>

<p>Sun et al. </p>



<p>ECM (pd-ECM) and bovine pericardium ECM (bp-ECM) 
were derived from freshly slaughtered animals to serve as con-
trols. Porcine skin from 6-month-old animals and bovine peri-
cardium from 18-to 24-month-old animals were cleaned 
manually to remove hairs, epidermis, and adipose tissue. 
Isolated dermis (˜1.0 mm thick) and pericardium (˜0.4-0.7 
mm thick) were aseptically decellularized in 2% (w/v) sodium 
deoxycholate in 20 mM 4-(2-hydroxyethyl)-1-pipera-
zineethanesulfonic acid (HEPES) (pH 8.0) containing 10 mM 
ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA). Decellularization 
was carried out with gentle agitation for 8 h at 22°C-24°C, and 
decellularized ECMs were washed in Dulbecco's phosphate-
buffered saline (PBS; pH 7.2) three times over a period of 18 
h. The minimally processed tissue ECMs were temporarily 
stored in PBS at 4°C, and were used for testing within a week. </p>

<p>Histological and scanning electron 
microscopic evaluation </p>

<p>For histological analysis, samples of ECM materials were 
rinsed in 0.9% saline for 1 h before fixation in 10% buffered 
formalin solution. Samples were routinely processed through 
dehydration, embedment in paraffin, and sectioning. Tissue 
slices were stained with hematoxylin-eosin (H&amp;E) stain. For 
scanning electron microscope (SEM) evaluation, tissue sam-
ples were fixed in 2% glutaraldehyde, cut to the desired size, 
and dehydrated through a series of ethanol solutions with 
increasing concentrations from 50% to 100%. Specimens in 
100% ethanol were gradually changed to 100% hexamethyl-
disilazane for drying. Dried specimens were mounted and 
coated with gold palladium under vacuum (&lt;8 Pa) for 120 s. 
The microstructures of samples were viewed, and micro-
graphs were captured using a desktop SEM (NeoScope 
JCM-5000; Jeol Ltd, Tokyo, Japan) at 10 kV. </p>

<p>Calorimetric analysis </p>

<p>Samples of ECM materials were rinsed in Dulbecco's PBS 
(pH 7.4). Samples (25-30 mg) were hermetically sealed in 
aluminum crucibles. Thermograms were recorded using dif-
ferential scanning calorimeter (Model Q2000; TA Instruments, 
New Castle, DE) from 2°C to 125°C at various heating rates 
between 0.02°C/min and 50°C/min. After calorimetric meas-
urement, small holes were punched on sealed crucibles with a 
pin, and the dry mass of samples was measured after dehydra-
tion between 105°C and 110°C under vacuum overnight. 
Thermograms were analyzed using the software <rs id="software-0" type="software">Universal 
Analysis 2000</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 4.5</rs>) to determine the onset tempera-
ture (T d ) and enthalpy (ΔΗ) of collagen denaturation. </p>

<p>Collagenase susceptibility assay </p>

<p>The susceptibility of ECM materials to type I collagenase 
(Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO) was tested at 37°C in vitro. 
Samples were rinsed in 0.9% saline, 60-80 mg material 
was placed in 2.0-mL Eppendorf tubes, and 1.5 mL of </p>

<p>pre-warmed 10 mM Tris-HCl buffer containing 2 mM 
CaCl 2 (pH 7.5) was added to each sample. Collagenase was 
added to the sample in a final enzymic activity of 100 units/mL 
for digestion at 37°C for up to 16 h. After digestion, sam-
ples were centrifuged, washed with distilled water, and 
freeze-dried. The resistance of tissue matrix to collagenase 
digestion was determined according to the dry mass of 
remaining tissue. </p>

<p>In vivo biological response study with non-
human primates </p>

<p>The study was performed in strict compliance with the rec-
ommendations in the Guide for the Care and Use of 
Laboratory Animals of the National Institutes of Health and 
other appropriated laws, as listed in the ethics statement 
above. The surgical procedure of abdominal wall repair 
according to Xu et al., 21 and the study protocol were approved 
by the IACUC, the Behavioral Sciences Foundation (St 
Kitts, Eastern Caribbean). All procedures used in this study, 
including surgical procedure, housing conditions, feeding 
regimens, and environmental enrichment, have been 
designed to alleviate suffering and to avoid discomfort, dis-
tress, and pain to the animals. Monkeys were housed at the 
test facility in a way such that they maintained visual con-
tact with other monkeys at all times, and kept outdoors in 
individual American Association for Accreditation of 
Laboratory Animal Care (AAALAC)-approved cages, pro-
tected from weather extremes and subject to the normal 
temperature and humidity levels to which the monkeys 
were accustomed in order to decrease external stress fac-
tors. They were fed with 20% Harlan 2050 (Harlan 
Laboratories, Indianopolis, IN) Teklad Global 20% Protein 
Primate Diet supplemented with fresh fruits and vegeta-
bles. Water was provided ad libitum via water bottles. 
Cages were cleaned and maintained on a daily basis per 
standard procedure at the animal care facility. The monkeys 
were monitored by the technical staff for any conditions 
requiring possible veterinary care. Animals selected for 
surgery received supplements for enrichment such as pro-
duce treats and bamboo branches. Tactile and sensory 
enrichment was provided in the form of puzzle feeders, 
which rotated around the colony. Any aspects of this study 
that might cause more than momentary or slight pain or 
distress to the animals was performed with appropriate sed-
atives, analgesics, or anesthetics. Animals that experienced 
severe or chronic pain or distress that could not be relieved 
were painlessly euthanized as deemed appropriate by the 
test facility's veterinarian. Additional detailed information 
has been provided as supplemental support information. 
Adult male vervet monkeys (Chlorocebus aethiops), 
3-6 kg, were screened for general health, and quarantined 
for 2 weeks before surgery. The monkeys were fasted for 
24 h prior to the surgical procedure, and each animal was 
given an injection of ketamine HCl 40-60 mg intramuscu-
larly (IM) as a pre-anesthetic to allow the technician to </p>



<p>Journal of Tissue Engineering </p>

<p>safely handle the monkey prior to transportation to the pro-
cedure room. Each monkey received an injection of cefazo-
lin sodium 125 mg IM (antibiotics) on the day of surgery. 
An intravenous (IV) catheter was placed in the monkey in 
order to provide access for IV fluids, which was maintained 
at a slow drip rate to keep the IV catheter patent and to 
assist flushing the line following IV injections. Just prior to 
the final preparation of the surgical site, the animal was 
given a combination of ketamine (10 mg/kg) and xylazine 
(1 mg/kg) IM. Additional ketamine/xylazine was given as 
needed throughout the procedure to maintain proper levels 
of anesthesia. For surgical implantation of a test material, a 
3 cm × 7 cm full-thickness defect was created in the abdom-
inal wall by removing the fascia, rectus muscle, and perito-
neum. The defect was repaired with a test scaffold by tissue 
approximation to the defect edge and fixation using 3-0 
polypropylene sutures. The area was draped using sterile 
drapes. Following the procedure, the monkeys were 
allowed to recover under the observation of a staff member, 
and were treated as necessary in order to assure a complete 
and uncomplicated recovery. Monkeys also received the 
analgesic drug flunixin meglumine at approximately 2.0-
5.0 mg/kg IM or buprenorphine at 0.01 mg/kg subcutane-
ously (SC) or IM either prior to the surgical procedure or 
immediately following surgery. Additional administration 
was allowed twice daily for 3 days or longer depending on 
signs of pain as determined by the facility veterinarian. 
Strattice, Veritas, and XenMatrix were investigated at 1-, 
3-, and 6-month time points, with three animals euthanized 
for each test material per time point. The gross assessment 
of repairs was made for herniation or bulging in animals 
over the course of implantation. On the day of termination, 
the monkeys were given an injection of ketamine HCl 40-
60 mg IM to allow the technician to safely handle the mon-
key prior to transportation to the necropsy room. Additional 
ketamine was given as needed throughout the procedure to 
maintain proper levels of anesthesia while drawing blood 
and performing the pre-explantation physical exam. After 
animals were sacrificed, explanted grafts were examined for 
scaffold integration with adjacent host tissue, and the pos-
sible presence of graft defect or hardening. The sizes of 
explanted scaffolds were measured, and percentage of graft 
contraction after implantation was calculated. Explanted 
samples were fixed in 10% buffered formalin solution for 
histological analysis as described earlier. Tissue sections 
from the center and interface of each graft material were 
stained with H&amp;E. Histological evaluation was done by 
blinded assessment for host cell infiltration, revasculariza-
tion, inflammatory response, and collagen remodeling. </p>

<p>Antibody determination after material 
implantation </p>

<p>Blood samples were taken after implantation at various time 
points up to 6 months. Serum was tested for the presence of </p>

<p>elevated antibodies reacting to implanted scaffolds (immu-
noglobulin G, IgG). Pre-implant samples were rinsed with 
0.9% saline, freeze-dried, and micronized using a cryo-mill 
with liquid nitrogen. Micronized tissue powder was sus-
pended in PBS, which was used to coat Immulon 96-well 
polystyrene microtiter plates (Thermo Fisher Scientific, 
Waltham, MA) by air-drying overnight. Serial dilutions of 
serum samples were incubated in the coated microtiter 
wells for 2 h. Plates were then washed and incubated for 1 
h with goat anti-human IgG conjugated to alkaline phos-
phatase. Plates were rinsed and incubated with p-nitrophe-
nyl phosphate substrate for 1 h for detection. Reaction 
product was measured at 405 nm in a plate reader, and the 
increase in antibody titer was determined according to the 
serial dilution curve. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Structural differences in scaffolds </p>

<p>The matrix structures of three scaffolds vary significantly 
(Figure 1). Both Strattice and XenMatrix are derived from 
porcine dermis with proprietary processing technologies. 
On histological examination as compared with unprocessed 
porcine dermis (supplemental Figure S1), the structural 
integrity of native dermis ECM is retained in Strattice with 
a uniform architecture of intact collagen bundle structures 
and the absence of cells. XenMatrix comprises an altered 
dermal matrix that shows structural dissimilarity from 
native dermal ECM. Collagen bundles in XenMatrix are 
fragmented and largely separated. The matrix of pericar-
dium-derived Veritas has a diffuse appearance that lacks the 
well-defined structural features in unprocessed pericardial 
ECM. On SEM examination, micrographs reveal more 
microscopic structural differences among the three scaf-
folds (Figure 2). Strattice appears as a tightly intertwined 
and/or interwoven scaffold of collagen bundles, the fibrillar 
ultra-structures of which are preserved at fibril and fiber 
levels. Large pores over 50 µm are few between collagen 
bundles, and are mostly void spaces of blood vessels or 
removed hair follicles. XenMatrix does not show the archi-
tecture of porcine dermal ECM. Collagen fibrils and fibers 
in XenMatrix are fused together, leading to the complete 
loss of fibrillar ultra-structures of collagen bundles. 
Collagen bundles of XenMatrix are condensed, resulting in 
the formation of many large pores within the matrix. Veritas 
shows a very loose scaffold of collagen bundles, and large 
pores over 50 µm are abundant. The fibrillar ultra-struc-
tures of collagen bundles in Veritas are also preserved at 
fibril and fiber levels. </p>

<p>Differences in calorimetric characteristics </p>

<p>The DSC thermogram of fresh porcine dermis consists of 
multiple overlapping endothermic peaks between 20°C and </p>

<p>Sun et al. </p>



<p>120°C (Figure 3). Upon heating at a scan rate of 3°C/min, 
protein denaturation starts at 54.0°C ± 0.2°C, and the event 
ends when temperature reaches around 90°C, with a total 
enthalpic value of 54.8 ± 2.4 J/g (n = 9). The complex ther-
mogram of unprocessed porcine dermis consists of three 
separate denaturation events (Peaks A, B, and C), which 
account for 16.7% ± 3.0%, 41.1% ± 4.8%, and 42.2% ± 
4.0%, respectively (supplemental Figure S2). Peak A disap-
pears after cell lysis and washing in saline or PBS. The pd-
ECM retains Peaks B and C, without any change in their 
onset and peak temperatures. The DSC thermogram of 
fresh bovine pericardium starts at a much higher tempera-
ture, 63.0°C ± 0.5°C, with a smaller enthalpic value of 45.6 
± 4.4 J/g (n = 10) (Figure 3). It appears that the thermogram 
of bovine pericardium consists of only Peaks B and C 
between 20°C and 120°C, and Peak A in the lower tempera-
ture region is insignificant. The minimally processed 
bovine pericardial ECM has essentially the same DSC ther-
mogram as fresh bovine pericardium (data not shown). 
Commercially available scaffolds have calorimetric 
thermograms that are different from those of </p>

<p>their respective unprocessed and/or minimally processed 
materials (Figure 4). Thermograms of these scaffolds con-
sist of two denaturation peaks, one with a peak width of 
about 10°C followed by a very broad peak with a width 
about 40°C. For Strattice and XenMatrix, Peak A is no 
longer present in finished scaffolds. Peaks B and C at the 
higher temperature region are still retained in finished scaf-
folds; however, the changes in denaturation temperature 
and curve shape (as compared to unprocessed dermis and 
minimally processed dermis) have demonstrated ECM 
alterations upon tissue processing (Figures 3 and 4). 
Strattice has an onset denaturation temperature of 55.5°C 
± 0.2°C, and an enthalpy of 56.6 ± 6.7 J/g (n = 5). The 
onset denaturation temperature of XenMatrix is decreased 
to a lower temperature (48.3°C ± 0.5°C, n = 6). There is no 
significant difference in enthalpy between Strattice and 
XenMatrix. The greatest change is observed in bovine per-
icardium-derived Veritas (Figures 3 and 4). The onset 
denaturation temperature of Veritas is decreased to 42.9°C 
± 0.2°C, whereas the enthalpy is increased to 56.6 ± 5.1 J/g 
(n = 3). </p>

<p>Figure 1. Histological micrographs of bioscaffolds. Histological micrographs of three commercially available bioscaffolds (cross sections 
with hematoxylin and eosin stain): (a) Strattice, (b) Veritas, and (c) XenMatrix. </p>



<p>Journal of Tissue Engineering </p>

<p>Figure 2. Micro-and ultrastructural features of bioscaffolds. Scanning electron micrographs of three commercially available bioscaffolds: (a-d) Strattice, (e-h): Veritas, and (i-l) 
XenMatrix. (a, b, e, f, i, and j) Cross sections and (c, d, g, h, k, and l) surface views. </p>

<p>Sun et al. </p>



<p>Figure 3. Thermograms of unprocessed animal tissues. 
Calorimetric thermograms of fresh bovine pericardium and 
porcine dermis at the scan rate of 3°C/min. Three independent 
test curves are superimposed for each material type. T d denotes 
the onset denaturation temperature. </p>

<p>To investigate further the changes in ECM properties 
after tissue processing, three scaffold products are analyzed 
with scan rates varying from 0.02°C/min to 50°C/min, 
which correspond to a change in time scale over three orders 
of magnitude (Figure 5(a)). The onset denaturation tempera-
ture of all ECM samples decreases as the scan rate is 
reduced, which is consistent with collagen denaturation as 
an irreversible, time-dependent kinetic process. Minimally 
processed native ECMs (i.e. porcine dermis ECM and 
bovine pericardium ECM) have higher onset denaturation 
temperatures than the derived commercial scaffolds, </p>

<p>indicating that all tissue-processing technologies resulted in 
modifications that destabilize scaffolds (Figure 5(a)). There 
are significant differences among three commercial scaf-
folds. The intrinsic onset denaturation temperature (extrapo-
lated to a scan rate of 0.01°C/min) is 55°C for the pd-ECM. 
The intrinsic onset denaturation temperature is reduced to 
51°C and 44°C for Strattice and XenMatrix, respectively. 
Although the onset denaturation temperature of bovine peri-
cardial ECM is higher than that of porcine dermal ECM, the 
derived Veritas has the lowest intrinsic onset denaturation 
temperature 
(38°C) 
(Figure 
5(a)). </p>

<p>Figure 4. Thermograms of bioscaffold denaturation. Calorimetric 
thermograms of three bioscaffolds at the scan rate of 3°C/min. 
Note that significant modifications of extracellular matrices are 
observed in finished bioscaffold products when compared to 
unprocessed fresh tissues (see Figure 3). </p>

<p>Figure 5. Effect of scan rates on bioscaffold denaturation 
temperatures: (a) Dependence of the onset denaturation 
temperatures (T d ) of bioscaffolds on the scan rate. 
Arrows indicate the extrapolated intrinsic T d . (b) Thermal 
stability of bioscaffolds at different temperatures as 
measured by the duration of time needed to denature </p>

<p>˜1 1% ECM (between the onset and peak temperature). </p>

<p>The inset shows the method of calculating the duration of 
denaturation time. </p>

<p>ECM: extracellular matrix; pd-ECM: minimally processed porcine dermis 
ECM; bp-ECM: minimally processed bovine pericardium ECM; DSC: dif-
ferential heating calorimetry. </p>



<p>Journal of Tissue Engineering </p>

<p>Process-caused modification and destabilization are also 
assessed by calculating the rate of protein denaturation at 
different onset temperatures (Figure 5(b)). The least stable 
ECM proteins denature between the onset denaturation tem-
perature and the first peak temperature during a calorimetric 
measurement. This portion accounts for 11.1% ± 2.4% of 
the total ECM proteins, assuming that the differential 
enthalpy is proportional to the mass of denatured ECM pro-
teins. The duration required to denature this portion of ECM 
proteins increased exponentially as temperature decreased. 
The ECM stability is in the order of bovine pericardial ECM 
&gt; porcine dermal ECM &gt; Strattice &gt; XenMatrix &gt; Veritas. 
The Veritas scaffold does not appear to be sufficiently stable 
at the human body temperature. </p>

<p>Differences in the susceptibility to 
collagenase </p>

<p>Figure 6 compares the susceptibility to type I collagenase 
between commercially available scaffolds and their respec-
tive minimally processed ECM materials. No significant 
difference is observed between Strattice scaffold </p>

<p>and pd-ECM. Under the testing condition, the half-life is 
measured to be 8.9 ± 0.8 h (n = 6) and 8.5 ± 1.1 h (n = 5) 
for Strattice and pd-ECM, respectively. These values are 
similar to that of the fresh porcine skin material (8.9 ± 1.2 
h, n = 7). The susceptibility of XenMatrix to type I colla-
genase is increased, with its half-life reduced to 4.8 ± 0.5 h 
(n = 3). The difference in the susceptibility to type I colla-
genase between Strattice and XenMatrix is statistically 
significant (p = 0.0001). The susceptibility of bovine peri-
cardium ECM to type I collagenase is higher than porcine 
dermis ECM, possibly due to the fact that bovine pericar-
dium is thinner and less dense than porcine dermis. The 
half-life of bp-ECM is 5.5 ± 0.6 h (n = 3). Veritas is the 
most susceptible to type I collagenase, with a half-life of 
1.1 ± 0.3 h (n = 2), and about 80% is degraded within 2 h 
of incubation at 37°C. </p>

<p>Differences in biological responses </p>

<p>In vivo evaluation using the abdominal wall repair primate 
model has demonstrated that three scaffold products exhibit 
distinctively different biological responses in soft tissue 
repair. All animals survived to the designated sacrifice date, 
with no herniation or bulging reported in any animals over 
the course of implantation. Gross evaluation of explanted 
grafts reveals no defect or graft hardening and shows good 
integration with adjacent host tissue for Strattice grafts. 
XenMatrix grafts show graft hardening and are less well 
integrated with surrounding host tissue at the 1-month and 
3-month time points. Veritas-explanted grafts are much 
smaller than the pre-implants, indicating in vivo graft con-
traction. The size of Veritas grafts is reduced by ˜6 0%, 
whereas the size of Strattice and XenMatrix grafts is 
reduced by ˜2 0%-30% (Figure 7). Histological evaluation 
demonstrates that Strattice is rapidly repopulated with host </p>

<p>Figure 6. Susceptibility of bioscaffolds to collagenase. Susceptibility 
of three bioscaffolds to type I collagenase at 37°C: (a) Strattice 
and XenMatrix are compared with pd-ECM and (b) Veritas is 
compared with bp-ECM. Data are mean ± standard deviation. </p>

<p>ECM: extracellular matrix; pd-ECM: minimally processed porcine dermis 
ECM; bp-ECM: minimally processed bovine pericardium ECM. </p>

<p>Figure 7. Contraction of implanted bioscaffolds. Changes of 
the size of implanted scaffolds after implantation in African 
green monkeys. All scaffold grafts were trimmed to 7 cm × 3 
cm (i.e. 21 cm 2 ) at the time of implantation. Explanted grafts 
were smaller than the originally implanted grafts due to graft 
contraction and/or resorption. Data are mean ± standard 
deviation. </p>

<p>Sun et al. </p>



<p>cells, and gradually remodeled over a period of 6 months, 
as indicated by new collagen deposition. Strattice results in 
minimal inflammatory response at the 1-month time point 
(Figure 8(a)-(c)). Veritas scaffold condensed and fused 
after 1-month of implantation into the primate, and lacked 
histological collagen structure as seen in the Veritas pre-
implant (Figures 1 and 8(d)). Host cell infiltration of Veritas 
grafts is limited to peripheral at the 1-month time point, and 
thus, the most graft area remains acellular. At the 3-and 
6-month time points, cell in-growth is stimulated. The 
implanted Veritas is difficult to be identified at the 3-month 
time point and appears to be completely absorbed with new 
collagen deposition observed at the implantation site. The 
implantation of Veritas results in moderate inflammation at 
the 1-month time point, and the inflammatory response 
lessens as the Veritas material is rapidly absorbed (Figure 
8(e) and (f)). Implanted XenMatrix has demonstrated lim-
ited host cell in-growth at the 1-month time point, with host 
cells (including fibroblasts and macrophages) being able to 
get into the large pores only. Despite XenMatrix possessing 
the highest porosity among three scaffold products (Figures 
1 and 8(g) to (i)), acellular areas are still observed at the 3-
and 6-month time points (Figure 8(h) and (i)). Cell in-
growth and new collagen deposition at the later time points 
occur at the slowly degraded and eroded scaffold areas. 
XenMatrix induces severe inflammation at all three time 
points, as demonstrated by the presence of numerous mac-
rophages and foreign-body giant cells. 
Figure 9 shows the elevation of systemic antibody (IgG) 
titer in animal serum in response to implanted scaffolds. 
Strattice results in the high IgG level initially (˜100-fold 
increase), and the IgG titer gradually diminishes thereafter. 
Animals with implanted Veritas only had a small transient 
increase in the IgG titer during the first month, which 
returned to baseline level thereafter. XenMatrix also ele-
vates the level of IgG titer in animals by ˜100-folds. Unlike 
Strattice, however, the high IgG level in animals with 
implanted XenMatrix remains unchanged for the entire 
experiment period (6 months), indicating a sustained 
humoral immune response. </p>

<p>Discussion and conclusion </p>

<p>This study aims to examine the relationship between ECM 
modifications by processing methods and the mechanisms 
of action in soft tissue repair and regeneration in vivo. 
Three commercially available scaffolds (Strattice, Veritas 
and XenMatrix) were selected for comparison for the fol-
lowing reasons. Tissue-processing methods for medical 
devices are validated to produce scaffolds of consistent 
quality. All three ECM scaffolds are non-cross-linked, 
packaged in the hydrated state, and terminally sterilized 
by e-beam irradiation. As a result, scaffold modifications 
are attributed mainly to tissue origin, process treatments 
for decellularization, and antigenicity reduction. The per-
formance of these scaffold products in human patients has </p>

<p>been documented, 12,38-42 and therefore, such a study could 
offer valuable biochemical and structural insights for the 
rational design of tissue engineering scaffolds for applica-
tions in human patients. In this study, we followed a previ-
ously described methodology that chooses in vitro ECM 
tests and in vivo animal models for evaluating the perfor-
mance of ECM scaffolds. 43 
Three-dimensional structural properties of scaffolds are 
known to play critical roles in supporting new tissue forma-
tion via in situ cell repopulation and revascularization that 
ultimately lead to the remodeling of the ECM scaffold into 
a functional tissue. Processing methods alter scaffold struc-
tures differently (Figures 1 and 2). The Strattice process 
causes no or little visible structural modification, yielding 
an ECM scaffold with microscopic architecture and ultras-
tructural features similar to that of a native porcine dermis 
(supplemental Figure S1). In contrast, the XenMatrix pro-
cess yields a substantially altered scaffold with few struc-
tural similarities to native dermal ECM. In vivo evaluation 
using the non-human primate model demonstrates a rapid 
fibroblast repopulation into Strattice ECM that is gradually 
remodeled (Figure 8(a)-(c)). Cell in-growth is limited in 
XenMatrix at the 1-month time point, despite the XenMatrix 
process being intentionally designed to loosen collagen net-
work to increase the scaffold porosity for earlier cell repop-
ulation, 33 and indeed, the XenMatrix scaffold has 
significantly more large pores than both native dermis and 
Strattice scaffold (Figures 1, 2 and supplemental Figure 
S1). The XenMatrix process results in the loss of fibrillar 
ultrastructural features of collagen bundles due to the con-
densation of collagen fibrils and fibers. Microscopic and 
ultrastructural features in scaffolds affect cell adhesion and 
migration. 44-46 The collagen structural damage by the 
XenMatrix process appears to outweigh the potential ben-
efit of the increased scaffold porosity. Even at the 3-and 
6-month time points (Figure 8(h) and (i)), acellular areas 
are still observed, and cell in-growth in XenMatrix is asso-
ciated with slowly degraded areas. The Veritas process 
results in some matrix modifications, but fibrillar ultra-
structures of collagen bundles are still preserved (Figures 1 
and 2, supplemental Figure S1). Cell in-growth into the 
Veritas scaffold is limited to the periphery at the 1-month 
time point (Figure 8(d)) but is stimulated at 3-and 6-month 
time points. It is apparent that cell repopulation into Veritas 
is associated with the change in Veritas after implantation. 
Collagen bundles in the H&amp;E histology of Veritas explanted 
at the 1-month time point were condensed (Figures 1 and 
8(d)), which might have hindered cell repopulation. The 
implanted Veritas had largely degraded at the 3-month time 
point (Figure 8(e)). 
Calorimetric analysis measures the changes in the ther-
mophysical and thermochemical integrity of ECM scaf-
folds (e.g. structural destabilization, degradation, partial 
denaturation and cross-linking). The thermal denaturation 
profile of an ECM scaffold depends not only on the stabil-
ity of its individual constituent proteins, but also on the </p>



<p>Journal of Tissue Engineering </p>

<p>Figure 8. Non-human primate cellular responses. Histological micrographs (cross sections with hematoxylin and eosin stain) of explanted bioscaffolds after implantation in African 
green monkey for (a, d, and g) 1, (b, e, and h) 3 and (c, f, and i) 6 months. (a-c) Strattice, (d-f): Veritas, and (g-i): XenMatrix. The insets are representative micrographs at a high 
magnification showing the cell types in grafted materials. The bracket points to the implanted material. </p>

<p>Sun et al. </p>



<p>supramolecular assembly of these proteins (i.e. fibrogene-
sis, fiber alignment, and deposition of non-collagen materi-
als)-the process to form a stable tissue matrix with 
unstable molecules. 47,48 Calorimetric analysis shows that 
all three scaffold products are less stable than ECMs of their 
respective source tissues, demonstrating that processing treat-
ments result in various degrees of ECM destabilization 
(Figure 4). The intrinsic matrix denaturation temperature is 
determined to be 51°C, 38°C, and 44°C for Strattice, Veritas, 
and XenMatrix, respectively (Figure 5). This intrinsic dena-
turation temperature is extrapolated to a scan rate of 0.01°C/ 
min, corresponding to the duration of ˜2 days for complete 
denaturation at the intrinsic denaturation temperature. The 
intrinsic denaturation temperature is 55°C for porcine dermal 
ECM. The Strattice process causes a moderate decrease by 
4°C, whereas the XenMatrix process results in a decrease of 
11°C. Nevertheless, XenMatrix is still stable at human body 
temperature. The Veritas scaffold with an intrinsic temperature 
of 38°C is not stable at human body temperature. It is conceiv-
able that, upon implantation, the Veritas scaffold would dena-
ture spontaneously over a few days or weeks. We hypothesize 
that the instability of Veritas at body temperature could be the 
cause for structural condensation (Figure 8(d)) and limited cell 
in-growth at the peripheral region of the scaffold. 
The decrease in thermal stability of scaffolds correlates 
with the increased vulnerability to enzyme degrada-
tion. 15,49,50 Significant differences exist in the susceptibility to 
collagenase among three scaffold products (Figure 6). Strattice 
has similar susceptibility to collagenase as fresh porcine der-
mis and minimally processed dermal ECM do. The suscepti-
bility of the XenMatrix scaffold to collagenase is increased, as 
shown by the reduced half-life. The reduced half-life of the 
XenMatrix scaffold may be associated with the increased scaf-
fold porosity by design as well as more severe matrix destabi-
lization by tissue processing (as seen from calorimetric data). 
The Veritas process increases the susceptibility to collagenase 
even more than the XenMatrix process. The half-life of the 
Veritas scaffold to collagenase digestion is only ˜2 0% of the 
half-life of the minimally processed bovine pericardial ECM. 
Not surprisingly, the Veritas scaffold is rapidly absorbed upon 
implantation in primates (Figures 7 and 8). 
In vivo evaluation using the functional primate model 
shows that three scaffold products elicit different biological 
responses, have distinct mechanisms of action for tissue regen-
eration, and yield various outcomes of repairs. Strattice is well 
integrated into the host tissue through the mechanisms of cell 
repopulation, revascularization of the ECM scaffold, and a 
gradual remodeling process to new tissue matrix (Figure 8). 
This mechanism of action is characterized by minimal to mild 
inflammatory responses (Figure 8) and some humoral immune 
reactions at earlier time points after scaffold implantation 
(Figure 9). The process is similar to normal wound healing 
that involves an earlier inflammatory response phase, recruit-
ment of different cell populations to the wound sites, and sub-
sequent remodeling of damaged tissues. The coordinated </p>

<p>structural and functional adaptations are likely driven by the 
positive interactions between the implanted ECM scaffold and 
repopulated host fibroblasts and other cell types. 51 Veritas 
demonstrates another mechanism of action, which is associ-
ated with moderate inflammation after implantation (Figure 
8), transient immune reactions (Figure 9), and rapid scaffold 
resorption. As the implanted Veritas ECM degrades, cell in-
growth is stimulated, and the implanted scaffold is replaced 
with new collagen deposition. There is no remodeling of the 
implanted Veritas scaffold. The host responses to implanted 
XenMatrix grafts represent another different mechanism of 
action in soft tissue repair. XenMatrix elicits severe inflamma-
tion and sustained humoral immune reactions throughout the 
entire period of the experiment (6 months). The implanted 
scaffold shows hardening, poor integration with surrounding 
host tissue, and slow degradation. The pathology of graft hard-
ening remains unclear. Graft hardening was documented pre-
viously for other biological scaffolds, including CollaMend 
(Davol, Cranston, RI), and Permacol (Tissue Science 
Laboratories, Aldershot, UK). 20 One common observation in 
this study and the earlier study 20 is the sustained presence of 
foreign-body giant cells and significant chronic inflammatory 
responses after implantation of these scaffolds into animals. 
Physiologically, hardening relates to the increased stiffness of 
tissue matrices, which could be caused by the formation of 
excessive fibrous tissue and/or encapsulation of implanted 
ECM grafts. There is evidence that the presence of foreign-
body giant cells and chronic inflammation is accompanied by 
the formation of dense, poorly organized fibrous tissue for 
implanted scaffolds (CuffPatch, Permacol, and TissueMend) 
that is designed to degrade slowly in vivo. 19 
Functional tissue repair is affected by a variety of 
dynamic tissue-regenerative mechanisms and processes. </p>

<p>Figure 9. Non-human primate immunological responses. Elevation 
of systemic antibody (IgG) titer in the serum of animals after 
implantation of bioscaffolds over 6 months. The fold increase 
in antibody titer as compared with serum obtained prior to 
implantation was plotted on a logarithmic scale. Data are mean 
± standard deviation. </p>



<p>Journal of Tissue Engineering </p>

<p>This study demonstrates that the manufacturing processes 
and tissue sources have significant impact on scaffold prop-
erties that may influence the mechanisms of action in tissue 
regeneration. The loss of biological and structural integrity 
of native ECMs is associated with severe inflammatory 
responses and sustained foreign-body reactions while hin-
dering normal healing and tissue integration. </p>

<p>Supporting information </p>

<p>Figure S1. Micrographs (histological cross sections, hema-
toxylin-eosin stain) of unprocessed porcine dermis (A) and 
unprocessed bovine pericardium (D). Scanning electron 
micrographs (cross sections) show microscopic and ultras-
tructural features of unprocessed porcine dermis (B, C) and 
unprocessed bovine pericardium (E, F). Native extracellu-
lar matrices appear as tightly woven collagen fiber net-
works and have well-defined microscopic and ultrastructural 
characteristics, which could be altered by different tissue-
processing methods. </p>

<p>Figure S2. De-convolution of the fresh porcine dermis calo-
rimetric thermogram. The complex thermogram (A) are de-
convoluted into individual peak components (B) using a 
mathematical software <rs id="software-1" type="software">PeakFit</rs> (PeakFit 4.12, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Systat Software</rs>, San Jose, CA), so that the changes of peak tem-
perature and percentage area of individual components could 
be evaluated after tissue processing. Peak temperatures and 
their percent enthalpy values are mean ± standard deviation. 
Peak A disappears after cell lysis in water and a wash in 
phosphate-buffered saline, suggesting its origin of cellular 
proteins and loosely bounded ECM proteins. Minimally pro-
cessed porcine dermis ECM retains Peak B and Peak C, 
without any change in their onset and peak temperatures. </p>

<p>Document S3. The detailed information about the animal 
welfare and care during the study. </p>

<p>The above data and information is available online with 
this article. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>W.Q.S., M.S., and H.X. conceived and designed the experi-
ments; W.Q.S., H.X., and J.L. performed the experiments; 
W.Q.S., H.X., and M.S. analyzed the data; W.Q.S., H.X., and 
J.L. contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools; and W.Q.S. 
wrote the article. </p>

<p>Declaration of conflicting interests </p>

<p>All authors are paid employees of LifeCell Corporation when the 
study was performed. The authors declare that there is no other 
conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>The research was supported by LifeCell Corporation, and received 
received no other specific grant from any funding agency in the 
public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors. </p>



<p>Sun et al. </p>





</text></tei>