<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3013778" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>TADB (http://bioinfo-mml.sjtu.edu.cn/TADB/) is an 
integrated database that provides comprehensive 
information about Type 2 toxin-antitoxin (TA) loci, 
genetic features that are richly distributed through-
out bacterial and archaeal genomes. Two-gene and 
much less frequently three-gene Type 2 TA loci code 
for cognate partners that have been hypothesized or 
demonstrated to play key roles in stress response, 
bacterial physiology and stabilization of horizontally 
acquired genetic elements. TADB offers a unique 
compilation of both predicted and experimentally 
supported Type 2 TA loci-relevant data and current-
ly contains 10 753 Type 2 TA gene pairs identified 
within 1240 prokaryotic genomes, and details of 
over 240 directly relevant scientific publications. A 
broad range of similarity search, sequence align-
ment, genome context browser and phylogenetic 
tools are readily accessible via TADB. We propose 
that TADB will facilitate efficient, multi-disciplinary 
and innovative exploration of the bacteria and 
archaea Type 2 TA space, better defining presently 
recognized TA-related phenomena and potentially 
even leading to yet-to-be envisaged frontiers. The 
TADB database, envisaged as a one-stop shop 
for Type 2 TA-related research, will be maintained, 
updated and improved regularly to ensure its 
ongoing maximum utility to the research 
community. </p>

<p>Bacterial and archaeal toxin-antitoxin (TA) loci, typically 
containing two but occasionally three tandem genes, code </p>

<p>for cognate partners that have been hypothesized or 
demonstrated to play key roles in stress response, bacterial 
physiology and stabilization of horizontally acquired 
genetic elements (1,2). The toxin genes invariably code 
for proteins, while matching antitoxin genes code for 
either antisense RNA or antitoxin proteins, resulting in 
classification as Type 1 or Type 2 TA loci, respectively. 
To date numerous phylogenetically and functionally 
distinct Type 2 TA systems have been identified through 
experimental and bioinformatics studies. In particular, 
since the advent of the genomics era it has become abun-
dantly clear that Type 2 TA loci are richly distributed 
throughout the genomes of almost all free-living bacteria 
and archaea (3-7). Individual bacterial and archael 
genomes may harbor between 0 and &gt;50 TA loci, with 
the vast majority encoding at least one TA locus. Con-
sistent with the focus of this study, all further references 
within this report to 'TA' loci/genes/proteins refer solely to 
corresponding counterparts in 'Type 2 TA' systems. 
TA toxin genes code for stable toxins that target either 
DNA replication or translation and these toxins are 
neutralized by short-lived protein antitoxins. As a 
general model for TA systems, the short-lived nature of 
the antitoxin ensures that cells which lose a TA locus and 
thus no longer produce the cognate 'immunity' antitoxin 
protein become susceptible to the stable toxin that has 
outlived the presence of its coding gene, resulting 
in toxin-mediated killing of the cell (2). Hence, prokary-
otic organisms harboring TA loci are considered by some 
investigators to be 'addicted' to their native repertoire of 
TA loci. When present on plasmids and other horizontally 
acquired elements, TA systems are frequently viewed as 
'selfish DNA' as many of these addiction systems have 
been shown to promote post-segregational killing of cells 
that have lost TA-encoding mobile genetic elements (8). A 
few TA loci have also been shown to confer within-host 
competitive advantage of the TA-encoding plasmid </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +86 21 62932943; Fax: +86 21 62932418; Email: hyou@sjtu.edu.cn </p>

<p>D606-D611 Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, Database issue 
Published online 6 October 2010 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkq908 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>against other host permissive plasmids (9). In addition, 
chromosomally encoded TA pairs have also been shown 
or postulated to play multiple other functions. These 
systems can act to stabilize large horizontally acquired 
chromosomal regions, such as integrons, by selecting 
against their loss (10). TA pairs also provide immunity 
to the host cell from the same or related toxin encoded 
on other co-resident mobile genetic elements, thus acting 
as anti-addiction modules by allowing for the loss of one 
or more 'redundant' anti-toxin gene and its carrier mobile 
genetic element (2,11). A major area of active research in 
the TA field relates to a postulated regulatory role in bac-
terial stress physiology and the formation of dormant or 
'persister' cells. Persister cells are involved in antibiotic 
resistance and pathogenicity in Mycobacterium tubercu-
losis and several other important human pathogens 
(2,12). In Escherichia coli, persister cells can be formed 
by fluctuations in the expression of the HipA toxin, 
encoded by the hipBA TA tandem genes (13,14). 
Expression of HipA over a certain threshold in small 
numbers of cells causes dormancy (14). This subset of 
dormant cells is able to survive antibiotics that are 
active against growing cells, thus allowing the infecting 
organism to survive an antimicrobial assault and regener-
ate in time from a small number of surviving persister 
cells. Thus TA systems may well contribute towards sto-
chastic variation within the population, gearing up indi-
vidual subsets of organisms distinctly to favor survival of 
the population itself in the face of a likely wide diversity of 
unpredictable environmental, competitive and hostile 
challenges ahead. 
Given the dramatic pace of expansion in experimental 
and bioinformatics data pertaining to TA systems in the 
last 10 years and the likely impending avalanche triggered 
by next-generation sequencing-facilitated prokaryotic-
and metagenomic-sequencing projects, we have created a 
<rs type="software">PostgreSQL</rs> database of Type 2 TA systems, known as 
TADB (http://bioinfo-mml.sjtu.edu.cn/TADB/), that 
provides for ready access, analysis, manipulation and ex-
ploitation of this invaluable biological information. We 
propose that TADB should serve as a 'one-stop-shop' 
for all Type 2 TA data sets and resources and are confi-
dent that in time it will facilitate efficient, 
multi-disciplinary and innovative exploration of the 
bacteria and archaea TA space, further defining presently 
recognized phenomena and potentially even leading to 
yet-to-be envisaged frontiers. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>As of 30 July 2010, TADB contains 10 753 type 2 TA gene 
pairs identified within 1240 genome sequences represen-
tative of 962 strains of phylogenetically diverse bacteria 
and archaea. The data in TADB are derived from compu-
tationally predicted data sets and/or reports of experimen-
tally validated TA genes. The <rs type="software">BLASTP</rs>-identified 921 TA 
loci present in 147 sequenced genomes reported by Gerdes 
and co-workers (3,7) were first uploaded and classified 
into eight TA families. Next, the 5806 TA loci found in 
604 genomes which had been assigned to 44 conserved TA </p>

<p>domain pairs by Makarova et al. (4) were archived in 
TADB. The database was then further complemented 
with the data set of <rs type="software">RASTA-Bacteria</rs> predicted TA 
loci identified in 883 annotated genomes. The <rs type="software">RASTA-
Bacteria</rs> algorithm utilizes <rs type="software">RPSBLAST</rs> search and 
typical characteristics of TA loci, such as a two-gene, 
co-directed module coding for small proteins, to identify 
TA hits (6). <rs type="software">RASTA-Bacteria</rs> TA pair hits with one score 
&gt;70% and the other &gt;60% were recorded by TADB, this 
strict cut-off yields broadly reliable TA candidates (6). 
Subsequently, the three data sets mentioned above were 
compared to ensure that only de-duplicated entries were 
included in TADB; identical TA loci from identical strains 
were eliminated. 
In addition, we have identified further examples of 
known or putative TA loci by searching PubMed using 
the search terms 'toxin AND antitoxin' and manually in-
specting all PubMed hits. Supplementary TA loci 
identified by this literature search strategy included six 
TA pairs, absent from the first three data sets mentioned 
above, in M. tuberculosis H37Rv (NC_000962) that had 
recently been (12). At present, TADB contains details of 
106 experimentally validated TA loci. Significantly, text 
mining has identified a further three TA families and 
three three-component TA families that belong to more 
recently identified TA families that would not be detected 
by the current version of <rs type="software">RASTA-Bacteria</rs>. Our TADB 
database now includes members of 11 two-component 
and 3 three-component TA families. These TA families 
were classified based on toxin protein sequence similarity 
and tertiary structure, as described in the reviews by 
Gerdes et al. (1) and Van Melderen and Saavedra De 
Bast (2) (See http://bioinfo-mml.sjtu.edu.cn/TADB/ 
Introduction.html for more details). We have also classi-
fied TADB entries by a second classification system based 
on identification of TA pairs sharing cognate TA domains 
and independent of wider protein-level similarity as sug-
gested recently by Makarova et al. (4), yet again offering 
the potential for future enhanced genome data mining and 
further expansion of the TADB database. TADB is 
expected to grow dramatically given next-generation 
sequencing-facilitated rapid acceleration in prokaryote-
focused whole genome sequencing projects. As more in-
formation about the TA loci becomes available, the 
database will be expanded and improved accordingly. 
TADB is implemented as a <rs type="software">PostgreSQL</rs> relational 
database. The ontology-based Chado schema (15) was 
employed to house annotations and sequences of 1000 
prokaryotic genomes which had been downloaded from 
the NCBI Refseq archive (16). A second customized 
schema was designed to organize the available experimen-
tal and in silico analyses data and references relating to TA 
loci reported in the literatures. TADB runs on a <rs type="software">Linux</rs> 
platform with the <rs type="software">Apache</rs> web-server. Web interfaces 
were developed using <rs type="software">HTML</rs>, <rs type="software">CSS</rs> and <rs type="software">JavaScript</rs>. The 
majority of data pipelines were developed with <rs type="software">PHP</rs> and 
<rs type="software">Perl</rs>. In addition, the following freely available compo-
nents were employed: (i) genome browser <rs type="software">Gbrowse</rs> (17); 
(ii) circular genome visualization tool <rs type="software">CGview</rs> (18); 
(iii) multiple sequence alignment and visualization tools, 
<rs type="software">MUSCLE</rs> (19) and <rs type="software">Jalview</rs> (20); (iv) primer design tool </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, Database issue D607 </p>

<p>Primer3Plus (21); (v) <rs type="software">IslandViewer</rs> (database of genomic 
islands) (22); (vi) dndDB (database of DNA backbone 
phosphorothioation) (23); (vii) ACLAME database 
(A CLAssification of genetic Mobile Elements) (24); 
(viii) GOLD database of genome sequencing projects (25). </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>TADB provides a flexible and biologist-friendly 
web-interface. It allows users to view an entire genome's 
TA locus repertoire, color coded by TA classification, 
within the context of the whole replicon and to access 
individual pages dedicated to each TA locus pair, toxin 
and antitoxin as required. The TADB homepage contains 
the following interfaces: 'Home', 'Browse' (browse by 
organism, TA family or TA conserved domains), 
'Search' (search by species, TA family, gene or protein), 
'Tools' (gene/protein sequence BLAST against TADB), 
'Download' (TA gene/protein sequences), 'References' 
(literatures relating to TA loci), 'Introduction' (description 
of the toxin protein-based TA family classification system 
and the TA domain pair-based classification system), 
'Submission' (report new TA loci to TADB), 'Links' and 
'Contact'. </p>

<p>TADB browse module </p>

<p>At the heart of TADB is the 'Browse by organism' page 
that provides a hyperlinked organized catalog of over 
900 prokaryotic genomes with TA systems identified by 
one of the above-mentioned strategies. TADB allows the 
users to view genomic maps flagged by hyperlinked TA loci 
color-coded by TA family to provide a genome-scale view 
TA locus repertoires. In addition, users can access individ-
ual pages dedicated to each TA locus pair, toxin and 
antitoxin as required. As an example, TA loci in 
Geobacter uraniireducens Rf4 (NCBI Refseq accession no. 
NC_009483) were analysed (Figure 1). Geobacter 
uraniireducens Rf4 is a Gram negative Delta 
Proteobacteria which can reduce uranium using acetate 
and other organic acids (Supplementary Figure S3C). 
Recently G. uraniireducens has been used experimentally 
in bioremediation of metal-contaminated subsurface envir-
onments (26). Tabulated (Figure 1A) and graphically dis-
played (Figure 1B) outputs of the 74 putative TA pairs with 
conserved TA domains (4) in G. uraniireducens Rf4 are as 
shown. In addition, a further eight putative TA loci pre-
dicted by <rs type="software">RASTA-Bacteria</rs> (6) are also included in these 
outputs. The genomic context of a selected TA locus is 
readily investigated further by using <rs type="software">Gbrowse</rs>, as shown 
for the putative TA locus Gura_2469-Gura_2470 (Figure 
1D). The putative toxin protein (yet to be experimentally 
characterized), Gura_2470, contains a MNT (minimal 
nucleotidyltransferase) domain, while its cognate putative 
antitoxin, Gura_2469, harbors a HEPN (higher eukaryotes 
and 
prokaryotes 
nucleotide-binding) 
domain 
(Supplementary Figure S3D) (4). Equivalent domain-level 
data are available for 12 other G. uraniireducens Rf4 
putative TA pairs archived within TADB (Supplementary 
Figure S3). Interestingly, a second putative TA pair 
Gura_2467-Gura_2468 (4) is located a short distance </p>

<p>upstream of the Gura_2469-Gura_2470 TA pair. This 
second toxin, Gura_2467, contains a RES domain 
(COG5654), which contains three highly conserved polar 
groups (arginine, glutamate and serine) that could form an 
active site. Its matching antitoxin, Gura_2468, contains an 
Xre family HTH (helix-turn-helix) domain (COG5642). 
Remarkably, the two tandem putative TA loci are located 
within a single 18-kb dnd island, details of which are 
archived within dndDB (Figure 1D) (23). Based on avail-
able data, the G. uraniireducens Rf4 dnd gene cluster 
(Gura_2472-2476) is likely to code for enzymes required 
for sequence-specific phosphorothioation of the DNA 
backbone (27). Consistent with a foreign origin, this 
18-kb dnd island exhibits a lower G+C content (51%) 
than the genome average (54%) and codes for two likely 
transposase proteins (Gura_2461 and Gura_2462). 
Gura_2466, one of the island borne genes that lies close to 
the two TA loci, codes for an unusual 4-oxalocrotonate 
tautomerase. This protein possesses one of the smallest 
enzyme subunits known (28). Bacteria belonging to the 
Geobacter genus are often the predominant species in a 
wide diversity of subsurface sediments under metal-
reducing conditions (29). Given the abundance of phylo-
genetically diverse and functionally distinct TA loci within 
G. uraniireducens Rf4, it would be tempting to speculate 
that cumulative acquisition of TA loci and/or associated 
physically-linked mobile genetic DNA directly contributed 
to the environmental success and hardiness of Geobacter. 
Using the 'Browse by TA family' link (Supplementary 
Figure S1), users can retrieve the full list of 11 
two-component and 3 three-component TA families that 
encompass the full set of current TADB entries that have 
to date been mapped to a specific family (Supplementary 
Figure S2). The TA family classification system used is 
based on that described in the reviews by Gerdes et al. 
(1) and Van Melderen and Saavedra De Bast (2). As of 
now, 949 TA loci in 159 genomes have been assigned into 
these 14 TA families. Similarly, via the 'Browse by TA 
related domain' link (Supplementary Figure S3), the 
5806 TA loci found in 604 genomes reported by 
Makarova et al. (4) have been organized into the 44 TA 
domain pair groupings. </p>

<p>TADB search options and tools </p>

<p>TADB offers several search tools with varied options. 
Through the 'Search' page, users can retrieve a specific 
object(s) in the TADB database by the following 
categories: species or genus, TA family, gene or protein. 
Via the 'Tools' page, users are able to blast a query 
sequence using <rs id="software-28" type="software">WU-BLAST</rs> <rs corresp="#software-28" type="version-number">2.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-28" type="creator">W. Gish</rs>, personal com-
munication) against TADB to find and visualize potential 
homologous matches. A NCBI <rs type="software">RPSBLAST</rs> (Reverse 
PSI-BLAST) (30) interface that relies on a position 
specific scoring matrix to identify potential toxin or anti-
toxin domains in a user-supplied protein sequence is also 
provided. </p>

<p>TADB reference module </p>

<p>The TADB reference section provides publication details 
of papers relating to TA systems that have been identified </p>

<p>D608 Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, Database issue </p>

<p>Figure 1. An overview of TADB data sets and outputs using the G. uraniireducens Rf4 (NC_009483) TA locus-rich genome as an example. (A) A 
selected sample of the 74 TA domain pairs identified in this organism by Makarova et al. (4), plus another eight putative TA pairs predicted by 
<rs type="software">RASTA-Bacteria</rs> (6) alone. (B) A segment of the circular genome map of G. uraniireducens Rf4 generated using <rs type="software">CGview</rs> (18) showing TA loci in 
color code by TA family and TA domain pair. (C) A partial view of the features and sequence of the putative toxin gene Gura_2470 as shown by 
TADB. Hyperlinks to NCBI Refseq Project, UniProtKB, PDB and/or KEGG are provided. An integrated version of <rs type="software">Primer3Plus</rs> (21) is available to 
facilitate design of PCR primers and selected TADB items can be searched against the ACLAME database of mobile genetic elements (24) using 
<rs type="software">Blast</rs> via a single link. (D) A schematic view of the wider genomic context of the putative TA locus Gura_2469-Gura_2470 using <rs type="software">Gbrowse</rs> (17). See 
text for details of the utility TADB-facilitated localized genome browsing strategy as highlighted by the example of the Gura_2469-Gura_2470 locus. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, Database issue D609 </p>

<p>by text mining the NCBI PubMed database. Direct links 
to matching PubMed entries are also offered. At present 
this resource contains records of over 240 directly relevant 
scientific publications. This reference collection will be 
updated on a monthly basis with new entries being 
subject to subsequent manual curation and organization 
in a timely manner. The TADB reference collection has 
been sorted by the following headings: experimental 
studies, in silico analysis, protein structure data 
(Supplementary Figure S2C). TADB links the reviewed 
literatures to relevant TA loci, TA family, toxin domain, 
antitoxin domain and species pages as indicated by the 
corresponding thumbnail icons. The TADB reference 
collection is also searchable by TA family, author, title, 
journal, year, PubMed ID and matching abstracts can be 
subjected to standard word searches. This provides an 
easily accessible literature resource that has been subjected 
to both text mining and manual curation. </p>

<p>Future directions </p>

<p>As future developments, we will shortly be updating the 
records of experimentally verified TA loci with more func-
tional information such as details of toxin targets, mech-
anisms of action of antitoxins, promoter, Shine-Dalgarno, 
terminator and identified TA loci regulators. Comparative 
analysis tool will also be incorporated into TADB to fa-
cilitate large scale synteny mapping of chromosomally 
encoded TA loci and their associated genomic islands. 
We are also exploring a pipeline, including the use of 
<rs type="software">RPSBLAST</rs>, to implement automated searches of 
annotated or unannotated genome sequences for presently 
undiscovered potential members of the TADB-recorded 
families. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>We envisage an evolving resource that maintains a 
growing variety of TA loci related data extracted and 
curated from experimental literature, submitted directly 
by users and derived by increasingly sophisticated bio-
informatics analyses of bacterial and archaeal DNA, 
RNA and protein sequences. The increasing abundance 
of omics data will undoubtedly drive major growth of 
TADB. A broad range of similarity search, sequence 
alignment, genome context browser and phylogenetic 
tools are readily accessible to allow for user-directed in-
terrogation of the database, examination of user-supplied 
sequences and other individualized directions of research. 
We propose that a unified resource such as TADB will 
facilitate efficient, multidisciplinary and innovative inves-
tigation of a wide range of aspects relating to prokaryotic 
TA systems. Studies of this nature are undoubtedly of 
major interest to many researchers given the complex 
genetic, evolutionary, biochemical, physiological and 
cellular processes frequently at the heart of operations of 
chromosome-and plasmid-encoded TA systems in diverse 
host organisms. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We are grateful to two anonymous referees for their 
constructive suggestions. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>National Natural Science Foundation of China; the 973 
program, Ministry of Science and Technology of China; a 
Royal Society-National Natural Science Foundation of 
China International Joint Project grant 2007/R3 (to K.R. 
and Z.D.); the Chen Xing Young Scholars Programme, 
Shanghai Jiaotong University (to H.-Y.O.); an Action 
Medical Research grant SP4255 (to K.R.); E.M.H.'s 
post was part-funded by an Innovation Fellowship; East 
Midlands Development Agency grant (to K.R.). Funding 
for open access charge: National Natural Science 
Foundation of China. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, Database issue D611 </p>

</text></tei>