<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3212591" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: The aim of this study was to assess the voiding dysfunction after rectal cancer surgery with total mesorectal excision 
(TME). 
Methods: This was part of a prospective study done in the rectal cancer patients who underwent surgery with TME between 
November 2006 and June 2008. Consecutive uroflowmetry, post-voided residual volume, and a voiding questionnaire were per-
formed at preoperatively and postoperatively. 
Results: A total of 50 patients were recruited in this study, including 28 male and 22 female. In the comparison of the preopera-
tive data with the postoperative 3-month data, a significant decrease in mean maximal flow rate, voided volume, and post-voided 
residual volume were found. In the comparison with the postoperative 6-month data, however only the maximal flow rate was 
decreased with statistical significance (P=0.02). In the comparison between surgical methods, abdominoperineal resection pa-
tients showed delayed recovery of maximal flow rate, voided volume, and post-voided residual volume. There was no significant 
difference in uroflowmetry parameters with advances in rectal cancer stage. 
Conclusions: Voiding dysfunction is common after rectal cancer surgery but can be recovered in 6 months after surgery or ear-
lier. Abdominoperineal resection was shown to be an unfavorable factor for postoperative voiding. Larger prospective study is 
needed to determine the long-term effect of rectal cancer surgery in relation to male and female baseline voiding condition. </p>

<p>Colorectal cancer is the third most prevalent cancer in men and 
in women is second only to breast cancer in the United States 
[1]. Survival of patients with rectal cancer has improved over 
the past two decades as a result of earlier diagnosis, radiothera-
py and advances in surgical techniques such as total mesorectal 
excision (TME) [2,3]. Recently, investigations have focused 
more on combining a cure with improved quality of life for pa-
tients after treatment. For urogenital complications, sexual and 
urinary dysfunction is common complications of rectal cancer 
surgery [4]. These complications can have a major impact on a 
patient's physical, psychological, social and emotional function-</p>

<p>ing, as well as his or her overall well-being [5]. Because the inci-
dence of rectal cancer is highest in the sixth and seventh decades 
of life, voiding dysfunction can become a more important 
problem although several western studies demonstrated that 
sexuality also remains an important aspect at those ages [6,7]. 
The incidence of voiding dysfunction after rectal cancer sur-
gery currently ranges from 30 to 70% [5,8,9]. Voiding dysfunc-
tion after rectal cancer surgery includes empting failure, stress 
incontinence and urgency, and among them empting failure 
make up most of the incidences. Difficulty in bladder emptying 
is generally improved after 3 months, but symptoms that per-
sisted 6 months after surgery are mainly permanent, and long-
term dysfunction is reported by 31% of patients [10]. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.5213/inj.2011.15.3.166 
pISSN 2093-4777 · eISSN 2093-6931 </p>

<p>www.einj.or.kr 167 </p>

<p>Kim, et al. • Voiding Dysfunction after Rectal Cancer Surgery </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.5213/inj.2011.15.3.166 </p>

<p>INJ </p>

<p>With the introduction of TME, nerve damage was no longer 
thought to be an inevitable event for rectal cancer surgery be-
cause the pelvic autonomic nerves are located just outside the 
mesorectal fascia, and are therefore not necessarily damaged by 
the TME procedure. However, voiding dysfunction still remains 
as one of the common complications after surgery [11]. 
One of the motives leading to this study is that patients are 
unlikely to mention voiding problems themselves, either be-
cause they are embarrassed or because they do not relate their 
symptoms to their rectal cancer treatment. We investigated 
voiding changes and their sequelae after TME in rectal cancer 
patients. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>The total of 50 patients who underwent TME from November 
2006 to June 2008 were recruited into this study. At first, this 
study was part of a prospective study to evaluate voiding func-
tion preoperatively and postoperatively. We retrospectively re-
viewed the data of 50 patients who were available for follow-up 
after approval by the Institutional Review Board. 
Patients with recurrent or metastatic disease, urinary symp-</p>

<p>tomatology (urgency, straining, urinary incontinence, or dys-
uria) or abnormalities in preoperative uroflowmetry, a history 
of urinary tract surgery, prior rectal surgery, or no preoperative 
urodynamic assessment were excluded. The patients' character-
istics and interventions performed are listed in Table 1. 
All of the operations were performed by two surgeons who 
were both experts in colorectal surgery. TME was performed 
according to the principles described by Heald et al. [12], and 
the pelvic autonomic nerves, including the hypogastric nerve 
and pelvic splanchnic plexus, were preserved a much as possi-
ble in all patients. In the cases of high anterior resection a tran-
section of the mesorectum was performed 5 cm from the tu-
mor, and in low anterior resection and abdominoperineal re-
section the entire mesorectum was removed. 
Three months and 6 months after the operation, all patients 
underwent a further sequential uroflowmetry and clinical in-
terview with the urologist to detect urinary symptomatology. 
Particular attention was paid to the presence of straining, uri-
nary incontinence, and urgency. 
Patients were instructed to avoid heavy lifting, exercise, and 
sexual intercourse for a minimum of 4 weeks postoperatively. 
Less strenuous activities of daily living could be resumed within 
1 to 2 weeks. For follow up, patients were educated to visit 1 week 
later, and every 3 months after the operation. The patients who 
presented with incontinence in the first visit were educated 
about and encouraged to perform pelvic floor exercise by a 
urologic nurse. 
The variables investigated included age, sex, type of interven-
tion, clinical stage, parameters of uroflowmetry, and urinary 
symptomatology. Comparative analysis was conducted by using 
the Pearson χ 
2 statistic or Fisher exact test for categorical data, </p>

<p>and paired t-test and Wilcoxon signed rank test for investiga-
tion of sequential continuous variables. All data were expressed 
as mean ±standard deviation, and <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 18.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS, Inc.</rs>., 
Chicago, IL, USA) software was used for statistical processing. 
Differences were considered to be significant when P&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>A total of 50 patients recruited in this study including 28 male 
and 22 female. There were no significant differences in baseline 
characteristics between the men and the women. The voiding 
dysfunctions presented by the patients included urgency, strain-
ing, urinary incontinence, and dysuria. The most common 
voiding symptom at 3 months after surgery was straining, which </p>

<p>Table 1. Patient characteristics </p>

<p>Parameter 
Value </p>

<p>No. of enrolled patients 
50 </p>

<p>Sex </p>

<p>Male 
28 (56.0) </p>

<p>Female 
22 (39.2) </p>

<p>Age at surgery (yr) 
67.2 (42-83) </p>

<p>Body mass index (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
24.8 (19.2-27.1) </p>

<p>Sexual activity </p>

<p>Active 
7 (14.0) </p>

<p>Inactive 
40 (80.0) </p>

<p>Operation type </p>

<p>Low anterior resection 
36 (72.0) </p>

<p>Abdominoperineal resection 
14 (28.0) </p>

<p>Tumor size (cm) 
4.8 (2.1-11.0) </p>

<p>Stage </p>

<p>Dukes A 
0 </p>

<p>Dukes B 
25 (50.0) </p>

<p>Dukes C 
21 (42.0) </p>

<p>Dukes D 
4 (8.0) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%) or range. </p>



<p>Kim, et al. • Voiding Dysfunction after Rectal Cancer Surgery </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.5213/inj.2011.15.3.166 </p>

<p>INJ </p>

<p>manifested in 19 patients (38.0%). The most common voiding 
symptom at 6 months after surgery was also straining, which 
manifested in 8 patients (16.0%). Incontinence was manifested 
in 13 patients (26.0%) at 3 months after surgery but 5 patients 
(10.0%) at 6 months after surgery. Rates of all of the voiding 
dysfunction symptoms decreased 6 months after surgery (Table 
2). The overall voiding dysfunction rate at 6 months after sur-
gery was 16.0%. Of the voiding dysfunction symptoms, strain-
ing showed a statistically significant difference between low an-
terior resection and abdominoperineal resection. The abdomi-
noperineal resection group had a higher rate of straining. 
Sequential results of the uroflowmetry parameters are showed 
in Fig. 1. The preoperative maximal flow rate, voided volume, 
and post-void residual volume were 24.6 ±5.2, 288 ±58, and 
19.8 ±17.0, respectively. At 3 months and 6 months after sur-
gery, these parameters were 14.6±6.2, 188±58, and 79.8±87.0 
and 19.6 ±5.2, 278 ±58, and 30.8 ±47.0, respectively. In the 
comparison of preoperative data with the 6 months data, only 
the maximal flow rate revealed a significant difference (P &lt; 
0.05). </p>

<p>When uroflowmetry parameters were compared between 
low anterior resection and abdominoperineal resection, the pa-
tients (n=18) showed unfavorable voiding outcomes (Tables 3, 
4). Except for voided volume, maximal flow rate, average flow 
rate, and post-voided residual volume showed delayed recovery, 
manifested as lower mean data, in the abdominoperineal resec-
tion patients. In the sequential data of the abdominoperinal re-
section patients, only the maximal flow rate at 6 months after 
surgery was lower (P =0.02) compared with the preoperative 
data. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In 1979 the TME technique was introduced by Heald. Instead 
of blind blunt dissection, this technique used sharp dissection 
under direct vision along pre-existing embryologically deter-
mined planes; dividing the visceral fascia surrounding the me-</p>

<p>Table 2. Voiding dysfunction symptoms reported at 3 and 6 
months after surgery </p>

<p>Parameters 
3 mo 
6 mo </p>

<p>Straining 
19 (38.0) 
8 (16.0) </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Incontinence 
13 (26.0) 
5 (10.0) </p>

<p>Urgency 
8 (16.0) 
5 (10.0) </p>

<p>Dysuria 
5 (10.0) 
3 (6.0) </p>

<p>Overall symptoms 
19 (38.0) 
8 (16.0) </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Need catheterization 
6 (12.0) 
2 (4.0) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%). </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Statistical significance by Mann-Whitney test between low anterior 
resection and abdominoperineal resection. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Sequential uroflowmetry parameters before and after 
rectal cancer surgery. VV, voided volume; Qmax, maximal flow 
rate; PVR, post-void residual volume. Data are analyzed by 
paired t-test. </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>P &gt; 0.05 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
Qmax 
PRV </p>

<p>P &gt; 0.05 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
VV </p>

<p>Preoperative 
3 mo 
6 mo </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparison of uroflowmetry parameters between LAR and APR (I) </p>

<p>Parameters 
LAR 
APR </p>

<p>Preoperative 
6 mo 
P-value 
Preoperative 
6 mo 
P-value </p>

<p>VV (mL) 
286 ± 46 
265 ± 56 
0.25 
292±59 
285±74 
0.94 </p>

<p>Qmax (mL/min) 
23.9 ± 5.6 
21.1 ± 6.4 
0.06 
25.6 ±5.4 
19.9±5.5 
0.01 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Qavg (mL/min) 
11.5 ± 3.7 
10.2 ± 3.5 
0.08 
12.1±4.4 
9.3±3.0 
0.18 </p>

<p>PVR (mL) 
19.8 ± 17.0 
22.2 ± 20.5 
0.11 
16.9±22.2 
34.6±45.7 
0.12 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean ± SD. 
LAR, low anterior resection; APR, abdominoperineal resection; VV, voided volume; Qmax, maximal flow rate; Qavg, average flow rate; PVR, post-
void residual volume. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Statistical significance by Wilcoxon signed rank test. </p>

<p>www.einj.or.kr 169 </p>

<p>Kim, et al. • Voiding Dysfunction after Rectal Cancer Surgery </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.5213/inj.2011.15.3.166 </p>

<p>INJ </p>

<p>sorectum from the pelvic parietal fascia overlying the pelvic 
floor [12,13]. The TME procedure resulted in improved surviv-
al (from 48 to &gt;60%), reduced local recurrence rates (from 
&gt;20 to &lt;10%), higher incidence of sphincter preservation and 
reduced blood loss [12,14]. By combining the nerve-preserving 
principle with the TME procedure, urogenital function re-
mained at normal levels in almost 90% of his patients without 
compromising oncological outcome [15]. 
Although the surgical technique has evolved to a high de-
gree, functional outcomes including voiding dysfunction and 
sexual dysfunction have not been reproduced in larger studies 
[8,16] Voiding dysfunction after rectal cancer surgery currently 
ranges from 30 to 70% [5,8,9]. Voiding dysfunction after rectal 
cancer surgery includes empting failure, stress incontinence 
and urgency, and among them empting failure makes up most 
of the incidences. Difficulty in bladder emptying is generally 
improved after 3 months, but symptoms that persist for 6 months 
after surgery are mainly permanent and long-term dysfunction 
is reported by 31% of patients [10]. 
Early postoperative changes which consist of detrusor hypo-
activity and diminished bladder sensation and manifest as uri-
nary retention and overflow incontinence can occur from 1 
week to 6 months after surgery [17]. This phenomenon is due </p>

<p>to typical effects of parasympathetic nerve damage on voiding. 
These effects can be transient, if the nerves are not completely 
divided, they are able to regenerate. Changes that persist for 
more than 1 year post operatively are mainly permanent, and 
usually consist of emptying difficulties due to a persistently 
noncontractile bladder [10]. In our study, the transient decrease 
in maximal flow rate at 3 months after the operation might be 
explained by postoperative inflammatory changes in the peri-
vesical tissues and the possible resolution of partial nerve dam-
age with time, resulting in improvement and even complete re-
covery [17]. 
Kneist et al. [18] reported a rate of severe voiding dysfunc-
tion, defined as the need for a permanent urinary catheter, of 
3.8% at hospital discharge and a long-term dysfunction rate of 
2.8% in this series. In another series, the rate of voiding dys-
function was 4.1 to 15 % at 3 months after surgery, althouth few 
studies reported the long-term voiding dysfunction rate, which 
is assumed to be far lower than the rate at 3 months after sur-
gery [19,20]. In our study, overall voiding dysfunction rates at 3 
months and 6 months were 38.0% and 16.0%, which is similar 
to the results of other trials (Table 5). 
The only predictive factor for the need to keep a urinary 
catheter was the failure to preserve or nonvisualization of the </p>

<p>Table 5. Voiding dysfunction results after rectal cancer surgery </p>

<p>Author 
Year 
Patients 
Women (%) 
Voiding dysfunction (%) </p>

<p>Havenga et al. [11] 
1996 
138 
39 
32 </p>

<p>Mass et al. [26] 
1998 
47 
30 
28 </p>

<p>Maurer et al. [27] 
1999 
60 
36 
24 </p>

<p>Sterk et al. [17] 
2005 
52 
30 
8 </p>

<p>Present data 
2011 
50 
39 
38 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>, 16 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Rate at 6 months after surgery. </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Rate at 6 months after surgery </p>

<p>Table 4. Comparison of uroflowmetry parameters between LAR and APR (II) </p>

<p>Parameters 
LAR 
APR 
P-value 
LAR 
APR 
P-value 
Preoperative 
6 mo </p>

<p>VV (mL) 
286 ± 46 
292 ± 59 
0.26 
265±56 
285±74 
0.94 </p>

<p>Qmax (mL/min) 
23.9 ± 5.6 
25.6 ± 5.4 
0.14 
21.1±6.4 
19.9±5.5 
0.03 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Qavg (mL/min) 
11.5 ± 3.7 
12.1 ± 4.4 
0.12 
10.2±3.5 
9.3±3.0 
0.04 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>PVR (mL) 
19.8 ± 17.0 
16.9 ± 22.2 
0.15 
22.2±20.5 
34.6±45.7 
0.02 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean ± SD. 
LAR, low anterior resection; APR, abdominoperineal resection; VV, voided volume; Qmax, maximal flow rate; Qavg, average flow rate; PVR, post-
void residual volume. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Statistical significance by Mann-Whitney test. </p>



<p>Kim, et al. • Voiding Dysfunction after Rectal Cancer Surgery </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.5213/inj.2011.15.3.166 </p>

<p>INJ </p>

<p>autonomic nervous system during the resection [18]. Urinary 
disorders are more severe when the colonic anastomosis is per-
formed close to the anus [11,19]. Predictive factors for post-op-
erative bladder dysfunction include low rectal cancer ( &lt;5 cm 
from the anal verge), lymph node involvement, and pre-opera-
tive urinary dysfunction [19]. 
Pelvic autonomic nerves can be damaged as a result of failure 
to identify them, either as a result of lack of anatomical knowl-
edge or simply because of poor visibility owing to bleeding or 
obesity [21]. The sympathetic nerves are at risk during presacral 
and ventrolateral dissection of the mesorectum and central ar-
terial ligation, and the parasympathetic nerve supply is espe-
cially at risk during deep dissection of the lateral planes. Low 
rectal cancer increases the risk of combined damage to the pel-
vic splanchnic nerves and levator ani nerves, due to the small 
surgical margin deep in the pelvis [22]. Inflammation following 
anastomotic leakage, dia thermic coagulation, sutures and ra-
diotherapy can cause pelvic nerve damage. Radiotherapy in 
particular can cause demyelination and affect the autonomic 
nerves, leading to nerve fibrosis and dysfunction [23]. The 
Dutch TME trial indicated, however, that radiotherapy does 
not contribute to the development of urinary dysfunction after 
rectal cancer treatment when surgical factors are taken into ac-
count [10]. 
Urogenital dysfunction after rectal cancer surgery is mainly 
dependent on surgical method. Abdominoperineal resection 
with the construction of a colostomy is associated with an in-
creased incidence of urinary incontinence compared with low 
anterior resection in which an anastomosis is created [24]. Our 
study revealed similar results in that the patients with abdomi-
noperineal resection had prolonged voiding dysfunction. The 
patient group with abdominoperineal resection showed delayed 
recovery of maximal flow rate and post voiding residual volume. 
Effective management of patients with voiding dysfunction 
after rectal cancer treatment is lacking. Although several treat-
ments have been introduced for voiding dysfunction including 
pelvic floor exercise and sacral nerve stimulation [25], most of 
the studies of the treatment of postoperative urogenital dys-
function deal with sexual problems. 
Our study had some limitations. The study cohort was small, 
which resulted in difficulties in analyzing the comparative pa-
rameters between males and females. Also we could not deter-
mine the effect of neoadjuvant treatment or adjuvant treatment 
because of the narrow inclusion criteria. 
In conclusion, the results of our study imply a favorable out-</p>

<p>come of voiding dysfunction at 6 months after surgery. Although 
the long-term prognosis of voiding dysfunction after surgery is 
favorable, voiding dysfunction should not be ignored because it 
is a common phenomenon and it disrupt the quality of life for 
more than 3 months postoperatively. Postoperative evaluation 
of patients' voiding outcome should be standard procedure at 
every follow-up appointment, and available treatment should 
be proposed if needed. Furthermore, nerve preservation during 
rectal cancer surgery needs to be given greater emphasis in sur-
gical practice. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was re-
ported. </p>



</text></tei>