<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3710983" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective: To assess the quality of reported consent </p>

<p>processes of cluster-randomised trials conducted in 
residential facilities for older people and to explore 
whether the focus on improving the general conduct 
and reporting of cluster-randomised trials influenced 
the quality of conduct and reporting of ethical 
processes in these trials. </p>

<p>Design: Systematic review of cluster-randomised trials </p>

<p>reports, published up to the end of 2010. </p>

<p>older people should be based on high-
quality, ethically sound, relevant research 
involving this patient population. 1 This must 
include studies in nursing and residential 
homes, where many of the growing numbers 
of frail older people live. Research in these 
settings poses ethical challenges, not least 
because many residents of nursing and 
residential homes are cognitively impaired, 2 
and therefore may have difficulty in </p>

<p>ARTICLE SUMMARY </p>

<p>Article focus </p>

<p>▪ The overall quality of consent processes in 
cluster-randomised trials (CRTs) conducted in 
residential facilities for older people. 
▪ The standard of reporting of consent processes 
and research ethics approval in publications 
describing CRTs in this context. 
▪ The potential association between the quality of 
this reporting and other quality markers such as 
accounting for clustering. </p>

<p>Key messages </p>

<p>▪ The majority of investigators of CRTs in nursing 
and residential homes understand when it is 
necessary to obtain individual consent for resi-
dents' participation. 
▪ The ethical principles underlying the need to 
assess capacity and the use of proxies appear to 
be poorly understood in these trials. 
▪ The quality of reporting ethical approval and 
consent processes is also poor in these trials. </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ The relatively small number of included trials 
precludes extensive formal statistical analyses of 
associations between the quality of consent pro-
cesses and possible determinants. 
▪ Published reports may not fully reflect the ethical 
procedures because of space limitations. 
▪ The criteria we used to assess whether individual 
consent for participation was needed in a trial 
were compiled to help those designing trials and 
not easy to use for assessment of trial reports. </p>

<p>DiazOrdaz K, Slowther A-M, Potter R, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003057. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003057 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>understanding information usually provided in consent 
processes or may lack capacity to consent to participate. 
International ethical standards for research include 
the requirement for valid consent from participants who 
have capacity, 3 the obligation to take all practical mea-
sures to maximise understanding and facilitate capaci-
tous consent, and the adherence to appropriate 
guidance when capacity is lacking. Since capacity is deci-
sion specific, researchers must assess capacity for each 
potential participant during the recruitment process; 
reliance on the opinion of others, standardised tests or 
previous assessments of capacity for other decisions is 
not adequate. 4-7 If an individual lacks capacity, research-
ers should follow the relevant regulatory framework 
depending on the nature of the study and the legal juris-
diction in which it takes place. However, guidance on 
the conduct of research involving people who lack cap-
acity is often not clearly understood, even by research 
ethics committees 8 or easily put into practice. 9 
When cluster-randomised trials are conducted in resi-
dential homes, there are additional ethical challenges, as 
well as statistical challenges. 10-12 In these trials, clusters are 
randomised rather than individuals themselves. When the 
interventions being evaluated are aimed primarily at 
homes, for example, a change in the type of light fittings, 13 
an individual's refusal to participate is meaningless, 
though there may still be a need to obtain individual 
consent for assessment of outcome measures and for data 
collection. 14 An international research group recently pro-
duced draft recommendations to clarify appropriate 
ethical conduct in cluster randomised trials, including 
recommendations about when investigators need to 
obtain individual consent to participate in these trials and 
when they do not. In line with international ethical guide-
lines, the group recommend that consent be obtained 
from research participants unless a waiver of consent has 
been approved by the relevant research ethics commit-
tee. 15 However, a recent review of 300 cluster randomised 
trials by this research group showed that investigators were 
less likely to report obtaining ethical approval and to 
report obtaining participant consent than in individually 
randomised trials. 16 The International Committee of 
Medical Journal Editors requires authors to indicate 
whether the research reported complied with the stan-
dards set by the relevant research ethics committee and 
were in accordance with the Helsinki Declaration. 17 
Where there is doubt about compliance with the 
Declaration, the requirements state that 'the authors must 
explain the rationale for their approach and demonstrate 
that the institutional review body explicitly approved the 
doubtful aspects of the study'. As cluster randomised trials 
raise concerns about appropriate consent processes, there 
is an obligation on researchers to report the approach 
taken and their reasons for it. Given the risk of lack of 
decision-making capacity in this research population, this 
obligation could be expected to include reporting pro-
cesses for assessing capacity and compliance with the rele-
vant regulation when participants lack capacity. </p>

<p>As a result of our own efforts to conduct consent pro-
cesses in a large cluster-randomised trial in nursing and 
residential homes in the UK, 18 we wanted to explore, as 
part of a systematic review of the quality of such trials 
( paper submitted), how other researchers had 
approached this double challenge of ethical conduct in 
cluster-randomised trials in nursing and residential 
homes, and provide guidance for future investigators. In 
this paper, we make specific recommendations for 
improving the reporting and conduct of consent pro-
cesses in these trials based on weaknesses we identify in 
reporting, conducting consent processes, and under-
standing when consent from participants is and is not 
necessary. We also explore whether the focus on improv-
ing the general conduct and reporting of cluster-
randomised trials and discussions of ethical issues in 
these trials in the early part of the 21st century was asso-
ciated with a change in the quality of conduct and 
reporting of ethical processes in these trials. In addition, 
we assess whether the reporting of these processes was 
of higher quality if the trials appeared to be of higher 
quality in other respects. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Inclusion and identification 
We included cluster-randomised trials conducted in resi-
dential facilities for older people. We used the Medical 
Subject Headings definition of residential care facilities: 
long-term care facilities which provide supervision and 
assistance in activities of daily living with medical and 
nursing services when required, and extended this defin-
ition to include other group-living arrangements where 
some care is provided, for example, retirement villages. 
Trials were included if the unit of randomisation was the 
facility or a part of it, for example, a ward, wing or floor, 
and the majority of the trial participants were 60 years 
old or over. We included all such trials published up to 
the end of 2010, without language restrictions. We 
searched PubMed in January 2011 for reports of relevant 
trials (full search strategy in table A in web appendix A). 
In addition, we hand-searched the electronic archives of 
five journals (British Medical Journal, Journal of the 
American Medical Association, BMC Health Services Research, 
Age and Ageing and the Journal of the American Geriatrics 
Society) back to 2001, reviewed the references of each eli-
gible report identified using Web of Knowledge, and 
contacted experts to identify any further trials. 
Secondary reports of the same trial were excluded. </p>

<p>Data extraction 
One researcher extracted data from all reports; a 
second, independent extraction was carried out by other 
members of the research team. We used written guid-
ance on extraction, agreed in advance, resolving discrep-
ancies by discussion. We extracted data from all trial 
reports on whether approval by an ethics committee and 
individual consent/assent were reported. If consent/ </p>



<p>DiazOrdaz K, Slowther A-M, Potter R, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003057. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003057 </p>

<p>A systematic review of consent processes of CRTs in residential homes </p>

<p>assent was reported, we extracted all quotes relating to 
consent processes. We emailed twice a 10% sample of 
authors for further information. For trials in which indi-
vidual consent/assent was not reported, we extracted 
data on type of intervention and method of data collec-
tion in order to judge whether it would have been legit-
imate not to obtain consent for individual participation. 
Data on year of publication and markers of methodo-
logical quality were extracted from the trial reports, as 
part of a review of the quality of these trials, based on 
the same sample ( paper submitted). Following a previ-
ous review, 16 we used accounting for clustering in the 
sample size calculations and analysis of the trials as two 
methodological quality markers, and publication in a 
journal putting a stronger emphasis on following the 
CONSORT statement as a marker of journal focus on 
the quality of reporting in general, although this state-
ment does not explicitly recommend reporting ethical 
approval and consent (see web appendix A for details). 
The review protocol is available from authors. </p>

<p>Analysis 
To assess reporting, we present proportions reporting 
ethical approval and seeking individual consent for par-
ticipation and, for trials for which authors reported 
obtaining such consent, proportions assessing capacity, 
using proxies for consent (including type of proxy), 
excluding cognitively impaired individuals and obtaining 
consent only in the intervention arm. 
To assess the conduct of consent processes, two 
researchers independently scored the quality of the cap-
acity assessment, use of proxies and processes for obtain-
ing assent using the criteria shown in table 1, resolving 
discrepancies by discussion. The scores from each of 
these were summed to provide a total score for the 
quality of consent processes: high (score=3 or higher), </p>

<p>medium (score=2) or low (score=1). Some reports did 
not provide enough information to provide a score. 
Two researchers independently judged whether such 
consent was necessary in trials for which the authors 
had not reported obtaining individual consent, using 
guidance produced by an international research group 
that has produced ethical guidelines for cluster-
randomised trials. This group defined research 
participants as anyone in at least one of the following 
categories: (1) a recipient of an experimental (or 
control) intervention; (2) someone who is the direct 
target of an experimental (or control) manipulation of 
his/her environment; (3) someone from whom a 
researcher collects data about that individual (4) or 
someone about whom an investigator obtains identifi-
able private information for the purpose of collecting 
data. 15 We first judged home residents as research parti-
cipants if they fell into either category (1) or (2). When 
they did not, we additionally examined data collection 
procedures, assessing residents as research participants if 
they fell into category (3) or (4). When we found it diffi-
cult to judge whether collection from routine data 
involved identifiable private information, and the inter-
vention procedures posed no more than minimal risk, 
we assumed that a waiver of consent would have been 
acceptable. 
To explore any association between the focus on 
improving reporting in general and discussion of ethical 
issues in cluster trials in the early part of the 21st 
century, and the conduct and reporting of ethical pro-
cesses in such trials, we present proportions reporting 
ethical approval, individual consent and the quality of 
the consent processes for studies reported in or before 
or after the publication of the extended CONSORT 
statement for cluster-randomised trials in 2004. Various 
publications discussing the ethical conduct of trials were 
published just before or around the same time. 11 12 14 19 </p>

<p>Table 1 Criteria to assess quality of consent/agreement processes and associated scores </p>

<p>Issue 
Criterion used to assess quality 
Score </p>

<p>Assessing 
capacity </p>

<p>Evidence that the individual had been given information relevant to the trial and their 
understanding was assessed directly by the trial team </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Researchers applied an instrument to measure the level of cognitive impairment (eg, mini-mental 
state examination) to each individual and based their assessment of capacity to consent on this </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>A carer (eg, nursing home staff and general practitioner) was shown the study information sheet 
and asked to give an opinion whether the individual would be able to understand the information 
in order to give informed consent </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Researchers based their consent process on the level of cognitive impairment as perceived by 
the carers without specific reference to the information needed to understand the trial </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Use of proxies 
For participants who were deemed to lack capacity, consent/agreement was obtained from next 
of kin/legal representative/carer </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Consent/agreement was not obtained from next of kin/legal representative/carer 
0 
Assent procedure 
(if consent was 
obtained via 
proxy) </p>

<p>Verbal assent was obtained from the participants when receiving the intervention treatment or at 
the time of data collection ORIf neither treatment nor data collection involved the participant 
directly (eg, data collected from medical records), assent was not required </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>No assent was obtained 
0 </p>

<p>DiazOrdaz K, Slowther A-M, Potter R, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003057. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003057 </p>



<p>A systematic review of consent processes of CRTs in residential homes </p>

<p>We also examined trends over time in reporting ethical 
approval, reporting individual consent and quality of the 
consent processes, using logistic regression or ordinal 
logistic regression as appropriate, testing for assumptions 
of the models as appropriate and using a 5% signifi-
cance level in all analyses. Analyses were undertaken in 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">Stata</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">V.11</rs>. 20 
To see whether ethical reporting and conduct are 
better addressed by those whose trial reports were of 
higher quality in other respects or published in journals 
that put a greater emphasis on the quality of reporting, 
we fitted further logistic and ordinal regression models 
as appropriate, with accounting for clustering in sample 
size calculations, accounting for clustering in the analysis 
and the strength of the journal's endorsement of the 
extended CONSORT statement (no endorsement and 
weak endorsement vs moderate and strong endorse-
ment) as predictors. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
We identified 308 published reports via our electronic 
search, rejecting 248 on the basis of titles or abstracts. 
Additionally, 27 reports were found by hand-searching 
and reference-searching and three from consulting 
experts, making a total of 90 full-text papers to be exam-
ined (figure 1 in web appendix B). From these, 73 
primary reports met our eligibility criteria (see table C 
in web appendix C for a full-reference list). Basic charac-
teristics are reported in table 2. 
The strength of the CONSORT endorsement of the 
journals is reported in table B in web appendix 
A. Authors reported obtaining approval from a research 
ethics committee in 59 (81%) trials, obtaining individual </p>

<p>consent to participate in 51 (70%) trials and obtaining 
both in 45 (62%) trials. 
Among the 51 trials in which authors reported obtain-
ing individual consent, the process used to assess cap-
acity was described in detail for only 8 trials: in 4 trials, 
researchers asked the general practitioner or main staff 
carer for an assessment of capacity, and in 4 other trials, 
they interviewed each eligible resident. Nevertheless, 
proxies, usually next of kin, were used for consent in 37 
trials (table 3). Six of these trials, evaluating specific 
dementia interventions, described their processes in suf-
ficient detail for us to ascertain that they definitely did 
not assess capacity in any residents. In a further six 
trials, those deemed cognitively impaired were excluded 
from the trial, and in three other trials, consent was 
sought only in the experimental intervention arm. We 
rated only six publications as high for the quality of 
consent processes; none scored the maximum possible 
of six points. Twenty-two trial reports (43%) did not 
contain sufficient detail for us to score them. We did not 
receive any replies to our emails to a 10% sample of 
authors for further information about processes for 
assessing capacity and obtaining consent. 
Of the 22 trials for which authors did not report 
obtaining individual resident consent, we judged that in 
14 consent was either not required, or the description 
made it difficult to judge if consent was required, but if 
it had been, a waiver of consent could been appropriate 
(table 3). Examples of interventions used in these trials 
were staff training in fall prevention, or influenza vaccin-
ation administered to residence staff. In 8 of these 14 
trials, authors reported obtaining ethical approval. Of 
the 8 of the 22 trials that we judged needed consent 
from individual participants, 1 included an intervention 
aimed directly at residents, 1 included an intervention 
that was a manipulation of a resident's environment; 
both papers reported obtaining ethical approval. Five 
trials collected data directly from participants, and one 
collected identifiable data from other sources; of these, 
four reported obtaining ethical approval. 
As we judged that only eight of the trials in the review 
that did not report obtaining individual consent needed 
to do so, we did not perform any formal statistical ana-
lyses related to the propensity to obtain consent. There 
was a 14% higher odds of reporting ethical approval per 
year (95% CI 1.01 to 1.29). Ethical approval was more 
likely to be reported for trials in which clustering was 
accounted for correctly in the sample size calculation 
(OR 6.17 (95% CI 0.76 to 50.73)) and in the analysis 
(OR 2.66 (95% CI 0.78 to 9.03)). Among reports pub-
lished post-2004 (44 reports), the odds of reporting 
ethical approval was 8.85 (95% CI 1.34 to 58.34) times 
higher among those reports published in journals with 
moderate-to-strong extended CONSORT endorsement, 
when compared with those published in journals with 
low CONSORT endorsement. 
Among those trials for which authors reported obtain-
ing individual consent, the quality of consent processes </p>

<p>Table 2 Characteristics of included reports </p>

<p>Characteristic </p>

<p>Number of 
trials (%) </p>

<p>Publication year 
Published between 1992 and 2004 
29 (40) 
Published between 2005 and 2010 
44 (60) 
Country 
USA 
17 (23) 
UK 
16 (22) 
The Netherlands 
9 (12) 
Canada* 
7 (10) 
Australia 
5 (7) 
Sweden 
5 (7) 
Others 
14 (19) 
Clustering accounted for in sample size 
calculation </p>

<p>20 (27) </p>

<p>Clustering accounted for in analysis 
54 (74) 
Journal of publication endorses 
extended CONSORT statement for 
cluster-randomised trials 
(moderate-to-strong endorsement) † </p>

<p>33 (75) </p>

<p>*Of which two jointly with the USA. 
 †Based on the 44 reports published after 2004. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>DiazOrdaz K, Slowther A-M, Potter R, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003057. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003057 </p>

<p>A systematic review of consent processes of CRTs in residential homes </p>

<p>appeared to improve over time (ordinal logistic OR 1.12 
(95% CI 0.98 to 1.28)). Relationships between other 
quality markers and the quality of consent processes 
were weaker and not statistically significant at the 5% 
level, with ordinal logistic ORs of 1.65 (95% CI 0.53 to 
5.12) for the association with accounting for clustering 
in the sample size calculation, 2.49 (95% CI 0.77 to 
8.04) for the association with accounting for clustering 
in the analysis and 0.84 (95% 0.16 to 4.39) for the asso-
ciation with CONSORT endorsement. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
The majority of authors of trials in our review appeared 
to correctly understand when consent for residents' par-
ticipation was needed. However, the quality of reporting 
the ethical approval and consent processes was generally 
poor. Furthermore, 16% of trials reported ethically ques-
tionable practices: 8% seeking proxy consent without an 
assessment of residents' capacity, and 8% excluding 
patients with cognitive impairment without this assess-
ment. Authors of 22 trials did not provide enough infor-
mation for us to comment on the ethical quality of their 
consent processes. Trials published later are more likely </p>

<p>to report obtaining ethical approval and have higher 
quality consent processes. The reporting of ethical 
approval but not the quality of the consent process 
appears higher in trials in which other methodological 
quality markers and journal endorsement of reporting 
quality were also high. </p>

<p>Strengths and weaknesses 
Our rigorous review processes ensured that we included 
the majority of cluster randomised trials in residential 
and nursing homes. In spite of the limited potential for 
statistical analysis with only 73 trials in total and only 51 
reporting obtaining consent, our data suggest some 
trends in reporting of ethical approval and processes 
and some associations with other quality markers, 
though it is difficult to ascertain whether these trends 
are sustained, as we have not included papers reported 
since 2011. 
Our assessment of the quality of consent processes 
may not fully reflect conduct because space limitations 
in journals can preclude detailed descriptions. Owing to 
a lack of data, we were unable to assess the extent 
to which investigators had modified information given to 
potential participants to allow for cognitive impairment. </p>

<p>Table 3 Prevalence of characteristics of consent processes stratified by whether obtaining of individual consent was 
reported </p>

<p>Trials that report obtaining individual consent </p>

<p>Total 
N=51 </p>

<p>Report obtaining 
ethical approval 
N=45 </p>

<p>Did not report 
obtaining ethical 
approval N=6 </p>

<p>Published 
1992-2004 
N=22 </p>

<p>Published 
2005-2010 
N=29 </p>

<p>Reporting using proxy for consent 
37 (72%) 34 (76%) 
3 (50%) 
13 (59%) 
24 (83%) 
Type of proxy 
Next of kin or other relative 
19 (37%) 19 (42%) 
0 (0%) 
8 (36%) 
11 (38%) 
Family members or guardians 
6 (12%) 
4 (9%) 
2 (33%) 
3 (14%) 
3 (10%) 
Legal or designated guardian 
11 (22%) 10 (22%) 
1 (17%) 
2 (9%) 
9 (31%) 
Member of staff or relative 
1 (3%) 
1 (2%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) 
1 (3%) 
Reported process to assess 
capacity </p>

<p>8 (16%) 
7 (16%) 
1 (16%) 
2 (9%) 
6 (21%) </p>

<p>Quality of consent process: 
Insufficient details reported 
22 (43%) 18 (40%) 
4 (67%) 
12 (59%) 
10 (31%) 
Poor 
15 (29%) 15 (34%) 
0 (0%) 
5 (23%) 
10 (34%) 
Fair 
8 (16%) 
7 (16%) 
1 (17%) 
3 (14%) 
5 (17%) 
High 
6 (12%) 
5 (11%) 
1 (17%) 
2 (9%) 
4 (14%) </p>

<p>Trials that did not report obtaining individual consent </p>

<p>Total 
N=22 
N=14 
N=8 
N=7 
N=15 </p>

<p>No consent needed because of 
nature of intervention and data 
collection* </p>

<p>14 
8 (57%) 
6 (75%) 
5 (72%) 
9 (60%) </p>

<p>Consent needed because of data 
collection procedures </p>

<p>6 
4 (29%) 
2 (25%) 
1 (14%) 
5 (33%) </p>

<p>Consent needed because of type of 
intervention </p>

<p>2 
2 (14%) 
0 (0%) 
1 (14%) 
1 (7%) </p>

<p>*The intervention was aimed directly at the cluster or cluster staff, and there was no direct data collection from the home residents; there might 
have been identifiable private information obtained from other sources, but this was unclear and, if there were, we judged that a waiver could 
have been appropriate. </p>

<p>DiazOrdaz K, Slowther A-M, Potter R, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003057. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003057 </p>



<p>A systematic review of consent processes of CRTs in residential homes </p>

<p>Since we were unable to obtain further information 
from the selected sample of authors, it is not possible to 
establish the extent to which our findings reflect defi-
ciencies in study conduct or reporting or both. 
Moreover, the nature of the cluster intervention 
means that on many occasions a component of the inter-
vention is targeted at the residential home staff or at the 
healthcare professionals dedicated to the home. In 
these cases, the corresponding staff would be considered 
as research participants. As the focus of the present 
study was residents' consent procedures, we did not 
extract details on the nature of interventions, except for 
those 22 studies that did not report obtaining consent 
from the residents or their representatives. Among those 
studies, 21 interventions were targeted at the home staff 
or healthcare professionals, and informed consent 
should therefore have been obtained from them. 
However, only one study explicitly reported obtaining 
such consent. 
While this study supports previous research suggesting 
that reporting of ethics processes in cluster-randomised 
trials is poor, 16 it also provides reassurance that in 
general investigators are aware of the need to gain 
consent when necessary. Our study raises some con-
cerns, however, about the processes of obtaining a valid 
consent in cluster-randomised trials including partici-
pants with cognitive impairment. In this area, the 
correct ethical processes may be less well understood. In 
addition, investigators conducting cluster-randomised 
trials may have greater opportunity to overlook appropri-
ate ethical processes in obtaining individual consent 
than investigators conducting individually randomised 
trials because the focus in trial design is on initial 
recruitment, consent and randomisation of homes 
rather than of individuals. 
In 2004, a review of publications of trials including 
participants with Alzheimer's disease showed a similar 
lack of reporting of research ethics review and consent 
processes. 21 A review of 300 cluster-randomised trials 
found slightly higher proportions of trials reporting 
ethics committee reviews and obtaining consent. 16 This 
probably reflects the recent timescale of that review and 
the fact that it was not restricted to trials in residential 
and nursing homes. That review suggested, as does our 
review, greater reporting of ethical approval by authors 
of more recent trials and by authors of trials in which 
clustering was accounted for in the sample size calcula-
tions. Previous research highlights that assessing capacity 
can be difficult; that even experienced assessors often 
disagree in their assessment 22 ; that response rates from 
next of kin can be disappointing 23 24 ; and that proxy 
decisionmakers tend to be less likely to consent to 
research than participants themselves. 25 As far as we 
know, however, no previous work has attempted to 
review and score the quality of consent processes within 
empirical trials that include substantial numbers of 
adults who lack capacity. Similarly, we know of no previ-
ous research exploring the extent to which investigators </p>

<p>in cluster-randomised trials follow appropriate ethical 
processes in relation to obtaining individual consent. 
We agree with previous researchers that improvements 
are needed in the reporting of ethical approval and 
consent processes in cluster-randomised trials, 16 as well 
as in research with vulnerable adults. 21 Without consist-
ent accurate reporting, it is difficult to be sure that 
appropriate processes have been followed, or to improve 
such processes via further research and development. As 
full details of consent processes can take up consider-
able space, we recommend that a full description is 
given in an on-line supplement and a brief summary in 
the main article, at a minimum including whether or 
not investigators obtained ethics approval and consent 
for individual participation; if they did obtain such 
consent, who from; if they did not obtain consent, why </p>

<p>Box 1 Guidelines for individual informed consent pro-
cesses in adults involved in cluster-randomised trials in 
nursing or residential homes </p>

<p>1 The need for individual informed consent should be assessed 
using the recently drafted Ottawa guidelines recommendations 
regarding who a research participant is in these trials. An 
ethics committee should approve any decision not to obtain 
consent because individuals are not considered as research 
participants. Consent should be obtained from all research par-
ticipants unless the appropriate ethics committee agrees to a 
waiver. This waiver should be obtained even when the indivi-
duals are not research participants but routinely collected data 
pertaining to the individuals are to be used, and these data are 
not fully anonymised 
2 Where individual consent is required, the potential participant 
should be approached in the first instance and provided with 
information in an appropriate form to facilitate understanding 
and promote capacity 3 26 
3 If there is concern that the person does not have capacity, 
either during the consent process or because of a previously 
diagnosed cognitive impairment, capacity should be explicitly 
assessed by the researcher and recorded in the study docu-
mentation together with the next step in the consent process 
in accordance with the relevant legal framework (seek consent 
if person has capacity; identify a legally authorised proxy or 
consultee if person lacks capacity) 3 26 
4 Exclusion of potential participants because of cognitive impair-
ment should be explicitly justified (someone with cognitive 
impairment should not be assumed to lack capacity) 26 
5 Inclusion of participants who lack capacity should be explicitly 
justified. (The research cannot be carried out with people who 
have capacity and will directly benefit the participant or others 
with the same condition) 3 
6 Tests of cognitive function, such as the Mini Mental State 
Examination (MMSE), cannot be used as a proxy for capacity, 
but there is some evidence that they can be useful as a screen-
ing tool to identify participants in whom a full assessment of 
capacity is required 27 28 
7 For those who lack capacity, if data collection or the interven-
tion involves participants directly, then their assent should be 
obtained at the time of data collection or intervention 3 </p>



<p>DiazOrdaz K, Slowther A-M, Potter R, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003057. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003057 </p>

<p>A systematic review of consent processes of CRTs in residential homes </p>

<p>not; and who assessed capacity if this was necessary. 
While the accurate reporting of consent processes is 
important for transparency and ethical accountability, a 
more fundamental requirement is that the consent 
process does in fact comply with accepted ethical princi-
ples and regulatory standards. We have uncovered a 
need for greater understanding of how to conduct the 
consent process when researchers face the double chal-
lenge of including vulnerable adults in cluster-
randomised trials. Based on our findings, we present a 
guide to best practice for research involving older frail 
adults in residential care (box 1). All items are based on 
best practice with regard to the information we extracted 
from the trials in this review. Item 1 refers to the need 
to obtain ethical approval and consent and the judge-
ment about whom to approach for consent. Items 2-6 
refer to the information we extracted on the process for 
assessing capacity and obtaining consent. The guide 
draws on relevant ethical and legal requirements includ-
ing the Declaration of Helsinki, the Mental Capacity Act 
(England and Wales), and the Ottawa Statement. That 
the research is complex and obtaining valid consent is 
difficult is not a justification for treating this group of 
research participants with less care in relation to consent 
than that afforded to participants in a standard individu-
ally randomised trial involving competent adults. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements We thank Dr Robert Froud for extracting some of the 
data used in this review. </p>

<p>Contributors SE conceived the study. All authors contributed to the design. 
A-MS advised on the quality of capacity assessment and consent processes 
and designed the system for scoring consent processes. KDO wrote the 
protocol and extraction forms. The four authors undertook independent data 
extraction. KDO conducted all analyses. All authors had full access to all the 
data. KDO, SE and A-MS took primary responsibility for writing the 
manuscript and all authors provided comments on all versions of the paper. 
RF helped in extracting some data used in this review. </p>

<p>Funding This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in 
the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors. KDO was supported by a 
Research Methods Fellowship awarded by the National Institute for Health 
Research UK. </p>

<p>Competing interests KDO and SE accept full responsibility for the work 
and/or the conduct of the study, had access to the data and controlled the 
decision to publish. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement Statistical code and extraction dataset available from 
the corresponding author. </p>



<p>DiazOrdaz K, Slowther A-M, Potter R, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003057. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003057 </p>



<p>A systematic review of consent processes of CRTs in residential homes </p>

</text></tei>