<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3280433" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>(−)-Epigallocatechin-3-O-gallate (EGCG) has useful antiviral, antimicrobial, antitoxin, and 
antitumor properties. Previously, Mori et al. (2008) found that addition of long acyl chains 
(C16-18) to EGCG enhanced its anti-influenza virus activity up to 44-fold. The chemical sta-
bility of EGCG against oxidative degradation was also enhanced by acylation. We further 
evaluated the in vitro activity spectrum of the EGCG derivatives against a wide range of bac-
teria and fungi. A series of EGCG O-acyl derivatives were synthesized by lipase-catalyzed 
transesterification. These derivatives exhibited several-fold higher activities than EGCG, 
particularly against Gram-positive organisms. Antifungal MICs of the derivatives were also 
two to fourfold lower than those of EGCG. The activities of the EGCG derivatives against 
Gram-negative bacteria were not distinguishable from those of EGCG. Among the deriv-
atives evaluated, MICs of dioctanoate and palmitate (C16) for 17 Staphylococcus aureus 
strains were 4-32 μg/ml, although MIC of EGCG for these 17 strains was ≥128 μg/ml. 
C16 demonstrated rapid bactericidal activity against methicillin-resistant S. aureus (MRSA) 
ATCC43300 at ≥16 μg/ml. The enhanced activity of C16 against S. aureus was supported 
by its increased membrane-permeabilizing activity determined by increased SYTOX Green 
uptake. The EGCG derivatives were exported in Escherichia coli using the efflux pump 
AcrAB-TolC. The tolC deletion mutant exhibited higher sensitivity to EGCG and the deriv-
atives than wild-type. Addition of long alkyl chains to EGCG significantly enhanced its 
activities against several bacteria and fungi, particularly against S. aureus including MRSA. 
C16 might potentially become under specified circumstances an alternative or supplement 
to antibiotics and disinfectants in the future. </p>

<p>Green tea has long been a daily food in Japan with beneficial 
health effects. Antibacterial and antitoxin effects of tea (Camellia 
sinensis) leaves are already proved in Japan in 1930s (Shima-
mura, 2009). After World War II, anti-influenza virus activity of 
tea extracts was published in 1949 (Green, 1949), and antibac-
terial activity of tea was published in India (Das, 1962). More 
than a quarter of a century later, antibacterial activity of tea 
was eventually rediscovered in 1989 (Toda et al., 1989). Since 
then, recent studies proved that polyphenol components of tea 
leaves have antitoxin (Hara et al., 1990; Toda et al., 1990; Hisano 
et al., 2003), antiviral (Mukoyama et al., 1991; Nakayama et al., 
1993; Yamaguchi et al., 2002), and antitumor properties (Mukhtar 
et al., 1992; Shimamura and Hara, 1997) other than antimicro-
bial activity (Toda et al., 1989; Yam et al., 1997). Tea polyphenols 
have broad antibacterial spectrum, and inhibit various kinds of 
pathogenic bacteria such as Bacillus cereus, Campylobacter spp., 
Clostridium perfringens, Escherichia coli O157, Helicobacter pylori, 
Legionella pneumophila, Mycobacterium tuberculosis, Mycoplasma </p>

<p>pneumonia, Proteus vulgaris, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Salmonella 
spp., Serratia marcescens, Staphylococcus spp., oral pathogenic 
Streptococci (Friedman, 2007). In polyphenols, catechins belong 
to the flavan-3-ol class of flavonoids. Catechins are thermo sta-
ble and stable in acidic condition although those are unstable 
in neutral and alkali condition. (−)-Epigallocatechin-3-O-gallate 
(EGCG) is the major polyphenolic compound found in green tea 
and it has the strongest activity in various useful properties. How-
ever, although antiviral properties of tea polyphenols have been 
demonstrated also in vivo (Xiao et al., 2008), EGCG is not so 
useful for clinical use because of its poor membrane permeabil-
ity, low chemical stability, and rapid metabolism. Previously, we 
synthesized a series of EGCG fatty acid monoester derivatives by 
lipase-catalyzed transesterification and found that addition of long 
acyl chains (C16-18) enhanced the anti-influenza virus activity of 
EGCG up to 44-fold (Mori et al., 2008). Acylation also enhanced 
the in vitro antitumor activities of EGCG in an alkyl chain length-
dependent manner (Matsumura et al., 2008). Furthermore, the 
chemical stability of EGCG in tissue culture medium was enhanced </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 53 | 1 </p>

<p>Matsumoto et al. </p>

<p>Acylation-enhanced EGCG antimicrobial activities </p>

<p>10-fold by acylation (Data not shown). But effects of acylation 
on antimicrobial and antitoxin activities of EGCG have not yet 
been evaluated until now. In this study, we additionally synthesized 
unsaturated fatty acid esters and dioctanoyl esters, and evaluated 
the in vitro activities of the acylated EGCG derivatives against 
a wide range of bacteria and fungi. These derivatives exhibited 
increased antimicrobial activities, particularly against Staphylococ-
cus aureus and some fungal species. The antibacterial activity of 
palmitate was evaluated in detail. Taken together, these data show 
a potential use of EGCG O-acyl derivatives as novel antimicrobial 
agents. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>SYNTHESIS OF EGCG O-ACYL DERIVATIVES </p>

<p>A series of EGCG O-acyl derivatives (Figure 1; Table 1) were 
synthesized by lipase-catalyzed transesterification, according to </p>

<p>FIGURE 1 | Lipase-catalyzed synthesis of EGCG fatty acid esters. One 
or two of R 
1-4 are substituted with fatty acids. </p>

<p>a method reported previously (Mori et al., 2008). This method 
yielded B-ring-modified esters as the major products except linole-
nate ester (C18TE). In case of synthesis of saturated fatty acid 
monoesters, the ratio of regioisomers was consistent regard-
less of the alkyl chain length. Unsaturated fatty acid esters 
and dioctanoyl esters (C8 × 2) were also synthesized, and the 
ratio of their regioisomers is summarized in Table 1. Mix-
tures of these isomers were used without isolation because 
they have similar chemical properties and the antiviral activ-
ities of these mixtures did not vary with their composition 
ratio (Mori et al., 2008). Log P values were calculated by a 
software; <rs id="software-0" type="software">ChemBioDraw Ultra</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 11</rs> and used as lipophilicity 
index (Table 1). Higher log P means higher lipophilicity. The 
derivatives were dissolved in DMSO and diluted with distilled 
water. </p>

<p>BACTERIAL STRAINS </p>

<p>In total, 17 S. aureus strains [9 methicillin-sensitive S. aureus 
(MSSA) and 8 methicillin-resistant S. aureus (MRSA) strains]. 
Five MSSA and seven MRSA strains were clinically iso-
lated from Japan (Table 2). E. coli MG1655 (wild-type) 
and its efflux pump gene deletion mutants, ΔacrB, ΔacrD, 
ΔacrEF, and ΔtolC constructed by phage P1-mediated trans-
duction (Davis et al., 1980; Nishino et al., 2008) were used 
to evaluate the effects of efflux pumps on the susceptibil-
ity of E. coli to EGCG. Moreover, standard strains of var-
ious bacterial and fungal species (Tables 3-5) were also 
analyzed. </p>

<p>Table 1 | EGCG fatty acid esters and the ratio of their regioisomers. </p>

<p>Abbreviation 
Acyl group 
Position of acyl group on EGCG </p>

<p>fatty acid esters (%) a ; R 1 :R 2 :R 3 :R 4 </p>

<p>Log P c </p>

<p>EGCG 
None 
2.07 </p>

<p>C8 (octanoate) 
35:39:6:20 
4.79 </p>

<p>C12 (laurate) 
30:39:9:22 
6.46 </p>

<p>C8 × 2 (dioctanoate) 
ND b 
7.50 </p>

<p>C16 (palmitate) 
38:35:7:20 
8.13 </p>

<p>C16E (palmitoleate) 
28:37:9:26 
7.81 </p>

<p>C18 (stearate) 
38:35:7:20 
8.97* </p>

<p>C18E (oleate) 
41:34:5:20 
8.65* </p>

<p>C18DE (linoleate) 
28:27:5:45 
8.33* </p>

<p>C18TE (linolenate) 
15:19:4:62 
8.01 </p>

<p>C20 (eicosanoate) 
28:37:9:26 
9.80* </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>The ratio of regioisomers was determined by 
1 H-NMR spectroscopy. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>The regioisomers could not be determined by 
1 H-NMR, but the product was identified by mass </p>

<p>spectroscopy. 
c Log P values were calculated using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">ChemBioDraw Ultra</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">ver. 11</rs> software. *The values were estimated on the basis of the log P values of fatty </p>

<p>acids. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Microbiology | Antimicrobials, Resistance and Chemotherapy </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 53 | 2 </p>

<p>Matsumoto et al. </p>

<p>Acylation-enhanced EGCG antimicrobial activities </p>

<p>Table 2 | MICs of EGCG derivatives for S. aureus. </p>

<p>Strain 
MIC: μg/ml </p>

<p>EGCG and its derivatives 
Antimicrobials </p>

<p>C8 × 2 
C16 
C16E 
C18 
C18E 
C18DE 
C18TE 
EGCG 
AMP 
IPM 
ERY </p>

<p>MSSA </p>

<p>NCTC8325 
4 
8 
16 
16 
16 
16 
4 
128 
0.125 
0.008 
0.25 </p>

<p>ATCC25923 
16 
16 
32 
32 
32 
32 
32 
&gt;128 
0.25 
0.031 
0.5 </p>

<p>ATCC12600 
8 
16 
16 
32 
32 
16 
16 
&gt;128 
0.5 
0.031 
0.5 </p>

<p>ATCC29213 
16 
16 
16 
32 
32 
16 
16 
&gt;128 
4 
0.063 
0.5 </p>

<p>S1* 
16 
16 
16 
32 
32 
16 
16 
&gt;128 
8 
0.031 
0.5 </p>

<p>S2* 
16 
16 
16 
32 
32 
16 
16 
&gt;128 
8 
0.031 
0.5 </p>

<p>S3* 
16 
16 
16 
32 
32 
16 
16 
&gt;128 
8 
0.031 
64 </p>

<p>S4* 
16 
16 
16 
32 
32 
16 
16 
&gt;128 
0.5 
0.063 
1 </p>

<p>S5* 
16 
16 
16 
32 
32 
16 
16 
128 
0.5 
0.008 
1 </p>

<p>MRSA </p>

<p>ATCC43300 
16 
16 
16 
32 
32 
16 
16 
&gt;128 
32 
≤0.125 
&gt;128 </p>

<p>R1* 
16 
16 
16 
32 
32 
32 
16 
&gt;128 
64 
≤0.125 
&gt;128 </p>

<p>R2* 
16 
16 
16 
32 
16 
16 
16 
&gt;128 
64 
≤0.125 
0.5 </p>

<p>R3* 
4 
8 
8 
16 
8 
8 
8 
128 
64 
4 
&gt;128 </p>

<p>R4* 
16 
32 
64 
128 
64 
64 
64 
&gt;128 
128 
&gt;16 
&gt;128 </p>

<p>R5* 
16 
16 
16 
32 
16 
16 
16 
&gt;128 
128 
2 
&gt;128 </p>

<p>R6* 
32 
32 
64 
64 
64 
32 
64 
&gt;128 
32 
&gt;16 
&gt;128 </p>

<p>R7* 
16 
16 
16 
64 
32 
16 
16 
&gt;128 
128 
16 
&gt;128 </p>

<p>*Clinical isolates from Japan. </p>

<p>Table 3 | Antibacterial activities of C16 against Gram-positive bacteria. </p>

<p>Organism 
(MIC: μg/ml) </p>

<p>C16 
EGCG 
AMX 
CFZ 
ERY 
VAN </p>

<p>Bacillus subtilis ATCC6051 
16 
64 
0.06 
0.25 
≤0.03 
0.125 </p>

<p>Bacillus cereus ATCC14579 
16 
64 
2 
64 
0.06 
0.5 </p>

<p>Staphylococcus epidermidis ATCC14990 
8 
128 
0.125 
0.5 
0.125 
1 </p>

<p>Streptococcus pneumoniae ATCC49619 
16 
32 
≤0.03 
1 
≤0.03 
0.125 </p>

<p>Streptococcus pyogenes ATCC19615 
64 
128 
≤0.03 
0.25 
≤0.03 
0.25 </p>

<p>Streptococcus agalactiae ATCC13813 
&gt;64 
&gt;128 
≤0.03 
0.125 
≤0.03 
0.25 </p>

<p>Enterococcus faecalis ATCC29212 
16 
256 
0.25 
32 
2 
2 </p>

<p>Micrococcus luteus ATCC9341 
32 
128 
0.06 
2 
≤0.03 
0.5 </p>

<p>ANTIBACTERIAL AGENTS AND CHEMICALS </p>

<p>Ampicillin (AMP), amoxicillin (AMX), cefazolin (CFZ), and van-
comycin (VAN) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich Co. (St Louis, 
USA). Imipenem (IPM, Banyu Pharmaceutical Co., Tokyo, Japan), 
erythromycin (ERY, Nacalai Tesque Inc., Kyoto, Japan), teicoplanin 
(TEC, Astellas Pharma Inc., Tokyo, Japan), and nisin (MP Bio-
medicals, LLC, Illkirch, France) were also used. Fluconazole (FLC, 
Sigma-Aldrich Co.) was used for experiments with fungi. </p>

<p>DETERMINATION OF MICs </p>

<p>MICs were determined by the micro broth dilution method using 
Mueller-Hinton broth (Difco, Becton, Dickinson, and Company </p>

<p>Japan, Tokyo, Japan) according to guidelines M07-A8 of the Clini-
cal and Laboratory Standards Institute (2009; CLSI, Wayne, PA, 
USA). OD 600 was determined using a microplate reader after 
overnight incubation. For Figure 2, average and SD of OD 600 
of four wells for each concentration were calculated. RPMI 
1640 medium (Sigma-Aldrich Co.) buffered with 0.165 M 3-(N -
morpholino) propane sulfonic acid at pH 7.0 was used for fungi. 
Effects of peptidoglycan from S. aureus, d-Ala-d-Ala, and 
lipopolysaccharide (LPS; all purchased from Sigma-Aldrich Co.) 
on the antistaphylococcal activities of C16 were evaluated by 
comparison of MIC with or without 30 μg/ml of each bacterial 
cell component according to the literature (Zhao et al., 2001). </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 53 | 3 </p>

<p>Matsumoto et al. </p>

<p>Acylation-enhanced EGCG antimicrobial activities </p>

<p>Table 4 | Antibacterial activities of C16 against Gram-negative bacteria. </p>

<p>Organism 
(MIC: μg/ml) </p>

<p>C16 
EGCG 
AMX 
CFZ 
ERY 
VAN </p>

<p>Neisseria meningitidis* 
16 
32 
0.25 
0.5 
0.25 
2 </p>

<p>Neisseria gonorrhoeae ATCC49226 
16 
32 
0.5 
4 
4 
32 </p>

<p>Haemophilus influenzae ATCC49766 
&gt;64 
&gt;256 
0.5 
2 
8 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Moraxella catarrhalis* 
64 
128 
0.25 
0.5 
0.125 
64 </p>

<p>Escherichia coli ATCC25922 
&gt;64 
&gt;256 
8 
2 
64 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Klebsiella pneumoniae ATCC13883 
&gt;64 
&gt;256 
&gt;64 
2 
64 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Klebsiella oxytoca ATCC8724 
&gt;64 
&gt;256 
64 
2 
128 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Citrobacter freundii ATCC8090 
&gt;64 
&gt;256 
64 
32 
128 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Enterobacter cloacae ATCC13047 
&gt;64 
&gt;256 
&gt;64 
&gt;128 
&gt;128 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Enterobacter aerogenes ATCC13048 
&gt;64 
&gt;256 
&gt;64 
128 
128 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Proteus mirabilis ATCC29906 
&gt;64 
&gt;256 
0.5 
4 
&gt;128 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Proteus vulgaris ATCC13315 
&gt;64 
&gt;256 
16 
32 
&gt;64 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Serratia marcescens ATCC13880 
&gt;64 
&gt;256 
64 
&gt;64 
64 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Salmonella typhimurium IID1000 
&gt;64 
&gt;256 
0.5 
1 
64 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Yersinia enterocolitica ATCC9610 
&gt;64 
&gt;256 
4 
1 
32 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Aeromonas hydrophila ATCC7966 
&gt;64 
&gt;256 
&gt;64 
32 
16 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Pseudomonas aeruginosa ATCC7700 
&gt;64 
&gt;256 
&gt;64 
&gt;128 
128 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Pseudomonas fluorescence ATCC8750 
&gt;64 
&gt;256 
8 
16 
32 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia ATCC13637 
&gt;64 
&gt;256 
&gt;64 
128 
16 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Campylobacter jejuni ATCC33291 
8 
8 
4 
&gt;64 
2 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>Helicobacter pylori ATCC43504 
16 
16 
≤0.03 
0.25 
0.125 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>*A clinical isolates from Japan. </p>

<p>Table 5 | Antifungal activities of EGCG derivatives. </p>

<p>Organism 
EGCG and its derivatives (MIC: μg/ml) </p>

<p>C8 × 2 
C16 
C16E 
C18 
C18E 
C18DE 
C18TE 
EGCG 
Fluconazole </p>

<p>Candida albicans ATCC24433 
32 
32 
16 
16 
16 
16 
16 
64 
0.25 </p>

<p>Candida parapsilosis ATCC22019 
16 
16 
16 
16 
16 
16 
16 
64 
2 </p>

<p>Candida tropicalis ATCC750 
32 
32 
16 
32 
32 
32 
16 
64 
2 </p>

<p>Candida krusei ATCC6258 
16 
16 
16 
16 
16 
16 
16 
64 
32 </p>

<p>Candida glabrata ATCC90030 
16 
16 
16 
16 
16 
32 
32 
32 
16 </p>

<p>Cryptococcus neoformans ATCC90112 
16 
8 
8 
16 
16 
8 
8 
64 
1 </p>

<p>Aspergillus fumigatus* 
32 
32 
16 
32 
32 
32 
16 
64 
&gt;64 </p>

<p>*A clinical isolate from Japan. </p>

<p>The combinatorial effects of C16 or EGCG with IPM or 
AMP on MRSA were determined by the checkerboard method 
(Martinez-Irujo et al., 1996; Hu et al., 2001). The fractional 
inhibitory concentration (FIC) indices were calculated as fol-
lows: FIC = [MIC A in combination /MIC A alone + MIC B in combination / 
MIC B alone ]. Synergy was defined as an FIC index of less than 0.5 
and addition as an FIC index of 0.5-1.0. </p>

<p>DETERMINATION OF KILLING ACTIVITIES </p>

<p>Killing curves of C16 against MRSA ATCC43300, E. coli MG1655, 
and P. aeruginosa PAO1 were plotted and evaluated. Bacterial 
suspensions were diluted to approximately 1.0 × 10 5 CFUs/ml </p>

<p>in Mueller-Hinton broth. Bacterial counts were determined at 
selected time intervals of 0, 2, 4, and 6 h by enumerating the 
colonies formed after plating 10-fold serially diluted specimens 
of 100 μl aliquots on two Mueller-Hinton agar plates for each 
dilution; the plates were incubated at 37˚C. The average numbers 
and SD of two to four plates were calculated. </p>

<p>SYTOX GREEN UPTAKE ASSAY TO DETERMINE MEMBRANE DAMAGE </p>

<p>Exponentially growing cells of MSSA ATCC25923 and MRSA 
ATCC43300 harvested in phosphate-buffered saline were used. 
SYTOX Green (Lonza Walkersville, Inc., USA) is a high-affinity 
nucleic acid stain that can easily penetrate cells with compromised </p>

<p>Frontiers in Microbiology | Antimicrobials, Resistance and Chemotherapy </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 53 | 4 </p>

<p>Matsumoto et al. </p>

<p>Acylation-enhanced EGCG antimicrobial activities </p>

<p>membranes but not those with intact membranes. Membrane 
integrity was determined after exposure to C16, EGCG or nisin 
for 15 min by measuring SYTOX Green uptake. Using the plate 
reader, fluorescence was determined (Ex/Em: 504/523 nm) after 
10 min incubation with SYTOX Green in a black 384-well plate 
(Matsumoto et al., 2011). The means and SD values of triple data 
were calculated. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN ACYL CHAIN LENGTH AND ACTIVITIES OF 
EGCG O-ACYL DERIVATIVES AGAINST S. AUREUS </p>

<p>Structures of the EGCG O-acyl derivatives and the ratio of each 
acyl component are listed in Figure 1 and Table 1. S. aureus is one 
of the most sensitive organisms to tea extract (Toda et al., 1989). 
The effect of acyl chain length on antistaphylococcal activity was 
evaluated (Figure 2) on the basis of the results of a previous study 
on antiviral activities of the acylated EGCG derivatives against 
influenza virus. These antiviral activities were increased in an 
acyl chain length-dependent manner (Mori et al., 2008). Growth 
inhibitory activities of EGCG for MSSA ATCC25923 and MRSA 
ATCC43300 were not increased by C8, but were increased by acyl 
chains longer than C12. However, these activities decreased in the 
derivatives with an acyl chain length longer than C18. C12 and 
C16 showed the strongest activity (MIC; 8 μg/ml) against both 
ATCC25923 and ATCC43300 strains. We then synthesized C8 × 2, 
C16E, C18E, C18DE, and C18TE and evaluated the effect of dia-
cyl as well as unsaturated acyl chains against 17 S. aureus strains 
including 8 MRSA strains (Table 2). Although most of these strains 
had similar sensitivities to the EGCG derivatives, some MRSA 
strains, particularly IPM-resistant strains, exhibited higher MICs. 
C8 × 2 was similar to C16 and had the strongest activity among 
this set of derivatives. In C18 series of derivatives, unsaturation of 
fatty acid moieties increased the antimicrobial activity, although 
this effect was not evident in C16. The log P values of these deriva-
tives indicated that water solubility improved by the introduction </p>

<p>of an unsaturated bond into C18 (Table 1). Among the deriv-
atives evaluated, MICs of C8 × 2 and C16 for all the 17 strains 
were ≤32 μg/ml, although MICs of EGCG for these strains were 
≥128 μg/ml. </p>

<p>ANTIMICROBIAL ACTIVITIES OF C16 AGAINST VARIOUS SPECIES </p>

<p>Antibacterial and antifungal activities of C16 are presented in 
Tables 3-5. Table 3 shows MICs for Gram-positive organisms 
other than S. aureus. C16 showed several-fold higher activities than 
EGCG against these microbial strains except Streptococci, against 
which there was less than twofold difference between MICs of both 
compounds. C16 exhibited 16-fold superior activities against S. 
epidermidis and Enterococcus faecalis than EGCG. Suppression of 
growth of Gram-negative bacteria was barely detected at the high-
est concentrations of C16 or EGCG (Table 4), making it difficult to 
distinguish the differences in their activities based on their MICs. 
While Gram-negative bacteria tend to be insensitive to EGCG, C. 
jejuni and H. pylori were highly sensitive to EGCG and C16. Neis-
seria meningitidis and N. gonorrhoeae also exhibited sensitivity 
to C16. 
Antifungal activity of EGCG and its acyl derivatives were evalu-
ated against various species of Candida, Cryptococcus neoformans, 
and Aspergillus fumigatus (Table 5). MICs of the derivatives for 
these fungi were two to fourfold superior to those of EGCG. C16E 
exhibited the highest activities against these fungi. Introduction 
of unsaturated bonds into the acyl chain tended to increase the 
antifungal activities of the derivatives. </p>

<p>KILLING ACTIVITIES OF C16 </p>

<p>The rapid bactericidal activity of tea extracts against S. aureus are 
known through research on the antibacterial activities of cate-
chins (Toda et al., 1989). A time-kill study was conducted against 
MRSA ATCC43300, E. coli MG1655, and P. aeruginosa PAO1 
(Figure 3). C16 demonstrated rapid bactericidal activity against 
MRSA at ≥16 μg/ml. However, 128 μg/ml of C16 only showed </p>

<p>FIGURE 2 | Acyl chain length of EGCG derivatives and their antistaphylococcal activities against MSSA ATCC25923 (A) and MRSA ATCC43300 (B). 
Mean ∓ SD of each four wells optical density (600 nm) after 18 h incubation are shown. </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 53 | 5 </p>

<p>Matsumoto et al. </p>

<p>Acylation-enhanced EGCG antimicrobial activities </p>

<p>FIGURE 3 | Killing activity of C16 against MRSA ATCC43300 (A), E. coli 
MG1655 (B), and P. aeruginosa PAO1 (C). Cells were incubated with C16 in 
Muller-Hinton broth at 37˚C on a shaker. Residual cells after 2, 4, and 6 h </p>

<p>incubation were counted as colonies grown on the Mueller-Hinton agar 
plates. Mean ∓ SD of the residual CFUs calculated from two to four plates are 
shown. </p>

<p>bacteriostatic activity against E. coli MG1655 and P. aeruginosa 
PAO1. </p>

<p>COMBINATORIAL EFFECTS OF C16 ON ANTIBACTERIAL ACTIVITY OF 
β-LACTAMS IN THE CHECKERBOARD METHOD </p>

<p>The synergistic effects of EGCG with β-lactams have been well 
described (Hu et al., 2001, 2002a). C16 and EGCG were evaluated 
in combination with IPM or AMP against MRSA strains (Figures 4 
and 5). We used two MRSA strains, IPM-sensitive ATCC43300 
and IPM-resistant clinical isolate R3. C16 enhanced the activ-
ities of IPM and AMP against both MRSA strains (Figure 4); 
the FIC indices were 0.5-1.0. On the other hand, EGCG exhib-
ited negative activity with IPM against IPM-sensitive ATCC43300 
(Figure 5A), although synergy between EGCG and IPM (FIC 
index &lt; 0.07) against IPM-resistant strain R3 was remarkable 
(Figure 5B). EGCG also showed pronounced synergistic activ-
ity with AMP against both MRSA strains (FIC indices &lt;0.188; 
Figures 4C,D). In other words, MIC of IPM for R3 was decreased 
by 8 μg/ml EGCG from &gt;4 to 0.063 μg/ml, whereas 8 μg/ml of 
C16 inhibited the growth of R3 by itself. C16 and EGCG exhib-
ited negative activity with IPM or AMP against MSSA (data not 
shown) which was similar to that shown in Figure 5A. </p>

<p>EFFECT OF PEPTIDOGLYCAN ON ANTISTAPHYLOCOCCAL ACTIVITY 
OF C16 </p>

<p>The bactericidal activity of EGCG against S. aureus was blocked 
by the purified peptidoglycan (Yoda et al., 2004). Effects of pep-
tidoglycan, d-Ala-d-Ala, and LPS, on the activity of C16 against 
MSSA ATCC25923 and MRSA ATCC43300 were determined by 
changes in MIC caused by the addition of each component to the 
medium (Table 6). MICs of C16 for both bacterial strains were 
reproducible and doubled in the presence of peptidoglycan as well 
as MICs of glycopeptide,VAN, and TEC. However MICs of C16 did 
not change with the addition of d-Ala-d-Ala or LPS. In contrast, 
MICs of VAN and TEC increased 8-and 32-fold respectively, with 
the addition of d-Ala-d-Ala, the target molecule of glycopeptides 
in cell walls. </p>

<p>FIGURE 4 | Combinatorial effects of C16 with IPM (A,B) or AMP (C,D) 
against MRSA strains. Optical densities (600 nm) after 18 h incubation 
were determined by the checkerboard method. </p>

<p>EFFECT OF EFFLUX PUMP DELETION ON ACTIVITIES OF EGCG O-ACYL 
DERIVATIVES IN E. COLI </p>

<p>Efflux pumps are major resistant factors in Gram-negative bacteria 
(Poole et al., 1993; Nikaido, 1998; Li and Nikaido, 2004). E. coli has 
several pumps that effect drug resistance (Nishino and Yamaguchi, 
2001). Effects of deletion of genes associated with three of these 
pumps, AcrAB-TolC, AcrCD-TolC, and AcrEF-TolC were evalu-
ated. AcrAB-TolC is the most powerful pump that is constitutively 
expressed in E. coli and has a broad substrate profile (Nishino and 
Yamaguchi, 2001). To evaluate the possibility of EGCG and its 
derivatives to act as a substrate for efflux pumps, MICs of the 
EGCG derivatives for efflux pump gene deletion mutants of E. 
coli MG1655 were determined (Table 7). MICs of all tested deriv-
atives and EGCG for ΔacrB and ΔtolC were lower than those 
for the wild-type strain. The acrD or acrEF deletion had almost 
no effect on the activities of the EGCG derivatives against E. coli. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Microbiology | Antimicrobials, Resistance and Chemotherapy </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 53 | 6 </p>

<p>Matsumoto et al. </p>

<p>Acylation-enhanced EGCG antimicrobial activities </p>

<p>FIGURE 5 | Combinatorial effects of EGCG with IPM (A,B) or AMP (C,D) 
against MRSA strains. Optical densities (600 nm) after 18 h incubation 
were determined by the checkerboard method. </p>

<p>Table 6 | Effect of peptidoglycan, D-Ala-D-Ala, and lipopolysaccharide </p>

<p>on antistaphylococcal activity of C16. </p>

<p>Agents 
ATCC25923 (MIC: μg/ml) 
ATCC43300 (MIC: μg/ml) </p>

<p>control 
PG 
D-Ala 
LPS 
control 
PG 
D-Ala </p>

<p>C16 
16 
32 
16 
16 
8 
16 
8 </p>

<p>VAN 
2 
4 
1 6 
2 
1 
2 
1 6 </p>

<p>TEC 
1 
2 
3 2 
1 
0.5 
1 
1 6 </p>

<p>AMP 
0.25 
0.25 
0.25 
0.25 
16 
8 
16 </p>

<p>Staphylococcus aureus ATCC25923 and methicillin-resistant S. aureus </p>

<p>ATCC43300 were used. PG, peptidoglycan; D-Ala, D-Ala-D-Ala; LPS, </p>

<p>lipopolysaccharide. Bold letters indicate increased MICs versus control. </p>

<p>EGCG and its acyl derivatives were considered to be substrates for 
AcrAB-TolC. Susceptibility of ΔtolC, a mutant in which all TolC-
dependent pumps are inactive, to the C8 × 2 was fourfold higher 
than that to EGCG. </p>

<p>MEMBRANE DAMAGE DETERMINED BY SYTOX GREEN UPTAKE ASSAY </p>

<p>The bacterial membrane is considered to be one of the 
most effective targets of catechins (Kajiya et al., 2004). The 
membrane-disrupting activities of C16 were compared with those 
of EGCG in MSSA ATCC25923 and MRSA ATCC43300 (Figure 6). 
Under this condition, a polycyclic antibacterial peptide nisin at 
1 μg/ml significantly increased SYTOX Green uptake in both 
bacterial strains. In a concentration-dependent manner, C16 
increased SYTOX Green uptake at ≥8 μg/ml (a half of MIC) 
after 15 min incubation with S. aureus cells, while EGCG did not 
induce SYTOX Green uptake at 128 μg/ml. EGCG at 64 μg/ml 
actually exhibited a protective effect; SYTOX Green uptake was 
less than a half of the dye uptake observed with controls. C16 dis-
rupted the membrane of S. aureus more effectively than EGCG, 
which supports the previously observed low MIC of C16 for S. 
aureus. </p>

<p>Table 7 | Activities of EGCG derivatives against efflux pump gene </p>

<p>deletion mutants of E. coli. </p>

<p>Strains 
EGCG and its derivatives (MIC: μg/ml) </p>

<p>C8 × 2 
C16 
C16E 
C18TE 
EGCG </p>

<p>MG1655 (Wild-type) 
&gt;128 
&gt;128 
&gt;128 
&gt;128 
&gt;256 </p>

<p>ΔacrB 
64 
64 
64 
64 
128 </p>

<p>ΔtolC 
32 
64 
64 
64 
128 </p>

<p>ΔacrD 
&gt;128 
&gt;128 
&gt;128 
&gt;128 
&gt;256 </p>

<p>ΔacrEF 
&gt;128 
&gt;128 
&gt;128 
&gt;128 
&gt;256 </p>

<p>Escherichia coli MG1655 and its efflux pump gene deletion mutants were used. </p>

<p>FIGURE 6 | Membrane damage caused by C16 determined by SYTOX 
Green uptake assay. Fluorescence was determined (Ex/Em: 504/523 nm) 
after 10 min incubation with SYTOX Green in a black 384-well plate using a 
microplate reader after incubation with the antimicrobial compound for 
15 min. Fluorescence is shown as a ratio to that of control. Data represent 
Mean ∓ SD (n = 3). *A polycyclic antibacterial peptide. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Staphylococcus aureus is one of the most sensitive bacteria to tea 
polyphenols. The rapid bactericidal activity of tea extracts against 
S. aureus was demonstrated in 1989 (Toda et al., 1989), and the 
mechanism underlying the killing activity of catechin by disrupt-
ing the lipid bilayer of the membrane (Ikigai et al., 1993). Subse-
quently, interaction of catechin with lipid bilayers has been studied 
in detail (Kumazawa et al., 2004; Uekusa et al., 2007; Kajiya et al., 
2008; Kamihira et al., 2008; Sirk et al., 2008, 2009, 2011; Sun et al., 
2009). Previously, Kajiya et al. synthesized (+)-Catechin deriva-
tives with different alkyl chain lengths and found the antibacterial 
activity increased markedly with elongation of the alkyl chain 
lengths of the derivatives and reached a maximum at a chain of 
four to seven carbons. Lipophilicity and the membrane-disrupting 
ability of these derivatives correlate with their antibacterial activ-
ities against Gram-positive organisms (Kajiya et al., 2004). In our 
study, addition of acyl chains longer than C12 to EGCG signifi-
cantly enhanced its antibacterial activities particularly against S. 
aureus including MRSA. However, the activity of EGCG O-acyl 
derivatives decreased in the derivatives with an acyl chain length 
longer than C18, so that C12 and C16 had the highest activity 
against S. aureus (Figure 2). MICs of C8 × 2 for the 17 S. aureus </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 53 | 7 </p>

<p>Matsumoto et al. </p>

<p>Acylation-enhanced EGCG antimicrobial activities </p>

<p>strains were the lowest and comparable to those of C16 (Table 2). 
The increased activities of these derivatives against S. aureus are 
probably a result of their enhanced affinity of their long acyl chains 
to interact with membranes. In fact, 8 μg/ml of C16 showed sig-
nificant membrane-permeabilizing activity in S. aureus. On the 
other hand, EGCG inhibited SYTOX Green uptake to less than a 
half of the control at 64 μg/ml (Figure 6). As an explanation of the 
opposite effect of 64 μg/ml EGCG in SYTOX Green uptake assay, 
peptidoglycan-binding activity of EGCG could be higher than its 
affinity to membrane and interfered penetration of SYTOX Green 
into Staphylococcal cells. SYTOX Green would be permeabilized 
by EGCG in concentrations higher than its MIC. Against influenza 
virus, C16 also exhibited the strongest activity, suggesting an inter-
action with the viral membrane (Mori et al., 2008); however, the 
derivatives with acyl chains longer than 16 exhibited decreased 
activities probably because of their decreased solubility. The role 
of decreased solubility as being a possible reason was deduced from 
the higher lipophilicity speculated from the higher log P values in 
C18 and C20 (Table 1). Introduction of an unsaturated bond into 
the acyl chain tended to reduce lipophilicity and recover the activ-
ity, although it was not very effective in C16 (Table 2). Anyway, 
influenza virus is more sensitive to C16 than S. aureus and E. coli. 
The effect of acyl chain length on antistaphylococcal activity of 
EGCG was similar but not coincident with that on anti-influenza 
virus activity of it. The difference might come from the different 
surface structure of these pathogens such as cell wall in S. aureus 
rather than common lipid bilayer. Outer membrane and cell wall 
of bacteria might protect lipid bilayer from polyphenols. Acylation 
might possible to enhance interaction of EGCG with lipid bilayer 
but not break through outer membrane. 
Synergistic activities of EGCG with β-lactams against MRSA 
have been studied previously (Hu et al., 2001, 2002a). Contem-
porary, EGCG is shown to have no effect on penicillin-binding 
protein 2 (PBP2 ; protein causative of methicillin-resistance in 
MRSA) mRNA expression or PBP2 production (Zhao et al., 2001). 
In combinatorial effects with other cell wall synthesis inhibitors, 
EGCG also enhance activity of dl-cycloserine (Zhao et al., 2001), 
but antagonizes the activity of VAN and TEC against MRSA 
(Hu et al., 2002b). Furthermore, EGCG antagonizes the activ-
ity of polymyxin B against E. coli (Hu et al., 2002b). EGCG 
interferes with cell wall integrity by directly binding to pepti-
doglycan, and this might be the major reason for the synergism 
between EGCG and β-lactams. EGCG might also bind directly 
to glycopeptides and then interfere with their activities (Hu 
et al., 2002b). In our results, C16 activity against S. aureus was 
decreased with the addition of peptidoglycan, but not of d-Ala-d-
Ala (Table 6), which indicates that C16 binding to peptidoglycan 
occurs because of some peptidoglycan structural moieties other 
than d-Ala-d-Ala. The peptidoglycan-binding ability of C16 with-
out a d-Ala-d-Ala-mediated mechanism could adversely affect 
its antibacterial activity against S. aureus. In fact, 64 μg/ml of 
EGCG decreased SYTOX Green uptake in S. aureus (Figure 5), 
which indicates a potential protective effect of EGCG on the 
surface of bacteria. Binding of EGCG to peptidoglycan might 
interfere with binding of glycopeptides to d-Ala-d-Ala residue. 
In addition, EGCG inhibits the activity of various β-lactamases 
not only from S. aureus but also from Gram-negative bacteria, </p>

<p>including carbapenem-hydrolyzing enzyme, IMP-1 (Zhao et al., 
2002, 2003). However, most cephalosporins and carbapenems 
are stable against penicillinase from S. aureus. For this reason, 
β-lactamase-inactivating activity of EGCG cannot explain the 
mechanism of synergistic activity between EGCG and IPM against 
MRSA. When we focus on the action mechanism of β-lactam, there 
are four different cell wall synthesizing enzymes in S. aureus. PBP2 
alone might not completely fulfill the functions of these other 
intrinsic S. aureus PBPs (Zapun et al., 2008). Actually, synergism 
between carbapenems and other β-lactams having different PBP 
affinities against MRSA has also been reported (Sumita and Mit-
suhashi, 1991). Cell wall synthesis partially affected by β-lactam 
would provide an easy access for EGCG to the membrane of 
MRSA. In contrast, C16 appears to access the membrane more 
easily than EGCG (Figure 6). Therefore, the combinatorial effect 
of β-lactam with C16 against MRSA might be weak. In fact, the 
combinatorial effects of C16 with AMP and IPM (Figure 3) were 
mostly within additive category (FIC indices &gt;0.5), and were not 
as strong as those of EGCG with AMP (Figure 5). 
Different EGCG susceptibility of Staphylococci and Gram-
negative rods are observed due to the different EGCG affinities 
toward various cell wall components (Yoda et al., 2004). EGCG 
activity against Enterobacteriaceae was weak and was not strongly 
enhanced by acylation (Table 4); however, we did detect higher 
activity of the EGCG fatty acid derivatives compared to EGCG 
against acrB or tolC deletion mutants of MG1655 (Table 7). 
AcrAB-TolC can export various compounds with very different 
structures (Nishino and Yamaguchi, 2001). EGCG and its deriva-
tives are now identified as substrates for AcrAB-TolC. Efflux and 
low outer membrane permeability could be a strong reason for the 
weaker activity of EGCG against Gram-negative bacteria such as 
E. coli. In higher concentrations, tea polyphenols can inhibit the 
growth of P. aeruginosa by permeabilizing its membrane (Yi et al., 
2010). In this study, 64 μg/ml of C16 inhibited the growth of P. 
aeruginosa PAO1, although it was not bactericidal (Figure 3). 
Acylation of EGCG enhanced its antimicrobial activity against 
various species of bacteria and fungi although it did not expand 
antibacterial spectrum (Tables 2-5). C8 × 2 and C16 had the 
strongest activity against bacteria, particularly against S. aureus 
including MRSA. Moreover, C16 is proved to have superior activ-
ity including antivirus (Mori et al., 2008; Kaihatsu et al., 2009) 
and antitumor (Matsumura et al., 2008) activities. Although effect 
of acylation on antitoxic property of EGCG is not yet evaluated, 
beneficial effect would not be expected on that because toxins 
are usually not associated with membrane. These findings are 
exciting and further research may support the finding that the 
broad activity of C16 could be invaluable for clinicians as an alter-
native disinfectant as well as an alternative treatment option to 
antibiotics, perhaps reducing the risk of antibiotic resistance. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We would like to thank Taiyo Kagaku Co. Ltd., Tokyo, Japan for 
their generous donation of EGCG. This study was supported by the 
Grant for Promotion of Fundamental Studies in Health Sciences 
of the National Institute of Biomedical Innovation, Grants from 
the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science, and the Ministry 
of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology of Japan. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Microbiology | Antimicrobials, Resistance and Chemotherapy </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 53 | 8 </p>

<p>Matsumoto et al. </p>

<p>Acylation-enhanced EGCG antimicrobial activities </p>





<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 53 | 9 </p>

<p>Matsumoto et al. </p>

<p>Acylation-enhanced EGCG antimicrobial activities </p>

<p>gallate against beta-lactamase-
producing species depending on 
location of beta-lactamase. J. Pharm. 
Pharmacol. 55, 735-740. 
Zhao, W. H., Hu, Z. Q., Hara, Y., 
and Shimamura, T. (2002). Inhi-
bition of penicillinase by epi-
gallocatechin gallate resulting in 
restoration of antibacterial activity 
of penicillin against penicillinase-
producing Staphylococcus aureus. 
Antimicrob. Agents Chemother. 46, 
2266-2268. </p>

<p>Zhao, W. H., Hu, Z. Q., Okubo, 
S., Hara, Y., and Shimamura, 
T. (2001). Mechanism of synergy 
between epigallocatechin gallate and 
beta-lactams against methicillin-
resistant Staphylococcus aureus. 
Antimicrob. Agents Chemother. 45, 
1737-1742. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest Statement: The 
authors declare that the research was 
conducted in the absence of any com-
mercial or financial relationships that </p>

<p>could be construed as a potential con-
flict of interest. </p>

<p>Received: 17 October 2011; accepted: 31 
January 2012; published online: 16 Feb-
ruary 2012. 
Citation: Matsumoto Y, Kaihatsu K, 
Nishino K, Ogawa M, Kato N and 
Yamaguchi A (2012) Antibacterial 
and antifungal activities of new acy-
lated derivatives of epigallocatechin 
gallate. Front. Microbio. 3:53. doi: 
10.3389/fmicb.2012.00053 </p>

<p>This article was submitted to Fron-
tiers in Antimicrobials, Resistance and 
Chemotherapy, a specialty of Frontiers in 
Microbiology. 
Copyright © 2012 Matsumoto, Kaihatsu, 
Nishino, Ogawa, Kato and Yamaguchi. 
This is an open-access article distributed 
under the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution Non Commercial License, 
which permits non-commercial use, dis-
tribution, and reproduction in other 
forums, provided the original authors and 
source are credited. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Microbiology | Antimicrobials, Resistance and Chemotherapy </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 53 | 10 </p>

</text></tei>