<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3648837" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>I 
In nt tr ro od du uc ct ti io on n: : Relationships between cardiac pressure and volume have been 
suggested as markers of cardiac contractility; parameters include stroke work 
and the maximal rate of pressure rise during isovolumic contraction (dP/dt max ). 
Patients with cancer often display dyspnea and fatigue. These are also frequent 
symptoms in patients with chronic heart failure (HF). The reasons for similar 
symptoms in cancer patients are unknown. Using the novel Nexfin Finapres 
technique, we sought to assess measures of cardiac performance in patients 
with cancer and compare these values with those from control subjects and 
patients with chronic HF. 
M 
Ma at te er ri ia al l a 
an nd d m me et th ho od ds s: : We prospectively studied 98 patients (control n = 18, 
chronic HF n = 37, advanced pancreatic or colorectal cancer n = 43) and assessed 
blood pressure (BP), stroke volume (SV), cardiac output (CO), and dP/dt max at 
rest. 
R Re es su ul lt ts s: : All parameters of interest could be assessed using the Nexfin Finapres 
technique with SV and CO being significantly higher in patients with cancer 
than in controls (both p &lt; 0.05). The SV was significantly higher in patients with 
chronic HF than in controls (p &lt; 0.05). In patients with cancer, SV correlated 
with age (r = -0.45, p &lt; 0.01) and body weight (r = +0.55, p = 0.0001). In chron-
ic HF, SV declined with increasing age (r = -0.49, p &lt; 0.01); in control subjects, 
SV increased with increasing body weight (r = +0.57, p = 0.01). 
C Co on nc cl lu us si io on ns s: : Patients with cancer tended to display elevated BP, CO, SV, and 
dP/dt max as compared to control subjects and patients with HF. These findings 
may reveal an elevated risk for cardiovascular diseases in this group. </p>

<p>K Ke ey y w wo or rd ds s: : heart failure, cancer, hemodynamics, cardiac output, stroke volume. </p>

<p>A Ad dd dr re es ss s f fo or r c co or rr re es sp po on nd de en nc ce e: : 
Cardiac performance can be described by vari-
ous cardiac indices. Although heart failure (HF) is 
much more than mere pump failure but a multi-
facetted clinical syndrome, it can be described as 
the worst perturbation of cardiac performance 
[1-4]. One of the most accepted clinical parameters 
to describe HF severity is left ventricular ejection 
fraction (LVEF). Unfortunately, LVEF is also the least 
specific of all indices of contractility [5] and does 
not provide much insight into how a patient will 
develop clinically. An ideal parameter would, from 
a pathophysiological standpoint, be independent 
of afterload, preload, heart rate, and the state of 
remodeling. Relations between cardiac pressure and 
volume come closest to achieving this [6]. Thus, 
interesting parameters include stroke work and the 
maximal rate of pressure rise during isovolumic 
contraction (dP/dt max ) [5], and it would be desirable 
to measure these parameters non-invasively. 
The Finapres method was developed in the late 
1970s for continuous and non-invasive assessments 
of finger arterial pressure. Based on the volume-
clamp method by Panez, it allows blood pressure 
(BP) monitoring throughout the cardiac cycle. The 
technique has become a widely accepted substi-
tute for invasive intraarterial BP measurements. 
Recently, the Nexfin TM monitor became available, 
allowing not only continuous measurements of BP 
using the volume-clamp technique, but also calcu-
lation of cardiac output (CO). The reproducibility of 
the Nexfin BP assessment has been validated in 
several patient populations including healthy sub-
jects [7], pregnant women [8], and in patients </p>

<p>undergoing abdominal or orthopedic surgery [9] or 
surgery with the requirement of cardiopulmonary 
bypass [10]. The measurement of CO has been val-
idated in the latter group and in critically ill patients 
on a surgical intensive care unit [11]. 
In patients with HF, CO is expected to be re -
duced as a consequence of reductions in stroke vol-
ume (SV). The reduction in SV is a result of systolic 
or diastolic dysfunction. In patients with cancer 
such hemodynamic parameters have not been 
intensively investigated thus far. Patients with can-
cer often display dyspnea and fatigue, which are 
also frequent symptoms in patients with chronic 
HF [12]. The exact reasons for such symptoms in 
cancer are unknown. Some chemotherapy agents, 
such as anthracyclines, have been shown to be car-
diotoxic [13]. However, almost all cancer patients 
present with such symptoms independent of which 
agents they are being treated with or even if they 
are not undergoing chemotherapy. 
We aimed to investigate hemodynamic param-
eters in patients with cancer and compare our find-
ings with those of healthy control subjects and 
patients with chronic HF. Thus, we prospectively 
assessed BP, heart rate, CO, SV, and dP/dt max in 
patients with advanced cancer using the non-inva-
sive Nexfin technique. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>P 
Pa at ti ie en nt t r 
re ec cr ru ui it tm me en nt t </p>

<p>We prospectively studied 98 subjects in three 
different cohorts of patients, recruited at the Char-
ité Medical School, Campus Virchow-Klinikum, </p>

<p>V Va ar ri ia ab bl le es s 
C Co on nt tr ro ol l ( (n n = = 1 18 8) ) 
C Ch hr ro on ni ic c H HF F ( (n n = = 3 37 7) ) 
C Ca an nc ce er r ( (n n = = 4 43 3) ) 
A AN NO OV VA A 
V Va al lu ue e o of f p p </p>

<p>Age [years] 
62.4 ±9.7 
64.9 ±9.2 
59.1 ±11.2 + 
0.05 </p>

<p>Sex (% male) 
50 
83.8** 
41.9 +++ 
0.0001 </p>

<p>Weight [kg] 
72.2 ±11.4 
85.9 ±22.4** 
72.4 ±15.3 ++ 
0.002 </p>

<p>Body mass index [kg/m 2 ] 
25.2 ±3.2 
28.0 ±6.3 
24.9 ±3.3 + 
0.03 </p>

<p>NYHA class 
-
2.4 ±0.5 
-</p>

<p>LVEF [%] 
60.5 ±5.1 
35.0 ±8.1*** 
60.7 ±6.2 +++ 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Etiology or diagnosis [%] 
-
CAD: 67.5 
PCA: 23.3 
-
DCM: 32.4 
CRC: 76.7 </p>

<p>Hemoglobin [g/dl] 
13.7 ±0.9 
13.6 ±1.5 
11.7 ±1.5*** ,+++ 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Leukocytes [nl -1 ] 
5.8 ±1.7 
7.6 ±1.8** 
5.7 ±2.0 +++ 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Platelets [nl -1 ] 
277 ±95 
231 ±90 
249 ±92 
0.3 </p>

<p>Sodium [mmol/l] 
141 ±2 
140 ±4 
140 ±3 
0.7 </p>

<p>Creatinine [mg/dl] 
0.8 ±0.1 
1.1 ±0.3*** 
0.8 ±0.2 +++ 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>T Ta ab bl le e I I. . Subjects' clinical characteristics at baseline </p>

<p>CAD -coronary artery disease, CRC -colorectal cancer, DCM -dilated cardiomyopathy, LVEF -left ventricular ejection fraction, 
PCA -pancreatic cancer. *vs. control subjects, + vs. patients with CHF. One symbol -p &lt; 0.05, two symbols -p &lt; 0.01, three symbols -p &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Arch Med Sci 2, April / 2013 </p>



<p>Non-invasive assessment of cardiac hemodynamics in patients with advanced cancer and with chronic heart failure: a pilot feasibility study </p>

<p>Berlin, Germany. Thus, we included 37 patients with 
stable chronic HF, 43 patients with advanced can-
cer, and 18 healthy subjects of similar age. The sub-
jects' characteristics are provided in Table I, and 
patients' medication in Table II. 
The diagnosis of chronic HF was based on appro-
priate clinical signs and symptoms according to cur-
rent guidelines issued by the European Society of 
Cardiology [14], together with documented objec-
tive evidence of left ventricular diastolic or systolic 
dysfunction. The etiology of HF was coronary artery 
disease or dilated cardiomyopathy. No patient with 
chronic HF had signs of peripheral or pulmonary 
edema or was limited by exertional angina. We 
excluded patients younger than 18 years of age, 
with an acute myocardial infarction and those with 
a history of unstable angina, or stroke within three 
months prior to being studied. The diagnosis of can-
cer (pancreatic cancer, n = 10, colorectal cancer, 
n = 33) was based on histopathological examination. 
All patients had advanced cancer stage III or IV, were 
clinically stable, and received unchanged medica-
tion for at least four weeks. All patients with pan-
creatic cancer were receiving current chemothera-
py while in the study, 4 patients gemcitabine only. 
Six patients were participating in clinical trials to 
investigate novel chemotherapy regimens, 3 pa -
tients a combination of gemcitabine and afliber-
cept or placebo, 2 patients a combination of gem-
citabine with or without sorafenib, and 1 patient 
a combination of oxaliplatin, folic acid, 5-fluo-
rouracil, and lapatinib. Among patients with col-
orectal cancer, 29 patients (88%) had undergone 
surgical tumor resection at the time of examina-
tion. A total of 21 patients with colorectal cancer 
(64%) were receiving current chemotherapy while 
in the study, 15 of them were receiving 5-fluo-
rouracil, 2 patients capecitabine, 7 irinotecan, 
7 oxaliplatin, 8 bevacizumab, 1 cetuximab, 2 pani-
tumumab and 1 mitomycin, according to different 
regimens. One patient was receiving radiotherapy. 
In all cohorts we excluded subjects with clinical 
signs of infection, severe neuro-muscular disease, 
rheumatoid arthritis, or significant renal dysfunc-
tion (serum creatinine &gt; 2.5 mg/dl). The local ethics 
committee approved the study and all patients gave 
written informed consent. </p>

<p>A As ss se es ss sm me en nt t o of f b 
bl lo oo od d p pr re es ss su ur re e, , c ca ar rd di ia ac c o ou ut tp pu ut t, , 
a an nd d l le ef ft t v ve en nt tr ri ic cu ul la ar r e ej je ec ct ti io on n f fr ra ac ct ti io on n </p>

<p>We used the Nexfin method (BMEYE B.V., Ams-
terdam, The Netherlands) to assess BP, heart rate, 
CO, SV, and dP/dt max . The technique has been 
described previously [15] and the monitoring sys-
tem is an approved medical device in Switzerland. 
It is based on the development of a pulsatile 
unloading of the finger arterial wall that is picked 
up by an inflatable cuff with a built-in photoelec-</p>

<p>tric plethysmograph. Carbon oxide is calculated dur-
ing BP measurements. Measurements were per-
formed after at least 15 min of rest in a supine posi-
tion. The cuff was applied around the patient's 
middle finger as recommended by the manufac-
turer. In all subjects, LVEF was assessed using Simp-
son's technique, biplane. </p>

<p>S St ta at ti is st ti ic ca al l a 
an na al ly ys si is s </p>

<p>Data are expressed as mean ± standard devia-
tion. Data were checked for normal distribution 
before analysis using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. 
Fisher's exact test, analysis of variance (ANOVA) with 
Fisher's post hoc test, and simple regression analy-
sis were used as appropriate. A value of p &lt; 0.05 
was considered significant. All statistics were per-
formed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">StatView</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.0</rs> software for Macintosh 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Abacus Concepts, Berkley, CA</rs>). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>We studied 18 control subjects, 37 patients with 
chronic HF, and 43 patients with advanced cancer. 
The patients' baseline characteristics are provided 
in Table I. Arterial hypertension was present in 
9 (20.9%), and atrial fibrillation in 1 (2.3%) of all can-
cer patients. No significant difference was detected 
with regards to age between control subjects and 
the two patient groups (all p &gt; 0.05) but patients 
with chronic HF were somewhat older than patients 
with cancer (p = 0.01). We detected a significantly 
higher weight in patients with chronic HF as com-
pared to control subjects and patients with cancer 
(both p &lt; 0.01) as well as a higher body mass index 
(BMI) than patients with cancer (p = 0.01). Patients 
with chronic HF presented with a significantly low-
er LVEF than controls or patients with cancer (both 
p &lt; 0.0001). Serum creatinine was significantly high-
er in patients with chronic HF as compared to either 
controls or patients with cancer (both p &lt; 0.001, </p>

<p>V Va ar ri ia ab bl le es s 
C Co on nt tr ro ol l C Ch hr ro on ni ic c H HF F C Ca an nc ce er r 
( (n n = = 1 18 8) ) 
( (n n = = 3 37 7) ) ( (n n = = 4 43 3) ) </p>

<p>ACE inhibitor or ARB [%] 
-
94.6 
23.3 </p>

<p>β-Blocker [%] 
-
97.3 
14.0 </p>

<p>Aspirin [%] 
-
69.4 
2.3 </p>

<p>Loop diuretic [%] 
-
50.0 
4.7 </p>

<p>Aldosterone antagonist [%] 
-
54.1 
4.7 </p>

<p>Statin [%] 
-
73.0 
4.7 </p>

<p>Warfarin or 
-
29.7 
7.0 
phenprocoumon [%] </p>

<p>Digitalis [%] 
-
13.9 
-</p>

<p>T Ta ab bl le e I II I. . Subjects' cardiovascular medication at base-
line </p>

<p>ACE -angiotensin-converting enzyme, ARB -angiotensin receptor 
blocker </p>



<p>Arch Med Sci 2, April / 2013 </p>

<p>S. von Haehling, M. Lainscak, T. Kung, L. Cramer, S. Fülster, U. Pelzer, B. Hildebrandt, A. Sandek, J.C. Schefold, M. Rauchhaus, W. Doehner, S.D. Anker </p>

<p>Table I). We detected significant differences for 
hemoglobin with significantly lower values among 
patients with cancer as compared to controls or 
patients with chronic HF (both p &lt; 0.0001). Patients 
with chronic HF presented with elevated leukocyte 
counts when compared with both other groups 
(both p &lt; 0.01, Table I). 
Data derived from the Nexfin technique includ-
ed systolic and diastolic BP, heart rate, CO, SV, and 
dP/dt max . These values are given in Table III. Sys-
tolic BP was significantly higher in patients with 
cancer as compared to patients with chronic HF 
(p = 0.0002). Likewise, diastolic BP was significantly 
higher in patients with cancer as well as in control 
subjects compared to patients with chronic HF 
(both p &lt; 0.003, Table III). Cancer patients showed 
a significantly higher heart rate compared to chron-
ic HF (p = 0.03). The CO and SV were significantly 
higher in cancer patients compared to control sub-
jects (both p &lt; 0.02); these values are depicted in 
Figure 1. Likewise, patients with HF showed higher 
levels of SV than control subjects (p = 0.03). The 
values for dP/dt max were significantly higher in 
patients with cancer as compared to patients with 
chronic HF (p = 0.008, Table III). </p>

<p>The SV correlated significantly with age and body 
weight. These associations are depicted in Figure 2. 
However, significant negative correlations between 
SV and age were only present in patients with can-
cer and in patients with chronic HF. Likewise, we 
observed significant positive correlations between 
SV and weight only in patients with cancer and in 
control subjects. We detected significant correla-
tions between CO and age, weight, and heart rate, 
although these associations were not evident in all 
groups of subjects. The CO correlated with age in 
patients with chronic HF (r = -0.54, p = 0.0006) and 
in patients with cancer (r = -0.49, p = 0.0008), but 
not in control subjects (r = -0.24, p = 0.33). The CO 
correlated with body weight and heart rate only in 
control subjects (weight: r = +0.67, p = 0.003; heart 
rate: r = +0.50, p = 0.03) and in patients with can-
cer (weight: r = +0.34, p = 0.03; heart rate: r = +0.52, 
p = 0.0003). A trend towards association between 
CO and hemoglobin was detected only in control 
subjects (r = +0.53, p = 0.05). An overview of these 
associations is provided in Figure 3. 
We detected consistent correlations between 
dP/dt max and CO in controls (r = +0.47, p = 0.047), 
patients with chronic HF (r = +0.53, p = 0.0008), </p>

<p>V Va ar ri ia ab bl le es s 
C Co on nt tr ro ol l ( (n n = = 1 18 8) ) 
C Ch hr ro on ni ic c H HF F ( (n n = = 3 37 7) ) 
C Ca an nc ce er r ( (n n = = 4 43 3) ) 
A AN NO OV VA A 
V Va al lu ue e o of f p p </p>

<p>BP systolic [mm Hg] 
121 ±18 
110 ±21 
129 ±23 
0.0008 </p>

<p>BP diastolic [mm Hg] 
72 ±12 
63 ±12 
72 ±10 
0.0006 </p>

<p>Heart rate [min -1 ] 
69 ±11 
67 ±13 
72 ±10 
0.1 </p>

<p>Cardiac output [l/min] 
4.5 ±1.2 
4.9 ±1.3 
5.5 ±1.2 
0.006 </p>

<p>Stroke volume [ml] 
66 ±13 
77 ±21* 
78 ±15* 
0.05 </p>

<p>dP/dt max [mm Hg/s] 
724 ±251 
667 ±238 
852 ±371 
0.03 </p>

<p>T Ta ab bl le e I II II I. . Data derived using the Nexfin technique </p>

<p>*p &lt; 0.05 vs. control </p>

<p>C Co on nt tr ro ol l 
C Ch hr ro on ni ic c H HF F 
C Ca an nc ce er r 
( (n n = = 1 18 8) ) 
( (n n = = 3 37 7) ) 
( (n n = = 4 43 3) ) </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 1 1. . Stroke volume (SV, A A) and cardiac output (CO, B B) as assessed using the Nexfin technique in the three groups 
of subjects </p>

<p>S SV V [ [m ml l] ] </p>

<p>p = 0.02 </p>

<p>p = 0.03 
7 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
C Co on nt tr ro ol l 
C Ch hr ro on ni ic c H HF F 
C Ca an nc ce er r 
( (n n = = 1 18 8) ) 
( (n n = = 3 37 7) ) 
( (n n = 
= 4 43 3) ) </p>

<p>C CO O [ [l l] ] </p>

<p>p = 0.03 </p>

<p>p &lt; 0.01 
120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A A 
B B </p>

<p>Arch Med Sci 2, April / 2013 </p>



<p>Non-invasive assessment of cardiac hemodynamics in patients with advanced cancer and with chronic heart failure: a pilot feasibility study </p>

<p>and in patients with cancer (r = +0.45, p = 0.003). 
Similar associations were found between dP/dtmax 
and SV in these patient groups (control: r = +0.47, 
p = 0.0497; chronic HF: r = +0.50, p = 0.002; can-
cer: r = +0.39, p = 0.01). Further, dP/dt max correlat-
ed with systolic BP (control: r = +0.64, p = 0.005; 
chronic HF: r = +0.77, p &lt; 0.0001; cancer: r = +0.83, 
p &lt; 0.0001). A correlation between dP/dt max and 
diastolic BP was present only in patients with 
chronic HF (r = +0.40, p = 0.02) and those with can-
cer (r = +0.50, p = 0.0006) but not in controls 
(r = +0.41, p = 0.09). No significant relationship was 
detected between LVEF and dP/dt max (control: 
r = -0.47, p = 0.08; chronic HF: r = +0.25, p = 0.15; 
cancer: r = +0.08, p = 0.64) or between heart rate 
and dP/dt max (all p &gt; 0.3). A correlation between 
body weight and dP/dt max was evident only in con-
trol subjects (r = +0.53, p = 0.03). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We have shown that patients with cancer pres-
ent with pronounced higher SV and CO values than 
control subjects. Patients with HF showed lower 
LVEF and more severe kidney impairment than con-
trol subjects or patients with cancer. Hemoglobin 
values were lower in patients with cancer as com-
pared to control subjects and patients with chron-
ic HF. Likewise, SV was higher in patients with 
chronic HF than in control subjects. Major deter-
minants for these variables appear to be age and 
body weight. Hemoglobin seems to have an influ-
ence on CO only in control subjects. 
Elevated resting CO and heart rate predispose 
patients to develop cardiac disorders such as arte-
rial hypertension [16]. In obese subjects, it is well 
established that not only CO is augmented, but also 
SV, and left ventricular filling pressure [17]. Indeed, 
earlier studies had demonstrated that increases in </p>

<p>CO in obese patients are primarily related to high-
er SV rather than higher heart rate [18]. Increases 
in CO and SV are necessary to meet the higher-
than-usual metabolic requirements in these pa -
tients. This is also a likely explanation for increas-
es in both values observed in patients with cancer. 
Altogether, it appears that patients with cancer 
tend to have higher values for BP, CO, SV, and also 
for dP/dt max . This may represent cardiovascular dis-
turbances in this group or at least a higher cardio-
vascular risk compared to control subjects. The only 
study that aimed to assess CO in cancer subjects 
thus far investigated patients with hematological can-
cer using ultrasound cardiac output monitoring tech-
nique. They showed an initial increase in CO after 
commencement of chemotherapy with a subsequent 
quick decrease in CO remaining decreased for the rest </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 2 2. . Correlations between stroke volume (SV) and age (A A) or weight (B B) for control subjects (open circles), 
patients with chronic heart failure (HF, full dark grey circles), and patients with cancer (full light grey circles) </p>

<p>S SV V [ [m ml l] ] </p>

<p>Cancer 
(r = -0.45, 
p = 0.0024) </p>

<p>Chronic HF 
(r = -0.49, 
p = 0.0021) </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>S SV V [ [m ml l] ] </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A 
A 
B B </p>

<p>20 
30 
40 
50 
60 
70 
80 
90 
A Ag ge e [ [y ye ea ar rs s] ] </p>

<p>20 
40 
60 
80 
100 
120 
140 
160 
W We ei ig gh ht t [ [k kg g] ] </p>

<p>Control 
(r = -0.12, 
p = 0.6) </p>

<p>Chronic HF 
(r = +0.14, 
p = 0.4) </p>

<p>Control 
(r = +0.57, 
p = 0.01) </p>

<p>Cancer 
(r = +0.55, 
p = 0.0001) </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 3 3. . Values of r for simple regression analyses 
between cardiac output (dependent) and several clin-
ical variables in control subjects (white bars), 
patients with chronic heart failure (HF, dark grey 
bars), and patients with cancer (light grey bars) </p>

<p>*p &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>V Va al lu ue e o </p>

<p>of f r r </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0 
Control 
Chronic HF 
Cancer 
A g e [ y e a r s ] 
W 
e i g h t [ k g ] </p>

<p>B P s y s t o l i c [ m </p>

<p>m 
H g ] </p>

<p>B P d i a s t o l i c [ m </p>

<p>m 
H g ] </p>

<p>H e a r t r a t e [ m </p>

<p>i n -1 ] 
L V E F [ % </p>

<p>] </p>

<p>H a e m </p>

<p>o g l o b i n [ g / d l ] </p>

<p>C r e a t i n i n e [ m </p>

<p>g / d l ] </p>



<p>Arch Med Sci 2, April / 2013 </p>

<p>S. von Haehling, M. Lainscak, T. Kung, L. Cramer, S. Fülster, U. Pelzer, B. Hildebrandt, A. Sandek, J.C. Schefold, M. Rauchhaus, W. Doehner, S.D. Anker </p>

<p>of time [19]. These results could be explained by 
severe cardiotoxicity of anthracyclines [13]. 
Several determinants of cardiac hemodynamics 
have been discussed in the literature over the last 
decades. The CO is known to correlate with sever-
al factors including increasing age [20] and obesi-
ty [16]. Both CO and heart rate can be reduced by 
use of, for example, β-blockers. The CO has been 
shown to be associated with body weight [15, 18]. 
This was also the case in our study in control sub-
jects and in patients with cancer, but not in patients 
with chronic HF. This fact might be due to the 
patient cohort studied that presented with signifi-
cantly higher body weight than all other groups 
(Table I); however, it is more likely that the use of 
β-blockers in patients with chronic HF influenced 
the presence of this association. Indeed, O'Malley 
et al. [21] assessed the association between CO and 
body weight in untreated dogs with experimental 
heart failure and found a strong positive correla-
tion, similar to our findings in controls and in 
patients with cancer. 
A decrease in CO with advancing age has been 
reported already decades ago [22]. Although this 
association was not found among our control sub-
jects, it was present in patients with cancer and in 
those with chronic HF. Although there were no sta-
tistical differences with regards to age distribution 
between patients and controls, the age range of 
patients with cancer was broader than that of our 
control subjects (Figure 3). This has to be consid-
ered in the interpretation of our results. 
For clinicians, the findings for LVEF and creati-
nine do not come as a surprise. Alterations in leuko-
cyte counts (i.e. increased leukocyte levels in 
patients with chronic HF) have been described pre-
viously and might be explained by an altered dis-
tribution of leukocyte subsets [23]. It is interesting 
to note that in conflict with current literature 
patients with chronic HF showed a higher SV than 
control subjects in the present study. This might be 
due to the patient cohort investigated that pre-
sented with significantly higher body weight than 
all other groups and because all patients were 
under stable therapy for HF. 
A note of caution should be added particularly for 
the measurement of dP/dt max , because the periph-
eral assessment with the Nexfin technique does not 
provide measurements that are identical with inva-
sive measurement. Indeed, in normal subjects 
dP/dt max should be in the range 1500-2000 mm Hg/s 
[24]; in our study, the mean value was 724 mm Hg/s 
(Table III). Thus, comparisons between patient groups 
such as the one that we did or comparisons before 
and after therapeutic interventions may be applica-
ble, but the notion of a peripheral measurement 
should be heeded. Our study has a number of limi-
tations. The number of subjects is small, particular-</p>

<p>ly in the group of control subjects, and the distribu-
tion of gender, body weight, and hemoglobin was 
not well matched between groups as our patients 
were recruited from typical patients attending the 
out-patient departments of our hospital. This fact 
should be considered when looking at the data. In 
addition, we did not perform serial measurements 
that would allow the analysis of intra-individual 
changes and the assessment of test reproducibility. 
Our echocardiography testing remained preliminary 
in scope, and we were therefore not able to compare 
findings from the Nexfin technique with our echo 
data. 
The Nexfin technique is easy to use in clinical 
routine and in research settings and may provide 
useful information on cardiac performance. It has 
been validated using different standard assess-
ments of CO [25-27]. It has recently been suggest-
ed that the similarity of clinical signs and symp-
toms of patients with chronic HF and those with 
cancer may have a basis in cardiac alterations in 
the patient with cancer [28]. In other words, exer-
tional dyspnea, fatigue, and body wasting in 
patients with advanced cancer may partly be 
a reflection of developing HF. In our study, patients 
with cancer tended to show elevated values of BP, 
CO, SV, and dP/dt max , displaying at least a higher 
cardiovascular risk in this group. Both CO and heart 
rate can be reduced by use of, for example, β-block-
ers. Our data suggest that such kind of treatments 
may have beneficial effects on cardiovascular func-
tion in these patients in the long term. These find-
ings warrant further investigation in larger studies. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Part of this work was supported by the European 
Commission under the 7 th Framework Programme 
(FP7/2007-2013) under grant agreement number 
241558 (SICA-HF -Studies Investigating Co-mor-
bidities Aggravating Heart Failure [29]). </p>



<p>Arch Med Sci 2, April / 2013 </p>





</text></tei>