<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3717207" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The availability of well-annotated genome sequences for a vari-
ety of organisms has provided a strong foundation on which 
much biological knowledge has been assembled, including the 
generation of comprehensive genetic resources. This has been </p>

<p>achieved in several model organisms, including E. coli, 
S. cerevisiae, S. pombe, A. thaliana, C. elegans, and 
D. melanogaster, greatly facilitating studies focused on single 
genes and enabling genome-wide genetic screens. 
Annotation of the human genome has identified over 20,000 
protein-coding genes as well as many noncoding RNAs. Despite 
the dramatic increase in the knowledge of variation in human 
genomes, the normal function of many genes is still unknown 
or predicted from sequence analysis alone, and consequently, 
the disease significance of rare variants remains obscure. 
Furthermore, there remains a large bias toward research on a 
small number of the best-known genes (Edwards et al., 2011). 
Realizing the full value of the complete human genome sequence 
requires broadening this focus, and the availability of compre-
hensive biological resources will facilitate this process. 
The mouse is a key model organism for assessing mammalian 
gene function, providing access to conserved processes such 
as development, metabolism, and physiology. Genetic studies 
in mice, mostly via targeted mutagenesis in ES cells, have 
described a function for 7,229 genes (ftp://ftp.informatics.jax. 
org/pub/reports/MGI_PhenotypicAllele.rpt, February 2013). The 
vast majority of these studies have been directed at previously 
studied (known) genes, driven by previous biological knowledge. 
Phenotype-driven screens have also identified genes associated 
with specific phenotypes, although to a smaller extent. Although 
targeted mutagenesis has been very successful, the global distri-
bution of the effort has resulted in significant heterogeneity in 
allele design, genetic background of mice used, and their pheno-
typic analysis. Furthermore, the biological focus of most targeted 
knockout experiments is constrained by the expertise of the </p>



<p>Open access under CC BY-NC-ND license. </p>

<p>specific research group. As a result, many phenotypes have 
not been detected, and consequently, the full biological function 
of many genes studied using knockout mice is significantly 
underreported. 
Some efforts to generate and phenotype sizeable sets of new 
targeted alleles of genes of interest have been reported previ-
ously (e.g., Tang et al., 2010). These studies focused on specific 
categories of molecules such as secreted and transmembrane 
proteins or other ''drugable'' targets. Other research centers 
have established mouse clinics, with the aim of carrying out a 
comprehensive analysis of the phenotypes of mutant lines of 
specific interest (e.g., Fuchs et al., 2012; Wakana et al., 2009; 
Laughlin et al., 2012). 
The genome-wide set of targeted mutations in ES cells estab-
lished by the KOMP, EUCOMM, and MirKO programs (Skarnes 
et al., 2011; Prosser et al., 2011; Park et al., 2012) provides an 
opportunity to conduct systematic, large-scale gene function 
analysis in a mammalian system without the variables inherent 
in studies by individual groups. The Sanger Institute's Mouse 
Genetics Project (MGP) was one of the first programs to pursue 
this objective, established in 2006 when the first targeted ES 
cells became available. The MGP later expanded to contribute 
to a European phenotyping effort, EUMODIC, and more recently 
has become a founding member of the International Mouse Phe-
notyping Consortium (IMPC). Summaries of the developing 
efforts and aspirations of the IMPC have been reported (e.g., 
Brown and Moore, 2012; Ayadi et al., 2012). As the first estab-
lished large-scale project using the KOMP/EUCOMM ES cells, 
the MGP has provided pilot data to inform the design of the inter-
national effort, such as the advantages of a single pipeline 
design, optimum numbers of mice, and details of variance for 
specific phenotyping tests. To date, the MGP has generated 
more than 900 lines of mutants using KOMP/EUCOMM 
resources (http://www.sanger.ac.uk/mouseportal/), and here, 
we describe the analysis of 489 of these for viability and fertility 
and 250 lines that have passed through a systematic screen 
for adult phenotypes, providing a glimpse into the wealth of bio-
logical insight that will emerge from these programs. Publicly 
available data enable the construction of new hypotheses, and 
the mouse mutants provide an invaluable resource for follow-
up studies. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Genes and Alleles 
Mice carrying targeted knockout first conditional-ready alleles 
from the KOMP/EUCOMM ES cell resources (Figures S1A and 
S1B available online; Skarnes et al., 2011) were established on 
a C57BL/6 genetic background. The mutants generated are 
listed in Tables S1 and S2, and all are available through public 
repositories including EMMA (http://www.emmanet.org/) and 
KOMP (http://www.komp.org/). Two classes of alleles are repre-
sented: those targeted with a promoter-driven selectable 
marker, and those with promoterless targeting vectors. Most 
are expected to be null alleles based on previous experience 
with this design (Mitchell et al., 2001; Testa et al., 2004). Data 
from 25 alleles showed that most (15) had &lt;0.5% of normal tran-
script level detected in liver with a minority (4) showing a ''leaki-</p>

<p>ness'' of $20% (column X; Table S2). The structure of each allele 
was confirmed when established in mice (Figure S1C). </p>

<p>Viability 
Viability was assessed at postnatal day 14 (P14) by genotyping 
offspring of heterozygous crosses (Figure 1A). Data from 489 
targeted alleles are summarized in Figure 2A. Overall, 58% 
were fully viable, whereas 29% produced no homozygotes at 
P14 and were classed as lethal, consistent with the proportion 
of homozygous embryonic/perinatal lethal mutants reported by 
MGI (2,183 of 7,229 lines of mice [30%]; ftp://ftp.informatics. 
jax.org/pub/reports/MGI_PhenoGenoMP.rpt, February 2013). A 
further 13% produced fewer than 13% homozygotes and were 
considered to be subviable. Genes required for survival included 
alleles generated with both promoter-driven and promoterless 
selection cassettes, but the latter were significantly more likely 
to be lethal (Figure 2B; Table S3) despite a greater level of persis-
tent gene expression (11 of 14 promotor-driven compared with 
4 of 11 promotorless alleles with &lt;0.5% expression; column X; 
Table S2). 
Alleles classed as lethal or subviable at P14 were further 
assessed at E14.5 (Figure 2C). From 143 alleles examined, 
48% (68 genes) produced no homozygotes, indicating embry-
onic lethality and complete resorption by E14.5. One-third of 
alleles (n = 45) produced the expected number of homozygous 
embryos, whereas 30 (21%) produced fewer than expected 
homozygotes. Of the 75 mutant lines that produced homozy-
gous embryos, 34 exhibited one or more morphological defect 
(Figure 2D). Some mutants (n = 23) presented with specific 
abnormalities including craniofacial defects and polydactyly, 
whereas 11 lines displayed only generalized indicators of devel-
opmental defects, edema, and/or growth retardation (Figure 2D). 
Examples are illustrated in Figures 2E-2G. </p>

<p>Fertility 
Fertility of heterozygotes was assessed from heterozygous inter-
crosses. Of 489 alleles assessed, all heterozygotes were able to 
produce offspring. Homozygous mutants for 307 of the viable 
lines were then assessed. A homozygous infertility rate of 
5.2% (n = 16) was observed (Figure 2H), strongly male biased 
with 15 of 16 genes exhibiting male infertility. A total of 11 
genes affected only males, whereas just 1 was female specific 
(Pabpc1l). Of these 16 genes, 7 have not previously been asso-
ciated with infertility. Although some were good candidates such 
as Usp42, expressed during mouse spermatogenesis (Kim et al., 
2007), others are novel genes such as 3010026O09Rik and may 
suggest new pathways or mechanisms influencing fertility. </p>

<p>Adult Phenotypes 
We report here the results of our screen of the first 250 lines to 
complete all primary phenotyping pipelines. In contrast to previ-
ous focused screens by Mitchell et al. (2001) and Tang et al. 
(2010), a broad range of gene products was included. The 250 
genes reported span all chromosomes except Y (Figure S1D) 
and include eight control lines published previously and 87 
genes proposed by the research community. For 34 of the 250 
genes, no functional information has been published. A compar-
ison of this gene set with all mouse genes indicates minimal </p>

<p>Cell 154, 452-464, July 18, 2013 ª2013 The Authors 453 </p>

<p>GO term enrichment spread over a variety of processes and 
underrepresentation only in sensory perception of smell, indi-
cating that the gene set can be regarded as a reasonable sample 
of the genome. 
A series of tests was used (Figure 1B), designed to detect 
robust variations in phenotypes that were key indicators of a 
broad spectrum of disease categories. Of the 250 reported lines, 
104 were either lethal or subviable; most of these were screened 
as heterozygotes (n = 90), and the remaining lines were screened 
as homozygotes and/or hemizygotes (n = 160). All mutant lines 
generated passed through all primary phenotypic screens. For 
most tests in the pipeline, seven males and seven females 
were used, tested in small batches so that the data for each 
genotype were gathered on different days (Figure S2A). Assays 
culminated in the collection of samples at 16 weeks of age 
(Table S4). The primary screen included a high-fat diet challenge 
to exacerbate any latent phenotypes. Separate pipelines 
included challenges with two infectious agents: Salmonella 
Typhimurium and Citrobacter rodentium (Table S4). 
Phenotypic data from the first 250 mutant alleles through the 
adult pipelines are summarized in Tables S1 and S2, with signif-</p>

<p>icant differences from the control baseline (hits) indicated by a 
red box. To make robust phenotypic calls, a reference range 
method was implemented that uses accumulated wild-type 
(WT) data to identify and refine the 95% reference range (Fig-
ure S2B). Mutant data were compared to the relevant reference 
range and variant phenotypes determined using a standardized 
set of rules (Figure S3). We aimed to highlight phenotypes with 
large effect sizes. This approach results in conservative calls 
and minimizes false positives. There was very little missing 
data (2.14% of all calls; Table S2). The maximum number of 
parameters collected per line was 263. Of these, 147 were cate-
gorical variables, for example normal or abnormal teeth, whereas 
116, such as plasma magnesium levels, exhibited a continuous 
distribution from which outliers were identified. Examples of 
parameters with continuous variables (cholesterol, high-density 
lipoprotein [HDL], low-density lipoprotein [LDL], mean weights, 
and auditory brainstem responses [ABR]) are illustrated in 
Figure 3. 
Gene expression was examined by whole-mount lacZ reporter 
gene expression in 41 tissues and organs of adults, typically 
using heterozygotes (R6 weeks old; n = 243 lines; Table S1). </p>

<p>Figure 1. Illustration of the Phenotyping Pipelines </p>

<p>(A) An overview of the typical workflow from chimera to entry into phenotyping pipelines, encompassing homozygous (Hom) viability, fertility, and target gene 
expression profiling using the lacZ reporter. Het, heterozygous. 
(B) The Sanger Institute MGP clinical phenotyping pipeline showing tests performed during each week. Seven male and seven female mutant mice are processed 
for each allele screened. In addition, seven male and seven female WT controls per genetic background are processed every week. 
See also Figure S1 and Tables S1 and S2. </p>



<p>Ubiquitous expression was recorded for eight lines (3.3%) and 
complete absence of expression in nine lines (3.7%). Of the 
remaining lines, 168 (69.1%) showed expression in &lt;20 of the 
tissues, suggesting a relatively specific expression pattern, 
whereas 58 (23.9%) were more broadly expressed (R20 tissues 
with detectable lacZ expression). 
The data and images can be viewed on the Sanger Institute's 
mouse portal, accompanied by step-by-step examples of how to 
access the data (http://www.sanger.ac.uk/mouseportal/). Much 
of the raw data can be downloaded from the MGP Phenotyping 
Biomart (http://www.sanger.ac.uk/htgt/biomart/martview/) for 
further analysis. Summaries can be found by searching for 
each gene of interest in Wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ 
Category:Genes_mutated_in_mice) and Mouse Genome Infor-
matics (http://www.informatics.jax.org/). </p>

<p>Many Unexpected Phenotypes Discovered 
A few examples of the wide range of phenotypes we discovered 
are illustrated in Figure 4. Body weight and fat/lean composition 
were among the most common anomalies, with both overweight 
(n = 2) and underweight (n = 21) mutants discovered. The Kptn 
mutant is an example of an unexpected phenotype. Kptn is a 
putative actin binding protein proposed as a candidate for deaf-
ness because it is expressed in sensory hair cells (Bearer et al., 
2000). Instead, the homozygous Kptn mutant has increased 
body weight on a high-fat diet (Figure 4A) and increased bacterial 
counts following Salmonella Typhimurium challenge but normal 
hearing (Table S2). Additional new phenotypes were detected 
in genes that had been published previously, such as reduced 
grip strength and ankylosis of the metacarpophalangeal joints 
in Dnase1l2 mutants (Fischer et al., 2011), delayed response in 
the hot plate test in Git2 mutants (Schmalzigaug et al., 2009), 
and small sebaceous glands in Cbx7 mutants (Forzati et al., 
2012) (Figures 4B-4E, 4G, and 4H). Phenotypes were also 
detected in genes that had not been published previously, 
such as impaired hearing in Fam107b mutants and elevated 
plasma magnesium concentration in Rg9mtd2 mutants (Figures 
4F and 4I, respectively). These examples demonstrate that many 
phenotypes will be missed unless they are specifically looked for 
and illustrate the value of carrying out a broad range of screens 
with all mutants going through all screens. They also reveal our 
collective inability to predict phenotypes based on sequence 
or expression pattern alone. </p>

<p>Haploinsufficient and Nonessential Genes 
Haploinsufficient phenotypes were detected in 38 of 90 (42%) of 
these lines. Thus, haploinsufficiency is relatively common, sug-
gesting that screening heterozygotes of knockout lines can yield 
valuable insight into gene function and provide models for domi-
nantly inherited human disorders. All 90 genes screened as het-
erozygotes had at least 1 hit (usually viability) and together gave 
a total of 181 hits (ranging from 1 to 14 per line), an average of 2.0 
per line, or 1.0 per line if we consider that abnormal viability is a 
feature of the homozygote. The distributions of phenotypic hits 
are shown in Figures 5A and 5B. Two examples of haploinsuffi-
ciency are illustrated in Figures 4J-4N. 
A total of 837 phenotypic variants were detected in the 250 
mutant lines, 1.27% of the total calls (Tables S1 and S2). Of </p>

<p>the lines screened as homozygotes or hemizygotes, 35% 
(56 of 160) appeared completely normal in our screen. There 
are several possible explanations for the lack of a detected 
phenotype, such as incomplete inactivation of the gene, a 
subtle change in phenotype not detected by our screen, or 
the gene may be nonessential. So far, there is no overlap be-
tween the 56 mouse lines with no detected phenotype and 
genes homozygously inactivated in humans, but both data 
sets are limited in coverage to date (MacArthur et al., 2012). 
The remaining 104 homozygous/hemizygous lines gave a total 
of 656 hits (range 0-41 per line), an average of 6.3 hits per 
line. </p>

<p>Sensitivity of the MGP Screen 
To assess the sensitivity of our screen, the phenotypes were 
compared with published data on alternative alleles where avail-
able. A total of 91 of 250 genes had published data reported in 
MGI (Table S5), and for 61 of these, our observations detected 
features of the published phenotypes. Importantly, for 56 genes, 
a new phenotype was detected by our screen (column K, Table 
S5). For 31 genes, features of the published phenotype were 
assessed but not detected by our pipeline. For example, 
Asxl1 tm1Bc/tm1Bc mice are published as being viable (Fisher 
et al., 2010), but we found that Asxl1 tm1a(EUCOMM)Wtsi homo-
zygotes were lethal, with none detected among 276 progeny 
from heterozygous intercrosses (c 2 = 95.13, df = 2; p &lt; 2.2 3 
10 À16 ). These discrepant cases may reflect differences in the 
allele and/or genetic background. In other cases (77 genes), 
the reported characteristics required a specialized test not 
included in our screen, such as the calcium signaling defect 
in cardiomyocytes of Anxa6 tm1Moss/tm1Moss mutants (Hawkins 
et al., 1999). </p>

<p>New Mouse Models for Human Disease 
The data set reported here includes 59 orthologs of known 
human disease genes. We compared our data with human dis-
ease features described in OMIM (Table S6). Approximately 
half (27) of these mutants exhibited phenotypes that were 
broadly consistent with the human phenotype. However, many 
additional phenotypes were detected in the mouse mutants sug-
gesting additional features that might also occur in patients that 
have hitherto not been reported. Interestingly, a large proportion 
of genes underlying recessive disorders in humans are homozy-
gous lethal in mice (17 of 37 genes), possibly because the human 
mutations are not as disruptive as the mouse alleles. Of the 59 
genes, 26 represent the first mouse mutant with publicly avail-
able data. Three examples (Sms, Ap4e1, and Smc3) represent-
ing the first targeted mouse mutant for each gene are illustrated 
in Figure 6, and all show similar phenotypic features to their 
human counterparts. 
SMS mutations in humans cause X-linked Snyder-Robinson 
syndrome involving hypotonia, unsteady gait, diminished muscle 
mass, kyphoscoliosis, osteoporosis, facial asymmetry, and intel-
lectual disability (Cason et al., 2003). Hemizygous Sms mutant 
male mice showed reduced muscle strength, lean mass and 
bone mineral density, lumbar lordosis (Figures 6A-6E), and 
growth retardation, recapitulating features of the human disease. 
In addition, male infertility was detected, suggesting a feature </p>

<p>Cell 154, 452-464, July 18, 2013 ª2013 The Authors 455 </p>

<p>(legend on next page) </p>

<p>456 Cell 154, 452-464, July 18, 2013 ª2013 The Authors </p>

<p>that may not have been recognized in humans with SMS 
mutations. 
Spastic paraplegia 51, autosomal recessive, is caused by 
mutations in AP4E1 and leads to spastic tetraplegia with hyper-
reflexia and generalized hypertonia, microcephaly, intellectual 
disability and dilated ventricles, cerebellar atrophy, and/or 
abnormal white matter (Abou Jamra et al., 2011; Moreno-De-
Luca et al., 2011). Homozygous Ap4e1 mutant mice displayed 
several similarities such as increased lateral ventricle area, 
decreased corpus callosum span, and decreased rearing (Fig-
ures 6F-6J). In addition, hematological changes suggestive of 
anemia were detected in female Ap4e1 mutants, which have 
not been reported in humans. 
The third example is SMC3, associated with dominantly 
inherited Cornelia de Lange syndrome 3, featuring facial dys-
morphism, hirsutism, growth retardation, neurodevelopmental 
delay, and upper-limb anomalies (Deardorff et al., 2007). Smc3 
mutant mice displayed homozygous lethality (prior to E14.5) 
and reduced heterozygote viability at P14 (45% instead of the 
expected 67%; p 0 = 0.0064). Surviving Smc3 heterozygotes 
showed reduced body weight, and a subset showed a distinct 
craniofacial morphology (Figures 6K-6M). Distinct Smc3 expres-
sion in hair follicles and key brain substructures was revealed 
using lacZ (Figures 6N and 6O), noteworthy because of the hir-
sutism and neurodevelopmental delay aspects of Cornelia 
de Lange syndrome 3. In addition, an increase in the number 
of helper and cytotoxic T cells was observed in the mutant 
mice, again indicating an aspect that might contribute to the 
phenotype of patients but that has not yet been reported. </p>

<p>Pleiotropic Effects of Mutations 
The phenotypes detected in this study vary from discrete spe-
cific defects (e.g., decreased platelet cell number in Crlf3 tm1a/ 
tm1a mutants) to complex phenotypes in which many organ sys-
tems are involved (e.g., Spns2 tm1a(KOMP)Wtsi homozygotes show 
eye, hearing, and immune defects; Nijnik et al., 2012). The distri-
bution of phenotypic hits is shown in Figures 5A and 5B for ho-
mozygous and heterozygous mutants, respectively. The peak 
for homozygotes was the category with no detected abnormal-
ities, whereas the second biggest group consists of mutants 
with just one phenotypic call. The lines examined as heterozy-</p>

<p>gotes all have at least one hit (viability), but 20 lines have in addi-
tion one other abnormal phenotype, and a handful have several. 
Classifying parameters into five disease categories, we analyzed 
the distribution of disease areas represented across all 250 
mouse lines. The most common phenotypic call was in the cate-
gory reproduction, development, and musculoskeletal 
(Figure 5C). 
Some abnormal phenotypes are clearly not primary effects; 
for example, reduced weight may be a secondary consequence 
of a number of different primary defects. Given that certain 
phenotypic features would be expected to co-occur frequently, 
reflecting physiological or developmental associations, a prin-
cipal component analysis was conducted to look for correlated 
patterns in the data. Plotting principal component 1 against 2 
revealed four main clusters of mouse lines (colored ovoids in 
Figure 5D). The separation along principal component 2 arises 
from viability. The remaining separation of clusters marked by 
red and green from clusters marked blue and yellow (Figure 5D) 
arises from body weight and associated variables, including 
DEXA measurements and energy use (Figure 5E). Body weight 
is a common covariable in disease (Reed et al., 2008), so it is 
not surprising that it dominates the principal component 
analysis. </p>

<p>Features of Essential Genes 
Genes are generally defined as essential if they are required for 
survival or fertility. Studies in yeast and worms suggest that 
genes with paralogs are much less likely to be essential, presum-
ably because the paralog can compensate for the function of the 
inactivated gene (Gu et al., 2003; Conant and Wagner, 2004). 
Previous analyses of published data on mouse knockouts did 
not find a significant difference in essential genes between 
singleton and duplicated genes (Liang and Li, 2007; Liao and 
Zhang, 2007). However, the published gene set is biased toward 
genes involved in development (Makino et al., 2009). In contrast, 
we found that genes in our set without a paralog were more than 
twice as likely to be essential, a significant effect (Table S3; 
Figure 7A). 
We next asked if the essential genes in our gene set are more 
likely to be involved in a protein complex, using an experimen-
tally validated data set of human protein complexes from the </p>

<p>Figure 2. Homozygous Viability and Fertility Overview </p>

<p>(A) Homozygous viability at P14 was assessed in 489 EUCOMM/KOMP targeted alleles. A minimum of 28 live progeny were required to assign viability status. 
Lines with 0% homozygotes were classed as lethal, &gt;0% and %13% as subviable, and &gt;13% as viable. 
(B) Comparison of homozygous viability data from targeted alleles carrying either a promoter-driven or promoterless neomycin selection cassette. 
(C) Lines classed as lethal or subviable at P14 were further assessed for viability at E14.5. Of the 205 targeted alleles eligible for this recessive lethality screen, 143 
are reported here. A total of 28 embryos were required to assign viability status, and outcomes were categorized by both the number and dysmorphology of 
homozygous offspring. 
(D) A basic dysmorphology screen encompassing 12 parameters was performed on all embryos for the 75 targeted alleles classed as viable or subviable at E14.5. 
A total of 34 targeted alleles showed one or more abnormality, and the percentage incidence is presented. 
(E-G) Examples of E14.5 dysmorphology (arrowheads indicate abnormalities) are presented. Homozygous progeny were detected at a Mendelian frequency in all 
three examples. Sixty-seven percent (six of nine) Mks1 tm1a/tm1a embryos presented with edema, polydactyly, and eye defects (E). Sixty-two percent (five of eight) 
Spnb2 tm1a/tm1a embryos presented with edema and hemorrhage (F). Eighty-six percent (six of seven) Psat1 tm1a/tm1a embryos presented with growth retardation, 
exencephaly, and craniofacial abnormalities (G). 
(H) Fertility was assessed in homozygous viable lines (307 mouse lines assessed from a total of 331 eligible lines). At least four independent 6-week-old mice of 
each sex were mated for a minimum of 6 weeks, and if progeny were born, the line was classed as fertile, regardless of if the progeny survived to weaning. Of note 
is the strong skew toward male (blue circle) fertility issues (15 of 16 genes) compared to 4 of 15 genes that displayed female (red circle) fertility issues. 
See also Table S3. </p>

<p>Cell 154, 452-464, July 18, 2013 ª2013 The Authors 457 </p>

<p>CORUM database (Ruepp et al., 2010). We found that genes with 
a human ortholog that is part of a complex were significantly 
more likely to be essential (Table S3; Figure 7B). 
Finally, we asked if there were certain types of gene products 
that were more likely to be important for viability/fertility than 
others. In humans, transcription factor mutations appear 
enhanced in prenatal disease, and enzymes are overrepresented 
in diseases with onset in the first year after birth (Jimenez-San-
chez et al., 2001). We investigated four classes of protein identi-
fied by GO terms: transcription factors (n = 7), transmembrane 
proteins (n = 50), enzymes (n = 131), and chromatin-associated 
proteins (n = 24). Numbers of each were limited, but there was 
no significant enrichment for essential genes among any of the 
four groups (Tables S2 and S3). 
In summary, we found that essential genes were less likely to 
have a paralog and more likely to be part of a protein complex, 
but no specific class of protein appeared more likely to be pre-
dictive of essentiality. </p>

<p>Annotating the Function of Novel Genes 
There is a large bias in the literature toward analysis of known 
genes (Edwards et al., 2011), but are genes that have yet to be 
examined experimentally less likely to underlie disease? Genes 
in our set that had no associated publications (other than high-
throughput genome-wide reports) were compared with genes 
where some aspect of their function had been described. The 
proportion of essential genes among the novel set was not 
significantly different from the known genes (Figure 7C). 
Furthermore, there was no significant difference in the number 
of hits observed per line between known and novel genes (Ta-
bles S2 and S3). As a second test, we asked if genes with or-
thologs involved in human disease (having an OMIM disease 
ID) were enriched in essential genes or the number of pheno-
typic hits compared with genes not (yet) ascribed to human dis-
ease, but there was no significant difference (Tables S2 and S3; 
Figure 7D). Finally, we compared genes that had been pro-
posed for inclusion by the community (n = 87) with those with 
no specific request to ask if genes of interest to the community 
were more likely to be essential or to have detected pheno-
types. There was no significant difference between the two 
groups (Table S3). Thus, known genes are no more likely to 
be involved in disease than novel genes, emphasizing that 
much new biology will be uncovered from the analysis of muta-
tions in novel genes. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Data Distributions for Selected Parameters </p>

<p>(A-F) Distribution of mean total cholesterol (A and B), mean HDL cholesterol (C 
and D), and mean LDL cholesterol (E and F) at 16 weeks of age in both sexes for 
250 unique alleles. Outliers are identified by gene name. The insets in (A)-(F) 
present the data for one outlier, Sec16b tm1a/tm1a (red circles represent indi-
vidual mice), compared to the WT controls processed during the same week 
(green circles), and a cumulative baseline of all WT mice of that age, sex, and 
genetic background (&gt;260 WT mice) is presented as the median and 95% 
confidence interval. 
(G and H) Distribution of mean body weight at 16 weeks in (G) female and (H) 
male mutant lines of mice. Outliers are identified by gene name. 
(I) Distribution of mean click ABR threshold at 14 weeks (typically n = 4, 
independent of sex). Outliers are identified by gene name including positive 
controls highlighted in red. </p>



<p>Figure 4. Examples of Novel Phenotypes from a Wide Range of Assays with Particular Focus on Novel Genes </p>

<p>(A) Elevated body weight gain of Kptn tm1a/tm1a females (n = 7) fed a high-fat diet from 4 weeks of age. Mean ± SD body weight is plotted against age for 
Kptn tm1a/tm1a females (red line) and local WT controls run during the same weeks (n = 16; green line). The median and 95% reference range (2.5% and 97.5%; 
dotted lines) for all WT mice of the same genetic background and sex (n = 956 females) are displayed on the pale green background. 
(B) Reduced grip strength in Dnase1l2 tm1a/tm1a males (n = 7) (red symbols) compared with controls (n = 8) (green symbols) and the reference range (n = 289). Each 
mouse is represented as a single symbol on the graph. Median, 25 th and 75 th percentile (box), and the lowest and highest data point still within 1.53 the 
interquartile range (IQR) (whiskers) are shown. 
(C and D) Ankylosis of the metacarpophalangeal joints (arrowheads) shown by X-ray in Dnase1l2 tm1a/tm1a mice (C) (six of seven males; five of seven females) 
compared with WT controls (D) correlates with reduced grip strength (B). 
(E) Increased latency to respond to heat stimulus in Git2 Gt(XG510)Byg/ Gt(XG510)Byg females (n = 6) (red symbols) compared with controls (n = 4) (green symbols) and 
the reference range (n = 115), with box and whisker plots on the left (see Figure 4B legend). 
(F) Mild hearing impairment at the middle range of frequencies in Fam107b tm1a/tm1a mutants (n = 8) (red line shows mean ± SD) compared with controls (n = 10) and 
the reference range (n = 440). 
(G) Smaller sebaceous glands (indicated by bracket) in Cbx7 tm1a/tm1a mutant tail skin hairs compared with WT (H). 
(I) Increased plasma magnesium levels in Rg9mtd2 tm1a/tm1a males (n = 8) (red symbols) compared with local controls (n = 15) (green symbols) and the reference 
range (n = 241), with box and whisker plots on the left (see Figure 4B legend). 
(J) Decreased lean mass in Atp5a1 tm1a/+ females (n = 3) (blue symbols) compared with local controls (n = 15) (green symbols) and the reference range (n = 757), 
with box and whisker plots on the left (see Figure 4B legend). 
(K and L) Histopathology showed opacities in the vitreous of eyes from Asx11 tm1a/+ mice (K) (arrowheads; scale bar, 500 mm) compared with empty vitreous 
in WT (L). 
(M and N) Higher magnification revealed round opacities extending from the lens into the vitreous (arrowheads; scale bar, 50 mm) in Asx11 tm1a/+ mice (M) 
compared with a normal lens contained within the lens capsule in WT mice (N). 
See also Table S5. </p>

<p>Cell 154, 452-464, July 18, 2013 ª2013 The Authors 459 </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Genetic studies in mice via targeted mutagenesis of ES cells 
have been successful at illuminating selected aspects of the 
function of more than 7,000 mammalian genes. However, until 
recently, these studies have been conducted by individual labo-
ratories and largely directed at previously studied genes. The 
focused collection of phenotypic information from these mutants 
has been very information rich, but many aspects remain unde-
tected because they are outside the area of interest of the labo-
ratory generating the mutant. Individual endeavors have led to 
wide variation in allele design and genetic backgrounds used, 
and all too often, the mutant is not available to other groups for 
further analysis. In contrast, the mutant mice described here 
have the advantage of a common genetic background and a </p>

<p>Figure 5. Characteristics of Phenotypic Hits 
Detected </p>

<p>(A) Distribution of the number of phenotypic hits in 
each line screened as homozygotes showing the 
peak at no hits but a long tail of lines with multiple 
hits up to 41. 
(B) Distribution of hits in lines screened as het-
erozygotes; all lines had at least one hit (for 
viability) with a spread up to 14 hits. 
(C) Distribution of lines with hits in different disease 
areas showing a peak of lines with just one area 
affected (colors indicate which areas) but some 
lines with multiple disease areas involved, indi-
cating a high degree of pleiotropy. 
(D) Principal component analysis score scatterplot 
showing the deviation of each gene from the first 
two principal components to visualize the clus-
tering in genes within the multidimensional space. 
The black ovoid represents the Hotelling's T 2 95% 
confidence limits. Colored ovoids mark four 
different clusters of mutant lines. The two main 
principal components (or latent variables) in the 
model are significant in explaining 19.2% and 
11.7% of the variation, respectively, and are 
predictive. 
(E) Principal component analysis contribution plot 
indicating the contribution of the variables to the 
separation between the red and green clusters 
compared to the blue and yellow clusters in (D). 
Major phenotypic contributions are labeled. 
Key to variables is presented in Table S7. </p>

<p>standard allele design with the option of 
generating conditional mutations, and all 
are available from public repositories. 
The phenotyping described here was 
not intended to provide an exhaustive 
characterization of the phenotype of the 
mutant lines but, rather, to place mutant 
alleles into broad categories by using 
screens, generating a pool of genetic re-
sources from which individual mutants 
can be selected based on their pheno-
type for secondary follow-up studies. 
Several of the mutants have been 
analyzed further following an initial phenotypic observation in 
the screen, and these add to the depth of our knowledge of bio-
logical mechanisms of disease (e.g., Nijnik et al., 2012; Crossan 
et al., 2011). As the assembled data expands, it will become 
possible to discern patterns between phenotypes and come to 
more holistic conclusions about categories of genes. Genes 
linked by common phenotypes can be grouped together to 
test for regulatory or other functional interactions and ultimately 
placed into pathways that in turn will implicate other genes in the 
disease process. For example, of the four genes associated with 
abnormal fasting glucose levels in our data set, Slc16a2 can be 
linked to Ldha via regulation of L-triiodothyronine (Friesema 
et al., 2006; Miller et al., 2001), but the other two genes, Nsun2 
and Cyb561, have no reported regulatory links apart from 
in vitro protein-protein interactions, so these represent </p>



<p>Figure 6. Correlated Disease Characteristics in Knockouts of Three Known Human Disease Genes </p>

<p>(A-E) Male hemizygotes for the Sms mutation showed similar features to X-linked Snyder-Robinson syndrome. 
(A) Reduced grip strength in Sms/Y mice (n = 8) (purple symbols) compared with WT controls (n = 30) (green symbols) and the reference range (n = 793). Each 
mouse is represented as a single symbol on the graph, with box and whisker plots on the left (see Figure 4B legend). 
(B and C) Decreased lean mass (B) and bone mineral density (C) in Sms/Y mice (n = 8) (purple symbols) compared with controls (n = 27) (green symbols) and the 
reference range (n = 753), with box and whisker plots on the left (see Figure 4B legend). 
(D and E) Lumbar lordosis shown by X-ray (seven of eight males) in Sms/Y (E) compared with WT (D). </p>

<p>(legend continued on next page) </p>

<p>Cell 154, 452-464, July 18, 2013 ª2013 The Authors 461 </p>

<p>candidates to investigate further. Already some broad conclu-
sions can be drawn from the data set, such as the value of 
analyzing novel genes, the increased incidence of essentiality 
in genes with no paralog, and the increased number of genes 
required for male compared to female fertility. Many completely 
unexpected associations between genes and phenotypes 
have been discovered, illustrating the value of a broad-based 
screen. 
Another aspect of our study was the examination of heterozy-
gous mutants, a genotype that often is not studied by individual 
laboratories. Although this was restricted to mutants that dis-
played lethality or subviability of homozygotes, it revealed a 
number of genes with haploinsufficiency, a feature commonly 
associated with mutations in the human genome but rarely 
described in mouse knockouts. 
The tests used in screening varied considerably in their 
complexity, cost, and suitability in a high-throughput scenario. 
The performance of these tests across 250 alleles provided 
insight into those that should be included or excluded in the 
efforts to examine 5,000 alleles through the activities of the 
IMPC. Key considerations are variance in the control group, 
specificity, sensitivity, effect size, and redundancy. </p>

<p>The major contribution of null alleles will be an improved 
understanding of biological processes and molecular mecha-
nisms of disease. The null allele will give insight into the temporal 
and spatial requirements for the gene and will contribute to the 
establishment of gene networks involved in mammalian disease 
processes. Furthermore, our data set demonstrates that many 
features of human Mendelian diseases can be found in the cor-
responding mouse mutant. The mouse alleles studied here are 
expected to be null alleles or strong hypomorphs, which may 
not always reflect the consequence of the human mutation. 
However, null alleles should reveal haploinsufficiency and reces-
sive effects due to deleterious mutations such as frameshift and 
nonsense mutations. Null alleles in the mouse are likely to make 
the largest impact upon understanding human diseases caused 
by rare variants of large effect size. Complex multifactorial dis-
eases, which may depend on human-specific variants with small 
effect size or more specific molecular effects such as gain-of-
function mutations, will require more customized approaches 
such as knockin of specific human mutations. Alternative 
approaches using the mouse for discovering loci underlying 
complex disease include the Hybrid Mouse Diversity panel and 
the Collaborative Cross (reviewed by Flint and Eskin, 2012). </p>

<p>(F-J) Ap4e1 tm1a/tm1a mice displayed similarities to spastic quadriplegic cerebral palsy 4. 
(F-I) Increased lateral ventricle area (arrowheads in F and G) and decreased corpus callosum span (solid lines in F and G) in Ap4e1 tm1a/tm1a mice (G) compared 
with WT mice (F) with measurements plotted (mean ± SD) in (H) and (I), respectively (*p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01; n = 3 mutant males and 34 WT males). Error bars in (H) 
and (I) are SD. 
(J) Decreased rearing in Ap4e1 tm1a/tm1a females (n = 7) (red symbols) compared with WT controls (n = 8) (green symbols) and the reference range (n = 180), with 
box and whisker plots on the left (see Figure 4B legend). 
(K-O) Surviving Smc3 tm1a/+ mice showed similar features to Cornelia de Lange syndrome 3. 
(K) Decreased body weight in Smc3 tm1a/+ females (n = 7) fed on high-fat diet. Mean ± SD body weight is plotted against age for Smc3 tm1a/+ females (blue line), 
WT mice (n = 24; green line), and the reference range (n = 948). 
(L and M) Distinct craniofacial abnormalities in Smc3 tm1a/+ mice including upturned snout (M) (three of seven males, one of seven females), which was not 
observed in WTs (L) (n = 850 male and 859 female). 
(N and O) The lacZ reporter gene revealed a distinct Smc3 expression pattern including (N) hair follicles and (O) key brain substructures, noteworthy because of 
the hirsutism and neurodevelopmental delay aspects of Cornelia de Lange syndrome 3. 
See also Table S6. </p>

<p>Figure 7. Features Associated with Essen-
tial Genes </p>

<p>Essential genes (black bars) are compared with 
genes that are not essential for viability (red bars). 
The asterisk (*) indicates significant difference. ns, 
no significant difference in proportion of essential 
genes between the two categories. Statistics are 
presented in Table S3. 
(A) Genes with no paralog show a significantly 
larger proportion of essential lines than genes with 
at least one paralog. 
(B) Genes predicted to contribute to protein 
complexes showed a significantly larger propor-
tion of essential lines than genes not predicted to 
contribute to a complex. 
(C) Novel genes showed no significant difference 
in proportion of essential genes or number of hits 
than known genes. 
(D) Genes known to underlie human disease were 
no more likely to be essential than genes not yet 
associated with human disease. </p>



<p>These allow interrogation of many different loci simultaneously 
and study of epistatic interactions and can lead to identification 
of single gene variants causing disease (e.g., Orozco et al., 2012; 
Andreux et al., 2012), when variants affecting the trait of interest 
are present in the founders. ENU mutagenesis is another power-
ful technique that can be used to produce allelic series of muta-
tions with differing effects upon function of single genes (e.g., 
Andrews et al., 2012). However, the null alleles that we describe 
here are a complement to these alternative approaches and will 
be invaluable for defining mechanisms of gene function on a 
standard genetic background. 
The study described in this report builds on the large KOMP/ 
EUCOMM resource of targeted mutations in mouse ES cells 
(Skarnes et al., 2011) and illustrates the breadth of phenotypic 
information that can be garnered from an organized effort. The 
Clinical Phenotyping Pipeline optimized here has been adopted 
by several other programs within the IMPC; multiple groups are 
now working together to extend what is described in this report 
for 250 genes to 5,000 genes over the next 4 years with the vision 
that this will eventually cover all protein-coding genes. The pri-
mary phenotypes and genetic resources emerging from these 
programs will make a significant contribution to our understand-
ing of mammalian gene function. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>Animals 
Mice carrying knockout first conditional-ready alleles (Figures S1A and S1B) 
were generated from the KOMP/EUCOMM targeted ES cell resource using 
standard techniques. Eight in-house lines were included as known mutant 
controls. Details of the 250 lines can be found in Table S2. All lines are available 
from http://www.knockoutmouse.org/; or mouseinterest@sanger.ac.uk. Mice 
were maintained in a specific pathogen-free unit under a 12 hr light, 12 hr dark 
cycle with ad libitum access to water and food. The care and use of mice were 
in accordance with the UK Home Office regulations, UK Animals (Scientific 
Procedures) Act of 1986. </p>

<p>Genotyping and Allele Quality Control 
Short-range, long-range and quantitative PCR strategies (http://www. 
knockoutmouse.org/kb/25/) were used to evaluate the quality of each allele 
(Figure S1C). A subset of these assays was used to genotype offspring. The 
degree of knockdown in homozygotes was assessed by qRT-PCR of adult 
liver in a subset known to show expression in liver. Details are given in 
Extended Experimental Procedures. </p>

<p>Phenotyping Pipeline and Tests 
The typical workflow from chimera to primary phenotyping pipelines and an 
outline of the clinical phenotyping pipeline are presented in Figure 1. Details 
of batch size are given in Figure S2A. These pipelines include established tests 
used to characterize systematically every line of mice as described in Table S4. </p>

<p>Histochemical Analysis of the lacZ Reporter 
Adult whole-mount lacZ reporter gene expression was carried out essentially 
as described by Valenzuela et al. (2003). </p>

<p>Statistical and Bioinformatic Analysis 
For continuous data, including time course, a reference range approach was 
used to identify phenotypic variants as detailed in Figures S3A and S3B. 
Fisher's exact test was used to assess categorical data (Figure S3C). These 
automated calls were complemented by a manual assessment made by 
biological experts. An example of the establishment of the reference range 
is given in Figure S2B. </p>

<p>Downstream data analysis was performed using <rs id="software-3" type="software">SPSS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">version 17.0.2</rs>), R, 
and <rs id="software-0" type="software">SIMCA-P</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V-12.0</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Umetrics</rs>). The data structure and biological question 
determined the statistical test used; details are in Table S3. Principal compo-
nents analysis was performed in SIMCA-P (http://www.umetrics.com). 
Further details of analyses and gene annotations are given in Extended 
Experimental Procedures. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTAL INFORMATION </p>

<p>Supplemental Information includes Extended Experimental Procedures, three 
figures, seven tables, and a complete list of contributors from the Sanger Insti-
tute Mouse Genetics Project and can be found with this article online at http:// 
dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2013.06.022. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Alex Bateman, Lars Barquist, Steve O'Rahilly, Keith Burling, Seth 
Grant, Pentao Liu, and Lorraine Everett for advice and the EUMODIC con-
sortium for discussions. This work was supported by the Wellcome Trust 
(grant Nos. 098051 to Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute and RG45277 PCAG/ 
116 to F.M.W.), Medical Research Council (to K.P.S. and F.M.W.), European 
Commission (EUMODIC contract No. LSHG-CT-2006-037188), NIH 
(EY08213 to S.H.T. and 5K08EY020530-02 to V.B.M.), Research to Prevent 
Blindness (to S.H.T. and V.B.M.), Australian Research Council (DP1092723 
to I.S.), and Cancer Research UK (to D.J.A.). J.K.W. and K.P.S. conceived 
and devised the single phenotyping pipeline and principles of analysis and pre-
sentation of the data; R.R.S., J.K.W., R.H., J.R.B., and E.R. managed mouse 
production and genotyping; J.N.B. and J.S. managed mouse breeding; 
A.K.G., C.P., J.E., D.S., N.I., and J.K.W. managed mouse phenotyping and 
analyzed data; the Sanger Institute Mouse Genetics Project team contributed 
to all aspects of the work; S.C. and G.D. led the infectious challenge screen; 
V.B.M. and S.H.T. led the eye histopathology screen; I.S. and F.M.W. led the 
skin screen; J.F. led the brain histopathology screen; D.J.A. led the micronu-
cleus screen; J.N.B. and J.R.B. managed mouse distribution; J.K.W., 
A.K.G., M.B., and K.P.S. compiled Tables S1, S2, S5, and S6; N.A.K., D.M., 
D.S., and M.B. carried out annotation and statistical analysis; N.C.A., 
D.G.M., and W.C.S. led development of informatics support; D.W.L. wrote 
Wiki pages for the mutants; J.K.W., D.J.A., R.R.S., and K.P.S. led the project; 
and K.P.S., A.B., and J.K.W. wrote the paper with contributions from all 
authors. </p>

<p>Received: March 14, 2013 
Revised: May 10, 2013 
Accepted: June 17, 2013 
Published: July 18, 2013 </p>





</text></tei>