<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3939369" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Study Design: Retrospective analysis of radiological images. 
Purpose: To determine the prevalence of lumbosacral transition vertebra (LSTV) and to study its significance with respect to clinically 
significant spinal symptoms, disc degeneration and herniation. 
Overview of Literature: LSTV is the most common congenital anomaly of the lumbosacral spine. The prevalence has been debated 
to vary between 7% and 30%, and its relationship to back pain, disc degeneration and herniation has also not been established. 
Methods: The study involved examining the radiological images of 3 groups of patients. Group A consisted of kidney urinary bladder 
(KUB) X-rays of patients attending urology outpatient clinic. Group B consisted of X-rays with or without magnetic resonance images 
(MRIs) of patients at-tending a spine outpatient clinic, and group C consisted of X-rays and MRI of patients who had undergone sur-
gery for lumbar disc herniation. One thousand patients meeting the inclusion criteria were selected to be in each group. LSTV was 
classified by Castellvi's classification and disc degeneration was assessed by Pfirrmann's grading on MRI scans. 
Results: The prevalence of LSTV among urology outpatients, spine outpatients and discectomy patients was 8.1%, 14%, and 16.9% 
respectively. LSTV patients showed a higher Pfirrmann's grade of degeneration of the last mobile disc. Results were found to be sig-
nificant statistically. 
Conclusions: The prevalence of LSTV in spinal outpatients and discectomy patients was significantly higher as compared to those 
attending the urology outpatient clinic. There was a definite causal relationship between the transitional vertebra and the degenera-
tion of the disc immediately cephalad to it. </p>

<p>Clinical Study </p>

<p>Asian Spine J 2014;8(1):51-58 • http://dx.Lumbosacral transition vertebra (LSTV) is the most 
common congenital anomaly of the lumbosacral spine 
and may manifest either as a sacral assimilation of the 
5th lumbar vertebra (sacralisation) or separation of the 
1st sacral vertebra into the lumbar spine (lumbarisation) 
[1,2]. The prevalence of LSTV is said to vary between 7% </p>

<p>and 30% in various studies [3]. Apazidis et al. [4] studied 
kidney urinary bladder (KUB) radiographs of patients at-
tending a urology clinic and described the prevalence of 
LSTV to be 35% in the American population. LSTV as a 
cause of low back pain was first described in 1917 as the 
Bartolotti syndrome [5]. However, its significance with 
respect to low back pain has been debated by several au-
thors since then [6]. A causal relationship between LSTV </p>

<p>Vijay Sekharappa et al. 
 
Asian Spine J 2014;8(1):51-58 </p>

<p>and disc degeneration and herniation has also been not 
well established, with some authors reporting a higher 
rate of degeneration adjacent to the LSTV [7,8], while 
others [9-11] have reported no such association. The 
objective of this study was to determine the prevalence 
of LSTV and to study its significance with respect to 
clinically significant symptoms (low back pain and/or ra-
dicular leg pain), radiological disc degeneration and disc 
herniations. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>This study was designed as a retrospective analysis of ra-
diological images (X-ray and magnetic resonance imag-
ing [MRI]) of 3 groups of patients. </p>

<p>1. Group A (urology outpatients) </p>

<p>This group consisted of the KUB X-rays of patients at-
tending the urology outpatient department (OPD). It 
was ensured that each X-ray that was included showed 
adequate visualization of the following anatomical struc-
tures-the last thoracic vertebra with the attached rib, all 
the lumbar vertebrae including the transverse processes 
of the first and last lumbar vertebrae, sacrum and iliac 
crests. Patients with poor quality radiographs or where 
there was suboptimal visualization of all of the above-
mentioned anatomical landmarks, as well as those with </p>

<p>a visible pathological lesion in the lumbar spine were ex-
cluded. Patients with radiological records showing lum-
bar spinal imaging or OPD records showing a visit to the 
spinal OPD clinic were excluded from group A. </p>

<p>2. Group B (spine outpatients) </p>

<p>This group consisted of patients with X-rays with or with-
out an MRI lumbosacral (LS) spine attending the spine 
OPD. Patients with poorly exposed films, films showing 
severe osteoporosis of the vertebra with biconvex disc 
spaces, vertebral destruction due to trauma/infection/ 
tumor, postoperative changes such as a laminectomy 
defect, implants in situ, isthmic spondylolisthesis or 
spondylolysis, degenerative listhesis of grade 2 and above, 
deformities such as scoliosis, features suggestive of an-
kylosing spondylitis, and hypertrophic osteoarthropathy, 
and those operated single level discectomy were excluded 
from group B. </p>

<p>3. Group C (discectomy patients) </p>

<p>This group consisted of X-rays and MRI LS spine of pa-
tients operated on for single level disc herniation of any 
of the last three mobile discs. Patients with multilevel disc 
herniation, high lumbar disc prolapse (above the third 
mobile disc), canal stenosis without disc prolapse, or with 
any other pathological condition in the adjacent levels </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D 
E </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Castellvi's types of lumbosacral transition vertebra (LSTV). (A) X-ray showing normal lumbosacral spine (non-LSTV). (B) X-
ray showing type Ib LSTV. Type I: dysplastic transverse process with a width more than 19 mm. Unilateral (type Ia) and bilateral (type 
Ib). (C) X-ray showing type IIa LSTV. Type II: presence of pseudoarthosis between the transverse process and ala of the sacrum. 
Unilateral (type Ia) and bilateral (type Ib). (D) X-ray showing type IIIb LSTV. Type III: presence of bony fusion between transverse 
process and ala of sacrum. Unilateral (type Ia) and bilateral (type Ib). (E) X-ray showing type IV. Type IV: presence of pseudoarthro-
sis on one side and bony fusion on the other. </p>

<p>Lumbosacral transition vertebra </p>

<p>Asian Spine Journal 
Asian Spine Journal </p>



<p>such as tumor or infection were excluded. 
The numbering of the lumbar vertebrae was done ac-
cording to the method described by Bron et al. [1]. Ac-
cording to this method, a vertebra showing the presence 
of an attached rib, either fully formed or rudimentary, 
was considered to be the last thoracic vertebra, and the 
next caudal vertebra was named the first lumbar vertebra. 
The intercristal line on the antero-posterior radiograph 
of the lumbar spine was considered to correspond to the </p>

<p>L4-L5 disc space, as described by Chakraverty et al. [12]. 
An upward and laterally directed transverse process was 
considered to belong to a thoracic vertebra, whereas a 
horizontally directed transverse process was considered 
to belong to a lumbar vertebra. The lumbar vertebra with 
the longest transverse process was considered as the third 
lumbar vertebra. 
Based on these anatomical characteristics, we defined 
"lumbarisation of S1" as the presence of 5 distinct lumbar 
vertebrae with the transverse process of the first sacral 
vertebra either fusing with or forming a pseudarthrosis 
with the sacral ala. "Sacralization of L5" was said to occur 
when the transverse process of the last lumbar vertebra 
formed either a bony bridge or a pseudarthrosis with the 
sacral ala. The morphological type of LSTV was identified 
based on Castellvi's classification (Fig. 1) [1]. Castellvi's 
type I has been considered a variation of normal due to 
the presence of a mobile disc caudal to the vertebra in 
question and so was not called a transitional vertebra in 
our study. The last three mobile discs were numbered M1, 
M2, and M3 from a caudal to cephalad direction (Fig. 2). 
The presence of 4 or 6 lumbar vertebrae without a bony 
fusion or pseudoarthrosis at the last lumbar vertebra was 
considered as a thoracolumbar transition and these pa-
tients was excluded from the study (Fig. 3). 
Demographic data (age and sex), the presence of LSTV 
in the radiographic images and its type was recorded 
in all the 3 groups. Among the patients in group B who 
also had an MRI, disc degeneration was assessed by Pfir-
rmann's grading system (Fig. 4) [13]. Similar grading of 
disc degeneration was done in group C at the non herni-
ated levels, i.e., if M1 was the herniated level, Pfirrmann's 
grading was assigned to the discs at the M2 and M3 </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Labelling of mobile discs from caudal to cephalad as M1, M2, 
and M3. </p>

<p>A 
B 
C 
D </p>

<p>Fig. 3. X-rays showing lumbosacral transitional vertebrae sacralisation (A), lumbarisation and thoracolumbar transitional verte-
brae (B), 4 lumbar vertebrae (C), and 6 lumbar vertebrae (D). </p>

<p>Vijay Sekharappa et al. 
 
Asian Spine J 2014;8(1):51-58 </p>

<p>levels. Based on this system, degeneration was graded as 
'normal' (Pfirrmann's grade I), 'mild' (Pfirrmann's grade 
II) and 'advanced' (grades III-V). This was based on Lam 
et al. [14]'s findings of a positive provocative discography 
in 0%, 9%, and 71% of patients with Pfirrmann's grades I, 
II, III respectively and 100% in patients with Pfirrmann's 
grade IV and V. Lam et al. [14] stated that Pfirrmann's 
grading correlated strongly with the clinical symptoms. 
Radiological images of 1,000 consecutive patients meet-
ing the inclusion criteria were selected for each group 
retrospectively from the hospital's OPD and operation 
records. The sample size of 3,000 was calculated from a 
similar study by Kong et al. [11], in which they found no 
significant difference between the LSTV and non-LSTV 
groups in degenerative spondylolisthesis patients, with a 
p-value of 0.8 and a sample size of 78, using "the N mas-
ter software. " In order to maintain consistency and avoid 
inter-observer variability, all the observations, classifica-
tions and grading were done by a single qualified spinal 
surgeon. The study was conducted in a major tertiary care 
centre with a daily OPD input of 6,000 patients including 
all specialities. The chi-square and proportion tests were 
used to compare 2 sets of variables and a p-value of less 
than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. Statisti-
cal analysis was done using 'The <rs type="software">R</rs> statistical software' by </p>

<p>a qualified statistician. Probability and relative risks were 
also calculated using the same software. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The prevalence of LSTV in groups A, B, and C was 8.1%, 
14%, and 16.9% respectively, with an overall prevalence 
of 13% (Table 1). The type IIA pattern was found to be 
the commonest followed by type IIIB. The prevalence of 
LSTV in groups B and C was found to be significantly 
higher than in group A (p&lt;0.001). The overall prevalence 
of sacralization was 11% and lumbarisation was 2%. The 
prevalence of LSTV was higher in females in all the 3 
groups by about 1.3 times compared to males (Table 2). 
Among the total of 1,000 patients in group B, there 
were 786 patients who only had X-rays and 214 patients 
with both X-rays and MRIs. The prevalence of LSTV 
in these two groups was found to be 12.7% and 18.7%, 
respectively (Table 3), a difference that was statistically 
significant (p=0.025), indicating that LSTV was more 
likely to be encountered in patients symptomatic enough 
to require MRI scanning. 
Among the 214 patients who had an MRI, we com-
pared Pfirrmann's grading between the LSTV and non-
LSTV groups at M1, M2 and M3 separately (Fig. 5). At </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>D 
E </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Pfirrmann's grading of disc degeneration on T2-weighted magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) image. (A) Grade 1: nucleus 
appears homogenously white, disc height is preserved, clear distinction between nucleus and annulus. (B) Grade 2: similar to 
grade 1 except for some signal intensity changes in the nucleus like horizontal clefts. (C) Grade 3: nucleus appears gray, disc 
height preserved or slightly reduced, distinction between nucleus and annulus is unclear. (D) Grade 4: nucleus appears black, with 
moderate reduction in the disc height without any distinction between nucleus and annulus. (E) Grade 5: completely collapsed 
homogenously black disc. </p>

<p>Lumbosacral transition vertebra </p>

<p>Asian Spine Journal 
Asian Spine Journal </p>



<p>M1, the LSTV group had significantly advanced degener-
ation (Pfirrmann's grades 3-5) as compared to non-LSTV 
patients (p=0.003). The corresponding degeneration pat-
terns at the M2 and M3 levels did not show statistical dif-
ferences between the LSTV and non-LSTV groups. 
In group C, we assessed the prevalence of LSTV in pa-
tients who had undergone single-level disc surgery at M1, </p>

<p>M2, or M3 levels separately, and found the prevalence 
to be 29.4%, 2.9% and 11.3% respectively (Table 4). The 
prevalence of LSTV in this group (group C) at each level 
(M1, M2, and M3) was compared with those of group 
A using the proportion test. At M1, the prevalence was 
significantly higher, and at M2, it was significantly lower, 
with a p-value of less than 0.001, and there was no differ-
ence at M3. 
Finally, we assigned Pfirrmann's grade to the non-
herniated discs in all of the 1,000 patients in group C; i.e., 
if the herniation was at M1, then Pfirrmann's grade of M2 
and M3 were recorded. We then compared Pfirrmann's 
grading between the LSTV and non-LSTV groups at each 
level (M1, M2, and M3) separately, as was previously 
done for group B (Fig. 6). The pattern of Pfirrmann's 
grading between the LSTV and non-LSTV groups were 
similar to that in group B. At M1, the LSTV group had a 
significantly higher prevalence of mild and advanced de-
generation as compared to the non-LSTV group (p=0.017 
and p=0.02). At M2 there was an equal incidence of mild 
degeneration in both groups, but the LSTV group had 
significantly less advanced degeneration as compared to 
the non-LSTV group (p=0.001). At M3, the LSTV group 
had a significantly lower prevalence of mild as well as 
advanced degeneration as compared to the non-LSTV </p>

<p>Table 1. Number of cases and prevalence of LSTV in each group </p>

<p>Group No. of cases 
No. of LSTV 
Prevalence (%) 
S 
L </p>

<p>Types </p>

<p>IIA 
IIB 
IIIA 
IIIB 
IV </p>

<p>A 
1,000 
81 
8.10 
65 
16 
36 
4 
9 
26 
6 </p>

<p>B 
1,000 
140 
14.00 
120 
20 
53 
7 
3 
64 
10 </p>

<p>C 
1,000 
169 
16.90 
145 
24 
68 
9 
10 
61 
12 </p>

<p>Total 
3,000 
390 
13 
330 
60 
157 
20 
22 
151 
28 </p>

<p>LSTV, lumbosacral transition vertebra; S, sacralised lumbar vertebra; L, lumbarailsed sacrum. </p>

<p>Table 2. Sex specific prevalence of LSTV in each group </p>

<p>Group </p>

<p>Male 
Female </p>

<p>LSTV 
Total cases Prevalence (%) 
LSTV 
Total cases Prevalence (%) </p>

<p>A 
51 
711 
7.10 
30 
289 
10.30 </p>

<p>B 
75 
582 
12.90 
65 
418 
15.50 </p>

<p>C 
114 
750 
15.20 
55 
250 
22.80 </p>

<p>Total 
240 
2,043 
11.70 
150 
957 
15.50 </p>

<p>LSTV, lumbosacral transition vertebra. </p>

<p>Table 3. Number of cases and prevalance of LSTV among patients 
who had X-ray alone and those who had X-ray and MRI both </p>

<p>Patients with/ 
without MRI </p>

<p>No. of 
LSTV </p>

<p>Total 
cases 
Prevalence (%) </p>

<p>Patients with MRI 
40 
214 
18.69 </p>

<p>Patients without MRI 
100 
786 
12.70 </p>

<p>LSTV, lumbosacral transition vertebra; MRI, magnetic resonance imag-
ing. </p>

<p>Table 4. Prevelance of LSTV in patients with disc herniation at M1, 
M2, and M3 in group C </p>

<p>Level of disc 
herniation </p>

<p>Total 
cases </p>

<p>No. of 
LSTV 
Prevalence (%) </p>

<p>M1 
511 
150 
29.35 </p>

<p>M2 
436 
13 
2.90 </p>

<p>M3 
53 
6 
11.32 </p>

<p>LSTV, lumbosacral transition vertebra. </p>

<p>Vijay Sekharappa et al. 
 
Asian Spine J 2014;8(1):51-58 </p>

<p>group (p=0.002 and p=0.025, respectively). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Our study showed a statistically significant higher preva-
lence of LSTV among spinal OPD patients and discec-
tomy patients as compared to urology OPD patients. 
However, group A, consisting of patients attending the 
urology OPD, may not be representative of the general 
or purely asymptomatic population. But when this group 
was considered as a whole, patients were definitely was 
less symptomatic with respect to the back than group B, 
as all the patients in group B were symptomatic and hence 
had consulted the spinal OPD. Moreover, estimating the 
prevalence in purely asymptomatic people would involve </p>

<p>exposing otherwise healthy people to harmful radiation, 
which would be unethical and unacceptable. The method 
of using KUB X-rays has been employed by other authors 
such as Apazidis et al. [4], whose study is described in the 
literature. For these reasons, group A would be the best 
possible group, although not ideal, to serve as a control 
for comparison with symptomatic spinal outpatients and 
patients in the discectomy groups. 
The fact that spine imaging studies are undertaken 
in our outpatient clinic, not as a routine but only in the 
presence of any red flags such as extremes of age, daily 
activities affected, presence of constitutional symptoms, 
persistent pain not relieved with medication, indicated 
that group B represented a population with clinically 
significant spinal symptoms. The subgroup of patients in </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Comparison between number of cases and percentage of each Pfirrmann's grade (PF) in lumbosacral transition vertebra (LSTV) 
and non-LSTV groups at M1 (A), M2 (B), and M3 (C), with area diagram depicting the same group B. M1 showing greater degen-
eration in the LSTV groups with the M2 and M3 levels showing a similar pattern between the LSTV and non-LSTV groups. </p>

<p>Lumbosacral transition vertebra </p>

<p>Asian Spine Journal 
Asian Spine Journal </p>



<p>group B who had both X-ray and MRI done were even 
more representative of the population with clinically 
significant symptoms, as their symptoms were severe 
enough to warrant an expensive investigation such as 
MRI. Our study showed a statistically significant higher 
prevalence of LSTV in this subgroup as well, when com-
pared to group A or the subgroup of group B who had 
X-ray alone. 
Statistically, the probability or the relative risk of find-
ing a transitional vertebra in a patient with clinically 
significant spinal symptoms would be 1.75 times higher 
than in patients attending a urology OPD with non-
spinal complaints. This probability would increase to 2.3 
times among patients with symptoms severe enough to 
require an MRI and increase to 3.6 times among patients </p>

<p>with last mobile disc herniation requiring discectomies. 
Based on these observations, it is possible to conclude 
that LSTV is more like to be seen in patients with clini-
cally significant spinal symptoms and even more so in 
those operated on for disc herniation of the last mobile 
disc. However, whether LSTV is the cause of the spinal 
symptoms or disc herniation could not be established by 
this study, but it does give a hint as to the direction fur-
ther investigations should take. 
The degree of discal degeneration on MRI showed 
distinctly different patterns in the LSTV and non-LSTV 
groups. Advanced discal degeneration (Pfirmann's grades 
3-5) at the level supra-adjacent to the LSTV (i.e., at M1) 
was encountered significantly more commonly in the 
LSTV group (p=0.003). From these results, our study </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Comparison between number of cases and percentage of each Pfirrmann's grade of the discs at the non herniated levels (PF) 
in the lumbosacral transition vertebra (LSTV) and non-LSTV groups at M1 (A), M2 (B), and M3 (C), with an area diagram depicting 
the same in group C. M1 showing greater degeneration in the LSTV groups with the M2 and M3 levels showing a similar pattern 
between the LSTV and non-LSTV groups. </p>

<p>Vijay Sekharappa et al. 
 
Asian Spine J 2014;8(1):51-58 </p>

<p>established a definite causal relationship between the 
transitional vertebra and degeneration of the disc imme-
diately cephalad to it. The most likely explanation for this 
is that the motion segment cephalad to the LSTV has to 
bear additional stresses by virtue of it being juxtaposed to 
a relatively non-mobile segment, with the stresses borne 
by it similar to the stresses encountered by a disc adjacent 
to a mono-segmental fusion. The fact that discal degen-
eration at levels further cephalad (M2 and M3) showed a 
similar pattern in both the LSTV and non-LSTV groups 
further strengthens this argument. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>The prevalence of LSTV in urology outpatients, spinal 
outpatients and discectomy patients was 8%, 14%, and 
17% respectively, with an overall prevalence of 13%. Fe-
males had about 1.3 times higher prevalence of LSTV as 
compared to males. Almost 30% of patients operated on 
for symptomatic last mobile disc herniation had LSTV. 
The probability of finding LSTV in patients with clinical 
symptoms requiring an X-ray, those requiring an MRI 
and those requiring surgery for last mobile disc hernia-
tion was 1.75, 2.3, and 3.6 times higher respectively than 
those attending a urology OPD with non spinal symp-
toms. There was a definite causal relationship between the 
transitional vertebra and degeneration of the disc imme-
diately cephalad to it. Whether this is the cause of spinal 
symptoms and last mobile disc herniations in people with 
transitional vertebra requires further study. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article 
was reported. </p>



</text></tei>