<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3309253" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective To compare the voice onset time (VOT) differences of Korean stops in the initial and intervocalic 
positions between the aphasic patients with peculiarities of aspiration and a control group. 
Method We examined 15 aphasic patients (nine males, six females) who had suff ered a stroke (average age 49.7 
years) and 15 healthy controls (average age 47.4 years). An aphasia examination was made by an aphasia battery of 
three standard tests and VOT was analyzed instrumentally. Stop consonants in the initial and intervocalic position 
were measured to categorize them according to aphasia types, place of articulation, and manner of articulation. 
Results VOT of the aphasic patients with peculiarities of aspiration had a greater difference than that of the 
controls, indicating that the temporal non-coordination between the laryngeal adjustment and oral articulators of 
aphasic patients happens due to the VOT of stops in the initial and intervocalic positions (p&lt;0.05). 
Conclusion VOT of stop consonants in the initial position produced by aphasic patients tends to be proportional 
to their breathing. It can cause glottal width and make aphasic patients' VOT duration longer. Lastly, the method 
to measure the VOT of aphasic patients is more significant for the types of phonation than for the places of 
articulation, and makes it possible to induce abnormal VOT. </p>

<p>Aphasia is a partial or general disorder of recognition 
systems and other communication mechanisms, which 
are the basis of language patterns and language itself, 
and which is due to damage to the speech portion of the 
central nervous system, and it is often defined as the 
neurological disability to understand or form language. 1 
Also, the language disorder of aphasic patients can be 
categorized in two ways: typological, in which one or 
more aspects of language understanding, where the 
output of aphasia patients is invaded, and non-typo-
lo gical, in which all other aspects of language under-</p>

<p>Received August 6, 2010; Accepted June 21, 2011 
Corresponding author: Myoung-Hwan Ko 
Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, Chonbuk National 
University Medical School, San 2-20, Keumam-dong, Dukjin-gu, Jeonju 
561-180, Korea 
Tel: +82-63-250-1795, Fax: +82-63-254-4145, E-mail: mhko@chonbuk. 
ac.kr 
This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted 
noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, 
provided the original work is properly cited. 
Copyright © 2011 by Korean Academy of Rehabilitation Medicine </p>

<p>Voice Onset Time Variations of Korean Stop Consonants in Aphasic Speakers </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>standing and output have been damaged. 2 How ever, 
there can be some cases where this defi nition might not 
be limited to language and the cognitive process or the 
domain of language. 3 
Generally, a language disorder from cerebral damage is 
termed 'aphasia' and a speech sound disorder is termed 
'dysarthria' . For several decades, cerebral neurologists, 
psychologists, and linguists have studied mainly aphasia 
lan guage disorder. Recent advances phonology and 
sound analysis equipment have enabled the study of dys-
ar thria, which occurs when aphasia patients speak. In 
the phonological field, 4 phonological codes or damage 
to work memory have been intensively studied, while 
the voice onset time (VOT) of aphasic patients and the 
length of vowels and syllables have been studied and 
compared with a control group in the fi eld of acoustics. 5 
The study of temporal abnormalities, 6 especially those 
related to VOT and the length of syllables of aphasic 
patients, has contributed to the study of damage to lan-
guage or word exercise plans, or the apraxia func tion, 
and the evaluative study of time coordination 7 bet ween 
larynx and oral articulating organs. It also has em-
phasized the importance of articulation places and the 
output of the voiced and voiceless consonants of stop 
con sonants. 8 Such studies make it possible to expand 
the range of interpretation for the speech evaluation of </p>

<p>apha sia patients, and VOT studies can be understood as 
extensive, involving speech exercise plans and apraxia 
function. 
VOT has been used as a phonological clue or index for 
the study of interaction between articulating exercises 
and laryngeal adjustment. Th us, this study aimed to ad-
dress the hypothesis that, in the Korean language, the 
phonological characteristics of consonants rather than 
those of vowels are more focused because the VOT 
shows the degree of aspiration better in the beginning 
of the speech when the stop sounds are articulated, and 
is used as a main measure in light of the fact that it can 
show phonological diff erence according to the places of 
consonants and the types of phonation. Also, to analyze 
whether there is any difference in phonetic processes 
according to articulation places phonologically, the out-
put of voiced and voiceless consonants was analyzed 
according to the articulation sites, and the sound spec-
tral time of the phonetic environment was compared 
and evaluated, to be used as the baseline data for the 
evaluation and diagnosis of aphasic patients. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study subjects 
Subjects were 15 aphasic patients (nine males and six </p>

<p>Table 1. General Characteristics of the Subjects </p>

<p>Number 
Sex 
Age 
Education POT (months) 
Conventional MRI or CT feature 
AQ 
1 
M 
51 
12 
11 
MCA Hemorrhagic 
58.19 
2 
F 
36 
14 
12 
BG ICH 
92.62 
3 
M 
58 
12 
47 
MCA Infarction 
64.75 
4 
M 
53 
16 
20 
MCA Infarction 
40.16 
5 
M 
69 
6 
34 
Cardiomegaly 
58.19 
6 
M 
66 
18 
13 
MCA Infarction 
33.61 
7 
M 
52 
12 
56 
T&amp;L Hematoma 
58.19 
8 
M 
50 
16 
4 
MCA Infarction 
52.46 
9 
F 
27 
16 
6 
MCA Infarction 
96.72 
10 
F 
49 
12 
56 
FT&amp;I Aneurysma 
74.59 
11 
F 
48 
12 
16 
MCA Infarction &amp; Hemorrhage 
77.87 
12 
F 
47 
12 
16 
BG Hematoma 
86.06 
13 
M 
53 
12 
42 
BG encephalomalacia 
84.43 
14 
F 
34 
16 
29 
Frontal Heterogeneous 
94.26 
15 
M 
52 
12 
3 
BG Cystic Encephalomalacia 
75.41 </p>

<p>POT: Post onset time, MRI: Magnetic resonance image, CT: Computed tomography, AQ: Aphasia quotient, MCA: 
Middle cerebral artery, BG: Basal ganglia, T&amp;L: Temporal lentiform, FT&amp;I: Frontal temporal &amp; insular </p>

<p>Seung-Rho Lee, et al. </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>females) who were diagnosed with cerebral infarction, 
cerebral hemorrhage, cerebral hematoma, and/or an-
e u rysm-related diagnosis from the Department of Phy-
sical Medicine and Rehabilitation, Chonbuk National 
University, between August 20, 2008 and February 28, 
2009. Their average age was 49.7±11.02 years (Table 1). 
When evaluated, they had no sensitivity problems and 
were right-handers before they were diagnosed. Subjects 
of the control group were similar to the patients in their 
age (47.4±8.24), sex, dialects, and right-handedness. Th ey 
had no problems with their hearing and language use, 
and did not have any anatomical drug problems either. </p>

<p>Methods 
Evaluation of aphasia: To evaluate their aphasia, the 
Chonbuk National University Aphasia Battery (CNUAB) 
was used. The battery is comprised of three test kits: 
Japanese Standard Language Test of Aphasia, 9 the Min-
nesota Test for Differential Diagnosis of Aphasia, 10 and 
the Boston Diagnostic Aphasia Examination. 11 Table 2 
shows the test scores for the language evaluation of the 
experimental group. 
Acoustic evaluation: Evaluation of the articulation dis-
order of the aphasia patients was done using the words 
of the VPI Articulation Differential Examination kit, 12 
with single-or multi-syllable words made up of CV 
(con sonant vowel) or CVC (C: stop sound) types, which </p>

<p>have meaning (Table 3). As subjects of the experimental 
group could read colloquial language, they were asked 
to read the cards on which pictures and words were 
pro vided together. If they could not respond within 
15 seconds, they were given oral stimulus. The voice 
files of the subjects were stored and analyzed using the 
Computerized Speech Lab Model 4500 KayPentax (Mon-
tvale, NJ, USA). The sampling rate of the voice files was 
11,025 Hz, which operated at 100 points (161.50 Hz) </p>

<p>Table 2. Test Scores for Language Evaluation in Stroke with Aphasia </p>

<p>Number 
Hearing 
Speaking 
Reading 
Writing 
Accounting 
Average scores 
1 
56.12 
47.72 
60 
100 
50 
58.19 
2 
88.33 
100 
84.52 
100 
83.33 
92.62 
3 
68.86 
67.22 
68.22 
67.45 
58.8 
64.75 
4 
40 
47.35 
60 
7.25 
17.47 
40.16 
5 
64.67 
60 
72.56 
67.55 
NA 
58.19 
6 
56.23 
27.33 
36.12 
13.33 
33.67 
33.61 
7 
72.64 
49.86 
72.89 
67.34 
25.78 
58.19 
8 
60 
56.45 
60 
33.45 
33.45 
52.46 
9 
88.67 
98.78 
100 
100 
100 
96.72 
10 
84.67 
69.56 
72.67 
100 
50 
74.59 
11 
92.67 
71.87 
80 
100 
42.35 
77.87 
12 
100 
69.34 
100 
100 
75.89 
86.06 
13 
100 
64.55 
100 
100 
75 
84.43 
14 
96.21 
87.89 
100 
100 
100 
94.26 
15 
80 
58.55 
96.23 
87.98 
75.65 
75.41 </p>

<p>NA: No assessment </p>

<p>Table 3. Target Phonemes for VOT in Aphasic Patients </p>

<p>and Control Groups </p>

<p>Target sound Target phonemes 
Test words 
Stops 
/p/ 
/pεc h u/ 
/p h / 
/ p h oto/ 
/p'/ 
/p'ul/ 
/t/ 
/twεci/ 
/t h / 
/ t h aco/ 
/t'/ 
/t'alki/ 
/k/ 
/kεkuli/ 
/k h / 
/ k h ok'ili/ 
/k'/ 
/k'ac h i/ 
Aff ricatives 
/c/ 
/cepi/ 
/c h / 
/ c h itsol/ 
/c'/ 
/c'akc'aki/ </p>

<p>VOT: Voice onset time </p>

<p>Voice Onset Time Variations of Korean Stop Consonants in Aphasic Speakers </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>above the Nyquest Frequency. Th e VOT was analyzed on 
the broadband spectrum. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses 
For statistical analysis, <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 14.0</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, USA) was used to discriminate the 
signifi cance using one-way ANOVA analysis independent 
samples, t-test mean comparison on the voiced and 
voiceless according to the places of articulation, types 
of phonation, and the places of articulation in the inter-
vocalic VCV combinations. To verify the identity of the 
variance of the two groups, it was statistically analyzed by 
f value. Th e quantitative evaluation of the VOT category 
was done based on the previous research methods which 
used the comparison of mean diff erence. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Comparison of VOT difference ac cording to types of 
aphasic patients 
After testing the aphasic patients, differential and 
variance analyses of the results were done and com-
pared with the results of the control group. In the dif-
ferential analysis of the VOT length according to apha-
sia types, the length of the VOT was the shortest in 
ano mic aphasic patients (49.04 ms) and there was no 
significant difference with the control group, yet all the 
other patients revealed significant differences (p&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>In addition, the length of the VOT and vowels of the 
experimental group were longer compared with the 
results of the control group, which was consistent with 
the results of the previous study. 13 </p>

<p>Comparison of VOT diff erences ac cording to the places 
of articulation and types of phonation 
Based on the study results show that VOT closely related 
with aspiration degree and that this is related to the 
length of the VOT, we compared the VOT diff erence with 
aphasic patients who displayed aspiration according 
to the articulation places and phonation types. While 
the vocal cords remained distant during the lead time, 
aphasic patients revealed diff erences in phonation types 
(Table 4) rather than in articulation sites (Table 5). </p>

<p>Phenomenon of voicing in the VCV (Vowel, Voiceless 
consonant) combination 
To observe voicing phenomenon, the voicing errors and 
voice lead times of aphasic patients with pronounced as-
piration were analyzed. When they were analyzed on the 
spectrogram with four voiced words (/kεkuli/, /p h oto/, 
/t h aco/, /cepi/) according to the articulation places, 
only the bilabial sounds showed significant differences 
(p&lt;0.05) and the lead time was long (Fig. 1-A , 1-B) in 
diff erential analysis with the control group (Table 5). </p>

<p>Table 5. VOT ANOVA of Articulation Positions and the VOT t-test of Aphasic Patients and Control Groups </p>

<p>Bilabial 
Alveolar 
Palatal 
Velar 
f 
p 
Average 
53.85 
55.2 
66.36 
63.49* 
0.99 
0.399 
SD 
45.97 
40.54 
39.07 
39.72 </p>

<p>ANOVA: Analysis of variance, SD: Standard deviation 
*p&lt;0.05, by t-test to control group 
Unit: ms </p>

<p>Table 4. VOT ANOVA of Phonation Type and the VOT t-test of Aphasic Patients and Control Groups </p>

<p>Lax 
Aspirated 
Tense 
f 
p 
Average 
65.49*  § 
98.54  †,∥ 
30.42  ‡ 
11.77 
0.000 
SD 
39.2 
12.36 
30.39 </p>

<p>ANOVA: Analysis of variance, SD: Standard deviation 
*p&lt;0.05, compared to aspirated, p&lt;0.05, compared to tense,  † p&lt;0.05, compared to lax, p&lt;0.01, compared to tense, </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>p&lt;0.01, compared to lax, p&lt;0.01, compared to aspirated,  §,∥ p&lt;0.05, by t-test to control group 
Unit: ms </p>

<p>Seung-Rho Lee, et al. </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>VOT comparison ac cording to the types of phonation 
VOT had a close relationship with the degrees of aspi-
ration or glottal width, and all types of aphasic patients 
revealed significant differences in VOT compared with 
the control group (Table 6). Also, the length of VOT was 
related with the aspiration, as evidenced by significant 
diff erences articulating the aspirated normal sound and 
aspiration (Table 4). In other words, the noise interval 
can be understood as a voice lag until the vowel formant 
is observed after the vertical spike on the spectrogram, 
which is observed due to the opening of the stop sound 
that is located at the word-initial. In addition, the fi nding 
that the length of the VOT of aphasic patients was longer 
than that of the normal control group indicated that 
the sound timing could vary relating to the lead time 
between abnormal or vocal abduction and oral plosive, 
owing to non-coordination between larynx and oral 
articulating organs, due to the turbulence which is 
formed at larynx. 14 Th ese results are likely attributable to 
an inelastic stiff ness of the larynx and the loss of exercise </p>

<p>due to the damage to the central nervous system and 
cranial nerves, 15 so the VOT differences arise according 
to the degree of damage to the interaction between the 
tongue, pharynx, and larynx, which are related with stop 
sounds. 
As word-initial stop sounds come out as either white or 
short noise intervals on the spectrogram, owing to a lack 
of energy because of their articulating characteristics, 
there could not be any information found to notify the 
articulating places. However, according to the VOT 
length, types of phonation can be categorized into nor-
mal, aspirated, or fortis sounds. One thing that could be 
understood is that there was a difference according to 
the degrees of VOT aspiration at word-initial of aphasic 
patients (Table 4, Fig. 2-A), confi rming that the phonation 
type analysis of the VOT of aphasic patients with more 
degrees of aspiration is more signifi cant than that of the 
articulating sites. </p>

<p>Output of voiced · voiceless consonants 
The experimental group was asked to speak normal 
Korean sounds that consisted of phonologically conso-</p>

<p>Fig. 1. Relative comparison of VOT, VD duration and lead time between aphasic patients (A) and normal controls (B). Th ese 
fi gures indicate that VOT, VD duration and lead time of aphasic patient are longer than those of normal control (VD: vowel 
duration, a: initial VOT, b: initial vowel duration, c: hold, d: lead time, e: second vowel duration, f: total duration). </p>

<p>Table 6. VOT ANOVA of Aphasia Types and the VOT t-test of Aphasic Patients and Control Groups </p>

<p>Broca's 
Conduction 
Anomic 
Global 
f 
p 
Average 
52.65* ∥ 
75.74  † ¶ 
49.04  ‡ 
97.14  § ** 
17.95 
0.000 
SD 
28.46 
45.83 
25.99 
58.62 </p>

<p>ANOVA: Analysis of variance, SD: Standard deviation 
*p&lt;0.05, compared to conduction, p&lt;0.01, compared to global,  † p&lt;0.05, compared to Broca's, p&lt;0.01, compared 
to anomic,  ‡ p&lt;0.01, compared to conduction, p&lt;0.01, compared to global,  § p&lt;0.01, compared to Broca's, p&lt;0.01, 
compared to anomic, ∥, ¶ p&lt;0.01, by t-test to control group, **p&lt;0.05, by t-test to control group 
Unit: ms </p>

<p>Voice Onset Time Variations of Korean Stop Consonants in Aphasic Speakers </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>nants. When the 15 patients of the experimental group 
were asked to speak four VCV words, each to find out 
the articulating positions, 58% (35/60) of the words were 
uttered as consonants, and bilabial and velar sounds 
showed differences with the control group in lead time 
(Table 7). 
According to a prior study 16 on the phonological as-
pects, some studies have indicated that words uttered as 
voiced or voiceless depend on the speaker's phonation 
speed or phonological environment, but in the case of 
aphasic patients they showed diff erent results from those 
of the control group in voicing errors and the lead time of 
intervocalic VCV. However, sometimes lead time and the 
vowel length before the consonant stop sound are often 
measured and compared because it is not always true 
that all aphasic patients make voicing errors. As seen in 
Fig. 1-A and 1-B, the c interval was long as the lead time 
in aphasic patients and the vowel length is also shown 
long, consistent with previous studies. 17,18 Some studies </p>

<p>have assumed that the output diff erence of voiced · un-
vo iced consonants of aphasic patients are the interaction 
between the muscles of arytenoids cartilage and posterior 
cricoarytenoid cartilage, which are known to control the 
distinction of the voiced and voiceless consonants. 19 
Although the normal sound of VCV has a small amount 
of aspiration, the vocal cord's vibration interval (d) in 
aphasic patients turns out long, which means that there 
could be a temporal non-coordination between the 
larynx and the oral articulating organs, not only at the 
word-initial, but also at the intervocalic VCV. Th is should 
be examined more widely in more subjects. </p>

<p>Critical points 
The critical points of this paper are as follows: the ex-
pe rimental group was not large enough, subjects were 
locally concentrated, and the evaluation tools for the 
aphasic patients used for this study have not yet been 
recognized offi cially as the standard. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>This study was performed to find out the temporal 
abnor malities of aphasic patients. Their VOT was mea-
sured using word-initial stop consonants to provide 
diff erential analysis according to the places of articulation 
and the types of phonation, as well as measuring the 
differential analysis of voicing errors and lead time in 
intervocalic VCV (C: stop consonant) combination. 
The research results show that since the word-initial </p>

<p>Table 7. The t-test of Voiced Lead Time of Aphasic Pa-</p>

<p>tients and Control Groups </p>

<p>/kεkuli/ 
/p h oto/ 
/t h aco/ 
/cepi/ 
Average 
13.01 
49.33 
14.45 
42.56 
SD 
5.2 
37.13 
5.96 
26.96 
p 
0.053 
0.128 
0.216 
0.0455* </p>

<p>SD: Standard deviation 
*p&lt;0.05 by t-test 
Unit: ms </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Comparison of (A) phonation types and (B) articulation positions. Phonation types were signifi cantly showed 
diff erences than articulation positions compared with normal control group. </p>

<p>Seung-Rho Lee, et al. </p>



<p>www.e-arm.org </p>

<p>VOT of aphasic patients is proportional to the degrees of 
aspiration, VOT could be much better analyzed by the 
types of phonation than at the places of articulation, and 
there is a significant difference from normal people. In 
the analysis of the output of voiced · voiceless consonants 
of aphasic patients, more than half (approximately 58%) 
of the aphasic subjects showed voicing errors. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant of the Korea 
Healthcare technology R&amp;D Project, Ministry for Health, 
Welfare &amp; Family Aff airs, Republic of Korea (A091220). </p>



</text></tei>