<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3913674" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>In human societies, cooperative behaviors such as food sharing </p>

<p>1,2   are often enforced by reciprocity. By making small sacrifices to 
help certain individuals in need, humans consciously or uncon-
sciously make strategic social investments that strengthen social 
relationships in the short term and yield reciprocal benefits in the 
long-term. Such reciprocity requires that cooperative investments 
are contingent on cooperative returns. As a result, cooperative 
behavior leads to higher fitness gains than more selfish behavior. 
Claims of reciprocity in nonhuman animals, however, are 
controversial for several reasons. Authors disagree on what key 
properties define reciprocity. 
3-5 Naturalistic field studies tend to 
demonstrate correlations but not contingency between helping 
acts, and most controlled experiments involve helping acts with 
trivial costs or that require training, making their interpretation 
difficult. </p>

<p>4,5   Perhaps most importantly, reciprocity in social vertebrates may 
be embedded within complex social relationships. Decades of 
studies on primate cooperation suggest that cooperative behaviors </p>

<p>*Correspondence to: Gerald Carter; Email: gcarter@umd.edu 
Submitted: 06/04/13; Revised: 07/16/13; Accepted: 07/16/13 
Citation: Carter G, Wilkinson G. Does food sharing in vampire bats 
demonstrate reciprocity? Commun Integre Biol 2013; 6: e25783; 
http://dx.doi.org/10.4161/cib.25783 </p>

<p>Claims of reciprocity (or reciprocal altruism) in animal societies 
often ignite controversy because authors disagree over 
definitions, naturalistic studies tend to demonstrate correlation 
not causation, and controlled experiments often involve 
artificial conditions. Food sharing among common vampire 
bats has been a classic textbook example of reciprocity, but 
this conclusion has been contested by alternative explanations. 
Here, we review factors that predict food sharing in vampire 
bats based on previously published and unpublished data, 
validate previous published results with more precise 
relatedness estimates, and describe current evidence for and 
against alternative explanations for its evolutionary stability. 
Although correlational evidence indicates a role for both direct 
and indirect fitness benefits, unequivocally demonstrating 
reciprocity in vampire bats still requires testing if and how bats 
respond to non-reciprocation. </p>

<p>Does food sharing in vampire bats demonstrate 
reciprocity? </p>

<p>Gerald Carter* and Gerald wilkinson </p>

<p>University of Maryland; College Park, MD USA </p>

<p>Keywords: cooperation, food sharing, reciprocity, vampire bats </p>

<p>like food sharing and social grooming are based on social bonds 
that are reciprocal over the long-term but do not necessarily 
involve strictly contingent short-term tit-for-tat exchanges. </p>

<p>3,6-8 </p>

<p>Experimental demonstrations of contingent reciprocity are dif-
ficult under these social conditions because the importance of 
single events may be overshadowed by a foundation of past coop-
erative behaviors, which are often difficult to manipulate under 
natural conditions. 
1,3,8 A further complication is that individuals 
may exchange different kinds of services, and exchange rates may 
differ based on social status or access to resources. </p>

<p>9   One of the early classic examples of non-human reciprocity is 
the regurgitation of blood among female common vampire bats 
(Desmodus rotundus). 
10 Food sharing among vampire bats might 
represent a powerful non-primate model for testing mechanisms 
of reciprocity because it is energetically costly to donors yet vol-
untary, and it is natural yet relatively easy to induce and measure. 
Moreover, reciprocal food sharing occurs between both kin and 
non-kin vampire bats, and may provide both direct and indirect 
fitness benefits. 
10,11 The reciprocity hypothesis for vampire bat 
food sharing has, however, become increasingly contested. </p>

<p>4,12-17   In a recent study, 
11 we addressed some, but not all, of the alterna-
tive explanations for food sharing. Here, we review the known 
correlates of food sharing in vampire bats using both previously 
published and unpublished data, briefly discuss various defini-
tions of the term reciprocity, and then describe evidence for and 
against various explanations for why vampire bats share food. </p>

<p>Correlates of Food Sharing in Vampire Bats </p>

<p>Kinship. Regurgitated food sharing in common vampire bats 
(Desmodus rotundus) was first noticed between mothers and pups 
in captivity, 
18 but was later recognized as an important social 
behavior among adults in a field study conducted in Costa Rica 
from 1978 to 1983. 
10 Here, vampire bats frequently switched 
between several roost trees and co-roosted with kin and non-kin. 
Mean kinship (relatedness) estimates within roosting groups were 
estimated at r = 0.03-0.11, 
19 yet 95% of food sharing observed 
in the wild occurred between close kin (r &gt; 0.2). Out of 110 
food-sharing observations, 70% were mothers feeding their pups 
(r = 0.5). Of the 21 remaining non-maternal sharing events where 
kinship and co-roosting associations were known, 16 involved 
close kin (r = 0.25 or greater) and only one involved non-kin. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>e25783-2 </p>

<p>Communicative &amp; Integrative Biology 
volume 6 Issue 6 </p>

<p>In particular, previously unpublished data from 2010 suggests 
that food sharing may require social bonds that require devel-
opment over long periods of time. In Trinidad, we captured 5 
females at 5 sites that were 20-90 km apart. We conducted 3 
separate food-sharing experiments to see if these previously unfa-
miliar individuals would begin sharing food after being kept in 
captivity together for several weeks. To assess changes in allog-
rooming over time, we also conducted random focal sampling 
of allogrooming. We ranked the amount of time each bat spent 
grooming others, then tested whether the mean ranks across bats 
increased over time using a permutation test (<rs type="software">lmPerm package</rs> 
in R). We never observed food sharing, but we found that bats 
began begging others on the second and third sets of fasting tri-
als on days 21 and 36 (Table 1). We also found that allogroom-
ing increased over time among the previously unfamiliar bats 
[R 
2 = 0.45, F(1,10) = 8.3, p = 0.018]. 
We conducted other trials with groups of female common 
vampire bats that may have been previously familiar. Two groups 
in Trinidad and Belize were captured flying in close proximity 
(in the same mist net within a roughly 5 min period). We tested 
another group of vampire bats captured from the same tree hol-
low in Trinidad, but again with unknown levels of association. 
In all 4 groups (n = 48 fasting trials), we observed some begging 
but no food sharing. </p>

<p>These observations suggest that vampire bats are capable of kin 
discrimination and that food sharing elevates indirect fitness. 
Association. Even after controlling for kinship, non-maternal 
food sharing was also explained by frequency of interaction; in all 
21 non-maternal cases, co-roosting association was greater than 
60%. 
10 Association also predicted non-kin regurgitations in a 
captive fasting experiment where 9 bats from two different popu-
lations were housed together. 
10 In these experiments, bats selected 
from the same population were frequent roost-mates, and only 
one pair was related. A random bat was deprived of food each 
night, then placed with others that had been fed and observed for 
2 h, and this was repeated until all bats had been fasted at least 
twice. Fasted bats were weighed before and after the 2 h period to 
determine mass gain. Fasted bats were fed by bats from the same 
population in 12 of the 13 observed cases of food sharing, while 
sharing across populations occurred once. 
From 2010 to 2013, we have repeated this fasting experiment 
with several groups of common vampire bats that were either cap-
tive-born or captured from the wild at the same or different loca-
tions (Table 1). Overall, fasting trials induced food sharing more 
often among frequent roostmates and long-term captive bats than 
those caught from the same roost or area with unknown associa-
tions (Table 1), which is consistent with the hypothesis that food 
sharing requires long-term associations. </p>

<p>Table 1. Captive fasting trials with 8 groups of common vampire bats </p>

<p>Bats 
Previous association 
Kinship estimate </p>

<p>(mean+/−SD, range) </p>

<p>Begging or sharing?* 
Source </p>

<p>5 females 
Unfamiliar bats caught at different locations in 
Trinidad then placed together for 6 d </p>

<p>0.05 +/− 0.08**, </p>

<p>0-0.19 </p>

<p>(25 loci) </p>

<p>No begging after 6 
d, begging only at 21 
and 36 d </p>

<p>Unpublished </p>

<p>6 females 
Captured together in mist nets from one location in 
Trinidad </p>

<p>0.02 +/− 0.04, </p>

<p>0-0.14 </p>

<p>(25 loci) </p>

<p>Begging only 
Unpublished </p>

<p>5 females 
Captured together in a mist net from one site in Belize 
0.03 +/− 0.07, </p>

<p>0-0.23 </p>

<p>(22 loci) </p>

<p>Begging only 
Unpublished </p>

<p>6 females, 1 male 
Captured together from same roost tree in Trinidad 
0.04 +/− 0.06, </p>

<p>0-0.26 </p>

<p>(25 loci) </p>

<p>Begging only 
Unpublished </p>

<p>8 females, 1 male 
Known frequent roostmates from a site in Costa Rica 
0.01 +/− 0.06, </p>

<p>0-0.25 </p>

<p>(maternal pedigree) </p>

<p>Yes 
wilkinson, 1984 </p>

<p>4 females, 2 males 
Long-term captivity 
0.15 +/− 0.06, </p>

<p>(maternal pedigree) </p>

<p>Yes 
DeNault and 
McFarlane, 1995 </p>

<p>9 females, 16 
males </p>

<p>Long-term captivity 
0.06 +/− 0.10, </p>

<p>0-0.58 </p>

<p>(25 loci) </p>

<p>Yes 
Carter and 
wilkinson, 2013 </p>

<p>6 females, 1 male 
Long-term captivity 
0.14 +/− 0.14, </p>

<p>0-0.46 </p>

<p>(25 loci) </p>

<p>Yes 
Unpublished </p>

<p>*Begging is defined as the fasted subject licking the mouth of a conspecific; sharing involves the same plus subsequent weight gain in the fasted 
subject. **Note that bats sampled randomly from a wild population should have zero relatedness. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>Communicative &amp; Integrative Biology 
e25783-3 </p>

<p>trial, r = 0.9), and defined food sharing as the log-transformed 
donation rate from A to B, reciprocal help as the log-transformed 
donation rate from B to A, and kinship as the genetic related-
ness estimate between A and B. 
11 Some individuals originated 
from different captive populations, but all bats were housed in 
the same flight cage for several years. Under these conditions, 
we found that reciprocal help, but not kinship, predicted food 
sharing. Other predictors of food sharing included social groom-
ing, donor sex, and a positive interaction between reciprocal help 
and kinship, which revealed that related pairs shared with even 
greater symmetry compared with less-related pairs. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>In the original paper, we used 13 microsatellite loci to esti-
mate kinship, 
11 but we have since reanalyzed the data using more 
precise kinship estimates based on information from 25 variable 
microsatellite loci, and our conclusions have remained the same. 
Our new updated model (adjusted R 
2 = 0.38, F(5,306) = 37.0) 
still includes reciprocal help (β = 0.32, p &lt; 0.0002), donor sex 
(β = 0.26, p &lt; 0.0002), allogrooming received (β = 0.20, p &lt; 
0.0002), and the interaction between kinship and reciprocal help 
(β = 0.06, p = 0.04) in the same order of relative importance. The 
model still does not include kinship (β = 0.07, p = 0.6). 
Reciprocal help (averaged over all trials) predicted food shar-
ing better than past help (in recent previous trials). In other 
words, reciprocity was most evident in the form of symmetrical 
helping across pairs rather than within pairs. We conducted a 
test of temporal contingency and found that the amount given 
from A to B in each trial correlated with the total amount previ-
ously given from B to A during the most recent donation. Yet, 
the correlation was weak (r = 0.28) and apparent only after 
controlling for the total amount received by the recipient in the 
trial. 
11 Hungry bats were fed by an average of 4 partners per trial, 
and these were typically the same partners across repeated trials 
but not always. In summary, the bats did not perform strictly 
balanced exchanges in isolated pairs, and symmetry in sharing 
was most obvious over longer time spans as found in primate 
cooperation. </p>

<p>3,8 </p>

<p>Do Vampire Bats Exhibit Reciprocity? </p>

<p>Definitions. Answering this question requires crossing an unfor-
tunate semantic quagmire. Definitions of reciprocity have varied 
greatly over time and between authors 
3-6,21-24 ever since Trivers </p>

<p>21   first described "reciprocal altruism" (now widely recognized as 
a misnomer since reciprocal altruism enforces mutual benefit). 
In this paper, Trivers 
21 implicitly lumped all helping behaviors 
yielding future direct fitness benefits into his definition, but he 
later clarified reciprocal altruism as a special case of this broader 
category. </p>

<p>25   In sharp contrast, we observed food sharing consistently 
among kin and non-kin that have been housed together in long-
term captivity (Table 1). Under these conditions, all females are 
generally fed when fasted, including females born in different 
populations but housed with others for multiple years (discussed 
below). Although observations of food sharing have been mostly 
restricted to groups with known levels of high association, sharing 
between bats from different populations has also been observed 
once in Costa Rica. 
10 Therefore, factors other than previous asso-
ciation, such as variations in behavior due to geographic origin or 
stress, might also explain the presence or absence of food sharing 
across these groups (Table 1). 
A final line of evidence that association influences food shar-
ing is that male vampire bats do not form stable associations nor 
share food in the wild, but they do share food in captivity where 
associations are stable. 
20 In a 1995 study with 10 captive vam-
pire bats, DeNault and McFarlane 
20 found that 2 adult males 
that were related (r = 0.26) roosted in close proximity, performed 
mutual allogrooming, and both donated and reciprocated food. 
The authors failed however to find a correlation between kinship 
and presence of food sharing across all bats. 
Reciprocal help. The amount of food given from bat A to bat 
B is predicted by the amount of food given from bat B to A. This 
latter value can be measured in at least 2 ways. For predicting the 
food sharing rate from bat A to B, a predictor we call "reciprocal 
help" is the average sharing rate from B to A over the longest pos-
sible time span. In contrast, for predicting food given from A to 
B at a given trial, a predictor we call "past help" is the presence 
or amount of food given from B to A in one or more previous tri-
als. Past help should predict food sharing if the helping decisions 
of bats are determined by recent past social experience, whereas 
reciprocal help should predict food sharing even better if bats 
accrue social information over longer time periods. 
In the 1984 study, 
10 6 opportunities were created where a cap-
tive fasted bat could have been fed by unrelated bats that it fed 
previously, and this occurred 4 times, more than expected by 
chance. In this captive experiment, past help predicted donations 
but only when kin were absent, while in previous field observa-
tions, kinship predicted donations but all cases of reciprocal help 
were not known (Table 2). Therefore, the roles of reciprocal help 
and kinship could not be tested simultaneously in the original 
study. </p>

<p>10   In a more recent 2013 study, 
11 we tested the relative roles of 
reciprocal help and kinship, by inducing 204 cases of food-shar-
ing in 20 common vampire bats of mixed sex (9 females) and 
kinship over a 2-y period. For all potential pairs that could share 
food, we estimated donation amounts by time spent mouth-lick-
ing (which strongly correlated with mass gained during the 2 h </p>

<p>Table 2. Factors predicting food sharing in vampire bats </p>

<p>Study 
No. donations No. bats 
Co-roosting association 
Kinship 
Reciprocal help </p>

<p>wilkinson (1984) field data 
110 
184 
Yes 
Yes 
? </p>

<p>wilkinson (1984) captive data 
13 
9 
Yes 
Controlled at 0 
Yes </p>

<p>DeNault and McFarlane (1995) 
10 
6 
Controlled at 100% 
No 
? </p>

<p>Carter and wilkinson (2013) 
204 
25 
Controlled at 100% 
Not after controlling other factors 
Yes </p>



<p>Communicative &amp; Integrative Biology 
volume 6 Issue 6 </p>

<p>the relative importance of partner control and partner choice in 
vampire bats would be difficult, and would involve comparing 
how bats respond to non-reciprocation in both the presence and 
absence of alternative partners. 
Resource exchange markets should be less common between 
conspecifics, which have access to the same pool of resources, but 
such models can still apply to vampire bats for two reasons. First, 
one cooperative service, such as grooming, can be traded for oth-
ers, as found in primates. 
7-9,36 This possibility could be verified by 
testing if a partner that is unable to reciprocate food donations 
compensates by increasing time spent grooming. Second, even 
if blood is only exchanged for blood, its value for each vampire 
bat fluctuates largely over a 24 h period and differs drastically 
depending on whether that individual has fed successfully. 
10 This 
is because, like social carnivores that hunt cooperatively, vampire 
bats typically acquire either a large meal or none at all. Unlike 
social hunters however, vampire bats usually feed individually 
rather than as a group, and blood may be easier to share at the 
roost than at the wound site. It is worth noting however that 
vampire bats have also been observed both fighting and feeding 
at the same wound. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>The Social Bond Hypothesis </p>

<p>If we assume that non-kin food sharing is adaptive, then its evolu-
tionary stability requires that bats cannot exploit food sharing by 
receiving donations while donating less than average amounts to 
others in need (i.e., cheating). One hypothesis is that cheating is 
prevented by both kin discrimination and enforcement through 
reciprocity. 
10,23 This hypothesis predicts that bats should dis-
criminate between kin and non-kin, but also between 2 equally 
related partners that yield different cooperative returns. 
Such dual enforcement could occur through long-term, kin-
biased social bonds. If bats form social bonds that provide mostly 
direct, but also indirect fitness benefits, and if the adaptive value 
of social bonds is actively enforced by reciprocity, then several 
observations can be explained. 
23 First, this would explain why 
kinship predicts sharing in wild bats (where such bonds may typ-
ically form among kin), but not in captive bats when controlling 
for association, social grooming, and reciprocal help. 
11 Second, it 
would explain why the food-sharing network in both captive and 
wild vampire bats is female-biased, symmetrical, consistent, and 
correlated with mutual social grooming. Finally, complex social 
bonds as found in some primates, 
7 could also help explain why 
vampire bats are outliers for residual brain and neocortex size 
among bats. </p>

<p>37,38   The social bond hypothesis for food sharing predicts that 
vampire bats will make cooperative investments of different types 
(e.g., social grooming, tolerance for feeding at the same source) 
within the same food-sharing partners over time, alter these 
cooperative investments slowly depending on how the coopera-
tive returns compare with other individuals (partner choice) and 
past returns (partner control), and compensate for inabilities 
to reciprocate food sharing by increasing other services, such 
as social grooming. Finally, food sharing manipulation should 
be possible not only by controlling social experiences, but also </p>

<p>The broadest definitions of reciprocity are based on observed 
outcomes. For example, some authors use reciprocity to refer 
merely to correlations between help given and received when 
controlling for kinship, 
26 or in other cases even when such help-
ing is based on kinship (e.g., "symmetry-based reciprocity"). </p>

<p>27,28   Food sharing in vampire bats clearly fits these very broad defini-
tions. On the other end of the spectrum are very narrow defi-
nitions. For instance, some authors suggest reciprocity requires 
planned investments and expected returns where "individuals 
must choose between the immediate reward of defecting and the 
long-term reward of cooperating." </p>

<p>12   Some authors distinguish between positive reciprocity 
(rewarding cooperators) and negative reciprocity (punishing 
cheats), or between reciprocity (where costly cooperative invest-
ments are made by both partners) and pseudoreciprocity (where 
costly investment by one partner leads to a non-costly byprod-
uct benefit from the other). 
4,29 Such distinctions can be useful 
in some contexts, but can also create confusion. For example, 
many reciprocity definitions require showing that a helping act 
poses not only energetic costs but also "net fitness costs at the 
time it is provided in natural populations." 
4 Helping behaviors 
typically pose some energetic cost, but there is no putative case of 
cooperation where this "temporary fitness cost" has been demon-
strated. 
4 Indeed, it is unclear how an experimenter could clearly 
demonstrate that an adaptive helping behavior (which increases 
expected lifetime fitness by definition) somehow simultaneously 
decreases expected lifetime fitness temporarily during the social 
interaction. 
For our purposes, we define reciprocity broadly as "a condi-
tional enforcement strategy where individuals preferentially help 
partners that reciprocate and withhold help to partners that do 
not." Importantly, such enforcement could occur through part-
ner choice, partner control strategies or both, since either mecha-
nism leads to an outcome that rewards cooperation and punishes 
cheating. 
5,6,9,30-34 This operational definition implies an ultimate-
level function because the necessity to contingently adjust coop-
erative investments is an expected design feature if investments 
pose fitness costs and cheating has created selective pressure to 
enforce cooperation. Finally, this definition clarifies exactly what 
is still needed to demonstrate reciprocity: an experimental test 
of whether bats will decrease aid to partners that are rendered 
unable to reciprocate. 
Partner choice or partner control. Reciprocity defined in this 
broad way is synonymous with the enforcement of mutual bene-
fits, 
24 a phenomenon that has been well-demonstrated in interspe-
cific mutualisms. For example, both plants and their mycorrhizal 
fungal symbionts prefer to exchange nutrients with partners that 
offer the best returns on investment. 
35 In some cases, reciprocity 
might occur primarily through partner choice. Biological mar-
kets 
30,31 often result when different types of organisms have access 
to different resources, and at least one type can choose among 
several exchange partners. In this case, reciprocity may occur pri-
marily through partner choice and partner switching. The more 
partners are locked into a repeated dyadic interaction, the more 
likely that enforcement will take the form of partner control 
(reward and punishment of the same partner over time). Testing </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>Communicative &amp; Integrative Biology 
e25783-5 </p>

<p>food sharing poses a large benefit to recipients, and kinship 
between donors and possible recipients has a low mean and 
high variance. 
10,19 Hence, indiscriminate sharing within roosts 
is unlikely to be evolutionarily stable when individuals vary in 
cooperativeness or against enforcement strategies such as kin dis-
crimination or reciprocity. 
If we instead assume vampire bats can discriminate among 
kin, but do not exhibit reciprocity, then it is difficult to explain 
why reciprocal help, but not kinship, predicts food sharing under 
captive conditions unless long-term captivity somehow disrupts 
natural kin discrimination behavior. In summary, alternative 
explanations can make fewer assumptions, but not without 
explaining less of what we know about vampire bat food sharing. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Evidence for kin discrimination often relies on correlational evi-
dence without demonstration of exact mechanisms, yet skeptics 
of reciprocity increasingly require far more stringent evidence 
than mere correlation or even contingency. 
3,4,6,12 Vampire bats 
demonstrate symmetrical exchanges of help, but it has yet to be 
demonstrated that vampire bats use conditional enforcement 
to prevent cheating. There are two obvious gaps in knowledge. 
First, can vampire bats discriminate kin when past association is 
controlled? Second, do bats change investments based on coop-
erative returns? Additional experiments answering these ques-
tions should provide valuable insight into the mechanisms that 
maintain food sharing in these intriguing animals. </p>

<p>Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest were disclosed. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Frantisek Baluska for inviting us to write this paper. 
Ronald Noe and an anonymous reviewer provided helpful com-
ments. Lauren Leffer, Micah Miles, and Adi Shaked helped 
with data collection. New work described here was supported 
by grants from the Cosmos Club Foundation, Sigma Xi, the 
American Society of Mammalogy, and with permission of the 
Trinidad Forestry Division, Wildlife Section. </p>

<p>by direct manipulation of hormonal and neural mechanisms of 
social bonding. </p>

<p>Alternative Explanations </p>

<p>Several alternative models of vampire bat food sharing assume 
that enforcement of cooperation is not necessary. One example is 
pseudoreciprocity, 
13,39 which assumes that food sharing is stable 
because it ensures the survival of roost-mates that are valuable 
for providing some byproduct service such as broadcasting social 
information about prey locations 
40,41 or for keeping offspring 
warm. 
42 But even in these scenarios subtle cheating may be 
possible. </p>

<p>43   Another suggestion is that non-kin food sharing is manipu-
lation not cooperation. 
4 Harassment often plays an important 
role in primate sharing, 
7,44,45 but is unlikely to strongly influ-
ence food sharing in vampire bats because begging bats are easily 
rejected and donors initiate the majority of food-sharing bouts 
by approaching, grooming, and licking the mouth of hungry 
subjects. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Multilevel selection models of vampire bat food sharing argue 
that neither kin discrimination nor reciprocity is needed to sta-
bilize food sharing, because cooperative genotypes can assort 
themselves passively without enforcement behaviors. 
14,16,17 To 
explain these scenarios from an inclusive fitness perspective, 
indiscriminate sharing within roosts is expected to provide indi-
rect fitness benefits as long as the average within-roost kinship 
exceeds 0.05. 
14 If helping nearby non-kin is simply less costly to 
inclusive fitness than allowing kin to starve, then selection can 
favor indiscriminate or imprecise kin altruism based on prox-
imity, association, or familiarity. This is especially likely when 
limited dispersal is typical under natural conditions. 
46 It is then 
possible that these symmetrical, but imprecise, cues also lead to 
symmetrical helping in captivity. 
These models face several problems. Kin-biased sharing in 
adult wild bats is still evident after controlling for association. </p>

<p>10   Food sharing relationships are consistent and non-random within 
groups. 
11 Furthermore, both theory and comparative evidence </p>

<p>46   predict the evolution of strong kin discrimination under the 
socioecological conditions faced by vampire bats. Specifically, </p>





<p>Communicative &amp; Integrative Biology 
volume 6 Issue 6 </p>



</text></tei>