<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3158666" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives T o derive and validate a clinical score to risk 
stratify children presenting with acute infection. 
Study design and participants Observational cohort 
study of children presenting with suspected infection 
to an emergency department in England. Detailed data 
were collected prospectively on presenting clinical 
features, laboratory investigations and outcome. Clinical 
predictors of serious bacterial infection (SBI) were 
explored in multivariate logistic regression models using 
part of the dataset, each model was then validated in 
an independent part of the dataset, and the best model 
was chosen for derivation of a clinical risk score for SBI. 
The ability of this score to risk stratify children with SBI 
was then assessed in the entire dataset. 
Main outcome measure Final diagnosis of SBI 
according to criteria defi ned by the Royal College 
of Paediatrics and Child Health working group on 
Recognising Acute Illness in Children. 
Results Data from 1951 children were analysed. 74 
(3.8%) had SBI. The sensitivity of individual clinical signs 
was poor, although some were highly specifi c for SBI. A 
score was derived with reasonable ability to discriminate 
SBI (area under the receiver operator characteristics 
curve 0.77, 95% CI 0.71 to 0.83) and risk stratify children 
with suspected SBI. 
Conclusions This study demonstrates the potential 
utility of a clinical score in risk stratifying children with 
suspected SBI. Further work should aim to validate 
the score and its impact on clinical decision making 
in different settings, and ideally incorporate it into a 
broader management algorithm including additional 
investigations to further stratify a child's risk. </p>

<p>Serious bacterial infections (SBIs) are a leading 
cause of morbidity and mortality among children 
worldwide. A recent review of child deaths in 
England, Wales and Northern Ireland confi rmed 
that the largest single cause of death in children 
dying of an acute physical illness was infection, 
and found evidence that healthcare professionals 
in both hospital and primary care had diffi culty 
identifying serious illness in children. 1 In another 
study of over 400 children with meningococcal 
sepsis in the UK, only half were referred to hospi-
tal at their fi rst primary care consultation, usually 
after a delay of several hours following the fi rst 
symptoms and/or signs of sepsis. 2 Early recogni-
tion of SBIs is associated with better treatment 
outcomes 3 4 but is challenging as many of the 
early clinical features also occur in self-limiting 
illnesses. In developed countries, discriminat-
ing serious infection from self-limiting illness </p>

<p>1 Royal College of Paediatrics 
and Child Health (RCPCH) 
Working Group on Recognising 
Acute Illness in Children, 
London, UK 
2 Department of Paediatrics, 
Imperial College London, 
London, UK 
3 Department of Medical 
Education and Social Care, 
University of Leicester, 
Leicester, UK 
4 Oxford University Department 
of Primary Health Care, 
Institute of Health Sciences, 
Oxford, UK 
5 Department of Family 
Medicine, Oregon Health &amp; 
Science University, Portl and, 
Oregon, USA 
6 Centre for Population 
Sciences, University of 
Nottingham, Nottingham, UK 
7 Paediatric Intensive Care Unit, 
Great Ormond Street Hospital, 
London, UK 
8 Paediatric Department, 
Pinderfi elds Hospital, 
Wakefi eld, UK </p>

<p>Correspondence to 
Dr Andrew J Brent, KEMRI-
Wellcome Trust Research 
Programme, PO Box 230, 
80108 Kilifi , Kenya; 
dr.a.brent@gmail.com </p>

<p>Risk score to stratify children with suspected serious 
bacterial infection: observational cohort study </p>

<p>Andrew J Brent, 1,2 Monica Lakhanpaul, 1,3 Matthew Thompson, 1,4,5 Jacqueline Collier, 1,6 
Samiran Ray, 7 Nelly Ninis, 1,2 Michael Levin, 1,2 Roddy MacFaul 1,8 </p>

<p>i s further complicated by the low prevalence of 
serious infection in children presenting to hos-
pital emergency departments as well as primary 
care settings. 5 Better clinical tools are therefore 
required to improve the recognition of children 
with serious acute illness, particularly SBIs. 1 6 7  Clinical prediction rules utilising key clini-
cal features to generate a diagnostic or prognos-
tic score are increasingly used to risk stratify 
patients in a wide variety of clinical situations, 
particularly those in which diagnostic decisions 
are complicated, and in some areas have had a 
major impact on clinical service delivery. 8 -15 We 
aimed to develop a simple clinical score with the 
ability to risk stratify children with possible SBIs 
presenting to a paediatric emergency department. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Patients and setting </p>

<p>As part of a large prospective study of patient care 
pathways, detailed clinical data were collected 
prospectively on all children presenting to the 
Queen's Medical Centre Emergency Department 
in Nottingham between September 2000 and 
March 2001, and September 2001 and March 2002, </p>

<p>What i s already known on this topic </p>

<p>Serious bacterial infections (SBI) are a leading </p>

<p>▶ </p>

<p>cause of childhood illness and death in the UK 
and worldwide. 
In clinical practice, discriminating children </p>

<p>▶ </p>

<p>with SBI from those with other self-limiting 
infections is challenging. 
A simple, validated clinical tool to risk stratify </p>

<p>▶ </p>

<p>and guide further management of children with 
suspected SBI would greatly improve their 
care. </p>

<p>What t his study adds </p>

<p>The high specifi city for SBI of some clinical </p>

<p>▶ </p>

<p>signs supports their use in clinical guidelines to 
identify seriously ill children. 
The utility of a simple clinical score to stratify </p>

<p>▶ </p>

<p>children according to SBI risk is clearly 
demonstrated. 
Combining this clinical tool with laboratory </p>

<p>▶ </p>

<p>tests in a broader management algorithm may 
further improve SBI diagnosis pathways. </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>Arch Dis Child 2011;96:361-367. doi:10.1136/adc.2010.183111 </p>

<p>
with the exception of neonates and children requiring imme-
diate emergency resuscitation at presentation. A triage nurse 
recorded vital signs prior to assessment by emergency depart-
ment clinical staff. All clinical data including investigations, 
management and fi nal diagnoses were directly entered onto a 
standard proforma. Completed proformas were then scanned 
using <rs type="software">Formic</rs> electronic data capture software to minimise 
data entry errors. Study clinicians checked the data for com-
pleteness, resolved data gaps and inconsistencies by re-review 
of the clinical notes, and recorded additional clinical data on 
children who were admitted. Children who re-attended hos-
pital within 1 week of discharge from either the emergency 
department or the ward were identifi ed from the electronic 
patient register, their notes reviewed, and fi nal diagnoses and 
SBI classifi cation amended in the light of their second pre-
sentation. A consultant paediatrician re-reviewed the patient 
records of all those admitted to check the accuracy of the data, 
particularly in relation to the fi nal diagnosis recorded. 
Children were eligible for inclusion in this analysis if their 
differential diagnosis at presentation included acute infection. 
We excluded from the analysis children for whom data were 
insuffi cient to confi dently assign outcome, or who had missing 
dates of birth. </p>

<p>Clinical defi nitions </p>

<p>Automated measurements were used for temperature (tym-
panic thermometer), pulse rate, blood pressure and pulse oxim-
etry. Tachypnoea, tachycardia and hypotension were defi ned 
according to UK Advanced Paediatric Life Support guidelines 16 ; 
children for whom no blood pressure recordings were available 
were assumed not to be hypotensive for the purpose of the 
analysis. We adopted pragmatic defi nitions of mild hypoxia 
(SaO 2 &lt;95% and/or documented oxygen therapy) and severe 
hypoxia (SaO 2 &lt;90% and/or SaO 2 &lt;92% despite documented 
oxygen therapy), and defi ned a 'risk factor for infection' as 
a documented history of any condition known to increase a 
child's risk of invasive bacterial infection. Developmental 
delay was included separately as a potential risk factor, since 
several studies have documented an increased rate and sever-
ity of acute illness including infection among this group. 17 18  Other defi nitions refl ected those commonly used in clini-
cal practice ( table 1 ); data collected routinely on all children 
included level of consciousness, capillary refi ll time, hydration 
status, and presence and type of rash. 
SBI was defi ned a priori as admission to hospital plus any of 
the following (in the absence of an alternative non-infective or 
non-bacterial diagnosis to explain the clinical and laboratory 
fi ndings): positive bacterial cultures from blood or another nor-
mally sterile site in the appropriate clinical context, radiologi-
cal signs of pneumonia, clinical meningitis plus a cerebrospinal 
fl uid polymorphonuclear leukocytosis, acute febrile purpura, 
deep collection(s) requiring intravenous antibiotics±surgical 
drainage, a white blood cell count ≥20×10 9 /l, a C reactive pro-
tein ≥120 mg/l, or a fi nal diagnosis of septic arthritis, osteomy-
elitis, empyema or mastoiditis. </p>

<p>Statistical methods </p>

<p>Analyses were performed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Stata</rs> v <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">10</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">StataCorp</rs> LP). The 
distribution of each variable was summarised with respect to 
SBI, and crude OR derived. The sensitivity, specifi city, positive 
and negative predictive values (PPV, NPV) and positive and 
negative likelihood ratios (LR+, LR−) were reported for each 
variable. </p>

<p>We randomly assigned each child to either a 'derivation' 
or a 'validation' dataset, such that ~85% of children were 
in the derivation set. Multivariate logistic regression models 
were then derived using the derivation set to develop a clini-
cal prediction score for SBI. We included in the model only 
variables with at least a weak association with SBI in the uni-
variate analysis (likelihood ratio test (LRT) p value ≤0.1), fi rst 
confi ning this to categorical variables (which are more easily 
applied in clinical practice), and then repeating the analysis 
using the available continuous data to explore to what extent 
this improved the model. 
Backwards stepwise logistic regression was performed fi rst 
using 'standard' selection criteria, such that variables not sig-
nifi cantly associated with SBI (Wald p value &lt;0.5; t test p value 
≤0.1 for continuous variables) are sequentially dropped from 
the model, and then using 'sign OK' selection, 19 whereby vari-
ables are eliminated from the model only if the sign (+ or −) 
of the regression coeffi cient (β) is discordant with known or 
expected clinical associations (since standard selection criteria 
may not be optimal in the analysis of smaller datasets 15 19 -21 ). 
Each model took the form: SBI=α+β 1 X 1 +β 2 X 2 +β 3 X 3 +... 
+β i X i , where α is a constant, β i are the regression coeffi cients 
for each variable (X i ) in the model, and X i are coded as 0 or 
1 (for binary variables), integers (for ordered categorical vari-
ables) or continuous numbers (for continuous variables). For 
each model we generated a score for each child, such that the 
score=β 1 X 1 +β 2 X 2 +β 3 X 3 +... +β i X i . The ability of each score to 
discriminate children with SBI was quantifi ed in the deriva-
tion dataset, and validated in the validation dataset, by cal-
culating the area under the receiver operator characteristics 
(ROC) curve (AUC) of score as a predictor of SBI. 
Finally, the best model was selected to derive a simpler score 
for clinical use. Criteria for model selection included both 
discriminant ability (defi ned by the AUC) and model simplic-
ity. We generated a simplifi ed clinical prediction score using 
weightings defi ned by the β coeffi cients of the chosen model, 
multiplied if necessary by a constant, and rounded as far as 
possible to the nearest integer. The discriminant ability of this 
fi nal 'SBI score' was tested by plotting an ROC curve of the 
score as a predictor of SBI in the entire dataset (derivation and 
validation sets combined). Risks of SBI were presented strati-
fi ed by score. </p>

<p>Ethics approval </p>

<p>Ethics approval was granted by the Nottingham Research 
Ethics Committee and the ethics committee of the London 
School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>There were 2341 eligible children, of whom 17 were excluded 
because insuffi cient data were available to confi dently deter-
mine outcome. A further 373 children were excluded because 
their date of birth and therefore their age could not be posi-
tively determined from the hospital records due to uncertainty 
in interpreting their handwritten unique patient identifi er 
number on the proforma; the proportion of children with SBI 
did not differ signifi cantly between those for whom age data 
were and were not available (p=0.47). 
The fi nal analysis therefore included 1951 children. Their 
median age was 19 months (range 1 month to 15 years) and 
55.4% were boys. Five hundred and forty-six (28.0%) chil-
dren were admitted at fi rst presentation, of whom 72 had 
SBI. Thirty-six children re-attended hospital within a week </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>Arch Dis Child 2011;96:361-367. doi:10.1136/adc.2010.183111 </p>

<p>
of their initial presentation and within the same illness epi-
sode, 18 of whom were admitted and 2 of whom had SBI. The 
principal fi nal diagnoses of the 74 (3.8%) children with SBI 
included pneumonia (52), sepsis without a clear focus (14), 
soft tissue infections (5), urinary sepsis (2) and tonsillitis plus 
sepsis (1). 
Several clinical variables were strongly associated with SBI 
in the univariate analysis ( table 1 ), including signs of a child's 
a neurologic, haemodynamic and respiratory state, and a 
known risk factor for infection. Although hypotension was </p>

<p>Table 1 Univariable associations between clinical variables a nd risk of serious bacterial infection (SBI) in children presenting to the emergency 
department </p>

<p>Clinical variable 
N* 
SBI, n (%) 
OR 
95% CI 
p Value </p>

<p>Age group 
Infants (1-11 months) 
701 
26 (3.7) 
1.35 
0.31 to 5.81 
0.784 
Preschool (12-59 months) 
855 
31 (3.6) 
1.32 
0.31 to 5.62 
School age (5-11 years) 
323 
15 (4.6) 
1.70 
0.38 to 7.65 
Adolescents (12-15 years) 
72 
2 (2.8) 
1.00 
-
Sex 
Male 
1081 
39 (3.6) 
1.00 
-
0.562 
Female 
850 
35 (4.1) 
1.15 
0.72 to 1.83 
Risk factor for infection  † 
No 
1898 
66 (3.5) 
1.00 
-
&lt;0.0001 
Yes 
53 
8 (15.1) 
4.93 
2.23 to 10.9 
Developmental delay 
No 
1923 
70 (3.6) 
1.00 
-
0.003 
Yes 
28 
4 (14.3) 
4.41 
1.49 to 13.1 
Consciousness level (AVPU score) 
Alert 
1913 
70 (3.7) 
1.00 
-
0.027 
Responds to voice 
18 
0 (0.0) 
0.00 
-
Responds to pain 
5 
2 (40.0) 
17.6 
2.86 to 107.7 
Unresponsive 
1 
0 (0.0) 
0.00 
-
State variation 
Awake 
1909 
68 (3.6) 
1.00 
-
&lt;0.0001 
Eyes close briefl y 
31 
6 (19.4) 
6.50 
2.57 to 16.4 
Falls asleep 
1 
0 (0.0) 
0.00 
-
Temperature  ‡ 
35.0-36.4°C 
426 
9 (2.1) 
0.82 
0.37 to 1.82 
&lt;0.0001 
36.5-37.5°C 
780 
20 (2.6) 
1.00 
-
37.5-38.4°C 
205 
17 (4.4) 
1.86 
1.01 to 3.43 
≥38.5°C 
305 
28 (9.2) 
4.10 
2.39 to 7.05 
Tachycardia 
Not tachycardic 
974 
22 (2.3) 
1.00 
-
0.0001 
Tachycardic 
651 
39 (6.0) 
2.76 
1.61 to 4.71 
Capillary refi ll time 
&lt;2 s 
1755 
65 (3.7) 
1.00 
-
&lt;0.0001 
≥2 s 
40 
7 (17.5) 
5.52 
2.34 to 13.0 
Hydration status 
Well hydrated 
1834 
58 (3.2) 
1.00 
-
&lt;0.0001 
Dry mucous membranes 
102 
12 (11.8) 
4.08 
2.11 to 7.90 
Reduced skin turgor 
9 
4 (44.4) 
24.5 
6.30 to 95.3 
Hypotension  § 
Not hypotensive 
1947 
74 (3.8) 
1.00 
-
0.691 
Hypotensive 
4 
0 (0.0) 
0.00 
-
Tachypnoea 
Not tachypnoeic 
656 
19 (2.9) 
1.00 
-
0.028 
Tachypnoeic 
932 
48 (5.2) 
1.82 
1.06 to 3.13 
Hypoxia 
Not hypoxic 
1620 
49 (3.0) 
1.00 
-
&lt;0.0001 
Mild hypoxia 
265 
16 (6.0) 
2.06 
1.15 to 3.68 
Severe hypoxia 
66 
9 (13.6) 
5.06 
2.36 to 10.9 
Purpuric rash 
None 
1666 
66 (4.0) 
1.00 
-
0.641 
Purpuric rash 
16 
1 (6.3) 
1.62 
0.21 to 12.4 
Petechial rash 
None 
1666 
66 (4.0) 
1.00 
-
0.793 
Petechial rash 
42 
2 (4.8) 
1.21 
0.29 to 5.13 
Macular rash 
None 
1757 
70 (4.0) 
1.00 
-
0.184 
Macular rash 
194 
4 (2.1) 
0.51 
0.18 to 1.41 </p>

<p>*N indicates the total number children in a particular category. Note that the sum of N across all categories of a particular variable is equal to the total number of children 
for which data were available for that variable. For most variables this is less than the total number of children (1032) included in the analysis due to missing data for that 
particular variable. 
 † Identifi ed risk factors for bacterial infection in this analysis included neutropaenia, sickle cell disease, primary ciliary dyskinesia, Down's syndrome, glycogen storage 
disease 1b, Hunter's syndrome, Hurler's syndrome, cryptogenic cirrhosis, biliary atresia, vesico-ureteric refl ux, hydronephrosis, congenital pneumonia and a documented 
history of recurrent bacterial infections. 
 ‡ Temperature categories 35.0-36.4°C and 36.5-37.5°C were combined in the multivariate analysis to allow temperature to be modelled as a linear variable. No children had 
a temperature &lt;35.0°C in this study. 
 § Blood pressure recordings were only available for 94 children; the remaining children were classifi ed as not hypotensive for the purposes of the analysis. </p>

<p>not signifi cantly associated with SBI, it is important to note 
that blood pressure data were only available for 103 (5.3%) 
children. 
The predictive values of each variable are summarised in 
table 2 . Apart from tachypnoea (sensitivity 71.6%), the sensi-
tivity of most clinical signs was poor. However, some clinical 
signs, such a s those of reduced level of consciousness/alertness 
and impaired perfusion were highly specifi c, and demonstrated 
more clinically useful positive likelihood ratios. The low prior 
probability of SBI in this population explains the apparently </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>Arch Dis Child 2011;96:361-367. doi:10.1136/adc.2010.183111 </p>

<p>
high negative predictive values of many variables, refl ected in 
the poor utility of most negative likelihood ratios. 
After random weighted allocation of children to the deri-
vation and validation sets, the derivation set comprised 1600 
(85.2%) children without SBI and 64 (86.5%) children with 
SBI. The models with the best discriminative ability were 
those derived using 'sign OK' selection. For the 'sign OK' 
model confi ned to categorical variables, the AUCs in the der-
ivation and validation sets were 0.76 (0.68 to 0.82) a nd 0.85 
(0.71 to 0.99), respectively. Inclusion of continuous data in the 
model did not markedly improve performance (AUC 0.76 and 
0.86 in the derivation and validation sets, respectively), so the 
simpler model confi ned to categorical variables was selected. 
Regression coeffi cients and adjusted ORs and 95% CIs for each 
variable included in this model are given in table 3 . A modifi ed 
SBI score was derived based on the β coeffi cients of this model, 
such that: </p>

<p>Table 2 Predictive value of clinical variables for serious bacterial infection </p>

<p>Clinical variable 
Sensitivity, % (95% CI) Specifi city, % (95% CI) PPV, % (95% CI) 
NPV, % (95% CI) 
LR+ (95% CI) 
LR− (95% CI) </p>

<p>Risk factor for infection 
10.8 (4.8 to 20.2) 
97.6 (96.8 to 98.2) 
15.1 (6.7 to 28.0) 
96.5 (95.6 to 97.3) 
4.5 (3.3 to 6.2) 
0.91 (0.67 to 1.25) 
Developmental delay 
5.4 (1.5 to 13.3) 
98.7 (98.1 to 99.2) 
14.3 (4.0 to 32.7) 
96.4 (95.4 to 97.2) 
4.2 (4.2 to 4.3) 
0.96 (0.95 to 0.97) 
Consciousness level 
Not alert* 
2.8 (0.34 to 9.7) 
98.8 (98.2 to 99.3) 
8.3 (1.0 to 27.0) 
97.5 (96.7 to 98.1) 
2.4 (1.7 to 3.3) 
0.98 (0.7 to 1.4) 
No response to voice 
2.8 (0.34 to 9.7) 
99.8 (99.5 to 99.9) 
33.3 (4.3 to 77.7) 
96.4 (95.4 to 97.2) 13.0 (9.2 to 18.2) 0.97 (0.69 to 1.4) 
Unresponsive 
0.0 (0.0 to 5.0) † 
99.9 (99.7 to 100.0) 
0.0 (0.0 to 97.5) † 96.1 (95.2 to 97.0) 
0.0 
1.0 
State variation 
Eyes close briefl y or falls asleep 
8.1 (3.0 to 16.8) 
98.6 (98.0 to 99.1) 
18.8 (7.2 to 36.4) 
96.4 (95.5 to 97.2) 
5.8 (7.0 to 4.9) 
0.93 (0.78 to 1.1) 
Falls asleep 
0.0 (0.0 to 4.9) † 
99.9 (99.7 to 100.0) 
0.0 (0.0 to 97.5) † 96.2 (95.2 to 97.0) 
0.0 
1.0 
Temperature 
≥37.5°C 
60.8 (48.8 to 72.0) 
64.5 (62.2 to 66.7) 
6.5 (4.8 to 8.6) 
2.4 (1.6 to 3.4) 
1.7 (0.65 to 4.5) 0.61 (0.23 to 1.61) 
≥38.5°C 
37.8 (26.8 to 49.9) 
84.8 (83.1 to 86.4) 
9.2 (6.2 to 13.0) 
97.1 (96.1 to 97.9) 
2.5 (1.1 to 5.7) 
0.73 (0.32 to 1.7) 
Tachycardia 
63.9 (50.6 to 75.8) 
60.9 (58.4 to 63.3) 
6.0 (4.3 to 8.1) 
97.7 (96.6 to 98.6) 
1.6 (0.67 to 4.0) 0.59 (0.24 to 1.5) 
Capillary refi ll time ≥2 s 
9.7 (4.0 to 19.0) 
98.1 (97.3 to 98.7) 
17.5 (7.3 to 32.8) 
96.3 (95.3 to 97.1) 
5.1 (4.0 to 6.5) 
0.92 (0.72 to 1.2) 
Hydration status 
Dry mucous membranes 
21.6 (12.9 to 32.7) 
94.9 (93.8 to 95.9) 
14.4 (8.5 to 22.4) 
96.8 (95.9 to 97.6) 
4.3 (2.3 to 7.8) 
0.83 (0.45 to 1.5) 
Reduced skin turgor 
5.4 (1.5 to 13.3) 
99.7 (99.4 to 99.9) 
44.4 (13.7 to 78.8) 96.4 (95.4 to 97.2) 20.2 (20.1 to 20.4) 0.95 (0.94 to 0.96) 
Hypotension 
0.0 (0.0 to 4.9) † 
99.8 (99.5 to 99.9) 
0.0 (0.0 to 60.2)  † 96.2 (95.3 to 97.0) 
0.0 
1.0 
Tachypnoea 
71.6 (59.3 to 82.0) 
41.9 (39.4 to 44.4) 
5.2 (3.8 to 6.8) 
97.1 (95.5 to 98.2) 
1.2 (0.47 to 3.2) 0.68 (0.26 to 1.8) 
Hypoxia 
Mild or severe 
33.8 (23.2 to 45.7) 
83.7 (81.9 to 85.3) 
7.6 (4.9 to 10.9) 
97.0 (96.0 to 97.8) 
2.1 (0.95 to 4.5) 0.79 (0.36 to 1.7) 
Severe 
12.2 (5.7 to 21.8) 
97.0 (96.1 to 97.7) 
13.6 (6.4 to 24.3) 
966 (95.6 to 97.3) 
4.0 (2.8 to 5.8) 
0.91 (0.63 to 1.3) 
Rash 
Purpuric rash 
1.5 (0.04 to 8.0) 
99.1 (98.5 to 99.5) 
6.3 (0.2 to 30.2) 
96.0 (95.0 to 96.9) 
1.6 (0.8 to 3.2) 
0.99 (0.50 to 2.0) 
Petechial rash 
2.9 (0.4 to 10.2) 
97.6 (96.7 to 98.3) 
4.8 (0.6 to 16.2) 
96.0 (95.0 to 96.9) 
1.1 (0.79 to 1.6) 
1.0 (0.71 to 1.4) 
Macular rash 
5.4 (1.5 to 13.3) 
89.9 (88.4 to 91.2) 
2.1 (0.6 to 5.2) 
96.0 (95.0 to 96.9) 
0.53 (0.53 to 0.54) 1.1 (1.0 to 1.1) </p>

<p>*Not alert indicates only responds to voice or pain, or unresponsive. 
 † One sided, 97.5% CI. 
LR+, likelihood ratio of a positive test; LR−, likelihood ratio of a negative test; NPV, predictive value of a negative test; PPV, predictive value o f a positive test. </p>

<p>Table 3 Regression coeffi cients (β), and adjusted OR and 95% CI for 
variables included in the chosen model </p>

<p>Variables 
β Coeffi cient OR 
95% CI 
p Value </p>

<p>History of developmental delay 1.6807 
5.4 
1.6 to 18.6 
0.008 
Risk factor for infection 
1.4408 
4.2 
0.9 to 20.9 
0.077 
State variation 
0.2336 
1.3 
0.3 to 4.7 
0.728 
Temperature category 
0.6643 
1.9 
1.4 to 2.7 
&lt;0.001 
Capillary refi ll time 
0.6595 
1.9 
0.6 to 5.8 
0.243 
Dehydration category 
1.3651 
39 
2.0 to 7.6 
&lt;0.001 
Tachypnoea 
0.1760 
1.2 
0.6 to 2.2 
0.585 
Hypoxia category 
0.4734 
1.6 
1.1 to 2.4 
0.026 </p>

<p>The AUC for SBI score as a predictor of SBI in the derivation 
and validation sets combined was 0.77 (95% CI 0.71 to 0.83; 
fi gure 1 ). Table 4 shows t he SBI score in tabular form more 
conveniently for clinical use, and risks of SBI stratifi ed by SB I 
score are shown in table 5 . </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>By exploring the feasibility of developing a clinical prediction 
score for risk stratifi cation of suspected serious bacterial ill-
ness in children, this study addresses an important challenge 
in everyday clinical practice in the UK and other developed 
countries. 1 2 5 7 Among children presenting to emergency care 
in whom infection was suspected (where the prior probability 
of SBI was 5%), our SBI score was able to rule out SBI with 
reasonable confi dence and precision in three quarters of chil-
dren in the dataset to whom the score was applied (SBI score 
≤5 associated with &lt;2% risk of SBI), to identify children at the 
highest risk of SBI (a third of children with an SBI score &gt;8 had 
SBI) and to risk stratify the remaining children into groups 
with increasing risk. 
We modelled continuous data as categorical and continu-
ous variables in separate models. Although less suitable for the 
development of a clinical prediction score for clinicians, con-
tinuous variables maximise information 15 22 and can be util-
ised in computer-assisted diagnostic pathways. However, their 
inclusion in the model did not improve discriminative ability 
suffi ciently to justify the increased complexity. 
Previous studies in developed countries have attempted to 
derive clinical scores as a tool to identify seriously ill children 
at presentation. 23 -35 Most were carried out in populations 
with a higher incidence of SBI prior to the introduction of </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>Arch Dis Child 2011;96:361-367. doi:10.1136/adc.2010.183111 </p>

<p>
routine vaccination against Haemophilus infl uenza type b (Hib) 
and Streptococcus pneumoniae ; others were designed to predict 
the need for admission to intensive care. 9 Moreover, promis-
ing initial reports of diagnostic performance have not always 
been consistently reproducible. 27 36 37 This probably refl ects 
a combination of the inherent over-optimism of data-driven 
model predictions based on small datasets, 15 19 21 38 -40 failure 
to validate models and/or scores in an independent dataset, 15 19  and spectrum bias arising from the use of case-control 
designs. 41 -43 In a recent study based mainly in primary care, a 
clinical algorithm was derived with the ability to rule out SBI 
with reasonable confi dence. 44 However, these results have not 
been validated in an independent dataset, and negative predic-
tive values are likely to be lower in emergency department set-
tings where the prior probability of SBI is higher. 
The strengths of our study include the large number of chil-
dren studied, detailed review of all clinical and laboratory data 
to assign outcome, validation of the model in an independent 
part of the dataset, and inclusion of all children presenting with 
suspected SBI in a cohort study design, which suggests the pre-
dictive value of our SBI score should be generalisable to other 
similar settings. Furthermore, focusing on children with sus-
pected SBI rather than all children with serious illness allowed 
inclusion of clinical risk factors specifi c to infection, and may 
have helped improve model specifi city. It is important to stress 
that while the SBI score should be generalisable to emergency 
departments in the developed world, it is unlikely to be appli-
cable to developing world settings where the prevalence of SBI 
among paediatric presentations is much higher and there may 
be other important risk factors for infection such as malnutri-
tion and HIV. 5  A potential limitation of the study concerns the defi nition 
of SBI. No single, reliable gold standard exists for the diagnosis 
of invasive bacterial infections in children. Although cultures 
from blood and other sterile sites are highly specifi c, sensitiv-
ity is limited. 45 -47 The defi nition of SBI used has been formu-
lated to take account of all available clinical and laboratory 
information in defi ning each clinical syndrome, including a 
child's response to treatment, and is designed to capture all 
children with invasive or otherwise SBIs who require admis-
sion to hospital. A potential criticism is the risk of incorpo-
ration bias, since clinicians are not blind to the admission </p>

<p>Figure 1 Receiver operator characteristics (ROC) curve of serious 
bacterial infection score as a predictor of serious bacterial infection in 
the entire dataset. </p>

<p>Table 4 Serious bacterial infection (SBI) score f or prediction of 
serious bacterial infection </p>

<p>Clinical variable 
Score* </p>

<p>Developmental delay 
No delay 
0 
Delay 
4 
Risk factor for infection 
No risk factor 
0 
Risk factor present 
2 
State variation 
Eyes open 
0 
Eyes close briefl y 
1 
Falls asleep 
2 
Temperature 
&lt;37.5°C 
0 
37.5-38.4°C 
1 
≥38.5°C 
2 
Capillary refi ll time (s) 
&lt;2 
0 
≥2 
1 
Hydration status 
Well hydrated 
0 
Dry mucous membranes 
2 
Reduced skin turgor 
4 
Respiratory rate 
Not tachypnoeic 
0 
Tachypnoeic 
1 
Hypoxia 
Not hypoxic 
0 
Mild hypoxia 
1 
Severe hypoxia 
2 </p>

<p>*Score indicates the sum of scores for each clinical variable (maximum score 18). 
Table 5 sho ws risks of serious bacterial infection stratifi ed by SBI score. </p>

<p>clinical variables studied, which are likely to infl uence admis-
sion decisions; inclusion of clinical and laboratory data from 
the entire admission in assigning outcome is likely to only 
partly mitigate this bias. Nevertheless, we believe the defi -
nition adopted represents a pragmatic working defi nition of 
SBI. Importantly, we were also able to identify those children 
discharged from hospital who re-attended within a week, 
and to amend their SBI classifi cation as required. While we 
cannot exclude the possibility that other children may have 
re-presented elsewhere, the nearest emergency department, 
which does not have a dedicated paediatric section, is 18 miles 
away, so the chance of this is small. Similarly, since sudden 
childhood death is rare in this population and most cases are 
brought to hospital, the chance of a child in this study dying at 
home and not re-attending hospital is also small. 
Missing data also limit the power of our analysis. Although 
the proportion of data missing for individual variables was 
generally small, this became more signifi cant in the multivari-
ate analysis. Blood pressure is not routinely measured in pae-
diatric clinical practice except in the sickest children, so data 
were missing for most patients. Nevertheless, blood pressure 
may have an important role in predicting SBI that this analy-
sis would not be able to identify. The number of children for 
whom age data were missing is unfortunate as it further limits 
study power; however, this is unlikely to have introduced any 
bias since the underlying problem (poor legibility of the pro-
forma) is unlikely to be related to the clinical presentation and 
was not associated with SBI. 
Finally, measurement error is also possible, since emergency 
department staff assessed each clinical sign using routine clin-
ical tools. For some variables this is likely to be minimal since 
automated measurements were used. Arguably, even for other 
variables this may be seen as a strength of the study, since it 
increases its generalisability to the routine clinical setting. 
The implications of this study for clinical practice are three-
fold. First, the specifi city of some clinical signs for SBI (such </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>Arch Dis Child 2011;96:361-367. doi:10.1136/adc.2010.183111 </p>

<p>
as reduced activity or level of consciousness, prolonged capil-
lary refi ll time and reduced skin turgor) support the National 
Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence clinical guidelines 7  which use these clinical features as 'red fl ags' to identify seri-
ously ill children. The presence of these features in a febrile 
child should prompt a careful clinical assessment. Second, it 
clearly demonstrates the potential utility of a clinical score to 
stratify children according to their risk of SBI. Such a score 
might be incorporated into electronic decision support and 
medical records. Finally, it underlines the need to use such 
a clinical score as part of a broader algorithm to guide man-
agement decisions (including additional investigations, plans 
for review or admission for observation) to further stratify 
a child's risk. Future research should explore the benefi t of 
including in the model other risk factors such as immunisation 
status, routine blood pressure measurement, and other poten-
tial markers of sepsis such as limb pain or cool peripheries, 2  investigate how laboratory tests such as C-reactive protein, 
procalcitonin and white blood cell count may best be incorpo-
rated into a clinical algorithm to refi ne a child's risk status, and 
further validate the performance and impact 14 48 of the score 
in different acute paediatric settings, including primary care. </p>

<p>Contributors AJB and ML are joint fi rst authors. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors would like to thank Dr Terence Stephenson for 
his contributions to the initial data collection. </p>

<p>The study was carried out on behalf of the Royal College of Paediatrics and Child 
Health (RCPCH) working group on Recognising Acute Illness in Children (RAIC). MT is 
a member of University of Oxford Department of Primary Health Care which is part of 
the NIHR National School of Primary Care Research. ML is a member of the Leicester 
Collaboration for Leadership in Applied Health Research and Care (CLARCH) team 
and Director of the Health Education Research and Development Unit (HERADU). </p>

<p>Funding AJB is supported by a Wellcome Trust research training fellowship 
(081697). The authors wish to thank the Well Child Medical Charity for their 
funding of the studies in Nottingham a nd of this study. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Ethics approval This study was conducted with the approval of the Nottingham 
Research Ethics Committee and the ethics committee of the London School of 
Hygiene and Tropical Medicine. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>



<p>Original article </p>

<p> 
Arch Dis Child April 2011 Vol 96 No 4 </p>



</text></tei>