<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3769764" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:46+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>An agar-degrading Pseudoalteromonas sp. AG52 bacterial strain was identified from the red seaweed </p>

<p>Gelidium amansii collected from Jeju Island, Korea. A -agarase gene which has 96.8% nucleotide identity </p>

<p>to Aeromonas -agarase was cloned from this strain, and was designated as agaA. The coding region is </p>

<p>870 bp, encoding 290 amino acids and possesses characteristic features of the glycoside hydrolase family </p>

<p>(GHF)-16. The predicted molecular mass of the mature protein was 32 kDa. The recombinant -agarase </p>

<p>(rAgaA) was overexpressed in Escherichia coli and purified as a fusion protein. The optimal temperature </p>

<p>and pH for activity were 55 
o C and 5.5, respectively. The enzyme had a specific activity of 105.1 and 79.5 </p>

<p>unit/mg toward agar and agarose, respectively. The pattern of agar hydrolysis demonstrated that the </p>

<p>enzyme is an endo-type -agarase, producing neoagarohexaose and neoagarotetraose as the final main </p>

<p>products. </p>

<p>Since, Pseudoalteromonas sp. AG52 encodes an agaA gene, which has greater identity to Aeromonas -</p>

<p>agarase, the enzyme could be considered as novel, with its unique bio chemical characteristics. Altogether, </p>

<p>the purified rAgaA has potential for use in industrial applications such as development of cosmetics and </p>

<p>pharmaceuticals. </p>

<p>The main component of the cell wall of marine red algae </p>

<p>(Rhodophyceaea) is agar, and it is composed of agarose (4) and </p>

<p>agaropectin (12). Agarases are the hydrolytic enzymes mostly </p>

<p>found in marine habitats (5, 39), which are responsible for the </p>

<p>breakdown of agar and agar-derived compounds, and result in </p>

<p>oligosaccharides that have various bioactivities (9, 25). Based </p>

<p>on the pattern of hydrolysis of the substrates, agarases are </p>

<p>grouped into -agarases and -agarases (3, 19). To date, most </p>

<p>*Corresponding Author. Mailing address: Department of Marine Life Science, Jeju National University, Jeju, 690-756, Republic of Korea.; Tel: +82-64-754-
3472 Fax: +82-64-756-3493.; E-mail: jehee@jejunu.ac.kr </p>

<p>877 </p>

<p>Oh, C. et al. 
Characterization of a novel -agarase from Psudoalteromonas sp. AG52 </p>

<p>of the agarolytic enzymes isolated, purified and characterized </p>

<p>have been from microorganisms, with the majority of the </p>

<p>genera being marine bacteria. Among these known agarases, </p>

<p>most belong to the -agarase group and few biochemical </p>

<p>studies have been reported for -agarases (39, 44). Several -</p>

<p>agarases have been purified and characterized from species </p>

<p>including Pseudoalteromonas (43, 48), Pseudomonas (16, 17,   33), Alteromonas (19, 24, 29, 39, 49), Agarivorans (15, 20), </p>

<p>Vibrio (2, 6, 14, 45), Cytophage (11, 47), Bacillus (46) and </p>

<p>Saccharophagus (13). Cloning and expression of -agarase </p>

<p>encoding genes has been reported from Pseudoalteromonas </p>

<p>(30), Pseudomonas (17, 27, 41), Agarivorans (28, 34), </p>

<p>Microbulbifer (35-37), Vibrio (45, 50), Zobellia (22) and </p>

<p>Streptomyces (23). </p>

<p>Our laboratory is currently conducting research on the </p>

<p>characterization of a number of -agarases and the biochemical </p>

<p>properties of recombinant proteins, from various bacterial </p>

<p>species isolated from the marine environment. In this study, </p>

<p>Pseudoalteromonas sp. AG52 was isolated from the Jeju Island </p>

<p>coastal environment, from which a -agarase gene was </p>

<p>subsequently isolated and designated as agaA. We cloned the </p>

<p>gene, overexpressed the protein in Escherichia coli (E. coli) </p>

<p>and purified the recombinant -agarase (rAgaA) from </p>

<p>Pseudoalteromonas sp. AG52. In addition, purified rAgaA was </p>

<p>analyzed for biochemical properties such as specific activities </p>

<p>and optimum reaction conditions. Until recently, the </p>

<p>Pseudoalteromonas sp. -agarase was an unknown entity. </p>

<p>Herein we examine and describe in depth this enzyme, which </p>

<p>upon analysis showed greater identity to Aeromonas -agarase. </p>

<p>The characterization of this novel enzyme could be beneficial </p>

<p>to a variety of industries. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Isolation of agarase-producing bacteria strain </p>

<p>Agarolytic bacteria were isolated from the red seaweed, </p>

<p>Gelidium amansii from the south coast of Jeju Island, Republic </p>

<p>of Korea. The crushed seaweeds were spread, on on SWT </p>

<p>(0.3% Tryptone and 1.5% agar in seawater), SWY (0.3% yeast </p>

<p>extract and 1.5% agar in seawater) and marine agar plates </p>

<p>(Difco, Detroit, USA). Positive colonies showing clear zones </p>

<p>or pits were picked out from the selection plates, and re-</p>

<p>streaked The pure colonies were selected by repeat streaking </p>

<p>under the same conditions and inoculated in their respective </p>

<p>broths including 0.2% agar, then incubated at 30 
o C. The stock </p>

<p>was prepared from the bacteria culture using 20% glycerol, </p>

<p>then samples were stored at -70 
o C. Polymerase Chain Reaction </p>

<p>(PCR) was performed for 16S rDNA sequence amplification </p>

<p>from the extracted genomic DNA of isolated bacteria. The </p>

<p>universal primers (16S-27F as forward and 16S-1492R as </p>

<p>reverse) used for the PCR are shown in Table 1. The sequence </p>

<p>was analyzed using the <rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">NCBI</rs> <rs id="software-6" type="software">Blast N</rs> program and the </p>

<p><rs type="software">DNAssist</rs> program. </p>

<p>Partial agaA gene amplification </p>

<p>All of the cloning experiments were carried out according </p>

<p>to Sambrook et al. (42) with slight modifications. From </p>

<p>analyzing the sequences of other agarase genes from NCBI </p>

<p>database, three sets of forward and reverse primers were </p>

<p>designed (Table 1) and those mix primers (Mix-AGA-F1 and </p>

<p>R1, Mix-CY-F2 and R2, Mix-Sa-F3 and R3) were used for </p>

<p>initial partial agarase amplification using genomic DNA as </p>

<p>template and Ex Taq DNA polymerase (Takara, Japan). </p>

<p>Long and Accurate Polymerase Chain Reaction (LA PCR) </p>

<p>for detection of full length agaA </p>

<p>The complete agaA was cloned using a LA PCR in vitro </p>

<p>cloning kit (Takara, Korea), according to the manufacturer </p>

<p>instructions. Genomic DNA was digested with separate </p>

<p>restriction enzymes BamH I, EcoR I, Hind III and Xho I, and </p>

<p>subsequently the digested products were ligated with a BamH </p>

<p>I, EcoR I, Hind III and Xho I cassette, then used as a template </p>

<p>for LA PCR. LA52-F1 and LA52-F2 primers and LA52-R1 </p>

<p>and LA52-R2 primers were designed to identify the reverse </p>

<p>and forward sequence from the known partial sequence of </p>

<p>agaA, respectively (Table 1). The amplification of upstream or </p>

<p>downstream of the known sequence was performed using </p>

<p>LA52-R1 or LA52-F1 with C1 (from the cassette nucleotide </p>

<p>878 </p>

<p>Oh, C. et al. 
Characterization of a novel -agarase from Psudoalteromonas sp. AG52 </p>

<p>sequence), respectively. Taking the resultant product as the </p>

<p>template, PCR was performed to obtain upstream or </p>

<p>downstream of the known sequence using LA52-R2 or LA52-</p>

<p>F2 with C2 (from the cassette nucleotide sequence), </p>

<p>respectively. Product was sequenced, and the gene was </p>

<p>analyzed by nucleotide BLAST and Protein BLAST of </p>

<p>National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) </p>

<p>database. The signal peptide sequence of AgaA was predicted </p>

<p>through a <rs id="software-1" type="software">SignalP</rs> program (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/ SignalP</rs>/). The <rs id="software-2" type="software">LipoP</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">1.0</rs> Server (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="url">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/ services/LipoP</rs>/) was used for a gram-negative bacteria </p>

<p>lipoprotein site search analysis. Identity and percent similarity </p>

<p>of full-length amino acid sequences were calculated using </p>

<p><rs type="software">FASTA</rs> program (38). </p>

<p>Table 1. Oligonucleotide primers </p>

<p>Name 
Object 
Sequence (5' to 3' direction) </p>

<p>16S-27F 
16S rDNA sequence amplification 
AGAGTTTGATCMTGGCTCAG </p>

<p>16S-1492R 
16S rDNA sequence amplification 
TACGGYTACCTTGTTACGACTT </p>

<p>Mix-AGA-F1 
agaA partial sequence amplification 
CWTCKTATATWAATGCTTGGC </p>

<p>Mix-AGA-R1 
agaA partial sequence amplification 
TGGYTGRTAATCTTGAAATGG </p>

<p>Mix-CY-F2 
agaA partial sequence amplification 
YTNGARTAYTAYATHGAYGG </p>

<p>Mix-CY-R2 
agaA partial sequence amplification 
TTRTANACNCKDATCCARTC </p>

<p>Mix-Sa-F3 
agaA partial sequence amplification 
TCNATHCAYYTNTAYGAYTTYCC </p>

<p>Mix-Sa-R3 
agaA partial sequence amplification 
CCAYTCNGCYTTNACNGG </p>

<p>52LA-F1 
LA PCR Forward 1 
TCGTCGCTACGGTGTTCATTGGAA </p>

<p>52LA-F2 
LA PCR Forward 2 
TAGTTCGCAGCGTTTCAGGTCCTA </p>

<p>52LA-R1 
LA PCR Reverse 1 
ACGTGCATACGTTGGTCAAACCAC </p>

<p>52LA-R2 
LA PCR Reverse 2 
TGCCTCCATCGCATCAATTTCCTG </p>

<p>C1 
Cassette primers 
GTACATATTGTCGTTAGAACGCGTAATACGACTCA </p>

<p>C2 
Cassette primers 
CGTTAGAACGCGTAATACGACTCACTATAGGGAGA </p>

<p>Ag52-F1 
Cloning to pET-16b 
(GA) 3 CATATGGCAGATTGGGACGCATATAGTA (Nde I) </p>

<p>Ag52-R2 
Cloning to pET-16b 
(GA) 3 GGATCCTTAGTTTGCTTTGTAGACACGTATC (BamH I) </p>

<p>Cloning of AgaA coding sequence into the expression </p>

<p>vectors </p>

<p>Primer set Ag52-F1 and Ag52-R2 were designed with its </p>

<p>corresponding restriction enzyme sites (Table 1) to clone the </p>

<p>coding sequence into the pET16b expression vector (Novagen, </p>

<p>USA), without including its signal sequence. The vector and </p>

<p>PCR products were digested with restriction enzymes, ligated </p>

<p>and transformed into E. coli DH5 cells, and correct </p>

<p>recombinants (confirmed by restriction enzyme digestion and </p>

<p>sequencing) were transformed into E. coli BL21(DE3). </p>

<p>Recombinant cells were overexpressed in the presence of </p>

<p>isopropyl-ß-thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG) at a final </p>

<p>concentration of 1 mM. Briefly, 5 mL of an overnight grown </p>

<p>BL21(DE3) starter culture was inoculated into 100 mL Luria </p>

<p>broth with 100 L ampicillin (100 mg/mL) and 10 mM glucose </p>

<p>(0.2% final concentration) and incubated at 37 
o C. </p>

<p>Recombinant pET-16b-AgaA cells were induced for 24 h at 12 </p>

<p>o C, followed by cell harvesting (centrifugation at 4000 x g for </p>

<p>20 min at 4 
o C). The cells carrying the pET-16b-AgaA were </p>

<p>resuspended in 5 mL ice-cold 1x binding buffer (8x = 4M </p>

<p>NaCl, 160 mM Tris HCl, 40 mM imidazole, pH 7.9) and frozen </p>

<p>at -20 
o C overnight. After thawing on ice, the bacterial cells </p>

<p>879 </p>

<p>Oh, C. et al. 
Characterization of a novel -agarase from Psudoalteromonas sp. AG52 </p>

<p>were sonicated and supernatant was taken as a crude enzyme </p>

<p>after centrifugation. The crude rAgaA fusion protein fused with </p>

<p>His tag was purified using the His Bind purification Kit </p>

<p>(Novagen, USA). Elutes were collected in 500 L fractions and </p>

<p>respective elutes were run on 12% SDS-PAGE. The </p>

<p>concentrations of purified proteins were determined by the </p>

<p>method of Bradford using bovine serum albumin (BSA) as the </p>

<p>standard. </p>

<p>Agarase enzyme assay </p>

<p>Specific activity of purified rAgaA was determined </p>

<p>according to a modified method of Ohta et al. (35) using </p>

<p>different substrates including 1% food-grade agar, 1% agarose </p>

<p>and 1% carrageenan. Appropriately diluted enzyme solution </p>

<p>was added to different substrates in phosphate buffer (pH 7.0) </p>

<p>at 45 
o C, and was incubated at 45 
o C for 30 min. Activity was </p>

<p>expressed as the initial rate of agar hydrolysis by measuring the </p>

<p>release of reducing ends using the 3,5-dinitrosalicylic acid </p>

<p>(DNS) procedure (32) with D-galactose as the standard. One </p>

<p>unit of the enzyme activity was defined as the amount of </p>

<p>protein per min produced 1 mol of reducing sugar as D-</p>

<p>galactose under condition of the assay. </p>

<p>Biochemical characterization of rAgaA </p>

<p>In each experiment, 1% agar solution and purified agarase </p>

<p>were mixed and incubated at various times and temperatures as </p>

<p>described. The relative agarase activity was determined by the </p>

<p>DNS method. The optimum temperature of rAgaA activity was </p>

<p>determined by monitoring the relative enzymatic activity at </p>

<p>temperatures ranging from 40-65 
o C with 5 
o C intervals at pH </p>

<p>7.0. Optimum pH was tested from pH 4.5-9.0 with pH 0.5 </p>

<p>intervals at 45 
o C. Acetate buffer and phosphate buffer were </p>

<p>used for pH 4.5-6.0 and pH 6.5-9.0, respectively. The </p>

<p>thermostability of rAgaA was evaluated by measuring the </p>

<p>residual activity of the enzyme after incubation at the </p>

<p>temperatures between 40-55 
o C for 30, 60 and 120 min. The </p>

<p>effects of various metal ion salts and chelators on purified </p>

<p>rAgaA activity were tested by determining the activity in the </p>

<p>presence of 2 mM of various ions or chelators (CaCl 2 , CuSO 4 , </p>

<p>FeSO 4 , KCl, MgSO 4 , MnCl 2 , NaCl and EDTA) in a final </p>

<p>concentration and incubated at 45 
o C for 30 min. The control </p>

<p>was the assay mixture, with no addition of metal ion salts or </p>

<p>chelators. </p>

<p>Identification of rAgaA hydrolyzed agar products </p>

<p>Thin layer chromatography (TLC) was used to identify the </p>

<p>hydrolysis products of agar and neoagarooligosaccharides. </p>

<p>Neoagarohexanitol (NA6) was purchased from Sigma (USA) </p>

<p>and neoagarotetraose (NA4) and neoagarobiose (NA2) (NA4 + </p>

<p>NA2) were prepared by digestion of neoagarohexanitol using </p>

<p>commercial -agarase (New England Biolab, USA). D-(+)-</p>

<p>galactose was purchased from Sigma (USA), and all above </p>

<p>mentioned oligosaccharides were used as standards. Moreover, </p>

<p>food-grade agar and NA6 were used as substrates for the </p>

<p>reactions. The reaction of purified agarase and agar was carried </p>

<p>out in 200 L reactions containing 20 L of purified agarase </p>

<p>and 180 L of 1% agar at 45 
o C for 30, 60, and 120 min. The </p>

<p>NA6 substrate was incubated separately with 20 L of purified </p>

<p>agarase at 45 
o C for 120 min. Subsequently, the reaction </p>

<p>mixtures were applied to a silica gel 60 TLC plate (Merck, </p>

<p>Germany). The TLC plates were developed using a solvent </p>

<p>system consisting of n-butanol: acetic acid: water (2:1:1, v/v). </p>

<p>After hydrolysis of substrates, the resultant oligosaccharide </p>

<p>spots were visualized by spraying 10% H 2 SO 4 on the plate, </p>

<p>then heating it on a hot plate. </p>

<p>Nucleotide sequence accession number </p>

<p>The Pseudoalteromonas sp. AG52 -agarase nucleotide </p>

<p>sequence was submitted to the NCBI database with accession </p>

<p>number FJ979637. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Identification of the agarase-producing bacteria </p>

<p>Initially, agarase-producing marine bacteria were isolated </p>

<p>from selection plates showing clear zones. The 16S rRNA </p>

<p>sequence analyses results showed that the isolated bacteria </p>

<p>from seaweed was 99% similar to Pseudoalteromonas sp. and </p>

<p>880 </p>

<p>Oh, C. et al. 
Characterization of a novel -agarase from Psudoalteromonas sp. AG52 </p>

<p>is assigned to the genus Pseudoalteromonas and named </p>

<p>Pseudoalteromonas sp. AG52. This strain was deposited in </p>

<p>Korean Culture Collection Center of Microorganisms </p>

<p>(KCCM), Rep. of Korea with accession number KCCM 42924. </p>

<p>Cloning of -agarase from Pseudoalteromonas sp AG52 </p>

<p>The partial agaA sequence (651 bp) followed by full </p>

<p>length sequence was amplified as described in Materials and </p>

<p>Methods. The nucleotide and deduced amino acid sequences of </p>

<p>Pseudoalteromonas sp. AG52 -agarase is shown in Figure 1. </p>

<p>The agaA gene open reading frame (ORF) consists of a 870 bp </p>

<p>encoding a protein of 290 amino acids. The agaA has a </p>

<p>putative molecular mass of 32 kDa with an isoelectric point of </p>

<p>5.8. The signal peptide (1-21 aa) and lipoprotein signal peptide </p>

<p>(signal peptidase II) were identified in the N-terminal </p>

<p>sequence. Additionally, a characteristic GHF-16 -agarase </p>

<p>family domain (Cys 
22 -Lys 
287 ), catalytically active site residues </p>

<p>(Tyr 
69 , Asp 
71 , Trp 
72 , Trp 
139 , Ser 
145 , Asp 
150 , Glu 
153 , Phe 
176 , </p>

<p>Arg 
178 , Glu 
257 , Glu 
259 ), and calcium binding residues (Gln 
47 , </p>

<p>Phe 
48 , Asn 
49 , Gly 
91 , Ala 
92 , Asp 
282 , Trp 
283 ) were identified in the </p>

<p>sequence. The agaA nucleotide sequence showed 96.4% and </p>

<p>74.9% nucleotide identity to -agarase sequence of Aeromonas </p>

<p>sp. (Accession number U61972) and Pseudoalteromonas </p>

<p>atlantica (accession number M73783), respectively. Database </p>

<p>searches using BLASTP yielded results showing homology to </p>

<p>other known GHF-16 family agarases. Pairwise comparison of </p>

<p>AgaA amino acid sequence to known agarases is shown in </p>

<p>Table 2. Interestingly, AgaA amino acid sequence shares </p>

<p>96.9% identity and 99.3% similarity with Aeromonas sp. -</p>

<p>agarase (accession number AAF03246). The P. atlantica -</p>

<p>agarase coding sequence (accession number AAA91888) </p>

<p>shares only 84.5% identity, and 92.4% similarity with AgaA. </p>

<p>The multiple alignment shows conserved catalytic and calcium </p>

<p>binding residues of AG52 when compared with other GHF-16 </p>

<p>agarases (Figure 2). The phylogenetic analysis of the AgaA </p>

<p>amino acid sequence including known -agarase amino acid </p>

<p>sequences of different members of the -agarase family </p>

<p>(GHF16, 52 and 82) was constructed using the neighbor-</p>

<p>joining method as shown in Figure 3. The AgaA coding </p>

<p>sequence was clustered with GHF-16 -agarases, and formed a </p>

<p>monophyletic clade with -agarase of Aeromonas sp. and P. </p>

<p>atlantica (AAA91888). However, it was also closely grouped </p>

<p>with Aeromonas -agarase. </p>

<p>Purification and Biochemical characterization of rAgaA </p>

<p>Successfully purified rAgaA agarase in pET-16b as a </p>

<p>fusion protein was approximately 33 kDa, which was in </p>

<p>agreement with the predicted molecular mass of AgaA (Figure </p>

<p>4), hence enzyme characterization was carried out with the </p>

<p>fusion protein. </p>

<p>The specific activity of purified rAgaA towards agar and </p>

<p>agarose were 105.1 and 79.5 unit/mg, respectively. The </p>

<p>optimum reaction temperature of the purified rAG52 was 55 
o C </p>

<p>(Figure 5A), however, more than 50% of the relative activity </p>

<p>was observed between 40 and 60 
o C. The effect of pH on </p>

<p>purified enzyme is shown in Figure 5B. The maximal activity </p>

<p>was observed at pH 5.5 and the enzyme was stable (more than </p>

<p>60% relative activity) in the range of buffers from pH 4.5-9 </p>

<p>under the conditions of the assay. The temperature dependence </p>

<p>of the rAgaA activity on agar was determined by measuring the </p>

<p>activity at various temperatures for 120 min. The effect of </p>

<p>temperature on the stability of rAG52 is shown in Figure 5C. </p>

<p>The thermostability of rAgaA was retained upto 80% at 40 
o C </p>

<p>for 30 min. When temperature was increased to 45, 50 and 55 </p>

<p>o C for 30 min, the enzyme relative activity was decreased to </p>

<p>20-30%. Nevertheless, the enzyme was fairly stable (50% </p>

<p>relative activity) at 40 
o C for 60 min of incubation. Moreover, </p>

<p>addition of 2 mM CaCl 2 to the reaction mixture at 40 
o C was </p>

<p>enhanced the thermostability by 20 and 15% at 60 and 120 </p>

<p>min, respectively (Figure 5D). The effect of metal ion salts and </p>

<p>chelators on the activity of purified rAgaA enzyme is shown in </p>

<p>Figure 6. rAgaA relative activity was totally inhibited by </p>

<p>divalent metal salts such as CuSO 4 and ZnSO 4 (each at 2 mM </p>

<p>final concentration). Moreover, 2 mM EDTA inhibited the </p>

<p>enzyme activity by 60%. In contrast, 2 mM FeSO 4 and 2 mM </p>

<p>KCl enhanced the activity of rAgaA more than the other metal </p>

<p>ion salts present in seawater. </p>

<p>881 </p>

<p>Oh, C. et al. 
Characterization of a novel -agarase from Psudoalteromonas sp. AG52 </p>

<p>Figure 1. The nucleotide and deduced amino acid sequences of the -agarase of Pseudoalteromonas sp. AG52. The predicted lipoprotein signal </p>

<p>peptide is underlined and signal peptide sequence is in bold face. The start (ATG) and stop (TAA) codons are in bold italics and stop codon is </p>

<p>marked with an asterisk (*). The GHF-16 -agarase domain is in italics. Active sites and calcium binding residues are in boxes and dotted boxes, </p>

<p>respectively. </p>

<p>882 </p>

<p>Oh, C. et al. 
Characterization of a novel -agarase from Psudoalteromonas sp. AG52 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Multiple alignment of -agarase amino acid sequences of Pseudoalteromonas sp. AG52 with known agarases. The inverted triangles </p>

<p>( ) highlight the conserved catalytic residues, and black circles ( ) represent the conserved residues involved in calcium ion binding. Identical </p>

<p>residues in all sequences are shaded in gray and indicated by (*) under the column, conserved substitutions are indicated by (:), and semi-</p>

<p>conserved substitutions are indicated by (.). Deletions are indicated by dashes. Sequence sources: Aeromonas sp. -agarase (AAF03246), </p>

<p>Pseudoalteromonas atlantica -agarase I (AAA91888), Zobellia galactanivorans -agarase A (AAF21820), Zobellia galactanivorans -agarase </p>

<p>B (AAF21821). </p>

<p>883 </p>

<p>Oh, C. et al. 
Characterization of a novel -agarase from Psudoalteromonas sp. AG52 </p>

<p>Table 2. Pairwise analysis and comparisons of the deduced amino acid sequence of Pseudoalteromonas sp. AG52 -agarase with other </p>

<p>known -agarases. </p>

<p>Species 
Accession number 
Identity (%) 
Amino acids 
Aeromonas sp. -agarase 
AAF03246 
96.9 
290 
Pseudoalteromonas atlantica -agarase 
AAA91888 
84.5 
290 
AguD uncultured bacterium -agarase 
AAP49316 
45.2 
449 
Zobellia galactanivorans -agarase B 
AAF21821 
39.3 
353 
Pseudomonas sp. ND137 agarase 
BAB79291 
38.7 
441 </p>

<p>Microbulbifer thermotolerans agarase 
BAD29947 
36.1 
433 
Microbulbifer elongatus agarase 
BAC99022 
35.6 
441 
Cellvibrio sp. OA-2007 putative agarase 
BAH16616 
32.3 
596 
Saccharophagus degradans -agarase I 
AAT67062 
26.8 
593 
Zobellia galactanivorans -agarase A 
AAF21820 
26.0 
539 
Pseudoalteromonas sp. CY24 agarase 
AAN39119 
24.1 
453 </p>

<p>Figure 3. Phylogenetic analysis of AgaA with known agarases based on amino acid sequence. Phylogenetic analysis was done by the Neighbor </p>

<p>Joining method using <rs id="software-4" type="software">MEGA</rs><rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">3.1</rs>, based on sequence alignment using <rs id="software-5" type="software">ClustalW</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">1.81</rs>). Numbers indicate the bootstrap confidence values of 1000 </p>

<p>replicates. The accession numbers of the selected agarase sequences are as follows: AB178483, agarase (Agarivorans sp. JAMB-A11); </p>

<p>EF051475, QM38 agarase (Agarivorans sp. QM38); EF100136, -agarase (Agarivorans sp. JA-1); AAA25696, -agarase precursor </p>

<p>(Pseudoalteromonas atlantica); AAP49346, AguB; AAP70390, AguH; AAP70365, AguK; AAP49316, AguD from uncultured bacterium; </p>

<p>AAA91888, -agarase I (Pseudoalteromonas atlantica); AAF03246, -agarase (Aeromonas sp.); AB124837, agarase (Microbulbifer </p>

<p>thermotolerans); BAC99022, agarase (Microbulbifer elongatus); BAB79291, agarase, (Pseudomonas sp. ND137; AAF21821, -agarase B </p>

<p>precursor (Zobellia galactanivorans); AAF21820, -agarase A precursor (Zobellia galactanivorans); AAN39119, extracellular agarase </p>

<p>precursor, (Pseudoalteromonas sp. CY24); CAB61795, extracellular agarase precursor (Streptomyces coelicolor A3); AAP70364, AguJ </p>

<p>(uncultured bacterium); BAA04744, -agarase (Vibrio sp.); BAA03541, -agarase (Vibrio sp. JT0107); BAH16616, agarase (Cellvibrio sp. OA-</p>

<p>2007); AAT67062, -agarase I (Saccharophagus degradans); AB160954, -agarase (Microbulbifer thermotolerans). </p>

<p>884 </p>

<p>Oh, C. et al. 
Characterization of a novel -agarase from Psudoalteromonas sp. AG52 </p>

<p>Figure 4. SDS-PAGE of the rAgaA. Samples of rAgaA were separated on 12% SDS-PAGE and stained with Coomassie brilliant blue. M: </p>

<p>molecular mass marker (BioRad, USA). Lane 1: total cellular extract from E. coli BL21 (DE3) before induction; lane 2: total cellular soluble </p>

<p>extract after induction; lane 3: total cellular insoluble extract after induction; lane 4: purified rAgaA. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Characterization of biochemical properties of purified rAgaA. A. The effect of temperature on the rAgaA. The effect of temperature on </p>

<p>enzyme activity was determined under standard assay conditions as described in Materials and Methods, at temperatures ranging between 40-65 </p>

<p>o C. B. The effect of pH on the activity of rAgaA. Optimum pH for rAgaA activity was examined from pH 4.5-9.0 at pH 0.5 intervals at 45 
o C </p>

<p>under standard assay conditions (described in Materials and Methods) using acetate (pH 4.5-6.0) and phosphate buffer (pH 6.5-9.0). C. The </p>

<p>effect of thermostability on rAgaA at different temperatures at different time points. Thermostability was determined by measurement of residual </p>

<p>activity under standard assay conditions as described in Materials and Methods at temperatures between 40-55 
o C for 30, 60 and 120 min. D. The </p>

<p>effect of 2 mM CaCl 2 on thermostability of rAgaA. </p>

<p>885 </p>

<p>Oh, C. et al. 
Characterization of a novel -agarase from Psudoalteromonas sp. AG52 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>N o n e 
C a C l 2 
C u S O </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>E D T A 
F e S O </p>

<p>4 
K C l 
M 
g S O </p>

<p>4 
M 
n C l 2 
N a C l 
Z n S O 4 </p>

<p>Relative activity (%) --</p>

<p>* </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>*** 
*** 
*** </p>

<p>**** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>**** </p>

<p>Figure 6. The effects of metal ions and metal salts on the activity of purified rAgaA. Various ions or chelators (CaCl 2 , CuSO 4 , </p>

<p>FeSO 4 , KCl, MgSO 4 , MnCl 2 , NaCl and EDTA) at a final concentration of 2 mM were included in the reaction buffer to test the </p>

<p>activity of rAgaA at 45 
o C for 30 min. The data presented are the average of three replicates. Means with the same number of stars </p>

<p>are not significantly different at p&lt;0.05, based on ANOVA. Error bars represent + SD. </p>

<p>Identification of hydrolysis products of the rAgaA by TLC </p>

<p>Hydrolysis patterns of the purified rAgaA against food-</p>

<p>grade agar and neoagarohexanitol (NA6) are shown in Figure </p>

<p>7. When rAgaA was incubated with agar, two distinct spots </p>

<p>namely, NA6 and NA4 were observed on TLC plates at 30, 60 </p>

<p>and 120 min after the reaction. Furthermore, the distinct spot of </p>

<p>NA4 was observed when rAgaA was incubated with NA6. </p>

<p>Figure 7. TLC of hydrolysis products of the </p>

<p>purified rAgaA on food-grade agar and neoagaro-</p>

<p>oligosaccharides. The assay of rAgaA and agar </p>

<p>were performed in 200 l reactions containing 20 </p>

<p>L of purified agarase and 180 L of 1% agar at 45 </p>

<p>o C for 30, 60, and 120 min. The NA6 substrate was </p>

<p>incubated with 20 µl of rAgaA separately at 45 
o C </p>

<p>for 
120 
min. 
Neoagarohexaitol 
(NA6), </p>

<p>neoagarotetraose (NA4), neoagarobiose (NA2) and </p>

<p>D-(+)-galactose (G) were used as standards (STD). </p>

<p>886 </p>

<p>Oh, C. et al. 
Characterization of a novel -agarase from Psudoalteromonas sp. AG52 </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, a newly found marine bacterial isolate was </p>

<p>assigned to the genus Pseudoalteromonas based on the 16S </p>

<p>rDNA sequence analysis. We report herein the cloning and </p>

<p>sequencing of the -agarase gene with -agarase activity from </p>

<p>Pseudoalteromonas sp. AG52, which has greater identity to the </p>

<p>Aeromonas 
-agarase 
coding 
sequence 
than 
the </p>

<p>Pseudoalteromonas sp. -agarase coding sequence in the NCBI </p>

<p>Genbank. It was shown in this study that agaA was genetically </p>

<p>closely related to the GHF-16 -agarases, and hence this gene </p>

<p>should be classified into the GHF-16 family. The primary </p>

<p>structure of the Pseudoalteromonas sp. AG52 -agarase shows </p>

<p>regions homologous to GHF-16 family members, which </p>

<p>include catalytic domains belonging to GHF-16, which </p>

<p>hydrolyze the internal -1,4-linkage of agar, producing </p>

<p>neoagarooligosaccharides. BLASTP and pairwise analysis of </p>

<p>agaA full length coding sequence with other agarases which </p>

<p>belong to the GHF-16 family showed overall sequence </p>

<p>identities ranging from 24-97%. Some of the -agarases encode </p>

<p>for a modular protein consisting of a signal peptide, catalytic </p>

<p>module and C-terminal domain of unknown function or a </p>

<p>carbohydrate binding module (1, 35), and this may be the </p>

<p>reason for having low identity, even within the same family. It </p>

<p>has been reported that homologous regions in most of the </p>

<p>reported GHF-16 agarases were present in catalytic module of </p>

<p>the -agarases (1). This further confirms the heterogeneity of </p>

<p>the amino acid sequences in length, catalytic properties and </p>

<p>substrate specificities in agarases. Furthermore, the results of </p>

<p>the phylogenetic analysis support the idea that many -agarases </p>

<p>may have evolved from a common ancestral form, and, that </p>

<p>domain shuffling may contribute significantly to the diversity </p>

<p>of the agarases (7,10). Even though the protein is divergent </p>

<p>from the primary sequences, AgaA features strictly conserved </p>

<p>catalytic residues, which show conservation among the GHF-</p>

<p>16 family members. Glutamic and aspartic acid are the highly </p>

<p>conserved active site residues, which are responsible for </p>

<p>catalytic activity in the GHF (30). According to previous </p>

<p>reports (1, 31), the conserved Glu 
148 and Glu 
153 are responsible </p>

<p>for acting as the nucleophile and the acidic/basic residues, </p>

<p>respectively, in AgaA. The third conserved acidic residue at </p>

<p>Asp 
150 , is responsible for maintaining the charges in the </p>

<p>environment of catalytic amino acids. The lipoprotein signal </p>

<p>peptide is one of the secretion systems reported for gram </p>

<p>negative bacteria (40) and such a signal was predicted in the </p>

<p>AgaA sequence at the N-terminal where Cys 
16 may be linked to </p>

<p>the lipid moiety. However, in this study, the cleavage of N-</p>

<p>terminal hydrophobic segment is by either signal peptidase I or </p>

<p>signal peptidase II is not known clearly and remains to be </p>

<p>elucidated. Using pET16b, intracellular AgaA was expressed </p>

<p>efficiently and purified as a fusion protein. The purified </p>

<p>agarase had a molecular mass of 33 kDa, which is close to </p>

<p>those reported for -agarases from Pseudoalteromonas sp. N-1 </p>

<p>(33 kDa) (48) and Pseudomonas atlantica (32 kDa) (33); but, </p>

<p>smaller than agarases reported for Alteromonas sp. (52 kDa) </p>

<p>(29) and Pseudomonas sp. W7 (59 kDa) (17); and, larger than </p>

<p>agarases reported for Vibrio sp. AP-2 (20kDa) (2). AgaA </p>

<p>hydrolyzes agar to give NA6 and NA4 as the main products, </p>

<p>suggesting that the enzyme is a -agarase, in accordance with </p>

<p>most of the reported GHF-16 -agarases (1, 43). </p>

<p>Generally, most of the GHF-16 -agarases that have been </p>

<p>characterized so far, have optimal function at 40 
o C and pH </p>

<p>optimums in the range of neutral to mild alkaline (50). rAgaA </p>

<p>has an optimum temperature (55 
o C) that is higher than the </p>

<p>gelling temperature of agar (40 
o C) with broad range of pH. </p>

<p>These are properties which are useful for the production of </p>

<p>industrially important oligosaccharides from marine algae or </p>

<p>agar. These findings are in contrast with earlier reported pH </p>

<p>and temperature optima at 7 and 30 
o C, respectively, for a </p>

<p>purified -agarase from Pseudoalteromonas sp. (48). A </p>

<p>temperature optimum at 40 
o C and a pH optimum of 6.0 have </p>

<p>been reported for recombinant 
-agarase AgaB from </p>

<p>Pseudoalteromonas sp. CY24 (30). In contrast to the </p>

<p>experimentally determined optimum temperature of rAgaA </p>

<p>activity, thermal stability profiles of this protein showed that </p>

<p>the enzyme is stable under 45 
o C even after 30 min incubation, </p>

<p>however, it becomes inactivated at higher temperatures. The </p>

<p>enzyme at 40 
o C retained 50% activity even after 1 h of </p>

<p>887 </p>

<p>Oh, C. et al. 
Characterization of a novel -agarase from Psudoalteromonas sp. AG52 </p>

<p>incubation, indicating that this enzyme might be used under </p>

<p>mild heating conditions. In addition, the enzyme stability was </p>

<p>considerably enhanced in the presence of CaCl 2 , and enzyme </p>

<p>retained more than 15% of its initial activity after 1 and 2 h of </p>

<p>incubation with CaCl 2 . Several published studies support these </p>

<p>results, where a major role is proposed for Ca 
2+ in stabilization </p>

<p>of enzymes at higher temperatures (18, 21). It was reported that </p>

<p>the reason for this may be due to the strengthening of </p>

<p>interactions inside the protein molecule, and probably by the </p>

<p>binding of Ca 
2+ to an autolysis site (8, 26). It has been reported </p>

<p>that a catalytic module of -agarase ( -AgaA_CM) of Z. </p>

<p>galactetanivorans Dsij, had Ca 
2+ bound on the convex face of </p>

<p>the protein in an octahedral geometry, coordinating with the </p>

<p>backbone carbonyl oxygen atoms of Ser 
47 , Ser 
91 , and Asp 
279 , a </p>

<p>carboxylate oxygen of Asp 
279 , Asn 
49 , and Asp 
22 , and one water </p>

<p>molecule. In the -agarase ( -AgaB) of Z. galactetanivorans </p>

<p>Dsij, the Ca 
2+ was positioned in the same locations in a </p>

<p>pentahedral manner to the backbone carbonyl oxygen atom of </p>

<p>Asn 
83 , Gly 
127 , and Asp 
343 , a carboxylate oxygen of Asp 
343 , and </p>

<p>one water molecule (1). Interestingly, in AG52, the Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>binding residues were located at the same positions at Gln 
47 , </p>

<p>Gly </p>

<p>91 </p>

<p>and Asp 
282 , however, the precise geometrical </p>

<p>arrangement of Ca 
2+ binding needs to be investigated in future. </p>

<p>In addition, analysis of the amino acid sequence for agaA </p>

<p>confirms the evidence that the Asp, which is responsible for </p>

<p>side-chain interaction with Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>, is conserved among the GHF-</p>

<p>16 family members (1). Moreover, among the metal ions, </p>

<p>which are mainly present in seawater (Na </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, Mg </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>, K 
+ and Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>), </p>

<p>K 
+ shows considerable effect on rAgaA activity, suggesting </p>

<p>that the red algae is originating from the marine environment. </p>

<p>It is possible that the reason that Zn 
2+ has an inhibitory effect </p>

<p>on rAgaA might be the structural alteration of the enzyme due </p>

<p>to the affinity of the heavy metals for the SH, CO and NH </p>

<p>moieties of the amino acids in the protein. </p>

<p>In conclusion, a marine bacterium Pseudoalteromonas sp. </p>

<p>was isolated from red algae in the Jeju island (Korea) coastal </p>

<p>environment. AgaA features homologous catalytic domains </p>

<p>belonging to the GHF-16 family, and has characteristic </p>

<p>properties indicating neoagarooligosaccharide production. Due </p>

<p>to 
the 
reported 
functional 
properties 
of 
the </p>

<p>neoagarooligosaccharides (25) when obtained from agar, the </p>

<p>purified r rAgaA enzyme has potential for usage in industries </p>

<p>for the production of pharmaceuticals and cosmetics. To </p>

<p>further advance the research, the crystal structure and three-</p>

<p>dimensional structure analyses need to be carried out in order </p>

<p>to understand the mechanism of the catalysis of rAgaA in </p>

<p>detail, and thereby investigate the structure-function </p>

<p>relationships of the protein. Since no primary structural and </p>

<p>functional characteristics have been reported for Aeromonas -</p>

<p>agarases to date, the current investigation will be useful for </p>

<p>studying the structure, function and evolution of Aeromonas -</p>

<p>agarase as well. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This research was financially supported by the Ministry of </p>

<p>Education, Science Technology (MEST) and Korea Industrial </p>

<p>Technology Foundation (KOTEF) through the Human </p>

<p>Resource Training Project for Regional Innovation, and by a </p>

<p>research grant (PE98472) from Korea Ocean Research &amp; </p>

<p>Development Institute. </p>







</text></tei>