<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3371588" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>, are relieved by completely different ways. To find out how the 
instabilities of the unusual oxidation states of the transition-metal ions in oxides are relieved, we made solid 
solution of CaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 and LaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 and investigated their temperature-dependent transitions. </p>

<p>Results 
Each solid-solution sample was confirmed by synchrotron X-ray diffraction (XRD) data (see Supplementary Fig. 
S1) to be a single phase at high temperatures and to be crystallized with a cubic Im-3 A-site-ordered double-
perovskite structure. Oxygen off-stoichiometry was not detected in the Rietveld structure refinements, and 
the refined occupancies for Ca and La at the A site were within 2% of those corresponding to the designed </p>

<p>composition Ca 12x La x Cu 3 Fe 4 O 12 (see Supplementary Fig. S1 and 
Supplementary Table S1 for the refinement results). When changing 
the A-site composition x the lattice constant at 450 K changes line-
arly in accordance with Vegard's law (Fig. 2a). No superlattice 
reflection was observed in the diffraction patterns, suggesting the 
absence of any extra ordering in the solid solution. Each 
Mössbauer spectrum at high temperatures showed a paramagnetic 
singlet component (Fig. 3), further confirming that each of the sam-
ples consisted of a single-phase solid solution. Note that the isomer 
shift values of the Mössbauer spectra of the paramagnetic states at 
400 K gradually increase with increasing x (see Supplementary Fig. 
S2), suggesting that the Fe oxidation state decreases slightly. 
Furthermore, the bond valence sums (BVS) of Fe at 450 K, which 
are obtained from the structure refinements, gradually decrease with 
increasing x while those of Cu remain unchanged (Fig. 2b). The 
results suggest that electrons are doped into the Fe site instead of 
the Cu site by the La 
31 substitution for Ca 
21 at the A site. Thus, as 
we expected from the end compositions, the ionic formula of a </p>

<p>solid-solution sample at high temperature can be described as 
(Ca </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>12x La </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>x )Cu </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>3 Fe </p>

<p>(42x/4)1 </p>

<p>4 O 12 . 
For CaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 (x 5 0.0) a phase transition at 210 K is evident 
in the temperature dependence of the lattice parameter (Fig. 2c), and 
below that temperature very weak superstructure peaks, indicating 
rock-salt-type B-site ordering, were observed in the synchrotron 
XRD patterns. The ferrimagnetic transition (Fig. 4) and the metal-
to-insulator transition (see Supplementary Fig. S3), together with the 
change in the Mössbauer spectra (Fig. 3a), confirm that the B-site CD 
occurs at 210 K, as we reported previously </p>

<p>19,21   . In the other end 
compound LaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 (x 5 1.0), a first-order isostructural phase 
transition takes place at 393 K, as shown by the large increase of the 
lattice parameter with decreasing temperature (Fig. 2c). At the trans-
ition temperature the Fe-O bond length increases significantly 
whereas the Cu-O bond length decreases, decreasing the BVS for 
Fe and increasing it for Cu. From the Mössbauer spectra shown in 
Fig. 3b, one can infer that above the transition temperature there is a 
paramagnetic component of unusual high-valence Fe that has an 
isomer shift of &lt;0.17 mm s 
21 and that at 300 K there is a single 
component of magnetically ordered Fe </p>

<p>31   . In addition, the compound 
changes from a high-temperature paramagnetic metal to a low-tem-
perature antiferromagnetic insulator at the phase transition (Fig. 4 
and Supplementary Fig. S3). Thus it is concluded that the compound 
changes from a high-temperature La </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>Cu </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>3 Fe </p>

<p>3.751 </p>

<p>4 O 12 phase to a 
low-temperature La </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>Cu </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>3 Fe </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>4 O 12 phase as a result of the intersite 
CT between the A'-site Cu and B-site Fe. No CD behavior, either that 
shown by CaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 or the more complicated one shown by 
La 12x Sr x FeO 32d </p>

<p>22-24   , is seen in LaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 </p>

<p>20,25   . 
The temperature dependence of the XRD patterns of the 
Ca 3/4 La 1/4 Cu 3 Fe 4 O 12 sample (x 5 1/4) shows electronic phase 
separation below 210 K (Supplementary Fig. S4). The large increase 
in the lattice parameter at 210 K with decreasing temperature indi-
cates the appearance of the CT phase (Fig. 2c). On the other hand, 
the temperature dependence of the magnetic susceptibility shows a 
behavior similar to that shown by CaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 , namely a sharp 
ferrimagnetic increase below &lt;210 K but with a lower magnetiza-
tion (Fig. 4) indicative of the CD transition. These are consis-
tent with the Mössbauer spectrum at 4 K shown in Fig. 3c, which 
consists of a pair of Fe 
31 /Fe 
51 (29.6%/28.5%) components for the </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Crystal structure of the A-site-ordered double-perovskite 
AA' 3 B 4 O 12 . The A, A', B, and O atoms are respectively represented by 
green, purple, blue, and red spheres. The atom positions in the cubic Im-3 
(No. 204) symmetry are A at the 2a site (0, 0, 0), A' at the 6b site (0, 1/2, 
1/2), B at the 8c site (1/4, 1/4, 1/4), and at O at the 24g site (x, y, 0), where 
x &lt; 0.30 and y &lt; 0.17. </p>

<p>7.40 </p>

<p>7.35 </p>

<p>7.30 </p>

<p>7.25 
Lattice parameter / Å </p>

<p>500 
400 
300 
200 
100 </p>

<p>Temperature / K </p>

<p>x = 1.0 </p>

<p>x = 3/4 </p>

<p>x = 1/2 </p>

<p>x = 1/4 </p>

<p>x = 0.0 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>7.40 </p>

<p>7.36 </p>

<p>7.32 </p>

<p>7.28 
Lattice parameter / Å </p>

<p>T = 450 K </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>3.8 
3.6 
3.4 </p>

<p>Composition x </p>

<p>2.4 
2.2 
2.0 
Cu BVS Fe BVS </p>

<p>0.0 
1/4 
1/2 
3/4 1.0 </p>

<p>T = 450 K </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Composition and temperature dependences of the lattice parameter of the Ca 12x La x Cu 3 Fe 4 O 12 solid solution. (a) Lattice parameters of the </p>

<p>high-temperature phases at 450 K plotted as a function of composition x. The linear change follows Vegard's law, confirming that the samples are solid 
solutions. (b) BVS changes for Fe (blue) at the B site and Cu (green) at the A' site in the high-temperature phase of the Ca 12x La x Cu 3 Fe 4 O 12 solid solution. 
BVS was calculated from the results of the structure refinements for the synchrotron XRD data obtained at 450 K. (c) Temperature dependence of lattice 
parameters of solid-solution samples. Data shown by closed symbols were obtained from synchrotron XRD and data shown by open symbols were 
obtained from laboratory XRD with Mo and Cu sources. The square, circle and triangle markers represent the high-temperature, charge-transferred and 
charge-disproportionated phases, respectively. Negative (Da , 0 with increasing T) and positive (Da . 0 with increasing T) thermal-expansion-like 
changes respectively indicate intersite CT and the CD transitions. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 449 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00449 </p>

<p>
charge-disproportionated phase and a magnetic ordered Fe 
31 com-
ponent (41.9%) for the phase due to CT. It is thus clear that below 
210 K phases due to CD and CT coexist. 
When the further La-doped Ca 1/2 La 1/2 Cu 3 Fe 4 O 12 (x 5 1/2) is 
cooled its lattice parameter increases sharply at 280 K (Fig. 2c), sug-
gesting the occurrence of CT. Note that at low temperatures its 
diffraction peaks are rather broad (Supplementary Fig. S4). In the 
magnetic susceptibility data, a sharp decrease is found at 280 K, also 
indicating a CT transition like that in LaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 . When the sam-
ple was further cooled, a CD-like increase was seen near 210 K, 
although the magnetization is more than an order of magnitude 
lower than that of CaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 at low temperatures (Fig. 4). The 
Mössbauer spectra change accordingly with decreasing tempera-
ture (Fig. 3d). A single paramagnetic component is seen at high 
temperatures, and in the spectrum at 228 K a sextet (82%) origin-
ating from magnetically ordered Fe 
31 is seen in addition to the 
high-temperature singlet (18%). At 4 K the high-temperature singlet 
changes to a Fe </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>/Fe 
51 sextet pair (refined area of each component: 
12.8%/11.9%), confirming that CD occurs in roughly 25% of the 
sample. 
For Ca 1/4 La 3/4 Cu 3 Fe 4 O 12 (x 5 3/4) the changes in the temper-
ature-dependence of the XRD patterns (Supplementary Fig. S4) 
and the lattice parameters derived from them (Fig. 2c) indicate that 
intersite CT transition occurs around 330 K. In the Mössbauer spec-
tra a paramagnetic component of high-valence Fe with an isomer </p>

<p>shift 0.12 mm s 
21 is seen at 400 K, while a single component from 
magnetically ordered Fe 
31 is seen at 4 K, suggesting that most of the 
sample undergoes a CT transition (Fig. 3e). These CT behaviors are 
consistent with the observed sharp decrease in the magnetic suscept-
ibility (Fig. 4) and the large increase in the resistivity below 330 K 
(Supplementary Fig. S3). Although a very minor CD-like transition 
around 210 K is seen in the magnetic susceptibility measurement, 
the charge-disproportionated phase is not as evident in the Möss-
bauer spectra and the XRD patterns. 
A compositional phase diagram of the Ca 12x La x Cu 3 Fe 4 O 12 solid 
solution is derived from all the experimental results described 
above and is shown in Fig. 5. For CaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 (x 5 0.0) a CD 
transition is seen at 210 K. For x 5 1/4 both CD and CT transi-
tions are seen at almost the same temperature, &lt;210 K, where 
about 60% of the sample shows CD while the other 40% shows 
CT. For x 5 1/2, around 280 K CT occurs on cooling in about 75% 
of the sample and the other 25% remains in the high-temperature 
state with unusually high-valence Fe. The remaining high-temper-
ature phase then undergoes CD at 210 K, which is the same as the 
CD transition temperature for the x 5 0.0 sample. Below this 
temperature, phases due to CD and CT coexist. For x 5 3/4 the 
CT transition occurs around 330 K in most of the sample and a 
very minor charge-disproportionated phase appears below 210 K. 
And for LaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 (x 5 1.0), only CT transition is observed at 
393 K. In summary, the intersite CT transition temperatures (T CT ) </p>

<p>Transmission </p>

<p>-10 
0 
10 </p>

<p>x = 1/4 </p>

<p>400 K </p>

<p>300 K </p>

<p>4 K </p>

<p>Fe </p>

<p>3+ </p>

<p>Fe </p>

<p>3+ </p>

<p>Fe </p>

<p>5+ </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>-10 
0 
10 </p>

<p>x = 1/2 </p>

<p>400 K </p>

<p>300 K </p>

<p>4 K </p>

<p>Fe </p>

<p>3+ </p>

<p>Fe </p>

<p>3+ </p>

<p>Fe </p>

<p>5+ </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>-10 
0 
10 </p>

<p>x = 3/4 </p>

<p>400 K </p>

<p>300 K </p>

<p>4 K </p>

<p>Fe </p>

<p>3+ </p>

<p>Fe </p>

<p>3+ </p>

<p>Transmission </p>

<p>-10 
0 
10 </p>

<p>x = 1.0 </p>

<p>423 K </p>

<p>300 K </p>

<p>Fe </p>

<p>3+ </p>

<p>Transmission </p>

<p>-10 
0 
10 
Velocity / mm s </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>Velocity / mm s </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>Velocity / mm s </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>x = 0.0 </p>

<p>300 K </p>

<p>4 K </p>

<p>Fe </p>

<p>3+ </p>

<p>Fe </p>

<p>5+ </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>b 
a </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Mössbauer spectra of the Ca 12x La x Cu 3 Fe 4 O 12 solid solution at selected temperatures. The observed spectra and fitting curves are represented </p>

<p>by dots and solid lines, respectively. The high-temperature spectra shown in red have a single component due to paramagnetic high-valence Fe, and each 
the low-temperature spectrum shown in blue is a magnetically ordered Fe 
31 sextet originating from the phase due to CT. The spectra shown in orange and 
green are respectively those of charge-disproportionated Fe 
31 and Fe 
51 . Note that the spectrum weights of Fe 
31 and Fe 
51 in the charge-disproportionated 
phase are always close to 151. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 449 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00449 </p>

<p>
in the solid solution samples increase with increasing La doping 
(i.e., with increasing x), while the CD transition temperatures 
(T CD ) do not change from that of CaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 . </p>

<p>Discussion 
Note again that at high temperatures each solid-solution sample is a 
single phase and that the A-site substitution of La 
31 for Ca 
21 causes 
electron doping at the B-site Fe. Nevertheless, the electronic phase 
separation in the samples with the intermediate compositions is clearly 
seen at low temperatures. For x 5 1/2, for example, the high-temper-
ature phase can be described as ACu </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>3 Fe </p>

<p>3.8751 </p>

<p>4 O 12 , and the CT trans-
ition at 330 K changes some portion of the sample to ACu </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>3 Fe </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>4 O 12 , 
leaving the remaining portion of the sample to be a phase with 
unusually high-valence Fe. In a simple ionic model, this change can 
be described as ACu </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>3 Fe </p>

<p>3.8751 </p>

<p>4 O 12 R 50%ACu </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>3 Fe </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>4 O 12 1 
50%ACu </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>3 Fe </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>4 O 12 . Although such an electronic phase-separation 
behavior seems to be uncommon, we could never observe a transition 
of the whole sample, such as a CT-like ACu </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>3 Fe </p>

<p>3.8751 </p>

<p>4 O 12 R 
ACu </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>3 Fe </p>

<p>3.1251 </p>

<p>4 O 12 transition or a CD-like ACu </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>3 Fe </p>

<p>3.8751 </p>

<p>4 O 12 R 
ACu </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>3 Fe </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>2.25 Fe </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>1.75 O 12 transition. Further decreasing temperature 
induces the CD transition for the ACu </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>3 Fe </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>4 O 12 portion at 210 K, 
where ACu </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>3 Fe </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>2 Fe </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>2 O 12 is stabilized. Although the observed frac-
tions of the CT and CD phases (75%/25%) determined from the areas of 
the Mössbauer spectra measured at 4 K are rather different from the 
50%/50% fractions predicted by the simple ionic model, they are reas-
onably close to the predicted ones. An important point is that the 
Fe </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>:Fe 
51 ratios in the CD phases are always close to 151. 
Furthermore, none of the T CD of the samples changes with composition 
x, suggesting that the observed CD transitions are essentially the same in 
the entire solid solution. The XRD peak broadening seen at low tem-
peratures strongly suggests that the domains of the phases due to CD 
and CT coexist on a microscopic scale. 
Why are the instabilities of these unusual oxidation states of Fe 
relieved in different ways? And why do we see both the CD and CT 
transitions in a single-phase sample? As discussed in previous reports 
on some specific oxides, high-oxidation-state transition-metal ions 
like Fe, Co, Ni, and Cu have very low-lying 3d levels, and the covalent 
electronic states due to the strong hybridization of 3d and oxygen 2p 
orbitals produce oxygen p holes (ligand holes) </p>

<p>26-35   . Thus, realistic 
electronic pictures of the unusual Fe 
41 , Fe 
51 , and Cu 
31 states can 
respectively be described as d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>L, d 
5 L </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, and d 
9 L, where L represent a 
ligand hole. Indeed, unlike the isoelectric Mn 
31 (t 2g 
3 e g </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>), Fe 
41 (d 
4 ) 
with octahedral oxygen coordination does not show Jahn-Teller dis-
tortion. With the ligand-hole picture, CD in CaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 is 
expressed as (4d 
5 L R 2d 
5 1 2d 
5 L </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>), similar to that in CaFeO 3 . The 
transition is regarded as a redistribution of the ligand holes in the Fe 
sites, making the Fe-O bonds alternately shorter and longer in a rock-
salt-type manner (Fig. 6a). The rock-salt-type ordering should con-
tribute to minimizing the lattice energy and stabilizing the CD phase. 
Because at high temperatures the ligand holes are itinerant, as we see 
in the metallic conductivity, the CD transition in CaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 can 
be regarded as the localization of the ligand holes at the Fe sites, 
or in other words, as a charge ordering of the ligand holes. In 
LaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 , on the other hand, the CT between the A'-site Cu ions 
and the B-site Fe ions is mediated by the transfer of ligand holes (3d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>1 4d 
5 L 
0.75 R 3d 
9 L 1 4d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>) from the Fe site to the Cu site (Fig. 6c). This 
ligand-hole transfer is also linked to the lattice change with the iso-
tropic volume expansion. Since the charge transferred phase is insu-
lating, the intersite CT transition can also be regarded as the 
localization of the ligand holes at the Cu site. Since the observed 
metal-to-insulator transition is caused by the localization of an 
odd number of itinerant ligand holes without breaking the cubic 
structural symmetry, it can be regarded as a Mott transition of the 
igand holes. It is clear that the difference between the CD and CT 
transitions is only the localization site of the ligand holes, so the 
energy difference between them should not be significant. This also 
explains why the charge-disproportionated and the charge-trans-
ferred phases coexist in the solid solution. 
At high temperatures the ligand holes in the solid solution are 
homogeneously distributed at the Fe sites like d 
5 L 
d (d 5 12x/4) </p>

<p>6.0 </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>4.0 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>M/H / emu mol </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>M/H / emu mol </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>500 
400 
300 
200 
100 
0 
Temperature / K </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.00 
500 
400 
300 
200 
Temperature / K </p>

<p>x = 0.0 
x = 1/4 
x = 1/2 
x = 3/4 
x = 1.0 </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Temperature dependence of the magnetic susceptibility of the </p>

<p>Ca 12x La x Cu 3 Fe 4 O 12 solid solution. The samples were zero-field cooled 
and the measurements were made under a 1 T external magnetic field. The 
large increase in magnetization at 210 K indicates the ferrimagnetic 
transition accompanying the CD transition. The inset shows the magnified 
view of temperature dependence of the magnetic susceptibility of samples 
with x 5 1/2, 3/4 and 1.0. The decrease in magnetic susceptibility is the 
result of antiferromagnetism due to the intersite CT transition. </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Compositional phase diagram for the Ca 12x La x Cu 3 Fe 4 O 12 </p>

<p>solid solution. At high temperatures the whole solid solution is a single 
phase. Different charge behaviors are seen in the end-composition 
compounds: CD in CaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 (x 5 0.0) and intersite CT in 
LaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 (x 5 1.0). In the intermediate-composition samples, phases 
due to both CD and CT coexist at low temperatures. With increasing 
ligand-hole concentration d (decreasing La substitution at the A site), T CT 
decreases but T CD remains constant. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 449 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00449 </p>

<p>
and they are itinerant. When temperature decreases, the ligand holes 
lose kinetic energy and become unstable, resulting in the localization. 
The instability of the itinerant ligand holes is first relieved by trans-
ferring the ligand holes from the Fe site to the Cu site, and the 
localization at the Cu site produces the d 
9 L state. This also explains 
the change of the T CT in the solid solution. Because the ligand-hole 
concentration d increases with decreasing x, the high-temperature 
state with a higher concentration of the itinerant holes is more stable 
over a wider temperature range and thus the T CT decreases. The Cu </p>

<p>21   counter cation in the A-site-ordered perovskite-structure oxide plays 
a crucial role in accepting the ligand holes. It is also interesting that 
the CT transition in the intermediate compositions does not occur in 
the whole sample but leaves some portion (domains) with itinerant 
ligand holes at the Fe site, causing an electronic phase separation. 
With further decreasing temperature, the instability of the remaining 
itinerant ligand holes is relieved by CD in which the d 
5 /d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>L 
2 states are 
ordered alternately (Fig. 6b). In the higher ligand-hole-concentration 
region (0.0 # x # 1/4), T CT is lower than (or almost the same as) T CD , 
and thus the CT is not observed. 
In conclusion, the unusual high-valence Fe ions are stabilized in 
the high-pressure synthesized A-site-ordered perovskite-structure 
Ca 12x La x Cu 3 Fe 4 O 12 solid-solution samples, and the end-composi-
tion compounds CaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 and LaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 display distinct 
charge behaviors, respectively charge disproportionation (CD) 
and intersite charge transfer (CT). Compounds with intermediate 
compositions first show intersite CT transition in part of the sample 
and then show CD in the rest of the sample. In this system, d orbitals 
of Fe at the B site and Cu at the A' site strongly hybridize with p 
orbitals of oxygen, producing ligand holes, and the distinct charge 
behaviors can be explained by the localization of the itinerant ligand 
holes at low temperatures. In the charge-disproportionated phase the 
ligand holes are localized at the Fe site and the transition is regarded 
as one to the rock-salt-type charge ordering of the ligand holes. The </p>

<p>CD transition is essentially the same in all solid-solution samples, so 
the T CD is same regardless of their La content. In the intersite CT, on 
the other hand, the ligand holes are localized at the Cu site and the 
transition can be regarded as a Mott transition of the ligand holes. 
T CT decreases with increasing concentration of the ligand-hole car-
riers. In the A-site-ordered perovskite-structure oxides, transition-
metals at both A' and B sites mediate A'-A', A'-B, and B-B interactions 
that lead to intriguing physical properties </p>

<p>36-41   . The ligand holes pro-
duced by the strong hybridization of transition-metal cation d orbi-
tals and oxygen p orbitals also play important roles in giving rise to 
various electronic and structural properties. The present A-site-
ordered perovskite-structure Ca 12x La x Cu 3 Fe 4 O 12 solid solution is 
a novel example exhibiting interplay of the interactions mediated 
by the ligand holes. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Polycrystalline samples of the A-site-ordered double-perovskite solid solution 
Ca 1-x La x Cu 3 Fe 4 O 12 (x 5 0.0, 1/4, 1/2, 3/4 and 1.0) were prepared, at 15 GPa and 
1300 K, from stoichiometric amounts of Ca 2 Fe 2 O 5 , La 2 O 3 , CuO, Fe 2 O 3 , and the 
oxidizing agent KClO 4 by using a multianvil press. Synchrotron XRD patterns at 
temperatures between 100 and 450 K were collected at beamline BL02B2, SPring-8, 
Japan, with wavelength 0.7737405 Å , and the profiles were analyzed with Rietveld 
method by using the <rs type="software">General Structure Analysis System</rs> (GSAS) software package </p>

<p>42,43   . 
The XRD patterns at temperatures between 80 and 400 K were also collected using a 
Rigaku RINT diffractometer with a Mo and a Cu source. Magnetic susceptibility, 
magnetization, and electric conductivity were measured using a Quantum Design 
Magnetic Properties Measurement System (MPMS) and Quantum Design Physical 
Properties Measurement System (PPMS). The 
57 Fe Mössbauer spectra were obtained 
in transmission geometry in combination with a constant-acceleration spectrometer 
using </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>Co/Rh as a radiation source. a-Fe was used as a control for velocity calibration 
and isomer shift. The obtained spectra were fitted by a least-squares method with 
Lorentzian functions. </p>

<p>1. Jette, E. R. &amp; Foote, F. An X-ray study of the wüstite (FeO) solid solutions. J. Chem. 
Phys. 1, 29-36 (1933). </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d 
5 L </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d 
5 L </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>L 
d 
9 L 
d 
9 L </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>L 
d 
9 L 
d 
9 L </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>d 
9 L 
d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>L 
d 
9 L 
d 
9 L 
d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>L 
L 
L 
L 
L 
L </p>

<p>0.875 </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>0.875 </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>0.875 </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>0.875 </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>0.875 </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>L 
L </p>

<p>Temperature / K </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 a 
b 
c </p>

<p>Phase ratio </p>

<p>Figure 6 | Ligand-hole localization model of charge disproportionation and intersite charge-transfer transition behaviors. At high temperatures the </p>

<p>ligand holes L are homogeneously distributed at the Fe sites, and here the ligand-hole concentration increases from (c) to (a). (a) The CD (4Fe 
41 R 2Fe </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>1 2Fe </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>) at 210 K in CaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 is described as 4d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>L R 2d 
5 1 2d 
5 L 
2 and can be regarded as the localization of the ligand holes at the Fe site (charge 
ordering of L). (c) The intersite CT (3Cu 
21 1 4Fe 
3.751 R 3Cu 
31 1 4Fe </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>) at 393 K in LaCu 3 Fe 4 O 12 is described as 3d 
9 1 4d </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>L 
0.75 R 3d </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>L 1 4d 
5 and can be 
regarded as the localization of the ligand holes at the Cu site (a Mott transition of L). (b) In the intermediate-composition samples (e.g., x 5 1/2), with 
decreasing temperature the ligand holes are first localized at the Cu site by making CT-phase domains (about 75% of the sample). When temperature 
decreases further, the ligand holes in the other portion (25%) of the sample are localized at the Fe site, making CD-phase domains. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 449 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00449 </p>



<p>
Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Y. W. Long and M. Azuma for help in high-pressure synthesis experiments, H. 
Sawa and E. Nishibori for helping in the temperature-dependent XRD measurements at 
Nagoya University, and J. Kim and N. Tsuji for their help with synchrotron XRD 
measurements at BL02B2 in SPring-8. We are also grateful to Z. Hiroi for discussion. This 
work was supported in part by a Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research 19GS0207, by the 
Global Centers of Excellence Program ''International Center for Integrated Research and 
Advanced Education in Materials Science,'' and by a grant for the Project of Integrated 
Research on Chemical Synthesis from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science 
and Technology of Japan. The work was also supported by the Japan Science and 
Technology Agency's CREST program. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>W.-T. C. and Y. S. conceived and designed the study. W.-T. C. and T. S. prepared the 
samples and measured the structural and physical properties. N. H. performed the 
Mössbauer experiments. All of the authors contributed to the interpretation and discussion 
of the experimental results. W.-T. C, T. S. and Y. S. wrote the manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>License: This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivative Works 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy 
of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Chen, W.-T., Saito, T., Hayashi, N., Takano, M. &amp; Shimakawa, Y. 
Ligand-hole localization in oxides with unusual valence Fe. Sci. Rep. 2, 449; DOI:10.1038/ 
srep00449 (2012). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 449 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00449 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>