<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3569118" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: Agonists of α7-nicotinic acetylcholine receptors (nAChRs) have been developed as potential therapeutic drugs for 
neuropsychiatric diseases such as schizophrenia and Alzheimer's disease. Positron emission tomography (PET) is a noninvasive 
brain imaging technique to measure receptor occupancy in the living human brain. Although much effort has been expended 
to create specific PET radioligands for α7-nAChRs in the brain, only 4-[ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]methylphenyl-1,4-diazabicyclo[3.2.2.]non-
ane-4-carboxylate ([ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001) is currently available for clinical studies. In contrast, two 5-hydroxytryptamine-3 (5-HT3) 
receptor antagonists, tropisetron and ondansetron, have been used to treat patients with chemotherapy-induced or postoperative 
nausea and vomiting. Furthermore, tropisetron, but not ondansetron, possesses high affinity for α7-nAChRs. In the present 
study, we evaluated the receptor occupancy in the human brain after a single oral administration of tropisetron and ondansetron 
using [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001 and PET. 
Methods: Two serial dynamic PET scans using [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001 in healthy non-smoking male subjects were performed before 
and after receiving an oral administration of these medications. 
Results: A single oral administration of tropisetron, but not ondansetron, decreased the total distribution volume of [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-
1001 in the human brain. 
Conclusion: This study shows that tropisetron, but not ondansetron, could bind to α7-nAChRs in the human brain after a single 
oral administration. Therefore, [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001 may be a useful PET radioligand to measure the occupancy of α7-nAChRs in 
the human brain. </p>

<p>The main subtypes of nicotinic acetylcholine receptors 
(nAChRs) in the central nervous system are the α4β2 
and α7 subtypes. α7-nAChRs have lower affinity for 
acetylcholine compared with α4β2 nAChRs 
1) and dem-</p>

<p>onstrate a high capacity for calcium influx that equals or 
exceeds N-methyl-D-aspartate receptors, suggesting its 
significant role in regulating a variety of downstream sig-
naling events. 
2) Accumulating evidence suggests that α7-</p>

<p>nAChRs play a role in the pathophysiology of several neu-</p>

<p>ropsychiatric diseases such as schizophrenia, Alzhei-
mer's disease, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, and 
Parkinson's disease. 
3-7) A number of pharmaceutical pro-</p>

<p>grams have been developing selective agonists and pos-
itive allosteric modulators of α7-nAChRs 
7-15) as potential </p>

<p>therapeutic drugs for these diseases. However, it is diffi-
cult to evaluate the potential dose regimens of these drugs 
for treating these diseases. 
Positron emission tomography (PET) is one of the brain 
imaging techniques that can measure biochemical and 
physiological information in the living human brain. The 
distribution and density of receptors in the living human 
brain can be visualized noninvasively by PET using re-
ceptor-specific radioligands, and the receptor-radioligand 
binding can be quantified by appropriate tracer kinetic 
models. 
16,17) Much effort has been devoted to visualize α7-</p>

<p>nAChRs in the human brain by PET, but the development </p>



<p>Table 1. Affinities of tropisetron and ondansetron at 5-HT3 re-
ceptors, α7-nAChRs, and α4β2nAChRs </p>

<p>Drugs 
Ki for 5-HT3 
receptors </p>

<p>Ki for 
α7-nAChRs </p>

<p>Ki for 
α4β2nAChRs </p>

<p>5.3 nM 
6.9 nM 
55,000 nM </p>

<p>12 nM 
＞10,000 nM 
46,000 nM </p>

<p>Data are from Reference. </p>

<p>31) </p>

<p>of specific radioligands that depict α7-nAChRs has been 
hampered by the relatively low levels of α7-nAChRs in 
the brain. 
18-20) Generally, α-bungarotoxin and methyl-</p>

<p>lycaconitine (MLA) are well known to be specific and po-
tent α7-nAChR antagonists, but due to their large molec-
ular weights, they have difficulty passing through the 
blood-brain barrier, which makes them unfavorable as 
PET radioligands. 
21-23) Consequently, a number of com-</p>

<p>pounds have been developed and evaluated as potential 
PET radioligands for α7-nAChRs. 
6,24) However, only </p>

<p>4-[ 
11 C]methylphenyl-1,4-diazabicyclo[3.2.2.]nonane-4-</p>

<p>carboxylate ([ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001) has been used in human 
studies. </p>

<p>25-27) </p>

<p>Potent 5-hydroxytryptamine-3 (5-HT 3 ) receptor antag-
onists such as tropisetron and ondansetron have been used 
to treat patients with chemotherapy-induced or post-
operative nausea and vomiting. 
28-30) Tropisetron is a parti-</p>

<p>al agonist of α7-nAChRs with high affinity (Ki=6.9 nM), 
whereas ondansetron has low affinity for α7-nAChRs 
(Ki＞10,000 nM) (Table 1). 
31,32) Both drugs lack affinity </p>

<p>for α4β2-nAChRs (Table 1). In the present study, we in-
vestigated whether a single administration of tropisetron 
or ondansetron would bind to α7-nAChRs in the intact 
human brain using [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001 and PET. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Subjects </p>

<p>This study was approved by the Ethics Committees of 
Tokyo Metropolitan Institute of Gerontology (Tokyo, 
Japan) and Chiba University Graduate School of Medi-</p>

<p>cine (Chiba, Japan). Twelve healthy non-smoking male 
volunteers participated in the study (mean age, 22.2 years; 
SD, 3.0; range, 20-31). Written informed consent was ob-
tained from each subject after the procedures had been 
fully explained. None of the subjects had any neurological 
or psychological findings, and none showed any abnor-
malities on the brain magnetic resonance imaging scan 
taken between the two PET scans. None had been receiv-
ing any medications of any kind, and none had a history of 
alcoholism. </p>

<p>[ 
11 C]CHIBA-1001 and PET </p>

<p>Each volunteer participated in two [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001-
PET scans, one before and one after oral administration of 
tropisetron or ondansetron. The second PET scan took 
place 3-3.5 hours after taking the medication to coincide 
with the peak plasma level. After oral administration of a 
single dose of tropisetron (5 mg), blood concentration 
reaches a peak in approximately 3.4 hours in healthy 
Japanese male subjects. 
33) Accordingly, we collected ve-</p>

<p>nous blood samples (except from one volunteer for techni-
cal reasons) just before tracer injection of the second PET 
scan to monitor the tropisetron concentration. Plasma tro-
pisetron concentration was measured by high perform-
ance liquid chromatography (HPLC) followed by tandem 
mass spectrometry. In the case of ondansetron, the second 
PET scan occurred 2 hours after administration, as the 
concentration in blood reaches its peak in approximately 2 
hours after oral administration of a single dose of ondanse-
tron (4 mg) in healthy Japanese male subjects. 
34) Volun-</p>

<p>teers were randomly administered either tropisetron (5, 
10, or 20 mg, n=3 for each dose; Navoban </p>

<p>Ⓡ </p>

<p>, Novartis 
Pharma KK, Tokyo, Japan) or ondansetron (8 mg, n=3; 
Zofran </p>

<p>Ⓡ </p>

<p>, GlaxoSmithKline KK, Tokyo, Japan). PET was 
performed at the Positron Medical Center, Tokyo Metro-
politan Institute of Gerontology with a SET 2400W scan-
ner (Shimadzu Co., Kyoto, Japan). 
35) The spatial reso-</p>

<p>lution was 4.4 mm full width at half maximum in the trans-
verse direction and 6.5 mm full width at half maximum in 
the axial direction. A transmission scan was performed 
with a rotating </p>

<p>68 </p>

<p>Ga/ </p>

<p>68 </p>

<p>Ge rod source for 5 minutes for atte-
nuation correction before the administration of [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-
1001, which was prepared as described previously. 
25) A </p>

<p>dynamic series of decay-corrected PET data acquisition 
data were collected in the two-dimensional mode for 90 
minutes starting at the time of the intravenous bolus in-
jection of [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001 (injected dose, 518±53 
MBq; specific activity, 42.7±22.6 TBq/mmol). The frame 
arrangement was 10 seconds×6 frames, 30 seconds×3 </p>

<p>Occupancy of α7-nAChRs in Human Brain by Tropisetron 113 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Total distribution volume (VT) 
images of [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001 positron 
emission tomography before and 
after single oral administration of 
tropisetron or ondansetron. The up-
per pair represents VT images at 
baseline (left) and at tropisetron (20 
mg)-loading (right) in the same 
subject. The lower pair shows VT 
images at baseline (left) and on-
dansetron (8 mg)-loading (right) in 
another subject. </p>

<p>frames, 60 seconds×5 frames, 150 seconds×5 frames, and 
300 seconds×14 frames. The dynamic image was recon-
structed with a filtered back-projection algorithm using a 
Butterworth filter (1.25 cycles/cm, order 2); the image 
matrix was 128×128×31, and the voxel size was 2×2×6.25 
mm. Each subject was placed in a supine position with 
eyes closed. Immediately after the bolus injection, 12 arte-
rial blood samples were collected at 10-second intervals 
over 2 minutes, and the remaining 14 samples were col-
lected at longer intervals, for a total of 26 samples. All 
samples were manually drawn. Plasma was separated, 
weighed and measured for radioactivity with a sodium-io-
dide well scintillation counter. Six samples collected at 3, 
10, 20, 30, 40, and 60 minutes were further processed by 
HPLC for metabolite analysis. </p>

<p>25) </p>

<p>Data Analysis </p>

<p>Image manipulations were performed using the "<rs id="software-0" type="software">Dr. 
View</rs>", <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 5.2</rs> medical image processing application 
package (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">AJS Inc.</rs>., Tokyo, Japan). Regions of interest 
(ROIs) were defined over the frontal, temporal, parietal, 
and occipital cortices, head of the caudate nucleus, puta-
men, and cerebellum with reference to a coregistered 
magnetic resonance image, which served as an anatomical 
guide. The total distribution volume (VT) of [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-
1001 was calculated from the regional time-activity curve 
and the metabolite-corrected input function using Logan 
graphical analysis. 
36,37) Blocking rates (%) by tropisetron </p>

<p>or ondansetron were calculated for each ROI as 100×[(V T 
at baseline−V T at loading)/V T at baseline]%. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Representative V T images of [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001 before 
and after tropisetron (20 mg) and ondansetron (8 mg) 
loading are shown in Fig. 1. Radioactivity in the human 
brain after intravenous administration of [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-
1001 was widely distributed throughout, consistent with 
our previous report using postmortem human brain 
tissues. 
38) A single administration of 20 mg tropisetron de-</p>

<p>creased the VT of [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C] CHIBA-1001 in the brain (Fig. 1), 
whereas ondansetron (8 mg) had no effect. The mean 
blocking rates of the whole brain by 5 mg, 10 mg, and 20 
mg tropisetron were 1.2±0.02% (mean±SD, n=3), 7.6 
±0.03% (n=3), and 14.1±0.02% (n=3), respectively. In 
contrast, the mean blocking rate of ondansetron of the 
whole brain was −0.4±0.03% (n=3). As shown in Fig. 2, 
single administration of tropisetron blocked the binding of 
[ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001 in the human brain in a dose-depend-
ent manner, whereas a single administration of ondanse-
tron had almost no effect. Furthermore, a significant (r= 
0.979, p＜0.001) positive correlation was observed be-
tween the plasma concentration of tropisetron and the ad-
ministered dose of tropisetron (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The present study showed that a single oral admin-
istration of tropisetron, but not ondansetron, blocks the 
binding of [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001 in the human brain in a 
dose-dependent manner. </p>



<p>Fig. 2. Blocking rates of [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001 by tropisetron and on-
dansetron. The mean±standard deviation of three subjects for 
each dose is shown. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Correlations between the administered dose of tropisetron 
and the plasma concentration of tropisetron. There is a significant 
(r=0.979, p＜0.001) positive correlation between the administered 
dose of tropisetron and plasma concentration. Plasma samples 
were taken 3-3.5 hours after administration of tropisetron. </p>

<p>Deficient inhibitory processing of the P50 audi-
tory-evoked potential is a pathophysiological feature of 
schizophrenia. Several lines of evidence suggest that α7-
nicotinic receptors play a critical role in this phenomenon. 
Previously, we reported that tropisetron improved defi-
cient auditory inhibition processing in DBA/2 mice and 
that the improvement by tropisetron could be antagonized 
by co-administration of the α7-nAChR antagonist MLA. </p>

<p>39) </p>

<p>Furthermore, we also reported that phencyclidine (PCP)-
induced cognitive deficits in mice improve by subsequent 
subchronic administration of tropisetron, but not ondanse-
tron, and that the improvement was antagonized by co-ad-
ministration of MLA. 
40) These preclinical findings sug-</p>

<p>gest that tropisetron could improve abnormal auditory 
sensory gating and PCP-induced cognitive deficits in 
mice via α7-nAChRs. 
39,40) In clinical studies, we re-</p>

<p>ported that a single oral administration of tropisetron (10 
mg) improved deficits in P50 suppression in non-smoking 
patients with schizophrenia. 
41) A recent randomized, pla-</p>

<p>cebo-controlled study of tropisetron showed that tropise-
tron (10 mg/day for 8 weeks) significantly improved audi-
tory sensory gating P50 deficits and attentional deficits in 
non-smoking patients with schizophrenia. 
42) Taken to-</p>

<p>gether with these previous findings, the present study 
shows that tropisetron may bind to α7-nAChRs in the hu-
man brain after a single oral administration, suggesting 
the role of α7-nAChRs in the mechanisms of its efficacy. 
Of all ROIs, the highest blocking rate, approximately 
22.6%, was seen in the cerebellum by 20 mg of tropi-</p>

<p>setron. The dose-blocking rate relationship of tropisetron 
did not follow the simplified Hill equation of occupancy 
=Occupancy max [F/(F＋ED 50 )], where Occupancy max re-
fers to maximal occupancy, F is dose or plasma concen-
tration of tropisetron, and ED50 is the plasma tropisetron 
level resulting in 50% maximal occupancy. This suggests 
that 20 mg of tropisetron is not sufficient to saturate the 
blocking of [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001. Increasing the dose of tro-
pisetron may reveal higher blocking rates, but we avoided 
this for safety reasons. The dose of ondansetron was lim-
ited to 8 mg due to the same safety reasons. 
[ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001 PET data were well described with a 
one-tissue two-compartment model, but the direct deriva-
tion of the specific binding potential (BPND) as BPND=k3/ 
k 4 in a two-tissue three-compartment model was unstable </p>

<p>(data not shown). Furthermore, as the radioactivity after 
administration of [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001 was widely distri-
buted throughout the human brain, there was no reference 
region for the indirect derivation of BP ND . Therefore, we 
used VT for quantitative analysis of [ 
11 C]CHIBA-1001 </p>

<p>PET data in this study. 
Although CHIBA-1001 is devoid of activity (inhibition 
lower than 50%) for the 28 standard receptor-binding pro-
file, 
27) we recently reported that the non-specific binding </p>

<p>of [ </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>H]CHIBA-1001 is relatively high in membranes from 
postmortem human brain samples. 
38) In the present study, </p>

<p>the exact occupancy of α7-nAChR by tropisetron could 
not be determined because V T , which is used for quantita-
tive analysis of [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001 PET data, includes 
both specific and nonspecific binding. Despite these limi-
tations, this study suggests that [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001 may be 
a useful PET ligand for blocking studies of α7-nAChR </p>

<p>Occupancy of α7-nAChRs in Human Brain by Tropisetron 115 </p>

<p>drugs in the human brain, particularly because more suit-
able PET ligands for human study are not currently 
available. 
In conclusion, the present study showed that a single or-
al administration of tropisetron, but not ondansetron, 
blocked the binding of [ 
11 C]CHIBA-1001 in the human </p>

<p>brain and also suggests that [ 
11 C]CHIBA-1001 may be a </p>

<p>useful PET ligand for blocking studies of α7-nAChRs in 
the human brain, although [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]CHIBA-1001 exhibits a 
high level of non-specific binding in the human brain. 
Therefore, the development of novel PET ligands with 
low non-specific binding will be necessary. </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant from the Program 
for Promotion of Fundamental Studies in Health Sciences 
of the National Institute of Biomedical Innovation of 
Japan (Grant ID: 06-46, to K. Hashimoto and K. 
Ishiwata). We thank Mr. Kunpei Hayashi, Dr. Kenji 
Ishibashi, Mr. Keiichi Kawasaki, and Ms. Hiroko 
Tsukinari for technical assistance. </p>



<p>■ Acknowledgments </p>





</text></tei>