<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3988440" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: We determined the effects of alpha-blockers and quinolone in patients with 
chronic prostatitis/chronic pelvic pain syndrome (CP/CPPS) classified by National 
Institute of Health (NIH) consensus group. 
Materials and Methods: Data from a total of 111 patients who were diagnosed with 
CP/CPPS between June 2010 and June 2012 were analyzed retrospectively. The pa-
tients were classified into group 1 (category IIIA, n=40) and group 2 (category IIIB, 
n=71). Treatment using alfuzosin and levofloxacin was given to both groups for 6 weeks. 
International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS) and NIH Chronic Prostatitis Symptom 
Index were measured before and after therapy. 
Results: Group 1 had a significant decrease in total IPSS score, CPSI pain score, CPSI 
quality of life (QoL) score, and total CPSI score (p=0.043, p=0.006, p=0.015, and 
p=0.006, respectively). Group 2 had a significant decrease in IPSS voiding symptom 
score, IPSS storage symptom score, total IPSS, CPSI pain score, CPSI voiding score, 
CPSI QoL score, and total CPSI score (p=0.002, p=0.004, p=0.001, p=0.001, p=0.006, 
p=0.001, and p=0.001, respectively). The CPSI score was reduced by 6 points or more 
in 50.0% of patients (n=18) in group 1 and in 51.6% of patients (n=32) in group 2. 
However, there was no statistically significant difference between the changes in IPSS 
and CPSI scores across the 2 groups. 
Conclusions: Although combination treatment reduced the CPSI score in both groups, 
there was no significant difference between the groups after combination treatment. 
We suggest that factors other than inflammation also contribute to symptoms asso-
ciated with CP/CPPS. </p>

<p>Chronic prostatitis/chronic pelvic pain syndrome (CP/CPPS) 
represents one of the most commonly encountered disease 
entities. About 25% of patients who come to a urology clinic 
are thought to belong to the chronic prostatitis group [1]. 
Currently, the National Institutes of Health (NIH) clas-
sifies prostatitis into 4 categories depending on urine and 
prostatic fluid analysis, which includes microscopic exami-
nation and cultures. Of all cases, more than 90% of sympto-
matic prostatitis is categorized as NIH category type III, 
which is defined by the presence of chronic pelvic pain and </p>

<p>possibly voiding symptoms without uropathogenic bac-
teria. The new NIH classification for category III further 
defined these men as either category IIIA (inflammatory) 
or IIIB (noninflammatory) on the basis of the presence of 
significant white blood cells (WBCs) in prostatic-specific 
specimens (i.e., expressed prostatic secretion [EPS], urine 
specimen after prostatic massage [VB3], and semen) [2,3], 
However, although some research has confirmed the effec-
tiveness of various treatments according to the NIH classi-
fication, no difference in outcome was shown in the two 
groups. Therefore, this study was conducted to evaluate 
clinical outcomes in the treatment of CP/CPPS according </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2014;55:276-280 </p>

<p>Clinical Significance of NIH Classification </p>



<p>TABLE 1. Baseline characteristics of patients with CP/CPPS </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Prostatitis classification </p>

<p>IIIA (n=40) 
IIIB (n=71) p-value </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Age (y) 
Prostate volume (mL) 
PSA (ng/mL) 
Qmax (mL/s) 
CPSI 
Pain 
Voiding 
QoL 
Total 
IPSS 
Voiding 
Storage 
Total </p>

<p>54.91±11.75 
29.04±13.28 
1.45±1.21 
16.33±9.73 </p>

<p>9.00±4.78 
4.37±3.25 
7.05±2.46 
20.37±8.05 </p>

<p>7.29±6.61 
5.58±4.15 
12.87±9.87 </p>

<p>51.15±13.43 
28.79±10.14 
1.13±1.16 
15.85±7.20 </p>

<p>8.43±5.44 
4.57±3.15 
7.48±2.90 
20.65±9.64 </p>

<p>8.51±4.47 
6.57±4.36 
15.04±7.96 </p>

<p>0.196 
0.925 
0.247 
0.182 </p>

<p>0.686 
0.813 
0.561 
0.909 </p>

<p>0.422 
0.361 
0.321 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±standard deviation. 
CP/CPPS, chronic prostatitis/chronic pelvic pain syndrome; PSA, 
prostate-specific antigen; CPSI, Chronic Prostatitis Symptom 
Index; QoL, quality of life; IPSS, International Prostate Symptom 
Score. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>:Independent t-test. </p>

<p>to NIH classification. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>A retrospective review was performed of 111 patients with 
a diagnosis of CP/CPPS who were managed at Yonsei 
University Wonju Severance Christian Hospital between 
June 2010 and June 2012. The diagnosis of CP/CPPS was 
made by physical examination, microscopic analysis of 
urine and standard microbiological cultures, transrectal 
ultrasonography, and serum prostate-specific antigen 
(PSA) measurements. Patients were included in the study 
if they had experienced pain or discomfort in the pelvic re-
gion for at least 3 months [4]. We excluded patients with 
urinary tract infection, hypoechoic lesions on transrectal 
prostate ultrasound, serum PSA levels greater than or 
equal to 4 ng/dL, a history of antibiotic treatment in the 6 
months preceding the initial visit, invasive prostate-re-
lated procedures (transurethral resection of the prostate, 
transurethral incision of the prostate, or transurethral 
needle ablation), genitourinary cancer, inflammatory bow-
el disease, active urethral stricture, prostate or bladder 
surgery, or neurologic diseases affecting the bladder. 
Depending on the number of WBCs in the EPS or VB3, 
each patient was designated into the 2 NIH subgroups dis-
cussed above. A patient was assigned to the NIH category 
IIIA group if the WBC count in the EPS was equal to or 
greater than 10 per high power field (HPF) or the WBC 
count in the VB3 was equal to or greater than 5 per HPF. 
Conversely, a patient was assigned to IIIB if the WBC count 
in the EPS was less than 10 per HPF or the WBC count in 
the VB3 was less than 5 per HPF [2]. Both groups were eval-
uated before the treatment and 6 weeks after the treatment 
by using NIH Chronic Prostatitis Symptom Index 
(NIH-CPSI) scores and the International Prostate Symp-
tom Score (IPSS). Determination of the presence or ab-
sence of the therapeutic effect was defined as when the 
CPSI score fell 6 points or more [5]. All the patients were 
treated with once-daily alpha-blockers (alfuzosin 10 g) and 
quinolone (levofloxacin 500 mg) for 6 weeks. 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">PASW</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 18.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA) was used 
for all statistical analyses. The Wilcoxon signed-rank test 
was used to compare the baseline scores with posttreat-
ment scores. Paired t-test and chi-square test were used to 
analyze the efficacy of treatment between groups. Trea-
tment outcome was analyzed by logistic regression, ad-
justed for age, prostate volume, IPSS, and category of 
CP/CPPS. A p-value of less than 0.05 was considered stat-
istically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Of the 111 patients, 41 were classified into group 1 (cate-
gory IIIA) and 71 patients into group 2 (category IIIB) on 
the basis of WBCs and culture results. The patients' mean 
age was 54.91±11.75 years in group 1 and 51.15±13.43 
years in group 2. The total IPSS was 12.87±9.87 for group </p>

<p>1 and 15.04±7.96 for group 2. The total CPSI was 
20.29±7.72 in group 1 and 20.48±9.66 in group 2. Baseline 
characteristics including age, prostate volume, PSA, mean 
maximal urine flow rate on uroflowmetry, CPSI score, and 
IPSS were not significantly different between the two 
groups (Table 1). 
Table 2 lists the mean IPSS and NIH-CPSI before and 
after the combination therapy. The total IPSS was sig-
nificantly decreased in group 1 (from 16.00±10.86 to 
12.14±9.02, p=0.043) and group 2 (from 17.93±5.19 to 
17.00±7.32, p=0.001). The IPSS voiding symptom subscore 
was significantly decreased in group 2 (from 9.93±3.14 to 
10.79±5.14, p=0.002). The IPSS storage symptom subscore 
was significantly decreased in group 2 (from 8.14±3.99 to 
6.21±3.57, p=0.004). The CPSI pain score was significantly 
decreased in group 1 (from 8.28±4.68 to 5.33±3.64, 
p=0.006) and group 2 (from 8.52±5.13 to 5.94±4.32, 
p=0.001). The CPSI voiding symptom score was sig-
nificantly decreased in Group 2 (from 5.00±3.35 to 
3.65±2.72, p=0.006). The CPSI QoL symptom score was sig-
nificantly decreased in group 1 (from 7.33±2.35 to 
6.06±2.07, p=0.015) and group 2 (from 7.71±2.74 to 
5.81±2.75, p=0.001). The total CPSI score was significantly 
decreased in group 1 (from 20.11±7.63 to 15.11±6.93, 
p=0.006) and group 2 (from 21.23±9.38 to 15.39±7.87, 
p=0.001). The CPSI total score was reduced by 6 points or 
more in 50% of the patients in group 1 (n=18) and 51.6% 
of the patients in group 2 (n=32). No significant differences 
(p=0.913) in treatment outcomes were observed between 
the two groups. As shown in Table 3, there were no statisti-
cally significant differences in treatment outcomes after 
adjustment for age, prostate volume, and IPSS. </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2014;55:276-280 </p>



<p>Sung et al </p>

<p>TABLE 2. IPSS and CPSI among 2 groups before and after the α-blocker and quinolone treatment </p>

<p>IIIA (n=40) 
IIIB (n=71) </p>

<p>Pretreatment Posttreatment 
Difference 
Pretreatment 
Posttreatment 
Difference </p>

<p>IPSS 
Voiding symptom 
8.57±6.52 
7.14±4.88 
-1.43±2.63 
9.93±3.14 
10.79±5.14 
-2.57±4.83 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Storage symptom 
7.43±4.86 
5.00±4.39 
-2.43±3.10 
8.14±3.99 
6.21±3.57 
-2.64±2.76 a 
Total 
16.00±10.86 
12.14±9.02 
-3.86±4.10 a 
17.93±5.19 
17.00±7.32 
-5.43±5.18 a 
CPSI 
Pain 
8.28±4.68 
5.33±3.64 
-2.94±4.08 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>8.52±5.13 
5.94±4.32 
-2.58±3.88 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Voiding symptom 
4.56±3.14 
3.72±3.19 
-0.83±1.68 
5.00±3.35 
3.65±2.72 
-1.35±2.53 a 
QoL 
7.33±2.35 
6.06±2.07 
-1.28±1.93 a 
7.71±2.74 
5.81±2.75 
-1.90±1.90 a 
Total 
20.11±7.63 
15.11±6.93 
-5.00±6.30 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>21.23±9.38 
15.39±7.87 
-5.84±6.48 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±standard deviation. 
IPSS, International Prostate Symptom Score; CPSI, Chronic Prostatitis Symptom Index; QoL, quality of life. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>:p＜0.05 between baseline and after treatment. </p>

<p>TABLE 3. Treatment outcome odds ratios, adjusted for age, 
prostate volume, IPSS, and category of CP/CPPS </p>

<p>Variable 
Treatment outcome, OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Age≥50 y 
Prostate volume≥30 mL 
IPSS 
＜8 
8-20 
≥21 
Category IIIB </p>

<p>0.260 (0.034-1.978) 
2.753 (0.546-13.883) </p>

<p>1 
3.181 (0.222-45.580) 
2.151 (0.122-37.886) 
1.825 (0.377-8.833) </p>

<p>IPSS, International Prostate Symptom Score; CP/CPPS, chronic 
prostatitis/chronic pelvic pain syndrome; OR, odds ratio; CI, con-
fidence interval. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>:Logistic regression. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>CP/CPPS is a common disorder that is typically accom-
panied by pain with ejaculation or discomfort in the pelvic 
or perineal region with prominent lower urinary tract 
symptoms [6-8]. Although prostatic inflammation has 
been identified in many patients with this syndrome, the 
etiology and pathophysiology of CP/CPPS remain un-
known [4-7]. 
The NIH consensus group identifies CP/CPPS on the ba-
sis of WBCs in the EPS, VB3, or semen without any evi-
dence of uropathogenic bacteria detected by standard mi-
crobiological methodology [7,8]. The Meares-Stamey 4-glass 
test or simpler 2-glass test has been used to diagnosis CP 
[7]. Since Mobley reported the usefulness of a semen cul-
ture in combination with urine culture, the new NIH con-
sensus classification is broader than the traditional ap-
proach, which was limited to the examination of EPS [6-9]. 
Krieger et al. [8] reported an increase in inflammation from 
52% to 93% when the diagnosis was based on the addition 
VB3 and seminal fluid analysis (SFA) to EPS. In contrast, 
the NIH-CPCRN case-control study determined that semi-</p>

<p>nal evaluation had little clinical value in differentiating 
prostatitis patients from normal controls [10]. In the pres-
ent study, we did not perform SFA. In fact, most urologists 
rarely perform the 4-glass test and SFA in clinical practice. 
Potential reasons are that the test is not sensitive nor spe-
cific, the therapeutic predictive value is poor, and the test 
is relatively expensive, time-consuming, and quite un-
comfortable for the patients [11,12]. 
Traditionally, patients with CP/CPPS receive empirical 
treatment. The most common treatments in clinical prac-
tice are antimicrobial agents and alpha-adrenergic re-
ceptor antagonists [13-15]. A European consensus report 
suggested that antibiotics are recommended for NIH cat-
egory IIIA but not for NIH category IIIB [13]. However, 
Nickel et al. [2] found no significant differences between 
NIH category II, IIIA, and IIIB after antibiotic treatment. 
A recent prospective study showed that levofloxacin ther-
apy was effective for CP/CPPS [14]. There are three reason-
able explanations, as follows. First, the antimicrobial 
agent may have a placebo effect; second, the antimicrobial 
agent may eradicate noncultured microorganisms; and 
third, the antimicrobial agents may have immunosu-
ppressive or anti-inflammatory effects [16]. Also, the treat-
ment outcome was checked after 6 weeks, because this is 
the usual interval of treatment with an antimicrobial agent 
and it is generally believed that the bacterial organisms re-
sponsible for symptoms should be eradicated within this 
time [17]. 
Alpha-adrenergic receptor blockers are proven to be an 
effective treatment for benign prostatic hypertrophy. They 
inhibit the smooth muscle tone within the prostate gland 
and in the region of the bladder neck [3-5]. Presumably, 
these drugs are used empirically in the management of 
CP/CPPS because of overlapping pathogenesis, such as 
sympathetic over-activation [5,17]. A recent systemic re-
view showed that alpha-adrenergic receptor blocker ther-
apy was associated with significant improvement in 
CP/CPPS symptoms [18]. Moreover, antibiotics and al-
pha-blocker combination therapy was more effective than </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2014;55:276-280 </p>

<p>Clinical Significance of NIH Classification </p>



<p>monotherapy in treating CP/CPPS [14,18]. In this study, 
the combination alfuzosin and levofloxacin therapy re-
sulted in significant improvements in both IPSS and 
NIH-CPSI scores. However, no significant difference in 
treatment outcome (improvements of at least 6 points or 
more on the NIH-CPSI total and domain scores) was ob-
served between NIH category IIIA and IIIB. This suggests 
that a systemic approach other than NIH classification by 
the WBC count may be necessary. 
In fact, our understanding of CP/CPPS has evolved with 
the development of the NIH classification. In our con-
temporary concept, CP/CPPS is not prostate-specific but 
incorporates other extraprostatic factors including pelvic 
muscle dysfunction, neurological disease, and psychiatric 
conditions [6-8]. Recently, Shoskes et al. [19] developed the 
clinical phenotyping system with six domain: urinary, psy-
chosocial, organ specific, infection, neurologic/systemic, 
and tenderness (UPOINT), and a European study modified 
the clinical phenotyping system with an additional sexual 
dysfunction domain (UPOINTS) [20]. They showed that 
the number of positive domains correlated with symptom 
severity, and UPOINT-directed multimodal therapy im-
proved symptoms and quality of life [21,22]. Therefore, be-
cause leukocytosis on EPS or VB3 and voiding symptoms 
only reveal organ-specific domains according to the 
UPOINT system, each patient should be assessed for not 
only laboratory findings such as a lower urinary tract local-
ization test, but also the nature of symptoms. Although 
51% of the patients showed clinical improvement in our 
study, there was no significant difference between NIH cat-
egory IIIA and IIIB. This may reflect the heterogeneous as-
pect of CP/CPPS rather than the laboratory results. 
As a result, we think that the NIH classification for 
CP/CPPS based on the presence or absence of WBCs in 
EPS, VB3, or semen is necessary as an initial diagnostic 
approach. However, from a therapeutic viewpoint, it has 
a limited role because of the multiple pathophysiologic fac-
tors that affect CP/CPPS. 
There were limitations to this study. First, we used only 
EPS-and VB3-based classification. Krieger et al. [8] noted 
that semen analysis will increase the rate of detection of 
category IIIA. Therefore, if the semen analysis had been en-
forced in our study, more patients would have been diag-
nosed with IIIA. Second, the treatment outcome was meas-
ured only after 6 weeks. It may take a longer period of treat-
ment before an improved symptom score is seen. 
Long-term follow-up is needed to support our results. 
Third, our study was designed as a retrospective review 
and had too small a number of cases to properly evaluate 
the impact of NIH classification on the outcomes of 
CP/CPPS. As such, a prospective randomized trial and 
long-term follow-up are needed. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>CP/CPPS is a highly prevalent, multifactorial condition 
that affects men of all ages. The NIH classification provided </p>

<p>useful information regarding potential etiologies and 
treatment in patients with CP/CPPS. However, the treat-
ment response rate between NIH classification IIIA and 
IIIB was not significantly different after antibiotics and al-
pha-blockers combination treatment. Therefore, we think 
that factors other than inflammation also contribute to 
symptoms associated with CP/CPPS, and consideration of 
multiple phenotypes by use of UPOINT will help in the 
treatment of CP/CPPS. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST 
The authors have nothing to disclose. </p>



<p>Korean J Urol 2014;55:276-280 </p>





</text></tei>