<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3218131" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: Recent literature has shown that lymph node ratio is superior to the absolute number of metastatic lymph nodes 
in predicting the prognosis in several malignances other than colorectal cancer. The aim of this study was to evaluate the 
prognostic significance of the lymph node ratio (LNR) in patients with stage III colorectal cancer. 
Methods: We included 186 stage III colorectal cancer patients who underwent a curative resection over a 10-year period 
in one hospital. The cutoff point of LNR was chosen as 0.07 because there was significant survival difference at that LNR. 
The Kaplan-Meier and the Cox proportional hazard models were used to evaluate the prognostic effect according to LNR. 
Results: There was statistically significant longer overall survival in the group of LNR &gt; 0.07 than in the group of LNR ≤ 7 
(P = 0.008). Especially, there was a survival difference for the N1 patients group (LN &lt; 4) according to LNR (5-year survival 
of N1 patients was lower in the group of LNR &gt; 0.07, P = 0.025), but there was no survival difference for the N2 group (4 
≥ LN) according to LNR. The multivariate analysis showed that the LNR is an independent prognostic factor. 
Conclusions: LNR can be considered as a more accurate and potent modality for prognostic stratifications in patients with 
stage III colorectal cancer. </p>

<p>Keywords: Colorectal cancer; Metastatic lymph node ratio; Prognostic factor </p>

<p>distant metastasis), form the basis for determining the prognosis 
[2]. Among them, lymph node metastasis is known to be one of 
the most important factors. As the survival rate has been shown 
to increase after adjuvant chemotherapy [2, 3], the existence of lymph 
node metastasis is grounds for advocating postoperative adjuvant 
chemotherapy or radiotherapy. Therefore, reporting the status of 
lymph nodes (both the number of nodes harvested and the num-
ber of metastatic lymph nodes) accurately is very critical in decid-
ing the postoperative treatments and in giving a prognosis. How-
ever, the expected prognosis when determined by the number of 
metastatic lymph nodes is not consistent in the patients whose 
stage is same. In addition, it is difficult to determine lymph node 
metastasis objectively as lymph node metastasis depends on the 
individual characteristics of the patient, the competence of the 
surgeon and the ability of the pathologist to isolate and collect 
lymph nodes [4, 5]. Current studies have found that the number 
of harvested lymph nodes is related to the disease-free and the 
overall survival rates of colorectal cancer patients [6-8]. In other 
words, a higher harvested lymph node number is associated with 
a higher survival rate in patients treated with a radical tumor re-
section [9, 10]. 
Against this background, a metastatic lymph node ratio (LNR) 
rather than an absolute metastatic lymph node count has been re-</p>

<p>Colorectal cancer has the second highest incidence globally among 
malignant tumors, and the prevalence and the incidence rate in 
South Korea are rising. Earlier studies have shown that the prog-
nostic factors for colorectal cancer are early detection, age at diag-
nosis, location of tumor, histological differentiation, depth of inva-
sion, lymph node metastasis, preoperative and postoperative plasma 
carcino embryonic antigen level, and degree of venous and neural 
invasion. Of these factors, depth of invasion, lymph node metas-
tasis and metastasis to other organs [1], as reflected in the current 
TNM staging (T, depth of invasion; N, lymph node metastasis; M, </p>

<p>Received: May 20, 2011 Accepted: August 7, 2011 
Correspondence to: Chang Hyeok An, M.D. 
Department of Surgery, Uijeongbu St.Mary's Hospital, The Catholic 
University of Korea School of Medicine, 65-1 Geumo-dong, Uijeongbu 
480-717, Korea 
Tel: +82-31-820-3998, Fax: +82-31-847-2717 
E-mail: achcolo@catholic.ac.kr </p>

<p>© 2011 The Korean Society of Coloproctology </p>

<p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-
Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted non-
commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Journal of The Korean Society of </p>

<p>Coloproctology </p>

<p>www.coloproctol.org 
261 </p>

<p>Volume 27, Number 5, 2011 </p>

<p>J Korean Soc Coloproctol 2011;27(5):260-265 </p>

<p>ported to be meaningful for reducing stage migration and for giv-
ing a prognosis for other types of solid cancers (stomach [11-13], 
breast [14], bladder [15], pancreas [16] and lung cancer [17]). Stud-
ies on the clinical meaning of the LNR as a prognostic factor have 
been performed for colorectal cancer patients [16, 18-23]. How-
ever, the clinical meaning of the LNR in colorectal cancer patients 
is still controversial as some researchers found no correlation be-
tween the LNR and the survival rate while others insisted that the 
LNR was a more critical prognostic factor than simple lymph node 
metastasis. Therefore, we conducted this study to determine whether 
the LNR is a stronger prognostic factor than the absolute number 
of metastatic lymph nodes in patients with stage III colorectal cancer. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>One hundred eighty-six stage III colorectal cancer patients under-
going a radical resection over 10 years at our hospital were evalu-
ated. Patients with a histologically-diagnosed non-adenocarcino-
mas or with an appendiceal or anal cancer were excluded from this 
study. 
Laparoscopic or open surgery was conducted for all of the pati-
ents by one surgeon, and depending on the location of the tumor, 
a standard colonic resection with lymph node dissection was done. 
The age and gender of the patients, the location of the tumors, the 
histological differentiation of the tumors, the depth of invasion, the 
number of harvested lymph nodes, the number of metastatic lymph 
nodes and the LNR were analyzed after the surgery. The LNR was 
defined as a ratio of the number of metastatic lymph nodes to the 
number of total harvested lymph nodes. The depth of invasion and 
the number of metastatic lymph nodes helped stage the disease 
using the current AJCC 7th edition [2]. 
The location of the tumors was classified into the right colon (from 
the cecum to the distal transverse colon), the left colon (from the 
splenic flexure to the sigmoid colon) and the rectum. Patients di-
agnosed with a stage III or higher disease postoperatively under-
went adjuvant chemotherapy, and postoperative follow-up was 
performed through chest X-ray, abdominal computed tomogra-
phy (CT) and tumor markers at six-month intervals for the first 
two years and at one-year intervals for the next three years. Local 
recurrence or metastasis to other organs was confirmed histologi-
cally, if it was available, and with radiologic examination if the for-
mer was not available. The LNR was divided into three regions, </p>

<p>less than 0.07, 0.08-0.20, and more than 0.20, as suggested by Pe-
schaud et al. [20], but the survival rates of the groups with LNR of 
0.08-0.20 and over 0.20 were not considerably different, so the pa-
tients were finally divided into two groups: One with LNR of less 
than 0.07 and the other with a LNR of 0.07 or greater. 
The statistical analysis was conducted with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">12.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA), and the survival curve was prepared us-
ing a Kaplan-Meier analysis. The univariate analysis and the mul-
tivariate analysis of prognostic factors were performed using the 
log-rank method and the Cox proportional hazard ratio, respec-
tively. A P-value of less than 0.05 was considered to be statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>Table 1. Total harvested lymph node (LN) numbers and LN number 
when harvested LN ≥ 12 according to tumor location </p>

<p>Total harvested / harvested LN ≥ 12 </p>

<p>Patient no. 
Mean ± standard deviation </p>

<p>Right 
117 / 83 
18.97 ± 9.7 / 22.13 ± 8.15 </p>

<p>Left 
183 / 89 
14.92 ± 9.53 / 20.33 ± 7.17 </p>

<p>Rectum 
184 / 86 
13.26 ± 10.23 / 21.19 ± 9.83 </p>

<p>Total 
484 / 258 
15.27 ± 10.07 / 21.20 ± 8.44 </p>

<p>Table 2. Clinicopathological characteristics of stage III colorectal can-
cer patients and 5-year survival (univariate analysis) </p>

<p>Characteristics 
No. of 
cases (%) </p>

<p>5-year 
survival (%) 
P-value </p>

<p>Age </p>

<p>&lt;60 
56 (30.1) 
79 
NS </p>

<p>≥60 
130 (69.9) 
73 </p>

<p>Sex </p>

<p>Male 
110 (59.1) 
74 
NS </p>

<p>Female 
76 (40.9) 
75 </p>

<p>T stage </p>

<p>T1 
7 (3.8) 
75 
0.005 </p>

<p>T2 
16 (8.6) 
75 </p>

<p>T3 
129 (69.4) 
64 </p>

<p>T4 
34 (18.3) 
41 </p>

<p>N Stage </p>

<p>N1 
125 (67.2) 
67 
0.006 </p>

<p>N2 
61 (32.8) 
49 </p>

<p>TNM stage </p>

<p>IIIA 
21 (11.3) 
88 
0.014 </p>

<p>IIIB 
104 (55.9) 
62 </p>

<p>IIIC 
61 (32.8) 
49 </p>

<p>Lymphatic invasion </p>

<p>No 
25 (13.6) 
67 
NS </p>

<p>Yes 
159 (86.4) 
60 </p>

<p>Venous invasion </p>

<p>No 
171 (93.4) 
62 
0.006 </p>

<p>Yes 
12 (6.6) 
39 </p>

<p>Perineural invasion </p>

<p>No 
132 (72.9) 
65 
0.020 </p>

<p>Yes 
49 (27.1) 
45 </p>

<p>NS, no significant. </p>

<p>Journal of The Korean Society of </p>

<p>Coloproctology </p>

<p>www.coloproctol.org 
262 </p>

<p>Clinical Significance of Lymph Node Ratio in Stage III Colorectal Cancer </p>

<p>Yo Han Park, et al. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Four hundred eighty-four colorectal cancer patients underwent 
radical surgery at our hospital over 10 years. The tumors were lo-
cated in the right colon, the left colon and the rectum in 117, 183, 
and 184 patients, respectively. When considering the overall resec-
tions (both adequate and inadequate as per the AJCC criteria), the 
total numbers of harvested lymph nodes were 18, 14 and 13, on 
average, for the right colon, the left colon and the rectum, respec-
tively; the harvested lymph node number for the right colon was 
significantly higher (P &lt; 0.001) in this group. However, when ex-
clusively considering cases with adequate resections with 12 or more 
LNs, the numbers of lymph nodes harvested by the locations of </p>

<p>the tumors were not significantly different (Table 1). 
This study included only 186 stage III colorectal cancer patients, 
and patients with ages over 60 years (130) accounted for 69.9% of 
the total. The clinicopathological characteristics of the patients are 
shown in Table 2. Among these patients, the five-year survival rate 
was lower for a higher T stage and for more advanced stage III 
colorectal cancer. The survival rate of the stage N1 group was higher 
than that of the stage N2 group, 67% and 49% respectively (Fig. 1). 
Fig. 2A presents the five-year survival rate by LNR in stage III 
colorectal cancer patients. The five-year survival rate was the high-
est in the group with a LNR of less than 0.07 while those of the 
groups with a LNR of 0.08-0.20 and more than 0.20 were not sig-
nificantly different. When the total patients were finally divided 
into two groups with a LNR of less than 0.07 and a LNR of 0.07 or 
greater, the former recorded a higher five-year survival rate, and 
the difference was statistically significant (Fig. 2B). 
To determine the effect of LNR on the prognosis, the five-year 
survival rate by LNR was investigated at each N stage, and the sur-
vival curves are shown in Fig. 3A and Fig. 3B. In the N1 group with 
three or less metastatic lymph nodes, the survival rate of the group 
with a LNR of less than 0.07 was significantly higher than that of 
the group with a LNR of 0.07 or greater. In the N2 group, the dif-
ference in the survival rates between the two groups was not sig-
nificant. 
When colon cancer and rectal cancer were compared, the five-
year survival rates of colon cancer patients were different with a 
LNR of 0.07 as the standard, but the difference did not have a sta-
tistical meaning (P = 0.143) (Fig. 4A). The rates of rectal cancer 
patients showed a statistically significant difference with the same 
standard (Fig. 4B). 
A multivariate analysis of the clinicopathological characteristics, 
which were found to be significant with a P-value of less than 0.05 </p>

<p>Cumulative survival </p>

<p>Months </p>

<p>P = 0.006 </p>

<p>N1 </p>

<p>N2 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Five-year survival curve in stage III colorectal cancer patients 
according to metastatic lymph node number (N staging). </p>

<p>Cumulative survival 
Cumulative survival </p>

<p>Months 
Months </p>

<p>P = 0.015 
P = 0.008 </p>

<p>0.01-0.17 
0.01-0.17 </p>

<p>0.08-0.20 
&gt;0.07 </p>

<p>&gt;0.20 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 
0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>Fig. 2. (A) Five-year survival curve in stage III colorectal cancer patients according to metastatic lymph node ratio (3 groups: LNR, 0.01-0.07; 
0.08-0.20; &gt;0.20). (B) Five-year survival curve in stage III colorectal cancer patients according to metastatic lymph node ratio (2 groups: LNR, 
0.01-0.07; &gt;0.07). </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Journal of The Korean Society of </p>

<p>Coloproctology </p>

<p>www.coloproctol.org 
263 </p>

<p>Volume 27, Number 5, 2011 </p>

<p>J Korean Soc Coloproctol 2011;27(5):260-265 </p>

<p>on the univariate analysis, of stage III colorectal cancer patients 
revealed that LNR, T staging and neural invasion had a significant 
correlation with the prognosis. Of them, LNR was found to be one 
of the most critical prognostic factors, with an odds ratio of 4.3 
(Table 3). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Amongst the prognostic factors, the depth of invasion, lymph node 
metastasis and metastasis to other organs have been found to be 
closely related with the prognosis for colorectal cancer [1]. The sta-
tus of lymph node metastasis has been recognized as the one factor 
exerting the strongest influence on the prognosis. However, the 
lymph node metastasis depends on the individual characteristics 
of the patient and the competence of the surgeon and the patholo-
gist, thus making it difficult to assess the status accurately [4, 5]. 
For example, more lymph nodes are harvested in young patients, 
females and thin patients when considering the demographic char-
acteristics, from the right colon when considering the location of 
the tumor and at larger hospitals and by more experienced surgeons </p>

<p>Cumulative survival 
Cumulative survival </p>

<p>Months 
Months </p>

<p>P = 0.025 
P = 0.143 </p>

<p>0.01-0.17 
&gt;0.07 </p>

<p>&gt;0.07 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 
0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>Fig. 3. (A) Five-year survival curve in metastatic lymph node number &lt;4 (N1 staging) cancer patients according to metastatic lymph node ratio. 
(B) Five-year survival curve in metastatic lymph node number ≥4 (N2 staging) cancer patients according to metastatic lymph node ratio. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Cumulative survival 
Cumulative survival </p>

<p>Months 
Months </p>

<p>P = 0.0143 
P = 0.029 </p>

<p>0.01-0.17 
0.01-0.17 </p>

<p>&gt;0.07 
&gt;0.07 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 
0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>Fig. 4. (A) Five-year survival curve in stage III colon cancer patients according to metastatic lymph node ratio (cut-off point, 0.07). (B) Five-
year survival curve in stage III rectal cancer patients according to metastatic lymph node ratio (cut-off point, 0.07). </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Table 3. Significance of prognostic factors through multivariate analysis </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Odds ratio 
95% CI 
P-value </p>

<p>Lymph node ratio 
4.377 
1.029-18.607 
0.046 </p>

<p>Stage 
1.694 
1.001-2.869 
0.048 </p>

<p>Per neural invasion 
1.004 
1.004-3.451 
0.050 </p>

<p>CI, confidence interval. </p>

<p>Journal of The Korean Society of </p>

<p>Coloproctology </p>

<p>www.coloproctol.org 
264 </p>

<p>Clinical Significance of Lymph Node Ratio in Stage III Colorectal Cancer </p>

<p>Yo Han Park, et al. </p>

<p>in general [4, 6, 24, 25]. In addition, lymph node metastasis is found 
through RT-PCR in patients without metastasis in the current TNM 
staging [26], and stage migration (reported first by Feinstein and 
called Will Rogers phenomenon; the current AJCC TNM staging 
says that the same number of metastatic lymph nodes leads to the 
same prognosis even though the numbers of harvested lymph nodes 
are different [27]) can be shown, even in stage III colorectal cancer 
patients, to cause a deviation in the survival rate when only the ab-
solute number of metastatic lymph nodes is considered [18]. Be-
cause giving a prognosis for colorectal cancer based on the above 
criteria has led to some criticism, the concept of the LNR, which 
has been accepted as a clinically meaningful prognostic factor for 
other types of solid malignant tumors, has been introduced in stud-
ies on colorectal cancer [19-23, 28]. 
According to the results of this study, when the patients in N1 and 
N2 stages were divided by LNR, respectively, the five-year survival 
rates were different by LNR in patients in the N1 stage (Fig. 3A). 
That shows that the patients divided by N staging based on the ab-
solute number of metastatic lymph nodes are not distributed con-
sistently and that the use of LNR, along with the current TNM stag-
ing, can give a better prognosis. Unlike our expectation, the five-
year survival rates of the patients in N2 stage were not different by 
LNR (Fig. 3B) and that is thought to have been due to cut off of 
0.07 not being appropriate for showing a significant difference in 
the survival rates among the patients in N2 stage. 
This study compared the survival rate by LNR after dividing the 
colorectal cancer patients into colon cancer and rectal cancer pa-
tients. When the LNR (0.07) used for rectal cancer was applied to 
colon cancer, the accuracy of predicting the survival rate was slightly 
reduced (Fig. 4). A cut-off point to present a statistically significant 
difference in survival rate of colon cancer patients must be differ-
ent from the value of 0.07 used for rectal cancer; thus, appropriate 
the cut-off points need to be determined to obtain a significant 
difference in the survival rate by the location of the tumor. 
The multivariate analysis found that the LNR, independently, 
had the most important effect among the prognostic factors for 
colorectal cancer (Table 3) because the LNR is thought to decrease 
the effect of stage migration in colorectal cancer. Inoue et al. [12]  and Bando et al. [13] insisted that the LNR was meaningful for 
giving a prognosis because it reduced stage migration. These find-
ings suggest that the LNR can replace N staging and that a revi-
sion of the current TNM staging is needed. 
Previous studies have used various cut-off points for the LNR: 0.0, 
0.05, 0.10, 0.20, 0.25, 0.40, 0.50, and 0.75. Most of the studies de-
termined the cut-off points by using the LNR to draw the Kaplan-
Meier survival curve [29]. This study also performed statistical anal-
yses with the various cut-off points of the LNR applied in previous 
studies and found that 0.07 and 0.20, as suggested by Peschaud et 
al. [20], produced the largest difference in the survival rate when 
all patients were divided into three groups with the cut-off points. 
In each study, including this study, the survival rate, the disease-
free rate and cancer-related survival rate were significantly differ-</p>

<p>ent among the patients classified by cut-off points. However, the 
studies utilized various cut-off points. Thus, if the LNR is to be 
used as a prognostic factor, a standardization of cut-off points for 
the LNR is necessary for stratification of stages with better corre-
lation with the prognosis. 
This study had a limitation in that the number of total subjects 
was not as large as in a retrospective study. In addition, it included 
all rectal cancer patients for whom lymph node resection had been 
limited due to preoperative radiotherapy. 
Our data show that patients divided by N staging based on an ab-
solute number of metastatic lymph nodes are not distributed con-
sistently. The use of LNR, along with the current TNM staging, 
can better predict the prognosis for N1 stage of colorectal cancer 
and may be an independent prognostic factor in stage III colorec-
tal cancer. A large-scale study to determine appropriate cut-off 
points for LNR to play a role as an independent prognostic factor 
in stage III colorectal cancer is needed. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported. </p>



<p>Journal of The Korean Society of </p>

<p>Coloproctology </p>

<p>www.coloproctol.org </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>