<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3524521" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Turing models have been proposed to explain the emergence of digits during limb development. However, 
so far the molecular components that would give rise to Turing patterns are elusive. We have recently shown 
that a particular type of receptor-ligand interaction can give rise to Schnakenberg-type Turing patterns, 
which reproduce patterning during lung and kidney branching morphogenesis. Recent knockout 
experiments have identified Smad4 as a key protein in digit patterning. We show here that the BMP-receptor 
interaction meets the conditions for a Schnakenberg-type Turing pattern, and that the resulting model 
reproduces available wildtype and mutant data on the expression patterns of BMP, its receptor, and Fgfs in 
the apical ectodermal ridge (AER) when solved on a realistic 2D domain that we extracted from limb bud 
images of E11.5 mouse embryos. We propose that receptor-ligand-based mechanisms serve as a molecular 
basis for the emergence of Turing patterns in many developing tissues. </p>

<p>3   . These 
extra digits formed a mirror image of the normal forelimb, i.e. 1234554321 in mice and 234432 in chicken. Here 
numbers refer to digits with the lowest number referring to the most anterior digit in the wildtype (i.e. the thumb 
in humans). The effect was shown to be concentration-dependent in that a smaller number of grafted cells 
induced fewer digits and failed to induce the most posterior identities in the anterior limb bud 
3 . Wolpert's 
French Flag model explained these experiments by suggesting that digit number and identity were determined 
by the local concentration of a chemical compound 
4 . This compound was predicted to be produced in the ZPA 
and to diffuse across the limb bud, thereby creating a concentration gradient. Decades after the grafting experi-
ments had suggested that patterning was induced by a diffusible compound, Sonic hedgehog (SHH) was isolated 
and shown to affect patterning in a concentration-dependent manner </p>

<p>5,6   . In agreement with the morphogen 
model, SHH is expressed in cells of the ZPA and diffuses across the limb bud </p>

<p>7   . In mice that do not express 
SHH only digit 1 develops 
8 , and in the polydactylous mouse mutant extra toes (Xt) SHH is expressed also in the 
anterior region of the limb bud 
9 . 
However, several other experiments question this simple morphogen model and suggest that a more complex 
mechanism determines digit patterning during limb bud development. For one, polydactyly is still observed even 
when SHH expression is abolished in the extra toe (Xt) mutant </p>

<p>10   . Moreover, an experiment in which SHH 
expression is stopped prematurely at different stages during limb development results in an alternating 
anterior-posterior sequence of digit formation that cannot be reconciled with the standard morphogen model </p>

<p>11   . 
Thus the shortest pulse that yielded an additional digit induced formation of digit 4, followed by digit 2, and then 
digits 3 and 5. Based on the morphogen model digits would be expected to emerge simultaneously or in an 
anterior-posterior sequence. 
Experiments in which SHH-expressing cells were marked revealed that descendants of the SHH-producing 
cells could be found far beyond the small posterior zone in which SHH expression can be detected </p>

<p>7,12   . 
Descendants of the SHH-producing cells filled almost half of the limb bud and encompassed all cells in the 
two most posterior digits and also contributed to the middle digit </p>

<p>7,12   . Based on this observation it was suggested 
that it is the length for which cells express and secrete SHH (and therefore experience a high SHH concentration) 
that determines digit specification </p>

<p>7,12   . This model, however, still cannot explain the observed sequence of digit 
formation. </p>

<p>SUBJECT AREAS: </p>

<p>EMBRYONIC INDUCTION </p>

<p>BIOCHEMICAL REACTION 
NETWORKS </p>

<p>CELLULAR SIGNALLING 
NETWORKS </p>

<p>COMPUTATIONAL MODELS </p>

<p>Received 
24 October 2012 </p>

<p>Accepted 
30 November 2012 </p>

<p>Published 
18 December 2012 </p>

<p>Correspondence and </p>

<p>requests for materials </p>

<p>should be addressed to </p>

<p>D.I. (dagmar.iber@ </p>

<p>bsse.ethz.ch) </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 991 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00991 
1 </p>

<p>A number of mathematical models have been developed to explain 
limb bud development and digit patterning. Based on experimental 
observations, the earliest model defined some 40 years ago a set of 
simple rules to recapitulate the observed changes in the limb buds' 
size and shape </p>

<p>13   . The modelling effort highlighted the importance of 
oriented cell division to obtain the elongated shape that is character-
istic of the limb bud. Recent 3D imaging data in combination with a 
Navier-stokes description of the tissue as an viscous fluid indeed 
confirmed that isotropic proliferation alone is insufficient to explain 
the shape and size changes during limb bud development </p>

<p>14   . Local 
gain rates much higher than the measured proliferation rates as well 
as loss rates had to be included; these may reflect oriented cell divi-
sion and directed cell migration. The description of the limb tissue as 
a viscous fluid was first introduced by Dillon and Othmer who 
studied a model where the local growth rate (the source term in 
the Navier stokes equation) depended on the concentration of two 
signaling factors, SHH and FGF </p>

<p>15   . A more recent model for limb bud 
growth explores the impact of differential tissue elasticity 
16 . Other 
models have focused on particular regulatory interactions that pat-
tern the limb expression domains, i.e. the AER-ZPA regulatory inter-
action 
17 , the establishment of the proximal and distal signaling 
centers </p>

<p>18   , and the diffusivity of SHH </p>

<p>19   . 
Most models, however, have focused on the skeletal patterns that 
emerge during limb bud development </p>

<p>20-29   . A number of different 
model types have been studied ranging from continuous to cell-based 
models and from rule-based stochastic models to reaction-diffusion 
models; for reviews see </p>

<p>30,31   . Turing mechanisms are a particular type 
of reaction-diffusion models 
32 and have been frequently invoked to 
explain the emergence of pattern during development </p>

<p>33   ; they have 
been studied in the context of limb patterning since 1979 </p>

<p>34   . In Turing 
models the number of modes (patterns) increases with larger domain 
size. Newman and co-workers showed that the different number of 
skeletal elements in the stylopod, zeugopod, and autopod in anterior-
posterior direction can in principle be achieved as a result of the 
increase in the proximal-distal length; here they have to assume that 
patterns emerge sequential in stylopod, zeugopod, and autopod and 
are fixed (frozen) upon their emergence </p>

<p>23   . Newman and co-workers </p>

<p>further showed that parameter values can be identified that give 
realistic steady state pattern if the equations are solved on static 
domains whose shapes are based on the limb shapes of various fos-
sils 
35 . However, there is no evidence that the patterning domain in the 
embryo has the same shape as the adult fossil and patterning is well 
known to occur on a growing rather than static domain. Miura and 
co-workers explored how the speed of pattern emergence could be 
affected 
24 and studied Turing patterning on growing limb domains </p>

<p>22   . 
In particular, Miura and co-workers show that a Turing model can 
explain the increased number of digits in the doublefoot mutant with 
the observed increased domain size </p>

<p>22   . 
The many computational studies show that Turing models, in 
principle, are sufficiently flexible to account for the experimentally 
observed pattern in wildtype and mutant limb buds. However, in 
spite of the demonstrated sensitivity of Turing models to domain 
size and particular reaction types and kinetics the models have so 
far not been solved on realistic domains with biochemically real-
istic reaction kinetics. Recent efforts in this direction have been 
made by the Newman group who propose TGF-beta family 
ligands as the activator and FGFs, Noggin, Notch and/or CHL2 
as the inhibitor in their Turing models with Schnakenberg kin-
etics 
21,23,35 . However, mutant mice with defects in TGF-beta 
36 , 
FGF 
37-39 , Noggin 
40 , and Notch 
41 signaling all have digits, while 
CHL2 expression has been found to be restricted to chondrocytes 
of various developing joint cartilage surfaces and connective tis-
sues in reproductive organs 
42 . While it is possible that the appar-
ent robustness of the patterning mechanism to these mutations is 
a consequence of redundant regulatory interactions, we wondered 
whether the reported regulatory interactions would allow us to 
construct a model that would be consistent with available experi-
mental data and that would not have to rest on missing data and 
redundancy arguments. 
Advances in experimental techniques now provide us with 
detailed information regarding the domain geometries </p>

<p>14   , the timing 
of the processes, and the regulatory interactions </p>

<p>1,2,43   . Limb buds first 
form around embryonic day (E)9.5 while expression of Sox9, an early 
marker for tissue condensations, is first observed around E10.5 in the </p>

<p>Figure 1 | The emergence of pattern on the limb bud-shaped domain. (A-H) The expression pattern of Sox9 in mouse embryos with developmental </p>

<p>time (in embryonic days). Panel (A-E) was reproduced from Fig. 1A-E in </p>

<p>44 </p>

<p>; Panel (F-H) was reproduced from Fig. 2 in </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>. (J-L) The distribution of the 
BR 
2 complex at different simulation times (J) t 5 150, (K) t 5 350 (L) t 5 750. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 991 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00991 </p>

<p>
central mesenchyme of the limb bud (Fig. 1A </p>

<p>44 </p>

<p>). Around E11 the 
Sox9 expression pattern splits and a region in the stalk patterns the 
stylopod, two patches mark the zeugopod, and a region of strong 
expression marks the autopod (Fig. 1B,F, </p>

<p>44,45   ). Around E11.5 the 
autopod expression pattern splits into distinct patches that mark 
the different digits (Fig. 1C,G, </p>

<p>44,45   ). Over the next day more defined 
and elongated Sox9 expression pattern emerge that resemble the final 
digit structure (Fig. 1D,E,H </p>

<p>44,45   ). Sox9 expression has been shown to 
be stimulated by BMP-2 
46 and the BMP-2 dependent increase in Sox9 
then triggers increased expression of Noggin 
47 which acts as an ant-
agonist of BMP signaling by sequestering BMP in inactive com-
plexes </p>

<p>48   . Noggin null mice form digits, but the digit condensations 
are much wider than in wildtype 
40 . Much as Sox9, Noggin is 
expressed in digit condensations and serves as a marker of endo-
chondral differentiation </p>

<p>40   . 
Even though BMPs also induce the expression of the BMP ant-
agonist Gremlin </p>

<p>49   , Gremlin (unlike Noggin) is expressed in the inter-
digital space rather than in the digit condensations 
50 . Another study 
notes a concentration-dependent regulation of Gremlin expression 
in that low concentrations of BMP2 upregulate Gremlin while high 
concentrations of BMP2 downregulate Gremlin in limb mesench-
yme cultures </p>

<p>51   . It is thus possible that stronger BMP signaling in the 
digit condensations induces Sox9 while weaker BMP signaling in the 
interdigital space induces Gremlin. Similarly, it has been suggested 
that low BMP concentrations support expression of FGF8 while high 
BMP concentrations repress FGF4 and FGF8 expression in the 
apical ectodermal ridge (AER) </p>

<p>52,53   . Two different BMP receptors 
are expressed in the limb mesenchyme, BMPR1a (ALK3) and 
BMPR1b (ALK6) that bind the different BMP ligands with different 
affinities. BMPR1a binds mainly BMP4 while BMPR1b binds BMP4, 
BMP2 and less well to BMP7 </p>

<p>54,55   . The BMP4-BMPR1b affinity has 
been established in a Scatchard plot as Kd 5 530 pM </p>

<p>55   . Activin 
receptors (ActRI/ALK2 and ActRII) are also expressed in the limb 
mesenchyme 
56 but appear to bind their BMP ligands with lower 
affinity 
57 . BMP7 binds ActRII with 3-fold higher affinity compared 
to BMP2 (Kd 5 1.7 mM versus 5.4 mM) and binds ActRI/ALK2 only 
with low affinity (Kd 5 143 mM) </p>

<p>57   . It should be noted that the values 
are based on Biacore measurements and thus do not adequately 
reflect the cooperative binding effects. 
In both mouse and chicken expression of BMPR1b is restricted to 
precartilaginous condensations 
58,59 while Bmpr1a is expressed at low 
levels throughout the limb bud mesenchyme </p>

<p>59,60   . In the chicken 
Bmpr1a expression is elevated at the border between precartilagi-
nous condensations and mesenchyme, but low or absent in the 
precartilaginous condensations. Accordingly, overexpression of 
dominant negative (DN)-BRK-2 (the chicken receptor that corre-
sponds to the mouse BMPR1B receptor) blocks chondrogenesis, but 
not overexpression of (DN)-BRK-1 (which corresponds to mouse 
BMPR1A) or DN-ActR1 </p>

<p>60,61   . BMPR1B thus appears to be the major 
transducer of BMP signals in chicken limb condensations. 
In the chicken the two receptors have been shown to be engaged in 
different regulatory interactions. Thus BMP beads induce noggin, 
tgfb2, and bmpr1b expression only when implanted into the tip of the 
chicken digit, but not when implanted in the interdigital space. Also 
bmpr1a is not expressed when BMP beads are implanted in the 
interdigital space while expression of the bmpR-1b gene was 
enhanced in the adjacent digits with the spatial distribution appear-
ing displaced toward the margin of the digits adjacent to the bead </p>

<p>62   . 
It therefore seems that in the chicken only BMPR1b (but not 
BMPR1a) enhances its own expression in response to ligand binding. 
TGF-beta beads also induce the expression of noggin in the inter-
digital regions but only with a time delay: noggin expression is 
detected after 30 hours, while bmpr1b expression becomes detect-
able in the interdigital region already after 10 hours. TGF-beta thus 
most likely induces noggin expression indirectly by inducing bmpr1b 
expression </p>

<p>62   . </p>

<p>There are important differences between mouse and chicken limb 
development as there are differences between forelimb and hindlimb 
development. We will therefore mainly focus on mouse forelimb bud 
development and comment on other limb buds as appropriate. In the 
mouse both Bmpr1a and BmpR1b expression is elevated in the pre-
cartilaginous condensations and Bmpr1a and Bmpr1b can compens-
ate for each other </p>

<p>59,60   . BMPR1b null mice show normal digit 
patterning and no differences in Sox9 expression are observed in 
wild-type and BmprIB2/2 limbs up to and including E12.5, indi-
cating that the prechondrogenic limb mesenchyme is specified and is 
able to form condensations up to this time </p>

<p>60,63,64   . BmprIA2/2 
embryos are not viable and the severity of the BmprIA2/2 con-
ditional knock-out depends on the stage at which BmprIA2/2 is 
removed. Cre-mediated excision in Col2-Cre mice seems to occur 
only in forming cartilaginous condensations, while in Prx1-Cre mice, 
it acts in limb mesenchyme at much earlier stages (95% active by 
E.10.5) 
63 . If BMP receptor type IA is removed with Col2-Cre digit 
condensations can still be observed while in Prx1-Cre mice no digits 
form in the forelimb </p>

<p>63   . The mutants have shortened limbs and show 
almost complete agenesis of the autopod because of reduced cell 
proliferation </p>

<p>63   . Moreover, the expression of BMP target genes 
Msx1/2 and Grem are severely reduced. BMPR1b appears to rescue 
Msx1/2 expression. However, the expression is then colocalized 
with the patchy BMPR1B expression </p>

<p>63   . In the mouse BMPR1a 
thus appears to be the major transducer of BMP signals in limb 
condensations. 
In the limb there are three important BMP ligands: BMP2, BMP4, 
and BMP7 </p>

<p>65   . BMP2 and BMP4 appear to be the most important BMP 
ligands, but also in the BMP2: BMP4 double conditional knock-out 
some digits still form </p>

<p>66   . At E12.5 BMP2 is expressed predominantly 
in the interdigital webbing, BMP4 is expressed along the whole AER, 
and BMP7 expression is ubiquitous in the limb bud </p>

<p>65   . Bmp2 con-
ditional mutants form five digits, conditional inactivation of a gene 
for BMP4 results in a polydactylous phenotype </p>

<p>67   , but in BMP2:BMP4 
conditional mutants two posterior digits are missing even though the 
limb field is broader </p>

<p>66   . Bmp7 null mice show an occasional anterior 
polydactyly </p>

<p>65   . Importantly, even though BMP4 expression is reduced 
in the conditional BMP4 knock-out BMP signaling activity is 
increased </p>

<p>68   . To avoid the redundant role of multiple BMP ligands 
and receptors Zeller and co-workers conditionally removed the 
downstream signaling protein Smad4 (Co-Smad). The mutants still 
express Sox9 in the autopod but the pattern does not split into 
digits </p>

<p>69   . Smad4-dependent signaling is therefore necessary for digit 
formation. 
BMP signaling is embedded in a larger network that most impor-
tantly comprises FGFs and SHH in the limb. BMP signaling inter-
feres with FGF-dependent signaling, at least in part by repressing 
expression of its receptor FGFR1 </p>

<p>70   . FGF-loaded beads in turn repress 
BMPR1b and Noggin expression in chicken limb buds </p>

<p>62   . In mouse 
limb buds FGFs repress the expression of the BMP antagonists 
Gremlin 
71 and enhance the expression of SHH in the ZPA, which 
in turn enhances Gremlin expression. SHH induces the expression of 
BMP-2 and BMP-7 in chicken limb buds, and with a delay that of 
BRK2 (BMPR1b) </p>

<p>61   . Without SHH digits cannot form unless express-
ion of Gli3 is removed as well </p>

<p>10   . In the absence of SHH signaling Gli3 
forms the Gli3 repressor which prevents the expression of Gremlin 
and many other genes. However, in the absence of both SHH and 
Gli3 more digits appear than in the wildtype. Neither SHH nor Gli3 
are therefore necessary for digit formation. Both Fgf4 and SHH 
expression terminate around E12 
43 but Fgf8 continues to be 
expressed in the AER. 
Given the complex regulatory interactions it is difficult to under-
stand and predict the regulatory outcome by verbal reasoning. We 
therefore sought to build and analyse a computational model of these 
interactions. In light of the presence of digits without Shh/Gli3, and 
the absence of digits in BMPR1A and SMAD4 conditional mutants </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 991 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00991 </p>

<p>
we focus on BMP-dependent signaling to explain the observed pat-
terning of Sox9 in the limb bud. We find that the interactions 
between BMP and BMP receptor give rise to a Schnakenberg-type 
Turing mechanism. When we solve the model on a realistic domain 
we obtain patterns that are similar to those observed in experiments 
with wildtype and mutant mice. We propose that the observed pat-
terning during limb bud development may be the consequence of a 
Turing type patterning mechanism that arises from the interactions 
between BMPs and their receptor. </p>

<p>Results 
Model. The core signaling pathways that regulate limb patterning 
have been well characterized and comprise, SHH, GLI, Gremlin, 
BMP, FGF, and their receptors </p>

<p>1,72   . Digit patterning is still observed 
in the absence of Gremlin 
73 , Noggin </p>

<p>40   , SHH and GLI3 </p>

<p>10   , but not in the 
absence of BMPR1A 
63 and Smad4, an essential protein in BMP 
signaling </p>

<p>69   . We therefore neglect all dispensable network elements 
and focus on BMP signaling to explain digit patterning. We will 
include FGF as an important modulator and growth factor. Shh-
dependent signaling is also an important modulator of BMP 
signaling in the limb bud and is clearly important to establish 
the anterior-posterior polarity. Turing patterns have been 
shown to persist in the presence of such a modulating gradient </p>

<p>74   . 
Accordingly, we focus on the mechanism that enables the emergence 
of digits in the autopod and we will neglect the detailed effects of Shh 
and how these enable the establishment of anterior-posterior polarity 
that results in the formation of a thumb and a pinky. 
BMP (which we denote by B) and FGF (denoted by F) are secreted 
proteins and diffuse much faster than the BMP receptor (denoted by 
R) which resides in the plasma membrane. Experiments on the BMP 
Drosophila homologue Dpp suggest that the majority of ligand-
bound receptors, C, are internalised rapidly and reside mainly inside 
the cell </p>

<p>75   . We will therefore ignore diffusion of the receptor-ligand </p>

<p>complex. We write </p>

<p>D j (j 5 B, R, F) for the diffusion coefficients with </p>



<p>D R = D B , D F </p>

<p>76,77   . We write </p>

<p>D: D : </p>

<p>½ for the diffusion fluxes where D </p>

<p>denotes the Laplacian operator in Cartesian coordinates, and con-
centration. The characteristic length of gradients depends both on 
the speed of diffusion and their removal. In the absence of contrary 
experimental evidence we will assume the simplest relation, linear 
decay, at rates d j [j] for all components (i.e. j 5 B, R, C, F). 
BMPs are dimers and one BMP molecule can therefore bind two 
receptors </p>

<p>78   . The rate of BMP-receptor binding is therefore propor-
tional to R 
2 B, and we use k on and k off as the binding and dissociation 
rate constants. BMP2 signaling has been shown to reduce BMP2 
expression in the limb bud 
79 and we therefore make the rate of 
BMP production negatively dependent on the BMP-receptor com-</p>

<p>plex, C, i.e. we write for the BMP production rate P B 
K B 
K B z C 
½ 
and 
thus obtain for the BMP and BMP-receptor dynamics </p>

<p>_ 
B 
Â Ã~ </p>

<p>D B D B </p>

<p>½ 
|fflfflffl{zfflfflffl} </p>

<p>diffusion </p>

<p>z P B 
K B 
K B z C 
½ 
|fflfflfflfflfflffl ffl{zfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>production </p>

<p>{d B B 
½ 
|fflfflffl ffl{zfflfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>degradation </p>

<p>{k on R 
½ 
2 B 
½ zk off C 
½ 
|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>complex formation </p>

<p>ð1Þ </p>

<p>_ 
C 
Â Ã~k 
on R 
½ 
2 B 
½ {k off C 
½ 
|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl} </p>

<p>complex formation </p>

<p>{d C C 
½ 
|fflfflffl ffl{zfflfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>degradation </p>

<p>: 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>Signaling of BMP-bound receptors positively regulates receptor pro-
duction </p>

<p>62   , and we therefore must make receptor production depend-
ent on the concentration of C. In the absence of contrary data we will 
use the simplest possible relation for the receptor production rate and 
write P R ([C]) 5 p R 1 p C [C] where p R and p C are constants, 
_ 
R 
Â Ã~ </p>

<p>D R D R </p>

<p>½ 
|fflfflffl{zfflfflffl} </p>

<p>diffusion </p>

<p>z p R zp C C 
½ 
ð Þ 
|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl} </p>

<p>production </p>

<p>{d R R 
½ 
|fflfflffl ffl{zfflfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>degradation </p>

<p>{2k on R 
½ 
2 B 
½ zk off C 
½ 
|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>complex formation </p>

<p>: ð3Þ </p>

<p>We can simplify this set of equations if we assume that the dynamics 
of the receptor-ligand complex are fast such that the receptor-ligand </p>

<p>complex assumes a quasi steady-state. The concentration of bound 
receptor, C, is then proportional to R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B, i.e. </p>

<p>C 
½ * 
k on 
k off zd C 
R 
½ 
2 B 
½ ~K C R 
½ 
2 B 
½ ; K C~k </p>

<p>on </p>

<p>k off zd C 
: 
ð4Þ </p>

<p>Equations (1,3) are sufficient for pattern formation and would reduce 
to the classical Turing model of Schnakenberg-type if we were to set 
p C 5 2d C , and d B 5 0. 
BMP expression and activity is modulated by FGF and Gremlin </p>

<p>68   . 
BMP induces Gremlin expression and Gremlin then binds and 
sequesters BMP in an inactive complex </p>

<p>51,80   . Gremlin can in principle 
be secreted, but experimental evidence suggests that BMP4 activation 
and secretion are also negatively regulated by an intracellular 
Gremlin-BMP4 interaction </p>

<p>81   . We therefore do not consider 
Gremlin diffusion. Since experiments suggest that also Gremlin is 
a dimer 
82 we assume 151 binding between BMP and Gremlin at rate 
k </p>

<p>' </p>

<p>on [B][G] and dissociation at rate k </p>

<p>' </p>

<p>off [BG] where we write G for 
Gremlin and BG for the BMP-Gremlin complex. If we model BMP-</p>

<p>induced expression by a Hill function 
B 
½ </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>B 
½ 
n zk n </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>with Hill constant K G </p>

<p>and Hill coefficient n, and assume that dissociation of the complex (at 
rate k </p>

<p>' </p>

<p>off ) is much faster than its degradation then the previous system 
of equations would need to be expanded to include </p>

<p>_ 
B 
Â Ã~ </p>

<p>D B D B </p>

<p>½ 
|fflfflffl{zfflfflffl} </p>

<p>dif f usion </p>

<p>z P B z 
K B 
K B z C 
½ 
|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl} </p>

<p>production </p>

<p>{d B B 
½ 
|fflfflffl ffl{zfflfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>degradation </p>

<p>{ k </p>

<p>' </p>

<p>on R 
½ 
2 B 
½ zk </p>

<p>' </p>

<p>of f C 
½ 
|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl} </p>

<p>complex f ormation </p>

<p>{ k </p>

<p>' </p>

<p>on G 
½ B 
½ {k </p>

<p>' </p>

<p>of f BG 
½ 
À 
Á </p>

<p>|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl} </p>

<p>complex f ormation </p>

<p>_ 
G 
Â Ã~p </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>B 
½ </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>B 
½ 
n zK n </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>|fflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>production </p>

<p>{d G G 
½ 
|fflfflfflffl{zfflfflfflffl} </p>

<p>degradation </p>

<p>{k </p>

<p>' </p>

<p>on G 
½ B 
½ zk </p>

<p>' </p>

<p>of f BG 
½ 
|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>complex f ormation </p>

<p>_ 
BG 
Â Ã~k ' 
on G 
½ B 
½ {k </p>

<p>' </p>

<p>of f BG 
½ 
|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl} </p>

<p>complex f ormation </p>

<p>: </p>

<p>ð5Þ </p>

<p>Experiments show that Gremlin is induced by BMP already early 
during limb development </p>

<p>68   . If we assume rapid formation of the 
BMP-Gremlin complex in comparison with other reactions we can 
use a quasi-steady state approximation for complex concentration: </p>

<p>_ 
BG 
Â Ã~k ' 
on G 
½ B 
½ {k </p>

<p>' </p>

<p>off BG 
½ 
|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>complex formation~0 </p>

<p>: 
ð6Þ </p>

<p>The terms for complex formation thus disappear from the equations 
for Gremlin and BMP and the equation for Gremlin uncouples from 
the other equations. Gremlin seems thus not to affect the patterning 
module directly. We therefore ignore the Gremlin-BMP interaction 
in this model, and we will show that the observed oligodactily in the 
Gremlin knock-outs can be explained with the reduced limb bud size. 
Given the importance of FGFs for limb patterning we extended 
the model to also include FGF signaling. Much as BMP, FGFs 
can diffuse rapidly </p>

<p>83   . BMP expression is induced by FGF and the 
parameter P B in (1) thus becomes a function of FGF, F, i.e. </p>

<p>P B F 
ð Þ~p b zp </p>

<p>Ã 
B </p>

<p>F 
½ </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>F 
½ 
n zK n </p>

<p>BF </p>

<p>K B 
K B z C 
½ 
, where K BF and n and the Hill </p>

<p>constant and Hill coefficient respectively. Signaling of BMP-bound 
receptors, C , R 
2 B (4), has been found to both stimulate and inhibit 
FGF-dependent processes </p>

<p>53,84   . Such inconsistent observations may 
be the result of a concentration-dependency of signaling, and it has 
been suggested that high levels of BMP signaling interfere with FGF-
dependent processes while lower levels may positively regulate FGF 
expression in the AER </p>

<p>85   . Hence FGF activity is best described as </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 991 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00991 </p>

<p>
P F C 
½ 
ð Þ~p F 
C 
½ </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>C 
½ 
n zK </p>

<p>n 
F1 </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>n 
F2 </p>

<p>C 
½ 
n zK </p>

<p>n 
F2 </p>

<p>, where K F1 = K F2 are the Hill </p>

<p>constants for the activating and the inhibitory impacts of BMP sig-
naling and n is the Hill coefficient. Here we note that FGF expression 
is restricted to the apical ectodermal ridge (AER), and p F is therefore 
non-zero only on the distal boundary of the domain (dashed part of 
Fig. 2C; simulated expression patterns are shown in Fig. S1, S3G-J). 
We then write for the FGF dynamics </p>

<p>_ 
F 
Â Ã~ 
D F D F 
½ 
|fflffl ffl{zfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>diffusion </p>

<p>z p F 
C 
½ </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>C 
½ 
n zK </p>

<p>n 
F1 </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>n 
F2 </p>

<p>C 
½ 
n zK </p>

<p>n 
F2 </p>

<p>|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>production </p>

<p>{ d F F 
½ 
|ffl{zffl} </p>

<p>degradation </p>

<p>: 
ð7Þ </p>

<p>FGFs repress the expression of the BMP antagonist Gremlin, and 
enhance SHH expression in the ZPA, which in turn enhances 
Gremlin expression. However, as discussed above the Gremlin 
dynamics uncouple from the other equations, while the expression 
of SHH terminates before the expression pattern of Sox9 has 
assumed the characteristic digit pattern 
43-45 and digit patterning 
can still be observed in limb buds when expression of Shh (and 
Gli3) is removed in knock-outs </p>

<p>10   . We thus neither include Gremlin 
nor SHH in the model. </p>

<p>Summary. We propose that the observed patterning in BMP 
signaling is the result of regulatory interactions between BMP, B, 
its receptor R, and FGFs, F as summarized graphically in Fig. 2A. 
The effective interactions in this model are graphically summarized 
in Fig. 2B. As final set of equations we have </p>

<p>_ 
B 
Â Ã~ </p>

<p>D B D B </p>

<p>½ zp b zp </p>

<p>Ã 
B </p>

<p>F 
½ </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>F 
½ 
n zK n </p>

<p>BF </p>

<p>K B 
K B zK C R 
½ 
2 B 
½ </p>

<p>{ </p>

<p>d C K C R 
½ 
2 B 
½ {d B B 
½ </p>

<p>_ 
R 
Â Ã~ </p>

<p>D R D R </p>

<p>½ zp R z p C {2d C 
ð 
Þ K C R 
½ 
2 B 
½ {d R R </p>

<p>_ 
F 
Â Ã~ 
D F D F 
½ zp F 
K C R 
½ 
2 B 
½ 
À 
Á n </p>

<p>K C R 
½ 
2 B 
½ 
À 
Á n zK </p>

<p>n 
F1 </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>n 
F2 </p>

<p>K C R 
½ 
2 B 
½ 
À 
Á n zK </p>

<p>n 
F2 </p>

<p>{d F F 
½ : </p>

<p>ð8Þ </p>

<p>We note that FGFs are not part of the core patterning mechanism. 
For large FGF concentrations ([F] ? K BF ) the equation for F 
uncouples from the other two equations and if the constitutive 
BMP expression p B , p </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>B was sufficiently large patterning could be 
obtained also without FGFs. Further regulatory interactions (like 
those with Gremlin) may tune the parameter values. </p>

<p>Parameter values. The measurement of the parameter values (i.e. 
diffusion coefficients, production and degradation rates) in vivo is 
complicated and has only been carried out in few model systems, but 
not in the limb </p>

<p>86-88   . However, our conclusions do not depend on 
the exact values of parameters, but mainly depend on their 
relative values as can be seen by non-dimensionalizing the model. 
To nondimensionalize the model we need to choose characteristic 
length and time scales, as well as characteristic concentrations. As 
characteristic time scale we use T 5 1/d F , i.e. t 5 Tt. As characteristic 
length scale we chose the characteristic length of the FGF gradient 
l~ffi 
ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
D F =d F 
p 
, i.e. x 5 lf. We non-dimensionalize the FGF 
concentration with respect to the Hill constant K BF , i.e. F 5 [F]/ 
K BF , and the BMP and receptor concentrations with respect to the 
characteristic concentration c 0 5 (K B /K C ) </p>

<p>1/3 </p>

<p>, i.e. B 5 [B]/c 0 , R 5 [R]/ </p>

<p>c 0 . After re-grouping parameters as d i~d </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>d F 
except d C~d </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>d F 
K C c </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 , </p>

<p>r i~p </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>d F c 0 
except r F~p </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>K BF d F 
, n~p </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>d F 
K C c </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 , k i~K </p>

<p>Fi </p>

<p>c 3 
0 K C~K </p>

<p>Fi </p>

<p>K B 
, and </p>

<p>D B~ 
D B </p>



<p>D F 
, D R~ 
D R </p>



<p>D F 
we obtain </p>

<p>LB 
Lt~D 
B D f Bzr B zr </p>

<p>Ã 
B </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>1zF n </p>

<p>1 
1zR 2 B 
{d C R 
2 B{d B B 
ð9Þ </p>

<p>LR 
Lt~D 
R D f Rzr R z n{2d C 
ð 
Þ R 
2 B{d R R 
ð10Þ </p>

<p>LF 
Lt~D 
f Fzr F </p>

<p>R 
2 B 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>R 2 B 
ð 
Þ 
n zk n </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>n 
2 </p>

<p>R 2 B 
ð 
Þ 
n zk n </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>{F: 
ð11Þ </p>

<p>The dimensionless model contains five parameters less and the 
patterning mechanism no longer depends on absolute diffusion 
and decay constants, but only on the relative diffusion coefficients 
and the relative decay rates. Similarly, the absolute protein 
concentrations do not matter but only the relative concentrations 
(as result from the relative expression and decay rates) relative to the 
Hill constant and the effective binding constant K C . </p>

<p>Domain and boundary conditions. The equations were solved on a 
domain whose shape was extracted from limb bud images at E12.5 as 
well as on a growing domain. The idealized domain is shown in 
Fig. 2C. We used zero-flux boundary conditions for B and R as the 
developing limb does not exchange with the surrounding except at 
the flank which is ignored here. FGF production in the AER was 
implemented as a flux boundary condition, i.e. </p>

<p>n : +F~r F 
R 
2 B 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>R 2 B 
ð 
Þ 
n zk </p>

<p>n 
1 </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>n 
2 </p>

<p>R 2 B 
ð 
Þ 
n zk </p>

<p>n 
2 </p>

<p>ð12Þ </p>

<p>whereñ refers to the unit normal vector. We also considered 
alternative implementations with production in a thin layer (Fig. 
S1B-E) or with Eq. 11 defined on the boundary (Fig. S1F). A thin 
layer with flux boundary conditions (Fig. S1C) and with Eq. 11 
defined on the boundary (Fig. S1C) give similar patterns to those 
observed with flux boundary condition on the outer boundary (Fig. 
S1A). A thin layer with either constant (Fig. S1E) or BMP-dependent 
FGF production (Fig. S1D) yielded overall the same pattern (same 
number of spots) but the shape of the spots was different. </p>

<p>Figure 2 | The model. (A) The network represents the regulatory </p>

<p>interactions that were considered in the model. Thus BMP binds the 
receptor reversibly to form BMP-receptor complexes. BMP-receptor 
complexes induce the production of receptors and enhances FGF activity. 
FGF induces BMP expression. (B) The effective regulatory interactions as 
captured by Eq (9)-(11). Thus BMP, B, has a positive impact on receptors, 
R, and on FGF, F, (both via BMP-receptor complexes that are not included 
here). Receptors are auto-activating (when bound by BMP), while BMP 
are auto-inhibitory (as they enhance their own decay by receptor binding). 
FGF and BMP are mutually enhancing each other. For more details see text. 
(C) The computational domain based on the shape of an E11.5 limb bud. 
The values for the different lengths are summarized in Table S1. R i are the 
radial axes of the elliptical limb bud. H 0 and W 0 are the height and width of 
the stalk. H 1 represents the height of the domain in the stalk where the BMP 
expression is enhanced. The dashed line indicates the AER where AER-
FGFs are expressed. For details see text. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 991 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00991 </p>

<p>
Modelling domain growth. Proliferation is not uniform within the 
limb domain but the velocity field has not been published </p>

<p>14   . We 
therefore measured the proximal-distal axis of limb buds over 
developmental time and find that the growth rate is approximately 
linear (Fig. 3A) and we are therefore using a linear growth law with 
growth rate v g . We can then write for the proximal-distal length of 
the limb bud 
L t 
ð Þ~ L 0 z v g t where 
L 0 denotes the initial proximal-
distal length of the limb bud, and t denotes time. 
To conserve mass (rather than concentration) the reaction-
diffusion equations for the soluble factors B and F, equations 9 and 
11 must be expanded to include the advection and dilution terms </p>

<p>89   , 
i.e. </p>

<p>L X 
½ 
Lt 
z+ u X 
½ 
ð </p>

<p>Þ~D x D X </p>

<p>½ zR X 
½ 
ð Þ 
ð13Þ </p>

<p>where u denotes the growth speed. For homogeneous growth at rate </p>

<p>v g in proximal-distal direction y we then have u~_ 
L 
L 
y~ 
v g </p>

<p>L 0 z v g t 
y </p>

<p>such that </p>

<p>L X 
½ 
Lt 
z 
_ 
L 
L 
X 
½ z y+ X 
½ 
ð 
Þ 
L X 
½ 
Lt 
z 
v g </p>

<p>L 0 z v g t 
X 
½ z y 
L X 
½ 
L y </p>



<p>
D x D X </p>

<p>½ zR X 
½ 
ð Þ: </p>

<p>ð14Þ </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Impact of growth on patterning. (A) The increase in the length of the proximal-distal mouse limb bud axis with developmental time (in </p>

<p>embryonic days) measured from forty limb buds images. Linear growth can be observed at rate of 0.6 6 0.1 mm per day (B) Impact of the number of spots 
(digits) on the growth rate. 5 spots (digits) can be obtained over a wider range of growth rates only if we reduce the FGF production rate by 3-fold 
(r Fgrowth &lt;r Fstatic </p>

<p>3, red line); r Fgrowth~rFstatic , black line). (C-E) Snapshots of simulated limb buds at different points. The domain was grown in the 
proximal-distal axes linearly from 20% of final size in 8000 timesteps with r Fgrowth &lt;r Fstatic </p>

<p>3. To prevent the horse shoe patterning from splitting up into 
digits early, r </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>B had to be decreased from 1.3 to 1 by 0.1 every 2000 time and we set r B2 5 5 r B1 to ensure the stalk has uniform patterning. (C) Limb bud at t 
5 4000 and 60% of final size. (D) Limb bud at t 5 5300 and 73% of final size. (E) Limb bud at t 5 8000 and 100% of final size. (F-H) The expression 
pattern of Sox9 in mouse embryos with developmental time (in embryonic days) as reproduced from Fig. 2 in </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 991 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00991 </p>

<p>
To model local growth at the limb boundary (Fig. 4) the direction of 
growth was set to be normal to the boundary and proportional to the 
local FGF concentration, i.e.ũ~v g F 
mñ where vg is the growth speed 
andñ is the unit normal vector on the boundary. The exponent m was 
set to four, even though we note that similar results can be obtained 
with m 5 2. </p>

<p>Patterning on the limb domain. Since the model is an example of a 
Schnakenberg Turing-type model 
90 we expected to find parameter 
ranges for which we would observe the emergence of patterns. To 
judge whether such mechanism could yield realistic patterns in a 
realistic time frame we solved the model on a domain that had 
been extracted from limb bud images taken at E11.5. Sox9 
expression is induced in response to BMP signaling 
91 , and we were 
therefore interested in the pattern of the BMP-receptor complex (C 
5 R 
2 B) which will mark the regions of active BMP signaling. This 
pattern is necessarily distinct from the pattern of BMP expression 
which remains uniform. In spite of uniform expression of BMP we 
observe the emergence of pattern in the BMP-receptor signaling 
domains that resemble the Sox9 pattern observed in experiments 
(Fig. 1J-L). Thus initially (at t 5 150) we observe strong BMP 
signaling (BMP-receptor binding) in the stalk (Fig. 1J) (marking 
the stylopod (s) in the limb bud images in Fig. 1B or the humerus 
(h) in Fig. 1F), two distinct spots in the transition zone from stalk to 
handplate (marking the zeugopod (z) in the limb bud images in 
Fig. 1B or radia (r) and ulna (u) in Fig. 1F) and a homogenous 
expression in the handplate (marking the autopod (a) in the limb 
bud images in Fig. 1B; digit 4 can be discerned already in Fig. 1F). 
Within Dt 5 200 the pattern in the handplate splits in the simulation 
(Fig. 1K) and distinct condensations can be discerned that mark 
digits 2-5 in the limb bud images (Fig. 1C,G). For the horseshoe 
pattern to split the BMP expression rate at the proximal end of the 
domain (rate r b2 ) must be 3-fold higher than the BMP expression 
rate in the ''hand plate'' (rate r b1 ). Without such a local increase in 
BMP expression the horseshoe pattern would not split. With time 
the digit condensations further elongate (Fig. 1D,E,H). In the 
simulations the digit condensations split while elongating (Fig. 1L). 
Elongation of patterns becomes more realistic if we solve the model 
on a uniformly growing domain (Fig. 3E) or if we allow the domain to </p>

<p>expand in direction of the highest FGF concentration (Fig. 4). Such 
deforming growth towards higher FGF concentrations is also 
observed in cultured limb buds </p>

<p>38,92   . To achieve the characteristic 
digit shape it is important that the FGF concentrates distally from 
the BMP-receptor spots (Fig. 4A-C) as also observed in limb buds 
(Fig. 4D). This is achieved only if BMP-receptor signaling has pre-
dominantly a positive impact on FGF expression, i.e. if the BMP 
concentration is relatively low such that k 1 , R 
2 B = k 2 . We 
therefore predict that at the time of digit formation BMP signaling 
enhances rather than represses FGF8 expression. We should stress 
that this is necessary only in order to obtain the correct positioning of 
the FGF8 expression domain. The BMP-receptor pattern described 
above can be obtained independently of whether BMP regulates FGF 
signaling positively or negatively. 
In our simulations 5 spots emerge simultaneously in the handplate 
while in the developing limb digits appear in a sequence (4,2,3/5,1) 
with digit 1 appearing much later than the other digits. Also the 
appearance of digit 1 appears to be regulated in a different way from 
the other digits. Thus digit 1 is still formed in SHH knock-out 
mutants 
10 while digit 1 is lost in FGF8 knock-out mutants 
38 . The 
patterns depend on the specific choice of parameters (Table 1), 
and four instead of five spots could easily be obtained by altering 
any but the receptor expression rate (Fig. 5A). Alternatively the rate 
of FGF expression r F could be lowered 10-fold on the anterior side 
initially and then increase over time; such asymmetry in expression 
pattern is indeed observed in the limb bud. Thus while Fgf8 is 
expressed uniformly in the AER, expression of Fgf4 appears to be 
biased to the posterior site of the limb bud. FGF8 is expressed already 
early during limb bud development and remains expressed through-
out the patterning process while Fgf4 expression is first detected 
around E10.5 and ceases around E12. As a result we expect enhanced 
FGF production in the posterior part of the limb bud at the onset of 
Sox9 expression. However, in this paper we will continue to analyse 
homogenous expression patterns. </p>

<p>Regulatory impact of the parameters. The patterns depend on the 
specific choice of parameters (Table 1) and since the parameters are 
difficult to determine accurately in experiments we wondered how 
sensitive our results would be to variations in parameter values. We </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Free deformation of the domain according to the local concentration of FGF. The FGF patterning gets split up at the positions of the digits due </p>

<p>to the positive feedback of the BR 
2 complex on FGF. The domain can then be deformed by allowing growth normal to the surface according to the local </p>

<p>concentration of FGF. The growth rate is equivalent to [FGF] 
4 3 v g . (A-C) Expression of FGF on the boundary (i.e. r B zr </p>

<p>Ã 
B </p>

<p>R 
2 B 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>R 2 B 
ð 
Þ 
n z K B 
ð Þ 
n ) at different 
simulation times t 5 500, 1500 and 2500. (D) FGF8 expression pattern in mouse limb at E13.5; adapted from Fig. 2C in </p>

<p>95 </p>

<p>; (E-G) The spatial distribution 
of the BR 
2 complex at t 5 500, 1500 and 2500. (H) Sox9 expression pattern in mouse limb buds at E13.5; adapted from Fig. 8M in </p>

<p>104 </p>

<p>. Note that the rates of 
receptor and BMP degradation were increased by 10 percent relative to the standard values used. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 991 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00991 </p>

<p>
find that all model parameters affect the pattern (Fig. 5A). 
Nonetheless the stable parameter ranges are sufficiently wide that 
molecular noise should not affect the patterning process. Parameters 
with particular wide stable ranges include d B , the rate of BMP 
degradation, which can be varied 6-fold without affecting the 
pattern, as well as the expression rates r b2 , r R and r F for BMP, 
receptor, and FGF and the threshold for BMP-dependent FGF 
expression, k 1 . 
Since we know the time scale of the process we can relate the non-
dimensional kinetic rates to their dimensional counterparts. In our 
simulations splitting of the pattern in the handplate takes about Dt 5 
100. The processes of one embryonic day (86400 seconds) therefore 
corresponds to Dt $ 200 such that t 5 1 corresponds to at least t 5 T 
3 t 5 432 seconds in dimensional time. Accordingly the rate of FGF 
removal would correspond to d F 5 1/T , 2 3 10 
23 s 
21 in dimen-
sional terms which is similar to the experimentally reported value of 
10 
23 s 
21 87 . Since in our simulations any change in the rate of FGF 
removal can be counterbalanced by a change in FGF expression 
(Fig. 5B) a two-fold lower rate in FGF removal could also be obtained 
if we reduced the FGF expression rate by about 10-fold. 
The size of the limb bud changes over time but is about 2 milli-
meters (mm) at E12.5, the final time of our simulation. Accordingly 
the length scale is l 5 2 mm/(H 0 1 R 1 1 R 2 )5 2 mm/19.35 5 0.1 
mm and the FGF diffusion coefficient in the model corresponds to 
34 mm 
2 s 
21 . We further require that BMP diffuses about 2.7-fold 
faster than FGF which brings the BMP diffusion constant close to 
the diffusion constant D , 100 mm 
2 s 
21 that is typically measured for 
soluble proteins 
87 unless diffusion is impeded by adsorption to the 
surface 
86 . We further require that the BMP receptor diffuses about 
100-fold more slowly than the BMP protein. The typical range for 
diffusional constants of membrane proteins is several orders of mag-
nitude lower than for proteins in solution (i.e. D 5 0.1 2 0.001 mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>21 76,77   ). A 100-fold reduced diffusion constant may still overesti-
mate the receptor diffusion constant, in particular because the 
receptor would then diffuse a distance of 3.5 cell lengths </p>

<p>(l~ffi 
ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
2D R t 1=2 
p^3 
5 mm) within its receptor half-life time of t 1/2 5 
ln(2)/d R 5 960 s even though receptors are mainly restricted to 
the surface of single cells. We therefore also tested alternative para-
meterizations in which the receptor diffusion constant is 400-fold 
lower than the BMP diffusion constant. Importantly we still obtain </p>

<p>Table 1 | Values of the dimensionless parameters </p>

<p>Parameter </p>

<p>Non-dim 
value 
Description </p>

<p>Production Rates 
r F 
243.1 
max production rate of F 
r R 
0.0145 
Constant production rate of R 
n 
1.361 
max C-dependent rate of R 
production 
r </p>

<p>Ã 
B </p>

<p>12 ? r R </p>

<p>max F-dependent rate of B 
production 
r B1 
0.063 
Constant production rate of B 
in the ''handplate'' 
r B2 </p>

<p>3 ? r B1 </p>

<p>Constant production rate of B 
in the lower stalk (H 1 ) 
Diffusion Coefficients 
D B 
2.7 
BMP diffusion constant 
D R </p>

<p>0.01 ? D B </p>

<p>Receptor diffusion constant 
Decay constants 
d R 
0.135 
Receptor decay constant 
d B </p>

<p>0.15 ? d r </p>

<p>BMP decay constant 
d C 
n/3 
Receptor-ligand complex decay 
constant 
Regulation 
n 
2 
Hill coefficient 
k 1 
0.06588 
Hill constant for BMP R FGF 
positive feedback 
k 2 
very large 
Hill constant for BMP '' FGF 
negative feedback 
Domain Size 
R Ref 
7.74 
Reference radius </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Parameter dependency of patterning. (A) Local stability </p>

<p>analysis. Each parameter as perturbed independently from the reference 
value given in Table 1 as indicated on the vertical axis and the range was 
recorded for which pattern were qualitatively preserved on a static domain. 
The numbers above and below the bar indicate how many digits were either 
gained (1) or lost (2) as the range was exceeded. (B) The parameter space 
for which the pattern is preserved is larger (black line) if parameters are 
changed together as illustrated for the FGF production and degradation 
rates. The simulations were analyzed at t 5 750. Please note that the FGF 
degradation rate determines the time scale of the simulations (T 5 1/d F ). 
Compensation with the FGF production rate thus allow us to simulate the 
processes on different time scales. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 991 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00991 </p>

<p>
qualitative similar, yet smaller and sharper, patterns also with a much 
lower receptor diffusion constant as long as the FGF and BMP 
expression are adjusted accordingly. 
The pattern is also very sensitive to some of the protein expression 
rates. While there are no reported measurements of protein express-
ion rates and concentrations for the limb bud that these constraints 
could be related to, there is a large number of mutant phenotypes that 
can be used for a qualitative comparison. These will be discussed in 
the following. </p>

<p>FGF. Many different FGFs are expressed during limb development. 
In the model we consider only those FGFs that are important during 
digit formation, i.e. FGF4 and FGF8. In mice that are lacking both 
Fgf4 and Fgf8 function in the forelimb AER limb bud mesenchyme 
fails to survive and the limb does not develop </p>

<p>93   . FGF4 is expressed 
only transiently in the limb bud (between E10 and E12 </p>

<p>37,43   ) and 
removal of only FGF4 does not affect digit patterning </p>

<p>39,94   . The 
effect of Fgf8 removal depends on the developmental stage. 
Inactivating Fgf8 in early limb ectoderm (Msx2-cre;Fgf8 hindlimbs 
and in RAR-cre;Fgf8 forelimbs) causes a substantial reduction in 
limb-bud size, a delay in SHH expression, misregulation of Fgf4 
expression, and loss of digit 1 (the thumb) 
38 . In contrast, when 
functional Fgf8 is transiently expressed, as in Msx2-cre;Fgf8 
forelimbs, digit 1 is present and digit 2 or 3 is lost </p>

<p>37   . If we remove 
50% of Fgf expression in our model we observe less separation 
between the spots, similar to what would be expected in syndactyly 
(Fig. 6A). To lose a digit we need to reduce FGF expression to less 
than 10% of its normal levels. In this case we lose the middle digit as is 
the case in Msx2-cre;Fgf8 forelimbs without causing syndactyly. One </p>

<p>explanation for the quantitative differences could be the dominance 
of FGF8 expression at later stages of limb bud development such that 
removal of Fgf8 corresponds to removing 90% of FGF activity. 
All of the skeletal defects caused by inactivation of Fgf8 can 
be rescued when Fgf4 is expressed in place of Fgf8 
95 . On the protein 
level FGF4 can thus functionally replace FGF8 in limb skeletal 
development. An increase in FGF signaling that occurs when the 
Fgf4 gain-of-function allele is activated in a wild-type limb bud 
causes formation of a supernumerary posterior digit (postaxial poly-
dactyly), as well as cutaneous syndactyly between all the digits </p>

<p>95   . 
Increasing Fgf expression by 50% indeed results in supernumerary 
digits (Fig. 6B). If the additional expression is restricted to the pos-
terior side (where Fgf4 is predominantly expressed) then the 50% 
increase results in the posterior placement of one supernumerary 
digit as well as a merging of spots on the anterior side which would 
correspond to syndactyly (Fig. 6C). 
The model further predicts that the expression and distribution of 
FGFs remains homogenous initially, but subsequently forms distinct 
patches as indeed observed in experiments (Fig. S3G-J). </p>

<p>BMP. There are several BMPs expressed in the developing limb, 
including most importantly BMP2, BMP4, and BMP7 </p>

<p>65   . Much as 
observed for BMP2 in experiments 
79 we predict BMP to be first 
expressed rather homogenously at the boundary of the domain 
and to be subsequently expressed most strongly outside the digit 
domains. In our simulation a lower BMP production rate leads to 
digit loss (Fig. 6E) as indeed observed in the BMP2:BMP4 
conditional knock-out </p>

<p>66   . A 30% increased production rate results 
in polydactyly in our simulation (Fig. 6F) and ectopically </p>

<p>Figure 6 | The impact of protein production rates on digit numbers. (A-D) The impact of changes in the FGF production rate on patterning. (A) A 91% </p>

<p>reduction in the FGF expression rate results in the loss of one pattern (digit). (B) Additional spots emerge as the FGF production rate is increased 
uniformly by 50%. (C) One additional spot emerges on the posterior site (RHS) if FGF expression is enhanced by 50% only on the posterior site (RHS). 
Spots on the anterior side (LHS) merge as characteristic for syndactyly. (D) The number of digits at different relative FGF production rates (1 corresponds 
to the reference rate in Table 1) for t 5 750. Loss of digits at higher FGF production rates is due to presence of stripes; spots can be recovered if simulations 
are run longer. (E-H) The impact of changes in the BMP production rate. (E) Digits are lost when the BMP production rate is reduced to 50%. (F) 
Additional spots emerge as the BMP production rate is increased by 30%. (G) The pattern merge (polysyndactily) as the BMP production rate is increased 
by 50%. (H) The number of digits at different relative BMP production rates (1 corresponds to the reference rate in Table 1) for t 5 750. Note that at 
higher production rates pattern merge and digits are no longer observed. The constant but spatially modulated BMP production rates r B1 , r B2 (black and 
blue lines) and the FGF-dependent BMP production rate r B* (red line) have different effects on the patterning. The spatially modulated BMP r B2 in the 
stalk has little impact at larger values because most BMP then binds to receptors in the stalk. The spot(s) at the proximal end of the stalk and the two spots 
appearing at the transition from the stalk to the circular domain were preserved under all conditions and thus not counted. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 991 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00991 </p>

<p>
expressed BMP2 indeed induces duplication of digit 2 and 
bifurcation of digit 3 </p>

<p>84   . Moreover, conditional inactivation of the 
gene for BMP4 results in polydactyly 
67 and other experiments 
reveal that even though conditional inactivation of a gene for 
BMP4 downregulates BMP4 expression, the overall amount of 
BMP signaling increases 
68 . As the BMP expression rate is further 
increased in our simulations ($50% increase) the patterns merge 
to give rise to polysyndactily (Fig. 6G). Such strong over-
expression has not yet been achieved in mutants so that we cannot 
check this prediction. </p>

<p>BMP receptor. Conditional mutants of BMP receptor type IA lack 
digits. Since the receptor is an integral part of the proposed Turing 
mechanism we obtain loss of digits also in the model. Hypomorphic 
mutants of the BMP receptor have not been described; the model 
would predict loss of digits (Fig. S3). Mild overexpression of the 
receptor should lead to a gain of digits while stronger over-
expression will lead to a loss of patterning (Fig. S3). 
We conclude that the expression rates of BMP and BMP receptor 
need to be tightly controlled to permit patterning. While FGF is not 
an essential part of the patterning module FGF enhances BMP pro-
duction and can thus affect the number of digits. </p>

<p>The impact of domain size and shape. Turing patterns depend on 
the size of the computational domain and more modes (patterns) 
emerge as the size of the domain increases </p>

<p>90   . Several mouse mutants 
have been reported with different shapes and sizes of their limb 
domain, and larger domains typically correlate with increased digit 
numbers. Thus GLI3 mutants are polydactylous and the limb 
domain seems to be widened to 130% while Gremlin mutants are 
oligodactylous and the limb domain is shrink to about 60% of its 
original size </p>

<p>10,73   . Previous theoretical models showed that such a 
correlation can in principle be explained with Turing models 
22 , but 
the domain shapes were not based on real limb buds and no 
quantitative comparison of domain size and digit number was 
previously carried out. When we shrink the computational domain 
uniformly to 60% of its original size we observe a decrease to two 
BMP-receptor (BR </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) patches (Fig. 7A,B), much as is observed in 
experiments </p>

<p>73   . When we enlarge the computational domain 
uniformly to 130% of its original size the digit number more than 
doubles (Fig. 7A). However, in the GLI3 
2/2 mutant the expansion is 
observed only along the anterior-posterior axis </p>

<p>10   . If we increase only 
the anterior-posterior axis of the limb bud to 130% we observe four 
additional digits which emerge mainly in the middle of the domain 
(Fig. 7C,D). A closer analysis of GLI3 
2/2 mutants reveals that limb 
buds are expanded mainly to the anterior side and that extra digits 
are concentrated in the anterior domain, while the posterior side is 
about normal. When we analysed a domain that was expanded by 
160% to the anterior and constant on the posterior side we observed 
three additional spots which now emerge in the anterior side 
(Fig. 7E,F). This corresponds well to the 8 digits observed in the 
GLI32/2 null mouse </p>

<p>10   . </p>

<p>The impact of growth. The limb bud grows while patterns emerge. 
Given the importance of domain size and shape we wondered how 
growth would affect the patterning process. We measured images of 
limb buds between E9 and E13 and noticed an almost linear growth 
in proximal-distal direction (Fig. 3A). Limb buds increase in length 
by about 5-fold within the first four days of development. When we 
solved the model on a linearly, uniformly growing domain we obtain 
similar patterns as before (Fig. 3C). However, the number of digits 
strongly depends on the growth speed (Fig. 3B). For low growth rates 
we can adjust the number of digits with the help of the other 
parameters. For increasing growth speeds the speed greatly affects 
the patterning process and we both lose and gain digits (Fig. 3B). As 
the growth speed further increases patterns merge and eventually all 
digits are lost (Fig. 3B). From Figure 3A we can estimate the growth </p>

<p>speed as about 7.7 nanometers per second. In dimensionless terms (T 
5 432 sec and l 5 0.1 mm) this corresponds to a growth speed of 
about v g 5 0.03 which is too large to permit patterning (Fig. 3B). This 
may be the reason why there is a the complex pre-patterning process 
that we do not consider in this model and which starts already 
around E9.5 
1,2 . The complex regulatory interactions prior to the 
emergence of digits adjust the expression domains of BMP and 
FGFs in the limb bud. Such embedding of a Turing mechanism 
into a sophisticated regulatory network may be important to 
permit the patterning process to proceed on a rapidly growing 
domain. Further experiments combined with more detailed 
modelling also of the other parts of the regulatory network present 
in the developing limb will, however, be required to either confirm a 
receptor-ligand based Turing mechanism (embedded in a wider 
network) or to define an alternative mechanism for digit 
patterning on the rapidly growing limb bud. </p>

<p>Discussion 
Limb development has been studied for decades and much is known 
about the molecular networks that regulate limb development </p>

<p>1,2   . </p>

<p>Figure 7 | Impact of domain size on patterning. (A) Number of spots </p>

<p>(digits) on a domain that is changed uniformly in its size. (B) Patterning on 
a domain that is uniformly shrunk to 60% of its normal size. (C) Number 
of spots (digits) on a domain where the length of the posterior and anterior 
axes (R 3 and R 4 ) are changed as indicated. (D) Patterning on a domain 
where the AP axis (R 3 and R 4 ) is expanded to 130% of its normal size. (E) 
Number of spots (digits) on a domain where the length of the anterior axis 
(R 3 ) is changed as indicated. (F) Patterning on a domain where the anterior 
axis (R 3 ) is expanded to 160% of its normal size. Note: The spot(s) at the 
proximal end of the stalk and the two spots appearing at the transition 
from the stalk to the circular domain were preserved under all conditions 
and are thus not counted in panels A,C,E. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 991 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00991 </p>

<p>
Based on the available information BMP signaling appears to be the 
key signaling pathway that regulates the expression of Sox9, the first 
marker of digit condensations. When modelling BMP signaling we 
noticed that the regulatory interactions with its receptor constitute a 
Turing mechanisms. Pattern thus easily emerge. The emerging pat-
tern sensitively depended on the shape and size of the domain, and 
only when we solved the set of equations on a domain that had been 
extracted from limb bud images we could reproduce patterns of 
BMP-receptor activity that resembled the experimentally observed 
patterns for Sox9. An important test for the suitability of a math-
ematical model is its consistency of model predictions with a wide 
range of independent experimental observations. Limb bud develop-
ment has been studied intensively and a large body of experimental 
results exists to test the model with. If parameters are chosen appro-
priately also the phenotype of available mutants can be reproduced. 
The mechanism is robust to small changes in the parameters as may 
arise from molecular noise. 
Interestingly, while we achieve good correspondence to available 
experimental data on the static domain, formation of a Turing pat-
tern fails on a domain that grows as fast as measured in the embryo. 
We propose that the early pre-patterning that involves also SHH/ 
Ptch/Gli signaling as well as the many other regulatory interactions 
that we ignore in this simple model are in place to support the 
patterning mechanism on a rapidly growing domain. We are cur-
rently developing a simulation for these processes to better under-
stand the impact of these earlier regulatory processes. 
Many models have previously been proposed to explain the emer-
gence of digits, and Turing models in particular have been found 
previously to be sufficiently flexible to recapitulate the various pat-
terning aspects of digit emergence </p>

<p>30,31,34   . So far, however, it had been 
difficult to link the components of a potential Turing mechanism to 
the molecular constituents. We propose that the Turing pattern in 
the limb arises from a ligand-receptor interaction. For this to work 
the ligand needs to be a dimer as is the case for BMPs 
78 . Moreover, the 
receptor needs to diffuse, yet at a much lower speed than the ligands 
as is indeed the case. We notice that the diffusion constant that we are 
using in this simulation is on the high end of what is plausible; lower 
receptor diffusion constants can be accommodated but the pattern is 
then sharper and smaller. Again it is possible and plausible that the 
additional regulatory interactions in the limb bud help to expand the 
pattern. 
We have previously proposed a mechanism for branch point 
and branch mode selection in the developing lung 
96 . Inte-
restingly, also here receptor-ligand interactions gave rise to a 
Turing pattern that could recapitulate the different observed 
branching patterns in the developing lung for physiological para-
meters and a similar mechanism can be identified also for the 
developing kidney (Menshykau et al, submitted). While all three 
systems are based on different signaling proteins (i.e. BMPs in the 
limb, SHH in the lung, and GDNF in the ureter) they may all 
exploit the same mechanism to pattern an embryonic field in that 
these proteins are all multimers that interact with their receptors in 
a way that induces receptor expression. Interestingly, while BMP 
can affect its own expression either in a positive or negative feed-
back via FGFs 
52,53 , SHH in the lung clearly engages in a negative 
feedback via FGF10, while GDNF in the ureter engages in a pos-
itive feedback via Wnt signaling 
97 . We can obtain the same pattern 
with a positive and a negative feedback in the limb, lung, and 
ureter. However, we notice that the possible parameter space is 
wider in case of a positive feedback. It will be interesting to model 
further embryonic self-organizing systems to see whether a recep-
tor-ligand interaction may be a general paradigm to enable Turing 
pattern to emerge in developmental systems. 
Further advancements in our understanding of limb development 
will require the development of three-dimensional models and 
the inclusion of more signaling factors. The parameterization and </p>

<p>validation of such models will require new experimental data that 
also reveal the three dimensional dynamics. Such information can 
now be acquired with the help of optical projection tomographs </p>

<p>98   . 
Further advances in experimental techniques can thus be expected to 
provide exciting new insights into the regulatory processes of digit 
formation during limb development. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Numerical solution of PDEs. The PDEs were solved with finite element methods as 
implemented in <rs id="software-1" type="software">COMSOL Multiphysics</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">4.1 and 4.2</rs>. COMSOL Multiphysics is a well-
established software package and several studies confirm that COMSOL provides 
accurate solutions to reaction-diffusion equations both on constant 
99 and growing 
two-dimensional domains </p>

<p>100-102   . Both mesh and the time step were refined until 
further refinement no longer resulted in noticeable improvements as judged by eye. 
The simulations were optimised for computational efficiency as described in 
103 . </p>

<p> </p>

<p>
 </p>



<p>
Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors are grateful for permission from Development to reproduce Fig 1A-E from 
Kawakami et al., Fig 2 from Stricker &amp; Mundlos, Fig 2C from Lu et al., and Fig. 8M from 
Bangs et al., to the Zeller group for sharing unpublished data, to Victoria Nemeth and 
Marcus Groote for discussions of numerical methods, and to the Iber group for the critical 
reading of the manuscript. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>DI and CK developed the model. AB, CK, PG and DM carried out the analysis. DI wrote the 
manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>License: This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareALike 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this 
license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Badugu, A., Kraemer, C., Germann, P., Menshykau, D. &amp; Iber, D. 
Digit patterning during limb development as a result of the BMP-receptor interaction. Sci. 
Rep. 2, 991; DOI:10.1038/srep00991 (2012). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 991 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00991 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>