<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3449286" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Porphyry systems supply most copper and significant gold to our economy. Recent studies indicate that they 
are frequently associated with high Sr/Y magmatic rocks, but the meaning of this association remains 
elusive. Understanding the association between high Sr/Y magmatic rocks and porphyry-type deposits is 
essential to develop genetic models that can be used for exploration purposes. Here we present results on a 
Pleistocene volcano of Ecuador that highlight the behaviour of copper in magmas with variable (but 
generally high) Sr/Y values. We provide indirect evidence for Cu partitioning into a fluid phase exsolved at 
depths of ,15 km from high Sr/Y (.70) andesitic magmas before sulphide saturation. This lends support to 
the hypothesis that large amounts of Cu-and S-bearing fluids can be accumulated into and released from a 
long-lived high Sr/Y deep andesitic reservoir to a shallower magmatic-hydrothermal system with the 
potential of generating large porphyry-type deposits. </p>

<p>Material 1). Therefore, the Pilavo magmatic system is suitable for the 
investigation of magmatic processes potentially associated with the 
development of porphyry systems. 
Basaltic andesites of Pilavo are characterized by variable contents of 
incompatible elements (e.g., Th, U, Zr, REE, Sr, Ba) and Sr/Y values 
(40 to 80), which are a result of contrasting residence times in the mid-
crustal reservoir </p>

<p>37   . Incompatible element poorer magmas with lower 
Sr/Y (40-50) did not evolve significantly in the mid-crustal reservoir 
and reflect the compositions of the hydrous, high-alumina basaltic 
andesites formed at the mantle-crust boundary </p>

<p>37   . These magmas crys-
tallized small amounts of amphibole (,3% modal) during ascent to 
shallow levels where degassing caused extensive plagioclase crystalliza-
tion, magma stalling, and mixing in the conduit (at P,0.1 GPa) with 
high-alumina basaltic magmas coming from depth </p>

<p>37   . In contrast, 
incompatible element-rich magmas with higher Sr/Y (.50 and up 
to 80) resulted from more or less prolonged evolution in the mid-
crustal (,0.4 GPa) composite reservoir where they fractionated, 
assimilated and were recharged by the high-alumina mafic magma </p>

<p>37   . 
Magmas with higher Sr/Y values contain significantly more amphibole 
(up to ,20% modal) </p>

<p>37   . Therefore, modal amphibole concentrations 
suggest that increasing water contents in magmas with higher Sr/Y 
values occur as a consequence of more extensive fractionation at mid-
crustal levels </p>

<p>37   . Throughout the series, magmas are strongly oxidized 
(fO 2 5NNO11.5 to 13.3). The high oxidation state of the Pilavo 
magmas is recorded by magnetite-ilmenite pairs within amphibole 
and is likely the result of both an oxidized mantle source and an 
intracrustal evolution in which amphibole fractionation occurs </p>

<p>37   . </p>

<p>Results 
We have analysed Cu contents in plagioclase, amphibole and clin-
opyroxene phenocrysts by LA-ICPMS (see Methods and Supple-
mentary Material 2). Maximum Cu pyroxene contents remain consis-
tently below 30 ppm throughout the Pilavo series rocks (Sup-
plementary Material 2). In contrast, maximum Cu amphibole and 
Cu plagioclase contents vary with rock geochemistry (Figure 1): rocks 
with lower Sr/Y values have much higher Cu amphibole (.200 ppm) 
and Cu plagioclase (generally 400-500 but up to .2000 ppm) than 
rocks with high Sr/Y (Cu plagioclase and Cu amphibole 5 40250 ppm). 
In low Sr/Y rocks the highest Cu plagioclase contents occur in plagio-
clase growth zones with abundant fluid and melt inclusions, situated 
between core and rim (Figures 2a-b). Within the inclusion-free 
zones the Cu plagioclase contents drop significantly (,5 ppm; Sup-
plementary Materials 2 and 5). During ablation, Cu amphibole exhibits 
a smooth and stable intensity signal (Supplementary Material 3). In 
contrast, the Cu plagioclase intensities resulting from the ablation of the 
inclusion-rich areas of plagioclase vary erratically with high peaks 
lifting the average concentrations of the time-integrated analyses 
(Supplementary Material 3). These peaks are likely the result of 
ablating Cu-rich inclusions within the plagioclase. In order to test 
such a hypothesis we have investigated by SEM plagioclase fragments 
that had been hammer-broken and not washed to preserve the integ-
rity of soluble phases possibly occurring in fluid inclusions. Indeed, 
SEM imaging reveals tiny (#1 mm) Cu-Fe-sulphides within mm to 
sub-mm sized fluid inclusions, which are too small to be individually 
analysed by LA-ICPMS (Figures 2c-f and Supplementary Material 
4). These are the most likely candidates for the Cu peaks observed 
within the LA-ICPMS analyses of plagioclases. Apart from the Cu-Fe 
sulphide phases no other mineral phases are visible in these ''empty'' 
inclusions. Additionally, we did not observe salt deposits within 
and/or around the broken inclusions, which would have formed by 
sudden evaporation of a saline fluid at the moment of the hammer-
induced opening of the inclusions (Figures 2b-c and Supplemen-
tary Material 4). We consider this as an indirect evidence for a 
low-salinity, vapour-rich nature of the fluid of these inclusions. 
Only in one case we observed a possible salt deposit around a broken 
fluid inclusion containing a Cu-Fe-sulphide (Figure b of Supple-
mentary Material 4). This might suggest the occurrence also of some 
saline fluid inclusions. 
In Pilavo rocks plagioclase occurs dominantly as micro-pheno-
crysts in the groundmass, suggesting that it has crystallized during 
decompression at shallow levels. This is supported by a decrease in 
the anorthite content from the inclusion-rich cores (An$80 mol.%) 
to the inclusion-free rims (An#70 mol.%). Such an anorthite change 
is consistent with a decrease in the water content of the magma 
coexisting with plagioclase </p>

<p>37,38   . Thus, the melt/fluid inclusion-rich 
zones document plagioclase growth during decompression-induced 
degassing. During degassing Cu, as experimentally predicted </p>

<p>39-41   , has 
partitioned into the vapour-rich fluid phase, which was trapped 
within the plagioclase-hosted fluid inclusions. Cu-sulphides have 
subsequently precipitated from such vapour-rich fluid phase within 
the inclusions. 
The systematically decreasing Cu amphibole concentrations in rocks 
with increasing Sr/Y values and decreasing MgO (Figure 1a) cannot 
reflect magmatic fractionation of Cu-bearing minerals. Sulphides, 
which can incorporate large amounts of Cu </p>

<p>42   , are clearly late-stage 
in both lower (see above) and higher Sr/Y rocks (see below). The Cu 
partition coefficient between melt and a clinopyroxene-amphibole 
assemblage fractionating in Pilavo magmas with a conservative ratio 
of 1:1 
37 is .1. Therefore, Cu concentrations would increase in the 
residual melt during fractionation of such an assemblage (amphibole 
and clinopyroxene partition coefficient values from 
43 and http:// 
earthref.org/GERM/, respectively). This is supported by: (i) the 
core-to-rim increase of Cu amphibole concentrations in amphiboles 
of lower Sr/Y rocks, (ii) the core-to-rim decreases in compatible </p>

<p>3.2 
3.4 
3.6 
3.8 
0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>E05064 
E05150 
E05151 
E05153 
E05156 
E05067 
E05066 </p>

<p>E05151 
E05150 
E05064 
E05066 
E05153 
E05156 
E05067 </p>

<p>Cu 
amph (ppm) </p>

<p>Sr/Y = 79 
Sr/Y=49 </p>

<p>whole rock Cu </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>1600 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>2400 </p>

<p>Cu 
plag (ppm) </p>

<p>3.2 
3.4 
3.6 
3.8 </p>

<p>MgO wr (wt.%) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Maximum Cu concentrations in amphiboles (a) and </p>

<p>plagioclases (b) decrease with increasing evolution (lower MgO, higher 
Sr/Y) of the host whole rocks. Cu-Fe-sulphides appear as inclusions in 
magnetite only in the more evolved rocks, colour-coded on the upper part 
of the diagram: green5very few sulphides (,10% of magnetite grains host 
sulphides); light yellow5medium number of sulphides (10-30%); 
yellow5abundant sulphides (.30%). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 685 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00685 </p>

<p>
elements (Mg, Ni) and (iii) the core-to-rim increases in incompatible 
elements (e.g., Zr, La, Hf) (Supplementary Material 6). Such zoning 
highlights the incompatible behaviour of Cu during magmatic dif-
ferentiation under oxidized conditions </p>

<p>44   . We have modelled the </p>

<p>increase of Cu concentrations in Pilavo magmas that would result 
from their evolution through the recharge, assimilation, fractional cry-
stallization (RAFC) process proposed by </p>

<p>37   . Modelling is based on 5 
steps of RAFC (Supplementary Material 7) for a mildly incompatible </p>

<p>Figure 2 | SE images (a-c, e) and EDS spectra (d, f) of unwashed and unpolished hammer-broken fragments of basaltic andesite (sample E05150). The </p>

<p>images show fluid/melt inclusion-rich zones within plagioclase phenocrysts (a) with abundant empty fluid inclusions (b) and the occurrence of Cu-Fe-
sulphides within some of them (c-d). The most common occurrence of Cu-Fe-sulphides is that of Figure 2c (see Supplementary Material 4 for additional 
pictures). Apart from the Cu-Fe-sulphide phase (c) no other mineral phases are visible in these inclusions. Additionally within and around the inclusions 
we never observed salt deposits that might have formed upon hammer-induced rupture of the fluid inclusions if these contained saline fluids. This 
suggests that the inclusions are low-salinity, essentially vapour-rich. In one case (e-f) we observed the occurrence of a crystalline (pseudo-)octahedral Cu-
(Fe-)sulphide in association with magnetite in a fluid inclusion perhaps associated with melt (gl?). (g) BSE image of groundmass magnetite with ilmenite 
exsolutions along crystallographic planes and Cu-Fe-sulphide inclusions displaying quenched textures consisting of rounded blebs of a Cu-poor phase 
(10-20 wt.% Cu: dark grey) inside a Cu-richer (30-40 wt.% Cu: bright) host (EDS analyses: Supplementary Material 9 and 10). The shapes of the 
inclusions are often delimited by crystallographic planes (dashed red lines), parallel to the ilmenite exsolutions (sample E05067). Groundmass magnetite 
hosting a swarm of Cu-Fe-sulphide inclusions (h) parallel to growing crystal surfaces (?) (reflected light, parallel nicols: sample E05156). Abbreviations: Pl 
5 plagioclase; Mag 5 magnetite; gl 5 glass. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 685 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00685 </p>

<p>
behaviour of Cu ( </p>

<p>Cu </p>

<p>K melt/bulk minerals 5 2). The calculated Cu concen-
trations for the most evolved Pilavo magma with the highest (,80) Sr/ 
Y value of Pilavo rocks would be ,100 ppm. This is significantly 
higher than the measured Cu concentrations (37-58 ppm) in whole 
rocks with similarly high Sr/Y values (70-80). 
An alternative which can explain the decreasing Cu amphibole con-
centrations in the rocks with higher Sr/Y values is that amphibole has 
crystallized from or has equilibrated with magmas that have prev-
iously exsolved a fluid phase (see also </p>

<p>33,45   ). In fact, Cu will partition 
into the fluid phase upon fluid saturation of a magma (K fluid/melt .1 
for Cu </p>

<p>39-41   ) and the magma coexisting with such a fluid will conse-
quently become Cu-poorer. Although recent work by 
46 suggests rela-
tively low volatile phase/mafic melt partition coefficients of 2-6 for 
Cu, these values were calculated for an anhydrous basaltic melt. The 
water-rich Pilavo basaltic andesite magmas share little resemblance 
to anhydrous magmas and clearly additional work is needed 
46 to 
quantify Cu partitioning into a fluid phase exsolved from hydrous 
andesitic magmas. Amphiboles crystallized at P,0.4 GPa in the 
more evolved (higher Sr/Y) rocks of Pilavo </p>

<p>37   . Therefore, fluid satura-
tion and the associated Cu partitioning into such fluid phase must 
have occurred at relatively deep crustal levels (up to ,15 km). 
Cu amphibole contents correlate significantly with Li amphibole con-
tents within each sample (Figure 3a; see also </p>

<p>43   ). Like Cu, also Li 
has a K fluid/melt .1 
47 but K amphibole/fluid for Li/Cu is .1 </p>

<p>43,48   , i.e., 
Li has less affinity for the fluid phase compared to Cu. Therefore, </p>

<p>systematically shallower slopes of Cu-Li correlations in amphiboles 
of increasingly evolved (higher Sr/Y) rocks (Figure 3b) further sup-
port amphibole crystallization from or equilibration with magmas 
that have increasingly exsolved a fluid phase. Diffusive equilibration 
of Cu in amphibole, potentially explaining the low Cu and flat core-
to-rim Cu profiles of amphiboles from higher Sr/Y rocks (Supple-
mentary Material 6), would require only a few years of magmatic 
residence time (Supplementary Material 8). That in higher Sr/Y 
rocks most of the Cu has partitioned into the fluid phase at high 
pressure is further confirmed by the very low Cu contents in the 
fluid/melt inclusion-rich zones of their plagioclase phenocrysts com-
pared to the fluid/melt inclusion-rich zones of plagioclase in lower 
Sr/Y rocks (Supplementary Material 5). In other words, in contrast 
with lower Sr/Y magmas there was little Cu left in the higher Sr/Y 
magmas during shallow level decompression-driven fluid exsolution 
when plagioclase phenocrysts crystallized. 
Higher Sr/Y rocks have similar whole rock Cu contents (37-
58 ppm) to lower Sr/Y rocks (32-64 ppm). However, our modelling 
(see above and Supplementary Material 7) indicates that the most 
evolved magmas (with higher Sr/Y values) should contain higher Cu 
concentrations (,100 ppm) than those actually measured in the 
similarly evolved whole rocks (,60 ppm). From this we infer that 
a portion of the Cu has escaped from the Cu-rich and high Sr/Y 
andesitic magma along with the fluid phase. Cu is hosted by different 
mineral phases in the two rock types. In higher Sr/Y rocks the bulk of 
Cu is hosted by abundant, several mm-sized, Cu-Fe-sulphides occur-
ring within groundmass magnetite (Figure 2e-f; Supplementary 
Material 9). In lower Sr/Y rocks such large Cu-Fe sulphides asso-
ciated with magnetite have not been observed and the bulk of Cu 
occurs in the tiny (#1 mm) Cu-sulphides within plagioclase-hosted 
fluid inclusions (Figure 2c) and in Cu-rich amphiboles. The exclusive 
association of Cu-sulphides with magnetite in high Sr/Y rocks high-
lights the important role of magnetite crystallization in causing 
sulphide saturation in silicate magmas </p>

<p>44,49   . Following </p>

<p>44   , sulphide sat-
uration might have occurred within the melt boundary layer sur-
rounding growing magnetite due to a rapid switch in sulphur 
redox conditions, which was triggered by magnetite crystallization. 
Based on textural observations </p>

<p>37   , the groundmass magnetite of high 
Sr/Y rocks crystallized late, after amphibole and synchronous with 
plagioclase and clinopyroxene microcrysts. These observations are in 
agreement with the crystallization sequence of hydrous andesite at 
P.0.2 GPa 
50 (Figure 4). The association of Cu-Fe-sulphides with 
late-stage magnetite indicates that magnetite-induced sulphide sat-
uration of the magma occurred after the high pressure Cu partition-
ing into the fluid phase. A partial fluid-to-sulphide melt transfer of 
Cu and S from the fluid phase into the sulphide melt formed in the 
boundary layer around magnetite crystals could have been prompted 
by the preferential aggregation of fluid bubbles to crystallising mag-
netite </p>

<p>51   . Alternatively, Cu hosted by Cu-sulphides could have been 
derived from the residual Cu present in the melt after fluid partition-
ing at high pressure. </p>

<p>Discussion 
Porphyry systems result from a complex combination of magmatic, 
hydrothermal and tectonic factors 
52 and, despite common general 
features, significant differences exist among them. In this work we 
explore the reasons why several major porphyry systems are spatially 
and temporally associated with high Sr/Y magmas. Nonetheless, we 
would like to emphasize that not all porphyry systems have an appar-
ent association with high Sr/Y magmas and that alternative inter-
pretations, differing more or less significantly from our, have been 
proposed for the association of porphyry-type deposits with high Sr/ 
Y magmas </p>

<p>3,7,9,10,21   . 
Our results provide indirect evidence that Cu partitions into a fluid 
phase before sulphide saturation at both shallow (,0.1 GPa) and 
relatively deep (up to ,0.4 GPa) crustal levels. Analyses of coexisting </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Correlations between Cu and Li contents of amphiboles in </p>

<p>Pilavo andesites. (a) Cu and Li contents of amphiboles (Cu amph , Li amph ) 
correlate within each whole rock sample (except E05066) following linear 
trends with different slopes: E05150, Cu51.83*Li-39.21, R50.91; E05153, 
Cu51.03*Li13.15, R50.91; E05066, Cu50.62*Li115.75, R50.32; 
E05151, Cu50.69*Li-32.93, R50.79; E05156, Cu50.42*Li13.61, 
R50.87; E05067, Cu50.37*Li19.62, R50.73; E05064, 
Cu50.10*Li11.96, R50.78. (b) Cu-Li slopes defined by amphibole 
populations of each different whole rock sample (Figure 3a) correlate with 
evolution indices of the whole rock (e.g., MgO). Sample E05066 has not 
been plotted because of the poor correlation coefficient defined by its 
amphiboles in the Cu-Li space (Figure 3a). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 685 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00685 </p>

<p>
fluid and melt inclusions (which have not been observed in Pilavo 
rocks) could possibly provide direct evidence for such a process. Our 
results are consistent with the idea that ore fluids can derive metals 
directly from mafic-intermediate magmas 
26 in addition to remobiliz-
ing them from earlier magmatic sulphides </p>

<p>29-31   . Importantly, Cu par-
titioning into a fluid exsolved from andesitic magma at high-pressure 
(,0.4 GPa) may provide an explanation for the preferential asso-
ciation of many porphyry-type deposits with high Sr/Y magmas as 
opposed to low Sr/Y ones. 
Pilavo magmas with lower Sr/Y values (40-50) owe their signature 
to limited amphibole fractionation, which resulted from a short to 
negligible residence time in a composite mid-crustal reservoir </p>

<p>37   . 
They have exsolved fluids by decompression at shallow levels, likely 
below the single-phase fluid field (vapour1liquid: Figure 4). Cu-
sulphides trapped in empty inclusions of plagioclases (Figures 2c-f) 
record the shallow level exsolution from the magma of a Cu-bearing, </p>

<p>mostly vapour-rich fluid. However, vapour exsolution at shallow 
levels is not considered to be favourable for large porphyry Cu forma-
tion </p>

<p>53   . This is due to the fact that vapours are easily dispersed to the 
atmosphere at these shallow levels and have metal concentrations 
generally too low to form economic deposits </p>

<p>53   . Large porphyry depos-
its are usually considered to be formed by a single-phase fluid of 
variably low salinity exsolved at deeper levels </p>

<p>1,53   . 
Magmas at Pilavo, as well as other well-studied magmatic systems 
associated with porphyry-type deposits (e.g., Yanacocha </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>, Tampakan </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>, 
porphyry systems in Iran and Pakistan </p>

<p>22   ), developed high Sr/Y (.50 
and up to 80) signatures through a combination of fractionation, cru-
stal melting and assimilation. All these processes occurred at pressures 
at which amphibole preceded plagioclase crystallization (,0.4 GPa at 
Pilavo). In andesite and basaltic andesite magmas amphibole precedes 
plagioclase fractionation above a pressure threshold (,0.2 GPa), 
which roughly coincides with the vapour1liquid coexistence lines of 
low to intermediate salinity fluids (Figure 4). It follows that andesitic 
magmas that develop high Sr/Y signatures through high-pressure 
(.,0.2 GPa) crystallization of amphibole will exsolve a single-phase 
fluid when they reach fluid saturation (Figure 4). Our results show that 
Cu may efficiently partition into this single-phase fluid exsolved from 
an andesitic oxidized magma crystallizing at depth, before sulphide 
saturation. 
Fluid saturation in magmas evolving at deep levels, which are 
therefore likely to develop high Sr/Y signatures, has already been 
proposed as a solution to the conundrum of excess sulfur released 
during many volcanic arc eruptions </p>

<p>45   . Our data suggest that oxidized, 
high Sr/Y magmas formed through mid-crustal fractionation 6 
crustal melting and assimilation likely coexist at depth with an excess 
fluid containing not only S but also Cu. The evidence of a Cu-bearing 
excess fluid in the higher Sr/Y andesitic magmas of Pilavo reconciles 
into a coherent model of porphyry systems: (i) the idea that shallow 
porphyry systems are fed by Cu-bearing fluids escaping periodically 
from a deep mafic/intermediate reservoir and/or advected with the 
magma itself </p>

<p>32,33   , and (ii) the spatial-temporal association of por-
phyry systems with high Sr/Y magmas (see above). In this model 
cyclic replenishments of the deep reservoir by mafic recharges may 
cause cyclic fluid saturation through high-pressure crystallization 
(see also 
7 ). By this way fluid and metal flux from the deep mafic-
intermediate reservoir may continue for prolonged time because 
deep reservoirs are more easily kept at mature thermal conditions 
by recharge processes than shallow ones. This results in a long-lived, 
continuous fertilization of the shallow magmatic-hydrothermal sys-
tems 
7,8 and is consistent with the long hydrothermal life of giant 
porphyry systems (e.g. </p>

<p>54   ). During this time, and depending on crustal 
stress conditions, the high Sr/Y signature may also be episodically 
transferred to shallower levels by magma pulses ascending from the 
deep reservoir. This may cause the frequent, but not universal, asso-
ciation of high Sr/Y magmatic rocks with large porphyry systems. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>In situ trace element analyses of amphibole, clinopyroxene and plagioclase were 
carried out on polished thin sections by LA-ICP-MS using a Perkin Elmer ELAN 6100 
DRC ICP-MS equipped with a 193 nm EXCIMER Geolas laser at the University of 
Lausanne (Switzerland). Operating conditions of the laser were: 8 Hz frequency, 
100 mJ energy, 35 or 60 mm spot size. CaO contents determined by microprobe in the 
area of subsequent ablation with the laser were used for internal standardization by 
reference to an SRM612 NIST external standard. Raw data were reduced off-line 
using the <rs type="software">LAMTRACE</rs> software </p>

<p>55-57   . Element concentrations are reported in 
Supplementary Material 2. The reproducibility (1s) of the measured trace elements 
in the SRM612 standard is ,10%. 
SEM imaging and EDS analyses were carried out on a JSM-7001F JEOL scanning 
electron microscope at the Section of Earth and Environmental Sciences, University 
of Geneva (Switzerland) on both thin polished sections and hammer-broken, air gun-
blown and unwashed rock splits to avoid dissolution of soluble minerals potentially 
present in fluid inclusions. </p>

<p>1. Sillitoe, R. H. Porphyry copper systems. Econ. Geol. 105, 3-41 (2010). </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0 
1100 
1050 
1000 
950 
900 
850 
800 
750 
700 
650 
600 </p>

<p>V+L </p>

<p>SPF </p>

<p>5 w t. % H2 O </p>

<p>4 w t. % H 2 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>3 
w t . % </p>

<p>H 
2 O </p>

<p>2 wt.% H2O </p>

<p>P (GPa) </p>

<p>T (°C) </p>

<p>Pl in </p>

<p>M a g in (a n d ) </p>

<p>A m 
in </p>

<p>V+H 
low Sr/Y </p>

<p>V+ L co ex is te nc e lin e (1 0 w t.% N aC l) </p>

<p>band </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>band 
and </p>

<p>high Sr/Y </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 
2 </p>

<p>V +L co ex is te nc e lin e (3 0-45 w t.% N aC l) </p>

<p>Figure 4 | P-T plot showing the first appearance boundaries of most </p>

<p>common mineral phases (Pl5plagioclase; Am5amphibole; 
Mag5magnetite) in water-saturated basaltic andesite (band) and 
andesite (and) magma buffered at NNO11 to NNO12 (from 
21 ; for 
simplicity the boundaries of clinopyroxene and olivine have been 
omitted). Also shown are the solubility curves of a fluid (75 mol.% H 2 O, 
25 mol.% CO 2 ) in a basaltic magma calculated with <rs id="software-0" type="software">VolatileCalc</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">1_1</rs> </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>, the 
projected vapour1liquid coexistence surface for salinities of 10 wt.% and 
30-45 wt.% NaCl (green, extrapolated above 1000uC) and the 
vapour1liquid1halite coexistence curve (blue) from 
59 (V5vapour, 
L5liquid, H5halite, F5single-phase fluid). The orange path 1 represents a 
hypothetical fluid-unsaturated (e.g., H 2 O52.5 wt.%) basaltic andesite/ 
andesite magma that ascends rapidly to shallow level until it becomes fluid-
saturated upon hitting the 2.5 wt.% H 2 O boundary. This magma will 
exsolve a fluid below the vapour1liquid coexistence line and will not have 
significantly high Sr/Y because it will not fractionate amphibole. If the 
same magma undergoes isobaric crystallization at P. ,0.2 GPa (red paths 
2) it will eventually become fluid-saturated in the single-phase fluid field, 
above the vapour1liquid coexistence line. Because amphibole always 
precedes plagioclase crystallization above the vapour1liquid coexistence 
line in andesitic magmas and almost at any pressure above the V1L 
coexistence line for basaltic andesite magmas (except a small gap between 
,0.19 and ,0.22 GPa), it follows that development of high Sr/Y 
signatures and exsolution of fluids in the single phase field are intimately 
bound together. Hydrous andesitic magmas rising rapidly to shallow levels 
have magnetite close to the liquidus (orange path 1), which might cause 
sulphide saturation before fluid exsolution, depending on the initial water 
content of the magma. In contrast, andesitic magmas evolving at 
P.0.2 GPa and thus acquiring high Sr/Y signatures (red paths 2) will 
crystallize magnetite late thus making possible the partitioning of Cu into 
an exsolved fluid before magnetite-induced sulphide saturation 
incorporates magmatic Cu. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 685 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00685 </p>

<p>
 </p>



<p>
Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We acknowledge the Swiss National Science Foundation (projects N. 200020-117616 and 
200020_126896 granted to MC) for funding this study. We thank the constructive reviews 
of Adam Simon, Sue Kay and Keiko Hattori. We are also grateful to Ryan Cochrane for 
reviewing the English of the manuscript and to Agathe Martignier for the help during SEM 
imaging. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>MC, AU and KK were involved in designing the study and collecting and analysing the data. 
BB was involved in collecting the samples and providing the geological background. MC, 
AU, KK, and BB were involved in the writing and editing. All authors reviewed the 
manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>License: This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivative Works 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy 
of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Chiaradia, M., Ulianov, A., Kouzmanov, K. &amp; Beate, B. Why large 
porphyry Cu deposits like high Sr/Y magmas? Sci. Rep. 2, 685; DOI:10.1038/srep00685 
(2012). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 2 : 685 | DOI: 10.1038/srep00685 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>