<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3386500" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Background: Even with high coverage of vaccination programs, Bordetella pertussis is still reported in various 
countries. It causes a high rate of mortality and morbidity in infants while it could be asymptomatic in adults. At the 
present study, we are going to evaluate the frequency of B. pertussis among received specimens. </p>

<p>Methods: This cross-sectional study was performed on 138 children under one year who were suspected to have whooping 
cough from October 2008 to March in 2011. Nasopharyngeal dacron and rayon swabs and sera were used for PCR and 
serology respectively. </p>

<p>Results: The mean age of the subjects was 1.9± 0.9 months. PCR was positive in 12 cases; ELISA was in agreement with 
PCR results except in one case that showed the specific antibody at borderline limit. </p>

<p>Conclusion: The rate of reported positive results showed that pertussis not only is still present in the community, but the 
number of the asymptomatic cases who are able to transmit the disease may be considerable. </p>

<p>Pertussis is a severe disease in children and has remained 
one of the 10 causes of death in infants in the entire world. 
Reports show occurrence of about 10 million infected cases 
with almost 400,000 pertussis-related deaths annually [1-3]. 
Whooping cough usually manifests in wide spectrum of 
signs from asymptomatic presentation to a mild coughing 
illness in adolescents and adults who have partial immunity 
due to past vaccination or a full spectrum of symptoms in 
unimmunized patients. Hence, infection cannot be accurately 
diagnosed by just clinical presentations. Laboratory tests 
need to be used for confirmation of the diagnosis in those 
patients with suggestive clinical signs and symptoms or 
those having a history of exposure to the infected patients. 
However, negative tests cannot be accepted as a definitive 
result for excluding whooping cough. Therefore, it is 
necessary to apply improved laboratory diagnosis tests [1]. </p>

<p>Diagnosis of whooping cough is often delayed in adults 
and older children, because of the lack of classic symptoms 
and also low awareness of some physicians. Late diagnosis 
of infection results in remaining of the patient among the 
community and transmission of infection for several weeks. 
ELISAs test, based on the rise of antibody titers is one of the 
main diagnostic procedures in unvaccinated cases. It uses 
specific B. pertussis proteins as antigens, with increases in </p>

<p>*Address correspondence to this author at the Research Center and Health 
Reference Laboratory, Ministry of Health and Medical Education, Tehran, 
Iran; Tel: +982166728112-13; Fax: +982166728121; 
E-mail: rahbar_reflab@yahoo.com </p>

<p>IgA or IgG antibody titers to pertussis toxin (PT), 
filamentous hemmaglutinin (FHA). The greatest sensitivity 
and specificity is reported to be achieved for the serological 
diagnosis of B. pertussis infection by measuring of the 
antibody titer of PT [4]. It was also mentioned that only 
humoral responses to pertussis toxin were shown to be 
consistent among vaccinated and unvaccinated patients [5]. </p>

<p>The use of PCR for the diagnosis of pertussis is 
increasingly being used since it provides sensitive and rapid 
results [6-9]. CDC and World Health Organization (WHO) 
have now included a positive PCR in lab definition of 
pertussis (Bamberger 2008). European Research Program for 
Improved Pertussis Strain Characterization and Surveillance 
has also insisted on the application of real-time PCR in order 
to have more sensitive results than isolation method to 
diagnosis B. pertussis, even after the initiation of antibiotic 
therapy. However, it is believed that the newer molecular 
technique has not provided satisfactory results in the older 
population who have less typical symptoms and often late 
clinical presentation [10, 11]. </p>

<p>In our study, we determined the prevalence of B. 
pertussis among infants suspected to have whopping cough 
by PCR. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patients: This cross-sectional study was performed in 
children less than six months old who were suspected to 
have whooping cough and were referred from physicians or 
other private clinical laboratories during October 2008 to 
March in 2011. The patients were asked for their vaccination </p>

<p>Detection of Bordetella pertussis in Infants Suspected </p>

<p>The Open Respiratory Medicine Journal, 2012, Volume 6 35 </p>

<p>history and tested for the rise of specific antibody by PCR 
method. Totally, 138 specimens (93 male and 45 female 
patients) were examined. </p>

<p>Specimens: Nasopharyngeal dacron and rayon swabs (at 
restrict condition for respiratory sampling) and sera were 
used for PCR and serology respectively. </p>

<p>ELISA: The immunity of the infants to whooping cough 
and their vaccination history was checked before sampling. 
ELISA was applied solely for unvaccinated children. 
Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assays was applied by the 
commercial kit (IBL International, GmbH, Hamburg, 
Germany). This kit was able to detect bordetella antigen 
containing pertussis toxin (PT) and filamentary 
haemagglutinine (FHA) to indicate recent Bordetella 
infection by determination of IgM and IgA antibodies. The 
procedure was followed as indicated by the manufacturer. 
According to the manufacturer's classification, values of &lt;16 
U⁄ml, 16-24 U⁄ml and &gt;24 U⁄ml were considered as 
negative, equivocal and positive, respectively. </p>

<p>DNA extraction and PCR protocols: DNA extraction was 
performed in an identical manner for all patients. The samples 
were extracted by High Pure PCR Template preparation kit 
(Roche Co.). B. pertussis PCR kit (DNA Technology, Russia) 
was applied to detect the specific genome in the patients 
samples. The kit was specific signal based method. This kit had 
specific primers for amplification 417 base pair of template. 
Five l of template, 10 l PCR buffer, 10 l mixture 
(containing specific primers and dNTP, 2.5 U taq polymerase) 
were mixed and amplified according to the kit guideline. The 
applied PCR kit was constructed in a format of competitive 
PCR with internal control. Provided specific primers could also 
amplify a product with 560 base pair as internal control as well 
as the specific product to ensure of proper extraction and 
removal of any expected inhibitors. The kit also contained 
specific probes labeled by fam and hex for specific and internal 
products respectively. These probes enabled us to increase the 
sensitivity and reduce contamination rate that are detected by 
the fluorescence detector [3]. </p>

<p>Data collection Analysis procedure: The analyzed 
results were expressed by the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 16</rs>) in 
percentage. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>A paroxysmal cough was observed at the sampling in all 
positive cases. IgM and IgA ELISA were positive in 11 
cases. The result of ELISA test showed the rise of specific 
antibody at equivocal limit in one case that had been 
vaccinated a few days before sampling. Vaccination history 
was being asked from each patient at the sampling time. All 
those ELISA positive cases had no vaccination history. </p>

<p>On the other hand PCR was positive in all ELISA 
positive including the case with borderline limit result (Fig. 
1). The mean age of the subjects was 1.9 ± 0.9 months, eight 
were male and the rest were female. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Analyzed data revealed that despite the high coverage of 
vaccination in recent years in Iran, pertussis is still observed 
in some cases. It means infection persists in the community 
in asymptomatic people. </p>

<p>Detected antibody in infants could be maternal antibodies 
or rise of antibody level due to vaccination [11] after two 
months old. Vaccination program in Iran are at age 2, 4, 6 
and 18 months with a booster at 4 to 6 years old. It is 
recommended that the vaccination be repeated ten years after 
last vaccination. Unfortunately, reports show that most 
people do not repeat it after primary school. Reported data 
from Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) 
surveillance from 1990-2003 confirmed incidence of 
pertussis has been increased with a nearly tenfold rise among 
adolescents [12], especially in persons aged 10-19 years and 
over 20 years [13]. Panahi (et al. 2007) has also studied 
those patients with prolonged cough who were referred to 
Zanjan hospital (a city in western part of Iran) and reported 
that 18.7% of the adults were infected with B. pertussis [14]. 
Therefore, it shows an unexpected high frequency rate of 
pertussis in adolescents which could be an alarm for public 
health system. </p>

<p>There is no accurate report of pertussis incidence in Iran, 
since most laboratories do not run a diagnostic test for it or if 
they do, the diagnostic procedure is not accurate. On the 
other hand, applying culture and isolation method is faced 
with some problems [15-17]. Some of the most encountered </p>

<p>Fig. (1). Analyzing PCR product by fluorescence detector. Rows 1, and 2 are negative and positive controls respectively, row 3 to 5 are 
patient's samples. Rows 6 and 7 are background. Column 6 shows emitted signals of each reaction. Black and white colors represents 
specific and competitive. The results of sample 198, 200 and 201 are positive, failure and negative. Sample number 200 shows an inhibition 
that is due to improper extraction that must be repeated after new extraction or re-sampling. </p>

<p>* Normalization values </p>

<p>Tube 
Sample 
Result 
SR 
IC 
SR (Specific Reaction) 
IC (Internal Control) 
1/0 
NC 
0.99 
10.11 </p>

<p>2/0 
PC 
+ 
11.90 
7.41 </p>

<p>3/0 
74 
+ 
8.56 
4.36 </p>

<p>4/0 
75 
Failure 
0.94 
1.12 </p>

<p>5/0 
76 
-
0.95 
6.82 </p>

<p>6/bg 
(Bordetella) </p>

<p>(Background) 
(Background) 
1.00 
1.04 </p>

<p>7/bg 
(Bordetella) </p>

<p>(Background) 
(Background) 
1.00 
0.99 </p>



<p>Hajia et al. </p>

<p>influential parameters would be delayed or improper 
techniques of specimen collection and inappropriate 
specimen transportation [4]. In this situation, the yield of 
culture is decreased specially in those laboratories that are 
not prepared, while requested specimens should be 
immediately plated onto selective and specific media [1]. 
Therefore, PCR has been applied more frequently in 
suspected infants since it provides more rapid and sensitive 
result than culture. </p>

<p>The Center for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) 
recommends the use of PCR to support the diagnosis of 
pertussis in those with 2 or more weeks of coughing [12]. 
However, there is a variation in the sensitivity of the 
different PCR assays, because of the different DNA 
purification techniques, PCR primers, reaction conditions, 
and product detection methods [18]. However Ghanaie (et al. 
2011) has reported PCR can be considered as a helpful tool 
for whooping cough criteria, since duration of coughing was 
longer in those children with a positive PCR than in those 
with a negative one [19]. </p>

<p>In this study we applied PCR method to diagnosis 
whooping cough by using confirmed protocols. Applied 
protocols were proved to have sufficient stability and 
reproducibility of the results than the home made protocols. 
Real time PCR method has recently been reported with a 
high sensitivity ratio [20]. However, our PCR signal based 
method had high agreement with ELISA in results in our 
study, since all these positive cases had no vaccination 
history [21]. </p>

<p>Previous researches showed that antibody responses to 
FHA are not specific to B. pertussis in unvaccinated cases, 
because it occurs following other Bordetella species; 
moreover, these antibodies may be cross-reacting epitopes to 
other bacteria including H. influenzae and M. pneumoniae. 
Thus, the best sensitivity and specificity for the serological 
diagnosis of B. pertussis infection is by ELISA measurement 
of IgM and IgA antibodies to PT in unimmunized cases [4]. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>The rate of reported positive results showed that pertussis 
not only is still present in the community, but the number of 
the asymptomatic, cases who are able to transmit the disease 
may be considerable. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT </p>

<p>The authors like to thank all the physicians, especially 
those who consulted us on the agreement of results with the 
clinical presentation of examined patients. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>Declared none. </p>



<p>Received: April 23, 2012 
Revised: May 17, 2012 
Accepted: May 23, 2012 </p>

<p>© Hajia et al.; Licensee Bentham Open. 
This is an open access article licensed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) 
which permits unrestricted, non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the work is properly cited. </p>

</text></tei>