<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3321481" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Differences in the oscillatory EEG dynamics of reading open class (OC) and closed class 
(CC) words have previously been found (Bastiaansen et al., 2005) and are thought to 
reflect differences in lexical-semantic content between these word classes. In particu-
lar, the theta-band (4-7 Hz) seems to play a prominent role in lexical-semantic retrieval. We 
tested whether this theta effect is robust in an older population of subjects. Additionally, 
we examined how the context of a word can modulate the oscillatory dynamics underly-
ing retrieval for the two different classes of words. Older participants (mean age 55) read 
words presented in either syntactically correct sentences or in a scrambled order ("scram-
bled sentence") while their EEG was recorded. We performed time-frequency analysis to 
examine how power varied based on the context or class of the word. We observed larger 
power decreases in the alpha (8-12 Hz) band between 200-700 ms for the OC compared to 
CC words, but this was true only for the scrambled sentence context. We did not observe 
differences in theta power between these conditions. Context exerted an effect on the 
alpha and low beta (13-18 Hz) bands between 0 and 700 ms. These results suggest that 
the previously observed word class effects on theta power changes in a younger participant 
sample do not seem to be a robust effect in this older population. Though this is an indi-
rect comparison between studies, it may suggest the existence of aging effects on word 
retrieval dynamics for different populations. Additionally, the interaction between word 
class and context suggests that word retrieval mechanisms interact with sentence-level 
comprehension mechanisms in the alpha-band. </p>

<p>Understanding the myriad of operations underlying language 
comprehension in the brain is an ongoing challenge in the field. 
Neuronal networks supporting these operations must dynami-
cally assemble locally and flexibly communicate across long dis-
tances. But how does the brain do this? A growing number 
of studies on the oscillatory dynamics during language pro-
cessing are revealing new insights into these mechanisms (for 
a review, see Bastiaansen and Hagoort, 2006). Oscillatory syn-
chronization is thought to reflect the transient formation of 
functional brain networks (Varela et al., 2001; Fries, 2005), 
and this synchronization can be measured through EEG or 
MEG spectral analysis. Power analysis is thought to reflect the 
recruitment of local neuronal networks while coherence analy-
sis reflects dynamic linking between brain areas involved in 
a global network. Additionally, analyzing oscillatory dynamics 
may reveal a rich set of information that is not currently seen 
during event-related potential (ERP) analysis because the ERP 
tends to average out non-phase-locked signals. Thus the study 
of oscillatory dynamics is a promising method to complement </p>

<p>current ERP analysis and examine functional networks for lan-
guage processing. 
The network dynamics of lexical-semantic processing are still 
not fully understood. Previous studies have indicated that theta 
oscillations (4-7 Hz) are involved in these networks for lexical-
semantic retrieval. Bastiaansen et al. (2005) observed greater theta 
power increases between 300 and 500 ms when subjects read open 
class (OC) words compared to closed class (CC) words in a short 
story context. Since OC words carry more semantic informa-
tion than CC words, they are thought to probe lexical-semantic 
retrieval processing more deeply than CC words. In addition, 
these authors observed greater alpha (8-12 Hz) power decreases 
between 300 and 500 ms at right occipitotemporal electrodes for 
OC than CC words. Thus alpha power decreases may also be 
related to semantic retrieval. A study comparing nouns with dif-
ferent semantic features (primarily visual vs. auditory) also found 
differences in theta power increases between 100 and 400 ms (Bas-
tiaansen et al., 2008). The theta effect was larger for the "visual" 
nouns at occipital electrodes while it was larger at temporal elec-
trodes for "auditory" nouns suggesting that theta scalp topography </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 97 | 1 </p>



<p>Mellem et al. </p>

<p>Oscillatory dynamics of class and context </p>

<p>reflects the sensory features of the words. Both studies point to 
a role for theta oscillations in the retrieval of lexical-semantic 
information, but the robustness of this effect has yet to be fully 
established. 
In the present study, we focus on the role of oscillatory dynamics 
in retrieving OC vs. CC words. Specifically, we want to investigate 
the robustness of the previously established theta and alpha effects 
in different contexts and in a different population. Our motiva-
tion stems from how the factors of context and age affect the 
well-studied N400 ERP component. The N400 is a negative-going 
potential between 300 and 500 ms that reflects lexical-semantic 
processing. Evidence shows that the N400 is modulated by both 
the class (e.g., Van Petten and Kutas, 1991; Nobre and McCarthy, 
1994; King and Kutas, 1995; Münte et al., 2001) and context 
of words (e.g., Kutas and Hillyard, 1980, 1984). An interaction 
between word class and context has also been reflected in the 
N400 (Van Petten and Kutas, 1991). Thus we have chosen to 
experimentally manipulate both word class (OC, CC) and context 
(sentence, scrambled sentence) in this study to further investi-
gate any interaction between the two factors on the oscillatory 
dynamics during word reading. Aging also affects the amplitude 
and latency of the N400 (Harbin et al., 1984; Gunter et al., 1992; 
Kutas and Iragui, 1998), and could potentially modulate oscilla-
tory responses. So far, the oscillatory dynamics of lexical-semantic 
processing have not been investigated in an older population 
(Bastiaansen et al., 2005 tested younger participants, aged 21-
28) though the changes in the N400 suggest that there may be 
changes in the underlying semantic processing mechanisms with 
age. Hence we have chosen to test in an older population. An 
additional aim is to examine gamma band (&gt;30 Hz) dynam-
ics. This will extend the previous study on OC and CC words 
(Bastiaansen et al., 2005) which did not examine gamma oscil-
lations though prior research has suggested that it is involved in 
lexical-semantic processing (Pulvermüller et al., 1999; Mainy et al., 
2008). 
To summarize, we will be testing for word class and context 
effects in older subjects as well as for any interaction between 
these factors. We predict that modulation of theta and alpha power 
will reflect greater lexical-semantic processing for OC words than 
CC words. Additionally, we expect that an interaction between 
class and context will reflect how word-level and sentence-level 
processing interact. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>SUBJECTS </p>

<p>Fourteen healthy volunteers participated in the experiment and 
received monetary compensation for their participation. Two 
were excluded from the analysis due to excessive eye move-
ments. Two additional subjects were excluded due to missing 
or corrupted files. Thus analyses were performed on data from 
10 healthy subjects (mean age 55, age range 44-77, five males). 
All were right-handed, native English speakers without a his-
tory of neurological disorders. None were on medications that 
would have affected their performance during this study. All 
gave informed consent (approved by the Georgetown University 
Medical Center Institutional Review Board) before starting the 
experiment. </p>

<p>STIMULI </p>

<p>Fifty-six sentences were created to include as wide a variety of 
CC words as possible. The number of words per sentence ranged 
from 10 to 20 with an average of 15. The sentences were derived 
from 163 unique OC words (e.g., nouns, verbs, and adjectives) and 
69 unique CC words (e.g., pronouns, prepositions, and conjunc-
tions). After repetitions of these words, sentences contained a total 
of 863 words, but a subset of 645 critical words (CW) was selected 
for analysis. This allowed us to exclude first and last words to avoid 
start-up and wrap-up effects as well as any words that fit into both 
open and closed categories. Additionally, each of the 56 sentences 
was turned into a scrambled sentence, e.g., the sentence "the girl 
sat on the floor" became "sat floor the girl on the." Thus each CW 
occurred both in a sentence context and in a scrambled sentence 
context. There were 640 CWs in the set of scrambled sentences (a 
few had to be removed post hoc); thus subjects read a total of 1285 
CWs. Among the total set of CWs, we examined 695 OC words 
and 590 CC words. 
The selected OC words ranged in length from 2 to 13 characters 
and had a log frequency of 0-3.66 (Kucera-Francis log frequency 
per million words). The selected CC words ranged in length from 
1 to 15 characters and had a frequency of 0.30-4.84. The aver-
age length of OC vs. CC words differed significantly [OC: 5.78 
and CC: 3.57; t (643) = 14.29, p &lt; 0.001]; similarly, there were sig-
nificant differences in the log frequency [OC: 2.05 and CC: 3.68; 
t (643) = −23.98, p &lt; 0.001]. </p>

<p>DESIGN AND PROCEDURE </p>

<p>We used a 2 × 2 within-subjects factorial design with factors con-
text (sentence or scrambled sentence) and word class (OC or CC). 
Subjects were instructed to silently read words presented on a CRT 
computer monitor and respond to comprehension questions spo-
ken by the experimenter after each trial. The words appeared in 
white lower-case letters on black background in Arial font. The 
words subtended a horizontal visual angle of at most 4.8˚(for 
the 15-letter word). The subjects were asked to minimize any 
movements and eyeblinking while words were on the screen. The 
schematic (Figure 1) shows the general organization of the para-
digm and task. Stimuli were presented in four blocks of sentences 
alternating with four blocks of scrambled sentences per session 
(out of two sessions). Each sentence block contained 14 trials of 
sentences while each scrambled sentence block contained 14 trials 
of scrambled sentences; thus in each session there were 112 trials. 
Within a trial, words were displayed one at a time at the center 
of the screen for 400 ms with an ISI of 400 ms (stimulus onset 
asynchrony was 800 ms) until the end of the sentence or scram-
bled sentence. Trials were also repeated with a word ISI of 800 ms 
(randomly interspersed with 400 ms trials), but these trials are not 
examined here. For half of the sentences, the sentence context was 
presented first. For the other half of the sentences, the scrambled 
sentence context was presented first; thus, the order of context 
(sentence vs. scramble sentence) was counterbalanced. 
Between each trial, subjects answered questions to confirm that 
they were reading the words. The questions varied based on the 
type of trial: for example, "Was this sentence about a circus?" for a 
sentence or "Did you see the word 'circus'?" for a scrambled sen-
tence. The experimenter manually recorded the responses. Average </p>

<p>Frontiers in Psychology | Language Sciences </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 97 | 2 </p>

<p>Mellem et al. </p>

<p>Oscillatory dynamics of class and context </p>

<p>FIGURE 1 | Schematic representing the general organization of 
the paradigm and the task. Alternating blocks of sentences and 
scrambled sentences (order counterbalanced across subjects) were 
presented to the subjects. Each sentence block contained 14 trials </p>

<p>of sentences while each scrambled sentence block contained 14 
trials of scrambled sentences. The experimenter asked the subject 
questions after each trial to ensure subject comprehension and 
attention. </p>

<p>accuracy was 86% for the sentence questions and 70% for the 
scrambled sentence questions which indicates an overall attentive-
ness to the readings. Data from both correct and incorrect trials 
were subject to preprocessing and analysis. The inter-trial inter-
val varied based on response time of the subject to the question. 
While reaction time was not collected, subjects typically responded 
within several seconds. All subjects saw all words in both contexts 
across two sessions separated by 1 week. Each session was under 
2 h, including time for preparation, recording, and cleanup. </p>

<p>EEG RECORDING AND PREPROCESSING </p>

<p>Scalp EEG was continuously recorded from 64 tin electrodes 
mounted in an elastic cap (Electro-cap International, USA). Elec-
trodes were also placed above and below the right eye and on 
the outer canthi of both eyes to record vertical and horizontal 
eye movements and blinks. The signals were referenced to the 
left mastoid and sampled at a rate of 500 Hz. Impedance at each 
electrode was kept at or below 5 kΩ. The signals were amplified 
by Neuroscan SynAmps2 amplifiers (Neuroscan, USA) and fil-
tered on-line with a band-pass filter (0.05-100 Hz, 24-dB/octave 
attenuation). Data were stored off-line for further analysis. 
For all preprocessing and subsequent analysis, we used the 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">FieldTrip toolbox</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Oostenveld</rs> et al., 2011) which is implemented 
in <rs id="software-1" type="software">Matlab</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Mathworks</rs>, MA, USA). We performed the following 
preprocessing steps: re-referencing to the average of the left and 
right mastoid channels, band-pass filtering 0.3-100, 60 Hz line fil-
tering, and artifact removal. Prior to artifact removal, EEG epochs 
were extracted from the continuous EEG from 1000 ms before, 
to 2000 ms after onset of the CWs. Single word epochs with arti-
facts that occurred between 200 ms before to 800 ms after stimulus 
onset were removed from analysis. A Z -score based algorithm was 
used to detect eye blinks and eye movements, and other artifacts 
were detected with a threshold algorithm. After removal, about 
70% of single word epochs remained. There were an average (mar-
ginal means) of 436 single word epochs in the sentence condition, 
462 in the scrambled sentence condition, 480 in the OC condi-
tion, and 417 in the CC condition. The cell means were 220 for 
OC in sentence, 260 for OC in scrambled sentence, 216 for CC </p>

<p>in sentence, and 202 for CC in scrambled sentence. A two-way 
ANOVA on these groups did not reveal statistical differences in 
the remaining number of words between these conditions. </p>

<p>TIME-FREQUENCY ANALYSIS </p>

<p>In order to reveal event-related changes in power for the different 
frequency components of the EEG, time-frequency representa-
tions (TFR) of the single word trial data were computed by 
using the multi-taper approach described by Mitra and Pesaran 
(1999). TFRs were constructed in two different, partially over-
lapping frequency ranges. In the low-frequency range (2-30 Hz), 
2.5-Hz frequency-smoothing and 400 ms time-smoothing Han-
ning windows were used to compute power changes in frequency 
steps of 1 Hz and time steps of 10 ms. In the high-frequency range 
(25-100 Hz), power changes were computed in 2.5-Hz frequency 
steps and 10 ms time steps, with 2.5-Hz frequency-smoothing and 
400 ms time-smoothing discrete prolate spheroidal sequence win-
dows. These calculations were performed starting 500 ms before 
the word appeared on the screen to 1500 ms after the word onset. 
We calculated TFRs in two different ways to examine both evoked 
and induced activity, i.e., oscillatory activity that is both phase-
locked and non-phase-locked to the stimuli. For the first method, 
we calculated the TFRs on individual trials and averaged across 
those trials; this analysis reflects both induced and evoked activity. 
For the second method, we calculated the ERP by averaging over 
trials and then calculated the TFRs; this analysis reflects evoked 
activity only. By performing both types of analysis, we were able 
to determine if any effects were due to evoked or induced activity. 
The TFRs of single word epochs were averaged across the fol-
lowing four conditions: words in a sentence, words in a scrambled 
sentence, OC words, CC words. To calculate the event-related 
power changes, the TFRs were expressed as percent increases or 
decreases relative to a 200-ms pre-stimulus baseline. </p>

<p>STATISTICAL ANALYSIS </p>

<p>The significance of the difference between each two pairs of condi-
tions was evaluated by means of a cluster-based random permuta-
tion test (Maris and Oostenveld, 2007). This approach controls the </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 97 | 3 </p>

<p>Mellem et al. </p>

<p>Oscillatory dynamics of class and context </p>

<p>Type-1 error rate in a situation involving multiple comparisons. 
The cluster-based random permutation test naturally takes care of 
interactions between time points, electrodes, and frequency bins by 
identifying clusters of significant differences between conditions 
in the time, space, and frequency dimensions. The procedure is 
briefly described below. 
First, for every data point (electrode by time by frequency) of 
two conditions, a simple dependent-samples t -test is performed 
(giving uncorrected p-values). All adjacent data points exceed-
ing a preset significance level (5%) are grouped into clusters. For 
each cluster the sum of the t -statistics is used in the cluster-level 
test statistic. Next, a null distribution which assumes no differ-
ence between conditions is created. This distribution is obtained 
by 500 times randomly assigning the conditions in subjects and 
calculating the largest cluster-level statistic for each randomiza-
tion. Finally, the actually observed cluster-level test statistics are 
compared against the null distribution, and clusters falling in the 
highest or lowest 2.5th percentile are considered significant. 
We examined the main effects of context and class by perform-
ing the pairwise comparisons sentence-scrambled sentence and 
OC-CC, respectively. Then we tested for an interaction between 
class and context using the permutation test as follows: first we did 
two subtractions (1) OC in scrambled sentence-CC in scrambled 
sentence and (2) OC in sentence-CC in sentence. Then we tested 
whether these subtractions are different (i.e., whether there is an 
interaction between the two factors) by performing a permutation 
test on these two subtractions. The resulting p-value pertains to 
the interaction effect. For each contrast, we performed the clus-
ter analysis separately on lower frequencies (4-30 Hz) and higher 
frequencies (25-100 Hz). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The evoked analysis only revealed activity centered at 150 ms 
in the alpha-band. Additionally, we did not find any significant 
effects in the evoked responses for either the OC-CC comparison 
(Figure 2A) or the sentence-scrambled sentence (S-SS) compar-
ison (Figure 2B). The significant effects presented below thus 
reflect induced activity. </p>

<p>MAIN EFFECT OF CLASS </p>

<p>The contrast OC-CC revealed a significant main effect of class in 
the alpha range (Figure 3). A cluster spanning 200-700 ms was 
present in the analysis (p = 0.046). This effect resulted from a 
greater power decrease for OC words than for CC words. This was 
a widespread effect strongest over right occipital and left frontal 
areas. We examined but did not find a significant cluster in the 
gamma range. </p>

<p>MAIN EFFECT OF CONTEXT </p>

<p>The contrast sentence-scrambled sentence revealed a significant 
cluster spanning 0-700 ms in the alpha and low beta range 
(p = 0.006; Figure 4). The overall effect indicated by this single 
negative cluster resulted from less power in the sentence con-
dition than the scrambled sentence condition, specifically, an 
early smaller increase followed by a greater decrease. The clus-
ter spanned both anterior and posterior areas. We examined but 
did not find a significant cluster in the gamma range. </p>

<p>INTERACTION EFFECT </p>

<p>The interaction effect was marginally significant (p = 0.08) for 
lower frequencies; however, since establishing a possible interac-
tion between context and word class was one of the central issues 
behind this work, we also tested the simple effects. We found a 
significant cluster for the OC-CC contrast in the scrambled sen-
tence context (p = 0.016) which was centered on the alpha range 
between 150 and 700 ms (Figure 5). We did not find a significant 
cluster for the OC-CC contrast in the sentence context. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In order to examine the role of oscillatory dynamics during lexical-
semantic processing in an older population, we studied changes in 
power as subjects read OC and CC words in different contexts. Our 
results indicate that alpha (8-12 Hz) oscillations are differentially 
involved in reading words of different class, while both alpha and 
low beta (13-18 Hz) are implicated in reading words in different 
contexts. To follow-up on the previous study of OC and CC words 
(Bastiaansen et al., 2005), we also examined how context can affect 
reading words of different classes. 
The main finding of the study was a greater power decrease in 
the alpha-band for OC than CC words; this effect spanned 200-
600 ms over left frontal and right posterior areas. While power 
increases in the theta and gamma bands typically reflect active 
processing, the opposite is true for the alpha frequency range. 
Here, power decreases are generally thought to reflect more cor-
tical processing or engagement (e.g., Jokisch and Jensen, 2007; 
Klimesch et al., 2007). As OC words carry more lexical-semantics 
than CC words, reading OC words involves more lexical-semantic 
retrieval. Thus our results support the notion that alpha power 
decreases may be related to lexical-semantic retrieval operations. 
Evidence for this relationship comes from several other stud-
ies. In their comparison of OC vs. CC words, Bastiaansen et al. 
(2005) found not only theta power increases but also significant 
alpha power decreases between 300 and 500 ms at right posterior 
channels. The topography of our alpha effect looks remarkably 
similar to the topography found in their study. This suggests that 
alpha reflects similar processes in both studies. Studies of semantic 
judgment tasks have further implicated the involvement of alpha 
power decreases with semantic processing (Klimesch et al., 1997; 
Röhm et al., 2001; reviewed in Klimesch, 1999). Evidence from 
several studies also suggests that alpha power decreases can reflect 
increased attention (see Klimesch, 1999 for a review). It is unlikely 
that there were greater attentional demands in reading OC words 
compared with CC words; thus we favor a semantic interpretation 
for the word class effect. 
Given the consistency in the alpha response across studies, it 
was notable that we did not observe a significant effect in the theta 
range. The main results from the motivating studies (Bastiaansen 
et al., 2005, 2008) pointed to theta power increases as involved 
in lexical-semantic retrieval in a younger population of subjects. 
In contrast, our data suggest that theta power may not play a 
role in lexical-semantic processing in an older population. Instead, 
for older participants, semantic processing mechanisms may rely 
more on alpha oscillatory dynamics. We want to emphasize that 
the comparison of these effects across the two different studies is 
indirect and qualitative at best. Our study cannot speak directly </p>

<p>Frontiers in Psychology | Language Sciences </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 97 | 4 </p>

<p>Mellem et al. </p>

<p>Oscillatory dynamics of class and context </p>

<p>FIGURE 2 | Time-frequency representations (TFRs) of evoked data. 
(A) The evoked responses for open class (OC) and closed class (CC) 
conditions at a left frontal channel (F3). TFRs are shown separately for the OC 
and CC conditions, the raw difference between these conditions (OC-CC), </p>

<p>and the statistically thresholded difference (Masked). Plots are shown as a 
relative change compared to baseline. (B) The evoked responses for sentence 
(S) and scrambled sentence (SS) conditions at a left frontal channel (FC3). No 
significant difference exists for either comparison. </p>

<p>to aging effects in the theta and alpha-bands but rather suggests 
the existence of aging effects, a suggestion that should be further 
investigated by a direct comparison between two age groups in a 
subsequent study. Still a comparison between the studies is war-
ranted as they used similar stimuli (open and closed class words 
in a sentence context presented at the same duration and rate 
as our study) and tasks (participants were instructed to read the 
words and were asked comprehension questions). Two main dif-
ferences were the inclusion of a second variable in our study, that 
of context (Bastiaansen et al., 2005 did not present words outside 
of a sentence context), and the languages of presentation (Dutch 
vs. English). There is no evidence that oscillatory dynamics differ 
based on the testing language. 
Previous evidence suggests that theta power may decrease with 
age. Studies of working memory have observed that theta power 
in older subjects decreases relative to younger subjects (Karrasch 
et al., 2004; Cummins and Finnigan, 2007). Thus it is possible that 
we are observing an effect of aging in the shift from theta-band </p>

<p>effects to alpha-band effects though this cannot be said with more 
confidence without younger controls. Ultimately, the previously 
established theta power increase does not appear to be a robust 
phenomenon related to lexical-semantic retrieval in all popula-
tions. Further work directly comparing these different populations 
within the same study would lend more support to the hypothesis 
that decreases in theta power during lexical-semantic processing 
are related to aging. 
The observation that alpha and beta power was smaller for 
words in a sentence than a scrambled sentence between 0 and 
700 ms suggests that context modulates the oscillatory dynam-
ics in these bands. A methodological challenge exists, however, in 
interpreting this context effect. Since our time-frequency analysis 
computed all power changes relative to pre-word baselines, the 
post-word differences observed in the sentence-scrambled sen-
tence contrast may have two possible causes: (1) the processing-
related differences of these words, and (2) the processing-related 
differences in the baseline periods before each open or closed </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 97 | 5 </p>

<p>Mellem et al. </p>

<p>Oscillatory dynamics of class and context </p>

<p>FIGURE 3 | Time-frequency representations showing the alpha-band 
difference between the OC and CC conditions at a left frontal channel </p>

<p>(F3). The topography shows the raw difference between conditions during the 
time of the significant alpha effect. See legend to Figure 2 for more details. </p>

<p>FIGURE 4 | Time-frequency representations showing the alpha-and low beta-band difference between the sentence and scrambled sentence 
conditions at a left frontal channel (FC3). See legend to Figure 2 for details. </p>

<p>class word. The reason for these baseline differences is that the 
baseline power in the sentence context is likely to be influenced 
by sentence-level processes such as syntactic parsing, seman-
tic integration, working memory demands, or even attentional 
demands. These processes are probably not (or at least to a lesser 
extent) engaged in the scrambled sentence context which leads 
to the possible differences in baseline power between sentence 
and scrambled sentence conditions. Therefore, as this compar-
ison was not ideally controlled, we would feel it misleading 
to interpret the alpha and beta power changes as specifically 
reflecting one of these sentence-level processes. Further work with 
more tightly controlled conditions could help disambiguate the 
observed context main effects. </p>

<p>The previous study of OC and CC words by Bastiaansen et al. 
(2005) only included words within a sentence context; thus it was 
not clear if the observed effects solely reflected word-level pro-
cessing or may include sentence-level processing also. In order to 
examine how reading words of different class may be affected by 
context, we inspected the interaction between these factors. We fol-
lowed up the marginally significant interaction with simple effects 
tests of OC-CC in the scrambled sentence context and OC-CC 
in the sentence context and only found a significant effect for the 
contrast in the scrambled sentence context. Thus the class effect 
observed in the scrambled sentence context does not show up in 
the sentence context. This might indicate that the main effect of 
class is driven mainly by words in the scrambled sentence context </p>

<p>Frontiers in Psychology | Language Sciences </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 97 | 6 </p>

<p>Mellem et al. </p>

<p>Oscillatory dynamics of class and context </p>

<p>FIGURE 5 | TFRs showing (A) the alpha-band difference between the OC and CC conditions in the scrambled sentence (SS) context at a right posterior 
channel (O2), and (B) no significant difference between the OC and CC conditions in the sentence (S) context. See legend to Figure 2 for details. </p>

<p>and therefore primarily reflects word retrieval mechanisms. But 
alpha power decreases are present in both main effects of word 
class and context which suggests that alpha is driven by both word 
retrieval and sentence processing. We tentatively propose that an 
interaction between word class and context arises because the class 
effect is being obscured by sentence-level processing such that it is 
not seen in the sentence context. As mentioned above, alpha power 
decreases have been previously linked to attentional processing 
(see Klimesch, 1999 for a review). Thus one possibility is that larger 
attention-related alpha decreases in the sentence context may make 
it difficult to reliably detect the additional alpha decreases due to 
word class differences, at least not as clearly as observed in the 
scrambled sentence context. Thus greater attentional allocation 
during sentence reading than during scrambled sentence reading 
may be "swamping" the class effect. </p>

<p>Additionally, we wanted to extend the previous study on OC vs. 
CC words (Bastiaansen et al., 2005) by examining potential effects 
in the gamma frequency band (i.e., above 30 Hz). However, we did 
not observe significant gamma power changes between OC and 
CC words. Since a relationship between gamma power increases 
and sentence-level semantic unification/integration has previously 
been observed (Hagoort et al., 2004; Hald et al., 2006; Pena and 
Melloni, 2011), this absence of gamma band effects might suggest 
that processing lexical-semantics relies partly on different neu-
ronal mechanisms from processing sentence-level semantics. The 
current literature suggests that the neuronal dynamics of lexical-
semantic processing may be confined to the lower frequencies, as 
opposed to previously observed sentence-level semantic processes 
which are situated in the gamma frequency range. However, more 
work is needed to further substantiate such a claim. </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 97 | 7 </p>

<p>Mellem et al. </p>

<p>Oscillatory dynamics of class and context </p>

<p>Several potential confounds exist in this study. In comparing 
OC and CC words to examine differences in semantic content, 
it must be remembered that these word classes naturally have 
different frequencies and lengths. While we did see significant dif-
ferences in both frequency and length, evidence is currently lacking 
that these variables affect oscillatory dynamics. Bastiaansen et al. 
(2005) did not find that word frequency influenced the amplitude 
of oscillatory responses. Thus, it is probably unlikely that any word 
frequency difference would influence our power results. Another 
potential confound is repetition effects as we had more repeti-
tions for CC words than OC words. We did try to minimize this 
repetition and maximize exposure to a variety of CC words by 
including 69 unique CC words, but more repetition for CC words 
naturally reflects the higher word frequency of CC words. To our 
knowledge, there are no published reports of repetition effects on 
oscillatory dynamics during visual word processing with repetition 
lags greater than one (as we had here). </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>We observed a word class effect only in the alpha-band in a sample 
of older subjects. Thus the previously observed word class effects 
on theta power changes in a younger participant sample do not 
seem to be a robust effect across populations of different age. This 
suggests that there may be different neuronal dynamics during 
word retrieval for different populations. Moreover, the interaction 
between word class and context suggests that there is an interaction 
of word retrieval mechanisms with sentence-level comprehension 
mechanisms in the alpha-band. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was partially supported by NIDCD R01 DC007169 
and R01 HD036019 (Rhonda B. Friedman and Lea K. 
Pilgrim), NIDCD F31DC010545 (Monika S. Mellem), and NCRR 
R21RR025786 (Andrei V. Medvedev). Preparation of the manu-
script was partially supported by NIDCD R01 DC10780. </p>



<p>Conflict of Interest Statement: The 
authors declare that the research was 
conducted in the absence of any com-
mercial or financial relationships that 
could be construed as a potential con-
flict of interest. </p>

<p>Received: 20 December 2011; accepted: 14 
March 2012; published online: 
April 
2012. 
Citation: Mellem MS, Bastiaansen 
MCM, Pilgrim LK, Medvedev AV 
and Friedman RB (2012) Word 
class and context affect alpha-band 
oscillatory dynamics in an older pop-
ulation. Front. Psychology 3:97. doi: 
10.3389/fpsyg.2012.00097 
This article was submitted to Frontiers in 
Language Sciences, a specialty of Frontiers 
in Psychology. 
Copyright © 2012 Mellem, Bastiaansen, 
Pilgrim, Medvedev and Friedman. This 
is an open-access article distributed under 
the terms of the Creative Commons Attri-
bution Non Commercial License, which 
permits non-commercial use, distribu-
tion, and reproduction in other forums, 
provided the original authors and source 
are credited. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Psychology | Language Sciences </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 97 | 8 </p>

<p>09 </p>

</text></tei>