<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3428639" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objectives: There is a relationship between infant feeding method and 
maternal postpartum depression (PPD). This study was carried out in an 
Iranian population to compare the prevalence of PPD symptoms between 
breast feeding and non-breast feeding mothers for first time. 
Methods: Four health centers in Ahvas were selected by random 
sampling in 2009. At first 78 non-breast feeding mothers at two months 
postpartum were recruited in the study and then 78 breast feeding 
mothers were recruited through random sampling. They were re-
assessed in six months postpartum period. Demographic and obstetric 
data questionnaire and Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale (EPDS) 
were used . </p>

<p>Results: There was a significant difference in prevalence of Edinburgh 
Postnatal Depression Scale positive between breast feeding (2.5%) and </p>

<p>non-breast feeding mothers (19.4%) (p=0.004). 
Conclusion: Infant feeding method may be related to maternal mood 
disorder and breast feeding mothers are less depressed. Breastfeeding 
may decrease PPD. </p>

<p>Tashakori, Zamani , Davasaz Irani </p>

<p> 
Iranian J Psychiatry 7:2, Spring 2012 </p>

<p>They found "consistent trends that women with 
depressive symptomatology may be at increased risk to 
prematurely discontinue BF, report more BF worries 
and difficulties, and have decreased levels of BF self-
efficacy. There is also beginning evidence to suggest 
that they might be less likely to initiate BF and to do it 
exclusively." Dennis CL et al. suggested additional 
research to confirm their results and examine the 
unidirectional pathway of negative effect of maternal 
mood on infant-feeding outcomes rather than reverse 
pathway (10). Therefore, we compared the prevalence 
of PPD symptoms between BF and non BF mothers to 
assess inverse relationship between BF problems and 
PPD. To our best knowledge, this is the first study 
carried out in Iranian population to compare the 
prevalence of PPD symptoms between BF and non BF 
mothers. </p>

<p>Materials and Method </p>

<p>This is a descriptive-analytic case-control study. The 
study was approved by Institutional Review Board of 
Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences 
(AJUMS). Four health centers in Ahvaz were selected 
by random sampling in 2009. Staff members of these 
health centers collaborated in data collection and a 
medical student collected questionnaire from these 
health centers. Because of low prevalence of non-BF 
mothers, at first, all non-BF mothers (78 non-BF 
mothers) attending health centers were requested to 
participate in the study and then 78 BF mothers 
participated through random sampling and their 
consent was acquired orally. We tried to consider 
similarity in other variables such as some risk factors 
of PPD (21) between the two groups. Exclusive BF is 
defined as the feeding of breast milk only, and no other 
liquids or solids with the exception of drops or syrups 
consisting of vitamins, minerals supplements, or 
medicines (25). This method was assumed for at least 
six months (6) for the BF group, and they were re-
assessedfour months later for continuation of BF. 
Mothers who discontinued BF due to precautions for 
taking medications were excluded. 
Participants were asked to complete demographic and 
obstetric data questionnaires and Edinburgh Postnatal 
Depression Scale (EPDS). Demographic and obstetric 
data questionnaires contained maternal age, 
employment history, educational level, economic 
status, previous history of depression or PPD, previous 
history of abortion or still birth, type of delivery, 
gender of infant, number of previous pregnancies, 
infant gender satisfaction, pregnancy satisfaction, and 
reason for BF cessation. 
The EPDS is a 10-item self-report scale for measuring 
the intensity of depressive symptoms experienced 
within the past 7 days. Each statement is rated on a 
scale from 0 to 3 ("yes, most of the time" to "no, not at 
all"), total score ranging from 0 to 30. Seven of the 10 
items are scored reversely (26). The cut-off score for 
indication of PPD is 12/13 or greater (26-29). For the 
first time, Cox et al. designed EPDS as a screening tool </p>

<p>for the secondary prevention of PPD (30) with 
established validity and reliability. A cut-off score of 
13 or greater identified probable postnatal depression 
with a sensitivity of 86% and a specificity of 78% (31). 
The best cut-off point in Iranian sample is 12/13 with 
sensitivity of 95.3% and specificity of 87/9% (32), 
which can be used 6-8 weeks after delivery to screen 
for PPD (5). We used EPDS with cut-off of 12 and 
translated it to Farsi. 
Data were analyzed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Package for 
the Social Sciences (SPSS</rs>) windows <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 13.0</rs>. 
Results were calculated as frequencies (%), means and 
standard deviations. Groups' comparisons were done 
by chi-square test and odds ratio (95% confidence 
interval) and t-test. A probability of P&lt;0.05 was 
considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Seventy-two non-BF mothers and 78 BF mothers 
completed the questionnaires. Questionnaires of six 
non BF mothers were excluded because they were not 
filled completely. Table 1 demonstrates demographic 
data, and table 2 shows obstetric data of the 
participants). The two groups were similar in different 
variables. Most of them were 20-30 years old, 
homekeeper, had a high school diploma, with moderate 
economic status (table1), and were satisfied with their 
pregnancy and infant's gender (table 2). Most of them 
had vaginal delivery, one child, and negative previous 
history of depression, PPD, abortion, still birth and 
pregnancy (table 2). The most common reason of BF 
cessation among non BF mothers with or without PPD 
was subjective feeling of having poor lactation (table 
3). There was a significant difference in EPDS score 
between BF (16.40 ± 4.10) and non BF (18.06 ± 2.69) 
mothers, and rate of women with EPDS≥12 was 
significantly higher in the non BF group (n=14) than 
BF group (n=2) (P=0.004, t =2.9, df=148). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, prevalence of postpartum depression 
symptoms in non-BF mothers was significantly higher 
than BF mothers. Therefore, there is a probable 
association between non-BF and depressive symptoms 
among mothers in eight weeks after delivery. 
This result is relatively consistent with other studies (8-
10). In a study carried out by Thome M et al. they 
concluded that depressive symptoms are associated 
with lower levels of exclusive BF (8). Abou-Saleh MT 
et al. also found that BF mothers have significantly 
lower level of PPD symptoms (9), but their sample size 
was noticeably smaller as compared to this study. 
Additionally, in those studies, exclusive BF was well 
defined, whereas in this study exclusive BF has been 
defined based on WHO's definition. These differences 
make the comparison of our results with other studies 
more difficult. In the systematic review of Dennis CL 
et al., seven studies found a relationship between BF 
and lower level of depressive symptoms (10). </p>

<p>Published by Tehran University of Medical Sciences (www.tums.ac.ir) </p>

<p>Comparison Of Prevalence Of Postpartum Depression… </p>

<p> 
Iranian J Psychiatry 7:2, Spring 2012 </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic data of breastfeeding and non breastfeeding mothers </p>

<p>BF 
Non BF 
number 
% 
number 
% 
Age (year) 
20-30 
64 
82.05 
62 
86.11 
31-40 
14 
17.94 
10 
13.88 
p=0.30 
t=1.04 
df=148 
Employment 
Employed 
58 
74.35 
52 
74.28 
homekeeper 
20 
25.64 
18 
25.71 
P=0.016 
Z=0.5 
Economic status 
High 
33 
42.85 
22 
31.42 
Medium 
41 
53.24 
44 
62.85 
low 
3 
3.89 
4 
5.71 
Educational level 
illiterate 
0 
0 
3 
4.22 
Primary school 
13 
16.66 
12 
16.90 
Middle school 
6 
7.92 
13 
18.30 
High school 
37 
47.43 
28 
39.43 
University 
22 
28.20 
15 
21.12 
*breastfeeding </p>

<p>Table 2: obstetric data of breastfeeding and non breastfeeding mothers </p>

<p>BF 
Non BF 
number 
% 
number 
% 
Previous delivery 
1 
46 
61.33 
35 
50.00 
2 
17 
22.66 
24 
34.28 
3 
10 
13.33 
8 
11.42 
4 
2 
2.66 
3 
4.28 
pregnancy satisfaction 
Yes 
75 
96.15 
62 
86.11 
No 
3 
3.84 
10 
13.88 
P=0.053 
Z=1.9 
Infant gender satisfaction 
Yes 
75 
96.15 
62 
86.21 
No 
3 
3.84 
10 
13.88 
P=0.314 
Z=1.01 
Type of delivery 
Cesarean section 
34 
43.58 
22 
31.42 
vaginal 
44 
56.41 
48 
68.57 
P=2.04 
Z=1.27 
abortion or still birth 
Yes 
11 
14.38 
9 
12.50 
no 
66 
85.71 
63 
87.50 
P=0.204 
Z=1.27 
Number of offspring 
1 
49 
62.82 
34 
48.57 
2 
17 
21.79 
24 
34.28 
3 
10 
12.82 
8 
11.42 
4 
2 
2.56 
3 
4.28 
5 or more 
0 
0 
1 
1.42 
previous depression or PPD* 
Yes 
4 
5.12 
7 
9.72 
No 
74 
94.87 
65 
90.27 
P=0.135 
Z=1.4 
*postpartum depression </p>

<p>Table 3: the reasons of breastfeeding cessation in non breastfeeding mothers </p>

<p>non BF mothers 
with or without PPD 
non BF mothers with PPD </p>

<p>reason of BF cessation 
number 
% 
number 
% </p>

<p>Low weight of infant 
11 
15.27 
5 
35.71 
feeling of inadequate lactation 
48 
66.66 
9 
64.28 
Small breast 
3 
4.16 
0 
0 
Advise of other person 
4 
5.55 
0 
0 
Maternal illness 
6 
8.33 
0 
0 
total 
72 
100 
14 
100 </p>

<p>Published by Tehran University of Medical Sciences (www.tums.ac.ir) </p>

<p>Tashakori, Zamani , Davasaz Irani </p>

<p> 
Iranian J Psychiatry 7:2, Spring 2012 </p>

<p>The relationship between non-BF and depression might 
share some similarities with BF discontinuation and 
child loss which can lead to depression (33). Gallup Jr 
GG et al. suggested that "the decision to bottle feed 
unwittingly mimics conditions associated with the 
death of an infant. Child loss is a well-documented 
trigger for depression particularly in mothers, and 
growing evidence shows that bottle feeding is a risk 
factor for postpartum depression (34)." In this study, 
the most common reason of non-BF was subjective 
feeling of having poor lactation and low weight in 
infants. This result is consistent with previous 
hypothesis about cognitive errors in depression (33). 
Thus, worrying about infant or lactation may be related 
to depression. Galler JR et al. assessed 226 mother-
infant dyads and found that women who believed that 
BF was better than bottle feeding at seven weeks 
postpartum were more likely to continue BF up to six 
months postpartum, and were also less depressed at 
seven weeks and six months postpartum. Galler JR et 
al., also concluded that feeding attitudes and maternal 
mood are closely linked, but each of them contributed 
independently to BF, especially at six months after 
childbirth (35). On the other hand, the relationship 
between maternal identity, early BF cessation and 
distress is complex. Cooke M et al. concluded that the 
relationship between BF cessation and EPDS score is 
varied according to Maternal Role Attainment (MRA) 
level. Women with high MRA level and no longer 
duration of BF had higher EPDS scores and distress 
compared to women with low MRA level and those 
with high MRA level and continuation of BF. They 
suggested it may be helpful to provide support, 
psychological assessment, and to highlight strong 
belief about the importance of BF and maternal role for 
those women who decide to stop BF earlier (36). 
Other psychological effects of BF may be through 
autonomic responses and endocrine system. BF 
increases parasympathetic/sympathetic activity ratio 
among mothers, while an inverse change is occurred by 
bottle feeding (3). Also, BF increases maternal-fetal 
bonding by oxytocin secretion (7) and can 
consequently lead to lower level of distress (37). 
Besides, both depressed mothers and their infants are 
more relaxed during BF than bottle feeding (2). 
In sum, BF and PPD may have a reciprocal 
relationship. Mothers with PPD may not initiate or 
continue BF or do it exclusively. Conversely, non-BF 
mothers may experience higher levels of PPD. 
Encouraging BF continuation may prevent or decrease 
depressive symptoms. 
This study had some limitations. One limitation was 
the small sample size due to voluntary participation 
and lower prevalence of non-BF. Another limitation 
was difficulty in controlling for potential confounding 
variables, because of many potential risk factors for 
PPD. Another limitation of this study was the probable 
absence of mothers with severe depression. Also, we 
did not assume the time of initiation or cessation of BF. 
Comparison of our results with that of other studies </p>

<p>was difficult due to some methodological differences 
such as BF definition, EPDS cut-off points and 
different self -report measures. 
Conclusion: our results suggest that PPD symptoms 
may be higher in non-exclusive BF mothers as 
compared to exclusive BF mothers. This finding 
supports the need for mental health screening of non-
BF mothers and mothers who decide to discontinue 
exclusive BF. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Special thanks to Ahvaz Jundishapur University of 
Medical Sciences for their financial support. </p>

<p> 
between 
infant-feeding 
outcomes 
and 
postpartum 
depression: 
a 
qualitative 
systematic review. Pediatrics 2009; 123: 736-
751. 
11. Sadock BJ, Sadock VA, Kaplan HI. Kaplan 
and Sadock's synopsis of psychiatry : 
behavioral sciences/clinical psychiatry, 10 </p>

<p>th </p>

<p>eds. Baltimore: Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins; 
2007. </p>

<p>Published by Tehran University of Medical Sciences (www.tums.ac.ir) </p>

<p>Comparison Of Prevalence Of Postpartum Depression… </p>

<p> 
Iranian J Psychiatry 7:2, Spring 2012 </p>



<p>Published by Tehran University of Medical Sciences (www.tums.ac.ir) </p>

</text></tei>