<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3809360" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Bortezomib is a proteasome inhibitor used for the treatment of relapsed/refractory multiple myeloma (MM). However, intrinsic 
and acquired resistance to bortezomib has already been observed in MM patients. In a previous report, we demonstrated that 
changes in the expression of mitochondrial genes lead to changes in mitochondrial activity and bortezomib susceptibility or 
resistance, and their combined effects contribute to the differential sensitivity or resistance of MM cells to bortezomib. Here 
we report that the combination treatment of bortezomib and 2-methoxyestradiol (2ME), a natural estrogen metabolite, induces 
mitochondria-mediated apoptotic cell death of bortezomib-resistant MM KMS20 cells via mitochondrial reactive oxygen species 
(ROS) overproduction. Bortezomib plus 2ME treatment induces a higher level of cell death compared with treatment with 
bortezomib alone and increases mitochondrial ROS and Ca 2 þ levels in KMS20 cells. Pretreatment with the antioxidant 
N-acetyl-L-cysteine scavenges mitochondrial ROS and decreases cell death after treatment with bortezomib plus 2ME in KMS20 
cells. Moreover, we observed that treatment with bortezomib plus 2ME maintains the activation of c-Jun N-terminal kinase 
(JNK) and mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase kinase 4/7 (MKK4/7). Collectively, combination treatment with bortezomib 
and 2ME induces cell death via JNK-MKK4/7 activation by overproduction of mitochondrial ROS. Therefore, combination 
therapy with specific mitochondrial-targeting drugs may prove useful to the development of novel strategies for the treatment 
of bortezomib-resistant MM patients. 
tumorigenesis. 6,7 Therefore, there is a growing need for the 
development of optimal combinations of these novel agents to 
improve the survival of patients suffering from myeloma. 
Recently, we reported a role for mitochondria in resistance 
to bortezomib-induced cell death and found that human 
MM KMS20 cells were resistant to bortezomib due to 
potentiation of mitochondrial function. 8 In that report, 
changes in the expression levels of certain genes, such as 
cyclophilin D, the mitochondrial calcium uniporter, and 
superoxide dismutase 2, led to changes in both mito-
chondrial activity and bortezomib susceptibility or resistance; 
their combined effects contributed to differential sensitivity or 
resistance of MM cells to bortezomib. Specifically, we showed 
that changes in mitochondrial reactive oxygen species (ROS) 
levels via depletion of superoxide dismutase 2 and treatment </p>

<p>National Research Laboratory for Mitochondrial Signaling, Department of Physiology, College of Medicine, Cardiovascular and Metabolic Disease Center, 
Inje University, Busan, Korea 
Correspondence: Professor J Han, National Research Laboratory for Mitochondrial Signaling, Department of Physiology, College of Medicine, Cardiovascular 
and Metabolic Disease Center, Inje University, 633-165 Gaegeum-dong, Busanjin-gu, Busan 614-735, Korea. 
E-mail: phyhanj@inje.ac.kr 
Received 25 April 2013; revised 23 July 2013; accepted 1 August 2013 </p>

<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine (2013) 45, e50; doi:10.1038/emm.2013.104 
&amp; 2013 KSBMB. All rights reserved 2092-6413/13 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/emm </p>

<p>with 2-methoxyestradiol (2ME), known as a SOD inhibitor, 
induced bortezomib-resistant MM cell death. However, the 
mechanisms that regulate the enhancement of cell death 
after treatment of bortezomib-resistant KMS20 cells with a 
combination of 2ME and bortezomib remain unknown. 
The compound 2ME is a natural metabolite of the endo-
genous estrogens 17b-estradiol and 2-hydroxyestradiol. 9 
Recent studies showed that 2ME exerts both anti-tumor and 
anti-angiogenic activities on various tumors, and 2ME is 
currently in a clinical trial as a cancer treatment. 10 The anti-
tumor mechanism of 2ME is multi-faceted, including the 
induction of G1 or G2/M cell cycle arrest and tumor cell 
apoptosis; the increased expression of FAS, p53 and p21WAF1; 
the activation of c-jun N-terminal activated kinase (JNK); 
the inhibition of tubulin polymerization; the formation of 
ROS; the mitochondrial release of cytochrome c. 11-19 In recent 
years, many clinical trials have evaluated the therapeutic 
efficacy of 2ME against MM. However, little is known about 
the molecular events implicated in the ability of 2ME to 
overcome bortezomib resistance. 
In this study, we investigated the anti-myeloma activity of 
the combination treatment of 2ME and bortezomib in 
bortezomib-resistant KMS20 cells. We found that this com-
bined treatment induces mitochondria-mediated cell death via 
mitochondrial ROS overproduction and JNK activation in 
bortezomib-resistant KMS20 cells. Moreover, we present 
evidence that the initial event in the mechanism of action of 
2ME is the induction of ROS in mitochondria, which leads to 
bortezomib resistance. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Reagents </p>

<p>Bortezomib was purchased from Selleck Biochemicals (Houston, TX, 
USA). The fluorescent dyes tetramethylrhodamine, ethyl ester, per-
chlorate (TMRE), and rhod-2AM were purchased from Invitrogen 
(Carlsbad, CA, USA). The chemicals 2ME, N-acetyl-L-cysteine (NAc), 
and L-buthionine-sulfoximine were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich 
(St Louis, MO, USA). </p>

<p>Cell culture </p>

<p>KMS20, KMS26 and KMS28BM cells were originally obtained from 
the Kawasaki Medical School (Kurashiki, Japan) and were maintained 
in RPMI 1640 (Lonza). The culture medium was supplemented with 
10% fetal bovine serum (Lonza) and 1% antibiotic-antimycotic 
solution (Invitrogen), and cells were grown in a 5% CO 2 incubator. </p>

<p>Western blot and subcellular fractionation </p>

<p>Cells were lysed in lysis buffer A (20 mM HEPES (pH 7.5), 1 mM 
EDTA, 2 mM EGTA, 150 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, 1% Triton X-100 
and protease cocktail I/II (Sigma-Aldrich)). Proteins were separated 
by sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis and 
transferred onto nitrocellulose membranes; membranes were blocked 
with 5% skim milk in 0.01 M Tris-buffered saline (pH 7.5) containing 
0.5% Tween 20 and incubated with the appropriate primary 
antibodies. For cytochrome c release after bortezomib plus 2ME 
treatment, subcellular fractions were obtained using the ProteoExtract 
Subcellular Proteome Extraction Kit (Calbiochem, La Jolla, CA, USA). 
The purity of each fraction was verified using the following selective </p>

<p>markers: a-tubulin (cytosolic marker) and mitochondrial protein 
peroxiredoxin III (mitochondrial marker). 20 </p>

<p>Flow cytometry for detection of cell death </p>

<p>To estimate cell death, fluorescein isothiocyanate-conjugated, annexin 
V-specific antibody was labeled with propidium iodide (PI), accord-
ing to the manufacturer's instructions (BD Biosciences, Franklin 
Lakes, NJ, USA). Annexin V-and/or PI-positive cells were analyzed by 
FACSCanto flow cytometry (BD Biosciences). Cell cycle distribution 
was determined by DNA staining with PI (Sigma). A total of 1 Â 10 6 
cells were collected and fixed in 70% ethanol. Cell pellets 
were suspended in PI and simultaneously treated with RNase at 
37 1C for 30 min. The percentages of cells in different phases of the 
cell cycle were measured using a FACSCalibur flow cytometer (BD 
Biosciences). </p>

<p>Measurement of mitochondrial ROS </p>

<p>Mitochondrial ROS generation was assessed using Mito-Sox red 
(Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR, USA). KMS20 cells were seeded 
onto 30-mm culture dishes at a density of 3 Â 10 5 cells and incubated 
with 1 mM Mito-Sox for 20 min at 37 1C. For quantitative analysis of 
ROS generation, Mito-Sox-treated cells were analyzed by flow 
cytometry using a FACSCantoII instrument. Fluorescence images of 
Mito-Sox-loaded cells were acquired using a confocal laser scanning 
microscope (LSM700, Carl-Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany) and 
analyzed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Axiovision microscope software</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 4.8.2</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Carl-Zeiss</rs>). </p>

<p>Mitochondria membrane potential analysis </p>

<p>Mitochondrial membrane potential (DC m ) was assessed in KMS20 
cells using the DC m -specific fluorescent dye, TMRE. Cells (1 Â 10 6 ) 
from each group were incubated with 200 nM TMRE for 20 min at 
37 1C. TMRE-loaded cells were analyzed using a FACSCantoII flow 
cytometer (BD Biosciences). Fluorescence images of TMRE-loaded 
cells were acquired using a confocal laser scanning microscope 
(Carl-Zeiss). </p>

<p>Mitochondria calcium concentration assay </p>

<p>Mitochondria Ca 2 þ relative concentrations were analyzed in KMS20 
cells using the mitochondrial Ca 2 þ -sensitive fluorescent dye, rhod-
2AM. A cold/warm incubation protocol was used to exclusively load 
mitochondria with rhod-2AM. Briefly, cells (1 Â 10 6 cells per sample) 
were washed with phosphate-buffered saline and stained with 5 mM 
rhod-2AM in normal Tyrode's solution containing 143 mM NaCl, 
5.4 mM KCl, 1.8 mM CaCl 2 , 0.5 mM MgCl 2 , 5.5 mM glucose and 5 mM 
HEPES (pH 7.4 with KOH) for 120 min at 4 1C, followed by a 30-min 
incubation at 37 1C. Rhod-2AM-loaded cells were analyzed using a 
FACSCantoII flow cytometer (BD Biosciences). Fluorescence images 
of TMRE-loaded cells were acquired using a confocal laser scanning 
microscope (Carl-Zeiss). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data were analyzed using the Student's t-test and <rs id="software-0" type="software">SigmaPlot</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">8.0</rs> 
software; P values were derived to assess statistical significance as 
follows: *Po0.05; **Po0.01; and ***Po0.001. Data for all figures 
are expressed as the means±standard deviation (s.d.) of three 
independent experiments. </p>

<p>Inducing bortezomib-resistant cell death 
I-S Song et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Combination treatment with bortezomib plus 2ME induces 
cell death of bortezomib-resistant KMS20 cells 
We previously showed that mitochondrial functional 
differences, including DC m , oxygen consumption rate, ATP 
production and Ca 2 þ retention capacity, were involved in the 
susceptibility of MM cells to undergo bortezomib-mediated 
cell death. 8 In that report, we showed that MM cell lines had 
different susceptibilities against bortezomib according to their 
mitochondrial function. Specifically, KMS20 cells were 
resistant to bortezomib-mediated cell death. As shown in 
Figure 1a, fewer than 30% of KMS20 cells underwent cell 
death, even after 75 nM bortezomib treatment. We have now 
extended our work to investigate the combination of borte-
zomib and 2ME in bortezomib-resistant KMS20 cells. 
We first determined the single effects of 2ME in bortezomib-
resistant KMS20 cells and bortezomib-sensitive KMS28BM 
cells before examining the combination effects of 2ME. As 
shown in Figure 1b, cell death was induced slightly in 
bortezomib-resistant KMS20 cells but was induced in over 
50% of bortezomib-sensitive KMS28BM cells. Therefore, 
KMS20 cells showed resistance after a single treatment with 
either bortezomib or 2ME. To examine the beneficial effect of 
combination treatment with bortezomib and 2ME, we per-
formed flow cytometric analyses after labeling with PI/annexin 
V-fluorescein isothiocyanate in KMS20 cells. KMS20 cells were 
cultured in different concentrations of bortezomib containing 
1 mM 2ME for 48 h. Combination treatment significantly 
increased cell death in KMS20 and KMS26 cells in a 
bortezomib dose-dependent manner (Figure 1c). To verify 
whether the effects of combination treatment were induced by 
apoptosis, sub-G1 phase DNA content was measured after 
bortezomib or combination treatment of KMS20 cells. 
DNA content analysis also revealed a population of cells in </p>

<p>the sub-G1 hypodiploid phase, indicating that apoptosis 
was significantly increased in KMS20 cells treated with 
bortezomib plus 2ME in a bortezomib dose-dependent man-
ner (Figure 1d). 
Immunoreactive bands for cleaved caspase-8 and caspase-3 
were more intense in lysates after combined treatment than in 
lysates after a single treatment (Figure 2a). We examined 
whether mitochondria were involved in combined treatment-
induced cell death. In the mitochondrial apoptotic pathway, 
the signaling mediator between the cytosol and mitochondria 
is cytochrome c. Thus, cytochrome c release was compared in 
bortezomib-treated KMS20 cells and in cells treated with both 
bortezomib and 2ME. Cytochrome c release was markedly 
increased in the cytosol of cells treated with both compounds 
compared with cells treated only with bortezomib (Figure 2b). 
As a result of this release, caspase-3 activation was subse-
quently enhanced in cells receiving the combination treatment 
compared with cells receiving a single treatment (Figure 2a). 
These results indicate that KMS20 is a bortezomib-resistant 
MM cell line and that combination treatment with 2ME can 
induce a cell death mechanism in these bortezomib-resistant 
cells. Moreover, we reported that mitochondrial activity 
contributes to the differential sensitivity or resistance of MM 
cells to bortezomib in our previous study. Thereby, we propose 
that the combination treatment of 2ME and bortezomib may 
induce cell death via the regulation of mitochondria activity of 
bortezomib-resistant KMS20 cells. </p>

<p>Combination treatment with bortezomib and 2ME induces 
mitochondrial dysfunction via overproduction of 
mitochondrial ROS in KMS20 cells 
To investigate the connection between induction of cell death 
by combination treatment and mitochondrial activity in 
bortezomib-resistant MM, we examined mitochondrial </p>

<p>Figure 1 Combination effects of 2-methoxyestradiol (2ME) and bortezomib on apoptosis of KMS20 cells. (a) KMS cells were incubated 
with different doses of bortezomib, and cell viability was determined by fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) analysis after propidium 
iodide (PI)/annexin V-based staining. (b) KMS20 (left panel) and KMS28BM (right panel) cells were treated with 2ME at the indicated 
doses for 48 h and subjected to FACS analysis as described above. (c) KMS20 (left panel) and KMS26 (right panel) cells were treated 
with bortezomib plus 2ME for 48 h at the indicated doses, and cell death was measured as described above. (d) Sub-G1 percentage 
(apoptotic cell population) was measured by PI staining and flow cytometry after 48 h. </p>

<p>Inducing bortezomib-resistant cell death 
I-S Song et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>

<p>function by assessing [Ca 2 þ ] M , DC m and mitochondrial ROS 
production. First, we measured mitochondrial ROS levels 
using an oxidant-sensitive fluorescent dye, Mito-SOX red. 
While bortezomib treatment alone did not trigger superoxide 
anion production in KMS20 cells, the combination treatment 
resulted in a remarkable increase in mitochondrial ROS levels 
(Figures 3a and d). Next, we determined whether the increase 
in mitochondrial Ca 2 þ concentrations contributes to cyto-
toxicity after combination treatment. KMS20 cells were 
incubated in the presence of different bortezomib concentra-
tions plus 2ME (1 mM) for 48 h, treated with rhod-2AM and 
subjected to flow cytometry (Figure 3b). We observed an 
increase in [Ca 2 þ ] M after bortezomib plus 2ME treatment. 
However, the increase in [Ca 2 þ ] M was independent of the 
dose of bortezomib, as shown in Figure 3b. We next examined 
the effects of bortezomib plus 2ME on the levels of DC m in 
KMS20 cells. The levels of DC m were measured using TMRE, 
which accumulates in mitochondria via a DC m -driven process. 
Because uptake of TMRE into mitochondria depends on 
DC m , a collapse of DC m is associated with a decrease in the 
fluorescence intensity of TMRE. Flow cytometric analyses of 
red fluorescence indicated that the combination treatment of 
KMS20 cells exhibited a depolarization of DC m and that this 
response increased according to the dosage of bortezomib as 
the level of mitochondrial ROS (Figure 3c). Taken together, 
these data suggest that increased mitochondrial ROS levels 
may cause combination treatment-induced cell death in 
KMS20 cells. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Combination treatment with bortezomib plus 2-methoxy-
estradiol (2ME) induces caspase activation via a mitochondria-
mediated intrinsic apoptotic pathway. (a) KMS20 cells were treated 
with bortezomib plus 2ME at the indicated doses for 48 h 
and subjected to western blotting using the indicated anti-
bodies. (b) KMS20 cells were treated with bortezomib plus 2ME 
for 48 h, and cells were separated into cytosolic and mito-
chondrial fractions. Tubulin and Prx3 were used as cytosolic 
and mitochondrial markers, respectively. PARP, poly (ADP-ribose) 
polymerase. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Combination treatment with bortezomib plus 2-methoxyestradiol (2ME) enhances mitochondrial reactive oxygen species 
production, leading to mitochondrial dysfunction. (a) KMS20 cells were treated with bortezomib plus 2ME at the indicated doses, 
subjected to flow cytometry after staining with Mito-Sox and quantified. (b) Mitochondrial Ca 2 þ concentrations in KMS20 cells were 
measured before and after treatment with bortezomib and/or 2ME using a FACSCantoII instrument. (c) Mitochondrial membrane potential 
(DC m ) in KMS20 cells treated with bortezomib plus 2ME was measured by tetramethylrhodamine, ethyl ester, perchlorate (TMRE) 
staining and fluorescence-activated cell sorting analysis. (d) KMS20 cells were treated with bortezomib plus 2ME for 48 h, and cells were 
stained with Mito-Sox, rhod-2AM and TMRE, and analyzed by confocal microscopy. </p>

<p>Inducing bortezomib-resistant cell death 
I-S Song et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>

<p>Increased mitochondrial ROS levels after bortezomib plus 
2ME treatment induces KMS20 cell death via prolonged JNK 
activation 
To determine whether the increase in mitochondrial ROS 
levels causes cell death in response to combination treatment, 
we used NAc as an antioxidant. 16 We found that NAc 
successfully scavenged mitochondrial ROS after treatment 
with bortezomib plus 2ME in KMS20 cells (Figure 4a). Next, 
we examined the effects of treatment with bortezomib plus 
2ME and NAc in KMS20 cells by performing a western blot 
(Figure 4b). KMS20 cells treated with bortezomib plus 2ME 
were more sensitive to bortezomib-mediated cell death than a 
single treatment with bortezomib. Pretreatment with NAc 
reduced the rate of cell death that had increased after 
combination treatment with 2ME and bortezomib in KMS20 
cells. Moreover, the effects of combination treatment were fully 
reversed by the addition of zVAD-fmk, whereas it was not 
increased by the addition of L-buthionine-sulfoximine, a 
known pro-oxidant. These results suggest that the increase of 
ROS via 2ME treatment can overcome bortezomib resistance. 
Therefore, we performed flow cytometric analyses after label-
ing with PI/annexin V-fluorescein isothiocyanate in KMS20 </p>

<p>cells to confirm these results (Figure 4c). As shown in 
Figure 4c, the pattern of cell death was identical to the western 
blotting results. Especially, increase of cell death by addition of 
L-buthionine-sulfoximine was not observed as well as in 
western blot. These results indicate that cell death induced 
by treatment with 2ME plus bortezomib likely involves 
mitochondrial ROS overproduction. Additionally, JNK, whose 
activation is sustained by mitochondrial ROS, 21 was also 
phosphorylated after combination treatment. From these 
data, we propose that activation of JNK is actively involved 
in the induction of cell death after bortezomib plus 2ME 
treatment. 
To determine the regulators of apoptotic cell death after 
treatment with bortezomib plus 2ME, we analyzed the activity 
of mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) associated with 
cell death induced by mitochondrial ROS in KMS20 cells. 
Stress-activated JNK and p38 regulate a variety of intracellular 
processes in response to environmental stresses, cytokines, 
ROS and growth factors. KMS20 cells treated with either 
bortezomib alone or bortezomib plus 2ME for 48 h were 
subjected to western blot analysis using anti-p-p38MAPK 
and p-SAPK/JNK antibodies (Figure 5a). Phosphorylated </p>

<p>Figure 4 Suppression of bortezomib/2-methoxyestradiol (2ME)-induced mitochondrial reactive oxygen species (ROS) accumulation in 
N-acetyl-L-cysteine (NAc)-treated KMS20 cells. (a) KMS20 cells were pretreated with the indicated doses of NAc for 1 h, and co-treated 
with bortezomib plus 2ME for 48 h. Mitochondrial ROS production was measured using a FACSCantoII instrument after Mito-Sox staining. 
(b, c) KMS20 cells were pretreated with NAc (5 mM), L-buthionine-sulfoximine (BSO) and zVAD-fmk (10 mM) for 1 h as indicated on the 
figure, and co-treated with bortezomib plus 2ME for 48 h. (b) Cells were subjected to western blotting using the indicated antibodies and 
(c) cell viability was determined by fluorescence-activated cell sorting analysis after propidium iodide/annexin V-based staining. PARP, 
poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase. </p>

<p>Inducing bortezomib-resistant cell death 
I-S Song et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>

<p>p38MAPK levels were unchanged, even after combined 
treatment, whereas phosphorylation of JNK increased after 
bortezomib plus 2ME treatment. 
To further investigate the mechanism of cell death after 
combination treatment with bortezomib and 2ME, KMS20 
cells were treated with bortezomib plus 2ME at various times. 
Treatment with both bortezomib and 2ME sustained JNK 
activation at later time points, whereas, as expected from 
previous data, neither p38MAPK nor ERK activation was 
detected in KMS20 cells. Moreover, JNK is known to be 
activated by both MKK4 and MKK7. 22 Figure 5b shows a 
sustained phase of MKK4/MKK7 phosphorylation, in accor-
dance with the cleavage of poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase, 
after combination treatment with bortezomib and 2ME. 
Additionally, it is noteworthy that cell death in the Bort/ 
2ME-treated cells was dramatically reduced when a SP600125, 
a JNK inhibitor, was co-treated (Figure 5c). Together, these 
data demonstrate that combination treatment with bortezo-
mib and 2ME prolongs MKK4/7-JNK activation by an over-
production of ROS due to mitochondrial dysfunction and that 
a sustained MKK4/7-JNK activation has a crucial role in cell 
death. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Bortezomib is a dipeptidyl boronic acid derivative that inhibits 
the chymotrypsin-like activity of proteasomes; it has received 
United States Food and Drug Administration approval for the 
treatment of relapsed/refractory MM. However, a majority of 
patients with relapsed or refractory MM do not respond to 
such treatment, and resistance is common. 23,24 Here, we show 
that the treatment of bortezomib-resistant MM cells with 
bortezomib plus 2ME induces cell death via mitochondrial 
dysfunction, which regulates resistance to apoptosis in 
response to bortezomib. Thus, to develop an effective 
therapeutic regimen for bortezomib-resistant MM, we 
evaluated the effects of this combination treatment on 
mitochondria dysfunction so as to increase cell death 
susceptibility in response to bortezomib. We demonstrated 
different susceptibilities of three MM cell lines: KMS20, 
KMS26 and KMS28BM (Figure 1). KMS20 cells were shown 
to be quite resistant to bortezomib treatment. Even the highest 
concentration (100 nM bortezomib) failed to induce more than 
50% apoptosis in KMS20 cells. On the other hand, KMS20 
cells treated with bortezomib plus 2ME displayed abrupt 
apoptosis in a bortezomib dose-dependent manner (Figures </p>

<p>Figure 5 Involvement of c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK) phosphorylation, but not p38 and ERK, in the acceleration of cell death induced 
by bortezomib plus 2-methoxyestradiol (2ME). (a) Cells were treated with bortezomib plus 2ME for 48 h and subjected to western blotting 
analysis with the indicated antibodies. The same membrane was reprobed with antibodies to JNK, p38MAPK or ERK. (b) The effects of 
combination treatment on the sustained activation of JNK in KMS20 cells are shown after exposure to bortezomib plus 2ME for the 
indicated times. The cells were subjected to western blotting analysis with the indicated antibodies. (c) Cells were treated with 
bortezomib and 2ME in the presence or absence of 10 mmol l À1 of SP600125 (JNK-specific inhibitor). Cell death percentage 
representing annexin V( þ )/propidium iodide( þ )-stained cells, which were analyzed by flow cytometry. PARP, poly (ADP-ribose) 
polymerase. </p>

<p>Inducing bortezomib-resistant cell death 
I-S Song et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>

<p>1c and d). Moreover, when bortezomib and 2ME were 
administered in a dose-dependent manner, procaspase-8 was 
cleaved into activated caspase-8 (Figure 2). Cleaved caspases-8 
activate procaspase-3, which induces cells to undergo apopto-
sis. Cytochrome c is also released from mitochondria by 
activated caspase-8. From these data, we believe that the 
combination treatment of bortezomib plus 2ME is a novel, 
promising therapy for bortezomib-resistant MM. 
In a previous report, we showed that changes in mitochon-
drial activity contribute to differential sensitivity or resistance 
of MM cells to bortezomib. 8 Therefore, we examined the 
sensitizing effects of combination treatment on mitochondrial 
function (Figure 3). Mitochondrial ROS levels, after combina-
tion treatment with bortezomib and 2ME, were dramatically 
increased and dependent on bortezomib dose (Figure 3a). 
Mitochondrial Ca 2 þ levels increased regardless of bortezomib 
dose after combination treatment (Figure 3b), whereas DC m 
drastically declined according to bortezomib dose (Figure 3c). 
These data suggest that increased mitochondrial ROS levels </p>

<p>regulate cell death after combination treatment with bortezo-
mib and 2ME. 
To evaluate the role of mitochondrial ROS, KMS20 cells 
were treated with bortezomib plus 2ME in the presence or 
absence of inhibitors for caspase (zVAD-fmk) and ROS (NAc). 
As shown in Figure 4a, mitochondrial ROS levels that were 
increased after combination treatment were attenuated by 
pretreatment with NAc. Cell death induced by combination 
treatment was reduced by pretreatment with zVAD-fmk and 
NAc, suggesting that the effects of combination treatment on 
MM cell death involve coordination among caspases and ROS-
dependent pathways. This interpretation is based on the 
increase in apoptosis seen after 2ME, presumably via a 
mitochondria redox-dependent mechanism. 25 The hypothesis 
that ROS has a critical role in apoptotic signal transduction 
has emerged from several observations. ROS production 
induced by 2ME was previously described in hepatocellular 
carcinoma cells, 15 and treatment of leukemia cells with 2ME 
resulted in apoptosis via the generation of superoxide anion. 13 </p>

<p>Figure 6 Proposed mechanism for the acceleration of cell death induced by bortezomib plus 2-methoxyestradiol (2ME) treatment of 
bortezomib-resistant multiple myeloma (MM) cells. The cytotoxic effect of bortezomib seems to arise partially from inhibition of the anti-
apoptotic transcription factor nuclear factor B. Bortezomib has also effects on MM biology, such as dysregulating Ca 2 þ homeostasis and 
endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress-induced apoptosis (red line). However, single-bortezomib therapy can cause both intrinsic and acquired 
resistance in MM patients. In bortezomib-resistant MM cells, bortezomib alone failed to reach a critical threshold to induce apoptosis 
because of improvements in mitochondrial activities, such as reactive oxygen species (ROS) elimination via increases in antioxidant 
proteins, membrane potential and calcium capacity, resulting in the negative regulation of the mitochondrial-mediated apoptotic cell 
death pathway (red lines). Conversely, when bortezomib plus 2ME treatment is used, overproduction of ROS in mitochondria is induced, 
diffusing ROS outside of mitochondria and blocking both mitogen-activated protein kinase phosphatases and MKK4/7. This causes the 
activation of c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK), via phosphorylation and activation downstream of ASK1, which is activated via ROS, 
eventually leading to the activation of a caspase cascade and cell death (black lines). </p>

<p>Inducing bortezomib-resistant cell death 
I-S Song et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>

<p>Moreover, induction of JNK activation by H 2 O 2 was recently 
demonstrated in several cell lines. 26-28 Generally, activation of 
JNK and p38 MAPK is known to be highly responsible to ROS 
shift, implicating its additional role as a ROS sensor of cells. 
Cell survival and death are tightly correlated with early/ 
transient and late/sustained activation of JNK and p38, 
respectively, under oxidative conditions. 29-31 This implies 
that oxidative cell death is dependent on the extent and/or 
duration of MAPKs activation. 
Our data show that JNK phosphorylation is linked to cell 
death after combination treatment with bortezomib plus 2ME 
(Figure 4b). JNK activation and cell death induction after 
combination treatment were both decreased by pretreatment 
with NAc and zVAD-fmk. In addition, H 2 O 2 has been shown 
to activate all three types of MAPKs in diverse cell types. 16,32-36 
We have confirmed the activation of all three types of MAPKs 
in KMS20 cells after bortezomib and 2ME treatment 
(Figure 5a). JNK activation, but neither p38 nor ERK activa-
tion, was consistently induced after combination treatment. 
These data suggest that cell death after combination treatment 
with bortezomib plus 2ME depends on JNK activation via 
increased ROS levels due to mitochondrial dysfunction. 
However, the JNK activation pathway has both pro-and 
anti-apoptotic properties. 37 In other words, sustained JNK 
activation is predominantly associated with induction of 
apoptosis, whereas transient JNK activation is involved in 
cell survival. 38 As shown in Figure 5b, our results clearly show 
that the sustained activation of JNK, which may be attributable 
to the inactivation of MAPK phosphatases by ROS, 21,39,40 was 
induced by bortezomib plus 2ME treatment in parallel with 
poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase cleavage. In contrast, the 
activation of both p38 and ERK was maintained after 
combination treatment of KMS20 cells. Furthermore, our 
data show a sustained phase of MKK4/7 phosphorylation 
(a known activator of JNK), in accordance with poly (ADP-
ribose) polymerase cleavage, in KMS20 cells treated with 
bortezomib plus 2ME. These results suggest that mito-
chondrial ROS after combination treatment acts to regulate 
only JNK activation in KMS20 cells. Collectively, these findings 
allow us to propose a comprehensive model for the role of 
combination treatment with bortezomib and 2ME in 
bortezomib-resistant MM cells (Figure 6). Among the proteins 
known to be involved in redox signaling, ASK1 is the 
best-characterized ROS target molecule. 41 ASK1 activation, 
induced by ROS, results in the activation of the MKK-JNK 
pathway. 42,43 Moreover, mitochondrial ROS leads to the 
prolonged activation of JNK via the inactivation of MAPK 
phosphatases. 21,39,40 Eventually, prolonged activation of JNK 
leads to the activation of caspases and cell death. 
In summary, this study reports for the first time that 
combination treatment with bortezomib and 2ME is a novel 
therapeutic strategy for bortezomib-resistant MM; combination 
treatment facilitates the leak of ROS due to mitochondrial 
dysfunction, sustains the activation of the JNK/caspase axis and 
induces bortezomib/2ME-mediated cell death in bortezomib-
resistant MM. Given that combination treatment specifically </p>

<p>induces the death of bortezomib-resistant MM cells, the 
combination of bortezomib and 2ME offers excellent trans-
lational potential and promises to be a novel MM therapy. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant from the National R&amp;D Program 
for Cancer Control, Ministry for Health, Welfare and Family affairs, 
Republic of Korea (0920040), a Priority Research Centers Program 
through the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by 
the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology (2010-0020224) 
and a Basic Science Research Program through the National Research 
Foundation of Korea(NRF) funded by the Ministry of Education, 
Science and Technology (2012R1A1A2041700). </p>



<p>Inducing bortezomib-resistant cell death 
I-S Song et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>



<p>Inducing bortezomib-resistant cell death 
I-S Song et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>

</text></tei>