<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3641311" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: We investigated the mRNA levels of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor (PPAR)-α, 
PPAR-γ, adipokines, and cytokines in the lung tissue of lean and obese mice with and without ovalbumin 
(OVA) challenge, and the effect of rosiglitazone, a PPAR-γ agonist. 
Methods: We developed 6 mice models: OVA-challenged lean mice with and without rosiglitazone; 
obese mice with and without rosiglitazone; and OVA-challenged obese mice with and without rosiglita-
zone. We performed real-time polymerase chain reaction for leptin, leptin receptor, adiponectin, 
vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α, transforming growth factor 
(TGF)-β, PPAR-α and PPAR-γ from the lung tissue and determined the cell counts and cytokine levels 
in the bronchoalveolar lavage fluid. 
Results: Mice with OVA challenge showed airway hyperresponsiveness. The lung mRNA levels of 
PPARα and PPAR-γ increased significantly in obese mice with OVA challenge compared to that in other 
types of mice and decreased after rosiglitazone administeration. Leptin and leptin receptor expression 
increased in obese mice with and without OVA challenge and decreased following rosiglitazone treat-
ment. Adiponectin mRNA level increased in lean mice with OVA challenge. Lung VEGF, TNF-α, and 
TGF-β mRNA levels increased in obese mice with and without OVA challenge compared to that in 
the control mice. However, rosiglitazone reduced only TGF-β expression in obese mice, and even 
augmented VEGF expression in all types of mice. Rosiglitazone treatment did not reduce airway res-
ponsiveness, but increased neutrophils and macrophages in the bronchoalveolar lavage fluid. 
Conclusion: PPAR-α and PPAR-γ expressions were upregulated in the lung tissue of OVA-challenged 
obese mice however, rosiglitazone treatment did not downregulate airway inflammation in these mice. </p>

<p>Epidemiological data show an increased incidence of asthma in overweight or obese 
children and adults. The relative risk of incident asthma increases with increasing 
body mass, which has been associated with enhancement of asthma symptoms, airway </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3345/kjp.2013.56.4.151 </p>

<p>SL Ryu, et al. • Effect of obesity on asthma </p>



<p>hyperresponsiveness (AHR) and atopy </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>. Obesity is particularly 
important for severe asthma because more than 75% of asth 
matic individuals visiting the emergency room are obese or 
overweight 
1) . Obesity may be related to the steroidresistant </p>

<p>asthma. 
Consumption of a highfat diet has been shown to lead to lipid 
accumulation and inflammatory signaling in key neuronal subsets 
involved in the regulation of biochemical resistance to insulin, 
leptin, and other regulatory hormones and nutrient signals </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>. 
In order to understand the effect of dietary fat on obesity 
predisposition, we sought to identify molecular metabolic 
regulators that may be lipid sensitive. Peroxisome proliferator 
activated receptor (PPAR) γ is member of the PPAR family of 
nuclear receptors, a class of lipid activated transcription factors 
belonging to the nuclear receptor superfamily </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>. 
Current evidence suggests that obesity related changes in 
the production of adiposederived cytokines, adipokines, may 
modulate asthma. Alterations in the production of the adipo 
kines such asleptin and adiponectin could play a critical role in 
mediating airway inflammation and AHR </p>

<p>3) </p>

<p>. 
PPARs are a family of ligandactivated transcription factors 
belonging to the nuclear hormone receptor family and related 
to retinoid, glucocorticoid, and thyroid hormone receptors </p>

<p>4) </p>

<p>. The 
presence of PPARs has been demonstrated in a variety of cells 
associated with lung inflammation </p>

<p>5) </p>

<p>. The widespread dis tribution 
of PPAR in the airway suggests that they may play important 
roles in both lung health and disease </p>

<p>6) </p>

<p>. 
PPARs can be involved in the inflammatory cascade of asth 
ma, and treatment with PPAR agonists may reduce airway in 
flammation </p>

<p>4) </p>

<p>. The activation of PPAR γ and PPARα is thought 
to downregulate proinflammatory gene expression and inflam 
matory cell functions </p>

<p>4) </p>

<p>. PPAR γ ligands inhibit the release of 
proinflammatory cytokines from activated macroph ages, airway 
epithelial cells, and eosinophils, and decrease AHR, basement 
membrane thickness, collagen deposition, and eosinophilia in 
murine models of asthma </p>

<p>7) </p>

<p>. 
There have been a few studies for the effect of PPAR γ agonist 
on airway inflammation in asthmatics, however there is no data 
on obesity, especially on obese asthma. The presents study aimed 
to compare the mRNA levels of lung PPAR γ and PPARα 
among lean and obese mice with and without ovalbumin (OVA) 
challenge and investigate the effect of rosiglitazone on cytokines 
related to airway inflammation and airway respon siveness. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>We developed a mouse model of chronic asthma with or 
without obesity. Mice were divided into 7 groups: control 
group, lean OVAchallenged groups with (A) and without (B) </p>

<p>rosiglitazone, obese groups with (C) and without (D) rosiglitazone, 
and obese OVAchallenged groups with (E) and without (F) 
rosiglitazone. Each group was comprised of 6 mice. The animal 
experimental protocol was approved by the Animal Subjects 
Committee. </p>

<p>1. Sensitization and antigen challenge protocol </p>

<p>1) Obese model 
Sixweekold female C57BL/6J mice (Central Lab. Animal 
Inc., Seoul, Korea) were fed a highfat diet in which 45% of the 
calories are derived from fat (Feedlab, Guri, Korea) for a period of 16 
weeks. Food intake and body weight were measured every 7 days 
during the study period. Mice were allowed free access to water 
and food and housed 4 per cage in a temperaturecontrolled room 
with a 12:12hour lightdark cycle. Nonobese mice were given a 
standard diet. Rosiglitazone was administered with diet in 0.01% 
concentration. 
2) Chronic asthma model 
Sixweekold female C57BL/6J mice were immunized by 
subcutaneous injection on days 0, 7, 14, and 21 with 25 μg of 
OVA (grade V; SigmaAldrich Co., St. Louis, MO, USA) adsorbed 
to 1 mg of aluminum hydroxide (SigmaAldrich Co.) in 200 μL 
of phosphatebuffered saline (PBS). Intranasal OVA challenges 
(20 μg/50 μL in PBS) were administered on days 27, 29, and 31 
under isoflurane anesthesia. Intranasal OVA challenges were 
repeated twice per week until week 18 of the study period. Age 
and sexmatched control mice were treated the same way with 
PBS but without OVA. Mice were sacrificed 24 hours after the 
final OVA challenge, and bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) and lung 
tissues were obtained. 
3) Measurement of AHR 
AHR was assessed by a singlechamber wholebody plethys 
mograph (Allmedicus, Anyang, Korea). The enhanced pause 
(Penh) was used to monitor airway responsiveness. In the 
plethysmograph, mice were exposed for 3 minutes to nebulized 
PBS to establish baseline Penh values, and were subsequently 
exposed to increasing concentrations of nebulized methacholine 
(3-50 mg/mL; SigmaAldrich Co.) in PBS using an Aerosonic 
ultrasonic nebulizer (DeVilbiss, Somerset, PA, USA). Following 
each nebulization, recordings were taken for 3 minutes. The Penh 
values measured during each 3minute sequence were averaged 
and are expressed for each methacholine concentration. 
4) Analysis of cells in BAL fluid 
Mice were sacrificed after measuring AHR. The trachea was 
exposed and cannulated with silicone tubing attached to a 
23gauge needle on a 1 mL syringe. After the instillation of 1 
mL of sterile PBS into the lung, the BAL fluid was withdrawn. 
The BAL fluid was stained with a hematology analyzer, XE2100 
(Sysmex, Kobe, Japan) after cytospinning (7 minutes at 2,000 
rpm). Total cell count was performed using a hemacyto meter. </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3345/kjp.2013.56.4.151 </p>

<p>Korean J Pediatr 2013;56(4):151-158 </p>

<p>2. Data analysis </p>

<p>Results for each group were compared by analysis of variance, 
followed by Dunn's multiple comparison of means. <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> ver. 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">10.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA) was used for analysis. A P 
value of &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. All results 
are given as mean±standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>1. Effect of high-fat diet on body weight </p>

<p>Obese groups fed 45% highfat diet with and without OVA 
challenge weighed significantly more than other groups fed a 
normal diet. At the end of the study, mice in group C and D reached 
27.8 g and 27.7 g, while control mice weighted 22.5 g, and 23% 
(9.6 g weight gain) and 24% (9.9 g weight gain) more weight 
gain than that of control group (4.5 g weight gain), respectively 
(P&lt;0.05). Groups E and F gained more weight by 16% (8.3 g weight 
gain) and 14% (7.7 g weight gain) compared to control group, 
respectively (P&lt;0.05). Groups A and B mice showedno difference 
in weight (4.5 g and 2.7 g weight gain, re spectively) compared to 
control mice (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>2. Airway inflammation </p>

<p>Total cell numbers and macrophage numbers in BAL fluid 
increased significantly in groups A to F mice compared to the 
control group (P&lt;0.05). Groups A, B, E, and F mice also showed 
a significant increase in total cell and macrophage numbers 
compared to groups C and D mice (P&lt;0.05). Groups A, B, E and </p>

<p>After counting 400 leukocytes on the slide by light microscopy, 
the percentage of eosinophils, neutrophils, lym phocytes, and 
macrophages were calculated. Supernatants were stored at 70℃. 
5) Analysis of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) 
and transforming growth factor (TGF)-β in BAL fluid 
VEGF and TGFβ concentrations were measured using enzyme 
linked immunosorbent assay kit (R&amp;D, Minneapolis, MN, USA) 
in BAL fluid according to the manufacturer's in structions. 
6) RNA isolation and real-time reverse transcription-poly-
merase chain reaction (RT-PCR) 
Lung tissues were analyzed by realtime PCR for leptin, leptin 
receptor, adiponectin, adiponectin receptor (Adipor1 &amp; Adipor2), 
VEGF, TGFβ, and TNFα. Total RNA was isolated from lung 
tissue using Trizol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). Total 
RNA, at a concentration of 2 μg, was reversetranscribed with 
Moloney murine leukemia virus reverse transcriptase (MMLVRT) 
and oligo 
8) 12-18 primer (Invitrogen), to generate cDNA. Briefly, </p>

<p>RNA was denatured for 10 minutes at 72℃, then immediately 
placed on ice for 5 minutes. Denatured RNA was mixed with 
MMLVRT, MMLVRT buffer, and dNTP mixture, and incubated for 
1 hour at 42℃. The reagent was inactivated by heating at 95℃ for 
2 minutes. Synthesized cDNA was am plified by realtime PCR 
(LightCycler 480, Roche, Lewis, UK) using SYBR green (Invi 
trogen) and specific primers (Bioneer Co., Daejon, Korea). The 
following primers were used: leptin, forward: 5'TGGCTTTG 
GTCCTATCTGTC3', re verse: 5' TCCTGGTGACAATGGTCTTG3' 
(GenBank ac ce ssion number: BC125245); leptin receptor, forward: 
5'TGTCTCAGCTACATCTCTGC3', reverse: 5'CTGAACCATCCA 
GTCTCTTG3' (GenBank accession number: BC082551); adiponec 
tin, forward: 5'AGAGAAAGGAGATGCAGGTC3', reverse: 
5'TGAACGCT GAGCGATACACA3' (GenBank accession number: 
NM009605); Adipor1, forward: 5'AGATGGGCTGGTTCTT CCTC 
3', reverse: 5'CAGACAACTCAGACTCTTCC3' (GenBank accession 
num ber: NM1283203); Adipor2, forward: 5'ATGTTTGCCACC 
CCTCAGTA3', reverse: 5'CAGATGTCACATTTGCCAGG3' 
(GenBank accession number: NM197985); VEGF, forward: 5' 
GTGGACATCTTCCAGGAGTA3', reverse: 5'TTCATCGTTACAG 
CAGCCTG3' (GenBank accession number: BC061468); TGF, 
forward: 5'AGTGTGGAGCAACATGTGGA3', reverse: 5'GTAC 
AACTCCAGTGACGTCA3' (GenBank accession number: 
BC013738); TNFα, : 5'CGCTCTTCTGTCTACTGAAC3', reverse: 
5'CTACAGGCTTGTCACTCGAA3' (GenBank accession num ber: 
NM013693). Each cycle consisted of denaturation at 94℃ for 15 
seconds, annealing at 55℃ for 10 seconds, and extension at 72℃ 
for 20 seconds. Quantification was performed using the com 
parative 2(delta delta Ct) method; expression levels for the target 
genes were normalized to the βactin of each sample. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Effect of high-fat diet on body mass. Mice fed a high-fat diet (groups 
C, D, E, and F) weighed significantly more than control mice, whereas mice 
fed a normal diet (groups A and B) showed no difference in weight compared 
to control mice at after 18 weeks of the study period. Group A, lean mice with 
ovalbumin (OVA) challenge; group B, rosiglitazone-treated lean mice with 
OVA challenge; group C, obese mice without OVA challenge; group D, rosigli-
tazone-treated obese mice without OVA challenge; group E, obese mice 
with OVA challenge; and group F, rosiglitazone-treated obese mice with OVA 
challenge. </p>

<p>Weight (g) </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3345/kjp.2013.56.4.151 </p>

<p>SL Ryu, et al. • Effect of obesity on asthma </p>



<p>Leptin and leptin receptor mRNA levels increased in groups 
C and E mice compared to control mice, and rosiglitazone de 
creased leptin and leptin receptor mRNA levels in both mice 
(groups D and F). However, administration of rosiglitazone 
showed increased expression of leptin and leptin receptor mRNA 
levels in group B mice compared to group A mice. 
Adiponectin mRNA levels increased significantly in group 
A mice compared to control mice and showed a tendency of </p>

<p>F mice had significantly increased number of eosinophils in 
the BAL fluid compared to those in the control group (P&lt;0.05), 
whereas groups C and D mice showed no significant increase 
in eosinophils compared to control group. Mice in groups C, D, 
E, and F showed significant increases in neutrophil numbers 
in BAL fluid compared to control mice (P&lt;0.05). Rosiglitazone 
treatment didn't affect cell numbers in BAL fluid compared to 
notreatment in each group (Fig. 2). </p>

<p>3. AHR to methacholine </p>

<p>Increasing doses of methacholine induced an increase in 
airway resistance in all types of mice. The Penh increase was 
higher in groups A, B, E and F mice than in control mice, re 
vealing the induction of AHR in OVAchallenged mice. How ever, 
groups C and D mice didn't show AHR. Rosiglitazone treatment 
did not affect AHR in each type of mice with no ro siglitazone 
treatment (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>4. Expression of PPAR-α, PPAR-γ , leptin, leptin receptor and 
adiponectin mRNA in lung tissue of mice </p>

<p>To assess the effect of obesity on lung inflammation and 
expression of adipokines in mice, we measured mRNA levels of 
PPARα, PPAR γ , leptin, leptin receptor, adiponectin, adipo nectin 
receptor, VEGF, TNFα and TGFβ in lung tissue of mice by real 
time PCR. 
Expression of PPARα and PPAR γ increased significantly in 
group E mice compared to control mice, which decreased signifi 
cantly when rosiglitazone was treated (group F). There were no 
differences in PPARα and PPAR γ expressions in groups A, B, C, 
and D mice compared to control mice (Fig. 4A). </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* * </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Effect of obesity and ovalbumin (OVA) challenge on total and differential cell counts in the broncho-
alveolar lavage (BAL) fluid. The mice in groups A, B, E, and F showed a significant increase in the numbers 
of total cells, eosinophils, and macrophages compared to control mice and mice in groups C and D. 
Com pared to the control group, the mice in groups C and D showed increased numbers in total cell and 
macrophage counts, but not in the number of eosinophils. The number of neutrophils increased signifi-
cantly in the mice in groups C, D, E, and F compared to that in control mice. group A, lean mice with OVA 
challenge; group B, rosiglitazone-treated lean mice with OVA challenge; group C, obese mice without 
OVA challenge; group D, rosiglitazone-treated obese mice without OVA challenge; group E, obese mice 
with OVA challenge; and group F, rosiglitazone-treated obese mice with OVA challenge. *P&lt;0.05 vs. 
control, groups C, and D mice. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. control mice. </p>

<p>Cells in BAL fluid (10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>/uL) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Airway reactivity towards increasing concentrations of methacholine. 
Mice in groups A and B showed airway reactivity at methacholine dose of 
12.5 mg/mL, group E mice at 25 mg/mL, and group F mice at 50 mg/mL 
compared to control mice. However, mice in groups C and D did not show 
airway hyperresponsiveness compared to control mice. group A, lean mice 
with ovalbumin (OVA) challenge; group B, rosiglitazone-treated lean mice 
with OVA challenge; group C, obese mice without OVA challenge; group D, 
rosiglitazone-treated obese mice without OVA challenge; group E, obese 
mice with OVA challenge; and group F, rosiglitazone-treated obese mice with 
OVA challenge. *P&lt;0.05 vs. control. </p>

<p>Penh </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3345/kjp.2013.56.4.151 </p>

<p>Korean J Pediatr 2013;56(4):151-158 </p>

<p>decrease in group C mice. Administration of rosiglitazone in 
creased adiponectin mRNA levels in group D mice compared to 
group C mice, while it showed decreased tendency in group B 
mice compared to group A mice (Fig. 4B). </p>

<p>5. VEGF, TNF-α, and TGF-β levels in BAL fluid and mRNA ex-
pression in lung tissue of mice </p>

<p>VEGF mRNA levels increased significantly in groups A, C, and 
E mice compared to control mice, which augmented more when 
rosiglitazone was administered (groups B, D, and F, respectively) 
compared to no rosiglitazone treatment. Lung mRNA levels 
of TNFα and TGFβ increased significantly in groups C and E 
mice compared to control mice. Rosiglitazone also increased 
TNFα mRNA levels in group F mice compared to group E 
mice, however decreased TGFβ mRNA levels in group D mice 
compared to group C mice (P&lt;0.05) (Fig. 5A). 
VEGF levels in BAL fluid were also higher in groups A, C, </p>

<p>and E mice than in control mice, which increased significantly 
in rosiglitazonetreated mice (groups B, D, and F, respectively). 
Concentration of TGFβ in BAL fluid augmented in groups C and 
E mice compared to control mice, which decreased signifi cantly 
in group D mice compared to group C mice (Fig. 5B, C). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We compared PPAR γ and PPARα mRNA levels in lung tissue 
of mice with OVA challenge and/or obesity, and also investigated 
the effect of rosiglitazone on lung expressions of PPAR γ 
and PPARα. PPAR γ and PPARα mRNA levels increased 
significantly in obese mice with OVA challenge compared to lean 
mice with OVA challenge and obese mice as well as control mice, 
and decreased significantly when rosigli tazone was treated. 
PPAR γ has been suggested as an indicator of airway inflam 
mation and remodeling in asthma </p>

<p>9) </p>

<p>. A study indicated a positive 
correlation between PPAR γ expression and airway remodeling 
in asthma such as subbasement membrane thickening, collagen 
deposition, and increase of proliferating cells in the epithelium 
and submucosa area </p>

<p>10) </p>

<p>. Intensity of PPAR γ expression in the 
bronchial submucosa, the airway epithelium and the smooth 
muscle also showed negative correlation with the forced expir 
atory volume values. Furthermore, steroids restrained PPAR γ 
expression in lung tissue </p>

<p>10) </p>

<p>. Expression of PPAR γ is also related to 
obesity. In our previous study, PPAR γ expression also increased in 
obese rat </p>

<p>11) </p>

<p>. We found PPAR γ mRNA level was higher in obese 
mice with OVA challenge than obese mice or lean mice with 
OVA challenge, which suggests synergistic effect of obesity and 
asthma on PPAR γ expression. To our knowledge, there has been 
no report that investigated PPAR γ and PPARα expressions in 
obese mice with OVA challenge. 
Asthma is a chronic inflammatory airway disease, and obe 
sity also represents a lowgrade chronic inflammatory state. 
Considering obese patients have more difficulties in controlling 
asthma and decreased responsiveness to inhaled corticosteroid </p>

<p>12) </p>

<p>, 
PPAR γ or PPARα agonist can be a good can didate for controll 
ing difficult asthma in obese asthmatics. 
There are a few clinical studies for the therapeutic effect of 
PPAR γ ligands in asthma. Pioglitazone improved wheezing 
and coughing in patients with asthma, and asthma symptoms 
restarted when the pioglitazone treatment was discontinued </p>

<p>13) </p>

<p>. 
Another study shows that rosiglitazone improved lung function, 
compared with inhaled corticosteroid in steroidresistant 
smoker with asthma </p>

<p>14) </p>

<p>, and PPAR γ agonists reduced the asthma 
symp toms and levels of Th2 cytokines, adhesion molecules, 
chemokines, and TGFβ1 in toluene diisocyanateinduced 
asthma </p>

<p>15) </p>

<p>. On the contrary, PPAR γ genetic expression has been 
shown to be reduced in asthmatic patients after an allergen </p>

<p>Fig. 4. ThemRNA levels of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor (PPAR)-
γ , PPAR-α, leptin, leptin receptor, and adiponectinin the lung tissue of mice 
and the effect of rosiglitazone treatment. Expression of PPAR-α and PPAR-γ 
increased significantly in group E mice compared to that in control mice, and 
it decreased significantly with rosiglitazone treatment in group F mice (A). 
Leptin and leptin receptor increased significantly in the mice in groups C and 
E compared to that in control mice, and these decreased significantly with 
rosiglitazone treatment. Adiponectin increased significantly in group A mice 
compared to that in control mice, and rosiglitazone augmented adiponectin 
mRNA level in group D mice compared to that in group C mice (B). Group A, 
lean mice with ovalbumin (OVA) challenge; Group B, rosiglitazone-treated 
lean mice with OVA challenge; Group C, obese mice without OVA challenge; 
Group D, rosiglitazone-treated obese mice without OVA challenge; Group E, 
obese mice with OVA challenge; and Group F, rosiglitazone-treated obese 
mice with OVA challenge. *P&lt;0.05 vs. control. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. each group of 
mice without rosiglitazone treatment. </p>

<p>α 
γ </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p>Fold change in mRNA expression </p>

<p>Fold change in mRNA expression </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3345/kjp.2013.56.4.151 </p>

<p>SL Ryu, et al. • Effect of obesity on asthma </p>



<p>challenge, and inversely related to airway inflammation </p>

<p>16) </p>

<p>. In 
mature adipocytes, PPAR γ interacts with several coactivators 
with chromatin modifying activities, repress and enhance its 
transcriptional activity </p>

<p>17) </p>

<p>. Although PPAR γ and PPARα lung 
expressions didn't increase significantly in mice with OVA 
challenge and with obesity, we found a tendency of in crease. As 
a result, rosiglitazone administration decreased the lung PPAR γ 
and PPARα mRNA levels in mice with OVA challenge. We can 
figure out the possibility of significance with the increase of study 
subjects in the future study. 
The direct mechanism for the relationship between obesity 
and asthma has not been established yet. Leptin is a hormone 
secreted preferentially by adipose tissue, exerting pleiotropic 
effects such as body weight homeostasis, reproduction and 
hematopoiesis </p>

<p>18) </p>

<p>. Leptin acts as a proinflammatory cytokine, 
and its blood level is elevated in obese people. Leptin receptor is 
expressed in airway smooth muscle </p>

<p>19) </p>

<p>, and leptin promoted VEGF 
release by human airway smooth muscle cells </p>

<p>20) </p>

<p>. In this study, leptin </p>

<p>as well as leptin receptor demonstrated increased mRNA levels 
in obese mice with and without OVA challenge, which decreased 
with rosiglitazone. However, they didn't show significant 
increase in mice with OVA challenge compared to control mice, 
and there was no difference in the expression of leptin and leptin 
receptor between obese mice with and without OVA challenge. 
Rosiglitazone administration to the preadipocytes isolated from 
obese mice, resulted in the diffe rentiation into mature adipo 
cytes. The inhibitory effect of leptin on rosiglitazone induced 
adipocyte differentiation was also accompanied by the decreased 
expression of adipogenic transcription factors. Rosiglitazone was 
decreased in the presence of leptin </p>

<p>18) </p>

<p>. Leptin may be related to 
obesity itself, not asthma, and may not be a contributing factor 
for poorly controlled asthma in obese asthmatics. There has 
been no data onthe effect of rosiglitazone on leptin regulation 
in asthma. Contrary to our study, another study demonstrated 
rosiglitazone increased leptin levels in obese mice, while 
decreased leptin levels in lean mice </p>

<p>3) </p>

<p>. However, they tried short </p>

<p>Fig. 5. The mRNA levels of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), transforming growth factor (TGF)-β, and 
tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α in the lung tissue of mice and the effect of rosiglitazone in the bronchoalveolar 
lavage (BAL) fluid. VEGF expression in the lung increased significantly in the mice in groups A, C, and E and was 
augmented significantly after rosiglitazone treatment. TNF-α and TGF-β expression in the mice in groups C and 
E increased significantly compared to that in control mice. TNF-α expression was augmented with rosiglitazone 
treatment in group F mice compared to that in group E mice, while TGF-β expression decreased significantly in 
group D mice compared to that in group C mice (A). VEGF concentration in the BAL fluid was higher in the mice 
in groups A, C, and E than in control mice and increased significantly in each group of mice with rosiglitazone 
treatment (groups B, D, and F). TGF-β level in the BAL fluid was higher in the mice groups C and E than in control 
mice and decreased signifi cantly in group D mice with rosiglitazone treatment (B and C). Group A, lean mice with 
ovalbumin (OVA) challenge; group B, rosiglitazone-treated lean mice with OVA challenge; group C, obese mice 
without OVA challenge; group D, rosiglitazone-treated obese mice without OVA challenge; group E, obese mice 
with OVA challenge; and group F, rosiglitazone-treated obese mice with OVA challenge. *P&lt;0.05 vs. control. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. each group of mice without rosiglitazone treatment. </p>

<p>α 
β </p>

<p>β </p>

<p>TGF- 
TNF- </p>

<p>TGF- </p>

<p>Fold change in mRNA expression </p>

<p>VEGF (pg/mL) 
TGF-β </p>

<p>(pg/mL) </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3345/kjp.2013.56.4.151 </p>

<p>Korean J Pediatr 2013;56(4):151-158 </p>

<p>course 1 week treatment of rosiglitazone on airway as opposed 
to 18 weeks administration in this study. 
Adiponectin may play an antiinflammatory role in obesity 
related diseases </p>

<p>21) </p>

<p>. Adiponectin receptors are expressed in airway 
smooth muscle </p>

<p>20) </p>

<p>. In this study, lung expression of adiponectin 
increased significantly in mice with OVA challenge, and decreased 
in obese mice. However, there was no significant difference 
in obese mice with OVA challenge compared to control mice. 
Until now, there has been no data which investi gated the lung 
expression of adiponectin in obese mice with OVA challenge. 
Lung adiponectin may not be a major factor to regulate the 
airway inflammation in obese asthmatics. 
Proinflammatory cytokines such as TNF, TGF, and VEGF 
are increased in obesity. They are also an important cytokines 
in regulating airway inflammation in asthma </p>

<p>20,22,23) </p>

<p>. We found 
augmented lung expression of VEGF, TNFα, and TGFβ in both 
obese mice with and without OVA challenge, and VEGF mRNA 
level also increased in lean mice with OVA challenge. However, 
there was no synergistic increase of cytokine expressions in 
obese mice with OVA challenge compared to lean mice with OVA 
challenge or obese mice. In this study, rosiglitazone enhanced 
lung VEGF mRNA level in all types of mice, and TNFα mRNA 
level in obese mice with OVA chal lenge. This is supported 
by another study with murine model with chronic asthma, 
which shows increased VEGF and TGFβ levels in BAL fluid 
of ciglitazonetreated asthma mice </p>

<p>24) </p>

<p>. However, other studies 
showed PPAR agonists decreased serum VEGF levels and lung 
expression of TGFβ 
7,25) , and reduced expression of TNFα </p>

<p>in adipocytes ofobese mice treated with the PPAR γ agonist 
troglitazone </p>

<p>26) </p>

<p>. We can assume VEGF, TNFα, and TGFβ are not 
major contributing cytokines regulated by rosiglitazone in obese 
asthmatics. There has been no data on the effect of rosiglitazone 
on cytokine expressions in obese asthmatics. 
This study was limited by relatively small number of subjects 
and no measurement of AHR and airway inflammation. How 
ever, this is the same method to develop chronic asthma model 
in mice 
24) . And we administered rosiglitazone into the diet, </p>

<p>not into the airway. The method and type of PPAR γ agonist 
as well as the duration of administration can make difference. 
However, there has been only a few studies using murine model of 
obese asthmatics, and to our knowledge, this is the first study 
comparing lung expression of PPAR, adipokines, and cytokines 
according to obesity and OVA challenge. 
Taken together, this study suggests that PPARα and PPAR γ lung 
expression is augmented in obese mice with OVA challenge, and 
PPAR γ agonist dose not downregulate VEGF, TNFα, and TGFβ 
expressions in lung tissue of obese asthma. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was 
reported. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This study was supported by Kangbuk Samsung Hospital 
Medical Research Fund. </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3345/kjp.2013.56.4.151 </p>

<p>SL Ryu, et al. • Effect of obesity on asthma </p>





</text></tei>