<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3773590" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: We have performed both open partial nephrectomy (OPN) and laparoscopic 
radiofrequency ablation (RFA) on selected patients since January 2007 and have been 
following these patients through serial laboratory assessments and computed tomog-
raphy (CT). The purpose of the present study was to evaluate long-term oncologic out-
comes and renal function status for laparoscopic RFA versus OPN at a minimum fol-
low-up of 3 years. 
Materials and Methods: A total of 55 patients with exophytic, single small renal masses 
were treated with either OPN (n=14) or laparoscopic RFA (n=41) by a single surgeon. 
The indications for laparoscopic RFA were as follows: 1) cases with the greatest di-
mension of the renal mass ＜3 cm, and 2) cases in which the collecting system, renal 
calyx, and great vessels were free from the tumor margins by 1 cm. 
Results: The estimated blood loss (EBL), the operation time, and the mean number of 
hospital days was significantly lower in the laparoscopic RFA group than in the OPN 
group. Oncologic data did not differ significantly between the two groups. Creatine 
clearance levels did not differ significantly compared with those before the operation 
in either group. 
Conclusions: Our data suggest excellent therapeutic outcomes with laparoscopic RFA 
with achievement of effective operative times, hospital stays, and EBL compared with 
OPN. According to our indications for laparoscopic RFA, laparoscopic RFA is an effec-
tive minimally invasive therapy for the treatment of small renal masses, yielding onco-
logic outcomes and renal function equivalent to those of OPN. </p>

<p>The recent widespread use of contrast-enhanced computed 
tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging has con-
tributed to increasing the detection of small renal masses 
(SRMs) [1-3]. Incidentally discovered SRMs are typically 
low-stage, slow-growing masses with low malignancy po-
tential [4]. Thus, the standard treatment for a SRM has 
shifted from radical nephrectomy to partial nephrectomy 
(PN), which has been shown to confer equivalent oncologic 
and functional outcomes to those of radical nephrectomy for 
patients with renal tumors smaller than 4 cm [5,6]. Lucas </p>

<p>et al. [7] reported that radical nephrectomy carries seven 
times the risk of developing stage 3 chronic kidney disease 
as that in similar patients undergoing PN or radiofrequency 
ablation (RFA). Along with the developments of minimally 
invasive approaches, laparoscopic PN has been reported to 
have oncological efficacy comparable to that of open PN 
(OPN). Laparoscopic PN requires high laparoscopic dexter-
ity, however, and even for those with experience requires a 
longer ischemic time and is associated with more complica-
tions than OPN [8,9]. Thus, current treatment guidelines 
recommend the use of thermal ablative therapies for the pri-
mary treatment of SRMs for older patients, those with sig-</p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2013;54:603-608 </p>



<p>Youn et al </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Patient demographics and tumor characteristics of 55 patients </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Open partial nephrectomy (n=14) 
Laparoscopic RFA (n=41) 
p-value </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Age (y) 
Follow-up (mo) 
Maximum tumor diameter (cm) 
Body mass index (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
Baseline serum creatinine (mg/dL) 
Baseline hemoglobin (g/dL) 
Male/female 
Right/left 
ASA score 
1 
2 
Tumor location 
Upper 
Middle 
Lower </p>

<p>53.92±16.14 
50.0±16.9 
2.4±0.79 
25±4.73 
0.82±0.17 
13.60±1.95 
8/6 
10/4 </p>

<p>4 
10 </p>

<p>2 
10 
2 </p>

<p>59.15±12.26 
51.0±15.8 
2.3±1.27 
25±5.24 
0.83±0.22 
13.69±1.93 
22/19 
27/14 </p>

<p>13 
28 </p>

<p>4 
26 
11 </p>

<p>0.21 
0.57 
0.07 
0.42 
0.59 
0.86 
0.77 
0.71 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.71 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.45 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±standard deviation or number. 
RFA, radiofrequency ablation; ASA, American Society of Anesthesiologists. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>:Mann-Whitney U test. p-values ＜0.05 were considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>:Pearson chi-square test between the two groups 
was used for analysis of the characteristics of each group. </p>

<p>nificant medical comorbidities who are poor surgical candi-
dates, those with genetic predispositions to recurrent tumor 
formation, and those with imperative indications for PN pro-
cedures [10,11]. The basis for these recommendations is the 
lack of long-term oncologic efficacy data, the unreliability of 
measures of treatment efficacy, and the higher rates of local 
recurrence compared with surgery in the setting of re-
currence [10]. The potential benefits of ablative techniques 
are reduced perioperative morbidity, shorter hospital stay, 
faster recovery, and preservation of renal function [12]. 
Surgical margins are not considered as a treatment end-
point, which further underscores how the principles defin-
ing successful ablation differ from those for surgical ex-
tirpation [13]. Since then, many reports have been published 
on RFA for SRMs, which have shown favorable outcomes in 
terms of local tumor control [14-17]. 
In laparoscopic RFA, the kidney surrounding the tumor 
is exposed and the perirenal fat covering the tumor is re-
moved and sent for pathology. A steerable laparoscopic ul-
trasound probe is introduced to visualize the tumor size 
and location. The electrode probe is placed in the deepest 
part of the renal tumor under real-time laparoscopic ultra-
sound guidance [13]. 
We have been performing both OPN and laparoscopic 
RFA on selected patients since January 2007 and have 
been researching these patients with serial laboratory as-
sessments and imaging tools such as CT. This study was 
performed with long-term oncologic data for the purpose 
of evaluating oncologic outcomes and renal function status 
at a minimum follow-up of 3 years. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Since January 2007, 55 patients with exophytic solitary </p>

<p>SRMs were treated with either OPN or laparoscopic RFA 
by a single surgeon. Patient demographics and tumor char-
acteristics are shown in Table 1. Laparoscopic RFA was 
performed in a transperitoneal or retroperitoneal ap-
proach according to tumor location, whereas PN was per-
formed in a retroperitoneal approach. All cases of laparo-
scopic RFA had undergone preablative biopsy. However, 
we did not perform frozen biopsy. The indication for treat-
ment was a solid enhancing renal mass shown on CT. The 
choice of approach was based on tumor location, clinical 
judgment, or patient preference; RFA was primarily in-
dicated as a treatment for an exophytic renal mass of less 
than 4 cm in the greatest dimension. The use of RFA was 
primarily considered in contraindicated patients who had 
an endophytic tumor, because injury to the collecting sys-
tem could result. Ureteral protection should be considered 
when laparoscopic RFA is to be performed in cases of an en-
dophytic tumor near the pelvis and ureter [18]. Thus, the 
indications for operative laparoscopic RFA were as follows: 
1) cases in which the greatest dimension of the renal mass 
was ＜3 cm, 2) cases in which the collecting system and re-
nal calyx were free from the tumor margins by 1 cm, and 
3) cases in which the great vessels were free from the tumor 
margins by 1 cm. We conducted OPN for patients with exo-
phytic solitary SRMs. RFA was performed with a 200 W 
generator (Radionics, Burlington, MA, USA) and a single 
(with one 3.0-cm tip) internally cooled electrode (Radio-
nics, Burlington, MA, USA) with an impedance-controlled 
pulsed current. The tip size was selected according to tumor 
size and location. The ablation time was a maximum of 12 
min for one cycle, and the ablation cycle was repeated if the 
target temperature achieved was suboptimal. On the basis 
of the size and location of the tumor, overlapping ablations 
were performed in some patients by repositioning the elec-</p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2013;54:603-608 </p>

<p>Small Renal Mass Treatment Effect </p>



<p>TABLE 2. Perioperative and postoperative characteristics </p>

<p>Variable 
Open partial nephrectomy (n=14) 
Laparoscopic RFA (n=41) 
p-value </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Operation time (min) 
Mean hospital stay (d) 
Radiofrequency ablation (mL) 
Postoperative serum Cr (mg/dL) 
Pathologic results 
Renal cell carcinoma 
Angiomyolipoma 
Failure 
Complications (major) 
Recurrence of tumor 
Metastasis </p>

<p>148.64±40.86 
12.28±3.29 
64.8±45 
0.89±0.32 </p>

<p>12 (85.71) 
2 (14.29) 
0 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>103.27±28.36 
8.33±3.23 
40.5±20 
0.88±0.29 </p>

<p>31 (75.61) 
10 (24.39) 
1 
1 
0 
0 </p>

<p>0.04 
0.00 
0.03 
0.87 </p>

<p>0.42 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.56 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.56 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±standard deviation or number (%). 
RFA, radiofrequency ablation; Cr, creatinine; RCC, renal cell carcinoma. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>:Mann-Whitney U test. p-values ＜0.05 were considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>:Pearson chi-square test between the two groups 
was used for analysis of the characteristics of each group. </p>

<p>trode to completely ablate the entire tumor. OPN was per-
formed in a retroperitoneal approach. 
The follow-up for each patient included chest radiog-
raphy, laboratory tests, and CT. For evaluation of ther-
apeutic efficacy, the absence of enhancement inside the tu-
mor was taken to indicate technical success. A follow-up CT 
was conducted at intervals of 1, 3, and 6 months and then 
every 6 months over the years. One-month follow-up CT 
was performed to determine whether there was any rem-
nant or residual enhancement of the ablated lesion. 
Complete treatment resulted when nonenhancement was 
achieved. The technical success rate was defined as com-
plete ablation of the tumor following the initial procedure 
or additional sessions with a 1-month follow-up. Recu-
rrence was defined as growth of the tumor or any new en-
hancing portions at 3 months after confirmed nonenhance-
ment of the initial RFA lesion. Mann-Whitney U test, 
Pearson's chi-square test, and repeated-measures analy-
sis of variance between the two groups were used for analy-
sis of the characteristics of each group. A p-value ＜0.05 was 
considered statistically significant. Statistical analyses 
were performed by using IBM <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">18.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Co.</rs>., 
Armonk, NY, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>A total of 14 patients underwent OPN and 41 patients un-
derwent laparoscopic RFA. Table 1 summarizes the pa-
tients' characteristics. The patients' mean age, the mean 
follow-up time, body mass index, baseline serum crea-
tinine, and baseline serum hemoglobin did not differ sig-
nificantly between the two groups. Also, tumor location 
and sex were similar in the two groups. All patients had an 
American Society of Anesthesiologists score of 1 to 2. The 
maximum tumor diameter (2.3±1.27 cm) in the laparo-
scopic RFA group was similar to that in the OPN group 
(2.4±0.79 cm, p=0.07). Table 2 summarizes the perioper-</p>

<p>ative and postoperative characteristics. The estimated 
blood loss (EBL) in the laparoscopic RFA group (40.5±20 
mL) was significantly lower than in the OPN group 
(64.8±45 mL, p=0.03). The operation time (103.27±28.36 
minutes) in the laparoscopic RFA group was significantly 
shorter than in the OPN group (148.64±40.86 minutes, 
p=0.04).The mean hospital stay (8.33±3.23 days) in the lap-
aroscopic RFA group was significantly shorter than in the 
OPN group (12.28±3.29 days, p=0.00). The OPN group had 
a cold ischemic time of 20 (15.5±24.5 minutes). The laparo-
scopic RFA group had no cold ischemic time. Pathologic re-
sults with renal cell carcinoma were slightly lower in the 
laparoscopic RFA group (31/41, 75.61%) than in the OPN 
group (12/14, 85.71%; p=0.42). No recurrence or metastasis 
was seen in either group. During the mean follow-up period 
of 50 months, radiologic evidence of incomplete ablation 
was found in 1 case (1/41, 2.44%) in the RFA group. One 
month after the initial laparoscopic RFA, an 86-year-old 
patient had an enhanced remaining tumor by CT. The pa-
tient underwent repeat laparoscopic RFA. The patient had 
no findings of recurrence on radiological follow-up after 12 
months. The OPN group had no radiologic evidence of tu-
mor failure or recurrence. 
There was one postoperative major complication. The 
case was in the laparoscopic RFA group (1/41, 2.44%). In 
March 2007, after 1 month, the patient had an upper ure-
teral stricture. At the 3-month follow-up CT, the patient 
had renal shrinkage. We conducted nephrectomy after 4 
months. This case was our center's third laparoscopic RFA 
case. No patients in either group had minor complications 
such as transfusion, atelectasis, or wound infection. 
The postoperative serum creatinine (0.88±0.29) in the 
laparoscopic RFA group was similar to that in the OPN 
group (0.89±0.32, p=0.87). Concerning the effect of both 
groups on preserving renal function, creatinine clearance 
according to Cockcroft and Gault equation levels in the lap-
aroscopic RFA group was not significantly different from </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2013;54:603-608 </p>



<p>Youn et al </p>

<p>TABLE 3. Renal function of preoperative and postoperative CCr between the two groups </p>

<p>Preoperative value 
Postoperative 1-year value 
p-value </p>

<p>Laparoscopic RFA CCr (mL/min) 
Open partial nephrectomy CCr (mL/min) </p>

<p>73.75±2.75 
72.91±2.13 </p>

<p>70.23±2.91 
68.62±2.34 
0.31 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±standard deviation. p=comparison by repeated measures analysis of variance test between the two 
groups. 
CCr, creatine clearance=[(140-age)×IBW/Scr×72]×(0.85 for females); RFA, radiofrequency ablation; IBW, ideal body weight; Scr, serum 
creatine. </p>

<p>that in the OPN group (p=0.31), as shown in Table 3. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>OPN has replaced radical nephrectomy as the treatment 
of choice of SRMs [10]. One of the major reasons for this 
guideline recommendation by the American Urological 
Association and the European Association of Urology is the 
lack of long-term oncologic efficacy data for RFA compared 
with OPN. RFA was initially introduced to treat selected 
patients who had high surgical or anesthetic risk with a 
solitary tumor or multifocal renal tumors. Various reports 
on local tumor control have so far been promising [14-17]. 
The outcomes of RFA are affected by the following fac-
tors: tumor size and location, tissue impedance, ablation 
time, amount of energy delivered, and surface area of the 
electrodes. Mylona et al. [19] reported a complete response 
of 85.7% for tumors less than 3 cm after the initial RFA but 
reported a noticeably smaller response rate with tumors 
greater than 5 cm in size. Also, Lucas et al. [7] reported that 
RFA is superior to PN in terms of preserving renal function 
in patients with SRMs. 
The criteria of therapeutic response were based on the 
report by Goldberg et al. [20]. Complete response is defined 
as the absence of any enhancement within the tumor as ob-
served in the preoperative contrast-enhanced CT image. A 
benign periablation enhancement, which can measure up 
to 12 mm, typically suggests a transient benign physiologic 
response to a thermal injury and may persist for up to 3 
months after the ablation. On the other hand, irregular pe-
ripheral enhancement represents a residual tumor that 
may exist at the ablative margin. The local recurrence rate 
varies from 0% to 11.1% in cases in which technical success 
is achieved during the initial RFA [21]. 
RFA is known to cause coagulation necrosis within the 
tumor by the following mechanism. When electrical cur-
rent from the uninsulated RF electrode is delivered to the 
tumor, ionic agitation occurs in the tissue, resulting in heat 
energy [22]. The location of the tumor may also influence 
the ablative outcome. It is reported that the ablative effect 
on a centrally located tumor is lower because of the heat 
sink effect of central blood vessels near the renal hilum, in 
which regional vascular flow reduces the extent of the ther-
mally induced coagulation. By contrast, the ablative effect 
on exophytic tumors is higher because these tumors are </p>

<p>easy to target with the RFA probe and because the insulat-
ing effect of the surrounding perirenal fat allows the ach-
ievement of higher temperatures during RFA [14,23]. 
Ureteral protection should be considered when laparo-
scopic RFA is to be performed in a tumor near the renal pel-
vis and ureter [18]. Thus, cases in which the tumors are lo-
cated within 2 cm of the collecting system and great vessels 
were not offered laparoscopic RFA. In this study, one pa-
tient had incomplete ablation among 41 patients (2.44%). 
With a mean follow-up of 51 months, no distant metastasis 
has been observed. The overall survival rate was 100%. The 
results of this study demonstrate that patients with SRMs 
matched for location and size had less EBL, shorter oper-
ation time, and shorter hospital stay after laparoscopic 
RFA than after OPN. However, the two groups showed no 
significant differences in renal function. Pettus et al. [24] 
reported that a single RFA session for a solitary renal mass 
did not affect the glomerular filtration rate . Nevertheless, 
this study also concluded that RFA is superior to OPN in 
terms of the patient's general condition. Furthermore, 
shifts in renal function were not found to be related to tumor 
size or location but rather to creatinine clearance. Recen-
tly, another report concluded that RFA achieves moderate 
local control (5-year disease-free survival, 74%) and may 
be especially appropriate in elderly patients with a short 
life expectancy who prefer local treatment [25]. 
The reported complications include perinephric hema-
toma, gross hematuria, pyonephrosis, ureteral stricture, 
damages to adjacent organs, pain, and paresthesias 
[26,27]. In addition, RFA of a central tumor can cause other 
complications including AV fistula, segmental infarction, 
and urinary obstruction [28-30]. Although one patient had 
an upper ureteral stricture and renal shrinkage after RFA 
(1/41, 2.44%) and needed to undergo nephrectomy, the case 
was an early case of our center and did not strictly meet our 
inclusion criteria for laparoscopic RFA. 
Our study had several limitations that warrant discu-
ssion. First, the data were retrospective, introducing the 
potential for selection bias and additional confounders. 
Second, given factors such as referral patterns to our in-
stitution and the wide variability in RFA devices among 
other institutions, our outcomes may not by generalizable 
to other centers. Third, our inclusion criteria may be 
unusual. Many other centers perform percutaneous RFA 
according to our inclusion criteria for laparoscopic RFA. </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2013;54:603-608 </p>

<p>Small Renal Mass Treatment Effect </p>



<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>Our data suggest excellent therapeutic outcomes with lap-
aroscopic RFA with achievement of effective operative 
times, hospital stays, and EBL compared with OPN. There 
were no significant differences in the complication rates or 
failure between the two procedures. Also, preservation of 
renal function did not differ significantly between the 
procedures. According to our operative indication of an exo-
phytic single SRM, the indications for laparoscopic RFA 
were an SRM (size ＜3 cm) for which the collecting system, 
renal calyx, and great vessel were free from the tumor mar-
gins by 1 cm. Laparoscopic RFA is an effective minimally 
invasive therapy for the treatment of SRMs, yielding 
long-term oncologic outcomes equivalent to those of OPN. 
Prospective randomized studies in diverse patient pop-
ulations will help to further define the role of laparoscopic 
RFA as an acceptable treatment alternative to surgery for 
the definitive management of SRMs. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST 
The authors have nothing to disclose. </p>



<p>Korean J Urol 2013;54:603-608 </p>





</text></tei>