<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3563119" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:37+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives: To evaluate whether four types of low-</p>

<p>cost interventions in the working environment can 
promote the small everyday lifestyle adaptations that 
can halt the epidemics of obesity and hypertension 
when maintained long term. </p>

<p>Design: A single-blind uninterrupted time-series </p>

<p>intervention study consisting of four study periods: 
run-in (2 weeks), baseline (2 weeks), intervention 
(2 weeks), and after intervention 2 weeks). </p>

<p>Setting: University Medical Centre with over 11 000 </p>

<p>employees, over 1000 hospital beds and over 2000 
customers visiting the hospital restaurant each day. </p>

<p>Participants: Hospital staff and visitors. 
Interventions: (1) Point-of-decision prompts on </p>

<p>hospital elevator doors promoting stair use. (2) Point-
of-purchase prompts in the hospital restaurant 
promoting reduced-salt soup. (3) Point-of-purchase 
prompts in the hospital restaurant promoting lean 
croissants. (4) Reversal of the accessibility and 
availability of diet margarine and butter in the hospital 
restaurant. </p>

<p>Main outcome measures: (1) Number of passages </p>

<p>through 15 different parts of the hospital staircases. 
(2) Number and ratio of normal-salt and reduced-salt 
soup purchased. (3) Number and ratio of butter 
croissants and lean croissants purchased. (4) Number 
and ratio of diet margarine and butter purchased. </p>

<p>Results: Elevator signs increased the mean 24-h </p>

<p>number of stair passages per measurement site 
(baseline: 992 ± </p>

<p>À 479 on week days and 208 ± 
À 116 on </p>

<p>weekend days) by 11.2% (95% CI 8.7% to 13.7%). This 
effect was maintained at least 2 weeks after the point-of-
decision prompts were removed. Point-of-purchase 
prompts promoting low-salt soup and lean croissants 
did not result in altered purchase behaviour. The ratio 
between the purchase of margarine and butter was 
changed sevenfold ( p&lt;0.01) by reversing the positions 
of these products in the hospital restaurant. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Healthy lifestyle adaptations in the </p>

<p>working environment can be effectively promoted by 
making healthy choices easier than unhealthy ones. 
Educational prompts at points-of-decision moderately 
increase stair climbing, but do not affect healthy food 
choices. </p>

<p>Protocol registration: Clinicaltrials.gov identifier </p>

<p>number: NCT01574040. </p>

<p>INTRODUCTION 
In modern sedentary society, middle-aged 
men and women on average gain approxi-
mately one pound weight each year. </p>

<p>1 2 </p>

<p>Resultantly, up to 28% of European men and 
up to 37% of European women are classified 
as obese (body mass index &gt;30 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). 
3 The 
cumulative gap between energy intake and 
expenditure causing this yearly 1 pound 
weight gain, however, is approximately 
3500 kcal or less depending on a person's 
initial body weight. 
4 This means that the 
obesity epidemic on average is caused by a </p>

<p>ARTICLE SUMMARY </p>

<p>Article focus </p>

<p>▪ To evaluate whether four types of low-cost inter-
ventions in the working environment can promote 
the small everyday lifestyle adaptations that can 
halt the epidemics of obesity and hypertension 
when maintained long term. </p>

<p>Key messages </p>

<p>▪ Because adults spend much of the day working, 
small lifestyle adaptations in the work environ-
ment can potentially halt the epidemics of obesity 
and hypertension on the long term. 
▪ Educational prompts at points-of-decision moder-
ately increase use of the stairs instead of the ele-
vator, but do not affect choices between healthy 
and unhealthy food alternatives in the worksite 
restaurant. 
▪ Accessibility of healthy food items in the work-
site restaurant has a major impact on purchase 
behaviour. </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ Four different types of interventions were evalu-
ated simultaneously using a single study design. 
▪ The study was performed in a large University 
Medical Centre with over 11 000 employees who 
were unaware of the study taking place and, thus, 
completely blinded to the study hypotheses. 
▪ Although randomisation of the interventions was 
not feasible, extraneous factors were kept con-
stant and adjusted for. </p>

<p>Dorresteijn JAN, van der Graaf Y, Zheng K, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002125. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002125 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>daily energy imbalance between intake and expenditure of 
about 10 kcal. 
5 This amount of energy expenditure can be 
achieved by as little as 1 min stair walking. 
6 Moreover, the 
reduction of energy intake that can be achieved by choos-
ing a lean food product alternative often exceeds 10 kcal 
by far. Prospective studies support that small changes in 
dietary pattern or physical activity are indeed associated 
with concomitant weight change. 
7 Yet, the increasing 
prevalence of obesity demonstrates that adopting such 
seemingly easy lifestyle changes in every day life is in fact 
tremendously challenging. 
Another thread to public health that has arisen in 
recent years is excess salt consumption, causing hyperten-
sion and cardiovascular disease. 
8 9 Because salt is fre-
quently used for preservation and seasoning of processed 
food products, excess sodium intake often goes 
unnoticed and is difficult to avoid. Although health-
policy makers are well aware of the dangers of consuming 
too much salt, they too consume more than 6 g salt per 
day themselves. This follows from a recent study in The 
Netherlands, showing that the mean salt content of a 
single hot meal in staff canteens of health policy makers 
is 7.1 g. 
10 Excess salt consumption, in part, explains the 
current increase of the worldwide prevalence of 
hypertension. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>To 'eat less and exercise more' means changing individ-
ual lifestyle behaviours that have gradually been adopted 
over decades. This is often found difficult and rarely 
maintained long term. Because adults spend approxi-
mately half their waking hours working, we aimed to 
evaluate whether several types of low-cost interventions in 
the working environment can stimulate the healthy life-
style adaptations in everyday life that may contribute to 
halting the epidemics of obesity and hypertension. </p>

<p>METHODS 
We performed a single-blind time-series intervention study 
in the University Medical Centre in Utrecht, The 
Netherlands, with over 11 000 employees and over 1000 
hospital beds. Participants were a dynamic study popula-
tion of staff and visitors of this hospital who were not 
informed about the study taking place. The study started 
13 February 2012 and lasted 8 weeks, not including public 
holidays. During this 8 weeks period, the effect of four 
types of interventions was studied simultaneously. The </p>

<p>study period was subdivided in four phases of 2 weeks 
each: a run-in period, a baseline period, an intervention 
period and an after-intervention period (figure 1). 
Outcome measurements were performed on a daily basis 
before (baseline period), during (intervention period) 
and after the interventions (after-intervention period). 
The first intervention was aimed at promoting stair 
climbing. The energy expenditure during 1 min stair 
climbing is approximately 10 kcal. 
12 Thus, the problem 
of weight gain during adult life could on average be pre-
vented by one additional minute stair climbing each day. 
Each of the three wings of the hospital where the study 
took place is equipped with three fast, parallel-operating 
and spacious elevators. Opposite all elevator doors is a 
broad, well-lit staircase, decorated with photographs on 
the walls and not portioned off by a door. Stair use 
between each of the six floor levels of the three main hos-
pital wings (ie, 15 measurement spots) was defined by the 
number of passages (both up or down), measured by 
Fastcount SP RS wireless infrared interruption counters 
(Solvatronics B.V., Amsterdam, The Netherlands). The 
cumulative value of each interruption counter was 
recorded each day of the study period at 17:30. During 
the intervention period, signs were placed right above 
the elevator buttons stating 'Stair climbing increases 
energy expenditure 11-fold' (see online supplementary 
appendix figure 1). These signs were removed during the 
after-intervention period. 
The second intervention was aimed at reducing salt 
intake. A previous study showed that the average salt 
content of a hot lunch (soup and non-vegetarian hot 
dish) in our hospital restaurant is as much as 8.5 g. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Pilot sampling for the present study revealed that this 
constitutes of an average 2.4 (SD 0.3) grams salt in an 
average 200 ml soup cup. The restaurant in the hospital 
where this study took place welcomes over 2000 
staff members and visitors each week day. Every day, 
two types of soup are offered side by side, a clear soup 
(eg, chicken, vegetables, noodle,, etc) and a cream soup 
(eg, mushroom, asparagus, tomato,, etc). During the 
entire study period, the salt content of the cream soup 
(but not the clear soup) was reduced by approximately 
30% to 1.7 (SD 0.1) g on average. During the 2 weeks of 
the intervention period, signs were placed at the soup 
counter stating 'The cream soup contains 30% less salt 
and contributes to a healthy blood pressure' (see online </p>

<p>Figure 1 Flow cart of the study design. </p>



<p>Dorresteijn JAN, van der Graaf Y, Zheng K, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002125. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002125 </p>

<p>Promotion of a healthy lifestyle in the work environment </p>

<p>supplementary appendix figure 2). Both types of soup 
were priced equally and available in excess until closure 
time of the restaurant. The number of normal salt 
(clear) soup cups and reduced salt (cream) soup cups 
purchased on each week day was recorded from the 
pay-desk computer system. 
The third intervention was aimed at reducing calorie 
intake and consumption of saturated fatty acids. Butter 
croissants are a popular lunch item in The Netherlands. 
Yet a 40 g butter croissant contains 8 g fat. 
13 Half of the 
157 kcal in one butter croissant are, thus, derived from 
its fat content. 
13 Therefore, a lean croissant, containing 
30% less fat (approximately 20 fewer kilocalories), was 
introduced in the hospital restaurant prior to this study. 
The lean and the butter croissants were similar in price, 
appearance and taste. Each week day, a standard 
amount of 45 butter croissants and 45 lean croissants 
were placed in separate baskets next to each other 
without signs pointing out the difference between the 
two. Each type had its own baskets and the positions of 
these baskets remained unchanged during the study 
period. During the intervention period, promotional 
signs were placed on the baskets of the lean croissants, 
stating 'The saturated (unhealthy) fat content of this 
croissant is 30% lower' (see online supplementary 
appendix figure 3). Once the first type of croissants was 
sold out (ie, once the choice option disappeared), the 
remaining croissants of the other type were counted by 
the investigator and considered unsold. 
Finally, the fourth intervention was also aimed at redu-
cing calorie intake and consumption of saturated fatty 
acids. Sandwiches are a major constituent of a typical 
Dutch lunch and consumption of at least 10 g margarine 
or butter each day (sufficient for one sandwich) is not 
unusual. 
14 One serving of 10 g butter, however, contains 
8 g (mostly saturated) fat (74 kcal). 
13 Alternatively, the 
hospital restaurant where this study took place offers 
diet margarine containing 6 or even 4 g (mostly unsatur-
ated) fat per 10 g serving (54 or 34 kcal, respectively). </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Because margarine compared to butter has a longer 
shelf life outside the refrigerator, margarine cups are 
normally presented at four centrally located and 
easy-to-reach positions in the hospital restaurant, while 
butter cups are placed in one of the fridges and are, 
thus, harder to reach. During the 2 weeks intervention 
period, we observed how changing the positions of these 
products (ie, the accessibility) affected the purchase of 
butter and margarine as recorded from the pay desk 
computer system. Both margarine and butter cups were 
available in abundance during the entire course of the 
study. Thus, customers who preferred one or the other 
product for its taste were able to purchase it at any time 
during the course of the study. 
As a measure of the number of staff and visitors in the 
hospital on each day, the number of restaurant custo-
mers was recorded from the pay desk computer system. 
The institutional review board of the University Medical 
Centre Utrecht approved the study. The study was </p>

<p>registered on http://www.clinicaltrials.gov; unique iden-
tifier NCT01574040. </p>

<p>Data analyses 
The number of persons passing through the staircases 
was expressed per 24 h. Because the absolute number of 
passages differed substantially between the 15 different 
measurement sites, counts were expressed as percentage 
of baseline average. Baseline average was defined as the 
mean number of passages per 24 h over all days of the 
baseline period at each measurement site. After rescal-
ing, all separate observations were included in linear 
regression models that were used to calculate the average 
percentage change in stair use over all measurement sites 
during the intervention period and during the 2 weeks 
thereafter. To increase model precision, a variable 
'weekend day (yes/no)' was included to account for the 
reduced number of staff during the weekends. Similar to 
one previous study, 
16 results are presented with and 
without additional adjustment for the number of hospital 
restaurant customers on each day, reflecting variations in 
building occupancy. Results were stratified by hospital 
wing and floor level to assess the consistency of our find-
ings. Recordings of the number of passages through the 
staircases from one measurement site were missing on 
three separate days (0.4% of all measurements) owing to 
technical failure of the person counter. These were 
excluded from the analyses. 
The average numbers of clear soup cups and cream 
soup cups purchased on weekdays during each study 
period were expressed per 1000 restaurant visitors and as 
the ratio between the two. Similarly, the average numbers 
of butter and margarine servings purchased on weekdays 
during each study period were also expressed per 1000 
restaurant visitors and as the ratio between the two. The 
average numbers of butter croissants and lean croissants, 
however, were expressed as the average number pur-
chased until the first type was sold out and the ratio 
between those two. p Values for difference between the 
intervention period and the baseline period and between 
the after-intervention period and the baseline period 
were based on unpaired t tests. Few missing data on con-
sumption of croissants (n=2; 7%), soup cups (n=1; 3%) 
and margarine or butter (n=1; 3%) that occurred due to 
study personnel's incidental incompliance with the study 
protocol were excluded from the analyses. 
Analyses were conducted with <rs id="software-0" type="software">R statistical software</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v.2.11.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">http://www.R-project.org</rs>). </p>

<p>RESULTS 
The main characteristics of the three study periods are 
demonstrated in table 1. The number of week days and 
weekend days in each study period was exactly equal and 
no difference was observed in the average number of hos-
pital restaurant customers. Yet, more sunny days occurred 
during the intervention period and maximum </p>

<p>Dorresteijn JAN, van der Graaf Y, Zheng K, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002125. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002125 </p>



<p>Promotion of a healthy lifestyle in the work environment </p>

<p>temperature was a few degrees higher during the interven-
tion and after-intervention period compared to baseline. 
During the baseline period, the mean 24 hr number </p>

<p>of stair passages per measurement site was 992 (± À an SD 
of 479) on week days and 208 (± À 116) on weekend days. </p>

<p>Table 2 shows that stair use increased during the inter-
vention period by 8.5% (95% CI 5.8% to 11.1%) on 
average or 11.2% (95% CI 8.7% to 13.7%) when 
adjusted for the number of restaurant customers, reflect-
ing the number of staff and visitors inside the hospital 
building on each day. The largest increase in stair use 
was observed in the second hospital wing, whereas no 
change was observed in the first hospital wing ( p value 
for overall difference between the hospital wings &lt;0.01). 
Similarly, an increase was observed at all floor levels 
except between levels 0 and 1, although the difference 
between the floor levels was not significant ( p value 
0.26). Floor level 0 is the basement level of the hospital 
building that is mainly used for transportation of goods. </p>

<p>After the elevator signs were removed, increased stair 
use was maintained during the after-intervention period. 
Figure 2 demonstrates that promotion of the reduced-
salt cream soup did not affect the number of normal salt 
clear soup cups or reduced-salt cream soup cups sold or 
the ratio between them. Observed differences were in the 
hypothesised direction, but not statistically significant. This 
is also true for the number of butter croissants and lean 
croissants that were purchased. Compared to baseline, the 
ratio between lean and butter croissants was unchanged 
during the intervention period, but increased during the 
after-intervention period from 0.67 ± </p>

<p>À 0.18 to 0.90 ± 
À 0.18 </p>

<p>(p=0.02). Reversing the positions of margarine and butter, 
making the unhealthy food option (ie, butter) temporarily 
better accessible, decreased the ratio of margarine and 
butter servings that were sold from 7.3 ± </p>

<p>À 1.9 to 1.1 ± 
À 0.2 </p>

<p>(p&lt;0.01), thus leading to unhealthy behaviour. This effect 
completely disappeared after the baseline situation was 
restored during the after-intervention period. </p>

<p>Table 2 Effect of the intervention on stair use </p>

<p>Baseline stair use (number 
of passages per 24 h) 
Mean percentage change (95% CI) 
Week days 
Weekend days 
Intervention period* 
After-intervention period* </p>

<p>Overall (crude) 
992±479 
208±116 
8.5% (5.8% to 11.1%) 
9.9% (7.3% to 12.6%) 
Overall (adjusted)  † 
11.2% (8.7% to 13.7%) 
10.9% (8.4% to 13.3%) 
Stratified by hospital wing 
1st wing 
995±421 
246±102 
1.1% (−3.6% to 5.8%) 
6.6% (1.9% to 11.3%) 
2nd wing 
1116±589 
221±146 
15.8% (11.9% to 19.8%) 
15.3% (11.4% to 19.2%) 
3rd wing 
869±384 
158±79 
8.5% (4.4% to 12.6%) 
7.8% (3.7% to 11.9%) 
Stratified by floor level 
Level 0 to 1 
880±268 
189±93 
3.4% (−2.2% to 9.0%) 
5.1% (−0.6% to 10.7%) 
Level 1 to 2 
1610±289 
346±116 
8.4% (3.8% to 13.0%) 
7.8% (3.2% to 12.5%) 
Level 2 to 3 
1211±321 
239±76 
9.1% (3.8% to 14.3%) 
8.4% (3.1% to 13.7%) 
Level 3 to 4 
874±128 
191±51 
10.5% (5.1% to 16.0%) 
11.8% (6.4% to 17.3%) 
Level 4 to 5 
355±100 
77±30 
10.9% (2.9% to 18.9%) 
16.4% (8.4% to 24.4%) </p>

<p>*All analyses are adjusted for reduced stair use during weekend days. 
 †Additional adjustment for the number of hospital restaurant visitors as a measure of the number of staff and visitors inside the hospital on 
each day. </p>

<p>Table 1 Characteristics of the study periods </p>

<p>Baseline 
period </p>

<p>Intervention 
period </p>

<p>After-intervention 
period </p>

<p>Value for 
difference* </p>

<p>Week days 
10 (71%) 
10 (71%) 
10 (71%) 
1.00 
Weekend days 
4 (29%) 
4 (29%) 
4 (29%) 
Weather type † 
Sunny days 
3 (21%) 
10 (71%) 
4 (29%) 
0.03 
Cloudy days 
8 (57%) 
4 (29%) 
9 (64%) 
Rainy days 
3 (21%) 
0 (0%) 
1 (7%) 
Maximum temperature (°C) † 
9.5±2.0 
13.1±3.1 
12.1±3.4 
0.01 
Daily no. of restaurant customers 
Week days 
2273±154 
2193±137 
2250±132 
0.44 
Weekend days 
342±56 
324±12 
318±30 
0.22 </p>

<p>Data are presented as No. (%) or Mean±SD. 
*p Values are based on a Pearson χ 
2 or analysis of variance tests. 
 †Local weather was recorded from http://www.meteogroup.com. </p>



<p>Dorresteijn JAN, van der Graaf Y, Zheng K, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002125. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002125 </p>

<p>Promotion of a healthy lifestyle in the work environment </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Although the actual energy expenditure deficit may 
differ between individuals and from day to day, gradual 
weight gain of one pound per year during adult life 
could on average be prevented by consumption of 10 
fewer kilocalories or expenditure of 10 additional kilo-
calories on a daily basis. In this time-series study, that 
was performed in a large University Medical Centre, we 
have evaluated the effects of four low-cost interventions 
in the work environment aimed at promoting healthy 
lifestyle modifications that could make this 10 kcal differ-
ence. Point-of-decision prompts on elevator doors were 
shown to increase the number of hospital staff and </p>

<p>visitors taking the stairs by 11.2% and the behavioural 
change was maintained at least until 2 weeks after the 
intervention. Signs promoting healthy food alternatives 
in the hospital restaurant, on the other hand, did not 
have a major effect on food choices. Indeed, a somewhat 
increased consumption of lean compared to butter crois-
sants was observed in this study. Yet, although a delayed 
effect of the intervention cannot be excluded, the rela-
tion between this increase and the promotional inter-
vention is uncertain because it was observed only after 
the promotional signs were already removed. Strikingly, 
however, the largest effect on health behaviour was 
achieved by modification of the accessibility of a healthy </p>

<p>Figure 2 Effect of the interventions on reducing salt, calorie and (saturated) fat intake in the hospital restaurant. </p>

<p>Dorresteijn JAN, van der Graaf Y, Zheng K, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002125. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002125 </p>



<p>Promotion of a healthy lifestyle in the work environment </p>

<p>food product and its unhealthy alternative. Diet margar-
ine compared to butter was consumed seven times less 
often when it was presented at a single, somewhat 
distant position in the hospital restaurant instead of mul-
tiple, centrally located and easy-to-reach positions. 
The present study was performed in a single centre 
and the intervention was non-randomised. Yet, this 
single study centre was a large University Medical Centre 
with over 11 000 employees, over 1000 hospital beds and 
over 2000 customers visiting the hospital restaurant each 
day, thus contributing to a large number of study obser-
vations. Randomisation was not feasible owing to the 
nature of the intervention. Instead, extraneous factors 
were kept as stable as possible. For example, the study 
period was scheduled in such a way that public holidays 
were not included. Also, results were adjusted for the 
number of customers of the hospital restaurant as a 
measure of building occupancy, like was done in one 
previous study also. 
16 Thus, although no data about ele-
vator use were obtained during the study, we were able 
to ascertain that changes in the number of passages 
through the staircases were not just due to changes in 
building occupancy. A factor that could not be stabilised, 
however, was the weather type. Warmer weather during 
the intervention period may have influenced food 
choices. Especially, hot soup may be more popular on 
colder days. Although this may explain why promotional 
signs did not increase the consumption of low-salt cream 
soup, a concomitant (stronger) reduction of the con-
sumption of normal-salt was not observed. Still, the ratio 
between normal-salt and low-salt soup moved in the 
hypothesised direction during the intervention period 
and it is not inconceivable that a significant difference 
would have been observed if more observations were 
made. The interventions in this study lasted 2 weeks and 
it could not be inferred from this study whether any 
effects last if the interventions are continued long term. 
Similarly, measurements went on until 2 weeks after the 
interventions. Whereas promotion of stair climbing still 
exerted positive effects during those 2 weeks while the 
elevator signs were already removed, it remains uncer-
tain whether those effects are maintained after a longer 
period. Unfortunately, we were unable to discriminate 
whether the effect of the elevator signs was due to 
increased stair use by hospital employees or by visitors 
or both. The largest increase was observed in the hos-
pital wing that is closest to the main entrance and 
attracts the largest number of visitors. Yet, the fact that 
stair use remained increased after removal of the 
point-of-decision prompts suggests a behavioural change 
of hospital staff. Also, we were unable to assess whether 
changes in stair use were caused by increased stair clim-
bing, stair descent or a combination of both. Notably, 
stair climbing requires at least twice the energy expend-
iture of stair-descent making climbing the preferred 
public health target. 
17 A final limitation of this study is 
that we were unable to assess whether the interventions 
affected weight or blood pressure. This is because the </p>

<p>follow-up period was too short and because we did 
measure these outcomes. A notable strength of this 
study is that the participants (ie, employees and visitors 
of the hospital) were unaware of the study taking place 
and, thus, completely blinded to the study hypotheses. 
This is important, because such awareness during the 
before-intervention and the after-intervention periods 
could potentially result in underestimation of the effect 
of the interventions. Moreover, a unique feature of this 
study is that four types of interventions are evaluated 
simultaneously so that a comparison can be made as to 
which type of intervention is most effective. 
Promoting stair climbing in public buildings or at the 
work site has since long been a well-recognised opportun-
ity for increasing engagement in physical activity by 
adults. 
18 The effect of point-of-decision prompts, like the 
elevator signs in the present study, have been evaluated 
by previous studies. 
18 19 Like the present study, most of 
these studies follow a time-series design, but study settings 
vary substantially. Studies in settings where elevator use is 
the alternative to stair use, like in the present study, show 
that point-of-decision prompts increase stair use by a 
median of 5%, which is lower than the 11.2% that was 
observed in the present study. 
18-20 Much larger effects 
are typically observed in settings where escalators are the 
alternative to stair use (median increase of 77%), but 
escalators are uncommon in work environments. </p>

<p>18-20 </p>

<p>Enhancements to stairs or stairwells (eg, foot steps, 
adding artwork, painting walls, etc) have been proposed 
to reinforce the effect of point-of-decision prompts, but 
there is insufficient evidence to support their effective-
ness. 
18 Studies, evaluating point-of-purchase educational 
interventions aimed at promoting healthy food items, 
suggests that product health information does not have 
significant effects on actual purchase behaviour in super-
markets or restaurants. 
21 22 This is in accordance with 
our observations that consumption of reduced-salt soup 
and lean croissants was unaffected by the promotional 
signs. The effect of increasing the availability of and 
access to healthy food items on purchase behaviour is less 
well studied, but available evidence supports our observa-
tion that increased ease of access to an unhealthy option 
results in less healthy choices. 
23 24 One type of 
point-of-purchase intervention that was not evaluated in 
the present study is the effect of financial reward by dis-
counting healthy compared to unhealthy food, which 
may also be effective. 
24-26 In addition, decreasing portion 
sizes has been proposed as a method to reduce caloric 
intake, but the effect of such intervention is compro-
mised because smaller meals are often compensated by 
purchasing additional food items. 
27 Finally, it may well be 
that the effects of isolated interventions can be enhanced 
by combining them with a promotional campaign. 
In conclusion, the present study shows that educa-
tional prompts at points of decision are moderately 
effective or ineffective for promoting a more healthy life-
style. The accessibility of healthy food items in the work-
site restaurant, however, had a major impact on </p>



<p>Dorresteijn JAN, van der Graaf Y, Zheng K, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002125. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002125 </p>

<p>Promotion of a healthy lifestyle in the work environment </p>

<p>purchase behaviour. Small changes in everyday behavi-
our may on the long term have important impact on 
body weight and blood pressure. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements We gratefully acknowledge the contribution of Tim 
Leegwater (restaurant floor manager), Stef Baan (chef cook of the restaurant 
kitchen), Jan de Bruin (cluster manager nutrition), Leonie J Braskamp 
(restaurant department manager) and other employees of the hospital 
restaurant for their enthusiasm and collaboration. Furthermore, we express 
our gratitude to Corrie AMP Scholman and Frans R Urban (Department of 
Human Resources) for their involvement in organising and funding this study. 
This study provided the two outcome assessors of this study with the 
opportunity to burn an estimated 30 000 kcal during data collection over an 
8 weeks period, thereby achieving a higher level of physical fitness. </p>

<p>Contributors JANDwas involved in conception of the research question, data 
collection and data handling, design and execution of data analyses, 
interpretation of the results, drafting of the manuscript. YvdG and WS were 
involved in conception of the research question, interpretation of the results, 
revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content. KLZ carried out 
data collection and data handling, design and execution of data analyses, 
revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content. FLJV was 
involved in conception of the research question, design of data analyses, 
interpretation of the results, revision of the manuscript for important 
intellectual content. </p>

<p>Funding This study was supported by a grant from the Human Resource 
Department of the University Medical Centre Utrecht, who had no role in the 
conduct of the analyses or drafting of the report. All statistical analyses were 
carried out by the investigators. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Ethics approval The Ethics Committee of the UMCU approved the study. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement There are no additional data available. </p>



<p>Dorresteijn JAN, van der Graaf Y, Zheng K, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e002125. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002125 </p>



<p>Promotion of a healthy lifestyle in the work environment </p>

</text></tei>