<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3474945" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Borrelia-specific antibodies are not detectable until several weeks after infection and even if they are present, 
they are no proof of an active infection. Since the sensitivity of culture and PCR for the diagnosis or exclusion of borrelio-
sis is too low, a method is required that detects an active Borrelia infection as early as possible. For this purpose, a lym-
phocyte transformation test (LTT) using lysate antigens of Borrelia burgdorferi sensu stricto, Borrelia afzelii and Borrelia 
garinii and recombinant OspC was developed and validated through investigations of seronegative and seropositive 
healthy individuals as well as of seropositive patients with clinically manifested borreliosis. The sensitivity of the LTT in 
clinical borreliosis before antibiotic treatment was determined as 89,4% while the specificity was 98,7%. In 1480 patients 
with clinically suspected borreliosis, results from serology and LTT were comparable in 79.8% of cases. 18% were sero-
logically positive and LTT-negative. These were mainly patients with borreliosis after antibiotic therapy. 2.2% showed a 
negative serology and a positive LTT result. Half of them had an early erythema migrans. Following antibiotic treatment, 
the LTT became negative or borderline in patients with early manifestations of borreliosis, whereas in patients with late 
symptoms, it showed a regression while still remaining positive. Therefore, we propose the follow-up monitoring of dis-
seminated Borrelia infections as the main indication for the Borrelia-LTT. </p>

<p>The symptoms associated with the systemic phase of 
Lyme borreliosis can be highly varied and ambiguous. In 
these cases, the detection of Borrelia-specific antibodies (se-
rological laboratory diagnosis) becomes important for the 
diagnosis and treatment decision. The necessarily high qual-
ity demands cannot yet be completely fulfilled by Borrelia 
serology due to the following reasons: 1) Borrelia-specific </p>

<p>*Address correspondence to this author at the Institut für Medizinische 
Diagnostik Berlin, Nicolaistraße 22, 12247 Berlin, Germany; 
Tel: +49-30-77001220; Fax: +49-30-77001236; 
E-mail: v.baehr@imd-berlin.de </p>

<p>IgM antibodies, and IgG antibodies in particular, cannot be 
detected until several weeks after infection [1, 2].Seronega-
tive cases with late stage Lyme borreliosis have also been 
recently described [3]. But these are becoming more rare 
with the increasing quality of the assays following the intro-
duction of recombinant Borrelia antigens. 2) The heterogene-
ity of Borrelia species and strains within a species requires a 
polymorphism of the Borrelia-specific protein antigens [4, 
5]. This is a difficult problem for the sensitivity of Borrelia 
serology. 3) IgM antibodies against Borrelia OspC may be of 
the nonspecific type [4, 5]. 4) A positive serological finding 
alone is not proof of a current active Borrelia infection [1, 4, 
5]. 5) Borrelia serology is not suitable for the monitoring of 
therapy and evaluation of progress as IgG and IgM antibod-
ies may persist for years after borreliosis has been cured [6]. </p>

<p>The direct detection of Borrelia by culture or PCR has a 
high diagnostic value in the case of a positive result, but a 
negative result does not rule out Lyme borreliosis [4, 5]. </p>

<p>There is currently no method available which, in addition 
to the serology, answers the question as to whether a specific 
case is a status post Borrelia infection or active borreliosis. </p>

<p>Each humoral immune response to an infection requires a 
specific cellular immune response with clonal proliferation 
of various antigen-specific lymphocyte subpopulations. Of 
central importance here are antigen-specific T helper lym-
phocytes (CD4 
+ T H cells). In addition to effector T cells, 
long-lived T and B memory lymphocytes are formed. In the 
presence of antigen-presenting cells and protein antigens, </p>

<p>Lymphocyte Transformation Test for Borreliosis </p>

<p>The Open Neurology Journal, 2012, Volume 6 105 </p>

<p>specific CD4 
+ T memory cells also proliferate in vitro. The 
lymphocyte transformation test (LTT), also known as the 
lymphocyte proliferation or lymphocyte activation test, is 
based on this principle [7]. Shortly after the discovery of B. 
burgdorferi, it was demonstrated that blood lymphocytes 
from Lyme borreliosis patients proliferate in the presence of 
Borrelia lysates [8, 9]. Published data on the diagnostic value 
of the Borrelia-LTT, especially in seronegative patients, can 
be found beginning in 1988 [10-17]. However, false positive 
LTT reactions have also been described [18-20]. Important 
for the motivation of our investigations presented here were 
observations that positive LTT reactions of blood lympho-
cytes to Borrelia antigens declined significantly or were neg-
ative after antibiotic treatment of Lyme borreliosis [12, 14, 
16, 21]. This leads to the hypothesis that Borrelia-specific T 
helper cells circulate in the blood in detectable numbers only 
during an active immune response against Borrelia and per-
sist in a non-florid infection in lymphoid organs. </p>

<p>Using improved cell culture and measurement techniques 
as well as our own experience in the development of antigen-
specific LTT applications, we will seek to answer using re-
evaluation of patient data the following questions: </p>

<p>1. Is there a correlation between the results of Borrelia 
serology and Borrelia-LTT? </p>

<p>2. What are the Borrelia-LTT results in clinically healthy 
seropositive subjects? </p>

<p>3. Is it possible to obtain an indication of the respective 
species involved from the LTT reactions to antigens of 
the three Borrelia species? </p>

<p>4. Are Borrelia-LTT results influenced by antibiotic treat-
ment? </p>

<p>5. How high are the sensitivity and specificity of the Bor-
relia-LTT? </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Subjects and Patients 
All laboratory tests were performed in the course of rou-
tine diagnostic procedures that were applied to prove or to 
exclude borreliosis, respectively. </p>

<p>The statistical re-evaluation was performed retroactive 
considering the laboratory data and the documented clinical 
data by the doctors. </p>

<p>The seronegative control group (n = 160) included 120 
clinically healthy subjects (blood donors) and 40 patients 
with autoimmune diseases (rheumatoid arthritis, lupus ery-
thematosus viszeralis, Hashimoto's thyroiditis, diabetes mel-
litus type 1) (86 men, 74 women, aged 18 to 72 years). </p>

<p>The seropositive group included patients with clinical 
borreliosis (n = 94); erythema migrans (n = 28), acute mono-
arthritis (n = 14), Bannwarth's syndrome (n = 6), migrating 
arthromyalgias (n = 34), facial palsy (n = 5) , acute neuro-
borreliosis (n = 7) as well as clinically healthy subjects (n = 
48) including forest workers and hunters, persons working 
full time in agriculture and horticulture and hobby gardeners 
(34 men, 14 women; aged 24-72 years). </p>

<p>Borrelia serology and Borrelia-LTT were investigated in 
parallel in patients with unknown serology but clinical diag-
nosis of suspected Lyme borreliosis (n = 1480). </p>

<p>Patients with clinical borreliosis with positive or un-
known serology were used for LTT progression studies. </p>

<p>The blood of 20 healthy persons was used for the pre-
liminary finding of appropriate antigen concentrations for the 
LTT. </p>

<p>Borrelia Serology 
For antibody determination, recombinant Borrelia IgG 
and IgM ELISA (Mikrogen, Munich, Germany) and the IgG 
and IgM immunoblot / recombinant immunoblot (Mikrogen) 
were used. The immunoblot contains the following specific 
recombinant Borrelia antigens: p100, p41 int (B. afzelii., B. 
garinii.), p41 (B. sensu stricto), p39, p31, p25, p18, VslE. </p>

<p>The tests and evaluation of the results were performed 
according to the working instructions of the manufacturer. 
The results for the ELISA test are given as "negative" or 
"positive". Only the results of the Borrelia immunoblot were 
evaluated for the classification of the subjects / patients as 
"seronegative", "borderline" or "seropositive". </p>

<p>Borrelia Antigens 
Purified lyophilized lysate antigens generated from day 6 
cultures of Borrelia sensu stricto (strain LW2 isolated from 
skin biopsy), Borrelia afzelii (strain Pko, DSM No. 16073) 
and Borrelia garinii (strain PBi isolated from CSF, Pet-
tenkofer Institute, Munich) were kindly provided by Sera-
mun, Heidesee, Germany. Seramun determined the protein 
content in purified lysate using the BCA Protein Assay Kit 
(Pierce, Prod. No: 23225). Each lysate contains, among oth-
ers, the following antigens: p83/100; p58; p43; p41; p39; 
p30; p22-25; p21; p19; p17. Antigens were tested by using 
IgG immunoblot (Fig. 1, supplementary data). All lysate 
antigens used in the LTT test are tested by Seramun with 8 
positive and negative control sera in the solid phase IgG and 
IgM ELISA. Only those lysates were used for the LTT test 
that reacted with positive control sera only, and not with 
negative control sera. </p>

<p>Recombinant OspC of B. afzelii (host cell E. coli TG) 
was provided by Micromun, Greifswald, Germany. The pro-
tein is purified through Ni Sepharose (Amersham Biosci-
ence) and purity testing was performed by Microimun using 
polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. </p>

<p>Lymphocyte Transformation Test (Syn. Lymphocyte 
Proliferation Test) 
10 ml of heparinized venous blood were obtained under 
sterile conditions and processed by density gradient centrifu-
gation to obtain peripheral blood mononuclear cells (85-95% 
lymphocytes and 5-15% monocytes) as described elsewhere 
[21]. After washing the cells with PBS (PAA Laboratories, 
Linz, Austria), the cell pellet was resuspended to obtain a 
cell count of 1 x 10 
6 /ml in cell culture medium (RPMI 1640; 
PAA) supplemented with 2 mM L-glutamine (PAA), 100 
µg/ml gentamicin (PAA) and 5% autologous serum. To im-
prove antigen presentation and suppression of nonspecific </p>

<p>106 The Open Neurology Journal, 2012, Volume 6 </p>

<p>Baehr et al. </p>

<p>cell activation, recombinant interferon-α (rIFNα2b, Scher-
ing-Plough, Kenilworth, USA) was added to all assays at a 
concentration of 125 U/ml (23). To inhibit nonspecific acti-
vating effects caused by the lipoids and lipoproteins con-
tained in the Borrelia lysate antigen preparations, polymyxin 
B (PAA) is used in a final concentration of 5 µg/ml. All as-
says were performed in triplicates. Cell stimulation was per-
formed by using 2 x 10 
5 cells/well in a 96-well microplate 
(Nunclon, Wiesbaden, Germany) for 6 days at 37°C and 5% 
CO 2 atmosphere. Cells were labeled with 
3 H-thymidine (1 
µCi/ml, Hartmann Analytics, Braunschweig, Germany) 12 
hours prior to cell harvest. Cell harvest was performed on 
glass fiber filters (Wallac, Lund, Sweden) using a cell har-
vester (Wallac). The incorporated 
3 H-thymidine activity was 
measured as "counts per minute" (cpm) with a solid phase 
beta counter (Wallac). Mean value of the triplicates are used 
for analysis. The results for each antigen are given as a stim-
ulation index (SI; ratio of cpm of the culture with and w/o 
test antigen). </p>

<p>To demonstrate the functional integrity of the immune 
cells, positive controls were performed in parallel. As an 
antigen-presenting cell-dependent positive control a recall 
antigen mixture of tetatoxoid (GlaxoSmithKline, Munich, 
Germany), influenza split antigen (GlaxoSmithKline) and 
cytomegalovirus antigen (Abbott, Wiesbaden, Germany) is 
used. As mitogen control the nonspecific cell stimulator 
pokeweed mitogen (PWM, PAA) is added in a concentration 
of 1.5 µg/ml. The test evaluation is performed only if antigen 
control reaches SI &gt; 5 and mitogen control reaches SI &gt; 20. </p>

<p>For the assessment of the Borrelia-LTT we used the fol-
lowing cut-offs: </p>

<p>SI &lt; 3 = negative test result, </p>

<p>SI &gt; 5 = positive test result, </p>

<p>SI 3 to 5 = weak positive test result. </p>

<p>For the validation of the Borrelia-LTT a test result is 
considered positive if at least two of the four Borrelia anti-
gens show SI values of 3 and higher. </p>

<p>Statistics 
The sensitivity of the LTT was evaluated by taking the 
percentual number of LTT positive patients in relation to all </p>

<p>seropositive patients with clinical borreliosis. The specificity 
was calculated by taking the relative number of LTT nega-
tive results in a group of seronegative clinical healthy sub-
jects. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis for the LTT validation results was 
performed by using the Chi-square test (<rs id="software-0" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad</rs> 
software, La Jolla, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Determining the Appropriate Test Dose of Antigen for 
the Borrelia-LTT 
To validate the antigen specificity of the Borrelia-LTT, 
blood samples were used from 20 clinically healthy Borrelia-
seronegative volunteers. Isolated PBMC were tested in a 
dilution series (12, 8, 4, 2, 1, 0.5 µg/ml) of the 4 Borrelia test 
antigens in the LTT assay. Using this setting the highest an-
tigen concentration for the Borrelia-LTT which did not give 
any positive (SI from 3) or borderline (SI&gt; 2 &lt;3) LTT result 
was determined. The working concentrations per assay cal-
culated in this manner contained 1 μg of protein for the lys-
ate antigen of B. sensu stricto, 2 μg each of the lysate anti-
gens of B. afzelii and B. garinii, and 0.5 μg for rOspC. All 
further tests were performed with the given antigen concen-
trations. </p>

<p>Sensitivity and Specificity of the Borrelia-LTT 
The results of the validation studies for the Borrelia-LTT 
are summarized in Table 1. </p>

<p>In 160 seronegative subjects/patients (120 healthy sero-
negative and 40 patients with autoimmune diseases), a speci-
ficity of 98,7% was found if the borderline results of SI &gt; 2 &lt; 
3 were evaluated as negative. Weak false positive reactions 
(SI&gt; 3 &lt;5) were detected in only 2 cases. No differences 
were found between clinically healthy subjects and patients 
with autoimmune diseases. </p>

<p>In 94 seropositive patients with clinical borreliosis before 
antibiotic treatment, the sensitivity of the Borrelia-LTT (SI 
&gt;3 to 28) was 89.4%. Ten proved to be negative (10,6%). 
From the 13 patients with a typical clinical picture of neuro-
borreliosis, 10 showed positive results in the LTT. Two out 
of 5 patients with facial palsy and 1 out of 7 patients with </p>

<p>Table 1. Results of Validation Studies of the Borrelia-LTT </p>

<p>Borrelia-LTT Results </p>

<p>Negative SI &lt; 3 
Positive SI &gt;3 </p>

<p>n 
(%) 
n 
(%) </p>

<p>Seronegative control group </p>

<p>n=160 
158 
(98,7) 
2 
(1.3) </p>

<p>Seropositive test subject group, clinically healthy </p>

<p>n=48 
44 
(91,6) 
4 
(8.4) </p>

<p>Seropositive patients, clinical borreliosis </p>

<p>n=94 
10 
(10,6) 
84 
(89.4) </p>

<p>Lymphocyte Transformation Test for Borreliosis </p>

<p>The Open Neurology Journal, 2012, Volume 6 107 </p>

<p>acute neuroborreliosis showed a negative LTT. </p>

<p>In 48 clinically healthy seropositive subjects, 91,6% (n = 
44) were found to be negative and 8.4% (n = 4) showed 
weak positive results in the Borrelia-LTT. The specificity of 
the positive Borrelia-LTT for clinically active borreliosis 
was 91.6% in this group. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis showed a significant difference for the 
LTT of the Borrelia-IgG/IgM seropositive patients who are 
clinically active from clinically healthy seropositive patients 
(p &lt;0.0001, Chi-square test). </p>

<p>Correlation of Borrelia Serology (Immunoblot) and Bor-
relia-LTT 
The correspondence of Borrelia serology and Borrelia-
LTT was studied by re-evaluation of simultaneously con-
ducted laboratory results of 1480 patients with clinical suspi-
cion of borreliosis by parallel determination of the serology 
and the Borrelia-LTT. </p>

<p>In 1182 out of 1480 patients (79.8%), the Borrelia serol-
ogy and Borrelia-LTT showed corresponding results. 37,8% 
(n=560) showed a positive serology and a positive LTT 
whereas 42% (n=622) were LTT as well as serology nega-
tive. The combination of a positive serology with a negative 
Borrelia-LTT was found in 266 patients (18.0%). 32 patients 
(2.2%) were seronegative and LTT-positive. </p>

<p>The discrepant results were followed up retrospectively 
with the treating physicians in order to clarify any contribu-
tion of other clinical conditions (Tables 2a and 2b). The se-
ropositive/LTT-negative group consisted predominantly of 
patients with status post antibiotic treatment of Lyme bor-
reliosis (n=240, 90,2%). In the remaining 26 patients only 
IgM antibodies against OspC were detected. In these cases, 
there was evidence of rheumatoid arthritis (n = 15), reactive 
arthritis (n = 3) or of a recent EBV infection (n = 5). </p>

<p>Among the 32 subjects with the seronegative/LTT-
positive constellation, 16 of the patients (50%) had early 
erythema migrans at the time of blood sample collection. 
The clinical symptoms of the remaining 16 patients were 
ambiguous -6 of them had a positive IgG and another 6 had 
a positive IgM ELISA test, in each case without the detection 
of specific bands in the immunoblot. Therefore, 16 (1.1%) of 
the 1480 Borrelia-LTT results must be regarded as false 
positives. </p>

<p>The number of false negative results for the Borrelia-LTT 
can only be determined from the group of 94 seropositive, 
clinically confirmed borreliosis patients of the validation 
phase. The rate in these cases was 10.6% (n = 10). </p>

<p>We would like to mention, that the setting of the study 
was not suitable to clarify the specificity or sensitivity of the 
serological tests itself because only the exact clinical evalua-
tion would be suitable as gold standard for this purpose. </p>

<p>Borrelia Lysate Antigens of Three Different Borrelia 
Species have Proven to be Largely Cross-reactive in the 
Borrelia-LTT 
340 positive Borrelia-LTT results were evaluated with 
regard to the number of positive reactions in each individual 
test using the 3 lysate antigens and rOspC (Table 3). A posi-
tive reaction to only one antigen was observed only in rare 
cases and regarded as unspecific. </p>

<p>The results show that the lysate antigens of all three Bor-
relia species are predominantly cross-reactive in the Borre-
lia-LTT. </p>

<p>Positive Borrelia-LTT Declines Significantly Following 
Antibiotic Treatment 
In addition, follow-up investigations before and 4-6 
weeks after a three-week antibiotic treatment were per-
formed in 230 patients with a positive Borrelia-LTT (SI &gt; 5 </p>

<p>Table 2a. Analysis of the Constellation of a Positive Borrelia Serology/ Negative LTT </p>

<p>n 
(%) </p>

<p>Borreliosis after antibiotic therapy (no clinical findings) 
240 
(90.2) </p>

<p>Rheumatoid arthritis, LEV 
15 
(5.7) </p>

<p>Status post primary EBV infection 
5 
(1.9) </p>

<p>Reactive arthritis 
3 
(1.1) </p>

<p>unclassifiable 
3 
(1.1) </p>

<p>(n = 266) </p>

<p>Table 2b. Analysis of the Constellation of a Negative Borrelia Serology/ Positive LTT </p>

<p>n 
(%) </p>

<p>Erythema migrans 
16 
(50.0) </p>

<p>Positive Borrelia ELISA IgM, IgG, immunoblot negative 
12 
(37.5) </p>

<p>unclassifiable 
4 
(12.5) </p>

<p>(n = 32) </p>



<p>Baehr et al. </p>

<p>with 3 Borrelia antigens). 140 of them had a clinical early 
borreliosis and 90 late manifestations of borreliosis. The 
division into early (n = 140) and late manifestations (n = 90) 
was based on existing clinical data and the probable time of 
infection, i.e., less than (early borreliosis) or more than one 
year (late borreliosis) (Table 4). </p>

<p>A significant decrease in SI values in the Borrelia-LTT 
became apparent after the antibiotic treatment. Among those 
with early manifestations, 92% of patients had negative or 
borderline LTT results 4 to 6 weeks after antibiotic treat-
ment. By contrast, this was true of only 53% of patients with 
late manifestations. The retrospective evaluation of clinical 
data indicated, that in parallel to the LTT, clinical symptoms 
also regressed significantly or were no longer present. In 
cases of late manifestations with a persistent positive Borre-
lia-LTT, partial to complete resistance to treatment of the 
symptoms was observed. </p>

<p>The serological findings did not change significantly dur-
ing the same period. In some cases, an increase in the ab-
sorbance of the Borrelia ELISA for IgG and IgM antibodies 
was found. Due to the low sensitivity of the PCR in blood 
we refrained from performing this parallel analysis in our 
study. </p>

<p>Follow-up Studies of the Borrelia-LTT Over a Period of 
One Year 
From the group of early manifestations, 12 patients (ery-</p>

<p>thema migrans, n = 9; acute neuroborreliosis, n = 3), and 
from the group of late borreliosis, 18 patients (Lyme arthri-
tis, n = 12; chronic neuroborreliosis, n = 6) both the serology 
and the Borrelia-LTT were performed at least every 3 
months in the course of a year. An additional LTT testing is 
normally performed if a recurrence of Lyme borreliosis is 
clinically suspected. </p>

<p>The serological findings in all cases showed no signifi-
cant qualitative changes. Among patients with early manifes-
tations, the Borrelia-LTT that were negative after antibiotic 
treatment were again weakly positive in only three cases 
(clinical manifestations were diffuse arthromyalgia and, in 
one case, painful swelling of an ankle); otherwise, the LTT 
results in this group were stable negatives (Table 5a ). </p>

<p>Patients with late borreliosis (Table 5b) showed in 16 of 
18 cases intermittent multiple increases in SI values, associ-
ated with a clinical increase in symptoms in each case. After 
antibiotic treatment, the SI values decreased again. These 
"peaks" were also observed after the Borrelia-LTT had be-
come negative. </p>

<p>Only 3 patients (No. 3, 11 and 12) showed a reactivation 
after antibiotic treatment. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
In order to investigate the diagnostic value of the Borre-
lia-LTT, we performed several in vitro investigations and re-
evaluated patient data and analytical values of patients which </p>

<p>Table 3. Number of Positive Reactions to the 4 Borrelia Antigens in Patients with Positive Borrelia LTT </p>

<p>n 
(%) </p>

<p>SI &gt; 3 for all four Borrelia antigens 
162 
(47.6) </p>

<p>SI &gt;3 in 3 lysate antigens, OspC &lt; 3 
76 
(22.3) </p>

<p>SI &gt; 3 in 2 lysate antigens, OspC &gt; 3 
63 
(18.5) </p>

<p>SI &gt; 3 in 2 lysate antigens, OspC &lt; 3 
24 
(7.1) </p>

<p>SI &gt; 3 in 1 lysate antigen, OspC &gt; 3 
15 
(4.5) </p>

<p>(n = 340) </p>

<p>Table 4. Comparison of Borrelia-LTT in Patients with Early Versus Late Borreliosis Manifestations </p>

<p>Early Manifestations (n = 140), Before Therapy SI &gt; 5 
n 
(%) </p>

<p>SI &lt; 2 
109 
(77.8) </p>

<p>SI &gt;2 &lt; 3 
20 
(14.3) </p>

<p>SI &gt;3 &lt;5 
9 
(6.4) </p>

<p>after antibiotic therapy </p>

<p>SI &gt;5 
2 
(1.5) </p>

<p>Late Manifestations (n= 90), Before Treatment SI &gt; 5 
n 
(%) </p>

<p>SI &lt; 2 
20 
(223) </p>

<p>SI &gt;2 &lt; 3 
28 
(31.0) </p>

<p>SI &gt;3 &lt;5 
32 
(35.6) </p>

<p>after antibiotic therapy </p>

<p>SI &gt; 5 
10 
(11.1) </p>

<p>(SI &lt;2 =negative; SI &gt;2&lt;3 = borderline, SI &gt;3&lt;5 = weak positive; SI &gt;5 = positive) </p>

<p>Lymphocyte Transformation Test for Borreliosis </p>

<p>The Open Neurology Journal, 2012, Volume 6 109 </p>

<p>Table 5a. Borrelia-LTT Follow-Up Studies (Early Manifestations) </p>

<p>Month 
0 
3 
6 
9 
12 </p>

<p>patient 1 
6.8 
&lt;2* 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 </p>

<p>patient 2 
9,6 
&lt;2* 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 </p>

<p>patient 3 
10.9 
&lt;2* 
&lt;2 
6.8 
&lt;2* </p>

<p>patient 4 
12.6 
&lt;2* 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 </p>

<p>patient 5 
10.2 
&lt;2* 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 </p>

<p>patient 6 
8.4 
&lt;2* 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 </p>

<p>patient 7 
11.8 
&lt;3* 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 </p>

<p>patient 8 
8.8 
&lt;2* 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 </p>

<p>patient 9 
19.6 
&lt;3* 
&lt;3 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 </p>

<p>patient 10 
13.4 
&lt;3* 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 </p>

<p>patient 11 
6.5 
&lt;2* 
&lt;2 
4.2 
&lt;2* </p>

<p>patient 12 
10.2 
&lt;3* 
4.8 
&lt;3* 
&lt;2 </p>

<p>(* 4-6 weeks after antibiotic therapy) 
Shown are the results of follow-up studies with the Borrelia-LTT for 12 patients with early manifestations of borreliosis (mainly E. migrans) over a period of 1 
year from the date of initial diagnosis before therapy (the highest of the 4 respective SI values of the Borrelia-LTT is given). 
Only 3 patients (No. 3, 11 and 12) showed a reactivation after antibiotic treatment. </p>

<p>Table 5b. Borrelia-LTT Follow-up Studies (Late Manifestations) </p>

<p>Month 
0 
3 
6 
9 
12 </p>

<p>patient 1 
12.2 
&lt;2* 
4.8 
&lt;2* 
4.2 </p>

<p>patient 2 
9.4 
3.3* 
&lt;2* 
5.8 
&lt;2* </p>

<p>patient 3 
9.8 
4.8* 
&lt;2* 
6.2* 
3.9* </p>

<p>patient 4 
10.6 
5.2* 
3.5* 
&lt;2* 
6.4 </p>

<p>patient 5 
8.5 
&lt;2* 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 </p>

<p>patient 6 
16.2 
6.0* 
3.2* 
7.2 
4.8* </p>

<p>patient 7 
14.8 
&lt;3* 
&lt;2 
4.9 
&lt;2* </p>

<p>patient 8 
10.8 
6.2* 
3.8* 
8.2 
3.6* </p>

<p>patient 9 
6.3 
&lt;2* 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 </p>

<p>patient 10 
8.2 
&lt;2* 
&lt;2 
5.6 
&lt;2* </p>

<p>patient 11 
6.6 
&lt;2* 
&lt;2 
3.8 
3.1* </p>

<p>patient 12 
9.1 
&lt;3* 
4.2 
3.6 
&lt;2* </p>

<p>patient 13 
7.8 
4.8 
4.2* 
&lt;3* 
3.8 </p>

<p>patient 14 
6.9 
&lt;2* 
3.6 
&lt;2* 
4.9 </p>

<p>patient 15 
9.6 
&lt;2* 
5.4 
&lt;2* 
3.1 </p>

<p>patient 16 
12.1 
4.2 
3.1* 
&lt;2* 
&lt;2 </p>

<p>patient 17 
14.4 
5.4 
4.8* 
&lt;3* 
4.5 </p>

<p>patient 18 
10.6 
&lt;3* 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 
&lt;2 </p>

<p>(* 4-6 weeks after antibiotic therapy) 
Shown are the results of follow-up studies with the Borrelia-LTT over a period of 1 year in 18 patients with late manifestations of borreliosis (an infection 
more than 2 years previously). Only 3 patients (No. 5, 9 and 10) showed no reactivations after initial treatment with antibiotics. </p>

<p>were investigated routinely in our laboratory. </p>

<p>A Borrelia-LTT with one recombinant antigen and lysate 
antigens of the three relevant Borrelia species (B. sensu stric-</p>

<p>to, B. afzelii and B.garinii) was developed and tested. The 
results achieved thus allow us to answer the following ques-
tions: </p>

<p>110 The Open Neurology Journal, 2012, Volume 6 </p>

<p>Baehr et al. </p>

<p>1. In patients with clinical borreliosis prior to the start of 
antibiotic therapy, there is a high degree of correspondence 
between the results of Borrelia serology and Borrelia-LTT 
studies. </p>

<p>2. The sensitivity of the Borrelia-LTT is 89.4% for clini-
cally active borreliosis, with a specificity of 98,7%. </p>

<p>3. The lysate antigens of the three species of Borrelia and 
the recombinant OspC cross-reacted in the Borrelia-LTT. 
Therefore, it is not possible to determine the respective spe-
cies involved. </p>

<p>4. The negative results in clinically healthy seropositive 
subjects and the studies before and after antibiotic treatment 
of patients with clinically active disease are a strong indica-
tion that the Borrelia-LTT with lymphocytes from peripheral 
blood is positive only when the immune system is currently 
being stimulated by Borrelia. The proof that the test responds 
only during an active Borrelia infection could only be pro-
vided by the simultaneous detection of Borrelia by culture or 
Borrelia PCR (Borrelia DNA detection). In our patient co-
hort, this was demonstrated in only 6 out of the 32 cases test-
ed by Borrelia PCR. </p>

<p>The results of our study differ in part from some pub-
lished data which show a low specificity of the Borrelia-LTT 
[24, 25]. This is very likely due to methodology. The addi-
tion of interferon-α to the cell culture medium inhibits non-
specific proliferation of lymphocytes and promotes the func-
tion of antigen-presenting cells. This improves the discrimi-
natory power of positive and negative LTT results, even 
though the SI values of the positive reactions and the blank 
values are lower than in assays without interferon [23]. An-
other modification is the use of polymyxin B for the elimina-
tion of nonspecific activating lipid groups from the Borrelia 
lysates and traces of LPS from the rOspC expressed in E. 
coli. In this way, common, nonspecific borderline and weak 
positive LTT reactions were eliminated (data not shown). </p>

<p>Of great importance are the selection and especially the 
dosage of the Borrelia test antigens. Lysate antigens, kindly 
provided by Seramun (Heidesee), were specially purified for 
the ELISA test and showed no positive reactions with nega-
tive control sera. Nevertheless, the presence of Borrelia-
nonspecific proteins in the lysates that may cross-react with 
other bacterial species may be unavoidable. </p>

<p>Our own experience in the development of antigen-
specific LTT applications show that the "specific diagnostic 
width" of the test antigens is particularly important. For the 
Borrelia-LTT, therefore, it was necessary to consider wheth-
er those concentrations of Borrelia test antigens which cause 
barely any positive/borderline LTT reactions in 20 seronega-
tive subjects, are sufficient to detect Borrelia-specific helper 
cells in the blood of patients with clinical borreliosis. </p>

<p>Obviously, the advantage of the Borrelia-LTT presented 
here is the use of a mixture of Borrelia-specific antigens in 
the Borrelia lysates. This is confirmed by the calculated sen-
sitivity of 89,6% and specificity of about 98,7% for seroposi-
tive clinical borreliosis prior to antibiotic therapy. In con-
trast, in preliminary tests with all recombinant Borrelia pro-
teins (p93, p39, p34, p25, p18) available to us, only the 
rOspC (p25) was proven to be a suitable test antigen for the 
Borrelia-LTT. For all other proteins, the "specific diagnostic </p>

<p>width" was too small (results of these preliminary tests are 
not shown). Nevertheless, the use of lysate antigens in LTT 
studies is, in principle, problematic, since each new antigen 
batch has to be tested in parallel with the previously used 
antigen batch. Therefore, the studies presented here were 
carried out with two different batches of antigen, which was 
especially important for the LTT results. The results 
achieved so far with lysate antigens, however, encourage us 
to test mixtures of recombinant antigens or Borrelia antigens 
purified from lysates in the LTT in the future in order to 
achieve well-defined reproducible test antigens. </p>

<p>A strong argument for the Borrelia-specific LTT reac-
tions to the test antigens used is the fact that the positive re-
actions following antibiotic treatment were always regres-
sive, and in early manifestations of Lyme borreliosis, they 
were predominantly negative. These results correspond to 
observations of other authors [12, 14, 16, 21], but also con-
tradict other reports [24, 25, 26]. The discrepancies are very 
likely due to the LTT method modified by us and the differ-
ent antigens. According to our results, it is very likely that 
Borrelia-specific T helper cells, after overcoming the active 
infection (i.e., elimination of Borrelia antigens), migrate 
mainly from the bloodstream into the lymph nodes or spleen, 
and therefore their numbers in the blood are lower than the 
detection limit for the LTT. An allergen elimination test has 
the same effect in appropriate LTT applications in patients 
with type IV allergies to medications (non-published per-
sonal observation). Since the total number of T cells in the 
blood is relatively constant in individuals and even decreases 
with age, it is justified to assume that Borrelia-specific T 
cells circulate only during an active confrontation of the im-
mune system with appropriate antigens in large numbers in 
the blood. </p>

<p>A Borrelia-LTT test that has become negative is not evi-
dence, however, that a Borrelia infection has been cured. 
This was demonstrated in follow-up studies over a one year 
period in patients with late borreliosis. Borrelia that persist in 
spite of antibiotic treatment, which have been described mul-
tiple times [27, 28, 29, 30], are very likely responsible for 
this phenomenon. After reactivation of the infection with 
renewed antigen presence, apparently Borrelia-specific T 
cells are rapidly mobilized from the lymphoid organs. The 
clinical symptoms and the course of the LTT reactions sug-
gest that these patients could suffer from persistent or latent 
borreliosis with phases of reactivation. For this reason doubts 
are arising about the prevailing opinion that a single, con-
cerning dose and duration appropriate, antibiotic treatment is 
sufficient to eliminate the Borrelia completely. </p>

<p>We were able to confirm an important piece of informa-
tion from Krause et al [12] on the beneficial effect of autolo-
gous serum for Borrelia-LTT. It is very likely that the anti-
bodies contained in the serum form immune complexes with 
Borrelia antigens and thus promote uptake by antigen-
presenting cells. </p>

<p>In summary, the following conclusions can be made for 
the use of the Borrelia-LTT: </p>

<p>1. Except for early manifestations of borreliosis (2 to 6 
weeks after infection), the detection of Borrelia-specific an-
tibodies to confirm the clinical diagnosis of borreliosis is </p>

<p>Lymphocyte Transformation Test for Borreliosis </p>

<p>The Open Neurology Journal, 2012, Volume 6 111 </p>

<p>often sufficient. Only in the case of an unclear clinical pic-
ture of borreliosis coupled with negative or borderline serol-
ogy the Borrelia-LTT can be beneficial in order to make a 
decision regarding the indication for antibiotic treatment 
since it also exhibits a clear positive reaction in the case of 
early manifestations. </p>

<p>2. In the case of infections in the more remote past with an 
ambiguous clinical picture and positive Borrelia serology, 
the Borrelia-LTT provides an important indication as wheth-
er an active Borrelia infection could exist. The Borrelia se-
rology is not suitable in this case, and the direct pathogen 
detection methods (PCR or culture) are also not sufficient for 
answering this question due to their low sensitivity. It must 
be noted, however, that it is not only the results of the Borre-
lia-LTT that are important for the indication for antibiotic 
treatment, but also the medical history and the current clini-
cal picture. </p>

<p>3. It has been shown that the Borrelia-LTT can be used to 
evaluate the success of antibiotic treatment, although the 
clinical course is also particularly important. However, the 
symptoms of disseminated borreliosis may persist after suc-
cessful treatment for some time, however. An LTT follow-up 
examination is reasonable, at the earliest, 4 to 6 weeks after 
the completion of therapy. This interval is necessary be-
cause, on the one hand, possibly surviving Borrelia can be-
come active during this time and, on the other hand, Borre-
lia-specific T cells persist in the blood for some time after 
elimination of the antigens. The Borrelia-LTT should not be 
performed during antibiotic therapy because, in our experi-
ence, the result will be negative, but soon after discontinua-
tion of treatment, it may again become positive. </p>

<p>Criticism is often based on the frequency of false-
positive results of the Borrelia-LTT (5). This problem con-
tinues to exist unless there is sufficient testing of the antigen 
specificity of the Borrelia-LTT. In the case of frequently 
false positive reactions, the dose of the test antigens is too 
high. Currently, since there is no available gold standard for 
the laboratory diagnosis of borreliosis or its exclusion, the 
Borrelia-LTT can only be validated according to clinical and 
serological findings. Nevertheless, there are still gaps in the 
validation that we conducted. For instance, it was only pos-
sible in individual cases to examine patients with active 
syphilis (n = 3) or leptospirosis infection (n = 2) for potential 
cross reactivity. In these few cases, there was no evidence of 
such cross-reactivity in the Borrelia-LTT. Allergies, auto-
immune diseases and acute, persistent and latent viral infec-
tions (including HIV, EBV, CMV, VZV) have now been 
excluded, by further investigations, as a possible cause of 
false-positive reactions (unpublished data). </p>

<p>The Borrelia-LTT cannot provide any information on 
whether a patient has ever had a Borrelia infection. This 
question is largely answered only by serology. Our studies 
presented here and the results of other authors [12, 14, 16, 
21], particularly the work of Valentine-Thon et al. on LTT-
MELISA [31], provide good arguments that the positive Bor-
relia-LTT indicates an active borreliosis which, however, 
could only be definitely proven in conjunction with positive 
detection of Borrelia. However, we succeeded in doing so in 
only 3 seronegative patients with erythema migrans using 
positive Borrelia-PCR in the blood (unpublished data). </p>

<p>The in vitro antigen-induced lymphocyte proliferation is 
the approved cellular immunological method for detecting 
antigen-specific memory T helper cells. In addition and prior 
to clonal lymphocyte proliferation, however, a series of im-
munologically relevant genes for both cell surface markers 
and especially cytokines such as interleukin-2 and interferon-
γ are activated, which in turn are used as the basis for newer 
cellular immunological laboratory methods. An example is 
the QuantiFERON test (interferon-γ stimulation) performed 
to detect a Mycobacter tuberculosis infection [32]. However, 
a distinction between a latent and florid infection is not pos-
sible with this test, however. Currently, the ELISPOT test 
(quantitative determination of cytokine-producing lympho-
cytes) is used in vaccine research in particular, and is also 
being tested in patients with a Borrelia infection. According 
to the previously published results by Forsberg et al. and our 
own experiences, even though seropositive individuals are 
detected by the ELISPOT assay, a differentiation between 
symptomatic and asymptomatic Borrelia infections was not 
possible [33-35]. The advantage of antigen-specific cyto-
kine-stimulation assays would be that, while 6 days are re-
quired for an antigen-specific LTT test, the incubation period 
for the cytokine assay is only about 24 hours. It should be 
noted, however, that the biology on which these cellular im-
munological test systems are based is very different. While 
in the LTT setting T helper memory cells are clearly identi-
fied as cytokine producers, also other lymphocyte subpopu-
lations like NK cells, and (depending on the cytokine) also 
monocytes are being taken into consideration as cytokine 
producers. However, cellular short-term stimulation methods 
are rather sensitive to nonspecific activations, while, in the 
LTT such influences dominate only during the first 48 to 72 
hours, and thus have virtually disappeared after 6 days at the 
time the cellular proliferation is measured. For the particular 
issue of florid or non-active Borrelia infection, the situation 
is even more difficult since there is usually no gold standard 
available (i.e., patients with positive detection of live Borre-
lia). In this difficult situation, a new method should always 
be validated in comparison with an extensively proven 
method. The aim of our investigations were therefore to 
evaluate the results previously obtained with an optimized 
Borrelia-LTT in order to provide a basis for necessary com-
parative prospective studies with cellular immunological 
methods based on antigen-specific gene activation or cyto-
kine stimulation. In our opinion, the Borrelia-LTT presented 
here fulfills the associated requirements. </p>

<p>Finally, it should be emphasized again that the primacy 
for the diagnosis of borreliosis remains with the medical 
history and clinical symptoms. In second place is the deter-
mination of Borrelia-specific antibodies in the blood or cere-
bral synovial fluid. With the Borrelia-LTT another diagnos-
tic tool is available that can help to clarify issues for the in-
dication of antibiotic treatment. The Borrelia-LTT is particu-
larly important, however, for assessing the effects of therapy 
if the initial findings are positive, as they should prove nega-
tive four weeks after the end of therapy, or at least should 
prove to have declined significantly. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST 
The authors confirm that this article content has no con-
flicts of interest. </p>

<p>112 The Open Neurology Journal, 2012, Volume 6 </p>

<p>Baehr et al. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS 
None declared. </p>



<p>Received: April 28, 2012 
Revised: June 22, 2012 
Accepted: July 02, 2012 </p>

<p>© Beahr et al.; Licensee Bentham Open. </p>

<p>This is an open access article licensed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons. 
org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits unrestricted, non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the work is properly cited. </p>

</text></tei>