<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3404480" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>SUMMARY </p>

<p>Global coverage of infant Haemophilus influenzae type b (Hib) vaccination has increased 
considerably during the past decade, partly due to GAVI Alliance donations of the vaccine to 
low-income countries. In settings where large numbers of children receive only one or two vaccine 
doses rather than the recommended three doses, dose-specific efficacy estimates are needed to 
predict impact. The objective of this meta-analysis is to determine Hib vaccine efficacy against 
different clinical outcomes after receiving one, two or three doses of vaccine. Studies were eligible 
for inclusion if a prospective, controlled design had been used to evaluate commercially available 
Hib conjugate vaccines. Eight studies were included. Pooled vaccine efficacies against invasive 
Hib disease after one, two or three doses of vaccine were 59 %, 92% and 93 %, respectively. The 
meta-analysis provides robust estimates for use in decision-analytical models designed to predict 
the impact of Hib vaccine. </p>

<p>Haemophilus influenzae type b (Hib) is an encap-
sulated, Gram-negative coccobacillus that can cause 
childhood meningitis, pneumonia and a number of 
rarer forms of disease, such as epiglottitis, septicaemia 
and cellulitis [1]. Hib conjugate vaccines have gradu-
ally been introduced into more and more routine 
programmes since the early 1990s. While 89 countries 
used the vaccine in 2004, the number had increased to </p>

<p>172 countries by 2011 [2]. In low-and lower-middle-
income countries, introduction of the vaccine has to a 
large extent been facilitated by support from the 
GAVI Alliance [3]. 
The first Hib vaccine was produced in the early 
1970s and composed of purified Hib capsular poly-
saccharide. However, since this vaccine was only ef-
fective in children aged &gt;2 years it was not widely 
used [4]. More immunogenic vaccines were developed 
in the late 1980s by conjugating capsular poly-
saccharides to protein carriers. Four different Hib 
conjugate vaccines have been developed, diverging in 
the carrier protein, the method of conjugation, and 
in the structure and lengths of the polysaccharide </p>

<p>The online version of this article is published within an Open Access environment subject to the conditions of the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike licence &lt;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.5/&gt;. The written permission of 
Cambridge University Press must be obtained for commercial re-use. </p>

<p>* Author for correspondence: Dr U. K. Griffiths, Department of 
Global Health and Development, London School of Hygiene and 
Tropical Medicine, 15-17 Tavistock Place, London WC1H 9SH, 
UK. 
(Email: ulla.griffiths@lshtm.ac.uk) </p>

<p>Epidemiol. Infect. (2012), 140, 1343-1355. f Cambridge University Press 2012 
doi:10.1017/S0950268812000957 </p>

<p>polyribosolribitol phosphate (PRP) element [4]. The 
four vaccine types are known as PRP-D, PRP-OMP, 
HbOC and PRP-T. The PRP-D vaccine was licensed 
following a randomized controlled trial (RCT) in 
Finnish children [5], but when it subsequently proved 
ineffective in preventing Hib disease in Alaskan na-
tives [6], production was stopped. Hence, today only 
the other three vaccines are in use. While the World 
Health Organization does not differentiate between 
the three vaccines [7], they are not identical ; for ex-
ample, PRP-OMP induces a substantial antibody re-
sponse after a single dose while PRP-T and HbOC 
require two doses [8]. 
Vaccine efficacy is measured in RCTs with the 
aim of determining whether infection is reduced 
under ideal conditions designed to maximize disease 
detection [9]. The objective of this meta-analysis is 
to determine dose-specific efficacy of commercially 
available Hib vaccines against different clinical out-
comes. These estimates are important parameter va-
lues when modelling the impact and cost-effectiveness 
of Hib vaccine [10]. In simple models, the vaccine-
preventable disease burden is estimated as: </p>

<p>disease 
incidence 
r 
vaccine 
coverage (3 doses) 
r 
vaccine 
efficacy (3 doses) 
: </p>

<p>While such estimates will clearly exclude the potential 
indirect 'herd immunity ' benefits for unvaccinated 
children, they will also underestimate the direct im-
pact attributed to partially vaccinated children. In 
low-and lower-middle-income settings with weak 
health systems, many children receive only one or two 
vaccine doses rather than the recommended three. 
Since vaccine efficacy will be lower in these partially 
vaccinated children, dose-specific estimates of vaccine 
efficacy are required to improve estimates of expected 
vaccine impact. If possible, other factors, such as late 
vaccination, should also be incorporated into esti-
mates of the direct effect of a vaccination programme 
[11]. Moreover, with more new vaccines being intro-
duced, such as pneumococcal and rotavirus vaccines, 
the routine vaccination schedule is being questioned 
with regard to the appropriate age and timing of 
vaccination [12]. Pooled dose-specific efficacy esti-
mates from all RCTs are a crucial piece of infor-
mation needed to guide these considerations. 
One other meta-analysis of Hib vaccine RCTs was 
identified before the present review was started. 
Obonyo &amp; Lau searched the literature until 2005 
and included eight studies, two of which were of the 
PRP-D vaccine [13]. The pooled efficacy estimate </p>

<p>against invasive Hib disease was found to be 84 % 
[95 % confidence interval (CI) 70-99]. As is common 
in the reporting of vaccine trial results, few dose-spe-
cific values were presented. 
Vaccine effectiveness studies are designed to 
measure protectiveness under field conditions. These 
can either be a prospective cohort study, a case-
control study, or data can be accumulated retro-
spectively from routine surveillance. For establishing 
Hib vaccine effectiveness the case-control method, 
where a group of cases with the target outcome, most 
frequently Hib meningitis, is contrasted with a group 
of controls who did not develop the target outcome, is 
the most commonly used method [14]. An important 
challenge of case-control studies is, however, to pro-
duce convincing evidence that the vaccinated and 
unvaccinated populations are sufficiently alike in all 
relevant characteristics other than vaccination to 
allow a reasonable conclusion that the differences 
between groups are attributable to vaccine efficacy. 
A meta-analysis of Hib vaccine effectiveness studies 
was published by O'Loughlin et al. in 2010 [14]. 
Twenty-five studies, of which 14 were case-control 
studies, were identified. Three of the studies reported 
vaccine effectiveness against invasive Hib disease after 
three doses and the pooled estimate was 95 % (95 % 
CI 82-99). One of the conclusions from this review 
was that the effectiveness of Hib vaccine has been 
well documented and the need for more case-control 
studies is minimal [14]. </p>

<p>Search strategy and study selection </p>

<p>Recommendations of the Preferred Reporting Items 
for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) 
statement were used [15]. Studies were identified from 
the Cochrane Controlled Trials Register (CCTR) 
using the search term 'haemophilus vaccine ' in March 
2011. The CCTR is a bibliographical database of 
controlled trials systematically identified from Med-
line and EMBASE by contributors of the Cochrane 
Collaboration [16]. Reference lists in identified papers 
were checked and experts in the field were contacted 
to confirm that no studies had been missed. 
Studies were eligible for inclusion if they compared 
a commercially available Hib vaccine with placebo, if 
clinical endpoints were reported, and if participants 
had been allocated prospectively using random or 
quasi-random allocation. To maximize the amount of 
data available, quality measures were not used as ex-
clusion criteria. There were no language restrictions. </p>

<p> 
U. K. Griffiths and others </p>

<p>Data extraction and quality assessment were per-
formed by two authors independently (U.K.G. and 
A.C.). Extracted data included setting, type of Hib 
vaccine, schedule, dosage, duration, number of Hib 
disease cases according to study group, and total 
numbers of children in both groups. Cochrane's Risk 
of Bias tool was used to assess the methodological 
quality of the trials [17]. </p>

<p>Outcome measures </p>

<p>In most epidemiological studies of Hib disease, focus 
is solely placed on invasive disease, defined as the 
isolation of Hib from a sterile site such as the blood-
stream, synovial fluid or cerebrospinal fluid. Non-
invasive disease occurs when Hib has been isolated 
from a non-sterile site, such as an external ear or 
throat swab. All severe types of Hib diseases, such as 
pneumonia, meningitis, epiglottitis and sepsis, are in-
vasive. However, the aetiology of invasive pneumonia 
is intrinsically difficult to determine [18]. The only </p>

<p>method which would reliably determine the aetiology 
is culture of lung aspirate, but this procedure is 
invasive and not ethically feasible in all RCTs. 
Moreover, selection bias will occur if antibiotics are 
commonly used before seeking healthcare as this will 
markedly reduce the sensitivity of the lung aspirate 
test [19]. Blood culture is only useful when pneumonia 
is associated with bacteraemia, which is only in a 
fraction of cases. The yield from blood culture in 
patients with Hib pneumonia has ranged from 10 % 
to 30% [20, 21]. Hence, since there are currently no 
validated and specific methods for confirming the 
pathogen-specific bacterial aetiology of pneumonia, 
several non-specific pneumonia endpoints have been 
used in Hib vaccine RCTs. 
The following outcomes were included in the meta-
analysis : (i) confirmed invasive Hib disease, (ii) con-
firmed Hib meningitis, (iii) confirmed Hib pneu-
monia, (iv) clinical meningitis, (v) radiologically (or 
chest X-ray) confirmed pneumonia, (vi) hospitalized 
pneumonia and (vii) clinical pneumonia. In addition, 
efficacy estimates were calculated according to the 
number of doses of Hib vaccine received as either (i) 
only one dose, (ii) only two doses or (iii) three doses. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>All statistical analyses were performed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 11</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">StataCorp.</rs>., USA). Trial results were ex-
pressed as percent vaccine efficacy, defined as 1 -
relative risk. Estimates were pooled using a random-
effects model applying the DerSimonian &amp; Laird 
approach [22]. Heterogeneity was assessed using the 
x 
2 test with a P value of &lt;0 . 10 indicating statistical 
significance and by the I 
2 statistic, which measures the 
percentage of variation attributable to heterogeneity. 
A value of 0% indicates no observed heterogeneity 
and larger values show increasing heterogeneity [23]. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Characteristics of eligible trials </p>

<p>The search strategy yielded 493 references (Fig. 1). 
After removing duplicates, 474 titles and abstracts 
were screened and 459 papers excluded. The most 
common reason for exclusion at this stage was that 
the study reported only safety and immunogenicity of 
the vaccine with no clinical endpoints. Fifteen papers 
were retrieved for full-text review and seven of these 
were excluded. One of the excluded studies was a </p>

<p>493 articles identified from 
Cochrane Clinical Trial Registry </p>

<p>474 articles screened after 
duplicates removed </p>

<p>459 articles excluded </p>

<p>-268 no clinical endpoints 
-147 not Hib 
-17 adult vaccination 
-13 polysaccharide vaccine 
-12 reviews 
-2 PRP-D vaccine trials </p>

<p>15 articles assessed for 
eligibility </p>

<p>7 articles excluded </p>

<p>-1 letter 
-1 carriage study 
-1 PRP-D vaccine trial 
-1 descriptive study 
-2 case-control studies 
-1 HBoC study without a 
prospective control group </p>

<p>8 articles included in 
meta-analysis </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Study selection. </p>

<p>The efficacy of Hib vaccine : a systematic review </p>

<p>
large, Finnish prospective study where children 
born on even-numbered days received HbOC vaccine 
and those born on uneven-numbered days received 
PRP-D vaccine [24]. Vaccine efficacy was estimated 
by comparing the number of Hib disease cases during 
the study period with the number expected based on 
historical routine surveillance data. The study was 
excluded because the comparison group was histori-
cal, not prospective. 
Six of the eight included papers evaluated PRP-T, 
one HbOC and one PRP-OMP vaccines (see Table 1). 
The studies by Lagos and Levine analysed the same 
trial participants. Three of the studies were from the 
USA and the remaining from England, Chile, The 
Gambia and Indonesia. One of the US studies was 
conducted in a Navajo Indian reservation, targeting a 
group with one of the highest incidences of Hib dis-
ease in the world [25]. In this trial only two doses of 
Hib vaccine were administered, while three doses were 
evaluated in the seven remaining studies. The study by 
Vadheim ended prematurely due to inclusion of the 
HbOC vaccine in the US routine vaccination schedule 
while the study was ongoing, so no vaccine efficacy 
estimates were reported because the sample sizes were 
too small to achieve sufficient power. In all the stud-
ies, follow-up stopped after a specified time period. 
The study by Booy had the shortest follow-up time 
and the study by Mulholland the longest, with the 
oldest children being aged 18 and 30 months, re-
spectively, when the studies ended (Table 1). 
Outcome measures used in the trials are summar-
ized in Table 2. The outcome measure used by most of 
the studies was invasive Hib disease. While all types of 
Hib diseases are included within the invasive disease 
group, meningitis is likely to be the most frequent type 
of syndrome detected. In the study by Gessner, the 
only outcome measure that included aetiological 
confirmation was Hib meningitis. The studies by 
Booy, Levine and Vadheim did not report vaccine 
efficacy for less than three vaccine doses. 
Clinical, non-specific pneumonia outcomes were 
included in the RCTs from Chile, The Gambia and 
Indonesia. Since pneumonia disease incidence is con-
siderably less in high-income than low-income coun-
tries, non-specific pneumonia endpoints were not 
relevant to include in the RCTs from England and the 
USA. However, in low-income countries prevention 
of pneumonia may be the primary argument for in-
troducing Hib vaccine, so it was crucial for the studies 
in these countries to measure efficacy against pneu-
monia. 
Table 1. Trial characteristics </p>

<p>First author 
(ref.) </p>

<p>Year 
recruitment </p>

<p>started </p>

<p>Location </p>

<p>Type of Hib 
vaccine </p>

<p>Vaccine 
manufacturer 
Hib vaccine 
schedule (weeks) </p>

<p>No. of children 
enrolled in study </p>

<p>Age when 
follow-up ended 
(months) </p>

<p>Black [41] </p>

<p>1988 </p>

<p>California, USA </p>

<p>PRP-HbOC 
Praxis Biologics </p>

<p>8, 16, 24 </p>

<p>61,080 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Booy [42] </p>

<p>1991 
Oxford region, England </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>Pasteur Me´rieux </p>

<p>8, 12, 16 </p>

<p>27,860 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Gessner [27] </p>

<p>1998 </p>

<p>Lombok, Indonesia </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>Aventis Pasteur </p>

<p>6, 10, 14 </p>

<p>55,073 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Lagos [43] </p>

<p>1992 </p>

<p>Santiago, Chile </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>Pasteur Me´rieux </p>

<p>8, 16, 24 </p>

<p>76,533 </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>Levine [44] </p>

<p>1992 </p>

<p>Santiago, Chile </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>Pasteur Me´rieux </p>

<p>8, 16, 24 </p>

<p>21,420 </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Mulholland [21] </p>

<p>1993 
Western region of The Gambia </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>Pasteur Me´rieux </p>

<p>8, 12, 16 </p>

<p>42,848 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Santosham [25] </p>

<p>1988 
Navajo Indian Reservation, USA </p>

<p>PRP-OMP </p>

<p>Merck </p>

<p>6, 12 </p>

<p>5,166 </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Vadheim [45] </p>

<p>1989 </p>

<p>California, USA </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>Pasteur Me´rieux </p>

<p>8, 16, 24 </p>

<p>10,317 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p> 
U. K. Griffiths and others </p>

<p>Methodological quality of trials and risk of bias </p>

<p>The domains specified in Cochrane's Risk of Bias tool 
are summarized in Table 3. Risks of bias due to ran-
domization, sequence generation and allocation con-
cealment were relatively low in all the studies. Even 
though two studies were not randomized, it seems 
unlikely that the results would be biased for this 
reason. However, four of the studies were not blinded 
and this leads to risk of bias. In the three studies 
where confirmed Hib disease was the only endpoint, 
the risk of bias would most likely be low because the 
microbiologists undertaking the tests for Hib were not 
aware of the child's vaccination status. However, in 
the Levine study, radiological and hospitalized pneu-
monia were the chosen endpoints and assessments of 
these were made from hospital records of children 
with known vaccination status, leading to moderate 
risk of bias. With regard to inclusion of all random-
ized participants, all the studies suffer from high risk 
of bias due to the inherent difficulties of diagnosing 
Hib. Even in the studies with enhanced surveillance, it 
is possible that not all Hib cases were detected. The 
risk of detection bias is especially large in the three 
studies with non-specific (or all-cause) pneumonia as 
an outcome. 
An additional risk of bias in the studies using 
non-specific pneumonia outcomes is that estimated 
Hib vaccine efficacy will vary with the relative pro-
portion of Hib pneumonia occurring during the study 
period. Since many of the other pathogens that cause 
pneumonia are known to be seasonal, such as for in-
stance respiratory synical virus (RSV) or influenza, 
this could be a problem. Hib vaccine efficacy against 
clinical pneumonia would for instance be less in a 
year with a RSV pneumonia outbreak than in a year 
with low RSV incidence [26]. Since all the trials 
lasted for more than one year, seasonal fluctuations 
might have been evened out to some extent, but 
the risk of this bias is apparent. This is also an im-
portant limitation to bear in mind when general-
izing the efficacy values to other settings where 
the relative proportion of Hib pneumonia may be 
different. 
The risk of publication bias is considered low for 
vaccine trials. Since these are large trials involving 
thousands of children and lasting several years, there 
is strong pressure on investigators and vaccine manu-
facturers to publish the results. It is thus highly un-
likely that any Hib vaccine RCTs have taken place 
without being published. 
Table 2. Outcome measures of included studies </p>

<p>Author (ref.) </p>

<p>Confirmed Hib 
invasive disease </p>

<p>Confirmed Hib 
meningitis </p>

<p>Confirmed Hib 
pneumonia </p>

<p>Clinical 
meningitis* </p>

<p>Radiological 
pneumonia </p>

<p>Clinical 
pneumonia </p>

<p>Hospitalised 
pneumonia </p>

<p>No. of doses … 1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Black [41] </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>Booy [42] </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>Gessner [27]* </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>Levine [44] </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>Lagos [43] </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>Mulholland [21] </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>Santosham [25] </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>Vadheim [45] </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>No. of studies </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>* Gessner included three definitions for clinical meningitis : possible, probable and hospitalized meningitis. </p>

<p>The efficacy of Hib vaccine : a systematic review </p>

<p>
Table 3. Assessment of risk of bias in the included trials </p>

<p>First author 
(ref.) </p>

<p>Unit of 
randomization 
Sequence generation 
Blinding 
Allocation concealment 
Outcome reporting </p>

<p>Black [41] 
Individual 
Placebo group was 
refusers and children 
born on the first 
5 days of a month </p>

<p>No, but microbiologists 
performing tests for Hib 
were unaware of 
vaccination status </p>

<p>n.a. 
Enhanced surveillance to detect 
all Hib patients treated in 
the study area </p>

<p>Booy [42] 
Cluster 
Hib vaccine districts 
determined from 
availability of 
computer systems </p>

<p>No, but microbiologists 
performing tests for Hib 
were unaware of 
vaccination status </p>

<p>n.a. 
Enhanced surveillance to detect 
all Hib patients treated in 
the study area </p>

<p>Gessner [27] 
Cluster 
Random 
Double blinding 
Vaccine vials identical 
except four colour codes; 
two for Hib and two for placebo. 
Code in a locked vault </p>

<p>Education for diagnosis and 
referral. Young women in every 
village to identify children with 
pneumonia and get them to hospital. 
Families reimbursed costs 
Lagos [43] 
Cluster 
Random 
No, but microbiologists 
performing tests for Hib 
were unaware of 
vaccination status </p>

<p>n.a. 
Active surveillance at 11 hospitals 
in Santiago. Bacteriology laboratory 
reports reviewed weekly </p>

<p>Levine [44] 
Cluster 
Random 
No 
n.a. 
Retrospective review of five 
ICD-9 pneumonia 
discharge diagnoses 
Mulholland [21] 
Individual 
Random 
Double blinding 
Five vaccine vial codes used 
for Hib and five others for 
placebo. Only safety monitoring 
group knew the code </p>

<p>Study children presenting to 
health centres due to any illness 
referred to study physician </p>

<p>Santosham [25] 
Cluster 
Random 
Double blinding 
Vaccine and placebo vials had 
similar appearances. Code not 
known until end of study </p>

<p>Active and passive 
surveillance throughout 
study area 
Vadheim [45] 
Individual 
Random 
Double blinding 
No details given on method used 
Active and passive surveillance 
throughout study area </p>

<p>n.a., Not available. </p>



<p>U. K. Griffiths and others </p>

<p>Vaccine efficacy </p>

<p>The pooled efficacy estimates against confirmed, in-
vasive Hib disease following three, two and one dose 
are 93 % (95 % CI 83-97), 92% (95 % CI 69-98) and 
59 % (95 % CI x20 to 86), respectively (Fig. 2). There 
is no heterogeneity in the studies for three and two 
doses and only low heterogeneity for one dose 
(I 
2 =28 . 5 %), which is attributable to the Santosham 
study of the PRP-OMP vaccine reporting consider-
ably higher efficacy than the two other studies. 
The pooled one-dose estimate of the trials using 
the PRP-T and the HbOC vaccines, respectively, is 
47 % (95 % CI x28 to 70) with no heterogeneity 
(I 
2 =0 . 0 %). The children in the vaccine groups who 
experienced Hib disease after one or two doses re-
mained incompletely immunized during the course of 
the studies. Hence, the cases did not occur during the 
inter-vaccination intervals. 
For confirmed Hib meningitis there is no hetero-
geneity in any of the dose-specific estimates, but due 
to the relatively small sample sizes, the confidence in-
tervals are wide for one and two doses (Fig. 3). 
Moreover, since the Santosham trial only estimated 
one-and two-dose efficacy, the pooled value for three 
doses (88 %, 95 % CI 46-97) is less than for two doses 
(92 %, 95% CI 37-99). The pooled one-dose estimate 
is 62% (95 % CI x29 to 89). </p>

<p>Data on confirmed Hib pneumonia were only 
available from the Mulholland and Santosham stu-
dies, and Santosham did not identify any cases fol-
lowing two doses. The Mulholland midpoint efficacy 
estimates of both two and three doses were 91 % 
(95 % CI x66 to 99) and the pooled estimate between 
Mulholland and Santosham following one dose was 
67 % (95 % CI x44 to 93). 
Vaccine efficacy against radiological pneumonia 
with three doses was 22% in both the Levine and 
Mulholland studies, but the result was negative in the 
study by Gessner, causing large heterogeneity 
(I 
2 =68 . 9 %) (Fig. 4). Hence, the pooled estimate has 
limited validity. The pooled estimate without the 
Gessner study was 22% (95 % CI 6-35) with no het-
erogeneity (I 
2 =0 . 0 %). 
Hib vaccine efficacy against hospitalized pneu-
monia following three doses of vaccine was reported 
by Gessner and Levine (Fig. 4). There is, however, 
also large heterogeneity between these two studies 
and the pooled estimate is not meaningful. While 
Levine found a vaccine efficacy of 26% (95 % CI 
7-41), Gessner only estimated it as 2 % (95 % CI x8 
to 10). 
Clinical pneumonia efficacy after three doses was 
reported by Gessner and Mulholland and found to 
be 4 % (95 % CI 1-7) in both studies (Fig. 4). 
However, due to the larger number of cases detected </p>

<p>Three doses </p>

<p>Black [41] </p>

<p>Booy [42] </p>

<p>Lagos [43] </p>

<p>Mulholland [21] </p>

<p>Vadheim [45] </p>

<p>Subtotal (I 
2 = 0·0%, p = 0·970) </p>

<p>Two doses only </p>

<p>Black [41] </p>

<p>Mulholland [21] </p>

<p>Santosham [25] </p>

<p>Subtotal (I 
2 = 0·0%, p = 0·972) </p>

<p>One dose only </p>

<p>Black [41] </p>

<p>Mulholland [21] </p>

<p>Santosham [25] </p>

<p>Subtotal (I 
2 = 28·5%, p = 0·247) </p>

<p>Author </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>UK </p>

<p>Chile </p>

<p>Gambia </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>Gambia </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>Gambia </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>Country </p>

<p>HBoC </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>HBoC </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>PRP-OMP </p>

<p>HBoC </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>PRP-OMP </p>

<p>Type 
of Hib 
vaccine </p>

<p>12/21232 </p>

<p>18/13320 </p>

<p>25/36741 </p>

<p>19/17919 </p>

<p>3/5106 </p>

<p>77/94318 </p>

<p>6/4724 </p>

<p>10/2349 </p>

<p>14/2105 </p>

<p>30/9178 </p>

<p>4/4968 </p>

<p>9/1098 </p>

<p>8/505 </p>

<p>21/6571 </p>

<p>Events, 
control </p>

<p>10·30 </p>

<p>20·30 </p>

<p>39·68 </p>

<p>20·35 </p>

<p>9·37 </p>

<p>100·00 </p>

<p>20·12 </p>

<p>39·41 </p>

<p>40·47 </p>

<p>100·00 </p>

<p>35·36 </p>

<p>51·95 </p>

<p>12·69 </p>

<p>100·00 </p>

<p>% 
Weight </p>

<p>96 (31 to 100) </p>

<p>94 (58 to 99) </p>

<p>92 (65 to 98) </p>

<p>95 (60 to 99) </p>

<p>86 (-171 to 99) </p>

<p>93 (83 to 97) </p>

<p>92 (-38 to 100) </p>

<p>90 (20 to 99) </p>

<p>93 (44 to 99) </p>

<p>92 (69 to 98) </p>

<p>24 (-238 to 83) </p>

<p>56 (-30 to 85) </p>

<p>94 (3 to 100) </p>

<p>59 (-20 to 86) </p>

<p>Vaccine 
efficacy (%) </p>

<p>0·04 (0·00-0·69) </p>

<p>0·06 (0·01-0·42) </p>

<p>0·08 (0·02-0·35) </p>

<p>0·05 (0·01-0·40) </p>

<p>0·14 (0·01-2·71) </p>

<p>0·07 (0·03-0·17) </p>

<p>0·08 (0·00-1·38) </p>

<p>0·10 (0·01-0·80) </p>

<p>0·07 (0·01-0·56) </p>

<p>0·08 (0·02-0·31) </p>

<p>0·76 (0·17-3·38) </p>

<p>0·44 (0·15-1·30) </p>

<p>0·06 (0·00-0·97) </p>

<p>0·41 (0·14-1·20) </p>

<p>RR (95% CI) </p>

<p>0/20800 </p>

<p>1/13320 </p>

<p>2/35264 </p>

<p>1/17794 </p>

<p>0/5211 </p>

<p>4/92389 </p>

<p>0/4681 </p>

<p>1/2299 </p>

<p>1/2056 </p>

<p>2/9036 </p>

<p>3/4919 </p>

<p>5/1397 </p>

<p>0/532 </p>

<p>8/6848 </p>

<p>Events, 
vaccine </p>

<p>Favours vaccine </p>

<p>1 
0·001 
10 </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Hib vaccine efficacy against confirmed invasive Hib disease. </p>

<p>The efficacy of Hib vaccine : a systematic review </p>

<p>
in Indonesia compared to The Gambia, the weight of 
the Gessner study in the pooled estimate is as high as 
92 . 3%. 
Clinical meningitis was only included in the study 
by Gessner and three different types were included ; 
probable, possible and hospitalized meningitis 
(Table 4). There were consistently less cases in the 
vaccinated compared to the placebo group and two of </p>

<p>the efficacy estimates were significant at the 95 % le-
vel. This indicated that, in the Indonesian environ-
ment, many cases of Hib meningitis were reaching a 
health facility, but either did not have a lumbar 
puncture or lumbar puncture was done and found to 
have the microscopic appearance of meningitis, but 
for reasons of specimen handling or microbiological 
procedures, Hib was not cultured. </p>

<p>Three doses </p>

<p>Gessner [27] </p>

<p>Mulholland [21] </p>

<p>Subtotal (I 
2 = 0·0%, p = 0·584) </p>

<p>Two doses only </p>

<p>Mulholland [21] </p>

<p>Santosham [25] </p>

<p>Subtotal (I 
2 = 0·0%, p = 0·759) </p>

<p>One dose only </p>

<p>Gessner [27] </p>

<p>Mulholland [21] </p>

<p>Santosham [25] </p>

<p>Subtotal (I 
2 = 0·0%, p = 0·479) </p>

<p>Author </p>

<p>Indonesia </p>

<p>Gambia </p>

<p>Gambia </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>Indonesia </p>

<p>Gambia </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>Country </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>PRP-OMP </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>PRP-T </p>

<p>PRP-OMP </p>

<p>Type 
of Hib 
vaccine </p>

<p>5/19150 </p>

<p>12/17919 </p>

<p>17/37069 </p>

<p>4/2349 </p>

<p>8/2105 </p>

<p>12/4454 </p>

<p>1/3815 </p>

<p>4/1089 </p>

<p>5/497 </p>

<p>10/5401 </p>

<p>Events, 
control </p>

<p>47·44 </p>

<p>52·56 </p>

<p>100·00 </p>

<p>48·79 </p>

<p>51·21 </p>

<p>100·00 </p>

<p>14·69 </p>

<p>67·33 </p>

<p>17·98 </p>

<p>100·00 </p>

<p>% 
Weight </p>

<p>81 (-63 to 98) </p>

<p>92 (35 to 99) </p>

<p>88 (46 to 97) </p>

<p>89 (-111 to 99) </p>

<p>94 (-4 to 100) </p>

<p>92 (37 to 99) </p>

<p>68 (-683 to 99) </p>

<p>42 (-161 to 87) </p>

<p>92 (-53 to 100) </p>

<p>62 (-29 to 89) </p>

<p>Vaccine 
efficacy (%) </p>

<p>0·19 (0·02-1·63) </p>

<p>0·08 (0·01-0·65) </p>

<p>0·12 (0·03-0·54) </p>

<p>0·11 (0·01-2·11) </p>

<p>0·06 (0·00-1·04) </p>

<p>0·08 (0·01-0·63) </p>

<p>0·32 (0·01-7·83) </p>

<p>0·58 (0·13-2·61) </p>

<p>0·08 (0·00-1·53) </p>

<p>0·38 (0·11-1·29) </p>

<p>RR (95% CI) </p>

<p>1/20156 </p>

<p>1/17794 </p>

<p>2/37950 </p>

<p>0/2299 </p>

<p>0/2056 </p>

<p>0/4355 </p>

<p>0/3988 </p>

<p>3/1397 </p>

<p>0/532 </p>

<p>3/5917 </p>

<p>Events, 
vaccine </p>

<p>Favours vaccine </p>

<p>1 
0·001 
10 </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Hib vaccine efficacy against confirmed Hib meningitis. </p>

<p>Hospitalised </p>

<p>Gessner [27] </p>

<p>Levine [44] </p>

<p>Subtotal (I 
2 = 80·6%, p = 0·023) </p>

<p>Radiological </p>

<p>Gessner [27] </p>

<p>Levine [44] </p>

<p>Mulholland [21] </p>

<p>Subtotal (I 
2 = 68·4%, p = 0·042) </p>

<p>Clinical </p>

<p>Gessner [27] </p>

<p>Mulholland [21] </p>

<p>Subtotal (I 
2 = 0·0%, p = 0·946) </p>

<p>Author </p>

<p>Indonesia </p>

<p>Chile </p>

<p>Indonesia </p>

<p>Chile </p>

<p>Gambia </p>

<p>Indonesia </p>

<p>Gambia </p>

<p>Country </p>

<p>893/18916 </p>

<p>163/10274 </p>

<p>1056/29190 </p>

<p>191/19104 </p>

<p>85/10274 </p>

<p>170/17919 </p>

<p>446/47297 </p>

<p>4870/17748 </p>

<p>570/18489 </p>

<p>5440/36237 </p>

<p>Events, 
control </p>

<p>57·12 </p>

<p>42·88 </p>

<p>100·00 </p>

<p>37·83 </p>

<p>27·41 </p>

<p>34·75 </p>

<p>100·00 </p>

<p>92·26 </p>

<p>7·74 </p>

<p>100·00 </p>

<p>% 
Weight </p>

<p>2 (-8 to 10) </p>

<p>26 (7 to 41) </p>

<p>13 (-15 to 34) </p>

<p>-10 (-33 to 9) </p>

<p>22 (-7 to 43) </p>

<p>22 (2 to 38) </p>

<p>11 (-14 to 30) </p>

<p>4 (0 to 7) </p>

<p>4 (-8 to 15) </p>

<p>4 (1 to 7) </p>

<p>Vaccine 
efficacy (%) </p>

<p>0·98 (0·90-1·08) </p>

<p>0·74 (0·59-0·93) </p>

<p>0·87 (0·66-1·15) </p>

<p>1·10 (0·91-1·33) </p>

<p>0·78 (0·57-1·07) </p>

<p>0·78 (0·62-0·98) </p>

<p>0·89 (0·70-1·14) </p>

<p>0·96 (0·93-1·00) </p>

<p>0·96 (0·85-1·08) </p>

<p>0·96 (0·93-0·99) </p>

<p>RR (95% CI) </p>

<p>926/19934 </p>

<p>131/11146 </p>

<p>1057/31080 </p>

<p>221/20102 </p>

<p>72/11146 </p>

<p>132/17794 </p>

<p>425/49042 </p>

<p>4957/18762 </p>

<p>526/17794 </p>

<p>5483/36556 </p>

<p>Events, 
vaccine </p>

<p>Favours vaccine </p>

<p>1 
0·01 
10 </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Hib vaccine efficacy against non-specific pneumonia outcome measures. </p>

<p> 
U. K. Griffiths and others </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>All the studies demonstrated high vaccine efficacy 
against confirmed invasive Hib disease following two 
and three doses, and there was no heterogeneity in the 
pooled estimate. With one dose, the pooled estimate 
was 59 % (95 % CI x20 to 86) and there was only low 
heterogeneity. Hence, the vaccine efficacy evidence 
against invasive disease is convincing and robust for 
all dose regimens. This conclusion is similar to the 
findings of O'Loughlin and colleagues in their meta-
analysis of observational studies [14]. The pooled 
vaccine effectiveness estimate against invasive Hib 
disease from three case-control studies was 95 % 
(95 % CI 82-99) after three doses and 92% (95 % CI 
81-97) following two doses. In the meta-analysis of 
RCTs by Obonyo &amp; Lau, vaccine efficacy against in-
vasive Hib disease after three doses was only 84 % 
(95 % CI 69-92). The reason for the higher pooled 
estimate in the new analysis is partly the exclusion of 
the PRP-D trials, but also that Obonyo &amp; Lau com-
bined all doses into one analysis, so that children re-
ceiving only one dose, only two doses and all three 
doses were included in the same estimate. 
The evidence for confirmed Hib meningitis and 
confirmed Hib pneumonia is less robust because few 
studies report on these, so the pooled estimates are 
based on small sample sizes, which give wide confi-
dence intervals. As both diseases are contained within 
the overall group of invasive Hib disease, these effi-
cacy estimates should be used instead of seeking to 
categorize according to invasive Hib disease type. 
As expected, the strength of the evidence of vaccine 
efficacy against the three, non-specific pneumonia 
outcomes is less than for confirmed Hib disease. For </p>

<p>hospitalized pneumonia the heterogeneity is too large 
for the efficacy estimate to be meaningful. The large 
heterogeneity between the Indonesian and Chilean 
studies may partly be due different case detection 
methods. Pneumonia detection in Indonesia was 
based on individual presentation for medical care, but 
supported by village health workers whose task was 
to identify children in the community with possible 
severe respiratory disease and refer them for treat-
ment. By contrast, cases were retrospectively ident-
ified from patient records in Chile. Another possible 
explanation is differences between the two sites in the 
distribution of non-Hib pneumonia aetiologies. For 
example, a large burden of RSV infection in one 
site will lower the measured vaccine effectiveness even 
if the two sites have similar vaccine-preventable 
Hib disease incidences, as has been described pre-
viously [26]. Consequently, for clinical (rather than 
microbiologically confirmed) outcomes, vaccine-
preventable disease incidence may be a better measure 
than vaccine efficacy. 
The Indonesian trial by Gessner did not detect an 
impact on radiological pneumonia [27]. The study 
authors have proposed several possible explanations 
why pneumonias with lobar infiltrate or pleural ef-
fusion were not preventable with Hib vaccine. First, 
Hib may not be an important cause of pneumonia in 
Indonesia ; this seems unlikely, since the vaccine-
preventable disease incidence measured against all 
severe or clinical pneumonias was as high or higher 
than in other studies [24]. Second, some characteristic 
of children in South East Asia could lead to a different 
pneumonia presentation ; this also seems unlikely 
since many children presented with a lobar infiltrate 
meeting the WHO case definition. Last, and perhaps </p>

<p>Table 4. Vaccine efficacy against clinical meningitis in Lombok, Indonesia </p>

<p>Outcome measure </p>

<p>No. of Hib 
vaccine doses </p>

<p>Cases/total children 
Vaccine 
efficacy </p>

<p>95 % CI </p>

<p>P value 
Hib 
Placebo 
Low 
High </p>

<p>Probable bacterial meningitis 
1 
1/3989 
6/3816 
84 % 
x32 
98 
0 . 06 
Probable bacterial meningitis 
2 
5/4006 
6/3963 
18 % 
x170 
75 
0 . 77 
Probable bacterial meningitis 
3 
9/20152 
20/19147 
57 % 
6 
81 
0 . 04* 
Possible bacterial meningitis 
1 
3/3989 
9/3819 
68 % 
x18 
91 
0 . 09 
Possible bacterial meningitis 
2 
6/4006 
6/3963 
1 % 
x206 
68 
1 . 00 
Possible bacterial meningitis 
3 
17/20152 
34/19144 
53 % 
15 
73 
0 . 01* 
Hospitalized meningitis 
1 
21/3993 
34/3824 
41 % 
x2 
66 
0 . 06 
Hospitalized meningitis 
2 
33/4010 
41/3971 
20 % 
x26 
49 
0 . 35 
Hospitalized meningitis 
3 
118/20144 
121/19131 
7 % 
x19 
28 
0 . 56 </p>

<p>CI, Confidence interval. 
* Significant at the 95 % level using Fisher's exact t test. </p>

<p>The efficacy of Hib vaccine : a systematic review </p>

<p>
most likely, early antibiotic use through self-
medication or early intervention could have modified 
the evolution of Hib pneumonia [26]. 
The two remaining studies by Mulholland and 
Levine found a remarkably similar result of 22 % 
vaccine efficacy against radiological pneumonia, in 
spite of different definitions used. In The Gambia, 
standardized radiology readings were used while in 
Chile radiology reports were searched for key words, 
such as 'alveolar consolidation '. The 22 % estimate is, 
however, less than in three case-control studies from 
Bangladesh, Dominican Republic and Colombia, 
which reported effectiveness against radiological 
pneumonia as 32 %, 31% and 55 %, respectively [14]. 
In a study by Theodoratou et al. [28], these three 
studies were combined with the RCTs of Gessner, 
Levine and Mulholland and a pooled Hib vaccine ef-
fectiveness estimate of 18 % against radiological 
pneumonia was generated. There was considerable 
heterogeneity in the pooled estimate, but this problem 
was not addressed in the study [28]. 
It must be emphasized that the radiological pneu-
monia outcome measure imposes a large risk of bias 
due to the many definition problems of reading chest 
X-rays. This was particularly illustrated in the case-
control study from Bangladesh where chest radio-
graphs were taken of 2679 children with clinical 
pneumonia [29]. According to per-protocol readings, 
17 . 7 % cases were identified as having radiologically 
confirmed pneumonia. However, when the radio-
graphs were read by a WHO panel, it was concluded 
that 26 . 0% were radiologically confirmed, and only 
13 . 2 % of cases were radiologically confirmed by both 
per-protocol readings and WHO readings [29]. It is 
thus difficult to determine which estimate to use, and 
the choice greatly affects the vaccine effectiveness es-
timate. When using the per-protocol readings, the 
preventable fraction for radiologically confirmed 
pneumonia was 17 % following at least two doses of 
Hib vaccine. When the WHO readings were used, the 
vaccine was associated with 15% protection, and 
when the subset considered positive by both sets of 
readings was used the vaccine offered 34% protection 
[29]. 
The pooled vaccine efficacy estimate against clinical 
pneumonia appears robust as there is no heterogen-
eity between the two studies. It is noteworthy that the 
two studies found such comparable results as there is 
a high risk of bias with this non-specific outcome 
measure. However, with only two studies the evidence 
is limited and as discussed earlier, the estimates </p>

<p>cannot be generalized to other settings without 
caution due to potential fluctuations in clinical pneu-
monia aetiology between countries and years. 
Vaccine efficacy data against non-specific outcomes 
must be interpreted cautiously. While vaccine efficacy 
against microbiologically confirmed outcomes reflects 
the ability of the vaccine to induce protective im-
munity against infection and disease, vaccine efficacy 
against non-specific outcomes reflects vaccine per-
formance in combination with the epidemiological 
context in which the vaccine is used. For example, 
vaccine efficacy may change by number of doses based 
on a different distribution of aetiologies at different 
immunization ages. 
The PRP-T and the HbOC vaccines showed similar 
dose-specific efficacy values, but the PRP-OMP vac-
cine, which has different kinetics to the other two 
vaccines, had larger efficacy following one dose. The 
PRP-OMP vaccine has shown significantly higher 
immunogenicity after the first dose than the two 
others in all studies comparing the vaccines [8]. While 
all three vaccines are indicated for primary infant 
immunization, PRP-OMP may afford a marginal ad-
vantage in populations with high disease burden and 
carriage prevalence in young infants. For example, in 
Alaska Native children -who during the pre-vaccine 
era had among the highest Hib disease incidence rates 
ever recorded [30] -a change from PRP-OMP to 
HbOC vaccine in 1996 led to an increase in invasive 
Hib disease incidence from 19 . 8 to 91 . 1 cases/100 000 
children aged &lt;5 years [31]. When the state subse-
quently switched back to PRP-OMP vaccine, disease 
incidence decreased to 0/100 000 in 2004 [31]. 
Nevertheless, most countries in Africa have reported 
a high Hib disease burden in young infants pre-
vaccine, and yet have achieved and sustained 
near elimination of Hib disease with PRP-T [32], in-
dicating this vaccine is also appropriate in these 
situations. 
There was no significant difference between two 
and three doses, with efficacy against invasive Hib 
disease being 92 % and 93% following two and three 
doses, respectively. In theory, then, the routine 
schedule could be reduced to two instead of three 
doses. A study evaluating this option found that while 
PRP-T elicited high immune response after two doses, 
this was not universally true of PRP-HbOC, with 
only 87 % of infants reaching seroprotective con-
centrations [33]. The authors concluded that before 
switching to a two-dose regimen, additional studies 
would be needed [33]. These studies have not been </p>

<p> 
U. K. Griffiths and others </p>

<p>conducted, and moreover, additional barriers to a 
two-dose schedule exist. First, studies would need to 
confirm vaccine effectiveness against carriage, since 
indirect protection is a critical component of overall 
disease reduction and second, additional studies 
would need to confirm long-term immunity and pro-
tection against carriage, as well as booster responses 
with a two-dose schedule. Programmatically, Hib 
vaccine is now widely introduced in combination with 
DTP and other vaccines with a primary three-dose 
schedule, which has large advantages. For these 
reasons, it is unlikely that any country would consider 
a two-dose primary series without a booster. How-
ever, if countries were to switch to a 2+1 schedule for 
pneumococcal vaccines, our analysis supports the use 
of the same schedule for Hib vaccine. 
While not evaluated in this study, choices of vac-
cine formulations and schedules must also consider 
the immune status of the population, particularly the 
effects of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) in-
fection and malnutrition. For example, HIV infection 
leads to decreased immunogenicity [34] ; however, 
population impact against Hib disease in HIV-
endemic areas has varied with South Africa showing 
reduced impact [35] and Malawi showing high impact 
[36]. 
Waning immunity and the possible need for a 
booster dose is another important issue to consider. 
Since the medium follow-up time of the studies was 
only 24 months, they do not provide evidence re-
garding the long-term protection of the vaccine. 
While all high-income and some middle-income 
countries recommend a Hib vaccine booster dose at 
12-15 months, this has not been included in im-
munization schedules in low-income countries. The 
reason for not including a booster dose is partly due 
to the increased cost, which is not affordable, but also 
because the average age of Hib infection is substan-
tially lower in low-income compared to high-income 
countries [37]. It is, however, extremely important to 
closely monitor the impact of Hib vaccine in low-
income countries to establish whether a booster dose 
is also needed in these settings. In South Africa an 
increase in invasive Hib disease cases was observed 
several years after a three-dose primary vaccination 
schedule was commenced. Surveillance data showed 
that about 60 % of Hib vaccine failures were in HIV-
negative children and 55 % occurred in children aged 
&gt;18 months ; an age group that may benefit directly 
from a booster dose. In 2010 South African children 
began receiving a Hib booster [38]. </p>

<p>Boosting is important in sustaining both direct 
protection and indirect effects through reduction in 
carriage. Although we could not evaluate the effect of 
different schedules on carriage, this issue is of primary 
importance, since much of the overall protection 
against disease afforded by Hib vaccination pro-
grammes derives from indirect effects. In the UK, an 
increase in vaccine failure 8 years after routine vacci-
nation commenced in 1999 was at least partly because 
of a greater than expected decline in Hib antibody 
response following a schedule without a booster in the 
second year of life, which had been masked by the 
initial vaccination catch-up programme of all children 
aged &lt;5 years in 1992 [39]. Moreover, the loss of 
protection against Hib disease in children resulted in a 
significant increase in adult disease, probably because 
reduced carriage and transmission in young children 
had diminished opportunities for natural boosting of 
immunity in adults, who had very low Hib antibody 
levels [40]. This suggests that control of carriage and 
disease in young children has important impact in 
older children and adults. 
Investigators of large-scale vaccination trials do 
not routinely report dose-specific outcomes despite 
their potential importance for the impact and cost-
effectiveness of immunization programmes. Estimates 
of dose-specific vaccine efficacy provide a direct way 
for analysts and decision makers to account for vac-
cine impact in partially vaccinated children. Models 
that do not account for partial protection will under-
estimate overall programme effectiveness in popu-
lations with high drop-out rates between doses. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Dr Phil Edwards for useful discussions on 
meta-analysis methods and an anonymous reviewer 
for important suggestions. 
This paper is dedicated to the memory of our 
co-author, colleague, and friend, Dr Endang 
Sedyaningsih, the Indonesian Minister of Health, 
who died on 2 May 2012. </p>

<p>DECLARATION OF INTEREST </p>

<p>None. </p>



<p>The efficacy of Hib vaccine : a systematic review </p>



<p>
 
U. K. Griffiths and others </p>



<p>The efficacy of Hib vaccine : a systematic review </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>