<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3927206" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Hereditary cataracts are clinically and genetically heterogeneous lens diseases that cause a significant 
proportion of visual impairment and blindness in children. Human cataracts have been linked with 
mutations in two genes, GJA3 and GJA8, respectively. To identify the causative mutation in a family with 
hereditary cataracts, family members were screened for mutations by PCR for both genes. Sequencing the 
coding regions of GJA8, coding for connexin 50, revealed a C . A transversion at nucleotide 264, which 
caused p.P88T mutation. To dissect the molecular consequences of this mutation, plasmids carrying 
wild-type and mutant mouse ORFs of Gja8 were generated and ectopically expressed in HEK293 cells and 
human lens epithelial cells, respectively. The recombinant proteins were assessed by confocal microscopy 
and Western blotting. The results demonstrate that the molecular consequences of the p.P88T mutation in 
GJA8 include changes in connexin 50 protein localization patterns, accumulation of mutant protein, and 
increased cell growth. </p>

<p>p.P88T Mutation in GJA8 identification and analysis. Direct cycle 
sequencing of the amplified fragments of the GJA8 gene in one 
affected individual (IV: 3) identified a C . A transversion in exon 
2 at nucleotide 264 (Figure 2A) with no other changes in the coding 
sequence of GJA8. This transversion caused a substitution of 
Threonine (T) for Proline (P) at codon 88 (p.P88T). Results of 
additional sequencing demonstrated that this mutation co-
segregated with all affected individuals in the family, and was not 
observed in any of the unaffected family members. Denaturing 
HPLC analysis confirmed this mutation, which cosegregated with 
all affected individuals in the family, and this mutation was not 
observed in any of the unaffected family members or 100 normal 
controls. The remainder of the coding sequence, including that of 
GJA3, did not show any sequence change. The p.P88T mutation was 
not present in multiple databases, including the dbSNPs (v130), 
HapMap, 1000 Genome, and 702 in-house exome data. 
Multiple-sequence alignments of Cx50 in various species were 
obtained (Figure 2B). We found that codon 88, where mutation 
(p.P88T) occurred, is located within a highly conserved region. To 
date, 33 mutations have been identified in human Cx50; we sum-
marize all reported mutations in Figure 3. The prevalence of changes 
in proline 88 indicates that this residue is a mutation hot spot. The 
p.P88T substitution changes a nonpolar residue to a polar residue at 
this key site in the protein. The online bioinformatics software <rs id="software-0" type="software">SIFT</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">http://sift.jcvi.org/</rs>/) predicts a deleterious effect of this substitution. 
Taken together, these data indicate that the p.P88T substitution is a 
causative disease mutation rather than a simple polymorphism. </p>

<p>Different expression pattern and high expression level of mutant 
protein. To dissect the molecular consequences of the mutation 
identified in this family, we generated the patients-associated Flag-
tagged and GFP-tagged Cx50 mutants. Specifically, genes coding for 
wild-type and mutant Cx50 were inserted into two eukaryotic gene 
expression vectors (pSIN and pEGFPc1), respectively. Meanwhile, 
Flag, which is a robust and commonly used epitope, was also added to 
the pSIN construct. 
Confocal immunocytochemical analysis showed that cells trans-
fected with wild-type (WT) Cx50 had characteristic punctate plasma 
membrane staining. Limited staining was also detected intracellu-
larly in 293 cells (Figure 4A). In contrast, the localization of proteins 
affected by the p.P88T connexin mutation was different, with lower 
level of plasma membrane staining and evidence of accumulations of 
the protein in the cytoplasm and plasma membrane. A similar gene 
expression pattern has been observed with a different cell line 
(human lens epithelial cells, HLE cells; Figure 4B) and a different 
tag (EGFP; Figure 4C, 4D). 
We further took advantage of a membrane-tagged expression of 
RFP, encoded by the pmTmG plasmid (original from Addgene 
http://www.addgene.org/17787/), and used it as control for labeling 
the plasma membrane, which confirms that the p.P88T Cx50 mutant 
protein has a distinct expression pattern of connexins (see Supple-
mentary Fig. S1online), compared with that of wild-type. This find-
ing is consistent with a previous study that demonstrated ectopic 
expression of P88S and P88Q Cx50 mutant protein in an expression 
pattern that is distinct from wild-type 4,11 . 
Western blotting analysis of extracts from the cells expressing 
connexins clearly showed a much higher expression of mutated con-
nexins (Figure 5). Furthermore, several different lengths of Cx50 
(about 60 kd, 50 kd, 43 kd) have been detected, possibly as a result 
of cleavage by caspase-3-like protease during expression. In addition, 
protein post-translational modification may exist 12 . </p>

<p>Mutated Cx50 has a positive effect on cell growth. Current evi-
dence suggests that Cx50 is likely to play a role in cell growth during 
lens development. We therefore investigated the effects of the muta-
tion on this process by observing the cell colony size in puromycin 
selected cells with stable expressing Flag-tagged Cx50 proteins. We 
found that stable ectopic expression of mutated Cx50 led to a much 
larger colony size when compared with wild-type control (Figure 6). 
Furthermore, cell growth curves (see Supplementary Fig. S2 online) 
also showed higher rates of cell growth for lines tranfected with 
mutated Cx50 protein. These data indicate that at least, mutated 
Cx50 has a positive effect on cell growth in vitro. </p>

<p>Discussion 
More than 90% of the soluble proteins in the lens are crystallins. In 
our previous studies, we identified several mutations in different </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Cataracts pedigree and phenotype. (A). Cataracts pedigree. </p>

<p>Squares and circles symbolize males and females, respectively. Black and 
white lines denote affected status and unaffected status, respectively. Arrow 
indicates proband. Individuals underlined in blue represent those enrolled 
in the study. 1 represents wild-type GJA8 allele, 2 represents allele with 
mutation. (B). Photographs of affected individuals of this family. The 
phenotype of the proband (IV: 3) is bilateral complete opacification of the 
fetal nucleus and the cortex; its phenotype is total cataract. </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Mutation analysis. (A). DNA sequence chromatogram analysis. DNA sequence chromatograms of the unaffected members (top) and </p>

<p>affected members (bottom) in a family with autosomal dominant total cataracts. A single base alteration of C . A transversion in exon 2 causes a 
conservative substitution of Pro to Thr at codon 88 (p.P88T). (B). Multiple protein sequence alignments. Multiple-sequence alignment of Cx50 from 
different species and Cx family members (Cx43, Cx40) from human revealed that codon 88, where the mutation (p.P88T) occurred, was located within a 
highly conserved region. The ''mut.'' sequence indicates the sequence with the mutation detected in this family. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4121 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04121 </p>

<p>
Figure 3 | Schematic diagram of Cx50 reported mutations. Schematic diagram of Cx50 protein containing all reported human mutations associated with </p>

<p>cataracts. The identified mutation in this study is marked with red arrow. </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Distinct protein localization patterns of p.P88T mutation. (A, B). Immunofluorescent imaging of Cx50-Flag and EGFP (control) showing </p>

<p>transiently transfected 293 cells (A) and HLE cells (B) with Cx50-WT, p.P88T mutant, and pSin EGFP backbone plasmids (control). Cells were 
immunostained with anti-Flag monoclonal antibody. DAPI shows nuclear DNA staining. Arrows mark the accumulation of the mutant protein in the 
cytoplasm and plasma membrane. (C, D). Immunofluorescent imaging of EGFP fusion proteins showing transiently transfected 293 cells (C) and HLE 
cells (D) with Cx50-WT p.P88T mutant, and pEGFPc1 backbone plasmids (control). DAPI shows nuclear DNA staining. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4121 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04121 </p>

<p>
genes responsible for inherited cataracts 13-16 . In order to maintain 
solubility properties of crystallins and to ensure transparency, the 
lens must have sophisticated mechanisms to control ionic balance 
and water content. Hence, an extensive network of gap junctions 
provides low-resistance pathways for both electrical and metabolic 
coupling of lens epithelial-epithelial, epithelial-fiber and, and fiber-
fiber cells 17 . Three connexins (Cx43, Cx46 and Cx50) have been 
identified in human lens 4,18 . Because mutations in GJA1, coding for 
Cx43, cause human occulodentodigital dysplasia (ODDD), which is 
a distinct disease from cataracts, we excluded it as a candidate gene 
responsible for cataracts in the present family. Cx46 and Cx50 are the 
two most abundant connexins in lens fiber cells and lens epithelial 
cells, and mutations in these two genes have been reported to cause 
cataracts. To date, there are 33 identified mutations in human Cx50, 
summarized in Figure 3. p.P88S (CCG to TCG, mutation nucleotide 
underscored, with phenotype Zonular pulverulent cataracts), 
p.P88Q (CCG to CAG, with Lamellar pulverulent and balloon-like 
with Y-sutural cataracts) but not p.P88T (CCG to ACG, with total 
cataracts, this work) were previously reported 4,19 . </p>

<p>The mutation identified here highlights that the mutational hot 
spot residue 88 of Cx50 is critical for its function, and provides 
additional evidence to show that cataracts is a genetically heterogen-
eous disease, especially since different mutations at the same residue 
render different phenotypes. 
Proline can introduce bends in transmembrane helices, and 
because of its rigidity can act as a conformational 'switch', allowing 
parts of proteins to adopt alternative conformations, such as 
domain-swapped dimmers 20 . Mutations of proline residues in con-
nexins may disrupt the protein structure and further effect the trans-
location and subcellular localization of the final protein. Our initial 
hypothesis is that the mutation may just disrupt the location of the 
protein, causing the mutant protein to predominantly localize in 
the cytoplasm, compared to localization of the wild-type protein in 
the cellular membrane. But both wild-type and mutant recombinant 
proteins are localized to the cytoplasm and cell membrane (Figure 4; 
supplementary Figure S1). The distinctive recombinant proteins 
expression level of the same construct was observed in different cell 
lines (Figure 4). 
We observed a much higher expression level of p.P88T mutant 
Cx50 protein (Figure 5), compared with the wild-type, which is 
consistent with the results of the P88S mutant protein 21 . The altered 
degradation of the P88S mutant protein observed in that study was 
proposed to lead to the higher expression level of P88S. A similar 
mechanism may allow the p.P88T mutant to achieve a much higher 
protein expression level. 
There are reports that connexin may control cell growth 22 , while 
whether p.P88T mutation have the effects on the cells growth or not 
is still an open question. We were surprised to find that stable ectopic 
expression of mutated Cx50 led to a much larger colony when com-
pared with wild-type control (Figure 6), and higher growth rates were 
confirmed by cell growth curve assay (see Supplementary Fig. S2 
online). These data indicate that mutated Cx50 has a positive effect 
on cell growth in vitro. Xia et al. showed that mice heterozygous for a 
Gja8 point mutation (R205G) have cataracts and smaller lenses, 
while severe cataracts are seen in homozygous mice 23 . While further 
studies are needed to determine whether lens cells from the patients 
have a growth advantage or not, results from this in vitro cell growth 
assay clearly show a striking difference between the wild-type and 
mutant protein. 
As to the accurate gene diagnosis of cataracts, so far, it is still an 
ongoing challenge, because the relatively large numbers (18) of 
disease genes make it one of the most complicated single-
gene genetic disorders. Although Capture Next Generation 
Sequencing offers alternative mutation screening techniques for 
heterogeneous inherited diseases 24 , the cost and bioinformatics 
analysis represent the limiting factors for gene diagnosis. Here, 
we showed an example of using a functional cloning approach </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Much higher expression level of p.P88T mutant protein. </p>

<p>Western blotting for Cx50 and EGFP (control). The blots were probed with 
the anti-Flag antibody. Only two groups of cells produced a protein band, 
which includes about 60 kDa, 50 kDa, 43 kDa. No band was detected in 
the EGFP control. </p>

<p>Figure 6 | A positive effect of p.P88T mutant protein on cell growth. (A, B). Colony size of 293 cells with stable ectopic overexpression of Cx50. Stable </p>

<p>ectopic overexpression of p.P88T mutated Cx50 led to a much larger cell colony when compared with wild-type control. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4121 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04121 </p>

<p>
to identify the responsible gene for hereditary cataracts. It will 
be valuable for genetic counseling of the family members and 
prenatal diagnosis. This study also highlights that it may be mean-
ingful to directly screen these connexin coding genes for muta-
tions in families with human hereditary cataracts, especially families 
with total cataracts. 
We conclude that a novel mutation in Cx50, p.P88T, has been 
identified as the causative mutation in a family with hereditary dom-
inant congenital cataracts. We found a distinct localization pattern 
for mutant protein, an increased accumulation of mutant protein, 
and a positive effect on cell growth, which may account for the 
molecular mechanisms underlying cataracts in this family. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Patients. This study conformed to the tenets of the Declaration of Helsinki (sixth 
revision, 2008) and was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Eye hospital, 
Wenzhou Medical University. The family members in this study have given 
written informed consent to publication of their case details. Ten members from 
the family were recruited, including three affected and seven unaffected members 
(Figure 1). Clinical and ophthalmological examinations were performed by 
ophthalmologists. A 5 ml venous blood sample was drawn into an 
ethylenediamine tetraacetic acid (EDTA) sample tube from every subject. 
Genomic DNA was extracted from peripheral blood leukocytes using the Wizard 
Genomic DNA Purification Kit (Promega, Beijing, China) according to the 
manufacturer's instructions. </p>

<p>Mutation screening and analysis. We designed a set of eight primer pairs (see 
Supplementary Table S1 online) to amplify the exons and flanking intron 
sequences of GJA3 (NM_021954) and GJA8 (NM_005267). Oligonucleotide 
primers and PCR information for amplification are shown in Supplementary 
Table S1. PCR products were sequenced on an ABI PRISM 3730 DNA Sequencer. 
Denaturing high-performance liquid chromatography (DHPLC, Wave DHPLC; 
Transgenomic, San Jose, CA) was used to confirm the identified mutation in the 
GJA8 gene using a commercial system on the patients, family members, and 100 
normal controls as previously described 14 . Briefly, gene specific PCR primers (see 
Supplementary Table S1 online, Exon2a) were used to amplify the fragment that 
harbored the point mutation. After the amplification, about 100 ng of the PCR 
product was denatured for 3 min at 96uC and then gradually reannealed by 
decreasing sample temperature from 95 to 55uC over a period of 30 min. PCR 
products were then separated with a DHPLC machine as follows: initial 
concentration at 44% of buffer A (0.1 M triethylammonium acetate, TEAA; 
Transgenomic) and 56% of buffer B (0.1 M TEAA containing 25% acetonitrile; 
Transgenomic) at 62.0uC. 
Using the websites of NCBI and UCSC, we obtained the Cx50 sequence from 
Homo sapiens, Rattus norvegicus, Mus musculus, Heterocephalus glaber, Tupaia 
chinensis, Pteropus alecto and sequences of Cx40 and Cx43 from Homo sapiens. 
Using DNAMAN biosoftware, multiple-sequence alignment of Cx50 sequences 
from these species was obtained. Furthermore, we used the online bioinformatics 
software <rs id="software-2" type="software">SIFT</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="url">http://sift.jcvi.org/</rs>/) to predict whether the amino acid substitution 
p.P88T in Cx50 could have a phenotypic effect. </p>

<p>Cloning and expression of proteins. Recombinant mouse wild-type and mutant 
p.P88T Cx50 coding fragments were prepared as previously described 14 . Flag 
sequence was added into the coding fragments to get a C-terminal Flag tag. Genes 
coding for Cx50 wild-type, Cx50 mutant, and EGFP proteins were inserted into 
eukaryotic expression Vectors pSin or pEGFPc1 to obtain pSin-WT, pSin-Mut., 
pSin-EGFP, pEGFPc1-WT, and pEGFPc1-mut., respectively. DNA sequencing 
confirmed the desired specific sequence in each construct. 
The recombinant plasmids were expressed in human embryonic kidney (293) 
cells and human lens epithelial cells (HLE). Briefly, cells were seeded at day 0 and 
transfected on day 1. For transient gene expression, cells were fixed with 4% 
paraformaldehyde at day 3 and then incubated with corresponding antibodies. To 
label plasma membrane, membrane-tagged expressions of RFP, coding from 
pmTmG plasmid, were used as a control. Stable cell lines of the transfection (pSin 
vectors) were obtained by selecting with puromycin for an additional 10 days. To 
measure colony size, the puromycin-resistant colonies from 293 cells were 
obtained by puromycin selection and then trypsinized &amp; re-seeded at the same cell 
numbers. After another twelve days, the dishes were stained with Commassie 
Blue. Cell growth curve was performed according to manufacturer's protocol 
(Roche, cat No.05015944001). </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence and Western blotting. The cells were permeabilized with 0.1% 
Triton X-100 and blocked in solution, then incubated with anti-Flag antibody. It was 
recognized with secondary antibodies and DAPI was used to label the cellular nuclei. 
The cells were observed under laser confocal microscope. 
The expression of the wild-type and mutant proteins was analyzed on 
SDS-PAGE under reducing conditions. The proteins were recognized by anti-Flag 
antibodies. </p>



<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank the family for their participation in this project. We are indebted to Dr. Jinyu Wu 
(Institute of Genomic Medicine, Wenzhou Medical University) for scanning the present 
mutations and Dr.Charles Murry (University of Washington) for providing pmTmG 
plasmid. This work was supported by grants from the Chinese National Program on Key 
Basic Research Project (973 Program, 2013CB967502, FG), Natural Science Foundation of 
China (81201181/H1818, FG), Zhejiang Provincial &amp; Ministry of Health research fund for 
medical sciences (201339279, FG), Wenzhou Medical University PI Start-Up Grant (QTJ 
12011, FG). </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>F.G. formulated the idea of the paper and supervised the research. X.L.G., Y.L.Z., X.L., 
Y.M.W., J.N.L., J.H.Y., Z.B.J. and J.Q. collected the samples and performed the experiments. 
X.L.G. and F.G. performed data analyses, F.G. wrote the manuscript. All authors have read 
and approved the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4121 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04121 </p>

<p>
How to cite this article: Ge, X.-L. et al. Identification of a Novel GJA8 (Cx50) Point 
Mutation Causes Human Dominant Congenital Cataracts. Sci. Rep. 4, 4121; DOI:10.1038/ 
srep04121 (2014). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported license. To view a copy of this license, 
visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4121 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04121 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>