<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3198078" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVE-Tribbles 3 (TRB3) is associated with insulin resis-
tance, an important trigger in the development of diabetic cardio-
myopathy (DCM). We sought to determine whether TRB3 plays 
a major role in modulating DCM and the mechanisms involved. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS-The type 2 diabetic 
rat model was induced by high-fat diet and low-dose streptozo-
tocin. We evaluated the characteristics of type 2 DCM by serial 
echocardiography and metabolite tests, Western blot analysis for 
TRB3 expression, and histopathologic analyses of cardiomyocyte 
density, lipids accumulation, cardiac inflammation, and fibrosis 
area. We then used gene silencing to investigate the role of TRB3 
in the pathophysiologic features of DCM. </p>

<p>RESULTS-Rats with DCM showed severe insulin resistance, 
left ventricular dysfunction, aberrant lipids deposition, cardiac 
inflammation, fibrosis, and TRB3 overexpression. We found that 
the silencing of TRB3 ameliorated metabolic disturbance and in-
sulin resistance; myocardial hypertrophy, lipids accumulation, in-
flammation, fibrosis, and elevated collagen I-to-III content ratio in 
DCM rats were significantly decreased. These anatomic findings 
were accompanied by significant improvements in cardiac function. 
Furthermore, with TRB3 gene silencing, the inhibited phosphoryla-
tion of Akt was restored and the increased phosphorylation of 
extracellular signal-regulated kinase 1/2 and Jun NH 2 -terminal ki-
nase in DCM was significantly decreased. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS-TRB3 gene silencing may exert a protective 
effect on DCM by improving selective insulin resistance, impli-
cating its potential role for treatment of human DCM. Diabetes 
60:2963-2974, 2011 </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>iabetic cardiomyopathy (DCM), which occurs in 
patients with diabetes, carries a substantial risk 
concerning the subsequent development of heart 
failure and increased mortality (1). Different 
pathophysiological stimuli are involved in its development 
and mediate tissue injury leading to left ventricle (LV) sys-
tolic and diastolic dysfunction. Insulin resistance is con-
sidered to play a causal role in the pathogenesis and 
development of DCM (2-4). Insulin resistance is associated 
with increased LV mass (5) and deterioration of LV diastolic </p>

<p>function (6). However, the underlying relevance of insulin 
resistance leading to altered myocardial structure remains 
incompletely understood. 
Tribbles 3 (TRB3) is a pseudokinase with increased 
activity in response to fasting that binds to and inhibits the 
activation of the serine-threonine kinase Akt in the liver (7,8). 
Indeed, humans with a gain-of-function mutation in TRB3 
show increased insulin resistance and diabetes-associated 
complications (9,10). These observations have led to the 
suggestion that TRB3 elevation contributes to insulin re-
sistance. TRB3 also serves as a molecular switch and regu-
lates the activation of the three classes of mitogen-activated 
protein kinases (MAPKs) (11). TRB3 binds to and regulates 
MAPK kinase, thus controlling the activation of MAPK by 
incoming signals (11). However, the TRB3/MAPK signal-
transduction pathway has not been investigated in vivo on 
cardiac tissues directly. 
Akt and MAPK are the most important pathways involved 
in selective insulin resistance (12), and activated MAPK 
contributes to the development of cardiac fibrosis (13-15). 
Thus, we hypothesized that upregulated TRB3 induced by 
insulin resistance might participate in the pathophysiologi-
cal process of DCM. First, we established the type 2 DCM 
model and determined the relationships among TRB3 ex-
pression, cardiac remodeling, and cardiac function in the 
model. To further elucidate the role of TRB3 in DCM, we 
used TRB3 gene silencing in vivo to explore the mecha-
nisms of TRB3 in DCM as a potential target for treatment. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>Induction of diabetes. Sixty male Sprague-Dawley rats (120-140 g) were 
purchased from the experimental animal center of Shandong University of 
Traditional Chinese Medicine (Ji'nan, China). The animals were housed at 22°C 
with 12-h light-dark cycles. After 1 week of acclimatization, intraperitoneal 
glucose tolerance test (IPGTT) and intraperitoneal insulin tolerance test 
(IPITT) were performed. The rats were then randomized into four groups: 
control, chow + streptozotocin (STZ), high-fat (HF) diet, and diabetes. HF and 
diabetic groups were fed an HF diet (34.5% fat, 17.5% protein, 48% carbohy-
drate; Beijing HFK Bio-Technology, China), and the other two groups received 
normal chow. Four weeks later, IPGTT and IPITT were performed again, and 
blood was sampled through the jugular vein. Fasting blood glucose (FBG) and 
fasting insulin were measured, and the insulin sensitivity index [ISI = ln(FBG 3 
fasting insulin) 
21 ] was calculated. Diabetes was induced by a single in-
traperitoneal injection of STZ (Sigma, St. Louis, MO; 27.5 mg/kg i.p. in 0.1 mol/L 
citrate buffer, pH 4.5) to rats with insulin resistance. Rats in the chow + STZ 
group received the same dose of STZ. The control and HF groups received 
citrate buffer (intraperitoneally) alone. One week after STZ administration, rats 
with FBG .11.1 mmol/L in two consecutive analyses were considered the di-
abetic rat model. After 16 weeks of diabetes, rats were killed. All experimental 
procedures were performed in accordance with animal protocols approved by 
the Shandong University Animal Care Committee. 
IPGTT and IPITT. Glucose tolerance was assessed by IPGTT after rats fasted 
for 12 h. A bolus of glucose (1 g/kg i.p.) was injected, and blood samples were 
collected sequentially from the tail vein at 0, 15, 30, 60, and 120 min and tested 
for glucose. Plasma glucose was measured with a One-Touch Glucometer 
(LifeScan, Milpitas, CA). The mean area under the receiver operating char-
acteristic curve (AUC) was calculated for glucose. </p>

<p>From the Key Laboratory of Cardiovascular Remodeling and Function Re-
search, To evaluate insulin tolerance, IPITT was performed after rats fasted for 4 h. 
A bolus of insulin (1 unit/kg i.p.) was administered, and blood samples were 
taken for glucose measurement as described above. 
Blood analyses. After rats fasted overnight, we collected jugular blood. Total 
cholesterol, triglyceride levels, and FBG were analyzed with use of the Bayer 
1650 blood chemistry analyzer (Bayer, Tarrytown, NY). Free fatty acid (FFA) 
concentrations were measured using an enzymatic test kit (CSB-E08770r; 
HuaMei BIO-TECH, Wuhan, China). Fasting insulin level was measured by 
enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay. ISI was calculated. 
Echocardiography and measurement of blood pressure. Echocardiogra-
phy involved use of the Vevo770 imaging system (VisualSonics, Toronto, 
Canada). Images were obtained from two-dimensional, M-mode, pulsed-wave 
Doppler and tissue Doppler imaging. All measurements were performed by the 
same observer and were the average of six consecutive cardiac cycles. Wall 
thickness and LV dimensions were obtained from a long-axis view at the level of 
chordae tendineae. Diameters of left ventricular end diastole, left ventricular 
end-diastolic posterior wall, and septum thickness, as well as left ventricular 
ejection fraction (LVEF) and fractional shortening (FS), were measured 
according to the American Society of Echocardiography guidelines (16). The 
mitral-valve pulsed Doppler recordings were obtained from the apical four-
chamber view. After pulsed Doppler, we evaluated transmitral flow velocity 
variables, including peak E, peak A, and the E-to-A (E/A) ratio. Isovolumetric 
contraction time, isovolumetric relaxation time, and ejection time were mea-
sured and were used to calculate the Tei index (Tei index = Isovolumetric 
contraction time + isovolumetric relaxation time/ejection time). The tissue 
Doppler imaging of the mitral annulus was obtained from the apical four-
chamber view. We analyzed early (E9) and late (A9) diastolic velocity and 
calculated E9/A9 and E/E9. 
For quantitative analysis of integrated backscatter (IBS) of the LV, we used 
a commercially available software package (acoustic densitometry; Phillips 
Medical Systems, Netherlands) (17). Two-dimensional echocardiographic 
images, including LV long-axis and apical four-chamber views, were obtained. 
The following variables were measured: time-averaged IBS, cyclic variation of 
integrated backscatter (CVIB), and standardized IBS (IB%). 
Heart rate, systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, and mean 
arterial pressure were measured with a noninvasive tail-cuff system (Softron 
BP-98A; Softron, Tokyo, Japan) as described previously (18). 
Hemodynamic measurement. Rats under deep anesthesia underwent hemo-
dynamic measurement. A fluid-filled catheter was advanced from the right 
carotid artery into the LV, and the left ventricular end diastolic pressure 
(LVEDP) was measured. 
Histology and morphometric analysis. Paraformaldehyde (4%)-fixed hearts 
were bisected transversely at the midventricular level, embedded in paraffin, 
and cut into 4-mm sections. A single myocyte was measured with images 
captured from hematoxylin and eosin-stained sections. The myocyte cross-
sectional area was assessed under 3400 magnification within the LV, and </p>

<p>a mean was obtained by quantitative morphometry with automated image 
analysis (<rs id="software-2" type="software">Image-Pro Plus</rs>, Version <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">5.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Media Cybernatics</rs>, Houston, TX). 
Dark green-stained collagen fibers were quantified as a measure of fibrosis 
in Masson trichrome-stained sections. The collagen volume fraction (CVF) 
and perivascular collagen area/luminal area (PVCA/LA) were analyzed by 
quantitative morphometry with automated image analysis (<rs id="software-3" type="software">Image-Pro Plus</rs>, 
Version <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">5.0</rs>). CVF was calculated as reported previously (19). Perivascular 
collagen was excluded from the CVF measurement. To normalize the PVCA 
around vessels with different sizes, the perivascular collagen content was 
represented as the PVCA-to-LA ratio. 
Interstitial and perivascular fibrosis were evaluated by Picrosirius red 
staining. Sections were stained with 0.5% sirius red (Sigma) in saturated picric 
acid for 25 min. Collagen was stained red. 
Myocardial frozen sections (5 mm) were stained with Oil Red O (Sigma) for 
10 min, washed, and then counterstained with hematoxylin for 30 s. A Nikon 
microscope (Nikon, Melville, NY) was used to capture the Oil Red O-stained 
tissue sections. 
Hydroxyproline analysis. The collagen content of myocardial tissue was 
determined by hydroxyproline assay (20). Tissue hydrolysate was detected by 
use of an ELISA kit (F15649; Westang Bio-Tech, Shanghai, China). Data were 
expressed as micrograms collagen per milligram dry weight, with the as-
sumption that collagen contains an average of 13.5% hydroxyproline (21). 
Immunohistochemical staining. Paraffin sections underwent immunohisto-
chemistry by a microwave-based antigen retrieval method. The sections were 
incubated with primary rabbit polyclonal anti-collagen I, anti-collagen III, 
anti-tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-a, and anti-interleukin (IL)-6 antibodies 
(Abcam, Cambridge, MA) overnight and then with a matching biotinylated 
secondary antibody for 30 min at 37°C. Negative controls were omission of the 
primary antibody. The stained sections were developed with diaminobenzidine 
and counterstained with hematoxylin. The results were viewed under a con-
focal FV 1000 SPD laser scanning microscope (Olympus, Japan). 
Quantitative real-time RT-PCR. Total RNA was prepared with the TRIzol 
reagent (Gibco/Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA). RT-PCR was performed using the 
following primers: b-actin, forward 59-AGA CCT TCA ACA CCC CAG-39 and 
reverse 59-CAC GAT TTC CCT CTC AGC-39; brain natriuretic protein, forward 
59-GGG CTG TGA CGG GCT GAG GTT-39 and reverse 59-AGT TTG TGC TGG 
AAG ATA AGA3-9; TRB3, forward 59-TGA TGC TGT CTG GAT GAC AA-39 and 
reverse 59-GTG AAT GGG GAC TTT GGT CT-39; TNF-a, forward 59-CAC GCT 
CTT CTG TCT ACT GA-39 and reverse 59-GGA CTC CGT GAT GTC TAA GT-39; 
and IL-6, forward 59-ACC ACT TCA CAA GTC GGA GG-39 and reverse 592ACA 
GTG CAT CAT CGC TGT TC-39. Reactions were carried out on a real-time PCR 
thermocycler (IQ5 Real-Time PCR cycler; Bio-Rad), using SYBR green as 
fluorescence dye. Relative expression analysis involved the 2 
2 △△CT method. 
Western blot analysis. Western blot analysis was as described previously 
(22). We used antibodies against TRB3 (Calbiochem, La Jolla, CA), collagen I, 
collagen III, TNF-a, IL-6 (Abcam), phospho (p)-extracellular signal-regulated </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Diabetic (DM) rats show metabolic disturbance. A: Total cholesterol (TC) levels. B: Triglyceride (TG) levels. C: FFAs. D: FBG. E: Fasting 
insulin (FINS). F: ISI. Data are mean 6 SEM; n = 7-10 per group. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. control;  †P &lt; 0.05 vs. HF; #P &lt; 0.05 vs. chow + STZ. w, weeks. </p>

<p>TRB3 GENE SILENCING AND DIABETIC CARDIOMYOPATHY </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>kinase (ERK)/ERK, p-p38/p38 MAPK, p-Jun NH 2 -terminal kinase (JNK)/JNK, 
and p-Akt/Akt (Cell Signaling Technology, Beverly, MA), followed by anti-IgG 
horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody. TRB3, collagen I, 
collagen III, TNF-a, and IL-6 protein levels were normalized to that of b-actin 
as an internal control and phosphospecific proteins to that of total protein. 
Gene silencing of TRB3. Sixty rats were randomized to receive TRB3 small 
interfering RNA (siRNA) or vehicle treatment. Gene silencing occurred imme-
diately after the appearance of LV diastolic dysfunction. After 12 weeks of di-
abetes, both E/A and E9/A9 were ,1.0 as assessed by echocardiography in 
diabetic rats. Animals were then injected via the jugular vein with 2.5 3 10 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>plaque-forming units of an adenovirus harboring TRB3 gene (TRB3-siRNA) or 
a control empty virus (vehicle). Adenovirus transfer was repeated in 2 weeks. 
According to our present and previous studies (23), TRB3 level was increased in 
HF diet-fed and high fructose-fed rats. Previous studies have shown that insulin 
resistance was a hallmark of obesity (24) and metabolic syndrome (25). In light 
of the interaction between TRB3 and insulin resistance, we also investigated the 
effect of TRB3-siRNA on HF diet-induced cardiac injury. Four weeks after the 
first adenovirus injection, rats were killed. The heart was excised and weighed. 
Statistical analysis. Values are presented as mean 6 SEM. <rs id="software-4" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">16.0</rs> (SPSS, 
Chicago, IL) was used for statistical analysis. Results were compared by one-way 
ANOVA, followed by Tukey-Kramer post hoc test and independent samples 
t test. A P , 0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Generation of type 2 DCM model 
General characteristics of diabetic rats. As expected, 
the rats in the diabetic group had the highest values of 
water intake, food intake, and urine volume compared 
with the other three groups (P , 0.01 ; P , 0.001). Heart 
weight was significantly higher in the diabetic group than 
in the control and chow + STZ groups (P , 0.01) (Sup-
plementary Table 1). 
Glucose and insulin tolerance. After a 4-week HF diet, 
insulin resistance was confirmed by IPGTT and IPITT. By 
IPGTT, the levels of blood glucose in the diabetic group 
were significantly higher at week 4 than at baseline at all of 
the time points tested except at 15 min (Supplementary 
Fig. 1A1). The AUC across the time for glucose level was 
higher at week 4 than at baseline (29.08 6 1.27 vs. 25.09 6 
0.73, respectively; P , 0.05) (Supplementary Fig. 1A2). 
Similarly, IPITT revealed impaired insulin sensitivity </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Deterioration of cardiac function in diabetic (DM) rats. A1: Representative two-dimensional echocardiograms. A2: Representative M-mode 
echocardiograms. A3: Representative pulsed-wave Doppler echocardiograms of mitral inflow. A4: Representative tissue Doppler echocardiograms. 
B-F: Sequential evaluations of left ventricular end diastolic diameter (LVEDd) (B), LVEF (C), FS (D), E/A (E), and E9/A9 (F). G: Electrocar-
diogram of control and DM groups at the end of the experiment. H: Pressure curves of cardiac catheterization. I: Analysis of LVEDP. Data are 
mean 6 SEM; n = 7-10 per group. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01, ***P &lt; 0.001 vs. control;  †P &lt; 0.05 vs. HF. w, weeks. (A high-quality digital representation 
of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>Y. TI AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 </p>

<p>
(Supplementary Fig. 1A3 and A4). Thus, the diabetic group 
showed insulin resistance after a 4-week HF diet. 
At the end of the experiment, the diabetic group showed 
impaired glucose tolerance on IPGTT compared with the 
other three groups; blood glucose levels especially were 
significantly elevated at all time points compared with the 
control (P , 0.05) (Supplementary Fig. 1B1). The diabetic 
group showed the highest mean AUC on both IPGTT and 
IPITT (Supplementary Fig. 1B2 and B4). Similarly, the 
chow + STZ and HF groups showed higher mean AUC on 
both IPGTT and IPITT compared with the control (P , 0.05) 
(Supplementary Fig. 1B2 and B4). 
Total cholesterol, triglyceride, FFA, and FBG con-
centrations. The biochemical values are given in Fig. 1. 
After 4 weeks of an HF diet, serum triglyceride and FFA 
levels were significantly higher in the HF and diabetic groups 
than in the control and chow + STZ groups (P , 0.05). The </p>

<p>ISI was markedly decreased in the HF and diabetic groups 
(P , 0.05). Insulin resistance appeared at week 4 in rats 
fed an HF diet. One week after STZ injection, FBG was 
remarkably elevated in the diabetic group and remained 
elevated until the end of the experiment. ISI consistently 
decreased in the diabetic group after the onset of di-
abetes. Simultaneously, in the diabetic group, serum 
total cholesterol, total triglyceride, and FFA levels were 
maintained at higher levels than the control (P , 0.05) 
during diabetes. Thus, the diabetic model induced by 
an HF diet and low-dose STZ was characterized by in-
sulin resistance, moderate hyperglycemia, and hyper-
lipidemia, resembling the state of chemical diabetes in 
humans. 
LV dysfunction assessed by echocardiography and 
catheterization. We evaluated ejection fraction, FS, E/A, 
and E9/A9 to investigate changes in systolic and diastolic </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Pathology features of DCM. Cardiac hypertrophy in diabetic (DM) rats. A1: Heart size (scale bar: 2 mm). A2: Representative cross sections 
of hearts at the papillary muscle level (scale bar: 2 mm). A3: Longitudinal sections of LV stained with hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E; scale bar: 
50 mm). A4: Transverse sections of LV stained with H&amp;E (scale bar: 50 mm). B: Quantitative data of heart weight to body weight (HW-to-BW) ratio. 
C: Morphometric quantification of myocyte size. D: Relative mRNA expression of brain natriuretic protein (BNP). E: Cardiac fibrosis in diabetic 
rats is shown. Masson trichrome staining (collagen is green and myocardium red; scale bar: 50 mm [E1]) and Picrosirius red staining (collagen 
fibers stained bright red, bright-field [E2], dark-field [E3]; scale bar: 100 mm) show interstitial fibrosis. Masson trichrome staining (E4) (scale bar: 
100 mm) and Picrosirius red staining (bright-field [E5], dark-field [E6]; scale bar: 100 mm) show perivascular fibrosis. F: Quantitative analysis of 
CVF. G: Collagen content determined by hydroxyproline assay. H: Quantitative analysis of PVCA/LA. Data are mean 6 SEM; n = 6. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 
0.01, ***P &lt; 0.001 vs. control;  †P &lt; 0.05,  † †P &lt; 0.01,  ‡P &lt; 0.001 vs. HF; #P &lt; 0.05, ##P &lt; 0.01 vs. chow + STZ. (A high-quality digital representation 
of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>TRB3 GENE SILENCING AND DIABETIC CARDIOMYOPATHY </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>function. Similar to the pattern in humans, in rats, diastolic 
dysfunction precedes systolic dysfunction, beginning from 
2 to 3 months after the induction of diabetes (26). In our 
study, at 6 weeks after the onset of diabetes (at week 11), 
the diabetic rats showed a moderate decrease in E/A and 
E9/A9 compared with the control (P , 0.05) (Fig. 2E and F); 
LVEF and FS were impaired from week 17 (Fig. 2C and D). 
At the end of the experiment, LVEF, FS, E/A, and E9/A9 
were further decreased in the diabetic group, with the re-
duction in E/A and E9/A9 more pronounced. LVEF, FS, E/A, 
and E9/A9 were also reduced in the chow + STZ group 
compared with the control (P , 0.05) (Fig. 2C-F) at the end 
of the experiment. Left ventricular end-diastolic diameter 
was the highest in the diabetic group (Fig. 2B). 
To further confirm the LV diastolic dysfunction, LVEDP 
was measured by cardiac catheterization. Diabetic rats had 
the highest LV pressure (Fig. 2H and I). The chow + STZ and 
HF groups showed higher LV pressure compared with the 
control (P , 0.01 ; P , 0.001) (Fig. 2H and I). In summary, </p>

<p>both systolic and diastolic dysfunction developed and pro-
gressed during DCM, with predominant deterioration of di-
astolic function. 
Pathology characteristics of diabetic rats. The heart 
weight to body weight ratio was 25% higher in the diabetic 
group than the control group (P , 0.01) (Fig. 3B), and LV 
myocyte size was 40 and 31% higher, respectively, than the 
control and HF groups (P , 0.001) (Fig. 3C). Furthermore, 
the relative mRNA expression of brain natriuretic protein, 
a marker of LV hypertrophy (27), was higher in diabetic 
than control and HF rats (P , 0.05) (Fig. 3D). 
The diabetic group showed cardiac fibrosis, with a dif-
fuse, small, patchy, and nonuniform pattern, as well as 
destroyed and disorganized collagen network structure in 
the interstitial (Fig. 3E1-E3) and perivascular (Fig. 3E4-E6) 
areas. CVF and collagen content were higher in the diabetic 
group than the other groups (P , 0.05 ; P , 0.001) (Fig. 3F 
and G), as was PVCA/LA (P , 0.001) (Fig. 3H). These his-
tological changes were confirmed by echocardiographic </p>

<p>FIG. 4. Diabetic (DM) rats showed excessive myocardial lipids deposition and inflammation. A: Representative Oil Red O-stained myocardial 
sections (scale bar: 20 mm). B: Semiquantification of Oil Red O staining. Data are mean 6 SEM of six independent observations in each group. 
C and D: Relative mRNA expression of myocardial TNF-a and IL-6. E: Immunohistochemical staining for myocardial TNF-a and IL-6 (brown 
staining considered positive staining; scale bar: 50 mm). F: Representative Western blot of myocardial TNF-a and IL-6. G and H: Western blot 
analyses of TNF-a (G) and IL-6 (H). Data are mean 6 SEM. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01, ***P &lt; 0.001 vs. control;  † †P &lt; 0.01,  ‡P &lt; 0.001 vs. HF; #P &lt; 0.05, 
##P &lt; 0.01 vs. chow + STZ. (A high-quality digital representation of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>Y. TI AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 </p>

<p>
results. The diabetic group showed increased IB% and 
decreased CVIB in the interventricular septum and LV 
posterior and lateral walls compared with the control and 
HF groups (P , 0.05) (Supplementary Table 2). Similarly, 
CVF, collagen content, and PVCA/LA were significantly 
increased in the chow + STZ and HF groups compared 
with the control (P , 0.01 ; P , 0.001) (Fig. 3F-H). 
Coincident with cardiac dysfunction and hypertrophy, 
myocardial lipid analysis revealed striking myocardial ac-
cumulation of triglycerides in diabetic rats (Fig. 4A and B). 
Diabetic rats had higher Oil Red O-staining areas than other 
groups (Fig. 4B). The mRNA expression levels of TNF-a and 
IL-6 were significantly higher in the diabetic group compared 
with the control (P , 0.05, P , 0.01) (Fig. 4C and D). The 
protein expression levels of TNF-a and IL-6 were signifi-
cantly increased in the diabetic group compared with the </p>

<p>other three groups (Fig. 4E-H). Likewise, the protein 
expression of TNF-a and IL-6 content was increased in 
the chow + STZ and HF groups compared with the control 
(P , 0.01 ; P , 0.001) (Fig. 4F-H). 
Immunohistochemistry and Western blot analysis 
revealed the protein expression of collagen I and III content 
increased in the diabetic group (Fig. 5A and B), and the 
collagen I-to-III ratio significantly elevated compared with 
the control group (216 6 16% vs. 100 6 6%, respectively; 
P , 0.001) (Fig. 5C). Likewise, the protein expression of 
collagen I and III content was increased in the chow + 
STZ and HF groups compared with the control (P , 0.01 
; P , 0.001) (Fig. 5A-C). 
These results show the established type 2 DCM model, 
with insulin resistance, severe LV dysfunction, and myo-
cardial remodeling. </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Diabetes increases collagen I (coll I) and collagen III (coll III) content, suppresses Akt phosphorylation, and partly activates TRB3/MAPK 
pathway. A: Representative immunohistochemical staining of collagen I and III (brown staining considered positive staining; scale bar: 50 mm). 
B: Representative Western blot of collagen I and III content. C: Western blot analysis of collagen I, collagen III, and collagen I-to-III ratio. 
D: Relative mRNA expression and protein content of myocardial TRB3. E: Western blot analysis of p-Akt/Akt, p-ERK/ERK, p-p38/p38, and p-JNK/JNK. 
Data are mean 6 SEM. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01, ***P &lt; 0.001 vs. control;  †P &lt; 0.05,  † †P &lt; 0.01,  ‡P &lt; 0.001 vs. HF; #P &lt; 0.05, ##P &lt; 0.01, ###P &lt; 0.001 
vs. chow + STZ. DM, diabetic rats. (A high-quality digital representation of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>TRB3 GENE SILENCING AND DIABETIC CARDIOMYOPATHY </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>Activated TRB3/MAPK signaling pathway in DCM. 
Cardiac TRB3 mRNA and protein expression was signifi-
cantly increased in diabetic rats (Fig. 5D). We detected Akt 
expression in the myocardium. The phosphorylation of Akt 
was significantly lower in the diabetic group than in the 
control and HF groups (Fig. 5E). 
Accompanied by TRB3 overexpression, the phosphory-
lation of ERK1/2 and JNK was markedly increased, whereas 
that of p38 MAPK was decreased (Fig. 5E), which suggested 
that the TRB3/MAPK signaling pathway participates in the 
pathogenesis of DCM. 
TRB3 gene silencing reverses DCM 
Detection of cardiac TRB3 expression by Western 
blot analysis after gene silencing. When compared 
with vehicle treatment, TRB3-siRNA treatment con-
ferred downregulated mRNA and protein expression of 
cardiac TRB3 (Fig. 6A). The mRNA and protein ex-
pression of hepatic TRB3 was also downregulated com-
pared with the vehicles (Supplementary Fig. 2). </p>

<p>TRB3 gene silencing ameliorated metabolism. Water 
intake and urine volume were decreased in the diabetic 
group with TRB3-siRNA treatment (Supplementary Table 3). 
The elevated serum levels of total cholesterol, triglyceride, 
FFA, and FBG were greatly reduced after 4-week trans-
fection (Supplementary Fig. 3A-D). 
TRB3 gene silencing improved glucose tolerance and 
insulin sensitivity. With TRB3 gene silencing, ISI was 
higher in the diabetic TRB3-siRNA group than vehicle 
(25.17 6 0.14 vs. 25.67 6 0.14, respectively; P , 0.05) 
(Supplementary Fig. 3F). With TRB3-siRNA treatment, 
IPGTT and IPITT results showed a blood glucose level 
significantly lower for TRB3-siRNA-treated rats than the 
vehicle group (P , 0.05) (Supplementary Fig. 4A and B). 
The AUC for glucose and insulin was lower for the diabetic 
than the vehicle group (P , 0.05) (Supplementary Fig. 4C 
and D). The TRB3-siRNA HF group showed lower mean 
AUC on both IPGTT and IPITT than the vehicle group (P , 
0.05) (Supplementary Fig. 4C and D). </p>

<p>FIG. 6. TRB3 gene therapy improves cardiac function in diabetic (DM) rats. A: Relative mRNA expression and protein content of myocardial TRB3 
in gene-silencing groups. B: Representative echocardiograms. C-G: Sequential evaluations of left ventricular end diastolic diameter (LVEDd) (C), 
FS (D), LVEF (E), E/A (F), and E9/A9 (G). H: Pressure curves of cardiac catheterization. I: Analysis of LVEDP with TRB3-siRNA silencing. Data are 
mean 6 SEM; n = 7-10 per group.  §P &lt; 0.05,  § §P &lt; 0.01 vs. DM + vehicle. w, weeks. (A high-quality digital representation of this figure is available 
in the online issue.) </p>

<p>Y. TI AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 </p>

<p>
Recovery of cardiac function in DCM after TRB3 
silencing. During the 4-week follow-up after TRB3-siRNA 
treatment, FS and E9/A9 were improved in the diabetic 
group compared with the vehicle group (FS, 37.66 6 1.09 vs. 
34.83 6 0.57, P , 0.05; E9/A9, 1.08 6 0.11 vs. 0.67 6 0.03, P , 
0.01) (Fig. 6D and G), which suggests that TRB3-siRNA 
treatment prevented LV dysfunction. The decreased LVEDP 
in the TRB3-siRNA diabetic group compared with the vehi-
cle group (12.93 6 1.77 vs. 17.77 6 1.29 mmHg, respectively; 
P , 0.01) (Fig. 6I) reconfirmed the beneficial effect of TRB3-
siRNA on improving LV diastolic dysfunction. Likewise, the 
LVEDP was reduced in the TRB3-siRNA HF group com-
pared with the vehicle group (P , 0.05) (Fig. 6I). 
TRB3 gene silencing reverses myocardial remodeling, 
lipids accumulation, and cardiac inflammation in 
DCM. With TRB3-siRNA treatment, heart weight-to-body 
weight ratio and myocyte size were significantly decreased 
in the diabetic versus the vehicle group (heart weight-to-
body weight ratio: 2.67 6 0.13 vs. 3.49 6 0.36 mg/g, P , 
0.05; myocyte size: 384.32 6 8.69 vs. 440.14 6 4.47 mm 
2 , 
P , 0.01) (Fig. 7B and C). The mRNA expression of 
brain natriuretic protein was lower in both the HF and 
diabetic groups than in the vehicle control (P , 0.001) </p>

<p>(Fig. 7D). CVF and PVCA/LA were reduced (P , 0.001, 
P , 0.01) (Fig. 7F and H). In addition, collagen content 
was lower in the diabetic group than the vehicle group 
(10.17 6 0.41 vs. 13.84 6 0.48 mg/mg LV weight, respectively; 
P , 0.001) (Fig. 7G). Likewise, CVF and PVCA/LA were 
decreased in the TRB3-siRNA HF group (P , 0.05, P , 0.01) 
(Fig. 7F and H). In keeping with these observations, the 
decreased IB% and increased CVIB acquired from the 
IBS of the LV reconfirmed the improved pathological 
manifestations (P , 0.05 ; P , 0.001) (Supplementary 
Table 4). 
The aberrant lipids accumulation within cardiomyocytes 
in diabetic rats was markedly reduced after TRB3 silenc-
ing (P , 0.001) (Fig. 8A and B). Immunohistochemical 
staining and Western blot revealed a significant decrease of 
TNF-a and IL-6 content in the TRB3-siRNA diabetic group 
compared with those of the vehicle (P , 0.001) (Fig. 8E-H). 
Similarly, lipids accumulation and cardiac inflammation 
were reduced in the TRB3-siRNA HF group (P , 0.01, P , 
0.001) (Fig. 8B and E-H). 
TRB3 gene silencing reduced the collagen I-to-III ratio 
and regulated Akt and MAPK pathway. With TRB3-
siRNA treatment, collagen I and the collagen I-to-III ratio </p>

<p>FIG. 7. TRB3 gene therapy decreases myocardial hypertrophy and fibrosis in HF and diabetic (DM) groups. A1: Heart size (scale bar: 2 mm). 
A2: Representative cross sections of hearts at the papillary muscle level (scale bar: 2 mm). A3: Longitudinal sections of LV stained with hema-
toxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) (scale bar: 50 mm). A4: Transverse section of LV stained with H&amp;E (scale bar: 50 mm). B-D: Quantitative data for heart 
weight to body weight (HW-to-BW) ratio, myocyte size, and relative brain natriuretic protein (BNP) mRNA expression. E1-6: Representative 
Masson trichrome staining and Picrosirius red staining. F-H: Quantitative analyses of CVF, collagen content, and PVCA/LA. Data are mean 6 SEM; 
n = 7-10 per group. (A high-quality digital representation of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>TRB3 GENE SILENCING AND DIABETIC CARDIOMYOPATHY </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>were lower in the diabetic than vehicle group (P , 0.001) 
(Fig. 9B and C). The decrease in collagen III content was 
not as great as that of collagen I (P , 0.01) (Fig. 9B and C). 
The inhibited phosphorylation of p-Akt in the diabetic 
group was restored after TRB3 silencing (Fig. 9D). 
With TRB3 silencing, the phosphorylation of ERK1/2 
and JNK was abolished by 53 and 46%, respectively, in the 
diabetic group (Fig. 9D); however, the phosphorylation of 
p38 MAPK was enhanced compared with the vehicle group 
(Fig. 9D). Thus, TRB3 gene silencing appeared to have dif-
ferential effects on ERK1/2, JNK, and p38 MAPK: inhibiting 
ERK1/2 and JNK activation (with a more pronounced effect 
on ERK1/2) but activating p38 MAPK. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>TRB3 is associated with insulin resistance, an important 
trigger in the development of DCM. We found TRB3 was </p>

<p>involved in the pathogenesis of DCM. TRB3 gene silenc-
ing alleviated DCM mainly by modulating MAPK and Akt 
pathways in type 2 diabetes. Thus, TRB3 has a pivotal 
role in DCM and could be an attractive drug target for 
treating type 2 diabetes. 
TRB3, a critical mediator for insulin resistance, is 
implicated in DCM. The insulin-Akt signaling pathway 
regulates mitogenic effects in virtually all metabolic tissues, 
and proteins that inhibit Akt activity are considered potential 
inducers of insulin resistance (28). An example of such 
a protein is the catalytically inactive pseudokinase TRB3 (7). 
TRB3 is overexpressed in murine models of insulin re-
sistance (7,8). In the current study, diabetic rats showed 
severe insulin resistance and increased TRB3 level. Akt ac-
tivation was inhibited. These findings are in accordance with 
previous studies (7,8,28), which indicates insulin resistance 
exists in our type 2 diabetic rat model at the molecular level. </p>

<p>FIG. 8. TRB3 gene silencing decreases aberrant lipid accumulation and cardiac inflammation. A: Representative Oil Red O-stained myocardial sections 
(scale bar: 20 mm). B: Semiquantification of Oil Red O staining. Data are mean 6 SEM of six independent observations in each group. C and D: Relative 
mRNA expression of myocardial TNF-a and IL-6. E: Immunohistochemical staining for myocardial TNF-a and IL-6 (brown staining considered positive 
staining; scale bar: 50 mm). F: Representative Western blot of myocardial TNF-a and IL-6. G and H: Western blot analyses of TNF-a (G) and IL-6 (H). 
Data are mean 6 SEM. DM, diabetic rats. (A high-quality digital representation of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>Y. TI AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 </p>

<p>
In an insulin-resistant state, the phosphatidylinositol 
3-kinase /Akt pathway appears to be selectively blunted, 
compared with the fully activated MAPK pathway (29). 
This situation is known as pathway-selective insulin re-
sistance (12). Kiss-Toth et al. (11) reported that TRB3 might 
be an important modulating protein of MAPK. We found 
TRB3 markedly upregulated in rats with diabetes, which was 
paralleled by increased ERK1/2 and JNK expression. Diabetic 
rats showed prominent collagen accumulation in interstitial 
and perivascular areas on Masson trichrome and Picrosirius 
red staining. Increased cardiac fibrosis, which can increase 
LV stiffness, is a common hallmark of DCM (30). Therefore, 
our diabetic rats showed severe DCM, which was further 
confirmed by elevated LVEDP. Previous studies have shown 
that activated MAPK plays an essential role in collagen syn-
thesis and cardiac fibrosis (15,31). Therefore, activation of 
TRB3 may contribute to the development and progression of 
DCM, possibly mediated by the MAPK pathway. </p>

<p>Together, these data suggest a pivotal role for TRB3 in 
selective insulin resistance by modulating Akt and MAPK 
pathways and implicated in the development of DCM. 
Effect of TRB3 silencing on DCM mediated by MAPK 
and Akt pathways. In light of the pivotal role of TRB3 in 
the development of DCM, we wondered whether down-
regulation of TRB3 could reverse the progression of DCM. 
According to our previous study (14), we used TRB3-
siRNA in vivo in rats. TRB3-siRNA treatment produced no 
notable adverse effects and no deaths in rats. TRB3 mRNA 
levels were significantly decreased, and the protein ex-
pression was reduced by ;60% with TRB3-siRNA treat-
ment in diabetic rats. Thus, global silencing of TRB3 was 
feasible and effective. 
With TRB3 silencing, the impaired glucose tolerance 
and decreased insulin sensitivity were improved, and the 
inhibited activation of Akt was restored. So TRB3 si-
lencing could improve insulin resistance and lower blood </p>

<p>FIG. 9. TRB3 gene silencing decreases collagen expression, restores the phosphorylation of p-Akt, and partly reverses MAPK activation. A: Rep-
resentative immunohistochemical staining showing collagen I and III (scale bar: 50 mm). B: Representative Western blot of collagen I and III. 
C: Western blot analyses of collagen I and III content and collagen I-to-III ratio. D: Western blot analysis of p-Akt/Akt, p-ERK/ERK, p-p38/p38MAPK, 
and p-JNK/JNK. Data are mean 6 SEM. DM, diabetic rats. (A high-quality digital representation of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>TRB3 GENE SILENCING AND DIABETIC CARDIOMYOPATHY </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>glucose, which was attributed to increased phosphory-
lation of Akt (32). 
In addition to improving metabolic disturbance, TRB3 
silencing reduced the aberrant interstitial and perivascular 
collagen accumulation, as well as total collagen content. 
Echocardiography and catheterization results revealed that 
the LV diastolic dysfunction was improved, which was at-
tributed to decreased cardiac fibrosis and reduced collagen 
I-to-collagen III ratio (33). Thus, TRB3 silencing attenuated 
DCM. 
As discussed above, the MAPK pathway likely mediated 
TRB3-related cardiac fibrosis. Intriguingly, we found 
a generalized decrease in phosphorylation of JNK and es-
pecially ERK1/2 in with TRB3 silencing. Combined with 
previous studies (12,14,34), the improvements in cardiac 
fibrosis were primarily attributed to the decreased activa-
tion of ERK1/2. So TRB3 is an effective target to amelio-
rate DCM mainly through the ERK/MAPK pathway. 
With silencing of TRB3, enhanced phosphorylation of 
ERK/MAPK was suppressed, whereas the impaired Akt ac-
tivity was upregulated. These alterations resulted in overall 
improvement of selective insulin resistance. In accordance 
with these changes at the molecular level, TRB3 silencing 
attenuated the cardiac fibrosis and metabolic disturbance in 
type 2 diabetic rats. 
Furthermore, lipids accumulation (35) and inflammation 
(36) in the cardiac tissue play a pivotal role in the patho-
physiology of DCM. In the current study, we also referred to 
these aspects. TRB3 silencing reduced the aberrant lipids 
deposition and cardiac inflammation. However, the un-
derlying mechanisms remain unclear. Further studies have 
to reveal the impact of TRB3 silencing on these effects. 
Conclusions. TRB3, as a critical regulator for selective 
insulin resistance, was implicated in DCM. The cardiopro-
tective effects with TRB3 silencing suggest a potential role 
for TRB3 inhibitors in treating DCM in type 2 diabetes. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by research grants from Key 
Technologies R &amp; D Program of Shandong Province 
(2006GG2202020 and 2010G0020262), the Natural Science 
Foundation of Shandong Province (Y2005C11, ZR2009CM022, 
ZR2009CM025, and BS2009YY026), the National Natural Sci-
ence Foundation of China (30670874, 30871038, 30971215, 
81070192, and 81070141), and the National Basic Research 
Program of China (973 Program, grant 2009CB521904). 
No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article 
were reported. 
Y.T. and G.-l.X. researched data and wrote the manu-
script. Z.-h.W. researched data and contributed to discus-
sion. X.-l.B., W.-y.D., J.W., and G.-h.J. researched data. P.-l.B., 
M.Z., and W.Z. wrote, reviewed, and edited the manuscript. 
Y.Z. reviewed and edited the manuscript. </p>



<p>Y. TI AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 </p>



<p>
 
DIABETES, VOL. 60, NOVEMBER 2011 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

</text></tei>