<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3595621" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Number of clinical trials (CTs) conducted in Iran 
has increased during the past few years (1, 2). Of 
total 10,550 projects conducted in medical re-
search in 2011, 1027 clinical trial files have been 
reviewed in local and national Ethics Committees 
(3) and some 1147 CTs have been registered in 
Iranian Registry of Clinical Trials (IRCT) from a 
total number of 2951 CTs from 2008 to date (4). 
Not all clinical trials conducted in the country are 
aimed to evaluate efficacy and safety of new prod-
ucts and/or to provide evidence for obtaining </p>

<p>market authorization. From a regulatory point of 
view, Ministry of Health and Medical Education 
(MOHME) in Iran, is to establish quality stan-
dards for all medicines registered and to assure 
quality and safety of all medicinal products in 
pharmaceutical market. Food and Drug Organiza-
tion (FDO), within MOHME, as the highest na-
tional regulatory authority over pharmaceutical 
sector, is responsible for this function. 
To address concerns described, FDO has estab-
lished Clinical Trial Committee (CTC) following </p>

<p>Abstract 
Background: Clinical Trial Committee (CTC) has been established in Food and Drug Organization (FDO), in 2003 
to assure efficacy and safety of all types of medicinal products which are meant to be registered in Iran Drug List 
and/or obtain market authorization. 
Methods: All clinical trial files, meeting minutes and databases in CTC secretariat in FDO were reviewed. Relevant 
information and data extracted, analyzed and reported. 
Results: Total number of clinical trial (CT) files received by CTC, in 2011, was 76 cases: 21 CT protocols, 45 CT 
reports and 10 requests for importation of investigational new medicinal products (IMPs). Number of CT files 
received for herbal and natural products was 8 cases while CT files reviewed for vaccines and biological products was 
50; 66% of all CT files received. Local industries sponsored 28 CT studies while 47 studies were supported by 
multinational/foreign companies. Of all CT files reviewed, 54 cases accounted for phase III CTs and 20 cases for 
phase IV and periodic safety updated reports (PSUR). With respect to the decisions made by CTC in 2011, 23 out of 
45 CT reports were approved and the number of clinical trial authorizations (CTA) issued were 11; 52% of all CT 
protocols reviewed. 
Conclusion: Results presented in this report are indicative of a positive trend in compliance of pharmaceutical 
industries and clinical research groups to national regulations of CTs and IR-GCP. Effective communication with 
different parties involved in regulatory and industry sides of CTs will further enhance conducting quality CTs. </p>

<p>Keywords: Regulation, Clinical trials, Iran, Clinical Trial Committee, Report, Iran </p>

<p>Hosseini et al.: Regulatory Aspects of Clinical Trials in Iran … </p>

<p>Available at: http://ijph.tums.ac.ir </p>

<p>
adaptation of Good Clinical Practice (GCP) intro-
duced by the World Health Organization (WHO), 
in 2003. CTC operates under the directorate of 
pharmaceutical and narcotic affairs in FDO and 
closely works with National and Regional Ethics 
Committees (NEC &amp; RECs) and the Iranian Regi-
stry of Clinical Trials (IRCT) in the deputy minis-
try for research and technology, within MOHME 
(5). In fact, CTC, ECs and IRCT construct the 
regulatory framework for oversight of clinical tri-
als in Iran, although the latter had originally been 
established for transparency and validation for 
publications of clinical trial results (1). Currently, 9 
members are serving in CTC including a secreta-
riat, 2 representatives from professional offices in 
FDO, 3 academic members from medical 
universities and 3 academic members from FDO 
Research Centre. A representative from NEC also 
attends the CTC meetings for coordination. 
CTC is supported by a secretariat team of 4, based 
in FDO, and a collaborative network of 90 
reviewers of different specialty from highly re-
puted clinicians and researchers in medical 
universities all over the country. Clinical trial re-
viewer network has been developed and estab-
lished over the past 3 years. 
CTC has been approved, in 2010, by WHO for its 
function on oversight of clinical trials as a part of 
WHO program of National Regulatory Authority 
(NRA) assessment for vaccine quality (6). As a 
WHO recommendation, NRA is required to in-
form the scientific community on regulation of 
clinical trials in the country and presents its annual 
performance on decisions taken on CT files re-
viewed. 
We, therefore, in this report provide CTC perfor-
mance outcome indicators in its third year of 
activity from a regulatory point of view to have 
met WHO NRA assessment program require-
ments. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>This was a review in which all of the CT files, 
meeting agenda, minutes and relevant documents, 
received in 2011 by CTC secretariat in FDO, were </p>

<p>hand searched and data and information extracted 
to measure outcome indicators for CT function in 
the country. Indicators measured included (a) 
number of CT files and applications received in 
the reference year; (b) number of CT files received 
in defined categories i.e. vaccines, biologic prod-
ucts other than vaccines, herbal and natural prod-
ucts, chemical and medical devices in the refer-
ence year; (c) number of decisions taken (approved, 
deferred for clarification or disapproved) on CT 
applications and CT reports; (d) average number 
of days for taking decisions (e) number of CTs in-
spected in the reference year; (f) average number 
of days spent for each GCP inspection. 
Other information such as phase and sponsorship 
of CTs has also been extracted from the databases 
in the CTC secretariat in FDO. The data file was 
constructed in <rs type="software">Microsoft Excel</rs> and analyzed using 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences</rs> Version 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">12.0</rs> and the results presented. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Total number of CT files received by CTC, in 
2011, was 76 cases of which 21 files were CT 
protocols, 45 were CT reports and the remaining 
were requests for importation of investigational 
new medicinal products (IMPs). 
While number of CT files received for herbal and 
natural products was 8, CT file for both vaccines 
and biological products accounted for the highest 
frequency cases received by CTC in the reference 
year (i.e. 50 out of 76; 65%) (Table 1). 
Local industries have sponsored 28 CT studies in 
2011 while sponsors for 47 studies were for-
eign/multinational companies of which in most of 
the cases, CTC reviewed and made the decisions 
based on the documents and reports submitted 
for registration of their products. 
Of all CT files reviewed in 2011, 71% accounted 
for phase III clinical trials while 20 phase IV and 
periodic safety updated reports (PSUR) were re-
viewed by the CTC in the reference year (Table 1). 
With respect to the decisions made by CTC in 
2011, 23 out of 45 clinical trial reports were ap-</p>

<p>Iranian J Publ Health, Vol. 42, No.1, Jan 2013, pp. 102-106 </p>

<p> 
Available at: http://ijph.tums.ac.ir </p>

<p>proved, 20 cases were deferred for clarification 
and 2 reports were rejected (Table 2). </p>

<p>Table 1: CT files received by CTC secretariat in 
2011 </p>

<p>Type 
n % 
Protocols 
21 28 
Interim and final reports 
45 59 
Importation of an IMP* 
10 13 
Category 
Vaccines 
17 22 
Biological products other than vac-
cines </p>

<p>33 43 </p>

<p>Herbal and natural products 
8 11 
Chemical products &amp; medical devices 
18 24 
Sponsor 
Local industry 
28 37 
Multinational/foreign company 
47 62 
Investigator initiated 
1 
1 
Design of CT 
Phase II 
2 
3 
Phase III clinical trials 
54 71 
Phase IV &amp; PSUR** 
20 26 
*: Investigational Medicinal Product; **: Periodic 
Safety Update Report </p>

<p>Number of clinical trial authorizations (CTA) 
issued by CTC, in 2011, were 11 (52% of all CT 
protocols reviewed) that was higher from those in 
previous two years (i.e. 1 and 2, respectively). This 
represents preparation of higher quality CT proto-
cols due to more effective communication 
amongst CTC, pharmaceutical industries and the 
scientific community and enhanced compliance to 
regulation of clinical trials. Average number of 
days for taking decisions by CTC, excluding the 
time spent by the sponsor for completing the 
documents and external reviewers, was 10.2 days 
in the reference year. This represents the time 
from which the feedback from last reviewer is re-
ceived by CTC secretariat to taking decision in the 
CTC and informing the sponsor and/or principal 
investigator. The average time from submission of 
a complete file by the sponsor to a written re-
sponse from CTC has normally been less than a 
week, however; several communications are 
usually made to announce the final CTC decision. </p>

<p>This is while a time elapse of approximately two 
months is spent sometimes, until all required 
documents are provided by the sponsor. </p>

<p>Table 2: Performance outcome of CTC in 2011 </p>

<p>Status of CT files 
n 
% 
Clinical Trial Reports 
Approved 
23 
51 
Deferred for clarification 
20 
44 
Rejected 
2 
5 
Protocols 
CT Authorization issued 
11 
52 
Deferred for modification 
6 
29 
Rejected/Stopped by Sponsor/PI 
for unknown reason </p>

<p>4 
19 </p>

<p>Average number of days spent for 
taking decisions by CTC </p>

<p>10.2 
-</p>

<p>Inspections conducted 
8 
-
Average number of days spent for 
each inspection </p>

<p>1.125 
-</p>

<p>CTC has conducted 8 GCP inspections in 2011 
that is an important attempt by the CTC and 
FDO for auditing clinical trials conducted in the 
country. A multi disciplinary team was recruited 
for each inspection that included 2-3 CTC mem-
bers, clinicians from relevant field of specialty 
from CTC reviewers and officers from the CTC 
secretariat. Inspection checklists which had been 
developed based on WHO recommendations for 
GCP inspections were filled out by each team 
member during the inspection, collected, out-
comes complied and feedback reports sent to the 
principal investigator in the clinical trial site 
and/through the sponsor. With respect to the 
time spent for each inspection, in 7 out of 8 
inspections that took a full working day. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Results presented in this report, provides further 
evidence that regulation of clinical trials in Iran is 
on the right track of moving forwards. Achieve-
ments and areas for improvement for more effi-
cient regulation of conduction of clinical trials are 
further discussed below. </p>

<p>Hosseini et al.: Regulatory Aspects of Clinical Trials in Iran … </p>

<p>Available at: http://ijph.tums.ac.ir </p>

<p>
Number of CT protocols submitted to CTC in 
2011 was almost doubled in the reference year 
compared with those of previous two years (12, 9 
for 2009 &amp; 2010, respectively) (7). This is because 
a number of knowledge based companies have 
been formed during the past couple of years, with 
the help of government, and manufactured several 
medicinal and biosimilar products which are sub-
ject to conducting clinical trials according to 
regulations. 
FDO has more efficiently regulated importation 
of IMPs in 2011 compared to previous two years. 
This is evident from the number of IMP files re-
viewed by CTC (i.e. 10, Table 1) compared to 
those in previous two years of 1 case in 2010 and 
3 cases in 2009 (7). 
With respect to CT files of herbal and natural 
products, it is to be mentioned that, in 2011 only, 
some 137 herbal and natural products have been 
registered in the country while only 8 CT files 
from this category were received by CTC, half of 
that in 2010 (7). This is suggesting that a more 
efficient process/procedure for reviewing CT files 
for herbal and natural products should be consi-
dered. 
Compliance of local pharmaceutical industries to 
the IR-GCP and national regulations of conduct-
ing CTs has considerably increased in the refer-
ence year. This was evident in submitted CT 
protocols by sponsors and also in GCP inspec-
tions conducted by CTC. Quality CT applications 
were more frequently submitted and required 
documents were provided in a shorter time period 
compared to previous two years in which these 
took a much longer time (7). Declaration of 
conflict of interest has also been well absorbed by 
parties involved in conduction of CTs although 
meetings are held in CTC to make sure different 
parties understand their clear roles and 
responsibilities. Calculation of the sample size 
remains a challenging issue in CT protocols 
submitted to CTC, especially for CT protocols on 
biosimilar products. Assumption of the main 
clinical outcome based on which the sample size is 
calculated has usually been unclear. The 
underlying problem for this, as explored in several 
meetings in CTC, was the cost for "reference </p>

<p>drugs" in CTs with "none-inferiority" design that 
was expressed as "unaffordable" by the sponsors. 
A compromised approach has been followed by 
CTC for making decisions on these cases. In a 
number of CT protocols reviewed, there was also 
ambiguity on randomization, blinding and/or 
clearly defining the details of investigational 
products such as batch number, expiry date and 
so on. 
CTC has conducted several GCP inspections in 
2011 (see above). While compliance to IR-GCP 
for conduction of CTs has considerably increased 
compared to previous years, regulations for IMPs 
such as labeling and documentation of inventory 
list were not properly appreciated. In some cases, 
corrections in the source data and case report 
forms were not properly documented and/or 
signatures of principal investigator or patients in 
patient consent forms were missing. 
Several workshops on IR-GCP were conducted in 
medical universities and clinical research centers 
based on the educational package previously 
developed (7). Evaluation of this educational 
package while demonstrated full coverage of 
needs and interests of participants, suggested fur-
ther optimization of the program. Several versions 
of IR-GCP educational package should therefore 
be developed based on the current package, to 
address special needs, roles and responsibilities of 
different stakeholders involved in conducting 
clinical trials. This activity is in process and will be 
implemented once it is finalized. 
The CT reviewers' network of more than 90 profes-
sionals has been established in 2011 and the first 
seminar of clinical trial reviewers has been held in 
the reference year upon which the role and 
responsibilities of CT reviewers, as FDO collabora-
tors, were defined, regulatory expectation addressed 
and the CTC reviewers' database updated. 
A positive impact of CTC in medical scientific 
communities, over 4 years of activity, is the estab-
lishment of a Contract Research Organization 
(CRO) in Tehran University of Medical Sciences 
(TUMS). This governmental CRO is supposed to 
provide consultation to clinical researchers and 
pharmaceutical industries, develop and prepare 
quality CT protocols, and conduct clinical trials in </p>

<p>Iranian J Publ Health, Vol. 42, No.1, Jan 2013, pp. 102-106 </p>

<p> 
Available at: http://ijph.tums.ac.ir </p>

<p>accordance with IR-GCP and national regulations 
of clinical trials. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>A positive trend in regulation and oversight of 
clinical trials has been initiated by CTC during the 
past few years. Further compliance of clinical re-
search groups and pharmaceutical industries to 
national regulations for clinical trials and IR-GCP 
has been demonstrated. This has been achieved by 
effective communication with different parties 
involved in both regulatory and industry sides for 
conduction of clinical trials. These contribute to 
enhancement of social confidence to the health 
system, national drug regulatory authorities, medi-
cal community and quality of pharmaceutical prod-
ucts. Further improvement will be achieved by 
more efficient inter-and intra-sectoral collabora-
tion for conducting quality clinical research. </p>

<p>Ethical considerations </p>

<p>Ethical issues (Including plagiarism, Informed 
Consent, misconduct, data fabrication and/or 
falsification, double publication and/or submis-
sion, redundancy, etc) have been completely ob-
served by the authors. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of 
interest. </p>



</text></tei>