<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3741479" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Objective. Alkaptonuria (AKU) is an ultra-rare autosomal recessive disease that currently lacks an 
appropriate therapy. Recently we provided experimental evidence that AKU is a secondary serum 
amyloid A (SAA)-based amyloidosis. The aim of the present work was to evaluate the use of antioxidants 
to inhibit SAA amyloid and pro-inflammatory cytokine release in AKU. </p>

<p>Methods. We adopted a human chondrocytic cell AKU model to evaluate the anti-amyloid capacity of a 
set of antioxidants that had previously been shown to counteract ochronosis in a serum AKU model. 
Amyloid presence was evaluated by Congo red staining. Homogentisic acid-induced SAA production 
and pro-inflammatory cytokine release (overexpressed in AKU patients) were evaluated by ELISA and 
multiplex systems, respectively. Lipid peroxidation was evaluated by means of a fluorescence-based 
assay. </p>

<p>Results. Our AKU model allowed us to prove the efficacy of ascorbic acid combined with N-acetylcys-
teine, taurine, phytic acid and lipoic acid in significantly inhibiting SAA production, pro-inflammatory cyto-
kine release and membrane lipid peroxidation. </p>

<p>Conclusion. All the tested antioxidant compounds were able to reduce the production of amyloid and 
may be the basis for establishing new therapies for AKU amyloidosis. </p>

<p>Alkaptonuria (AKU; MIM no. 203500) is an ultra-rare 
(1:250 0001 000 000 incidence) autosomal recessive 
inborn error of catabolism of the aromatic amino acids 
phenylalanine and tyrosine due to deficient activity of 
the enzyme homogentisate 1,2-dioxygenase (HGO; EC </p>

<p>1.13.11.5). This leads to the accumulation of homogentisic 
acid (HGA; 2,5-dihydroxyphenylacetic acid). HGA oxidizes 
to benzoquinone acetic acid (BQA), which in turn forms 
melanin-based polymers, deposited in the connective 
tissue of various organs, causing a pigmentation known 
as ochronosis, leading to dramatic tissue degeneration. 
A severe form of arthropathy is the most common clinical 
presentation of AKU but patients often suffer from cardio-
vascular disease (frequent cause of death) and kidney dis-
ease as well. There is no effective cure for AKU at the 
moment and treatment is symptomatic. 
The oxidation of HGA into BQA produces free radical 
species that are associated with tissue oxidative damage 
and are thought to cause degeneration by inciting inflam-
mation [1]. 
We introduced novel human ochronotic cell, tissue and 
serum models and undertook preclinical testing of </p>

<p>1 Immunoematologia Trasfusionale, Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria 
Senese, Policlinico Le Scotte, Siena, Italy, 
2 Dipartimento di 
Biotecnologie, Chimica e Farmacia, Università degli Studi di Siena, 
Siena, Italy, 
3 Dipartimento di Scienze Mediche, Chirurgiche e 
Neuroscienze, Università degli Studi di Siena, Policlinico Le Scotte, 
Siena, Italy and 
4 Dipartimento di Medicina Molecolare e dello Sviluppo, 
Università degli Studi di Siena, Policlinico Le Scotte, Siena, Italy. </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Annalisa Santucci, Università degli Studi di Siena, 
Dipartimento di Biotecnologie, Chimica e Farmacia, via Fiorentina 1, 
53100 Siena, Italy. E-mail: annalisa.santucci@unisi.it </p>

<p>Submitted 6 December 2012; revised version accepted 3 April 2013. </p>

<p>! The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the British Society for Rheumatology. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, 
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>RHEUMATOLOGY </p>

<p>Rheumatology 2013;52:16671673 
doi:10.1093/rheumatology/ket185 
Advance Access publication 23 May 2013 </p>

<p>CLINICAL 
SCIENCE </p>

<p>potential antioxidant therapies for AKU [210]. We previ-
ously found that HGA-induced production of ochronotic 
pigment is accompanied by lipid peroxidation (LPO), 
decreased activity of the enzyme glutathione peroxidase 
and massive depletion of thiol groups, together with 
increased protein carbonylation and thiol oxidation, 
suggesting protein aggregation as one of the possible out-
comes of such an oxidative stress [3, 57]. 
More recently we provided experimental evidence that 
AKU is a secondary serum amyloid A (SAA)-based amyl-
oidosis, thus opening novel perspectives for its treatment 
[11]. Interestingly, we observed a co-localization of 
SAA-amyloid and ochronotic pigment [11]. 
In the present work we further exploited our human 
chondrocytic cell AKU model to evaluate the anti-amyloid 
capacity of antioxidants that we had previously shown to 
be able to counteract ochronosis in a serum AKU model 
[3]. We found that all the tested antioxidant compounds 
(ascorbic acid, N-acetylcysteine, taurine, lipoic acid and 
phytic acid) were able to significantly reduce the produc-
tion of amyloid, inhibit HGA-induced pro-inflammatory 
cytokines and may be the basis for establishing new 
therapies for AKU. </p>

<p>Patients and methods </p>

<p>The study was conducted following approval of the local 
university hospital ethics committee (Comitato Etico 
Locale dell'Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria Senese). 
All patients gave written informed consent prior to inclu-
sion in the study. All reagents were from Sigma-Aldrich (St 
Louis, MO, USA), if not otherwise specified. </p>

<p>AKU cell models and antioxidant treatment </p>

<p>The cell model used for this work was previously 
developed by us and consists of human chondrocytes 
treated with 0.33 mM HGA up to the development of 
ochronosis [2, 4]. First passage chondrocytes were 
seeded into 24-well plates (4 Â 10 
4 cells/well) and grown </p>

<p>until confluence. Chondrocytes were pre-incubated for 
24 h in culture medium in the absence or presence of 
various concentrations of antioxidants previously deter-
mined by us to be effective in reducing ochronotic pig-
ment formation in a serum model of AKU [3]. Stock 
solutions of 100 mM ascorbic acid (Asc), N-acetylcysteine 
(Nac) and taurine (Tau) and a stock solution of 15 mM 
phytic acid (Phy) were prepared in sterile PBS. Lipoic 
acid (Lip) (15 mM) was prepared in sterile dimethyl sulph-
oxide. All the solutions were freshly prepared immediately 
before use, protected from sunlight and serially diluted 
with fresh culture medium to obtain the desired final con-
centrations. For the first screenings, 10 
À5 M antioxidants 
and 0.33 mM HGA (final concentration) were tested; in a 
second phase we focused our research on Nac + Asc and 
tested such antioxidants at 10 
À6 and 10 
À7 M (each) in 
combination. Cells not challenged with exogenously 
added HGA were used as controls. </p>

<p>AKU chondrocytes </p>

<p>Alkaptonuric chondrocytes for the determination of 
released pro-inflammatory cytokines were obtained from 
articular cartilage of AKU patients and cultured, as 
described previously [5, 8, 10]. </p>

<p>Congo Red staining </p>

<p>After 8 days of culture, cells were fixed with 70% ethanol 
for 15 min and observed by microscopy after Congo Red 
(CR) staining, following a modified protocol [12, 13] to 
allow a perfect distinction between collagen and amyloid. 
Samples were incubated in 1% CR for 40 min, washed in 
water, incubated for 10 s in 1 ml of 1% sodium hydroxide 
in 100 ml of 50% ethanol, incubated for 30 s in Mayer's 
haematoxylin, sequentially washed in 50%, 75% and 95% 
ethanol, mounted and observed under a polarized light 
microscope (Zeiss Axio Lab.A1, Arese, Milano, Italy). 
Moreover, CR birefringence was quantified in the polar-
ized images by <rs id="software-0" type="software">Photoshop</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">CSII</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Adobe Systems</rs>, 
Mountain View, CA, USA). Three 20Â fields were chosen 
as to best reflect the overall CR birefringence of cells con-
tained on the entire slide. Total black area was automat-
ically selected. Subsequently the selection was inverted to 
evidence birefringence areas. The number of birefrin-
gence pixels was extrapolated and normalized with the 
total cell number in each field. Finally, based on the ratio 
birefringent pixels/cells, the percentage of birefringence 
inhibition of each antioxidant in HGA-treated cells was 
evaluated. We also evaluated the birefringence generated 
by the cell exposition to each antioxidant compound with-
out HGA treatment. </p>

<p>SAA release measurement </p>

<p>SAA levels were measured in cell culture supernatant by 
ELISA (Invitrogen-Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA) 
after 8 days of culture with or without treatments. </p>

<p>Pro-inflammatory cytokine measurement </p>

<p>The release of a panel of pro-inflammatory cytokines was 
evaluated in cell culture supernatants by Bioplex (Bio-
Rad, Milan, Italy) after 8 days of culture with or without 
treatment. </p>

<p>LPO assay </p>

<p>Human chondrocytes were incubated with a fluorescent 
fatty acid probe (50 mM), 4,4-difluoro-5-(4-phenyl-1,3-
butadienyl)-4-bora-3a,4a-diaza-s-indacene-3-undecanoic 
acid (C11-BODIPY </p>

<p>581/591 </p>

<p>, Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR, 
USA) at 37 
C for 30 min. C11-BODIPY 
581/591 is able to </p>

<p>intercalate in the phospholipids bilayer and LPO was loca-
lized by observing the changes in C11BODIPY 
581/591 fluor-</p>

<p>escence. The intact probe fluoresces red when it is 
intercalated into the membrane ( excitation = 590 nm 
and emission = 635 nm) and shifts to green ( excita-
tion = 485 nm and emission = 535 nm) after oxidative 
radicals attack. Excess probe was removed by washing 
the cells twice with PBS. After incubation with the 
probe, samples were treated with HGA, Nac + Asc or 
Nac + Asc + HGA at 37 
C and 5% CO 2 for 2 h. The staining </p>

<p>1668 </p>

<p>www.rheumatology.oxfordjournals.org </p>

<p>Adriano Spreafico et al. </p>

<p>was examined by Leitz Aristoplan microscope fluores-
cence (Leica, Wetzlar, Germany). Representative 
images were taken in specific areas of samples using 
Leica Q Fluoro Standard, <rs type="software">Leica Chantal</rs> software. The per-
centage of cells showing a high green fluorescence was 
calculated against the total number of cells in each 
sample. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Student's t-test was used when appropriate. Two-tailed 
analysis with P &lt;0.05 was considered significant. 
Correlation analysis was performed using Pearson's 
correlation. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>We evaluated HGA-induced amyloid production in human 
chondrocytes in the absence or presence of antioxidants 
such as Asc, Nac, Asc combined with Nac, Phy, Tau and 
Lip. Our in vitro AKU model allowed a semi-quantitative </p>

<p>analysis of the production of amyloid due to HGA addition 
[11] and its reduction due to treatments with different 
concentrations of antioxidant compounds. CR birefrin-
gence was chosen as a reference parameter to evaluate 
amyloid presence and quantity in cultured AKU chondro-
cytes model. All compounds tested at 10 
À5 M concentra-
tion were able to significantly inhibit amyloid formation 
(Fig. 1A). In particular, 50%, 66% and 71% decreases in 
CR birefringence were observed for Phy, Tau and Lip, 
respectively. We had previously evaluated the beneficial 
effect of the combination of Nac + Asc in counteracting 
ochronosis [3]. In the present work, Nac + Asc confirmed 
their dose-dependent synergistic activity ranging from 
86% to 97% inhibition of amyloid formation (Fig. 1B). 
The Nac + Asc combination was then adopted as the 
elective antioxidant for further investigation. 
HGA-treated chondrocytes express SAA and release it 
in culture supernatant, as revealed in our AKU cell model 
(Fig. 2). HGA treatment increased SAA levels of 
48% with respect to controls. Pretreatment with the </p>

<p>FIG. 1 Antioxidant treatment inhibits HGA-induced amyloid formation in human chondrocytes. </p>

<p>(A, B) HGA-treated human chondrocytes were pretreated with antioxidants and amyloid presence was revealed by CR 
staining. Magnification Â20. (B) Dose-response effect of treatment with N-acetylcysteine and ascorbic acid. 
Magnification Â20. (C) Semi-quantitative analysis of birefringence reduction. Data are the mean of three independent 
experiments each performed in triplicate. P &lt; 0.05. All data were significant. </p>

<p>www.rheumatology.oxfordjournals.org </p>



<p>Antioxidants for alkaptonuric amyloidosis </p>

<p>combination of Nac + Asc was able to decrease SAA 
levels to those of controls (Fig. 2). 
Chondrocytes treated with 0.33 mM HGA also ex-
pressed and released several pro-inflammatory cytokines 
(Fig. 3). Although we are the first to show the expression of 
such pro-inflammatory cytokines under AKU conditions </p>

<p>(Figs. 3 and 4) [11], the role of these molecules in other 
rheumatic diseases, and particularly in cartilage degener-
ation, has been clearly reported. IL-6 is involved in cartil-
age degradation and enhances the production of SAA. 
IL-7 is involved in cartilage destruction not only indirectly 
via inflammatory cells, but also directly via IL-7R-express-
ing chondrocytes [14]. Production of IL-8, MCP-1 and 
MIP-1a by synoviocytes from OA patients has been 
demonstrated both in vivo and in vitro [15]. Although 
in vivo the role of IL-12 is less clear, in vitro studies sug-
gest that IL-12 has a pro-inflammatory function in arthritis. 
IL-2 induces the secretion of IL-1, TNF-a and TNF-b. 
Cytokines such as IL-1 and TNF-a produced by activated 
synoviocytes, mononuclear cells or articular cartilage it-
self significantly upregulate metalloproteinase gene 
expression and the neutralization of IL-1 and/or TNF-a 
upregulation of metalloproteinase gene expression 
appears to be a logical development in the potential med-
ical therapy of OA. IL-17 shows properties similar to those 
of IL-1b and TNF-a. They induce in vitro the synthesis of </p>

<p>FIG. 4 Pro-inflammatory cytokines IL-6 and IL-8 are 
overexpressed in chondrocytes from AKU patients. </p>

<p>(A) IL-6 is overexpressed in chondrocytes from AKU 
patients compared with non-diseased cells. Data are 
reported as the average concentration from three patients 
expressed in pg/ml and are the mean of three independ-
ent experiments each performed in triplicate. P &lt; 0.05. 
(B) IL-8 is overexpressed in chondrocytes from AKU 
patients compared with non-diseased cells. Data are 
reported as the average concentration from three patients 
expressed in pg/ml and are the mean of three independ-
ent experiments each performed in triplicate. P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>FIG. 3 Pro-inflammatory cytokines are overexpressed in 
HGA-treated human chondrocytes, and Nac + Asc 
treatment restores control levels. </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>150% </p>

<p>200% </p>

<p>250% </p>

<p>Ctr 
Eotaxin 
INF-Alpha2 
IL-1Alpha 
IL-1Beta 
IL-2 
IL-3 
IL-5 
IL-6 
IL-7 
IL-8 
IL-12(p40) 
IL-12(p70) 
IL-13 
IL-17 
IP-10 
MCP-1 
MIP-1Alpha 
MIP-1Beta 
TNF-Alpha 
TNF-Beta </p>

<p>0.3mMHGA 
0.3 mMHGA+10E-6MNac+10-6MAsc </p>

<p>Data are the mean of three independent experiments each 
performed in triplicate. P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>FIG. 2 HGA-treated human chondrocytes overexpress 
and release SAA, and Nac + Asc treatment restores con-
trol levels. </p>

<p>Data are the mean of three independent experiments each 
performed in triplicate. P &lt; 0.05. </p>



<p>www.rheumatology.oxfordjournals.org </p>

<p>Adriano Spreafico et al. </p>

<p>nitric oxide and metalloproteases by chondrocytes and 
the production of IL-6 and IL-8 by fibroblasts [16]. 
Eotaxin-1 plays an important role in cartilage degrad-
ation in OA [17]. The combined treatment with 10 
À6 M 
Nac + Asc proved to be able to significantly decrease 
pro-inflammatory cytokine levels or even restore control 
levels (Fig. 3). 
Indeed, once evaluated in chondrocytes extracted from 
cartilage of AKU patients [5], we found overexpression 
and release of high levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines 
IL-6 (9-fold change with respect to control, Fig. 4A) and 
IL-8 (20-fold change with respect to control, Fig. 4B). 
In human chondrocytes we observed that LPO localiza-
tion was extended to the whole plasma membrane 
(Fig. 5A). The percentage of high green fluorescence, an 
index of LPO, observed in samples treated with HGA 
(0.33 mM) confirmed that this compound induced LPO 
on chondrocyte plasma membranes after 2 h of treatment 
(83.3% ± 7.5%); this percentage was higher compared 
with that of cells treated with HGA in the presence of 
Nac + Asc (HGA + Nac + Asc, 40.6% ± 4.5%). Samples 
treated with antioxidants (Nac + Asc) and without any 
treatment (control) showed a low percentage of high 
green fluorescence, 21% ± 6% and 15.3% ± 2.5%, 
respectively (Fig. 5). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>There is no appropriate therapy for AKU at the moment. 
Alkaptonuric ochronosis can be treated symptomatically 
during the early stages, whereas for end stages total joint 
replacement may be required. We have recently shown 
that SAA amyloidosis is a secondary complication of 
AKU, due to a chronic inflammatory status derived from 
HGA-BQA-melanin-induced oxidative stress [7, 11]. We 
also proved that MTX has excellent efficacy in inhibiting 
the production of amyloid in our AKU model chondro-
cytes, suggesting the introduction of its use in AKU ther-
apy [11]. This and other alternative treatments (i.e. 
administration of antioxidants) would be useful, especially 
for those symptomatic AKU patients for whom the therapy 
with nitisinone (the only orphan drug so far recognized for 
AKU) failed in a clinical trial [18]. 
Oxidative stress is a key mechanism for the develop-
ment of alkaptonuric ochronosis and, consequently, 
ochronotic arthropathy and for the development of any 
form of amyloidosis as well. 
Oxidized proteins are generally more prone to misfold-
ing and aggregation [19]. It is well known that HGA under-
goes spontaneous oxidation into BQA, and that such a 
process is a source of ROS, further promoting oxidative 
stress [20]. In our previous work we highlighted that BQA-
mediated toxicity may provide a mechanistic link between 
oxidative stress and structural/functional organization of 
macromolecules and the production of ochronotic pig-
ment through the propagation of oxidative stress and en-
hancement of protein aggregation [7]. 
Both HGA and BQA can also deplete systemic or local 
antioxidants, causing oxidative damage of macromol-
ecules; although alkaptonuric ochronosis develops </p>

<p>around the third to fourth decade of life, its real onset 
may be the consequence of repeated oxidative damage 
of target tissues initiated by HGA auto-oxidation. This 
implies that at some point in the development of ochro-
nosis, antioxidant defences may be overwhelmed by ROS 
or their by-products originated by the circulating HGA and 
BQA excess. In this case, a suitable antioxidant therapy, 
especially if preventative, may be helpful in delaying dis-
ease progression. To this end, the identification of the 
right compound to be used and its optimal concentration 
are of crucial importance. 
We previously reported that AKU cells are markedly 
oxidized and try to react to this type of stress [37]. We 
also proposed the use of antioxidants to prevent the 
oxidation of HGA into BQA that induces the production 
of ROS, thus causing tissue damage by inciting 
inflammation [3, 4, 6, 7]. Treatment of AKU patients with 
Asc to prevent HGA oxidation is very controversial, 
since Asc can act as a pro-oxidant and auto-co-oxidate 
with HGA, leading to the production of additional 
ROS [20]. 
It has been demonstrated that Nac, whose safety is 
supported by more than 40 years of clinical use, inhibits 
HGA polymerization [21, 22], and we also proved the ef-
ficacy of the co-administration of Nac and Asc to coun-
teract the negative effects of HGA for the treatment of 
ochronotic arthropathy [3, 4]. In fact, Nac and Asc have 
additive properties and Nac is able to prevent the pro-
oxidative effects of Asc [23]. In a previous work, we 
showed in an in vitro serum model that the most effective 
antioxidant compounds in reducing the production of 
HGA-induced ochronotic pigment and in protecting 
protein thiols and proteins from carbonylation are Phy, 
Tau, Lip and Nac + Asc [3]. 
Membrane unsaturated fatty acids are susceptible to 
oxidative damage and the resultant LPO can alter mem-
brane fluidity and permeability. We have already indi-
cated in an in vitro serum model that HGA can induce 
LPO [7]. Interestingly, our previous study [11] found 
amyloid deposits on the surface of AKU cartilage that 
is directly bathed in SF and/or in the perivascular area 
of the synovia. These observations indicate the possi-
bility that oxidative damage and consequent hyperper-
meability in synovial vessels may promote plasma 
proteins such as SAA to pass through the vessels and 
deposit in the articular tissues. The low molecular 
weight of SAA, its high affinity for the extracellular 
matrix, namely collagen, and its high plasma concentra-
tion in AKU may promote such a passage. If this hy-
pothesis is true, redox therapy or strategies aimed at 
blocking oxidative stimulant formation could be useful 
in the prevention and treatment of AKU and of the 
related amyloidosis. Here we presented data indicating 
lipid peroxidative damage of chondrocyte plasma mem-
brane due to HGA that may be counteracted by tested 
antioxidants. 
In the present work we also showed that HGA-treated 
human chondrocytes released SAA and that Nac + Asc 
can have a beneficial effect in restoring normal levels. In </p>

<p>www.rheumatology.oxfordjournals.org </p>



<p>Antioxidants for alkaptonuric amyloidosis </p>

<p>the evaluation of antioxidant treatments in an in vitro 
model of alkaptonuric ochronosis we also established 
the efficacy of Nac + Asc, Tau, Phy and Lip in counteract-
ing the production of HGA-related amyloid deposits [11]. </p>

<p>HGA-treated cells overexpressed various cytokines, 
including IL-8, IL-6 and TNF-a [11]. We have previously 
shown that AKU patients have high levels of plasma SAA, 
suggesting SAA to be involved in the pathogenesis of AKU 
[11]. However, it remained unclear whether SAA was 
involved in the overproduction of pro-inflammatory cyto-
kines in AKU tissues. SAA is implicated in rheumatoid in-
flammatory processes through stimulating chondrocytes 
to produce IL-6 that in turn is recognized as the main 
inducer of most acute-phase proteins, including SAA. 
Therefore SAA-induced IL-6 production may enhance 
the sustained SAA production in an autocrine manner 
that perpetuates the rheumatoid inflammation. Here we 
showed that chondrocytes extracted from AKU patients' 
cartilage produce high levels of IL-8 and IL-6, suggesting 
that these ILs could play a role in AKU progression. Taken 
together, the results obtained in this study demonstrate 
that it is possible to take advantage of the adoption of 
molecules that combine a range of important antioxidant 
and anti-amyloidogenic properties for the treatment of 
AKU. </p>

<p>Rheumatology key messages </p>

<p>. The identification of antioxidants as potential thera-
peutics will be beneficial for AKU amyloidosis 
treatment. 
. Antioxidants inhibit SAA production and pro-inflam-
matory cytokine release in alkaptonuria. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors thank aim AKU, Associazione Italiana Malati 
di Alcaptonuria (ORPHA263402), Toscana Life Sciences 
Orphan_1 project, Fondazione Monte dei Paschi di 
Siena 2008-2010 and FP7 Research &amp; Innovation Grant 
304985-2 DevelopAKUre. </p>

<p>Funding: This work was supported by Telethon Italy grant 
GGP10058. </p>

<p>Disclosure statement: The authors have declared no con-
flicts of interest. </p>



<p>2 Tinti L, Taylor AM, Santucci A et al. Development of an 
in vitro model to investigate joint ochronosis in alkapto-
nuria. Rheumatology 2010;50:2717. </p>

<p>3 Braconi D, Laschi M, Amato L et al. Evaluation 
of anti-oxidant treatments in an in vitro model 
of alkaptonuric ochronosis. Rheumatology 2010;49: 
197583. </p>

<p>4 Tinti L, Spreafico A, Braconi D et al. Evaluation of anti-
oxidant drugs for the treatment of ochronotic alkaptonuria </p>

<p>FIG. 5 LPO assay. </p>

<p>(A) Fluorescence micrographs of human chondrocytes 
treated with HGA, N-acetylcysteine + ascorbic acid (Nac/ 
Asc), HGA in the presence of N-acetylcysteine + ascorbic 
acid (HGA + Nac/Asc); CTR: human chondrocytes without 
any treatment. For each sample, two micrographs were 
acquired (only specific areas are shown): red colour 
showing the intercalated probe in the membrane and 
green colour showing the intensity of LPO. Bar = 5 mm. 
(B) Mean and S.D. of the percentage of human chondro-
cytes (calculated against the total number of cells) that 
showed a high green fluorescence (C11-BODIPY </p>

<p>581/591 </p>

<p>probe), an index of LPO, are reported. </p>



<p>www.rheumatology.oxfordjournals.org </p>

<p>Adriano Spreafico et al. </p>





<p>Antioxidants for alkaptonuric amyloidosis </p>

</text></tei>