<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3998155" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Schistosomiasis-associated pulmonary arterial hypertension (SPAH) is a major concern worldwide. 
However, the role of gender-specific contributing factors in SPAH is unknown. </p>

<p>Objective: We investigated how systolic pulmonary artery pressure (SPAP) values and the presence of severe SPAP relate 
to gender, menopausal status, and pregnancy history in SPAH patients. </p>

<p>Methods: Seventy-nine patients diagnosed with SPAH from 2000 to 2009 were assessed and 66 were enrolled in the study. 
Information about age, menopausal status, pregnancy, echocardiography-derived SPAP, and invasive mean pulmonary 
artery pressure (mPAP) was collected from medical records. The relation between values of SPAP and mPAP and their 
agreement for severe disease were assessed. Regression models assessed the association of gender, menopausal status, 
and pregnancy history with SPAP values and the presence of severe SPAP. </p>

<p>Results: Moderate correlation and good agreement for severe disease were found between mPAP and SPAP. Mean SPAP 
values were similar for men and women. A trend toward higher values of SPAP was found for non-menopausal women 
compared to men. Higher SPAP values were found for menopausal compared to non-menopausal women; the values 
were non-significant after adjustment for age. Pregnancy history had no association with SPAP. Menopause and positive 
pregnancy had no association with severe SPAP. </p>

<p>Conclusion: In SPAH patients, neither gender, nor menopausal status, nor pregnancy history showed independent 
correlation with SPAP values assessed by echocardiography. (Arq Bras Cardiol. 2013;101(2):154-159) </p>

<p>Keywords: Hypertension, Pulmonary; Schistosomiasis; Pregnancy; Menopause; Echocardiography, Doppler. </p>

<p>Acronym and abbreviation list </p>

<p>mPAP -mean pulmonary artery pressure </p>

<p>PAH -pulmonary arterial hypertension </p>

<p>SPAP -pulmonary artery systolic pressure </p>

<p>SPAH -schistosomiasis-associated pulmonary arterial 
hypertension </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Schistosomiasis affects about 207 million people worldwide 
and is known as a potential trigger for the pulmonary 
arterial hypertension (PAH) immune-inflammatory pathway. </p>

<p>Schistosomiasis-associated PAH (SPAH) is recognized as one 
of the most important etiologies of PAH -with a prevalence 
of approximately 5% in patients with hepatosplenic 
schistosomiasis. PAH is a high-risk condition, related to 
elevated rates of mortality </p>

<p>1-6   . However, literature regarding 
the clinical presentation of SPAH is limited. </p>

<p>Echocardiography-derived systolic pulmonary artery 
pressure (SPAP) is usually used to screen patients suspected 
of PAH. Adding right atrial pressure to the pressure gradient 
between right atrium and ventricle has been validated as 
a method to assess SPAP over the decades 
7,8 . In fact, SPAP 
assessed by Doppler-echocardiography is a well-established 
method in clinical practice, being widely available, 
inexpensive, and safe 
9-15 . </p>

<p>In PAH clinical presentation, the role of gender-specific 
characteristics is controversial. Despite the evidence that 
female hormonal balance could be related to pulmonary 
artery pressure, studies have failed to demonstrate significant 
differences in the prognosis of PAH in men compared to 
women 
16-18 . Moreover, the interest in menopausal aspects 
of PAH is growing, as postmenopausal women have shown 
significant susceptibility to elevated pulmonary pressure </p>

<p>19,20   . </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Armstrong et al. 
SPAP, gender, menopause, and pregnancy in SAPAH </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2013;101(2):154-159 </p>

<p>We investigated how SPAP values and severity relate 
to gender in patients with SPAH. We also explored the 
association of SPAP with menopausal status and pregnancy 
history in the female population. Finally, we compared 
echocardiography-derived SPAP values to values of invasive 
mean pulmonary artery pressure (mPAP). </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study design and population </p>

<p>We enrolled 89 patients (67% women) who had been 
diagnosed with SPAH by the Pulmonary Hypertension 
Group at University of Pernambuco (Recife, Brazil) between 
January 2000 and November 2009. Investigation for 
PAH follows the protocol suggested by Gaine and Rubin, 
including diagnostic right-chamber catheterization to 
ensure values of mPAP &gt; 25 mmHg and pulmonary capillary 
wedge pressure (PCWP) &lt;15 mmHg 
21 . The diagnosis 
of schistosomiasis is individually assessed and based on 
exposure history and stool samples, with confirmatory rectal 
biopsy and/or serology in specific cases 
22 . In the absence of 
other etiology, SPAH was defined when schistosomiasis and 
portal fibrosis were present in a patient with PAH assessed 
by invasive right-chamber catheterization. Our study was 
approved by the local ethics committee. </p>

<p>SPAP assessment </p>

<p>SPAP data were collected from the first registered 
echocardiogram performed and interpreted by staff 
cardiologists at the institution of enrolment. Suboptimal 
echocardiogram views or inadequate tricuspid regurgitation 
were present in 4 men and 9 women. The institution's 
protocol to assess SPAP dictates the following: (a) patient 
in the left lateral decubitus position; (b) color flow 
Doppler imaging is used to identify and guide alignment 
of the cursor with the tricuspid regurgitant jet; (c) using 
continuous-wave Doppler, tricuspid regurgitation velocity is 
assessed from different views to measure peak velocity (v); 
(d) transtricuspid pressure gradient is calculated using the 
modified Bernoulli equation (4v 
2 ) 
7 ; (e) right atrial pressure 
is evaluated by assessing the respiratory variation in the 
diameter of the inferior vena cava (values estimated as 
5, 10, or 15 mmHg); and (f) SPAP is calculated by adding 
the transtricuspid pressure gradient to the atrial pressure 
estimate. The measurement is not performed if there is 
evidence of obstruction to pulmonary artery flow, such as 
pulmonary stenosis or right ventricular outflow obstruction. </p>

<p>Additional data acquisition </p>

<p>Information on age, menopausal status, and pregnancy 
history at the diagnosis of SPAH was collected from 
medical records on all patients followed in the institution. 
Information on menopausal status was present in 35 women 
(58% menopause positive) and data on pregnancy 
history was collected in 20 women (13 had positive 
history for pregnancy; 56% vs. 73% for non-menopausal 
vs. menopausal women, respectively). Invasive mean 
pulmonary artery pressure (mPAP), assessed by diagnostic </p>

<p>right-chamber catheterization, was also collected if the 
interval to the assessment of echocardiography-derived 
SPAP did not exceed 6 months (n = 42; 81% females; 
age 44.5 ± 14.3 years; SPAP 96.7 ± 28.8 mmHg; and 
mPAP 60.3 ± 14.7 mmHg). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The software <rs id="software-0" type="software">STATA</rs>, version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">11.2</rs>, was used to perform 
the statistical analysis on a cross-sectional basis. Student's 
t-test was used to assess differences between mean values 
and the z-test was used to assess differences between 
proportions. Severe SPAP and mPAP were defined as the 
4 
th quartile in both cases (≥ 120 mmHg and ≥ 76 mmHg 
for SPAP and mPAP, respectively). The relationship between 
echocardiography-derived SPAP and invasive mPAP was 
assessed by Pearson's correlation. Percent agreement and 
Cohen's kappa coefficient for severe classification of SPAP 
and mPAP were also computed. </p>

<p>The relation of SPAP, gender, and menopausal status 
was assessed using linear regression. Logistic regression was 
used to compute odds ratios for severe SPAP, according to 
gender and menopausal status. Regression models were 
performed on univariate and multivariate bases, adjusted 
to age at diagnosis. Menopausal status as a predictor of 
SPAP values was compared to male gender and as a binary 
variable in a female-only subset. For a subgroup of women 
diagnosed with SPAH, an additional analysis assessed the 
influence of pregnancy history (used as a binary variable) 
in the regression models. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>A total of 66 patients with data on SPAP were included. 
Patient characteristics are shown in Table 1, arranged 
according to gender and menopausal status. A moderate 
correlation was found between mPAP and SPAP (r = 0.51, 
p &lt; 0.001; Figure 1). In this group, both methods classified 
10 cases as severe SPAH, agreeing in 82% of the classifications 
(Kappa coefficient = 0.3; p &lt; 0.01). Mean SPAP values 
were similar for men and women (Table 1). In addition, no 
significant difference was found when menopausal women 
were compared to men. However, higher values of SPAP 
were found for non-menopausal women compared to men, 
with a trend in significance (Table 2). </p>

<p>Among females, statistically significant higher mean 
SPAP values and ages were found for menopausal 
women (Table 1). However, the differences become 
non-significant after adjustment for age. The mean 
SPAP was 118.3 ± 32.3 mmHg and 95.1 ± 26.2 mmHg 
(p = 0.1) for women without and with previous pregnancy, 
respectively. No statistical significance was found when 
history of pregnancies was added as a covariate (Table 2). </p>

<p>C o n s i d e r i n g t h e p r e d i c t i o n o f s e v e r e S PA H 
(SPAP &gt; 120 mmHg), the presence of menopause and a 
positive history for pregnancy were consistently associated 
with low odds ratios; however, although trends were present, 
no statistically significant odds ratio was reported (Table 3). </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Armstrong et al. 
SPAP, gender, menopause, and pregnancy in SAPAH </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2013;101(2):154-159 </p>

<p>Figure 1 -Scatter plot for the correlation between echocardiography-derived SPAP and invasive mPAP in patients with schistosomiasis-associated pulmonary 
hypertension (n = 42). SPAP: Systolic pulmonary artery pressure by echocardiography; mPAP: mean pulmonary artery pressure by invasive measurement. </p>

<p>Table 1 -Characteristics of patients with schistosomiasis-associated pulmonary hypertension, arranged according to gender and 
menopausal status </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Gender (mean ± SD) 
Menopausal status (mean ± SD) </p>

<p>Men 
(n = 15) </p>

<p>Women 
(n = 51) 
p 
Absent 
(n = 15) </p>

<p>Present 
(n = 20) 
p </p>

<p>Age at diagnosis (years) 
46.8 ± 12.8 
45.9 ± 15.1 
0.8 
29.4 ± 6.8 
58.4 ± 9.8 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>SPAP (mmHg) 
87.8 ± 31.6 
93.8 ± 28.3 
0.5 
110.7 ± 26.0 
86.5 ± 20.0 
0.003 </p>

<p>Number of pregnancies 
NA 
3.2 ± 2.8 
NA 
1.6 ± 0.5 
4.2 ± 3.2 
0.098 </p>

<p>SD: standard deviation; SPAP: systolic pulmonary artery pressure; NA: non-applicable. Mean number of pregnancies excludes patients without history of pregnancy 
(7 cases overall; 2 with positive menopausal status). T-test was used to acquire p-values. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>More than 770 million people worldwide are at risk of 
contracting schistosomiasis 
2,23 . The prevalence of elevated 
pulmonary pressures in patients with schistosomiasis is still 
controversial, but it has been reported as one of the most 
important etiologies of PAH 
1-5,24,25 . This is the first study 
to assess the influence of gender on echocardiography-
derived SPAP and to investigate the role of menopausal 
status and pregnancy history among patients diagnosed 
with SPAH. </p>

<p>The estimation of SPAP by Doppler echocardiography is 
validated, safe, usually feasible, and universally adopted in 
screening protocols for PAH </p>

<p>8,26-28   . We showed a moderate 
correlation between echocardiography-derived SPAP and invasive 
measurement of mPAP in patients with SPAH (Figure 1), with 
82% of agreement and a fair Kappa coefficient when classifying 
the most severe cases. mPAP values assessed by right-chamber 
catheterization are considered the gold standard for the diagnosis 
of PAH. Similar to our study, diverse reports have shown that the 
correlation between SPAP values estimated by echocardiography 
and determined invasively is moderate to strong </p>

<p>7,11,12,29,30   . </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Armstrong et al. 
SPAP, gender, menopause, and pregnancy in SAPAH </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2013;101(2):154-159 </p>

<p>Table 2 -Linear regression models for SPAP (mmHg) according to gender, menopausal status, and pregnancy history </p>

<p>Predictor 
n 
Regression coefficients (p value) </p>

<p>Univariate 
MODEL 1 
MODEL 2 </p>

<p>Female (vs. male) 
66 
6.0 (0.48) 
13.7 (0.09) </p>

<p>NA 
non-menopausal women (vs. male) 
51 
22.9 (0.02) 
23.4 (0.05) </p>

<p>Menopausal women (vs. male) 
51 
-1.3 (0.88) 
5.4 (0.59) </p>

<p>Menopausal present (vs. absent) </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>36 
-24.2 (0.003) 
-8.4 (0.58) 
-38.7 (0.11) </p>

<p>Pregnancy present (vs. absent) 
20 
-23.1 (0.10) 
-13.9 (0.31) 
-20.1 (0.15) </p>

<p>SPAP: systolic pulmonary artery pressure; NA: non-applicable. MODEL 1 -adjusted for age; MODEL 2 -age, menopausal status, and pregnancy history in the same 
model.  § In MODEL 2, analysis used n = 20. </p>

<p>Table 3 -Logistic regression models for severe SPAP (≥ 120 mmHg) according to gender, menopausal status, and pregnancy history </p>

<p>Predictor 
n 
Odds Ratio (p value) </p>

<p>Univariate 
MODEL 1 
MODEL 2 </p>

<p>Female (vs. male) 
66 
1.2 (0.77) 
1.7 (0.51) </p>

<p>NA 
non-menopausal women (vs. male) 
51 
2.0 (0.41) 
5.5 (0.19) </p>

<p>Menopausal women (vs. male) 
51 
0.4 (0.38) 
0.4 (0.39) </p>

<p>Menopausal present (vs. absent) </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>36 
0.2 (0.09) 
0.4 (0.62) 
0.03 (0.14) </p>

<p>Pregnancy present (vs. absent) 
20 
0.2 (0.14) 
0.3 (0.27) 
0.1 (0.13) </p>

<p>SPAP: systolic pulmonary arterial pressure; NA: non-applicable. MODEL 1 -adjusted for age; MODEL 2 -age, menopausal status, and pregnancy history in the same 
model. 
 § In MODEL 2, analysis used n = 20. </p>

<p>We found a predominance of females in our SPAH 
patients (67%). A similar predominance of females has 
been reported for other PAH etiologies, but the real 
influence of gender in PAH is still controversial. The higher 
prevalence of PAH in women compared to men, the 
thrombogenic effects of estrogen, and the fluctuation of 
estrogen metabolites may indicate potential negative effects 
of female physiology on the pulmonary vasculature 
31,32 . 
Estrogen, however, also showed benefits for pulmonary 
vasculature in both acute and chronic experimental models 
of pulmonary hypertension 
31,32 . We found similar values of 
SPAP in men and women with SPAH. Moreover, gender had 
no statistically significant predictive ability for SPAP when 
adjusted for age at diagnosis (Table 2). </p>

<p>Pulmonary artery vasoreactivity is affected by changes in 
estrogen levels, even in a physiological range 
33 . Menopausal 
status represents an important decrease in the circulating 
estrogen in women. Among patients with systemic sclerosis, 
postmenopausal women have shown an increased risk for 
the development of PAH 
19 . In fact, the majority of pulmonary 
hypertensive women in the University of Colorado Pulmonary 
Hypertension Center were postmenopausal 
20 . Our study has 
intrinsic limitations related to the information on menopausal 
status collected from medical records. In addition, the real 
influence of hormonal imbalance could not be assessed, 
due to the absence of serum hormonal values in our data. </p>

<p>In the subset of SPAH patients who were women, the 
association between menopausal status and SPAP had no 
statistical significance when adjusted for age (Table 2). In 
univariate analysis with SPAH patients, non-menopausal 
females showed significantly higher SPAP values compared 
to men; however, this association had borderline statistical 
significance (p = 0.05) after adjustment for age (Table 2). 
Our results suggest that the differences found comparing 
post-menopausal and non-menopausal subjects are due to 
the influence of age on SPAP. In fact, the positive correlation 
between SPAP values and age has been seen in a large 
population of participants free of PAH. In this population, the 
relationship seems to be mediated by left ventricular diastolic 
dysfunction and systemic vascular stiffening 
34 . </p>

<p>Hormonal and hemodynamic changes that occur during 
pregnancy contribute to the high maternal mortality in 
women with pulmonary vascular disease 
35 . The influence 
of previous pregnancies on the clinical presentation of 
SPAH, however, is unknown. In 20 women at the time 
of diagnosis for SPAH, we assessed the influence of a 
positive pregnancy history on the values of SPAP. Thus, 
the reduced number of patients probably limited the 
analysis. In our population, positive pregnancy history did 
not show statistically significant association with SPAP in 
women with SPAH. </p>

<p>157 </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Armstrong et al. 
SPAP, gender, menopause, and pregnancy in SAPAH </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2013;101(2):154-159 </p>



<p>References </p>

<p>There is evidence that female hormonal imbalance 
may relate to the severity of pulmonary pressure values. 
Experimental models showed more severe pulmonary 
hypertension in chronically hypoxemic rodents that have 
had their ovaries removed than those with intact ovaries. In 
this study, the return of estrogens after an ovariectomy led 
to a regression to baseline levels of pulmonary pressure 
36 . 
Moreover, a history of previous pregnancies showed 
prognostic value in pregnant patients with pulmonary 
hypertension 
37 . We investigated how gender, menopausal 
status, and pregnancy history predicted severe SPAP values 
(&gt; 120 mmHg) in SPAH patients, but found no statistically 
significant association (Table 3). </p>

<p>Our study contributes to the knowledge of SPAH clinical 
presentation and its relation to gender, menopausal status, 
and pregnancy history; however, the role of gender-specific 
characteristics in the pathological processes of SPAH is yet 
to be defined. Further studies are needed to establish the 
relations between gender particularities and SPAH clinical 
presentation. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In a population of SPAH patients, neither gender, 
nor menopausal status, nor pregnancy history showed a 
statistically significant, independent relationship to SPAP 
values assessed by echocardiography. Differences in SPAP 
that appear to be related to menopausal status seem to be 
mediated by age differences. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>Conception and design of the research: Armstrong AC, 
Bandeira AMP, Correia LCL, Lima JAC, Sobral Filho DC; 
Acquisition of data: Armstrong AC, Bandeira AMP, Melo 
HCO, Silveira CAM, Albuquerque E, Moraes Jr. JC, Silva 
AML, Sobral Filho DC; Analysis and interpretation of the 
data: Armstrong AC, Bandeira AMP, Correia LCL, Melo HCO, 
Silveira CAM, Albuquerque E, Moraes Jr. JC, Silva AML, 
Lima JAC, Sobral Filho DC; Statistical analysis: Armstrong 
AC, Bandeira AMP, Correia LCL, Sobral Filho DC; Writing of 
the manuscript: Armstrong AC, Lima JAC, Sobral Filho DC; 
Critical revision of the manuscript for intellectual content: 
Armstrong AC, Bandeira AMP, Correia LC, Melo HCO, 
Silveira CAM, Albuquerque E, Moraes Jr. JC, Silva AML, Lima 
JAC, Sobral Filho DC. </p>

<p>Potential Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article 
was reported. </p>

<p>Sources of Funding </p>

<p>There were no external funding sources for this study. </p>

<p>Study Association </p>

<p>This article is part of the thesis of master submitted 
by Anderson da Costa Armstrong, from Universidade de 
Pernambuco. </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Armstrong et al. 
SPAP, gender, menopause, and pregnancy in SAPAH </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2013;101(2):154-159 </p>





</text></tei>