<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3329738" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:43+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>One of the important goals of most biological investigations is to classify and organize the 
experimental findings so that they are readily useful for deriving generalized rules. Although 
there is a huge amount of information on RNA structures in PDB, there are redundant 
files, ambiguous synthetic sequences etc. Moreover, a systematic hierarchical organiza-
tion, reflecting RNA classification, is missing in PDB. In this investigation, we have classified 
all the available RNA structures from PDB through a programmatic approach. Hence, it 
would be now a simple assignment to regularly update the classification as and when 
new structures are released. The classification can further determine (i) a non-redundant 
set of RNA structures and (ii) if available, a set of structures of identical sequence and 
function, which can highlight structural polymorphism, ligand-induced conformational alter-
ations etc. Presently, we have classified the available structures (2095 PDB entries having 
RNA chain longer than nine nucleotides solved by X-ray crystallography or NMR spec-
troscopy) into nine functional classes.The structures of same function and same source are 
mostly seen to be similar with subtle differences depending on their functional complexa-
tion. The web-server is available online at http://www.saha.ac.in/biop/www/HD-RNAS.html 
and is updated regularly. </p>

<p>Keeping pace with advancement in the field of RNA functions, 
the number of RNA structures whose coordinates are available 
in the Protein Data Bank (PDB; Berman et al., 2000) is growing 
rapidly. The total number of structures of RNA with oligomeric 
or polymeric length, as available in July 2011, is 2095 and the 
number is increasing at a pace of about 100 per year. The deter-
mination of various RNA structures, such as the hammerhead 
ribozyme (Scott et al., 1995), SRP-RNA (Zwieb et al., 2005), and 
the 5S, 16S and 23S RNAs of ribosome has greatly increased our 
knowledge of RNA folds and the three-dimensional organization 
of RNA chains (Batey et al., 1999; Ferre-d'Amare and Doudna, 
1999; Hermann and Patel, 1999). Collectively, these structures pro-
vide a large amount of information about RNA structural motifs 
(Moore, 1999). Similar exponential growth in number of crystal 
structures of proteins is also taking place in the PDB. Consider-
ing the need of classification of these proteins, there are a number 
of methods available, such as SCOP (Murzin et al., 1995; Hub-
bard et al., 1997), FSSP (Holm and Sander, 1997), Pisces (Wang 
and Dunbrack, 2005), BIPA (Lee and Blundell, 2009) etc. These 
methods can classify a protein structure based on its structural 
class, source organism, secondary structure content, resolution, 
etc. One can further determine a set of non-redundant structures 
of proteins, which are not evolutionarily related, for a statistical 
analysis in an unbiased method. In a similar manner, it is also 
necessary to organize the available RNA structures to determine 
different structure-function relationships. Furthermore, it is often </p>

<p>important to compare several structures of RNA of same function 
and from same source, which have identical sequence, to under-
stand effect of ligand binding, crystallization environments etc., 
on the three-dimensional folding. Such sets of structures could 
reveal significant information on structural flexibility, binding 
thermodynamics etc., of the biological macromolecules (Halder 
and Bhattacharyya, 2010; Samanta et al., 2010). They carry signa-
tures that may indicate variations introduced in the molecular 
structure due to ligand binding or alteration of crystallization 
conditions. In our recent study, we also found that structural vari-
ability of double-helical RNA as observed in molecular dynamics 
simulation studies mimic that of the crystallographic ensembles 
(Halder and Bhattacharyya, 2010; Halder and Bhattacharyya, man-
uscript in preparation). Likewise, the differences in RNA structural 
organization among various species can be studied if a classifica-
tion is available. A non-redundant set of RNA structures is also 
necessary to analyze the local environments at basepairing level, 
which provided important information in recent analyses of struc-
ture and energetics of different non-canonical basepairs (Panigrahi 
et al., 2011). Databases like RNABase (Murthy and Rose, 2003) and 
SCOR (Klosterman et al., 2002) attempted to classify the available 
RNA structures but failed to regularly update these only by man-
ual curation of the RNA structures, as the number of structures 
is increasing quite fast. Any PDB structure released after 2004 is 
not classified by SCOR and RNABase database can no longer be 
accessed at the published address www.rnabase.org. Also, there are 
more activities toward classification of RNA structures on the basis </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 59 | 1 </p>

<p>Ray et al. </p>

<p>Structural classification of RNA </p>

<p>of secondary structure (Tamura et al., 2004; Sarver et al., 2008), 
canonical as well as unusual base pairing (Lu and Olson, 2003; 
Das et al., 2006; Roy et al., 2008), isosteric base pairs (Leontis et al., 
2002), etc., but the determination of non-redundant set of struc-
tures is only done partially by a few groups (Leontis and Westhof, 
2001; Stombaugh et al., 2009). 
In order to organize and classify the information of RNA 
structures in PDB files and make it available to the general 
users, we have developed a web-server, called Hierarchical Data-
base of RNA Structures (HD-RNAS; http://www.saha.ac.in/biop/ 
www/HD-RNAS.html, see Figure 1). Keeping in mind that some 
of the earlier attempts to classify RNA structures failed to keep 
pace with the structure determination speed, we have adapted 
an automated programmatic scheme with minimal or no manual 
intervention for the classification procedure. With the number of 
RNA structures increasing rapidly, there is a constant pressure of 
regularly updating this database. As the classification and database 
creation processes are done by an Octave program, our auto-
mated tool is capable of frequently classifying the newly released 
structures. Hence we expect that HD-RNAS can remain dynamic 
and would not phase out like the earlier attempts. Some man-
ual curation is obviously involved in this automated procedure 
to avoid erroneous results. Whenever new structures are released 
in PDB, they are classified accordingly and verified manually for 
any inaccuracy. The programmatic scheme is flexible enough to be 
modified to ensure proper classification of all the RNA structures 
in case of discrepancies. </p>

<p>CLASSIFICATION METHODOLOGY </p>

<p>We focus on PDB files containing at least one RNA chain having 
length equal to or greater than 10 nucleotides, as shorter fragments </p>

<p>than this length cannot be expected to fold back and form a sec-
ondary structure of biological relevance. RNA chains shorter than 
10 nucleotides usually form double helix pairing with their com-
plimentary strands, and do not form a secondary structure on 
their own. 
A total of 2095 RNA structure entries were reported by the 
PDB search engine in July, 2011. We have developed a software in 
<rs type="software">GNU-Octave</rs>, which is similar to <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> scripting language, that </p>

<p>i) Programmatically examines and reads the information of all 
the RNA structures from the PDB files and classifies them, 
ii) Creates the necessary database files, and 
iii) Creates the web-layout of HTML pages displayed in the server 
containing major information of each RNA chain. </p>

<p>These HTML files are published in the web. Text-based CGI-
Perl codes have been created for back-end support of different 
search applications, which are available in HD-RNAS. The web-
server is available at http://www.saha.ac.in/biop/www/HD-RNAS. 
html 
At the first stage, the RNA structures are classified according to 
their functional classes, e.g., tRNA, rRNA, mRNA etc. Along with 
these most common ones, we have also included some other types 
like ribozymes, riboswitches, ribonucleases, and signal recognition 
particle (SRP) RNAs, keeping in mind their growing significance 
in maintaining cellular machinery and their specific structural 
patterns. A number of PDB files correspond to multi-molecular 
complexes of several RNA as well as protein chains and informa-
tion about these individual RNA chains is given in the PDB file as 
MOL_ID 1, MOL_ID 2 etc. Hence, one PDB file can be classified 
as belonging to several different classes simultaneously. We have </p>

<p>FIGURE 1 | HD-RNAS homepage. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Genetics | Bioinformatics and Computational Biology </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 59 | 2 </p>

<p>Ray et al. </p>

<p>Structural classification of RNA </p>

<p>made no attempt to classify the structures of DNA or protein 
chains. The main steps of our Octave code for classifying RNA can 
be summarized as: </p>

<p>(S1) We have looked for several specific keywords in the MOL_ID 
field to classify each chain individually into one of the seven 
major classes for mRNA, SRP-RNA, tRNA, rRNA, Ribonucle-
ase, Riboswitch, and Ribozyme. Table 1 shows the complete 
mapping of keywords used for the function assignment. In a 
few cases the functions are not clearly understood from the 
information in MOL_ID field alone. In those cases, we have 
additionally looked at HEADER and the first KEYWDS field 
of the PDB files also. 
(S2) There are some RNA structures of various other functions. 
As the numbers of structures for these functional classes are 
very small, at present we have clustered those under the class 
named 'Other-RNA' . This class also contains RNA chains 
of significant length (at least 10 nucleotides) and obtained 
from a natural source, for which no appropriate function 
could be assigned. There are large numbers of synthetic RNA 
structures for which no source organism or functional type 
can be determined. These sequences together comprise the 
"Unannotated RNA" class. 
(S3) The rRNA and tRNA molecules are classified into further 
subclasses. The rRNA structures are classified according to 
5S, 16S, 23S, and 28S (for eukaryotic organisms), depending 
on their sedimentation coefficients and ribosomal fragments, 
which group only the defined partial structures. The tRNA 
structures are classified according to the amino acid or stop 
codon names. 
(S4) The structures are then classified according to the source 
organism from which the RNA molecules were isolated 
and crystallized. We have placed each chain accord-
ing to the organism information as supplied by the 
SOURCE field of PDB files. In some of the cases, where 
ORGANISM_SCIENTIFIC field do not produce any source 
information, the source organism has been extracted from 
the OTHER_DETAILS field. For example, chain A of PDB </p>

<p>Table 1 | Special keywords and their corresponding classification for a </p>

<p>RNA chain. </p>

<p>Keywords 
Significance </p>

<p>UTR, EXON, INTRON 
mRNA </p>

<p>CODON, ANTIOCODON, ACCEPTOR </p>

<p>tRNA-fragment, A-site, P-site, E-site, tRNA X-MER </p>

<p>(e.g., tRNA 30-MER) </p>

<p>tRNA </p>

<p>OPAL or AMBER or OCHRE 
tRNA -OPAL or </p>

<p>AMBER or OCHRE </p>

<p>RIBONUCLEASE P, RNASE P 
Ribonuclease </p>

<p>FMET, FME, INITIATOR, INI, PRIMER 
tRNA </p>

<p>S-TURN, CATALYTIC RNA, HAMMERHEAD 
Ribozyme </p>

<p>APTAMER 
Riboswitch </p>

<p>4.8S, 5S, 5.8S, 16S, 18S, 23S, 28S, 30S, 50S, 70S, </p>

<p>80S </p>

<p>rRNA </p>

<p>4.5S, 7S, 7SL 
SRP-RNA </p>

<p>entry 1YSV is annotated as "SYNTHETIC" in the "SOURCE" 
field, whereas OTHER_DETAILS field describes that the 
sequence is taken from human. Thus, we have put the struc-
ture in "Homo sapiens" mRNA class. Quite a number of PDB 
files contain different types of RNA molecules obtained from 
different source organisms. For example, PDB entry 2J00 is 
consisted of 16S ribosomal RNA chains from T. thermophilus, 
A-site, P-site, and E-site tRNAs from Escherichia coli and a 
synthetic mRNA. We have, therefore, placed this PDB entry 
into all the RNA classes along with their corresponding chain 
identifiers (see Figure 2). 
(S5) We found that many PDB files do not contain exact source of 
the RNA chains, and have been indicated as synthetic. How-
ever, their size and function indicate that these sequences are 
from some biological organism. In order to determine the 
actual source of these RNA chains, we have used BLAST 
(Altschul et al., 1997) algorithm for sequence alignment. 
We have used nucleotide sequence database from NCBI as 
available on June, 2011 and compared our synthetic RNA 
sequences with all of them. We have picked up the hits hav-
ing E-value less than 1.0 × 10 −5 , number of aligned bases 
greater than 99% of the complete chain length of synthetic 
sequence, and sequence identity 99% or greater. 
(S6) Finally, we have programmatically created a master database 
file and all the HTML pages that describe the classification. 
These HTML files contain major information of each RNA 
chain, such as PDB-ID, chain name, functional class, source, 
resolution, chain length, free R-factor, and release date of 
the entry. Each structure is hyper-linked to the correspond-
ing information page on PDB-site. RNA structures solved by 
NMR spectroscopy have poorer resolution than X-ray crystal 
structures and are assigned with a large resolution value and 
R-factor of 99.0. 
(S7) In order to determine the non-redundant set of RNA struc-
tures at a given resolution, we pick up the structures with 
best resolution and R-factor (free R-value) from each sub-
class. Sometimes smaller fragments of a functional RNA are 
classified as a full-length functional RNA due to improper 
information in PDB and often these fragments are of better 
resolution than the other full-length structures. In order to 
avoid picking up such fragmented chains as representatives, 
we have put a length constraint so that the representative 
structure from a class should be 80% or more of the average 
length of that structural class. For example, the best repre-
sentative structure of E. coli 23S rRNA should be chain A 
from PDB 1Q9A as this structure have the best resolution 
in its class (1.04Å). However, this structure represents only a 
fragmented part (27 nucleotides) of the complete RNA chain. 
Thus it is replaced by chain A of PDB 3R8S (resolution: 3.0Å, 
length: 2903 nucleotides) as the representative of its class. 
The non-redundant dataset is available at the web-server for 
various unbiased statistical analysis purposes. </p>

<p>Our classified database is maintained in a flat-file format, with-
out any database management system. This has been possible since 
we do not keep the large PDB files at the web-server and our com-
plete database is quite small. The web-server also provides different </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 59 | 3 </p>

<p>Ray et al. </p>

<p>Structural classification of RNA </p>

<p>FIGURE 2 | Proper classification of individual RNA chains present in 2J00 in HD-RNAS. </p>

<p>search options with user-specified criteria like source organism 
or functional types. Sequence of the RNA chains in plain text 
formats can be obtained from the search result pages. Similarly, 
one can search for PDB files in the database containing a given 
sequence motif. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>PRESENT STATUS </p>

<p>We found 2095 RNA structures were available in PDB in July, 2011. 
We further rejected 345 crystal structures as these do not contain 
RNA chains of significant length. Presently, the database contains 
1750 PDB files having structures of 2636 RNA chains with signifi-
cant length. We have 263 structures clustered in the "Other-RNA" 
group including IRES RNA, viral RNA, miRNA, snoRNA etc. For 
the "Unannotated RNA" class, it is seen that most of the unanno-
tated RNA chains are shorter than 30 nucleotides (650 out of 737), 
whereas functional RNAs are generally larger. There are, however, 
a few entries in the unannotated class, such as 1KH6, 1P6V, 2B57 
etc., which have significant length. </p>

<p>BLAST SEARCH FOR SYNTHETIC SEQUENCES </p>

<p>There are many structures where the source organism is men-
tioned as "SYNTHETIC" by the depositors, whereas one expects 
these sequences to be derived from some natural organisms, as 
they correspond to quite long RNA chains. In some of the cases, 
however, the depositors mentioned about the source organism in 
the OTHER_DETAILS field of the PDB file. But the information is 
not provided in machine-interpretable format. The proper source 
organisms of 66 RNA sequences, which were imperfectly desig-
nated as synthetic, have been revealed by BLAST search. There are </p>

<p>also some PDB entries like 1DFU, 1EHZ etc., where natural sources 
of the RNA sequences are mentioned in the OTHER_DETAILS 
field; yet, they have been designated as synthetic ones probably 
because they have been synthesized by in vitro transcription. We 
have not done BLAST search for source determination of the syn-
thetic sequences having length smaller than 30 nucleotides, as the 
significance of BLAST result are poor in these cases and multiple 
hits with identical E-values are often observed. We could deter-
mine source of five (out of 14) E. coli tRNA Gln using BLAST (see 
Figure 3). Wherever possible, we have manually crosschecked the 
validity of BLAST result from the OTHER_DETAILS field of PDB 
entries and the results are found to be in good agreement (see 
Table 2). </p>

<p>NON-REDUNDANT DATASET </p>

<p>To obtain an unbiased set of RNA structures, we have derived a 
non-redundant dataset consisting of the best representative struc-
tures from each of the classes. These representative structures are 
the ones with best resolution or, in case there are more than one 
entries having resolution values identical to the best one, the struc-
ture with smallest R-factor and larger length. As the unannotated 
structures include huge number of structures and most of them 
are unrelated, we tried to pick up more than one representatives 
from this clan. In order to remove redundant repeats of struc-
tures, we have calculated sequence identity among the structures 
of synthetic RNAs in the unannotated-RNA group. In cases where 
two sequences are 100% identical, we have considered that of 
the best resolution and R-factor as the representative one. The 
non-redundant dataset thus obtained contains 849 RNA chains 
from 702 PDB entries. Sometimes, this non-redundant set may </p>

<p>Frontiers in Genetics | Bioinformatics and Computational Biology </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 59 | 4 </p>

<p>Ray et al. </p>

<p>Structural classification of RNA </p>

<p>FIGURE 3 | BLAST search results for E. coli tRNA 
Gln . </p>

<p>contain more than one ribosomal RNA structures from the same 
group, as they contain RNA chains belonging to different classes, 
such as tRNA, mRNA, rRNA etc. We have not attempted to remove 
these, as inter-chain base pairings are also important in higher 
order organization of RNA structures. The web-server is also 
equipped with a search tool to determine a non-redundant set 
of structures with user-defined criteria of functional type, source 
organism, chain length, and resolution. Such non-redundant set 
of RNA structures was used recently in analyzing structure and 
energetics of different non-canonical basepairs (Panigrahi et al., 
2011). 
In our non-redundant dataset, we find that there are a large 
number of structures of RNA with length less than 30 nucleotides. 
These are mainly synthetic sequences for which functional anno-
tation is unavailable. Among the 849 structures, 491 sequences do 
not carry any functional information, among which 427 sequences 
are of insignificant length (&lt; 30 nucleotide). As the functional 
RNA molecules are generally of length larger than 30-residues, 
we also generate a suggested non-redundant set containing repre-
sentative structures from each of the functional classes as well as 
representatives from the unannotated groups with larger length. 
The members are selected with resolution better than 3.5Å to make 
it a meaningful set of structures for real applications. This set has 
159 structures, including only 22 functionally unannotated RNA 
structures of synthetic source. We have kept no structure solved 
by NMR spectroscopy in the non-redundant set, as there is no way 
one can determine quality of the data. The structures determined 
by cryo-electron microscopy are automatically removed because 
of their poor resolution. </p>

<p>APPLICATIONS </p>

<p>The database can be searched for a set of RNA structural entries 
according to functional type or source organism. Also, a combined 
search can be performed using advanced options where a user can 
specify the chain length as well as a resolution cutoff of the crystal 
structures. Furthermore, one can determine if there are any struc-
tures whose sequence is identical to a given nucleotide sequence. 
At present, only scientific names of the organisms are accepted for 
search criteria in "Advanced Search Options" of our web-server. 
As the classification shows, there are many RNA classes where 
the numbers of PDB files are 10 or greater. These subclasses 
have been shown in Table 3 and corresponding MOL_ID's are 
shown as a suffix to the PDB-ID. They carry signatures that 
may indicate variations introduced in the molecular structure 
due to ligand binding or alteration of crystallization conditions. 
Eventually, they can be referred to as crystallographic ensem-
bles in analogy with statistical ensembles obtained from mol-
ecular dynamics or Monte Carlo simulations as done recently 
(Halder and Bhattacharyya, 2010; Samanta et al., 2010). We have 
performed pair-wise secondary structure comparison for these 
classes to compare the structural similarity between them. For 
secondary structure assignment, the base pairing patterns of 
each RNA structure in a functional class have been obtained 
using <rs id="software-5" type="software">BPFind</rs> software tool (Das et al., <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-date">2006</rs>). <rs type="software">BPFind</rs> gives 
us the secondary structure of a nucleic acid at the basepair-
ing level. These secondary structural information of basepairing 
for each chain have been converted to a one-dimensional string 
of characters: H, N, T, and L corresponding to Watson-Crick 
base pairs, non-canonical base pairs, base triplets, and unpaired </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 59 | 5 </p>

<p>Ray et al. </p>

<p>Structural classification of RNA </p>

<p>Table 2 | Validation of BLAST search results. </p>

<p>PDB 
Chain 
BLAST result 
PDB description </p>

<p>1ASY 
R, S 
BLAST gb M25168.1 YSCTRDCER S.cerevisiae Asp-tRNA 149 </p>

<p>2e-34 </p>

<p>Yeast aspartyl-tRNA synthetase complexed with tRNA Asp </p>

<p>1ASZ 
R, S 
BLAST gb M25168.1 YSCTRDCER S.cerevisiae Asp-tRNA 149 </p>

<p>2e-34 </p>

<p>Yeast aspartyl-tRNA synthetase complexed with tRNA Asp </p>

<p>1GID 
A, B 
BLAST emb V01416.1 Fragments of a Tetrahymena gene for </p>

<p>26s rRNA with. . . 311 8e-83 </p>

<p>Tetrahymena group I INTRON </p>

<p>1HR2 
A, B 
BLAST emb V01416.1 Fragments of a Tetrahymena gene for </p>

<p>26s rRNA with. . . 295 4e-78 </p>

<p>Tetrahymena group I INTRON </p>

<p>1IVS 
C, D 
BLAST dbj AB080139.1 Thermus thermophilus tRNA-Val 149 </p>

<p>2e-34 </p>

<p>Thermus thermophilus valyl-tRNA synthetase complexed with </p>

<p>tRNA(VAL) </p>

<p>1U9S 
A 
BLAST gb AE017221.1 Thermus thermophilus HB27, complete </p>

<p>genome 319 3e-85 </p>

<p>Thermus thermophilus </p>

<p>1VTQ 
A 
BLAST gb M25168.1 YSCTRDCER S.cerevisiae Asp-tRNA 149 </p>

<p>2e-34 </p>

<p>Yeast t-RNA-Asp </p>

<p>2CSX 
C, D 
BLAST gb AE000657.1 Aquifex aeolicus VF5, complete genome </p>

<p>149 2e-34 </p>

<p>Aquifex aeolicus methionyl-tRNA synthetase complexed with </p>

<p>tRNA(MET) </p>

<p>2CT8 
C, D 
BLAST gb AE000657.1 Aquifex aeolicus VF5, complete genome </p>

<p>147 1e-33 </p>

<p>Aquifex aeolicus methionyl-tRNA synthetase complexed with </p>

<p>tRNA(MET) </p>

<p>2CV0 
C, D 
BLAST gb AE017221.1 Thermus thermophilus HB27, complete </p>

<p>genome 149 2e-34 </p>

<p>Glutamyl-tRNA synthetase from thermus thermophilus in com-</p>

<p>plex with tRNA(GLU) </p>

<p>2CV1 
C, D 
BLAST gb AE017221.1 Thermus thermophilus HB27, complete </p>

<p>genome 149 2e-34 </p>

<p>Glutamyl-tRNA synthetase from thermus thermophilus in com-</p>

<p>plex with tRNA(GLU) </p>

<p>2CV2 
C, D 
BLAST gb AE017221.1 Thermus thermophilus HB27, complete </p>

<p>genome 149 2e-34 </p>

<p>Glutamyl-tRNA synthetase from thermus thermophilus in com-</p>

<p>plex with tRNA(GLU) </p>

<p>2DXI 
C, D 
BLAST gb AE017221.1 Thermus thermophilus HB27, complete </p>

<p>genome 149 2e-34 </p>

<p>Glutamyl-tRNA synthetase from thermus thermophilus com-</p>

<p>plexed with tRNA(GLU) </p>

<p>2IHX 
B 
BLAST gb M21526.1 ALRSRCAC Rous sarcoma virus defective </p>

<p>mutant PR2257. . . 149 2e-34 </p>

<p>Sequence occurs naturally in rous sarcoma virus (RSV) </p>

<p>2NOQ 
A 
BLAST gb AF218039.1 AF218039 Cricket paralysis virus </p>

<p>non-structural pol. . . 377 e-102 </p>

<p>Ribosome-bound cricket paralysis virus IRES RNA </p>

<p>2ZNI 
C, D 
BLAST dbj AP008230.1 Desulfitobacterium hafniense Y51 </p>

<p>DNA, complete g. . . 143 1e-32 </p>

<p>Pyrrolysyl-tRNA synthetase-tRNA(PYL) complex from desulfito-</p>

<p>bacterium hafniense </p>

<p>3AKZ 
F, H, G, E 
BLAST gb AE000512.1 Thermotoga maritima MSB8, complete </p>

<p>genome 147 1e-33 </p>

<p>Thermotoga maritima non-discriminating glutamyl-tRNA syn-</p>

<p>thetase in complex with tRNAGLN </p>

<p>3AL0 
E 
BLAST gb AE000512.1 Thermotoga maritima MSB8, complete </p>

<p>genome 147 1e-33 </p>

<p>Glutamine transamidosome from thermotoga maritima in the </p>

<p>glutamylation state </p>

<p>3FOZ 
D 
BLAST gb CP002185.1 Escherichia coli W, complete genome </p>

<p>137 3e-3137 8e-31 </p>

<p>E. Coli isopentenyl-tRNA transferase in complex with E. coli </p>

<p>tRNA(PHE) </p>

<p>3Q50 
A 
BLAST gb AE008691.1 Thermoanaerobacter tengcongensis </p>

<p>MB4, complete ge. . . 66 8e-10 </p>

<p>Based on the sequence of class I, type 1 PREQ1 riboswitch </p>

<p>aptamer from T. tengcongensis </p>

<p>3Q51 
A 
BLAST gb AE008691.1 Thermoanaerobacter tengcongensis </p>

<p>MB4, complete ge. . . 66 8e-10 </p>

<p>Based on the sequence of class I, type 1 PREQ1 riboswitch </p>

<p>aptamer from T. tengcongensis </p>

<p>bases, respectively. The secondary structures thus obtained corre-
spond to individual RNA chains separately and do not consider 
inter-chain base pairing information. These secondary structural 
sequences are then compared with that of the best representa-
tive structure of that class using Needleman-Wunsch algorithm 
(Needleman and Wunsch, 1970) as implemented in <rs id="software-7" type="software">EMBOSS</rs> 
(Rice et al., <rs corresp="#software-7" type="version-date">2000</rs>). An identity scoring matrix (EDNAMAT) was 
used for such alignment with a gap-open penalty of −10.0 and 
gap-extension penalty of -0.5. We find that the average simi-
larity is 80% or more for a set of similar structures of a given </p>

<p>class having 30 or more RNA chains. The detailed analyses of 
structural variation among these crystallographic ensembles are 
beyond the scope of this paper and would be presented else-
where. Here a point to note is that secondary structure comparison 
have not been performed for crystal structures with resolution 
worse than 3.5Å because of the poor quality of secondary struc-
tural information obtained from such structures. RNA structures 
solved by NMR spectroscopy or electron microscopy are also 
not included in secondary structure comparison for the same 
reason. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Genetics | Bioinformatics and Computational Biology </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 59 | 6 </p>

<p>Ray et al. </p>

<p>Structural classification of RNA </p>

<p>Table 3 | Subclasses where the number of PDB files are 10 or greater and their structural variation. </p>

<p>Functional type 
Organism 
No. of PDB files* 
Representative structure 
Average similarity 
SD </p>

<p>16S rRNA 
Escherichia coli 
26 (25) 
3OFP_A 
0.9053 
0.0403 </p>

<p>16S rRNA 
Thermus thermophilus 
73 (69) 
2VQE_A 
0.8556 
0.0579 </p>

<p>5S rRNA 
Deinococcus radiodurans 
12 (12) 
2ZJR_Y 
0.6792 
0.1558 </p>

<p>5S rRNA 
Escherichia coli 
27 (24) 
3OFQ_B 
0.8896 
0.0454 </p>

<p>5S rRNA 
Haloarcula marismortui 
61 (61) 
1VQO_9 
0.9077 
0.0451 </p>

<p>5S rRNA 
Thermus thermophilus 
45 (44) 
2J01_B 
0.8349 
0.0952 </p>

<p>23S rRNA 
Deinococcus radiodurans 
23 (23) 
2ZJR_X 
0.6582 
0.1306 </p>

<p>23S rRNA 
Escherichia coli 
30 (30) 
3OFR_A 
0.742 
0.2972 </p>

<p>23S rRNA 
Haloarcula marismortui 
65 (58) 
1VQO_0 
0.9714 
0.0128 </p>

<p>23S rRNA 
Thermus thermophilus 
44 (41) 
2J01_A 
0.9516 
0.03 </p>

<p>tRNA fMet 
Escherichia coli 
20 (20) 
2FMT_C/D 
0.8499 
0.0943 </p>

<p>tRNA Gln 
Escherichia coli 
14 (14) 
1ZJW 
0.7755 
0.2094 </p>

<p>tRNA Phe 
Escherichia coli 
55 (55) 
3FOZ_D 
0.5269 
0.2425 </p>

<p>*Numbers in parentheses give the total no. of structures after removing outliers. </p>

<p>Table 4 | Function assignment to RNAs of the other-RNA class. </p>

<p>Query 
Length 
Original function 
Best match 
Predicted function 
Best score 
Average 
SD 
Prediction score </p>

<p>1FIR-A 
76 
tRNA Lys 
1EVV-A 
tRNA Phe 
362.00 
131.60 
13.62 
16.92 </p>

<p>2B57-A 
65 
Riboswitch 
2XNZ-A 
Riboswitch 
307.00 
99.34 
11.35 
18.29 </p>

<p>2ZZM-B 
88 
tRNA Leu 
1WZ2-D 
tRNA Leu 
326.50 
118.16 
14.40 
14.46 </p>

<p>2ZZN-C 
75 
tRNA Cys 
3KFU-L 
tRNA Asn 
304.00 
128.54 
12.98 
13.52 </p>

<p>2ZZN-D 
75 
tRNA Cys 
1F7U-B 
tRNA Arg 
309.00 
135.00 
13.32 
13.06 </p>

<p>3KIQ-a 
1504 
rRNA 
2VQE-A 
16S rRNA 
5904.50 
2062.09 
46.95 
81.85 </p>

<p>3KIQ-v 
77 
tRNA 
2FMT-D 
tRNA Fmet 
349.00 
150.39 
15.36 
12.93 </p>

<p>3KIR-A 
2848 
rRNA 
2XG0-A 
rRNA fragment 
12839.00 
3764.09 
55.97 
162.13 </p>

<p>3KIR-B 
119 
rRNA 
2J01-B 
5S rRNA 
505.00 
156.37 
13.11 
26.60 </p>

<p>3KIS-a 
1504 
rRNA 
2VQE-A 
16S rRNA 
5904.50 
2068.17 
46.28 
82.89 </p>

<p>3KIS-v 
77 
tRNA 
2ZUE-B 
tRNA Arg 
342.00 
146.26 
11.99 
16.32 </p>

<p>3KIT-A 
2848 
rRNA 
2XG0-A 
rRNA fragment 
12821.00 
3779.68 
61.28 
147.53 </p>

<p>3KIT-B 
119 
rRNA 
2J01-B 
5S rRNA 
523.00 
148.25 
13.61 
27.54 </p>

<p>3KNN-W 
75 
tRNA 
1F7U-B 
tRNA Arg 
279.00 
129.06 
12.13 
12.36 </p>

<p>3KNN-X 
77 
tRNA Fmet 
2FMT-D 
tRNA Fmet 
331.00 
147.96 
14.51 
12.62 </p>

<p>1VFG-D 
75 
Primer tRNA 
2V0G-F 
tRNA Leu 
138.00 
93.55 
8.51 
5.22 </p>

<p>3KNN-Y 
75 
tRNA 
2XQD-W 
tRNA 
208.00 
146.06 
11.57 
5.35 </p>

<p>3MOJ-A 
74 
23S rRNA 
2XG0-A 
rRNA fragment 
196.50 
158.28 
8.48 
4.51 </p>

<p>3NPB-A 
119 
Riboswitch 
2A64-A 
Ribonuclease 
318.00 
255.50 
15.32 
4.08 </p>

<p>3R9X-C 
35 
16S rRNA 
1M5O-E 
Ribozyme 
142.00 
83.44 
13.25 
4.42 </p>

<p>3KIS-w 
77 
tRNA 
2XG0-A 
rRNA fragment 
164.50 
160.35 
12.56 
0.33 </p>

<p>3KIQ-w 
77 
tRNA 
2XG0-A 
rRNA fragment 
211.00 
203.98 
10.29 
0.68 </p>

<p>1P6V-B 
68 
tmRNA 
2XG0-A 
rRNA fragment 
146.00 
107.33 
8.65 
4.47 </p>

<p>1P6V-D 
68 
tmRNA 
3IAB-R 
Ribonuclease 
102.00 
65.03 
10.56 
3.50 </p>

<p>1S03-A 
47 
mRNA 
2ZNI-D 
tRNA Lys 
178.50 
127.49 
9.00 
5.67 </p>

<p>1S03-B 
47 
mRNA 
2ZNI-D 
tRNA Lys 
178.50 
127.83 
9.54 
5.31 </p>

<p>1VFG-C 
75 
Primer tRNA 
2XG0-A 
rRNA fragment 
123.50 
105.85 
6.09 
2.90 </p>

<p>Comparison of secondary structure can also be useful to pre-
dict the functions of unannotated RNAs. As mentioned in the 
earlier section, the functional types of many RNA chains that 
have been placed under the other-RNA and unannotated-RNA 
classes could not be obtained from the PDB files unambiguously. </p>

<p>However, we find that there are a number of structures in these 
two types, which are of significant length (30 nucleotide or more). 
We have performed structural comparison of these RNA chains 
with known functional RNAs available in the suggested non-
redundant dataset, consisting of only X-ray crystal structures with </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 59 | 7 </p>

<p>Ray et al. </p>

<p>Structural classification of RNA </p>

<p>resolution better than 3.5Å. For the secondary structure align-
ment, the basepairing pattern for each RNA structure in the 
non-redundant dataset, obtained using <rs type="software">BPFind</rs> software, com-
prises a database of known structural forms of well-classified 
functional RNAs. In a similar way, the secondary structural 
data for each of the unannotated RNA chains were generated 
and compared against the database of known structural forms. 
Thus, the secondary structural information of an unannotated 
RNA chain has been aligned with secondary structural informa-
tion of each RNA chain present in the non-redundant dataset 
using Needleman-Wunsch algorithm for global sequence align-
ment. We have assigned probable function of an unannotated 
RNA as identical to some known structural form with which the 
best similarity score is obtained. For example, chain A of 1FIR 
shows highest score of 362 against chain A of 1EVV (Table 4). </p>

<p>To validate the results of our function prediction method and 
to remove any false positive, we have used the bootstrapping 
method. For each pair of unannotated query and its best match 
in the non-redundant dataset, the best match secondary struc-
ture has been shuffled to generate a set of 100 random secondary 
structures having the same composition. Thus, the secondary 
structure sequence for chain A of 1EVV has been shuffled to 
generate 100 random sequence files and aligned secondary struc-
ture of 1FIR (chain: A) with all these 100 random sequences. 
Average and SD of these alignment scores have been calculated 
(Tables 4 and 5). We find that in many cases the original best 
match score and the average score against random sequences 
are quite similar (e.g., 3NVK, 1VFG, etc.). Figure 4 shows 
distributions of the random scores along with the actual predictive 
scores for two representative systems. Obviously, prediction </p>

<p>Table 5 | Function annotation to unannotated RNAs. </p>

<p>Unannotated RNA </p>

<p>Query 
Length 
Original function 
Best match 
Predicted function 
Best score 
Average 
SD 
Prediction score </p>

<p>1JBR-D 
31 
28S rRNA 
1Q96-B 
28S rRNA 
117.00 
39.56 
7.76 
9.98 </p>

<p>2HW8-B 
36 
mRNA 
1ZHO-H 
mRNA 
180.00 
66.01 
8.86 
12.86 </p>

<p>2ZH1-B 
33 
tRNA Phe 
3AKZ-G 
tRNA Gln 
154.50 
87.89 
9.13 
7.30 </p>

<p>3DS7-A 
67 
Guanine riboswitch 
1U8D-A 
mRNA (Riboswitch) 
317.00 
109.10 
10.63 
19.56 </p>

<p>3DS7-B 
67 
Guanine riboswitch 
1U8D-A 
mRNA (Riboswitch) 
299.00 
107.86 
10.67 
17.92 </p>

<p>3HJW-D 
58 
H/ACA snoRNA 
1WZ2-D 
tRNA Leu 
197.00 
105.06 
11.43 
8.04 </p>

<p>3ICQ-D 
67 
tRNA 
1EVV-A 
tRNA Phe 
212.00 
102.10 
10.20 
10.78 </p>

<p>3ICQ-E 
67 
tRNA 
2Y10-V 
tRNA Trp 
230.00 
116.67 
10.18 
11.13 </p>

<p>3LWO-D 
58 
H/ACA RNA 
1WZ2-D 
tRNA Leu 
197.00 
105.99 
13.15 
6.92 </p>

<p>3LWP-D 
58 
H/ACA snoRNA 
1WZ2-D 
tRNA Leu 
197.00 
107.14 
12.43 
7.23 </p>

<p>3LWQ-D 
58 
H/ACA snoRNA 
1WZ2-D 
tRNA Leu 
197.00 
105.22 
11.26 
8.15 </p>

<p>3LWR-D 
58 
H/ACA snoRNA 
1WZ2-D 
tRNA Leu 
197.00 
107.21 
11.17 
8.04 </p>

<p>3LWV-D 
58 
H/ACA RNA 
1WZ2-D 
tRNA Leu 
197.00 
107.64 
13.11 
6.82 </p>

<p>3OUY-C 
35 
tRNA Ile 
3A3A-A 
tRNA Sel 
157.00 
95.52 
8.96 
6.86 </p>

<p>3OV7-C 
34 
tRNA Ile 
3AKZ-G 
tRNA Gln 
134.00 
78.04 
9.20 
6.08 </p>

<p>3OVA-C 
34 
tRNA Ile 
3AKZ-G 
tRNA Gln 
159.50 
88.13 
9.76 
7.31 </p>

<p>3OVB-C 
35 
tRNA Ile 
3AKZ-G 
tRNA Gln 
164.50 
86.64 
9.72 
8.01 </p>

<p>3OVB-D 
35 
tRNA Ile 
3A3A-A 
tRNA Sel 
175.00 
104.03 
10.02 
7.09 </p>

<p>3OVS-C 
34 
tRNA Ile 
3A3A-A 
tRNA Sel 
170.00 
103.36 
9.39 
7.10 </p>

<p>3OVS-D 
34 
tRNA Ile 
3AKZ-G 
tRNA Gln 
142.00 
75.11 
9.84 
6.80 </p>

<p>3OV7-D 
34 
tRNA Ile 
3A3A-A 
tRNA Sel 
152.00 
95.84 
10.76 
5.22 </p>

<p>3OUY-D 
35 
tRNA Ile 
3A3A-A 
tRNA Sel 
139.00 
88.53 
9.62 
5.25 </p>

<p>2HVY-E 
65 
H/ACA 
3R8S-B 
5S rRNA 
196.00 
109.93 
12.66 
6.80 </p>

<p>3HAX-E 
63 
H/ACA 
1M5O-E 
Ribozyme 
201.50 
104.17 
14.31 
6.80 </p>

<p>3P22-C 
40 
Guide RNA 
3IAB-R 
Ribonuclease 
167.00 
91.79 
11.09 
6.78 </p>

<p>3P22-E 
40 
Guide RNA 
3IAB-R 
Ribonuclease 
167.00 
89.59 
11.18 
6.92 </p>

<p>3P22-G 
40 
Guide RNA 
3IAB-R 
Ribonuclease 
167.00 
92.37 
12.71 
5.87 </p>

<p>1DDY-A 
35 
Aptamer 
2A64-A 
Ribonuclease 
94.00 
68.71 
9.19 
2.75 </p>

<p>1DDY-C 
35 
Aptamer 
2A64-A 
Ribonuclease 
94.00 
67.48 
8.89 
2.99 </p>

<p>1DDY-E 
35 
Aptamer 
2A64-A 
Ribonuclease 
94.00 
67.40 
8.49 
3.14 </p>

<p>1DDY-G 
35 
Aptamer 
2A64-A 
Ribonuclease 
94.00 
68.01 
9.96 
2.61 </p>

<p>1KH6-A 
48 
IRES RNA (viral) 
3AM1-B 
tRNA 
164.00 
120.80 
8.39 
5.15 </p>

<p>1XJR-A 
47 
s2m RNA (viral) 
3ADD-D 
tRNA Sel 
125.50 
98.22 
9.22 
2.96 </p>

<p>3NVK-K 
34 
Box C/D snoRNA 
2XG0-A 
rRNA Fragment 
73.50 
71.68 
5.87 
0.31 </p>

<p>3NVK-L 
34 
Box C/D snoRNA 
2XQD-W 
tRNA 
68.00 
59.05 
6.88 
1.30 </p>

<p>3P22-A 
40 
Guide RNA 
1EUY-B 
tRNA Gln 
155.00 
86.87 
9.14 
7.45 </p>

<p>Frontiers in Genetics | Bioinformatics and Computational Biology </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 59 | 8 </p>

<p>Ray et al. </p>

<p>Structural classification of RNA </p>

<p>FIGURE 4 | Bootstrapping method for function prediction. Blue-
random scores, red-best match score. (A) Chain v of 3KIS, (B) chain w of 
3KIS. For chain v, the best score is significantly larger than random average 
score giving correct prediction, whereas for chain w, best match score lies 
within the range of random scores, leading to false prediction 
(Table 4). </p>

<p>of function of w-chain of 3KIS is questionable (Figure 4b) while 
that of v-chain of 3KIS is a good prediction. This quality depends 
on (original score for best match -average score from random 
sequences)/SD of random scores, as given in the last column of 
Tables 4 and 5. It is found that when these values are larger 
than 6 or 7, the predictions are generally correct. We have tried 
to manually examine our results against the original functions as 
obtained from literature study and found them to be in very good 
agreement. 
Using the above procedure, we have been able to predict the 
functions of 17 RNA structures from the "Unannotated-RNA" 
class and 18 more from the "Other-RNA" class. The results of 
the function assignments are shown in Tables 4 and 5. Struc-
tures of H/ACA box snoRNAs, like 3HJW (chain D), 3LWP (chain 
D), 3LWQ (chain D), 3LWR (chain D), and 3P22 (chain A), have 
been predicted as tRNAs. In these cases, the snoRNAs are bound 
with tRNA-processing proteins and thus have tRNA-like structural 
motifs for proper recognition. Also, the sub-divisions of different 
tRNAs can be predicted with limited accuracy only, as the sec-
ondary structure of tRNAs is nearly universal among different 
sub-types. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Hierarchical Database of RNA Structures is an evolving resource 
that is expected to grow and incorporate more and more RNA 
structures as and when they are solved and made available from 
PDB. We have used the PDB files in plain text format, instead 
of XML files, as these do not contain any extra information but 
require significantly more storage due to their huge size. The clas-
sification of RNA structures are done by an automated tool, a code 
written in high-level GNU-Octave language, which takes roughly 
3 h to classify 2095 PDB files in a 3.0 GHz "Pentium 4" processor 
with 1GB RAM. Most importantly, out of these 3 h, the classifica-
tion job takes only a part and nearly 2 h are used by the BLAST 
search program. However, this task is carried out once in a month 
during creation of the database and does not affect users. There is 
also an inbuilt function called "pdbread" in the recent versions of 
Matlab which can read a PDB file into a structure and can also store 
the relevant information. Although, a small part of our program 
and the function "pdbread" are similar, the function "pdbread" 
demands more time to gather the complete information includ-
ing the coordinate data from a big PDB file. However, our routine 
skips the coordinate data in the PDB file to reduce CPU time. 
The program code is a flexible one and certainly there would be 
necessity for modifications when structures of altogether new RNA 
with function as yet unknown or when structures of more siRNA, 
miRNA, virus etc., would be available. However, we can easily 
modify the code in future to characterize these structures into new 
functional classes. Similarly, when several structures of a sub-sub-
class would be available, it is expected to open up new directions 
of research toward understanding ligand or environment-induced 
structural alterations. For instance, it would be interesting to 
understand conformational variations between ligand-bound and 
ligand-free states of riboswitches, between ribosome structures 
with or without tRNA bound to it, free tRNA and tRNA com-
plexed with synthatase etc. Such structural comparisons can also 
be used to detect the functional class of unannotated RNA struc-
tures. We have used a simple mechanism for prediction of function 
of unknown RNA structures but it can be improved by betterment 
of the scoring matrix or by using graph-theoretic approach. We 
are planning to include the predicted functions in later versions of 
the database. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We are thankful to Dr. Devapriya Chowdhury, JNU, New Delhi, 
India, and Dr. Rahul Banerjee, SINP, India, for suggestions. We are 
thankful to Ms. Shreya Pakrashi, Ms. Tania Sen, and Ms. Rishika 
Sengupta for technical support. Funding: This work has been par-
tially supported by Dept. of Biotechnology, India and CBAUNP 
project of Dept. of Atomic Energy, Govt. of India. </p>





<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 59 | 9 </p>

<p>Ray et al. </p>

<p>Structural classification of RNA </p>



<p>Conflict of Interest Statement: The 
authors declare that the research was 
conducted in the absence of any com-
mercial or financial relationships that 
could be construed as a potential con-
flict of interest. </p>

<p>Received: 26 December 2011; accepted: 29 
March 2012; published online: 18 April 
2012. 
Citation: Ray SS, Halder S, Kaypee S 
and Bhattacharyya D (2012) HD-RNAS: 
an automated hierarchical database of 
RNA structures. Front. Gene. 3:59. doi: 
10.3389/fgene.2012.00059 
This article was submitted to Frontiers in 
Bioinformatics and Computational Biol-
ogy, a specialty of Frontiers in Genetics. 
Copyright © 2012 Ray, Halder, Kaypee 
and Bhattacharyya. This is an open-
access article distributed under the terms 
of the Creative Commons Attribution 
Non Commercial License, which per-
mits non-commercial use, distribution, 
and reproduction in other forums, pro-
vided the original authors and source are 
credited. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Genetics | Bioinformatics and Computational Biology </p>

<p>April 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 59 | 10 </p>

</text></tei>