<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3245093" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:32+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Wikipedia, the online encyclopedia, is the most 
famous wiki in use today. It contains over 3.7 
million pages of content; with many pages written 
on scientific subject matters that include peer-
reviewed citations, yet are written in an accessible 
manner and generally reflect the consensus opin-
ion of the community. In this, the 19th Annual 
Database Issue of Nucleic Acids Research, there 
are 11 articles that describe the use of a wiki in 
relation to a biological database. In this commen-
tary, we discuss how biological databases can be 
integrated with Wikipedia, thereby utilising the 
pre-existing infrastructure, tools and above all, 
large community of authors (or Wikipedians). The 
limitations to the content that can be included in 
Wikipedia are highlighted, with examples drawn 
from articles found in this issue and other 
wiki-based resources, indicating why other wiki so-
lutions are necessary. We discuss the merits of 
using open wikis, like Wikipedia, versus other 
models, with particular reference to potential van-
dalism. Finally, we raise the question about the 
future role of dedicated database biocurators in 
context of the thousands of crowdsourced, commu-
nity annotations that are now being stored in wikis. </p>

<p>Over the recent years of the NAR Database Issue, there 
has been an increasing trend of articles being submitted 
where the database makes substantial use of a wiki. A wiki 
is a web-based tool for the curation and editing of a set of 
web pages. So, why have wikis become so popular? This 
trend is not specific to biological databases and the popu-
larity of wikis stems from their simplicity and availability. 
A wiki provides a simple framework for capturing and 
sharing of data, generated by any user with a web </p>

<p>browser and the appropriate permissions to edit the wiki 
content. Indeed, Ward Cunningham, developer of the first 
wiki software, described it as being 'the simplest online 
database that could possibly work' (see http://en 
.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Wiki&amp;oldid=457195 
237). The most famous wiki on the web today is 
Wikipedia, the online encyclopedia. Wikipedia currently 
contains over 3.7 million pages of content, most of which 
can be edited by anyone. A large proportion of search 
engine queries return a Wikipedia article as one of the 
top hits. Consequently, most users of the web have come 
across a wiki in some shape or form, even if they did not 
realise it. 
So, how do wikis relate to biological databases? 
Traditionally, these databases have employed small 
teams of expert curators, typically based at one (or 
maybe a few sites), to write the scientific content regarding 
the entries in the database. However, with the advent of 
wikis, the curation burden can be distributed to many 
more people, unrestricted by geographical location, or 
simply 'crowdsourced'. Moreover, wikis allows the scien-
tists who are experts on a given topic to be engaged and to 
share their knowledge, rather than a biological curator 
having to generate content based on published literature. 
The openness of wikis seems odd to many scientists who 
are used to the peer-review model used for publications. 
Some scientists may assume, incorrectly, that because 
anyone can edit a wiki at any time, the content must be 
flawed, especially if they do not know who that user is. </p>

<p>WIKIS AND BILOGICAL DATABASES </p>

<p>Vandalism and the danger of open wikis </p>

<p>For Pfam and Rfam we adopted the use of Wikipedia as 
the wiki model. One of the main reasons that we came to 
this decision is because we believed that the openness and 
profile of Wikipedia embraces the highest number of po-
tential editors. As there is no need to log-in, users can 
more readily edit the text, even for simple typographical 
corrections. There is then instant user gratification of 
seeing the change appear in the article. Furthermore, </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +01223 495330; Fax: +01223 494919; Email: finnr@janelia.hhmi.org </p>

<p>Published online 5 December 2011 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, Database issue D9-D12 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkr1195 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>this approach takes advantage of 'hot topics' as they 
suddenly spike in public interest. Huss et al. (1) elegantly 
showed the correlated trend between hot topics in the 
news (as measured by Google searches) and the number 
of edits in Wikipedia in relation to the GeneWiki project. 
We have observed similar trends between the release of 
prominent papers and the number of edits to pages per-
taining to those articles. 
However, the open nature is also a potential drawback 
of using Wikipedia, as anyone can freely edit the content, 
in any way they see fit. Articles in Wikipedia have little 
provenance on each editor, and the lack of editing restric-
tions increases the likelihood that content will be inappro-
priately edited. Inappropriate editing falls into two broad 
categories, (i) blatant, malicious defacing of the content or 
addition of spam links and advertising; and (ii) the more 
subtle errors introduced, either intentionally or due to 
mis-understanding, resulting in misleading content. The 
former are obvious to someone reading the content and 
may cause offence. This sort of editing is a common 
problem for high profile wikis, such as Wikipedia. 
However, due to the large community of editors and the 
use of bots (programs that automatically edit pages) most 
vandalism of this nature is promptly reverted. It is the 
second type that is more worrying to a scientist. For 
example, on 3 June 2007, an anonymous Wikipedian 
(a user who has not logged in) modified the article on 
the regulatory RNA 'Riboswitches' to include a reference 
to an episode of the cartoon 'The Simpsons' that featured 
Ribwiches. It was not until 17 June 2007 that this was 
removed. It is unclear whether this was done maliciously, 
or whether it was caused by a confusion between 
Ribwiches and Riboswitches. Overall, inappropriate 
editing is rare for pages related to biology and occurs at 
very low rates. Since Rfam started to use Wikipedia to 
manage the textual annotation of RNA families in 2007, 
1% of all edits have been reverted, by the Rfam curators 
or the greater Wikipedia community, suggesting that they 
may be vandalism (2). Similar numbers are presented for 
the GeneWiki project (3), with these authors estimating 
that vandalism is observed less than one page view in 
every 3000, a rate much lower than other articles in 
Wikipedia. 
For many scientists, a closed wiki (restricted by user 
login, not to be confused with private, where viewing the 
content is restricted) may seem to be the obvious choice: 
who would trust a paper where the authors were anonym-
ous? You want to know the provenance of the edit and to 
know that the user has been vetted in some way to ensure 
they have the appropriate scientific background. While 
this undoubtedly helps ensure the validity of the content, 
there is an 'energy barrier' to overcome. Any new user 
must first obtain a username and password and this 
initial, albeit small, energy barrier will deter many casual 
browsers who might only want to make a small change. 
This undoubtedly restricts the user base, probably to those 
who have a vested interest in the database-this may be 
the desired effect. With a defined user group, it is signifi-
cantly easier to enforce more consistency in the layout, 
media and textual content of each wiki page. </p>

<p>An intermediate solution between open and closed wikis 
has been adopted by some of the wiki databases that are 
published in this issue. In this model, although the wiki is 
closed there is a relatively low barrier to being accepted as 
an editor. In the 'vampire' model adopted by GONUTS 
(4) and EcoliWiki (5) any registered user can create new 
user accounts for their colleagues. Thus, the burden of 
maintaining the editor list is shared among all editors. 
There are 11 different articles in this Database Issue of 
NAR that describe the use of wikis as all or part of the 
database, listed in Table 1. Despite the use of different 
wiki implementations and the varied data that are being 
annotated, those articles reporting numbers of wiki edits 
are typically reporting thousands of edits per year (3-5,6). 
These numbers are consistent with those that we have 
observed (2). 
Interestingly, both resources that utilise Wikipedia 
describe independently developed quality control proced-
ures for Wikipedia articles. Pfam (and Rfam) uses the 
Wikipedia API to track new edits and present them to 
the biocurators for approval to ensure that the changes 
to the article are appropriate, before the article is dis-
played on the database website (7). The authors of the 
GeneWiki project have developed the <rs type="software">WikiTrust</rs> 
resource (3), which works via a <rs type="software">Firefox</rs> plug-in, to mark 
up Wikipedia articles according to the Wikipedian's repu-
tation. Both approaches have their merits and are both 
aimed at maintaining quality in the open wiki setting. </p>

<p>Database integration levels with Wikipeida </p>

<p>There are many ways that a database can be integrated 
with Wikipedia. The GeneWiki project is completely con-
tained within Wikipedia as a portal, which acts like a 
homepage to the project-there is no standalone 
database. Each gene annotated by the project corresponds 
to a full article. But, full articles are not the only way to 
contribute to Wikipedia and expose biological databases. 
For example, the 'infoboxes' found on the right side on 
many Wikipedia pages provide a more structured way of 
adding data. The PDB database of protein structures (8) 
has a large number of links from infoboxes in Wikipedia. 
So, although it would not make sense to have a Wikipedia 
article about any particular protein crystal structure, 
the information is very relevant to readers of articles 
about biological molecules. Biological databases such as 
UniProtKB (9) are increasingly adding links to Wikipedia 
articles because the information is recognized as valuable. 
Pfam and Rfam adopt a model where having identified 
relevant articles in Wikipedia, we not only link to them, 
but we also import the articles back into our web pages. 
This is made possible by the open license used by 
Wikipedia. If a user wishes to change the annotation 
that Pfam or Rfam displays then they only need to go 
to Wikipedia to edit that article. </p>

<p>Leveraging the Wikipedia community </p>

<p>There are a number of excellent forums for discussing how 
to incorporate your ideas into Wikipedia. This is highly 
recommended before embarking on a mass of changes that 
may not be appropriate for Wikipedia but may be </p>



<p>tweaked and modified in order to make a positive contri-
bution. Many well-meaning editors are put off by negative 
responses and even wholesale removal of their initial edits 
and articles. For example, if you added hundreds of 
links to your database from Wikipedia this is likely to 
be viewed simply as advertising. By engaging the existing 
communities these problems can be avoided, vastly im-
proving the editing experience. Of particular importance 
to the readers here are the WikiProjects: 'Molecular and 
Cellular Biology' and 'Computational Biology' and the 
'Gene Wiki' Portal (3). Wiki-colleagues there will be 
happy to make useful suggestions and may get involved 
in your project. Keep in mind that your main focus should 
be improving Wikipedia and not promoting your sphere 
of influence or getting more people to view your product. 
It is worth starting by editing some articles to get an idea 
of how Wikipedia works, as well as building up a history 
of trusted edits. Wikipedia editors will take you more ser-
iously if you are seen as one of them. For more advice on 
getting involved in Wikipedia there is a 10 simple rules 
article with plenty of useful advice (10). </p>

<p>Wikipedia infrastructure and content </p>

<p>In this section, we are not planning on comparing different 
wiki applications, which should be based on the require-
ments of the database, for example, database storage 
engine, programming language, file uploads and so on 
(see http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comparison_of_wiki_ 
software). Rather, can an existing wiki, such as 
Wikipedia be used as the wiki, rather than duplicating 
software and hardware and going through the hardship 
of maintaining the infrastructure yourself? 
This decision is almost certainly going to be influenced 
by whether an open or closed user base is required. If the 
database wants to control the user access, then that 
database will have to maintain the wiki. However, other 
factors will influence whether Wikipedia is appropriate. 
Not all content is appropriate for Wikipedia, as facts 
need to be cited to a reliable, published source (http:// 
en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Verifiability) and the 
content needs to be devoid of jargon and accessible to a 
broad audience. For example, the wiki TOPSAN (11) </p>

<p>includes user's conjecture as to the function of certain 
protein domains, based on unpublished structures and 
other experiments, this sort of content would violate 
Wikipedia's policy regarding 'No Original Research' and 
would 
be 
removed 
(http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ 
Wikipedia:No_original_research). 
Other wikis, such as PDBwiki (12) and SNPedia (13) 
contain data that are too specific to be included in an 
encyclopedia such as Wikipedia. Therefore, both the 
type of content and granularity of entries need to be care-
fully considered before using Wikipedia. Concepts that are 
unlikely to be considered notable by the broader 
Wikipedia community should not have their own entries. 
For example, each of the 24 534 SNPs in SNPedia or the 
75 245 structures in PDBwiki are not significant in their 
own right. However, these data sets may make excellent 
sections on less specific articles, such as on a notable gene 
with SNPs influencing phenotype and structures 
elucidating function. Furthermore, SNPedia does not 
maintain Wikipedia's 'No original research' policy and 
instead actively invites well-documented original 
research. Two important questions that you need to ask 
when thinking about adding to Wikipedia are: are your 
data notable and verifiable? And, should it be merged with 
existing Wikipedia entries rather than creating new and 
overly specific entries? </p>

<p>The limitations of wikis in relation to biological databases </p>

<p>Are wikis the future of biological databases? Well, the 
answer is yes, and no. They help bridge the vast gap 
between the amount of human-annotated data compared 
to unannotated data. Where annotations do exist, the use 
of wikis can help to improve the annotation and keep it 
relevant. But, wikis are extremely simple and are unlikely 
to replace the complex relational organisation of many 
biological databases. Furthermore, when using 
Wikipedia, the database that uses a particular article has 
no control over future revisions even though they may 
have created it. We have already mentioned editing, but 
there is a more substantial control issue. An article, if the 
Wikipedia community considers it appropriate, can be 
deleted or merged into another article. Although </p>

<p>Table 1. A list of the databases utilising wikis that appear in this issue </p>

<p>Resource 
URL 
Brief description </p>

<p>EcoliWiki 
http://ecoliwiki.net 
Escherichia coli strain, phage, plasmid, and mobile genetic element 
information resource 
GeneWiki 
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portal:Gene_Wiki 
Collection of human gene annotations 
GONUTS 
http://gowiki.tamu.edu 
Gene ontology application guide 
Metadatabase 
http://metadatabase.org 
Catalogue of biological databases 
959 Nematode genomes 
http://www.nematodes.org 
Nematode sequencing project resource 
Pfam 
http://pfam.janelia.org; http://pfam.sanger.ac.uk 
Database of protein families, with annotations stored in Wikipedia 
SEQwiki 
http://SEQwiki.org 
Catalogue of tools, technologies and tutorials for high-throughput 
sequencing 
SNPedia 
http://www.SNPedia.com 
Resource of the functional consequences of human genetic 
variation 
SubtiWiki 
http://subtiwiki.uni-goettingen.de 
Collection of Bacillus subtilis genome annotations 
WikiPathways 
http://www.wikipathways.org 
Pathway curation and annotations 
XanthusBase 
http://www.xanthusbase.org 
Annotation resource for Myococcus xanthus and related bacteria </p>



<p>page-redirects are maintained, the article may be substan-
tially different to the original article that was cited. In our 
experience, the deleting or merging of entries is a rare 
event and tends to improve content for articles used by 
Pfam or Rfam. However, this goes back to the point of 
thinking about granularity and content of the article in 
Wikipedia in the first place. 
In the case of Pfam and Rfam, there is a logical 
marriage with Wikipedia that stores the annotations for 
the families. All the other family data, such as multiple 
sequence alignments are stored in a local MySQL 
database. As well as the relational data model, wikis 
also do not lend themselves to storing data entities such 
as alignments, structures and probabilistic models. Most 
databases have extensive quality control procedures, 
which do not fit the simple edit and save model of the 
wiki. Consequently, other mechanisms are required to 
add new entries to the database [for an example from 
Pfam, see ref. (7)], but wikis, in whatever form, provide 
an excellent platform for storing free text annotations that 
are editable by a distributed user community. </p>

<p>Is the work of a dedicated database biocurator at an end? </p>

<p>There is a risk to the funding of biological databases and 
biocurators that can be created by the implementation of 
successful community annotation. Will funders and grant 
reviewers think that biological databases can be curated 
by a diffuse network of volunteers? This is certainly not 
the case and at the core of every successful wiki database 
are a group of dedicated experts who do the bulk of the 
data curation. One of the lessons from wiki databases is 
that there is a large community of people who are 
prepared to make a small number of changes to their 
subject of interest. But this piecemeal contribution will 
not give a comprehensive set of data that is required for 
biological integration of data. However, we envisage that 
the role of biocurators may change. Instead of solely 
curating entries, they will need to train new users, verify 
edits and resolve conflicts as they arise. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Wikis are undoubtedly changing the way some biological 
databases operate, providing an established solution to 
community annotation. Adopting a wiki means that a par-
ticular resource is no longer a closed, static resource 
(between public data releases) that cannot be improved 
by its users. The challenge is now to get scientists 
en masse to generate and edit articles. How editors 
receive credit for their work on the article is unclear. 
Assuming they work on the subject area, wiki articles 
provide them an opportunity to showcase their work in 
context of the field at the very least. Curation of biological 
data must be crowdsourced if there is any chance to com-
prehensively annotate the vast datasets that are being 
generated and the scientific community should feel respon-
sible. Hopefully this article has provoked thoughts as to 
how a wiki, especially Wikipedia, may work for a resource </p>

<p>that you are responsible for or use. The growing number 
of databases using wikis suggests that they are here to 
stay, we now face the issue of how to overcome the 
social engineering required to get everyone involved. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Howard Hughes Medical Institute (to R.D.F); Rutherford 
Discovery Fellowship from NZ Government (to P.P.G.); 
Wellcome Trust (WT098051 to A.B.). The open access 
publication charge for this paper has been waived by 
Oxford University Press-NAR Editorial Board 
members are entitled to one free paper per year in recog-
nition of their work on behalf of the journal. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>





</text></tei>