<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3542452" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: To assess the position and movements of the hyoid bone during 
deglutition in patients with open bite. Methods: Thirty-six subjects were divided 
into 2 groups according to the presence of anterior open bite. The open bite group 
(OBG) and control group each comprised 18 patients with a mean overbite of -4.9 
± 1.9 mm and 1.9 ± 0.7 mm. The position of the hyoid bone during the 4 stages 
of deglutition was evaluated by measuring vertical and horizontal movement of 
the bone. Results: Interactions of group and stage showed no significant effect 
on the measurements (p &gt; 0.05). However, when group and stage were evaluated 
individually, they showed significant effects on the measurements (p &lt; 0.001). In 
OBG, the hyoid bone was more inferiorly and posteriorly positioned, and this 
position continued during the deglutition stages. Conclusions: The hyoid bone 
reaches the maximum anterior position at the oral stage and maximum superior 
position at the pharyngeal stage during deglutition. Open bite does not change the 
displacement pattern of the bone during deglutition. The hyoid bone is positioned 
more inferiorly and posteriorly in patients with open bite because of released 
tension on the suprahyoid muscles. 
[Korean J Orthod 2012;42(6):318-328] </p>

<p>The hyoid bone is unique because it has no bony articu-
lation. However, it is an insertion element for muscles, 
ligaments, and fasciae attached to the mandible, clavicle, 
sternum, cranium, and cervical vertebrae. The hyoid bone 
is an important part of the musculoskeletal apparatus of 
the craniofacial complex and factors affecting this system 
might have not only local but systemic effects as well. </p>

<p>1   Mandibular repositioning by advancement or setback 
sur geries reportedly changes the position of the hyoid 
bone by causing alterations in the tension of the supra-
hyoid and infrahyoid muscles, neck extensor muscles, and 
cervical fasciae. 
2-4 Its position also changes in relation to 
postural changes of the head and tongue, malocclusion, 
and facial type. 
1,5-9 Several authors reported that the posi-
tion of the hyoid bone is affected by the biomechanics of 
the suprahyoid and infrahyoid muscles and the elastic 
membranes of the larynx and trachea. 
10,11 Andersen, </p>

<p>12   Subtelny and Sakuda, 
13 and Haralabakis et al. 
9 studied the 
position of the hyoid bone in patients with open bite and 
observed the stability of its vertical position. However, 
Haralabakis et al., 
9 who also evaluated the horizontal 
position of the hyoid bone according to a vertical line 
drawn from the Frankfort horizontal (FH) plane at 
porion, reported that it is positioned more pos te riorly 
in patients with open bite. Yet the horizontal distance 
of the hyoid bone from the cervical spine, pharynx, and 
mandibular plane (MP) is not influenced by open bite. 
In most previous studies, cephalometric measurements 
were used to determine hyoid bone positioning. How-
ever, as this bone moves forward and upward during 
swallowing, evaluation of its movements during de-
glu ti tion is more important than investigating its static 
posi tion. Mays et al. 
14 evaluated the influence of crani-
ofacial morphology on hyoid bone movements by 
video fluoroscopy and demonstrated that the forward 
displacement of the hyoid bone during liquid swallowing 
is significantly related to craniofacial morphology. For 
instance, as the FH-MP angle (FMA) increases, the 
forward displacement of the hyoid bone decreases. These 
authors suggested that the observed effects are related to 
the biomechanics of the suprahyoid musculature. Sloan et 
al. 
15 also analyzed hyoid bone behavior during deglutition 
by cinefluorography and detected two distinct movement 
patterns: a circular pattern and an oblique, elliptical 
pattern. 
Postural changes in the mandible and tongue affect 
the position of the hyoid bone. 
5-8 Open bite is usually 
associated with posterior rotation of the mandible and 
changes in the tongue posture and deglutitive tongue 
movements. 
16-18 Therefore, open bite may also affect 
the position and movements of the hyoid bone during 
deglutition. The aim of this retrospective study was to </p>

<p>assess the position and movements of the hyoid bone 
during deglutition in patients with open bite by real-
time balanced turbo field echo (B-TFE) cine magnetic 
resonance imaging (cine MRI). </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Subjects 
The cine MRI images used in this study were selected 
from records obtained to evaluate deglutitive tongue 
move ments in patients with open bite and Class II maloc-
clusions. 
18,19 This study was initiated after obtaining 
institutional approval from Gulhane Military Medical 
Academy's Ethics Committee (1491-373-07). Images of 
36 patients with normal overjet (1 -3 mm) were selected. 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">G*Power</rs> software (v<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">3.1.3</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Franz Faul</rs>, Universitat Kiel, 
Germany) was used to determine the power of the sample 
size. 
20 A sample size of 36 patients was considered suf-
ficient to provide more than 60% power for detecting 
significant differences with an effect size of 0.30 between 
groups at a 0.05 significance level. 
Two groups were formed according to the presence of 
anterior open bite (at least −2 mm). The open bite group 
(OBG) included 18 patients (14 girls and 4 boys) with a 
mean age of 14.5 ± 2.7 years and mean overbite of −4.9 ± 
1.9 mm. The control group (CG) comprised 18 patients (11 
girls and 7 boys) with a mean age of 16.4 ± 0.9 years and 
mean overbite of 1.9 ± 0.7 mm. Cephalometric analyses </p>

<p>Figure 1. Anatomical structures visible on cine magnetic 
resonance imaging (a) nasal cavity, (b) nasopharynx, (c) 
tongue, (d) lips, (e) incisors, (f) floor of the mouth, (g) 
hyoid bone, (h) symphysis, (i) pharynx, (j) larynx, (k) spinal 
column, (l) spinal cord, (m) epiglottis, (n) cricoid cartilage 
and cricotracheal membrane, (o) trachea, and (p) upper 
portion of the esophagus. </p>

<p>Karacay et al • Hyoid bone movements in subjects with open bite </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4041/kjod.2012.42.6.318 </p>

<p>revealed that 4 patients in the OBG and 2 patients in 
the CG had mild skeletal Class II malocclusions with an 
ANB angle of 5 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>, although their overjet was in the normal 
range. Other patients had skeletal Class I malocclusions 
and ANB angles ranging from 1 
o to 4 
o . In the OBG, 
the MP angle (SN-GoGn) was 35.56 ± 1.69 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>, FMA was 
28.17 ± 1.62 
o , and the palatal plane (PP) angle (SN-
PP) was 5.72 ± 1.28°, revealing posterior rotation of the 
mandible and anterior rotation of the PP. In the CG, these 
measurements were 32.61 ± 1.33 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>, 23.83 ± 1.29 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>, and 7.28 
± 1.32 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>, respectively. None of the patients had complaints 
related to masticatory difficulty, dysphasia, or swallowing 
disorders. </p>

<p>Cine MRI and stages of deglutition 
A detailed description of the dynamic images obtained 
by B-TFE cine MRI (New Intera Nova; Philips Medical 
Systems, Best, The Netherlands) has been presented in 
our previous reports. 
18,19 Figure 1 shows the anatomical 
structures visible on these images. For each patient, 
images of the following 4 stages of deglutition during 
water swallowing were determined by a consensus of 3 
specialists and printed on radiographs. 
Stage 1 (oral preparatory stage): The tongue tip contacts 
the maxillary incisors and/or the palatal mucosa (Figure 
2A). 
Stage 2 (oral stage): The dorsum of the tongue loses 
contact with the soft palate (Figure 2B). 
Stage 3 (pharyngeal stage): The bolus crosses the 
posterior or inferior margin of the mandibular ramus 
(Figure 2C). 
Stage 4 (esophageal stage): The bolus enters the eso-
phageal opening (Figure 2D). </p>

<p>Measurements 
To determine the position and movements of the hyoid 
bone during deglutition, linear measurements were 
obtained from the printed radiographs by the same </p>

<p>investigator (SG) to avoid inter-examiner variability. The 
distance between the hyoid bone and point sella (H-S), 
the vertical distance between the hyoid bone and PP (H-
PP), and the vertical distance between the hyoid bone 
and a line connecting the most anteroinferior point of the 
third cervical vertebra and retrognathion (H-C3RGN) 
were used to evaluate the vertical movement of the </p>

<p>Figure 2. Stages of deglutition. A, stage 1 (oral preparatory stage), the tongue tip contacts the maxillary incisors and/ 
or the palatal mucosa; B, stage 2 (oral stage), the dorsum of the tongue loses contact with the soft palate; C, stage 3 
(pharyngeal stage), the bolus crosses the posterior or inferior margin of the mandibular ramus; and D, stage 4 (esophageal 
stage), the bolus enters the esophageal opening. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Measurements used for evaluating hyoid bone 
movements. (1) H-S, distance between hyoidale (H, the 
most anterosuperior point of the hyoid bone) and point 
sella (S); (2) H-PP, perpendicular distance of hyoidale 
to the palatal plane (PP); (3) H-C3RGN, perpendicular 
distance of hyoidale to the line connecting the most 
anteroinferior point of the third cervical vertebra (C3) 
and retrognathion (RNG, the most prominent point of 
the posterior border of the symphysis); (4) H-C3, distance 
between hyoidale and the most anteroinferior point 
of the third cervical vertebra; and (5) H-RGN, distance 
between hyoidale and retrognathion. </p>

<p>Karacay et al • Hyoid bone movements in subjects with open bite </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4041/kjod.2012.42.6.318 </p>

<p>hyoid bone. The horizontal movement was evaluated by 
measuring the distances between the hyoid bone and the 
most anteroinferior point of the third cervical vertebra 
(H-C3) as well as the distance between the hyoid bone 
and retrognathion (H-RGN) (Figure 3). 
The measurements of 10 patients were repeated 1 month </p>

<p>later, and reliability was evaluated by using intraclass 
correlation coefficients (ICCs) and Bland-Altman plots. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
All statistical analyses were performed with <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> for 
Windows (version <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">15</rs>, IBM <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, </p>

<p>Figure 4. Bland-Altman plots of the average differences 
in the measurements. A, H-S; B, H-C3RGN; C, H-PP; 
D, H-C3; and E, H-RGN. The overall bias of each 
measurement is shown, along with the 95% agreement 
interval. SD, Standard deviation. Refer to Figure 3 for 
measurements and abbreviations. </p>

<p>Karacay et al • Hyoid bone movements in subjects with open bite </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4041/kjod.2012.42.6.318 </p>

<p>USA). The Shapiro-Wilks and Levene tests were applied 
to the data and mean ages, which were both found to 
be normally distributed and showed homogeneity of 
variance between groups. Therefore, parametric tests were 
performed for further analysis. Within-group differences 
in the stages of deglutition were analyzed with the paired-
samples t-test. Repeated-measures analysis of variance 
(ANOVA) was used to evaluate the differences between 
groups and the significance of the interaction between 
stages and groups. p ≤ 0.05 was considered significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The ICCs for H-S, H-C3RGN, H-PP, H-C3, and H-RGN 
measurements were 0.99 (95% confidence interval [CI] 
= 0.96 to 0.99), 0.86 (95% CI = 0.40 to 0.96), 0.98 (95% 
CI = 0.92 to 0.99), 0.96 (95% CI = 0.83 to 0.99), and 0.97 
(95% CI = 0.90 to 0.99), respectively. Bland-Altman plots 
showed a high degree of agreement (Figure 4). 
Descriptive statistics of the measurements are presented 
in Table 1. In this table, mean values and standard devia-
tions of the measurements according to the stages are 
shown for both OBG and CG. 
With regard to the vertical movement of the hyoid bone 
(Tables 2 and 3), the OBG and CG showed significant 
decreases in the H-S measurement (p &lt; 0.001 and p &lt; 
0.01, respectively) between stages 1 and 2 and between 
stages 1 and 3. However, the groups showed significant 
increases (p &lt; 0.001 and p &lt; 0.01, respectively) at stage 4, 
as determined by the comparisons between stages 2 and 
4 and stages 3 and 4. However, only the OBG showed a 
significant difference between stages 1 and 4 (p &lt; 0.05). 
Similarly, the H-C3RGN measurement significantly 
decreased between stages 1 and 2 and between stages 1 
and 3, but significantly increased between stages 2 and 4 </p>

<p>and stages 3 and 4 in the OBG (p &lt; 0.01). On the other 
hand, in the CG, this measurement showed significant 
changes only between stages 1 and 2 (p &lt; 0.01) and 
stages 1 and 3 (p &lt; 0.05). Moreover, both groups showed 
significant decreases in the H-PP measurement at stages 
2 and 3 when compared with stage 1 (p &lt; 0.001 for the 
OBG; p &lt; 0.01 and p &lt; 0.001, respectively, for the CG). 
Significant increases in this measurement were also 
found between stages 2 and 4 and between stages 3 and 
4 in the OBG (p &lt; 0.001) and CG (p &lt; 0.05 and p &lt; 0.01, 
respectively). 
Figures 5A-5C show the displacement of the hyoid bone 
according to the H-S, H-C3RGN, and H-PP measure-
ments in both groups. The hyoid bone was located more 
inferiorly at all stages in the OBG than in the CG. In 
terms of the H-S and H-C3RGN measurements, the hyoid 
bone reached its most superior position at stage 3 in both 
groups. However, in the case of H-PP, the hyoid bone 
reached its most superior position at stage 2 in the OBG. 
In the evaluation of the horizontal movement (Tables 
2 and 3) of the hyoid bone, a significant increase in the 
H-C3 measurement was observed in between stages 1 and 
2 in the OBG (p &lt; 0.001) and CG (p &lt; 0.01). Although the 
increases between stages 1 and 3 and stages 1 and 4 were 
not significant in the OBG (p &gt; 0.05), they were significant 
in the CG (p &lt; 0.05). The H-C3 measurement decreased 
between stages 2 and 3, stages 2 and 4, and stages 3 and 4 
in both groups, but a significant change was determined 
only between stages 2 and 4 in the OBG (p &lt; 0.05). When 
the H-RGN measurement was evaluated, a significant 
decrease between stages 1 and 2 was found in both the 
OBG (p &lt; 0.05) and the CG (p &lt; 0.001). A significant 
decrease was also found between stages 1 and 3 in the CG 
(p &lt; 0.05). This measurement increased between stages 2 
and 3, stages 2 and 4, and stages 3 and 4 in both groups, </p>

<p>Table 1. Descriptive statistics of the measurements (unit : mm) </p>

<p>Stage 1 
Stage 2 
Stage 3 
Stage 4 </p>

<p>H-S 
OBG 
115.33 (6.544) 
102.83 (7.446) 
101.17 (7.687) 
114.11 (6.258) </p>

<p>CG 
105.05 (7.089) 
95.85 (9.281) 
95.90 (9.049) 
104.55 (7.977) </p>

<p>H-C3RGN 
OBG 
14.89 (1.875) 
13.11 (2.349) 
12.89 (1.875) 
15.00 (2.196) </p>

<p>CG 
13.20 (2.042) 
11.20 (2.587) 
11.30 (3.097) 
12.65 (3.528) </p>

<p>H-PP 
OBG 
67.78 (3.474) 
61.22 (4.882) 
61.61 (4.717) 
67.94 (3.811) </p>

<p>CG 
60.75 (3.291) 
55.60 (6.336) 
54.60 (4.210) 
59.60 (5.557) </p>

<p>H-C3 
OBG 
33.56 (2.595) 
36.72 (2.653) 
35.06 (3.134) 
35.00 (2.029) </p>

<p>CG 
35.70 (3.854) 
39.05 (4.058) 
38.30 (3.757) 
38.05 (3.103) </p>

<p>H-RGN 
OBG 
36.06 (4.108) 
32.33 (3.272) 
34.94 (3.489) 
35.11 (3.394) </p>

<p>CG 
39.25 (3.059) 
35.85 (2.323) 
36.90 (3.354) 
37.15 (2.777) </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean (standard deviation). 
OBG, Open bite group (n = 18); CG, control group (n = 18). 
Refer to Figure 3 for measurements and abbreviations. </p>

<p>Karacay et al • Hyoid bone movements in subjects with open bite </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4041/kjod.2012.42.6.318 </p>

<p>but significant changes were determined only between 
stages 2 and 3 and stages 2 and 4 in the OBG (p &lt; 0.05). 
The hyoid bone was closer to the third cervical vertebra 
and retrognathion at all stages in the OBG when com-
pared to the CG (Figure 5D and 5E). According to H-C3 
and H-RGN measurements, the hyoid bone reached 
its most anterior position at stage 2 and returned to its 
normal position gradually during stages 3 and 4 in both </p>

<p>groups. 
Interactions between groups and stages had no signifi-
cant effects on the measurements (p &gt; 0.05). How ever, 
when these factors were analyzed individually, the 
effects of group on the measurements were found to be 
significant (p &lt; 0.001 for H-S, H-PP, and H-RGN; p &lt; 
0.01 for H-C3RGN and H-C3). Similarly, stage also had 
significant effects (p &lt; 0.001 for H-S and H-PP; p &lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>Table 2. Differences in the measurements between the stages of deglutition in the open bite group (n=18) </p>

<p>Stage </p>

<p>Paired differences 
t 
p-value 
Mean 
Standard 
deviation </p>

<p>Standard error 
mean </p>

<p>H-S 
1 -2 
12.500 
7.733 
1.823 
6.858 
0.000* </p>

<p>1 -3 
14167 
8.726 
2.057 
6.888 
0.000* </p>

<p>1 -4 
1.222 
2.315 
0.546 
2.240 
0.039* </p>

<p>2 -3 
1.667 
5.099 
1.202 
1.387 
0.183 </p>

<p>2 -4 
−11.278 
7.274 
1.715 
−6.577 
0.000* </p>

<p>3 -4 
−12.944 
7.840 
1.848 
−7.005 
0.000* </p>

<p>H-C3RGN 
1 -2 
1.778 
1.833 
0.432 
4.115 
0.001* </p>

<p>1 -3 
2.000 
2.425 
0.572 
3.499 
0.003* </p>

<p>1 -4 
−0.111 
2.166 
0.511 
−0.218 
0.830 </p>

<p>2 -3 
0.222 
2.579 
0.608 
0.366 
0.719 </p>

<p>2 -4 
−1.889 
2.632 
0.620 
−3.045 
0.007* </p>

<p>3 -4 
−2.111 
2.847 
0.671 
−3.146 
0.006* </p>

<p>H-PP 
1 -2 
6.556 
5.159 
1.216 
5.391 
0.000* </p>

<p>1 -3 
6.167 
5.854 
1.380 
4.470 
0.000* </p>

<p>1 -4 
−0.167 
4.004 
0.944 
−0.177 
0.862 </p>

<p>2 -3 
−0.389 
4.578 
1.079 
−0.360 
0.723 </p>

<p>2 -4 
−6.722 
5.859 
1.381 
-4.868 
0.000* </p>

<p>3 -4 
−6.333 
4.887 
1.152 
−5.498 
0.000* </p>

<p>H-C3 
1 -2 
−3.167 
2.792 
0.658 
−4.812 
0.000* </p>

<p>1 -3 
−1.500 
4.260 
1.004 
−1.494 
0.154 </p>

<p>1 -4 
−1.444 
3.258 
0.768 
−1.881 
0.077 </p>

<p>2 -3 
1.667 
4.678 
1.103 
1.512 
0.149 </p>

<p>2 -4 
1.722 
3.268 
0.770 
2.236 
0.039* </p>

<p>3 -4 
0.056 
3.572 
0.842 
0.066 
0.948 </p>

<p>H-RGN 
1 -2 
3.722 
5.707 
1.345 
2.767 
0.013* </p>

<p>1 -3 
1.111 
6.144 
1.448 
0.767 
0.453 </p>

<p>1 -4 
0.944 
4.608 
1.086 
0.870 
0.397 </p>

<p>2 -3 
−2.611 
4.118 
0.971 
−2.690 
0.015* </p>

<p>2 -4 
−2.778 
4.622 
1.089 
−2.550 
0.021* </p>

<p>3 -4 
−0.167 
5.448 
1.284 
−0.130 
0.898 </p>

<p>*Statistically significant (by 2-tailed test). 
Refer to Figure 3 for measurements and abbreviations. </p>

<p>Karacay et al • Hyoid bone movements in subjects with open bite </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4041/kjod.2012.42.6.318 </p>

<p>for H-RGN, H-C3RGN, and H-C3) (Table 4). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The hyoid bone moves upward and downward by the 
contraction of the suprahyoid musculature and relaxation 
of the cricopharyngeus. 
21 This synergistic contraction 
and relaxation also facilitates displacement of the tongue, 
pulls the larynx forward and upward, and opens the </p>

<p>upper esophageal sphincter, permitting the bolus to enter 
the esophagus. 
21,22 These phenomena are accompanied 
by the sealing of the larynx, which is essential for safe 
swallowing. As the suprahyoid muscles are attached to 
several craniofacial landmarks, including the mandibular 
symphysis, inferior border of the mandible, base of the 
skull, and tongue, a relationship exists between the hyoid, 
tongue, and mandible during swallowing. 
Previous studies using cine MRI revealed that move-</p>

<p>Table 3. Differences in the measurements between the stages of deglutition in the control group (n=18) </p>

<p>Stage </p>

<p>Paired differences 
t 
p-value 
Mean 
Standard 
deviation </p>

<p>Standard error 
mean </p>

<p>H-S 
1 -2 
9.200 
9.666 
2.161 
4.257 
0.000* </p>

<p>1 -3 
9.150 
13.531 
3.026 
3.024 
0.007* </p>

<p>1 -4 
0.500 
3.804 
0.851 
0.588 
0.564 </p>

<p>2 -3 
−0.050 
12.800 
2.862 
−0.017 
0.986 </p>

<p>2 -4 
−8.700 
10.579 
2.365 
−3.678 
0.002* </p>

<p>3 -4 
−8.650 
13.888 
3.105 
−2.785 
0.012* </p>

<p>H-C3RGN 
1 -2 
2.000 
2.449 
0.548 
3.651 
0.002* </p>

<p>1 -3 
1.900 
2.972 
0.665 
2.859 
0.010* </p>

<p>1 -4 
0.550 
3.348 
0.749 
0.735 
0.471 </p>

<p>2 -3 
−0.100 
3.493 
0.781 
−0.128 
0.899 </p>

<p>2 -4 
−1.450 
4.383 
0.980 
−1.480 
0.155 </p>

<p>3 -4 
−1.350 
4.271 
0.955 
−1.414 
0.174 </p>

<p>H-PP 
1 -2 
5.150 
7.250 
1.621 
3.177 
0.005* </p>

<p>1 -3 
6.150 
4.452 
0.995 
6.178 
0.000* </p>

<p>1 -4 
1.150 
4.308 
0.963 
1.194 
0.247 </p>

<p>2 -3 
1.000 
6.122 
1.369 
0.731 
0.474 </p>

<p>2 -4 
−4.000 
7.616 
1.703 
−2.349 
0.030* </p>

<p>3 -4 
−5.000 
6.601 
1.476 
−3.387 
0.003* </p>

<p>H-C3 
1 -2 
−3.350 
4.404 
0.985 
−3.402 
0.003* </p>

<p>1 -3 
−2.600 
4.535 
1.014 
−2.564 
0.019* </p>

<p>1 -4 
−2.350 
4.848 
1.084 
−2.168 
0.043* </p>

<p>2 -3 
0.750 
3.567 
0.798 
0.940 
0.359 </p>

<p>2 -4 
1.000 
5.099 
1.140 
0.877 
0.391 </p>

<p>3 -4 
0.250 
3.611 
0.807 
0.310 
0.760 </p>

<p>H-RGN 
1 -2 
3.400 
3.331 
0.745 
4.565 
0.000* </p>

<p>1 -3 
2.350 
4.557 
1.019 
2.306 
0.033* </p>

<p>1 -4 
2.100 
4.564 
1.021 
2.058 
0.054 </p>

<p>2 -3 
−1.050 
3.034 
0.679 
−1.547 
0.138 </p>

<p>2 -4 
−1.300 
4.181 
0.935 
−1.390 
0.180 </p>

<p>3 -4 
−0.250 
4.038 
0.903 
−0.277 
0.785 </p>

<p>*Statistically significant (by 2-tailed test). 
Refer to Figure 3 for measurements and abbreviations. </p>

<p>Karacay et al • Hyoid bone movements in subjects with open bite </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4041/kjod.2012.42.6.318 </p>

<p>ments during deglutition are affected by the dentofacial 
morphology and adaptive changes at the tip, dorsum, and 
root of the tongue. 
18,23-25 Fujiki et al. 
17 and Akin et al. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>reported compensatory coordination of tongue move-
ment, soft palate movement, and pharyngeal constrictor 
muscle activity during deglutition in patients with open 
bite, but the effects on hyoid bone movements during </p>

<p>deglutition were not evaluated. Therefore, we evaluated 
the effects of anterior open bite on hyoid bone movements 
during deglutition by cine MRI, a noninvasive and reliable 
technique. To the best of our knowledge, no such study 
has ever been performed. The turbo-FLASH sequence 
was preferred because this sequence provides the best 
temporal resolution and sufficient spatial resolution </p>

<p>Figure 5. Plots of the mean A, H-S; B, H-C3RGN; C, H-
PP; D, H-C3; and E, H-RGN values as a function of the 
stages of deglutition in the open bite group (group 1) 
and the control group (group 2). Refer to Figure 3 for 
measurements and abbreviations. </p>

<p>Karacay et al • Hyoid bone movements in subjects with open bite </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4041/kjod.2012.42.6.318 </p>

<p>during motion. 
26 Water-swallowing sets are reportedly 
more reliable than dry-swallowing sets for distinguishing 
the stages of deglutition because the borders of soft 
tissues, especially the tongue, can be easily and correctly 
determined. 
23 In this study, we used 10 mL water as 
the bolus. Standardization of the bolus volume is also 
important because it affects the movements of the hyoid 
bone. </p>

<p>27   In the current study, the vertical measurements revealed 
that patients with open bite had an inferiorly positioned 
hyoid bone during all stages of deglutition. When the 
movement of the hyoid bone was evaluated according to 
sella and the plane connecting the third cervical verte-
bra and retrognathion, both groups showed superior 
displacement of the hyoid bone from stage 1 to stages 2 
and 3. The hyoid bone reached its most superior position 
at stage 3 and nearly returned to its initial position at 
stage 4. However, evaluation according to the PP revealed 
that the hyoid bone reached its most superior position 
at stage 2 in patients with open bite. This difference is 
probably related to anterior rotation of the PP frequently 
encountered in patients with anterior open bite. Ander-
sen 
12 and Subtelny and Sakuda 
13 compared the vertical 
positions of the hyoid bone between patients with 
open bite and those with normal occlusion. Contrary 
to our findings, they found no significant differences 
between these groups. However, supporting our results, 
Haralabakis et al. 
9 found that the distance between the 
hyoid bone and PP is greater in patients with open bite, 
indicating an inferior position of the hyoid bone. 
With regard to the horizontal measurements, the hyoid 
bone was closer to both the third cervical vertebra and 
retrognathion in patients with open bite. This result 
may seem to be conflicting. However, posterior rotation 
of the mandible is common in patients with anterior 
open bite 
28 and may explain our findings. Depending on 
posterior mandibular rotation, the symphysis is located 
more inferiorly and posteriorly in these patients. The 
horizontal measurements revealed that, in both groups, 
the hyoid bone was displaced anteriorly from stage 1 to 
stage 2, reached its most anterior position at stage 2, and 
was gradually displaced in a posterior direction at stages 3 
and 4. The inferior and posterior positioning of the hyoid </p>

<p>bone during all stages of deglutition in patients with 
open bite can be explained by the released tension of the 
suprahyoid muscles. 
Similar to our findings, many previous studies have 
showed a close association between the inclination of the 
hyoid bone and mandibular inclination. 
7,9,29 Tallgren and 
Solow 
7 reported that the vertical positional changes in the 
hyoid bone follow the patterns of change in mandi bular 
inclination, whereas the horizontal positional changes 
mainly follow the changes in cervical inclination and 
craniofacial angulation. In our opinion, the closer posi-
tion of the hyoid bone to the third cervical vertebra in 
patients with open bite is related to hyperextension of the 
head in these patients, causing the cervical spine to be 
stretched and decreasing the distance between the third 
cervical vertebra and hyoid bone. In accordance with our 
view, Opdebeeck et al. 
30 reported that the cross-section of 
the lower pharynx is reduced and that the hyoid bone is 
closer to the cervical spine in subjects with a high FMA. 
Encroachment of the vital pharyngeal space induces 
stret ching of the cervical spine and hyperextension of 
the head. Jena and Duggal, 
29 who evaluated hyoid bone 
posi tion in subjects with different vertical jaw dysplasias, 
also reported that subjects with short face and long face 
syndromes have anteriorly and posteriorly positioned 
hyoid bones, respectively. Haralabakis et al. 
9 found that 
the horizontal distance between the hyoid bone and the 
perpendicular line from the FH plane at porion is greater 
in patients with open bite, indicating a more posterior 
position of the hyoid bone. However, Subtelny and 
Sakuda 
13 found no difference in the horizontal position of 
the hyoid bone in patients with open bite, contrary to our 
findings. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>1. Real-time B-TFE cine MRI is a valuable tool to evaluate 
the movements of the hyoid bone during deglutition. 
2. The hyoid bone reaches its most anterior and superior 
positions at the oral (stage 2) and pharyngeal (stage 
3) stages of deglutition, respectively. Open bite does 
not affect the displacement pattern of the hyoid bone 
during deglutition. </p>

<p>Table 4. Effects of group and stage on the measurements </p>

<p>H-S 
H-C3RGN 
H-PP 
H-C3 
H-RGN </p>

<p>F 
p 
F 
p 
F 
p 
F 
p 
F 
p </p>

<p>Group 
58.467 
0.000* 16.583 
0.001* 112.700 
0.000* 16.696 
0.001* 28.243 
0.000* </p>

<p>Stage 
14.267 
0.000* 
9.610 
0.001* 
11.455 
0.000* 
7.279 
0.003* 10.518 
0.001* </p>

<p>Group × stage 
1.404 
0.280 
0.053 
0.983 
0.518 
0.677 
0.264 
0.850 
0.975 
0.431 </p>

<p>*Statistically significant (by repeated-measures ANOVA). 
Refer to Figure 3 for measurements and abbreviations. </p>

<p>Karacay et al • Hyoid bone movements in subjects with open bite </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4041/kjod.2012.42.6.318 </p>

<p>3. The hyoid bone is positioned more inferiorly and 
posteriorly in patients with open bite because of rele-
ased tension of the suprahyoid muscles. </p>



<p>Karacay et al • Hyoid bone movements in subjects with open bite </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>





</text></tei>