<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3768664" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>We studied the peptide-degrading anaerobic communities of methanogenic reactors from two mesophilic </p>

<p>full-scale modified upflow anaerobic sludge blanket (UASB) reactors treating brewery wastewater in </p>

<p>Colombia. Most probable number (MPN) counts varied between 7.1 x 10 
8 and 6.6 x 10 
9 bacteria/g volatile </p>

<p>suspended solids VSS (Methanogenic Reactor 1) and 7.2 x 10 
6 and 6.4 x 10 
7 bacteria/g (VSS) </p>

<p>(Methanogenic Reactor 2). Metabolites detected in the highest positive MPN dilutions in both reactors </p>

<p>were mostly acetate, propionate, isovalerate and, in some cases, negligible concentrations of butyrate. </p>

<p>Using the highest positive dilutions of MPN counts, 50 dominant strains were isolated from both reactors, </p>

<p>and 12 strains were selected for sequencing their 16S rRNA gene based on their phenotypic characteristics. </p>

<p>The small-subunit rRNA gene sequences indicated that these strains were affiliated to the families </p>

<p>Propionibacteriaceae, Clostridiaceae and Syntrophomonadaceae in the low G + C gram-positive group </p>

<p>and Desulfovibrio spp. in the class δ-Proteobacteria. The main metabolites detected in the highest positive </p>

<p>dilutions of MPN and the presence of Syntrophomonadaceae indicate the effect of the syntrophic </p>

<p>associations on the bioconversion of these substrates in methanogenic reactors. Additionally, the potential </p>

<p>utilization of external electron acceptors for the complete degradation of amino acids by Clostridium </p>

<p>strains confirms the relevance of these acceptors in the transformation of peptides and amino acids in these </p>

<p>systems. </p>

<p>Recent studies on microbial diversity in anaerobic reactors </p>

<p>report the presence of Proteobacteria (Alfa, Beta, Delta and </p>

<p>Gamma), Firmicutes, Cytophaga-Flexibacter-Bacteroides, </p>

<p>Spirochaetes, Chloroflexi, Planctomyces, and Synergistes (17, </p>

<p>34, 9, 44, 35, 7, 11, 3, 15, 38). The actual diversity and its role </p>

<p>in anaerobic reactors remain unclear but the dynamics of </p>

<p>microbial composition inside the reactors is related to </p>

<p>wastewater characteristics and operational conditions (24, 26). </p>

<p>*Corresponding Author. Mailing address: Unidad de Saneamiento y Biotecnología Ambiental (USBA). Departamento de Biología. Pontificia Universidad 
Javeriana, P.O.B. 56710, Bogotá, Colombia.; Tel: +571 320 83 20 ext. 4170 Fax: +571 3208320 ext. 4056.; E-mail: baena@javeriana.edu.co </p>

<p>708 </p>

<p>Díaz, C. et al. 
Peptidolytic microbial community of brewery industries </p>

<p>The relative abundance and the role of peptide-degrading </p>

<p>communities in methanogenic reactors have been largely </p>

<p>ignored. Although proteins and peptides are an important </p>

<p>component of the wastes produced by the food industries, the </p>

<p>anaerobic organisms that degrade these wastes in UASB </p>

<p>reactors are still not well characterized (29, 39). In anaerobic </p>

<p>reactors, proteins are hydrolyzed down to peptides and amino </p>

<p>acids, which are fermented to volatile fatty acids and finally </p>

<p>converted to methane and carbon dioxide . All these processes </p>

<p>take place due to the interactions between microbial </p>

<p>populations. Knowledge of microbial community associated to </p>

<p>a specific role is relevant to optimize the anaerobic digestion </p>

<p>process and increase the stability of the process. The isolation </p>

<p>of peptide and aminoacidolytic species has shed light on their </p>

<p>complex relations and interactions and has brought into focus </p>

<p>the importance of their study in order to enhance the control </p>

<p>strategies of the anaerobic reactors. The objective of this study </p>

<p>was, therefore, to quantify the most probable number (MPN) of </p>

<p>peptide-degrading microorganisms on methanogenic reactors </p>

<p>treating brewery wastewater, and to identify, from the highest </p>

<p>positive MPN dilutions, the dominant communities of peptide </p>

<p>and amino acid degrading microorganisms and their main </p>

<p>physiological characteristics. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Collection of samples and source of the microbial inocula </p>

<p>Flocculent mesophilic sludge samples were collected from </p>

<p>the methanogenic reactors of two full-scale anaerobic brewery </p>

<p>wastewater reactors operating continuously in two phases </p>

<p>(acidogenic and methanogenic) during 4 years. Reactor 1 (M1) </p>

<p>and reactor 2 (M2) of 500 and 325 m 
3 capacity respectively, </p>

<p>were maintained at an Hydraulic Retention Time (HRT) of 25 </p>

<p>h. The Chemical Organic Demand (COD) values were </p>

<p>approximately 2,700 mg.l 
-1 . Major constituents of the </p>

<p>wastewater were carbohydrates (36 to 42% of the total COD) </p>

<p>and proteins (10 to 21% of the total COD). The pH was 7.2 and </p>

<p>temperature varied between 28 and 30 ºC. Sludge samples were </p>

<p>collected from methanogenic reactors in 3 to 4 sampling events </p>

<p>within a 200-day period of continuous operation, in order to </p>

<p>detect changes over time in numbers of peptide-degrading </p>

<p>microorganisms. Samples from reactor 1 were labelled M1 A </p>

<p>and M1 B for the first experimental unit, and M2 A and M2 B for </p>

<p>the second experimental unit. Samples from reactor 2 were </p>

<p>labelled M A and M B . Microbial analyses were carried out with </p>

<p>these sub-samples. </p>

<p>Preparation of the sludge samples and microbial counts </p>

<p>using the Most Probable Number technique (MPN) </p>

<p>Ten ml of sludge of each sub-sample were homogenized in </p>

<p>anaerobic conditions using a tissue grinder. Serial dilutions </p>

<p>from 10 
-1 to 10 
-10 were prepared from each sub-sample and all </p>

<p>the procedures were carried out according to 12 (2007). </p>

<p>The MPN technique was used with three tubes per </p>

<p>dilution, and peptide-degrading microorganisms were </p>

<p>quantified according to 22 (1969) anaerobic techniques </p>

<p>modified by 27(1974). Each sub-sample was cultured in a basal </p>

<p>mineral medium (6) and different series were set: series A 1: </p>

<p>supplemented with 0.2% casaminoacids; series A 2: 0.2% </p>

<p>casaminoacids plus 20 mM thiosulfate; series B 1: 0.2% </p>

<p>pepticase; series B 2 : 0.2% pepticase plus 20 mM thiosulfate; </p>

<p>series C 1: control without substrate and thiosulfate; and C 2: </p>

<p>control with thiosulfate alone. Thiosulfate was evaluated as a </p>

<p>final electron acceptor that favors the growth of peptide-</p>

<p>degrading microorganisms able to use thiosulfate instead of </p>

<p>sulfate as an electron acceptor, and/or to quantify directly </p>

<p>Sulfate-Reducing Bacteria (SRB) that degrade peptides and </p>

<p>amino acids. After an incubation period of 4 weeks at 37 °C, </p>

<p>the results of MPN were reported as MPN/g VSS. The criteria </p>

<p>to determine positive growth in the tubes were: an increase in </p>

<p>optical density (580 nm), production of sulfide or methane </p>

<p>compared to the control series, and microscopic observation. </p>

<p>Analytical Methods </p>

<p>The parameters pH, COD, and volatile suspended solids </p>

<p>(VSS) were analyzed according to Standard Methods (2). In the </p>

<p>series without thiosulfate, methane formation was evaluated </p>

<p>using a Shimadzu gas chromatograph (Model GC-14B) </p>



<p>Díaz, C. et al. 
Peptidolytic microbial community of brewery industries </p>

<p>equipped with an HP-1 column (30 m x 0.53 mm x 0.88 µm) </p>

<p>and a flame ionization detector at 200 ºC. Column temperature </p>

<p>was 50 °C and the injection port temperature was 120 °C. </p>

<p>Nitrogen (N 2 ) was used as the carrier gas. Production of sulfide </p>

<p>in 
the 
presence 
of 
thiosulfate 
was 
measured </p>

<p>spectrophotometrically (8). Microbial growth and formation of </p>

<p>metabolites were analyzed after four weeks of incubation. The </p>

<p>end-products (volatile fatty acids) were measured by a </p>

<p>Shimadzu High Pressure Liquid Chromatographer equipped </p>

<p>with a C18 reverse-phase ultra aqueous column (150 mm x </p>

<p>4.6mm ID), with Diode Array Detector (SPD-M20A) at 210 </p>

<p>nm. </p>

<p>Isolation of dominant peptidolytic bacteria </p>

<p>From the highest positive MPN dilutions of the two </p>

<p>treatment plants, isolation was performed in solid medium with </p>

<p>2% noble agar (Sigma®) following the roll tube technique (6). </p>

<p>Five different culture series were obtained with basic medium </p>

<p>supplemented with casaminoacids, pepticase and gelatin at a </p>

<p>concentration of 0.8% (w/v), and alanine, valine, isoleucine </p>

<p>and serine at a concentration of 10 mM. These five series were </p>

<p>incubated at 37°C during 15 days. Isolated strains were purified </p>

<p>through the repeated use of the roll tube technique until axenic </p>

<p>cultures were obtained. Cell morphology was determined using </p>

<p>a phase-contrast microscope. Studies on substrate utilization </p>

<p>were carried out in basal medium containing 0.02% (w/v) yeast </p>

<p>extract. Alanine, glutamate, arginine, valine, serine, threonine, </p>

<p>histidine, and isoleucine were tested at a final concentration of </p>

<p>10 mM; yeast extract, peptone, pepticase and casaminoacids </p>

<p>were tested at a final concentration of 0.5 % (w/v); and lactate, </p>

<p>piruvate, acetate, propionate, butirate, maltose, D-xilose, D-</p>

<p>manitol, D-arabinose, D-glucose, and ethanol at a final </p>

<p>concentration of 20 mM. The end-products were measured by </p>

<p>High Pressure Liquid Chromatography as described before. </p>

<p>Spores were evaluated under the microscope from cultures </p>

<p>incubated at 80 °C for up to 20 min, and at 90°C for up to 10 </p>

<p>min followed by subculturing into growth medium. To </p>

<p>examine the utilization of potential electron acceptors, 20mM </p>

<p>thiosulfate, 20 mM sulfate, 2 mM sulfite, and 1.0 % (w/v) </p>

<p>elemental sulfur were used in basal medium with a carbon </p>

<p>source selected depending on the results of substrate utilization </p>

<p>studies. Sulfide was determined spectrophotometrically, as </p>

<p>indicated above. </p>

<p>Mixed culture experiments </p>

<p>Methanotrophic microorganisms were used in co-culture </p>

<p>with selected strains to evaluate the degradation of peptides </p>

<p>and amino acids. Methanothermobacter thermoautotrophicus Z </p>

<p>245 and Methanospirillum hungatei (gently donated by Dr. </p>

<p>Caroline Plugge, Laboratory of Microbiology, Wageningen </p>

<p>University, Netherlands) and Methanobacterium formicicum </p>

<p>(DSM 1535) were grown under a H 2 :CO 2 (80:20) atmosphere </p>

<p>in basal medium, containing 0.1% (w/v) yeast extract, M. </p>

<p>thermoautotrophicus Z 245 incubated at 50ºC and M. hungatei </p>

<p>and M. formicicum at 37 °C.. The isolated strains Ile-2 and </p>

<p>Gela were grown in basal medium containing 2% (w/v) </p>

<p>pepticase and 0.02% yeast extract and incubated at 37°C and </p>

<p>50°C, respectively. The inoculum from methanogenic archaea </p>

<p>and isolated strains (10%) were injected into tubes containing 5 </p>

<p>ml basal medium, 0.02% (w/v) yeast extract and selected </p>

<p>amino acids (arginine, histidine, alanine, threonine, isoleucine, </p>

<p>glutamate and valine) at a final concentration of 10 mM and, </p>

<p>casaminoacids at 
1.0 % (w/v). The co-cultures (M. </p>

<p>thermoautotrophicus Z 245 and strain Gela; M. formicicum or </p>

<p>M. hungatei and strain Ile-2) were incubated for 2 weeks after </p>

<p>the end-products were determined. The controls used were </p>

<p>basal medium containing 0.02% yeast extract but lacking </p>

<p>amino acids. Amino acid degradation via the Stickland reaction </p>

<p>was tested in a basal medium containing 10 mM alanine as </p>

<p>electron donor and 20 mM glycine, serine, proline or arginine </p>

<p>as electron acceptor. </p>

<p>Analysis of the 16s rRNA gene sequences of the isolated </p>

<p>strains </p>

<p>Methods for purifying DNA, PCR-amplification, </p>

<p>sequencing of the 16S rRNA gene and phylogeny were as </p>

<p>described previously (30, 43, 36). Partial sequences generated </p>

<p>were assembled using <rs id="software-1" type="software">BioEdit</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">v5.0.1</rs> (19) and the consensus </p>

<p>710 </p>

<p>Díaz, C. et al. 
Peptidolytic microbial community of brewery industries </p>

<p>sequence of 1,430 nucleotides was corrected manually for </p>

<p>errors. The most closely related sequences in the GenBank </p>

<p>(version 152) and the Ribosomal Database Project II (RDP) </p>

<p>(release 10) identified using BLAST (1) were extracted, </p>

<p>aligned and manually adjusted according to the 16S rRNA </p>

<p>secondary structure obtained from RDP using <rs type="software">BioEdit</rs>. </p>

<p>Nucleotide ambiguities were omitted and evolutionary </p>

<p>distances calculated by using the Jukes and Cantor option (23) </p>

<p>in TreeCon (41). Phylogenetic trees were constructed from </p>

<p>evolutionary distances using the Neighbour-Joining method </p>

<p>(32). Tree topology was re-examined by bootstrap method </p>

<p>(1000) of re-sampling (14). The 16S rRNA sequences from this </p>

<p>study have been submitted to NCBI GenBank Database under </p>

<p>accession numbers EU937733 to EU937739; EU980605 to </p>

<p>EU980608, and AY 642589. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was performed by a completely random </p>

<p>design with a 2x2 factorial arrangement corresponding to these </p>

<p>variables: substrates, electron acceptors, and interactions </p>

<p>between them. Four replicates were made. Variance was </p>

<p>analyzed with the program <rs id="software-3" type="software">Statistix</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">7.0</rs> for Windows. The </p>

<p>dependent variable (number of microorganisms) was </p>

<p>transformed using the log 10 function in order to reduce the </p>

<p>variation coefficient and to apply parametric statistics. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The efficiency on removal of COD in UASB reactors </p>

<p>ranged between 81 and 92% during the study. The pH values </p>

<p>fluctuated between 6.8 and 7.0. The ratio of volatile fatty acids: </p>

<p>alkalinity (VFA:Alk) was around 0.84 , indicating high values </p>

<p>for VFA. The temperature varied between 28 and 31°C. </p>

<p>Microbiological Analysis </p>

<p>Most probable number (MPN) counts varied between 7.1 x </p>

<p>10 
8 and 6.6 x 10 
9 bacteria/g VSS (Reactor 1) and 7.2 x 10 
6 and </p>

<p>6.4 x 10 
7 bacteria/g VSS (Reactor 2) (Tables 1 and 2). </p>

<p>Variance analysis (level of confidence of 95%) did not show a </p>

<p>significant influence of substrates or thiosulfate over the </p>

<p>peptide-degrading population density in both reactors (p &gt; </p>

<p>0.05). Significant changes in the count values through time </p>

<p>were not observed. The two-phase anaerobic digesters allow </p>

<p>enrichment for different bacteria in each acidogenic and </p>

<p>methanogenic reactor linked to the available substrates and </p>

<p>operational conditions (24). In our study, high microbial counts </p>

<p>of peptide-degrading microorganisms obtained indicate that </p>

<p>degradation of peptides is an important metabolic activity in </p>

<p>the methanogenic reactors. </p>

<p>Table 1. MPN of peptidolytic populations of flocculent sludge (Reactor 1). </p>

<p>Series 
Sampling 1 
Cell/g VSS* </p>

<p>Sampling 2 
Cell/g VSS* </p>

<p>Sampling 3 
Cell/g VSS* </p>

<p>Sampling 4 
Cell/g VSS* 
A1: MB + Casa 
5.1 x 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>2.5 x 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>1.8 x10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>3.2 x 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>A2: MB + Casa+ Thio 
8.2 x10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>2.5 x 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>4.8 x 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>1.7 x 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>B1: MB + Pept 
6.0 x 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>4.9 x 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>6.6 x 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>6.6 x 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>B2: MB + Pep +Thio 
7.1 x 10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>2.1x 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>1.8 x 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>1.8 x 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>* Arithmetical average of four replicates 
MB: Basal medium; Casa: 0.2% w/v casaminoacids; Pept: 0.2% w/v pepticase; Thio: 20mM Thiosulfate </p>

<p>Table 2. MPN of peptide-degrading populations of flocculent sludge (Reactor 2). </p>

<p>Series 
Sampling 1 
Cells/g VSS* </p>

<p>Sampling 2 
Cells/g VSS* </p>

<p>Sampling 3 
Cells/g VSS* 
A1: MB + Casa 
1.1 x 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>3.5 x 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>6.4 x 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>A2: MB + Casa+ Thio 
1.1 x 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>6.4 x 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>3.7 x 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>B1: MB + Pept 
2.6 x 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>2.2 x 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>2.7 x 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>B2: MB + Pep +Thio 
2.6 x 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>7.2 x 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>3.2 x 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>* Arithmetical average of two replicates 
MB: Basal medium; Casa: 0.2% w/v casaminoacids; Pept: 0.2% w/v pepticase; Thio: 20mM Thiosulfate </p>



<p>Díaz, C. et al. 
Peptidolytic microbial community of brewery industries </p>

<p>The main metabolites detected in the highest positive </p>

<p>dilutions of the series of cultures were acetate, propionate, and </p>

<p>isovalerate, and in some cases, negligible concentrations of </p>

<p>butyrate. This volatile fatty acid (VFA) production could be </p>

<p>explained by a population selection according to the type of </p>

<p>substrate (10). Single amino acids can be degraded either </p>

<p>through fermentation or oxidative deamination linked to proton </p>

<p>reduction and, the reducing equivalents produced can be </p>

<p>removed by a biological or a chemical electron scavenger (37, </p>

<p>33). This is possible via interspecies hydrogen transfer in the </p>

<p>presence of hydrogenotrophic methanogens or SRB, but also </p>

<p>when thiosulfate acts as the final electron acceptor (13). </p>

<p>Peptide and amino acid-degrading microorganisms produce </p>

<p>acetate, propionate, and the corresponding branched-chain fatty </p>

<p>acids syntrophically, depending on the degraded amino acids </p>

<p>(5). In our study, the formation of VFA can be related to the </p>

<p>degradation of amino acids in the presence of thiosulfate as </p>

<p>electron acceptor or in syntrophic association with </p>

<p>hydrogenotrophic methanogenic bacteria coming from the </p>

<p>initial inocula. In the thiosulfate series, sulfide values between </p>

<p>5 and 8 mM were detected, indicating its reduction during the </p>

<p>oxidation of carbon sources. Additionally, in absence of </p>

<p>thiosulfate, a low concentration of methane was detected in the </p>

<p>highest positive dilutions. </p>

<p>On the other hand, it has been established that the fast </p>

<p>growing peptidolytic organisms that do not depend on </p>

<p>syntrophic associations produce butyrate as the main </p>

<p>metabolite (28). The negligible concentrations of butyrate </p>

<p>obtained in our counts and the fact that none of the 50 isolated </p>

<p>strains produced butyrate as final metabolite, help to confirm </p>

<p>that these dominant peptide-degrading bacteria, that utilize </p>

<p>peptide and/or amino acids as the sole carbon and energy </p>

<p>source can depend on syntrophic associations or final electron </p>

<p>acceptors. </p>

<p>Isolation of dominant peptidolytic bacteria </p>

<p>During the last sampling event, 50 strains with different </p>

<p>morphological characteristics were isolated from both reactors: </p>

<p>Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacilli, motile and non-</p>

<p>motile, spore and non-spore forming, single or paired, in chains </p>

<p>or in groups. The isolated strains were grouped by their </p>

<p>phenotypic characteristics, such as Gram stain, strict </p>

<p>anaerobiosis, spore formation, motility and degradation of </p>

<p>peptides and / or amino acids. Subsequently, some of these </p>

<p>microorganisms were selected for sequenciation and analysis </p>

<p>of the 16S rRNA gene. Finally, 12 microorganisms named M-</p>

<p>1, MD-4, Ser-1, Ser-2, Ala-1, Val-6, Gela-Thio, Gela, MG-2, </p>

<p>B2-2M, MP-6, e Ile-2 were evaluated. </p>

<p>Phylogenetic analysis of the 16S rRNA gene sequence </p>

<p>grouped these strains (Figure 1) into three phyla: </p>

<p>Proteobacteria, Actinobacteria and Firmicutes. Four strains </p>

<p>isolated from the series without thiosulfate and identified as </p>

<p>Desulfovibrio vulgaris (strains M-1 and MD-4) and </p>

<p>Desulfovibrio desulfuricans (strains Ser-1 and Ser-2) belong to </p>

<p>the class δ-Proteobacteria. These strains fermented serine in </p>

<p>absence of an external electron acceptor, producing acetate as </p>

<p>the main metabolite. The presence of peptide and amino acid </p>

<p>degraders via fermentation of the genus Desulfovibrio in, </p>

<p>anaerobic reactors has been widely reported (4, 20, 24). The </p>

<p>presence of SRB in the highest positive dilutions of the </p>

<p>microbial counts in this study would indicate their possible role </p>

<p>in the fermentation of amino acids in methanogenic reactors </p>

<p>where sulfate appears at low concentrations (values of sulfate </p>

<p>detected ranged from 4 to 29 mg.l 
-1 in both reactors). </p>

<p>Strains MP-6 and B2-2M, belonging to the phylum </p>

<p>Actinobacteria, 
were 
grouped 
in 
the 
family </p>

<p>Propionibacteriaceae. 
They 
are 
strictly 
anaerobic </p>

<p>saccharolytic organisms, non-motile and mesophilic. Strain </p>

<p>MP-6 produces acetate and propionate from glucose, and </p>

<p>ferments yeast extract but does not use external electron </p>

<p>acceptors. Strain B2-2M produces acetate and traces of ethanol </p>

<p>from glucose, it also ferments casaminoacids, peptone, </p>

<p>pepticase, arginine and yeast extract, and it is able to reduce </p>

<p>the elemental sulfur to hydrogen sulfide. Based on the analysis </p>

<p>of the 16S rRNA gene both strains are close to the clone B2, </p>

<p>isolated from a microbial enrichment with propionate from an </p>

<p>712 </p>

<p>Díaz, C. et al. 
Peptidolytic microbial community of brewery industries </p>

<p>anaerobic reactor (31) (98% similarity) and also related to </p>

<p>Propionibacterium lymphophilum with 93% of similarity. </p>

<p>Luteococcus peritonei is related with 91% and 94% similarity </p>

<p>to strains MP-6 and B2-2M respectively. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Tree constructed using Neighbour-Joining method (Jukes-Cantor correction) based on 16S rRNA gene sequences </p>

<p>showing the position of strains MP6, B2M2, GELA, ILE-2, SER1, SER2, MD4, M1, MG2, GELA-TIO, ALA1, VAL6 and some </p>

<p>related taxa. Bootstrap values (expressed as percentages of 1,000 replications) above 95% are shown at branch points (Bar: 0.1 </p>

<p>substitutions per nucleotide position). </p>

<p>Phylum Firmicutes was represented by three different </p>

<p>families 
(Clostridiaceae, 
Eubacteriaceae, 
and </p>

<p>Syntrophomonadaceae). The majority of strains related to the </p>

<p>degradation of proteins and/amino acids are affiliated to this </p>

<p>phylum. These organisms could play a central role in the </p>

<p>degradation of proteins, peptides and amino acids as reported </p>

<p>by 39 (2005) and indicated by our own results. Strain Ala-1 </p>

<p>belongs to the family Eubacteriaceae and was identified as </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>Chloroflexus aggregans DSM 9485 
T (D32255) </p>

<p>Propionimicrobium lymphophilum DSM4903 
T (AJ003056) </p>

<p>Clostridium lactatifermentans DSM14214 
T (AY033434) 
Clostridium populeti DSM5832 
T (X71853) </p>

<p>ILE-2 (AY642589) </p>

<p>Desulfovibrio desulfuricans DSM642 
T (AF192153) </p>

<p>Clostridium propionicum DSM1682 
T (X77841) </p>

<p>Clostridium oroticum DSM1287 
T (M59109) </p>

<p>Desulfovibrio vulgaris DSM644 
T (AY362360) </p>

<p>Clostridium subterminale DSM6970 
T (X68451) </p>

<p>Brooklawnia cerclae JCM 14918 
T (DQ196625) </p>

<p>Thermovirga lienii DSM17291 
T (DQ071273) </p>

<p>Clostridium neopropionicum DSM3847 
T (X76746) 
VAL6 (EU937739) </p>

<p>ALA1 (EU980608) 
Eubacterium contortum DSM3982 
T (L34615) 
GELA-THIO (EU937738) 
Clostridium tunisiense (AY187622) </p>

<p>MG2 (EU937735) 
Clostridium thiosulfatireducens DSM13105 
T (AF317650) 
GELA (EU937736) 
Thermanaerovibrio velox DSM12556 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>Aminobacterium colombiense DSM12261 
T (AF069287) 
Aminobacterium mobile DSM12262 
T (AF073521) 
SER2 (EU980606) 
SER1 (EU980605) </p>

<p>Desulfovibrio oxamicus DSM1925 
T (DQ122124) 
Desulfovibrio longreachensis ACM3958 
T (Z24450) </p>

<p>MD4 (EU937737) 
M1 (EU937733) 
Propionibacterium cyclohexanicum ATCC700429 
T (D82046) 
Propionibacterium australiense ATCCBAA-264 
T (AY883040) </p>

<p>MP6 (EU937734) 
B2M2 (EU980607) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>98 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>99 </p>

<p>98 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>713 </p>

<p>Díaz, C. et al. 
Peptidolytic microbial community of brewery industries </p>

<p>Eubacterium contortum (99% of similarity). This strain is </p>

<p>strictly anaerobic, mesophilic and saccharolytic, but does not </p>

<p>degrade casamino acids, pepticase or peptone and does not use </p>

<p>external electron acceptors. Although 
the 
family </p>

<p>Eubacteriaceae includes species such as Eubacterium </p>

<p>acidaminophilum capable of using aminoacids and peptides </p>

<p>(45), strain Ala-1 did not degrade peptides or amino acids. This </p>

<p>strain probably grew at the expense of the metabolites </p>

<p>produced by other organisms in the highest positive dilutions </p>

<p>of the counts. </p>

<p>Strains Gela-Thio, MG-2 and Val-6 belong to the family </p>

<p>Clostridiaceae and share similarity percentages of 98, 99 and </p>

<p>95% with C. tunisiense (40), C. thiosulfatireducens (21) and C. </p>

<p>neopropionicum, respectively. Strains Gela-Thio, Val-6 and </p>

<p>MG-2 are strictly anaerobic, mesophilic, asaccharolytic and </p>

<p>ferment peptides and amino acids mainly producing acetate and </p>

<p>propionate. As electron acceptors, strains Gela-Thio and Val-6 </p>

<p>use elemental sulfur and strain MG-2 uses thiosulfate. Based </p>

<p>on the similarity of 16S rRNA gene sequences, strain Gela-</p>

<p>Thio is identified as C. tunisiense, and strain MG-2 as C. </p>

<p>thiosulfatireducens. The value of similarity between strain Val-</p>

<p>6 and C. neopropionicum and their phenotypic differences do </p>

<p>not allow identifying strain Val-6 as C. neopropionicum. Our </p>

<p>results demonstrate that isolates in presence of electron </p>

<p>acceptors (elemental sulfur or thiosulfate) can degrade amino </p>

<p>acids via oxidative deamination. These external electron </p>

<p>acceptors are important in the degradation of amino acids since </p>

<p>they remove the reducing equivalents formed during their </p>

<p>degradation. This mechanism has been reported in anaerobic </p>

<p>bacteria 
such 
as 
Thermoanaerobacter 
spp. 
and </p>

<p>Dethiosulfovibrio spp. (13, 25). Strain MG-2, besides using </p>

<p>thiosulfate as final electron acceptor, also uses the Stickland </p>

<p>reaction to degrade amino acids. Strain Val-6 could be </p>

<p>identified as a new species of the genus Clostridium, according </p>

<p>to the analysis of their 16S rRNA sequence and observed </p>

<p>phenotypic differences, but further studies are needed in order </p>

<p>to confirm this hypothesis. </p>

<p>Strains Gela (Figure 2) and Ile-2 belong to the family </p>

<p>Syntrophomonadaceae, which includes a group of anaerobes </p>

<p>that commonly grow in syntrophic associations with hydrogen </p>

<p>and formate using methanogens. Strain Gela is strictly </p>

<p>anaerobic, thermophilic (optimum growth at 50ºC), motile, </p>

<p>non-spore forming and saccharolytic. This strain fermented </p>

<p>amino acids (serine, threonine, histidine, glutamate, valine, </p>

<p>isoleucine, leucine, and arginine) and peptides (casamino acids, </p>

<p>peptone and yeast extract) and reduced elemental sulfur to </p>

<p>hydrogen sulfide as external electron acceptor. It showed a </p>

<p>similarity of 96% with Thermanaerovibrio acidaminovorans </p>

<p>and could only completely degrade amino acids as alanine, </p>

<p>valine, leucine and glutamate in syntrophic association with </p>

<p>hydrogenotrophic 
organisms 
(Methanothermobacter </p>

<p>thermoautotrophicus strain Z245) (Table 3). These </p>

<p>characteristics 
are 
shared 
with 
Thermanaerovibrio </p>

<p>acidaminovorans. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Photomicrograph with phase contrast microscope of cells of strain Gela in exponential growth phase (Bar: 5 µm). </p>



<p>Díaz, C. et al. 
Peptidolytic microbial community of brewery industries </p>

<p>Table 3. Conversion of substrates by strain Gela in the presence of the absence of Methanothermobacter thermoautotrophicus </p>

<p>Z245 </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>Substrate 
Products analyzed (mM) </p>

<p>acetate 
propionate 
(b) H 2 /CH 4 
others </p>

<p>Glu 
1.0 
4.6 
5.4 </p>

<p>Glu + Z245 
5.3 
7.2 
14.4 </p>

<p>Arg 
&gt;0.5 
1.6 
2.0 </p>

<p>Arg + Z 245 
&gt;0.5 
8.7 
23.6 </p>

<p>Ile 
&gt;0.5 
0.0 
2.5 
0.5 2-methyl-butyrate </p>

<p>Ile + Z 245 
&gt;0.5 
0.0 
22.8 
8.9 2-methyl-butyrate </p>

<p>Ala 
1.54 
0.0 
2.0 </p>

<p>Ala + Z 245 
11.3 
0.0 
16.8 </p>

<p>Val 
0.0 
0.0 
1.6 
2.7 iso-butyrate </p>

<p>Val + Z 245 
0.0 
0.0 
12.0 
7.9 iso-butyrate </p>

<p>Leu 
0.0 
0.0 
3.4 
1.4 iso-valerate </p>

<p>Leu + Z 245 
0.0 
0.0 
16 
9.5 iso-valerate </p>

<p>Ornithine 
0.64 
1.4 
3.2 </p>

<p>Ornithine + Z 245 
&gt;0.5 
8.2 
22.4 </p>

<p>Casa 
6.8 
5.3 </p>

<p>Casa + Z 245 
12.6 
15.2 
31.2 
2.4 iso-butyrate; 2.85 2-methyl-butyrate </p>

<p>His 
&gt;0.5 
3.2 
2.3 
17.5 formate </p>

<p>His + Z 245 
&gt;0.5 
6.5 
12 </p>

<p>Thr 
16.7 
&gt;0.5 
&gt;0.5 </p>

<p>Thr + Z 245 
9.2 
&gt;0.2 </p>

<p>a Results were recorded after 2 weeks of incubation at 50°C. The basal medium contained yeast extract (0.02% w/v) and substrates at a final 
concentration of 10 mM. Tubes containing basal medium with yeast extract (0.02%) and lacking substrates were used as control. The final 
concentrations were determined by subtracting the values obtained from the control tubes from those of utilized substrates. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>CH4 production is expressed as hydrogen. H2 was not detected in co-cultures. </p>

<p>Strain Ile-2 is a Gram-negative, slightly curved, strictly </p>

<p>anaerobic, mesophilic (optimum growth at 42ºC) bacillus and </p>

<p>we could define it as a new genus named Aminiphilus (12). The </p>

<p>strain showed a similarity of 85% with Aminomonas </p>

<p>paucivorans (5) and of 95% with clone BB48 isolated from </p>

<p>16S rDNA genomic libraries of anaerobic reactors (17, 7). This </p>

<p>strain fermented peptides and amino acids such as serine, </p>

<p>alanine, glutamate, isoleucine and valine, mainly producing </p>

<p>acetate, propionate and short-chained fatty acids. However, it </p>

<p>did not degrade threonine or glycine, substrates commonly </p>

<p>used by A. paucivorans. </p>

<p>Syntrophomonadaceae is represented by 16 genera that </p>

<p>have been isolated from anaerobic wastewater treatment </p>

<p>systems and oil wells. The majority of their members use </p>

<p>syntrophic associations with hydrogenotrophic organisms to </p>

<p>completely degrade amino acids and/or peptides. The presence </p>

<p>of organisms of the division Synergistes (family </p>

<p>Syntrophomonadaceae) was evaluated in 93 anaerobic </p>

<p>ecosystems (18), concluding that the ecophysiologic role of the </p>

<p>majority of these organisms is the degradation of amino acids. </p>

<p>715 </p>

<p>Díaz, C. et al. 
Peptidolytic microbial community of brewery industries </p>

<p>Interestingly, in a reactor fed with bovine serum albumin, </p>

<p>when the growth of methanogenic microorganisms was </p>

<p>favored, the dominant populations were related to the genus </p>

<p>Aminobacterium (39) that could use syntrophic associations to </p>

<p>degrade substrates (6). Our study also concludes that in the </p>

<p>absence of methanogenic organisms, the degradation pathway </p>

<p>of peptide and amino acids is linked to fast growing organisms </p>

<p>of the genus Clostridium. Recently, a new example of an </p>

<p>asaccharolytic amino acid degrading bacterium within the </p>

<p>phylum 'Synergistetes' named Cloacibacillus evryensis was </p>

<p>reported by 16. (2008), from an anaerobic sludge digester, </p>

<p>indicating its role in this kind of ecosystems. The organisms of </p>

<p>the division Synergistes that are phylogenetically related to the </p>

<p>family Syntrophomonadaceae, share the ability to degrade </p>

<p>amino acids (18), whether by syntrophic associations or by the </p>

<p>presence of an external electron acceptor. It was pointed out </p>

<p>that in absence of either of these mechanisms, there is a </p>

<p>relationship between phylogeny and function among members </p>

<p>of this division, related to the conversion of peptides and amino </p>

<p>acids in anaerobic ecosystems (42). </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>These methanogenic reactors exhibit an important </p>

<p>anaerobic community of the domain Bacteria. Using </p>

<p>conventional techniques, we identified peptide and/or amino </p>

<p>acid degrading microorganisms and their activities in anaerobic </p>

<p>reactors. The analysis of metabolites produced and the </p>

<p>presence of species of microorganisms of the family </p>

<p>Syntrophomonadaceae, strains Ile-2 and Gela, indicates the </p>

<p>possible effect of the syntrophic associations on the </p>

<p>bioconversion of these substrates in methanogenic reactors. </p>

<p>Furthermore, the utilization of external electron acceptors for </p>

<p>the complete degradation of amino acids by strains Val-6, MG-</p>

<p>2 and Gela-Thio confirms the relevance of these acceptors in </p>

<p>the transformation of peptides and amino acids in these </p>

<p>anaerobic systems. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by IFS (International Foundation </p>

<p>for Science) and COLCIENCIAS (Instituto Colombiano para el </p>

<p>Desarrollo de la Ciencia y la Tecnología). We thank Eng. Juan </p>

<p>Carlos Hoyos of Cervecería Bavaria for providing the </p>

<p>physicochemical data of the two treatment systems, and Dr. </p>

<p>Caroline Plugge of the Laboratory of Microbiology, </p>

<p>Wageningen University, for allowing us to evaluate the </p>

<p>metabolism of strain GELA in her lab. </p>







</text></tei>