<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3654430" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Brassinosteroids (BRs) are steroidal plant hormones that play an important role in the growth and development of plants. 
The biosynthesis of sterols and BRs as well as the signalling cascade they induce in plants have been elucidated largely 
through metabolic studies and the analysis of mutants in Arabidopsis and rice. Only fragmentary details about BR signal-
ling in other plant species are known. Here a forward genetics strategy was used in Petunia hybrida, by which 19 families 
with phenotypic alterations typical for BR deficiency mutants were identified. In all mutants, the endogenous BR levels 
were severely reduced. In seven families, the tagged genes were revealed as the petunia BR biosynthesis genes CYP90A1 
and CYP85A1 and the BR receptor gene BRI1. In addition, several homologues of key regulators of the BR signalling 
pathway were cloned from petunia based on homology with their Arabidopsis counterparts, including the BRI1 receptor, 
a member of the BES1/BZR1 transcription factor family (PhBEH2), and two GSK3-like kinases (PSK8 and PSK9). PhBEH2 
was shown to interact with PSK8 and 14-3-3 proteins in yeast, revealing similar interactions to those during BR signalling 
in Arabidopsis. Interestingly, PhBEH2 also interacted with proteins implicated in other signalling pathways. This suggests 
that PhBEH2 might function as an important hub in the cross-talk between diverse signalling pathways. </p>

<p>The importance of steroidal hormones in mammalian devel-
opment has already been known for almost eight decades. 
The idea that plant steroids have hormonal functions arose 
when scientists reported the isolation of brassinolide (BL), 
a steroid with strong plant growth-promoting activity, from 
bee-collected pollen of Brassica napus L. (Grove et al., 1979). 
Brassinosteroids (BRs) are widely distributed among the </p>

<p>plant kingdom and so far they have been found in gymno-
sperms, monocots, dicots, a pteridophyte, a bryophyte, and a 
chlorophyte (Bajguz and Tretyn, 2003). The subsequent iden-
tification of several BR biosynthesis and signalling mutants 
further supported the importance of these compounds for 
growth and development, and nowadays BRs are accepted 
as phytohormones. BRs are involved in various growth and </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), which 
permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact 
journals.permissions@oup.com. </p>

<p>© The Author(2) [2013]. </p>



<p>developmental processes such as cell division and elonga-
tion, vascular differentiation, abiotic and biotic stresses, 
photomorphogenesis, germination, senescence, and fertility 
(Clouse and Sasse, 1998; Bajguz and Hayat, 2009). 
The sterol biosynthesis pathway can be divided into three 
domains (Fig. 1). In the first part, the mevalonate-derived 
squalene is converted via multiple steps into 24-methylene 
lophenol. Subsequently, the pathway diverges into two down-
stream branches. One branch produces sitosterol and stigmas-
terol, while the other produces campesterol. These sterols are 
integrated into cellular membrane components. In addition, the 
biosynthetic precursor campesterol is utilized to synthesize BRs 
(Lindsey et al., 2003). Plants have multiple ways to synthesize 
BL from campesterol. Detailed studies on the BR biosynthe-
sis route in Catharanthus roseus and Arabidopsis thaliana led to 
the identification of two parallel branched routes, better known 
as the early and late C-6 oxidation pathways that converge at 
catasterone (Fig. 1). The two pathways are linked to each other, 
implying that they are not totally autonomous (Shimada et al., 
2001). Although the early and late C-6 oxidation pathways are 
found throughout the plant kingdom, it seems that in species 
such as tomato and tobacco the late C-6 oxidation pathway 
is more prevalent (Nomura et al., 2001). Fujioka et al. (2002) 
identified an early C-22 oxidation pathway, also named the 
CN-independent pathway, that merges into the late C-6 oxida-
tion pathway, constituting the major route to produce biologi-
cally active BRs as shown in Fig. 1 (Onishi et al., 2012; Zhao and 
Li, 2012). In addition, two shortcuts were reported that convert 
22-OH-3-one and 3-epi-6-deoxoCT via C-23 hydroxylation to 
6-deoxy3DT and 6-deoxyTY, respectively (Ohnishi et al., 2006). 
A number of sterol and BR biosynthesis mutants have 
been described, predominantly in Arabidopsis, and many of 
the genes have been cloned and studied (reviewed by Clouse, 
2002). BR biosynthesis mutants and some sterol mutants such 
as dwarf7 (dwf7), diminuto (dim), and dwarf5 (dwf5) can be 
rescued by exogenous application of BR. However, mutants 
that are affected in genes functioning in early steps of the 
sterol biosynthesis pathway such as FACKEL (FK), STEROL 
METHYL TRANSFERASE 1 and 2 (SMT1, SMT2), and 
HYDRA1 (HYD1) are embryo lethal and cannot be rescued 
by application of exogenous BR. Presumably, the absence of 
these sterols interferes with membrane integrity. 
BR signalling has primarily been elaborated by studies in 
Arabidopsis. The currently known BR signalling pathway in 
Arabidopsis runs from membrane to nucleus (reviewed by 
Clouse, 2011). A key event is the degradation of a negative regu-
lator of BR signalling, the Arabidopsis GSK3/SHAGGY-like 
kinase BRASSINOSTEROID INSENSITIVE 2 (BIN2; Kim 
et al., 2009). The negative effect of BIN2 on BR signalling is per-
formed via phosphorylation of the closely related plant-specific 
transcription factors BRI1-EMS-SUPPRESSOR 1 (BES1) and 
BRASSINOZOLE RESISTANT 1 (BZR1; Wang et al., 2002; 
Yin et al., 2002). It was shown that other Arabidopsis GSK3-
like protein kinases (ASKs) act redundantly with BIN2 in the 
BR signalling pathway (Vert and Chory, 2006; Kim et al., 2009; 
Yan et al., 2009; Rozhon et al., 2010). Phosphorylation of BES1/ 
BZR1 results in inhibition of their activity through proteasome-
mediated degradation, cytoplasmic retention by 14-3-3 proteins, </p>

<p>and inhibition of their DNA binding and transcription activa-
tion activities (Li et al., 2001; He et al., 2002; Yin et al., 2002; 
Vert and Chory, 2006; Gampala et al., 2007; Ryu et al., 2007). 
Here an extensive analysis of BR biosynthesis and signalling 
in petunia is presented. The goal of the study is to examine to 
what extent the biosynthesis of steroids and BRs and the signal-
ling cascades downstream in plants are conserved. The authors' 
petunia collection was browsed for mutants that exhibit a typi-
cal BR deficiency phenotype; five BR biosynthesis or signalling 
mutants were identified and their BR content was determined. 
In three cases, the tagged genes could be identified. Furthermore, 
several petunia homologues of key components of the BR sig-
nalling pathway in Arabidopsis were isolated and it was deter-
mined if a similar network of interactions between these factors 
can occur. It was also found that several components of other 
hormone pathways could interact with the petunia homologue 
of a member of the BES1/BZR1 family of transcription fac-
tors. These interactions reveal new mechanisms, not previously 
recognized, that suggest extensive cross-talk between BR signal-
ling and other hormone signalling pathways. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Brassinolide application 
Young plantlets were each sprayed each 2 d or 3 d until run-off with 
1 μM 24-epibrassinolide (Wako Biochemistry) or with a solvent con-
trol (0.01% ethanol and 0.1% Tween-20) for a couple of weeks. </p>

<p>Purification and GC-MS analysis of sterols and BRs in 
petunia tissue 
Petunia plantlets were freeze-dried and subjected to extraction and chro-
matography according to Nomura et al. (1999). In high-performance 
liquid chromatography, fractions 48/49 (22-OH-CR and 28-nor-6-deox-
oCT), 50/51 (22-OH-3-one, 6-deoxoCT), and 52/53 (3-epi-6-deoxoCT) 
were collected in addition to the fractions cited in Nomura et al. (1999). 
The respective BRs were derivatized and analysed by gas chromatogra-
phy-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) as described (Nomura et al., 2001) 
except that a Shimadzu GC-MS2010 was used. Sterols in petunia were 
analysed according to Nomura et al. (2004). </p>

<p>Genomic DNA isolation and PCR 
Petunia DNA was isolated by grinding one young leaf in liquid nitro-
gen. To this 400 μl of DNA extraction buffer was added (0.1 M TRIS 
pH 8.0, 0.5 M NaCl, 50 mM EDTA, and 10 mM β-mercaptoethanol) 
and samples were incubated for 15-30 min at 65 °C. Next 250 μl of 
phenol/chloroform was added, and samples were shaken and subse-
quently centrifuged for 5 min at maximum speed in a microcentri-
fuge. The supernatant was transferred to a clean tube and DNA was 
precipitated using 2-propanol and washed with 70% ethanol. The 
pellet was dissolved in 100 μl of H 2 O containing DNase-free RNase 
(10 mg ml -1 ) followed by an incubation step for 15-30 min at 65 °C. 
PCRs were performed by using 2 μl of genomic DNA in a stand-
ard PCR. The nucleotide sequences of the primers used are listed in 
Supplementary Table S1 available at JXB online. </p>

<p>Isolation of 3' gene fragments by rapid amplification of cDNA 
ends (RACE) PCR 
In order to isolate cDNA fragments, total RNA was isolated from 
leaves followed by first-strand cDNA synthesis using the RACE1 
primer as described previously (Quattrocchio et al., 2006). PCR </p>

<p>Brassinosteroids in Petunia hybrida | 2437 </p>

<p>amplification was carried out using gene-specific primers or, to iso-
late 3' ends of cDNAs, by using one gene-specific primer in com-
bination with the RACE2 primer under standard PCR conditions 
(annealing temperature 55 °C). All primer sequences used are listed in 
Supplementary Table S1 at JXB online. PCR fragments were directly 
sequenced or cloned in pGEM-Teasy (Promega) and sequenced. </p>

<p>Isolation of 5' gene fragments by SOTI-PCR 
To complete sequences at the 5' end, for some genes a somatic inser-
tion-mediated PCR was performed (Rebocho et al., 2008). Here, 
somatic dTph1 insertions in the target gene that may occur in some 
cells of petunia W138 plants were used. W138 genomic DNA was 
subjected to nested PCR using gene-specific primers and dTph1 
transposon primers (see Supplementary Table S1 at JXB online). In </p>

<p>the first PCR, the dTph1 transposon primers out11 or out12 were 
used in a standard PCR with annealing temperature 55 °C. In the 
second, nested PCR, 1 μl of the out11 reaction was re-amplified with 
out15 and a nested gene-specific primer, while the out12 reaction 
was re-amplified with out6 and a nested gene-specific primer. The 
second reaction was a touch-down PCR where annealing started at 
70 °C and decreased by 1 °C every cycle until reaching 55 °C, fol-
lowed by 25 additional cycles at 55 °C. PCR fragments were directly 
sequenced or cloned in pGEM-Teasy (Promega) and sequenced. </p>

<p>Phylogenetic analysis 
Phylogenetic trees were generated using the Neighbor-Joining 
method of <rs type="software">ClustalX</rs> (ftp://ftp.ebi.ac.uk/pub/software/clustalw2/). 
Bootstrap mode (1000 replications) was used for estimating the level </p>

<p>N 
C 
o 
x 
o 
-
6 
) 
N 
C 
( 
l 
o 
n 
e 
t 
s 
e 
p 
m 
a 
C 
e 
n 
o 
-
3 
e 
n 
o 
-
3 
-
n 
e 
-
4 
) 
R 
C 
( 
l 
o 
r 
e 
t 
s 
e 
p 
m 
a 
C </p>

<p>Cathasterone(CT) 
6-deoxoCT 
22-OH-3-one 
22-OH-4-en-3-one 
22-OH-CR </p>

<p>22,23-diOHCR 
22,23-diOH-4-en-3-
one </p>

<p>3-epi-6-deoxo-CT </p>

<p>) 
E 
T 
( 
e 
n 
o 
r 
e 
t 
s 
a 
e 
T 
E 
T 
o 
x 
o 
e 
d 
-
6 </p>

<p>3-dehydroTE(3DT) 
6-deoxo3DT </p>

<p>Typhasterol(TY) </p>

<p>Catasterone(CS) </p>

<p>Brassinolide </p>

<p>6-deoxoTY </p>

<p>6-deoxoCS </p>

<p>24-Methylene 
lophenol 
Episterol 
5-Dehydro-
episterol </p>

<p>24-Methylene-
cholesterol </p>

<p>24-Ethylidene-
lophenol </p>

<p>5-Dehydro-
avenasterol 
Isofucosterol 
Sitosterol 
Stigmasterol </p>

<p>Cycloeucalenol </p>

<p>4α-Methyl-
fecosterol </p>

<p>δ8,14-Sterol </p>

<p>24-Methylene-
cycloartenol 
Cycloartenol 
Squalene-2,3-
epooxide </p>

<p>membranes </p>

<p>CYP90C1/D1 
CYP90C1/D1 </p>

<p>CYP90C1/D1 </p>

<p>DET2 </p>

<p>DET2 </p>

<p>CYP90C1/D1 
CYP90C1/D1 </p>

<p>1 
B 
0 
9 
P 
Y 
C 
1 
B 
0 
9 
P 
Y 
C 
1 
B 
0 
9 
P 
Y 
C </p>

<p>DIM </p>

<p>CYP90B1 </p>

<p>CYP90C1/D1 </p>

<p>CYP85A1/A2 </p>

<p>CYP90A1 </p>

<p>CYP85A1/A2 </p>

<p>CYP85A1/A2 </p>

<p>CYP85A1/A2 </p>

<p>CYP85A2 </p>

<p>CYP90B1 </p>

<p>DWF5 
DWF7 </p>

<p>SMT2 </p>

<p>δ7-Avenasterol </p>

<p>DWF7 
DWF5 
DIM 
CYP710A </p>

<p>HYD1 </p>

<p>FK </p>

<p>Obutusifoliol </p>

<p>Squalene 
Mevalonate </p>

<p>SMT1 </p>

<p>Cyclopropyl isomerase </p>

<p>CYP51G1 </p>

<p>CYP51G1 </p>

<p>CAS1 
Epoxidase </p>

<p>DET2 </p>

<p>CYP90A1 </p>

<p>Cholesterol </p>

<p>CYP90A1 </p>

<p>CYP90A1 </p>

<p>Late C-6 oxidation pathway </p>

<p>Early C-6 oxidation pathway </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Biosynthesis of steroids and BRs, and the Arabidopsis enzymes involved. The metabolic products are shown in boxes and the 
enzymes involved in the pathway are depicted in red. The predominant pathway to synthesize BL runs from the campestanol (CN)-
independent pathway and late C-6 oxodation pathway and is indicated by the red arrows. The CN-dependent pathway is represented 
by the green arrows. Compounds measured in this study are indicated in a green box. </p>



<p>of confidence assigned to the particular nodes in the tree. The tree 
was visualized with the help of <rs id="software-0" type="software">Treeviewer</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">1.6.6</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">http://taxonomy.zoology.gla.ac.uk/rod/treeview.html</rs>) and rooted using <rs id="software-3" type="software">ClustalW</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-3" type="url">http://www.bioinformatics.nl/tools/clustalw.html</rs>). 
Alignments 
were coloured using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Boxshade</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://www.ch.embnet.org/</rs>). </p>

<p>Yeast two-hybrid screen 
The full-length coding sequence of PhBEH2 was amplified by 
reverse transcription-PCR (RT-PCR) on total RNA isolated from 
leaves using Phusion polymerase (Finnzymes) and primers M736 and 
M737. The amplification product was cloned in the EcoRI/SalI sites 
in pBD-GAL4 and pAD-GAL4 (Stratagene). The PSK8-GAL4BD 
fusion was made by cutting PhBEH2 yeast two-hybrid interactor 78 
with EcoRI/SalI and ligation of the fragment in pBD-GAL4. The 
plasmids were introduced into the yeast strain PJ69 (James et al., 
1996), which carries HIS3, ADE2, and LACZ reporter genes driven 
by distinct GAL4-responsive promoters. For the yeast two-hybrid 
screen, PhBEH2/PSK8 was used as bait against a cDNA library 
from young petunia inflorescences (Souer et al., 2008). The library 
screen was performed as described previously (Quattrocchio et al., 
2006). A total of 100 000 and 300 000 transformed yeast cells were 
screened for PhBEH2 and PSK8, respectively. Plasmid DNA was iso-
lated from positive (HIS, ADE) colonies, transformed to Escherichia 
coli, sequenced, and subsequently reintroduced in PJ69 together with 
the bait plasmid expressing PhBEH2/PSK8 to confirm interactions. 
For the yeast two-hybrid assay between members of the BES1/ 
BZR1 family and GSK3/SHAGGY-like family, members from 
Arabidopsis and petunia were amplified by RT-PCR using Phusion 
polymerase (Finnzymes) on Petunia leaf total RNA or from exist-
ing plasmid clones. The amplification products were cloned in 
EcoRI/SalI sites in pBD-GAL4 and/or pAD-GAL4 (Stratagene). </p>

<p>BiFC (bimolecular fluorescence complementation) analysis 
For expression in protoplasts, full-length coding sequences and the 
N-and C-terminal halves of yellow fluorescent protein (YFP) were 
amplified with primers containing attB sites facilitating (Multisite) 
Gateway cloning (Invitrogen). After recombination in pDONR vec-
tors, the obtained entry clones were recombined with the destination 
vectors V141 (pK7FWG2) to generate PhBEH2-GFP (green fluo-
rescent protein) or V137 (pK2GW7.0) to generate the split YFP ver-
sions. The Gateway vector V154 (pB7WGY2.0) expressing free YFP 
was used as a control. </p>

<p>Accession numbers 
Sequence data from this article can be found in the GenBank data library 
under accession numbers KC633285 (PhDWARF7), KC633286, 
(PhCPD), KC633287 (PhCYP85), KC633288 (PhDWARF5), 
KC633289 (PhDET3), KC633290 (PhSMT2), KC633291 (PhROT3), 
KC633292 (PhDIM), KC633293 (PhDWARF4), KC633294 
(PhDET2), KC633295 (PhBRI1), KC633296 (PhPSK9), KC633297 
(PhPSK8), KC633298 (PhBEH2), KC633299 (PROTEIN 
INTERACTING with BEH2 1 (PIB1), KC633300 (PIB8), KC633301 
(PIB16), KC633302 (PIB16), KC633303 (PIB25), KC633304 (PIB41), 
KC633305 (PIB60), KC633306 (PIB67), KC633307 (PIB81), 
KC633308 [PROTEIN INTERACTING with GSK3 1 (PIG1)], 
KC633309 (PIG3), KC633310 PIG4), KC633311 (PIG16), KC633312 
(PIG21), KC633313 (PIG28) and KC633314 (PIG93). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Identification of petunia sterol/BR biosynthesis and 
signalling mutants </p>

<p>In order to study BR biosynthesis and signalling in petunia, 
populations of the mutagenic Petunia hybrida line W138 were </p>

<p>visually screened (Gerats et al., 1990; van Houwelingen et al., 
1998). Nineteen mutant families (Table 1) with similar pheno-
types were identified that phenocopy sterol/BR biosynthesis 
or signalling mutants from other species. All mutants exhib-
ited the reduced stature and dark round shiny leaves typi-
cal for plants with BR deficiency (Fig. 2A, B). Due to their 
appearance, these mutants were named compact disc (cd). 
In order to identify whether these mutants are BR bio-
synthesis or signalling mutants, individual mutant plants 
were sprayed 2-3 times a week with 1 μM 24-epibrassi-
nolide. Of 19 mutant families, 18 clearly responded to the 
steroid, resulting in elongation of internodes, petioles, 
and leaves (Table 1, Fig. 2C). Complementation of the 
mutant phenotype in these plants indicated that these are 
sterol/BR biosynthesis mutants. Only one mutant family, 
cd10 P2020 , did not respond to exogenous application of 
24-epibrassinolide, suggesting that it is mutated in a BR 
signalling gene. 
Cross-pollination between the mutant families revealed 
that the 19 mutants could be assigned to five different com-
plementation groups (see Table 1). Ten families identified at 
Enza Zaden harbour a dTph1 insertion in the same BR bio-
synthesis gene, CD9. As some of these families are derived 
from a common ancestor (see Table 1), it is likely that they 
represent only three different alleles. Taken together, the total 
number of sterol/BR biosynthesis gene hits is four, while the 
remaining mutant cd10 represents a signalling mutant. All 
mutants have a short robust stature with thick, small, round, 
and dark-green leaves, with only some slight differences in the 
severity of the dwarfish phenotype between the complemen-
tation groups. The cd10 mutants remained extremely small 
and, even after growing for months in the greenhouse, did 
not flower. The biosynthesis mutants clearly grew slowly and 
flowered later, and fertility seemed to be reduced in the cd2 
and especially in the cd1 mutants. </p>

<p>BR and steroid levels in cd mutants </p>

<p>To characterize the mutations further, quantitative GC-MS 
analysis was used to measure endogenous steroid and BR 
levels in the wild type and cd mutants (Tables 2, 3). Wild-
type petunia, like tomato, does not accumulate BL, but rather 
castasterone (CS), as the bioactive compound (Table 2). In 
the cd1 mutant, the levels of CS and 6-deoxoCS were greatly 
reduced. The amounts of sterols were similar to those of the 
wild type, indicating no lesion in sterol biosynthesis. Therefore, 
cd1 seems to be mutated in an unknown brassinosteroid 
enzyme. Concomitantly with a large decrease in the CS and 
6-deoxoCS levels, the cd2 mutant overaccumulated 22-OH-
CR, indicating a mutation in the petunia CYP90A1 (CPD) 
gene. In the cd3 mutant, massive accumulation of 6-deoxoCS 
was observed, suggesting that this mutant has a defect in the 
conversion of 6-deoxoCS to castasterone, a reaction that in 
tomato is catalysed by the CYP85A1 enzyme (Bishop et al., 
1999). In the cd9 mutant, sterols are abundant but the path-
way end-products CS and 6-deoxoCS were severely reduced. 
In cd9, 22-OH-CR, 22-OH-3-one, and 6-deoxoCT accumu-
lated, suggesting a mutation in a CYP90C1-or CYP90D1-like </p>

<p>Brassinosteroids in Petunia hybrida | 2439 </p>

<p>Table 1. Overview of cd alleles and results of complementation 
experiment by brassinolide treatment. </p>

<p>Locus 
Allele 
Origin 
Complemented 
by BR a </p>

<p>cd1 
cd1-W503 
VU 
Yes 
cd1-K2078 
Nijmegen 
Yes 
cd2 b 
cd2-W2254 
VU 
Yes 
cd2-P2013 
ENZA 
Yes 
cd2-P2015 
ENZA 
Yes 
cd2-P2018 
ENZA 
Yes 
cd3 
cd3-D2213 
VU 
Yes 
cd3-P2014 
ENZA 
Yes 
cd9 c 
cd9-P2016 
ENZA 
Yes 
cd9-P2019 
ENZA 
Yes 
cd9-P2021 
ENZA 
Yes 
cd9-P2022 
ENZA 
Yes 
cd9-P2023 
ENZA 
Yes 
cd9-P2024 
ENZA 
Yes 
cd9-P2025 
ENZA 
Yes 
cd9-P2026 
ENZA 
Yes 
cd9-P2027 
ENZA 
Yes 
cd9-P2028 
ENZA 
Yes 
cd10 
cd10-P2020 
ENZA 
No </p>

<p>a Complementation was tested by spraying with 1 μM 
24-epibrassinolide. 
b Due to reduced fertility, cd2 allelism was confirmed molecularly as 
independent insertions in PhCYP90A1 (see text). 
c cd9 P2016 , cd9 P2019 , cd9 P2022 , cd9 P2024 , cd9 P2025 , cd9 P2026 , cd9 P2027 , 
and cd9 P2028 are derived from a common ancestor and thus might 
represent identical alleles. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Petunia BR biosynthesis and signalling mutants. (A) Phenotype of 4-week-old Petunia hybrida wild-type (left) and cd1 W503 , 
cd2 P2015 , cd3 D2213 , and cd9 P2023 plants. (B) Top view of a cd1 W503 mutant. (C) Complementation of the cd2 P2013 mutant but not 
of the cd10 P2020 mutant by spraying with 1 μM 24-epibrassinolide (+BL). Mock indicates plantlets treated with a solution without 
24-epibrassinolide. </p>

<p>Table 2. Endogenous BR levels of wild-type petunia (W138), cd1, 
cd2, cd3, and cd9 plants (ng kg -1 FW). </p>

<p>Wild type 
cd1 
cd2 
cd3 
cd9 </p>

<p>Tissue FW (g) 
95.0 
88.0 
82.1 
102.0 
26.6 
BR/steroid 
BL 
ND 
ND 
ND 
ND 
ND 
CS 
943 
24 
92 
15 
63 
6-DeoxoCS 
7621 
157 
86 
59 668 
84 
6-DeoxoTY 
566 
610 
488 
1008 
512 
6-Deoxo3DT 
116 
135 
202 
230 
257 
6-DeoxoTE 
191 
142 
170 
109 
ND 
6-DeoxoCT 
4471 
7770 
4055 
1668 
12 260 
TY 
Lost 
Lost 
Lost 
Lost 
ND 
3DT 
ND 
ND 
ND 
ND 
ND 
TE 
ND 
ND 
ND 
ND 
ND 
22-OH-CR a 
754 
1151 
4337 
392 
4956 
22-OH-3-one a 
2858 
5275 
1208 
1471 
16 739 
3-Epi-6-deoxoCT a 
6571 
3891 
1531 
5715 
10 777 </p>

<p>FW, fresh weight; ND, not detectable; lost, internal standards not 
recovered. 
a Quantified by peak areas because internal standards are 
unavailable. 
Abbreviations of BRs: BL (brassinolide), CS (castasterone), 
6-deoxoCS (6-deoxocastasterone), 6-deoxoTY (6-deoxotyphasterol), 
6-deoxoTE (6-deoxoteasterone), 6-deoxoCT (6-deoxocathasterone), 
TY (typhasterol), 3DT (3-dehydroteasterone), TE (teasterone), 
22-OH-CR [(22S)22-hydroxycampsterol], 22-OH-3-one 
[(22S,24R)-22-hydroxy-5-ergostan-3-one], 3-epi-6-deoxoCT 
(3-epi-6-deoxocathasterone). </p>



<p>enzyme. In conclusion, it was found that cd1, cd2, cd3, and 
cd9 are all BR deficient. </p>

<p>cd2 and cd3 encode the petunia CYP90A1 and 
CYP85A1 homologues, respectively </p>

<p>The biochemical analysis of BR content in cd mutants in 
some cases provided clues on the identity of the affected </p>

<p>gene. Using a combination of database mining and primer 
design based on sequences of Solanaceae species (e.g. tomato, 
tobacco, potato, etc.; Supplementary Table S1 at JXB 
online), it was possible to clone gene and/or cDNA fragments 
of petunia homologues of the Arabidopsis BR biosynthesis 
genes CYP90A1, DWF5, CYP85A1, DIM, DWF7, SMT2, 
DETIOLATED2 (DET2), DWARF4 (DWF4), and CYP90C1 
(ROT3), and a number of signalling genes (see below). 
The obtained sequence data of petunia BR biosynthesis 
genes were used to determine in each cd mutant if any of 
these known genes is disrupted by a dTph1 insertion. When 
DNA isolated from cd2 plants (Fig. 3A) was used as a tem-
plate, PCRs identified dTph1 insertions at different sites in the 
petunia homologue of the BR biosynthesis gene CYP90A1 
(Szekeres et al., 1996) (Fig. 3D, F). The dTph1 transposon 
insertion in allele cd2 W2254 was found in the first exon, ~80 
nucleotides after the ATG. The other three mutants (cd2 P2013 , 
cd2 P2015 , and cd2 P2018 ) carry a dTph1 insertion at differ-
ent sites in the second exon (Fig. 3D). Plants in progeny of 
cd2 W2254 occasionally gave rise to revertant shoots (Fig. 3B). </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Molecular analysis of two BR biosynthesis mutant families. (A) Mutant phenotype of a cd2 W2254 plant. (B) A cd2 W2254 plant 
that develops a revertant shoot (cd2 M2194-4 ). (C) PCR with CYP90A1-specific primers on genomic DNA extracted from plants carrying 
various CYP90A1 alleles. (D) Schematic drawing of the petunia CYP90A1 gene and mutant alleles. (E) Schematic drawing of the petunia 
CYP85A1 gene and mutant alleles. In D and E, boxes represent exons and the thin lines represent introns. The triangles and line 
illustrate the dTph1 transposon insertions and footprint in the indicated alleles. (F) Sequence analysis of the dTph1 insertions in various 
CYP90A1 and CYP85A1 alleles. The red sequence indicates the target site duplication. </p>

<p>Table 3. Endogenous steroid levels of wild-type petunia (W138), 
cd1, and cd9 plants (g kg -1 FW). </p>

<p>Steroid 
Wild type 
cd1 
cd9 </p>

<p>Cholesterol 
3.4 
4.7 
4.5 
24-Methylenecholesterol 
24.0 
19.0 
30.0 
Campesterol 
30.2 
42.0 
71.5 
Isofucosterol 
140.2 
392.0 
376.0 
Stigmasterol 
19.3 
14.0 
31.9 
Sitosterol 
36.0 
79.9 
92.3 </p>

<p>Brassinosteroids in Petunia hybrida | 2441 </p>

<p>PCR and sequence analysis on genomic DNA extracted from 
a revertant shoot (cd2 M2194-4 ) revealed excision of dTph1 from 
CYP90A1, leaving a 6 bp footprint (Fig. 3F). Furthermore, a 
stable cd2 mutant (cd2 M2194-1 ) was identified in which excision 
of dTph1 created an 8 bp footprint (Fig. 3F). 
The identity of cd3 P2014 was revealed by mining a 3D 
indexed petunia insertion database generated from the 
ENZA population (Vandenbussche et al., 2008). A trans-
poson-flanking sequence unique for family P2014 showed 
homology to CYP85A1 (Bishop et al., 1999). The dTph1 
element was identified in exon 6 of the petunia CYP85A1 
homologue (Fig. 3E). In progeny of cd3 P2014 , a stable 
mutant was shown to carry a mutant allele containing a 
7 bp footprint (cd3 S2007 ). In plants carrying the cd3 D2213 
allele, a transposable element could not be identified in the 
petunia CYP85A1 homologue. However, sequencing of the 
CYP85A1 coding sequence from one of the progeny (family 
cd3-K2066) showed an 8 bp footprint in exon 1, indicating 
the previous existence of a transposable element at this site 
(Fig. 3E, F). 
Analysis of cd1 and cd9 mutants did not reveal trans-
poson insertions in the putative petunia homologues of 
DWARF5, DET3, DIM, DWARF7, SMT2, DET2, DWARF4, 
or ROT3. It must be said that the complete sequences of 
these genes are currently unknown. As 3' sequences (DIM), 
5' sequences (DWARF5, CYP85, DWARF7, SMT2), or both 
(DET3, DET2, DWARF4, ROT3) are unknown, it cannot 
be excluded that there are dTph1 insertions present in these 
parts of the gene. In the 3D indexed petunia insertion data-
base (Vandenbussche et al., 2008), transposon insertions 
were identified in petunia homologues of DIM and DET2, 
both without phenotypic consequences, suggesting that these </p>

<p>genes are redundant in petunia (see the Supplementary data 
at JXB online). </p>

<p>cd10 is mutated in the petunia BRI homologue </p>

<p>In Arabidopsis, BRs are perceived by the leucine-rich repeat 
(LRR) receptor-like kinase BRI1 (Li and Chory, 1997). 
From the P. hybrida expressed sequence tag (EST) collec-
tion, a sequence that showed a high degree of similarity to 
the 3' end of BRI1 (GenBank accession no. CV294320) was 
retrieved. The full-length mRNA sequence of W138 PhBRI1 
was obtained via RACE-PCR and SOTI-PCR (see the 
Materials and methods). Comparison of the derived amino 
acid sequence of PhBRI1 with AtBRI1, OsBRI1, LeBRI1, 
and NbBRI1 revealed 63.3, 53.4, 84.1, and 91.3% identity, 
respectively (Fig. 4A; Supplementary Fig. S1 at JXB online). 
Similar to the other identified BRIs, PhBRI1 has an LRR 
domain, a putative leucine-zipper motif, a transmembrane 
domain to anchor the protein in the plasma membrane, 
and a cytoplasmic kinase domain (Fig. 4B; Supplementary 
Fig. S1). The BRI1 extracellular domain of petunia con-
tains 25 tandem N-terminal LRRs, which is interrupted by 
a 68 amino acid non-repetitive island between the 21st and 
22nd LRR. 
Because cd10 P2020 failed to respond to application of 24-epi-
brassinolide, cd10 was assumed to be mutated in a BR signal-
ling gene (Fig. 2C). One of the prime candidates for being hit 
in cd10 P2020 is the homologue of the Arabidopsis BR receptor, 
BRI1. PCR analysis on genomic DNA with PhBRI1-specific 
primers revealed that cd10 plants indeed contain an inser-
tion in the 5' part of the gene (Fig. 4C, D). Sequence analy-
sis of the 5' part of PhBRI1 in cd10 revealed that the dTph1 </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Characterization of the BRI1 receptor from petunia. (A) Phylogenetic tree constructed using derived amino acid sequences of 
the BRI1 homologue isolated from petunia and various other species [At, Arabiopsis thaliana; Hv, Hordeum vulgare; Os, Oryzia sativa; 
Le, Lycoperscicon esculentum (Solanum lycopersicum); Nb, Nicotiana benthamiana; Nt, Nicotiana tabacum; Ps, Pisum sativum; and 
Ph, Petunia hybrida]. The petunia BRI1 protein (PhBRI1) is underlined. CLAVATA1 from Arabidopsis was used as an outgroup. GenBank 
accession numbers are provided in Supplementary Table S2 at JXB online. (B) Schematic drawing of PhBRI1 with its predicted 
functional domains. The triangle indicates the dTph1 transposon insertion in cd10 P2020 . (C) PCR with BRI1-specific primers on genomic 
DNA extracted from cd10 P2020 and wild-type plants. (D) Sequence analysis of the dTph1 insertion in cd10. The underlined sequence 
indicates the target site duplication. </p>



<p>transposable element was inserted in the third LRR sequence 
motif (Fig. 4B). </p>

<p>Identification of a BEH2 orthologue in petunia </p>

<p>To explore the BR signalling cascade in petunia further, 
the aim was to identify signalling components downstream 
of PhBRI1. In Arabidopsis, the BES1/BZR1 transcrip-
tion factor family plays an important role in the regulation 
of BR-responsive genes (Zhao et al., 2002). A PCR-based 
approach was performed to identify potential petunia homo-
logues. Primers were developed based on the sequences of 
all six BES1/BZR1 family members of Arabidopsis and a 
nested 3' RACE-PCR on petunia leaf cDNA yielded a PCR 
fragment of the desired size. Sequence analysis revealed high 
sequence identity with members of the BES1/BZR1 family. 
The 5' end was isolated by SOTI-PCR (see the Materials 
and methods). The derived amino acid sequence has the 
highest sequence identity to the BES1/BZR1 family mem-
ber AtBEH2 (64.2%) and therefore the clone was named 
PhBEH2 (Fig. 5A; Supplementary Fig. S2 at JXB online). 
Like the previously characterized BES1/BZR1 family mem-
bers from Arabidopsis, PhBEH2 has a putative bipartite 
nuclear localization signal (NLS) at its N-terminus. The 
central part of PhBEH2 is rich in serine/threonine residues 
that match with the phosphorylation sites for GSK3 kinases 
(Wang et al., 2002). In addition a PEST motif was identified 
that seems to play an important role in protein degradation 
as BES1 and BZR1 proteins were stabilized in bes1-D and 
bzr1-D mutants carrying a mutation in this motif (Wang 
et al., 2002; Yin et al., 2002). </p>

<p>PhBEH2 binds to a GSK3/SHAGGY-like kinase and 
14-3-3 proteins </p>

<p>To identify proteins that interact with PhBEH2, a yeast 
two-hybrid screen was performed. As many transcription 
factors carry activation domains, auto-activation of the full-
length cDNA of PhBEH2 on yeast reporters was tested first. 
Indeed, introduction of the PhBEH2-GAL4-binding domain 
fusion resulted in some activation of the HIS reporter, but 
selection on histidine and adenine resulted in no growth 
(Supplementary Fig. S4 at JXB online) Subsequently, the 
full-length cDNA of PhBEH2 was used as bait to screen a 
two-hybrid cDNA library made from young petunia inflores-
cence, and 12 interacting proteins were found (Fig. 5B, C). 
Sequence analysis showed that five of these proteins were 
14-3-3 proteins. Another interesting interacting partner, 
which was named PSK8, had high similarity to the GSK3-like 
kinase BIN2 from Arabidopsis (Fig. 5C). Other interaction 
partners include proteins homologous to SECRET AGENT 
(SEC), which is an O-linked N-acetylglucosamine transferase 
(OGT), ARIA (ARMADILLO Repeat protein Interacting 
with ABF2), TPL (TOPLESS), and two RRM (RNA recog-
nition motif) proteins of which one is a homologue of FPA 
(Flowering Protein A; Fig. 5C). 
To verify some of the interactions found in yeast in 
plant cells, BiFC was used in petunia leaf protoplasts (Hu </p>

<p>et al., 2002). As numerous interactions with PhBEH2 were 
detected, the search was restricted to interactions known 
from Arabidopsis research. In addition, the aim was to verify 
the interaction with the potential OGT PhSEC. As positive 
controls, free YFP as well as a fusion between PhBEH2 and 
GFP were used (Fig. 5D, E). When fused to GFP, BEH2 was 
mainly detected in the nucleus, but clearly in the cytoplasm 
too. For BiFC, translational fusions of PhBEH2, Ph14-
3-3k, PSK8, and PhSEC with the N-and C-terminal halves 
of YFP were generated. Interaction was detected between 
PhBEH2 and 14-3-3k (Fig. 5G), PSK8 (Fig. 5F, H), and 
PhSEC (Fig. 5I). The interaction between PhBEH2 and 14-3-
3k occurred in the cytoplasm and nucleus, whereas interac-
tion with PSK8 and PhSEC appeared almost exclusively in 
the nucleus. It thus seems that at least in the case of 14-3-3k, 
PSK8, and PhSEC, the interaction with PhBEH2 can also 
occur in plant cells. </p>

<p>Isolation and characterization of two group II members 
of the GSK3/SHAGGY-like family from petunia </p>

<p>One of the interacting partners of PhBEH2 was PSK8, a pro-
tein that has strong homology to the GSK3-like kinase BIN2 
from Arabidopsis (Fig. 6A; Supplementary Fig. S3 at JXB 
online). From a previous yeast two-hybrid screen, performed 
in the authors' laboratory, using one of the transcription fac-
tors involved in flower pigmentation as bait, another GSK3-
like kinase was identified as an artefact. As this clone lacked 
the 5' half of the cDNA, SOTI-PCRs (see the Materials and 
methods) were performed to isolate the remaining part. This 
clone was renamed PSK9. Both PSK8 and PSK9 are related 
to BIN2 as they group together with the other group II ASKs 
(Fig. 6A). Kim et al. (2009) showed that the phosphatase 
BSU1 inactivates BIN2 by dephosphorylation at pTyr200. 
This tyrosine residue is also conserved in PSK8 and PSK9 
(Supplementary Fig. S3). 
To gain more insight into the function of PSK8, a yeast 
two-hybrid screen was performed, where full-length PSK8 
was used as bait to screen a cDNA library made from young 
petunia inflorescences. Eight different cDNAs that interacted 
with PSK8 were identified. The interacting partners included 
two different LRR-extensins, REMORIN, and several 
unknown proteins. (Fig. 6B, C). </p>

<p>Key regulators of the petunia/Arabidopsis BR pathway 
are functionally homologous </p>

<p>PSK8 and PSK9 are highly homologous to the group II 
GSK3/SHAGGY-like kinases from Arabidopsis, and this 
prompted the examination of whether they also have func-
tional homology. In order to investigate this, yeast two-hybrid 
assays were performed with members of the BES1/BZR1 
family and the group II GSK3/SHAGGY-like kinases from 
Arabidopsis and petunia. AtBIN2 interacted with AtBES1, 
AtBZR1, and also with BEH2 from petunia (Fig. 7). A simi-
lar behaviour was found for the petunia BIN2 homologue 
PSK8. However, PSK9 did not bind to PhBEH2 or to 
the Arabidopsis members. As the interaction with PSK8/ </p>

<p>Brassinosteroids in Petunia hybrida | 2443 </p>

<p>BIN2 showed that the fusions of BES/BZR proteins with 
GAL4-AD are functional in yeast, it seems that either PSK9 
does not interact with the BES1/BZR1 family or the fusion 
between PSK9 and the GAL4-binding domain is somehow 
not functional. The yeast-two hybrid results suggest that 
group II GSK3/SHAGGY-like kinases and members of the 
BES/BZR1 family from Arabidopsis and petunia are structur-
ally highly homologous. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The synthesis of BRs and the signalling cascade downstream 
of the bioactive compounds have been largely elucidated over 
the past 10 years (Fujioka and Yokota, 2003; Clouse, 2011). 
As in many plant research areas, these findings basically orig-
inate from Arabidopsis. Partial confirmation of evolution-
ary conservation as well as additions came from numerous 
reports on BR biosynthesis and signalling in other species </p>

<p>(e.g. Nomura et al., 2001; Montoya et al., 2002; Bai et al., 
2007; Koh et al., 2007). The available resources in petunia 
have been used to identify large parts of the BR biosynthesis 
and signalling route. The initial results point to conserved BR 
biosynthesis genes and interacting signalling proteins, as well 
as to potential new relationships between hormone signalling 
pathways. </p>

<p>Novel and known BR mutants </p>

<p>Generally, a mutation in a BR biosynthesis gene causes 
the accumulation of a precursor(s) that should have been 
metabolized and a reduction of the (end)product(s). In the 
cd2 mutant, accumulation of 22-OH-CR, which has been 
recognized as the first metabolite of campesterol in the early 
C-22 oxidation branch of BR biosynthesis, was observed 
(Fujita et al., 2006; Fig. 1). A high level of accumulation of 
22-OH-CR was also observed by Ohnishi et al. (2012) when </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Characterization of PhBEH2 and the identification of binding partners by a yeast two-hybrid screen. (A) Phylogenetic tree 
constructed using derived amino acid sequences of PhBEH2 and the BES1/BZR1 family from Arabidopsis. GenBank accession 
numbers are provided in Supplementary Table S2 at JXB online. (B) The full-length sequence of PhBEH2 was fused to the yeast 
GAL4-binding domain and screened against a cDNA library made from young petunia inflorescences. Interactions were measured by 
growth on medium lacking histidine (-LTH) or histidine and adenine (-LTHA), and by blue colouring using 5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indolyl-
β-d-galactosidase (-LT X-gal). (C) Classification of the positive clones from B. As indicated, for some proteins, a homologue with known 
function is found in Arabidopsis. (D-I) Verification of interactions in petunia protoplasts by BiFC (Hu et al., 2002). (D) Free YFP; (E) 
PhBEH2-GFP; (F) PhBEH2-YFPN and PSK8-YFPC; (G) PhBEH2-YFPN and 14-3-3κ-YFPC; (H) PSK8-YFPN and PhBEH2-YFPC; 
(I) PhSEC-YFPN and PhBEH2-YFPC. All constructs are driven by the 35S promoter. All panels show a transformed as well as an 
untransformed protoplast. </p>



<p>they researched the cpd/cyp90a1 mutant. The biochemi-
cal evidence strongly suggested that CD2 is homologous to 
CPD/CYP90A1, although the product, 22-OH-4-en-3-one, 
has not been analysed. Indeed, molecular analysis confirmed 
CD2 as the petunia homologue of CYP90A1 (Fig. 3; Szekeres 
et al., 1996). In cd3, the build-up of 6-deoxoCS and the con-
comitant reduction of CS was observed, indicating a lesion in 
CYP85A1. Once more the biochemical data were confirmed 
as cd3 was found to be mutated in the petunia homologue of 
CYP85A1 (Fig. 3; Bishop et al., 1996). 
Endogenous levels of upstream BRs in cd1 are quite simi-
lar to those of the wild type, and sterol levels are normal. 
However, the levels of both 6-deoxoCS and CS, which appear </p>

<p>in the last steps of biosynthesis, are reduced. No accumula-
tion of other measured BR biosynthesis intermediates could 
be identified. Thus, the nature of the cd1 mutation is currently 
unknown and it might represent an enzyme that has not been 
identified yet in any other plant species. In cd9, the levels of 
22-OH-3-one, 3-epi-6-deoxoCT, and 6-deoxoCT that are sub-
strates of CYP90C1 (ROT3)/CYP90D1 were higher as com-
pared with the wild type, indicating a potential deficiency in 
a CYP90C1/CYP90D1-like activity (Fig. 1). However, the 
Arabidopsis CYP90C1/CYP90D1 double mutant does not 
accumulate 22-OH-3-one, 3-epi-6-deoxoCT, and 6-deoxoCT 
(Ohnishi et al., 2006). It thus seems that, in contrast to the sit-
uation in Arabidopsis, the CYP90C1 (ROT3)/CYP90D1 activ-
ity in petunia is encoded by a single enzyme. dTph1 insertions 
could not be found in the ROT3 homologue of cd9, but it 
cannot be ruled out that the insertion might be located in the 
5' or 3' part that currently is lacking. Altogether, the evidence 
available points to unknown BR biosynthesis enzymes or per-
haps regulators of BR biosynthesis enzymes mutated in cd1 
or cd9. Cloning of the responsible genes can be accomplished 
in the future by using amplified fragment length polymor-
phim (AFLP)-based transposon display or high throughput 
sequencing of dTph1-flanking sequences (Van den Broeck 
et al., 1998; Vandenbussche et al., 2008). </p>

<p>BR signalling mutants </p>

<p>The single signalling mutant that was identified, cd10, was 
shown to harbour an insertion in the petunia homologue of 
the BR receptor, BRI1 (Li and Chory et al., 1997). The cd10 
mutant exhibits an extremely dwarfed stature and did not 
flower at all. All known bri1 mutants do flower, except the </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Phylogenetic analysis of PSK8/9 and the identification of PSK8 binding partners by a yeast two-hybrid screen. (A) Phylogenetic 
tree constructed of derived amino acid sequences of PSK8/9 and GSK3-like kinases from Arabidopsis and petunia. MPK1 from 
Arabidopsis was used as an outgroup to construct the tree, but is not shown in this tree. GenBank accession numbers are shown in 
Supplementary Table S2 at JXB online. (B) Interaction of PSK8 with eight different clones in a yeast two-hybrid assay. Interactions were 
measured by growth on medium lacking histidine (-LTH) or histidine and adenine (-LTHA), and by blue colouring using 5-bromo-4-
chloro-3-indolyl-β-d-galactosidase (-LT X-gal). (C) Classification of the positive clones from B. When a clear homologue in Arabidopsis is 
found, their AGI identifier is listed. </p>

<p>Fig. 7. The BES1/BZR1 family and group II GSK3/SHAGGY-
like kinases from petunia and Arabidopsis are functionally 
homologous. Full-length sequences of AtBIN2, PSK8, and PSK9 
were fused to the GAL4-binding domain, and AtBZR1, AtBES1, 
and PhBEH2 to the GAL4 activation domain, and tested for 
interaction. Interactions were measured by growth on medium 
lacking histidine (-LTH) or histidine and adenine (-LTHA). </p>

<p>Brassinosteroids in Petunia hybrida | 2445 </p>

<p>osbri1 mutant from rice (Nakamura et al., 2006). The strong 
mutants from rice and petunia might reflect complete loss of 
BRI1 function, whereas in other species either only partial 
loss-of-function alleles were identified, partial redundancy in 
BRI1 function might exist, and/or another non BR-dependent 
flowering pathway plays a dominant role. 
In an amino acid alignment of BRI1 from different spe-
cies, the highest similarity was observed in the crucial kinase 
domain (Supplementary Fig. S1 at JXB online; Tang et al., 
2008; X. Wang et al., 2008). The extracellular domain of 
PhBRI1 contains 25 tandem N-terminal LRRs and a 68 
amino acid non-repetitive island between the 21st and 22nd 
LRR. This island together with LRR22 has proved to be 
important for BR binding by BRI1 in Arabidopsis (Kinoshita 
et al., 2005). Thus it seems that the perception of the BR hor-
mone is evolutionarily well conserved. 
Apart from PhBRI1, petunia homologues belonging to the 
BES1/BZR1 family as well as GSK3-like kinases, key com-
ponents of the BR signalling pathway in Arabidopsis, were 
cloned. The BES1/BZR1 family homologue that was iso-
lated from petunia (PhBEH2) showed the highest sequence 
identity to the BES1/BZR1 family member BEH2 (64.2%). 
In Arabidopsis, the bzr1/bes1 double mutant only exhibits a 
semi-dwarf phenotype. It thus seems likely that BEH2 and 
perhaps other members of the BES1/BZR1 family are redun-
dant to BES1 and BZR1. </p>

<p>Interactions between BR signalling components </p>

<p>The interaction spectrum of PhBEH2 in yeast supports a 
role in BR signalling. First, PhBEH2 is capable of interact-
ing with Arabidopsis BIN2 (Fig. 7), a proven negative regula-
tor of BR signalling (Li et al., 2001). Secondly, the PhBEH2 
protein interacted with several 14-3-3 proteins (Fig. 5C). 
Previous research in Arabidopsis showed that 14-3-3 proteins 
increase the cytoplasmic retention of phosphorylated BES1/ 
BZR1 (Gampala et al., 2007). Mutation of a BIN2 phospho-
rylation site in BZR1 was shown to abolish 14-3-3 binding, 
leading to increased nuclear localization of the BES1/BZR1 
protein (Bai et al., 2007; Gampala et al., 2007). Like AtBZR1 
and AtBES1, PhBEH2 also possesses the conserved puta-
tive 14-3-3-binding site, suggesting that the regulation of the 
BZR1/BES1 family by 14-3-3 proteins might be conserved 
among plants. Thirdly, PhBEH2 interacted with a petunia 
GSK3-like kinase (PSK8) that belongs to the group II GSK3-
like kinases (Figs 5, 7). Arabidopsis group II GSK3-like 
kinases have been shown to regulate BR signalling negatively 
by phosphorylating the BZR1/BES1 family (Vert and Chory, 
2006; Yan et al., 2009; Rhozon et al., 2010). To reveal the 
involvement of PSK8 in BR signalling, phosphorylation of 
PhBEH2 by PSK8 should be demonstrated and knock-outs 
might ultimately reveal their function. In addition to PSK8, 
another group II member (PSK9) was also identified in petu-
nia. Based solely on similarity, it seems likely that PSK9 is 
also involved in BR signalling. The lack of interaction with 
PhBEH2 and Arabidopsis BES1 and BZR1 might be due to 
aberrant processing of the PSK9-GAL4 fusion RNA and/or 
protein in yeast. </p>

<p>Identification of new interactions </p>

<p>The present yeast two-hybrid screen with PhBEH2 revealed 
several interacting proteins that function in diverse signal 
transduction pathways. This suggests that PhBEH2 could 
be an important hub between BR and other signalling path-
ways. Recently, a number of reports highlighted interac-
tions between BR signalling and other hormone pathways 
(reviewed by Choudhary et al., 2012). 
One of the most interesting partners of PhBEH2 is a pro-
tein homologous to the Arabidopsis gene SECRET AGENT 
(SEC) encoding an OGT (Hartweck et al., 2002, 2006). For 
SEC, the interaction was confirmed in yeast using BiFC in 
petunia protoplasts (Fig. 5I). SEC catalyses the transfer of a 
single O-linked-N-acetylglucosamine to specific serine/threo-
nine residues. SEC is partly redundant with another OGT in 
Arabidopsis called SPINDLY (SPY). Shimada et al. (2006) 
reported that mutation of the rice SPINDLY gene (OsSPY) 
reduced the expression of several BR biosynthesis genes and 
OsBRI1. As expected, the levels of sterol and BR compounds 
were slightly up-regulated in the OsSPY knock-out mutant. 
O-GlcNAcylation of target proteins might affect their 
activity, localization, stability, and interactions with other 
proteins. The fact that OGTs add acetylglucosamine to ser-
ine/threonine residues of proteins suggests a model where 
OGTs and GSKs compete for modification of these residues 
in the BES/BZR family of proteins. Such a scenario, where an 
OGT competes with a kinase, is a widely recognized mecha-
nism in animal research (Kamemura et al., 2002; Z. Wang 
et al., 2008; Butkinaree et al., 2009). Most strikingly, there 
are specific examples where GSK3 phosphorylation and 
O-GlcNAcylation occur on the same site of proteins (Wang 
et al., 2007). It would be interesting to see whether PhSEC 
adds acetylglucosamine to PhBEH2 and, if so, what the con-
sequences are for the function of PhBEH2. 
Multiple links between petunia BR signalling components 
and other pathways were identified. For instance, PhBEH2 
interacts with a protein that has high sequence homology to 
ARIA, a positive regulator of the ABA signalling cascade. 
PhBEH2 also interacts with two proteins containing RRMs. 
One of the RRM proteins is a homologue of FPA, a gene that 
regulates flowering time in Arabidopsis via a pathway that is 
independent of daylength (Schomburg et al., 2001). Various 
connections between flowering and BRs have been revealed 
(Domagalska et al., 2007; Lee et al., 2008a, b; Yu et al., 2008). 
This is consistent with the finding that BR biosynthesis 
mutants as well as signalling mutants are late flowering or, 
like the cd10 (petunia bri1) mutant, non-flowering. Although 
interesting, further research should confirm these findings. 
Remarkably, no known homologues of the BR signalling 
pathway were found in the yeast two-hybrid screen performed 
with PSK8. Using PhBEH2 as bait, PSK8 was isolated, but 
using the same cDNA library the reverse interaction was not 
identified. It might be that none of the BES1/BZR1 family 
members present in the library is in-frame with the GAL4-
binding domain. Nonetheless, the yeast two-hybrid screen 
with PSK8 might have revealed other roles of group II GSK 
kinases that have not been recognized yet. </p>



<p>PSK8 interacted with a number of proteins that are poorly 
characterized. Among these are a member of the LLR-
extensin (LRX) and of the REMORIN family. So far, the 
action of GSK kinases in plants was found to occur via phos-
phorylation of transcription factors such as those belonging 
to the BES1/BZR family. Here, the identified interactions 
infer a direct role for GSK3-like proteins in the regulation of 
enzyme-like proteins, a mechanism that has interfaces with 
some of the roles of GSK3 in animals. </p>

<p>Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data are available at JXB online. 
Figure S1. Alignment of the deduced amino acid sequences 
of BRI1 and homologues. 
Figure S2. Alignment of the deduced amino acid sequences 
of BES/BZR and homologues. 
Figure S3. Alignment of the deduced amino acid sequences 
of class II GSK3/SHAGGY-like kinases from Arabidopsis 
and petunia. 
Figure S4. Yeast one-hybrid to test for autoactivation 
of baits. 
Table S1. Primers used for PCR. 
Table S2. GenBank accession numbers </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Allan Awanijan and Longinus Igbojionu for their 
assistance during some of the cloning experiments, Iris Bijker 
and Serena Della Pina for their help with the BiFC experi-
ment, and Maartje Kuijpers for plant care. NV was supported 
by a grant from the Netherlands Organisation for Scientific 
Research (NWO). TY was supported by the MEXT-
Supported Program for the Strategic Research Foundation at 
Private Universities, 2008-2012. </p>



<p>Brassinosteroids in Petunia hybrida | 2447 </p>







</text></tei>