<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3780496" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objetivos: Los objetivos de este estudio fueron 
obtener datos piloto sobre la satisfacción en el 
trabajo de establecimientos de cadena en el área de 
Tucson e identificar las facetas de la práctica 
comunitaria que tienen mayor contribución a la 
satisfacción con el trabajo. 
Métodos: Este fue un estudio transversal en 
farmacias de cadena del área de Tucson. Se utilizó 
el cuestionario de Warr-Cook-Wall de satisfacción 
con el trabajo para evaluar la satisfacción de los 
farmacéuticos comunitarios con su puesto actual. 
Este estudio usó el análisis de Rasch para evaluar la 
validez y la fiabilidad del cuestionario. Las 
puntuaciones de Rasch obtenidas de cada 
respondente fueron usadas como variable 
dependiente en los análisis univariado y bivariado 
para evaluar las diferencias en la satisfacción con el 
trabajo. 
Resultados: Un total de 32 farmacéuticos 
respondieron de las 129 farmacias comunitarias de 
cadena en las ciudades de Tucson, Marana and Oro 
Valley, Arizona. La media (DE) de la puntuación 
de satisfacción con el trabajo fue de 0,93 (2,1). Los 
resultados del análisis bivariado indican que los 
farmacéuticos del área de Tucson con práctica fuera 
de la farmacia comunitaria estaban menos 
satisfechos que los que no la tenían (p&lt;0,01). 
Conclusiones: Este estudio piloto sugiere que tener 
experiencia fuera de la farmacia comunitaria afecta 
a la satisfacción con el trabajo. Además, los 
hallazgos de este estudio indican que existe 
evidencia fiable y válida para apoyar el uso del 
cuestionario Warr-Cook-Wall para evaluar la 
satisfacción general con el trabajo en la práctica de 
la farmacia comunitaria en cadenas. </p>

<p>Palabras clave: Satisfacción en el Trabajo. Rol 
Profesional. Práctica Profesional. Farmacéuticos. 
Estados Unidos. </p>

<p>Pharmacist job satisfaction, or dissatisfaction, plays 
a major role in many aspects of community 
pharmacy practice. 
1,2 An article by Saari et al. 
demonstrates that poor job satisfaction is directly 
associated with performance, especially for 
professionals like pharmacists. 
1 These performance 
problems can include incorrectly filling prescriptions, </p>

<p>Original Research </p>

<p>Job satisfaction among chain community 
pharmacists: results from a pilot study </p>

<p>Ana L. HINCAPIE, Stephanie YANDOW, Stephanie HINES, Megan MARTINEAU, Terri WARHOLAK. </p>

<p>Received (first version): 27-Jul-2012 
Accepted: 15-Dec-2012 </p>

<p>Hincapie AL, Yandow S, Hines S, Martineau M, Warholak T. Job satisfaction among chain community pharmacists: 
results from a pilot study. Pharmacy Practice (Internet) 2012 Oct-Dec;10(4):227-233. </p>

<p>www.pharmacypractice.org (ISSN: 1886-3655) </p>



<p>not detecting drug interactions and poor patient 
counseling. Thus, dissatisfaction may also affect the 
way that patients view the pharmacist and patients 
may then be inclined limit their interactions with the 
pharmacist. 3 It is important to realize that a 
decrease in pharmacist performance could cause 
patient harm or even death. </p>

<p>4,5 </p>

<p>If a pharmacist is dissatisfied with his/her career, 
there is a potential for increased job turnover. 1,6 
Pharmacists job satisfaction has been found to be 
negatively associated with job turnover 
6 , that is 
pharmacists with low levels job of satisfaction are 
more likely to resign their positions. 
6-8 Pharmacist 
job satisfaction does not only affect the pharmacist 
at his/her workplace, but has the potential to affect 
many other aspects of his/her pharmacist life. 
Research suggests that there is a strong link 
between job satisfaction and overall life 
satisfaction. 
4 If a pharmacist is not satisfied with 
his/her work he/she may bring those ill feelings from 
their job home and allow them to affect his/her life 
outside of the work place. </p>

<p>There are limited preliminary studies exploring 
aspects that impact community pharmacists job 
satisfaction and most of current evidence has been 
conducted in hospital settings. National surveys of 
community pharmacists show that perceived 
workload, and information technologies may have 
an effect on job satisfaction. 3,9,10 In addition, 
continuing pharmacy education and preceptorship 
have been identified to be significant predictors of 
career and job satisfaction among community 
pharmacists. 
2,11 Other factors that have been shown 
to affect job satisfaction are treatment by 
management 10,12 
and 
other 
interpersonal 
interactions including patient contact and coworkers 
relationships 
8,13 , 
compensation 
7,14 , 
pharmacy 
ownership 4 , and practice setting. 
14-16 Community 
and chain pharmacists were found to be less 
satisfied with their jobs than pharmacists in other 
settings. 
15 The effect of demographic characteristics 
such age, sex, and education level on community 
pharmacist job satisfaction is still contradictory in 
the published literature. 7,10,15,16 </p>

<p>Most of the studies examining the factors affecting 
job satisfaction for community pharmacists have 
used instruments developed, validated and used in 
hospital settings 
17 , which may not capture factors 
within the realm of community pharmacy. 
Additionally, previous studies have measured 
satisfaction with single-item or a limited number of 
Likert type rating scales within larger studies that 
assess general aspects of pharmacy worklife 4,8,18 
and thus they may not capture the different traits of 
the job satisfaction multidimensional construct. 
Finally, some studies have adapted instruments 
from other settings to measure community 
pharmacy facets not assessed with available 
standardized tools. 
14,19-21 However these studies 
used narrow population samples, thus more 
evidenced is needed to support validity of such 
instruments in community pharmacy. </p>

<p>Using the Warr-Cook-Wall questionnaire of job 
satisfaction, the objectives of this study are to: (1) 
obtain pilot data concerning the job satisfaction of </p>

<p>Tucson area retail chain setting; 2) identify the 
facets of community practice that have the greatest 
contribution to job satisfaction; and 3) investigate 
the validity and reliability of the Warr-Cook-Wall 
questionnaire within a US community pharmacy 
study sample. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Sample </p>

<p>This investigation involved an anonymous cross-
sectional study of chain pharmacists in the Tucson 
area. A comprehensive list of all chain pharmacies 
in the Tucson area, including Oro Valley and 
Marana, was compiled from online lists of stores 
obtained from each respective chain's website. 
There were 129 chain community pharmacies within 
this geographical area, all of which were included in 
questionnaire distribution. Each of the chain 
community pharmacies were faxed a questionnaire 
and cover letter a total of three times with 
approximately one month between distribution 
waves. Each store was sent one copy of the 
questionnaire and a cover letter explaining the study 
during each wave. The cover letter explained study 
goals, intent of the investigators, information about 
anonymity and included instructions on how to 
return the questionnaire (i.e. fax number). The cover 
letter also included a web address where the survey 
was available online. The cover letter encouraged 
all pharmacists working at each pharmacy to 
complete the survey. The store was responsible for 
making enough copies so that each pharmacist 
could complete his or her own survey. Responses 
were faxed back to a phone number that put the 
response directly into an email account. Received 
data were introduced into an Excel spreadsheet for 
analysis. This project was approved by the IRB at 
the University of Arizona. </p>

<p>Instrumentation </p>

<p>The questionnaire used for this study consisted of 
nine questions regarding job satisfaction and eleven 
questions regarding pharmacist demographics. The 
nine questions regarding job satisfaction were taken 
from the Warr-Cook-Wall scale job satisfaction 
questionnaire modified version 
20 that includes a 
"patient interaction" item and were used to evaluate 
pharmacists' satisfaction with their current position. 
All nine items measured job satisfaction using a 4 
point Likert-scale with response options "very 
satisfied," "satisfied," "somewhat satisfied," and "not 
at all satisfied." Although the original scale measure 
satisfaction in a 7-point scale, a 4-point scale was 
used to decrease misinterpretation and mid-point 
selection. In previous studies in United Kingdom 
and New Zealand community pharmacists, the 
Warr-Cook-Wall job satisfaction scale obtained a 
Cronbach's alpha coefficient of 0.90. </p>

<p>20,21 </p>

<p>Pharmacists were asked what type of degree they 
held, the number of years of experience they had in 
pharmacy practice, and whether they had outside 
community pharmacy experience. Pharmacist were 
also asked five questions related to pharmacists 
work status: 1) type of chain pharmacy at which 
they were employed; 2) number of work hours </p>

<p>Hincapie AL, Yandow S, Hines S, Martineau M, Warholak T. Job satisfaction among chain community pharmacists: 
results from a pilot study. Pharmacy Practice (Internet) 2012 Oct-Dec;10(4):227-233. </p>

<p>www.pharmacypractice.org (ISSN: 1886-3655) </p>



<p>worked per week; 3) the length of their longest work 
day (in hours); 4) average number of prescriptions 
filled per week; 5) if he/she is the pharmacists in 
charge; and 6) availability of patient services at their 
pharmacy. The inclusion of these questions was 
based on previous research on job satisfaction in 
community pharmacy. </p>

<p>2,3,12,20 </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>We used Rasch analysis to assess the validity and 
reliability of the questionnaire. 
19 The general 
consensus on the minimum sample size for Rasch 
analyses is 30 subjects. 
22 In Rasch analysis two 
types of fit statistics are used to assess how well the 
model fit the empirical data: Infit and Outfit for items 
mean squares (MNSQ). Infit MNSQ is an index 
weighted by the difference between persons' ability 
and item difficulty, which makes it more sensitive to 
unexpected responses. Outfit MNSQ is an 
unweighted index more sensitive to extreme 
responses. High infit and outfit (underfit) reflect lack 
of predictability of an item. Low infit and outfit 
(overfit) indicate over-predictability of an item. </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Mean-squares are expected to be around 1.0. An 
aspect of validity is unidimensionality, which 
indicates that items in a scale are measuring the 
same construct. To assess the unidimensionality of 
the questionnaire, the items Infit and Outfit MNSQ 
statistics were evaluated. An Infit MNSQ or Outfit 
MNSQ greater than 1.4, which denotes 40 percent 
more variance than expected, indicates that the 
item may be measuring a different construct; and an 
Infit MNSQ or Outfit MNSQ lower that 0.6 indicates 
item redundancy. 
24,25 Items that do not meet the Infit 
and Outfit MNSQ criteria were removed from the 
model. To evaluate whether the 4 point-Likert rating 
scaled used ("very satisfied" to "not satisfied at all") 
fits the Rasch model criteria, the following 
characteristics were assessed (Linacre): (1) at least 
10 observations per category; (2) regular 
observation distribution; (3) average measures 
advance monotonically with category; (4) outfit 
MNSQ less than 2; (5) step calibration advance; (6) 
ratings imply measures and measure imply ratings; 
and (7) step difficulties advance greater than or 
equal to 1.4 logits and less than 5 logits. </p>

<p>Construct validity was determined by examining the 
gaps in the measurement of each item's calibration 
value. Z-test analysis was used to determine the 
significance of gaps. The presence of significant 
gaps indicates that some domains of the job 
satisfaction construct are not assessed. 
25 Reliability 
refers to the level of true and error variance in an 
observed score. The Rasch person reliability index 
denotes the reproducibility of person placement 
across other items measuring the same construct, 
which is equivalent to the Cronbach's alpha (test 
reliability) in classical test theory. </p>

<p>22,23,26 </p>

<p>An overall score of job satisfaction among 
community pharmacists in Tucson was calculated 
converting the ordinal responses from the Warr-
Cook-Wall questionnaire to interval data (logits) with 
the Rasch Model if the Rasch model's requirements 
mentioned above were met. A higher score in logits 
represents greater job satisfaction (logits typically 
ranges from -4 to 4). The Rasch overall score was </p>

<p>used as a continuous variable in descriptive, and 
non-parametric bivariate analyses to explore 
differences in job satisfaction and age, type of 
degree 
(PharmD/Non-PharmD), 
years 
of 
experience, 
workload 
(Avg. 
prescription 
volume/week, and whether they worked more than 
36 hours/week), type of pharmacy chain 
(Grocery/non-grocery), having experience outside of 
community practice (yes/no), provision of patient 
care services at the pharmacy (yes/no) and job 
position (Pharmacist in charge yes/no) the selection 
of these variables was based on previous studies. 15 
Statistical significance was set at 0.05. The 
statistical software used were <rs type="software">Winsteps</rs> for Rasch 
analyses and <rs id="software-1" type="software">STATA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">11</rs>. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>During the period from August 2011 through 
November 2011, a total of 32 pharmacists 
responded from 129 chain community pharmacies 
in the cities of Tucson, Marana and Oro Valley, 
Arizona. Twenty-two questionnaires were received 
via fax while 10 were submitted online. Our 
estimated response rate was roughly 12%, which 
was calculated using an average of 2 pharmacists 
per store. The true count of pharmacists working at 
each store was not available. Pharmacists holding a 
Doctor of Pharmacy degree (PharmD) made up 
68% (n=21) of respondents and the remaining 32% 
(n=11) of respondents held a Bachelor of Science in 
Pharmacy (BS) degree. Fifty-five percent of 
pharmacists surveyed (n=16) were employed at a 
grocery chain and 45% (n=13) were based out of a 
non-grocery chain store and almost two thirds 
(n=30) of participants were pharmacists in charge. 
Most of respondents indicated that they provided 
patient care services (94% n=30). Additional 
demographic data can be found in Table 1. </p>

<p>Validity and Reliability Results for the modifies 
Warr-Cook-Wall questionnaire </p>

<p>Total fit (Infit and Outfit MNSQ) for persons and 
items were 1.01 and 1.02 respectively, which are 
around the expected 1.0.This indicates that the data 
fit the model appropriately and responses show a 
logical pattern. The item measures, standard errors, 
and fit statistics for each item are described in Table 
2. All but items 3 and 8 fit the expected Infit and 
Outfit MNSQ 
27 range between 0.6 and 1.4, which 
means that they were not overfitting or misfitting 
items; the two items that did not meet these criteria 
were removed from the analysis. Additionally, the 
model reliability estimate was 0.83, which is higher 
than the accepted 0.7 threshold. 
28 The persons' 
mean score of job satisfaction was 0.93, which 
indicates that pharmacists found items moderately 
easy to agree with. </p>

<p>Table 1. Respondent Demographics (n=32) 
Mean 
SD 
Years of experience in pharmacy 
practice 
17 
11 </p>

<p>Average 
number 
of 
prescriptions 
dispensed per week 
1281 795 </p>

<p>Number of technician hours per week 
137 
70 
Participant age (years) 
40 
10 
Longest work day (hours) 
12 
2 
SD=Standard deviations </p>

<p>Hincapie AL, Yandow S, Hines S, Martineau M, Warholak T. Job satisfaction among chain community pharmacists: 
results from a pilot study. Pharmacy Practice (Internet) 2012 Oct-Dec;10(4):227-233. </p>

<p>www.pharmacypractice.org (ISSN: 1886-3655) </p>



<p>Table 3 and Figure 1 show that the instrument 
demonstrated appropriate functioning of the rating 
scale categories used. The number of observations 
in each category was greater than 10 and the 
average category measures increased with the 
rating scale categories. Pharmacists responding 
with a "1-Not Satisfied at all" showed an average 
measure (-1.64) lower than those responding with a 
"2-Satisfied" (average measure= -0.36), etc. There 
was no evidence of misfit categories (Outfit MNSQ 
&lt;2), and the probability curve in Figure 1 depicts 
that all category values were more likely to be used 
at some point of the continuum thus no inversions 
were found. </p>

<p>Figure 2 shows the order of the items relative to the 
optimized rating categories and measures and what 
would be expected to be more or less challenging. 
From this Figure, it appears that there were gaps in 
the measurement continuum (between items 5 and 
7, and items 1 and 9), which were not statistically 
significant (p=0.2). Additionally, the item related to 
patient contact was the easiest to endorse, which 
means that the respondents were more likely to 
agree with this statement. </p>

<p>Job satisfaction analysis </p>

<p>The mean (Standard Deviation) Rasch score for job 
satisfaction was 0.93 (2.1) (See Table 2), which 
indicates that pharmacists found items moderately 
easy to agree with. Table 4 displays the results of 
the analysis exploring differences between 
respondents' overall Rasch job satisfaction scores 
and multiple work related factors. It was found that 
pharmacists' job satisfaction score was statistically 
significantly smaller for those who reported having 
experience outside community practice. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This paper reports the results of a pilot study that 
assessed the job satisfaction of Tucson area retail 
chain setting. Findings from this study indicate that 
responding pharmacists in the Tucson area with 
practice experience outside community pharmacy 
were less satisfied with their job. These findings are 
consistent with those of previously published 
research. 
3,15,29 Several reasons can be thought to 
explain these results. First, there could be a 
perception of over-qualification for the job that may 
not be present while working in hospital settings. 
This is reflected in the responses to the item 
"opportunities to use abilities" where only one 
quarter of respondents indicated, "very satisfied" to 
this item. Second, pharmacist in community settings 
may be have limited opportunities to growth within 
the organization. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>The instrument used in this study showed validity 
and reliability as determined by the Rasch model 
when two items were removed from the original 
questionnaire: satisfaction with colleagues and 
amount of variety in the job. Examination of the 
items that misfit the model reveled a fit MNSQ 
greater than two, which indicates that these items 
showed excessive unexplained noise. This may be 
explained by misunderstanding of the items. </p>

<p>"Recognition you get for good work" was the item 
most challenging to agree with. This is consistent </p>

<p>Table 2. Frequency of participant responses and Rasch item fit statistics for the Warr-Cook-Wall questionnaire 
How would you rate 
your satisfaction 
with… </p>

<p>Very 
satisfied 
n (%) </p>

<p>Somewhat 
satisfied 
n (%) </p>

<p>Satisfied 
n 
(%) </p>

<p>Not at all 
satisfied 
n (%) </p>

<p>Item 
measures 
SD 
MNSQ 
Infit </p>

<p>MSNQ 
Outfit </p>

<p>1. Physical working 
conditions 
9(29) 
13(42) 
7(22) 
2(6) 
-0.44 
0.28 
1.13 
1.11 </p>

<p>2. Freedom to choose 
methods of working 
5(16) 
11(35) 
12(39) 
3(10) 
0.45 
0.28 
0.86 
0.84 </p>

<p>3. Colleagues* 
20(62) 
6(19) 
6(19) 
0(0) 
N/A 
N/A 
N/A 
N/A 
4. Recognition you get 
for good work 
9(28) 
8(25) 
7(22) 
8(25) 
0.61 
0.28 
1.13 
1.14 </p>

<p>5. Financial 
Remunerations 
14(44) 
4(12) 
12(37) 
2(6) 
-0.36 
0.28 
0.98 
0.97 </p>

<p>6. Opportunity to use 
abilities 
8(25) 
11(35) 
8(25) 
5(17) 
0.29 
0.28 
0.73 
0.74 </p>

<p>7. Hours of work 
9(28) 
10(34) 
9(28) 
4(12) 
0.13 
0.28 
1.13 
1.23 
8. Amount of variety in 
job* 
9(28) 
11(31) 
9(28) 
3(9) 
N/A 
N/A 
N/A 
N/A </p>

<p>9. Patient contact 
16(50) 
3(9) 
12(37) 
1(3) 
-0.69 
0.28 
1.12 
0.94 
Average 
measure </p>

<p>SD 
Model 
reliability 
Pharmacists' overall job satisfaction measure 
0.93 
2.11 
0.83 
N/A=Not applicable, *Item 3 and 8 were eliminated from the analysis due to Rasch model misfit, SD= Standard Deviation, 
MNSQ= Mean square residuals </p>

<p>Figure 1. Rasch category probabilities </p>

<p>Hincapie AL, Yandow S, Hines S, Martineau M, Warholak T. Job satisfaction among chain community pharmacists: 
results from a pilot study. Pharmacy Practice (Internet) 2012 Oct-Dec;10(4):227-233. </p>

<p>www.pharmacypractice.org (ISSN: 1886-3655) </p>



<p>with the Maslow's Theory of Motivation of job 
satisfaction where "recognition" is a factor located at 
a higher level; and can be achieved only after 
social, safety and psychological needs are met. </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>On the other hand, "Patient contact" was the easiest 
item to endorse. This could occur because 
community pharmacists in chain settings have more 
patient contact, which favors interpersonal 
interactions. Research has found that pharmacist 
value these interpersonal interactions and 
determine their intention to stay on a job. 8 </p>

<p>Due to an unintentional inversion of the response 
scale during questionnaire development, we 
expected to find an inversion of the probability curve 
in the Rash model. However, the analysis showed 
that respondents did not detect the inversion of the 
questionnaire scale. That is, respondents selected 
the option "satisfied" as it was "somewhat satisfied." 
This could be explained by a potential familiarity 
with 4-point Likert-scale surveys that may facilitate 
the identification of the anchors in the scale without 
carefully reading options in between. Additionally, 
research shows that people tend to respond on the 
left side of a scale and response order bias is 
affected by readers' habits. </p>

<p>31,32 </p>

<p>An area for future research may include broadening 
the variable "experience outside community 
practice" to determine to what pharmacists are 
comparing to, when assessing their level of 
satisfaction. Aspects to consider include the extent 
to which the use of clinical skills in other settings 
affects job satisfaction and years and related 
activities of experience working outside community 
practice. </p>

<p>As several of the previously reviewed studies have 
confirmed, the lack of satisfaction with job can have 
negative impacts on patient care and safety and can 
even be a motivating factor for leaving the job or the 
profession all together. Conversely, researchers 
have found that pharmacists that are more satisfied 
with their work are highly motivated to do a good job 
and make patients and employees encounters with 
the pharmacist more positive. 2 For this reason, 
pharmacy job satisfaction surveys are an important 
part of identifying the weaknesses of a specific job 
so that those weaknesses can be corrected or 
minimized, while maximizing the strengths, which 
leads to a better and safer experience for everyone 
involved. </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>This study analyzed information from pharmacists 
working within the cities of Tucson, Marana and Oro 
Valley and results may not be generalizable to 
pharmacists in other geographic locations. The 
compiled list of all the pharmacies in the geographic 
location did not include independent pharmacies, so 
the study cannot be generalized to other pharmacy 
types. Another limitation is that some pharmacists 
might not have been in the pharmacy on the day of 
questionnaire dissemination, which means it is 
possible that not all of the pharmacists received a 
questionnaire or to know if a pharmacist actually 
filled the questionnaire. Even if a pharmacist 
received a questionnaire he or she may not have 
completed it, or the pharmacy manager may not 
have distributed the questionnaires to all of the 
pharmacists working at the store. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>This pilot evaluation suggests that experience 
outside community practice affects pharmacist job 
satisfaction. Additionally, findings from this study 
indicate that there is reliability and validity evidence 
to support the use of the modifies Warr-Cook-Wall 
questionnaire for assessing overall job satisfaction 
in chain community pharmacy practice. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>No funding was provided for this project. </p>

<p>Table 3. Rasch scale category fit statistics </p>

<p>Category Label 
Observed 
Count </p>

<p>Average 
Measure </p>

<p>Infit 
MNSQ </p>

<p>Outfit 
MNSQ 
Threshold </p>

<p>Not at all satisfied 
25 
-1.64 
0.87 
0.88 
-
Satisfied 
67 
-0.36 
1.17 
1.13 
-2.02 
Somewhat satisfied 
60 
0.55 
1.19 
1.11 
0.19 
Very satisfied 
70 
2.44 
0.84 
0.85 
1.83 
MNSQ= Mean square residuals </p>

<p>Table 4. Factors associated with job satisfaction scores 
Mean 
SD 
p-value 
Type of degree held* 
Bachelor of Science 
Doctor of Pharmacy </p>

<p>1.05 
0.68 </p>

<p>1.9 
2.1 </p>

<p>0.64 </p>

<p>Type of pharmacy chain* 
Grocery 
Non-Grocery </p>

<p>0.61 
0.88 </p>

<p>2.09 
2.19 </p>

<p>0.74 </p>

<p>Experience outside of community pharmacy* 
Yes 
No </p>

<p>-0.03 
1.78 </p>

<p>2.06 
1.85 </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>Provide patient care services* 
Yes 
No </p>

<p>0.99 
0 </p>

<p>2.16 
2.34 </p>

<p>0.53 </p>

<p>Work more than 36 hours/week* 
Yes 
No </p>

<p>0.95 
0.74 </p>

<p>2.21 
1.86 </p>

<p>0.85 </p>

<p>Pharmacist in charge (yes/no)* 
Yes 
No </p>

<p>0.94 
0.55 </p>

<p>2.266 
1.68 </p>

<p>0.61 </p>

<p>Years of experience** 
&lt;10 
10-20 
21-30 
&gt;30 </p>

<p>0.03 
1.76 
0.96 
3.42 </p>

<p>1.99 
1.96 
2.31 
1.99 </p>

<p>0.31 </p>

<p>Avg. prescription volume/week** 
&lt;1000 
1000-1500 
&gt;1500 </p>

<p>0.23 
1.63 
0.29 </p>

<p>1.61 
2.23 
2.27 </p>

<p>0.22 </p>

<p>Longest work day (hours)** 
&lt;10 
10-13 
&gt;13 </p>

<p>-0.18 
1.06 
1.51 </p>

<p>1.49 
2.26 
1.98 </p>

<p>0.21 </p>

<p>Age*** 
0.08 
0.67 
* Two-sample t-test 
**One -way ANOVA 
***Person correlation coefficient </p>

<p>Figure 2. Rasch content validity gap analysis </p>



<p>Hincapie AL, Yandow S, Hines S, Martineau M, Warholak T. Job satisfaction among chain community pharmacists: 
results from a pilot study. Pharmacy Practice (Internet) 2012 Oct-Dec;10(4):227-233. </p>

<p>www.pharmacypractice.org (ISSN: 1886-3655) </p>





</text></tei>