<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3373399" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The lymphatic vasculature initially develops as a primitive plexus 
of identical vessels, all expressing the hyaluronan receptor 
lymphatic vessel endothelial hyaluronan receptor 1 (LYVE-1). 
This plexus is extensively remodeled to give rise to the func-
tional lymphatic vasculature, which consists of two distinct 
vessel types: lymphatic capillaries (also called initial lymphat-
ics) and collecting lymphatic vessels (Jurisic and Detmar, 2009;  Tammela and Alitalo, 2010). Only blind-ended lymphatic cap-
illaries retain expression of LYVE-1, and their distinctive mor-
phology is ideally suited to their function; loose, overlapping 
cell-cell junctions, discontinuous basement membrane (BM), 
and wide lumens allow efficient absorption of protein-rich fluid 
from the interstitium. The fluid is further drained into the col-
lecting lymphatic vessels, which develop luminal valves and </p>

<p>a BM, and recruit smooth muscle cells (SMC), to assist in the 
unidirectional propulsion of lymph (Jurisic and Detmar, 2009;  Tammela and Alitalo, 2010). 
In the blood vessels, the vascular BM is an important 
structural component, which is formed predominantly of Col-
lagen IV, laminin, nidogen/entactin, and heparan sulfate proteo-
glycans (Sasaki et al., 2004). It helps to keep the vessel wall 
structure in shape and withstand mechanical forces generated 
by pulsatile blood flow and vasoconstriction, which regulates 
blood flow and pressure. In addition to its structural impor-
tance, more recent studies have revealed a complex function-
ality of the vascular BM, including involvement in endothelial 
cell (EC) migration, proliferation, survival, signal transduction, 
and vessel morphogenesis (Aszódi et al., 2006). In addition, 
because the vascular BM is produced by and shared between 
ECs and SMCs, it directly interacts with both cell types to 
modulate their behavior and communication. For example, </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>ctive lymph transport relies on smooth muscle cell 
(SMC) contractions around collecting lymphatic 
vessels, yet regulation of lymphatic vessel wall 
assembly and lymphatic pumping are poorly understood. 
Here, we identify Reelin, an extracellular matrix glyco-
protein previously implicated in central nervous system 
development, as an important regulator of lymphatic 
vascular development. Reelin-deficient mice showed 
abnormal collecting lymphatic vessels, characterized by 
a reduced number of SMCs, abnormal expression of 
lymphatic capillary marker lymphatic vessel endothelial 
hyaluronan receptor 1 (LYVE-1), and impaired function. 
Furthermore, we show that SMC recruitment to lymphatic </p>

<p>vessels stimulated release and proteolytic processing of 
endothelium-derived Reelin. Lymphatic endothelial cells 
in turn responded to Reelin by up-regulating monocyte 
chemotactic protein 1 (MCP1) expression, which suggests 
an autocrine mechanism for Reelin-mediated control of 
endothelial factor expression upstream of SMC recruit-
ment. These results uncover a mechanism by which Reelin 
signaling is activated by communication between the 
two cell types of the collecting lymphatic vessels-smooth 
muscle and endothelial cells-and highlight a hitherto 
unrecognized and important function for SMCs in lym-
phatic vessel morphogenesis and function. </p>

<p>Smooth muscle-endothelial cell communication 
activates Reelin signaling and regulates lymphatic 
vessel formation </p>

<p>Sophie Lutter, Sherry Xie, Florence Tatin, and Taija Makinen </p>

<p>Lymphatic Development Laboratory, Cancer Research UK London Research Institute, London WC2A 3LY, England, UK </p>

<p>© 2012 Lutter et al. This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution-
Noncommercial-Share Alike-No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the pub-
lication date (see http://www.rupress.org/terms). After six months it is available under a 
Creative Commons License (Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, 
as described at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). </p>

<p>T H E J O U R N A L O F C E L L B I O L O G Y </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 197 • NUMBER 6 • 2012 
838 </p>

<p>down-regulation of LYVE-1 expression (Fig. 1, E-G). Desmin 
and -SMA were coexpressed in lymphatic SMCs (Fig. 1 H). 
Another characteristic feature of collecting lymphatic ves-
sels is the presence of vascular BM. To investigate if matrix de-
position can serve as a marker of collecting vessel differentiation, 
we examined the expression of Collagen IV and Laminin-5 
in the developing vessels. At P14, Collagen IV was evident in 
LYVE-1-positive vessels that had no SMCs (Fig. 1, I and I), 
which suggests its deposition by ECs. At later stages, Collagen IV 
was found predominantly around collecting vessels (Fig. 1, 
J and J), with lower levels in capillaries (not depicted; Pflicke  and Sixt, 2009). Conversely, Laminin-5 expression was not de-
tectable in prospective collecting lymphatic vessels before SMC 
recruitment, except in luminal valves (Fig. 1, K and K; Bazigou  et al., 2009). In more matured collecting vessels, Laminin-5 
staining highlighted the SMCs around collecting vessels (Fig. 1, 
L and L), which suggests that these cells are its main source. 
However, in the blood vasculature, Laminin-5 is produced by 
ECs (Wu et al., 2009), and additional expression by lymphatic 
endothelium that may be induced upon SMC contact cannot be 
excluded. In summary, these results suggest that both endothelial 
and SMCs contribute to the production of matrix components of 
the lymphatic BM. In addition, deposition of ECM may provide 
the earliest sign of collecting vessel specification (Fig. 1 M). </p>

<p>Identification of Reelin as a lymphatic </p>

<p>endothelial-specific matrix molecule </p>

<p>To further characterize lymphatic vessel wall assembly, we 
attempted to identify new specific components of the lymphatic 
BM. We dissected mesenteric collecting lymphatic vessels, arter-
ies, and veins of P7 mice and identified differentially expressed 
genes using Affymetrix expression arrays. The reliability of the 
dataset was demonstrated by the identification of several known 
lymphatic, arterial, and venous markers that were up-or down-
regulated in the appropriate datasets (Table S1). 14 genes 
involved in ECM formation, composition, or degradation were 
up-regulated more than twofold in the lymphatic vessels in com-
parison to the blood vessels (Tables S2 and S3). Preferential 
expression of Efemp1, Spock3, and Nid2 in lymphatic in com-
parison to blood vessels was further confirmed by immuno-
fluorescence of mouse skin or Western blot analysis of primary 
ECs (Fig. S1, A-D). Among the identified genes, we focused on 
Reelin that was found as being expressed almost fivefold higher 
in the lymphatic vessels compared with the veins (Table S2). 
Previously, specific Reelin immunoreactivity was reported in the 
developing lymphatic vessels in rat and human (Samama and  Boehm, 2005). We further confirmed lymphatic specific expres-
sion of Reelin in vivo in murine embryonic (Fig. 2, A and A) and 
postnatal (Fig. 2, B-E; and Fig. S1, E-F) lymphatic vasculature 
of the skin and mesentery. The apparent expression in arteries that 
was detected in microarray profiling (Table S2) was likely caused 
by contaminating nerve tissue expressing Reelin (Fig. S1, E-E‴). </p>

<p>Differential localization of Reelin in mature </p>

<p>lymphatic capillaries and collecting vessels </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence for Reelin in the postnatal mesenteric and 
dermal lymphatic vasculature revealed intense perinuclear and </p>

<p>endothelial-derived ECM can stimulate proliferation of SMC in 
vitro (Figueroa et al., 2004). Similarly, Heparan-sulfate (HS), 
deposited by ECs, can support mural cell attachment on the ves-
sels in vivo; however, the mural cells require cell-autonomous 
HS to efficiently polarize and migrate to the nascent blood 
vessels (Stenzel et al., 2009). ECM molecules can also partici-
pate in storing, masking, presenting, or sequestering growth 
factors, thereby modulating their bioavailability and activity 
(Hynes, 2009). Furthermore, during development, the vascular 
BMs undergo compositional and structural alterations, including 
conformational changes and proteolytic processing of specific 
matrix components, which can provide important angiogenic or 
anti-angiogenic cues (for review see Kalluri, 2003). 
In contrast to the vascular BM, little is known of the 
composition and importance of the ECM of lymphatic vessels. 
Here, we identify Reelin as a lymphatic-specific matrix mol-
ecule and demonstrate its important function in the formation 
of functional collecting lymphatic vessels. In addition, we 
uncover a unique mechanism by which Reelin signaling is acti-
vated via communication between the two cell types that form 
the collecting vessels: endothelial and SMCs. The specific de-
fects displayed by the Reln-deficient mice further highlight a 
hitherto unrecognized important function of SMCs in lymphatic 
vessel morphogenesis and function. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Characterization of collecting </p>

<p>vessel formation and lymphatic </p>

<p>vascular wall assembly </p>

<p>To establish a timeline and a defined set of markers of lym-
phatic collecting vessel differentiation, we investigated SMC 
recruitment to dermal lymphatic vessels using antibodies against 
-smooth muscle actin (-SMA), desmin, and NG2, the markers 
of SMCs and pericytes; and against LYVE-1, a marker of imma-
ture lymphatic vessels and lymphatic capillaries. The develop-
ing vasculature was analyzed in mouse ear skin, which allows 
whole-mount visualization of vessels that grow postnatally into 
the ear to form a primary vascular plexus, which is subsequently 
remodeled into a functional vessel network consisting of lym-
phatic capillaries and collecting vessels (Mäkinen et al., 2005). 
During the first postnatal week, the expanding dermal lymphatic 
vasculature of the ear was devoid of SMCs and the endothelia 
was uniformly positive for LYVE-1 (unpublished data). At post-
natal day 12 (P12), LYVE-1 was down-regulated in specific areas 
(Fig. 1 A). Although the first -SMA-positive SMCs could be 
found loosely attached to the lymphatic vessels at this stage, 
LYVE-1 down-regulation did not correlate with their presence 
(Fig. 1 A and not depicted). At P14, developing collecting ves-
sels acquired SMCs, which were found predominantly in areas 
of low LYVE-1 expression (Fig. 1 B). By P16, lymphatic 
collecting vessels were identified by their prominent SMC cover-
age and absent LYVE-1 expression (Fig. 1 C). NG2, a marker of vas-
cular pericytes, was not expressed in lymphatic SMCs (Fig. 1 D), 
whereas desmin-positive SMCs were found only in lymphatic 
vessels that had acquired features of mature collecting vessels, 
such as prominent SMC coverage, luminal valves, and complete </p>

<p> 
Reelin in lymphatic development • Lutter et al. </p>

<p>used nonpermeabilized tissue, together with tyramide signal 
amplification (TSA) procedure, to allow specific staining of 
extracellular proteins. Under these conditions, low Reelin immuno-
reactivity was detected in the lymphatic capillaries (Fig. 2, 
F and F), whereas intense, patchy labeling of collecting lymphatic </p>

<p>punctuated staining in the blind-ended lymphatic capillaries 
(Fig. 2, B, B, D, and D). In contrast, the collecting vessels 
showed a weaker, diffuse Reelin immunoreactivity (Fig. 2, C, 
C, E, and E). To test if the differential protein distribution 
was related to different subcellular localization of Reelin, we </p>

<p>Figure 1. SMC recruitment and ECM deposition during collecting vessel formation. (A-H) Immunofluorescence staining of wild-type ear skin at the indicated 
stages (P12, P14, P16, or P21) with antibodies against LYVE-1 (green, A-C and E-G), -SMA (red, A-D and H), desmin (red, E-G; green, H), PECAM-1 
(blue, A-C and E-G), and Podoplanin (blue, D). Arrows in A indicate areas of LYVE-1 down-regulation before SMC recruitment. The arrow in D indicates 
an NG2-positive blood vessel, and the arrowhead in D indicates an NG2-negative collecting vessel. P, postnatal day. (I-L) Immunofluorescence staining 
of wild-type ear skin at P14 (I, I, K, and K) and P16 (J, J, L, and L) with antibodies against Collagen IV (green I-J), Laminin-5 (green K-L), -SMA 
(red), and LYVE-1 (blue). Arrows show Laminin-5 expression in luminal valves and arrowheads indicate expression of Laminin-5 by SMC. The broken 
line in K outlines the LYVE-1 
 collecting vessel. The asterisks in K and L show LYVE-1 
+ lymphatic capillaries. Bars, 50 µm. (M) Schematic timeline of dermal 
collecting lymphatic vessel differentiation. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 197 • NUMBER 6 • 2012 </p>

<p>
by the lymphatic ECs (LECs) into the ECM of the collecting 
vessels, but remains intracellular in the endothelia of lym-
phatic capillaries. </p>

<p>SMC contact activates Reelin signaling by </p>

<p>stimulating its secretion from lymphatic </p>

<p>endothelia and proteolytic processing </p>

<p>We conjectured that the secretion of Reelin into the ECM 
could be related to SMC recruitment in the collecting vessels. 
To test this, we analyzed Reelin expression and secretion by 
the LECs that were either cultured alone or together with SMCs. </p>

<p>vessels was observed (Fig. 2, G and G). Particularly strong 
immunoreactivity for extracellular Reelin (Fig. 2, G and G), 
but not for total Reelin protein (Fig. S1, E and E), was ob-
served around lymphatic valves, which suggests that Reelin 
is preferentially deposited in the valve regions, possibly by 
binding to specific matrix components that are enriched in 
these areas. Co-staining with cell compartment-specific markers 
suggested that intracellular Reelin in lymphatic capillaries 
resided predominantly in the endoplasmic reticulum (Fig. S1,  G and H), similar to what has been reported in neurons (Tinnes  et al., 2011). Together, these data suggest that Reelin is secreted </p>

<p>Figure 2. Reelin is a lymphatic endothelial-specific matrix molecule that shows differential distribution in lymphatic capillaries and collecting vessels. 
(A and A) Immunofluorescence of E16 dorsal skin for Reelin (green), LYVE-1 (red), and PECAM-1 (blue). Arrowheads and arrows indicates Reelin-positive 
and -negative lymphatic and blood vessels, respectively. (B-G) Immunofluorescence staining of P6 mesentery (B-C) and P21 ear-skin (D-G), with antibodies 
against Reelin (green) and -SMA (red). Blue staining (in B) is for PECAM-1 and (in D-E) for LYVE-1. Boxed areas in D and E are magnified in D and E, 
showing Reelin expression only. Vessel borders are highlighted by broken lines in B, C, D, E, and F). Tissue was unpermeabilized in F-G to detect 
extracellular proteins, and the fluorescent signal was amplified using TSA technology. The arrowhead in F indicates weak Reelin immunoreactivity outside 
capillary LECs. Bars: (A, D, E, F and G) 50 µm; (B and C) 500 µm; (D' and E') 20 µm. </p>

<p> 
Reelin in lymphatic development • Lutter et al. </p>

<p>contact stimulates the secretion of Reelin from the LECs and its 
proteolytic processing, which suggests that SMC recruitment to 
the collecting lymphatic vessels activates Reelin signaling. </p>

<p>Defective collecting lymphatic vessel </p>

<p>formation in Reelin-deficient mice </p>

<p>To investigate the physiological function of Reelin in lymphatic 
vasculature, we analyzed the dermal lymphatic vessels in 
Reelin (encoded by Reln)-deficient Reeler mice (D'Arcangelo  et al., 1995). The mature dermal lymphatic vasculature is com-
posed of three types of vessels: collecting vessels, precollectors, 
and capillaries. Precollectors share features of both capillaries 
and collecting vessels; in most cases they are LYVE-1-positive 
vessels that contain luminal valves but no SMCs. They often 
abruptly branch off the main LYVE-1-negative collecting vessel 
(Fig. 4 A, see also Fig. 4 F). However, in some cases, transi-
tion from one type of vessel to another is more gradual; indi-
vidual -SMA-positive cells can be found attached on vessels 
that contain some LYVE-1 
+ ECs (unpublished data). Notably, 
however, SMCs are rarely found directly attached to LYVE-1 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>LECs, or on uniformly LYVE-1 
+ vessels. Because the defini-
tion of precollecting vessel is ambiguous, in this study we con-
sidered only two vessel categories that we defined as collecting 
vessels based on the presence of -SMA 
+ SMCs and as capillar-
ies based on positive LYVE-1 immunoreactivity. 
We observed an apparently normal LYVE-1-positive der-
mal lymphatic capillary network in the ears of the Reln-deficient </p>

<p>Lymphatic endothelial-specific expression of Reelin was main-
tained in vitro, as assessed by quantitative PCR (qPCR) analy-
ses of RNA extracted from primary human LECs, blood vascular 
ECs (BECs), and SMCs (Fig. 3 A). In addition, immunoprecipi-
tation and Western blot analysis using an antibody that recog-
nizes an epitope at the N terminus of Reelin (Fig. 3 B) confirmed 
that only LECs produced Reelin protein (Fig. 3 C). Analysis 
of the medium from LECs revealed secretion of full-length 
450-kD Reelin polypeptide that was partially processed by 
cleavage within the C terminus (Fig. 3 B; Jossin et al., 2007) to 
give rise to a smaller fragment of 370 kD (Fig. 3 D). When 
LECs were co-cultured with SMCs, secretion of full-length 
Reelin into the medium was increased, with a corresponding 
increase in the production of the 370-kD fragment, whereas the 
production of Reelin was not affected (Fig. 3, D and E). In 
addition, a second processing event in the N terminus resulted 
in the formation of a 180-kD fragment (Fig. 3, B and 3D) and a 
central Reelin fragment, which is capable of binding and activa-
tion of the canonical Reelin receptors ApoER2 and VLDLR 
(Jossin et al., 2007). Incubation of supernatant from LECs with 
SMCs confirmed that SMCs can mediate the second N-terminal 
processing event (Fig. 3 F). No increase in Reelin secretion or 
processing was observed when LECs were cultured in the con-
ditioned medium collected from the SMCs, or on extracellular 
matrices produced by fibroblasts (unpublished data), which 
suggests that the effect was not mediated by an SMC-derived 
secreted protein. Together, these results demonstrate that SMC </p>

<p>Figure 3. Reelin secretion and process-
ing is stimulated by SMC contact. (A) qPCR 
analysis showing relative RELN expression 
in three independent samples of LEC, BEC, 
and HUVSMC and two samples of HAoSMC. 
Mean ± SEM is plotted (error bars). (B) Schematic 
of Reelin structure, showing antibody binding 
sites (asterisks), cleavage sites, and products. 
The arrows and arrowheads indicate poly-
peptides that are visualized in Western blot-
ting: arrow, full-length protein; arrowhead, 
C-terminally cleaved polypeptide; open arrow-
head, N-and C-terminally cleaved polypeptide. 
Adapted from Jossin et al. (2007). (C and D) 
Analysis of whole-cell lysate (C) and medium 
(D) of LEC and SMC cultured either alone or 
together by immunoprecipitation and Western 
blotting with antibodies to Reelin. The arrows 
indicates full-length Reelin, arrowheads indi-
cate cleavage products. Analysis of whole cell 
lysate in C by Western blotting with antibod-
ies to CD31/PECAM-1 (for LEC) and -SMA 
(for SMC) show that equivalent numbers of 
cells were used. (E) Quantification of Reelin 
protein levels, normalized to CD31/PECAM-1, 
in whole cell lysate (black bars) and culture 
medium (gray bars). Data represent mean 
(n = 3) ± SEM (error bars). (F) Analysis of 
LEC-conditioned medium alone or after in-
cubation with SMC. Note the cleavage pro-
duct of 180 kD only in the presence of SMC 
(open arrowhead). </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 197 • NUMBER 6 • 2012 </p>

<p>
formation of luminal valves (Fig. S2, G-H; and Fig. 4, H and I); 
however, deposition of SMC-derived Laminin-5 was strongly 
decreased (Fig. S2, I-J). In addition, Reln mutants displayed 
irregular lymphatic vessel diameter, with abnormal constrictions 
and swellings (Fig. 4, B and K). These defects were not secondary 
to nervous system defects because normal patterning of the nerves 
was found in Reln mutant ears (Fig. S2, C and D). In contrast to 
the dermal collecting lymphatic vessels, the large collecting ves-
sels of the mesentery appeared normal in Reln-deficient mice, as 
indicated by normal morphology and SMC coverage (Fig. S3). In 
summary, these data show that Reln deficiency leads to specific 
defects in dermal collecting lymphatic vessel formation. </p>

<p>mice (Fig. S2, A and B). To allow unambiguous distinction of 
collecting vessels, we traced the entire vessel from the proximal to 
the distal end of the ear. In comparison to LYVE-1-negative col-
lecting vessels in wild-type mice, Reln mutant vessels maintained 
an abnormally high level of LYVE-1 (Fig. 4, A-C; and Fig. S2, 
E and F). In addition, Reln mutants showed reduced SMC cover-
age when compared with wild-type vessels (Fig. 4, D-G and J). 
Although a similar proximal-to-distal decrease was observed, in 
each vessel quarter the SMC coverage was significantly lower in 
Reln mutant compared with the wild type (Fig. 4 J). The early 
differentiation of dermal collecting vessels appeared normal 
in Reln mutants, as indicated by deposition of Collagen IV and </p>

<p>Figure 4. Reduced SMC coverage and defective collecting lymphatic vessel differentiation in Reln-deficient mice. (A, B, and D-I) Immunofluorescence 
of ear skin from wild-type (A, D, F, and H) and Reln 
/ (B, E, G, and I) mice for the indicated proteins. For A and B, individual images (projections of 
confocal z stacks) were aligned to trace the entire collecting vessel from the proximal (Q1) to distal (Q4) end, and the overlapping blood vasculature 
was blacked out for clarity (original images are shown in Fig. S2). Broken lines outline the collecting vessels. (C) LYVE-1 immunoreactivity in wild-type 
and Reln 
/ vessels (mean ± SEM [error bars]; n = 6 vessels). (J) SMC coverage in vessel quarters (mean ± SEM; n ≥ 12 vessels). (K) Quantification of 
widest and narrowest vessel points and the difference between the two (n ≥ 12 vessels). The boxes represent interquartile range, lines indicate mean, and 
whiskers indicate minimum and maximum values. *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01; ***, P &lt; 0.005. Bars: (A and B) 200 µm; (D-I) 50 µm. </p>

<p> 
Reelin in lymphatic development • Lutter et al. </p>

<p>"leakiness" (Scallan and Huxley, 2010). To further assess the 
potential impairment of lymphatic function, we used the Evans 
blue method to allow quantitative measurement of dye content 
of the inguinal lymph nodes after hind limb footpad injection. 
Control mice showed significantly more dye in the lymph nodes 
when compared with the Reln 
/ mice (Fig. 5 E). In addition, 
we performed real-time imaging of the uptake of indocyanine 
green (ICG) dye by lymphatic vessels by measuring the increase 
in the fluorescent signal in the vessel over time after injection 
of the dye into the hind limb footpad. Abnormal dye uptake was 
observed in the Reln mutant mice compared with their control 
littermates (Fig. 5 F). All except one Reln-deficient mouse dis-
played reduction in the rate of lymphatic flow, whereas one 
showed an abnormally fast dye uptake. In control littermates, 
the dye reached the inguinal lymph nodes within seconds 
(Fig. 5 G and Fig. S4 A). In contrast, in most Reln mutants, 
no ICG dye was detectable in the lymph nodes at the end of 
5 min of imaging (Fig. 5 G and Fig. S4 B). In spite of impaired 
lymphatic function, no apparent edema or ascites formation 
could be observed in the mutant mice (unpublished data). </p>

<p>Impaired lymphatic vessel function </p>

<p>in Reelin mutant mice </p>

<p>To assess if the observed morphological defects affect lymphatic 
function in Reln mutants, we investigated the uptake and trans-
port of large-molecular-weight fluorescent dextran-injected 
intradermally in the ear. In wild-type mice, the dye was quickly 
taken up into the vessels surrounding the injection site (Fig. 5 A). 
However, except for in the immediate vicinity of the injec-
tion site, dye was rarely seen in LYVE-1-positive capillaries, 
whereas the collecting vessels were strongly positive (Fig. 5 B). 
In contrast, in Reln 
/ mice we frequently observed no dye 
in vessels near the injection site (Fig. 5 C), which suggests 
impaired lymphatic function. When dye was taken up, it was 
retained in LYVE-1-positive vessels (Fig. 5 D). We also ob-
served dye at the vessel edges in the mutant ear (Fig. 5 D), 
which may be indicative of dye leakage from the vessel and re-
tention within the BM, further suggesting functional deficiency in 
the collecting vessels of these mice. It is possible that discontin-
uous coverage of SMC around collecting lymphatic vessels may 
aid solute exchange and therefore increase collecting vessel </p>

<p>Figure 5. Functional impairment in Reln 
/ collecting lymphatic vessels. (A-D) P21 wild-type (A and B) and Reln 
/ (C and D) ear skin, injected with FITC-
dextran (green) and costained with antibodies against -SMA (red; A and C) and LYVE-1 (blue, A and C; and red, B and D). The broken line in A and C 
indicates the injection site, and arrows point to adjacent lymphatic vessels. Arrows in B and D point to LYVE-1-positive capillaries, and the arrowhead in 
B indicates an LYVE-1-negative collecting vessel filled with FITC-dextran. The broken line in B outlines the collecting vessel and its connection to LYVE-1 
+ cap-
illaries (not outlined). (E) Quantification of Evans blue dye content in inguinal lymph nodes of control and Reln 
/ mice after 5 min of injection into the hind 
limb footpad. Values from individual lymph nodes and mean values are plotted (error bars; n = 11 [Ctrl] and 6 [Reln </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>] mice). (F) Efficiency of fluorescent 
signal, representing efficiency of lymphatic flow, in a defined region of a vessel after ICG injection into the hind limb footpad over time. (G) Representative 
images of control and Reln 
/ hind limbs after ICG dye injections at three time points (excluding a 6-8-s delay before recording was started). In control 
but not in Reln 
/ mice, the dye reached the inguinal lymph node (asterisks). Bars: (A-D) 100 µm; (G) 0.5 cm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 197 • NUMBER 6 • 2012 </p>

<p>
lymphatic vessels have been largely ignored, yet they are 
likely important because of the distinct functions of lymphatic 
capillaries and collecting vessels in mediating fluid absorbance 
and transport, respectively (Jurisic and Detmar, 2009; Tammela  and Alitalo, 2010). In this study, we identify Reelin as the first 
lymphatic specific ECM protein and demonstrate its important 
function in the formation of functional collecting vessels. 
Reelin is a large glycoprotein previously implicated in the 
development of the nervous system. Our analyses revealed that 
Reelin is additionally widely expressed in the lymphatic vascu-
lature, both during development and in adult tissues. Although 
Reelin was produced by LEC in both the capillaries and collect-
ing vessels, only the latter showed efficient secretion. Consistent 
with this, Reln-deficient mice had normal lymphatic capillaries 
but exhibited specific dermal collecting vessel defects, character-
ized by reduced SMC coverage and high expression of lym-
phatic capillary marker LYVE-1. Interestingly, SMCs were 
frequently found in direct contact with LYVE-1 
+ LECs in the 
mutant but not in wild-type vessels. Notably, however, the larg-
est collecting vessels, such as mesenteric lymphatic vessels that 
acquire more elaborate and continuous smooth muscle cover-
age, were apparently normal in Reln mutants, which suggests 
that there are different requirements for the formation of vessels 
of different calibers. We also noted a difference in the initiation 
of collecting vessel maturation in these two tissues. Although 
the developing dermal collecting vessels underwent a gradual 
increase in SMC coverage and concomitant decrease in LYVE-1 
expression in a proximal-to-distal direction over a period of 
several days, the mesenteric lymphatic vessels rapidly acquired 
SMCs along their entire length, which was only later followed 
by down-regulation of LYVE-1 expression. These observations 
further suggest that the mechanisms regulating collecting vessel 
formation may differ depending on the caliber of the vessel and 
tissue environment. 
Previous data on various mouse models lacking key com-
ponents required for mural cell (MC) recruitment attest to their 
importance in the formation and maintenance of functional 
blood vessels (Hellström et al., 2001). However, because of 
embryonic lethality, none of the MC-deficient mice described 
so far have allowed the investigation of the importance of lym-
phatic SMC in vivo. Our study describes for the first time a 
mouse model that shows a lymphatic-specific deficiency in 
SMCs, which occur in the absence of blood vascular or other 
major lymphatic defects. Concurrent with reduced SMC cover-
age, the Reln-deficient collecting vessels were enlarged and 
displayed irregular vessel diameters. Such defects are consis-
tent with phenotypes described for pericyte-deficient blood 
vessels (Hellström et al., 2001), which suggests that lymphatic 
SMC may have similar roles in the maintenance of vessel stabil-
ity to those of the blood vascular system. However, important 
functional differences between lymphatic and blood vascular 
SMC exist. Although blood flow is generated by the beating 
heart and the vascular SMCs are involved in regulating vascular 
tone, the lymphatic vessels themselves must generate the force 
required for lymph propulsion (for review see von der Weid  and Zawieja, 2004). This action is dependent on lymphatic 
SMCs, which, unlike the vascular SMCs, are able to undergo </p>

<p>Reelin induces production of SMC </p>

<p>recruitment factor MCP-1 in LECs </p>

<p>via a noncanonical signaling pathway </p>

<p>In the nervous system, Reelin mediates its functions via two 
members of the low-density lipoprotein receptor family, VLDLR 
and ApoER2 (Trommsdorff et al., 1999). Both receptors were 
expressed in cultured primary SMCs and LECs (Fig. S5 A). 
In addition, VLDLR was expressed in lymphatic endothelia 
in vivo (Fig. S5, B-C). This suggests that either cell type-LEC 
or SMC-could therefore respond to Reelin to regulate SMC 
recruitment during collecting vessel formation. However, 
although LEC-conditioned medium promoted SMC migration 
in a transwell assay, this was not affected by a function-blocking 
antibody to Reelin (Fig. 5 E and S5 D). Furthermore, Reelin 
did not stimulate migration of SMCs (Fig. S5 D), which sug-
gests that Reelin is not the LEC-derived factor responsible 
for SMC recruitment. We therefore tested a possibility that 
Reelin acts in an autocrine fashion in LECs to induce produc-
tion of SMC recruitment factors. Indeed, we found a transient 
increase in the expression of MCP1/CCR2, a known regula-
tor of SMC recruitment and migration (Fig. S5 D; Religa et al.,  2005; Ma et al., 2008; Aplin et al., 2010), in LECs upon Reelin 
stimulation (Fig. 6, A and B), whereas the expression of four 
other genes implicated in SMC recruitment was not affected 
(Fig. 6, A and B). Increased Angiopoietin-2 expression that 
was induced similarly by control and full-length Reelin con-
taining 293 supernatant was likely caused by a high level 
of VEGF produced by these cells (Kärpänen et al., 2006), 
which has previously been shown to stimulate Ang-2 expres-
sion in LECs (Veikkola et al., 2003). Notably, MCP1 expres-
sion showed only a modest increase upon stimulation with 
the central Reelin fragment (Fig. 6 A), which suggests that 
the canonical Reelin signaling pathway was not responsible 
for this effect. In agreement, analysis of Vldlr and Apoer2 double 
mutant mice revealed normal lymphatic vasculature (Figs. 5 G;  Fig. 6, C and D; and Fig. S5 F). In addition, mouse mutants 
lacking Dab1, an intracellular adaptor molecule activated in re-
sponse to Reelin signaling, showed normal lymphatic vessels 
(Fig. 6 E and Fig. S5 H). All parameters measured were normal 
(Fig. 6, F-H), with the exception that the Vldlr 
/ ;Apoer2 </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>vessels showed a modest decrease in SMC coverage in the distal-
most quarter (Fig. 6 F). In addition, lymphatic function was 
not impaired in these mice (Fig. S5 I). In summary, these re-
sults suggest that Reelin acts in an autocrine fashion in the 
LECs to regulate SMC recruitment and collecting vessel 
differentiation (Fig. 7). Interestingly, unlike in the nervous 
system, the canonical signaling pathway is not required for 
Reelin signaling in lymphatic vessels, which suggests the in-
volvement of alternative receptors. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Although proteins of the vascular BM are known to play diverse 
and essential roles in the maintenance of both the structural 
and biological function of the vessel, the composition and 
function of the lymphatic BM remains poorly characterized. Fur-
thermore, differences in the BM surrounding different types of </p>

<p> 
Reelin in lymphatic development • Lutter et al. </p>

<p>reach their destination at the marginal zone of the cortex, Ree-
lin acts as a stop signal by inducing neuronal detachment from 
radial glial scaffold and stabilization of the cytoskeleton (Hartfuss  et al., 2003; Chai et al., 2009; Zhao and Frotscher, 2010). These 
opposite functions of Reelin may be explained, at least in part, 
by binding and activation of different receptors: VLDLR and 
ApoER2 (Hack et al., 2007). Proteolytic processing by matrix 
metalloproteinases may also play an important role in regulating 
diffusion and receptor-binding properties of Reelin (Lambert de  Rouvroit et al., 1999; Jossin et al., 2007; Tinnes et al., 2011). 
Although the central part of Reelin binds VLDLR and ApoER2, 
the N-terminal region mediates protein aggregation and has been 
suggested to regulate signaling by anchoring the protein to the </p>

<p>both tonic and phasic contractions (Wang et al., 2009). The 
impaired lymphatic function may imply that, in addition to 
the observed morphological abnormalities, Reln deficiency can 
directly affect SMC contractility and lymph pumping. These find-
ings may have clinical significance, as congenital lymphedema 
has been observed in some human patients carrying mutations 
in the RELN gene (Hong et al., 2000). 
In spite of intense studies during the past decade, the exact 
cellular function of Reelin has remained unclear. In early cortico-
genesis, Reelin stimulates neuronal migration by attracting lead-
ing processes and inducing their branching and attachment to the 
ECM (Ogawa et al., 1995; Tissir and Goffinet, 2003; Franco et al.,  2011). In contrast, at later stages, when the migrating neurons </p>

<p>Figure 6. LECs respond to Reelin via noncanonical signaling pathway. (A and B) Fold change in expression of SMC recruitment genes after Reelin stimula-
tion. Note the strong increase in MCP1 expression at 4 and 8 h in cells stimulated with full-length Reelin containing supernatant from HEK 293 cells only. 
The mean ± SEM of three experiments is plotted (error bars). *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.001. (C-E) Immunofluorescence staining of P21 ear skin from wild-type 
(C), Apoer2 </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>;Vldlr 
/ (D), and Dab1 
Scm (E) mice using LYVE-1 (green), -SMA (red), and Podoplanin (blue) antibodies. Individual images were aligned 
to trace the vessel from the proximal to the distal end, and overlapping blood vasculature was blacked out for clarity. A segment from the middle section of 
each vessel is displayed (original images are shown in Fig. S5). (F) SMC coverage in vessel quarters (mean ± SEM [error bars]; n ≥ 6 vessels per genotype). 
*, P = 0.04. (G) Quantification of the widest and narrowest vessel points and the difference between the two. Boxes represents interquartile range, lines 
indicates mean, and whiskers indicate minimum and maximum values. (H) LYVE-1 immunoreactivity in collecting vessels (mean ± SEM [error bars]; n ≥ 6 
vessels). All differences in F-H were nonsignificant, except where indicated. Bars, 200 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 197 • NUMBER 6 • 2012 </p>

<p>
Normal lymphatic development in Apoer2;Vldlr double mutant 
mice, which display an identical neurological phenotype com-
pared with Reln mutants (Trommsdorff et al., 1999), further 
indicates that the collecting vessel defects in Reln-deficient 
mice are not secondary to nervous system defects or the failure 
of these mice to gain weight, but instead suggests involvement 
of alternative Reelin receptors. 
In summary, we have demonstrated an unexpected 
function of Reelin in regulating the formation of functional 
larger-caliber lymphatic vessels. Our results have uncovered 
a mechanism by which a specific signaling pathway is activated 
by communication between the two cell types of lymphatic 
vessels-EC and SMC-and demonstrate for the first time 
that SMCs play an important role in regulating lymphatic 
morphogenesis and function. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Antibodies 
The antibodies used for immunofluorescence were rat antibodies to mouse 
platelet EC adhesion molecule 1 (PECAM-1; MEC3.1, BD); rabbit anti-
bodies to mouse Laminin-5 (provided by L. Sorokin, University of Münster, 
Münster, Germany; Ringelmann et al., 1999), Desmin (Abcam), Collagen IV 
(AbD Serotec), GFP (Invitrogen), LYVE-1 (ReliaTech), Erp57 (Abcam), and 
Golph4 (Abcam); rabbit antibody to human Efemp1 (Abcam); hamster 
antibodies to mouse PECAM-1 (Millipore) and Podoplanin (Developmental 
Studies Hybridoma Bank); goat antibodies to mouse Integrin-9, Reelin, 
and VLDLR (all from R&amp;D Systems); mouse antibody to mouse acetylated 
-tubulin (Abcam; used in conjunction with mouse-on-mouse blocking 
reagents [Vector Laboratories]); and Cy3-conjugated mouse antibody 
against -SMA (Sigma-Aldrich). Secondary antibodies conjugated to Cy2, 
Cy3, or Cy5 were obtained from Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories, 
Inc. Antibodies used for Western blot analysis were rabbit antibodies 
to human Efemp1 (Abcam), Nidogen2 (Immundiagnostik), and Spock3 
(Abcam), and mouse antibody to human -tubulin (Sigma-Aldrich). </p>

<p>Mice 
Reeler (Reln </p>

<p>rl </p>

<p>) and Dab1 
scm (A/A-Dab1 </p>

<p>scm </p>

<p>/J) mice were obtained from The 
Jackson Laboratory. Apoer2 </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>;Vldlr 
/ mice were obtained by cross-
breeding of mice lacking Apoer2 or Vldlr, which carry an insertion of a 
Neomycin cassette to replace exons 17 and 18, or into exon 5, leading to 
deletion of part of the coding sequence and disruption of the reading </p>

<p>ECM (Utsunomiya-Tate et al., 2000; Kubo et al., 2002; Zhao  and Frotscher, 2010). Because the cleavage products generated 
in LEC/SMC cultures were identical to those documented in 
the nervous system (Jossin et al., 2007), the same mechanism of 
processing is likely. However, although functionally important 
(Jossin et al., 2007), it is unclear how the processing is regu-
lated in vivo and whether the individual cleavage products have 
specific, or even opposite functions. Interestingly, mechanisms 
where proteolytic processing produces protein fragments that 
exhibit opposing effects on angiogenesis to those of the parental 
molecule have been described for a subclass of vascular ECM 
proteins (for review see Kalluri, 2003). 
In the developing nervous system, Reelin is produced 
mainly by Cajal-Retzius neurons in the cortex, where it instructs 
newly born neurons to assume their position and orientation 
(D'Arcangelo et al., 1995; Tissir and Goffinet, 2003). During 
this process, the neurons are intimately apposed to radial glial 
cells that form a scaffold along which the neuroblasts migrate, 
and both cell types rely on Reelin signaling to direct correct 
patterning of the cortex (Hartfuss et al., 2003; Tissir and Goffinet,  2003; Keilani and Sugaya, 2008; Zhao and Frotscher, 2010). 
In the lymphatic system, we found that Reelin was produced 
exclusively by ECs, while its release and proteolytic processing 
was stimulated by the adjacent SMCs. This suggests a mechanism 
by which Reelin signaling is activated via communication 
of the two cell types that form the collecting vessels. We 
further found that LECs, in turn, respond to Reelin by up-
regulating the expression of monocyte chemotactic protein 1 
(MCP1), a factor known to promote SMC migration and prolif-
eration (Religa et al., 2005; Ma et al., 2008; Aplin et al., 2010). 
This suggests an autocrine function of Reelin in the LECs in 
controlling the expression of factors involved in SMC recruit-
ment. Interestingly, although the canonical Reelin receptors 
VLDLR and ApoER2 were expressed in the lymphatic vascu-
lature, Apoer2;Vldlr double mutant mice did not recapitulate 
the phenotype observed in Reln-deficient lymphatic vessels. </p>

<p>Figure 7. Model of Reelin signaling during collecting lymphatic vessel formation. Reelin (red stars) is produced by LEC (gray cells). Upon SMC (blue cell) 
contact, Reelin is secreted from LEC (red cells) and cleaved to release diffusible fragments (red gradient). Reelin can stimulate expression of MCP1 in LECs 
to enhance further SMC recruitment. </p>

<p> 
Reelin in lymphatic development • Lutter et al. </p>

<p>littermate controls (n = 3 per each genotype, two vessels per mouse). 
The images were aligned and processed using <rs id="software-5" type="software">Photoshop</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">CS4</rs> or CS5 
(<rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">Adobe</rs>). Thresholding and quantification of the whole-vessel images 
were performed using MetaMorph Imaging software (Molecular Devices). 
An inclusive threshold was applied to the -SMA channel so that the 
background was captured by, while all SMC were excluded from, the 
threshold. The length of the vessel was measured and divided into quar-
ters. A region was drawn around each vessel segment, excluding over-
lapping blood vessels. The SMC coverage was calculated and 
subtracted from 100%. A similar thresholding technique was used to 
quantify the percentage of LVYE-1 immunofluorescence. The line tool in 
MetaMorph was used to measure the width of the widest and narrowest 
vessel points. </p>

<p>Analysis of lymphatic vessel function 
For qualitative analysis of lymphatic vessel function, FITC-dextran (8 mg/ml 
in PBS; Sigma-Aldrich) was injected intradermally into the ears of anaes-
thetized mice and analyzed by confocal microscopy. For quantitative 
analysis, 2 µl of ICG dye (1% in dH 2 O; Sigma-Aldrich) was injected into 
the footpads of anaesthetized mice inside the IVIS Spectrum Whole Body 
Imaging System (Caliper Life Sciences). Image acquisition and analysis 
was performed with <rs id="software-7" type="software">Living Image</rs> <rs corresp="#software-7" type="version-number">3</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-7" type="creator">Caliper Life Sciences</rs>) using 
the following parameters: field of view 6.6, binning 8, and F-stop 2. 
70 images were taken with a 2-s exposure time and no delay between 
acquisitions, which resulted in an image every 3-4 s. The efficiency of 
the fluorescent signal was measured in a region of interest (ROI) created 
around a small area of the lymphatic vessel above the knee. The mean 
efficiency against time was plotted using <rs id="software-8" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-number">5</rs> software, using 4 s as 
an interval. For the quantitative Evans blue assay, 2 µl Evan's blue dye 
(2%; Sigma-Aldrich) was injected into the hind limb footpad. After 5 min, 
the mice were sacrificed and inguinal lymph nodes were dissected. Both 
inguinal lymph nodes were weighed together and a mean value was used 
to calculate dye content in each of them separately. Each lymph node was 
placed in 5 µl formamide at 60°C for 24 h, followed by an absorbance 
reading at 620 nm. Evans blue concentration was calculated using a stan-
dard curve and presented as dye content per gram of tissue. </p>

<p>Cell culture 
Human LECs, isolated from primary dermal microvascular EC cultures (Promo-
Cell; Mäkinen et al., 2001), human umbilical venous SMCs (HUVSMCs; 
TCS Cellworks), and aortic SMCs (PromoCell) were cultured in endothelial 
or SMC growth medium (Promocell). For co-culture experiments, LEC were 
plated on fibronectin-coated plates at 50% confluency in IgG-stripped EC 
growth medium 4 h before an equal number of HUVSMC were added to 
the culture. Medium was collected and the cells were lysed 2 d after 
plating. Supernatant from HEK 293 cells transfected with pCrL (full-length 
mouse Reelin cDNA; a gift from Tom Curran, Joseph Stokes Jr. Research 
Institute, The Children's Hospital of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, PA) and 
untransfected control cells was concentrated 25× using an Amicon ultra-15 
centrifugal filter unit (Sigma-Aldrich) and used for stimulation of LEC or 
SMC at dilution 1:20. </p>

<p>Reelin stimulation 
LEC were starved overnight in serum-free EC growth medium, then sup-
plemented with 0.2% BSA, hEGF-5, and HC-500, followed by stimulation 
with full-length Reelin supernatant from HEK 293 cells (diluted 1:20), 
control supernatant (diluted 1:20), or recombinant central Reelin fragment 
(R&amp;D Systems) for 4, 8, or 24 h. RNA was extracted using RNeasy Mini kit 
(QIAGEN) according to the manufacturer's instructions and used for qPCR 
analysis using the following Taqman probes (Applied Biosystems): PDGFB, 
Hs00966522_m1; ANGPT2, Hs01048042_m1; TGF1, Hs00998133_m1; 
HBEGF, Hs00181813_m1; and CCL2/MCP-1, Hs00234140_m1 and 
GAPDH; Hs99999905_m1. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis 
Cell growth medium was collected and clarified by centrifugation, and the 
cells were lysed in Triton X-100 lysis buffer (50 mM Tris, pH 7.5, 120 mM 
NaCl, 10% glycerol, 1% Triton X-100) supplemented with Complete Pro-
tease inhibitors (Roche). Cell lysate and growth medium were subjected to 
immunoprecipitation and/or Western blot analysis using mouse antibodies 
against human Reelin (EMD) and PECAM-1 (Dako), or Cy3-conjugated 
mouse anti--SMA (Sigma-Aldrich). Quantification was performed using 
ImageJ, and the ratio of Reelin in the lysate and medium, normalized to 
CD31/PECAM-1, was calculated for LEC/SMC co-culture relative to LEC 
cultured alone. </p>

<p>frame, respectively (Frykman et al., 1995; Trommsdorff et al., 1999). Both 
lines were provided by J. Herz (University of Texas Southwestern Medical 
Center, Austin, TX). Vegfr3 
lz mice in which the first coding exon of Vegfr3 
gene was replaced by a lacZ cassette were provided by K. Alitalo (University 
of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland). The mice were maintained on C57BL/6J 
background except for Dab1 </p>

<p>scm </p>

<p>, which were on C3HeB/FeJ* DC/Le back-
ground. All three mutant strains lacking components of the Reelin signaling 
pathway exhibited an ataxic gait and tremors starting around two weeks 
of age. In addition, homozygous Reeler and Apoer2 </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>;Vldlr 
/ mutant 
mice, but not Dab1 
scm mutants, were smaller in size, weighing 50-60% 
of the weight of the littermate controls at three weeks of age when most 
analyses were done. All mouse experiments were approved by the UK 
Home Office. </p>

<p>Microarray analysis 
To identify lymphatic-specific ECM molecules, mesenteric arteries, veins, 
and lymphatic vessels were dissected from P7 wild-type (C57BL/6J) pups. 
Samples from nine animals (in two litters) were pooled. Total RNA was 
extracted and RNase-treated using an RNeasy Micro kit (QIAGEN) as per 
the manufacturer's instructions. 100 ng of RNA from two independent sam-
ples of each vessel was amplified using WT-Ovation Pico RNA Amplifica-
tion System (NuGEN) and used for expression profiling using the Mouse 
exon 1.0 ST Array (Affymetrix), according to the manufacturer's instruc-
tions. The array data were processed using robust multiarray analysis 
(Irizarry et al., 2003) to generate gene-level signal estimates for core level 
probe sets. The arrays were normalized using quantile normalization and 
antigenomic probes used to model the background. Quantification was run 
using apt-1.10.0 from Affymetrix. Before statistical analysis, all Affymetrix 
control probe sets were removed. Gene changes were selected using a 
linear model where the standard errors were corrected using empirical 
Bayes shrinkage (fdr &lt; 0.05). To identify lymphatic-specific transcriptional 
changes, we applied a nestedF procedure across the three contrasts, selecting 
genes significant in only the lymphatic groups (fdr &lt; 0.05). Analysis 
was performed in Bioconductor (Gentleman et al., 2004) using <rs type="software">Limma</rs>. 
Genes that were expressed at least twofold higher in different vessel types 
were searched in Uniprot database to identify proteins involved in ECM 
function or structure. </p>

<p>Immunostaining and X-Gal staining 
For whole-mount immunostaining, tissue was fixed in 4% paraformalde-
hyde, permeabilized in 0.3% Triton X-100 in PBS, and blocked in PBST 
plus 3% milk. Primary antibodies were incubated at 4°C overnight in 
blocking buffer. After washing in PBSTx, the samples were incubated with 
fluorescence-conjugated secondary antibodies in blocking PBSTx plus 1% 
milk before further washing and mounting in Mowiol. Reelin staining in 
Figs. S1 (E-F) and Fig. 2 (F-G), and VLDLR staining in Fig. S5 (B-C) were 
amplified using the TSA Fluorescein Tyramide Reagent Pack (PerkinElmer). 
For VLDLR staining (Fig. S5, B-C), goat anti-mouse VLDLR antibody 
(R&amp;D Systems) was pre-absorbed with a Vldlr 
/ ear in TNB buffer (0.1 M 
Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 0.15 M NaCl, and 0.5% blocking buffer [supplied in kit]) 
overnight before resuming normal amplification and staining protocol with 
a wild-type or mutant ear, as detailed above. Immunostaining for Fig. 2 (F-G) 
was performed in the absence of Triton X-100. Staining for -galactosidase 
activity in the lymphatic vessels in Vegfr3 
lz mice was done using the sub-
strate X-Gal (5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indolyl--d-galactopyranoside), and the 
images were acquired with a stereomicroscope (MZ16F) equipped with 
camera (DFC420C) and Microsystems software (all from Leica). </p>

<p>Image acquisition and quantitative analyses 
Confocal images for Figs. 2 (B and C), 3 (G and H), 6 (C-E), S3 (A-D), 
and S5 (F-H), were acquired at room temperature using a confocal micro-
scope (LSM 710; Zeiss Imager.Z2 and Zen 2009 software; Carl Zeiss) 
with a Plan-Apochromat 20×/0.8 NA air objective lens (Fig. 6, C-E; and  Fig. S5, F-H) or DIC Plan-Apochromat 40×/1.3 NA water immersion 
objective lens (Fig. 2, B and C; Fig. 3, G and H; and Fig. S3, A-D). All other 
confocal images were acquired using an LSM 510 microscope (Axioplan 2 
and LSM 510 version 3.2 software; all from Carl Zeiss), with Plan-Apochromat 
10×/0.45 NA (Fig. S2, A-D) or 20×/0.75 NA (Fig. 4, A and B; and Fig. 
S2, E and F) air objective lenses, or Korr C-Apochromat 63×/1.2 NA 
(Fig. S1, G and H) or 40×/1.2 NA (all other images) water immersion 
objective lenses. All confocal images, except Fig. S1 (G and H), repre-
sent maximum projection images of confocal z stacks. For visualization of 
collecting vessels from the proximal to distal end of the ear, images were 
captured along the length of three randomly chosen collecting lymphatic 
vessels from Reln 
/ (n = 5) and wild-type (n = 4) mice. The same analysis 
was performed for Apoer2 
/ ;Vldlr 
/ , Dab1 
Scm , and their respective </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 197 • NUMBER 6 • 2012 </p>



<p>
Transwell migration assay 
Migration assay was performed using 6.5-mm Transwell with 8 µm poly-
carbonate membrane inserts (Corning) in a 24-well plate. The lower face 
of the membrane was coated with 1 µg/ml fibronectin (Sigma-Aldrich) 
before use. Confluent HUVSMC were serum-deprived in SMC growth 
medium containing 0.2% BSA for 22 h. 1 × 10 
5 cells were seeded in 
the upper chamber and allowed to migrate toward EC growth medium 
(control) or conditioned medium collected from LECs over a 48-h period, 
full-length Reelin supernatant from HEK 293 cells (diluted 1:20), control 
supernatant (diluted 1:20), 10 ng/ml MCP-1 (R&amp;D Systems), or 3 ng/ml 
PDGF-BB (R&amp;D Systems) over a 23-h period. Reelin function was inhibited 
using blocking antibody against Reelin (CR-50, 50 µg/ml; MBL). Cells 
on the upper face of the membrane were removed and migrated cells on 
the lower face were fixed and stained with 0.5% crystal violet solution 
in 25% methanol. Images of the filters were acquired with a stereomicro-
scope (MZ16 F) equipped with a camera (DFC420C) and <rs id="software-9" type="software">Microsystems</rs> 
software (all from <rs corresp="#software-9" type="creator">Leica</rs>). After photographing, the incorporated dye was 
solubilized in 0.2 ml sodium citrate solution, followed by absorbance 
reading at 550 nm. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
P-values were calculated using unpaired two-tailed Student's t tests. </p>

<p>Online supplemental material 
Fig. S1 shows the identification of extracellular matrix-associated proteins 
that are preferentially expressed in lymphatic vessels. Fig. S2 shows the 
characterization of Reeler phenotype in the skin. Fig. S3 shows the char-
acterization of Reeler phenotype in the mesentery. Fig. S4 shows real-time 
imaging of lymphatic function in 3-wk-old control and Reln-deficient mice. 
Fig. S5 shows the involvement of Reelin signaling pathway components in 
lymphatic development and the effect of Reelin on SMC migration. Table S1 
presents the validation of microarray data for known markers of lymphatic 
vessels, arteries, and veins. Table S2 shows genes associated with extra-
cellular matrix that were differentially expressed in lymphatic and blood 
vessels. Table S3 shows the full dataset that was used for the validation of 
microarray hits. Online supplemental material is available at http://www 
.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201110132/DC1. </p>

<p>We thank Joachim Herz for Apoer2 and Vldlr mice, Michael Frotscher and 
Hans Bock for sending these mice to us, Kari Alitalo for Vegfr3 
lz mice, Lydia 
Sorokin for Laminin-5 antibodies, and Tom Curran for the pCrl plasmid. We 
thank the CRUK GeneChip Service Facility at Cancer Research UK Paterson 
Institute for performing the microarray experiments, Phil East for analysis of mi-
croarray data, Francois Lassailly for help with whole-body imaging, and the 
animal unit staff at the London Research Institute for animal husbandry. 
This work was supported by Cancer Research UK (S. Lutter, S. Xie, 
F. Tatin, and T. Makinen) and EMBO Young Investigator Program (T. Makinen). </p>

<p>Submitted: 31 October 2011 
Accepted: 2 May 2012 </p>



<p> 
Reelin in lymphatic development • Lutter et al. </p>



</text></tei>