<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3819448" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Lee W, et al. 
Weissella confusa bacteremia </p>



<p>www.annlabmed.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3343/alm.2013.33.6.459 </p>

<p>ance mass spectrometer (Shimadzu Corporation, Kyoto, Japan) 
and analyzed with the VITEK MS IVD v1 database (bioMérieux 
Inc.). The strain was identified as W. confusa, which has a simi-
lar biochemical profile to that of Leuconostoc [1], with a confi-
dence value of 99.9%. In addition, we performed 16S rRNA 
gene sequencing of a PCR product sized about 1.5 kb by using 
the universal primers 8F (5'-AGA GTT TGA TCC TGG CTC AG-3') 
and 1541R (5'-AAG GAG GTG ATC CAG CCG CA-3') and com-
pared the obtained sequence with the EzTaxon database [9] and 
the bioinformatic bacterial identification database [10]. When the 
sequence was submitted to the ExTaxon database, the isolate re-
vealed 99.66% similarity (1,471/1,476 bp) with W. confusa. The 
next closest matches were W. cibaria, W. oryzae, W. viridescens, 
and W. paramesenteroides with similarities of 99.06% (1,480/ 
1,494 bp), 96.66% (1,417/1,466 bp), 96.28% (1,422/1,477 bp), </p>

<p>and 96.18% (1,434/1,491 bp), respectively. In the bioinformatic 
bacterial identification database search, the isolate exhibited 
99.66% similarity (1,467/1,472 bp) with W. confusa AB023241 
followed by W. confusa AB682449, W. confusa AB596944, W. 
cibaria AB682356, and W. cibaria AJ295989 with similarities of 
99.60% (1,485/1,491 bp), 99.60% (1,485/1,491 bp), 98.99% 
(1,476/1,491 bp), and 98.86% (1,474/1,491 bp), respectively. 
A phylogenetic tree, which was constructed with the neighbor-
joining method by using Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analy-
sis (<rs id="software-1" type="software">MEGA</rs>) software <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 5.05</rs> [11], revealed this isolate to be 
W. confusa (Fig. 3). 
Empirical therapy with ceftriaxone was initiated after blood 
culture submission. In spite of the treatment, fever persisted for 
3 days and the C-reactive protein level did not decrease. The 
ceftriaxone treatment was changed to teicoplanin plus piperacil-
lin-tazobactam after isolation of gram-positive coccobacilli from 
the blood culture. Fever and other symptoms subsided with the 
new regimen. All subsequent blood cultures were negative, and 
the patient was discharged on the 9th hospital day with an un-
eventful recovery. 
On the basis of the 16S rRNA gene sequence analysis, Leuco-
nostoc paramesenteroides and related species among the cata-
lase-negative, vancomycin-resistant, gram-positive cocci were 
reclassified into a new genus, Weissella, in 1993 [12]. There are 
16 species in the Weissella genus, but only W. confusa (previ-
ously Lactobacillus confusus) and W. cibaria have been isolated </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Small-sized α-hemolytic colonies of Weissella confusa on a 
sheep blood agar plate grown at 37°C with 5% CO2 after 24 hr of 
incubation. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Weissella confusa Gram stain morphology from a sheep 
blood agar plate ( × 1,000). </p>

<p>Weissella confusa AB596944 </p>

<p>Weissella confusa AB023241 
Weissella cibaria AB682356 
Weissella cibaria AJ295989 
Weissella oryzae AB690345 
Weissella paramesenteroides AB023238 
Weissella paramesenteroides FJ751790 
Weissella hellenica AB680902 
Weissella hellenica X95981 
Weissella paramesenteroides S67831 
Weissella soli AY028260 
Weissella minor AB022920 
Weissella viridescens AB023236 
Weissella ceti FN813251 
Weissella kandleri AB022922 
Weissella hanii AY040669 
Weissella koreensis AY035891 
99 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>95 </p>

<p>46 </p>

<p>93 </p>

<p>92 </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>87 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 Weissella confusa AB682449 
YMC-12-5-B1425 (case) </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Neighbor-joining phylogenetic tree based on 16S rRNA 
gene sequences of our Weissella confusa isolate and 18 similar or-
ganisms. Numbers at branch nodes are bootstrap values. The bar 
represents 0.5% sequence divergence. </p>

<p>Lee W, et al. 
Weissella confusa bacteremia </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3343/alm.2013.33.6.459 </p>

<p>www.annlabmed.org </p>

<p>from clinical specimens. While W. confusa infections are not 
common, a case of infectious endocarditis caused by W. confusa 
in Korea has been reported [5]. The characteristics of 10 bacte-
remia cases of W. confusa in Taiwan were reviewed [8]. Among 
the 43 isolates, which were identified as either Lactobacillus or 
Leuconostoc species using commercial identification systems, 
10 isolates were confirmed as W. confusa using 16S rRNA gene 
sequencing, and all affected patients had complex medical con-
ditions and/or an immunocompromised status. In additional re-
ports, W. confusa isolates could not be identified using conven-
tional identification systems except by 16S rRNA gene sequence 
analysis, and most patients were immunocompromised [2-4, 6]. 
When clinical isolates cannot be identified by using conven-
tional methods, 16S rRNA gene sequence analysis can be useful 
[13]. However, routine application of 16S rRNA gene sequencing 
has some limitations since it is relatively expensive and time-con-
suming. On the other hand, MALDI-TOF MS can identify bacteria 
within a few minutes using colonies grown on culture plates, and 
it can reduce the turnaround time and the cost of expendables 
[14]. During the past several years, there have been numerous 
reports demonstrating the accuracy and reliability of the MALDI-
TOF MS system [15-18]. 
In this case, gram-positive coccobacilli from the blood culture 
was initially suspected to be a Leuconostoc species due to its 
biochemical characteristics, i.e., vancomycin resistance and 
negative results with catalase, pyrrolidonyl-arylamidase, and leu-
cine aminopeptidase [1]. However, the isolate was identified as 
W. confusa using MALDI-TOF MS, which was confirmed by 16S 
rRNA gene sequence analysis. 
W. confusa is taxonomically very closely related to W. cibaria, 
but can be differentiated form W. cibaria because of differences 
in the biochemical characteristics, e.g., it is positive for fermen-
tation of galatose and xylose and negative for fermentation of 
arabinose [19]. However, both species cannot be differentiated 
by using the VITEK MS system alone because W. cibaria is not 
included in the VITEK MS IVD v1 database. Therefore, 16S 
rRNA gene sequence analysis and/or additional biochemical 
tests are needed for the accurate identification. 
In blood cultures, contaminations of normal skin flora occur 
often and include coagulase-negative staphylococci, Corynebac-
terium species, Propionibacterium acnes, Micrococcus species, 
and viridans group streptococci [20]. Unless the isolate grows in 
multiple blood culture sets, identification to the species level 
may not be warranted. Although the W. confusa isolate was cul-
tured from only 1 set in this study and the patient was not im-
munocompromised, we regarded the strain as the true patho-</p>

<p>gen because the C-reactive protein level was markedly elevated. 
Furthermore, fever persisted despite treatment with ceftriaxone 
and subsided after changing the regimen to teicoplanin plus 
piperacillin-tazobactam, which is one of the regimens for the 
treatment of W. confusa infections. 
The standard methods and interpretation criteria of antimicro-
bial susceptibilities for W. confusa are not yet established. In a 
recent study [8], amoxicillin-clavulanic acid, ampicillin-sulbac-
tam, piperacillin-tazobactam, daptomycin, moxifloxacin, doripe-
nem, and tigecycline revealed relatively good in vitro activity and 
were recommended for the treatment of W. confusa infections. 
In summary, we described a second case of bacteremia 
caused by W. confusa in an immunocompetent host. The isolate 
was not identified when commercial identification kits were used 
but could be identified using 16S rRNA gene sequence analysis 
and a MALDI-TOF MS system. When blood cultures show 
growth of catalase-negative, gram-positive coccobacilli with neg-
ative pyrrolidonyl-arylamidase and leucine aminopeptidase reac-
tion, clinical microbiologists should be aware of the possibility of 
W. confusa infection. </p>

<p>Authors' Disclosures of Potential Conflicts of 
Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were re-
ported. </p>



<p>Lee W, et al. 
Weissella confusa bacteremia </p>





</text></tei>