<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3671002" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: The optimal time between neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy (CRT) and surgery for rectal cancer has been debated. 
This study evaluated the influence of this interval on oncological outcomes. Methods: We compared postoperative complica-
tions, pathological downstaging, disease recurrence, and survival in patients with locally advanced rectal cancer who under-
went surgical resection ＜8 weeks (group A, n = 105) to those who had surgery ≥8 weeks (group B, n = 48) after neoadjuvant 
CRT. Results: Of 153 patients, 117 (76.5%) were male and 36 (23.5%) were female. Mean age was 57.8 years (range, 28 to 79 
years). There was no difference in the rate of sphincter preserving surgery between the two groups (group A, 82.7% vs. group 
B, 77.6%; P = 0.509). The longer interval group had decreased postoperative complications, although statistical significance 
was not reached (group A, 28.8% vs. group B, 14.3%; P = 0.068). A total of 111 (group A, 75 [71.4%] and group B, 36 [75%]) pa-
tients were downstaged and 26 (group A, 17 [16.2%] and group B, 9 [18%]) achieved pathological complete response (pCR). 
There was no significant difference in the pCR rate (P = 0.817). The longer interval group experienced significant improve-
ment in the nodal (N) downstaging rate (group A, 46.7% vs. group B, 66.7%; P = 0.024). The local recurrence (P = 0.279), dis-
tant recurrence (P = 0.427), disease-free survival (P = 0.967), and overall survival (P = 0.825) rates were not significantly 
different. Conclusion: It is worth delaying surgical resection for 8 weeks or more after completion of CRT as it is safe and is 
associated with higher nodal downstaging rates. </p>

<p>Multimodality treatment, with preoperative chemo-</p>

<p>radiotherapy (CRT) and optimal surgery including total </p>

<p>mesorectal excision (TME) has recently been considered </p>

<p>the standard treatment for patients with locally advanced </p>

<p>rectal cancer [1-3]. This approach is associated with re-</p>

<p>duced local recurrence, increased downstaging and great-</p>

<p>er rates of sphincter preservation [3-10]. </p>

<p>However, the optimal time between neoadjuvant CRT </p>

<p>and surgery remains debatable. In the 1999 Lyon R90-01 </p>

<p>trial, the only trial to randomize patients to different inter-</p>

<p>Optimal timing of surgery after CRT </p>

<p>thesurgery.or.kr </p>



<p>val lengths, Francois et al. [11] compared short (within 2 </p>

<p>weeks) and long (6 to 8 weeks) interval groups following </p>

<p>preoperative radiotherapy (RT) and showed that the lon-</p>

<p>ger interval was associated with better clinical tumor re-</p>

<p>sponse, pathological downstaging, and a nonsignificant </p>

<p>trend towards increased sphincter preservation. They sug-</p>

<p>gested that a long interval may increase the chance of suc-</p>

<p>cessful sphincter-saving surgery through improved tu-</p>

<p>mor response. As a consequence, this 6-to 8-week interval </p>

<p>has become part of the standard protocol for the treatment </p>

<p>of mid and low rectal cancer [1,12]. However, some inves-</p>

<p>tigators recently suggested that increased intervals could </p>

<p>potentially increase the tumor downstaging effect because </p>

<p>radiation-induced necrosis appears to be a time-depend-</p>

<p>ent phenomenon [4]. Nevertheless, many surgeons have </p>

<p>hesitated to delay surgery beyond 6 to 8 weeks due to con-</p>

<p>cerns that radiation-induced pelvic fibrosis may increase </p>

<p>the technical difficulty of the operation, and increase the </p>

<p>risk of surgical complications and loco-regional re-</p>

<p>currence [4,13]. For these reasons, we retrospectively re-</p>

<p>viewed our data, comparing the outcomes of patients who </p>

<p>were operated on greater than or equal to 8 weeks after </p>

<p>completion of CRT to that of patients who were operated </p>

<p>on less than 8 weeks after CRT. </p>

<p>The aim of this study was to analyze the influence of the </p>

<p>time interval from completion of neoadjuvant CRT to sur-</p>

<p>gery on oncologic outcomes including tumor down-</p>

<p>staging, complications, local and systemic recurrence, dis-</p>

<p>ease-free survival (DFS), and overall survival (OS). </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Patient characteristics </p>

<p>We performed a retrospective review of a prospectively </p>

<p>entered database on 163 consecutive patients with locally </p>

<p>advanced rectal cancer who underwent preoperative CRT </p>

<p>followed by radical resection for curative intent between </p>

<p>November 2005 and July 2009 at our department. </p>

<p>Of these, 10 patients were excluded; six because of prior </p>

<p>cancer operation (three had stomach cancer, one had max-</p>

<p>illary cancer, one had cervical cancer, and one patient had </p>

<p>lung cancer), two patients underwent emergency oper-</p>

<p>ation, and two patients did not complete CRT. The remain-</p>

<p>ing 153 patients were analyzed. </p>

<p>Staging workup was performed before preoperative </p>

<p>CRT in all patients using a combination of physical exami-</p>

<p>nation including digital rectal examination, carcinoem-</p>

<p>bryonic antigen (CEA) levels, colonoscopy with or with-</p>

<p>out rigid proctoscopy, computed tomography (CT) scan-</p>

<p>ning of abdomen and pelvis, and pelvic magnetic reso-</p>

<p>nance imaging (MRI) with or without transrectal ultra-</p>

<p>sonography. Staging workup was repeated before surgery. </p>

<p>Preoperative chemoradiation therapy </p>

<p>All patients received neoadjuvant CRT. Preoperative ra-</p>

<p>diation therapy of 45 Gy/25 fractions was delivered to the </p>

<p>pelvis, followed by a 5.4 Gy boost to the primary tumor </p>

<p>over a period of 5 weeks using linear accelerators with en-</p>

<p>ergy of 10 MV. The median radiation dose received was </p>

<p>5,040 cGy (96.1%). The radiation field was as follows: the </p>

<p>upper margin was 1.5 cm above the sacral promontory (L5 </p>

<p>level), and the lateral margin was 1.5 cm lateral to the bony </p>

<p>pelvis to include the pelvic lymph nodes. During radiation </p>

<p>therapy, all patients were examined on a weekly basis to </p>

<p>evaluate toxicity. All patients received their planned radia-</p>

<p>tion prescription. </p>

<p>Chemotherapy was administered concurrently with ra-</p>

<p>diotherapy and the regimen was 5-fluorouracil (5-FU)-</p>

<p>based and delivered as intravenous bolus injection of two </p>

<p>cycles of 5-FU (425 mg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>/day) and leucovorin (20 </p>

<p>mg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>/day) for 5 days during the first and fifth weeks of </p>

<p>radiation therapy. The other chemotherapy regimens were </p>

<p>CPT-11/S-1 (16%), TS-1/irinotecan (12%), or Xeloda (6%). </p>

<p>Surgical resection </p>

<p>Surgery was scheduled 6 to 8 weeks after the com-</p>

<p>pletion of CRT, but because of logistic, scheduling, and </p>

<p>other clinical factors, the practical interval varied from 4 to </p>

<p>14 weeks. Surgery was performed by expert colorectal sur-</p>

<p>geons who adhered to the oncologic principals of TME </p>

<p>with pelvic autonomic nerve preservation. Tumor meso-</p>

<p>rectal excision (TME) was introduced by Heald [14] in </p>

<p>1979. It advocates for sharp pelvic dissection based on pel-</p>

<p>vic anatomy under direct vision along the plane of the </p>

<p>proper rectal fascia, resulting in en bloc removal of rectal </p>

<p>Duck Hyoun Jeong, et al. </p>



<p>thesurgery.or.kr </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Distribution of interval lengths. </p>

<p>Table 1. Patient and tumor characteristics </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Group A (＜8 wk, n = 105) 
Group B (≥8 wk, n = 48) 
P-value </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
58.4 ± 12.1 
56.4 ± 10.2 
0.316 
Body mass index (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
22.9 ± 2.7 
22.7 ± 2.4 
0.640 
Gender 
0.684 
Male 
79 (75.2) 
38 (79.2) 
Female 
26 (24.8) 
10 (20.8) 
Pretreatment stage 
0.408 
I 
6 (5.7) 
3 (6.2) 
IIA:IIB:IIC 
23:0:7 (21.9:0:6.7), 30 (28.6) 
5:0:2 (10.4:0:4.2), 7 (14.6) 
IIIA:IIIB:IIIC 
2:46:21 (1.9:43.8:20.0), 69 (65.7) 
3:25:10 (6.3:52.1:20.8), 38 (79.2) 
Pretreatment T stage 
0.676 
cT1 
1 (1.0) 
0 (0) 
cT2 
7 (6.6) 
6 (12.5) 
cT3 
75 (71.4) 
33 (68.7) 
cT4 
22 (21.0) 
9 (18.8) 
Pretreatment N stage 
0.243 
cN0 
36 (34.3) 
10 (20.8) 
cN1 
53 (50.5) 
29 (60.4) 
cN2 
16 (15.2) 
9 (18.8) 
Histology 
0.858 
AWD 
26 (24.7) 
9 (18.7) 
AMD 
65 (61.9) 
34 (70.8) 
APD 
5 (4.8) 
2 (4.2) 
Mucinous adenocarcinoma 
5 (4.8) 
2 (4.2) 
Others 
4 (3.8) 
1 (2.1) 
Distance from anal verge (cm) 
4.8 ± 2.6 
4.7 ± 2.7 
0.689 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation or number (%). 
AWD, adenocarcinoma well differentiated; AMD, adenocarcinoma moderately differentiated; APD, adenocarcinoma poorly differentiated. </p>

<p>cancer and surrounding mesorectum containing lymph </p>

<p>nodes. All specimens were assessed grossly for the quality </p>

<p>of TME by an expert pathologist. All specimens were iden-</p>

<p>tified as complete or nearly complete. </p>

<p>Postoperative follow-up </p>

<p>All patients were closely followed up by the surgeons, </p>

<p>medical oncologists, and radiation oncologists in the </p>

<p>Colorectal Cancer Clinic at our institution. Postoperative </p>

<p>follow-up on all patients was conducted every three </p>

<p>months for two years. Clinical examination, measurement </p>

<p>of serum CEA levels, and chest X-rays were performed </p>

<p>during each follow-up. After two years, patients under-</p>

<p>went follow-up examinations every six months. Abdo-</p>

<p>minopelvic CT was first done at the sixth postoperative </p>

<p>month and then yearly thereafter. An additional pelvic </p>

<p>MRI was done when routine CT scan failed to discriminate </p>

<p>suspicious lesions in the pelvic cavity. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analysis for group comparisons was per-</p>

<p>formed using Pearson's χ 
2 test, Fisher's exact test, or </p>

<p>Student's t-test, depending on the nature of the data. A </p>

<p>two-sided P-value less than 0.05 was considered statisti-</p>

<p>cally significant. OS was defined as the time between sur-</p>

<p>Optimal timing of surgery after CRT </p>

<p>thesurgery.or.kr </p>



<p>Table 2. Surgical results and complications </p>

<p>Variable 
Group A (＜8 wk, n = 105) 
Group B (≥8 wk, n = 48) 
P-value </p>

<p>Median time interval from CRT to surgery 
45.0 
64.0 
＜0.001 
Sphincter-preserving surgery 
87 (82.9) 
37 (77.1) 
0.505 
Operation type 
0.341 
AR 
1 (1.0) 
0 (0) 
LAR 
83 (79.0) 
33 (68.8) 
APR 
18 (17.1) 
11 (22.9) 
Hartmann's operation 
1 (1.0) 
2 (4.2) 
Transanal excision 
2 (1.9) 
2 (4.2) 
Operation time (min) 
288.6 ± 91.9 
282.8 ± 87.3 
0.711 
Intraoperative transfusion (mL), cases (%) 
18.1 ± 75.4, 7 (6.7) 
29.2 ± 130.4, 3 (6.3) 
0.586 
Diverting stoma 
63 (60.0) 
33 (68.8) 
0.368 
Proximal magin (cm) 
14.0 ± 5.7 
14.4 ± 4.3 
0.669 
Distal margin (cm) 
2.4 ± 2.1 
2.7 ± 1.9 
0.363 
CRM (mm) 
9.0 ± 4.3 
9.2 ± 3.4 
0.773 
CRM positive rate 
4 (3.8) 
3 (6.3) 
0.679 
Hospital stay (day) 
18.1 ± 13.6 
17.7 ± 7.8 
0.841 
Complication 
30 (28.6) 
7 (14.6) 
0.069 
Anastomotic leakage 
5 (4.8) 
0 (0) 
Obstruction/ileus 
7 (6.7) 
2 (4.1) 
Stenosis 
1 (1.0) 
1 (2.0) 
Fistula of rectovagina 
0 (0) 
1 (2.0) 
Pelvic abscess 
2 (1.9) 
1 (2.0) 
Sexual dysfunction 
1 (1.0) 
1 (2.0) 
Urinary retention 
6 (5.8) 
0 (0) 
Wound dehiscence 
1 (1.0) 
0 (0) 
Other complication 
7 (6.7) 
1 (2.0) 
Reoperation 
8 (7.6) 
1 (2.1) 
0.274 
Local recurrence 
9 (8.6) 
7 (14.6) 
0.267 
Distant recurrence 
31 (29.5) 
11 (22.9) 
0.440 </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%) or mean ± standard deviation. 
CRT, chemoradiotherapy; AR, anterior resection; LAR, low anterior resection; APR, abdominoperineal resection; CRM, circumferential 
resection margin. </p>

<p>gery and death or last follow-up, and local DFS as the time </p>

<p>to local recurrence or last follow-up. Survival curves were </p>

<p>constructed using Kaplan-Meier estimates and the surviv-</p>

<p>al of the groups was compared using log-rank tests. All </p>

<p>statistical tests were performed using IBM <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">18.0</rs> </p>

<p>(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Co.</rs>., Armonk, NY, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Patient and tumor characteristics </p>

<p>Overall, 153 patients were eligible for the study. The pa-</p>

<p>tient population consisted of 117 males (76.5%) and 36 fe-</p>

<p>males (23.5%) with mean age of 57.8 years (range, 28 to 79 </p>

<p>years). The median body mass index was 22.83 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(range, 16.36 to 28.96 kg/m 
2 ) and median tumor distance </p>

<p>from the anal verge was 4.8 cm (range, 1 to 15 cm). </p>

<p>The interval from completion of chemoradiotherapy to </p>

<p>surgery ranged from 28 to 99 days (median, 52 days) (Fig. </p>

<p>1). Of the 153 patients, 105 (68.6%) underwent surgery less </p>

<p>than 8 weeks after CRT completion (group A), whereas 48 </p>

<p>patients (31.4%) underwent surgery greater than or equal </p>

<p>to 8 weeks after CRT (group B). The two groups did not </p>

<p>differ in age, gender ratio, location of tumor from anal </p>

<p>verge, or distribution of clinical T-stage and N-stage. </p>

<p>Patient demographics and tumor characteristic are shown </p>

<p>in Table 1. </p>

<p>Duck Hyoun Jeong, et al. </p>



<p>thesurgery.or.kr </p>

<p>Table 3. Pathologic response rate after surgery </p>

<p>Tumor response 
Group A (＜8 
wk, n = 105) </p>

<p>Group B (≥8 
wk, n = 48) 
P-value </p>

<p>Pathologic tumor response 
No downstaging 
30 (28.6) 
12 (25.0) 
0.700 
Downstaging 
75 (71.4) 
36 (75.0) 
0.700 
T downstage 
62 (59.0) 
24 (50.0) 
0.380 
N downstage 
49 (46.7) 
32 (66.7) 
0.021 
pCR 
17 (16.2) 
9 (18.8) 
0.817 
Pathologic T stage 
0.955 
ypT0 
19 (18.1) 
9 (18.8) 
ypT1 
11 (10.5) 
3 (6.3) 
ypT2 
22 (21.0) 
10 (20.8) 
ypT3 
50 (47.6) 
25 (52.1) 
ypT4 
3 (2.9) 
1 (2.1) 
Pathologic N stage 
0.557 
ypN0 
75 (71.4) 
37 (77.1) 
ypN1 
20 (19.0) 
9 (18.8) 
ypN2 
10 (9.5) 
2 (4.2) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%). 
No downstaging, clinical stage ≤ pathologic stage; downstaging, 
clinical stage ＞ pathologic stage; pathologic complete response 
(pCR) absence of viable adenocarcinoma cells in the surgical 
specimen, including primary tumor and lymph nodes (Mandard 
grade 1). </p>

<p>Surgical characteristics and perioperative compli-
cations </p>

<p>In group A, patients underwent surgery a mean of 45 </p>

<p>days (interval range, 38.8 to 51.2 days) after CRT com-</p>

<p>pared to 66 days (interval range, 55.9 to 76.8 days) in group </p>

<p>B. Sphincter preservation was unaffected by the time inter-</p>

<p>val between completion of chemoradiation and surgery </p>

<p>(group A, 87 [82.9%] vs. group B, 37 [77.1%]; P = 0.505). The </p>

<p>type of surgery (low anterior resection, 75.8%), operative </p>

<p>time (median, 286 minutes), resection margin, number of </p>

<p>blood transfusions given during surgery (10 cases, 6.5%), </p>

<p>length of hospital stay (median, 18 days), and the use of di-</p>

<p>verting stoma in patients undergoing sphincter-preserv-</p>

<p>ing procedures were not influenced by the time interval </p>

<p>(Table 2). </p>

<p>A longer interval between chemoradiation and surgery </p>

<p>had the effect of decreasing postoperative complications, </p>

<p>although statistical significance was not reached (group A, </p>

<p>28.6% vs. group B, 14.6%; P = 0.069). In group A, five anas-</p>

<p>tomotic leakages occurred in contrast to none in group B. </p>

<p>There was no significant difference in the rate of local or </p>

<p>distant recurrence between the groups. </p>

<p>Pathologic response </p>

<p>A total of 111 patients (72.5%) experienced overall </p>

<p>downstaging (i.e., clinical stage ＞ pathologic stage), and </p>

<p>26 patients (17%) achieved pathologic complete response </p>

<p>(pCR). However, 42 patients (27%) did not achieve down-</p>

<p>staging (i.e., clinical stage ≤ pathologic stage). No differ-</p>

<p>ence in T downstaging was observed (group A, 59.0% vs. </p>

<p>group B, 50.0%; P = 0.380). Patients operated after an inter-</p>

<p>val to surgery greater than or equal to 8 weeks (group B) </p>

<p>had significantly higher rate of nodal (N) downstaging </p>

<p>than those operated less than 8 weeks (group A) after che-</p>

<p>moradiation (group A, 46.7% vs. group B, 66.7%; P = 0.021). </p>

<p>There was no significant difference in the pCR rate (group </p>

<p>A, 16.2% vs. group B, 18.8%; P = 0.817) (Table 3). </p>

<p>Oncological outcomes </p>

<p>The median follow-up time from surgery was 38 </p>

<p>months (range, 19 to 63 months). At 3 years, overall local </p>

<p>recurrence was 9.3% (group A, 7.8% vs. group B, 12.7%; P </p>

<p>= 0.279), distant metastasis was noted in 26.3% (group A, </p>

<p>24% vs. group B, 18.9%; P = 0.427), DFS was 66.8% (group </p>

<p>A, 64.8% vs. group B, 66.7%; P = 0.967), and OS was 91.1% </p>

<p>(group A: 90.2% vs. group B: 87.2%, P = 0.825). The local re-</p>

<p>currence, distant metastasis, DFS, and OS rates were not </p>

<p>significantly different between the groups (Fig. 2). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy followed by TME is </p>

<p>now considered the gold standard for initial treatment of </p>

<p>locally advanced rectal cancers [1]. This strategy has been </p>

<p>shown to achieve pathologic downstaging and sphinc-</p>

<p>ter-preserving surgery as well as improve local control </p>

<p>[15,16]. The Dutch Colorectal Cancer Group recently </p>

<p>showed that preoperative radiotherapy reduced 10-year </p>

<p>local recurrence by more than 50% relative to surgery </p>

<p>alone without an OS benefit [7]. </p>

<p>After completion of CRT, surgery was usually per-</p>

<p>formed after 4 to 6 weeks, but there were various debates </p>

<p>about this period [1,12]. Recently, some investigators sug-</p>

<p>Optimal timing of surgery after CRT </p>

<p>thesurgery.or.kr </p>



<p>Fig. 2. Kaplan-Meier estimates for oncologic outcomes. </p>

<p>gested that an increased interval was associated with high-</p>

<p>er rates of pCR and downstaging, decreased recurrence, </p>

<p>and improved DFS [4,12,15,17]. Nevertheless, many sur-</p>

<p>geons were concerned that further delays would increase </p>

<p>difficulty with the operation, including fibrosis and may </p>

<p>result in increased surgical morbidity [1,4,12,18,19]. For </p>

<p>these reasons, some surgeons suggest operation as early as </p>

<p>possible, if there is no oncological benefit derived by the </p>

<p>difference in time interval between completion of CRT and </p>

<p>surgery [2,20-22]. Moore et al. [23] observed more frequent </p>

<p>anastomotic complications (0% vs. 7%, P = 0.05) among pa-</p>

<p>tients undergoing surgery more than 44 days after </p>

<p>chemoradiation. Withers and Haustermans [24] reported </p>

<p>that a longer interval after RT may increase the risk of </p>

<p>emergence of subclinical tumors, which can grow more </p>

<p>rapidly than the primary tumor, and change the risk of de-</p>

<p>veloping distant metastases. </p>

<p>However, our findings refute this argument. Although </p>

<p>statistical significance was not reached, our findings </p>

<p>showed a trend towards decreased postoperative compli-</p>

<p>cation rate in patients operated on ≥8 weeks after CRT </p>

<p>(group A, 28.6% vs. group B, 14.6%, P = 0.069). No anasto-</p>

<p>motic leaks occurred in the delayed surgery group (group </p>

<p>B). These complication rates compare favorably with pre-</p>

<p>vious studies [12,25]. Stein et al. [16] were reported that </p>

<p>three patients in the 4-to 8-week interval group had anas-</p>

<p>tomotic leaks and two underwent reoperation, but none of </p>

<p>the patients in the 10-to 14-week interval group had leaks. </p>

<p>Duck Hyoun Jeong, et al. </p>



<p>thesurgery.or.kr </p>

<p>Kerr et al. [25] reported that shorter intervals independent-</p>

<p>ly predicted anastomotic leakage and perineal wound </p>

<p>complications. Various investigators have confirmed that </p>

<p>longer intervals between neoadjuvant CRT and surgery </p>

<p>are associated with favorable pathological findings and </p>

<p>lower recurrence rates [1,11,13,15,16,23,25]. </p>

<p>De Campos-Lobato et al. [1] showed that a more than </p>

<p>8-week interval between completion of CRT and surgery </p>

<p>was associated with significant improvement in the pCR </p>

<p>rate (30.8% vs. 16.5%, P = 0.03) and decreased the 3-year lo-</p>

<p>cal recurrence rate (1.2% vs. 10.5%, P = 0.04). </p>

<p>Tulchinsky et al. [15] found that a neoadjuvant CRT-sur-</p>

<p>gery interval ＞7 weeks was associated with higher rates </p>

<p>of pCR and near pCR (17% vs. 35%, P = 0.03), decreased re-</p>

<p>currence, and improved DFS (P = 0.05). However, this was </p>

<p>not replicated in the present study. We observed a pCR </p>

<p>rate of 17%, and there was no difference in the pCR rate be-</p>

<p>tween the groups (16.2% vs. 18.8%, P = 0.817). In addition, </p>

<p>there were no differences in T downstaging (59.0% vs. </p>

<p>50.0%, P = 0.380). However, our results showed a sig-</p>

<p>nificantly increased rate of nodal downstaging in patients </p>

<p>operated on after an interval ≥8 weeks compared to those </p>

<p>operated on after an interval ＜8 weeks (46.7% vs. 66.7%, P </p>

<p>= 0.021). </p>

<p>In many investigations, lower pathological nodal stage </p>

<p>was associated with improved recurrence and DFS rates, </p>

<p>and is considered a consistent and strong predictor of sur-</p>

<p>vival rates [17,26-29]. Kim et al. [29] observed that histo-</p>

<p>pathological N downstaging was the most important </p>

<p>prognostic factor. Our study failed to show any significant </p>

<p>improvement in oncological outcomes including local re-</p>

<p>currence, systemic recurrence, DFS, and OS when surgery </p>

<p>was delayed beyond 8 weeks; but we ascertained that </p>

<p>there was no higher recurrence rate or lower survival rate </p>

<p>associated with delaying surgery. We are confident that </p>

<p>such a delay in surgery is not detrimental to patients. </p>

<p>Some investigators attempted to show that an interval </p>

<p>longer than 10 weeks between completion of CRT and sur-</p>

<p>gery is more effective. Tran et al. [12] observed that pa-</p>

<p>tients had more tumor shrinkage when surgery was de-</p>

<p>ferred for a few more weeks and suggested the adaptation </p>

<p>of a delayed interval between chemoradiation and surgery </p>

<p>of 10 to 14 weeks. Garcia-Aguilar et al. [13] indicated that </p>

<p>increasing the time interval between completion of CRT </p>

<p>and TME (to an average of 11 weeks) may increase the pCR </p>

<p>rate without significantly increasing CRT-or chemo-</p>

<p>therapy-related adverse events, operative difficulty, or </p>

<p>postoperative complications compared to traditional neo-</p>

<p>adjuvant CRT and an average delay of 6 weeks. </p>

<p>This study is subject to potential bias and certain limi-</p>

<p>tations due to its retrospective nature. When analyzed this </p>

<p>cohort stratified into ＞10 weeks and ＞12 weeks, we could </p>

<p>not find any statistical significances due to the type and </p>

<p>amount of data available. Although our general approach </p>

<p>has been to wait 6 to 8 weeks after completion of CRT, the </p>

<p>time interval was decided according to individual surgeon </p>

<p>preference. </p>

<p>In conclusion, our findings suggested that an interval </p>

<p>between neoadjuvant CRT and surgery greater than or </p>

<p>equal to 8 weeks showed a trend toward decreased post-</p>

<p>operative complication rate and was associated with sig-</p>

<p>nificantly increasing rate of nodal downstaging. For these </p>

<p>reasons, prospective randomized studies of appropriate </p>

<p>statistical power comparing various time intervals are re-</p>

<p>quired to examine the optimal timing. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article </p>

<p>was reported. </p>



<p>Optimal timing of surgery after CRT </p>

<p>thesurgery.or.kr </p>





</text></tei>