<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3408515" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Emergence agitation is associated with increased morbidity and hospital costs. However, there have </p>

<p>been few reports in the medical literature on the occurrence of emergence agitation in adults. The aim of this study </p>

<p>was to compare emergence agitation between sevoflurane and propofol anesthesia in adults after closed reduction of </p>

<p>nasal bone fracture. </p>

<p>Methods: Forty adults (ASA I-II, 20-60 yr) undergoing closed reduction of nasal bone fracture were randomly </p>

<p>assigned to either sevoflurane or propofol group and anesthesia was maintained with sevoflurane or propofol. The </p>

<p>bispectral index (BIS) was monitored and maintained within 40-60. At the end of surgery, patients were transported </p>

<p>to the post anesthetic care unit (PACU) and agitation state scale was checked by Aono's four-point scale (AFPS). </p>

<p>Emergence agitation was defined as and AFPS score of 3 or 4. Pain score were measured by numeric rating scale (NRS) </p>

<p>on arrival and peak value at PACU. </p>

<p>Results: Nine (45.0%) patients in the sevoflurane group and 2 (10.0%) patients in the propofol group developed </p>

<p>emergence agitation in the PACU (P = 0.031). There was no correlation between peak NRS and Aono's four-point </p>

<p>scale. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Propofol may decrease incidence of emergence agitation compared to sevoflurane in adults under-</p>

<p>going closed reduction of nasal bone fracture. (Korean J Anesthesiol 2012; 63: 48-53) </p>

<p>Closed reduction of nasal bone fracture is performed under 
general anesthesia due to the intense pain it causes, despite it 
being a short surgery. Many patients complain of discomfort 
in breathing because of the intranasal packing performed 
to prevent bleeding. Due to the short surgery time, and to 
prevent absorption of intranasal bleeding, it is preferable to 
use an anesthetic with rapid emergence. Sevoflurane has the 
characteristics of rapid induction and emergence of general 
anesthesia due to its low blood-gas partition coefficient and 
blood-tissue partition coefficient [1], hence it is an appropriate 
drug for general anesthesia in short surgeries such as closed 
reduction of nasal bone fracture. However, emergence agitation 
frequently occurs with sevoflurane; in particular pediatric 
patients, are known to have a higher incidence of emergence 
agitation with sevoflurane compared to other inhalation 
anesthetics [2,3]. There are reports that propofol has rapid 
anesthesia induction and emergence of general anesthesia. 
Moreover, compared to sevoflurane, it causes lower incidence 
of emergence agitation when anesthesia is maintained through 
intravenous administration [4]. 
Emergence agitation can often occur after anesthesia and 
can increase the risk of falling, bleeding, self-extubation, and 
removal of endotracheal tubes, and there is the need for con-
tin uous monitoring of patients by recovery room staffs and 
treatments such as drug administration or physical restraint of 
the patient [5]. However, most research regarding emergence 
agitation is conducted on pediatric patients, and there is little 
data on adult patients. Therefore, the authors in this study 
compared the incidence and degree of emergence agitation 
with sevoflurane and propofol, which are commonly used 
anesthetics, in adult patients scheduled for closed reduction of 
nasal bone fracture. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board 
of the hospital, and the purpose and method were explained 
to the patient and guardian prior to surgery to obtain informed 
consent. The study was conducted on 40 adult patients aged 20-
60 in American Society of Anesthesiologists class 1 or 2 who were 
scheduled for closed reduction of nasal bone fracture. Patients 
with signs or symptoms of infection in the upper respiratory 
tract, history of sleep apnea, administered medication for 
psychiatric diseases were excluded from the study. Using the 
table of random sampling numbers, the patients were randomly 
assigned to sevoflurane (group S) or propofol (group P). A 
medical attendant who was unaware of the grouping of the 
patients evaluated each patient's response in recovering from </p>

<p>anesthesia during his or her stay in the recovery room. 
All patients were transported to the operating room without 
preoperative medication, and the patients were reminded 
that there could be discomfort from nasal packing following 
the surgery. All patients had the following monitoring devices 
attached: electrocardiography, noninvasive blood pressure, 
pulse oximetry monitor, and BIS. While patients were being 
administered 100% oxygen through a face mask, they received 
fentanyl 1 μg/kg by IV injection. For the purposes of group com-
parison, patients in group S received thiopental 5 mg/kg by IV 
injection and group P received propofol 2 mg/kg by IV injection. 
Both groups of patients received 1 mg/kg of succinylcholine by 
IV injection. After fasciculation had passed, manual ventilation 
was continued, and anesthesia was maintained through 
sevoflurane 4 vol% or by continuous injection of propofol at 
200 μg/kg/min, according to group until BIS level reached 60. 
After BIS reached 60, endotracheal intubation was performed, 
and anesthesia was then maintained through controlling 
the concentration of sevoflurane and the injection speed of 
propofol so the BIS value remained 40-60. Respiration rate and 
tidal volume were controlled so end-tidal CO 2 concentration 
was maintained at 30-34 mmHg, and a total of 2 L/min of 
nitrous oxide and oxygen was administered in a 1 : 1 ratio as 
inhalation gas. Additional opioids were not used during surgery 
in any of the patients, and when blood pressure showed a 
difference of more than ± 20% from basal levels, labetalol or 
ephedrine was injected IV for adjustment. All patients received 
bilateral nasal packs. After the completion of surgery when the 
operating surgeon attached the nasal splint, all anesthesia was 
ceased and 100% oxygen was administered to all patients. An 
anesthesiologist was assigned to observe the recovery state 
of each patient, and was responsible for the recovery. When 
spontaneous respiration and muscle strength of the patient 
recovered sufficiently to allow the patient to respond to verbal 
stimulation and after the patient's open eyes had opened, the 
endotracheal tube was removed and the patient was trans-
ported to the recovery room. 
After the patient had opened his or her eyes as a response to 
language stimulation, the degree of emergence agitation of the 
patient was measured using Aono's four-point scale (Table 1). 
The degree of pain was investigated through a numeric rating 
scale (NRS) (0 = no pain, 10 = unimaginably severe pain). The 
measurements were repeated every 2 minutes to obtain the </p>

<p>Table 1. Aono's Four-Point Scale </p>

<p>Calm 
Not calm, but could be easily calmed 
Moderately agitated or restless 
Combative, excited, disoriented </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 </p>



<p>www.ekja.org </p>

<p>Vol. 63, No. 1, July 2012 
Emergence agitation in adults </p>

<p>peak NRS and peak Aono's four-point scale scores. In addition, 
the exposure time to anesthetics, surgery time, time from end 
of surgery to extubation, and duration of emergence agitation 
were investigated. Patients received 25 μg fentanyl IV when their 
NRS score was found to be higher than 3; the total amount of 
fentanyl administered was recorded. When emergence agitation 
continued for more than 3 minutes, 10 mg of nalbuphine was 
administered IV. When emergence agitation continued for more 
than 1 min after drug administration, patients received 10 mg 
nalbuphine was injected IV, repeatedly. 
The patients were observed for the occurrence of compli-
cations or side effects, while being observed for nausea, 
vomiting, tremors, and hypersalivation. If a patient was experi-
enced nausea or vomiting, the patient received 0.3 mg ramo-
setron by IV; pethidine 25 mg was administered IV to patients 
if they were experiencing tremors. When respiratory failure or 
laryngospasm occurred, assisted respiration was performed, 
and endotracheal intubation was performed again if considered 
necessary. Emergence agitation was defined to be when the 
Aono's four-point scale score was 3 or higher [6]. When the 
patient was hemodynamically stable, could maintain their 
own airway, and oxygen saturation was maintained at greater 
than 95% during atmospheric respiration, the patient was 
transported to the ward, and the duration of stay in the recovery 
room was recorded. 
Data was expressed as mean ± standard deviation, and <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 12.0</rs> was used in the statistical analysis. The t-test was 
used in the analysis of parametric data between the 2 groups, 
and the Mann-Whitney U test was used for non-parametric data. 
In the case of categorical data, the chi-square test was used, and 
the Fisher's exact test was used when necessary. Spearman's 
correlation was used to analyze the correlation between patient's 
pain and emergence agitation. Findings were con sidered to be 
statistically significant when the P value was less than 0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>There were no statistically significant differences in the 
demographic and perioperative data of the 2 groups. NRS 
scores in the recovery room and the administered amount of 
fentanyl showed no statistically significant differences between 
the 2 groups (Table 2). 
Emergence agitation occurred in 9 patients in group S 
(45.0%), and 2 patients in group P (10.0%), so the incidence of 
emergence agitation was higher in group S (P = 0.031) (Table 3). 
There were no differences observed in the incidence of 
severe emergence agitation, defined as an Aono's four-point 
scale score of 4. There was no correlation between peak NRS 
score and peak Aono's four-point scale score, and there were no 
patients who displayed complications or side effects after the 
surgery in either group. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Emergence agitation is a state of aggressive agitation that 
occurs temporarily in the process of emerging from anesthesia, </p>

<p>Table 2. Demographic and Perioperative Data </p>

<p>Group S (n = 20) 
Group P (n = 20) </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
Sex (M/F) 
Height (cm) 
Weight (kg) 
Duration of surgery (min) 
Duration of anesthetic exposure (min) 
Time from end of surgery to extubation (min) 
Time to discharge from PACU (min) 
Duration of agitation (min) 
Peak NRS 
Total amount of fentanyl in the PACU (μg) </p>

<p>33.00 ± 2.73 
16/4 
169.10 ± 1.84 
66.41 ± 1.74 
12.85 ± 1.57 
23.85 ± 1.64 
10.35 ± 1.01 
32.00 ± 2.22 
0.98 ± 0.25 
4.10 ± 0.45 
25.00 ± 6.54 </p>

<p>35.20 ± 2.43 
15/5 
168.45 ± 1.43 
69.30 ± 2.28 
14.85 ± 1.19 
22.25 ± 1.31 
10.95 ± 0.89 
33.30 ± 1.58 
0.85 ± 0.36 
4.90 ± 0.41 
33.75 ± 6.90 </p>

<p>Values are mean ± SD. Group S: sevoflurane group, Group P: propofol group, PACU: postanesthetic care unit, NRS: numeric rating scale, 0: no 
pain to 10: worst imaginable pain. </p>

<p>Table 3. Postoperative Aono's Four-Point Scale, Agitation </p>

<p>Group S (n = 20) 
Group P (n = 20) </p>

<p>Aono's four point scale 
1 
2 
3 
4 
Emergence agitation 
3 + 4 </p>

<p>1 (5.0%) 
10 (50.0%) 
7 (35%) 
2 (10.0%) </p>

<p>9 (45.0%)* </p>

<p>14 (70.0%) 
4 (20.0%) 
2 (10.0%) 
0 (0.0%) </p>

<p>2 (10.0%) </p>

<p>Values are number of patients. Aono's four-point scale 3 or 4 are con-
sidered as emergence agitation. Group S: sevofluarane group, Group P: 
propofol group, *P &lt; 0.05 compared with group P. </p>

<p> 
www.ekja.org </p>

<p>Korean J Anesthesiol 
Kim, et al. </p>

<p>and occurs most often during the early stages of emergence. 
The incidence of emergence agitation in adults is less frequent 
compared to pediatric patients, so little research has been done 
on adults. However, the occurrence of emergence agitation 
in adults results in a greater possibility of injury, and medical 
staff may not be able to restrain the agitation. Thus, there could 
may be the need for more medical staff available compared to 
pediatric patients, as problems can arise in the safety of both 
the patient and the medical staff. In the case of closed reduction 
of nasal bone fracture, in our study, there could be discomfort 
from the nasal packing performed to prevent post-operative 
bleeding. 
The incidence of emergence agitation in adults differs accor-
ding to the researcher. Lepouse et al. [5] reported it as 3%, Yu 
et al. [7] as 21.3%, Radtke et al. [8] as 5%, and in our study it 
was 27.3%. There are no clearly fixed criteria used to evaluate 
the occurrence of emergence agitation and its intensity in 
existing studies, but the Aono's four-point scale, Riker Sedation-
Agitation Scale, Richmond Agitation-Sedation Scale, or 
personally categorized criteria have been used. The difference 
in incidence of emergence agitation according to researchers 
is considered to be from differences in criteria or differences in 
the standards used to define emergence agitation. There were 
no differences in incidence of emergence agitation between IV 
anesthetics and inhalation anesthetics according to Radtke et 
al.; however, in the research of Lepouse et al. and Yu et al., the 
incidence of emergence agitation was lower in the group that 
received IV anesthetics compared to the group that received 
sevoflurane. In our study, the propofol group had a lower 
incidence of emergence agitation compared to the sevoflurane 
group. 
Sevoflurane has low blood-gas solubility, so fast inducement 
of and recovery from anesthesia is possible. In addition, the 
smell is pleasant, the drug causes less irritation to the airway 
than other inhalation anesthetics, and it has high cardiovascular 
stability; hence, it is a widely used drug. However, there are 
reports that sevoflurane has a higher rate of emergence agitation 
occurrence compared to other anesthetics [1,2]. In our study, 
also, group S exhibited a higher incidence of emergence agitation. 
The causes of emergence agitation when using sevoflurane 
are known to be rapid emergence time [9], young age [6], 
short anesthesia time, exterior stimulation, and pain [10], and 
combined administration of medication [11]. However, in 
our study, there were no differences between the groups in 
emergence time, age, anesthesia time, and post-operative pain, 
so the emergence agitation of sevoflurane cannot be explained. 
Cohen et al. [12] suggested that the cause of emergence 
agitation in patients who had undergone anesthesia with sevo-
flurane was that the difference in recovery speed within the 
nervous system increases the sensitivity to stimulation from </p>

<p>the surrounding environment, creating a state of functional 
dissocia tion. Another theory is that emergence agitation occurs 
from the changes and relationship of gamma-aminobutyric acid 
(GABA) A receptors in the central nervous system, and in the 
model of Sachedev and Kruck, the mechanism of excitement is 
explained to result from decreased inhibitory signals from the 
globus pallidus interna and substantia nigra, and the inability to 
suppress thalamocortical neurons and brain stem neurons due 
to disorder in the nervous system [13]. 
Propofol is an IV anesthetic with rapid excretion through the 
kidneys, and it is a drug with a rapid recovery time from general 
anesthesia as the patient emerges when the blood concentration 
decreases to lower than 50%. However, in contrast to sevoflurane, 
propofol does not have a high incidence of emergence agitation 
in pediatric patients [12]. This is considered to result from the 
smooth recovery [3], remaining sedative effect in the early 
stages of emergence, and the euphoria caused by the drug [14]. 
Compared to inhalation anesthetics, propofol has a decreased 
occurrence of nausea and vomiting, and characteristically has a 
lower occurrence of hangover. This is considered to be related to 
the reduction in occurrence of emergence agitation. 
Kim et al. [15] compared emergence agitation in pediatric 
patients who were administered propofol or sevoflurane as 
anesthesia for tonsillectomy. The incidence of emergence 
agitation in the propofol group was reported to be 60%, while 
the incidence of emergence agitation in the sevoflurane group 
was 83%. When compared with our study, the overall incidence 
of emergence agitation is higher in children than adults, but 
our study also found a lower incidence of emergence agitation 
in the propofol group than in the sevoflurane group. In the 
research of Kim et al., the incidence of severe emergence 
agitation with aggression, with an Aono's four-point scale score 
of 4, was 10% with propofol and 20% with sevoflurane. In our 
study, emergence agitation with an Aono's four point scale score 
of 4 was not observed in the propofol group and showed a 10% 
occurrence in the sevoflurane group, so it is considered that 
severe emergence agitation occurs more frequently in children. 
Previous studies have suggested that post-operative pain can 
be a risk factor related to emergence agitation [7], but in our 
study there was no correlation between the patient's NRS score 
and Aono's four-point scale score, and no significant difference 
in the amount of fentanyl administered between the 2 groups. 
There is a report that the incidence of emergence agitation 
decreased in pediatric patients who had received sevoflurane 
when ketorolac 0.5 mg/kg or fentanyl 1 μg/kg was administered 
[16], but there are also numerous reports suggesting that there is 
no relationship between pain control and emergence agitation 
[16-19]. 
Previous studies have reported methods to prevent emergence 
agitation. Abu-shahwan [20] reported that in pediatric patients </p>



<p>www.ekja.org </p>

<p>Vol. 63, No. 1, July 2012 
Emergence agitation in adults </p>

<p>who underwent general anesthesia with sevoflurane for 
MRI, emergence agitation could be reduced with additional 
administration of propofol 1 mg/kg, and that in the case of 
performing general anesthesia with sevoflurane for dental 
treatment, additional administration of ketamine 0.25 mg/ 
kg reduced emergence agitation [21]. Isik et al. [22] reported 
that when sevoflurane was used for MRI, IV administration 
of dexmedetomidine 1 μg/kg reduced the occurrence of 
emergence delirium. Other than these, there are reports that 
fentanyl, nalbuphine, midazolam, and lidocaine are effective in 
reducing emergence agitation [22-24]. In our study, nalbuphine 
10 mg was to be IV administered every minute when a state of 
emergence agitation continued for more than 3 minutes, but 
emergence agitation in both groups was measured to last for 
about 1 minute, so additional administration of medication was 
unnecessary. A total of 24 patients reported an NRS score of 3 or 
higher; in these cases, fentanyl was administered to the patients 
by IV. 
A limitation of this study is that we did not measure the 
patient's degree of anxiety before surgery. Lepouse et al. 
[5] reported that preoperative anxiety was a risk factor for 
emergence agitation, and in the research of Kain et al. [25], pre-
operative anxiety was related to delirium or changes in behavior 
after surgery. However, in our study we did not measure the 
degree of preoperative anxiety in the subjects. Furthermore, 
as all of the patients in our study received no preoperative 
medication, we did not consider whether the degree of 
preoperative anxiety or preoperative administration of drugs, 
such as benzodiazepines, could be related to the occurrence of 
emergence agitation. 
In conclusion, the incidence of emergence agitation in 
adult patients, who underwent closed reduction of nasal 
bone fracture, was lower in the group that underwent general 
anesthesia using propofol than in the group that received sevo-
flurane. There was no correlation between postoperative pain 
and severity of emergence agitation. However, there is the need 
for further research on patients undergoing other surgeries 
to confirm whether propofol can reduce the incidence of 
emergence agitation in adult patients. </p>



<p> 
www.ekja.org </p>



</text></tei>