<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3580823" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>The effects of glucose on aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis in Arabidopsis thaliana were investigated in this study by 
using mutants related to aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis and regulation, as well as glucose signalling. The results 
showed that glucose significantly increased the contents of individual and total aliphatic glucosinolates. Expression 
of MYB28 and MYB29, two key transcription factors in aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis, was also induced by 
glucose. Consistently, the increased accumulation of aliphatic glucosinolates and the up-regulated expression of 
CYP79F1 and CYP79F2 induced by glucose disappeared in the double mutant myb28myb29. MYB28 and MYB29 
synergistically functioned in the glucose-induced biosynthesis of aliphatic glucosinolates, but MYB28 was predomi-
nant over MYB29. Interestingly, the content of total aliphatic glucosinolates and the expression level of MYB28 and 
MYB29 were substantially reduced in the glucose insensitive mutant gin2-1 and the ABA insensitive 5 (abi5-7) mutant 
compared with the wild type. In addition, total aliphatic glucosinolates accumulated much less in another sugar-
insensitive RGS1 (regulator of G-protein signaling 1) mutant (rgs1-2) than in the wild type. These results suggest that 
glucose-promoted aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis is regulated by HXK1-and/or RGS1-mediated signalling via 
transcription factors, MYB28, MYB29, and ABI5. </p>

<p>Glucosinolates are a group of nitrogen-and sulphur-contain-
ing secondary metabolites found mainly in Brassicaceae crops. 
They can be grouped into aliphatic, aromatic, and indolic 
glucosinolates based on their different side chain structures 
(Grubb and Abel, 2006; Agerbirk and Olsen, 2012). It is well 
known that glucosinolates and their degradation products 
have diverse biological functions that range from anticarcino-
genic activities to plant defence against pathogens and herbi-
vores (Fahey et al., 1997; Grubb and Abel, 2006; Yatusevich, 
2008; Kos et al., 2012; Saavedra et al., 2012). Aliphatic </p>

<p>glucosinolates have been demonstrated to play an important 
role in plant-herbivore interactions and non-host resistance 
in the Arabidopsis-Pseudomonas pathosystem (Beekwilder 
et al., 2008; Fan et al., 2011). 
To date, almost all genes involved in the glucosinolate 
biosynthetic pathway have been identified (Yan and Chen, 
2007; Sønderby et al., 2010). CYP79F1 and CYP79F2 are 
two important genes whose products catalyse accumulation 
of long-chain aliphatic glucosinolates, while the product of 
CYP79F1 also functions in the biosynthesis of short-chain </p>



<p>aliphatic glucosinolates (Reintanz et al., 2001; Chen et al., 
2003; Tantikanjana et al., 2004). In addition, MYB28, 
MYB29, and MYB76 have been identified as transcription 
factors in aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis with partial 
functional redundancy. Among them, MYB28 plays the most 
important role in aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis, fol-
lowed by MYB29 and MYB76 (Hirai et al., 2007; Gigolashvili 
et al., 2009). Furthermore, many abiotic factors including 
nitrogen and sulphur nutrients as well as the plant hormones 
have been reported to affect the profile and content of glu-
cosinolates (Kliebenstein et al., 2002; Mikkelsen et al., 2003; 
Mewis et al., 2005; Aires et al., 2006; Chen et al., 2006; Falk 
et al., 2007; Bano, 2010; Chen et al., 2011; Liu et al., 2011). 
Sugars play important roles in plant growth and develop-
ment as a carbon and energy source. They can also act as 
effective signalling molecules throughout plant life (Rolland 
et al., 2006; Ramon et al., 2008; Bolouri-Moghaddam et al., 
2010; Smeekens et al., 2010). Hexokinase (HXK), the first 
enzyme involved in glucose catabolism, can sense glucose 
and initiate the signalling pathway in Arabidopsis (Moore 
et al., 2003). The network of HXK1-dependent glucose and 
ABA signalling has been identified, and the ABA-insensitive 
abi5 mutant is insensitive to glucose (León and Sheen, 2003; 
Ramon et al., 2008). Furthermore, it is reported that a regu-
lator of G-protein signalling (AtRGS1) acts as a cell surface 
receptor and functions in a HXK-independent glucose sig-
nalling pathway (Chen and Jones, 2004; Rolland et al., 2006). 
In previous studies, sugar-regulated plant secondary metabo-
lites were observed in several Brassica vegetables (Guo et al., 
2011; Wei et al., 2011). The induction of anthocyanin bio-
synthesis by sucrose has been clearly illustrated (Teng et al., 
2005). Cross-talk between sucrose and hormone signalling 
pathways in the regulation of the anthocyanin biosynthetic 
pathway has also been reported (Loreti et al., 2008). Apart 
from the reports showing that glucose induces the expression 
of MYB28 in Arabidopsis (Li et al., 2006; Gigolashvili et al., 
2007), little information is available on the role of glucose in 
aliphatic glucosinolate accumulation. In this study, the aim 
was to investigate the regulatory mechanism of glucose on 
aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis, and to identify the com-
ponents involved in glucose signalling. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Plants and growth conditions 
Seeds were sterilized for 30 s in 75% ethanol and washed with ster-
ile water twice, and then immersed in 10% sodium hypochlorite for 
2 min, followed by washing with sterile water four times. Except for 
the experiments shown in Supplementary Figs S1, S3, and S6, avail-
able at JXB online, plant growth conditions in all experiments were 
as follows. The seeds were stratified for 3 d at 4 °C, and transferred 
into flasks (~50 seeds per flask) with 40 ml of liquid growth medium 
[full-strength sterilized Murashige-Skoog (MS) salt solution+0.5% 
glucose]. Plants were grown under a photoperiod of 16 h light/8 h 
dark with gentle shaking (135 rpm) for 10 d in a plant growth cham-
ber at 21 °C (Loreti et al., 2008). For Supplementary Figs S1 and S3, 
experiments were carried out with solid culture as follows: surface-
sterilized seeds were planted on 0.5% agar plates containing MS salt 
and 0.5% glucose. In the experiment shown in Supplementary Fig. </p>

<p>S6, MS salt solution was replaced with half-strength sterilized MS 
salt solution. Seeds were grown in a plant growth chamber under the 
same conditions mentioned above after being incubated at 4 °C for 
3 d. Mutant seeds of gin2-1 were generously provided by Dr Sheng 
Teng (Shanghai Institute of Plant Physiology and Ecology, Chinese 
Academy of Sciences). The rgs1-2 seeds was obtained from Dr Jirong 
Huang (Shanghai Institute of Plant Physiology and Ecology, Chinese 
Academy of Sciences). Mutant seeds of myb28 (SALK_136312) 
and myb29 (CS121027) were purchased from ABRC (Arabidopsis 
Biological Resource Center) (Hirai et al., 2007; Beekwilder et al., 
2008). The double knock-out mutant myb28myb29 was a gift from 
Dr Piero Morandini, University of Milan, Italy (Beekwilder et al., 
2008). The genetic background of all mutants was Columbia (Col-0), 
except for gin2-1 which was Landsberg (Ler). </p>

<p>Glucose and sorbitol treatments 
Sterilized glucose and sorbitol were added to the flasks after 10 d at 
final concentrations of 1, 3, and 5% (w/v) with water as a control. 
For solid culture, 10-day-old seedlings were transferred to MS agar 
plates with 3% glucose or 3% sorbitol. After treatments, plants were 
cultured in the same condition as before and were collected at differ-
ent time points for analysis. </p>

<p>Glucosinolate assay 
Seedlings were harvested 1, 3, and 5 d after treatment. Glucosinolates 
were extracted and analysed as previously described, with minor 
modifications (Sun et al., 2011a, b). Fresh tissues (100 mg) were boiled 
in 1 ml of water for 10 min. After recovery of the liquid, the residues 
were washed with water (1 ml), and the combined aqueous extract 
was applied to a DEAE-Sephadex A-25 (30 mg) column (pyridine 
acetate form). The column was washed three times with 20 mM pyri-
dine acetate and twice with water. The glucosinolates were converted 
into their desulpho analogues by overnight treatment with 100 µl 
of 0.1% (1.4 U) aryl sulphatase, and the desulphoglucosinolates 
were eluted with 2 × 0.5 ml of water. The high-performance liquid 
chromatography (HPLC) analysis was performed using Shimadzu 
HPLC (Shimadzu, Kyoto, Japan), consisting of two LC-20AT sol-
vent delivery units, a DGU-20A3 degasser, a CTO-10ASVP column 
oven, an SIL-20A autosampler, and an SPD-M20A diode array 
detector. The HPLC system was connected to a computer with <rs id="software-1" type="software">LC 
solution</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">Version 1.25</rs> Software. A Hypersil C18 column (5 µm par-
ticle size, 4.6 mm×250 mm; Elite Analytical Instruments Co. Ltd, 
Dalian, China) was used with a mobile phase of acetonitrile and 
water at a flow rate of 1.0 ml min -1 . The procedure employed iso-
cratic elution with 1.5% acetonitrile for the first 5 min; a linear gra-
dient to 20% acetonitrile over the next 15 min; followed by isocratic 
elution with 20% acetonitrile for the final 13 min. A 20 µl sample 
was injected onto the column by an autosampler. Absorbance was 
detected at 226 nm. Sinigrin (Sigma, St Louis, MO, USA) was used 
as an internal standard for calculation of molar concentrations of 
individual glucosinolates, and relative response factors were applied 
to correct absorbance differences between the standard and other 
glucosinolates (Brown et al., 2003). Data were given as nmol mg -1 
FW (fresh weight). </p>

<p>RNA isolation and expression analysis 
Seedlings were collected at different time points (0, 6, 12, 18, 24, 
and 36 h after treatment) and immediately immersed in liquid nitro-
gen. Total RNA was isolated from ~100 mg of Arabidopsis leaves 
using the Trizol reagent according to the manufacturer's instruc-
tion (Takara, Japan). RNA samples were reversed transcribed into 
cDNAs using Prime Script RT Master Mix (Takara, Japan). 
Real-time quantitative PCR (qPCR) was performed in a total vol-
ume of 20 µl, including 2 µl of diluted cDNA, 1 µl of each primer 
(5 µM), and 10 µl of 2× SYBR Green PCR Master Mix (Takara, 
Japan) on an Applied Biosystems StepOne Real-Time PCR Systems </p>

<p>Glucose on aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis | 1099 </p>

<p>(Applied Biosystems, USA) according to the kit manual. The qPCR 
program was conducted at 95 °C for 10 s first, followed by 40 cycles of 
95 °C for 5 s, and 60 °C for 30 s. The expression level of Arabidopsis 
ACTIN2 was used as an internal control and the expression of other 
genes was computed with the 2 -ΔΔCT method (Livak and Schmittgen, 
2001). The primers used in this work are listed in Table 1. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Statistical analysis was performed using the SPSS package program 
version 11.5 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). For Figs 1-3, and 
Supplementary Figs S1, S2, and S4-S6 at JXB online, differences in 
glucosinolate accumulation among different treatments were tested, 
while differences in Fig. 5A were tested among different mutants. 
They all were analysed by one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA), 
followed by the least significant difference (LSD) test at a 95% con-
fidence level (P &lt; 0.05). For Figs 6A, B, 7A, and Supplementary 
Fig. S3, differences in glucosinolate accumulation among different 
mutants were analysed using independent-samples t-test. The values 
are reported as means with standard error for all results. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Effect of glucose on glucosinolate contents in 
Arabidopsis </p>

<p>To study the role of glucose in glucosinolate biosynthesis, 
10-day-old seedlings of Arabidopsis wild-type (Col-0) were 
treated with different concentrations (1, 3, and 5%) of glu-
cose or sorbitol (as an osmotic control) and sampled 1, 3, and 
5 d after each treatment. As shown in Fig. 1, the contents of 
4MSOB (4-methylsulphinylbutyl glucosinolate, the predom-
inant aliphatic glucosinolate) and the total aliphatic glucosi-
nolates increased significantly at almost all time points under 
all the tested concentrations except for 1 d after 1% glucose or 
sorbitol treatment. Similarly, the contents of I3M (indol-3-yl-
methyl glucosinolate, the predominant indolic glucosinolate) 
and the total indolic glucosinolates were also enhanced sig-
nificantly by glucose (Fig. 2). Furthermore, glucose promoted 
glucosinolate accumulation in a time-dependent manner 
(Figs 1, 2). It should be noted that glucose stimulated accu-
mulation of glucosinolates much more than sorbitol, indicat-
ing that the regulatory mechanism of glucose and sorbitol on 
glucosinolate biosynthesis is different. </p>

<p>Since vitrification occurred in some seedlings 5 d after 
treatment, the effect of glucose on glucosinolate biosynthesis 
was studied using plants treated with a moderate concentra-
tion (3%) for 3 d. Under this condition, the contents of major 
aliphatic glucosinolates, 3MSOP (3-methylsulphinylpropyl 
glucosinolate), 4MTB (4-methylthiobutyl glucosinolate), and 
4MSOB, and total aliphatic glucosinolates notably increased 
by 146, 30, 38, and 31%, respectively, compared with sorbi-
tol treatment (Fig. 3A). In addition, significant increases in 
4MOI3M (4-methoxyindol-3-ylmethyl glucosinolate), I3M, 
and total indolic glucosinolates were also observed 3 d after 
3% glucose treatment compared with sorbitol treatment 
(Fig. 3B). 
To verify the effect of glucose on aliphatic glucosinolate 
biosynthesis, solid media were used to grow seedlings (for 
details see the Materials and methods). The results showed 
the same trend as the liquid culture (Supplementary Fig. S1 at 
JXB online). Because there exists an interaction between glu-
cose and nitrogen (Price et al., 2004), liquid growth medium 
including half-strength MS salt solution with 0.5% glucose, 
which contains a lower nitrogen concentration, was used to 
confirm the induction of glucose, and strong induction of 
glucose still can be observed (Supplementary Fig. S6). In 
addition, the content of total aliphatic glucosinolates was 
also measured at 0, 6, 12, 24, and 36 h after glucose treatment 
to investigate the time-course accumulation of aliphatic glu-
cosinolates (Supplementary Fig. S2). A significant difference 
in total aliphatic glucosinolates between glucose and sorbitol 
treatment occurred 24 h after treatment. </p>

<p>Glucose induces expression of transcription factors 
and biosynthetic genes in the aliphatic glucosinolate 
pathway </p>

<p>MYB28 and MYB29 are two major regulators for aliphatic 
glucosinolate biosynthesis, and the double mutant myb-
28myb29 does not accumulate any aliphatic glucosinolates 
(Gigolashvili et al., 2007, 2008; Hirai et al., 2007; Sønderby 
et al., 2007; Beekwilder et al., 2008). CYP79F1 and CYP79F2 
encode two core biosynthetic enzymes catalysing the produc-
tion of aliphatic glucosinolates (Tantikanjana et al., 2004; </p>

<p>Table 1. Primer sequences used for quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR). </p>

<p>Target gene 
Locus code 
Primer sequence 
Reference </p>

<p>ACTIN2 
AT3G18780 
5'-TAACTCTCCCGCTATGTATGTCGC-3' 
5'-CCACTGAGCACAATGTTACCGTAC-3' </p>

<p>Gigolashvili et al. (2007) </p>

<p>CYP79F1 
AT1G16410 
5'-CCATACCCTTTTCACATCCTACTAGTCT-3' 
5'-GTAGATTGCCGAGGATGGGC-3' </p>

<p>Gigolashvili et al. (2007) </p>

<p>CYP79F2 
AT1G16400 
5'-ACTAGGATTTATCGTCTTCATCGCA-3' 
5'-CTAGGACGAGTCATGATTAGTTCGG-3' </p>

<p>Gigolashvili et al. (2007) </p>

<p>MYB28 
AT5G61420 
5'-TCCCTGACAAATACTCTTGCTGAAT-3' 
5'-CATTGTGGTTATCTCCTCCGAATT-3' </p>

<p>Gigolashvili et al. (2007) </p>

<p>MYB29 
AT5G07690 
5'-CAATACTGGAGGAGGATATAACC-3' 
5'-AGTTCTTGTCGTCATAATCTTGG-3' </p>

<p>Beekwilder et al. (2008) </p>

<p>MYB76 
AT5G07700 
5'-ACGTTTAATCGATGATGGCA-3' 
5'-ATGGGCTCAACTGGATTAGG-3' </p>

<p>Designed by software 
www.genscript.com </p>



<p>Sønderby et al., 2010). Here the data showed that the expres-
sion of all the four genes responded positively to exogenous 
glucose treatment at a time point as early as 6 h (Fig. 4). The 
expression of the genes was induced with a steady rise after 6 h, 
peaked at 18 h (MYB28 and CYP79F2) or 24 h (MYB29 and 
CYP79F1), and then decreased sharply at 36 h. The expres-
sion levels of MYB28, MYB29, CYP79F1, and CYP79F2 
increased by ~8.4-, 2.5-, 1.8-, and 1.3-fold, respectively, at 18 h 
after the 3% glucose treatment when compared with sorbitol 
treatment. So, 18 h after treatment was set as the harvest point 
of Arabidopsis plants for further analysis of gene expression. </p>

<p>Effect of glucose on aliphatic glucosinolate 
biosynthesis in myb28, myb29 and myb28myb29 
mutants </p>

<p>The level of total aliphatic glucosinolates was examined in 
myb28 and myb29 under glucose treatment. As shown in 
Fig. 5A, the level of total aliphatic glucosinolates decreased 
significantly in both mutants, especially in myb28. In myb28, 
although the contents of 4MTB and 4MSOB increased with 
glucose treatment (data not shown), the content of total ali-
phatic glucosinolates was much lower than that in the wild </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>(D) </p>

<p>(E) </p>

<p>concentration </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>water 
sorbitol 
glucose </p>

<p>Total Aliphatic GS </p>

<p>nm ol m g </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 
c </p>

<p>(F) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>nm ol m g </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 
b 
c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1% 
3% 
5% 
0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>nm ol m g -1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 
b 
c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>water 
sorbitol 
glucose </p>

<p>nm ol m g -1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>a 
ab </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>(B) </p>

<p>(C) </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>4MSOB </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>nm ol m g -1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 
b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>1% 
3% 
5% 
0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>nm ol m g -1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>concentration </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 
b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Effect of glucose on accumulation of aliphatic glucosinolates (GS) in a time-course experiment. Total aliphatic glucosinolates and 
4MSOB were measured in 10-day-old Arabidopsis seedlings treated with 1, 3, and 5% glucose, and sorbitol. Samples were collected 
after 1 d (A, D), 3 d (B, E), and 5 d (C, F). Each data point represents the mean of three independent biological replicates per treatment 
(mean ±SE). Values not sharing a common letter are significantly different at P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Glucose on aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis | 1101 </p>

<p>type. Interestingly, glucose treatment rescued the chemotype 
of low contents of individual and total aliphatic glucosi-
nolates in the myb29 mutant. 
The transcriptional level of MYB28, MYB29, CYP79F1, 
and CYP79F2 was determined in myb28 and myb29 mutants. 
As shown in Fig. 5B, glucose treatment dramatically increased 
the expression level of MYB28 in both wild-type and myb29 
plants compared with sorbitol treatment, which produced a 
slightly increased MYB28 expression level. MYB29 expres-
sion was also substantially induced by glucose in the wild type, 
but glucose-induced expression of MYB29 was very weak in 
myb28 (Fig. 5C). The expression pattern of CYP79F1 and 
CYP79F2 was similar to that of MYB28 (Fig. 5D, E). These 
results indicate that MYB28 is a key transcription factor for 
expression of genes involved in aliphatic glucosinolate bio-
synthesis. No detectable aliphatic glucosinolates were found 
in the myb28myb29 double mutant with or without glucose </p>

<p>treatment (Fig. 5A). Consistently, the expression levels of 
CYP79F1 and CYP79F2 were almost undetectable in the 
double mutant (Fig. 5F, G). </p>

<p>Effect of glucose on aliphatic glucosinolate 
biosynthesis in gin2-1 and rgs1-2 mutants </p>

<p>The HXK1 null mutant gin2-1 is glucose insensitive (Moore 
et al., 2003), while rgs1-2, a null mutant of the gene encoding 
RGS protein (AtRGS1), is insensitive to glucose and sucrose 
(Chen and Jones, 2004). Accumulation of total aliphatic glu-
cosinolates was analysed in these two mutants along with their 
wild types under liquid culture. As shown in Fig. 6A and B, 
the level of total aliphatic glucosinolates in gin2-1 and rgs1-2 
decreased by 46% and 23%, respectively, when compared with 
the corresponding wild types. Similar results were also observed 
when the mutants were grown on the solid culture medium </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>water 
sorbitol 
glucose </p>

<p>concentration </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>(B) </p>

<p>nmol mg -1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>I3M </p>

<p>a 
b 
b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>(C) </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>nmol mg -1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 
b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 
c </p>

<p>1% 
3% 
5% 
0.00 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>b 
b </p>

<p>nmol mg -1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 
c </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>concentration </p>

<p>water 
sorbitol 
glucose </p>

<p>Total Indolic GS </p>

<p>nmol mg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>ab 
b 
c </p>

<p>b 
a </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>nmol mg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>b b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1% 
3% 
5% 
0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>(F) </p>

<p>(E) </p>

<p>(D) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>nmol mg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>b b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 
b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Effect of glucose on accumulation of indolic glucosinolates in a time-course experiment. Total indolic glucosinolates and I3M 
were measured in 10-day-old Arabidopsis seedlings treated with 1, 3, and 5% glucose, and sorbitol. Samples were collected after 1 d 
(A, D), 3 d (B, E), and 5 d (C, F). Each data point represents the mean of three independent biological replicates (mean ±SE). Values not 
sharing a common letter are significantly different at P &lt; 0.05. </p>



<p>(Supplementary Fig. S3 at JXB online). Furthermore, glucose 
treatment did not rescue the chemotype of low glucosinolates 
in the mutant plants. The total aliphatic glucosinolate content 
was significantly lower in gin2-1 and rgs1-2 plants than that 
in the control under glucose treatment. These results indicate 
that HXK1 and RGS1 are involved in the glucose-regulated 
aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis. 
Considering that HXK1 controls gene transcription via 
interaction with several protein families including MYB in 
the nucleus (Rolland et al., 2006), the expression level of three 
transcription factors involved in aliphatic glucosinolate bio-
synthesis (MYB28, MYB29, and MYB76) was investigated in 
gin2-1 mutant plants. Although glucose treatment increased 
the expression of MYB28 and MYB29 in the gin2-1 mutant 
when compared with sorbitol treatment (Fig. 6C, D), severely </p>

<p>lower expression levels of MYB28, MYB29, and MYB76 
(Fig. 6C, D, E) were found in gin2-1 as compared with Ler 
after glucose treatment. </p>

<p>Effect of glucose on aliphatic glucosinolate 
biosynthesis in the abi5 mutant </p>

<p>A significant decrease in total aliphatic glucosinolates was 
observed in the abi5-7 mutant in comparison with the wild type 
with or without glucose treatment (Fig. 7A). Furthermore, 
expression levels of MYB28, MYB29, and MYB76 in abi5-7 
were substantially lower than that in the wild type after glu-
cose treatment (Fig. 7B-D). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Glucose-induced aliphatic glucosinolate accumulation </p>

<p>Sugars were first recognized to be the prime carbon supply 
and energy source in plants. However, reports on their regula-
tory functions have been increasing in recent years (Smeekens 
et al., 2010). The regulatory mechanism of sucrose in anthocy-
anin biosynthesis has been well elucidated (Teng et al., 2005). 
In addition, previous studies indicated that sugars could 
boost the accumulation of health-promoting compounds in 
Brassica vegetables (Guo et al., 2011; Wei et al., 2011). As a 
signalling molecule, glucose controls plant growth, develop-
ment, metabolism, and stress resistance (Ramon et al., 2008). 
In the current study, the results indicated that glucose posi-
tively regulated aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis. Aliphatic 
glucosinolates can be greatly induced through MYB tran-
scription factors by glucose in a time-and dose-dependent 
manner (Figs 1, 4), while aliphatic glucosinolate accumula-
tion was severely disrupted in the glucose signalling mutants 
gin2-1 and rgs1-2 (Fig. 6A, B). In addition, because glucosi-
nolate contents could be affected by several abiotic stress fac-
tors, such as salt, drought, and water (López-Berenguer et al., 
2008; Khan et al., 2010; Yuan et al., 2010), sorbitol was taken 
as an osmotic stress control and its effect on glucosinolates 
was not as strong as that of glucose. Moreover, fructose, the 
isomer of glucose, which can interconvert with glucose and 
enter the metabolic pathway of glucosinolates with the form 
of glucose-6-phosphate as intermediate (Henry et al., 1991; 
Bhagavan and Ha, 2011), could not mimic the induction by 
glucose of glucosinolate accumulation (Supplementary Fig. 
S4 at JXB online). In addition, the glucose analogue man-
nose, the substrate of HXK1 phosphorylation, which can also 
trigger the signalling function of HXK1 (Ramon et al., 2008), 
did not have a similar induction to glucose (Supplementary 
Fig. S5). To sum up, glucose induces aliphatic glucosinolate 
accumulation as a signalling molecule in Arabidopsis thaliana 
through a mechanism different from mannose. </p>

<p>Induction of aliphatic glucosinolates by glucose 
through MYB transcription factors </p>

<p>MYB28 and MYB29 are the two vital transcription fac-
tors in aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis in A. thaliana </p>

<p>I3M 
4 MOI3M 
1 MOI3M 
T otal Indolic GS </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>b 
a a a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>water 
sorbitol 
glucose </p>

<p>nmol mg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>(B) </p>

<p>3MSOP 
4 MSOB 
4MTB 
8MSOO Total Aliphatic GS </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>0.45 </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c 
b </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>b b 
a a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>water 
sorbitol 
glucose </p>

<p>nmol mg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Effect of glucose on accumulation of individual and total 
aliphatic and indolic glucosinolates. (A) Total aliphatic glucosinolates 
and four aliphatic glucosinolates 3MSOP, 4MSOB, 4MTB, and 
8MSOO (8-methylsulphinyloctyl glucosinolate). (B) Total indolic 
glucosinolates and three indolic glucosinolates I3M, 4MOI3M, and 
1MOI3M (1-methoxyindol-3-ylmethyl) were measured in 10-day-
old Arabidopsis seedlings treated with 3% glucose and sorbitol. 
Samples were collected 3 d after treatment. Each data point 
represents the mean of three independent biological replicates per 
treatment (mean ±SE). Values not sharing a common letter are 
significantly different at P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Glucose on aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis | 1103 </p>

<p>(Gigolashvili et al., 2009). Almost all the biosynthetic genes 
in the aliphatic glucosinolate pathway can be positively regu-
lated by these two transcription factors (Yan and Chen, 2007). 
To test whether aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis induced 
by glucose was due to the up-regulation of MYB transcrip-
tion factors, qPCR was applied to determine the expression 
pattern of MYB28 and MYB29 after glucose treatment. As 
expected, induction of these two genes was similar at differ-
ent time points except that the expression of MYB28 had an 
earlier peak than that of MYB29. This exactly reflected that 
MYB28 could regulate the expression of MYB29 (Yatusevich, 
2008) (Fig. 4A, B). In addition, the expression levels of 
CYP79F1 and CYP79F2, the key structural genes in aliphatic 
glucosinolate biosynthesis, were also enhanced after glucose 
treatment (Fig. 4C, D). The induction occurred within the 
first 6 h, which was a little earlier than glucosinolate enhance-
ment. This indicates that the expression of transcription fac-
tors can sense changes in the environment in a shorter time 
than the production of secondary metabolites. The results 
are consistent with previous reports on Brassica crops with 
sucrose treatment (Guo et al., 2011; Wei et al., 2011). 
To obtain a deeper understanding of the role that the main 
transcriptional regulators and structural genes played in the 
regulation of aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis in response 
to glucose, three mutants, myb28, myb29, and myb28myb29, </p>

<p>were used for further analysis. MYB28 is the predominant 
transcription factor belonging to the MYB family control-
ling the profiles of aliphatic glucosinolates, and it is mainly 
responsible for long-chain and short-chain aliphatic glucosi-
nolates, while MYB29 participates more in short-chain ali-
phatic glucosinolates. In the present study, myb28 showed 
a very severe lack of aliphatic glucosinolates compared 
with myb29 (Hirai et al., 2007; Gigolashvili et al., 2008; 
Yatusevich, 2008) (Fig. 5A). Surprisingly, the reduction could 
be recovered by glucose supplementation in myb29 but not 
in the case of myb28 (Fig. 5A). This is due to the fact that 
these two transcription factors have functional redundancy in 
regulation of aliphatic glucosinolate, in which MYB28 takes 
a master role while MYB29 has an accessory role (Hirai et al., 
2007). According to previous reports (Yatusevich, 2008), 
MYB29 can be induced by MYB28. Thus, when myb29 
was treated with glucose, the strong expression of MYB28, 
induced by glucose, could compensate the decreased level of 
MYB29 expression (Fig. 5B, C). When MYB28 is knocked 
out, the expression of MYB29 is still lower than that in Col-0 
even under glucose treatment (Fig. 5C). Interestingly, the 
induction by glucose of total aliphatic glucosinolates and the 
expression of MYB29 in mutant myb28 were much weaker 
than that in Col-0. This observation indicated that the strong 
induction by glucose of the expression of MYB29 in Col-0 is </p>

<p>0h 
6h 
12h 
18h 
24h 
36h </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>water 
sorbitol 
glucose </p>

<p>MYB28 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>0h 
6h 
12h 
18h 
24h 
36h 
0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>water 
sorbitol 
glucose </p>

<p>MYB29 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>0h 
6h 
12h 
18h 
24h 
36h 
0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>water 
sorbitol 
glucose </p>

<p>CYP79F1 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>0h 
6h 
12h 
18h 
24h 
36h 
0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Hours after treatment </p>

<p>(D) </p>

<p>water 
sorbitol 
glucose </p>

<p>CYP79F2 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>(A) 
(B) </p>

<p>(C) </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Effect of glucose on the expression level of MYB28 (A), MYB29 (B), CYP79F1 (C), and CYP79F2 (D). The expression level was 
measured in 10-day-old Arabidopsis seedlings treated with 3% glucose or sorbitol. Samples used for qPCR experiment were collected 0, 
6, 12, 18, 24, and 36 h after treatment, respectively. Each data point represents the mean of three independent biological replicates per 
treatment (mean ±SE). Relative expression values are given compared with 0 h non-treated seedlings (0 h=1). </p>



<p>water 
s orbitol 
g lucose 
-1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>CYP79F1 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>Col-0 
myb28myb29 </p>

<p>water 
s orbitol 
g lucose 
-1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 
Col-0 
myb28myb29 </p>

<p>CYP79F2 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>(F) 
(G) </p>

<p>water 
s orbitol 
g lucose </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 
Col 
myb28 
myb29 </p>

<p>MYB28 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>water 
s orbitol 
g lucose </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>MYB29 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>water 
s orbitol 
g lucose </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>CYP79F1 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>water 
s orbitol 
g lucose </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>(E) </p>

<p>CYP79F2 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>(B) 
(C) </p>

<p>(D) </p>

<p>water 
s orbitol 
g lucose </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>d 
d 
b 
c 
c 
c </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>nmol mg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>Col-0 
myb28 
myb29 
myb28myb29 </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Total aliphatic glucosinolates content of myb28 and myb29 (A). Effect of glucose on MYB28 (B), MYB29 (C), CYP79F1 (D), 
and CYP79F2 (E) expression level in myb28 and myb29, and of CYP79F1 (F), CYP79F2 (G) in the myb28myb29 double mutant. 
Samples used for glucosinolate assay were collected 3 d after treatment. Samples used for qPCR experiment were collected 18 h 
after treatment. Each data point represents the mean of three independent biological replicates per treatment (mean ±SE). Values 
not sharing a common letter are significantly different at P &lt; 0.05. Relative expression values are given compared with seedlings 
treated by water. </p>

<p>Glucose on aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis | 1105 </p>

<p>partly due to the regulation of MYB28 (Fig. 4). These results 
may explain why myb28 contained a significantly reduced level 
of aliphatic glucosinolates with or without glucose treatment. 
Aliphatic glucosinolates and the expression of CYP79F1 
and CYP79F2 could not be detected in the loss-of-function 
mutant myb28myb29 (Fig. 5F, G), which is consistent with 
previous surveys (Sønderby et al., 2007). Interestingly, it 
contained no detectable aliphatic glucosinolates even when 
treated with glucose. Previous research has illustrated that 
CYP79F1 and CYP79F2 could be regulated by MYB factors 
(MYB28, MYB29, and MYB76) (Gigolashvili et al., 2008). 
Here the up-regulated expression of CYP79F1 and CYP79F2 </p>

<p>in Col-0 was not observed in myb28myb29 before and after 
glucose treatment. These findings suggest that the MYB tran-
script factors are induced by glucose, and then regulate the 
expression of structural genes which finally lead to the accu-
mulation of aliphatic glucosinolate. </p>

<p>HXK1-and RGS1-dependent regulation of aliphatic 
glucosinolate biosynthesis by glucose </p>

<p>HXKs are one of the most conserved sugar sensors together 
with other sugar kinases in the plant kingdom. In A. thali-
ana, six HXK and HXK-like genes have been identified so far </p>

<p>water 
s obitol 
glucose 
0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>Total Aliphatic GS </p>

<p>Ler 
gin2-1 </p>

<p>nmol mg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>water 
s obitol 
glucose 
0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>(B) </p>

<p>Total Aliphatic GS </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>nmol mg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>Col-0 
rgs1-2 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>water 
s orbitol 
g lucose 
0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>MYB28 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>Ler 
gin2-1 </p>

<p>water 
s orbitol 
g lucose 
0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>MYB29 </p>

<p>Ler 
gin2-1 </p>

<p>water 
s orbitol 
g lucose </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>(E) </p>

<p>(D) 
(C) </p>

<p>Ler 
gin2-1 </p>

<p>MYB76 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Total aliphatic glucosinolate content of gin2-1 and rgs1-2 (A, B). Effect of glucose on the MYB28, MYB29, and MYB76 
expression level in the gin2-1 mutant (C, D, E). Arabidopsis seedlings (10-day-old) were treated with 3% glucose or sorbitol. Samples 
used for glucosinolate assay were collected 3 d after treatment. Samples used for qPCR experiment were collected 18 h after treatment. 
Each data point represents the mean of three independent biological replicates per treatment (mean ±SE). Values not sharing a common 
letter are significantly different at P &lt; 0.05. Relative expression values are given compared with seedlings treated by water. </p>



<p>(Ramon et al., 2008) and they carry out diverse and distinct 
functions in glucose metabolism and signalling. AtHXK1 has 
been characterized as an intracellular glucose sensor (Bolouri-
Moghaddam et al., 2010). HXK1-dependent glucose signalling 
can affect plant growth, which relies on the endogenous glu-
cose level and the sensitivity to glucose in plants (Ramon et al., 
2008). In addition, there are other glucose-sensing and signal-
ling pathways independent of HXK1. It has been reported 
that the signalling pathway of sugar-induced anthocyanin 
accumulation is independent of HXK1 (Xiao et al., 2000; Teng 
et al., 2005). Furthermore, the fructose signalling can function 
independently of the HXK1 glucose sensor (Li et al., 2011). In 
A. thaliana, RGS1 is a regulator of G-protein signalling pro-
tein, which modulates plant cell proliferation and may serve 
as a glucose sensor located on the cell surface, independent of 
HXK1 (Chen and Jones, 2004; Ramon et al., 2008). 
In the present study, the relationship between HXK1/ 
RGS1 and aliphatic glucosinolates was analysed using their 
corresponding mutants, gin2-1 and rgs1-2. Both mutants are 
glucose insensitive. According to the present results, gin2-1 
and rgs1-2 mutants showed a notable decrease in the level of 
total aliphatic glucosinolates whether treated with glucose 
or not, when compared with their corresponding controls 
(Fig. 6A, B). This suggested that HXK1 and RGS1 might </p>

<p>both participate in the regulation of aliphatic glucosinolate 
biosynthesis. It has been reported that HXK1 regulates 
transcription and proteasome-mediated degradation of the 
EIN3 (ETHYLENE INSENSITIVE3) transcription fac-
tor in the nucleus, and several types of transcription factors 
are involved in sugar-regulated transcription (Rolland et al., 
2006; Ramon et al., 2008). Therefore, the gene expression pat-
tern of three MYB transcription factors involved in aliphatic 
glucosinolate biosynthesis (MYB28, MYB29, and MYB76) 
was analysed in gin2-1 mutants, and a substantial decrease in 
the expression level in response to glucose was observed when 
compared with the wild type (Fig. 6C-E). This is undoubtedly 
another piece of evidence for HXK1-dependent induction 
of aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis by glucose signalling 
through MYB factors. </p>

<p>ABI5 is involved in the regulation of aliphatic 
glucosinolate biosynthesis by glucose </p>

<p>Previous studies have indicated that glucose signalling is a 
complex network, and cross-talk between glucose signalling 
and phytohormone signalling was elucidated (Gazzarrini 
and McCourt, 2001; Dekkers et al., 2008). ABA signalling 
and sugar sensing share several common components, and </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>0.45 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Total Aliphatic GS </p>

<p>nmol mg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>FW </p>

<p>Col-0 
abi5-7 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>(D) </p>

<p>MYB28 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>(B) 
(A) </p>

<p>(C) </p>

<p>water 
s orbitol 
glucose </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>MYB29 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>water 
s orbitol 
glucose </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>MYB76 </p>

<p>Relative expression </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Total aliphatic glucosinolate content and effect of glucose on the MYB28, MYB29, and MYB76 expression level in abi5-7. 
Arabidopsis seedlings (10-day-old) were treated with 3% glucose or sorbitol. (A) Samples were collected 3 d after treatment. (B-D) 
Samples were collected 18 h after treatment. Each data point represents the mean of three independent biological replicates per 
treatment (mean ±SE). Values not sharing a common letter are significantly different at P &lt; 0.05. Relative expression values are given 
compared with seedlings treated by water. </p>

<p>Glucose on aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis | 1107 </p>

<p>many glucose-insensitive mutants are also allelic to ABA 
biosynthetic or signalling mutants (Finkelstein and Gibson, 
2002; Rook et al., 2006). ABI5 (ABA-insensitive 5) encodes a 
transcription factor belonging to a large basic leucine zipper 
(bZIP) gene family, conferring on abi5-7 a glucose-insensi-
tive phenotype. ABI5 is therefore a putative glucose signal-
ling component downstream of HXK1 (Ramon et al., 2008; 
Reeves et al., 2011). In this study, abi5-7 was deficient in 
total aliphatic glucosinolate content before and after glucose 
treatment when compared with the wild type, as well as the 
expression level of MYB transcription factors after glucose 
treatment (Fig. 7). These results suggested that ABI5 might 
be involved in the regulation of aliphatic glucosinolate bio-
synthesis as a glucose signalling component downstream 
of HXK1. 
In conclusion, glucose induces the accumulation of ali-
phatic glucosinolate as a signalling molecule by modulating 
MYB transcription factors (MYB28 and MYB29), which 
participated in the regulation of aliphatic glucosinolate bio-
synthesis, with MYB28 as a master component. Furthermore, 
two distinct glucose sensors, HXK1 and RGS1, as well as 
ABI5, a putative glucose signalling component located down-
stream of HXK1, are proved to be involved in the network of 
glucose signalling to regulate aliphatic glucosinolate biosyn-
thesis. The abolishment of increased expression of MYB28, 
MYB29, and MYB76 induced by glucose in gin2-1 and abi5-7 
mutants in the present study indicates an interaction between 
HXK1 or ABI5 and the MYB factors involved in regulation 
of aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis. 
Further analysis of the interplay between HXK1/ABI5 
and MYB28/MYB29/MYB76 will help to elucidate the regu-
latory mechanism of aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis 
induced by glucose signalling. Another possibility of glucose 
enhancing sulphate assimilation should also be considered. 
Glucosinolates are sulphur-rich plant metabolites, and sulphur 
fertilization usually causes an increase in glucosinolate content 
(Falk et al., 2007). Previous reports showed that sugars (sucrose 
and glucose) at low concentration induced APR (adenosine 
5-phosphosulphate reductase) activity and enhanced sulphate 
uptake (Kopriva et al., 2002; Hesse et al., 2003; Kopriva, 2006). 
Therefore, further investigation is needed to elucidate whether 
glucose induces the accumulation of glucosinolates by regulat-
ing sulphate assimilation and uptake. </p>

<p>Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data are available at JXB online. 
Figure S1. Effect of glucose on accumulation of total ali-
phatic glucosinolates with the solid culture method. 
Figure S2. Effect of glucose on accumulation of total ali-
phatic glucosinolates during 36 h after treatment. 
Figure S3. Total content of aliphatic glucosinolates of 
mutants gin2-1 and rgs1-2 grown on solid culture medium. 
Figure S4. Effect of fructose on the accumulation of total 
aliphatic glucosinolates. 
Figure S5. Effect of mannose on the accumulation of total 
aliphatic glucosinolates. </p>

<p>Figure S6. Effect of glucose on the accumulation of total 
aliphatic glucosinolates in Arabidopsis cultured in half-
strength MS salt solution. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work was supported by grants from National Science 
Foundation of China (NO. 31270343), National Key 
Laboratory of Plant Molecular Genetics (2010-2011), 
National High-tech R&amp;D Program of China (863 program 
2008AA10Z111), Fok Ying Tong Education Foundation 
(104034), and NCET-05-0516. </p>







<p>Glucose on aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis | 1109 </p>



</text></tei>