<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3007589" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:45+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Despite California's 1994 statewide smoking ban, exposure to secondhand smoke (SHS) continues in California's Indian casinos. Few data are available 
on exposure to airborne fine particles (PM 2.5 ) in casinos, especially on a statewide basis. We sought to measure PM 2.5 concentrations in Indian casinos 
widely distributed across California, exploring differences due to casino size, separation of smoking and non-smoking areas, and area smoker density. 
A selection of 36 out of the 58 Indian casinos throughout California were each visited for 1-3 h on weekend or holiday evenings, using two or more 
concealed monitors to measure PM 2.5 concentrations every 10 s. For each casino, the physical dimensions and the number of patrons and smokers were 
estimated. As a preliminary assessment of representativeness, we also measured eight casinos in Reno, NV. The average PM 2.5 concentration for the 
smoking slot machine areas (63 mg/m 3 ) was nine times as high as outdoors (7 mg/m 3 ), whereas casino non-smoking restaurants (29 mg/m 3 ) were four times 
as high. Levels in non-smoking slot machine areas varied: complete physical separation reduced concentrations almost to outdoor levels, but two other 
separation types had mean levels that were 13 and 29 mg/m 3 , respectively, higher than outdoors. Elevated PM 2.5 concentrations in casinos can be 
attributed primarily to SHS. Average PM 2.5 concentrations during 0.5-1 h visits to smoking areas exceeded 35 mg/m 3 for 90% of the casino visits. 
Exposure to secondhand smoke (SHS) has been implicated as 
a risk factor for cardiovascular diseases, pulmonary mal-
function, lung cancer, and mortality (Brennan et al., 2004; 
Nazaroff and Singer, 2004; CDC, 2005; California EPA, 
2006; Surgeon General, 2006). Barnoya and Glantz (2005) 
found brief exposures (minutes to hours) to SHS were 
associated with adverse cardiovascular effects nearly as large 
(80-90%) as those experienced by chronic active smokers. 
SHS is a major indoor source of airborne fine particles 
(PM 2.5 ), which have been associated with a range of acute 
and chronic diseases (Pope et al., 2001, 2009; U.S. EPA, 
2006). Currently, 164 countries have adopted comprehensive 
or partial smoke-free legislation (Koh et al., 2007; WHO, 
2009). As of April 2009, 15 states in the United States, plus </p>

<p>Washington DC, have enacted smoke-free laws in all 
workplaces, including bars and restaurants (ANRF, 2009). 
California was the first state to enact a statewide ban on 
smoking in indoor workplaces. In 1994, California passed its 
Smoke-free Indoor Workplace Act, which prohibits smoking 
in enclosed places of employment (except tobacconists), 
including bars (1998) and restaurants. Some California 
towns and cities have subsequently passed stricter laws 
banning smoking outdoors near public buildings, in outdoor 
restaurant patios, and even in some apartment buildings. In 
2007, California adopted a statewide law banning smoking in 
cars if children are present. However, due to the sovereign 
nation status of Indian tribes, exposure to SHS continues in 
nearly all California Indian casinos. 
Indoor SHS in casinos imposes significant health risks on 
casino employees as well as on non-smoking patrons. 
Moreover, employees working on tribal reservations are 
not covered by California's worker safety laws (Dunstan, 
1998). Earlier studies have found post-work shift or post-visit 
increases in the nicotine metabolite, cotinine, in casino 
employees and patrons (Trout et al., 1998; Wakefield et al., 
2005; Abrams et al., 2006; Larsson et al., 2008; CDC, 2009; 
Repace, 2009). Two studies found increases in a tobacco-
specific carcinogen in non-smoking casino patrons and </p>

<p>Received 14 October 2009; accepted 17 December 2009; published online 
17 February 2010 </p>

<p>1. Address all correspondence to: Professor Lynn M. Hildemann, 
Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, Stanford University, 
473 Via Ortega, Rm. 391, Stanford, CA 94305, USA. 
Tel.: þ 1 650 723 0819. Fax: þ 1 650 723 7058. 
E-mail: hildemann@stanford.edu </p>

<p>Journal of Exposure Science and Environmental Epidemiology (2011) 21, 31-41 
r 2011 Nature America, Inc. All rights reserved 1559-0631/11 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/jes </p>

<p>dealers, respectively (Anderson et al., 2003; CDC, 2009). 
Other studies (Kado et al., 1991; Trout et al., 1998; 
Hammond, 1999) have examined airborne nicotine concen-
trations in casinos, and Larsson et al. (2008) reported that 
exposures for 87% of workers exceeded a nicotine threshold 
(0.5 mg/m 3 ) associated with health risks. A survey of London 
casino workers (Pilkington et al., 2007) reported respiratory 
and sensory irritation symptoms associated with SHS 
exposure. 
Exposures to SHS in hospitality locations and workplaces 
have been measured across the world (Siegel and Skeer, 
2003; Hyland et al., 2008; Lo´pez et al., 2008). However, the 
few published studies measuring fine particle concentrations 
inside casinos have considered relatively few casinos (Repace, 
2004, 2009). 
To the best of our knowledge, this study is the first to 
survey PM 2.5 exposures in casinos on a statewide basis. 
Using a standardized protocol, we discreetly measured PM 2.5 
inside a selection of 36 casinos spread throughout California 
(including smoking areas, non-smoking areas, and restau-
rants), as well as outdoors. We also evaluated the effective-
ness of different methods of separating the non-smoking 
from the smoking areas. Finally, as an initial exploration of 
whether the PM 2.5 levels measured in California might also 
reflect casinos in other locations, we surveyed eight casinos in 
Reno, NV. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Research Location and Sample Selection </p>

<p>We surveyed 36 out of the 58 California Indian casinos (12 
January to 25 December 2008), spanning locations across 
California (Figure 1). The locations, physical area, and the 
number of slot machines were tabulated for all 
58 casinos from California Indian casino official websites. 
Each casino was classified based on the reported number of 
slot machines, as follows: small (o500), medium (500-1400), 
or large (41400 slot machines). We sampled 10-15 casinos 
in each size range during nine trips covering different parts of 
the state. On each trip, we visited as many casinos as possible 
over a 3-8-day period. In addition, we visited what is, to the 
best of our knowledge, the only smoke-free Indian casino in 
California. We also surveyed, for comparison, eight casinos 
in Reno, NV, using the same sampling protocol. </p>

<p>Monitoring Protocol </p>

<p>Most casinos were sampled on weekend or holiday evenings, 
when occupancy was high. On each casino visit, two or more 
investigators carried concealed real-time (i.e. continuous) 
aerosol monitors (AM510 SidePak laser photometer; TSI, 
Shoreview, MN, USA) with a short intake (Tygon tubing) 
protruding from a handbag or pocket, with data logged </p>

<p>every 10 s. The monitors were equipped with a 2.5-mm size-
selective impactor. 
The sampling locations at each casino included (1) 
outdoors (10-min periods before-and-after indoor sampling), 
(2) smoking slot machine areas (one 30-min period for small 
casinos, two 30-min periods for medium or large casinos), (3) 
non-smoking slot machine areas (30 min), and (4) restaurants 
(B1 h). When sampling in smoking slot machine or non-
smoking slot machine locations, the investigators followed 
separate routes without returning to the same area. While 
outdoors or at restaurants, the investigators walked or sat 
side-by-side. The protocol included an additional collocation 
period (B10 min) in a non-smoking slot machine area or 
restaurant in which two or more monitors were placed side-
by-side to compare readings. A typical sampling event started 
at 1800-2000 hours and lasted for 1-4 h, depending on the 
size and complexity of the casino. </p>

<p>Quality Assurance of Aerosol Monitors </p>

<p>The SidePak monitors determine the mass concentration 
from the intensity of scattered laser light. The monitor has a 
lower detection limit of 1 mg/m 3 and an upper detection limit 
of 20,000 mg/m 3 (TSI, 2008). The light scattering properties 
of particles vary with the size and composition of particles. 
Thus, it is essential to calibrate for the type of particles being 
sampled. 
Before and after the field survey, we compared 12 SidePak 
monitors with gravimetric PM 2.5 measurements. Fresh SHS 
was introduced into a 3 m 3 chamber by a volunteer smoker, 
with four samples collected spanning a concentration range 
typical of indoor SHS levels (40-400 mg/m 3 ). The relative 
humidity was 40% and 47%, respectively, for the before-
and-after experiments. 
For each SHS level, we collected pairs of gravimetric 
PM 2.5 samples onto PTFE membrane filters (47 mm 
diameter, 2-mm pore size, Pall Corp., Ann Arbor, MI, 
USA) downstream of a cyclone separator, using critical 
orifices to maintain a stable flow rate through each filter. 
Flow rates were measured before and after by a primary flow 
(bubble) calibrator (Gilian Instrument Corp., West Caldwell, 
NJ, USA). 
Gravimetric filters were equilibrated for over 24 h at 
controlled relative humidity (B60%) and temperature 
(701F) and then weighed before-and-after sampling using a 
Mettler M3 Microbalance (Mettler-Toledo, Columbus, OH, 
USA). 
The slope from a linear regression of the gravimetric 
PM 2.5 versus each SidePak determined the multiplication 
factor (custom calibration factor) for rescaling the SidePak's 
data. For individual monitors, custom calibration factors 
ranged from 0.24 to 0.31, with an average of 0.29 
(SD ¼ 0.02) before and 0.28 (SD ¼ 0.02) after the field 
survey. R 2 values were all above 0.995; intercepts were 
close to zero. The average absolute deviation of calibration </p>

<p>Fine particles and smoking activity in casinos 
Jiang et al. </p>

<p> 
Journal of Exposure Science and Environmental Epidemiology (2011) 21(1) </p>

<p>factors between before-and-after experiments was 4% (range, 
0-8%; SD ¼ 3%). The average monitor precision was 3% 
(range, 1-12%; SD ¼ 3%). Our calibration factors, which 
were nearly identical to values found by Lee et al. (2008) 
for SHS with SidePak monitors, were applied to all casino 
measurements (relative humidity was always under 47%). 
We scaled the measurements for each individual monitor by 
multiplying by the average of the before-and-after calibration 
factors. </p>

<p>Counting Protocol and Casino Dimensions </p>

<p>For each casino sampled, one investigator F the counter F 
measured the casino dimensions, and counted slot machines, 
players, and active smokers, while one or more other 
investigators measured PM 2.5 concentrations carrying 
concealed SidePak monitors. For smaller casinos, the 
counter counted every slot machine, player, and active </p>

<p>smoker on the casino gaming floor by walking through 
smoking and non-smoking slot machine areas, for 30 min 
each. In casinos where counting the entire slot area was not 
feasible within 30 min, the counter counted in randomly 
selected rows of slot machines throughout a large portion of 
the gaming area. 
The occupancy (%) of a casino gaming area was 
calculated as: </p>

<p>Occupancy ð%Þ ¼ 
Total Number of Patrons 
Total Number of Slot Machines 
Â100% </p>

<p>ð1Þ </p>

<p>The active smoking prevalence (%) within the casino smoking 
area was defined as: </p>

<p>Active Smoking Prevalence ð%Þ </p>

<p>¼ 
Total Number of Active Smokers 
Total Number of Patrons 
Â100% 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>Figure 1. Map of California showing the locations and size categories of the 36 Indian casinos sampled. </p>

<p>Fine particles and smoking activity in casinos 
Jiang et al. </p>

<p>Journal of Exposure Science and Environmental Epidemiology (2011) 21(1) </p>

<p>
We measured the horizontal dimensions of each casino by 
calibrated foot pacing. Each active smoker was counted only 
once. The area smoker density (active smokers/100 m 2 ) was 
calculated as: </p>

<p>Area Smoker Density ðactive smokers=100 m 2 Þ </p>

<p>¼ 
100ÂTotal Number of Active Smokers 
Floor Area for Slot Machines ðm 2 Þ </p>

<p>ð3Þ </p>

<p>Data Analysis </p>

<p>We applied descriptive statistics, linear regression analysis, 
analysis of variance (ANOVA), paired t-test, and the 
Shapiro-Wilks test for normality. <rs id="software-2" type="software">SigmaPlot</rs> software, 
<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">Version 11.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Systat Software</rs>, San Jose, CA, USA), and 
the <rs id="software-1" type="software">R statistical package</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">Version 2.5.1</rs> (R Development 
Core Team, 2008) were used to perform the analyses. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>California Casino Sample Characteristics </p>

<p>The 58 casinos in California comprised 22 small, 15 medium, 
and 21 large ones. Our sample consisted of 11 small 
(including 1 smoke-free location), 10 medium, and 15 large 
casinos (Figure 1). The number of slot machines ranged from 
B200 to over 3000, and gaming floor areas ranged from 
B280 m 2 to over 65,000 m 2 . All but four of the casinos had 
slot machines on a single floor. The temperature and relative 
humidity inside each casino, measured by a digital Hygro-
Thermometer (Sunleaves, Bloomington, IN, USA), was 
70-801F and 16-46%, respectively. 
Occupancy and active smoking prevalence were obtained 
for 35 casino visits, and area smoker density for 31 visits 
(Table 1). The occupancy on weekend and holiday evenings 
averaged 48% (range, 12-87%); the active smoking 
prevalence averaged 11% (range, 5-25%); and the area 
smoker density averaged 2.3 active smokers/100 m 2 (range, 
0.5-5.3 active smokers/100 m 2 ). The mean occupancy in 
large casinos (60%) was significantly higher (one-way 
ANOVA, Po0.05) than in medium (43%) and small casinos 
(34%). However, the mean active smoking prevalence was 
significantly higher in small casinos (16%, versus 10% for 
large and medium casinos; Po0.05). Differences in the mean 
area smoker density by casino size were not statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>PM 2.5 Concentrations in Smoking Areas </p>

<p>Figure 2 shows an example of the PM 2.5 concentrations as a 
function of time measured in a casino. As the two 
investigators moved independently through the smoking 
areas, momentary differences in concentrations were sub-
stantial; however, the average values for each location were 
quite similar. </p>

<p>The mean PM 2.5 concentration over 0.5-1 h in the 
smoking sections ranged from 18 to 183 mg/m 3 and averaged 
63 mg/m 3 , with 50% of the visits exceeding 50 mg/m 3 ; 20% 
exceeding 80 mg/m 3 ; and 5% exceeding 100 mg/m 3 . The 
average PM 2.5 concentrations in smoking areas among the 
three casino sizes were not significantly different. 
Results from duplicate visits to four casinos (LE, LH, MB, 
and MH, Table 1) showed variations in indoor PM 2.5 
concentrations between visits. These may be attributable, for 
example, to changes in smoking activity and/or occupancy 
immediately before the sampling events, which would change 
the initial background PM 2.5 level. Three of the four first 
visits involved sampling and counting in just a portion of the 
casino; thus spatial heterogeneity could also be a factor. 
Shorter-term exposures ranged much higher. For example, 
the maximum 1-min PM 2.5 concentrations in casino smoking 
areas ranged from 44 to 291 mg/m 3 , with an average of the 
maxima of 116 mg/m 3 (SD ¼ 55 mg/m 3 ). The maximum 
1-min concentrations were 12-223 mg/m 3 higher than the 
0.5-1 h mean concentrations for the 39 visits in casino 
smoking areas (Supplementary Table S1). 
The relationship between average incremental concentra-
tions (concentration greater than the outdoors) in smoking 
areas and the area smoker densities is shown in Figure 3. 
Significant scatter in the data was expected due to differences 
in building characteristics that were not measured, such as the 
ventilation rate and ceiling heights. The linear regression 
results indicated area smoker density was positively asso-
ciated with incremental smoking PM 2.5 concentrations in 
California casinos with r ¼ 0.52. This result implied that 27% 
of the variation in the incremental PM 2.5 concentrations 
could be explained by the area smoker density (R 2 ¼ 0.27; 
n ¼ 31). 
Figure 4 shows frequency distributions of the average 
PM 2.5 measurements from the casinos at four locations: 
(1) smoking slot machine areas, (2) non-smoking slot 
machine areas, (3) outdoors, and (4) restaurants. The relative 
straightness of the frequency distributions in locations (1), 
(2), and (3) indicated a tendency toward a lognormal 
distribution. With the exception of one outlier, indoor 
smoking concentrations could be treated as normally 
distributed, but outdoor data did not fit a normal distribution 
(Shapiro-Wilks test; Po0.001). The distribution of the 
relatively small sample of restaurant data (n ¼ 20) appeared 
neither normal nor lognormal. </p>

<p>Comparison of Smoking Versus Non-smoking Areas </p>

<p>In 23 of the 35 smoking casinos, there were signs marking 
slot machine areas prohibiting smoking. The average PM 2.5 
concentration in the non-smoking areas was 22 mg/m 3 (range, 
1-81 mg/m 3 ). We compared three methods of separation from 
the smoking areas: (1) no physical separation F the non-
smoking section was not in a separate room; (2) semi-
separation F a separate non-smoking room but no closing </p>

<p>Fine particles and smoking activity in casinos 
Jiang et al. </p>

<p> 
Journal of Exposure Science and Environmental Epidemiology (2011) 21(1) </p>

<p>doors; and (3) complete physical separation F a separate 
room with closing doors. The average PM 2.5 levels shown 
in Figure 5 for non-smoking areas with no separation 
(43 mg/m 3 , n ¼ 8) and with semi-separation (20 mg/m 3 , n ¼ 9) 
were significantly higher than in areas with complete 
separation (7.9 mg/m 3 , n ¼ 10) (one-way ANOVA, Po0.05). </p>

<p>On average, the PM 2.5 concentration in casino gaming 
areas with smokers was 36 mg/m 3 higher than in non-
smoking gaming areas. In non-smoking areas with no 
separation, the average PM 2.5 concentration was not 
significantly lower than the adjacent smoking areas. In con-
trast, PM 2.5 concentrations in semi-separated or completely </p>

<p>Table 1. Summary statistics for the 36 California casinos in the statewide survey. </p>

<p>Casino ID a 
Average concentrations (mg/m 3 ) 
O c c u p a n c y 
(%) </p>

<p>Active smoking 
prevalence (%) </p>

<p>Area smoker density 
(active smokers/100 m 2 ) 
Smoking 
Outdoor 
Non-smoking 
Restaurant </p>

<p>LA 
42.7 
1.6 
15.6 
23.1 
87.1 
4.9 
1.41 
LB 
39.9 
19.0 
24.2 
19.0 
54.4 
6.3 
1.38 
LC 
86.7 
9.6 
7.9 
60.5 
39.9 
9.9 
1.78 
LD 
35.9 
6.9 
16.3 
36.4 
43.5 
5.0 
1.00 
LE b 
40.8 
9.5 
25.5 
18.8 
52.8 
7.5 
F </p>

<p>LE2 c 
88.8 
29.7 
44.5 
20.7 
70.7 
6.3 
2.15 
LF 
49.3 
16.3 
4.4 
35.6 
48.7 
6.2 
1.79 
LG 
47.4 
1.3 
F 
1.2 
24.1 
18.7 
1.70 
LH b 
42.0 
8.5 
3.9 
34.4 
47.1 
8.9 
F </p>

<p>LH2 c 
45.8 
2.3 
12.3 
41.1 
67.5 
9.6 
2.56 
LI 
57.4 
2.2 
1.0 
4.0 
78.6 
8.3 
3.16 
LJ 
74.0 
4.2 
9.8 
5.1 
69.0 
14.1 
4.54 
LK 
109.6 
5.3 
F 
F 
63.5 
14.1 
4.18 
LM 
72.1 
4.4 
6.5 
F 
62.5 
17.5 
5.09 
LN 
62.4 
1.3 
57.2 
34.6 
87.2 
7.7 
3.15 
LO 
77.0 
7.4 
75.6 
56.9 
F 
F 
F </p>

<p>LP 
75.8 
1.3 
24.6 
F 
F 
F 
F </p>

<p>MA 
73.4 
3.3 
F 
64.1 
37.0 
18.9 
F </p>

<p>MB b 
30.2 
4.4 
5.0 
8.0 
17.6 
11.4 
F </p>

<p>MB2 c 
21.2 
3.4 
6.6 
F 
24.1 
10.3 
0.98 
MC 
45.7 
12.2 
16.5 
19.4 
39.6 
9.1 
1.39 
MD 
60.5 
2.9 
32.6 
43.7 
19.6 
10.8 
1.27 
ME 
66.0 
4.5 
F 
F 
29.1 
5.0 
0.48 
MF 
68.2 
7.9 
81.2 
F 
73.0 
10.0 
1.84 
MG 
94.1 
2.4 
32.1 
F 
77.8 
8.6 
3.16 
MH 
83.8 
5.4 
8.4 
F 
52.8 
8.8 
1.51 
MH2 c 
75.5 
7.6 
14.1 
F 
50.5 
7.9 
1.29 
MI 
44.0 
6.7 
16.5 
F 
F 
F 
F </p>

<p>MJ 
52.7 
6.7 
11.2 
22.5 
51.8 
7.4 
1.07 
SA 
48.2 
5.8 
F 
F 
5.7 
10.0 
0.46 
SB 
29.2 
5.1 
23.1 
F 
23.7 
25.4 
3.96 
SC 
76.6 
13.6 
F 
F 
41.8 
14.4 
3.82 
SD 
63.7 
3.5 
F 
F 
62.2 
15.7 
5.25 
SE 
70.8 
7.4 
25.2 
20.4 
33.1 
19.8 
2.91 
SF 
64.5 
3.2 
F 
F 
43.5 
9.9 
1.68 
SG 
42.1 
7.3 
F 
F 
20.1 
21.4 
1.83 
SH 
105.0 
4.4 
F 
F 
61.0 
13.1 
4.86 
SI 
18.5 
0.8 
F 
F 
16.9 
10.2 
0.93 
SJ 
183.4 
14.1 
F 
F 
F 
F 
F </p>

<p>NS 
F 
4.9 
4.8 
F 
26.0 
F 
F </p>

<p>Mean d 
63.2 
6.7 
22.3 
28.5 
47.9 
11.2 
2.34 </p>

<p>SD d 
29.4 
5.7 
20.7 
18.4 
21.5 
5.1 
1.41 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>IDs starting with ''L'', ''M'', and ''S'' indicate large, medium, and small casinos, respectively. ''NS'' is the only non-smoking casino. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Sampling and counting took place only in a portion of the casino, of an undetermined area. 
c Second visits for four casinos. </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Calculated only for smoking casinos. </p>

<p>Fine particles and smoking activity in casinos 
Jiang et al. </p>

<p>Journal of Exposure Science and Environmental Epidemiology (2011) 21(1) </p>

<p>
separated non-smoking areas were significantly lower than in 
the nearby smoking areas (paired t-test, Po0.01). 
For those casinos that have both smoking and non-
smoking slot machine areas (n ¼ 27), we examined how 
strongly the smoking areas affected the nearby non-smoking 
areas. We chose 60 mg/m 3 , a value close to the median 
(57.4 mg/m 3 ) to subdivide these casinos into two groups of </p>

<p>approximately equal size: the low concentration casinos 
(n ¼ 14) had average PM 2.5 levels below 60 mg/m 3 in the 
smoking areas, and the high concentration casinos (n ¼ 13) 
were above 60 mg/m 3 in the smoking areas (Figure 6). For all 
three non-smoking separation types, low concentration 
casinos had the lower average PM 2.5 levels. The difference 
in the average non-smoking PM 2.5 level between low 
concentration casinos and high concentration casinos was 
greatest for areas with no separation, and smallest for 
areas with complete physical separation. Thus, PM 2.5 levels 
in smoking areas had a greater impact on adjacent non-
smoking areas if no physical barriers existed between the two 
sections. </p>

<p>PM 2.5 Concentrations for Outdoors, Restaurants, Other 
Locations </p>

<p>The PM 2.5 concentrations measured outdoors averaged 
7 mg/m 3 ; with one exception (during a nearby forest fire), 
all outdoor locations were below 19 mg/m 3 (Table 1). On 
average, the PM 2.5 concentration in indoor smoking areas 
was 56 mg/m 3 higher than outdoors. Compared with outdoor 
measurements, the average PM 2.5 concentration in non-
smoking areas was 36 mg/m 3 higher for no separation, 
12 mg/m 3 higher for semi-separation (both statistically 
significant, Po0.01), and 1 mg/m 3 higher for complete 
separation (not statistically significant). 
The mean PM 2.5 level of 29 mg/m 3 in the non-smoking 
restaurants (n ¼ 20), where children were often present, was 
22 mg/m 3 above the average outdoor concentration, and 7 mg/m 3 
higher than the non-smoking gaming areas. 
In three of the smoking casinos, the mean PM 2.5 
concentrations in non-smoking poker rooms were 64, 22, </p>

<p>Figure 2. A time-series plot illustrating the sampling protocol performed by two investigators visiting three locations in a casino. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Linear regression analysis of incremental PM 2.5 concentra-
tions (concentrations above the outdoor levels) in the smoking areas of 
California casinos versus area smoking densities (n ¼ 31). Regression 
equation: PM 2.5 concentration ¼ 8.3 Â (area smoker density) þ 34.7 
(R 2 ¼ 0.27; r ¼ 0.52). The star symbol represents the average 
incremental PM 2.5 concentration for the average smoker density 
observed in seven Reno smoking casinos. </p>

<p>Fine particles and smoking activity in casinos 
Jiang et al. </p>

<p> 
Journal of Exposure Science and Environmental Epidemiology (2011) 21(1) </p>

<p>and 14 mg/m 3 . Other non-smoking locations measured 
included a casino delicatessen (11 mg/m 3 ), bowling alley 
(31 mg/m 3 ), and bingo room (10 mg/m 3 ). </p>

<p>A Smoke-Free Casino </p>

<p>There was one small casino in California that banned smoking 
indoors (see star symbol on map in Figure 1). The average 
PM 2.5 level inside this casino was 5.4 mg/m 3 , comparable to the 
mean outdoor concentration (5.5 mg/m 3 ). The indoor PM 2.5 
level in this smoke-free casino was less than 1/10th the average in 
the smoking areas of the 35 other casinos, and 1/4th the average 
in the non-smoking areas of the casinos that allowed smoking. </p>

<p>PM 2.5 Concentrations in Reno Casinos </p>

<p>To initially explore, using the same sampling and monitoring 
protocol, whether the relationship seen in the California 
casinos between incremental PM 2.5 concentrations and area 
smoker density might hold for other locations, we also 
measured eight non-Indian casinos in Reno, including one 
smoke-free casino (Supplementary Tables S2 and S3). 
For the seven Reno smoking casinos, the average PM 2.5 
level in the smoking areas during weekend evenings was 
37 mg/m 3 , 30 times as high as outdoors (1.2 mg/m 3 ). The 
restaurants averaged 17 mg/m 3 (n ¼ 5). The mean PM 2.5 
levels for designated non-smoking areas were 10 and 7 mg/m 3 
for two areas with semi-separation, lower than in one other 
area with no physical separation (22 mg/m 3 ). Casino 
occupancy averaged 38% (range, 31-49%), active smoking </p>

<p>Smoking Slot Machine Areas </p>

<p>Cumulative Frequency (%) </p>

<p>PM 
2.5 Concentration (µg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>PM 
2.5 Concentration (µg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Nonsmoking Slot Machine Areas </p>

<p>Cumulative Frequency (%) </p>

<p>PM </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>Concentration (µg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Outdoors </p>

<p>Cumulative Frequency (%) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Restaurants </p>

<p>Cumulative Frequency (%) </p>

<p>PM </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>Concentration (µg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Mean = 63.2 µg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>SD = 29.4 µg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Median = 62.4 µg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>n = 39 </p>

<p>Mean = 22.3 µg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>SD = 20.7 µg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Median = 16.3µg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>n = 27 </p>

<p>Mean = 6.7 µg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>SD = 5.7 µg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Median = 5.3 µg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>n = 39 </p>

<p>Mean = 28.5 µg/m 3 
SD = 18.4 µg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Median = 22.8 µg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>n = 20 </p>

<p>1 
5 10 20 30 
50 
70 80 90 95 98 99 
2 </p>

<p>1 
5 10 20 30 
50 
70 80 90 95 98 99 
2 </p>

<p>2 
10 20 30 
50 
70 80 
90 95 98 
5 </p>

<p>2 
10 20 30 
50 
70 80 
90 95 98 
5 </p>

<p>Figure 4. Frequency distribution plots for PM 2.5 concentrations in the (a) smoking areas, (b) non-smoking areas, (c) outdoors, and (d) restaurants 
of the 39 visits to 35 smoking Indian casinos in California. </p>

<p>Separation Type </p>

<p>No Separation 
Semi-Separation Complete Separation </p>

<p>NonSmoking PM 
2.5 Concentration (µg/m 3 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>Figure 5. Box plots comparing average PM 2.5 levels in casino non-
smoking gaming areas stratified by three separation methods. Boxes 
represent the interquartile range (25th-75th percentiles, median 
indicated by horizontal line), and whiskers extend to the 5th and 
95th percentiles. </p>

<p>Fine particles and smoking activity in casinos 
Jiang et al. </p>

<p>Journal of Exposure Science and Environmental Epidemiology (2011) 21(1) </p>

<p>
prevalence averaged 10% (range, 7-12%), and area smoker 
density averaged 0.9 active smokers/100 m 2 (range, 0.4-1.3 
active smokers/100 m 2 ). Temperature and relative humidity 
inside these casinos were 70-751F and 20-30%, respectively. 
The average PM 2.5 concentration inside the one non-smoking 
Reno casino was 0.6 mg/m 3 , compared with an average outdoor 
concentration of 1.2 mg/m 3 ; the occupancy was 20%. 
We compared the PM 2.5 concentrations in the smoking areas 
of Reno casinos to California casinos, accounting for smoker 
density (Figure 3). The average incremental smoking concen-
tration of Reno casinos (shown as a star) falls within the 95% 
confidence interval about the mean for the California casinos. 
Thus, when the effects of outdoor concentrations and smoker 
density are included, the average PM 2.5 concentration 
measured in smoking areas of these Reno casinos is consistent 
with the relationship for the means of California casinos. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The active smoking prevalence averaged 11% for California 
casinos and 10% for Reno casinos, higher than the average </p>

<p>of 8.5% in a Delaware casino (Repace, 2004), and 7% at 
casinos in Las Vegas, Reno, and Lake Tahoe (Pritsos et al., 
2008) and in Pennsylvania (Repace, 2009). Repace (2009) 
estimates the ''adult smoking prevalence'' as three times the 
active smoking prevalence, making the adult smoking 
prevalence in California smoking casinos much higher than 
the state's adult smoking prevalence of 13% (CDPH, 2008). 
We found a positive correlation between area smoker 
density and incremental PM 2.5 concentration. However, the 
area smoker density alone is not sufficient to predict 
incremental PM 2.5 concentrations. Measurements of other 
building characteristics, such as the ventilation rates and 
ceiling heights, are necessary to better interpret indoor PM 2.5 
levels. For example, Repace (2009) has used the indoor and 
outdoor CO 2 difference, along with occupancy counts, to 
assess ventilation rates in casinos, and the results suggest that 
the PM 2.5 concentration is inversely proportional to the 
ventilation rate per occupant. In an unpublished analysis, 
Repace and coworkers found that the R 2 value of the 
regression between incremental PM 2.5 concentrations and the 
ratio of smoker density to ventilation rate per occupant was 
close to 0.8 (n ¼ 7). Measuring CO 2 concentrations and </p>

<p>Separation Type </p>

<p>Nonsmoking PM 
2.5 Concentrations (µg/m 3 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>Low Concentration Casinos </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>High Concentration Casinos </p>

<p>No 
Separation </p>

<p>Semi-
Separation </p>

<p>Complete 
Separation </p>

<p>No 
Separation </p>

<p>Semi-
Separation </p>

<p>Complete 
Separation </p>

<p>Nonsmoking PM 2.5 Concentration at Low Casinos </p>

<p>Nonsmoking PM 2.5 Concentration at High Casinos </p>

<p>Average Nonsmoking PM 2.5 concentration at Low Casinos </p>

<p>Average Nonsmoking PM 2.5 concentration at High Casinos </p>

<p>Figure 6. Interaction effects of PM 2.5 levels in casino smoking areas and three methods of separating the non-smoking areas on PM 2.5 levels in 
casino non-smoking gaming areas. Average PM 2.5 concentrations in smoking slot machine areas for low concentration casinos were below 60 mg/m 3 
and for high concentration casinos were above 60 mg/m 3 . </p>

<p>Fine particles and smoking activity in casinos 
Jiang et al. </p>

<p> 
Journal of Exposure Science and Environmental Epidemiology (2011) 21(1) </p>

<p>including ventilation estimates in regression analysis is 
expected to improve our ability to explain variation in 
PM 2.5 levels. 
The only short-term U.S. EPA National Air Quality 
Standard for PM 2.5 is a 24-h standard for ambient (outdoor) 
levels, set at 35 mg/m 3 . We found that 90% of the average 
0.5-1 h PM 2.5 concentrations measured on weekend and 
holiday evenings in the smoking areas of California casinos 
exceeded 35 mg/m 3 . If we consider the highest 1 h average 
PM 2.5 concentration of 183 mg/m 3 measured in a casino 
smoking area, a person (such as an employee) spending 8 h in 
the casino with zero exposure for the remaining 16 h would 
experience a 24-h exposure of 61 mg/m 3 , well above the U.S. 
EPA standard. 
The range of mean PM 2.5 concentrations for the California 
casino smoking areas was similar to the range for three Las 
Vegas (CDC, 2009), one Delaware (Repace, 2004), and three 
Pennsylvania casinos (Repace, 2009). Variations among 
study sites were expected due to differences in smoker 
densities, ventilation, and building characteristics. Variations 
in PM 2.5 for duplicate visits to a given study site also were 
expected, and were observed for four casinos. In addition 
to variables such as smoker activity, occupancy, and 
spatial heterogeneity, differences in the initial indoor 
concentrations (e.g. due to higher or lower smoking activity 
before the start of sampling) could also contribute. Ott et al. 
(1996) also found substantial variability in respirable particle 
concentrations for 26 visits to a sports tavern that allowed 
smoking. 
The fine particle levels we observed in casino smoking 
areas were also comparable to levels previously observed in 
other public places. For example, the study measuring PM 3.5 
on 26 visits to a sports tavern before the California smoking 
ban yielded concentrations of 25-180 mg/m 3 with an incre-
mental mean concentration of 57 mg/m 3 (Ott et al., 1996), 
almost identical to the incremental mean concentration of 
56 mg/m 3 for our Indian casinos. In Italy, before a smoking 
ban, average PM 2.5 concentrations included 47 mg/m 3 in 
14 bars, 111 mg/m 3 in 12 restaurants, and 150 mg/m 3 in 8 video 
game parlors (Valente et al., 2007). A German study reported 
median PM 2.5 levels of 178 mg/m 3 for 11 restaurants, and 
192 mg/m 3 for 7 pubs (Bolte et al., 2008). In smoking areas of 
two coffee shops in Taiwan, median PM 2.5 concentrations 
were 106 and 80 mg/m 3 (Lung et al., 2004). In UK bars and 
pubs with mechanical ventilation, the median PM 2.5 
concentration was 57 mg/m 3 when smoking was allowed 
(Carrington et al., 2003). In Texas, before a smoking ban, the 
average PM 2.5 level was 151 mg/m 3 in 17 bars (Waring and 
Siegel, 2007). 
Our findings indicate that non-smoking areas with no 
physical barriers provided little protection from exposures to 
SHS; this has also been reported for other public locations 
(Cains et al., 2004; Lung et al., 2004). Designating separate 
rooms as non-smoking areas, especially with closed doors, </p>

<p>was somewhat effective in reducing PM 2.5 levels. However, 
for 23 of 27 visits, the mean PM 2.5 levels in indoor non-smoking 
areas were higher than outdoors. Similarly, Cains et al. (2004) 
reported that separated non-smoking rooms in Australian social 
and gaming clubs reduced PM 10 concentrations more than non-
smoking areas contiguous with the smoking areas. Other 
previous studies (Carrington et al., 2003; Cenko et al., 2004) 
have concluded that a separated ventilation system was not 
effective, and that exposure to SHS in non-smoking areas may 
still represent an appreciable health risk. 
Determining exposure is essential for assessing health 
effects. There has been increasing interest in health effects 
associated with very short-term (i.e. a few minutes) exposure 
to SHS (Barnoya and Glantz, 2005). In 2001, Pope et al. 
found that a 2-h exposure to SHS with an average PM 3 level 
of 78 mg/m 3 was associated with decrements in heart rate 
variability and increased cardiac vulnerability. In our study, 7 
out of 39 casino visits of 0.5-1 h had mean PM 2.5 
concentrations higher than 78 mg/m 3 . A comprehensive 
review (Pope and Dockery, 2006) found evidence that a 
20 mg/m 3 increase in long-term average outdoor PM 2.5 
concentration is associated with a 20% increase in cardio-
pulmonary mortality. If the toxicity of PM 2.5 from SHS is 
similar to outdoor PM 2.5 , then frequent exposure to the 
average elevation of 56 mg/m 3 observed in smoking areas of 
California casinos is likely to be associated with significant 
increases in adverse health effects. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>PM 2.5 concentrations in the smoking areas of 35 smoking Indian 
casinos in California averaged 63 mg/m 3 , 3 times as high as in the 
non-smoking areas (22 mg/m 3 ), 2 times as high as in casino 
restaurants (29 mg/m 3 ), and 410 times as high as in the smoke-
free casino (5.4 mg/m 3 ). These results, taken together, strongly 
indicate that SHS is the predominant cause of elevated PM 2.5 
concentrations in the casinos sampled. In addition, we found: </p>

<p>Average concentrations in indoor smoking areas, non-
smoking areas, and restaurants were, respectively, 56, 15 
and 22 mg/m 3 above outdoor levels. 
In contrast, the two non-smoking casinos measured (one 
in Reno and one in California) had indoor concentrations 
that were as low as outdoors. 
For 90% of the casino visits, mean concentrations in 
smoking areas averaged over 0.5-1 h exceeded 35 mg/m 3 . 
Separated non-smoking rooms with closing doors had 
lower PM 2.5 concentrations than rooms with open doors 
or non-smoking areas with no physical separation. 
The indoor PM 2.5 mean concentration of 7 Reno non-
Indian casinos was consistent with mean concentrations in 
the smoking areas of 35 California Indian casinos when 
adjusted for outdoor levels and area smoker density. </p>

<p>Fine particles and smoking activity in casinos 
Jiang et al. </p>

<p>Journal of Exposure Science and Environmental Epidemiology (2011) 21(1) </p>

<p>
The results of this study represent PM 2.5 concentrations 
measured in single visits on weekend and holiday evenings in 
slot machine areas and restaurants of California Indian 
casinos. As our results illuminate the potential health risks 
for people spending time inside smoking casinos, they are 
valuable to casino workers, unions, owners, the general 
public, and government agencies, who make decisions on 
smoking bans. Exposure to the average elevation of 56 mg/m 3 
observed in smoking areas of California casinos is likely 
to be associated with significant increases in adverse health 
effects. In addition to characterizing PM 2.5 concentrations at 
other times and locations, future studies should more 
intensively examine casino worker exposures, the impact of 
building characteristics, and particle levels before-and-after 
smoking bans. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>Mr. Repace is an international secondhand smoke consultant to 
governmental and private entities, and has served as an expert 
witness in litigation between workers injured by secondhand 
smoke and casinos, as well as the tobacco industry. The other 
authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We acknowledge the Flight Attendant Medical Research 
Institute for supporting this research, and Le verne McClure, 
John Moye and Thivanka Muthumalage for sampling some 
casinos. This paper represents the views of the authors and not 
necessarily those of the sponsor. Mention of commercial 
products does not constitute endorsement or recommendation. </p>



<p> 
Journal of Exposure Science and Environmental Epidemiology (2011) 21(1) </p>



<p>Fine particles and smoking activity in casinos 
Jiang et al. </p>

<p>Journal of Exposure Science and Environmental Epidemiology (2011) 21(1) </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>