<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3065992" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The genus Plagiostoma (Gnomoniaceae, Diaporthales) includes 
microscopic fungi that inhabit the leaves, stems, twigs, and branches 
of woody and herbaceous plants from a range of families including 
the Betulaceae, Euphorbiaceae, Geraniaceae, Hippocastanaceae, 
Oleaceae, Polygonaceae, Salicaceae, Sapindaceae, and 
Staphylaceae in temperate regions of the Northern Hemisphere 
(Sogonov et al. 2008). Although some species of Plagiostoma 
cause diseases, most do not show symptoms prior to production 
of perithecia on dead tissues. Described by Fuckel (1870), 
the morphological concept of Plagiostoma remained relatively 
unchanged (Barr 1978, Monod 1983) until recently. Multigene 
phylogenetic studies suggest that the genus Plagiostoma forms 
a highly supported monophyletic clade that includes the type 
species of Plagiostoma, P. euphorbiae, and the type species of 
Cryptodiaporthe, C. aesculi, among others (Mejía et al. 2008,  Sogonov et al. 2008). Sogonov et al. (2008) included 13 species 
in the genus Plagiostoma, several of which were previously placed 
in Cryptodiaporthe. 
A brief historical account of the major taxonomic treatments 
of Plagiostoma and Cryptodiaporthe illustrates the views of 
these genera through time. Fuckel (1870) proposed the genus 
Plagiostoma for sphaericeaous species characterised by 
flattened perithecia oriented horizontally having short, lateral, 
erumpent necks. Fuckel (1870) included the genera Ceratostoma, 
Gnomonia, Linospora, Melanospora, and Rhaphidospora together 
with Plagiostoma in the tribe Ceratostomeae of the Sphaeriacei. In 
his original description of Plagiostoma, Fuckel (1870) included four </p>

<p>species, P. euphorbiae, P. petiolicola, P devexum, and P. suspecta. 
Fuckel's concept of Plagiostoma was followed by Höhnel (1917)  and von Arx (1951) who, like Fuckel, considered Plagiostoma to 
be relatively closely related to Gnomonia, the name on which the 
Gnomoniaceae is based. These authors differentiated Gnomonia 
from Plagiostoma mainly by orientation of the perithecial neck. 
Gnomonia was characterised by having central, upright, perithecial 
necks in contrast to species of Plagiostoma with eccentric, 
laterally oriented, perithecial necks. In her treatment of the order 
Diaporthales, Barr (1978) followed Fuckel's concept of Plagiostoma 
and placed Gnomonia and Plagiostoma in the same suborder 
Gnomoniineae but in different families, i.e. Gnomonia in the 
Gnomoniaceae and Plagiostoma in the Valsaceae. The Valsaceae 
was defined based on having "beaks oblique or lateral, erumpent 
separately or converging through stromatic disc" (Barr, 1978 p.  15). Barr (1978) made nine new combinations in Plagiostoma 
expanding the number of species in the genus to 13.  In his monograph of the Gnomoniaceae, Monod (1983)  accepted most species treated by Barr (1978). However, Monod 
considered that the typification of Plagiostoma as P. euphorbiae 
by Höhnel (1917) was not representative of Plagiostoma because 
the perithecial necks of this species are eccentric rather than 
lateral as stipulated by Fuckel (1870). Monod (1983) transferred 
P. euphorbiae to the genus Gnomonia and re-typified Plagiostoma 
with P. devexum. In agreement with Barr (1991) and Sogonov et al.  (2008) the typification of the genus Plagiostoma with P. euphorbiae 
by Höhnel (1917) is accepted here because this typification 
predates Monod (1983) and is in accordance with Article 10 of the 
International Code of Botanical Nomenclature (McNeill et al. 2006). </p>

<p>A systematic account of the genus Plagiostoma (Gnomoniaceae, Diaporthales) 
based on morphology, host-associations, and a four-gene phylogeny </p>

<p>L.C. Mejía 
1, 2, 3* , L.A. Castlebury 
1 , A.Y. Rossman 
1 , M.V. Sogonov 
4 and J.F. White, Jr. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 Systematic Mycology &amp; Microbiology Laboratory, USDA-ARS, Rm. 304, B010A, 10300 Baltimore Ave., Beltsville, MD 20705, USA; 
2 Department of Plant Biology and Pathology, 
Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ 08901, USA; 
3 Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute Apartado 0843-03092 Balboa, Ancon, Republic of Panama; 
4 EMSL Analytical, 
Inc., 10768 Baltimore Ave., Beltsville, MD 20705, USA </p>

<p>*Correspondence: Luis Mejía, MejiaLC@si.edu </p>

<p>Abstract: Members of the genus Plagiostoma inhabit leaves, stems, twigs, and branches of woody and herbaceous plants predominantly in the temperate Northern Hemisphere. 
An account of all known species of Plagiostoma including Cryptodiaporthe is presented based on analyses of morphological, cultural, and DNA sequence data. Multigene 
phylogenetic analyses of DNA sequences from four genes (β-tubulin, ITS, rpb2, and tef1-α) revealed eight previously undescribed phylogenetic species and an association 
between a clade composed of 11 species of Plagiostoma and the host family Salicaceae. In this paper these eight new species of Plagiostoma are described, four species are 
redescribed, and four new combinations are proposed. A key to the 25 accepted species of Plagiostoma based on host, shape, and size of perithecia, perithecial arrangement 
in the host, and microscopic characteristics of the asci and ascospores is provided. Disposition of additional names in Cryptodiaporthe and Plagiostoma is also discussed. </p>

<p>Key words: Ascomycota, Betulaceae, epitypification, Fraxinus, new species, phylogeny, Salicaceae, Sordariomycetidae. 
Taxonomic novelties: Plagiostoma dilatatum L.C. Mejía, sp. nov., Plagiostoma exstocollum L.C. Mejía, sp. nov., Plagiostoma imperceptibile L.C. Mejía, sp. nov., Plagiostoma 
oregonense L.C. Mejía, sp. nov., Plagiostoma ovalisporum L.C. Mejía, sp. nov., Plagiostoma samuelsii L.C. Mejía, sp. nov., Plagiostoma versatile L.C. Mejía &amp; Sogonov, sp. 
nov., Plagiostoma yunnanense L.C. Mejía &amp; Zhu L. Yang, sp. nov., Plagiostoma apiculatum (Wallr.) L.C. Mejía, comb. nov., Plagiostoma convexum (Preuss) L.C. Mejía, comb. 
nov., Plagiostoma populinum (Fuckel) L.C. Mejía, comb. nov., Plagiostoma pulchellum (Sacc. &amp; Briard) L.C. Mejía, comb. nov. </p>

<p>212 </p>

<p>Mejía et al. </p>

<p>Taxon 
Specimen Culture 
Country 
Host 
Collector β-tubulin ITS 
rpb2 
tef1-α </p>

<p>Apiognomonia hystrix 
CBS-H 11343 CBS 911.79 
Switzerland 
Acer 
pseudoplatanus </p>

<p>M. Monod 
GU366973 DQ313549 EU219260 GU353957 </p>

<p>Apiognomonia veneta 
NA 
CBS 897.79 
Switzerland 
Platanus orientalis M. Monod 
GU377974 DQ313532 EU219259 GU353958 
Plagiostoma aesculi 
BPI 748430 CBS 109765 
Austria 
Aesculus 
hippocastaneum </p>

<p>W. Jaklitsch GU367021 DQ323530 EU199138 GU354004 </p>

<p>BPI 878950 CBS 126127 
(= LCM 447.01) </p>

<p>Germany 
Aesculus 
hippocastaneum </p>

<p>L.C. Mejía 
GU367019 GU367076 GU367110 GU354002 </p>

<p>BPI 878950 LCM 447b.01 Germany 
Aesculus 
hippocastaneum </p>

<p>L.C. Mejía 
GU367020 GU367077 GU367111 GU354003 </p>

<p>BPI 840942 CBS 121905 
Austria 
Aesculus 
hippocastaneum </p>

<p>W. Jaklitsch GU367022 EU254994 EU219269 GU354005 </p>

<p>Plagiostoma amygdalinae 
NA 
CBS 791.79 
Switzerland 
Euphorbia 
amygdaloides </p>

<p>M. Monod 
GU367030 EU254995 GU367113 GU354012 </p>

<p>Plagiostoma apiculatum 
BPI 747938 CBS 109775 
(= AR 3455) </p>

<p>Austria 
Salix sp. 
W. Jaklitsch GU367008 DQ323529 EU199141 GU353990 </p>

<p>BPI 878951 LCM 393.01 
France 
Salix dasyclados L.C. Mejía 
GU367010 GU367067 GU367101 GU353992 
BPI 878952 CBS 126126 
(= LCM 436.01) </p>

<p>USA: WA 
Salix sitchensis 
L.C. Mejía 
GU367009 GU367066 GU367100 GU353991 </p>

<p>Plagiostoma barriae 
BPI 878954 LCM 601.01 
USA: WA 
Acer 
macrophyllum </p>

<p>L.C. Mejía 
GU366996 GU367054 GU367091 GU353980 </p>

<p>Plagiostoma convexum 
BPI 843490 CBS 123206 
USA: NY 
Salix sp. 
L. Vasilyeva GU367011 EU255047 -
GU353994 
Plagiostoma devexum 
BPI 843489 CBS 123201 
USA: NY 
Polygonum sp. 
L. Vasilyeva GU367027 EU255001 EU219258 GU354010 
Plagiostoma dilatatum 
BPI 878957 CBS 124976 
(= LCM 402.02) </p>

<p>France 
Salix irrorata 
L.C. Mejía 
GU367013 GU367070 GU367104 GU353996 </p>

<p>BPI 878958 LCM 403.02 
France 
Salix caprea 
L.C. Mejía 
GU367012 GU367069 GU367103 GU353995 
Plagiostoma euphorbiaceum NA 
CBS 816.79 
Switzerland 
Euphorbia 
palustris </p>

<p>M. Monod 
GU367031 EU255003 -
GU354013 </p>

<p>Plagiostoma euphorbiae 
NA 
CBS 340.78 
The Netherlands Euphorbia 
palustris </p>

<p>W. Gams 
GU367034 DQ323532 EU219292 GU354016 </p>

<p>Plagiostoma exstocollum 
BPI 878961 CBS 127662 
(= LCM 468.01) </p>

<p>USA: OR 
Corylus californica L.C. Mejía 
GU366988 GU367046 GU367086 GU353972 </p>

<p>BPI 878959 LCM 422.01 
USA: OR 
Corylus californica L.C. Mejía 
GU366985 GU367043 GU367085 GU353969 
Plagiostoma fraxini 
BPI 746412 CBS 109498 
USA: MD 
Fraxinus 
pennsylvanica </p>

<p>S. Redlin 
GU367033 AY455810 EU219263 GU354015 </p>

<p>Plagiostoma geranii 
NA 
CBS 824.79 
Switzerland 
Geranium 
sylvaticum </p>

<p>M. Monod 
GU367032 EU255009 EU219273 GU354014 </p>

<p>Plagiostoma imperceptibile BPI 878967 LCM 456.01 
USA: CA 
Salix sp. 
L.C. Mejía 
GU367002 GU367059 GU367094 GU353984 
Plagiostoma oregonense 
BPI 878968 CBS 126124 
(= LCM 597.01) </p>

<p>USA: OR 
Salix sp. 
L.C. Mejía 
GU367016 GU367073 GU367107 GU353999 </p>

<p>Plagiostoma ovalisporum 
BPI 878969 CBS 124977 
(= LCM 458.01) </p>

<p>USA: ID 
Salix sp. 
L.C. Mejía 
GU367015 GU367072 GU367106 GU353998 </p>

<p>Plagiostoma petiolophilum 
BPI 878970 CBS 126123 
(= LCM 181.01) </p>

<p>USA: NY 
Acer spicatum 
L.C. Mejía 
GU367023 GU367078 GU367112 GU354006 </p>

<p>BPI 863769 AR 3821 
USA: NY 
Acer sp. 
L. Vasilyeva GU367025 EU255039 EU219257 GU354008 
Plagiostoma populinum 
NA 
CBS 144.57 
The Netherlands Populus 
trichocarpa </p>

<p>B. Gerrits van 
den Ende </p>

<p>GU367018 GU367075 GU367109 GU354001 </p>

<p>NA 
CBS 174.58 
The Netherlands Populus 
canadensis </p>

<p>B. Gerrits van 
den Ende </p>

<p>GU367017 GU367074 GU367108 GU354000 </p>

<p>Plagiostoma pulchellum 
BPI 878971 CBS 126653 
(= LCM 365.04) </p>

<p>USA: MD 
Salix babylonica L.C. Mejía 
GU367006 GU367063 GU367098 GU353987 </p>

<p>BPI 878972 LCM 371.02 
USA: MD 
Salix babylonica L.C. Mejía 
GU367007 GU367064 GU367099 GU353988 
BPI 878973 LCM 438.04 
USA: WA 
Salix lucida 
L.C. Mejía 
GU366004 GU367061 GU367096 GU353985 
BPI 878974 LCM 623.01 
Argentina 
Salix 
humboldtiana </p>

<p>L.C. Mejía 
GU367005 GU367062 GU367097 GU353986 </p>

<p>NA 
CBS 170.69 
The Netherlands Populus 
balsamifera </p>

<p>Unknown 
-
EU255043 -
GU353989 </p>

<p>Plagiostoma rhododendri 
NA 
CBS 847.79 
Switzerland 
Rhododendron 
hirsutum </p>

<p>M. Monod 
GU367026 EU255044 EU2192578 GU354009 </p>

<p>Plagiostoma robergeanum 
BPI 843593 CBS 121472 
Austria 
Staphylea pinnata W. Jaklitsch GU367029 EU255046 EU219262 GU354011 
Plagiostoma salicellum 
BPI 843527 CBS 121466 
(= AR 3828) </p>

<p>Austria 
Salix alba 
W. Jaklitsch GU366978 EU254996 EU219278 GU353962 </p>

<p>BPI 878975 CBS 126121 
(= LCM 449.01) </p>

<p>Germany 
Salix repens 
L.C. Mejía 
GU366977 GU367037 GU367081 GU353961 </p>

<p>Plagiostoma samuelsii 
BPI 878977 CBS 125668 
(= LCM 454.04) </p>

<p>USA: CA 
Alnus tenuifolia 
L.C. Mejía 
GU366993 GU367051 GU367089 GU353977 </p>

<p>BPI 878979 LCM 596.01 
USA: WA 
Alnus sp. 
L.C. Mejía 
GU366994 GU367052 GU367090 GU353978 
Plagiostoma versatile 
BPI 878980 CBS 124978 
(= LCM 594.01) </p>

<p>USA: WA 
Salix scouleriana L.C. Mejía 
GU366979 GU367038 GU367082 GU393963 </p>

<p>BPI 878981 LCM 595.01 
USA: WA 
Salix scouleriana L.C. Mejía 
GU366980 GU367039 GU367083 GU393964 
BPI 878982 LCM 598.01 
USA: OR 
Salix sp. 
L.C. Mejía 
GU366981 GU367040 GU367084 GU393965 
BPI 877702 CBS 121251 
Canada 
Salix sp. 
M.V. Sogonov GU366982 EU255059 EU219268 GU393966 </p>

<p>Table 1. Isolates with sequences included in the phylogenetic analysis of Plagiostoma. Types and epitypes are indicated in bold. </p>



<p>www.studiesinmycology.org </p>

<p>a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma </p>

<p>In addition, the character of perithecial neck orientation has been 
found not to be phylogenetically informative (Sogonov et al. 2008). 
Cryptodiaporthe was described by Petrak (1921) for species with 
euvalsoid arrangement of perithecia and, in contrast to Diaporthe, 
lacks a blackened margin in the substratum surrounding the 
perithecia. In describing Cryptodiaporthe, Petrak (1921) designated 
C. aesculi as type and included C. hystrix and C. populina. Later, 
Wehmeyer (1933) recircumscribed Cryptodiaporthe emphasising 
the lack of a blackened margin within the substratum and made 17 
new combinations in this genus for species previously included in 
Diaporthe expanding the genus to 19 species. 
In this study, specimens of Plagiostoma were collected 
primarily from North America but also from South America, Europe, 
and China. Among these recent collections eight new species were 
discovered and a number of described species were recollected, 
cultured, and sequenced. A multigene phylogenetic analysis is 
provided of 24 of the 25 species of Plagiostoma accepted here. 
Eight new species are described and illustrated, four species are 
redescribed, and four new combinations are proposed. A key to 
the 25 accepted species of Plagiostoma is provided along with the 
disposition of additional species names in Cryptodiaporthe and 
Plagiostoma. </p>

<p>MATERIAL AND METHODS </p>

<p>Collection of specimens, culture preparation, and 
morphological observations </p>

<p>Collections were made as listed in Table 1 from the following 
countries mainly during the spring and summers of 2007 and 2008: 
Argentina (Tucumán), China (Yunnan), France (Deux-Sèvres 
Département), Germany (Frankfurt), and the United States of 
America (California, Maryland, New York, Oregon, Washington). 
Specimens consisting of overwintered, dead, attached, or fallen 
twigs and branches with perithecia were placed in paper bags, air-
dried, and stored at 8-10 °C in sealed plastic bags for a period of 
1 wk to 6 mo before processing. All specimens are deposited in the 
U.S. National Fungus Collections (BPI). 
Observations, measurements, and digital imaging of 
morphological characters and isolation of cultures were performed 
using the same equipment and procedures as in Mejía et al. (2008). 
<rs id="software-8" type="software">AxioVision</rs> v. <rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-number">4.7.2.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-8" type="creator">Carl Zeiss Image Solutions</rs>, Carl Zeiss, New  York, NY, USA) was used in conjunction with those methods to 
measure structures. Fresh specimens were mounted in water for 
microscopic observations; dried specimens were mounted in 3 % 
potassium hydroxide. Cultural characteristics were observed on 
Potato Dextrose Agar (PDA, Difco™, Becton, Dickinson &amp; Co., 
Sparks, MD, USA) 7 d after plating as described in Mejía et al.  (2008). Colony diameters were measured twice perpendicularly 
and averaged and thus are listed as average colony diameter 
(a.c.d.). Representative cultures of species considered in this study 
were deposited at the Centraalbureau voor Schimmelcultures 
(CBS, The Netherlands) as listed in Table 1. </p>

<p>DNA extraction and PCR amplification </p>

<p>DNA extractions were done as described by Mejía et al. (2008)  using a Fast Prep FP 120 with Lysing Matrix "A" (MP Biomedicals, 
Solon, OH, USA) for mechanical lysis. Four gene fragments 
were amplified and sequenced for the phylogenetic analyses: the 
complete nuclear ribosomal internal transcribed spacer regions 1 
and 2 including 5.8 S rDNA (ITS), regions of the RNA polymerase 
second largest subunit (rpb2), beta-tubulin (β-tubulin), and 
translation elongation factor 1-alpha (tef1-α) genes. The ITS and 
rpb2 genes were amplified and sequenced as described in Mejía et  al. (2008) in 25 μL reactions with two internal sequencing primers 
designed specifically for species of Plagiostoma: rpb2 Plag-F (5' 
CGT CGC TGC ATY ATC TCR CA 3') and rpb2 Plag-R (5' TGY 
GAG ATR ATG CAG CGA CG 3'). β-tubulin was amplified using 
primers T1 and T22 and sequenced with the PCR primers and 
the internal primers T2 and T12 from O'Donnell &amp; Cigelnik (1997). 
For some isolates it was necessary to amplify the tef1-α region 
in two fragments using the following primer combinations: EF1-
728F /EF1-1199R and EF1-983F/ EF1-1567R (Carbone &amp; Kohn  1999, Castlebury, unpubl. data, for primer 1199R 5' GGG AAG TAC 
CMG TGA TCA TGT 3', Rehner 2001). The rpb2 gene could not be 
amplified for P. convexum, P. euphorbiaceum, and P. pulchellum 
CBS 170.69. In addition, β-tubulin could not be amplified for P. 
pulchellum CBS 170.69. For the purpose of determining taxonomic 
affinities of species previously described as Cryptodiaporthe or 
Plagiostoma but not congeneric with P. euphorbiae (type species), 
a region of the nuclear ribosomal large subunit (LSU) was amplified 
as described in Castlebury et al. (2002). </p>

<p>Phylogenetic analyses </p>

<p>Editing and alignment of DNA sequences were performed as 
described in Mejía et al. (2008). Individual genes were aligned 
separately and subsequently concatenated into a single alignment. 
Table 1 includes detailed information about the gene sequences 
including GenBank numbers. The concatenated sequence 
alignment includes β-tubulin (1584 bp), ITS (625 bp), rpb2 (1212 
bp), and tef1-α (1149 bp) for a total of 4570 bp and 45 isolates. 
The taxa included in this alignment represent 24 of the 25 accepted 
species of Plagiostoma with Apiognomonia hystrix and A. veneta 
as outgroup taxa. Outgroup selection was based on the sister 
relationship of the genus Apiognomonia with Plagiostoma as 
inferred by a three-gene phylogeny of the family Gnomoniaceae 
(Sogonov et al. 2008). Positions with ambiguous alignment were 
excluded from the analyses. 
The concatenated alignment was partitioned by gene and codon 
position for β-tubulin, rpb2, and tef1-α using <rs id="software-9" type="software">PAUP</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-9" type="creator">Swofford</rs> 2002). 
The gene partitions were analysed for conflict with the partition 
homogeneity test (PHT) as implemented in <rs id="software-10" type="software">PAUP</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-10" type="creator">Swofford</rs> 2002) 
using the following settings: 100 homogeneity replicates, 10 random 
sequence addition replicates, and MULTREES off. Conflict among 
gene partitions was assessed by reciprocal bootstrap analyses 
(Reeb et al. 2004) using distance settings for each partition as </p>

<p>Taxon 
Specimen Culture 
Country 
Host 
Collector β-tubulin ITS 
rpb2 
tef1-α </p>

<p>Plagiostoma yunnanense 
BPI 878983 CBS 124979 
China 
Salix sp. 
L.C. Mejía 
GU366975 GU367035 GU367079 GU353959 
(= LCM 513.03) </p>

<p>Plagiostoma yunnanense 
BPI 878983 LCM 513.02 
China 
Salix sp. 
L.C. Mejía 
GU366976 GU367036 GU367080 GU353960 </p>

<p>Table 1. (Continued). </p>



<p>Mejía et al. </p>

<p>determined by Modeltest v. 3.7 (Posada &amp; Crandall 1998) following 
the Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC). 
Genes were first analysed individually and then as a combined 
alignment using maximum parsimony, Bayesian, and maximum 
likelihood analyses. Trees and bootstrap support of branches 
were estimated by MP analysis as in Sogonov et al. (2008) with 
all characters considered unordered with equal weight and an 
additional analysis with unordered characters weighted as follows: 
weight = 3 for first and second codon positions and weight = 1 
for third codon position. Additionally, trees were estimated using 
Bayesian analysis with the program MrBayes v. 3.1.2 (Huelsenbeck  &amp; Ronquist 2001) as described in Sogonov et al. (2008) with 
sampling every 500 generations. Model settings for each gene 
were determined using the program <rs id="software-13" type="software">MrModeltest</rs> v. <rs corresp="#software-13" type="version-number">2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-13" type="creator">Nylander</rs>  2004) and selected based on the Akaike Information Criterion 
(AIC). The first 50 000 generations were discarded (burn-in period) 
based on comparison of tree likelihood scores. A 50 % majority rule 
consensus tree and a consensus phylogram were constructed from 
the trees saved after the burn-in period. The Bayesian posterior 
probabilities (PP) of nodes of the consensus trees are presented 
in Fig. 1. Trees were also estimated by Maximum Likelihood (ML) 
analysis using the program <rs id="software-14" type="software">PAUP</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-14" type="creator">Swofford</rs> 2002) as described in 
Sogonov et al. (2008) with Modeltest v. 3.7 (Posada &amp; Crandall 1998)  used to estimate the best model for the concatenated alignment. 
Maximum likelihood bootstrap analysis was not conducted. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Collection of specimens </p>

<p>The following plant species are reported as new hosts for species of 
Plagiostoma: Alnus tenuifolia, Salix dasyclados, S. humboldtiana,  S. irrorata, S. lucida, and S. sitchensis (Table 1). Plagiostoma 
pulchellum from Argentina and P. yunnanense from southwestern 
China were collected in regions where no species of Plagiostoma 
had been previously reported. </p>

<p>Phylogenetic analyses </p>

<p>The partition homogeneity test suggested conflict among the four 
genes (ITS, rpb2, β-tubulin, and tef1-α) sequenced for this study (P 
= 0.01) with rpb2 as the source of this conflict. For combinations 
of the remaining three genes (ITS, β-tubulin, and tef1-α), no 
incongruence among gene trees was detected when all three were 
analysed (P = 0.09), with P = 0.07 for ITS and β-tubulin and P = 
0.24 for ITS and tef1-α. The following are the likelihood settings 
estimated for each gene for the reciprocal NJ bootstrap analyses: 
ITS: Base = equal Nst = 2 TRatio = 2.5434 Rates = equal Pinvar = 
0.8337; rpb2: Base = equal Nst = 6 Rmat = (1.0000 4.6961 1.0000 
1.0000 13.3827) Rates = gamma Shape = 0.2029 Pinvar = 0; 
β-tubulin: Base = (0.2006 0.3249 0.2505) Nst = 2 TRatio = 2.1757 
Rates = gamma Shape = 0.5017 Pinvar = 0; and tef1-α: Base = 
(0.1918 0.3110 0.2229) Nst = 2 TRatio = 1.8586 Rates = gamma 
Shape = 0.6109 Pinvar = 0. 
The ITS, β-tubulin, and tef1-α trees individually resolved terminal 
clades for most of the species analysed. Trees for each gene are 
provided -see online Supplementary Information. No single gene 
analysis resolved all the species of Plagiostoma with bootstrap 
support higher than 70 %. The following numbers of species were 
resolved by genes with bootstrap &gt; 70 %: ITS = 11, rpb2 = 9, </p>

<p>β-tubulin = 12, and tef1-α = 11. In general, rpb2 was not as useful for 
resolving clades of closely related species as the other three genes. 
The ITS gene resolved and supported all terminal clades except P. 
amygdalinae and P. euphorbiaceae for which the sequences were 
nearly identical. However, it did not support backbone nodes at 
levels greater than 70 %. In contrast, bootstrap support greater than 
90 % for all backbone nodes containing two or more species was 
obtained in the β-tubulin, rpb2, and tef1-α gene trees. The topology 
of the individual gene trees differed only slightly. One topological 
conflict supported by bootstrap values greater than 70 % was 
observed between the β-tubulin analysis resulting in a clade (97 %) 
that included all species of Plagiostoma on Salicaceae and the rpb2 
analysis resulting in a clade (72 %) that included some but not all the 
species on Salicaceae with some species on other hosts. 
Phylogenetic trees resulting from the combined four-gene 
dataset (ITS, β-tubulin, rpb2, and tef1-α) were compared with 
those resulting from the ITS, β-tubulin, tef1-α dataset found to 
be conflict-free by the PHT. Maximum parsimony analyses of the 
four-gene combination resulted in 114 equally parsimonious trees 
(length = 1713, CI = 0.689, RI = 0.809) for the unweighted analysis 
and 42 equally parsimonious trees (length = 2062, CI = 0.689, 
RI = 0.807) for the weighted analysis. Fifty percent majority rule 
consensus trees computed for each analysis did not differ in the 
terminal species clades but higher bootstrap support was obtained 
for several clades in the weighted analysis. Maximum parsimony 
analysis of the three-gene combination composed of ITS, β-tubulin, 
and tef-α resulted in eight equally parsimonious trees (length = 
1275, CI = 0.707, RI = 0.817). The tree topologies obtained by 
MP analyses of the two alignments did not contradict each other; 
however, bootstrap support for several nodes increased in analyses 
of the four-gene combination. Therefore, subsequent analyses 
were performed on the four-gene combination. 
The following models were the best estimates for each gene 
and were applied during the Bayesian analyses: HKY + I + G for 
ITS and tef1-α, SYM + G for rpb2, and HKY + G for β-tubulin. The 
model TrN+G was estimated to be the best for the entire alignment by 
both hLRT and BIC and those settings were applied to the maximum 
likelihood analysis: Base = (0.2245 0.2859 0.2454) Nst = 6 Rmat 
= (1.0000 3.5234 1.0000 1.0000 5.8336) Rates = gamma Shape 
= 0.2849 Pinvar = 0. Bayesian, ML, MP, and weighted parsimony 
(WP) analyses of the four-gene alignment all resulted in the same 
topology. Maximum likelihood analysis of the concatenated alignment 
of four genes resulted in one tree -lnL score of 13921.12887 and 
is presented as the inferred phylogeny of Plagiostoma (Fig. 1). 
Bayesian PP and MP bootstraps are shown above and below the 
branches. This phylogeny of Plagiostoma supports the recognition of 
eight new species, which are described in the taxonomic section of 
this work. Bayesian PP and MP bootstrap supports greater than 90 
% were obtained for all the species of Plagiostoma in this multigene 
phylogeny. Plagiostoma euphorbiae-verrucosae is not included in the 
multigene phylogeny as only the ITS was available for this species. 
This species was confirmed as belonging in Plagiostoma by analysis 
of ITS sequences (tree not shown). </p>

<p>Evaluation of clades and species </p>

<p>Both Bayesian analysis and MP bootstrapping support a clade 
containing 11 species that occurs exclusively on hosts of the family 
Salicaceae. All of these species occur on the bark of twigs and 
branches with one species, Plagiostoma versatile, also occurring 
in the leaf midvein and petioles. Within the species on Salicaceae, </p>



<p>www.studiesinmycology.org </p>

<p>a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma </p>

<p>one clade consists of four closely related species characterised by 
having an expanded perithecial neck: P. apiculatum, P. dilatatum, P. 
imperceptibile, and P. pulchellum. These species are distinguished by 
morphological features such as perithecium size, ascospore size and 
length-to-width (l : w) ratio, and hyphal colour in culture. Plagiostoma 
imperceptibile is characterised by having ascospores longer than 18 
μm but with a length-width ratio (l : w) less than five. Plagiostoma </p>

<p>pulchellum is characterised by having ascospores with a l : w greater 
than five and by producing rosy-coloured hyphae that become dark 
green on PDA. Plagiostoma apiculatum and P. dilatatum are similar 
to one another but the perithecia and ascospores of P. dilatatum are 
larger than those of P. apiculatum. Plagiostoma convexum with a 
moderately expanded perithecial neck is highly supported (&gt; 95 % 
MP, PP) as basal to these four species. </p>

<p>LCM 623.01 P. pulchellum 
CBS 170.69 P. pulchellum 
LCM 371.02 P. pulchellum 
LCM 365.04 P. pulchellum 
LCM 438.04 P. pulchellum 
LCM 456.01 P. imperceptibile 
LCM 436.01 P. apiculatum 
LCM 393.01 P. apiculatum 
CBS 109775 P. apiculatum 
LCM 403.02 P. dilatatum 
LCM 402.02 P. dilatatum 
CBS 123206 P. convexum 
CBS 174.58 P. populinum 
CBS 144.57 P. populinum 
LCM 458.01 P. ovalisporum 
LCM 594.01 P. versatile ** 
LCM 598.01 P. versatile ** 
LCM 595.01 P. versatile ** 
CBS 121251 P. versatile ** 
LCM 449.01 P. salicellum 
CBS 121466 P. salicellum 
LCM 513.03 P. yunnanense 
LCM 513.02 P. yunnanense 
LCM 597.01 P. oregonense 
LCM 422.01 P. exstocollum 
LCM 468.01 P. exstocollum 
CBS 847.79 P. rhododendri ** 
LCM 454.04 P. samuelsii 
LCM 596.01 P. samuelsii 
CBS 791.79 P. amygdalinae * 
CBS 340.78 DQ323532 P. euphorbiae 
CBS 816.79 EU255003 P. euphorbiaceum 
CBS 109498 AY455810 P. fraxini * 
CBS 123201 EU255001 P. devexum * 
LCM 601.01 P. barriae * 
LCM 181.01 P. petiolophilum ** 
BPI 863769 P. petiolophilum ** 
CBS 824.79 P. geranii * 
LCM 447.01 P. aesculi 
CBS 109765 P. aesculi 
LCM 447b.01 P. aesculi 
CBS 121905 P. aesculi 
CBS 121472 P. robergeanum 
CBS 911.79 DQ313549 Apiognomonia hystrix 
CBS 897.79 DQ313532 Apiognomonia veneta </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>100 
97 </p>

<p>100 
73 </p>

<p>100 
97 </p>

<p>100 
97 </p>

<p>100 
100 </p>

<p>100 
95 </p>

<p>100 
100 </p>

<p>100 
100 
81 </p>

<p>100 
100 
100 
100 </p>

<p>100 
99 </p>

<p>100 
100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 
81 </p>

<p>100 
100 
100 
100 
100 
100 </p>

<p>100 
100 </p>

<p>100 
87 </p>

<p>100 
96 </p>

<p>100 
87 </p>

<p>98 
70 
100 
73 </p>

<p>100 
83 </p>

<p>100 
100 </p>

<p>100 
100 
98 
72 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 
100 </p>

<p>100 
100 </p>

<p>Species on Salicaceae </p>

<p>Species with 
expanded necks </p>

<p>Species with 
cylindrical necks </p>

<p>* Species on leaves 
** Species on bark and leaves 
Most species exclusively on bark </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree (ML score = -lnL 13921.12887) estimated from sequences of the β-tubulin, ITS, rpb2, and tef1-α genes for 24 species of 
Plagiostoma and two species of Apiognomonia. Bayesian posterior probabilities greater than 80 % are shown above each branch and maximum parsimony bootstrap values 
greater than 70 % are shown below branches. Trees for each gene were also generated; see online Supplementary Information. </p>



<p>Mejía et al. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma ovalisporum and the pathogenic species P. 
populinum are closely related and contained within a larger clade 
including the five species previously mentioned (100 % MP, PP). 
The remaining species of Plagiostoma on Salicaceae form a weakly 
supported clade sister to the species on Salicaceae with expanded 
necks mentioned above. This clade contains three species having 
cylindrical, usually elongated, perithecial necks, and elongated 
ascospores: P. salicellum, P. versatile, and P. yunnanense. The 
remaining member of this clade, P. oregonense, is characterised by 
short, expanded perithecial necks and short ascospores. 
Bayesian PP and MP bootstrapping also support a clade 
(83 % MP, 100 % PP) of eight species with hosts representing 
a range of woody and herbaceous plant families. One of the 
subclades in this group is composed of three species that grow 
on Euphorbiaceae: P. amygdalinae, P. euphorbiaceum, and P. 
euphorbiae, type species of the genus. Basal to these species is P. 
fraxinum on Fraxinus pennsylvanica. A second subclade contains 
P. exstocollum and P. samuelsii both on betulaceous hosts and P. 
rhododendri on Rhododendron. The rest of the species included in 
the tree, namely P. aesculi, P. barriae, P. geranii, P. petiolophilum, 
and P. robergeanum, are relatively distant from one another and 
the species previously mentioned. Plagiostoma robergeanum, a 
species that grows on Staphylea (Staphyleaceae) in Europe, was 
basal to the other species of Plagiostoma. 
Specimens of P. pulchellum were collected in Europe, North 
America (USA), and South America (Argentina). This species is 
recognised as the most widely distributed species of Plagiostoma 
included in this study and is presented here as the first report of 
Gnomoniaceae for South America. Plagiostoma yunnanense is the 
first report of Plagiostoma for China. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Due to the morphological diversity in species of Plagiostoma, as 
illustrated in Figs 2-6, no single morphological character is unique 
or diagnostic for this genus. The following morphological characters 
differentiate Plagiostoma from other genera of the Gnomoniaceae 
as defined by Sogonov et al. (2008, table 2). Unlike Gnomonia, 
species of Plagiostoma have perithecia that often collapse from 
the base when dry as illustrated in Sogonov et al. (2008, fig. 43  B-C). In Plagiostoma the neck length is short to long about equal 
or less than the diameter of perithecia, while in Ophiognomonia the 
perithecial neck length is usually very long, often pointed, and 2.5-
5 times the perithecial diameter. Species of Ophiognomonia occur 
only on leaves while those of Plagiostoma are found on leaves as 
well as woody tissues. Except for P. rhododendri, the ascospores of 
Plagiostoma are not broader at the upper part as in Gnomoniopsis. 
Ascospores of Plagiostoma are never cylindrical or femuroid as 
in Cryptosporella. Species of Plagiostoma with ellipsoid, aseptate 
ascospores similar to those of C. hypodermia do not have a valsoid 
arrangement of perithecia as do species of Cryptosporella. 
Species of Plagiostoma, except for P. rhododendri, are not 
apiosporous, differentiating them from species of Apiognomonia 
except A. hystrix, which possesses flattened perithecial necks. 
Species of Pleuroceras have elongated ascospores that are quite 
distinct from those of Plagiostoma. The type and only species of 
Ditopella, D. ditopa, is characterised by having polysporic asci. 
Phragmoporthe conformis, a species closely related to Ditopella 
ditopa, is characterised by phragmosporic ascospores, a character 
not present in Plagiostoma. The perithecia of Amphiporthe </p>

<p>hranicensis, the type species of Amphiporthe, are grouped near 
the base of the entostroma and, thus, are different from those 
found in Plagiostoma. In addition, Amphiporthe hranicensis 
produces perithecia in clusters of up to 20, with perithecial necks 
protruding as a group from the host periderm and surrounded by 
gray stromatic tissue. 
Perithecial neck characters and ascospore morphology are the 
most important characters for differentiating Plagiostoma from other 
genera in the Gnomoniaceae. Host identity, geographic locality, 
and presence or absence of stroma are secondary characters for 
the identification of species. For example, the presence of white 
stromatic tissues surrounding the emerging perithecial necks 
is diagnostic in species such as P. aesculi, P. salicellum, and P. 
samuelsii. Within Plagiostoma perithecial neck shape ranges from 
very short, cylindrical to expanded and thick or thin, cylindrical and 
elongated with various shapes in the opening area, e.g. conic, 
flared, or rounded. In one species, P. versatile, the perithecial 
neck can be both very short when on twigs or elongated when on 
a leaf midvein suggesting that this structure varies with substrate. 
Four species, P. apiculatum, P. convexum, P. dilatatum, and P. 
imperceptibile, are characterised by having an apically expanded 
perithecial neck. The expanded neck was noticed by Wallroth 
(1833, as coronatum dilatatis) and Butin (1958, as cushion-or pad-
like structure) but neither of these authors used this character to 
differentiate species. This structure may be involved in rupture of 
host periderm and release of the ascospores. 
The asci of Plagiostoma are clavate, obclavate, ovoidal, 
cylindrical, or cylindric-fusoid, generally with a short stalk but with 
a long stalk in P. imperceptibile. Ascospores of Plagiostoma are 
ellipsoid, ellipsoid-fusoid, oblong-ellipsoid, or ovoid usually with one 
median septum, although three species, P. euphorbiae-verrucosae, 
P. fraxini, and P. ovalisporum, have non-septate ascospores and 
one species, P. rhododendri, is apiosporous. Ascospores vary in 
size from short, 7.7-13.8 × 2.2-6.6 μm in P. fraxini, to relatively 
long, 18-27 × 3-4 μm in P. versatile and P. yunnanense. Most 
species lack appendages although P. salicellum has short, thick, 
evanescent appendages and P. devexum and P. samuelsii may 
have long, thin appendages. Morphological characters that are 
phylogenetically informative for subclades of Plagiostoma include 
the expanded neck characteristic of species with broadly ellipsoid 
ascospores versus the cylindrical neck characteristic of species 
with narrowly ellipsoidal ascospores. 
In traditional classification schemes of the Diaporthales, 
Cryptodiaporthe and Plagiostoma were considered distinct and 
not closely related genera, each with a specific morphology and 
arrangement of perithecia (Barr 1978, Kobayashi 1970, Monod  1983). Species of Plagiostoma were characterised by the lack of a 
stroma and production of a single perithecium, primarily on leaves. 
Species of Cryptodiaporthe were characterised by production of a 
rudimentary stroma and grouped perithecia, primarily in the bark 
of their host branches. The differences between Cryptodiaporthe 
and Plagiostoma have been emphasised such that some authors 
placed them in different families or subfamilies (Barr 1978,  Wehmeyer 1975). 
Monod's (1983) concept of Plagiostoma differed significantly 
from the concept presented here. Of the 13 species treated by Monod  (1983) as Plagiostoma, only Plagiostoma devexum is accepted 
here in that genus. Of the 13 species of Plagiostoma accepted by 
Sogonov et al. (2008), only P. euphorbiae and P. devexum were 
originally described as Plagiostoma with Plagiostoma barriae newly 
described in that work. Plagiostoma aesculi and P. salicellum were 
previously regarded by Wehmeyer (1933) as Cryptodiaporthe. Four </p>



<p>www.studiesinmycology.org </p>

<p>a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma </p>

<p>additional species of Cryptodiaporthe are here formally combined 
in Plagiostoma, namely P. apiculatum, P. convexum, P. populinum, 
and P. pulchellum. The recognition of these four species formerly 
classified as Cryptodiaporthe salicina broadens the range of 
morphological and ecological traits of the genus Plagiostoma. The 
pathogenic species, P. apiculatum, P. fraxini, and P. populinum, 
contrasts with the concept of Plagiostoma as primarily saprobic. 
The economically important species of Plagiostoma are 
pathogens that cause cankers on willows and poplars. Plagiostoma 
apiculatum (synonym Cryptodiaporthe salicella) is here determined 
to be the correct name for the fungus causing a canker disease 
of willow (Sinclair &amp; Lyon 2005). This species, referred to by the 
anamorph Diplodina microsperma, has been reported as the most 
abundant endophyte in healthy twigs of Salix fragilis in England 
(Petrini &amp; Fisher 1990) and is thus an important component of the 
host microbiota. Similarly, the closely related species P. dilatatum, 
P. imperceptibile, and P. pulchellum form a black halo or spot on 
the host surface, a feature that may be associated with the early 
stages of canker development. Whether or not these species 
are primarily pathogenic or establish an asymptomatic infection 
that later develops into cankers needs to be determined. These </p>

<p>species form a highly supported monophyletic group (Fig. 1) 
characterised by having an expanded perithecial neck and broad 
ellipsoid to renoid ascospores. This group of species is part of 
a larger, highly supported clade that also includes P. convexum, 
P. ovalisporum, and P. populinum (synonym Cryptodiaporthe 
populea), the pathogen causing a canker of poplars. Plagiostoma 
fraxini causes anthracnose on ash (Fraxinus pennsylvanica) and 
fringetree (Chionanthus retusis) (Gregory et al. 2004, Sinclair &amp;  Lyon 2005), and is sister to the clade containing three species on 
Euphorbiaceae. 
Species of Plagiostoma occur on a broad range of host plant 
families within the Eudicots, although most species are associated 
with Rosids. This study shows an association between a clade 
composed of 11 species of Plagiostoma and the host family 
Salicaceae (Fig. 1) especially on the genus Salix. Most of the 
species of Plagiostoma on Salix have expanded necks. These 
findings agree with those for other genera within the Gnomoniaceae 
that are associated primarily with specific host genera in the 
Betulaceae such as Cryptosporella on Alnus and Betula (Mejía et  al. 2008) and Gnomonia on the Coryloideae (Sogonov et al. 2008). </p>

<p>TAXONOMY </p>

<p>KEY TO SPECIES OF PlaGiostoma </p>





<p>Mejía et al. </p>





<p>www.studiesinmycology.org </p>

<p>a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma </p>

<p>DESCRIPTIONS </p>

<p>Plagiostoma Fuckel, Jahrb. Nassauischen Vereins Naturk. 
23-24: 118. 1870. </p>

<p>Lectotype designated by Höhnel (1917): Plagiostoma euphorbiae 
(Fuckel) Fuckel, Jahrb. Nassauischen Vereins Naturk. 23-24: 118. 
1870. </p>

<p>= Cryptodiaporthe Petr., Ann. Mycol. 19: 118. 1921. Lectotype designated 
by Clements and Shear (1931): Cryptodiaporthe aesculi (Fuckel) Petr., now 
Plagiostoma aesculi (Fuckel) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 62: 69. 2008. 
= Rostrocoronophora Munk, Dansk Bot. Arkiv 15: 98. 1953. Type: R. geranii 
(Hollós) Munk, now Plagiostoma geranii (Hollós) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 62: 
72. 2008. </p>

<p>Anamorph: Diplodina Westend., Bull. Acad. Roy. Sci. Belgique, sér. 
2, 2: 562. 1857. </p>

<p>Anamorph type species: Diplodina salicis Westend., Bull. Acad. 
R. Sci. Belg., Cl. Sci., sér. 2 12(7) (1857), now recognised as 
Diplodina microsperma (Johnst.) B. Sutton, Mycol. Pap. 141: 69. 
1977 fide Sutton (1980). </p>

<p>Perithecia produced in dead, fallen or still attached host organs, 
immersed in bark of stems, branches, and twigs, in midvein or petiole 
of leaves (P. fraxini on leaf lamina), on stalks of herbaceous plants, 
and on peduncles (P. rhododendri). Most species initially appearing as 
conic-shaped or rounded elevations, usually 0.2-0.5 mm high × 1-2 
mm diam, produced where a single perithecium or group of perithecia 
push up host surface from below. Perithecial necks protrude through 
epidermis or periderm making a small hole or slit, with perithecia 
partially or completely exposed by peeling host periderm. In bark, 
perithecia arranged in groups or solitary, scattered, numerous; in 
leaves, perithecia discrete, but growing close together. Stroma scanty, 
flocculose, gray, brownish, cream, yellowish white, or whitish. Perithecia 
black, globose, slightly flattened or suboblate, usually collapsed from 
base when dry, with or without stromatic tissue surrounding neck. Neck 
central to marginal, mostly cylindrical, also flattened, short and stout, 
upright, straight or contorted, or slanted and straight; 30-150 μm diam 
not including expanded area, with or without a disk-like expansion, up to 
450 μm diam; apex rounded, acute, flared, cupulate, papillate, or conic, 
black, brown, yellow or hyaline, with or without furrows. Asci clavate, 
obclavate, ovoidal to cylindrical and cylindric-fusoid, usually with a 
short stalk, with a long stalk in P. imperceptibile, with a conspicuous 
apical ring that may appear single and thick or as two refractive bodies, 
eight ascospores arranged obliquely parallel, biseriate, multiseriate, or 
twisted. Ascospores ellipsoid, ellipsoid-fusoid, oblong-ellipsoid, ovoid, 
hyaline, non-or 1-septate, constricted or not at median to submedian 
septum, apiosporous in P. rhododendri, often with four or more rounded 
guttules, or appearing granulated, with or without an appendage at 
each end. Cultures of Plagiostoma generally grow moderately (4 cm) to 
fast (5-6 cm) diam after 7 d on PDA, velvety, granular, with concentric 
halo, with scant aerial mycelium, translucent, white, pale to very dark 
gray, hazel, dark green, olive or with various dark yellow to orange 
pigmentation, margins fringed, stringed, or root-like. </p>

<p>Species of Plagiostoma </p>

<p>Plagiostoma aesculi (Fuckel) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 62: 69. 
2008. </p>

<p>Basionym: Cryptospora aesculi Fuckel, Jahrb. Nassauischen 
Vereins Naturk. 23-24: 193. 1870. </p>

<p>≡ Cryptosporella aesculi (Fuckel) Sacc., Michelia 1: 30. 1877. </p>

<p>[≡ Diaporthe aesculi (Fuckel) Höhn., Ann. Mycol. 16: 116. 1918, nom. 
illeg. non Cooke &amp; Harkn. 1881] 
≡ Cryptodiaporthe aesculi (Fuckel) Petr., Ann. Mycol. 19:119. 1921. </p>

<p>Note: Sogonov et al. (2008) provided a description and illustrations 
of this species. Cultures are illustrated here in Fig. 7A-B. </p>

<p>Specimen examined: Germany, Langen, on branches of Aesculus hippocastaneum, 
L.C. Mejía, BPI 878950, culture LCM 447.01 = CBS 126127. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma amygdalinae (Fuckel) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 
62: 70. 2008. </p>

<p>Basionym: Gnomonia amygdalinae Fuckel, Jahrb. Nassauischen 
Vereins Naturk. 23-24: 121. 1870. </p>

<p>≡ Gnomoniella amygdalinae (Fuckel) Sacc., Syll. Fung. 1: 418. 1882. 
= Gnomoniella amygdalinae f. euphorbiae-stepposae Sandu, Stud. Cercet. 
Biol., Bot. 18: 18. 1966 fide Monod (1983). </p>

<p>Note: Monod (1983) provided a detailed description of this species as 
Gnomonia amygdalinae. Although ITS sequences of P. amygdalinae 
(Monod 207 = CBS 791.79) and P. euphorbiaceum (MS196 = CBS  121241, Monod 465 = CBS 816.79) suggest that these taxa are 
the same, the multigene phylogeny obtained here reveals that P. 
amygdalinae and P. euphorbiaceum are distinct species. Plagiostoma 
amygdalinae occurs on leaves and has a longer and thinner 
perithecial neck, shorter asci, thinner apical ring, and ascospores not 
constricted at septum and thinner than P. euphorbiaceum that occurs 
on twigs, stems, and branches (also see Monod 1983). </p>

<p>Plagiostoma apiculatum (Wallr.) L.C. Mejía, comb. nov. 
MycoBank MB515689. Figs 2A-J, 7C-F </p>

<p>Basionym: Sphaeria apiculata Wallr., Fl. Crypt. Germ. 2: 778. 1833. </p>

<p>≡ Metasphaeria apiculata (Wallr.) Sacc., Syll. Fung. 2: 166. 1883. 
≡ Gnomonia apiculata (Wallr.) G. Winter, Rabenh., Kryptog.-Fl., ed. 2, 
vol. 1(2): 589. 1887. 
≡ Diaporthe spina Fuckel var. apiculata (Wallr.) Rehm, Ann. Mycol. 7: 
404. 1909. 
≡ Cryptodiaporthe apiculata (Wallr.) Petr., Ann. Mycol. 19: 177. 1921. </p>

<p>Anamorph: Diplodina microsperma (Johnst.) B. Sutton, Mycol. Pap. 
141: 69. 1977. </p>

<p>Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary, scattered, appearing initially 
as slight punctiform elevations of periderm surrounded by a black 
halo with tip of neck protruding through slit, usually with three 
short radiating slits, halo paler in some collections, later becoming 
completely black, globose, (223-)252-364(-440) μm high × 
(349-)370-476(-477) μm diam (mean = 314 × 429 μm, SD 59, 
77, n = 8), each with one neck. Neck central to eccentric, straight 
to oblique, with a pale brown papilla, with an expanded area that 
appears disk-like, sometimes evident only as a thick neck, initially 
below epidermis, becoming exposed, producing a black halo at 
surface, (115-)159-256(-351) μm long (mean = 208, SD 78, n = 
8), expanded area (187-)224-340(-389) μm diam (mean = 284, 
SD 74, n = 8), (62.5-)81-128(-134) μm diam at apex (mean = 104, 
SD 29, n = 7). Asci cylindrical, (45-)51-80(-86) × 10-16(-18) μm 
(mean = 68 × 13, SD 15, 4, n = 19), apical ring 2.5-5.0 μm diam, 
variable in shape e.g. elongated as two bodies or hexagonal, with 
eight ascospores arranged biseriate to multiseriate. Ascospores 
oblong-ellipsoid, slightly tapering to rounded ends, straight to 
slightly curved, one median to submedian septum, not constricted, 
(12-)16-18.5(-21) × (3-)5-6(-7) μm (mean = 16.5 × 5.5, SD 2.5, 
1.0, n = 106), l : w (2.4-)2.9-3.2(-4) (mean = 3.0, SD 0.3, n = 106), 
with granular cytoplasm. </p>



<p>Mejía et al. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Morphology on natural substrate. A-J: Plagiostoma apiculatum: A,B,I,J = BPI 799002 (lectotype), C-G = BPI 747938 (epitype), H = BPI 878952. K-R. P. convexum: K-M 
= BPI 799418 (lectotype), L-R = BPI 843490 (epitype). Bars = (A, K) 1 mm; (B-F, L, O-Q) 100 μm; (G-J, M-N, R) 10 μm. </p>



<p>www.studiesinmycology.org </p>

<p>a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma </p>

<p>Cultures: Moderate to fast growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 5 cm (SD  0.4, n = 4), thin aerial mycelium of velvety granular texture, central 
area vinaceous buff 45, with scattered black mycelial clumps of 0.5 
mm diam in central area, margin white, stringy; reverse similar but 
slightly darker. </p>

<p>Habitat and host: On dead twigs and branches of Salix spp., Salix 
alba, S. alba subsp. vitellina, S. dasyclados, and S. sitchensis 
(Salicaceae). </p>

<p>Distribution: Europe and North America. </p>

<p>Lectotype of Sphaeria apiculata designated here: BPI 799092, 
labelled Sphaeria apiculata Wallr., ex. Herb. Strasbourg. </p>

<p>Epitype of Sphaeria apiculata designated here: Austria, Vienna, 
21 
st district, Marchfeldkanalweg, MTB 7764/1, on Salix sp., 20 May 
2000, W. Jaklitsch 1463, BPI 747938, derived culture CBS 109775 
= AR3455. </p>

<p>Exsiccatus examined: Fungi Rhenani 918, as Sphaeria apiculata, 
from Salix vitellina, BPI bound. </p>

<p>Additional specimens examined: Austria, Vienna, St. Margareten im Rosental, 
Kaernten, Drau-Auen, 9452/1, on Salix alba, 2 May 2002, W. Jaklitsch 1890, 
BPI 843511, derived culture AR 3826; St. Margareten im Rosental, Drau-Auen, 
Kaernten. 9452/2, on Salix alba, 14 Apr. 2001, W. Jaklitsch 1741, BPI 872037. 
France, Deux-Sèvres Département, Melle, Melle Arboretum, 15 Apr. 2008, on twigs 
of Salix dasyclados, L.C. Mejía 393, BPI 878951, derived cultures L.C. Mejía 393.01 
and CBS 124974 = LCM393.03. USA, Washington, Kitsap County, Kitsap Memorial 
State Park, on twigs of Salix sitchensis, 28 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 436, BPI 878952, 
derived culture CBS 126126 = LCM436.01. </p>

<p>Notes: The specimen designated here as lectotype is part of the 
collection of Sphaeria apiculata referred to in the protologue. It 
agrees with Wallroth's description of S. apiculata. Fuckel (1870)  recircumscribed Sphaeria apiculata Wallr. based on Fungi Rhenani 
918. The original Latin description of Sphaeria apiculata includes 
morphological characters of the perithecia such as an apiculate 
papilla, i.e. "coronatum dilatatis", here interpreted as the disk-
shaped expansion of the perithecial neck, and "nucleo atro" at 
the apex. These morphological characters are present in the type 
specimen BPI 799092 of S. apiculata designated here as the 
lectotype. The protologue of S. apiculata by Wallroth (1833) does 
not include a description of the ascospores, however, the fungus on 
this specimen contains broadly ellipsoid ascospores. This specimen 
and thus Plagiostoma apiculatum is distinctive and differs from 
Plagiostoma salicellum as discussed under that species. 
The concept of the name Sphaeria apiculata has been confused. 
The following is an account of this species and its various synonyms 
based on the results of our study of the original description, type 
specimens, and relevant later specimens. Höhnel (1917), Petrak  (1921), and later authors considered Sphaeria apiculata to have 
narrowly elongated ascospores while Wehmeyer (1933) recognised 
this species as having broadly ellipsoid ascospores and considered 
Cryptodiaporthe salicina to be a synonym. Höhnel (1917) examined 
specimens made by Rehm, Krieger, and his own of Diaporthe spina 
and considered this name to be a synonym of Sphaeria apiculata. 
He acknowledged differences in perithecial neck length among 
collections of these two species. To determine the synonymy 
of these two species we compared the original description of D. 
spina with the original description of S. apiculata by Wallroth (1833) 
as well as the recircumscription by Fuckel (1870). In his original </p>

<p>description of D. spina Fuckel (1870) provided a drawing that is 
quite unlike the original description of S. apiculata. Based on the 
comparison of descriptions and the specimens observed, we do not 
consider S. apiculata and D. spina to be synonyms. The synonymy 
of these two species proposed by Höhnel (1917) and accepted 
by Petrak's (1921) who provided a description of Cryptodiaporthe 
apiculata (≡ Sphaeria apiculata ) may be the reason that later 
authors considered S. apiculata to be characterised by narrow, 
elongated ascospores as described and observed for D. spina. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma barriae Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 62: 69. 2008. </p>

<p>Note: Sogonov et al. (2008) provided a description and illustrations 
of this species. Cultures of isolates used in this study are illustrated 
in Fig. 7G-H. Originally described from the state of Washington 
(USA), this species is here reported from Oregon. </p>

<p>Specimens examined: USA, Oregon, on Acer sp., coll. L.C. Mejía LCM 484.01, 
BPI 878953, derived culture CBS 126125 = LCM 484.01; Washington, on Acer 
macrophyllum, L.C. Mejía 601, BPI 87895, derived culture LCM 601.01. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma convexum (Preuss) L.C. Mejía, comb. nov. 
MycoBank MB515690. Fig. 2K-R. </p>

<p>Basionym: Sphaeria convexa Preuss, Linnea 26: 714. 1853. </p>

<p>≡ Diaporthe convexa (Preuss) Sacc., Syll. Fung. 1: 630. 1882. 
= Cryptodiaporthe salicina Wehm. as (Curr.) Wehm., The Genus Diaporthe 
Nitschke and its Segregates p. 194. 1933. 
[≡ Sphaeria salicina Curr., Trans. Linn. Soc. Lond., 22: 279, 1858 non 
Sphaeria salicina Pers., 1796] 
≡ Diaporthe punctata (Cooke) Berl. &amp; Voglino, Syll. Fung., Add. 108. 
1886. </p>

<p>Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary or in groups of up to four, 
appearing initially as slight conic elevation of periderm with apex 
protruding through a small hole, black, globose, (180-)213-258(-
326) μm high × (282-)303-352(-415) μm diam (mean = 238 × 329, 
SD 38, 44, n = 13), each with one neck. Neck central to eccentric, 
cylindrical, thick, usually thicker toward apex, some thicker elsewhere 
on neck, upright, diagonally straight, or curved, closely appressed 
when in groups, (82-)161-204(-222) μm long (mean = 176, SD 36, 
n = 13), (71-)82-104(-121) μm diam at base (mean = 95, SD 16, n = 
13), (64-)78-108(-128) μm diam at apex (mean = 93, SD 21, n = 13), 
apex usually paler. Asci clavate, (54-)60-63(-69) × (14-)15-18(-20) 
μm (mean = 61 × 17, SD 4.5, 2.2, n = 8) apical ring 3.0-4.0 μm diam, 
with eight ascospores arranged obliquely parallel to multiseriate. 
Ascospores ellipsoid-fusoid, tapering toward rounded ends, curved 
or straight, one median to submedian septum, constricted, (16-)18-
20(-22) × 4-5 μm (mean = 18.5 × 4.5, SD 1.0, 0.4, n = 51), l : w 
(3.2-)3.9-4.5(-4.9) (mean = 4.2, SD 0.4, n = 51), with four refractive 
bodies of various shapes, often globose. </p>

<p>Habitat and host: On twigs of Salix spp. </p>

<p>Distribution: Germany, USA (New York). </p>

<p>Lectotype specimen of Sphaeria convexa designated here: 
Sphaeria convexa Preuss, without other data, ex. Herb. Brussels in 
Shear study collection types and rarities, BPI 799418. </p>

<p>Epitype specimen of Sphaeria convexa designated here: USA, 
New York, Tompkins Co., near Ithaca, Arnot Forest, on Salix sp., 12 
Jul 2002, L. Vasilyeva, BPI 843490, derived culture CBS 123206. </p>



<p>Mejía et al. </p>

<p>Notes: Plagiostoma convexum as Sphaeria convexa was 
considered a synonym of Cryptodiaporthe salicina by Wehmeyer 
(1933). Plagiostoma convexum has ascospores that agree with 
those drawn by Wehmeyer (1933 as C. salicina, plate XIII, figs 
3-5). In his description of S. salicina, Currey (1858) mentions 
that the septum in the sporidia (ascospores) is "often very 
difficult to make out", but the ascospores in his drawing have a 
septum. The rest of his description agrees with the description 
of S. convexa. It also agrees with the lectotype specimen of S. 
convexa, BPI 799418 ex. Herb. Brussels with a note on the label 
saying apparently from Preuss). This evidence suggests that S. 
salicina Curr. 1858 and S. convexa Preuss 1852 represent the 
same species. Because S. salicina Curr. is a later homonym 
of Sphaeria salicina Pers. 1796, this basionym cannot be used 
and the next available epithet is S. convexa; hence the correct 
name for this taxon is Plagiostoma convexum. The specimen BPI 
799418 is here designated the lectotype and the specimen BPI 
843490 with the ex-epitype culture CBS 123206 is designated the 
epitype of Sphaeria convexa. 
Wehmeyer (1933) listed 28 synonyms of Cryptodiaporthe 
salicina. Among specimens that Wehmeyer (1933) recognised 
under that name, Butin (1958) elaborated differences in ascospore 
morphology, conidial state, host, and ecological characteristics 
and distinguished three species: C. apiculata (Wallr.) Petr., 
C. populea (Sacc.) Butin, and C. pulchella (Sacc.) Butin, here 
accepted as Plagiostoma apiculatum, P. populinum, and P. 
pulchellum. Butin (1958) did not consider any of these species 
to be conspecific with Sphaeria salicina Curr. On the contrary he 
listed Cryptodiaporthe salicina based on Sphaeria salicina Curr. 
as a synonym of Cryptodiaporthe salicella, here recognised as 
Plagiostoma salicellum. Although Wehmeyer (1933) listed Sphaeria 
sphingiophora Oudem. 1873 [≡ Diaporthe sphingiophora (Oudem.) 
Sacc.] as a synonym of C. salicella, S. sphingiophora occurs on 
Cornus. It is unlikely to be the same species as P. convexum. 
Diaporthe cupulata Berl. &amp; Destrée was considered a synonym of 
Sphaeria convexa by Wehmeyer (1933), however, the ascospore 
sizes of these species are different. We do not consider them to 
be synonymous. The specimen at BPI of Sphaeria salicina Pers., 
Scleromyceti Sueciae 10, was examined and determined to be a 
species of Valsa. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma devexum (Desm.) Fuckel, Jahrb. Nassauischen 
Vereins Naturk. 23-24: 119. 1870. </p>

<p>Basionym: Sphaeria devexa Desm., Pl. Cryptog. Nord. de France, 
Edit. II, Ser. II, No. 367. 1856. </p>

<p>≡ Gnomonia devexa (Desm.) Auersw. in Gonn. &amp; Rabenh., Mycol. Europ. 
5/6: 23. 1869. 
≡ Gnomoniella devexa (Desm.) Sacc., Syll. Fung. 1: 417. 1881. 
≡ Gnomoniopsis devexa (Desm.) Moesz &amp; Smarods, Bot. Közlem. 38: 
68. 1941. 
= Sphaeria excentrica Cooke &amp; Peck, Annual Rep. New York State Mus. 25: 
105. 1873 fide Monod (1983). 
≡ Gnomoniella excentrica (Cooke &amp; Peck) Sacc., Syll. Fung. 1: 418. 1882. 
= Diaporthe sechalinensis Sacc., Atti Del Congr. Bot. Di Palermo 1902: 52. 
1902 fide Monod (1983). 
= Ceriosporella polygoni A. L. Sm. &amp; Ramsb., Trans. Brit. Mycol. Soc. 4: 325. 
1914 fide Monod (1983). </p>

<p>Note: Barr (1978) and Monod (1983) provided detailed descriptions 
of this species. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma dilatatum L.C. Mejía, sp. nov. MycoBank 
MB515700. Figs 3A-D, 7I-L. </p>

<p>Etymology: dilatatum -dilate; referring to the dilated or expanded 
area of the perithecial neck that appears disk-like when seen from 
above, and like a thick collar in section. </p>

<p>Perithecia globosa, (277-)320-442(-502) μm elata, (382-)475-572(-642) μm 
diametro; rostrum breve, apice punctatum, (152-)257-308(-327) μm longum, cum 
expansa area disciformi vertice visu, simili collo in sectione, (217-)352-401(-452) 
μm diametro ubi latissima, (92-)95-108(-122) μm diametro apice. Ascosporae 
reniformes vel oblongo-ellipticae, uni-septatae, constrictae ubi medianae vel 
submedianae septatae, (12-)13-15(-22) × (4-)4-5(-7) μm, L:l (2.6-)3.0-3.3(-3.8). </p>

<p>Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary or aggregated, appearing 
initially as slight elevation of periderm surrounded by a black halo, 
later developing into a black circular spot, apex protruding through 
a tiny slit, globose, (277-)320-442(-502) μm high × (382-)475-
572(-642) μm diam (mean = 383 × 515, SD 78, 79, n1 = 11, n2 = 
10), each with one neck. Neck central to eccentric, relatively short, 
with punctate ostiolar opening, expanded, initially below epidermis, 
appearing disk-like when seen from above, like a thick collar in 
section, becoming exposed, with black halo or circular area below 
epidermis, when epidermis removed, exposing expanded neck and 
apex, sometimes two necks joined at expanded area; sometimes 
black mycelium of developing conidioma above perithecia; neck 
(152-)257-308(-327) μm long (mean = 263, SD 61, n = 10), (217-) 
352-401(-452) μm diam at base (mean = 367, SD 67, n = 10), 
(92-)95-108(-122) μm diam at apex (mean = 103, SD 10, n = 9). 
Asci cylindric, (48-)54-62(-77) × (8-)12-14(-18) μm (mean = 58 × 
13, SD 7.2, 2.5, n = 15), long stalked, apical ring 2.1-4.3 μm diam, 
appearing rectangular, with eight ascospores arranged obliquely 
parallel to multiseriate. Ascospores renoid to oblong-ellipsoid, 
slightly tapering to rounded ends, slightly curved, one, median to 
submedian septum, slightly constricted, (12-)13-15(-22) × 4-5(-
7) μm (mean = 15 × 5, SD 2.5, 1.0, n = 48), l : w (2.6-)3.0-3.3(-3.8) 
(mean = 3.2, SD 0.3, n = 48), with granular cytoplasm. </p>

<p>Cultures: Moderate to fast growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 5.2 cm 
(SD 0.2, n = 8), thin aerial mycelium of velvety to granular texture, 
whitish to vinaceous buff 86, becoming olivaceous 48 toward 
margin; fasiculate mycelium buff 45 developing from concave 
central area; reverse same; 7 d a.c.d. denser mycelium hazel 
88 in centre, with vinaceous 86, black droplets on surface, with 
immersed mycelium dark, reverse dark, with a lighter halo and 
whitish to translucent margin. </p>

<p>Habitat and host: On dead, still attached twigs of Salix caprea and 
S. irrorata (Salicaceae). </p>

<p>Distribution: France (Melle). </p>

<p>Holotype: France, Deux-Sèvres Département, Melle, Melle 
Arboretum, on Salix irrorata, 15 Apr 2008, L.C. Mejía 402, BPI 
878959, derived cultures CBS 124976 = LCM 402.02, = LCM402.01. </p>

<p>Additional specimens examined: France, Deux-Sèvres Département, Foret del' 
Hermitain, on Salix caprea, 17 Apr. 2008, L.C. Mejía 403, BPI 878958, derived 
cultures LCM403.01, LCM403.02. </p>

<p>Notes: The intricate mycelium that develops above the body of the 
perithecia in some pustules resembles the conidioma of Diplodina, 
the anamorph of Plagiostoma. </p>



<p>www.studiesinmycology.org </p>

<p>a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma </p>



<p>Fig. 3. Morphology on natural substrate. A-D: Plagiostoma dilatatum: A-C = BPI 878959 (holotype), D = BPI 878958. E-H: P. exstocollum: E-G = BPI 878961 (holotype), H = 
BPI 878964. I-M: P. imperceptibile BPI 878967 (holotype). Bars = (A, E, I) 1mm; (M) 200 μm; (B, F, H, J) 100 μm; (C-D) 20 μm; (G, K-L) 10 μm. </p>



<p>Mejía et al. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma euphorbiae-verrucosae (M. Monod) Sogonov,  Stud. Mycol. 62: 72. 2008   Basionym: Gnomoniella euphorbiae-verrucosae M. Monod, Beih.  Sydowia 9: 42. 1983. </p>

<p>Note: Monod (1983) provided a detailed description of this species. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma exstocollum L.C. Mejía, sp. nov. 
MycoBank MB515701. Figs 3E-H, 7M-P. </p>

<p>Etymology: exsto -standing out; collus -neck, referring to the 
perithecial neck that emerges from the host periderm. </p>

<p>Perithecia suboblata, (186-)194-227(-278) μm etata, (219-)269-336(-341) μm 
diámetro, rostrum (197-)247-281(-382) μm longum, (50-)53-63(-67) μm diamwtro basi, 
(39-)44-49(-50) μm diametro apice. Ascosporae ellipsoideae, uni-septatae, constrictae 
ubi submedianae septatae, (9-)10-15(-16) × (2-)2-3(-4) μm, L:l (3-)4-4.5(-6). </p>

<p>Perithecia immersed in bark, aggregated in groups up to 12, joined 
by a scanty, brownish to cream stroma, occasionally solitary, 
appearing as elevations in bark where perithecial necks emerge 
through slit or crack in periderm, usually ellipsoid in shape when 
seen from top, black, suboblate, (186-)194-227(-278) μm high × 
(219-)269-336(-341) μm diam (mean = 216 × 293, SD 31, 49, 
n = 9), each with one neck. Neck marginal, slightly sulcate, long, 
(197-)247-281(-382) μm long (mean = 270, SD 54, n = 9), (50-) 
53-63(-67) μm diam at base (mean = 59, SD 6.1, n = 9), (39-)44-
49(-50) μm diam at apex (mean = 46, SD 3.7, n = 9). Asci cylindric 
to clavate, (15-)39-57(-76) × (3.5-)6.5-11(-13) μm (mean = 49.5 
× 8.5, SD 15.1, 2.6, n = 26), apical ring 1.5-3.5 μm diam, with eight 
ascospores arranged biseriate. Ascospores ellipsoid, tapering to 
rounded ends, 1-septate, constricted at submedian septum, (9-) 
10-15(-16) × 2-3(-4) μm (mean = 12.5 × 3.0, SD 2.4, 0.7, n = 49), l 
: w (3-)4-4.5(-6) (mean = 4.3, SD 0.4, n = 49), usually with at least 
four refractive circular bodies in each ascospore, two large ones on 
each side of septum, one smaller one at end of each cell. </p>

<p>Cultures: Moderate to fast growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 4.3 cm 
(SD 1, n = 16), thin aerial mycelium appearing velvety, margin 
fringed, stringy, whitish to buff 45 or vinaceous buff 86 from top, with 
a slightly to pronounced halo of thick, white mycelium extending 
about 2 cm from centre, reverse whitish to buff 45. </p>

<p>Habitat and host: On dead, still attached, overwintered twigs of 
Corylus californica (Betulaceae). </p>

<p>Distribution: USA (Oregon). </p>

<p>Holotype: USA, Oregon, Jackson Co., Upper Rogue River, River 
Bridge Campground, on Corylus californica, 20 May 2008, L.C. 
Mejía 468, BPI 878961, derived culture CBS 127663 = LCM468.01. </p>

<p>Specimens examined: USA, Oregon, Jackson Co., River Bridge Campground, 
Upper Rogue River, on Corylus californica, 20 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 469, BPI 
878962; on Corylus californica, 21 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 422, BPI 878959, derived 
culture LCM422.02; on Corylus californica, 21 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 472, BPI 
878963, derived culture LCM472.01; Upper Rogue River trail, on Corylus californica, 
21 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 473, BPI 878964, derived culture LCM473.01; Oregon, 
Lane Co., Willamette National Forest, Salmon Creek, 22 May 2008. L.C. Mejía 483, 
BPI 878965, derived culture LCM483.01; on Corylus californica, 23 May 2008, L.C. 
Mejía 464, BPI 878960, derived culture LCM464. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma fraxini (Redlin &amp; Stack) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 
62: 72. 2008. </p>

<p>Basionym: Gnomoniella fraxini Redlin &amp; Stack, Mycotaxon 32:185.  1988. </p>

<p>Note: This species, often as its anamorph referred to as Discula 
fraxinea (Peck) Redlin &amp; Stack, causes an anthracnose disease of 
ash and fringetree (Oleaceae) known most commonly in the eastern 
and midwestern United States, rarely from Oregon (Gregory et al.  2004, Rossman et al. 2004). Redlin &amp; Stack (1988) provided a 
detailed description of this species as Gnomoniella fraxini. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma geranii (Hollós) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 62: 72. 
2008. </p>

<p>Basionym: Gnomonia geranii Hollós, Annls. Mus. Nat. Hung. 7: 52. 
1909. </p>

<p>≡ Rostrocoronophora geranii (Hollós) Munk, Dansk Bot. Arkiv 15: 98. 
1953. </p>

<p>Note: Müller &amp; Arx (1962) and Monod (1983) provided detailed 
descriptions of this species as Gnomonia geranii. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma imperceptibile L.C. Mejía, sp. nov. MycoBank 
MB515702. Figs 3I-M, 7Q-R. </p>

<p>Etymology: imperceptibile referring to the very short, non-protruding 
neck, thus the species is difficult to see in nature. </p>

<p>Perithecia globosa, (289-)309-356(-414) μm elata, (385-)412-462(-504) μm 
diametro, rostrum breve, (136-)175-211(-225) μm longum, cum expansa area, 
disciformi vertice visu, simili collo in sectione, (251-)301-318(-351) μm diametro 
ubi latissima, (87-)89-100(-113) μm diametro apice. Ascosporae reniformes vel 
oblongo-ellipticae, uniseptatae, constrictae ubi septatae, (18-)19-20(-21) × (5-)6-
7(-8) μm, L:l (2.5-)2.9-3.1(-3.8). </p>

<p>Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary, appearing as slight elevations 
of periderm, central area pale, delimited by black halo from which 
apex of neck protrudes, black, globose, (289-)309-356(-414) μm 
high × (385-)412-462(-504) μm diam (mean = 338 × 437, SD 44, 
41, n = 7), each with one neck. Neck central to eccentric, short, with 
apex scarcely protruding through a tiny slit, with neck expanded 
below epidermis, disk-like when seen from above, like a thick collar 
in section, with black halo or circular black spot through epidermis 
or black when exposed, (136-)175-211(-225) μm long (mean 
= 189, SD 38, n = 4), (251-)301-318(-351) μm diam at widest 
point (mean = 307, SD 36.3, n = 5), (87-)89-100(-113) μm diam 
at apex (mean = 97.5, SD 10.5, n = 5). Asci ovoid elongate, often 
with long, slender, persistent stalk, (67-)76-80(-87) × (13-)18-
21(-24) μm (mean = 77.5 × 19.5, SD 4.9, 3.1, n = 11), apical ring 
3.0-4.5 μm diam, with eight ascospores arranged obliquely parallel 
to multiseriate. Ascospores renoid to oblong-ellipsoid, slightly 
tapering to broadly rounded ends, slightly curved, one median 
septum, slightly constricted, (18-)19-20(-21) × (5-)6-7(-8) μm 
(mean = 19.5 × 6.5, SD 0.9, 0.6, n = 45), l : w (2.5-)3(-4) (mean = 
3, SD 0.3, n = 45), with granular cytoplasm. </p>

<p>Cultures: Moderate growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 4 cm (SD 0.4, 
n = 4), thin aerial mycelium of velvety, powdery texture, margin 
stringy, colour grey becoming vinaceous buff 86 from the top, 
reverse isabelline 65. </p>

<p>Habitat and host: On twigs of Salix sp. (Salicaeae). </p>

<p>Distribution: USA (California). </p>



<p>www.studiesinmycology.org </p>

<p>a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma </p>

<p>Holotype: USA, California, Shasta Co., Cow Creek, close to Old 
Station, on Salix sp., 18 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 456, BPI 878967, 
derived cultures LCM456.01 and LCM456.02 = CBS 127495. </p>

<p>Note: Plagiostoma imperceptibile has an expanded neck similar to 
other species in the clade, specifically P. apiculatum, P. convexum, 
P. dilatatum, and P. pulchellum (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>Plagiostoma oregonense L.C. Mejía, sp. nov. MycoBank 
MB515703. Figs 4A-C, 7S-T. </p>

<p>Etymology: oregonense -from Oregon, referring to the only state in 
the USA where it was collected. </p>

<p>Perithecia subglobosa, (261-)270-326(-373) μm elata, (369-)381-400(-407) μm 
diametro; rostrum breve, (156-)168-182(-185) μm longum, cum expansa area, 
disciformi vertice visu, simili collo in sectione, (176-)182-204(-221) μm diametro 
ubi latissima, 119-120(-121) μm diametro apice. Ascosporae latoellipticae vel 
ellipticae, uni-septatae, constrictae medianae vel submedianae septatae, (16-)17-
19(-22)×(4-)6(-7) μm, L:l (2.6-)2.9-3.2(-4.0). </p>

<p>Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary, evident as conic-shaped 
elevation of periderm with neck protruding, black, globose to 
subglobose, (261-)270-326(-373) μm high × (369-)381-400(-
407) μm diam (mean = 304 × 389, SD 60, 19, n = 3), each with 
one neck. Neck eccentric or lateral, expanded, usually attached to 
periderm, (156-)168-182(-185) μm long (mean = 173, SD 16, n = 
3), (176-)182-204(-221) μm diam at base (mean = 195, SD 23, n = 
3), (119-)119-120(-121) μm diam at apex (mean = 120, SD 1.0, n 
= 3). Asci cylindric, (74-)78-92(-95) × (12-)15-17(-19) μm (mean 
= 86 × 16, SD 8, 2, n = 10), apical ring 2.8-4.0 μm diam, looks 
like a stretched hexagon, with eight ascospores arranged obliquely 
parallel or biseriate. Ascospores broadly ellipsoid to ellipsoid, with 
rounded ends, 1-septate, constricted at median to submedian 
septum, (16-)17-19(-22) × (4.5-)5.5-6(-7) μm (mean = 18.0 × 
6.0, SD 1.5, 0.5, n = 36), l : w (2.6-)2.9-3.2(-4.0) (mean = 3.1, SD 
0.3, n = 36), with granular cytoplasm. </p>

<p>Cultures: Moderate growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 4.6 cm (SD 
0.1, n = 2), thin aerial mycelium of felty texture, margin fringed, 
stringy, central area white, with a halo of aerial mycelium 1.5 cm 
from centre, marginal area buff 45m, reverse with a central circular 
area of 2 cm diam fawn 87. </p>

<p>Habitat and host: On overwintered branches of Salix sp. 
(Salicaceae). </p>

<p>Distribution: USA (Oregon). </p>

<p>Holotype: USA, Oregon, Lincoln Co., Fogarty Creek, on Salix 
sp., 24 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 597, BPI 878968, derived culture 
LCM597.01 = CBS 126124. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma ovalisporum L.C. Mejía, sp. nov. Figs 4D-H, 
7U-V. </p>

<p>Etymology: ovalis -ovoid; sporum -spore, referring to the ovoid 
shape of the ascospores. </p>

<p>Perithecia globosa, (246-)277-363(-385) μm elata, (394-)403-414(-427) μm 
diametro; rostrum breve, (131-)146-159(-162) μm longum, apice cupulatum, 
(125-)136-153(-194) μm basi, (113-)117-160(-168) μm diametro apice. Ascosporae 
ovoideae, non-septatae, (12-)14-16(-17) × (7-)7-8(-9) μm, L:l (1.6-) 1.8-2.0(-2.2). </p>

<p>Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary, or in groups up to five, usually 
in a row, scattered, erumpent, appearing as raised, conical area 
of bark periderm, with neck protruding through slit or hole, black, 
globose, (246-)277-363(-385) μm high × (394-)403-414(-427) 
μm diam (mean = 322 × 409, SD 57, 11, n = 6), each with one neck. 
Neck lateral, short and thick, apex cupulate, (131-)146-159(-162) 
μm long (mean = 151, SD 12, n = 6), (125-)136-153(-194) μm 
diam at base (mean = 150, SD 24, n = 6), (113-)117-160(-168) 
μm diam at apex (mean = 139, SD 24, n = 6). Asci cylindric to 
obclavate, (63.5-) 68.5-75.5(-87.5) × (12.5-)14.5-17(-18) μm 
(mean = 72 × 15.5, SD 6.5, 1.5, n = 19), apical ring 3.5-4.5 μm 
diam, with eight ascospores arranged obliquely parallel to biseriate. 
Ascospores ovoid, non-septate, appearing double-walled, more 
evident when stained with cotton blue lactophenol or Melzer's 
reagent, (12-)14-16(-17) × 7-8(-9) μm (mean = 15 × 7.5, SD 1.2, 
0.5, n = 35), l : w (1.6-)1.8-2(-2.2) (mean = 1.9, SD 0.1, n = 35). </p>

<p>Cultures: Moderate growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 4.2 cm (SD 0.1, 
n = 2), thin aerial mycelium of felty texture, margin fringed, like 
roots, whitish, with denser mycelium in centre within a radius of 
1 cm, reverse buff 45 becoming dark grey, whitish in the margin. </p>

<p>Habitat and host: On dead twigs of Salix sp. (Salicaceae). </p>

<p>Holotype: USA, Idaho, Idaho Co., near Burgdorf, Burgdorf Rd. 
FR246, parking area at camping site at Three Mile Creek, approx. 
GPS: N45º 18.139 W 115º 55.782, elevation 6309 ft, on dead twigs 
of Salix sp., 5 Sep. 2008 (NAMA Annual Foray, Orson K. Miller Jr. 
Memorial Foray), A.M. Minnis s.n., BPI 878969, derived culture 
CBS 124977 = LCM458.01. </p>

<p>Notes: This species differs from other species of Plagiostoma 
by having ovoid, non-septate ascospores. The other two 
known species of Plagiostoma with non-septate ascospores, P. 
euphorbiae-verrucosae and P. fraxini, occur on hosts other than 
Salix and their ascospores are ellipsoid-fusoid. Unlike P. dilatatum, 
P. ovalisporum does not have a circular black halo or spot at the 
point where the perithecial necks emerge through the periderm. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma petiolophilum (Peck) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 
62: 72. 2008. </p>

<p>Basionym: Sphaeria petiolophila Peck, Annual Rep. New York 
State Mus. 35: 144. 1884. </p>

<p>≡ Gnomonia petiolophila (Peck) Berl. &amp; Voglino, Syll. Fung. Addit. 1-4: 
90. 1886. 
≡ Cryptodiaporthe petiolophila (Peck) M.E. Barr, Mycol. Mem. 7: 136. 1978.   Notes: Barr (1978) provided a detailed description of this species 
as Cryptodiaporthe petiolophila. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma populinum (Fuckel) L.C. Mejía, comb. nov.  MycoBank MB515705.   Basionym: Cryptospora populina Fuckel, Jahrb. Nassauischen  Vereins Naturk. 23/24: 193. 1870.   = Diaporthe populea Sacc. in Mouton, Bull. Soc. Roy. Bot. Belgique 26: 174.  1887 fide Butin (1958). 
≡ Cryptodiaporthe populea (Sacc.) Butin, Sydowia 11: 31. 1958 [1957]. </p>

<p>Moderate to fast growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 3.3 cm (SD 1.2, n 
= 8), thin aerial mycelium of velvety or felty texture, whitish to buff 
45 or rosy buff 6 in central area and isabeline 65 in the margin, 
with some droplets (honey 64) in the centre, with fringed margin 
appearing like roots, reverse whitish to fawn 87 or honey 64, in </p>



<p>Mejía et al. </p>

<p>some cultures becoming dark and with a concentric halo light. 
Cultures are illustrated in Fig. 8A-D. </p>

<p>Notes: Butin (1958) presented a full description with illustrations 
of this species as Cryptodiaporthe populea. Because the name </p>

<p>Cryptodiaporthe populina (Fuckel)Petr. based on Valsa populina 
Fuckel was already occupied in Cryptodiaporthe, Butin (1958)  based his new combination on Diaporthe populea Sacc. When 
placed in Plagiostoma the basionym Cryptospora populina Fuckel 
provides the oldest epithet for this species. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Morphology on natural substrate. A-C: Plagiostoma oregonense BPI 878968 (holotype). D-H. P. ovalisporum: BPI 878969 (holotype). I-M. P. pulchellum: I, M = BPI 
878971, J = BPI 878974, K-L = BPI 878972. Bars = (A, D, I) 1 mm; (K) 300 μm; (B, E, J) 100 μm; (H, L-M) 20 μm; (C, F-G) 10 μm. </p>



<p>www.studiesinmycology.org </p>

<p>a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma </p>

<p>Plagiostoma pulchellum (Sacc. &amp; Briard) L.C. Mejía, comb. 
nov. MycoBank MB515706. Figs 4I-M, 8E-J. </p>

<p>Basionym: Diaporthe pulchella Sacc. &amp; Briard in Sacc., Atti Ist. 
Veneto Sci. 2, Ser. 6, 437. 1884. </p>

<p>≡ Cryptodiaporthe pulchella (Sacc. &amp; Briard) Butin, Phytopathol. Z. 32:  407. 1958.  = Diaporthe recedens Sacc., Ann. Mycol. 12: 290 1914 fide Butin (1958). </p>

<p>Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary, often growing close together, 
appearing initially as slight elevation of periderm, with black halo 
or black spot where apex protrudes through a small hole, black, 
globose, (311-)371-473(-613) μm high × (467-)483-642(-660) 
μm diam (mean = 435 × 563, SD 128, 99, n = 4), each with one neck. 
Neck central to eccentric, straight to oblique, with an expanded disk-
like area, initially below epidermis, becoming exposed with time, 
producing black halo or spot at surface, (169-)173-319(-388) μm 
long (mean = 257, SD 105, n = 4), (153-)209-256(-306) μm diam 
at widest point (mean = 231, SD 62.5, n = 4), (93-)99-160(-212) 
μm diam at apex (mean = 137, SD 54, n = 4). Asci ovoid elongated, 
(75-)85-107(-117) × (15-)17-21(-24) μm (mean = 95 × 19, SD  13.5, 3.0, n = 15), apical ring 4-4.8 μm diam, very thick, with eight 
ascospores arranged obliquely parallel to multiseriate. Ascospores 
oblong ellipsoid-elongated, slightly tapering, with rounded ends, 
straight to slightly curved, one median to submedian septum, not 
constricted, (17-)18-22(-27) × (5-)6-7(-7.5) μm (mean = 20.3 ×  6.3, SD 2.9, 0.6, n = 39), l : w (2.5-)2.9-3.4(-4.4) (mean = 3.2, SD  0.4, n = 39), with granular cytoplasm. </p>

<p>Cultures: Moderate growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 3.9 cm (0.8 n = 6), 
thin aerial mycelium whitish to rosy vinaceous 58 colour, of velvety, 
granular texture due to mycelial clumps ca. 500 um diam, isabeline 
65, produced in central area of 2.4 cm diam, central area appearing 
often moist, margin translucent to buff 45, with hyphae extending 
radially, stringy, becoming fringed toward margin; reverse whitish 
to rosy vinaceous 58 or olivaceous. At 14 d small black and dark 
green slimy droplet surrounded by a second halo rosy vinaceous 
58 with white greyish margin, reverse same colour pattern. </p>

<p>Habitat and host: On dead, still attached branches of Populus 
balsamifera, Populus sp., Salix babylonica, S. humboldtiana and  S. lucida (Salicaceae). </p>

<p>Distribution: North America, South America (Argentina), and 
Europe. </p>

<p>Type specimen: France, Troyes, on branch of Populus alba cv. 
pyramidalis, Briard n. 5, PAD-not available. </p>

<p>Specimens examined: Argentina, Tucumán, vicinity of Villa Nougués, on twigs of 
Salix humboldtiana, 16 Nov 2008, L.C. Mejía 623, BPI 878974, derived cultures 
LCM623.01 and LCM623.03. Netherlands, ex leaf of Populus balsamifera, (CBS 
170.69 as Cryptodiaporthe pulchella. USA, Maryland, Prince George's Co., 
Beltsville, USDA-BARC, outside of B011A, on twigs of Salix babylonica, 3 Mar 
2008, Amy Y. Rossman &amp; L.C. Mejía 365, BPI 878971, derived culture LCM365.04 
= CBS 126653; Maryland, Prince George's Co., Greenbelt, Lake Artemisia, on twigs 
of Salix babylonica, 15 Mar 2008, L.C. Mejía 371, BPI 878972, derived culture 
LCM371.02; Washington, Kitsap Co., Kitsap Memorial State Park, on twigs of Salix 
lucida, 28 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 438, BPI 878973, derived cultures LCM438.03 (= 
CBS 126122) and LCM438.04. </p>

<p>Notes: Butin (1958) refers to this species as saprobic on Populus 
spp. The evidence presented in this study shows that this species 
also infects Salix spp. and has a more extensive geographic 
distribution than previously reported. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma rhododendri (Auersw.) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 
62: 72. 2008. </p>

<p>Basionym: Gnomonia rhododendri Auersw. in Gonn. &amp; Rabenh., 
Mycol. Europ. 5/6: 26. 1869. </p>

<p>≡ Apiognomonia rhododendri (Auersw.) Remler, Bibliotheca Mycologica 
68: 74. 1979. </p>

<p>Note: Remler (1979 as A. rhododendri) and Monod (1983 as G. 
rhododendri) presented descriptions of this species. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma robergeanum (Desm.) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 
62: 73. 2008. </p>

<p>Basionym: Sphaeria robergeana Desm., Ann. Sci. Nat. Bot. ser. 3, 
16: 306. 1851. </p>

<p>≡ Diaporthe robergeana (Desm.) Niessl. in Rabenh., Fungi Europ. 2222. 
1882. 
≡ Cryptodiaporthe robergeana (Desm.) Wehm., The Genus Diaporthe 
Nitschke and its Segregates p. 200. 1933. </p>

<p>Note: Wehmeyer (1933) provided a description of this species as 
Cryptodiaporthe robergeana. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma salicellum (Fr.) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 62: 73. 
2008. Fig. 5A-H. </p>

<p>Basionym: Sphaeria salicella Fr., Syst. Mycol. 2: 377. 1823. </p>

<p>≡ Diaporthe salicella (Fr.) Sacc., Mycotheca Venet. 135. 1873. 
≡ Gnomonia salicella (Fr.) J. Schröt., Pilze Schles. 3, 2: 392.1897. 
≡ Chorostate salicella (Fr.) Traverso, Fl. Ital. Crypt. 2: 203. 1906. 
≡ Cryptodiaporthe salicella (Fr.) Wehm., The Genus Diaporthe Nitschke 
and its Segregates p. 193. 1933. </p>

<p>Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary or in groups up to five, 
scattered, evident as slight elevation of periderm, black, 
subglobose, (157-)208-308(-331) μm high × (339-)372-410(-
507) μm diam (mean = 257 × 397, SD 60, 43, n = 11), each with 
one neck. Neck cylindrical, eccentric to lateral, surrounded by a 
whitish stroma, (96-)147-202(-308) μm long (mean = 177, SD 67, 
n = 11), (61-)80-84(-95) μm diam at base (mean = 81, SD 8.8, n 
= 11), (54-)74-85(-91) μm diam at apex (mean = 79, SD 10, n = 
11). Asci cylindric to clavate, (40-)51.5-59(-63) × (11-)13-14(-15) 
μm (mean = 55 × 13, SD 5.8, 1.4, n = 15), with apical ring 2.0-3.5 
μm diam, with eight ascospores arranged obliquely parallel or 
irregularly seriate. Ascospores ellipsoid-elongated, slightly tapering 
toward rounded ends, 1-septate, often with short appendages 
1.5-2 μm, slightly constricted at median to submedian septum, 
(14-)17-20(-27) × 3-4(-5) μm (mean = 18.5 × 3.5, SD 2.3, 0.5, n 
= 57), l : w (3.2-)5.2-6.6(-8.7) (mean = 5.9, SD 1.1, n = 57), with 
granular cytoplasm. </p>

<p>Habitat and host: On dead, still attached branches of Salix alba, S. 
repens, and Salix sp. (Salicaceae). </p>

<p>Distribution: Europe. </p>

<p>Lectotype of Sphaeria salicella designated here: Scleromyceti 
Sueciae 188 issued 1821, Sbarbaro Collection, BPI exsiccati). </p>

<p>Epitype of Sphaeria salicella designated here: Austria, St. 
Margareten im Rosental, Kaernten, Drau-Auen. 9452/1, as 
Cryptodiaporthe apiculata on Salix alba, 2 May 2002, W. Jaklitsch 
1889, BPI 843527, derived culture CBS 121466. </p>

<p>Additional specimen examined: Germany, Langen, on Salix repens, L.C. Mejía , 
BPI 878975, derived culture CBS 126121 = LCM 449.01. </p>



<p>Mejía et al. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Morphology on natural substrate. A-H: Plagiostoma salicellum: A, B, D, G = Scleromyceti Sueciae 188 (lectotype), C, E, F, H = BPI 843527 (epitype); note whitish 
stromatic tissue surrounding perithecial neck in Figs 5.5 B and C. I-O: P. samuelsii: I, M, P = BPI 878977 (holotype), N-O = BPI 878979. Bars = (A) 1 mm; (I) 500 μm; (C, J) 
200 μm; (B, K) 100 μm; (D-G) 20 μm; (H, L-P) 10 μm. </p>



<p>www.studiesinmycology.org </p>

<p>a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma </p>

<p>Notes: The application of the name Sphaeria salicella Fr. has been 
the source of confusion and the subject of taxonomic studies since 
the 1800's. It was clearly specified by Fries (1823) that this name 
is typified by Fries : Scleromyceti Sueciae 188 issued in 1821. 
According to Wehmeyer (1933) and Butin (1958) confusion about 
this name was in part due to the fact that different parts of exsiccati 
Scleromyceti Sueciae 188 contain different species. One of the 
two species has the narrowly ellipsoid, elongated ascospores of P. 
salicellum while the other has the broadly ellipsoid ascospores of P. 
apiculatum. Not recognising the confusion regarding Scleromyceti 
Sueciae 188, Petrak (1921) wrongly suggested that S. salicella 
was characterised by having broadly ellipsoid ascospores and 
made a new combination Cryptodiaporthe salicella (Fr.) Petr. in 
addition to the new combination C. apiculata (Wallr.) Petr. based 
on S. apiculata Wallr. The latter species was wrongly considered 
to have narrowly ellipsoid, elongated ascospores. It is not clear if 
Petrak (1921) looked at the type specimen of S. apiculata or if he 
based his conclusions solely on the description of S. apiculata by 
Wallroth (1833). 
Wehmeyer (1933) arrived at a conclusion different from that of 
Petrak (1921). Wehmeyer (1933) studied the exsiccati Scleromyceti 
Sueciae 188 at the Farlow Herbarium and determined that this 
number and hence S. salicella Fr. were characterised by having 
narrowly ellipsoid, elongated ascospores. To use his words, S. 
salicella represents "the narrow-spored species". He synonymised 
S. salicella Fr. with C. apiculata (Wallr.) Petr. and published the 
combination C. salicella (Fr.) Wehm. (1933) non Petrak (1921). In 
addition, Wehmeyer (1933) made the new combination C. salicina 
(Curr.) Wehm. based on S. salicina Curr. for species having broadly 
ellipsoid ascospores (see notes under P. convexum). Later Butin  (1958) studied species of Cryptodiaporthe on Populus and Salix, 
examined Scleromyceti Sueciae 188 at Uppsala Herbarium, and 
suggested that S. salicella should be understood as the species 
with broadly ellipsoid ascospores and followed Petrak's concept of 
S. salicella. 
We studied the Scleromyceti Sueciae 188 (Sbarbaro collection) 
available at the BPI Herbarium as well as other exsiccati of taxa 
that have been synonymised with S. salicella and C. salicina 
including S. apiculata. In doing so we paid close attention to the 
original descriptions of S. apiculata Wallr. and S. salicella Fr. In 
referring to Scleromyceti Sueciae 188 Fries (1823) described 
S. salicella as having a powdery "albicant" (whitish) stroma and 
that the multiple ostioles are "erumpent simultaneously". The 
specimen of Scleromyceti Sueciae 188 at BPI includes all of these 
morphological characters and has ascospores that are ellipsoid 
elongated (see Fig. 5A, B, D, and G). 
In their treatment of Plagiostoma, Sogonov et al. (2008) made 
the combination Plagiostoma salicellum (Fr.) Sogonov. In our study 
of P. salicellum we noticed that ascospore length and width can 
be quite variable, even within an ascus, but with a prevalence of 
elongated ascospores (Fig. 5A-H). A second specimen, BPI 878975 
from Germany on Salix repens, was sequenced and determined 
to be conspecific with the epitype of P. salicellum within a major 
clade containing two other species having cylindrical ostioles and 
ellipsoid elongated ascospores. Unlike the lectotype and epitype of 
P. salicellium, the ascospores of BPI 878975 are ellipsoid but not 
elongated. In spite of this difference in ascospore morphology, BPI 
878975 is P. salicellum based on the cylindrical perithecial neck 
surrounded by a whitish stroma as well as DNA sequence data. 
In summary Plagiostoma salicellum is characterised by having 
cylindrical perithecial necks surrounded by a whitish stroma and 
ascospores predominantly ellipsoid-elongated, less commonly </p>

<p>ellipsoid, tapering to slightly acute, rounded ends (Fig. 5D-G), 
unlike P. apiculatum that has oblong ellipsoid to renoid, broadly 
rounded ascospores (Fig. 2H-J). </p>

<p>Plagiostoma samuelsii L.C. Mejía, sp. nov. MycoBank 
MB515707. Figs 5I-O, 8M-P. </p>

<p>Etymology: Named in honour of distinguished mycologist Gary J. 
Samuels for his outstanding contributions to the systematics of 
Pyrenomycetes. </p>

<p>Perithecia subglobosa, (192-)204-258(-305) μm elata, (295-)302-327(-334) μm 
diametro, rostrum conicum, (114-)128-161(-170) μm longum, (69-)72-74(-81) 
μm diametro basi, (58-)62-73(-78) μm diametro apice. Ascosporae ellipticae, uni-
septatae, constrictae ubi medianae vel submedianae septatae, (10-)11-12(-19) × 
3-4 μm, appendiculatae duabus extremitatibus, anguste filiformes, ascosporis vulgo 
2-plo longiores, appendices deliquescentes. </p>

<p>Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary or in groups up to five, 
scattered on substrate, evident as conical shaped elevations of host 
periderm with necks protruding through small holes in periderm, 
black, subglobose, (192-)204-258(-305) μm high × (295-)302-
327(-334) μm diam (mean = 239 × 313, SD 43, 16, n = 6), each 
with one neck. Neck eccentric to lateral, surrounded by a whitish 
stroma, cone-shaped with rounded apex, (114-)128-161(-170) μm 
long (mean = 145, SD 23, n = 6), (69-)72-74(-81) μm at base 
(mean = 73.8, SD 3.9, n = 6), (58-)62-73(-78) μm at apex (mean 
= 67.5, SD 8.0, n = 6). Asci cylindric to clavate, (32-)42-62(-79) 
× (6-)7-11(-12) μm (mean = 53 × 9, SD 13, 2.1, n = 24), apical 
ring 1.8-3.6 μm diam, with eight ascospores arranged obliquely 
parallel or biseriate. Ascospores ellipsoid, 1-septate, constricted at 
median to submedian septum, with two deliquescent appendages, 
one at end of each cell, narrowly filiform, usually twice the length of 
ascospores, (10-)11-12(-19) × 3-4 μm (mean = 12 × 3.5, SD 1.4, 
0.2, n = 48), l : w (2.8-)3.2-3.5(-4.8) (mean = 3.4, SD 0.4, n = 48), 
with four refractive bodies in each cell, two big ones near septum, 
one smaller one at end of each cell. </p>

<p>Cultures: Fast growth on PDA after 7 d reaching edge of petri plates 
of 6 cm diam (n = 8), thin aerial mycelium of felty to granular texture, 
fringed, stringy margin, with concentric halo of dense mycelium 1.4 
cm from centre, buff 45 inside halo or central region, white toward 
margin, some cultures with depression at concentric halo, reverse 
honey 64 developing a halo fawn 87 near margin. </p>

<p>Habitat and host: On dead, still attached twigs and branches of 
Alnus incana var. tenuifolia, A. rubra, and Alnus spp. (Betulaceae). </p>

<p>Distribution: USA (California, Oregon, Washington). </p>

<p>Holotype: USA, California, Plumas Co., Little Last Chance 
Creek, Chilcook Campground, on Alnus incana var. tenuifolia, 17 
May 2008, L.C. Mejía 454, BPI 878977, derived CBS 125668 = 
LCM454.04. </p>

<p>Specimens examined: USA, Oregon, Jackson Co., Upper Rogue River, on Alnus 
(tenuifolia?), 21 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 419, BPI 878976, derived culture LCM419.01 
and LCM419.02; Upper Rogue River trail on Alnus sp. 21 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 474, 
BPI 878978, derived culture LCM474.01; Washington, Clallam Co., Crescent Lake, 
on Alnus rubra (branch on soil), 27 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 596, BPI 878979, derived 
culture LCM596.01. </p>

<p>Notes: Plagiostoma samuelsii is the only species of Plagiostoma on 
leaves of Alnus except for P. jensenii M.E. Barr. Unlike P. samuelsii, </p>



<p>Mejía et al. </p>

<p>P. jensenii lacks a stroma and perithecial neck and has longer 
and wider ascospores (20-30 × 4-6 μm) with very short pulvinate 
appendages (Barr 1991). Most likely P. jensenii does not belong in 
Plagiostoma. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma versatile L.C. Mejía &amp; Sogonov, sp. nov. 
MycoBank MB515708. Figs 6A-C, 8Q-V. </p>

<p>Etymology: versatile -versatile, referring to the occurrence of this 
species on different plant organs, twigs, branches, and leaves; and 
to the variable nature of the perithecia that grow with short necks 
on twigs and branches and with medium to long necks on leaves. </p>

<p>Perithecia subglobosa, (178-)194-317(-345) μm elata, (232-)264-378(-444) μm 
diametro; rostrum cylindricum, (60-)77-137(-226) μm longum, (51-)56-80(-87) 
μm diamtro basi, (37-)49-60(-76) μm apice. Ascosporae elliptico-elongatae, uni-
septatae, constrictae ubi medianae vel submedianae septatae, (18-)20-23(-25) × 
3-4 μm, L:l (4.9-)5.6-6.8(-8.6). </p>

<p>Perithecia immersed in bark of twigs or in midvein and petioles of 
adaxial and abaxial side of leaves, solitary or in pairs, scattered, 
on twigs evident as slight elevations of periderm that appear black, 
upper part of perithecia showing a few cell layers below epidermis, 
on leaves producing swollen, raised areas on midvein, becoming 
highly erumpent, cracking periderm and leaving an ellipsoidal 
cavity, with longer neck on leaves than on twigs, black, subglobose, 
(178-)194-317(-345) μm high × (232-)264-378(-444) μm diam 
(mean = 248 × 323, SD 68.5, 78, n = 8), each with one neck. 
Neck eccentric to lateral, short, ostiolar opening sulcate with four 
grooves, (60-)77-137(-226) μm long (mean = 115, SD 59.7, n = 
8), (51-)56-80(-87) μm diam at base (mean = 68.5, SD 13.4, n =  8), (37-)49-60(-76) μm diam at apex (mean = 55, SD 11.8, n = 8). 
Asci cylindric to clavate, (49-)54-66(-71) × (11-)13-16(-20) μm 
(mean = 60 × 15, SD 7.5, 2.5, n = 15), apical ring 2.0-3.5 μm diam, 
with eight ascospores arranged biseriate. Ascospores ellipsoid 
elongated, slightly tapering toward rounded ends, 1-septate, 
constricted at median to submedian septum, (18-)20-23(-25) 
× 3-4 μm (mean = 21.5 × 3.5, SD 2.0, 0.4, n = 36), l : w (4.9-
)5.6-6.8(-8.6) (mean = 6.2, SD 1.0, n = 36), usually with four large 
refractive bodies, two near septum, one in each end of cells. </p>

<p>Cultures: Fast growth on PDA after 7 d reaching the edge of petri 
plates of 6 cm diam (n = 12), thin aerial mycelium of felty to granular </p>

<p>texture, margin fringed, like roots, buff 45 with clumps of white 
mycelium, with a halo of elevated mycelium at 1.5 cm from centre, 
reverse buff 45 becoming dark, with halo visible from reverse. </p>

<p>Habitat and hosts: On dead twigs of Salix scouleriana and Salix sp., 
on overwintered leaves of Salix sp. (Salicaceae). </p>

<p>Distribution: USA (Oregon, Washington); Canada (British 
Columbia). </p>

<p>Holotype: USA, Washington, Jefferson Co., intersection of Upper 
Hoh River Road &amp; Route 101, on Salix scouleriana, 27 May 
2008, L.C. Mejía 594, BPI 878980, derived culture CBS 124978 
= LCM594.01. </p>

<p>Additional specimens examined: Canada, British Columbia, Vancouver, on 
overwintered dead leaves of Salix sp., 12 May 2006, M. V. Sogonov 379, BPI 877702, 
derived culture CBS 121251 = AR4294. USA, Oregon, Lane Co., Willamette Pass, 
on Salix sp., 22 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 598, BPI 878982, derived culture LCM598.01; 
Washington, Jefferson Co., Hoh River Campground, on Salix scouleriana, 27 May 
2008, L.C. Mejía 595, BPI 878981, derived culture LCM595.01. </p>

<p>Notes: The ascospores of this species are similar to those of 
Plagiostoma salicellum, however, the perithecial necks of P. 
versatile lack the whitish stroma characteristic of P. salicellum. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma yunnanense L.C. Mejía &amp; Zhu L. Yang, sp. 
nov. MycoBank MB515709. Figs 6D-F, 8W-X. </p>

<p>Etymology: referring to the place where this species was collected: 
Yunnan, China. </p>

<p>Perithecia globosa, (231-)267-311(-318) μm elata, (282-)312-352(-362) μm 
diametro, rostrum cylindricum, contortum, (315-)318-321(-322) μm longum, (77-) 
78-81(-82) μm diametro basi, (57-)59-63(-66) μm diametro apice. Ascosporae 
elliptico-elongatae, uni-septatae, leviter vel non constrictum ubi septatae, (19-)23-
26(-27) × 3-4, L:l (6. 6-)6.8-7.9(-8.2). </p>

<p>Perithecia immersed, solitary or in groups, numerous, appearing 
as conical elevations of periderm where necks protrude, black, 
globose, (231-)267-311(-318) μm high × (282-)312-352(-362) 
μm diam (mean = 284 × 328, SD 48, 42, n = 3), each with one neck. 
Neck eccentric, contorted, (315-)318-321(-322) μm long (mean = 
319, SD 3.8, n = 3), (77-)78-81(-82) μm diam at base (mean = 79, </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Morphology on natural substrate. A-C. Plagiostoma versatile: A-B = BPI 878980 (holotype), C = BPI 877702. D-F. P. yunnanense BPI 878983 (holotype). Bars = (A, 
C-D, F) 200 μm; (B, E) 10 μm. </p>



<p>www.studiesinmycology.org </p>

<p>a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma </p>



<p>Cultures: Moderate growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 3.4 cm (SD 
0.2, n = 4). Mycelium of granular texture, margin stringy, whitish 
with granules, becoming grey or vinaceous buff, reverse with dark 
inclusions near centre, most of colony whitish. </p>

<p>Habitat and host: On dead, still attached branches of Salix sp. 
(Salicaceae). </p>

<p>Distribution: China (Yunnan). </p>

<p>Holotype: China, Yunnan, Ailoshan, on Salix sp., 14 Jul. 2008, L.C. 
Mejía 513, BPI 878983, derived cultures CBS 124979 = LCM513.03 
and LCM513.02. </p>

<p>Additional names in Cryptodiaporthe and Plagiostoma </p>

<p>Cryptodiaporthe acerinum J. Reid &amp; Cain, Canad. J. Bot. 
40: 839. 1962. </p>

<p>Notes: A fresh specimen determined to be this species was cultured 
and sequenced. Analyses of LSU and RPB2 sequences place this 
species in a basal branch of the Gnomoniaceae. </p>

<p>Specimen examined: USA, New York, Adirondacks, Cranberry Lake, on dead branch 
of Acer sp., 13 Jun. 2002, L. Vasilyeva, BPI 870989, culture CBS 121465 = AR 3822. </p>

<p>Cryptodiaporthe aculeans (Schwein.) Wehm., The Genus 
Diaporthe Nitschke and its Segregates p. 212. 1933. </p>

<p>Basionym: Sphaeria aculeans Schwein., Trans. Am. Phil. Soc., 
New Series 4(2): 204. 1834,. [1832]. </p>

<p>Notes: The only available culture of this species was sequenced. 
Analyses of LSU sequences place this species in a clade sister to 
the Melanconidaceae. </p>

<p>Culture sequenced: Japan, on branch of Rhus javanica, isol. G. 
Okada, CBS 525.85. </p>

<p>Cryptodiaporthe aubertii (Westend.) Wehm., The Genus 
Diaporthe Nitschke and its Segregates 202. 1933. </p>

<p>Basionym: Sphaeria aubertii Westend., Bull. Acad. R. Sci. Belg., Cl. 
Sci., sér. 2: tab. 7, no. 5. 1859. </p>

<p>Notes: A culture of this species was sequenced. Analyses of this 
LSU sequence suggests that this species is related to the genus 
Cryptosporella within the Gnomoniaceae. </p>

<p>Culture sequenced: Sweden, Småland, on Myrica gale, 14 Apr. 
1989, K. &amp; L. Holm, isol. O. Constantinescu 89-53, CBS 114196. </p>

<p>Cryptodiaporthe galericulata (Tul. &amp; C. Tul.) Wehm., The 
Genus Diaporthe Nitschke and its Segregates p. 211. 1933. </p>

<p>Basionym: Valsa galericulata Tul. &amp; C. Tul., Select. Fung. Carpol. 
(Paris) 2: 203. 1863. </p>

<p>Notes: A fresh specimen determined to be this species was cultured 
and sequenced. Analyses of LSU sequences suggest this species 
belongs in the Sydowiellaceae. </p>

<p>Specimen examined: USA, Tennessee, Great Smoky Mts. National Park, near 
Cosby, Horse Trail, on Fagus grandifolia, 25 Mar. 2002, L. Vasilyeva, BPI 863767 
ex culture AR 3811. </p>

<p>Cryptodiaporthe liquidambaris Petr., Sydowia 5: 236. 1951. </p>

<p>Notes: A fresh specimen determined to be this species was cultured 
and sequenced. Analyses of LSU sequences place this species 
within the Diaporthales but not within any described family. </p>

<p>Specimen examined: USA, Maryland, Beltsville, on overwintered twig of Liquidambar 
styraciflua, 15 May 2001, M. Barr, isol. A. Rossman, BPI 749123 culture AR 3648 
(now dead). </p>

<p>Cryptodiaporthe macounii (Dearn.) Wehm., The Genus 
Diaporthe Nitschke and its Segregates p. 191. 1933. </p>

<p>Basionym: Diaporthe macounii Dearn., Mycologia 8: 100. 1916. </p>

<p>Note: This species was included in the genus Gnomoniopsis 
(Gnomoniaceae) by Sogonov et al. (2008). </p>

<p>Cryptodiaporthe vepris (Delacr.) Petr., Ann. Mycol. 32: 445. 
1934. </p>

<p>Basionym: Sphaeria vepris Delacr., Fungi europ. 443. 1862. </p>

<p>Notes: A fresh specimen determined to be this species was cultured 
and sequenced. Analyses of LSU sequences place this species 
within the Diaporthales but not in any described family. </p>

<p>Specimen examined: Austria, Wograda, St. Margareten, Kaernten, on Rubus 
idaeus, 27 Oct. 2000, W. Jaklitsch 1661, isol. A. Rossman, BPI 749132, culture 
AR 3559. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma acerophilum (Dearn. &amp; House) M.E. Barr, 
Mycol. Mem. 7: 113. 1978. </p>

<p>Basionym: Gnomoniopsis acerophila Dearn. &amp; House, Bull. New 
York State Mus. 233-234: 36. 1921. </p>

<p>Notes: A fresh specimen determined to be this species was cultured 
and sequenced. This species falls within the Gnomoniaceae 
according to analyses of ITS sequences but not within any known 
genus. The perithecial neck of this species is lateral, upright, and 
slightly curved at the apex. </p>

<p>Specimens examined: USA, New York, Sullivan Co., Roscoe, on overwintered 
leaves of Acer pensylvanicum, Jul. 2005, M.V. Sogonov MS 0302, BPI 877681; 
Tennessee, Blount Co., Great Smoky Mountains National Park, Cades Cove, on 
overwintered petioles of Acer pensylvanicum, 24 May 2006, M.V. Sogonov MS 0467, 
BPI 877679; Sevier Co., Great Smoky Mountains National Park, on overwintered 
leaves and petioles of Acer pensylvanicum, 22 May 2006, M.V. Sogonov MS 0473, 
BPI 877682. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma alneum (Fr.) Arx, Antonie van Leeuwenhoek 
17: 264. 1951. </p>

<p>= Sphaeria alnea Fr. : Fr., Observ. mycol. 1: 185. 1815 : Syst. Mycol. 2: 520. 
1823. </p>

<p>Notes: This species is now regarded as Gnomonia alnea (Fr.) 
Sogonov and was described and illustrated in Sogonov et al. 
(2008). </p>



<p>Mejía et al. </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Culture morphology. A-B. Plagiostoma aesculi. CBS 126127 = LCM447.01. C-F. P. apiculatum. C-D. LCM 393.01. E-F. CBS 126126 = LCM436.01. G-H. P. barriae. 
LCM 601.02. I-L. P. dilatatum. I-J. LCM 402.01. K-L. LCM 403.01. M-P. P. exstocollum. M-N. LCM 422.02. O-P. LCM 468.02. Q-R. P. imperceptibile. LCM 456.01. S-T. 
P. oregonense. Ex-type CBS 126124 = LCM 597.01. U-V. P. ovalisporum.LCM 458.05. W-X. P. petiolophilum. CBS 126123 = LCM 181.01. A-D, I-L, W-X. Colony habit, 10 d, 
23 °C. E-H, M-R, U-V. Colony habit, 9 d, 23 °C. S-T. Colony habit, 7 d, 23 °C. A, C, E, G, I, K, M, O, Q, S, U, W. Reverse. B, D, F, H, J, L, N, P, R, T, V, X. Surface. </p>



<p>www.studiesinmycology.org </p>

<p>a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma </p>

<p>Fig. 8. Culture morphology. A-D. Plagiostoma populinum. A-B. CBS 144.57. C-D. CBS 174.58. E-J. P. pulchellum. E-F. LCM 438.04. G-H. LCM 371.02. I-J. LCM 623.01. 
K-L. P. salicellum. CBS 126121 = LCM449.01. M-P. P. samuelsii. M-N. Ex-type CBS 125668 = LCM 454.04. O-P. LCM 596.01. Q-V. P. versatile. Q-R. Ex-type CBS 124978 
= LCM 594.01. S-T. LCM 595.01. U-V. LCM 598.01. W-X. P. yunnanense. Ex-type CBS 124979 = LCM 513.03. A-D, G-H, W-X. Colony habit, 10 d, 23 °C. E-F, K-N. Colony 
habit, 9 d, 23 °C. I-J, O-V. Colony habit, 7 d, 23 °C. A, C, E, G, I, K, M, O, Q, S, U, W. Reverse. B, D, F, H, J, L, N, P, R, T, V, X. Surface. </p>



<p>Mejía et al. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma arnstadtiense (Auersw.) M. Monod, Beihefte 
Sydowia 9: 143. 1983. </p>

<p>Basionym: Gnomonia arnstadtiensis Auersw. in Gonnerm. &amp; 
Robenh., Mycol. Europ. 5/6: 22. 1869. </p>

<p>Notes: This species is now accepted in Gnomonia according to 
Sogonov et al. (2008). </p>

<p>Plagiostoma bavaricum (Rehm) M.E. Barr, Mycol. Mem. 7: 
112. 1978. </p>

<p>Basionym: Hypospila bavarica Rehm, Ann. Mycol. 6:322. 1908. </p>

<p>Note: Based on an LSU sequence, this species belongs in the 
Gnomoniaceae but it cannot be placed in a genus. </p>

<p>Culture sequenced: Switzerland, on Acer opalus, M. Monod, 
CBS 772.79. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma conradii (Ellis) M.E. Barr, Mycol. Mem. 7: 107. 
1978. </p>

<p>Basionym: Diaporthe conradii Ellis, Am. Nat. 17: 316. 1883. </p>

<p>Notes: A fresh specimen determined to be this species was cultured 
and sequenced. Analysis of the LSU sequence suggests this species 
is closely related to Cryptodiaporthe aubertii and Cryptosporella but 
not within any known genus in the Gnomoniaceae. The perithecial 
neck of this species is lateral and upright. </p>

<p>Specimen examined: USA, New Jersey, on living stems of Hudsonia tomentosa, G. 
Bills, BPI 746482, culture CBS 109761 = AR 3488. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma inclinatum (Auersw.) M.E. Barr, Mycol. Mem. 
7: 115. 1978. </p>

<p>Basionym: Gnomonia inclinata Auersw. in Rabenh., Mycol. Europ. 
5/6: 27. 1869. </p>

<p>[≡ Sphaeria inclinata Desm., Ann. Sci. Nat. Bot. III, 16: 315. 1851 non 
Schwein. 1832] </p>

<p>Notes: Two isolates of this species were sequenced. This species 
apparently belongs in the Gnomoniaceae but it cannot be placed 
in a genus. </p>

<p>Cultures sequenced: The Netherlands, on dead leaf of Acer 
pseudoplatanus, CBS 209.67. Switzerland, on Acer platanoides, 
M. Monod, CBS 830.79. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma jensenii M.E. Barr, Mycotaxon 41: 298. 1991. </p>

<p>Note: Based on the lack of a perithecial neck and the pulvinate 
appendages on the ascospores, P. jensenii most likely does not 
belong in Plagiostoma. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma lugubre (P. Karst.) Bolay, Ber. Schweiz. Bot. 
Ges. 81: 436. 1972. </p>

<p>Basionym: Gnomonia lugubris P. Karst., Bidr. Känn. Finl. Nat. Folk 
23: 121. 1873. </p>

<p>Note: The disposition of this species was not investigated in this 
study. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma magnoliae (Ellis) M.E. Barr, Mycol. Mem. 7: 
117. 1978. </p>

<p>Basionym: Gnomonia magnoliae Ellis, Amer. Nat. 17: 318. 1883. </p>

<p>Notes: This species has been reported in leaves of Magnolia 
virginiana in North America. The perithecial neck of this species 
is lateral and obliquely upright as drawn by Barr (1978). The 
disposition of this species was not investigated in this study. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma micromegalum (Ellis &amp; Everh.) M.E. Barr, 
Mycol. Mem. 7: 112. 1978. </p>

<p>Basionym: Diaporthe micromegala Ellis &amp; Everh., Proc. Acad. Nat. 
Sci. Philadelphia 1893: 449. 1894. </p>

<p>Notes: This species is now placed in Ophiognomonia as O. 
micromegala (Ellis &amp; Everh.) Sogonov according to Sogonov et al. 
(2008). </p>

<p>Plagiostoma petrakii (E. Müll.) M. Monod, Beihefte Sydowia 
9: 146. 1983. </p>

<p>Basionym: Plagiostigme petrakii E. Müll., Sydowia 18:90. 1965. </p>

<p>Note: No material of this species was located. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma pseudobavaricum M. Monod, Beihefte 
Sydowia 9: 151. 1983. </p>

<p>Notes: ITS sequences of this species were included in a 
phylogenetic analysis. Although closely related to Apiognomonia 
and Plagiostoma, the results suggest that this species may 
represent an undescribed genus within the Gnomoniaceae. </p>

<p>Specimens examined: USA, New York, Adirondack Mts., Cranberry Lake, on 
petioles of Acer sp., 22 Jun. 2002, L. Vasilyeva, BPI 843494, ex culture AR 3819; 
ibid., 23 Jun. 2002, L. Vasilyeva, BPI 843495, ex culture AR 3894; Tennessee, 
Sevier Co., Great Smokey Mountains National Park, on overwintered petioles of 
Acer saccharum, 22 May 2006, M.V. Sogonov MS 0483, BPI 877700. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma robertiani (Petr.) M.E. Barr, Mycol. Mem. 7: 
113. 1978. </p>

<p>Basionym: Gnomonia robertiani Petr., Ann. Mycol. 23: 122. 1925. </p>

<p>Note: No material of this species was located. </p>

<p>Plagiostoma tormentillae (Lind) Bolay, Ber. Schwiz. Bot. 
Ges. 81: 436. 1971. </p>

<p>Basionym: Gnomoniella tormentillae Lind, Bot. Tidsskr. 41: 217. 
1931. </p>

<p>Note: This species is now recognised as Gnomoniopsis tormentillae 
(Lind) Sogonov according to Sogonov et al. (2008). </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This work was funded by the National Science Foundation Partnerships for 
Enhancing Expertise in Taxonomy (NSF 03-28364). Additional funding for field 
work by LCM was received through Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ, from 
the Neyra Fund, the Spencer Davis Research Award from the Department of Plant 
Biology and Pathology, a Special Study Support Award, and a Graduate School 
Travel Award and through the Backus Award from the Mycological Society of 
America. Much appreciation is extended to Lena Struwe for her valuable comments 
and insights during the course of this work. We acknowledge and appreciate </p>



<p>www.studiesinmycology.org </p>

<p>a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma </p>

<p>Andrew Minnis for providing a specimen from which the new species Plagiostoma 
ovalisporum was described and for nomenclatural advice. Christian Feuillet kindly 
provided translations of the diagnoses into Latin. Tunesha Phipps and Sasha Allen 
are sincerely acknowledged for their technical expertise in the molecular laboratory. 
LCM appreciates the following people for graciously hosting visits for collecting 
and facilitating the shipment of specimens: Michael Giraurd, Adriana Hladki, Tina 
Hoffman, Christian Lechat, Christophe Lecuru, and Ralph Mangelsdorff. Special 
thanks to Zhu LiangYang for hosting LCM and providing superb logistical support 
during his collecting trip in China. </p>



</text></tei>