<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3001088" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:39+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Alternative splicing has emerged as an important 
target for molecular therapies. Splice-switching 
oligonucleotides (SSOs) modulate alternative 
splicing by hybridizing to pre-mRNA sequences 
involved in splicing and blocking access to the tran-
script by splicing factors. Recently, the efficacy of 
SSOs has been established in various animal 
disease models; however, the application of SSOs 
against cancer targets has been hindered by poor 
in vivo delivery of antisense therapeutics to tumor 
cells. The apoptotic regulator Bcl-x is alternatively 
spliced to express anti-apoptotic Bcl-x L and pro-
apoptotic Bcl-x S . Bcl-x L is upregulated in many 
cancers and is associated with chemoresistance, 
distinguishing it as an important target for cancer 
therapy. We previously showed that redirection 
of Bcl-x pre-mRNA splicing from Bcl-x L to -x S 
induced apoptosis in breast and prostate cancer 
cells. In this study, the effect of SSO-induced Bcl-x 
splice-switching on metastatic melanoma was as-
sessed in cell culture and B16F10 tumor xenografts. 
SSOs were delivered in vivo using lipid 
nanoparticles. Administration of nanoparticle with 
Bcl-x SSO resulted in modification of Bcl-x 
pre-mRNA splicing in lung metastases and 
reduced tumor load, while nanoparticle alone 
or formulated with a control SSO had no effect. 
Our findings demonstrate in vivo anti-tumor 
activity of SSOs that modulate Bcl-x pre-mRNA 
splicing. </p>

<p>Over 90% of multi-exon pre-mRNA transcripts undergo 
alternative splicing (1) and up to one-half of </p>

<p>disease-causing mutations affect splicing (2). Thus, in 
addition to its significant contribution to proteome 
diversity, alternative splicing constitutes an important 
therapeutic target (3). Splice-switching oligonucleotides 
(SSOs) modulate alternative splicing by hybridizing 
to pre-mRNA sequences involved in splicing and 
blocking access by various splicing factors (4,5). Unlike 
siRNA and traditional antisense approaches, which lead 
to RNA degradation by RISC and RNase H-mediated 
cleavage, respectively, direction of pre-mRNA splicing 
requires that the SSO-targeted RNA is not degraded. 
This is achieved by altering the oligonucleotide 
sugar-phosphate backbone as in, for example, the 
2 
0 -O-methoxyethyl (MOE) ribose modification (6,7). In 
order to realize their full therapeutic utility, SSOs must 
be efficiently delivered to the pharmacological site of 
action in vivo (8). This can be achieved by exploiting the 
inherent pharmacodynamic properties of the SSO chemis-
try (9,10), conjugation of cell penetrating peptides (11-13), 
and the use of nanoparticle carriers (14). As a result, in vivo 
efficacy has been established for SSOs in animal models of 
inflammatory disease, b-thalassemia and Duchenne 
muscular dystrophy (DMD) [For a recent review, see 
(15)], and early phase clinical trials using SSOs to treat 
DMD have yielded promising results (16,17). 
Previously, this laboratory and others applied SSOs 
to manipulate the splicing pattern of the apoptotic regu-
lator Bcl-x. Through alternative splicing, the Bcl-x gene 
yields two major protein isoforms with opposing func-
tions, anti-apoptotic Bcl-x L and pro-apoptotic Bcl-x S 
(18) (Figure 1A). Bcl-x L is upregulated in a number of 
cancers and confers resistance to a broad range of 
chemotherapeutic drugs (19). Bcl-x S antagonizes the 
anti-apoptotic activity of Bcl-x L and another anti-
apoptotic protein, Bcl-2 (20,21). Redirection of Bcl-x 
splicing from Bcl-x L to -x S induced apoptosis and 
increased chemosensitivity in cancer cells in culture (22-
24); however, the anti-tumor effect of this strategy remains 
to be demonstrated in vivo. </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 919 966 4343; Fax: +1 919 966 5640; Email: john_bauman@med.unc.edu </p>

<p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. </p>

<p>8348-8356 Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 22 
Published online 18 August 2010 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkq731 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Because the SSO effectively converts Bcl-x L to Bcl-x S , 
cancers expressing high levels of Bcl-x L represent good 
candidates for treatment with Bcl-x SSO (23). Metastatic 
melanoma is an aggressive malignancy with poor progno-
sis and disease progression is associated with increased 
Bcl-x L expression (25,26) . Xenografts of murine B16F10 
melanoma cells provide a good model of this aggressive 
cancer because they express Bcl-x L and are syngeneic to 
C57BL/6 mice, obviating the need for immunocomprom-
ised animals and providing a more realistic environment 
for drug testing. In this model, B16F10 murine melanoma 
cells localize to the lungs shortly after injection into the 
tail vein, providing a concise and predictable experimental 
time-course. In addition, the cell line used here expressed 
luciferase, providing an easily quantified measure of the 
tumor load. We previously failed to detect activity 
of systemically-delivered free SSOs in tumor xenografts. 
Thus, for this work we employed a liposome-DNA-
polycation (LPD) nanoparticle (NP) formulation 
designed by the Huang laboratory (27-29), which 
delivered siRNA to tumor cells in the B16F10 xenograft 
model (30,31). In previous work, Huang and colleagues 
demonstrated enhanced tumor cell-specific uptake of this 
NP formulation by surface-modification with anisamide, 
a ligand of the sigma receptor, which is upregulated in </p>

<p>many cancers (32,33) and is expressed in B16F10 cells 
(27,30,31,34). 
Our findings show that delivery of Bcl-x SSO by the 
LPD NP resulted in modification of Bcl-x mRNA 
splicing in lung metastases and reduction of tumor load. 
This marks the first demonstration of SSO-induced 
splicing modification in tumor cells in vivo and provides 
support for Bcl-x splice-switching as a potential anti-
tumor strategy. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>2 
0 -O-methoxyethyl 
(MOE)-phosphorothioate 
SSOs 
(Figure 1B) were synthesized by ISIS Pharmaceuticals 
(Carlsbad, CA, USA). The Bcl-x SSO was targeted to 
the 5 
0 -splice site of exon II in Bcl-x pre-mRNA (5 
0 -TGG 
TTCTTACCCAGCCGCCG-3 
0 , ISIS 105751) (35). An 
oligonucleotide targeted to aberrantly spliced human 
b-globin intron (5 
0 -GCTATTACCTTAACCCAG-3 
0 , 
ISIS 18204) (10) was used as negative control. For 
nanoparticle preparation cholesterol, protamine sulfate, 
calf thymus DNA and cloning water were purchased 
from Sigma-Aldrich (St Louis, MO, USA). DOTAP 
stock solution (20 mg/ml) was purchased from Avanti 
Polar Lipids (Alabaster, AL, USA). </p>

<p>Cell culture and transfection </p>

<p>B16F10 mouse melanoma cells expressing sigma receptors 
were used as model cells in this study (36). B16F10 cells 
stably expressing the firefly luciferase gene were provided 
by Dr Pilar Blancafort (University of North Carolina, 
Department of Pharmacology, NC, USA) (31). The cells 
were maintained in high-glucose Dulbecco's modified 
Eagle's medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine 
serum and a 5% penicillin/streptomycin solution 
(GIBCO, Grand Island, NY, USA) at 37 
C and 5% 
CO 2 . Cells were seeded in 24-or 6-well plates at 
7.0 Â 10 
5 and 5.0 Â 10 
5 cells/well, respectively, $24 h 
prior 
to 
transfection. 
Cells 
were 
transfected 
with LipofectAmine 2000 (Invitrogen) in Opti-MEM 
(Invitrogen) per the manufacturer's recommendation. </p>

<p>RNA Isolation and analysis </p>

<p>Total RNA from cells or tissue was isolated using TRI 
Reagent (Molecular Research Center, Cincinnati, OH, 
USA) according to the manufacturer's protocol using 
800 ml for $5 mg tissue samples. Next, 200 ng of total 
RNA was subjected to RT-PCR (5 
0 -CATGGCAGCAG 
TGAAGCAAG-3 
0 , Bcl-x forward primer; 5 
0 -GCATTGT 
TCCCGTAGAGATCC-3 
0 , Bcl-x reverse primer; 5 
0 -GTG 
CAGCGCAACCACGAGAC-3 
0 , Mcl-1 forward primer; 
5 
0 -GCAGCACATTTCTGATGCCG-3 
0 , Mcl-1 reverse 
primer) with rTth polymerase (Applied Biosystems, 
Foster City, CA, USA). Cycles of PCR proceeded 
at 95 
C for 3 min, followed by 22 cycles of 95 
C for 30 s, 
56 
C for 30 s, and 72 
C for 1 min. The PCR contained 
Cy5-conjugated dCTP (GE Healthcare) for visualiza-
tion. The PCR products were separated on a </p>

<p>Bcl-x L 
Bcl-x S </p>

<p>Anti-apoptotic 
Pro-apoptotic </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Bcl-x 
pre-mRNA </p>

<p>Bcl-x 
spliced mRNA </p>

<p>II 
III </p>

<p>+ SSO </p>

<p>II 
III 
II 
III </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O 
O </p>

<p>P 
S </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>O O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>O 
BASE </p>

<p>Me </p>

<p>BASE </p>

<p>Me </p>

<p>Figure 1. Direction of Bcl-x alternative splicing by SSO. (A) Use of the 
downstream or upstream alternative 5 
0 -splice site within exon II of 
Bcl-x pre-mRNA yields anti-apoptotic Bcl-x L or pro-apoptotic Bcl-x S , 
respectively. SSO targeted to the downstream splice site redirects the 
splicing machinery to the upstream alternative splice site, resulting in a 
simultaneous decrease in production of Bcl-x L and increase in produc-
tion of Bcl-x S . (B) Chemical structure of MOE phosphorothioate (PS) 
oligonucleotide. The MOE ribose modification confers RNase-H 
non-competence and increased affinity for target mRNA, while the 
PS inter-nucleotide linkage improves serum stability and bioavailability. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 22 8349 </p>

<p>10% non-denaturing polyacrylamide gel (Invitrogen) and 
bands were visualized on a Typhoon 9400 Imager (GE 
Healthcare). Images were quantified using <rs id="software-0" type="software">ImageQuant</rs> 
analysis software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 5.2</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Molecular Dynamics</rs>). 
The percentage of Bcl-x S in each lane was determined by 
dividing the intensity of the 162-bp band (Bcl-x S ) by the 
total intensities of the 351 (Bcl-x L ) and 162-bp (Bcl-x S ) 
bands. The identity of the 162-bp band was confirmed 
by sequencing by the UNC-CH Genome Analysis Facility. </p>

<p>Cell viability assay </p>

<p>Cell viability in response to SSO treatment was assessed, 
with slight modifications, by a previously described 
clonogenic assay (23). Briefly, 24 h after oligonucleotide 
transfection in six-well plates, 250 cells were re-plated 
in 10-cm plates. After 10 days under normal culture con-
ditions surviving colonies were stained with 2% methylene 
blue (Sigma) in 50% ethanol for 10 min. Colonies larger 
than 50 cells were counted. As a positive control for the 
assay, cells were treated with 1 mM staurosporine (STS). </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>Cells (5.0 Â 10 
5 cells/well in a six-well plate) were washed 
twice with ice-cold PBS and lysed in RIPA buffer 
(radioimmune precipitation assay buffer; 50 mM Tris-
HCl, 150 mM NaCl, 5 mM EDTA, 1% Triton X-100, 
0.1% SDS and 1% sodium deoxycholate) and a cocktail 
of protease inhibitors (Sigma). Total protein was quantified 
with the Quick Start Bradford Protein Assay Kit (Bio-Rad 
Laboratories, Inc., Hercules, CA, USA). Total protein 
(20 mg) was separated by electrophoresis on a 4-12% 
pre-cast Bis-Tris gel (Invitrogen) and electrotransferred 
to a polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) membrane. 
Membranes were stained with Ponceau's stain to confirm 
equal loading and transfer. Membranes were blocked for 
1 h in BLOTTO (5% w/v non-fat dry milk in TBS, 0.1% 
Tween) or StartingBlock Buffer (Pierce) and incubated 
overnight at 4 
C with primary antibodies: polyclonal 
Bcl-x antibody (1:2000; BD Transduction Labs), poly-
clonal PARP antibody (1:2000; Cell Signaling 9452) and 
mouse anti-b-actin monoclonal antibody (1:10 000; 
Sigma). Membranes were then incubated for 1 h with 
horseradish peroxidase-conjugated anti-mouse (1:100 000; 
Sigma) or goat anti-rabbit (1:10 000; Abcam) secondary 
antibodies. Blots were developed with ECL Plus reagents 
(GE Healthcare) and exposed to film (GE Healthcare). 
Bcl-x L , Bcl-x S , b-actin, cleaved PARP and full-length 
PARP migrated at 30, 22, 42, 89 and 116 kDa, respectively. 
b-Actin was used to confirm equal protein loading. </p>

<p>Preparation of SSO-containing nanoparticles </p>

<p>LPD NPs were prepared as described earlier (30,31). 
Briefly, naked NP were obtained by quickly mixing 
150 ml suspension A (16.6 mM liposomes (DOTAP/choles-
terol molar ratio = 1:1, and 400 mg/ml protamine in 5% 
dextrose) with 150 ml solution B (320 mg/ml oligonucleo-
tide and 320 mg/ml calf thymus DNA in 5% dextrose) 
followed by incubation at room temperature for 10 min. 
The naked NP suspension (300 ml) was further incubated 
with 75.6 ml micellar solution of DSPE-PEG 2000 -anisamide </p>

<p>(10 mg/ml) [synthesized in the Huang lab as reported 
earlier (34)] at 50 
C for 10 min and then allowed 
to stand at room temperature for 10 min. The resulting 
formulation was used within 20 min for the following 
experiments. These methods resulted in encapsulation of 
&gt;90% oligoncuelotide or siRNA in previous studies 
(28,37,38). </p>

<p>Animal studies </p>

<p>Female C57BL/six mice of ages 6-8 weeks (16-18 g) were 
purchased from Charles River Laboratories (Wilmington, 
MA, USA). All experiments performed on the animals 
were in accordance with and approved by the 
Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at the 
University of North Carolina. The mouse model was 
established by i.v. injection of 2 Â 10 
5 luciferase-expressing 
B16F10 cells on Day 0. Animals were i.v. injected with 
vehicle only (PBS), NP only (2.4 mg/kg), control 
or Bcl-x SSO NP (2.4 mg/kg), or free control or Bcl-x 
SSO (2.4 or 10 mg/kg) on Days 3-6 after tumor inocula-
tion. On Day 7, some animals were euthanized for analysis 
of RNA splicing. For animals treated with free SSO, only 
RNA was analyzed. For animals treated with NP, blood 
was collected for analysis of toxicity marker. On Day 17 
the remaining animals were euthanized for the analysis 
of tumor load. Tumor load was determined by measuring 
luciferase 
activity 
within 
tumor-bearing 
lungs, 
as described earlier (30,31). </p>

<p>Toxicity assays </p>

<p>Twenty-four hours after the final injection, blood samples 
were collected and serum was isolated. Analyses of serum 
aspartate 
aminotransferase 
(AST) 
and 
alanine 
aminotransferase (ALT) were performed at the Animal 
Clinical Laboratory Core Facility (University of North 
Carolina) using a Vitro 250 Chemical Analyzer 
(Ortho-Clinical Diagnostics, Rochester, NY, USA). 
Serum interleuikin-12 was measured with the 
enzyme-linked immunosorbant assay (ELISA) according 
to the manufacturer's protocol (BD Biosciences, San 
Diego, CA, USA). As a negative control, ALT/AST 
serum levels from untreated tumor-free mice were also 
measured. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Luciferase data were analyzed by one-way analysis of 
variance (ANOVA) and Tukey's post-test using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Prism</rs> 
statistical software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">GraphPad</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 4.03</rs>). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Modification of Bcl-x pre-mRNA in melanoma cells </p>

<p>Transfection of B16F10 cells with MOE-PS Bcl-x SSO 
targeted to the downstream 5 
0 -splice site of Bcl-x exon 
2 (Figure 1) induced a dose-dependant shift in splicing 
of Bcl-x pre-mRNA from anti-apoptotic Bcl-x L 
to pro-apoptotic Bcl-x S , while a control SSO had no 
effect on splicing (Figure 2A and B). Consistent with 
these results, probing of total protein from treated cells </p>



<p>with anti-Bcl-x antibody showed SSO-dependent reduc-
tion in the level Bcl-x L protein (Figure 2C). We were 
unable to detect the expected Bcl-x S protein because the 
endogenous level of murine Bcl-x S expression was below 
the threshold required by available antibodies 
(Supplementary Figure S1). Importantly, SSO treatment 
resulted also in a dose-dependant decrease in cell viability, 
as evidenced by a clonogenic cell death assay (Figure 3A). 
This was accompanied by cleavage of poly (ADP-ribose) 
polymerase (PARP), indicating that the observed cell 
death was due to apoptosis (Figure 3B). These effects 
were absent in untreated and mock-transfected cells, and 
cells transfected with a control SSO. In addition, the Bcl-x 
SSO had no effect on the pre-mRNA splicing of Mcl-1, a 
closely related gene that shares sequence homology at the </p>

<p>5 
0 -splice site, supporting sequence specificity of the Bcl-x 
SSO (Supplementary Figure S2). </p>

<p>Activity of Bcl-x SSO in vivo </p>

<p>To facilitate SSO delivery to cancer cells in tumor-bearing 
mice, an LPD NP developed by the Huang laboratory was 
used (30,31). The SSO and a carrier DNA (calf thymus 
DNA) were complexed by protamine into a compact core 
which was then coated with cationic lipids to form the NP 
(Figure 4). The surface of the NP was further modified 
with an anisamide ligand-conjugated polyethylene glycol 
(PEG)-lipid for targeting the sigma receptor-expressing 
B16F10 cells. This NP formulation could efficiently, 
specifically and with low toxicity deliver siRNA 
to tumor cells in the B16F10 tumor model, as shown 
earlier (30,31). </p>

<p>Un Mo 
Bcl-x L </p>

<p>Bcl-x S </p>

<p>Control SSO 
Bcl-x SSO </p>

<p>0 
4 
11 
33 
100 300 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Bcl-x SSO </p>

<p>Control SSO </p>

<p>SSO Concentration (nM) </p>

<p>% Bcl-x </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>β-actin </p>

<p>Bcl-x L </p>

<p>Un 
Mo </p>

<p>Ctrl 
SSO </p>

<p>Bcl-x 
SSO </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Exon 2 
Exon 3 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>3 0 0 
1 0 0 
3 3 
1 1 
4 n M 
3 0 0 
1 0 0 
3 3 
1 1 
4 n M </p>

<p>Figure 2. SSO induced Bcl-x splice-switching in B16F10 murine 
melanoma cells. (A) RT-PCR analysis of Bcl-x mRNA from cells trans-
fected with control and Bcl-x SSO 24 h posttransfection. The Bcl-x SSO 
induces dose-dependant switching of Bcl-x mRNA splicing from 
anti-apoptotic Bcl-x L to pro-apoptotic Bcl-x S . Error bars indicate 
mean ± SD (n = 3). (B) Sequence analysis of the RT-PCR product 
corresponding to Bcl-x S showing exons 2 and 3 joined at the 
upstream alternative splice site. (C) Immunoblot analysis of cells 
treated with 100 nM Bcl-x SSO 48 h posttransfection. The SSO 
induces a reduction in the Bcl-x L protein isoform. Detection of 
b-actin confirms equal loading. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Bcl-x SSO 
Un 
Control SSO </p>

<p>Un 
Mo 
Ctrl 
Bcl-x </p>

<p>Cleaved PARP </p>

<p>β-actin </p>

<p>Full-length PARP </p>

<p>20 
40 
80 
0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>125 
Ctrl SSO 
Bcl-x SSO </p>

<p>SSO Concentration (nM) 
Viable cells (%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>125 
DMSO 
STS </p>

<p>Figure 3. Bcl-x SSO induces cell death in B16F10 murine melanoma 
cells. (A) Effect of Bcl-x and control SSO on cell viability as determined 
by a clonogenic assay. Top panel shows images of representative plates 
at 80 nM concentration. Bottom left panel expresses viability of 
SSO-treated cells relative to untreated cells. Error bars indicate 
mean ± SD (n = 3-4). Bottom right panel shows viability of cells 
treated with 1 mM staurosporine (STS) relative to DMSO-treated 
cells. (B) Western blot of protein from cells treated with control and 
Bcl-x SSOs for 24 h. The presence of PARP cleavage in Bcl-x 
SSO-treated cells confirms that the observed decrease in cell viability 
is due to apoptosis. Detection of b-actin confirms equal loading. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 22 8351 </p>

<p>B16F10 murine melanoma cells localize in the lungs 
shortly after injection into the tail vein of C57BL/6 
mice. In the absence of treatment, the mice die $22 days 
following inoculation (30). This rapid course of disease 
dictated the treatment protocol ('Materials and 
Methods' section). RT-PCR analysis of total RNA from 
the tumor-bearing lungs of animals euthanized on Day 7 
showed induction of Bcl-x S mRNA expression in animals 
treated with the Bcl-x SSO NP formulation. This effect 
was dose-dependant, as increasing the number of injec-
tions resulted in a greater degree of Bcl-x splice-switching 
from Bcl-x L to Bcl-x S mRNA in the tumor nodules 
(Supplementary Figure S3). In contrast, Bcl-x S mRNA 
levels in animals treated with control SSO NP formulation 
or free SSO were no different than in animals treated with 
PBS only (Figure 5A and Supplementary Figure S4). 
Modification of Bcl-x splicing in the liver was barely 
detectable in Bcl-x SSO NP-treated animals and undetect-
able in animals treated with control SSO NP or PBS only 
(Figure 5A). As a measure of tumor load, luciferase </p>

<p>activity was assayed in lysates from tumor-bearing lungs 
of animals euthanized on Day 17. A dramatic reduction in 
luciferase activity was seen in animals treated with Bcl-x 
SSO NP compared to animals treated with NP only, 
control SSO NP, or PBS only (Figure 5B and C). 
Statistical analysis (ANOVA, Tukey's post-test) revealed 
that the reduction in luciferase activity in animals treated 
with Bcl-x SSO NP was significant compared to animals 
treated with PBS only (P &lt; 0.001), NP only (P &lt; 0.05) and 
control SSO NP (P &lt; 0.05) (Figure 5B). </p>

<p>Toxicity studies </p>

<p>To determine the potential toxicities of NP and SSO treat-
ment, serum levels of toxicity markers were analyzed in 
mice euthanized on Day 7 following tumor inoculation. 
Tissues with a leaky endothelial wall, such as the liver, 
allow significant uptake of NP (39). Accordingly, we 
analyzed serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and 
alanine aminotransferase (ALT) levels as markers 
of liver toxicity. Mean ALT and AST levels among treat-
ment groups were within the normal range (Figure 6A and 
B). To test the possibility that components of the NP 
formulation might trigger an inflammatory response, 
serum levels of the pro-inflammatory cytokine IL-12 
were also analyzed. Elevated IL-12 levels relative to 
the PBS control were observed in NP treatment groups 
(Empty NP, P &lt; 0.01; Control SSO P &lt; 0.001) 
(Figure 6C). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Alternative splicing has emerged as an important target 
for molecular therapies (15). Clinical trials using SSOs to 
treat DMD have yielded promising preliminary results 
(16,17), while numerous recent reports have confirmed 
the in vivo efficacy of SSOs in treating animal models 
of disease (15). SSOs have been applied against cancer 
targets in vitro (22,23,40), however in vivo validation of 
their efficacy has been hindered by the poor delivery 
of antisense therapeutics to tumor cells in vivo (8,41). 
Here we show that an SSO in LPD NP formulation was 
effective in delivery to tumor cells in the B16F10 model 
system (27,30,31). 
Our data indicate that SSO-induced redirection of Bcl-x 
pre-mRNA splicing from Bcl-x L to -x S induced apoptosis 
and subsequent cell death in a dose-dependant manner 
in B16F10 melanoma cells in culture (Figures 2 and 3). 
In vivo, redirection of Bcl-x pre-mRNA splicing was 
associated with a significant reduction of tumor burden 
in rapidly growing and highly tumorigenic B16F10 lung 
metastases (Figure 5A-C). This finding is consistent with 
our in vitro data, as well as previous work in prostate and 
breast cancer cells (22,23). Interestingly, in this model 
both in cell culture and in vivo xenografts, modification 
of Bcl-x pre-mRNA splicing alone induced cell death, 
whereas in non-small cell lung carcinoma (A549) cells 
adjuvant chemotherapy was needed (24). Bcl-x L expres-
sion may therefore be critical for survival of B16F10 
cells, consistent with reports that increased Bcl-x L expres-
sion is associated with melanoma progression and </p>

<p>SSO </p>

<p>Calf Thymus DNA 
Protamine </p>

<p>Liposomes </p>

<p>PEG lipids, 
anisamide </p>

<p>Figure 4. Schematic depiction of the preparation of SSO encapsulated 
LPD NP. The SSO was encapsulated into a condensed core with a high 
molecular weight polyanion (calf thymus DNA) and protamine, which 
was then coated with cationic liposomes. PEG lipids were inserted into 
the resultant bilayer to shield the positive charge and prevent aggrega-
tion in circulation. Anisamide, a commonly used targeting ligand that 
binds the sigma receptor, was conjugated to the distal end of the PEG 
lipids. </p>



<p>metastasis (25,26). Thus, other pharmacological agents 
that target Bcl-x L may warrant further investigation in 
metastatic melanoma. 
Our cell culture data are consistent with the predicted 
SSO mechanism of action. Namely, that Bcl-x 
SSO-induced modulation of Bcl-x pre-mRNA splicing 
reduced the level of Bcl-x L, and increased the level 
of Bcl-x S splice variants, causing apoptosis of cancer 
cells. This is evident at the RNA level, and is further 
supported by the dramatic reduction of Bcl-x L protein 
and by induction of PARP cleavage (Figure 2C, 3C). 
Although SSO induced Bcl-x S mRNA, we were unable 
to confirm concomitant production of Bcl-x S protein by 
immunoblotting procedures. This was in spite of screening 
several commercially available antibodies and including 
attempts to concentrate the protein by immunopre-
cipitation prior to western analysis. This is likely because 
the maximum level of endogenous Bcl-x S protein 
that could be induced by the SSO was below that which 
could be detected by available antibodies (Supplementary 
Figure S1). </p>

<p>In vivo, RT-PCR analysis of total RNA from 
tumor-bearing lungs demonstrated that Bcl-x splicing 
was shifted $10% from Bcl-x L to the -x S splice variant. 
Yet this treatment led to marked reduction of tumor load 
in treated animals. Two interpretations of these results are 
possible. One, that in vivo even a minor reduction of 
Bcl-x L levels and concomitant increase in Bcl-x S , leads to 
death of cancer cells or at least inhibits their proliferation. 
However, it is also possible that the cells which took up 
the SSO more efficiently were more effectively killed 
by apoptosis and thus eliminated from the tissue subjected 
to subsequent analysis. If this is the case, RT-PCR under-
estimates the actual level of SSO-induced splice-switching. 
BH3 mimetics comprise a novel class of cancer drugs 
that competitively antagonize the Bcl-2 anti-apoptotic 
proteins (42). For example, the small molecule ABT-737 
binds Bcl-2, Bcl-x L and Bcl-w proteins with nanomolar 
affinity. It induced apoptosis in lymphoma and small-cell 
lung carcinoma cells in culture, and caused tumor regres-
sion and improved survival in preclinical studies (43). 
By modifying the splicing pattern of Bcl-x, the SSO can </p>

<p>P B S 
N P o n ly 
C o n tr o l S S O N P 
B c l-x S S O N P </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>% Luicferase activity </p>

<p>* 
** </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>PBS </p>

<p>Control 
SSO NP </p>

<p>Bcl-x 
SSO NP </p>

<p>Bcl-x L </p>

<p>Bcl-x S </p>

<p>Bcl-x L </p>

<p>Bcl-x S </p>

<p>Liver </p>

<p>Tumor-bearing lung </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>PBS </p>

<p>Bcl-x SSO NP </p>

<p>NP only </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Control SSO NP </p>

<p>Figure 5. Effects of LPD-NP-delivered SSO in B16F10 tumor-bearing lungs. (A) RT-PCR analysis of Bcl-x mRNA splicing in the tumor-bearing 
lungs (upper panel) and liver (lower panel) of mice treated with vehicle only (PBS), empty NP, control SSO-formulated NP and Bcl-x 
SSO-formulated NP. (B) Luciferase activity in the tumor-loaded lungs on Day 17 after injections on Days 3-6. Asterisks denote statistical signifi-
cance thresholds (*P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.001, determined by ANOVA and Tukey's posttest). Untreated n = 26, NP only n = 8, Control SSO NP n = 13, 
Bcl-x SSO NP n = 9. (C) Representative images of lungs excised from tumor-bearing mice on Day 17 following four injections of 2.4 mg/kg NP 
formulations on Days 3-6. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 22 8353 </p>

<p>be thought of as prompting the tumor cell to produce an 
endogenous BH3 mimetic, Bcl-x S , capable of antagonizing 
Bcl-2 and Bcl-x L and promoting apoptosis. 
NPs are known to accumulate non-specifically in the 
liver due to the fenestrated vasculature (39). We did not </p>

<p>observe significant Bcl-x splice-switching in the liver 
(Figure 5A), and ALT and AST serum levels of the treat-
ment groups was within the normal range (Figure 6A and 
B). This suggests that liver uptake of the NP was limited 
and did not translate into significant biological activity 
or toxicity. In some tumor-bearing, control mice AST 
and AST values were &gt;100 U/L suggesting that this 
could be a rare response to tumor burden. We did detect 
a modest elevation of serum IL-12 levels in NP treatment 
groups relative to the PBS control (Figure 6C). A previous 
report with the LPD NP showed more pronounced induc-
tion of inflammatory toxicity at doses !1.2 mg/kg (29,30). 
However, that study analyzed local toxicity from lung 
lysate, whereas we analyzed serum from systemic circula-
tion. It is unclear whether this small but statistically 
significant increase is biologically relevant. Elevated 
IL-12 could be due to unmethylated CpG motifs present 
in the calf thymus DNA component of the NP. While we 
cannot exclude the possibility that the observed IL-12 
increase contributed to the antitumor effect of the Bcl-x 
SSO, this seems unlikely because IL-12 induction was 
observed in all NP treatment groups, whereas reduction 
of tumor load was only evident in animals treated with the 
Bcl-x SSO. 
The inclusion of calf thymus DNA in the NP compli-
cates the use of this formulation from a pharmaceutics 
and regulatory perspective. Recently, Chono et al. (38) 
replaced calf thymus DNA with a high molecular weight 
anionic polysaccharide, hyaluronic acid, resulting in a NP 
containing cationic liposome, protamine and hyaluronic 
acid (LPH). The LPH formulation delivered siRNA 
in vivo with potency similar to that of the LPD formula-
tion; however, induction of both IL-6 and IL-12 cytokines 
by LPH was significantly lower than that of the corres-
ponding LPD containing the calf thymus DNA. The LPH 
NP formulation could be employed for delivery of SSOs 
and other antisense therapeutics to tumors in future 
studies. 
Our results extend previous findings on the LPD NP 
formulation, which delivered siRNA to the cytoplasm, 
the site of dicer activity, to oligonucleotides that 
function in the nucleus, the site of splicing modulation. 
Thus, through delivery of SSOs, liposome-based NP 
formulations may be used not only to downregulate, 
but also to upregulate endogenous gene expression, as 
is evidenced by the induction of Bcl-x S mRNA 
we observed. In addition, our findings are consistent 
with Bcl-x pre-mRNA splice switching as a possible 
anti-tumor strategy in melanoma as well as other 
malignancies expressing Bcl-x L . </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank Dr Rudy Juliano from UNC for 
critical reading of the manuscript. The authors thank 
Dr Brett Monia for a kind gift of 2 
0 -O-MOE </p>

<p>IL-12 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>Serum conc. (pg/ml) </p>

<p>ALT </p>

<p>U n t r e a t e d </p>

<p>P B S 
N P o n ly 
C o n t r o l S S O 
B c l-x S S O </p>

<p>U n t r e a t e d </p>

<p>P B S </p>

<p>P B S </p>

<p>N P o n ly </p>

<p>N P o n ly </p>

<p>C o n t r o l S S O </p>

<p>C o n t r o l S S O </p>

<p>N P </p>

<p>B c l-x S S O </p>

<p>B c l-x S S O </p>

<p>N P </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>Serum conc. (U/L) </p>

<p>AST </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>Serum conc. (U/L) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Figure 6. Serum enzyme and cytokine analysis. ALT (A), AST (B) and 
IL-12 (C) serum levels of untreated tumor-free and tumor-bearing 
C57BL/6 mice 24 h after the last of four consecutive daily treatments. 
Treatments consisted of i.v. injections of vehicle only (PBS), NP 
formulated with control SSO, or NP formulated with SSO targeted 
to Bcl-x. </p>



<p>oligonucleotides used in this work and Jennifer Roberts 
for technical assistance. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>American Heart Association (predoctoral fellowship to 
J.A.B.); National Institutes of Health (PO1-GM-59299 
to R.K.; R01-CA129835 to L.H.). Funding for open 
access charge: National Institutes of Health (PO1-GM-
59299). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. R.K. is a full-time employee 
of AVI Biopharma Inc., Bothell, WA, USA, a company 
that develops RNA-based drugs. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 22 8355 </p>





</text></tei>