<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3361050" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A b s t r a c t </p>

<p>Introduction: Lesch's typology differentiates alcoholics into different treatment 
response subgroups. The effects of ethanol are mediated, to an important extent, 
via the GABA-ergic system. 
Material and methods: We have evaluated the linkage disequilibrium patterns 
and haplotype frequencies of GABRG1 and GABRA2 genes in 133 alcoholics divid-
ed according to Lesch's typology and in 145 matched controls. 
Results: Besides several relationships at a threshold of statistical significance, 
we found no significant differences in the haplotype distribution of these genes 
between alcoholics and controls. 
Conclusions: Lesch's typology may not be related with the genotype of alco-
holics -at least in terms of genes with an established role in the development 
of dependency. </p>

<p>Alcohol dependence (AD) is a highly prevalent disorder that is associ-
ated with serious morbidity and mortality. The development of alcohol 
dependence is the result of an interaction between environmental and 
hereditary factors. According to twin, adoption and family studies, the her-
itability of alcoholism ranges between 50% and 60% [1]. 
While studies have found that genetic factors account for a substan-
tial amount of variance in alcohol consumption, there is inconsistent evi-
dence on which polymorphisms are related to alcohol use and serious alco-
hol problems. 
Lesch et al. [2] distinguished four evolutionary types of alcoholics, 
depending on the family history of alcoholism, previous personal psy-
chopathology, and hypothetical neurobiological background. According to 
Lesch's typology (LT), type I alcoholics (the so-called model of 'allergy') suf-
fer from heavy alcohol withdrawal syndrome, probably associated with 
dopamine deficits, and tend to use alcohol to weaken withdrawal symp-
toms. Patients of type II (model of anxiety of conflict) use alcohol as self-
medication because of its anxiolytic effect. In alcoholics of type III, the 
main characteristic is of an affective disorder and thus alcohol is used as </p>

<p>Corresponding author: 
Dr. Anna Grzywacz 
Department of Psychiatry 
Pomeranian Medical 
University 
26 Broniewskiego 
71-460 Szczecin, Poland 
Phone: +48 91 454 06 53 
Fax: +48 91 454 07 33 
E-mail: 
annagrzywacz@gazeta.pl </p>

<p>Clinical research </p>

<p>1 Department of Psychiatry, Pomeranian Medical University, Szczecin, Poland 
2 Department of Molecular Neuropharmacology, Institute of Pharmacology, 
Polish Academy of Sciences, Cracow, Poland 
3 Department of Pharmacology, Institute of Psychiatry and Neurology, Warsaw, Poland </p>

<p>Submitted: 4 February 2011 
Accepted: 24 July 2011 </p>

<p>Arch Med Sci 2012; 8, 2: 357-361 
DOI: 10.5114/aoms.2012.28565 
Copyright © 2012 Termedia &amp; Banach </p>



<p>Arch Med Sci 2, April / 2012 </p>

<p>Anna Grzywacz, Iwona Małecka, Michał Korostyński, Ryszard Przewłocki, Przemysław Bieńkowski, Jerzy Samochowiec </p>

<p>an antidepressant by these subjects. Type IV pa -
tients (alcohol drinking as adaptation) show pre-
morbid cerebral defects, behavioural disorders, and 
a high social burden [2]. 
Currently performed studies deal with the pos-
sible genetic background of alcoholism amongst LT 
subjects. The glutamine gene is one of the candi-
date genes tested in this context. GABA-ergic neu-
rotransmission is supposed to play a central role in 
the behavioural effects of alcohol, particularly seda-
tion, tolerance, loss of motor coordination, and 
withdrawal [3]. Previous studies have implicated 
GABA-A receptor genes with AD, alcohol use pat-
terns, and levels of response to alcohol [4]. 
Animal studies may provide clues to the poten-
tial mechanism by which GABRA2 influences the 
risk for alcohol dependence. Research in animals 
selectively manipulated for the GABA α1, α2, α3, 
α5 receptor subtypes suggests that the α2 subtype 
selectively mediates the anxiolytic properties of 
diazepam [5]. Baseline anxiety, rates of anxiety dis-
orders, and responses to anxiolytic agents, such as 
benzodiazepines or alcohol, or other substance 
dependence-related phenotypes, were revealed to 
differ among individuals as a function of the 
GABRA2 haplotypes [6]. 
Genome wide linkage scans implicate a region 
of chromosome 4p12 harbouring a cluster of four 
genes encoding GABA-A receptor subunits as 
a potential genetic background of LT [7, 8]. Also 
another cluster of GABA-A receptor genes (GABRA1, 
GABRA6, GABRB2 and GABRG2) on chromosome 
5q was revealed to be significantly associated with 
drinking behaviours, such as the level of response 
to alcohol, history of blackouts, age of first drunk-
enness, and alcohol dependence [4, 9]. 
Importantly, a study by Covault et al. [10] sug-
gests that markers in the 5' region of the GABRAG1 
gene, which encodes the GABA-A receptor γ-1 sub-
mit, are in linkage disequilibrium (LD) with mark-
ers found in the GABRAA2 gene adjacent to the 
GABRAG1 gene and also located in chromosome 4p. 
Moreover, markers in the 5' region of the GABRAG1 
gene show associations with AD in 2 samples of 
individuals of European ancestry [10]. 
Therefore, it is hypothesized that certain poly-
morphisms of the GABRAG1 gene will be associat-
ed with lower levels of response to alcohol, heav-
ier drinking patterns, and more alcohol-related 
problems in a group of hazardous drinkers [10]. </p>

<p>To understand the reported associations, we 
sought to understand the linkage disequilibrium (LD) 
patterns and haplotype structures of GABRG1 and 
GABRA2 in Polish alcoholics depending on their clas-
sification to certain phenotypes of Lesch's typology. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>This study included a group of 133 Caucasian 
subjects, with no history of psychiatric disorders 
other than alcohol or nicotine dependence as clas-
sified by ICD-10. According to Lesch's typology, 39 AD 
subjects were of type I, 33 patients of type II, 
41 patients of type III, and 20 patients of type IV. 
The control group comprised 145 unrelated indi-
viduals matched for ethnicity and gender, and 
excluded for mental disorders using the Primary 
Care Evaluation of Mental Disorders (Prime MD) 
questionnaire. All subjects were recruited in the 
North West region of Poland. Alcohol use and fam-
ily history of alcoholism were assessed by means 
of a structured interview, based on the Polish ver-
sion of Semi-Structured Assessment on Genetics 
in Alcoholism (SSAGA). 
The study protocol was approved by the local 
Ethic Committee of Pomeranian Medical Universi-
ty and all the participants provided their written 
informed consent. 
Genomic DNA was extracted from venous blood 
samples using a salting out method. SNP rs1391166 
A/T, rs1497577 A/T, and rs10034075 A/G polymor-
phisms of GABRG1 and GABRA2 polymorphisms 
rs2119767 A/T, rs16859354 G/T, rs13152740 A/G, 
rs279836 A/T, rs279826 A/G, rs279844 A/T, 
rs3775282 C/T, rs279871 A/G, rs17537141 C/T, 
rs529826 C/T, and rs572227 A/G were analysed. 
Single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) genotyping 
was carried out using the Centaurus (Nanogen) 
platform [11]. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical 
Package for Social Sciences</rs> (SPSS) <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 9</rs>. Dif-
ferences between controls and alcoholics were test-
ed using the χ 2 test and considered significant if 
the type 1 error was less than 5% using <rs type="software">SPSS</rs>. The 
Hardy Weinberg equilibrium was calculated using 
the <rs type="software">SAS</rs> computer program for Windows. Odds 
ratios and confidence intervals at 95% were also 
calculated. Haplotype frequencies and linkage dis-
equilibrium were calculated using R with <rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Biocon-ductor</rs> packages <rs id="software-4" type="software">haplo.stats</rs> and <rs type="software">genetics</rs>. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>GABRG1 </p>

<p>In the group of alcoholics and controls, high val-
ues of D' were observed between gab1 (rs 1391166) 
and gab2 (rs 1497577) polymorphisms as well as 
between gab1 and gab3 (rs 10034075) or gab2 and 
gab3 polymorphisms (Table I). Alcoholics and non-</p>

<p>gab1 
gab2 
gab3 </p>

<p>gab1 D' 
0.99 
0.84 </p>

<p>gab2 D' 
0.91 </p>

<p>Table I. Linkage disequilibrium of the GABRG1 loci in 
AD subjects (n = 133) and the controls (n = 145) </p>

<p>gab1 -polymorphism rs 1391166 A/T, gab2 -polymorphism rs 1497577 
A/T, gab 3 -polymorphism rs 10034075 A/G </p>

<p>Arch Med Sci 2, April / 2012 </p>



<p>GABA-A receptor genes do not play a role in genetics of Lesch's typology in Caucasian subjects </p>

<p>alcoholics did not differ significantly in terms of 
3-SNP GABRG1 haplotype frequencies. No signifi-
cant differences in GABRG1 haplotype distributions 
were also observed between subgroups of alco-
holics selected based on Lesch's typology and non-
drinking controls. </p>

<p>GABRA2 </p>

<p>The values of D' ranged from 0.02 to 0.99 in this 
study population (Table II). Similar to GABRG1, no 
significant differences in 11-SNP GABRA2 haplotype 
frequencies were observed in the population of 
alcoholics compared to non-alcoholics. No signifi-
cant differences in terms of GABRA2 haplotype dis-
tributions were also observed between Lesch I, II or 
IV alcoholics and the controls. In a subgroup of 
Lesch III alcoholics, the frequency of T-G-A-A-G-T-
C-G-C-C-A haplotype was higher compared to non-
alcoholics, but this difference was at a threshold of 
statistical significance (p = 0.04508). </p>

<p>GABRG1 and GABRA2 </p>

<p>LD analysis for GABRG1 and GABRA2 showed 
high variability of D' values, which ranged from 0.01 
to 0.99 (Table III). The groups of alcoholics and non-
alcoholics did not differ in terms of 14-SNP GABRA2 
and GABRG1 haplotype frequencies. Although T-T-
G-A-G-T-T-A-T-T-G-T-T-G haplotype was absent in 
the controls and observed in some alcoholics, even 
this difference was only at the significance thresh-
old (p = 0.02104). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Sub-typing of alcohol dependence has become 
an important issue as studies have proposed dif-
ferent neurobiological mechanisms in regards to 
alcoholism in recent years. It was shown that alco-
hol dependence reflects a wide range of different </p>

<p>phenotypes, including psychological, social, and 
neurobiological factors. Different methods of sub-
typing have been proposed over the last few 
decades, one of them being Lesch's typology of 
alcohol dependence [12]. 
Results from a genome-wide linkage scan by the 
Collaborative Study on the Genetics of Alcoholism 
showed a suggestive linkage to alcohol dependence 
in the region of the GABA receptor gene cluster on 
chromosome 4p13-p12. This region contains the 
GABRG1, GABRA2, GABRA4, and GABRB1 genes, 
encoding γ-1, α-2, α-4, and β-1 subunits of the 
GABA A receptor, respectively. Association studies 
on some of these loci have indicated that a genet-
ic predisposition to alcohol dependence is related 
to polymorphic variation at GABRA2 or near this 
gene [6, 13-15]. 
Ittiwut et al. [16] focused on two adjacent GABA A 
receptor subunit genes, including one which has 
been associated with risk for alcohol dependence 
in several previous studies. To define the linkage 
disequilibrium in the chromosomal region exten-
sively, more SNPs covering the GABRG1 gene locat-
ed telomerically to GABRA2 on chromosome 4p 
were studied. These studies concluded that this is 
in fact the case, and associations observed with 
GABRA2 might be attributable to functional genet-
ic variations at the GABRG1 locus, or that there may 
be disease-related variants at both loci. This may 
facilitate our understanding of the reported asso-
ciations between GABRA2 polymorphisms and AD 
and permit a more informed search for the func-
tional variant or variants underlying this associa-
tion -a search that must now extend into the inter-
genic region and the GABRG1 locus [16]. 
Covault et al. [10] extended their findings on 
associations between alcohol dependence and the 
chromosome 4 GABA A gene cluster by examining 
the intergenic extent of the GABRA2 3' region hap-</p>

<p>g2 
g3 
g4 
g5 
g6 
g7 
g8 
g9 
g10 
g11 </p>

<p>g1 D' 
0.93 
0.90 
0.05 
0.32 
0.34 
0.99 
0.02 
0.99 
0.05 
0.06 </p>

<p>g2 D' 
0.93 
0.05 
0.07 
0.12 
0.89 
0.05 
0.91 
0.03 
0.02 </p>

<p>g3 D' 
0.34 
0.26 
0.22 
0.93 
0.39 
0.96 
0.36 
0.32 </p>

<p>g4 D' 
0.99 
0.97 
0.93 
0.96 
0.99 
0.97 
0.87 </p>

<p>g5 D' 
0.99 
0.92 
0.95 
0.99 
0.97 
0.85 </p>

<p>g6 D' 
0.92 
0.95 
0.99 
0.97 
0.85 </p>

<p>g7 D' 
0.93 
0.99 
0.94 
0.86 </p>

<p>g8 D' 
0.99 
0.99 
0.96 </p>

<p>g9 D' 
0.99 
0.99 </p>

<p>g10 D' 
0.96 </p>

<p>Table II. Linkage disequilibrium of GABRGA2 loci in AD subjects (n = 133) and the controls (n = 145) </p>

<p>GABRGA2 polymorphisms: g1 -rs2119767 A/T, g2 -rs16859354 G/T, g3 -rs13152740 A/G, g4 -rs279836 A/T, g5 -rs279826 A/G, g6 -rs279844 
A/T, g7 -rs3775282 C/T, g8 -rs279871 A/G, g9 -rs17537141 C/T, g10 -rs529826 C/T, g11 -rs572227 A/G </p>



<p>Arch Med Sci 2, April / 2012 </p>

<p>Anna Grzywacz, Iwona Małecka, Michał Korostyński, Ryszard Przewłocki, Przemysław Bieńkowski, Jerzy Samochowiec </p>

<p>lotype block associated with alcohol dependence 
and by examining markers in adjacent haplotype 
block in the 5' region of GABRG1. They observed 
a stronger association between GABRG1 upstream 
markers in the GABRA2 haplotype block [10]. 
The key to fully understanding the aetiology of 
alcohol dependence, however, is to associate these 
aforementioned genetic findings with behavioural 
patterns of AD, including Lesch's typology of phe-
notypes. This typology is important since it is wide-
ly used in Europe and especially in German-speak-
ing countries and integrates biological, social, and 
psychological factors into the classification system 
[2, 17]. Our previous study focused on genetic vari-
ants of the dopamine transporter DAT, D2 receptor 
(DRD2), serotonin transporter (5HTT), and catechol-
O-methyltransferase (COMT) in different subgroups 
of Lesch's typology. We have found no evidence for 
the role of these gene polymorphisms in Lesch type 
1 and 2 subjects [18]. 
In this study, we focussed on GABA-ergic neu-
rotransmission and the impact of GABA receptors 
on different subgroups of Lesch's typology. We 
investigated the genetics of Lesch's typology and 
the GABRG1 and GABRA2 genes. From a neurobio-
logical standpoint, genetic variations in the GABRG1 
locus may modulate susceptibility to AD through 
mechanisms of reward and/or drug response. In 
the rat brain, the λ-1 subunit of the GABA A recep-
tor, encoded by the GABRG1 gene, is expressed 
selectively in only a few regions such as the amyg-
dale, striatum, and substantia nigra [19]. These 
regions in turn are often implicated in the addic-
tion and reward mechanisms [1]. </p>

<p>Interestingly, this study showed no significant 
differences in GABRG1 and GABRA2 haplotype dis-
tributions between the subgroups of alcoholics with 
various Lesch's phenotypes and the controls with 
no AD. Consequently, in view of this study's find-
ings and our previous experiments [18], Lesch's 
typology may not be related to the genotype of AD 
subjects -at least in terms of genes with an already 
established role in the development of dependen-
cy. It should be remembered that alcoholism is 
a complex disease with strong environmental deter-
minants. Since Lesch's typology is based mostly on 
environmental criteria, this may be the reason that 
no genetic background of this classification has 
been found thus far. Perhaps other typologies of 
AD, e.g. Cloninger, Babor, or Early/Late onset [20], 
would be associated with GABA-A polymorphisms. 
On the other hand, alcoholism is considered 
a multigenetic disease [21] and some genes other 
than GABA-A may still exist undiscovered and 
determine the phenotype of AD subjects. 
In conclusion, larger -possibly multicentre -
studies are needed to finally uncover the role of 
GABA-A genes in determining Lesch's phenotypes 
and other phenotypic traits in AD subjects. More-
over, other candidate genes with a possible impact 
on the phenotype of alcohol-dependent individu-
als should be sought. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant (No. NN 
402 189335) from the Ministry of Science and Edu-
cation. </p>

<p>g2 
g3 
g4 
g5 
g6 
g7 
g8 
g9 
g10 
g11 
g12 
g13 
g14 </p>

<p>g1 D' 0.93 
0.89 
0.03 
0.30 
0.35 
0.99 
0.01 
0.99 
0.03 
0.04 
0.35 
0.05 
0.04 </p>

<p>g2 D' 
0.93 
0.04 
0.08 
0.13 
0.88 
0.03 
0.9 
0.01 
0.04 
0.11 
0.03 
0.12 </p>

<p>g3 D' 
0.36 
0.28 
0.24 
0.93 
0.41 
0.96 
0.38 
0.34 
0.26 
0.25 
0.17 </p>

<p>g4 D' 
0.99 
0.97 
0.93 
0.96 
0.99 
0.97 
0.87 
0.51 
0.48 
0.53 </p>

<p>g5 D' 
0.99 
0.91 
0.95 
0.99 
0.96 
0.85 
0.58 
0.38 
0.35 </p>

<p>g6 D' 
0.92 
0.95 
0.99 
0.97 
0.85 
0.57 
0.35 
0.33 </p>

<p>g7 D' 
0.93 
0.99 
0.93 
0.86 
0.57 
0.45 
0.4 </p>

<p>g8 D' 
0.99 
0.99 
0.96 
0.58 
0.53 
0.52 </p>

<p>g9 D' 
0.99 
0.99 
0.63 
0.72 
0.55 </p>

<p>g10 D' 
0.96 
0.56 
0.51 
0.53 </p>

<p>g11 D' 
0.53 
0.49 
0.46 </p>

<p>g12 D' 
0.99 
0.81 </p>

<p>g13 D' 
0.93 </p>

<p>Table III. Linkage disequilibrium (LD) of the GABRA2 and GABRG1 loci in AD subjects (n = 133) and the controls (n = 145) </p>

<p>GABRGA2 and GABRG1 polymorphisms: g1 -rs2119767 (GABRA2) A/T, g2 -rs16859354 (GABRA2) G/T, g3 -rs13152740 (GABRA2) A/G, 
g4 -rs279836 (GABRA2) A/T, g5 -rs279826 (GABRA2) A/G, g6 -rs279844 (GABRA2) A/T, g7 -rs3775282 (GABRA2) C/T, g8 -rs279871 (GABRA2) 
A/G, g9 -rs17537141 (GABRA2) C/T, g10 -rs529826 (GABRA2) C/T, g11 -rs572227 (GABRA2) A/G, g12 -rs1391166 (GABRG1) A/T, g13 -rs1497577 
(GABRG1) A/T, g14 -rs10034075 (GABRG1) A/G </p>

<p>Arch Med Sci 2, April / 2012 </p>



<p>GABA-A receptor genes do not play a role in genetics of Lesch's typology in Caucasian subjects </p>



</text></tei>