<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3768955" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The present study reports statistical medial optimization for chitinase production by a novel bacterial strain </p>

<p>isolated from soil recently, which the name Chitinolyticbacter meiyuanensis SYBC-H1 is proposed. A </p>

<p>sequential statistical methodology comprising of Plackett-Burman and response surface methodology (RSM) </p>

<p>was applied to enhance the fermentative production of chitinase, in which inulin was firstly used as an </p>

<p>effective carbon source. As a result, maximum chitinase activity of 5.17 U/mL was obtained in the </p>

<p>optimized medium, which was 15.5-fold higher than that in the basal medium. The triplicate verification </p>

<p>experiments were performed under the optimized nutrients levels which indicated that it well agreed with the </p>

<p>predicted value. </p>

<p>Chitin is the second most abundant insoluble </p>

<p>biodegradable polymer, which exists naturally in the biosphere </p>

<p>as a structural polysaccharide of -1,4-N-acetyl-D-glucosamine </p>

<p>(16). It is highly distributed in nature, as a constituent of insect </p>

<p>exoskeleton, shells of crustaceans, fungal cell walls (11), and </p>

<p>algae components (5). More than 1×10 11 tons of chitin are </p>

<p>estimated to be produced annually in marine waters alone, </p>

<p>mostly by copepods (24). Most of chitin for commercial are </p>

<p>come from shrimp shellfish waste. </p>

<p>Chitinase (E.C.3.2.1.14) are enzymes capable of </p>

<p>hydrolyzing chitin to its oligo and monomeric components. </p>

<p>Microorganisms (5), higher plants (17), even lower animals </p>

<p>and birds (3) are known to produce chitinase. Microorganisms </p>

<p>are well investigated, Serratia marcescens is the most common </p>

<p>and well known microorganism for chitinase production (4). </p>

<p>Recently, chitinase are gaining much attention worldwide </p>

<p>*Corresponding Author. Mailing address: The Key Laboratory of Industrial Biotechnology, Ministry of Education, School of Biotechnology, Jiangnan 
University, Wuxi 214122, People's Republic of China..; Tel/Fax.: +86 510 8532 6880.; E-mail: liaoxiangru@163.com </p>



<p>Hao, Z. et al. 
Chitanase production from C. meiyuanensis </p>

<p>(7, 8, 12, 26), because of their wide range of biotechnological </p>

<p>applications in such as generation of fungal protoplasts (12), </p>

<p>shellfish waste management, production of single cell protein </p>

<p>(34), and specially in the production of chitooligosaccharides </p>

<p>(immune 
enhancers), 
N-acetyl-glucosamine, 
or </p>

<p>chitooligosaccharides for various applications (34), and in </p>

<p>biocontrol of fungal plant pathogens (6). </p>

<p>In order to industrially convert the complex chitin to </p>

<p>simple or proper compounds, much work has been done to </p>

<p>improve the production of chitinase by a cheap and energy-</p>

<p>saving process using genetically modified organisms (18) </p>

<p>and/or multistage fermentation system. An enhancing effect of </p>

<p>glucose on chitinase production was reported by Bhushan when </p>

<p>glucose was used with chitin as carbon source (2). However, a </p>

<p>suppressing effect of glucose on chitinase production was </p>

<p>reported by Miyashita et al. (23). Therefore, the current </p>

<p>challenge is to further enhance the enzyme activity via strain </p>

<p>selection and culture conditions optimization. </p>

<p>In the conventional method, the medium is optimized by </p>

<p>changing one factor at a time while keeping others at a constant </p>

<p>level (26, 33), which is laborious and often leads to wrong </p>

<p>conclusions (20). Multivariate experiments are designed not </p>

<p>only to reduce the number of necessary experiments in the </p>

<p>optimization process, but also to produce more defined results </p>

<p>than those available by univariate strategies (27). Plackett-</p>

<p>Burman (P-B) and response-surface methodology (RSM) are </p>

<p>multivariate analyzing tools comprising of mathematical and </p>

<p>statistical techniques for generating empirical models that </p>

<p>obtained importance for optimizing production conditions of </p>

<p>industrially high value products such as chemicals, enzymes, </p>

<p>and for studying enzyme kinetics. The statistical tool has been </p>

<p>used in many biotechnological processes namely optimization </p>

<p>of culture conditions (19), enzyme production (32), ethanol </p>

<p>production (10), and biomass production (36). It was also </p>

<p>useful for optimizing the yield of recombinant products such as </p>

<p>actinorhodin (9), nisin (21), lysozyme (14), alkaline protease </p>

<p>(1), and hirudin (28) as well as extracellular polysaccharides </p>

<p>and biomass (13). However, there have been few studies on </p>

<p>chitinase production using (P-B) and RSM (31). </p>

<p>A novel bacterial strain was isolated from soil recently, </p>

<p>which named Chitinolyticbacter meiyuanensis SYBC-H1. In </p>

<p>this paper, the effect of the addition of inulin to the liquid </p>

<p>culture of the strain was investigated, and RSM, an efficient </p>

<p>experimental strategy, was applied in optimizing the medial </p>

<p>composition to improve the production of chitinase. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Microorganism </p>

<p>The chitinase-producing bacterium was isolated in our </p>

<p>laboratory from the soil samples collected from Meiyuan Park </p>

<p>(33°56´N,120°18´E), Wuxi city, China. The physiological and </p>

<p>biochemical tests of the isolated chitinase-producing strain </p>

<p>were done as described in Bergey's manual of systematic </p>

<p>bacteriology (15). The strain was further identified according </p>

<p>to 16S rRNA studies. The obtained sequence was searched </p>

<p>against the GenBank database and homology studies were </p>

<p>undertaken to identify the isolate. Initially sequence was </p>

<p>analyzed at National Center for Biotechnology Information </p>

<p>(NCBI) server (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov). Nearly complete </p>

<p>16S rRNA gene sequence of the isolate, consisting of 1,526 </p>

<p>nucleotides, was determined and deposited in the DDBJ/ </p>

<p>GenBank/ EMBL database under the accession number of </p>

<p>GQ981314. Homology search indicated that the strain SYB-H1 </p>

<p>had sequence identity of 95.0% to SAY 3 
T (AB 453176) as </p>

<p>closest relative (30). On the basis of physiological, biochemical </p>

<p>and 16S rRNA gene sequence study, the isolate was identified </p>

<p>as gen. nov., sp. nov. (22) and named Chitinolyticbacter </p>

<p>meiyuanensis SYBC-H1, which was deposited into the China </p>

<p>General 
Microbiological 
Culture 
Collection 
Center </p>

<p>(CGMCC3438) and American Type Culture Collection (ATCC </p>

<p>BAA-2140). The strain was first studied on fermentation. </p>

<p>Preparation of seed culture </p>

<p>The stock culture was maintained on nutrient agar slants kept at </p>



<p>Hao, Z. et al. 
Chitanase production from C. meiyuanensis </p>



<p>colony in a plate containing the medium composed of (g/L) 2.0 </p>

<p>glucose, 4.0 peptone </p>



<p>0.7 KH 2 PO 4 , 0.5 MgSO 4 ·7H 2 O, 0.3 </p>

<p>K 2 HPO 4 , 0.02 FeSO 4 ·7H 2 O, and 20.0 agar. In order to have </p>

<p>stable strains, the cells were transferred into a fresh medium for </p>

<p>several times. After incubated for 2 days at 30 o C, a loop full of </p>

<p>the colony from the flat plate is transferred to 50 mL seed </p>

<p>medium composed of (g/L) 2.0 glucose, 4.0 peptone, 0.7 </p>

<p>KH 2 PO 4 , 0.5 MgSO 4 ·7H 2 O, 0.3 K 2 HPO 4 and 0.02 FeSO 4 ·7H 2 O </p>

<p>in 250 mL shake flasks and incubated at 30 °C for 12 hour on a </p>

<p>rotary shaker (200 rpm). The cells growth was monitored by </p>

<p>absorbance measurement at 600 nm with a UV-visible </p>

<p>spectrophotometer. For shake flask culture, the liquid medium </p>

<p>was sterilized in the autoclave at 121°C for 20 min, and pH </p>

<p>was adjusted to 7.0 before autoclaving. </p>

<p>Culture conditions </p>

<p>Chitinase production was carried out by shake-flask </p>

<p>culture. Medium were determined according to the result of the </p>

<p>Plackett-Burman factorial and the Response Surface Method </p>

<p>design. The pH was adjusted to 6.5 before autoclaving at 121 o C </p>

<p>for 20 min. Subsequently </p>



<p>inoculated with 4 % (w/w) seed and </p>

<p>incubated at 30 o C for 72 h under shaking at 200 rpm. The broth </p>

<p>was centrifuged at 10,000×g for 10 min at 4 o C, and the </p>

<p>supernatant was used for chitinase assay. </p>

<p>Effect of incubation period on the chitinase production </p>

<p>Flasks containing 50 ml of production medium were </p>

<p>inoculated with 4.0% seed culture and incubated at 30 o C with </p>

<p>constant shaking at 200 rpm. Following incubation for 12 h </p>

<p>intervals, fermentation broth was centrifuged and chitinase </p>

<p>activity was determined. </p>

<p>Assay of chitinase activity </p>

<p>The chitinase activity was measured by reduction of 3,5-</p>

<p>dinitrosalicylic acid, in the presence of the aminosugar N-</p>

<p>acetyl-D-glucosamine (NAG) released by enzymatic hydrolysis </p>

<p>of colloid chitin according to the method described by Rojas-</p>

<p>Avelizapa et al. (29). The absorbance was recorded at 530 nm. </p>

<p>Readings were compared with a standard curve prepared with a </p>

<p>series of dilutions of NAG (0-5.0 mmol/mL) and 3, 5-</p>

<p>dinitrosalicylic acids. The chitinase activity was assayed in </p>

<p>triplicate and the average enzyme activity with standard </p>

<p>deviations was measured using software of <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">11.5</rs>. One </p>

<p>unit chitinase activity (U) was defined as the amount of </p>

<p>enzyme required for producing 1 mmol of NAG at 37 o C in 1 </p>

<p>minute. </p>

<p>Screening of critical media components using a Plackett-</p>

<p>Burman design </p>

<p>The Plackett-Burman factorial design was used to select </p>

<p>significant medium components affecting the production of </p>

<p>chitinase. Previous studies showed that peptone, urea, corn </p>

<p>steep liquor powder, ammonium sulfate, glucose, inulin, starch, </p>

<p>sodium sulfate, fructose , and Magnesium sulfate were effective </p>

<p>medial components for process modeling. A total of fourteen </p>

<p>process variables comprising of ten medial components </p>

<p>(peptone, urea, corn steep liquor powder, ammonium sulfate, </p>

<p>glucose, inulin, starch, sodium sulfate, fructose , and </p>

<p>Magnesium sulfate) and one dummy variable were studied in </p>

<p>Plackett-Burman screening experiments. Each variable was </p>

<p>represented at 3 levels, upper ('high, +'), intermediate ('center </p>

<p>point, 0') and lower ('low, -') levels of the range covered by </p>

<p>each variable and the response (Tables 1 and 2). Experimental </p>

<p>responses were analyzed by first order model by the following </p>

<p>equation Y=o+i x i where Y is the response for chitinase </p>

<p>production, o is the model intercept and i is the linear </p>

<p>coefficient, and x i is the level of the independent variable. </p>

<p>According to the Stat-Ease analysis, a first-order model could </p>

<p>be obtained from the regression results of fractional factorial </p>

<p>experiment. This model describes the interaction among factors </p>

<p>and it is used to screen and evaluate important factors that </p>

<p>influence the response. From the regression analysis of the </p>

<p>variables, the factors having significant effect on chitinase </p>



<p>Hao, Z. et al. 
Chitanase production from C. meiyuanensis </p>

<p>production were further optimized by RSM. </p>

<p>Optimization of medium with the Response Surface </p>

<p>Method </p>

<p>Inulin, urea, and sodium sulfate were identified as the key </p>

<p>factors that influenced chitinase production from the above </p>

<p>experiments (Table 3), and their suitable concentration ranges </p>

<p>were also preliminarily determined. Consequently, RSM was </p>

<p>employed to optimize the four most significant factors, namely </p>

<p>inulin, urea, sodium sulfate, and chitin powder (particle size &lt; </p>

<p>100 mesh), which had been screened by fractional factorial </p>

<p>design for chitinase production enhancement based on central </p>

<p>composite design. The four independent factors were studied at </p>

<p>five different levels (−1.41, −1, 0, +1, and +1.41) as shown in </p>

<p>Table 4. The factors were coded according to Eq. 1: </p>

<p>x i =(X i -X 0 )/X i , i = 1, 2,.., k 
(1) </p>

<p>Where Xi and xi are the actual value and codified value, </p>

<p>respectively. X 0 is the value of Xi at center point, and </p>

<p>¡ </p>

<p>Xi is </p>

<p>the step change value. The second-order model used to fit the </p>

<p>response to the independent variables is shown in Eq. 2: </p>

<p>Y = 0 + i x i + i x 2 
i + ij x i x j , i = 1, 2, ..., k (2) </p>

<p>Where Y is the predicted response, x i and x j are the coded </p>

<p>independent factors that influence the response variable Y, o is </p>

<p>the intercept, i represents the linear effect of x i , ij represents </p>

<p>the interaction between x i and x j , and ij represents the quadratic </p>

<p>effect of x i . <rs id="software-1" type="software">Design Expert</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 7.1.5</rs> statistical software </p>

<p>(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Stat-Ease</rs>, Minneapolis, MN) was used for the experimental </p>

<p>design and regression analysis of the experimental data. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis of the model was performed to evaluate the </p>

<p>analysis of variance (ANOVA). The quality of the polynomial </p>

<p>model equation was judged statistically by the coefficient of </p>

<p>determination R 2 , and its statistical significance was </p>

<p>determined by an F test. The significance of the regression </p>

<p>coefficients was tested by t test. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Screening of significant factors by Plackett-Burman design </p>

<p>In the Plackett-Burman model, 14 experiments were </p>

<p>required tests to screen the importance of eleven medium </p>

<p>components derived from single-factor optimization (Tables 1 </p>

<p>and 2). The values of Prob &gt; F less than 0.05 implied that </p>

<p>model terms were significant. From the experimental data, all </p>

<p>of these variables could distinctly affect the production of </p>

<p>chitinase (Table 3). Among them, Corn steep liquor powder, </p>

<p>glucose, starch, and magnesium sulfate exerted negative effect, </p>

<p>whereas the other six variables exerted positive effects on the </p>

<p>production of chitinase. The optimum variables (urea, inulin, </p>

<p>and sodium sulfate) were further evaluated by a response </p>

<p>surface methodology (RSM) design. </p>

<p>Table 1. Variables representing medium components used in Plackett-Burman design </p>

<p>Variables 
Medium 
component </p>

<p>¢ ¢ 
¢ ¢ </p>

<p>values 
(g/L) </p>

<p>0 values 
(g/L) </p>

<p>£ £ 
£ £ </p>

<p>values 
(g/L) 
X 1 
Peptone 
5.00(+) 
3.00 
1.00(-) 
X 2 
Urea 
1.30(+) 
0.78 
0.26(-) 
X 3 
Corn steep powder 
1.33(+) 
0.80 
0.27(-) 
X 4 
Ammonium sulfate 
2.86(+) 
1.72 
0.57(-) 
X 5 
Glucose 
2.00(+) 
1.20 
0.40(-) 
X 6 
Inulin 
1.16(+) 
0.70 
0.23(+) 
X 7 
Starch 
1.95(+) 
1.17 
0.39(-) 
X 8 
Magnesium sulfate 
0.492(+) 
0.30 
0.098(-) 
X 9 
Fructose 
2.00(+) 
1.20 
0.40(-) 
X 10 
Sodium sulfate 
0.284(+) 
0.17 
0.057(-) </p>

<p>X1-X10 represent different assigned variables (Peptone, Urea, Corn steep liquor powder, Ammonium sulfate, Glucose, Inulin, 
Starch, Magnesium sulfate, Fructose, Sodium sulfate); the sign '+' is for high concentration of variables, '0' is for intermediate 
concentration of variables and '¤ ' is for low concentration of variables. </p>



<p>Hao, Z. et al. 
Chitanase production from C. meiyuanensis </p>

<p>Table 2. Plackett-Burman experimental design matrix with the observed response (Chitinase activity). The values showed in the table </p>

<p>were averaged from two independent triplicate experiments with means less than 5 %. </p>

<p>X1-X10 represent different assigned variables(Peptone, Urea, Corn steep liquor powder, Ammonium sulfate, Glucose, Inulin, 
Starch, Magnesium sulfate, Fructose, Sodium sulfate), and D are the unassigned⁄dummy variable; the sign '+' is for high 
concentration of variables, the sign '0' is for middle concentration of variables and '¤ ' is for low concentration of variables. </p>

<p>Table 3. Statistical analysis of medium components for chitinase production by Plackett-Burman design. </p>

<p>X1-X10 represent different assigned variables(Peptone, Urea, Corn steep liquor powder, Ammonium sulfate, Glucose, Inulin, Starch, 
Magnesium sulfate, Fructose, Sodium sulfate) 
Std. Dev. = 0.021; R-Squared = 0.999; Mean = 0.91; Adj R-Squared = 0.9941; 
C.V. % = 2.30; Pred R-Squared = 0.9843; PRESS = 0.014; Adeq Precision = 46.992 </p>

<p>Optimization using RSM </p>

<p>To search for the optimum combination of these </p>

<p>components in the culture medium, a CCD experimental plan </p>

<p>was carried out. Their suitable concentrations ranges were </p>

<p>preliminarily determined. Table 4 shows various combinations </p>

<p>used and the corresponding chitinase yield. Data were analyzed </p>

<p>by linear multiple regression using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Design-Expert</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 7.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Stat-Ease,Inc</rs>.) and the following equation was obtained. </p>

<p>Y=4.68+0.34X1+0.25X2+0.52X3+0.16X4+0.041X1X2+0.025X1X3-0.19X1X4 </p>

<p>-0.11X2X3+0.19 X2X4+0.39X3X4-0.95X1 2 -0.32 X2 2 -0.53 X3 2 -0.16 X4 2 (3) </p>

<p>Where X 1 , X 2 , X 3 and X 4 are the symbols of concentration </p>

<p>of inulin, urea, chitin and sodium sulfate, respectively. The </p>

<p>experimental results revealed that this mathematical tool could </p>

<p>satisfactorily explain the effects of the variables concentration </p>

<p>(inulin, urea, chitin, and Sodium Sulfate) in chitinase </p>

<p>production of Chitinolyticbacter meiyuanensis SYBC-H1 in </p>

<p>shake-flask cultures. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) for the </p>

<p>Quadratic model were shown in Table 5. Value of ''Model </p>

<p>Variables 
Run 
X 1 
X 2 
X 3 
X 4 
X 5 
X 6 
X 7 
X 8 
X 9 
X 10 
D 
Chitinase 
(U/ml) 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § 
¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 
0.79 
2 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § 
¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>0.88 
3 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>0.70 
4 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0.93 
5 
1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1.26 
6 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § 
¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>0.75 
7 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 
0.41 
8 
1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1.27 
9 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § 
¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 
1 
1.32 
10 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § 
¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
0.72 
11 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0.89 
12 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § 
¦ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>0.84 
13 
1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1.11 
14 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ 
¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>¥ 
 § ¦ </p>

<p>1 
0.98 </p>

<p>Source 
Medium 
component 
Sum of 
squares 
Coefficient 
estimate 
Mean 
square 
Stdized 
Effects 
F-value 
P-value 
Prob¨¨ 
 
¨ ¨ </p>

<p>F 
Model 
0.89 
0.91 
0.089 
204.12 
0.0049 
X 1 
Peptone 
0.009 
0.028 
0.009 
0.055 
20.74 
0.0450 
X 2 
Urea 
0.092 
0.088 
0.092 
0.18 
210.00 
0.0047 
X 3 
Corn steep liquor powder 
0.049 
-0.064 
0.049 
-0.13 
112.93 
0.0087 
X 4 
Ammonium sulfate 
0.037 
0.056 
0.037 
0.11 
85.5 
0.0115 
X 5 
Glucose 
0.044 
-0.061 
0.044 
-0.12 
101.50 
0.0097 
X 6 
Inulin 
0.11 
0.098 
0.11 
0.20 
260.74 
0.0038 
X 7 
Starch 
0.072 
-0.078 
0.072 
-0.16 
164.74 
0.0060 
X 8 
sodium sulfate 
0.16 
-0.11 
0.16 
-0.23 
357.50 
0.0028 
X 9 
Fructose 
0.29 
0.15 
0.29 
0.31 
651.90 
0.0015 
X 10 
Magnesium sulfate 
0.033 
0.053 
0.033 
0.11 
75.6 
0.0130 </p>



<p>Hao, Z. et al. 
Chitanase production from C. meiyuanensis </p>

<p>Prob&gt;F'' less than 0.0060 implied that the model was high </p>

<p>significant. In this case X 1 , X 3 , X 1 
2 and X 3 
2 are significant model </p>

<p>terms. The ''Lack of Fit Prob&gt;F value'' of 0.335 showed that the </p>

<p>lack of fit is insignificant. The R 2 coefficient obtained, of 0.8422, </p>

<p>suggests that it is a reliable model and that 84.22% of the sample </p>

<p>variation of chitinase yield is attributed to a high correlation </p>

<p>between the independent variables. Only 15.78% of the total </p>

<p>variation of chitinase production was not explained by the model. </p>

<p>The 
relatively 
high-adjusted 
determination 
coefficient </p>

<p>(R 2 
Adj =0.6582) accounts for significance of the model. The 
coefficient of variation (CV) indicated the degree of precision with </p>

<p>which the calculations were compared. Usually, a high CV value </p>

<p>represents low reliability of the experiment. The low value </p>

<p>obtained (CV = 25.76%) showed a small residual variability data </p>

<p>and the greater reliability of the experiments performed. The </p>

<p>observed chitinase activity (the response) versus those factors </p>

<p>from the empirical model equation 2 was shown in Figure 1, </p>

<p>which indicated that the predicted data of the response from the </p>

<p>empirical model was in agreement with the observed ones in the </p>

<p>range of the operating variables. The graphical representation </p>

<p>provides a method to visualize the relationship between the </p>

<p>response and experimental levels of each variable and the type of </p>

<p>interactions between test variables to deduce the optimum </p>

<p>conditions. In this design, the response surface curves for the four </p>

<p>variables were shown in Figure 2. The response surface </p>

<p>representing chitinase was a function of concentrations of the two </p>

<p>medium components with another nutrient being at a zero level. </p>

<p>The regression equation, maximized by the <rs id="software-3" type="software">Design Expert</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">7.0</rs> </p>

<p>(Minneapolis, USA) software, allowed to obtain the following </p>

<p>optimal coded units for test variables: X 1 = 0.1, X 2 = 0.55, X 3 = </p>

<p>0.80 and X 4 = 1.00, which corresponded to optimal concentrations </p>

<p>of (g/L) 3.10 urea, 3.55 inulin, 3.80 chitin and 0.64 sodium sulfate, </p>

<p>for the maximal chitinase activity of the 5.17 U/mL, predicted by </p>

<p>the mathematical model with a high model accuracy. The P values </p>

<p>are used for checking the significance of each coefficient which, in </p>

<p>turn, it is necessary to understand the pattern of the mutual </p>

<p>interactions between the important variables, and the small </p>

<p>magnitude of P values means that the corresponding coefficients </p>

<p>are more significant. A positive coefficient represents an effect </p>

<p>that favors the optimization of chitinase yield, while a negative </p>

<p>value indicates an antagonistic effect. </p>

<p>Table 4. Experimental design and results of the central composite design. The values showed in the table were averaged from two </p>

<p>independent triplicate experiments with means less than 5 %. </p>

<p>Variables/levels 
Inulin 
Urea 
Chitin 
sodium sulfate </p>

<p>Chitinase 
(U/ml) 
Trial 
Coded 
value 
Actual value 
(g/L) 
Coded 
value 
Actual value 
(g/L) 
Coded 
value 
Actual value 
(g/L) 
Coded 
value 
Actual value 
(mM) 
Experimental </p>

<p>1 
-1 
2 
-1 
2 
-1 
2 
-1 
1 
1.41 
2 
0 
3 
-
1.59 
0 
3 
0 
2 
3.13 
3 
-1 
2 
1 
4 
-1 
2 
1 
3 
1.63 
4 
1 
4 
-1 
2 
1 
4 
-1 
1 
2.92 
5 
0 
3 
0 
3 
0 
3 
0 
2 
4.51 
6 
-1 
2 
-1 
2 
1 
4 
1 
3 
3.01 
7 
+ 
4.41 
0 
3 
0 
3 
0 
2 
1.59 
8 
1 
4 
1 
4 
-1 
2 
1 
3 
3.73 
9 
1 
4 
-1 
2 
-1 
2 
1 
3 
0.83 
10 
-1 
2 
-1 
2 
1 
4 
-1 
1 
1.50 
11 
1 
4 
1 
4 
1 
4 
1 
3 
3.63 
12 
0 
3 
0 
3 
-
1.59 
0 
2 
1.35 
13 
0 
3 
+ 
4.41 
0 
3 
0 
2 
4.41 
14 
0 
3 
0 
3 
+ 
4.41 
0 
2 
4.51 
15 
0 
3 
0 
3 
0 
3 
+ 
3.41 
4.44 
16 
-1 
2 
1 
4 
1 
4 
-1 
1 
1.64 
17 
-1 
2 
1 
4 
-1 
2 
-1 
1 
2.18 
18 
-1 
2 
-1 
2 
-1 
2 
1 
3 
1.80 
19 
0 
3 
0 
3 
0 
3 
0 
2 
4.73 
20 
1 
4 
1 
4 
-1 
2 
-1 
1 
2.43 
21 
-1 
2 
1 
4 
1 
4 
1 
3 
3.70 
22 
-
1.59 
0 
3 
0 
3 
0 
2 
0.91 
23 
1 
4 
1 
4 
1 
4 
-1 
1 
3.11 
24 
0 
3 
0 
3 
0 
3 
-
0.59 
4.36 
25 
1 
4 
-1 
2 
1 
4 
1 
3 
3.82 
26 
1 
4 
-1 
2 
-1 
2 
-1 
1 
3.25 
27 
0 
3 
0 
3 
0 
3 
0 
2 
4.80 
is the axial spacing and the signs, ' </p>

<p>© </p>

<p>
' and ' ' represent the positive and negative directions respectively. Value of is 1.414 </p>



<p>Hao, Z. et al. 
Chitanase production from C. meiyuanensis </p>

<p>Table 5. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) for the Quadratic model </p>

<p>Source 
df 
Coefficient 
Estimate 
Sum 
squares 
Mean 
square 
F ratio 
Prob. 
level 
model 
14 
4.68 
36.67 
2.62 
4.58 
0.0060 
X 1-Inulin 
1 
0.34 
2.80 
2.80 
4.89 
0.0472 
X 2-Urea 
1 
0.25 
1.54 
1.54 
2.70 
0.1265 
X 3-Chitin 
1 
0.52 
6.40 
6.40 
11.18 
0.0059 
X 4-sodium sulfate 
1 
0.16 
0.62 
0.62 
1.08 
0.3191 
X 1 ×X 2 
1 
0.041 
0.026 
0.026 
0.046 
0.8338 
X 1 ×X 3 
1 
0.025 
9.851 
9.851 
0.017 
0.8978 
X 1 ×X 4 
1 
-0.19 
0.60 
0.60 
1.05 
0.3251 
X 2 ×X 3 
1 
-0.11 
0.21 
0.21 
0.37 
0.5547 
X 2 ×X 4 
1 
0.19 
0.55 
0.55 
0.96 
0.3469 
X 3 ×X 4 
1 
0.39 
2.45 
2.45 
4.28 
0.0607 
X 1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 
-0.95 
19.25 
19.25 
33.62 
0.0001 
X 2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 
-0.32 
2.19 
2.19 
3.82 
0.0742 
X 3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 
-0.53 
6.01 
6.01 
10.05 
0.0071 
X 4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 
-0.16 
0.56 
0.56 
0.98 
0.3427 
Residual 
12 
6.87 
0.57 
Lack of fit 
10 
8.82 
0.68 
29.20 
0.335 
Total error 
2 
0.047 
0.023 
Corrected total 
26 
43.54 </p>

<p>R-Squared =0.8422, Adj R-Squared =0.6582, C.V.=25.76%, 
Adeq Precision ratio=7.948 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Plot of predicted vs actual chitinase activity (U/mL </p>

<p>values)(different color represents the corresponding chitinase activity </p>

<p>in the figure). </p>

<p>The regression equation was represented in 3-D response </p>

<p>surface plots, and each contour curve corresponds to an infinite </p>

<p>number of combinations between two test variables, while the </p>

<p>third was maintained at their zero level. The chitinase for </p>

<p>different concentrations of the variables could also be </p>

<p>predicated from the respective response surface plots (Figure </p>

<p>2). The maximum predicted yield was indicated by the surface </p>

<p>confined in the response surface diagram. </p>

<p>Figure 2. 3D response surface curve for effects of Inulin, Urea and </p>

<p>their mutual interaction on chitinase production by SYBC-H1. Other </p>

<p>variables held at their zero level. </p>



<p>Hao, Z. et al. 
Chitanase production from C. meiyuanensis </p>

<p>Fermentation time courses under optimized and non-</p>

<p>optimized conditions were given in Figure 3. Both time courses </p>

<p>showed disparity fermentation process trend. Initially, chitinase </p>

<p>yield was very low, and after a lag phase of near 48 hours, </p>

<p>chitinase yield gradually increased. After about 84 hours of </p>

<p>incubation, chitinase reached the maximum yield. The time </p>

<p>course showed that the optimized fermentation conditions </p>

<p>change the chitinase producing process. After the enzyme </p>

<p>activity reached maximum, the production of chitinase reduced </p>

<p>rapidly, which was similar to the previous reports (26, 33). The </p>

<p>reduction of chitinase might be caused by proteinase </p>

<p>degradation or inactivation of the chitinase by unclear </p>

<p>mechanisms. In many submerged fermentation processes, when </p>

<p>the products reached the highest yield, further increase in </p>

<p>incubation time could decrease the yield due to the degradation </p>

<p>of metabolites. </p>

<p>Figure 3. The time-course of chitinase production by SYBC-H1 </p>

<p>before and after the optimization (: Original, : Optimum </p>

<p>medium). </p>

<p>Table 6. Effect of medium composition on chitinase production </p>

<p>Factors 
Original 
Optimum medium 
Urea (g/L) 
-
3.10 
Inulin (g/L) 
-
3.55 
Chitin (g/L) 
1.00 
3.80 
Sodium sulfate (g/L) 
-
0.64 
Glucose(g/L) 
1.20 
-
Yeast extract(g/L) 
4.00 
-
Mineral medium 
* 
* 
Chitinase(U/ml) 
0.49 ± 0.2 
5.17 ± 0.4 </p>

<p>*mineral medium(g/l): K2HPO4 0.7; KH2PO4; MgSO4.7H2O 0.5; FeSO4.7H2O 
0.2 </p>

<p>Optimization and Model Verification </p>

<p>From the study of plots, the maximum production of </p>

<p>chitinase was obtained when the concentration (g/L) of 3.1 </p>

<p>urea, 3.55 inulin, 3.8 chitin, 0.64 sodium sulfate, 0.7 KH 2 PO 4 , </p>

<p>0.5 MgSO 4 ·7H 2 O, 0.02 FeSO 4 ·7H 2 O, and 0.3 K 2 HPO 4 (Table </p>

<p>6) were used for flask fermentation at 30 o C for 96 h. The </p>

<p>maximum value of chitinase yield predicted from this model </p>

<p>was 5.17 U/mL. To verify the predicted results, the triplicate </p>

<p>verification experiments were performed under the optimized </p>

<p>nutrients levels. The mean value of the chitinase activity was </p>

<p>5.16±0.15 U/mL, which was well agreed with the predicted </p>

<p>value (5.17 U/mL). As a result, the models developed were </p>

<p>considered to be accurate and reliable for predicting the </p>

<p>production of chitinase by Chitinolyticbacter meiyuanensis </p>

<p>SYBC-H1. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Chitin is usually thought as a kind of renewable </p>

<p>polysaccharides and organic nitrogenous substance that only </p>

<p>second respectively to cellulose and protein in abundance (11). </p>

<p>From further study more and more unique properties are being </p>

<p>discovered. Chitin, especially its derivatives, are of interest to </p>

<p>people due to their diverse applications. However, chitin is </p>

<p>insoluble in aqueous solutions and therefore can not be utilized </p>

<p>directly. Chitin is currently tapped with acid hydrolysis which </p>

<p>incurs some negative effects, e.g. being difficult to control and </p>

<p>giving rise to environmental problems. Chitinases hydrolyze </p>

<p>chitin is the future direction of research. So far chitinase can be </p>

<p>found everywhere in a variety of microorganisms, nevertheless </p>

<p>the production level is far from being enough for </p>

<p>commercialization. For that reason, isolating novel chitinase-</p>

<p>producing microorganisms and production optimization for </p>

<p>high productivity are of great importance to the industry. A </p>

<p>strain with strong chitinolytic activity was isolated in our </p>

<p>laboratory from the soil samples named Chitinolyticbacter </p>

<p>meiyuanensis SYBC-H1 which is gen. nov., sp. nov. The </p>

<p>traditional one factor at a time process requires a complete </p>



<p>Hao, Z. et al. 
Chitanase production from C. meiyuanensis </p>

<p>series of experiments for important factors of interest, which is </p>

<p>laborious and time consuming. Furthermore, such methods </p>

<p>could not provide information for the interactions of the </p>

<p>factors. Statistical methodology could locate the most </p>

<p>important factors levels with minimum effort and time; </p>

<p>moreover, it could reveal the interaction among the factor. In </p>

<p>this study, a sequential statistical methodology comprising of </p>

<p>Plackett-Burman and response surface methodology were </p>

<p>applied to enhance the fermentative production of chitinase. A </p>

<p>quadratic polynomial equation suggested by the RSM model </p>

<p>was then validated experientially. The synthesis of extracellular </p>

<p>enzymes such as chitinase depends on carbon and nitrogen. </p>

<p>The composition of culture medium has been optimized before, </p>

<p>in which glucose principally serves as carbon source (35). In </p>

<p>the research, urea, inulin, chitin powder and sodium sulfate </p>

<p>were found to be significant factors controlling chitinase yield. </p>

<p>This is the first report suggesting a whole new carbon source to </p>

<p>produce chitinase through employment of inulin as substrate. </p>

<p>Inulin, a D-fructose polymer terminated by glucose residue, </p>

<p>makes up 80% or so of the dry matter of Jerusalem artichoke </p>

<p>tubers, and for many years it has been proposed to be a </p>

<p>possible feedstock for ethanol production (25). As </p>

<p>demonstrated in this paper, Inulin can also be used as an </p>

<p>effective carbon source to chitinase yield with much lower cost </p>

<p>in substrate. </p>

<p>The study using RSM based on CCD established an </p>

<p>efficient model to describe the process. During the process of </p>

<p>chitinase production, chitin acts as not only inducer, but also </p>

<p>carbon source and nitrogen source. Furthermore, preliminary </p>

<p>experiments indicated that chitinase production was </p>

<p>significantly influenced by chitin. The high similarity between </p>

<p>the observed value and the predicted ones showed that the </p>

<p>RSM was an accurate and applicable tool to optimize culture </p>

<p>medium for chitinase yield in Chitinolyticbacter meiyuanensis </p>

<p>SYBC-H1 industry. By utilizing the statistical methodology, </p>

<p>the optimum chitinase activity was determined to be 5.17 </p>

<p>U/mL. Under optimized culture conditions, the chitinase </p>

<p>activity was 15-fold than that under the original culture </p>

<p>conditions. In particular, the culture time was also decreased. </p>

<p>Although chitinase activity slightly lower than Streptomyces </p>

<p>(26), but it is low cost in substrate. To further increase the yield </p>

<p>of chitinase, we will attempt to construct recombinant </p>

<p>Chitinolyticbacter meiyuanensis SYBC-H1 using the molecular </p>

<p>biotechnology. Further works will be continued in our studies. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This work was financially supported by the National High </p>

<p>Technology and Development Program of China (863 </p>

<p>Program, grant No. 2010AA101501), National Institutes of </p>

<p>Health grant GM-33048, the scientific &amp; technological </p>

<p>personnel service project of the ministry of science and </p>

<p>technology (Grant No. 2009GJ10038), the national natural </p>

<p>science foundation of China (Grant No. 21045007), special </p>

<p>funds of science &amp; technology innovation of science and </p>

<p>technology department of Jiangsu province (Grant No. </p>

<p>BY2010117), and the Fundamental Research Funds for the </p>

<p>Central Universities JUSRP21120. </p>







</text></tei>