<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3532996" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective: Rural north-central Liberia has one of the </p>

<p>world's highest maternal mortality ratios. We studied 
health facility birthing service utilisation and the 
motives of women seeking or not seeking facility-
based care in north-central Liberia. </p>

<p>Design: Cross-sectional community-based structured </p>

<p>interviews and health facility medical record review. </p>

<p>Setting: A regional hospital and the surrounding </p>

<p>communities in rural north-central Liberia. </p>

<p>Participants: A convenience sample of 307 women </p>

<p>between 15 and 49 years participated in structured 
interviews. 1031 deliveries performed in the regional 
hospital were included in the record review. </p>

<p>Primary outcomes: Delivery within a health facility </p>

<p>and caesarean delivery rates were used as indicators of 
direct utilisation of care and as markers of availability 
of maternal health services. </p>

<p>Results: Of 280 interview respondents with a prior </p>

<p>childbirth, only 47 (16.8%) delivered their last child in a 
health facility. Women who did not use formal services 
cited cost, sudden labour and family tradition or religion 
as their principal reasons for home delivery. At the 
regional hospital, the caesarean delivery rate was 35.5%. </p>

<p>Conclusions: There is an enormous unmet need for </p>

<p>maternal health services in north-central Liberia. Greater 
outreach and referral services as well as community-
based education among women, family members and 
traditional midwives are vital to improve the timely 
utilisation of care. </p>

<p>Goal 5 calls for a three-quarters reduction in 
MMR globally by 2015. Strides have been 
made toward this target; however, large-scale 
international programmes have not reduced 
maternal mortality significantly in areas of the 
world that bear the greatest burden. </p>

<p>1 6 7 </p>

<p>Programmes to reduce maternal mortality 
must consider the local context of maternal 
mortality and access to maternal health ser-
vices if they are to be effective. 
7-9 Recent 
efforts to improve the measurement of mater-
nal mortality globally have yielded more accur-
ate and complete data. 
1 Still, there is a paucity 
of primary community information in many 
countries with the highest MMR, such as 
Liberia. 
1 3 10 11 In addition, a high degree of 
variability in MMR and access to maternal care 
exists within communities. </p>

<p>12 13 </p>

<p>ARTICLE SUMMARY </p>

<p>Article focus </p>

<p>▪ Evaluate the utilisation rate of key maternal 
health services in north-central Liberia. 
▪ Assess the barriers to seeking facility-based 
maternal health services. </p>

<p>Key messages </p>

<p>▪ There is a massive unmet need for maternal 
health services in rural Liberia, including facility-
based delivery and caesarean section. 
▪ Significant barriers to access included cost, 
transport and family tradition of home delivery 
with a traditional midwife. 
▪ Local facility-based and community-based assess-
ments of maternal health services are critical in 
order to accurately measure community needs and 
inform policy and programmatic interventions. </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ Design strengths included the use of mixed facility-
and community-based methodologies to assess 
local utilisation of maternal health services in a 
highly underserved and under-researched region. 
▪ Study limitations included non-randomised sam-
pling of participants in community interviews 
and limited quality of comprehensive data in 
hospital records. </p>

<p>Gartland MG, Taryor VD, Norman AM, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e001602. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001602 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>In areas with high maternal mortality and poor infor-
mation systems where data on maternal mortality are not 
available, process indicators related to this outcome can 
be highly informative to evaluate the unmet need for 
maternal healthcare. Process indicators for maternal 
mortality include the proportion of women who deliver 
in a health facility under skilled attendance and the rate 
of caesarean delivery. 
14-16 These indicators are easier to 
capture partly because maternal death is difficult to 
ascertain, especially in rural areas, or may occur in small 
catchment areas with low numbers over a short evalu-
ation timespan. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>Liberia is among the poorest countries in the world; it 
has 1 of the 10 highest national MMR of any nation. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Hogan et al 
1 estimated MMR in Liberia to be 859 
(uncertainty interval, 547-1287) maternal deaths per 
100 000 live births in 2008. By comparison, the MMR 
in Ghana, among the lowest in the region, was 409 
(248-633), and in neighbour Sierra Leone, it was 1033 
(635-1627), the region's highest. The wide uncertainty 
intervals are reflective of the relative lack of data cap-
tured by poor health information systems in Liberia, 
which is still recovering from a 14-year civil war that 
ended in 2003. Health infrastructure and human 
resources were decimated during that span. In 2009, the 
country was estimated to have a deficit of 10 000 health-
care workers. 
19 The 2007 Liberia Demographic and 
Health Survey confirms a corresponding gap in access to 
essential services, citing only 46% of women in Liberia 
deliver under skilled attendance in health facilities. 
12 In 
addition, the national caesarean delivery rate in 2007 
was 3.5%, and &lt;1.0% in rural parts of the country. </p>

<p>12 20 </p>

<p>As Liberia rebuilds its health infrastructure and targets 
maternal mortality, community-level research is needed 
to appropriately direct maternal health interventions. 
The objective of this study was to characterise utilisa-
tion of maternal health services, including facility deliv-
ery and caesarean delivery, in rural north-central Liberia 
and describe the motives of women seeking or not 
seeking facility-based care. </p>

<p>METHODS 
We conducted a cross-sectional study employing a struc-
tured interview in a community setting, as well as a 
review of medical records at the local hospital. The indi-
vidual structured interview comprised of questions on 
the behaviour and attitudes of women regarding mater-
nal healthcare. Eight communities were chosen based 
on the presence of existing outreach programmes for 
antenatal education and childhood immunisations for a 
regional hospital in Nimba County, located in north-
central Liberia. All communities were within 15 km of 
the hospital. More than 95% of the county's 462 000 
residents live in a rural setting. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>All women between the ages of 15-49 years were eli-
gible, consonant with age sampling of the 2007 Liberia 
Demographic and Health Survey. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Women were </p>

<p>approached for participation in their homes or in other 
public spaces such as community meeting places. All 
households and public locations in each village were 
visited once, resulting in a convenience sample given 
absenteeism. Community health workers were trained to 
conduct 25 min standardised interviews. Questions in 
English were designed in collaboration with clinicians, 
public health technicians and community health 
workers in Liberia. Interviews were conducted orally in 
English or Mano, a language spoken in the region, as 
per a participant's preference. The interviewers were 
trained to record responses including multiple answers 
given to open-ended questions. Responses were coded 
by a member of the research team. Verbal informed 
consent was obtained from all participants. Women 
received a small non-monetary compensation (value≈US 
$2) for their time. 
The review of medical records involved a retrospective 
evaluation of all deliveries at a regional hospital in 
Nimba County using general medical and operating 
room records. Data were extracted on method of deliv-
ery, incidence of stillbirth and maternal and fetal indica-
tions for caesarean delivery. Extraction was performed 
by a hospital data officer and a medical student. </p>

<p>STATISTICAL ANALYSIS 
Participant responses were analysed for frequencies, 
means and SDs as indicated. Participant characteristics 
were correlated with their interview responses. 
Nulliparous women were excluded from analysis of ques-
tions related to prior deliveries. Respondents with 
missing data were dropped from all analyses. Fisher's 
exact test was used to evaluate categorical variables and 
Student's t test was used for continuous variables. All 
analyses were performed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.9.1.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, 
Cary, North Carolina, USA). Our primary outcomes of 
interest were facility delivery rate assessed in the commu-
nity and caesarean delivery rate in a regional hospital. 
Data were kept anonymous at all times by removing all 
identifiers. Ethical approval was granted by the 
Vanderbilt University Institutional Review Board and the 
Medical Director of the Liberian hospital. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Between May 2009 and August 2009, 316 women were 
approached to participate in community interviews. Of 
these 307 (97.2%) met eligibility criteria, consented and 
completed the interview. There was 1 (0.3%) documen-
ted refusal. Participants had a mean age of 30.5 (SD + 
7.5; table 1). The mean parity was 4.8 (SD + 3.0). More 
than half (n=174, 57.1%) of women reported having no 
formal education. There were 6 (2.0%) nulliparous 
women and 21 (6.8%) who chose not to answer ques-
tions regarding the site of delivery in the immediate 
prior pregnancy. Of the remaining 280 women, 210 
(75.0%) reported delivering their previous child at 
home with a traditional midwife (TM) and 23 (8.2%) at </p>



<p>Gartland MG, Taryor VD, Norman AM, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e001602. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001602 </p>

<p>Facility delivery and caesarean section in north-central Liberia </p>

<p>home without a TM. Interviewers then asked the open-
ended question, "Why did you choose to deliver your 
child in this place?" for which multiple responses were 
accepted. Responses for those delivering at home 
included, 'cost' or 'difficulty with transport' (31.5%), 
'quick onset of labour' (30.6%), 'family tradition' or 
'religion' (16.9%), 'TM is safe' (16.9%) and 'conflict' or 
'flooding' (3.7%). Women who reported delivering in a 
hospital responded, 'labour complications at home' 
(57.8%), 'hospital nearby' (13.3%), 'antenatal referral' 
(11.1%) 'safety' (11.1%) and 'previous caesarean deliv-
ery' (6.7%). 
In women who reported delivering at home, and 
those who reported delivering in a hospital, there was 
no statistical evidence to suggest a difference in age, 
parity, relationship status or whether a woman reporting 
losing a child during a prior pregnancy (table 2). 
Women who reported delivering at home were less likely 
to have education at or beyond the primary level, a 
result that had borderline statistical significance 
( p=0.057). </p>

<p>In a 1-year period between April 2008 and March 
2009, 949 live births occurred in the study hospital. In 
the same period, 82 stillbirths were recorded, 8% of 
total births (n=1031). The rate of caesarean delivery at 
the hospital was 35.5% (n=337). The stillbirth rate in 
the caesarean subset was 12.4%. Common indications 
for caesarean delivery included cephalopelvic dispropor-
tion (50%), previous caesarean delivery (12.7%), ante-
partum haemorrhage due to placenta previa or 
placental abruption (10.2%), eclampsia (8.5%), breech 
presentation (5.0%) and ruptured uterus (4.2%). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
In structured interviews conducted in villages proximate 
to a hospital in Nimba County, Liberia, only one in six 
women reported delivering their last child in a hospital, 
that is, 83.2% of women reported their last delivery to 
have been at home. Of women delivering at a regional 
hospital, 35.5% were by caesarean section and 8% were 
stillborn. These metrics indicate severe underutilisation 
of timely, supervised, institutional birthing services 
among women in north-central Liberia. Participants 
reported financial and transportation barriers to seeking 
care, as well as cultural traditions including the practice 
of delivery under the care of a TM. (Traditional midwife 
is the term used in Liberia, analogous to the traditional 
birth attendant in other nations.) Further, more than 
half of women who delivered their last child in a hos-
pital did do so only after experiencing complications in 
labour at home. This was validated by the hospital's high 
caesarean section rate. These findings of underutilisa-
tion of the formal health sector are similar to those of a 
2011 study in the same region of Liberia that high-
lighted the impact of geographic and financial barriers, 
perceptions of quality in the formal and informal health-
care systems, and prevailing care by informal health 
workers, including TM, on the healthcare utilisation. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>Table 2 Comparison of characteristics of rural Liberian 
women who reported delivering their last child at home or 
in hospital, excluding nulliparous women (n=280) </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Home 
Hospital </p>

<p>p 
Value </p>

<p>Age, mean years (SD) 
30.9 (7.3) 29.6 (8.3) 0.29 
Parity, mean no. (SD) 
4.9 (2.9) 4.5 (3.2) 0.32 
Education level, no. (%) 
None 
139 (59.9) 20 (43.5) 0.057 
Some primary 
84 (36.2) 22 (47.8) 
Completed primary or 
greater </p>

<p>9 (3.9) 
4 (8.7) </p>

<p>Relationship status, no. (%) 
Married 
168 (72.1) 33 (70.2) 0.86 
Unmarried 
65 (27.9) 14 (29.8) 
Lost a child during prior 
pregnancy, no. (%) 
Yes 
86 (36.9) 18 (38.3) 0.87 
No 
147 (63.1) 29 (61.7) </p>

<p>Table 1 Interview responses of women (n=307)* 
interviewed in their homes in rural northern Liberia in 2010 </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Value </p>

<p>Age,* mean years (SD) 
30.5 (7.5) 
Parity,* mean no. (SD) 
4.8 (3.0) 
Education level, no. (%) 
No formal education 
174 (57.1) 
Some primary 
114 (37.4) 
Completed primary or greater 
17 (5.6) 
Relationship status, no. (%) 
Married 
223 (72.6) 
Unmarried 
84 (27.4) 
Lost a child during prior pregnancy, no. (%) 
Yes 
113 (37.0) 
No 
192 (63.0) 
Site of delivery in immediate prior pregnancy, 
no. (%) † 
Hospital 
47 (16.8) 
Home with traditional midwife (TM) 
210 (75.0) 
Home without TM 
23 (8.2) 
Why did you choose to deliver your child in this 
place? † 
Home, no. (%) 
'Cost' or 'Difficulty with transport' 
69 (31.5) 
'Quick onset of labour' 
67 (30.6) 
'Family tradition' or 'Religion' 
37 (16.9) 
'TM is safe' 
37 (16.9) 
'Conflict' or 'Flooding' 
8 (3.7) 
Hospital, no. (%) 
'Labour complications at home' 
26 (57.8) 
'Hospital nearby' 
6 (13.3) 
'Antenatal referral' 
5 (11.1) 
'Hospital is safer' 
5 (11.1) 
'Previous caesarean delivery' 
3 (6.7) </p>

<p>*Totals may not add to 307 due to missing values. 280 
respondents reported age. 305 respondents reported parity. 
 †N=280 excluding nulliparous women. </p>

<p>Gartland MG, Taryor VD, Norman AM, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e001602. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001602 </p>



<p>Facility delivery and caesarean section in north-central Liberia </p>

<p>The rates of hospital delivery in our study were signifi-
cantly lower than the national (46.3%) and county 
(32.6%) statistics reported in 2007 for skilled attendance 
at delivery, a related metric used by the WHO and 
Liberia Ministry of Health to assess women's access to 
safe maternal health services. 
4 12 Skilled attendance 
differs from facility delivery in the requirement of super-
vision of childbirth by a physician, nurse, trained 
midwife or physician's assistant. 
11 This is deemed vital to 
the early recognition of life-threatening intrapartum 
complications, and their effective management. </p>

<p>5 14 </p>

<p>While hospital delivery is a pre-requisite for skilled 
attendance in Liberia where home deliveries are rarely 
supervised by a professional in the above cadres, it is not 
necessarily true that all hospital deliveries have the 
appropriate personnel present. Therefore, our mea-
sured rates of facility delivery potentially overestimate 
the true figure for safe delivery under skilled attendance 
among the participants. 
The definition for skilled attendants notably excludes 
TM because they do not have access to resources for 
medical or surgical management of labour. 
4 Women 
under TM care who have conditions such as dystocia, 
eclampsia or bleeding are exceedingly vulnerable. In 
addition, TM have limited training in the recognition of 
complications, and in the study community there were 
no formal mechanisms for timely referral if complica-
tions arose. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>When we compared women who delivered their last 
child at home to those who delivered in a hospital, only 
education differed; home-delivered women were more 
likely to report having no formal education. Previous 
studies have demonstrated the alarming inequalities in 
access to maternal healthcare based on education levels, 
as well as wealth, rural venue and religion. </p>

<p>7 13 22 </p>

<p>In our review of hospital medical and operating room 
records we found that caesarean delivery accounted for 
more than a third of all deliveries, though there were 
relatively few births at the facility in the study period. 
The hospital serves a region of approximately 250 000 
people where nearly 10 000 births were expected annu-
ally. 
12 In addition it is the only facility within a 35 km 
radius with capacity to provide caesarean delivery 
service. While smaller health facilities in the region 
equipped to offer assisted vaginal delivery may provide 
services in a portion of births in the catchment area, the 
delivery number at the study site is still very low and 
reflects the trend towards home delivery found in 
interviews. 
In addition, the high rate of caesarean delivery may 
stem from referral of complicated cases from other facil-
ities and late presentation after attempted home deliv-
ery. 
23 24 Prolonged labour, antepartum haemorrhage 
and ruptured uterus were the common antecedents to 
caesarean delivery. 
25 Unfortunately, we were not able to 
ascertain the duration of labour, location where labour 
was initiated and delays in accessing care. Prior research 
in the region using the 'three-delays' model found </p>

<p>significant delays at all three stages-deciding to seek 
care, reaching a health facility and receiving needed 
care at the facility. 
10 23 These prior studies similarly high-
lighted the importance of family and TM influence on 
timely access to care. 
Caesarean delivery is cited as a life-saving component 
of 
Comprehensive 
Emergency 
Obstetric 
Care 
(EmOC). 
16 Criteria for Comprehensive EmOC include 
24 h caesarean delivery and blood transfusion availabil-
ity. 
26 Notably, these standards were not met by this 
regional hospital. Typical obstacles to the delivery of 
Comprehensive EmOC in the region include human 
resource shortages, intermittent electricity supplied 
exclusively by generator, and scarcity of donated blood 
that often necessitates donations from the patient's 
family at the time of the operation. 
Limitations of our study included non-randomised 
sampling of participants in community interviews. In fact, 
convenience recruitment in proximate communities with 
active hospital outreach programmes in maternal and 
child health may have over-represented 'health-seekers' 
and women with access to hospital services, or skewed the 
sample population in unknown ways by excluding women 
who were not at home when interviewers visited. 
Unfortunately we do not have data from communities 
without hospital outreach programmes for comparison. 
In addition, refusal to participate among women 
approached was not documented consistently by survey 
administrators so we are unable to accurately report on 
this figure. Finally, the hospital-based portion of our 
study was limited by poor medical record keeping and 
organisation, and missing data, particularly pertaining to 
'history of present illness', a key timeline necessary to 
evaluate the dynamic causes of birth complications in the 
context of home and facility delivery. 
In summary, the combination of community and facil-
ity data enabled us to identify deficiencies in the utilisa-
tion of maternal health services in north-central Liberia. 
Many women in need of such services did not access 
them, even if care was available locally. Additionally, 
there was a high rate of serious complications among 
women presenting to the hospital for caesarean delivery. 
Greater outreach and referral services as well as educa-
tion among women and TM are needed to improve 
timely utilisation of care. Our study also highlights the 
importance of performing local assessments of maternal 
health services in order to accurately measure commu-
nity needs that otherwise may be underestimated by 
national surveys. These geographically focused evalua-
tions are critical to inform policy and programmatic 
interventions at the community level. </p>

<p>Funding This paper was funded by Office of the Dean, Vanderbilt University 
School of Medicine (Emphasis Program) and the Vanderbilt Institute for 
Global Health. </p>

<p>Contributorship All authors were involved in the design of the study, the 
analysis of data and the writing and editing of this paper. All of them had full 
access to all the data in the study and can take responsibility for the integrity </p>



<p>Gartland MG, Taryor VD, Norman AM, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e001602. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001602 </p>

<p>Facility delivery and caesarean section in north-central Liberia </p>

<p>of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis and made important 
intellectual contributions to the content and approved the final version. MGG 
conducted interviews with participants and wrote the first draft of the paper </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement There are no additional unpublished data available. </p>



<p>Gartland MG, Taryor VD, Norman AM, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e001602. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001602 </p>



<p>Facility delivery and caesarean section in north-central Liberia </p>

</text></tei>