<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3619072" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Human papillomavirus 16 infection has been proven to be associated with oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinomas 
(SCCs) and is probably the main reason of the reported increase in the incidence. The role of high-risk (HR) HPV for carcinogenesis 
of other sites in the head and neck awaits confirmation. With the aim to evaluate the prevalence of HPV infection and the reliability 
of different diagnostic tools in SCCs of different sites, 109 consecutive untreated head and neck SCCs were enroled, and fresh 
tumour samples collected. </p>

<p>Methods: Human papillomavirus DNA was detected by Digene Hybrid Capture 2 (HC2). Human papillomavirus E6 and E7 mRNA 
were detected by NucliSENS EasyQ HPVv1. P16 expression was evaluated by immunohistochemistry. </p>

<p>Results: In all, 12.84% of cases were infected by HR genotypes and 1.84% by low-risk genotypes. Human papillomavirus 
16 accounted for 87% of HR infections. The overall agreement between DNA and RNA detection is 99.1%. Although p16 
expression clearly correlates with HPV infection (P ¼ 0.0051), the inter-rater agreement is poor (k ¼ 0.27). The oropharynx showed 
the highest HR HPV infection rate (47.6%) and was also the only site in which p16 immunohistochemistry revealed to be a fair, 
but not excellent, diagnostic assay (k ¼ 0.61). </p>

<p>Conclusion: The prognostic role of HR HPV infection in oropharyngeal oncology, with its potential clinical applications, 
underscores the need for a consensus on the most appropriate detection methods. The present results suggest that viral 
mRNA detection could be the standard for fresh samples, whereas DNA detection could be routinely used in formalin-fixed, 
paraffin-embedded samples. </p>

<p>*Correspondence: Dr F Bussu; E-mail: francescobussu@yahoo.it </p>

<p>Received 10 October 2012; revised 14 January 2013; accepted 17 January 2013; published online 12 February 2013 </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Cancer Research UK. All rights reserved 0007 -0920/13 </p>

<p>FULL PAPER </p>

<p>Keywords: HPV infection; head and neck carcinogenesis; diagnostic assay; molecular characterisation; p16 immunohistochemistry. </p>

<p>British Journal of Cancer (2013) 108, 1157-1162 | doi: 10.1038/bjc.2013.55 </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.55 
1157 </p>

<p>More than 50 000 cases of head and neck cancer, mostly squamous 
cell carcinomas (head and neck SCCs (HNSCCs)), are estimated to 
have occurred in the United States in 2011, causing about 13 000 
deaths (Siegel et al, 2011). Head and neck squamous cell 
carcinomas grossly accounts for 3.5% of all malignant tumours 
in the United States (Siegel et al, 2011), although in other parts of 
the world, such as India, Southeast Asia and Brazil, these tumours 
are much more prevalent (Shah and Lydiatt, 1995). 
The best established risk factors are cigarette smoking and 
alcohol abuse (Shah and Patel, 2003; De Vita et al, 2008), although 
infection with high-risk (HR) HPV, whose role in carcinogenesis of 
the uterine cervix has been extensively studied (De Vita et al, 
2008), is another emerging risk factor. The emergence of HR 
HPV infection underlies the marked increase in oropharyngeal 
SCC incidence (Hammarstedt et al, 2006; Chaturvedi et al, 
2011), especially in the young (Sturgis and Cinciripini, 2007). 
Nevertheless, HNSCCs are an extremely heterogeneous group of 
tumours both from a molecular (Huang et al, 2002; Bosch et al, 
2004) and a clinical point of view (Shah and Patel, 2003). The main 
clinical heterogeneity factor is the site of origin, which correlates 
with specific risk factors, symptoms, stage at diagnosis, tendency to 
local and distant metastasis, chemo-and radiosensitivity and 
ultimately prognosis (Shah and Patel, 2003; De Vita et al, 2008). In 
this context, the role of HR HPV in oropharyngeal carcinogenesis 
is established, as HPV infection predicts chemo-radiosensitivity 
and better prognosis (Gillison et al, 2000; Gillison, 2009; Ang et al, 
2010); on the other hand, evidence of its significance in other head 
and neck sites is definitely lacking (Gillison et al, 2000). 
The increasing epidemiologic role of HPV and its value as a 
prognostic marker have raised great interest given their potential 
clinical implications in head and neck oncology, stimulating several 
studies in the past 10 years. Most of the acquired data on HPV-
driven carcinogenesis comes from the uterine cervix model, 
although its validity in head and neck remains to be confirmed. 
For example, studies on the cervix model assigned the most 
significant role in the induction of malignant transformation to the 
E6 and E7 genes and their respective proteins (Munger et al, 1989; 
McDougall, 1994), showing that E7 interacts with and degrades 
RB, which then releases the transcription factor E2F from RB 
inhibition and upregulates p16 </p>

<p>INK4A </p>

<p>, providing the molecular basis 
for the typical p16 overexpression in cervical SCC (Dyson et al, 
1989; Kiyono et al, 1998). Hence, detection of p16 overexpression 
by immunohistochemistry (IHC) has been proposed as a surrogate 
for HPV detection in the head and neck. 
This study aims primarily to assess the prevalence of HPV 
infection in SCCs at different sites in the head and neck, and to deter-
mine the reliability of p16 immunohistochemistry as a diagnostic tool 
for HPV infection in head and neck oncology, in comparison with 
mRNA detection, which can be considered the gold standard. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patient characteristics. From March 2009 to October 2010, 109 
patients affected by primary, previously untreated, HNSCC, arising 
from hypopharynx, oropharynx, oral cavity and larynx, were enroled 
in this study. Patients were evaluated by the multidisciplinary head 
and neck tumour board of the Policlinico Agostino Gemelli, 
Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore (Rome, Italy) (Table 1). 
Following squamous histology confirmation, completion 
of the diagnosis and staging according to the TNM classification 
(Edge et al, 2010) with a strict and careful clinicoradiological 
assessment of the site and subsite of origin (Table 1), and treatment 
planning, patients signed an informed consent for their participa-
tion in this study, which had been previously approved by the 
ethical committee. </p>

<p>HPV detection. Fresh tumour samples were obtained by biopsy 
and immediately stored as RNA at À 80 1C until tested. Each 
sample was used for DNA and RNA detection. Nucleic acids' </p>

<p>Table 1. Descriptive statistics of the main variables concerning patients 
and tumour parameters </p>

<p>Characteristic 
109 patients </p>

<p>Age at diagnosis </p>

<p>Median 
63 
Range 
32-84 </p>

<p>Follow-up period (months) </p>

<p>Median 
13 
Range 
3-32 </p>

<p>Pack-years of cigarette smoking </p>

<p>Median 
29 
Range 
0-88 </p>

<p>Sex, no. (%) </p>

<p>Male 
88 (80.73%) 
Female 
21 (19.27%) </p>

<p>Site of origin, 
no. (%) </p>

<p>Subsite, no. (%) </p>

<p>Hypopharynx 
9 (8.26%) 
Post-cricoid region 3 (2.75%) 
Pyriform sinus 6 (5.5%) 
Larynx 
46 (42.2%) 
Glottic 18 (16.51%) 
Supraglottic 15 (13.76%) 
Transglottic 12 (11.01%) 
Subglottic 1 (0.92%) 
Oral cavity 
33 (30.28%) 
Cheek 3 (2.75%) 
Floor of mouth 8 (7.34%) 
Hard palate 4 (3.67%) 
Mobile tongue 15 (13.76%) 
Retromolar trigone 3 (2.75%) 
Oropharynx 
21 (19.27%) 
Base of tongue 6 (5.5%) 
Posterior wall 1 (0.92%) 
Soft palate 1 (0.92%) 
Tonsil 13 (11.93%) </p>

<p>Primarytreatment, no. (%) </p>

<p>Surgical 
61 (57.55%) 
Radiochemotherapy 
45 (42.45%) </p>

<p>AJCC stage, no. (%) </p>

<p>I 
8 (7.34%) 
II 
21 (19.27%) 
III 
20 (18.35%) 
IV 
IVa 53 (48.62%), IVb 5 (4.59%), IVc 2 (1.83%) </p>

<p>cT classification, no.(%) </p>

<p>T1 
12 (11.01%) 
T2 
32 (29.36%) 
T3 
22 (20.18%) 
T4a 
43 (39.45%) </p>

<p>cN classification, no.(%) </p>

<p>N0 
61 (55.96%) 
N1 
10 (9.17%) 
N2a 
1 (0.92%) 
N2b 
18 (16.51%) 
N2c 
14 (12.84%) 
N3 
5 (4.59%) </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
HPV detection in head and neck SCC </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.55 </p>

<p>extraction from tissues was performed with the NucliSens 
easyMAG platform (BioMérieux, Rome, Italy), according to the 
manufacturer's instructions. Human papillomavirus DNA detec-
tion was performed with the Digene Hybrid Capture 2 (HC2) assay 
(Qiagen Inc., Valencia, CA, USA), which allows the detection of 18 
HPV genotypes, and can differentiate between HR HPV (types 16, 
18, 31, 33, 35, 39, 45, 51, 52, 58, 59 and 68) and low-risk (LR) HPV 
(types 6, 11, 42, 43 and 44), but does not allow the identification of 
specific genotypes. 
As for RNA, samples were analysed for HPV E6 and E7 mRNA 
by NucliSENS EasyQ HPV v.1 test (BioMérieux, Rome, Italy), 
based on the NASBA technique. It specifically detects the E6/E7 
mRNA of five HR HPV types (HPV16/18/31/33/45); the other HR 
and LR genotypes are not detectable with this assay. Briefly, three 
premixes were made by the reconstitution of reagent spheres in the 
reagent diluent, followed by the addition of primer/molecular 
beacon mixes (either U1A/HPV16, HPV18/31 or HPV33/45). 
A measure of 10 ml of premix were distributed to each well, 
followed by 5 ml sample, and incubated for 4 min at 65 1C and 
2 min at 41 1C. The reaction was started by the addition of enzymes 
and measured in real time using the EasyQ analyser 
at 41 1C. Data analysis was performed using the <rs type="software">EasyQ Director</rs> 
software. </p>

<p>P16 immunohistochemistry. Formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded 
(FFPE) tumour specimens were evaluated for p16 expression with 
a monoclonal antibody (clone E6H4; CINtec p16INK4a Histology 
Kit; Mtm-Laboratories, Heidelberg, Germany).Tissue sections were 
cut at 2 to 4 mm and deparaffinised. Cervical cancer sections known 
to be HPV positive were used as a positive control and omission of 
primary antibody was used as a negative control. After antigen 
unmasking for 20±1 min at 95 to 99 1C in Tris buffer, pH 9.0, 
slides were allowed to cool down in the solution for 20 ± 1 min to 
room temperature. Endogenous peroxidase blocking was per-
formed in 3% hydrogen peroxide for 5 ± 1 min. Slides were then 
stained with the primary antibody (p16ink4a ready to use for 
40 ± 1 min at room temperature) and then with the visualisation 
reagent provided with the kit for 30±1 min at room temperature. </p>

<p>After development with substrate-chromogen solution (DAB; 
Mtm-Laboratories, Heidelberg, Germany) for 10 ± 1 min, p16-
stained slides were finally counterstained with haematoxylin 
(Dako) (Negri et al, 2008). Positive p16 expression was defined 
as a strong and diffuse nuclear and cytoplasmic staining in 70% or 
more of the tumour cells. Immunohistochemical evaluation was 
carried out by three histopathologists in independent readings 
(VGV, GFZ and GR). Each reader was 'blinded' to the results 
obtained for HPV infection and to the results obtained by the other 
histopathologists. Cases that varied among readers were re-
evaluated to determine a consensus. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Statistical analysis was performed using 
the <rs id="software-0" type="software">JMP</rs> software, release <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">7.0.1</rs>, from the <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs> (Cary, 
NC, USA). 
Correlation between p16 IHC and HPV status itself was 
evaluated by w 
2 . 
The agreement among detection methods was quantified by 
calculating k, which is a measure of agreement and takes on the 
value zero if there is no more agreement between test and outcome 
than can be expected on the basis of chance. It is considered that 
k values o0.4 represent poor agreement, values between 0.4 and 
0.75 fair to good agreement and values 40.75 excellent agreement. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Patient and tumour characteristics are shown in Table 1. None of 
the patients who accepted to participate in this study was lost at 
follow-up. 
The most frequent site of origin of the SCC was the larynx (42%), 
followed by oral cavity (30%) and oropharynx (19%), whereas the 
most frequent subsite was the glottis. A marked prevalence of 
advanced stages was observed (stages III and IV together account for 
473% of the cases in our series). In particular, 440% of our patients 
had clinically positive lymph nodes at diagnosis. These results are in 
agreement with the epidemiology of HNSCC in Italy (Bray et al, 
2002; Ferlay et al, 2010). 
DNA of LR HPV genotypes was found only in 2 out of 109 cases 
(1.8%), whereas DNA of HR genotypes was detected in 13 cases 
(12%), with one case of HR and LR co-infection. Human 
papillomavirus mRNA detection demonstrated that 12 out of 14 
HR HPV cases were due to HPV 16. Interestingly, the two 
remaining HR HPV referred to tumours localising outside the 
oropharynx (in the oral cavity and glottic larynx, respectively; 
Table 2), and were identified as HPV18 and 45. In any case, 
HPV16 was by far the most frequent genotype detected and the 
only one detected in the tonsil, base of the tongue and supraglottic 
larynx, which were in turn the most frequently positive subsites. In 
fact, most HR-positive cases were in the oropharynx (10 out of 14), 
in which the overall prevalence of HR HPV infection was 47.6%; 
conversely, HR HPV infection rate did not reach 5% in the present 
series (4/88) when all other head and neck sites were pooled 
together. Positivity to p16 immunostaining was markedly more 
frequent in the whole series (25%) and, in contrast to HPV 
infection, it was commonly recorded outside the oropharynx 
(19/88: 21.6%). 
Many authors (Braakhuis et al, 2004; Shi et al, 2009; Schlecht 
et al, 2011) consider mRNA detection performed on fresh samples 
to be the most reliable diagnostic test for HR HPV infection in the 
cervix and also in the head and neck; for this reason, we decided to 
define mRNA detection as the standard when assessing the value of 
the other detection methods by the estimation of k. The overall 
agreement between the HPV genomic DNA detection results and 
the mRNA detection was close to 100% (k ¼ 0.96), being absolute 
in all sites except the glottic larynx, where the Digene test missed 
an unexpected positivity for the mRNA of HPV45, associated with </p>

<p>Table 1. ( Continued ) </p>

<p>Characteristic 
109 patients </p>

<p>Grading, no.(%) </p>

<p>G1 
3 (2.75%) 
G2 
63 (57.8%) 
G3 
43 (39.45%) </p>

<p>HPV DNA, no.(%) </p>

<p>Negative 
95 (87.16%) 
High-risk HPV 
12 (11.01%) 
High and low risk 
1 (0.92%) 
Low risk 
1 (0.92%) </p>

<p>High-risk HPV RNA, no.(%) </p>

<p>Negative 
95 (87.16%) 
HPV16 
12 (11.01%) 
HPV18 
1 (0.92%) 
HPV45 
1 (0.92%) </p>

<p>P16 immunostaining </p>

<p>Positive 
21 (24.77%) 
Negative 
88 (75.23%) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: AJCC ¼ American Joint Committee on Cancer; cN ¼ clinical N; 
cT ¼ clinical T; HPV ¼ human papillomavirus. </p>

<p>HPV detection in head and neck SCC 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.55 </p>

<p>
HNSCC in only a few reports (Lindel et al, 2001). On the other 
hand, even though the correlation between p16 IHC and HPV 
status itself was clear (P ¼ 0.0051 at w </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>), when p16 was evaluated as 
a diagnostic test, the agreement rate was poor (k ¼ 0.27) with a 
0.23 error rate. The oropharynx, where the higher rate of HR HPV 
infection was observed (47.6%), was also the only site in which the 
agreement rate of p16 IHC (k ¼ 0.61) was fair (Table 2). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The increasing epidemiologic role of HPV and its value as 
prognostic marker in head and neck oncology has stimulated a 
growing number of studies in the past 10 years; nevertheless, some 
critical issues, such as the real prevalence of HR HPV infection in 
sites outside the oropharynx and the methods of choice to diagnose 
the infection itself in HNSCC, have not yet been definitely defined. 
The results of this study confirm the relevance of HPV infection 
as a risk factor for oropharyngeal SCC (Gillison et al, 2000; 
Gillison, 2009). However, the prevalence of HPV infection in SCC 
of other head and neck sites was found definitely lower than what 
was reported in recent studies (Sethi et al, 2011; Heath et al, 2012). 
Hence, the role of HPV as a risk factor for non-oropharyngeal sites 
remains to be fully evaluated, appearing certainly less relevant. The 
subsite with the highest prevalence (13.3%) outside the oropharynx 
was the supraglottic larynx, whose marginal region is contiguous 
with the oropharynx. This may explain the HR HPV infection rate 
reported in some studies on laryngeal SCCs (Almadori et al, 2001, 
2002). Notably, our total (13%) and oropharyngeal (47.6%) 
positivity rates are very close to those from a recent study 
evaluating the overall genetic pattern of HNSCCs (Stransky et al, 
2011) in a different population from a different geographic area 
(North America). 
Human papillomavirus 16 mRNA was detected in about 86% of 
all HPV-positive samples, and in 100% of the positive samples 
from the oropharynx and the supraglottic larynx (Table 2). This 
finding confirms also in the Italian population that only HPV16 
can be classified at present as cancer causing in oropharyngeal </p>

<p>tissues (Bouvard et al, 2009). Notably, the other HPV genotypes 
were detected in non-oropharyngeal subsites: in the floor of the 
mouth (HPV18) and the glottic larynx (HPV45). However, an 
effective and conclusive evaluation of the putative association of 
specific HPV genotypes with different sites in head and neck 
requires a wider study with more homogeneous series according to 
the site of origin of the SCCs. 
Concern has been expressed that the hypersensitivity of viral 
genomic DNA detection methods (Braakhuis et al, 2004; Kreimer 
et al, 2005) would increase the risk of identifying contaminant 
HPV, leading to a high number of false positives. In this study, 
viral genomic DNA detection shows 100% specificity (no false-
positive cases) when compared with the mRNA detection test. In 
addition, only the HPV45-positive case (sensitivity: 93%) was not 
detected by the genomic DNA technique used, which may 
therefore be considered a perfect surrogate of HPV16 mRNA 
detection in HNSCC samples. Such reliability of genomic DNA 
HPV-detecting techniques in HNSCCs seems confirmed also by 
the recent influential paper of Stransky and co-workers (2011), 
performing an accurate mutational profiling. 
Some authors (Smeets et al, 2007; Marur et al, 2010; El-Naggar 
and Westra, 2011; Harris et al, 2011) expressed concerns on the use 
of p16 IHC as a surrogate marker for the HPV infection in the 
head and neck. However, several groups, probably assuming that 
data acquired from the uterine cervix could be easily translated in 
other models, have considered for a long time p16 expression as 
equivalent to HPV infection in all head and neck sites, even those 
outside the oropharynx (Lassen et al, 2011), where the prevalence 
of proved HR HPV infection was markedly lower (Gillison et al, 
2000; Stransky et al, 2011). These assumptions may have detracted 
from a thorough evaluation of diagnostic tools for HPV in head 
and neck oncology and may have led to an overestimation of the 
HPV infection relevance in head and neck carcinogenesis 
(Kaminagakura et al, 2011; Lassen et al, 2011). A recent study 
(Schlecht et al, 2011) compared p16 IHC with in situ hybridisation 
and concluded that the former is a better surrogate for HPV 
mRNA detection, despite the reported sensitivity of 69% in the 
oropharynx and only 52% in the head and neck as a whole. The 
overall low specificity of p16 IHC for the diagnosis of HR HPV </p>

<p>Table 2. Results of the different detection methods for HPV infection in our series </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Site of origin, no. </p>

<p>HPV status 
(high-risk 
HPV RNA), 
no. (%) </p>

<p>High-risk 
HPV DNA, 
no. (j) </p>

<p>P16 
over-
expression (j) </p>

<p>Subsite of 
origin, no. </p>

<p>HPV RNA 
positivity 
(genotype), % </p>

<p>HPV DNA 
positivity 
(high vs 
low risk), % </p>

<p>P16 IHC 
positivity, % </p>

<p>Hypopharynx, 9 
0 
0 
1 
Post-cricoid region, 3 
0 
0 
0 
Pyriform sinus, 6 
0 
0 
1, 17% </p>

<p>Larynx, 46 
3 (6.5%) 
2 (0.79) 
8 (0.1) 
Glottic, 18 
1 (HPV45), 5% 
0 
4, 22% 
Supraglottic, 15 
2 (HPV16), 13.3% 
2 (high risk), 13.3% 
4, 27% 
Transglottic, 12 
0 
0 
0 
Subglottic, 1 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>Oral cavity, 33 
1 (3%) 
1 (1) 
10 ( À 0.058) 
Cheek, 3 
0 
0 
0 
Floor of mouth, 8 
1 (HPV18), 12.5% 1(low þ high risk), 12.5% 
0 
Hard palate, 4 
0 
0 
2, 50% 
Mobile tongue, 15 
0 
1 (low risk), 6% 
8, 53% 
Retromolar trigone, 3 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>Oropharynx, 21 
10 (47.6%) 
10 (1) 
8 (0.61) 
Base of tongue, 6 
3 (HPV16), 50% 
3 (high risk), 50% 
2, 33% 
Posterior wall, 1 
0 
0 
0 
Soft palate, 1 
0 
0 
0 
Tonsil, 13 
7 (HPV16), 54% 
7 (high risk), 54% 
6, 46% </p>

<p>Abbreviations: HPV ¼ human papillomavirus. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>In the left part of the table the agreement (j) of Digene (HPV DNA) and p16 IHC with the reference method (RNA), by site of origin is shown. In the right part, the results of the different 
detection methods are shown in detail for each subsite, evidencing that HPV16 is by far the most frequent genotype (12 out of 14 high-risk cases), and the only one in the oropharynx, and that 
most positive cases (10 out of 14) arose from the tonsil and from the base of the tongue. The only high-risk case missed by Digene was in the glottic larynx and was positive for HPV45 RNA. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
HPV detection in head and neck SCC </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.55 </p>

<p>infection in the present series is striking and is certainly very 
different to what was observed in the cervix, in which virtually all 
the SCCs are associated with HR HPV and p16 overexpression. 
In the head and neck, where causative factors, clinical behaviours 
and molecular profiles, are definitely more heterogeneous 
(Braakhuis et al, 2004; Agrawal et al, 2011; Stransky et al, 2011), 
p16 overexpression may derive from different mechanisms than 
HR HPV infection (El-Naggar and Westra, 2011), especially in 
mobile tongue SCC (53% of positivity without any demonstration 
of HR HPV infection in the present series). The present results 
undermine the usefulness of p16 as a diagnostic surrogate for HPV 
infection in sites outside the oropharynx. In the oropharynx, p16 
overexpression is associated with HPV infection, and agreement 
can be considered fair (k ¼ 0.61) but not excellent. A recent work 
demonstrated a low diagnostic value for p16 immunohistochem-
istry in oropharyngeal SCCs arising outside tonsils and base of 
tongue (Marklund et al, 2012). In our opinion, even in the 
oropharynx, there is no reason to prefer a surrogate, such as p16 
IHC, to more reliable and direct diagnostic methods based on HPV 
nucleic acid detection, which are objective, as they do not require 
the reading of a trained histopathologist, and are becoming less 
expensive and widely available in the microbiology departments all 
over the world. Another option for the diagnosis of HPV infection 
in FFPE samples could be the algorithm proposed by Smeets et al 
(2007)), involving both p16 immunohistochemistry and GP5 þ / 
6 þ PCR. 
One of the main issues of head and neck oncology is that, 
despite the multiplicity of clinical prognosticators, the only 
consistent clinical predictors for disease control and disease-
specific survival of SCCs are T and, to a greater extent, N (Spector 
et al, 2001; Franchin et al, 2003; Licitra et al, 2003; Shah and Patel, 
2003), and the stratification of patients remains often inadequate. 
This is probably due, in spite of the histological homogeneity (most 
head and neck malignancies are SCC), to the extreme biological 
heterogeneity, and contributes to a lack of consistency in treatment 
planning. The molecular characterisation is an attempt to define 
homogeneous groups of patients for prognosis as well as for 
responsiveness to treatments (Almadori et al, 2005). The growing 
body of evidence about the prognostic role of HR HPV infection in 
oropharyngeal oncology (Gillison et al, 2000; Kumar et al, 2008; 
Worden et al, 2008; Gillison, 2009; Ang et al, 2010), which is 
associated with a better prognosis and an increased radio-
sensitivity, suggests that it may be a useful molecular marker to 
be integrated in the clinical management of oropharyngeal SCCs. 
Nevertheless, the inconsistency of detection methods for the most 
studied molecular markers in head and neck oncology, and for 
HPV infection in particular, is probably one of the main obstacles 
to their employment in the clinic (Almadori et al, 2008; Bussu et al, 
2012). For this reason, a consensus on the methods to be used for 
HR HPV detection in HNSCC is mandatory (Braakhuis et al, 
2009), and this study provides useful indications. In fact, mRNA 
detection, considered the gold standard for the diagnosis of HPV 
infection (Braakhuis et al, 2004; Shi et al, 2009; Schlecht et al, 
2011), could be performed when fresh tumour samples are 
available; on the other hand, genomic DNA-based methods, alone 
or combined with other assays in a diagnostic algorithm (Smeets 
et al, 2007), if the high specificity of new genomic DNA detecting 
techniques will be confirmed and validated, could be used on 
common FFPE samples. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Lawrence Banks and Miranda Thomas for the precious 
comments and suggestions. The study was funded exclusively with 
the research grant D1.1 by Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore. </p>



<p>HPV detection in head and neck SCC 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.55 </p>



<p>
This work is published under the standard license to publish agree-
ment. After 12 months the work will become freely available and 
the license terms will switch to a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
HPV detection in head and neck SCC </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.55 </p>

</text></tei>