<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3708637" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Background and objectives: One of the greatest challenges of health care systems at the dawn of the 
21st century is tuberculosis (TB). Drug resistant strains of TB are becoming a global public health 
risk. These strains commonly appear due to faulty therapies. Patients frequently stop treatment due 
to the toxicity of anti-tubercular treatment (ATT) drugs. Amla (Emblica officinalis) is a well-known 
Unani single drug. Jawarish amla is a Unani compound formulation which is commonly used to 
administer amla. This study tested the efficacy of Jawarish amla as an adjuvant to ATT drugs in 
reducing their side effects. </p>

<p>Methodology: Half of forty eligible pulmonary tuberculosis patients were randomly assigned to Test 
(Group B) and the other half to Control (Group A). Six grams of Jawarish amla twice daily was 
administered to the test group, and the same dosage of placebo was administered to control group 
along with directly observed treatment, short course chemotherapy (DOTS) for 60 days. Fisher exact 
test and paired t-test were applied for efficacy evaluation. Grading of symptoms was done to assess 
the toxicity of ATT and outcome of the adjuvant. </p>

<p>Results and discussion: Significant improvements were observed in almost all subjective and 
objective parameters. The exceptions were serum creatine and serum uric acid, which showed non-
significant slight elevations within normal limits. </p>

<p>Conclusion: Jawarish amla was ascertained to be safe and effective adjuvant of DOTS in combating the 
adverse effects of ATT drugs. </p>

<p>Published 2013-Feb-12; Corrected 2013-Mar-8 DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.5915/44-1-9988 </p>

<p>JIMA: Vol 44, 2012, Page 3 of 9 </p>

<p>Jawarish is derived from the Persian word gowarish, 
which means the granular semisolid that tends to 
stay longer in the gastrointestinal tract to enhance 
its digestive power and to potentiate liver. </p>

<p>Administration of Conventional DOTS and Adjuvant 
Regime 
Patient-friendly boxes were prepared. They 
consisted of two kinds of pouches for intensive or 
initial phase (12 blisters) and continuous phase (48 
blisters) of treatment. The pouches were 
administered for six or eight months at the 
patients' primary health centers (PHCs), which are 
the community health centers or nearby hospitals 
to which patients would come three times per 
week during the initial phase and once weekly 
during the continuous phase. PHCs are generally 
one to two kilometers from the patients' homes. 
During the initial two month intensive phase, 
patients swallowed the drugs under the 
supervision of the doctors and drug providers at 
the time of their thrice weekly visits. In the 
subsequent continuous phase of TB treatment, 
patients received seven-day blister packs at their 
PHCs, and, after taking the initial day's dose at the 
PHC, take the remaining six days of medicine on 
their own. 
All study participants from the various PHCs 
came to NIUM to receive the supply of adjuvant 
drug of either Jawarish amla or placebo, given in 
fifteen-day dose packs. Placebo of adjuvant drug 
was a sweet and morphologically similar, 
semisolid paste of similar color made by starch 
and sugar, given with the same dose of 6 grams, 
twice daily for two months. The adjuvant drug was 
taken 6 grams twice daily for two months after 
meal at their home. The Jawarish amla was 
prepared fresh and distributed at NIUM every two 
weeks to the patients during the two-month study 
period. 
All clinically suspected outpatients and 
inpatients of NIUM with history of cough for more </p>

<p>willing to give consent were excluded from the 
study. 
Ethical clearance was obtained from the 
institutional ethical committee for biomedical 
sciences at the National Institute of Unani 
Medicine (NIUM), Bangalore. There were 54 
enrolled patients. Of the fourteen cases who could 
not complete the study, one patient of the placebo 
group died without any known immediate cause. 
Ten others dropped out from the study within one 
month of the trial. Three patients of the test group 
who came from other places returned to their 
homes for completion of DOTS therapy as they 
were unable to in Bangalore until the completion 
of the DOTS regime. Fourteen cases did not 
complete the study. The remaining 40 patients 
were equally randomized and matched into Test 
Group B, DOTS plus adjuvant drug, and Control 
Group A, DOTS plus adjuvant placebo, by table of 
random numbers calculated by <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Stat Trek</rs>'s 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">Random Number Generator</rs>. </p>

<p>Selection Criteria for Adjuvant Drug 
The fruit amla is used for many ailments, 
particularly in South India. It is easily available 
and cheap. Retrolective survey of ancient 
literature and scientific studies revealed that amla 
(Emblica officinalis) is an antipyretic, hepato-
protective, appetizer, anti-tussive, nervine tonic, 
antihemorrhagic, anti-inflammatory drug 7 which 
strengthens the vital organs and stomach and 
enhances vision. It is also a good blood purifier 
which inhibits production of morbid balgham and 
sauda. Amla is a well known Unani single drug. 
Amla is the richest source of natural heat stable 
vitamin C. It is a powerful antioxidant and boosts 
immunity. It restores vitality and rejuvenates all 
of the vital organs. 9 
Jawarish amla is a sweet, semi-solid and 
granular unani compound formulation. Its chief 
ingredient is amla (Emblica officinalis), which 
is processed in cow milk and sugar. The term </p>

<p>Published 2013-Feb-12; Corrected 2013-Mar-8 DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.5915/44-1-9988 </p>

<p>JIMA: Vol 44, 2012, Page 4 of 9 </p>

<p>Table 1. Unani Medical Terms 
English and/or Latin 
Transliteration </p>

<p>‫أردو‬ </p>

<p>Indian Gooseberry (Phyllanthus emblica, syn. 
Emblica officinalis) </p>

<p>Amla </p>

<p>‫آملہ‬ </p>

<p>Sweet, semi-solid and granular preparation of 
Unani compound formulation 
Jawarish </p>

<p>‫وارش‬ ‫ج‬ </p>

<p>Gastric ulcer 
quruhul meda </p>

<p>‫عد‬ ‫م‬ ‫ال‬ ‫روح‬ ‫ق‬ 
‫ة‬ </p>

<p>Hyperacidity 
ḥumuzatul meda </p>

<p>‫مو‬ ‫ح‬ 
‫ۃ‬ ‫ض‬ 
‫عد‬ ‫م‬ ‫ال‬ 
‫ة‬ </p>

<p>Headache 
ṣuda </p>

<p>‫صداع‬ </p>

<p>Biliary Diarrhea 
ishāl-e ṣafravī </p>

<p>‫اسہال‬ 
‫ر‬ ‫ف‬ ‫ص‬ 
‫وی‬ </p>

<p>Pulmonary tuberculosis 
Diqq-e revi </p>

<p>‫وی‬ ‫ری‬ ‫دق‬ </p>

<p>Phlegm (humor) 
Balgham </p>

<p>‫م‬ ‫غ‬ ‫ل‬ ‫ب‬ </p>

<p>Black bile or melancholy (humor) 
Sauda </p>

<p>‫سودا‬ </p>

<p>than two weeks were investigated for pulmonary 
Koch's. Eligible patients were enrolled into the 
study with their written consent. All clinically 
suspect patients had chest x-rays (PA views) at 
NIUM. Two sputum samples (early morning and 
spot) were collected and sent to the designated 
microscopic centre, Leggere PHC, for acid-fast 
bacilli (AFB) examination as a routine diagnostic 
procedure. All diagnosed cases of pulmonary 
tuberculosis were advised to come for two week 
followup and adjuvant, Jawarish Amla or placebo, 
was prescribed, 6 grams twice daily for two 
months. 
In India, patients diagnosed with TB and 
prescribed DOTS are provided with DOTS 
treatment cards. Each card contains a unique TB 
number and enables tracking of associated lab </p>

<p>results and other case-related information. All 
patients' DOTS treatment cards were verified 
before enrolling in the study. The cards were 
photocopied and retained for authenticity. 
Investigations were carried out for diagnosis, 
exclusion and assessment of the objective 
parameters in various treatment groups. 
Investigations done in every case included 
complete hemogram, erythrocyte sedimentation 
rate, fasting blood glucose, serum creatinine, 
serum uric acid, alanine aminotransferase (ALT), 
aspartate aminotransferase (AST), serum alkaline 
phosphatase (ALP), serum total bilirubin, HIV I &amp; 
II, chest x-ray PA view and sputum smear test for 
AFB. 
Investigations for objective evaluation were 
assessed at zero days (before starting) and on </p>

<p>Published 2013-Feb-12; Corrected 2013-Mar-8 DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.5915/44-1-9988 </p>

<p>JIMA: Vol 44, 2012, Page 5 of 9 </p>

<p>60 th day (after completion) of the treatment at 
NIUM. Investigations for exclusion and diagnostic 
criteria were taken at pre-treatment assessment. 
Sputum for AFB was examined before treatment 
and after completion of initial phase and 
continuous phase in the patients' respective 
health centers at regular standard intervals as a 
protocol of DOTS. 
The study's parameters were subjective and 
objective. The subjective parameters were the 
adverse reactions the patients reported. Adverse 
reactions' severity was classified as minor, major 
and other. The minor reactions were nausea, 
vomiting, anorexia, abdominal pain, itching, rash, 
joint pain, and burning sensation in feet. The 
major reactions were jaundice, constipation, skin 
rash and flu syndrome. Other side effects were 
bitter taste, angina, diarrhea, sweating, insomnia 
and body pain. 10,11 Before starting treatment, each 
sign and symptom was recorded in the case report 
form for their grades at the initial visit. Any 
worsening or improvement in parameters was 
noted down at every follow-up visit until the end 
of the treatment. 
The 
liver 
function 
tests 
alanine 
aminotransferase 
(ALT), 
aspartate 
aminotransferase (AST), alkaline phosphatase and 
total bilirubin and the renal function tests serum 
creatinine and serum uric acid are objective 
parameters of DOTS toxicity. 4,12,13,14 These tests 
were administered for efficacy evaluation of 
adjuvant drug. 
After 60 days of the treatment, the pre-and 
post-treatment values of different parameters 
(subjective and objective) were analyzed and 
subjected to comparisons and statistical analysis 
to evaluate the efficacy of the treatment. Patient's 
compliance to treatment and improvements in 
adverse reactions to the ATT treatment and in 
signs and symptoms of tuberculosis were closely 
watched throughout the study. 
Paired t-test was applied to analyze the intra </p>

<p>group comparison of pre-and post-treatment 
variables, and unpaired t-test and Fisher exact test 
was applied to compare inter groups after 
treatment variables. <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.2</rs>, <rs id="software-5" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">15.0</rs>, <rs id="software-3" type="software">Stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">10.1</rs>, 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">MedCalc</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">9.0.1</rs>, <rs id="software-4" type="software">Systat</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">12.0</rs> and <rs id="software-6" type="software">R environment</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">ver.2.11.1</rs> were used for the analysis of the data. 
Results on continuous measurements are 
presented on mean ± SD (range) and results on 
categorical measurements were presented in 
Number (%). Significant figures were stated as p 
0.05. 
The safety of the treatment was assessed 
clinically at every visit of follow up and 
discontinuation of study medication was the 
prime tool of safety measure. However, there was 
no such consequence observed which had 
negative impact on our study. </p>

<p>Results 
Efficacy evaluation of Jawarish Amla on Subjective 
Parameters 
The minor side effects of the incidence of 
nausea (p&lt;0.001), vomiting (p&lt;0.001), abdominal 
pain (p&lt;0.001), itching (p&lt;0.001) and burning 
sensation in feet (p&lt;0.001) were significantly less 
in Group B than in Group A. The major side effects 
of the incidence of jaundice (p&lt;0.001) and skin 
rashes (p=0.003) were significantly less in Group B 
than in Group B. No patient in Group B developed 
flu during the trial. All patients in Group B who 
began the trial with flu were relieved of its 
symptoms during the trial. In Group A, 6 patients 
developed the symptoms of flu, and they persisted 
throughout the therapy. 
Other evaluated side effects included bitter 
taste, diarrhea, insomnia and body ache. Bitter 
taste was a very common problem among the 
studied patients and a common reason for them to 
abandon the DOTS regime. A significant (p&lt;0.001) 
reduction in bitter taste occurred in Group B. All 
patients in Group A developed diarrhea during the 
course of DOTS regime. All patients of Group B </p>

<p>Published 2013-Feb-12; Corrected 2013-Mar-8 DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.5915/44-1-9988 </p>

<p>JIMA: Vol 44, 2012, Page 6 of 9 </p>

<p>Table 2: Efficacy evaluation of Jawarish Amla on serum creatinine (mg/dl) (n=40) 
Group 
BT 
AT 
P value </p>

<p>Group A 
0.87±0.1 
0.94±0.12 
0.067 </p>

<p>Group B 
0.87±0.2 
0.88±0.12 
1.000 </p>

<p>P value 
0.943 
0.166 
-</p>

<p>Table 3. Efficacy evaluation of Jawarish Amla on serum uric acid (mg/dl) (n=40) 
Group 
BT 
AT 
P value </p>

<p>Group A 
5.35±1.4 
5.89±1. 5 
0.068 </p>

<p>Group B 
5.48±1.5 
5.75±1.6 
0.437 </p>

<p>P value 
0.770 
0.772 
-</p>

<p>Table 4: Efficacy evaluation of Jawarish Amla on liver function tests (n=40) 
Liver 
Function 
Test 
Group 
BT 
AT 
P value </p>

<p>ALT IU/L </p>

<p>Group A 
23.6±9 
33.2±12.6 
0.005 </p>

<p>Group B 
44.6±63.40 
23.8±8.2 
0.140 </p>

<p>P value 
0.152 
0.008 </p>

<p>AST IU/L </p>

<p>Group A 
22.30±11.20 
39.00±22.95 
0.001 </p>

<p>Group B 
46.55±72.67 
23.10±12.20 
0.162 </p>

<p>P value 
0.148 
0.009 
-</p>

<p>Alkaline 
Phosphatase 
IU/L </p>

<p>Group A 
125.40±33.33 
141.20±33.31 
0.069 </p>

<p>Group B 
158.95±73.16 
118.60±29.68 
0.036* </p>

<p>P value 
0.070+ 
0.029* 
-</p>

<p>Total 
Bilirubin 
mg/dl </p>

<p>Group A 
0.59±0.22 
0.84±0.25 
0.002** </p>

<p>Group B 
0.68±0.32 
0.67±0.45 
0.932 </p>

<p>P value 
0.295 
0.150 
-</p>

<p>who had diarrhea got significant (p&lt;0.001) relief. 
The incidence of insomnia (p&lt;0.001) and body ache 
(p&lt;0.04) was significantly less in Group B than in 
Group A. 
Effect on sweating and joint pain was not 
statistically significant in test group, although it 
was clinically effective. This may be because of the 
small sample size. 
In this study, the hepato-protective, 
gastrointestinal, skin and anti-inflammatory </p>

<p>effects of the test drug are demonstrated. No 
clinically significant side effects were observed in 
test group, and overall compliance to the 
treatment was found excellent. </p>

<p>Efficacy evaluation of Jawarish Amla on Objective 
Parameters 
Serum creatinine and serum uric acid levels 
after treatment were lower in Group B than in 
Group A, but the differences were not statistically </p>

<p>Published 2013-Feb-12; Corrected 2013-Mar-8 DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.5915/44-1-9988 </p>

<p>JIMA: Vol 44, 2012, Page 7 of 9 </p>

<p>significant. Pre-and post-treatment values were 
within normal ranges. (Tables 2 and 3) 
Over the course of treatment, average ALT 
decreased in Group B, but the decrease was not 
statistically significant. ALT in Group A showed a 
significant increase (p=0.005) pre-and post-
treatment. Group B's ALT values were significantly 
lower after treatment than those of Group A 
(p=0.008) (Table 4). 
Group A's AST values increased significantly 
pre-and post-treatment (p=0.001). The decrease in 
Group B's AST values was not statistically 
significant. Group B's AST values were 
significantly lower after treatment than those of 
Group A (p=0.009) (Table 4). 
Group A's alkaline phosphatase values did not 
increase significantly pre-and post-treatment. 
The decrease in Group B's alkaline phosphatase 
values was statistically significant (p=0.036). Group 
B's alkaline phosphatase values were significantly 
lower after treatment than those of Group A 
(p=0.029) (Table 4). 
Group A's total bilirubin values increased 
significantly pre-and post-treatment (p=0.002). 
The change in Group B's total bilirubin values was 
not statistically significant. Group B's total 
bilirubin values were not significantly lower after 
treatment than those of Group A (Table 4). </p>

<p>Discussion 
The significantly lower incidence of nausea 
(p&lt;0.001), abdominal pain (p&lt;0.001) and bitter 
taste (p&lt;0.001) may be due to the fact that Jawarish 
amla heals quruh-e meda (anti-peptic ulcer) and 
reduces humuzat-e meda (acidity). 8,15 Amla also has 
antispasmodic activity. 16 This may have 
contributed to the reduced abdominal pain. 
Likewise, Jawarish amla is anti-emetic, 17 and this 
may be the cause of the lower (p&lt;0.001) incidence 
of vomiting. The lower incidence of itching 
(p&lt;0.001*) and skin rashes (p=0.003) in Group B 
may be attributed to the blood purifying, 8 anti-</p>

<p>histaminic 16 and cooling and soothing 9 properties 
of Jawarish amla. These same cooling and soothing 
effects may have relived the symptom of burning 
sensation in feet (p&lt;0.001). 
Amla is a hepato-protective drug. 8,9 This may 
explain the reduced incidence of jaundice 
(p&lt;0.001) as a major adverse reaction in Group B. 
Likewise, the ALT (p=0.008), AST (p=0.009) and 
alkaline phosphatase (p=0.029) values in Group B 
after treatment were significantly lower than 
those of Group A. Even though the difference in 
total bilirubin values after treatment between the 
groups was not significant, Group A's values 
increased during the ATT (p=0.002) while Group 
B's did not. 
The reduction in flu-like syndrome in Group A 
may be attributed to the immunomodulatory, 
antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and antiviral 
properties of amla. 6,16 The reduced incidence of 
diarrhea may be attributed to the fact that amla 
stops biliary diarrhea (ishāl-e ṣafravī), 3 one of the 
types of ishāl (diarrhea). 15 
Insomnia was increased in Group A and 
decreased in Group B with p&lt;0.001. This may be 
attributed to the strengthening effect on brain, 15 
cooling and soothing 9 effects, reduction of suda 
and humuzat-e meda 14 and digestive properties 8 of 
amla and/or Jawarish amla. Body ache increased in 
Group A and decreased in Group B with p&lt;0.04*. 
This may be attributed to the strengthening effect 
of amla and/or Jawarish amla on vital organs 9 and 
its anti-inflammatory 16 and analgesic activity. 15 </p>

<p>Conclusion 
The overall effect of the test drug Jawarish amla 
was found quite encouraging in pulmonary 
tuberculosis (diqq-e revi). Significant improvement 
was observed in nausea, vomiting, anorexia, 
abdominal pain, itching, burning sensation in feet, 
jaundice, skin rashes, flu like syndrome, bitter 
taste, diarrhea, constipation, insomnia, body ache, 
ALT, AST, alkaline phosphatase and total bilirubin </p>

<p>Published 2013-Feb-12; Corrected 2013-Mar-8 DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.5915/44-1-9988 </p>

<p>JIMA: Vol 44, 2012, Page 8 of 9 </p>

<p>in test group in comparison to control group. 
The test drug in this study was safe and 
effective in checking the adverse effects of ATT 
drugs used in DOTS therapy. It may thus be an 
excellent adjuvant to DOTS in the community 
management of pulmonary tuberculosis (diqq-e 
revi). This adjuvant therapy should be selected for 
study involving a large sample size. If the results 
of this study are confirmed, it should then be 
implemented in India's Revised National 
Tuberculosis Control Programme (RNTCP) for 
checking the adverse reaction of DOTS and 
efficacy improvement. </p>

<p>Acknowledgement 
We gratefully acknowledge the former NIUM 
Director, Professor M.A. Jafri, for his kind 
permission and providing other necessary 
facilities in carrying out the trial. We are also 
indebted to Health and Family Welfare 
Department, Karnataka State and immensely 
thankful to the designated microscopic centre 
(DMC), Leggere PHC staff for their continuous co-
operation throughout this work. We also owe 
gratitude to Dr. K. P. Suresh, Scientist 
(Biostatistics), National Institute of Animal 
Nutrition and Physiology (NIAN &amp; P), Bangalore, 
for his help in statistical evaluation for this study. </p>



</text></tei>