<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3309518" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Siblings of individuals with autism have over 20 times the population risk of autism. Evidence of comparable, but less marked, 
cognitive and social communication deficits in siblings suggests a role for these traits in the search for biomarkers of familial 
risk. However, no neuroimaging biomarkers of familial risk have been identified to date. Here we show, for the first time, that the 
neural response to facial expression of emotion differs between unaffected siblings and healthy controls with no family history of 
autism. Strikingly, the functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) response to happy versus neutral faces was significantly 
reduced in unaffected siblings compared with controls within a number of brain areas implicated in empathy and face 
processing. The response in unaffected siblings did not differ significantly from the response in autism. Furthermore, 
investigation of the response to faces versus fixation crosses suggested that, within the context of this study, an atypical 
response specifically to happy faces, rather than to faces in general, accounts for the observed sibling versus controls 
difference and is a clear biomarker of familial risk. Our findings suggest that an atypical implicit response to facial expression of 
emotion may form the basis of impaired emotional reactivity in autism and in the broader autism phenotype in relatives. These 
results demonstrate that the fMRI response to facial expression of emotion is a candidate neuroimaging endophenotype for 
autism, and may offer far-reaching insights into the etiology of autism. 
Siblings of individuals with autism have a greatly enhanced 
risk of developing autism-estimated to be in excess of a 20-
fold increase compared with the general population. 1-3 
Furthermore, it is increasingly understood that many appar-
ently unaffected siblings (and their parents, as another 
example of first-degree relatives) display subtle impairments 
in the cognitive domains characteristically affected by 
autism. 4-7 Siblings of individuals with autism have however 
been the subject of relatively little neuroimaging research. 8-10 
The concept of an endophenotype-a marker of familial risk 
for a condition-has in recent years become the focus of 
considerable attention in neuropsychiatric research. Although 
the term was first used in the 1960s in the field of insect 
biology, 11 within a few years it was applied within psychiatry. 12 
An endophenotype is a heritable feature associated with a 
condition, present in affected individuals regardless of 
whether their condition is manifested, which co-segregates 
with the condition in families and which is present in 
unaffected family members at a higher rate than in the 
general population. 13 In such family members, endopheno-
types represent instances in which genes associated with a 
particular condition exert measurable effects in individuals in 
whom they are insufficient to cause the condition itself to </p>

<p>become manifest. The promise of characterizing endopheno-
types lies in their hypothesized intermediate position between 
genotype and phenotype. Syndromes such as autism, 
schizophrenia and bipolar disorder are complex constellations 
of clinical signs and symptoms. Considerable phenotypic 
heterogeneity exists within clinical populations and it is 
likely that the etiologies of these conditions contain hetero-
geneity too. In the case of autism, it has been recognized that 
a unitary cause is unlikely. 14 Attempts to characterize the 
genetics of these conditions therefore will ultimately be 
hampered by a reliance on traditional classificatory systems 
that coalesce this heterogeneity into a unitary diagnosis. 
As a smaller and simpler phenotypic unit than the condition 
itself, the etiology of the endophenotype is likely to be 
correspondingly simpler: it can be said to be 'closer to the 
level of gene action'. 15 
Difficulties in empathy and in the understanding of social 
stimuli and situations form a central aspect of the autistic 
phenotype. 16 The neurophysiological response to faces, and 
in particular facial emotional expressions, is atypical in autism. 
This has been documented using electroencephalography, 17 
magnetoencephalography, 18 positron emission tomogra-
phy 19 and functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) 20 </p>

<p>Received 21 April 2011; revised 2 June 2011; accepted 3 June 2011 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Psychiatry, Autism Research Centre, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK; 2 Department of Psychiatry, Herchel Smith Building for Brain and Mind 
Sciences, University of Cambridge, Cambridge Biomedical Campus, Cambridge, UK and 3 MRC Cognition and Brain Sciences Unit, Cambridge, UK 
Correspondence: Dr MD Spencer, Department of Psychiatry, Autism Research Centre, University of Cambridge, Douglas House, 18b Trumpington Road, Cambridge 
CB2 8AH, UK. 
E-mail: mds1003@cam.ac.uk 
Keywords: autism; endophenotype; fMRI; genetic; sibling </p>

<p>Citation: Transl Psychiatry (2011) 1, e19, doi:10.1038/tp.2011.18 </p>

<p>&amp; 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited All rights reserved 2158-3188/11 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/tp </p>

<p>studies. A considerable body of evidence reveals atypical 
fMRI response to faces and other social stimuli within a 
network of brain structures that has been termed the 'social 
brain'. 21,22 This comprises the amygdala and its interconnec-
tions with the superior temporal sulcus (STS), orbitofrontal 
cortex, anterior cingulate cortex and fusiform face area (FFA), 
among other regions. The STS is of particular importance not 
only in being activated during a range of mentalizing tasks in 
controls 23 but also as a site within which brain structure and 
function correlate with autistic traits in the general popula-
tion. 24 Similarly, the FFA located within the fusiform gyrus of 
the occipitotemporal cortex is particularly activated by facial 
stimuli in controls 25 and is greatly reduced in activation in 
people with autism. 20 Given reports of social deficits in 
relatives of those with autism, 26 the neural response to 
emotional expressions in faces seems a promising area within 
which to investigate possible endophenotypes of autism. 
The aim of this study was to investigate the neural response 
to facial expressions of emotion in adolescents with autism, 
their unaffected siblings and controls with no family history of 
autism, in order to enable the separation of neurobiological 
markers associated with familial risk for autism from those 
associated with the condition itself, and thus to suggest 
candidate endophenotypes of autism. </p>

<p>Participants and methods </p>

<p>Participants. Participants comprised 40 adolescents (aged 
12-18 years) with an autism spectrum disorder (ASD) 
diagnosed as either autism or Asperger syndrome, 40 
unaffected siblings and 40 typically developing controls. All 
ASD participants met Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of 
Mental Disorders, fourth edition criteria 16 for autism or 
Asperger syndrome, and were assessed as positive on 
both the Autism Diagnostic Interview-Revised 27 and the 
Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule-Generic. 28 
Participants with autism and their siblings were recruited by 
approaching support groups for families with autism and 
schools; controls were recruited through notices in schools 
and community groups in similar neighborhoods to the 
participants in the autism and sibling groups-in order to 
minimize possible confounds relating to geography and 
demographics. All siblings and controls scored below thresh-
old on a screening tool for ASD-the Social Communication 
Questionnaire. 29 Siblings were full biological siblings of the 
participants with autism, based on parental report; controls 
were defined as having no history of an ASD within any first-or 
second-degree relative. General exclusion criteria were: full-
scale intelligence quotient (IQ) o70 as measured using the 
Wechsler Abbreviated Scale of Intelligence, 30 any psychiatric 
diagnosis (other than ASD in the autism group), any current or 
previous psychotropic medication, any history of seizures, 
any history of head injury or intracranial surgery and any 
history of drug abuse. 
Participants with autism (35 males:5 females) had mean 
age 14.56 years (range: 12.01-18.53; s.d.: 1.74) and mean IQ 
106.5 (range: 73-146; s.d.: 16.6). Siblings (12 males:28 
females) had mean age 14.83 years (range: 12.01-18.95; 
s.d.: 2.14) and mean IQ 113.1 (range: 88-133; s.d.: 10.1). </p>

<p>Controls (20 males:20 females) had mean age 15.06 years 
(range: 12.08-18.17; s.d.: 1.63) and mean IQ 112.4 (range: 
83-136; s.d.: 11.1). Groups did not differ in terms of mean age 
(P ¼ 0.481; F ¼ 0.737). The autism group had significantly 
lower mean IQ than the sibling group (P ¼ 0.033; F ¼ 4.71) but 
not the control group (P ¼ 0.065; F ¼ 3.50). Importantly, for 
our investigation of markers of familial risk expressed as 
differences between sibling and control groups, sibling and 
control groups did not differ in terms of mean IQ (P ¼ 0.753; 
F ¼ 0.100). 
The protocol was approved by the Cambridgeshire 1 
Research Ethics Committee. All participants and their parents 
provided written informed consent. </p>

<p>Task protocol. Participants completed a task of implicit 
facial emotion processing comprising eight blocks of happy 
faces, eight blocks of fearful faces, eight blocks of neutral 
faces and eight blocks of fixation crosses. Facial stimuli were 
from an established battery of emotional faces, 31 and 
comprised eight different facial identities expressing happy, 
fearful and neutral expressions (that is, 24 faces in total). 
Stimuli were presented in a blocked design in one of two 
pseudorandom orders (which were counterbalanced across 
all participants in each study group) and were presented in 
<rs type="software">e-Prime version 2.0 Professional</rs> (Psychological Software 
Tools, Pittsburgh, PA, USA). Each block lasted 20 s and 
comprised four stimuli presented for 4 s each with an 
interstimulus interval of 1 s. Blocks were separated by a 2 s 
interblock interval. During task conditions (happy, fearful and 
neutral faces) participants were required to press one of 
two buttons to indicate the gender of the face using a 
button box held in the right hand. During fixation blocks, 
the participants were required to stare passively at a 
fixation cross. As with the facial blocks, four fixation cross 
stimuli were presented for 4 s each with an interstimulus 
interval of 1 s. </p>

<p>Imaging protocol. All participants were scanned using 
the same Siemens 3T Tim Trio scanner (Siemens Healthcare, 
Erlangen, Germany) at the Medical Research Council Cogni-
tion and Brain Sciences Unit, Cambridge, UK. Func-
tional images were acquired with a gradient echo planar 
imaging sequence with the following parameters: repetition 
time ¼ 2000 ms, echo time ¼ 30 ms, voxel size ¼ 3 Â 3 Â 3 mm, 
field of view ¼ 192 Â 192 mm, 64 Â 64 acquisition matrix and a 
781 flip angle. In all, 32 slices were acquired descending in the 
transverse plane (slice thickness ¼ 3 mm, slice gap ¼ 25%). 
Each volume was acquired over 2 s and the first three volumes 
were discarded to avoid equilibration effects. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Behavioral data. Behavioral data comprising accuracy and 
reaction time of response on the sex discrimination task were 
recorded in order to investigate whether any participant 
performed at or below the level of chance and analyzed using 
analysis of variance in <rs id="software-8" type="software">PASW Statistics</rs> 18, Release <rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-number">Version 18.0.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-8" type="creator">SPSS</rs>, Chicago, IL, USA). The effect of group on 
accuracy (P ¼ 0.111; F ¼ 2.241) and reaction time 
(P ¼ 0.191; F ¼ 1.679) of response was not statistically 
significant (analyses covarying for age and sex). Only two </p>

<p>A novel functional brain imaging endophenotype of autism 
MD Spencer et al </p>



<p>Translational Psychiatry </p>

<p>participants (one participant with autism and one control) 
performed at or below the level of chance on the sex 
discrimination task. In case this was indicative of reduced 
attention to the facial stimuli, all analyses were repeated 
excluding these two participants to confirm that all 
statistically significant results reported were robust to the 
exclusion of the data from these two participants. </p>

<p>Imaging data. Preprocessing and first-level analyses were 
performed in SPM8 (Wellcome Department of Cognitive 
Neurology, London, UK) implemented using the automatic 
analysis platform as previously described 32 (Medical Research 
Council Cognition and Brain Sciences Unit, Cambridge, UK) 
according to the standard Medical Research Council Cogni-
tion and Brain Sciences Unit pipeline comprising sinc 
interpolation to correct for the acquisition of different brain 
slices at different times, coregistration of echo planar imaging 
and structural scans, normalization to Montreal Neurological 
Institute (MNI) space 33 and smoothing using a Gaussian 
kernel of 10 mm full width at half maximum. For each 
subject, fMRI responses were modeled using a canonical 
hemodynamic response function and the general linear model 
was used to perform a first level, within-participants analysis 
on the functional data from each subject individually for the 
primary contrasts (happy minus neutral and fearful minus 
neutral faces), with spatial realignment parameters entered as 
covariates. </p>

<p>To characterize the patterns of activation within the brain in 
the three participant groups, the first-level contrast images for 
each study group were taken through to a second-level 
analysis using a random-effects model, with age and sex 
specified as covariates. Group-level activation maps were 
generated with a global threshold set at Po0.05 following 
correction for multiple comparisons on a whole-brain level 
family-wise error (FWE) basis, and with a cluster extent (k E ) 
threshold set at 20 voxels. In the same way, all activation 
results quoted (Table 1) are after the whole-brain level FWE 
correction for multiple comparisons and k E threshold of 
20 voxels. 
To investigate possible biomarkers of familial risk as com-
pared with autism versus control differences, we examined 
between-group differences in the fMRI response in autism, 
sibling and control participants within the specific brain regions 
identified as being significantly activated in the control group. We 
therefore defined our regions of interest as the clusters of FWE 
corrected Po0.05 significant activation within the control group 
activation maps (Table 1), and used <rs type="software">MarsBar</rs> 34 to extract mean 
activations for the primary contrast (happy minus neutral and 
fearful minus neutral) for each subject for each region of interest. 
For illustration, we plotted these FWE corrected activation 
maps onto the canonical Montreal Neuroimaging Institute 
(MNI) 152 template brain image 33 using SPM8, and onto a 
three-dimensional-rendered template brain image using <rs id="software-5" type="software">MRI-
cron</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="url">http://www.sph.sc.edu/comd/rorden/mricron/</rs>/). 35 </p>

<p>Table 1 Main activations to happy and fearful versus neutral faces </p>

<p>MNI coordinates 
P-value 
(FWE-corrected) </p>

<p>Z-score 
Cluster 
size </p>

<p>Region </p>

<p>x 
y 
z 
k E (voxels) </p>

<p>Happy versus neutral faces 
Control group 
À28 
10 
54 
0.002 
5.07 
129 
Left superior frontal gyrus 
46 
20 
À16 
0.003 
4.90 
78 
Right temporal pole 
À42 
14 
À16 
0.004 
4.86 
200 
Left temporal pole 
À36 
À62 
24 
0.006 
4.76 
77 
Left temporoparietal junction 
À54 
À64 
10 
0.009 
4.66 
115 
Left posterior STS 
44 
À52 
À28 
0.010 
4.65 
60 
Right FFA 
À4 
26 
54 
0.012 
4.60 
64 
Left dorsomedial prefrontal cortex 
66 
À28 
2 
0.015 
4.54 
32 
Right middle STS 
28 
À92 
8 
0.018 
4.51 
26 
Right cuneus 
À62 
À52 
4 
0.026 
4.41 
26 
Left middle STS 
À24 
À94 
8 
0.031 
4.37 
20 
Left cuneus </p>

<p>Sibling group 
Nil </p>

<p>Autism group 
Nil </p>

<p>Fearful versus neutral faces 
Control group 
44 
À48 
À22 
0.006 
4.78 
38 
Right FFA </p>

<p>Sibling group 
40 
À42 
À16 
0.005 
4.80 
33 
Right FFA </p>

<p>Autism group 
Nil </p>

<p>Abbreviations: FFA, fusiform face area; FWE, family-wise error; MNI, Montreal Neuroimaging Institute; STS, superior temporal sulcus. 
Activated brain regions, corresponding MNI coordinates, cluster sizes, Z-scores and P-values. All analyses are corrected for multiple comparisons, and P-values are 
expressed following whole brain level FWE correction at the threshold of Po0.05. </p>

<p>A novel functional brain imaging endophenotype of autism 
MD Spencer et al </p>



<p>Translational Psychiatry </p>

<p>We conducted analyses of variance within <rs id="software-11" type="software">PASW Statistics</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-11" type="version-number">18</rs> to measure the overall effect of group on the primary 
contrast activation data (happy minus neutral and fearful 
minus neutral) for each region of interest. Age and sex were 
modeled as covariates in all analyses. Similarly, we used 
analyses of variance to investigate autism versus control, 
control versus sibling and autism versus sibling differences, 
again taking age and sex as covariates. We investigated 
linear trend effects across the three groups using polynomial 
regression, and where a statistically significant linear effect 
was found, we examined the quadratic effect to confirm that 
this was nonsignificant. We plotted the mean activation 
contrast estimate (expressed in arbitrary units ± standard 
error of the mean) for the three study groups. 
To investigate whether the atypical response to happy 
versus neutral faces was driven by an atypical response to 
happy or neutral faces, or to both, we examined the response 
to faces versus fixation crosses. First-level analysis was as 
above, taking the primary contrasts as happy and neutral 
faces versus fixation crosses. Second-level statistical analy-
sis proceeded as described above for the emotional versus 
neutral contrasts. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Neural response to facial expressions of emotion: happy 
versus neutral faces. We examined the differential 
response within the brain to happy compared with neutral 
faces. In controls, happy faces elicited increased activation 
compared with neutral faces (Figure 1 and Table 1) within a 
range of areas strongly implicated in face processing, 
empathy and mentalizing: the right (P ¼ 0.003) and left 
(P ¼ 0.004) temporal poles, left temporoparietal junction 
(P ¼ 0.006), left posterior STS (P ¼ 0.009), right FFA 
(P ¼ 0.010), dorsomedial prefrontal cortex (P ¼ 0.012) and 
right (P ¼ 0.015) and left (P ¼ 0.026) middle STS. Increased 
activation was also detected in the left superior frontal gyrus 
(P ¼ 0.002) and the right (P ¼ 0.018) and left (P ¼ 0.031) 
cuneus. All P-values are expressed following correction for 
multiple comparisons on a whole-brain level FWE basis. In 
contrast, no activation differences were detected within 
sibling and autism groups at the threshold of Po0.05 FWE 
corrected. 
To investigate biomarkers of familial risk compared with 
autism versus control differences, we examined between-
group differences in the fMRI response in autism, sibling and 
control participants within the specific brain regions identified 
above as being significantly activated in controls to happy 
versus neutral faces (listed in Table 1). For all 11 brain 
regions, activation was significantly reduced in autism 
compared with controls, with siblings demonstrating an 
intermediate degree of impairment. 
Activation in siblings was significantly reduced compared 
with controls for 7 of the 11 brain regions: the left superior 
frontal gyrus (P ¼ 0.001; F ¼ 11.664), the right (P ¼ 0.002; 
F ¼ 9.986) and left (P ¼ 0.005; F ¼ 8.551) temporal poles, the 
right middle (P ¼ 0.004; F ¼ 9.068) and left posterior 
(P ¼ 0.016; F ¼ 6.064) STS, the left dorsomedial prefrontal 
cortex (P ¼ 0.005; F ¼ 8.570) and the right FFA (P ¼ 0.044; </p>

<p>F ¼ 4.184) (univariate analyses of variance, covarying for age 
and sex; Figures 1 and 2). Furthermore, for all 11 regions, 
activation in the autism group was significantly reduced 
compared with controls, the effect of group was significant 
across all the three groups, and polynomial regression linear 
contrast effects across all the three groups were significant </p>

<p>Middle 
STS </p>

<p>Temporal 
pole </p>

<p>FFA 
-28 
+2 
-16 </p>

<p>4.6 </p>

<p>4.8 </p>

<p>5.2 </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>DMPFC 
Superior 
frontal </p>

<p>Cuneus </p>

<p>Left 
Right </p>

<p>Posterior 
STS </p>

<p>TPJ </p>

<p>P = 0.004 
P = 0.001 
P = 0.002 </p>

<p>+10 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>-0.1 </p>

<p>autism sibling control </p>

<p>autism sibling control </p>

<p>autism sibling control </p>

<p>autism sibling control 
autism sibling control </p>

<p>autism sibling control 
autism sibling control </p>

<p>autism sibling control 
autism sibling control </p>

<p>autism sibling control 
autism sibling control </p>

<p>contrast estimate +/-SE </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>-0.1 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>-0.2 
contrast estimate +/-SE </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>-0.1 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>-0.2 
contrast estimate +/-SE </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>-0.1 
contrast estimate +/-SE </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 
contrast estimate +/-SE </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 
contrast estimate +/-SE </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.0 
contrast estimate +/-SE </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>-0.1 </p>

<p>-0.2 
contrast estimate +/-SE </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>-0.1 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>-0.2 
contrast estimate +/-SE </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>-0.1 
contrast estimate +/-SE </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>-0.1 </p>

<p>-0.2 
contrast estimate +/-SE </p>

<p>+24 
+54 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 
P &lt; 0.001 
P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Left superior 
frontal gyrus </p>

<p>Right temporal pole 
Right middle STS </p>

<p>Left posterior 
STS </p>

<p>Left temporal pole 
Left DMPFC </p>

<p>P = 0.005 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P = 0.016 </p>

<p>P = 0.002 </p>

<p>P = 0.005 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Right FFA 
Left middle STS </p>

<p>P = 0.044 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P = 0.003 
P = 0.007 </p>

<p>P = 0.001 
P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Left cuneus </p>

<p>Left TPJ 
Right cuneus </p>

<p>Figure 1 Neural response to happy versus neutral faces. Activation differences 
(means ± s.e.m.) between the functional magnetic resonance imaging response to 
happy and neutral faces in adolescents with autism (n ¼ 40), unaffected siblings 
(n ¼ 40) and controls (n ¼ 40). Activation map indicates neural response to happy 
versus neutral faces in controls, and shows activations to happy versus neutral 
faces (Po0.05, FWE corrected) overlaid onto the canonical Montreal Neurological 
Institute (MNI) 152 template brain image (axial section, z-coordinate indicated in 
Montreal Neurological Institute space), with the colored bar indicating the T-value of 
the plotted activation differences. DMPFC, dorsomedial prefrontal cortex; FFA, 
fusiform face area; STS, superior temporal sulcus; TPJ, temporoparietal junction. </p>

<p>A novel functional brain imaging endophenotype of autism 
MD Spencer et al </p>



<p>Translational Psychiatry </p>

<p>with no significant quadratic component. For all 11 regions, 
activation in the autism group did not differ statistically 
significantly from activation in siblings (Table 2). </p>

<p>Neural response to facial expression of emotion: fearful 
versus neutral faces. In controls and in siblings, fearful 
faces elicited increased activation compared with neutral 
faces (Figure 3 and Table 1) within the right FFA (controls: 
P ¼ 0.006, siblings P ¼ 0.005; FWE corrected). However, the 
autism group did not display any significant activation 
differences at the threshold Po0.05 FWE corrected. 
As with the happy versus neutral analyses above, we 
examined between-group differences in the fMRI response in 
autism, sibling and control participants within the right FFA, 
characterized above as the brain region significantly activated 
in controls in fearful versus neutral faces. Activation in the </p>

<p>autism group was significantly reduced compared with 
controls and a significant polynomial regression linear 
contrast effect with no significant quadratic component was 
detected across all the three groups (Figure 3 and Table 2). 
However, activation in the sibling group did not differ 
significantly from activation in controls or the autism group. </p>

<p>Neural response to faces versus fixation crosses. These 
findings demonstrate a clear linear progression across 
autism, sibling and control groups for atypical fMRI 
activation to happy versus neutral faces. To address the 
question as to whether the neural basis for this marker is an 
atypical neural response to happy faces, neutral faces or to 
both, we used the same brain regions defined by the 
significant activations within controls to happy versus 
neutral faces (comprising the 11 clusters listed in Table 1) </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>-0.1 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>-0.2 </p>

<p>autism sibling </p>

<p>Middle STS 
Superior frontal 
gyrus 
Right 
Left </p>

<p>Temporal pole 
Temporal pole </p>

<p>control 
autism sibling control </p>

<p>autism sibling control 
autism sibling control </p>

<p>contrast estimate +/-SE </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>-0.1 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>-0.2 
contrast estimate +/-SE </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>-0.1 
contrast estimate +/-SE </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>-0.1 </p>

<p>-0.2 
contrast estimate +/-SE </p>

<p>P = 0.004 
P = 0.001 </p>

<p>P = 0.005 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 
P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P = 0.002 </p>

<p>Figure 2 Differences between 'unaffected' siblings and controls with no family history of autism in the neural response to happy versus neutral faces. Activation differences 
(means ± s.e.m.) between the functional magnetic resonance imaging response to happy and neutral faces in adolescents with autism (n ¼ 40), unaffected siblings (n ¼ 40) 
and controls (n ¼ 40). Activation map corrected for multiple comparisons at Po0.05 family-wise error corrected, and overlaid onto a three-dimensional-rendered template 
brain within <rs type="software">MRIcron</rs>. STS, superior temporal sulcus. </p>

<p>Table 2 Between-group differences in activations to emotional versus neutral faces </p>

<p>Region of significant activation 
in controls </p>

<p>Between-group differences 
P-value (F-statistic) </p>

<p>Effect of group 
(across all three groups) </p>

<p>Polynomial regression 
linear trend effect </p>

<p>Control versus 
sibling </p>

<p>Control 
versus 
autism </p>

<p>Sibling versus 
autism </p>

<p>P-value 
(F statistic) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Happy versus neutral faces 
Left superior frontal gyrus 
0.001 (11.664) o0.001 (17.222) 
NS 
o0.001 (9.448) 
o0.001 
Right temporal pole 
0.002 (9.986) o0.001 (13.703) 
NS 
o0.001 (8.994) 
o0.001 
Right middle STS 
0.004 (9.068) o0.001 (18.608) 
NS 
o0.001 (11.073) 
o0.001 
Left dorsomedial prefrontal cortex 0.005 (8.570) o0.001 (18.714) 
NS 
o0.001 (8.957) 
o0.001 
Left temporal pole 
0.005 (8.551) o0.001 (15.181) 
NS 
o0.001 (8.763) 
o0.001 
Left posterior STS 
0.016 (6.064) 
0.002 (9.790) 
NS 
0.002 (6.335) 
0.001 
Right FFA 
0.044 (4.184) o0.001 (21.161) 
NS 
o0.001 (9.813) 
o0.001 
Left middle STS 
NS 
o0.001 (13.595) 
NS 
0.002 (6.711) 
o0.001 
Left cuneus 
NS 
0.001 (10.918) 
NS 
0.004 (5.899) 
0.001 
Left temporoparietal junction 
NS 
0.003 (9.769) 
NS 
0.010 (4.802) 
0.003 
Right cuneus 
NS 
0.007 (7.772) 
NS 
0.014 (4.400) 
0.004 </p>

<p>Fearful versus neutral faces 
Right FFA 
NS 
0.025 (5.193) 
NS 
NS 
0.017 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: FFA, fusiform face area; NS, not significant; STS, superior temporal sulcus. </p>

<p>A novel functional brain imaging endophenotype of autism 
MD Spencer et al </p>



<p>Translational Psychiatry </p>

<p>to extract activation contrast data for happy and neutral faces 
versus fixation crosses. For happy faces versus fixation 
crosses, we demonstrated a significant polynomial regre-
ssion linear contrast effect (with no significant quadratic 
component) for all 11 regions: the right FFA (P ¼ 0.001), left 
dorsomedial prefrontal cortex (P ¼ 0.001), left (P ¼ 0.001) and 
right (P ¼ 0.013) temporal poles, left posterior STS 
(P ¼ 0.010), right (P ¼ 0.002) and left (P ¼ 0.016) middle 
STS, right (P ¼ 0.007) and left (P ¼ 0.008) cuneus, left 
temporoparietal junction (P ¼ 0.007) and left superior frontal 
gyrus (P ¼ 0.026). In contrast, no statistically significant 
polynomial regression linear contrast effects were 
demonstrated for neutral faces versus fixation crosses. This 
strongly suggests that, within the context of this study, an 
atypical response specifically to happy faces accounts for the 
atypical response to happy versus neutral faces in autism and 
sibling groups. This therefore provides a clear biomarker of 
familial risk for autism. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Hypoactivation of the FFA and related 'social brain' areas in 
response to facial stimuli is one of the most consistently 
reported fMRI findings in autism. 20 We have shown that 
activation in a range of brain areas, including the FFA, is 
significantly reduced in autism compared with controls in 
response to emotional versus neutral faces, and furthermore 
our findings indicate that the response within the FFA itself 
differs significantly between siblings and controls. Moreover, 
in siblings with no autism spectrum diagnosis and no manifest 
severe behavioral features of autism, we have demonstrated </p>

<p>significant differences from controls in terms of the fMRI 
response to happy versus neutral faces within a range of other 
brain areas, particularly regions related to the STS and 
temporal poles. 
Importantly, the emotion and control conditions differed 
only in terms of facial expression-with all other aspects of 
these conditions, such as those related to the sex discrimina-
tion task, being identical. This suggests that it is specifically 
the implicit response to facial expression of emotion rather 
than some other aspect of the task that is associated with the 
significant sibling versus control differences observed. 
The temporal poles, STS, temporoparietal junction and 
medial prefrontal cortex form a network of brain areas strongly 
implicated 23,36-38 in empathy, mentalizing and theory of mind 
(the ability to attribute mental states to others). On the basis of 
the set of emotions tested here (happiness and fear), the 
finding of an atypical neural response within these brain areas 
in autism and sibling groups specifically to happy faces may 
reflect the possibility that an implicit response to happy faces 
is driven by empathy-impairments of which have a central 
role within the phenotype of autism-whereas the response to 
fearful stimuli (found in this study to be intact in siblings but not 
individuals with autism) is likely driven by their role as 
indicators of threat. Observed facial fear and anger may be 
of sufficient evolutionary importance as danger cues that, 
unlike facial happiness, they elicit an intact response in the 
broader phenotype of autism. This is consistent with reports 39 
of an intact 'anger superiority effect' in autism, where angry 
faces are salient and easier to spot within a collection of faces 
than happy faces. 
We did not select sibling pairs on the basis of gender and 
hence, in keeping with known gender ratios in high-functioning 
autism and Asperger syndrome, there is an over-representa-
tion of males in the autism group. Gender is a very unlikely 
explanation for our results, particularly as we have demon-
strated a strong fit to a linear trend across all three study 
groups (autismosiblingsocontrols), whereas the gender 
differences between autism versus sibling and sibling versus 
control groups are in opposite directions. Furthermore, our 
main findings of significant sibling versus control differences 
(see Table 2) are most unlikely to be driven by gender as there 
was no significant effect of gender in our analysis of variance 
for happy versus neutral faces for these seven brain regions. 
A potential statistical limitation of this study is that 
participants with autism, their siblings and controls were 
compared within the same analysis of variance models, 
whereas the autism and sibling groups are not independent of 
one another. However, our main findings of sibling versus 
control differences are not affected by this potential limitation. 
The heterogeneous phenotype and likely non-unitary 
nature 14 of autism require a dissection of the condition into 
simpler building blocks with the goal of characterizing the 
etiology of autism at the fine-resolution level of specific 
components of neural structure or function and their genetic 
associates. We propose that the fMRI response to happy 
versus neutral faces within these brain areas is an endophe-
notype of autism. As a biomarker of familial risk for autism, this 
candidate endophenotype has the advantage of being a 
quantitative measure, with greater statistical power than 
categorical measures. These findings offer an attractive </p>

<p>autism </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>-48 </p>

<p>4.8 </p>

<p>4.6 </p>

<p>sibling </p>

<p>Right FFA </p>

<p>control </p>

<p>P = 0.025 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.0 
contrast estimate +/-SE </p>

<p>Figure 3 Neural response to fearful versus neutral faces. Activation differences 
(means±s.e.m.) between the functional magnetic resonance imaging response to 
fearful and neutral faces in the right FFA in adolescents with autism (n ¼ 40), 
unaffected siblings (n ¼ 40) and controls (n ¼ 40). Activation map indicates neural 
response to fearful versus neutral faces in controls, corrected for multiple 
comparisons at Po0.05 family-wise error corrected and overlaid onto the canonical 
Montreal Neurological Institute (MNI) 152 template brain image (coronal section, 
y-coordinate indicated in Montreal Neurological Institute space), with the colored bar 
indicating the T-value of the plotted activation differences. Activation map overlaid 
onto a three-dimensional-rendered template brain within MRIcron. FFA, fusiform 
face area. </p>

<p>A novel functional brain imaging endophenotype of autism 
MD Spencer et al </p>



<p>Translational Psychiatry </p>

<p>strategy to future genetic research, investigating the genetic 
correlates of this candidate endophenotype. 
Kanner's original description of autism 40 highlighted the role 
of impaired 'emotional reactivity' in the phenotype of autism, 
together with the observation of similar traits in family 
members. Our findings suggest that an atypical implicit 
response to facial expression of emotion may form the basis 
of impaired emotional reactivity in autism and in the broader 
autism phenotype 26,41 in relatives. The identification of this 
fMRI endophenotype of autism may serve as an important 
step toward an understanding of the causal mechanisms that 
underlie autism at a neural and genetic level. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>ETB is employed half-time by the University of Cambridge and 
half-time by GlaxoSmithKline plc. All the other authors declare 
no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements. We are grateful to all participants and their families </p>

<p>for their participation in our study and to all autism support organizations that helped 
with recruitment. We are grateful for the technical assistance of Dr Cinly Ooi. This 
research was funded by an MRC Clinician Scientist Fellowship to MDS from the UK 
Medical Research Council (G0701919). LRC is supported by the Gates Cambridge 
Scholarship Trust. </p>



<p>Translational Psychiatry is an open-access journal 
published by Nature Publishing Group. This work is 
licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share 
Alike 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/ </p>

<p>A novel functional brain imaging endophenotype of autism 
MD Spencer et al </p>



<p>Translational Psychiatry </p>

</text></tei>