<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3824685" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Results </p>

<p>PDCD4 is lowly expressed in NPC. From Lee et al.'s </p>

<p>15   microarray data (GSE2370), PDCD4 was downexpressed in 
NPC tissues compared with NP tissues by an average of 
0.60 folds (Figure 1A). This expression pattern was similar to 
our microarray data comparing NPC cells and NP tissues. </p>

<p>9   QPCR analysis indicated that the PDCD4 expression level 
was significantly decreased in eight NPC cell lines and NPCs 
in comparison to NP tissues (Po0.0001) (Figure 1B). 
Furthermore, we also observed the decreased expression 
tendency of PDCD4 in clinical stage of III-IV compared with 
I-II (Supplementary Figure S1A) and lymph node metastasis 
(N classification) of N2-N3 compared with N0-N1 
(Supplementary Figure S1B). However, no statistically 
significant difference was shown in T3-T4 compared with 
T1-T2 (Supplementary Figure S1C) as well as in M1 
compared with M0 (Supplementary Figure S1D). Similar to 
mRNA expression pattern, the PDCD4 protein expression 
was significantly decreased in five NPCs in comparison to 
three NPs using western blot examination (Figure 1C). 
Finally, immunohistochemical staining indicated that PDCD4 
protein was lowly expressed in NPC samples compared with 
noncancerous tissues (Po0.001, Figure 1D; Supplementary 
Table S9). </p>

<p>Downregulated protein expression of PDCD4 was 
associated with NPC progression and poor prognosis. 
We analyzed the relationship between clinicopathologic 
characteristics and PDCD4 expression levels in individuals 
with NPC (Supplementary Table S10). We did not find a 
significant association of PDCD4 expression levels with 
patient's age, sex, smoking status, family tumor history, 
disease recurrence or distant metastasis (M classification) in 
190 NPC cases. However, we observed that the reduced 
expression level of PDCD4 was markedly correlated with 
tumor size (T classification; P ¼ 0.026), lymph node metas-
tasis (N classification; N0-N1 versus N2-N3, P ¼ 0.036) and 
clinical stage (I-II versus III-IV, P ¼ 0.002) in NPC patients. 
In addition, we observed that the level of PDCD4 protein 
expression was significantly correlated with overall survival, 
as patients with lower levels of PDCD4 expression had 
poorer survival (Figure 1E) than those with higher levels of 
PDCD4 expression (Po0.001). Furthermore, we also found 
that increased expression of PDCD4 showed better prog-
nosis in NPC patients, regardless of disease stage, T, N and 
M classifications (Supplementary Figures S2A-F). Multi-
variate analysis showed that decreased PDCD4 expression 
was a poor independent prognostic factor for NPC patients 
(Po0.001; Supplementary Table S11). </p>

<p>PDCD4 inhibits cell proliferation, cell cycle and induces 
cell apoptosis. To study the biological functions of PDCD4, 
we used a PDCD4-less-expressing NPC cell line 5-8F and 
introduced PDCD4 into these cells using lentivirus containing 
PDCD4 gene. Clone1 and 2 cells with the highest PDCD4 
expression were obtained in seven stably transfected cell 
clones by qPCR and western blot assays (Figures 2a and b). 
The growth curves and colony formation assay showed that 
PDCD4 significantly inhibited cell proliferation of clone1 and </p>

<p>2 cells in comparison to scramble and parental line 5-8F cells 
(Figures 2c and d). Furthermore, we also observed that 
overexpressed PDCD4 blocked cell cycle transition from G1 
to S and G2 phase(Figure 2e) and induced cell apoptosis in 
clone1 and 2 cells compared with their control 
cells(Figure 2f). To further confirm the growth-suppressive 
effect of PDCD4, we performed in vivo tumorigenesis study 
in nude mice. The results showed that the average volume of 
these two clone cells was significantly decreased compared 
with scramble cells (Figure 2g). Immunohistochemistry 
examination indicated increased PDCD4 expression in 
clone1 and 2 xenograft tumor specimens than in scramble 
cells (Figure 2h). Interestingly, inversed results were also 
observed in short hairpin RNA (shRNA)-mediated suppres-
sion of PDCD4 in HONE1 and SUNE1 NPC cells with the 
highest mRNA expression levels of PDCD4 (Supplementary 
Figures S3A-C). We found that suppressing PDCD4 
significantly elevated cell proliferation, colony formation, cell 
cycle transition and cell survival in shPDCD4 NPC cells in 
comparison to shScramble NPC cells (Supplementary 
Figures S3D-G). </p>

<p>PDCD4 regulated PI3K/AKT and JNK, cell cycle, cell 
apoptosis and C-JUN. PDCD4 has been reported to 
regulate PI3K/AKT pathway and JNK expression in some 
tumors. 
16,17 In this study, we also examined the effect of 
PDCD4 on the expression of PI3K/AKT and JNK pathways in 
NPC. Western blot analysis showed that overexpressed or 
reduced PDCD4 significantly reduced or increased the 
expression of phos-PI3K and phos-AKT (Figures 3a and b), 
but not their total protein levels (Supplementary Figures S4A 
and B), respectively. Furthermore, we also observed the 
suppressed or elevated expression of JNK in PDCD4-
overexpressed or PDCD4-reduced NPC cells, respectively 
(Figures 3a and b). In previous studies, C-JUN, cell cycle and 
cell apoptosis signals-associated moleculars as downstream 
signals had been shown to be modulated by PI3K/AKT and 
JNK pathways, </p>

<p>8,11,18   we thus examined their protein 
expression in PDCD4-overexpressed NPC 5-8F cells and 
PDCD4-suppressed NPC HONE1 and SUNE1 cells. Using 
western blotting analysis, we first examined the expression of 
C-JUN (AP1) and cell cycle factors associated with cell 
proliferation. We found that knocking down endogenous 
PDCD4 expression or introduction of PDCD4 induced or 
blocked the expression of C-JUN, pRB C-MYC, CCND1 and 
E2F1, respectively (Figures 3c and d). However, the change 
in the expression of CDK4, p15 and p27 (Supplementary 
Figures S4A and B) was not observed in both the cell types. 
Moreover, we observed that knocking down endogenous 
PDCD4 expression or introduction of PDCD4 induced or 
decreased the expression of BCL2-mediated suppression of 
the cleavage of CASP9, 3, 6, 7, and PARP in NPC cells 
(Figures 4a and b). </p>

<p>PDCD4 modulated the expression of miR-184 in NPC. To 
investigate the effect of PDCD4 on miRNAs in NPC, we used 
miRNA chip to compare the differential miRNAs between 
shPDCD4 and shScramble SUNE1 cells. We found that miR-
184 was markedly downregulated in shPDCD4 cells 
(Figure 5a). Further, we used qPCR to confirm the reliability </p>

<p>PDCD4 and miR-184 in NPC 
Y Zhen et al </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>0.60-fold </p>

<p>Survival time(Months) </p>

<p>N P C 1 </p>

<p>PDCD4 </p>

<p>-actin </p>

<p>N P 3 
N P 2 
N P 1 
N P C 5 
N P C 4 
N P C 3 
N P C 2 </p>

<p>Figure 1 Reduced expression of PDCD4 promoted the progression and poor prognosis of NPC patients. (A) Decreased PDCD4 expression was shown in NPC by 
microarray data analysis of GSE2370 data set retrieved from the GEO database. (B) Compared with nasopharynx tissues, PDCD4 expression was markedly decreased in 
NPC tissues and NPC cells (Po0.001). (C) Compared with nasopharynx tissues, PDCD4 protein expression was significantly downregulated in NPC tissues. (D) PDCD4 
expression was progressively decreased in NPC samples compared with normal nasopharynx tissues, squamous epithelium and atypical hyperplasia. (1) PDCD4 expression 
in normal epithelium, a-d: strong expression; (2) PDCD4 expression in squamous epithelium, e: strong expression; (3) PDCD4 expression in NPC, f-i: Strong and positive 
expression; j-m: weak expression and negative expression. (E) Lower levels of PDCD4 reduced the survival time of NPC patients </p>

<p>PDCD4 and miR-184 in NPC 
Y Zhen et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>PDCD4 and miR-184 in NPC 
Y Zhen et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>JNK1 </p>

<p>p-PI3K </p>

<p>p-AKT </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>E2F1 </p>

<p>P-Rb (780s) </p>

<p>C-MYC </p>

<p>CCND1 </p>

<p>C-Jun </p>

<p>P-Rb(780s) </p>

<p>C-Jun </p>

<p>C-MYC </p>

<p>CCND1 </p>

<p>E2F1 </p>

<p>JNK1 </p>

<p>p-PI3K </p>

<p>p-AKT </p>

<p>-actin 
-actin </p>

<p>HONE1 
SUNE1 
5-8F </p>

<p>5-8F 
HONE1 
SUNE1 </p>

<p>Figure 3 PDCD4 controls the expression of cell cycle and transcription factor C-JUN in NPC via PI3K/AKT/JNK pathway. (a) Overexpressed PDCD4 suppressed the 
expression of pPI3K, pAKT and JNK in clone 1 and 2 cells compared with scramble cells. (b) Reduced PDCD4 elevated the expression of pPI3K, pAKT and JNK in shPDCD4 
SUNE1 and HONE1 cells compared with their respective controls. (c) Restored PDCD4 inhibited the expression of C-MYC, CCND1, pRB (Ser780), E2F1 and C-JUN in clone 
1 and 2 cells compared with scramble cells. (d) Downregulated PDCD4 expression stimulated the C-MYC, CCND1, pRB (Ser780), E2F1 and C-JUN expression in shPDCD4 
SUNE1 and HONE1 cells compared with their respective controls </p>

<p>Figure 2 Overexpressed PDCD4 expression suppressed cell proliferation and cell cycle transition and induced cell apoptosis. (a) PDCD4 was highly reexpressed in clone 
1-7 detected by qPCR after infection and selection. (b) Restoration of PDCD4 protein expression was examined in clone 1 and 2 single clone cells compared with scramble 
and 5-8F cells by western blot. Because of the fusion protein from PDCD4 and green fluorescent protein (GFP), the fusion protein of scramble and 5-8F cells cannot be 
detected. (c, d) In vitro proliferative ability of NPC cells was significantly inhibited in PDCD4-overexpressing clone 1 and 2 cells compared with scramble and 5-8F cells by MTT 
assay and plate clone assay. (e) Restored PDCD4 expression markedly inhibited the cell cycle transition from G1 to S and G2 in vitro. (f) Increased PDCD4 expression induced 
cell apoptosis in NPC 5-8F cells. (g) Compared with scramble cells, tumorigenicity of clone 1 and 2 cells was markedly reduced in vivo. (h) PDCD4 protein was highly 
expressed in PDCD4-overexpressing clone 1 and 2 cells compared with scramble cells by immunohistochemistry assay. Data are presented as mean±S.D. of three 
independent experiments (*Po0.05) </p>

<p>Cleaved-CASP9 
Cleaved-CASP9 </p>

<p>Cleaved-CASP3 
Cleaved-CASP3 </p>

<p>Cleaved-CASP6 
Cleaved-CASP6 </p>

<p>Cleaved-CASP7 
Cleaved-CASP7 </p>

<p>Cleaved-PARP 
Cleaved-PARP </p>

<p>BCL-2 
BCL-2 </p>

<p>GAPDH 
GAPDH </p>

<p>HONE1 
5-8F 
SUNE1 </p>

<p>Figure 4 PDCD4 mediated cell apoptosis in NPC. (a) Restoration of PDCD4 expression induced the cleavage of CASP9, 3, 6, 7 and PARP and suppressed BCL2 
expression. (b) Stably knocking down the expression of PDCD4 by shRNA reduced the cleavage of CASP9, 3, 6, 7 and PARP and elevated the expression of BCL2 </p>

<p>PDCD4 and miR-184 in NPC 
Y Zhen et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>of miRNA chip in knocking down the expression of PDCD4 in 
NPC cells (Figure 5b). Furthermore, we also validated the 
upregulated expression of miR-184 in PDCD4-overex-
pressed 5-8F NPC cells (Figure 5c). </p>

<p>Overexpressed miR-184 inhibits cell proliferation and 
induces apoptosis in NPC. To study the biological 
functions of miR-184, we introduced miR-184 mimics into 
NPC SUNE1 and 5-8F cell lines. Compared with negative 
control of miR-184, we found that miR-184 inhibited cell 
growth in NPC cells by MTT assays (Supplementary Figure 
S5A). Furthermore, we observed that apoptotic cells were 
significantly increased in miR-184 mimics-treated cells 
(Supplementary Figure S5B). To confirm whether miR-184 
can revert the promotion of cell growth in PDCD4-absent 
cells, we transfected miR-184 mimics into shPDCD4 HONE1 
and SUNE1 cells. The results showed that miR-184 
significantly decreased the cell growth in shPDCD4 NPC 
cells (Supplementary Figure S5C), suggesting miR-184 as a 
positive modulator of PDCD4 in NPC. </p>

<p>miR-184 directly targeting BCL2 and C-MYC suppressed 
cell cycle signal and stimulated mitochondrial apoptosis 
pathway. To study the mechanism of miR-184 suppressing 
cell proliferation and promoting cell apoptosis in NPC, we 
examined expression of cell cycle and apoptotic genes. 
Interestingly, similar to PDCD4-mediated pathways, miR-184 
mimics suppressed the expression of pRB, C-MYC, CCND1 
and E2F1 (Figure 6a) but not p15 and CDK4 in cell cycle 
transition (Supplementary Figure S6), downregulated the 
BCL2 expression and induced the cleavage of CASP9, 3, 6, 
7 and PARP (Figure 6b) but not PDCD4 in apoptosis 
pathway (Supplementary Figure S6). Furthermore, we found 
that BCL2 and C-MYC were potentially direct targets of 
miR-184 by RNAhybrid and miRwalk assays (Supplementary 
Figure S7). In a preceding experiment, miR-184 mimics 
downregulated the protein expression of BCL2 and C-MYC in </p>

<p>NPC. Subsequently, we transfected miR-184 inhibitor into 
SUNE1 and 5-8F cells and found elevated expression levels 
of BCL2 and C-MYC (Figure 6c). We further performed 
luciferase reporter assay to determine whether miR-184 
could directly target the C-MYC coding region (CDS) and 
3 
0 UTR of BCL2 in NPC cells. Wild-type (wt) or mutant (mt) 
3'UTR vector of BCL2 and miR-184 mimics or inhibitor NPC 
cells were cotransfected with NPC SUNE1 cells. The results 
showed a significant decrease of luciferase activity in wt 
vector transfected with miR-184 mimics (Figure 6d, lanes 1 
and 2; Po0.001) or an obvious increase of luciferase activity 
by using miR-184 inhibitor (Figure 6d, lanes 3 and 4; 
Po0.001) when compared with miR control, whereas the 
activity of mt vector was unaffected (Figure 6d, lanes 5 and 6, 
P ¼ 0.092) by using miR-184 mimics or inhibitor. Similar to 
the result of BCL2, a significant decrease of luciferase 
activity in wt vector of C-MYC CDS was showed by using 
miR-184 mimics (Figure 6e, lanes 1 and 2 Po0.001) or an 
obvious increase of luciferase activity by transfecting miR-
184 inhibitor (Figure 6e, lanes 3 and 4; Po0.001) compared 
with miR control; whereas the activity of mt vector was 
unaffected (Figure 6e, lanes 5 and 6, P ¼ 0.36) by using miR-
184 mimics or inhibitor. Taken together, these results 
strongly supported that BCL2 and C-MYC were the direct 
targets of miR-184 in NPC cells. </p>

<p>PDCD4 induced the expression of miR-184 by modulat-
ing PI3K/AKT/JNK/C-JUN pathway. The promoter region 
of human miR-184 contains AP-1 (C-JUN) binding sites. To 
examine the role of AP-1 (C-JUN) in regulating miR-184, we 
first used small-interfering RNAs (siRNAs) to suppress the 
expression of C-JUN in NPC SUNE1 and 5-8F cells by 
western blot (Figure 7a). Further, qPCR analysis indicated 
that the expression of miR-184 was markedly increased in 
both the cells with knocked down expression of C-JUN 
(Figure 7b), which suggested that C-JUN is an upstream 
regulator of miR-184. In a subsequent investigation, we used </p>

<p>Figure 5 PDCD4 regulated the expression of miR-184 in NPC. (a) miR-184 was notably downregulated in shRNA-PDCD4-treated SUNE1 NPC cells by miRNA array 
analysis. (b) Real-time PCR confirmed the downregulated expression of miR-184 in shPDCD4-treated SUNE1 and HONE1 cells. (c) Upregulated expression of miR-184 was 
shown in PDCD4-overexpressed NPC 5-8F cells </p>

<p>PDCD4 and miR-184 in NPC 
Y Zhen et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>chromatin immunoprecipitation combined with qPCR analy-
sis to confirm that C-JUN could bind putative miR-184 
promoter and activate its expression in NPC (Figure 7c). 
Finally, we used specific inhibitor of PI3K to suppress the 
expression of PI3K or specific siRNA to reduce JNK 
expression and observed that the protein expression of 
C-JUN was decreased in NPC SUNE1 and 5-8F cells 
(Figures 7d and e). Our results demonstrated that PDCD4 
stimulated the expression of miR-184 through PI3K/AKT/ 
JNK/C-JUN pathway. </p>

<p>Reduced expression tendency of miR-184 was positively 
correlated with the expression of PDCD4 in NPC. We 
further measured the mRNA levels of miR-184 in NPC 
specimens and NP tissues. The results showed that although 
the decreased tendency of average expression level of miR-
184 was shown in NPC specimens compared with NP 
tissues, the mean differences did not reach statistical 
significance (Supplementary Figure S8A; P ¼ 0.24). Interest-
ingly, we observed that miR-184 expression was markedly 
higher in clinical I-II stage than that in clinical III-IV stage in </p>

<p>NPC samples (Supplementary Figure S8B; P ¼ 0.029). 
Furthermore, a nonsignificant increase of miR-184 expres-
sion was also observed in T1-T2 and N0-NI compared with 
T3-T4 and N2-N3 (Supplementary Figure S8C and D; 
P ¼ 0.081 and P ¼ 0.085, respectively). However, no statis-
tically significant difference was shown in M0 compared with 
M1 (Supplementary Figure S8E; P ¼ 0.677). Furthermore, 
we found that reduced miR-184 expression was positively 
correlated with PDCD4 expression (Supplementary Figure 
S8F; P ¼ 0.008) in the same NPC specimens. </p>

<p>Disscussion </p>

<p>PDCD4, a cytoplasmic and nuclear expression protein, has a 
significant role in the suppression of tumor growth. 
9 However, 
its roles and molecular mechanisms linking the initiation and 
development of NPC are seldom reported. </p>

<p>9   In this study, we first observed the significantly decreased 
expression of PDCD4 in NPC tissues and cells compared with 
NP tissues by qPCR and western blot. Moreover, we 
observed that specific PDCD4 protein staining was found in </p>

<p>BCL-2 </p>

<p>-actin </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>Cleaved-Casp9 </p>

<p>Cleaved-CASP3 </p>

<p>Cleaved-Casp6 </p>

<p>Cleaved-Casp7 </p>

<p>Cleaved-PARP </p>

<p>E2F1 </p>

<p>CCND1 </p>

<p>SUNE1 </p>

<p>SUNE1 </p>

<p>wt 3'UTR 
psiCHECK-2 </p>

<p>mt 3'UTR 
miR-184 mimics </p>

<p>miR-184 inhibitor </p>

<p>wt CDS 
psiCHECK-2 </p>

<p>mt CDS 
miR-184 mimics </p>

<p>miR-184 inhibitor </p>

<p>BCL2 </p>

<p>SUNE1 </p>

<p>BCL2 </p>

<p>C-MYC </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0 
1 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>-
-
-
-
-
-
-</p>

<p>-
-
-
-
-</p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>2 
3 
4 
5 
6 </p>

<p>10 
Relative luciferase 
activity 
20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 
Relative luciferase 
activity 
60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>1 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>-
-
-
-
-
-
-</p>

<p>-
-
-
-
-</p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>2 
3 
4 
5 
6 </p>

<p>P-Rb(780s) </p>

<p>C-Myc </p>

<p>-actin </p>

<p>C-MYC </p>

<p>5-8F </p>

<p>5-8F </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>5-8F </p>

<p>Figure 6 MiR-184 directly targeted BCL2 and C-MYC suppressing cell cycle and stimulating cell apoptosis signals. (a) The introduction of miR-184 mimics suppressed the 
expression of pRB (ser 780), C-MYC, CCND1 and E2F1 in cell cycle. (b) Transfection of miR-184 mimics reduced BCL2 expression and induced the cleavage of CASP9, 3, 6, 
7 and PARP in apoptosis pathway. (c) BCL2 and C-MYC expression was elevated with the transfection of miR-184 inhibitor at 100 nm in NPC SUNE1 and 5-8F cells. 
(d) Luciferase reporter assay was used to determine miR-184 directly targeting the 3 
0 UTR of BCL2. (e) Luciferase reporter assay was used to determine miR-184 directly 
targeting the coding region of C-MYC. Data are presented as mean ± S.D. of three independent experiments (*Po0.05) </p>

<p>PDCD4 and miR-184 in NPC 
Y Zhen et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>the cytoplasm and nuclei of malignant epithelial cells and 
noncancerous tissues but predominantly expressed in cyto-
plasm by immunohistochemistry. Furthermore, we also found 
that attenuated PDCD4 expression was negatively associated 
with T classification, N classification and clinical stages of 
NPC patients. Furthermore, we also observed that lost 
PDCD4 protein expression in NPC was positively correlated 
with patient's overall survival. Patients with lower expression 
of PDCD4 protein had a shorter overall survival time. 
Multivariate analyses showed that decreased expression of 
PDCD4 protein was a significant independent predictor of 
poor prognosis for NPC patients. The results mentioned 
above suggested PDCD4 as a significant suppressor 
in NPC, which is similar to other reports of PDCD4 in some 
tumors. </p>

<p>19-22   Subsequently, we presented the evidence that PDCD4 was 
taken a tumor suppressor participating in NPC pathogenesis. </p>

<p>We found that PDCD4-mediated growth suppression attri-
buted to cell cycle transition obstacle by repressing the 
expression of cell cycle factors, including C-MYC, CCND1, 
pRb and E2F1, and transcription factor C-Jun, and the 
elevation of cell apoptosis level by inducing the cleavage of 
CASP9, 3, 6, 7 and PARP. 
In previous studies, PDCD4-mediated miRNA regulation in 
tumor cell growth and apoptosis was rarely reported. In this 
investigation, miR-184 was shown to be significantly down-
expressed in NPC cells of knocking down PDCD4 expression 
compared to scramble NPC cells by miRNA array and qPCR 
examinations. Dysregulation of miR-184 was preliminarily 
reported as a potential oncomir promoting cell proliferation 
and blocking cell apoptosis in tongue carcinoma. 
23 In 
subsequent studies, miR-184 was shown as a tumor 
suppressor involved in suppressing cell survival and growth 
by targeting AKT2 in neuroblastoma cell. 
24 In our study, </p>

<p>C-JUN </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>SUNE1 </p>

<p>SUNE1 </p>

<p>* 
5 -8F </p>

<p>JNK1 </p>

<p>-actin </p>

<p>SUNE1 </p>

<p>P-PI3K </p>

<p>C-JUN </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>AKT </p>

<p>P-AKT </p>

<p>P1 
P2 </p>

<p>P3 
miR-184 </p>

<p>miR-184 </p>

<p>SUNE1 </p>

<p>5-8F </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* 
8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 
expression folds </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 
expression folds </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>si-C-JUN Scramble si-C-JUN Scramble </p>

<p>C-JUN </p>

<p>5-8F </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>5-8F </p>

<p>Figure 7 PDCD4 regulated the expression of miR-184 via PI3K/AKT/JNK pathway in NPC. (a) siRNAs were used to suppress the C-JUN expression by western blot 
examination. (b) Knocking down C-JUN expression by siRNA stimulated the expression of miR-184 in NPC SUNE1 and 5-8F cells. (c) From mock and pcDNA3.1-C-JUN-
transfected SUNE1 cells was immunoprecipitated with anti-C-JUN and a normal rabbit IgG. The AP-1 binding sites on the immunoprecipitated DNA was determined by 
quantitative RT-PCR. Amplification of input chromatin (input) before immunoprecipitation was served as positive controls for chromatin extraction and PCR amplification. 
Chromatin immunoprecipitation using a non-specific antibody (normal human IgG) served as negative controls. QPCR analysis indicated that C-Jun could bind more miR-184 
promoter region than that in control group in NPC SUNE1 cells. (d) Suppressing the expression of PI3K by its specific inhibitor Ly294002 (50 nM) reduced pPI3K, pAKT and 
C-JUN expression in NPC SUNE1 and 5-8F cells, but did not induce AKT expression change. (e) Knocking down JNK1 suppressed the expression of C-Jun in NPC SUNE1 
and 5-8F cells. (f) Specific inhibition of JNK1 by siRNA decreased the expression of JNK and C-Jun in NPC cells. Data are presented as mean±S.D. of three independent 
experiments (*Po0.05) </p>

<p>PDCD4 and miR-184 in NPC 
Y Zhen et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>miR-184, identified as a potential tumor suppressor, 
repressed cell growth by modulating C-MYC-controlled cell 
cycle transition and BCL2-suppressed mitochondrion apop-
tosis, which was consistent with the role of PDCD4 in NPC. 
However, miR-184 mimics did not control the expression of 
PDCD4, which hinted that miR-184 was a downstream 
regulator of PDCD4. Subsequently, we investigated miR-
184-regulated genes possibly involved in cell cycle and 
apoptosis pathways. Excitingly, C-MYC coding region and 
BCL-2 3 
0 UTR were predicted as miR-184-targeted region by 
bioinformatics assay. Our experiments further validated this 
speculation that miR-184 directly targeted C-MYC and BCL-2 
expression. These results demonstrated that miR-184 parti-
cipated in PDCD4-mediated suppression of cell growth and 
survival in NPC. 
To understand the molecular mechanism of PDCD4-modu-
lated miR-184, we first employed bioinformatics assay to find 
that there were binding sites of AP1 (C-JUN), an oncogenic 
transcription factor also regulated by PI3K/AKT and JNK 
signal, 
25,26 a classic pathway stimulating tumor pathogen-
esis, 
27-29 in putative promoter region of miR-184. We speculated 
that PDCD4 might participate in modulating the expression of 
miR-184 through PI3K/AKT and JNK/C-JUN pathway. Our 
results demonstrated that PDCD4 inactivated PI3K/AKT and 
JNK-mediated activation of C-JUN, which reduced the repres-
sion of miR-184 promoter and stimulated miR-184 expression in 
NPC. These results were in line with our expectation. 
In addition to the effects of miR-184-mediated suppression 
of PDCD4 in cell proliferation and survival in NPC, we 
observed that the expression pattern of miR-184 was 
analogous to that of PDCD4 in NPC. Furthermore, we also 
found that miR-184 was positively correlated with PDCD4 
mRNA levels, suggesting that miR-184 might have important 
roles in NPC tumorigenesis of PDCD4 dysfunction. 
As summarized in Supplementary Figure S9, this study 
provided evidence that PDCD4 was downregulated and its 
reduced expression in cellular cytoplasm facilitated the develop-
ment and poor prognosis in NPC. Furthermore, we also identified 
the abnormal pathways of PDCD4 in suppressing cell growth and 
survival by miR-184-mediated direct targeting of BCL2 and 
C-MYC via PI3K/AKT and JNK/C-Jun pathway in NPC. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods 
Cell culture. Eight NPC cell lines 5-8F, 6-10B, CNE1, CNE2, C666-1, HONE1, 
HNE1 and SUNE1 were maintained in RPMI 1640 medium supplemented with 
10% newborn calf serum (NBCS) (PAA Laboratories, Inc., Pasching, Austria). All 
the cell lines were incubated in a humidified chamber with 5% CO 2 at 371C. </p>

<p>Collection of primary NPC and noncancerous nasopharynx 
specimens and ethics statement. Sixty-three fresh NPC tissues, 20 
fresh nasopharynx tissuses, 190 paraffin-embedded undifferentiated NPC 
specimens and 121 paraffin-embedded noncancerous nasopharynx specimens 
(including 76 normal epithelium, 22 squamous epithelium and 23 atypical 
hyperplasia epithelium) were obtained at the time of diagnosis before any therapy 
from People's Hospital in Zhongshan City (Guangdong, China). In these 190 NPC 
cases with clinical and prognosis information, there were 128 male and 62 female 
patients with age ranging from 19 to 80 years (median, 49.12 years). 
The clinical follow-up time of patients ranged from 4 to 126 months. The clinical 
processes were approved by the Ethics Committees of People's Hospital of 
Zhongshan City. The patients provided informed consents. The pathologic stage 
of all specimens was confirmed according to the 1997 NPC staging system of 
the WHO. </p>

<p>Analysis of microarray data. Microarray data set (GEO accession 
number: GSE2370) from five representative EBV-negative NPC cell lines: 
TW01, TW03, TW04, TW06 and CGBM1 and normal nasal mucosal epithelial 
submitted by Lee was retrieved from the GEO database and differentially 
expressed genes were screened with a selection criteria based on our previous 
investigation. </p>

<p>9   Construction of pGC-FU-PDCD4-GFP vector and lentivirus 
infection. PDCD4 cDNA was cloned into an AgeI-digested pGC-FU-GFP 
lentivirus vector (Genechem Incorporation, Shanghai, China). The resulting 
lentivirus vector together with pHelper1 and pHelper2 vectors were cotrans-
fected into 293FT cells for 84 h using lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, 
CA, USA) to generate lentiviral stock. The lentiviral particles were used to infect 
5-8F cells with high ability of tumorigenesis and metastasis, 
30 and colonies with 
GFP expression were selected to expand culture for further investigation. </p>

<p>Establishment of NPC HONE1 and SUNE1 cells with stable 
expression of PDCD4 shRNA. We selected two shRNA sequences in 
1290 and 1605 of PDCD4 mRNA sequence (Supplementary Table S1) for 
targeting PDCD4 gene using the BLOCK-It RNAi Designer (Invitrogen). The 
preparation of lentiviral vectors expressing human PDCD4 shRNA was performed 
using the pLVTHM-GFP lentiviral RNAi expression system. 
31 NPC HONE1 and 
SUNE1 cells were infected with lentiviral particles containing specific or negative 
control vectors, and the polyclonal cells with GFP signals were selected for further 
experiments using FACS flow cytometer assay. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis. Cells were lysed in RIPA buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl, 
pH8.0; 1 mM ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid, pH 8.0; 5 mM DTT; 2% sodium 
dodecyl sulfate (SDS)), and protein concentration was determined using BCA 
assay (Beyotime, Beijing, China). Total protein (30 mg) was resolved using a 10% 
SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis gel and electro-transferred to polyviny-
lidene fluoride membranes (Invitrogen). Membranes were blocked with 5% non-fat 
dry milk (for phosphorylation antibody, adding BSA) in Tris-buffered saline (pH 
7.5), followed by immunobloting overnight at 41C with anti-PDCD4 antibody 
(1 : 1000; Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, MA, USA), anti-b-actin, GAPDH, 
CCND1, CDK4, p21, E2F1 and p15 antibody (1 : 400; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, 
Santa Cruz, CA, USA), anti-pRb (Ser780), C-MYC, C-JUN, AKT, pAKT (Ser473), 
PI3K, pPI3K (Tyr458), cleaved-caspase 3, 6, 7, 9, PARP (1 : 1000; Cell Signaling 
Technology), BCL2 (1 : 1000; Abcam, Cambridge, UK), JNK and p27 (1 : 1000; 
Epitomics, Burlingame, CA, USA). A horseradish peroxidase-conjugated anti-
rabbit and anti-mouse IgG antibody was used as the secondary antibody 
(Zhongshan, Beijing, China). Signals were detected using enhanced chemilumi-
nescence reagents (Pierce, Rockford, IL, USA). </p>

<p>RNA isolation, reverse transcription, and qRT-PCR. RNA was 
extracted from the NPC cell lines, NPC tissues and normal nasopharynx tissues 
using Trizol (Takara, Shiga, Japan). For miR-184 qRT-PCR, RNA was transcribed 
into cDNA and amplified with specific sense primers (Supplementary Table S2), 
and general antisense primer was supplied by manufacturer using miRNA 
PrimeScript RT Enzyme Mix kit according to the manufacturer's instructions 
(Ambion, Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA). For PDCD4 and C-JUN qRT-
PCR, RNA was transcribed into cDNA and amplified with specific sense/antisense 
primer (Supplementary Table S3). The assays were performed in accordance with 
manufacturer's instructions (Takara). The PCR reaction for each gene was 
repeated three times. miRNA and mRNA expression were normalized to U6 
(Supplementary Table S2) and ARF5 (Supplementary Table S3), respectively, 
using the 2 
À DDCt method. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry and evaluation of staining. Paraffin 
sections (4 mm) from samples were deparaffinized in 100% xylene and rehydrated 
in descending ethanol series and water according to standard protocols. Heat-
induced antigen retrieval was performed in 10 mM citrate buffer for 2 min at 1001C. 
Endogenous peroxidase activity and nonspecific antigen were blocked with 
peroxidase-blocking reagent containing 3% hydrogen peroxide and serum, 
followed by incubation with rabbit anti-human PDCD4 antibody (1 : 100, Cell 
Signaling Technology) for overnight at 41C. After washing, the sections were 
incubated with biotin-labeled rabbit anti-goat antibody for 10 min at room 
temperature, and subsequently were incubated with streptavidin-conjugated 
horseradish peroxidase (Maixin, Fuzhou, China). The peroxidase reaction was </p>

<p>PDCD4 and miR-184 in NPC 
Y Zhen et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>developed using 3,3-diaminobenzidine chromogen solution in DAB buffer 
substrate. Sections were visualized with DAB and counterstained with 
hematoxylin, mounted in neutral gum and analyzed using a bright field 
microscope. The immunohistochemically stained tissue sections were reviewed 
and scored separately by two pathologists blinded to the clinical parameters. 
For cytoplasmic staining, the score was evaluated according to the sum of cytoplasm 
staining intensity and the percentage of positive staining areas of cells. The 
staining intensity was scored as previously described (0-3) 
10 and the percentage 
of positive staining areas of cells was defined as a scale of 0-3 (0: o10%, 1: 
10-25%, 2: 26-75% and 3: Z76%). For statistical analysis, a final staining score 
of 0-4 and 5-6 in cytoplasm was considered to be low and high expression, 
respectively. </p>

<p>Cell cycle analysis. For cell cycle analysis, cells were seeded on 10-cm 
diameter plates in RPMI 1640 containing 10% NBCS. After incubation for 48 h, a 
total of 5 Â 10 
6 cells were harvested, rinsed with cold PBS and fixed with 70% 
ice-cold ethanol for 48 h at 41C. Fixed cells were rinsed with cold PBS followed by 
incubation with PBS containing 10 mg/ml propidium iodide and 0.5 mg/ml RNase A 
for 30 min at 371C. The DNA content of labeled cells was acquired using FACS 
cytometry assay (BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA). Each experiment 
was performed in triplicate. </p>

<p>Apoptosis assays. Apoptosis was demonstrated by Annexin V-Cy5 
Apoptosis Detection Kit K103-25 (Biovision Corporation, San Francisco, CA, 
USA). Briefly, 1-5 Â 10 
5 cells were collected, washed twice in cold PBS and 
resuspended in 500 ml binding buffer. The suspension cells were stained with 5 ml 
Annexin V-Cy5 and incubated for 5 min at room temperature in the dark. Apoptotic 
cells were assessed using FACS (BD Biosciences). Experiments were performed 
in multiples to qualify apoptosis by phosphatidylserine externalization. </p>

<p>Cell proliferation analysis. Cell proliferation was analyzed using MTT 
assay. Briefly, 1 Â 10 
3 cells were seeded into a 96-well plate with quadruplicate 
repeat for each condition. For shRNA-PDCD4 and pGC-FU-PDCD4, the cells were 
incubated for 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 and 7 days. For miR-184 mimics, the cells were 
incubated for 1, 2 and 3 days. Twenty microliters of MTT (5 mg/ml) (Sigma, St 
Louis, MO, USA) was added to each well and incubated for 4 h. At the end of 
incubation, the supernatants were removed and 150 ml of DMSO (Sigma) was 
added to each well. The absorbance value (OD) of each well was measured at 
490 nm. Experiments were performed three times. </p>

<p>Colony formation assay. Cells were plated in six-well culture plates at 100 
cells/well. Each cell group had two wells. After incubation for 12 days at 371C, 
cells were washed twice with PBS and stained with the Giemsa solution (Sigma-
Aldrich Corporation, St. Louis, MO, USA). The number of colonies containing Z50 
cells was counted under a microscope. The colony formation efficiency was 
calculated as (number of colonies/number of cells inoculated) Â 100%. </p>

<p>In vivo tumorigenesis in nude mice. A total of 1 Â 10 
6 logarithmically 
grown 5-8F cells transfected with pGC-FU-GFP-PDCD4 (clone 1 and 2) and the 
control pGC-FU-GFP vector (scramble) in 0.1 ml RPMI 1640 medium were 
subcutaneously injected into the left flank of 4-6-week-old male BALB/c nu/nu 
mice. The mice were maintained in a barrier facility on HEPA-filtered racks. The 
animals were fed with an autoclaved laboratory rodent diet. All animal studies 
were conducted in accordance with the principles and procedures outlined in 
Southern Medical University Guide for the Care and Use of Animals under 
assurance number SCXK (Guangdong) 2008-0002. After 19 days the mice were 
killed and tumor tissues were excised and weighted. </p>

<p>miRNA array for shPDCD4. We used a custom-made, two-channel oligo 
array (CCDTM-miRNA850-V4px) from NIH including 713 human, mammalian 
and viral mature antisense miRs plus two internal controls with seven serial 
dilutions, 
16 which were endowed by Professor Wang E and Marincola FM from 
National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, USA. Total RNA samples (6-7 mg ) 
isolated from each shPDCD4 and its control NPC SUNE1 cells were labeled by 
Cy5-dCTP and Cy3-dCTP, respectively, in a reverse transcription reaction. The 
balanced mixture of Cy5-and Cy3-labeled targets was cohybridized against 
miRNA chips. The experiments were repeated four times and the data were 
analyzed using and BRB ArrayTools V3.7.2 software (National Cancer Institute, 
Bethesda, MD, USA). </p>

<p>miRNA target validation. BCL2 and C-MYC were predicted to be directly 
regulated targets of miR-184 by RNAhybrid (The BiBiServ, Bielefeld, Germany) 
and miRwalk softwares (University of Heidelberg, Mannheim, Germany). A 420-bp 
fragment of BCL2 3 
0 UTR or 309-bp fragment of C-MYC CDS (coding sequence) 
amplified by PCR primers (Supplementary Table S4) was cloned into psiCHECK-2 
vectors (named wt). Site-directed mutagenesis of the miR-184 binding site in 
BCL2 3 
0 UTR and C-MYC CDS were performed using GeneTailor Site-Directed 
Mutagenesis System (Invitrogen; named mt). For reporter assays, wt or mt vector 
and the control vector psiCHECK-2 vector were cotransfected into SUNE1 
cells with miR-184 mimics or inhibitor. Luciferase activity was measured at 48 h 
after transfection using the Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay System (Promega 
Corporation, Madison, WI , USA). </p>

<p>Transient transfection with siRNAs or miR-184 mimics/inhibitor 
or PI3K inhibitor Ly294002. siRNA for C-JUN and JNK1 (Supplementary 
Tables S5 and 6) (RiboBio Inc., Guangzhou, China) or miR-184 mimics and its 
inhibitor were designed and synthesized (GenePharma Co., Ltd, Shanghai, 
China). The sequence of each miRNA and their controls are shown in 
Supplementary Table S7. PI3K inhibitor Ly294002 was bought from Sigma. 
Twenty-four hours before transfection, NPC cells 5-8F and SUNE1 were plated 
onto a 6-or 96-well plate (Nest, Biotech, China) at 30-50% confluence. siRNA or 
miRNAs were then transfected at a working concentration of 100 nM using 
TurboFect siRNA Transfection Reagent (Fermentas, Vilnius, Lithuania) according 
to the manufacturer's protocol. Cells were collected after 48-72 h for the further 
experiments. </p>

<p>Chromatin immunoprecipitation assay. DNA-protein complexes were 
immunoprecipitated from SUNE1 cells by using the Chromatin Immunoprecipita-
tion Kit (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA) according to the manufacturer's protocol with 
the following polyclonal antibodies: anti-C-JUN and normal mouse IgG (Millipore), 
the latter served as a control for nonspecific DNA binding. The precipitated DNA 
was subjected to qPCR analysis using specific primers. The primers 
(Supplementary Table S8) were utilized to amplify across the miR-184 promoter 
region. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. All data were analyzed for statistical significance using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS</rs>, Chicago, IL, USA). The chi-square test was applied 
to the examination of relationship between PDCD4 expression levels and 
clinicopathological characteristics. Survival analysis was performed using Kaplan-
Meier method. Multivariate Cox proportional hazards method was used for 
analyzing the relationship between the variables and patient's survival time. The 
relationship between PDCD4 and miR-184 expression was explored by Pearson 
test. Two-tailed Student's t test was used for comparisons of two independent 
groups. One-way ANOVA was used to determine the differences between groups 
for all in vitro analyses. A P-value of o0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest 
The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements. This study was supported by National Nature Science 
Fund of China (No. 81372184, No. 30872856 and No. 81272268) (http:// 
www.nsfc.gov.cn), Nature Science Fund of Guangdong Province No. 
S2013010014724), new star plan of Pearl River Science and Technology from 
Guangzhou City (No. 2011J2200009) and Guangdong Province Breeding Project 
Plan (LYM11102). </p>





<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>





<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

</text></tei>