<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3132874" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Citation Van Trump JI, et al. 2011. Humic acid-oxidizing, nitrate-reducing bacteria in agricultural soils. mBio 2(4):e00044-11. investigate the microbiology of HA oxidation in agricultural soils 
with both culture-dependent and culture-independent tech-
niques. Our culture-dependent studies revealed the existence of a 
large and diverse population of NHOx and provided several novel 
isolates. NHOx populations coupled the oxidation of reduced HA 
to substantial nitrate reduction in advective flow columns. A 16S 
rRNA gene-based high-density oligonucleotide microarray (Phy-
loChip) (30) illustrated a phylogenetic response, with specific taxa 
enriched exlusively in HA-amended soils relative to control and 
background treatments. Together, the results presented in this 
article demonstrate that NHOx are prevalent in agricultural soils 
and may play an important role in nitrate respiration. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Most probable number analysis. Most probable number (MPN) 
tubes were scored for microbial AH 2 DS oxidation based upon a 
visual color change from red (hydroquinone) to yellow (quinone) 
and microscopic examination. NHOx populations ranged from 
3.3 10 4 cells g 1 in native grassland soil to over 10 6 cells g 1 in 
native woodland and corn plot soils (Fig. 1). When MPN tubes 
were left undisturbed for an extended period, gas production was 
evident as small bubbles on the tube walls in positive tubes. Uni-
noculated tubes and inoculated tubes without nitrate remained 
red with no visible bubble production. 
The positive scored 10 3 dilution tubes for each soil type were 
examined for extent of nitrate reduction and nitrite production 
relative to cell-free control medium. In all cases, nitrate reduction 
relative to control tubes was apparent (Fig. 1). No nitrate reduc-
tion or nitrite production occurred in uninoculated MPN tubes 
(data not shown). In most cases, low concentrations of nitrite 
were produced, but nitrate reduction was in stoichiometric excess 
of nitrite production in all tubes tested (Fig. 1). Along with the 
observation of gas bubbles, these results support active denitrifi-
cation coupled to AH 2 DS oxidation within each inoculated MPN 
series. </p>

<p>Pure cultures. Several NHOx isolates were obtained from the 
MPN series. Analyses of 16S rRNA gene sequences revealed that all 
isolates were phylogenetically distinct members of the Proteobac-
teria (see Fig. S1 in the supplemental material). In the presence of 
nitrate and acetate (100 M), all AH 2 DS-respiring NHOx isolates 
grew to higher cell densities than in controls lacking AH 2 DS, dem-
onstrating that hydroquinone oxidation was coupled to growth 
(data not shown). While none of the tested isolates degraded the 
anthraquinone, each culture supported a different pattern of re-
spiratory nitrate reduction. For example, strain A7, a gammapro-
teobacterium of the Pseudomonas genus, produced a transient ni-
trite spike during nitrate-dependent AH 2 DS oxidation. In 
contrast, strain A5, a betaproteobacterium, produced nitrite as the 
end product of the metabolism, and strain D1, an alphaproteo-
bacterium, reduced nitrate without observable nitrite accumula-
tion. 
Column studies. In order to examine the effect of reduced HA 
electron donors on nitrate reduction in dynamic soil systems, ad-
vective up-flow column studies . Sealed anaerobic columns inoc-
ulated with corn plot soil were constructed using one column per 
treatment as described in Materials and Methods (see Fig. S2 in the 
supplemental material). During the initial 7-day equilibration pe-
riod, limited nitrate reduction occurred in all columns in the ab-
sence of electron donor amendment, suggesting the presence of an 
electron donor intrinsic to the soil. After equilibration, the col-
umns were continuously injected at port A with electron acceptor 
medium containing approximately 0.5 mM nitrate. Directly 
above this point at port B, electron donor treatments (donor-free 
medium, oxidized HA medium, or reduced HA medium), were 
continually injected at the same flow rate. Bromide tracers in elec-
tron donor treatments allowed for dilution factor calculation 
throughout each column. 
(i) Column performance. Average retention times were 164 
56 h throughout operation for the donor-free control column, 139 
30 h for the oxidized HA column, and 135 9 h for the reduced 
HA column. Total flow was very similar between columns for each 
time point (data not shown), suggesting that cross-comparison of 
column treatments for extent of nitrate reduction could be rea-
sonably achieved. Bromide tracer data indicated similar donor 
medium gradients between column treatments and an approxi-
mate 1:1 mixing of donor and acceptor media within each column 
(data not shown). 
(ii) Donor-free control column. During the initial equilibra-
tion, each column hosted a limited amount of nitrate reduction 
(data not shown). The trend was sustained for the control column 
continually injected with donor-free medium (Fig. 2; see Fig. S3a 
in the supplemental material). By the end of the experimental 
period, samples collected from each port of the column contained 
similar nitrate concentrations (163, 161, 166, and 185 M for 
ports 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively), indicating a limited concentra-
tion gradient throughout the length of the column. This suggests 
that the majority of the microbial nitrate removal occurred be-
tween the injection ports and sampling port 1. Based upon the 
observed 1:1 mixing ratio of the two types of media, the donor-
free column removed an average of 33% (82 M) of the intro-
duced nitrate by the end of the experimental time period. Nitrite 
production in the donor-free column was never detected at con-
centrations higher than 10 M (data not shown), suggesting the 
production of more-reduced respiratory end products. </p>

<p>FIG 1 Populations of AH 2 DS-oxidizing, nitrate-reducing cells and degrees of </p>

<p>nitrate reduction and nitrite production. Grey bars represent populations of 
AH 2 DS-oxidizing, nitrate-reducing cells in agricultural soils as measured by 
MPN analysis (6.4 10 6 cells g 1 in native wooded soil, 6.5 10 6 cells g 1 in 
soil from a plot of corn, 1.8 10 6 cells g 1 for soil from a soybean plot with a 
slurry added to the soil, 2.0 10 5 cells g 1 for soil from a soybean plot with no 
slurry added, and 3.3 10 4 cells g 1 for native grassland [bluegrass]). The 
degrees of nitrate reduction and nitrite production are also indicated for the 
10 3 dilution of each MPN series. </p>

<p>Van Trump et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
July/August 2011 Volume 2 Issue 4 e00044-11 </p>

<p>(iii) Oxidized HA column. Relative to the no-donor control, 
the column treated with oxidized HA supported a greater extent of 
nitrate reduction (Fig. 2; see Fig. S3b in the supplemental mate-
rial). By the end of the experimental period, the average nitrate 
concentration across the oxidized HA column was 115 M, sug-
gesting a 54% reduction of the introduced nitrate based upon the </p>

<p>observed 1:1 mixing ratio of the media. Similarly to the donor-free 
column, there was a minimal nitrate gradient along the length of 
the column by the end of the operation (124, 105, 110, and 
122 M for ports 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively), suggesting that the 
majority of the microbial nitrate reduction was limited to the area 
between the injection ports and sampling port 1. Nitrite produc-
tion (0 M to 21.9 M) was limited and transient. Fe(III) back-
titration revealed that the oxidized HA medium contained a mod-
erate amount of reduced functionalities amounting to 448.7 
37.8 reducing microequivalents (Eq). Reducing equivalents 
were also detected in samples collected from the oxidized HA 
columns at ports 1 and 4 (Fig. 3a). Over time, the column com-
munity was capable of more rapidly oxidizing introduced HA mi-
croequivalents (Fig. 3a). By the end of the experimental time pe-
riod, essentially all reduced microequivalents were oxidized 
immediately at port 1, suggesting development of a HA-oxidizing 
community colocalized with the most active zone of apparent ni-
trate reduction near the point of donor medium injection. Assum-
ing a five-electron transfer to dinitrogen gas and accounting for 
1:1 mixing of the media, oxidation of these reduced functionalities 
in donor medium (224 Eq) accounted for approximately 33% of 
the total observed nitrate reduction observed in acceptor medium 
(135 M; 675 Eq) within the oxidized HA column. The remain-
ing nitrate reduction may be accounted for by the intrinsic elec-
tron donating capacity of inoculum soil, degradation of intro-
duced HA, or degradation of labile organics associated with HA. 
(iv) Reduced HA column. The greatest extent of nitrate reduc-
tion was observed in the reduced HA treatment (Fig. 2; see Fig. S3c </p>

<p>FIG 2 Effective influent nitrate concentration (accounting for dilution) and </p>

<p>measured effluent nitrate concentration throughout operation in columns 
treated with no electron donor, oxidized HA, or reduced HA electron donor 
medium. </p>

<p>FIG 3 Reduced functional group content of oxidized (a) and reduced (b) HA treatments over time at ports 1 and 4 of each column. Time is measured as days </p>

<p>after the addition of an electron donor and is shown on the x axes. Reduced functionality (in microequivalents) is given on the y axes. </p>

<p>Humic Acid-Oxidizing, Nitrate-Reducing Bacteria </p>

<p>July/August 2011 Volume 2 Issue 4 e00044-11 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 3 </p>

<p>in the supplemental material). Again, there was a limited nitrate 
gradient along the length of the column by the end of operation 
(40, 40, 23, and 53 M for ports 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively) with an 
average concentration of 39 M, indicating 84% reduction of the 
theoretically present nitrate when accounting for mixing of the 
media (Fig. 2). Similarly to the other columns, nitrite concentra-
tions were low, between 0 and 19 M throughout the column 
matrix over the experimental time period (data not shown). 
Reduced HA medium contained 1,053.7 30.2 reducing Eq 
in reduced humic moieties, which was equivalent to 527 reducing 
Eq upon 1:1 dilution in the column. Essentially all of these re-
ducing equivalents were oxidized at port 1, near the donor injec-
tion point, by the end of the experimental time period (Fig. 3b). 
Assuming complete reduction of nitrate to N 2 (5-electron trans-
fer), the extent of HA oxidation accounts for approximately 40% 
of the total nitrate reduction observed in the reduced HA column, 
suggesting that HA oxidation was a significant nitrate reduction 
driver in the experimental system. 
(v) Electron balance. As illustrated in the no-donor control 
column and calculated for HA-treated columns, donor species 
intrinsic to soil as well as potential degradation of HA or HA-
associated organics, supported nitrate reduction in each column 
system. Nevertheless, the presence of reduced HA functionalities 
increased the nitrate reduction capacity of column systems, ac-
counting for up to 40% of total observed respiratory activity. The 
difference in nitrate reduction between oxidized and reduced col-
umn treatments (211 M to 135 M) is approximately 76 M, 
corresponding to 380 Eq of additional electron transfer, assum-
ing production of dinitrogen gas. The additional reduced func-
tionalities in the reduced HA treatment relative to the oxidized 
treatment (approximately 303 Eq accounting for dilution) 
therefore accounts for approximately 80% of the additional ni-
trate reduction observed. This correlation implies that the addi-
tional electron donating capacity of the reduced HA treatment can 
be attributed to the enhanced content of reduced functional 
groups. 
Relative to the no-donor control, the oxidized HA treatment 
supported a greater extent of microbial nitrate reduction. The 
additional nitrate reduction was partially accounted for by the 
intrinsic reduced functionalities observed for HA. 
(vi) Possible role for iron content of HA. The amount of elec-
tron donating capacity attributable to the iron content [Fe(II)] of 
the HA is expected to be small relative to the electron donating 
capacity attributable to reduced organic functional groups. In un-
diluted donor media, the reduced HA treatment contained ap-
proximately 1,054 Eq of reduced functionalities as calculated by 
back-titration. Meanwhile, the total maximum iron content of 
reduced HA solution was 125 M based upon technical specifica-
tions of the reagent. Even if all of the iron in the reduced HA 
treatment were in the ferrous form, Fe(II) would account for only 
12% of the total electron donating capacity. 
In general, concentrations of Fe(II) detected at ports 1 and 4 of 
the HA column treatments were low (39 to 102 M) relative to the 
reduced organic functional group content of donor media. Addi-
tionally, Fe(II) concentrations detected at ports 1 and 4 were sim-
ilar between the reduced HA treatment (39 to 102 M) and the 
oxidized HA treatment (40 to 98 M). Together with calculation 
of total iron content in the donor media above, these observations 
suggest that Fe(II) does not account for a substantial portion of </p>

<p>the difference in respiratory activity observed between oxidized 
and reduced HA treatments. 
PhyloChip microbial community analysis. To discern which 
bacterial taxa were specifically associated with the reduced HA 
treatment, the microbial community from port 1, where most 
NHOx activity took place, was characterized across the three col-
umn treatments upon completion of the experiment. DNA was 
extracted in three replicate samples from the no-donor control 
column (control), oxidized HA column (oxidized), reduced HA 
column (reduced), as well as from the initial inoculum (inocu-
lum). The isolated DNA was combined for each treatment and 
PCR amplified with archaeal and bacterial primers, and the com-
munity was characterized using PhyloChip as previously de-
scribed (31). 
The four samples contained a diverse microbial community, 
which varied from the initial inoculum in richness, composition, 
and distribution based on column amendment. In the HA-treated 
columns, the richness of the bacterial community decreased from 
the initial inoculum (1,559 operational taxonomic units [OTUs]) 
in the reduced HA column (18%; 1,343 OTUs) and in the oxi-
dized HA column (15%; 1,394 OTUs), while richness slightly 
increased in the nondonor control (5%; 1,638 taxa). In contrast 
to the bacterial community, the richness, composition, and distri-
bution of the archaeal community after HA treatment did not 
differ from that of the initial inoculum. 
To better characterize the response of HA treatment on specific 
bacterial taxa, a subtractive analysis using 16S rRNA gene hybrid-
ization intensity scores from each of the oxidized and reduced HA 
columns relative to the control column was performed. Twelve 
phyla of the Bacteria domain increased in relative abundance in 
both HA-treated columns compared to the control column (see 
Fig. S4 in the supplemental material). Of these phyla, the Acido-
bacteria, Actinobacteria, Bacteroidetes, Firmicutes, and Proteobac-
teria were most enriched in response to HA treatment. Together, 
the decrease in bacterial OTU richness coupled with an increase of 
specific bacterial taxa implies that the HA impart a selective pres-
sure on the bacterial community that increases the dominance of 
specific bacterial OTUs. 
To visualize the bacterial response to HA treatment, we con-
structed a phylogenetic tree with 16S rRNA gene sequences from 
the five most enriched phyla (365 total OTUs) relative to the no-
donor control (Fig. 4). The Acidobacteria phylum was nearly 
evenly enriched in both the oxidized and reduced HA columns 
(purple shading), while others like the Firmicutes (reduced; red 
shading) and Bacteroidetes (oxidized; blue shading) were enriched 
exclusively in one HA-treated column and not the other. Of the 66 
Firmicutes sequences enriched by HA treatment, 97% (64 OTUs) 
were identified in the reduced HA column and only 3% (2 OTUs) 
were identified in the oxidized HA column. On the other hand, 20 
of the 21 (95%) enriched Bacteroidetes sequences were identified 
in the oxidized column, while only 3 Bacteroidetes OTUs (14%) 
were enriched in the reduced column (Fig. 4). 
Unlike the Acidobacteria, Firmicutes, and Bacteroidetes, which 
had a phylum level response to HA treatment, the Actinobacteria 
and Proteobacteria response varied within each phylum. The Be-
taproteobacteria exhibited a class level response, with all of the 
sequences detected in the columns being enriched in the reduced 
HA column, indicating a functional role for these organisms in 
HA oxidation (Fig. 4). The Alphaproteobacteria demonstrated a 
discrete family level response to HA treatment, with certain orders </p>

<p>Van Trump et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
July/August 2011 Volume 2 Issue 4 e00044-11 </p>

<p>like the Bradyrhizobiales and Rhizobiales predominantly enriched 
in the oxidized column, while the enrichment of Caulobacterales 
and Sphigomonadales taxa was found only in the reduced column. 
Although members of the Gammaproteobacteria, Actinobacteria, 
and, to an extent, Deltaproteobacteria did increase in proportional 
abundance in HA-treated columns relative to the control column, 
this response was stochastic and did not corroborate phylogenetic 
affiliation (Fig. 4). The Geobacteraceae, in the Deltaproteobacteria, 
were a notable exception to this trend, as they were exclusively 
enriched in the reduced HA column (Fig. 4) and decreased in the </p>

<p>oxidized treatment relative to the control. Collectively, the Phy-
loChip results uncover much broader bacterial phylogenetic di-
versity associated with HA environments than has been previously 
observed. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>These studies illustrate the prevalence and diversity of nitrate-
reducing, HA-oxidizing bacteria in agricultural soils. Likewise, 
data presented here track the oxidation of reduced HA in com-
plex, advective flow systems, as well as microbial community shifts </p>

<p>FIG 4 A maximum likelihood tree constructed from 16S rRNA PhyloChip sequences and selected isolates illustrates the phylogenetic position of taxa enriched </p>

<p>in abundance in columns treated with humic substance relative to the no-donor control column. To differentiate the response to HA treatment, PhyloChip-
identified OTUs are shown by small purple circles if they were enriched in both the reduced and oxidized HA treatments, while the OTUs are shown by small red 
circles if they were enriched in the reduced HA treatments only and shown by small blue circles if they were enriched in the oxidized HA treatments only. A similar 
color scheme also identifies the 16S rRNA sequences of bacteria isolated as part of this study (numbered 8 to 14, 23, 24, 2 and 6), as well as bacterial isolates 
previously reported to be capable of HA redox reactions (remaining isolate numbers) (Materials and Methods). The colored pie-shaped wedges correspond to 
taxa with a collective HA response, with those increasing in reduced humic substance column (red wedge), oxidized humic substance column (blue wedge), or 
both columns (purple wedge) denoted. Bar, 300 inferred nucleotide changes per position rRNA gene sequence. </p>

<p>Humic Acid-Oxidizing, Nitrate-Reducing Bacteria </p>

<p>July/August 2011 Volume 2 Issue 4 e00044-11 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 5 </p>

<p>associated with HA treatments. Taken together, these results sug-
gest that a large, diverse, and potentially active population of 
nitrate-dependent humic acid-oxidizing bacteria exist in agricul-
tural soils and that specific organisms may respond to the presence 
of HA. 
Phylogenetically diverse NHOx microorganisms have already 
been shown to be common in nonagricultural soils, wetlands, and 
marine sediments (21). Similar ubiquity and diversity of NHOx 
populations were observed in this study which utilized source soils 
collected from a limited geographical area and differing only in 
plant cover or fertilizer treatment. The populations of NHOx ob-
served in this study varied between 10 4 cells g 1 soil (native grass-
land soil) and 10 6 cells g 1 soil (forest and corn plot soil). Notably, 
MPN-based studies of heterotrophic nitrate-reducing bacteria in 
agricultural soils routinely reveal populations between 10 4 and 
10 6 cells g 1 soil, in the same log range as the MPN analysis per-
formed here (32, 33). Although total heterotrophic nitrate-
reducing bacterial populations were not enumerated in this study, 
it is plausible that a significant portion of culturable nitrate-
respiring organisms present in agricultural soils are capable of HA 
oxidation. Many of the isolates in this study were members of the 
Alcaligenes or Pseudomonas genera, which have routinely been iso-
lated as denitrifying organisms from agricultural and rhizosphere 
soils (1, 32, 34). This observation highlights the potential cultur-
ing bias inherent to MPN and isolation analyses but suggests that 
previously described denitrifying bacteria in soil from plots con-
taining plants may also prove capable of HA oxidation. 
Native microbial populations in corn plot soil oxidized re-
duced functional groups within HA coupled to nitrate reduction 
in an advective system. The presence of reduced functional groups 
increased the electron donating capacity of HA, and the reduced 
functional group content roughly correlated with the difference in 
oxidation state between similar HA treatments. However, addi-
tion of either HA always supported a greater extent of nitrate 
reduction than would be expected based solely upon oxidation of 
the reduced functional group content alone. This discrepancy per-
sists when electron donors intrinsic to the soil were accounted for 
in no-donor control systems. One potential explanation for this 
observation is microbial degradation of HA or HA-associated or-
ganics. Enhanced denitrification in response to humic amend-
ments has been illustrated for soils and wetland or riverbed sedi-
ments (7, 14, 35, 36). These studies did not generally discriminate 
between degradative oxidation of humic materials and nondegra-
dative oxidation of reduced functional groups. Although HA were 
potentially slowly degraded in column systems studied here, oxi-
dation of reduced functional groups still accounted for a signifi-
cant percentage of the nitrate respired in both oxidized and re-
duced HA columns (up to 40%). 
There are few studies examining the influence of humic acids 
on bacterial communities in the literature. Here, a 16S rRNA 
gene-based phylogenetic microarray characterized the effect of 
oxidized and reduced HA treatment on the resident bacterial 
community in agricultural soil to better understand the role of 
reduced HA on bacterial communities. Specific bacterial se-
quences enriched in the reduced HA column included members 
of the Acidobacteria, Firmicutes, Betaproteobacteria, Caulobactera-
les, and Sphingomonadales of the Alphaproteobacteria and Geobac-
teraceae of the Deltaproteobacteria (Fig. 4). 
Of these taxa, only the Acidobacteria contained a majority of 
sequences which were also enriched in the oxidized HA-treated </p>

<p>column. A survey exploring the relative abundance of bacterial 
phyla within 71 soils from a range of ecosystems revealed a strong 
and ubiquitous inverse relationship between carbon availability 
and Acidobacteria abundance (37). Consequently, it is important 
to note that the enrichment of 16S rRNA gene sequences in this 
column study may not be a direct result of HA oxidation and 
reduction but an artifact of the microbial habitat created by the 
addition of HA (37). However, it is well documented that isolated 
members of the Acidobacteria are capable of both oxidation and 
reduction of quinone moieties (20), which suggests a physiologi-
cal role in HA redox reactions for the Acidobacteria in these HA-
amended columns. Unlike the Acidobacteria, Firmicutes sequences 
were identified only in reduced HA-treated columns. This selec-
tive enrichment of Firmicutes only in reduced HA columns sug-
gests a functional role for these species in oxidation of reduced HA 
functional groups. 
Within the Proteobacteria, each class reported a unique re-
sponse to reduced HA. All 25 taxa that were identified as enriched 
relative to the control in the Betaproteobacteria were identified in 
the reduced HA column, with only five of these taxa increasing in 
the oxidized HA column. Correspondingly, a majority of the bac-
teria isolated as part of this study supported this finding, with 
seven of the NHOx isolates belonging to the Betaproteobacteria 
within the order Burkholderiales. Two of our isolates were closely 
related to Ralstonia sp., and five isolates were most closely related 
to Achromobacter sp. Further supporting our findings based on 
pure culture and community results, a recent study also identified 
the dominance of 16S rRNA gene sequences from the Burkhold-
eriales, Ralstonia, and Cupriavidus spp. in reduced HA biofilms 
but not detected in controls not treated with humic acid (38). 
In the Deltaproteobacteria, enrichment of members of the Geo-
bacteraceae was consistent with previous studies demonstrating 
microbial oxidation of humic substances by several members of 
this family (20). However, it is also well documented that these 
bacteria are also capable of reduction of humic substances (39, 
40), yet none of these members were enriched in the oxidized 
column relative to the control. The presence of excess nitrate in 
the system may have thermodynamically precluded (41, 42) or 
reduced the selective importance of HA-reducing respiratory pro-
cesses by these organisms. 
Like the Deltaproteobacteria, certain orders of the Alphaproteo-
bacteria phylum (Caulobacterales and Sphigomonadales) were en-
riched only in reduced HA columns. These taxa are routinely iso-
lated as members of the rhizosphere, but little is known regarding 
their role in humic substance redox reactions. It is plausible that 
the enrichment of these 16S rRNA gene sequences and our isolates 
reflect a previously unidentified role for alphaproteobacterial rhi-
zosphere bacteria in HA oxidation coupled to denitrification. 
Collectively, the results from our culture-dependent and 
-independent research suggest that a diverse set of microorgan-
isms may be capable of oxidizing humic material coupled to ni-
trate reduction in agricultural soils. Furthermore, these results 
suggest that HA oxidation can potentially account for a significant 
percentage of denitrification observed in these soil types. Future 
studies examining the role of reduced humic materials in donating 
electrons for microbial respiration and the influence of these com-
pounds on the structure and function of microbial communities 
are warranted. </p>

<p>Van Trump et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
July/August 2011 Volume 2 Issue 4 e00044-11 </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Medium techniques. Basal, bicarbonate-buffered medium (pH 6.8 to 7.0) 
was utilized for MPN and isolate characterization studies. Media were 
prepared anaerobically under 80:20 N 2 -CO 2 headspace as previously de-
scribed (43). Where noted, quinone-or hydroquinone-containing media 
were prepared by adding AQDS at concentrations of 5 mM total an-
thraquinone. To prepare AH 2 DS, AQDS solutions were degassed and 
then bubbled with 80:20 H 2 -CO 2 in the presence of palladium-coated 
aluminum chips (21, 44). When a red color developed, the medium was 
bubbled for 20 min with 80:20 N 2 -CO 2 to remove dissolved H 2 and sub-
sequently decanted away from the palladium into pressure tubes or serum 
bottles before autoclaving. Acetate (0.1 mM) and nitrate (10.0 mM) were 
added as sodium salts from anoxic sterile stock solutions. 
The medium for column experiments was comprised of 10 mM phos-
phate buffer (pH 7.2) amended with 5 ml liter 1 trace mineral solution 
(45). The medium was boiled and cooled under N 2 gas and then sealed 
and autoclaved in 2-liter bottles. Electron acceptor medium contained 
nitrate (1.0 or 0.5 mM) added from stock solutions. Different electron 
donor media (donor-free, oxidized HA, and reduced HA media) were 
prepared for each column treatment. Donor-free medium consisted of 
phosphate-buffered water and mineral solution only. Oxidized HA treat-
ments were prepared by adding 0.5 g liter 1 of Aldrich HA to previously 
degassed and cooled media prior to autoclaving. Reduced HA treatments 
were prepared by adding 0.5 g liter 1 of the same HA stock to degassed 
medium, chemically reducing the HA as previously described (44), and 
bubbling the medium for 20 minutes with N 2 to remove H 2 prior to 
autoclaving. Each donor bottle was supplemented with 200 M bromide 
tracer from stock aqueous solutions of sodium salts. 
Analytical techniques. Anions were quantified by ion chromatogra-
phy on a Dionex DX500 employing a CD20 conductivity detector sup-
pressed with an ASRS-ULTRA II 4-mm system. Nitrate and nitrite con-
centrations were resolved on an IonPac AS9-HC anion-exchange column, 
with a 9 mM Na 2 CO 3 mobile phase at a flow rate of 1 ml min 1 . AH 2 DS 
and reduced humic acid concentrations were analyzed by ferric citrate 
back-titration or spectrophotometrically as previously described (21, 39, 
40). Total anthraquinone concentrations were determined by aerating 
filtered samples and quantifying AQDS as previously described (29). 
Fe(II) was quantified with a ferrozine assay as previously described (46). 
MPN analysis and isolation/characterization of pure cultures. A 
family farm in the Platte River valley near Linwood, NE, was chosen as a 
sampling site. Soils were collected from the top 12 inches of plots contain-
ing corn or soy (either amended or unamended with swine manure in the 
previous growing season), as well as from native bluegrass grasslands and 
wooded areas containing ash, elm, oak, and cedar trees adjacent to the 
cultivated areas. The samples were sealed in autoclaved mason jars, 
brought to the laboratory, and subjected to most probable number 
(MPN) analysis for nitrate-reducing, AH 2 DS-oxidizing microorganisms 
as previously described, with an 87-day incubation period (21). Nitrate 
reduction and nitrite production in MPN tubes was measured via anion 
analysis of 0.2-m-filtered subsamples from the 10 3 dilution series. Pure 
cultures of AH 2 DS-oxidizing, nitrate-reducing cells were obtained utiliz-
ing an agar shaking tube method previously described (21). Selected iso-
lates were characterized for AH 2 DS-oxidizing, nitrate-reducing capabili-
ties in the presence of 100 M acetate as a suitable carbon source. 
Phylogenetic analysis of isolates. Genomic DNA (gDNA) was ex-
tracted from isolate growth cultures oxidizing AH 2 DS with a MoBio 
Power Soil DNA kit (MoBio Laboratories Inc., Solana Beach, CA) per the 
manufacturer's protocol. The 16S rRNA gene was amplified from gDNA 
extracts with universal primers 27F (5=-AGAGTTTGATCCTGGCTCAG) 
and 1492R (5=-GGTTACCTTGTTACGACTT) (F stands for forward and 
R stands for reverse in the primer names). 16S rRNA gene amplification 
was performed with Takara Ex Taq HS according to the manufacturer's 
protocol. Isolation of genomic DNA, 16S rRNA gene-specific PCR, and 
sequencing of PCR products were conducted as described previously (27, 
31). 16S rRNA gene sequences were aligned with <rs id="software-4" type="software">MUSCLE</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">3.6</rs> (47), and </p>

<p>Bayesian analysis of 16S rRNA gene phylogeny was completed with 
<rs id="software-8" type="software">MrBayes</rs> <rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-number">3.2</rs> (48, 49). The program was run with four chains until the 
standard deviation of the split frequencies was stabilized below 0.01, in 
this case for 450,000 generations, with a sample frequency of 1,000. The 
first 25% of the samples were discarded for accurate estimation of the 
posterior probability distribution of the summary tree. 
Humic column experiments. Up-flow glass column reactors were 
constructed as diagrammed in Fig. S1 in the supplemental material. The 
columns were filled with a matrix containing 1 N HCl-washed, autoclaved 
3-mm-diameter glass beads (Walter Stern no. 100C) inoculated 10% (wt/ 
wt) by manual mixing with corn plot soil (~750 ml total matrix volume/ 
column). The columns were sparged with He, sealed with rubber stop-
pers, and covered with aluminum foil. The columns were incubated for 
2 days with approximately 370 ml of medium containing 500 M nitrate 
to allow for microbial adherence and then equilibrated for flow rate and 
nitrate breakthrough over 7 days by continually injecting port A with 
electron acceptor medium (1.0 mM nitrate) and port B with donor-free 
medium (average total flow rate of 3.1 0.2 ml/h). After 7 days, the 
nitrate concentrations in continually injected acceptor medium were re-
duced to 0.5 mM, and donor treatments commenced through continual 
injection of donor medium at port B. Donor treatments were as follows: 
donor-free medium, 0.5 g/liter oxidized Aldrich HA medium, and 0.5 g/ 
liter reduced Aldrich HA medium. Column performance was assessed by 
frequent retention time and total medium flowthrough measurements. 
Nitrate, nitrite, bromide, and reduced HA content were analyzed at time 
points along the length of each column at ports 1, 2, 3, and 4. Reduced HA 
content was defined as the difference between Fe(II) generated in back-
titration reactions and Fe(II) present in the native initial sample prior to 
Fe(III) citrate addition and was calculated as follows: reduced HA 
Fe(II) back-titration -Fe(II) initial . 
PhyloChip. To characterize changes in the bacterial community after 
humic acid treatment, DNA was extracted from the initial inoculum and 
from port 1 of each of three columns (no donor, oxidized HA, and re-
duced HA). Due to the high humic content of the soil, the previously 
described extraction protocol (31) was modified to increase DNA quality 
and yields. Specifically, 50 l of 0.1 M aluminum ammonium sulfate was 
added as flocculent to the cetyltrimethylammonium bromide (CTAB) 
extraction buffer to minimize coextraction of humic acid material, and 
nucleic acids were precipitated for two hours at room temperature with 
polyethylene glycol (PEG) rather than isopropanol (31). Extractions three 
times for each soil sample with pellets from each sample combined and 
resuspended in 100 l of Tris-EDTA (TE) buffer. Coextraction of humic 
material in samples from the HA-treated columns resulted in brown re-
suspended DNA that failed to amplify by PCR. To remove humic sub-
stance contamination from the DNA, all the resuspended DNA samples 
were purified using the MoBio Power Soil DNA kit according to the man-
ufacturer's protocol apart from the fact that the samples were gently 
mixed rather than beadbeated or vortexed. DNA quality and quantifica-
tion were assessed by gel visualization. PCR amplification was conducted 
as previously described (Wrighton et al. [31]); the amplifications over a 
gradient using 8 different annealing temperatures and nondegenerate 
primers and were restricted to 25 cycles to minimize PCR bias. The 
amount of PCR product loaded onto the chips, target fragmentation, 
biotin labeling, PhyloChip hybridization, scanning, and staining, as well 
as background subtraction, noise calculation, and detection and quanti-
fication criteria were based on the protocol given in reference 30. 
PhyloChip arrays from the initial inoculum, no-donor control col-
umn, oxidized humic substance column, and reduced humic substance 
column. For bacterial richness, a taxon was considered present in the 
sample when 90% or more of its assigned probe pairs for its correspond-
ing probe set were positive (positive fraction of 0.90). To determine the 
differences in bacterial community composition, nonmetric multidimen-
sional scaling (NMDS) was performed on PhyloChip hybridization data 
using the statistical package Primer V (Plymouth Marine Laboratory, 
Plymouth, United Kingdom). To discriminate the bacterial populations </p>

<p>Humic Acid-Oxidizing, Nitrate-Reducing Bacteria </p>

<p>July/August 2011 Volume 2 Issue 4 e00044-11 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 7 </p>

<p>enriched in the humic acid-treated columns, a subtractive analysis be-
tween the controls and humic acid-treated columns was performed. 
With the intention of illustrating the phylogenetic response to HA 
across the 5 most enriched phyla, a maximum likelihood tree was con-
structed using the 365 16S rRNA sequences from the five dominant phyla 
demonstrated to be enriched relative to the control in either or both col-
umns treated with humic acid. The sequences were aligned with <rs id="software-6" type="software">MUSCLE</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">3.6</rs> (Edgar), and phylogenetic analysis was performed with <rs type="software">RAxML</rs> (Sta-
matakis). 16S rRNA sequences of previously isolated humic substance-
oxidizing and -reducing bacteria and the bacteria characterized as part of 
this study (numbered isolates 8 to 14, 23, 24, and 26) are also included in 
the phylogenetic analyses and resulting tree. Isolate sequences are num-
bered as follows (accession numbers are given in the parentheses; all ac-
cession numbers are for the GenBank databank, except for accession 
numbers beginning with NC_, which are for the NCBI databank): 1, De-
chloromonas sp. strain MissR (AF170357); 2, Dechloromonas aromatica 
(CP000089); 3, Dechloromonas sp. strain JJ (AY032611); 4, Dechloromo-
nas agitata (AF047462); 5, Azospira (Dechlorosoma) suillum (AF170348); 
6, Azoarcus evansii (X77679); 7, Azoarcus sp. strain HA (AF482683); 8, 
strain C7b; 9, strain C7a; 10, strain B7; 11, strain B2; 12, strain Bcol1; 13, 
strain A4; 14, strain A5; 15, Shewanella oneidensis MR-1 (NC_004347); 16, 
Shewanella algae isolate 62 (DQ883817); 17, Escherichia coli K-12 
(NC_010473); 18, Pseudomonas sp. strain NMX (AF482685); 19, strain 
A7, 20, Pseudomonas sp. strain BU (AF482684); 21, Marinobacter sp. 
strain SBS (AF482686); 22, Paracoccus denitrificans (Y16927); 23, Agro-
bacterium sp. strain PB (AF482682); 24, strain D5; 25, strain D1; 26, strain 
A1; 27, Dechlorospirillum sp. strain VDY (EF405824); 28, Dechlorospiril-
lum sp. strain WD (AF170352); 29, Geothrix fermentans (EF405824); 30, 
Geobacter metallirreducens (AF170352); and 31, Myxobacterium sp. strain 
KC (AF482687). The isolate sequences are color coded based on the re-
ported humic substance response. A phylogenetic response is defined 
when 85% of the OTUs in a group respond uniformly to HA treatment. 
Taxon level responses are denoted with shading with colors similar to 
those used for the OTU designations. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Lonnie Spies for allowing access to his farm and surrounding 
properties. 
Funding for K.C.W. is through the UC Berkeley Sustainable Products 
&amp; Solutions (SPS) Program, and the Chang Tien Fellowship. Research on 
microbial humic substance oxidation in the laboratory of J.D.C. is sup-
ported through grant 2005-35107-16237 by the Natural Research Initia-
tive of the USDA. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIAL </p>

<p>Supplemental material for this article may be found at http://mbio.asm.org 
/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1128/mBio.00044-11/-/DCSupplemental. 
Figure S1, DOC file, 0.408 MB. 
Figure S2, DOC file, 0.220 MB. 
Figure S3, DOC file, 0.673 MB. 
Figure S4, DOC file, 0.704 MB. </p>





<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
July/August 2011 Volume 2 Issue 4 e00044-11 </p>



<p>Humic Acid-Oxidizing, Nitrate-Reducing Bacteria </p>

<p>July/August 2011 Volume 2 Issue 4 e00044-11 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 9 </p>

</text></tei>