<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3236159" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Introduction: Vascular pedicle width (VPW), a measurement obtained from a chest radiograph (CR), 
is thought to be an indicator of circulating blood volume. To date there are only a handful of studies that 
demonstrate a correlation between high VPW and volume overload, each utilizing different VPW 
values and CR techniques. Our objective was to determine a mean VPW measurement from erect and 
supine CRs and to determine whether VPW correlates with volume overload. </p>

<p>Methods: MEDLINE database, Web of Science, and the Cochrane Central Register of Controlled 
Trials were searched electronically for relevant articles. References from the original and review 
publications selected electronically were manually searched for additional relevant articles. Two 
investigators independently reviewed relevant articles for inclusion criteria and data extraction. Mean 
VPW measurements from both supine and erect CRs and their correlation with volume overload were 
calculated. </p>

<p>Results: Data from 8 studies with a total of 363 subjects were included, resulting in mean VPW 
measurements of 71 mm (95% confidence interval [CI] 64.9-77.3) and 62 mm (95% CI 49.3-75.1) for 
supine and erect CRs, respectively. The correlation coefficients for volume overload and VPW were 
0.81 (95% CI 0.74-0.86) for both CR techniques and 0.81 (95% CI 0.72-0.87) for supine CR and 0.80 
(95% CI 0.69-0.87) for erect CR, respectively. </p>

<p>Articles were selected if VPW was measured on CR in 
patients in either erect or supine positions and if volume 
overload had been evaluated by invasive and/or noninvasive 
techniques, including pulmonary artery occlusion pressure 
(PAOP), global end diastolic volume, intrathoracic blood 
volume index, left atrial emptying fraction (LAEF), or total 
blood volume. Studies that did not report a mean value or 
standard deviation (SD) were excluded. Two reviewers also 
independently assessed each included study and evaluated the 
quality of each article using the Jadad score. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>The mean VPW, SD, correlation coefficient, and sample 
size were obtained from each study. <rs id="software-1" type="software">Comprehensive meta-
analysis</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">2.2</rs> and <rs id="software-2" type="software">Stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">11</rs> (College Station, Texas) 
were used for data analysis. 
26 The summary effect of mean 
VPW (weighted mean) was estimated by assigning weight as 
the inverse of its variance method in the fixed effects of meta-
analysis. 
27 A random effect model, utilizing the DerSimonian 
and Laird method, estimated the summary effect of mean 
VPW. 
28 Similarly, fixed and random effects were estimated for 
cardiothoracic ratio (CTR) as well as correlation coefficiency. 
Two subgroups, erect and supine, were analyzed for VPW 
values. The Q-test, which is a chi-square method, was used for 
comparison between these 2 groups based on Cochran 
method. 
29 A P value less than 0.05 was considered a 
statistically significant difference between groups. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Eight studies (2 retrospective and 6 prospective) with 363 
subjects were included in the meta-analysis (Table 1). With the 
exception of 2 studies that did not mention who measured </p>

<p>VPW, in most studies, VPW was measured by radiologists. </p>

<p>15,18 </p>

<p>Volume overload and/or pulmonary edema were evaluated 
using either invasive or noninvasive methods, as mentioned 
above. Only VPWs measured in volume overload and/or 
pulmonary edema patients are included in this meta-analysis. 
Seven studies were excluded because they either belonged to 
review papers or contained a lack of reportable data </p>

<p>6,11,20-24 </p>

<p>(refer to Figure 3 for flow diagram of selection). 
The meta-analysis results of VPW measurement in patients 
with volume overload are shown in Table 2. VPW 
measurements from 2 CR groups were compared: those with 
erect and supine views. The mean VPW value was 62.2 mm 
(95% confidence interval [CI] 49.3-75.1 mm) in the erect 
group and 71.1 mm (95% CI 64.9-77.3 mm) in the supine 
group. VPW measurements between the erect and supine CR 
groups were statistically significant (Q value ¼ 77.3, P , 
0.001). Regardless of CR technique, the larger the VPW value 
measured, the higher the change in the patient's volume 
overload (r ¼ 0.81, Q ¼ 0.06, P ¼ 0.volume overload contribute to a relatively high interstudy 
variability, lowered power, and statistical effect. Additionally, 
there was no consistent gold standard to which volume overload 
was measured, making this study extremely hard to analyze 
quantitatively when compared to VPW values. 
A funnel plot is designed to check the existence of 
publication bias in meta-analysis. Studies with publication bias 
usually obtain an asymmetric funnel plot. 
30 We did funnel plots 
on both erect and supine mean VPW (data not shown). Our 
results showed that the supine VPW measurement has less 
publication bias than did the erect VPW measurement. 
However, publication bias is only one of the possible 
explanations for funnel plot asymmetry. Factors that can affect 
the funnel plot asymmetry include but are not limited to 
language bias, citation bias, the size of effect differing 
according to study size, and poor methodological design of 
small studies, etc. 
31,32 As a result of the limited data, this meta-
analysis included both prospective and retrospective studies. In 
the erect VPW group, there are only 2 small studies included, 
which could significantly affect the results and cause an 
asymmetric funnel plot. 
Studies that reported only cut-off VPW values chosen from 
receiver operating characteristic curves are not included in this 
meta-analysis as a result of lack of VPW mean and SD 
values. 
11,20-24 This could result in eschewed data and poor 
meta-analysis due to incomplete enrollment of all studies. In 
addition, although bigger VPW values correlated with higher 
PAOP, wider inferior vena cava (IVC) diameter, higher LAEF, 
and worsening total circulating blood volume, because of the 
limited numbers of subjects enrolled, no large validation studies 
were performed individually. </p>

<p>33-51 </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
The data from this meta-analysis report VPW values from 
both erect and supine CR techniques that support the 
correlation between volume overload and increased VPW 
measurements. 
11,12,33-35 Prior studies were limited by small 
sample size, varying VPW measurements, and CR technique 
(supine and erect). VPW was initially described using 72-inch 
erect periapical radiographs. However, supine CRs are 
commonly performed in critically ill patients using a portable 
radiograph machine. Thus, it is critical to address the difference 
in VPW values based on the position of the patient for CR. 
VPW measured 
11 on supine CRs in normal volunteers 
increased by 17% as a result of gravity. In addition, VPW 
values can be altered by respiratory effects or by subjects' 
previous medical problems, especially cardiovascular 
diseases. 
11 For these reasons, the accuracy of VPW 
measurements on supine CR and its correlation with volume 
status has been questioned. 
Four studies included in this meta-analysis used the supine 
CR technique for VPW measurements on subjects in the 
intensive care unit setting. Mean VPW values on supine CRs 
were significantly larger than in erect CRs (62 mm vs 71 mm, Q 
¼ 77.3, P , 0.001). Analysis of statistical heterogeneity is done 
using the Q statistic, which is a measure of the variability 
among studies related to the outcome variable. We chose the 
results from the random effect model on VPW value since the 
heterogeneity is presented (P , 0.001). In contrast, results of 
correlation coefficient from fixed-effects model are used 
because no statistically significant difference was found 
between studies (Q ¼ 0.06, P . 0.05). Our results indicate that 
different VPW cut-off values need to be considered when using </p>

<p>Figure 3. Flow diagram of search results for meta-analysis. </p>

<p>Address for Correspondence: Hao Wang, MD, PhD, JPS Health 
Network, Department of Emergency Medicine, 1500 S Main St, Fort 
Worth, TX 76104. E-mail: hwang01@jpshealth.org. </p>

<p>Conflicts of Interest: By the WestJEM article submission 
agreement, all authors are required to disclose all affiliations, </p>

<p>funding sources, and financial or management relationships that 
could be perceived as potential sources of bias. The authors 
disclosed none. </p>



<p>Wang et al 
Vascular Pedicle Width and Volume Overload </p>

<p>Volume XII, NO. 4 : November 2011 
Western Journal of Emergency Medicine </p>



<p>
Vascular Pedicle Width and Volume Overload 
Wang et al </p>

<p>Western Journal of Emergency Medicine 
Volume XII, NO. 4 : November 2011 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>