<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3731646" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The catalytic purification of automobile exhaust gases (CO, NO x and hydrocarbons) is one of the most 
practiced conversion processes used to lower the emissions and to reduce the air pollution. Nevertheless, the 
good performance of exhaust gas purification catalysts often requires the high consumption of noble metals 
such as platinum. Here we report that the Brønsted acid sites on the external surface of a microporous 
silicoaluminophosphate (SAPO) act as a promoter for exhaust gas purification, effectively cutting the 
loading amount of platinum in the catalyst without sacrifice of performance. It is revealed that in the 
Pt-loaded SAPO-CHA catalyst, there exists a remarkable synergistic effect between the Brønsted acid sites 
and the Pt nanoparticles, the former helping to adsorb and activate the hydrocarbon molecules for NO 
reduction during the catalytic process. The thermal stability of SAPO-CHA also makes the composite 
catalyst stable and reusable without activity decay. </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>he simultaneous catalytic removal of major pollutants CO, NO x and hydrocarbons (HCs) from the exhaust 
gases of a gasoline engine is an important conversion process to reduce the emissions of toxic gases from 
automobiles. Platinum-containing catalysts have attracted increasing attention in the past decades because 
of their superior activity as a catalyst not only for redox reactions but also for purification of automobile exhaust 
gases </p>

<p>1-5 </p>

<p>. Many researches have been focused on the development of Pt-loaded catalysts that are desired to 
effectively eliminate the emission of harmful gases under practical operation conditions </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>. Despite great efforts 
to date with significant successes, the good performance of catalysts usually leads to high consumption of 
expensive noble metals, and recovery of noble metals from spent catalysts is required. In general, the performance 
of a catalyst is also heavily dependent on the physical and chemical properties of its support, which should possess 
not only a considerable surface area to sustain a uniform dispersion of noble metals, but also strong interaction 
with the metals to promote the redox reactions 
6 . In this context, the selection of suitable supports is very critical in 
determining the performance and the cost of Pt-containing catalysts for purifying emission gases. 
To optimize catalyst supports for stabilizing Pt nanoparticles, materials that allow access to activating substrates 
and/or elevating the activity of Pt nanoparticles are preferred. Microporous crystalline silicoaluminophosphates 
(SAPOs) are an important class of molecular sieve materials which have been widely used in adsorption, separation 
and catalysis. Among the SAPOs, chabazite-type SAPO (SAPO-CHA) 
7 with small pores and fairly strong Brønsted 
acidity has shown excellent catalytic activity and shape selectivity in methanol-to-olefin (MTO) conversion 
8-10 and 
HC transformation </p>

<p>11-13 </p>

<p>. It is thus rather promising to integrate the catalytic activity of SAPO-CHA with rich 
Brønsted acid sites and Pt nanoparticles for efficient removal of automobile exhaust gases, which also contain HCs, 
under even mild conditions. Although previous studies have used SAPO-CHA containing metal cations for 
removal of NO x through a selective-catalytic-reduction (SCR) pathway </p>

<p>14-16 </p>

<p>, the exploitation of rich Brønsted acid 
sites in SAPO-CHA support for activating noble metal nanoparticles to simultaneously purify the major pollutants 
CO, NO x and HC of a gasoline engine emission has not been described yet. In this report, we demonstrate the 
remarkable promotion effect of Brønsted acid sites of SAPO-CHA on the catalytic performance of supported Pt 
catalyst for purification of automobile exhaust gases. Accordingly, the catalyst cost may be reduced markedly by 
decreasing the Pt-loading amount on the SAPO-CHA material without sacrifice of catalytic performance. </p>

<p>(AlPO-CHA) with similar CHA framework structure (Fig. S1) was 
also prepared as Brønsted acid-free reference material </p>

<p>17,18 </p>

<p>. In SAPO-
CHA, a part of the PO 4 tetrahedra are replaced by SiO 4 units, 
resulting in negative charges which may be balanced by extra-
framework protons, that is, Brønsted acid sites discussed in this 
work. Pt nanoparticles were loaded on the surface of AlPO-CHA 
and SAPO-CHA through an impregnation approach, and the 
resulting materials are designated as Pt/AlPO-CHA and Pt/SAPO-
CHA, respectively. For comparison, a Pt-loaded alumina material 
(Pt/Al 2 O 3 ) was also prepared similarly and used as a reference. Pt 
nanoparticles were mainly dispersed on the external surface of the 
molecular sieves as the size of Pt nanoparticles observed in the TEM 
image (Figure S2) is much larger that the pore size of the molecular 
sieves. </p>

<p>Distribution of Brønsted acid sites. The distribution of Brønsted 
acid sites was initially investigated by temperature-programmed 
desorption (TPD) measurements (Fig. 1a), where NH 3 and 
pyridine were used as the probe molecules. The NH 3 -TPD profiles 
with two strong desorption peaks at temperatures of 680 and 850 K 
reveal a rich amount of Brønsted acid sites on the surface of SAPO-
CHA based materials and also the Brønsted-acid-free nature of 
AlPO-CHA materials (Figure 1a). This observation has been 
doubly confirmed by the Fourier transform infrared (FTIR) 
spectra of dehydrated SAPO-CHA with strong absorptions at 3630 
and 3600 cm 
21 (Fig. S3). Pyridine molecules with a large dynamic 
diameter (0.65 nm) cannot diffuse into the micropores (window size 
0.43 nm) of SAPO-CHA, and were thus used as probe molecules to 
characterize the acidity of the external surfaces of SAPO-CHA. The 
strong signal at 1540 cm 
21 , arising from protonated pyridinium 
cations, in the FTIR spectrum (Fig. 1b) of pyridine-adsorbed 
samples indicates a substantial amount of Brønsted acid sites on </p>

<p>the external surface of SAPO-CHA, whilst such a signal disapp-
eared in the spectra of Brønsted-acid-free AlPO-CHA. </p>

<p>Chemical state of the Pt on the surface of various supports. The Pt 
nanoparticles are believed to be highly active in many impor-
tant catalytic reactions as compared with their oxide PtO 2 </p>

<p>19,20 </p>

<p>. For 
conventional Pt-containing catalysts (e.g. Pt/Al 2 O 3 ), a pre-activation 
process to reduce the PtO 2 component to metallic Pt has to be 
conducted at an elevated temperature before practical use and/or 
reuse, resulting in additional cost due to the consumption of H 2 
gas and electric energy. The stability of the metallic Pt should also 
be seriously considered in designing new sustainable catalysts. Both 
the X-ray absorption near-edge structure (XANES) spectra (Figure 
S4) and Fourier transformed extended X-ray absorption fine 
structure (EXAFS) spectra (Figure 1c) of the Pt species dispersed 
on SAPO-CHA and AlPO-CHA are similar to those of Pt foil, 
rather speaking for the formation of metallic Pt nanoparticles. As 
described previously, the Pt species on Al 2 O 3 exist mainly as Pt 
oxide </p>

<p>21,22 </p>

<p>. The representative schematic illustrations for the Pt 
species dispersed on different supports are shown in the inset of 
Fig. 1c. It can be envisaged that the nature of the support gives a 
significant impact on the state of Pt species generated on the support. 
No obvious reduction peaks were observed for Pt/SAPO-CHA and 
Pt/AlPO-CHA materials in the temperature-programmed reduction 
(TPR) experiments (Fig. S5), and this is to say that the high-
temperature activation process in H 2 is not essential for Pt/SAPO-
CHA catalyst. It is thus quite convenient for Pt/SAPO-CHA to be 
directly used in purification of automobile exhaust gases. </p>

<p>The catalytic performance. The catalytic activities of the Pt-loaded 
materials were tested in the purification of the exhaust gases of a 
gasoline engine. The conversions of exhaust gases (NO, CO and </p>

<p>Figure 1 | General characterization of Pt/AlPO-CHA, Pt/SAPO-CHA and Pt/Al 2 O 3 . (a) NH 3 -TPD profiles. There are rich Brønsted acid sites on </p>

<p>the internal and external surfaces of the as-prepared Pt/SAPO-CHA, while no such sites exist in the Pt/AlPO-CHA material. (b) FTIR spectra of pyridine-
adsorbed SAPO-CHA outgased at 573 K (red) and 373 K (green) and AlPO-CHA outgased at 573 K (black) and 373 K (blue). (c) Fourier-transformed 
EXAFS spectra (solid lines) along with theoretical fits (dashed lines), which indicate that the Pt species on SAPO-CHA and AlPO-CHA are mainly metal 
nanoparticles, whereas on Al 2 O 3 they are mainly Pt oxide. a.u. 5 arbitrary units. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 2349 | DOI: 10.1038/srep02349 </p>

<p>
C 3 H 6 ) over Pt/SAPO-CHA and control catalysts were monitored at 
gradually increased reaction temperatures. Previously, C 3 H 6 has 
been widely applied as a typical model of HCs to evaluate the 
catalytic performance of catalysts in purification of automobile 
exhaust gases, and it was thus used in this work accordingly. As 
shown in Figure 2, the conversions of C 3 H 6 , NO and CO over Pt/ 
SAPO-CHA are all higher than those of Pt/AlPO-CHA and Pt/Al 2 O 3 
with the same Pt-loading content (0.5 wt%). The temperature at a 
conversion of 50% of C 3 H 6 over Pt/SAPO-CHA is 549 K, nearly 100 
and 50 K lower than that over Pt/Al 2 O 3 and Pt/AlPO-CHA 
respectively (Fig. 2), while the temperature at a conversion of 90% 
of C 3 H 6 is about 578 K for Pt/SAPO-CHA, also much lower than 
those of Pt/AlPO-CHA (630 K) and Pt/Al 2 O 3 (655 K). Moreover, 
bare SAPO-CHA as the catalyst gave no conversion of C 3 H 6 , NO and 
CO, suggesting that only Pt particles acted as the active cites for such 
a catalytic reaction. The turnover frequencies (TOF) over Pt/SAPO-
CHA were calculated to be 0.014, 0.019 and 0.217 s 
21 respectively for 
C 3 H 6 , NO and CO at a temperature of 575 K. These TOF values are 
distinctly higher than those of all the other catalysts (including the 
Pt/Al 2 O 3 -aging material) used in this work, and than those of Pt-, 
Pd-, or Rh-NPs based catalysts reported in the literature under 
similar conditions (Table S1) </p>

<p>23-27 </p>

<p>. Furthermore, products of NO 
conversion have been identified through gas chromatograph (GC) 
and gas-phase FTIR measurements. As shown in Figure S6, typical IR 
bands of N 2 O gas at 2212 and 2235 cm 
21 were detected in the spectra 
of products catalyzed over Pt/AlPO-CHA and Pt/Al 2 O 3 , showing the 
moderate selectivity of these catalysts. The fact that the peaks of N 2 O 
gas were not present in the spectra of purified gases over Pt/SAPO-
CHA reveals the high selectivity of this catalyst in the purification of 
exhausting gases, again speaking for the advantage of SAPO-CHA as 
the catalyst support here. 
The content of Pt loaded also affects the catalytic performance of 
the resulting catalysts to a considerable extent (Fig. S7). The activity 
of the catalysts increased with increasing amount of Pt components. 
It is noteworthy that the catalytic performance of Pt/SAPO-CHA 
with a Pt loading as low as 0.25 wt% is comparable with that of Pt/ 
Al 2 O 3 with a Pt loading as high as 1.0 wt%. As an excellent catalyst 
support, SAPO-CHA can significantly reduce the amount of the 
noble metal Pt and thus the cost of the catalyst. </p>

<p>Discussion 
To find out how the Brønsted acid affects the catalytic activity, it is 
essential to understand the nature of the acid sites in the SAPO-CHA 
molecular sieve. Individual Brønsted acid site is a hydroxyl proton 
located at bridging oxygen between tetrahedrally coordinated silicon 
and aluminum atoms (Figure 3b). Previous studies indicated that 
adsorption of olefins (e.g. C 3 H 6 here) on Brønsted acid sites tend 
to be transformed to alkoxy species with a carbeniumion-like feature, 
which can undergo further reactions to become other derivative </p>

<p>products in various task-specific catalytic reactions </p>

<p>28-30 </p>

<p>. We thus 
calculated the structure of the SAPO-CHA using relativistic density 
functional theory (DFT) to elucidate the function of Brønsted acid in 
the catalytic transformation of C 3 H 6 . The simulation results suggest a 
very high electron density around the Brønsted acid sites (Fig. 3b), 
which facilitates the adsorption and activation of C 3 H 6 molecules for 
conversion into covalent alkoxy species in the catalytic reactions </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>. 
Moreover, the high electron density of the Pt nanoparticles will also 
be enhanced once Pt nanoparticles form a contact at the electron-
rich surface of SAPO-CHA, promising a possibility to improve the 
catalytic activity of Pt nanoparticles. The facts that the bare SAPO-
CHA with rich Brønsted acid sites offered no obvious activity for 
purifying exhaust gases (Figure S7) and gave much better catalytic 
performance as catalyst support than that of Brønsted-acid-site-free 
AlPO-CHA reveals an obvious synergistic effect between the 
Brønsted acid sites and the Pt nanoparticles. Such a synergistic effect 
facilitates conversion of C 3 H 6 and NO gases via simultaneously 
lowering the energy barrier of the oxidation reaction of HCs and 
enhancing the activity of Pt nanoparticles (Fig. 3c, Supplementary 
Movie S1). 
On the basis of our experimental and calculation results in 
combination with the observations reported in the literature </p>

<p>32-35 </p>

<p>, a 
catalytic cycle for the exhaust gas purification reaction over the Pt/ 
SAPO-CHA catalyst is proposed and depicted in Fig. 3d. First, the 
C 3 H 6 molecules are attracted by the Brønsted acid sites (step i), 
followed by conversion into covalent alkoxy species (step ii). These 
species are oxidized by O 2 over adjacent Pt nanoparticle, leading to 
the formation of acetate, H 2 O, and CO 2 (step iii, iv). The acetate 
further react with NO to form nitrogen-containing organic inter-
mediates (step v), which are further converted via formate (step vi) 
and HNCO species and finally into N 2 and CO 2 by following the 
reaction of NCO 
2 1 NO 5 N 2 1 CO 2 (step vii). 
Reusability of the Pt/SAPO-CHA catalysts is another important 
aspect for practical application. To enhance the stability and thus keep 
the activity of Pt-nanoparticle based catalysts, the morphology and 
composition of the as-formed Pt nanoparticles should be maintained 
during catalytic reactions. The advantage of SAPO-CHA over the 
conventional c-Al 2 O 3 as a catalyst support to prevent the metallic Pt 
from oxidation has been demonstrated earlier in this communication, 
and is also confirmed by HRTEM analysis (Figure S8). It is found that 
the SAPO-CHA as well as AlPO-CHA with abundant PO 4 tetrahedra 
in the framework and the external surface (Fig. S9) can act as efficient 
stabilizer to improve the homogeneous dispersion of Pt nanoparticles 
and keep them from agglomeration during reactions (Fig. S8). 
The thermal and chemical stability of catalyst supports is equally 
important to ensure their reusability. The structure and crystallinity of 
SAPO-CHA remains unchanged after reaction as confirmed by the 
FTIR (Fig. S9) and XRD (Fig. S10) analysis. As conventional catalysts 
for hydrogen transformation, zeolitic catalysts, including SAPO-CHA </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Catalytic performances of Pt/AlPO-CHA, Pt/SAPO-CHA and Pt/Al 2 O 3 with the same Pt content of 0.5 wt%. (a) Conversion of CO, </p>

<p>(b) conversion of C 3 H 6 , and (c) conversion of NO. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 2349 | DOI: 10.1038/srep02349 </p>

<p>
here, generally suffer from deactivation induced by the formation of 
coke inside the micropores. As expected, the thermogravimetric ana-
lysis (TGA) result reveals formation of coke (20 wt%) in the used Pt/ 
SAPO-CHA catalyst (Fig. S11). Nevertheless, the conversions of CO, 
NO and C 3 H 6 over Pt/SAPO-CHA at a space velocity of 34,000 mL 
gcat 
21 h </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>, do not show any obvious decay over a 1,000-minute run at 
620 K (in Fig. S12), suggesting that the coke formed during the cata-
lytic reaction has no influence on activity of the Pt/SAPO-CHA cata-
lyst. The NH 3 -TPD (Fig. S13) and pyridine-TPD (Fig. S14) results 
suggest that coke forms only inside the micropores of SAPO-CHA 
and the amount of the Brønsted acid sites on the external surface is 
not varied. This observation well explains why the formation of coke 
leads to negligible deactivation as the Pt nanoparticles are mostly 
distributed on the external surface of the Pt/SAPO-CHA catalyst. 
On the other hand, it is exactly the Pt nanoparticles that catalyzes 
the complete transformation of propene to CO 2 and H 2 O with con-
comitant NO reduction, and prevents the formation of coke on the 
external surface of the SAPO-CHA material. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Materials. All the reagents for synthesis and preparation were of analytic grade and 
used as received without further purification. Aluminum hydroxide and fumed silica 
were purchased from Aldrich. Phosphoric acid (85 wt%), hydrofluoric acid (40 wt%), 
cyclohexylamine and morpholine were all purchased from Shanghai Chemical 
Reagent Factory. c-alumina (Al 2 O 3 with a BET surface area of 200 m 
2 g </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>) was 
provided by Beijing Chemical Factory. </p>

<p>Preparation of SAPO-CHA and AlPO-CHA. The SAPO-CHA precursor was 
synthesized by a hydrothermal method from the gel with a molar composition of 
1.0cyclohexylamine: 0.5SiO 2 : 1.0Al 2 O 3 : 0.9P 2 O 5 : 55H 2 O following the procedure 
reported by Ashtekar et al </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>. Typically, 3.7 g of pseudoboehmite was first dispersed 
into 20 g of distilled water with stirring, followed by the addition of 0.75 g of fumed 
silica. After stirred at room temperature for one hour, 4.5 g of H 3 PO 4 and then 3.6 g 
of cyclohexylamine were added slowly to the above mixture under vigorous stirring. 
After three hours, the resulting mixture was loaded to a Teflon-lined stainless steel 
autoclave and heated at 453 K for 10 days. The crystalline product was filtered off, 
washed with deionized water and dried at 333 K overnight. The as-synthesized </p>

<p>material was calcined at 873 K in air for 24 hours to remove the template. The molar 
ratio Si : Al : P of the obtained SAPO-CHA was estimated to be 154.353.5 from the 
XRF results. 
For comparison, microporous AlPO-CHA without Brønsted acidity was also 
prepared hydrothermally from the gel with a molar composition of 1.0 morpholine: 
1.0 Al 2 O 3 : 1.0 P 2 O 5 : 60 H 2 O: 0.02 HF, following the procedure reported in the 
literature 
37 . </p>

<p>Loading of Pt. Pt was loaded onto SAPO-CHA, AlPO-CHA, and c-Al 2 O 3 by a 
modified wet impregnation method, leading to the formation of Pt/SAPO-CHA, Pt/ 
AlPO-CHA, and Pt/Al 2 O 3 , respectively. Prior to the impregnation, SAPO-CHA and 
AlPO-CHA were calcined at 873 K in air for 24 hours to decompose the organic 
template within the micropores, while c-Al 2 O 3 was dried at 383 K for five hours to 
remove the physically adsorbed H 2 O molecules and other species. A certain amount 
of H 2 PtCl 6 was dissolved into 10 mL of ethanol. The calcined SAPO-CHA, AlPO-
CHA, and c-Al 2 O 3 powders were then dispersed into the above ethanolic solution, 
respectively. These mixtures were kept at 333 K for two hours with vigorous stirring. 
Finally, Pt loaded samples, Pt/SAPO-CHA, Pt/AlPO-CHA, and Pt/Al 2 O 3 , were 
obtained by removal of the ethanol solvent with a rotary evaporator at 333 K. After 
dried at 383 K for 12 hours, the Pt loaded samples were sieved to 20-40 meshes. For 
comparison, a Pt/Al 2 O 3 sample was also prepared through aging the Pt-impregnated 
Pt/Al 2 O 3 at approximately 1173 K for five hours, and the corresponding sample was 
designated Pt/Al 2 O 3 -aging. </p>

<p>General characterization. The powder X-ray diffraction (XRD) patterns were 
recorded on a Rigaku Dmax-2200 diffractometer (Rigaku, Japan) with Cu Ka 
radiation (l 5 1.5418 Å ). The distribution and crystal lattice of Pt were examined 
with a transmission electron microscope (JEM-2100F, JEOL, Japan), operating at 
200 kV. The morphology of the samples was observed with a scanning electron 
microscope (SEM) (JEOL JSM-6700F, Japan), operated at 5 kV. Nitrogen adsorption/ 
desorption analyses were performed on a Micromeritics ASAP 2010 M 1 C nitrogen 
adsorption instrument (Micrometritices Inc., USA) at 77 K. The contents of Pt 
loaded in the samples were determined by inductively coupled plasma spectroscopy 
(Thermo Electron Corporaton). Approximately 0.5 wt% Pt was loaded in the Pt/ 
SAPO-CHA, Pt/AlPO-CHA, and Pt/Al 2 O 3 samples. 
Hydrogen temperature programmed reduction (H 2 -TPR) of the samples was 
performed in a quartz tube reactor equipped with a thermal conductivity detector 
(TCD). 200 mg of sample was pretreated under He flow (50 mL min </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>) at 
673 K for 30 min to remove the adsorbed water. After cooled to 323 K, the sample 
was exposed to a flow of 5% H 2 /He (50 mL min </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>) and the temperature was raised to 
1073 K at a rate of 10 K min </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>. The TPD experiments of adsorbed pyridine and 
NH 3 were performed in a quartz tube reactor equipped with a TCD. After saturated </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Schematic representation for the effect of Brønsted acid sites on catalytic reactions of exhaust gases. (a) The particle of the SAPO-CHA </p>

<p>crystal. (b) The simulated STM image of SAPO-CHA, showing high electron density (red) around the Brønsted acid site. (c) The activation of a propene 
molecule facilitated by the Brønsted acid site. (d) The proposed synergistic mechanism between the surface Brønsted acid sites and the Pt nanoparticles on 
the external surface of SAPO-CHA. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 2349 | DOI: 10.1038/srep02349 </p>

<p>
with ammonia or pyridine, the samples were purged with pure He at 373 K 
for two hours. Then, the samples were heated to 973 K at ramp rate of 10 K min </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>under helium flow (50 mL min </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>). The FTIR spectra were recorded on a Bruker IFS 
66 v/S FTIR spectrometer equipped with a deuterated triglycine sulfate (DTGS) 
detector. 
The Pt L 3 -edge X-ray absorption spectra (XAS) were obtained on the BL14W1 
beamline at the Shanghai Synchrotron Radiation Facility (SSRF), operated at 
3.5 GeV with injection currents of 140-210 mA. A Si (111) double-crystal mono-
chromator was used to reduce harmonic component of the monochrome beam. All 
the samples were measured in fluorescence mode. The powder of a sample was 
pressed into a self-supporting disk, which was then sealed with Kapton membrane 
and subjected to XAS measurement. The <rs type="software">IFEFFIT</rs> software was used to calibrate the 
energy scale, to correct the background signal and to normalize the intensity. Reliable 
parameters for the Z (Pt, Pt) and Z (Pt, O) contributions were determined by 
multiple-shell fitting in r space with application of k 
3 and k 
1 weightings in the Fourier 
transformations. </p>

<p>DFT calculations of the charge density around proton H 
1 in SAPO-CHA. Calcula-
tions were carried out using the <rs type="software">CASTEP</rs> periodic density functional theory (DFT) 
package. The exchange-correlation energy and potential were described self-
consistently within the generalized gradient approximation (GGA-PW91). The self-
consistent PW91 density was determined by iterative diagonalization of the 
Kohn2Sham Hamiltonian. The wave functions were expanded with the plane wave, 
and the ultra-soft pseudo-potential method was used to reduce the number of plane 
waves. Plane waves were used as a basis set with an energy cutoff of 340 eV .The 
electron density was approximated using a multipolar expansion up to hexadecapole. 
Typical overbinding associated with local density functionals was rectified through 
the use of the gradient-corrected Perdew-Burke-Ernzerhof (PBE) functional. The 
Brillouin-zone integration was performed using a 2 3 2 3 2 Monkhorst-Pack (MP) 
grid. The STM images were simulated using the Tersoff-Hamann approach with a 
bias voltage of 2 V. </p>

<p>Evaluation of the catalytic property. The catalytic performance of the samples for 
purifying emission gases was evaluated in a fixed-bed reactor. Approximately 250 mg 
of the sample was loaded into a tube quartz reactor, and then was reduced in situ with 
the simulated feed gas, containing 0.82 vol% O 2 , 0.12 vol% NO, 1.10 vol% CO, 0.08 
vol% C 3 H 6 and balance He at 673 K for two hours. After cooling to 303 K, the feed gas 
was allowed to pass through the reactor at a flow rate of 180 mL min </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>(corresponding to a space velocity of 43,200 mL h 
21 gcat </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>). The effluent gas 
composition was analyzed on-line by two gas chromatographs (Shimadzu, GC-2014) 
equipped with a 5A column coupled with a thermal conductivity detector, and an Rtx-
1 column coupled with a flame-ionization detector. Concentrations of NO x were 
determined by FTIR analyzer with Bruker IFS 66 v/S FTIR spectrometer, equipped 
with a quartz sample holder with CaF 4 windows. </p>



<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was financially supported by the National Basic Research Program of China 
(2013CB934102, 2011CB808703), the National Natural Science Foundation, and the Shoei 
Chemical Inc. We thank Shanghai Synchrotron Radiation Facility for the X-ray absorption 
measurement. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>W.F. and J.S.C. developed the idea and designed the experiments. W.F. performed the 
sample fabrication, measurements and data analysis. W.F., H.L.B., X.H.L., K.X.W., X.W., 
Y.Y.C. and J.S.C. analyzed the data, and discussed the results. W.F., X.H.L., K.X.W. and 
J.S.C. co-wrote the paper. J.S.C. planned and supervised the project. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 2349 | DOI: 10.1038/srep02349 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>