<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3710919" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Influenza is one of the most common infectious diseases, with global epidemics oc-
curring every 10-40 years. Although relatively benign, influenza can be associated with 
significant morbidity and mortality; influenza-related complications include pneu-
monia, encephalitis, myocarditis, and gradual deterioration of organ functions. Annu-
al vaccination is the primary measure for preventing influenza-related morbidity and 
mortality, but the vaccine supply can be limited in an early pandemic situation. To pre-
pare for potential vaccine shortages under an influenza pandemic, several antigen-
sparing strategies have been investigated. These include adjuvanted vaccines and new </p>

<p>115 </p>

<p>© Korean Vaccine Society. </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the 
terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Com-
mercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted non-commercial 
use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, pro-
vided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>K O R E A N 
V A C C I N E 
S O C I E T Y </p>

<p>K O R E A N 
A C C I N E 
O C I E T Y </p>

<p>V 
S </p>

<p>http://www.ecevr.org/ </p>

<p>Clin Exp Vaccine Res 2013;2:115-119 
http://dx.doi.org/10.7774/cevr.2013.2.2.115 
pISSN 2287-3651 • eISSN 2287-366X </p>

<p>Joon Young Song 1,2 , 
Hee Jin Cheong 1,2 , Ji Yun Noh 1,2 , 
Tae Un Yang 1 , Yu Bin Seo 1 , 
Kyung-Wook Hong 1 , In Seon Kim 1 , 
Won Suk Choi 1 , Woo Joo Kim 1,2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department 
of Internal Medicine, 2 Asian Pacific Influenza 
Institute, Korea University College of Medicine, 
Seoul, Korea </p>

<p>Received: March 21, 2013 
Revised: March 31, 2013 
Accepted: April 10, 2013 </p>

<p>Corresponding author: Hee Jin Cheong, MD, PhD 
Division of Infectious Disease, Department of 
Internal Medicine, Korea University Guro Hospital, 
148 Gurodong-ro, Guro-gu, Seoul 152-703, Korea 
Tel: +82-2-2626-3050, Fax: +82-2-2626-1105 
E-mail: heejinmd@medimail.co.kr </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this 
article was reported. </p>

<p>Purpose: To prepare for vaccine shortages under an influenza pandemic, several antigen-
sparing strategies have been investigated. This study was aimed to evaluate the immunoge-
nicity of influenza vaccine at reduced intradermal and full intramuscular dose. 
Materials and Methods: We compared the effect of one-fifth and one-half intradermal doses 
to the full intramuscular dose on immunogenicity in healthy young adults, using a commercial 
influenza vaccine. A hemagglutination inhibition assay was used to compare the immunoge-
nicity of the vaccination methods. 
Results: The one-fifth intradermal dose (3 µg hemagglutinin antigen, HA) was given to 30 par-
ticipants, the one-half intradermal dose (7.5 µg HA) was given to 30, and the full intramuscular 
dose (15 µg HA) was given to 32. No significant differences among injection routes and dos-
ages were seen for seroprotection rate, seroconversion rate, or geometric mean titer (GMT) 
fold-increase for A/H1N1, A/H3N2, and B at around 4 weeks from vaccination. Although GMT 
for influenza B was significantly lower at six months for the one-fifth intradermal vaccination 
compared to the full-dose intramuscular vaccination (32.8 vs. 63.2, p=0.048), all three groups 
met the Evaluation of Medicinal Products (EMA) immunogenicity criteria through 1 to 6 months. 
Conclusion: Intradermal administration of a one-fifth dose of influenza vaccine elicited anti-
body responses comparable to the intradermal one-half dose and a conventional intramuscu-
lar vaccination at 1 month post-vaccination. The immunogenicity of the one-fifth intradermal 
dose was sufficient to meet the requirement for the EMA criteria at six months after influenza 
vaccination. </p>

<p>Keywords: Vaccines, Influenza vaccines, Immunogenicity, Intradermal injections, Adult </p>

<p>Long-term immunogenicity of the 
influenza vaccine at reduced 
intradermal and full intramuscular 
doses among healthy young adults </p>

<p>Joon Young Song et al • Intradermal influenza vaccination </p>

<p> 
http://www.ecevr.org/ </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.7774/cevr.2013.2.2.115 </p>

<p>methods of administering vaccines such as intradermal and 
subcutaneous injection. 
Intradermal influenza vaccination requires less antigen to 
be as effective as regular intramuscular vaccination. The im-
proved immune response is due to the higher level of den-
dritic cells in the dermis than in the muscle [1-3]. Further-
more, the dermis has a rich supply of blood and lymphatic 
vessels that aids circulation of immune cells [4,5]. 
In this study, we compared the long-term immunogenicity 
of intradermal vaccination at one-fifth and one-half doses to 
full-dose intramuscular vaccination of a commercial influen-
za vaccine in healthy young adults. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Vaccine and study design </p>

<p>During the 2006-2007 influenza season, we compared the 
long-term immunogenicity in healthy young adults of an in-
tradermal influenza vaccination at one-fifth and one-half the 
conventional antigenic contents with an intramuscular vac-
cination at the conventional dose (Fig. 1). We randomly as-
signed 96 participants in a 1:1:1 ratio to three vaccination 
groups: intradermal one-fifth dose (0.1 mL, 3 µg hemaggluti-
nin antigen [HA]/strain), intradermal one-half (0.25 mL, 7.5 
µg HA/strain), and intramuscular full-dose (0.5 mL, 15 µg 
HA/strain). Serum hemagglutinin inhibition (HI) antibody 
titers were determined for recommended influenza strains 
pre-vaccination and at one and six months after vaccination. </p>

<p>The trivalent inactivated split vaccine (Influenza HA vac-
cine, Green Cross, Yongin, Korea), containing 15 µg HA/strain 
per 0.5 mL dose, was used. The vaccine contained the follow-
ing influenza strains: A/New Caledonia/20/99 (H1N1)-like 
virus, A/Wisconsin/67/2005 (H3N2)-like virus, and B/Mal-
aysia/2506/2004-like virus. 
Subjects enrolled in the study were healthy young adults 
aged 18-30 years. Exclusion criteria included immunosup-
pressant use, hypersensitivity to any vaccine component (in-
cluding eggs), or a history of Guillain-Barre syndrome. Other 
exclusion criteria included thrombocytopenia, any coagula-
tion disorder contraindicating intramuscular injection, or 
current febrile illness or another acute illness. Anyone who 
received gamma globulin during the previous three months 
or any other vaccination within the past 30 days was excluded. 
The study was approved by the ethics committee of Korea 
University Guro Hospital (IRB No. KUGH0691) and was con-
ducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and 
Good Clinical Practice. All participants provided written, in-
formed consent before enrollment. Venous blood samples of 
10 mL were taken on day 0, post-vaccination day 30±7, and 
post-vaccination day 180±7. </p>

<p>HI assay </p>

<p>Standard microtiter HI assays was performed as previously 
described [6]. A titer of ≥1:40 was considered a protective 
level [7,8]. Geometric mean titer (GMT) was determined pre-
vaccination and at 1 month and 6 months post-vaccination. 
Serologic response, measured by HI antibody titer, was as-
sessed using the criteria of the Evaluation of Medicinal Prod-
ucts (EMA) [9]. To confirm protective immunogenicity, at 
least one of the following three criteria were required for each 
influenza virus strain: 1) GMT-fold increase &gt;2.5-fold, 2) Se-
roprotection rate &gt;70%, and 3) Seroconversion rate &gt;40%. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>All statistical analysis was by <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">15.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., 
Chicago, IL, USA). Descriptive statistics are reported as num-
ber of participants and corresponding percentage. HI anti-
body titers are expressed as geometric mean with 95% confi-
dence interval. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to as-
sess variation of GMTs among groups for each time point; 
multiple comparison tests were based on Turkey's method. 
Categorical variables were analyzed using chi-square test 
(Fisher's exact test for less than 30 samples). Statistical signifi-
cance was signified by a p-value less than 0.05. </p>

<p>Enrolled and randomized 
n = 96 </p>

<p>3 µg ID 
n = 32 </p>

<p>7.5 µg ID 
n = 32 </p>

<p>15 µg IM 
n = 32 </p>

<p>Complete 
n = 30 </p>

<p>Complete 
n = 30 </p>

<p>Complete 
n = 32 </p>

<p>6 mo F/U </p>

<p>Randomization </p>

<p>Fig. 1. A total of 96 healthy adults were enrolled in the study and as-
signed to one of three vaccination regimens, receiving intradermal (ID) 
one-fifth dose (0.1 mL, 3 µg hemagglutinin antigen [HA]), ID one-half 
dose (0.25 mL, 7.5 µg HA) or intramuscular (IM) full-dose (0.5 mL, 15 
µg HA) vaccination. Immunogenicity was assessed up to six months 
after vaccination. F/U, follow-up. </p>

<p>Joon Young Song et al • Intradermal influenza vaccination </p>

<p> 
http://www.ecevr.org/ </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.7774/cevr.2013.2.2.115 </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Among 96 enrolled participants, 4 were dropped from the 
study because of declining serum sampling. The experimen-
tal groups were comprised of 30, 30, and 32 participants in 
the intradermal one-fifth dose (0.1 mL, 3 µg HA), intradermal 
one-half dose (0.25 mL, 7.5 µg HA), and intramuscular full-</p>

<p>dose (0.5 mL, 15 µg HA) groups, respectively. Baseline demo-
graphic characteristics of patients are in Table 1. No remark-
able differences were observed between the groups. 
All three groups met the EMA immunogenicity criteria in 
the 1-6 month study period (Table 2). For influenza A/H1N1 
virus, the seroprotection (titer≥1:40) rates for the groups were 
80.0% for the one-fifth dose, 90.0% for the one-half dose, and </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline characteristics of study subjects </p>

<p>Characteristic 
One-fifth dose, intradermal 
(n = 30) 
One-half dose, intradermal 
(n = 30) 
Full-dose, intramuscular 
(n = 32) 
p-value </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
24.7± 1.6 
25.3± 2.1 
25.3± 2.3 
0.431 
Male (%) 
17 (56.7) 
18 (60.0) 
22 (68.8) 
0.597 
Influenza vaccination in the previous year (%) 
6 (20.0) 
6 (20.0) 
6 (18.8) 
0.990 
BMI (kg/m 2 ) 
20.9± 2.3 
21.7± 2.9 
21.9± 3.2 
0.301 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean± SD or n (%). 
SD, standard deviation; BMI, body mass index. </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparison of short-and long-term immune responses after influenza vaccination, by hemagglutination inhibition assay </p>

<p>Subtype 
Parameters of 
immunogenicity 
One-fifth dose, 
intradermal (n = 30) 
One-half dose, 
intradermal (n = 30) 
Full dose, intramuscular 
(n = 32) 
p-value </p>

<p>Influenza A/H1N1 Sero-protection rate (%) 
1 mo post-vaccination 
6 mo post-vaccination 
Sero-conversion rate (%) 
1 mo post-vaccination 
6 mo post-vaccination 
Geometric mean titer 
Pre-vaccination 
1 mo post-vaccination 
6 mo post-vaccination </p>

<p>80.0 (62.5-90.4) 
76.7 (58.9-88.1) </p>

<p>43.3 (27.3-60.9) 
36.7 (21.9-54.6) </p>

<p>26.0 (17.5-38.5) 
106.3 (65.5-172.7) 
97.3 (59.7-158.5) </p>

<p>90.0 (74.2-96.4) 
90.0 (74.2-96.4) </p>

<p>40.0 (24.5-57.8) 
40.0 (24.5-57.8) </p>

<p>35.9 (24.6-52.4) 
150.5 (99.7-227.2) 
119.5 (78.8-181.1) </p>

<p>87.5 (71.8-94.9) 
87.5 (71.8-94.9) </p>

<p>46.9 (30.8-63.6) 
43.8 (28.1-60.8) </p>

<p>33.0 (20.7-52.5) 
129.2 (87.1-191.4) 
115.9 (77.9-172.4) </p>

<p>0.511 
0.309 </p>

<p>0.861 
0.850 </p>

<p>0.513 
0.515 
0.764 
Influenza A/H3N2 Sero-protection rate (%) 
1 mo post-vaccination 
6 mo post-vaccination 
Sero-conversion rate (%) 
1 mo post-vaccination 
6 mo post-vaccination 
Geometric mean titer 
Pre-vaccination 
1 mo post-vaccination 
6 mo post-vaccination </p>

<p>70.0 (52.0-83.3) 
70.0 (52.0-83.3) </p>

<p>43.3 (27.3-60.9) 
43.3 (27.3-60.9) </p>

<p>20.8 (15.8-27.3) 
74.4 (48.6-113.7) 
66.5 (44.7-98.9) </p>

<p>90.0 (74.2-96.4) 
90.0 (74.2-96.4) </p>

<p>50.0 (33.1-66.9) 
43.3 (27.3-60.9) </p>

<p>26.0 (18.6-36.3) 
92.7 (65.9-130.2) 
92.7 (65.0-131.9) </p>

<p>84.4 (68.1-93.0) 
84.4 (68.1-93.0) </p>

<p>56.3 (39.2-71.9) 
56.3 (39.2-71.9) </p>

<p>25.4 (18.4-35.3) 
95.4 (66.7-136.4) 
101.7 (68.9-150.1) </p>

<p>0.120 
0.120 </p>

<p>0.597 
0.498 </p>

<p>0.525 
0.581 
0.241 
Influenza B 
Sero-protection rate (%) 
1 mo post-vaccination 
6 mo post-vaccination 
Sero-conversion rate (%) 
1 mo post-vaccination 
6 mo post-vaccination 
Geometric mean titer 
Pre-vaccination 
1 mo post-vaccination 
6 mo post-vaccination </p>

<p>60.0 (42.2-75.5) 
60.0 (42.2-75.5) </p>

<p>40.0 (24.5-57.8) 
26.7 (14.2-44.6) </p>

<p>12.7 (9.9-16.3) 
42.3 (29.5-60.6) 
32.8 (22.7-47.4) a </p>

<p>60.0 (42.2-75.5) 
60.0 (42.2-75.5) </p>

<p>40.0 (24.5-57.8) 
40.0 (24.5-57.8) </p>

<p>13.0 (9.9-17.0) 
55.6 (39.2-78.9) 
54.4 (38.2-77.4) a,b </p>

<p>71.9 (54.5-84.4) 
68.8 (52.3-82.0) </p>

<p>46.9 (30.8-63.6) 
46.9 (30.8-63.6) </p>

<p>13.3 (10.3-17.1) 
71.9 (49.2-105.3) 
63.2 (40.3-99.1) b </p>

<p>0.527 
0.710 </p>

<p>0.817 
0.252 </p>

<p>0.969 
0.114 
0.048 </p>

<p>The same letters indicate non-significant differences between groups based on Tukey's multiple comparison tests. 
The numbers in parentheses represent 95% confidence interval. </p>

<p>Joon Young Song et al • Intradermal influenza vaccination </p>

<p> 
http://www.ecevr.org/ </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.7774/cevr.2013.2.2.115 </p>

<p>87.5% for the full dose. For A/H3N2 virus, rates were 70.0% 
for the one-fifth dose, 90.0% for the one-half dose, and 84.4% 
for the full dose. For influenza B virus, rates were 60.0%, 60.0%, 
and 71.9%. No significant intergroup differences were observ-
ed at 1 month or 6 months post-vaccination (Table 2). GMTs 
increased by &gt;2.5 in the 1-6 months for all 3 strains irrespec-
tive of injection route or dosage (Fig. 2). Seroconversion rates 
were above 40% for all three strains at 1 month post-vaccina-
tion, but the rate for influenza B declined to less than 40% at 
6 months for the one-fifth dose vaccination (Table 2). GMT 
for influenza B was significantly lower at 6 months after the 
one-fifth intradermal dose compared to the full-dose intra-
muscular vaccination: 32.8 vs. 63.2 (p=0.048) (Table 2). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study showed that the immunogenicity of one-fifth and 
one-half doses of intradermal seasonal influenza vaccine 
were largely comparable to full-dose intramuscular vaccina-
tion in healthy young adults. All three groups satisfied the 
EMA immunogenicity criteria for influenza vaccines, althou-
gh the intradermal one-fifth dose vaccination elicited lower 
antibody responses than the intradermal one-half dose and 
the conventional dose of an intramuscular vaccination. Intra-
muscular vaccination bypasses the skin's immune system, 
while intradermal vaccination targets dense populations of 
dendritic cells in the skin. Skin is considered a desirable tar-
get for vaccination; about 25% of the skin is covered by den-
dritic cells, which are postulated to acquire antigens in pe-
ripheral tissue by priming naive T cells [1-3]. Moreover, anti-
gen is suggested to become trapped in the cutaneous tissue 
for long periods after intradermal injection, compared to in-</p>

<p>tramuscular injection [10]. 
Several trials of intradermal influenza vaccines have stud-
ied the characteristic features of the dermal immune system 
in adults of diverse ages [11,12]. A recent literature review [11] 
found 10 trials using reduced-dose intradermal influenza 
vaccines ranging from 3 to 9 µg HA per strain. Among these 
trials, five used a 3-µg dose [2,13-16]. Of the 10 trials, 8 found 
comparable responses between intradermal influenza vac-
cines at a reduced dose and a full-dose intramuscular vac-
cine [2,13,15-20]. One trial showed that a dose-sparing intra-
dermal vaccine was superior to a conventional-dose intra-
muscular vaccine [21]. Thus, intradermal influenza vaccines 
at a reduced dose can be immunogenic in a way that is com-
parable to a full-dose intramuscular vaccine. However, data 
on antibody persistence has been insufficient. In this study, 
we showed that even a one-fifth dose of an intradermal vac-
cine induced antibody responses that persisted for six months. 
This study has some limitations. First, we did not include 
elderly people, so long-term immunogenicity needs to be in-
vestigated among this population. Second, cross-reactive im-
munogenicity against drifted strains was not evaluated. Third, 
the history of influenza infections in the previous year was 
not considered. 
Recently, the United States expanded the recommenda-
tion of influenza vaccination to children and adults without 
high-risk conditions [22]. In addition to these increased re-
quirements, we experienced vaccine shortages during the 
2009 influenza pandemic, and the United States suffered 
from vaccine shortages from the contamination of a vaccine-
producing plant during the 2004-2005 season [23]. Thus, dose-
sparing intradermal vaccines might be an effective strategy 
for preparation for an influenza pandemic, and could also be </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Geometric mean titer (GMT) fold-increases were assessed at 1 month post-vaccination (A) and 6 months post-vaccination (B), by hemag-
glutination inhibition assay. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
3 μg intradermal 
7.5 μg intradermal 
15 μg intradermal </p>

<p>GMT fold increase </p>

<p>H1N1 
H3N2 
B </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
3 μg intradermal 
7.5 μg intradermal 
15 μg intradermal </p>

<p>GMT fold increase </p>

<p>H1N1 
H3N2 
B </p>

<p>Joon Young Song et al • Intradermal influenza vaccination </p>

<p> 
http://www.ecevr.org/ </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.7774/cevr.2013.2.2.115 </p>

<p>useful during interpandemic periods. </p>



</text></tei>