<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3526355" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The inhibitory programmed death 1 (PD-1)-programmed death ligand 1 (PD-L1) pathway 
contributes to the functional down-regulation of T cell responses during persistent systemic 
and local virus infections. The blockade of PD-1-PD-L1-mediated inhibition is considered 
as a therapeutic approach to reinvigorate antiviral T cell responses. Yet previous studies 
reported that PD-L1-deficient mice develop fatal pathology during early systemic lympho-
cytic choriomeningitis virus (LCMV) infection, suggesting a host protective role of T cell 
down-regulation. As the exact mechanisms of pathology development remained unclear, we 
set out to delineate in detail the underlying pathogenesis. Mice deficient in PD-1-PD-L1 
signaling or lacking PD-1 signaling in CD8 T cells succumbed to fatal CD8 T cell-mediated 
immunopathology early after systemic LCMV infection. In the absence of regulation via 
PD-1, CD8 T cells killed infected vascular endothelial cells via perforin-mediated cytolysis, 
thereby severely compromising vascular integrity. This resulted in systemic vascular leakage 
and a consequential collapse of the circulatory system. Our results indicate that the 
PD-1-PD-L1 pathway protects the vascular system from severe CD8 T cell-mediated dam-
age during early systemic LCMV infection, highlighting a pivotal physiological role of T cell 
down-regulation and suggesting the potential development of immunopathological side 
effects when interfering with the PD-1-PD-L1 pathway during systemic virus infections. </p>

<p>2486 </p>

<p>Endothelial guard from T cell killing | Frebel et al. </p>

<p>As reported for PD-L1 KO mice, PD-1 KO mice also suc-
cumbed to a systemic LCMV clone 13 infection (10 6 pfu) 
with similar kinetics (Fig. 1 A). This also applied to a systemic 
infection (10 6 pfu) with the more virulent strain LCMV doc-
ile. In contrast, PD-1 KO mice did not succumb to a rapidly 
controlled LCMV infection when infected with 10 2 pfu of 
LCMV docile. Thus, lethal pathology only developed during 
a systemic infection which, in the following experiments, was 
established by infecting with 10 6 pfu of LCMV docile. 
As a quantitative parameter to determine disease onset 
and progression, we longitudinally measured the core tem-
perature of WT C57BL/6 and PD-1 KO mice after LCMV 
infection. Concurrent with the emergence of visible disease 
symptoms (hunched back, ruffled fur, and reduced motoric 
activity), PD-1 KO mice exhibited a sharp decrease of core 
temperature from days 5 to 6 post infection (p.i.) which was 
not observed in asymptomatic WT mice (Fig. 1 B). As the 
above experiments implied the impairment of PD-1-PD-L1 
signaling to cause pathology development, we speculated that 
the administration of blocking anti-PD-L1 (PD-L1) anti-
body would also evoke fatal pathology in systemically in-
fected WT mice. Although untreated WT mice remained 
asymptomatic, PD-L1-treated WT mice displayed the same 
disease symptoms and kinetics that were observed in infected 
PD-1 KO mice (Fig. 1 C). 
As the inhibitory PD-1-PD-L1 pathway was reported to 
contribute to T cell down-regulation early after systemic 
LCMV infection (Barber et al., 2006), we investigated a possi-
ble role of the antiviral T cell response in pathology develop-
ment. The emergence of disease symptoms simultaneously with 
the onset of the antiviral T cell response also suggested an in-
volvement of virus-specific T cells. We found that depleting 
CD8 T cells entirely prevented disease development of infected 
PD-1 KO mice, whereas the depletion of CD4 T cells had no 
effect (Fig. 1 D). These results indicated that PD-1 KO mice 
succumbed to a CD8 T cell-mediated pathology. A compari-
son of CD8 T cell responses in WT and PD-1 KO mice on day 6 
p.i. revealed increased numbers of LCMV-specific CD8 
T cells in the spleens of PD-1 KO mice and increased inflam-
matory infiltration of the periphery (liver) with virus-specific 
CD8 T cells, total CD8 T cells, CD4 T cells, and inflammatory 
polymorphonuclear cells (unpublished data). Consistent with 
an enhanced antiviral CD8 T cell response, PD-1 KO mice ex-
hibited modestly improved virus control (unpublished data). 
PD-1 deficiency also resulted in elevated serum levels of the 
proinflammatory cytokines IFN-, TNF, and IL-6 (Fig. 1 E) 
and in moderately elevated serum concentrations of the liver 
aspartate aminotransferase (AST) compared with infection-
matched WT mice (Fig. 1 F). In addition, only PD-1 KO mice 
suffered from focal hepatocellular necrosis in the form of visible 
lesion in liver tissue (unpublished data). </p>

<p>PD-1 deficiency renders virus-specific CD8 T cells pathogenic 
To investigate the role of PD-1 exclusively in virus-specific 
CD8 T cells, we crossed TCR transgenic P14 mice with PD-1 
KO mice. This enabled us to obtain a PD-1-deficient </p>

<p>2009, 2010; Nakamoto et al., 2009; Velu et al., 2009). This 
persistently high expression level was observed to be driven 
by the sustained presence of viral antigen (Bucks et al., 2009; 
Mueller and Ahmed, 2009) and to significantly contribute to 
T cell down-regulation, as the antibody-mediated blockade 
of PD-1-PD-L1 signaling partially restored the function of 
previously unresponsive T cells (Barber et al., 2006; Day 
et al., 2006; Blackburn et al., 2008). As viral persistence is 
supposed to be intimately linked to the down-regulation of 
antiviral T cell responses, restoring T cell function through 
the blockade of PD-1 or its ligand PD-L1 is considered as a 
therapeutic approach to treat HIV and persistent HCV infec-
tions in humans (Urbani et al., 2008; Nakamoto et al., 2009; 
Velu et al., 2009; Chiodi, 2010). 
However, the increasing number of studies reporting 
PD-1-PD-L1-mediated down-regulation of T cell responses 
during persistent bacterial or viral infections suggests a poten-
tially vital role of this inhibitory pathway. A growing body of 
evidence from mouse model systems indicates that the im-
pairment of the PD-1-PD-L1 pathway can cause aggravated 
if not lethal pathology during distinct infections (Iwai et al., 
2003; Barber et al., 2006, 2011; Lázár-Molnár et al., 2010; 
Mueller et al., 2010; Phares et al., 2010; Chen et al., 2011). 
Barber et al. (2006) showed that PD-L1 KO mice succumb 
to a systemic LCMV infection within 7 d, indicating a pro-
tective role of this pathway during the early phase of systemic 
infection. Likewise, Mueller et al. (2010) described a rapid 
development of fatal pathology in systemically infected mice 
that lacked PD-L1 expression on nonhematopoietic cells. 
Yet the pathophysiological mechanisms that contribute to 
pathology development under conditions of PD-1-PD-L1 
deficiency have remained elusive. It also remained unknown 
which specific nonhematopoietic cell type required PD-L1 
expression to prevent fatal pathology. 
In this study, we investigated the role of the PD-1-PD-
L1 pathway during the early phase of systemic LCMV infec-
tion. We determined the impact of impaired PD-1-PD-L1 
signaling on early virus-directed immune responses and elu-
cidated the immunological processes that lead to fatality. We 
found that pathology was driven by virus-specific CD8 
T cells and depended on the expression of perforin. During 
systemic infection, endothelial cells strongly up-regulated 
PD-L1 expression on their cell surface which inhibited the 
killing of infected endothelial cells by virus-specific CD8 
T cells. PD-1 deficiency or the Ab-mediated blockade of 
PD-L1 facilitated endothelial cell killing, leading to increased 
vascular permeability and ultimately to circulatory collapse. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
PD-1 KO mice succumb to CD8 T cell-mediated pathology 
during systemic LCMV infection 
A previous study indicated a lethal outcome of systemic LCMV 
infection in PD-L1-deficient mice (Barber et al., 2006). To 
confirm that this fatal pathology was the result of deficient sig-
naling via the PD-1-PD-L1 pathway, we examined the course 
of systemic LCMV infection in PD-1 (receptor) KO mice. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 13 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>

<p>2487 </p>

<p>AST and the formation of focal necrotic liver lesions (Fig. 2 E) 
as described above in PD-1 KO mice (Fig. 1 F). Moreover, 
the transfer of 2.5 × 10 4 PD-1 / P14 cells to WT mice led 
to the development of fatal pathology on day 6 p.i. as seen in 
PD-1 KO mice (Fig. 2 F), with pathology development being 
more severe when transferring higher numbers of PD-1 / 
P14 cells. This was in sharp contrast to PD-1 +/+ P14-trans-
ferred WT mice, which did not develop any disease symp-
toms when transferred with 2.5 × 10 4 P14 cells. These data 
demonstrate that selective PD-1 deficiency in virus-specific 
CD8 T cells results in significantly enhanced functional capac-
ity, which leads to the development of fatal pathology on day 6 
after systemic LCMV infection. </p>

<p>Perforin and nonhematopoietic H-2D b expression 
are required for pathology development 
We next aimed at determining the cellular effector mecha-
nisms underlying the pathogenicity of PD-1 KO CD8 T cells 
during early systemic LCMV infection. As the T cell effector 
cytokines IFN- and TNF were measured in significantly </p>

<p>monoclonal CD8 T cell population that was specific for the 
LCMV epitope GP33 (P14 cells). We adoptively transferred 
WT mice either with 10 4 PD-1 / or PD-1 +/+ P14 cells, fol-
lowed by a systemic LCMV infection. On day 6 p.i., mice 
were sacrificed and compared for the expansion and func-
tional capacity of transferred CD8 T cell populations. We 
found that PD-1 / P14 cells expanded to higher percentages 
and total numbers in the spleen compared with PD-1 +/+ P14 
cells (Fig. 2 A). Moreover, the percentage of IFN--produc-
ing cells within transferred P14 cells was significantly higher 
when these were PD-1 deficient. This, in combination with 
a higher mean fluorescence intensity of IFN- in transferred 
PD-1 / P14 cells (Fig. 2 B), suggested an increased func-
tional capacity of PD-1-deficient virus-specific CD8 T cells 
on day 6 p.i. Accordingly, we found PD-1 / P14-transferred 
WT mice to display higher serum concentrations of IFN- 
(Fig. 2 C) and modestly improved virus control in the spleen 
compared with PD-1 +/+ P14-transferred WT mice (Fig. 2 D). 
The enhanced antiviral response of PD-1-deficient CD8 
T cells was also reflected by increased serum concentrations of </p>

<p>Figure 1. PD-1 KO mice develop fatal 
CD8 T cell-dependent pathology during 
early systemic LCMV infection. (A) PD-1 KO 
mice were infected with 10 6 pfu LCMV clone 
13, 10 6 pfu LCMV docile, or 10 2 pfu LCMV 
docile and monitored for morbidity (hunched 
back, ruffled fur, and reduced motoric activity). 
(B and C) Core temperatures were measured 
in WT and PD-1 KO mice (B), untreated and 
PD-L1-treated WT mice (C). (D) Morbidity 
was monitored in undepleted and CD8 
T cell-or CD4 T cell-depleted PD-1 KO mice at 
the indicated times after infection with 10 6 
pfu LCMV docile. (E) Cytokine concentrations 
in the sera of WT and PD-1 KO mice were 
analyzed on day 6 after 10 6 pfu LCMV docile 
infection. A-E: n = 3-4 mice per group. 
Means ± SEM from one representative of two 
experiments are shown. (F) Liver AST concen-
trations in the sera of WT and PD-1 KO mice 
were determined on day 6 after infection. WT, 
n = 8 mice; KO, n = 7 mice. Means ± SEM 
from two pooled experiments are shown. 
*, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01 (unpaired two-tailed 
Student's t test). </p>



<p>Endothelial guard from T cell killing | Frebel et al. </p>

<p>neutralizations of IFN- and TNF in PD-1 KO mice during 
systemic infection. As shown in Fig. 3 A, the double neutral-
ization of IFN- and TNF did not prevent pathology devel-
opment but rather showed a trend toward accelerated disease </p>

<p>increased concentrations (6.2-and 2.7-fold, respectively) in 
the sera of PD-1 KO mice compared with infection-matched 
WT mice, we hypothesized these cytokines to contribute to 
pathology. To test this, we conducted antibody-mediated </p>

<p>Figure 2. PD-1-deficient virus-specific CD8 
T cells are more functional and pathogenic. 
(A and B) WT mice were transferred with 10 4 
PD-1 +/+ or PD-1 / P14 cells, followed by 10 6 pfu LCMV 
docile infection on the next day. On day 6 p.i., per-
centages and total numbers of splenic P14 cells 
were determined. The percentage of IFN--produc-
ing cells in transferred P14 cells (A) and the mean 
fluorescence intensity of IFN- (B) were measured 
after restimulation with GP33 peptide. n = 3-4 
mice per group. Means ± SEM from one represen-
tative of two experiments are shown. (C) Serum 
concentrations of IFN- were analyzed on day 6 
after infection. n = 3-4 mice per group. Means ± 
SEM from one representative of two experiments 
are shown. (D) Splenic virus titers were analyzed on 
day 6 after infection. n = 8 mice per group. Means ± 
SEM from two pooled experiments are shown. 
(E) Serum levels of liver AST were determined and 
photos of PBS-perfused liver lobes were taken on 
day 6 p.i. The arrow indicates a focal necrotic liver 
lesion. n = 3-4 mice per group. Means ± SEM from 
one representative of two experiments and photos 
from representative mice from one of two experi-
ments are shown. (F) WT mice were transferred 
with 2.5 × 10 4 PD-1 +/+ or PD-1 / P14 cells, fol-
lowed by 10 6 pfu LCMV docile infection and core 
temperature was monitored. n = 4 mice per group. 
Means ± SEM from one representative of two 
experiments are shown. *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01 
(unpaired two-tailed Student's t test). </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 13 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>WT bone marrow (WT→WT). To circumvent the problem 
of impaired thymic development of H-2D b -restricted T cells 
in WT→H-2D b KO chimeric mice, 2.5 × 10 4 PD-1 / P14 
cells were transferred to all mice, followed by systemic LCMV 
infection. As illustrated in Fig. 3 D, WT→WT chimeric 
mice developed clear disease symptoms on day 6 after sys-
temic infection in contrast to WT→H-2D b KO chimeric 
mice that only exhibited a slight decrease of core tempera-
ture. These results indicated perforin and nonhematopoietic 
H-2D b , but not IFN-, TNF, or IL-6, to be involved in pa-
thology development. </p>

<p>PD-L1 blockade enhances endothelial cell killing 
by virus-specific CD8 T cells 
Based on the observation that CD8 T cells, perforin, and 
nonhematopoietic H-2D b expression were crucial for fatal 
pathology, we screened the animals for severe tissue damage 
in vital organs which could be made responsible for fatality. 
However, histological analysis of the liver, lung, kidney, 
heart, and brain did not reveal signs of notable organ damage 
in the form of apoptotic or necrotic regions apart from focal 
hepatocellular lesions and liver steatosis (unpublished data). 
The only moderate increase in AST levels (Fig. 1 F), com-
parable serum albumin concentrations, and normal blood 
glucose concentrations in WT and PD-1 KO mice excluded 
acute liver failure (not depicted). We concluded that fatal 
pathology did not develop as a result of critical tissue damage 
in the above-mentioned vital organs. 
Several studies described a strong up-regulation of PD-L1 
expression on vascular endothelial cells under inflamma-
tory conditions (Eppihimer et al., 2002; Rodig et al., 2003; 
Grabie et al., 2007). We speculated that vascular endothelial </p>

<p>progression. We had also measured elevated levels of IL-6 
(5.7-fold) in the sera of PD-1 KO mice. Araki et al. (2010) 
reported a contribution of elevated IL-6 and TNF levels to 
fatal, CD8 T cell-dependent pathology in calcineurin inhibitor-
treated WT mice after acute LCMV infection. We thus in-
vestigated if a blockade of the IL-6 receptor combined with 
TNF neutralization could prevent fatality in PD-1 KO mice. 
This also failed to prevent disease development, which was 
reflected by the strong decline of core temperature in treated 
PD-1 KO mice (Fig. 3 B). 
Apart from the secretion of soluble effectors, CD8 T cells 
drive virus-infected cells into apoptosis, which is crucial for 
LCMV control in vivo (Kägi et al., 1994). We determined 
the impact of CD8 T cell cytotoxicity on pathology develop-
ment by treating WT and perforin-deficient mice (PKOB) 
with PD-L1. Although PD-L1-treated WT mice displayed 
the characteristic decline of core temperature on day 6 p.i., 
the core temperature in PD-L1-treated PKOB mice remained 
constant as in untreated PKOB mice (Fig. 3 C). Importantly, 
we measured comparable percentages of splenic GP33-
specific CD8 T cells in PD-L1-treated WT and PKOB 
mice, indicating that the expansion of virus-specific CD8 
T cells was not impaired in perforin-deficient mice (un-
published data). Based on the severity and fast kinetics of 
pathology development, we speculated that recognition of 
virally infected nonhematopoietic cells by cytotoxic T cells 
would be involved. To test this hypothesis, we generated 
bone marrow chimeric mice that lacked H-2D b expression 
on nonhematopoietic cells through reconstituting the hema-
topoietic compartment of lethally irradiated H-2D b KO mice 
with WT bone marrow cells (WT→H-2D b KO). As a con-
trol, lethally irradiated WT mice were reconstituted with </p>

<p>Figure 3. Perforin and nonhematopoietic 
H-2D b expression are required for pathology 
development. (A and B) Core temperatures 
were measured in WT mice, PD-1 KO mice, 
and IFN- + TNF-treated PD-1 KO mice 
(A) or IL-6R + TNF-treated PD-1 KO 
mice (B) after 10 6 pfu LCMV docile infection. 
(C) Core temperatures were monitored in 
untreated WT and PKOB mice and in PD-L1-
treated WT and PKOB mice after infection. 
A-C: n = 3-4 mice per group. Means ± SEM 
from one representative of two experiments 
are shown. **, P &lt; 0.01 (unpaired two-tailed 
Student's t test). (D) WT→WT and WT→H-2D b 
KO chimeric mice were transferred with 2.5 × 
10 4 PD-1 / P14 cells, followed by 10 6 pfu 
LCMV docile infection and monitoring of core 
temperature. WT→WT, n = 9 mice per group; 
WT→H-2D b KO, n = 12 mice per group. 
Means ± SEM from two pooled experiments 
are shown. **, P &lt; 0.01 (unpaired two-tailed 
Student's t test). </p>



<p>Endothelial guard from T cell killing | Frebel et al. </p>

<p>cells might up-regulate PD-L1 under the inflammatory con-
ditions of a systemic LCMV infection and thereby inhibit the 
killing of LCMV-infected endothelium by activated, PD-1-
expressing CD8 T cells. In contrast, PD-1-deficient CD8 
T cells would not be inhibited by PD-L1 and thus effectively 
kill LCMV-infected vascular endothelial cells. To test this 
hypothesis, the expression level of PD-L1 on liver and lung 
endothelial cells was analyzed ex vivo on day 6 p.i. We de-
tected a strong up-regulation of PD-L1 on endothelial cells 
from both organs in infected WT and PD-1 KO mice com-
pared with endothelial cells from naive WT mice (Fig. 4 A). 
Furthermore, we found the vast majority of liver and lung 
endothelial cells to be infected with LCMV on day 6 p.i., 
indicated by strong intracellular staining with the LCMV 
nucleoprotein-specific antibody VL-4 (Fig. 4 A). 
To assess whether endothelial cells up-regulate PD-L1 
in response to inflammatory mediators or as the result of a 
direct infection with LCMV, WT mice were infected with 
10 2 pfu of LCMV WE. After 6 d, this rapidly controlled in-
fection was localized to the spleen, leaving lung endothelial 
cells uninfected (Fig. 4 B). However, the uninfected endo-
thelial cells exhibited a significantly increased expression 
level of PD-L1 compared with naive WT mice, indicating 
that the up-regulation of PD-L1 expression was indepen-
dent of a direct infection but rather a response to systemic 
inflammatory mediators during LCMV infection. 
We now examined the impact of PD-1-PD-L1 signaling 
on endothelial cell killing by CD8 T cells from systemically 
infected mice. The mouse endothelial cell line MS-1 was left 
untreated or cultured in the presence of IFN- for 48 h, 
which led to a pronounced up-regulation of PD-L1 on the 
cell surface (Fig. 4 C). Next, cells were pulsed with LCMV 
peptides (GP33+NP396) in the presence or absence of block-
ing PD-L1 antibody and subsequently co-cultured with 
CD8 T cells purified from the spleens of P14-transferred WT 
mice on day 6 p.i. Consistent with previous results (Barber 
et al., 2006), LCMV-specific CD8 T cells had strongly up-
regulated PD-1 expression in response to systemic LCMV in-
fection (Fig. 4 D). We found that the killing of antigen-pulsed 
endothelial cells was clearly influenced by PD-1-PD-L1 sig-
naling, with modest killing of PD-L1-expressing endothelial 
cells which was markedly increased (twofold on average) 
when PD-1-PD-L1 signaling was blocked (Fig. 4 E). 
To directly verify whether killing of infected endothelial 
cells occurred in vivo, lung tissue of naive and systemically 
infected mice was isolated and examined for apoptotic endo-
thelium by immunofluorescence microscopy. Although no 
apoptotic endothelial cells were detected in naive mice, 
apoptosis was prevalent in endothelium of WT and PD-1 
KO mice 5-6 d p.i. (Fig. 5 A). A quantitative analysis re-
vealed significantly elevated numbers of apoptotic endothe-
lial cells in lung sections of infected PD-1 KO mice compared </p>

<p>Figure 4. Endothelial PD-L1 expression inhibits CD8 T cell-mediated 
killing. (A) CD31 + CD144 + cells from lungs and livers of naive WT, 
infected WT, and infected PD-1 KO mice were analyzed for PD-L1 expres-
sion and LCMV infection (VL-4 staining) on day 6 after 10 6 pfu LCMV 
docile infection. Histograms depict data from one representative of two 
analyzed mice per group. Data from one representative of three experi-
ments are shown. (B) Lung CD31 + CD144 + cells of naive and 10 2 pfu LCMV 
WE-infected WT mice were analyzed for PD-L1 expression and LCMV 
infection (VL-4 staining) on day 6 p.i. Histograms depict data from one 
mouse each. Data from one representative of two experiments are shown. 
(C) Untreated, IFN--treated, and IFN- + PD-L1-treated MS-I cells 
were analyzed for PD-L1 expression and pulsed with GP33+NP396 pep-
tide to serve as target cells in a chromium release assay. (D) PD-1 expres-
sion levels of endogenous CD8 T cells and transferred P14 cells were 
determined on day 6 after systemic infection. C and D: histograms depict 
data from one representative of two experiments. (E) CD8 T cells were 
purified from four P14-transferred mice on day 6 p.i. and mixed with 
chromium-labeled, antigen-pulsed MS-I cells at the indicated effector to </p>

<p>target ratios. Chromium release was analyzed in duplicates. Means ± SEM 
from one representative of three experiments are shown. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 13 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>extracted EB in the lung (Fig. 6 B). Vascular damage uncovers 
procoagulant structures, such as tissue factor-bearing cells and 
connective tissue, which trigger vascular coagulation (Cines 
et al., 1998; Dahlbäck, 2000). As evidence for an activated clot-
ting system, we found increased concentrations of thrombin-
antithrombin (TAT) complexes in infected animals that were 
most pronounced in PD-1 KO mice (Fig. 6 C). Severely de-
creased platelet counts in infected PD-1 KO as compared with 
WT mice further supported a more pronounced procoagu-
lant stage in infected PD-1-deficient mice (Fig. 6 D). 
We next determined whether factors we had shown to be 
dispensable or required for pathology development had simi-
lar effects on vascular permeability. Consistent with the above 
results (Fig. 3 B), a simultaneous blockade of IL-6R and neu-
tralization of TNF did not reduce the elevated levels of vascu-
lar permeability in PD-1 KO mice (Fig. 6 E). We, however, 
observed a significant reduction of vascular permeability in 
the lungs and livers of PD-L1-treated PKOB mice com-
pared with PD-L1-treated WT mice (Fig. 6 F). Particularly 
in the lung, the PD-L1-mediated increase of vascular leak-
age was reduced by &gt;66% in the absence of perforin. More-
over, PD-1 / P14 cell-mediated vascular permeabilization 
was completely abrogated in the lungs of WT→H-2D b KO 
chimeric mice compared with WT→WT chimeric mice, which 
exhibited high vascular permeability (Fig. 6 G). Together, 
these results indicate a significant role of perforin-mediated 
cell lysis and nonhematopoietic H-2D b expression in the loss 
of vascular integrity particularly in the lungs of PD-1 KO 
mice during early systemic LCMV infection. </p>

<p>with WT mice (Fig. 5 B). Importantly, impaired PD-1-PD-L1 
signaling had a stronger impact on endothelial cell killing in 
the presence of perforin than in PKOB mice, further corrob-
orating the perforin-dependent endothelial cell apoptosis 
in vivo (Fig. 5 B). We also assessed the impact of impaired 
PD-1-PD-L1 signaling on the killing of infected endothelial 
cells by flow cytometry. Consistent with the above results, 
we found decreased total numbers of endothelial cells in the 
lungs of PD-L1-treated WT mice compared with untreated 
WT mice on day 6 p.i. (Fig. 5 C). In conclusion, these data 
demonstrate that endothelial cells from WT and PD-1 KO 
mice are permissive for LCMV during systemic infection 
and up-regulate PD-L1 under inflammatory conditions. This 
PD-L1 up-regulation inhibited life-threatening killing of 
virus antigen-presenting endothelial cells by activated CD8 
T cells which was restored by PD-L1 blockade. </p>

<p>Vascular integrity is compromised in PD-1 KO mice 
Endothelial cells represent the physiological barrier between 
the vascular space and the organ interstitium. Thus, killing of 
endothelial cells can compromise vascular integrity. We com-
pared the vascular permeability in the kidney, liver, lung, and 
brain in infected PD-1 KO mice to the permeability in WT 
mice. As a surrogate for vascular barrier function, we deter-
mined the amount of albumin-bound Evan's blue (EB) recov-
ered from the interstitium of each organ 20 min after i.v. 
injection of the dye. As shown in Fig. 6 A, PD-1 deficiency 
caused elevated levels of vascular permeability in all analyzed 
organs on day 6 p.i., with the most pronounced increase of </p>

<p>Figure 5. Pulmonary endothelial cells are 
driven into apoptosis after systemic LCMV 
infection. (A) In situ analysis of lung sections 
from naive and infected WT and PD-1 KO 
mice on days 5-6 after 10 6 pfu LCMV docile 
infection. Representative immunofluorescence 
stainings with the indicated antibodies are 
shown. The arrows indicate apoptotic endo-
thelial cells as identified by TUNEL + CD31 + 
cells. n = 7 mice. Bars, 20 µm. (B) Quantifi-
cation of CD31 + TUNEL + cells in immunofluor-
escence stainings of pulmonary vessels on 
day 5 p.i. Numbers of CD31 + TUNEL + cells were 
normalized to vessel areas and two to three 
sections per mouse were considered for quan-
tification. WT, n = 4 mice; wt PD-L1, n = 4 
mice; PD-1 KO, n = 3 mice; PKOB, n = 3 mice; 
PKOB PD-L1, n = 3 mice. Means ± SEM from 
two pooled experiments are shown. n.s.: not 
significant. (C) Total numbers of lung 
CD31 + CD144 + cells were determined in naive 
and infected WT and PD-L1-treated WT 
mice on day 6 p.i. n = 5-6 mice per group. 
Means ± SEM from two pooled experiments 
are shown. *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01 (unpaired 
two-tailed Student's t test). </p>

<p>2492 </p>

<p>Endothelial guard from T cell killing | Frebel et al. </p>

<p>Figure 6. PD-1 KO mice exhibit systemically increased vascular permeability. (A) EB was injected i.v. to WT and PD-1 KO mice on day 6 after 10 6 
pfu LCMV docile infection and EB extravasation was analyzed in the kidney, liver, lung, and brain. The mean EB concentration in organs of WT mice was 
normalized to 1. Values in PD-1 KO mice were calculated accordingly. WT, n = 10 mice; KO, n = 5-6 mice. Means ± SEM from three pooled experiments 
are shown. (B) Photos of PBS-perfused lung lobes from WT and PD-1 KO mice were taken after EB injection on day 6 after infection. Photos from repre-
sentative mice from one of two experiments are shown. (C) TAT plasma concentrations were determined in naive WT and PD-1 KO mice and infected WT, 
PD-L1-treated WT, and PD-1 KO mice on day 6 p.i. Infected, n = 3-4 mice per group; naive, n = 1 mouse per group. Means ± SEM from one representa-
tive of two experiments are shown. (D) Total numbers of blood platelets were determined in WT and PD-1 KO mice on day 6 after infection. n = 2-4 mice 
per group. Means ± SEM from one representative of two experiments are shown. (E) EB extravasation was determined in the kidney, liver, and lung of 
infected WT, PD-1 KO, and IL-6R + TNF-treated PD-1 KO mice on day 6 after systemic infection. n = 6-8 mice per group. Means ± SEM from two 
pooled experiments are shown. (F) EB extravasation was analyzed in the kidney, liver, and lung of untreated WT and PKOB mice and PD-L1-treated WT 
and PKOB mice on day 6 p.i. n = 6-8 mice per group. Means ± SEM from two pooled experiments are shown. n.s.: not significant. (G) EB extravasation </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 13 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>physiologically normal values during the entire measurement. 
Thus, the absence of PD-1-PD-L1-mediated inhibition led 
to a CD8 T cell-dependent systemic increase of vascular per-
meability with a consecutive hypovolemic shock. 
In conclusion, our data demonstrate a pivotal role of the 
PD-1-PD-L1 pathway in the functional down-regulation 
of virus-specific CD8 T cells during early systemic LCMV 
infection. This down-regulation prevents vascular damage 
caused by the killing of virus-infected endothelial cells, which 
rapidly culminates in fatal circulatory failure. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Besides its acknowledged role in tolerance and autoimmu-
nity, increasing evidence is found for an immunoregulatory 
function of the PD-1-PD-L1 pathway in cancer immunol-
ogy and infectious diseases (Driessens et al., 2009; Virgin et al., 
2009; Brown et al., 2010; Francisco et al., 2010). We now 
describe a critical inhibitory role of this pathway for pro-
tecting the vascular system from CD8 T cell-mediated dam-
age during systemic virus infection of mice. PD-1 deficiency 
or PD-L1 blockade both led to fatal pathology early after 
systemic LCMV infection. Pathology development was driven 
by PD-1 KO CD8 T cells, which exhibited significantly 
enhanced functionality compared with WT CD8 T cells. 
Although IFN-, TNF, and IL-6R signaling were dispensable 
for pathology development, perforin-mediated effector func-
tions and nonhematopoietic H-2D b expression were crucially 
involved. We found that compromised PD-1-PD-L1 signal-
ing enhanced endothelial cell killing by virus-specific CD8 
T cells, leading to reduced endothelial cell numbers and in-
creased vascular permeability. Consequently, infected PD-1 
KO mice suffered from pulmonary edema and critical hypo-
tension. These results suggest that PD-1-PD-L1-mediated 
inhibition of cytotoxic T cell activity protects from self-
inflicted damage of the circulatory system during early sys-
temic viral infection. 
The fact that pathology is clearly CD8 T cell dependent 
is consistent with results from Mueller et al. (2010), who 
demonstrated that the absence of PD-L1 in nonhematopoi-
etic cells resulted in fatality after systemic LCMV infection. 
However, we further delineated this mechanism by showing 
that PD-1 deficiency in CD8 T cells was sufficient for the 
development of fatal pathology and that this was linked to 
perforin-mediated effector functions. The above study also 
demonstrated that the absence of PD-L1 on hematopoietic 
cells led to fatal pathology, albeit with delayed kinetics. This 
very likely resulted from the documented increase in num-
bers and function of virus-specific CD8 T cells caused by the 
absence of down-regulation by PD-L1-deficient hematopoi-
etic cells. Although our in vitro killing assays indicated that 
PD-L1 expression on endothelial cells confers a significant </p>

<p>PD-1 KO mice suffer from pulmonary edema 
and severe hypotension 
Increasing vascular permeability can cause edema formation 
in the organ interstitium (Goldenberg et al., 2011; Matthay 
and Zemans, 2011). As significantly higher amounts of EB 
were extracted from PD-1 KO lungs than from WT lungs, 
we compared the extent of pulmonary edema formation on 
day 6 p.i. The wet/dry weight ratio of an organ increases 
with accumulating interstitial fluid. We observed significantly 
higher wet/dry weight ratios for lungs isolated from diseased 
PD-1 KO mice than from WT mice (Fig. 7 A). An additional 
breach of the endothelial barrier between vascular and alveo-
lar space leads to the accumulation of plasma in the airways. 
This would result in elevated total protein concentrations in 
the bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL). Although protein concen-
trations were comparable in naive WT and PD-1 KO mice, 
infected PD-1 KO mice exhibited significantly more total 
protein in the BAL than infected WT mice (Fig. 7 B). This 
independently pointed toward the development of pulmo-
nary edema in PD-1 KO mice in addition to the elevated 
wet/dry weight ratios. The increase of albumin in the BAL 
of PD-1 KO mice indicated exudation and not transudation 
as underlying mechanism (Fig. 7 C). Furthermore, the lungs 
of infected PD-1 KO mice exhibited focal intraalveolar hem-
orrhage (Fig. 7 D), and histological sections of nonperfused 
lung tissue confirmed the extensive formation of interstitial 
edema with few regions of alveolar edema that were absent in 
sections of infected WT mice (Fig. 7 F). As previous results 
had suggested vascular permeabilization to be significantly 
dependent on perforin expression (Fig. 6 F), BAL albumin 
concentrations were also determined in untreated and PD-
L1-treated WT and PKOB mice. In contrast to treated WT 
mice, treated PKOB mice did not exhibit increased albumin 
concentrations in the BAL, whereas untreated mice exhibited 
comparably low levels (Fig. 7 E). 
We next asked if pulmonary edema formation in PD-1 
KO mice might impair respiratory gas exchange. An analy-
sis of arterial blood revealed that gas exchange at rest was 
sufficient and peripheral oxygen delivery was not impaired 
in PD-1 KO mice (Fig. 7 G). Considering the systemic na-
ture and degree of vessel permeability in infected PD-1 KO 
mice, the consequences of increased vascular permeability on 
the circulatory system were investigated. We found that the 
mean arterial pressure in PD-1 KO mice was reduced to critical 
levels (50 mmHg) on day 6 p.i., whereas the mean pressure 
in WT mice was within the normal range (100-120 mmHg; 
Fig. 7 H). A longitudinal analysis showed a progressive and 
rapid decrease of blood pressure in PD-1 KO and PD-L1-
treated WT mice starting on late day 5 p.i. and reaching criti-
cal levels on day 6 p.i. (Fig. 7 I). This was in sharp contrast 
to WT and CD8-depleted PD-1 KO mice which exhibited </p>

<p>was analyzed in the lungs of 2.5 × 10 4 PD-1 / P14 cell-transferred WT→WT and WT→H-2D b KO chimeric mice on day 6 p.i. WT→WT, n = 7 mice per 
group; WT→H-2D b KO, n = 12 mice per group. Means ± SEM from two pooled experiments are shown. *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01 (unpaired two-tailed 
Student's t test). </p>



<p>Endothelial guard from T cell killing | Frebel et al. </p>

<p>Figure 7. PD-1 KO mice develop pulmonary edema and severe hypotension. (A) Wet/dry weight ratios of whole lungs from WT and PD-1 KO mice 
were determined on day 6 after 10 6 pfu LCMV docile infection. n = 3-4 mice per group. Means ± SEM from one representative of two experiments are 
shown. (B and C) Total protein concentrations (B) and albumin concentrations (C) were determined in the BAL supernatant of naive and infected WT and 
PD-1 KO mice on day 6 p.i. Infected, n = 6-7 mice per group; naive, n = 1 mouse per group. Means ± SEM from two pooled experiments are shown. 
(D and F) Photos were taken of nonperfused, PFA-fixed lung lobes (D) and H&amp;E-stained lung sections (F) from WT and PD-1 KO mice on day 6 after infec-
tion. Photos from representative mice from one of two experiments are shown. Bars, 150 µm. (E) Albumin concentrations were determined in the BAL 
supernatant of untreated and PD-L1-treated WT and PKOB mice on day 6 p.i. Treated, n = 7-8 mice per group; untreated, n = 3 mice per group. Means ± 
SEM from two pooled experiments are shown. (G) O 2 saturation and lactate concentration in arterial blood were measured in WT and PD-1 KO mice on 
day 6 p.i. n = 4 mice per group. Means ± SEM from one representative of two experiments are shown. n.s.: not significant. (H) Mean arterial blood pres-
sure was determined in WT and PD-1 KO mice on day 6 p.i. n = 4 mice per group. Means ± SEM from one representative of two experiments are shown. 
(I) Blood pressure was determined in WT, PD-L1-treated WT, PD-1 KO, and CD8 T cell-depleted PD-1 KO mice between days 4 and 6 after infection. 
n = 4 mice per group. Means ± SEM are shown. **, P &lt; 0.01 (unpaired two-tailed Student's t test). </p>

<p>degree of protection against lysis by PD-1-expressing CD8 
T cells, this protection is not complete. Hence, a strong in-
crease in numbers and function of virus-specific CD8 T cells 
in mice with PD-L1 deficiency on hematopoietic cells might </p>

<p>overcome the threshold of PD-L1-conferred protection in 
endothelial cells. Unlike speculations in previous studies of 
immunopathology in PD-1-PD-L1 KO mice (Mueller et al., 
2010; Phares et al., 2010; Chen et al., 2011), we found that </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 13 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS), an enzyme which 
is required for the generation of polymorphonuclear cell-
derived NOs, was described to significantly contribute to he-
patic virus control after systemic LCMV infection and increased 
cerebral iNOS transcription coincided with elevated serum 
levels of nitrite/nitrate during lethal intracranial LCMV in-
fection (Campbell et al., 1994; Campbell, 1996; Guidotti et al., 
2000). To test for a possible role of polymorphonuclear 
cell-derived NOs in pathology development, we treated 
iNOS-deficient mice with PD-L1 followed by systemic 
LCMV infection. As seen with WT mice, the blockade of 
PD-1-PD-L1 signaling induced pathology development in 
infected iNOS-deficient mice on day 6 p.i., which indicated 
the dispensability of polymorphonuclear cell-derived NOs 
for pathology development (unpublished data). Moreover, 
the depletion of a major polymorphonuclear cell type, neu-
trophils, with a Ly-6G-targeting antibody did not prevent 
pathology development in infected PD-1 KO mice (unpub-
lished data). Although our data strongly support a CD8 T cell-
mediated mechanism of immunopathology, other cell types, 
such as NK cells or NKT cells, also bear the potential of per-
forin-mediated cell lysis. Yet treatment of infected PD-1 KO 
mice with depleting NK1.1 antibody did not prevent pa-
thology development (unpublished data). 
The loss of vascular integrity in systemically infected 
PD-1 KO mice caused the formation of pulmonary edema. 
Despite edematous septa and scattered intraalveolar fluid ac-
cumulation, no evidence of impaired pulmonary gas ex-
change was found at rest. A more prolonged leakage of fluid 
into the alveolar space might be required to overcome the 
lung's overcapacity at rest to significantly impact gas ex-
change. Although leaking plasma into organ interstitium can 
impair organ function, it can also affect the circulatory sys-
tem. Increased vascular permeability and intravascular coag-
ulation during endotoxic sepsis or hemorrhagic fever are 
associated with critical hypotension (Srikiatkhachorn, 2009; 
Goldenberg et al., 2011). A longitudinal measurement of the 
arterial blood pressure revealed a CD8 T cell-mediated pro-
gressive decrease of arterial blood pressure in diseased PD-1 
KO and PD-L1-treated WT mice to levels which do not 
allow for sufficient organ perfusion. 
The application of PD-1-PD-L1 pathway-blocking anti-
bodies is considered as a therapeutic approach to reinvigorate 
down-regulated T cell responses during advanced systemic 
infections (Barber et al., 2006; Day et al., 2006; Lafon et al., 
2008; Chiodi, 2010; Bhadra et al., 2011; Telcian et al., 2011), 
vaccinations (Ha et al., 2008), and antitumor treatments 
(Brahmer et al., 2010; Kline and Gajewski, 2010; Mkrtichyan 
et al., 2011). The release of PD-1-PD-L1-mediated immune 
inhibition can hold promise for specific therapeutic settings 
but might also bear considerable detrimental potential. For 
instance, the blockade of another member of the CD28 
superfamily, CTLA-4, in the context of cancer treatments, 
caused diverse immune-related side effects like colitis/diarrhea, 
dermatitis, hepatitis, and endocrinopathies (Berman et al., 2010; 
Di Giacomo et al., 2010). Moreover, a recent clinical study </p>

<p>the proinflammatory cytokines IFN-, TNF, and IL-6 were 
not required for pathology development. Yet a potential ca-
veat of these results is that cytokines cannot be neutralized to 
100% by the application of blocking antibodies. 
In agreement with results of Rodig et al. (2003), blocking 
of PD-L1 clearly enhanced the killing of antigen-pulsed en-
dothelial cells by in vivo-activated CD8 T cells in vitro. 
The inhibition of endothelial cell killing through PD-L1 up-
regulation might be particularly potent during systemic LCMV 
infection, as virus-specific CD8 T cells exhibit a high expres-
sion level of PD-1. Furthermore, our observations are sup-
ported by reports of ameliorated CD8 T cell-dependent organ 
damage by endothelial PD-L1 expression during experi-
mentally induced myocarditis (Grabie et al., 2007), transplant 
vasculopathy (Bolinger et al., 2010), and viral hepatitis (Iwai 
et al., 2003). 
The increased extent of interstitial EB extravasation in 
multiple organs showed that PD-1 deficiency led to elevated 
vascular permeability during systemic LCMV infection. This 
was most prominent in the lung, perhaps because this organ 
has the largest endothelial area or because lung endothelium is 
more affected than other endothelia. The more modest extent 
of EB extravasation in organs of PD-L1-treated PKOB mice 
suggested a significant role of perforin in the increase of vascu-
lar permeability. However, the increase detected in the ab-
sence of perforin expression also indicated a contribution of 
additional factors. Potential mechanisms might be Fas/FasL-
and TRAIL/DR4/5-mediated killing of endothelial cells or 
alterations of endothelial cell adhesion through soluble media-
tors other than IFN-, TNF, or IL-6. Yet the level of vascular 
permeability observed in PD-L1-treated PKOB mice was 
insufficient to cause fatal pathology. The important role of 
perforin-mediated cell lysis in vascular permeabilization is in 
contrast to pathologies with similar clinical pictures, for exam-
ple, sepsis, where inflammatory mediators were found to drive 
pathogenesis (Tracey et al., 1987; Leon et al., 1998; Shresta 
et al., 2006). Furthermore, pathogenic PD-1 / P14 cells 
failed to increase vascular permeability in the lungs of non-
hematopoietic H-2D b -deficient mice, whereas mice expressing 
nonhematopoietic H-2D b exhibited clearly increased vascular 
permeability. This observation indicated a central role of non-
hematopoietic antigen presentation in the permeabilization 
of the pulmonary vasculature. A potential caveat of this ex-
periment is the additional endogenous H-2D b -restricted CD8 
T cell response in WT→WT chimeric mice which is absent 
in WT→H-2D b chimeras. However, endogenous T cells are 
subjected to strong PD-1-PD-L1-mediated down-regulation 
and likely exert a negligible impact on pathology development 
compared with the transferred 2.5 × 10 4 PD-1 / P14 cells. 
As CD8 T cell-mediated recruitment of polymorpho-
nuclear cells was suggested to contribute to fatal CNS pathology 
after intracranial LCMV infection (Kim et al., 2009), we con-
sidered a role of polymorphonuclear cells in the development 
of the pathology described here. A major effector mechanism 
of polymorphonuclear cells is the production of cytotoxic 
and vasodilatative nitric oxide species (NOs). The activity of </p>



<p>Endothelial guard from T cell killing | Frebel et al. </p>

<p>Mice and infections. The following mouse strains were housed and bred in 
specific pathogen-free facilities at the Institute of Microbiology, ETH Zurich, or 
at the RCC Füllinsdorf, Switzerland: C57BL/6 mice, PD-1 KO (Pdcd1 / ) 
mice (Nishimura et al., 1998), PKOB mice (Kägi et al., 1994), H-2D b KO mice 
(Pascolo et al., 1997), and CD45.1 + P14 mice. All KO and transgenic mice were 
on a C57BL/6 background with &gt;10 backcrosses. C57BL/6 mice were also 
purchased from Elevage Janvier. Transgenic CD45.1 + P14 mice expressing a 
TCR specific for the LCMV epitope GP33-41 were described previously 
(Pircher et al., 1990). CD45.1 + P14 mice were crossed with PD-1 KO mice to 
generate PD-1 / CD45.1 + P14 mice. All animals were used at 6-14 wk of age. 
This also applied to PD-1 KO mice that had been reported to spontaneously 
develop mild autoimmune disease only with advanced age (6 mo or older; 
Nishimura et al., 1999). The LCMV isolates clone 13, docile, and WE were 
provided by R.M. Zinkernagel (University Hospital, Zurich, Switzerland). For 
LCMV infection, mice were injected i.v. with 200 or 10 6 pfu of respective 
strains. The viral peptides GP33-41 (GP33; KAVYNFATM) and NP396-404 
(NP396; FQPQNGQFI) were purchased from NeoMPS (Strasbourg, France). </p>

<p>Core temperature and experiment endpoint. Mice were anesthetized for 
90 s with isoflurane (3.5% in oxygen) and the core temperature was mea-
sured in the rectum using a rectal temperature probe of a Homeothermic 
Blanket Control Unit (Harvard Apparatus). In accordance with veterinary 
office regulations, mice that exhibited a &gt;15% decrease of the steady-state 
rectal temperature (35.5°C) were considered to be irreversibly diseased and 
euthanized immediately. </p>

<p>Tetramers, antibodies, neutralizations, blockades, and depletions. 
APC-conjugated peptide-MHC class I tetrameric complexes were produced 
as previously described (Altman et al., 1996). All antibodies for flow cyto-
metric analysis were purchased from BioLegend (LucernaChem) or BD. For 
double neutralization of IFN- and TNF, 500 µg IFN- (clone: R4-6A2 
or XMG1.1; BioXCell) and 500 µg TNF (clone: XT3.11; BioXCell) were 
injected i.p. on days 1, 3, and 5 p.i. For simultaneous neutralization of TNF 
and blockade of IL-6R, 660 µg IL-6R (clone: 15A7; BioXCell) and 500 µg 
TNF (clone: XT3.11; BioXCell) were injected i.p. on days 1, 3, and 5 p.i. 
For T cell depletion, mice were injected i.p. with 200 µg CD4 (clone: YTS 
191.1) or with 200 µg CD8 (clone: YTS169) every second day starting on 
day 3 p.i. For PD-L1 blockade, 200 µg PD-L1 (clone: 10F.9G2; BioXCell) 
were injected i.p. daily from days 0 to 5 p.i. </p>

<p>Stimulation of lymphocytes and flow cytometry. Lymphocytes were 
isolated from organs of PBS-perfused mice and stimulated with 1 µg/ml 
GP33 + 1 µg/ml NP396 peptide in the presence of 10 µg/ml Brefeldin A 
(Sigma-Aldrich) for 5 h at 37°C. For analysis of degranulation, 1 µl CD107a 
was added during the stimulation. Surface staining was conducted for 30 min 
at 4°C. Afterward, cells were fixed and permeabilized in 500 µl 2× FACS 
Lyse (BD) with 0.05% Tween 20 (Sigma-Aldrich) for 10 min at room tem-
perature. The cells were washed and intracellular staining was conducted for 
30 min at room temperature. Cells were washed and resuspended in PBS 
containing 1% PFA (Sigma-Aldrich). Flow cytometric analysis was performed 
using an LSRII flow cytometer in combination with <rs id="software-0" type="software">FACSDiva</rs> software 
(both <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">BD</rs>). Raw data were analyzed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">FlowJo</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Tree Star</rs>). </p>

<p>Cell isolation, adoptive transfers, and cell line. CD8 T cells were puri-
fied from spleen single cell suspensions using MACS microbeads for positive 
selection of CD8 T cells in combination with LS columns (Miltenyi Biotec) 
according to the manufacturer's instructions. 1 × 10 4 or 2.5 × 10 4 purified 
CD8 T cells isolated from naive PD-1 +/+ CD45.1 + P14 or PD-1 / CD45.1 + 
P14 mice were adoptively transferred into naive recipient mice on day 1 p.i. 
The endothelial cell line MS-I was obtained from R.A. Schuepbach. </p>

<p>Analysis of serum cytokine, serum liver AST, serum albumin, BAL 
albumin, BAL total protein, and blood glucose concentrations. 
Serum cytokine concentrations were measured using Cytometric Bead Array 
kits (BD) according to the manufacturer's instructions. The obtained raw data </p>

<p>investigating the benefit of PD-1 blockade in the context of 
cancer treatment showed adverse events including pneumo-
nitis (Brahmer et al., 2012; Topalian et al., 2012). Our results 
now highlight important aspects that might be worth consid-
ering for therapeutic approaches targeting the PD-1-PD-L1 
pathway; although an increase of T cell function by PD-L1 
blockade during the advanced phase of systemic LCMV 
infection improves virus control apparently devoid of clini-
cally relevant immunopathology (Barber et al., 2006), PD-L1 
blockade in the early phase of the same infection is lethal. 
This suggests divergent roles of PD-1-PD-L1-mediated 
immunoinhibition during distinct phases of the infection, 
being host-protective during the early phase but promot-
ing pathogen persistence during the advanced phase. Accord-
ingly, the timing of PD-L1 blockade might be crucial to 
avoid adverse side effects. Our data further indicate that 
the pathogen's biology and pathogen-specific aspects of 
the immune response have to be taken into consideration. 
Pathology could only be induced using LCMV inoculum 
doses that led to the systemic infection of endothelial cells 
at the time of extensive T cell expansion. Therefore, it is 
likely that the systemic nature of the infection, as well as a 
viral tropism which includes endothelial cells, is required 
to evoke the described pathology of the vascular system. 
This view is supported by a recent study describing a new 
infection model of a further endothelial cell-tropic Arena-
virus, Lassa virus, where the infection of WT mice caused 
increased vascular permeability and edema formation with 
a strict CD8 T cell dependence of the pathology (Flatz et al., 
2010). Interestingly, Lassa virus and LCMV share their cellular 
receptor, -Dystroglycan, which is expressed by endothe-
lial cells (Kunz et al., 2001, 2005). Moreover, Lassa virus 
was shown to infect human and nonhuman primate endo-
thelial cells (Lukashevich et al., 1999; Hensley et al., 2011), 
whereas the infection of nonhuman primates is associated 
with coagulopathy and hypotension (Fisher-Hoch et al., 
1987). As the systemic LCMV infection of WT mice already 
caused a mild increase of vascular permeability and intra-
vascular coagulation compared with naive WT mice, it can be 
speculated that PD-L1 blockade aggravates a clinically silent 
pathology during systemic LCMV infection which might 
have comparable pathophysiological mechanisms to those 
observed during Lassa virus infection. 
In summary, we identified a mechanism through which the 
inhibitory PD-1-PD-L1 pathway protects vascular integrity 
during early systemic LCMV infection by down-modulating 
cytotoxic CD8 T cell effector functions. Our findings pro-
vide relevant insights for the development of therapeutic 
approaches that aim at intervening with the PD-1-PD-L1 
pathway and potentially other negative regulatory pathways. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Ethics statement. This study was performed in strict accordance with the 
guidelines of the animal experimentation law (SR 455.163; TVV) of the Swiss 
Federal Government. The protocol was approved by Cantonal Veterinary Office 
of the canton of Zurich, Switzerland (Permit number 146/2008). </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 13 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>

<p>2497 </p>

<p>Wet/dry weight ratio. The thorax of lethally anesthetized mice was 
opened and the hilum of the right lung was closed immediately with surgical 
filament. The prepared right lung was removed and weighed (wet weight). 
After drying for &gt;30 h at 60°C, the lung was weighed (dry weight) and the 
wet/dry weight ratio was calculated. </p>

<p>Analysis of blood oxygenation and arterial blood pressure. Arterial 
blood gases and blood pressure were analyzed in conscious and resting mice. 
While anesthetized with isoflurane (2-2.5% in oxygen), mice were im-
planted with a polyethylene catheter into the left femoral artery. After apply-
ing two drops of 2% lidocaine solution (Streuli) to the wound, it was closed 
and mice were allowed to recover from anesthesia for 15 min while continu-
ously recording blood pressure with a piezoelectric pressure transducer and a 
PowerLab system (ADInstruments). 100 µl blood was drawn from the cath-
eter for blood gas and lactate measurements (AVL700 Radiometer). Mice 
were euthanized by cervical dislocation after drawing blood. Kinetics of 
the systolic arterial blood pressure were measured noninvasively using the 
BP-2000 Blood Pressure Analysis System (Visitech Systems). </p>

<p>Statistics. Statistical significance was determined with an unpaired two-tailed 
Student's t test in <rs id="software-5" type="software">Prism</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>). </p>

<p>We would like to thank Nathalie Oetiker and Franziska Wagen (ETH Zurich), as 
well as Karin Eugster and Eva Allgäuer (Cantonal Hospital St. Gallen), for technical 
assistance. In addition, we thank Bernhard Odermatt (University Hospital Zurich) 
for the analysis of histological sections and Daniel Binder (Cantonal Hospital 
Winterthur) for determining blood cell counts. We also thank Mrs. Frebber from 
Siemens Healthcare for providing the Enzygnost Tat micro kit. We are grateful for 
the analysis of AST and albumin concentrations in serum and BAL conducted by the 
Department of Clinical Chemistry, University Hospital Zurich. 
This work was funded by the ETH Zurich and the Swiss National Science 
Foundation (grant no. 310030-113947 to A. Oxenius). 
The authors declare no financial or commercial conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Submitted: 11 May 2012 
Accepted: 13 November 2012 </p>

<p><rs id="software-2" type="software">FCAP Array</rs><rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Soft Flow Inc.</rs></p>

<p>Histopathology. Multiple liver lobes were taken from PBS-perfused mice, em-
bedded in Tissue-Tek OCT compound (Sakura) and snap-frozen in liquid nitro-
gen. Sections were cut in a cryostat and stained with H&amp;E. For lung histology, 
multiple lobes were taken from nonperfused mice and fixed in PBS buffered for-
malin. Fixed tissue was embedded in paraffin and sections were stained with H&amp;E 
at the Cantonal Hospital, St. Gallen, Switzerland. All sections were examined by 
a pathologist blinded to the specific experimental conditions. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence. Isolated nonperfused lungs were immersed in BSS, 
snap frozen in liquid nitrogen and cut in a cryostat. For cryopreservation, 
10-µm tissue sections were fixed in acetone for 10 min. After thawing, tissue 
sections were air dried and TUNEL staining was performed according to the 
manufacturer's protocol for the In situ Cell Death Detection kit TMR red 
(Roche). For surface stainings, sections were incubated with CD31 Alex-
648 (LucernaChem) in a humidified chamber for 2 h at room temperature 
and nuclei were visualized with DAPI. Images were acquired on the con-
focal microscope LSM 710 (Carl Zeiss) and processed using the <rs id="software-3" type="software">ZEN</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-date">2009</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Carl Zeiss</rs>) software and <rs id="software-4" type="software">DRAW X4</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Corel</rs>). </p>

<p>Virus loads and chromium release assay. Virus loads were determined 
in the spleen, one lung lobe, and one brain hemisphere as previously de-
scribed (Battegay et al., 1991). For chromium release assays, four WT mice 
were transferred with 2.5 × 10 4 P14 cells and infected with 10 6 pfu LCMV 
docile on the next day. On day 6 p.i., splenic CD8 T cells were purified and 
used as effector cells. As target cells, MS-I cells were cultured with and with-
out 100 U/ml IFN- for 48 h and labeled with 100 µCi of Na 2 
51 CrO 4 
(Hartmann Analytic) for 90 min at 37°C. At the same time, cells were pulsed 
with the LCMV peptides GP33 (1 µg/ml) + NP396 (1 µg/ml) and incu-
bated with 30 µg/ml PD-L1 (clone: 10F.9G2; BioXCell), where indicated. 
Cells were washed twice and co-cultured with effector cells at given ratios in 
duplicates in a 96-well plate for 6 h at 37°C. Spontaneous release (SR) was 
measured with target cells only in triplicate and maximum release (MR) with 
target cells plus 2N HCl in triplicate. After incubation, supernatant was 
taken from each well and chromium release was measured using a Packard 
Cobra Auto Gamma Counter (PerkinElmer). Specific lysis was calculated 
according to the following formula: % specific lysis = (CPM Sample  CPM SR )/ 
(CPM MR  CPM SR ) × 100. </p>

<p>Bone marrow chimeric mice. Chimeric mice were generated by trans-
ferring 5 × 10 6 bone marrow cells isolated from C57BL/6 mice to recipients 
that had been lethally irradiated (950 rad) 1 d before the transfer. During the 
first 14 d of reconstitution, mice were treated with a 1:250 dilution of Borgal 
24% (Intervet) in drinking water. Chimeric mice were used for experiments 
6 wk after reconstitution. </p>

<p>Analysis of vascular permeability. Mice were injected i.v. with 200 µl of 
0.5% EB in PBS. After 20 min, mice were lethally anesthetized and transcar-
dially perfused with 10 ml PBS to remove intravascular EB. One liver lobe, 
one kidney, two lung lobes, and one brain hemisphere were excised and 
weighed. To extract extravascular EB, each organ was incubated in 1 ml form-
amide overnight at 56°C. The amount of extracted EB was determined by a 
photometrical analysis of the EB-formamide solution at 620 nm and by 
comparing to an EB standard curve. </p>

<p>Plasma TAT concentrations and platelet counts. Plasma TAT con-
centrations were analyzed using the Enzygnost Tat micro kit (Siemens 
Healthcare) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Blood platelet 
counts were determined at the Hematology Department of the Cantonal 
Hospital, Winterthur, Switzerland. </p>



<p>JEM Vol. 209, No. 13 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>





</text></tei>