<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3834693" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A b s t r a c t </p>

<p>I In nt tr ro od du uc ct ti io on n: : Photoaging is the superposition of chronic ultraviolet (UV)-induced damage on intrinsic aging. Telom-
ere length is a molecular marker of cell aging, and genomic instability due to telomere shortening has been linked 
to several aging-related diseases. 
A Ai im m: : To explore the effects of different doses of ultraviolet A (UVA) on the length of telomeres in human skin fibro -
blasts and partly reveal the mechanism of skin photoaging initiated by UVA irradiation. 
M Ma at te er ri ia al l a an nd d m 
me et th ho od ds s: Primary cultured human skin fibroblasts were irradiated with different doses of UVA light. 
Cell viability, cell cycle phase, β-galactosidase, and the length of telomeres were assessed by 3-(4,5-di me thyl -
thiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide assay, flow cytometry, cytochemical staining, and real-time polymerase 
chain reactions, respectively. 
R Re es su ul lt ts s: : After UVA irradiation, inhibited proliferation, S phase accumulation and increased expression of senescence-
associated β-galactosidase were observed in cultured fibroblasts. Moreover, the length of telomeres in UVA-treat-
ed cells was shortened in a dose-dependent manner as compared to controls (p &lt; 0.05). 
C Co on nc cl lu us si io on ns s: : These results suggest that telomere length in human dermal fibroblasts can be shortened by a single 
high dosage of UVA radiation, and that acute photodamage might contribute to early photoaging in human skin 
via rapid telomere shortening. This study potentially provides the basis for better understanding of the molecular 
mechanism of photoaging. </p>

<p>K Ke ey y w wo or rd ds s: : photoaging, human fibroblast, ultraviolet A, cell cycle, telomere. </p>

<p>Photoaging is the superposition of chronic ultraviolet 
(UV)-induced damage on intrinsic aging. It accounts for 
denaturation of dermal elastic fibers and characteristic deep 
wrinkles, and is a well-known factor leading to skin can-
cer [1, 2]. 
Telomere length is a molecular marker of cell aging, and 
genomic instability due to telomere shortening has been 
linked to aging-related diseases, especially cancer [3]. It has 
been postulated that telomere shortening played an 
important role in photoaging [4, 5]. Recent studies have sug-
gested that intrinsic aging and photoaging share a com-
mon pathway involving telomere-generated signaling 
that is responsible for most clinical manifestations of skin </p>

<p>aging [1, 4, 6]. However, an earlier study showed that telom-
ere length did not differ significantly between sun-
exposed and sun-protected skin [7, 8]. Thus, whether the 
length of telomere is shortened in photoaging remains 
unclear. </p>

<p>Aim </p>

<p>Ultraviolet A (UVA), the principal component of solar 
radiation, penetrates deep into the dermis [9]. In this study, 
we investigated the photodamaging effects of different dos-
es of UVA radiation on cultured human skin fibroblasts 
(HSFs), focusing on proliferation, cell cycle, senescence-
associated β-galactosidase expression and telomere 
length [10]. </p>

<p>Postępy Dermatologii i Alergologii XXX; 2013/1 </p>



<p>Bin Yin, Xian Jiang </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of 
West China Hospital. All the parents of all donors provid-
ed signed written consent. </p>

<p>C Ce el ll l c cu ul lt tu ur re e </p>

<p>Primary HSF cultures were obtained by outgrowth from 
the foreskins of healthy human donors aged 3-10 years [11]. 
Tissue specimens were washed in Dulbecco's modified 
Eagle's medium (DMEM; Gibco BRL, Gaithersburg, MD, USA) 
with 100 IU/ml penicillin and 100 µg/ml streptomycin (Gib-
co), minced finely and allowed to adhere to plastic flasks. 
Cells were maintained in DMEM supplemented with 10% 
fetal bovine serum (FBS; Thermo Scientific HyClone, 
Logan, UT, USA) and incubated at 37°C in a humidified 
atmosphere of 5% CO 2 -95% air [12, 13]. When the cells 
reached 80% confluence, subculture was conducted at 
a split ratio of 1 : 3. Cells were utilized between passages 
3 and 5. </p>

<p>U UV VA A i ir rr ra ad di ia at ti io on n </p>

<p>Human skin fibroblasts were inoculated in 6-and 
96-well plates and 35 mm dishes, cultured to 80% con-
fluence and then irradiated with UVA. Before irradiation, 
the culture medium was replaced by phosphate-buffered 
saline (PBS; Gibco). A UVA desktop apparatus (Sigma High-
tech, Shanghai, China) was used as the light source with 
a spectrum of 320-400 nm as certified by the manufacturer. 
A 6-mm thick glass plate was used to block UVB emissions. 
UVA intensity was measured using a digital radiometer (Sig-
ma, Shanghai, China). The exposure distance was 20 cm. 
During irradiation, the plates or dishes were cooled on ice 
to avoid cell damage from heating. After irradiation, the 
cells were immediately further incubated in fresh DMEM 
containing 10% FBS at 37°C in a humidified atmosphere 
of 5% CO 2 . Cell viability and other tests were performed 
24 h post-irradiation. Cells in the control group were treat-
ed the same as the irradiated cells except for the absence 
of UVA irradiation. Four doses of UVA were used in this 
study, including 5, 10, 15 and 20 J/cm 2 . </p>

<p>C Ce el ll l v 
vi ia ab bi il li it ty y m me ea as su ur re em me en nt t </p>

<p>To determine cell viability, a 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-
2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT; Gibco) assay 
was performed. HSFs (2 × 10 3 per well) were incubated in 
96-well plates overnight before irradiation to allow attach-
ment to the wells. The cells were incubated post-irradia-
tion for 24 h. MTT (20 µl of 5 mg/ml) was added to each 
well and the cells were incubated for 4 h at 37°C. The super-
natant was then removed and 100 µl dimethyl sulfoxide 
was added. The optical density was measured on 
a microplate reader (Spectra Max 190; Molecular Devices, 
Sunnyvale, CA, USA) at 490 nm to determine the viable cell 
percentage. </p>

<p>C Ce el ll l c 
cy yc cl le e a 
an na al ly ys si is s </p>

<p>After UVA irradiation, HSFs were incubated for 24 h be -
fore trypsinization and centrifugation. Collected cells were 
washed twice with cold PBS and fixed in 70% ethanol at 
4°C overnight. The cells were then treated with 50 mg/l 
RNase (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) and stained with 
50 mg/l propidium iodide (Sigma) in the dark at 37°C for 
30 min. The cell cycle was analyzed using flow cytometry 
(Cytomics FC500; Beckman Coulter, Fullerton CA, USA). </p>

<p>S Se en ne es sc ce en nc ce e--a as ss so oc ci ia at te ed d β--g ga al la ac ct to os si id da as se e s st ta ai in ni in ng g </p>

<p>Human skin fibroblasts were incubated for 24 h after 
UVA irradiation, and then trypsinized and further incubated 
for 24 h in 6-well plates (1 × 10 4 per well) (BD Falcon, Los 
Angeles, CA, USA). A Senescence β-Galactosidase Stain-
ing Kit (Beyotime, Shanghai, China) was used as previously 
described [14]. Briefly, cells were washed with PBS, fixed 
for 15 min in 3% formaldehyde, rinsed three times with PBS 
and stained at 37°C with 1 ml X-Gal solution overnight. 
Staining was evident in 12-16 h. Visual fields were select-
ed randomly and up to 500 cells were counted at 200× mag-
nification. β-Galactosidase-positive cells were expressed 
as a percentage of the total number of counted cells. </p>

<p>D DN NA A e ex xt tr ra ac ct ti io on n a 
an nd d r 
re el la at ti iv ve e q 
qu ua an nt ti it ta at ti iv ve e r 
re ea al l--t ti im me e 
p po ol ly ym me er ra as se e c 
ch ha ai in n r 
re ea ac ct ti io on n </p>

<p>Relative quantitative real-time polymerase chain reac-
tion (PCR) analysis was performed 24 h post-irradiation. 
To measure telomere length, total DNA was extracted using 
a Genomic DNA Extraction Kit (Dongsheng Biotech, 
Guangzhou, China) according to the manufacturer's man-
ual. Genomic DNA was quantified using a UV-Vis spec-
trophotometer (Smart Spectro 2000; LaMotte, Chestertown, 
MD, USA). 
Mean telomere length was determined using quanti-
tative real-time PCR as described previously [15]. This 
method measures the average ratio between the telom-
ere repeat copy number and that of a single-copy gene 
(36B4; T/S ratio) in each sample. The T/S ratio is propor-
tional to the average telomere length, and the relative 
telomere length can therefore be calculated quantitatively. 
Real-time PCR reactions were performed using an iCycler 
(Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). 
Duplicate DNA samples were amplified in parallel in 
20 µl PCR reactions containing 35 ng sample DNA, 10 µl 
Power SYBR Green Master Mix (Applied Biosystems, Fos-
ter City, CA, USA) and 1 µM of primers specific for telom-
eres (1: 5'-GGTTTTTGAGGGTGAGGGTGAGGGTGAGGGT-
GAGGGT-3'; 2: 5'-TCCCGACTATCCCTATCCCTATCCCTATCC-
CTATCCCTA-3') or the single-copy gene (36B4u: 5'-CAGCAA-
GTGGGAAGGTGTAATCC-3'; 36B4d: 5'-CCCATTCTATCAT-
CAACGGGTACAA-3'). 
Thermal cycling began with 95°C incubation for 10 min 
followed by 40 cycles of 95°C for 20 s and 54°C for 2 min 
(for telomeres) or 58°C for 1 min (for 36B4). Standard curves </p>

<p>Postępy Dermatologii i Alergologii XXX; 2013/1 </p>



<p>were established for each assay using serial dilutions of 
sample DNA (five concentrations, dilution factor ~2). 
Linear correlation coefficients (r 2 ) for telomere and 36B4 
standard curves were 0.98 and 0.99, respectively. Relative 
telomere length was calculated from T/S ratio = 2 -∆Ct , where 
∆Ct = Ct telomere -Ct 36B4 . </p>

<p>S St ta at ti is st ti ic ca al l a an na al ly ys si is s </p>

<p>All experiments were repeated at least three times. The 
results were expressed as mean ± SD. Data were analyzed 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13.0</rs>. Value of p &lt; 0.05 was considered statis-
tically significant. Student's t-test was used to compare two 
means. To compare multiple means, one-way analysis of 
variance in conjunction with Dunnett's test was performed. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>U UV VA A i ir rr ra ad di ia at ti io on n d de ec cr re ea as se es s c ce el ll l v vi ia ab bi il li it ty y 
The cytotoxicity of UVA irradiation was evaluated by 
MTT assay at 24 h post-irradiation. Compared with neg-
ative controls, the viability of irradiated fibroblasts was 
decreased in a dose-dependent manner. Inhibition of pro-
liferation was observed in cells exposed to a dose of 15 J/cm 2 
or 20 J/cm 2 (p &lt; 0.05; Figure 1). </p>

<p>U UV VA A i ir rr ra ad di ia at ti io on n i in nd du uc ce es s c ce el ll l c 
cy yc cl le e a ar rr re es st t i in n h hu um ma an n s 
sk ki in n 
f fi ib br ro ob bl la as st ts s </p>

<p>The dependence of HSF cell cycle distribution on 
a UVA dose at 24 h post-irradiation was illustrated by a typ-
ical series of flow cytometry histograms (Figure 2). Com-
pared with non-irradiated controls, the proportion of 
UVA-irradiated fibroblasts in S phase was significantly 
increased at 24 h (p &lt; 0.05), whereas the proportion in G2 
phase was significantly decreased (p &lt; 0.05). This effect 
was dose dependent (Table 1). Moreover, a statistically sig-
nificant difference in the proportion of cells in G1 phase 
was seen between the 20 J/cm 2 group and negative con-
trols (Table 1). </p>

<p>U UV VA A i ir rr ra ad di ia at ti io on n i in nc cr re ea as se es s t 
th he e e 
ex xp pr re es ss si io on n 
o of f β 
β--g ga al la ac ct to os si id da as se e i in n h hu um ma an n s sk ki in n f fi ib br ro ob bl la as st ts s </p>

<p>β-Galactosidase expression was increased in a dose-
dependent manner after UVA irradiation (Figure 3). UVA </p>

<p>doses of 15 J/cm 2 and 20 J/cm 2 induced a significant in -
crease in β-galactosidase activity compared with that in 
the control group (p &lt; 0.05) (Figure 3). </p>

<p>U UV VA A i ir rr ra ad di ia at ti io on n d de ec cr re ea as se es s m me ea an n t te el lo om me er re e l le en ng gt th h 
i in n h hu um ma an n s sk ki in n f fi ib br ro ob bl la as st ts s </p>

<p>After incubation for 24 h post-irradiation, mean telom-
ere length was evaluated using relative quantitative real-
time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and was found to 
be reduced in a dose-dependent manner (Figure 4). There 
was a statistically significant difference between the 
high dose groups (10, 15 and 20 J/cm 2 ) and the sham-irra-
diated controls (p &lt; 0.05) (Figure 4). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The major findings of this study are as follows. First-
ly, UVA irradiation decreases cell viability. Secondly, UVA 
irradiation induces cell cycle arrest in HSFs. Thirdly, UVA 
irradiation increases the expression of β-galactosidase in 
HSFs. Finally, UVA irradiation decreases mean telomere 
length in HSFs. 
UVA doses below 10 J/cm 2 administered to fibroblasts 
in vitro are of physiological relevance as it is similar to the 
dose at which human skin is exposed in sunlight for 
15-30 min during summer, at noon at a latitude of 30-35°N 
[16]. In this study, we found that the viability of cultured </p>

<p>Telomere shortening in cultured human dermal fibroblasts is associated with acute photodamage induced by UVA irradiation </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 1 1. . Ultraviolet A irradiation decreases the viability of 
cultured HSFs at 24 h post-irradiation </p>

<p>*p &lt; 0.05 compared with controls 
C Ce el ll l v vi ia ab bi il li it ty y ( (% % o of f c co on nt tr ro ol l) ) </p>

<p>U UV VA A [ [J J/ /c cm m 2 2 ] ] </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 </p>

<p>T Ta ab bl le e 1 1. . Effects of ultraviolet A irradiation on the cell cycle of cultured HSFs at 24 h post-irradiation </p>

<p>G Gr ro ou up p 
D Do os se e [ [J J/ /c cm m 2 2 ] ] 
% %G G1 1 
% %S S 
% %G G2 2 </p>

<p>Control 
0 
74.43 ±2.84 
13.23 ±2.02 
12.33 ±0.82 </p>

<p>UVA 
5 
69.93 ±1.91 
24.6 ±1.13* 
5.48 ±0.78* </p>

<p>UVA 
10 
70.23 ±1.33 
26.46 ±1.51* 
3.29 ±0.26* </p>

<p>UVA 
15 
68.35 ±1.61 
31.26 ±1.36* 
0.37 ±0.26* </p>

<p>UVA 
20 
63.53 ±0.96* 
36.23 ±1.11* 
0.23 ±0.31* </p>

<p>*p &lt; 0.05, compared with control, UVA -ultraviolet A </p>

<p>Postępy Dermatologii i Alergologii XXX; 2013/1 </p>



<p>Bin Yin, Xian Jiang </p>

<p>C Ce el ll l n nu um mb be er r </p>

<p>2520 </p>

<p>2100 </p>

<p>1680 </p>

<p>1260 </p>

<p>840 </p>

<p>420 </p>

<p>0 
0 
32 
64 
96 
128 
160 
192 
224 
256 
D DN NA A C Co on nt te en nt t </p>

<p>F 
Fi ig gu ur re e 2 2. . The cell cycle distribution of cultured HSFs depends 
on ultraviolet A dose at 24 h post-irradiation: A A -controls, 
B 
B -5 J/cm 2 , C 
C -10 J/cm 2 , D 
D -15 J/cm 2 , E 
E -20 J/cm 2 </p>

<p>A 
A </p>

<p>%G1 = 73.3 
%G2 = 12.3 
%S = 14.4 </p>

<p>C Ce el ll l n nu um mb be er r </p>

<p>840 </p>

<p>700 </p>

<p>560 </p>

<p>420 </p>

<p>280 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>0 0 
32 
64 
96 
128 
160 
192 
224 
256 
D DN NA A C Co on nt te en nt t </p>

<p>C C </p>

<p>%G1 = 70.1 
%G2 = 3.46 
%S = 26.4 </p>

<p>C Ce el ll l n nu um mb be er r </p>

<p>1320 </p>

<p>1100 </p>

<p>880 </p>

<p>660 </p>

<p>440 </p>

<p>220 </p>

<p>0 0 
32 
64 
96 
128 
160 
192 
224 
256 
D DN NA A C Co on nt te en nt t </p>

<p>E E </p>

<p>%G1 = 64.7 
%G2 = 0 
%S = 36.3 </p>

<p>3000 </p>

<p>2500 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>0 0 
32 
64 
96 
128 
160 
192 
224 
256 
D DN NA A C Co on nt te en nt t </p>

<p>%G1 = 67.3 
%G2 = 0.342 
%S = 32.3 </p>

<p>C Ce el ll l n nu um mb be er r </p>

<p>2640 </p>

<p>2200 </p>

<p>1760 </p>

<p>1320 </p>

<p>880 </p>

<p>440 </p>

<p>0 
0 
32 
64 
96 
128 
160 
192 
224 
256 
D DN NA A C Co on nt te en nt t </p>

<p>B B </p>

<p>%G1 = 69.4 
%G2 = 5.83 
%S = 24.8 </p>

<p>fibroblasts decreased as the intensity of irradiation 
increased. Doses less than 10 J/cm 2 did not affect prolif-
eration, suggesting that cell repair mechanisms can over-
come the stress generated by irradiation at this intensi-</p>

<p>ty. However, at doses over 10 J/cm 2 , the proliferation of 
fibroblast was inhibited, suggesting that the cytotoxicity 
induced by a larger dose of UVA cannot be repaired com-
pletely. </p>

<p>D D </p>

<p>C Ce el ll l n nu um mb be er r </p>

<p>Postępy Dermatologii i Alergologii XXX; 2013/1 </p>



<p>Telomere shortening in cultured human dermal fibroblasts is associated with acute photodamage induced by UVA irradiation </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 3 
3. . Ultraviolet A irradiation increased the expression 
of senescence-associated β-galactosidase in HSFs </p>

<p>*p &lt; 0.05 compared with controls </p>

<p>1 
10 00 0% %β 
β--G Ga al l p po os si it ti iv ve e c ce el ll ls s </p>

<p>U UV VA A [ [J J/ /c cm m 2 2 ] ] </p>

<p>100 
90 
80 
70 
60 
50 
40 
30 
20 
10 
0 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 </p>

<p>F Fi ig gu ur re e 4 4. . Ultraviolet A irradiation decreased the mean length 
of telomeres in HSFs at 24 h post-irradiation </p>

<p>*p &lt; 0.05 compared with controls </p>

<p>T T/ /S S </p>

<p>U UV VA A [ [J J/ /c cm m 2 
2 ] ] </p>

<p>2 
1.8 
1.6 
1.4 
1.2 
1 
0.8 
0.6 
0.4 
0.2 
0 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 </p>

<p>Features of cell senescence, including growth arrest and 
increased β-galactosidase expression, were also observed 
following a single large dose of UVA. Progression through 
S phase is slowed in eukaryotic cells with damaged DNA, 
allowing time for DNA repair before the genome is repli-
cated [17]. The S-M checkpoint depends on completion of 
DNA synthesis, preventing mitosis in the presence of incom-
pletely replicated DNA due to replication inhibitors or DNA 
damage that blocks replication fork progression [18]. In our 
study, UVA irradiation of cultured fibroblasts resulted in 
cell cycle alterations, especially S phase accumulation, sug-
gesting that UVA inhibits cell proliferation by inducing an 
S phase delay. Our data are consistent with a previous report 
[19] on the role of the DNA damage checkpoint response 
in UVA-induced inhibition of DNA replication. β-Galac-
tosidase has been widely used to demonstrate the onset 
of cell senescence [20]. In this study, in groups irradiated 
with UVA doses higher than 10 J/cm 2 , the expression of the 
enzyme was significantly increased. Here, we confirm that 
cytotoxicity induced by a single large dose of UVA may 
accelerate the aging processes. 
We found that mean telomere length in UVA-irradiat-
ed fibroblasts decreased with increased doses, and a sig-
nificant difference was observed between the high dosage 
groups and negative controls. Thus, acute photodamage 
might contribute to early photoaging in human skin as a con-
sequence of rapid telomere shortening. Telomere depen-
dent replicative senescence is an established stress-dam-
age response [21]. UVA causes oxidative stress indirectly via 
reactive oxygen species generated after the absorption of 
light energy [22, 23], and oxidative stress may lead to telom-
ere shortening [24, 25]. When telomeres reach a critical 
length, loop disruption may occur naturally [26], increas-
ing the probability of telomere uncapping. It remains con-
troversial whether telomere shortening results from accu-
mulation of DNA damage at the telomere or the lack of 
certain repair mechanisms within human chromosomal DNA. 
However, recent data suggest that telomere-initiated </p>

<p>senescence reflects a DNA damage checkpoint response that 
is activated with a direct contribution from dysfunctional 
telomeres [27]. The signaling pathway connecting telom-
ere uncapping and replicative senescence appears to be the 
same as that activated by DNA damage [21]. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>Telomere length in human dermal fibroblasts can be 
shortened by a single high dosage of UVA radiation, and 
that acute photodamage might contribute to early pho-
toaging in human skin via rapid telomere shortening. This 
study potentially provides the basis for better understanding 
of the molecular mechanism of photoaging. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This study was supported by Programs for Basic 
Research and Application of Sichuan China (No. 2010JY0061) 
and by the Scientific Research Starting Foundation for 
Returned Overseas Chinese Scholars, Ministry of Educa-
tion, China (Grant No. [2011] 508). </p>



<p>Postępy Dermatologii i Alergologii XXX; 2013/1 </p>





</text></tei>