<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3464321" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: To establish and validate a formula to predict spectral domain (SD)-optical coherence tomography 
(OCT) retinal nerve fiber layer (RNFL) thickness from time domain (TD)-OCT RNFL measurements and other 
factors. 
Methods: SD-OCT and TD-OCT scans were obtained on the same day from healthy participants and patients 
with glaucoma. Univariate and multivariate linear regression relationships were analyzed to convert average 
Stratus TD-OCT measurements to average Cirrus SD-OCT measurements. Additional baseline characteris-
tics included age, sex, intraocular pressure, central corneal thickness, spherical equivalent, anterior chamber 
depth, optic disc area, visual field (VF) mean deviation, and pattern standard deviation. The formula was gen-
erated using a training set of 220 patients and then evaluated on a validation dataset of 105 patients. 
Results: The training set included 71 healthy participants and 149 patients with glaucoma. The validation set 
included 27 healthy participants and 78 patients with glaucoma. Univariate analysis determined that TD-OCT 
RNFL thickness, age, optic disc area, VF mean deviation, and pattern standard deviation were significantly 
associated with SD-OCT RNFL thickness. Multivariate regression analysis using available variables yielded 
the following equation: SD-OCT RNFL = 0.746 × TD-OCT RNFL + 17.104 (determination coefficient [R 2 ] = 0.879). 
In the validation sample, the multiple regression model explained 85.6% of the variance in the SD-OCT RNFL 
thickness. 
Conclusions: The proposed formula based on TD-OCT RNFL thickness may be useful in predicting SD-OCT 
RNFL thickness. Other factors associated with SD-OCT RNFL thickness, such as age, disc area, and mean 
deviation, did not contribute to the accuracy of the final equation. </p>



<p>Korean J Ophthalmol Vol.26, No.5, 2012 </p>

<p>corporates spectral domain (SD) imaging, which offers 
significant advantages over traditional TD-OCT tech-
niques, including a faster scanning speed and higher-reso-
lution RNFL imaging [6,7]. Many patients who have been 
scanned with Stratus OCT can now potentially be scanned 
with Cirrus OCT (Carl Zeiss Meditec) [8]. The clinical rel-
evance of the new SD technology requires data from these 
devices to be compared with preexisting, widely accepted 
TD standards and with each other [9]. 
Previous studies have indicated that measurements with 
TD-OCT and SD-OCT instruments cannot be considered 
interchangeable, although the two types of measurements 
have been strongly correlated [8-14]. Equations based on 
regression models to calculate SD-OCT RNFL thickness 
measurements from TD-OCT RNFL measurements in pa-
tients with glaucoma have been previously proposed [8,15]. 
However, no equation has yet been developed that specifi-
cally estimates SD-OCT RNFL thickness in consideration 
of clinical and demographic variables. 
The present study was designed to determine the rela-
tionship between RNFL thickness measurements from 
TD-OCT and SD-OCT in normal participants and patients 
with glaucoma and to develop a new formula using regres-
sion analysis to predict SD-OCT RNFL thickness that 
includes clinical and demographic factors. Cross-validation 
analysis was then used to evaluate the validity of this novel 
formula. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Participants </p>

<p>Participants were consecutively enrolled from the 
Glaucoma-Cataract Clinic of Severance Hospital at Yon-
sei University (Seoul, Korea) from January 2009 to June 
2010. The Severance Hospital Institutional Review Board 
approved the protocol, and the study complied with the te-
nets of the Declaration of Helsinki. Informed consent was 
obtained from all participants prior to their participation in 
the study. 
All participants underwent a full ophthalmic exami-
nation, which included measurements of visual acuity, 
refraction, and intraocular pressure (by Goldmann appla-
nation tonometry), as well as slit lamp examination, goni-
oscopy, fundus examination with a 90 D lens, pachymetry 
(DGH-1000 instrument; DGH Technology Inc., Frazer, PA, 
USA), and visual field (VF) testing with standard auto-
mated perimetry (Humphrey field analyzer II with Swed-
ish Interactive Thresholding Algorithm standard 24-2, 
Carl Zeiss Meditec). A reliable VF test result was defined 
as less than 20% fixation loss and false-positive and false-
negative errors less than 15%. Axial ocular dimensions, 
including axial length and anterior chamber depth, were 
measured using partial laser interferometry (IOL master, </p>

<p>Carl Zeiss Meditec). All eyes underwent Stratus TD-OCT 
and Cirrus SD-OCT after pupillary dilation (minimum di-
ameter, 5 mm). Disc area measurements were obtained us-
ing the optic nerve head mode of Stratus OCT (Carl Zeiss 
Meditec). All measurements in any individual patient were 
performed within a single day. 
Normal eyes had a best corrected visual acuity of 20 / 40 
or better, with a refractive error between +3.00 and -8.00 
diopters, intraocular pressure of 21 mmHg or lower, open 
angle on gonioscopy, normal fundus examination, normal-
appearing optic nerve head, and reliable normal VF tests 
with normal glaucoma hemifield test results, as well as a 
normal mean deviation and pattern standard deviation ( p 
&gt; 0.05). 
Glaucomatous eyes were defined as eyes with a glauco-
matous VF defect confirmed by two reliable VF examina-
tions and by the appearance of a glaucomatous optic disc 
with typical loss of neuroretinal rim as judged by slit lamp 
biomicroscopy (cup-to-disc ratio, &gt;0.7; intereye cup asym-
metry, &gt;0.2; or neuroretinal rim notching, focal thinning, 
disc hemorrhage, or vertical elongation of the optic cup). 
Intraocular pressure was not used as a criterion for the 
glaucoma group. A field defect was defined as having three 
or more significant ( p &lt; 0.05) non-edged contiguous points 
with at least one at the p &lt; 0.01 level, located on the same 
side of the horizontal meridian in the pattern deviation 
plot, classified as outside normal limits in the glaucoma 
hemifield test, and confirmed with at least two VF exami-
nations. Only patients with open anterior chamber angle, a 
corrected visual acuity of 20 / 40 or better, and refractive 
error from +3.00 to -8.00 diopters were selected. Eyes with 
conditions affecting RNFL thickness measurements, such 
as diabetic retinopathy, degenerative or exudative reti-
nopathy, optic nerve head drusen, peripapillary atrophy, or 
tilted disc syndrome, were excluded from the study [16-18]. 
Participants who had undergone previous ocular surgery 
or who had vitreous opacity were also excluded from the 
study. </p>

<p>Optical coherence tomography technique </p>

<p>Cross-sectional imaging of the peripapillary area was 
first performed using Stratus-OCT (software ver. 4.0.1). 
The average RNFL thickness was measured with the Fast 
RNFL scan program, which consisted of three sets of 256 
A-scans along a circle with a 3.46 mm diameter centered 
on the optic disc, which was controlled by the examiner. 
The scanning took 1.92 seconds to complete. 
The average RNFL thickness was then determined us-
ing the optic disc cube protocol on Cirrus OCT (software 
ver. 3.0). This protocol generates a cube of data through a 
6-mm square grid by acquiring a series of 200 horizontal 
scan lines, each of which is composed of 200 A-scans. A 
calculation circle 3.46 mm in diameter and consisting of </p>



<p>KH Lee, et al. Predicting OCT RNFL Measurements </p>

<p>256 A-scans was automatically positioned around the optic 
disc. 
A single, well-trained technician performed all OCT 
examinations. The signal strength of each scan on the Stra-
tus and Cirrus was at least 6 (range, 0 to 10). Scans with 
misalignment, segmentation failure, or decentration of the 
measurement circle were excluded from the analysis. </p>

<p>Training and validation sets </p>

<p>The cohort was randomly subdivided into a training set 
and a validation set. In total, 325 participants enrolled in 
the present study, of whom 220 were randomly selected as 
the training sample; the remaining 105 participants consti-
tuted the validation sample. The associations between TD-
OCT RNFL thickness and SD-OCT RNFL thickness iden-
tified in the training set were then independently evaluated 
using the validation set. </p>

<p>Statistical methods </p>

<p>For cases in which both eyes of a patient were eligible 
for analysis, one eye was randomly selected to be evaluated 
for the present study. Scatter plots showing the differences 
between the two measurements and their averages were 
used to assess agreement between the two measurement 
types (SD-OCT and TD-OCT RNFL measurements, and 
observed and predicted SD-OCT RNFL measurements us-
ing our equation), as described by Bland and Altman [19]. 
The 95% limits of agreement, which were centered around 
the means of the differences, were also determined. 
The relationships between OCT measurements and other 
baseline characteristics were assessed by linear regres-</p>

<p>sion applied to the training sample consisting of a random 
sample of 220 of the 325 participants. Demographic and 
clinical variables assessed in the current study included 
age, sex, intraocular pressure, central corneal thickness, 
spherical equivalent, axial length, anterior chamber depth, 
optic disc area, VF mean deviation, and pattern standard 
deviation. Factors demonstrating a significant relationship 
(a p-value less than 0.1 as determined by univariate regres-
sion analysis) were further analyzed using multiple step-
wise regression analyses. A regression model for predicting 
SD-OCT RNFL measurements was established based on 
these results. Predicted SD-OCT RNFL thickness values 
were calculated according to this formula and compared 
with the actual SD-OCT RNFL thickness measurements 
to evaluate the performance of the prediction equation. 
The regression coefficients calculated from the train-
ing sample were then applied to obtain predicted SD-OCT 
RNFL thicknesses in a separate validation sample consist-
ing of 105 participants from the total sample group of 325 
participants. Statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">ver. 12.0.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). A p-value less 
than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Participant characteristics </p>

<p>Measurements and evaluation results of 325 eyes from 
325 patients were included in the present study. Patient 
characteristics of the training and validation sets are 
presented in Table 1. The mean age and sex proportions 
were similar between the training and validation samples. 
The training set included 71 healthy participants and 149 </p>

<p>Table 1. Characteristics of the study population </p>

<p>Training set (n = 220) 
Validation set (n = 105) 
p-value 
Age (yr) 
53.19 ± 16.00 
52.26 ± 16.18 
0.624 
Female sex 
102 (46.4) 
57 (54.3) 
0.182 
Intraocular pressure (mmHg) 
14.03 ± 3.11 
13.79 ± 3.17 
0.516 
Central corneal thickness (μm) 
548.61 ± 38.74 
541.40 ± 32.17 
0.169 
Spherical equivalent (diopters) 
-1.48 ± 3.17 
-1.31 ± 2.58 
0.722 
Axial length (mm) 
24.44 ± 1.60 
24.44 ± 1.50 
0.987 
Anterior chamber depth (mm) 
3.28 ± 0.50 
3.26 ± 0.61 
0.776 
Optic disc area (mm 2 ) 
2.73 ± 0.57 
2.70 ± 0.60 
0.643 
Mean deviation (dB) 
-4.97 ± 5.77 
-5.58 ± 6.35 
0.396 
Pattern standard deviation (dB) 
4.09 ± 3.57 
4.49 ± 3.91 
0.361 
Mean RNFL thickness by TD-OCT (μm) 
89.93 ± 18.45 
86.60 ± 18.53 
0.547 
Mean RNFL thickness by SD-OCT (μm) 
84.27 ± 14.71 
82.91 ± 14.39 
0.430 
Signal strength by TD-OCT 
8.04 ± 1.35 
8.04 ± 1.39 
0.084 
Signal strength by SD-OCT 
8.12 ± 1.06 
7.90 ± 1.02 
0.992 
Diagnosis 
Normal 
71 (32.3) 
27 (25.7) 
0.228 
Glaucoma 
149 (67.7) 
78 (74.3) 
Values are presented mean ± SD or as number (%). 
RNFL = retinal nerve fiber layer; TD = time domain; OCT = optical coherence tomography; SD = spectral domain. </p>



<p>Korean J Ophthalmol Vol.26, No.5, 2012 </p>

<p>patients with glaucoma. The validation set included 27 
healthy participants and 78 patients with glaucoma. </p>

<p>Comparison of Stratus OCT and Cirrus OCT retinal 
nerve fiber layer thickness measurements </p>

<p>As shown in Fig. 1, TD-OCT RNFL measurements 
overestimated SD-OCT RNFL measurements, especially 
in cases of greater RNFL thickness (slope = 1.181, p &lt; 
0.001, R 2 = 0.872, standard error [SE] of estimate = 6.61), 
although the measurements were highly positively corre-
lated (r = 0.934, p &lt; 0.001). Fig. 2 shows the Bland-Altman 
plots used to assess agreement of the mean RNFL mea-
surements between the two devices. Analysis of the plot 
revealed a considerable discrepancy between the RNFL 
thickness measurements obtained by the two instruments. 
The limit of agreement range (95% confidence interval [CI]) 
of the mean RNFL thickness between the two OCTs was 
27.9 μm. Additionally, a significant proportional bias of the 
mean RNFL thickness measurements existed between the 
Stratus and Cirrus devices (r = -0.233, p &lt; 0.001). For thin-
ner RNFLs, the Stratus measurements tended to be thinner 
than the Cirrus measurements, whereas for thicker RN-
FLs, Stratus measurements tended to be thicker than the 
Cirrus measurements. The mean measurement difference 
between the Stratus and Cirrus devices was -5.67 ± 7.11 μm 
(Cirrus OCT minus Stratus OCT RNFL thicknesses; 95% 
CI, -6.44 to -4.89). </p>

<p>Prediction of SD-OCT RNFL thickness from multiple 
regression models </p>

<p>Univariate analysis indicated that TD-OCT RNFL 
thickness, age, optic disc area, VF mean deviation, and VF 
pattern standard deviation were significantly associated 
with SD-OCT RNFL thickness. In contrast, the effects of 
intraocular pressure, central corneal thickness, spherical 
equivalent, axial length, and anterior chamber depth on the 
estimated SD-OCT RNFL thickness were negligible (Table 
2). Variables with a p-value less than 0.1 were included in 
the final model. Because mean deviation and pattern stan-
dard deviation were highly correlated with each other, only 
mean deviation was included in the multivariate stepwise 
regression analyses. 
Table 3 shows the results of the multivariate stepwise 
regression analyses used for the prediction of SD-OCT 
RNFL thickness. The multiple linear regression analysis 
generated the following prediction equation: SD-OCT 
RNFL thickness = 0.746 × TD-OCT RNFL thickness 
+ 17.104. The R 2 value indicates that the model explains 
87.9% of the variability between the TD-OCT and SD-
OCT RNFL thicknesses (residual variance = 5.125). TD-
OCT RNFL thickness was the only significant factor in 
the final model, which did not change based on inclusion 
of various variable combination sets. The R 2 of the final 
equation was similar to that of an equation which did not 
consider any demographic or clinical variables (equation 1). 
Other equations for estimating SD-RNFL thickness also 
exhibited reasonable R 2 and minimal bias. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Relationship between thicknesses of spectral domain 
(SD)-optical coherence tomography (OCT) retinal nerve fiber 
layer (RNFL) and time domain (TD)-OCT RNFL (slope = 1.181, 
p &lt; 0.001; intercept = -9.497; adjusted determination coefficient = 
0.872; standard error of estimate = 6.61). </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>40 
50 </p>

<p>SD-OCT RNFL thickness ((m) </p>

<p>TD-OCT RNFL thickness ((m) </p>

<p>60 
70 
80 
90 
100 
110 
120 
130 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>110 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>130 </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Bland-Altman plot comparing the mean retinal nerve fiber 
layer (RNFL) thickness measurements obtained with spectral 
domain (SD)-optical coherence tomography (OCT) and time 
domain (TD)-OCT. The difference between both measurements 
is plotted against the average of both measurements (slope = 
-0.233, p &lt; 0.001). Mean difference ± standard deviation: SD-
OCT minus TD-OCT, -5.67 ± 7.11 μm; 95% confidence interval, 
-6.44 to -4.89; limits of agreement, -19.6 to 8.3 μm. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-5 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>-15 </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>-25 </p>

<p>40 
50 
60 
70 
80 
90 
100 
110 
120 
130 </p>

<p>+1.96 SD </p>

<p>8.3 </p>

<p>Mean </p>

<p>-5.7 </p>

<p>-1.96 SD </p>

<p>-19.6 </p>

<p>140 
Difference in RNFL thickness ((m) 
(SD-OCT minus TD-OCT) </p>

<p>Average of SD-OCT and TD-OCT RNFL thickness ((m) </p>



<p>KH Lee, et al. Predicting OCT RNFL Measurements </p>

<p>Relationship between predicted SD-OCT RNFL thick-
ness and measured thickness </p>

<p>Table 4 shows the categorical comparison of the absolute 
difference between the TD-OCT and SD-OCT measure-
ments or between the observed and predicted SD-OCT 
RNFL thicknesses. For RNFLs of average thickness, 
the difference between the SD-OCT and TD-OCT mea-
surements was within 10 μm in 152 (69.1%) patients and 
within 5 μm in 81 (36.8%) patients. SD-OCT and TD-OCT </p>

<p>measurements differed by more than 15 μm in 23 (10.5%) 
patients. Comparing the observed and calculated SD-
OCT RNFL measurements using our formula revealed no 
measurements differences greater than 15 μm. A predicted 
average RNFL thickness within 10 μm of the observed 
measurement was detected in 210 (95.5%) eyes and that 
within 5 μm of the observed measurement was detected in 
121 (55.0%) eyes. 
Fig. 3 shows a scatter plot of the measured versus pre-
dicted SD-OCT RNFL thickness values as determined by </p>

<p>Table 2. Predictors of SD-OCT RNFL thickness (univariate linear regression analysis, n = 220) </p>

<p>Mean RNFL thickness by SD-OCT </p>

<p>Regression coefficient 
F 
p-value 
95% CI </p>

<p>Mean RNFL thickness by TD-OCT 
0.747 
1582.453 * 
&lt;0.001 * 
0.710 to 0.784 
Age 
-0.151 
6.052 * 
0.015 * 
-0.272 to -0.030 
Female gender 
0.738 
0.137 
0.711 
-3.189 to 4.665 
Intraocular pressure 
0.232 
0.525 
0.469 
-0.399 to 0.864 
Central corneal thickness 
0.048 
2.405 
0.123 
-0.013 to 0.108 
Spherical equivalent 
0.259 
0.397 
0.530 
-0.553 to 1.070 
Axial length 
-0.097 
0.020 
0.889 
-1.465 to 1.271 
Anterior chamber depth 
0.950 
0.183 
0.670 
-3.437 to 5.337 
Optic disc area 
5.524 
10.192 * 
0.002 * 
2.114 to 8.934 
Mean deviation 
1.437 
101.684 * 
&lt;0.001 * 
1.156 to 1.718 
Pattern standard deviation 
-2.317 
100.394 * 
&lt;0.001 * 
-2.773 to -1.861 
SD = spectral domain; OCT = optical coherence tomography; RNFL = retinal nerve fiber layer; CI = confidence interval; TD = time do-
main. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Statistically significant values. </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparison of equations that predict SD-OCT RNFL thickness (multiple linear regression, n = 220) </p>

<p>Included Variables 
Regression Formula 
Adjusted 
R 2 
Residual 
variance </p>

<p>Mean bias ± 
standard deviation (μm) 
(observed minus measured) 
Final 
equation 
TD-OCT RNFL, 
MD, disc area, age 
0.746 × TD-OCT RNFL + 17.104 0.879 
5.125 
-0.04 ± 5.22 </p>

<p>Equation 1 TD-OCT RNFL 
0.747 × TD-OCT RNFL + 17.068 0.878 
5.130 
-0.09 ± 5.22 
Equation 2 TD-OCT RNFL, MD 
0.746 × TD-OCT RNFL + 17.169 0.878 
5.121 
-0.10 ± 5.22 
Equation 3 TD-OCT RNFL, MD, 
disc area 
0.746 × TD-OCT RNFL + 17.104 0.879 
5.125 
-0.04 ± 5.22 </p>

<p>SD = spectral domain; OCT = optical coherence tomography; RNFL = retinal nerve fiber layer; R 2 = determination coefficient; TD = time 
domain; MD = mean deviation. </p>

<p>Table 4. Categorical comparison of difference between absolute measurements (Fisher's exact test, n = 220) </p>

<p>Absolute measurement difference (μm) </p>

<p>No. of eyes (%) 
p-value 
Difference between SD-OCT and 
TD-OCT RNFL thickness 
Difference between observed and 
predicted SD-OCT RNFL thickness </p>

<p>&gt;20 
1 (0.5) 
0 (0) 
&lt;0.001 
15 to 20 
22 (10.0) 
0 (0) 
10 to 15 
45 (20.5) 
10 (4.5) 
5 to 10 
71 (32.3) 
89 (40.5) 
&lt;5 
81 (36.8) 
121 (55.0) 
SD = spectral domain; OCT = optical coherence tomography; TD = time domain; RNFL = retinal nerve fiber layer. </p>



<p>Korean J Ophthalmol Vol.26, No.5, 2012 </p>

<p>our regression model. As expected, the RNFL thickness 
measurements predicted with our formula systematically 
deviated only minimally from the measured SD-OCT 
RNFL thickness (slope = 0.881, p &lt; 0.001, R 2 = 0.872, SE of 
estimate = 4.93). 
A Bland-Altman plot showing the agreement in SD-
OCT RNFL thickness between observed and predicted 
measurements is shown in Fig. 4. This analysis demon-
strated good agreement between measured and predicted 
SD-OCT RNFL thicknesses. Estimated RNFL thicknesses 
calculated by our equation showed minimal bias compared 
to the observed RNFL thicknesses (mean measurement 
difference, -0.04 ± 5.22 μm; measured minus predicted 
RNFL thicknesses; 95% CI, -0.61 to 0.53). The slope of the 
regression line of the difference between the measured and 
predicted values compared to the average of the two was 
slightly positive and statistically significant, indicating the 
existence of proportional bias (r = 0.060, p = 0.004). The 
plots demonstrate a wide range of agreement between ob-
served and predicted RNFL thickness measurements (limit 
of agreement width, 20.5 μm). </p>

<p>Verification of the prediction model </p>

<p>The validation dataset confirmed that SD-OCT RNFL 
thickness was directly correlated with the TD-OCT RNFL 
thickness. The multiple regression model explained 85.6% 
of the variance of the SD-OCT RNFL thicknesses in the </p>

<p>validation sample (residual variance = 5.481). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Detecting disease progression in patients with glaucoma 
is essential for patient monitoring and to evaluate the ef-
ficacy of therapy. The present study provides an equation 
that can predict SD-OCT RNFL measurements using 
conventional TD-OCT RNFL measurements. Other for-
mulas have been proposed to calculate SD-OCT RNFL 
thicknesses [8,15], but none have adjusted for demographic 
and clinical variables. To improve the predictive accuracy 
of our equation, clinical and demographic variables were 
included in addition to the TD-OCT RNFL measure-
ments. Univariate analysis showed that factors associated 
with greater SD-OCT RNFL thickness included greater 
TD-OCT RNFL thickness, younger age, larger disc area, 
higher mean deviation, and lower pattern standard devia-
tion. Stepwise multiple regression analysis was then used 
to determine the best combination set of variables to pre-
dict SD-OCT RNFL thickness. The results of the analysis 
indicated that the best and final equation included only 
TD-OCT RNFL thickness. </p>

<p>Discrepancies between TD-OCT and SD-OCT mea-
surements </p>

<p>OCT measurements are not interchangeable and should 
be interpreted considering the various scanning protocols 
and segmentation algorithms of different devices [9,10]. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Relationship between observed and predicted spectral 
domain (SD)-optical coherence tomography (OCT) retinal nerve 
fiber layer (RNFL) thickness (slope = 0.881, p &lt; 0.001; intercept = 
10.019; adjusted determination coefficient = 0.872; standard error 
of estimate = 4.93). </p>

<p>130 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>110 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>40 
50 </p>

<p>Observed SD-OCT RNFL thickness ((m) </p>

<p>Predicted SD-OCT RNFL thickness ((m) </p>

<p>60 
70 
80 
90 
100 
110 
120 
130 </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Bland-Altman plot showing observed versus predicted 
spectral domain (SD)-optical coherence tomography (OCT) 
retinal nerve fiber layer (RNFL) thickness. The difference 
between both measurements is plotted against the average of 
both measurements (slope = 0.060, p = 0.004). Mean difference ± 
standard deviation: observed minus predicted, -0.04 ± 5.22 μm; 
95% confidence interval, -0.61 to 0.53; limits of agreement, -10.3 
to 10.2 μm). </p>

<p>+1.96 SD </p>

<p>10.2 </p>

<p>Mean </p>

<p>-0.0 </p>

<p>-1.96 SD </p>

<p>-10.3 
Difference in RNFL thickness ((m) 
(observed minus predicted) </p>

<p>Average of observed and predicted SD-OCT RNFL thickness ((m) </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-5 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>-15 </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>-25 </p>

<p>40 
50 
60 
70 
80 
90 
100 
110 
120 
130 
140 </p>



<p>KH Lee, et al. Predicting OCT RNFL Measurements </p>

<p>The reason underlying this difference in OCT techniques 
may be that new OCT systems involve improved axial 
resolution compared to the previous generation [20]. By 
producing higher resolution scans compared to TD-OCT, 
SD-OCT may provide measurements that reflect a more 
accurate delineation of RNFL margins [11]. Alternatively, 
the discrepancy in measurements may be related to in-
trinsic differences between the instruments and software 
edge-detection algorithms that measure the RNFL [11,14]. 
The segmentation algorithms for TD-OCT and SD-OCT 
are different: Cirrus identifies the bottom of the nerve fi-
ber layer, whereas Stratus localizes the top of the ganglion 
cell layer [8]. Another reason for the differences may be 
because the scan registration process performed by the 
Cirrus algorithms is fully automated, which reduces the 
likelihood of operator error [10,11,14,20,21]. 
Bland-Altman plots showed that, for thinner RNFLs, the 
Stratus measurement values tended to be smaller compared 
to values determined by Cirrus. In cases of great RNFL 
thicknesses, Stratus measurements tended to be thicker 
than measurements determined by Cirrus. These results 
are generally consistent with earlier studies reporting dif-
ferences in the measurement values between 3D OCT-1000 
(Topcon Inc., Paramus, NJ, USA) and Stratus OCT [12], 
RTVue-100 (Optovue Inc., Fremont, CA, USA) and Stra-
tus OCT [13], and Cirrus OCT and Stratus OCT [8-11,21]. 
A possible explanation why Cirrus OCT yields thicker 
measurements in severely diseased eyes and thinner mea-
surements in healthy eyes compared to Stratus OCT is the 
difference in the inclusion of exposed blood vessels in the 
measurements [8]. In cases of thin RNFLs, the TD-OCT 
algorithm is not sufficiently sensitive to local changes and 
includes few of the blood vessels in regions where most of 
the axons are lost, while the SD-OCT algorithm incorpo-
rates most of the blood vessels when determining RNFL 
thickness. In contrast, the SD-OCT algorithm is sensitive 
to local signal changes and thus does not include the shad-
ows of the blood vessels present in thick RNFLs, whereas 
TD-OCT does include shadows from major blood vessels 
[12]. </p>

<p>Consideration of covariates in predicting SD-OCT 
RNFL thickness </p>

<p>In the present study, the authors attempted to develop a 
valuable prediction model for RNFL measurements using 
a new imaging device considering both clinical and demo-
graphic variables. Multivariate analysis results indicated 
that no factors were useful as covariates for constructing 
a predictive formula for SD-OCT RNFL thickness. The 
results showed that a formula considering clinical and de-
mographic variables was not able to more precisely predict 
SD-OCT RNFL thickness than a simple formula. A pos-
sible explanation is that the relationship between clinical/ </p>

<p>demographic variables and TD-OCT RNFL measurements 
is very similar to the relationship between these variables 
and SD-OCT RNFL measurements. RNFL thickness 
as measured by TD-OCT was associated with age ( p = 
0.002), disc area ( p = 0.004), mean deviation ( p &lt; 0.001), 
pattern standard deviation ( p &lt; 0.001), and signal strength 
( p &lt; 0.001). Consistent with TD-OCT, RNFL thickness as 
measured by SD-OCT was associated with age (p = 0.015), 
optic disc area ( p = 0.002), mean deviation ( p &lt; 0.001), pat-
tern standard deviation ( p &lt; 0.001), and signal strength ( p 
= 0.010). </p>

<p>Remaining unpredictability </p>

<p>In the present study, RNFL values estimated using our 
formula derived from TD-OCT RNFL measurements 
were consistent with the observed SD-OCT RNFL mea-
surements, and the average bias (-0.04 ± 5.22, observed 
minus estimated) and proportional bias (slope = 0.060, p 
&lt; 0.001) were quite small. However, the limit of agree-
ment range (average bias ± 1.96 standard deviation of the 
difference) was relatively broad (-10.3 to 10.2 μm). The 
limits of axial resolution for the Stratus OCT and Cirrus 
OCT instruments is taken as 10 μm and 5 μm, respectively 
[20,22]. The 95% limit of agreement between the observed 
and predicted values was 20.5 μm and was greater than the 
limit of resolution of both the Stratus OCT and the Cirrus 
OCT. 
Measurement variations may have contributed to the 
large range of the agreement limit in the current study. The 
clinical utility of any instrument depends on the reproduc-
ibility of its measurements. With SD technology, the image 
acquisition time and resolution are improved compared 
with those of the TD-OCT technique. The reproducibility 
of RNFL measurements with the SD-OCT was reported to 
be higher than that with the TD-OCT both in normal par-
ticipants and in patients with glaucoma [23,24]. However, 
our formula calculated SD-OCT RNFL thickness from 
TD-OCT RNFL values. Therefore, predicted SD-OCT 
RNFL measurements have greater test-retest variability 
than those expected with actual SD-OCT scanning. </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>The present study has several limitations. The study 
included a small number of participants, and the valida-
tion sample was drawn from the same population as the 
training sample. Thus, the performance of the equation in 
populations with different distributions of patient charac-
teristics may not be the same as the performance observed 
in the validation sample. Signal strength was not consid-
ered in the present study. Because signal strength has been 
shown to affect RNFL thickness measurements using TD-
OCT [25], the differences in signal strength between the </p>



<p>Korean J Ophthalmol Vol.26, No.5, 2012 </p>

<p>two instruments may be a possible cause of variability 
[11,26]. However, only scans with adequate signal strength 
were included in the present study, and no differences in 
signal strength were observed between scans taken with 
the two devices (paired t-test, p = 0.437). Lastly, caution 
should be taken in direct application of this formula in ev-
eryday clinical practice. Although this formula has a defi-
nite practical advantage in SD-OCT RNFL prediction, the 
limit of agreement widths between observed and predicted 
SD-OCT RNFL thicknesses were high, and the difference 
between measurements was greater than 5 μm in 45% of 
the patients. A comprehensive general assessment is re-
quired to interpret the predicted values. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>In the present study, equations were developed to pre-
dict SD-OCT RNFL thickness using multiple regression 
applied to a randomly-selected training sample of 220 pa-
tients and validated in 105 patients in the study cohort. The 
findings indicate that the application of this formula yields 
an accurate SD-OCT RNFL thickness predicted from TD-
OCT RNFL thickness in healthy participants and patients 
with glaucoma. The inclusion of other clinical and demo-
graphic factors to correct TD-OCT RNFL thickness did 
not improve the prediction accuracy in this study group. 
Validation with a larger cohort and broader distribution of 
other possible confounding variables is warranted. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article 
was reported. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant of the Korea Health 
technology R&amp;D Project, Ministry of Health &amp; Welfare, 
Republic of Korea (A101727, CYK and A110395, NRK). </p>





<p>KH Lee, et al. Predicting OCT RNFL Measurements </p>



</text></tei>