<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3619103" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Objective: This study aimed to explore clinical and virological characteristics of chronic hepatitis 
B (CHB) patients with hepatic steatosis in order to provide a theoretical basis for the prevention 
and control of hepatic steatosis. 
Methods: A total of 360 CHB inpatients were recruited from Affiliated Dongnan Hospital of 
Xiamen University and divided into hepatic steatosis group and non-hepatic steatosis group. The 
body mass index (BMI), waist-to-hip ratio (WHR), fasting blood glucose (FBG), triglyceride (TG), 
total cholesterol (TC), aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), gamma-glutamyl 
transpeptidase (GGT), hepatitis B e antigen (HBeAg), hepatitis B virus DNA (HBV DNA) and 
hepatic histological changes were detected and compared between the two groups. The associa-
tion of these factors with hepatic steatosis was evaluated in CHB patients. 
Results: BMI, FPG, TG, TC, GGT, AST and HBV DNA showed statistically significant differences 
between two groups (P&lt;0.01). The patients with hepatic steatosis had markedly higher BMI, FBG, 
TG and TC than those without steatosis did. No significant differences were found in ALT and 
HBeAg between two groups (P&gt;0.05). In male patients, there was marked difference in the WHR 
between two groups (P &lt; 0.01), which was not found in female patients (P &gt; 0.05). The severity of 
hepatic steatosis increased in patients with hepatic steatosis, compared to those without steatosis 
(P &lt; 0. 01), but the severities of inflammation and fibrosis in the non-hepatic steatosis group were 
dramatically higher than those in the hepatic steatosis group (P &lt; 0. 01). 
Conclusions: BMI, WHR, FBG, TG and TC appeared to be influencing factors of CHB combined 
with hepatic steatosis. Hepatic steatosis in CHB patients was closely related to changes in an-
thropometric indices and metabolic factors but not HBV. It is necessary to improve these factors 
to effectively prevent hepatic steatosis in CHB patients. </p>

<p>The incidences of hyperlipidemia, obesity and 
diabetes mellitus increase significantly over years due 
to change in lifestyle, high-fat and high-sugar diet and 
lack of physical exercise. Correspondingly, the prev-
alence of hepatic steatosis is on the rise, being the se-
cond commonest liver disease in developed countries. 
Hepatic steatosis is associated with hyperlipidemia, 
hypertension, type 2 diabetes mellitus, car-</p>

<p>dio-cerebrovascular diseases and some malignant 
tumors [1]. At the moment, hepatic steatosis ranks 
among the second commonest liver disease around 
the world secondary only to viral hepatitis, which 
imposes a large burden on human health. It is well 
known that hepatic steatosis plays an important role 
in hepatic inflammatory necrosis and fibrosis devel-
opment in patients with chronic hepatitis C (CHC), </p>

<p>Ivyspring </p>

<p>International Publisher </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2013, Vol. 10 </p>



<p>and both the metabolic status and hepatitis C virus 
(HCV) are involved in the pathogenesis of hepatic 
steatosis [4]. Hepatic steatosis is frequently found in 
chronic hepatitis B (CHB) [5], a common epidemic 
disease in China. However, factors affecting the de-
velopment of hepatic steatosis in CHB patients remain 
obscure despite coexisting of CHB and hepatic stea-
tosis is frequently observed in clinical practice [6]. 
This study compared the clinical features among CHB 
patients with and without hepatic steatosis, so as to 
explore the factors affecting the development of he-
patic steatosis in CHB patients and to provide evi-
dence for clinical prevention and treatment of these 
conditions. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>A total of 291 CHB inpatients were recruited 
from the Affiliated Dongnan Hospital of Xiamen 
University between January 2008 and June 2011. CHB 
was diagnosed on the basis of clinical presentations 
and pathological features according to the "Guide-
lines for Prevention and Treatment of Chronic Hepa-
titis B (2010 version)" [7]. Infection of hepatitis A virus 
(HAV), HCV, hepatitis D virus (HDV) and hepatitis E 
virus (HEV), drug-induced hepatitis, alcoholic hepa-
titis and autoimmune hepatitis were ruled out before 
study. These patients were divided into two groups 
according to the presence of hepatic steatosis. Among 
all participants, 132 were diagnosed with hepatic ste-
atosis (120 men and 12 women, age: 10-63 years [37.05 
± 9.55 years]) and hepatic steatosis was not observed 
in remaining 159 patients (138 men and 21 women, 
age: 19-65 years, [40.38 ± 16.61 years]). This study was 
approved by the Clinical Ethics Committee of Affili-
ated Dongnan Hospital of Xiamen University, and 
informed consent was obtained from all patients be-
fore study. </p>

<p>Anthropometry </p>

<p>The height, weight, waist and hip circumference 
were measured in all patients. Waist circumference 
was measured using a steel measuring tape, with 
measurements made halfway between the lower 
border of the ribs and the anterior superior iliac spine 
in a horizontal plane. Hip circumference was meas-
ured at the level of the greater femoral trochanter. All 
the subjects were clothed as lightly as possible, bare-
footed in a standing position, and examined by two 
well-trained physicians. Body mass index (BMI) and 
waist-to-hip ratio (WHR) were calculated with fol-
lowing equations: BMI = weight (kg)/height 2 (m 2 ); 
WHR = waist circumference (cm)/hip circumference </p>

<p>(cm). </p>

<p>Serum assays </p>

<p>Subjects were fasted for 12 h and 5 ml of venous 
blood was collected in the morning. The levels of 
glucose (FBG), triglyceride (TG), total cholesterol 
(TC), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine ami-
notransferase (ALT) and γ-glutamyltransferase (GGT) 
were determined. </p>

<p>Serum markers of HBV </p>

<p>HBV markers were measured by enzyme-linked 
immunosorbent assay (ELISA) with a commercial-
ly-available kit (Livzon Group Reagent Factory, 
Guangdong, China) according to the manufacturer's 
instructions. </p>

<p>Detection of HBV DNA </p>

<p>HBV DNA level was determined by quantitative 
real-time fluorescence polymerase chain reaction 
(qPCR) using a AG-9600 Thermal Station and a 
AG-9600 Amplisensor Minilyzer (Biotronic, USA). 
The fluorescent reagent and the standard HBV DNA 
were provided by the same company. Asymmetric 
primer 1 was 5′-TGTCTCGTGTTACAGGCGGGGT-3', 
asymmetric primer 2 was 5′-GAGGCATAGCAGC 
AGGAGAAGAG-3', and fluorescent primer was 
5′-TCGCTGGAAGTGTCTGCGGCGT-3'. One copy 
was defined as 3.2 kb HBV DNA in 1 ml of serum, and 
data were expressed as N = 10 × copies/ml. </p>

<p>Diagnostic criteria </p>

<p>According to the BMI criteria for Asians devel-
oped by the Regional Office for the Western Pacific 
Region of World Health Organization (WHO) (2000) 
[8], normal weight, overweight and obesity were de-
fined as BMI= 18.5-23.0 kg/m 2 , 23.0-25.0 kg/m 2 and ≥ 
25.0 kg/m 2 , respectively. Central obesity was deter-
mined by WHR ≥ 0.9 (male) or ≥ 0.8 (female). Hyper-
glycemia was diagnosed when the FBG was ≥ 5.6 
mmol/L according to the diagnostic criteria of diabe-
tes mellitus by WHO (1999) [9] and the recommended 
criteria of diabetes mellitus by American Diabetes 
Association (ADA) (2003) [10]. Hypertriglyceridemia 
and hypercholesterolemia were diagnosed when TG 
was ≥ 1.7 mmol/L and TC was ≥ 5.2 mmol/L, respec-
tively, according to the Guidelines on Prevention and 
Treatment of Blood Lipid Abnormality in Chinese 
Adults [11]. HBV DNA of ≥ 10 3 copies/ml was con-
sidered positive for virus replication. Hepatic steato-
sis was graded as: F0 (no significant lipid droplets in 
hepatocytes), F1 (&lt; 30% hepatocytes with microvesic-
ular steatosis), F2 (30~50% hepatocytes involved), F3 
(50~75% hepatocytes involved) and F4 (&gt;75% 
hepatocytes involved) [12]. </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2013, Vol. 10 </p>



<p>Hepatic histology </p>

<p>Liver biopsy was performed to obtain the spec-
imens under the ultrasound guidance within 1 week 
after admission, using a needle by which a negative 
pressure (suction) was applied. Each specimen was 
longer than 2 cm and had more than 10 portal areas. 
Specimens were immediately fixed in 4% formalde-
hyde, dehydrated, embedded, sliced, and examined 
after hematoxylin-eosin staining, Masson's trichrome 
staining and reticular fiber staining. All the sections 
were blindly and independently assessed by 2 expe-
rienced pathologists [13]. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>A case-control study was conducted. Variables 
with normal distribution were compared using rank 
sum test. Quantitative data were expressed as means 
± standard deviation (SD). Where appropriate, com-
parisons were performed using a paired t test or a 
Mann-Whitney U test. Qualitative data were pre-
sented as rate and compared with Chi-square test. A 
value of P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically signifi-
cant. Statistical analysis was done with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 13.0</rs> for Windows. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Comparison of genders, ages and anthropo-
metric indices </p>

<p>There were no significant differences in gender 
or age between two groups (P &gt; 0.05). The CHB pa-
tients with hepatic steatosis had significantly higher 
BMI (26.89 ± 2.78 kg/m 2 ) than those without steatosis 
did (21.17 ± 2.96 kg/m 2 ) (Figure 1; P &lt; 0.01). The WHR 
of male patients with steatosis (0.93 ± 0.05) was 
markedly higher than those without steatosis did 
(0.87 ± 0.06) (P &lt; 0.01). However, the WHR of female 
patients was comparable between two groups (P &gt; 
0.05) (Table 1). </p>

<p>Figure 1. BMI of CHB patients with and without hepatic steatosis </p>

<p>Table 1. Gender, age and anthropometric indices of CHB 
patients with and without hepatic steatosis. </p>

<p>Hepatic steatosis 
group 
Non-hepatic steato-
sis group 
P </p>

<p>Number 
132 
159 
-
Gender 
0.270 </p>

<p>Male (n, %) 
120 (90.91%) 
138 (86.79%) </p>

<p>Female (n, %) 
12 (9.09%) 
21 (13.21%) </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
37.05±9.55 
40.38±16.61 
0.220 </p>

<p>BMI (kg/m 2 ) 
26.89±2.78 
21.17±2.96 
0.000 </p>

<p>WHR </p>

<p>Male 
0.93±0.05 
0.87±0.06 
0.000 </p>

<p>Female 
0.88±0.06 
0.87±0.06 
0.711 </p>

<p>Serum biochemical parameters </p>

<p>CHB patients with steatosis had significantly 
higher levels of FBG, TG and TC than those without 
steatosis did (P &lt; 0.01) (Figure 2). On the other hand, 
GGT and AST were markedly higher in patients 
without steatosis than in those with steatosis (P &lt; 
0.01). There was no significant difference in ALT be-
tween two groups (P &gt; 0.05) (Table 2). </p>

<p>Figure 2. FBG, TG and TC of CHB patients with and without 
hepatic steatosis </p>

<p>Table 2. Serum biochemical parameters of CHB patients 
with and without hepatic steatosis. </p>

<p>Hepatic steatosis 
group 
Non-hepatic 
steatosis group 
P </p>

<p>FBG (mmol/L) 
5.11±0.62 
4.94±1.89 
0.000 </p>

<p>TG (mmol/L) 
1.81±0.89 
1.21±0.79 
0.000 </p>

<p>TC (mmol/L) 
5.29±1.05 
4.25±1.58 
0.000 </p>

<p>GGT (IU/L) 
65.04±53.89 
146.48±200.39 
0.009 </p>

<p>AST (IU/L) 
65.60±71.52 
165.35±180.57 
0.003 </p>

<p>ALT (IU/L) 
135.39±151.99 
273.99±336. 88 
0.385 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2013, Vol. 10 </p>



<p>Virological parameters </p>

<p>There was no significant difference in positive 
rate of HBeAg between two groups (P &gt; 0.05), while 
the positive rate of HBV DNA in non-hepatic steatosis 
group was significantly higher (P &lt; 0.01). The positive 
rates of HBeAg and HBV DNA in patients with stea-
tosis were 43.18% and 70.45%, respectively, while they 
were 49.06% and 84.91%, respectively, in patients 
without steatosis (Table 3). </p>

<p>Table 3. Virological parameters of CHB patients with and 
without hepatic steatosis. </p>

<p>Hepatic steatosis 
group (N=132) 
Non-hepatic steatosis 
group (N=159) 
P </p>

<p>HBeAg 
0.317 </p>

<p>+ 
57 (43.18%) 
78 (49.06%) </p>

<p>-
75 (56.82%) 
81 (50.94%) </p>

<p>HBV 
DNA 
0.003 </p>

<p>+ 
93 (70.45%) 
135 (84.91%) </p>

<p>-
39 (29.55%) 
24 (15.09%) </p>

<p>Pathological findings </p>

<p>Patients with hepatic steatosis had more severe 
fatty degeneration than those without hepatic steato-
sis did (P &lt; 0. 01). However, the prevalence of hepatic 
inflammation and fibrosis were markedly higher in 
patients without steatosis when compared with those 
with steatosis (P &lt; 0. 01). Histological features of CHB 
patients with and without hepatic steatosis are sum-
marized in Table 4. </p>

<p>Table 4. Histological features of CHB patients with and 
without hepatic steatosis. </p>

<p>Hepatic steatosis 
group (N=132) 
Non-hepatic steatosis 
group (N=159) 
P </p>

<p>Steatosis 
0.000 
F0 
0 
159 
F1 
36 
0 
F2 
48 
0 
F3 
43 
0 
F4 
5 
0 
Inflammation activity 
0.000 
G0 
78 
0 
G1 
29 
18 
G2 
25 
98 
G3 
0 
43 
Fibrosis stage 
0.000 
S1 
118 
35 
S2 
13 
97 
S3 
0 
22 
S4 
1 
5 </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The incidence of CHB is decreasing as a result of 
effective implementation of hepatitis B vaccination, 
and the proportion of HBV carriers also significantly 
declines due to proper use of antiviral agents [14]. The 
prevalence of HBsAg positive patients in China also 
decreases, although it is still as high as 7.18% [7]. In 
clinical practice, hepatic steatosis is frequently found 
in CHB patients [6] with a reported incidence of 
18%-27% [15, 16]. With the improvement of living 
standard and change in lifestyle in recent years, the 
distributions of BMI, WHR and WC also significantly 
alter. The BMI, WHR and WC are continuously in-
creasing in both developed and developing countries. 
The numbers of overweight and obese subjects are 
14.6 billion and 500 million, respectively, around the 
world [17]. The prevalence of hepatic steatosis in CHB 
patients tends to increase over years, and patients 
with these conditions may develop cirrhosis or even 
hepatocarcinoma [2]. Hepatic steatosis can be induced 
by excessive alcohol intake, drug abuse, nutrition 
imbalance and metabolic diseases and is generally 
associated with hyperlipidemia, hypertension, type 2 
diabetes mellitus, cardio-cerebrovascular diseases and 
some malignant tumors, exerting important impacts 
on human health [18]. CHB patients usually have 
different lifestyles and diet habits from healthy people 
because of lack of exercise and improvement in appe-
tite during recovery period. Therefore, to determine 
factors influencing the development of hepatic stea-
tosis in CHB patients may help us in the prevention 
and treatment of these conditions. It is also crucial for 
screening and confirming these influencing factors of 
these diseases so that we can timely prevent and early 
diagnose steatosis in CHB patients. 
This was a case-control study on CHB patients 
with and without hepatic steatosis which was con-
firmed by clinical and pathological features. There 
were no significant differences in gender and age 
between two groups. Our results showed that the BMI 
of steatosis patients was significantly higher than that 
of non-steatosis patients. The mean WHR of male pa-
tients differed between two group, which was not 
observed in female patients, probably because of dif-
ferent distribution patterns of body fat between males 
and females [19]. It is well known that WHR is one of 
most important anthropometric indices that can pre-
dict the occurrence of simple fatty liver [20]. The pre-
sent study showed that CHB patients with steatosis 
had higher BMI and WHR than those without steato-
sis did. CHB patients are more likely to develop he-
patic steatosis as their BMI and WHR increase, sug-
gesting that increased BMI and WHR may promote </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2013, Vol. 10 </p>



<p>hepatic fat deposition in CHB patients. Thus, to con-
trol the increases in BMI and WHR is an effective way 
to prevent hepatic steatosis in CHB patients. Moreo-
ver, steatosis patients had higher levels of FBG, TG 
and TC than non-steatosis patients, indicating that 
inflammation in the liver is related to disordered me-
tabolism of blood glucose and lipid (especially hy-
pertriglyceridemia). It is important to closely monitor 
the BMI, WHR, blood glucose and lipid and to treat 
hypertriglyceridemia in CHB patients which may 
prevent the occurrence of hepatic steatosis. In addi-
tion, the levels of ALT, AST and GGT were signifi-
cantly higher in steatosis patients than in 
non-steatosis patients. It is possible that CHB patients 
with hepatic steatosis develop metabolic disorders, 
according to the increased BMI and WHR. The meta-
bolic disorders may interact with CHB, further caus-
ing damage to liver function [22]. Our results indi-
cated that, in order to prevent hepatic steatosis in 
CHB patients, it is beneficial to periodically monitor 
BMI and WHR, to properly control the blood glucose 
and lipid, as well as to educate these patients about 
healthy lifestyle, scientific dieting and physical exer-
cise. 
A large body of evidence has demonstrated that 
HCV combined with hepatic steatosis is associated 
with type 3 HCV gene, which accounts for 80% of all 
HCV infections [4]. The mechanism of type 3 HCV 
infection lies in that the core protein of HCV inhibits 
the activity of microsomal triglyceride transfer protein 
and interferes with the assembly and secretion of very 
low density lipoprotein [21]. In the present study, the 
positive rates of HBeAg and HBV DNA were com-
pared between patients with and without steatosis, 
and results showed that there was no significant dif-
ference in the positive rate of HBeAg between two 
groups, while the positive rate of HBV DNA was sig-
nificantly different. These results suggest that liver 
injury in CHB patients without hepatic steatosis is 
related to HBV. The positive rate of HBV DNA in pa-
tients with steatosis was lower than that in patients 
without steatosis, which means that HBV is not di-
rectly related to the hepatic steatosis in CHB patients. 
It was reported that the HBV DNA load was signifi-
cantly lower in CHB patients with hepatic steatosis 
than in those without hepatic steatosis and that he-
patic steatosis in CHB patients was not related to HBV 
infection [23]. Previous clinical studies revealed that 
both CHB patients with hepatic steatosis and hepatic 
steatosis patients had hyperlipidemia and obesity, 
suggesting that the occurrence and development of 
hepatic steatosis in CHB patients are closely associ-
ated with metabolic factors [24], which is consistent 
with our results. </p>

<p>Pathological examination in the present study 
showed that the prevalence of hepatic inflammation 
and fibrosis was significantly higher in patients 
without steatosis, suggesting that, when HBV infec-
tion and hepatic steatosis coexist, hepatic steatosis 
may not affect the severity of hepatic inflammation 
and fibrosis of patients with HBV infection, but these 
results remain to be confirmed in epidemiologic 
studies and clinical cohort studies. 
Early diagnosis of hepatic steatosis in CHB pa-
tients seems to be difficult. The pathological features 
are the golden standard for the diagnosis of hepatic 
steatosis in CHB patients, but it is impossible for wide 
application in clinical practice. In addition, the non-
invasive method of fibroscan for diagnosis of hepatic 
steatosis is currently in the exploratory stage [25, 26]. 
Our findings showed that anthropometric indices and 
metabolic factors were related to hepatic steatosis in 
CHB patients, and BMI, WHR, FBG, TG and TC, but 
not HBV, were influencing factors of steatosis. 
Therefore, to monitor anthropometric indices (espe-
cially BMI and WHR) and to measure biochemical 
parameters (such as FBG, TG and TC) are helpful for 
early diagnosis of hepatic steatosis, evaluation of an-
tiviral treatment and improvement of prognosis in 
CHB patients. There are some limitations in this 
study, such as lack of evaluation of antiviral treat-
ment. It remains controversial whether hepatic stea-
tosis influences the efficacy of antiviral therapy. Clin-
ical investigations showed that treatment with poly-
ethylene glycol interferon in CHB patients with he-
patic steatosis for 48 weeks had no influence on the 
virological response but altered the biochemical re-
sponse [27]. However, another study showed that 
hepatic steatosis was significantly associated with 
Entecavir treatment failure [28]. Thus, the antiviral 
treatment in CHB patient with hepatic steatosis needs 
to be further assessed to determine whether the he-
patic steatosis affects the efficacy of antiviral treat-
ment. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>The study was supported by the Zhangzhou 
Technology Project (Z04094) and Tianqing Hepatic 
Disease Fund of Chinese Foundation of Hepatitis 
Prevention and Control (TQGB2011018). </p>

<p>Competing Interests </p>

<p>The authors have declared that no competing 
interest exists. </p>



<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2013, Vol. 10 </p>





<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>

</text></tei>