<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3600908" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>CCR9 and 47 are the major trafficking receptors for lymphocyte migration to the gut, 
and their expression is induced during lymphocyte activation under the influence of reti-
noic acid (RA). We report here that BATF (basic leucine zipper transcription factor, ATF-
like), an AP-1 protein family factor, is required for optimal expression of CCR9 and 47 
by T helper cells. BATF-deficient (knockout [KO]) mice had reduced numbers of effector T 
and regulatory T cells in the intestine. The intestinal T cells in BATF KO mice expressed 
CCR9 and 47 at abnormally low levels compared with their wild-type (WT) counterparts, 
and BATF KO CD4 + T cells failed to up-regulate the expression of CCR9 and 47 to WT 
levels in response to RA. Defective binding of RAR and histone acetylation at the regula-
tory regions of the CCR9 and Itg-4 genes were observed in BATF KO T cells. As a result, 
BATF KO effector and FoxP3 + T cells failed to populate the intestine, and neither popula-
tion functioned normally in the induction and regulation of colitis. Our results establish 
BATF as a cellular factor required for normal expression of CCR9 and 47 and for the 
homeostasis and effector functions of T cell populations in the intestine. </p>

<p>476 </p>

<p>BATF and gut-homing receptors | Wang et al. </p>

<p>for 47 were reduced in the small intestinal LP of BATF 
KO mice (Fig. 2, A and B). A considerable decrease in CCR9 
and 47 expression was also detected in CD8 + T cells in the 
small intestine but not in other organs (Fig. 2 C). </p>

<p>Naive BATF KO CD4 + T cells are ineffective 
in up-regulating CCR9 and 47 in response to RA 
Expression of CCR9 and 47 by T cells is induced by RA 
(Iwata et al., 2004). We next examined whether BATF KO 
naive T cells are defective in up­regulating trafficking recep­ 
tors in response to T cell activation in the presence of RA 
in vitro. Compared with WT CD4 + T cells, BATF KO naive 
T cells showed less up­regulation of CCR9 in response to 
RA (Fig. 3 A). Similarly, BATF KO naive T cells were unable 
to up­regulate 47 to WT levels. Similar results were ob­ 
tained with concanavalin A (Fig. 3 A) or with OVA 323-339 when 
OT­II BATF KO T cells were used (not depicted). At the 
mRNA level, expression of both CCR9 and Itg-4 in re­ 
sponse to RA was defective in BATF KO T cells (Fig. 3 B). 
However, expression of Itg-7 mRNA by BATF KO T cells 
was comparable with WT T cells. We examined other chemo­ 
kine receptors such as CCR4, CCR6, CCR7, and CXCR4 
(Fig. 3 C) and did not detect any significant differences in 
expression of these receptors between WT and BATF KO 
T cells cultured with or without RA. RA enhances the induc­ 
tion of FoxP3 + T cells by TGF1 (Kang et al., 2007; Mucida 
et al., 2007), and this response was intact in BATF KO T cells 
(Fig. 3 D). However, BATF KO T regulatory cells (iT reg cells) 
induced with RA and TGF1 were deficient in expression 
of CCR9 and 47 (Fig. 3 E). These results indicate that 
expression of gut­homing receptors in BATF KO T helper 
cells to RA is defective, whereas differentiation of T reg cells 
was normal. </p>

<p>BATF KO T cells regain the ability to express 47 
and CCR9 upon gene complementation 
It is possible that BATF KO T cells are defective in ex­ 
pression of CCR9 and 47 as the result of a block in cell 
development rather than the absence of functional BATF. 
This was addressed using retroviral gene complementation 
in BATF KO T cells. We constructed retroviral vectors 
expressing the full­length and two truncated versions of 
BATF and used these to complement the BATF deficiency 
in T cells (Fig. 4 A). Enforced BATF expression induced a 
low level of 47 but did not induce CCR9 in the absence 
of exogenous RA (Fig. 4, B and C). This modest induc­ 
tion of 47 is likely caused by residual RA that is present 
in the culture medium. BATF KO CD4 + T cells were able 
to normally express CCR9 and 47 in response to RA 
when the full­length BATF protein was expressed (Fig. 4, 
B and C). A low but detectable activity was observed for 
a BATF mutant deleted for the first exon (BATF2), and this 
was predicted because the protein retains the Jun dimeriza­ 
tion and DNA­binding domains of BATF (Fig. 4, B and C). 
In contrast, a nonfunctional BATF protein deleted for the 
first and second exons (BATF1) did not have such activities. </p>

<p>BATF (basic leucine zipper transcription factor, ATF­like) 
is a basic leucine zipper (b­Zip) transcription factor of the AP­1 
protein family (Dorsey et al., 1995). BATF is widely expressed 
in the immune system, including T and B cells. It hetero­ 
dimerizes with Jun proteins for transcriptional regulatory activity 
(Dorsey et al., 1995; Echlin et al., 2000; Williams et al., 2001). 
BATF is required for the generation of Th17 cells and T­Fh 
cells but is dispensable for development of Th1 cells and FoxP3 + 
T cells (Schraml et al., 2009; Betz et al., 2010; Ise et al., 2011). 
It has been reported that BATF can suppress Sirt1 expression 
and control the ATP level and effector function of CD8 + 
T cells (Kuroda et al., 2011). Additionally, BATF deficiency is 
associated with the loss of activation­induced cytidine deami­ 
nase (AID) expression and class switch recombination in B cells 
(Betz et al., 2010; Ise et al., 2011), and BATF recently has been 
shown to regulate a DNA damage-induced differentiation 
checkpoint important for the maintenance of hematopoietic 
stem cells (Wang et al., 2012). 
We report here that BATF is required for optimal ex­ 
pression of CCR9 and 47 by gut­homing CD4 + T cells 
in response to the RA signal. BATF KO mice are numeri­ 
cally deficient for T cells in the intestine. BATF­deficient 
effector T helper cells and FoxP3 + T cells are ineffective in 
migration into the intestine and fail to function as effector 
cells and suppressor cells, respectively. BATF is required for 
CD4 + T cells to up­regulate the gut­homing receptors in 
response to RA upon antigen priming and to migrate into 
and populate the intestine. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
T helper cells are numerically deficient 
in the intestine of BATF KO mice 
BATF KO mice generated by targeted deletion of either 
exons one and two or exon three of the Batf gene have been 
previously described to have relatively normal numbers of 
T cells in secondary lymphoid tissues (Schraml et al., 2009; 
Betz et al., 2010). When we examined the intestine by immuno­ 
histochemistry, CD4 + T cells were numerically deficient in 
the LP compartment of the small intestinal villi (Fig. 1 A). 
CD8 + T cells were present but also decreased in numbers in 
the small intestinal villi of the BATF KO mice. Flow cytome­ 
try analysis revealed that the frequency of CD4 + T cells was 
decreased significantly in the colon and the small intestinal LP 
(Fig. 1 B). CD4 + T cells were decreased also in PPs but not in 
the mesenteric LN (MLN). When FoxP3 + CD4 + T cells were 
examined, they were more decreased in the colon and the 
small intestine than in MLN or PPs (Fig. 1, B and C). CD8 + 
T cells were significantly decreased in PPs and the small intes­ 
tine (Fig. 1, A-C). 
In an effort to provide an explanation for the deficiency 
of CD4 + T cells in the intestine, we examined the expression 
of CCR9 and 47 (Fig. 2 A). Both FoxP3 + and FoxP3  
CD4 + T cells in the small intestine of BATF KO mice ex­ 
pressed CCR9 at reduced levels compared with WT mice 
(Fig. 2, A and B). Numbers of CD4 + FoxP3 + T cells positive </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 210, No. 3 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>

<p>477 </p>

<p>and RAR was examined and was found to be normal in 
BATF KO T cells cultured in the presence and absence of 
RA (Fig. 5 A). We examined the sequence structure of the 
regulatory region of the CCR9 and Itg4 genes. We found 
several RAR and BATF binding sites in the 5 upstream 
regions of the mouse CCR9 and Itg4 genes (Fig. S1 and 
Table S1). Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) followed 
by genomic DNA PCR on WT T cells activated in the </p>

<p>These results demonstrate that BATF KO CD4 + T cells are 
not developmentally defective but rather are functionally de­ 
fective in expression of the gut­homing receptors. </p>

<p>Defective binding of RAR to the regulatory regions 
of the CCR9 and Itg-4 genes in BATF deficiency 
To gain insights into the defective expression of CCR9 and 
47 in BATF deficiency, the expression of RAR, RAR, </p>

<p>Figure 1. BATF KO mice are deficient with T cells in the intestine. (A) CD4 and CD8 cells in the small intestinal villi of WT and BATF KO mice were 
examined by immunohistochemistry. Bars, 50 µm. (B) CD4 + FoxP3  effector, CD4 + FoxP3 + regulatory, and CD8 + T cells in selected organs were analyzed by 
flow cytometry. (C) Absolute numbers of each cell population in the indicated organs. Representative (A and B) and pooled (C) data obtained from four ex-
periments using 6-8-wk-old mice are shown. All error bars are SEM obtained from pooled data. Significant differences from WT T cells are shown (*, P &lt; 0.05). </p>



<p>BATF and gut-homing receptors | Wang et al. </p>

<p>class I and II deacetylase inhibitors restored the expression of 
the gut­homing receptors (Fig. 5 E). However, inhibition of 
Sirt1 was not effective. </p>

<p>BATF KO T cells fail to migrate to various compartments 
of the intestine 
Defective expression of CCR9 and 47 is expected to 
negatively influence the homing of BATF KO T cells to 
the gut. We determined the short­term homing ability of 
BATF KO T cells in vivo. Naive CD4 + T cells from WT 
and BATF KO mice were activated in the presence of RA 
for 6 d and examined for chemotaxis to the CCR9 ligand 
CCL25 in vitro (Fig. 6 A). Chemotaxis by RA­treated 
BATF KO CD4 + T cells was inefficient compared with 
WT T cells (Fig. 6 A), which is explained by the CCR9 
deficiency. When introduced via a tail vein injection and 
examined 20 h later by flow cytometry, RA­treated BATF 
KO CD4 + T cells were poorly represented in the small 
intestine compared with WT T cells (Fig. 6 B). The flow 
cytometry technique is useful for assessing cell migration 
into an organ but cannot accurately evaluate cell migration </p>

<p>presence of RA revealed the binding of RAR and BATF 
to 18 regions in the 44­kbp 5 upstream region of the CCR9 
gene as well as to the 5 upstream region of the Itg4 gene 
(Fig. 5, B and C). The binding of RAR to the CCR9 and 
Itg4 genes was abnormally low in BATF KO T cells (Fig. 5, 
B and C). Moreover, the level of acetylated histone 4 pro­ 
tein was very low in the regulatory regions of CCR9 and 
Itg4 genes. In line with this, the promoter activity of a 
1.3­kbp region spanning the 5 upstream regulatory region of 
Itg-4 gene was significantly lower in BATF KO than WT 
T cells (Fig. 5 D). 
Nuclear hormone receptor function involves a series of 
enzymatic modifications of proteins including the acetyla­ 
tion of histone proteins for gene expression (Rosenfeld et al., 
2006). It has been reported that expression of Sirt1, a histone 
deacetylase (HDAC) class III enzyme, is induced in BATF 
deficiency to decrease acetylation of histones in CD8 + T cells 
(Kuroda et al., 2011). To determine the role of histone acety­ 
lation in expression of CCR9 and 47 in BATF deficiency, 
we used inhibitors of HDACs (trichostatin A and BML­210 
for class I/II; Ex­527 for Sirt1). Increased acetylation through </p>

<p>Figure 2. BATF KO gut T cells are defi-
cient in expression of CCR9 and 47. 
(A) Expression of the indicated trafficking 
receptors by CD4 + FoxP3 +/ T cell subsets 
were analyzed by flow cytometry. (B) Graphs 
show absolute cell numbers. (C) Expression 
of CCR9 and 47 by CD8 + T cells. Graphs 
show frequencies of CCR9 + or 47 + CD8 + 
T cells in the indicated organs. Representa-
tive (A) and pooled (n = 8-11 for B; n = 5 
for C) data obtained from at least five ex-
periments using 6-8-wk-old mice are shown. 
All error bars are SEM obtained from pooled 
data. Significant differences between WT and 
BATF KO T cells are shown (*, P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 210, No. 3 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>

<p>479 </p>

<p>and large intestinal LP and PPs was defective. Migration to 
MLN was decreased by 30% compared with WT T cells. 
One disadvantage of confocal imaging on tissue sections is 
that the areas viewed are limited by sectioning, and it is </p>

<p>into specific microenvironments within an organ. To ex­ 
amine cell migration to specific tissue sites, frozen sections of 
the tissues were examined by confocal microscopy (Fig. 6 C). 
We found that migration of CD4 + T cells into the small </p>

<p>Figure 3. BATF KO T cells are defective in up-regulation of CCR9 and 47 but not in becoming FoxP3 + T cells in response to RA. (A) CD4 + 
naive T cells were activated in the presence of RA, and expression of CCR9 and 47 was examined by flow cytometry. (B) Expression of the trafficking 
receptor genes at the mRNA by cultured CD4 + naive T cells was examined by quantitative RT-PCR. Normalized values to -actin levels are shown. (C) Ex-
pression of other chemokine receptors was examined by flow cytometry. (D) RA-dependent induction of FoxP3 + T cells in vitro from naive CD4 + T cells 
was examined by flow cytometry. Naive CD4 + T cells were in vitro activated with concanavalin A and IL-2 in the presence or absence of 10 nM RA for 5 d. 
1 ng/ml TGF1 was added to culture. (E) Expression of CCR9 and 47 by WT and BATF KO FoxP3 + cells induced by RA and TGF1. All graphs show 
pooled data obtained from four experiments (*, P &lt; 0.05). All error bars are SEM obtained from pooled data. </p>



<p>BATF and gut-homing receptors | Wang et al. </p>

<p>BATF KO CD4 + T cells fail to induce inflammation 
in the intestine 
BATF KO CD4 + T cells may not effectively induce inflam­ 
mation in the intestine because of their poor migration to 
the tissue. We tested this possibility using the colitis model 
in Rag1 / mice. Rag1 / mice were injected with T reg cell-
depleted naive CD4 + T cells isolated from WT or BATF KO 
mice. Naive BATF KO CD4 + T cells did not decrease the 
weight of Rag1 / mice as effectively as WT T cells (Fig. 8 A). 
Histological examination revealed only mild inflammation 
in the Rag1 / mice injected with naive BATF KO CD4 + 
T cells (Fig. 8 B). This is in contrast to the severe inflamma­ 
tion seen in both the proximal and distal colon of the Rag1 / 
mice injected with naive WT T cells. The numbers of Th1 
cells, which are the major effector T cells to induce inflamma­ 
tion in this model, were decreased in the colon of Rag1 / 
mice injected with naive BATF KO CD4 + T cells (Fig. 8 C). 
The specific decrease of Th1 cells in the colon indicates that 
BATF is required for Th1 effector T cell population in the in­ 
flamed gut tissue. Also decreased were the numbers of Th17 
and T reg cells in the colon and the small intestine (Fig. 8 C). 
This decrease in Th17 cell numbers in all tissues, including the 
spleen, is in line with the previous reports demonstrating that 
BATF KO T cells are impaired in their ability to differentiate 
into Th17 cells (Schraml et al., 2009; Betz et al., 2010). Over­ 
all, these results demonstrate the defective population and in­ 
flammatory function of BATF KO T cells in the intestine. </p>

<p>often difficult to locate tissue sites such as small lymphoid 
patches in the intestine. To overcome this issue, we used 
multiphoton microscopy to image whole­mounted tis­ 
sues (Fig. 6 D). Using this technique, we confirmed that 
the migration of BATF KO T cells into the small intestine 
and colon was severely compromised. Additionally, we 
found that migration of RA­conditioned BATF KO T cells 
to both colonic patches and PPs was defective as well. 
Three­dimensional (3D) images of the differential migration 
into the indicated whole­mounted tissues are shown in 
Videos 1-3. </p>

<p>BATF KO mice are defective in forming intestinal FoxP3 + 
and FoxP3  T cells after oral/intragastric immunization 
Oral immunization increases antigen­specific T cells, par­ 
ticularly FoxP3 + T cells, in the intestine. We examined 
whether antigen­specific (OT­II) BATF KO T cells can 
populate the small intestine after mucosal immunization 
with OVA. OVA­specific BATF KO FoxP3 + CD4 + T cells 
failed to populate the small intestine (Fig. 7, A and B). 
However, there was no significant difference in the num­ 
bers of these cells populating other organs such as PPs, MLN, 
spleen, and peripheral LN (PLN). OVA­specific BATF 
KO FoxP3  non­T reg cells also failed to populate the small 
intestine after immunization, whereas their population in 
other organs except PPs were not affected significantly 
(Fig. 7, A and B). </p>

<p>Figure 4. Enforced BATF expression restores 
the gut-homing receptor deficiency of BATF KO 
T cells. (A) Retroviral vectors expressing the full-
length and truncated versions of BATF were con-
structed. BATF-deficient T cells were infected by 
retroviral vectors expressing the full-length or 
truncated BATF genes. (B and C) Expression of CCR9 
and 47 was determined by flow cytometry 4 d 
after infection, and the data are shown as dot plots (B) 
and graphs (C). The graphs show combined data 
from three experiments. All error bars are SEM ob-
tained from pooled data. Significant differences 
from the control groups are shown (*, P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 210, No. 3 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>

<p>481 </p>

<p>The defective effector function of BATF KO CD4 + 
T cells may also be caused by problems in cell activation, 
death, or proliferation. In this regard, a lymphoproliferative </p>

<p>Figure 5. RAR fails to bind the 5 regulatory regions of the mouse CCR9 and Itg-4 genes in BATF deficiency. WT or BATF KO CD4 + T cells were 
activated for 4-5 d with concanavalin A, IL-2, and RA. (A) Expression of nuclear RAR genes in BATF KO CD4 + T cells was examined by quantitative RT-PCR. 
Normalized values to -actin levels are shown. (B and C) The binding of RAR and BATF and histone H4 acetylation on the CCR9 gene (B) or the Itg-4 gene 
(C) were assessed by ChIP assay. Representative PCR data with duplicated measurements are shown. (D) WT or BATF KO CD4 + T cells were activated for 4-5 d 
with anti-CD3/CD28 in the presence of IL-2 and 10 nM RA and transfected with pGL4-5-Itg-4. The cells were reactivated with anti-CD3/28 + IL2 in the 
presence of 20 nM RA for 16 h, and luciferase activity was normalized to control Renilla luciferase activity. (E) Naive WT or BATF KO CD4 + T cells were acti-
vated with anti-CD3/CD28 or concanavalin A for 4-5 d in the presence of IL-2 and 10 nM RA and the indicated HDAC inhibitors (TSA, BML-210, or EX-527), 
and the expression of CCR9 and 47 was measured by flow cytometry. Graphs show the percentage of cells expressing CCR9 or 47. All of the experi-
ments were performed at least three times, and pooled (A, D, and E) or representative (B and C) data are shown. Error bars are SEM obtained from pooled data 
(A, D, and E) or differences between duplicated measurements (B and C). Significant differences from the KO control group are shown (*, P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>disorder caused by increased T cell survival has been observed 
in aged mice overexpressing BATF (Logan et al., 2012). 
We observed that BATF KO CD4 + T cells were comparable </p>



<p>BATF and gut-homing receptors | Wang et al. </p>

<p>BATF KO iT reg cells fail to suppress 
inflammation in the intestine 
As shown in Fig. 3 E, iT reg cells derived from naive BATF 
KO CD4 + T cells were deficient in the expression of CCR9 
and 47. We examined whether this deficiency would af­ 
fect the in vivo suppressive function of BATF KO iT reg cells. 
RA­treated BATF KO iT reg cells were as effective as WT 
iT reg cells in suppressing responder T cells in vitro (Fig. 10 A). 
Thus, function of the BATF KO iT reg cells is intact in vitro. 
We next compared the suppressive functions of CD45.2 + 
iT reg cells generated from naive WT and BATF KO CD4 + 
T cells in vivo in the T cell-induced colitis model. RA­treated 
BATF KO iT reg cells were not as effective as WT T reg cells 
in suppressing the weight loss induced by the inflammatory </p>

<p>with WT T cells in loss of CD62L and up­regulation of CD69 
in response to anti­CD3/28 + IL­2 (Fig. 9 A). Moreover, 
BATF KO CD4 + T cells did not display significant differ­ 
ences in cell death after T cell activation (Fig. 9 B). Expansion 
of OT­II CD4 + T cells after parenteral immunization was also 
largely intact (Fig. 9 C). Similarly, homeostatic CD4 + T cell 
expansion in lymphopenic Rag1 / mice was slightly de­ 
creased but was not defective (Fig. 9 D). Absolute numbers 
of BATF KO CD4 + T cells in the spleen and PLN were 
comparable with WT, but the numbers in the intestinal LP 
and the intestine­draining LN (MLN) were decreased as 
expected (Fig. 9 E). These results indicate that general cell 
processes such as cell activation, death, and proliferation ap­ 
pear largely intact in BATF KO T cells. </p>

<p>Figure 6. Defective migration of BATF 
KO CD4 + T cells into the intestine. (A) WT 
and BATF KO CD4 + T cells were activated 
with RA for 5 d and then added to the upper 
chamber in a Transwell assay. 3 µg/ml CCL25 
was added to the lower chamber, and the 
cells in the lower chamber were counted 
after 3 h. The data are shown as percent net 
migration after normalization to input cells 
and subtraction of the background migration 
rates. (B) WT and BATF KO CD4 + T cells were 
activated for 5-6 d with concanavalin A, IL-2, 
and RA and were then differentially labeled 
with CFSE and TRITC. The cells were mixed in 
a 1:1 ratio and injected i.v. into WT mice. 
(B and C) Numbers of cells in the indicated 
organs were assessed by flow cytometry (B) 
or confocal microscopy (C) after 20 h. Bars, 
50 µm. (B) The homing index indicates the 
frequency of KO cells relative to WT cells. 
(D) The tissues were examined also with multi-
photon microscopy. Pooled data from three 
experiments are shown in A and B. Pooled 
data from multiple images (3-12) obtained 
from two independent experiments are 
shown in C and D. All error bars are SEM 
obtained from pooled data. Significant dif-
ferences between WT and BATF KO T cells 
are shown (*, P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 210, No. 3 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>important not only for effector T cells in inducing intestinal 
inflammation but also for T reg cells in controlling inflammation. 
The findings implicate BATF as a key regulator of T cell-
mediated immune responses and inflammation in the intestine. 
Our results indicate that BATF deficiency makes CD4 + 
T cells less responsive to the RA signal in up­regulating the 
gut­homing receptors. RA, produced by gut epithelial cells 
and dendritic cells, is the major inducer of CCR9 and 47. 
In this process, RAR plays an important role as the receptor 
for RA and works together with the TCR activation signal to 
up­regulate CCR9 (Iwata et al., 2004). RA also plays an im­ 
portant role in up­regulating the Itg­4 subunit of the 47 
integrin (Kang et al., 2011). The Itg­7 subunit of 47 is 
expressed constitutively and increased further by TGF1 (Kang 
et al., 2011). Our results indicate that expression of Itg-4, but 
not Itg-7, is defective at the mRNA level in BATF deficiency. 
Defective expression of the gut­homing receptors by BATF 
KO CD4 + T cells can result in inefficient migration of these 
T cells into the intestine. The CCR9 ligand, CCL25 (also called 
TECK), is highly expressed in the epithelial cells of the small 
intestine (Kunkel et al., 2000). CCR9 deficiency leads to de­ 
fective homing of memory T cells into the small intestinal LP 
(Stenstad et al., 2006). 47 is required for migration into the 
whole intestine because its adhesion receptor, MAdCAM­1, 
is expressed on intestinal endothelial cells (Sigmundsdottir 
and Butcher, 2008). MAdCAM­1 is expressed also on the </p>

<p>activity of WT T cells (Fig. 10 B). Histological examination 
revealed that only WT iT reg cells, but not BATF KO iT reg cells, 
effectively suppressed colitis (Fig. 10 C). BATF KO iT reg cells 
were also less effective than WT iT reg cells in decreasing the 
number of CD45.1 + (WT naive T cell derived) Th1 effector 
cells in the MLN and colon (Fig. 10 D). Th17 cells, which are 
generally suppressed by Th1 cells, were reciprocally increased 
with injection of WT iT reg cells but not with BATF KO 
iT reg cells. Fewer CD45.2 + BATF KO iT reg cells than WT 
iT reg cells were found in the colon but not in the MLN of the 
Rag1 / mice (Fig. 10 E), indicating defective population of 
the transferred BATF KO iT reg cells in the colon but not in 
the MLN in the inflammatory condition. Overall, these results 
demonstrate that BATF is required for the in vivo population 
of T reg cells in the gut and their regulatory activity on the 
Th1 cell activity and tissue inflammation. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Our study identified BATF as a cellular factor required for 
the optimal expression of CCR9 and 47 by T cells, partic­ 
ularly CD4 + T cells, in response to RA. We provided evidence 
that naive CD4 + T cells require BATF to up­regulate the gut­ 
homing receptors during T cell activation and differentiation. 
BATF is important for the expression of gut­homing recep­ 
tors by both effector cells and FoxP3 + T reg cells. Moreover, this 
role of BATF in regulating gut­homing receptor expression is </p>

<p>Figure 7. Defective population of CD4 + T cells in the intestine after intragastric immunization. WT and BATF KO OT-II CD4 + T cells were trans-
ferred into CD45.1 + mice, and the mice were intragastrically immunized with OVA. The mice were sacrificed 12 d later. (A) CD4 + CD45.2 + T cell subsets in 
the intestine and other organs were examined by flow cytometry. (B) Absolute numbers of CD4 + CD45.2 + FoxP3 + and FoxP3  CD4 + T cells in various or-
gans are shown. Pooled data obtained from three experiments (n = 5-7/group) are shown. All error bars are SEM obtained from pooled data. Significant 
differences (P &lt; 0.05) from non-OVA-treated groups (*) or WT counterparts (**) are shown. </p>



<p>BATF and gut-homing receptors | Wang et al. </p>

<p>oral immunization. Also defective was the population of non­ 
T reg cells in the intestine. Although the short­term homing of 
T cells into PPs is somewhat defective, oral immunization still 
normally induced population of T cells in PPs and other lym­ 
phoid tissues such as spleen and PLN. This is perhaps because 
T cell migration to secondary lymphoid tissues involves traf­ 
ficking receptors that are not regulated by BATF. In this re­ 
gard, it has been shown that T cell migration into PPs can be 
mediated also by an 47­independent mechanism mediated 
by L­selectin (Bargatze et al., 1995; Warnock et al., 2000). 
Our results indicate that BATF deficiency has a signifi­ 
cant functional consequence on the induction and regulation 
of tissue inflammation in the intestine. BATF KO T cells fail 
to induce colitis in Rag1 / mice. Also, BATF KO FoxP3 + 
T cells fail to suppress colitis induced by inflammatory T cells. </p>

<p>endothelial cells in PPs (Streeter et al., 1988), and therefore, 
BATF KO T cells with low 47 expression are inefficient 
for migration into PPs. Additionally, migration of BATF KO 
T cells to colonic patches was defective, indicating that BATF 
expression is important for T cell migration into the gut­ 
associated lymphoid tissues and nonlymphoid tissue areas. 
Oral or intragastric immunization induces immune toler­ 
ance in the intestine in part by generating gut­homing T reg cells 
in the intestine (Thorstenson and Khoruts, 2001; Nagatani 
et al., 2004). Gut­homing receptors such as CCR9 and 47 
are required for the proper induction of immune tolerance in 
the intestine, probably because of the need for efficient mi­ 
gration of T reg cells into the intestine in the process (Cassani 
et al., 2011). Our results revealed that BATF deficiency leads 
to defective population of T reg cells in the small intestine after </p>

<p>Figure 8. BATF KO T cells are defective in 
inducing colitis. Rag1 / mice were injected with the 
naive CD4 + CD25  T cells isolated from WT or BATF 
KO mice. (A) Weight change after injection of WT or 
BATF KO naive CD4 + CD25  T cells was monitored. 
(B) Histological changes of the intestine of Rag1 / 
mice injected with naive CD4 + CD25  T cells were 
examined at the time of mouse termination. 
Bars, 200 µm. (C) Frequencies of Th1, Th17, and 
FoxP3 + T cells in Rag1 / mice injected with naive 
CD4 + CD25  T cells were determined by flow cytom-
etry. Pooled data obtained from three experiments 
are shown in the graphs (n ≥ 10/group). All error 
bars are SEM obtained from pooled data. Significant 
differences between indicated groups or from WT 
groups are shown (*, P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 210, No. 3 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>

<p>485 </p>

<p>of BATF KO T cells in response to antigens and in a lympho­ 
penic condition are not impaired. 
The result of our retroviral gene transfer study demon­ 
strated that BATF expression allows BATF KO T cells to re­ 
gain sensitivity to the RA signal and up­regulate the two 
homing receptors. How BATF regulates gene expression and 
cell function is an active area of research. The in vitro analysis 
of BATF function indicates a role for the protein in the sup­ 
pression of AP­1 transcriptional activity (Echlin et al., 2000). 
BATF inhibits expression of the nicotinamide adenine di­ 
nucleotide (NAD + )-dependent deacetylase Sirt1, which in turn 
results in increased T­bet expression (Kuroda et al., 2011). In 
contrast, BATF has been shown to be associated with tran­ 
scriptional activation of several genes in Th17 cells and with 
the induction of AID (Schraml et al., 2009; Ise et al., 2011). 
BATF and IRF­4 can cooperate to induce the IL10, IL-17a, 
and IL-21 genes in T cells and to regulate the development </p>

<p>In an inflammatory condition, BATF KO effector Th1 cells 
and FoxP3 + T cells failed to populate the colon. These results 
suggest that BATF is important for the generation of func­ 
tionally competent effector and suppressor T cells with a nor­ 
mal gut migratory capacity. Although this study focuses on the 
migration aspect, BATF is known to have additional func­ 
tions in regulation of T cell function. Although BATF is not 
required to generate Th1 cells and FoxP3 + T cells, BATF is 
required to generate Th17 cells and T­Fh cells. It has been re­ 
ported that BATF is required for generation of effector CD8 + 
T cells (Kuroda et al., 2011) and for a check point in the self­ 
renewal of hematopoietic stem cells in response to DNA 
damage (Wang et al., 2012). Thus, other phenotypes of BATF 
KO mice in addition to the migration defect could contrib­ 
ute to the ineffective function of effector and suppressor T cells 
in control of tissue inflammation in the intestine. Nevertheless, 
we did confirm that the basic activation, survival, and expansion </p>

<p>Figure 9. BATF KO T cells are largely intact in activation, survival, and proliferation. (A-E) WT and BATF KO CD4 + T cells were examined 
in vitro for activation (A) and survival (B) and in vivo for proliferation (C-E). T cells were activated with anti-CD3, anti-CD28, and IL-2 for 4 d, and ex-
pression of CD69 and CD62L (A) and cell death based on staining with annexin V and propidium iodide (PI; B) were examined. (C) CD45.1 mice were 
injected i.v. with 10 million CFSE-labeled WT or BATF KO OT-II CD4 + T cells and were immunized i.p. with OVA in complete Freund's adjuvant. CFSE 
dilution was examined by flow cytometry 5 d later. (D) Rag1 / mice were injected i.v. with 10 million CFSE-labeled WT or BATF KO CD4 + T cells. The 
host mice were examined 14 d later for CFSE dilution. (E) Absolute numbers of WT and BATF KO CD4 + T cells expanded in the indicated organs of 
Rag1 / mice are shown. Pooled data obtained from three experiments are shown in the graphs (n ≥ 10/group). All error bars are SEM obtained from 
pooled data. Significant differences from WT groups are shown (*, P &lt; 0.05). </p>



<p>BATF and gut-homing receptors | Wang et al. </p>

<p>machinery and the activities of several coactivators and re­ 
pressors. In conclusion, this study identified a novel function 
for BATF in up­regulating the major gut­homing receptors 
on T helper cells. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Mice. Batf Z/Z mice with the third exon deleted in the Batf gene have 
been described previously (Betz et al., 2010) and will be referred to as 
BATF KO mice in this article. C57BL/6 mice breeding pairs were purchased 
from Harlan. BATF KO mice were backcrossed on the C57BL/6 back­ 
ground for &gt;10 generations. Congenic CD45.1 C57BL/6, OT­II (C57BL/6­ 
Tg(TcraTcrb)425Cbn/J), and Rag1 / mice (B6.129S7­Rag1tm1Mom/J) 
were obtained from the Jackson Laboratory. OT­II mice were crossed to 
BATF KO mice to generate OT­II BATF KO mice. All mice used in this 
study were maintained at Purdue University, and experiments were per­ 
formed according to approved protocols by the Purdue University Animal 
Care and Use Committee. Generally, the mice were used between 6 and 
8 wk of age at the start of each experiment. </p>

<p>of CD8 + dendritic cells (Glasmacher et al., 2012; Li et al., 
2012; Tussiwand et al., 2012). Several BATF­ and RAR­ 
binding sites are present in the 5 regulatory regions of the 
CCR9 and Itg-4 genes. With one exception, all of these bind­ 
ing sites on the CCR9 gene and all of the BATF­binding sites 
on the Itg-4 gene do not possess the features of AP­1-IRF 
composite elements, suggesting that the expression of the 
gut­trafficking receptors would likely involve a different reg­ 
ulatory mechanism. Histone modification by acetylation is 
critical for chromatin remodeling for gene expression in re­ 
sponse to nuclear hormone receptor ligands (Rosenfeld et al., 
2006). Our results indicate that RAR binding and histone 
acetylation at the CCR9 and Itg4 genes are important for 
expression of the gut­homing receptors and are regulated by 
BATF. The detailed interaction underlying the regulation of 
the trafficking receptor genes will require further study as it may 
involve cross talk between BATF and the RAR expression </p>

<p>Figure 10. BATF KO iT reg cells, although 
equally suppressive in vitro as WT iT reg 
cells, are unable to suppress colitis. BATF 
KO and WT iT reg cells were prepared in vitro 
from naive CD4 + T cells through activation 
with concanavalin A in the presence of 
TGF1 and 10 nM RA for 6 d. (A) The 
iT reg cells were examined for their suppres-
sive activity on proliferation of target 
(CD4 + CD25  ) T cells based on frequencies 
(percentages) of CFSE-diluted cells deter-
mined by flow cytometry. (B-E) Rag1 / 
mice were injected i.p. with 0.6 × 10 6 WT 
CD45.1 + naive CD4 + CD25  T cells and 1.2 × 
10 6 WT or BATF KO CD45.2 + iT reg cells, and 
weight change (B), histological changes on 
day 25-28 (C), frequencies of Th1, Th17, and 
FoxP3 + T cells derived from the naive 
CD4 + CD25  T cells (D), and frequencies of 
FoxP3 + cells derived from the injected 
iT reg cells (E) were examined. Bars, 200 µm. 
The mice (n = 9-10/group) were sacrificed 
on day 25-28 after T cell transfer when some 
mice lost &gt;20% of their original weight. 
Pooled data obtained from three experi-
ments are shown in the graphs. All error 
bars are SEM obtained from pooled data. 
Significant differences between indicated 
groups or between WT and BATF KO groups 
are shown (*, P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 210, No. 3 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>(Promega). Relative light units (RLU) after normalization of firefly lucifer­ 
ase activity with Renilla luciferase (pRL) activity are shown. </p>

<p>Short-term homing experiments and confocal analysis to determine 
localization of injected cells. For homing experiments, naive CD4 + T cells 
isolated from splenocytes and LN cells of WT and BATF KO mice were cul­ 
tured for 5-6 d in complete RPMI 1640 medium (10% FBS) supplemented 
with 2.5 µg/ml concanavalin A, 25 U/ml hIL­2, and 10 nM RA. WT cells 
(10 7 cells/mouse; labeled with CFSE; Invitrogen) and BATF KO cells 
(10 7 cells/mouse; labeled with tetramethylrhodamine isothiocyanate; Invit­ 
rogen) were coinjected i.v. into normal C57BL/6 mice. The host mice were 
sacrificed 20 h later, and indicated organs were harvested. The numbers of 
injected CD4 + cells migrated into each organ were determined with flow 
cytometry. Absolute numbers of T cells that migrated into various organs and 
homing index were determined as described previously (Wang et al., 2010). </p>

<p>Confocal and multiphoton microscopy. Spleen, MLN, small intestine, 
colon, and PPs were harvested from 8-10­wk­old mice and frozen in Tissue­ 
Tek OCT Compound (Sakura). The tissue blocks were cut into 6­µm sections, 
fixed in cold acetone, and stained with combinations of FITC/PE/APC­ 
conjugated antibodies to CD4 (RM4­5), cytokeratin (AE1/AE3), and CD8 
(53-6.7). The images were collected with an LSM 710 (Carl Zeiss) or SP5 II 
(Leica) confocal microscope. The 3D images were acquired on paraformal­ 
dehyde­fixed whole­mounted tissues with an SP5 multiphoton System 
(Leica) with Mai Tai Deep See Tunable IR Laser (IR laser set at 800 nm; fil­ 
ters were 430-480 for second harmonic generation, 500-595 for CFSE, and 
595-605 for TRITC). Acquisition volume was 300 × 300 × 100 µm, and 
z­axis resolution was 0.5 µm. </p>

<p>T cell population in the intestine after intragastric immunization. 
T reg cell-depleted CD4 + CD25  T cells were isolated from WT OT­II and 
BATF KO OT­II (CD45.2) mice. The OT­II T cells (10 7 cells/mouse) were 
adoptively transferred i.v. into CD45.1 congenic mice. 2 d later, the recipient 
mice were injected with OVA protein (100 mg/injection in 200 µl of PBS; 
Sigma­Aldrich) intragastrically with a round­tip needle. On the next day, this 
immunization was repeated once. 12 d later, mice were sacrificed to examine 
the numbers of CD4 + FoxP3 + and FoxP3  T cells in indicated organs. </p>

<p>In vitro T reg cell assay. For assessing the T reg cell activity, CFSE­labeled 
CD4 + CD25  T cells (target cells, 3 × 10 4 cells/well) and iT reg cells as 
suppressors were co­cultured in round­bottom 96­well plates for 3 d at the 
indicated ratios with 2 µg/ml anti­CD3 antibody and irradiated splenic 
cells (9 × 10 4 cells/well). iT reg cells were generated in vitro with culturing 
CD4 + CD25  naive T cells for 6 d in the presence of 1 ng/ml TGF1, 10 nM 
RA, and 2.5 µg/ml concanavalin A. Dilution of CFSE indicating cell prolif­ 
eration was determined by flow cytometry. </p>

<p>Induction of colitis in Rag1 / mice and in vivo assessment of 
T reg cell function. For assessment of effector T cell function, Rag1 / mice 
were injected i.p. with 0.6 × 10 6 WT or BATF KO naive T cells. For com­ 
parison of T reg cell function, 0.6 × 10 6 WT naive T cells were injected together 
with 1.2 × 10 6 WT or BATF KO iT reg cells. Weight change was monitored, 
and the mice were sacrificed on day 25-28 after T cell transfer when some 
mice lost &gt;20% of their original weight. Intestinal inflammation in Rag1 / 
mice was scored as previously described (Wang et al., 2010) based on the de­ 
gree of leukocyte infiltration, mucosal hyperplasia, and loss of villi on a scale of 
0-4. The histological images were obtained with a wide­field DM2000 micro­ 
scope equipped with a DFC295 color camera (Leica) at 100 magnification. </p>

<p>T cell proliferation in vivo. For assessment of T cell proliferation in vivo, 
10 7 CFSE­labeled CD4 + T cells were injected i.v. into Rag1 / mice, and the 
host mice were sacrificed on day 14. For assessment of antigen­dependent 
T cell proliferation, CD45.1 congenic mice were injected i.v. with 10 7 CFSE­ 
labeled WT or BATF KO OT­II CD4 + T cells and immunized i.p. with 250 µg 
OVA in complete Freund's adjuvant. The host mice were sacrificed 5 d </p>

<p>Cell culture. Single cell suspensions of LNs (mesenteric, inguinal, auxiliary, 
and brachial) and spleens were prepared by grinding tissues through an iron 
mesh. CD4 + T cells were isolated by a CD4 + T cell isolation kit (Miltenyi 
Biotec). The cells were further processed for isolation of T reg cell-depleted 
CD4 + CD25  CD44  CD69  naive T cells with an AutoMACS separator 
(Miltenyi Biotec) as previously described (Kang et al., 2011). The cells were 
cultured for 5-6 d in complete RPMI 1640 medium (10% FBS) supple­ 
mented with 100 U/ml hIL­2. When indicated, 1 ng/ml hTGF­1 and/or 
10 nM RA (all­trans RA) was added. As T cell activators, 2.5 µg/ml con­ 
canavalin A or OVA 323-339 peptide (at 1 µg/ml with 3× irradiated splenocytes 
for OT­II cells) was used. All cytokines were obtained from R&amp;D Systems or 
PeproTech. When indicated, HDAC inhibitors such as 10 µM EX­527 (Sigma­ 
Aldrich), 5 nM trichostatin (Enzo Life Sciences), and 10 µM BML­210 
(Sigma­Aldrich) were added to the T cell culture. </p>

<p>Flow cytometry. Expression of chemokine receptors and integrins was 
examined as previously described (Kang et al., 2011). Single cell suspensions, 
isolated from various organs of mice, were stained with antibodies to CCR9 
(clone 242503) and 47 (clone DATK32). For cells stained with unconju­ 
gated antibodies, biotin­labeled secondary antibodies and tertiary PE/PerCP/ 
APC­streptavidin (BD) were used along with antibodies to CD44 and CD4. 
When necessary, the cells were further stained with antibodies to FoxP3 
(FJK­16s; eBioscience) according to the manufacturer's protocol. </p>

<p>Chemotaxis assay. The chemotaxis assay was performed and analyzed as 
described previously (Wang et al., 2010). In brief, 5 × 10 5 T cells, activated 
in the presence or absence of 10 nM RA for 5 d, were added to the upper 
chamber of Transwell inserts (Corning) and allowed to migrate to the 
lower chamber containing 3 µg/ml murine CCL25 (R&amp;D Systems) for 
3 h. The cells in the lower chambers were collected, stained, and quanti­ 
tated by flow cytometry. </p>

<p>Retroviral expression of BATF. The full­length and truncated coding 
regions of the mouse BATF cDNA were amplified by PCR using the 
primers described in Table S2. Amplified DNA fragments were cloned into 
a retroviral vector with GFP expression to help identify transduced cells 
(Wang et al., 2009) and sequenced for accuracy. A retrovirus packaging 
cell line (Phoenix­ECO) was transfected with the vectors, and activated 
T cells were infected with culture supernatant containing the recombinant 
virus. The T cells were previously activated for 36 h with IL­2 and con­ 
canavalin A in the presence or absence of 10 nM RA. The virus­infected 
T cells were harvested 4 d later, and GFP + T cells were examined for CCR9 
and 47 expression. </p>

<p>Bioinformatics and ChIP assays. The <rs type="software">VISTA</rs> bioinformatics tool was 
used to determine conserved noncoding sequences. ChIP assays were per­ 
formed as described previously (Kang et al., 2011). CD4 + T cells (5 × 10 6 
naive per sample), cultured in the presence of 100 U/ml IL­2, 1.5 µg/ml 
concanavalin A, and 10 nM RA for 4-5 d, were used for ChIP assays. DNA 
protein complexes were immunoprecipitated using 4 µg anti­BATF (rabbit 
polyclonal; Cell Signaling Technology), anti­RAR (rabbit polyclonal; Santa 
Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.), and anti-acetyl­histone H4 antibodies (EMD 
Millipore). Real­time PCR detection using the primers described in Table S3 
was conducted with a 7500 Sequence Detection System using the SYBR 
green Master Mix (Applied Biosystems). </p>

<p>Transfection and reporter assay. Before transfection, T cells were cultured 
with 10 nM RA and 100 U/ml IL­2 with plate­bound 5 µg/ml anti­CD3 
and 2 µg/ml anti­CD28 for 4 d in complete RPMI medium replaced every 
2 d. Activated CD4 + T cells (5 × 10 6 cells per sample) were transfected with 
20 µg pGL4.1­5­Itg­4 (pGL4.1 harboring the 1.3 kbp 5 regulatory region 
of the mouse Itg-4 gene) and 3.5 µg pRL with the Mouse T Cell Nucleo­ 
fector kit (Lonza). The cells were rested at 37°C for 4-5 h and activated with 
plate­bound anti­CD3, anti­CD28, and 100 U/ml IL­2 in the presence 100 nM 
RA for 16 h before measurement with the Dual Luciferase Assay System </p>



<p>Statistical analyses. Means with SEM are shown in most of the figures. 
Student's paired t test (two tailed) was used to determine the significance of 
differences between two groups. The weight change data in Figs. 8 and 10 
was examined with a repeated measures ANOVA (<rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 9.2</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>.). P­values ≤ 0.05 were considered significant. </p>

<p>Online supplemental material. Fig. S1 shows the regulatory regions of 
CCR9 and Itg-4 genes and the binding sites for RAR and BATF examined 
in this study. Videos 1-3 show 3D images of the WT and BATF KO T cells 
migrated into the spleen and PLN (Video 1), a PP and colonic patch 
(Video 2), and the small intestinal LP and colon (Video 3). Tables S1-S3 list 
primer sequences and putative binding sites for RAR and BATF. Online 
supplemental material is available at http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/ 
full/jem.20121088/DC1. </p>

<p>This study was supported, in part, by grants from the National Institutes of Health 
(NIH; R01AI074745, R01DK076616, 1S10RR02829, and R01AI080769), Crohn's and 
Colitis Foundation of America, and National Multiple Sclerosis Foundation to 
C.H. Kim and the NIH (R01CA114381) to E.J. Taparowsky. 
The authors declare there are no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Submitted: 22 May 2012 
Accepted: 25 January 2013 </p>



</text></tei>