<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3686433" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
In this paper, we performed a comprehensive re-annotation of protein-coding genes by a systematic 
method combining composition-and similarity-based approaches in 10 complete bacterial genomes of 
the family Neisseriaceae. First, 418 hypothetical genes were predicted as non-coding using the compos-
ition-based method and 413 were eliminated from the gene list. Both the scatter plot and cluster of ortho-
logous groups (COG) fraction analyses supported the result. Second, from 20 to 400 hypothetical proteins 
were assigned with functions in each of the 10 strains based on the homology search. Among newly assigned 
functions, 397 are so detailed to have definite gene names. Third, 106 genes missed by the original annota-
tions were picked up by an ab initio gene finder combined with similarity alignment. Transcriptional experi-
ments validated the effectiveness of this method in Laribacter hongkongensis and Chromobacterium 
violaceum. Among the 106 newly found genes, some deserve particular interests. For example, 27 transpo-
sases were newly found in Neiserria meningitidis alpha14. In Neiserria gonorrhoeae NCCP11945, four new 
genes with putative functions and definite names (nusG, rpsN, rpmD and infA) were found and homologues of 
them usually are essential for survival in bacteria. The updated annotations for the 10 Neisseriaceae 
genomes provide a more accurate prediction of protein-coding genes and a more detailed functional infor-
mation of hypothetical proteins. It will benefit research into the lifestyle, metabolism, environmental adap-
tion and pathogenicity of the Neisseriaceae species. The re-annotation procedure could be used directly, or 
after the adaption of detailed methods, for checking annotations of any other bacterial or archaeal genomes. 
The emergence of next-generation DNA sequencing 
techniques accelerate tremendously the increment of </p>

<p>sequences deposited in public nucleotide databases. 
The wealth of sequence data stimulates wonderful op-
portunity to understand the biological process of 
various living species. To achieve this aim, two of the </p>

<p># The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Kazusa DNA Research Institute. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-
nc/3.0/), which permits non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For 
commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com. </p>

<p>DNA RESEARCH 20, 273-286, (2013) 
doi:10.1093/dnares/dst009 
Advance Access publication on 9 April 2013 </p>

<p>essential steps are identifying all protein-coding genes 
and trying to assign their functions. They are jointly 
named as genome annotation. The quality of the 
genome annotation is very vital. If one genome 
could not be annotated accurately but still submitted 
to the public database, not only subsequent 
researches based on it may encounter problems but 
also annotations of after sequenced closely related 
genomes would be influenced. The annotation 
errors may propagate and finally affect more and 
more genomes. Recognizing this serious problem, 
Ouzounis and Kap 
1 appealed to update regularly the 
genome annotation by latest database and methods. 
As for prokaryotes, dozens of genomes have been 
re-annotated. 
2 Three kinds of re-annotations are 
often performed in sequenced prokaryotic genomes. 
First, and rather early, falsely predicted protein-
coding genes are eliminated from the original annota-
tion using composition-based methods. For example, 
Wang and Zhang 
3 suggested that 172 annotated 
genes were very unlikely to encode proteins in the 
genome of Vibrio cholerae based on single-nucleotide 
frequencies. One of the typical re-annotation cases of 
archaea was associated with Aeropyrum pernix K1, in 
which protein-coding genes were over-annotated up 
to 60% by the original sequencing institute. 
4 -6 It is 
lucky that this major error has been corrected by 
using proteome approaches and bioinformatics 
methods. 
7 -10 Amsacta moorei entomopoxvirus may 
have the most over-annotated protein-coding genes 
among sequenced viruses. 
11 Guo and Yu 
12 suggested 
that 38 of 294 originally annotated genes did not 
encode proteins based on the Z-curve method. By 
using another graphical method, Yu and Sun 
13 con-
firmed this speculation. 
Second, some genes may be missed by the original 
annotation and could be picked up by the ab initio 
gene finding method and further confirmed by the 
similarity alignment or transcription and/or protein 
expression proofs. For example, Zhou et al. 
14 newly 
added 278 potential genes by the similarity align-
ment and another 147 by detectable mRNA tran-
scriptions in the genome of Xanthomonas campestris. 
Very recently, Du et al. 
15 newly added eight potential 
genes by the similarity-based method in the archaeon 
Pyrobaculum aerophilum. 
Assigning functions to hypothetical proteins consti-
tutes the last kind of re-annotation. This type of re-an-
notation may be performed by using the homology 
alignment or by functional genomic experiments. 
For example, 149 hypothetical proteins were assigned 
detailed functions according to the strict homology 
information in the genome of Erwinia carotovora. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>A similar method was employed to the genome of 
P. aerophilum and 80 hypothetical proteins were 
assigned with functional information. 
15 Based on </p>

<p>cellular fractions and expression profiles under differ-
ent culture conditions, Okamoto and Yamada 
17 pro-
vided general functional information for 126 
hypothetical proteins in the genome of Streptococcus 
pyogenes. 
In this study, we performed all three types of re-an-
notation in 10 complete genomes of the 
Neisseriaceae family. As far as our knowledge goes, 
the only example involved with all three types of re-
annotation is the updated annotation in the 
genome of P. aerophilum. 
15 Through them, the out-
dated annotation may be corrected as far as possible. 
However, alternative approaches may be utilized to 
obtain similar results with the systematic method 
used here. Compared with our previous work, </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>here, we used transcriptional analyses to validate the 
effectiveness of our method to pick up new genes. 
The Neisseriaceae family belongs to b-proteobacteria. 
Among the 10 Neisseriaceae strains analyzed in this 
work, seven belong to the genus Neisseria and all 
can colonize the mucosal surfaces of many animals. 
Neiserria meningitidis, as one of the most common 
causes of bacterial meningitis, are most virulent in 
human. 
18 Laribacter hongkongensis is a recently 
sequenced bacterium associated with invasive blood 
stream infections in patients with liver cirrhosis as 
well as gastroenteritis and traveler's diarrhea. </p>

<p>19 -22 </p>

<p>Updated annotations of these bacterial strains would 
help to understand their pathogenicities and environ-
ment adaptation capacities. </p>

<p>2. Material and methods </p>

<p>2.1 Data source 
Ten complete genomes of the family Neisseriaceae 
were included in this work. They were Chromo-
bacterium violaceum ATCC 12472 (RefSeq accession 
number: NC_005085), L. hongkongensis HLHK9 
(NC_012559), N. gonorrhoeae FA 1090 (NC_002946), 
N. gonorrhoeae NCCP11945 (NC_011035), N. lactamica 
020-06 (NC_014752), N. meningitidis 053442 
(NC_010120), N. meningitidis alpha14 (NC_013016), 
N. meningitidis MC58 (NC_0031112), N. meningitidis 
Z2491 (NC_003116) and Pseudogulbenkiania sp. 
NH8B (NC_016002). Among them, two strains of 
N. gonorrhoeae and four strains of N. meningitidis and 
L. hongkongensis are pathogens. In fact, dozens of strains 
in the family Neisseriaceae have been sequenced. </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>However, the NCBI RefSeq project provides curated anno-
tations only for these strains. 
24 In this work, we chose the 
10 complete genomes to perform re-annotation. </p>

<p>2.2 Method to pick up missed genes 
In each sequenced genome, there are always some 
bona fide genes that have been missed by the original </p>

<p>274 
Gene Re-Annotation in the Neisseriaceae Family 
[Vol. 20, </p>

<p>annotation. For example, Warren et al. 
25 uncovered 
38 895 intergenic open reading frames (ORFs), 
readily identified as putative genes by similarity to 
currently annotated genes, from 1297 prokaryotic 
replicons based on across-genome alignment. New 
genes could be confirmed by the similarity alignment 
or by transcription or proteome analyses. In this work, 
we first used the <rs id="software-1" type="software">ZCURVE</rs> 
26 program, which is freely 
available at <rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://tubic.tju.edu.cn/Zcurve_B</rs>/, to pick 
out all candidate genes that did not have same 5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>terminals with all genes in the original annotation. 
The candidate may overlap one annotated gene with 
their sequences but they did not correspond to the 
same reading frame. Then those candidate new 
genes would be filtered by blast 
27 against the NCBI 
nr database. If one candidate met the following 
three conditions, it would be regarded as genuine 
genes: (i) it had the significant similarity (E-value , 
10 
220 , Coverage . 60% and Identity . 50%) with 
annotated genes in bacteria beyond the same genus 
in the database, and it had the similar length with 
the counterpart (difference , 20%); (ii) it had coun-
terpart in the cluster of orthologous groups (COG) 
database, i.e. it could be assigned within an existed 
COG cluster; (iii) it did not overlap annotated genes 
with any bases or it had a smaller E-value and a 
higher identity score against functional genes in the 
other genomes in the case of overlapping. This 
process has been standardized in this work. For each 
of the 10 strains, all parameters in the whole 
process were fixed. </p>

<p>2.3 Method to eliminate over-annotated genes 
A composition-based method was used to eliminate 
over-annotated genes. The method is based on the 
Z-curve representation of the DNA sequences, which 
has been successfully used to find genes in various 
microbes. 
3,7,9,12,15,16,28,29 In this analysis, 33 Z-curve 
variables were adopted, 
26 including nine variables of 
phase-dependent single-nucleotide frequencies 
28 and 
24 of phase-dependent dinucleotide frequencies. 
26 In 
fact, there are 36 variables denoting phase-dependent 
dinucleotides. 
30 However, long-range correlations 
between the first and third codon positions tend to be 
weaker and so 12 variables associated with them were 
discarded. For details about these variables, refer to 
Guo et al. 
26 Besides 33 classifying features, the 
Fisher linear discrimination algorithm was used to 
optimally differentiate protein-coding and non-coding 
sequences, the procedure was as detailed previously. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>The training set of the classifying model comprised a 
positive sample set and a negative sample set. The posi-
tive sample set was those function-known genes with </p>

<p>definite names, e.g. gyrB as the name of gene encoding 
protein of DNA gyrase subunit B. The negative sample 
was generated by a randomly shuffling sequence of 
the positive sample and thus destroying its natural 
structure. After parameters have been trained based 
on positive and negative samples, all hypothetical pro-
teins would be decided to be genuine genes or falsely 
annotated non-coding sequences. The latter would be 
eliminated in the updated annotation. The scatter plot 
in Figure 1 illustrates the effectiveness of the method 
to eliminate non-coding ORFs from the collection of 
hypothetical proteins. A web server has been con-
structed to check hypothetical genes and eliminate 
non-coding ORFs in any sequenced bacterial or archaeal 
genomes, which is freely available at http://147.8.74. 
24/Zfisher/. </p>

<p>2.4 Method to assign functions to hypothetical proteins 
Hypothetical proteins after refining by the above 
process would be submitted to the nr database. 
Those with highly significant similarities with func-
tion-known genes in the database would be assigned 
the same functions. To achieve more sensitive results, 
amino acid (aa) sequences of hypothetical genes were 
actually aligned against protein sequences translated 
from the nr nucleotide database. 
27 To ensure strict 
homology, the aligned length covered at least 80% 
of each gene with the identity of .70% and the 
E-value of ,1e220. According to the above thresh-
olds, if one hypothetical gene with a translated aa 
sequence matched two or more proteins with the 
same functions, then the function information 
would be transferred to the hypothetical protein. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>2.5 Bacterial strains and growth conditions 
Laribacter hongkongensis HLHK9 is a clinical isolate 
in Hong Kong and its complete genome sequence 
was available recently. 
21 It was grown at 378C, in 
brain heart infusion (BHI) broth or on BHI agar plates 
(BD, USA). Chromobacterium violaceum ATCC 12472 is 
a type strain and its complete genome sequence is 
also available in Genbank. 
31 Chromobacterium viola-
ceum was cultured in nutrient broth or nutrient agar 
(Oxoid, England) at 268C. Unless indicated otherwise, 
bacteria were cultured to the log-phase for experiment 
( 0.6 at OD 600 ). </p>

<p>2.6 Reverse transcription -polymerase chain reaction 
The total bacterial RNA was extracted by using the 
RNeasy mini kit following the manufacturer's instruc-
tions (Qiagen, Germany). Genomic DNA was removed </p>

<p>No. 3] 
F.-B. Guo et al. 
275 </p>

<p>by DNase digestion using RNase-free DNase I (Roche 
Diagnostic, Switzerland) as described by the manufac-
turer. Reverse transcription (RT) was performed using 
Superscript III Reverse Transcriptase (Invitrogen, 
Carlsbad, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer's 
recommendations. One microlitre of cDNA was used 
as a template for RT-polymerase chain reaction 
(PCR) with each specific primer pair. Mock RT-PCR 
without reverse transcriptase was also conducted as 
control. Triplicate assays using RNAs extracted in 
three independent experiments were performed for 
each target gene. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Eliminated non-coding ORFs and the graphic proof 
All ab initio gene finders would predict a certain 
number of non-coding ORFs as potential genes and 
these predictions constitute false positives of gene an-
notation. 
32 To ensure less species-specific genes be 
missed from the annotation result, one or more ab 
initio gene finders are necessary in the process of an-
notating prokaryotic genomes. 
33 Often, similarity 
alignment methods are combined with ab initio 
methods to achieve better results. Because of the </p>

<p>Figure 1. Distribution of GC 2 versus GC 3 for four types of sequences. The x-axis indicates the value of GC 2 and the y-axis denotes the value 
of GC 3 . (A) For 969 function-known genes in L. hongkongensis; (B) for 86 predicted non-coding genes in L. hongkongensis; (C) for 915 
retained hypothetical genes in L. hongkongensis and (D) for 20 horizontally transferred genes in P. aeruginosa. </p>

<p>276 
Gene Re-Annotation in the Neisseriaceae Family 
[Vol. 20, </p>

<p>intervention of the latter, it is not inevitable that some 
non-coding ORFs will appear in the final list of poten-
tial genes in every sequenced genome. 
34 They may 
constitute source of annotation errors of closely 
related genomes and thus should be eliminated 
from the current annotations. According to the 
RefSeq 
24 annotation for each Neisseriaceae strain, all 
annotated genes could be classified into three 
groups. The first group contains only function-
known genes with definite names. The last group 
includes those genes encoding hypothetical proteins. 
The remaining genes constitute the second group. 
Obviously, the first group encodes proteins without 
any uncertainty. Coding potentials of the third group 
would be doubted to some extent. Therefore, we focus 
on the third group, hypothetical genes, in this work. 
Numbers of genes belong to the first and third 
groups and genomic characteristics of each strain 
are listed in Table 1. As can been seen, ratios of the 
numbers of the first and third class genes to the 
total gene number vary significantly. For example, 
N. gonorrhoeae FA 1090 has the highest ratio of hypo-
thetical genes, whereas almost the least ratio of func-
tion-known genes with definite names. This illustrates 
that the function annotation in this strain is much 
poorer compared with the other strains. The variation 
of the gene ratio is associated with many factors, such 
as annotation methods, genomic G þ C contents and 
the number of closely related genomes that have 
been sequenced when annotating the strain. 
The training set needed the Z-curve method with 
33 variables was used to filter over-annotated genes 
from the RefSeq annotations of 10 Neisseriaceae 
strains. For each of them, function-known genes 
with definite names were chosen and shuffled 
sequences were correspondingly generated. Thus, 
the training set was obtained. For example, in L. hon-
gkongensis, the training set was comprised of 969 
function-known genes that correspond to positive 
samples, and 969 shuffled sequences corresponding 
to negative samples. Based on the training set, the dis-
criminant model was built. The accuracy of the model 
based on 5-fold cross-validation is listed in Table 2 for 
each of the 10 strains. With the model, each hypo-
thetical protein was decided to be a genuine gene 
or a falsely predicted ORF. Consequently, 86 hypothet-
ical genes were predicted as a non-coding ORF by the 
Z-curve method in the genome of L. hongkongensis. 
Prediction of 86 hypothetical genes as non-coding 
is based on the assumption that all protein-coding 
genes should have similar nucleotide composition in 
one specific bacterial genome. 
28 That is to say, hypo-
thetical genes should have similar composition fea-
tures with function-known genes in L. hongkongensis. 
If not, they should have been over-annotated as 
genes. The scatter plot of the nucleotide distribution </p>

<p>of 969 function-known genes and 86 predicted 
non-coding ORFs is shown in Figure 1A and B. As 
can be seen, non-coding ORFs are distributed far 
away from function-known genes. In detail, almost 
all function-known genes lie far above the diagonal 
and G þ C contents of them at the second codon posi-
tions are much lower than that at the third codon 
positions, whereas almost all 86 non-coding ORFs 
locate around the diagonal, indicating that their G þ 
C contents at the second positions are approximate 
to that at the third codon positions. The need to 
encode functional proteins exerts severe constrain 
on the nucleotide composition of genes. 
35 Previous 
work showed a similar nucleotide distribution of func-
tional genes in seven high G þ C prokaryotic 
genomes. 
36,37 Therefore, the distinct nucleotide com-
position between 86 hypothetical genes and the 
function-known genes draw them away from being 
genuine genes. Nucleotide compositions for the 915 
retained hypothetical genes are shown in Figure 1C. 
Different from 86 predicted non-coding ORFs, most 
of the retained hypothetical genes have a similar dis-
tribution of GC 2 versus GC 3 with function-known 
genes. 
The COG database has been widely used during the an-
notation process of sequenced bacterial genomes. </p>

<p>5,38 </p>

<p>Belonging to a COG is believed to be a very reliable evi-
dence of protein-coding genes. 
38,39 In L. hongkongensis, 
954 among 967 function-known genes have been 
assigned a COG code. However, only 1 of 86 predicted 
non-coding ORFs has the COG code. Based on the 
above analyses, these 86 ORFs are very unlikely to 
encode proteins. COG statistics information for the 
other nine strains is shown in Table 2. As can been 
seen, the COG ratio of predicted non-coding ORFs is ex-
tremely lower than that of genes with known functions 
and definite names. Summarily, 7260 among 7426 
(97.8%) genes belonging to the first class are assigned 
with COG codes in the 10 Neisseriaceae genomes. In 
comparison, only 5 of 418 (1.2%) predicted non-
coding ORFs could be assigned to the COG database, in-
dicating that our prediction is much accurate in another 
sense. These five ORFs with COG codes are likely to con-
stitute falsely predictions of our method because having 
COG counterparts has been believed to be one of the 
reliable evidences of encoding proteins. Finally, we 
only eliminated the remaining 413 hypothetical pro-
teins from the RefSeq annotations in the 10 complete 
genomes. Details of them are listed in Supplementary 
Table S1. 
As is well known, horizontally transferred genes 
may also have a different nucleotide composition 
with core genes to some extent. The DarkHorse data-
base stores horizontally transferred genes in 
sequenced bacterial genomes. Entries in it are all 
those predicted by comparative genomes methods </p>

<p>No. 3] 
F.-B. Guo et al. 
277 </p>

<p>and hence are very reliable. However, the information 
of HGT is not available for L. hongkongensis in the 
DarkHorse. To circumvent this problem, we fall back 
on the bacterial strain Pseudomonas aeruginosa PA01, 
which also has a high G þ C content, and the distribu-
tion of GC 2 versus GC 3 for function-known genes has 
shown to be similar to that of L. hongkongensis. </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>Furthermore, as an early sequenced genome, the 
gene annotation of it is very reliable and so could be 
used a good reference. For the genome, 22 horizon-
tally transferred genes were extracted from the 
DarkHorse. As can be seen from Figure 1D, the nu-
cleotide distribution of horizontally transferred </p>

<p>genes tends to be similar to that in Figure 1A. 
Although the DarkHorse genes have basically similar 
nucleotide compositions with function-known genes, 
it does not mean the 86 ORFs in Figure 1B are all def-
initely non-coding. In fact, there may still be the pos-
sibility that some of the genes, particularly those with 
GC 2 between 0.3 and 0.6, are falsely predicted as 
non-coding because of their very recent transfers. To 
investigate the possibility of clusters of horizontally 
transferred genes, we checked the chromosomal loca-
tions of these 86 ORFs and found that they not have 
any cluster pattern. Therefore, it is sure that, at least, 
most of the 85 eliminated ORFs do not belong to </p>

<p>Table 1. Statistical information in genomes of the 10 Neisseriaceae strains </p>

<p>Strains 
Published 
year </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Gene 
density 
(kb) </p>

<p>Genome size 
(bp) </p>

<p>Gene 
number </p>

<p>G þ C 
content (%) </p>

<p>First class gene 
(ratio) </p>

<p>Third class gene 
(ratio) </p>

<p>C. violaceum 
18 September 
2003 </p>

<p>0.927 
4 751 080 
4405 
64.8 
1494 (33.9%) 
1714 (38.9%) </p>

<p>L. hongkongensis 
14 April 2009 1.021 
3 169 329 
3235 
62.4 
969 (30.0%) 
1001 (30.1%) </p>

<p>N. gonorrhoeae FA 
1090 </p>

<p>15 February 
2005 </p>

<p>0.930 
2 153 922 
2002 
52.7 
266 (13.3%) 
800 (40.0%) </p>

<p>N. gonorrhoeae 
NCCP11945 </p>

<p>9 July 2008 
1.195 
2 232 025 
2668 
52.4 
244 (9.1%) 
996 (37.3%) </p>

<p>N. lactamica 
16 December 
2010 </p>

<p>0.888 
2 220 606 
1972 
52.3 
744 (37.7%) 
657 (33.3%) </p>

<p>N. meningitidis 
053442 </p>

<p>3 December 
2007 </p>

<p>0.938 
2 153 416 
2020 
51.7 
875 (43.3%) 
645 (31.9%) </p>

<p>N. meningitidis Alpha 
14 </p>

<p>24 July 2009 
0.872 
2 145 295 
1872 
52.0 
865 (46.2%) 
467 (25.0%) </p>

<p>N. meningitidis MC58 
10 March 
2000 </p>

<p>0.908 
2 272 360 
2063 
51.5 
806 (39.1%) 
810 (39.3%) </p>

<p>N. meningitidis Z2491 30 March 
2000 </p>

<p>0.874 
2 184 406 
1909 
51.8 
459 (24.0%) 
669 (35.0%) </p>

<p>Pseudogulbenkiania 
8 September 
2011 </p>

<p>0.926 
4 332 995 
4012 
64.4 
704 (17.5%) 
831 (20.7%) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Information of published date were extracted from http://www.genomesonline.org/. </p>

<p>Table 2. Accuracy based on 5-fold cross-validation and the COG ratio in each strain </p>

<p>Strain 
Accuracy of the method (%) 
Class 1 with COG 
(% ratio) </p>

<p>Predicted 
non-coding ORFs </p>

<p>Predicted non-coding 
with COG (% ratio) </p>

<p>C. violaceum 
100 
1457 (97.5) 
88 
0 (0) </p>

<p>L. hongkongensis 
99.90 
954 (98.7) 
86 
1 (1.2) </p>

<p>N. gonorrhoeae FA 1090 
100 
263 (98.9) 
24 
1 (4.2) </p>

<p>N. gonorrhoeae NCCP11945 
100 
241 (98.9) 
56 
0 (0) </p>

<p>N. lactamica 
99.87 
725 (97.4) 
8 
0 (0) </p>

<p>N. meningitidis 053442 
99.77 
851 (97.3) 
37 
1 (2.7) </p>

<p>N. meningitidis Alpha 14 
99.77 
840 (97.1) 
25 
1 (4.0) </p>

<p>N. meningitidis MC58 
99.75 
790 (98.0) 
48 
0 (0) </p>

<p>N. meningitidis Z2491 
100 
456 (99.3) 
12 
0 (0) </p>

<p>Pseudogulbenkiania 
99.86 
683 (97.0) 
34 
1 (2.9) </p>

<p>278 
Gene Re-Annotation in the Neisseriaceae Family 
[Vol. 20, </p>

<p>horizontally transferred genes and are indeed non-
coding. Also note that 11 of the 20 horizontally trans-
ferred genes have been assigned the COG code and 
this ratio is much higher than that of the collective 
of the 85 eliminated ORFs. </p>

<p>3.2. Missed genes found by joint methods and their 
functions 
During the process of annotating sequenced 
genomes, some genuine genes may be missed 
because the annotators pursue a balance between 
the number of all annotated genes and that of 
finding genuine genes and ensure not too high 
falsely positive predictions. 
14,25,40 The method for 
picking up missed genes was a two-step process by 
combining the ab initio gene finding and the blast 
search. With this method, we found a varying 
number of missed genes with potential functions 
(Table 3). For example, eight new genes were added 
in L. hongkongensis, and details for them are listed in 
Table 4. RT-PCR analyses validated the transcriptions 
of all eight sequences (Fig. 2). Out of the 10 newly 
found genes in the genome of C. violaceum, transcrip-
tions of eight ones are validated with RT-PCR and the 
exceptions are (Table 6) CV_A0007 and CV_A0010 
(Fig. 3). All the amplification with genome DNA was 
positive (data not shown). Therefore, transcriptional 
analyses illustrated that the method was effective for 
picking up new genes and had very high accuracy. 
However, this method is only applicable to picking 
up genes having homologues in other genomes but 
not to strain-specific genes. In the other genomes, </p>

<p>the method was directly used and without experi-
mental validation. 
Among the eight new genes in L. hongkongensis, 
only two do not have any overlapping bases with 
annotated genes and they are LHK_A0003 and 
LHK_A0004. The details of the eight genes and their 
corresponding functions and the details of PCR 
primers and conditions used in the validation experi-
ments are listed in Tables 4 and 5, respectively. For 
each of the remaining six overlapping genes, the 
region spanned by the two PCR primers does not 
overlap with the annotated genes and thus could 
reduce false-positive errors for the transcription trace. 
The six genes are analyzed as follows. LHK_A0001 
overlaps the annotated gene LHK_00511. According 
to the annotation, the two sequences have the same 
potential function of encoding the phosphoserine 
phosphatase. LHK_A0001 has the similarity score of 
the E-value of 10 
249 and Identity of 55% and the simi-
larity score of LHK_00511 is the E-value of 10 
239 and 
Identity of 65%. We could not decide which of them is 
the genuine gene based on the scores. LHK_00511 
has the length of only 211 bp, which is much shorter 
than the length ( 669 bp) of known genes with the 
same function in other genomes. LHK_A0001 has 
the length of 471 bp. Based on the length information, 
LHK_A0001 is more likely to encode the phosphoser-
ine phosphatase than LHK_00511. LHK_A0002 over-
laps the annotated gene LHK_00916 with only 
29 bp. LHK_A0002 is predicted to code for site-specific 
recombinase and LHK_00916 encodes replicase. 
Because they have so little overlap and have different 
functions, it is very likely that they are both genuine 
genes. LHK_A0005 has the potential function of en-
coding the Na 
þ -dependent transporter. LHK_A0006 
overlaps 61 bp with one functional gene but they 
locate on two different DNA strands. LHK_A0007 
and the annotated rpsI gene (LHK_02777) constitute 
an interesting overlap. After the blast alignment, both 
of them are found to be significantly similar to the 
rpsI gene in the other genomes. As shown in 
Figure 4, LHK_A0007 matches the last 141 bp 
(57 aa) of the other rpsI genes and LHK_02777 
matches the first 219 bp (73 aa). LHK_A0007 and 
LHK_02777 as a whole just constitute a complete 
rpsI gene (130 aa). In fact, LHK_A0007 and LHK_ 
02777 are adjacent and overlapping. For the overlap-
ping part, LHK_A0007 has the correct reading frame 
but the LHK_02777 does not have the correct frame, 
according to the other rpsI genes. Therefore, it is 
suggested that there has appeared an event of 
nucleotide insertion/deletion for the rpsI gene in 
L. hongkongensis. After point mutation, the single 
reading frame changed to two different ORFs. In this 
work, the two generated segments could be tran-
scribed and should have functions. But we do not </p>

<p>Table 3. Numbers of revised genes, which contains newly found 
genes, hypothetical genes with newly assigned functions, 
eliminated ORFs and disrupted ORFs </p>

<p>Strains 
Newly 
found 
genes </p>

<p>Newly 
assigned 
functions </p>

<p>Eliminated 
ORFs </p>

<p>Disrupted 
ORFs </p>

<p>C. violaceum 
10 
120 
88 
0 </p>

<p>L. hongkongensis 
8 
2 0 
8 5 
2 </p>

<p>N. gonorrhoeae FA 
1090 </p>

<p>18 
400 
23 
23 </p>

<p>N. gonorrhoeae 
NCCP11945 </p>

<p>9 
207 
56 
0 </p>

<p>N. lactamica 
5 
218 
8 
8 </p>

<p>N. meningitidis 
053442 </p>

<p>6 
214 
36 
19 </p>

<p>N. meningitidis 
Alpha 14 </p>

<p>30 
214 
24 
14 </p>

<p>N. meningitidis 
MC58 </p>

<p>11 
331 
48 
27 </p>

<p>N. meningitidis 
Z2491 </p>

<p>8 
299 
12 
20 </p>

<p>Pseudogulbenkiania 
1 
4 6 
3 3 
0 </p>

<p>No. 3] 
F.-B. Guo et al. 
279 </p>

<p>know whether they have the same function of encod-
ing ribosomal protein S9. Finally, LHK_A0008 has pos-
sible function of coding for thioesterase. </p>

<p>For the 10 newly found potential genes in C. viola-
ceum, there are not so serious cases of overlapping 
with annotated genes as in L. hongkongensis. Either </p>

<p>Figure 2. RT-PCR confirmations of eight newly found genes in L. hongkongensis. mRNAs corresponding to candidate genes were evaluated 
by RT-PCR (RT). We used no transcriptase-containing sample as negative control (NRT) and PCR with genomic DNA as a positive control </p>

<p>(PC). </p>

<p>Table 5. PCR primers and annealing temperature for the eight newly found genes in L. hongkongensis </p>

<p>ID 
Primer pair 
Primer sequence 
Annealing temperature </p>

<p>LHK_A0001 
LPW20036 
LPW20037 </p>

<p>GCATGCCGAATTCCTCGAAG 
TCCGGGCCTTCTTCCAGTTC </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>LHK_A0002 
LPW20038 
LPW20039 </p>

<p>ACGCGCTTTGATTCGGGAAC 
GCGTTCGCATAACCGTACAG </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>LHK_A0003 
LPW20046 
LPW20047 </p>

<p>TGGCCAATCCGATCGTGAC 
CCTCCTGAGCGTTTCAAG </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>LHK_A0004 
LPW19946 
LPW19947 </p>

<p>ATTCATCCGTCGTGGCTAAG 
TGACCACAAGCAGCCACATC </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>LHK_A0005 
LPW19950 
LPW19951 </p>

<p>TGGGCGCCATGATCACCTAC 
CGGCAGGCATGGTGATGAAG </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>LHK_A0006 
LPW19952 
LPW19953 </p>

<p>TGGCGCTTCATCCGCATCAC 
TCCGGCATCAGTACCGAGAC </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>LHK_A0007 
LPW20545 
LPW20546 </p>

<p>CATCACCCGTGCCCTGAT 
CTTGGAGAACTGCTTGCG </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>LHK_A0008 
LPW20048 
LPW20049 </p>

<p>CTGACACCCGGTGCAGTTTC 
CTGGCGTAATCCACCCAGAC </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>Table 4. Details of the eight newly found genes in the genome of L. hongkongensis </p>

<p>ID 
Position 
COG 
Coverage, E-value, 
Identity </p>

<p>Potential function </p>

<p>LHK_A0001 476554 -477024 (þ) 
COG0560E 92%, 1e249, 55% 
Phosphoserine phosphatase </p>

<p>LHK_A0002 880771 -881358 (þ) 
COG1961L 97%, 2e272, 60% 
Site-specific recombinases </p>

<p>LHK_A0003 1391850-1392488 (2) 
COG2869C 98%, 6e266, 51% 
Naþ-transporting nicotinamide adenine 
dinucleotide </p>

<p>LHK_A0004 1570970-1571566 (þ) 
COG2864C 100%, 1e2110, 81% 
Thiosulphate reductase cytochrome subunit B </p>

<p>LHK_A0005 1848723-1850306 (2) 
COG0733R 63%, 3e2156, 73% 
Naþ-dependent transporters of the sodium: 
neurotransmitter symporter family </p>

<p>LHK_A0006 2282651-2283334 (þ) 
COG0778C 77%, 3e273, 66% 
Putative Cob(II)yrinic acid a,c-diamide reductase 
(BluB) </p>

<p>LHK_A0007 2660234-2660422 (2) 
COG0103J 96%, 2e228, 88% 
Ribosomal protein S9 </p>

<p>LHK_A0008 2875641-2876057 (2) 
COG0824R 91%, 7e255, 64% 
Predicted thioesterase </p>

<p>280 
Gene Re-Annotation in the Neisseriaceae Family 
[Vol. 20, </p>

<p>Table 6. Details of the 10 newly found genes in the genome of C. violaceum </p>

<p>ID 
Position 
COG 
Coverage, E-value, 
Identity </p>

<p>Potential function </p>

<p>CV_A0001 486035 -487360 (þ) 
COG0845Q 
100%, 0, 72% 
Membrane-fusion protein </p>

<p>CV_A0002 487503 -489461 (þ) 
COG0750M 
100%, 0, 71% 
Membrane-associated Zn-dependent proteases </p>

<p>CV_A0003 1025430-1025810 
(þ) </p>

<p>COG3536S 
89%, 4e267, 83% 
Uncharacterized bacterial conserved region (BCR) </p>

<p>CV_A0004 1026544-1027152 
(þ) </p>

<p>COG3165S 
95%, 6e288, 66% 
Uncharacterized BCR </p>

<p>CV_A0005 1956990-1958684 
(þ) </p>

<p>COG0654HC 88%, 3e2177, 53% 
2-polyprenyl-6-methoxyphenol hydroxylase </p>

<p>CV_A0006 2305072-2305416 
(2) </p>

<p>COG3628R 
99%, 4e253, 71% 
Phage baseplate assembly protein </p>

<p>CV_A0007 2362585-2363220 
(2) </p>

<p>COG0693R 
92%, 1e270, 54% 
Intracellular protease/amidase </p>

<p>CV_A0008 4207595-4208386 
(þ) </p>

<p>COG0614P 
85%, 6e294, 67% 
ABC-type cobalamin/Fe3þ-siderophores transport 
systems </p>

<p>CV_A0009 4462117-4463199 
(2) </p>

<p>COG0438M 
96%, 5e2137, 62% 
Predicted glycosyltransferases </p>

<p>CV_A0010 4588140-4588436 
(2) </p>

<p>COG1872S 
98%, 3e247, 75% 
Uncharacterized ancient conserved region </p>

<p>Figure 3. RT-PCR confirmations of newly found potential genes in C. violaceum. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Matching relationship of aa sequences encoded by LHK_02777 and LHK_A0007 with the RpsI protein in the genome of 
Pseudogulbenkiania. The plot is adapted from the result generated by the NCBI blast application. In the search, the query is 
LHK_02777 and LHK_A0007, respectively, whereas the rpsI protein constitutes the subject. </p>

<p>No. 3] 
F.-B. Guo et al. 
281 </p>

<p>the overlapping part is shorter than 15 bp or the over-
lapping gene is annotated as hypothetical protein that 
has not significant similarity with known genes in the 
public database. Details of the 10 genes and their cor-
responding functions and the details of PCR primers 
and conditions used in the validation experiments 
are listed in Tables 6 and 7, respectively. The two 
negative samples with RT-PCR analysis may consti-
tute falsely positive predictions of our method, or 
alternatively, they are expressed only in special 
conditions. 
In the other nine Neisseriaceae strains, there were 
also newly found genes with potential functions. In 
N. gonorrhoeae FA 1090, only 1 of 18 newly added 
genes overlaps the annotated genes and the overlap-
ping part is 20 bp. Among the 18 genes, the function 
information of four are so detailed to have definite 
gene names and they encode thiol:disulfide inter-
change protein DsbD, sulphate ABC transporter 
permease protein CysU, 23S rRNA (guanosine-2 
0 -O-)-
methyltransferase RlmB and septum site-determining 
protein MinD, respectively. In N. gonorrhoeae 
NCCP11945, nine new genes are found. Among 
them, five do not overlap annotated genes. Four of 
the five genes have putative important function 
based on very high similarity and they encode tran-
scription antiterminator (Nusg), 30S ribosomal 
protein S14 (RpsN), 30S ribosomal protein L30 
(RpmD) and translation initiation factor IF-1 (InfA). 
In N. lactamica, none of the five newly added genes 
overlap annotated genes. Among them, three encode </p>

<p>DNA transport competence protein (ComeA), one 
encodes transposases and one encodes the TonB-
dependent receptor. In Pseudogulbenkiania, only one 
gene is added. Interestingly, this gene has the same 5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>terminal with the annotated gene (NH8B_2210) but 
they do not have the same stop codon. The 
NH8B_2210 is much longer than the newly added 
one and they have the same reading frame. 
According to the RefSeq annotation for NH8B_2210, 
the original authors seemed to have predicted that 
there is a stop codon treated as the selenocystein 
codon. By blast against the public database, the 
newly added gene is shown to be a more reliable pre-
diction because it has the same length with counter-
parts in distantly related species where as the 
annotated does not. 
In the four strains of N. meningitidis, from 6 to 30 
new genes were added and very few of them overlap 
the annotated genes. The strain alpha14 N. meningiti-
dis has the most found new genes and interestingly 
27 among the 30 new genes encode transposases. 
Although their aa identities with known transposases 
in genomes beyond the Neisseria genus tend to be just 
slightly higher than 50%, the identity is higher than 
80% for each of them with counterparts in the same 
genus. Furthermore, the coverage at each case is 
greater than 90%. Therefore, predicted functions of 
encoding transposases for the 27 new genes are reli-
able. According to the RefSeq annotation, none of 
the genes code for transposases in this strain. 
However, 55, 29 and 33 transposases have been 
annotated in the other three strains of N. meningitidis. 
The lower sensitivity of the ab initio gene finder used 
in the annotation of N. meningitidis alpha14 is sug-
gested to be responsible for the missing of transpo-
sases. In fact, some of transposases, which aid the 
integration insertion of genomic islands or single hori-
zontally transferred gene, tend to own abnormal nu-
cleotide composition and are easily missed by 
composition-based programmes. 
41 In addition, some 
genes with important functions have been added in 
the N. meningitidis genomes, such as the haemoglobin 
receptor in 053442, transcription elongation factor 
(greA) in alpha14, protein methyltransferase (hemK) 
in Z2491, leucyl aminopeptidase ( pepA) and allopha-
nate hydrolase subunit 2 in MC58. Details of the 106 
newly found genes in the 10 Neisseriaceae strains are 
listed in Supplementary Table S2. </p>

<p>3.3. Hypothetical proteins with newly assigned 
functions 
For the genomes sequenced several years ago, func-
tional information may be outdated. 
16,29 Especially, 
some hypothetical genes may have functional coun-
terparts in current databases, 
16 whereas they are </p>

<p>Table 7. PCR primers and annealing temperature for the 10 
newly found potential genes in C. violaceum </p>

<p>ID Primer pair Primer sequence 
Annealing 
temperature </p>

<p>1 
LPW21817 
LPW21818 </p>

<p>CTGGCATTGACCGATGAC 
CGAAGCGTTGGGATACAG </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>2 
LPW21819 
LPW21820 </p>

<p>CTGTATCGCCTGGTGTTG 
GCCCTTGCTCTGCAAATC </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>3 
LPW21821 
LPW21822 </p>

<p>TGCCCATGTCAGGACTTG 
GAGCTTGTCCAGGTATTG </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>4 
LPW21823 
LPW21824 </p>

<p>GATTTGTCGCGGGTGTTC 
GAAGCGTTGAACCAGATG </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>5 
LPW21825 
LPW21826 </p>

<p>CATGAGGTTAGCCCTTTC 
GCCATCGACGAAATACAG </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>6 
LPW21827 
LPW21828 </p>

<p>CAGTGCATCCGCATCATC 
GCTCCCATTGCCGAATAG </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>7 
LPW21829 
LPW21830 </p>

<p>CAGGAAGACCTGTCTTAC 
CTGGCAAAGTCCTCTTCC </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>8 
LPW21835 
LPW21836 </p>

<p>CGCAGCTGAAGCAGCTGAAG 
CGGCTTGAAACCGTTGAG </p>

<p>48 </p>

<p>9 
LPW21837 
LPW21838 </p>

<p>TTGAGCTACGGCATAGAC 
GCCAGCCGTTTCAGATTC </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>10 LPW21839 
LPW21840 </p>

<p>CGTCTGACGCTGCATGTG 
GTCGCCGGACAACAATTC </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>282 
Gene Re-Annotation in the Neisseriaceae Family 
[Vol. 20, </p>

<p>still annotated as hypothetical. This section is aiming 
to provide functional information for hypothetical 
genes in the 10 Neisseriaceae strains by using the 
similarity search method. To ensure reliable function 
transfer, severe homologous conditions were 
adopted. After the blast search, varying numbers of 
hypothetical proteins were assigned functions in the 
10 Neisseriaceae genomes (Table 3). Among them, 
L. hongkongensis and Pseudogulbenkiania have the 
least numbers perhaps because their genomes were 
most recently sequenced. In the two strains of the 
N. gonorrhoeae, the strain FA 1090 has the larger 
number of assigned functions and it just was 
sequenced earlier than NCCP11945. 
23,42 Among 
the four strains of the species, N. meningitidis MC58 
has the largest number and it just was sequenced 
earliest among them. 
23 Therefore, the number of 
hypothetical proteins with newly assigned functions 
may be tightly associated with sequenced time of 
the genome. In fact, if one genome has been 
sequenced at earlier year, it should have more func-
tional counterparts in the current public database 
but not existed at that time. 
29 The original annotation 
would be more outdated for earlier sequenced 
genome in the sense of function information. 
Among newly assigned functions, some have been 
provided definite names (Table 8) and this transferred 
annotation information should be unquestionable. 
For example, the hypothetical gene LHK_02863 in 
L. hongkongensis has been assigned not only the func-
tion encoding iron-sulphur cluster assembly protein 
but also the definite name 'IscA'. Some other genes 
were assigned with detailed functions and would be 
reliable with this function because stringent homolo-
gous criteria were adopted. However, there are still 
some hypothetical proteins with only general 
functions, such as membrane proteins, lipoproteins 
and periplasmic proteins (Table 8). This type of 
rough function information would give help for 
the determination of more detailed functions. </p>

<p>Interestingly, the number of assigned membrane pro-
teins tends to be larger than periplasmic proteins and 
much larger than lipoproteins in most cases (Table 8). 
It is suggested that this information corresponds to 
their natural ranks existing in the genome. Details of 
assigned functions for each of the 10 Neisseriaceae 
strains are listed in Supplementary Table S3. </p>

<p>3.4. Disrupted ORFs 
During the process of genome re-annotation for the 
10 Neisseriaceae strains, we found an interesting phe-
nomenon. In a specific genome, two adjacent ORFs, 
which are predicted as genes by the <rs type="software">ZCURVE</rs> 
program, have the same function with known genes 
in the other species. The total length of the two 
ORFs just corresponds to that of the known counter-
parts or just a little different from them. Based on 
similarity scores, both of the two ORFs should be pre-
dicted as genes with the corresponding function. 
However, either of them is much shorter than the 
functional counterpart and could not constitute a 
homologue in the sense of length information. 
Perrodou et al. 
43 stated that unrecognized frameshifts, 
in-frame stop codons and sequencing errors often led 
to interrupted coding sequences. Very recently, 
Sharma et al. 
44 performed a pilot study on bacterial 
genes with disrupted ORFs. Their results indicated 
that many disrupted genes likely utilized the non-
standard decoding mechanisms: programmed riboso-
mal frameshifting and programmed transcriptional 
realignment. Given that our recognized adjacent 
ORFs have identical functions, they should originate 
from the disruption of a longer gene by a frameshift 
or an in-frame stop codon and rarely by the sequen-
cing error. Numbers of disrupted ORFs are listed 
in Table 3 and details of them are illustrated in 
Supplementary Table S4. Totally, 111 disrupted 
ORFs (or partial genes) were identified in six strains 
of the genus Neisseria and two in L. hongkongensis. </p>

<p>Table 8. Among hypothetical gene with assigned functions, the numbers of genes with definite names, those encoding membrane 
proteins, lipoproteins and periplasmic proteins </p>

<p>Strains 
With definite name 
Membrane protein 
Lipoprotein 
Periplasmic protein 
C. violaceum 
29 
5 
1 
1 </p>

<p>L. hongkongensis 
9 
3 
0 
0 </p>

<p>N. gonorrhoeae FA 1090 
105 
72 
25 
31 </p>

<p>N. gonorrhoeae NCCP11945 
34 
25 
6 
8 </p>

<p>N. lactamica 
39 
25 
6 
21 </p>

<p>N. meningitidis 053442 
30 
21 
4 
19 </p>

<p>N. meningitidis Alpha 14 
19 
67 
16 
26 </p>

<p>N. meningitidis MC58 
47 
77 
26 
17 </p>

<p>N. meningitidis Z2491 
78 
33 
8 
18 </p>

<p>Pseudogulbenkiania 
7 
9 
5 
0 </p>

<p>No. 3] 
F.-B. Guo et al. 
283 </p>

<p>According to Sharma et al., 
44 some of the disrupted 
ORFs still encode proteins. Consistent with this, 
both of the disrupted ORFs LHK_A0007 (newly 
predicted) and LHK_02777 (originally annotated) 
are found to be transcribed in L. hongkongensis cells 
by the PCR experiment. Further wet experiment on 
functions of the other disrupted ORFs would be 
interesting. </p>

<p>4. Discussions </p>

<p>The genome annotation would be outdated with 
the functional information when several years 
passed since the sequencing. Latest database may 
contain new functional genes which were not yet 
assigned functional information when the analyzed 
genome was sequenced. 
29 Those newly added func-
tional information would provide the source of func-
tion transfer for some hypothetical genes in the 
analyzed genome. Sometimes, a few genes missed 
by the original annotation may be found with the 
similarity alignment. 
25 In this work, a total of 2069 
hypothetical genes were assigned with general or 
detailed functions based on homology search 
against latest database. Among the 10 Neisseriaceae 
strains, N. gonorrhoeae FA 1090 and N. meningitidis 
MC58 and Z2491 were sequenced and annotated 
earlier. 
23 Correspondingly, the numbers of newly 
assigned functions in them are the largest. 
Therefore, the time from the sequencing is longer 
and the function annotation is more likely to be out-
dated. As for newly found genes, all 10 strains except 
N. meningitidis alpha14 contain a small number. In 
fact, it is rather difficult to find genes missed by the 
original annotation using the similarity-based 
method. When annotating the genome originally, pre-
dicted genes, particularly those having similar coun-
terparts, would be retained as far as possible. 
Therefore, newly identified genes usually are only 
those having counterparts newly added in the data-
base. As an exception, as many as 30 genes were 
newly found in the strain of N. meningitidis 
alpha14 and 27 of them correspond to transpo-
sases. We speculate that the less sensitivity of the 
ab initio programme, which has been used in the ori-
ginal annotation, for the external genes leads to the 
missing of the 27 genes associated with insertion 
function. 
Besides the published date, the quality of the origin-
al annotation is another determining factor of the 
extent of errors. 
33 As an example, N. gonorrhoeae 
NCCP11945 has the highest gene density according 
to the RefSeq annotations among the seven Neisseria 
strains. Correspondingly, the largest number of hypo-
thetical genes has been excluded from this strain. </p>

<p>When annotating this genome, only one ab initio 
gene finder was used. 
42 Usually, two or more ab 
initio programmes are used in annotating the other 
bacterial genomes. Based on the very abnormal 
gene density of the strain, we suppose that there 
may still be non-coding ORFs, besides the 56 ones 
excluded by us. Besides the annotation method and 
sequencing time, some other factors also cause the 
different extent of errors. For example, genes in high 
G þ C bacterial genomes are shown to be difficultly 
predicted with high accuracy and this is caused by 
the fact that many long ORFs appear in this type of 
genomes. 
32 In addition, the genome could be diffi-
cultly predicted accurately if there are only distantly 
related species in the public databases. </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>We should note that there still probably are non-
coding ORFs and missed genes after the present 
updated annotation in the 10 Neisseriaceae strains. 
To assure reliable results, we picked up only those 
sequences with very higher similarities when identify-
ing missed genes and we used the method with lower 
specificity when excluding non-coding ORFs. In add-
ition, some thoroughly new genes, which have not sig-
nificant similarities with any known genes, may be 
found by combing ab initio programme and wet ex-
perimental validation. However, the 106 newly 
found genes are those having similar counterparts 
based on latest databases. Also note that different 
detailed methods may be used to check the annota-
tions of the other bacterial genomes, although the 
present systematic method has shown to be effective 
and reliable. For example, the recently developed ab 
initio gene finder <rs type="software">Prodigal</rs>, 
32 which has lower false 
positives could replace or jointly used with <rs id="software-6" type="software">ZCURVE</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">1.0</rs>. Here, we used only the latter because the use of 
both of them generates basically consistent results 
(data not shown). The <rs type="software">RPGM</rs> program, 
39 which is 
also based on the graphical representation of the 
DNA sequence, could be chosen as an alternative to 
eliminate non-coding ORFs. </p>

<p>Supplementary data: Supplementary Data are 
available at www.dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements: The authors are grateful to 
the editor and the anonymous reviewers for their 
valuable suggestions and comments, which has led to 
the improvement of this article. We thank Mr Zhong-
Shan Cheng for helpful discussions. We also thank 
Miss Annette Y. P. Wong for helps in constructing the 
website.: Conflict of Interest statement. None declared. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Hong Kong 
Scholars Program (XJ2011005), National Natural </p>

<p>284 
Gene Re-Annotation in the Neisseriaceae Family 
[Vol. 20, </p>

<p>Science Foundation of China (31071109) and the 
programme for New Century Excellent Talents in 
University (NCET-11-0059). </p>



</text></tei>