<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3785600" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:41+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background Ever since lipoabdominoplasty was first developed to achieve better aesthetic 
outcomes and less morbidity, the rate of seroma formation, especially in obese patients, has 
disturbed plastic surgeons. The aim of this study was to evaluate the effect of fibrin sealant 
in the prevention of seroma formation after lipoabdominoplasty in obese patients. 
Methods Sixty patients with a body mass index (BMI) between 30 and 39.9 were assigned 
randomly to 1 of 2 groups (30 patients each). Group A underwent lipoabdominoplasty with 
fibrin glue, while group B underwent traditional lipoabdominoplasty; both had closed suction 
drainage applied to the abdomen. The patients' demographics and postoperative complications 
were recorded. Seroma was detected using abdominal ultrasound examinations at two postop 
erative periods: between postoperative days 10 and 12 and, between postoperative days 18 
and 21. 
Results The age range was 31 to 55 years (38.5 ± 9.5 years) in group A and 25 to 58 years 
(37.8 ± 9.1 years) in group B, while the mean BMI was 31.4 to 39.9 kg/m 
2 (32.6 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) in group 
A and 32.7 to 37.4 kg/m 
2 (31.5 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) in group B. In group A, the patients had a complication 
rate of 10% in group A versus 43% in group B (P &lt; 0.05). The incidence of seroma formation 
was 3% in the fibrin glue group but 37% in the lipoabdominoplastyalone group (P &lt; 0.05). 
Conclusions Lipoabdominoplasty with the use of autologous fibrin sealant is a very effective 
method that significantly reduces the rate of postoperative seroma. </p>

<p>Keywords Seroma prevention / Lipoabdominoplasty / Autologous fibrin sealant / Fibrin tissue 
adhesive / Obesity </p>

<p>Received: 11 Mar 2013 • Revised: 29 May 2013 • Accepted: 30 May 2013 
pISSN: 22346163 • eISSN: 22346171 • http://dx.doi.org/10.5999/aps.2013.40.5.621 • Arch Plast Surg 2013;40:621626 </p>

<p>This article was presented at the 41st 
Annual International Congress of 
the Egyptian Society of Plastic and 
Reconstructive Surgeons in on October 
27-30, 2011 in Sharm El Sheikh, Egypt. </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant 
to this article was reported. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>



<p>Mabrouk AA et al. Fibrin sealant and lipoabdominoplasty </p>

<p>Demographic 
Fibrin sealant 
Traditional 
lipoabdominoplasty </p>

<p>Number 
30 
30 
Age (yr) 
31-55 
25-58 
Body mass index 
31.4-39.9 
32.7-37.4 </p>

<p>Table 1. Patient data for each of the 2 groups </p>

<p>of compression garments during the postoperative period [5,6]. 
Tissue adhesives have been used to provoke adhesion of the 
surfaces in many surgical situations and have assisted in reduc-
ing the need for drainage and minimizing the rate of postopera-
tive seroma [7,8]. 
Most of the studies that have been performed concerning 
postoperative seroma have included only individuals with nor-
mal body mass index (BMI) scores. Therefore, in our study we 
performed lipoabdominoplasty on obese grade 1 and 2 patients 
using fibrin glue, to augment previous studies searching for bio-
logical sealants to decrease the rate of seroma formation. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>The study was carried out over a period of 3 years. Sixty patients 
were included with a predominance of women (women, 58; 
men, 2). Thirty patients underwent lipoabdominoplasty with 
the use of autologous fibrin glue, and the other 30 patients 
underwent traditional lipoabdominoplasty. All of the patients 
had Rohrich type IV B deformities [9] (significant skin and fat 
excess with diastasis of the rectus muscle), and their BMI scores 
were equal to or greater than 30 and less than 40 (i.e., obese grade 
1 and 2 according to the International Classification of Adult 
Underweight, Overweight and Obesity according to BMI de-
veloped by the WHO) [10]. 
The patients' ages ranged between 31 and 55 years (38.5 ± 9.5) 
in the fibrin glue group and ranged between 25 and 58 years 
(37.8 ± 9.1) in the traditional lipoabdominoplasty group. The 
BMI scores of the patients undergoing fibrin glue application 
ranged from 31.4 to 39.9, with an average of 32.6. In the patients 
who underwent traditional lipoabdominoplasty, the BMI ranged 
from 32.7 to 37.4, with an average of 31.5 (Table 1). 
Smokers and patients with a history of diabetes, cardiac prob-
lems and vascular diseases, previous abdominal surgery, or com-
plaints of umbilical or paraumbilical hernias, or who had experi-
enced significant weight loss were excluded from the study. 
The surgical technique was performed similarly in both groups 
except for the fibrin sealant application: 1) Marking was done 
first by drawing a 12-cm horizontal supra-pubic line that was 7 cm 
from the vulvar commissure. Two oblique lines of 10 cm each 
were drawn in the direction of the iliac crest; then the liposuc-</p>

<p>tion areas were marked. 2) Venous blood was drawn into a tube 
containing an anticoagulant (citrate dextrose) to avoid platelet 
activation and degranulation (50 mL). The first centrifugation, 
called the "soft spin" (3,600 rpm), allows blood separation into 
three layers, namely the bottom-most RBC layer (55% of total 
volume), topmost acellular plasma layer called platelet poor 
plasma (PPP) (40% of total volume), and an intermediate 
platelet-rich plasma (PRP) layer (5% of total volume) called 
the "buffy coat". This tube underwent a second centrifugation 
(2,400 rpm), called the "hard spin". This allowed the platelets 
(PRP) to settle at the bottom of the tube with a very few red 
blood cells. The acellular plasma, PPP (80% of the volume), was 
found at the top. Most of the PPP was removed with a syringe, 
and the remaining PRP was shaken well [11]. This PRP was 
then mixed with bovine thrombin (0.2 mL for every 1 mL of 
PRP) and 10% calcium chloride (0.1 mL) at the time of applica-
tion in a petri dish. 3) The super wet technique for infiltration 
of the supraumbilical region and flanks was carried out using a 
1:500,000 adrenaline/saline solution; then liposuction using 
4-mm and 5-mm cannulas to remove the fat of the deep and 
superficial layers was performed. The volume of the lipoaspirate 
was an average of 3,200 ± 780 mL with an average infiltrate of 
3,500 ± 600 mL for group A, while in group B the lipoaspirate 
was 3,150 ± 730 and the average infiltrate was 3,300 ± 560. The 
fat thickness was maintained at about 2.5 cm to avoid vascular 
impairment and contour deformities. 4) After liposuction, a 
central lower abdominal incision was made down to the level 
just above the muscle, dissecting the abdomen using a scalpel to 
the level of the umbilicus. After dissection and trimming of the 
umbilicus stack; the dissection was continued superiorly to the 
xiphoid, with lateral dissection up to 7.5 cm from the midline. 
5) Plication of the recti was completed in two layers, followed 
by removal of the excess infraumbilical skin. A V-shaped inci-
sion was made 2 cm above where the umbilical position was 
marked for exteriorization of the umbilicus; then a total of 20 
mL of platelet gel was applied in group A patients starting from 
the xiphoid process to the incision, with continuous external 
pressure applied to the abdomen after application of every 5 mL 
until the end of the closure of the incision (Fig. 1). 6) Placement 
of 2 silicone suction drains was done in both groups, followed 
by closure of Scarpa's fascia using PDS (2-0) suture. The dermal 
and subcuticular layers were then sutured using PDS (3-0) su-
ture. A non-adhesive dressing like Vaseline gauze was used. 
Postoperatively, the patients were encouraged to ambulate 
within 12 to 18 hours. All of the patients in both groups were 
hospitalized for 5 days with administration of antibiotics, analge-
sics, and antiedema medications until the drains were removed 
when the daily drainage volume was less than 30 mL, which </p>

<p>Vol. 40 / No. 5 / September 2013 </p>



<p>was on the 5th day in most cases, and the patients were then dis-
charged. The sutures were removed by the 15th day. Use of the 
compression garments was continued for 4 weeks. 
All of the patients underwent abdominal ultrasound exami-
nations at 2 postoperative periods: 1) between postoperative 
days 10 and 12 and, 2) between postoperative days 18 and 21. 
The examinations were performed by the same examiner using </p>

<p>an ultrasound system (Antares, Siemens, Brazil); longitudinal, 
transverse, and oblique scans of the 5 abdominal regions were 
made. A total volume of 20 mL of liquid from the 5 regions were 
considered positive for seroma, and an ultrasound-guided punc-
ture was performed for drainage of the seroma. 
Preoperative and postoperative digital photographs were taken 
at least one month after the operation and every six months 
thereafter using a Nikon Coolpix P500 digital camera (12.1 Mpx, 
36X optical zoom, Tokyo, Japan). The follow-up period ranged 
from six to twelve months. 
Statistical analysis of the results was performed by <rs id="software-0" type="software">MedCalc</rs> 
software ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.6.2.0</rs> (Mariakerke, Belgium). The results are ex-
pressed as mean+standard deviation. Wilcoxon's rank sum test 
was used for comparisons of same-group paired data. A value 
of P &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. With small sample sizes 
in groups, only very strong differences between groups can be 
detected. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>In all of the patients and both techniques, there were no deaths, 
major complications, anesthesia complications, or deep vein 
thrombosis. All of the patients suffered from pain, ecchymosis, 
and edema postoperatively, but to varying degrees. The pain was </p>

<p>In group A, after the limited dissection of the abdominal flap and 
plication of the rectus muscles, application of the fibrin glue is 
performed just before skin closure. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Application of the fibrin sealant </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>A 31-year-old female with a body mass index of 32 (A, B) show the anteroposterior view preoperatively and postoperatively, (C, D) show the left 
oblique view preoperatively and postoperatively, (E, F) show the right oblique view preoperatively and postoperatively. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. An example from the group A patients </p>



<p>Mabrouk AA et al. Fibrin sealant and lipoabdominoplasty </p>

<p>Total primary 
cases = 60 </p>

<p>Fibrin 
sealant </p>

<p>Traditional lipoab-
dominoplasty 
P-value </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Total complications 
3 (10) 
13 (43) 
0.004 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Seroma 
1 (3) 
11 (37) 
0.001 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Other 
2 (7) 
2 (7) 
Suprapubic epidermolysis 
2 (7) 
1 (3) 
0.365 
Skin necrosis 
0 ( 
1 (3) 
1.000 </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%). </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Significant differences. Group A had a significantly lower total complication rate 
and seroma formation rate compared to group B. </p>

<p>moderate and decreased gradually over time. However, the ec-
chymosis was severe but disappeared completely after 3 weeks. 
Edema and indurations occurred, but to a moderate degree, and 
declined gradually, disappearing after 4 to 6 weeks (Figs. 2, 3). 
The total complication rate in group A was 10% (n=3), which 
was significantly less than the rate for group B, at 43% (P=0.004). 
Concerning seroma formation, only 3% of the cases (n = 1) 
had collections detected by abdominal ultrasound during both 
periods for patients undergoing fibrin glue application, which 
was significantly less than the incidence in the traditional lipoab-
dominoplasty group of 37% of the cases (n = 11) (P = 0.001). 
These patients with seromas underwent ultrasound-guided 
aspiration two times weekly until clinical resolution with no un-
eventful consequences related to the seroma or drainage. 
Other than seroma, there was no difference in the skin necro-
sis rate (fibrin glue, 0%; traditional lipoabdominoplasty, 6.7%) 
or suprapubic epidermolyses (fibrin glue, 6.7%; traditional 
lipoabdominoplasty, 10%) (Table 2). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Since Callia's original description of abdominoplasty in 1963, 
this technique has evolved greatly in response to demands for 
better results, smaller scars, faster postoperative recovery, and, </p>

<p>above all, fewer postoperative complications [12]. 
The first description of the association between lipoplasty and 
full abdominoplasty was reported in 1991 by Matarasso [13], 
who performed lipoplasty of the abdominal flap with wide un-
dermining and classified the areas that could be aspirated on the 
basis of the blood supply of the abdominal wall. He stated that 
the lateral and superior areas are safe, while the central medial 
flap must be suctioned cautiously. 
As the work by Saldanha et al. [14] demonstrated no increased 
complications when liposuction was added to full abdomino-
plasty, this fear has begun to dissipate, with lipoabdominoplasty 
becoming a more commonplace procedure. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>Table 2. Complications and revision rates in each of the 2 
groups </p>

<p>A 36-year-old female with a body mass index of 36.9 from group B (A, B) show the anteroposterior view preoperatively and postoperatively, (C, D) 
show the right oblique view preoperatively and postoperatively, (E, F) show the left oblique view preoperatively and postoperatively. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. An example from group B patients </p>

<p>Vol. 40 / No. 5 / September 2013 </p>



<p>Although this technique has gained a huge popularity, many 
surgeons have performed it only for patients with normal BMI 
scores with good results. In 2009, Brauman and Capocci [3] 
performed lipoabdominoplasty on 337 consecutive patients 
with an average BMI of 29.3 kg/m 
2 (range, 19.5-41.7 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). 
The authors observed that seroma (5 cases; 1.4%) occurred 
more frequently in patients with high BMI scores, massive 
weight loss, and following diastasis repair. 
This is not the case in our country, where a BMI over 30 kg/ 
m 
2 is a common finding; thus in the present study, we tried to 
assess the applicability of lipoabdominoplasty in obese patients 
having BMIs ranging from 30 to 39.9 in light of the postopera-
tive complication rate and aesthetic outcome. 
Few studies have been published concerning the rate of com-
plications among the patients who underwent lipoabdomino-
plasty and had a high BMI. Heller et al. [2] detected the presence 
of seroma, but at a lower rate in comparison with abdomino-
plasty alone in 31 patients (BMI ranging from 19.9 to 39.3 with 
a mean of 28.2) who underwent a combined procedure of 
abdominal liposuction and inverted V-pattern abdominoplasty. 
Rangaswamy [15] detected no seroma in his last 100 patients 
from 120 patients, among whom 90% were either clearly obese 
or overweight with a mean BMI of 33. 
Rather than the frequent refinement of the lipoabdomino-
plasty procedure, postoperative seroma was common, but the 
incidence was less than in conventional abdominoplasty and 
many studies have been performed with the aim of reducing it 
[16,17]. 
Khan [18] applied progressive tension sutures, which had been 
previously described by Pollock and Pollock [19], to his lipoab-
dominoplasty cases to reduce the incidence of seroma, and he 
found that the rate did decrease but did not disappear. 
In 2010, a study by Di Martino et al. [20] proved that patients 
who had abdominoplasty with quilting sutures and those who 
had lipoabdominoplasty both had a lower incidence of seroma 
than conventional abdominoplasty. However, the authors oper-
ated upon patients with a BMI lower than 30 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, which is 
not always the case in patients seeking abdominoplasty in our 
country. 
Fibrin glue functions as a tissue sealant through the formation 
of a fibrin clot initiated by activation and aggregation of platelets. 
The fibrin clot then provides a matrix for the migration of tissue 
forming cells and endothelial cells involved in angiogenesis and 
the remodeling of the clot into repair tissue. The use of fibrin 
sealants under the skin flap prior to closure is well accepted and 
significantly reduces prolonged wound drainage and seroma 
formation [21]. 
Walgenbach et al. [22], conducted a trial on patients under-</p>

<p>going abdominoplasty to assess the use of a lysine-derived 
urethane adhesive (TissuGlu, Cohera Medical, Pittsburg, PA 
USA). They found that the mean total drain volume tended 
to be lower than in the control patients who underwent an 
identical procedure but without application of TissuGlu. In 
their study, they treated patients with normal BMI scores, and 
they did conventional abdominoplasty without liposuction or 
quilting sutures but with the use of synthetic glue; their results 
showed a decreased rate of postoperative seroma. 
In a preliminary study done by Schettino et al. [23], they ana-
lyzed data from 12 patients undergoing abdominoplasty using 
autologous plasma in its less platelet-concentrated portion (bio-
logical glue) and they found a reduction in postoperative col-
lections, mainly seroma. The present study was carried out on 
30 patients with high BMI scores who underwent lipoabdomi-
noplasty with the usage of fibrin glue to obliterate the present 
dead space, and only 1 case of seroma formation occurred after 
removal of the drains. 
To conclude, our study augments other recent studies [24,25]  that report the promising outcomes of the usage of autologous 
fibrin sealant with lipoabdominoplasty. This technique seems to 
reduce postoperative seroma; however, to compensate for the 
limitations of our study, more studies with larger sample sizes 
and power analysis, as well as research on the cost of fibrin seal-
ants and the duration of surgery are needed. 
Lipoabdominoplasty with the use of autologous fibrin sealant 
is a very effective method that significantly reduces the rate of 
postoperative seroma. </p>





<p>Mabrouk AA et al. Fibrin sealant and lipoabdominoplasty </p>



</text></tei>