<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3049466" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Oxygen transport imposes a possible constraint on the brain's ability to sustain variable metabolic 
demands, but oxygen diffusion in the cerebral cortex has not yet been observed directly. We show 
that concurrent two-photon fluorescence imaging of endogenous nicotinamide adenine dinucleo-
tide (NADH) and the cortical microcirculation exposes well-defined boundaries of tissue oxygen 
diffusion in the mouse cortex. The NADH fluorescence increases rapidly over a narrow, very low pO 2 
range with a p 50 of 3.4 ± 0.6 mm Hg, thereby establishing a nearly binary reporter of significant, 
metabolically limiting hypoxia. The transient cortical tissue boundaries of NADH fluorescence 
exhibit remarkably delineated geometrical patterns, which define the limits of tissue oxygen 
diffusion from the cortical microcirculation and bear a striking resemblance to the ideal Krogh tissue 
cylinder. The visualization of microvessels and their regional contribution to oxygen delivery 
establishes penetrating arterioles as major oxygen sources in addition to the capillary network and 
confirms the existence of cortical oxygen fields with steep microregional oxygen gradients. Thus, 
two-photon NADH imaging can be applied to expose vascular supply regions and to localize 
functionally relevant microregional cortical hypoxia with micrometer spatial resolution. </p>

<p>A fundamental impediment to the current investiga-
tion of cortical function is the uncertain causality 
between changes in neural activity, cerebral blood 
flow, and tissue oxygenation under nonactivated and 
activated conditions (Raichle and Mintun, 2006). 
Thus, the physiological purpose that leads to the 
highly conserved response of increased cerebral </p>

<p>blood flow to focally stimulated brain tissue (Roy  and Sherrington, 1890) remains an enigma. Never-
theless, many contemporary neuroimaging studies 
rely exclusively on localizing the hemodynamic 
response. Although the total amount of oxygen 
transported to the brain exceeds the total consumed 
oxygen by a factor of B2.5 (Buchweitz et al, 1980), 
oxygen is distributed from the vasculature to the 
brain parenchyma solely by diffusion, with uncer-
tainties regarding the functional relevance of peri-
vascular tissue oxygen gradients (Thews, 1960a;  Ndubuizu and LaManna, 2007) and oxygen diffusion 
times (Masamoto et al, 2007) for neurometabolic 
(Thompson et al, 2003; Masamoto et al, 2003) and 
neurovascular coupling (Buxton and Frank, 1997;  Vafaee and Gjedde, 2000; Mintun et al, 2001; Gjedde,  2002). 
A direct experimental observation of tissue 
oxygen diffusion from the cortical microcirculation </p>

<p>Received 29 March 2010; revised 6 August 2010; accepted 17 
August 2010; published online 22 September 2010 </p>

<p>Correspondence: Dr KA Kasischke, Department of Neurology, 
University of Rochester Medical Center, 601 Elmwood Avenue, 
Box 645, Rochester, NY 14642, USA. 
E-mail: karl_kasischke@urmc.rochester.edu 
This study was supported by the DANA foundation (Brain and 
Immunoimaging Program), the American Heart Association 
(0635595T), the ALS Association (#1112), NIH-NINDS (NS38073, 
NS50315), and NIH-NCI (CA68409). </p>

<p>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism (2011) 31, 68-81 
&amp; 2011 ISCBFM All rights reserved 0271-678X/11 </p>

<p>www.jcbfm.com </p>

<p>could expose the actual geometry of cortical vas-
cular supply regions (Fletcher, 1978; Wang and  Bassingthwaigthe, 2001), provide clarification for 
this mismatch between oxygen supply and demand, 
and further assist in the interpretation of functional 
neuroimaging studies. Such observations are not 
feasible using conventional polarographic oxygen 
measurements because the exact three-dimensional 
origin of the measurement with respect to the 
diffusion boundary is unknown and further because 
of uncertainties regarding their spatial resolution 
(Connelly, 1957). 
The intracellular coenzyme nicotinamide adenine 
dinucleotide (NADH) has long been used as an 
intrinsically fluorescent indicator for cellular meta-
bolic states and tissue oxygen supply in vivo (Chance  et al, 1962), and it was more recently shown that 
two-photon NADH imaging enables high-resolution 
imaging and spectroscopy of metabolic transitions 
and hypoxia in hippocampal tissue slices (Kasischke  et al, 2004; Vishwasrao et al, 2005) and mouse cortex 
(Takano et al, 2007). In this study, we resolve well-
defined tissue boundaries of NADH fluorescence in 
the mouse cortex and their strong geometric associa-
tion with the regional microcirculation. We provide a 
biophysical interpretation of the observed NADH 
patterns as observable boundaries of tissue oxygen 
diffusion. This enables the visualization of cortical 
vascular supply regions and the localization of 
functionally relevant microregional cortical hypoxia 
with micrometer spatial resolution. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Mice, Physiological Monitoring, Cranial Window 
Surgery </p>

<p>All experiments were approved by the University Commit-
tee on Animal Resources of the University of Rochester 
Medical Center. We used C57/Bl6 mice (Jackson Labora-
tory, Bar Harbor, ME, USA), FVB-Ntac mice (Taconic 
Farms, Germantown, NY, USA) and transgenic mice (B6-
Tg(Eno2-YFP/Cox8a)1819R21Rwb/J) with neuron-specific 
expression of mitochondrially targeted yellow fluorescent 
protein (YFP) under control of the neuron-specific 
enolase2 (Eno2) promoter (Misgeld et al, 2007). All mice 
were used at age 10 to 12 weeks. C57Bl6 and Eno2-YFP/ 
Cox8a mice were anesthetized with isoflurane (1% to 
1.5%) and ventilated through a facemask. FVB mice were 
anesthetized with ketamine (0.12 mg/g intraperitoneally) 
and xylazine (0.01 mg/g intraperitoneally) and ventilated 
through a tracheostomy using a small animal ventilator 
(SAR-830, CWE Inc., Woodland Hills, CA, USA) set at 
100 breaths/min with a tidal volume of 0.3 to 0.4 mL. The 
body temperature was maintained using a water-flow 
heating pad (TP-500, Gaymar, Orchard Park, NY, USA) 
and a temperature controller (ACT1000, WPI Inc., Sarasota, 
FL, USA). The femoral artery was cannulated for measure-
ments of systemic blood pressure (BLPR2/SYS-BP1, WPI 
Inc.) and blood gases (Ciba-Corning 238, GMI Inc., Ramsey, 
MN, USA). Blood gases in our mice were pO 2 = 108 ± 8 </p>

<p>mm Hg, pCO 2 = 33±5 mm Hg, and pH = 7.32±0.03 (avera- ge±s.d., n = 6). Optical access to the cortex was provided 
through a parietal craniectomy (diameter 3 to 4 mm 
centered at bregma À0.5 mm, lateral 3 mm). A metal plate 
was glued to the skull, the dura mater removed, and 
artificial cerebrospinal fluid containing (in mmol/L) 126 
NaCl, 2.5 KCl, 1.25 NaH 2 PO 4 , 2 MgCl 2 , 2 CaCl 2 , 10 glucose, 
and 26 NaHCO 3 , pH 7.4, was applied. The window was 
covered with 2% agarose dissolved in artificial cerebrosp-
inal fluid at 371C and a 0.17-mm glass coverslip. For the 
purpose of two-photon microangiographies the femoral 
vein was injected with Texas-Red-dextran (MW 70 kDa, 
D1830, Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Bright Field Imaging of the Pial Vasculature </p>

<p>Cranial window-prepared mice were mounted on the 
microscope stage. The cortex was illuminated with white 
light using a fiber optic illuminator (DC-950-Fiber-Lite, 
Dolan-Jenner, Boxborough, MA, USA). Bright field images 
of the cortex were captured using a CMOS camera (Moticam 
1000, Motic, Xiamen, China) at Â 4 NA 0.13 air objective 
(Olympus, Tokyo, Japan; UPlanFLN) and a Â 10 NA 0.45 
(Zeiss C-Apochromat, Oberkochen, Germany) water-immer-
sion objective. Pial arterioles and venules were identified by 
direction of blood flow, color, and branching pattern. </p>

<p>Two-Photon Imaging of Nicotinamide Adenine 
Dinucleotide and the Microcirculation </p>

<p>We used an Olympus Fluoview1000-AOM or Fluoview300 
multiphoton imaging system with femtosecond Ti:Sa lasers 
as excitation sources (Spectra-Physics MaiTai or MaiTaiHP 
Deep See). For imaging, we used Â 10 NA 0.45 (Zeiss 
C-Apochromat), Â 20 NA 0.95 (Olympus XLUMPlan F), or 
Â 25 NA 1.05 (Olympus XLPlan N) water-immersion 
objectives. Images were taken at 12-bit depth at a resolution 
of 512 Â 512 pixels with a pixel dwell time of 2 micro-
seconds. The NADH and Texas-Red-dextran were two-
photon excited at 710 nm, YFP at 900 nm. Fluorescence 
was separated from the excitation light using a dichroic 
mirror/near-IR-blocking filter combination (FF665-Di01; 
FF01-680/SP, Semrock, Rochester, NY, USA) divided into 
two channels using a dichroic mirror (505DCXRU, Chroma, 
Rockingham, VT, USA), and bandpass filtered (NADH-
Semrock FF460/80, YFP-Chroma 535/30ET, Texas-Red-
dextran-Semrock FF607/36). All optical bandpass filters 
are specified according to the manufacturer's convention 
'center wavelength/filter bandwidth'. Two-photon micro-
angiographies were taken from the pial surface down 
to layer IV using 1 mm z-steps. Concurrent two-photon 
imaging of NADH and the vasculature was performed at 
imaging depths ranging from 50 to 200 mm. The laser power 
after the objective was kept below 10 mW. To conduct four-
color imaging of neurons, astrocytes, microvessels, and 
NADH in the cortex, we used transgenic mice with expres-
sion of YFP in a subset of cortical neurons (Jackson Labs, 
B6.Cg-TgN(Thy1-YFPH)2Jrs). We labeled astrocytes in these 
mice by topically application of the astrocyte-specific dye 
sulforhodamine 101 (5 mmol/L in artificial cerebrospinal </p>

<p>Two-photon NADH imaging of oxygen diffusion 
KA Kasischke et al </p>



<p>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism (2011) 31, 68-81 </p>

<p>fluid, Sigma S7635, St Louis, MO, USA), and labeled the blood 
serum by injecting red fluorescent (655 nm) water-soluble 
quantum dots (Invitrogen, Q21021MP) into the femoral vein. </p>

<p>Whisker Stimulation, Hypoxemia, Electrophysiology, 
Measurement of Tissue Oxygen, and Cerebral Blood 
Flow </p>

<p>We induced neural activity in the barrel cortex with 
electrical whisker stimulation using repeated 5 Hz trains, 
with a duration of 20 seconds separated by a 2-minute 
interval during an 8-minute period. Pulses (1.2 mA, 
0.3 milliseconds) were generated using a stimulator/isola-
tion unit (Master8/ISO-Flex, AMPI, Jerusalem, Israel) and 
applied through two insulated electrodes (E363/1, Plastics 
One, Roanoke, VA, USA) placed against the lower posterior 
quadrant of the whisker field. Extracellular recordings of 
the local field potential and the DC potential were obtained 
through patch pipettes (TW150F-4, WPI) with a tip 
diameter of 2 to 3 mm. The electrodes were filled with 
artificial cerebrospinal fluid and placed in the imaging 
plane in cortical layer I at a depth of 50 to 100 mm. The 
local field potential signals were amplified using an 
Axopatch 200B amplifier (Axon Instruments, Sunnyvale, 
CA, USA), bandpass filtered at 1 to 100 Hz, and digitized 
at 20 kHz (Digidata 1320, Axon Instruments). For measure-
ment of cerebral blood flow, we used a laser Doppler 
system, with a 1-mm needle probe (BLF21, Transonic 
Systems Inc., Ithaca, NY, USA) that was placed above the 
barrel cortex. For direct oxygen measurements in layer I, 
we used customized Clark-type electrodes, with a fast 
response time and a 3 to 4 mm tip diameter (Unisense A/S, 
Aarhus, Denmark). These oxygen electrodes were cali-
brated before each experiment in saline equilibrated with 
room air (21% O 2 ) and a solution of ascorbate in NaOH (0% 
O 2 ). Experimental hypoxemia was induced by lowering the 
oxygen concentration in the inspired air from 21% to 10% 
for a period of 120 seconds. </p>

<p>Fluorescence Spectroscopy </p>

<p>Intrinsic fluorescence from cortical layer I was two-photon 
excited at 710 nm, focused into a 1-mm diameter multi-
mode fiber and coupled into a cooled spectrometer 
(BWT1112E, B&amp;W-Tek Inc. Newark, DE, USA). Reference 
spectra of purified -NADH (Sigma, N9410-15VL) in 
aqueous solution and bound to mitochondrial malate-
dehydrogenase (Worthington Biochemical Corp., Lake-
wood, NJ, USA) were taken at 340 nm excitation using a 
Cary Eclipse fluorescence spectrometer (Varian Inc., Palo 
Alto, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Image Processing and Visualization </p>

<p>We performed image analysis using Matlab (MathWorks 
Inc., Natick, MA, USA). Thus, we digitally registered bright 
field images of the pial vasculature with the corresponding 
two-photon microangiographies. We then followed the 
arterial or venous vascular trees until they branched into </p>

<p>capillaries and digitally pseudocolored them. For three-
dimensional reconstructions of the Texas-Red-dextran 
labeled cerebral vasculature, we intensity adjusted the 
z-stacks, Fourier filtered, and visualized them using maxi-
mum intensity projections. We restricted image analysis to 
averaging subsequent images with calculation of the mean 
and the s.d. for each pixel, and normalizing the 12-bit pixel 
intensities of the Fluoview1000 images to a continuous 
gray-intensity scale ranging from 0 to 1. </p>

<p>Curve Fitting and Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>We used <rs id="software-1" type="software">OriginPro</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">8</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">OriginLab</rs>, Northampton, MA, USA) 
software to create graphs, for curve fitting, and statistical 
testing. We measured NADH tissue fluorescence (% of 
baseline) as a function of tissue pO 2 (mm Hg). In Figure 1D, 
we show a fit of the sigmoidal Boltzmann function, </p>

<p>NADH % 
½ ¼ A 2 þ 
A 1 À A 2 
1 þ exp ðpO2Àp50Þ=dx 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>to these measurements. We performed hypothesis testing 
using independent, two-sample t-tests with an a-level of 
0.01. We tested the normality of the sample distribution of 
our data with the Shapiro-Wilk test, and we determined 
the equality of the sample variances with Levene's test. We 
report experimental error as±s.d. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Blue Intrinsic Tissue Fluorescence Is a Specific 
Reporter for Nicotinamide Adenine Dinucleotide 
and a Sensitive Indicator of Cellular Hypoxia </p>

<p>We first addressed the specificity of intrinsic tissue 
fluorescence of the mouse somatosensory cortex as a 
reporter for NADH. Using a combined multiphoton 
imaging and spectroscopy setup (Figure 1A), we 
acquired fluorescence emission spectra from layer I 
on two-photon excitation at 710 nm. To minimize the 
interference from hemoglobin absorption, we took 
the spectra from tissue volumes that were free of 
large blood vessels. The bounded position of the 
intrinsic fluorescence spectrum (Figure 1B, black 
plot, avg. ± s.d from six mice) between the spectrum 
of free, aqueous NADH (Figure 1B, red plot) and the 
blue-shifted spectrum of NADH bound to mitochon-
drial malate-dehydrogenase (Figure 1B, blue plot) 
shows that intracellular NADH in the neocortex 
exists in equilibrium between free and protein-
bound molecules, in analogy to the hippocampal 
neuropil (Vishwasrao et al, 2005). The strong 
congruity of the spectra depicted in Figure 1B 
establishes that intrinsic signal is essentially pure 
pyridine nucleotide fluorescence with spectrally 
indistinguishable fractions from NADH and nicotin-
amide adenine dinucleotide phosphate (NADPH). As 
NADH contributes B86% and NADPH contributes 
only B14% to the total tissue concentrations of the 
reduced pyridine nucleotides in the mouse cortex 
(Klaidman et al, 1995), the intrinsic tissue fluores-</p>

<p>Two-photon NADH imaging of oxygen diffusion 
KA Kasischke et al </p>



<p>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism (2011) 31, 68-81 </p>

<p>cence can be interpreted as predominately represent-
ing NADH and thus as a specific reporter for neural 
energy metabolism. 
As the next step, we calibrated the NADH 
fluorescence intensity in layer I as a function of 
tissue oxygenation by concurrent NADH imaging and 
Clark electrode oxygen measurements during experi-
mentally induced hypoxemia (Figure 1C). Controlled 
hypoxemia was induced by gradual reduction of the 
oxygen concentration in the ventilated gas mixture 
from 21% to 0%. The inverse relationship between 
NADH fluorescence and oxygen becomes obvious 
when plotting the tissue fluorescence as a function of 
the extracellular oxygen tension (Figure 1D). The 
NADH fluorescence remained first unchanged, with 
decreasing tissue oxygen levels from 25 to 10 mm Hg 
and eventually exhibited an abrupt increase at 
extracellular tissue oxygen levels below 10 mm Hg. 
Our measurements of the oxygen dependence of 
NADH fluorescence in mouse cortex are consistent 
with previously published studies on mitochondrial 
metabolism in cultured cells. Wilson et al (1979a)  reported that there is little change in intramitochon-
drial (NAD 
+ /NADH) until very low oxygen tensions </p>

<p>are reached. It was also reported that the respiratory 
rate is essentially independent of oxygen concentra-
tions above 20 mM (B12 mm Hg), which is in full 
agreement with the flat slope of our calibration curve 
between 10 and 25 mm Hg. Mathematical modeling 
(Wilson et al, 1979b) suggested that mitochondrial 
(NAD 
+ /NADH) may still be weakly dependent on 
oxygen concentration at higher concentrations 
throughout the entire physiological range up to 
200 mM (B120 mm Hg), albeit with a slope much less 
than that noted below 10 mm Hg. 
The red line in Figure 1D shows the fit of the 
sigmoidal Boltzmann function (R 
2 = 0.99) to these 
measurements. Using equation (1), we extracted the 
two asymptotes A 1 = 193.85 ± 30.81, A 2 = 100.26 ± 
0.96 and the inflection point p 50 = 3.43 ± 0.62 mm Hg 
with dx = 1.15±0.09. The oxygen tension p 50 for half-
maximum NADH fluorescence indicates loss of 
respiratory chain function and mitochondrial ATP 
production and is equivalent to the critical extra-
cellular oxygen tension for the brain. Our estimate 
of the critical extracellular oxygen tension of 
3.4±0.6 mm Hg is in good agreement with a previous 
report of critical oxygen tensions in the brain of 1 to </p>

<p>PMT2 </p>

<p>Exc. 
beam </p>

<p>D 
C 
1 </p>

<p>spectro-
meter </p>

<p>oxygen 
electrode 
4 µm tip </p>

<p>mouse 
head </p>

<p>PMT1 </p>

<p>imaging module </p>

<p>spectroscopy module </p>

<p>D 
C 
2 </p>

<p>NIR 
block. 
filter </p>

<p>focus. 
lens </p>

<p>Figure 1 Intrinsic fluorescence from the mouse cortex reports nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NADH) and increases steeply at 
very low oxygen levels. (A) Schematic of the combined two-photon imaging and spectroscopy setup used to acquire the images, 
spectroscopy, and oxygen measurements from mouse cortical layer I. (B) The intrinsic tissue fluorescence exhibits a well-defined, 
solitary emission spectrum (black plot, avg.±s.d., n = 6) when two-photon excited at 710 nm. This spectrum lies bounded between 
the spectra of free NADH (red plot) and protein-bound NADH (blue plot). (C) To determine the relationship between NADH 
fluorescence and tissue oxygenation, we concurrently imaged NADH fluorescence (red plot) and directly measured the tissue 
oxygenation (blue plot) with Clark electrodes. We induced hypoxemia by reducing the oxygen fraction of the inspired gas mixture from 
21% to 0% at a rate of B16% over 10 seconds. (D) When plotting NADH tissue fluorescence as a function of tissue oxygen tension 
(x-and y-error bars are s.d., n = 3), the inverse relationship between NADH and oxygen becomes obvious. The inflection 
point p 50 = 3.4 ± 0.6 mm Hg of the sigmoidal curve fit (red line, R 
2 = 0.99) indicates the critical extracellular oxygen tension for 
cortical layer I. </p>

<p>Two-photon NADH imaging of oxygen diffusion 
KA Kasischke et al </p>



<p>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism (2011) 31, 68-81 </p>

<p>3 mm Hg (MacMillan and Siesjö , 1971) and also with 
the reported p 50 for mitochondrial oxidation reduc-
tion of 2.5 mm Hg (Hull and Foster, 2001). The 
critical oxygen tensions stated here lie all within 
the broad range between 0.01 and &lt; 9 mm Hg 
reported in the classical literature (Chance, 1957). </p>

<p>Geometric Relationship Between Nicotinamide 
Adenine Dinucleotide Tissue Patches and the 
Cortical Microcirculation </p>

<p>At the beginning of each intravital imaging experi-
ment, we verified the integrity of the cranial window 
site under bright field illumination (Figure 2A) and 
identified arterioles and venules using branching 
pattern, blood flow direction, and blood color as 
independent criteria. A subsequent two-photon 
angiography of the same area (Figure 2B) was 
conducted to determine the arteriolar and venous 
vascular trees in three dimensions. 
The NADH fluorescence in layer I under resting 
conditions with 21% inspired oxygen exhibited 
transient tissue patches with steeply elevated NADH 
fluorescence, delineated by conspicuous borders 
with circular indentations (Figure 2C). The NADH 
fluorescence levels within the tissue patches were 
48% to 58% elevated with respect to adjacent tissue 
with uniformly low NADH fluorescence. We could 
consistently unmask these tissue patches with short 
(20 seconds) episodes of mild hypoxemia that we 
induced by lowering the oxygen concentration in the 
ventilated gas mixture from 21% to 15% oxygen. 
Electrophysiological recordings under these condi-
tions revealed a transient silencing of the sponta-
neous electrical activity with only minimal shifts of 
the DC potential (Supplementary Figure S1). The 
stability of the DC potential excludes pathological 
conditions like anoxic depolarization or spreading 
depression (Takano et al, 2007), as underlying causes 
for the observed NADH patches. Possible confound-
ing effects of anesthesia were addressed by using two </p>

<p>fundamentally different regimes (isoflurane or 
ketamine/xylazine). The NADH tissue patches were 
consistently observed under both regimens, and they 
did not respond to changes in anesthetic depth. 
To answer the question whether the inhomoge-
neous NADH tissue fluorescence is related to the 
distribution of neuronal mitochondria in the neuro-
pil of layer I or is an independent signal, we used 
transgenic mice with pan-cortical, neuron-specific 
expression of mitochondrially targeted YFP (Misgeld  et al, 2007). These mice offer the unique opportunity 
to directly compare the distributions of NADH </p>

<p>Figure 2 Geometric relationship between tissue regions with 
elevated nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NADH) fluores-
cence and cortical blood vessels. (A) The bright field image 
shows the intact surface and microcirculation in the pia and 
layer I of the mouse somatosensory cortex under the cranial 
window. (B) Subsequent two-photon angiography. (C) The 
intrinsic NADH fluorescence exhibits steep intensity gradients 
in regions distant to the vasculature. (D) Homogeneous 
distribution of neuronal mitochondria, labeled with targeted 
YFP (Eno2-YFP/Cox8a). (E) The superimposition of NADH 
fluorescence with pseudocolored arterioles (red) and venules 
(blue) exposes a strong geometric association of the NADH 
tissue gradients to the cerebral microcirculation. The yellow 
sketches highlight circular borders enclosing perpendicularly 
oriented vessels; the orange sketches highlight linear borders 
parallel to horizontally oriented vessels. Scale bars represent 
200 mm. </p>

<p>Two-photon NADH imaging of oxygen diffusion 
KA Kasischke et al </p>



<p>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism (2011) 31, 68-81 </p>

<p>fluorescence and neuronal mitochondria in the same 
cortical region. In stark contrast to the described 
heterogeneities in the NADH tissue fluorescence, the 
spatial distribution of YFP fluorescence from neuro-
nal mitochondria was homogenous, regardless of 
their location within the vascular bed (Figure 2D). 
The even distribution of neuronal mitochondria 
described here is consistent with a regionally uni-
form metabolic rate for oxygen in layer I. In contrast, 
the sharply delineated, dark appearance of the 
cortical blood vessels in both the NADH and 
mitochondrial YFP fluorescence images can be 
attributed to the high two-photon absorptivity of 
hemoglobin (Clay et al, 2007). </p>

<p>To further delineate the apparent spatial relation-
ship between NADH tissue patches and the 
microcirculation, we digitally superimposed pseudo-
colored arterioles (red in Figure 2E) and venules 
(blue in Figure 2E) over the raw NADH image 
(grayscale, Figure 2E). The montage highlights dis-
tinct circular indentations (yellow sketches) and 
linear borders (orange sketches) of the NADH tissue 
patches. These NADH tissue patches were always 
located in tissue areas distant to regional blood 
vessels, notably at greater distances to arterioles than 
to venules. We further conducted four-compartment 
fluorescence imaging of NADH (Figure 3A), neuronal 
processes (Figure 3B), astrocytes (Figure 3C), and the </p>

<p>Figure 3 Four-compartment imaging of nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NADH), neuronal processes, astrocytes, and cortical 
blood vessels. (A) Intrinsic NADH fluorescence, (B) YFP-expressing neuronal processes, (C) sulforhodamine-stained astrocytes, (D) 
quantum-dot label blood vessels in layer I. (E) The merge of the four compartments (A-D) reveals no spatial relationship between the 
NADH tissue patches and neuronal processes or astrocytes. (F) The indentations that define the boundaries of the NADH tissue 
patches are indeed of circular geometry, as demonstrated in G by their close match with superimposed circles (red pseudocolor) with 
radii R between 18 and 39 mm. (H) The further superimposition of the microangiography (cyan pseudocolor) confirms that circular 
indentations that delineate NADH tissue patches are concentric, which their respective central blood vessels. Scale bars represent 
100 mm. </p>

<p>Two-photon NADH imaging of oxygen diffusion 
KA Kasischke et al </p>



<p>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism (2011) 31, 68-81 </p>

<p>vasculature (Figure 3D) under resting conditions, 
with 21% inspired oxygen to investigate whether the 
NADH patches were related to the distribution of 
cellular elements in the neuropil of layer I. However, 
the superimposition of all four fluorescence channels 
(Figure 3E) did not reveal any association of NADH 
patches to astrocytes or neuronal processes in layer I, 
whereas it confirmed their strong geometrical asso-
ciation with neighboring blood vessels (Figures 3F-3H). 
The described geometry is instantly recognizable and 
consistent with an underlying relationship to oxygen 
supply from the vascular bed. Thus, the boundaries 
of the tissue patches could be related to the perimeter 
of oxygen diffusion from neighboring microvessels. 
We interpreted these tissue NADH patches as 
hypoxic (pO 2 r3.4 mm Hg) watershed areas and 
asked whether similar patterns could be observed 
in the physiologically activated brain. </p>

<p>Unmasking of the Krogh Tissue Cylinder </p>

<p>Focal neural activity in the barrel cortex was induced 
by intermittent whisker stimulation using 20 second 
trains at 5 Hz and validated by recording of 
well-described neurovascular responses in layer I 
(Supplementary Figure S2), specifically bursts of 
local field potentials, the hemodynamic response, 
and the previously reported (Thompson et al, 2003;  Masamoto et al, 2003) biphasic change in tissue 
oxygenation. We applied five intermittent 20 second 
trains separated by 2 minute-intervals during an 
8-minute period. The microregional intensity dis-
tribution of the time-averaged NADH tissue fluores-
cence (Figure 4A) in layer I appeared homogenous. 
However, we frequently observed evanescent, spa-
tially confined NADH transients delineated by 
conspicuous circular borders. These microregional 
fluctuations emerged at various times during the 
stimulation period, some appeared spontaneously, 
whereas others were correlated with the applied 
stimuli. To quantitatively isolate such metabolically 
labile regions, we computed the s.d. for each pixel of 
the time series. The visualization of the s.d. (Figure 4B) 
reveals a distinctively geometrical tissue pattern, 
which is consistent with two intersecting circles. 
Their boundaries are defined by the visible, steep 
transition from low to high s.d., and they effectively 
separate inner regions with stable NADH fluores-
cence from outer regions with fluctuating NADH 
fluorescence. To determine the radius R of the 
described tissue circles, we measured their radial 
pixel intensity values within a well-defined segment 
(Figure 4C). Details of this complex measurement are 
provided in the Supplementary Text. We then fitted a 
sigmoidal function (red line in Figure 4D) to the 
radial intensity profile (blue symbols in Figure 4D) 
and used its inflection point, x o , as a definition of R. 
The boundaries of the two intersecting circles 
(yellow sketches in Figure 4E) are now objectively 
defined, with radii R of 43 and 68 mm, respectively. </p>

<p>Two-photon microangiography revealed the cross-
section of a solitary central blood vessel in each 
circle, here two arterioles (red pseudocolor in Figure 
4E) with radii r of B6 and 13 mm, respectively. 
The well-defined geometry of the observed tissue 
and vessel boundaries in Figure 4E strikingly 
resembles the two-dimensional projection of the </p>

<p>Figure 4 Two-photon nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide 
(NADH) imaging enables direct visualization of the Krogh tissue 
cylinder. (A) The NADH fluorescence in layer I of the barrel 
cortex, averaged over an 8-minute period with intermittent 
whisker stimulation. Note homogeneous regional intensity 
distribution of NADH with disseminated bright cellular elements 
and dark blood vessels. (B) Visualization of the s.d. (depicted in 
vertical scale bar on the right) of the time series distinguishes 
two intersecting circular tissue regions. (C) To determine their 
radius R, we measured the radial pixel intensity profile within a 
well-defined tissue segment, here bounded by two cyan lines 
and the red circle. The red dot marks the midpoint of the central 
blood vessel. (D) Graph of the radial pixel intensity profile (blue 
symbols). The inflection point, x 0 , of the fitted sigmoidal curve 
(red line) defines the radius R, here 68.2 mm. (E) The 
superimposition of the pseudocolored microangiography (arter-
ioles in red and capillaries in pink pseudocolor) reveals that the 
two intersecting tissue circles (yellow sketches) have the cross-
section of arterioles at their center. (F) Sketch of the Krogh 
cylinder as proposed in 1919 where a central blood vessel with 
radius r supplies a tissue cylinder with radius R with radially 
diffusing oxygen. Scale bars in panels A-E represent 50 mm. </p>

<p>Two-photon NADH imaging of oxygen diffusion 
KA Kasischke et al </p>



<p>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism (2011) 31, 68-81 </p>

<p>ideal 'Krogh tissue cylinder' (Krogh, 1919) as shown 
in the sketch in Figure 4F. The influential concept of 
the Krogh tissue cylinder was proposed in 1919 as a 
mathematical description of radial oxygen diffusion 
from capillaries into skeletal muscle, and it has 
provided the groundwork for many subsequent 
models of tissue oxygen supply (Thews, 1960a;  Popel, 1989; Foster et al, 1991). On the basis of the 
strong geometrical analogy to the Krogh cylinder, we 
hypothesized that boundaries between tissue regions 
with steady and fluctuating NADH fluorescence 
represent the perimeter of radial oxygen diffusion 
from the central blood vessel into the surrounding 
neuropil. In this scenario, the cylindrical NADH 
tissue boundary is the physical equivalent of the 
second boundary condition of the Krogh model, 
which is defined as the point where the microregio-
nal tissue pO 2 approximates the critical oxygen 
tension p 50 necessary to sustain mitochondrial 
respiration. In this transitional zone, minute fluctua-
tions in vascular supply or microregional tissue 
utilization of oxygen will lead to toggling between 
zero-order and first-order oxygen metabolism with 
oscillations between low and high NADH fluores-
cence levels. Consequently, the radius R of the 
cylindrical NADH boundary must be defined by the 
competition between vascular oxygen delivery 
through diffusion and the tissue metabolic rate for 
oxygen. As the next step, we adapted the Krogh 
model for the rodent cortex. </p>

<p>Adaptation of the Krogh-Erlang Model for the Rodent 
Cortex </p>

<p>The Krogh model postulates that a central capillary 
with radius r and infinite length supplies a con-
centric tissue cylinder with radius R with radially 
diffusing oxygen. The axi-symmetric steady-state 
diffusion equation for this system in cylindrical 
coordinates (Foster et al, 1991) is 
1 
r 0 </p>

<p>d 
dr 0 r 
0 K 
dT 
dr 0 </p>



<p>¼ p 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>with the Krogh diffusion constant K, the constant 
rate of oxygen consumption p, and the oxygen 
tension T at radial distance r 
0 from the capillary 
wall. The two boundary conditions are (1) tissue 
oxygen equals capillary oxygen at the vessel wall and 
(2) metabolic flux is zero due to critically low oxygen 
concentration at the edge of the Krogh tissue 
cylinder. The solution of equation (2) is the Krogh-
Erlang equation (Krogh, 1919) </p>

<p>T x ¼ T o À 
p 
K </p>

<p>1 
2 
R 
2 Á ln 
x 
r </p>

<p>
À 
x 
2 À r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>



<p>
: 
ð3Þ </p>

<p>Here, T o is the capillary oxygen tension (atm), and T x 
is the tissue oxygen tension at radial distance x (cm) 
from the capillary center. For brain tissue, the rate of 
oxygen consumption p is equivalent to the product 
of the cerebral metabolic rate of oxygen (CMRO 2 ) and </p>

<p>the density r of brain tissue. For rat cortex (Eklö f  et al, 1973)   p ¼ CMRO 2 Á r ¼ 10:2 
mL 
100 g min 
Á 1:05 
g 
cm 3 </p>

<p>¼ 0:107 min 
À1 : 
ð4Þ </p>

<p>The Krogh diffusion constant K is the product of the 
oxygen diffusion coefficient D and the oxygen 
solubility a (Verduin, 1955). For rat brain at 371C 
(Thews, 1960b) </p>

<p>K ¼ D Á a ¼ 1:7 Á 10 
À5 cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>sec 
Â2:2 Á 10 </p>

<p>À2 </p>

<p>cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>cm 3 atm </p>

<p>¼ 2:3Â10 </p>

<p>À5 </p>

<p>cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>min atm 
: 
ð5Þ </p>

<p>For the case of the second boundary condition, x = R, 
the simplified Krogh-Erlang equation is rearranged 
to afford the intravascular oxygen tension </p>

<p>T 0 ¼ T R þ 
p 
K </p>

<p>1 
2 
R 
2 Á ln 
R 
r </p>

<p>
À 
R 
2 À r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>



<p>
: 
ð6Þ </p>

<p>By definition, the microregional oxygen tension T R at 
the cylinder boundary is rate limiting. Using equa-
tion (1), we have determined that the rate limiting 
extracellular oxygen concentration, as displayed by 
the p 50 for half-maximum NADH tissue fluorescence, 
T R , is B3.4 mm Hg (Figure 1D). We further substitute 
the numeric values for p and K and convert the 
original units used by Krogh for the oxygen tension 
and the radial distances from (atm) and (cm) to 
(mm Hg) and (mm) </p>

<p>T 0 ¼ 3:4 mm Hg þ 0:0177 
mm Hg 
mm 2 </p>

<p>Á R 
2 Á ln 
R 
r </p>

<p>
À 
R 
2 À r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 </p>



<p>
: 
ð7Þ </p>

<p>By directly imaging the central vessel radius r and 
the Krogh cylinder radius R in the mouse cortex 
(Figure 4E) and further assuming a constant meta-
bolic rate, we can now infer the intravascular oxygen 
tension according to equation (7) and thus the 
absolute microregional tissue oxygen tension within 
the Krogh cylinder at any radial distance x from the 
vessel center according to equation (3). 
A visualization of an ideal Krogh tissue cylinder 
according to our adaptation of the Krogh model is 
provided in Figure 5. The radial pO 2 gradient within 
the cylinder (Figure 5A) is derived from equation (3). 
We then apply equation (1) with the previously 
extracted parameters A 1 , A 2 , p 50 , and dx as a transfer 
function to infer the radial NADH fluorescence 
intensity (Figure 5B) from the oxygen distribution. 
Corresponding ideal tissue pO 2 and NADH fluores-
cence intensity maps are shown in Figures 5C and 
5D. The predicted NADH fluorescence within an 
ideal Krogh cylinder exhibits a steep increase in the 
vicinity of the diffusion boundary R (Figure 5D), 
which is in good agreement with our experimentally 
observed NADH tissue cylinders. </p>

<p>Two-photon NADH imaging of oxygen diffusion 
KA Kasischke et al </p>



<p>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism (2011) 31, 68-81 </p>

<p>Capillary-Depleted Tissue Cylinders Surround 
Penetrating Arterioles </p>

<p>The NADH-bounded tissue cylinders were best 
defined in areas surrounding penetrating arterioles 
and we noted their surprisingly large radii of 
54±5 mm (avg.±s.d., n = 90). According to our 
interpretation, this implies radial oxygen diffusion 
distances of &gt; 50 mm, which exceeds known 
intercapillary diffusion distances of r24 mm (Thews,  1960a). In other words, the central penetrating 
arteriole is implied as the sole oxygen source for 
the entire tissue cylinder and consequently any 
further vessels within the tissue cylinder must be 
absent. To test this strong prediction, we conducted 
high-resolution three-dimensional reconstructions of 
the cerebral microvasculature encompassing cortical 
layers I to IV. Indeed, these reconstructions consis-
tently revealed a complete absence of the otherwise 
dense cortical capillary network in the vicinity of 
penetrating arterioles (Figures 6A-6D) extending 
over several hundred micrometers along the length 
axis of penetrating arterioles. The first branching 
point of penetrating arterioles into lower-order 
arterioles was typically observed in cortical layer IV 
(Figures 6E and 6F). The radius of these capillary-
depleted tissue cylinders was 53±9 mm (avg.±s.d., 
n = 48). These vascular reconstructions unequivo-</p>

<p>cally establish penetrating arterioles as major pri-
mary oxygen sources with large radial diffusion 
distances of &gt; 50 mm. The congruity of the capil-
lary-depleted tissue cylinders and the periarteriolar 
NADH-bounded tissue cylinders further confirms </p>

<p>Figure 5 Visualization of pO 2 and nicotinamide adenine 
dinucleotide (NADH) fluorescence within an ideal Krogh tissue 
cylinder. (A) Predicted radial tissue oxygen gradient in an ideal 
Krogh tissue cylinder with boundaries r = 13 mm and 
R = 68 mm. The variable x refers to the radial distance from 
the center of the cylinder. (B) By applying equation (1) as a 
transfer function between tissue pO 2 and NADH tissue 
fluorescence, we can predict the ideal NADH fluorescence 
profile within the tissue cylinder. (C) Corresponding two-
dimensional visualization of oxygen tension and (D) NADH 
fluorescence intensity distribution within the ideal tissue 
cylinder. </p>

<p>Figure 6 Microangiographies reveal capillary-depleted tissue 
cylinders surrounding penetrating arterioles. (A-D) Maximum 
intensity projections of the microcirculation in the somatosen-
sory mouse cortex consistently reveal the striking absence of the 
dense cortical capillary network in an elongated coaxial tissue 
cylinder in the vicinity of penetrating arterioles. The four shown 
horizontal projections were derived from four mice and range 
from cortical layers I to IV. Communicating and penetrating 
arterioles are pseudocolored in red, major venules in blue. The 
corresponding coronal (E) and sagittal (F) projections of the 
angiography stack shown in D confirm the full three-dimensional 
extent of the periarteriolar avascular tissue cylinder with a length 
of B350 mm until lower-order arterioles branch laterally off the 
penetrating arteriole. Scale bars represent 50 mm. </p>

<p>Two-photon NADH imaging of oxygen diffusion 
KA Kasischke et al </p>



<p>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism (2011) 31, 68-81 </p>

<p>our hypothesis that these geometrically delineated 
NADH tissue patterns can be interpreted in terms of 
Krogh tissue cylinders. </p>

<p>Diminished Vascular Supply Regions Under 
Hypoxemic Conditions </p>

<p>The Krogh model predicts that under conditions of 
decreased vascular oxygen supply, the tissue cylin-
ders will be diminished in size and may eventually 
become isolated. This allowed us to directly test our 
interpretation of NADH tissue boundaries as oxygen 
diffusion boundaries by subjecting the mice to 
controlled hypoxemia. We therefore lowered the 
inspired oxygen concentration from 21% to 10% 
for a period of 2 minutes. The resulting drop of the 
pO 2 in the femoral artery from the physiological 
value of 108 ± 9 to 49 ± 11 mm Hg (avg. ± s.d., n = 6 
mice) is sufficient to induce moderate hypoxia </p>

<p>(Xu and LaManna, 2006) in the cerebral cortex. As 
predicted, moderate hypoxia led to an increase in 
NADH fluorescence, which was spatially highly 
heterogeneous. The first changes noted were the 
appearance of NADH tissue patches in tissue regions 
distant to blood vessels. These anoxic micro-
watershed zones gradually expanded towards peri-
vascular tissue regions, unmasking numerous iso-
lated pericapillary tissue cylinders (Figure 7A). 
Accordingly, moderate tissue hypoxia exposed the 
much larger Krogh cylinder surrounding a penetrat-
ing arteriole which branches of a horizontally ori-
ented surface arteriole (Figures 7B-7D). </p>

<p>Heterogeneous Cortical Oxygenation Under Normoxic 
and Hypoxemic Conditions </p>

<p>The observed tissue and vascular geometries can 
now be applied to our adaptation of the Krogh </p>

<p>tissue oxygen [mmHg] </p>

<p>20 
40 
60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>dist. from vessel [µm] </p>

<p>Arterioles 
Normoxia 
Hypoxia </p>

<p>Venules 
Normoxia 
Hypoxia </p>

<p>Capillaries 
Normoxia 
Hypoxia </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>25% </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>Arterioles 
Venules 
Capillaries </p>

<p>Arterioles 
Venules 
Capillaries </p>

<p>Arterioles 
Venules 
Capillaries </p>

<p>Figure 7 Heterogeneous cortical oxygenation under normoxic and hypoxemic conditions. (A) The nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide 
(NADH) tissue pattern under hypoxemic conditions reveals multiple isolated pericapillary tissue cylinders. (B-D) Unmasking of a 
large tissue cylinder surrounding a penetrating arteriole by hypoxemia. (B) Baseline NADH fluorescence under normoxic conditions. 
(C) NADH pattern in the same region during hypoxemia. (D) Pseudocolor visualization of hypoxemia induced NADH percent changes 
between panels B and C. Sketches of the regional arterioles (red), venules (blue), and capillaries (magenta) are superimposed. 
(E) Scatter plot of r and R for all 441 observed Krogh cylinders. (F) Broad range of tissue oxygen spans in vascular supply regions 
under normoxic conditions (21% inspired oxygen). (G) Reduced tissue oxygen spans in vascular supply regions during experimentally 
induced hypoxemia (10% inspired oxygen). (H) Average vascular oxygen tensions under normoxic and hypoxemic conditions. 
(I) Average tissue cylinder radius R under normoxic and hypoxemic conditions. (J) Inferred tissue oxygen gradients within the 
observed vascular supply regions under normoxic (colored plots) and hypoxemic (black plots) conditions. Scale bars in panels A-D 
represent 50 mm. </p>

<p>Two-photon NADH imaging of oxygen diffusion 
KA Kasischke et al </p>



<p>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism (2011) 31, 68-81 </p>

<p>model. From our total of 441 observations of the 
Krogh tissue cylinder radius R and the center vessel 
radius r (Figure 7E), the tissue oxygen span T 0 -T R 
ranging from the vessel wall to the edge of the Krogh 
cylinder within a given vascular supply region can 
be derived according to equation (6). The broad 
oxygen spans inferred from our observations (Figure 
7F) under normoxic conditions are in general 
agreement with the regional distribution of our direct 
polarographic oxygen measurements in layer I 
(Supplementary Figure S3) and with previous oxy-
gen measurements (Ndubuizu and LaManna, 2007). 
However, we cannot directly relate polarographic 
measurements to inferred oxygen gradients because 
the exact three-dimensional location of the electrode 
tip with respect to nearby microvessels is unknown. 
Thus, direct electrode measurements cannot be 
assigned to a specific vascular supply region with 
certainty. A further assignment to a defined position 
within a given vascular supply region seem even 
more problematic, especially when considering 
the uncertainties regarding the sensitive volume of 
oxygen electrodes. 
With T R B3.4 mm Hg, equation (7) yields average 
vascular oxygen tensions of 94 ± 18 mm Hg (s.d.) 
for arterioles, 28 ± 11 mm Hg for capillaries, and 
38±13 mm Hg for venules in cortical layer I under 
normoxic conditions (Figure 7H, top). We can further 
determine the average diffusion distances for each 
vessel type (Figure 7I). Our numbers are in good 
agreement with direct measurements of surface 
(Vovenko, 1999) and perivascular (Duling et al,  1979) oxygen tensions of arterioles, venules, and 
capillaries in the mammalian brain. We observed 
capillary oxygen levels slightly below venous oxygen 
tension as has been reported previously (Vovenko,  1999). Possible explanations could be the existence 
of arterio-venous shunting in the cortical circulation 
or more likely a selection bias caused by the masking 
of pericapillary NADH gradients because of 
highly overlapping capillary oxygen supply regions 
in well-oxygenated tissue volumes (Wang and  Bassingthwaigthe, 2001). 
Using our model, we can provide a quantitative 
description of the complex changes in cortical 
oxygenation between normoxia (PaO 2 108 ± 9 mm Hg) 
and moderate cortical hypoxia (PaO 2 49±11 mm Hg). 
We observed a considerable reduction of tissue 
oxygen spans (compare Figures 7F and 7G) and a 
drop of vascular pO 2 to 45±16 mm Hg (avg.±s.d.)  in arterioles, 10±5 mm Hg in capillaries, and 
10 ± 6 mm Hg in venules (Figure 7H). The drop of 
the inferred vascular pO 2 reached unambiguous 
significance levels (P50.001) with high statistical 
power ( &gt; 0.99) for all three vessel types. We can 
further quantify the radial shrinkage of vascular 
supply regions (Figure 7I) and diminished tissue 
oxygen gradients (Figure 7J). Notably, complete 
tissue cylinders with diameters of B60 to 100 mm 
surrounding penetrating arterioles remain ade-
quately oxygenated under hypoxemic conditions. </p>

<p>This is illustrated in the example shown in Figure 
7D. An implication with possible clinical relevance 
is that significant periarteriolar cortex volumes are 
not directly affected by moderate cortical hypoxia. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We describe well-defined cylindrical patterns of 
NADH tissue fluorescence in the mouse cortex and 
their close spatial association with the regional 
microcirculation. We propose that the observed 
NADH tissue boundaries provide the physical re-
presentation of tissue boundaries of oxygen diffusion 
from the cortical microcirculation. Our interpreta-
tion further implies that we can expose cortical 
vascular supply regions, localize functionally rele-
vant microregional cortical hypoxia and infer micro-
regional cortical oxygenation with cubic micron 
spatial resolution. Such three-dimensional spatially 
resolved observations are not feasible with existing 
methodologies. </p>

<p>Interpretation of Cylindrical Nicotinamide Adenine 
Dinucleotide Tissue Patterns as Oxygen Diffusion 
Boundaries </p>

<p>Our experimental observations that NADH tissue 
boundaries exhibit a well-defined cylindrical geo-
metry and enclose a coaxial central blood vessel are 
independent of any theory, model, or assumption. 
The probability that such distinct vascular and tissue 
geometries emerge by chance is infinitely small and 
their strong resemblance to the ideal Krogh tissue 
cylinder implies an underlying relationship to tissue 
oxygen diffusion. This relationship is further vali-
dated by the congruity of NADH-bounded tissue 
cylinders and capillary-depleted tissue cylinders 
surrounding penetrating arterioles and by the ex-
posure of diminished vascular supply regions under 
hypoxemic conditions. 
An important consideration is that elevated NADH 
tissue fluorescence could also be explained by 
metabolic state 4, a condition that is characterized 
by low ADP levels as a result of decreased energy 
demand (Chance and Williams, 1955). The reason is 
that both metabolic states 4 and 5 (rate limiting 
hypoxia) are characterized by high levels of NADH. 
However, state 4 is aerobic, whereas state 5 is 
anaerobic. Thus, tissue in state 4 would not exhibit 
the cylindrical geometry of an oxygen diffusion 
boundary observed in our experiments. </p>

<p>Advantages and Limitations of Our Approach </p>

<p>The Krogh model is a steady-state model and does 
not afford a measure of cerebral blood flow. The 
NADH-bounded tissue cylinders will be observed 
under any condition where the local pO 2 is close to 
p 50 , regardless of the underlying factors contributing </p>

<p>Two-photon NADH imaging of oxygen diffusion 
KA Kasischke et al </p>



<p>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism (2011) 31, 68-81 </p>

<p>to this oxygenation status. Thus, although our 
imaging approach allows us to resolve microregional 
hypoxia with cubic micron resolution, it does not 
afford direct information on the nature of the under-
lying physiological or pathophysiological condition. 
An inherent advantage of our approach is the fact 
that the localization of oxygen diffusion boundaries 
is solely based on the direct recognition of cylind-
rical NADH tissue boundaries in our images and is 
therefore independent of any assumptions regarding 
the metabolic rate p and the diffusion constant K. 
Accordingly, our estimate of the oxygen level p 50 at 
the diffusion boundary R depends only on the 
experimentally derived calibration curve shown in 
Figure 1D and its analysis using equation (1), 
regardless of p and K. In contrast, our estimates of 
the pO 2 in the central blood vessel and the 
surrounding tissue oxygen gradients are derived 
from the Krogh-Erlang equation (3) and are therefore 
linearly dependent on the assumed values for the 
metabolic rate p and the diffusion constant K. 
The simple, ideal Krogh model is directly applic-
able to the special case of the penetrating arterioles, 
with unilateral blood flow in parallel, linear vessels 
that are depleted of surrounding capillaries. 
Obviously, the Krogh model has limitations for 
primarily capillary networks with convoluted and 
asymmetric perfusion (Krogh, 1919; Fletcher, 1978). 
The concern is that capillary domains, which are a 
descriptive measure of capillary spacing, and asso-
ciated capillary supply regions are not congruent 
(Wang and Bassingthwaigthe, 2001). Thus, a more 
uniform oxygen distribution would be expected, 
challenging the wide span of tissue oxygen levels 
as predicted by the Krogh model. However, refined 
mathematical descriptions with objectively mea-
sured vascular geometries and flow relationships 
are frequently beyond analytical solutions and have 
not yet afforded a significantly improved correlation 
with experimental measurements (Thews, 1960a;  Fletcher, 1978; Mintun et al, 2001). Indeed, numer-
ous studies confirm highly nonuniform oxygen 
distribution in the cortex, and it has been suggested 
that microregional oxygen gradients provide a more 
appropriate representation of the actual cortical 
oxygenation in contrast to regionally averaged oxy-
gen tensions (Ndubuizu and LaManna, 2007). 
High-resolution optical imaging of all forms is 
constrained by the optical properties (absorption and 
scattering) of tissue. Although the near infrared 
two-photon excitation can penetrate to depths 
corresponding to layer IV, the blue/green NADH 
fluorescence originating at this depth is rapidly 
attenuated by scattering and the intense absorption 
of hemoglobin at these wavelengths. This difficulty 
is amplified by the low two-photon absorption cross-
section of NADH (0.07 GM at 710 nm), which is 
1/100 to 1/1000 the magnitude of conventional fluo-
rophores (Kasischke et al, 2004). For these reasons, 
it appears fundamentally impossible to image NADH 
fluorescence in the deeper cortical layers. </p>

<p>Direct Arteriolar Contribution to Cortical Oxygen 
Supply </p>

<p>We have established that the arteriolar system is 
largely responsible for the heterogeneous oxygen 
distribution and even shapes the capillary distribu-
tion in the cortex. Most prominently, penetrating 
arterioles, which are perfectly positioned to regulate 
the delivery of blood to cortical columns (Nishimura  et al, 2007), are the exclusive oxygen source for 
capillary-depleted coaxial tissue cylinders with 
diameters well above 100 mm and which extend from 
cortical layers I to IV. 
The persistence of physiologically adequate peri-
arteriolar oxygen gradients during experimentally 
induced moderate cortical hypoxia in our experi-
ments may further explain the distinct distribution 
of microstrokes in autoradiographic and histological 
studies of ischemic (Welsh et al, 1977) or hypoxemic 
(Pulsinelli and Duffy, 1979) mammalian cortex. In 
these studies, investigators noted sparing of the 
region surrounding penetrating arterioles, and hy-
pothesized that persistence of periarteriolar tissue 
oxygen gradients in the hypoxic brain might account 
for this, which is confirmed by our data. The 
pathophysiological relevance of perivascular tissue 
oxygen gradients was further substantiated in clini-
cally more relevant stroke models, where focal 
cerebral ischemia in primates preferentially affected 
neurons distant from their neighboring microvessels 
(Mabuchi et al, 2005). </p>

<p>Possible Physiological Relevance of Microregional 
Tissue Hypoxia in the Cortex </p>

<p>Our results support the notion that a significant 
fraction of cortical neurons exist normally in a low 
oxygen environment (Gjedde, 2002; Ndubuizu and  LaManna, 2007). Under such conditions, cortical 
oxygenation must be closely regulated within the 
limits of normal brain function and any focal 
increase in the cerebral metabolic rate or a reduction 
in vascular oxygen supply would inevitably increase 
the likelihood of hypoxia in cortical watershed 
regions. Microregional tissue hypoxia would also 
contribute to elevated lactate levels in the focally 
stimulated brain (Prichard et al, 1991; Sappey- Marinier et al, 1992). In this context, our results 
raise the question whether the watershed areas 
observed under our cranial window preparations 
are physiological phenomena and may further be 
related to the natural function of the cerebrovascular 
control system. 
For example, the possibility that mitochondria 
sense a declining oxygen tension and directly or 
indirectly trigger a blood flow increase (Gjedde,  2002) is in agreement with recent studies that have 
posited a regulatory role for the redox state of neural 
cells on cerebral blood flow (Ido et al, 2004;  Vlassenko et al, 2006). The cellular redox state is 
determined by the cytosolic NADH/NAD 
+ ratio, </p>

<p>Two-photon NADH imaging of oxygen diffusion 
KA Kasischke et al </p>



<p>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism (2011) 31, 68-81 </p>

<p>which exists in near-equilibrium with the intracel-
lular lactate/pyruvate ratio. Thus, the proposed 
mechanism is that increased cytosolic NADH will 
increase the electron transfer from NADH to oxidized 
enzymes in signaling pathways that activate consti-
tutive nitric oxide synthase to increase cerebral 
blood flow. Under hypoxic conditions, cytosolic 
NADH will be maximally elevated because of 
increased anaerobic glycolysis and cessation of its 
reoxidation to NAD </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>by mitochondrial electron 
shuttling. In this scenario, microregional tissue 
patches with elevated NADH levels would activate 
signaling cascades, which increase cerebral blood 
flow with a subsequent increase in microregional 
tissue oxygen levels, ultimately linking tissue meta-
bolic states to the hemodynamic response. 
Future applications of concurrent two-photon 
fluorescence imaging of endogenous NADH and the 
cortical microcirculation may allow for the inclusive 
investigation of neurometabolic and neurovascular 
coupling and expose the role of inadequate or 
restricted tissue oxygen supply in neurovascular 
diseases and the aging brain. </p>

<p>Disclosure/conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>



<p>Two-photon NADH imaging of oxygen diffusion 
KA Kasischke et al </p>



<p>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism (2011) 31, 68-81 </p>



<p>Two-photon NADH imaging of oxygen diffusion 
KA Kasischke et al </p>



<p>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism (2011) 31, 68-81 </p>

</text></tei>