<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3727320" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Oxidative stress plays an important role in cancer development and treatment. Recent data 
implicate the tumor suppressor BRCA1 in regulating oxidative stress, but the molecular 
mechanism and the impact in BRCA1-associated tumorigenesis remain unclear. Here, we 
show that BRCA1 regulates Nrf2-dependent antioxidant signaling by physically interacting 
with Nrf2 and promoting its stability and activation. BRCA1-deficient mouse primary 
mammary epithelial cells show low expression of Nrf2-regulated antioxidant enzymes and 
accumulate reactive oxygen species (ROS) that impair survival in vivo. Increased Nrf2 
activation rescues survival and ROS levels in BRCA1-null cells. Interestingly, 53BP1 inacti-
vation, which has been shown to alleviate several defects associated with BRCA1 loss, 
rescues survival of BRCA1-null cells without restoring ROS levels. We demonstrate that 
estrogen treatment partially restores Nrf2 levels in the absence of BRCA1. Our data sug-
gest that Nrf2-regulated antioxidant response plays a crucial role in controlling survival 
downstream of BRCA1 loss. The ability of estrogen to induce Nrf2 posits an involvement 
of an estrogen-Nrf2 connection in BRCA1 tumor suppression. Lastly, BRCA1-mutated 
tumors retain a defective antioxidant response that increases the sensitivity to oxidative 
stress. In conclusion, the role of BRCA1 in regulating Nrf2 activity suggests important 
implications for both the etiology and treatment of BRCA1-related cancers. </p>



<p>Role of Nrf2 in BRCA1-related cancers | Gorrini et al. </p>

<p>is the result of impaired Nrf2-driven antioxidant signaling. 
We demonstrated that BRCA1 is a novel Nrf2-binding pro-
tein that affects Keap1-mediated Nrf2 ubiquitination activity, 
thereby controlling Nrf2 stability and activation. In BRCA1-
deficient cells, up-regulation of the Nrf2-mediated antioxi-
dant pathway through inactivation of Keap1 rescues cell 
survival defects and ROS levels induced by BRCA1 loss-of-
function. Interestingly, human BRCA1-mutated breast tumor 
cells also retain a defective Nrf2 antioxidant response that im-
pinges on their sensitivity to oxidative stress and cisplatin treat-
ment. Our work establishes a physiological function of BRCA1 
in ROS regulation in the mammary gland and sheds light on 
the role of oxidative stress in BRCA1-mediated tumor sup-
pression with important therapeutic implications. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
BRCA1 loss-of-function in MECs causes ROS accumulation 
To investigate the link between BRCA1 expression and ROS 
levels in MECs, we down-regulated Brca1 in immortalized 
mouse mammary COMMA-1D cells using a doxycycline 
(dox)-inducible lentiviral shRNA (Fig. 1 A). As shown in 
Fig. 1 B, cells with low Brca1 expression (+dox) had high 
ROS levels compared with dox-untreated cells (dox). Con-
sistent with this result, ROS also accumulated in human 
MECs (HMECs) infected with a lentiviral shRNA against 
human BRCA1 (shBRCA1) compared with cells expressing 
an shRNA directed toward Luciferase (Luc; shLUC) used as 
control (Fig. 1, C and D).  We next determined ROS levels in Brca1-deficient pri-
mary MECs (pMECs) using a previously generated Brca1 
conditional knockout mouse (B1 f/f ) carrying a cre-inducible 
deletion of Brca1 exons 5-13 (Liu et al., 2007). Targeted Brca1 
deletion to the mammary gland epithelium was achieved by 
crossing B1 f/f mice to K14cre mice (Jonkers et al., 2001) to 
obtain K14cre;Brca1 f/f mice (KB1 f/f ) along with K14cre (K) 
and K14cre;Bf/+ (KB1 f/+ ) control mice. K14 is mainly expressed 
in mammary stem cells (MaSCs) and basal cells (Shackleton  et al., 2006). However, analysis of pMECs isolated from fe-
males obtained by crossing K14cre mice with a transgenic strain 
expressing the red fluorescent protein Tomato (Muzumdar  et al., 2007) showed that K14cre was active in both MaSCs/ 
basal and luminal cells (not depicted). PCR with genomic DNA 
from pMECs isolated from #4 mammary glands of B1 +/+ , 
B1 f/+ , B1 f/f , and KB1 f/f mice showed cre-mediated deletion of 
Brca1 exons 5-13 only in KB1 f/f samples (Fig. 1 E). Quantitative 
PCR (qPCR) with genomic DNA confirmed a significant re-
duction of Brca1 WT allele in KB1 f/f pMECs (Fig. 1 F), which 
correlated with low Brca1 mRNA expression in KB1 f/f pMECs 
compared with K and KB1 f/+ controls (Fig. 1 G). Consequently, 
KB1 f/f pMECs also had low Brca1 protein levels (Fig. 1 H). 
Intracellular ROS staining showed that KB1 f/f pMECs had 
higher ROS than K and KB1 f/+ pMECs (Fig. 1 I). 
Mammary glands contain distinct cell subpopulations that 
vary in their repopulating capacity and differentiation mark-
ers (Shackleton et al., 2006; Stingl et al., 2006). Immunostain-
ing of pMECs with antibodies (Abs) specific for the epithelial </p>

<p>the antioxidant enzymes SOD2, GLS2, and SEPHS1 are required 
for in vivo mammary tumorigenesis (Possemato et al., 2011). 
ROS detoxifying enzymes are predominantly driven by 
the transcription factor Nrf2 (NF-E2-related factor 2), which 
is tightly regulated by Keap1 (KELCH-like ECH-associated 
protein 1)-mediated ubiquitination (Kobayashi et al., 2004). 
Oncogenic events that regulate Nrf2 transcription or alter its 
protein stability would presumably provide a survival advan-
tage. Indeed, oncogenic K-Ras or c-Myc transcriptionally 
regulates Nrf2 to activate an antioxidant program and lower 
intracellular ROS that is required for cell proliferation and 
tumorigenesis (DeNicola et al., 2011). Nrf2 has also been im-
plicated in controlling cell proliferation downstream of the 
hyperactivated oncogenic PI3K/Akt pathway (Mitsuishi et al.,  2012). In breast cancer, deregulation of NRF2 stability by 
KEAP1 silencing through promoter hypermethylation has 
been recently reported in a subset of tumors that are more 
frequently estrogen receptor (ER) positive and human epi-
dermal growth factor receptor 2 negative (Barbano et al.,  2013). Although KEAP1 mutations are rare, genome-wide 
sequencing of human breast cancers identified a KEAP1 
mutation (C23Y) that disrupts its interaction with NRF2, 
leading to increased NRF2 protein stability and antioxidant 
signaling in a subset of human breast cancers (Sjöblom et al.,  2006; Nioi and Nguyen, 2007). 
Loss-of-function mutations in the tumor suppressor gene 
BRCA1 account for 5-10% of breast cancer cases in the 
Western world and confer increased risk for development of 
ovarian cancer (Narod and Foulkes, 2004). Because these tu-
mors are characterized by high genomic instability, lack of 
DNA repair as the result of BRCA1 inactivation is consid-
ered the main cause of tumor formation. However, new func-
tions of BRCA1 such as the regulation of the oncogenic 
microRNA 155 (Chang et al., 2011), the maintenance of het-
erochromatin structure (Zhu et al., 2011), and the modulation 
of oxidative stress (Vurusaner et al., 2012) have been recently 
discovered. In the context of oxidative stress, BRCA1 over-
expression in human breast cancer cells up-regulates several 
antioxidant genes and reduces H 2 O 2 -induced DNA damage 
and apoptosis (Bae et al., 2004; Saha et al., 2009). Although 
Brca1 loss-of-function in mouse embryonic fibroblasts from 
Brca1 11/11 mutant mice shows higher ROS levels than cells 
from Brca1 WT mice and is more sensitive to apoptosis induced 
by oxidative stress (Cao et al., 2007), the mechanism by which 
BRCA1 regulates oxidative stress and its impact in BRCA1-
associated tumorigenesis has not been fully uncovered. 
In this study, we investigated the link between BRCA1 
and oxidative stress both in normal MECs and in breast tu-
mors. We used a Brca1 conditional knockout mouse (Liu et al.,  2007) to specifically delete the Brca1 gene in the mammary 
gland. Although Brca1 deletion under the control of K14-or 
K6a-driven cre recombinase does not lead to any observable 
changes in the mammary gland (Liu et al., 2007; Smart et al.,  2011), our study of primary and immortalized mouse and 
human BRCA1-deficient MECs shows that BRCA1 defi-
ciency results in ROS accumulation in these cells. This effect </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 210, No. 8 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>When we evaluated Nrf2 expression in KB1 f/f pMECs, 
we found that both mRNA (Fig. 2 A) and protein levels 
(Fig. 2 B) were significantly lower in Brca1-deficient cells 
compared with control cells (B1 f/f ). These data are supported 
by previous findings that BRCA1 binds the Nrf2 promoter 
and regulates its transcription (Kang et al., 2011). Consistent 
with low Nrf2 expression, KB1 f/f pMECs showed reduced 
mRNA levels of the Nrf2 transcriptional targets Nqo1 and 
Hmox1 compared with controls (Fig. 2, C and D). 
We next determined whether BRCA1 expression also 
regulated Nrf2 levels and activity in response to exogenous 
oxidative stress in vitro. COMMA-1D cells were treated with 
l-buthionine-sulfoximine (BSO), a specific inhibitor of glu-
tathione synthesis (Griffith, 1999; Marí et al., 2009). BSO 
treatment resulted in ROS accumulation (not depicted) and 
Nrf2 protein accumulation (Fig. 2 E) with no change of Nrf2 
mRNA levels (Fig. 2 F). Interestingly, Brca1 silencing by specific </p>

<p>surface markers CD24 and CD49f ( Joshi et al., 2010) revealed 
that both KB1 f/f MaSC-enriched basal cells (CD24 + CD49f high ) 
and luminal cells (CD24 + CD49f low ) showed elevated ROS 
compared with B1 f/f controls (Fig. 1 J). Together, these results 
demonstrate that in MECs, both in vitro and in vivo down-
regulation of BRCA1 expression induce accumulation of in-
tracellular ROS levels. </p>

<p>BRCA1-deficient cells have a reduced 
Nrf2-mediated antioxidant response 
Intracellular ROS levels can be regulated by the activity of 
antioxidant enzymes whose expression depends on the tran-
scription factor Nrf2 (Kensler and Wakabayashi, 2010). Al-
though Nrf2 activation is mainly controlled by protein stability 
(Li and Kong, 2009), recent data suggest that Nrf2 mRNA 
expression is also important in regulating Nrf2 activity (Kwak  et al., 2002; DeNicola et al., 2011; Yang et al., 2011). </p>

<p>Figure 1. BRCA1 loss-of-function induces high ROS levels in MECs. (A) Brca1 mRNA expression in COMMA-1D cells infected with dox-inducible 
Brca1 shRNA and treated (+dox) or not (dox) with dox. (B) Quantitation of ROS in COMMA-1D cells as processed in A. (C) BRCA1 mRNA levels in HMECs 
infected with Luc shRNA (control) or BRCA1 shRNA. (D) Quantitation of ROS in HMEC as treated in C. (A-D) Data represent the mean ± SEM of three bio-
logical replicates. (E) Representative PCR with genomic DNA isolated from B1 +/+ , B1 f/+ , B1 f/f , and KB1 f/f pMECs using specific primers for detection of Brca1 
WT allele, loxP site in intron 3 (F), or cre-mediated deleted allele (). Primers are described in Liu et al. (2007) and Table S1. (F) qPCR with genomic DNA 
from K, KB1 f/+ , and KB1 f/f pMECs using specific primers directed against Brca1 WT allele as reported in Table S1. (G) BRCA1 mRNA levels in K, KB1 f/+ , and 
KB1 f/f pMECs. (H) Representative analysis of BRCA1 protein levels in K and KB1 f/f pMECs. Vinculin was used as a loading control. (I) ROS levels in K, KB1 f/+ , 
and KB1 f/f pMECs. (F, G, and I) Data represent the mean ± SEM of n = 5 mice of each genotype. (J) Representative FACS profile of ROS levels in MaSC/basal 
and luminal cell subpopulations in B1 f/f and KB1 f/f pMECs stained with DCF-DA. *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01. </p>



<p>Role of Nrf2 in BRCA1-related cancers | Gorrini et al. </p>

<p>the notion that BRCA1 may be an Nrf2 transcriptional target 
gene regulated through an antioxidant response element in 
the BRCA1 promoter (Wang et al., 2013). Overall, our data 
suggest the existence of a positive feedback loop regulation 
between BRCA1 and Nrf2 that may be necessary for an effi-
cient cellular antioxidant response. </p>

<p>BRCA1 interacts with Nrf2 and promotes its stability 
Nrf2 protein is tightly regulated by Keap1, a substrate adap-
tor for Cul3-based E3 ubiquitin ligase (Li and Kong, 2009). 
Under resting conditions, Keap1 binding triggers Nrf2 ubiq-
uitination and degradation. Under oxidative stress con-
ditions, Keap1 is oxidized on specific cysteine residues, which 
affect Nrf2 binding, thereby preventing Nrf2 degradation 
and resulting in transactivation of Nrf2-dependent anti-
oxidant genes. </p>

<p>siRNAs (siBRCA1) negatively affected both BSO-induced 
Nrf2 protein increase (Fig. 2 E) and Nrf2 mRNA expression 
in both untreated (control) and BSO-treated cells (Fig. 2 F). 
Brca1 inactivation also resulted in down-regulation of the Nrf2 
target genes Nqo1 and Hmox1 after BSO treatment (Fig. 2 G). 
We found that oxidative stress induced by BSO also in-
creased Brca1 mRNA (Fig. 2 G) and protein (Fig. 2 H) levels. 
BRCA1 expression has been shown to be regulated in a 
cell cycle-dependent manner (Chen et al., 1996). However, 
Brca1 up-regulation by BSO was not caused by cell cycle 
changes (Fig. 2 I), but rather by high ROS levels because co-
treatment of BSO with a vitamin E-derived antioxidant, 
Trolox (Davies et al., 1988), abrogated Brca1 mRNA accumu-
lation (Fig. 2 J). Of note, Brca1 expression was down-regulated 
in COMMA-1D cells treated with Nrf2 siRNA, similarly to 
Nrf2-target NQO1 (Fig. 2 K). These results further support </p>

<p>Figure 2. Brca1 expression is regulated by oxidative stress and controls Nrf2 abundance and transactivation activity. (A) Nrf2 mRNA levels in 
B1 f/f and KB1 f/f pMECs. (B) Representative immunoblot of Nrf2 protein levels in pMECs from B1 f/f (n = 2) and KB1 f/f (n = 3) mice. Western blot quantitation 
is shown below. (C and D) RT-PCR analysis of Nrf2 targets, Nqo1 (C) and Hmox1 (D), in B1 f/f and KB1 f/f pMECs. (A, C, and D) Data are the mean ± SEM 
of n = 5 mice of each genotype. (E) Representative immunoblot of Nrf2 protein levels in control (Con) or BSO-treated COMMA-1D cells after transfection 
with scrambled siRNA (siScr) or Brca1-specific siRNA (siBrca1). (F) Nrf2 mRNA levels in cells treated as in E. (G) Expression levels of Nqo1, Hmox1, and 
Brca1 mRNAs in cells treated as in E. (H) Representative immunoblot of Brca1 protein levels in control and BSO-treated COMMA-1D cells. Vinculin was 
used as a loading control. (I) Representative cell cycle profile by PI staining of control or BSO (1 or 2 mM)-treated COMMA-1D cells. (J) Brca1 mRNA levels 
in COMMA-1D cells that have been left untreated (Con) or after treatment with Trolox, BSO, and Trolox plus BSO for 48 h. (K) Nqo1 and Brca1 mRNA ex-
pression in untreated COMMA-1D cells transfected with scrambled siRNA or Nrf2-specific siRNA (siNrf2). (F, G, J, and K) Data represent the mean ± SEM 
of three biological replicates. *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 210, No. 8 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>endogenous interaction was also found using an affinity-purified 
Ab against mouse Brca1 (Fig. 3 C; Bouwman et al., 2010). 
To determine whether BRCA1 interfered with Keap1-
mediated Nrf2 ubiquitination, we performed an in vivo ubiqui-
tination assay by transfecting 293FT cells with GFP-NRF2, 
His-KEAP1, and HA-ubiquitin, with or without Myc-BRCA1. 
As shown in Fig. 3 D, Keap1-mediated ubiquitination of 
GFP-NRF2 was abrogated by Myc-BRCA1 overexpression. 
Myc-BRCA1 was unable to dissociate the NRF2-KEAP1 
complex because His-KEAP1 equally immunoprecipitated 
using GFP-NRF2 with or without Myc-BRCA1 (Fig. 3 D). 
Thus, upon oxidative stress, BRCA1 up-regulation interferes 
with KEAP1-mediated NRF2 ubiquitination, resulting in 
NRF2 protein accumulation. </p>

<p>We determined whether down-regulation of Nrf2 protein 
levels in Brca1-deficient cells was not only caused by low 
mRNA expression but also a consequence of low protein stabil-
ity. GFP-tagged NRF2 and Myc-tagged BRCA1 were tran-
siently overexpressed in 293FT cells in the presence or absence 
of BSO to induce oxidative stress. GFP-NRF2 was detected in 
Myc-BRCA1 immunoprecipitates, and complex formation was 
increased by oxidative stress (Fig. 3 A). Similarly to GFP-NRF2, 
Myc-BRCA1 accumulated upon BSO treatment, suggesting 
the involvement of posttranslational regulation of exogenously 
expressed BRCA1 in the presence of oxidative stress. 
Endogenous Brca1-Nrf2 interaction was confirmed by re-
ciprocal Brca1 and Nrf2 immunoprecipitations in control 
and BSO-treated COMMA-1D cells (Fig. 3 B). The mutual </p>

<p>Figure 3. BRCA1 physically interacts with Nrf2 and affects Keap1-mediated Nrf2 ubiquitination. (A) 293FT cells were transfected with Myc-BRCA1 
and GFP-NRF2 constructs and then left untreated (Con) or treated with BSO. BRCA1 was immunoprecipitated with anti-Myc Ab. The blot was probed with 
anti-Myc and anti-GFP Abs. "" indicates untreated EV control. Vinculin was used as a loading control. (B) COMMA-1D cells were left untreated (Con) or 
treated with BSO and processed for immunoprecipitation (IP) with anti-Nrf2 (H-300) or anti-Brca1 (C20) Abs to detect the endogenous Brca1 and Nrf2 
proteins. (C) COMMA-1D cells were treated as in B and subjected to immunoprecipitation with anti-mouse Brca1 Ab to detect endogenous Brca1 and 
Nrf2 complex. Nrf2 was detected with an affinity-purified Ab as described in Materials and methods. (B and C) IgG served as an isotype control. (D) 293FT 
cells were transfected with constructs expressing HA-ubiquitin, His-KEAP1, GFP-NRF2, and/or Myc-BRCA1 (as indicated). Immunoprecipitation was per-
formed with anti-GFP Ab followed by Western blot to detect ubiquitinated NRF2 (HA, GFP) and His-KEAP1. (E) 293FT cells were transfected with Myc-
BRCA1, His-KEAP1, HA-WT NRF2 (WT), HA-79 EGTE NRF2 mutant ( 79 EGTE), and HA-29 DLG NRF2 mutant ( 29 DLG). Immunoprecipitation was performed with 
anti-HA Ab, and Western blot was probed with anti-Myc and anti-His Abs. The asterisk indicates an unspecific band. </p>



<p>Role of Nrf2 in BRCA1-related cancers | Gorrini et al. </p>

<p>confirmed similar CK14 and Luc signals in both KLuc f/+ and 
KB1 f/f Luc f/+ outgrowths (Fig. 4 E). Whole-mount staining 
with carmine aluminum of 4-wk-old outgrowths from KLuc f/+ 
and KB1 f/f Luc f/+ pMECs did not reveal any major morpho-
logical differences (Fig. 4 F). However, the repopulation defects 
reached a dramatic phenotype at 24 wk after transplantation. 
As shown by hematoxylin-eosin staining at 24 wk after injec-
tion, normal ducts were present in outgrowths from KLuc f/+ 
cells, whereas outgrowths from KB1 f/f Luc f/+ cells showed dis-
organized ductal structures (Fig. 4 G). 
Both BRCA1 loss and high ROS levels have been associ-
ated with cellular senescence and DNA damage. Interestingly, 
compared with control KLuc f/+ pMECs, KB1 f/f Luc f/+ pMECs 
from 8-wk-old outgrowths showed increased mRNA levels 
of the senescence markers p16/INK4A and p19/ARF (Fig. 4, 
H and I) and evidence of DNA damage as measured by 
H2AX staining (Fig. 4 J). Loss of Brca1 can also lead to up-
regulation of the cell cycle arrest gene p21/Cdkn1a (Hakem  et al., 1996, 1997). However, KB1 f/f Luc f/+ pMECs did not show 
any increase in p21 expression (Fig. 4 K). These data demon-
strate that Brca1-deficient pMECs initially survive in vivo trans-
plantation in the clear mammary fat pad but soon lose their 
repopulation capacity as a result of the onset of senescence, pre-
sumably triggered by DNA damage and ROS accumulation. </p>

<p>Nrf2 activation restores ROS levels and survival 
in Brca1-deficient MECs 
We next determined whether constitutive Nrf2 activation could 
rescue Brca1-dependent ROS accumulation and in vivo sur-
vival defects. COMMA-1D cells were infected with lentiviral 
shRNA against Keap1 to stabilize and activate Nrf2. As 
expected, Keap1 shRNA-infected cells (Keap1 shRNA) had 
low Keap1 expression (Fig. 5 A) and elevated expression of 
Nqo1 (Fig. 5 D and not depicted) compared with empty vec-
tor (EV) control. EV-and Keap1 shRNA-infected cells were 
subsequently transfected with scrambled siRNAs (siScr) or 
Brca1 siRNA (siBrca1), and ROS levels were measured. As 
shown in Fig. 5 D, Keap1 silencing lowered ROS levels in 
control siScr cells but to a greater extent in siBrca1 cells. To 
evaluate whether modulation of ROS levels was caused by 
Nrf2 activation, we measured Nqo1 expression in the same 
transfected cell lines. Keap1 shRNA significantly increased 
Nqo1 levels both in siScr and siBrca1 cells (Fig. 5 E). 
53BP1 inactivation has been shown to rescue the prolif-
erative defects associated with BRCA1 loss-of-function. 
In particular, 53BP1 loss alleviates G2/M cell cycle arrest, 
ATM-dependent checkpoint response, and genomic insta-
bility (Cao et al., 2009; Bouwman et al., 2010; Bunting et al.,  2010). To investigate the impact of 53BP1 loss on ROS reg-
ulation, we used COMMA1-D cells infected with 53bp1 
shRNA and cotransfected with siScr or siBrca1 (Fig. 5, B 
and C). Surprisingly, 53bp1 shRNA did not affect intracel-
lular ROS levels in control cells or alleviate ROS accumula-
tion caused by Brca1 down-regulation (Fig. 5 C). In addition, 
53bp1 shRNA did not alter Nqo1 down-regulation caused 
by Brca1 siRNA (Fig. 5 D). </p>

<p>The capacity of BRCA1 to interfere with KEAP1-mediated 
NRF2 ubiquitination prompted us to evaluate which domain 
of NRF2 protein mediated the binding to BRCA1. NRF2 
and KEAP1 interaction is based on a two-site substrate recog-
nition model at two distinct domains of NRF2, the ETGE 
and DLG motifs, known as the "hinge and latch mechanism" 
(Li and Kong, 2009). We determined the possibility that BRCA1 
interfered with KEAP1 binding to one of these two domains. 
HA-tagged WT NRF2 and HA-tagged NRF2 mutants 
where the 29 DLG or 79 ETGE motif were replaced with ala-
nine residues (Chen et al., 2009) were expressed in 293FT 
cells along with Myc-BRCA1 and His-KEAP1. Immunopre-
cipitation of HA-tagged NRF2 proteins showed that muta-
tion of 79 ETGE diminished both KEAP1 and BRCA1 binding 
to NRF2, whereas replacement of 29 DLG did not affect either 
KEAP1 or BRCA1 affinity for NRF2 (Fig. 3 E). 
As previously reported, the ETGE domain is the strongest 
interacting motif between Nrf2 and Keap1 compared with 
the DLG motifs (Chen et al., 2009). Our data postulate a sce-
nario in which BRCA1 interferes with the conformational 
dynamics of NRF2-KEAP1 interaction at the ETGE site, 
thus affecting NRF2 ubiquitination and stability. </p>

<p>Brca1-deficient pMECs have a limited lifespan in vivo 
Antioxidant signaling and efficient DNA repair are essential 
for hematopoietic stem cell self-renewal (Pang, 2011). Simi-
larly, high oxidative stress caused by ATM deficiency triggers 
senescence and limits long-term in vivo repopulation of the 
hematopoietic compartment (Ito et al., 2004). ROS levels 
have been demonstrated to regulate mammary stem/progeni-
tor cell function (Diehn et al., 2009). To determine in vivo 
whether MaSC functions were impaired by ROS accumula-
tion associated with BRCA1 deficiency, we subjected pMECs 
to a mammary fat pad transplantation assay. 
One of the most unique features of mammary gland stud-
ies is the ability to transplant pMECs into their normal micro-
environment and assess their in vivo growth and differentiation 
capabilities (Smith and Medina, 2008). To track transplanted 
pMECs in vivo, we crossed KB1 f/f mice with Luc-expressing 
transgenic mice (Safran et al., 2003) and generated B1 f/f Luc f/+ 
(negative control), KLuc f/+ , and KB1 f/f Luc f/+ progeny (Fig. 4 A). 
In KB1 f/f Luc f/+ mice, K14cre activation controls both Luc ex-
pression and Brca1 deletion. pMECs isolated from B1 f/f Luc f/+ , 
KLuc f/+ , and KB1 f/f Luc f/+ mice were injected into precleared 
mammary fat pads of isogenic 21-d-old FVB recipient mice. 
Anesthetized mice received intraperitoneal luciferin administra-
tion, and Luc activity was analyzed in pMEC outgrowths using 
IVIS imaging. KB1 f/f Luc f/+ pMECs produced Luc-positive 
outgrowths by 4 wk after injection, similar to control KLuc f/+ 
pMECs, but by 8 wk, Luc activity in KB1 f/f Luc f/+ pMECs 
was progressively lost until barely detectable at 24 wk after 
injection (Fig. 4, B and C). Genomic DNA qPCR in pMECs 
isolated from 4-wk-old KB1 f/f Luc f/+ outgrowths confirmed 
low levels of Brca1 WT allele compared with KLuc f/+ control 
cells, suggesting that the majority of pMECs lacked Brca1 ex-
pression (Fig. 4 D). Furthermore, immunohistochemical analysis </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 210, No. 8 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>to cell survival associated with suppression of 53bp1, which 
appears to be independent of Nrf2 transactivation and regula-
tion of ROS. </p>

<p>Estrogen induces an Nrf2-dependent antioxidant response 
Tumor development in BRCA1 mutation carriers is largely re-
stricted to hormonally regulated tissues. Although mouse 
BRCA1 tumor models do not recapitulate the exquisite organ 
specificity of the human cancer counterpart, some mouse studies </p>

<p>We then evaluated whether Keap1 or 53bp1 inactivation 
could rescue the repopulation defects associated with Brca1 
loss in vivo by fat pad transplantation assay. Lentiviral-mediated 
down-regulation of Keap1 and 53bp1 restored cell survival in 
KB1 f/f pMECs into the precleared fat pad of normal recipient 
mice to a level similar to KLuc f/+ pMECs (Fig. 5, E and F). 
These data show that suppression of Keap1 rescues cell sur-
vival defects associated with Brca1 deficiency through Nrf2-
dependent regulation of intracellular ROS. This is in contrast </p>

<p>Figure 4. Brca1-deficient pMECs can regenerate a functional mammary gland but have a limited lifespan in vivo. (A) Breeding strategy 
used to obtain B1 f/f Luc f/+ , KLuc f/+ , and KB1 f/f Luc f/+ animals used for in vivo fat pad transplantation assays. pMECs isolated from B1 f/f Luc f/+ , KLuc f/+ , 
and KB1 f/f Luc f/+ donor mice were transplanted in 21-wk-old recipient mice to generate outgrowths. (B) In vivo Luc activity in outgrowths derived 
from B1 f/f Luc f/+ (mouse 1 as negative control), KLuc f/+ (mice 2 and 8 as positive controls), and KB1 f/f Luc f/+ (mice 3-7) pMECs at 4 and 24 wk after 
transplantation. (C) Quantitation of Luc activity shown in B using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Living Image</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3.0</rs> software. (D) qPCR of Brca1 WT allele with genomic DNA from 
pMECs isolated from KLuc f/+ and KB1 f/f Luc f/+ 4-wk outgrowths. (E) Immunohistochemical staining of 4-wk KLuc f/+ and KB1 f/f Luc f/+ outgrowths with 
anti-Luc and anti-CK14 Abs. Phase-contrast images of the same glands are shown below. (F) Whole-mount staining of KLuc f/+ and KB1 f/f Luc f/+ 4-wk 
outgrowths. Terminal end buds are shown at higher magnification. (G) Hematoxylin-eosin staining of KLuc f/+ and KB1 f/f Luc f/+ outgrowths at 24 wk 
after transplantation. Data are representative of 10 outgrowths examined per genotype. Bars: (E) 16 µm; (F and G) 50 µm. (H and I) RT-PCR analysis 
of p16/INK4 (H) and p19/ARF (I) mRNA levels in KLuc f/+ and KB1 f/f Luc f/+ 8-wk outgrowths. (J) pMECs from KLuc f/+ and KB1 f/f Luc f/+ 8-wk outgrowths 
were stained with FITC-H2AX and analyzed by flow cytometry. (K) p21/Cdkn1a mRNA levels in pMECs from KLuc f/+ and KB1 f/f Luc f/+ 8-wk out-
growths. (C, D, and H-K) Data represent the mean ± SEM of n = 5 outgrowths of each genotype. *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01. </p>



<p>Role of Nrf2 in BRCA1-related cancers | Gorrini et al. </p>

<p>elevated GCLM and HMOX1 mRNA expression (Fig. 6 C 
and not depicted). 
E2 has been shown to elicit pleiotropic effects, including 
cell cycle regulation (Foster et al., 2001) and ROS generation, 
through oxidative metabolism or by acting on mitochondrial 
uncoupling proteins (Fussell et al., 2011). To evaluate whether 
NRF2 accumulation was caused by E2-induced ROS in-
crease, we measured ROS levels in MCF7 at 4 h after treat-
ment with 10 nM E2, but we did not detect any changes in 
ROS levels between E2-treated cells and control cells (Fig. 6 D). 
Similarly, we did not observe any difference in cell cycle 
profile between E2-starved MCF7 cells before and after E2 </p>

<p>suggest that estrogen (E2)-mediated survival of BRCA1-
deficient cells is at the basis of BRCA1 tissue-specific tumor 
suppression (Elledge and Amon, 2002; Li et al., 2007). 
To determine whether E2-regulated signaling can coun-
teract Nrf2 defective response induced by BRCA1 loss, we 
treated the E2-responsive human breast cancer cell line MCF7 
with 17- estradiol (E2). As previously reported (Dubik and  Shiu, 1992), c-MYC mRNA was up-regulated by 10 nM 
E2 treatment in MCF7 cells (not depicted). Interestingly, E2 
stimulation led to significant NRF2 protein increase (Fig. 6 A), 
with no change in NRF2 mRNA expression (Fig. 6 B). 
E2 also induced NRF2-driven transactivation, as shown by </p>

<p>Figure 5. Keap1 down-regulation rescues in vivo survival defect and ROS levels in BRCA1-deficient cells. (A) Keap1 mRNA levels in 
COMMA-1D cells infected with EV or Keap1 shRNA. (B) 53bp1 mRNA levels in COMMA-1D cells infected with EV or 53bp1 shRNA. (C) ROS levels in 
COMMA-1D cells stably expressing EV or Keap1 and 53bp1 shRNAs after transfection with scrambled siRNA (siScr) or Brca1-specific siRNA (siBrca1). 
Data are normalized to ROS levels in EV/siScr cells. (D) Nqo1 mRNA levels in cells as described in C. Data are normalized to siScr/EV cells. (A-D) Data 
represent the mean ± SEM of three biological replicates. (E) Representative images of in vivo Luc activity in outgrowths derived from KLuc f/+ pMECs 
(mouse 1, positive control) and KB1 f/f Luc f/+ pMECs infected with EV (mouse 2), Keap1 shRNA (mice 3 and 4), or 53bp1 shRNA (mice 5 and 6). (F) Quan-
titation of Luc activity shown in E using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Living Image</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">3.0</rs> software. Data represent the mean ± SEM from n = 5 outgrowths of each combination. 
*, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 210, No. 8 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>treatment resulted in differential Nrf 2 protein accumulation 
in B1 f/f versus KB1 f/f pMECs (Fig. 6 J). Untreated KB1 f/f cells 
showed undetectable Nrf2 levels that increased after 2-h treat-
ment with E2 to a level similar to control B1 f/f cells but lower 
than 2-h E2-treated B1 f/f cells. This result shows that E2 may res-
cue compromised Nrf2 stabilization in the absence of BRCA1 
to counteract ROS accumulation and promote cell survival. </p>

<p>Nrf2 antioxidant signaling is defective 
in human BRCA1-mutated breast tumor cells 
To determine whether human BRCA1-mutated tumor cells 
retain a defective NRF2 antioxidant response, we analyzed 
human breast cancer HCC1937 cells (Scully et al., 1999) either 
carrying a 5382insC BRCA1 mutation (HCC mut ) or reconsti-
tuted with WT BRCA1 (HCC WT ). Reconstitution of HCC mut 
cells with WT functional BRCA1 increased BRCA1 mRNA 
levels (Fig. 7 A), reduced intracellular ROS levels (Fig. 7 B), and 
lowered sensitivity to oxidative stress-induced cell death after 
treatment with a high dose of BSO (Fig. 7 C). </p>

<p>stimulation (Fig. 6 E). E2 treatment of the ER-positive mouse 
MEC line, HC11, also resulted in Nrf2 protein accumulation 
(Fig. 6 F) and expression of the Nrf2 target gene, Gclm (Fig. 
6 G). Collectively, these data suggest that E2 results in Nrf2 
accumulation and activation. 
To explore whether E2 induced an Nrf2-dependent anti-
oxidant program in vivo, E2 was administered to bilaterally 
ovariectomized FVB mice. After 2 wk of administration, 
MaSCs/basal and luminal cells were sorted from mammary 
gland isolates obtained from vehicle-and E2-treated mice. E2 
responsiveness was confirmed by up-regulation of the E2-
responsive gene Greb1 (Ghosh et al., 2000) in both MaSCs/ 
basal and luminal cells (not depicted). Interestingly, the Nrf2 
targets Gclm and Nqo1 were mainly up-regulated by E2 in 
MaSCs/basal cells (Fig. 6, H and I). Because MaSCs/basal cells 
lack ER expression, these data suggest that in vivo E2-induced 
Nrf2 activation occurs through a paracrine mechanism. 
The capacity of E2 to induce Nrf2 accumulation was next 
evaluated in BRCA1-deleted pMECs. We found that in vitro E2 </p>

<p>Figure 6. Estrogen stimulates an Nrf2-regulated antioxidant response. (A) Representative immunoblot analysis of NRF2 protein in estrogen 
(E2)-starved MCF7 cells that were treated with 10 nM E2 for 2 or 4 h. (B and C) MCF7 cells that were left untreated (Con) or treated as in A for 4 h were 
used to detect NRF2 (B) and GCLM (C) mRNA levels by RT-PCR. (D) Representative ROS analysis by FACS in MCF7 cells treated as in B. (E) Representative 
cell cycle analysis by PI staining of control (Con) or E2-treated MCF7 cells (10 nM for 4 h). (F) HC11 cells were left untreated or stimulated with different 
doses of E2 as indicated for 4-h Nrf2, and vinculin protein levels were detected. Representative Western blot is shown. (G) Gclm mRNA levels in HC11 
treated with 10 nM E2 for 4 h. (B, C, and G) Data represent the mean ± SEM of three biological replicates. (H and I) RT-PCR analysis of Gclm (H) and Nqo1 
(I) mRNA levels in luminal (L) and MaSC/basal (B) cells isolated from ovariectomized FVB mice that were treated with vehicle or 0.14 mg E2 for 14 d. Data 
represent the mean ± SEM of n = 3 independent isolates. L, B = luminal or MaSC/basal cells from vehicle-treated mice; L+E2, B+E2 = luminal or basal 
cells from E2-treated mice (n = 3/group). (J) Representative Western blot analysis of Nrf2 protein levels in B1 f/f and KB1 f/f pMECs treated with 10 nM E2 
for 2 and 4 h. Vinculin was used as a loading control. *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01. </p>



<p>Role of Nrf2 in BRCA1-related cancers | Gorrini et al. </p>

<p>whether modulating ROS levels may alter platinum sensitivity. 
HCC WT and HCC mut cells were treated with cisplatin after 
KEAP1 down-regulation by siRNA. As previously reported 
(Tassone et al., 2009), HCC mut cells were more sensitive to 
cisplatin than HCC WT cells but only at higher concentration 
(30 µM compared with 10 µM; Fig. 7 H). Because 30 µM cis-
platin induced high levels of cell death, we determined the 
role of KEAP1 siRNA in cells treated with low-dose (10 µM) 
cisplatin. We found that KEAP1 down-regulation prefer-
entially decreased cisplatin-induced cell death in HCC mut 
cells compared with HCC WT cells (Fig. 7 I). These data sug-
gest that constitutive NRF2 signaling achieved by KEAP1 </p>

<p>We determined whether increased sensitivity of HCC mut 
cells to BSO was in part caused by compromised NRF2 sig-
naling. Compared with HCC WT cells, HCC mut cells failed to 
up-regulate NRF2 upon BSO treatment (Fig. 7 D). However, 
transfection with KEAP1 siRNA increased the expression of 
the NRF2 target genes NQO1 (Fig. 7 E) and GCLM (Fig. 7 F) 
and reduced intracellular ROS levels to a similar extent in 
both HCC mut and HCC WT (Fig. 7 G). 
BRCA1-associated tumors are more sensitive to inter-
strand DNA cross-linking agents, such as cisplatin and carbo-
platin (D'Andrea, 2010). As platinum-based therapy generates 
high intracellular ROS levels (Conklin, 2004), we evaluated </p>

<p>Figure 7. Reconstitution of WT BRCA1 in a human BRCA1-mutated breast cancer cell line restores Nrf2 activation. (A) RT-PCR analysis of 
BRCA1 mRNA levels in HCC WT and HCC mut cells. (B) Quantitation of ROS levels analyzed by FACS in HCC WT and HCC mut cells. (C) Cell viability of HCC WT 
and HCC mut cells at 4 d after treatment with 5 mM BSO. Data are the mean percentage ± SEM of viable cells compared with untreated controls (n = 3/group). 
(D) Representative immunoblot of NRF2 protein levels in HCC WT and HCC mut cells that were left untreated (Con) or treated with the indicated doses of 
BSO. H3 served as a loading control. (E and F) NQO1 (E) and GCLM (F) expression levels in HCC WT and HCC mut cells transfected with scrambled siRNA 
(siScr) and KEAP1 siRNA (siKEAP1). (G) ROS levels in siScr-and siKeap1-transfected HCC WT and HCC mut cells. Data in siKeap1 cells are normalized 
to siScr controls for each cell line (n = 3/group). Data represent the mean ± SEM of three biological replicates, normalized to siScr-transfected 
cells. (H) Analysis of apoptosis by Annexin V/7-AAD staining of HCC WT and HCC mut cells left untreated (Con) or treated with 10 or 30 µM cisplatin 
for 24 h. (I) Analysis of apoptosis by Annexin V/7-AAD staining in siScr-and siKeap1-transfected HCC WT and HCC mut cells left untreated (Con) 
or treated with 10 µM cisplatin (CIS) for 24 h. Data are normalized to untreated siScr cells for each cell line. (A, B, E, F, H, and I) Data represent the 
mean ± SEM of three biological replicates. *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 210, No. 8 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>555 breast tumors from three independent gene expression da-
tasets (Pawitan et al., 2005; Chin et al., 2006; Sabatier et al.,  2011). Tumor subtype classification was determined as de-
scribed in each study. We found that the lowest NQO1 expres-
sion levels were characteristic of basal-like tumors (Fig. 8, E-G), 
suggesting that NQO1 deregulation may be involved in both 
BRCA1-mutated tumors and sporadic basal-like tumors. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Our current understanding of BRCA1-related breast carci-
nogenesis posits that, in carriers of BRCA1 mutations, loss of 
heterozygosity of the remaining WT BRCA1 allele must be 
accompanied by a secondary event such as p53 inactivation to 
achieve full transformation (Foulkes, 2008). Cells lacking both 
p53 and BRCA1 are genomically unstable and acquire addi-
tional mutations that drive tumor development such as loss of 
PTEN (Saal et al., 2008). Recent data suggest that 53BP1 in-
activation also alleviates the proliferation defects, DNA damage 
hypersensitivity, and genomic instability induced by BRCA1 
deficiency (Cao et al., 2009; Bouwman et al., 2010; Bunting  et al., 2010). 
Our work provides new insights in BRCA1-associated 
tumorigenesis through the regulation of oxidative stress. We 
showed that BRCA1-deficient cells have increased ROS levels </p>

<p>silencing modulates the sensitivity to cisplatin in BRCA1-
mutated tumor cells. </p>

<p>NQO1 expression correlates with tumor-associated 
BRCA1 loss or mutation 
We next evaluated whether mouse and human BRCA1-
related tumors show evidence of impaired Nrf2 activation. 
Mouse mammary tumors were generated from crossing con-
ditional p53 f/f with KB1 f/f mice as previously described (Liu  et al., 2007). Immunohistochemical analysis of KB1 f/f p53 f/f 
mammary tumors showed low expression of the Nrf2 target 
gene Nqo1 compared with normal mammary acini (Fig. 8 A). 
To translate our experimental findings to primary human 
breast tumors, we examined the expression levels of NQO1 
in publicly available gene expression datasets from three cohorts 
of, respectively, 577, 117, and 75 primary breast cancer tumors 
with known BRCA1 mutational status (Jönsson et al., 2012;  van 't Veer et al., 2002; Waddell et al., 2010). All three analyses 
showed that NQO1 expression levels were significantly lower 
in tumors from BRCA1 mutation carriers (Fig. 8, B-D). 
The strong association between BRCA1 mutations and 
BRCA1 promoter hypermethylation within the basal-like sub-
type (Jönsson et al., 2012) prompted us to determine NQO1 
expression levels in primary sporadic breast tumors. We analyzed </p>

<p>Figure 8. NQO1 is down-regulated in Brca1-null mouse mammary tumors and BRCA1-mutated human breast cancers. (A) Immunohistochemical 
analysis of Nqo1 protein in normal mouse mammary gland (left) and in a mammary tumor arising in a K14cre Brca1 f/f p53 f/f mouse (KB1 f/f p53 f/f ; right). Re-
sults are representative of five glands from normal FVB mice and five tumors from KB1 f/f p53 f/f mice. Bars, 50 µm. (B-D) Box plots representing NQO1 mRNA 
levels in human primary BRCA1-mutated breast cancers (BRCA1 mut ) and BRCA1-proficient breast cancers (BRCA1 WT ) from three different datasets as indi-
cated in each panel and described in Materials and methods. (E-G) Dot plots showing NQO1 mRNA levels in the indicated human primary breast tumor 
subtypes from three different datasets as indicated in each panel and described in Materials and methods. Vertical lines indicate the variability outside the 
upper and lower quartiles represented in the box plots. P-values were determined by Kruskal-Wallis analysis. *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01; ***, P &lt; 0.0001. </p>



<p>Role of Nrf2 in BRCA1-related cancers | Gorrini et al. </p>

<p>Cell lines and culture conditions. The following cell lines were used: 
COMMA-1D cells (provided by S. Muthuswamy, Ontario Cancer Institute, 
Toronto, Ontario, Canada) in DMEM/F12 medium containing 10% FBS, 
l-glutamine, 1 µg/ml hydrocortisone (Sigma-Aldrich), 5 µg/ml insulin 
(Sigma-Aldrich), and 5 ng/ml epidermal growth factor (EGF; Sigma-
Aldrich); mouse HC11 cells (provided by M. Jason, University of Toronto, 
Toronto, Ontario, Canada) in RPMI 1640 medium containing 10% FBS, 
l-glutamine, 5 µg/ml insulin, and 5 ng/ml EGF; MCF7 cells (provided 
by H. Okada, The Campbell Family Cancer Research Institute, Toronto, 
Ontario, Canada) in DMEM with 10% FBS; and HCC1937 BRCA1 mu-
tant breast cancer cells (HCC mut ) and HCC1937 reconstituted with WT 
BRCA1 (HCC WT ; provided by R. Scully, Harvard Medical School and 
Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center, Boston, MA) in RPMI 1640 with 
10% FBS (Scully et al., 1999). 
Oxidative stress was induced for 48 h in medium containing 2 mM BSO 
(Sigma-Aldrich). In the experiments with antioxidants, cells were cotreated 
with both 250 µM Trolox and BSO. For estrogen treatment, MCF7, HC11, 
and pMECs were maintained in their respective E2-stripped media (Phenol 
red-free media and with 10% charcoal-filtered FBS) for 3 d before addition 
of 10 nM 17- estradiol (E2; Sigma-Aldrich) for 2 or 4 h. HCC cells were 
exposed to 10 or 30 µM cisplatin for 24-h treatment. </p>

<p>Mouse and HMEC isolation, flow cytometric analysis, and cell sort-
ing. Mouse pMECs were obtained through dissociation of #4 mammary 
glands and processed as described previously (Joshi et al., 2010). All reagents 
were obtained from STEMCELL Technologies. For flow cytometry, cells 
were stained with the Abs PE-anti-CD24 (STEMCELL Technologies) and 
APC-anti-CD49f (R&amp;D Systems). pMECs were either sorted to &gt;96% 
purity using a FACSAria instrument (BD) or cultured in serum-free medium 
for 3 d to kill stromal fibroblasts. Flow cytometry for H2AX was determined 
using FITC-anti-H2AX Ab (EMD Millipore) after intracellular fixation and 
permeabilization with buffers from eBioscience according to the manufac-
turers' instructions. 
HMECs were isolated from fresh human mammary tissue as described 
previously (Gauthier et al., 2007). Human tissue was obtained with informed 
patient consent and Institutional Research Ethics Board approval from 
St. Michael's Hospital and the University Health Network. </p>

<p>Mammary fat pad transplantation. pMECs (2 × 10 5 /genotype) from 
B1 f/f Luc f/+ , KLuc f/+ , and KB1 f/f Luc f/+ mice were resuspended 1:1 in 1× 
PBS/Matrigel (Matrigel Matrix High Concentration; BD) and injected into 
precleared fat pads of 21-d-old FVB recipient mice. Fat pad clearance of pre-
existing epithelium was performed as previously described (Joshi et al., 2010). 
For in vivo tracking of engrafted pMECs, 150 mg d-luciferin (Caliper)/kg 
mouse body weight was injected into the intraperitoneal cavity of anes-
thetized mice. Outgrowths were analyzed by in vivo imaging (IVIS Spec-
trum; PerkinElmer), and Luc activity was measured using <rs id="software-3" type="software">Living Image Software</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">4.3</rs>. </p>

<p>Genomic DNA PCR. Genomic DNA was extracted from pMECs using 
the NucleoSpin Tissue kit (Macherey-Nagel) according to the manufactur-
er's protocol. For qualitative PCR, P1, P2, P3, and P4 DNA primers were 
used as described in Liu et al. (2007). For qPCR, specific primers that detect 
a DNA region comprised within exon 5-13 that is missing in KB1 f/f mice 
were used (gBrca1_F/R) along with an internal control (gIC_F/R). See Table S1 
for primer sequences. </p>

<p>RT-PCR. RNA was isolated using the NucleoSpin RNA II kit (Macherey-
Nagel) and reverse transcribed using the iScript cDNA synthesis kit (Bio-
Rad Laboratories) according to the manufacturers' instructions. qRT-PCR 
was performed using SYBR green primers (Applied Biosystems). Samples 
from ovariectomized mice were processed for RNA isolation and cDNA 
preparation as previously described (Joshi et al., 2010). qRT-PCR was per-
formed using SYBR green primers. All data were normalized to values ob-
tained for luminal and MaSCs/basal cells isolated from their respective 
vehicle-treated mice. </p>

<p>(Fig. 1) caused by impaired Nrf2-mediated antioxidant signal-
ing (Fig. 2) and BRCA1 regulates Nrf2 transcription and 
protein stability by interacting with Nrf2 (Figs. 2 and 3). Our 
data also postulate the existence of a positive regulatory feed-
back loop between BRCA1 and Nrf2 that is sustained by 
other recent studies (Kang et al., 2011; Wang et al., 2013). 
We then translated our in vitro findings to the in vivo fat 
pad transplantation assay. In the absence of additional events, 
we demonstrated that BRCA1-related oxidative stress is, at 
least partially, responsible for the impaired repopulation de-
fects of Brca1-null pMECs in the mammary gland (Figs. 4 
and 5). As a proof, Nrf2 constitutive activation by Keap1 si-
lencing is able to rescue ROS levels, Nqo1 down-regulation, 
and in vivo survival caused by Brca1 deficiency (Fig. 5). 
The role of BRCA1 as sensor and regulator of ROS has 
important implications in BRCA1-associated tumor forma-
tion. Among the previously characterized cellular defects in-
duced by BRCA1 deficiency such as lack of DNA repair and 
cell cycle abnormalities, high oxidative stress may represent 
another barrier that prevents transformation of BRCA1-
deficient cells. 
From this study, it appears that the control of DNA damage 
signaling through 53BP1 and the regulation of ROS homeo-
stasis through Nrf2 are two parallel and independent path-
ways downstream of BRCA1. However, both pathways are 
required to alleviate the survival defect in BRCA1-null cells. 
The tissue specificity of the tumors that develop in 
BRCA1 mutation carriers invokes a critical role for estrogen 
signaling. Our findings suggest that estrogen plays a role in 
regulating Nrf2 activation and in particular may counteract 
down-regulation of Nrf2-dependent signaling induced by 
BRCA1 loss to promote cell survival (Fig. 6). Increased sur-
vival of BRCA1-deficient cells permits proliferation and in-
creases genomic instability and acquisition of p53, 53BP1, and/or 
PTEN mutations that promote malignant transformation. 
Current efforts are devoted to the discovery of novel and 
more efficacious therapies to treat BRCA1-mutated breast 
cancers (Drost and Jonkers, 2009; Foulkes et al., 2010). In this 
context, our study suggests that deregulated Nrf2-dependent 
antioxidant signaling sensitizes human BRCA1-mutated tu-
mors to chemotherapy-induced oxidative stress and may pro-
vide new avenues for therapeutic intervention. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Mice. K14cre transgenic mice and p53 conditional knockout mice were ob-
tained from A. Berns (Netherlands Cancer Institute, Amsterdam, Netherlands;  Jonkers et al., 2001). Brca1 conditional knockout mice were provided by 
J. Jonkers (Liu et al., 2007). Luc-expressing transgenic mice were purchased 
from the Jackson Laboratory (Safran et al., 2003). All of the strains were in the 
FVB background. TdTomato mice in the 129/B6 background were pur-
chased from the Jackson Laboratory (Madisen et al., 2010). Mice were main-
tained and handled according to protocols approved by the Animal Care and 
Use Committee of the University Health Network, Toronto, Ontario, Canada. 
Before mammary gland isolation, 8-10-wk-old females were staged by vagi-
nal smear cytology as described previously (Joshi et al., 2010). For in vivo 
estrogen experiments, mice were ovariectomized and treated as described 
previously (Joshi et al., 2010). </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 210, No. 8 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>resuspended in NuPAGE LDS sample buffer (Invitrogen), and incubated at 
70°C for 5 min before loading on precast SDS-PAGE protein gels (Invitro-
gen). For immunoprecipitation of ubiquitinated GFP-Nrf2, 25 µM MG132 
(Sigma-Aldrich) was added 4 h before cell lysis. 
For endogenous immunoprecipitations, we modified the protocol de-
scribed above as follows. Cells lysed in RIPA buffer and lysates (&gt;1 mg) 
were incubated at 4°C with 2 µg of primary Ab for 16 h followed by incuba-
tion with Protein A-agarose beads (GE Healthcare) for 1 h. 
Immunoblotting was performed using standard protocols with the fol-
lowing primary Abs: Nrf2 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.), mouse Nrf2 (gift 
from D. Tuveson [Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, Cold Spring, New York]  and E. Schmidt [Montana State University, Bozeman, MT]), BRCA1 (Santa 
Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.), mouse BRCA1 (GH118; gift from J. Jonkers), 
vinculin (Abcam), -actin (Sigma-Aldrich), H3 (Genetex), Myc (Cell Signal-
ing Technology), GFP (Novus Biologicals), and His (Invitrogen). Anti-mouse 
and anti-rabbit HRP-conjugated secondary Abs were obtained from Thermo 
Fisher Scientific. When required, immunoblots were quantified by <rs id="software-5" type="software">ImageJ</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">1.45</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">National Institutes of Health</rs>). </p>

<p>Whole-mount mammary gland staining. #4 mammary glands were 
dissected and placed on glass slides and fixed overnight with Carnoy's solu-
tion (1:3:6 glacial acetic/chloroform/ethanol). The glands were rehydrated 
before staining with aluminum carmine overnight. After dehydration, glands 
were cleared in toluene and mounted. Imaging was performed on a stereo 
microscope (MZ16F; Leica) in conjunction with Volocity acquisition soft-
ware (version 4.0; PerkinElmer). </p>

<p>Tissue preparation and immunohistochemistry. Mammary glands from 
normal FVB, KLuc f/+ , and KB1 f/f Luc f/+ mice and mammary tumors from 
KB1 f/f p53 f/f mice were fixed in formalin, processed, and embedded in paraf-
fin for sectioning. 5-µm paraffin sections were dewaxed and rehydrated ac-
cording to standard procedures. 
In case of staining with anti-Luc (Sigma-Aldrich) and anti-CK14 (Co-
vance), microwave antigen retrieval using 10 mM Tris EDTA, pH 9, was used. 
Primary Abs were incubated overnight at 4°C. Secondary Abs were applied 
after washing using 1× PBS (Cy2-conjugated anti-rabbit and Cy3-conjugated 
anti-mouse; Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories, Inc.) and were incu-
bated at room temperature for 45 min. Slides were washed with PBS and 
mounted using Entellan. Imaging was performed on a DM6000 fluorescent 
microscope (Leica) with appropriate filter sets and high-resolution camera 
(C4742-80; Hamamatsu Photonics) in conjunction with Volocity acquisition 
software (version 4.0). 
In case of staining with anti-NQO1 Ab (Abcam), antigen retrieval was 
performed in 1 µM EDTA, pH 9.0, and sections were incubated overnight at 
4°C with the primary Ab. Antigen-Ab complexes were visualized using the 
VECTASTAIN Elite ABC kit followed by 3,3-diaminobenzidine staining 
(DAB; Vector Laboratories) and counterstained with Mayer's hematoxylin 
(Thermo Fisher Scientific). Specimens were viewed with a brightfield and 
epifluorescence microscope (Leica DM2500 equipped with Micropublisher 
3.3-QI imaging camera) using <rs id="software-6" type="software">Q-Capture Pro</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">QImaging</rs>) and 
processed with <rs id="software-7" type="software">Photoshop</rs> <rs corresp="#software-7" type="version-number">CS5</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-7" type="creator">Adobe</rs>). </p>

<p>Statistical analyses. Results were reported as the mean ± SEM. Two-
sided independent Student's t test without equal variance assumption was 
used to determine p-values (*, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01). For analysis of gene 
expression microarray in primary human breast tumors, box plots and dot 
plots were performed on three publicly available datasets of BRCA1 mu-
tated breast tumors (van 't Veer et al., 2002; Jönsson et al., 2010; Waddell  et al., 2010) and on three sporadic breast tumor datasets (Pawitan et al.,  2005; Chin et al., 2006; Sabatier et al., 2011), respectively. Tumor subtype 
classification was determined as described in each study. Values indicated 
in the plots are median-centered levels of NQO1 gene expression as as-
sessed from normalized microarray data. Differences in NQO1 (201468_ 
s_at) mRNA levels among breast tumor subtypes were evaluated using 
Man-Whitney analysis. </p>

<p>Mouse -actin, mouse ribosomal protein S9 (rps9), and human ribo-
somal protein S18 (rps18) were used as housekeeping genes to determine 
relative mRNA expression. All RT-PCR primer sequences are described 
in Table S2. </p>

<p>Cell cycle analysis. Cell cycle analysis was performed by propidium iodide 
(PI) staining. In brief, cells were fixed overnight in cold 70% ethanol. After 
washes with 1× PBS, cells were treated with 50 µl of 100 µg/ml stock of 
RNase and stained with 200 µl PI (from 50 µg/ml stock solution). Cells were 
analyzed by a FACSCalibur flow cytometer (BD) immediately after staining. 
Cell cycle distribution was analyzed as typical DNA content histogram. </p>

<p>Apoptosis measurement. Apoptosis was evaluated by Annexin V/7-AAD 
staining. In brief, cells were collected and stained with PE-conjugated An-
nexin V and 7-AAD for 15 min at room temperature in 10× binding buffer. 
All reagents were purchased from BD. Cells were analyzed by a FACSCalibur 
flow cytometer immediately after staining. </p>

<p>ROS measurement. To measure intracellular ROS in pMECs, surface-
stained cells were incubated with 300 nM CM-H 2 DCFDA (DCF-DA; Invit-
rogen) for 10 min at 37°C. DCF-DA fluorescence was analyzed by flow 
cytometry using a FACSCanto instrument (BD) and FlowJo software (Tree 
Star). Because HCC mut or HCC WT cells express GFP, ROS measurements 
were performed in these cells using dihydroethidium (DHE; Sigma-Aldrich). 
Mean fluorescence values (FL-1 for DCF-DA or FL-2 for DHE) were dis-
played as bar graphs. In case of sorted luminal and MaSCs/basal pMECs, data 
were shown in the form of histogram overlays using the %Max option, which 
scaled each population curve to mode = 100% on the y axis and log10 FL-1 
(DCF-DA) fluorescence intensity on the x axis. </p>

<p>Cell viability measurement. Cell viability was measured by Trypan blue 
exclusion assay. In brief, 10 5 HCC1937 cells were seeded in 6-well plates 
24 h before being treated with 5 mM BSO for 4 d. Trypan blue-negative viable 
cells were scored each day after staining with 0.4% Trypan blue solution. </p>

<p>Gene silencing by siRNA oligonucleotides and lentiviral shRNAs. 
For gene silencing by siRNA, the following Thermo Fisher Scientific siR-
NAs were used: nontargeting scrambled siRNA, mouse Brca1 siRNA, mouse 
Nfe2l2 siRNA, human NFE2L2 siRNA, and human KEAP1 siRNA. For 
siRNA experiments, cells were transfected with 25-100 pmol siRNA using 
Lipofectamine 2000 in a 6-well plate. Transfection media was removed after 
5 h. Transfected cells were cultured for 24-48 h before experiments. For 
shRNA experiments, the following lentiviral shRNA constructs were used: 
dox-inducible lentiviral mouse Brca1 shRNA from Thermo Fisher Scientific 
(pTRIPZ) and lentiviral pLKO shRNAs against human Luc, mouse 
Trp53bp1, and mouse Keap1 (a gift of T. Ketela, University of Toronto). The 
human BRCA1 shRNA target sequence, 5-AAGCTCCTCTCACT-
CTTCAGT-3 (Sankaran et al., 2005), was subcloned into pLKO.1puro len-
tiviral vector (Addgene). Lentiviruses were produced in 293FT packaging 
cells transfected with Lipofectamine 2000. Cells were infected with lentivi-
ruses in the presence of 8 µg/ml Polybrene (Sigma-Aldrich) for 4 (HMECs) 
and 18 h (COMMA-1D; pMECs). Cells were cultured for 24 h after infection 
before antibiotic selection with 2-4 µg/ml puromycin (Sigma-Aldrich). pMECs 
were in vivo injected the day after infection without antibiotic selection. </p>

<p>Immunoprecipitation and immunoblotting. Immunoprecipitations 
were performed in 293FT cells using Lipofectamine 2000 with the following 
overexpression constructs: Myc-BRCA1 (provided by R. Hakem, Ontario 
Cancer Institute; Wilson et al., 1997); HA-ubiquitin (gift of E. Guccione, A*Star, 
Singapore); His-Keap1 (gift of J.P. Ting, University of North Carolina at Cha-
pel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC); GFP-Nrf2 (Addgene; Invitrogen); and HA-Nrf2, 
HA-29 DLG Nrf2, and HA-79 ETGE Nrf2 (gifts of D.D. Zhang, University of 
Arizona, Tucson, AZ). Cells were collected at 36 h after transfection and lysed 
in RIPA buffer. Lysates (&gt;1 mg) were incubated at 4°C first with 2 µg of 
primary Ab for 2 h followed by incubation with Protein A-agarose beads 
(GE Healthcare) for 1 h. Beads were washed three times with RIPA buffer, </p>



<p>Role of Nrf2 in BRCA1-related cancers | Gorrini et al. </p>

<p> 
This research was partially supported by a European Molecular Biology 
Organization Long-term Fellowship to C. Gorrini and by grants from the Canadian 
Institutes of Health Research to M.L. Gauthier and T.W. Mak and from the Ontario 
Ministry of Health and Long-Term Care (OMOHLTC) to T.W. Mak. Please note that 
the views expressed do not necessarily reflect those of the OMOHLTC. 
The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose. </p>

<p>Submitted: 19 June 2012 
Accepted: 12 June 2013 </p>



<p>JEM Vol. 210, No. 8 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>







<p>Role of Nrf2 in BRCA1-related cancers | Gorrini et al. </p>



</text></tei>