<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3055594" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Mycobacterium tuberculosis arabinogalactan (AG) is an 
essential cell wall component. It provides a molecular fra-
mework serving to connect peptidoglycan to the outer 
mycolic acid layer. The biosynthesis of the arabinan 
domains of AG and lipoarabinomannan (LAM) occurs via 
a combination of membrane bound arabinofuranosyltrans-
ferases, all of which utilize decaprenol-1-monophosphora-
binose as a substrate. The source of arabinose ultimately 
destined for deposition into cell wall AG or LAM orig-
inates exclusively from phosphoribosyl-1-pyrophosphate 
( pRpp), a central metabolite which is also required for 
other essential metabolic processes, such as de novo purine 
and pyrimidine biosyntheses. In M. tuberculosis, a single 
pRpp synthetase enzyme (Mt-PrsA) is solely responsible 
for the generation of pRpp, by catalyzing the transfer of 
pyrophosphate from ATP to the C1 hydroxyl position of 
ribose-5-phosphate. Here, we report a detailed biochemical 
and biophysical study of Mt-PrsA, which exhibits the most 
rapid enzyme kinetics reported for a pRpp synthetase. </p>

<p>As we enter into the second decade of the twenty-first 
century, tuberculosis (TB) continues to cause more deaths and 
human suffering than any other infectious disease (Dye  2006). The number of new TB cases is increasing at an 
alarming pace, as does the prevalence of drug-resistant stains 
of the causative agent, Mycobacterium tuberculosis, in the 
form of multidrug-resistant TB (MDR-TB) and extensively </p>

<p>drug-resistant TB (XDR-TB; Madariaga et al. 2008). The 
need for new drugs and vaccines to combat this major burden 
to human health is overwhelming. 
The unique hydrophobic cell wall of M. tuberculosis forms 
a primary defensive barrier to the onslaught of toxic insult 
during the host immune response. The current chemothera-
peutic regime used to treat TB includes the administration of 
isoniazid and ethambutol, both of which target crucial steps 
in the biosynthesis and the assembly of the M. tuberculosis 
cell wall (Banerjee et al. 1994; Belanger et al. 1996). 
However, whilst these cell wall inhibitors are excellent at 
effectively killing actively dividing cells, certain subpopu-
lations of bacilli, labeled as "persisters", exhibit transient 
resistance to many of the drugs used to treat TB (Wayne and  Sohaskey 2001). The precise molecular mechanism of this 
latent infection caused by persistent bacilli is poorly under-
stood. However, in the pursuit of identifying suitable cellular 
targets and the development of new anti-TB chemotherapeutic 
agents, we must address the phenomenon of persistence to 
truly eradicate the disease. Recently, it has been shown that 
certain processes of metabolic pathways involved in mycobac-
terial cellular energy metabolism, such as respiratory ATP 
biosynthesis, represent excellent physiological targets for 
the effective killing of latent populations of TB bacilli 
(Koul et al. 2007, 2008; Rao et al. 2008; Bald and Koul  2010). Phospho-α-D-ribosyl-1-pyrophosphate ( pRpp) is a 
central metabolite that links the pentose phosphate pathway to 
the de novo and the salvage biosynthetic pathways of purine 
and pyrimidine production, NAD and NADP cofactor biosyn-
thesis, as well as histidine and tryptophan biosynthesis 
(Hove-Jensen 1988). It is therefore considered that pRpp is 
required at all times during the life cycle of both prokaryotic 
and eukaryotic cells (Hove-Jensen 1989; Tozzi et al. 2006). 
In addition to these central metabolic processes, members 
belonging to the Corynebacteriacae, such as mycobacteria, 
have evolved an almost unique biochemical pathway, utilizing 
pRpp as a high-energy biosynthetic precursor for cell wall 
arabinan biosynthesis (Wojtkiewicz et al. 1988; Scherman  et al. 1995, 1996; Figure 1). The gene product of Rv3806c 
encodes for a membrane bound pRpp:decaprenol-1-
monophosphate 5-phosphoribosyltransferase (DPPR synthase) 
which catalyzes the formation of DPPR and pyrophosphate 
from pRpp and decaprenol-1-monophosphate (DP; Huang  et al. 2005). DPPR then undergoes C5-dephosphorylation to 
decaprenol-1-monophosphoribose (DPR) and epimerization 
about the C2-OH position of the ribosyl moiety catalyzed by </p>

<p>1 To whom correspondence should be addressed: Tel: +44-121-415-8125; Fax: 
+44-121-414-5925; e-mail: g.besra@bham.ac.uk </p>

<p>Glycobiology vol. 21 no. 4 pp. 410-425, 2011 
doi:10.1093/glycob/cwq173 
Advance Access publication on November 2, 2010 </p>

<p>© The Author 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 
Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any 
medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com. </p>



<p>a two-step heteromeric oxidation/reduction process (Mikusova  et al. 2005). In M. tuberculosis, Rv3790 encodes for 
an 
FAD-containing 
oxidoreductase 
(DprE1) 
which 
oxidizes the ribosyl C2-OH group to the keto sugar 
decaprenol-1-monophosphoryl-2-keto-β-erythro-pentofuranose 
(DPX) which is subsequently reduced by DprE2 (encoded by 
Rv3791) forming decaprenol-1-monophosphoarabinose (DPA; 
Mikusova et al. 2005), which is the sole high-energy 
lipid-linked substrate for the GT-C family arabinofuranosyl-
transferases (AraTs) which are involved in cell wall arabinan 
polymerization (Alderwick et al. 2007). 
Mycobacterial arabinan is a highly branched polysaccharide 
consisting of arabinose units arranged into specific repeating 
motifs, and it predominantly features in the heteropolysacchar-
ide arabinogalactan (AG), which is a crucial component of 
the mycobacterial cell wall (Daffé et al. 1990; Besra et al.  1995). Three arabinan domains are covalently linked via an 
Araf-α(1 → 5)-Galf glycosidic bond to the 8th, 10th and 12th </p>

<p>positions of a single linear polysaccharide composed of 30 
alternating β(1 → 5) and β(1 → 6) Galf residues forming the 
galactan domain of AG (Alderwick et al. 2005). AG is a 
structural macromolecule and serves to function as a molecu-
lar scaffold linking peptidoglycan to the mycolic acids, 
forming a highly impermeable and hydrophobic layer sur-
rounding the mycobacterial cell (McNeil et al. 1991). 
Arabinan is also present in the form of lipoarabinomannan 
(LAM), a highly immunogenic lipoglycan, which is involved 
in modulating the host immune response (Briken et al. 2004). 
In terms of chemical composition, arabinan represents 18% 
of mycobacterial cell wall biomass (Ortalo-Magne et al.  1995). Therefore, during cell elongation and division of the 
mycobacterial bacilli, it is necessary for there to be a readily 
available supply of pRpp for the efficient incorporation of ara-
binose into newly synthesized cell wall material. During this 
process, the metabolic demand for pRpp is likely to increase 
dramatically and the elevated levels required for effective </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Proposed metabolic pathway depicting the importance of Mt-PrsA for the generation of pRpp in M. tuberculosis. R5P is generated via the catabolism of 
glucose through the pentose phosphate pathway, a process ubiquitous throughout nature. Like all pRpp synthetase enzymes, Mt-PrsA catalyses the transfer of 
pyrophosphate from ATP to the C1-OH group of R5P forming pRpp and AMP. In a process unique to members belonging to the Corynebacteriaceae, such 
as M. tuberculosis, pRpp is utilized as the sole metabolic intermediate in the formation of DPA, which is a crucial substrate required for mycobacterial 
cell wall assembly. DP, decaprenol-1-monophosphate; DPA, decaprenol-1-monophosphoarabinose; DPR, decaprenol-1-monophosphoribose; DPPR, 
decaprenol-1-monophosphoribose-5-phosphate; DPX, decaprenol-1-monophosphoryl-2-keto-β-erythro-pentofuranose; pRpp, phosphoribosyl-1-pyrophosphate; 
R5P, ribose -5-phosphate. </p>

<p>Mycobacterium tuberculosis pRpp synthetase </p>



<p>arabinan biosynthesis must be maintained. The enzyme pRpp 
synthetase (ATP:α-D-ribose-5-phosphate (R5P) pyrophospho-
transferase; EC2.7.6.1) belongs to a family of enzymes that 
catalyze the transfer of the β,γ-diphosphate moiety from ATP 
to the C1-OH group of α-D-R5P and the gene(s) encoding for 
this enzyme(s) is present in all living organisms (Hove-Jensen  1985; Carter et al. 1997; Krath and Hove-Jensen 1999). It is 
predicted that the M. tuberculosis H37Rv genome codes for 
only one pRpp synthetase (Rv1017c), which is annotated as 
Mt-PrsA (Cole and Barrell 1998). 
In this study, we report a detailed biochemical characteriz-
ation of recombinant Mt-PrsA and provide evidence which 
confirms the essentiality of this gene for the maintenance of 
cell growth, division and integrity. Mt-PrsA displays an absol-
ute requirement for inorganic phosphate for enzyme activation 
and will accept either Mg 
2+ or Mn 
2+ as divalent cations, 
which serve to coordinate the phosphate moieties of ATP 
during enzyme catalysis. Using a continuous enzyme coupled 
spectrophotometric assay, we report a detailed kinetic charac-
terization of Mt-PrsA, which displays the highest specific 
activity measured for any pRpp synthetase studied to date. By 
investigating the oligomeric state of Mt-PrsA in solution and 
measuring the ligand-binding properties of its substrates, we 
provide evidence suggesting that the mechanism by which 
ADP inhibits Mt-PrsA activity, results from the binding of 
ADP to an allosteric site, and as a consequence, induces the 
stabilization of an inactive, hexameric oligomeric species. </p>

<p>Results 
Evidence suggesting that Mt-prsA is an essential gene 
for the maintenance of cellular integrity 
Mt-prsA is predicted to be an essential gene as determined by 
high-density transposon mutagenesis (Sassetti et al. 2003). 
This is not unsurprising, considering the apparent physiologi-
cal importance of Mt-PrsA in the provision of pRpp for 
central metabolic pathways and the formation of the cell wall 
biosynthetic precursor DPA (Wolucka et al. 1994; Scherman  et al. 1995). We have previously used Corynebacterium gluta-
micum as an excellent model system for the study of complex 
cell wall biosynthetic processes, and we have reported the 
phenotypic characterization of several cell wall mutants, 
which would otherwise be essential in mycobacterial systems 
(Gande et al. 2004; Alderwick et al. 2005; Alderwick, Dover,  et al. 2006; Alderwick, Seidel, et al. 2006; Seidel et al. 2007;  Birch et al. 2008). A bioinformatics analysis of 
several Corynebacteriaceae genomes revealed that NCgl0945 
(Cg-prsA) was the likely C. glutamicum ortholog of Mt-prsA 
(Rv1017c). These corresponding gene products share 71% 
identity (83% similarity), and the gene locus is conserved 
within the Corynebacteriaceae indicating that this region is 
syntenic. We attempted to inactivate Cg-prsA in C. glutami-
cum, by using the disruption vector pK18mob-Cg-prsA-int, 
carrying 304 bp of Cg-prsA. In a control experiment, we used 
the previously reported pK18mob-Cg-ppm1-int construct, 
which affords the successful inactivation of the gene encoding 
for the polyprenyl monophosphomannose synthase ( ppm1) of 
C. glutamicum, which is a gene of similar size to that of 
Cg-prsA (Gibson et al. 2003). Both inactivation vectors were </p>

<p>used in parallel experiments for the transformation of wild-
type (WT) C. glutamicum to kanamycin resistance (Kan 
R ). 
Whilst we were able to easily generate C. glutamicum Kan </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>colonies from the pK18mob-Cg-ppm1-int construct, we were 
required to conduct several rounds of electroporation using 
pK18mob-Cg-prsA-int before obtaining three separate C. glu-
tamicum Kan 
R clones. This indicates that the recombination 
events appeared to have taken place at unexpected and, as yet, 
undefined loci. From this analysis, we concluded that 
Cg-prsA is an essential gene and its function is necessary for 
the growth and integrity of C. glutamicum, even when grown 
on rich Brain Heart Infusion (BHI) medium. </p>

<p>Overexpression, purification and pRpp synthetase activity 
of recombinant Mt-PrsA 
Overexpression of Mt-PrsA in Escherichia coli C41 cells and 
the subsequent purification by IMAC resulted in a preparation 
of Mt-PrsA that was stable in solution at a concentration of 2 
mg/mL. A coomassie-stained 12% SDS-PAGE analysis of 
Mt-PrsA revealed a band that migrated to a position of 35 
kDa, which is in accordance with the expected molecular 
weight of Mt-PrsA, and was estimated to be at least 98% 
pure. To determine if recombinant Mt-PrsA was active, we 
performed a radiochemical assay to measure the pyropho-
sphate transfer from ATP to the C1-OH group of 
[ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]-uniformly labeled R5P (Boss et al. 1984). Starting with 
[ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]-U-D-glucose and replicating the first three enzymic reac-
tions of the pentose phosphate pathway in vitro using com-
mercially available enzymes (Roche and Sigma), we prepared 
a source of purified [ 
14 C]-U-α-D-R5P as a substrate for sub-
sequent enzyme assays. In a time course assay, recombinant 
Mt-PrsA exhibited rapid pRpp synthetase activity which was 
dependent upon the presence of either of the divalent cations 
Mg 
2+ and Mn </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>, with slight preference for the latter 
(Figure 2A). During the assay, p[ 
14 C]Rpp is susceptible to 
product degradation due to hydrolysis of the labile C1-OH 
pyrophosphate bond, which accounts for the relatively small 
increase in band density (relating to p[ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]Rpp) over the 
course of the assay. Addition of EDTA to the reaction mix 
inhibited the formation of p[ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]Rpp (data not shown) and 
the inclusion of CaCl 2 , in replacement of MgCl 2 or MnCl 2 , 
also resulted in the loss of Mt-PrsA activity (Figure 2A). 
Mt-PrsA was found to be most active at a pH of 6.5, but also 
showed activity across a broad range of pH levels (4.5-9.5) 
and was only found to be inactive at high pH (10.5; data not 
shown). In accordance with previous studies of pRpp synthe-
tases (Prs) from other organisms, Mt-PrsA was strongly inhib-
ited by the presence of ADP, which has been shown to be an 
allosteric modulator of this class of enzymes (Figure 2B) 
(Switzer and Sogin 1973; Gibson et al. 1982; Arnvig et al.  1990; Eriksen et al. 2000; Willemoes et al. 2000). </p>

<p>Mt-PrsA-dependent metabolic channeling of R5P into 
mycobacterial cell wall biosynthetic precursors 
Apart from being a key metabolite in the de novo and salvage 
pathways of purine and pyrimidine biosynthesis, as well as 
histidine, tryptophan, NAD and NADP metabolism, pRpp 
serves as a high-energy intermediate in the formation of the 
mycobacterial cell wall precursor DPR (Figure 1; Scherman </p>

<p>LJ Alderwick et al. </p>



<p>et al. 1995). We investigated the conversion of [ 
14 C]-U-D-R5P 
([ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]-R5P) into the cell wall AraT substrate DPA and its pre-
cursor, DPR. Assays were conducted using membranes pre-
pared from M. smegmatis which provided a source of DPPR 
synthase (Huang et al. 2005), which was necessary to investi-
gate incorporation of [ 
14 C]-R5P into the lipid-linked organic 
extractable material. When assays were performed with just 
[ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]-R5P and membranes, no radioactive product was detect-
able in the organic phase, as depicted in Figure 3 (lane 1). </p>

<p>In this instance, all radioactivities remained in the aqueous 
phase of the assay work-up (data not shown). In addition, 
M. smegmatis P60 (a preparation of cell wall material rich in 
proteins associated with cell wall processes) exhibited no 
pRpp synthetase activity (Figure 3, lane 2). When recombi-
nant Mt-PrsA is included in the assay, the formation of 
DPPR and DPR can be clearly observed (Figure 3, lane 3). It 
is likely that DPPR undergoes enzyme catalyzed 
5'-dephosphorylation, resulting in the formation of DPR. In </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Time course assay showing the Mt-PrsA catalyzed formation of p[ 
14 C]Rpp from [ 
14 C]R5P and ATP. Assays contained Mt-PrsA, 50 mM Pi, 2 mM ATP 
supplemented with either 2 mM Mg 
2+ , Mn 
2+ or Ca 
2+ as illustrated in (A), and in the presence of ADP at a final concentration of 2 mM in (B). Assays were 
incubated at 37°C, and aliquots were removed from the assay mix at 0, 10, 30 and 60 s and the reactions halted by quenching with the addition of formic acid. 
Samples were applied to a glass-backed PEI-cellulose TLC plate and developed in 0.85 M KH 2 PO 4 ( pH 3.4). The plate was inspected for radioactive spots 
relating to p[ 
14 C]Rpp and [ 
14 C]R5P by autoradiography through the exposure of TLCs to X-ray film (Kodak X-Omat). </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Analysis of Mt-PrsA-dependent [ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]-R5P incorporation into the M. smegmatis AraT substrate DPA via p[ 
14 C]Rpp. The basic assays mixture contained 
(amongst other components described in the Materials and methods section) membranes prepared from M. smegmatis, 100,000 cpm [ 
14 C]-R5P, 50 µg of DP and 
2 mM ATP. Individual assays were carried out at 37°C and included the addition of no further additive; lane 1, M. smegmatis P60; lane 2, Mt-PrsA; lane 3, 
Mt-PrsA and NaWO 4 and NaF both at a final concentration of 2 mM; lane 4, Mt-PrsA and M. smegmatis P60; lane 5, Mt-PrsA, M. smegmatis P60 and 2 mM of 
both NaWO 4 and NaF; lane 6 and finally Mt-PrsA, M. smegmatis P60 and 2 mM ADP in lane 7. After an incubation at 37°C for 30 min, assays were quenched 
and products extracted from the assay mix by organic solvent extraction as described in the Materials and methods section. Samples relating to each assay were 
loaded onto a silica gel TLC plates, developed in CHCl 3 /CH 3 OH/CH 3 COONH 4 /NH 4 OH/H 2 O (180:140:9:9:23 v/v/v/v/v) and bands migrating to the position of 
DPA, DPR, DPX and DPPR were visualized by autoradiography, exposure of TLCs to X-ray film (Kodak X-Omat) and compared to previously isolated known 
standards (Mikusova et al. 2005; Alderwick et al. 2006a). </p>

<p>Mycobacterium tuberculosis pRpp synthetase </p>



<p>M. tuberculosis, Rv3807c is an excellent candidate for this 
enzyme since it codes for a putative membrane bound PAP2 
phosphatase directly adjacent to the DPPR synthase 
(Rv3806c; Figure 1; Cole and Barrell 1998). Mycobacterium 
smegmatis has a direct ortholog of this phosphatase encoded 
by MSMEG6402, which explains the apparent conversion of 
DPPR to DPR observed in this assay. The combined addition 
of sodium fluoride and sodium tungstate (known phosphatase 
inhibitors; Stankiewicz and Gresser 1988) to the assay mix, 
results in a diminished level of DPR formation and a corre-
sponding increase in a band migrating to a lower position on 
the TLC identified as being DPPR (Figure 3, lane 4). When 
Mt-PrsA is used in combination with M. smegmatis P60, two 
additional bands can be observed migrating in close proximity 
to DPR, which correspond to the subsequent conversion of 
DPR to DPX and DPA, by the endogenous P60 activity of 
DprE1 and DrpE2, respectively (Figure 3, lane 5; Mikusova  et al. 2005). The inclusion of sodium fluoride and sodium 
tungstate dramatically reduced the conversion of DPPR to 
DPA, suggesting that the two-step epimerization of the C2-
OH group of ribose by DprE1 and DprE2 occurs after 5' 
dephosphorylation (Figure 3, lane 6). The inclusion of ADP 
to the reaction mix completely ablated the formation of any 
organic extractable material, clearly indicating that the ADP </p>

<p>inhibition of Mt-PrsA results in the total loss of DPPR for-
mation (Figure 3, lane 7). 
In a separate experiment, assays were carried out in 
the presence of a neoglycolipid acceptor [Araf-α(1 → 
5)-Araf-O-(CH 2 )CH 3 ], which is specific for measuring the 
activity of the cell wall biosynthetic arabinofuranosyltrans-
ferases EmbA, EmbB, EmbC and AftB (Lee et al. 1997;  Seidel et al. 2007), all of which reside in the membrane due 
to the polytopic nature of these GT-C family glycosyltrans-
ferases. AraT activity was measured after product isolation by 
organic extraction and analysis by TLC and autoradiography. 
AraT assays carried out in the absence of Mt-PrsA afforded 
no AraT-dependent product formation (Figure 4, lane 1). 
Upon addition of Mt-PrsA, two closely migrating bands could 
be observed with the top bad attributed to α(1 → 5)-Araf 
transfer to the acceptor by either EmbA, EmbB, EmbC or a 
combination and the lower band attributed to β(1 → 2)-Araf 
transfer resulting from AftB activity (Figure 4, lane 2), as 
described previously (Lee et al. 1997). Addition of the 
EmbA, EmbB and EmbC inhibitor ethambutol (EMB), 
resulted in the loss of the upper band with only the lower 
band remaining, this being due to the noninhibitory effect of 
EMB on the terminal β(1 → 2) capping enzyme, AftB (Seidel  et al. 2007; Figure 4, lane 3). As a consequence of allosteric 
inhibition of Mt-PrsA and the resultant loss of in vitro 
Mt-PrsA-dependent pRpp formation, the inclusion of ADP in 
the assay mixture led to the inhibition of any AraT-dependent 
product formation (Figure 4, lane 4). </p>

<p>Kinetic characterization of Mt-PrsA substrates and 
inhibitors using a continuous spectrophotometric assay 
Due to the rapid enzymic activity of recombinant Mt-PrsA 
using the radioactive assay described previously, we sought to 
link Mt-PrsA catalyzed AMP product release to a 
three-enzyme coupled assay system, thus enabling us to 
measure NADH oxidation at 340 nm in a continuous spectro-
photometric assay, which has been described similarly else-
where (Braven et al. 1984). This system (described in the 
Materials and methods section) enabled us to record detailed 
measurements of the steady-state enzyme kinetics of Mt-PrsA. 
Plotting the steady-state reaction velocity (ν) calculated from 
Eq. (1), as a function of increasing concentrations of R5P at 
the saturating levels of ATP, results in a hyperbolic curve dis-
playing the Michelis-Menton kinetics (Figure 5A). Nonlinear 
regression analysis using Eq. (2) derived a K m of 8.2 µM 
(±2.72 SE) for R5P and a V max of 530 µmol 
−1 min 
−1 mg </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>and a specificity constant (K cat /K m ) of 7.43 × 10 
6 M 
−1 s </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>. As 
previously described using the radiochemical assay, Mt-PrsA 
requires the presence of Pi at a concentration of 50 mM for 
full enzyme activation, which is illustrated in Figure 5A. 
However, at reduced levels of Pi (5 mM), the subsequent 
addition of R5P results in partial substrate inhibition, an effect 
that has been observed elsewhere [Willemoes et al. 2000; data 
fitted to Eq. (3)], with little or no activity recorded in the 
absence of Pi (Figure 5A). This is likely due to Mt-PrsA 
being incompletely activated by Pi at low [Pi], meaning that 
at low R5P concentrations, the relatively high-affinity catalytic 
site for R5P is occupied and the normal Micheli-Menton kin-
etics occur until R5P reaches a concentration that results in </p>

<p>Fig. 4. AraT assays carried out via the Mt-PrsA-dependent conversion of 
[ 
14 C]-R5P to p[ 
14 C]Rpp and subsequent chase into a neoglycolipid acceptor. 
The absolute dependence of the cell wall AraT enzymes on the availability 
of pRpp was investigated using the neoglycolipid acceptor Ara 2 . The basic 
assay contained (amongst other components described in the Materials and 
methods section) 0.5 mg of membranes and P60 from M. smegmatis, 2 mM 
α-D-Araf-(1 → 5)-α-D-Araf-O-(CH 2 ) 7 CH 3 , 100,000 cpm [ 
14 C]-R5P, 50 µg of 
DP and 2 mM ATP. Assays were initiated by the addition of [ 
14 C]-R5P and 
incubated for 1 h at 37°C. Individual assays carried out contained the addition 
of no Mt-PrsA, lane 1; 30 µg of Mt-PrsA, lane 2; 30 µg of Mt-PrsA and 100 
µg/mL of EMB, lane 3 and 30 µg of Mt-PrsA and 2 mM ADP, lane 
4. [ 
14 C]-Araf-linked products were extracted from the assay mix as described 
in the Materials and methods section and subsequently applied to a silica gel 
TLC plates, developed in CHCl 3 :CH 2 OH:H 2 O:NH 4 OH (65:25:3.6:0.5, v/v/v/ 
v) and visualized by autoradiography from exposure of TLCs to X-ray film 
(Kodak X-Omat; Lee et al. 1997; Seidel et al. 2007). </p>

<p>LJ Alderwick et al. </p>



<p>the occupancy of a second low-affinity inhibitory site which 
would otherwise be occupied by Pi at higher [Pi]. Kinetic 
analysis of Mt-PrsA with increasing ATP concentrations at 
saturating levels of R5P results in a sigmoidal response 
showing positive cooperativity (Figure 5B). Data obtained 
from measuring ν against increasing concentrations of ATP at 
various Pi concentrations was fitted to Eq. (4). At activating 
levels of [Pi] (50 mM), the S 0.5 and the V max for ATP were 
calculated as being 62.65 µM (±12.04 SE) and 601 µmol </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>min 
−1 mg 
−1 (±66.39 SE), respectively. An apparent Hill coef-
ficient (n) of 1.68 indicates a strong positive cooperativity 
during increasing [ATP]. However, when fitted to Eq. (4) 
using nonlinear regression analysis, this effect diminishes at 
low [Pi] resulting in a ν vs. [ATP] response with altered 
kinetic constants (Figure 5B). It has been reported elsewhere 
that Prs enzymes from other organisms are allosterically 
inhibited by the presence of ADP (Switzer and Sogin 1973;  Gibson et al. 1982; Arnvig et al. 1990; Eriksen et al. 2000;  Willemoes et al. 2000). We measured the effect of ADP on ν 
as a function of increasing [R5P] and [ATP]. At saturating </p>

<p>concentrations of ATP, the addition of ADP resulted in non-
competitive inhibition of Mt-PrsA with a calculated K i of 320 
µM (±53.51 SE) against increasing [R5P] [data fitted to Eq. 
(5); Figure 6A]. When we measured the effect of ADP on the 
kinetic response of Mt-PrsA to increasing [ATP] and sub-
sequent fitting of the data to Eq. (6) (Figure 6B), we calcu-
lated a K i of 522 µM (±45.78 SE). </p>

<p>Biophysical characterization of Mt-PrsA: oligomeric state 
and ligand-binding studies 
Mt-PrsA homologs from other organisms have been reported 
to aggregate in solution in various homo-oligomeric states, 
ranging from dimer to octamer (Schubert et al. 1975; Arnvig  et al. 1990; Li et al. 2007). Using analytical ultracentrifuga-
tion, we performed a set of sedimentation velocity exper-
iments on Mt-PrsA in the absence or the presence of R5P, 
ATP and ADP at saturating concentrations (Figure 7). 
Analysis of each experiment by interpretation of the molar 
mass distribution c(M) indicates that Mt-PrsA in solution 
alone reaches a dynamic equilibrium between two molecular 
species with peaks centered over 100,000 and 205,000 </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Enzyme activity of Mt-PrsA and kinetic characterization of R5P (A) 
and ATP (B) using a continuous enzyme-coupled spectrophotometric assay. 
(A) A plot of velocity (ν) of Mt-PrsA to increasing [R5P] in the presence of 
50 mM Pi (filled circles), 5 mM Pi (filled squares) and no Pi (filled triangle). 
Data for 50 mM Pi fitted to Eq. (2), and data obtained for 5 mM Pi and no 
Pi were fitted to Eq. (3). (B) A plot of velocity (ν) of Mt-PrsA to increasing 
[ATP] in the presence of 50 mM Pi (filled circles), 5 mM Pi (filled squares) 
and no Pi (filled triangle), all of which were fitted to Eq. (4) using nonlinear 
regression analysis. All data points plotted (calculated mean) represent 
experiments performed in triplicate using three independent preparations of 
recombinant Mt-PrsA. Calculated standard errors (±SE) for kinetic constants 
are reported in the manuscript where appropriate. </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Inhibition of Mt-PrsA activity by the addition of ADP when titrated 
with R5P (A) and ATP (B) using a continuous enzyme-coupled 
spectrophotometric assay. (A) A plot of velocity (ν) of Mt-PrsA response to 
increasing [R5P] in the presence of no ADP (filled circles), 0.1 mM ADP 
(filled squares) and 2 mM ADP (filled triangle). Data were fitted to Eq. (5) 
using nonlinear regression analysis. (B) A plot of velocity (ν) of Mt-PrsA 
response to increasing [ATP] in the presence of no ADP (filled circles), 0.1 
mM ADP (filled squares) and 2 mM ADP (filled triangles). Data were fitted 
to Eq. (6) using nonlinear regression analysis. All data points plotted 
(calculated mean) represent experiments performed in triplicate using three 
independent preparations of recombinant Mt-PrsA. Calculated standard errors 
(±SE) for kinetic constants are reported in the manuscript where appropriate. </p>

<p>Mycobacterium tuberculosis pRpp synthetase </p>



<p>Da, which relate to Mt-PrsA in a trimeric and hexameric 
aggregation state, respectively (Figure 7, black line). The 
inclusion of 5 mM R5P showed no apparent change in the 
equilibrium or oligomeric state of Mt-PrsA in solution, and 
the c(M) vs. Mw distribution aligned well with that of 
Mt-PrsA in the absence of ligand (Figure 7, red line). The 
addition of 5 mM ATP to Mt-PrsA resulted in an altered c(M) 
distribution with a peak centered over 70,000 Da, equating 
to a Mt-PrsA homodimer, and concomitant reduction in the 
intensity of the hexameric species, when compared with 
Mt-PrsA alone (Figure 7, blue line). Interestingly, when we 
performed a similar experiment in combination with 5 mM 
ADP, the ratio of c(M) distribution shifted toward an increase 
in the hexameric state with a corresponding reduction in tri-
meric species (Figure 7, green line). Mt-PrsA contains within 
its primary amino acid sequence, three naturally occurring 
tryptophan residues at position Trp 5, Trp 74 and Trp 188. We 
used intrinsic tryptophan fluorescence (ITF) spectroscopy to 
probe the binding properties of R5P, ATP and ADP for 
Mt-PrsA. We performed a fluorescence emission (F emission ) 
scan of Mt-PrsA in solution by recording (F emission ) output 
between 300 and 400 nm, upon excitation at λ 292nm . Mt-PrsA 
gave a maximum fluorescence emission ðF </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>emission Þ at a wave-
length of 335 nm, thus providing a basal F emission coordinate 
for the collection of subsequent ITF data. The change in fluor-
escence emission (ΔF emission ) was calculated by subtracting 
the F emission (recorded 5 min after each ligand titration) away 
from ðF </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>emission Þ, and the data were then plotted against [L]. 
Nonlinear regression analysis of ΔF emission vs. [R5P] using 
Eq. (7) shows a hyperbolic isothermal ligand-binding curve 
for R5P, with a calculated K d of 24.8 µM (±6.77 SE; 
Figure 8A). We sought to investigate what effect ATP might 
have on the K d for R5P; however, the inclusion of both ATP 
and R5P would obviously result in enzyme catalysis and the 
formation of pRpp and AMP. Due to the relatively high 
specific activity of Mt-PrsA, the addition of R5P and ATP at 
concentrations required for the effective measurement of </p>

<p>ligand-binding constants by ITF would result in a reaction 
that would go to completion within the 5 min time-frame 
required to establish binding equilibrium. Therefore, due to 
the stability of the imidodiphophate moity and lack of 
enzyme-catalyzed phosphate transfer, we used the ATP analog 
5'-adenylyl-β,γ-imidodiphosphate (AMPPNP) as an ATP 
ligand substitute for binding assays, when carried out in con-
junction with R5P. Mt-PrsA was titrated with increasing 
[AMPPNP] using identical increments carried out during ATP 
ligand-binding experiments. Subsequent nonlinear regression 
analysis and comparison of the ΔF emission vs. [AMPPNP] and 
ΔF emission vs. [ATP] plots (data not shown) resulted in a 
strong correlation (R 
2 = 0.986) as well as extremely similar 
dissociation constants of 28.29 µM (±0.54 SE) and 31.02 µM 
(±0.62 SE) for ATP and AMPPNP, respectively. With the 
similarly calculated Hill coefficients (n) of 4, the almost 
identical binding properties of ATP and AMPPNP for 
Mt-PrsA allowed us to confidently substitute AMPPNP for 
ATP during binding assays carried out in combination with 
R5P. In this regard, when R5P was titrated against Mt-PrsA in 
the presence of 5 mM AMPPNP, the apparent K d for R5P 
decreased to 21.36 µM (±4.84 SE). This data indicates that 
the Mt-PrsA-AMPPNP complex exhibits a slightly higher 
affinity for R5P when compared with Apo-Mt-PrsA </p>

<p>Fig. 8. Binding kinetics of R5P (A) and the ATP analog (AMPPNP) (B) to 
Mt-PrsA using ITF spectroscopy. ITF spectroscopy was used to determine the 
binding properties of Mt-PrsA for its substrates R5P and ATP. Ligand-binding 
assays were carried out as described in the Materials and methods section. 
(A) A plot of ΔF emission vs. [R5P] in the presence of no AMPPNP (filled 
squares) and 5 mM AMPPNP (filled circles) which was fitted to Eq. (7). (B) 
A plot of ΔF emission vs. [AMPPNP] in the presence of no R5P (filled squares) 
and 5 mM R5P (filled circles) which was fitted to Eq. (9). </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Mt-PrsA self-assembly analysis using analytical ultracentrifugation. 
Sedimentation velocity experiments were conducted to investigate the 
oligomeric state of Mt-PrsA in solution in the presence of no additional 
ligands (black line), 5 mM R5P (red line), 5 mM ATP (blue line) and 5 mM 
ADP (green line). Individual plots represent the molar mass distribution c(M) 
vs. the apparent molecular weight (Da). Arrows indicate the calculated 
oligomeric state of Mt-PrsA in each sedimentation velocity experiment. </p>

<p>LJ Alderwick et al. </p>



<p>(Figure 8A). In the reverse experiment where ΔF emission vs. 
[AMPPNP] was measured in the presence or the absence of 
5 mM R5P (Figure 8B), the affinity of Mt-PrsA-R5P for 
AMPPNP increased slightly, as is evident from the reduction 
in K d to 28.22 µM (±0.54 SE) and an increase in the Hill 
coefficient (n) to 5 by a value of 1. In light of the previous 
AUC experiment, which suggests that the addition of ADP 
induces a shift toward Mt-PrsA hexamerization, we performed 
an ITF experiment by titrating Mt-PrsA with increasing [ADP] 
(Figure 9A). Unsurprisingly, the ΔF emission vs. [ADP] plot dis-
plays a sigmoidal cooperative-binding response with an appar-
ent K d of 512.6 µM (±39.57 SE) and a Hill coefficient of 
2. Since ATP and ADP bind to Mt-PrsA at separate sites and 
induce very different aggregation states, the apparent 2-fold 
difference in the F max recorded for ATP and ADP is most 
likely due to the differing effects each of these ligands have 
on the chemical environments surrounding the tryptophan 
residues providing the source of F emission in Mt-PrsA (Eriksen  et al. 2000). The inclusion of ADP at two different 
concentrations (0.1 and 2.0 mM) in separate ITF [ATP]  ligand-binding assays causes a significant increase in the 
apparent K d of ATP for its Mt-PrsA-binding site 
(K </p>

<p>ATP 
d </p>

<p>¼ 31:22and90:1 mM at a concentration of 0.1 and 2.0 
mM ADP, respectively), clearly illustrating allosteric </p>

<p>inhibition of Mt-PrsA-ATP complex formation (Figure 9B). 
The change in the slope of the curve as a function of [ATP] in 
separate ITF experiments carried out at increasing ADP con-
centrations, clearly illustrates a reduction in the homotropic 
cooperative binding of ATP for Mt-PrsA, which was con-
firmed by calculating the resultant Hill coefficients 
(Figure 9B). The ligand-binding properties of ADP for 
Mt-PrsA, in the presence of ATP, compare well with the inhi-
bition constant calculated for ADP [K i = 522 µM (±45.78 SE)] 
obtained from the kinetic analysis of ν vs. [ATP] at saturating 
[R5P] (Figure 6B). </p>

<p>Structural model of Mt-PrsA 
An alignment of Mt-PrsA with its related Corynebacterineae 
PrsA orthologs as well as other bacterial Prs homologs from 
Bacillus subtilis (Bs_PrsA), E. coli (Ec_PrsA) and 
Streptomyces coelicolor (Sc_PrsA), and the three human Prs 
isoforms (Human_PrsA1-3) clearly illustrate the high level of 
primary sequence conservation between all variants 
(Figure 10). Mt-PrsA shares very high sequence identity with 
its Corynebacterineae counterparts (92% Mycobacterium 
leprae, 87% M. smegmatis and 71% C. glutamicum) and a 
moderate level of sequence identity with Mt-PrsA homologs 
in S. coleicolor (61%), E. coli (43%) and B. subtilis (43%). 
Interestingly, the three human Prs isoforms also share 40% 
sequence identity with Mt-PrsA. Both of the human type 1 
and B. subtilis pRpp synthetase X-ray crystal structures have 
been solved (Eriksen et al. 2000; Li et al. 2007). Each of 
these structures was solved in the Apo form and in complex 
with AMP, which is located in the ATP-binding pocket of the 
active site. Interestingly, the Bs-PrsA structure was solved in 
complex with an additional molecule of ADP, thus revealing 
its position and mode of action in the allosteric regulatory site 
of the enzyme (Eriksen et al. 2000). Since Mt-PrsA shares 
highest sequence homology with Bs-PrsA, we constructed a 
homology model of Mt-PrsA using the structure of Bs-Prs in 
complex with AMP and ADP as a template (Eriksen et al.  2000; Figure 11). Using crystallographic symmetry data from 
the Bs-Prs structure, we arranged the Mt-PrsA homology 
model into its hexameric form (Figure 11A). Each monomer 
is composed of two subunits, which is related by a 3-fold axis 
perpendicular to an additional 2-fold planar rotational sym-
metry. Many of the residues involved in binding at the inter-
face between monomers are well conserved, with notable 
differences highlighted by the position of red spheres in 
Figure 11A. With only a few exceptions, the sequence align-
ment of Mt-PrsA and Bs-Prs indicates that most of the resi-
dues involved in enzyme catalysis and allosteric regulation are 
conserved which, in turn, are suitably positioned in the 
Mt-PrsA homology model compared with Bs-Prs. A note-
worthy difference in the Mt-PrsA catalytic site is the presence 
of Asn45, which is arranged to form contacts with the ADP 
ligand (Figure 11B). In the Bs-Prs structure, the equivalent 
residue is Asp42. In addition, further comparison of the two 
structures suggests that the Mt-PrsA homology model retains 
all of the important residues required for the regulatory site, 
apart from Gly88 (Ala85 in Bs-Prs), which participates in the 
formation of contacts to ADP with a neighboring Ser89 
(Figure 11B). An interesting observation in the model of </p>

<p>Fig. 9. Binding kinetics of ADP and ATP to Mt-PrsA using ITF spectroscopy. 
ITF spectroscopy was used to determine the binding properties of Mt-PrsA 
for it's allosteric inhibitor ADP in competition with ATP. Ligand-binding 
assays were carried out as described in the Materials and methods section. 
(A) A plot of ΔF emission vs. [ADP] (filled circles) which was fitted to Eq. (8). 
(B) A plot of ΔF emission vs. [ATP] in the presence of no ADP (filled squares), 
0.1 mM ADP (filled triangles) and 2.0 mM ADP (filled inverted triangles) 
which was fitted to Eq. (10). </p>

<p>Mycobacterium tuberculosis pRpp synthetase </p>



<p>Fig. 10. Sequence alignment of various prokaryotic pRpp synthetases. Protein sequences from M. tuberculosis (Mt_PrsA), M. smegmatis (Ms_PrsA), M. leprae 
(Ml_PrsA), C. glutamicum (Cg_PrsA), S. coleicolor (Sc_PrsA), B. subtilis (Bs_PrsA), E. coli (Ec-PrsA) and the three PrsA isoforms (Human_PrsA1-3) were 
aligned using CLUSTALW and annotated with ESPRIPT. Triangles represent residues involved in catalysis. Filled circles indicate conserved and open circles 
highlight nonconserved residues involved in allosteric regulation. His109 and Gly111 are highlighted with stars, indicating two residues only found in the flexible 
loop region of Corynebacterianeae PrsA homologs. The diamonds indentify the location of the residues involved in the formation of a salt bridge in Bs-PrsA and 
Human-PrsA1. </p>

<p>LJ Alderwick et al. </p>



<p>Mt-PrsA is the presence of His109 in the "flexible loop" 
formed by Mt-PrsA residues Lys108-Arg112. Ala106 is the 
equivalent residue in Bs-Prs, and it appears to play little if no 
part in binding or coordination of the ADP ligand. This flex-
ible loop region, which contains many conserved residues 
(Figure 10), has been identified as displaying some of the 
largest variation in backbone conformation, and the confor-
mational changes that occur upon substrate binding are con-
sidered to be important for catalysis (Eriksen et al. 2000). The 
presence of a His residue in the Mt-PrsA flexible loop region 
might allow for multiple hydrogen bonding opportunities 
between His109 and the ATP substrate in the catalytic site 
(Figure 11B). Gly111 is another conserved residue located in 
the flexible loop of mycobacterial PrsA enzymes, which in 
the majority of other bacterial homologs is typically replaced 
by a Ser that makes H-bond interactions with the α-phosphate 
of ADP in the allosteric site (Figure 11C). Both the 
Human-PrsA1 and the Bs-PrsA homodimers are stabilized by 
a salt bridge at the N-terminal interface formed between two 
conserved residues (Asn114 and Asp139, and Asn120 and 
Asp145, respectively) (Eriksen et al. 2000; Li et al. 2007). 
From the sequence alignment and the Mt-PrsA homology 
model, it is worth noting that the equivalent Asn residue is 
replaced by an aspartic acid (Asp122) which would sit in 
close proximity to Asp147. Therefore, it is reasonable to 
assume that unlike Human-PrsA1 and Bs-PrsA, a salt bridge 
does not occur at the Mt-PrsA dimer interface. Interestingly, 
the Human-PrsA1 Asn114 (Asp122 in Mt-PrsA) is often 
mutated to a Ser in the cells of patients suffering from gout </p>

<p>(Becker et al. 1995). It has been reported that the molecular 
mechanism behind the 50% increase in N114S mutant 
enzyme activity is caused by a disruption of a salt bridge, 
which would otherwise stabilizes the dimer interface (Liu  et al. 2009). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The presence of D-arabinose in living organisms is rarely 
observed. Whilst the utilization of D-arabinopyranose seems to 
be confined to glycoconjugate formation in trypanosomatid 
parasites (Turnock and Ferguson 2007), arabinose in the 
furanose configuration (Araf ) is exclusively used by bacteria in 
the formation of cell surface polysaccharides and the biosyn-
thesis of glycolipid antigens. Members belonging to the 
Corynebacterineae, such as M. tuberculosis and C. glutami-
cum, contain large quantities of Araf in the form of arabinan, 
which in turn, is covalently attached to galactan and mannan, 
thus forming AG and LAM, respectively. Whilst LAM exerts 
its biological activity by subverting the host immune response, 
the primary function of AG is to provide a highly branched 
molecular scaffold, linking the murein sacculus to the hydro-
phobic mycolate layer. Since arabinan is an essential com-
ponent of the TB cell wall and is targeted by treatment with 
EMB, other enzymes involved in its formation might present 
themselves as potential putative drug targets. In this regard, 
DPPR synthetase (Rv3806c) is a novel enzyme catalyzing the 
transfer of pRpp to decaprenol-1-monphosphate forming </p>

<p>Fig. 11. Homology model of Mt-PrsA. (A) Mt-PrsA arranged into its hexameric quaternary conformation. Carbon atoms of the ADP ligands located at the 
catalytic and regulatory sites of the Mt-PrsA hexamer are colored in orange and green, respectively. Red spheres located at K10, D169, G194, D205-V208 and 
F322 indicate regions of the Mt-PrsA dimmer that include insertions or deletions with respect to the Bs-Prs structure. The triangle in the middle represents 3-fold 
symmetry, where as the arrow parallel to the plane indicates 2-fold rotational symmetry. Catalytic (B) and regulatory (C) sites of the Mt-PrsA homology model. 
The yellow and the blue spheres indicate A85/G88 and S109/G111 substitution between the Bs-Prs and Mt-PrsA structures, respectively. </p>

<p>Mycobacterium tuberculosis pRpp synthetase </p>



<p>DPPR (Figure 1), represents the first committed step toward 
the biosynthesis of DPA (an exclusive cell wall AraT substrate) 
and, as a consequence of its genetic disruption in C. glutami-
cum (a model organism used to study M. tuberculosis cell wall 
physiology), affords a phenotype displaying retarded growth, 
and a severely altered cell wall composition which is comple-
tely deficient in arabinan (Alderwick et al. 2005). In addition, 
DprE1 (Rv3790) has been shown to be the molecular target of 
benzothiazinones, a new class of antimycobacterial agents, 
which can effectively kill MDR and XDR strains of TB by 
blocking the C2-OH epimerization of DPR to DPA (Makarov  et al. 2009). Some of the current front line drugs used to treat 
TB include cell wall inhibitors. However, the incidence of 
MDR and XDR-TB cases is alarmingly high and continues to 
rise (Madariaga et al. 2008). Since the M. tuberculosis cell 
wall is a valid drug target, we must continue to investigate the 
physiology, biochemistry and metabolic pathways involved in 
its assembly to assist our efforts of developing new anti-TB 
therapies. However, nondividing drug-tolerant populations of 
"persistent" TB bacilli fail to be eradicated from the host, 
giving rise to a latent infection as a result of subsequent granu-
loma formation (Barry et al. 2009). Inhibition of the cell wall 
biosynthetic processes of TB bacilli responsible for latent 
infections is of no consequence, this being due to the fact that 
persistent TB bacilli are not undergoing active cell growth and 
division. However, these "dormant" TB bacilli still require a 
basal level of "energy" metabolites in order to maintain critical 
cellular functions (Koul et al. 2008). 
pRpp is a central metabolite ubiquitous in nature providing 
a high-energy substrate for the biosynthesis of histidine, try-
phophan, NAD, NADP and both the de novo and the salvage 
pathways involved in nucleoside metabolism (Hove-Jensen 
1988; Figure 1). In addition to these central metabolic pro-
cesses, the Corynebacterineae have evolved a unique pathway 
in which pRpp is siphoned into cell wall arabinan biosyn-
thesis (Figure 1). In M. tuberculosis, Mt-PrsA is entirely 
responsible for the provision of pRpp and its cellular function 
bridges five different metabolic pathways (Figure 1). The 
omphalic nature of Mt-PrsA places a heavy burden on its bio-
logical function, especially during cell growth and division, 
when the cellular requirement for pRpp increases significantly. 
In this study, we describe the biochemical characterization of 
Mt-PrsA, which displays the highest recorded specific activity 
for a pRpp synthetase of 530 µmol 
−1 min 
−1 mg </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>. The K m for 
R5P was calculated to be in the submicromolar range of 8.2 
µM, suggesting a rapid enzyme turnover with a calculated 
specificity constant (K cat /K m ) of 7.4 × 10 
6 M 
−1 s </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>. This rela-
tively high efficiency of Mt-PrsA fits well with the physio-
logical function of the enzyme during cell wall biosynthesis, 
considering the increased demand for pRpp that is required 
for antecedent DPA biosynthesis. Mt-PrsA displays clear 
homotropic cooperativity for ATP, with an apparent S 0.5 
62.65 µM, which is extremely low considering the intracellu-
lar concentration of ATP is considered to be between 3 and 5 
mM. The homology model generated for Mt-PrsA contains 
many structural features of other pRpp synthetases that have 
been solved to date. The majority of the active site residues 
modeled in Mt-PrsA are conserved with those from other 
Mt-PrsA homologs, and it appears that the appropriate </p>

<p>configuration of amino acid side chains compares well with 
the B. subtilis structure. This is also the case for the regulatory 
site in which ADP binds to allosterically modulate the 
enzyme. However, an interesting observation is the 
presence of His109 in the flexible loop region of Mt-PrsA, a 
residue exclusively conserved within members of the 
Corynebacterineae. Considering the close proximity of His109 
to both the catalytic and the regulatory sites of Mt-PrsA, and 
its potential to make direct contacts with both ATP and ADP 
ligands, the presence of this conserved His in the flexible 
region of mycobacterial pRpp synthetases might provide some 
explanation for the relatively high K cat . pRpp synthetase 
superactivity is observed in human type-1 N114S mutants 
(Becker et al. 1995). This increase in activity is a result of the 
loss of a salt bridge formed between two monomers which 
induces small but significant changes to the catalytic and 
regulatory sites of the enzyme (Liu et al. 2009). Interestingly, 
the homology model of Mt-PrsA suggests that a salt bridge 
between the equivalent residues does not occur thus reducing 
the stability of the dimer interface. In mycobacteria, the bio-
synthesis of pRpp is required at a rate which is sufficient to 
not only supply central metabolic processes, such as de novo 
nucleoside biosynthesis, but also at a necessary level to meet 
the increased demands for pRpp during cell wall biosynthesis 
(Scherman et al. 1995, 1996). It seems plausible that pRpp 
synthetases from Corynebacterineae species have evolved a 
highly efficient version of the enzyme to account for the 
increased metabolic flux of pRpp, during various physiologi-
cal states. pRpp synthetases in other organisms undergo strin-
gent control by virtue of allosteric modulation from ADP. In 
this regard, Mt-PrsA also appears to be no different, display-
ing clear inhibition of enzyme activity between 0.5 and 2.0 
mM ADP. When taken together, the data relating to ADP inhi-
bition and the subsequent complex formation with Mt-PrsA 
suggest that the mechanism employed for the allosteric regu-
lation of Mt-PrsA by ADP is through the formation of an 
Mt-PrsA hexamer (Arnvig et al. 1990). This net increase in 
Mt-PrsA hexamer oligomerization suggests that the efficacy of 
ATP for its Mt-PrsA catalytic site decreases, as a consequence 
of ADP allosteric modulation. The three human PrsA iso-
forms share a very high sequence identity (91-95% 
between all three); however, the subtle differences that do 
occur appear in the regions of the enzyme that are important 
for catalysis and allosteric regulation. Inhibition studies 
using two aminopyrimidopyrimidine nucleotide analogs 
4-methoxy-8-(β-D-ribofuranosylamino)-pyrimido-[5,4-d]-pyri-
midine and 4-amino-8-(β-D-ribofuranosylamino) -pyrimido-
[5,4-d]-pyrimidine show differential levels of inhibition of 
human pRpp synthetases (Fry et al. 1995). Carbocyclic 
analogs of R5P are another class of compounds that show 
differential inhibition when tested against Salmonella typhi-
murium, B. subtilis and human pRpp synthetases (Parry et al.  1996). In this regard, the development of a similar library of 
compounds targeted for the specific inhibition of Mt-PrsA 
might warrant further investigation. Understanding the meta-
bolic pathways that are essential for persistent TB infections, 
such as mycobacterial energy metabolism, in combination 
with pathways involved in cell wall assembly seems a plaus-
ible strategy for the development of new antimycobacterial 
drugs. </p>

<p>LJ Alderwick et al. </p>



<p>Materials and methods 
Bacterial strains cloning procedures 
Escherichia coli top 10 cells (Invitrogen) were used to propa-
gate plasmids during all cloning experiments, and the 
overexpression of Mt-PrsA was carried out in E. coli C41 
(DE3) (Lucigen). Phusion DNA polymerase was purchased 
from New England Biolabs, and all restriction enzymes and 
T4 DNA ligase were purchased from Fermentas. 
Oligonucleotides were purchased from Eurofins-MWG and 
PCR fragments were purified using QIAquick Gel Extraction 
Kit (Qiagen). Plasmids were purified using the Qiaprep 
Purification Kit (Qiagen). </p>

<p>Generation of C. glutamicum prsA-null mutant 
For the genomic disruption of NCgl0945 (Cg-prsA), we con-
structed the plasmid pK18mob-Cg-prsA-int, using the primer 
pair pNCgl0945_intfor (GCGAGCCAATTTCTGCTCGC) 
and pNCgl0945_intrev (GACAACCTGGTTTGCTACCTC), 
to amplify C. glutamicum WT chromosomal DNA. The result-
ing DNA fragment was treated with AvaI/KpnI and ligated 
into the nonreplicative vector pK18mob (Schafer et al. 1994), 
which was similarly treated with AvaI/KpnI. The DNA integ-
rity of the resulting construct pK18mob-Cg-prsA-int was con-
firmed by sequencing and used for the transformation of C. 
glutamicum by electroporation and selected for resistance to 
kanamycin at 25 µg/mL on BHIS medium. </p>

<p>Construction of Mt-PrsA expression vector 
The 981 bp coding region for Mt-PrsA (annotated as 
Rv1017c) in the M. tuberculosis H37Rv genome was ampli-
fied by PCR using the following primer pairs (restriction sites 
underlined) GATCGATCGCTAGCTTGAGCCACGACTGGA 
CCGATAATCGC (forward) and GATCGATCCTCGAG 
TGCGTCCCCGTCGAAAAGTCCTGTTAC (reverse). This 
DNA fragment was restricted with the appropriate enzymes 
(NheI and XhoI) and ligated into pET23b digested with identi-
cal enzymes, thus yielding pET23b-Mt-prsA, which encodes 
for a C-terminal His 6 -tagged protein. DNA sequencing and 
construct verification were carried out at the University of 
Birmingham School of Bioscience Genomics Facility. </p>

<p>Expression and purification of Mt-PrsA 
Escherichia coli C41 (DE3) cells were transformed with 
pET23b-Mt-prsA and selected on the LB agar supplemented 
with 100 µg/mL of amplicillin. Recombinant E. coli cells har-
boring pET23b-Mt-prsA were used to inoculate an overnight 
of 5 mL LB supplemented with 100 µg/mL of amplicillin. 
This overnight was then used to inoculate 2 × 1 L LB medium 
supplemented with 100 µg/mL of amplicillin and incubated at 
37°C with shaking until A 600 reached 0.5. IPTG was then 
added at a final concentration of 1 mM and growth continued 
for an additional 12 h at 16°C with shaking. Cells were har-
vested by centrifugation at 6000 × g for 15 min and washed 
with 20 mL of phosphate buffered saline. Pellets were then 
frozen until further use. For purification, one pellet was 
thawed and resuspended into 50 mM KH 2 PO 4 ( pH 7.9), 300 
mM NaCl, 20 mM imidazole, one complete protease inhibitor 
cocktail tablet (Roche) and DNAse and RNAse both at a final </p>

<p>concentration of 50 µg/mL. The cell suspension was disrupted 
by sonication at a pulse rate of 30 s ON and 30 s OFF for a 
total of 10 cycles. The cell slurry was centrifuged for 30 min, 
28,000 × g at a temperature of 4°C. The supernatant was 
collected and passed over a 5 mL HiTrap Ni 
2+ -NTA agarose 
column (GE Healthcare), which was previously equilibrated 
with 50 mM KH 2 PO 4 ( pH 7.9), 300 mM NaCl and 20 
mM imidazole. Elution occurred via a stepwise gradient of 
50-500 mM imidazole in 50 mM KH 2 PO 4 ( pH 7.9), 300 mM 
NaCl and 10 mL of fractions were collected. Mt-PrsA was 
detected to be present and 98% pure in the 250 mM imida-
zole fraction, as determined by 12% SDS-PAGE analysis. 
The 250 mM imidazole fractions of Mt-PrsA was first dia-
lyzed against 2 L of KH 2 PO 4 ( pH 7.9), 150 mM NaCl, 5 mM 
EDTA and 1 mM DTT at 4°C and then against 2 L of 
KH 2 PO 4 ( pH 7.9), 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM DTT and 10% gly-
cerol. After dialysis, the protein concentration was determined 
using the bicinchoninic acid procedure (Pierce) and bovine 
serum albumin as a standard. </p>

<p>Preparation of [ 
14 C]-R5P </p>

<p>We prepared a source of [ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]-R5P using a modified process 
as described in Boss et al. (1984), for the subsequent use in 
Mt-PrsA assays. One hundred microcuries of [ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]-U-D-
glucose (100 µL in 70% ethanol; ARC Radiochemicals) was 
dried in a 14 mL glass tube under compressed nitrogen and 
then resuspended in 500 µL of 50 mM KH 2 PO 4 ( pH 7.9), 150 
mM NaCl, 5 mM MgCl 2 and 0.5 mM MnCl 2 . Twenty microli-
ters of ATP (100 mM stock) and 20 µL of NADP (100 mM 
stock) was added to the suspension. Twenty microliters of hex-
okinase/glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase enzyme mix 
(Roche) was added and incubated at 37°C for 15 min. A few 
grains of 6-phosphogluconic dehydrogenase (Sigma) and a 
further 20 µL of NADP (100 mM stock) were added and incu-
bated for 15 min at 37°C. A few grains of phosphoribose 
mutase (Sigma) were added to the reaction mix and incubated 
for a further 15 min at 37°C followed by another addition of 
20 µL of NADP (100 mM stock) and final incubation at 37°C 
for 15 min. The reaction mix was then diluted with H 2 O to a 
final volume of 3 mL and passed through a 10 kDa MWCO 
centrifugal filtration device (Millipore). The filtrate ( 3 mL) 
was then loaded onto a 3 mL LC-SAX anion exchange car-
tridge (Supelco) pre-equilibrated with H 2 O. The column was 
then washed three times with 3 mL of H 2 O. The column was 
then washed with a 100-1000 mM stepwise gradient of 
sodium acetate (3 mL of fractions of 100 mM increments). 
Each fraction (1 µL) was applied to a glass-backed 
PEI-cellulose TLC plate and developed in 0.85 M KH 2 PO 4 
( pH 3.4). After drying, the TLC plate was exposed overnight 
to a Kodak autoradiography film for visualization of 
radioactive phospho-sugars. [ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]-R5P eluted as a single 
band (when compared with the known standards) in the 
200 mM sodium acetate fraction with a specific activity of 
33,333 cpm/µL. </p>

<p>Radiochemical assay of Mt-PrsA activity 
The enzymatic activity of Mt-PrsA was determined by moni-
toring the transfer of PPi from ATP to the C1-OH group of 
enzymatically synthesized [ 
14 C]-R5P forming p[ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]Rpp and </p>

<p>Mycobacterium tuberculosis pRpp synthetase </p>

<p>421 </p>

<p>AMP. The basic reaction mix contained 50 mM KH 2 PO 4 (pH 
7.5), 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM DTT, 10% glycerol, varying 
amounts of [ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]-D-R5P [stored in 200 mM sodium acetate 
(33,333 cpm/µL)], 2 mM ATP and 30 µg of Mt-PrsA (15 µL) 
in a final volume of 100 µL. On occasions, MgCl 2 , MnCl 2 , 
CaCl 2 , ADP and EDTA were included in the reaction mix 
either separately or in combination, all at a final concentration 
of 2 mM. Reactions were initiated by the addition of Mt-PrsA 
and incubated at 37°C for 10 min. Reactions were quenched 
by the addition of 10 µL of 0.4 M formic acid. The mixture 
(1.1 µL) was applied to a glass-backed PEI-cellulose TLC 
plate and developed in 0.85 M KH 2 PO 4 ( pH 3.4). After 
drying, the plate was inspected for radioactive spots by either 
exposure to a Kodak film followed by autoradiography or a 
PhosphorImager (Molecular Dynamics). All experiments were 
repeated in triplicate. </p>

<p>Metabolism of [ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]-R5P into mycobacterial cell wall 
biosynthetic precursors 
Membranes (containing membrane bound enzymes involved 
in lipid-linked cell wall biosynthetic processes) and "P60" 
[a percoll-derived cell-free fraction-rich carbohydrate and 
enzymes associated with cell wall processes as described in 
Besra et al. (1997)] fractions from M. smegmatis were pre-
pared as described previously (Besra et al. 1997; Lee et al.  1997; Alderwick, Dover, et al. 2006) and resuspended 
in buffer A [50 mM MOPS ( pH 7.9), containing 5 mM 
β-mercaptoethanol and 10 mM MgCl 2 ] to a final concen-
tration of 15 and 10 mg/mL for membrane and P60 fractions, 
respectively. Fifty micrograms of DP [Larodan Lipids, 
Malmo, Sweden; 5 mg/mL stored in CHCl 3 /CH 3 OH (2:1, 
v/v)] was dried in a 1.5 mL Eppendorf tube under compressed 
nitrogen and was resuspended by the addition of 10 µL of a 
solution of 50 mM MOPS ( pH 7.9), 50 mM KH 2 PO 4 , 150 
mM NaCl, 1 mM MnCl 2 , 1 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM DTT and 1% 
IgePal CA-630 (Sigma) followed by bath sonication. The 
basic assay mix consisted of 0.5 mg of M. smegmatis mem-
branes (33 µL), 2 mM ATP, 50 mM MOPS ( pH 7.9), 50 mM 
KH 2 PO 4 , 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM MnCl 2 , 1 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM 
DTT, 100,000 cpm [ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]-R5P (3 µL) in a final volume of 
200 µL. NaWO 4 and NaF as well as ADP were included in 
separate assay reactions at a final concentration of 2 mM for 
all inhibition studies. 0.5 mg of M. smegmatis P60 (50 µL) 
was added where appropriate. Reactions were initiated by the 
addition of 30 µg of Mt-PrsA (15 µL) and incubated at 37°C 
for 30 min. Assays were quenched by the addition of 1.33 mL 
of CHCl 3 /CH 3 OH (1:1, v/v), mixed for 30 min and centri-
fuged at 27,000 × g to remove the precipitated proteinaceous 
material. The supernatant was removed to a separate tube and 
combined with 670 µL of CHCl 3 and 287 µL of H 2 O, mixed 
for 15 min and centrifuged for 5 min at 4000 × g to form a 
biphase. The lower organic phase was removed and washed 
twice with 765 µL of CHCl 3 /CH 3 OH/H 2 O (3:47:48, v/v/v) 
and then dried under compressed nitrogen. Samples were then 
resuspended in 100 µL of CHCl 3 /CH 3 OH (2:1, v/v) and an 
aliquot subject to TLC analysis using silica gel plates (5735 
silica gel 60F254, Merck) developed in CHCl 3 /CH 3 OH/ 
CH 3 COONH 4 /NH 4 OH/H 2 O (180:140:9:9:23, v/v/v/v/v) and </p>

<p>visualized by autoradiography by exposure of TLCs to X-ray 
film (Kodak X-Omat) as described in Mikusova et al. (2005). </p>

<p>Metabolism of [ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]-R5P into mycobacterial cell wall 
biosynthetic precursors and the subsequent AraT-dependent 
transfer to a neoglycolipid acceptor. 
Membranes and P60 from M. smegmatis were prepared as 
described in Materials and Methods. The neoglycolipid accep-
tor used in this study was the disaccharide α-D-Araf-(1 → 
5)-α-D-Araf-O-(CH 2 ) 7 CH 3 (Ara 2 ), which has been previously 
reported by us (Lee et al. 1997; Seidel et al. 2007). In individ-
ual assays, the 8 µL of Ara 2 acceptor (stored in CHCl 3 / 
CH 3 OH, 2:1, v/v at 20 mM) and 50 µg of DP [Larodan Lipids; 
5 mg/mL stored in CHCl 3 /CH 3 OH (2:1, v/v)] was aliquoted 
into 1.5 mL Eppendorf tubes and dried under nitrogen. The 
AraT assay was carried out as described previously (Lee et al.  1997; Seidel et al. 2007) with modifications. IgePal™ 
(Sigma-Aldrich) was added (0.1%, v/v) with the appropriate 
amount of buffer A (final volume of 100 µL). Tubes were 
sonicated for 15 min to resuspend lipid-linked substrates and 
then mixed with the remaining assay components, which 
included 0.5 mg of M. smegmatis membranes (33 µL), 0.5 mg 
of M. smegmatis P60 (50 µL), 30 µg of Mt-PrsA (15 µL), 1 
mM ATP, 1 mM NADP and in some cases EMB (100 µg/mL). 
Assays were incubated for 1 h at 37°C and quenched by the 
addition of 633 µL of CHCl 3 /CH 3 OH (1:1, v/v). After mixing 
and centrifugation at 27,000 × g for 15 min at 4°C, the super-
natant was removed and dried under nitrogen. The residue was 
then resuspended in 700 µL of CH 3 CH 2 OH/H 2 O (1:1, v/v) 
and loaded onto a 1 mL LC-SAX strong anion exchange car-
tridge (Supelco), pre-equilibrated with CH 3 CH 2 OH/H 2 O (1:1, 
v/v). The column was washed with 2 mL of CH 3 CH 2 OH and 
the eluate collected, dried and partitioned between the two 
phases arising from a mixture of n-butanol (3 mL) and water 
(3 mL). The resulting organic phase was recovered following 
centrifugation at 3500 × g and the aqueous phase again 
extracted twice with 3 mL of water-saturated n-butanol. The 
pooled 
extracts 
were 
back-washed 
twice 
with 
n-butanol-saturated water (3 mL). The n-butanol fraction was 
dried and resuspended in 200 µL of butanol. The extracted 
radiolabeled material was quantified by liquid scintillation 
counting using 10% of the labeled material and 5 mL of 
EcoScintA (National Diagnostics, Atlanta). The incorporation 
of [ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]-Araf into Ara 2 was determined by subtracting counts 
present in control assays (incubations in the absence of accep-
tor). The remaining labeled material was subjected to TLC 
using CHCl 3 :CH 2 OH:H 2 O:NH 4 OH (65:25:3.6:0.5, v/v/v/v) on 
aluminum-backed silica gel plates (5735 silica gel 60F254, 
Merck) and products were visualized by autoradiography, 
exposing the TLCs to X-ray film (Kodak X-Omat). </p>

<p>Continuous enzyme-coupled spectrophotometric assay 
and kinetic characterization of Mt-PrsA substrates 
By using a modified assay described by Braven et al. (1984), 
the amount of AMP produced as a product of Mt-PrsA cataly-
sis was measured indirectly by monitoring the decrease in the 
absorbance of NADH at 340 nm via the following enzyme 
couple: 1. R5P + ATP → pRpp + AMP, catalyzed by Mt-PrsA; 
2. AMP + ATP → 2 ADP, catalyzed by myokinase (MK); 3. 2 </p>

<p>LJ Alderwick et al. </p>



<p>ADP + 2 phosphoenolpyruvate (PEP) → 2 pyruvate + 2 ATP, 
catalyzed by pyruvate kinase (PK) and 4. 2 pyruvate + 2 
NADH + 2 H 
+ → 2 lactate + 2 NAD 
+ , catalyzed by lactate 
dehydrogenase (LDH). This perpetual enzyme couple 
immediately replenishes the pool of ATP and results in a stoi-
chiometry of 1 mol NADH oxidized by LDH for every 2 mol 
AMP produced by Mt-PrsA. The following formula was used 
to calculate the rate of reaction thus allowing for a detailed 
kinetic characterization of Mt-PrsA </p>

<p>v ¼ 
DA s </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>2 
Â 6220 M </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>ð1Þ </p>

<p>where ν is the steady-state rate of the reaction, ΔA the change 
in absorbance at 340 nm and 6220 M 
−1 the molecular extinc-
tion coefficient of NADH measured at 340 nm. The reaction 
mixture comprised of 50 mM KH 2 PO 4 ( pH 7.9), 150 mM 
NaCl, 0.25 mM DTT, 2 mM MnCl 2 , 2.0 mM PEP, 1.0 mM 
NADH and 5 mM NaF, MK, PK and LDH were added to the 
mix all at a concentration of 0.2 U/mL. Variable amounts of 
ATP, R5P and ADP were added to the reaction mix for 
enzyme kinetic and inhibitor studies. Reactions were initiated 
by the addition of R5P. All kinetic experiments were carried 
out in triplicate (from three different independent protein 
preparations of purified recombinant Mt-PrsA), and data 
points (calculated mean) and standard errors (±SE) relating to 
the enzyme steady-state velocities (ν) (µmol min 
−1 mg </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>) 
derived from Eq. (1) under various substrate and inhibitor 
conditions were analyzed by nonlinear regression analysis and 
fitted to the appropriate Eqs. (2)-(6) using the <rs type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> software package. Eq. (2) is the Michelis-Menten 
equation for hyperbolic substrate saturation kinetics and Eq. 
(3) applies to the nonlinear regression of substrate inhibition. 
Eq. (4) is the Hill equation for calculating cooperative sub-
strate saturation kinetics, Eq. (5) applies to noncompetitive 
enzyme inhibition of a hyperbolic enzyme response and 
Eq. (6) is derived from combining Eqs. (4) and (5) to give an 
expression for noncompetitive enzyme inhibition of a 
cooperative sigmoidal response to increasing substrate concen-
trations. </p>

<p>n ¼ V max Â 
S 
K m þ S 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>n ¼ V app Â 
S 
K m þ S Â ð1 þ S=K i Þ 
ð3Þ </p>

<p>n ¼ V app Â 
S </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>0:5 þ S n </p>

<p>ð4Þ </p>

<p>n ¼ V app Â 
S 
K m ð1 þ I=K is Þ þ SðI þ I=K ii Þ 
ð5Þ </p>

<p>n ¼ V app Â 
S </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>0:5 ð1 þ I=K is Þ þ S n ð1 þ I=K ii Þ </p>

<p>ð6Þ </p>

<p>where V max is the maximum enzyme velocity, V app the appar-
ent maximal enzyme velocity, S the concentration of the sub-
strate being varied, I the inhibitor concentration, K m the 
apparent Michelis-Menten constant for S, S 0.5 the half-
saturation concentration for S, n the apparent Hill coefficient 
for S, K is and K ii the dissociation constants of the [I] for E 
and ES, respectively. </p>

<p>Analytical ultracentrifugation 
Sedimentation velocity experiments were performed using a 
Beckman Optima XL-A analytical ultracentrifuge equipped 
with absorbance optics. Mt-PrsA [dialyzed into 50 mM 
KH 2 PO 4 ( pH 7.9), 300 mM NaCl, 1 mM DTT] was loaded 
into cells with two channel Epon center pieces and quartz 
windows. A total of 100 absorbance scans (280 nm) were 
recorded (40,000 rpm, 4°C) for each sample, representing the 
full extent of sedimentation of the sample. Data analysis was 
performed using the <rs id="software-2" type="software">SEDFIT</rs> software fitting a single friction 
coefficient (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Schuck</rs> 2004). </p>

<p>ITF spectroscopy 
ITF experiments were carried out using a PTI QuantaMaster™ 
40 spectrofluorimeter and data recorded using the <rs type="software">FeliX32</rs> 
software. The excitation wavelength was set at 292 nm, and 
the fluorescence emission (F emission ) spectra were recorded 
between 300 and 400 nm for each ligand aliquot added to a 
200 µL solution containing 70 µM Mt-PrsA. 50 mM KH 2 PO 4 
( pH 7.9), 150 mM NaCl, 0.25 mM DTT, 2 mM MnCl 2 was 
used as a buffer for the measurement of R5P, ATP and 
AMPPNP ligand binding (or a combination) to Mt-PrsA. A 
plot of the change in fluorescence emission (ΔF emission ) inten-
sity at λ 335nm vs. [L] was fitted to Eq. (7) for R5P, Eq. (8) for 
ATP and ADP for independent additions, Eq. (9) for R5P in 
combination with AMPPNP and Eq. (10) for ATP and ADP in 
combination using <rs type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> software </p>

<p>DF emission ¼ F max Â 
L 
ðK d þ LÞ 
ð7Þ </p>

<p>DF emission ¼ F max Â 
L n 
ðK </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>d þ L n Þ </p>

<p>ð8Þ </p>

<p>DF emission ¼ F </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>max Â </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>ðK d þ L a Þ 
þ F </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>max Â </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>nb </p>

<p>ðK </p>

<p>nb </p>

<p>d þ L nb Þ </p>

<p>ð9Þ </p>

<p>DF emission ¼ F </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>max Â </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>na </p>

<p>ðK </p>

<p>na </p>

<p>d þ L na Þ </p>

<p>þ F </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>max Â </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>nb </p>

<p>ðK </p>

<p>nb </p>

<p>d þ L nb Þ </p>

<p>ð10Þ </p>

<p>where F max indicates the maximum change in fluorescence 
emission, K d the concentration of ligand required to achieve 
half maximum fluorescence, L the concentration of ligand and 
n the Hill coefficient. Both a and b relate to the relative par-
ameters determined for two separate ligands included in a 
binding assay. </p>

<p>Mycobacterium tuberculosis pRpp synthetase </p>



<p>Generation of a Mt-PrsA homology model 
A homology model of the molecular structure of Mt-PrsA was 
derived based on the crystal structure of B. subtilis Prs 
(Eriksen et al. 2000). Models were obtained from several 
web-based modeling servers, including SWISS-MODEL 
(Schwede et al. 2003), Geno3D (Combet et al. 2002) and 
3D-JIGSAW (Bates et al. 2001). The homology models were 
analyzed in comparison with the Bs-Prs structures in complex 
with SO 4 
− or mADP (PDB entry 1DKR and 1DKU; Eriksen  et al. 2000). </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>G.S.B. acknowledges support in the form of a Personal 
Research Chair from Mr. James Bardrick, Royal Society 
Wolfson Research Merit Award, as a former Lister 
Institute-Jenner Research Fellow, the Medical Research 
Council and The Wellcome Trust (081569/Z/06/Z). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>None declared. </p>

<p>Abbreviations </p>

<p>AG, arabinogalactan; AMPPNP, ATP analog 5'-adenylyl-β, 
γ-imidodiphosphate; 
Ara 2 , 
α-D-Araf-(1 → 5)-α-D-Araf-O-
(CH 2 ) 7 CH 3 ; AraT, arabinofuranosyltransferase; [ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]-R5P, 
[ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]-U-D-R5P; DP, decaprenol-1-monophosphate; DPA, 
decaprenol-1-monophosphorarabinose; DPR, decaprenol-1-
monophosphoribose; DPPR, decaprenol-1-monophosphori 
bose-5-phosphate; DPX, decaprenol-1-monophosphoryl-2-
keto-β-erythro-pentofuranose; EMB, ethambutol; ITF, intrinsic 
tryptophan fluorescence; LAM, lipoarabinomannan; LDH, 
lactate dehydrogenase; MDR, multidrug resistant; MK, myoki-
nase; Mt-PrsA, Mycobacterium tuberculosis phosphoribosyl-1-
pyrophosphate synthetase; PEP, phosphoenolpyruvate; PK, pyr-
uvate kinase; pRpp, phosphoribosyl-1-pyrophosphate; R5P, 
ribose-5-phosphate; TB, tuberculosis; WT, wild type; XDR, 
extensively drug resistant. </p>









</text></tei>