<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3956627" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Currently, synthetic hydroxyapatite nanoparticles (HANPs) are used in nanomedi-</p>

<p>cine fields. The delivery of nanomedicine to the bloodstream exposes the cardiovascular system 
to a potential threat. However, the possible adverse cardiovascular effects of HANPs remain 
unclear. Current observations using coculture models of endothelial cells and monocytes with 
HANPs to mimic the complex physiological functionality of the vascular system demonstrate 
that monocytes could play an important role in the mechanisms of endothelium dysfunction 
induced by the exposure to HANPs. Our transmission electron microscopy analysis revealed 
that both monocytes and endothelial cells could take up HANPs. Moreover, our findings 
demonstrated that at a subcytotoxic dose, HANPs alone did not cause direct endothelial cell 
injury, but they did induce an indirect activation of endothelial cells, resulting in increased 
interleukin-6 production and elevated adhesion molecule expression after coculture with 
monocytes. The potential proinflammatory effect of HANPs is largely mediated by the release 
of soluble factors from the activated monocytes, leading to an inflammatory response of the 
endothelium, which is possibly dependent on p38/c-Jun N-terminal kinase, and nuclear factor-
kappa B signaling activation. The use of in vitro monocyte-endothelial cell coculture models 
for the biocompatibility assessment of HANPs could reveal their potential proinflammatory 
effects on endothelial cells, suggesting that exposure to HANPs possibly increases the risk of 
cardiovascular disease. 
Synthetic hydroxyapatite (HA) (Ca 10 [PO 4 ] 6 [OH] 2 ), a typical bioceramic with good 
osteoconductive and osteoinductive capabilities, has been used clinically for many 
years. 1 Currently, nanotechnology has entered the field of biomaterials, resulting 
in the rapid development of nano-based HA. Due to their better bioactivity, their 
excellent capacity to penetrate cell membranes, and their increased circulation 
time, HA nanoparticles (HANPs) have gradually garnered significant interest 
in various medical fields, such as bone tissue engineering, cardiovascular graft 
coating, contrast agent synthesis, drug delivery, and gene therapy. 2-5 In these cases 
of therapeutic and diagnostic application, HANPs may become systemically avail-
able, which increases the risk of their exposure to the blood vessels. It has been 
proposed that atherosclerotic complications may occur with the continued use of 
HANPs. 3,6 Thus, in terms of human health, the main potential adverse effect of 
HANPs on the cardiovascular system needs to be carefully assessed before reach-
ing the clinical application stage. </p>

<p>Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of Nanomedicine 
11 March 2014 </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1262 </p>

<p>liu and sun </p>

<p>It is well known that synthetic nanoparticles (NPs) can 
enter the vascular system intentionally by injection in the 
form of nanomedicines or nanodiagnostics. 7 Accordingly, 
endothelial cells (ECs), which form the inner cellular lin-
ing of the entire cardiovascular system, have direct contact 
with these NPs. In addition to ECs, NPs may simultaneously 
encounter circulating immune cells upon introduction into 
the blood circulation. Monocytes/macrophages are the 
body's first line of defense and are recognized as important 
contributors to atherosclerosis via interactions with ECs. 
Thus, considering the fundamental role exerted by both ECs 
and monocytes in cardiovascular events, to understand the 
interaction of monocytes and ECs, both with each other 
and with NPs, it is very important to assess NP-induced 
cardiovascular effects. In recent years, several toxicology 
studies have demonstrated that diesel particulates can 
indirectly activate ECs via exposure to macrophages, with 
even more profound effects than those generated by direct 
exposure to ECs. 8-10 Our current studies also found that 
silica NPs could significantly augment proinflammatory 
and procoagulant responses in ECs through monocyte-EC 
interactions. 11 However, to the best of our knowledge, most 
studies are still focused on the direct biological response of 
engineered HANPs to monocultures of cells in the endothe-
lium or the immune system; 5,12-18 as such, the coculture of 
monocytes and ECs with HANPs has received little atten-
tion in this regard. 
In this study, to model an in vivo vascular microenvi-
ronment when HANPs enter into systemic circulation, we 
established an in vitro coculture model using THP-1 cells 
(monocytes) and human umbilical vein ECs (HUVECs). 
By utilizing this in vitro system, we investigated both the 
direct and the integrated/indirect effects of NPs on ECs in 
the presence or absence of THP-1 cells to evaluate the 
potential cardiovascular toxicity of HANPs. First, HANPs 
were synthesized, and their physiochemical characteristics 
were studied. Subsequently, HANP biocompatibility was 
assessed at the level of specific features, including cell viabil-
ity, cellular uptake, cytokine production, and cell adhesion 
molecule (CAM) expression in HUVECs and THP-1 cells in 
monoculture and in HUVECs/THP-1 cells cocultured with 
HANPs. Moreover, the proinflammatory effects of HANPs 
on ECs were compared following their exposure to direct 
contact with the coculture, and after exposure to monocyte-
derived soluble factors. Finally, to investigate the signaling 
pathway activated by HANPs in ECs cocultured with THP-1 
cells, we measured the stimulation of mitogen-activated 
protein kinases (MAPKs) and nuclear factor-kappa B (NF-
κB) in HUVECs. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Preparation and characterization 
of haNPs </p>

<p>HANPs were synthesized using a chemical precipitation 
method according to our previously published procedures. 19 
Briefly, the pH of a Ca(NO 3 ) 2 solution was adjusted to 
12 by adding a concentrated ammonia solution, and an 
(NH 4 ) 2 HPO 4 solution (pH =12) was added dropwise during 
vigorous stirring. A voluminous precipitate was formed. 
The reaction mixture was gently boiled for 10 minutes. The 
precipitate was allowed to settle, and it was subsequently 
separated from the supernatant by centrifugation. The HA 
precipitate was washed with distilled water, frozen at −20°C, 
and lyophilized. The size and shape of the HANPs were 
examined using transmission electron microscopy (TEM) 
(JEOL, Tokyo, Japan). The structure of HANPs was exam-
ined by X-ray diffraction (XRD) using a RINT2000 vertical 
goniometer (Rigaku Corporation, Tokyo, Japan). The powder 
was examined with Ni filtered CuKα radiation generated 
at 40 kV and 100 mA. The powders were scanned from 
10°-80° 2θ with a scan speed of 2° per minute. The peak of 
the obtained XRD pattern was compared with standard HA 
in the Joint Committee on Power Diffraction Standards file 
available in software (No 09-0432). Energy-dispersive X-ray 
spectroscopy can be used to find the chemical composition 
of materials. Thus, for the elemental analysis, a Hitachi 
S-2600N-type scanning electron microscope (Hitachi Ltd, 
Tokyo, Japan) was equipped with an energy dispersive 
X-ray attachment (EDAX Inc., Mahwah, NJ, USA) to create 
element composition spectra. The hydrodynamic size and 
surface charge (zeta potential) of the HANP dispersions 
were characterized using the Zetasizer Nano ZS (Malvern 
Instruments, Malvern, UK) utilizing dynamic light scattering 
and electrophoretic light scattering, respectively. The specific 
surface area of the HANPs was determined by the Brunauer-
Emmett-Teller method using a surface area analyzer (ASAP 
2020; Micromeritics Instrument Corporation, Norcross, GA, 
USA) after pre-preparation of samples by heating at 200°C 
in a stream of N 2 in excess of 24 hours. </p>

<p>endotoxin measurement </p>

<p>The endotoxin content in the HANP dispersions was tested 
using the Limulus amebocyte lysate kinetic chromogenic assay 
(Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, USA). The endotoxin content in 
the HANP dispersions used in the study was below 1 EU/mL. </p>

<p>cell preparation and culture </p>

<p>HUVECs were isolated from freshly obtained human umbili-
cal cord using our previously published method. 20 Briefly, the </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1263 </p>

<p>Proinflammatory effects of hydroxyapatite nanoparticles </p>

<p>umbilical vein was rinsed three times with phosphate buffered 
saline (PBS) containing 100 µg/mL of penicillin/ streptomycin 
(Gibco ® ; Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA), filled 
with 0.1% collagenase I (Sigma-Aldrich) and incubated for 
15 minutes at 37°C. After harvesting, the ECs were placed in 
75 cm 2 tissue culture flasks (Corning Incorporated, Corning, 
NY, USA) and grown in EC medium (ScienCell Research 
Labs, Carlsbad, CA, USA). HUVECs between the third and 
sixth passages were used in our experiments. The phenotype 
of the ECs was confirmed by performing immunofluorescence 
using monoclonal antibodies for the von Willebrand factor 
(vWF) (ShangHai ChangDao Biotech Co, Ltd, Shanghai, 
People's Republic of China). 
Human monocytes (THP-1 cells) were purchased from the 
Cell Bank of the Chinese Academy of Sciences (Shanghai, 
People's Republic of China) and were cultured in Roswell 
Park Memorial Institute (RPMI) 1640 medium (Gibco ® ; 
Life Technologies) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine 
serum (Biochrom AG, Berlin, Germany) and 100 µg/mL of 
penicillin/streptomycin. 
For the coculture of monocytes and HUVECs, THP-1 
cells (1 × 10 6 cells/mL) were added onto confluent HUVEC 
layers (5 × 10 5 cells/mL) in six-well plates. Contact cocultures 
were performed in the presence or absence of HANPs for 
24 hours. Meanwhile, to prevent direct cell contact between 
monocytes and HUVECs, at the end of the 24-hour incuba-
tion, the supernatants were collected, cleared of cells by 
centrifugation, and transferred to stimulate the HUVECs or 
monocytes for 24 hours and cultured in parallel. </p>

<p>Cell viability assays </p>

<p>Cell viability was measured by assessment of mitochondrial 
function using the CellTiter 96 ® AQueous One Solution 
assay (Promega Corporation, Madison, WI, USA). The 
solution reagent contains a tetrazolium compound (3-[4, 
5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl]-5-[3-carboxymethoxyphenyl]-2-
[4-sulfophenyl]-2H-tetrazolium, inner salt; MTS) and an 
electron coupling reagent (phenazine ethosulfate). After 
seeding the cells for 24 hours, differing concentrations of 
HANPs were added to the 96-well plates. The cultures were 
further incubated for 24 hours, and 20 µL of MTS agent was 
then directly added to each well. After a 4-hour incubation 
period, the absorbance of formazan was measured at 490 nm 
using a microplate reader (Wellscan MK3, Labsystems 
Dragon, Inc., Helsinki, Finland). </p>

<p>Particle uptake </p>

<p>To determine the cellular uptake and localization of the par-
ticles, HUVECs and THP-1 cells were individually exposed </p>

<p>to HANPs (100 µg/mL) for 24 hours and analyzed by TEM. 
After incubation for 24 hours with HANPs, the cells were 
washed with a PBS solution, trypsinized, and centrifuged. 
Next, the cell pellets were fixed in a 0.1 M PBS solution 
containing 2.5% glutaraldehyde for 4 hours. The cells were 
dehydrated through a series of ethanol washes (70% for 
15 minutes, 90% for 15 minutes, and 100% for 15 minutes, 
twice) and embedded in Epon-Araldite resin (polymerization 
at 65°C for 15 hours). Thin sections containing the cells were 
placed on the grids and stained for 1 minute each with 4% 
uranyl acetate (in acetone: water, 1:1) and 0.2% Reynolds' 
lead citrate (in water), air-dried, and imaged under TEM. </p>

<p>Cytokine measurement </p>

<p>For cytokine analysis (interleukin [IL]-6, IL-8, IL-1β, and 
tumor necrosis factor-alpha [TNF-α]), the supernatants of 
HUVECs or THP-1 cells in cocultures or monocultures 
exposed to HANPs (100 µg/mL) were collected after 
24 hours, immediately centrifuged to remove the cells, and 
then frozen at −80°C until the analysis was performed. The 
amounts of IL-6, IL-8, IL-1β, and TNF-α were quantified 
with an immunoassay kit (R&amp;D Systems, Inc., Minneapolis, 
MN, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence flow cytometry </p>

<p>The levels of surface markers expressed on HUVECs were 
assessed using flow cytometry. After 24 hours of coculture or 
monoculture in the absence or presence of HANPs (100 µg/mL), 
HUVECs were released from the wells after washing with PBS. 
The following mouse antihuman monoclonal antibodies were 
used: intercellular adhesion molecule (ICAM-1) (cluster of 
differentiation [CD]54-PE; eBioscience, Inc., San Diego, CA, 
USA); vascular CAM-1 (VCAM-1) (CD106 fluorescein iso-
thiocyanate isomer 1; BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA); 
E-selectin (CD62E-APC; BD Biosciences); and vWF (BD 
Biosciences). Subsequently, HUVECs were collected and 
labeled with the abovementioned specific antibodies at room 
temperature for 45 minutes in the dark, washed extensively, 
and then subsequently fixed with 1% paraformaldehyde. 
All samples were analyzed using a FACScan™ flow cytometer 
(BD, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA). The data were analyzed with 
CellQuest™ software (BD Biosciences). </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>Protein expression was determined using Western blot. Briefly, 
following the incubation periods, HUVECs were washed 
once with ice-cold PBS and lysed in ice-cold radioimmu-
noprecipitation assay buffer (Applygen Technologies Inc., 
Beijing, People's Republic of China) containing 1 mM of </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1264 </p>

<p>liu and sun </p>

<p>phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (Sigma-Aldrich) and a phos-
phatase inhibitor cocktail (Sigma-Aldrich) for 30 minutes. 
After centrifuging the lysates at 12,000 rpm at 4°C for 
10 minutes, the supernatants were collected and stored at 
−80°C for future use. The protein concentrations of these </p>

<p>extracts were determined by performing a bicinchoninic 
acid protein assay (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, 
USA). Equal amounts of protein samples (40 µg) were sepa-
rated using 10% sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gels 
(SDS-PAGE) and subsequently transferred onto nitrocellulose 
membranes (Amersham plc, Amersham, UK). Membranes 
were blocked with 5% nonfat milk buffer and incubated with 
anti-p-p38, anti-p-p-c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK), anti-JNK 
(1:1,000, rabbit polyclonal antibodies; Bioworld Technology, 
St Louis Park, MN, USA), anti-p-38 (1:1,000, rabbit poly-
clonal antibodies; Cell Signaling Technology, Inc., Danvers, 
MA, USA), and anti-β-actin (1:1,000, a mouse polyclonal 
antibody), (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc., Dallas, TX, 
USA) at 4°C overnight, washed with Tris-buffered saline and 
incubated with a horseradish peroxidase-conjugated antirabbit 
immunoglobulin (Ig)G/antimouse IgG secondary antibody at 
37°C for 1 hour. The antibody-bound proteins were detected 
using an enhanced chemiluminescence reagent (EMD Mil-
lipore, Billerica, MA, USA). Quantification of the Western 
blot and electrophoretic mobility shift assay (EMSA) data 
were performed by measuring the intensity of the band using 
the <rs id="software-1" type="software">ImageJ</rs> analysis program (Image J, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">NIH</rs>). </p>

<p>Electrophoretic mobility shift assay (EMSA) </p>

<p>EMSA was used to assess the NF-κB activation of HUVECs. 
Briefly, following the incubation periods, HUVEC nuclear 
extracts were prepared using Nuclear and Cytoplasmic 
Extraction Reagents (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The protein 
concentration of each nuclear extract was quantified using the 
bicinchoninic acid protein assay. Ten micrograms of nuclear 
protein was incubated in binding buffer containing 50 ng/µL of 
poly (dI ⋅ dC), 2.5% glycerol, 0.05% NP-40, 5 mM of MgCl 2 , 
and 20 fmol of Biotin end-labeled oligonucleotides at room 
temperature for 20 minutes. The labeled oligonucleotides had the 
following sequences: 5′-AGT TGA GGG GAC TTT CCC AGG 
C-3′ and 5′-GCC TGG GAA AGT CCC CTC AAC T-3′. Protein-
deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) complexes were separated from 
the free DNA probe via electrophoresis through 4% native poly-
acrylamide gels. Gels were dried, and protein-DNA complexes 
were then visualized using enhanced chemiluminescence. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The data are expressed as the means ± standard deviation 
or means ± standard error of the mean (SEM). Statistical </p>

<p>comparisons of the means were performed using one-way 
analysis of variance with <rs id="software-3" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">6.12</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>., Cary, NC, USA). The differences were considered to 
be significant when the P-value was ,0.05. </p>

<p>Results 
characterization and 
dispersion of haNPs </p>

<p>In this study, we investigated the main physicochemical 
properties of our synthetic HANPs. TEM analyses revealed 
that the HANPs were near spherical, or they exhibited 
slightly elongated shapes (an average of 15 nm in diam-
eter). The size and morphology of HANPs are illustrated in 
Figure 1A and B. The XRD pattern of the HANPs showed 
that the structure of the prepared sample was similar to that 
of the HA standard, as shown in Figure 1C. Our data of the 
HANPs are highly consistent with the standard HA database 
(powder diffraction file no 09-0432), indicating that the 
chief inorganic phase of our synthetic NPs is an HA crystal. 
Furthermore, our energy-dispersive X-ray spectroscopy data 
show that the Ca/P ratio in our samples is close to 1.67 which 
is similar to the theoretical value in HA, suggesting our 
synthetic HAP is of high purity (Figure 1D). Surface charge 
and hydrodynamic diameter are two important properties 
of NP dispersions in aqueous systems. For the remainder 
of the study, NPs were characterized in complete cell cul-
ture medium (1:1 mixture of EC medium and RPMI 1640 
medium). The hydrodynamic size of the NPs, as measured 
by dynamic light scattering, was approximately 248 nm, 
revealing that the NPs were well dispersed in the cell culture 
medium (Table 1). The zeta-potential of the NPs was deter-
mined and displayed a positive potential (−8.89 mV) in cell 
culture medium, indicating that the NPs presented a negative 
surface charge. Additionally, to examine the surface property 
of the HANPs, we estimated the Brunauer-Emmett-Teller-
specific surface area. As shown in Table 1, the specific sur-
face area of our prepared HANPs was 109 m 2 /g, which was 
significantly larger than the commercial HANPs measured 
by other researchers (7.4 m 2 /g), 15 indicating that the HANPs 
have a higher biological reactivity. 21-23 </p>

<p>effects of direct haNP exposure 
on HUVECs and THP-1 cell viability </p>

<p>To determine the effects of HANPs on HUVEC and THP-1 
cell viability in vitro, mitochondrial function was mea-
sured using the MTS assay after culturing with serial dilu-
tions (25 µg/mL, 50 µg/mL, 100 µg/mL, 200 µg/mL, and 
400 µg/mL) of HANPs for 24 hours. As depicted in Figure 2, 
both HUVEC and THP-1 cell viability decreased in relation </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1265 </p>

<p>Proinflammatory effects of hydroxyapatite nanoparticles </p>

<p>to increasing concentrations of HANPs. At concentrations 
of 100 µg/mL or below, no significant differences were 
observed in the cell viability between HANP-stimulated 
cells and untreated cells (P.0.05). After treatment with 
HANPs at 200 µg/mL and 400 µg/mL, HUVEC viability 
dramatically decreased to 65% and 59%, respectively. Simi-
larly, at 200 µg/mL and 400 µg/mL, HANPs also caused a </p>

<p>significant inhibition of mitochondrial function in THP-1 
cells (P,0.05). </p>

<p>cellular uptake and localization of haNPs </p>

<p>It is known that cellular uptake is not only a critical step 
in gene carrier or intracellular drug delivery, but it is also 
directly related to the biological impact of NPs. To follow </p>

<p>Table 1 characterization of the particle parameters of haNPs </p>

<p>Material 
Morphology 
Average diameter 
by TEM (nm) </p>

<p>Hydrodynamic 
size (nm) </p>

<p>Surface 
area (m 2 /g) </p>

<p>Zeta-potential 
(mV) </p>

<p>haNPs 
Near spherical 
15±5 
248±33 
109±0.34 
−8.89±0.04 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: HANPs, hydroxyapatite nanoparticles; TEM, transmission electron microscopy. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Characterization of hydroxyapatite nanoparticles. 
Notes: (A and B) Transmission electron microscopy image; inset: histogram showing size distribution; about 500 NPs were considered for the sample to obtain the size 
distribution histogram. (C) X-ray diffraction patterns. (D) Energy-dispersive X-ray spectroscopy spectra. 
Abbreviations: CPS, counts per second; KCnt, 1,000 counts; NPs, nanoparticles. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1266 </p>

<p>liu and sun </p>

<p>the internalization and intracellular localization of HANPs, 
HUVECs and THP-1 cells were exposed to the HANPs 
at a low toxic dose (100 µg/mL) and were then examined 
using TEM. As shown in Figure 3, most of the HANPs in 
HUVECs and THP-1 cells were confined to vesicles and 
lysosomes within the cytoplasm and did not enter the nucleus. 
Moreover, based on the imaging, HUVECs retained their 
cellular morphology without damage following the uptake 
of HANPs. In contrast, in HANP-stimulated THP-1 cells, 
several pseudopodia and large vacuoles appeared, indicating 
the activated state of the cell. </p>

<p>Cytokine production by HANPs 
in monoculture and cocultures </p>

<p>To obtain a more realistic assessment of the effects of HANPs 
on the human vascular system, this study simulated the human 
vasculature using a coculture model composed of ECs and 
monocytes. A proinflammatory response was first investigated 
after the cocultures were exposed to HANPs for 24 hours. 
Responses were compared with those of HUVECs or monocyte 
monocultures at the same condition. Four patterns of cytokine 
release (TNF-α, IL-1β, IL-6, and IL-8) were observed. As 
shown in Figure 4A and B, THP-1 cells exposed to HANPs 
exhibited significant increases in TNF-α (up to 15-fold) and 
IL-1β (up to twofold) in both monoculture and cocultures; 
however, cocultures with HUVECs had no appreciable effects 
on the levels of TNF-α and IL-1β compared with monocultures </p>

<p>stimulated with HANPs (P.0.05). Moreover, in HUVECs 
exposed to HANPs, no relevant increases were observed for 
any cytokine, whereas in the cocultures of HUVECs/THP-1 
cells with HANPs, a strong increase of IL-6 production was 
induced (Figure 4C and D). 
To clarify whether cell-derived soluble factors induced 
by HANPs are responsible for secondary proinflam-
matory cytokine release in cocultures, HUVECs and 
THP-1 cells were pretreated with HANPs for 24 hours, 
and the cell-free supernatant was collected to stimulate 
another cell type for 24 hours. As shown in Figure 4, the 
supernatants of HANP-stimulated THP-1 cells exhibited 
a significant increase in IL-6 release from HUVECs, 
whereas the supernatants of HANP-stimulated HUVECs 
revealed no effects on TNF-α and IL-1β release from 
the THP-1 cells, suggesting that HANPs might cause an 
indirect activated effect on HUVECs by monocyte-derived 
soluble factors. </p>

<p>endothelial adhesion molecule 
expression induced by HANPs 
in monoculture and cocultures </p>

<p>To further evaluate EC activation in HANP-stimulated cocul-
tures, endothelial adhesion molecule expression (CD106, 
CD54, and CD62E) was measured using flow cytometry. 
As shown in Figure 5, HANPs alone did not induce CD54, 
CD106, or CD62E expression; however, when cocultured 
with THP-1 cells, HANPs significantly increased the per-
centage of HUVECs that expressed CD54, CD106, and 
CDD62E. In addition, the supernatants of HANP-stimulated 
monocytes also increased the expression of CD54, CD106, 
and CD62E. To investigate whether HUVEC monolay-
ers in HANP-stimulated coculture would become more 
adherent for leukocytes, flow cytometry was performed to 
examine the vWF expression of HUVECs. As shown in 
Figure 5C, the vWF expression of separated HUVECs from 
the HANP-treated coculture was decreased to 91.9%±2.12%, 
slightly lower than the untreated HUVECs (99.2%±0.69%) 
(P,0.05), indicating that there might be some monocyte 
adhesion to HUVECs. </p>

<p>Involvement of p38, JNK, and NF-κB 
in the activation of hUVecs in haNP-
stimulated cocultures </p>

<p>To clarify the possible signaling pathway of the proin-
flammatory effects of HANPs on HUVECs in coculture, 
the activation levels of JNK, p38, and NF-κB were </p>

<p>&amp; 
&amp; </p>

<p># 
# </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>HUVECs 
THP-1 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>C o n t r o l 
2 5 µ g / m L 
5 0 µ g / m L 
1 0 0 µ g / m L 
2 0 0 µ g / m L 
4 0 0 µ g / m L </p>

<p>Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>Figure 2 Cytotoxicity of hydroxyapatite nanoparticles to HUVEC and THP-1 cells. 
Notes: cells were exposed to increasing doses of hydroxyapatite nanoparticles for 
24 hours, and cytotoxicity was determined by the MTS assay. Normal HUVECs or 
ThP-1 cells without nanoparticle treatment served as control. results are presented 
in mean ± standard error of the mean of the three independent experiments; each 
was carried out in triplicate. # P,0.05; **P,0.01 versus control; &amp; P,0.05 significant 
difference between the compared groups. 
Abbreviations: HUVECs, human umbilical vein endothelial cells; MTS, 3-(4, 
5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-5-(3-carboxymethoxyphenyl)-2-(4-sulfophenyl)-2H-
tetrazolium. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1267 </p>

<p>Proinflammatory effects of hydroxyapatite nanoparticles </p>

<p>detected in HANP-stimulated cocultures. As depicted in 
Figure 6A, the cocultures had significantly elevated JNK 
and p38 MAPK phosphorylation levels after treatment 
with HANPs when compared with ECs cultured alone. 
Similarly, NF-κB was significantly activated in HANP-
stimulated HUVEC cocultures compared with HUVECs 
in monoculture (Figure 6B). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Recently, more efforts have been focused on the possibility of 
utilizing synthetic HANPs for multiple applications, such as 
magnetic resonance imaging, antimicrobial treatments, drug 
delivery, and gene transfection; however, their biocompat-
ibility and toxicity remain unclear. 3,6 A major limitation of 
in vitro cell models in investigations of NP-induced biological </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>E 
F </p>

<p>G 
H 
N </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>Figure 3 Uptake of HANPs by HUVEC and THP-1 cells. 
Notes: TEM micrographs of cells exposed for 24 hours to HANPs. (A and B) HUVECs without any treatment; (C and D) HUVECs treated with HANPs; (E and F) THP-1 
cells without any treatment; (G and H) THP-1 cells treated with HANPs. (A, C, E and G) Overall cell morphology (scale bar: 2 µm). (B, D, F and H) Higher magnification 
of cells in red boxed areas (scale bar: 1 µm). White arrows denote nanoparticles. Red arrows indicate the protrusion of the plasma membrane for phagocytosis. 
Abbreviations: N, nucleus; HANPs, hydroxyapatite nanoparticles; HUVECs, human umbilical vein endothelial cells; TEM, transmission electron microscopy. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1268 </p>

<p>liu and sun </p>

<p>effects is that common monoculture systems do not represent 
a realistic model of how NPs will interact with a specific 
organ of the body due to the lack of cellular interactions 
and extracellular signal communications that are important 
in an in vivo situation. 24 The present study using coculture 
models of ECs and monocytes with HANPs to mimic the 
complex physiological functionality of the vascular system 
demonstrate that monocytes could play an important role 
in the mechanisms of endothelium dysfunction induced by 
HANP exposure. According to our findings, at a subcytotoxic 
dose, direct HANP exposure did not cause EC injury, but 
when cocultured with THP-1 cells, we observed a significant 
inflammatory activation of HUVECs. This process is possibly 
dependent on the action of monocyte-derived soluble factors 
via p38/JNK MAPK and NF-κB activation. Thus, in the 
present study, we observed a series of cellular and molecular 
interactions initiated by HANPs between monocytes and ECs 
that resulted in an inflammatory cascade through a complex 
network of pathways. </p>

<p>In this study, HUVECs and THP-1 cells were used to 
evaluate the cytotoxic effect of HANPs by the MTS assay. 
ECs and monocytes were selected because NPs intravenously 
administered into the systemic circulation are the most 
common route of exposure to nanomedicine. At concentra-
tions of 200 µg/mL and greater, HANPs became cytotoxic 
in both cell types (Figure 2). Exposure to a subcytotoxic 
dose can help identify potential health effects of NPs other 
than those due to cytotoxicity; 25 thus, we chose to work 
with a lower particle concentration in the following stud-
ies (100 µg/mL). Under these conditions, neither cell type 
exhibited dramatic cell death after a 24-hour treatment with 
NPs. Given that it has been demonstrated that the cellular 
uptake of NPs plays a pivotal role in the alteration of various 
cellular functions, such as cell viability and the inflammatory 
response, 26 the internalization and intracellular localization 
of HANPs were subsequently examined by TEM. In this 
assay, different cellular uptake behaviors were observed 
in HUVECs and THP-1 cells after treatment with HANPs </p>

<p>** ** 
** 
* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>&amp; </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1,200 </p>

<p>1,000 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>H A N P s + E C </p>

<p>E C </p>

<p>E C + T H P -1 
H A N P s + T H P -1 </p>

<p>T H P -1 </p>

<p>T H P -1 </p>

<p>H A N P s + T H P -1 
E C + T H P -1 
H A N P s + E C </p>

<p>H A N P s + T H P -1 + E C 
(H 
A N P s + T H P -1 )s + E C </p>

<p>E C 
T H P -1 </p>

<p>H A N P s + T H P -1 
E C + T H P -1 
H A N P s + E C </p>

<p>H A N P s + T H P -1 + E C 
(H 
A N P s + T H P -1 )s + E C </p>

<p>E C </p>

<p>H A N P s + T H P -1 + E C 
(H 
A N P s + E C )s + T H P -1 </p>

<p>H A N P s + E C </p>

<p>E C </p>

<p>E C + T H P -1 
H A N P s + T H P -1 </p>

<p>T H P -1 </p>

<p>H A N P s + T H P -1 + E C 
(H 
A N P s + E C )s + T H P -1 </p>

<p>TNF-α release (pg/mL) 
IL-1β release (pg/mL) </p>

<p>IL-6 release (pg/mL) 
IL-8 release (pg/mL) </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>Figure 4 Proinflammatory cytokine production induced by HANPs in mono-and cocultures. 
Notes: (A) TNF-α release; (B) IL-1β release; (C) IL-6 release; (D) IL-8 release. Normal HUVECs or THP-1 cells or cocultures without NPs treatment served as control. 
results are presented as the mean ± standard error of the mean of three independent experiments, each of which was carried out in triplicate. *P,0.05; **P,0.01 versus 
control; &amp; P,0.05 significant difference between compared groups. 
Abbreviations: TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-alpha; EC, endothelial cells; HANPs, hydroxyapatite nanoparticles; (HANPs+THP-1)s+ec, human umbilical vein endothelial 
cells treated with supernatants of hydroxyapatite nanoparticle-stimulated THP-1 cells; (HANPs+ECs)+THP-1, THP-1 cells treated with the supernatants of hydroxyapatite 
nanoparticle-stimulated human umbilical vein endothelial cells; IL, interleukin; NPs, nanoparticles. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1269 </p>

<p>Proinflammatory effects of hydroxyapatite nanoparticles </p>

<p>for 24 hours (Figure 3). In both cell lines, the HANPs were 
tightly packed and largely confined to spherical vesicles 
resembling lysosomes within the cytoplasm. Importantly, 
after HANP uptake, HUVECs did not display a change of 
morphology (Figure 3C-D). In contrast, a prominent change </p>

<p>in THP-1 cells was observed, which included increased 
phagocytic activity, as demonstrated by large vacuoles and 
multiple pseudopodia of the plasma membrane, suggesting 
the potential immune activation of these particular cells 
(Figure 3G-H). </p>

<p>110 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>CD106 </p>

<p>CD54 </p>

<p>CD62E </p>

<p>E C </p>

<p>T H P -1 + E C 
H A N P s + E C </p>

<p>H A N P s + T H P -1 + E C 
( H A N P s + T H P -1 ) s + E C </p>

<p>CAMs expression 
(positive cells %) </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>CD54-PE </p>

<p>CD62E-APC </p>

<p>CD106-FITC </p>

<p>CD106-FITC </p>

<p>EC 
THP-1+EC </p>

<p>THP-1+EC </p>

<p>HANPs+EC </p>

<p>HANPs+EC </p>

<p>HANPs+THP-1+EC </p>

<p>HANPs+THP-1+EC </p>

<p>(HANPs+THP-1)s+EC </p>

<p>(HANPs+THP-1)s+EC </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>* * </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>** 
^ ^ </p>

<p>^ </p>

<p>Counts 
Counts 
Counts </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 50 
10 0 
10 4 </p>

<p>91.2%±0.68% 
91.4%±0.43% </p>

<p>10 0 
10 4 
10 0 
10 4 </p>

<p>vWF-FITC </p>

<p>THP-1+EC 
H ANPs+THP-1+EC 
EC </p>

<p>M 
M 2 
M 
M 2 </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>M 2 </p>

<p>91.9%±2.12% </p>

<p>Figure 5 CAMs expression induced by HANPs in HUVECs in mono-and cocultures. 
Notes: (A) Dot-plot of flow cytometry analysis showing the expressions of CD54, CD106, and CD62E on HUVECs in mono-and cocultures exposed to HANPs for 
24 hours. (B) Bar graph shows the percentage of CD54-, CD106-, and CD62E-positive cells in NP-stimulated HUVECs in monoculture or in coculture. (C) The vWF 
expression on hUVecs in haNP-stimulated cocultures. Normal hUVecs served as the negative control. Data represent the means ± standard error of the means; n=3. 
*P,0.05; **P,0.01 versus control; ^ P,0.05 versus hUVecs with haNPs. 
Abbreviations: CD, cluster of differentiation; EC, endothelial cells; FITC, fluorescein isothiocyanate isomer 1; HANPs, hydroxyapatite nanoparticles; vWF, von Willebrand 
factor; CAMs, cell adhesion molecules; HUVECs, human umbilical vein endothelial cells; NP, nanoparticle; n, number. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1270 </p>

<p>liu and sun </p>

<p>Cytokines are important regulators of immune, 
inflammatory, and vascular reactions, and they play critical 
roles in cardiovascular disease. 27 Among these cytokines, 
TNF-α and IL-1β are generally markers of monocyte 
activation. Moreover, IL-6 is clinically considered a bio-
marker of endothelial dysfunction and an independent risk 
factor for atherosclerosis. 28,29 As a next step, to further inves-
tigate the impact of NP uptake on the cell activation status, 
we measured the concentrations of TNF-α, IL-1β, IL-6, and 
IL-8 present in HUVECs and THP-1 cell supernatants after 
direct exposure to HANPs. These experiments demonstrated 
that increased levels of TNF-α and IL-1β were released in </p>

<p>THP-1 cells after treatment with HANPs (Figure 4A and B), 
whereas no proinflammatory cytokines were released in 
HUVECs alone (Figure 4C and D). 
Since the interaction of the monocytes and ECs that line 
the blood vessels is a critical process in vascular homeostasis 
and in pathological conditions of inflammation or thrombo-
sis, the monocyte-EC coculture model is frequently used to 
assess the biocompatibility of synthetic materials, such as 
vascular grafts, artificial hearts, and coronary-artery stents 
for vascular application. 30-34 Recently, some researchers have 
attempted to use an in vitro coculture model of immune 
cells and ECs to evaluate the inflammatory potential of </p>

<p>p-p38 </p>

<p>p38 </p>

<p>p-JNK </p>

<p>JNK </p>

<p>β-actin </p>

<p>NF-kB </p>

<p>Free probe </p>

<p>H A N P s + E C 
E C 
T H P -1 + E C 
H A N P s + T H P -1 + E C 
H A N P s + E C 
E C 
T H P -1 + E C H A N P s + T H P -1 + E C </p>

<p>EC 
HANPs+EC 
THP-1+EC 
HANPs+THP-1+EC </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.8 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 
p-p38 
p38 
p-JNK 
JNK </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>H A N P s + E C </p>

<p>E C </p>

<p>T H P -1 + E C </p>

<p>H A N P s + T H P -1 + E C </p>

<p>Relative band intensities 
Total density </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>Figure 6 The activation of JNK, p38, and NF-κB by HANPs in HUVECs in mono-and cocultures. 
Notes: (A) The activation of JNK and p38 by HANPs in HUVECs in mono-and cocultures. Aliquots of cell lysates were separated by SDS-PAGE and analyzed for protein 
expression by Western blotting, as described in section 2. β-actin was used as an internal control to monitor for equal loading. (B) The activation of NF-κB by HANPs 
in HUVECs in mono-and cocultures. (C) The relative density of the bands normalized to beta-actin by gray value analysis (β-actin as control); (D) The total density of 
the NF-κB band by gray value analysis. NF-κB DNA-binding activity was assayed by electrophoretic mobility shift assay as described in the Materials and methods section. 
**Represents a statistically significant difference from EC (P,0.01). 
Abbreviations: JNK, c-Jun N-terminal kinase; EC, endothelial cells; HANPs, hydroxyapatite nanoparticles; NF-κB, nuclear factor-kappa B; HUVECs, human umbilical vein 
endothelial cells; SDS-Page, sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1271 </p>

<p>Proinflammatory effects of hydroxyapatite nanoparticles </p>

<p>nanomaterials, and they found that exposure to these NPs (for 
example, titanium dioxide [TiO 2 ] or silicone dioxide [SiO 2 ]) in 
direct-contact cocultures led to dramatically elevated levels of 
proinflammatory cytokines. 10,35 Here, we found that the cocul-
ture of HUVEC/THP-1 cells resulted in an approximately 
twofold increase in IL-6 concentrations compared with the 
individual cell types alone (Figure 4C). Separating the two 
cell types and treating HUVECs with conditioned media 
from HANP-exposed THP-1 cells also significantly increased 
the release of IL-6, indicating that the induction of IL-6 in 
HUVECs may be largely dependent on the HANP-activated 
monocytes (Figure 4C). Previous studies have reported that 
noncontact cocultures of ECs and macrophages/monocytes 
strongly induced more potent inflammatory cytokine release 
in ECs upon silica particle exposure compared with mon-
ocultures alone. 36,37 However, coculture or treatment with 
the supernatants from HANP-stimulated HUVECs did not 
increase the levels of TNF-α and IL-1β in THP-1 cells when 
compared with the THP-1 cells directly exposed to HANPs, 
indicating that the HANP-stimulated ECs were relatively 
ineffective on monocyte activation (Figure 4A and B). 
When undergoing activation, apart from IL-6, ECs also 
express various CAMs, such as ICAM-1 (CD54), VCAM-1 
(CD106), and E-selectins (CD62E). Generally, ICAM-1 is 
constitutively present in ECs, and its expression is increased 
by proinflammatory stimuli. 38 VCAM-1 and E-selectin are not 
routinely expressed under physiologic conditions, but they 
can be induced in activated endothelium. The expression of 
VCAM-1 and E-selectin is important in the initial steps of 
monocyte recruitment to atherosclerotic lesions and in the 
rolling of monocytes on the endothelial surface, whereas 
ICAM-1 is involved in the firm adhesion step in leukocyte 
infiltration. 39,40 CAM expression and established markers of 
endothelial dysfunction have been clinically considered to 
be associated with cardiovascular risk factors, and they may 
predict the development of cardiovascular disease. 41 Thus, to 
further verify the contribution of monocytes in EC activation 
induced by HANP exposure, CAM expression in HUVECs 
was measured using flow cytometry. Consistent with proin-
flammatory cytokine results after exposure to HANPs, cocul-
tures of ECs and monocytes had significantly greater increased 
levels of VCAM-1, E-selectin and ICAM-1 expression com-
pared with HUVECs cultured alone. vWF is considered to 
be a classic marker of ECs, because it has been found only in 
ECs, megakaryocytes, and platelets. 42 Thus, we assessed the 
THP-1 cells' adhesion to HUVECs by cell-specific surface 
markers (vWF). Our data showed that the vWF expression 
of separated HUVECs from the HANP-treated coculture was 
slightly lower than that of the HUVECs from the untreated </p>

<p>coculture (P,0.05), indicating that HANPs may elicit an 
attachment of monocytes to HUVECs. Additionally, HUVECs 
incubated with supernatants of HANP-stimulated monocytes 
expressed levels of VCAM-1, E-selectin, and ICAM-1 that 
were similar to those generated by the direct-contact coculture 
system, suggesting that monocyte-derived soluble factors 
were responsible for the activation of ECs (Figure 5). Among 
the soluble mediators possibly involved, TNF-α and IL-1β, 
which are primarily produced by monocytes and are well-
known inducers of EC activation,were good candidates. 43 
Taken together, these results suggest that direct exposure 
to HANPs could result in TNF-α and IL-1β production in 
THP-1 cells and that both cytokines, once released, might 
stimulate IL-6 generation and CAM expression by HUVECs. 
These results were consistent with those from previous stud-
ies that demonstrated that the release of TNF-α and IL-1β 
from particle-activated monocytes/macrophages might be the 
critical determinants for increased synthesis of IL-6 or CAM 
expression in ECs. 7,9,36 
It is a widely accepted view that intracellular MAPK 
signaling cascades probably play an important role in the 
pathogenesis of cardiovascular disease. 39 To clarify the possible 
signaling pathway of the proinflammatory effects of HANPs 
on HUVECs in coculture, we detected the activation levels 
of JNK, p38, and NF-κB. p38 and JNK belong to the MAPK 
superfamily and are stress-activated serine/threonine protein 
kinases with major functions in apoptosis, cytokine produc-
tion, transcriptional regulation, and inflammation. 44 Various 
inflammatory cytokines are capable of activating p38 and JNK 
MAPK, which has been shown to regulate inflammation and 
induce endothelial dysfunction. 45,46 In addition, NF-κB is also 
a critical transcription factor involved in the transcription of 
proinflammatory cytokines and the expression of CAMs, such 
as E-selectin, VCAM-1, and ICAM-1. 47,48 Our results clearly 
demonstrated that HANPs alone could not induce JNK, p38, 
or NF-κB activation in HUVECs; however, HANP-stimulated 
cocultures significantly elevated the phosphorylation levels of 
p38/JNK MAPK and the activity of NF-κB, suggesting that 
the activation of JNK, p38, and NF-κB in ECs by exposure to 
HANPs required the involvement of monocytes. It has been 
demonstrated that IL-1β mainly induces proinflammatory 
cytokine release, such as IL-6 gene expression in HUVECs, 
which is a p38/JNK-dependent process. 49 However, TNF-α 
more profoundly affected the expression of CAMs via the 
NF-κB pathway. 49 TNF-α and IL-1β release by HANP-stim-
ulated monocytes may induce p38/JNK MAPK and NF-κB 
activation in HUVECs, suggesting that HANPs can indirectly 
induce ECs' inflammatory response by activating monocytes. 
However, in this study, although we have found that HANPs </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1272 </p>

<p>liu and sun </p>

<p>could directly induce TNF-α and IL-1β release from mono-
cytes, and that these cytokines released by HANP-stimulated 
monocytes play a critical role in monocyte-mediated inflamma-
tory activation in HUVECs, we cannot rule out other potential 
proinflammatory mechanisms of HANP-activated monocytes 
against HUVECs. The detailed mechanism of this phenomenon 
needs to be further investigated. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In summary, our data provide evidence that HANPs could 
be taken up by both monocytes and ECs, and that HANP 
phagocytosis caused an inflammatory response in mono-
cytes, but not in ECs. In addition, although HANPs had no 
direct effect on endothelial inflammation, we determined 
that HANPs induced an indirect activation of ECs, result-
ing in increased IL-6 production and elevated adhesion 
molecule expression after coculture with monocytes. The 
potential proinflammatory effect of HANPs is primarily 
mediated by the release of soluble factors from activated 
monocytes, which leads to an inflammatory response 
of the endothelium that is possibly dependent on p38/ 
JNK MAPK and NF-κB signaling activation. Thus, the 
use of the in vitro monocyte-EC coculture model on the 
biocompatibility assessment of HANPs could reveal their 
potential proinflammatory effects on ECs, suggesting that 
exposure to HANPs could increase the risk of cardiovas-
cular disease. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by grants from the National Natural 
Science Foundation of China (no 81271700, no 81201191, 
no 31070843), and the Shanghai Sci-Tech Committee 
Foundation (13DZ2291100). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



</text></tei>