<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3865386" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives: There has not previously been a systematic </p>

<p>comparison of awards for research funding in infectious 
diseases by sex. We investigated funding awards to UK 
institutions for all infectious disease research from 1997 
to 2010, across disease categories and along the 
research and development continuum. </p>

<p>Design: Systematic comparison. 
Methods: Data were obtained from several sources for </p>

<p>awards from the period 1997 to 2010 and each study 
assigned to-disease categories; type of science 
(preclinical, phases I-III trials, product development, 
implementation research); categories of funding 
organisation. Fold differences and statistical analysis were 
used to compare total investment, study numbers, mean 
grant and median grant between men and women. </p>

<p>Results: 6052 studies were included in the final </p>

<p>analysis, comprising 4357 grants (72%) awarded to men 
and 1695 grants (28%) awarded to women, totalling 
£2.274 billion. Of this, men received £1.786 billion 
(78.5%) and women £488 million (21.5%). The median 
value of award was greater for men (£179 389; IQR 
£59 146-£371 977) than women (£125 556; IQR 
£30 982-£261 834). Awards were greater for male 
principal investigators (PIs) across all infectious disease 
systems, excepting neurological infections and sexually 
transmitted infections. The proportion of total funding 
awarded to women ranged from 14.3% in 1998 to 26.8% 
in 2009 (mean 21.4%), and was lowest for preclinical 
research at 18.2% (£285.5 million of £1.573 billion) and 
highest for operational research at 30.9% (£151.4 million 
of £489.7 million). </p>

<p>Conclusions: There are consistent differences in </p>

<p>funding received by men and women PIs: women have 
fewer funded studies and receive less funding in absolute 
and in relative terms; the median funding awarded to 
women is lower across most infectious disease areas, by 
funder, and type of science. These differences remain 
broadly unchanged over the 14-year study period. </p>

<p>explored the extent and reasons for the 
observed differences between men and 
women scientists. Women comprise 50% of 
the European Union (EU) student popula-
tion and 45% of doctoral students, but only 
one-third of career researchers are women-
a figure that is lower for senior positions. 1 
In 2001, a Wellcome Trust survey concluded 
that although women were as successful as 
men in securing funding for biomedical 
research, they were less likely to apply for grant 
funds because of their status in scientific insti-
tutions and the level of support they received. 2 
An analysis of Wellcome Trust awards in 2000-
2008 revealed a significant gender difference 
in the amount of funding awarded, even after 
adjusting for the seniority of the principal 
investigator (PI), concluding "the most likely 
explanation for the difference in amounts 
awarded to women and men is that women are </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ This is the first study to present detailed data 
and rigorously quantify funding differences 
between men and women researchers in infec-
tious disease research in the UK. 
▪ Our results provides new and additional evidence 
on differences on funding for men and women 
researchers highlighted in earlier studies and 
provides a case for new research to explain 
the source of these differences, especially given 
the government commitments to increase the 
number of women in science. 
▪ We were unable to assess the success and 
failure rates by gender and thus cannot 
comment on the extent of inequalities or bias. 
As we could not feasibly access data on the aca-
demic ranking of principal investigators, we were 
hence unable to adjust for levels of seniority 
across both genders. A follow-up study incorpor-
ating these data would allow for more meaning-
ful conclusions to be drawn about the nature of 
any possible disparities. </p>

<p>Head MG, Fitchett JR, Cooke MK, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003362. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003362 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>systematically less ambitious in the amounts of funding 
requested in their grant applications." 3 In 2011, around 
44% of academics in UK universities were women, yet only 
39% of senior lecturers and 19% of professors were 
women. 4 Furthermore, a number of studies from the USA 
have shown that women in science are disadvantaged com-
pared to men. 5-7 
The low numbers of women in science and the 
reasons for this anomaly are a matter of concern for 
scientists and policy-makers. Although the UK Medical 
Research Council (MRC) has a gender equality scheme, 
which briefly states that gender equality is reflected 
in agreements with research organisations receiving 
MRC funding, it is not clear how the scheme is 
implemented. 8 
While several initiatives have aimed to increase the 
numbers of women involved in science, there are no 
affirmative actions or binding policies in the UK or 
Europe to definitively ensure that women are better 
represented in science. Indeed, some initiatives aimed at 
increasing women in science have been criticised. For 
example, in 2012, the European Commission campaign 
targeting 13-year-old to 18-year-old secondary school stu-
dents 9 was rebuked and described as an insult to women 
in science, 10 11 with the offending video clip removed 
from the EU campaign website. The effects of cam-
paigns aimed at raising the profile of women in 
science 12 13 have not been assessed. 
We have previously undertaken a systematic analysis of 
research funding awarded to UK institutions for all infec-
tious disease research for the 14-year period from 1997 to 
2010. 14 Here, we use the dataset gathered for this earlier 
study to examine trends over time, the distribution of 
funding awarded to men and women PIs across specific 
infections, funder categories and along the research and 
development (R&amp;D) continuum, extending from preclin-
ical to clinical and operational research. </p>

<p>METHODS 
We obtained data from several sources for infectious 
disease research studies where funding was awarded 
between 1997 and 2010. The methods for the original 
study are elaborated in detail elsewhere 14 and sum-
marised here. We identified 325 922 studies for screen-
ing that covered all areas of disease from several 
funders, and filtered these to identify funding for infec-
tious diseases where the lead institution was in the UK 
in the period and the year of award 1997-2010. We 
obtained data from publicly available sources and dir-
ectly from the funders. We did not include private sector 
funding in the analysis, as pharmaceutical sector data 
were not publicly available. Figure 1 shows the sources of 
data and the numbers of studies included and excluded 
at each stage of screening to reach the final set of 
studies for detailed analysis. 
Data collection and cleaning took place alongside 
routine duties between 2006 and 2011, primarily by </p>

<p>MGH and assisted by JRF, MKC and FBW. Funding 
records could feasibly be obtained going back to 1997, 
hence the decision to cover awards during 1997-2010. 
We assigned each study to primary disease categories, 
and within each category we documented topic-specific 
subsections, including specific pathogen or disease. We 
allocated studies to one of four categories along the 
R&amp;D continuum: preclinical; phases I, II or III; product 
development; and operational research, and to 1 of the 
26 categories for funding organisations. 
Where the PI was named, we assigned them to men or 
women categories. The studies where only an initial was 
available for the forename were assigned as 'unclear' if 
we were unable to establish the PI's gender from a 
review of the literature, institutional websites or publicly 
available publications and documents. 
Reference to sexually transmitted infections excludes 
HIV. Neglected tropical diseases were categorised accord-
ing to the classification used by the WHO (http://www. 
who.int/neglected_diseases/diseases/en). Antimicrobial 
resistance includes antibacterial, antiviral, antifungal and 
antiparasitic studies. 
We converted grants awarded in a currency other than 
pounds sterling to UK pounds using the mean exchange 
rate in the year of the award. We adjusted grant funding 
amounts for inflation and reported in 2010 UK pounds. 
As well as excluding studies not immediately relevant 
to infection, we excluded unfunded studies, veterinary 
infectious disease research studies (unless there was a 
zoonotic component), those exploring the use of viral 
vectors to investigate non-communicable diseases, grants 
for symposia or meetings or studies with UK contribu-
tions (eg, as a collaborator), but the funding was 
awarded to a non-UK institution. 
We used <rs id="software-1" type="software">Microsoft Excel</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">versions 2000</rs> and 2007 to 
categorise studies. Where needed, data were exported 
into <rs type="software">Microsoft Access</rs> (versions 2000 and 2007) and spe-
cific keyword queries used to select precise sections of 
the data for analysis. We used <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.11.0</rs>) for statistical 
analysis and to generate figures. 
We used fold differences to compare total investment, 
number of studies, mean grant and median grant 
between men and women according to disease system, 
specific infection and funding organisation. 
We used the non-parametric Mann-Whitney rank-sum 
test to assess the distribution of funding by gender. 
The non-parametric K-sample test on equality of 
medians was applied to compare the median funding 
by gender, and reported as a χ 2 statistic without 
Yates' correction for continuity. The non-parametric 
Wilcoxon signed-rank test was applied when comparing 
matched data, such as time trends by gender. The sig-
nificance for all tests was defined at the 5% level (two-
sided p=0.05). 
We present differences between gender and do 
not attempt to investigate or imply bias or inequalities as 
we could not access data on unsuccessful grant 
applications. </p>



<p>Head MG, Fitchett JR, Cooke MK, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003362. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003362 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>RESULTS 
We identified 6165 studies from the 325 922 studies 
screened that were suitable for inclusion in our analysis. 
Of these, we were unable to ascertain the gender of the 
PI for 30 studies (0.5%). We excluded 83 studies (1.3%) 
that did not specify the PI's name or gender-these 
were funded by the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation 
(Gates Foundation; 38 studies; 0.6%) and the UK 
Department for International Development (DFID; 22 </p>

<p>studies; 0.4%), accounting for £321.2 million (12.3% of 
the total). We included 6052 studies in the final analysis, 
comprising 4357 grants (72%) awarded to men and 
1695 grants (28%) awarded to women, totalling £2.274 
billion, of which £1.786 billion (78.5%) were awarded to 
men and £488 million (21.5%) to women. 
The median value of grant funding was greater for 
men (£179 389; IQR £59 146-£371 977) than for women 
(£125 556; IQR £30 982-£261 834). Similarly, the mean </p>

<p>Figure 1 Methodology flow chart for filtering studies first by infectious disease and then by gender. BBSRC, Biotechnology and 
Biological Sciences Research Council; ESRC, Economic and Social Research Council; PI, principal investigator; R&amp;D, research 
and development. </p>

<p>Head MG, Fitchett JR, Cooke MK, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003362. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003362 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>value of the grant funding was greater for men 
(£409 910; SD £840 087) than for women (£288 011; SD 
£704 474). Figure 2 shows the distribution of the total 
investments and median funding awarded to PIs by 
gender over time. </p>

<p>Infectious disease system 
Table 1A (see web appendix 1) shows the total invest-
ment, total numbers of studies, mean grant funding, 
median grant funding and fold differences in funding 
according to nine disease systems and by gender of PI. 
We identified no infectious disease system where women 
led the majority of research efforts or were awarded the 
majority of funding. Median funding awards were 
greater for male PIs across all infectious disease systems, </p>

<p>with the exception of neurological infections and sexu-
ally transmitted infections. 
The greatest levels of funding awarded to men and to 
women were for research into respiratory infections and 
HIV. Men received a total of £312.1 million for research 
into respiratory infections compared with £84.4 million 
for women-a 3.70-fold difference-and a total of 
£290.8 million for HIV research compared with £79.7 
million for women-a 3.65-fold difference. 
The largest difference between total funding for men 
and for women was with gastrointestinal infections 
(5.65-fold difference) where women received only 15% 
of the total investment (£37 million) and spearheaded 
18.9% (149) of the studies and neurological infections 
(4.22-fold difference). The smallest difference between </p>

<p>Figure 2 (A) Total investment 
over time awarded to male and 
female principal investigators. (B) 
Median investment over time 
awarded to male and female 
principal investigators. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Head MG, Fitchett JR, Cooke MK, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003362. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003362 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>total funding for men and for women was in research 
into sexually transmitted infections (1.90-fold differ-
ence), where women received 35% (£45.4 million) of 
the total funding and led 49% (182) of the studies. 
The mean funding for grants was significantly greater 
for men (£409 910, SD £840 087) than for women 
(£288 011, SD £704 474). The differences in median 
funding were statistically significant ( p&gt;0.01) for gastro-
intestinal infections (men £328 021; SD £458 720) 
(women £248 615, SD £433 176), for haematological 
infections (men £417 889; SD £914 626) (women 
£306 126; SD £819 910) and for HIV (men £649 216; SD 
£1 550 920) (women £278 505; SD £545 657). 
The median funding for grants showed a similar pattern, 
with a significantly greater grant funding for men 
(£179 389; IQR £59 146-£371 977) than women (£125 556; 
IQR £30 983-£261 835). Differences in median funding 
were statistically significant (p&gt;0.05) for gastrointestinal 
infections (men £208 369; IQR £78 852-357 771) (women 
£155 066; IQR £43 637-£305 928), for hepatic infections 
(men £118 638; IQR £41 342-£269 629) (women £68 620; 
IQR £26 720-£221 952) and for HIV (men £163 462; IQR 
£39 153-£511 800) (women £114 272; IQR £29 880-
£305 339). </p>

<p>Specific infections 
Table 1B (see web appendix 1) shows total investment, 
total numbers of studies, mean grant funding, median 
grant funding and fold differences in funding according 
to specific infection by gender. 
Men received significantly higher levels of total 
research funding, spearheaded greater numbers of 
studies and were awarded greater median and mean 
funding for grants for malaria ( p=0.01), HIV ( p=0.01) 
and influenza ( p=0.04). 
Major differences between total funding for men and 
for women were observed for research into candida 
(47.75-fold difference), rotavirus (33.65-fold difference), 
Campylobacter (24.33-fold difference) and norovirus 
(23.33-fold difference). Smallest differences between 
total funding for men and women were observed for 
research into dengue (1.07-fold difference) and leish-
maniasis (1.55-fold difference). Women received greater 
total funding than men for research into leprosy 
(0.09-fold difference), diphtheria (0.18-fold difference), 
chlamydia (0.36-fold difference), syphilis (0.37-fold dif-
ference) and varicella zoster (0.54-fold difference). 
Differences in mean grant funding were statistically sig-
nificant (p&gt;0.05) for malaria research (men £590 422; SD 
£1 324 909) (women £318 054; SD £726 872), for influ-
enza (men £616 643; SD £881 493) (women £387 186; SD 
£489 997), for respiratory syncytial virus (men £485 283; 
SD £539 396) (women £187 931; SD £268 412) and for 
HIV (men £649 216; SD £1 550 920) (women £278 505; 
SD £545 657). 
Differences in median grant funding were statistically 
significant ( p&gt;0.05) for malaria research (men 
£209 646; IQR £63 826-£529 610) (women £143 358; </p>

<p>IQR £42 754-£314 524), for hepatitis C (men £124 797; 
IQR £42 475-£289 293) (women £67 265; IQR £29 880-
£233 467), for influenza (men £348 730; IQR £213 601-
£668 561) (women £200 787; IQR £124 210-£398 191), 
for herpes simplex virus (men £119 295; IQR £40 009-
£446 395) (women £309 610; IQR £147 885-£439 305) 
and for HIV (men £163 462; IQR £39 153-£511 800) 
(women £114 272; IQR £29 880-£305 339). 
Figure 3 shows the proportion of total funding awarded 
to PIs by gender over time and a breakdown of investment 
by research pipeline. The proportion of the total funding 
awarded to women ranged from 14.3% (in 1998) to 26.8% 
(in 2009), with a mean proportion of 21.4% for the period 
studied. The proportion of funding was lowest for preclin-
ical research at 18.2% (£285.5 million of £1.573 billion 
total) and highest for operational research at 30.9% 
(£151.4 million of £489.7 million). The funding for clin-
ical (phases I-III) research was 29.9% (£25.5 of £85.2) 
and for product development it amounted to 20.4% 
(£25.8 million of £126.6 million). </p>

<p>Funding organisation 
Table 2 (see web appendix 2) shows in detail the total 
investment, total numbers of studies, mean grant funding, 
median grant funding and fold differences in funding 
according to funding organisation and by gender. 
Public funding organisations invested a total of £1.025 
billion in research led by men (78.6%) and £279.8 in 
research led by women (21.4%). The greatest levels of 
funding awarded to men and to women were by the 
Wellcome Trust and the UK MRC. Major differences 
between funding awarded to men and to women PIs were 
by the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research 
Council (BBSRC), with a 6.12-fold difference. Smallest dif-
ferences between funding awarded to men and to women 
were by the UK Government funding streams such as the 
National Institute for Health Research, with a 1.66-fold dif-
ference. Mean grant funding from public funding organi-
sations was significantly greater for men at £595 361 (SD 
£1 080 718) than for women at £448 414 (SD £814 979). 
Differences were also statistically significant (p&gt;0.01) for 
UK MRC grants with men at £751 413 (SD £1 020 748) 
and women at £544 427 (SD £884 442) and for UK 
Government grants with men at £208 828 (SD £492 519) 
and women at £182 907 (SD £619 889). 
Median grant funding from public funding organisa-
tions had a similar pattern with significantly greater grant 
funding for men at £272 452 (IQR £138 322-£572 529) 
and women at £213 718 (IQR £92 880-£402 917). 
Differences were also statistically significant (p&gt;0.05) for 
UK MRC grants with men at £404 615 (IQR £ 210 068-
£811 860) and women at £286 679 (£178 182 to £468 998), 
and for UK Government grants with men at £129 660 
(IQR £23 761-£207 320) and women at £59 976 (IQR 
£12 564-£157 053). 
Philanthropic funding organisations invested a total of 
£691.7 million in research led by men (78.8%) and 
£185.9 million in research led by women (21.2%). </p>

<p>Head MG, Fitchett JR, Cooke MK, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003362. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003362 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Mean grant funding from philanthropic funding organi-
sations was significantly greater for men at £338 396 (SD 
£695 025) than for women at £242 014 (SD £711 420). 
Differences were also statistically significant (p&gt;0.01) for 
Wellcome Trust grants with men receiving £393 652 (SD 
£723 549) and women £230 168 (SD £362 836) and for 
other charitable funding organisations with men receiving 
£211 190 (SD £454 108) and women £271 842 (SD 
£1 208 852). 
Median grants from philanthropic funding organisa-
tions showed a similar pattern with significantly greater 
grant funding for men at £153 653 (IQR £58 589-
£302 774) and women at £114 173 (IQR £42 658-
£222 842). Differences were also statistically significant 
(p&gt;0.05) for Wellcome Trust grants with men receiving 
£191 461 (IQR £74 759-£362 424) and women £137 241 
(IQR £54 019-£250 723), and for other charitable funding </p>

<p>organisations with men receiving £91 991 (IQR £36 429-
£172 497) and women £76 058 (IQR £17 279-£150 727). 
Figure 4 shows the association between funding organ-
isation and total investment and median funding by 
gender. The MRC awarded the highest median amount 
in grants to women (£286 679; IQR £178 182-£468 998), 
but the median funding amount in grants for men were 
1.41-fold higher than that awarded to women (£404 615; 
IQR £210 068-£811 860). The European Commission 
awarded the highest mean grants to women at £923 364 
(SD £1 316 016); however, mean funding amount in 
grants for men was 1.44-fold higher at £1 325 149 (SD 
£2 409 860) than that for women. </p>

<p>Time trend 
Table 3 (see web appendix 3) shows in detail the trends 
in funding over time from 1997 to 2010 by gender of </p>

<p>Figure 3 (A) Proportion of 
investment over time awarded to 
male and female principal 
investigators. (B) Total investment 
by research pipeline awarded to 
male and female principal 
investigators. </p>



<p>Head MG, Fitchett JR, Cooke MK, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003362. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003362 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>PIs, with amounts and relative proportions each year of 
funding. Mean annual funding received was greater by 
men at £127.6 million (SD £48.7 million) than women 
at £34.9 million (SD £13.4 million). Proportions of 
annual funding received by men ranged from 73.2% to 
85.7%, with a mean of 78.6%. 
Proportions of annual funding received by women 
ranged from 14.3% to 26.8% with a mean of 21.4%. The 
largest annual funding received by men was £245.7 
million in 2000, and the smallest at £64.2 million in 
1997. The largest annual funding received by women 
was £59.6 million in 2002, with the smallest at £13.1 
million in 1998. 
Over the 14-year study period, the proportion of 
investment awarded to women each year remains rela-
tively unchanged with a mean of 21.4% of total (range 
14.3-26.8%; £13.1 million to £59.6 million). Figure 5 </p>

<p>shows the funding trends over time and fold differences 
in total investments by gender. The absolute difference 
in the funding amounts in the grants awarded to men 
and women ranges between £47.9 million and £190.1 
million, with a mean difference of £92.7 million (SD 
£38.3 million). The fold difference in grant funding for 
men and women ranged from 2.74 to 5.97, with a mean 
fold difference of 3.66. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
We present the first detailed and systematic comparison 
by sex of investments in infectious disease research in 
the UK for the 14-year period 1997-2010. We identified 
6165 studies funded by public and philanthropic 
funding organisations, with a total research investment 
of £2.6 billion. </p>

<p>Figure 4 (A) Association 
between funding organisation and 
total investment by gender. 
(B) Association between funding 
organisation and median award 
by gender. BBSRC, 
Biotechnology and Biological 
Sciences Research Council; 
DH, UK department of health; 
MRC, Medical Research Council. </p>

<p>Head MG, Fitchett JR, Cooke MK, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003362. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003362 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>We quantified the differences in research funding 
awarded by gender to show these to be substantial. The 
analysis shows clear and consistent differences between 
men and women PIs, with lower funding in terms of the 
total investment, the number of funded studies, the 
median funding awarded and the mean funding 
awarded across most of the infectious disease areas 
funded. Women received less funding in absolute 
amounts and in relative terms, by funder and the type of 
science funded along the R&amp;D pipeline. These differ-
ences in funding between men and women persist over 
time. 
We show large differences in median funding amounts 
for men and women researchers in investments by the </p>

<p>European Commission and the MRC. Such differences 
were much less apparent when comparing funding from 
the Department of Health and BBSRC, although the 
BBSRC awarded 86% of funding to men. The BBSRC 
almost entirely funds preclinical research, 14 and this 
matches the increased proportions of preclinical studies 
being led by male PIs. 
Our findings in infectious disease research, the most 
detailed until now, provide new evidence on differences 
between men and women researchers to reinforce the 
concerns raised in earlier studies. 4 15 16 Differences that 
are more marked at senior levels of academia need to 
be investigated to explain and account for the observed 
differences. </p>

<p>Figure 5 (A) Total investment 
and trend over time, by gender. 
(B) Fold difference of investment 
over time, by gender. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Head MG, Fitchett JR, Cooke MK, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003362. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003362 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>The reasons why the median awards across most infec-
tious disease conditions should be significantly less for 
women PIs cannot be deduced from the available data. 
Thus, it is not possible to recommend interventions to 
address this phenomenon, given that it is unclear if there 
is any bias or precisely what mechanisms are at play. The 
next step may be to investigate success rates by gender to 
assess how many women are applying and what proportion 
of the initial request for funding is actually allocated. 
There have been suggestions that women are systematic-
ally less ambitious in the amounts of funding requested in 
their grant applications when compared with men who are 
equivalently ranked academically, and that relatively 
simple mentoring programmes could at least partially over-
come this anomaly. 3 However, there is no evidence sup-
porting these assertions. Others have suggested that 
systems which ensure PI anonymity during review of grant 
funding submissions may help reduce the presence of any 
subtle gender biases, 17 though in practice this approach 
would be challenging as the experience of PI is a key 
factor when considering the suitability of request for 
research support. However, evidence on effective interven-
tions to address barriers for women scientists is lacking. 16 
Women of childbearing age are being disadvantaged in 
some areas of employment, even though in relation to sci-
entific endeavour, productivity as measured by published 
outputs is not significantly different between women with 
and without children. 15 </p>

<p>Study limitations 
Our analysis has several limitations. We rely on the accur-
acy of the original data from the funding organisations 
and, as described elsewhere, we have excluded data 
from the private sector as the publicly available data are 
incomplete. 14 
In the period analysed, we were not able to find data on 
the number of men and women PIs requesting financial 
support for research agencies from the funding sources 
studies. Hence, we were unable to assess the success and 
failure rates by gender. We also did not have complete data 
on the amount of funding initially requested, the gender 
of coapplicants for each study, the total pool of researchers 
in each disease area and within each type of science, or 
the proportion of awards made to clinical and non-clinical 
researchers, all of which would be useful pieces of infor-
mation in developing a clearer picture of the reasons for 
the presented differences. The proportion of doctors 
registered in the UK favours men (56.8% as of January 
2013) over women, 18 but the proportion of those carrying 
out research appears to be unknown. Understanding the 
distribution of researchers is critical to an understanding 
of the research landscape. 
We lacked data on the academic ranking of PIs and 
were hence unable to adjust for levels of seniority across 
both genders. We were unable to get data on gender 
from the Gates Foundation and DFID and hence were 
unable to clarify the gender of a small proportion of 
investigators, though we believe this limitation is not </p>

<p>likely to change the conclusions of the study. Our ana-
lysis focuses on infectious disease research, and analysis 
of other areas of scientific research would be needed if 
these differences persisted for all research areas. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS 
Notwithstanding the limitations, our systematic analysis 
shows an unequal distribution of investments in infec-
tious disease research for men and women. There are 
fewer women receiving funding as PIs in infectious 
disease research, with fewer studies funded with lower 
funding amounts when successful. 
Although earlier studies have discussed possible solu-
tions, including mentoring programmes and advertising 
campaigns, none have systematically explored the 
reasons why such differences persist. Hence, without an 
understanding of the reasons for the observed differ-
ences, the proposed solutions are not very meaningful. 
There is no evidence that women and men researchers 
are not equally capable; hence, other factors are likely 
to be at play to explain the observed differences which 
have persisted over the 14-year study period. From our 
data, the limitations mean that we cannot explain what 
these mechanisms might be. Research is needed to elu-
cidate an understanding of the factors that can explain 
the observed differences. A subanalysis of our dataset 
where information on academic rank at the time of 
award is obtained would allow for more meaningful con-
clusions. We strongly urge policy-makers, funders and 
scientists to urgently investigate the factors leading to 
the observed differences and develop policies developed 
to address them, in order to ensure that women are 
appropriately supported in scientific endeavour. </p>

<p>Author affiliations 
1 Research Department of Infection and Population Health, University College 
London, UCL Royal Free Campus, London, UK 
2 London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, London, UK 
3 Imperial College London, South Kensington Campus, London, UK 
4 Harvard School of Public Health, Harvard University, Boston, Massachusetts, 
USA </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors would like to thank Jennifer Harris and 
Raidah Haider for their input and assistance, and acknowledge the assistance 
of the research and development funding agencies for provision of data. </p>

<p>Contributors MGH designed the study with input from RA and JF and 
collated the dataset. JRF, FW and MKC checked and refined the dataset. JRF 
undertook data analysis and created the graphs and figures with input from 
MGH and RA. MGH, JRF and RA interpreted the data and wrote the first draft. 
MGH, JRF and RA refined the analysis and article with input from MKC and 
FBW. All authors reviewed and approved the final version. MH is the guarantor 
of the article. </p>

<p>Funding This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in 
the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors. </p>

<p>Competing interests RA has received research funding from the UK Medical 
Research Council, the UK National Institute for Health Research, UK CRC, UK 
EPSCRC, the UK Department for International Development and the UK 
Department of Health. RA is a member of the UL Medical Research Council 
Global Health Group. MGH works for the Infectious Disease Research Network, 
which has supported this work and is funded by the UK Department of Health. </p>

<p>Head MG, Fitchett JR, Cooke MK, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003362. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003362 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>JRF has received funds from the Wellcome Trust and is a steering group member 
for the Infectious Disease Research Network. MKC has received funding from the 
Medical Research Council and the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation. FBW has 
received funds from the UCLH Charitable Foundation. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement All gender data are available with this submission. 
Further data relating to the Research Investments project can be found at 
http://www.researchinvestments.org or by contacting MGH. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 3.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/ </p>





<p>Head MG, Fitchett JR, Cooke MK, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e003362. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003362 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>