<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3718976" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Centrioles are conserved microtubule (MT)-based organelles 
that are essential for the formation of centrosomes, cilia, and 
flagella. Centriole duplication is a tightly ordered event that 
involves the growth of a procentriole orthogonal to a preexisting 
centriole (Azimzadeh and Marshall, 2010; Nigg and Stearns,  2011). A core of only a few evolutionarily conserved proteins, 
including SAS-6, CPAP/SAS-4, and STIL/Ana2/SAS-5, is 
indispensable for centriole assembly in worms, flies, and humans 
(Brito et al., 2012; Gönczy, 2012). The onset of centriole 
assembly in human cells is triggered by the activation of PLK4 
(Kleylein-Sohn et al., 2007) and the recruitment of CEP152 
(Cizmecioglu et al., 2010; Dzhindzhev et al., 2010; Hatch et al.,  2010) to the surface of the mother centriole. STIL (Tang et al.,  2011; Arquint et al., 2012; Vulprecht et al., 2012) and hSAS-6 
(Strnad et al., 2007) are then recruited to the base of the nascent 
procentriole during the late G1 and early S phases. CEP135 
directly binds to hSAS-6 and CPAP, linking the cartwheel to 
the outer MTs (Lin et al., 2013). CPAP then promotes the assembly 
of nine triplet MTs during centriole biogenesis (Kohlmaier  et al., 2009; Schmidt et al., 2009; Tang et al., 2009). </p>

<p>CEP120 contains a C-terminal coiled-coil domain that 
is conserved in many organisms (Mahjoub et al., 2010). The 
putative orthologue of CEP120 (Uni2) in the green alga Chlam-
ydomonas reinhardtii is essential for basal body maturation 
and flagellogenesis (Piasecki et al., 2008). In mice, Cep120 is 
preferentially expressed in neural progenitors and is involved in 
controlling interkinetic nuclear migration (Xie et al., 2007). 
A recent study showed that Cep120 is up-regulated during the 
differentiation of mouse tracheal epithelial cells and is essential 
for centriole assembly (Mahjoub et al., 2010). However, the 
involved mechanisms are not yet clearly understood. 
We initially identified CPAP as being associated with 
the -tubulin complex (Hung et al., 2000). More recent stud-
ies have demonstrated that CPAP is a positive regulator of 
centriole length (Kohlmaier et al., 2009; Schmidt et al., 2009;  Tang et al., 2009) and that mutations in CPAP/CENPJ cause 
primary microcephaly in humans (Bond et al., 2005). Here, 
we show that CEP120 cooperates with CPAP to regulate cen-
triole elongation. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>entriole duplication begins with the formation of 
a single procentriole next to a preexisting centri-
ole. CPAP (centrosomal protein 4.1-associated 
protein) was previously reported to participate in cen-
triole elongation. Here, we show that CEP120 is a cell 
cycle-regulated protein that directly interacts with CPAP 
and is required for centriole duplication. CEP120 levels 
increased gradually from early S to G2/M and decreased 
significantly after mitosis. Forced overexpression of either 
CEP120 or CPAP not only induced the assembly of overly 
long centrioles but also produced atypical supernumerary 
centrioles that grew from these long centrioles. Depletion </p>

<p>of CEP120 inhibited CPAP-induced centriole elongation 
and vice versa, implying that these proteins work to-
gether to regulate centriole elongation. Furthermore, 
CEP120 was found to contain an N-terminal microtubule-
binding domain, a C-terminal dimerization domain, and 
a centriolar localization domain. Overexpression of a 
microtubule binding-defective CEP120-K76A mutant 
significantly suppressed the formation of elongated 
centrioles. Together, our results indicate that CEP120 is 
a CPAP-interacting protein that positively regulates cen-
triole elongation. </p>

<p>CEP120 interacts with CPAP and positively 
regulates centriole elongation </p>

<p>Yi-Nan Lin, Chien-Ting Wu, Yu-Chih Lin, Wen-Bin Hsu, Chieh-Ju C. Tang, Ching-Wen Chang, and Tang K. Tang </p>

<p>Institute of Biomedical Sciences, Academia Sinica, Taipei 11529, Taiwan </p>

<p>© 2013 Lin et al. This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution-Noncommercial-
Share Alike-No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see 
http://www.rupress.org/terms). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons 
License (Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, as described at 
http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). </p>

<p>T H E J O U R N A L O F C E L L B I O L O G Y </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 202 • NUMBER 2 • 2013 
212 </p>

<p>from a preexisting long centriole (Fig. 1 A, v-x). In contrast to 
the branched filaments described in Fig. 1 B, these Ac-Tub-
labeled filaments appeared to align almost vertically at a 90° 
angle to the preexisting filaments (Fig. 1 E), in a pattern similar 
to the growth of a procentriole from a mother centriole. Intrigu-
ingly, hSAS-6 (Fig. 1, A [v] and E) and STIL (Fig. 1, A [vi] and E), 
which are located asymmetrically to the proximal end of a 
daughter centriole (Strnad et al., 2007; Tang et al., 2011), were 
clearly detected at the bases of the protruding filaments. Fur-
thermore, some of the short Ac-Tub-labeled filaments appeared 
to protrude from the mother centrioles, which were marked 
by ODF2 (Fig. 1 A, vii) and CEP164 (Fig. 1 A, viii). 
Interestingly, the vertically aligned filaments (Fig. 1 E, 
arrowhead) induced by CEP120 overexpression appeared to 
differ from the branched filaments (Fig. 1 E, arrow) in two 
ways: nearly all of the branched filaments lacked the daughter 
centriolar proteins hSAS-6 and STIL at their branching sites 
(Fig. 1 E, arrow) and the branched filaments were usually not 
aligned vertically with respect to each other (Fig. 1 E). Thus, the 
branched filaments induced by CEP120 overexpression most 
likely represented abnormally splayed MTs extending from the 
elongated centrioles. Indeed, both the branched (Fig. 1, C [i and ii]  and D [i], red arrowheads) and vertically aligned MT-based fila-
ments (Fig. 1, C [iv and v] and D [ii], yellow arrowheads) could 
be clearly visualized by EM using different preparation methods 
(Fig. 1, C vs. D; and see Materials and methods). Furthermore, 
amplified atypical centrioles with vertically aligned filaments 
containing hSAS-6 at their bases were also detected in CPAP-
Myc-inducible cells (6%; Fig. 1 F, arrowhead). 
We examined the distribution of these atypical ectopic 
procentrioles from either ODF2-positive or -negative elongated 
centrioles. Our results showed that these ectopic procentrioles 
appeared to be distributed along the elongated centrioles and 
often formed above the ODF2 appendage protein (Fig. 1 G). 
A few ectopic procentrioles (&lt;3%) grew from the bases of 
ODF2-negative centrioles (Fig. 1 G). Together, we conclude 
that overexpression of CEP120 or CPAP produces atypical 
supernumerary centrioles and extra long MT-based filaments. 
This type of centriole amplification appears to differ from that 
observed in cells overexpressing PLK4 (Kleylein-Sohn et al.,  2007) or STIL (Tang et al., 2011), in which the amplified cen-
trioles are observed around the base of the mother centriole. 
The involved mechanism is not yet known. </p>

<p>CEP120-induced centriole elongation </p>

<p>shows a biphasic pattern </p>

<p>We next examined the timing of CEP120-induced filament 
formation during the cell cycle by confocal fluorescence micro-
scopy (Fig. S2 A) and FACS (Fig. S2 B), as shown in Fig. S2 C. 
After withdrawal of aphidicolin, we commonly observed a 
biphasic centriole elongation pattern during the cell cycle. The 
Ac-Tub-labeled filaments from both mother and daughter cen-
trioles appeared to elongate slowly during S phase (0-4 h after 
Tet induction), but increased rapidly during G2 and M phases 
(8-12 h after Tet induction; Fig. S2, A and D). A similar pattern 
was previously observed in CPAP-inducible cells (Tang et al.,  2009). Interestingly, endogenous CEP120 levels oscillated during </p>

<p>Results and discussion </p>

<p>CEP120 overexpression induces extra long </p>

<p>MT-based filaments with centriolar proteins </p>

<p>To investigate the molecular mechanism through which CEP120 
regulates centriole assembly, we generated U2OS-derived cell 
lines stably expressing full-length CEP120-Myc (CEP120-FL-
Myc) under the control of tetracycline (Tet). CEP120-Myc-
inducible cells were treated with or without Tet and analyzed 
by immunoblotting (Fig. S1 A) and confocal fluorescence micro-
scopy (Fig. S1 B). Intriguingly, nearly 80% of the CEP120-
Myc-inducible cells (clone #5; Fig. S1 C) produced extra long 
MT-based filamentous structures that stained positive for 
acetylated-tubulin (Ac-Tub) and appeared to extend from the 
ends of the centrioles (Fig. S1 B). A similar phenotype of extra 
long filaments was also observed to various degrees in other 
CEP120-Myc-inducible lines and in HEK 293T or HeLa cells 
transiently transfected with a CEP120-Myc construct (unpub-
lished data). 
Further immunofluorescence staining indicated that the 
extra long filaments contained several known centriolar pro-
teins, including centrin (Fig. 1 A, i) and CEP135 (Fig. 1 A, ii), 
and the bases of these long filaments appeared to be surrounded 
by the pericentriolar proteins -tubulin (Fig. 1 A, iii) and peri-
centrin (Fig. 1 A, iv). Two procentriole markers (hSAS-6 and 
STIL) were detected at the base of the centrioles (Fig. 1 A, v and 
vi). ODF2 and CEP164, two mother centriole appendage pro-
teins, were observed in the filaments (Fig. 1 A, vii and viii). 
The CPAP present in both mother and daughter centrioles was 
colocalized with CEP120 and spread along the Ac-Tub filaments 
(Fig. 1 A, ix). CP110, which normally marks the distal regions 
of centrioles, was frequently detected at the ends of these long 
filaments (Fig. 1 A, x). Intriguingly, a portion of cells with long 
branched filaments were also found in CEP120-Myc-inducible 
cells (10%; Fig. 1 B). 
Electron microscopy (EM) revealed that the extra long fil-
aments contained MT-based structures (Fig. 1, C [i and ii] and 
D [i]) that strongly resembled those previously observed in 
CPAP-inducible cells (Tang et al., 2009). A portion of the long 
MT-based filaments appeared to extend from the ends of mother 
centrioles, as marked by appendages (Fig. 1 C, iii). Based on 
these results, we conclude that CEP120 induced the production 
of long filaments containing proteins that are characteristic of 
centriolar cylinders and have a MT-based structure similar to 
that of a centriole. </p>

<p>Excess CEP120 induces atypical </p>

<p>supernumerary centrioles extending from a </p>

<p>preexisting long centriole </p>

<p>Unexpectedly, CEP120 overexpression also induced atypical 
centriole amplification. As shown in Fig. S1 D, 48 h after 
CEP120 induction, nearly 35% of asynchronously proliferating 
cells showed amplified (greater than four) centrioles with elon-
gated filaments (Fig. S1 E). 
Careful examination of the CEP120-induced filaments 
revealed a striking phenotype in a portion of CEP120-inducible 
cells (15%), with multiple short protruding filaments growing </p>

<p>213 
CEP120 regulates centriole elongation • Lin et al. </p>

<p>[ </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>S]methionine-labeled full-length CPAP (Fig. 2 E) and CEP120 
(Fig. 2 F), respectively. Together, these findings indicate that 
CEP120 directly interacts and forms a complex with CPAP both 
in vitro and in vivo. </p>

<p>CEP120 and CPAP work together to </p>

<p>promote centriole elongation </p>

<p>To test whether CEP120 is required for CPAP-induced centriole 
elongation, we treated CPAP-Myc-inducible cells (Tang et al.,  2009) as shown in Fig. 3 A. Our results showed that depletion 
of CEP120 significantly inhibited CPAP-induced centriole elon-
gation, from 65% (siControl) to 4% (siCEP120; Fig. 3 B). 
We next examined whether depletion of CEP120 affects 
the centriolar localization of CPAP. U2OS cells were transfected 
with siControl or siCEP120 as described in Fig. S3 A. We 
observed a weak to moderate reduction of CPAP targeting to the 
centriole in siCEP120-depleted cells (91% in siControl vs. 62% in 
siCEP120; Fig. S3 C, bottom). Furthermore, CEP120 depletion 
did not appear to affect the recruitment of hSAS-6 to the procen-
triole (Fig. S3 D), suggesting that the early step of procentriole </p>

<p>the cell cycle; they increased gradually from early S to G2/M 
and decreased significantly after mitosis (Fig. S2 E). This sug-
gests that the protein levels of CEP120 must be carefully regu-
lated to ensure that centrioles are formed correctly in terms of 
their numbers and lengths. </p>

<p>CEP120 directly interacts with CPAP </p>

<p>We next examined whether endogenous CEP120 can form a 
complex with CPAP. Our coimmunoprecipitation experiments 
showed that endogenous CEP120 did coprecipitate with CPAP 
(Fig. 2 B). To further map the interacting domains of CEP120 
and CPAP, we transfected Myc-tagged cDNA constructs encod-
ing various portions of CEP120 into HEK 293T cells and per-
formed immunoprecipitation with an anti-CPAP antibody. 
The CPAP-interacting domain was mapped to the central re-
gion (C3) of CEP120 (Fig. 2 C). Using a similar approach, 
we found that the C terminus of CPAP (CP3) interacts with 
CEP120 (Fig. 2 D). Furthermore, GST pull-down assays dem-
onstrated that GST-CEP120 (C3, residues 416-730) and GST-
CPAP (CP8-10, residues 895-1,070) directly interacted with </p>

<p>Figure 1. Overexpression of either CEP120 
or CPAP induces atypical centriole amplifica-
tion with extra long centrioles. (A-E) CEP120-
Myc-inducible cells were treated with Tet for 
48 h and analyzed by confocal fluorescence 
microscopy using the indicated antibodies 
(A, B, and E) or by EM (C and D). (C and 
D) The branched or vertically aligned MT-
based filaments are marked by red or yellow 
arrowheads, respectively. Red asterisks in C 
(iii) represent appendage structures. (D) The 
small black dots are nonspecific precipitates 
that possibly formed during sample prepara-
tion. (C) The mean length and width of these 
CEP120-induced filaments were 1,000 and 
195 nm, respectively (n = 40). (F) Excess 
CPAP induces the formation of atypical super-
numerary centrioles from a preexisting centri-
ole. CPAP-Myc-inducible cells were treated 
without (Tet) or with (+Tet) Tet for 48 h and 
analyzed by confocal fluorescence micros-
copy. (G) The distribution of atypical ectopic 
procentrioles growing from ODF2-positive 
or -negative centrioles (n = 119 from a single 
experiment). CEP120-Myc-inducible cells were 
treated with Tet for 48 h and immunostained 
with antibodies against ODF2 and Ac-Tub. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 202 • NUMBER 2 • 2013 </p>

<p>
seems to mostly affect CEP120-induced centriole elongation 
extending from newly assembled procentrioles. Similar effects 
were also observed in STIL-depleted cells (Fig. 3, G and H). 
Collectively, our results indicate that hSAS-6 and STIL are 
required for CEP120-mediated centriole elongation. </p>

<p>Characterization of CEP120 </p>

<p>functional domains </p>

<p>Given that CEP120 overexpression can induce extra long 
centrioles (Fig. 1), we sought to define the minimum region of 
CEP120 for such a function. We generated a series of CEP120-
Myc deletion mutants (Fig. 4 B), transiently expressed them 
in U2OS cells, and analyzed them by confocal fluorescence 
microscopy (Fig. 4 C). To our surprise, only the N3 construct 
(residues 1-894), comprising nearly the full-length CEP120, 
induced extra long centrioles (Fig. 4 C). Other mutants that 
lacked either the C (N4) or the N terminus (C7) of CEP120 failed 
to induce longer centrioles, implying that both termini are im-
portant for CEP120-mediated centriole elongation. 
To examine whether CEP120 possesses MT-binding ac-
tivity, we generated a series of CEP120-GFP deletion constructs 
(Fig. 4 D) and transiently expressed them in U2OS cells. Our 
results showed that both CEP120-FL-GFP (30%) and N5-GFP 
(42%) revealed a strong MT association pattern (Fig. 4 D). </p>

<p>formation was not perturbed by CEP120 depletion. Similarly, 
depletion of CPAP also severely decreased CEP120-induced 
centriole elongation (Fig. 3 C) and appeared to have weak or 
no effect on the targeting of CEP120 (Fig. S3 E) or hSAS-6 
(Fig. S3 F) to the centriole. We thus conclude that CEP120 and 
CPAP are both required for centriole elongation and seem to 
have a weak mutual dependence for their centriolar localization. </p>

<p>STIL and hSAS-6 are required for </p>

<p>CEP120-induced centriole elongation </p>

<p>Previous studies showed that two centriolar proteins located at 
the proximal end of the procentriole, hSAS-6 (Strnad et al.,  2007) and STIL (Tang et al., 2011), are required for the early 
events of procentriole formation. To examine whether hSAS-6 
and STIL are required for CEP120-induced centriole elonga-
tion, we treated CEP120-Myc inducible cells with sihSAS-6 
(Fig. 3, E and F) or siSTIL (Fig. 3, G and H), as described in 
Fig. 3 D. Our results showed that hSAS-6 depletion signifi-
cantly inhibited CEP120-induced centriole elongation (79% 
vs. 20%; Fig. 3 E). Intriguingly, 50% of sihSAS-6-treated 
cells contained a single mature mother centriole labeled by 
ODF2 (Fig. 3 F, ii), whereas the other cells contained either 
two short centrioles (31%; Fig. 3 F, iii) or a single long ODF2-
labeled centriole (19%; Fig. 3 F, iv). Thus, hSAS-6 depletion </p>

<p>Figure 2. CEP120 interacts with CPAP. (A) A sche-
matic representation of the interaction between 
CEP120 and CPAP. (B) Coimmunoprecipitation ex-
periments showed that endogenous CEP120 and 
CPAP form a complex in vivo. (C) CPAP interacts with 
the C3 domain of CEP120. (D) CEP120 interacts with 
the CP3 domain of CPAP. (E) Mapping the CPAP-
interacting domain in CEP120 by GST pull-down 
assays. Full-length [ </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>S]methionine-labeled CPAP pro-
teins were incubated with bead-bound GST or vari-
ous GST-CEP120-truncated proteins and analyzed 
by SDS-PAGE and autoradiography. (F) Mapping the 
CEP120-interacting domain in CPAP. </p>

<p> 
CEP120 regulates centriole elongation • Lin et al. </p>

<p>second (K76A or E55A), highly conserved basic (lysine, K) or 
acidic (glutamic acid, E) residues at the N terminus were 
replaced with a more neutral residue (alanine, A). Immunoflu-
orescence analyses showed that N5-K76A, but not N5-E55A, 
was impaired in its ability to bind MTs (Fig. 5, C and D). 
Furthermore, the formation of extra long centrioles was signifi-
cantly inhibited in cells expressing full-length K76A construct 
(Fig. 5, E and F). We thus conclude that the MT-binding activity 
of CEP120 is essential for its centriole-elongating activity. We 
also examined the dimerization activity of CEP120 and found 
that the E831P mutant greatly reduced the binding to itself 
(Fig. 5 B), but had only a mild inhibitory effect on centriole 
elongation (Fig. 5 F). Furthermore, the K76A mutant seemed to 
moderately inhibit normal centriole duplication (Fig. 5 H). 
How do centriolar MT triplets elongate and what molecular 
mechanism determines their final length? A recent study showed 
that the nucleotide status of tubulin controls Sas-4 (a fly homo-
logue of CPAP)-dependent recruitment of pericentriolar mate-
rial (Gopalakrishnan et al., 2012). One possible scenario is 
that CPAP at the proximal end of a centriole may bind to either 
tubulin-GDP or tubulin-GTP via its intrinsic tubulin dimer bind-
ing domain. Such an interaction might then induce a conforma-
tional change that regulates the formation of CPAP-CEP120 </p>

<p>Furthermore, MT cosedimentation experiments showed that 
GST-N5 could bind to and cosediment with MTs in the pellet 
(Fig. 4 E). These results suggest that the N terminus of CEP120 
(N5, residues 1-209) directly binds to MTs. 
We next examined the possible function of the C terminus 
of CEP120. A previous study showed that the C-terminal do-
main of mouse Cep120 is required for centriolar localization 
(Mahjoub et al., 2010). Consistent with this finding, we further 
narrowed down the centriolar localization to the C8 (residues 
731-894) of human CEP120 (Fig. 4 C). Unexpectedly, the 
C-terminal C2 domain (Fig. 4 F) also possessed the ability to 
homodimerize. Our coimmunoprecipitation experiments showed 
that the full-length CEP120-Myc and deletion constructs con-
taining the C8 fragment (N3 and C2) were able to form com-
plexes with full-length CEP120-GFP (Fig. 4 F), whereas the C8 
fragment alone exhibited a very weak association (Fig. 4 F). 
These results suggest that the C terminus of CEP120 is required 
for both centriolar localization and self-dimerization. 
To examine whether MT binding or self-dimerization is 
essential for CEP120-mediated centriole elongation, we gener-
ated two different types of mutants. The first contained a proline 
mutation (E831P or E876P) that disrupted the predicted -helical 
structure in the C-terminal coiled-coil domain (Fig. 5 A). In the </p>

<p>Figure 3. CEP120 cooperates with CPAP to promote centriole elongation and both hSAS-6 and STIL are required for CEP120-induced centriole elongation. 
(A-C) CPAP-Myc-(B) and CEP120-Myc (C)-inducible cells were treated as shown in A and analyzed by confocal fluorescence microscopy. The percent-
ages of CPAP-Myc-or CEP120-Myc-induced elongated or nonelongated procentrioles formed after siCEP120 (B) or siCPAP (C) treatment are shown. 
(D-H) Depletion of hSAS-6 or STIL inhibits CEP120-induced centriole elongation. CEP120-Myc-inducible cells were transfected with siControl, sihSAS-6 
(E and F), or siSTIL (G and H) as shown in D. Histograms illustrating the percentages of elongated or nonelongated centrioles induced by CEP120 overex-
pression in sihSAS-6-(E) or siSTIL-treated cells (G). Error bars represent means ± SD of 100 cells from three independent experiments. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 202 • NUMBER 2 • 2013 </p>

<p>
(5-GGAAGGAGATGCAAGAAGATATATT-3) were partially replaced 
without changing the amino acid sequence (5-GGAAGGAGATGCAG-
GAGGACATCTT-3) using the QuickChange kit. The sequences of all con-
structed plasmids were confirmed. The rabbit polyclonal antibody against 
CEP120 was raised using recombinant CEP120-His (residues 639-986) 
and affinity purified. The antibodies against CPAP (1:1,000 dilution; rabbit 
polyclonal raised against the C terminus of CPAP, residues 1,070-1,338; 
Hung et al., 2000), hSAS-6 (1:500 dilution; rabbit polyclonal against hSAS-6, 
residues 1-489; Tang et al., 2009), and centrin 2 (1:500 dilution; rabbit 
polyclonal against centrin2, residues 1-173; Tang et al., 2009) were ob-
tained as described previously. Other commercially available antibodies 
used in this study included anti-ODF2 and anti-Myc-FITC (Abcam); anti-Ac-Tub 
(Sigma-Aldrich); anti-STIL-441a (Bethyl Laboratories, Inc.); anti-Myc (4A6 
[EMD Millipore] or NB600-336 [Novus Biologicals]); and anti-GFP (BD). </p>

<p>Cell culture and transfection 
U2OS, HEK 293T, or HeLa cells were grown in Dulbecco's modified 
Eagle's medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum. Cells were 
transfected with various cDNA constructs using Lipofectamine 2000. </p>

<p>complex and other associated proteins. This CPAP-CEP120 
complex may help to assemble nine triplet MTs during centri-
ole biogenesis. Future experiments are clearly needed to verify 
this hypothesis. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Plasmids and antibodies 
The cDNA encoding full-length CEP120 was RT-PCR amplified from total 
RNA of human HEK 293T cells and subcloned in-frame into the pEGFP-N2 
(BD) or pcDNA4/TO/Myc-His-A (Invitrogen) vectors. To construct the GST 
fusion plasmids, cDNAs encoding various portions of CEP120 were fused 
in-frame to GST in the pGEX-4T vector. The GFP-or Myc-tagged CEP120 
mutant constructs were generated by site-directed mutagenesis using a 
QuikChange kit (Agilent Technologies). For siRNA-resistant CEP120 
plasmid construction, the nucleotides targeted by siCEP120#3 within 
the full-length wild-type CEP120 in the pcDNA4/TO/Myc-His-A vector </p>

<p>Figure 4. Mapping the functional domains of 
CEP120. (A) Summary of CEP120 functional 
domains. (B and C) Mapping the region re-
quired for CEP120-induced centriole elonga-
tion. U2OS cells were transiently transfected 
with various CEP120-Myc-truncated constructs 
(B) and analyzed by confocal fluorescence 
microscopy using antibodies against centrin and 
Myc (C). (D and E) Mapping the MT-binding 
domain in CEP120. Various GFP-tagged 
CEP120-truncated constructs (D) were tran-
siently expressed in U2OS cells and analyzed 
by confocal fluorescence microscopy. (E) A 
MT cosedimentation assay was performed by 
incubating various recombinant GST-CEP120 
proteins with purified tubulins and Taxol (20 µM). 
The supernatants (S) and pellets (P) were ana-
lyzed by immunoblotting. (F) Mapping the 
dimerization domain in CEP120. HEK 293T 
cells were cotransfected with various Myc-
tagged CEP120-truncated constructs and a 
full-length CEP120-GFP. 24 h after transfection, 
cell lysates were analyzed by immunopre-
cipitation and immunoblotting using the indi-
cated antibodies. </p>

<p>217 
CEP120 regulates centriole elongation • Lin et al. </p>

<p>were grown on ACLAR embedding film (7.8-mil thickness; EMS) for 1 d 
and induced with Tet for 2 d. The cells were then fixed with 2.5% glutaral-
dehyde in 0.1 M cacodylate buffer at 4°C for 1 h. The fixed cells were 
washed three times with washing buffer (0.1 M sodium cacodylate/4% 
sucrose, pH 7.4) at 4°C, post-fixed in 1% OsO4/0.1 M sodium cacodyl-
ate buffer for 1 h at 4°C, stained with 1% uranyl acetate for 1 h at 4°C, 
dehydrated with serial ethanol, and embedded in Spur resin. Thin sections 
(80 nm) were stained with 4% uranyl acetate and Reynold's lead citrate 
for 10 min. The samples were examined with an electron microscope 
(Tecnai G2 Spirit TWIN; FEI). </p>

<p>Immunoprecipitation and immunoblotting experiments 
To investigate whether endogenous CEP120 and CPAP forms a complex 
in vivo, HEK 293T cells were lysed in RIPA buffer with protease inhibitors 
(50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 1% NP-40, 20 mM -glycero-
phosphate, 20 mM NaF, 1 mM Na 3 VO 4 , and protease inhibitors including 
1 µg/µl leupeptin, 1 µg/µl pepstatin, and 1 µg/µl aprotinin) for 30 min at 
4°C. The cell lysates were centrifuged at 16,000 g at 4°C for 15 min. The 
supernatants were immunoprecipitated with anti-CEP120, anti-CPAP, or an 
irrelevant rabbit immunoglobulin (NIgG as a negative control) at 4°C over-
night, followed by incubation with Protein G-Sepharose beads at 4°C for 
2 h. The immunoprecipitates were then separated by SDS-PAGE, blotted 
onto a polyvinylidene fluoride microporous membrane (EMD Millipore), 
and probed with anti-CEP120 and anti-CPAP antibodies. HRP-conjugated 
secondary antibodies were used in a 1:5,000 dilution. The immunoreac-
tive bands were visualized using Luminata Crescendo Western HRP Sub-
strate (EMD Millipore). 
To study whether exogenously expressed CEP120-Myc is associated 
with GFP-CPAP, HEK 293T cells were transfected with indicated CEP120-Myc </p>

<p>To generate U2OS-based CEP120-Myc-and CPAP-Myc-inducible lines, 
cDNAs encoding full-length CEP120 or CPAP were subcloned into the 
pcDNA4/TO/Myc-His-A vector (Invitrogen), which is under the control of 
the CMV promoter and two Tet operator 2 sites. The Tet-inducible lines ex-
pressing CEP120-Myc or CPAP-Myc (Tang et al., 2009) were generated by 
transfection of U2OS-T-Rex cells that stably express the Tet repressor TetR. 
U2OS-T-Rex cells were produced by transfection with pcDNA6/TR encod-
ing TetR. To produce a functional construct, the Myc tag must place at the 
C terminus of CEP120. The expressions of CEP120-Myc and CPAP-Myc 
were induced by the addition of 1 µg/ml Tet to the culture medium. </p>

<p>Confocal fluorescence microscopy and EM analysis 
Cells on coverslips were cold treated for 1 h at 4°C and then fixed in meth-
anol at 20°C for 10 min. The cells were washed in PBS, blocked in 10% 
normal goat serum in PBS, and incubated with the indicated primary anti-
bodies. The cells were washed with PBS with 0.1% Tween 20 (PBST) and 
then incubated with Alexa Fluor 488-, Alexa Fluor 568-, or Alexa Fluor 
647-conjugated secondary antibodies (Invitrogen). DNA was counter-
stained with DAPI. The samples were mounted in Vectashield mounting 
media (Vector Laboratories) and viewed on a confocal system (LSM 700; 
Carl Zeiss) with a Plan Apochromat 100×/1.4 NA oil-immersion objec-
tive. Images were acquired with the ZEN or <rs id="software-0" type="software">AimImage Browser</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Carl Zeiss</rs>). 
For EM, CEP120-Myc-inducible cells (Fig. 1 C) were treated with 
Tet for 2 d. Cells were fixed in glutaraldehyde (2.5%) for 1 h, washed three 
times with PBS buffer, post-fixed in 2% osmium tetroxide (OsO4) for 1 h, 
dehydrated with serial ethanol, and embedded in LR white resin (Lin et al.,  2013). The samples were examined with a transmission electron micro-
scope (H7000; Hitachi). Alternatively, CEP120-Myc-inducible cells (Fig. 1 D) </p>

<p>Figure 5. Functional characterization of the 
MT-binding and dimerization activities of 
CEP120. (A) Schematic representation of the 
CEP120 protein showing the mutations in 
the MT-binding and dimerization domains. 
(B) The E831P mutant showed decreased dimer-
ization activity. HEK 293T cells were cotrans-
fected with vectors encoding CEP120-FL-GFP 
and a CEP120-FL-Myc (E831P or E876P) mutant, 
and cell lysates were analyzed by immuno-
precipitation and immunoblotting. (C and D) 
The N5-GFP-K76A mutant showed reduced MT-
binding activity. U2OS cells were transfected 
with wild-type or mutant N5-GFP constructs. 
48 h after transfection, cells were analyzed 
by confocal fluorescence microscopy (C). The 
percentages of transfected cDNA constructs 
that bound to MTs (MT bundle) are shown in 
D. (E and F) The effects of various CEP120 mu-
tants on centriole elongation. U2OS cells were 
transfected with wild-type CEP120-FL-GFP or 
various CEP120-FL-GFP mutant constructs. 
48 h after transfection, the cells were analyzed 
by confocal fluorescence microscopy (E) and 
the percentages of cells with elongated or 
nonelongated centrioles were calculated (F). 
(G and H) The effects of various CEP120 mu-
tants on normal centriole duplication. U2OS 
cells were treated as described in G. (H) Histo-
gram illustrating the percentages of cells show-
ing various centriole numbers after treatment. 
Error bars represent means ± SD of 100 cells 
from three independent experiments. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 202 • NUMBER 2 • 2013 </p>

<p>
This work was supported by Academia Sinica Investigator Award and 
partially by a grant from the National Science Council, Republic of China. 
The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Submitted: 12 December 2012 
Accepted: 6 June 2013 </p>



<p>Cell synchronization and FACS analysis 
For synchronization studies, cells were arrested at early S phase by double-
thymidine block (2 mM) or aphidicolin (2 µg/ml). To analyze endogenous 
CEP120 during the cell cycle, HeLa cells were incubated with 2 mM thymi-
dine for 15 h before transfer into fresh medium for 12 h, and were then 
incubated again in 2 mM thymidine for another 15 h. The synchronized 
cells were collected at different time points and subjected to immunoblot-
ting using the indicated antibodies or FACS (FACScan; BD) analysis. For 
FACS analysis, cells were fixed in ice-cold 100% ethanol for 30 min, 
washed with PBS, and stained with 40 µg/ml propidium iodide. To exam-
ine the timing of CEP120-induced centriole elongation during the cell cycle, 
CEP120-Myc-inducible cells were treated with 2 µg/ml aphidicolin and 
1 µg/ml Tet as shown in Fig. S2 C. At the indicated times after removal of 
aphidicolin, cells were analyzed by confocal immunofluorescence micro-
scopy and FACS. </p>

<p>siRNA studies 
The siRNAs used for hSAS-6, STIL, and CPAP were as described 
previously (Tang et al., 2011). The siRNAs used for CEP120 are as 
follows: siCEP120#1, 5-AAAUCAAAUGCACAGUAAGACUGGG-3; 
siCEP120#2, 5-UGCAAGAGCCUGCAUAUGAGCCAGU-3; siCEP120#3, 
5-AAUAUAUCUUCUUGCAUCUCCUUCC-3. All siRNAs and a nontar-
geting siRNA control were purchased from Invitrogen. Transfections were 
performed using Lipofectamine RNAiMAX reagents (Invitrogen) according 
to the manufacturer protocol. In brief, siRNAs (33 nM) were incubated 
with Lipofectamine RNAiMAX reagents for 20 min at room temperature. 
The siRNA-reagent complexes were added into the cells. After transfec-
tion, the cells were analyzed by immunoblotting and confocal fluores-
cence microscopy. </p>

<p>GST pull-down assay 
To examine a direct interaction between CEP120 and CPAP, various por-
tions of GST-CPAP or GST-CEP120 recombinant proteins were affinity puri-
fied by glutathione-agarose beads (Sigma-Aldrich) and used to pull down 
[ </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>S]methionine-labeled full-length CEP120 or CPAP that had been gener-
ated using an in vitro transcription/translation using the TNT T7 Quick 
Coupled Transcription/Translation System (Promega). GST was used as a 
negative control. After binding, the samples were separated by SDS-PAGE 
and analyzed by autoradiography. </p>

<p>MT sedimentation assay 
For in vitro MT cosedimentation assays, purified brain tubulin (2.5 mM; 
Cytoskeleton) was incubated with various GST-CEP120-truncated recombi-
nant proteins in BRB80 buffer (80 mM Pipes, pH 6.9, 1 mM EDTA, and 
1 mM MgCl 2 ) containing 20 µM Taxol, 1 mM GTP, and 1 mM DTT for 
30 min at 30°C (Lin et al., 2013). The samples were layered on top of 
50 µl of BRB80 buffer containing 50% glycerol and centrifuged in an ultra-
centrifuge (TLA-100; Beckman Coulter) at 100,000 g for 20 min at 30°C. 
The supernatants and pellets were then analyzed with SDS-PAGE followed 
by immunoblotting using the indicated antibodies. </p>

<p>Online supplemental material 
Fig. S1 shows additional data complementary to Fig. 1. Fig. S2 shows that 
CEP120-induced centriole elongation exhibits a biphasic pattern with slow 
growth in S phase and fast growth in G2 phase. Fig. S3 shows data on the 
centriolar localization of CPAP, CEP120, and hSAS-6 in CEP120-or CPAP-
depleted cells. Online supplemental material is available at http://www.jcb 
.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201212060/DC1. </p>

<p>We thank Shin-Yi Lin for generating the U2OS-based CEP120-Myc-inducible 
cell lines. We also thank Sue-Ping Lee and Sue-Ping Tsai at the EM core facility 
of Institute of Molecular Biology and the staff at the DNA sequencing core facility 
and the confocal microscopy core facility of the Institute of Biomedical Sciences 
for their technical assistance. </p>



</text></tei>