<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3193002" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>To identify genes involved in the response to the fire blight pathogen Erwinia amylovora in apple (Malus3domestica), 
expression profiles were investigated using an apple oligo (70-mer) array representing 40, 000 genes. Blossoms of 
a fire blight-susceptible apple cultivar Gala were collected from trees growing in the orchard, placed on a tray in the 
laboratory, and spray-inoculated with a suspension of E. amylovora at a concentration of 10 
8 cfu ml </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>. Uninoculated 
detached flowers served as controls at each time point. Expression profiles were captured at three different time 
points post-inoculation at 2, 8, and 24 h, together with those at 0 h (uninoculated). A total of about 3500 genes were 
found to be significantly modulated in response to at least one of the three time points. Among those, a total of 770, 
855, and 1002 genes were up-regulated, by 2-fold, at 2, 8, and 24 h following inoculation, respectively; while, 748, 
1024, and 1455 genes were down-regulated, by 2-fold, at 2, 8, and 24 h following inoculation, respectively. Over the 
three time points post-inoculation, 365 genes were commonly up-regulated and 374 genes were commonly down-
regulated. Both sets of genes were classified based on their functional categories. The majority of up-regulated 
genes were involved in metabolism, signal transduction, signalling, transport, and stress response. A number of 
transcripts encoding proteins/enzymes known to be up-regulated under particular biotic and abiotic stress were 
also up-regulated following E. amylovora treatment. Those up-or down-regulated genes encode transcription 
factors, signaling components, defense-related, transporter, and metabolism, all of which have been associated 
with disease responses in Arabidopsis and rice, suggesting similar response pathways are involved in apple 
blossoms. </p>

<p>Plants have developed various defence mechanisms that 
are associated with a number of early and late events with 
the initiation of both biotic and abiotic stresses. These 
plant defence responses include various physiological, 
molecular, and cellular events together with transcrip-
tional activation of multiple genes of both known and 
unknown biochemical functions as well as the accumula-</p>

<p>tion of secondary metabolites (Nakashita et al., 2003; 
Malnoy et al., 2007). These responses often entail the 
activation of the hypersensitive response (HR) and leading 
to the development of systemic acquired resistance (Ryals 
et al., 1996; Dangl and Jones, 2001). In addition, plants 
are capable of fortifying the extracellular matrix through 
cutin formation and callose deposition during pathogen </p>

<p>ª 2011 The Author(s). </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-
nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>infection (Dangl and Jones, 2001). A large-scale identifi-
cation and analysis of genes induced upon pathogen 
inoculation is an essential step toward understanding the 
mechanisms of the plant defence response, which, in turn, 
will aid in the development of disease-resistant lines 
(Venisse et al., 2002; Liu et al., 2008). 
Apple (Malus3domestica Borkh.) is one of the most 
important horticultural woody plants cultivated worldwide 
for its value as a fruit crop. The most economically important 
fruit and ornamental trees, such as apple (M.3domestica), 
pear (Pyrus communis), peach (Prunus persica), cherry (Prunus 
avium), strawberry (Fragaria spp.), apricot (Prunus armeniaca), 
almond (Prunus amygdalus), and rose (Rosa hybrida) all 
belong to the Rosaceae family (Shulaev et al., 2008). 
Fire blight disease is a highly destructive bacterial disease 
of apples and pears. The disease is caused by the bacterial 
pathogen Erwinia amylovora which infects almost all the 
aerial parts of the tree including blossoms, fruits, vegetative 
shoots, woody tissues, and rootstock crowns, resulting in 
blossom blight, shoot blight, and rootstock blight (Norelli 
et al., 2003). Due to the wide diversity of host tissues 
susceptible to infection and the limited number of manage-
ment tools available to control this disease, it has been 
difficult to eradicate or slow down the incidence of fire blight 
epidemics. Effective management includes, but is not limited 
to, reducing levels of inoculum in order to avoid the incidence 
of new infections, imposing barriers to the successful 
establishment of the pathogen, and reducing host susceptibil-
ity to infection (Aldwinckle and Beer, 1979). Management 
practices include the use of a few size-controlling rootstocks 
that are resistant to fire blight (Norelli et al., 2003) as most 
dwarfing rootstocks are susceptible to fire blight, and 
chemical treatments to enhance host resistance (Maxson-Stein 
et al., 2002). Recent efforts to develop genetically engineered 
apples expressing T 4 lysozyme and attacin genes and/or other 
antibacterial genes have been promising (Ko et al., 2002; 
Malnoy et al., 2007); however, commercial acceptance of such 
transgenic apples has not been successful. 
To date, genome-wide studies on host-pathogen inter-
actions for fire blight disease are not available. Recently, 
a genome-wide apple EST database has been established 
(Newcomb et al., 2006; Gasic et al., 2009), and apple 
microarrays have been created. Large-scale expression 
studies using microarrays to elucidate the molecular mech-
anisms of early fruit development (Lee et al., 2007), aroma 
production and red coloration (Schaffer et al., 2007), and 
fruit development (Janssen et al., 2008; Soria-Guerra et al., 
2011) have been conducted. Analysis of transcriptional 
changes in apple following E. amylovora infection using an 
apple microarray was recently conducted using 768 ESTs of 
apple defence-related genes (Pontais et al., 2008). This has 
provided some overview of those apple genes involved in 
the response to fire blight infection. 
In this study, an apple microarray of 40, 000 genes 
representing different tissues and conditions, including fire 
blight challenged tissues, was used to study expression 
profiles and to identify a set of genes that are regulated by 
the bacterial pathogen E. amylovora. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Plant material and pathogen inoculation 
Blossoms of apple cv. Gala were collected from established trees 
growing at the Pomology Research Center (Urbana, IL), and 
immediately placed on wet filter paper in two square aluminium 
foil trays. Blossoms in one tray were uninoculated (used as 
controls); whereas, blossoms in the second container were 
sprayed with a bacterial suspension of E. amylovora strain 
Ea1189. Bacterial cells were grown in Luria-Bertani (LB) 
medium at 28°C. The bacterial suspension culture (OD 600 ¼0.1 
(;10 
8 cfu ml 
À1 ) was sprayed onto apple blossoms. 
Both trays were covered with saran wrap, and incubated in 
a controlled chamber at high relative humidity (&gt;95%) and 24°C. 
Flowers were then collected at 0, 2, 8, and 24 h from each of the 
two trays. It is noteworthy to point out that no disease symptoms 
were observed on any of the blossoms throughout this 24 h 
sampling period as disease symptoms would normally appear 
within 5-7 d following bacterial inoculation and affect over 70% of 
blossoms, depending on the prevailing environmental conditions. </p>

<p>RNA extraction and quantification 
Total RNA was prepared from inoculated and non-inoculated 
tissues at 0, 2, 8, and 24 h post-inoculation (hpi) according to Gasic 
et al. (2004). Briefly, 1 g of flower tissue was ground into a fine 
powder in liquid nitrogen using a mortar and pestle, and 
homogenized with 10 ml of extraction buffer (2% CTAB, 2% PVP 
K-30, 10 mM TRIS-HCl pH 8.0, 25 mM EDTA, 2.0 M NaCl, and 
0.5 g spermidine). After vortexing, the tubes were incubated at 60°C 
for 15 min and an equal volume of chloroform-isoamylalcohol (24:1 
v/v) was added. Tubes were centrifuged at 12 000 g for 10 min at 
4°C. The supernatant was transferred to a new tube, an equal 
volume of chloroform-isoamylalcohol (24:1 v/v) was added, and this 
was centrifuged again. The supernatant was transferred to a new 
tube, and 7.5 M LiCl was added at 4°C for overnight precipitation. 
RNA was visualized in a denaturing formaldehyde 1.2% agarose gel 
and quantified using a NanoDrop ND-1000 Spectrophotometer 
(NanoDrop Technologies, Wilmington, DE). </p>

<p>cDNA synthesis and coupling with aa-dUTP to Cy dye ester 
A total of 15 lg RNA was used to synthesise cDNA using 
Superscript III (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) according to the 
manufacturer's instruction. Following coupling with aa-cDNA to 
Cy-dye ester, cDNA was purified using a QIAquic column to 
remove unincorporated aa-dUTP and free amines. cDNAs were 
quantified in a NanoDrop ND-1000 Spectrophotometer. </p>

<p>Microarray hybridization, scanning, and quantification 
The apple microarray, consisting of 40, 000 sequences, has been 
created from the assembly and clustering of expressed sequences 
derived from a total of 34 cDNA apple libraries. These libraries 
represented different apple tissues, both vegetative and reproductive 
(at different stages of development), and subjected to various biotic 
and abiotic stress conditions from a total of 13 different genotypes of 
apple. From these broadly representative cDNA libraries, 33, 825 
unique sequences were selected, together with an additional 6000 
sequences used as positive and negative controls. Altogether, these 
sequences were used to create a 40, 000 70-mer oligonucleotide-based 
apple microarray (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) (Soria-Guerra et al., 
2011). Oligos were resuspended in 150 mM NaPi pH 8.5 to a final 
concentration of 20 lM, and printed on ultragaps coated slides 
(Corning, Corning, NY) using a GeneMachine OmniGrid arrayer 
(Digilab, Inc., Holliston, MA) in a total of 48 blocks. 
Slides were briefly rehydrated in a steaming water bath and 
immediately placed slides on a 70-80°C hot block until all the 
moisture had evaporated. These were then cross-linked using 
a Strategene UV linker at 6000 uj3100, vigorously washed in </p>



<p>0.2% SDS for 2 min, and then gently shaken twice in milliQ water 
for 1 min. Slides were incubated for 45 min at 42°C in preheated 
pre-hybridization buffer (53 Denhardt's, 63 SSC, 0.1% SDS, 25 
lg ml 
À1 tRNA, and 20% formamide), washed five times consecu-
tively in MilliQ water for 1 min and isopropanol for 3-5 min, and 
then immediately dried by centrifugation. 
The Cy3-and Cy5-labelled cDNAs probes were mixed, concen-
trated by using speedVac for 90 min, and brought to a volume of 10 
Òll. After adding 40 ll 23 hybridization buffer (Ambion, Austin, 
TX), cDNA was denatured at 98°C for 3 min, and cooled on ice for 
30 s. Probes were then added to each slide, and covered with a Maui 
mixer AO (Bio Micro Systems, Salt Lake City, UT) cover slip. Slides 
were then placed in a hybridization chamber (Maui, Bio Micro 
Systems) and incubated overnight at 65°C. Following hybridization, 
slides were washed for 10 min with wash buffer I (13 SSC, 0.2% 
SDS), vigorously washed with wash buffer II (0.13 SSC, 0.2% SDS) 
for 5 min at room temperature, and subsequently washed twice with 
buffer III (0.13 SSC) for 5 min at room temperature. After a final 
wash, slides were dried by centrifugation and scanned at a resolution 
of 10 lm per pixel for fluorescence emission at 532 nm for Cy3 and 
at 635 nm for Cy5 using a GenePix 4000B scanner. </p>

<p>Experimental design 
Microarray hybridization and data analysis were performed follow-
ing the MIAME (minimum information about a microarray experi-
ment) guidelines for international standardization and quality control 
of microarray experiments (Brazma et al., 2001). For each time point 
analysed, two independent biological repeats were performed with 
the control and experimental cDNA clones labelled with Cy3 and 
Cy5 fluorescent dyes, respectively. In addition, a dye-swap was also 
included to eliminate any bias resulting from the two fluorescent 
dyes. A total of nine slides were used. 
All comparisons were made between E. amylovora-inoculated 
and uninoculated (control) flowers at each of the time points 
following treatment, including 2, 8, and 24 h. </p>

<p>Data normalization, filtering, statistical analysis, and clustering 
For data analysis using <rs id="software-0" type="software">GeneSpring GX</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">7.3.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Agilent Technolo-gies</rs>, Palo Alto, CA), a genome array file containing all the data 
for each of the oligos represented in the array was uploaded. A 
systematic approach was used to catalogue corresponding EST 
accession number, clone ID, top hit Arabidopsis ID and its 
description, corresponding gene ontologies to top hits, and 
associated EST IDs. This file was uploaded in <rs id="software-1" type="software">GeneSpring GX</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">7.3.1</rs> and used for analysis as the apple oligo genome. 
Data from a total of nine slides, containing intensity values for 
control and signal channels as well as flag values for present, absent, 
or marginal spots were uploaded and sample attributes were 
defined. Data were initially transformed for dye-swap for the 
appropriate samples, and all intensity values less than 0.01 or that 
were negative were converted to 0.01 to reset biologically irrelevant 
or otherwise unacceptable expression values. Following background 
subtraction and elimination of all spots flagged as marginal or 
absent, data were normalized using an intensity dependent LOW-
ESS (locally weighted scatter plot smoothing) normalization method 
to minimize systematic non-biological differences (Yang et al., </p>

<p>2002). Normalized data were then filtered onto expression levels 
(&gt;2-fold up-regulated or &gt;2-fold down-regulated) to obtain a set of 
genes with expression values in at least one of the comparisons 
made. This set was then used for statistical analysis for measurement 
of confidence (t test P value). Clustering analysis was performed 
using k-means clustering to grouped genes with similar transcript 
abundance profiles with 2-fold up and 2-fold down-regulated genes 
at different time points. </p>

<p>Microarray data validation by quantitative real-time-PCR (qRT-
PCR) analysis 
A total of five genes with relevant expression profiles from the Oligo 
array data were randomly selected to be validated by quantitative real-
time PCR (qPCR). Total RNA from blossoms was isolated using 
a modified Cetyltrimethylammonium bromide (CTAB) method (Gasic 
et al., 2004). Total RNA (2 lg) from each sample was treated with 
DNase I (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) and used for cDNA synthesis. 
The first-strand cDNA synthesis was performed with Oligo (dT) 
primer using SuperScript III RT kit (Invitrogen) according to the 
manufacturer's instructions. Specific primers (Table 1) were designed 
using a Fast PCR program (http://www.biocenter.helsinki.fi). The 
SYBR Green real-time PCR assay was carried out in a total volume 
of 25 ll, containing 12.5 ll of 23 SYBR Green I Master Mix 
(Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA), 0.2 lM (each) specific 
primers, and 100 ng of template cDNA. The amplification program 
consisted of 1 cycle of 95°C for 10 min, followed by 35 cycles of 
95°C for 15 s, and 60°C for 1 min. The fluorescent product was 
detected on the last step of each cycle. Following amplification, 
melting temperatures of PCR products were analysed to determine 
the specificity of the PCR product. Melting curves were obtained by 
slow heating at 0.5°C s </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>, from 60°C to 90°C while continuously 
monitoring the fluorescence signal. A negative control without 
a cDNA template was run with each analysis to evaluate the overall 
specificity. Amplifications were carried out in 96-well plates in a 7300 
Real Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems). All samples were run 
in triplicate. An apple actin gene (Apple_0902.385.C2.Contig633) was 
used as a constitutive control gene. The results were presented as 
fold-change relative to the wild type (WT) at 0 h. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Microarray analysis of gene expression in apple 
blossom following E. amylovora inoculation </p>

<p>To obtain an overall view of gene regulation during 
E. amylovora inoculation, microarray analyses were performed. 
Data obtained from scans of nine oligo arrays (70-mer) 
containing 40, 369 apple probe sets representing 40,000 
transcripts for each of the three time-point comparisons was 
quantified, uploaded into <rs id="software-2" type="software">GeneSpring</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">7.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Silicon Genetics</rs>, 
CA), transformed, filtered, and normalized (Gonzalez and 
Vodkin, 2007). Normalized data were further filtered for 
expression levels for quality control to eliminate genes in the </p>

<p>Table 1. Primers used for real-time RT-PCR </p>

<p>Systematic ID number 
Forward primer (5#/3#) 
Reverse primer (5#/3#) 
Size 
Annealing temperature </p>

<p>MdUI01753 
CGATGCAGCTTCGATCCCAACC 
TAGAGTCGCAGGCGTAACGTA 
206 
57.5 
MdUI15852 
TTGCAGGGAAGCTAAATCGTGGTC 
GATTGCGAAGTAGAATCCCATCG 
252 
57.6 
MdUI26615 
GTTACCGTGGCGTTCGACAA 
AAGAAGCGGCGGAGACGGAG 
228 
58 
MdUI22046 
GATCATGAGGAACAAATCGACGGA 
CACCACAAAAAGCAAACCAAGC 
232 
57.6 
MdUI00786 
GGAGACTCCTCACAAGGTTCTTGC 
CAGTATTTAACCACTGGGAGAGCA 
264 
57.9 </p>

<p>Differentially regulated genes during Erwinia amylovora infection in apple | 4853 </p>

<p>array with no values throughout the study. A t test analysis of 
these genes, with a cut-off P value of &lt;0.05, identified 
a collection of 3500 genes that were statistically significant for 
at least one of the three time points (Fig. 1). Among these, 
1561 genes were up-regulated (see Supplementary Table S1 at 
JXB online); while 1939 genes were down-regulated (see 
Supplementary Table S2 at JXB online). These collective 
groups of genes were then used for cluster analysis by k-means 
clustering and functional classification of individual members. 
Changes in expression of all probe sets on a representative 
microarray at different time points are presented in Fig. 1. </p>

<p>Cluster analysis by k-means and principal components 
analysis (PCA) </p>

<p>To visualize the global gene transcription profiles of apple 
blossoms during interactions with E. amylovora and to group 
genes that share similar profiles, a cluster analysis was 
conducted using statistically significant genes that were 
grouped into 12 sets according to their expression profiles 
using k-means (Fig. 2). This algorithm randomly divides genes 
into a user-defined number of clusters minimizing intra-cluster 
variability. Genes grouped within one set share a relatively 
similar expression profile; however, quantitative and qualitative 
expression differences among members of the same set are 
likely to occur. 
Principal component analysis (PCA), presented as a 3-D 
scatter plot in which the loadings for the first, second, and third 
principal components are plotted along the x, y, and z axes, 
respectively (Fig. 3), has revealed the largest fraction of the 
overall variability. Each point along the scatter plot corre-
sponds to a single gene. Genes that exhibit high levels of the 
first principal component and low levels of the second principal 
component are displayed in the lower right corner of the plot, 
and genes exhibiting equal levels of the two components lie 
along the diagonal. Variances explained by the three PCA 
components are 64.29% (x), 24.48% (y), and 11.23% (z), 
respectively. </p>

<p>Genes responding to E. amylovora inoculation in apple </p>

<p>Based on the scatter plot diagram (Fig. 1), numbers of both 
up-regulated (&gt;2-fold) and down-regulated (&lt;2-fold) genes </p>

<p>increased following inoculation. Based on the Venn dia-
gram, the numbers of up-regulated genes at 2, 8, and 24 h 
are 770, 855, and 1002, respectively; while the numbers of 
down-regulated genes at 2, 8, and 24 h are 748, 1024, and 
1455, respectively (Fig. 4). A total of 444 up-regulated genes 
and 432 down-regulated genes were common between 2 h 
and 8 h after inoculation. A total of 576 up-regulated genes 
and 698 down-regulated genes overlapped between 8 h and 
24 h after inoculation; moreover, 452 up-regulated genes 
and 630 down-regulated genes were common between 2 h 
and 24 h after inoculation. </p>

<p>Functional categorization of identified genes </p>

<p>To capture and assess the expression profiles of genes 
regulated during the first 24 h following inoculation, a total 
of 365 up-regulated and 374 down-regulated genes, that 
were commonly modulated at all three time points (Fig. 4; 
see Supplementary Table S3 at JXB online), were used to 
identify or assign putative functions for E. amylovora-
regulated genes. These were found to belong to the 
following functional categories (Fig. 5): 22% of commonly 
up-regulated genes and 17.4% of commonly down-regulated 
genes belonged to the 'metabolism' GO category including 
protein, lipid, carbohydrate, and primary metabolism; 7.7% 
of up-regulated genes and 6.1% of down-regulated genes 
belonged to the 'transcription' category; 5.5% of up-
regulated and 2.6% of down-regulated genes belonged to 
the 'transporter-related' category; 7.1% of up-regulated and 
5.9% of down-regulated genes belonged to the 'cellular 
communication/signaling mechanism' category; 3% of up-
regulated and 2.1% of down-regulated genes belonged to 
the 'defence' category; 1.3% of up-regulated and 3.5% of 
down-regulated genes belonged to the 'stress-relative' cate-
gory; 5.2% of up-regulated and 5.6% of down-regulated 
genes belonged to the 'cell wall related' category; 2.2% of 
up-regulated and 3.7% of down-regulated genes belonged to 
the 'cell components' category; while, 44.8% of up-regulated 
and 52.4% of down-regulated genes were 'unclassified' or 
were of unknown function proteins (Fig. 5; see Supplemen-
tary Table S3 at JXB online). The majority of up-regulated 
genes seem to be related to four major biological changes, </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Scatter plots of expression profiles of apple blossoms treated with Erwinia amylovora 2 h (A), 8 h (B), and 24 h (C) following 
pathogen inoculation. These plots represent the linear scatter distribution of all genes revealing up-and down-regulated genes at 2, 
8, and 24 h after treatment. All comparisons were made between inoculated (treated) and uninoculated (control) at each time point. </p>



<p>including metabolism (22%), transcription (7.7%), as well as 
signalling (7.1%) and transport (5.5%) (Fig. 5A), whereas 
the majority of down-regulated genes are related to three </p>

<p>major biological changes including metabolism (17.3%), 
transcription (6.1%), and signalling (5.8%) (Fig. 5B). 
Those up¼regulated genes involved in transcription 
include WRKY DNA-binding protein 18/33, zinc finger 
(MYND type) and (C3HC4-type) RING finger family 
proteins, PHD finger transcription factor, BTB and TAZ 
domain protein 1, myb domain protein 116, NAC domain 
containing protein 100, basic helix-loop-helix (bHLH) pro-
tein-related, and ethylene-response factor 1. In addition, 
genes involved in transport (e.g. high affinity K 
+ transporter 
5 and cation/H 
+ exchanger 2) as well as those involved in 
signalling, such as serine/threonine protein kinase, calcium-
and calmodulin-dependent protein kinase/kinase, and ethyl-
ene response sensor 1, are also up-regulated. Those genes 
related to enhanced disease resistance include pathogenesis-
related family proteins, acidic endochitinase, TIR-NBS class 
disease resistance proteins, stress response proteins, perox-
idases, and cell wall-associated protein b-galactosidase. 
Those four largest functional categories, except for the 
unclassified protein, of the down-regulated genes include those 
involved in transcription (6.1%), signalling (5.8%), cell wall-
related (5.6%), and stress (3.8%). Those down-regulated genes 
belonging to the transcription category mainly include the 
myb domain protein, DEAD/DEAH box helicase, zinc finger 
(DHHC type) family, and KOW domain-containing transcrip-
tion factor. Those down-regulated genes belonging to the 
signalling category mainly include those involved in histidine </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Cluster analysis of statistically significant genes using k-means. Genes are clustered in a pre-determined number of 12 sets using 
the k-means algorithm available from <rs id="software-3" type="software">Gene Spring</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">7.3.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Silicon Genetics</rs>, CA). Sets are numbered 1 to 6, and the total number of genes 
per set is recorded. Each set contains the schematic representation of the expression profile for each one of its members. For each 
diagram, the x-axis shows the three time points (2, 8, and 24 h), while the y-axis corresponds to fold change in the set of genes. (A) 
Expression profiles of more than 2-fold up-regulated genes. Set 1 consists of 307 genes; set 2, 195; set 3, 292; set 4, 359; set 5, 202; 
and set 6, 177 genes. (B) Expression profiles of more than 2-fold down-regulated genes. Set 1 consists of 301 genes; set 2, 548, set 3, 
352; set 4, 231, set 5, 325; and set 6, 172 genes. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Visualization of three-dimensional principal component 
analysis (PCA) of significantly up-regulated genes (1561) under one 
of the three conditions tested (2 h post-inoculation). </p>

<p>Differentially regulated genes during Erwinia amylovora infection in apple | 4855 </p>

<p>kinase, cyclin-dependent kinase, diacylglycerol kinase, leucine-
rich repeat transmembrane protein kinase, protein serine/ 
threonine kinase, 2-phosphoglycerate kinase, BRI1-associated 
receptor kinase, mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase 
kinase (MAPKKK), and ethylene insensitive 3. Some genes 
related to cell walls appear to be suppressed during fire blight 
interaction. These include endo-1,4-beta-glucanase, non-
specific lipid transfer protein, and proline-/glycine-rich family 
protein. Stress-related genes such as early responsive to 
dehydration and glutathione S-transferase, were found to be 
suppressed in apple blossoms following pathogen inoculation. </p>

<p>Verification of changes in gene expression using 
qRT-PCR </p>

<p>Several candidate genes were chosen to confirm their tran-
script abundance profiles throughout the three time points 
compared with the untreated control. Primers for selected 
genes were designed exclusively to amplify oligo sequences 
identified following microarray analysis (Table 1). </p>

<p>Overall, qRT-PCR results for these genes showed similar 
patterns of expression profiles to those obtained following 
microarray hybridization (Fig. 6). This indicated that tran-
script abundance profiles were consistent with those of the 
oligo microarray results. Therefore, the observed up-regulated 
and down-regulated gene expression patterns of the micro-
array analysis were supported by qRT-PCR analyses (Fig. 6). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Microarray-based gene expression profiling has been recog-
nized as a powerful tool to observe global gene expression and 
the physiological processes involved in response to a particular 
stimulus (Maleck et al., 2001; Schenk et al., 2000). To 
investigate the molecular controls into the response of apple 
blossoms to the fire blight pathogen E. amylovora, gene 
expression profiles were analysed using a 40, 000 apple oligo 
array. During the early stages following inoculation (2, 8, and 
24 h), a total of 3500 apple genes (8.75%) were differentially </p>

<p>Fig. 4. A generalized Venn diagram with three sets of 2, 8, and 24 h after treatment and their intersections. (A) Up-regulated genes and 
(B) down-regulated genes for each time point post-inoculation. All comparisons were made between inoculated (treated) and 
uninoculated (control) at each time point. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Pie charts corresponding to frequency of common up-regulated genes (A) and down-regulated genes (B) in each of the 
functional categories. </p>



<p>modulated in response to E. amylovora. Previously, Norelli 
et al. (2009) identified a total of 468 non-redundant apple 
ESTs isolated by suppressive subtractive hybridization (SSH) 
in response to challenge of leaves of 'Gale Gala' plants with 
E. amylovora strain Ea273 over a period of 96 h post-
inoculation. These expressed sequences were also identified in 
this study during the first 24 h following inoculation. 
As the apple cultivar Gala is known to be susceptible to fire 
blight, expression profiles of genes that are modulated 
following inoculation could probably serve in aiding the 
infection process. Therefore, the numbers of modulated genes 
as well as their levels of response over the 24 h post-
inoculation period should provide a global overview of the 
genetic controls during the early period of fire blight infection. </p>

<p>Regulation of defence-related genes by E. amylovora 
infection </p>

<p>About 3.02% of 365 commonly up-regulated fire blight-
responsive genes are classified to have a defence-related 
function. Approximately 90% of these defence-related proteins 
are up-regulated by more than 3-fold by 24 hpi. Among those, 
there are a number of pathogenesis-related (PR) proteins. PR 
proteins have been reported to be induced in several plant 
species during infection by viruses, viroids, fungi, or bacteria 
(Schenk et al., 2000; Cheong et al., 2002; Aswati Nair et al., 
2010). Induction of these proteins is not pathogen-specific, but 
determined by the form of reaction of the host plant. PR </p>

<p>proteins form protective barriers against pathogens leading to 
local or systemic resistance. In this study, transcriptional up-
regulation of PR proteins, TIR-NBS class disease resistance 
proteins, general stress response genes, such as peroxidases, 
and those possibly involved in antimicrobial metabolite 
production, such as cytochrome P450, have been detected. All 
of these proteins can be related to either local or systemic 
acquired resistance plant responses. Previously, Venisse et al. 
(2002) have reported that many defence mechanisms, including 
those of PR proteins, are elicited in both resistant and 
susceptible apple genotypes, although there is a delayed re-
sponse in a number of genes involved in branch pathways of 
the phenylpropanoid metabolism in tissues of the susceptible 
apple genotype, MM 106 apple rootstock, when challenged 
with a wild-type strain of E. amylovora. Moreover, Venisse 
et al. (2002) have indicated that E. amylovora is capable of 
transiently preventing transcription of several isoforms of 
genes encoding chalcone synthase (CHS), dihydroflavonol 
reductase (DFR), and flavonol synthase (FLS) in leaves of the 
apple rootstock MM111. 
In this study, induction of peroxidase was observed in the 
early stages of infection, thus suggesting activation of an 
oxidative burst. Oxidative burst in plant tissues has been 
reported to participate in the plant response to fungal and 
bacterial infection as well as upon treatment with different 
elicitors, and in response to both oxidative stress and 
wounding (Schenk et al., 2000; Venisse et al., 2002; Cheong 
et al., 2002). In fact, it has been reported that oxidative burst 
in flowers and shoots of susceptible apple tissues is observed 
during invasion of these tissues by E. amylovora (Venisse 
et al., 2002). Based on these findings, it is noteworthy to 
suggest that the oxidative burst is an essential component of 
the infection response in apple blossoms. </p>

<p>Regulation of signal transduction-related genes by 
E. amylovora infection </p>

<p>About 15% of all fire blight-responsive genes are classified to 
have a signal transduction-related function, such as transcrip-
tional regulators and signalling components. Of these genes, 
61% of transcription regulators and 56% of signaling genes 
are up-regulated by more than 3-fold following E. amylovora 
infection. This indicates that these signalling components are 
transcriptionally-regulated during fire blight infection in apple 
blossoms. A gene encoding calcium-and calmodulin-depen-
dent protein kinase is found to be up-regulated in apple 
blossoms following E. amylovora infection, suggesting that the 
calcium ion may be one of the key signals that initiate stress 
resistance reactions in blossoms. It has been reported that 
several CDPKs are likely to mediate biotic or abiotic stress 
responses. For example, one of the CDPKs has a known 
target, phenylalanine ammonia-lyase (PAL), which plays an 
important role in plant defence responses against fungal 
elicitation in cell suspension cultures of French bean (Allwood 
et al., 2002); while, a tobacco CDPK, NtCDPK2, is involved 
in defence response against Agrobacterium tumefaciens in-
fection (Romeis et al., 2001). Moreover, a non-expressor of 
PR genes, such as the Arabidopsis thaliana NPR1 gene, has </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Real-time polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) analysis of 
mRNA expression of randomly selected genes along with their 
corresponding microarray results at 2, 8, and 24 h. (A) Up-regulated 
genes; (B) down-regulated genes. </p>

<p>Differentially regulated genes during Erwinia amylovora infection in apple | 4857 </p>

<p>been identified as a key factor in transducing signals leading 
to systemic acquired resistance (Malnoy et al., 2007). Over-
expression of an apple homologue of NPR1 in transgenic lines 
of fire blight-susceptible apple genotypes, cv. Galaxy and the 
rootstock M26, led to the activation of several PR genes and 
contributed to significantly enhanced resistance to fire blight 
in transgenic lines of apple (Malnoy et al., 2007). 
In this study, some ethylene biosynthesis genes such as 
ethylene response sensor/receptor and ethylene response 1/two-
component response regulator are up-regulated by more than 
3-fold following E. amylovora treatment. Conversely, ethylene 
insensitive 3 is down-regulated. Ethylene response sensors/ 
receptors function as negative regulators; therefore, elevated 
expression of ethylene receptor genes may serve to reduce 
hormonal responses. A similar observation has been reported 
in tomato fruit following inoculation with the biocontrol yeast 
Cryptococcus laurentii (Jiang et al., 2009). During biotic and 
abiotic stress conditions, signalling components have also been 
shown to undergo transcriptional regulation (Schenk et al., 
2000). Interestingly, in this study, WRKY transcription factor 
and zinc finger (C3HC4-type RING finger and MYND type) 
family proteins are highly up-regulated in apple blossoms 
following E. amylovora treatment. WRKY proteins comprise 
a large family of transcription factors. As transcriptional 
regulators, WRKY factors are likely to act by directing 
temporal and spatial expression of specific genes, thereby 
ensuring proper cellular responses to internal and external 
stimuli (Ulker and Somssich, 2004). It has been reported that 
Arabidopsis plants expressing an AtWRKY18 showed 
enhanced levels of resistance to the bacterial pathogen 
Pseudomonas syringae (Chen and Chen, 2002). Thus, the 
observed up-regulation of WRKY transcription factor and 
zinc finger family proteins are also involved in the early 
defence responses of apple blossoms to E. amylovora infection. </p>

<p>Regulation of metabolism-related genes by 
E. amylovora infection </p>

<p>In this study, about 22% of commonly up-regulated and 17% 
of commonly down-regulated fire blight-responsive genes are 
involved in metabolism-related functions. Many of the genes 
in this category function as pathogen-responsive genes. This 
suggests that upon E. amylovora challenge, metabolism-
related genes are induced and serve as a key defence 
mechanism in apple. It is interesting to note that genes 
encoding enzymes that are involved in the mannose-binding 
lectin pathway are highly up-regulated. The mannose-binding 
lectin (MBL), also known as mannose binding protein (MBP), 
appears to be involved in pattern recognition in the first line 
of defence in the pre-immune host. Specifically, MBL 
recognizes carbohydrate patterns found along surfaces of 
large numbers of pathogenic micro-organisms, including 
bacteria, viruses, protozoa, and fungi, where it can activate its 
complements (Turner and Hamvas, 2000). Binding of MBL to 
a microorganism results in the activation of the lectin pathway 
of the complement system. E. amylovora infection strongly 
increases transcription of curculin-like (mannose-binding) 
lectin family protein genes in apple blossoms. </p>

<p>In this study, genes encoding enzymes involved in oxylipin 
signalling are found to be highly down-regulated. Lipoxyge-
nases (LOX) are enzymes that are widely found in higher 
plants. LOXs catalyse the synthesis of oxylipin which is 
a potent signalling molecule involved in the defence reactions 
of both animals and plants (Blee, 2002; La Camera, 2004). 
This enzyme is involved in the initiation of lipid peroxidation 
which contributes to the development of a hypersensitive 
reaction (HR) during an incompatible host-pathogen interac-
tion (Croft et al., 1990). The role of lipid peroxidation has been 
investigated as a possible early step in the signal transduction 
mechanism leading to phytoalexin synthesis (Cornille et al., 
1998). The primary products of LOX, fatty acid hydroper-
oxides, are highly reactive, and may cause oxidative membrane 
damage leading to cell necrosis and premature cell death 
(Hildebrand, 1998). In some cases, lipid pentadienyl, peroxyl 
free radicals, or other active oxygen species such as the 
superoxide anion may also be generated by LOX action (Roy 
et al., 1994). These reactive bursts occurring during the plant 
defence response have been reported to promote hypersensitive 
cell death (Levine et al., 1994). 
In this study, genes encoding enzymes involved in protease 
activity are also highly up-regulated. In plants, proteases play 
a key role in the regulation of biological processes, such as 
the recognition of pathogens and pests, and in the induction 
of effective defence responses. It is interesting to note that, in 
this study, members of the aspartyl protease family protein 
are up-regulated more than 3-fold during the early stages of 
E. amylovora infection, and this increases in expression up to 
5-fold at 24 h following inoculation. 
Based on expression profiles in this study, genes encoding 
enzymes involved in hydrolase activities are highly up-
regulated; thus, they are likely to be involved in the process 
of fire blight infection. Serine carboxypeptidases (SCPs) are 
proteins belonging to the hydrolase family (Fraser et al., 2005) 
that share characteristic structural features, including a signal 
sequence for intracellular trafficking and/or secretion, multiple 
N-linked glycosylation sites, and four evolutionarily conserved 
regions that consist of a substrate-binding domain and three 
catalytic sites (Vendrell and Aviles, 1999). It has been reported 
that a rice serine carboxypeptidase-like gene is involved in 
defence responses against biotic and oxidative stresses (Liu 
et al., 2008). Therefore, the observed up-regulation of SCPs in 
apple blossoms challenged with E. amylovora is of interest and 
deserves further investigation. </p>

<p>Regulation of cell wall organization-related genes by 
E. amylovora infection </p>

<p>In this study, approximately 5.2% of E. amylovora-responsive 
genes are related to cell wall related activities. Interestingly, 
most cell wall organization/modification-related genes are 
highly up-regulated (more than 3-fold) following E. amylo-
vora infection in apple blossoms. Increased expression of cell 
wall biosynthesis-and modification-related genes has also 
been observed in Arabidopsis following challenge with the 
fungal pathogen Alternaria. brassicicola or following wound-
ing stress (Schenk et al., 2000; Cheong et al., 2003). These </p>



<p>data further confirm the hypothesis that cell wall biosynthe-
sis, modification or fortification is essential in the plant host 
response to E. amylovora infection. </p>

<p>Regulation of hormone signalling-related genes by 
E. amylovora infection </p>

<p>Plant defence against pathogens and environmental stresses 
involves the regulation of a complex network of signalling 
cascades that involves several signalling molecules, includ-
ing salicylic acid (SA), jasmonic acid (JA), and ethylene 
(Schenk et al., 2000; Cheong et al., 2002). E. amylovora 
infection causes more than a 3-fold increased transcription 
of genes encoding ethylene response sensors, and, in 
particular, an ethylene response factor. Conversely, the 
down-regulation of transcription of an ethylene-insensitive 
gene is observed in E. amylovora-infected apple blossoms. 
This finding suggests that an ethylene response sensor/factor 
functions as a regulator to induce expression of ethylene 
responsive genes. Ruperti et al. (2002) have identified four 
ethylene response genes in abscission zones of young 
developing fruit of peach that were homologous to thauma-
tin-like proteins, PR-4 proteins, and to fungal and plant 
b-D-xylosidases. It is probable that the ethylene response 
sensor in apple is involved in regulating the expression of 
ethylene response factors that mediate cellular signalling 
following E. amylovora infection of apple blossoms. 
Brassinosteroids (BR) play various roles in disease 
resistance reactions in tobacco and rice (Nakashita et al., 
2003). In this study, a gene coding for the biosynthetic 
enzyme of BR, namely serine carboxypeptidase, is up-
regulated 5-fold following E. amylovora infection. This 
indicates that BR may also be involved in the response to 
E. amylovora infection in apple blossoms. 
Previously, Pontais et al. (2008) investigated transcriptional 
changes in apple in response to E. amylovora infection using 
less than 800 EST clones. It was reported that increased 
numbers of genes related to signal perception and transduction 
as well as a large number of pathogenesis-related (PR) proteins 
have been noted to be present in leaf tissues. In this study using 
an apple microarray comprised of 40, 000 genes, global 
expression of transcripts regulated by the bacterial pathogen 
E. amylovora in blossoms of apple cv. Gala provided a more 
comprehensive assessment of gene expression profiles at three 
different time points following infection. These findings provide 
an overview of the underlying mechanisms related to modula-
tion and regulation of various biochemical pathways in 
response to fire blight infection. However, it should be pointed 
out that some of the genes investigated in this microarray study 
lack annotation, and therefore their roles in the fire blight 
disease response are yet to be elucidated, which, in turn, may 
provide further insights into these findings. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>In this study, when blossoms of the apple cultivar Gala are 
infected with E. amylovora, many plant defence genes, </p>

<p>including those coding for PR proteins, are elicited within 
a period of 24 h following infection. Among the up-regulated 
genes are those involved in transcription, such as WRKY 
DNA-binding protein 18/33, zinc and RING finger family 
proteins, and ethylene-response factor 1, as well as those 
involved in transport, such as high affinity K 
+ transporter 5 
and cation/H 
+ exchanger 2, and those involved in signalling, 
such as serine/threonine protein kinase, calcium-and 
calmodulin-dependent protein kinase/kinase, and ethylene 
response sensor 1. However, these up-regulated groups of 
genes as well as those of PR family proteins, such as acidic 
endochitinase, TIR-NBS class disease resistance proteins, 
stress response proteins, peroxidases, and cell wall associated 
proteins are either not sustained for long durations following 
infection or they do not accumulate to high enough levels 
during the early stages of infection of apple blossoms in fire 
blight-susceptible apple genotypes, such as 'Gala'. Moreover, 
it is important to note that genes encoding enzymes involved 
in oxylipin signalling, LOX genes, are highly down-regulated 
in blossoms of 'Gala' during the first 24 h following E. 
amylovora infection. These signalling genes, together with 
those involved in modulating role(s) such as those coding for 
ethylene response sensors/factors, as well as those associated 
with cell wall hydrolase activities are all contributing to the 
regulation of the disease response; i.e. a delayed defence 
response, in apple blossoms during the early stages of 
infection in the fire blight-susceptible cv. Gala. </p>

<p>Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data can be found at JXB online. 
Supplementary Table 1. Listing of all up-regulated apple 
genes following Erwinia amylovora challenge of apple 
blossoms, at 2, 8, and 24 h post-inoculation with fold 
change and functional categories. 
Supplementary Table 2. Listing of all down-regulated 
apple genes following Erwinia amylovora challenge of apple 
blossoms, at 2, 8, and 24 h post-inoculation with fold 
change and functional categories. 
Supplementary Table 3. Listing of common up-regulated 
(A) and down-regulated (B) apple genes following Erwinia 
amylovora challenge of apple blossoms (2, 8, and 24 h) with 
fold change and functional categories. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work was partially funded by a grant received from the 
USDA-NIFA-SCRI grant AG 2009-51181-06023 (SSK) 
and an Illinois C-FAR grant 08I-020-3-Sen (YFZ). </p>



<p>Differentially regulated genes during Erwinia amylovora infection in apple | 4859 </p>







<p>Differentially regulated genes during Erwinia amylovora infection in apple | 4861 </p>

</text></tei>