<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3328383" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Mammalian telomeres are specialized structures that cap chro-
mosome termini, consisting of hundreds to thousands of tandem 
TTAGGG repeats complexed with several proteins including 
telomere-specific shelterins. Telomere ends are organized into 
protective structures termed t-loops (Griffith et al., 1999), which 
prevent telomeres from being mistaken as broken or damaged 
chromosomes by the DNA repair machinery. Formation of 
t-loops protects chromosome ends against inappropriate repair 
activities that could lead to fusions and deleterious recombination 
-mediated events. Maintenance of telomere structure and func-
tion requires efficient replication of telomeric DNA. It is 
known that the majority of telomere DNA is duplicated by 
conventional semiconservative DNA replication (for review 
see Gilson and Géli, 2007). However, the features of telomere 
replication programs (i.e., origin distribution, the efficiency 
of origin firing, termination site location, fork rate and direc-
tion, and timing) and how these programs influence replication 
efficiency are largely unknown. 
Telomeres challenge replication machinery because of the 
combination of their repetitive G-rich sequence and extensive </p>

<p>heterochromatization. Structural elements of telomeres, includ-
ing secondary structures such as G-quadruplexes (Paeschke 
et al., 2005; Lipps and Rhodes, 2009; Smith et al., 2011) and 
more complex structures such as t-loops, present potential im-
pediments to replication fork passage. Several studies in yeast 
and human cells suggest that telomeric DNA has an inherent 
ability to pause or stall replication forks (Ivessa et al., 2002; 
Makovets et al., 2004; Miller et al., 2006; Verdun and Karlseder, 
2006; Anand et al., 2012). We and others have shown that telo-
meric DNA is difficult to replicate, leading to telomere fragility 
under replication stress (Miller et al., 2006; Sfeir et al., 2009). 
Replication of G-rich sequences by cellular DNA polymerases 
appears to require assistance from other proteins. For example, 
the Saccharomyces cerevisiae Pif1 DNA helicase has been 
shown to play a key role in replication fork progression through 
quadruplex motifs in G-rich regions at nontelomeric sites in the 
genome (Paeschke et al., 2011). With specific regard to telo-
meres, the studies of Sfeir et al. (2009) have revealed that 
efficient replication of mammalian telomeres requires the in-
volvement of the shelterin protein TRF1. A similar requirement </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>elomeric and adjacent subtelomeric heterochromatin 
pose significant challenges to the DNA replication 
machinery. Little is known about how replication 
progresses through these regions in human cells. Using 
single molecule analysis of replicated DNA (SMARD), we 
delineate the replication programs-i.e., origin distribution, 
termination site location, and fork rate and direction-of 
specific telomeres/subtelomeres of individual human 
chromosomes in two embryonic stem (ES) cell lines and 
two primary somatic cell types. We observe that replica-
tion can initiate within human telomere repeats but was </p>

<p>most frequently accomplished by replisomes originat-
ing in the subtelomere. No major delay or pausing in 
fork progression was detected that might lead to telomere/ 
subtelomere fragility. In addition, telomeres from differ-
ent chromosomes from the same cell type displayed 
chromosome-specific replication programs rather than a 
universal program. Importantly, although there was some 
variation in the replication program of the same telomere 
in different cell types, the basic features of the program of 
a specific chromosome end appear to be conserved. </p>

<p>Human telomeres replicate using chromosome-
specific, rather than universal, replication programs </p>

<p>William C. Drosopoulos, 1,2 Settapong T. Kosiyatrakul, 1 Zi Yan, 1 Simone G. Calderano, 1 and Carl L. Schildkraut 1 </p>

<p>1 Department of Cell Biology and 2 Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Bronx, NY 10461 </p>

<p>© 2012 Drosopoulos et al. This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution-
Noncommercial-Share Alike-No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the pub-
lication date (see http://www.rupress.org/terms). After six months it is available under a 
Creative Commons License (Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, 
as described at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). </p>

<p>T H E J O U R N A L O F C E L L B I O L O G Y </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 197 • NUMBER 2 • 2012 
254 </p>

<p>their flanking subtelomeres. We demonstrate, for the first time, 
that the replication of human telomeres is most frequently 
accomplished by replisomes originating in the subtelomere. 
In addition, we find that telomere/subtelomeres from different 
chromosomes from the same cell type exhibit chromosome-
specific programs rather than a universal program. Importantly, 
we observe that, although some variation was seen in the repli-
cation program of the same telomere in the different cell types 
examined here, the basic features of the replication program 
appear to be conserved. Finally, we also have evidence that 
replication can initiate within the telomere repeats in certain 
human chromosomes. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Analysis of telomere replication programs </p>

<p>The extensive studies on yeast telomere replication by 2D gel 
electrophoresis represent the most detailed analysis of telo-
mere replication program features to date. However, because 
we wanted to obtain detailed information on individual mol-
ecules over an extensive length and 2D analysis does not dis-
criminate events in individual molecules, we used SMARD to 
analyze the replication of specific human telomeres in single 
DNA molecules. SMARD is a direct approach to capture im-
ages of individual replicated DNA molecules (Fig. 1). In brief, 
exponentially growing cells are sequentially pulsed with two 
different halogenated nucleosides, iododeoxyuridine (IdU) 
followed by chlorodeoxyuridine (CldU), to label replicating 
DNA. The replicated DNA is isolated and stretched on silanized 
glass slides, and the halogenated nucleosides incorporated 
in the replicated DNA were detected by immunostaining. 
Portions of molecules replicated during the IdU (first) pulse 
stain red, whereas areas of CldU incorporation (second pulse) 
stain green. Asymmetrically placed biotinylated FISH probes 
(blue) create a "bar code" used to identify molecules of inter-
est and to align the images of individual molecules, produc-
ing a composite profile of replication. Replication program 
events that can be detected by SMARD include: initiation sites 
(Fig. 1 B, i), replication forks (yellow arrows) moving in the 
5-to-3 (Fig. 1 b, ii) and 3-to-5 (Fig. 1 b, iii) directions, and ter-
minations (Fig. 1 b, iv). Fork orientation designation is based 
on the observed transitions from IdU to CldU (red to green), 
corresponding to forks that were active during the IdU-to-CldU 
transition. Molecules of each replication event class are arranged 
in order of increasing amounts of IdU incorporation. This was 
done in a nonsubjective manner by first identifying the specific 
stretched DNA strands of interest by FISH, and then arranging 
the photographic images of these molecules from the lowest to 
highest amount of incorporated IdU (red stain) as determined 
by visual inspection. 
In addition to the alignments of micrographic images 
of the molecules, replication events can be graphically repre-
sented as replication profiles, i.e., histograms of the percentage 
of IdU incorporation along each 5 kb of a segment (Fig. 1 b). 
Specific replication events produce characteristic features in 
replication profiles. Peaks represent early replicating regions, 
with sharp peaks indicating origins that are used frequently </p>

<p>for yeast telomere replication has been demonstrated for the 
TRF1/TRF2 homologue TAZ1 (Miller et al., 2006). 
Cytological examination of fluorescently labeled repli-
cated telomeres in metaphase spreads has provided valuable in-
formation on telomere replication (for review see Williams 
et al., 2011). However, this approach cannot be used to deter-
mine the specific characteristics of a replication program. More 
detailed analysis of telomere replication has been performed 
using 2D gel electrophoresis (Ivessa et al., 2002; Makovets 
et al., 2004; Miller et al., 2006; Anand et al., 2012). Although 
2D gel methodology can map origins and termination regions, 
as well as provide information on fork progression, in specific 
chromosomal segments, it is limited to analysis of small (2-10 kb) 
segments. Moreover, the data obtained from 2D analysis comes 
from a population of molecules; therefore events within indi-
vidual molecules cannot be discriminated. Recently, we applied 
an individual molecule approach termed single molecule analy-
sis of replicated DNA (SMARD) to examine mouse telomere 
replication (Sfeir et al., 2009). Although this initial study was 
performed on a population of total genomic telomeric mole-
cules, the design of SMARD allows for all features of replication 
programs to be mapped over large genomic regions, spanning as 
many as 500 kb, in specific individual molecules (Norio and 
Schildkraut, 2001, 2004). 
The replication of telomeres had been assumed to begin at 
initiation sites (origins) within the subtelomere, with telomeres 
being replicated by forks progressing from subtelomere to telo-
mere (Oganesian and Karlseder, 2009). However, the evidence 
for lack of initiation within telomeric DNA came primarily from 
yeast, where initiation occurs at well-defined autonomously 
replicating sequence (ARS) sequences. Origin-dependent ini-
tiation within telomeric DNA has been demonstrated in vitro 
in a Xenopus laevis cell-free system (Kurth and Gautier, 2010). 
In addition, studies linking the shelterin protein TRF2 to the 
recruitment of origin recognition complex (ORC) proteins to 
telomeres raised the possibility of initiation within human telo-
mere repeats (Atanasiu et al., 2006; Deng et al., 2007; Tatsumi 
et al., 2008). Our recent SMARD studies on the replication of 
mouse telomeres demonstrated that initiation can occur within 
telomeres (Sfeir et al., 2009). These studies suggested that 
initiation events in mouse telomeres are not common, imply-
ing that replication of telomeric DNA initiates predominantly 
from origins within adjacent subtelomeric regions or further 
upstream. With regard to the overall program of replication, it 
is currently unknown whether mammalian telomeres replicate 
using telomere-specific or universal replication programs. It 
is also not known if telomere replication programs are unique 
to, and thus defining features of, specific cell types. We have 
demonstrated that replication programs for several gene loci 
such as OCT4 and the immunoglobulin heavy chain (Igh) 
region vary between cell types (Norio et al., 2005; Guan et al., 
2009; Schultz et al., 2010). In our previous study, replication 
of total genomic telomeric DNA was analyzed, which provided 
only limited information regarding replication programs (Sfeir 
et al., 2009). In the present study we have used SMARD to 
examine the replication of specific human telomeres and deter-
mine how replication progresses through human telomeres and </p>

<p>255 
Human telomere replication programs • Drosopoulos et al. </p>

<p>We characterized the replication programs of several 
human telomere loci and their associated subtelomeric regions 
(140-270 kb) by SMARD to establish the extent of program 
variability. Four different human telomere/subtelomere loci, 
located at the ends of chromosome arms 5p, 7q, 10q, and 11q, 
were examined. These loci were selected based on the avail-
ability of restriction endonuclease sites that permit excision 
of the end of a chromosome in a segment of suitable length 
(140-300 kb) for SMARD analysis. SMARD was performed </p>

<p>while broad peaks indicate initiation zones. Valleys represent 
later replicating regions and sharp valleys indicate a termina-
tion site or zone. The progressive decrease in the percentage 
of IdU incorporation from one end of the segment to the other 
is indicative of replication progressing through the segment 
primarily in one direction from an external origin. In many 
cases, the replication profile represents a mixture of the above 
situations and reflects the predominant event in a population of 
DNA molecules. </p>

<p>Figure 1. SMARD. (A) Exponentially growing cells were labeled with the halogenated nucleosides IdU for 4 h followed by CldU for 4 h. Genomic DNA 
was then isolated. To avoid the breakage of large molecules, the cells were embedded in agarose. We used rare cutting restriction endonucleases to 
obtain unique large molecules of genomic DNA, which were separated by pulse field gel electrophoresis to enrich by size for the particular subtelomere 
segments of interest. Southern blotting was performed to identify the target segment within the gel, which was excised. The gel slice containing the segment 
of interest was melted and the enriched DNA in the melted gel solution was stretched on silanized glass slides. Fluorescent antibodies were used to identify 
regions where IdU (red) or CldU (green) were incorporated into the DNA. Immunodetected biotinylated FISH probes (blue) were used to identify the target 
molecules and to align the images of individual molecules to produce a composite profile of replication. (B) Specific replication events are identified by 
characteristic patterns in the aligned molecule images. DNA molecules with increasing red stain from one end indicate replication forks progressing in a 
single direction through the aligned region (ii and iii). Initiation events are indicated by a red tract flanked on both sides by green (i), whereas a green 
tract flanked on both sides by red (iv) indicates a termination event. Molecule alignments can be graphically depicted as histograms of the percentage of 
IdU incorporation along each 5 kb of a segment. Specific replication events produce characteristic features in these replication profiles. Positions of the 
centers of initiation zones are indicated by peaks (i), whereas termination events are indicated by valleys (iv). Replication progressing through the segment 
primarily in one direction (5 to 3 or 3 to 5) from an external origin is observed as a progressive decrease in the percentage of IdU incorporation from 
one end to the other across the segment (x axis; ii and iii). </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 197 • NUMBER 2 • 2012 </p>

<p>
Utilization of the SMARD approach required generation of 
specific FISH probes for identification of these segments, an 
important step not used in our studies on mouse telomeres. 
Because all telomeres consist of the identical sequence, the 
biotinylated locus-specific FISH probes used to identify particu-
lar telomeric/subtelomeric chromosomal segments had to be </p>

<p>on unsynchronized, exponentially growing, early passage cul-
tures of cells grown under physiological conditions. Telomere 
replication programs were determined for several cell types 
including embryonic stem (ES) cells (lines H1 and H9), HeLa 
cervical carcinoma cells, and primary somatic cells: microvas-
cular endothelial cells (MECs) and lung fibroblasts (IMR-90). </p>

<p>Figure 2. Initiation events occur throughout the subtelomere in the human 5p segment in three cell lines, and replication forks progress through the seg-
ment in both directions. SMARD analysis of three different cell lines indicated that the 5p telomere is replicated primarily by forks progressing from the 
subtelomere to the telomere. Alignments of replicated molecules fully labeled with both IdU (red) and CldU (green) are shown. A map of the 5p locus is 
depicted above each alignment, with the positions of the FISH probes (blue bars below) used for identifying and orienting the molecules indicated. Vertical 
orange lines indicate the positions of the ends of the subtelomeric FISH signals used to align the molecules. The boundary between the subtelomere and 
telomere is delineated by a vertical blue line. Yellow arrows mark sites of transition from IdU incorporation to CldU incorporation and indicate the direc-
tion of fork progression at the moment of transition during the replication of the molecule. Replication profiles, histograms of the percentage of molecules 
containing IdU per 5-kb interval along the segment, are shown below each alignment. Initiation events (red tracts surrounded by green) occur at multiple 
locations. The origins appear to be clustered around a 40-90-kb region centered 65-115-kb from the telomere, seen as a peak in the replication profiles. 
Aside from a leftward broadening of the initiation zone in IMR-90 cells, there was not much variation in the basic features of the replication program of the 
5p telomere in the two ES cell lines (H1 and H9) and the primary fibroblasts (IMR-90). </p>

<p> 
Human telomere replication programs • Drosopoulos et al. </p>

<p>containing 3-to-5 forks with short (&lt;10 kb) red tracts at 
the 3 end, detected (Fig. 2, H9 molecules 22 and 23). These 
results indicated that the 5p telomere is replicated primarily 
by forks progressing from subtelomere to telomere. In some 
cases forks progressing toward the telomere (5 to 3) were 
detected &gt;120 kb away from the telomere (Fig. 2, H9 mol-
ecules 11-13, H1 molecules 11-14, IMR-90 molecules 4-6), 
which suggests that in these molecules the telomere was rep-
licated from fairly distant origins. In addition, there was only 
one molecule containing more than one initiation event, and 
only one molecule contained a termination event (Fig. 2, H9 
molecules 3 and 39, respectively) which suggests that the seg-
ment is replicated primarily from a single origin per mole-
cule per cell cycle. Notably, there was no evidence of major 
fork pausing or stalling observed in the molecules examined. 
Specifically, we did not detect multiple molecules with IdU 
to CldU transitions (replication forks) in the same location, 
which is indicative of a major pause or stall site, either in the 
telomere or subtelomere. 
Some program variation was observed in the replication 
program of the 5p telomere in different cells, such as in the 
width of the initiation zone (Fig. 2) and the percentages of 
5-to-3 and 3-to-5 single fork molecules (Table 1). Specifi-
cally, in H9 ES cells the subtelomeric initiation zone spanned 
40 kb, whereas the zone was larger in H1 cells, spanning 60 kb, 
and larger still in IMR-90 primary fibroblast cells (90 kb). In 
the H1 and H9 ES cells, there were roughly equal numbers of 
5-to-3 and 3-to-5 forks (Fig. 2 and Table 1). However, in the 
IMR-90 cells, molecules with single forks were almost exclu-
sively 5-to-3 forks. This may be caused by a larger number of 
origins and/or more proximal origins outside of the segment in 
IMR-90 cells. Most importantly, although some program varia-
tion was seen in the replication program of the 5p telomere 
region in different cells, the basic features of the replication 
program were conserved. </p>

<p>based on specific subtelomeric sequences. Telomeres within 
the segments were identified with a telomere-specific bioti-
nylated peptide nucleic acid (PNA) probe. It should be noted 
that the biotinylated telomeric PNA probe, which hybridizes 
only to the G-rich strand, interferes with the detection of IdU 
and CldU in the telomere repeats in that strand. In principle, 
therefore, IdU and CldU incorporation in the telomere cannot 
be detected in half of the replicated molecules examined, the 
segments where the G-rich strand is the nascent (substituted) 
strand of the duplex. Consequently, labeled molecules whose 
telomeres are stained with PNA only (blue without any red or 
green) are observed, which presumably contain IdU and/or 
CldU substitutions in the G-rich strand. </p>

<p>Initiation events occur throughout the </p>

<p>human chromosome 5p telomere-containing </p>

<p>region, and replication forks move across </p>

<p>the segment from both directions </p>

<p>Genomic regions are replicated by a variety of programs. For 
example, a region can be replicated by several forks from out-
side of the region or many initiation sites within the region. 
These initiation sites are often present in a zone where many 
origins can be activated in an apparently stochastic manner. 
To determine how telomere-containing regions are replicated, 
we analyzed the replication of an 200-kb PmeI restriction 
fragment containing the chromosome 5p telomere and its 
associated subtelomeric region in three different cell lines by 
SMARD. This analysis revealed common features in the rep-
lication of this telomere in the cell types examined. We ob-
served frequent initiation events (a red patch surrounded by 
green) in the subtelomere, which occurred in a zone centered 
65-115 kb away from the telomere, depending on the cell type 
(Fig. 2). Initiation events within the 5p telomere were rare, 
as few molecules had patterns consistent with such events. 
Only in the H9 ES line were these molecules, i.e., molecules </p>

<p>Table 1. Replication events in telomeric chromosomal segments analyzed by SMARD </p>

<p>Telomere segment 
of chromosome </p>

<p>Approximate size 
of the segment </p>

<p>Cell type 
Replication events </p>

<p>Initiation 
5-to-3 fork 
3-to-5 fork 
Termination </p>

<p>5p 
200 kb 
ES (H1) 
10 (24%) 
18 (43%) 
14 (33%) 
0 (0%) 
5p 
200 kb 
ES (H9) 
10 (26%) 
11 (28%) 
17 (44%) 
1 (2%) 
5p 
200 kb 
Lung fibroblast 
(IMR-90) 
3 (15%) 
15 (75%) 
2 (10%) 
0 (0%) </p>

<p>7q 
200 kb 
ES (H9) 
3 (8%) 
18 (49%) 
12 (32%) 
4 (11%) 
10q 
210 kb 
ES (H1) 
0 (0%) 
28 (97%) 
0 (0%) 
1 (3%) 
10q 
210 kb 
ES (H9) 
2 (8%) 
17 (68%) 
2 (8%) 
4 (16%) 
10q 
270 kb 
Lung fibroblast 
(IMR-90) 
0 (0%) 
19 (100%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) </p>

<p>10q 
210 kb 
MEC 
2 (6%) 
22 (65%) 
2 (6%) 
8 (23%) 
10q 
240 kb 
HeLa 1.3 
3 (13%) 
13 (54%) 
2 (8%) 
6 (25%) 
11q 
140 kb 
ES (H1) 
19 (32%) 
22 (37%) 
16 (27%) 
2 (4%) 
11q 
140 kb 
ES (H9) 
17 (36%) 
21 (45%) 
7 (15%) 
2 (4%) 
11q 
140 kb 
MEC 
6 (25%) 
12 (50%) 
3 (12.5%) 
3 (12.5%) </p>

<p>A summary of all replication events detected in the SMARD analysis of telomere/subtelomere segments (Figs. 2-6) from the various cell types studied is shown. The 
number of fully IdU-and CldU-substituted (red-green) molecules containing initiations, terminations, or a single visible fork (5 to 3 or 3 to 5) is indicated. The per-
centage of a given event of the total events observed is indicated in parentheses. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 197 • NUMBER 2 • 2012 </p>

<p>
few molecules that contained forks moving away from the 
telomere (Fig. 3, H9 molecule 23, H1 molecule 29, and MEC 
molecules 28 and 29) did have patterns (forks with short, &lt;10-kb, 
red tracts at the 3 end), which strongly suggest initiation within 
the telomere. 
Importantly, in the majority of molecules with single 
forks, replication progressed in one direction, from subtelo-
mere to telomere (5 to 3; Fig. 3 and Table 1), and these forks 
initiated from origins &gt;100 kb from the telomere. Thus, in 
contrast to the 5p telomere, the 10q telomere appeared to be 
predominantly passively replicated by forks arising from dis-
tant origins (Fig. 3). Furthermore, as in the case of the 5p telo-
mere, there was some variation in the 10q programs between 
the cell types studied. Replication progressed solely from sub-
telomere to telomere in IMR-90 10q and almost exclusively 
from subtelomere to telomere in H1 10q. In MEC 10q, replica-
tion progressed mainly from subtelomere to telomere, and 
more frequently from subtelomere to telomere than from telo-
mere to subtelomere in H9. Accordingly, termination events 
were more frequently detected in H9 (molecules 22-25) and 
MEC (molecules 27-34), only occasionally seen in H1 cells </p>

<p>Replication progresses from origins located </p>

<p>&gt;100 kb from the human chromosome 10q </p>

<p>telomere-containing region, predominantly </p>

<p>from subtelomere to telomere </p>

<p>Our findings for the 5p telomere-containing segment indicated 
that the telomere was replicated primarily by forks progress-
ing from subtelomere to telomere. This result was the first 
direct evidence in support of the idea that human telomere 
replication mainly initiates in the subtelomere. To determine 
if this was generally the case for human telomeres and whether 
the program exhibited by the 5p telomere was common to 
other telomeres, we next examined the replication program 
of the chromosome 10q locus. Unlike the 5p segment, initia-
tion events were infrequently observed in the10q telomere/ 
subtelomere segment for any of the cell types examined. In H1 
and IMR-90 cells, no initiations were seen, while only two 
were detected (out of 25 molecules analyzed) in H9 cells and 
two (out of 34 molecules analyzed) in MECs (Fig. 3, H9 mol-
ecules 1 and 2, and MEC molecules 1 and 2). Although only a 
small number of molecules (four) with clear initiations sites 
(red patches surrounded by green) were detected, some of the </p>

<p>Figure 3. Replication forks progress toward the telomere from origins in the subtelomere of chromosome 10q in three cell types. SMARD analysis of the 
10q telomere segment in ES lines H9 and H1, primary lung fibroblast, IMR-90 cells, and primary microvascular endothelial MECs indicated that the four cell 
lines replicate this segment using very similar programs. In these lines, the 10q telomere is replicated primarily by forks progressing from the subtelomere 
to the telomere. This is reflected in the replication profile histograms, which show a progressive decrease in the percentage of IdU incorporation from 
5 to 3 across the segment, which is indicative of replication progressing through the segment primarily in one direction from an external origin. These distal 
subtelomeric origins are located predominantly &gt;200 kb from the telomere in all four lines. A region of mixed staining (blue-green or blue-red) is seen in 
the right half of many molecules resulting from nonspecific hybridization of the FISH probes. The yellow arrows indicate the direction of replication fork 
progression, and the vertical orange and blue lines demarcate the boundaries of sequences where fish probes bind, as described in the legend to Fig. 2. </p>

<p>259 
Human telomere replication programs • Drosopoulos et al. </p>

<p>The human 7q telomere segment in H9 </p>

<p>ES cells is replicated by forks originating </p>

<p>either within or near to the telomere, </p>

<p>or from outside of the segment </p>

<p>Our findings from the 5p, 10q, and 11q segments indicated that 
telomere replication was most frequently accomplished by forks 
that initiated in the subtelomere. This suggested that subtelo-
mere sequence organization could affect initiation site location. 
Human subtelomeres often contain large (&gt;1 kb) segments 
(duplicons), which are duplicated in other locations in the genome 
(for review see Riethman, 2008). All of the segments examined 
(5p, 10q, and 11q) contained duplicons (Fig. S1). To determine 
whether the absence of duplicons would influence subtelomeric 
origin use, we examined the replication of the chromosome 7q 
telomere, whose subtelomere is devoid of duplicons (Fig. S1). 
Our examination of the replication program of a 200-kb PmeI 
segment of chromosome 7 in H9 ES cells containing the 7q telo-
mere and adjacent subtelomeric region revealed distinct differ-
ences from the other telomere programs. In contrast to the H9 5p 
and 11q segments (Figs. 2 and 4), initiation in the subtelomeric 
portion of the H9 7q segment was relatively rare (only three ini-
tiations detected in 37 molecules with forks), which indicates 
that no initiation zone was present (Fig. 5) in the most telomere-
proximal 200 kb of the subtelomere. In addition, unlike the 
10q segment where molecules with 3-to-5 forks were rarely 
detected (Fig. 3), similar percentages of molecules containing 
5-to-3 and 3-to-5 forks were detected for the 7q segment 
(Fig. 5 and Table 1). Notably, the comparable percentages of 
5-to-3 and 3-to-5 single fork molecules, along with the low 
number of molecules detected with initiation events (three), indi-
cated that the 7q segment is replicated with similar frequency by 
forks originating either within (or near to) the telomere or from 
outside of the segment. This conclusion was further supported 
by the observed low frequency of termination events (Table 1), 
which occur when two simultaneously active forks collide. 
Importantly, the program observed for the 7q telomere 
differed from the programs of the other telomeres (5p, 10q, and 
11q) from the same cell line (H9), further demonstrating that 
individual telomeres in the same cell are replicated by telomere-
specific, rather than universal, programs. </p>

<p>Initiation events are more frequently </p>

<p>detected in 10q telomeres with an </p>

<p>increased length </p>

<p>Our results indicated that telomeres were most frequently rep-
licated by forks originating in the subtelomere. However, in al-
most all the telomeric regions studied here, there is at least one 
and often many forks proceeding from the region of the telo-
mere repeats, which is suggestive of initiation within or near the 
telomere. Initiation events (a significant red tract surrounded by 
green) are difficult to detect within the human telomere repeats 
because the repeats are only 10 kb in average size. To more firmly 
establish whether initiation occurs within the telomere repeats, 
we analyzed telomere replication in HeLa 1.3 cells, a line with a 
mean telomere length of 23 kb, more than twice as long as most 
human cells (Takai et al., 2010). We chose two telomere loci to 
examine: 7q and 10q. The 7q locus was chosen because it showed </p>

<p>(molecule 29), and not detected in IMR-90 cells (Table 1). In 
addition, as in the 5p telomere, fork pausing or stalling was 
not detected. 
Thus, most importantly, our comparison of the replication 
of different telomeres (Ch 5p and 10q) from the same cell types 
demonstrated that different individual telomeres in the same 
cell are replicated by chromosome arm-specific, rather than 
universal, programs. </p>

<p>Initiation events occur at many positions </p>

<p>in the human chromosome 11q telomere-</p>

<p>containing region, and forks move across </p>

<p>the segment in both directions </p>

<p>Our SMARD results indicated that the 5p and 10q loci dis-
played different replication programs, particularly with respect 
to origin site selection. One factor we considered that may 
influence initiation site selection is the timing of telomere 
replication. It has been shown that although human telomere 
replication occurs throughout S phase, specific telomeres rep-
licate early and others replicate late (Arnoult et al., 2010). 
Furthermore, it has been shown that the telomeres of the 5p 
and 10q segments, which exhibited differences in origin site 
selection, are replicated predominantly in mid and late S phase, 
respectively. Therefore, to determine if origin selection could 
be dependent on timing, we next examined the replication pro-
gram of the chromosome 11q telomere, another late replicating 
telomere, and its associated subtelomeric region. Our analysis 
of the 11q segment revealed that in the cell types studied there 
were similar program features. We observed frequent initia-
tion events in the segment, which occurred at many positions 
in 140-kb segment (Fig. 4). This differed from the 10q seg-
ment, where initiations were infrequently seen. It also differed 
from the program of the 5p segment, another locus that exhib-
ited frequent initiations, but where initiations were clustered 
in a smaller 40-90-kb region rather than throughout the seg-
ment. However, within the 11q segment there did appear to be 
preferred sites of initiation within a zone in the ES cell lines, 
which were located in similar locations in these cells (Fig. 4 
and replication profiles). Initiations were more frequently 
detected than terminations in 11q, particularly in the ES cell 
lines, which suggests that replication of the segment initiates 
predominantly from either one origin or two or more closely 
spaced origins. Importantly, although both the 11q and 10q 
telomeres replicate late in S phase, they have distinctly dif-
ferent replication programs, which suggests that timing is not 
major determinant of program features. Furthermore, only one 
molecule (Fig. 4, H9 molecule 39) exhibited a pattern that was 
consistent with initiation within the 11q telomere. Collectively, 
these findings indicated that the 11q telomere is replicated 
primarily by forks progressing from subtelomere to telomere. 
In addition, the proportion of particular types of replication 
events (initiations, terminations, and forks moving 5-to-3 
and 3-to-5) of the total replication events observed was simi-
lar in the cell lines examined (Table 1). Thus, as with the 5p 
and 10q telomeres, our SMARD analysis of the 11q telomere 
indicates that the replication program of a specific telomere 
appears similar in different cell types. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 197 • NUMBER 2 • 2012 </p>

<p>
Figure 4. Initiation events occur throughout the human 11q segment and forks move across the segment in both directions in three cell lines. SMARD 
analysis of the Ch11q telomere segment in human ES H9, H1, and IMR-90 fibroblast cells revealed similar program features. Frequent initiation events 
occurred throughout the full 140-kb length of the segment. Preferred sites of initiation, seen as peaks in the replication profile histograms, could be detected. 
In all three lines, the 11q telomere is replicated primarily by forks progressing from the subtelomere to the telomere. The yellow arrows indicate the direc-
tion of replication fork progression, and the vertical orange and blue lines demarcate the boundaries of sequences where fish probes bind, as described 
in the legend to Fig. 2. </p>

<p> 
Human telomere replication programs • Drosopoulos et al. </p>

<p>the most potential for telomeric initiation of the segments studied 
(see the preceding paragraphs); therefore, it should be the most 
likely segment to observe initiation within the telomere. The 
10q locus was chosen because it showed few potential telomeric 
initiations, allowing us to determine if increased telomere length 
could promote initiation in the telomere. Our initial SMARD ex-
amination of the 7q segment revealed that its telomeres were of 
similar size as the other cells examined; thus, 7q was not stud-
ied further. However, we found that the telomeres of the 10q 
segment were considerably larger, averaging 25 kb. The results 
for the 10q segment are shown in Fig. 6. Replication forks pro-
ceeding preferentially but not predominantly from 5 to 3 were 
observed, differing somewhat from the other cell lines examined 
(Fig. 3). In addition, termination events were frequently detected 
(Table 1) in a termination zone, seen as a valley in the replication 
profile histogram, centered 60 kb from the telomere/subtelomere 
border (Fig. 6). The presence of this zone indicates that the seg-
ment is frequently replicated by simultaneously active forks 
originating from separate regions of the chromosome. Impor-
tantly, we observed clear evidence for initiation in the telomere 
repeats in the HeLa cells. Telomeric initiation events were de-
tected in molecules containing terminations where the red tract 
of the 3-to-5 fork does not extend out from the telomere or 
extends only a few kilobases out from the telomere (Fig. 6, mol-
ecules 1-4). In these cases, the origins that gave rise to these 
forks must have been located within the telomere. The small 
number of initiation events within the subtelomere further indi-
cates that forks that progress in the 3-to-5 direction initiate in 
the telomere. Thus, similar to our observations in mouse cells 
(Sfeir et al., 2009; unpublished data), we find that initiation does 
occur within human telomere repeats. Moreover, because the 
10q termination zone, which is associated with initiation in the 
telomere, was seen in HeLa but not in the other cell lines studied 
(Fig. 3), this implies that replication initiates more frequently in 
the longer 10q telomeres of the HeLa cells. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Uniqueness of replication programs </p>

<p>Our studies reveal a common, fundamental feature of the replica-
tion programs of human telomeres. The replication of human telo-
meres is most frequently accomplished by replisomes originating 
in the subtelomere. However, the distances that subtelomeric 
replisomes travel to reach the telomere can differ significantly 
from one particular chromosome to another, reflecting varia-
tion in initiation profiles (replication programs; Fig. 7). In some 
subtelomeres (Ch 11q), zones where initiation events are fre-
quently supported occur within relatively close proximity to the </p>

<p>Figure 5. Initiation sites were rarely detected in the subtelomere of Ch 7q. 
SMARD analysis of the Ch 7 telomere/subtelomere segment of human ES 
H9 cells is shown. Few initiation or termination events were detected in the 
molecules examined. The lack of distinct peaks or valleys in the replication </p>

<p>profile histogram indicates the absence of preferred initiation or termina-
tion sites. Similar numbers of replication forks proceed in the telomere-
to-subtelomere (3-to-5) and subtelomere-to-telomere (5-to-3) directions. 
Many of the 5-to-3 forks appear to initiate from origins at least 150 kb 
from the telomere. The yellow arrows indicate the direction of replication 
fork progression, and the vertical orange and blue lines demarcate the 
boundaries of sequences where fish probes bind, as described in the leg-
end to Fig. 2. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 197 • NUMBER 2 • 2012 </p>

<p>
telomere. In contrast, initiations are uncommon near the telomere 
in other subtelomeres (Ch 10q), and forks from distant origins 
replicate the telomere. Thus, rather than using a universal 
program, it appears that different telomeres from the same cell 
type use telomere-specific replication programs. With telomere 
replication primarily originating from the subtelomere, it is 
not unexpected that telomere replication programs would be </p>

<p>Figure 6. Replication forks initiate within the telomere repeats in chromo-
some 10q in a HeLa cell line with long telomeres. SMARD analysis of the 
Ch10q telomere segment in HeLa 1.3, a line with a mean telomere length 
of 23 kb, more than twice as long as in most human cells (Takai et al., 
2010). Based on the length of the signals for the FISH probes, we estimate 
that the mean length of the telomeres in Ch10q is 40 kb. Telomeric initia-
tion events are detected in molecules containing terminations where the 
red tract of the 3-to-5 fork does not extend out of the telomere or extends 
only a few kilobases out from the telomere (molecules 1-4). The centers 
of telomeric initiation events are indicated by yellow asterisks. A termina-
tion zone, seen as a valley in the replication profile histogram centered 
60 kb from the telomere/subtelomere border, indicates the frequent use 
of two origins separated by at least 120 kb, which fire at similar times to 
replicate the segment. The yellow arrows indicate the direction of replica-
tion fork progression, and the vertical orange and blue lines demarcate 
the boundaries of sequences where fish probes bind, as described in the 
legend to Fig. 2. </p>

<p>chromosome arm-specific, given the high degree of interchro-
mosomal subtelomere variation (Fig. S1; for review see Riethman, 
2008). Surprisingly, although a particular subtelomere can ex-
hibit sequence polymorphism (for review see Riethman, 2008), 
the basic features of the replication program of a specific telo-
mere appear to be conserved from one cell type to another in 
the cell types examine here. </p>

<p>Significance of program features </p>

<p>The sequence orientation of telomeres is such that when repli-
cation forks proceed from the subtelomere into the telomere, 
the G-rich strand of the duplex serves as the template strand for 
lagging strand synthesis. When single-stranded, the G-rich strand 
has the potential to form G-quadruplexes or other structures that 
can challenge fork progression (Lipps and Rhodes, 2009). Because 
lagging strand templates have more extensive single-stranded 
portions than leading strand templates, these structures should 
have a higher likelihood of forming in lagging strand (G-rich) 
templates. Therefore, it could be potentially more difficult to 
replicate telomeres by forks moving from the subtelomere to 
the telomere than from the telomere toward the subtelomere 
(Fig. S2). However, although our findings indicate that initiation 
does occur in certain telomeres, and origins within the telomere 
(preferentially near the end) would be advantageous, human telo-
mere replication initiates predominantly in the subtelomere. 
Compensatory mechanisms appear to exist for dealing 
with difficulties in replicating G-rich strands by lagging strand 
synthesis, including the use of duplex-unwinding helicases. 
Efficient telomere lagging strand synthesis has been shown to 
be reliant on the Rec Q helicase WRN, which could act to re-
solve replication-challenging structures (Crabbe et al., 2004). 
Studies in yeast have suggested, however, that both lagging and 
leading strand telomere replication challenges the replication 
machinery. Telomeric sequences that were ectopically inserted 
into an internal, nonterminal position in a yeast chromosome 
were found to be equally capable of stalling replication forks 
(in the absence of Taz1), regardless of their orientation with re-
spect to the direction of replication (Miller et al., 2006). Further-
more, it was recently shown that the up-frameshift 1 (UPF1) 
helicase supports leading strand synthesis of human telomeres 
(Chawla et al., 2011). Thus, it appears that cells may be equally 
able to replicate telomeres from either direction. 
Replication forks can stall at particular sequences and 
result in double-strand breaks, leading to genome instability 
(Torres et al., 2004; Mirkin and Mirkin, 2007; Tourrière and 
Pasero, 2007; Branzei and Foiani, 2010). The potential for rep-
lication forks to pause or stall within human telomeres has been 
suggested (Verdun and Karlseder, 2006). The heterochromatic 
nature of subtelomeres may also present a potential hindrance 
to replication fork passage. It has been shown that replication 
forks move slowly through S. cerevisiae telomeres (Makovets 
et al., 2004). However, the rate of fork movement in the last 
100-200 kb of the human chromosomes examined here (Table 1) 
was very similar to that measured for internal genomic regions 
such as the Igh, OCT4, and other loci (Schultz et al., 2010). In 
addition, we did not observe evidence of fork pausing for an ex-
tended length of time. Specifically, we did not detect multiple </p>

<p>263 
Human telomere replication programs • Drosopoulos et al. </p>

<p>boundary in segments containing TERRA CpG promoters 
(Nergadze et al., 2009) are no more frequent than in segments 
lacking these promoters. It should be noted that it has also been 
shown that TERRA transcription appears to occur regardless of 
the presence of 61-29-37 CpG repeats. (Nergadze et al., 2009). 
For example, TERRA transcripts originating from 11q and Xp/Yp 
chromosome ends have been detected (Azzalin et al., 2007), 
although the same chromosome ends are apparently devoid of 
61-29-37 promoters (Nergadze et al., 2009). Importantly, a recent 
genome-wide study found that although moderately transcribed 
regions were generally associated with high initiation frequency 
in mammalian cells, few initiation events were detected in highly 
transcribed regions (Martin et al., 2011). Thus, not only the 
presence of transcriptional activity, but also the level of activity 
appear to be key in determining whether local transcription pro-
motes or represses initiation. In addition, TERRA transcripts 
may also have effects on origin site selection beyond those 
attributed to transcription-mediated local changes to chromatin. 
It has been recently proposed, based on in vitro observations, 
that TERRA and heterogeneous nuclear protein A1 regulate the 
timely exchange at telomeres between replication protein A (RPA) 
and POT1, both single-stranded DNA (ssDNA)-binding pro-
teins, during S phase (Flynn et al., 2011). In this light, TERRA 
molecules might mediate a molecular cross-talk between sub-
telomeric and telomeric replication factors, thereby contributing 
to initiation site selection. 
With regard to replication timing during the S phase, it 
has been shown that specific human telomeres replicate early 
and others later in S phase (Arnoult et al., 2010). Three of the 
telomeres of the segments we examined (7q, 10q, and 11q) were 
found to similarly replicate late in S phase, whereas the fourth 
(5p) replicated in early to mid S phase (Arnoult et al., 2010). </p>

<p>molecules with IdU-to-CldU transitions (replication forks) in 
the same location, either in the telomere or subtelomere, as has 
been observed at pause sites in the family of repeated sequences 
in the Epstein-Barr virus genome (Norio and Schildkraut, 2004). 
Pausing and stalling of forks in S. cerevisiae telomeric sequences 
has been well documented using 2D gels (Ivessa et al., 2002; 
Makovets et al., 2004; Anand et al., 2012). Replication interme-
diates formed by very brief pausing at a specific site, such as the 
subtelomere/telomere boundary, would represent a relatively 
small number of molecules containing forks at the same posi-
tion along the molecule. The small number of molecules con-
taining these pauses would not be detected by SMARD but can 
be detected by the 2D gels used in the yeast studies. In addition, 
differences in observed replication fork pausing may, in part, be 
caused by differences in structure-forming abilities of yeast and 
human telomeric sequences. Moreover, a recent study has strongly 
suggested that stalling in yeast telomeric sequences is protein-
mediated rather than DNA structure-mediated (Anand et al., 
2012). Thus, the differences in detected pausing/stalling between 
human and yeast telomeres may also reflect differences in 
telomere-bound protein contributions in addition to DNA sec-
ondary structure. </p>

<p>Determinants of telomere </p>

<p>replication programs </p>

<p>Because the majority of human telomere replication initiates in 
the subtelomere, the principal determinants of telomere replica-
tion programs are likely subtelomeric rather than telomeric in 
nature. Along with subtelomere sequence composition (Fig. S1), 
other potential factors that may contribute to the chromosome 
arm-specific replication programs include epigenetic modifica-
tions, local transcription, and timing of replication. Studies suggest 
that replication initiation can be associated with transcription 
start sites and nucleosome-free sites (Berbenetz et al., 2010; 
Karnani et al., 2010; Ding and MacAlpine, 2011; Lubelsky 
et al., 2011; Mesner et al., 2011; Valenzuela et al., 2011; for re-
view see Aladjem, 2007; Méchali, 2010; Schepers and Papior, 
2010). However, human subtelomeric DNA has been shown to 
be heavily methylated (Cross et al., 1990; de Lange et al., 1990; 
Brock et al., 1999), and mammalian subtelomeric chromatin 
has been shown to be hypoacetylated and to contain repressive 
trimethyl marks (Benetti et al., 2007), which are features of 
compact, silenced DNA. 
Nevertheless, human subtelomeres can be transcriptionally 
active (Riethman, 2008). Interestingly, of the telomere/subtelo-
mere segments studied here, subtelomeric initiation events occur 
much more frequently within the Ch 11q segment, which has 
only a single transcript mapped to it, compared with the Ch10q 
segment, which has over a dozen transcripts mapped to it. In 
addition to subtelomere transcription, the transcription of telo-
meres into telomeric repeat-containing RNA (TERRA), driven 
by CpG-island promoters located in the directly adjacent sub-
telomere, has recently been demonstrated (Azzalin et al., 2007; 
Nergadze et al., 2009). However, we find that the presence of 
these TERRA CpG promoter sites (Nergadze et al., 2009) does 
not appear to be associated with an increase of initiation at these 
loci. Initiation events very near or at the telomere/subtelomere </p>

<p>Figure 7. Schematic representation of the replication program of four 
different telomere/subtelomere segments of the ES and primary somatic 
cells studied here. This diagrammatic summary of representative molecules 
indicates that human telomeres do not exhibit a universal replication pro-
gram. The dotted vertical line indicates the boundary between the telomere 
and subtelomere. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 197 • NUMBER 2 • 2012 </p>

<p>
serum (Biocell), l-glutamine, 0.1 g/ml heparin, 0.05 g/ml ascorbic acid 
(Sigma-Aldrich), endothelial cell growth factor (Sigma-Aldrich), bovine 
brain extract (Clonetics), and penicillin-streptomycin as previously 
described (Schultz et al., 2010). 
HeLa 1.3 cervical carcinoma cells, a HeLa subclone with a mean 
telomere length of 23 kb (Takai et al., 2010), were a generous gift of 
T. de Lange (The Rockefeller University, New York, NY). The cells were 
cultured in DME (Hyclone) supplemented with FBS, l-glutamine, penicillin-
streptomycin, and nonessential amino acids. </p>

<p>SMARD 
SMARD was performed essentially as described previously (Fig. 1; Norio 
and Schildkraut, 2001, 2004; Schultz et al., 2010). Exponentially grow-
ing cells were sequentially pulse labeled with 30 µM IdU (for 4 h) followed 
by 30 µM CldU (4 h). Labeled cells were embedded in 0.5% low melting 
agarose (InCert; FMC) at 10 6 cells per 80-µl agarose cell plug and lysed 
overnight at 50°C in 1% n-lauroylsarcosine, and 0.5 M EDTA, pH 8, con-
taining 20 mg/ml proteinase K. The treated agarose cell plugs were then 
washed several times (1 h at 50°C) with TE (10 mM Tris, pH 8, and 1 mM 
EDTA), once with 200 µM phenylmethanesulfonyl fluoride in TE (1 h 
at 50°C), then several more times in TE (1 h at room temperature). The 
plugs were then equilibrated in restriction enzyme digestion buffer (New 
England Biolabs) for 2 h at room temperature and the DNA in the plugs 
was digested in situ with PmeI (50 U/plug). The treated plugs were cast 
into 0.7% gels (SeaPlaque GTG; Lonza), and the digested DNA was sepa-
rated by pulse field gel electrophoresis using a CHEF-DRII system (Bio-Rad 
Laboratories). Specific telomere/subtelomere chromosome segments within 
the gel were then located by performing Southern blotting on portion of the 
gel using subtelomere-specific probes. After Southern blotting, pulse field 
gel slices containing the telomere/subtelomere segments of interest were 
excised and melted (20 min at 70°C), and the DNA in the gel solution was 
stretched on microscope slides coated with 3-aminopropyltriethoxysilane 
(Sigma-Aldrich). The stretched DNA was denatured in alkali buffer (0.1 M 
NaOH in 70% ethanol and 0.1% -mercaptoethanol) and fixed in alkali 
buffer containing 0.5% glutaraldehyde. The denatured, fixed DNA was 
hybridized overnight with biotinylated probes at 37°C in humidified chamber. 
Biotinylated DNA FISH probes based on the following subtelomeric se-
quences were prepared by nick translation in the presence of biotin-16-dUTP 
(Roche) and used to identify specific telomeric/subtelomeric segments. 
Ch 5p: nucleotides 100,065-105,023 (probe 1), 104,858-108,992 
(probe 2), and 136,605-177,232 (probe 3); Ch 7q: nucleotides 
158,980,894-159,014,530 (probe 1), and 159,037,147-159,082,858 
(probe 2); Ch 10q: nucleotides 135,365,825-135,402,175 (probe 1) 
and 135,429,047-135,466,998 (probe 2); and Ch 11q: nucleo-
tides 134,841,259-134,846,641 (probe1), 134,846,750-134,850, 
820 (probe2), 134,850,242-134,854,333 (probe 3), 134,907,552-
134,909,757 (probe 4), and 134,912,615-134,917,753 (probe 5; all 
map coordinates were based on National Center for Biotechnology Infor-
mation Human Genome Map Build 37.3). A biotin-OO-(CCCTAA) 4 PNA 
probe (50 nM; BioSythesis) was used to identify the telomeric portion of 
the segment. After hybridization, the slides were blocked with 1% BSA for a 
minimum of 20 min and then incubated with an Alexa Fluor 350-conjugated 
NeutrAvidin antibody (Invitrogen) followed two rounds of incubation first 
with a biotinylated anti-avidin antibody (Vector) and then the Alexa Fluor 
350-conjugated NeutrAvidin antibody to detect the hybridized bioti-
nylated probes. Incorporated halogenated nucleotides were detected by 
incubating the slides with a mouse anti-IdU monoclonal antibody (BD) 
and a rat anti-CldU monoclonal antibody (Accurate) followed by Alexa 
Fluor 568-conjugated goat anti-mouse (Invitrogen) and Alexa Fluor 488-
conjugated goat anti-rat secondary antibodies (Invitrogen). </p>

<p>Microphotographic image acquisition 
Images of immunostained molecules were acquired at room temperature 
using a fluorescence microscope (Axioskop 2; Carl Zeiss) equipped with a 
Plan Apochromatic 100× 1.4 NA oil objective lens and a charge-coupled 
device camera (CoolSNAP HQ; Photometrics) using <rs id="software-2" type="software">IPLab</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">BD</rs>). 
Images were processed with <rs id="software-1" type="software">Photoshop</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Adobe</rs>) and aligned according to 
the FISH probe pattern using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Illustrator</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Adobe</rs>). </p>

<p>Online supplemental material 
Fig. S1 depicts the sequence organization of human telomere/subtelomere 
segments examined in this study. Fig. S2 illustrates telomere replica-
tion by forks progressing from telomeric versus subtelomeric origins. 
Online supplemental material is available at http://www.jcb.org/ 
cgi/content/full/jcb.201112083/DC1. </p>

<p>Given the distinctly different programs we observe, it appears 
that replication timing does not play a major role in shaping 
telomere replication programs. Interestingly, the timing of telo-
mere replication has also been shown to be chromosome-arm 
specific (Arnoult et al., 2010). From these studies, it has been 
proposed that subtelomeric sequences that direct nuclear local-
ization act as determinants of replication timing. However, 
because we did not observe a link between timing and other repli-
cation program features, it appears that sequence determinants 
of replication timing do not influence other features of telomere 
programs. Thus additional factors, possibly including ones 
telomeric in nature, contribute to subtelomeric initiation site 
selection and other program features. Moreover, telomere repli-
cation programs are likely the result of combined contributions 
by many or all of the above factors rather than determined by 
a single factor. </p>

<p>Importance of telomere </p>

<p>replication programs </p>

<p>Improper replication can lead to dysfunctional telomeres that 
can result in genomic instability, cellular senescence, and apop-
tosis. Certain replication programs may render telomeres more 
susceptible to dysfunction than other programs. Along these 
lines, the ability to initiate replication within the telomere may 
safeguard against dysfunction by providing for rescue of stalled 
telomere replication. The present characterization of human telo-
mere replication programs is an essential step in understanding 
their role in telomere function. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>



<p>We thank Drs. Sherri Schultz for characterizing the human ES and endothelial 
cells and additional assistance; Harold Reithman and Carol Elias for advice; 
and James Borowiec, Jeannine Gerhardt, Paolo Norio, and Joel Huberman for 
valuable suggestions in writing the manuscript. 
S.G. Calderano was supported by a fellowship from Fundação de 
Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo (FAPESP). This work was sup-
ported by National Institute of General Medicine Sciences grant 5R01-
GM045751 (to C.L. Schildkraut) and the Empire State Stem Cell Fund through 
New York State contract C024348 (to C.L. Schildkraut). The authors have no 
commercial affiliations or conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>Submitted: 15 December 2011 
Accepted: 19 March 2012 </p>



</text></tei>