<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3983507" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: There is a lack of information on female urinary incontinence (UI) in South Korea. We investigated the prevalence, risk 
factors, quality of life (QoL), and healthcare-seeking behaviors of women with UI. 
Methods: We included 9,873 women over the age of 20 years who had participated in the Korea National Health and Nutrition 
Examination Survey IV. The condition of UI was defined as answering "yes" to the question "Do you have UI?" Additionally, health 
care seeking behavior for UI was defined as answering "yes" to "Have you ever been treated for UI?" The EuroQoL-5 Dimension 
(EQ-5D) descriptive system was used to evaluate QoL. 
Results: The mean age of our sample was 49.7 years. The overall prevalence of UI was 7.9%. The prevalence of UI significantly 
increased with age. The rate of healthcare-seeking behavior for UI also significantly increased with age. However, the rate of health-
care seeking for UI was significantly lower when compared to the prevalence of UI. In our multivariate analysis, age, body mass 
index, and marriage were significantly and independently associated with UI. As the severity of all the subscales of EQ-5D in-
creased, the unadjusted odds ratio for UI also increased. After adjusting for potential confounders, the subscales of mobility, usual 
activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression from the EQ-5D were significantly associated with UI. 
Conclusions: UI is a common disease and is significantly associated with QoL. Our results suggest the need for developing pre-
ventive measures and treatment policies for UI. </p>

<p>The International Continence Society defines urinary inconti-
nence (UI) as "the complaint of any involuntary leakage of urine" 
[1]. UI is an important health problem resulting in psychologi-
cal, social, and hygienic impairment, thus affecting the lives of 
the patients as well as their family [2]. However, there are no 
studies on the overall prevalence, risk factors, quality of life (QoL), 
and healthcare-seeking behaviors of women with UI in South 
Korea. The only available data are from rural areas and sanato-
riums [3-5]. The aforementioned issues need to be addressed in </p>

<p>order to promote health and organize the healthcare services 
related to UI. Therefore, we undertook the present study using 
data from the Korea National Health and Nutrition Examina-
tion Survey IV (KNHANES) to investigate information about 
adult female UI. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study Subjects </p>

<p>This study utilized data from the KNHANES IV. The KNHANES 
was conducted by the Korea Centers for Disease Control and </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.5213/inj.2014.18.1.31 
pISSN 2093-4777 · eISSN 2093-6931 </p>



<p>Kwon and Lee • Incontinence in Korea </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.5213/inj.2014.18.1.31 </p>

<p>INJ </p>

<p>Prevention to examine the general health and nutritional status 
of Koreans. To select a representative sample of the Korean pop-
ulation, they used a stratified three-stage clustered probability 
design (local district → enumeration district → household). To 
date, four surveys have been completed as follows: I (1998), II 
(2001), III (2005), and IV (2007-2009). KNHANES IV enrolled 
31,705 individuals. Among them, 24,871 individuals participat-
ed in the survey. To elucidate the prevalence, risk factors, QoL, 
and healthcare-seeking behaviors of women with UI, we exclud-
ed subjects below the age of 20 years. Individuals with missing 
data on UI (n = 501) were also excluded. The final study cohort 
included 9,873 women. </p>

<p>Evaluation of the Prevalence of UI and the Rate of 
Healthcare-Seeking Behavior for UI </p>

<p>Individuals were classified as having UI if they responded "yes" 
to the survey question "Do you have UI?" Additionally, health-
care-seeking behavior for UI was defined as responding "yes" to 
the following question: "Have you ever been treated for UI?" </p>

<p>Estimation of QoL </p>

<p>The EuroQoL-5 Dimension (EQ-5D) descriptive system was 
used to evaluate QoL. The EQ-5D descriptive system describes 
general health in terms of five dimensions: mobility, self-care, 
usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression [6]. 
Each dimension has three levels, corresponding to no problems, 
some or moderate problems, and extreme problems, resulting 
in a total of 243 unique health states [6,7]. The EQ-5D is a well-
established and internationally used generic preference-based 
instrument for assessing health-related QoL [8]. The validity and 
reliability of Korean EQ-5D has been previously established [9]. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>We first calculated the prevalence of UI and the rate of health-
care-seeking behavior according to age group. We then evaluat-
ed the factors associated with UI. Finally, we evaluated the as-
sociation between UI and quality of life (using the EQ-5D) after 
adjusting for potential confounders (age, body mass index [BMI], 
home income, education, hypertension, diabetes, stroke, mari-
tal status, and place of residence). 
Statistical analyses included the chi-square test, Mantel-
Haenszel extension, and logistic regression analyses; these anal-
yses were performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 11.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chica-
go, IL, USA). Values of P &lt; 0.05 were considered statistically sig-
nificant. </p>

<p>Table 1. Socio-demographic characteristics </p>

<p>Variable 
Value </p>

<p>Age (yr), (n = 9,873) 
49.7 ± 16.7 </p>

<p>Height (cm), (n = 9,819) 
156.0 ± 6.7 </p>

<p>Weight (kg), (n = 9,822) 
57.0 ± 9.1 </p>

<p>Body mass index (kg/m 2 ), (n = 9,818) 
23.4 ± 3.5 </p>

<p>Waist circumference (n = 9,810) 
79.4 ± 10.0 </p>

<p>Place of residence (n = 9,873) </p>

<p>Urban (dong) 
7,268 (73.6) </p>

<p>Rural (eup/myeon) 
2,605 (26.4) </p>

<p>House (n = 9,873) </p>

<p>Apartment 
4,026 (40.8) </p>

<p>Other than apartment 
5,847 (59.2) </p>

<p>Individual income (n = 9,616) </p>

<p>1st Quartile (very low) 
2,389 (24.8) </p>

<p>2nd Quartile (low) 
2,418 (25.1) </p>

<p>3rd Quartile (high) 
2,408 (25.0) </p>

<p>4th Quartile (very high) 
2,401 (25.0) </p>

<p>Home income (n = 9,616) </p>

<p>1st Quartile (very low) 
2,201 (22.9) </p>

<p>2nd Quartile (low) 
2,412 (25.1) </p>

<p>3rd Quartile (high) 
2,507 (26.1) </p>

<p>4th Quartile (very high) 
2,496 (26.0) </p>

<p>Education (n = 8,626) </p>

<p>Elementary school 
3,536 (35.9) </p>

<p>Middle school 
1,016 (10.3) </p>

<p>High school 
3,131 (31.8) </p>

<p>College 
2,160 (21.9) </p>

<p>Married (n = 9,842) </p>

<p>Yes 
8,845 (89.9) </p>

<p>No 
997 (10.1) </p>

<p>Hypertension (n = 9,873) </p>

<p>Yes 
2,040 (20.7) </p>

<p>No 
7,833 (79.3) </p>

<p>Diabetes </p>

<p>Yes 
726 (7.4) </p>

<p>No 
9,147 (92.6) </p>

<p>Stroke </p>

<p>Yes 
206 (2.1) </p>

<p>No 
9,667 (97.9) </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation or number (%). </p>

<p>www.einj.org 33 </p>

<p>Kwon and Lee • Incontinence in Korea </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.5213/inj.2014.18.1.31 </p>

<p>INJ </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Patient Characteristics </p>

<p>Table 1 shows the baseline characteristics of subjects in this study. 
The mean age was 49.7 years. The mean body weight and BMI 
were 57.0 kg and 23.4 kg/m 2 , respectively. </p>

<p>Prevalence of Urinary Incontinence and Rate of Healthcare-
Seeking Behavior According to Age Group </p>

<p>The prevalence of UI was 7.9% (n = 777) among women over 
the age of 20 years. The prevalence of UI among women over 
the age of 40 years and 60 years was 10.1% and 10.3%, respec-
tively. Fig. 1 illustrates the prevalence of UI and the rate of 
healthcare-seeking behavior according to age group. The total 
number of women in their 20s, 30s, 40s, 50s, 60s, and above 70s 
was 1,193, 2,037, 1,919, 1,651, 1,581, and 1,492, respectively. 
The number of UI patients in their 20s, 30s, 40s, 50s, 60s, and 
above 70s was 10, 93, 178, 178, 173, and 145, respectively. Addi-
tionally, the number of women in their 20s, 30s, 40s, 50s, 60s, 
and above 70s who showed healthcare-seeking behavior for UI 
was 1, 1, 6, 4, 6, and 18, respectively. 
The prevalence of UI increased with age (P trend &lt; 0.001). 
The rate of healthcare-seeking behavior for UI (the number of 
individuals seeking health care for UI/total number in each age 
group) also increased with age (P trend &lt; 0.001). However, the 
rate of healthcare-seeking behavior for UI was significantly low-
er than the prevalence of UI (P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Factors Associated With Urinary Incontinence </p>

<p>Multivariate analysis identified age, BMI, and marriage as sig-
nificant independent risk factors for UI (Table 2). Income, edu-
cation, type of residence, hypertension, diabetes, and stroke 
were not independently associated with UI. </p>

<p>Relationship Between Urinary Incontinence and EQ-5D </p>

<p>As the severity of all the EQ-5D subscales increased, the unad-
justed OR for UI also increased (Table 3). After adjusting for 
potential confounders, the subscales for mobility, usual activi-
ties, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression remained signifi-</p>

<p>Table 2. Factors associated with urinary incontinence </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Adjusted OR (95% CI) a) 
P-value b) </p>

<p>Age 
1.011 (1.003-1.019) 
0.007 </p>

<p>Body mass index 
1.038 (1.015-1.062) 
0.001 </p>

<p>Married 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>No 
1.000 (references) </p>

<p>Yes 
7.835 (3.649-16.824) </p>

<p>Home income 
0.560 </p>

<p>1st Quartile (very low) 
1.000 (references) </p>

<p>2nd Quartile (low) 
1.027 (0.826-1.277) </p>

<p>3rd Quartile (high) 
1.067 (0.843-1.351) </p>

<p>4th Quartile (very high) 
1.180 (0.925-1.505) </p>

<p>Education 
0.098 </p>

<p>Elementary school 
1.000 (references) </p>

<p>Middle school 
1.128 (0.871-1.461) </p>

<p>High school 
0.821 (0.630-1.070) </p>

<p>College 
0.799 (0.576-1.109) </p>

<p>Hypertension 
0.182 </p>

<p>No 
1.000 (references) </p>

<p>Yes 
1.140 (0.940-1.382) </p>

<p>Diabetes 
0.514 </p>

<p>No 
1.000 (references) </p>

<p>Yes 
1.090 (0.842-1.411) </p>

<p>Stroke 
0.067 </p>

<p>No 
1.000 (references) </p>

<p>Yes 
1.458 (0.974-2.182) </p>

<p>House 
0.648 </p>

<p>Other than apartment 
1.000 (references) </p>

<p>Apartment 
1.040 (0.879-1.231) </p>

<p>OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Adjusting for all listed parameters. b) Logistic regression analyses. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. The prevalence of urinary incontinence (UI) and the rate 
of healthcare-seeking behavior for UI. The prevalence of UI and 
the rate of healthcare-seeking behavior for UI both increased 
with age (P trend &lt; 0.001). However, the rate of healthcare-seek-
ing behavior for UI was significantly lower than the prevalence of 
UI (P&lt;0.001). </p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>20.0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>0 20-29 30-39 40-49 50-59 60-69 
70+ 
Age groups (yr) </p>

<p>Prevalence 
Healthcare-seeking </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>4.6 </p>

<p>9.3 
10.8 
10.9 
9.7 </p>

<p>1.2 
0.4 
0.2 
0.3 
0.0 
0.1 </p>



<p>Kwon and Lee • Incontinence in Korea </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.5213/inj.2014.18.1.31 </p>

<p>INJ </p>

<p>cantly associated with UI (Table 3). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study evaluating 
the prevalence of female UI in South Korea. The prevalence of 
UI in this study was 7.9%, and this finding is similar to other 
Asian population studies that reported prevalence rates ranging 
from 4.8% to 13.0% [10,11]. According to the age group, the 
prevalence rates of UI among women over the ages of 40 and 
60 years were 10.1% and 10.3%, respectively. This finding was 
lower than the overall UI prevalence rates reported in Japanese 
women over the age of 40 years (53.7%) [12] and Taiwanese 
women aged 65 years or older (27.7%) [13]. However, it is im-
portant to note that the response rate of the Japanese survey 
was 53% and data were collected by mailed survey. In addition, 
the Taiwanese study only included women over the age of 65 </p>

<p>years, and population sampling was performed by randomly 
sampled town populations. These factors may account for the 
difference in the observed study results. 
Parity, age, and obesity are the three most thoroughly studied 
factors associated with UI [14-16]. In the present study, multi-
variate analysis identified age, BMI, and marriage as significant 
independent risk factors for UI. We were unable to assess parity 
as a risk factor because this information was not available in 
KNHANES IV. However, marital status, which is related to par-
ity, showed a significant association with UI. The number of 
unmarried mothers in Korea is lower than that in western 
countries, and Korean traditions dictate that childbirth should 
follow marriage. Thus, marriage could be interpreted as a proxy 
for parity in this study. The results of this study may be helpful 
in identifying cases of UI when establishing a health policy for 
women with UI in Korea. 
In this study, hypertension, diabetes, and stroke, which were </p>

<p>Table 3. Relationships between incontinence and quality of life assessed by EQ-5D </p>

<p>Variable 
Incontinence </p>

<p>Unadjusted OR 
P-value a) 
Adjusted OR b) 
P-value a) </p>

<p>Mobility 
&lt; 0.001 
0.037 </p>

<p>No problem 
1.000 (references) 
1.000 (references) </p>

<p>Some problem 
1.782 (1.520-2.089) 
1.219 (1.004-1.480) </p>

<p>Severe problem 
2.574 (1.445-4.587) 
1.852 (1.007-3.406) </p>

<p>Self-care 
0.000 
&lt; 0.001 
0.073 </p>

<p>No problem 
1.000 (references) 
1.000 (references) </p>

<p>Some problem 
1.853 (1.432-2.398) 
1.339 (1.012-1.771) </p>

<p>Severe problem 
2.211 (1.083-4.515) 
1.612 (0.738-3.521) </p>

<p>Usual activities 
&lt; 0.001 
0.013 </p>

<p>No problem 
1.000 (references) 
1.000 (references) </p>

<p>Some problem 
1.849 (1.541-2.219) 
1.337 (1.087-1.645) </p>

<p>Severe problem 
2.151 (1.373-3.369) 
1.471 (0.908-2.383) </p>

<p>Pain/discomfort 
&lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>No problem 
1.000 (references) 
1.000 (references) </p>

<p>Some problem 
2.095 (1.793-2.449) 
1.757 (1.487-2.076) </p>

<p>Severe problem 
2.803 (2.157-3.642) 
2.155 (1.612-2.882) </p>

<p>Anxiety/depression 
&lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>No problem 
1.000 (references) 
1.000 (references) </p>

<p>Some problem 
1.762 (1.483-2.094) 
1.537 (1.284-1.839) </p>

<p>Severe problem 
2.303 (1.494-3.552) 
1.843 (1.168-2.907) </p>

<p>EQ-5D, EuroQol-5 dimension; OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Logistic regression analyses. b) Adjusting for age, body mass index, home income, education, hypertension, diabetes, stroke, marital status, and place 
of residence. </p>

<p>www.einj.org 35 </p>

<p>Kwon and Lee • Incontinence in Korea </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.5213/inj.2014.18.1.31 </p>

<p>INJ </p>

<p>thought to be associated with neurogenic bladder dysfunction, 
were not related to UI. We were unable to study the subtypes of 
UI because of the lack of this data. This may explain why hy-
pertension, diabetes, and stroke were not identified as risk fac-
tors in this study. Further follow-up studies are required to elu-
cidate these risk factors. 
Compared to the prevalence rate of UI in Korean women, the 
consultation rate for UI is significantly lower, which is concor-
dant with the pattern observed worldwide. A recent review ar-
ticle reported that only one in four women with UI in the Unit-
ed States and one in three women in Europe had sought medi-
cal care for UI [15,17]. A study of UI in Japanese women showed 
that only 3% had ever consulted doctors or other healthcare 
professionals [12,16]. Chinese data show that the consultation 
rate was 25%. This low consultation rate may be explained by 
the common misconception that UI is not a disease, but a natu-
ral consequence of aging, and that UI is not treatable. 
In this study, UI was associated with an impaired QoL. After 
adjusting for potential confounders, impaired mobility, usual 
activity, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression were still as-
sociated with UI. A cross-sectional study from Turkey reported 
that 87.2% of women indicated that UI has a negative impact 
on their QoL [2]. Another study from the United States report-
ed that the UI group was almost twice as likely to feel depressed 
as the non-UI group, and that UI had a significant negative im-
pact on all aspects of QoL after adjusting for comorbidities and 
demographic differences [18]. The aforementioned results col-
lectively support the finding that UI is associated with an im-
paired QoL, regardless of ethnicity and nationality. 
The success rate of UI treatment has been reported to be very 
high. In up to 70% of women with mild stress UI, pelvic floor 
(Kegel) exercises can result in better control of the bladder when 
coughing, laughing, sneezing, or exercising [19]. In addition, 
long-term follow-up studies of surgical treatment (tension-free 
vaginal tape) for severe stress UI report that the cure rate ranges 
from 77% to 84.7% [20,21]. Furthermore, diverse treatment op-
tions (anticholinergics, alpha-blocker, botulinum toxin A, and 
neuromodulation) are available based on the patient's condition 
and the type of UI (urge, mixed, overflow, and functional/neu-
rogenic UI) [22]. Treatment of UI means improving the patient' s 
QoL [23,24]. However, compared with the prevalence rate of 
UI in Korean women, the consultation rate for UI is significantly 
low. Recently, the Health Insurance Review and Assessment 
Service reported that the number of anti-incontinence surgeries 
have increased from 5,944 cases in 2001 to 44,691 cases in 2006. </p>

<p>Despite this increase in the number of surgeries, the consulta-
tion rate for UI remains low. Therefore, we think that a more ef-
ficient health policy is required for women with UI in Korea. 
The present study had several limitations. First, the cross-
sectional nature of the dataset makes causal inferences prob-
lematic. Second, we cannot elucidate the relationship between 
UI and parity, which is a well-known risk factor for UI. In addi-
tion, we could not study the subtypes of UI, as this information 
was not available. Nevertheless, we think that our study pro-
vides meaningful results, as this is the first study to elucidate the 
prevalence, risk factors, healthcare-seeking behaviors, and QoL 
of women with UI in Korea. 
In conclusion, UI is a common disease and is significantly 
associated with QoL. Compared to the prevalence rate of UI in 
Korean women, the consultation rate for UI is significantly low-
er. Our results suggest the importance of developing preventive 
measures and treatment policies for UI. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was re-
ported. </p>







</text></tei>