<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3863971" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Solution-processed semiconductor quantum dot solar cells offer a path towards both reduced 
fabrication cost and higher efficiency enabled by novel processes such as hot-electron 
extraction and carrier multiplication. Here we use a new class of low-cost, low-toxicity 
CuInSe x S 2 À x quantum dots to demonstrate sensitized solar cells with certified efficiencies 
exceeding 5%. Among other material and device design improvements studied, use of a 
methanol-based polysulfide electrolyte results in a particularly dramatic enhancement in 
photocurrent and reduced series resistance. Despite the high vapour pressure of methanol, 
the solar cells are stable for months under ambient conditions, which is much longer than any 
previously reported quantum dot sensitized solar cell. This study demonstrates the large 
potential of CuInSe x S 2 À x quantum dots as active materials for the realization of low-cost, 
robust and efficient photovoltaics as well as a platform for investigating various advanced 
concepts derived from the unique physics of the nanoscale size regime. </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>olar cells utilizing colloidal quantum dots (QDs) as the 
light-absorbing material have seen rapid advances in recent 
years 1 from the first certified power conversion efficiency 
(PCE) of 3% reported in 2010 (ref. 2) to 47% last year 3 . These 
high-performance certified devices have used PbS QDs, and are 
notable for their low cost of fabrication and ability to efficiently 
harvest the near-infrared portion of the solar spectrum. 
Furthermore, the measurement of external quantum efficiencies 
(EQEs) above 100% using PbSe QDs 4 demonstrates the potential 
of these devices for surpassing the Shockley-Queisser limit 5 by 
employing carrier multiplication. Although recent progress in QD 
photovoltaics (PVs) based on PbX (X ¼ S, Se) QDs is promising, 
major challenges to reaching commercializable efficiencies remain. 
The primary factor limiting performance of these devices is high 
recombination losses in the active layer due to presence of charge 
traps that originate from surface states. This results in short 
diffusion lengths for minority carriers 6 in QD solids and ultimately 
limits the thickness of the active layer to o500 nm (Fig. 1a), which 
is insufficient for complete absorption of incident photons. 
Furthermore, the p-n heterojunction architecture requires 
fine control over carrier doping in order to tune the depletion 
width, which is another outstanding challenge 7-9 . The high 
atomic fraction of toxic lead atoms and the generally poor 
stability of PbX QDs under ambient conditions further complicate 
commercialization of this emerging technology, although PbS QD 
solar cells have been demonstrated with 1,000 h stability under 
continuous illumination in air 2 . 
An alternative device architecture for utilizing QD absorbers is 
the liquid-junction-sensitized solar cell pioneered by O'Regan and 
Grätzel 10,11 . In sensitized PVs, a meso-porous (mp) TiO 2 anode 
decorated with a narrow-gap absorber is contacted by an </p>

<p>electrolyte solution that provides a conductive pathway to a 
metal or semiconductor cathode (Fig. 1b). This architecture 
avoids inefficient QD-to-QD carrier transport by employing 
discrete interfacial charge-transfer steps in which a photo-excited 
electron transfers from the QD to TiO 2 , while the remaining hole 
is reduced by the electrolyte (Fig. 1c). 
Traditionally this device architecture has utilized dye molecules 
as light absorbers/sensitizers 10 . The best dye-sensitized solar cells 
(DSSCs) reach efficiencies in excess of 10%, with a current record 
of 12.3% 12 . However, despite the large promise, widespread 
application of DSSCs is complicated by inherent limitations of the 
dyes themselves, which usually contain low-abundance elements 
such as ruthenium, have limited absorption bandwidth and suffer 
from photo-bleaching and poor long-term chemical stability, 
particularly under strong illumination 13 . 
To circumvent the drawbacks of dyes, several groups have 
explored replacing them with QDs 14-18 . The investigated 
approaches include infusion of pre-synthesized colloidal QDs 
into the mp-TiO 2 (refs 17,19-21) and direct growth of 
semiconductor clusters within the matrix 14-16,22 . This latter 
method was used to achieve the highest reported (yet uncertified) 
efficiency of 5.6% in structures comprising PbS:Hg QDs deposited 
with a successive ionic layer adsorption reaction (SILAR) 23 . These 
devices however were highly unstable and degraded over a period 
of minutes, meaning that accurate characterization of their 
performance was extremely difficult due to transient changes in 
device characteristics. 
In principle, colloidal QD sensitizers can have several 
advantages over SILAR-deposited QDs that arise from the ability 
to synthesize them under optimal conditions. This allows for 
much better control over size, composition 20 , shape and </p>

<p>n-ZnO p-PbS MoO x </p>

<p>&lt; 500 nm </p>

<p>CISeS 
S 2-/S n 
2-Cu x S 
TiO 2 </p>

<p>&gt; 10 μm </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>FTO/TiO 2 /QDs/polysulfide </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>(Drift) </p>

<p>E F (TiO 2 ) </p>

<p>QD CB </p>

<p>E redox </p>

<p>(S 2-/Sn 2-) </p>

<p>V oc </p>

<p>QD VB </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>e </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>(Diffusion) </p>

<p>(ET) </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>(QD reduction) </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>a 
b 
c </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Working principles of colloidal QD solar cells. (a) Schematic of a typical thin-film p-n junction QD PV (PbS QDs are purple circles, the 
contacts are omitted); high recombination losses due to the long paths for minority carriers to reach the electrode ultimately limit the thickness of the 
QD layer. (b) Schematic of the QDSSC architecture (CISeS QDs are red triangles, the contacts are omitted) that avoids QD-to-QD carrier transport 
completely, and benefits from more complete light absorption and a modular design. See Methods and Supplementary Information for the details of device 
design and fabrication. (c) QDSSC photoanode (SEM (scanning electron microscope) cross-sectional image) along with a schematic band structure (VB 
and CB are valence and conduction bands, respectively) and the depiction of various steps of the light conversion process: (1) generation of an excited 
electron (e À )-hole (h þ ) pair by an absorbed solar photon, (2) electron transfer (ET) to TiO 2 , (3) electron drift followed by diffusion within the TiO 2 
anode, (4) hole transfer to (QD reduction by) polysulfides in the electrolyte (not necessarily after steps 2 or 3) and (5) hole collection by (oxidation of) 
the Cu x S electrode (not shown); E F is the Fermi level of the TiO 2 anode and E redox is the electrolyte redox potential. Scale bar, 10 mm. </p>

<p>heterostructuring, and generally results in QDs with improved 
crystallinity and stability. Indeed, we recently reported proof-of-
principle sensitized solar cells utilizing colloidally synthesized 
CuInSe x S 2 À x (CISeS) QDs 24 . This previous work was a synthesis-
focused effort on optimizing QD structural parameters for 
achieving more complete coverage of the solar spectrum, 
enhancing QD surface chemistry for multi-day stability and 
maximizing the loading of QDs into the pores of the TiO 2 matrix. 
In the course of this study, we determined that the optimal QD 
parameters corresponded to the CuInSe x S 2 À x alloy with x ¼ 1.4 
and an averaged QD size of B4.5 nm (in these pyramidal QDs, 
size is the measured length from an apex to the midpoint of the 
opposing edge of the triangular projections observed in TEM 
images). Without exploring the parameter space extensively, we 
also noted that exposing the QDs to Cd-oleate could be beneficial 
to QD-sensitized solar cell (QDSSC) performance. With an 
energy gap (E g ) of B1.3 eV, the optimized CISeS QDs allowed for 
B100% absorption and a maximum external quantum efficiency 
(EQE) of B45% (at 3 eV) and an overall uncertified PCE of 3.5% 
in the best devices. 24 QDSSCs based on CuInS 2 QDs (without Se) 
have also been reported in recent years with uncertified 
efficiencies as high as 4.7% 25-27 ; however, the maximum 
photocurrent achievable for this material is roughly the same as 
for CdSe QDs due to the relatively large bulk band-gap. 
In the present report we reveal a crucial effect of CISeS QD 
surface properties on device performance. Specifically, by utilizing 
inorganic passivation of the QDs with partial cation exchange 
using Zn 2þ or Cd 2þ ions prior to sensitization, we suppress non-
radiative recombination, which otherwise can outcompete fairly 
slow (45 ns) electron transfer into the mp-TiO 2 photoanode. 
Further, we demonstrate the importance of recapping with short 
ligands in order to achieve efficient sensitization via direct 
attachment 28 . In addition, we optimize the electrolyte 
composition and reveal the critical importance of improved 
wetting through methanol addition for achieving high 
performance in these liquid-junction solar cells. We find that in 
addition to improving short-circuit current, tuning electrolyte 
composition allows us to reduce series resistance of the devices 
and thus increase the fill factor (FF). A further improvement in 
FF is obtained via the utilization of a meso-textured, high-surface-
area Cu x S cathode. These coordinated efforts to understand and 
optimize the various stages of the photoconversion process have 
allowed us to achieve a record-long stability of several months 
under ambient conditions, the first-ever certified efficiency of 
5.1% and a champion efficiency of 5.5%, which are record values 
for this emerging class of PV devices and among the highest 
reported for QD PVs 29 . </p>

<p>Results 
Synthesis and surface modification of CISeS QDs. The synthesis 
of colloidal CISeS QDs uses 1-dodecanethiol (DDT) as an effec-
tive yet low-cost solvent, ligand and sulphur precursor; controlled 
amounts of trioctylphosphine selenide (TOP-Se) are added to 
produce an alloy of reduced band-gap 24,30 . This synthetic 
approach results in pyramidally shaped CuInSe x S 2 À x QDs 
(inset in Fig. 2a) with x as high as B1.6 (that is 80% Se anions, 
as measured by inductively coupled plasma optical emission 
spectroscopy (ICP-OES)). Utilizing as-synthesized CISeS QDs 
results in relatively poor PV performance 24 , which is primarily 
due to significant non-radiative losses associated with surface 
traps 30 . To address this issue, following the synthesis of the QDs, 
we treat them with a zinc oleate (Zn-oleate) solution, which 
results in temperature-controllable Zn 2þ exchange with surface 
Cu 1 þ and In 3 þ , cations (Supplementary Fig. S3). This procedure 
leads to a strong reduction in surface-related trap states as </p>

<p>evidenced by an increase in the PL intensity (Fig. 2a) and a 
lengthening of the PL lifetime 31,32 . The suppression of non-
radiative recombination also manifests as increased open-circuit 
voltage (V oc , from 0.33 V for untreated QDs to as high as 0.54 V 
in the case of the optimal treatment with Zn 2þ at 100°C) and 
short-circuit current (J sc , from 2.7-6.0 mA cm À 2 ) in devices 
(Fig. 2b; details can be found in Supplementary Table S2). 
However, as the degree of cation exchange increases, a maximum 
in device performance is quickly reached, and J sc then decreases 
even as the PL efficiency of QDs in solution increases (Fig. 2a). 
We attribute this phenomenon to partial suppression of electron 
transfer to TiO 2 by the increasingly thick Zn-rich surface layer, 
which serves as a barrier due to its significantly higher-lying 
conduction band 32 . This observation suggests that electron 
transfer to TiO 2 is fairly slow, especially after cation exchange 
with Zn 2þ , and is likely characterized by timescales comparable 
to those of exciton recombination in the QDs (tens of 
nanoseconds) 32 . 
In principle, treating the QDs in a colloidal suspension by 
cation exchange should be preferable to the commonly applied 
approach of depositing a thin layer of ZnS over the entire 
sensitized electrode by SILAR, since it enables greater flexibility in 
fabrication and characterization. On the other hand, ZnS 
deposited by SILAR may provide the benefits of inorganic 
passivation but without creating a barrier at the QD/TiO 2 
interface 33 . In a comparison study, when a ZnS SILAR post-
treatment (two monolayers) is applied to non-cation-exchanged 
CISeS QD-sensitized TiO 2 (Fig. 2b, orange curve), the 
enhancement is similar yet slightly less pronounced than the 
colloidal/cation-exchange method. 
While we have observed real performance enhancement using 
cation exchange with Zn 2þ , the tendency of thicker Zn-rich </p>

<p>surface layers to act as barriers to charge extraction is ultimately 
limiting. An isovalent alternative to Zn 2þ is Cd 2þ ; importantly, 
Cd(Se, S) has a lower-lying conduction band than Zn(Se, S) and 
therefore it might present a smaller (if any) barrier to electron 
transfer. We observe that the effect of cadmium oleate (Cd-oleate) 
exposure on CISeS QDs' optical properties is approximately the 
same as with Zn-oleate (Fig. 2a) 24 : absorption remains essentially 
unchanged, while the PL intensities (Fig. 2c) and lifetimes 
dramatically increase. However, analysis of the composition with 
ICP-OES (Supplementary Fig. S3) indicates that Cd-oleate is 
more reactive towards CISeS QDs at low temperature and results 
in a more aggressive exchange of cations. Comparing the 
performance of QDSSCs made from QDs treated with Zn-
oleate (Fig. 2b) and Cd-oleate (Fig. 2d) at various temperatures, 
we find that while Zn-treated QDs (PCE of 1.91%) show a 
significant improvement over untreated QDs (0.38%), Cd 
treatment produces even a greater enhancement in the PV 
performance (3.34%). The best devices incorporated CISeS QDs 
treated at 50°C, which corresponded to the mildest exposure to 
Cd 2þ ions with a resulting overall amount of cadmium in the 
sensitized film of o0.5 atomic %. The extremely low content of 
Cd in these devices significantly reduces concerns of potential 
toxicity relative to the already widely used CdTe thin-film 
solar cells. 
After Cd-treated QDs are recapped with short ligands (chosen 
from those in Fig. 3a), they are incorporated into a mp-TiO 2 
photoanode via soaking in dilute QD-octane or methanol 
solutions. We found that the identity of the ligand had a major 
impact on device performance. We observe that tert-butylamine </p>

<p>(tBA), n-butylamine (nBA) and sec-butylamine (sBA) are equally 
effective at achieving high QD-loading according to optical 
absorption measurements (Fig. 3b). Unlike most QDSSC reports, 
we achieve this high degree of loading (using butylamine) by 
direct attachment without the assistance of a high electric field 
(electrophoretic deposition) 27 or bifunctional linkers (for 
example, MPA) 25 . On the other hand, the use of the native 
ligands (oleylamine and DDT), mercaptoproprionic acid (MPA) 
or pyridine resulted in much poorer loading. Accordingly, we 
found that the choice of the ligand did not affect V oc , but did have 
a significant effect on J sc (Fig. 3d and Supplementary Table S4). 
Typically, improvement in only J sc would indicate that enhanced 
light-harvesting is the primary reason for the benefit of using the 
butylamines, rather than a reduction in recombination losses, 
which would be expected to impact V oc as well. However, 
in liquid-junction cells the absorber band-gap (that is, QD 
band-gap) can be well in excess of the maximum attainable V oc , 
which is determined by the energy difference between the TiO 2 
Fermi level and the redox potential of the electrolyte. In this case, 
the relationship between recombination, open-circuit voltage and 
short-circuit current is not as trivial as with solid-state solar cells, 
and so we can't fully rule out differences in recombination using 
these ligands. In fact, we do observe differences in the absorption-
normalized PL intensity (Fig. 3c) from QDs recapped with these 
ligands in solution (prior to sensitization), which indicates 
differences in non-radiative recombination related to surface 
traps. Therefore, in addition to differences in loading, J sc may also 
be impacted by non-radiative recombination within the QD 
absorbers. At this time we do not have a complete understanding </p>

<p>1.0 
1.1 
1.2 </p>

<p>CISeS QDs 
tBA </p>

<p>nBA 
sBA </p>

<p>MPA 
Pyridine </p>

<p>Normalized PL intensity </p>

<p>Photon energy (eV) </p>

<p>0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Current density (mA cm </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Voltage (V) </p>

<p>tBA 
nBA </p>

<p>sBA 
MPA 
Pyridine </p>

<p>nBA </p>

<p>tBA </p>

<p>sBA </p>

<p>MPA </p>

<p>Pyridine </p>

<p>1.0 
1.5 
2.0 
2.5 
3.0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>a 
b 
c </p>

<p>d 
e </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>tBA 
nBA </p>

<p>sBA 
MPA 
Pyridine </p>

<p>1-T (%) </p>

<p>Photon energy (eV) </p>

<p>0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Current density (mA cm -2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Voltage (V) </p>

<p>tBA 
nBA </p>

<p>nBA 
sBA </p>

<p>sBA 
MPA 
O </p>

<p>OH 
HS </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>NH 2 </p>

<p>NH 2 </p>

<p>NH 2 </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Organic passivation of QDs. (a) Molecular structures of ligands investigated in this work. (b) The absorbed fraction of incident radiation 
(as 1 À T, where T is film transmittance in %) of sensitized films using identical QDs recapped with various ligands. Contributions from absorption/ 
scattering by the glass/FTO/mp-TiO 2 substrate have been subtracted in each case; a scattering layer was not used for these measurements. 
(c) Absorption-normalized PL in solution of as-synthesized CISeS QDs (purple) and cation exchanged (Cd-OA 50°C treatment) after recapping with each 
ligand. (d) Current density versus voltage characteristics for each ligand 5 days after fabrication. (e) Performance of the QDSSCs after 60 days. Two 
devices are shown for the nBA (blue) and sBA (green) cases to demonstrate the reproducibility of the result. tBA is shown to have the highest J sc initially 
and after a period of months. These devices did not have the mp-TiO 2 scattering layer nor a ZnS SILAR coating. The devices fabricated with pyridine-
capped QDs failed after roughly 2 weeks. The photovoltaic performance properties related to d and e can be found in Supplementary Tables S4 and S5. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | of why sBA and nBA show poorer performance than tBA, but we 
note that the lower PL intensity (Fig. 3c) from QDs recapped with 
these isomers may implicate recombination as a factor. 
Furthermore, we find that devices made using QDs recapped 
with nBA show a surprisingly poor stability (blue curves on 
Fig. 3e) compared with sBA and tBA, which could also be related 
to the particular ineffectiveness of nBA at surface-trap 
passivation. 
The overall device performance (Fig. 3d) and longevity 
(Fig. 3e) were optimal with tBA. Relatively high band-edge PL 
quantum yield (QY) from tBA-capped QDs in solution (B20%, 
Supplementary Table S1) suggests that recapping with tBA is also 
effective at passivating surface traps, in addition to improving 
QD-loading and stability. Indeed, our observations confirm what 
others have reported: that effective organic passivation in 
combination with robust inorganic passivation is critical for 
high-performance QD PVs 3,34 . At the same time, the small length 
of the tBA ligand enables efficient electron extraction into TiO 2 
by allowing relatively intimate contact between QDs and 
the TiO 2 surface (Fig. 4a). Full understanding of the 
mechanism of initial attachment requires further study, but 
may be related to QD charging (electrostatic attraction to induced 
charges); however, once contact is made, Van-der-Waals forces 
and insolubility of the QDs in the electrolyte are likely to be the 
primary reasons for their robust and prolonged attachment to 
the mp-TiO 2 . 
As inferred from energy-dispersive X-ray (EDX) spectroscopy 
measurements of photoanode cross-sections (Fig. 4b), the use of 
this ligand results in QD/TiO 2 films with highly uniform loading 
throughout the mp-TiO 2 (Fig. 4c). By comparing QD constitu-
ents (for example, Cu, In, Se, S) to measured meso-porous 
support content (Ti), we estimate that B3% of the solid material 
(by atomic %) in the film is QD material. The fraction of QDs is 
reduced near the top of the film where a scattering layer of 
400 nm TiO 2 particles (presenting a lower surface area for 
attachment 28 ) is added prior to sensitization to improve light 
harvesting, which is consistent with SEM cross-section images 
showing the larger pores in the scattering layer are not filled with 
aggregated QDs. </p>

<p>Investigation of the methanol-based polysulfide electrolyte. 
Following electron transfer from a QD to the TiO 2 (Figs 1c and 
4a), the photogenerated hole is reduced by the electrolyte, which 
also serves as a hole transporting medium. In order to elucidate </p>

<p>the importance of electrolyte parameters, we explored dilution of 
the electrolyte with methanol 26,35 . Zewdu et al. 35 reported a 
synergistic effect of methanol in combination with a ZnS SILAR 
treatment of CdSe/CdS-sensitized TiO 2 , which was preliminarily 
attributed to improved wetting of the photoanode by the 
electrolyte. In our experiments, we observe a significantly 
greater improvement in the PV performance upon addition of 
methanol than previously seen. Specifically, as the aqueous 
polysulfide electrolyte (2 M Na 2 S and 2 M S) is diluted with 
methanol (Fig. 5a), the measurements of current-voltage (J-V) 
characteristics indicate a greatly increased photocurrent and a 
reduced series resistance (R series , determined as the inverse of the 
slope of the J-V curve at the V oc ), which leads to a higher FF. 
Reduced R series is likely due to the lower viscosity of methanol 
(0.54 mPa s) relative to water (0.89 mPa s), enabling faster ionic 
transport (ionic mobility increases with decreasing solvent 
viscosity). The enhancement in the photocurrent however can 
be caused by several effects. In our studies, we have considered 
three possibilities: (1) methanol can potentially act as a sacrificial 
electron donor aiding in the reduction of photogenerated 
holes 26,27 ; (2) it could improve electron injection efficiency by 
lowering the Fermi level of the TiO 2 film 36 and (3) it can lead to 
better contact between the QDs and the electrolyte due to 
improved wetting 35 . 
The first possibility can be excluded based on the prolonged 
stability of our device performance achieved without replenishing 
methanol in the electrolyte, which would be impossible if 
methanol served as a sacrificial donor. Furthermore, we observe 
in a control study that the PL QY from QD-sensitized films 
immersed in water or methanol without electrolyte is more than 
two orders of magnitude lower than that of the same films with 
electrolyte (Supplementary Table S1). Similar observations have 
been made in DSSCs where dye molecules remain oxidized for 
orders of magnitude longer timescales in the absence of a redox 
electrolyte 37,38 . This result suggests that in pure methanol, holes 
are not removed from the QDs, which leads to a build-up of a net 
positive charge in photo-excited QDs and associated activation of 
a fast non-radiative decay channel via Auger recombination of 
charged excitons 39,40 . 
This assessment is confirmed by transient absorption (TA) 
studies of carrier dynamics in QD-sensitized films upon their 
exposure to various solvents (Fig. 5b). In the case of dry 
methanol, the decay is dominated by a fast 20-50 ps component, 
which is consistent with Auger recombination of a positively 
charged exciton (positive trion), a process in which the electron-</p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
6 
8 10 
0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>a 
b 
c </p>

<p>Atomic (%) </p>

<p>Distance (μm) </p>

<p>S 
Cd 
In 
Sn 
Ti 
Cu 
Se </p>

<p>Arb. 
×0.1 </p>

<p>CISeS 
d 112 =3.17Å </p>

<p>TiO 2 
d 101 =3.48Å </p>

<p>e -</p>

<p>FTO </p>

<p>CISeS QDs/TiO 2 </p>

<p>Figure 4 | QD loading. (a) TEM image of a QD/TiO 2 heterojunction showing the intimate contact between them when tBA is used as a ligand. 
Scale bar, 5 nm. (b) SEM cross-sectional image of our champion device. The substrate used was fluorinated tin oxide (FTO)-coated glass. Scale bar, 10 mm. 
(c) EDX spectroscopy line scan of the cross-section showing the elemental composition of the sensitized film. Atomic percentages are of the total 
composition excluding oxygen (not shown) and tin (shown in orange, but arbitrarily scaled), and the titanium atomic percent is scaled down by a factor of 
10 for ease of comparison. </p>

<p>hole recombination energy is transferred to a pre-existing 
hole 39,41 (left inset in Fig. 5b). This suggests that the hole 
remaining in the QD following electron transfer to TiO 2 is not 
reduced by methanol in the absence of electrolyte and still 
remains in the QD when it absorbs the next photon. On the other 
hand, the QD hole is efficiently regenerated in the presence of 
electrolyte: the measured dynamics are nearly identical to those of 
isolated QDs dispersed in solution, which is dominated by 
recombination of neutral excitons (right inset in Fig. 5b). We also 
observe a less pronounced B400 ps decay component in 
methanol that we attribute to surface traps that are effectively 
passivated by the electrolyte. Further, these TA measurements 
conducted on samples exposed to electrolyte also provide a lower 
limit for the characteristic time of electron transfer of 45 ns, 
which is surprisingly long compared with some previous reports 
on photo-excited dynamics at QD-metal oxide interfaces 27,42 . 
However, this long time scale is consistent with our observation 
that various types of QD surface modification lead to correlated 
changes in QD PL emission efficiency and their performance in 
PV devices. These correlations would not have been observed if 
electron transfer was significantly faster than competing 
recombination mechanisms in isolated QDs. 
Next, we analyse the potential effect of methanol on the Fermi 
level of TiO 2 . It is known that methanol can modify TiO 2 surface 
structure 43 or undergo photochemical reactions in the presence of 
a catalyst 44 . Reactions between TiO 2 and methanol could increase 
photocurrent yield if they lead to a lowering of the TiO 2 Fermi 
level (that is, if TiO 2 is oxidized as a result of the reaction), as this 
would make electron injection from QDs even more favourable. 
In order to see the effects of intentional oxidation of a TiO 2 
anode, we use Li þ ions that are known to effectively remove 
electrons from the surface of TiO 2 (ref. 37). This approach has 
been utilized to realize B100% electron injection efficiency in 
CdSe-QDSSCs 36 . When we add Li 2 S to the electrolyte at 50% 
methanol concentration, we do indeed observe an increase in J sc ; 
however, it is accompanied by a reduction in the V oc 
(Supplementary Fig. S6 and Supplementary Table S7). Both of 
these are anticipated results of a lower TiO 2 Fermi level, which in 
addition to increasing J sc should also reduce the energy offset 
between the anode Fermi level and the electrolyte redox potential, 
decreasing V oc . If methanol were also oxidizing TiO 2 , then we 
would expect V oc to be reduced with increasing methanol </p>

<p>content, which is not observed; in fact, increasing amounts of 
methanol, if anything, lead to higher V oc (Fig. 5a). 
Finally, we analyse the third possibility, namely that improved 
wetting of the QD/TiO 2 surface by the methanolic electrolyte 
solution can facilitate hole extraction from the QDs and thus 
improve J sc . The degree of wetting of a solid material by a liquid 
depends on the relative surface tensions of the three joining 
interfaces (that is, g gas-liquid , g gas-solid , g liquid-solid ). As the 
electrolyte solvent changes from water to methanol, only 
the two tensions involving the liquid will be modified. Estimating 
the surface tension of mp-TiO 2 /QDs with various solvents (that 
is, g liquid-solid ) in an actual device is complicated by the high 
surface/volume ratio 45 , the hydrophobicity of the ligand-
passivated QD surfaces within the sensitized film, and by 
dramatic changes in wetting behaviour (TiO 2 becomes 
amphiphilic) under ultra-violet irradiation 46 . However, a 
comparison of the well-established surface tensions between air 
and most solvents (that is, g gas-liquid ), can be instructional in this 
case. The three-fold greater surface tension at a water-gas 
interface (g air-water ¼ 72 mN m À 1 ) than at a methanol-gas 
interface (g air-methanol ¼ 23 mN m À 1 ) means that methanol wets 
most surfaces better than water. In a simple test of placing a 
droplet of both solvents on a mp-TiO 2 film, methanol clearly 
demonstrated a greater tendency to wet the surface 
(Supplementary Fig. S5). As photocurrent relies directly on 
contact between the electrolyte and the QD surface (for hole 
extraction), our observations of increased J sc are consistent with 
improved wetting by the electrolyte. </p>

<p>Meso-textured Cu x S cathode. Another critical element of a 
sensitized solar cell is the cathode, which has a significant effect 
on the overall device performance through its influence on R series 
and thus FF. In our solar cells we employ a Cu x S cathode (Fig. 6), 
which allows us to obtain R series of 10 O Á cm 2 and FF of B0.60 in 
the best devices, among the highest for QDPVs. Our simple 
method for making the cathode is by chemical transformation of 
100-nm thick thermally evaporated Cu (on FTO) by exposure to 
the polysulfide electrolyte. Based on EDX measurements, the 
Cu x S has an x ¼ 1.0 stoichiometry upon fabrication (that is, 
covellite, a p-type metal), but it becomes sulphur enriched (x of 
ca. 0.8) after being used in a device. The observed level of relative 
copper deficiency corresponds to an even higher degree of p-type 
doping, which should greatly improve cathode conductivity. 
Further, after sulphurisation our cathodes develop a meso-
textured structure, characterized by a large surface area (Fig. 6b 
inset), which persists after many months of testing (Supple-
mentary Fig. S4) and facilitates charge collection from the 
electrolyte. Together with improved conductivity, this is likely a 
second major factor in reduced R series and improved performance 
in our devices compared with previously published studies 
typically with Cu 2 S, which is a semiconductor. To better under-
stand the contribution of the cathode and other factors (for 
example, charge-transfer resistance, electrolyte, mp-TiO 2 ) to the 
aggregate series resistance of the device (measured by the inverse 
slope of the J-V curve), impendence spectroscopy may be 
insightful. </p>

<p>QDSSC stability and certification. A common and critical issue 
with QDSSCs is their poor stability resulting from electro-
chemical corrosion of many candidate sensitizers 23,47 . As our 
QDs are synthesized under excess sulphur conditions, we 
expected that our CISeS QDs would be chemically stable in the 
presence of the sulphur-based electrolyte. However, as we added 
more Se to reduce the band-gap of the QDs, they became less 
stable in the electrolyte, probably due to the replacement of Se by </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 
400 
0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>QD/TiO 2 in methanol 
QD/TiO 2 in electrolyte 
QDs in octane </p>

<p>Normalized </p>

<p>−Δα </p>

<p>Delay (ps) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Current density (mA cm -2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Voltage (V) </p>

<p>0% 
25% 
50% 
75% </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>Figure 5 | Dependence of device performance on the electrolyte 
composition. (a) Current density versus voltage characteristics under 
simulated sunlight for QDSSCs with varying amounts of methanol in the 
electrolyte (reducing the polysulfide concentration by dilution). A ZnS 
SILAR coating was not used. A table of the photovoltaic performance 
properties can be found in Supplementary Table S6. (b) QD population 
decay monitored by probing the temporal evolution of the band-edge 
bleach with transient absorption. The traces in the figure correspond to 
isolated QDs dispersed in octane (black square), and QDs attached to the 
TiO 2 matrix exposed to either methanol (red triangle) or electrolyte (blue 
circle). </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms3887 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:2887 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms3887 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>S anions at the surface over time 24 . The chemical incompatibility 
problem is typically addressed in the QDSSCs by the application 
of a thin insulating ZnS layer deposited by SILAR. The partial 
cation exchange (with Cd 2þ or Zn 2þ ) of QDs in our devices 
prior to sensitization (discussed earlier) helps solve the stability 
issue, and allows for stable operation of the devices for 1-2 
months instead of 1-2 days 24 . To further improve the stability, we 
deposit two monolayers of ZnS using SILAR on photoanodes 
after they are sensitized with Cd-treated and tBA-recapped CISeS 
QDs. Following this procedure, the initial performance of a device 
is unchanged. However, the thin layer of ZnS seems to act as a 
good chemical barrier, which complements the existing barrier </p>

<p>due to cation exchange without appreciably suppressing hole 
extraction into the electrolyte (ZnS deposited by SILAR is not 
expected to influence electron extraction, as the QD-TiO 2 close 
contacts are established prior to ZnS application). Devices with 
the ZnS SILAR consistently showed prolonged stability under air 
exposure (Fig. 7a), although it is worth noting that even without 
the ZnS layer, some devices survived for up to 2 months (Fig. 3e). 
This is in drastic contrast to previously reported high-
performance QDSSCs that were stable for just a few minutes 23 . 
The eventual catastrophic failure of the devices with a ZnS SILAR 
coating was associated with electrode delamination (for example, 
Cu x S would peel off the substrate), which can be addressed by 
establishing better adhesion between layers during electrode 
fabrication. In order to better elucidate the true long-term 
stability of these devices, extended light-soaking tests should be 
conducted. Studies of the effect of light-soaking for 30 h indicate 
that the performance of our devices improves over the first 
B15 min, which we attribute to improved ionic transport 
due to heating of the electrolyte, and then stays unchanged 
once the device temperature stabilizes under the light source 
(Supplementary Fig. S8). 
The stability of our devices enabled us to have two of them 
(one with and one without a ZnS SILAR coating) certified by the 
PV Characterization Team at the National Renewable Energy 
Laboratory (NREL) 1 week after fabrication. Both devices were 
certified at 5.1% and the details of the certified performance can 
be found in Fig. 7a (device without ZnS) and in the 
Supplementary Fig. S2 (device with ZnS). As far as we know, 
these are the only certified performances reported for any </p>

<p>FTO </p>

<p>Glass </p>

<p>Cu x S </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>Figure 6 | Cu x S cathode. (a) SEM image of a cross-section of a fresh glass/ 
FTO/Cu x S cathode where x ¼ 1.0 according to EDX analysis. Scale bar, 1 mm. 
(b) SEM image from the top-down perspective of the cathode. Scale bar, 
10 mm. Higher magnification inset shows the flower-like structures with 
high surface area. Scale bar, 1 mm. </p>

<p>0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Current density (mA cm </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Voltage (V) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>= 5.51% </p>

<p>V oc = 0.56 V 
J sc = 16.8 mA cm </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>FF = 0.59 
R series = 10 Ω cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Current density (mA cm -2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Voltage (V) </p>

<p>3 days </p>

<p>7 days (NREL) </p>

<p>9 days </p>

<p>45 days </p>

<p>59 days </p>

<p>71 days </p>

<p>Temperature = 25.0 ± 2 °C </p>

<p>Device area = 0.2200 cm 2 
Zero voltage bias 
Light bias = 1.00 mA 
KG5-filtered bias </p>

<p>Efficiency = 5.13% </p>

<p>V oc = 0.5402 V </p>

<p>I sc = 3.9047 mA </p>

<p>J sc = 17.565 mA cm </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>Fill factor = 54.10% </p>

<p>I max = 3.2326 mA </p>

<p>V max = 0.3530 V </p>

<p>P max = 1.1410 mW </p>

<p>Spectrum: ASTM G173 global </p>

<p>Device temperature: 30.0 ± 5.0 °C </p>

<p>Device area: 0.2223 cm 2 </p>

<p>Irradiance: 1,000.0 W m -2 </p>

<p>0 
300 400 500 600 700 800 </p>

<p>Wavelength (nm) </p>

<p>900 1,000 1,100 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 
Quantum efficiency (%) </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>0 
-0.1 
0.0 
0.1 
0.2 
0.3 
0.4 </p>

<p>Voltage (V) </p>

<p>0.5 
0.6 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>3 
Current (mA) </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>X25 IV System 
PV Performance Characterization Team </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>c 
d </p>

<p>Figure 7 | Certified PV performance and stability. (a) Current density versus voltage characteristics of a QDSSC certified by NREL. (b) EQE spectra 
for the device measured at NREL. (c) Performance of our champion device (different from the one in a and b) over time, including the certification data from 
NREL. The device was tested further (for example, day 1, day 4, day 6, and so on), but these measurements are not included in for plot clarity. 
(d) Sequential measurements of our champion device at 71 days under constant illumination for B15 min. Each measurement takes 90 s, there was a 1 min 
delay between J-V measurements. The photovoltaic performance properties related to c and d can be found in Supplementary Tables S8 and S9. </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms3887 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:2887 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms3887 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>QDSSC, which is important for a variety of reasons (see 
Supplementary Discussion). We continued testing the certified 
device, which had a ZnS SILAR coating periodically, with storage 
under ambient but dark conditions (Fig. 7c). This device survived 
71 days, and maintained an efficiency of 5.5% through the final 
measurement using our in-house solar simulator under contin-
uous illumination (Fig. 7d and Supplementary Table S9), which is 
the highest reported for any colloidal (that is, non-SILAR) 
QDSSC. Interestingly, the NREL-certified photocurrent was 
B10% (relative) higher in this device than what we measured 
with our solar simulator, indicating that our 5.5% record 
measurement may be slightly underestimating the performance. 
Compared with a maximum possible EQE of B80% (considering 
absorption and reflection losses due to the fluorinated tin oxide 
on glass electrode), our best devices achieve a peak EQE of B60% 
at B3.0 eV, although it is considerably lower for lower-energy 
photons (Fig. 7b). The relatively low and non-flat EQE of our 
devices suggests that there is significant room for improvement of 
J sc by enhancing absorption (for example, via improved QD-
loading) and/or by optimizing internal charge collection efficien-
cies (for example, via faster charge extraction). Although we 
observe relatively high QD-loading by simply soaking the 
electrode in a dilute solution of (recapped) QDs, loading might 
be further improved by the use of electrophoretic deposition 27,48 
or by attachment using alternative bifunctional linkers 25,49 . </p>

<p>Discussion 
In summary, we have shown that QDSSCs can exhibit both high 
performance and high stability using low-toxicity materials and 
low-cost fabrication methods. We have identified optimal 
conditions for the sensitization of mp-TiO 2 with CISeS QDs 
using a very mild cation exchange with Zn 2þ or Cd 2þ followed 
by washing/recapping with tBA. Addition of a ZnS layer by 
SILAR does not lead to enhanced efficiency but further improves 
device stability. Adding methanol to the electrolyte significantly 
enhances the device performance by increasing photocurrent and 
lowering series resistance. We demonstrated a nanostructured 
Cu x S (where xo1.0) cathode can be made by a simple low-cost 
method, and acts as an extremely effective reducing catalyst for 
the polysulfide electrolyte and enabled us to achieve series 
resistances on par with the best DSSCs that use platinum. 
Recognizing the challenges in accurately characterizing PVs, and 
thus the difficulties in comparing between various published 
results, we report the first certified performance of a QDSSC at 
5.1% efficiency. Our champion efficiency approaches the highest 
reported values for any type of QD solar cells, yet our devices do 
not degrade for months even if stored in air: this is orders of 
magnitude longer than in any previous report on QD PVs. Given 
the fairly low EQEs even in our record devices, we expect that 
with further optimization, the performance of these novel PV 
devices can be enhanced considerably, making them competitive 
with well-established dye-sensitized solar cells. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Synthesis of CISeS QDs. CISeS QDs were synthesized via a modification of the Li 
et al. 30 method 24 . Typically, 1 mmol of copper iodide and 1 mmol of indium acetate 
are dissolved in 5 ml of 1-dodecanethiol and 1 ml of oleylamine, and the mixture is 
degassed under vacuum in a 50 ml flask at 100°C for 30 min. The solution was 
heated to 130°C until it became yellow and transparent, and then degassed again 
for 30 min at 100°C. The flask is then slowly heated to a growth temperature of 
230°C, but at a temperature of 220°C, slow injection of 6 mmol of 2 M TOP-Se 
(B12 ml h À 1 ) begins. After 30 min the reaction was cooled and the QDs were 
cleaned by dissolving in chloroform and precipitation with methanol. The 
precipitated QDs were collected by centrifugation and the supernatant was 
discarded. The QDs were stored in 5 ml of octane or ODE following cleaning. The 
synthesis typically results 490% chemical yield of QDs (relative to the copper and 
indium precursors). </p>

<p>Cation exchange and recapping of QDs. For cation exchange with Cd 2þ or 
Zn 2þ , a stock solution of 0.5 M cadmium or zinc oleate was prepared with 3:1 
oleic acid:Cd/Zn dissolved in ODE. 4 ml of the cleaned QDs in ODE solution 
(B50 mg ml À 1 ) were added to 4 ml of 0.5 M Cd or Zn-oleate solution and the 
temperature was set to 50-150°C for 10 min depending on the desired degree of 
cation exchange. Following cation exchange, the reaction solution was dissolved in 
chloroform, and then acetone was added to precipitate the QDs. The precipitated 
QDs were collected by centrifugation, and then dissolved in chloroform. </p>

<p>Ligand exchange of QDs. Following cation exchange and purification of QDs, 
methanol was added to precipitate the QDs from chloroform. Precipitated 
QDs were collected by centrifugation and the supernatant was discarded. 
For tBA, nBA, sBA and pyridine recapping, the ligand was used as a solvent to 
dissolve the precipitated QDs with sonication used to speed up dissolution and 
recapping. Then, methanol was added to precipitate the QDs, which were collected 
by centrifugation and the supernatant was discarded. The ligand was again used as 
a solvent to dissolve the precipitated QDs and these solutions were sonicated for a 
few minutes at room temperature. Methanol was added to precipitate the QDs, 
which were collected by centrifugation. The above process was optimized to give 
the highest QD-loading in the mp-TiO 2 film for tBA-capped QDs. The optimal 
conditions may be different for the other ligands. Longer exposure of the QDs 
to the new ligands or heating during exposure might give more complete 
recapping, but resulted in poorer loading, probably due to partial aggregation 
of QDs during recapping. The recapped QDs were dissolved in octane 
(B0.05 g ml À 1 ), and the solution was centrifuged to remove large aggregates 
that occasionally formed during recapping. Any precipitate was discarded. 
The QD-octane supernatant was diluted with octane to an optical density of 
B0.2 (B0.01 g ml À 1 ) at the 1S absorption peak (typically 850 nm), and used to 
prepare QD-sensitized mp-TiO 2 films. 
For MPA recapping, the QDs were recapped by dissolving precipitated QDs in a 
mixture of 1:1 chloroform and MPA, then precipitating by adding methanol, and 
centrifuged. The supernatant was discarded, and the QDs were dissolved in the 
same total volume of MPA and methanol (1:1). The solution was sonicated for a 
few minutes. Chloroform was added to precipitate the MPA-capped QDs, and the 
QDs were collected by centrifugation. The MPA-capped QDs were dissolved in 
methanol (B0.05-0.1 g ml À 1 ), and the solution was centrifuged to remove 
aggregates that formed during recapping and to remove partially recapped QDs. 
The QD-methanol supernatant was diluted with methanol to an absorbance of 
about 0.2 (B0.01 g ml À 1 ) at the 1S absorption peak (typically 850 nm), and used to 
prepare QD-sensitized mp-TiO 2 films. </p>

<p>Fabrication of QDSSCs. Scattering and non-scattering mp-TiO 2 films are pre-
pared by automated, iterative screen-printing (LS-150, New Long Seimitu Kogyo 
Co.) of TiO 2 pastes containing B20 nm and B400 nm TiO 2 particles, respectively, 
on fluorinated tin oxide (FTO)-coated glass. A dense blocking layer of TiO 2 is not 
used. The a-terpineol based pastes are fired at 500°C for 1 h under air. The 8 mm 
(or 13 mm with the scattering layer) thick mp-TiO 2 films are sensitized by soaking 
in dilute QD-octane solutions for 36 h. The films were then rinsed with octane 
(or methanol for MPA-capped QDs) to remove unattached QDs. The cathode is 
fabricated by thermally evaporating 100 nm of Cu onto a FTO-coated glass sub-
strate, and subsequent immersion in an aqueous polysulfide electrolyte (aqueous 
1 M Na 2 S plus 1 M S) for 15 min to form Cu x S/FTO. The device is completed by 
sandwiching the electrodes around a 40-50 mm Surlyn spacer (DuPont) and sealing 
by heating the polymer frame. Unless otherwise noted, the devices are filled with 
the polysulfide electrolyte composed of 1 M Na 2 S and 1 M S in methanol and water 
(1:1). For champion devices, silver paint and Cu wires was added to the contacts. 
The device active area is defined by a 0.47 cm by 0.47 cm (that is, 0.2209 cm 2 ) black 
metal aperture, which is slightly smaller than the mp-TiO 2 area. The mp-TiO 2 
scattering layer was only used for champion devices that were certified. As our 
device active area is relatively large we do not see significant device to device 
variations. However, we fabricated two devices for each case to confirm that any 
trends we observe are real. Duplicates of all devices were fabricated and tested for 
consistency and if the performance varied by 45% we repeated the study. </p>

<p>Transmission electron microscopy. TEM samples were prepared from a dilute 
solution of NCs in chloroform drop-cast onto Cu grids (obtained from Ted Pella) 
with a thin carbon film on a holey carbon support. TEM analysis was carried out 
with a JEOL 2010 TEM operating at 200 kV. </p>

<p>Scanning electron microscopy and X-ray dispersive spectroscopy. SEM sam-
ples were prepared by breaking a QDSSC anode or cathode in half. The SEM used a 
Quanta 400 field emission gun made by FEI Company. The 20 kV electron beam 
was scanned across the cross-section, and then the energy and the count of X-rays 
were measured. Elemental analysis was conducted using <rs type="software">Genesis EDX</rs> software. </p>

<p>Optical absorption and photoluminescence spectroscopy. All optical mea-
surements of QDs in solution were performed in either chloroform or octane using 
a quartz cuvette. UV-vis absorption spectra were obtained with Agilent 8453 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms3887 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:2887 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms3887 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>photodiode array spectrometer. PL measurements were performed using home-
build spectrofluorimeter consisting or 808 nm excitation diode laser, a liquid 
nitrogen-cooled InSb detector and a grating monochromator. The excitation beam 
was mechanically chopped at 3 kHz and the signal was measured using a lock-in 
amplifier. For PL quantum yield (QY) measurements, optically dilute samples were 
magnetically stirred and the QY values were measured using relative technique by 
comparing integrated PL intensities to an IR-26 dye standard. The spectra were 
corrected for the wavelength-dependence sensitivity of the system. </p>

<p>Solar cell characterization. A class ABA solar simulator (AM 1.5 G), built by PV 
Measurements, calibrated using a Newport-certified single crystal Si solar cell, was 
used to irradiate the QDSSCs during I-V measurement (in-house). The voltage was 
swept from À 0.1 to 0.6 V at 0.01 V per step with a 1 s delay-time prior to mea-
surement and 200 ms collection time at each point. A square black mask 
(0.2209 cm 2 ) was attached to the solar cells to precisely define the active area of the 
device. An additional black cardboard mask (B5 cm by 5 cm outer edges) was 
placed on top of the contacted device (masking area outside the 0.2209 cm 2 mask) 
immediately prior to current-voltage measurement to prevent scattering of light 
into the device by the contacting alligator clips. For continuous illumination 
testing, devices were shorted in between measurements. </p>



<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>H.M., N.S.M., J.M.P. and V.I.K. acknowledge the support of the Center for Advanced 
Solar Photophysics, an Energy Frontier Research Center (EFRC) funded by the US 
Department of Energy (DOE), Office of Science, Office of Basic Energy Sciences. N.F. was 
supported by Sharp Corporation under the Sharp-Los Alamos National Laboratory </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms3887 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:2887 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms3887 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>CRADA LA11C10656 PTS-001. The simulated sunlight current-voltage, SEM and EDX 
measurements were performed at the Center for Integrated Nanotechnologies, an Office 
of Science User Facility operated for the DOE Office of Science. We thank P.E. Heil for 
insightful discussions on reducing contact resistances. We thank A. Koposov for 
assistance with characterization of devices under continuous illumination. We thank 
K. Emery, P. Ciszek and the rest of the PV Characterization Team at NREL for 
performing the certifications. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>H.M. and N.F. designed this study and analysed the experimental results. H.M. syn-
thesized and modified the surfaces of the QDs. N.F. fabricated the QDSSCs. H.M. and 
N.F. characterized the QDSSCs. N.S.M. measured the PL, calculated the QY and 
measured the TA. J.M.P. and V.I.K. directed this study and provided guidance. H.M. 
and V.I.K. wrote the manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
naturecommunications </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Reprints and permission information is available online at http://npg.nature.com/ 
reprintsandpermissions/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: McDaniel, H. et al. An integrated approach to realizing high-
performance liquid-junction quantum dot sensitized solar cells. Nat. Commun. 4:2887 
doi: 10.1038/ncomms3887 (2013). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of 
this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms3887 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 4:2887 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms3887 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

</text></tei>