<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3994298" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Acupuncture is the process of stimulating skin regions called meridians or acupoints and has been 
used to treat pain-related symptoms. However, the pain-relieving effects of acupuncture may be 
different depending on acupoints. In the present study, the effects of acupuncture on behavioral 
responses and c-Fos expression were evaluated using a formalin test in male Sprague-Dawley rats 
in order to clarify the analgesic effects of three different acupoints. Each rat received manual 
acupuncture at the ST36 (Zusanli), SP9 (Yinlingquan) or BL60 (Kunlun) acupoint before formalin 
injection. Flinching and licking behaviors were counted by two blinded investigators. Fos-like 
immunoreactivity was examined by immunohistochemistry in the rat spinal cord. Manual acupuncture 
treatment at BL60 acupoint showed significant inhibition in flinching behavior but not in licking. 
Manual acupuncture at ST36 or SP9 tended to inhibit flinching and licking behaviors but the effects 
were not statistically significant. The acupuncture at ST36, SP9, or BL60 reduced c-Fos expression 
as compared with the control group. These results suggest that acupuncture especially at the BL60 
acupoint is more effective in relieving inflammatory pain than other acupoints. </p>

<p>Acupuncture, which has a 3,000-year-old history, is the 
process of stimulating skin regions called meridians or acu-
points [1] and has been used to treat pain-related symptoms 
caused by diseases such as rheumatic arthritis and osteo-
arthritis [2,3]. Although acupuncture was originated from 
Oriental countries, the pain-relieving effect of acupuncture 
stimulation has been widely recognized. As a result, acu-
puncture became one of the complementary and alternative 
medicinal treatments in even Western countries [4-7]. 
Acupuncture has also been suggested to be effective in re-
lieving inflammatory pain. 
ST36 (Zusanli) and SP9 (Yinlingquan) acupoints have 
been tried for pain-relieving effects of acupuncture stim-
ulation [8-15]. For example, Oh et al. [13] reported that 
manual acupuncture or electroacupuncture at ST36 and </p>

<p>SP9 relieves arthritic pain in rats. Cha et al. [8,9] observed 
that electroacupuncture at ST36 and SP9 relieves neuro-
pathic pain in rats. According to Shou et al. [14], electro-
acupuncture at ST36 and BL60 (Kunlun) inhibited thermal 
hyperalgesia in adjuvant arthritis model of rats. Our pre-
vious study [10] reported that electroacupuncture at BL60 
relieved formalin-induced pain in rats. 
However, the effects of manual acupuncture may be dif-
ferent from those of electroacupuncture. Furthermore, acu-
puncture stimulation at different acupoints may produce 
different pain-relieving effects. 
A variety of chemical irritants, such as formalin, carra-
geenan, and complete Freund's adjuvant (CFA), has been 
widely used in inflammatory pain studies. The formal-
in-induced pain model has more advantages than other 
chemicals because it is a better method for visually verify-
ing pain behaviors [16]. Subcutaneously injected formalin 
produces moderate and continuous pain generated by af-
fected tissue [17], while not requiring anesthesia [18]. 
Formalin-induced pain produces biphasic behavioral re-
sponses that last for approximately an hour, including 
flinching, licking, biting, and shaking. The early phase 
starts immediately after the injection of formalin and de-
creases gradually; then the late phase begins with increase 
in pain again after approximately ten minutes [16]. The 
early phase in the biphasic responses is likely caused by </p>



<p>KH Chang, et al </p>

<p>Fig. 1. A photograph indicating ST36 (Zusanli), SP9 (Yinlingquan), 
and BL60 (Kunlun) acupoints (see text for exact location of each 
acupoint). </p>

<p>direct tissue damage, while the late phase is due to periph-
eral inflammation and central sensitization [19]. In other 
words, the early and late phases have distinctive attributes, 
which allow the formalin-injected pain model to be one of 
the most effective methods for identifying the mechanism 
of pain. 
c-fos, a gene which can be immediately activated in neu-
rons following neural stimulation [20-22], has been widely 
used as an efficient way to measure pain and analgesia 
through the immunohistochemical method [23,24]. The ex-
pression of c-Fos can be detected in the central nervous sys-
tem when imposed by pain stimuli and has been broadly 
accepted as an indicator to reflect the intensity of pain. 
c-Fos expression, which occurs immediately after the noci-
ceptive stimulation, corresponds with the distribution of 
the nociceptive neurons which are identified electrophy-
siologically in the laminae I, II, V, and VI of the spinal 
dorsal horn [25]. In relation to acupuncture analgesia, c-Fos 
expression in the spinal dorsal horn may be different follow-
ing acupuncture stimulation depending on stimulated 
acupoints. 
Therefore, the present study was conducted to compare 
the pain-relieving effects produced by acupuncture stim-
ulation at three different acupoints. By using the formal-
in-induced pain model, we administered manual acu-
puncture at the ST36, SP9, and BL60 acupoints and ob-
served behavioral responses and c-Fos expressions. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>Adult male Sprague-Dawley rats (200∼250 g) were used. 
Animals were housed in plastic cages with soft bedding on 
a 12 h∼12 h light-dark cycle (light cycle: 08:00∼20:00) and 
at a constant temperature (22±2 o C) and humidity (50±10%). 
All animal experiments were approved by the Institutional 
Animal Care and Use Committee of Yonsei University 
Health System. </p>

<p>Experimental groups </p>

<p>The experiment was designed for five groups: a) formalin 
injection only, b) formalin injection following manual acu-
puncture on the ST36 acupoint (ST36-For), c) formalin in-
jection following manual acupuncture on the SP9 acupoint 
(SP9-For), d) formalin injection following manual acu-
puncture on the BL60 acupoint (BL60-For), and e) formalin 
injection following manual acupuncture on a non-acupoint 
(NA-For). In the formalin-injection-only group, inhalation 
anesthesia was administered with the same duration as the 
other groups under the same conditions. </p>

<p>Acupuncture needle and manual acupuncture </p>

<p>For manual acupuncture stimulation, we used stainless-
steel needles (0.3 mm in diameter and 30 mm in length, 
Dongbang Acupuncture Needle Factory, Chungcheong, 
Korea) [9]. Fig. 1 shows a photograph indicating ST36, SP9 
and BL60 acupoints. The ST36 acupoint is located between 
the tibia and fibula at approximately 5 mm lateral and 5 
mm lower to the anterior tubercle of the tibia [15]. The SP9 
acupoint is located in a depression between the posterior 
border of the tibia and the gastrocnemius muscle near the </p>

<p>knee joint or the inferior border of the medial condyle of 
the tibia [9]. The BL60 acupoint is located at the ankle joint 
level and between the external malleolus and tendon [26]. 
A lipid tissue found along the border of the body's trunk 
at the thigh on the ipsilateral side was selected as our 
non-acupoint [9]. 
Manual acupuncture was pre-treated onto the acupoint 
ipsilateral to formalin injection along with inhalation anes-
thesia of 2% enflurane (95% O2 and 5% CO2) [9]. A stain-
less-steel needle (0.3 mm in diameter) was inserted into 
the appropriate acupoint by twirling two times clockwise 
and counter-clockwise in each second. Such twirling con-
tinued for 1 min and paused for 9 min for 4 times which 
took a total of 40 min [27]. During the last 9 min, inhalation 
anesthesia was paused to recover the rats from anesthesia. 
ST36, SP9 and non-acupoint insertion was at a depth of 
4∼5 mm, while the BL60 depth insertion was 2∼3 mm. </p>

<p>Behavioral test </p>

<p>The rats were placed in an acrylic observation chamber 
(46×26×20 cm). A mirror was positioned underneath the 
chamber and was set at a 45 
o angle to secure a clear vision 
of the animal's paw. For animals in the completely awak-
ened experimental condition, 50μl of 5% diluted formalin 
was injected subcutaneously into the plantar surface of the 
left hindpaw using a 29-gauge needle. After the injection, 
the animals were placed back into the chamber for 60 min 
for video recording. The pain behaviors of the rats were 
analyzed by counting the flinching frequency and licking 
time of formalin-injected paws (the number of flinches and 
the duration of licking time as 5 min passes) throughout 
the recording time. After the video-recording, the rats were 
immediately subjected to c-Fos immunostaining. </p>

<p>c-Fos immuno-staining </p>

<p>After the behavioral test, the experimental animals were 
anesthetized with 25% urethane (1.25 g/kg i.p.) and per-
fused transcardially with 0.9% saline followed by 4% paraf-
ormaldehyde (in a 0.1-M phosphate buffer, pH 7.2). A seg-
ment of the spinal cord from L4 to L5 was post-fixated and 
then was placed into 30% sucrose overnight. Afterwards, 
10∼12μm frozen sections were cut in a cryostat (HM500, 
Microm, Walldorf, Germany). The sections were treated for 
30 min with 1% H2O2 in 30% methanol and incubated for 
30 min in a blocking solution (3% normal goat serum (NGS), 
1% bovine serum albumin (BSA) and 0.3% Triton-X). The 
primary antibody (c-Fos anti-rabbit polyclonal IgG, 1：250, </p>

<p>Acupuncture at Different Acupoints </p>



<p>Fig. 2. Comparison of flinching number between groups. The 
formalin-induced paw flinching number was divided into two 
phases (early phase, 0∼10 min; late phase, 10∼60 min). Experi-
mental groups were classified as follows: formalin-only (formalin-
injection only); ST36-For (manual acupuncture treatment at ST36 
before formalin injection); SP9-For (manual acupuncture treatment 
at SP9 before formalin injection); BL60-For (manual acupuncture 
treatment at BL60 before formalin injection); NA-For (manual 
acupuncture treatment at a non-acupoint before formalin injection). 
In the early phase, there was no marked change between any 
groups. In the late phase, however, the BL60-For group had a signi-
ficantly suppressed paw-flinching number induced by the intra-
plantar formalin injection. Each bar represents the group mean± 
SEM (*p＜0.05, one-way ANOVA followed by Dunnett's post-hoc 
multiple comparison). </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Comparison of licking time between different groups. 
Formalin-induced paw licking time was divided into two phases 
(early phase: 0∼10 min; late phase: 10∼60 min). Experimental 
groups were classified as follows: formalin-only (formalin-injection-
only group); ST36-For (manual acupuncture treatment at ST36 
before formalin injection); SP9-For (manual acupuncture treatment 
at SP9 before formalin injection); BL60-For (manual acupuncture 
treatment at BL60 before formalin injection); NA-For (manual 
acupuncture treatment at a non-acupoint before formalin injection). 
In both phases, there was no significant difference between any 
group. In the late phase, four acupoint groups (ST36-For; SP9-For; 
BL60-For; NA-For) that received manual acupuncture before 
formalin injection tended to have decreased paw-licking times 
compared with the Formalin-only group, but there was no 
significant difference between the four acupoint groups (p＞0.05, 
one-way ANOVA followed by Dunnett's post-hoc multiple 
comparison). Each bar represents the group mean±SEM. </p>

<p>Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Cruz, CA, US) was ap-
plied at 4 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C overnight. After being washed in PBS, sections 
were incubated with biotinylated secondary antibody 
(biotinylated anti-rabbit IgG, 1：200, Vector, Burlingame, 
CA, US) for two hr, followed by treatment using the ABC 
kit (Vector, Burlingame, CA, US) for 1 hr. The c-Fos-pos-
itive neurons were visualized using 3,3'-diaminobenzidine 
(DAB, Sigma Chemical Co., St. Louis, MO, US). 
Each section in the L4-5 segment of the spinal cord in 
each experimental animal was divided by laminae I-II and 
laminae III-VI regions according to the cytoarchitecture in 
the spinal cord. The number of c-Fos-positive neurons was 
automatically detected and counted using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">MetaMorph</rs> 
software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">Ver. 4.6</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Universal Imaging</rs>, Downingtown, PA, 
US) under ten magnifications through a microscope (Olym-
pus BX51 microscope, Tokyo, Japan) mounted with a CCD 
camera (Cool SNAP, Photometrics, Tucson, AZ, US). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>All data were assessed using the <rs type="software">Statistical Package for 
the Social Sciences</rs> (SPSS) 15.0 program (SPSS Ver. 15.0, 
SPSS Inc, Chicago, IL, US) and were presented as mean± 
S.E.M. Differences between either the behavioral test or the 
counting of c-Fos-positive neurons were analyzed using a 
one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Dunnett's 
post-hoc pair wise comparisons. A p-value less than 0.05 
was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Behavioral test </p>

<p>The effects of manual acupuncture stimulation at differ-
ent acupoints on flinching behavior are presented in Fig. </p>

<p>2. Flinching behavior in the early phase (0∼10 min) 
showed frequencies of 49.97±8.16, 44.94±6.42, 40.29±6.36, 
35.46±4.39, and 53.79±8.41 for the formalin-only group 
(n=14), the ST36-For group (n=14), the SP9-For group 
(n=16), the BL60-For group (n=14), and the NA-For group 
(n=15), respectively. No statistical significance was ob-
served in the behavioral responses of the early phase be-
tween the formalin-only group and the other manual-acu-
puncture groups (F4,67=1.132, p＞0.05). The flinching re-
sponses in the late phase (10∼60 min) showed frequencies 
of 307.33±30.56 (formalin-only group), 262.16±31.41 (ST36-
For group), 265.17±36.19 (SP9-For group), 178.38±24.21 
(BL60-For group), and 278.36±43.29 (NA-For group), 
respectively. In the between groups, the results of our 
ANOVA-based analysis were significant (F4,67=1.876, p 
＜0.05); post-hoc analysis showed that the behavioral re-
sponse significantly decreased in the BL60-For group 
(178.38±24.21) compared to that of the formalin-only group 
(307.33±30.56) (p＜0.05, one-way ANOVA followed by 
Dunnett's post-hoc multiple comparison) (Fig. 2). 
Fig. 3 shows the effects of manual acupuncture stim-
ulation at different acupoints on licking behavior. The lick-
ing response of pain behavior in the early phase (0∼10 min) 
lasted for 32.81±6.01 (Formalin-only group), 39.52±10.02 
(ST36-For group) 39.99±7.48 (SP9-For group), 32.65±7.82 
(BL60-For group), and 52.69±5.05 (NA-For group) seconds. 
The late phase (10∼60 min) was sustained for 412.64± 
45.52 (Formalin-only group), 346.36±44.33 (ST36-For group), 
336.76±39.91 (SP9-For group), 347.50±40.28 (BL60-For 
group), and 360.15±43.67 (NA-For group) seconds. No stat-
istical significance was found between the formalin-only 
group and the rest of the manual-acupuncture groups (early 
phase; F4,65=1.789, p＞0.05, late phase; F4,65=0.260, p＞0.05, 
one-way ANOVA) (Fig. 3). </p>



<p>KH Chang, et al </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Representative photographs 
of c-Fos-positive neurons in the 
dorsal horn of the spinal cord from 
different groups. (A) Formalin-injec-
tion-only group (Formalin-only); (B) 
Manual acupuncture treatment at 
ST36 before formalin injection (ST36-
For); (C) Manual acupuncture treat-
ment at SP9 before formalin injec-
tion (SP9-For); (D) Manual acupunc-
ture treatment at BL60 before for-
malin injection (BL60-For); (E) Ma-
nual acupuncture treatment at a 
non-acupoint before formalin inject-
ion (NA-For). (F) Normal intact group. 
Compared to the formalin-only group, 
there were distinguished decreases 
of c-Fos-positive neurons in the acu-
puncture groups on the ipsilateral 
side to formalin injection. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Number of c-Fos-positive neurons at different groups in 
laminae I-II and laminae III-VI on the L4 and L5 segments of the 
spinal cord ipsilateral to the site of formalin injection. Experi-
mental groups were classified as follows: normal (no treatment 
group); formalin-only (formalin-injection-only group); ST36-For 
(manual acupuncture treatment at ST36 before formalin injection); 
SP9-For (manual acupuncture treatment at SP9 before formalin 
injection); BL60-For (manual acupuncture treatment at BL60 
before formalin injection); and NA-For (manual acupuncture treat-
ment at a non-acupoint before formalin injection). ST36, SP9, BL60, 
and non-acupoint groups showed significantly decreased numbers 
of c-Fos-positive neurons in laminae I-II. The BL60 group in 
particular had significantly reduced c-Fos-positive neurons in 
laminae III-VI. The total number of c-Fos-positive neurons from 
laminae I to VI showed significantly inhibited c-Fos immunoreact-
ivity in the ST36, SP9 and BL60 groups. Each bar represents the 
group mean±SEM (*p＜0.05, **p＜0.01 for comparison between the 
normal group and all other groups, one-way ANOVA followed by 
Dunnett's post-hoc multiple comparison. 
# p＜0.05, 
## p＜0.01 for 
comparison between the formalin-only group and the ST36-For, 
SP9-For, BL60-For, and NA-For groups, one-way ANOVA followed 
by Dunnett's post-hoc multiple comparison). </p>

<p>c-Fos immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>The effects of acupuncture stimulation on c-Fos ex-
pressions are presented in Figs. 4 and 5. Fig. 4 shows repre-
sentative photographs of the c-Fos-positive neurons in each 
group, demonstrating that the activation of c-Fos-positive 
neurons was remarkably suppressed in the ST36-For, 
SP9-For and BL60-For groups compared to the formal-
in-only group. The observed numbers of c-Fos-positive neu-
rons in the laminae I-II were 403.50±156.19, 4461±433.75, 
2323.60±445.27, 2235.20±254.42, 2305.60±261.18, and 2958.20 
±309.14 in the intact (normal; n=4), formalin-only (n=5), 
ST36-For (n=5), SP9-For (n=5), BL60-For (n=5), and NA-
For (n=5) groups, respectively. When compared with the in-
tact group (403.50±156.19), all other groups showed a sig-
nificant increase in the number of c-Fos-positive neurons 
statistically (F5,23=14.087, p＜0.05, one-way ANOVA; p 
＜0.05, Dunnett's post-hoc multiple comparison). However, 
c-Fos expression was significantly decreased in all acu-
puncture treatment groups compared to the formalin-only 
group (F4,20=7.238, p＜0.05, one-way ANOVA; p＜0.05, 
Dunnett's post-hoc multiple comparison) (Fig. 5). 
In the case of laminae III-VI, the numbers of c-Fos-pos-
itive neurons were 222±82.16 (normal), 2107.08±350.02 
(formalin only), 1230.80±339.82 (ST36-For), 1123.60±131 
(SP9-For), 942.60±66.67 (BL60-For), and 1801.60±300.81 
(NA-For). In the formalin-only (2107.08±350.02), ST36-For 
(1230.80±339.82) and NA-For (1801.60±300.81) groups, 
c-Fos expression was significantly increased (F5,23=6.470, p 
＜0.05) compared to the normal group (222.02±82.16). 
When c-Fos expression was assessed between the formal-
in-only group and the rest of the four formalin-treated and 
acupuncture groups, the c-Fos expression was significantly 
suppressed only in the BL60-For group (F4,20=3.453, p 
＜0.05, one-way ANOVA; p＜0.05, Dunnett's post-hoc mul-
tiple comparison) (Fig. 5). 
The values from laminae I to VI in c-Fos-positive neurons 
were 625.50±238.24 (normal), 6569.00±703.25 (Formalin), 
3554.40±777.81 (ST36-For), 3358.80±331.15 (SP9-For), 
3248.20±315.02 (BL60-For), and 4759.80±290.66 (NA-For). 
All groups excluding the normal group (625.50±238.24) </p>

<p>showed a remarkable increase of c-Fos expression statisti-
cally (F4,20=6.470, p＜0.05, one-way ANOVA; p＜0.05, 
Dunnett's post-hoc multiple comparison). Except for the 
NA-For group, c-Fos expressions in acupuncture-treated </p>

<p>Acupuncture at Different Acupoints </p>



<p>groups were significantly lower compared to the formalin 
only group (F4,20=7.096, p＜0.05, one-way ANOVA; p＜0.05, 
Dunnett's post-hoc multiple comparison) (Fig. 5). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The formalin-induced pain model has three distinctive 
characteristics: two phases of nociceptive behavior, time 
limitations and a short duration compared to models of 
chronic pain, and a similar time course of pain induced by 
formalin injection in humans [17]. Previous studies have 
focused on the effect of electroacupuncture on inflammatory 
pain induced by irritant chemicals such as carrageenan, 
CFA, and formalin. For example, electro-acupuncture at the 
HE7, PE7, and ST36 acupoints is effective in inflammatory 
pain analgesia [28,29], and c-Fos expression is decreased 
by the electro-acupuncture at the SP6 acupoint [30]. To 
date, however, no research has assessed the analgesic effect 
of manual acupuncture on a formalin-induced pain. 
In this study, we compared the effect of manual acu-
puncture at three different acupoints on formalin-induced 
pain. As a result, only the BL60-For group exhibited a sig-
nificantly diminished flinching behavior in the late phase. 
This is consistent with our recent study in which electro-
acupuncture at the BL60 acupoint was effective in relieving 
pain and decreased the number of c-Fos-positive cells in 
the spinal cord of rats with formalin-induced pain [10]. 
According to previous studies, analgesic effects of manual 
acupuncture and electroacupuncture may be somewhat 
different. For example, Yu et al. [31] compared the effects 
of manual acupuncture and electroacupuncture at ST36 
acupoint on arthritis. They found that manual acupuncture 
and electroacupuncture can induce analgesia and suggested 
that the collagen fibers may contribute to the analgesic ef-
fect of manual acupuncture and the peripheral nerve re-
ceptors may contribute to the electroacupuncture-induced 
analgesia. Yuan et al. [32] recorded neural responses of 
neurons from the primary somatosensory cortex to electro-
acupuncture or manual acupuncture at ST36. And they 
found that the neurons responded to manual acupuncture 
and electroacupuncture but the extent of action of manual 
acupuncture was smaller than that of electroacupuncture, 
suggesting the difference of analgesic effects of manual acu-
puncture and electroacupuncture. Furthermore, Leung et 
al. [33] reported that the de qi sensation may be qual-
itatively and quantitatively different between manual acu-
puncture and electroacupuncture. Electroacupuncture has 
been known to be more effective in relieving pain than man-
ual acupuncture [34-36]. These studies suggest that electro-
acupuncture may be more effective in relieving pain than 
manual acupuncture. However, we observed the analgesic 
effect of manual acupuncture at BL60 in the present study 
similarly to our previous study in which electroacupuncture 
at BL60 produced the analgesic effect. 
Nevertheless, manual acupuncture at ST36 or SP9 was 
not effective in relieving formalin-induced pain. Similarly, 
Hao et al. [11] reported that electroacupuncture alone at 
ST36 produced significant analgesia in the tail-flick test, 
but not in the formalin test. They observed that electro-
acupuncture at ST36 enhanced the pain-relieving effect of 
intrathecal endomorphin-1 in the formalin test. Wen et al. 
[15] observed that electroacupuncture at ST36 suppressed 
formalin-induced pain under 0.5% halothane anesthesia 
and this pain-relieving effect mainly appeared at the late </p>

<p>phase. Therefore, acupuncture stimulation at ST36 or SP9 
may not produce strong analgesia relatively. 
The difference between the analgesic effect of BL60 stim-
ulation and that of ST36 or SP9 is of interest. This differ-
ence might be caused by the specificity of acupoints, since 
BL60 point as a meridian is known to cure back pain and 
the nerves in the plantar dermatomes (L3-L5) are con-
nected with a sciatic nerve segment. The ST36 acupoint, 
which is widely applicable for pain analgesia, is used in 
traditional Oriental medicine to treat gastrointestinal syn-
dromes rather than back pain or sciatic nerve damage [37]. 
Therefore, it is of particular significance that the BL60 acu-
point helps relieve pain. 
Even though there is no direct evidence regarding the 
analgesic effect of BL60 stimulation, the pain-relieving ef-
fect of acupuncture stimulation at acupoints on biphasic 
pain behavior in formalin test may be limited and mainly 
suppress the late phase in formalin test which reflects the 
injury-induced spinal sensitization [16]. Therefore, a 
change in the spinal cord may reflect the physiological and 
behavioral correlates produced by acupuncture analgesia. 
According to Coderre et al. [37], central neural changes 
which are essential for the expression of pain during the 
late phase occur during the early phase in the formal-
in-induced pain model. For example, tonic formalin pain is 
reduced by brief spinal anesthesia given before the formalin 
injection. Spinal anesthesia after the early phase did not 
reduce behavioral responses in the late phase. In brief, the 
pain-suppression effect that results from acupuncture stim-
ulation prior to the injection of formalin or before starting 
the early phase is stronger in the late phase rather than 
the early phase. In addition, the acupuncture stimulation 
appears to be highly related to the central components rath-
er than the peripheral ones. 
The amount of time spent in both the flinching response 
and the licking response is widely used as an indicator to 
evaluate the pain response in the formalin-induced pain 
model; a flinching response is a more-reliable indicator for 
pain than the licking response because flinching is less in-
fluenced by procedures and agents that affect various as-
pects of behavior than licking. Therefore, flinching may be 
a more robust parameter because it is less contaminated 
by other non-nociceptive behavioral changes [16]. These 
may suggest that acupuncture is more beneficial for reliev-
ing pain during the flinching response than in the licking 
response. 
Flinching behaviors had an identifiable decrease after 
acupuncture at BL60 along with concomitant decrease of 
c-Fos-positive neurons in the dorsal horn of the spinal cord. 
In contrast, pain behaviors evoked from formalin after acu-
puncture stimulation have no significant decrease in licking 
behaviors, These results imply that the mechanism of acu-
puncture analgesia against formalin-evoked inflammatory 
pain may be originated in the spinal cord and ascend to 
the supra-spinal area. 
Since the development of the immunohistochemical 
method by Hunt et al. [24] with an antigen of c-Fos protein, 
this method has been used as a marker to assess the in-
tensity of pain and the pain-suppressive effect, and the cor-
relation between nociceptive stimulation and c-Fos ex-
pression in the dorsal horn is already established [38,39]. 
c-Fos is largely expressed in the area of pain-transmitting 
neurons in the spinal cord and brain [38,39]. Laminae I, 
II and V in the spinal cord dorsal horn, where primary af-
ferent nerves are projected, show a prominent increase in </p>

<p>126 </p>

<p>KH Chang, et al </p>

<p>c-Fos expression after noxious stimulation [24]. The sup-
pression in c-Fos expression is closely related with the acti-
vation of endogenous opioid peptides. Previous studies have 
reported that in a formalin-induced pain model, c-Fos ex-
pression decreases by injection of N-methyl-D-aspartate 
(NMDA)-R1 antigens [40] and that c-Fos expression in the 
spinal cord due to nociceptive stimuli can be suppressed 
not only by analgesics like morphine [41] but also by nora-
drenaline [42] and NMDA-receptor antagonists [43]. Other 
reports have implied that the analgesic effects of acu-
puncture are related with the endogenous opioid system 
[44,45] as well as monoamine secretion in the midbrain and 
the activity of the autonomic nervous system [46-48]. 
In this study, c-Fos expression in laminae III-VI 
(including laminae V-VI, which are related with the late 
phase) was significantly reduced by the acupuncture treat-
ment at the BL60 acupoint as well as the ST36 and SP9 
acupoints. These results suggest that acupuncture an-
algesia against inflammatory pain induced by formalin was 
related to behavioral responses in the late phase rather 
than the early phase. In addition, the analgesic effects of 
acupuncture stimulation at ST36 and SP9 acupoints cannot 
be excluded even though behavioral analgesia produced by 
acupuncture at ST36 and SP9 was less than analgesia by 
acupuncture at BL60. However, the fact that the c-Fos ex-
pression in the early-phase-related laminae I-II sig-
nificantly decreased for all acupuncture groups including 
acupuncture at ST36, SP9, BL60, and non-acupoint com-
pared to the group that received formalin injection only was 
not explained by the specificity of these acupoints. This re-
sult indicates that acupuncture stimulation may be influen-
tial to diffuse noxious inhibitory control (DNIC) at least in 
part [15]. 
In conclusion, acupuncture stimulation at the BL60 acu-
point significantly inhibited not only flinching behavior in 
the late phase of the formalin test model but also c-Fos 
expression in the spinal dorsal horn. Acupuncture at ST36 
or SP9 acupoint tended to inhibit flinching behavior, but 
the analgesic effect was not statistically significant while 
it significantly inhibited c-Fos expression. These results 
suggest that the acupuncture stimulation at BL60 may be 
more effective in relieving inflammatory pain compared to 
the acupuncture at ST36 or SP9 acupoint. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This research was supported by the Basic Science Research 
Program through the National Research Foundation (NRF) 
funded by the Ministry of Science, ICT &amp; Future Planning 
(No. 2005-0049404). </p>







</text></tei>