<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3072005" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVE: Involvement of the left ventricular anterior wall in ST-elevation myocardial infarction has a worse 
prognosis compared with other regions. In non-ST-elevation myocardial infarction, noninvasive methods of locating 
the ischemic myocardial territory have been limited. The objective of this report is therefore to determine what 
factors are predictive of the anterior location of the ischemic myocardial territory. </p>

<p>METHODS: This study included 170 patients with non-ST-elevation myocardial infarction. Clinical, echocardio-
graphic, and laboratory characteristics, including B-type natriuretic peptide measured within 24 hours of 
hospitalization, and coronary angiographic features were analyzed. </p>

<p>RESULTS: The mean age was 64.5 ¡ 12.3 years, and 112 of the patients were male (66%). The median follow-up was 
23 months. The territory involved, as determined from the angiogram, was divided into anterior [n = 80 (47%)] 
regions and inferior and lateral [n = 90 (53%)] regions. Multivariate analysis showed that B-type natriuretic peptide 
was the only independent predictor of an anterior wall infarct [OR = 3.70 (95% CI: 1.61 -8.53); P = 0.002] in non-ST-
elevation myocardial infarction patients. Multivariate analysis also showed that B-type natriuretic peptide was an 
independent predictor of in-hospital cardiac events during index admission [OR = 5.05 (95% CI: 1.49 -17.12); 
P = 0.009] and of cardiac events occurring during follow-up [HR = 1.79 (95% CI: 1.05 -3.04); P = 0.032]. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS: B-type natriuretic peptide was the only factor independently associated with anterior wall 
involvement in non-ST-elevation myocardial infarction, and the peptide levels upon admission predicted in-hospital 
and subsequent cardiac events. </p>

<p>Previous studies 1,2 have shown that involvement of the 
left ventricular (LV) anterior wall in ST-elevation myocar-
dial infarction (STEMI) has a worse prognosis compared 
with involvement of other regions. STEMI of the anterior 
wall is associated with a larger infarction area, as 
determined by the enzyme peak and lower left ventricular 
ejection fraction (LVEF), in comparison with other walls. 3 
Also, the electrocardiogram (ECG) in STEMI is usually 
sufficient to diagnose which wall is affected. 4 
The importance of the involvement of the anterior wall in 
patients with non-ST-segment elevation myocardial infarc-
tion (NSTEMI) has not been widely studied. In NSTEMI, the </p>

<p>identification of involvement of the anterior wall on 
admission is not as obvious as in STEMI. Because anterior 
wall infarction may be associated with a poor prognosis, 
several studies 5-8 have been conducted to identify the 
ischemic LV wall in NSTEMI. These studies have used 
ECG to identify which wall was affected. However, ECG has 
limited ability to perform this function in NSTEMI because 
approximately 50% of patients have a normal or incon-
clusive pattern. 9 Other methods, such as stress echocardio-
graphy 10 and myocardial perfusion scintigraphy, 11 can 
locate the infarction site in NSTEMI patients, but both 
methods demand more complex health services and higher 
costs. However, in a recent report by Sadanandan et al. 12 of 
patients with unstable angina and NSTEMI, coronary 
angiography showed an association between BNP levels 
and involvement of the anterior descending coronary artery. 
The identification of myocardial ischemia involving the 
anterior wall in NSTEMI has potential utility in terms of 
patient management and prognosis. 7 The objective of this </p>

<p>Copyright ß 2011 CLINICS -This is an Open Access article distributed under 
the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits unrestricted non-
commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the 
original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2011;66(3):437-441 
DOI:10.1590/S1807-59322011000300013 </p>



<p>study was therefore to determine whether BNP levels can 
facilitate the identification of anterior wall myocardial 
ischemia in NSTEMI. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study Patients </p>

<p>This prospective study was composed of 170 consecutive 
patients with NSTEMI who were seen between January 2005 
and April 2006 and who were followed during and after 
hospitalization until September 2007. The median length of 
their hospital stay was 3 days (range: 1 to 125), and the 
median follow-up was 23 months (range: 0.04 to 32). 
Patients diagnosed with NSTEMI were selected according 
to the international consensus definition. 13 The Ethics 
Committee of the Heart Institute (InCor) approved this 
study, and written informed consent was obtained from all 
participants. </p>

<p>Laboratory Analyses </p>

<p>Routine blood samples were collected at admission with-
out regard to fasting status, and the troponin I, creatine 
kinase isozyme by mass assay (CK-MB), and BNP levels were 
measured. For the BNP determination, a specific kit for the 
ADVIA Centaur analyzer (Bayer Health Care Diagnostics, 
Tarrytown, NY) was used, which had a detection limit of 
2 pg/mL and range from 2 to 5000 pg/mL. The intra-and 
interassay coefficients of variation ranged from 2.1 to 4.7% for 
concentrations between 29 and 1700 pg/mL . For this study, a 
level of $100 pg/mL was considered abnormal based on the 
manufacturer's recommended cut-off value. 14,15 </p>

<p>Electrocardiography </p>

<p>ECGs were performed upon hospital admission and were 
repeated soon after medication was started. ECGs were 
analyzed blind to the results of coronary angiography. Each 
tracing was evaluated by two cardiologists for the presence 
or absence of acute ischemic changes based on the presence 
or absence of (1) ST-segment depression $ 0.5 mm and (2) T 
wave changes. Patients with acute ischemic changes were 
categorized according to the location of the acute ischemic 
region into groups with anterior (V1, V2, V3, V4), inferior 
(DII, DIII, aVF), or lateral wall (V5, V6, DI, aVL) involvement. </p>

<p>Echocardiography </p>

<p>Images were acquired using a transthoracic approach 
with M-mode, 2-dimensional, spectral Doppler (pulsed and 
continued) and color flow mapping. The LVEF was 
calculated using Simpson's method. </p>

<p>Angiographic Analysis </p>

<p>The angiography results were evaluated by physicians 
blinded to the ECG and enzyme values. Using angiography, 
the wall involved in the acute ischemia was determined by 
identifying the artery affected by a ruptured atherosclerotic 
plaque, a thrombus, or both. Criteria for identification were 
an eccentric lesion, cut or overlaying borders, a blurred 
lesion, globular intraluminal masses, contrast retention, and 
slow coronary flow. 16 </p>

<p>Clinical Events </p>

<p>The following events were recorded and used in the 
analyses: </p>

<p>(1) in-hospital events during index admission including 
composite endpoint by the first occurrence of (a) 
mortality in-hospital during index admission or (b) 
cardiovascular events including congestive heart fail-
ure, cardiogenic shock, or ischemic events; and 
(2) any events during follow-up including composite end-
point by the first occurrence of (a) in-hospital event 
during index admission, (b) mortality during follow-up, 
or (c) rehospitalization for any cause. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Normally distributed quantitative variables are expressed 
as means and standard deviations. Nonparametric variables 
are expressed as median, minimum, and maximum values. 
Differences in the distribution of selected characteristics 
between patient groups were examined using the chi-square 
test and Fisher's exact test for categorical variables. The 
analysis was performed using Student's t-test for normally 
distributed continuous variables and the Mann-Whitney 
and Kruskal-Wallis tests for nonparametric variables. 
Variables associated with wall location and events in 
univariate analysis (P , 0.10) were included in the multi-
variate analyses. Continuous variables were used as 
dichotomous variables to facilitate clinical interpretation 
and standardize the multivariate analysis. The receiver 
operating characteristic (ROC) curve was used to determine 
the area under the curve (AUC) or the c statistic; the cut-off 
point for BNP and other continuous variables with the best 
predictive value was used for wall location and cardiac 
events. A multiple logistic regression model was used for 
the selection of variables predictive of involvement of the 
anterior wall and for the occurrence of in-hospital events 
during index admission. Cox multivariate regression was 
used for the selection of independent prognostic factors 
of mortality and any follow-up events. Two-sided P 
values , 0.05 were considered statistically significant. All 
statistical analyses were performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical 
Package for Social Sciences (SPSS</rs>) software version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">11.0</rs> for 
Windows. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Table 1 presents clinical and demographic characteristics 
of the patients. The median BNP level at baseline was 
214.5 pg/mL (range: 7 to 2291); moreover, 66% of patients 
had BNP $ 100 pg/mL (116 patients). The median peak 
troponin I level was 6.9 ng/mL (range: 1 to 150), and the 
median peak CK-MB level was 19 ng/mL (range: 2 to 500). 
The echocardiogram LVEF was normal ($ 55%) in 55 
patients (32%), and the median LVEF was 47%. No 
statistically significant differences were observed between 
LVEF values regarding involvement of the anterior and 
lateral/inferior walls. 
ECG review was used to identify the wall involved, but 
the location of the ischemic territory in almost half (71 
patients, 42%) of the patients could not be categorized. ECG 
successfully showed anterior wall involvement in 43 
patients (25%), and inferior or lateral wall involvement in 
56 patients (33%). 
The most frequent treatment was PTCA, which was 
performed in 85 patients (50%), followed by medical 
treatment in 68 patients (40%), and CABG in 17 patients 
(10%). </p>

<p>BNP and location of NSTEMI 
Ramos RB et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2011;66(3):437-441 </p>



<p>Anterior vs. Inferior and Lateral Wall Location of 
Acute Myocardial Ischemia </p>

<p>Univariate analysis identified the significant predictive 
factors for anterior wall location to be a BNP level . 210 pg/ 
mL [RR = 1.78 (95% CI: 1.28-2.47); P,0.001] and anterior 
wall involvement on ECG [RR = 3.02 (95% CI: 2.02 -8.00); 
P,0.001]. A multivariate logistic regression analysis, how-
ever, revealed that a BNP level . 210 pg/mL remained the 
only independent predictor of the anterior wall as the 
location of acute myocardial ischemia [OR = 3.70 (95% CI: 
1.61 -8.53); P = 0.002]. </p>

<p>Any events during follow-up </p>

<p>The analysis using Cox multivariate regression of any 
events during follow-up showed that BUN levels . 39 mg/ 
dL [HR = 1.82 (95% CI: 1.13 -2.94); P = 0.014], baseline BNP 
values . 156 pg/mL [HR = 1.79 (95% CI: 1.05 -3.04), 
P = 0.032], and family history for CAD [HR = 0.61 (95% CI: 
0.38 -0.99); P = 0.045] were independent predictors among 
those evaluated. 
The Kaplan-Meier analysis showed a trend toward a 
greater risk of any event during follow-up (P for trend = 
0.064) when comparing anterior wall involvement with 
inferior or lateral wall involvement (Table 2, Figure 1). </p>

<p>Mortality </p>

<p>Cox multivariate analysis showed that previous heart 
failure [HR = 3.71 (95% CI: 1.44 -9.58); P = 0.007] and 
history of chest pain [HR = 0.28 (95% CI: 0.10-0.76); 
P = 0.012] were other independent predictors of mortality 
among those evaluated. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our study shows that the BNP level was the only variable 
able to locate ischemic myocardium in the LV anterior wall 
in patients with NSTEMI, independent of multiple other 
characteristics including heart disease risk factors and 
history of previous cardiovascular disease. Previous stu-
dies 5,6,17 have evaluated the location of the LV anterior wall 
in NSTEMI in relation to the prognosis, with most using 
ECG to identify the affected wall. For example, using 
electrocardiographic ST-segment and T-wave changes to 
categorize the patients, Kao et al. 5 studied 135 patients with 
NSTEMI and observed a higher rate of reinfarction and 
death in patients with involvement of the anterior wall in </p>

<p>Table 1 -Baseline characteristics of the overall patient population by ischemic wall as defined by angiography. </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>All patients 
n = 170 (%) </p>

<p>Anterior 
n = 80 (%) </p>

<p>Inferior / lateral 
n = 90 (%) 
P* </p>

<p>Demographic characteristics 
Age, years 
64.5¡12.3 
62.9¡11.4 
63.9¡11.3 
0.571 
Male sex, n (%) 
112 (66) 
49 (61) 
63 (70) 
0.230 
Clinical characteristics 
Onset of symptoms, hours 
7.4 (0.1 -170) 
7.4 (0.3-145) 
7 (0.1-170) 
0.921 
History of chest pain, n (%) 
157 (92) 
75 (94) 
82 (91) 
0.518 
History of dyspnea, n (%) 
43 (25) 
21 (26) 
22 (24) 
0.789 
Hypertension, n (%) 
146 (86) 
71 (89) 
75 (83) 
0.311 
Hypercholesterolemia, n (%) 
108 (63) 
48 (60) 
60 (67) 
0.367 
Diabetes mellitus, n (%) 
66 (39) 
30 (38) 
36 (40) 
0.738 
Family history of CAD, n (%) 
65 (38) 
30 (38) 
35 (39) 
0.955 
Current smoking, n (%) 
36 (21) 
15 (19) 
21 (23) 
0.465 
Previous PTCA, n (%) 
45 (27) 
21 (26) 
24 (27) 
0.951 
Previous CABG, n (%) 
37 (22) 
14 (18) 
23 (26) 
0.204 
Previous myocardial infarction, n (%) 
79 (47) 
34 (43) 
45 (50) 
0.328 
Previous heart failure, n (%) 
33 (19) 
17 (21) 
16 (18) 
0.568 
Laboratory tests 
Baseline BNP, pg/mL 
214.5 (7-2291) 
247 (7-1843) 
100 (12-1738) 
0.002 
Peak CK-MB mass, ng/mL 
19 (2-500) 
22 (2.4-500) 
22.8 (2-455) 
0.677 
Peak troponin I, ng/mL 
6.9 (1-150) 
7.3 (1-150) 
7.8 (1-150) 
0.845 
Electrocardiographic characteristics 
Anterior wall location, n (%) 
43 (25) 
36 (45) 
7 (8) 
,0.001 
Inferior or lateral wall location, n (%) 
56 (33) 
13 (16) 
43 (48) 
,0.001 
Echocardiographic features 
LVEF, % (range) 
47 (10-77) 
45 (12-77) 
50 (10-74) 
0.292 
Angiographic characteristics, n (%) 
1-vessel disease 
39 (23) 
23 (29) 
16 (18) 
0.089 
2-vessel disease 
44 (26) 
22 (28) 
22 (24) 
0.650 
3-vessel disease 
87 (51) 
35 (44) 
52 (58) 
0.068 </p>

<p>CAD = coronary artery disease; PTCA = percutaneous transluminal coronary angioplasty; CABG = coronary artery bypass grafting; LVEF = left ventricular 
ejection fraction; * P values for the comparison between the anterior wall and inferior/lateral wall. </p>

<p>Table 2 -Any events of the overall patient population by 
ischemic wall as defined by angiography. </p>

<p>Events </p>

<p>Anterior 
patients, 
n = 80 (%) </p>

<p>Inferior / lateral 
patients, 
n = 90 (%) </p>

<p>Any in-hospital cardiovascular 
event </p>

<p>27 (34) 
16 (14) </p>

<p>Congestive heart failure 
19 (24) 
14 (13) 
Cardiogenic shock 
8 (10) 
2 (1) 
All causes of death 
12 (15) 
14 (15) 
In-hospital 
5 (6) 
2 (2) 
During follow-up 
7 (9) 
12 (14) 
Rehospitalization 
30 (38) 
28 (31) 
Acute coronary syndrome 
18 (22) 
15 (17) 
Congestive heart failure 
5 (7) 
5 (6) 
Non-cardiac events 
7 (9) 
8 (9) </p>

<p>CLINICS 2011;66(3):437-441 
BNP and location of NSTEMI 
Ramos RB et al. </p>



<p>comparison with the inferior and lateral walls. In addition, 
Schechtman et al. 17 analyzed data from 544 patients with 
NSTEMI, excluding patients in Killip class IV. Using ECG to 
categorize the infarct location, they identified 51% of 
patients as having anterior wall ischemia and did not find 
higher mortality in these patients compared with those who 
had ischemia of the inferior or lateral walls. They did not 
locate the wall affected in 20% of their patients. 
Compared with these studies, the infarct location was not 
categorized in a greater number of patients in the present 
study. This may be due to our use of the new definition of 
NSTEMI, which includes a smaller area of infarct or 
ischemia that may have a smaller representation on ECG. 
The presence of other factors, such as previous MI, cardiac 
surgery, or left bundle-branch block, can also influence the 
accuracy of ECG. 
Similar to the present study, Haim et al. 6 used ECG to 
categorize patients with the first NSTEMI in the anterior or 
inferior and lateral walls and showed a higher rate of 
cardiac events in patients with NSTEMI of the anterior wall 
during a 1-year follow-up. 
All three of the above studies showed a higher incidence 
of heart failure in patients with NSTEMI of the anterior wall 
compared with the other walls. In our study, we observed 
previous heart failure in 21% of patients with involvement 
of anterior wall and in 18% of those with inferior and lateral 
wall ischemia. 
In the present study, a broad comparative analysis was 
performed to identify the variables with the greatest ability 
to determine involvement of the LV anterior wall versus 
inferior and lateral walls in NSTEMI patients, based on the 
location defined by coronary artery angiography. Although 
it is sometimes difficult to define the coronary artery 
involved, the culprit coronary artery was successfully 
identified for patients in this study. Patients with involve-
ment of the LV anterior wall on angiography had a higher 
frequency of detection of anterior wall location by ECG 
(P,0.001) and higher BNP levels (P = 0.002) (Table 1). In the 
final logistic regression multivariate analysis, the baseline </p>

<p>BNP value remained the only independent predictor of 
involvement of the LV anterior wall [OR = 3.70 (95% CI: 
1.61 -8.53); P = 0.002]. 
Serum BNP levels are associated with ventricular dys-
function in ACS. Additionally, several studies 12,18,19 have 
shown an association between high BNP levels and acute 
myocardial ischemia. Sadanandan et al. 12 reported that high 
BNP levels in unstable angina and NSTEMI were associated 
with tighter culprit vessel stenosis and lower flow in the 
artery involved, and the culprit artery was most often the 
anterior descending artery. Furthermore, Palazzuoli et al. 18 
selected a group of patients with stable angina, unstable 
angina, and NSTEMI and showed that elevated BNP levels, 
even in the absence of heart failure, were related to 3-or 4-
vessel disease in comparison with 1-or 2-vessel disease. 
Elevated BNP levels were also shown to be indicative of 
involvement of the anterior descending artery. 
The aforementioned studies 12,18 used univariate analysis 
to show a correlation between higher BNP levels and 
involvement of the anterior descending coronary artery. 
Conversely, the present study considered a broad set of 
variables to identify those with an independent ability to 
locate the involvement of the anterior wall. The independent 
and apparently exclusive ability of the BNP levels to predict 
the location in the LV anterior wall in a population sample 
including patients with a high frequency of previous heart 
failure may be explained by its correlation with the ischemic 
myocardial area at risk in this cohort. 
Risk stratification scores in NSTEMI are valued by current 
medical practices. The scores frequently used today are 
the American College of Cardiology/American Heart 
Association (ACC/AHA) prognostic classification 20 and 
the TIMI (Thrombolysis in Myocardial Infarction) risk 
score. 21 However, neither of these scores includes baseline 
BNP values. In a recent study, Khan et al. 22 used multi-
variate analysis to show that, in STEMI, the N-terminal pro-
BNP (NT-proBNP) value measured within the first 24 hours 
of admission was a better prognostic factor than the TIMI 
risk score at predicting mortality. In addition, Bazzino et 
al. 23 reported that in patients with non-ST-elevation ACS, 
the NT-proBNP level adds substantial information to the 
TIMI risk score and ACC/AHA classification. 
In the present study, there was a trend of more in-hospital 
events during index admission when the anterior wall was 
involved in NSTEMI when compared with patients with 
inferior and lateral wall ischemia. The Kaplan-Meier 
analysis also showed a tendency for patients with 
NSTEMI to have a higher frequency of any clinical event 
during follow-up (Figure 1). In the SPRINT study, the 
anterior wall infarction location was an independent 
predictor of the occurrence of composite events (death and 
rehospitalization for ACS) during a 1-year follow-up. 6 The 
present results may have been affected by differences 
between the populations and type of treatment performed 
in the two groups; more specifically, there was a high 
frequency of PTCA of the culprit artery (50%), CABG (10%), 
and drug therapy (40%), which likely reduced the recurrent 
event rate. </p>

<p>Study limitations </p>

<p>The small number of deaths limited the analysis and 
interpretation of mortality for the population sample. The 
cut-off points calculated for the continuous variables using 
the ROC curve were valid for this cohort, but further studies </p>

<p>Figure 1 -Kaplan-Meier any event-free survival curve during 
follow-up, in months, for patients with NSTEMI and according to 
the involvement of anterior vs. inferior and lateral walls as 
defined by angiography. </p>

<p>BNP and location of NSTEMI 
Ramos RB et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2011;66(3):437-441 </p>



<p>are required to confirm their applicability in clinical 
practice. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>BNP can independently predict the involvement of the 
anterior wall in comparison with the inferior or lateral walls 
in NSTEMI. This may explain one of the underlying 
mechanisms accounting for the independent ability of the 
baseline BNP levels to predict events during index admis-
sion hospitalization and long-term follow-up. </p>



<p>CLINICS 2011;66(3):437-441 
BNP and location of NSTEMI 
Ramos RB et al. </p>



</text></tei>