<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3487307" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>AbstrAct </p>

<p>The pulmonary vasculature is an important site of renin-angiotensin metabolism. While angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors 
and angiotensin II receptor blockers (collectively AIABs) have a role in left ventricular (LV) disease, the impact of AIABs on 
right ventricular (RV) function is unknown. AIAB use was determined by medication inventory during the Multi-Ethnic Study of 
Atherosclerosis baseline examination. RV measures were obtained via cardiac magnetic resonance imaging. The relationship 
between AIAB use and RV measures was assessed using multivariable linear regression, stratified by race/ethnicity, and adjusted 
for multiple covariates. AIAB use was associated with lower RV mass (-0.7 g, 95% confidence interval [CI] -1.3 to -0.1, P=0.03) 
in African Americans (N=1012) after adjustment for multiple covariates including LV mass. Among Caucasians (N=1591), AIAB 
use was associated with larger RV end-diastolic volume (3.7 mL, 95% CI 0.7-6.8, P=0.02) after adjustment for LV volume. No 
significant associations were seen between AIAB use and other RV measures or in Hispanic or Chinese American participants. 
AIAB use was associated with RV morphology in a race-specific and LV-independent manner, suggesting the renin-angiotensin 
system may play a unique role in RV structure and function. The use of AIABs in those with RV dysfunction warrants further study. </p>

<p>Chahal H, et al. The renin-angiotensin system 
and right ventricular structure and function: 
The MESA-Right Ventricle Study. Pulm Circ 
2012;2:379-86. </p>

<p>Pulmonary Circulation | July-September 2012 | Vol 2 | No 3 </p>

<p>
Ventetuolo et al.: ACE inhibitors, ARBs, and the RV </p>

<p>documented in the explanted lungs of pulmonary arterial 
hypertension (PAH) patients, and ACE2 expression increases 
in failing RVs of cardiac transplant recipients. 
[8,9] Manipulation 
of RAS pathways (via ACE inhibition or angiotensin II receptor 
blockade) could impact pulmonary vascular function and/or 
RV remodeling. The use of ACE inhibitors or angiotensin II 
receptor blockers (ARBs; collectively AIABs) in the treatment 
of pulmonary vascular disease and RV dysfunction is not 
supported by the small amount of available data, however. </p>

<p>[10-12] </p>

<p>We examined the relationship of AIAB use with RV structure 
and function assessed by cardiac magnetic resonance 
imaging (MRI) in a large cohort of participants without 
clinical cardiovascular disease. We hypothesized that AIAB 
use would be associated with higher RV ejection fraction 
(RVEF) and larger RV stroke volume (RVSV), lower RV 
mass, and smaller RV end-diastolic volume (RVEDV), and 
RV end-systolic volume (RVESV). Preliminary results from 
this study have been published in the abstract form. </p>

<p>[13] </p>

<p>MAtERIAlS ANd MEthodS </p>

<p>Study sample </p>

<p>The Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis (MESA) is a 
multicenter prospective cohort study to investigate the 
prevalence, correlates, and progression of subclinical 
cardiovascular disease in Caucasians, African Americans, 
Hispanics, and Chinese Americans. 
[14] In 2000-2002, MESA 
recruited 6814 subjects aged 45-84 years old from six U.S. 
communities: Forsyth County, NC; Northern Manhattan and 
the Bronx, NY; Baltimore City and Baltimore County, MD; St. 
Paul, MN; Chicago, IL; and Los Angeles, CA. Exclusion criteria 
included clinical cardiovascular disease, weight &gt; 300 lbs, 
pregnancy, or impediment to long-term participation. The 
presence of clinical cardiovascular disease was determined 
at participant screening by questionnaire. Participants were 
excluded if they answered "yes" to having been diagnosed 
by a physician with heart attack, stroke, transient ischemic 
attack, heart failure, angina, current atrial fibrillation, 
and/or to having undergone any prior cardiovascular 
procedure. Hypertension and diabetes were not exclusion 
criteria. The protocols of MESA and studies described herein 
were approved by the Institutional Review Boards of all 
collaborating institutions and the National Heart Lung and 
Blood Institute. The MESA-Right Ventricle Study is an ancillary 
study that planned for the selection of 4,634 participants 
with interpretable cardiac MRIs at the baseline examination 
for measurement of RV morphology, which was completed 
in 4204. Participants were sampled without regard to 
demographics, anthropometrics, or other clinical variables. </p>

<p>cardiac magnetic resonance imaging measures </p>

<p>The cardiac MRI protocol has been described 
elsewhere. 
[15] All imaging was performed on 1.5 T magnets </p>

<p>with a four-element phased-array surface coil positioned 
anteriorly and posteriorly and electrocardiographic gating. 
Imaging consisted of fast gradient echo cine images with 
temporal resolution ≤ 50 ms. </p>

<p>Methods for interpretation of the LV and RV measures 
have been previously reported. 
[15,16] Briefly, RV image 
analysis was performed by two independent analysts 
on Windows workstations using <rs id="software-0" type="software">QMASS software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v4.2</rs>, 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Medis</rs>, The Netherlands). The endocardial and epicardial 
borders of the RV were traced manually on short-axis 
cine images at end-diastole and end-systole. Papillary 
muscles and trabeculae were included in the RV volumes 
and excluded from RV mass. 
[17] RVEDV and RVESV were 
calculated using Simpson's rule by summation of areas 
on each slice multiplied by the sum of slice thickness and 
image gap. RV mass was determined at end-diastole as the 
difference between end-diastolic epicardial and endocardial 
volumes multiplied by the specific gravity of the heart 
(1.05 g/cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>). 
[15] RVSV was calculated by subtracting RVESV 
from RVEDV. RVEF was calculated by dividing RVSV by 
RVEDV. The intra-reader intraclass correlation coefficients 
(ICCs) from random, blinded re-reads of 229 scans for RV 
mass was 0.94 and for 230 scans was 0.99, 0.95, and 0.89 
for RVEDV, RVESV, and RVEF, respectively. The intra-reader 
ICC was 0.96 for RVSV. The inter-reader ICCs from random, 
blinded re-reads of 240 scans for RV mass, RVEDV, RVESV, 
and RVEF were 0.89, 0.96, 0.94, and 0.80, respectively. The 
inter-reader ICC for RVSV was 0.93. </p>

<p>Medication use </p>

<p>A validated medication inventory was used to assess 
medication use at the baseline exam. 
[18] Participants were 
asked to bring all containers for medications (prescription 
and non-prescription) used during the two weeks prior 
to the baseline visit. Interviewers transcribed all current 
medication names, strengths, and dosages from participant 
medication bottles. Participants were queried about actual 
medication intake during the two weeks prior to the visit, 
and interviewers recorded the average number of pills 
taken. In circumstances where no medication was taken, 
the interviewer coded medication intake as "0." </p>

<p>other covariates </p>

<p>Race/ethnicity was self-reported during the baseline exam 
according to 2000 US Census criteria as race (Caucasian, 
African American, Chinese American) and ethnicity 
(Hispanic or non-Hispanic). Standard questionnaires were 
used to ascertain smoking status and level of education. 
Height was measured to the nearest 0.1 cm with the 
participant in stocking feet and weight was measured to 
the nearest pound with the participant in light clothing 
using a balanced scale. Resting blood pressure was 
measured using the Dinamap Monitor PRO 100 (Critikon, 
Tampa, FL) automated oscillometric device. Hypertension </p>

<p>Pulmonary Circulation | July-September 2012 | Vol 2 | No 3 </p>



<p>Ventetuolo et al.: ACE inhibitors, ARBs, and the RV </p>

<p>was defined as systolic blood pressure &gt; 140 mmHg, 
diastolic blood pressure &gt; 90 mmHg, or current use of 
anti-hypertension medication. Fasting blood samples were 
drawn and sent to a central laboratory for measurement of 
glucose and lipids. The presence of diabetes mellitus was 
based on self-reported physician diagnosis or a fasting 
glucose value &gt; 126 mg/dL, the latter measured by rate 
reflectance spectrophotometry (Johnson and Johnson 
Clinical Diagnostics, Inc., Rochester, N.Y.). Fasting glucose of 
100-125 mg/dL was considered impaired fasting glucose. 
Spirometry (forced expiratory volume in 1 s [FEV1], forced 
vital capacity [FVC], and the FEV1/FVC ratio) was available 
for 2703 participants. </p>

<p>[19] </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Continuous variables were expressed as means and 
standard deviations. Categorical variables were expressed 
as percentages. As response to AIAB therapy differs 
by race, we decided a priori to stratify all analyses by 
race/ethnicity. 
[20] Significant (or borderline significant) 
interactions between AIAB use and race/ethnicity for 
RV volumes (P = 0.02 for RVEDV and P = 0.16 for RVESV, 
respectively) supported this approach. </p>

<p>Multivariate linear regression was used to assess the 
relationship of AIAB use with each RV parameter. Initial 
models included age, gender, height, and weight. Adjustment 
for height and weight avoided the assumptions made in 
indexing the RV measures to certain parameters of body size 
(e.g., body surface area), while accounting for differences 
in body size between participants. Models were further 
adjusted for hypertension and use of antihypertensive 
medications, systolic and diastolic blood pressure, 
creatinine, urine albumin, smoking (status and pack years), 
diabetes mellitus, impaired glucose tolerance, cholesterol, 
triglycerides, statin use, level of education, and respective 
LV parameters (e.g., the model for RVEF was adjusted 
for LV ejection fraction, and so forth). We assessed for 
collinearity of the main exposure (AIAB use) with the other 
blood pressure and treatment variables. Adjustment for LV 
parameters was performed to account for the contribution 
of LV abnormalities to RV changes (e.g., increased LV 
mass causing pulmonary venous hypertension leading to 
increased RV mass), to account for body size differences, 
and to examine RV-specific associations. RVSV was not 
adjusted for LV stroke volume considering the significant 
interdependence of these measures. </p>

<p>Because the RAS is active in the lung parenchyma and 
has been implicated in obstructive and restrictive lung 
diseases, we performed adjustment for lung function in 
the subgroup with available spirometry (N = 2,703). </p>

<p>[6,21] </p>

<p>Statistical significance was defined as P &lt; 0.05. Analyses 
were performed using STATA 10.0 (StataCorp, College 
Station, Tex.). </p>

<p>RESultS </p>

<p>MESA enrolled 6,814 participants of whom 5,098 had 
cardiac MRIs; 5,004 were interpretable for LV morphology 
(Fig. 1). Of these, 4,634 were selected for RV interpretation, 
4,484 were attempted to be read, and 4,204 had RV 
measures completed. In addition to participants using 
combination AIABs with diuretics (N=117), we excluded 
participants missing covariate data (N=96). The final 
study sample consisted of 3,991 participants, of whom 
1,591 (39.9%) were Caucasian, 1,012 (25.3%) were African 
American, 877 (22.0%) were Hispanic, and 511 (12.8%) 
were Chinese American. Of participants with available 
spirometry (N=2703), 964 (35.7%) were Caucasian, 
661 (24.4%) were African American, 597 (22.1%) were 
Hispanic, and 481 (17.8%) were Chinese American. </p>

<p>The study sample was similar to those excluded (Table 1). 
A total of 580 (14.5%) participants in the study sample 
were using AIABs, the majority of whom were using 
ACE inhibitors (446 of 580, 78.6%). Characteristics of 
the study sample stratified by race/ethnicity are shown 
in Table E1 (Access Supplemental Table E1 at www. 
pulmonarycirculation.org). African American participants 
were more likely to have hypertension and receive 
antihypertensive medications, including AIABs (details 
of African American and Caucasian participants stratified 
by AIAB use are shown in Table E2 (Access Supplemental </p>

<p>Figure 1: Study sample. MESA: Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis; MRI: 
magnetic resonance imaging; LV: left ventricle; RV: right ventricle; AIABs: 
angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors and angiotensin II receptor blockers. </p>

<p>6814 MESA baseline exam </p>

<p>3991 participants 
1591 caucasians 
1012 African Americans 
877 Hispanics 
511 Chinese Americans </p>

<p>96 missing covariate data 
117 taking AIABs with diuretics </p>

<p>5098 had MRI 
5004 had interpretable LV measures </p>

<p>2703 participants with available lung function 
964 Caucasians 
661 African Americans 
597 Hispanics 
481 Chinese Americans </p>

<p>4634 selected for RV interpretation 
4204 had complete RV measures </p>

<p>Pulmonary Circulation | July-September 2012 | Vol 2 | No 3 </p>

<p>
Ventetuolo et al.: ACE inhibitors, ARBs, and the RV </p>

<p>Table E2 at www.pulmonarycirculation.org). While there 
were differences across race/ethnicity in socioeconomic 
factors (e.g., education) with Caucasians tending to have 
higher levels of education, within group levels of education 
across AIAB use were similar. AIAB users were more likely 
to be using statins, but this did not vary across race/ 
ethnicity. Finally, Caucasian AIAB users were more likely to 
be prescribed beta-blockers (compared to non-users and </p>

<p>African Americans), while African American AIAB users 
were more likely to be prescribed calcium channel blockers 
(compared to non-users and Caucasians). </p>

<p>Angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor and 
angiotensin II receptor blocker use </p>

<p>In Caucasians, AIAB use was associated with a 3.7 mL 
larger RVEDV (95% confidence interval [CI] 0.7-6.8 mL, 
P = 0.02) and possibly a 2.4 mL larger RVSV (95% CI -0.6 
to 5.4 mL, P = 0.12; Table 2). The association with RVEDV 
was strengthened after adjustment for LV end-diastolic 
volume, implying an RV-specific relationship. There were 
no associations between AIAB use and RVEF, RV mass, or 
RVESV in Caucasians. </p>

<p>In African Americans, AIAB use was associated with a 0.7 g 
lower RV mass (95% CI -1.3 to -0.1 g, P = 0.03; Table 2). 
There was also a suggestion of smaller RVEDV and RVESV 
with AIAB use after adjustment for LV volumes (P = 
0.07 and 0.10, respectively). There were no significant 
associations seen between AIAB use and RVEF or RVSV in 
African Americans. </p>

<p>There were no significant associations between AIAB 
use and RV measures in Hispanic and Chinese American 
participants (Table 2). Analyses including participants using 
combination AIABs with diuretics (N = 117) did not alter the 
results, nor did analyses adjusting for beta-blocker and/or 
calcium channel blocker use (rather than adjustment for 
antihypertensive medications in general). Analysis of ACE 
inhibitor use alone showed similar results (data not shown). </p>

<p>Subgroup with available spirometry </p>

<p>We then assessed the smaller subgroup of participants with 
available spirometry (N = 2703). In Caucasians (N = 962), 
the effect estimates of AIAB use and RV morphology were 
similar to those seen in the total study sample and were not 
changed after adjustment for FEV1, FVC, and the FEV1/FVC 
ratio, but did not meet statistical significance likely due to 
smaller sample size (Table E3 [Access Supplemental Table E3 
at www.pulmonarycirculation.org]). In African Americans 
in this smaller sample (N = 661), AIAB use was associated 
with lower RV mass even after adjustment for LV mass 
(-0.6 g, 95% CI -1.4 to 0.1 g, P = 0.08) and smaller RVEDV 
(-4.3 mL, 95% CI -8.1 to -0.5 mL, P = 0.03). These effect 
estimates were unchanged after adjustment for spirometry. 
No associations were seen between AIAB use and any 
RV measures in Hispanic (N = 597) or Chinese American 
(N = 481) participants. </p>

<p>dIScuSSIoN </p>

<p>We found modest race-specific associations between AIAB 
use and measures of RV morphology in a large cohort of </p>

<p>Table 1: Characteristics of the total study sample and of 
those participants excluded </p>

<p>Number 
Total study 
sample </p>

<p>Excluded </p>

<p>3991 
2823 </p>

<p>Demographics 
Age (years) 
61.4±10.1 
63.2±10.3 
Male gender (%) 
47.7 
46.4 
Race/ethnicity (%) 
Caucasian 
39.9 
36.5 
African American 
25.3 
31.2 
Hispanic 
22.0 
21.9 
Chinese American 
12.8 
10.4 
Education (%) 
&lt; High school 
16.4 
20.4 
High school 
18.2 
18.2 
&lt; College (&gt; high school) 
28.3 
28.8 
≥ College 
37.1 
32.6 
Anthropometrics 
Height (cm) 
166.4±9.9 
166.3±10.2 
Weight (kg) 
77.3±16.1 
81.0±18.8 
Body mass index (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
27.8±4.9 
29.1±6.1 
Smoking status 
Never smoker (%) 
52.2 
47.7 
Former smoker (%) 
35.3 
38.5 
Current smoker (%) 
12.5 
13.8 
Pack years among ever smokers 
10.9±22.8 
12.2±21.4 
Disease prevalence 
Diabetes mellitus (%) 
Normal 
75.7 
70.3 
Impaired fasting glucose 
12.9 
15.2 
Untreated diabetes 
2.5 
2.9 
Treated diabetes 
8.9 
11.6 
Total cholesterol (mg/dL) 
194.5±35.0 
193.7±36.7 
High-density lipoprotein (mg/dL) 
51.1±15.0 
50.8±14.5 
Triglycerides (mg/dL) 
131.2±85.9 
132.3±92.9 
Statin use (%) 
14.4 
15.4 
Hypertension (%) 
41.2 
50.1 
Systolic blood pressure (mmHg) 
125.2±21.0 
128.6±22.0 
Diastolic blood pressure (mmHg) 
71.8±10.2 
72.1±10.4 
Antihypertensive use, n (%) 
33.9 
41.9 
AIAB use, n (%) 
580 (14.5) 
459 (16.3) 
ACEI use, n (%) 
446 (11.2) 
362 (12.9) 
ARB use, n (%) 
137 (3.3) 
97 (3.4) 
Creatinine 
1.0±0.2 
1.0±0.3 
Urine albumin 
2.4±14.0 
3.3±23.2 
RV measures 
RVEF (%) 
70.4±6.5 
RVSV (mL) 
86.8±20.7 
RV mass (g) 
21.0±4.5 
RVEDV (mL) 
124.1±31.0 
RVESV (mL) 
37.3±14.3 </p>

<p>Data shown as mean±standard deviation or %. AIAB: angiotensin-
converting enzyme inhibitors and angiotensin II receptor blockers; 
ACEI: angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors; ARB: angiotensin II 
receptor blockers; RV: right ventricle; RVEF: right ventricular ejection 
fraction; RVSV: right ventricular stroke volume; RVEDV: right ventricular 
end-diastolic volume; RVESV: right ventricular end-systolic volume </p>

<p>Pulmonary Circulation | July-September 2012 | Vol 2 | No 3 </p>



<p>Ventetuolo et al.: ACE inhibitors, ARBs, and the RV </p>

<p>participants without clinical cardiovascular disease. In 
Caucasians, AIAB use was associated with larger RVEDV 
and possibly larger RVSV while among African Americans 
AIAB use was associated with lower RV mass and possibly 
smaller RV volumes. These findings persisted even after 
adjustment for respective LV measures and spirometry, 
implying that RAS manipulation may uniquely impact 
RV morphology independent of effects on the LV and 
pulmonary function. To our knowledge, this is the largest 
study of AIAB use and RV structure and function measured 
by cardiac MRI. </p>

<p>Several small studies have shown acute hemodynamic 
benefits of AIABs in patients with pulmonary vascular 
disease (particularly hypoxia-related PH), but RV effects 
are largely unknown. 
[22-25] In a single study of four patients 
with PAH, captopril improved radionuclide measured RVEF, 
but it is difficult to know whether this improvement was 
driven by systemic afterload reduction and concomitantly 
increased LV ejection fraction. 
[22] The impact of AIABs on 
RV morphology has been studied in patients with systemic 
RVs from congenital heart disease with mixed results. </p>

<p>[26-28] </p>

<p>In the largest randomized trial (N = 17), Therrien and 
colleagues demonstrated that ramipril had no impact on </p>

<p>RVEF, mass, or volumes in adults with moderate systemic RV 
dysfunction. 
[27] Our study is the first to suggest that AIABs 
may have a role in RV modeling in the absence of clinical 
pulmonary or systemic vascular disease and ventricular 
dysfunction. While the effect sizes are modest, AIAB therapy 
leads to comparable effects in the LV after two years. 
[29] In 
severe PAH, long-term intravenous epoprostenol decreases 
RVEDV by on average 8 mL but leads to significant 
improvements in exercise capacity, functional status, and 
survival. 
[30,31] Similarly, it has been shown that a 10 mL 
change in RVSV during follow-up is a clinically relevant 
change for patients with pulmonary vascular disease. </p>

<p>[32] </p>

<p>In normal individuals, similar or smaller differences (in 
absolute or relative terms) may therefore have important 
physiologic effects. </p>

<p>It is surprising that AIABs may have an association with 
lower RV mass in African Americans but not in Caucasians. 
African Americans have greater LV mass and more LV 
hypertrophy as compared to Caucasians among healthy 
individuals and those with systemic hypertension. </p>

<p>[33-36] </p>

<p>While electrocardiographic LV hypertrophy has been 
shown to regress over time in both whites and non-whites 
treated with ARB-based therapy, African Americans </p>

<p>Table 2: Associations between AIAB use and RV measures in limited and fully adjusted models, by race/ethnicity </p>

<p>Number RV 
measure </p>

<p>Model 
Caucasians 
African Americans 
Hispanics 
Chinese Americans </p>

<p>1591 
1012 
877 
511 </p>

<p>Beta 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>P value 
Beta 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>P 
value </p>

<p>Beta 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>P value 
Beta 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>P 
value </p>

<p>RVEF (%) 
Limited </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.5 
(-0.4 to 1.4) </p>

<p>0.28 
0.5 
(-0.5 to 1.5) </p>

<p>0.34 
0.4 
(-0.7 to 1.6) </p>

<p>0.47 
-0.1 
(-1.7 to 1.4) </p>

<p>0.86 </p>

<p>Adjusted </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.0 
(-1.1 to 1.2) </p>

<p>0.95 
0.7 
(-0.6 to 1.9) </p>

<p>0.29 
0.1 
(-1.4 to 1.6) </p>

<p>0.91 
-0.9 
(-2.8 to 1.0) </p>

<p>0.36 </p>

<p>Adjusted + LVEF 
0.1 
(-0.9 to 1.2) </p>

<p>0.80 
0.6 
(-0.6 to 1.7) </p>

<p>0.36 
0.1 
(-1.3 to 1.4) </p>

<p>0.93 
-0.5 
(-2.3 to 1.3) </p>

<p>0.56 </p>

<p>RVSV (mL) 
Limited 
1.3 
(-1.2 to 3.7) </p>

<p>0.31 
-1.1 
(-3.8 to 1.6) </p>

<p>0.42 
1.5 
(-1.63 to 4.62) </p>

<p>0.35 
0.8 
(-2.7 to 4.3) </p>

<p>0.64 </p>

<p>Adjusted 
2.4 
(-0.6 to 5.4) </p>

<p>0.12 
-2.0 
(-5.3 to 1.3) </p>

<p>0.23 
0.7 
(-3.32 to 4.70) </p>

<p>0.74 
-0.2 
(-4.5 to 4.1) </p>

<p>0.93 </p>

<p>RV mass (g) 
Limited 
0.0 
(-0.5 to 0.6) </p>

<p>0.87 
-0.2 
(-0.7 to 0.4) </p>

<p>0.58 
0.3 
(-0.3 to 1.0) </p>

<p>0.30 
0.1 
(-0.7 to 0.8) </p>

<p>0.87 </p>

<p>Adjusted 
0.2 
(-0.4 to 0.9) </p>

<p>0.53 
-0.6 
(-1.3 to 0.0) </p>

<p>0.06 
-0.2 
(-1.0 to 0.7) </p>

<p>0.72 
-0.1 
(-1.0 to 0.9) </p>

<p>0.89 </p>

<p>Adjusted + LV mass 
0.0 
(-0.6 to 0.7) </p>

<p>0.90 
-0.7 
(-1.3 to -0.1) </p>

<p>0.03 
-0.4 
(-1.2 to 0.3) </p>

<p>0.26 
-0.3 
(-1.2 to 0.6) </p>

<p>0.46 </p>

<p>RVEDV (mL) 
Limited 
0.9 
(-2.5 to 4.2) </p>

<p>0.62 
-2.7 
(-6.3 to 0.9) </p>

<p>0.14 
1.3 
(-2.8 to 5.4) </p>

<p>0.54 
1.0 
(-3.7 to 5.7) </p>

<p>0.67 </p>

<p>Adjusted 
3.4 
(-0.7 to 7.5) </p>

<p>0.11 
-4.1 
(-8.5 to 0.3) </p>

<p>0.07 
0.7 
(-4.6 to 6.0) </p>

<p>0.81 
1.0 
(-4.7 to 6.8) </p>

<p>0.72 </p>

<p>Adjusted + LVEDV 
3.7 
(0.7 to 6.8) </p>

<p>0.02 
-3.0 
(-6.2 to 0.2) </p>

<p>0.07 
-0.1 
(-4.1 to 3.9) </p>

<p>0.96 
0.2 
(-4.4 to 4.7) </p>

<p>0.94 </p>

<p>RVESV (mL) 
Limited 
-0.4 
(-2.1 to 1.3) </p>

<p>0.63 
-1.6 
(-3.5 to 0.3) </p>

<p>0.09 
-0.2 
(-2.2 to 1.8) </p>

<p>0.83 
0.2 
(-2.1 to 2.5) </p>

<p>0.87 </p>

<p>Adjusted 
1.0 
(-1.1 to 3.1) </p>

<p>0.34 
-2.1 
(-4.4 to 0.2) </p>

<p>0.07 
-0.0 
(-2.6 to 2.6) </p>

<p>0.98 
1.2 
(-1.7 to 4.1) </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>Adjusted + LVESV 
1.0 
(-0.8 to 2.9) </p>

<p>0.26 
-1.7 
(-3.8 to 0.3) </p>

<p>0.10 
-0.4 
(-2.7 to 2.0) </p>

<p>0.76 
0.8 
(-1.8 to 3.5) </p>

<p>0.54 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Adjusted for age, gender, height, weight. b Limited model and use of antihypertensive medications, systolic and diastolic blood pressure, creatinine, urine 
albumin, smoking (status and pack-years), diabetes mellitus, impaired glucose tolerance, cholesterol, triglycerides, statin use, and level of education. 
AIAB: angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors and angiotensin II receptor blockers; RV: right ventricle; RVEF: right ventricular ejection fraction; RVSV : right 
ventricular stroke volume; RVEDV: right ventricular end-diastolic volume; RVESV: right ventricular end-systolic volume </p>

<p>Pulmonary Circulation | July-September 2012 | Vol 2 | No 3 </p>

<p>
Ventetuolo et al.: ACE inhibitors, ARBs, and the RV </p>

<p>are more likely to have persistent echocardiographic 
LV remodeling/hypertrophy despite antihypertensive 
therapy, and these changes predict future cardiovascular 
events. 
[37,38] Moreover, African Americans with heart 
failure treated with ACE inhibitors have a greater risk of 
clinical progression, worsening LV dysfunction, and death 
as compared to Caucasians. 
[20,39,40] It has been suggested 
that these race-specific differences may be due to innate 
differences in neurohumoral activation, blood pressure 
response, and/or genetic variation. African Americans 
may have greater nitric oxide deficits and endothelial 
damage than Caucasians (and therefore may be less 
likely to respond to RAS manipulation). 
[40,41] In the RV, we 
have shown that African Americans have lower RV mass 
and less RV hypertrophy when compared to Caucasians 
after adjustment for LV mass, suggesting an RV-specific 
relationship. PAH therapy (such as endothelin-receptor 
antagonists) appears to be less efficacious in African 
Americans than in whites, possibly due to disparate effects 
on the RV. 
[42] Taken together, these observations suggest 
that AIAB therapy may (1) distinctly impact the RV as 
compared to the LV, and (2) that these relationships not 
only vary by race-ethnicity but are unlike those observed 
in the LV, perhaps due to differential adaptation to pressure 
loading and alterations in the genetic signature. </p>

<p>[43] </p>

<p>Genetic variation in the ACE gene results in altered 
levels of cardiac ACE activity and the insertion/deletion 
polymorphism (ACE I/D) has been associated with LV 
hypertrophy, LV dysfunction, and mortality in heart 
failure. 
[44-46] While homozygotes for the deletion allele 
(ACE DD) are at increased risk for PAH, the ACE DD 
genotype appears to protect against RV dysfunction 
and preserve cardiac output. 
[47,48] Genotype frequency 
is known to vary by race/ethnicity, with the ACE DD 
genotype more commonly occurring in African Americans 
than the ACE I/D or ACE insertion/insertion genotypes. </p>

<p>[49] </p>

<p>It is possible that ACE gene interactions may explain the 
race/ethnicity differences seen here and that AIAB therapy 
may have pleiotropic effects on the pulmonary vasculature 
and the RV. </p>

<p>Whether the constellation of RV findings demonstrated (i.e., 
larger end-diastolic and stroke volumes in Caucasians vs. 
lower mass and volumes in African Americans) could be 
adaptive in individuals without clinical cardiovascular disease 
is not known. In the LV, moderate post-infarct dilatation 
has been proposed to be compensatory and may preserve 
stroke volume, yet large end-systolic volumes predict poor 
outcomes in high-risk patients. 
[29,50] In patients with systemic 
hypertension, lower LV stroke volume during antihypertensive 
treatment has been shown to predict cardiovascular risk, 
independent of LV morphology. 
[51] AIAB therapy in patients 
with cardiovascular disease has been shown to reduce LV 
mass and volumes, while exercise-induced increases in LV </p>

<p>mass in trained athletes and in RV mass in MESA participants 
are believed to be adaptive. </p>

<p>[29,37,38,52] </p>

<p>Our study has several limitations. No conclusions can be 
drawn about causality since this study was cross-sectional 
in nature. While we adjusted for multiple covariates, 
unmeasured or residual confounding is still possible, 
specifically confounding by indication. However, if present, 
we would expect such confounding effects of AIABs on 
both the RV and LV, so that adjustment for LV measures 
should eliminate the RV findings. This was not the case, 
as the associations between AIABs and RV morphology 
persisted despite LV adjustment, making confounding by 
indication less likely to explain our results. The duration of 
treatment with AIABs was not assessed. Some participants 
could have been treated for years with these medications, 
and others for only a short period of time. However, such 
misclassification would likely bias to the null (e.g., a 
participant treated for a few months before the baseline 
study visit would be unlikely to have any effects on RV 
morphology, yet would still be classified as an AIAB user). 
Therefore, it is possible that we have underestimated the 
associations between AIAB use and RV morphology. Finally, 
stratifying by race/ethnicity created smaller sample sizes in 
the Hispanic and Chinese American groups, likely limiting 
our power to detect associations. </p>

<p>We have shown that AIAB use is associated with RV mass 
and volumes in a race-specific and LV-independent manner 
in a large cohort of participants free of cardiovascular 
disease. The potential benefits of AIAB use in the setting of 
pulmonary vascular disease and in individuals with (or at 
risk for) RV dysfunction are unknown and warrant future 
study in randomized clinical trials. </p>

<p>AckNowlEdgMENtS </p>

<p>This manuscript has been reviewed by the MESA Investigators 
for scientific content and consistency of data interpretation with 
previous MESA publications. Significant comments have been 
incorporated prior to submission for publication. The authors 
thank the other investigators, staff, and participants of the MESA 
and MESA-Lung Studies for their valuable contributions. A full list 
of participating MESA Investigators and institutions can be found 
at http://www.mesa-nhlbi.org. </p>



<p>Pulmonary Circulation | July-September 2012 | Vol 2 | No 3 </p>



<p>Ventetuolo et al.: ACE inhibitors, ARBs, and the RV </p>



<p>Pulmonary Circulation | July-September 2012 | Vol 2 | No 3 </p>

<p>
Ventetuolo et al.: ACE inhibitors, ARBs, and the RV </p>



<p>Author Help: Reference checking facility </p>

<p>The manuscript system (www.journalonweb.com) allows the authors to check and verify the accuracy and style of references. The tool checks 
the references with PubMed as per a predefined style. Authors are encouraged to use this facility, before submitting articles to the journal. </p>

<p>• The style as well as bibliographic elements should be 100% accurate, to help get the references verified from the system. Even a </p>

<p>single spelling error or addition of issue number/month of publication will lead to an error when verifying the reference. </p>

<p>• Example of a correct style </p>

<p>Sheahan P, O'leary G, Lee G, Fitzgibbon J. Cystic cervical metastases: Incidence and diagnosis using fine needle aspiration biopsy. 
Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 2002;127:294-8. </p>

<p>• Only the references from journals indexed in PubMed will be checked. 
• Enter each reference in new line, without a serial number. 
• Add up to a maximum of 15 references at a time. 
• If the reference is correct for its bibliographic elements and punctuations, it will be shown as CORRECT and a link to the correct </p>

<p>article in PubMed will be given. </p>

<p>• If any of the bibliographic elements are missing, incorrect or extra (such as issue number), it will be shown as INCORRECT and link to </p>

<p>possible articles in PubMed will be given. </p>

</text></tei>