<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3128530" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT Interactions with vimentin intermediate filaments (VimIFs) affect the motility, dis-
tribution, and anchorage of mitochondria. In cells lacking VimIFs or in which VimIF organiza-
tion is disrupted, the motility of mitochondria is increased relative to control cells that ex-
press normal VimIF networks. Expression of wild-type VimIF in vimentin-null cells causes 
mitochondrial motility to return to normal (slower) rates. In contrast, expressing vimentin 
with mutations in the mid-region of the N-terminal non-α-helical domain (deletions of resi-
dues 41-96 or 45-70, or substitution of Pro-57 with Arg) did not inhibit mitochondrial motil-
ity even though these mutants retain their ability to assemble into VimIFs in vivo. It was also 
found that a vimentin peptide consisting of residues 41-94 localizes to mitochondria. Taken 
together, these data suggest that VimIFs bind directly or indirectly to mitochondria and an-
chor them within the cytoplasm. </p>

<p>Mitochondria are the major source of metabolic energy, and they 
regulate intracellular calcium levels and sequester apoptotic factors 
(Nicholls and Budd, 2000). To meet the varying energy demands of 
different regions of the cytoplasm, mitochondria require an efficient 
transport and tethering system. In support of this idea, it has been 
shown that mitochondria are delivered to and sequestered in areas 
of the cell where metabolic requirements are high (Morris and 
Hollenbeck, 1993; Chada and Hollenbeck, 2003). Mitochondrial 
transport involves microtubule-dependent kinesins and dyneins and 
actin-dependent myosins. Frequently, all three types of motors are 
present on the surface of a single mitochondrion and work in con-
cert to maintain the organelle's correct intracellular localization 
(Hollenbeck and Saxton, 2005). Pathological conditions in neurode-</p>

<p>generative diseases are associated with disrupted transport of mito-
chondria in neural cells (Baloh, 2008). 
There is evidence that the tethering of mitochondria involves in-
termediate filaments (IFs) (Linden et al., 1989; Leterrier et al., 1994; 
Wagner et al., 2003). In vertebrate cells, IFs form extensive intercon-
nected cytoskeletal networks that extend throughout the cytoplasm 
(Goldman et al., 2008). Depending on the cell type, cytoskeletal IFs 
are assembled from one or more of a large multigene family of ∼70 
members (Herrmann et al., 2009). Each type of IF protein chain con-
tains a highly conserved α-helical central rod domain flanked by 
variable, non-α-helical head and tail domains (Herrmann and Aebi, 
2000). The rod domains are responsible for the assembly of the dim-
ers (which are the building blocks of IF), and the head and tail re-
gions are thought to be exposed on the surface of mature 10-nm IF, 
thereby providing potential binding sites for other proteins and or-
ganelles, such as mitochondria. In support of this supposition, IFs 
have been implicated in docking mitochondria in muscle cells 
(Milner et al., 2000; Stone et al., 2007), nerve cells (Straube-West 
et al., 1996; Wagner et al., 2003), and fibroblasts (Mose-Larsen et al., 
1982; Summerhayes et al., 1983). There is also evidence that type III 
VimIFs and neurofilament heavy chain, a type IV IF protein, bind 
directly to mitochondria in vitro and that mitochondrial functions 
require IFs (Milner et al., 2000; Wagner et al., 2003;Tolstonog et al., 
2005; Tao et al., 2009). Mitochondria can also associate with IF 
through interactions with the cytolinker, plectin (Reipert et al., 1999; 
Rezniczek et al., 2003; Winter et al., 2008); and the depletion of </p>

<p>Monitoring Editor 
M. Bishr Omary 
University of Michigan </p>

<p>Received: Sep 15, 2010 
Revised: Apr 19, 2011 
Accepted: May 5, 2011 </p>

<p>MBoC | ARTICLE </p>

<p>Volume 22 July 1, 2011 </p>

<p>VimIFs control mitochondria movement | 2283 </p>

<p>taining the N-terminal domain and the 1A 
α-helical domain of the central rod fused to 
enhanced green fluorescent protein (EGFP)-
Vim (1-138) . EGFP-Vim (1-138) has been shown 
to disrupt VimIF organization (Kural et al., 
2007; Chang et al., 2009). Under these con-
ditions, the VimIF network in transfected 
cells is withdrawn from the cellular periphery 
and reorganized into an aggregate at the 
cell center (Figure 2A) (similar effects are 
seen in MFT-6 cells, not shown) (Kural et al., 
2007; Chang et al., 2009; Mendez et al., 
2010). Despite the fact that the microtubule 
system in these cells remains distributed 
throughout the cytoplasm (Figure 2C), the 
distribution of mitochondria is altered as 
shown by the clustering of these organelles 
in the central region of the cells where 
the majority of the reorganized VimIFs are 
plectin alters the shape of mitochondria, but has no impact on their 
motility (Winter et al., 2008). 
Mutations in IF proteins that cause the disruption of IF networks 
also alter the morphology, distribution, and functions of mitochon-
dria. For example, mutations in desmin IFs cause changes in the 
distribution and function of mitochondria in skeletal muscles and 
heart (Capetanaki, 2002), and a mutation in the neurofilament light 
chain that causes Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease results in the clus-
tering of mitochondria in the cell bodies of neurons (Brownlees 
et al., 2002). In keratinocytes of patients with epidermolysis bullosa 
simplex, caused by mutations in keratins 5 and 14, there is an abnor-
mal distribution of mitochondria (Uttam et al., 1996), and in hepato-
cytes expressing mutant keratins 8 and 18 there is enhanced sus-
ceptibility to apoptosis due to abnormalities in mitochondria (Gilbert 
et al., 2001). Morphological and functional changes in mitochondria 
have also been reported in vimentin-null fibroblasts (Tolstonog 
et al., 2001b). 
In this study we demonstrate that mitochondria associate with 
the non-α-helical N-terminal domain of vimentin and that this bind-
ing inhibits their motility. Overall, the results show that VimIFs play 
essential roles in regulating both the localization and motility of 
mitochondria. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
VimIFs inhibit the motility of mitochondria </p>

<p>The distribution patterns of mitochondria and VimIFs are similar in 
cultured fibroblasts. The network of long VimIFs in these cells en-
circles the nucleus and filaments extend radially toward the cell pe-
riphery. The mitochondria in these cells are also distributed through-
out the perinuclear region, and they are frequently oriented parallel 
to the VimIFs (Figure 1). Although mitochondria are clearly associ-
ated with long VimIFs, they do not appear to associate with the vi-
mentin squiggles or short IF present in the more peripheral cellular 
regions (Figure 1, B and C). The coalignment of mitochondria with 
VimIF could be explained either by their direct interaction or simply 
because the distribution of both depends on transport along mi-
crotubules that have a radial pattern in this cell type (Gyoeva and 
Gelfand, 1991; Rodionov et al., 1993; Prahlad et al., 1998). 
To determine whether this colocalization is caused by an interac-
tion between mitochondria and VimIFs, we analyzed mitochondrial 
distribution and motility in cells after perturbing the VimIF system. 
This analysis was accomplished by transfecting mouse 3T3 and 
MFT-6 fibroblasts with a dominant-negative mutant vimentin con-</p>

<p>FIGURE 1: Mitochondria colocalize with VimIF network in mouse fibroblasts. Cells (3T3) were 
stained with MitoTracker Red CMXRos (Invitrogen; see Materials and Methods). Cells were then 
fixed in methanol (4°C) and stained with anti-vimentin primary antibodies and with secondary 
anti-rabbit antibodies conjugated with AlexaFluor (Invitrogen). VimIFs, mitochondria, and 
phase-contrast image of the same cell are shown as overlay (A). Higher magnification images of 
the two regions shown in A are depicted in B and C; arrows in B show vimentin squiggles. Bar, 
10 μm. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2: Disruption of the VimIF network leads to an altered 
distribution of mitochondria. Cells (3T3) were transfected with 
plasmid pEGFP-Vim (1-138) (A-D) or for control with plasmid pEGFP-
Vim (E and F) using FuGene 6 (Roche). Cells at 24 h posttransfection 
were stained with MitoTracker Deep Red FM (Invitrogen; see 
Materials and Methods) (B, F pseudocolor) and then were fixed in 
methanol (-20°C) and stained with antibodies against α-tubulin 
(Serotech) (C) and anti-vimentin (A), and secondary antibodies 
conjugated with AlexaFluor 568 and AlexaFluor 488 (Invitrogen), 
respectively. (D) Overlay of images in A, B, and C. Normal IFs in the 
cell transfected with the control plasmid in E are visualized by EGFP. 
Bars, 10 μm. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>enabled mitochondria to move faster. By 
tracking the movements of individual mito-
chondria in mouse fibroblasts containing 
disrupted VimIF over time, we have deter-
mined that their motility increases by ∼70% 
(7.0 ± 0.7% vs. 4.0 ± 0.3% in nontransfected 
MFT-6 cells; see Figure 4A) (similar results 
were obtained with 3T3 cells; unpublished 
data). This finding suggests that normal ar-
rays of VimIFs can restrict the movements of 
mitochondria. We also assayed the motility 
of mitochondria in vimentin-null MFT-16 fi-
broblasts (see Materials and Methods; 
Holwell et al., 1997). The proportion of fast 
movements of mitochondria in these cells is 
twice the proportion of fast movements of 
mitochondria in normal (vim 
+/+ ) fibroblasts (9.0 ± 0.5% and 4.0 ± 
0.3%, respectively) (Figure 4B; see Materials and Methods). Further-
more, expression of VimIF in vim-null cells (depicted in Supplemen-
tal Figure S1B) slows the rate of mitochondrial motility to a value 
similar to that seen in normal fibroblasts (4.0 ± 0.7%) (Figure 4B; see 
Materials and Methods). These results support the hypothesis that 
IFs modulate mitochondrial movements. </p>

<p>The N-terminal domain of vimentin is involved in anchoring 
mitochondria </p>

<p>We next sought to determine whether the inhibitory effect of VimIF 
on rates of mitochondrial movements is passive, acting merely to 
obstruct their motility, or whether it results from the binding of 
VimIFs to mitochondria. In the latter case, we should be able to alter 
mitochondrial motility by mutating the interacting vimentin domain. 
To test this possibility, we expressed wild-type or mutated vimentin 
in vimentin-null MFT-16 cells. The design of 
the mutant forms of vimentin focused on 
deletions in the non-α-helical N-terminal 
domain (depicted in Figure 5A). The ratio-
nale for this approach is based on findings 
that numerous N-terminal deletions of vi-
mentin retain their ability to assemble into 
IFs in vitro and in vivo (Herrmann et al., 
1992; Shoeman et al., 2002). Figure 5B 
shows that the recombinant proteins are of 
the expected sizes, and that their expres-
sion level is low compared with endogenous 
vimentin in control cells. Each of these mu-
tant vimentins assembles into VimIF net-
works in vimentin-null cells (Supplemental 
Figure S1) which are indistinguishable from 
the VimIF networks in control cells (Supple-
mental Figure S1, A and B). Although these 
VimIF networks are distributed throughout 
the cytoplasm of transfected cells, they have 
different effects on mitochondrial motility. 
Specifically, the movement of mitochondria 
in cells expressing Vim Δ26-39 is similar to that 
of cells expressing wild-type vimentin 
(Figure 5C). In contrast, following the ex-
pression of either Vim Δ41-96 or Vim Δ45-70 , 
mitochondrial motility is similar to that in 
null cells, suggesting that the mitochondrial 
interacting domain could reside between 
amino acids 45-70. This region meets the </p>

<p>located (Figure 2, B and D). In contrast, 3T3 cells expressing EGFP-
tagged wild-type vimentin contain normal VimIF networks and a 
normal distribution of mitochondria (Figure 2, E and F; also see 
Yoon et al., 1998). These results show that the disruption of the 
VimIF network is accompanied by changes in the distribution and 
location of mitochondria, suggesting that mitochondria are tethered 
to VimIF. Further support for this interaction comes from cells ex-
pressing lower levels of EGFP-Vim (1-138) , in which we observe the 
partial disruption and fragmentation of VimIFs. In such cells, the lo-
calization of mitochondria remains largely unaltered, but they fre-
quently lose their extended morphology and their orientations 
along VimIF (Figure 3). Interestingly, at this stage, the EGFP-Vim (1-138) 
itself frequently associates with mitochondria, suggesting that this 
fragment may contain a mitochondrial binding site. 
We next determined whether the reorganization of VimIFs to-
ward the cell center induced by the expression of EGFP-Vim (1-138) </p>

<p>FIGURE 3: EGFP-Vim (1-138) localizes to mitochondria. Cells (3T3) were transfected with plasmid 
pEGFP-Vim (1-138) using FuGene 6 (Roche) and 24 h later were stained with MitoTracker Deep 
Red FM (Invitrogen; see Materials and Methods) (B) and then were fixed in methanol. 
(A) Epifluorescent image showing GFP localization. (C) Overlay of images in A and B. Bar, 10 μm. </p>

<p>FIGURE 4: An intact VimIF network alters mitochondrial motility. (A) MFT-6 cells transfected 
with pmCherry-Mito (left bar) or with pmCherry-Mito and pEGFP-Vim (1-138) (right bar) using 
Maxifectin (DiaM). (B) MFT-6 cells (+/+); vimentin-null MFT-16 cells (-/-); vimentin null MFT-16 
cotransfected with plasmids pVim and pEGFP-Vim (-/-, +Vim). Cells were also stained with 
MitoTracker Red CMXRos, and movements of fluorescently labeled mitochondria were recorded 
by time-lapse microscopy at 4-s intervals. Values are mean percentages of movements 
exceeding 0.2 μm/s ± SEM; n = number of cells, and, in brackets, the number of movements of 
mitochondria. Disrupting the intact VimIF network results in faster mitochondrial movements 
(A), whereas restoring the VimIF network in null cells slows mitochondrial movement (B). </p>

<p>Volume 22 July 1, 2011 </p>

<p>VimIFs control mitochondria movement | 2285 </p>

<p>polymerization, as evidenced by the loss of 
inhibition following treatment with Latruncu-
lin B (Lat B). To determine whether VimIFs 
modulate the association between mito-
chondria and F-actin, we examined the ef-
fects of LPA in vimentin-null cells. Following 
LPA treatment, the movements of mitochon-
dria in normal fibroblasts are inhibited as pre-
viously described (Figure 7A). In contrast, the 
movements of mitochondria in LPA-treated, 
vimentin-null cells are not altered (Figure 7A). 
Furthermore, treatment with Lat B increases 
the motility of mitochondria in normal fibro-
blasts, but has no effect on the motility of 
mitochondria in vimentin-null cells (Figure 7B). 
These data suggest that VimIFs anchor mito-
chondria and link them to F-actin. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Only a small fraction of mitochondria at the 
periphery of the cell moves with relatively 
high speed (Trinczek et al., 1999; De Vos 
et al., 2003; Minin et al., 2006), whereas the 
majority of these organelles remain immo-
bile or move slowly. The presence of immo-
bile organelles is probably explained by 
their anchoring at sites in the cytoplasm 
where a local supply of ATP is required. Our 
results show that VimIFs modulate mito-
chondrial movements in cultured cells. Our 
results also show that the slower movements 
of mitochondria in the presence of VimIFs is not simply attributable 
to a passive hindrance of their motility (Kural et al., 2007), but rather 
is due to specific interactions of mitochondria with these cytoskeletal 
structures. This conclusion is based on our results showing that sev-
eral vimentin mutants with altered N-terminal domains do not affect 
the motility of mitochondria, despite their ability to polymerize into 
VimIF networks. 
Previous studies suggest two possible mechanisms by which mi-
tochondria might bind to VimIFs: The binding could be mediated 
by an IF-associated protein, plectin isoform 1b, which has been 
shown to localize to mitochondria (Winter et al., 2008), and/or the N 
terminus of vimentin could be involved in a direct or indirect interac-
tion with these organelles (Tolstonog et al., 2001a). In this study we 
show that plectin localizes to all of the mutant forms of vimentin 
(see, e.g., Supplemental Figure S2, D-F, showing colocalization of 
plectin antibody with Vim (P57R) -IFs and data in Gerashchenko et al., 
2009). It is likely that plectin 1b binds to the mutant forms of vimen-
tin used in this study as they all contain the known plectin binding 
site (Rezniczek et al., 2003). It appears therefore that direct interac-
tion with vimentin is responsible for the inhibition of the mitochon-
drial movements. These data are further supported by the results of 
Winter and colleagues showing that plectin depletion does not alter 
mitochondrial motility (Winter et al., 2008). 
Our results also demonstrate that it is the N-terminal domain of 
vimentin which interacts with mitochondria. Furthermore, the frag-
ment of vimentin (residues 41-94) containing this putative binding 
site localized to mitochondria when expressed in vimentin-null 
cells. The proposed binding site meets the requirements for se-
quences targeted to the outer mitochondrial membrane (Allen 
et al., 2002; Rapaport, 2003). Thus it is possible that the availability 
of this binding site at the surface of VimIFs explains their ability to </p>

<p>requirements for sequences targeted to the outer mitochondrial 
membrane as it is moderately hydrophobic with two flanking re-
gions containing positively charged amino acids (depicted in 
Figure 6A) (Rapaport, 2003); there is also a proline residue that has 
been shown to be required for the efficient targeting of some mito-
chondria-localized proteins (Allen et al., 2002). To determine whether 
proline is required for targeting to mitochondria, we transfected 
MFT-16 cells with vimentin P57R (Figure 5A). This mutant forms typ-
ical IF networks in MFT-16 cells (Supplemental Figure S1C), but it 
does not inhibit mitochondrial motility (Figure 5C). 
We also determined whether an N-terminal fragment of vimentin 
containing the putative binding site is targeted to mitochondria 
when expressed in vimentin-null cells. For this we constructed a fu-
sion protein formed with residues 41-94 of vimentin (2 amino acids 
shorter than the deleted fragment in construct Vim Δ(41-96) due to the 
cloning procedure) and fluorescent protein Dendra2 (schematically 
depicted in Figure 6A). The results show that this chimeric protein 
strongly associates with mitochondria when expressed in vimentin-
null cells (Figure 6B). In contrast, a similar fragment bearing the P57R 
mutation does not associate with mitochondria, but distributes dif-
fusely throughout the cytoplasm (Figure 6D). It therefore appears 
that the N terminus of vimentin is involved in the interaction of IFs 
with mitochondria and that Pro-57 is essential for this interaction. </p>

<p>Interaction of mitochondria with F-actin is mediated 
by vimentin IFs </p>

<p>There is evidence that the regulation of mitochondrial motility also 
involves actin. In support of this evidence, we recently demonstrated 
that the growth factor lysophosphatidic acid (LPA), acting through the 
small GTPase RhoA and its effector mDia1, inhibits mitochondrial 
motility (Minin et al., 2006). This inhibition is dependent on actin </p>

<p>FIGURE 5: Effects of vimentin mutants on mitochondrial motility. (A) Schematic representation 
of wild type and mutant vimentin constructs used in this study. WT -full-length vimentin showing 
N-and C-terminal domains, and central domain formed by four α-helical rich regions; deletion 
mutants of vimentin: Vim Δ(26-39) , Vim Δ(41-96) , and Vim Δ(45-70) and full-length vimentin containing 
P57R point mutation. (B) Western blot analysis of vimentin expression in MFT-6 cells (+/+) using 
antibody RVIM-AT directed against mouse vimentin or MFT-16 cells before (-/-) or after 
transfection with plasmids encoding wild type or mutant forms of human vimentin using the V9 
antibody. α-tubulin was used as a loading control (DM1a antibody; Sigma). (C) Movements of 
mitochondria were analyzed in vimentin-null cells cotransfected with plasmids encoding the 
vimentin mutants and plasmids that encode the same mutants tagged with mCherry and 
pEGFP-Mito using Maxifectin. Only cells that contained well-formed IF networks (examples are 
shown in Supplemental Figure S1) were selected for the analysis. Values are mean percentage of 
movements exceeding 0.2 μm/s ± SEM; n = number of cells (approximately 500 movements in 
each cell). Statistical analysis (Student's t test) of the data is given in supplemental materials. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>This reasoning led us to propose that actin stress fibers are respon-
sible for anchoring mitochondria at the cell periphery. Here we show 
that the disruption of F-actin by Lat B, or the induction of stress fi-
bers by LPA, affects mitochondrial motility only in the presence of 
VimIFs. Thus, our results suggest that vimentin may act as an adap-
tor between mitochondria and actin microfilaments. We therefore 
propose that mitochondria are associated with VimIFs directly 
through binding to the vimentin N terminus and/or indirectly by 
means of plectin (Winter et al., 2008), whereas the interaction of 
VimIFs with F-actin structures is mediated by plectin (see Figure 8; 
Svitkina et al., 1996; Wiche, 1998). </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Cell culture </p>

<p>Mouse 3T3 cells (American Type Culture Collection, Manassas, 
VA) were maintained in DMEM (Invitrogen) supplemented with </p>

<p>directly bind to mitochondria. Further support for this proposition 
comes from our studies of the Pro57Arg replacement which pre-
vents the binding of the 41-94 amino acid fragment to mitochon-
dria. This replacement also prevents VimIF from suppressing mito-
chondrial motility. 
The regulation of this novel type of interaction between VimIF 
and mitochondria remains unknown. There are several serine resi-
dues within the putative mitochondrial binding domain of vimentin 
which are phosphorylated by known protein kinases, however. For 
example, Ser56 is phosphorylated by p21-activating kinase (Goto 
et al., 2002; Tang et al., 2005). Therefore it is possible that such mod-
ifications could regulate the association between VimIFs and mito-
chondria. 
It is also important to consider the role of VimIFs in the interac-
tion of mitochondria with other cytoskeletal structures. Previously 
we showed that the induction of stress fibers by LPA is accompanied 
by an inhibition of mitochondrial movements and their anchorage to 
the cell periphery (Minin et al., 2006). This effect, which is mediated 
by the small GTPase RhoA and its effector mDia1, can be completely 
abolished by the disruption of F-actin by Lat B (Minin et al., 2006). </p>

<p>FIGURE 7: VimIFs mediate the interaction of mitochondria with 
F-actin. Cells were transfected with plasmid pEGFP-Mito using 
Maxifectin. The movements of fluorescently labeled mitochondria in 
normal and vimentin-null cells were recorded using time-lapse video 
microscopy before and after incubation with 5 μM LPA for 5 min (A) or 
before and after incubation with 0.2 μM Lat B for 20 min (B). Values are 
mean percentage of movements exceeding 0.2 μm/s ± SEM; n = 
number of cells, and, in brackets, number of mitochondrial movements. </p>

<p>FIGURE 6: Localization of the vimentin N-terminal fragment Vim (41-94) 
and its mutant variant expressed in vimentin-null cells. (A) Schematic 
of the vimentin fragment tagged with the fluorescent protein 
Dendra2 (green aster); positively charged arginine residues are 
highlighted in green; R above P-57 represents the substitution of 
proline for arginine in mutant variant. Cells were transfected with 
pVim (41-94) -Dendra2 (B) or pVim (41-94) -P57R-Dendra2 (D) using 
Lipofectamine 2000, and mitochondria were stained with MitoTracker 
Red CMXRos (C and E). Bar, 10 μm. </p>

<p>Volume 22 July 1, 2011 </p>

<p>VimIFs control mitochondria movement | 2287 </p>

<p>of vimentin N terminus, PCR was performed with primers TT-
TAAGCTTATGGGCAGCGCGCTGCGCCCCA and AGTCGCGGC-
CGCTTACCACACCTGGCT and pVim (1-94) -Dendra2 as a template, 
and the resulting product encoding vimentin fragment fused to 
Dendra2 was inserted into the pDendra2-N vector cut with HindIII 
and NotI. The plasmid pVim (P57R) encoding vimentin with a Pro57Arg 
substitution was generated using a QuickChange Site-directed Mu-
tagenesis Kit (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA), according to the manufac-
turer's protocol. 
Transfection was performed using Maxifectin M (DiaM, 
Moscow, Russia), FuGene 6 (Roche, Pleasanton, CA), or Lipo-
fectamine 2000 (Invitrogen), according to the manufacturer's in-
structions. DNA (1 μg) was used for a 40-mm dish with 2 ml of 
medium. Cells were observed 16-20 h after transfection. For live 
cell analysis of mitochondrial movements in transiently trans-
fected cells, the expression level of recombinant vimentin variants 
was monitored by fluorescence microscopy of IFs labeled by co-
expressed EGFP-or mCherry-fused vimentin forms as described 
(Yoon et al., 1998), using cotransfection of plasmids encoding un-
labeled vimentin forms with plasmids encoding their EGFP-or 
mCherry-tagged variants. Only cells with dense IF meshwork were 
taken for further analysis (see examples in Supplemental Figure 
S1). To obtain flat cells with better distributed mitochondria, 
sparse cultures were usually used. Sixteen to twenty hours post-
transfection, 15 ng/ml MitoTrackerRed CMXRos or Deep Red FM 
(Invitrogen) was added to the culture medium and the cells incu-
bated for 30 min before this medium was removed and replaced 
with fresh medium. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence </p>

<p>IF staining in cell preparations was performed by indirect immuno-
fluorescence using the mouse monoclonal antibody V9 (Chemicon 
International, Martinsried/Munich, Germany), the polyclonal rabbit 
antibody anti-vimentin (Helfand et al., 2003), or RVIM-AT (which re-
acts with murine vimentin [Avsyuk et al., 1997]), and FITC-or TRITC-
labeled goat anti-mouse or goat anti-rabbit (The Jackson Labora-
tory, Bar Harbor, ME). Microtubules were stained using primary 
antibodies anti-α-tubulin (AbD Serotech, Raleigh, NC). Plectin was 
stained using antibody #46 (Wiche and Baker, 1982) and TRITC-
labeled goat anti-rabbit antibody (Jackson ImmunoResearch, 
West Grove, PA). Before staining, cells were either fixed with meth-
anol (-20°C) or 4% formaldehyde in phosphate-buffered saline 
(PBS) and permeabilized with 0.1% Triton X-100 or, for better reso-
lution of fine structures, first extracted with 1% Triton X-100 in 
50 mM imidazole buffer, pH 6.8, containing 50 mM KCl, 0.5 mM 
MgCl 2 , 0.1 mM EDTA, 1 mM EGTA, and then fixed with 4% formal-
dehyde in PBS. </p>

<p>Live cell imaging </p>

<p>Cells were grown on glass coverslips to a density of 50-70% conflu-
ence, and coverslips were mounted in a chamber filled with DMEM 
supplemented with 10% FCS. Temperature was maintained at 37 ± 
2ºC with an Air Stream Incubator (Zeiss, Göttingen, Germany). Time-
lapse epifluorescence microscopy was carried out on an Axiophot 
microscope (Zeiss) equipped with a Plan-Apochromat 63× 1.4 NA 
objective. Images were captured with a Micromax 782Y cooled 
CCD camera (Roper Scientific) driven by <rs type="software">WinView32</rs> software 
or with a AxioCam MRm camera (Zeiss) driven by <rs id="software-1" type="software">AxioVizion</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">4.6</rs> 
(Zeiss) software. The frames were collected every 4 s with an expo-
sure time of 0.5-1.0 s. To minimize phototoxic damage, a 100 W 
halogen lamp was used as a light source for fluorescent imaging 
of live cells. </p>

<p>10% fetal calf serum (FCS), 100 U/ml penicillin, and 100 μg/ml 
streptomycin. 
Murine cell lines MFT-16 (derived from a vimentin-knockout 
mouse) and MFT-6 (derived from a wild-type mouse) were provided 
by R. Evans (University of Colorado, Denver) (Holwell et al., 1997). 
These cells were maintained in DMEM supplemented with 10% 
FCS, 100 U/ml penicillin, and 100 μg/ml streptomycin. For micro-
scopic observations, cells were plated on coverslips at least 16-20 h 
before experiments were performed. </p>

<p>Plasmids and transfection </p>

<p>Mitochondria in cells were tagged using pEGFP-Mito or pmCherry-
Mito plasmid vectors that were prepared by modification of pEYFP-
Mito (Clontech, Mountain View, CA). Plasmids pEGFP-Vim and 
pEGFP-Vim (1-138) , which encode EGFP-tagged human vimentin and 
its N-terminal polypeptide (1-138 amino acids), respectively, were 
described previously (Yoon et al., 1998; Kural et al., 2007). Plasmids 
encoding unlabeled human vimentin and mCherry-tagged wild 
type and mutated human vimentin were prepared by modification 
of the plasmid pEGFP-Vim using standard techniques. Plasmids en-
coding vimentin mutants retaining the ability to form IFs were made 
as described previously (Gerashchenko et al., 2009). Briefly, to make 
the plasmid encoding Vim Δ(41-96) (Figure 5A), an inverted PCR was 
performed using the plasmid encoding human vimentin as a tem-
plate and the primers AAGAACACCCGCACCAACGAGA and 
CAGGCTGTAGGTGCGGGT. The resulting product was ligated by 
its blunt ends to make the deletion mutant. Similarly, the plasmids 
encoding Vim Δ(26-39) and Vim Δ(45-70) (Figure 5A) were generated by 
using the primer pairs 1) GCTCGGCCGGCTCGCGGTGCCCGG 
and 
CTGGGCAGCGCGCTGCGCCCCAGCACCA, 
and 
2) 
CAGCGCGCTGCCCAGGCTGTAGGT and CGGAGCAGCGTGC-
CCGGGGT, respectively. The plasmid pVim (41-94) -Dendra2 encod-
ing the fragment of the N-terminal domain of human vimentin 
tagged with fluorescent protein Dendra2 (Gurskaya et al., 2006) was 
prepared in two steps. First, we made the plasmid pVim (1-94) -Den-
dra2 encoding the entire head domain of human vimentin fused to 
the N terminus of Dendra2. For that purpose PCR was performed 
using the primers TTTAAGCTTATGTCCACCAGGT and AAACCG-
GTCCGGTGTTGATG, and the resulting product was inserted into 
vector pDendra2-N (Evrogene, Moscow, Russia) between HindIII-
Age1 sites. Then, to obtain the plasmid-encoding shorter fragment </p>

<p>FIGURE 8: Schematic representation of the association of VimIFs with 
mitochondria through vimentin N termini exposed on the filament 
surface and by means of plectin. IF interactions with F-actin bundles 
(stress fibers) mediated by plectin are also shown. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting </p>

<p>Electrophoretic separation of proteins was performed using discon-
tinuous 7.5% SDS-PAGE gels (Laemmli, 1970). For analysis of 
the expression of human vimentin and its mutants in transfected 
MFT-16 cells, samples of whole-cell protein extracts were run on 
gels and electroblotted onto nitrocellulose membrane (Hybond, GE 
Healthcare). Protein derived from whole-cell extracts of MFT-6 cells 
were also included in these analyses to show the level of endoge-
nously expressed vimentin. The blots were stained with Ponceau S, 
blocked for 1 h in 5% goat serum in PBS containing 0.1% Tween 20, 
and subsequently incubated with 1 μg/ml of either V9 directed 
against human vimentin or RVIM-AT against mouse vimentin, in 
blocking solution for 1 h. After washing, the blots were incubated 
with horseradish peroxidase-conjugated goat anti-rabbit or anti-
mouse immu noglobulin (Jackson ImmunoResearch, West Grove, 
PA) at a dilution of 1:5000 (vol:vol). Diaminobenzidine (Sigma, 
St. Louis, MO) was used to detect antibody binding. Tubulin was 
used as a loading control with anti-α-tubulin (DM1a; Sigma). </p>

<p>Quantitative analysis of mitochondrial motility </p>

<p>Image analysis was performed as described earlier (Minin et al., 
2006) using an open source image analysis software, <rs id="software-2" type="software">ImageJ</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-2" type="url">http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij</rs>). Because of the diverse morphology of 
mitochondria, we plotted the coordinates of one end for longer 
organelles and the center of mass for shorter ones. Mitochondrial 
motility was expressed in terms of the displacement distances and 
velocities. To define fast organelle movements, we applied a 
threshold of 200 nm/s. The values of the relative motility of mito-
chondria were expressed as mean percentages of fast movements 
in all recorded displacements ± SEM. In each experiment, 20-40 
individual mitochondrial movements were analyzed in each of 
10-15 cells. The significance of differences was estimated statisti-
cally by the paired-sample Student's t test. Variability of the values 
calculated for different cells in the samples was analyzed by the 
same method and was insignificant. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank R. Evans for the cell lines, K. Hahn for genetic constructs, 
G. Wiche for anti-plectin antibody, and Natalia Minina for excellent 
technical assistance. This work was funded by the Russian Academy 
of Sciences and Russian Foundation for Basic Research (Grants 
06-04-48452-a and 10-04-00414-a to A.A.M.) and by grants from 
the National Institutes of Health to V.I.G. (GM 52111) and R.D.G. 
(GM 036806). </p>



<p>Volume 22 July 1, 2011 </p>

<p>VimIFs control mitochondria movement | 2289 </p>



</text></tei>