<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3694247" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: A 28 amino-acid (aa) cell-penetrating peptide (p28) derived from azurin, a redox protein secreted from the 
opportunistic pathogen Pseudomonas aeruginosa, produces a post-translational increase in p53 in cancer cells by inhibiting its 
ubiquitination. </p>

<p>Methods: In silico computational simulations were used to predict motifs within the p53 DNA-binding domain (DBD) as potential 
sites for p28 binding. In vitro direct and competitive pull-down studies as well as western blot and RT-PCR analyses were used to 
validate predictions. </p>

<p>Results: The L1 loop (aa 112-124), a region within the S7-S8 loop (aa 214-236) and T140, P142, Q144, W146, R282 and L289 of the 
p53DBD were identified as potential sites for p28 binding. p28 decreased the level of the E3 ligase COP1 480%, in p53 
wt and </p>

<p>p53 
mut cells with no decrease in COP1 in p53dom/neg or p53null cells. Brief increases in the expression of the E3 ligases, </p>

<p>TOPORS, Pirh2 and HDM2 (human double minute 2) in p53 
wt and p53 
mut cells were in response to sustained increases in p53. </p>

<p>Conclusion: These data identify the specific motifs within the DBD of p53 that bind p28 and suggest that p28 inhibition of COP1 
binding results in the sustained, post-translational increase in p53 levels and subsequent inhibition of cancer cell growth 
independent of an HDM2 pathway. </p>

<p>The cupredoxin azurin preferentially enters a wide variety of 
cancer cells, inducing p53-mediated cytostatic and cytotoxic 
(apoptotic) effects in murine and human cancer cells (Yamada  et al, 2002; Punj et al, 2004; Apiyo and Wittung-Stafshede, 2005;  Bizzarri and Cannistraro, 2009). Molecular modeling and atomic 
force microscopy studies suggest that azurin binds to the flexible L 1 
and S 7 -S 8 loops of the p53 DNA-binding domain (DBD), forming 
a stable complex through tight protein-protein interactions (De  Grandis et al, 2007; Taranta et al, 2008). Amino acids (aa) 50-67 
(p18) and 50-77 (p28) of azurin represent the protein transport 
domain (Yamada et al, 2005; Taylor et al, 2009) and motif 
(Yamada et al, 2009) responsible for azurin's antiproliferative 
activity, respectively. Exposure of p53 
wt MCF-7 breast cancer cells 
to p28 induces a post-translational increase in the level and activity 
of p53, inhibits the cell cycle at the G 2 -M transition and induces 
apoptosis, but not in the isogenic p53 
dom/neg cell line MDD2 
(Shaulian et al, 1992; Yamada et al, 2009). </p>

<p>Intracellular levels of p53 are tightly regulated by a series of 
ubiquitin E3 ligases that promote ubiquitination and proteasomal 
degradation of p53 (Michael and Oren, 2003). The most prominent 
is HDM2 (human double minute 2) (Haupt et al, 1997). Current 
small-molecule HDM2 antagonists MI-219/AT-219, RITA, 
PXN727, Nutlins (cis-imidazoline analogues) and JNJ-26854165 
(Cheok et al, 2011) bind to HDM2 and inhibit the subsequent 
ubiquitination and proteolysis of wild-type p53. Unlike these 
agents, p28 forms a complex (Bizzarri et al, 2011) within aa 80-276 
of the p53DBD that decreases ubiquitination (Yamada et al, 2009)  and proteasomal degradation of p53 via an HDM2-independent 
pathway (Yamada et al, 2009). In addition to HDM2, other E3 
ligases, COP1 (constitutively photomorphogenic 1), Pirh2 (p53-
induced RING-H2 domain protein) and TOPORS (topoisomerase 
I binding, arginine/serine rich), also reportedly bind to p53 and 
negatively regulate intracellular levels of p53 (Leng et al, 2003;  Dornan et al, 2004a; Dornan et al, 2004b; Rajendra et al, 2004; </p>

<p>*Correspondence: Dr CW Beattie; E-mail: cbeattie@uic.edu </p>

<p>Received 26 April 2013; accepted 8 May 2013; published online 4 June 2013 </p>

<p>&amp; 2013 Cancer Research UK. All rights reserved 0007 -0920/13 </p>

<p>FULL PAPER </p>

<p>Keywords: p53; COP1; cell penetrating peptide; cell cycle; ubiquitination; E3 ligases </p>

<p>British Journal of Cancer (2013) 108, 2495-2504 | doi: 10.1038/bjc.2013.266 </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.266 
2495 </p>

<p>Dornan et al, 2006; Wang et al, 2011). COP1 is reportedly 
overexpressed in breast, ovarian and hepatocellular carcinomas, 
and gastric cancer (Li et al, 2012) predictive of survival in the latter 
(Dornan et al, 2004b), suggesting it contributes to the accelerated 
degradation of the p53 protein and attenuating the tumour 
suppressor function of p53 (Dornan et al, 2004b). Silencing COP1 
inhibits tumour growth and suggests COP1 may be a promising 
target for systemic therapy (Lee et al, 2010). 
In contrast, COP1 also reportedly acts as a developmentally 
dependent tumour suppressor (Migliorini et al, 2011; Vitari et al,  2011), interacting with the oncoprotein c-Jun (Bianchi et al, 2003)  to keep c-Jun at constitutively low levels in vivo and modulate 
c-Jun/AP-1 transcriptional activity in mice bred to be genetically 
hypomorphic at the COP1 locus (Migliorini et al, 2011). A COP1 
deficiency also reportedly leads to c-Jun upregulation in human 
cancer cells (Migliorini et al, 2011), suggesting COP1 is also a 
tumour suppressor that functions, at least in part, by antagonising 
c-Jun oncogenic activity in the absence of a genetic interaction 
between COP1 and p53 (Migliorini et al, 2011). Here, we report the 
underlying mechanism for the post-translational increase in 
p53 
wt,mut levels induced by p28 in breast cancer and melanoma 
cells. p28 inhibits the binding of COP1 to a specific motif of the 
p53DBD, leading to an autoreduction in COP1 levels (Dornan  et al, 2006) and an increase in the level of p53 in the absence of any 
alteration in c-Jun. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Peptide synthesis. p28 (Leu 
50 -Asp 
77 LSTAADMQGVVTDGMAS 
GLDKDYLKPDD, 2914 Da) was synthesised by C S Bio, Inc. 
(Menlo Park, CA, USA) at 495% purity and mass balance. </p>

<p>Molecular dynamics. Computer simulations were performed 
essentially as described (De Grandis et al, 2007; Bizzarri et al,  2009). Configurations for azurin and the DBD of p53 were taken 
from 1E5Z and 1TUP of PDB files, respectively. The 28 aa of p28 
was cut from the crystallographic structure for azurin and used to 
generate the configuration file subsequently applied to MD 
simulations at 300 K and P ¼ 1 bar. Complete details for MD are 
in the Supplementary Materials and Methods. </p>

<p>Docking studies. ClusPro (Kozakov et al, 2010) was used to 
conduct automated docking as a six-dimensional search within the 
rotational space between the two molecules. This generated a set of 
possible configurations for a predicted series of p53DBD-p28 
complexes that were ranked based on scoring. The predicted 
complexes were then subjected to cluster analysis under a pairwise 
binding site root mean squared deviation criterion. The cluster 
model with the best score was used to further compare the protein-
protein interface using the ProtorP: Protein-Protein Interface 
Analysis Server (Reynolds et al, 2009). </p>

<p>Cell proliferation and xenograft tumour assays. Human breast 
cancer cells MCF-7, p53  wt (ATCC, Manassas, VA, USA), the 
isogenic MDD2, p53 
dom/neg (Shaulian et al, 1992) (courtesy of Dr 
Andrei V. Gudkov, Roswell Park Cancer Institute, Buffalo, NY, 
USA) and MDA-MB-231, p53 </p>

<p>mut </p>

<p>, as well as normal breast (MCF-
10A, p53 
wt ) (ATCC) and melanoma cells (UISO-Mel-6, p53 
null ; 
UISO-Mel-23, p53 
mut ; UISO-Mel-29, p53 </p>

<p>wt </p>

<p>) (Kichina et al, 2003)  were cultured as described (Yamada et al, 2002; Punj et al, 2004;  Taylor et al, 2009). p28 is a stable peptide that binds to p53 in the 
cell nucleus (Yamada et al, 2009) with intracellular concentrations 
reaching 120 ng ml 
À 1 (p28) or 0.042 (mmol l 
À 1 ) 2 h post exposure 
to 100 mmol l 
À 1 p28, which eliminated the need for repeated 
exposure. The effect of p28 on cell growth was determined by 
direct cell counting (Taylor et al, 2009). </p>

<p>Human melanoma (Mel-29, -23 and -6) and breast cancer cells 
(MCF-7 and MDA-MB-231) were injected s.c. in the right flank of 
5-to 6-week-old male and female athymic mice (Punj et al, 2004;  Jia et al, 2011; Mehta et al, 2011). When tumours reached 3 mm in 
diameter, animals were randomised into control (20 mice) and 
treatment (10 mice) groups, and injected i.p. with DTIC (5-(3,3-
dimethyl-1-triazeno) imidazole-4-carboxamide), 4 mg kg 
À 1 , 3 Â 
/week (melanoma); paclitaxel, 12.8 mg kg 
À 1 i.p., days 10, 14, 21 
and 25 (breast cancer); or p28 10 or 20 mg kg 
À 1 i.p. 3 Â /week for 
30 days. Although p28 is rapidly cleared (t ½ 0.06 h; clearance 
(ml kg 
À 1 h 
À 1 ) 2159), it is also rapidly taken up (Vdss (ml kg 
À 1 ) 
297) at pharmacologically active doses (Punj et al, 2004; Jia et al,  2011; Mehta et al, 2011). p28 is also stable in murine serum (t 1/2 
B60 min) (Punj et al, 2004; Jia et al, 2011; Mehta et al, 2011)  assuring a continuous release of the mature peptide. At necropsy, 
tumours were dissected, freed of fat and weighed. Statistical 
comparisons were performed by analysis of variance ANOVA 
(control vs treatment) (<rs id="software-0" type="software">GraphPad InStat</rs> ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3.0</rs>, La Jolla, CA, 
USA). </p>

<p>Western blot analysis and RT-PCR. Human breast and mela-
noma cells were cultured with p28 at 50 mmol l 
À 1 for 24-72 h, 
whole-cell lysates prepared and western blot analysis conducted 
(Yamada et al, 2002; Yamada et al, 2009). A list of antibodies used 
is provided in Supplementary Materials and Methods. Band 
intensity was determined using UN-SCAN-IT (Silk Scientific 
Inc., Orem, Utah). Each control and experimental band was 
normalised by calculating the ratio of a specific protein/actin. Each 
experimental level was then expressed as the (relative) percentage 
of control. 
Total RNA was extracted from human breast and melanoma 
cells exposed to p28, and RT-PCR conducted as previously 
described (Yamada et al, 2009). Primer sets are described under 
Supplementary Materials. Each control and experimental band was 
normalised by calculating the ratio of a specific gene/GAPDH. 
Each experimental level was then expressed as the (relative) 
percentage of control. The data are representative of at least two 
independent measures. </p>

<p>Construction and purification of p53 fragments. Plasmid 
pGEX5X3 (GE Healthcare, Little Chalfont, United Kingdom) 
expressing GST fused to fragments of human p53 
wt were 
constructed by PCR (Yamada et al, 2009). DNA fragments 
encoding aa 1-80, 81-300, 81-160, 161-300 and 301-393 of p53 
were amplified with specific primer sets (Supplementary Materials 
and Methods) and GST-fusion proteins purified by Glutathione 
Sepharose 4B affinity chromatography and HiLoad Superdex 75 
gel-filtration column connected to the Ä KTAprime plus FPLC 
system (GE Healthcare) (Yamada et al, 2009). </p>

<p>GST pull-down assays. p28 binding to fragments of p53 was 
analysed using a GST pull-down assay (Yamada et al, 2009). GST 
fused to fragments of p53 and GST alone were bound to 
glutathione-Sepharose 4B beads (GE Healthcare), p28 added and 
incubated for 2 h. Each sample was loaded on 6% native-PAGE. 
Membranes were incubated with polyclonal anti-p28 antibody, 
washed three times with Tris-HCl containing 0.05% Tween 20, 
secondary rabbit IgG-HRP antibody (Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, 
USA). COP1 binding to p53 in the presence or absence of p28 was 
analysed using competitive pull-down assays (Hosaka et al, 2005). 
GST fused to fragments of p53 were immobilised on beads, 
followed by incubating with or without p28 (10-100 mole excess). 
Whole-cell lysates containing COP1 were prepared from MCF-7 
cells in PBS containing 0.1% Triton X-100, 10% glycerol and a 
protease inhibitor cocktail (Sigma-Aldrich). Soluble extracts were 
incubated with beads, each sample washed with PBS, pelleted and 
analysed with an anti-COP1 antibody. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Peptide inhibition of COP1 </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.266 </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Docking simulation of p28-p53 complex. ClusPro identified 
motifs spanning the L 1 loop (aa 112-124), within aa 139-146, a 
region within the S 7 -S 8 loop (aa 214-236) and R282 and L289 of 
the p53 DBD (Tu et al, 2008) that were involved in the binding 
between p28 and p53 (Figure 1A). Molecular surface and 
electrostatic potential plots of the p53DBD were calculated by 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">DeepView</rs> ver. <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">4.0.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics</rs>, Geneva, 
Switzerland) (Figure 1B). A blue, red and white colour gradient 
represents positive, negative and neutral (including hydrophobic 
aa) potentials on the molecular surface, respectively. The DNA-
binding surface of the p53DBD is highly cationic (blue). In 
contrast, the p28-binding area is essentially neutral (white), 
suggesting that electrostatic interaction may not have a role in 
p28 binding to p53 (Figure 1B). The amino-acid composition of 
the predicted p28-binding sites on p53 was FLHSGTAVTCTYPA 
LTPQWEGSDCTHRL or 43% hydrophobic, 36% neutral and 21% 
hydrophilic residues. p28 bound to 10 of 13 aa (77%) in the L 1 loop 
that were 50% hydrophobic, 40% neutral and 10% hydrophilic 
residues and 7 of 23 aa (30%), 14% hydrophobic, 43% neutral and 
43% hydrophilic, in the S 7 -S 8 loops (Figure 1C). The four amino 
acids residing between residues 139 and 147 predicted to bind p28 
are 50% hydrophobic and 50% neutral. These residues and the L 1 
and S 7 -S 8 loops are not located at or near the DNA-binding 
surface of p53 (R248 and R273 are direct DNA-binding residues on </p>

<p>p53), suggesting p28 does not interfere with the ability of p53 to 
bind to DNA (Figure 1B). The ClusPro best score model also 
predicted that amino-acid residues LSTAAMQVVGDYLKDD of 
p28 bind to p53. Fifty per cent of the predicted residues are 
hydrophobic, again suggesting that hydrophobic rather than 
electrostatic interaction is essential to the formation of the 
p28-p53 complex (Figure 1B). These results agree with computa-
tional docking (De Grandis et al, 2007) studies demonstrating that 
azurin binds to the L 1 and S 7 -S 8 loops of p53 through interaction 
of non-polar residues at the interface, creating a short-range 
hydrophobic interaction. A sequence map of the amino acids 
predicted to be involved in p28 binding and their relationship to 
the known binding sites of the E3 ubiquitin ligases that negatively 
regulate p53 is illustrated in Figure 1D. p28 does not bind to motifs 
shown to bind either HDM2 or Pirh2. </p>

<p>GST pull-down assays. p28-binding regions on p53 were mapped 
using a GST pull-down assay (Yamada et al, 2009). GST-p53 1-393  (full length p53), GST-p53 81-300 (p53DBD), GST-p53 81-160 and 
GST-p53 161-300 pulled down p28, but the N-(GST-p53 1-80 ) and 
C-terminus of p53 (GST-p53 301-393 ) and GST alone did not 
(Figure 2A). These results confirm computerised predictions of 
regions within the DBD of p53 likely to bind p28 (Figure 1A-D). 
We confirmed that binding motifs for p28 and COP1 overlap using 
competitive pull-down assays of purified GST-p53 and GST alone 
in the presence of excess p28. p28 induced a significant 
concentration-dependent reduction in the amount of COP1 </p>

<p>L 1 loop </p>

<p>S 7 -S 8 loop </p>

<p>F113 
L114 
H115 </p>

<p>S116 
G117 </p>

<p>T118 </p>

<p>A119 
V122 </p>

<p>T123 </p>

<p>C124 </p>

<p>E224 
G226 
S227 
D228 
C229 </p>

<p>T231 </p>

<p>H233 </p>

<p>1MEEPQSDPSVEPPLSQETFSDLWKLLPENNVLSPLPSQAMDDLMLSPDDIEQWFTEDPGPDEAPRMPEAA </p>

<p>71PRVAPAPAAPTPAAPAPAPSWPLSSSVPSQKTYQGSYGFRLGFLHSGTAKSVTCTYSPAL </p>

<p>131 NKMFCQLAKTCPVQLWVDSTPPPGTRVRAMAIYKQSQHMTEVVRRCPHHERCSDSDGLAP </p>

<p>191PQHLIRVEGNLRVEYLDDRNTFRHSVVVPYEPPEVGSDCTTIHYNYMCNSSCMGGMNRRP </p>

<p>251 ILTIITLEDSSGNLLGRNSFEVRVCACPGRDRRTEEENLRKKGEPHHELPPGSTKRALSN </p>

<p>311NTSSSPQPKKKPLDGEYFTLQIRGRERFEMFRELNEALELKDAQAGKEPGGSRAHSSHLK </p>

<p>371SKKGQSTSRHKKLMFKTEGPDSD </p>

<p>COP1 </p>

<p>HDM2 </p>

<p>Pirh2 </p>

<p>L 1 loop </p>

<p>COP1 </p>

<p>S 7 -S 8 loop </p>

<p>Figure 1. Docking model of p28 and p53. (A) The p28-p53 complex structure obtained from the best docking model. Blue: overall ribbon diagram 
of the p53DBD, green: L 1 and S 7 -S 8 loops. (B) Ribbon diagram of the p53DBD (yellow) superimposed on the electrostatic potential plot. p28 
(green) binds to hydrophobic pocket. (C) Relationship of p28 (green) and L 1 (blue) and S 7 -S 8 (yellow) loops of the p53DBD. (D) Map of 
E3 ligase binding regions superimposed on the full-length sequence of p53. p28-binding residues indicated in red. Binding regions of HDM2, 
COP1 and Pirh2 indicated in black, green and blue bars, respectively. COP1 binds to p53 in regions separate from HDM2. p28 and COP1 
share a binding motif within aa 92-160 of the p53DBD. </p>

<p>Peptide inhibition of COP1 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.266 </p>

<p>
binding to the DBD of p53 (Figure 2B). Fine mapping of the 
regions within the p53DBD revealed that p28 inhibited the binding 
of COP1 to only GST-p53 81-300 and GST-p53 81-160 , clearly 
demonstrating that p28 inhibits the binding of COP1 to p53 only 
where their respective binding sites overlap (Figure 2C). </p>

<p>Effect of p28 on the growth of human cancer cells. p28 produces 
a time and dose-related inhibition of p53 
wt tumour cell and 
xenograft growth (Yamada et al, 2009; Jia et al, 2011). Figure 3A 
shows that a 72-h exposure to p28 at 50 mmol l 
À 1 decreased the 
proliferation of (p53 
wt ) Mel-29 and (p53 
mut ) Mel-23, where p53 is 
internally deleted at aa 178-183 (Kichina et al, 2003), B25-30% 
from control. The inhibition was similar to that of 50 mmol l </p>

<p>À 1 </p>

<p>DTIC. Neither p28 nor DTIC altered the proliferation of p53 </p>

<p>null </p>

<p>Mel-6 cells. p28 also exhibited significant cytostatic activity on 
p53 
wt MCF-7 breast cancer cells with a similar reduction (B20%) 
in the number of (p53 
mut R280K) MDA-MB-231 cells after 72 h 
(Figure 3B). These observations, in contrast, p28 did not exhibit an 
antiproliferative effect on MDD2 (p53 
dom/neg ) or normal MCF-10A 
(p53 
wt ) mammary cells confirming previous results (Yamada et al, 
2009). Paclitaxel at 50 mmol l 
À 1 inhibited the growth of MCF-7 
and MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cells by B90% and MDD2 
(p53 
dom/neg ) and MCF-10 A (p53 
wt ) cells by B50% and 35%, 
respectively (Figure 3B). p28 also significantly decreased the weight 
of established p53 
wt Mel-29 and p53 
mut Mel-23 xenograft tumours 
in athymic mice (Figure 3C). p28 did not inhibit cell growth of 
p53 
null Mel-6 in vitro (Figure 3A) or in vivo (Figure 3C). p28 also 
decreased the weight of MCF-7 (p53 
wt ) and MDA-MB-213 
(p53 </p>

<p>mut </p>

<p>) xenograft tumours by B50 and 60% respectively, similar 
to the effect of a non-toxic dose of paclitaxel (Mi et al, 2002) 
(Figure 3D). The significant reduction in growth at 20 mg kg </p>

<p>À 1 </p>

<p>and lack of effect at 10 mg kg 
À 1 on MDA-MB-231 cells contrast 
sharply with the similarity in effect for either dose of p28 on 
p53 
wt MCF-7, Mel-29 or p53 
mut Mel-23 cells, suggesting the 
site of the mutation may be critical to overexpression of p53 
(Figures 4A and 5A) and to the overall effect of p28 on the 
proliferation of p53 
mut cancer cells. </p>

<p>p28 Alters the level of p53 and major downstream targets. The 
significant decrease in growth following exposure to p28 was 
associated with a sustained increase in the level of p53 in p53 </p>

<p>wt </p>

<p>MCF-7 and p53 
mut MDA-MB-231 cells (Figure 4A) and p53 </p>

<p>wt </p>

<p>Mel-29 and p53 
mut Mel-23 cells (Figure 5A) with no alteration in </p>

<p>the level of transcription of p53 (Figures 4B and 5B), confirming 
earlier results of an increase in p53 
wt MCF-7 cells in response to 
p28 (Yamada et al, 2009). The increase in the level of p53 protein 
in these lines was also directly associated with an increase in the 
level of transcription and translation of p21. p28 did not alter 
either the level or rate of transcription of p53 or p21 in p53 </p>

<p>dom/neg </p>

<p>MDD2, p53 
wt normal MCF-10A or p53 
null Mel-6 cells (Figures 4A 
and B, and 5A and B). Forkhead box M1 protein (FoxM1), an 
important regulator of the G 2 -M transition, was significantly 
reduced in MCF-7, Mel-29 and Mel-23 cells during exposure to 
p28, increased in p53 
dom/neg MDD2 cells at 48-72 h, and remained 
essentially unchanged in MDA-MB-231, MCF-10A and Mel-6 
cells, suggesting that downregulation of FoxM1 also contributed to 
inhibition of the cell cycle in p53 
wt MCF-7, Mel-29 and p53 </p>

<p>mut </p>

<p>Mel-23 cells. Although this may result from an inability of p53 </p>

<p>mut </p>

<p>to bind the p53 canonical consensus regions in the FOXM1 
promoter, p21 levels were sufficiently elevated to inhibit the 
proliferation of p53 
mut MDA-MB-231 cells, despite the over-
expression of FoxM1 (Figure 4A) (Bektas et al, 2008). This is not 
surprising because p53 mutants can often transactivate promoters 
containing a p21 responsive element (Campomenosi et al, 2001)  and loss of function in mutant p53 breast tumours does not 
represent a complete absence of activity (Williams et al, 1998). 
STMN1, an inhibitor of microtubule polymerisation (Belmont and  Mitchison, 1996) and critical for cell cycle progression, was not 
significantly decreased in any cancer cell line tested (Figures 4A 
and 5A), suggesting p28 inhibition of the cell cycle at G 2 -M is at 
G 2 and does not involve inhibition of microtubule formation. 
The p28-induced increase in p53 was associated with a 
significant decrease in the levels of COP1 in p53 
wt and p53 </p>

<p>mut </p>

<p>breast cancer and melanoma cells (Figures 4A and 5A). Exposure 
of p53 
wt MCF-7 and p53 
mut MDA-MB-231 cells to p28 reduced 
COP1 levels by B70% and 80%, respectively, over 24-72 h without 
altering the transcription of COP1 (Figure 4A). Exposure of p53 </p>

<p>wt </p>

<p>Mel-29 to p28 significantly reduced COP1 levels (B75%) at 24 h 
that gradually increased (B60% of control) at 72 h (Figure 5A). 
A similar effect on COP1 levels was observed in p53 
mut Mel-23 
cells. The lack of effect of p28 on COP1 levels in p53 
null Mel-6 and 
delayed increase in p53 
dom/neg MDD2 exposed to p28 suggest that 
the effects of p28 on COP1 are a function of a cell's p53 status. 
Moreover, as continued exposure to p28 does not significantly alter 
COP1 transcription in p53 
wt and p53 
mut cancer cells, the decrease </p>

<p>GST 
GST-p53 1-393 </p>

<p>p28 </p>

<p>100 43.7 73.4 (%) </p>

<p>GST 
GST-p53 </p>

<p>1-393 </p>

<p>GST-p53 </p>

<p>1-80 </p>

<p>GST-p53 </p>

<p>81-300 </p>

<p>GST-p53 </p>

<p>301-393 </p>

<p>GST-p53 </p>

<p>81-160 </p>

<p>GST-p53 </p>

<p>161-300 </p>

<p>GST 
GST-p53 </p>

<p>1-393 </p>

<p>GST-p53 </p>

<p>1-80 </p>

<p>GST-p53 </p>

<p>81-300 </p>

<p>GST-p53 </p>

<p>301-393 </p>

<p>GST-p53 </p>

<p>81-160 </p>

<p>GST-p53 </p>

<p>161-300 </p>

<p>p28 </p>

<p>Lysate </p>

<p>Lysate </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>-
-
-
-
-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-
-
-
-
-
-
-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
++ 
++ </p>

<p>Figure 2. p28-binding regions on p53. (A) Purified various fragments of p53 and GST alone were used for a GST pull-down assay. Each sample was 
analysed by immunoblotting with an anti-p28 antibody. (B) Competitive pull-down assay. Immobilised GST-p53 1-393 and GST alone on 
glutathione-Sepharose 4B beads were incubated in absence ( À ) or presence of p28 ( þ : 10, þ þ : 100 mole excess), followed by adding MCF-7 
lysates containing COP1. Samples were separated by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotted with an anti-COP1 antibody. Lysate: whole-cell lysates of 
MCF-7 used for the assay showed the stable expression of COP1. Numbers below COP1 bands were relative percentage to the level of COP1 
bound to p53 in absence of p28. (C) COP1 binding to various fragments of p53 in absence or presence of p28 was analysed using a similar 
competitive pull-down assay. Immobilised various fragments of p53 and GST alone were treated with or without p28 (100 mole excess), followed 
by incubation with MCF-7 lysates containing COP1. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Peptide inhibition of COP1 </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.266 </p>

<p>in the overall level of COP1 likely occurs through autodegradation 
(Dornan et al, 2006). </p>

<p>p28 Effects on minor E3 ubiquitin ligases. p28 produces a post-
translational increase in p53 through decreased ubiquitination and 
proteasomal degradation rather than transcriptional activation 
(Yamada et al, 2009). However, exposure to p28 transiently 
increased the transcription and level of TOPORS (48 h) in p53 </p>

<p>wt </p>

<p>MCF-7 cells, but did not significantly affect either the transcription 
or level of TOPORS in p53 
mut MDA-MB-231 cells (Figure 4A and 
B). This suggests the upregulation of TOPORS by wild-type p53 
was more efficient than with mutated p53. Exposure of p53 
wt Mel-
29 cells to p28 produced a sustained increase in the level of 
TOPORS that was not transcription dependent, whereas exposure 
of p53 
mut Mel-23 cells to p28 reduced the level of TOPORS over 
48 h, which was not preceded or accompanied by a change in 
transcription (Figure 5 A and B). The increase in the level and 
transcription of TOPORS in p53 
wt MCF-7 and Mel-29 cells and </p>

<p>lack of effect on p53 
mut MDA-MB-231 and Mel-23 cells suggest 
that changes in the level of TOPORS in response to p28 are 
dependent on p53 status and do not have a major role in the 
regulation of cell proliferation. 
p28 also induced a short-term (24 h) increase in the level of 
Pirh2 in p53 
wt MCF-7 and MDA-MB-231 cells without an 
accompanying increase in transcription, suggesting that the 
transient increase was in response to the p28-induced increase in 
p53 (Figure 4A and B). In contrast, p28 had no significant effect on 
the expression of the Pirh2 protein or transcription in p53 
wt Mel-
29 or p53 
mut Mel-23 cells (Figure 5A and B). Collectively, changes 
in the level of TOPORS and Pirh2 appeared dependent on the cell 
line treated as well as p53 status and are a minor factor in the 
regulation of wild-type or mutated p53. 
In contrast, the initial increase (24-48 h) and slow rise (72 h) in 
the level of the major E3 ligase HDM2 in p53 
wt MCF-7 and p53 </p>

<p>mut </p>

<p>MDA-MB-231 cells, respectively, was accompanied by a parallel 
increase in transcription. However, neither increase reflected the </p>

<p>% Control </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>% Control </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Mel-29 </p>

<p>10 mg kg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>n =8 </p>

<p>20 mg kg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>n =8 </p>

<p>DTIC 
n =8 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>Mel-23 </p>

<p>PBS 
n =18 </p>

<p>10 mg kg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>n =9 </p>

<p>20 mg kg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>n =8 </p>

<p>DTIC 
n =8 </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>Mel-6 </p>

<p>PBS 
n =14 </p>

<p>10 mg kg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>n =6 </p>

<p>DTIC 
n =5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>MDA-MB-231 </p>

<p>PBS 
n =5 </p>

<p>10 mg kg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>n =6 </p>

<p>20 mg kg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>n =5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>MCF-7 </p>

<p>Paclitaxel 
n = 8 </p>

<p>Paclitaxel 
n =5 </p>

<p>PBS 
n =15 </p>

<p>20 mg kg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>n = 3 </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>Mel-29 
Mel-23 
Mel-6 </p>

<p>Control 
p28, 50 µM 
DTIC, 50 µM 
Control 
p28, 50 µM 
Paclitaxel, 50 µM </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>MCF-7 
MDD2 
MDA-MB-231 MCF-10A </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 
Tumour weight (g) 
Tumour weight (g) 
Tumour weight (g) </p>

<p>PBS 
n =16 </p>

<p>Tumour weight (g) </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>1.50 </p>

<p>2.00 </p>

<p>2.50 </p>

<p>Tumour weight (g) </p>

<p>10 mg kg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>n = 5 </p>

<p>Figure 3. The effect of p28 on cell and xenograft growth. Human melanoma UISO-Mel-29, -23 and -6 (A) and breast cancer MCF-7, MDD2, 
MDA-MB-231 and normal MCF-10A cells (B) were exposed to p28, DTIC, paclitaxel or a similar volume of media without peptide for 
72 h and cells counted. Values represent the mean ± s.d. of three replicates. Reduction in Mel-23, 29 xenograft growth (C). Reduction of MCF-7, 
MDA-MB-231 xenograft growth (D). *Po0.05. </p>

<p>Peptide inhibition of COP1 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.266 </p>

<p>
sustained increase in p53 in response to p28. Unlike COP1, 
HDM2 levels were not significantly altered by p28 in p53 
wt Mel-29 
cells, but increased late in exposure (48-72 h) in p53 
mut Mel-23 
(Figure 5A). </p>

<p>p28 Effect on c-Jun. If COP1 acts as a developmentally dependent 
tumour suppressor (Migliorini et al, 2011; Vitari et al, 2011), 
interacting with the oncoprotein c-Jun (Bianchi et al, 2003) to keep 
c-Jun at constitutively low levels in vivo and COP1 deficiency leads 
to c-Jun upregulation in human cancer cells (Migliorini et al, 2011)  even in the absence of a genetic interaction between COP1 and p53 
(Migliorini et al, 2011), then exposure to p28 should significantly 
increase c-Jun levels in p53 
wt,mut,null cells. p28 did not significantly 
alter the level of c-Jun in either p53 
wt MCF-7, MDD2 or MCF-10A 
cells and transiently (48 h) reduced (38%) c-Jun levels in p53 </p>

<p>mut </p>

<p>MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cells (Figure 6A). In contrast, c-Jun 
was significantly decreased over 48-72 h in p53 
wt Mel-29 cells, 
briefly increased (48 h) in p53 
mut Mel-23 cells, and only increased 
slightly over 24 h in p53 
null Mel-6 cells (Figure 6C). The decrease in 
c-Jun in p53 
wt Mel-29 cells was accompanied by an increase in 
transcription (72 h), suggesting the increase was in response to the 
decrease in the level of the c-Jun protein (Figure 6B and D) rather 
than the result of a decrease in COP1 following exposure to p28. 
None of these results suggest that a sustained decrease in COP1 
results in an increase in the level and transcription of c-Jun 
(Migliorini et al, 2011). 
Moreover, the absence of any change in p53, COP1, p21, 
FOXM1, TORPORS, Pirh2 or HDM2 and the transient increase in </p>

<p>c-Jun in p53 
null Mel-6 cells in response to p28 suggest that the 
antiproliferative effects of p28 are mediated via the sustained 
increase in p53 and p21 independent of any effect on c-Jun 
(Migliorini et al, 2011). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Although most wild-type or mutated p53 tumours must certainly 
be dysfunctional (Wiman, 2006), cancer cells proliferate irrespec-
tive of p53 status. This suggests reactivation of p53-induced control 
of the cell cycle and apoptosis is a plausible therapeutic goal 
regardless of p53 status. The loss of wild-type p53 function or gain 
of new oncogenic properties may result, in part, from the 
numerous missense point mutations within the DBD of p53 
clustered into discrete hot spots (R175, G245, R248, R249, R273 
and R282) (Tu et al, 2008). However, the reported gain-of-function 
properties reportedly associated with p53 hot spot mutations may 
not be a universal phenomenon (Lee et al, 2012). Amino-acid 
residues R248 and R273 directly contact DNA while the remainder 
stabilises the structure of the DNA-binding motif within the DBD 
(Tu et al, 2008). In contrast, the flexible L 1 loop (aa 112-124) 
within the p53DBD is a mutational cold spot (Zupnick and Prives,  2006). Our models predicted that p28 would bind to the L 1 loop, a 
region of the S 7 -S 8 loop (aa 214-236) and T140, P142, Q144, 
W146, R282 and L289 of the p53DBD. This prediction was 
supported by GST pull-down assays (Figure 2A) and atomic force </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 72 (h) </p>

<p>FoxM1 </p>

<p>Actin </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 
72 (h) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>MCF-7 
MDD2 </p>

<p>153 
61 
42 
100 
186 
389 
398 </p>

<p>COP1 </p>

<p>TOPORS </p>

<p>STMN1 </p>

<p>Pirh2 </p>

<p>HDM2 </p>

<p>100 
207 (%) 
227 
214 </p>

<p>p53 </p>

<p>p21 </p>

<p>100 
132 
282 
257 </p>

<p>100 
109 
142 104 (%) </p>

<p>100 
105 
102 
98 </p>

<p>100 
92 
88 
86 
100 
115 
162 
119 </p>

<p>100 
199 
112 
89 
100 
107 
234 
101 </p>

<p>100 
141 
92 
102 
100 
113 
119 
193 </p>

<p>100 
153 
162 
117 
100 
106 
158 
162 </p>

<p>100 
87 
28 
27 
100 
99 
225 
259 </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 72 (h) </p>

<p>MDA-MB-231 </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 72 (h) </p>

<p>MCF-10A </p>

<p>100 
160 
151 169 (%) </p>

<p>100 
185 
227 
224 </p>

<p>100 
109 
105 
121 </p>

<p>100 
124 
102 94 (%) </p>

<p>100 
111 
103 
91 </p>

<p>100 
103 
113 
109 </p>

<p>100 
23 
13 
17 
100 
134 
111 
86 </p>

<p>100 
102 
112 
128 
100 
110 
103 
97 </p>

<p>100 
87 
105 
119 
100 
111 
107 
106 </p>

<p>100 
111 
159 
107 
100 
108 
106 
88 </p>

<p>100 
110 
111 
121 
100 
105 
106 
83 </p>

<p>FoxM1 </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>COP1 </p>

<p>TOPORS </p>

<p>Pirh2 </p>

<p>HDM2 </p>

<p>p53 </p>

<p>p21 </p>

<p>100 
110 
95 </p>

<p>100 
197 
174 
112 </p>

<p>100 
254 
140 
124 </p>

<p>1 0 0 
8 8 
9 2 
8 9 </p>

<p>100 
92 
110 
95 </p>

<p>100 
171 
179 
109 </p>

<p>100 
148 
86 
71 </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 
72 (h) 
0 
24 
48 72 (h) </p>

<p>MCF-7 
MDD2 </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 
72 (h) </p>

<p>MDA-MB-231 </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 
72 (h) </p>

<p>MCF-10A </p>

<p>100 
105 
115 
100 </p>

<p>100 
104 
117 
107 </p>

<p>100 
115 
96 
82 </p>

<p>100 
87 
195 
148 </p>

<p>100 
95 
109 
95 </p>

<p>100 
104 
136 
112 </p>

<p>100 
129 
132 
91 </p>

<p>100 
89 
106 
88 </p>

<p>100 
150 
142 
127 </p>

<p>100 
97 
113 
108 </p>

<p>1 0 0 
9 6 
8 7 
9 8 </p>

<p>100 
103 
82 
128 </p>

<p>100 
93 
92 
108 </p>

<p>100 
101 
106 
131 </p>

<p>1 0 0 
8 9 
9 0 
9 7 </p>

<p>1 0 0 
9 3 
9 1 
9 4 </p>

<p>100 
104 
97 
88 </p>

<p>100 
83 
106 
101 </p>

<p>100 
87 
101 
115 </p>

<p>100 
84 
102 
105 </p>

<p>100 
105 
97 
98 </p>

<p>123 </p>

<p>Figure 4. Stabilisation of p53 by E3 ligases on p53 
wt,mut breast cancer cells. (A) MCF-7, MDD2, MDA-MB-231, and MCF-10A cells were </p>

<p>treated with p28 at 50 mmol l 
À 1 for 24-72 h. Whole-cell lysates were subjected to western blot analysis. (B) The expression of each gene was </p>

<p>determined by RT-PCR. The numbers indicated below each band represent the relative to control (control expressed as 100%). </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Peptide inhibition of COP1 </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.266 </p>

<p>spectroscopy studies that indicated p28 binds with high affinity to 
the p53DBD (Bizzarri et al, 2011). 
Once bound, p28 produces an increase in the level of p53 </p>

<p>wt,mut </p>

<p>(Figures 4A and 5A), which is associated with an inhibition of cell 
proliferation in vitro and in vivo (Figure 3A-D). Neither the 
internal in frame deletion (aa 178-183) (Kichina et al, 2003) in p53 
in Mel-23 cells, which does not include the predicted binding sites 
for p28, nor the point mutation at R280K in MDA-MB-231 cells 
that leads to overexpression (Olivier et al, 2002) (Figure 4A) affects 
the binding of p28. This suggests that increasing an already 
elevated level of mutated p53 may also positively impact down-
stream targets within the cell cycle and apoptotic pathways 
(Ludwig et al, 1996; Campomenosi et al, 2001). 
The FoxM1, a transcription factor for genes regulating the G 2 -
M transition, is a major downstream target of p53 (Laoukili et al,  2005). Loss of FoxM1 leads to a delay in G 2 (Laoukili et al, 2005). 
p28 reduced the level of FoxM1 in p53 
wt MCF-7, p53 
wt Mel-29 and 
p53 
mut Mel-23 cells and inhibited cell proliferation, but did not 
reduce the high basal levels of FoxM1 in triple negative (ER 
À , 
PGR 
À , HER2 
À ) p53 
mut MDA-MB-231 cells (Figure 4A). The 
significant inverse correlation between FoxM1 expression and 
human epidermal growth factor 2 (HER2) (Bektas et al, 2008)  suggests overexpression of FoxM1 may result from this interaction 
or that the p53 
mut R280K in MDA-MB-231 cells may not allow 
binding to the promoter region of FoxM1. However, p28 did </p>

<p>increase the level of p21 in p53 
mut MDA-MB-231 cells (Figure 4A), 
in turn inhibiting the activity of the cyclin-CDK2 complex 
(Yamada et al, 2009). This suggests that inhibition of CDK by 
p21 provided an alternative pathway for the reduction in growth in 
the absence of a reduction in FoxM1. 
Intracellular levels of p53 are tightly regulated by a series of 
ubiquitin E3 ligases that promote ubiquitination and proteasome-
dependent degradation of p53 (Michael and Oren, 2003). HDM2 
or MDM2 is the major E3 ligase promoting p53 degradation 
(Haupt et al, 1997; Kubbutat et al, 1997), but TOPORS, Pirh2 and 
particularly COP1 also bind to and negatively regulate p53 (Leng  et al, 2003; Dornan et al, 2004b; Rajendra et al, 2004). Although 
TOPORS is expressed in most normal human tissues (Saleem et al,  2004), it is not expressed in colon cancer (Rajendra et al, 2004) and 
may not be an E3 ligase critical to p53 function in malignant cells. 
In contrast, Pirh2 expression is lower in normal compared with 
tumour cells and appears independent of the type of p53 mutation 
(Duan et al, 2006). The C-terminal domain of Pirh2 (aa 190-261) 
binds primarily to the tetramerisation domain (aa 325-355) of p53 
(Sheng et al, 2008) well removed from the binding sites for p28. 
Exposure to p28 did not reduce Pirh2 levels in either breast cancer 
or melanoma cells (Figures 4 and 5), producing only short-term 
increases that were not accompanied by an increase in transcrip-
tion. This suggests that only extant Pirh2 was recruited to degrade 
the increasing levels of p53. </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 72 (h) </p>

<p>FoxM1 </p>

<p>Actin </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 
72 (h) </p>

<p>STMN1 </p>

<p>HDM2 </p>

<p>100 
165 
148 </p>

<p>p53 </p>

<p>p21 </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 
72 (h) </p>

<p>FoxM1 </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>COP1 </p>

<p>TOPORS </p>

<p>Pirh2 </p>

<p>HDM2 </p>

<p>p53 </p>

<p>p21 </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 72 (h) 
0 
24 
48 72 (h) </p>

<p>UISO-Mel-29 
0 
24 
48 72 (h) </p>

<p>UISO-Mel-23 
UISO-Mel-6 </p>

<p>UISO-Mel-29 
UISO-Mel-23 
UISO-Mel-6 </p>

<p>156 </p>

<p>100 
123 
119 
121 
100 
98 
97 
96 </p>

<p>100 
140 
127 
121 </p>

<p>100 
144 
138 
124 </p>

<p>100 
68 
24 
58 
100 
83 
51 
94 
100 
97 
102 
92 </p>

<p>100 
94 
114 
92 
100 
113 
104 
127 
100 
116 
96 
108 </p>

<p>100 
106 
103 
98 
100 
105 
107 
97 </p>

<p>100 
74 
77 
74 
100 
79 
80 
124 
100 
122 
126 
108 </p>

<p>100 
111 
102 
117 
100 
90 
97 
97 
100 
98 
106 
99 </p>

<p>100 
103 
96 
106 
100 
132 
108 
119 
100 
109 
103 
107 </p>

<p>N.D. 
N.D. 
N.D. 
N.D. </p>

<p>N.D. 
N.D. 
N.D. 
N.D. </p>

<p>100 
90 
96 
86 
100 
93 
107 
88 
100 
96 
104 
100 </p>

<p>TOPORS </p>

<p>Pirh2 </p>

<p>100 
139 
129 
156 </p>

<p>100 
85 
89 
98 </p>

<p>100 
75 
70 
110 </p>

<p>100 
104 
105 
126 </p>

<p>100 
102 
98 
83 </p>

<p>100 
91 
97 
98 </p>

<p>COP1 </p>

<p>100 
59 
45 
76 
100 
92 
98 
78 
100 
38 
44 
74 </p>

<p>100 
102 
128 
120 
100 
98 
112 
86 
100 
128 
101 
108 </p>

<p>100 
72 
74 
69 
100 
90 
94 
89 
100 
109 
98 
106 </p>

<p>100 
84 
147 
81 
100 
62 
143 
53 
100 
104 
113 
92 </p>

<p>Figure 5. Stabilisation of p53 by E3 ligases on p53 
wt,mut melanoma cells. (A) Mel-29, Mel-23 and Mel-6 cells were treated with p28 at 50 mmol l </p>

<p>À 1 </p>

<p>for 24-72 h. (B) The expression of each gene was determined by RT-PCR. The numbers indicated below each band represent the relative to control 
(control expressed as 100%). </p>

<p>Peptide inhibition of COP1 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.266 </p>

<p>
p28 significantly increased the level and transcription of HDM2 
in p53 
wt MCF-7 cells over 24-72 h, while p53 levels remained 
elevated (Figure 4). The increase in HDM2 was minimal and 
delayed (72 h) in p53 
mut MDA-MB-231 cells. p28 had essentially 
no effect on HDM2 levels or transcription in p53 
wt Mel-29, and 
induced only a delayed increase in HDM2 protein and RNA levels 
in p53 
mut Mel-23 cells in spite of a sustained increase in p53 levels 
in both cell lines. 
COP1 is overexpressed in breast and ovarian cancers (Dornan  et al, 2004b), promotes p53 degradation via the proteasome 
pathway independently of HDM2 or Pirh2 (Dornan et al, 2004b)  and is able to ubiquitinate itself (Bianchi et al, 2003; Dornan et al,  2006). We confirm that COP1 binds to aa 92-160 and aa 318-393 
of p53 (Li et al, 2009). We show that p28 binds to specific motifs 
within the COP1-binding regions of the p53DBD, blocking COP1 
binding and the subsequent ubiquitination and proteasomal 
degradation of p53. These motifs are distinct (Figure 1D) from 
those binding HDM2. The significant reduction in COP1 levels in 
breast cancer and melanoma cells (Figures 4 and 5) is not 
accompanied by an increase in the transcription of COP1 message, 
indicating the loss in COP1 is through autodegradation (Dornan  et al, 2006). The p28-induced reduction in COP1 levels was also 
not accompanied by a significant or sustained increase in the 
transcription in c-Jun levels (Migliorini et al, 2011) that would be 
expected if a decrease in COP1 levels led to upregulation of c-Jun 
or altered its ubiquitination. Similarly, overexpression of COP1 
does not result in a decrease in steady-state levels of c-Jun nor 
reduce c-Jun half-life (Bianchi et al, 2003). 
The slight, transient increases and decreases in c-Jun levels were 
also unrelated to alterations in the expression of p53 or in c-Jun 
transcription (Figure 6) (Migliorini et al, 2011), and may result 
from as yet unknown modulating effects on the steady-state 
condition of c-Jun in individual cell lines as a result of exposure to 
p28. The sustained decrease in COP1 levels induced by p28 did not 
result in a c-Jun-dependent increase in cell proliferation (Figure 3) 
(Migliorini et al, 2011), again suggesting that a pharmacologically 
induced reduction in COP1 levels does not result in a c-Jun-
mediated increase in tumour cell proliferation in either p53 
wt or 
p53 
mut cancers (Migliorini et al, 2011). </p>

<p>On the basis of our findings, we propose a model for the 
stabilisation of p53 by p28 that results in a reduction in tumour 
growth through regulation of cell cycle-related genes. p28 binds 
to the L 1 loop (aa 112-124) and additional motifs within the 
COP1-binding regions of the p53DBD (Figure 1D), subsequently 
inhibiting COP1-mediated p53 proteasomal degradation and 
stabilising p53. Increased levels of p53 upregulate the downstream 
molecules p21 (Figures 4A and 5A) and p27 (Yamada et al, 2009)  in p53 
wt and, at least some, p53 
mut cancer cells, downregulating 
FoxM1, and leading to inhibition of cell cycle at G 2 -M. 
Currently, small molecules designed to inhibit HDM2-mediated 
ubiquitination are apparently only being tested in patients 
with p53 
wt tumours (Kojima et al, 2010). Unlike these small 
molecules, p28 preferentially enters wide variety of cancer cells 
(Taylor et al, 2009) and enhances the cellular level of p53 
wt,mut by 
inhibiting the binding of COP1 independent of the HDM2 
pathway. As such, p28 is a prototype molecule that exhibits 
efficacy in patients with advanced (Stage IV) p53 
wt,mut solid 
tumours (Warso et al, 2013). </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Scott Kennedy for editorial assistance. We thank CDG 
Therapeutics Inc. for the p28 used in these studies. Financial 
support was received from the Schenk Chair in Surgical 
Oncology, the Illinois Health Improvement Association and the 
NCI-DCT RAID programme. SS, ARB and SC thank the 
Italian Association for Cancer Research (AIRC No IG 10412) for 
supporting their research. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>All terms of the research agreement between CDG Therapeutics, 
Inc., and UIC are managed by UIC in accordance with its conflict 
of interest management policies. </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 72 (h) </p>

<p>Actin </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 72 (h) </p>

<p>MCF-7 
MDD2 </p>

<p>100 
91 (%) 
113 
93 </p>

<p>c-jun </p>

<p>100 
99 
94 101 (%) </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 72 (h) </p>

<p>MDA-MB-231 </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 72 (h) </p>

<p>MCF-10A </p>

<p>100 
92 
62 86 (%) 
100 
86 
96 100 (%) </p>

<p>UISO-Mel-29 
UISO-Mel-23 
UISO-Mel-6 </p>

<p>100 
82 
136 
68 (%) 
100 
129 
91 
114 (%) 
100 
98 
115 
118 (%) </p>

<p>Actin </p>

<p>c-jun </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 72 (h) 
0 
24 
48 72 (h) 
0 
24 
48 72 (h) </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 72 (h) 
0 
24 
48 72 (h) </p>

<p>MCF-7 
MDD2 
0 
24 
48 72 (h) </p>

<p>MDA-MB-231 
0 
24 
48 72 (h) </p>

<p>MCF-10A </p>

<p>UISO-Mel-29 
UISO-Mel-23 
UISO-Mel-6 
0 
24 
48 72 (h) 
0 
24 
48 72 (h) 
0 
24 48 72 (h) </p>

<p>c-jun </p>

<p>c-jun </p>

<p>100 
105 (%) 
96 
104 
100 
111 
110 104 (%) 
100 
109 
96 82 (%) 
100 
101 
95 98 (%) </p>

<p>100 
104 
102 
123 (%) 
100 
105 
104 
119 (%) 
100 
98 
104 
98 (%) </p>

<p>Figure 6. The effect of p28 on c-Jun. The protein level of c-Jun was determined in MCF-7, MDD2, MDA-MB-231 and MCF-10A cells (A), and 
Mel-29, Mel-23 and Mel-6 (C) treated with p28 at 50 mmol l 
À 1 for 24-72 h. The transcription level of c-Jun was determined by RT-PCR in </p>

<p>breast cell lines (B) and melanoma cells (D). The numbers indicated below each band represent the relative to control (control expressed as 100%). </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Peptide inhibition of COP1 </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.266 </p>



<p>Peptide inhibition of COP1 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.266 </p>



<p>
This work is published under the standard license to publish agree-
ment. After 12 months the work will become freely available and 
the license terms will switch to a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on British Journal of Cancer website (http://www.nature.com/bjc) </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Peptide inhibition of COP1 </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2013.266 </p>

</text></tei>