<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3549250" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives: To evaluate the cost effectiveness of soft </p>

<p>tissue injury management by emergency nurse 
practitioners (ENPs) and extended scope 
physiotherapists (ESPs) compared with the routine care 
provided by doctors in an emergency department (ED). </p>

<p>Design: Randomised, pragmatic trial of equivalence. 
Setting: A single ED in England. 
Participants: 372 patients were randomised, 126 to </p>

<p>the ESP group, 123 to the ENP group and 123 to the 
doctor group. Participants were adults (16 years and 
older) presenting to the ED with a peripheral soft 
tissue injury eligible for management by any of the 
three professional groups. </p>

<p>Interventions: Patients were randomised to treatment </p>

<p>by an ESP, ENP or routine care provided by doctors (of 
all grades). </p>

<p>Main outcome measures: Economic cost-</p>

<p>minimisation evaluation from a funder perspective of 
the National Health Service, England incorporating 
analysis of the direct, indirect and tangible costs of 
care in primary and secondary settings. </p>

<p>ARTICLE SUMMARY </p>

<p>Article focus </p>

<p>▪ This study reports a randomised, pragmatic trial 
of equivalence comparing nurse practitioners 
and extended scope physiotherapists (ESPs) 
with the routine care provided by doctors man-
aging minor injuries in the emergency depart-
ment (ED). </p>

<p>Key messages </p>

<p>▪ For this patient group, substituting routine care 
by doctors with an ESP or nurse practitioner 
workforce is likely to achieve equivalent cost at 
best. There is, however, a risk that such substitu-
tion would result in greater costs from the per-
spective of the National Health Service, the 
patient and society. It is the indirect costs asso-
ciated with care that make ESPs and nurse prac-
titioners less economically attractive. 
▪ While our companion paper demonstrates clin-
ical equivalence between the three professional 
groups, these economic results challenge the 
notion that training a non-medical workforce to 
undertake extensions in their roles is likely to 
prove cost effective. </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ The follow-up period was focused on the first 
8 weeks after injury, and there may be important 
indirect costs that were not captured by this 
study. 
▪ The research was undertaken at a single centre, 
and is therefore unlikely to be representative of 
all the UK ED; further multicentre work is 
required. 
▪ Since the number of practitioners was relatively 
small, it is not clear to what extent the findings 
can be generalised to all ESPs and nurse practi-
tioners working in the ED. Confirmation of these 
findings in additional settings would be valuable. </p>

<p>McClellan CM, Cramp F, Powell J, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e001116. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001116 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>injuries, and annual attendances are expected to increase. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Emergency nurse practitioners (ENPs) are senior nurses 
with additional training to autonomously assess, diagnose 
and treat patients with selected urgent conditions, particu-
larly minor illness and injury. ENPs are being increasingly 
employed in minor injuries care, and are considered an 
important part of future service delivery. 
1 2 Recently, 
extended scope physiotherapists (ESPs) have also been 
developed to undertake similar roles, including the man-
agement of minor injuries, but this opportunity has not 
been widely adopted or evaluated. </p>

<p>3 4 </p>

<p>The new roles of ENP and ESP should benefit both 
patients and staff. 
5 It is therefore important to establish 
who has the competencies needed to achieve high-
quality care in a cost effective manner. 
5-7 A companion 
paper concluded that the clinical outcomes of soft tissue 
injury treated by ESPs and ENPs in the ED were equiva-
lent to routine care provided by doctors. 
8 As all groups 
were clinically equivalent it is other factors such as cost, 
workforce sustainability, service provision and skill mix 
that become important in determining the future work-
force and models of service delivery. 
The aim of this research was to investigate the cost 
effectiveness of ENPs and ESPs in comparison with the 
routine care provided by doctors when treating soft 
tissue injuries in an English ED. </p>

<p>METHOD 
This was a randomised, pragmatic trial of equivalence 
undertaken in an adult ED in England. The aim was to 
evaluate and compare the cost effectiveness of the treat-
ment of soft tissue injury by three groups of emergency 
care professionals: ENPs, ESPs and doctors (of all 
grades). The full methodology of the randomised clin-
ical trial is detailed in a companion paper. 
8 The eco-
nomic evaluation, a cost-minimisation analysis, was 
undertaken from a funder perspective capturing the 
direct, indirect and intangible costs in primary and sec-
ondary care associated with patient care episodes. It was 
originally intended to undertake a cost utility and conse-
quence analysis, but the economic evaluation took the 
form of a cost minimisation analysis because the clinical 
trial demonstrated equivalence of patient outcome 
between the different healthcare professional groups. 
The economic information was captured in the first 
8 weeks following injury. 
The primary economic outcome measures were: the 
cost per hour of patient contact and the cost per patient 
per hour. The cost per patient per hour was calculated 
by dividing the salary cost of the different professional 
groups by their productivity, that is, the number of 
patients treated per hour. This provided information on 
cost in relation to the different productivity levels of dif-
ferent groups. The secondary outcomes were: the direct 
cost per hour of patient contact and the indirect costs of 
care per hour of patient contact. All the primary and 
secondary costs excluded educational costs, as these can </p>

<p>be treated as sunk costs or retrospective costs that have 
been incurred and cannot be recovered. The cost of 
training all medical professionals is substantial because 
the level of knowledge and skill required for ED roles 
requires acquisition of high-quality, costly education and 
practice. The costs including education have been evalu-
ated as part of a sensitivity analysis. </p>

<p>Direct costs 
The direct costs were obtained by attaching a questionnaire 
to the patient's notes with a simple tick box system identify-
ing all resources used. The unit cost of different healthcare 
professionals and follow-up appointments were calculated 
using the 2007/2008 unit cost of healthcare from the 
University of Kent. 
9 The cost of different healthcare profes-
sionals included the following: salary (as median point on 
pay scale), salary 'on costs', overheads, capital overheads, 
travel, contact times and non-London multiplier. The ENP 
and ESP pay level was calculated using the hospital-based 
ENP team manager, band 7 Agenda for Change. The 
doctor's pay level was calculated at a Foundation Trainee 2 
level (as no information was available specifically for a 
SHO or ST1/2 doctor level), specialist registrar and surgi-
cal consultant level. All resource costs and calculation 
methods are detailed in the trial protocol. </p>

<p>Indirect costs 
Indirect costs were obtained during the follow-up tele-
phone interviews using a questionnaire. The direct and 
indirect costs included in the economic analysis have 
been summarised in table 1. </p>

<p>SENSITIVITY ANALYSIS 
A sensitivity analysis was undertaken including the fol-
lowing elements: 
▸ Educational costs (undergraduate, postgraduate and 
continuous professional development costs from 
qualification through to retirement). </p>

<p>Table 1 The direct and indirect costs identified and 
measured in the economic evaluation </p>

<p>Direct costs 
Indirect costs </p>

<p>Resource use 
(crutches, tubigrip, etc) </p>

<p>Unplanned further healthcare 
visits (eg, to the ED or patient's 
general practitioner) 
Medications 
administered </p>

<p>Cost of travel and parking 
associated with the above 
Forward referral to 
orthopaedics </p>

<p>Additional items, such as pain 
relief or bandages, purchased 
since the first visit to the ED for 
the injury 
Forward referral to 
physiotherapy </p>

<p>Additional costs to the individual 
and others as a direct result of 
the injury 
ED reviews 
Forward referral to GP 
Cost of practitioner </p>



<p>McClellan CM, Cramp F, Powell J, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e001116. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001116 </p>

<p>Who is the cheapest at treating soft tissue injuries in emergency departments? </p>

<p>▸ Median costs (it is recommended that results are pre-
sented in mean not median values, which better rep-
resent true costs. 
10 The median results are useful as 
they indicate the cost to the majority of patients). 
▸ ESP and ENPs compared with different grades of hos-
pital doctor. 
▸ Different costs of treating upper-limb and lower-limb 
injuries. </p>

<p>DISCOUNTING 
In accordance with accepted recommendations, the 
costs have been presented in two different ways. 
11 The 
first uses original undiscounted values from 2007/2008. 
The second uses discounted values from 2007/2008 to 
2011 based on the UK government's social time prefer-
ence rate of 3.5%. 
12 Using this rate £1 : 00 in 2007/2008 
is worth £0.92 in 2011/2012. The undiscounted values 
are presented in the main text, while the discounted 
values are presented in table 2. </p>

<p>PRODUCTIVITY 
Patients were not advised to discount the effects of lost 
productivity when completing the SF-12v2. To eliminate 
the possibility of double-counting, the effects of lost </p>

<p>productivity on the utility score were not included in the 
indirect costs. </p>

<p>OPPORTUNITY AND MARGINAL COSTS 
The unit cost of healthcare used in the calculations 
accommodated the marginal and opportunity costs. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>STATISTICAL METHODS 
The sample size was calculated using equivalence 
margins rather than probability levels: further details are 
presented in the companion paper. 
8 The trial was 
powered to 90% and the minimum importance differ-
ence was 10% of cost. The results were analysed using 
an intention to treat and per protocol analysis. 
Economic evaluation data are invariably positively 
skewed, and it requires an alternative analysis. 
13 14 The 
study data were analysed using a non-parametric boot-
strapping technique. Bootstrapping makes no assump-
tions regarding the equality, variance or shape of the 
distribution, and takes into account skewness. 
15 It 
derives arithmetic means recommended by some 
authors 
10 that can be used to compare the groups and 
generates CIs using a computer-generated programme 
to repeatedly sample from the observed data which is 
then analysed. 
10 13 15 The bootstrapping was undertaken 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">STATA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.9</rs> software. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Three hundred and seventy-two patients provided 
consent and were randomised. One hundred and 
twenty-six were randomised to the ESP group, 123 to the 
ENP group and 123 to the doctor group. Table 2 pre-
sents the average undiscounted and discounted results. 
A CONSORT diagram is provided in figure 1, and 
details of follow-up in figure 2. Further information can 
be found in the companion paper. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Primary outcomes 
Cost per hour of patient care between different healthcare 
professionals 
The average cost per hour of patient contact was £80.91 
(CI 66.5 to 101.6) for doctors, £89.71 (73.0 to 118.7) for 
ESPs and £109.81 (83.0 to 142.1) for ENPs. The per 
protocol analysis provided similar findings. The results 
demonstrated that both the ESP and ENP group could 
not be cheaper than routine care; they are at best 
equivalent, and possibly more expensive. </p>

<p>Unit cost per patient per hour 
The ESP group treated an average of 3 patients per 
hour, whereas the ENPs treated 3.6 and the doctors 4.4 
patients per hour. The average cost per patient per hour 
was £54.93 (37.9 to 73.0) for doctors, £68.36 (50.6 to 
91.3) for ESPs and £86.47 (62.2 to 122.5) for ENPs. 
Again, the results demonstrated that both the ESP and </p>

<p>Table 2 Undiscounted and discounted costs </p>

<p>Outcome measure </p>

<p>Undiscounted 
cost (£) 
2007/2008 </p>

<p>Discounted 
cost (£) 
2011/2012 </p>

<p>Primary out comes 
The mean cost per 
hour of patient care 
between different 
healthcare 
professionals </p>

<p>Doctor 80.91 
Doctor 74.44 
ESPs 89.71 
ESPs 82.53 
ENPs 109.81 
ENPs 101.03 </p>

<p>The mean unit 
cost per patient 
per hour </p>

<p>Doctor 54.93 
Doctor 50.54 
ESPs 68.36 
ESPs 62.89 
ENPs 86.47 
ENPs 82.31 
Secondary outcomes 
The mean direct 
costs per hour of 
patient contact </p>

<p>Doctor 60.96 
Doctor 56.08 
ESPs 52.48 
ESPs 48.28 
ENPs 55.21 
ENPs 50.79 
The mean indirect 
costs per hour of 
patient contact </p>

<p>Doctor 19.60 
Doctor 18.03 
ESPs 39.56 
ESPs 36.40 
ENPs 52.70 
ENPs 48.48 
Sensitivity analysis 
The cost per hour 
of patient contact 
(including 
educational costs) </p>

<p>Doctor 92.26 
Doctor 84.88 
ESPs 92.71 
ESPs 85.29 
ENPs 110.82 
ENPs 101.95 </p>

<p>Cost per patient 
per hour (including 
educational costs) </p>

<p>Doctor 57.42 
Doctor 52.83 
ESPs 69.38 
ESPs 63.82 
ENPs 86.75 
ENPs 79.81 
Median costs 
(all costs) </p>

<p>Doctor 48.18 
Doctor 44.32 
ESPs 35.74 
ESPs 32.88 
ENPs 34.58 
ENPs 31.81 </p>

<p>ENP, emergency nurse practitioners; ESP, extended scope 
physiotherapists. </p>

<p>McClellan CM, Cramp F, Powell J, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e001116. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001116 </p>



<p>Who is the cheapest at treating soft tissue injuries in emergency departments? </p>

<p>ENP group could not be cheaper than routine care; 
they are at best equivalent, and possibly more expensive. </p>

<p>Secondary outcomes: the direct costs (secondary care) 
The average direct cost per hour of patient contact to the 
National Health Service (NHS) (secondary care) was 
£60.96 (51.1 to 73.6) for doctors, £52.48 (44.7 to 63.9) 
for ESPs and £55.21 (47.0 to 66.0) for ENPs. The ENP 
group was equivalent in cost to routine care. The ESP 
group could not be more expensive than routine care, 
and was either equivalent or cheaper. Some differences 
in direct costs between the three groups are noted below: 
▸ In total, 23.5% of patients were administered medica-
tion during their ED visit. The ESP group adminis-
tered medication to 3.6% of patients (n=3), the ENPs 
to 23.2% (n=19) and the doctors to 42.2% (n=38) of 
patients (Pearson's χ 
2 p&lt;0.001). 
▸ The ESP group administered a greater number of 
crutches (26.5%; n=22) compared with ENPs and 
doctors (9.5%; n=8 and 16.5%; n=15, respectively). 
▸ The ESP group provided 20.5% (n=17) of patients 
with a broad arm or collar and cuff sling compared 
with 8.4% (n=7) in the ENP group and 4.4% (n=4) 
in the doctor group. </p>

<p>Secondary outcomes: indirect costs ( patient and society) 
The average per patient indirect cost per hour of patient 
contact associated with the routine care provided by </p>

<p>doctors was £19.60 (11.2 to 38.6), compared with £39.56 
(25.6 to 59.0) for ESPs and £52.70 (33.0 to 81.6) for 
ENPs. The ESP and ENP groups could not cost less and 
were at best equivalent with the doctor group in terms 
of cost. Important observations regarding the indirect 
costs were as follows: 
▸ Patients treated by an ENP attended their general 
practitioner (GP) more frequently (26.4%; n=19) 
than those treated by an ESP (17.4%; n=12) or a 
doctor (13.2%; n=9). 
▸ The number of patients referred for an orthopaedic 
follow-up review was slightly higher in the ENP group 
(7.3%, n=6), compared with ESPs (4.8%, n=4) or 
doctors (5.6%, n=5), but the numbers were very 
small. 
▸ Approximately 60% of patient who attended the ED 
with an acute musculoskeletal injury purchased a 
combination of pain relief, bandages or complemen-
tary medicine to assist their recovery. There was no 
significant difference in purchased items between the 
groups (Pearsons's χ 
2 p=0.632). </p>

<p>SENSITIVITY ANALYSIS 
Cost per hour of patient contact 
(including educational costs) 
When including educational costs as part of a sensitivity 
analysis the average costs per hour of patient contact </p>

<p>Figure 1 CONSORT statement of trial recruitment. </p>



<p>McClellan CM, Cramp F, Powell J, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e001116. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001116 </p>

<p>Who is the cheapest at treating soft tissue injuries in emergency departments? </p>

<p>were £92.26 (78.2 to 115.3) for doctors, £92.71 (75.4 to 
117.7) for ESPs and £110.82 for ENPs (85.8 to 146.5). In 
this context the ESP group was equivalent to routine 
care while the ENP group could not be cheaper, and 
was either equivalent or possibly more expensive. </p>

<p>Cost per patient per hour (including educational costs) 
When including educational costs the average costs were 
£57.42 (43.5 to 81.3) for doctors, £69.38 (51.5 to 96.2) 
for ESPs and £86.75 (62.6 to 118.6) for ENPs. This 
demonstrated that both the ESP and ENP group could 
not be cheaper than routine care. </p>

<p>Median costs 
The median bootstrap results differed significantly. The 
average cost per hour was £35.74 (34.2 to 58.6) for the 
ESP group, £34.58 (32.5 to 62.6) for the ENP group 
and £48.18 (40.2 to 70.3) for the doctor group. In this 
analysis the ESP and ENP groups could not be more 
expensive, and are either equivalent or cheaper. The 
proportion of cost difference remained the same across 
all the economic calculations. </p>

<p>ENPs and ESPs compared with junior doctors 
ESPs £89.71 (73.0 to 118.7) were equivalent to junior 
doctors (Specialist Trainee years 1 and 2: ST1/2) £81.53 
(52.4 to 129.7) in all cost calculations. The ENP results 
£109.51 (83.0 to 142.1) were more uncertain, but with a 
trend towards equivalence. </p>

<p>ENPs and ESPs to registrars 
The ESPs £89.71 (73.0 to 118.7) and ENPs £109.51 (83.0 
to 142.1) were not equivalent to registrars £73.50 (54.0 
to 104.4) with regard to costs and the results were uncer-
tain, but with a trend towards equivalence. The ESP 
group, however, was equivalent to registrars when evalu-
ated per hour of patient contact including education 
costs. </p>

<p>Upper-limb versus lower-limb costs 
Sensitivity analysis demonstrated a consistently higher 
cost for lower-limb injury compared with upper limb. 
The average cost for all groups combined, including 
educational costs, was £81.81 for upper-limb injury and 
£98.45 for lower limb. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Patient follow-up. </p>

<p>McClellan CM, Cramp F, Powell J, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e001116. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001116 </p>



<p>Who is the cheapest at treating soft tissue injuries in emergency departments? </p>

<p>Difference between doctor grades 
A sensitivity analysis was undertaken to evaluate possible 
differences between junior doctors (ST1/ST2) and 
more senior grades (ST4-6). A bootstrapping technique 
indicated that the cost per hour of patient contact was 
similar: £39.40 (25.43 to 61.16) for ST1/2 doctors and 
£43.37 (19.22 to 67.52) for ST4-6 doctors at 8 weeks. 
However, the unit costs per patient did differ at £30.61 
(10.48 to 46.09) for ST1/2 and £11.21 (10.48 to 46.09) 
for ST4-6. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Statement of principal findings 
We report a randomised trial of equivalence comparing 
the cost of care by doctors, ENPs and ESPs managing 
minor injuries in EDs. We have demonstrated that the 
cost of substituting routine care by doctors with a pre-
dominantly ESP or ENP workforce is likely to be at 
best equivalent in cost with a high likelihood of greater 
cost from the perspective of the NHS, the patient and 
society. The cost per hour of patient contact for the dif-
ferent professional groups was £80.91 for doctors, £89.71 
for ESPs and £109.81 for ENPs. However, an economic 
analysis undertaken from the perspective of the NHS 
with costs limited to hospital-based secondary care 
changes this economic argument. In this context both 
the ESP and ENP are likely to be equivalent in cost to 
routine care, and the likelihood of costing less is greater 
than in the previous comparison. The direct cost per 
hour of patient contact was £60.96 for doctors, £52.48 
for ESPs and £55.21 for ENPs. It is therefore the indirect 
costs associated with care provided by ESPs and ENPs 
that make these options for management of soft tissue 
injuries in ED in England less economically attractive. </p>

<p>Strengths and weaknesses 
This study provides valuable cost-effectiveness data com-
paring different professional groups which, along with 
the associated clinical trial, can be used as a basis for 
decisions relating to workforce and service organisation. 
Methodological weaknesses have been outlined in the 
companion paper, 
8 but there are also limitations in this 
economic. First, the full economic evaluation was only 
undertaken in the first 8 weeks of injury. It is accepted 
that there will be additional indirect healthcare costs 
that have not been captured. It is encouraging that by 
8 weeks 86.6% of patients were 'a lot better' or 'com-
pletely better', but there may still be important longer 
term costs. Second, the accuracy of self-reported time 
spent with patients by each professional group was not 
verified. Doctors almost unanimously recorded 10 min 
for every patient consultation, whereas the ESPs and 
ENPs reported a wider spread of contact times. Third, 
the calculation of opportunity costs needs further con-
sideration. The lack of evidence evaluating the oppor-
tunity costs of extended roles has been highlighted by 
several authors. 
16-18 They have discussed the need to </p>

<p>evaluate the consequences of using highly skilled and 
experienced ENPs and ESPs to undertake new roles. By 
moving skilled workers away from their existing jobs 
other consequences follow such as deskilling the existing 
workforce, the cost associated with any reduction in 
quality or outcomes of care, the cost of training new staff 
as a replacement and the impact of the loss of knowl-
edge and clinical skill on a department. It would also be 
important to consider the consequences of reducing the 
number of doctors on patient care, future professional 
skills, postgraduate training and service. The unit cost of 
healthcare used in these calculations did accommodate 
the marginal and opportunity costs, 
9 but did not 
adequately investigate these forgone opportunities. A 
fourth consideration is that while the Doctor group are 
likely to be equivalent but possibly cheaper than the 
ESPs or ENPs the sensitivity analysis showed they were 
randomised to more of the relatively expensive lower-
limb injuries. This has the potential to overestimate the 
doctor group's cost. The randomisation process was 
robust enough to eliminate the possibility of bias and 
this allocation is likely to be due to chance. A fifth con-
sideration is that at the time this study was conducted it 
was not routine practice to issue sick notes/fit notes to 
patients attending the ED, and this applied to all profes-
sional groups (including doctors). The practice of 
issuing sick notes/fit notes to patients varies from hos-
pital to hospital, and may be a factor in subsequent 
behaviour, but we believe that the type of healthcare 
practitioner a patient sees may be more influential, and 
are currently investigating this in further research. 
Finally, economic evaluation and cost-effectiveness data 
are useful for comparisons between different services, 
but there remains some doubt regarding how the infor-
mation should be applied to inform decision 
making. 
19 20 Consequently, the findings of economic 
evaluations are not considered the dominant decision-
making criterion at a macro, meso or micro level in 
health services planning. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Comparisons with other studies 
There is only one comparable study: a non-inferiority 
trial comparing ESPs to routine care provided by ENPs 
or doctors. 
21 In this trial the researchers estimated that 
the cost of treatment and indirect costs to patients 
(using an intention-to-treat analysis) was £92.24 for a 
similarly skilled ESP compared with £95.25 for routine 
care. These costs are similar to the findings reported 
here. An association with increased indirect costs for 
ENPs working in extended roles was similar to previous 
studies. 
22 23 Sakr et al 
22 found that ENPs in minor injury 
units, but not in EDs, had higher follow-up rates which 
subsequently made the care more expensive than treat-
ment for similar injuries in EDs (by junior doctors). 
Venning et al 
23 found that it was the indirect costs of 
ENPs in GP practices that added to the overall cost of 
care. This may indicate a common theme around role </p>



<p>McClellan CM, Cramp F, Powell J, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e001116. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001116 </p>

<p>Who is the cheapest at treating soft tissue injuries in emergency departments? </p>

<p>substitution, and reflects the broader challenges of work-
force development within the NHS. </p>

<p>Study implications 
In the current climate of the NHS there are constraints 
on money, staff and skill mix, time, facilities, equipment 
and knowledge. 
11 13 While our companion paper 
demonstrates clinical equivalence between the profes-
sional groups, 
8 these economic results challenge the 
notion that training workforces to undertake extensions 
in their roles is cost effective. This may have wider impli-
cations for the commissioning of services and service 
delivery, and prove more complicated than a direct 
workforce substitution. Using economic evidence to 
make a judgement on present and future service deliv-
ery can be difficult, 
11 20 24-27 and these results highlight 
some of the challenges. If the information is used to 
provide healthcare from the perspective of the NHS, 
patient and society then ESPs and ENPs are likely to be 
equivalent in cost, or possibly more expensive. If the 
service is to be implemented in secondary care alone 
then the opposite applies. Third, if a view is taken at a 
national level, planning future service delivery and staff-
ing to include educational costs, then all three groups 
become more or less equivalent in terms of both clinical 
quality and cost. At this point it is other factors such as 
workforce availability and sustainability, service provision 
and skill mix that become important. The UK College 
of Emergency Medicine recognises the need to utilise 
extensions in roles due to increasing patient demand, 
reducing hours of work for junior doctors and national 
throughput standards. The use of ENPs and ESPs in 
extended roles will therefore make a significant contri-
bution to future minor injuries care. </p>

<p>28-33 </p>

<p>Future research 
A further larger scale pragmatic trial of equivalence 
throughout the UK, with significantly longer follow-up 
periods and incorporating all the patients managed by 
the different healthcare professionals, would be valuable 
but highly challenging. A qualitative study is warranted 
to explore the subsequent behaviour of patients treated 
for minor injury in an ED, particularly the factors that 
determine further unscheduled healthcare contact. 
Additional research is required to explore the costs and 
consequences of role substitution, both in EDs and in 
other areas of the healthcare system. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION 
These results challenge the notion that training the 
healthcare workforce to undertake extensions in their 
roles is cost effective. Taken together our two papers 
have established that ESPs and ENPs have the competen-
cies needed to achieve high-quality clinical outcomes, 
but they are not necessarily less expensive, depending 
on the perspective adopted. Further research is required 
to understand the underlying reasons for this. We have </p>

<p>not set out to establish the optimum still mix required, 
but believe our research will assist in future strategic 
decision-making. </p>

<p>Contributors CMM initiated the project with input to design and development 
from FC, JP and JB. CMM collected the data and undertook initial analysis 
with supervision and additional input from FC, JP and JB. CMM drafted the 
manuscript which was then revised and approved by FC, JP and JB. CMM 
acts as guarantor. </p>

<p>Funding The research was funded under a PhD bursary from The University 
of the West of England. </p>

<p>Competing interests 'All authors have completed the Unified Competing 
Interest form at http://www.icmje.org/coi_disclosure.pdf (available on request 
from the corresponding author) and declare that (1) CMM, FC, JP and JB 
have support from The University of the West of England for the submitted 
work; (2) CMM, FC,JP and JB have no relationships with The University of the 
West of England that might have an interest in the submitted work in the 
previous 3 years; (3) their spouses, partners, or children have no financial 
relationships that may be relevant to the submitted work; and (4) CMM, FC, 
JP and JB have no non-financial interests that may be relevant to the 
submitted work.' </p>

<p>Ethics approval Ethics approval was obtained by: (1) The Salisbury and South 
Wiltshire Ethics Committee, obtained on 4 May 2006 (ref: 06/Q2008/10). 
(2) The Faculty of Health and Social Care Ethics Committee at the University of 
the West of England, obtained on 10 July 2006 (ref: HSC/06/07/57). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement There are no additional data are available. </p>



<p>McClellan CM, Cramp F, Powell J, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e001116. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001116 </p>



<p>Who is the cheapest at treating soft tissue injuries in emergency departments? </p>





<p>McClellan CM, Cramp F, Powell J, et al. BMJ Open 2013;3:e001116. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001116 </p>

<p>Who is the cheapest at treating soft tissue injuries in emergency departments? </p>

</text></tei>