<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3003812" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Water stress decreases the availability of the gaseous substrate for ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/ 
oxygenase (Rubisco) by decreasing leaf conductance to CO 2 . In spite of limiting photosynthetic carbon assimilation, 
especially in those environments where drought is the predominant factor affecting plant growth and yield, the 
effects of water deprivation on the mechanisms that control Rubisco activity are unclear. In the present study, 11 
Mediterranean species, representing different growth forms, were subject to increasing levels of drought stress, the 
most severe one followed by rewatering. The results confirmed species-specific patterns in the decrease in the 
initial activity and activation state of Rubisco as drought stress and leaf dehydration intensified. Nevertheless, all 
species followed roughly the same trend when Rubisco activity was related to stomatal conductance (g s ) and 
chloroplastic CO 2 concentration (C c ), suggesting that deactivation of Rubisco sites could be induced by low C c , as 
a result of water stress. The threshold level of C c that triggered Rubisco deactivation was dependent on leaf 
characteristics and was related to the maximum attained for each species under non-stressing conditions. Those 
species adapted to low C c were more capable of maintaining active Rubisco as drought stress intensified. </p>

<p>Worldwide, water availability is considered the environmen-
tal factor that most strongly influences plant growth and 
yield (Boyer, 1982), and global climate change is expected to 
exacerbate water limitations in semi-arid ecosystems like the 
Mediterranean (IPCC 2007). Although photosynthesis has 
frequently been documented among the primary physiolog-
ical processes affected by water shortage, a controversy still 
exists on whether drought effects on photosynthesis are due 
to 'stomatal' or 'non-stomatal' limitations (Flexas and  Medrano, 2002; Lawlor and Cornic, 2002). Stomatal 
limitations result from the resistance to CO 2 diffusion from 
the atmosphere to intercellular leaf spaces, while non-
stomatal limitations are often assumed to be metabolic </p>

<p>constraints. However, there is increasing evidence that the 
conductance determining transfer of CO 2 from the intercel-
lular leaf spaces to the vicinity of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate 
carboxylase/oxygenase (Rubisco), i.e. the mesophyll con-
ductance, g m , has a finite value and frequently decreases 
under drought (Flexas et al., 2008; Warren, 2008). There-
fore, the controversy of 'stomatal' versus 'non-stomatal' 
limitations of photosynthesis has been replaced by 'diffu-
sive' versus 'metabolic' (or biochemical) limitations (Grassi  and Magnani, 2005; Galmés et al., 2007b). While it is well 
established that under mild to moderate stress, drought-
induced reductions in photosynthesis are mainly due to 
diffusive limitations-i.e. decreased stomatal and mesophyll </p>

<p>Abbreviations: C c , chloroplastic CO 2 concentration; DTT, dithiothreitol; EGTA, ethyleneglycol-bis(b-aminoethylether)-N,N,N#N#-tetraacetic acid; ETR, electron transfer 
rate; g m , mesophyll conductance; g s , stomatal conductance; LMA, leaf mass per area; MiWS, mild water stress; MoWS, moderate water stress; Na-DIECA, sodium 
diethyldithiocarbamate; PEG, polyethyleneglycol; PMSF, phenylmethylsulfonylfluoride; PPFD, photosynthetically active photon flux density; PVP, polyvinylpyrrolidone; 
Rubisco, ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase; RW, rewatered; RWC, relative water content; SeWS, severe water stress; SWC, soil water content; WW, 
well watered. 
ª 2010 The Author(s). </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-
nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>conductance-(Chaves et al. 2002; Flexas and Medrano,  2002), there is less of a consensus about the limiting process 
when drought intensity is increased. Similarly, there is much 
less information on the limitations to photosynthesis re-
covery by severely stressed plants when water is restored 
(Galmés et al., 2007b; Gallé et al., 2009). 
Current atmospheric CO 2 concentration is well below 
saturating for photosynthesis, so the metabolic rate that 
limits photosynthesis in the majority of plants is carboxyl-
ation by Rubisco rather than electron transport or RuBP 
regeneration, although sometimes a co-limitation of both 
metabolic components has been suggested (Lambers et al.,  2008). Under drought, CO 2 availability in leaves is further 
reduced because of stomatal closure, hence leading plants to 
operate in a CO 2 range where Rubisco carboxylation is the 
sole metabolic rate limiting photosynthesis. Therefore, 
despite claims that drought impairs chloroplast ATP 
synthesis and RuBP regeneration (Tezara et al., 1999), if 
any metabolic limitation occurs under drought this is very 
likely to be mediated by Rubisco activity (Flexas et al.,  2004; Grassi and Magnani, 2005). Rubisco activity can be 
estimated by calculations from in vitro and/or in vivo 
measurements (von Caemmerer, 2000). Estimates from 
in vivo measurements are based on the assumptions of the 
Farquhar model adapted to finite g m -i.e. calculation of the 
initial slope of the A N -C c curve or V c,max -(Farquhar et al.,  1980; Niinemets et al., 2009), and usually show that the 
carboxylation capacity is preserved until water stress 
becomes severe (Bota et al., 2004; Grassi and Magnani,  2005; Galmés et al., 2007b; Gallé et al., 2009). On the 
contrary, inconsistencies arise from in vitro measurements 
concerning the metabolic impairment of photosynthesis, 
and particularly of Rubisco activity, under drought. The 
reported effects of water stress on the activity of Rubisco 
differ between reports, precluding a definitive conclusion. 
Hence, observed effects range from major reductions of 
Rubisco activity (Majumdar et al., 1991; Maroco et al.,  2002; Parry et al., 2002), to minor decreases (Flexas et al.,  2006), and even no effect at all (Giménez et al., 1992;  Gunasekera and Berkowitz, 1993; Lal et al., 1996; Pankovic  et al., 1999; Delfine et al., 2001; Pelloux et al., 2001). This 
apparent controversy may be attributed to differences in the 
intensity of drought (Flexas et al., 2006). Alternatively, it 
may arise from interspecific differences, but there are 
studies reporting contradictory effects of water stress on 
Rubisco activity for the same species. For instance, Parry  et al. (2002) showed, in tobacco plants, that down-
regulation of Rubisco activity occurred concomitantly with 
decreases in the leaf relative water content (RWC), while 
Flexas et al. (2006) found no correlation between these 
parameters also in tobacco. In an attempt to explain such 
discrepancies, Flexas et al. (2004) demonstrated that differ-
ences between species disappeared when Rubisco activity 
was plotted against stomatal conductance (g s ) rather than 
RWC. However, a direct relationship between g s and 
Rubisco activity is unlikely. It is possible, though, that this 
observation might be due to an indirect effect, related to the 
influence of g s on the CO 2 concentration in leaves which, in </p>

<p>turn, also depends on the rate of assimilation, controlled by 
Rubisco activity (Flexas et al., 2004). 
Rubisco activity depends on (i) its activation by reaction 
with CO 2 , resulting in the carbamylation of a lysyl residue 
in its active site, (ii) the concentration of Rubisco, and 
(iii) the concentration of tight-binding inhibitors (Roy and  Andrews, 2000). An inverse correlation between the carba-
mylation state and Rubisco concentration has been reported 
(Quick et al., 1991; Ruuska et al., 1998; Eichelmann et al.,  2009). Changes in the concentration of Rubisco have been 
observed under water stress (e.g. Holaday et al., 1992), but 
even in this situation Rubisco concentration is considered to 
be present sufficiently in excess not to limit photosynthesis 
(Pickersgill, 1986; Warren and Adams, 2004). Increases in 
Rubisco tight-binding inhibitors have also been reported 
under conditions of water shortage, although this has 
not been firmly established (Parry et al., 2002). Therefore, 
adjustments of Rubisco activity under water stress are 
mainly attributed to changes in the carbamylation and 
activation state. In situations where light is saturating and 
leaf conductance does not limit CO 2 supply (i.e. in the 
absence of stress), the activation state of Rubisco is max-
imum (Sage et al., 1990). However, water stress, through 
changes in g s and g m , induces a decrease in the concentra-
tion of CO 2 in leaves and therefore in the amount of 
activator CO 2 bound by carbamylation to Rubisco. De-
activation of Rubisco by loss of the carbamate complex in 
the active site has been observed at substomatal CO 2 
concentrations (C i ) of &lt;100 lmol mol 
À1 in some species, 
but not in others (Perchorowicz and Jensen, 1983; von  Caemmerer and Edmondson, 1986; Sage et al., 1990). This 
threshold of internal CO 2 concentration coincides roughly 
with the threshold of chloroplastic CO 2 concentration (C c ) 
inducing decreases in in vivo V c,max in several species 
(Galmés et al., 2007b) and in vitro Rubisco activity in 
tobacco and soybean (Flexas et al., 2006). Overall, this 
evidence suggests that drought-driven effects on Rubisco 
activity are caused by CO 2 starvation and its consequent 
de-carbamylation of the Rubisco catalytic sites. Therefore, 
a survey relating Rubisco activity and C c for a larger 
number of species subjected to gradual imposition of water 
stress and recovery is justified and would help in defining 
the causes of metabolic limitation of photosynthesis under 
drought. 
Problems exist when directly relating in vitro measure-
ments of Rubisco activity to estimates of Rubisco activity 
derived from gas exchange measurements in leaves. In-
complete extraction of Rubisco, prior to activity analysis, 
has been shown to be responsible for inadequate activity to 
support photosynthetic rates measured by gas exchange in 
loblolly pine (Rogers et al., 2001). Rubisco extractions from 
leaves are often incomplete even when care is taken to 
prevent inactivation and precipitation by high contents of 
phenolic or other secondary compounds (Beadle et al.,  1983; Keys and Parry, 1990). There are also inaccuracies in 
estimating Rubisco activity from in vivo measurements of 
gas exchange in leaves and especially in the determination 
of g m needed for the model used. The combined gas </p>



<p>exchange and chlorophyll fluorescence methods for calcu-
lating g m rely on the estimation of parameters requiring 
a number of assumptions and subject to technical limita-
tions, which become relatively more important in certain 
groups of species, like sclerophylls, with leaves covered by 
hairs, and in heterobaric leaves (Flexas et al., 2008; Pons  et al., 2009). Despite these difficulties, qualitative relation-
ships of photosynthetic activity can be seen between in vitro 
and in vivo estimates. 
Here, a set of data showing the effects of water stress on 
Rubisco activity for 11 Mediterranean species from con-
trasting environments grown under common conditions is 
presented. The objectives of the present work were: (i) to 
test the relationship between in vitro measurements and 
in vivo estimations of Rubisco activity; (ii) to check whether 
there is a general pattern in the response of Rubisco activity 
to drought stress in different species, and if so, (iii) to 
discern whether drought-driven changes in Rubisco activity 
are related to C c . </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>Species selection and treatments </p>

<p>Eleven Mediterranean species naturally occurring in the 
Balearic Islands, six of them endemic to these islands, were 
selected for this study (see Galmés et al., 2007a for detailed 
description of the species). The selection of the species 
included taxons representing different growth forms and 
leaf habits: two evergreen sclerophyll shrubs (Pistacia 
lentiscus and Hypericum balearicum), two evergreen scle-
rophyll semi-shrubs (Limonium gibertii and Limonium 
magallufianum), three summer semi-deciduous shrubs 
(Lavatera maritima, Phlomis italica, and Cistus albidus), 
and four herbaceous (Beta maritima ssp. maritima, Beta 
maritima ssp. marcosii, Diplotaxis ibicensis, and Lysimachia 
minoricensis). D. ibicensis, B. maritima ssp. maritima, 
B. maritima ssp. marcosii, L. gibertii, L. magallufianum, and 
L. maritima are species inhabiting the coastal, driest, and 
hottest areas with annual precipitation typically &lt;400 l m </p>

<p>À2 </p>

<p>. 
P. lentiscus, H. balearicum, P. italica, and C. albidus are 
species typical of Mediterranean macchia with annual pre-
cipitation between 400 and 800 l m </p>

<p>À2 </p>

<p>. Finally, L. minoricensis 
lives near open water sources, and probably suffers less from 
water stress episodes. 
The ages of the plants differed because of the different 
phenology of the species selected. Plants of P. lentiscus, 
H. balearicum, C. albidus, P. italica, and L. maritima were 
3 years old, plants of L. magallufianum, and L. gibertii were 
18 months old, and plants of D. ibicensis, B. maritima ssp. 
marcosii, and B. maritima ssp. maritima were 6 months old 
at the onset of the experiments. Similarly, the different 
phenology also influenced the age of leaves used for 
measurements, which was ;1 month for those species with 
the highest rate of leaf emergence (i.e. herbaceous species), 
and ;2-4 months for the remaining species. 
Water treatments are explained in detail in Galmés et al.  (2007a). In brief: 10 adult plants per species were placed in </p>

<p>a controlled growth chamber with a 12 h photoperiod 
(26°C day, 20°C night) and a photon flux density at the 
top of the leaves of ;700 lmol m 
À2 s 
À1 . Plants were 
irrigated daily with 50% Hoagland's solution for 1 month. 
Measurements corresponding to well-watered treatment 
(WW) were made during the first day of the experiment 
and corresponded to plants watered at soil saturation. 
Thereafter, irrigation was stopped in five plants for each 
species. Pots were weighed daily to determine the amount 
of water loss. Plant water availability was referred to the 
control after measurement of soil dry weight in four 
samples representative of the substrate mixture used in the 
experiment. Measurements were performed on days 4, 8, 
and 13-17 after the last irrigation, when plants were 
regarded as affected by mild (MiWS), moderate (MoWS), 
and severe water stress (SeWS), respectively. Plants were 
considered to be under SeWS when g s was close to zero, 
which was achieved between 13 and 17 d after withholding 
water, depending on the species. At this time, pots were 
rewatered to field capacity, and recovery treatment (RW) 
was determined on the next day. Control plants were 
watered daily throughout the experiment and measured 
every 5-6 d to ensure they had maintained constant values. </p>

<p>Plant water status </p>

<p>Parameters related to plant water status, leaf relative water 
content (RWC PD ) and water potential (W PD ) were measured 
pre-dawn as indicated in Galmés et al. (2007a). </p>

<p>Photosynthetic measurements </p>

<p>Chlorophyll fluorescence parameters were measured on 
attached leaves using a portable pulse amplitude modulation 
fluorometer (PAM-2000; Walz, Effeltrich, Germany). At 
mid-morning, the PSII photochemical efficiency (DF/F m #) 
was determined by measuring the steady state fluorescence 
(F s ) and the maximum fluorescence (F m #) during a light-
saturating pulse of ;8000 lmol m 
À2 s </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>, following Genty  et al. (1989): </p>

<p>DF =F </p>

<p># </p>

<p>m ¼ </p>

<p>À 
F </p>

<p># </p>

<p>m À F s </p>

<p>Á 
=F </p>

<p># 
m </p>

<p>The electron transport rate (ETR) was then calculated as: </p>

<p>ETR ¼ DF =F </p>

<p># </p>

<p>m PPFDab </p>

<p>where PPFD is the photosynthetically active photon flux 
density, a is the leaf absorptance, and b is the distribution 
of absorbed energy between the two photosystems. b was 
assumed to be 0.5. Leaf absorptances were determined for 
all 11 species in 10 replicates on leaves of well-irrigated 
plants with a spectroradiometer coupled to an integration 
sphere (UniSpec; PP-Systems, Amesbury, MA, USA). 
A value of 0.84 was obtained for all species, except for 
C. albidus and P. italica (0.74 and 0.77, respectively). Potential 
changes in leaf absorptance with water stress were not </p>

<p>Rubisco activity in Mediterranean species under water stress | 655 </p>

<p>assessed and assumed to be small and to induce no important 
biases in the calculations of ETR. 
Light-saturated net CO 2 assimilation rates (A N ) and g s 
were measured at mid-morning on attached, fully developed 
young leaves of four to five plants per species and treat-
ment, using a gas exchange system (Li-6400; Li-Cor Inc., 
Lincoln, NE, USA). Environmental conditions in the leaf 
chamber consisted of a PPFD of 1500 lmol m 
À2 s </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>, 
a vapour pressure deficit of 1.0-1.5 kPa, an air temperature 
of 25°C, and an ambient CO 2 concentration (C a ) of 
400 lmol mol air 
À1 . After inducing steady-state photosyn-
thesis, the photosynthesis response to varying substomatal 
CO 2 concentration (C i ) was measured as explained in 
Galmés et al. (2007b). To transform A N -C i curves to A N -C c 
curves, the CO 2 concentration in the chloroplasts (C c ) was 
calculated from combined gas exchange and chlorophyll 
fluorescence measurements according to Epron et al. (1995)  and using the in vitro Rubisco specificity factor values from 
Galmés et al. (2005). </p>

<p>Biochemical measurements </p>

<p>For measurements of Rubisco activity, two leaf discs (1 cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>each) were punched, frozen immediately in liquid N 2 , and 
kept at -80°C until assay. Four to five replicates per species 
and treatment were taken at midday immediately after 
steady-state gas exchange measurements. Environmental 
conditions in the leaf chamber were identical to those 
explained above in the photosynthetic measurements 
section. 
For Rubisco activity analysis, samples were ground to 
a fine powder in a mortar, previously chilled with liquid 
nitrogen, and homogenized in 1 ml of an ice-cold 
extraction medium. Preliminary tests determined that the 
most appropriate protein extraction media for Rubisco 
(i.e. that yielded the maximum activity for each species) 
were: (A) 0.1 M Bicine, 50 mM b-mercaptoethanol, 11 mM 
sodium diethyldithiocarbamate (Na-DIECA), 6% (w/v) 
polyethyleneglycol (PEG) 4000, 1 mM benzamidine, 1 mM 
e-amino-n-caproic acid, and 1 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl-
fluoride (PMSF), at pH 8, and (B) containing 0.1 M 
HEPES, 3% (w/v) polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP) 25, 6% (w/v) 
PEG 4000, 50 mM b-mercaptoethanol, 2 mM dithiothreitol 
(DTT), 10% glycerol, 5 mM MgCl 2 , 5 mM ethyleneglycol-
bis(b-aminoethylether)-N,N,N'N'-tetraacetic acid (EGTA), 
and 2 mM PMSF, at pH 8.0. Buffer A was used to extract 
Rubisco from most of the species. Buffer B was used with 
P. lentiscus and C. albidus. Extracts were clarified by cen-
trifugation (12 000 rpm at 4°C for 1 min) and the 
supernatant immediately assayed at 25°C for Rubisco 
activity. 
Initial and total activities were determined according to 
Keys and Parry (1990). Initial activity was determined by 
adding 25 ll of supernatant to 475 ml of a CO 2 -free assay 
buffer containing 100 mM Bicine, pH 8.2, and 20 mM 
MgCl 2 , to which NaH </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>CO 3 (7.4 kBq lmol 
À1 ) and RuBP 
had been added, to concentrations of 10 and 0.4 mM, 
respectively, immediately prior to adding the extract. Total </p>

<p>activity was determined by incubating 20 ml of extract for 3 
min in 980 ml of the same assay buffer without RuBP and 
to allow for the carbamylation of all available active sites. 
The assay was started by adding RuBP to 0.4 mM as above. 
Rubisco activation state was obtained from the ratio of 
initial to total activity. 
Total soluble protein was determined on the same 
samples according to the method of Bradford (1976). </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Regression coefficients and bivariate correlations were 
calculated with the <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">11.0</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">Sigma Plot</rs> software package (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS</rs>, 
Chicago, IL, USA). A set of simple ANOVAs were per-
formed to compare different treatments. Differences between 
means were revealed by Duncan analyses (P&lt;0.05) per-
formed with the <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version">17.0</rs> software package. </p>

<p>Results and discussion </p>

<p>Progressive effects of water stress on Rubisco 
parameters </p>

<p>The response of pre-dawn leaf water potential (W PD ) and 
relative water content (RWC PD ) to water stress and re-
covery during this experiment has previously been reported 
(Galmés et al., 2007a). Leaf RWC PD and W PD decreased 
progressively with soil water content (SWC) in all species 
(Table 1). The largest decreases in RWC PD were observed at 
SeWS, and ranged from 38% for P. italica to 70% for 
L. magallufianum. Similarly, at SeWS W PD varied from less 
than -5 MPa for P. italica to -1 MPa for D. ibicensis. The 
extent of recovery 24 h after rewatering severely stressed 
plants depended on the species: all species except 
P. lentiscus and P. italica recovered RWC PD and W PD to 
values similar to those measured under WW conditions. 
All species showed a progressive decline in the Rubisco 
initial activity as water stress intensified, starting at MiWS, 
except for the two Beta spp. (Fig. 1). Rubisco activation 
state followed a slightly different pattern, maintaining 
values similar to those in irrigated plants under MiWS to 
MoWS, depending on the species, and declining under 
SeWS (Fig. 1). This trend is illustrated by the biphasic 
relationship between activation state and initial activity 
(Fig. 2), with an initial phase where activation state remains 
constant while initial activity decreases followed by a second 
phase where decreases in both parameters occurred concur-
rently. This fact suggests that under MiWS to MoWS, 
decreases in Rubisco activity are mainly due to decreases in 
the concentration of Rubisco reaction sites (i.e. initial and 
total Rubisco activity decrease concomitantly), either due to 
decreases in the enzyme concentration or to increases in the 
inhibitors bound to the sites of reaction. Early drought-
induced losses of Rubisco have been reported by both 
transcriptomic (Kawaguchi et al., 2003) and proteomic 
approaches (Holaday et al., 1992), although increases have 
also been reported in some species (Cramer et al., 2007;  Vincent et al., 2007). The species selected in this study, </p>



<p>although inhabiting contrasting environments, are typically 
Mediterranean, and therefore adapted to frequent but 
unpredictable drought events (Galmés et al., 2007a). 
Moreover, due to their relatively low g s and g m (Galmés 
et al., 2007a), they often present C c values close to or below 
the threshold of 100 lmol mol 
À1 , i.e. they operate normally 
close to conditions favourable for Rubisco inactivation 
(Perchorowicz and Jensen, 1983). Among potentially ad-
vantageous adaptations to such stress conditions, interac-
tions of Rubisco with tight-binding inhibitors would 
prevent Rubisco that is not being used for catalysis from 
being degraded by proteases (Parry et al., 2008). Thereafter, 
at MoWS to SeWS, deactivation of Rubisco becomes the 
predominant cause for decreased Rubisco activity, in 
agreement with previous reports (Sharkey and Seemann,  1989). When exposed to severe water stress, many plants 
accumulate osmolytes, such as proline, glycine betaine, and 
sugar alcohols (Yoshiba et al., 1997). In vitro analyses 
demonstrate that high concentrations of these osmolytes 
have potential to curtail the activity of Rubisco (Sivakumar   et al., 1998; Sivakumar et al., 2002). Therefore, the observed 
decrease in Rubisco activity at SeWS could be, at least 
partially, due to the accumulation of osmolytes. 
The recovery of Rubisco initial activity and activation 
state after SeWS was also species dependent. In general, 
activation state recovered better than initial activity, 
although with some exceptions, such as the two Limonium 
species (Fig. 1). This pattern is indicative of higher recovery 
of total activity as compared with initial activity, and 
consequently that an increase in the concentration of 
Rubisco active sites occurred after rewatering (Parry et al.,  2002). </p>

<p>Relationship between in vitro and in vivo estimates of 
Rubisco activity </p>

<p>Rapid, one-step homogenization procedures used for 
Rubisco extraction are required to preserve enzyme activa-
tion state (Keys and Parry, 1990). However, Rogers et al.  (2001) demonstrated that these procedures fail to efficiently </p>

<p>Table 1. SWC (expressed as a percentage of well-watered treatments), leaf RWC PD , and leaf W PD for the 11 species under the different 
treatments </p>

<p>Values are means6standard errors of four to five replicates. Data taken from Galmé s et al. (2007b). </p>

<p>Species 
WW 
MiWS 
MoWS 
SeWS 
RW </p>

<p>D. ibicensis 
SWC (%) 
100.060.0 
68.663.4 
37.565.3 
26.765.8 
89.764.1 
RWC PD 
80.261.3 
70.461.4 
67.563.2 
62.367.2 
79.962.8 
W PD 
-0.436-0.03 
-0.696-0.02 
-0.946-0.06 
-1.006-0.11 
-0.986-0.03 
L. minoricensis 
SWC (%) 
100.060.0 
65.662.6 
58.463.6 
49.564.6 
90.665.7 
RWC PD 
76.160.9 
70.666.2 
73.564.2 
44.763.8 
71.863.6 
W PD 
-0.576-0.08 
-1.196-0.31 
-1.316-0.39 
-2.796-0.26 
-0.646-0.07 
B. maritima ssp. marcosii 
SWC (%) 
100.060.0 
62.861.5 
19.565.0 
7.465.0 
90.862.1 
RWC PD 
80.163.8 
87.362.1 
78.061.7 
51.165.7 
86.762.0 
W PD 
-0.336-0.01 
-0.456-0.03 
-0.896-0.04 
-3.346-0.10 
-0.526-0.06 
B. maritima ssp. maritima 
SWC (%) 
100.060.0 
56.965.0 
26.861.2 
12.565.3 
91.463.2 
RWC PD 
78.060.9 
80.264.1 
79.062.5 
51.063.5 
84.761.9 
W PD 
-0.336-0.01 
-0.446-0.05 
-0.806-0.05 
-3.746-0.09 
-0.436-0.01 
L. magallufianum 
SWC (%) 
100.060.0 
54.262.3 
46.061.5 
40.161.3 
98.762.8 
RWC PD 
88.960.5 
85.862.0 
80.362.3 
69.561.6 
87.062.7 
W PD 
-0.536-0.03 
-0.556-0.07 
-0.656-0.07 
-1.386-0.14 
-1.026-0.03 
L. gibertii 
SWC (%) 
100.060.0 
56.863.4 
49.163.4 
44.663.4 
92.362.5 
RWC PD 
90.660.9 
88.361.9 
77.660.8 
66.865.1 
87.764.2 
W PD 
-0.556-0.03 
-0.496-0.04 
-0.616-0.03 
-1.056-0.09 
-0.936-0.07 
H. balearicum 
SWC (%) 
100.060.0 
85.967.3 
52.767.0 
30.765.9 
85.464.4 
RWC PD 
91.261.3 
93.161.1 
89.961.3 
48.765.2 
85.562.4 
W PD 
-0.386-0.00 
-0.436-0.02 
-0.666-0.05 
-2.966-0.16 
-0.946-0.14 
P. lentiscus 
SWC (%) 
100.060.0 
61.467.6 
25.568.2 
14.667.1 
88.665.5 
RWC PD 
94.860.5 
87.563.3 
86.163.8 
53.764.9 
81.265.4 </p>

<p>W PD 
-0.306-0.03 
-0.456-0.05 
-1.496-0.58 
-4.556-0.45 
-2.686-0.28 
P. italica 
SWC (%) 
100.060.0 
74.864.6 
57.061.8 
47.761.8 
114.765.4 
RWC PD 
83.661.5 
80.060.8 
75.660.8 
37.963.0 
74.461.6 </p>

<p>W PD 
-0.336-0.01 
-0.426-0.03 
-1.986-0.11 
&lt; -5.00 
-0.656-0.05 
C. albidus 
SWC (%) 
100.060.0 
72.764.9 
53.461.8 
42.762.9 
104.461.6 
RWC PD 
75.764.3 
88.364.3 
79.564.0 
46.066.1 
70.261.5 </p>

<p>W PD 
-0.516-0.04 
-0.686-0.06 
-1.146-0.14 
-4.126-0.56 
-2.106-0.10 
L. maritima 
SWC (%) 
100.060.0 
57.766.1 
35.966.8 
27.066.0 
91.163.4 
RWC PD 
86.662.3 
82.262.5 
73.463.5 
54.865.5 
80.663.2 
W PD 
-0.416-0.05 
-0.896-0.09 
-1.536-0.13 
-3.546-0.25 
-0.736-0.21 </p>

<p>Rubisco activity in Mediterranean species under water stress | 657 </p>

<p>extract Rubisco from leaves, and therefore lead to un-
derestimation of Rubisco activity. In the present study, 
Rubisco activity was ;20% of the estimated maximum 
velocity of carboxylation (V c,max ) in all 11 species (data not 
shown). Fig. 3 shows the relationship between Rubisco 
initial activity and V c,max , both parameters expressed as 
a percentage of the values at WW, to unify axis scales. </p>

<p>Despite such bias, the relationship between Rubisco initial 
activity and V c,max was linear and significant for each 
species (i.e. the lowest R 
2 was for H. balearicum with 
0.522), indicating that in vitro measurements of Rubisco 
activity were qualitatively consistent with in vivo values, as 
previously reported (e.g. Myers et al., 1999; Rogers et al.,  2001). On the other hand, it is also documented that the 
effectiveness of Rubisco extraction and assay procedures is 
dependent on the presence of phenols and other secondary 
metabolites (Beadle et al., 1983; Keys and Parry, 1990), 
which varies depending on the species and stress conditions 
(Turtola et al., 2003; André et al., 2009). This fact could 
explain differences in the slope of the relationship between 
Rubisco initial activity and V c,max between species (Fig. 3). 
In this sense, D. ibicensis, B. maritima ssp. maritima, 
P. italica, and L. maritima were the species presenting the 
highest slope, while L. magallufianum, L. gibertii, and 
B. maritima ssp. marcosii presented the lowest slope. 
Alternatively, it may be argued that the estimation of 
V c,max might be biased, due to the multiple assumptions 
included in its calculation. To test this possibility, it may be 
necessary to compare Rubisco activity values with some 
in vivo parameter, such as the ETR, which is more straight-
forward to determine. A 'photosynthetic control' exists in 
leaves where the balance between DpH, ATP synthesis, and 
redox state adjust supply to demand so that the [ATP]/ 
[ADP] and [NADPH]/[NADP 
+ ] ratios are remarkably 
constant in steady-state conditions (Foyer et al., 1990). 
Therefore, it is likely that the rate of electron transport in 
the thylakoids and Rubisco activity in the stroma are co-
regulated, and therefore ETR would indirectly reflect </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Rubisco initial activity (filled symbols) and activation state 
(open symbols) under different treatments: WW, MiWS, MoWS, 
SeWS, and RW. Values are means6SE of four to five replicates 
per species and treatment. Different letters denote statistical 
differences by Duncan test (P&lt;0.05) between treatments for each 
parameter. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Relationship between Rubisco initial activity and activation 
state. Values are means6SE of four to five replicates per species 
and treatment. Values from the RW treatment were excluded from 
this analysis. Symbols and species as follows: black circles, 
D. ibicensis; black squares, L. minoricensis; black triangles, 
B. maritima ssp. marcosii; upside down black triangles, 
B. maritima ssp. maritima; light-grey squares L. magallufianum; 
light-grey circles, L. gibertii, dark-grey circles, C. albidus; 
dark-grey, L. maritima; dark-grey triangles, P. italica; open circles, 
H. balearicum; and open squares, P. lentiscus. </p>



<p>variations in Rubisco activity. ETR is indeed co-regulated 
with V c,max in Mediterranean species (Galmés et al., 2007a), 
and its use in place of V c,max as a proxy for metabolic 
limitation results in very similar estimations of the latter 
under water stress (Gallé et al., 2009). In the present study, 
initial activity of Rubisco was highly correlated with ETR </p>

<p>(Fig. 4A), as it was with the CO 2 net assimilation rate (A N ) 
(Fig. 4B). These results confirm that despite potential 
activity losses during extraction, in vitro measurements of 
Rubisco activity were proportional to in vivo measurements 
and qualitatively representative of what occurs in vivo. 
Although the relationship between Rubisco initial activity 
and A N was linear when plotting all species together 
(Fig. 4B), it was logarithmic for 6 of the 11 species when 
considered individually (data not shown). In particular, 
some of the species with larger maximum A N and g s display 
a logarithmic response, while evergreen sclerophylls span-
ning a shorter range of values display a linear response. 
This could be related to the fact that the latter, due to lower 
maximum g s and g m , operate always at C c below the general 
inflexion point for Rubisco inactivation (see next section). </p>

<p>Causes for reduced Rubisco activity under water stress </p>

<p>Both Rubisco initial activity and its activation state 
presented a positive linear relationship when plotted against 
RWC PD (Fig. 5A, C); however, it turned into a logarithmic 
biphasic relationship when these two parameters were 
plotted against g s (Fig. 5B, D). Although all four correla-
tions were highly significant (P&lt;0.0001), by using g s the 
regression coefficients became higher, in agreement with 
previous surveys suggesting g s as a reference parameter 
(Medrano et al., 2002; Flexas et al., 2004). Moreover, when 
analysed for each individual species, the relationship 
between Rubisco parameters and RWC PD was significant 
for only three of the species (Table 2), while that with g s was 
generally significant (not shown) 
Rubisco initial activity and activation state did not 
correlate with the substomatal CO 2 concentration (C i ) 
(Fig. 6A, C). In fact, maximum values for initial activity 
and activation state were observed at intermediate C i 
values, perhaps reflecting the typical response of C i to 
drought consisting in decreases at mild to moderate stress 
followed by increases at more severe stress (Medrano et al.,  2002). By contrast, when plotting Rubisco initial activity 
and activation state against C c , significant correlations were 
observed (Fig. 6B, D). As occurred with RWC PD , the 
relationships between Rubisco initial activity and C c and 
between activation state and C c , presented an important 
scattering when plotting all species together. However, the 
regression coefficients generally improved when considering 
each species individually, being always higher than those 
with RWC PD (Table 2). By breaking the covariation 
between g s and RWC, Flexas et al. (2006) observed that 
down-regulation of Rubisco activity was not dependent on 
RWC, but occurred at a certain threshold of g s (&lt;0.05 mol 
m 
À2 s 
À1 ) and C c (&lt;100 lmol mol 
À1 ), although the relation-
ship between Rubisco activity and C c was less clear. In the 
present study, Rubisco initial activity correlated, at P &lt; 
0.05, with RWC for three species, and with C c for nine 
species (Table 2). A similar trend was observed for the 
activation state (Table 2). It is worth noting that RW values 
were not consistent with the relationship in several species. 
Remarkably, the poorest correlations were found in shrubs </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Relationship between Rubisco initial activity and maximum 
velocity of carboxylation (V c,max ) for the 11 species. To unify scales 
between different species, values are expressed in percentage 
with respect to WW plants, and represent means6SE of four to 
five replicates per species and treatment. Empty symbols repre-
sent values from RW treatments. Regression coefficients for each 
relationship are shown. </p>

<p>Rubisco activity in Mediterranean species under water stress | 659 </p>

<p>(H. balearicum, P. lentiscus, C. albidus, and P. italica), with 
higher leaf mass per area (LMA), while in all herbaceous 
(D. ibicensis, L. minoricensis, B. maritima ssp. marcosii, and 
B. maritima ssp. maritima), and semi-shrub (L. magallufia-
num and L. gibertii) species both Rubisco initial activity and 
its activation state significantly correlated with C c . In 
general, these data demonstrate that regulation of Rubisco 
activity is more related to CO 2 availability in the vicinity of 
the enzyme than to leaf hydration status. Species-dependent 
patterns of Rubisco activity regulation under drought stress </p>

<p>have previously been documented (Parry et al., 2002; Bota  et al., 2004; Flexas et al., 2006). 
The present results suggest that low C c induced by the 
imposition of water stress could induce deactivation of 
Rubisco sites. Previously, in vivo Rubisco deactivation was 
observed at C i &lt;100 lmol mol 
À1 in several species, e.g. 
Chenopodium albus, Raphanus sativus, Triticum aestivum, 
and Phaseolus vulgaris (Perchorowicz and Jensen, 1983; von  Caemmerer and Edmondson, 1986; Sage et al., 1990; Sage  et al., 2002). The K act [CO 2 ], i.e. the CO 2 concentration that </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Relationship between Rubisco initial activity and (A) ETR, and (B) A N . Values are means6standard error of four to five replicates 
per species and treatment. Values from rewatering treatments were excluded from this analysis. Regression coefficients and significance 
for each relationship are shown. Symbols and species are as in Fig. 2. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Relationship between Rubisco initial activity and activation state with the leaf RWC PD and g s . Values are means6SE of four to five 
replicates per species and treatment. Values from rewatering treatments were excluded from this analysis. Regression coefficients and 
significance for each relationship are shown. Symbols and species are as in Fig. 2. </p>



<p>supports half of the maximal activation has been reported 
to be 120 lmol mol 
À1 for in vitro systems with activase 
(Portis et al., 1986). Sage et al. (2002) suggested that in vivo 
K act [CO 2 ] is probably &lt;60 lmol mol 
À1 . In agreement with 
this suggestion, in the present study Rubisco activation 
started to decline at C c below ;120 lmol mol 
À1 (Fig. 6D). 
At this low C c , the equilibrium between carbamylated and 
decarbamylated Rubisco will shift towards the latter form. 
The major aim of the present study was to find global 
relationships between Rubisco activity and physiology 
under drought using several species pooled. However, it is 
clear that species belonging to very different growth forms 
and leaf habitats, even if they all often experience drought 
in their natural environments, undergo different average 
operational and maximum C c . For instance, evergreen 
sclerophylls show the lowest stomatal and mesophyll 
conductance even under irrigation (Galmés et al., 2007b), </p>

<p>and therefore the lowest maximum C c (Fig. 7, light-grey and 
empty symbols). Perennial and annual herbs, as well as 
semi-deciduous species, present much larger g s and g m when 
irrigated, and therefore experience larger C c (Fig. 7, black 
and dark-grey symbols). These differential features may 
induce differences in Rubisco between species. Indeed, 
Galmés et al. (2005) showed that Rubisco specificity factor 
positively scaled with sclerophylly, i.e. it was larger in 
species with lower g s and g m . It is shown here (Fig. 6D), as 
in Perchorowitz and Jensen (1983) and Flexas et al. (2006)  that, globally, inactivation of Rubisco is induced by a C c 
of &lt;100 lmol mol 
À1 . However, due to their intrinsic leaf 
morphology and physiology, evergreen species always 
operate at C c &lt;100 lmol mol 
À1 , even with stomata fully 
open (Fig. 7), while herbs and semi-deciduous plants 
present maximum C c values of between 130 and 200 lmol 
mol 
À1 , operating at lower C c only when subjected to 
drought. This seems to have induced evolutionary differ-
ences at the level of Rubisco activation sensitivity to C c . 
Hence, even when in all species the inflexion point for 
Rubisco inactivation is at a C c of ;100640 lmol mol </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>(Fig. 6), there is a linear correlation between the maximum 
operational C c and the actual value of C c at the inflexion 
point for Rubisco inactivation (Fig. 7). 
These results suggest that those species adapted to low 
C c,max are able to maintain active Rubisco at lower C c . One 
possible explanation could be that Rubisco from these species 
has an intrinsically lower K act [CO 2 ]. Another possibility is that 
Rubisco activase is more active or present in higher concen-
trations in these species. Higher concentration and/or activa-
tion of Rubisco activase would improve removal of RuBP and 
other tightly bound sugar phosphates from the sites of 
reaction (Portis et al., 2008). Finally, formation of side-
products, such as xylulose-1,5-bisphosphate and pentodiulose-
1,5-bisphosphate, from the enediol intermediate during 
Rubisco catalysis can progressively inhibit Rubisco turnover. 
Pearce (2006) demonstrated that the rate of production of 
these side-products increased when the [CO 2 ]/[O 2 ] ratio de-
creased, and such decreases occur under water stress (Galmés  et al., 2006). In consequence, differences in C c,ip may be 
caused by a lower rate of formation of side-products at a given 
C c for species with lower C c,ip . In addition, Pearce (2006) also 
suggested that species with a higher specificity factor produce 
relatively fewer side-products, and Galmés et al. (2005)  observed, by studying these same species included in the 
present work, that Rubisco specificity factor tended to be 
higher in species with sclerophyll leaves (and therefore lower 
C c,ip ). Differences among species and groups in Rubisco 
responses to drought will deserve better attention in future 
studies. </p>

<p>Concluding remarks </p>

<p>The present study shows that decreases in the activity of 
Rubisco in response to drought occur in well-adapted 
Mediterranean species belonging to different growth forms 
and leaf habits. Decreases in both Rubisco initial activity 
and its activation correlated better with changes in stomatal </p>

<p>Table 2. Bivariate correlations between Rubisco initial activity, 
Rubisco activation state, leaf RWC PD , and C c for the 11 species 
included in the study </p>

<p>Rewatering data were included in the analysis. Linear and logarithmic 
correlations were considered and values correspond to the best fit. </p>

<p>Initial activity 
Activation state </p>

<p>D. ibicensis 
RWC PD 
0.314 
0.388 
C c 
0.700 
0.840* 
L. minoricensis 
RWC PD 
0.725 
0.629 
C c 
0.862* 
0.888** 
B. maritima ssp. marcosii 
RWC PD 
0.821* 
0.673 
C c 
0.874** 
0.862* 
B. maritima ssp. maritima 
RWC PD 
0.724 
0.653 
C c 
0.927** 
0.754* 
L. magallufianum 
RWC PD 
0.785* 
0.527 
C c 
0.954** 
0.890** 
L. gibertii 
RWC PD 
0.725 
0.192 
C c 
0.758* 
0.992** 
H. balearicum 
RWC PD 
0.728 
0.818* 
C c 
0.080 
0.008 
P. lentiscus 
RWC PD 
0.687 
0.967** 
C c 
0.811* 
0.149 
C. albidus 
RWC PD 
0.651 
0.325 
C c 
0.800* 
0.375 
P. italica 
RWC PD 
0.334 
0.763* 
C c 
0.774* 
0.661 
L. maritime 
RWC PD 
0.958** 
0.957** 
C c 
0.822* 
0.780* </p>

<p>* P&lt;0.05; **P&lt;0.01. </p>

<p>Rubisco activity in Mediterranean species under water stress | 661 </p>

<p>conductance than with changes in relative water content. 
Since a direct effect of stomatal conductance on Rubisco is 
unlikely, we suggest that the effect is mediated by decreases 
in CO 2 availability induced by lower stomatal and meso-
phyll conductance, rather than by increases in leaf de-
hydration. In fact, both Rubisco initial activity, and 
especially, Rubisco activation, showed a threshold relation-
ship with in vivo estimated C c that matches theoretical 
values obtained from in vitro studies. While there are some 
differences between species in the precise C c threshold value 
so that species with low g s and thick leaves are able to 
maintain carbamylated Rubisco at lower values of C c , 
evergreen sclerophyll species operate most of their life 
below that threshold, due to low maximum g s and g m even 
when water is available. In herbs and semi-deciduous 
species, the threshold is often reached during the frequent 
droughts occurring in the Mediterranean. 
In conclusion, the results of the present study suggest that 
drought-driven decreases in C c may induce deactivation of 
Rubisco and that photosynthesis in Mediterranean species 
may be constrained by lower Rubisco activation as a conse-
quence of the need to keep stomata substantially closed in 
a water-scarce environment. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors are grateful to M Truyols and P Sastre for 
their excellent technical assistance during field and lab </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Relationship between the chloroplastic CO 2 concentration 
at its maximum (C c,max ) and at the inflexion point (C c,ip ) in the 
relationship between Rubisco activation state and C c . For all 
species, C c,max was C c at WW conditions. For the calculation of 
C c,ip , RW data were not considered. For all species, except 
L. minoricensis, a logarithmic function was applied in the 
relationship Rubisco activation state versus C c , and the lowest R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>was 0.883. L. minoricensis is not included in the analysis because 
its C c,ip could not be obtained (C c,ip &gt;100 lmol mol </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>) due to the 
linear relationship between Rubisco activation state and C c . 
Regression coefficient and significance of the relationship are 
shown. Symbols and species are as in Fig. 2. </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Relationship between Rubisco initial activity and activation state with substomatal (C i ) and chloroplastic (C c ) CO 2 concentration. 
Values are means6SE of four to five replicates per species and treatment. Values from rewatering treatments were excluded from this 
analysis. Regression coefficients and significance for each relationship are shown. Symbols and species are as in Fig. 2. </p>



<p>measurements. Dr AJ Keys is greatly acknowledged for 
improving earlier versions of the manuscript. This work was 
supported by project AGL2009-07999 (Plan Nacional,  Spain). </p>



<p>Rubisco activity in Mediterranean species under water stress | 663 </p>







<p>Rubisco activity in Mediterranean species under water stress | 665 </p>

</text></tei>