<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3505860" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Over the last decade, the detection of chromosomal abnormalities has shifted from conventional 
karyotyping under a light microscope to molecular detection using microarrays. The latter technology 
identified copy number variation as a major source of variation in the human genome; moreover, 
copy number variants were found responsible for 10-20% of cases of intellectual disability. Recent 
technological advances in microarray technology have also enabled the detection of very small local 
chromosomal rearrangements, sometimes affecting the function of only a single gene. Here, we illustrate 
how high resolution microarray analysis has led to increased insights into the contribution of specific 
genes in disease. </p>

<p>Karyotyping, a technique to visualize banded chromo-
somes under a light microscope, allows for the genome-
wide detection of chromosomal rearrangements with a 
resolution up to 5 Mb, roughly corresponding to the size 
of a single chromosome band. This technique led to the 
discovery of aneuploidies, such as Down's syndrome, 
caused by an additional chromosome 21, as well as large 
structural variants, including interchromosomal transloca-
tions. The introduction of targeted methods, such as 
fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) and multiplex 
ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), 
enabled the detection of smaller rearrangements with a 
resolution up to 150 kb -100 bp in selected regions of the 
genome. More recently, the development of microarrays 
has enabled the detection of small aberrations on a 
genome-wide scale [1-3]. The use of genome-wide arrays 
in populations of healthy controls led to the discovery of 
copy number variation. Copy number variants are defined 
as deletions or duplications not detectable by conven-
tional karyotyping, with a size of at least 1,000 bp [4]. 
Currently, this technique detects very local, small chro-
mosomal rearrangements of only a few kb in addition to 
large copy number variants in a routine basis. Such small 
aberrations may affect only a single gene and, thus, create </p>

<p>unique opportunities to study gene function. This report 
highlights some recent breakthroughs in genomic research 
made possible by the detection of such small abnormal-
ities and looks ahead to how the increased resolution of 
arrays can further contribute to gene discovery. </p>

<p>Copy number variants in the healthy population </p>

<p>Somewhat surprisingly, the percentage of our genome that 
can harbour copy number variants is still the subject of 
debate. The first large-scale microarray study utilising a 
26 K tiling path bacterial artificial chromosome (BAC) 
array platform estimated that 12% of the genome is 
subject to copy number variants [5]. Because of the probe 
size of at least 100 kb, these platforms typically over-
estimate individual copy number variant size and, 
consequently, also the total copy number variant content 
in our genome. However, after studying more than 2,000 
individuals on higher resolution arrays containing over 
550,000 probes, Shaikh et al. [6] and Itsara et al. [7] 
concluded that 16-19.4% of the genome is subject to copy 
number variants. This higher proportion is mainly a 
consequence of the increase in sample size compared to 
the previous study, as the total copy number variant 
content was composed of many small and rare copy 
number variants. Consequently, it would be reasonable to 
expect that the estimation of 3.7% copy number variable </p>



<p>(page number not for citation purposes) </p>

<p>Published: 01 November 2012 
© 2012 Faculty of 1000 Ltd </p>

<p>content in the genome, which was obtained by analysing 
just 41 HapMap individuals on a NimbleGen array set 
containing~42 million oligonucleotide probes -the 
microarray platform with the highest possible resolution 
today, would increase to a similar high percentage if the 
study population was sufficiently large to catalogue rare 
variants [8]. </p>

<p>Copy number variants identified by major studies on 
healthy populations, such as the HapMap project, which is 
aimed at cataloguing normal genetic variation in man, are 
accessible through the Database of Genomic Variants 
(DGV). This database currently holds 37 microarray 
studies, and is, thus, a rich catalogue of human variation 
in healthy individuals. According to the DGV statistics 
consulted in June 2012, about 50% of the human reference 
genome may be copy number variable in healthy 
individuals [4]. At the moment, it is uncertain whether 
the cumulative variation present in the database correctly 
represents the copy number variant content in our genome 
or whether this is an overestimation. For instance, some 
samples, most notably the HapMap samples, have been 
analysed multiple times, sometimes with strikingly differ-
ent outcomes in copy number variant content between 
different studies. </p>

<p>Whatever the exact percentage is, it has been demon-
strated that copy number variants are a primary source 
of human genetic variation [9]. For a comparison, the 
1,000 Genomes Project identified about 36.8 million 
single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs), covering 
only 1.3% of the genome [10]. Moreover, per genera-
tion locus-specific de novo mutation rates are 100 to 
1,000 times higher for copy number variants than for 
SNPs, which further emphasizes the role of copy 
number variants in the evolution and variation of the 
human genome [10-12]. </p>

<p>Copy number variants in disease </p>

<p>In our hands, specific causative copy number variants were 
found in about 10-20% of patients with intellectual 
disability in routine microarray screening, which is in line 
with published data [13]. Because of this high diagnostic 
yield, microarray analysis is gradually replacing karyotyp-
ing as the routine diagnostic test for genetic abnormalities 
in many clinical laboratories. </p>

<p>Very local chromosomal rearrangements 
When specific copy number variants cause consistent 
clinical manifestations across multiple patients, a micro-
deletion or microduplication syndrome can be defined. 
These syndromes can be divided into two groups: recurrent 
and non-recurrent microdeletion or microduplication 
syndromes, which differ in the clustering of the copy </p>

<p>number variant breakpoints. So far, over 50 clinically 
recognizable microdeletion and microduplication syn-
dromes associated with intellectual disability have been 
reported [13]. </p>

<p>Genomic disorders [14-16] are recurrent microdeletion 
and microduplication syndromes, characterized by copy 
number variants with an identical size and clustered 
breakpoints, explained by the presence of low copy 
repeats flanking the copy number variants. The local 
chromosomal architecture makes these regions prone to 
non-allelic homologous recombination (NAHR) [17], 
resulting in the deletion or duplication of the sequences 
in between the low copy repeats. The 17q21.31 micro-
deletion syndrome was one of the first defined genomic 
disorders identified through reverse phenotypics. It is 
characterized by mild to severe intellectual disability, 
hypotonia, friendly behaviour and specific facial 
dysmorphisms, as well as epilepsy, cardiac defects and 
urologic anomalies [18-20]. The deletion that causes this 
phenotype spans 900 kb and contains six genes. </p>

<p>Non-recurrent microdeletion and microduplication syn-
dromes are characterized by copy number variants in the 
same chromosomal region with non-identical break-
points. The associated copy number variants arise by 
means of different recombination-repair mechanisms, 
such as non homologous end joining (NHEJ), fork stalling 
and template switching (FoSTeS) and break induced 
replication (BIR), all based on the occurrence of micro-
homology at the breakpoints [17,21]. Non-recurrent 
disorders are frequently located in chromosomal regions 
that contain repetitive sequences. Examples include the 
Miller-Dieker syndrome, characterized by type I lissence-
phaly, severe psychomotor delay, hypotonia, epilepsy, 
microcephaly, feeding problems and typical facial fea-
tures. The causal deletions vary in size up to 2.5 Mb, but all 
share a 400 kb region containing nine genes at 17p13.3 
[22,23]. </p>

<p>Very local chromosomal rearrangements lead to the 
genetic dissection of microdeletion and microduplication 
syndromes and gene identification 
The specific phenotypes associated with microdeletion or 
microduplication syndromes are commonly attributed to 
an alteration in expression of dosage-sensitive genes in the 
copy number variant region. However, for many micro-
deletion and microduplication syndromes, there is much 
debate on the exact contribution of specific genes to the 
clinical manifestation of the patient. The increased resolu-
tion of current array platforms has enabled the identifica-
tion of atypical copy number variants affecting only part 
of the genomic region associated with the phenotype. By 
careful study of the clinical manifestations of patients </p>



<p>(page number not for citation purposes) </p>

<p>F1000 Biology Reports 2012, 4:22 
http://f1000.com/reports/b/4/22 </p>

<p>with small copy number variants, the role of individual 
genes in the disease has been elucidated in some cases 
(illustrated in figure 1 A-C). </p>

<p>For instance, two patients presenting with the typical 
symptoms of the 17q21.31 microdeletion syndrome 
were identified with a much smaller deletion comprising 
only two out of the six genes typically deleted [24]. 
Mutation analysis of these two candidate genes, MAPT 
and KANSL1, was performed in patients with the clinical 
characteristics of this disorder but without the typical 
deletion. Point mutations in the chromatin modifier 
gene KANSL1 were found in these patients, and it was 
concluded that the clinical characteristics of this genomic 
disorder can be caused by defects in this single gene 
[24,25]. Similarly, a long search to determine which of 
the genes deleted in the Prader-Willi syndrome are key 
contributors to the phenotype is nearly finished follow-
ing the identification of a patient with a small copy 
number variant inside the Prader-Willi syndrome cano-
nical region [26]. The child manifested most of the major 
symptoms of Prader-Willi syndrome and harboured an 
interstitial paternal deletion encompassing only the 
SNORD116 C/D box small nucleolar RNA (snoRNA) 
cluster. </p>

<p>In other cases, specific small copy number variants in the 
critical genomic region of microdeletion or microduplica-
tion syndromes can rule out the involvement of suspected 
candidate genes. We recently identified a pure hemizygous 
deletion of the CLIP2 gene, located within the Williams-
Beuren syndrome canonical region [27]. CLIP2, along with 
GTF2I and GTF2IRD1, were known as the key candidate 
genes for the characteristic cognitive and facial abnorm-
alities associated with the Williams-Beuren syndrome. We 
could not demonstrate any abnormalities in two healthy 
siblings carrying the CLIP2 deletion and, thus, concluded </p>

<p>that haploinsufficiency of this gene alone is not sufficient 
to cause any of the cognitive or facial features of this 
syndrome. </p>

<p>In many non-recurrent microdeletion and microduplica-
tion syndromes, careful correlation of local chromoso-
mal rearrangements to the clinical characteristics of the 
carriers has led to the identification of the disease gene 
within the candidate region. Talkowski et al. [28] recently 
pinpointed the MBD5 gene as the single causal locus for 
the intellectual disability, epilepsy and autism spectrum 
disorder (ASD) associated with the 2q23.1 microdele-
tion syndrome. This correlation was deduced by compar-
ing the molecular and phenotypic data of 65 patients for 
which MBD5 was the only affected gene in common. </p>

<p>Causative genes for several other genomic disorders have 
also been identified using the same approach, including 
MEF2C in the 5q14.3 microdeletion syndrome [29], SATB2 
in the 2q33.1 microdeletion syndrome [30], HDAC4 in 
the brachydactyly mental retardation syndrome [31], 
SHANK3 in the Phelan-McDermid syndrome/22q13 
deletion syndrome [32], and CREBBP in the Rubinstein-
Taybi syndrome [33]. Although these examples illustrate 
the importance of very local rearrangements in the study 
of genomic disorders, it should be noted that not each 
contiguous gene syndrome is due to deficits in only a 
single gene. </p>

<p>Very small local rearrangements can also pinpoint a 
disease gene outside regions of microdeletion or micro-
duplication syndromes. MYCN was identified as causative 
for the Feingold syndrome following the identification of 
copy number variants encompassing this gene in patients 
with the clinical characteristics of this syndrome [34]. In a 
similar way, the FOXF1 gene was identified as causative for 
alveolar capillary dysplasia [35]. Other examples include </p>

<p>Figure 1. The added value of a very small copy number variation in genetic discovery </p>

<p>LCR 
LCR </p>

<p>(A) Genomic disorder 
(B) Non-recurrent microdeleƟon or 
microduplicaƟon syndrome </p>

<p>(C) Monogenic disease </p>

<p>Schematic representation of the added value of a very small copy number variant (red) in the genetic dissection of recurrent and non-recurrent microdeletion 
and microduplication syndromes (A and B) in relation to previously reported copy number variants (blue), and for causative gene identification in monogenic 
diseases (C). </p>



<p>(page number not for citation purposes) </p>

<p>F1000 Biology Reports 2012, 4:22 
http://f1000.com/reports/b/4/22 </p>

<p>two studies flagging NRXN3 and CMIP as putative autism 
genes following the identification of rare microdeletions, 
including these genes in autistic patients [36,37]. </p>

<p>More causative gene identifications lie ahead of us 
With the introduction of higher resolution arrays in 
routine diagnostics, we can expect an increasing number 
of very local chromosomal rearrangements to be identi-
fied. These small copy number variants detected in 
patients are submitted to databases, such as DECIPHER, 
ECARUCA and ISCA, along with phenotypic information 
[38-44]. A closer look at the data submitted, for instance to 
DECIPHER, suggests that many more causative gene identi-
fications may lie ahead of us. In this database, currently 
containing publicly available data from 6,000 patients, 
about 80 de novo single gene aberrations are present, 
consisting of 55 deletions and 25 duplications. Using the 
<rs type="software">DAVID</rs> annotation tools [45], we found that 55% of these 
genes are expressed in the brain and 15% are involved in 
the functioning of the glutamate or N-methyl-D-aspartate 
(NMDA)-receptors (unpublished observations). Further-
more, genes involved in neurogenesis, differentiation and 
coding for developmental proteins are enriched in this set. 
These data clearly suggest a role for at least some of these 
small copy number variants in neurological disease. </p>

<p>As some microdeletion or microduplication syndromes 
cannot be attributed to a single gene defect, careful study of 
the clinical presentation in relation to the affected gene(s) is 
necessary to decide whether the observed abnormality is 
causative for (part of ) the phenotype of the patient [46]. 
Genotypic and phenotypic information stored in copy 
number variant databases are critical for the accurate 
interpretation of these results. However, the information in 
these databases should be used with caution as misanno-
tated entries appear to be present. For example, two 
individuals included in the DGV carry a deletion of the ELN 
gene, causing supravalvar aortic stenosis. In addition, single 
gene deletions of the KANSL1 gene, causal for the 17q21.31 
microdeletion syndrome, are present in this database. There 
are two possible explanations for this observation. First, 
these regions might be false positive results, as each 
microarray technology inherently yields a low amount of 
false positive results. Second, the variants may be bona fide 
but are not associated with the expected clinical phenotype 
in these individuals, either due to genetic background or to 
incomplete penetrance. In either case, the user should be 
aware of the associated phenotypes before filtering copy 
number variants against these databases. </p>

<p>Future directions </p>

<p>As the resolution of the arrays in routine diagnostics 
continues to increase, it can be expected that more very 
local rearrangements will be found. The interpretation of </p>

<p>the clinical consequences of such copy number variants 
will remain challenging. It is, therefore, important to 
integrate clinical information, functional annotation of 
affected genes, and published cases in interpretational 
workflows. This report illustrates how small copy 
number variants that affect a single gene only led to the 
identification of disease genes inside or outside regions 
of known microdeletion or microduplication syndromes. 
Thanks to the introduction of high-resolution microarray 
analysis in routine diagnostics in many laboratories, 
many more small copy number variants will be detected, 
and we expect that many more exciting discoveries lie 
ahead of us. </p>

<p>Abbreviations </p>

<p>ASD, autism spectrum disorder; BIR, break induced 
replication; DGV, Database of Genomic Variants; FISH, 
fluorescence in situ hybridization; FoSTeS, fork stalling and 
template switching; MLPA, multiplex ligation-dependent 
probe amplification; NAHR, non-allelic homologous 
recombination; NHEJ, non homologous end joining; 
NMDA, N-Methyl-D-aspartate; snoRNA, small nucleolar 
RNA; SNP, single nucleotide polymorphism. </p>

<p>Competing interests </p>

<p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>Our experimental work is supported by the Belgian 
National Fund for Scientific Research, Flanders (FWO), 
the University of Antwerp Industrial Research Fund 
(IOF) and the University of Antwerp Special Research 
Fund (BOF). </p>





<p>(page number not for citation purposes) </p>

<p>F1000 Biology Reports 2012, 4:22 
http://f1000.com/reports/b/4/22 </p>





<p>(page number not for citation purposes) </p>

<p>F1000 Biology Reports 2012, 4:22 
http://f1000.com/reports/b/4/22 </p>





<p>(page number not for citation purposes) </p>

<p>F1000 Biology Reports 2012, 4:22 
http://f1000.com/reports/b/4/22 </p>

</text></tei>