<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3507266" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:42+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Background: Cerebral hypoperfusion accompanies heart failure (HF) and is associated with 
reduced cognitive performance. Obesity is prevalent in persons with HF and is also a likely con-
tributor to cognitive function, as it has been independently linked to cognitive impairment in 
healthy individuals. The current study examined the association between obesity and cogni-
tive performance among older adults with HF and whether obesity interacts with cerebral hy-
poperfusion to exacerbate cognitive impairment. Methods: Patients with HF (n = 99, 67.46 8 
11.36 years of age) completed neuropsychological testing and impedance cardiography. Cere-
bral blood flow velocity (CBF-V) measured by transcranial Doppler sonography quantified ce-
rebral perfusion and body mass index (BMI) operationalized obesity. Results: A hierarchical 
regression analysis showed that lower CBF-V was associated with reduced performance on 
tests of attention/executive function and memory. Elevated BMI was independently associated 
with reduced attention/executive function and language test performance. Notably, a signifi-
cant interaction between CBF-V and BMI indicated that a combination of hypoperfusion and </p>

<p>high BMI has an especially adverse influence on attention/executive function in HF patients. 
Conclusions: The current findings suggest that cerebral hypoperfusion and obesity interact to 
impair cognitive performance in persons with HF. These results may have important clinical 
implications, as HF patients who are at high risk for cerebral hypoperfusion may benefit from 
weight reduction. </p>

<p>Nearly 6 million Americans currently have heart failure (HF) and an additional 660,000 
new cases of HF are diagnosed each year [1] . HF is also the most common reason for recur-
rent hospitalizations [2] and carries elevated risk of morality [3] , reduced functional inde-
pendence [4] , and poor quality of life [5] . HF also increases risk for cognitive impairment, 
Alzheimer's disease (AD), vascular dementia, and neuropathological insult [6-8] . Milder 
deficits in attention, executive function, memory, and language are also common and can be 
found in up to 75% of HF patients [9, 10] . Although the mechanisms for cognitive impair-
ment in HF are unclear, it is plausible that it stems from cerebral dysfunction predicated on 
deterioration of vascular health that causes cerebral hypoperfusion and subsequent ischemia 
[11] . Extant evidence also indicates that among HF patients, common vascular risk factors, 
such as type 2 diabetes, hypertension, depression, and obesity [12-14] , may exacerbate cogni-
tive dysfunction. 
Indeed, obesity is one of the more common vascular risk factor for HF [14] and is found 
in 1 40% of HF patients [15] . Obesity in HF and cardiovascular disease populations is associ-
ated with numerous adverse outcomes, including increased mortality risk [16] , reduced qual-
ity of life, poor emotional and physical well-being, and increased depressive symptomatol-
ogy [17] . Moreover, obesity is also associated with increased risk of AD [18] as well as cogni-
tive dysfunction and neuroimaging abnormalities independent of neurological and 
cardiovascular disease [19-21] . 
These findings suggest that obesity may exacerbate neuropathology and cognitive dys-
function in HF patients through additive independent influence or even through greater 
reductions in cerebral perfusion [22] . Thus, the purpose of the current study was to examine 
the independent effects of body mass index (BMI) on cognitive function among older adults 
with HF and to determine whether BMI interacts with cerebral perfusion to produce in-
creased cognitive deficits in this population. We hypothesized that reductions in cerebral 
blood flow (CBF) would be associated with poorer cognitive function and such deficits would 
be exacerbated by elevated BMI. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Participants 
The sample consisted of 99 consecutive participants with HF who were enrolled in an 
ongoing study examining neurocognitive function among older adults with HF. Participants 
were recruited from primary cardiology practices at Summa Health System in Akron, Ohio, 
and reflect the HF population receiving treatment at that facility. The inclusion criteria were 
age of 50-85 years, English as a primary language, and a diagnosis of New York Heart As-
sociation (NYHA) class II or III at the time of enrollment. NYHA was confirmed by a med-
ical record review. Potential participants were excluded for history of significant neurological 
disorder (e.g. dementia, stroke, multiple sclerosis, etc.), head injury with 1 10 min loss of con-</p>



<p>Cerebrovasc Dis Extra 2012;2:88-98 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000343222 
Published online: October 25, 2012 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Alosco et al.: Obesity Interacts with Cerebral Hypoperfusion to Exacerbate Cognitive 
Impairment in Older Adults with Heart Failure </p>

<p>www.karger.com/cee </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>

<p>sciousness, severe psychiatric disorder (e.g. schizophrenia, bipolar disorder), past or current 
substance abuse/dependence, and renal failure. Participants averaged 67.46 8 11.36 SD years 
of age, were 26.3% female, and 88.9% Caucasian. See table 1 for demographic and medical 
information. </p>

<p>Measures 
Neuropsychological Measures 
A brief battery of neuropsychological tests was administered to assess cognitive function 
across multiple domains. All neuropsychological tests used in the current study exhibit 
strong psychometric properties, including excellent reliability and validity. The domains and 
neuropsychological tests administered are as follows: 
• Global cognitive function: Modified Mini Mental State Examination [23] 
• Attention/executive function: Trail Making Test B [24] , Adaptive Rate Continuous 
Performance Test Hit Rate [25] , Letter Number Sequencing [26] , Stroop Color Word 
Interference Effect [27] , Frontal Assessment Battery [28] 
• Memory: the California Verbal Learning Test-II short delay free recall, long delay free 
recall, and total hits [29] 
• Language: Boston Naming Test [30] and Animal Fluency [31] </p>

<p>Cerebral Blood Flow 
We used transcranial Doppler ultrasonography under an expanded Stroke Prevention 
Trial in Sickle Cell Anemia (STOP) protocol [32] to assess CBF velocity (CBF-V) in the major 
brain arteries. The insonated arteries included the middle cerebral artery (MCA), the ante-
rior cerebral artery (ACA), posterior cerebellar artery (PCA), intracranial vertebral arteries, 
basilar artery, terminal internal carotid artery, intracranial internal carotid artery, and oph-
thalmic artery. For each artery, the measurements provide several indices including mean 
flow velocity. As the index of global cerebral perfusion, we used the mean CBF-V in the ACA, 
MCA, and PCA. The CBF-V measures in each artery (i.e. ACA, MCA, and PCA) have high 
test-retest reliability (i.e. r = 0.90 to r = 0.95) [33] . </p>

<p>Demographic characteristics 
Patients, n 
99 
Age, years 
67.46811.37 
Female, % 
26.3 
Caucasian, % 
88.9 
Education, years 
13.4482.84 
Clinical characteristics 
BMI 
29.9587.23 
Cardiac index 
2.7481.03 
Systolic BP, mm Hg 
115.88816.79 
Diastolic BP, mm Hg 
65.0589.73 
Diabetes, % 
32.3 
Myocardial infarction, % 
59.6 
Depression, % 
18.2 
Cerebral perfusion 
MCA, cm/s 
40.79811.33 
ACA, cm/s 
35.10810.86 
PCA, cm/s 
27.6088.12 
Global CBF-V, cm/s 
103.49825.73 </p>

<p>V alues are means 8 SD unless otherwise indicated. </p>

<p>Table 1. D emographic and 
clinical characteristics of 99 
older adults with HF </p>



<p>Cerebrovasc Dis Extra 2012;2:88-98 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000343222 
Published online: October 25, 2012 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Alosco et al.: Obesity Interacts with Cerebral Hypoperfusion to Exacerbate Cognitive 
Impairment in Older Adults with Heart Failure </p>

<p>www.karger.com/cee </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>

<p>HF Severity 
Cardiac output from a seated resting baseline estimated preservation of cardiac func-
tion. Impedance cardiography signals were recorded via a Hutcheson Impedance Cardio-
graph (Model HIC-3000, Bio-Impedance Technology, Chapel Hill, N.C., USA) using a tet-
rapolar band-electrode configuration. The electrocardiogram (ECG) was recorded from the 
Hutcheson Impedance Cardiograph using disposable ECG electrodes. The basal thoracic 
impedance (Zo), the first derivative of the pulsatile impedance (dZ/dt) and the ECG wave-
forms were processed using specialized ensemble-averaging software (<rs id="software-0" type="software">COP</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">BIT Inc</rs>., Chapel 
Hill, N.C., USA), which was used to derive stroke volume using the Kubicek equation. Fol-
lowing instrumentation, Impedance cardiographic signals were recorded for seven 40-sec-
ond periods during a 10-min resting baseline. Finally, all cardiac output measurements were 
divided by body surface area, yielding cardiac index ( table 1 ). 
Blood pressure (BP) was measured 7 times during the 10-min resting baseline using an 
automated oscillometric BP device (Accutor Plus Oscillometric BP Monitor, Datascope Corp., 
Mahwah, N.H., USA) providing systolic, diastolic, and mean arterial pressures. Initiating the 
BP reading triggered a concurrent 40-second impedance cardiography measure. The mean 
systolic and diastolic BP across the 7 trials served as the indices of systolic and diastolic BP. </p>

<p>Demographic and Medical History 
Demographic and medical characteristics were collected through a review of partici-
pants' medical charts and self-report. The summary of these characteristics is in table 1 . </p>

<p>Procedures 
The local Institutional Review Board approved the study procedures and all participants 
provided written informed consent prior to study enrollment. In addition to medical record 
review, participants completed demographic and medical history self-report measures. 
Height and weight were measured and used to calculate BMI. Individuals then completed 
impedance cardiography conducted by a trained research assistant to ascertain cardiac in-
dices. Finally, a brief neuropsychological test battery assessed attention/executive function, 
memory, and language. </p>

<p>Statistical Analyses 
To facilitate clinical interpretation and minimize discrepancy within scales, raw scores 
of the neuropsychological measures were transformed to T-scores (a distribution with a 
mean of 50 and a standard deviation of 10) using normative data correcting for age. Memo-
ry scores were corrected for gender. Composite scores were computed for attention/executive 
function, memory, and language that consisted of the mean of the T-scores of neuropsycho-
logical measures within each cognitive domain. 
Three separate multiple linear hierarchical regression models examined the interactive ef-
fect of BMI and CBF-V on each cognitive domain. All continuous predictors were transformed 
to Z-scores, gender was coded as 1 for males and 0 for females, and medical history was coded 
as 1 for a positive and 0 for a negative history. For all analyses, demographic and medical vari-
ables including age, gender, education, cardiac index, systolic and diastolic BP, and diagnostic 
history of diabetes, myocardial infarction, and depression were entered into the first block of 
the model. Medical history covariates were included in the model to account for the variance 
of common cardiovascular disease factors associated with obesity that influence cognitive 
function. BMI entered into the second block of the model and global CBF-V entered in the third 
block. Lastly, an interaction term consisting of the cross product of BMI and global CBF-V en-
tered in the final block. Partial correlation analysis adjusting for medical and demographic 
characteristics was also conducted to clarify the association between BMI and global CBF-V. </p>



<p>Cerebrovasc Dis Extra 2012;2:88-98 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000343222 
Published online: October 25, 2012 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Alosco et al.: Obesity Interacts with Cerebral Hypoperfusion to Exacerbate Cognitive 
Impairment in Older Adults with Heart Failure </p>

<p>www.karger.com/cee </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Cognitive Performance and Cerebral Perfusion 
The Modified Mini Mental State Examination score was used to assess global cognitive 
status within the sample. Overall, the sample mean was 93.69 8 4.59 SD, with 18.2% of the 
sample scoring ! 90, 40.4% between 90 and 95, and 41.4% 1 95 ( table 2 ). 
Lower global CBF-V was significantly associated with poorer attention/executive func-
tion ( ␤ = 0.28, p = 0.02) and memory ( ␤ = 0.26, p = 0.04), but not with language functioning 
(p = 0.85). See table 3 for a summary of hierarchical regression analyses for blocks 1-3. </p>

<p>Body Mass Index 
The HF patients had a mean BMI of 29.95 8 7.23 SD. According to common categoriza-
tion, 26.3% of the participants fell within the normal range (BMI 18.5-24.9), 36.4% were 
overweight (BMI 25-29.9), and 37.4% of the sample exhibited a BMI consistent with obesity 
(BMI 6 30). The BMI groups did not differ in age ( F (2,98) = 0.38, p = 0.69), gender composi-
tion ( 2 (2, n = 99) = 5.24, p = 0.07), education ( F (2,98) = 1.07, p = 0.35), systolic ( F (2,98) = 
0.51, p = 0.60) and diastolic ( F (2,98) = 0.07, p = 0.93) BP, and frequency of myocardial infarc-
tions ( 2 (2, n = 99) = 0.44, p = 0.80), diabetes ( 2 (2, n = 99) = 5.04, p = 0.08) or depression 
( 2 (2, n = 99) = 0.57, p = 0.75). However, across groups, greater BMI was associated with 
lower cardiac index ( F (2,98) = 12.99, p ! 0.01). Of note, partial correlation adjusting for age, 
gender, education, systolic and diastolic BP, and history of diabetes, myocardial infarction, 
and depression showed that higher BMI was associated with lower mean velocity in the MCA 
( r (89) = -0.24, p = 0.04). </p>

<p>BMI Is Independently Associated with Cognitive Function 
Elevated BMI was associated with reduced attention/executive ( ␤ = -0.28, p = 0.02) and 
language ( ␤ = -0.28, p = 0.02) scores after controlling for medical and demographic charac-</p>

<p>Table 2. D escriptive statistics of cognitive test performance (n = 99) </p>

<p>Raw test performance 
T-score </p>

<p>Global cognitive function 
3MS 
93.6984.59 
-
Attention/executive function 
ARCPT 
0.9080.06 
53.43814.53 
LNS 
9.2182.69 
52.2489.17 
TMTB, s 
116.66867.27 
46.37815.41 
Stroop interference effect 
1.4886.93 
51.4286.91 
Frontal Assessment Battery 
16.1182.16 
44.83821.13 
Memory 
CVLT SDFR 
7.4283.52 
47.47810.48 
CVLT LDFR 
7.9983.69 
47.58810.77 
CVLT recognition 
13.4682.40 
45.00812.12 
Language 
Boston Naming Test 
55.1783.93 
52.9289.40 
Animal Fluency 
19.7585.01 
55.38811.37 </p>

<p>V alues are means 8 SD. 3MS = Modified Mini Mental State Examination; ARCPT = Adaptive Rate 
Continuous Performance Test hit rate; LNS = Letter Number Sequencing; TMTB = Trail Making Test B; 
CVLT = California Verbal Learning Test; SDFR = short delay free recall; LDFR = long delay free recall. </p>



<p>Cerebrovasc Dis Extra 2012;2:88-98 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000343222 
Published online: October 25, 2012 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Alosco et al.: Obesity Interacts with Cerebral Hypoperfusion to Exacerbate Cognitive 
Impairment in Older Adults with Heart Failure </p>

<p>www.karger.com/cee </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>

<p>teristics. There was no significant association between BMI and memory performance ( ␤ = 
-0.13, p = 0.30). Partial correlations adjusting for age, gender, education, cardiac index, sys-
tolic and diastolic BP, and diagnostic history of diabetes, myocardial infarction, and depres-
sion showed that higher BMI was associated with poorer performance on the Stroop Color 
Word Interference ( r (88) = -0.25, p = 0.02), Trail Making Test B ( r (88) = -0.28, p = 0.01), the 
Adaptive Rate Continuous Performance Test Hit Rate ( r (88) = -0.21, p = 0.047), and Animal 
Fluency ( r (88) = -0.23, p = 0.03). </p>

<p>The Interactive Effects of Elevated BMI and Cerebral Hypoperfusion on Cognitive 
Function 
The interaction between BMI and global CBF-V ( ␤ = 0.22, ⌬ R 2 = 0.04, p = 0.04) demon-
strated predictive validity of attention/executive function after taking into account medical 
and demographic factors, BMI, and global CBF-V. The combined effect of elevated BMI and 
cerebral hypoperfusion exacerbated impairments in this domain. Figure 1 illustrates the in-
teraction between BMI and global CBF-V. This pattern did not emerge for memory (p = 0.37) 
or language (p = 0.98). </p>

<p>Table 3. A summary of hierarchical regressions examining predictors of cognitive function among older 
adults with HF (n = 99): blocks 1-3 </p>

<p>Variable 
Attention/executive 
function, b (SE b) </p>

<p>Memory 
b (SE b) </p>

<p>Language 
b (SE b) </p>

<p>Block 1 
Age 
-2.05 (1.15) 
-1.63 (1.13) 
-0.15 (0.91) 
Gender 
-3.91 (2.53) 
-3.21 (2.48) 
-0.83 (2.01) 
Education 
2.94 (1.08)** 
2.34 (1.06)* 
2.98 (0.85)** 
Cardiac index 
0.55 (1.01) 
-1.00 (0.99) 
0.05 (0.08) 
Systolic BP 
0.02 (0.10) 
0.03 (0.10) 
0.06 (0.15) 
Diastolic BP 
-0.02 (0.19) 
0.00 (0.18) 
-0.20 (0.15) 
Diabetes 
-1.97 (2.30) 
1.70 (2.25) 
-0.32 (1.82) 
MI 
0.89 (2.18) 
-0.07 (2.13) 
-2.22 (1.72) 
Depression 
-5.37 (2.91) 
-0.39 (2.86) 
-3.99 (2.31) 
R 2 
0.16 
0.10 
0.22 
F 
1.68 
1.04 
2.54 
P 
0.11 
0.42 
0.01 
Block 2 
BMI 
-2.76 (1.18)* 
-1.24 (1.19) 
-2.24 (0.94)* 
R 2 
0.21 
0.11 
0.27 
F for ⌬R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>5.43 
1.09 
5.70 
P 
0.02 
0.30 
0.02 
Block 3 
CBF-V 
2.82* 
2.55 (1.20)* 
-0.18 (0.97) 
R 2 
0.26 
0.16 
0.27 
F for ⌬R 2 
5.72 
4.55 
0.04 
P 
0.02 
0.04 
0.85 </p>

<p>b = Unstandardized regression coefficients; SE = standard error; MI = myocardial infarction. 
* p &lt; 0.05; ** p &lt; 0.01. </p>



<p>Cerebrovasc Dis Extra 2012;2:88-98 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000343222 
Published online: October 25, 2012 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Alosco et al.: Obesity Interacts with Cerebral Hypoperfusion to Exacerbate Cognitive 
Impairment in Older Adults with Heart Failure </p>

<p>www.karger.com/cee </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Consistent with the extant literature, we found that obesity was prevalent in the current 
sample of HF patients. Past work has linked cerebral hypoperfusion and obesity with adverse 
psychosocial outcomes in persons with HF [17] . The current study extends these findings by 
demonstrating that in addition to separate effects of reduced CBF and elevated BMI, their 
combination is associated with additional cognitive deficits in HF. 
We observed that elevated BMI and hypoperfusion are associated with reduced cogni-
tive performance independent of comorbid medical conditions. This is consistent with past 
work linking high BMI with poor neurocognitive outcomes [19-21] . The exact mechanisms 
by which a combination of obesity and hypoperfusion exacerbates cognitive impairment in 
HF remain unclear. Possible explanations include increased risk for vascular comorbidities 
such as diabetes and hypertension [34, 35] , or related vascular risk factors such as endothe-
lial dysfunction, poor cardiovascular fitness, and systemic inflammation [36-38] , which are 
common in obese persons. Recent research also raises the possibility that circulating bio-
markers, including ␤ -amyloid and brain-derived neurotrophic factor [39, 40] , might also 
influence neurocognitive outcomes in obese persons. These biomarkers are linked to cogni-
tive performance in patient and healthy samples [41-43] . Similarly, genetic factors may also 
be involved, as recent studies have linked the Fat Mass and Obesity gene (FTO) with in-
creased risk of AD [44] . Future work is needed to elucidate the specific mechanisms by which 
obesity affects brain functioning above and beyond HF-related pathology. 
The pathophysiological effect of reduced CBF has been theorized to underlie cognitive 
impairment in HF patients [11] . Interestingly, obesity is also independently associated with 
reduced cerebral perfusion and metabolic activity [22] . It is unclear if vascular abnormali-
ties, including reduced small vessel density, inflammation, arterial stiffness, and/or im-
paired vasodilation, cause hypoperfusion or reflect independent common causes of cogni-
tive impairment in such persons [45, 46] . For instance, cerebral hypoperfusion may help to </p>

<p>Fig. 1. The interactive effect of 
cerebral hypoperfusion and ele-
vated BMI on attention/execu-
tive function among older adults 
with HF. Higher scores on the x-
axis are reflective of elevated 
BMI and higher scores on the y-
axis represent better test perfor-
mance. </p>



<p>Cerebrovasc Dis Extra 2012;2:88-98 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000343222 
Published online: October 25, 2012 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Alosco et al.: Obesity Interacts with Cerebral Hypoperfusion to Exacerbate Cognitive 
Impairment in Older Adults with Heart Failure </p>

<p>www.karger.com/cee </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>

<p>explain the structural and functional neuroimaging abnormalities found in obese individ-
uals [19] . As reduced cerebral perfusion has also been linked with poorer neurocognitive 
outcomes among persons with mild cognitive impairment [47] , future research should in-
vestigate the neurological outcomes in HF patients with and without elevated BMI. In ad-
dition to these direct effects, studies should also examine the role of psychosocial risk fac-
tors on these outcomes. For example, obese individuals are often sedentary and physical 
activity is known to provide key benefits among HF patients, including improvements in 
cerebral hemodynamics [48] . 
The observed association between hypoperfusion and reduced scores on tests of atten-
tion/executive function and memory conforms to the reported sensitivity of these functions 
to vascular risk and vascular disease [10, 11] . In contrast, BMI was associated with perfor-
mance on attention/executive function and a higher-order language measure but not on 
memory tasks. Notably, only attention/executive function evidenced a significant CBF-BMI 
interaction effect. Thus, attention/executive function appears to be vulnerable to both risk 
factors and to their combined influence. Such sensitivity may reflect the fact that prefrontal 
brain regions that mediate executive functions are particularly susceptible to adverse effects 
of ischemia and subsequent structural damage [49] . Similarly, both obesity and HF are as-
sociated with impairments on tests of attention and executive function [11, 20, 21] . In con-
trast, the literature regarding the effects of obesity on memory is inconsistent [21, 50] . Pro-
spective studies are needed to clarify the effects of BMI on memory performance among HF 
patients, particularly since HF patients are frequently impaired in this domain [10] . 
The generalizability of the current findings is limited in several ways. First, the cross-
sectional design does not inform about the contribution of BMI or cerebral perfusion to cog-
nitive outcomes over time. Similarly, although BMI is a practical and commonly used index 
of obesity, it is a coarse measure. Future studies employing more detailed assessments such 
as dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA) may be beneficial through its ability to distin-
guish between fat and lean mass. More precise and detailed measures of cerebral perfusion 
(e.g. arterial spin labeling, positron emission tomography) may also provide details of re-
gional variations in CBF that might not be detected using transcranial Doppler. Finally, fu-
ture studies should also explore the influence of clinical comorbidities common to obese and 
HF patients (i.e. sleep apnea) on cognitive function, as such factors may also contribute to 
cerebral hypoperfusion and subsequent cognitive impairment in this population. 
In summary, this study demonstrates that cerebral hypoperfusion and obesity are as-
sociated with reduced attention/executive function among older adults with HF and that 
cognitive deficits are exacerbated by a combination of these factors. These findings have 
important clinical implications, as weight loss may alleviate cognitive dysfunction and re-
move at least one factor that exacerbates the adverse effects of hypoperfusion that accom-
panies HF. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Support for this work included National Institutes of Health grants DK075119 and 
HLO89311. N.R. is also supported by National Institutes of Health grant R37 AG011230. </p>

<p>Disclosure Statement </p>

<p>There are no conflicts of interest. </p>



<p>Cerebrovasc Dis Extra 2012;2:88-98 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000343222 
Published online: October 25, 2012 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Alosco et al.: Obesity Interacts with Cerebral Hypoperfusion to Exacerbate Cognitive 
Impairment in Older Adults with Heart Failure </p>

<p>www.karger.com/cee </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>





<p>Cerebrovasc Dis Extra 2012;2:88-98 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000343222 
Published online: October 25, 2012 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Alosco et al.: Obesity Interacts with Cerebral Hypoperfusion to Exacerbate Cognitive 
Impairment in Older Adults with Heart Failure </p>

<p>www.karger.com/cee </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>





<p>Cerebrovasc Dis Extra 2012;2:88-98 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000343222 
Published online: October 25, 2012 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Alosco et al.: Obesity Interacts with Cerebral Hypoperfusion to Exacerbate Cognitive 
Impairment in Older Adults with Heart Failure </p>

<p>www.karger.com/cee </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>



</text></tei>