<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3627965" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract Hypotrachyna (Vainio) Hale is a somewhat rare lichen genus found on the Korean Peninsula. Since it was first recorded 
more than two decades ago, no detailed taxonomic or revisionary study of the genus has been conducted. Thus, the present 
study was conducted to carry out a detailed taxonomic and revisionary study of Hypotrachyna in South Korea. This study was 
based on specimens deposited in the Korean Lichen Research Institute (KoLRI). Detailed taxonomic studies and a literature review 
confirmed the presence of seven species of Hypotrachyna from South Korea, including one new record, Hypotrachyna nodakensis 
(Asahina) Hale. Descriptions of each species with their morphological, anatomical and chemical characters together with a key to 
all known Hypotrachyna species are presented. </p>



<p>performed in solvent systems A (toluene:dioxin:acetic acid = 
180:45:5) and C (toluene:acetic acid = 85:15) [13]. All 
examined locations of specimens were mapped using the 
open source GIS software <rs id="software-0" type="software">Quantum GIS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">1.7.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">QGIS</rs>). Voucher 
specimens have been deposited in the herbarium of the 
Lichen and Allied Bio-resource Center at the KoLRI, Sunchon 
National University, South Korea. In the identification key, 
the newly reported species are indicated in bold. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Key to the all known species of Hypotrachyna in 
South Korea </p>

<p>1. Thallus isidiate or lobulate ·················································· 2 
1a. Thallus lacking isidia, sorediate or pustulate sorediate 
········································································································ 4 </p>

<p>2. Isidia absent, lobules present, medulla C−, barbatic acid 
present ··································································· H. physcioides 
2a. Isidiate thallus ······································································ 3 </p>

<p>3. Medulla C−, KC−, gyrophoric acid absent ······ H. ikomae 
3a. Medulla C± rose, KC+ rose or red, gyrophoric acid 
present ·································································· H. nodakensis </p>

<p>4. Soralia capitate, pustules absent, protocetraric acid present 
··········································································· H. pseudosinuosa 
4a. Soredia pustulate ································································· 5 </p>

<p>5. Upper cortex UV+ yellow, lichexanthone present 
················································································· H. osseoalba 
5a. Upper cortex UV-, lichexanthone absent ······················ 6 </p>

<p>6. Medulla C+ rose, KC+ rose or red, gyrophoric acid 
present ········································································ H. revoluta 
6a. Medulla C+ yellow or C−, KC+ orange, barbatic acid 
present ·········································································· H. exsecta </p>

<p>Species description. 
Hypotrachyna nodakensis (Asahina) Hale, Phytologia 28: 
341 (1974). 
Parmelia nodakensis Asahina 1959. 
Thallus foliose, loosely adnate to the substrate, 58 
cm across. Lobes subirregular, 1~5 mm wide; margins 
entire, eciliate apices subrotund. Upper surface pale 
yellowish grey, emaculate, smooth, without phyllidia and 
sorediate, sisidiate. Isidia simple to coralloid branched, 
somewhat brown tipped. Medulla white. Lower surface 
black with brown margin, sparsely rhizinate. Rhizines 
dichotomously branched, black. Apothecia and pycnidia 
not seen (Fig. 1). 
Chemistry: Cortex K+ (yellow), C−, KC−, P−; medulla 
K−, C+ (rose), KC+ (rose to red), P−. TLC: atranorin, 
chloroatranorin, gyrophoric acid, protolichesterinic acid 
(Fig. 2). </p>

<p>Remarks: H. nodakensis is new to South Korea and a 
somewhat rare species. It is characterized by the presence 
of simple to corraloid branched isidia and protolichesterinic 
and gyrophoric acids in the medulla. According to Chen et 
al. [14], H. nodakensis closely resembles H. infirma and H. 
ikomae due to the presence of isidia and fatty acids in the 
medulla. However, it differs from H. infirma by not having 
caperatic and norcaperatic acids in the medulla. H. ikomae 
has the same fatty acids in the medulla as H. nodakensis, 
but lacks gyrophoric acid. 
Specimens examined: Jeju Island, on bark (Cherry tree), 
33 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>27'6.94" N, 126 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>33'07.9" E, alt. 278 m, 19 Apr 2009, 
090041; Mt. Gaya, on bark, 35 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>47'54.8" N, 128 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>05'56.2" E, 
alt. 642 (675) m, 15 Apr 2004, 040193 (Fig. 3). 
Geographical distribution: This species has been reported 
from China [15] and Japan [16]. </p>

<p>Hypotrachyna osseoalba (Vain.) Y. S. Park &amp; Hale, Taxon 
38: 88 (1989). 
Parmelia osseoalba Vain., Ann. Bot. Soc. Zool. Bot. 
Fenn. Vanamo 1: 39 (1921). </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Hypotrachyna species. A, H. nodakensis (J. S. Hur, X. 
Y. Wang, J. A. Ryu, J. Y. Hur, 90041); B, H. osseoalba (J. S. 
Hur, 70056); C, H. revoluta (J. S. Hur, X. Y. Wang, J. A. Ryu, 
J. Y. Hur, 90338) (scale bars: A~C = 1 cm). </p>

<p>Lichen Genus Hypotrachyna in Korea 15 </p>

<p>Thallus foliose, adnate to loosely adnate, 3~8 cm across. 
Lobes crowded, sublinear, 1~3 mm wide; margins entire, 
eciliate, apices incised. Upper surface pale yellowish grey, 
emaculate, shiny, smooth, without isidia or phyllidia, 
sorediate. Soredia in coarse, laminal pustules or coralloid 
clusters. Medulla white. Lower surface black, densely 
rhizinate. Rhizines dichotomously branched, black. Apothecia 
and pycnidia not seen (Fig. 1). 
Chemistry: Cortex K−, UV+ (yellow), C−, KC−, P−; 
medulla K+ (reddish), C−, KC+ (red), P+ (orange). TLC: 
chloroatranrin, lichexanthone, lividic acid, physodic acid 
(Fig. 2). 
Remarks: This species is characterized by pustulate soredia 
and cortical lichexanthone (yellow under UV light). 
According to Elix [11], Hypotrachyna novella is very closely 
related to H. osseoalba, but is very rare and lacks vegetative 
propagules. 
Specimens examined: Mt. Baekseokbong, Gangwon-do, 
on rock, 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>28'7.39" N, 128 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>39'7.60" E, alt. 494 m, 16 May </p>

<p>2009, 090469; Mt. Bannon, Buk-myeon, Gangwon-do, on 
rock, 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>26'6.19" N, 128 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>45'49.0" E, alt. 1,064 m, 28 May 
2010, 100848; 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>26'6.37" N, 128 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>45'49.4" E, alt. 1,067 m, 28 
May 2010, 100838; Mt. Cheongwan, Jeollanam-do, on bark 
(Pinus sp.), 34 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>32'33.1" N, 126 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>55'46.7" E, alt. 300 m, 7 Oct 
2005, 050547; Mt. Joryeong, Chungcheongbuk-do, on bark 
(Pinus sp.), 36 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>49'00.2" N, 128 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>03'10.4" E, alt. 909 (965) m, 
27 Oct 2006, 061102, 061102-1; on rock, 36 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>49'00.9" N, 
128 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>02'53.7" E, alt. 784 (840) m, 27 Oct 2006, 061049; Mt. 
Kongduck, on rock, 36 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>45'00.3" N, 128 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>15'53.0" E, alt. 643 m, 
20 Jun 2007, 070080; Mt. Mangeun, Gyeongsangnam-do, 
on rock, 34 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>51'18.5" N, 127 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>51'49.6" E, alt. 618 m, 28 Apr 
2011, 110204; 34 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>51'25.3" N, 127 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>51'44.3" E, alt. 630 m, 28 Apr 
2011, 110198; Saryang Island, Gyeongsangnam-do, on rock, 
34 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>50'44.8" N, 128 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>12'13.9" E, alt. 266 m, 17 Mar 2007, 
070056; Mt. Talma, Jeollanam-do, on rock, 34 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>22'32.0" N, 
126 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>35'03.9" E, alt. 435 m, 26 Jul 2005, 050367; Mt. Weolchul, 
on bark (Pinus sp.), 34 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>45'22.3" N, 126 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>40'34.5" E, alt. 400 m, 
5 Apr 2003, 030120; Mt. Yang, Gyeongsangnam-do, on 
bark, 36 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>09'24.1" N, 127 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>36'22.2" E, alt. 580 (680) m, 3 Nov 
2006, 061204 (Fig. 3). 
Ecology and distribution: This species is commonly 
distributed in South Korea. According to Elix [11], this 
species occurs in cosmopolitan subtropical and temperate 
areas. </p>

<p>Hypotrachyna revoluta (Flörke) Hale, Smithson. Contrib. 
Bot. 25: 60 (1975). </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Thin layer chromatography profile of Hypotrachyna 
species in solvent system A. 1, H. nodakensis with 
chloroatranorin (a), atranorin (b), protolichesterinic acid (c), 
gyrophoric acid (d); 2, H. osseoalba with lichenoxanthone (e), 
lividic acid (f), physodic acid (g); 3, Control [Lethariella 
cladonioides (Nyl.) Krog] with norstictic acid (h); 4, H. 
revoluta with unknown 1 (i) and gyrophoric acid (j). </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Distribution of Hypotrachyna species in South Korea: 
H. nodakensis ( ▲ ), H. osseoalba (•), and H. revoluta (★). </p>



<p>Parmelia revoluta Flörke, in Sprengel, Syst. Veg., Ed. 
16 4: 248 (1827). 
Imbricaria revoluta Fw. In 28. Jahresber. Schlesisch. 
Gesellsch. Vaterl. Kultur 129 (1850). 
Imbricaria sinuosa f. concentrica Arnold, Flora, Jena 
53: 212 (1870). 
Parmelia forsteri Leight., in Lindsay, Bull. U. S. Natl. 
Mus. 9: 91 (1869). 
Parmelia laevigata var. forsteri (Leight.) Leight., 
Trans. Bot. Soc. Edinb. 9: 91 (1869). 
Parmelia quercina var. erratica (Linds.) Hillmann, 
Rabenh. Krypt. Fl., Ed. 2 (Leipzig) 9: 192 (1936). 
Parmelia revoluta var. concentrica (Arnold) Cromb., 
Monogr. Lich. Br. 1: 238 (1894). 
Parmelia revoluta var. erratica (Linds.) Zahlbr., Cat. 
Lich. Univers. 6: 195 (1929) [1930]. 
Parmelia revoluta var. minor Harm., in Kieffer, Bull. 
Soc. Hist. Nat. Metz: 53 (1895). 
Parmelia sinuosa var. erratica Linds., Trans. R. Soc. 
Edinb. 22: 216 (1859) [1861]. 
Parmelia sinuosa var. excentrica Mudd, Man. Br. 
Lich.: 96 (1861). 
Thallus loosely adnate to the substratum, thin, fragile, 4 
cm across. Lobes sublinear to subirregular, short, ascending 
at the tips, 1~3 mm wide. Upper surface mineral grey, 
smooth, emaculate, becoming pustulate towards the lobe 
tips, pustules becoming sorediate. Medulla white. Lower 
surface black, with brown marginal zone, sparsely rhizinate. 
Rhizines short, dichotomously branched. Apothecia and 
pycnidia not seen (Fig. 1). 
Chemistry: Cortex K+ (yellow), C−, KC−, P−; medulla 
K−, C+ (rose), KC+ (rose to red), P−. TLC: atranorin, 
chloroatranorin, gyrophoric acid, unknown 1 (Fig. 2). 
Remarks: This species is characterized by pustulate 
soredia, revolute lobes and the presence of gyrophoric acid 
in the medulla. According to Divakr and Upreti [12], this 
species is closely related to H. rockii by the nature of its 
soredia and C+ rose medulla, but the latter has a white 
maculate upper surface and evernic and lecanoric acids in 
the medulla. 
Specimens examined: Micheongol Valley, Gangwon-do, 
on bark, 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>56'10.6" N, 128 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>31'8.77" E, alt. 420 m, 14 May 
2009, 090338 (Fig. 3). 
Geographical distribution: In South Korea, H. revoluta 
was first reported by Kashiwadani et al. [17]. This species 
has also been reported in China [15], Japan [18], and most 
European countries. </p>

<p>Species excluded from this study. 
According to earlier publications by different authors, the 
Hypotrachyna taxa listed below have been reported from 
South Korea. Some of these taxa have not been found in 
South Korea or have been synonymized by other taxa. 
However, taxonomic details are provided for the following 
species, Hypotrachyna exsecta (Taylor) Hale, Hypotrachyna 
ikomae (Asahina) Hale, Hypotrachyna physcioides (Nyl.) </p>

<p>Hale and Hypotrachyna pseudosinuosa (Asahina) Hale, 
based on previous literature. </p>

<p>Hypotrachyna exsecta (Taylor) Hale, Phytologia 28: 341 
(1974). 
Parmelia exsecta Taylor, Lond. J. Bot. 6: 166 (1847). 
This species is characterized by pustules that become 
erumpent, eroded and granular-sorediate with age and by 
the presence of atranorin, chloroatranorin and barbatic 
acid in the medulla. This species is closely related to 
Hypotrachyna laevigata, but the latter has wider lobes and 
faint maculae without pustules [11]. 
According to Park [19], H. exsecta was first reported on 
cherry trees in South Korea. In addition to South Korea, 
this species has been reported in Australia [11], India [12], 
Japan [18], North Korea [20], Malaysia [21], and Papua 
New Guinea [22]. </p>

<p>Hypotrachyna ikomae (Asahina) Hale, Phytologia 28: 341 
(1974). 
Parmelia ikomae Ashahina, J. Jpn. Bot. 28: 134 
(1953). 
This species is characterized by broad, sublinear lobes 
with subrotund apices, cylindrical to irregularly thickened 
isidia and the presence of protolichesterinic, lichesterinic, 
nephrosterinic and isonephrosternic acids in the medulla 
[14]. 
H. ikomae was first reported in South Korea by Park 
[19]. This species has also been reported from China [14], 
Japan [23], and Malaysia [24]. </p>

<p>Hypotrachyna physcioides (Nyl.) Hale, Smithson. Contrib. 
Bot. 25: 54 (1975). 
Parmelia physcioides Nyl., Syn. Meth. Lich. 1: 385 
(1860). 
This species is characterized by a lack of vegetative 
propagules (rarely sparse lobules may be present) and the 
presence of a barbatic acid complex in the medulla. It is 
widely distributed and shows many morphological and 
chemical variations [14]. 
H. physcioides from South Korea was reported by Park 
[25]. This species has also been reported in many 
countries at tropical reagion. </p>

<p>Hypotrachyna pseudosinuosa (Asahina) Hale, Smithson. 
Contrib. Bot. 25: 58 (1975). 
Parmelia pseudosinosa Asahina, J. Jpn. Bot. 26: 329 
(1951). 
According to Chen et al. [14], H. pseudosinuosa is 
characterized by the presence of capitate, subterminal soralia, 
and protocetraric acid in the medulla. 
This species is widespread in panatropical regions 
including Brazil [26], China [14, 15], Costa Rica [27], Japan 
[18], Malaysia [21], Papua New Guinea [28], Taiwan [29], 
and Venezuela [30]. 
The following two Hypotrachyna species have been </p>

<p>Lichen Genus Hypotrachyna in Korea 17 </p>

<p>synonymized with the genus Remototrachyna. </p>

<p>Hypotrachyna incognita (Kurok.) Hale=Remototrachyna 
incognita (Kurok.) Divakar &amp; A. Crespo comb. nov. </p>

<p>Hypotrachyna koyaensis (Asahina) Hale=Remototrachyna 
koyaensis (Asahina) Divakar &amp; A. Crespo comb. nov. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by a grant from the Korean 
Forest Service Program (KNA 2012) through the Korean 
National Arboretum and the Korean National Research 
Resource Center Programme. </p>



</text></tei>