<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3902349" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective: Accurate, efficient and cost-effective </p>

<p>disposition of patients presenting to emergency 
departments (EDs) with symptoms suggestive of acute 
coronary syndromes (ACS) is a growing priority. Platelet 
activation is an early feature in the pathogenesis of ACS; 
thus, we sought to obtain an insight into whether point-
of-care testing of platelet function: (1) may assist in the 
rule-out of ACS; (2) may provide additional predictive 
value in identifying patients with non-cardiac symptoms 
versus ACS-positive patients and (3) is logistically 
feasible in the ED. </p>

<p>Design: Prospective cohort feasibility study. 
Setting: Two urban tertiary care sites, one located in the </p>

<p>USA and the second in Argentina. </p>

<p>Participants: 509 adult patients presenting with </p>

<p>symptoms of ACS. </p>

<p>Main outcome measures: Platelet reactivity was </p>

<p>quantified using the Platelet Function Analyzer-100, with 
closure time (seconds required for blood, aspirated under 
high shear, to occlude a 150 µm aperture) serving as the 
primary endpoint. Closure times were categorised as 
'normal' or 'prolonged', defined objectively as the 90th 
centile of the distribution for all participants enrolled in 
the study. Diagnosis of ACS was made using the 
standard criteria. The use of antiplatelet agents was not 
an exclusion criterion. </p>

<p>Results: Closure times for the study population ranged </p>

<p>from 47 to 300 s, with a 90th centile value of 138 s. The 
proportion of patients with closure times ≥138 s was 
significantly higher in patients with non-cardiac 
symptoms (41/330; 12.4%) versus the ACS-positive 
cohort (2/105 (1.9%); p=0.0006). The specificity of 
'prolonged' closure times (≥138 s) for a diagnosis of 
non-cardiac symptoms was 98.1%, with a positive 
predictive value of 95.4%. Multivariate analysis revealed 
that the closure time provided incremental, independent 
predictive value in the rule-out of ACS. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Point-of-care assessment of platelet </p>

<p>reactivity is feasible in the ED and may facilitate the rapid 
rule-out of ACS in patients with prolonged closure times. </p>

<p>CCTA in low-to-intermediate risk patients is reportedly 
safe and reduces ED costs and hospital length of stay. </p>

<p>3-5 </p>

<p>7 8 However, these benefits are accompanied by expos-
ure to radiation and associated with increases in diagnos-
tic testing and subsequent invasive procedures. </p>

<p>5 8 </p>

<p>Assessment of platelet activation, an early feature in the 
pathogenesis of ACS, 
9-14 has also been investigated as a pos-
sible benign strategy to expedite the diagnosis of ACS. </p>

<p>15 16 </p>

<p>Application of flow cytometry, the 'gold standard' for the 
quantitation of molecular indices of platelet activation, is, 
however, impractical for routine use under emergent condi-
tions. 
11 12 17 18 More importantly, classic molecular indices 
of platelet activation have not provided added benefit in the 
risk stratification of undifferentiated chest pain patients. </p>

<p>15 16 </p>

<p>We hypothesised that rapid assessment of platelet reactiv-
ity using a technically straightforward point-of-care device-
specifically, the Platelet Function Analyzer (PFA)-100 
(Siemens)-may represent a more feasible strategy to assist 
in the timely rule-out of ACS in the ED. Rather than quanti-
fying molecular markers of platelet activation-aggregation, 
the output of the PFA-100 is the 'closure time': that is, the 
time required for whole blood, aspirated under high shear, 
to occlude a small, 150 μm aperture in a membrane coated 
with standard platelet agonists (collagen-ADP or 
collagen-epinephrine). Although the PFA-100 is typically 
utilised to investigate the responsiveness of patients to 
aspirin and other antiplatelet therapies and aid in the 
detection of platelet dysfunction, </p>

<p>11 12 18-22 </p>

<p>, there is evidence 
to suggest that shortened closure times may be a marker of 
the acuity of coronary disease. 
10 Accordingly, our primary 
aims in this pilot study were to determine whether 
point-of-care testing of platelet function: (1) may assist in 
the rule-out of ACS; (2) may yield additional predictive 
value in identifying patients with non-cardiac symptoms 
versus ACS-positive patients and (3) is logistically feasible in 
an emergent setting. In addition, as a secondary analysis, we 
investigated whether the closure time may be of value in dis-
criminating between ST-elevation myocardial infarction 
(STEMI) and non-ST-elevation myocardial infarction 
(NSTEMI)/unstable angina (UA). </p>

<p>METHODS 
We conducted a prospective cohort feasibility study of 
patients presenting with potential ACS at two urban ter-
tiary care sites: the ED at the University of Massachusetts 
(UMASS)-Memorial Medical Center, University Campus, 
Worcester, Massachusetts, USA, and the Cardiology 
Department, Instituto Modelo de Cardiologia Privado 
SRL, Cordoba, Argentina. The enrolment period was 
from January 2007 to December 2010. At each site, 
patients were entered on a convenience basis: that is, 
enrolments were not consecutive but, rather, coincided 
with the work schedules of the study investigators. </p>

<p>Patient population 
Patients ≥18 years of age with a potential diagnosis of ACS 
(at the discretion of the treating physician and reflected </p>

<p>by orders for an ECG and cardiac biomarkers) were con-
sidered for enrolment in the study. The prospective exclu-
sion criteria were pregnancy, renal insufficiency (defined 
as serum creatine levels ≥1.5 mg/dL), anaemia (haemato-
crit &lt;30%), platelet count &lt;100 000/µL, major bleeding, 
any gastrointestinal bleeding, trauma or the inability to 
provide informed consent for any reason. The use of anti-
platelet agents was not an exclusion criterion. </p>

<p>Study enrolment and protocol 
As soon as possible after evaluation by ED staff, potential 
participants were approached for enrolment into the 
study. If the patient was too ill or otherwise unable to 
provide written consent, then proxy consent was 
attempted. If consent was obtained by proxy and the 
patient later became cognisant, they were given the 
option to continue or withdraw their participation in 
the study. If consent was withdrawn, all collected data 
were discarded. 
Blood used in the PFA-100 was drawn within &lt;1 h after 
presentation, at the same time as cardiac biomarker 
testing, and the closure time was measured within 3 h of 
collection. All samples were obtained via peripheral veni-
puncture and drawn into tubes containing 3.2% sodium 
citrate. Immediately before analysis, each sample was 
gently inverted; a 900 μL aliquot of whole blood was 
then applied to a collagen-ADP test cartridge and the 
closure time was quantified. Maximum test duration for 
the PFA-100 is 5 min; if the aperture is not occluded 
within this period, a closure time of '&gt;300 s' is displayed. 
On enrolment, patients were questioned regarding a 
history of bleeding or platelet function disorders and 
ingestion of known antiplatelet agents within the past 
7 days (aspirin, clopidogrel, non-steroidal anti-
inflammatory agents). In addition, the medical record 
was reviewed and the standard cardiac risk factors (dia-
betes, hypertension, hypercholesterolaemia, smoking, 
family history of heart disease) were recorded and used 
in the calculation of thrombolysis in myocardial infarc-
tion (TIMI) risk score. </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Patient diagnosis 
The final diagnosis (non-cardiac symptoms vs 
ACS-positive) was established via a standardised chart 
review. All reviews were conducted by physicians in a 
blinded manner, without knowledge of the closure time 
data. For participants enrolled at the Instituto Modelo 
de Cardiologia Privado, patients were seen by a cardiolo-
gist at the time of hospital presentation, and all reviews 
were performed by a team of cardiologists (WQ-C, GFT, 
FRZ, ECC and JPS). At UMASS, each patient was first 
seen by an Emergency Medicine physician at the time of 
hospital presentation, and each chart was reviewed by an 
ED physician (CED). For patients with a definitive diag-
nosis of non-cardiac symptoms (ie, patients with no 
ischaemic ECG changes, no positive markers or provoca-
tive cardiovascular test results, and no history of a diag-
nosis of ACS of any type in the chart), no additional </p>



<p>Darling CE, Sala Mercado JA, Quiroga-Castro W, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e003883. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003883 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>review was performed. However, for patients who: (1) 
had positive cardiac biomarkers during admission; (2) 
underwent cardiac catheterisation; (3) had a positive 
provocative cardiovascular test (eg, exercise stress test) 
or (4) had ischaemic ECG changes, the chart was 
reviewed by an ED physician and a cardiologist. In any 
case in which the diagnosis was uncertain, the decision 
was adjudicated by a cardiologist (CSS). 
Patients considered to be ACS positive were categorised 
into one of the two groups, STEMI or NSTEMI/UA, in 
accordance with the standard guidelines. 
24-26 Patients who 
did not meet these criteria were classified as having a diag-
nosis of non-cardiac chest pain/symptoms. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Our target sample size in this exploratory study was 
empiric. We reasoned that, as an approximate order of 
magnitude, ∼100 patients would be required in the 
ACS-positive group in order to have the likelihood of dis-
cerning a potential difference in the closure times 
between patients with non-cardiac symptoms and the 
ACS-positive cohort. Assuming that 75% of patients 
enrolled in the study would have a diagnosis of non-
cardiac chest pain (and thus 25% would be ACS posi-
tive), a total of approximately 400 patients would be 
required. To account for exclusions, target enrolment 
was set at ∼500 participants. </p>

<p>Univariate comparisons 
Our primary analyses focused on the comparison of 
patients in the two main outcome groups: non-cardiac 
symptoms versus ACS positive. All categorical data were 
compared using the Fisher's exact test and are reported 
as percentages. For continuous data, the D'Agostino and 
Pearson test was applied to determine normality and the 
appropriate parametric (t test) or non-parametric alter-
native (Mann-Whitney) tests were utilised. Secondary 
analysis (comparison of closure times among non-
cardiac chest pain, STEMI and NSTEMI/UA groups) 
was conducted using the Kruskal-Wallis test. Results are 
reported as mean±SD or medians with associated 10th 
and 90th centile ranges. </p>

<p>Sensitivity, specificity and multivariate analysis 
We made the prospective and arbitrary decision to cat-
egorise the closure time into 'normal' and "prolonged" 
values based on the 90th centile of the distribution for 
all patients enrolled in the study. Utilising the normal 
and prolonged values of closure time, the sensitivity, spe-
cificity, negative and positive predictive values and likeli-
hood ratio for identifying patients with non-cardiac 
symptoms were determined. Two reasons contributed to 
our choice of non-cardiac chest pain (rather than 
ACS positive) as the main outcome of interest: (1) this 
approach is consistent with current guidelines for the 
improvement of diagnostic accuracy 
1 8 and (2) we rea-
soned that prolonged closure times may be associated 
with the absence of ACS, whereas shorter closure times </p>

<p>may be manifest in either group of patients. Sensitivity, 
specificity, predictive values and the likelihood ratio are 
reported with associated 95% CIs. 
To determine whether the PFA closure time provides 
an additional predictive value to the standard clinical 
diagnostic information, a logistic regression was devel-
oped to assess its independent association with the main 
outcome of non-cardiac symptoms. Independent pre-
dictor variables considered to be mandatory in the 
model were the closure time (utilising continuous rather 
than the categorised values; the main predictor of inter-
est) and the TIMI risk score (representing standard clin-
ical information to predict ACS outcomes). To account 
for potential differences between UMASS and Cordoba, 
the study site was also added to the regression model. 
Other non-mandatory variables considered for inclusion 
were sex, a medical history of diabetes, hypertension, 
hypercholesterolaemia, smoking and clopidogrel use. As 
age and aspirin use are individually incorporated in the 
TIMI risk score, these variables were not considered for 
separate inclusion in the model. Non-mandatory vari-
ables were left in the model only if they yielded an 
increase in predictive value as determined by receiver 
operating characteristic (ROC) analysis or were of add-
itional importance based on the 2 log-likelihood ratio 
test. 
The reported estimate and adjusted OR for closure time 
were calculated for an increase in platelet closure time of 
10 s (rather than 1 s), a choice based on the premise that 
a 1 s increase would be of limited clinical usefulness. The 
final model was evaluated by c-statistic (area under the 
ROC curve) and the Hosmer and Lemeshow fit test. As a 
sensitivity test, the results were calculated using the 
general estimating equation (PROC GENMOD) with study 
site evaluated as a subject factor (cluster) rather than a 
term in the model. The Net Reclassification Index (NRI) 
and Integrated Discrimination Improvement (IDI) statistic 
were not included in the analyses, given the scepticism 
and criticisms that have been raised concerning their 
value in predicting the potential, incremental prognostic 
impact of novel biomarkers. </p>

<p>27 28 </p>

<p>Analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> V.<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.04</rs> 
(San Diego, California, USA) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">SAS</rs> V.<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">9.3</rs> (Carey, 
North Carolina, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Enrolment and exclusions 
A combined total of 509 patients were enrolled at the 
two study sites (figure 1). Sixty-one participants were 
excluded because the closure time data were not 
available. The reasons included technical errors 
(n=14), closure times &gt;300 s ( possibly due to mild 
thrombocytopenia, anaemia or inadequate mixing of 
the blood sample prior to testing; n=36) and failure 
to measure the closure time despite obtaining 
consent (n=11). An additional five participants were 
removed from analysis because exclusion criteria were </p>

<p>Darling CE, Sala Mercado JA, Quiroga-Castro W, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e003883. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003883 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>identified after consent was obtained (n=4), or 
consent was revoked after the blood sample was col-
lected (n=1). For the remaining 443 patients in 
whom the closure time was quantified, 8 were diag-
nosed with thrombotic events that were non-cardiac in 
origin and thus were excluded from further analysis. 
Accordingly, results are reported for 435 participants 
(324 enrolled at UMASS and 111 enrolled in 
Cordoba): 105 were diagnosed with ACS and 330 had 
non-cardiac symptoms. </p>

<p>Demographics 
As expected, 
29 the ACS-positive group had higher TIMI 
scores, was older, and had a higher proportion of male 
participants versus patients with non-cardiac symptoms 
(table 1). In addition, the incidence of hypercholesterol-
aemia and the use of clopidogrel were significantly 
higher in the ACS group. There were, however, no dif-
ferences in the use of aspirin, incidence of hypertension 
or diabetes, proportion of smokers or a reported family 
history of heart disease between the two groups. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Inclusion flow chart. </p>

<p>Table 1 Demographics: all patients </p>

<p>Non-cardiac symptoms (total n=330) 
ACS positive (total n=105) 
p Value </p>

<p>Age (years): mean±SD 
57±14 (n=328) 
61±13 (n=104) 
0.034 
Male 
65% (n=330) 
80% (n=105) 
0.004 
TIMI score: mean±SD 
1.9±1.4 (n=320) 
3.1±1.4 (n=104) 
&lt;0.0001 
Aspirin 
71% (n=321) 
64% (n=104) 
0.222 (ns) 
Clopidogrel 
11% (n=325) 
20% (n=104) 
0.031 
Smoker 
29% (n=322) 
28% (n=105) 
0.901(ns) 
Hypertension 
57% (n=322) 
62% (n=105) 
0.425 (ns) 
Hypercholesterolaemia 
57% (n=322) 
69% (n=105) 
0.030 
Diabetes 
24% (n=322) 
27% (n=105) 
0.601 (ns) 
Family history 
40% (n=319) 
41% (n=105) 
0.909 (ns) </p>

<p>ACS, acute coronary syndromes; TIMI, thrombolysis in myocardial infarction. </p>



<p>Darling CE, Sala Mercado JA, Quiroga-Castro W, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e003883. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003883 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Closure time 
There was a modest but significant difference in the 
median closure times in patients with non-cardiac symp-
toms versus the ACS-positive group: 91 vs 87 s, respect-
ively ( p=0.0061; figure 2A). When the ACS-positive 
group was divided into STEMI and combined NSTEMI/ 
UA cohorts, the modest differences in the closure time 
in the secondary three-group analysis remained signifi-
cant ( p=0.0001; figure 2C). 
Of potentially greater importance, patients with non-
cardiac symptoms versus ACS-positive patients were dis-
tinguished by differences in the proportion of the pro-
longed closure times. We found that 41/330 (12.4%) of 
patients with non-cardiac symptoms had closure times 
≥138 s (ie, the 90th centile of the distribution for all </p>

<p>patients enrolled in the study) while, in contrast, 2/105 
(1.9%) of patients in the ACS-positive group had closure 
times ≥ this value ( p=0.0006; figure 2B and table 2). 
The specificity and sensitivity of 'prolonged' closure 
times (≥138 s) for a diagnosis of non-cardiac symptoms 
were 98.1% and 12.4%, respectively, with a positive pre-
dictive value of 95.4%, a negative predictive value of 
26.3% and a likelihood ratio of 6.52 (table 3). </p>

<p>Site differences: UMASS versus Cordoba 
Patients at both sites displayed the expected differences 
in TIMI score, age and sex between non-cardiac chest 
pain and ACS-positive groups (data not shown). 
However, the participants enrolled in Cordoba were sig-
nificantly younger, with a higher proportion of males </p>

<p>Figure 2 Platelet Function 
Analyzer-100 closure time (s). (A) 
Median values with 10th, 25th, 
75th and 90th centiles: acute 
coronary syndromes 
(ACS)-positive patients and 
patients with non-cardiac 
symptoms. (B) Individual data 
points for all participants: 
ACS-positive patients and 
patients with non-cardiac 
symptoms. Lines denote the 80th, 
90th and 95th centiles of closure 
times for all patients enrolled in 
the study. (C) Individual data 
points for all participants: 
ST-elevation myocardial 
infarction, non-ST-elevation 
myocardial infarction/unstable 
angina cohorts and patients with 
non-cardiac symptoms. Lines 
denote the 80th, 90th and 95th 
centiles of closure times for all 
patients enrolled in the study. </p>

<p>Darling CE, Sala Mercado JA, Quiroga-Castro W, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e003883. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003883 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>and smokers but lower proportion of patients with dia-
betes, when compared with UMASS (table 4). In add-
ition, and as expected, 
30 31 aspirin use was significantly 
lower among the cohort in Cordoba versus the UMASS 
population (40% vs 80%, p&lt;0.0001, table 4). Despite 
these demographic differences, a higher incidence of 
prolonged closure times in patients with non-cardiac 
symptoms was observed at both sites: that is, the propor-
tion of participants with closure times ≥138 s was 13% vs 
10% in patients with non-cardiac chest pain and 1.9% vs 
2% in ACS-positive patients at UMASS versus Cordoba, 
respectively. </p>

<p>Closure time as an independent predictor of diagnosis 
Logistic regression analysis was first performed with manda-
tory variables (closure time, TIMI risk score) and non-
mandatory variables (study site, sex, diabetes, hypertension, 
hypercholesterolaemia, smoking, clopidogrel use) included 
in the regression model (data not shown). ROC analysis 
revealed that, among the non-mandatory variables, only 
study site (UMASS vs Cordoba) contributed to an increase 
to the predictive value of the model for a diagnosis of non-
cardiac symptoms. Comparison of ROC curves obtained by 
including the closure time, TIMI score and site in the 
model versus TIMI score and site alone showed a signifi-
cant, incremental increase in area under the curve with the 
addition of closure time (0.818 vs 0.795; p=0.009; figure 3). 
Accordingly, the final multivariate logistic regression model 
incorporated these three variables (table 5). 
For every 10 s increase in the closure time, the 
adjusted odds of a diagnosis of non-cardiac symptoms </p>

<p>was 1.17 (95% CI 1.06 to 1.29; table 5). That is, when 
controlling for TIMI risk score and study site: for every 
10 s increase, the prolonged closure time was associated 
with a 17% increase in the patient having non-cardiac 
chest pain. These results demonstrate that, irrespective of 
TIMI score and site, the closure time was associated with 
the diagnosis of non-cardiac symptoms, with closure time 
providing additional, incremental predictive value beyond that 
obtained by TIMI score. The model demonstrated good 
predictive characteristics (c=0.82) and model fit 
(χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=5.24, df=8; p=0.73). Finally, the sensitivity analysis 
that utilised a general estimating equation accounting 
for potential correlations among sites did not result in 
any important changes in the direction of the effects 
(adjusted odds for every 10 s increase in closure time: 
1.15 with 95% CI 1.10 to 1.23) or conclusions. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
In this study, we demonstrate that point-of-care testing of 
platelet reactivity using the PFA-100 is feasible in the envir-
onment of the ED. The results of our primary analysis 
revealed differences in closure times between patients with 
non-cardiac symptoms versus ACS-positive cohorts, with 
the most notable, discriminating feature being the higher 
incidence of prolonged closure times in the group with 
non-cardiac chest pain. Finally, the outcome of our multi-
variate analysis is consistent with the concept that the 
assessment of closure time provides incremental, inde-
pendent prognostic value beyond that obtained using the 
standard clinical predictor of TIMI score. </p>

<p>Assessment of platelet reactivity as a diagnostic tool for 
ACS in emergent settings 
It is well-established that heightened platelet activity 
occurs in the setting of ACS. 
9-11 13 14 32 Indeed, meas-
urement of platelet reactivity has been utilised in an 
effort to discern the stability of coronary disease, </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>predict the future incidence and outcomes of major 
adverse cardiovascular events, 
11 33-37 and, although 
results have been disappointing, guide the dosing of 
antiplatelet agents with the goal of improving out-
comes. 
32 38 39 Our current study differs from these previ-
ous reports, in that it focused on the assessment of 
platelet reactivity as an adjunct strategy to risk stratify 
patients with potential ACS in emergent conditions. 
Accordingly, the novelty of our study lies in our 
expanded analysis of the closure time, and the identifi-
cation of a more practical and feasible application of 
these data in the prognosis of ACS. 
Our observation of a modest but significant reduction 
in the median/mean closure times in patients with ACS 
is consistent with the outcomes of two previous, small 
ED studies. 
40 41 However, this ∼4 s difference is of a 
limited practical significance given the broad and over-
lapping distributions of closure times for patients with 
non-cardiac symptoms and the ACS-positive cohort 
(figure 2). Rather, we propose that the clinical utility of </p>

<p>Table 2 Incidence of prolonged closure time (≥138 s, 
defined as the 90th centile of the distribution of the study 
population) </p>

<p>Non-cardiac 
symptoms </p>

<p>ACS 
positive 
Total </p>

<p>Prolonged 
closure time 
Yes 
41 
2 
43 
No 
289 
103 
392 
Total 
330 
105 
435 </p>

<p>ACS, acute coronary syndromes. </p>

<p>Table 3 Sensitivity, specificity, positive and negative 
predictive values and likelihood ratio of prolonged closure 
time for a diagnosis of non-cardiac symptoms </p>

<p>95% CI </p>

<p>Sensitivity (%) 
12.4 
9.1 to 16.5 
Specificity (%) 
98.1 
93.3 to 99.8 
Positive predictive value (%) 
95.4 
84.2 to 99.4 
Negative predictive value (%) 
26.3 
22.0 to 30.9 
Likelihood ratio 
6.52 
1.61 to 26.51 </p>



<p>Darling CE, Sala Mercado JA, Quiroga-Castro W, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e003883. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003883 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>this test lies in the identification of patients with a prolonged 
closure time, a threshold that we objectively defined as the 
90th centile of the distribution of the study population. 
In this regard, we found that the prolonged closure time 
(≥138 s) had a high specificity, positive predictive value 
and likelihood ratio for a diagnosis of non-cardiac chest 
pain. </p>

<p>Strengths and weaknesses 
The results of our pilot study are consistent with the 
hypothesis that point-of-care testing of platelet reactivity 
may assist in the timely rule-out of ACS in the ED. 
Strengths of this approach include the fact that the 
assessment of closure time is technically straightforward 
and cost effective, with minimal patient risk (ie, does 
not involve exposure to radiation or additional invasive 
testing). In addition, our data suggest that the concept is 
generalisable. We observed significant differences in 
demographics (age and gender), the prevalence of spe-
cific risk factors (diabetes, smoking) and the use of anti-
platelet therapy (aspirin: table 4) between UMASS and 
Cordoba-findings that are in agreement with the pub-
lished reports focused on Argentine cohorts, 
30 31 42 and 
may underlie the robust contribution of study site as a 
predictor of outcome in our logistic regression model. 
Nonetheless, our results, obtained from two distinct 
healthcare systems and populations, consistently revealed 
a higher proportion of prolonged closure times in 
patients with non-cardiac symptoms. 
There is, however, an important caveat to this strategy. 
PFA testing will only contribute to the identification of a </p>

<p>subset of patients with non-cardiac symptoms, with the 
size of the subset and the potential value of the test 
dependent on the threshold used to define 'prolonged' 
closure times (figure 2 and table 6). For example, the 
prospective and arbitrary criterion used in our analysis 
(the 90th centile of closure times for all patients 
enrolled in the study) discerned an arguably modest 
12.4% of patients with a diagnosis of non-cardiac symp-
toms. However, expediting the discharge of even a small 
proportion of patients with a non-cardiac diagnosis 
would limit the costs, potential risks and patient stress 
associated with unneeded advanced diagnostic testing 
and possibly invasive procedures. 
1 2 Reducing the thresh-
old (ie, to the 80th centile of the distribution) would </p>

<p>Table 4 Demographics: UMASS vs Cordoba </p>

<p>UMASS all (total n=324) 
Cordoba all (total n=111) 
p Value </p>

<p>Age (years): mean±SD 
59±14 (n=324) 
56±12 (n=108) 
0.036 
Male 
65% (n=324) 
78% (n=111) 
0.009 
TIMI score: mean±SD 
2.3±1.5 (n=313) 
2.0±1.4 (n=111) 
0.142 (ns) 
Aspirin 
80% (n=314) 
40% (n=104) 
&lt;0.0001 
Clopidogrel 
15% (n=319) 
9% (n=111) 
0.146 (ns) 
Smoker 
26% (n=316) 
37% (n=111) 
0.038 
Hypertension 
61% (n=316) 
51% (n=111) 
0.093 (ns) 
Hypercholesterolaemia 
62% (n=316) 
53% (n=111) 
0.115 (ns) 
Diabetes 
28% (n=313) 
14% (n=111) 
0.005 
Family History 
44% (n=313) 
31% (n=51) 
0.014 </p>

<p>TIMI, thrombolysis in myocardial infarction. </p>

<p>Table 5 Multivariable logistic regression model (outcome 
modeled: non-cardiac symptoms) </p>

<p>Predictor 
Adjusted OR 
95% CI </p>

<p>Closure time 
1.17 
1.06 to 1.29 
TIMI risk score 
0.48 
0.40 to 0.59 
Study site 
7.21 
4.05 to 12.86 </p>

<p>(UMASS vs Cordoba). 
TIMI, thrombolysis in myocardial infarction. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) analysis. 
Comparison of ROC curves obtained by including the closure 
time, thrombolysis in myocardial infarction (TIMI) score and 
study site in the regression model versus the TIMI score and 
site alone showing a significant, incremental increase in area 
under the curve with the addition of closure time (0.818 vs 
0.795; p=0.009). </p>

<p>Darling CE, Sala Mercado JA, Quiroga-Castro W, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e003883. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003883 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>increase the size of the subset identified as ACS negative, 
with an accompanying (and increasingly unacceptable) 
loss in specificity because of the growing proportion of 
false positives (ACS-positive patients with prolonged 
closure times: figure 2 and table 6). In contrast, increas-
ing the threshold (ie, to the 95th centile) would identify 
a diminishing proportion of patients with non-cardiac 
symptoms with an increasing specificity (figure 2 and 
table 6). The appropriate definition of 'prolonged' 
closure time will therefore require refinement based on 
risk/benefit analysis. 
Finally, we emphasise that point-of-case assessment of 
platelet reactivity and identification of patients with 'pro-
longed' closure times clearly cannot function as a 
stand-alone test for the rule-out of ACS. Rather, measure-
ment of PFA closure times may serve as an adjunct to the 
current, standard ED practices. In support of this concept, 
our multivariate logistic regression model revealed that, 
irrespective of the TIMI score and study site (and, thus, 
irrespective of differences in demographics and aspirin 
use between sites), closure time was an independent pre-
dictor of the diagnosis of non-cardiac symptoms. </p>

<p>Summary, limitations and future directions 
We report that measurement of the closure time using 
the PFA-100 provides additional and independent, incre-
mental predictive value in the rule-out of ACS. 
Limitations of this pilot feasibility study include the 
enrolment of patients via convenience sampling, and dif-
ferences in the logistics of the chart review process 
between the two sites. In addition, neither monitoring 
of patient outcomes beyond hospital discharge (raising 
the possibility of potential misclassification of some 
patients) nor risk/benefit analysis of PFA testing was 
incorporated into the study design. We emphasise that 
point-of-care assessment of platelet reactivity cannot 
serve as a stand-alone test to either discern patients with 
non-cardiac symptoms versus ACS-positive patients or 
distinguish between STEMI versus NSTEMI/UA in the 
emergent setting-limitations that in all likelihood 
reflect the complex and multifactorial pathophysiology 
of acute myocardial ischaemia and infarction. Rather, 
our results suggest that the assessment of closure times 
may provide benefit by augmenting the standard ED 
diagnostic practices, a concept that warrants further 
large-scale multicentre investigation. </p>

<p>Author affiliations 
1 Department of Emergency Medicine, University of Massachusetts Medical 
School, Worcester, Massachusetts, USA 
2 Cardiovascular Research Institute, Wayne State University School of Medicine 
Detroit, Michigan, USA 
3 Department of Physiology, Wayne State University School of Medicine 
Detroit, Michigan, USA 
4 Division of Cardiology, Instituto Modelo de Cardiologia Privado SRL, 
Cordoba, Argentina 
5 Department of Cardiovascular Medicine, University of Massachusetts Medical 
School, Worcester, Massachusetts, USA 
6 Division of Hematology/Oncology, Center for Platelet Research Studies, 
Boston Children's Hospital, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Harvard Medical 
School, Boston, Massachusetts, USA 
7 Department of Emergency Medicine, Wayne State University School of 
Medicine, Detroit, Michigan, USA </p>

<p>Contributors KP, CED and ADM participated in conception and design of the 
study; all coauthors participated in analysis and interpretation of the data and 
final approval of the manuscript; KP, CED, RDW, PW, JASM, CSS and ADM 
participated in drafting of the manuscript or revising it critically for important 
intellectual content; all authors have had full access to all data and take 
responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the analysis. KP 
is the guarantor. </p>

<p>Funding Siemens Inc provided the Emergency Department at the University 
of Massachusetts Medical School and the Cardiology Department, Instituto 
Modelo de Cardiologia Privado SRL with PFA-100 devices on a loan basis, as 
well as partial support for the purchase of test cartridges used in this study. 
CED was supported in part by a Research Training Grant from the Society for 
Academic Emergency Medicine (SAEM), Des Plaines, Illinois, USA. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Patient consent Obtained. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Institutional Review Boards from the two study sites, 
University of Massachusetts (UMASS)-Memorial Medical Center, University 
Campus, Worcester, Massachusetts, USA, and the Cardiology Department, 
Instituto Modelo de Cardiologia Privado SRL, Cordoba, Argentina. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 3.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/ </p>



<p>Table 6 Effect of definition of 'Prolonged' closure time on specificity and positive predictive value for a diagnosis of 
non-cardiac symptoms </p>

<p>Threshold 
Specificity, 95% CI (%) 
Positive predictive value, 95% CI (%) </p>

<p>Patients with non-cardiac 
symptoms identified (%) </p>

<p>95th centile (≥160 s) 
100 (96.6 to 100) 
100 (83.9 to 100) 
6.4 (21/330) 
90th centile (≥138 s) 
98.1 (93.3 to 99.8) 
95.4 (84.2 to 99.4) 
12.4 (41/330) 
80th centile (≥117 s) 
88.6 (80.9 to 94.0) 
86.2 (77.2 to 92.7) 
22.7 (75/330) </p>



<p>Darling CE, Sala Mercado JA, Quiroga-Castro W, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e003883. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003883 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>



<p>Darling CE, Sala Mercado JA, Quiroga-Castro W, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e003883. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003883 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>