<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3028489" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: In vivo two-photon imaging through the pupil of the primate eye 
has the potential to become a useful tool for functional imaging of the 
retina. Two-photon excited fluorescence images of the macaque cone 
mosaic were obtained using a fluorescence adaptive optics scanning laser 
ophthalmoscope, overcoming the challenges of a low numerical aperture, 
imperfect optics of the eye, high required light levels, and eye motion. 
Although the specific fluorophores are as yet unknown, strong in vivo 
intrinsic fluorescence allowed images of the cone mosaic. Imaging intact ex 
vivo retina revealed that the strongest two-photon excited fluorescence 
signal comes from the cone inner segments. The fluorescence response 
increased following light stimulation, which could provide a functional 
measure of the effects of light on photoreceptors. </p>

<p>Human vision following light absorption by the retina is dependent on an initial 
phototransduction cascade that generates photocurrent and the subsequent regeneration of 
photopigments [1]. Much of our understanding of both these processes comes from in vitro 
work and animal models. Investigation of these pathways has been severely limited by 
difficulties in observing them in living eyes. However, it is valuable to study these processes 
in vivo in part because defects in these pathways can lead to irreversible blindness [2]. Though </p>

<p>#137817 -$15.00 USD Received 8 Nov 2010; revised 14 Dec 2010; accepted 14 Dec 2010; published 17 Dec 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2011 OSA </p>

<p>
the kinetics of rod and cone photopigments have been extensively investigated for more than 
50 years, functional measurements of other relevant molecules have not been possible. Here, 
we describe a new imaging method that marries adaptive optics and two-photon fluorescence 
imaging to demonstrate light dependent changes in individual photoreceptors inside the living 
primate eye. This technique could allow noninvasive monitoring of photoreceptor function in 
normal and diseased eyes. 
The poor optical quality of the mammalian eye and its rapid involuntary ocular motion 
generally precludes imaging at cellular resolution, but recent advances in high-resolution 
imaging with a fluorescence adaptive optics scanning laser ophthalmoscope (FAOSLO) 
coupled with novel image registration methods can overcome this difficulty [3-5]. Adaptive 
optics allows high-resolution imaging with the largest numerical aperture that can be obtained 
with a dilated pupil. Fluorescence imaging produces high contrast images of otherwise 
invisible structures. Although there are many different intrinsically-fluorescent molecules in 
the retina, many cannot be accessed in the living eye by single-photon fluorescence imaging. 
Excitation spectra for several molecules involved in photoreceptor function [6] fall below 400 
nm, where the eye's optics prevent light from reaching the retina [7]. We capitalized on two-
photon excited fluorescence by using a near infrared excitation wavelength to excite otherwise 
inaccessible fluorophores and produce the intrinsic contrast for imaging retinal structure. 
Two-photon fluorescence provides intrinsic axial resolution by preferentially exciting 
fluorophores near the focal plane. In addition, two-photon imaging will permit separation of 
functional imaging of retinal neurons from the intense visual stimulation that is produced by 
current single-photon imaging [3,4]. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>2.1. Fluorescence adaptive optics scanning laser ophthalmoscope (FAOSLO) </p>

<p>High-resolution images of the retina were obtained with a fluorescence adaptive optics 
scanning laser ophthalmoscope (FAOSLO). This second generation instrument (Fig. 1) is 
similar to the first generation FAOSLO previously described in detail [3]. For reflectance 
imaging, a 790 nm (Δ FWHM 17 nm) superluminescent diode (Broadlighter, Superlum Ireland, 
Carrigtwohill, Co. Cork, Ireland) was used. The source for wavefront sensing was a 904 nm 
laser diode. For two-photon excitation at 730 nm, the source was a Ti-sapphire laser (Mai Tai, 
Newport Spectra-Physics, Santa Clara, CA, USA) equipped with second-order dispersion 
compensation (DeepSee, Newport Spectra-Physics, Santa Clara, CA, USA). This source had 
an 80 MHz repetition rate and a pulse width less than 70 fs in air. During calibration, a water 
chamber equal in length to the axial length of a macaque eye with a sample of fluorescein 
beads was used to determine the optimum setting (peak at 21.64 ± 0.13 standard error of the 
mean) for dispersion compensation. Light reflected from the retina retraced the system's 
optical path and was collected through a confocal pinhole by a photomultiplier tube (H7422-
50, Hamamatsu, Japan). To maximize efficiency for two-photon imaging, emitted 
fluorescence from the eye was collected without being descanned. This required that the eye's 
pupil be imaged onto a second photomultiplier tube (H7422-40, Hamamatsu, Japan) after 
being reflected off a dichroic (FF665-Di02, Semrock, Rochester, NY, USA). The emitted 
fluorescene passed through two identical emission filters (E550sp-2p, Chroma, Bellows Falls, 
VT, USA) to prevent bleed-through from the imaging sources. Both reflectance and 
fluorescence images were reconstructed based on the known positions of the scanners at a 
given point in time. All images were acquired at 25Hz with 256 gray levels (8-bit depth). 
Adaptive optics was employed to overcome the poor optical quality of the primate eye and 
create a near diffraction-limited spot on the retina. A Hartmann-Shack wavefront sensor 
(lenslet array with a pitch of 203 μm and a focal length of 7.8 mm, having 30 lenslets across a 
7.2 mm diameter pupil as imaged into the eye's pupil) was used to measure optical aberrations 
of the eye, which then were corrected with a deformable mirror (Hi-Speed dm97, ALPAO, </p>

<p>#137817 -$15.00 USD Received 8 Nov 2010; revised 14 Dec 2010; accepted 14 Dec 2010; published 17 Dec 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2011 OSA </p>

<p>
Biviers, France). Magnification from the eye to the lenslet array was 0.87. The adaptive optics 
correction was operated at 10 Hz and ran in closed-loop during image acquisition. 
To compensate for the low fluorescence emission in a standard two-photon microscope, 
light at each pixel is integrated for a long period of time, but this is not possible in the living 
eye because of continual motion. Instead, up to 16,500 individual fluorescence frames (12 
minute acquisition) were registered and added together to produce the final image. Dual-
image capture and registration (custom software, <rs type="software">DeMotion</rs> [8]), in which the motion trace of 
a simultaneously obtained high signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) reflectance image is used to 
register a low SNR fluorescence video, was needed [3-5]. In addition, to compensate for the 
longitudinal chromatic aberration of the eye, the reflectance and two-photon excited 
fluorescence inputs were pre-adjusted to be focused on the same plane within the eye. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Schematic of the FAOSLO system. Changes in the vertical plane are outlined by the 
dashed lines. Inset: A plot of the transmission spectrum for two-photon emission collection into 
the detector. DM, deformable mirror; HS, horizontal scanner; LD, laser diode; PMT, 
photomultiplier tube; SLD, superluminescent diode; VS, vertical scanner; WFS, wavefront 
sensor. </p>

<p>2.2. FAOSLO imaging procedure </p>

<p>In vivo macaque (macaca mulatta) retinas were imaged during sessions lasting up to 6 hours. 
Primates were prepared for imaging according to procedures previously described in detail 
[4]. Primates were anaesthetized with an intramuscular injection of ketamine, diazepam and 
glycopyrrolate, then intubated and kept in deep stage III, plane 3 anaesthesia with isofluorane. 
Mydriasis and cycloplegia were induced with 1-2 drops each of 2.5% phenylephrine 
hydrochloride and 1% tropicamide. During imaging the eye was held open with a lid 
speculum and a rigid gas permeable contact lens was placed over the cornea to maintain 
corneal health and optical quality. The macaque's head post was attached to a gimbal mount 
designed to rotate about the eye's pupil and a translation stage provided minor pupil 
adjustments. Multiple locations across the macula could be imaged by adjusting the gimbal </p>

<p>#137817 -$15.00 USD Received 8 Nov 2010; revised 14 Dec 2010; accepted 14 Dec 2010; published 17 Dec 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2011 OSA </p>

<p>
mount. Two-photon imaging was performed repeatedly at a given location under variable 
conditions. Variables included the plane of focus, incident excitation power and dispersion 
compensation. Image acquisition at 6 locations began just prior to onset of the excitation laser, 
allowing fluorescence changes in response to the bleaching excitation light to be measured. 
In addition to FAOSLO imaging, fundus photography and fluorescein angiography were 
performed before and after initial FAOSLO imaging sessions to monitor retinal health and 
check for signs of light damage. The axial length of each eye was determined as the average 
of 10 A-scan ultrasound measurements (Quality Diagnostic Ultrasound, Storz/Teknar) and 
was used to convert the angular scale of the image to a linear scale on the retina according to 
the LeGrand eye model [9]. Retinal eccentricity was based on the distance from the foveal 
center for each imaged location when overlaid on a fundus photo. All animal procedures were 
approved by the University Committee on Animal Resources at the University of Rochester. </p>

<p>2.3. Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-3" type="software">PASW Statistics</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">18.0.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago IL, 
USA). When comparing two data sets, Pearson correlation coefficients were calculated and 
paired t-tests were performed. A one-way t-test was used to compare a mean to a constant 
value. In addition, a one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to test the relationship 
between cone spacing and retinal eccentricity. Differences were deemed significant when p ≤ 
0.05. </p>

<p>2.4. Ex vivo two-photon imaging of macaque retina </p>

<p>Immediately after a macaque (macaca fascicularis) was euthanized with anesthetic 
(Sleepaway, Fort Dodge Animal Health, Fort Dodge, IA, USA), the eyes were enucleated and 
maintained in carbogenated (95% O 2 and 5% CO 2 ) Ames' medium (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, 
USA), containing sodium bicarbonate (1.9 g/L) and glucose (0.8 g/L), and kept on ice. Except 
for a short period (approximately 10 minutes), when the tissue was moved to the imaging 
facility, the Ames' medium was continuously bubbled with carbogen. At room temperature 
and under dim red light, a small piece of the central retina with RPE and choroid attached was 
dissected and flattened onto a membrane filter with the ganglion cells facing up. 
The retinal preparation in Ames' medium was imaged at room temperature by using a 
two-photon microscope (Olympus FluoView 1000 AOM-MPM system, Center Valley, PA, 
USA) at 100x, with an objective of 1.05 NA (Olympus, Center Valley, PA, USA) for up to 3 
hours. The Ames' medium was not bubbled with carbogen during imaging. The microscope 
was set-up to mimic in vivo excitation and emission spectra. Image stacks in whole-mount 
views covering the depth of the photoreceptor layer were acquired in both the original pre-
bleached state, having been exposed only to dim red light, and then the post-bleached state, 
after a 2 minute exposure to blue (488 nm) light. The x, y and z pixel sizes of the image stacks 
were 0.124 μm, 0.124 μm and 0.25 μm, respectively. The time to acquire a single pixel was 2 
μs with Kalman 3 line averaging. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. In vivo two-photon images of the photoreceptor mosaic </p>

<p>To our knowledge, this is the first demonstration of two-photon excited fluorescence imaging 
of a living primate eye. In vivo two-photon excited fluorescence images of macaque retina 
revealed a regular array of spots (Fig. 2a) that correspond to the locations of cone 
photoreceptors imaged simultaneously by reflected near infrared light (Fig. 2b). Emission 
from two-photon excited fluorescence, rather than single photon fluorescence, was confirmed 
by several criteria: (1) the emitted power was a quadratic function of the excitation power (i.e. 
the mean power series exponent did not differ significantly from 2 by 1-way t-test; n = 8; α = 
0.05; p = 0.06) (Fig. 2d), (2) dispersion compensation increased fluorescence emission, and </p>

<p>#137817 -$15.00 USD Received 8 Nov 2010; revised 14 Dec 2010; accepted 14 Dec 2010; published 17 Dec 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2011 OSA </p>

<p>
(3) the emission wavelengths were shorter than the excitation wavelength. Two-photon 
signals were weak; a single two-photon excited fluorescence frame had 0.0002 -0.0007 
photons per pixel. The processed images, obtained by summing 16,500 frames, had a mean 
value of approximately 12 photons per pixel. The two-photon fluorescence emission 
originated from the cone photoreceptors because, with rare exceptions, each bright spot in the 
two-photon images (Fig. 2a-c) had a corresponding spot at the same location in the reflectance 
images of the cone mosaic. Moreover, this correspondence held at every eccentricity we 
studied (Fig. 3a-c). In some cases, cones that were not waveguiding light in the reflectance 
image, and hence may have been considered missing, were visible in the fluorescence image, 
indicating that they were probably viable cells (Fig. 2c). According to a paired t-test, the 
spacing of the cones and the spacing of the two-photon imaging spots, each determined from 
the Fourier spectra of the images, were not significantly different (n = 7; α = 0.05; p = 0.40) 
and both increased with eccentricity in a manner unique to the cone mosaic among cell classes 
in the primate retina (Fig. 3d). Although there is evidence for some fluorescence from rods, 
they were not clearly identifiable. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Images of the cone mosaic in the living primate retina. At 2.5° superior, (a) the two-
photon image and (b) the reflectance image show good correspondence. The cross correlation 
coefficient between these images is 0.9. In magnified sections (c) of the larger images, denoted 
by white rectangles in (a) and (b), the correspondence between individual cones can be 
observed (white arrows). Black arrows indicate a cone that was not reflecting light but shows a 
strong fluorescence signal. The images in (c) were low pass filtered to remove frequencies 
above the diffraction-limit, thereby improving cone visibility. Scale bars, 50 μm. The quadratic 
nature of the emitted fluorescence as a function of incident excitation power is shown (d). Error 
bars represent the standard error of the mean gray level among individual frames. </p>

<p>#137817 -$15.00 USD Received 8 Nov 2010; revised 14 Dec 2010; accepted 14 Dec 2010; published 17 Dec 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2011 OSA 
1 January 2011 / Vol. 2, No. 1 / BIOMEDICAL OPTICS EXPRESS 144 </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Mean cone spacing with eccentricity verifies that two-photon fluorescence originates 
from the cone mosaic. Shown are two-photon images of the cone mosaic in the living primate 
at three eccentricities in superior retina, (a) 5.5°, (b) 9.1° and (c) 13°. Scale bars, 50 μm. Cone 
spacing, as determined in Fourier space, is shown as a function of eccentricity (d) from two-
photon () and reflectance (Δ) images. Error bars represent the width of the secondary peak in 
the Fourier spectra. </p>

<p>3.2. Ex vivo two-photon images of the photoreceptor mosaic </p>

<p>To determine the origin of the two-photon fluorescence signal, two-photon imaging was 
performed on ex vivo macaque retina with the retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) and choroid 
attached. Two-photon excited fluorescence was observed through all retinal layers, from the 
ganglion cells to the RPE, consistent with previous studies [10-16]. The mosaic of rods and 
cones was most clearly distinguished in the post-bleached state (Fig. 4b). In the pre-bleached 
state, the edges of photoreceptors appeared indistinct (Fig. 4a). Relative to the pre-bleached 
state, bleaching increased the overall intensity of fluorescence more than two-fold. As shown 
in the transverse view of an 'average' cone (Fig. 4c), the strongest fluorescence signal was 
localized to the cone inner segments in both the pre-and post-bleached states. Based on these 
ex vivo observations, we infer that the in vivo two-photon fluorescence images of the cone 
mosaic also emanate from fluorophores located within the inner segments. </p>

<p>#137817 -$15.00 USD Received 8 Nov 2010; revised 14 Dec 2010; accepted 14 Dec 2010; published 17 Dec 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2011 OSA 
1 January 2011 / Vol. 2, No. 1 / BIOMEDICAL OPTICS EXPRESS 145 </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Two-photon fluorescence of photoreceptors in macaque macular region imaged ex vivo. 
Whole mount view of the photoreceptor inner segment mosaic showing large cones 
interspersed among the much smaller rods in (a) pre-bleached and (b) post-bleached states. 
These slices were collapsed across a 2.5 μm depth. (c) Digitally reconstructed transverse view 
of an 'average' cone, computed by averaging the data cropped from 18 identical voxels 
centered on 18 individual cones, in the post-bleached state showing the bright inner segment 
(IS) and a much dimmer outer segment (OS). Scale bar, 5 μm. </p>

<p>3.3. In vivo functional measurements </p>

<p>In the living macaque eye, we observed that fluorescence emission increased in response to 
photoreceptor bleaching, as measured by the mean gray level of each two-photon fluorescence 
frame (Fig. 5). This is consistent with ex vivo observations. Because of differences in cone 
density and vasculature, the magnitude of the increase in fluorescence varies with location 
from 1.3 to 2 times. The time constants for a 1/e increase ranged from 7 s to 32 s, longer than 
expected for cone bleaching (2 s). The measured changes in fluorescence can indicate 
increases in imaged fluorophore concentration. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Fluorescence emission response during photoreceptor bleaching. The results for three 
different retinal locations are shown. Data points are the means of 2 s time intervals and error 
bars represent the standard error of the means. Lines represent the best fits to the unbinned 
data. </p>

<p>#137817 -$15.00 USD Received 8 Nov 2010; revised 14 Dec 2010; accepted 14 Dec 2010; published 17 Dec 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2011 OSA 
1 January 2011 / Vol. 2, No. 1 / BIOMEDICAL OPTICS EXPRESS 146 </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>These results demonstrate that it is possible to image cellular structures in the living primate 
eye with two-photon fluorescence. The specific fluorophore(s) that were excited remain(s) to 
be determined. Fluorophores previously imaged in ex vivo photoreceptors have included 
mitochondrial flavin adenine dinucleotide (FAD) [15,16], reduced pyridine nucleotides 
involved in cellular metabolism (NADH and NADPH, collectively referred to as NAD(P)H) 
[6,13,15], A2-PE [16] and all-trans-retinol [6,13,15,17]. Because A2-PE and all-trans-retinol 
are products of the visual cycle that are predominately located in outer segments, substantial 
amounts would not be expected in cone inner segments. Fluorophores in cone inner segments 
can also include 11-cis-retinol [18] or compounds yet to be identified. 
Because of the low number of emitted fluorescent photons, it is not currently possible to 
experimentally identify in vivo fluorophores using the FAOSLO. NAD(P)H and retinol have 
similar two-photon excitation cross-sections [19]. At 730 nm, the wavelength used for 
fluorescence excitation, the two-photon cross-section of FAD is almost double that of 
NAD(P)H, but follows a similar action spectrum until it peaks again near 900 nm [20]. 
Although the emission peaks [6,19,20] are slightly separated, NAD(P)H, FAD and retinol are 
all easily detected by the broad emission collection in the FAOSLO. Given their spectral 
properties, emission from other fluorophores, such as A2-PE [16] or lipofuscin [21], is 
unlikely to be collected in significant quantities. 
In vivo two-photon imaging was achieved without observable retinal damage as assessed 
from 1 day to a year later by fundus photography and fluorescein angiography. Moreover, the 
same location could be imaged on separate occasions with no detectable change in the 
appearance of the fluorescence or reflectance images. If this method were to be used in 
humans, the light levels required would have to comply with the current American National 
Standard for the Safe Use of Lasers [22] which provides guidance for calculating maximum 
permissible exposures (MPEs) for ocular light incorporating about an order of magnitude of 
safety. MPE calculations for a scanning laser ophthalmoscope have been described in detail 
elsewhere [4,23]. For the FAOSLO, with imaging conditions described herein, the MPE is 
665 μW for a 12 minute exposure (the acquisition time for generating a single two-photon 
image). Successful in vivo two-photon imaging was achieved by using 3 to 3.5 mW of 
excitation power incident on the cornea, over 4.5 times the 12 minute ANSI MPE, but less 
than the damage threshold expected from experimental data for continuous wave illumination 
[24], a suitable comparison for thermal damage. With improvements in light efficiency, safe 
two-photon imaging of the living human eye appears to be feasible. 
In vivo imaging can provide insight into the molecular changes that occur during the 
phototransduction cascade and subsequent visual pigment regeneration. Improved 
understanding of the processes of vision in living healthy and diseased retina can help 
advance therapies for successful aging, as well as improve the diagnosis and treatment of 
some retinal pathologies [2]. Intrinsic signals have been investigated in vivo at low spatial 
resolution with a fundus camera [25,26] and at the cellular scale with OCT [27], an AOSLO 
[28] and an AO flood-illuminated camera [29]. In response to visible light stimuli, positive 
and negative changes in near-infrared reflectance have been observed, the origins of which are 
not completely understood. The observed intrinsic signals have been attributed to changes in 
vascular blood flow [25] and/or photoreceptor changes such as, membrane hyperpolarisation 
[26,28,29], cell swelling [26,28,29], and changes in refractive index or scattering properties 
[29]. These are indirect measures of the effects of chemical changes occurring in response to 
photoreceptor activation. Two-photon imaging of the living eye at a cellular scale has the 
potential to directly measure the changes in concentrations of fluorescent molecules involved 
in visual excitation. Using two-photon imaging in an isolated frog rod, Chen and colleagues 
[6] demonstrated an increase in the two-photon excited fluorescence signal following 
exposure to visible light. Spectroscopic measurements identified the fluorophores as </p>

<p>#137817 -$15.00 USD Received 8 Nov 2010; revised 14 Dec 2010; accepted 14 Dec 2010; published 17 Dec 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2011 OSA </p>

<p>
NAD(P)H in the rod inner segments and all-trans-retinol in the outer segments. They also 
obtained similar results with isolated mouse retina. Here, we have shown, in vivo and in an ex 
vivo preparation, an increase in two-photon fluorescence signal from cone inner segments in 
response to light exposures that would result in cone bleaching. 
When enabled by a high-resolution adaptive optics scanning laser ophthalmoscope, two-
photon imaging provides functional measurements at the cellular scale in the living eye. The 
nature of current functional measurements is still under investigation. The increased 
fluorescence may represent the creation of new fluorescent molecules or an increase in the 
concentration of existing fluorescent molecules either directly by the two-photon excitation 
light or by its stimulation of a visual response. The capability to image changes in cellular 
metabolism (if imaging FAD or NAD(P)H) or the influx and conversion of 11-cis-retinol in 
cone inner segments in response to visual stimuli is of interest, not only in young and aging 
healthy eyes, but also in eyes with retinal pathology. If the two-photon imaging signal 
emanates from NAD(P)H or FAD, mitochondrial dysfunction, such as that originating from 
Leber's hereditary optic neuropathy [30] or NARP (neurogenic muscle weakness, ataxia, 
retinitis pigmentosa) [31], the technique can display different fluorescence changes over time 
when compared to normal healthy eyes. Altered responses to light may also be observed with 
diseases of the visual cycle, including Leber's congenital amaurosis and Stargardt disease [2]. 
Two-photon fluorescence imaging capabilities could be highly useful for monitoring the 
efficacy of proposed therapies. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>With the use of an adaptive optics scanning laser ophthalmoscope with dual imaging 
capabilities, the many challenges for in vivo two-photon fluorescence imaging were overcome 
to produce the first two-photon fluorescence images of the living primate retina. Images were 
obtained with light levels that did not produce observable retinal damage. Although the 
specific fluorophore is as yet unknown, a strong in vivo fluorescence signal originates from 
cone inner segments producing images of the cone mosaic and providing functional 
measurements of an early stage in the visual process. Future applications of two-photon 
fluorescence imaging in the primate eye may also include the use of extrinsic fluorophores. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>For their assistance with this research, we thank Kamran Ahmad, John Moonan, Jennifer Norris, Lee 
Anne Schery and Robert Wolfe. Ex vivo two-photon imaging was performed at the Multiphoton Core 
Facility at the University of Rochester Medical Center with the assistance of Karl Kasischke, Gheorghe </p>

<p>Salahura and Anita Sun. We appreciate financial support from the following sources: Polgenix, Inc.; 
National Institute for Health, Bethesda, Maryland Grants P30-EY001319, R01-EY004367, BRP-
EY014375, T32-EY007125, R01-EY009339, R24-EY021126, R43-EY020715. This work made 
use of STC shared experimental facilities supported by the NSF under Agreement No. AST-9876783, </p>

<p>Research to Prevent Blindness. Alfredo Dubra-Suarez, Ph.D., holds a Career Award at the Scientific 
Interface from the Burroughs Welcome Fund; Klaus Tschira Foundation Heidelberg, Germany; 
European Life Scientist Organization; TECH 09-004 State of Ohio Department of Development; Third 
Frontier Commission. DeMotion image registration software was developed by Alfredo Dubra and Zach </p>

<p>Harvey with funding from Research to Prevent Blindness and the National Institute of Health, 
Bethesda, Maryland through the grants BRP-EY014375 and 5 K23 EY016700. Adaptive optics </p>

<p>control software was developed by Alfredo Dubra and Kamran Ahmad. </p>

<p>#137817 -$15.00 USD Received 8 Nov 2010; revised 14 Dec 2010; accepted 14 Dec 2010; published 17 Dec 2010 </p>

<p>(C) 2011 OSA 
1 January 2011 / Vol. 2, No. 1 / BIOMEDICAL OPTICS EXPRESS 148 </p>

</text></tei>