<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3071219" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>1 </p>

<p>HLA-DR 
1 ) and senescence 
(CD28 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CD57 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>) with subclinical carotid artery disease. 
Results. Compared with HIV-uninfected women, frequencies of CD4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD38 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>HLA-DR </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD38 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>HLA-
DR </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, and CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD28 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CD57 
1 T cells were higher among HIV-infected women, including those who achieved viral 
suppression while receiving antiretroviral treatment. Among HIV-infected women, adjusted for age, antiretroviral 
medications, and viral load, higher frequencies of activated CD4 
1 and CD8 
1 T cells and immunosenescent CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>T cells were associated with increased prevalence of carotid artery lesions (prevalence ratio lesions associated with 
activated CD4 
1 T cells, 1.6 per SD [95% confidence interval {CI}, 1.1-2.2]; P 5 .02; prevalence ratio lesions associated 
with activated CD8 
1 T cells, 2.0 per SD [95% CI, 1.2-3.3]; P , .01; prevalence ratio lesions associated with senescent 
CD8 
1 T cells, 1.9 per SD [95% CI, 1.1-3.1]; P 5 .01). 
Conclusions. HIV-associated T cell changes are associated with subclinical carotid artery abnormalities, which 
may be observed even among those patients achieving viral suppression with effective antiretroviral therapy. </p>

<p>As compared with control individuals without human 
immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection, HIV-infected 
patients have increased risk of acute cardiovascular 
disease (CVD) events including myocardial infarction </p>

<p>[1] and advanced subclinical vascular disease [2]. The 
CVD risk associated with HIV infection appears to be 
partially attenuated by antiretroviral treatment, since 
treatment interruption increases short-term risk of CVD 
events [3]. Although effective HIV therapy appears to 
reduce the risk of CVD, it may not fully reverse HIV-
associated vascular risk, and long-term exposure to HIV 
therapy may have direct adverse effects on CVD [4]. 
The mechanism for increased CVD risk in anti-
retroviral-treated and untreated HIV infection is likely 
multifactorial, involving pathways related to traditional 
vascular risk factors and antiretroviral drug toxicities. 
Chronic inflammation, which is a well-accepted CVD 
risk factor in the non-HIV setting, may also be impor-
tant. Many markers of inflammation, including T cell 
activation as defined by co-expression of CD38 and 
HLA-DR, are markedly elevated in individuals with </p>

<p>Received 8 March 2010; accepted 8 November 2010; electronically published 
10 January 2011. 
Potential conflicts of interest: None reported. 
Presented in part: 2010 Conference on Retroviruses and Opportunistic 
Infections, San Francisco, CA. Thursday, February 18, 2010. Paper #709. 
Reprints or correspondence: Dr Robert Kaplan, Albert Einstein College of 
Medicine, Bronx, NY 10461 (rkaplan@aecom.yu.edu). </p>

<p>The Journal of Infectious Diseases 2011;203:452-463 
Ó The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Infectious 
Diseases Society of America. All rights reserved. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/ 
2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction 
in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. 
1537-6613/2011/2034-0001$15.00 
DOI: 10.1093/infdis/jiq071 </p>

<p>452 d JID 2011:203 (15 February) d Kaplan et al. </p>

<p>untreated HIV infection and are only partially reversed by 
effective combination antiretroviral therapy [5, 6]. The fre-
quency of activated CD8 
1 T cells predicts the risk of disease </p>

<p>progression independent of other factors in untreated HIV 
infection [7] and is consistently associated with immunologic 
and perhaps clinical outcomes in the context of antiretroviral-
treated infection [6]. The role of activated T cells and their 
inflammatory products in atherosclerosis has been well 
studied [8], although whether vascular changes in HIV-in-
fected patients are influenced by systemic T cell activation 
remains uncertain. 
There is a growing body of literature suggesting that chronic 
viral infections cause accelerated aging of the immune system 
(called ''immunosenescence''). For example, cytomegalovirus 
(CMV) infection is associated with oligoclonal expansion of 
terminally differentiated T cells, decreased T cell repertoire, 
lower T cell proliferation rates, and increased levels of a number 
of inflammatory markers [9]. Untreated HIV infection produces 
a number of these same phenotypic and functional changes to 
the immune system [10]. More recently, evidence has emerged to 
suggest that immune senescence driven by responses to chronic 
infection may play a role in heart and vascular diseases [11]. 
Given the evidence that HIV infection is associated with in-
creased levels of immune activation, inflammation, and im-
munosenescence, we conducted a study to address the hypothesis 
that these pathways mediate the association of HIV infection with 
vascular disease. Archived specimens from a well-characterized 
longitudinal US cohort of HIV-infected and HIV-uninfected 
women were used to measure cell surface expression of CD38, 
HLA-DR, CD28, and CD57 on CD4 
1 and CD8 
1 T cells. We </p>

<p>then related activation (CD38 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>HLA-DR </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>) and senescent 
(CD28 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CD57 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>) T cell subsets with subclinical vascular disease as 
assessed by B-mode carotid artery ultrasound. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Study Population </p>

<p>This study was conducted among participants in the Women's 
Interagency HIV Study (WIHS), a prospective multicenter 
study. Participants were recruited in 2 waves (in 1994-1995 and  2001-2002) and completed study visits every 6 months. In April 
2004, a carotid ultrasound substudy was initiated which in-
cluded B-mode ultrasound imaging of the carotid arteries. For 
the present investigation, we conducted T cell phenotyping 
among 115 HIV-infected women who were &gt;40 years of age at 
the time of their carotid artery ultrasound scan and free of 
clinical vascular disease. A group of HIV-uninfected women 
(n 5 43) was also selected who were frequency-matched to the 
HIV-infected individuals by age (65 years) and race/ethnicity. 
The HIV-infected and HIV-uninfected groups had comparable 
demographic and socioeconomic characteristics and were </p>

<p>recruited using similar methods. Institutional review board 
approval and informed consent were obtained. </p>

<p>Carotid Artery Ultrasound </p>

<p>High-resolution B-mode carotid artery ultrasound was used to 
image the right common carotid artery, internal carotid artery, 
and carotid bifurcation [12]. Right distal common carotid artery 
intima-media thickness (cIMT) was measured. The presence of 
carotid lesions was defined as a focal intima-media thickness of 
.1.5 mm in any of the imaged segments. Standardized carotid 
artery ultrasound images were centrally measured by automated 
computerized edge detection by use of a software package de-
veloped in-house (Prowin patent, 2005, 2006). </p>

<p>Assays </p>

<p>HIV infection was determined via serologic testing using en-
zyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) and confirmed us-
ing Western blot assays. Plasma HIV RNA levels were quantified 
using nucleic-acid-sequence-based amplification commercial 
assays with a lower limit of quantification of 80 copies/mL 
(bioMérieux), and total peripheral CD4 
1 T cell counts were </p>

<p>measured with standard flow cytometric methods. T cell acti-
vation and senescence were measured by immunophenotyping 
performed at the University of California, San Francisco, Core 
Immunology Laboratory, using methods that have been opti-
mized and validated for frozen peripheral blood mononuclear 
cells (PBMCs). Cryopreserved PBMCs were rapidly thawed in 
warm medium, washed, stained with Viacount (Millipore), and 
run on a Guava PCA (Millipore) to determine cell number and 
viability. Samples with viability of ,40% were not analyzed. 
PBMCs were stained with aqua amine reactive dye (Invitrogen) 
to exclude nonviable cells and for surface expression of CD3, 
CD28 (BD Pharmingen), CD4, CD38, HLA-DR (BD Bio-
sciences), CD8 (Invitrogen), and CD57 (Biolegend). Stained 
cells were run on a customized BD LSR II and data analyzed 
using <rs id="software-1" type="software">FlowJo</rs> software, version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">8.8.4</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Tree Star</rs>) to quantitate 
CD4 
1 and CD8 
1 T cells expressing activation (CD38 and HLA-</p>

<p>DR) and senescence (CD28 
2 and CD57 
1 ) markers (Figure 1). </p>

<p>Data on CD38 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>HLA-DR 
1 and CD28 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CD57 
1 subsets were ex-</p>

<p>pressed as the percentage of T cells expressing these markers. </p>

<p>Clinical Variables </p>

<p>Key cardiovascular and HIV-related covariates were obtained by 
self-report and direct measurements. We defined highly active 
antiretroviral therapy (HAART) in accordance with US De-
partment of Health and Human Services guidelines. </p>

<p>Data Analyses </p>

<p>HIV-infected women were stratified as (1) untreated, (2) 
HAART-treated aviremic, or (3) treated with detectable viremia. 
Primary analyses examined carotid artery lesions and cIMT in 
relation to contemporaneous measures of T cell activation 
(CD38 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>HLA-DR </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>) and T cell senescence (CD28 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CD57 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>). </p>

<p>Kaplan T Cell Activation and Subclinical CVD d JID 2011:203 (15 February) d 453 </p>

<p>Multivariate analyses used log-binomial models for carotid le-
sion prevalence and linear regression models for cIMT. Initial 
analyses included adjustment for age and current use of protease 
inhibitors, nonnucleoside reverse-transcriptase inhibitors, and 
nucleoside reverse-transcriptase inhibitors. Additional nested 
models featured adjustment for concurrent viral load. Further 
adjustment for cumulative exposure to HIV medications and 
proportion of prior study visits with HIV RNA level of .4000 
copies/mL had no effect. We also performed adjustment for 
CD4 
1 T cell count and ratio of CD4 
1 T cells to CD8 
1 T cells. </p>

<p>Subsequent models examined the potential confounding effects 
of cardiovascular risk factors, socioeconomic factors, and use of 
cigarettes, alcohol, and injection drugs. To assess whether the 
nature of associations between T cell phenotypes and subclinical 
carotid artery disease was modified by HIV infection, we 
included interaction terms in models that included both HIV-
infected and HIV-uninfected groups and also conducted 
analyses stratified by presence or absence of HIV infection. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>HIV-infected women (n 5 115) and HIV-uninfected women 
(n 5 43) were comparable in age (mean age of HIV-infected 
women, 46 years; mean age of HIV-uninfected women, 47 years) 
and race/ethnicity (63% and 67% of HIV-infected and HIV-</p>

<p>uninfected women were African American, respectively, and 
28% and 23% of HIV-infected and HIV-uninfected women 
were Hispanic, respectively) (Table 1). Among HIV-infected 
women, 36% were not currently receiving antiretroviral treat-
ment, 39% were treated and had detectable viremia, and 25% 
were treated and had undetectable viremia. 
As compared with the overall WIHS cohort, the HIV-infected 
women in our study were slightly younger, were less likely to be 
non-Hispanic white, and had higher current viral load, but they 
did not otherwise differ significantly (P , .05) on variables 
shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>T Cell Activation Markers </p>

<p>Compared with HIV-uninfected women, HIV-infected women 
had markedly higher levels of CD4 
1 and CD8 
1 T cell activation </p>

<p>(P , .01) (Table 1 and Figure 2). These differences remained 
significant when we restricted the HIV-infected group to those 
who were treated with HAART and had achieved viral sup-
pression. Correlates of higher T cell activation included race/ 
ethnicity, lower high-density lipoprotein cholesterol level, lower 
CD4 
1 T cell count, lower ratio of CD4 
1 T cells to CD8 
1 T cells, </p>

<p>and higher viral load (Table 2). </p>

<p>T Cell Senescence Markers </p>

<p>In comparison with HIV-uninfected controls, the percentage 
of CD8 
1 T cells with an immunosenescent phenotype </p>

<p>(CD28 
2 CD57 
1 ) was increased among the HIV-infected </p>

<p>women (P , .01) (Table 1 and Figure 2). This difference 
persisted even among HIV-infected women who were re-
ceiving HAART and who had undetectable HIV RNA levels. 
Correlates of CD8 
1 CD28 
2 CD57 
1 T cells included race/eth-</p>

<p>nicity, smoking, and high-density lipoprotein cholesterol but 
not CD4 
1 T cell count or plasma HIV RNA level (Table 2). </p>

<p>CD38 
1 HLA-DR 
1 T Cells and Subclinical Carotid Artery Disease </p>

<p>Among the group of HIV-infected women, 19 had &gt;1 carotid 
lesions whereas 96 had no carotid lesions. HIV-infected women 
with carotid lesions had a significantly higher percentage of 
CD4 
1 T cells expressing activation markers (CD38 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>HLA-DR </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>) 
than those HIV-infected women without carotid lesions (P 5 
.02) (Figure 3). The percentage of CD8 
1 T cells expressing ac-</p>

<p>tivation markers was also higher in HIV-infected women with 
lesions than that among HIV-infected women without lesions 
(P 5 .04) (Figure 3). 
In adjusted models, among HIV-infected women, the prev-
alence of carotid lesions was directly associated with the per-
centage of CD4 
1 and CD8 
1 T cells expressing activation </p>

<p>markers. Adjusted for age and antiretroviral medication use, the 
prevalence ratio lesions was 1.6 per SD change in the percentage of 
CD4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD38 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>HLA-DR 
1 T cells (95% confidence interval [CI], </p>

<p>1.1-2.2; P 5 .02), and the prevalence ratio lesions was 2.0 per SD 
change in the percentage of CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD38 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>HLA-DR 
1 T cells </p>

<p>(95% CI, 1.2-3.3; P , .01) (Table 3). This association persisted </p>

<p>Figure 1. Expression of activation (CD38 and HLA-DR) and senescence 
(CD57 and CD28) markers on CD4 
1 and CD8 
1 T cells. Representative 
fluorescence-activated cell-sorting plots showing gating of T cells to 
define CD4 
1 and CD8 
1 T cells (A), activation markers to define CD38 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>HLA-DR 
1 T cells (B), and senescent markers to define CD28 
2 CD57 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>T cells (C). Data were compensated and analyzed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">FlowJo</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Treestar</rs>). Standard lymphocyte and singlet gates were drawn to exclude 
debris, monocytes, and doublets. Dead cells were excluded by gating on 
aqua amine reactive dye-negative cells, and total T cells were defined by 
CD3 
1 staining. Fluorescence-minus-1 controls were used to set T cell 
subpopulation gates. The mean peripheral blood mononuclear cell 
viability was 75.0% in human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-infected 
women and 77.5% in HIV-uninfected women. </p>

<p>454 d JID 2011:203 (15 February) d Kaplan et al. </p>

<p>Table 1. Characteristics of Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV)-Infected and HIV-Uninfected Women in the Women's Interagency HIV Study </p>

<p>HIV-infected women </p>

<p>HIV-uninfected 
women </p>

<p>Treated 
viremic 
Untreated </p>

<p>Treated 
viremic 
All </p>

<p>P, HIV-uninfected 
vs all HIV-infected 
women </p>

<p>P across HIV-uninfected 
and 3 HIV-infected 
groups </p>

<p>(N 5 43) 
(N 5 29) 
(N 5 41) 
(N 5 45) 
(N 5 115) </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Median/% IQR Median/% IQR Median/% IQR Median/% IQR Median/% IQR </p>

<p>Age, years 
47 
8 
45 
5 
47 
8 
47 
7 
46 
6 
.91 
.34 </p>

<p>Laboratory variables </p>

<p>CD4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD38 
1 DR 
1 T cells, % 
2.5 
1.5 
5 
3.8 
7.9 
8.5 
11.7 
13.3 
7.7 
9.4 
,.01 
,.01 
CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD38 
1 DR 
1 T cells, % 
7.3 
8.9 
15.1 
11.7 
34 
19.3 
31.3 
21.8 
28.9 
23.6 
,.01 
,.01 
CD4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD28 
2 CD57 
1 T cells, % 
1.8 
4.4 
1.8 
4.7 
2.9 
5.6 
3.1 
9.4 
2.5 
5.9 
.07 
.16 </p>

<p>CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD28 
2 CD57 
1 T cells, % 
22.7 
27.3 
30.2 
16 
37.3 
21.9 
36.9 
19.5 
35.8 
21.7 
,.01 
,.01 
Current viral load, copies/mL 
NA 
. 
80 
0 
4050 
25,575 
5500 
20,680 
1200 
15,920 
NA 
,.01 
Peak viral load, 31000 copies/mL 
NA 
. 
110 
330 
24 
83.6 
160 
343 
60 
305 
NA 
,.01 
Current CD4 cell count, cells/lL 
965 
486 
577 
298 
389 
311 
251 
315 
379 
357 
,.01 
,.01 
Nadir CD4 cell count, cells/lL 
782 
236 
196 
242 
327 
297 
151 
177 
209 
236 
,.01 
,.01 
CD4/CD8 ratio of .1, % 
100 
. 
31 
. 
12 
. 
9 
. 
16 
. 
,.01 
,.01 
LDL-C level, mg/dL 
104 
37 
99 
22 
93 
46 
92 
36 
97 
33 
.23 
.18 
HDL-C level, mg/dL 
56 
20 
50 
33 
40 
26 
45 
18 
45 
24 
,.01 
,.01 
LDL-C level of .160 mg/dL, % 
8 
. 
4 
. 
0 
. 
5 
. 
3 
. 
.18 
.39 </p>

<p>HDL-C level of ,40 mg/dL, % 
18 
. 
39 
. 
53 
. 
37 
. 
43 
. 
,.01 
.02 </p>

<p>Clinical variables </p>

<p>BMI, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>29 
12 
26 
6 
28 
6 
26 
7 
27 
6 
.07 
.16 </p>

<p>BMI categories, % 
,25 
26 
. 
34 
. 
28 
. 
34 
. 
32 
. 
.05 
.33 </p>

<p>25-30 
26 
. 
38 
. 
45 
. 
37 
. 
40 
. 
.30 
49 
. 
28 
. 
28 
. 
30 
. 
28 
. 
Weight, kg 
80 
31 
73 
16 
78 
22 
67 
27 
73 
22 
.06 
.11 </p>

<p>Antiretroviral drugs </p>

<p>Duration of HAART use, years 
NA 
. 
7 
3 
6 
5 
7 
3 
7 
3 
N A 
. 0 6 </p>

<p>No. of PIs used (current), 
a % 0 
NA 
. 
38 
. 
NA 
. 
24 
. 
55 
. 
NA 
.42 </p>

<p>1 
N A 
. 
34 
. 
. 
. 
48 
. 
27 
. 
2 
N A 
. 
28 
. 
. 
. 
28 
. 
18 
. 
Duration of PI use, years 
NA 
. 
3.2 
2.9 
NA 
. 
3.1 
4.1 
2.5 
4.2 
NA 
.94 </p>

<p>NRTI use (current), % 
NA 
. 
100 
. 
NA 
. 
98 
. 
63 
. 
NA 
.42 
Duration of NRTI use, years 
NA 
. 
7.5 
3.9 
NA 
. 
7.3 
3.9 
6 
6.8 
NA 
.50 </p>

<p>NNRTI use (current), % 
NA 
. 
52 
. 
NA 
. 
27 
. 
23 
. 
NA 
.03 
Kaplan T Cell Activation and Subclinical CVD d JID 2011:203 (15 February) d 455 </p>

<p>Table 1. (Continued) </p>

<p>HIV-infected women </p>

<p>HIV-uninfected 
women </p>

<p>Treated 
viremic 
Untreated </p>

<p>Treated 
viremic 
All </p>

<p>P, HIV-uninfected 
vs all HIV-infected 
women </p>

<p>P across HIV-uninfected 
and 3 HIV-infected 
groups </p>

<p>(N 5 43) 
(N 5 29) 
(N 5 41) 
(N 5 45) 
(N 5 115) </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Median/% IQR Median/% IQR Median/% IQR Median/% IQR Median/% IQR </p>

<p>Duration of NNRTI use, years 
NA 
. 
1.7 
2.4 
NA 
. 
.6 
1.7 
.3 
2.4 
NA 
.07 </p>

<p>Adherence to antiretroviral drugs, 
b % 
N A 
. 
90 
. 
NA 
. 
72 
. 
77 
. 
NA 
.03 </p>

<p>Abacavir use, % 
NA 
. 
21 
. 
NA 
. 
22 
. 
14 
. 
NA 
.88 
CVD risk factors </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>History of diabetes, % 
33 
. 
17 
. 
15 
. 
31 
. 
22 
. 
.15 
.15 </p>

<p>Diabetes medication use, % 
16 
. 
0 
. 
7 
. 
9 
. 
6 
. 
.046 
.12 </p>

<p>Lipid-lowering drug use, % 
2 
. 
10 
. 
5 
. 
7 
. 
7 
. 
.26 
.53 </p>

<p>Family history of CAD, % 
13 
. 
12 
. 
29 
. 
15 
. 
19 
. 
.41 
.20 </p>

<p>Hypertension, % 
44 
. 
38 
. 
39 
. 
42 
. 
40 
. 
.63 
.94 </p>

<p>Hepatitis C antibody positive, % 
40 
. 
41 
. 
44 
. 
59 
. 
49 
. 
.30 
.32 </p>

<p>Current smoking, % 
70 
. 
34 
. 
49 
. 
57 
. 
48 
. 
.01 
.17 
Race, % 
Other 
9 
. 
14 
. 
2 
. 
11 
. 
8 
. 
.85 
.37 </p>

<p>Hispanic 
23 
. 
31 
. 
27 
. 
26 
. 
28 
. 
African American 
67 
. 
55 
. 
71 
. 
63 
. 
63 
. </p>

<p>NOTE. P values were derived using the Kruskal-Wallis test for continuous variables and v 
2 test for categorical variables. BMI, body mass index; CAD, coronary artery disease; CVD, cardiovascular disease; HAART, highly 
active antiretroviral therapy; HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; IQR, interquartile range; LDL-C, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol; NA, not applicable; NNRTI, nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor; NRTI, 
nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor; PI, protease inhibitor. 
a PI use includes any use of ritonavir. </p>

<p>b Adherence was defined by self-report as taking .95% of the prescribed dose. </p>

<p>c Hypertension was defined as systolic blood pressure of &gt;140 mm Hg, diastolic blood pressure of &gt;90 mm Hg, or prior diagnosis of hypertension. Dyslipidemia was defined as LDL-C level of .160 mg/dL or HDL-C 
level of ,40 mg/dL. Diabetes was defined as fasting plasma glucose level of .126 mg/dL or prior diagnosis of diabetes mellitus with or without the use of antidiabetic medications. Family history of coronary disease was 
defined as a female first-degree relative with myocardial infarction or angina before age 65 or male first-degree relative with myocardial infarction or angina before age 55. </p>

<p>456 d JID 2011:203 (15 February) d Kaplan et al. </p>

<p>after adjustment for viral load and other potential confounders. 
The association of CD4 
1 T cell activation with carotid lesions </p>

<p>was attenuated after further adjustment for CD4 
1 T cell count </p>

<p>(adjusted prevalence ratio lesions , 1.1; 95% CI, .6-2.1) and after 
adjustment for the ratio of CD4 
1 T cells to CD8 
1 T cells (ad-</p>

<p>justed prevalence ratio lesions , 1.5; 95% CI, .8-2.6). In contrast, 
the association between CD8 
1 T cell activation and carotid le-</p>

<p>sions remained after adjustment for CD4 
1 T cell count and ratio </p>

<p>of CD4 
1 T cells to CD8 
1 T cells. </p>

<p>In contrast to the findings among HIV-infected women, we 
did not observe an association between T cell activation and 
increased prevalence of carotid lesions among HIV-uninfected 
women (Figure 3). Models that included interaction terms 
provided evidence of effect modification by HIV status, such 
that higher levels of T cell activation were associated with carotid 
lesions in the HIV-infected group but not in the HIV-uninfected 
group (significance tests for interaction, P 5 .06 for CD4 
1 T cell </p>

<p>activation and P 5 .02 for CD8 
1 T cell activation). </p>

<p>CD28 
2 CD57 
1 T Cells and Subclinical Carotid Artery Disease </p>

<p>Among HIV-infected women, unadjusted analyses showed 
a higher frequency of CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD28 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CD57 
1 T cells in those with </p>

<p>carotid lesions than in those without carotid lesions (P 5 .03) 
(Figure 3). After adjustment for age and use of antiretroviral 
medications, the prevalence ratio lesions for each SD change in the </p>

<p>percentage of CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD28 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CD57 
1 T cells was 1.9 (95% CI, 1.1-</p>

<p>3.1; P 5 .01) (Table 3). This significant association persisted 
after further adjustment for CD4 
1 T cell count, ratio of CD4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>T cells to CD8 
1 T cells, viral load, and other potential con-</p>

<p>founders. There were no differences in the frequency of CD4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD28 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CD57 
1 T cells between those with and those without </p>

<p>carotid lesions (Figure 3; Table 3). When we repeated the analysis 
using CD28 
2 alone rather than CD28 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CD57 
1 to define T cell </p>

<p>subsets, there was an association of CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD28 
2 T cells but not </p>

<p>CD4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD28 
2 T cells with carotid lesions (data not shown). </p>

<p>Models that included interaction terms were consistent with 
the hypothesis that higher levels of CD8 
1 T cell senescence were </p>

<p>associated with carotid lesions in the HIV-infected group but 
not in the HIV-uninfected group (significance test for interac-
tion, P 5 .009). 
In contrast to the findings for the outcome of carotid lesions, 
cIMT measurements were not associated with T cell activation 
or senescence markers in either HIV-infected women (Table 3) 
or HIV-uninfected women (data not shown). </p>

<p>Multivariate Analyses of T Cell Phenotypes Associated With 
Subclinical Carotid Artery Disease </p>

<p>When entered together into a multivariate model, both CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>T cell activation and CD8 
1 T cell senescence remained signifi-</p>

<p>cant or borderline significant in their associations with carotid </p>

<p>Figure 2. T cell activation (CD38 
1 HLA-DR 
1 ) and senescence (CD28 
2 CD57 
1 ) among 115 human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-infected women and 43 
HIV-uninfected women. HIV-infected women include 41 who were not receiving antiretroviral therapy at the time of the study (Untreated), 29 who were 
receiving highly active antiretroviral therapy and had no detectable plasma HIV (Aviremic), and 45 who were treated and had detectable plasma HIV 
(Viremic). P ,.01 (Kruskal-Wallis test) for CD4 
1 T cell activation, CD8 
1 T cell activation, and CD8 
1 T cell senescence in comparing the HIV-infected group 
with the HIV-uninfected group. For CD4 
1 T cell senescence, P 5 .07 in comparing the HIV-infected group with the HIV-uninfected group. </p>

<p>Kaplan T Cell Activation and Subclinical CVD d JID 2011:203 (15 February) d 457 </p>

<p>Table 2. Association of Clinical Variables With CD38 
1 HLA-DR 
1 (Activated) T Cells and CD28 
2 CD57 
1 (Senescent) T Cells Among Women With Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) 
Infection </p>

<p>Percentage of CD4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD38 
1 DR 
1 T cells </p>

<p>Percentage of CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD38 
1 DR 
1 T cells </p>

<p>Percentage of CD4 
1 CD28 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CD57 
1 T cells </p>

<p>Percentage of CD8 
1 CD28 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CD57 
1 T cells </p>

<p>Variable 
Median 
IQR 
P 
Median IQR 
P 
Median 
IQR 
P 
Median 
IQR 
P </p>

<p>Age, years 
40-44 
7.5 
8.9 
.85 
27.5 
25.5 
.61 
2.9 
5.4 
.97 
34.6 
21.6 
.83 </p>

<p>45-49 
7.7 
10.6 
27.5 
17.7 
2.4 
6.0 
36.7 
18.9 </p>

<p>&gt;50 
9.7 
10.9 
31.8 
20.1 
1.9 
5.2 
36.9 
18.7 </p>

<p>CD4 
1 T cell count, cells/lL 
,200 
19.4 
15.8 &lt;.01 
33.9 
26.6 &lt;.01 
3.6 
15.0 
.52 
37.7 
21.2 
.40 </p>

<p>200-349 
10.4 
8.7 
37.6 
21.2 
3.1 
6.3 
37.1 
16.2 </p>

<p>350-499 
6.1 
3.2 
27.4 
23.9 
2.0 
4.2 
33.5 
21.9 </p>

<p>&gt;500 
4.6 
3.1 
20.6 
19.2 
2.4 
5.6 
31.3 
22.5 </p>

<p>CD4/CD8 ratio 
&lt;1 
9.5 
10.1 &lt;.01 
32.3 
23.1 &lt;.01 
2.7 
6.0 
.37 
36.8 
20.2 
.11 </p>

<p>.1 
3.7 
2.2 
14.7 
11.8 
1.6 
4.3 
29.0 
17.7 </p>

<p>Prior visits with HIV RNA level of .4000 copies/mL 
a &lt;6 
5.7 
6.0 &lt;.01 
24.3 
22.6 
.08 
3.3 
5.6 
.30 
35.4 
19.4 
.74 </p>

<p>.6 
11.2 
9.7 
32.3 
20.2 
2.0 
6.3 
36.3 
23.3 </p>

<p>HIV RNA, copies/mL 
&lt;4000 
9.0 
9.4 &lt;.01 
25.5 
14.7 &lt;.01 
5.4 
6.7 
.56 
35.6 
14.6 
.98 </p>

<p>4000-60,000 
14.6 
10.3 
38.5 
16.6 
8.9 
16.6 
35.4 
14.0 </p>

<p>&gt;60,000 
17.7 
13.7 
40.7 
17.5 
3.4 
3.7 
34.3 
12.4 </p>

<p>PI use </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Never 
8.6 
8.5 
.40 
33.5 
21.3 
.18 
3.3 
5.0 
.81 
38.3 
15.9 
.51 </p>

<p>&lt;3.3 years 
7.7 
15.3 
26.4 
23.3 
2.1 
7.2 
33.1 
18.4 </p>

<p>.3.3 years 
7.3 
7.9 
27.1 
23.9 
2.9 
6.3 
33.5 
27.1 </p>

<p>NRTI use </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Never 
6.6 
5.8 
.46 
29.9 
10.9 
.52 
4.5 
5.3 
.63 
42.8 
20.8 
.62 </p>

<p>&lt;6.1 years 
9.4 
14.7 
32.4 
33.8 
2.3 
6.7 
36.6 
16.8 </p>

<p>.6.1 years 
7.3 
7.5 
27.1 
24.4 
2.6 
6.2 
33.6 
25.2 </p>

<p>NNRTI use </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Never 
7.3 
7.0 
.47 
29.3 
20.8 
.93 
3.3 
6.7 
.42 
33.5 
20.8 
.87 </p>

<p>&lt;1.9 years 
9.5 
10.4 
27.1 
16.0 
2.3 
4.2 
37.4 
23.3 </p>

<p>.1.9 years 
7.1 
8.3 
29.6 
32.3 
2.2 
5.1 
35.5 
18.4 </p>

<p>Abacavir use 
Yes 
8.1 
7.3 
.99 
27.1 
20.9 
.31 
2.1 
4.4 
.24 
30.7 
23.4 
.54 </p>

<p>No 
7.4 
10.6 
30.2 
23.5 
2.6 
5.9 
36.6 
21.7 </p>

<p>Adherence to antiretroviral medications 
Yes 
6.9 
8.2 
.06 
22.6 
26.8 
.45 
2.3 
5.9 
.73 
32.8 
15.8 
.28 
No 
11.6 
7.8 
29.3 
14.8 
2.9 
5.0 
42.5 
23.4 </p>

<p>Race/ethnicity 
African American 
4.0 
4.2 
.01 
24.8 
15.8 
.03 
.6 
4.6 
.05 
38.6 
16.5 
.02 </p>

<p>Hispanic 
9.5 
13.1 
36.7 
29.3 
3.8 
8.4 
38.4 
17.3 </p>

<p>White or other 
7.8 
8.6 
28.9 
21.7 
2.0 
6.1 
31.9 
19.1 </p>

<p>Smoking 
Current 
7.5 
9.1 
.79 
27.4 
19.1 
.54 
2.1 
5.9 
.22 
31.8 
17.8 
&lt;.01 
Past 
7.9 
10.0 
32.8 
27.3 
4.0 
5.0 
40.6 
19.7 </p>

<p>Never 
7.5 
10.4 
24.9 
31.6 
1.5 
6.3 
35.8 
20.7 </p>



<p>Table 2. (Continued) </p>

<p>Percentage of CD4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD38 
1 DR 
1 T cells </p>

<p>Percentage of CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD38 
1 DR 
1 T cells </p>

<p>Percentage of CD4 
1 CD28 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CD57 
1 T cells </p>

<p>Percentage of CD8 
1 CD28 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CD57 
1 T cells </p>

<p>Variable 
Median 
IQR 
P 
Median IQR 
P 
Median 
IQR 
P 
Median 
IQR 
P </p>

<p>Hepatitis C 
Yes 
7.5 
8.5 
.99 
28.2 
17.0 
.61 
2.0 
5.1 
.23 
36.8 
23.6 
.87 
No 
7.9 
11.3 
30.9 
30.0 
3.1 
6.6 
35.5 
19.4 </p>

<p>Hypertension 
Yes 
7.5 
12.1 
.24 
27.6 
26.2 
.86 
2.0 
4.8 
.88 
37.3 
24.5 
.71 </p>

<p>No 
7.9 
7.6 
30.3 
22.2 
2.8 
6.7 
34.3 
17.0 </p>

<p>Diabetes 
Yes 
7.7 
10.4 
.43 
23.2 
15.0 
.13 
1.6 
6.0 
.37 
33.6 
18.7 
.32 </p>

<p>No 
7.4 
8.9 
30.2 
23.7 
2.4 
5.7 
35.6 
21.6 </p>

<p>BMI 
,25 
7.5 
6.9 
.20 
30.3 
24.1 
.41 
2.8 
6.2 
.25 
32.3 
19.6 
.66 </p>

<p>25-30 
9.8 
10.8 
28.1 
22.3 
1.9 
4.3 
36.8 
24.7 </p>

<p>.30 
6.4 
9.7 
27.6 
28.6 
4.7 
6.5 
37.2 
15.2 
Diabetes medication use 
Yes 
13.2 
18.4 
.35 
26.1 
21.8 
.79 
4.3 
8.3 
.99 
31.1 
28.5 
.75 </p>

<p>No 
7.7 
9.0 
29.3 
26.0 
2.4 
5.9 
36.0 
21.1 </p>

<p>Lipid-lowering drug use 
Yes 
6.2 
6.2 
.07 
19.7 
18.8 
.08 
6.7 
2.9 
.05 
33.9 
11.2 
.70 </p>

<p>No 
7.9 
10.6 
29.1 
23.2 
2.3 
5.6 
36.3 
22.9 </p>

<p>Family History of CAD 
Yes 
7.3 
8.4 
.69 
29.5 
15.3 
.70 
1.9 
5.6 
.87 
43.2 
15.5 
.13 </p>

<p>No 
7.9 
9.2 
28.2 
21.9 
2.7 
6.3 
33.5 
19.6 </p>

<p>HDL-C level, mg/dL 
,40 
9.6 
10.4 
.07 
36.7 
28.1 &lt;.01 
1.6 
4.9 
.09 
38.4 
21.4 
.03 </p>

<p>&gt;40 
6.2 
8.6 
25.7 
22.2 
3.5 
6.2 
32.6 
19.6 
LDL-C level, mg/dL 
&lt;160 
7.4 
10.7 
.87 
29.1 
24.3 
.17 
2.6 
5.9 
.69 
36.3 
21.6 
.33 </p>

<p>.160 
9.5 
7.8 
12.8 
24.6 
2.3 
8.2 
31.1 
28.3 </p>

<p>Weight, kg </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>&lt;73 
9.0 
12.0 
.24 
30.3 
24.5 
.10 
2.0 
5.0 
.05 
34.3 
25.4 
.52 </p>

<p>.73 
6.5 
9.2 
27.4 
21.3 
3.3 
6.1 
37.2 
17.9 </p>

<p>NOTE. P values were derived using the (nonparametric) Wilcoxon and Kruskal-Wallis tests. BMI, body mass index; CAD, coronary artery disease; HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; IQR, interquartile range; 
LDL-C, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol; NNRTI, nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor; NRTI, nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor; PI, protease inhibitor. 
a Values presented represent those above or below the median value. For use of antiretroviral medication, categories were defined as never and 2 categories of ever use with total observed duration of use either below 
or above the median duration in the drug user group. </p>

<p>Kaplan T Cell Activation and Subclinical CVD d JID 2011:203 (15 February) d 459 </p>

<p>lesions. When mutually adjusted in the same model, the prev-
alence ratio lesions for each SD change in the percentage of 
CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD38 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>HLA-DR 
1 T cells was 1.9 (95% CI, 1.1-3.2; P 5 </p>

<p>.02), and the prevalence ratio lesions for each SD change in the </p>

<p>percentage of CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD28 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CD57 
1 T cells was 1.6 (95% CI, .9-</p>

<p>2.8; P 5 .09). 
We also examined CD4 
1 and CD8 
1 T cell activation simul-</p>

<p>taneously in relation to carotid lesions. When entered into </p>

<p>Figure 3. T-cell activation (CD38 
1 HLA-DR 
1 ) and senescence (CD28 
2 CD57 
1 ) in relation to carotid lesions. Among human immunodeficiency virus 
(HIV)-infected women, higher CD4 
1 CD38 
1 HLA-DR 
1 T cell frequency (P 5 .02) and higher CD8 
1 CD38 
1 HLA-DR 
1 T cell frequency (P 5 .04) were 
observed among 19 women with carotid lesions than among 96 women without carotid lesions. Similarly, among HIV-infected women, 
CD8 
1 CD28 
2 CD57 
1 T cell frequency was higher among those with carotid lesions than among those without carotid lesions (P 5 .03). No significant 
difference in CD4 
1 CD28 
2 CD57 
1 T cell frequency was observed in comparing HIV-infected women with and without lesions. Among 43 HIV-uninfected 
women, none of these T cell parameters differed according to the presence or absence of carotid lesions. P values were computed using the Kruskal-
Wallis test. </p>

<p>Table 3. Multivariate Associations of T Cell Activation and Senescence Markers With Subclinical Carotid Artery Disease Among 
Women With Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) Infection </p>

<p>Adjusted for age and current use of antiretroviral medications 
Also adjusted for HIV RNA level </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Effect 
estimate </p>

<p>95% confidence 
interval 
P </p>

<p>Effect 
estimate </p>

<p>95% confidence 
interval 
P </p>

<p>PR lesions for each SD increase 
in T cell marker </p>

<p>CD4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD38 
1 HLA-DR 
1 T cells 
1.6 
1.1-2.2 
.02 
1.6 
1.1-2.3 
.02 </p>

<p>CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD38 
1 HLA-DR 
1 T cells 
2.0 
1.2-3.3 
&lt;.01 
2.0 
1.2-3.3 
&lt;.01 
CD4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD28 
2 CD57 
1 T cells 
1.1 
.8-1.6 
.64 
1.1 
.8-1.6 
.61 </p>

<p>CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD28 
2 CD57 
1 T cells 
1.9 
1.1-3.1 
.01 
1.9 
1.1-3.1 
.01 </p>

<p>Increase in cIMT for each SD 
increase in T cell marker </p>

<p>CD4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD38 
1 HLA-DR 
1 T cells 
.001 
2.019 to .019 
.96 
.001 
2.019 to .021 
.92 </p>

<p>CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD38 
1 HLA-DR 
1 T cells 
2.002 
2.022 to .018 
.81 
2.002 
2.023 to .019 
.85 </p>

<p>CD4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD28 
2 CD57 
1 T cells 
.003 
2.016 to .022 
.74 
.003 
2.017 to .024 
.74 </p>

<p>CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD28 
2 CD57 
1 T cells 
2.006 
2.026 to .014 
.57 
2.006 
2.027 to .015 
.58 </p>

<p>NOTE. Measures of T cell activation and T cell senescence were log-transformed. The text describes results after adjustment for CD4 
1 T cell count and ratio of 
CD4 
1 T cells to CD8 
1 T-cells. Additional adjustment for participant characteristics described in Table 1 did not change the results substantially. cIMT, carotid intima-
media thickness of the right common carotid artery; PR lesions , prevalence ratio for carotid lesions. </p>



<p>a single model, CD8 
1 T cell activation remained significantly </p>

<p>associated with prevalence of carotid lesions (prevalence 
ratio lesions , 1.8; 95% CI, 1.0-3.3; P 5 .05), whereas CD4 
1 T cell </p>

<p>activation did not (prevalence ratio lesions , 1.2; 95% CI, .7-1.8; 
P 5 .54). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>HIV-infected individuals have an increased risk of CVD, and 
effective HIV therapy appears to improve CVD risk. We report 
several findings that suggest possible explanatory mechanisms 
for the association between HIV infection and vascular disease. 
First, consistent with prior data [6], HIV infection was associ-
ated with markedly elevated levels of activated (CD38 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>HLA-
DR </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>) peripheral T cells. Viremic suppression through effective 
antiretroviral therapy appeared to reduce but not completely 
reverse this process. Second, among HIV-infected women, T cell 
activation was associated with markers of subclinical carotid 
artery disease after adjustment for multiple confounders. Third, 
CD8 
1 T cell senescence (phenotypically defined by absence of </p>

<p>CD28 and presence of CD57) was also elevated in women with 
HIV disease, and the frequency of these cells was associated with 
subclinical carotid artery disease among HIV-infected women. 
Finally, these associations of T cell activation and senescence 
with carotid artery parameters were not observed in a pop-
ulation of HIV-uninfected controls who were studied using 
identical methods and who had comparable cardiovascular risk 
factor profiles. Collectively, these observations are consistent 
with a model in which HIV infection results in immune acti-
vation, accelerated immunologic aging, and the premature onset 
of CVD. Effective HIV treatment reduces but may not fully 
reverse this process. 
The ultrasound protocol used in this study was designed to 
capture several different carotid artery parameters. Among HIV-
infected women, T cell activation and senescence were associated 
with the presence of carotid lesions, defined as focal thickening 
(.1.5 mm) of the intima-media layer. These lesions typically 
form at branch points in the internal carotid artery and the 
carotid bifurcation, where turbulent blood flow evokes elabo-
ration of vascular cellular adhesion molecule-1 and other in-
flammatory mediators [13]. In contrast, we found no 
association between T cell activation and mean cIMT of the 
common carotid artery, a region that is not prone to the de-
velopment of symptomatic lesions. Longitudinal data show that 
common carotid artery wall thickness progresses more rapidly in 
patients with HIV infection who have poor viral control [14], 
although some prior studies have shown a stronger association 
of HIV disease with lesions in the internal carotid artery and 
carotid bifurcation than with common carotid artery thickness 
[15]. We speculate on potential explanations for these ob-
servations. Because of regional hemodynamics, the internal and 
bifurcation regions of the carotid may be more prone to the </p>

<p>development of inflammation-related vascular lesions. Patients 
with other inflammatory conditions such as rheumatoid ar-
thritis and systemic lupus erythematosus also appear to have 
normal common carotid cIMT but increased prevalence of ca-
rotid artery lesions [16, 17]. Alternatively, localized infection of 
vascular tissues by HIV [18] or other pathogens might produce 
focal lesions in the absence of generalized carotid artery wall 
thickening. It remains unclear whether the observed differences 
across carotid segments are biologically important or due to 
technical aspects of our cross-sectional imaging protocol. 
Although we lacked data on the coronary vasculature, a recent 
report demonstrated a high prevalence of obstructive coronary 
artery lesions among HIV-infected adults (6.5% vs 0% in con-
trols) who had no known history or symptoms of coronary 
disease [19]. 
Multivariate analyses appeared to suggest that CD8 
1 T cell </p>

<p>activation had the more robust association with carotid lesions 
when both CD4 
1 and CD8 
1 T cell activation were modeled </p>

<p>simultaneously. Mouse models of atherosclerosis (eg, low-
density lipoprotein receptor knockout [LDLR </p>

<p>2/2 </p>

<p>] mice and 
apolipoprotein E knockout [ApoE </p>

<p>2/2 </p>

<p>] mice) have more clearly 
implicated CD4 
1 T cells than CD8 
1 T cells in atherogenesis [8]. </p>

<p>However, as recently hypothesized by Andersson and colleagues 
[8], CD8 
1 T cells may become atherogenic in response to in-</p>

<p>tracellular infections even if they are not involved in athero-
genesis in normal circumstances. Notably, comparisons of our 
HIV-infected women with an HIV-uninfected control group 
suggested a weaker or null association of T cell activation with 
subclinical carotid artery disease in the absence of HIV infection. 
This may suggest that direct vascular effects of pathogens affecting 
HIV-infected individuals, or perhaps HIV itself, contributed to 
the association of immune activation with subclinical carotid 
artery disease in the HIV-infected group. Alternatively, the lack of 
significant findings in the HIV-uninfected controls may reflect 
a threshold of immune activation that is required to demonstrate 
an association with carotid wall thickness. It should be noted that 
although the percentage of activated CD4 cells was increased 
among patients with HIV infection, the absolute number of pe-
ripheral T cells may be reduced in HIV infection, and moreover, 
these measurements only reflect cells circulating in blood [20]. 
The mechanism whereby HIV causes increased inflammation 
and T cell activation is an active area of investigation and has 
important clinical implications for preventing HIV-related in-
fectious and noninfectious (eg, cardiovascular) morbidity. The 
degree of inflammation and immune activation is thought to be 
too high to be simply due to expansion of HIV-specific T cells. 
HIV infected persons are often co-infected with other patho-
gens, including CMV and the hepatitis viruses. Recent work by 
our group suggests that CMV may be an important cause of 
T cell changes in HIV disease, which is of interest given our 
previous findings that high levels of CMV-specific T cells are 
associated with increased cIMT [21]. HIV infection results in </p>

<p>Kaplan T Cell Activation and Subclinical CVD d JID 2011:203 (15 February) d 461 </p>

<p>dramatic changes to the gut mucosa, which appears to result in 
increased translocation of microbial products from the gut lu-
men into the systemic circulation. These changes may increase 
immune activation and potentially trigger inflammatory and 
procoagulant mechanisms that increase vascular risk [22]. Finally, 
irreversible changes in the lymphoid infrastructure-including 
collagen deposition in lymphatic tissues and loss of thymic 
function-may also contribute to the inflammatory environment 
that exists in HIV disease [23]. 
Immunosenescence is defined as the gradual age-related de-
cline in immune function that contributes to vaccine un-
responsiveness and other sequelae among the elderly. Although 
multiple perturbations to the adaptive and nonadaptive im-
mune system have been reported, the strongest and most con-
sistent correlates of immunosenescence include the oligoclonal 
expansion of memory effector CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD28 
2 T cells and the </p>

<p>expansion of CD57-expressing CD8 
1 T cells. These CD28 
2 cells </p>

<p>have limited ability to proliferate and are apoptosis-resistant 
[24]. Similar observations are emerging with regard to CD4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>T cells, which also appear to become more oligoclonal and less 
functional with age, particularly among CMV seropositive per-
sons [9]. As shown elsewhere and confirmed here, untreated 
HIV infection appears to result in expansion of phenotypically 
defined immunosenescent T cells. Importantly, we also show 
that the process of CD8 
1 T cell immunosenescence is not re-</p>

<p>versed by effective antiretroviral therapy. We further showed 
that HIV-associated changes in the immunosenescent profile of 
circulating T cells predicted increased frequency of carotid 
lesions. This is a novel finding that is consistent with a growing 
body of evidence. Enriched numbers of CD28 
2 T cells are found </p>

<p>in atherosclerotic plaques [25]. In patients with coronary dis-
ease, CMV infection contributes to loss of CD28 and telomeric 
shortening in CD8 
1 T cells, which in turn predicts cardiac </p>

<p>dysfunction [11]. CD4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD28 
2 T cells that recognize heat-shock </p>

<p>protein 60, an antigen that triggers atherosclerosis in animal 
models, have been implicated in severity and prognosis of cor-
onary disease [26, 27]. However, the present study of HIV-
infected women implicated CD8 
1 T cell senescence but not </p>

<p>CD4 
1 T cell senescence in subclinical atherosclerosis. Our data </p>

<p>support the emerging hypothesis that T cell subsets expressing 
markers of immunosenescence and terminal differentiation may 
be CVD mediators. 
Limitations of the present study include its observational 
study design and the measurement of immune activation and 
senescence at a single study visit. Use of HIV medications was 
not guided by our research protocol. However, we were able to 
control for detailed, prospectively collected longitudinal in-
formation on medication history [12]. The HIV-uninfected 
control group was relatively modest in size. Information on 
duration of HIV infection was lacking. We did not measure 
serum biomarkers of inflammatory mediators such as in-
terleukin 6, although we previously reported as part of the WIHS </p>

<p>that C-reactive protein did not predict carotid atherosclerosis 
among HIV-infected women independently of other clinical risk 
factors [28]. Although the measures of subclinical vascular dis-
ease used in this investigation predict incident CVD events in 
the general population, no studies have validated this assump-
tion in the HIV-infected population, and too few events are 
available in our cohort to test this assumption. 
In conclusion, our data provide further evidence that per-
sistent activation of the immune system is associated with vas-
cular abnormalities among HIV-infected individuals. This 
relationship was suggested by a small prior study that, unlike the 
present investigation, did not feature multivariate analyses, did 
not control for potential confounding effects of HIV-related and 
CVD-related variables, and lacked an HIV-uninfected control 
group [29]. These results have important implications for as-
sessment of vascular risk among adults with HIV infection. 
Additional research is needed to identify the events or exposures 
in HIV-infected adults that may drive T cell activation and se-
nescence (including immune responses to HIV, co-infections, or 
bacterial translocation) and, in turn, increase vascular risk. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by the National Institute of Allergy and In-
fectious Diseases, National Institutes of Health (grant numbers UO1-AI-
35004, UO1-AI-31834, UO1-AI-34994, UO1-AI-34989, UO1-AI-34993, 
UO1-AI-42590; grant P30AI027763 to University of California, San 
Francisco-Gladstone Institute of Virology and Immunology Center for 
AIDS Research); the National Institute of Child Health and Human 
Development (grant number UO1-HD-32632); the National Cancer 
Institute; the National Institute on Drug Abuse; the National Institute on 
Deafness and Other Communication Disorders; the National Center for 
Research Resources (grant number UL1 RR024131 to the University of 
California, San Francisco, Clinical and Translational Science Institute); and 
the National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute (grant numbers 
1R01HL095140, 1R01HL083760 to Albert Einstein College of Medicine). </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Women's Interagency HIV Study Collaborative Study Group centers 
(Principal Investigators) are as follows: New York City/Bronx Consortium 
(Kathryn Anastos); Brooklyn, NY (Howard Minkoff); Washington, DC, 
Metropolitan Consortium (Mary Young); The Connie Wofsy Study Con-
sortium of Northern California (Ruth Greenblatt); Los Angeles County/ 
Southern California Consortium (Alexandra Levine); Chicago Consortium 
(Mardge Cohen); and Data Coordinating Center (Stephen Gange). </p>







<p>Kaplan T Cell Activation and Subclinical CVD d JID 2011:203 (15 February) d 463 </p>

</text></tei>