<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3370925" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Chimerism is the presence in a host of genetically distinct cells 
that originated from another individual. 
1 Its existence has clearly 
been demonstrated in multiple fields such as hematopoietic stem 
cell 
2 or solid organ transplantation, 
3 non-depleted blood trans-
fusions 
4 and the most common form which is bidirectional 
maternal-fetal cell trafficking whereby cells from the fetus pass 
through the placenta and establish durable cell lineages within 
the mother. By delving a little deeper into this last topic, one 
can notice that normal fetal development directly correlates with 
previous and concomitant growth of the placenta. Placental 
development starts with trophoblast differentiation from tropho-
ectoderm, a key factor for implantation (which begins from the 
sixth day after fertilization). </p>

<p>5   Extravillous cytotrophoblastic cells literally invade the decidua 
basalis to form the fetal-maternal interface. Trophoblastic-derived 
cells enzymatically digest the maternal endometrium and even 
myometrium in a hypoxia to normoxia gradient, 
5 leading to 
constrained bleeding that forms numerous blood-filled lacunae. 
Extravillous infiltrating trophoblasts actively remodel maternal 
spiral afferent arteries resulting in a significant increase of vessel 
diameter (up to 10-fold) and a reduction of blood flow pressure, 
in order to assure enough blood provision for ongoing fetal 
requirements. 
6 Villous trophoblasts are responsible for chorionic 
villi formation, which augment the surface of contact allowing for 
an extensive and controlled nutrient and gas exchange between 
oxygen's high-avidity fetal erythrocytes and maternal blood in the 
intervillous space. Taking into account all the above-mentioned 
characteristics, it is reasonable to conclude that allogeneic cells are 
in very close contact during the fetal development process. Many </p>

<p>of the immunological hypo-reactivity mechanisms orchestrated 
in part by trophoblast and its derived cells have been described 
elsewhere, 
7,8 even though this tolerant state must live with a 
certain degree of inflammatory responses, thus enabling both 
blood flow increase and trophoblast invasion. The maintenance 
of this acquired tolerance in both the mother and the progeny 
has been studied, and persistent microchimerism is common </p>

<p>9   in the context of autoimmune diseases 
10,11 and even in tissue 
regeneration. </p>

<p>12   Our previous experimental background on the use of different 
stem cell sources 
13,14 has focused on studying immunological 
reactivity of newly implanted allogeneic cells used to regenerate 
cardiac damaged tissue. In order to graphically illustrate an early 
natural allogeneic contact that initiates the journey of a child's 
cells (in this case a son's cells) within the mother's blood and 
other tissues, we used a new procedure in microscopy imaging 
generating large scale panoramic pictures (LSPP). Unique aspects 
of the LSPP technique are that it provides high definition pictures 
covering large areas and permits a global contextualization of 
targeted zones or cells. </p>

<p>Results and Discussion </p>

<p>Using this novel imaging procedure, we composed an LSPP 
(Fig. 1A) covering a macroscopic area (rounding 1 mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) of the 
maternal decidua basalis surrounded by invasive fetal villi 
(Fig. 1B). Surprisingly, autofluorescence of extra-cellular matrix 
components within red and green channels helped in imaging 
global tissue structures without interfering with expected FISH 
probes fluorescence. As expected, the decidua contained maternal 
cells organized within the endometrial tissue (XX, nuclei showing </p>

<p>*Correspondence to: Antoni Bayes-Genis; Email: abayesgenis@gmail.com 
Submitted: 10/10/11; Revised: 01/04/12; Accepted: 01/20/12 
http://dx.doi.org/10.4161/chim.19439 </p>

<p>Chimerism 3:1, 18-20; January/February/March 2012; G 2012 Landes Bioscience </p>

<p> 
Chimerism 
Volume 3 Issue 1 </p>

<p>© 2012 Landes Bioscience. </p>

<p>Do not distribute. </p>

<p>two green dots) surrounded by fetal structures (cells containing 
one green "X" dot and one red "Y" dot within the same nucleus 
in Fig. 1B and C), suggesting a maternal micro-septum (Fig. 1B). 
It is also frequent to find in the placenta, fetal-derived structures 
infiltrating maternal tissues as shown with white arrows in 
Figure 1B, and even at the cell level as shown in Figure 1D 
and E. Figure 1F illustrates the presence of two distinct adjacent 
allogeneic cells from the mother and the baby at the fetal-maternal 
interface. After observing the exposed LSPP, it is reasonable to 
consider that fetal cells can easily be transferred and circulate </p>

<p>within maternal blood either because cells can migrate from 
villi or simply due to infiltrating cells. The question of how 
immunogenic processes of alloresponse have been altered can 
consequently be addressed. In other words, a deeper understand-
ing of this "nonaggression pact" at the fetal-maternal interface, in 
which two genetically distinct cell lineages coexist, may improve 
the options to mimic this procedure in transplantation, auto-
immunity and regenerative medicine using allogeneic sources. 
In summary, here we visualize the classic concept of chimerism 
by generating newly panoramic images of human placental </p>

<p>Figure 1. (A) LSPP were constructed using MosaiX (authorizing 10% of overlapping), Zstacking with focus correction for each quadrant, Stitching frames 
algorithm and Extended Focus functions from AxioVision v4.8.2 software. (B) Example of a resulting LSPP of the decidua basalis of a human placenta 
covering an area of 0.78 mm 
2 with a resolution of 30.5 megapixels. Decidua basalis was parallel to the sectioning surface. The fetal-maternal interface is 
labeled with PNA-X (Spectrum Green, green) and PNA-Y (Spectrum Orange, red) chromosome-specific probes. FISH was used for sex-typing and Dapi for 
nuclear staining (blue). The dotted line-delimited zone is the maternal decidua. White arrows show direct invasion of fetal structures into maternal tissue. 
(C) Common natural maternal cell (XX) distribution within tissues of the decidua. (D and E) Dispersed infiltrating fetal-derived cells (XY) neighboring 
maternal cells. (F) Two adjacent cells of maternal and fetal origin. Scale bars: (A) 50 mm; (C) 20 mm; (D-F) 10 mm. </p>

<p>BRIEF REPORT </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com 
Chimerism </p>

<p>
© 2012 Landes Bioscience. </p>

<p>Do not distribute. </p>

<p>sections following simple dual fluorescence in situ hybridization 
labeling to co-localize male fetal and maternal cells. Since this 
process generates vast amounts of data requiring advanced 
computer technology, we believe that generation of LSPP may 
be advantageous to map and explore large extensions of tissue. 
Thus, this novel technique may be extended to a broad diversity 
of experimental models, such as the visualization of large post-
infarct border zones following implantation of regenerative stem-
cell embedded patches. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Placenta collection. Written consent was obtained from each 
participant after an explanation of the study, which was previously 
approved by the local ethics committee. All participants had no 
previous pregnancy to ensure no confounding due to cells from 
previous gestations. Approaching term but prior to the onset of 
labor, placentas of male sons were collected in sterile conditions 
during routine C-sections. Vaginal birth was not chosen for study 
to obviate the risk of contamination due to passage within the 
vaginal tract. All enrolled donors had no complications during 
pregnancy or C-section. 
FISH staining. Initial material was obtained from a transversal 
section of 10 mm 
2 quadrant base of a caesarean placenta initiated 
from the chorionic plate down to decidua materna, thus including 
amnios, chorionic plate and vessels, fetal villi expansions and 
decidua materna. Segments were fixed with 10% formalin, then 
included in paraffin-embedded blocks and 4 mm sections were </p>

<p>used for fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) using specific 
probes (Dako) labeled with Spectrum Green and Spectrum 
Orange for X and Y chromosome respectively, according to 
manufacturer's recommendation. Tissue sections were also counter-
stained with 4',6-diamidino-2phenylindole (DAPI) (Vysis). 
Image capture and processing. All FISH stained samples were 
analyzed under an Axio Observer Z1 fluorescence microscope 
(Zeiss). LSPP methodology included first, area localization by 
MosaiX module and subsequent focus correction for each deter-
mined quadrant with a 10% of image overlapping. For each 
quadrant, the number of depth slices was defined using Zstacking 
module. All quadrants were then joined with Stitching overlap-
ping algorithm. Finally, obtained frames were consecutively 
organized in one single picture with the Extended Focus 
module. All modules used are contained in <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Zeiss</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">AxioVision</rs> 
v<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4.8.2</rs> software. </p>

<p>Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest were disclosed. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors are grateful to the members of the Gynecology and 
Obstetrics Department of the University Hospital Germans Trias 
i Pujol and V. Guirao for the priceless contributions in fluo-
rescence microscopy imaging. We also thank the invaluable advice 
received during revision. A.B.-G. has full access to all of the data 
in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data 
and the accuracy of the data analysis. </p>



<p> 
Chimerism 
Volume 3 Issue 1 </p>

</text></tei>