<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3384331" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Archaeal viruses have been the subject of recent 
interest due to the diversity discovered in their 
virion architectures. Recently, a new group of haloar-
chaeal pleomorphic viruses has been discovered. 
Archaeal viruses described to date comprise a relatively 
small group of prokaryotic viruses (1). Despite the small 
number, it is apparent that they exhibit a variety of 
morphologies (1,2). Among only 34 crenarchaeal viruses 
described such unique virion morphologies as bottle-and 
droplet-shaped, ovoid or bacilliform can be encountered 
(1,2). Although most of the $50 euryarchaeal viruses 
described resemble bacteriophages (3,4), new types of 
viruses have also been discovered (3,5,6). This diversity </p>

<p>of archaeal viruses is encompassed in ten families and a 
few unclassified groups (1). 
As more archaeal viruses are isolated, characterized and 
sequenced, comparative genomic analysis becomes a fre-
quently used tool giving insights into the diversity and 
evolution of these viruses (4,7-10). Studies on fusello-
viruses, lipothrixviruses, tailed archaeal viruses and 
proviruses showed that, similarly to bacteriophages, 
these viruses have mosaic genomes composed of variable 
and conserved regions, parts of which are derived from a 
shared pool of genes (4,8-12). The gene pool of archaeal 
viruses largely comprises open reading frames (ORFs) 
having significant similarity only to ORFs of other 
archaeal viruses or cells, and ORFans (13,14), genes that 
lack homologues in other genomes (15). Lately, many 
structural and functional studies have been undertaken 
in attempts to characterize proteins encoded by archaeal 
viruses (16-18). As a result, novel protein folds and viral 
proteins self-assembling into structures with rare 
symmetry were discovered (17,18). 
In a recent study, 40 new haloarchaeal viruses were 
isolated and further studied (3). Here we focus on a 
group of haloarchaeal pleomorphic viruses, which 
includes two earlier described members Halorubrum pleo-
morphic virus 1 (HRPV-1) and Haloarcula hispanica pleo-
morphic virus 1 (HHPV-1) (6,19,20) and four new 
members Halorubrum sp. pleomorphic viruses 2, 3 and 6 
(HRPV-2, HRPV3 and HRPV-6) (3,21) and Haloge-
ometricum sp. pleomorphic virus 1 (HGPV-1) (3). These 
pleomorphic viruses have a narrow host range and, except 
for HHPV-1, all infect a host that originates from the 
same sample as the virus (3). Analyses of the pleomorphic 
virions showed that the HRPV-1 and HHPV-1 viral par-
ticles consist of a genome enveloped in a lipid membrane 
with two major structural proteins (6,20,22). The smaller 
major structural protein, VP3, is predicted to contain 
several transmembrane (TM) helices, and in HRPV-1 
it was shown to be membrane-associated (22). The larger 
major structural protein, VP4, is N-terminally processed, 
exposed to the viral surface and anchored to the </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +358 9 19159102; Fax: +358 9 19159098; Email:elina.roine@helsinki.fi </p>

<p>Published online 6 March 2012 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 12 5523-5534 
doi:10.1093/nar/gks215 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>membrane with a C-terminal TM domain (6,20,22,23). 
Thus, the VP4 proteins are predicted to be involved in 
receptor binding and fusion of the host and viral mem-
branes (6,20,22,23). In HRPV-1, a third structural protein, 
VP8, which is a putative P-loop NTPase, has been 
identified (6). Both HRPV-1 and HHPV-1 contain a pre-
dicted ORF encoding a putative rolling circle replication 
initiation protein (RCR Rep) (6,20,24). 
HRPV-1 has a 7048-nucleotide (nt)-long circular 
single-stranded DNA (ssDNA) genome, whereas the 
HHPV-1 genome is a 8082-bp long circular double-
stranded DNA (dsDNA) molecule (6,20). Despite 
different genome types, these two viruses share a set of 
homologous proteins and their genomes are collinear 
(20). Both viruses share a conserved cluster of two 
protein-coding genes and four predicted ORFs (6,20). 
Putative proviral elements containing an entire set of the 
HRPV-1 and HHPV-1 homologues have been identified in 
the sequenced genomes of Haloferax volcanii DS2 and 
Halomicrobium mukohataei DSM 12286, as well as in 
Haloferax lucentense plasmid pHK2 (20,23,25). Some 
homologues were found in haloarchaeal virus His2 
(6,20). His2 virus has a linear 16 067-bp long dsDNA 
genome with inverted terminal repeats and with terminal 
proteins attached to 5 
0 termini (5,26). 
Here we report the genome sequences of the four new 
haloarchaeal pleomorphic viruses HRPV-2, HRPV-3, 
HRPV-6 and HGPV-1. The genomes of HRPV-3 and 
HGPV-1 are shown to be circular dsDNA molecules 
with localized single-strand interruptions. We present 
evidence for the discontinuous nature of HRPV-3 and 
HGPV-1 genomes and describe the interruptions in the 
HRPV-3 genome in more detail. Comparative genomic 
analysis of the expanded set of haloarchaeal pleomorphic 
viruses and related putative proviral regions confirms the 
presence of the conserved cluster of identified and putative 
genes also found in the linear dsDNA genome of His2, a 
previously described haloarchaeal virus (5). In parallel 
study (21), His2, which is currently classified as a 
spindle-shaped virus (5), is suggested to belong to the 
group of haloarchaeal pleomorphic viruses on the basis 
of the virion architecture. The comparative genomic 
analysis reported in this work supports this proposal 
and further shows that these pleomorphic viruses can be 
divided into three subgroups according to their gene 
content and genome organization. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Strains, culture conditions and stock solutions </p>

<p>Viruses and host strains used in this study are listed in 
Supplementary Table S1. For the modified growth 
medium (MGM) (27) used for the culture of all the host 
strains and viruses, the 30% artificial saltwater stock 
solution (SW) was diluted to 23% (MGM broth), 20% 
(MGM plates) or 18% (top layer agar) as described 
in the online resource-The HaloHandbook (http://www 
.haloarchaea.com/resources/halohandbook/index.html). 
Agar concentration of 1.4% for plates and 0.4% for 
the top layer agar was used. Viruses were propagated </p>

<p>and '2Â' purified from the lysates according to the 
protocol described in Atanasova and others (3). </p>

<p>Purification and analysis of the genomes </p>

<p>Viral genomic DNA was obtained from 2Â purified virus 
preparation by the phenol-chloroform extraction method 
as described previously (20). Shortly, 2Â purified viruses 
were diluted 1:10 or 1:20 in solution containing final con-
centrations of 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 1% (w/v) SDS, 
10 mM EDTA (pH 8.0) and 100-200 mM NaCl. 
Proteinase K (0.5 mg/ml) was added and the solution 
was incubated at +55 
C for 20 min. The solution was 
extracted with phenol and phenol-chloroform. DNA 
was precipitated from the final water phase with two 
volumes of ethanol in the presence of 0.2 M NaCl. 
The genomes were digested with DNase I (1 U of RQ1 
RNase-Free 
DNase/1 mg 
of 
genomic 
nucleic 
acid; Promega), Exonuclease I (20 U/1 mg of genome; 
Fermentas) and RNase A (4 mg/1 mg of genome; 
Promega). Mung Bean Nuclease (MBN, Promega) 
digests were done in 10 ml reactions for 30 min at +37 
C 
using 0.025 U, 0.5 U or 5 U of per 1 mg of DNA. Phage 
jX174 ssDNA genome and its dsDNA replicative form 
RFII (New England Biolabs) were used as controls. 
HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 genomic DNA were incubated 
with Sulfolobus DNA polymerase IV (2 U/1 mg of DNA; 
New England Biolabs) in a reaction containing 1Â enzyme 
buffer and 0.4 mM dNTP. Reactions were carried out at 
+37 
C for 3 h. Ligation was done with T4 DNA ligase 
(Fermentas) as described by manufacturer. </p>

<p>DNA manipulations </p>

<p>For cloning of the MBN-resistant fragments, MBN 
digested DNA of HRPV-3 was purified using QIAquick 
PCR purification kit (Qiagen) and ligated into pJET1.2/ 
blunt vectors utilizing a CloneJET 
TM PCR Cloning Kit 
(Fermentas). Ligation mixtures were transformed to com-
petent E. coli DH5a cells, and plasmid-containing colonies 
were selected on LB-plates supplemented with ampicillin 
(final concentration 150 mg/ml). Transformed colonies 
were screened for the presence of inserts by colony PCR 
using pJET1.2 forward and reverse primers (Fermentas). 
Selected plasmids were purified with QIAprep Spin 
Miniprep Kit (Qiagen), and the inserts were sequenced 
using pJET1.2 forward and reverse primers (Fermentas). 
For the localization of the discontinuities in the 
HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 genomes, the free 3 
0 hydroxyl 
ends of genomic DNA were labelled with DIG-11-dUTP 
by terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase (TdT, 
Fermentas). Tailing reactions for 0.5-1 mg of genomic 
DNA were carried out in 1Â TdT buffer containing 
0.25 mM CoCl 2 , 0.02 mM DIG-11-dUTP, 0.1 mM dATP 
and 15 U of TdT (Fermentas). Reactions were incubated 
at +37 
C for 40 min. After the tailing, DNA was 
concentrated in Microcon centrifugal filters with 
Ultracel </p>

<p>Õ </p>

<p>YM-100 membrane (Millipore) and digested 
with restriction enzymes. The digested fragments were 
separated in 1% agarose/1ÂTBE gel and transferred to 
nylon membrane (GE Osmonics). The DIG-11-dUTPs 
incorporated in genomic fragments were detected using </p>



<p>anti-digoxigenin-AP conjugate (Roche) and CDP-Star 
substrate (Roche) as described by the manufacturer. </p>

<p>Sequencing and annotation of the genomes </p>

<p>The obtained viral genomic DNA was amplified using a 
GenomePhi kit (GE Healthcare) and used to make 
barcoded (10 bp) fragment libraries for 454 sequencing 
on a Genome Sequencer FLX Titanium (Roche/454 Life 
Science). The reads were assembled using the <rs id="software-15" type="software">gsAssembler</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-15" type="creator">Roche/454 Life Science</rs>). The coverage of the different 
genomes was 17Â for HRPV-2, 14Â for HRPV-3, 300Â 
for HRPV-6 and 300Â for HGPV-1. The obtained 
assembly was verified with PCR products that for 
HRPV-2, HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 covered the whole 
genome. The final genome sequences were obtained by 
sequencing these PCR products. For HRPV-6, several 
Sanger sequencing runs confirmed the initial assembly. 
The primers used for PCR and sequencing are listed in 
Supplementary Table S2. For the verification of the 
discontinuous regions, genomic DNA was used in 
sequencing reactions with primers, which are also listed 
in Supplementary Table S2. All sequencing reactions 
were carried out by using BigDye Termination 
Chemistry v. 3.1 and analysed on an ABI 3130 (Applied 
Biosystems). Sequencing reactions were purified with 
CleanSeq (Agencourt) using a Beckman NX 
p robot 
(Beckman Coulter). Sequences were assembled and 
edited using GAP4. The sequences were submitted to 
GenBank and can be found under the accession 
numbers JN882264 (HRPV-2), JN882265 (HRPV-3), 
JN882266 (HRPV-6) and JN882267 (HGPV-1). 
The genome sequences were annotated using 
<rs id="software-17" type="software">DNAMaster</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-17" type="url">http://cobamide2.bio.pitt.edu</rs>, 
<rs corresp="#software-17" type="version-number">version5.22.2</rs>), <rs type="software">pDRAW32</rs> and <rs id="software-19" type="software">GeneMark.hmm for Prokaryotes</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-19" type="version-number">version 2.8</rs>). Homologous nucleotide and protein se-
quences were searched for using <rs type="software">BLASTN</rs> and <rs type="software">BLASTP</rs> 
tools, respectively, (28) available at the National Center 
for Biotechnology Information (NCBI). Manually refined 
annotations were based on <rs type="software">GeneMark.hmm</rs> coding poten-
tial analysis, the obtained protein chemistry data and 
colinearity with previously annotated pleomorphic virus 
genomes (6,20). The properties of identified proteins and 
the products of putative ORFs were analysed using expert 
protein analysis system (EXPASY) proteomics tools. 
Isoelectric points and molecular masses were determined 
using <rs type="software">Compute pI/MW</rs> tool (29). The signal sequences for 
VP4-like proteins were predicted using <rs id="software-25" type="software">Signal P</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-25" type="version-number">version3.0</rs>) (30) and <rs type="software">TatFind Servers</rs> (31). Conserved protein sig-
nature sequences were determined using <rs type="software">InterProScan</rs> 
(32). Putative trans-membrane regions of proteins were 
additionally determined using combined predictions by 
<rs type="software">TMHMM</rs> tool (33) and <rs type="software">TMPred</rs> tool (34). Coiled-coil 
regions were predicted using Coil tool (35). Multiple 
sequence alignments were generated using <rs type="software">T-Coffee</rs> (36), 
<rs type="software">Muscle</rs> (37) and <rs type="software">Praline</rs> (38). Conserved DNA motifs in 
aligned nucleotide sequences (<rs type="software">T-Coffee</rs>) were visualized 
with <rs type="software">WebLogo</rs> (39). </p>

<p>Phylogenetic analyses </p>

<p>Pairwise identity percentages between amino acid sequ-
ences of identified or putative proteins were determined 
using <rs id="software-36" type="software">EMBOSS Needle tool</rs> at <rs corresp="#software-36" type="creator">EMBL-EBI</rs>. Protein 
sequences were aligned with <rs type="software">T-Coffee</rs> program, and 
conserved blocks for the phylogenetic analysis were 
selected using <rs type="software">Gblocks</rs> (40). The phylogeny was recon-
structed by maximum likelihood method using <rs type="software">phyml</rs> 
algorithm (41). Resulting trees were visualized in 
<rs id="software-40" type="software">Phylodendron</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-40" type="url">http://iubio.bio.indiana.edu/soft/molbio/java/apps/trees/</rs>/). </p>

<p>HPLC-DAD-MS analysis of DNA </p>

<p>DNA extracted from HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 was dissolved 
in 20 mM NH 4 OAc pH 5.3 and incubated for 5 h at 37 
C 
in the presence of 3 U nuclease P1 (Roche Diagnostics, 
Mannheim, Germany) per 100 mg DNA. Snake venom 
phosphodiesterase (Worthington, Lakewood, USA) was 
then added to a concentration of 0.06 U per 100 mg 
DNA, and the mixture was incubated at 37 
C for 
another 2 h. Finally to convert the resulting mixture of 
mononucleotides to free nucleosides, 1/10 vol of 
10 Â SAP buffer (Fermentas, St. Leon-Roth, Germany) 
was added, followed by 3/20 vol of H 2 O, and ¼ vol of 
Shrimp Alkaline Phosphatase (SAP stock at 1 U/ml; 
from Fermentas, St. Leon-Roth, Germany). The mixture 
was incubated for 1 h at 37 
C. Additionally a commercial 
oligomer containing deoxy-5-methyl-cytidine was digested 
and used as reference sample (rGrUrCrA[m5C] 
rGrCrGrGrGrArGrArCrCrGrGrGrGrUrUrCrGrArUr-
UrCrCrCrCrGrArCrGrGrGrGrArGrCrCrA, Iba, Go¨ttin 
gen, Germany). 
The digested DNA was analysed on an Agilent 1260 
series equipped with a diode array detector (DAD) and 
Triple Quadrupol mass spectrometer Agilent 6460. 
A Synergy Fusion RP column (4 mm particle size, 80 Å 
pore size, 250 mm length and 2 mm inner diameter) from 
Phenomenex (Aschaffenburg, Germany) with a guard 
column was used at 35 
C. The solvents consisted of 
5 mM ammonium acetate buffer adjusted to pH 5.3 
using acetic acid (solvent A) and pure acetonitrile 
(solvent B). The elution started with 100% solvent 
A followed by a linear gradient to 20% solvent B at 
10 min. Initial conditions were regenerated by rinsing 
with 100% solvent A for 7 min. The flow rate was 
0.5 ml/min. 
The effluent from the column was first measured 
photometrical at 254 nm by the DAD for later quantifica-
tion followed by the mass spectrometer equipped with an 
electrospray ion source (Agilent Jet Stream). ESI param-
eters were as follows: gas temperature 300 
C, Gas flow 5 l/ 
min, Nebulizer pressure 35 psi, Sheath gas temperature 
350 
C, Sheath gas flow 12 l/min, capillary voltage 
3500 V. The MS was operated in positive ion mode moni-
toring multiple fragmentation reactions (MRM mode) at 
previously optimized conditions. The transitions and re-
tention times used for identification of nucleosides can be 
found in Figure 4B. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 12 5525 </p>

<p>Quantification of modified nucleosides </p>

<p>For quantification of detected modified nucleosides, the 
UV traces at 254 nm monitored by the DAD were used. 
According to (42), the differences of extinction coefficients 
between methylated and unmethlyated nucleobases are 
negligible; hence, identical coefficients were used for quan-
tification of C versus mC and A versus mA, respectively. 
The area under the absorption peak (AA) of each nucleo-
side was used for calculation of relative amounts using the 
formula %mC = AA(mC)/(AA(mC)+AA(C)Â100% for 
mC and %mA = AA(mA)/(AA(mA)+AA(A)Â100% for 
mA, respectively. </p>

<p>Protein analyses </p>

<p>The protein composition of the virions was analysed by 
16% SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE). 
The N-terminal sequences of the structural proteins were 
determined in the Protein Chemistry Core Laboratory, 
Institute of Biotechnology, University of Helsinki, as 
described previously (43). 
For the analysis of glycan modifications, 5 mg of virion 
proteins were separated in 16% SDS-PAGE and stained 
using the Pro-Q Emerald 300 Glycoprotein Gel Stain Kit 
(Invitrogen) as described by the manufacturer. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>In addition to the haloarchaeal pleomorphic viruses 
HRPV-1 and HHPV-1 reported before (6,20), four new 
pleomorphic viruses HRPV-2, HRPV-3, HRPV-6 and 
HGPV-1 were isolated from diverse geographical loca-
tions (3,21). The characterization of their life cycles 
and particle architectures by both biochemical dissoci-
ation and cryo-EM is described elsewhere (21). The 
N-terminal sequences of the structural proteins identified 
in this study are listed in Table 1. The virions were shown 
to contain two major structural proteins homologous to 
VP3 and VP4 proteins in HRPV-1 virus (6,21), the 
genome of which is used as a reference in this article 
(Figure 1). The names of the homologues in different 
viruses are shown in Table 1, and they will be referred 
to as VP3-like and VP4-like proteins further in the text. 
Other HRPV-1 protein homologues will be referred to in a 
similar manner (VP8-like proteins, ORF6-like and 
ORF7-like products). Besides VP3-like and VP4-like 
proteins, HGPV-1 contains one additional major struc-
tural protein (21). All major structural proteins were 
analysed for glycan modifications using in-gel staining. </p>

<p>Among the major structural proteins of the new viral 
isolates, no glycan modifications were detected (data not 
shown). </p>

<p>Genomic features </p>

<p>The genome types (DNA/RNA, single-stranded/double-
stranded) were determined using the standard digestions 
of isolated genomes with DNase, RNase and MBN as 
described in the Materials and Methods and in the 
previous reports for HRPV-1 and HHPV-1 (6,20). The 
results summarized in Table 2 show that the pleomorphic 
viruses contain either single-stranded or double-stranded 
DNA genomes. The dsDNA genomes of HRPV-3 and 
HGPV-1, however, were digested into distinct fragments 
by MBN, indicating possible single-stranded regions in the 
genomes (see below). All genomes are circular molecules 
varying in length between 8000 and 11 000 nt (Table 2). 
The circularity of the HRPV-1 and HHPV-1 genomes 
was demonstrated earlier (6,20). HRPV-2 and HRPV-6 
genomes were shown to be circular by exonuclease I 
digestion (data not shown). Isoforms of HRPV-3 and 
HGPV-1 genomes were visualized in 2D agarose gel (44) 
(Supplementary Materials and Methods, Supplementary 
Figure S1). Analysis revealed the existence of two major 
isoforms, one of which was attributed to relaxed circular, 
whereas the other one to linear form. Based on the results, 
we suggest that HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 genomes are also 
circular. The GC percentages of the viral genome 
sequences are shown in Table 2. Putative double-strand 
origins of replication (dso) are reported in the Suppl-
ementary results and the Supplementary Table S3. 
Analyses of the promoter and Shine-Dalgarno (SD) 
sequences are described in the Supplementary results. 
At the nucleotide level, the genomes show similarity 
reaching up to 74% along relatively short stretches 
($400 nt). HRPV-2 and HRPV-6 genomes are an excep-
tion, as they seem to share high identity (up to 97%) over 
DNA regions up to 4000 nt (Figure 1). </p>

<p>The haloarchaeal pleomorphic viruses can be divided into 
three subgroups </p>

<p>The genomes were analysed and annotated as described in 
the Materials and Methods. The properties of the putative 
and identified proteins are shown in Supplementary 
Tables S4-S7. The start site for the linearized nucleotide 
sequence is either the start site of the predicted ORF 
encoding the putative replication initiation protein or in 
the cases of HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 the first predicted ORF 
transcribed in the same direction as the genes coding for 
the major structural proteins (Figure 1). 
Genomic comparison (Figure 1) showed that HRPV-1, 
HHPV-1 and haloarchaeal pleomorphic virus genomes 
reported in this study share a cluster of five conserved 
genes, starting with genes encoding the VP3-like proteins 
and ending with genes coding for the VP8-like proteins. 
These viruses, although related, can be divided into two 
subgroups according to their genome organization. The 
first subgroup contains viruses HRPV-1, HRPV-2, 
HRPV-6 and HHPV-1. The genomes of HRPV-2 and 
HRPV-6 conform to the gene order previously reported </p>

<p>Table 1. N-terminal sequences of the major structural proteins 
determined in this study </p>

<p>Virus 
VP3-like protein 
VP4-like protein </p>

<p>HRPV-2 
(VP4) ASSYRNSMGS . . . 
(VP5) IAPLVGVGLA . . . 
HRPV-3 
(VP1) ATSKLSGFAG . . . 
(VP2) LAPLIAGXFL . . . 
HRPV-6 
(VP4) ASSYRNS . . . 
(VP5) IAPLVGYA . . . 
HGPV-1 
n.d. 
(VP4) EFVNCDLS . . . </p>

<p>n.d. -not determined. </p>



<p>for HRPV-1 and HHPV-1. In these genomes, the first 
predicted open reading frame (ORF1) encodes a putative 
RCR Rep (24) and is located one or two ORFs upstream 
of the conserved cluster. 
HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 form the other subgroup of 
haloarchaeal pleomorphic viruses. The most notable dif-
ference of HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 genomes compared to 
the first subgroup is that they do not contain the homo-
logue of the replication initiation protein. These genomes 
are clearly divided into two regions that are transcribed in 
opposite directions. In addition to the conserved cluster, 
these two viruses share two ORFs, not found in the 
genomes of the first subgroup of viruses (Figure 1). 
The earlier reported His2 virus (5) has four homologues 
belonging to the conserved cluster of pleomorphic viral </p>

<p>genes. However, it cannot be included in either one of 
the subgroups and clearly forms a third subgroup, in 
which it is currently the only member. In addition to the 
conserved cluster of genes, His2 major structural protein 
VP27 is a putative homologue of HGPV-1 major struc-
tural protein VP3 (21) (Figure 1). These two proteins are 
not homologues of VP3-like proteins but were suggested 
to serve similar function (21). </p>

<p>Related genetic elements in haloarchaeal genomes </p>

<p>In addition to the already reported Hfx. lucentense 
plasmid pHK2 and proviral regions in Haloferax 
volcanii DS2 (region 2) (20) and Halomicrobium muko-
hataei DSM 12286 (region 2) (23), there are several 
putative proviral elements found in the sequenced 
genomes of different haloarchaeal species (Table 3, 
Supplementary Figure S2, Supplementary Results) that 
are related to the viruses described in this study. Based 
on the colinearity, putative proviral regions can also be 
assigned to above-mentioned viral subgroups. Hmc. 
mukohataei region 2, Hfx. volcanii region 2 and Hfx. 
lucentense plasmid pHK2 can be assigned to the first 
subgroup, and the rest fall into the second subgroup 
(Table 3). </p>

<p>Replication initiation proteins </p>

<p>The genomes of the first subgroup of viruses contain the 
ORF1 encoding the putative RCR Reps (24). Despite </p>

<p>Figure 1. Schematic genomic alignment of the haloarchaeal pleomorphic viruses HHPV-1, HRPV-6, HRPV-2, HRPV-1, HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 as 
linear representation and His2 (5) (GenBank accession no AF191797). HRPV-1 genome is used as a reference. Genes encoding VP3-like, VP4-like 
and VP8-like protein homologues are marked below the alignment of the genomes. Genes encoding structural proteins of HGPV-1 and His2 
determined by M.K. Pietila¨et al. (21) are denoted by asterisk. Percentages of identical amino acids in homologous putative polypeptides and 
proteins are indicated. Subgroups to which viruses were assigned according to genome organization are indicated on the right. </p>

<p>Table 2. Properties of the characterized genomes </p>

<p>Viral genome 
Size (nt/bp) 
ssDNA/dsDNA 
GC% </p>

<p>HRPV-1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>7048 
ssDNA 
54.2% 
HHPV-1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>8082 
dsDNA 
55.8% 
HRPV-2 
10 656 
ssDNA 
63.7% 
HRPV-3 
8770 
dsDNA 
58.3% 
HRPV-6 
8549 
ssDNA 
62.7% 
HGPV-1 
9694 
dsDNA 
61.6% </p>

<p>a GenBank accession no FJ685651, (6). </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>GenBank accession no GU321093, (20). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 12 5527 </p>

<p>almost 100% identity between Reps of HRPV-2 and 
HRPV-6, our data confirm that replication initiation 
proteins are more diverged than other parts of the 
haloarchaeal pleomorphic virus genomes (20). As 
described in the Supplementary Results, the multiple 
sequence alignment suggested that the putative Rep 
proteins of the viruses and their homologues from the 
proviral elements could be divided into two clusters. </p>

<p>The conserved cluster of putative and identified genes </p>

<p>The first protein encoded by a conserved cluster of genes is 
VP3-like protein (Figure 1). It is a major structural protein 
of haloarchaeal pleomorphic viruses, predicted to contain 
several transmembrane regions. VP3-like proteins of the 
first subgroup of viruses and putative proviruses share 
extensive identity at the amino acid level ($50% and 
above, Supplementary Figure S3). In contrast, VP3-like 
proteins of the second subgroup show only $20% 
identity to each other and to homologues of the first 
subgroup members. 
The next protein encoded in the conserved cluster of 
genes is VP4-like major structural protein (Figure 1), 
forming the spike structure on the virion surface. This 
protein is processed during maturation. In order to 
predict the translation start site, the empirically deter-
mined N-termini (Table 1) together with <rs type="software">Signal P</rs> and 
<rs type="software">Tat find</rs> programs were used. Three of the manually 
annotated VP4-like protein precursors were predicted to 
have a twin-arginine signal sequence suggesting export of 
the protein in a folded state. Most of the VP4-like protein 
precursors share only $20% identity (Supplementary 
Table S8). Even though VP4-like polypeptides are much 
more diverse than VP3-like proteins, the secondary struc-
tures are predicted to be similar. All of them are also pre-
dicted to contain a coiled-coil region in the C-terminus of 
the protein just preceding the transmembrane domain that 
serves as a membrane anchor. 
The following members of the conserved cluster are 
ORF6-like and ORF7-like putative genes (Figure 1), 
encoding products of unknown function. Both of the 
putative proteins are predicted to have transmembrane 
domains. Putative ORF6-like gene products show rather 
low conservation among haloarchaeal viruses and proviral </p>

<p>regions (Supplementary Table S9). Between the majority 
of these proteins amino acid sequence identity varies in 
the range of 20-30%. It seems that the tendency of 
higher protein conservation among the same viral 
subgroup members observed for VP3-like protein does 
not apply to ORF6-like gene products. On the contrary, 
ORF7-like putative gene products do show higher conser-
vation among the members of the same viral subgroup 
with most of pairwise amino acid identities ranging 
between 30% and 40% (Supplementary Figure S4). 
The last predicted ORF that belongs to the conserved 
set of viral genes encodes VP8-like protein, a putative 
P-loop NTPase. Similarly to ORF7-like gene products, 
VP8-like proteins are more conserved among the 
members of the same viral subgroup with amino acid 
sequence identities varying from 40% to 50% (Supple-
mentary Figure S5). 
His2, the only representative of the third subgroup of 
haloarchaeal pleomorphic viruses, also contains a related 
conserved cluster (Figure 1). However, its identity to other 
pleomorphic viruses is low. 
Comparatively high conservation of VP3-like, VP8-like 
proteins and ORF7-like gene products among the viruses 
and proviral regions within the first two subgroups 
allowed the reconstruction of the phylogenetic history of 
these proteins (Supplementary Figures S3-S5). Analysis 
revealed that the phylogenetic history of VP3-like, 
VP8-like proteins and ORF7-like gene products (Supple-
mentary Figures S3-S5) is essentially the same. HGPV-1 
and proviral remnant in Hfx. volcanii region 1 were left 
out from this analysis, because their proteins share rather 
low identity with the proteins of the other second 
subgroup members. </p>

<p>HRPV-3 ORF9 and HGPV-1 ORF14 </p>

<p>All the haloarchaeal pleomorphic viruses and proviral 
regions belonging to the second subgroup share a 
predicted ORF that is encoded by the negative strand 
(Figure 1). These proteins are often predicted to contain 
winged helix-turn-helix (wHTH) DNA binding domain in 
their C-termini (Conserved Domain Database search 
E-values: 0.06 for HGPV-1 ORF14 product and 
1.27Â10 </p>

<p>À3 </p>

<p>for HRPV-3 ORF9 product). Putative </p>

<p>Table 3. The coordinates and the content of putative proviral regions related to haloarchaeal pleomorphic viruses </p>

<p>Sub group 
Archaeal strain (GenBank 
accession no) and proviral region </p>

<p>Positions of the 
proviral region (nt) </p>

<p>Genes included in 
proviral region </p>

<p>I 
Haloferax volcanii DS2 (NC_013967) region 2 
1 307 561-1 295 035 
HVO_1434-HVO_1422 
Halomicrobium mukohataei DSM 12286 (CP001688) region 2 
912 487-926 019 
Hmuk_0952-Hmuk_0965 
II 
Haloarcula hispanica ATCC 33960 (CP002923) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2 720 469-2 730 360 
HAH_2828-HAH_2836 
Haloarcula marismortui ATCC43049 (AY596297) region 1 
2 031 007-2 046 290 
rrnAC2284-rrnAC2297 
Haloarcula marismortui ATCC43049 (AY596297) region 2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2 134 852-2 146 679 
rrnAC2395-rrnAC2404 
Haloferax volcanii DS2 (NC_013967) region 1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>231 538-252 098 
HVO_0258-HVO_0280A 
Halomicrobium mukohataei DSM 12286 (CP001688) region 1 
435 432-448 356 
Hmuk_0455-Hmuk_0467 
Halopiger xanaduensis SH-6 (CP002839) region 1 
631 787-647 728 
Halxa_1313-Halxa1331 
Halopiger xanaduensis SH-6 (CP002839) region 2 
3 612 420-3 632 698 
Halxa_4253-Halxa_4277 
Halorhabdus utahensis DSM 12940 (NC_013158) 
771 758-788 395 
Huta_0789-Huta_0809 
Natrialba magadii ATCC 43099 (CP001932) 
284 491-266 777 
Nmag_0295-Nmag_0272 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>These putative proviral regions are referred to as proviral remnants. </p>



<p>HRPV-3 ORF9 and HGPV-1 ORF14 products share 50% 
identity (Figure 1). In addition, HRPV-3 ORF9 and 
HGPV-1 ORF14 products also show $43% identity to 
the products of ORFs Hqrw_6002 and Hqrw_7002 in 
Haloquadratum walsbyi plasmids PL6A and PL6B, 
respectively (45). </p>

<p>HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 genomes are discontinuous 
dsDNA molecules </p>

<p>The unusual nature of HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 genomes 
was initially noticed during the routine analysis of the 
genomes using different nucleases. Digestion of the 
genomes with MBN gave a set of distinct fragments sug-
gesting that the genomes consist mostly of dsDNA with 
some regions of ssDNA (Figure 2A). In the case of 
discontinuities in HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 genomes, free 
3 
0 OH ends should be able to serve as substrates for the 
TdT. Indeed, TdT was able to incorporate DIG-11-dUTP 
into the genomes of HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 as detected 
using anti-DIG-antibody. The label was incorporated 
roughly throughout the genome (data not shown). 
In order to study the nature of the discontinuities more 
closely, a wide range of MBN concentrations was used, 
starting from concentrations digesting only ssDNA (0.025 
U/1 mg of DNA), to concentrations that also act on nicked 
dsDNA (0.5 U/1 mg of DNA) and on dsDNA molecules 
(5 U/1 mg of DNA). The single-stranded jX174 virion 
DNA and the nicked dsDNA replicative form RFII 
were used as controls to show specificities of different 
MBN concentrations. Clear fragmented patterns of the 
HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 genomes were obtained when 
0.5 U and 5 U of MBN were used (Figure 2A), whereas 
smaller MBN concentration (0.025 U/1 mg of DNA) did 
not have any effect on the genomes (data not shown). 
The results suggest that the viral genomes contain nicks 
or short stretches of ssDNA. In order to resolve this, 
HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 genome were treated with either 
T4 DNA ligase alone or with Sulfolobus DNA polymerase 
IV and then T4 ligase followed by MBN digestion 
(Figure 2B). Ligase alone was not able to repair the 
genomes since MBN was still able to digest the genomes 
into separate fragments. However, the genomic DNA 
treated with Sulfolobus DNA polymerase IV and ligase 
was resistant to MBN concentrations digesting ssDNA. </p>

<p>Hence, the data suggest that the putative discontinuities 
in the dsDNA genomes are short regions of ssDNA. </p>

<p>Discontinuities in HRPV-3 genome are preceded by 
conserved DNA motif </p>

<p>In order to localize MBN-resistant fragments in HRPV-3 
and HGPV-1 genomes, the fragments were cloned into 
pJET1.2/blunt vectors and the ends of the cloned frag-
ments were sequenced (data not shown). Some of the 
mapped MBN-resistant fragments were overlapping and 
some parts in both genomes were not covered. Thus, the 
results were inconclusive. Alignment of the sequences 
around the ends of the cloned fragments of HRPV-3 
genome, however, indicated the presence of the DNA 
motif GCCCA (Figure 3A). In HGPV-1 genome the 
motif is less clear, but examination of sequences located 
at varying distances from the ends of the cloned fragments 
revealed a putative motif, which is currently under study 
(Sencilo and Roine, unpublished). 
HRPV-3 genome contains 27 sites with the motif GCC 
CA (Figure 3C). In a few cases, there are two and in one 
case there are three motifs in close proximity to each 
other. In order to verify that the sites with the motif or 
its reverse complement contain discontinuous regions, we 
first tested two sites by performing Sanger sequencing of 
the HRPV-3 genomic DNA with the primers reading 
through the motif along both DNA strands. In both 
sites, the sequencing signal decreased dramatically after 
the GCCCA motif, suggesting a discontinuous region in 
the opposite strand. When the same genomic regions were 
sequenced from generated PCR template, the drop in 
sequencing signal was not observed. This suggests that 
the drop of signal is caused by an inherent discontinuous 
property of the HRPV-3 genome (Figure 3B). In order to 
test the rest of the sites, we designed primers $100 nt 
upstream of the GCCCA motif when possible 
(Table S3). In 13 cases out of 19, a decrease in sequencing 
signal after the GCCCA motif was observed (Figure 3C). 
In most of the cases, we could also observe a 3 
0 dA 
overhang produced by Taq polymerase during Sanger 
sequencing after the motif, indicating a discontinuity in 
the template strand (Figure 3B). 
The distribution of the mapped discontinuities clearly 
exhibits polarity, which coincides with the switches of </p>

<p>Figure 2. Mung bean nuclease (MBN) analyses of HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 genomes. (A) Digestion of HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 genomes using con-
centrations of either 0.5 or 5 units (U) of MBN per 1 mg of genomic DNA. Virion jX174 DNA (ssDNA) and its replicative form RFII (dsDNA) 
were used as controls. (B) MBN digestions (0.5 U of MBN/1 mg of genomic DNA); the genomes were treated with either T4 DNA ligase (lig.) or 
Sulfolobus DNA polymerase IV and T4 DNA ligase (PolIV lig.). GeneRuler 
TM DNA ladder mix was used as a standard ('st.'). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 12 5529 </p>

<p>transcription from one strand to another (Figure 3C). All 
the discontinuities are located in the coding strand with 
one exception: a triplet of consecutive GCCCA motifs 
starting at the position 591 is located in the region of 
the strand which codes for VP4-like protein, meaning 
that the discontinuities are in the template strand. </p>

<p>HPLC analysis of nucleoside composition </p>

<p>The nucleoside composition of the viral genomes of 
HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 was analysed after digestion to nu-
cleosides and subsequent separation by chromatography. 
Detection of eluting nucleosides was done with a diode 
array detector and a mass spectrometer (HPLC-
DAD-MS). In addition to the four major nucleosides, 
two peaks appeared in the UV-chromatogram at 6.3 min 
and 9.9 min (Figure 4C), the molecular masses of which 
correspond to methylated derivatives of cytidine and ad-
enosine, respectively. Using the multiple fragmentation 
reaction monitoring (MRM) mode of the Triple 
Quadrupol, the fragmentation patterns of all nucleoside 
peaks were analysed. The mass transitions of the two 
methylated nucleosides (Figure 4A and B) showed that 
the methylgroups are located on the base and not on the 
sugar moiety. Retention time and fragmentation of the 
peak at 6.3 min were identical to methylated nucleoside </p>

<p>5-methylcytidine (mC). The peak of the base-methylated 
adenosine at 9.9 min, also present in both viral DNA 
digests, corresponds most probably to N </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>-methyla-
denosine (mA) which is already well described (46). 
Figure 4C shows the chromatograms taken at 254 nm of 
the viral digests used for calculation of relative nucleoside 
amounts. Both viral digests contain similar amounts of 
mC (0.58% and 0.66%) and slightly different amounts 
of mA (0.20% and 1.35%). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This study extends the genomic description of the new 
group of haloarchaeal pleomorphic viruses by adding 
the characterization of HRPV-2, HRPV-3, HRPV-6 and 
HGPV-1 genomes. Comparative genomic analysis of these 
new genomes together with the previously published 
HRPV-1 (6), HHPV-1 (20) and His2 (5) shows that, in 
general, this group of viruses has a collinear cluster of 
conserved genes. Analysis of the genomic content shows 
that although similar viruses can be found from wide geo-
graphical areas (3), the closely related ones were found 
from geographically close regions. 
Annotation of the genomes in this study relies not only 
on the predictions but also on the experimental data </p>

<p>Figure 3. Mapping of the discontinuous sites in the HRPV-3 genome. (A) Conserved nucleotides of the aligned sequences showing the identified 
motif found in the MBN-resistant fragment ends of HRPV-3. (B) Sanger sequencing of the genomic site with predicted discontinuity. A drop in 
sequencing signal was observed after the motif GCCCA when HRPV-3 genome was used as a template (7502 F_genome). Sequencing of corres-
ponding HRPV-3 fragment amplified by PCR (7502 F_PCR) showed no decrease in the signal. (C) HRPV-3 genome map with arrows marking 
predicted sites of discontinuities (GCCCA motif). The names of primers used to sequence the regions with putative discontinuities are noted above or 
below the arrow. Sites which were not possible to sequence because of the proximity of the other interruption are marked with grey arrow. Black 
arrows indicate the predicted sites of discontinuity where a sudden drop of sequencing signal was observed as exemplified by the above-placed 
sequencing chromatograph (7502F_genome). Red arrows indicate positions where no sequencing signal drop was detected despite the predicted motif 
for discontinuity. </p>



<p>obtained by protein chemistry (N-terminal sequences of 
proteins). Since the N-termini of the mature VP4-like 
proteins are known, it was possible to conclude that the 
automated prediction of translation initiation sites for 
these proteins often resulted in unusually long signal 
peptides. Thus, alternative start sites that retained the 
usual length of the signal peptides were chosen. 
Experimental data of the viral proteins also give us 
useful tools for assessing the original annotation of 
related proviral regions in haloarchaeal genomes. For 
example, the VP3 homologue of Hfx. volcanii DS2 
(HVO_1432) has been annotated as a fibronectin type 
III domain (Fn3)-containing protein (47). Due to the 
reasons outlined in the Supplementary Discussion, we 
suspect that the annotation of the HVO_1432 as a Fn3 
domain containing protein is erroneous. 
All the haloarchaeal pleomorphic viruses and related 
proviral elements contain a genomic region encoding the 
two major structural proteins and three putative gene 
products, possibly involved in viral assembly. We define 
this region as a conserved gene cluster. Among the </p>

<p>encoded proteins, VP3-like, VP8-like and ORF7-like 
gene products show the highest degree of conservation, 
and preliminary phylogenetic analyses suggest similar evo-
lutionary histories for these proteins. The set of genome 
sequences described here, however, is still too small and 
diverse to enable a proper phylogenetic analysis of genes 
encoded by the conserved cluster and their products. 
Good examples for this are VP4-like proteins. As dis-
cussed before (20,23), the VP4-like proteins do not 
usually show high identity because they are likely to 
serve as receptor recognition proteins. Exceptions to this 
are the VP4-like proteins of HRPV-2, HRPV-3 and 
HRPV-6 ($50-60% identity, Supplementary Table S8). 
This case most probably reflects the correlation between 
the relatedness of the VP4-like protein and the hosts of 
these viruses (Halorubrum). HRPV-1 also infects a host 
strain that has been designated as Halorubrum sp., but 
the VP4 protein similarity to those of HRPV-2, HRPV-3 
and HRPV-6 is much lower ($20%). Since the HRPV-1 
VP4 is the only protein among the VP4-like proteins that 
is shown to be glycosylated and glycans are often involved </p>

<p>Figure 4. LC-MS/MS analysis of HGPV-1 and HRPV-3 digests. (A) MRM chromatograms of a DNA digest, RNA digest including 
5-deoxymethylcytidine, HGPV-1 DNA digest and HRPV-3 DNA digest. (B) Reactions monitored by MRM and retention times of nucleosides. 
(C) UV traces at 254 nm of HGPV-1 DNA digest and HRPV-3 DNA digest used for semi-quantitative calculations. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 12 5531 </p>

<p>in specific recognition events, glycosylation may be the 
factor responsible for the observed difference. Host may 
not be the only selection pressure on the VP4-like proteins, 
however, because the VP4-like proteins of HHPV-1 and 
His2 infecting Har. hispanica are rather diverged. 
The pleomorphic viruses seem to be simple in terms of 
both the virion architecture (21,22) and the genome com-
position. The replicative form of the circular pleomorphic 
viral genomes is similar to the haloarchaeal plasmids. 
Thus, analogies to membrane vesicles containing plasmid 
DNA have been drawn (1,48). The pleomorphic viruses 
retard the host cell growth (6,20,21), which is also usual 
for many high-copy-number plasmids. Although the dis-
tinction between plasmids and replicating virus genomes 
can be difficult (49) and hybrids of plasmids and viruses 
have been reported (50), the pleomorphic haloarchaeal 
viruses described in this report fall into the category of 
viruses on the basis of at least two criteria. First, the 
replicon is packaged into a particle (51), and second, the 
replicon packaged encodes the structural proteins and 
the proteins required for the assembly of these particles. 
Although the modes of replication for the two viral 
subgroups identified in this study have not yet been 
elucidated, it is likely that they are different. The first 
subgroup members encode putative replication initiation 
protein (Rep) of rolling circle replication (RCR), suggest-
ing that these viruses replicate their genomes via RCR 
mechanism. Viruses belonging to the second subgroup 
do not encode Rep. The third subgroup member, His2, 
is predicted to use protein-primed replication for its 
linear genome (5,52). Thus, this is yet another excellent 
example of the related viruses having adopted different 
genome types and possibly also replication strategies 
(20,51). 
For the first two subgroups of pleomorphic viruses 
(Figure 1), there are many related putative proviruses or 
proviral remnants (6,20,23) (Table 3). Proviruses contain 
an integrase, and in most cases, we can identify a tRNA 
on the other end of the proviral region. The putative 
proviral regions usually have longer variable part of the 
genomes than the pleomorphic viruses do. It seems that 
the described pleomorphic viruses have systematically lost 
the integrase encoding genes and many putative genes 
from the regions with variable gene content. The only 
exception is HRPV-2 which still seems to have many 
putative genes that may not be necessary for the pleo-
morphic viral lifecycle sensu stricto. 
Although the genomes of HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 are 
dsDNA molecules they contain localized single-strand 
interruptions (Figures 2 and 3). In HRPV-3 genome, 
they are preceded by a specific motif GCCCA. Localized 
single-strand interruptions have been identified before in 
the tailed 'phiKMV-like viruses' of Pseudomonas 
aeruginosa (53,54) and T5 (55-57). In those viruses, the 
discontinuities were shown to be nicks that were located 
in one strand only, and in phage jkF77, they were shown 
to be located in intergenic regions (54). The function of the 
nicks for earlier reported viruses is not known, and the 
candidates for gene products generating these nicks have 
been hypothesized to be of viral origin (54). The results 
obtained in this study show that the interruptions in </p>

<p>HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 genomes are not nicks, but 
longer stretches of single-stranded DNA. Also, we do 
not have a candidate gene product for causing these inter-
ruptions in the HGPV-1 or HRPV-3 genome, and we 
speculate that in this case the putative enzyme is host 
encoded. Both HRPV-3 and HGPV-1 show methylation 
patterns of cytidine (mC) and adenosine (mA) which are 
well-known in DNA research and have not been found to 
influence the genomic integrity. Hence, there is no 
evidence that modified nucleosides are related to the dis-
continuous nature of the HRPV3 and HGPV1 virus 
genomes. Further studies are needed to elucidate the 
mechanism causing these short stretches of ssDNA and 
most importantly to determine their biological function. 
This study describes comparative genomic analyses of 
six pleomorphic viruses containing a conserved cluster of 
two identified and three predicted genes involved in the 
virion structure and assembly. His2 also contains homo-
logues of the same conserved cluster of genes. Although 
His2 virus is currently grouped with spindle-shaped virus 
His1 to the genus Salterprovirus, these two viruses share 
only one homologue, type B DNA polymerase (5). This 
suggests that His2 virus is more closely related to 
haloarchaeal pleomorphic viruses, than to spindle-shaped 
virus His1. A parallel study reports the analysis of virion 
morphology of these newly identified haloarchaeal pleo-
morphic viruses and earlier reported His2 (5) by quanti-
tative biochemical dissociation and electron cryo-
microscopy (cryo-EM) (21). It shows that the architectural 
principles of His2 are the same as those of the other 
haloarchaeal pleomorphic viruses. Taken together, our 
results are consistent with the above-mentioned findings 
(21) and allow us to further classify the haloarchaeal pleo-
morphic viruses into subgroups according to genome 
organization. On the basis of these results, we can now 
propose a new group of viruses, the group of seven pleo-
morphic haloarchaeal viruses, having similar principles of 
virion architecture, but different types of genomes. </p>

<p>ACCESSION NUMBERS </p>

<p>HRPV-2, HRPV-3, HRPV-6 and HGPV-1 viral genomes 
were submitted to GenBank under the accession numbers 
JN882264, JN882265, JN882266 and JN882267. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online: 
Supplementary Tables 1-9, Supplementary Figures 1-5, 
Supplementary Materials and Methods, Supplementary 
Results, Supplementary Discussion and Supplementary 
References [3,20-22,44,47,58-63]. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Dr. Hanna M. Oksanen for coordination of the 
virus production. Gunilla Ro¨nnholm and Professor Nisse 
Kalkkinen are acknowledged for the determination of the 
N-terminal sequences of the structural proteins. We thank 
Maija K. Pietila¨, Nina S. Atanasova, Violeta Manole, </p>



<p>Lassi Liljeroos, Professor Sarah J. Butcher, Dr. Hanna M. 
Oksanen and Professor Dennis H. Bamford who have 
conducted a parallel study, for providing the additional 
N-terminal sequences of the structural proteins. Professor 
Sarah J. Butcher and Professor Dennis H. Bamford 
are also thanked for the useful comments on the manu-
script. Sari Korhonen and Eija Stenius are thanked for 
the excellent technical assistance. Kirsi Lipponen, Eeva-
Marja Turkki, Pa¨ivi Laamanen and Hanna Turunen 
are acknowledged for excellent technical assistance in 
DNA sequencing work. A. S. is a fellow of Viikki 
Graduate School in Molecular Biosciences. We also 
thank University of Helsinki for the support to EU 
ESFRI Instruct Associate Centre for Virus Production 
and Purification used in this study. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>The University of Helsinki three year grant 2010-2012 (to 
E.R.) and Academy of Finland Centre of Excellence 
Program in Virus Research grant 11296841 (2006-2011). 
Funding for open access charge: University of Helsinki 
Three Year Grant to Elina Roine </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 12 5533 </p>





</text></tei>