<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3088464" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Background: Quality improvement (QI) initiatives 
characterised by iterative cycles of quantitative data 
analysis do not readily explain the organisational 
determinants of change. However, the integration of 
sociotechnical theory can inform more effective 
strategies. Our specific aims were to (1) describe 
a computerised decision support intervention intended 
to improve adherence with deep venous thrombosis 
(DVT) prophylaxis recommendations; and (2) show 
how sociotechnical theory expressed in 'Fit between 
Individuals, Task and Technology' framework (FITT) 
can identify and clarify the facilitators and barriers to 
QI work. 
Methods: A multidisciplinary team developed and 
implemented electronic menus with DVT prophylaxis 
recommendations. Stakeholders were interviewed and 
human factors were analysed to optimise integration. 
Menu exposure, order placement and clinical 
performance were measured. Vista tool extraction and 
chart review were used. Performance compliance pre-
implementation was 77%. 
Results: There were 80e110 eligible cases per month. 
Initial menu use rate was 20%. After barriers were 
classified and addressed using the FITT framework, 
use improved 50% to 90%. Tasks, users and 
technology issues in the FITT model and their 
interfaces were identified and addressed. Workflow 
styles, concerns about validity of guidelines, cycle 
times and perceived ambiguity of risk were issues 
identified. 
Conclusions: DVT prophylaxis in a surgical setting 
is fraught with socio-political agendas, cognitive 
dissonance and misaligned expectations. These 
must be sought and articulated if organisations 
are to respond to internal resistance to change. 
This case study demonstrates that QI teams using 
information technology must understand the clinical 
context, even in mature electronic health record 
environments, in order to implement sustainable 
systems. </p>

<p>BACKGROUND </p>

<p>In modern healthcare's knowledge-intensive 
environment, information technology (IT) 
is frequently incorporated into quality 
improvement (QI) initiatives to narrow 
provider knowledge gaps and influence the 
trajectory of behaviour. 
1 It follows then that </p>

<p>implementation specialists introducing new 
technology and computerised decision 
support (CDS) tend to use quality improve-
ment methods popularised by Deming (ie, 
the Plan-Do-Study-Act (PDSA) cycle) and 
Donabedian (ie, Structure-Process-Outcome 
(SPO) framework). 
2e4 These models improve </p>

<p>the rigour of an implementation by empha-
sising mechanisms of cause and effect and 
expressing performance outcomes quantita-
tively. However, QI initiatives are by their very 
nature, multi-dimensional and context 
dependent; the impact of technology on 
performance is often a function of the 
organisational culture as much as the tech-
nology or the systems-of-care. 
5 Unfortunately, </p>

<p>most QI models incompletely capture 
complex, heterogeneous and culturally 
textured healthcare systems activities. 
6 7 In </p>

<p>contrast, sociotechnical approaches drawn 
from the behavioural sciences explore the 
organisational and cultural interdepen-
dencies that influence technology adoption 
by incorporating facets of informatics, 
cognitive theory and organisational behav-
iour. </p>

<p>6  8e14 </p>

<p>Notably, Ammenwerth and 
colleagues have developed the 'Fit between 
Individuals, Task and Technology' framework 
(FITT), which expresses system change 
through the match between user group attri-
butes, characteristics of the implemented 
technology, and affected tasks (figure 1). </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>1 Portland Oregon VA Medical 
Center, Oregon Health and 
Sciences University, 
Portland, Oregon, USA 
2 Portland Oregon VA Medical 
Center, Portland, Oregon, 
USA </p>

<p>Correspondence to 
Blake J Lesselroth, Portland 
Center for Evaluation of 
Clinical Services, P3 MED, 
Portland Veterans Affairs 
Medical Center, 3710 
Southwest US Veterans 
Hospital Drive, Portland, 
Oregon, USA; 
blake.lesselroth@va.gov </p>

<p>Accepted 15 August 2010 
Published Online First 
5 January 2011 </p>

<p>This paper is freely available 
online under the BMJ 
Journals unlocked scheme, 
see http://qualitysafety.bmj. 
com/site/about/unlocked. 
xhtml </p>

<p>BMJ Qual Saf 2011;20:381e389. doi:10.1136/bmjqs.2010.042689 </p>



<p>Original research </p>

<p>This framework may be used as a heuristic to inform more 
effective and durable quality interventions. </p>

<p>15   The purpose of this manuscript is to show how quali-
tative assessment of organisational context can comple-
ment a QI implementation using information 
technology. Our specific aims are to (1) describe a CDS 
intervention intended to improve adherence with deep 
venous thrombosis (DVT) prophylaxis recommenda-
tions; (2) show how sociotechnical theory expressed in 
the FITT framework can help identify the facilitators and 
the barriers to adoption of new systems and (3) 
demonstrate how qualitative data categorised using the 
FITT model can complement the quantitative analysis 
characteristic of the PDSA model. </p>

<p>Problem statement 
Venous thromboembolism is a rare but devastating post-
operative complication affecting surgical patients and 
represents the most common preventable cause of in-
hospital death. 
16 17 It is estimated that unprophylaxed </p>

<p>patients undergoing major surgical procedures are at 
a 15e60% risk of developing a DVT. 
17 18 Several large </p>

<p>randomised controlled trials have shown that pharma-
cologic prophylaxis with the routine administration of 
low-dose anticoagulants or lower extremity automated 
compression devices can significantly reduce DVT risk 
and prevent fatal pulmonary embolism (PE). 
16e19 For </p>

<p>this reason, published guidelines endorse routine DVT 
prophylaxis. 
17 20 21 Likewise, the Veterans Affairs (VA) </p>

<p>National Office of Quality and Performance has estab-
lished performance standards requiring prophylaxis of 
most post-operative patients. </p>

<p>22   Our VA facility had struggled to meet the national VA 
DVT prophylaxis performance target (92% of candidate 
patients) since establishment as a quality measure in 
2007. Nationally conducted chart reviews showed that 
patients either did not receive prophylaxis or received 
non-standard prophylaxis 75% of the time. Conse-
quently, hospital executive leadership and the surgical 
department jointly sponsored the development and 
implementation of health record CDS and an educa-
tional campaign to encourage surgeon compliance with 
DVT prophylaxis recommendations. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Setting and context 
The study site is a 230-bed tertiary care teaching hospital 
serving United States veteran patients throughout the 
states of Oregon, Washington, Alaska and Idaho. The 
facility hospital and clinics use the VA computerised 
patient record system (CPRS), a HIMSS Stage 7 elec-
tronic record that supports computerised provider order 
entry. 
23 All patient data are stored in the VA health </p>

<p>record database, the Veterans Integrated Systems Tech-
nology Architecture (VistA). 
The Operative Care Division (OCD) is the adminis-
trative umbrella for university appointed staff in 
anaesthesia service, general surgery, and all surgical 
subspecialities. Residents rotate through OCD every 
30e90 days and write the majority of electronic orders. 
Surgical quality is quantitatively assessed using a subset 
of nationally defined indicators. Facility, regional 
and national executives use the External Peer Review 
Program (EPRP) measures to compare facilities, 
grade performance and inform quality improvement 
initiatives. </p>

<p>22   First improvement cycle: development of decision support 
Numerous studies have shown that CDS can improve 
physician compliance with best practices, therapeutic 
guidelines and preferred formularies. 
24 Trials focussing </p>

<p>specifically upon DVT prevention have shown that CDS 
can improve clinician adherence with recommended 
prophylaxis. 
25 26 Thus, our OCD sponsored develop-</p>

<p>ment of a prophylaxis CDS 'package' to improve 
compliance with recommended DVT prophylaxis. 
An interdisciplinary QI team consisting of a project 
manager, an internist, a pharmacist and three informa-
ticians was charged with the development and imple-
mentation of new electronic order menus. Subject 
matter experts were recruited to provide clinical content 
and test prototype menus. The facility Pharmacy and </p>

<p>Figure 1 The 'Fit between Individuals, Task and Technology' 
framework adapted from Ammenwerth et al. 
9 Success of 
quality improvement interventions is dependent upon the 
quality of fit between user, task and technology. The interfaces 
between each actor in the global activity system derive from 
several epistemological domains including cognitive sciences, 
social sciences and informatics. </p>

<p>382 </p>

<p>BMJ Qual Saf 2011;20:381e389. doi:10.1136/bmjqs.2010.042689 </p>

<p>Original research </p>

<p>Therapeutics committee provided oversight to ensure 
compliance with hospital prescribing policies and 
formulary use criteria. 
The team used a combination of Plan-Do-Study-Act 
(PDSA) and user-centred design (UCD) processes 
throughout menu development. 
27 28 Both processes </p>

<p>require multiple iterative cycles of incremental change 
informed by regular multi-modal evaluation (figure 2). 
The first step was assembly of a knowledge base and 
included a literature review of published clinical guide-
lines, collection of protocols from academic affiliates 
and discussions with subject matter experts. Next, the QI </p>

<p>team used non-participant observation and think-aloud 
protocols to study the cognitive tasks, ordering patterns, 
and workflow processes of users. Finally, the team used 
all data to assemble flowcharts of clinical tasks and menu 
design requirements. </p>

<p>29   The team enlisted surgeons to test a series of menu mock-
ups. Surgeon feedback was then used to build speciality-
specific order menus. Prophylaxis options were organised 
according to patient risk categories (figure 3). The team 
developed unique orders with embedded meta-data 'tags' 
to facilitate order tracking. These orders appeared every 
time clinicians accessed post-operative order sets. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Gantt chart illustrating deep venous thrombosis prophylaxis process improvement interventions according to Plan-Do-
Study-Act (PDSA) cycles. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Sample order menu reflecting patient risk categories, suggested prophylaxis options and alternatives if 
contraindications to pharmacologic prophylaxis exist. CAD, coronary artery disease; CHF, congestive heart failure; COPD, chronic 
obstructive pulmonary disease; INR, international normalized ratio; SCD, sequential compression devices; SQ, subcutaneous; 
TED, thromboembolic deterrent; tx, treatment; VTE, venous thromboembolism. </p>

<p>BMJ Qual Saf 2011;20:381e389. doi:10.1136/bmjqs.2010.042689 </p>



<p>Original research </p>

<p>An educational campaign accompanied release of the 
new order menus. The QI team members gave presen-
tations to the residents, pharmacists and nurses 
describing the purpose and design of the new menus. 
The surgical residents and staff attended morning 
reports dedicated to new menu content. The team 
posted informational flyers in all surgical staff and resi-
dent work areas and break rooms. </p>

<p>Second improvement cycle: analysis of human factors 
After the first cycle, we gathered additional data to assess 
the organisational impact of the CDS implementation. 
The team used a variety of qualitative methods including 
non-participatory observation, semi-structured interviews 
with surgeon focus groups and chart reviews of the 
prophylaxis orders to understand sociotechnical 
barriers. At each step of collection, we categorised data 
according to the FITT model criteria (table 1). Each 
component of the activity system (ie, user, task and 
technology) was clearly defined and each interface 
between components was explored by drawing from 
several epistemological disciplines including the social 
and cognitive sciences. 
The team designed interventions to address each 
identified FITT barrier. We worked on menu usability by 
streamlining workflow pathways, rephrasing risk assess-
ment criteria and reorganising resources. Addition of 
requested content such as new menus and corollary 
orders improved stakeholder buy-in. Guidelines were </p>

<p>clarified and order set pathways were simplified. Because 
the second PDSA cycle coincided with the start of the 
academic year, we incorporated menu-training sessions 
into the new resident orientation curriculum. </p>

<p>Data analysis 
Three metrics were established a priori to measure 
treatment effect: (1) the proportion of cases in which 
new order sets were displayed (ie, menu exposure); (2) 
the proportion of cases in which recommended 
prophylaxis was ordered using any process (ie, clinical 
performance) and (3) the proportion of cases in which 
prophylaxis orders were placed using the new menu (ie, 
menu use). Inclusion and exclusion criteria are listed in 
table 2. We used VistA database query tools to measure 
the frequency of menu exposure and the selection of 
prophylaxis orders. We assessed compliance with 
recommendations by manual chart review. The team 
used time series methods for data analysis. 
During the first improvement cycle, the team used 
several strategies to establish the internal and external 
validity of automated data collection. Our automated 
data collection method used the VistA database query 
utility to identify all enoxaparin, subcutaneous heparin 
and warfarin orders for patients meeting inclusion 
criteria. For patients with contraindications to anti-
coagulation, we queried charts for documentation of 
a contraindication and an order for compression 
devices. To establish the internal validity of our </p>

<p>Table 1 Sociotechnical issues identified by the team during CDS implementation and interventions taken to improve 
performance. Findings are categorised using the FITT framework (adapted from Ammenwerth et al </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Issues or barriers to CDS success 
Interventions to improve performance </p>

<p>Actors in 
System </p>

<p>Task 
&lt; Additional orders were needed 
to improve efficiency of order-entry time </p>

<p>&lt; Corollary orders created for each 
subspeciality to improve efficiency of 
transfer order-entry 
User 
&lt; Heterogeneous cohort of surgical 
subspecialists 
&lt; Ordering providers rotate frequently </p>

<p>&lt; Custom order menus created for each 
speciality 
&lt; Training was embedded in resident 
orientation 
Technology 
&lt; Orders needed to be tracked 
automatically 
&lt; No way to automatically capture 
contraindications </p>

<p>&lt; Unique prophylaxis order items built for 
tracking 
&lt; Created unique contraindication orders </p>

<p>Interfaces 
Task 
Technology </p>

<p>&lt; Surgeons used unexpected order menu 
pathways 
&lt; Orders embedded in deep in sets were 
overlooked </p>

<p>&lt; Obsolete pathways removed from the 
order menus 
&lt; Prophylaxis orders placed at start of 
pathway 
User 
technology </p>

<p>&lt; Risk categories were difficult to apply 
to patients 
&lt; Decision support content difficult to 
interpret </p>

<p>&lt; Prophylaxis options organised by 
procedure 
&lt; Content updated according to user 
feedback 
User task 
&lt; Guidelines discordant with local practice 
&lt; Providers unwilling to use enoxaparin 
or heparin </p>

<p>&lt; Clinical champions engaged to 
in-service trainees 
&lt; New warfarin order process developed 
with anticoagulation clinic </p>



<p>BMJ Qual Saf 2011;20:381e389. doi:10.1136/bmjqs.2010.042689 </p>

<p>Original research </p>

<p>automated query, a clinician reviewed all surgeries 
meeting inclusion criteria during one week in April 2008 
(N¼30), searching for appropriate medication orders 
and documentation of drug administration or evidence 
of compression device application. The automated query 
accurately captured 100% of menu usage, medication 
orders and compression device orders, but missed some 
documentation of compression device application. In 
three instances (10% of cases reviewed), the documen-
tation was captured in scanned ICU flowsheets, but not 
the chart notes. The automated database queries were 
incapable of extracting content from scanned docu-
ments. To establish external validity, the team compared 
local findings to facility data collected and scored by 
independent auditors (ie, national EPRP contractors). 
The compliance rate for 35 randomly selected charts was 
identical (compliance¼77%). 
To measure a potential relationship between use of the 
new menu and change in facility performance, we 
applied Pearson's correlation between the proportion of 
cases with recommended prophylaxis ordered and the 
use of the new order menu. All statistics were performed 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">14.0</rs>. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Quantitative findings 
There were 80e110 eligible surgical cases each month 
during the study period. General surgery, orthopaedics 
and urology had the highest case volume with approxi-
mately 30 cases per month per service. Neurosurgery 
averaged 10 cases per month and gynaecology 
completed one or two cases per month. The VA began 
measuring the frequency of DVT prophylaxis orders in 
FY2007. 
After the first implementation cycle, data suggested 
that providers rarely saw the new menus; providers </p>

<p>used embedded orders in only 10% to 20% of cases 
(figures 4 and 5). Chart review showed that surgeons 
used several patient-transfer order pathways that 
bypassed our new DVT prophylaxis menus. During the 
second cycle, reconfiguration of order menus 
appeared to improve order set accessibility; providers 
triggered the menu in over 90% of cases (figure 4). 
Average order use increased from 50% to 90% but 
adoption and use varied by speciality (figure 5). 
Services with the greatest case volume showed the 
greatest improvement; general surgery and neurosur-
gery had the largest absolute increase in prophylaxis 
compliance. 
Medical centre indicator performance also improved, 
exceeding the target by the end of the second PDSA 
cycle (figure 6). There was an overlap in the CIs for pre-
measures and post-measures of EPRP performance with 
the exception of Q1, 2010. Performance trends 
appeared to correlate with new menu use (Pearson's 
correlation coefficient¼0.832, p¼0.010), although 
a substantial number of orders were selected from 
other menu paths. Use of menu options strongly 
predicted performance measure success; 36 of 38 
randomly selected cases from the treatment cohort 
were compliant with the EPRP measures (PPV¼95%) 
(table 3). The two noncompliant cases used mechan-
ical prophylaxis when pharmacologic measures were 
indicated. </p>

<p>Table 2 Definitions, inclusion criteria and exclusion 
criteria for study sample </p>

<p>22   Data 
definition </p>

<p>Orders placed for prophylaxis: 
&lt; Subcutaneous low-dose heparin 
&lt; Low-dose enoxaparin 
&lt; Dose adjusted warfarin for DVT prophylaxis 
&lt; Sequential compression devices 
Inclusion 
criteria </p>

<p>&lt; Hospitalised for at least 24 h 
&lt; Operative procedure performed by general 
surgery, gynaecology, neurosurgery, 
orthopaedics or urology 
&lt; Admitted between 3/1/2008 and 12/31/ 
2009 
Exclusion 
criteria </p>

<p>&lt; Surgery lasted less than 30 min 
&lt; Patient underwent laparoscopic procedure 
&lt; Patient already receiving full-dose 
anticoagulation </p>

<p>Figure 4 Proportion of deep venous thrombosis prophylaxis 
eligible surgical cases in which the provider triggered the new 
prophylaxis order menu. These cases may or may not have 
received prophylaxis orders from the new menu. New menu 
use increased across all specialities and reached a steady 
state averaging 90%. During the study interval, case load for 
general surgery was approximately 100 per quarter; 
gynaecology 2e7; neurosurgery 20e30; 100 for orthopaedics; 
and 89e90 for urology. </p>

<p>BMJ Qual Saf 2011;20:381e389. doi:10.1136/bmjqs.2010.042689 </p>



<p>Original research </p>

<p>Qualitative findings 
Stakeholder interviews revealed several important tech-
nical and social barriers to CDS acceptance. We classified 
findings according to the components of the FITT 
framework (ie, user, technology, task) and the interfaces 
between components (table 1). The most important 
barriers identified included the presence of accessory or 
work-around pathways in CPRS, poor order set usability 
and misalignment between CDS recommendations and 
pre-existing surgical care patterns. Moreover, provider 
workflow was non-linear, and highly adaptive, affording 
ample opportunity to bypass our clinical pathways and 
recommended guidelines. 
When clinical pathways were used, providers initially 
struggled with the order sets. Surgeons had increased 
order entry time and a decrease in productivity. Focus 
group respondents argued that patient risk stratification 
guidelines were frequently not prescriptive enough to 
effectively apply to individual patients at the point-of-
care. Finally, many providers disagreed with the clinical 
guidelines, arguing that the risk of hemarthrosis 
outweighed the potential protection pharmacologic 
prophylaxis afforded against fatal PE. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our data suggest that surgeons variably used our DVT 
prophylaxis CDS, but that order use positively correlated 
with EPRP compliance. There appeared to be a gradual </p>

<p>increase in order use over time; the trend lines show 
three general trajectories (figure 5), a slow adoption rate 
after the first PDSA cycle, a second more rapid adoption 
rate after the second PDSA cycle and a third gradual rise 
over the last two quarters. We believe that technical 
design changes (eg, removal of accessory order path-
ways) were responsible for the rapid increase in utilisa-
tion between the first and the second cycle. The team 
identified several technical problems with the CDS that 
disrupted workflow or limited usability. These issues 
were partially design related and partially related to the 
limitations of the legacy electronic record (eg, VistA/ 
CPRS does not support complex branched logic). We 
suspect that the more gradual trajectories of perfor-
mance improvement were a reflection of slower 
socio-organisational change including new learning, 
peer-to-peer influences and socio-political forces. 
Although we sought to accelerate this process using 
multi-modal educational campaigns, these strategies 
appeared to be only marginally effective. In circum-
stances where surgeons were unfamiliar with patient risk 
categories and prophylaxis options, teaching initiatives 
or menu revision proved useful. Conversely, surgeons 
with firmly established practice patterns or expressing 
concerns about anticoagulation risks strongly resisted 
change. 
Although our intervention was successful, it illustrates 
the complex interplay between technical and human 
determinants. The quantitative PDSA cycle alone would </p>

<p>Figure 5 Proportion of deep venous thrombosis prophylaxis 
eligible surgical cases with prophylaxis orders selected from 
the new menu. There was a steep increase in prophylaxis 
order use from the new menu during the second Plan-Do-
Study-Act cycle. During the study interval, case load for 
general surgery was approximately 100 per quarter, 
gynaecology 2e7, neurosurgery 20e30, 100 for orthopaedics, 
and 89e90 for urology. </p>

<p>Figure 6 Proportion of surgical cases with prophylaxis orders 
selected from the new menu and facility performance on EPRP 
measures during the study time period. Error bars indicate 
95% CI for EPRP sample evaluation. Facility performance 
improved and met the EPRP measures target after the second 
cycle of implementation. Improvement correlated with the 
proportion of orders selected from the new menu (Pearson's 
correlation coefficient¼0.832; p¼0.010). DVT, deep venous 
thrombosis; EPRP, External Peer Review Program. </p>



<p>BMJ Qual Saf 2011;20:381e389. doi:10.1136/bmjqs.2010.042689 </p>

<p>Original research </p>

<p>not have elucidated many of the barriers that delayed 
CDS adoption. Its singular causeeeffect analytics do not 
provide information to understand the inherently multi-
variate nature of implementation science. Conversely, 
organisational change theories popularised by Rogers 
propose explanations for how groups adopt innovations 
across large-scale organisations. 
30 Rogers diffusion of </p>

<p>innovation theory describes several key organisational 
and technologic determinants of systemic change: (1) the 
characteristics of the technology, (2) users' readiness for 
change and (3) the organisational structure. When 
introducing new technology for the purposes of QI, it is 
important to explore entrenched stakeholder belief 
systems using exploratory methods and engage target 
users before applying incremental changes. By systemat-
ically studying the sociotechnical system, the imple-
mentation scientist can rationally choose interventions 
that accelerate improvement, limit resource expenditure 
and optimise the sociotechnical fit. 
The FITT framework provides a coherent and adapt-
able heuristic to direct qualitative enquiry, identify 
barriers to implementation, and classify themes for the 
purposes of developing a coordinated response. 
Furthermore, the framework operationalises the diffu-
sion of innovations theories popularised by Rogers in 
several discrete ways. 
30 The FITT framework (1) uses the </p>

<p>components of user and task to help recognise and 
optimise the intrinsic characteristics of innovations that 
influence adoption (eg, usability, compatibility, relative 
advantage); (2) the framework emphasises the impor-
tance of the user as an agent of the social system; early </p>

<p>adopters, innovation champions, opinion leaders and 
laggards all have an important influence upon the 
trajectory of adoption and (3) the framework normalises 
expectations for change in the context of QI; complex 
interventions that include a social, cultural, or behav-
ioural component are likely to experience several stages 
of adoption and follow a non-linear pattern of diffusion. 
Although, we cite several technical changes that we 
hypothesise had a direct impact on the rate of menu use, 
it is equally likely that the sigmoidal pattern of uptake, in 
part, reflects the recruitment of different user types 
along the adoption continuum. Engaging service chiefs 
and senior residents was critical for identifying 
improvement opportunities, gaining political capital 
within the OCD and developing internal momentum to 
promote menu use. 
In our example, the FITT framework provided 
a supplementary model, informing each component of 
the PDSA cycle. By striving to understand the barriers 
affecting activity system components and the interfaces 
between them, we were able to develop a plan that 
addressed user needs, implement an intervention that 
articulated with workflow, study the contextual determi-
nants of performance, and act in alignment with stake-
holder expectations. To our knowledge, this is the first 
report applying the FITT framework to a QI intervention 
and suitably captures the human-centred issues intrinsic 
to QI work. It enriched our QI methods by clarifying the 
basis of user resistance and highlighting the relationship 
between organisational attributes and outcomes. The 
framework draws strategies from the cognitive sciences, </p>

<p>Table 3 Review of 38 surgical cases with DVT prophylaxis ordered from the new menu. The results of the review indicated 
that all cases with DVT prophylaxis selected from the new menu met the recommended guideline </p>

<p>Speciality 
# Cases 
Principle procedure 
DVT prophylaxis ordered </p>

<p>General surgery 
12 
Tracheal incision 
Pyloric reconstruction 
Colectomy 
Colostomy 
Suture, small intestine 
Late wound closure 
Gallbladder removal 
Exploratory laparotomy </p>

<p>Heparin 5000 units SQ Q8H and/or 
compression devices </p>

<p>Gynaecology 
2 
Oophorectomy 
Extensive hysterectomy </p>

<p>Heparin 5000 units SQ Q8H </p>

<p>Neurosurgery 
3 
Skull drainage 
Meningeal leak repair 
Wound repair </p>

<p>Heparin 5000 units SQ Q12H and/or 
compression devices </p>

<p>Orthopaedics 
9 
Revise/replace knee joint 
Total hip arthroplasty 
Drain thigh/knee lesion 
Total knee arthroplasty </p>

<p>Warfarin 5 mg PO QPM and/or 
compression devices </p>

<p>Urology 
4 
Radical prostectomy 
Open radical nephrectomy 
Cystectomy </p>

<p>Heparin 5000 units SQ Q8H and/or 
compression devices </p>

<p>BMJ Qual Saf 2011;20:381e389. doi:10.1136/bmjqs.2010.042689 </p>



<p>Original research </p>

<p>anthropology and applied informatics, which in turn, 
helped inform better overall design. 
Despite the robustness of the FITT model to under-
stand user acceptance of technology, it is not the only one 
reported in the health informatics literature. 
8 31e35 Most </p>

<p>models are complementary, though few have been 
empirically tested in multiple settings and none have 
emerged as superior. Although the FITT model estab-
lishes an approach to assess the readiness of an organisa-
tion to adopt change and the specific facets deserving of 
study, it may not be suitable for all implementation efforts. 
For example, the framework may incompletely model the 
exchange of new information between unlike users in 
a heterogeneous clinician cohort. Also, the framework 
does not explicitly focus upon organisational behaviour 
and, therefore, may incompletely capture the cultural 
differences at the organisational, team or unit level. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Finally, the model was based on analysis of the literature 
and aimed at new technology implementations. It may be 
less capable of detecting sociotechnical barriers in sites 
where clinicians use mature electronic record systems 
with embedded CDS. In our case study, it is notable that 
many barriers were not identified until the second QI 
cycle. Many sociotechnical issues were deeply entrenched 
in the activity system and only recognised in an applied 
setting possibly because (1) end users may not be posi-
tioned to articulate technology requirements, (2) cogni-
tive dissonance and cultural resiliency are best observed in 
context, and (3) FITT dimensions are dynamic and tend 
to evolve in response to system change. </p>

<p>7 9   There are several limitations to this study that deserve 
mention. First, time series methods lack randomised 
controls or blinding and are sensitive to bias. Second, 
the team only examined a single medical centre. Hence, 
our results may not be generalisable. Finally, the time 
and resource constraints typical of quality improvement 
work limited our ability to gather qualitative data. We did 
not digitally record and code clinical activity or user 
narratives. Instead, we relied upon ethnographic survey 
techniques and field notes. 
There are also limitations beyond the parameters of 
this project that deserve mention. First, the model has 
not been well tested in diverse healthcare settings and, to 
our knowledge, has never been tested in a QI domain. 
Hence, it should be applied to other QI initiatives in 
a variety of healthcare contexts to ascertain its relevance 
to other CDS interventions and clinical sub-cultures. 
Second, the model is a theoretical representation of 
many co-existing processes and sub-cultures. Conse-
quently, it may oversimplify or incompletely capture the 
complex healthcare activity system with sufficient gran-
ularity to model all the drivers of change. Finally, the 
model does not take into account the axis of time. As we 
stated before, the introduction of innovations into </p>

<p>a system can have profound and complex social effects. 
Hence, it may be important to capture the organisa-
tional-state pre-implementation and track the evolution 
of state as work practices shift to reinforce the cultural 
norms threatened by new technology. For example, the 
framework did not explicitly articulate any transient 
socio-political phenomena, when, in fact, the facility did 
not have an identified section chief for Orthopaedics at 
the time of implementation. There may have been less 
faculty accountability and less stakeholder buy-in to the 
OCD strategic mission. </p>

<p>Conclusions 
In summary, our clinical decision support system 
increased provider adherence to DVT prophylaxis 
guidelines and positively correlated with medical centre 
performance. This report shows one potential approach 
to synthesising the complementary disciplines of QI and 
sociotechnical theory. Although rationalist improvement 
methodologies appropriately emphasise a data-driven 
ethic, sociotechnical heuristics such as the FITT model 
invoke social science discourse to explain the 'why' as 
much as the 'what' or 'how' of system design. Hidden 
socio-political agendas, dissonant cognitive frameworks, 
and misalignment of expectations must be articulated if 
organisations are to identify and respond intelligently to 
internal resistance to change. Furthermore, this case 
study demonstrates that QI teams leveraging informa-
tion technology must possess a nuanced understanding 
of context, even in mature electronic health record 
environments, if they expect to implement durable and 
sustainable change. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors wish to thank Dr. Jennifer Logan, Dr. Devan 
Kansagara, and Dr. Ana Quinones for their insightful comments during 
manuscript preparation. The authors also wish to thank Dr. David Douglas 
and the Portland VA Informatics Center for project support. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Ethics approval This study was conducted with the approval of the A QI/QA 
expedited review was issued by facility IRBdThis was a quality improvement 
initiative; the intervention was applied uniformly to surgical patients and staff 
as a QI actiondnon-standard care was neither extended or withheld from 
a patient cohortdproviders were not enrolled in treatment arms. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>





<p>BMJ Qual Saf 2011;20:381e389. doi:10.1136/bmjqs.2010.042689 </p>

<p>Original research </p>





<p>Original research </p>

</text></tei>