<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3522449" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Background/Aims: PiggyBac transposable element derived 1 (PGBD1) encodes a molecule in-
volved in epigenetic mechanisms that have been implicated in Alzheimer's disease (AD), and 
recent genome-wide association studies and meta-analyses have indicated that a single nucle-
otide polymorphism (SNP), rs3800324, in PGBD1 could be associated with AD and the age of 
onset. However, no Japanese patients were examined in these studies. The aim of the present 
study was to replicate the previous finding in Japanese AD cases. Methods: We performed a 
case-control study (211 cases and 156 controls) to investigate the association between PGBD1 
and Japanese AD using 4 tag SNPs including rs3800324. Results: Single SNP and haplotype 
analysis showed no association between AD and age of onset, whereas genotypic and allelic 
frequencies of the 4 of apolipoprotein E (APOE) showed an association with AD as expected. 
Conclusion: In Japanese AD, we observed no influence of PGBD1 , as either a risk factor or a 
modifier, even though APOE was associated with AD in this population. </p>

<p>Several studies have investigated the etiology of Alzheimer's disease (AD) and conduct-
ed genetic analyses to identify specific candidate genes. Mutations in amyloid-␤ precursor 
protein (A ␤ PP), presenilin-1 (PS1), and presenilin-2 (PS2) genes are well-known genetic 
causes for familial AD [1] . However, for sporadic and late-onset AD, although the 4 of apo-
lipoprotein E (APOE) is a robust genetic risk factor for AD [2] with a gene-dose effect [3] 
and a relationship with the age of onset [3, 4] , it cannot explain all aspects of the onset of 
AD [3] . Indeed, parallel to findings from genetic studies, environmental factors have also 
been implicated to play an integral role in AD. In addition to genetic candidates, environ-
mental factors have also arisen as risk factors for AD, including diabetes mellitus [5] , smok-
ing [6] , hypertension [7, 8] , and low levels of nutritional antioxidants (e.g., vitamin C and E) 
[9] . Previously, epidemiological factors such as epigenetic mechanisms have also been sug-
gested to play a role in AD [10, 11] . Epigenetics has been implicated in several complex dis-
eases. Hypotheses involving epigenetic mechanisms, which do not involve alterations in the 
DNA sequence, have been suggested regarding changes in gene expression and protein ac-
tivity or as additive factors for the genetic risk in AD patients. Previously, a relationship be-
tween DNA methylation, one type of epigenetic mechanisms, and AD was reported [12] . 
DNA methylation is also involved in retroposons, another type of epigenetic mechanisms 
[13, 14] . PiggyBac transposable element derived 1 (PGBD1) is a member of one of the fami-
lies of transposases related to transposons, and belongs to the subfamily of PGBD genes. 
This gene product is specifically expressed in the brain, but its exact function is still un-
known. A genome-wide association study of family-based case-control studies suggested 
that PGBD1 is involved in AD [15, 16] . In addition, although weak (the minor allele was as-
sociated with an age of onset 1 year earlier than the major allele), a single nucleotide poly-
morphism (SNP) in PGBD1 , rs3800324, has been shown to be associated with the age of 
onset in AD, as a risk modifier in a meta-analysis study [17] . However, no Japanese AD pa-
tients were examined in any of these studies. Thus, PGBD1 may be related to an important 
aspect of the pathophysiology of AD involving an epigenetic mechanism, especially retro-
posons. 
In the present study, we performed a case-control study to investigate whether PGBD1 
is associated with AD using Japanese common tag SNPs, and also if PGBD1 could modulate 
the age of AD onset considering the APOE genotype status. </p>

<p>Patients and Methods </p>

<p>Our samples from sporadic Japanese AD patients (n = 211, male:female = 98: 113) were 
obtained from the Department of Psychiatry, Juntendo University Hospital, Tokyo, Japan, 
and the Department of Psychiatry, Juntendo Koshigaya Hospital, Saitama, Japan. The con-
trol samples (n = 156, male:female = 74: 82) were obtained from healthy volunteers from our 
hospital staff who had no history of dementia or other neuropsychiatric diseases. All AD 
cases were diagnosed according to the NINCDS-ADRDA criteria [18] , and none had a fa-
milial history of AD. The mean age ( 8 SD) of the AD group (68.1 8 10.8 years) was not 
significantly different from that of the control group (62.1 8 8.1 years) with the Student t 
test (t = 5.87, p 1 0.05). Additionally, the distribution of males and females within the two 
groups was not significantly different ( 2 = 0.05, p 1 0.05). The previous study reported that 
the minor allele of rs3800324 in PGBD1 is associated with an age of onset only 1 year ear-
lier than the major allele [17] . Therefore, to accurately investigate the relationship between 
the age of onset and PGBD1 , only the apparent age of onset (accurate within less than 1 year) </p>



<p>Dement Geriatr Cogn Disord Extra 2012;2:496-502 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000345085 
Published online: November 10, 2012 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Ohnuma et al.: No Associations Found between PGBD1 and the Age of Onset in Japanese 
Patients Diagnosed with Sporadic Alzheimer's Disease </p>

<p>www.karger.com/dee </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>

<p>obtained from information from the patients' families (age when any criteria of NINCDS-
ADRDA had appeared) from 67 present AD cases (60.5 8 10.1 years; range 44-81) was used 
for analysis. An accurate age of onset, with an error less than 1 year, was not obtained from 
the remaining 144 patients, and these were excluded from the analysis regarding the age of 
onset. 
Written informed consent was obtained from all participants after the procedures had 
been fully explained in detail to each patient and his/her family. The present study was 
carried out in compliance with the World Medical Association's Declaration of Helsinki 
and was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Juntendo University School of Medi-
cine. 
Genomic DNA was extracted from peripheral white blood cells using a QIAamp DNA 
Blood Maxi kit (Qiagen, Courtaboeuf, France). For the selection of SNPs, tag SNPs for PGBD1 
[ r 
2 1 0.8, minor allele frequencies (MAF) 1 0.05] were chosen from the International HapMap 
Project database (release 27, Phase II + III, February 2009, on NCBI B36 assembly, dbSNP 
b126) using the TAGGER algorithm with a successful TaqMan probe design. Additionally, a 
reported missense SNP, rs3800324 (G 1 A, Gly244Glu) showing a MAF 1 0.05 within a Japa-
nese population, was also chosen as a candidate SNP for PGBD1 from the dbSNP database 
(http:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/). Thus, the following 4 SNPs were investigated for 
PGBD1 : rs2142731, rs3800324, rs3800327, and rs2142730 (the 'rs' notation in front of each 
SNP represents the identification from the US National Center for Biotechnology Informa-
tion SNP cluster within the dbSNP database; http:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/). All of 
these SNPs were analyzed using TaqMan technology (Assay-by-Design TM ). Excluding the 
missense SNP rs3800324, all other SNPs were intronic tag SNPs (genomic map and struc-
tures of the human PGBD1 gene, including the location of the SNPs, were shown in our pre-
vious study [19] ). All investigated SNPs were typed using TaqMan technology with an 
ABI7500 system (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, Calif., USA). All probes and primers were 
designed by the Assay-by-Design service for Applied Biosystems. Polymerase chain reaction 
(PCR) was done with the standard PCR MasterMix reagent kit using a 4-l volume. Addi-
tionally, to ensure the quality of the results, we confirmed the SNPs from a few randomly 
chosen individuals using a direct DNA sequencing method to check for errors in the TaqMan 
method. All genotypes determined by direct sequencing were in agreement with the geno-
types obtained by the TaqMan method for all investigated SNPs. Detailed information on 
PCR conditions and primer pairs is available upon request. APOE genotypes for all samples 
were determined according to a previous report [20] . 
Differences in age between healthy controls and patients were examined using two-
tailed Student's t test, and the 2 test was used to examine differences in gender distribution. 
For the case-control association study, Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) testing of the 
SNPs was done using SNPAlyze V7.0 Pro (Dynacom, Chiba, Japan). The HWE tests were 
carried out for all loci in patients and controls. Differences in genotypic and allelic frequen-
cies were evaluated based on the case-control design using 2 analysis. Linkage disequilib-
rium (LD), denoted as D ', was calculated from the haplotype frequency using the expecta-
tion-maximization algorithm. The LD block was also identified using <rs type="software">SNPAlyse</rs> software 
when D ' was greater than 0.75. Case-control haplotype analysis was also performed using 
<rs type="software">SNPAlyse</rs> software. Permutation analysis was used to determine the empirical significance 
and to calculate the p values based on 10,000 replications. The global p values represent the 
overall significance using the 2 test when the observed versus expected frequencies of all 
haplotypes are considered together. Individual haplotypes were tested for association by 
grouping all other haplotypes together and applying the 2 test with 1 d.f. All p values re-
ported are two-tailed. Statistical significance was defined at p ! 0.05. </p>



<p>Dement Geriatr Cogn Disord Extra 2012;2:496-502 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000345085 
Published online: November 10, 2012 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Ohnuma et al.: No Associations Found between PGBD1 and the Age of Onset in Japanese 
Patients Diagnosed with Sporadic Alzheimer's Disease </p>

<p>www.karger.com/dee </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>

<p>We performed power calculations using the Power Calculator (http://www.sph.umich. 
edu/csg/abecasis/CaTS/). Power was calculated under the prevalence of 0.05 using an addi-
tive or a multiplicative model, based on allelic frequencies of the associated markers ranging 
from 0.22 (rs2142731) to 0.44 (rs3800327), with odds ratios (ORs) ranging from 1.057 
(rs2142731) to 1.305 (rs2142730) for the SNPs investigated and an alpha level of 0.05. 
To analyze interactions between SNPs in PGBD1 and APOE genotypes, logistic regres-
sion analysis was performed using HealthSketch version 2.5 (Dynacom). The probability (P c ) 
of an individual being a case rather than a control is assumed to be affected by a set of SNPs, 
according to the logistic model. For example, logit(P) = b 0 + b 1 x 1 + b 2 x 2 for a single SNP. Here, 
we use a coding scheme x 1 = -1, 0, 1 and x 2 = -0.5, 0.5, -0.5 for genotypes homozygous for 
major alleles, heterozygous, and homozygous for minor alleles (for APOE , 4 was assumed 
to be the minor allele, and 2 and 3 were assumed to be major alleles simultaneously), re-
spectively, to represent an additive effect with x 1 and a dominant/recessive effect with x 2 . The 
weights were estimated with the maximum likelihood method and tested by comparison 
with the null hypothesis logit(P c ) = b 0 (constant). We performed a stepwise forward selection 
procedure with two purposes: the first was to test the relationships among multiple SNPs in 
PGBD1 and the APOE genotype, and the second was to confirm the interaction among the 
SNPs if a significant association with p ! 0.05 was shown with individual logistic models. 
Multiple regression analyses were performed to estimate the relationship among the age of 
onset, APOE status, and the 4 SNPs using <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS software</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">ver. 17.0</rs> for Windows (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">IBM, Chi- cago, Ill., USA</rs>). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Ultimately, 4 SNPs in PGBD1 were genotyped, and the APOE genotype status was ob-
tained in 211 patients with AD and 156 controls, with a genotyping completeness that ranged 
from 99.5 to 99.9%. Results for power analyses demonstrated that the power ranged from 14% 
(rs3800324) to 84% (rs2142730). No deviations from HWE in either patient or control sam-
ples were observed (all p 1 0.05; table 1 ). 
No SNPs in PGBD1 showed any significant association between their allelic or geno-
typic frequencies and AD ( table 1 ). D ' 1 0.75 was assumed to represent a strong LD, and re-
sults indicated that all investigated SNPs for each gene displayed a strong LD block in con-
trols and patients with AD (all D ' 1 0.95) as we previously reported in Japanese controls [19] . 
Additionally, case-control haplotype association analyses using windows of 2, 3, or 4 SNPs 
were performed (minor haplotypes with frequencies less than 3% in both the AD cases and 
controls were omitted), and no haplotype analysis showed a significant association with AD 
( table 1 ). As expected, genotypic and allelic frequencies of APOE showed a significant asso-
ciation with AD, with an increased frequency of 4 in AD ( table 1 ). 
We further evaluated the relationships and interactions among the 4 SNPs in PGBD1 and 
the APOE genotype using logistic regression analysis, which can test for a combinatorial ef-
fect of multiple SNPs and confirm interactions among the 4 SNPs in PGBD1 and the APOE 
genotype with a stepwise procedure. We did not identify any significant interactions be-
tween any combinations of SNPs. Again, only the additive and dominant/recessive models 
for APOE showed a significant association with the onset of AD (OR 2.11 and 1.96, respec-
tively, all p ! 0.01 based on the Wald test). 
Multiple regression analyses did not show any relationship among the age of onset, 
APOE status, and/or the 4 SNPs in PGBD1 (all p 1 0.05). </p>



<p>Dement Geriatr Cogn Disord Extra 2012;2:496-502 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000345085 
Published online: November 10, 2012 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Ohnuma et al.: No Associations Found between PGBD1 and the Age of Onset in Japanese 
Patients Diagnosed with Sporadic Alzheimer's Disease </p>

<p>www.karger.com/dee </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In the present study, PGBD1 , a member of one of the families of transposases that may 
be involved in AD [15, 16] , was investigated for an association with Japanese AD. No single 
SNP and/or haplotype in our case-control analysis of PGBD1 showed an association with 
Japanese AD. In addition, although a missense SNP, rs3800324 in PGBD1 , showed an asso-
ciation with the age of onset in AD as reported previously [17] , the association of the same 
SNP in the present group of Japanese participants was not replicated. That previous study 
was performed with a sufficiently large number of cases (2,455 Caucasian cases) [17] . We are 
aware that the main limitation of our present study is the small number of participants, and 
we should carefully interpret the present negative findings. Our results may have involved a 
type II error (false negative) because although the influence of the 4 allele in APOE in the 
present study showed statistical significance, the OR for the 4 allele in the present AD cas-
es (OR 2.177, 95% C 1.477-3.215) was lower than that observed in a previous study (OR 3.2, 
95% CI 2.9-3.5) [21] . This was probably due to the small number of cases. However, although 
the 4 genotypic and allelic frequencies were lower than expected, we observed a reproduc-
ible association in the present Japanese AD cases. Thus, we conclude that PGDB1 did not af-
fect the age of onset per se in Japanese AD patients to the same degree as the genetic influence 
of APOE . On the other hand, ethnic differences (Caucasian and Japanese) and differences in </p>

<p>Table 1. Distribution and statistical analysis of the PGBD1 polymorphisms and their 2, 3, and 4 SNP-based haplotype analy-
ses with APOE genotype distribution </p>

<p>a PGBD1 polymorphisms and their 2, 3, and 4 SNP-based haplotype analyses </p>

<p>Genotype frequency, n (%) 
p 
value </p>

<p>HWE 
Allele frequency 
n (%) </p>



<p>2 </p>

<p>p 
value </p>

<p>OR 
Haplotype analysis 
(global p value) </p>

<p>C*/AD** 
(95% CI) 
2 SNP-
b ased </p>

<p>3 SNP-
based </p>

<p>4 SNP-
based </p>

<p>rs2142731 A/A 
A/G 
G/G 
0.858 0.472/0.831 </p>

<p>A 
G 
0.095 0.758 </p>

<p>1.057 
AD 
128 (60.7) 74 (35.1) 9 (4.3) 
330 (78.2) 92 (21.8) 
(0.788-1.502) 
C 
91 (58.3) 59 (37.8) 6 (3.8) 
241 (77.2) 71 (22.7) 
0.718 </p>

<p>rs3800324 G/G 
G/A 
A/A 
0.930 0.857/0.900 </p>

<p>G 
A 
0.146 0.703 </p>

<p>1.062 
AD 
91 (43.1) 95 (45.0) 25 (11.8) 
277 (65.6) 145 (34.4) 
(0.779-1.448) 
0.525 
C 
70 (44.9) 69 (44.2) 17 (10.9) 
209 (67.0) 103 (33.0) 
0.852 
0.343 </p>

<p>rs3800327 G/G 
G/C 
C/C 
0.781 0.602/0.330 </p>

<p>G 
C 
0.425 0.515 </p>

<p>1.103 
AD 
62 (29.4) 112 (53.1) 37 (17.5) 
236 (55.9) 186 (44.1) 
(0.821-1.483) 
0.405 
C 
51 (32.7) 80 (51.3) 25 (16.0) 
182 (58.3) 130 (41.7) 
0.210 </p>

<p>rs2142730 C/C 
C/T 
T/T 
0.118 0.871/0.254 </p>

<p>C 
T 
2.781 0.095 </p>

<p>1.305 
AD 
102 (48.3) 95 (45.0) 14 (6.6) 
299 (70.9) 123 (29.1) 
(0.954-1.786) 
C 
67 (42.9) 69 (44.2) 20 (12.8) 
203 (65.1) 109 (34.9) </p>

<p>b APOE genotype distribution </p>

<p>Genotype frequency, n (%) 
p value Allele frequency, n (%) 
2 
OR 1 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>p value </p>

<p>2/2 2/3 2/4 3/3 
3/4 
4/4 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>AD 
1 (0.5) 4 (1.9) 3 (1.4) 117 (55.5) 66 (31.3) 20 (9.5) 
0.0017 
9 (2.1) 304 (72.0) 109 (25.8) 17.4 2.177 
0.0001 
C 
4 (2.6) 5 (3.2) 0 (0) 
106 (67.9) 39 (25.0) 2 (1.3) 
13 (4.2) 256 (82.1) 43 (13.8) 
(1.477-3.215) </p>

<p>C = Controls. p value in bold indicate statistical significance (p &lt; 0.05). 1 4 vs. others. </p>



<p>Dement Geriatr Cogn Disord Extra 2012;2:496-502 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000345085 
Published online: November 10, 2012 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Ohnuma et al.: No Associations Found between PGBD1 and the Age of Onset in Japanese 
Patients Diagnosed with Sporadic Alzheimer's Disease </p>

<p>www.karger.com/dee </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>

<p>the subtype of AD [late-onset AD in the previous study (mean age approx. 78 years) [17] and 
both early-and late-onset AD in the present study (mean age 8 SD 60.5 8 10.1 years, range 
44-81, for the 67 cases with the known age of onset)] may also have led to the different re-
sults. 
Here, we report our current data that will be used for a future meta-analysis study in 
Japanese AD patients and conclude that the influence of PGBD1 as genetic risk factor in dis-
ease onset and for the age of onset as a modifier factor is not present in Japanese sporadic 
AD. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>Funding for this study was provided by the Juntendo Institute of Mental Health in 2012. </p>

<p>Disclosure Statement </p>

<p>We have no potential conflicts of interest. </p>





<p>Dement Geriatr Cogn Disord Extra 2012;2:496-502 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000345085 
Published online: November 10, 2012 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Ohnuma et al.: No Associations Found between PGBD1 and the Age of Onset in Japanese 
Patients Diagnosed with Sporadic Alzheimer's Disease </p>

<p>www.karger.com/dee </p>

<p>© 2012 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>



</text></tei>