<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3296922" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Dietary intakes and plasma concentrations of retinol and carotenoids were estimated in assessing the vitamin A status of Korean adults living 
in Seoul and the metropolitan area. Three consecutive 24-h food recalls were collected from 106 healthy subjects (33 males and 73 females) aged 
20-59 years. Fasting blood samples of the subjects were obtained and plasma retinol and carotenoids were analyzed. The daily vitamin A intakes 
(mean ± SD) were 887.77 ± 401.35 μg retinol equivalents or 531.84 ± 226.42 μg retinol activity equivalents. There were no significant differences 
in vitamin A intakes among age groups. The retinol intake of subjects was 175.92 ± 129.87 μg/day. The retinol intake of the subjects in their 50's 
was significantly lower than those in their 20's and 30's (P &lt; 0.05). Provitamin A carotenoid intakes were 3,828.37 ± 2,196.29 μg/day β-carotene, 
472.57 ± 316.68 μg/day α-carotene, and 412.83 ± 306.46 μg/day β-cryptoxanthin. Approximately 17% of the subjects consumed vitamin A less than 
the Korean Estimated Average Requirements for vitamin A. The plasma retinol concentration was 1.22 ± 0.34 μmol/L. There was no significant 
difference in plasma retinol concentrations among age groups. However, the concentrations of β-carotene, lycopene, and lutein of subjects in their 
50's were significantly higher than those of in their 20's. Only one subject had a plasma retinol concentration &lt; 0.70 μmol/L indicating marginal 
vitamin A status. Plasma retinol concentration in 30% of the subjects was 0.70-&lt; 1.05 μmol/L, which is interpreted as the concentration possibly 
responsive to greater intake of vitamin A. In conclusion, dietary intakes and status of vitamin A were generally adequate in Korean adults examined 
in this study. </p>

<p>Vitamin A is a generic term referring to both preformed 
retinoids and provitamin A carotenoids (α-carotene, β-carotene, 
and β-cryptoxanthin). Retinoids are present only in foods of 
animal origin such as liver, meats, and dairy products, while fruits 
and vegetables are major sources of provitamin A carotenoids. 
Vitamin A is an essential nutrient for eye health, gene expression, 
immune function, and growth in human beings [1]. One of the 
functions of provitamin A carotenoids is their ability to convert 
into retinols in the body [1], and carotenoids (α-carotene, β 
-carotene, β-cryptoxanthin, lutein, zeaxanthin, and lycopene) 
have been suggested to play a role as antioxidants, which are 
associated with a decrease of DNA damage and lipid peroxida-
tion, a maintenance of immune function, as well as inhibition 
of cancer [2-5]. Several epidemiological studies have shown that 
high intakes of fruits and vegetables containing carotenoids are 
associated with relatively low incidences of chronic diseases 
including cardiovascular disease and certain types of cancers [6-8]. 
The Food and Nutrition Board of the Institute of Medicine 
(IOM) in 2001 set a new unit, μg retinol activity equivalents </p>

<p>(μg RAE), to report the Dietary Reference Intakes (DRIs) values 
for vitamin A in the US and Canada [1]. However, the DRIs 
for Koreans, revised in 2010 by the Korean Nutrition Society, 
were given μg retinol equivalents (μg RE) for vitamin A 
recommendations [9] because the bioavailability and bioactivity 
of provitamin A carotenoids has not been determined as of yet 
for Koreans. For the dietary provitamin A carotenoids (α 
-carotene, β-carotene, and β-cryptoxanthin), μg RAE has been 
set as being equivalent to 24 μg, 12 μg, and 24 μg, respectively 
[1]; however, the provitamin A equivalency of μg RE is two 
times higher than that of μg RAE [9]. 
The new equivalency factor by the IOM makes very little 
difference in assessing the adequacy of adult diets whose intake 
of animal products of vitamin A already exceeds their recom-
mendations of vitamin A, while for adults who obtain most of 
their vitamin A from carotenoids of plant products, this new 
conversion factor, μg RAE, for provitamin A carotenoids makes 
an important difference in estimating their dietary vitamin A 
intakes. Recently, Noh et al. [10] reported that Korean adults 
obtained over 80% of vitamin A from plant foods. Although 
average vitamin A intakes of Koreans are over the Recommended </p>

<p>This research was financially supported by the 2010 research fund from the National Research Foundation of Korea (20100017207). 
 § Corresponding Author: Youn-Ok Cho, Tel. 82-2-901-8376, Fax. 82-2-901-8372, Email. yunokcho@duksung.ac.kr 
Received: November 25, 2011, Revised: January 13, 2012, Accepted: January 19, 2012 
ⓒ2012 The Korean Nutrition Society and the Korean Society of Community Nutrition 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>46 </p>

<p>Vitamin A status of Korean adults </p>

<p>Nutrient Intakes (RNI) given as μg RE [9], the vitamin A status 
of Koreans may not be acceptable. Thus, it is important to 
identify vitamin A status with the intakes calculated in both μg 
RE and μg RAE along with an appropriate biochemical index 
indicating vitamin A status in Korean adults. 
Carotenoids are known to function as antioxidants in the body 
[11,12]. Several studies in other countries have reported the 
carotenoid intakes of individuals with their respective plasma 
concentrations [13-16]. However, dietary intake and plasma 
concentrations of carotenoids have been not determined in 
Korean adults. 
Therefore, the purposes of this study were to estimate the 
dietary intake and plasma concentration of retinol and carotenoids 
(α-carotene, β-carotene, β-cryptoxanthin, lutein, zeaxanthin, and 
lycopene) and to assess vitamin A status of 20-59 years old adults 
in Seoul as well as in the metropolitan area in Korea. </p>

<p>Subjects and Methods </p>

<p>Subjects </p>

<p>Healthy adults participated in this study where subjects were 
aged from 20 to 59 years (33 males and 73 females) living in 
Seoul and the metropolitan area between June 2009 and January 
2010. The Institutional Review Board of Duksung Women's 
University approved the study and informed consent was 
obtained from each subject. </p>

<p>Anthropometric measurements </p>

<p>Interviewers measured the weights and heights of subjects in 
light clothing and barefoot. Body mass index (BMI) was calculated 
as weight divided by squared height (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). BMI was evaluated 
by using World Health Organization (WHO) standards for Asians 
[17]. In adults, BMI less than 18.5 kg/m 
2 is defined as under-</p>

<p>weight, BMI of 18.5 to 22.9 kg/m 
2 as normal weight, BMI of </p>

<p>23 to 24.9 kg/m 
2 as overweight, BMI of 25 to 29.9 kg/m 
2 as </p>

<p>obese I, and BMI of more than 30 kg/m 
2 as obese II. </p>

<p>Dietary intake measurement </p>

<p>Three consecutive 24-hour food recalls (2 weekdays and 1 
weekend day) were obtained from each subject by trained 
interviewers using food models. Retinol intakes were estimated 
using a <rs id="software-2" type="software">CAN-pro</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">3.0</rs> nutritional analysis program developed by 
<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">the Korean Nutrition Society</rs> [18]. Carotenoid intakes (α-carotene, 
β-carotene, β-cryptoxanthin, lutein, zeaxanthin, and lycopene) 
were measured by the values of the book, "Phytonutrient Contents 
in Vegetable/Fruits/Legumes," reporting carotenoid contents in 
plant foods [19], the values of carotenoids in some Korean foods 
[20,21], and the carotenoid values in the United States Department 
of Agriculture Food database [22]. Dietary vitamin A intakes </p>

<p>in this study were calculated with retinol and provitamin A 
carotenoid intakes as both μg RE and as μg RAE (μg RE = μg 
retinol + μg β-carotene/6 + μg α-carotene/12 + μg β-cryptoxanthin/ 
12, μg RAE = μg retinol + μg β-carotene/12 + μg α-carotene/24 
+ μg β-cryptoxanthin/24). </p>

<p>Biochemical measurements </p>

<p>Blood samples were collected from the subjects who had fasted 
overnight. Blood was protected from light and was kept cold 
on crushed ice. Blood samples were centrifuged at 3,000rpm at 
5℃ for 10 minutes, and then plasma was frozen at -70℃ until 
analysis. The standards for α-carotene, β-carotene, and lycopene 
were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA). β 
-cryptoxanthin, lutein, and zeaxanthin were purchased from 
Indofine Chemical Company, Inc (Hillsborough, NJ, USA). All 
reagents purchased and used in this study were HPLC grade. 
Plasma retinol and carotenoids were analyzed using the 
high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) method by 
Kim et al. [11]. The HPLC system consisted of two 515 pumps, 
710 auto injector, 2487 dual λ absorbance detector (Waters 
Associates, Inc., Milford, MA, USA), and a C18 reversed-phase 
HPLC column (201 TP54, Vydac, Columbia, MD, USA, 25cm 
× 4.6 mm, 5 μm particle size). Wavelengths of 325 and 450 nm 
were used for the determination of retinol and carotenoids, 
respectively. The HPLC mobile phase was a mixture of 800 mL 
acetonitrile, 100 mL tetrahydrofuran, 60 mL methanol, and 40 
mL of 1% ammonium acetate solution in distilled water contain-
ing 0.1% butylatedhydroxyltoluene. Minimum detectable levels 
were 0.06 ng retinol, 0.09 ng α-carotene, 0.19 ng β-carotene, 
0.11 ng β-cryptoxanthin, 0.06 ng lutein, 0.03 ng zeaxanthin, and 
0.29 ng lycopene. Reproducibility was measured by analyzing 
one of plasma sample in this study in duplicate each time samples 
were analyzed, and the coefficients of variance were &lt; 6% for 
retinol and &lt; 8% for each of the carotenoids. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data were analyzed by age groups (20-29, 30-39, 40-49 and 
50-59 years) using <rs id="software-3" type="software">SAS</rs> version 9.1.3 software (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">SAS Institute, Inc.</rs>., Cary, NC, USA). The differences among age groups were 
analyzed using one-way ANOVA with the Least Significant 
Difference post-hoc test [23]. Pearson's correlation coefficients 
were calculated to determine correlations between intakes and 
plasma concentrations of retinol and carotenoids. Differences 
were considered significant at P &lt; 0.05. Values are reported as 
means ± standard deviations. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Table 1 shows anthropometric measurements of the subjects 
by age group. The mean weight, height, and BMI (mean ± SD) </p>

<p>Sungah Kim et al. </p>



<p>20-29 years (n = 51) 
30-39 years (n = 24) 
40-49 years (n = 21) 
50-59 years (n = 10) 
Total (n = 106) </p>

<p>Male (n) 
20 
7 
3 
3 
33 </p>

<p>F e m a l e ( n ) 
3 1 
1 7 
1 8 
7 
7 3 </p>

<p>Weight (kg) 
61.71 ± 10.39 
62.25 ± 11.53 
61.14 ± 7.70 
58.90 ± 4.65 
61.45 ± 9.72 </p>

<p>Height (cm) 
166.71 ± 7.80 </p>

<p>a1) </p>

<p>165.42 ± 9.49 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>160.33 ± 5.38 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>158.30 ± 3.74 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>164.36 ± 8.06 </p>

<p>BMI 
2) (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
22.16 ± 3.17 
22.63 ± 2.79 
23.75 ± 2.42 
23.51 ± 1.71 
22.71 ± 2.88 </p>

<p>1) Means within a row not sharing the same superscript letters differ significantly (P &lt; 0.05). 
2) Body Mass Index. </p>

<p>Table 1. Anthropometric measurement of 106 adults aged 20-59 years living in Seoul and the metropolitan area in Korea </p>

<p>20-29 years (n = 51) 
30-39 years (n = 24) 
40-49 years (n = 21) 
50-59 years (n = 10) 
Total (n = 106) </p>

<p>Retinol (μg / day) 
197.01 ± 141.57 </p>

<p>a1) </p>

<p>203.59 ± 150.74 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>133.51 ± 60.28 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>91.00 ± 50.20 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>175.92 ± 129.87 </p>

<p>α-Carotene (μg / day) 
454.98 ± 299.70 
483.53 ± 342.89 
519.05 ± 339.09 
438.43 ± 326.52 
472.57 ± 316.68 </p>

<p>β-Carotene (μg / day) 
3,248.87 ± 1,574.92 
4,346.06 ± 2,913.91 
4,150.47 ± 2,246.49 
4,864.99 ± 2,351.43 
3,828.37 ± 2,196.29 </p>

<p>β-Cryptoxanthin (μg / day) 
384.34 ± 301.73 
450.42 ± 318.05 
436.62 ± 307.63 
417.91 ± 333.76 
412.82 ± 306.46 </p>

<p>Lutein/Zeaxanthin (μg / day) 
2,303.99 ± 1,379.94 
3,517.30 ± 3,487.79 
3,757.21 ± 3,396.43 
3,842.26 ± 2,588.78 
3,011.73 ± 2,611.84 </p>

<p>Lycopene (μg / day) 
2,397.15 ± 3,632.38 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>5,852.89 ± 7,199.24 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>7,132.25 ± 6,863.11 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>8,309.91 ± 1,3361.41 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>4,675.47 ± 6,6871.20 </p>

<p>Vitamin A (μg RE </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) / day) 
808.44 ± 327.54 
1,005.76 ± 512.86 
904.90 ± 412.77 
973.19 ± 388.48 
887.77 ± 401.35 </p>

<p>Vitamin A (μg RAE </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) / day) 
502.73 ± 208.44 
604.67 ± 276.57 
519.21 ± 220.52 
532.09 ± 184.11 
531.84 ± 226.42 </p>

<p>1) Means within a row not sharing the same superscript letters differ significantly (P &lt; 0.05). 
2) Retinol equivalents. 
3) Retinol activity equivalents. </p>

<p>Table 2. Dietary intakes of retinol, carotenoids, and vitamin A of 106 adults aged 20-59 years living in Seoul and the metropolitan area in Korea </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Percentages of Korean adults consuming vitamin A less than Korean 
Dietary Reference Intakes (DRI) and less than US/Canadian DRI. None of the 
subjects consumed vitamin A more than Tolerable Upper Intake Level in Korean 
DRI and US/Canadian DRI. Estimated Average Requirement, EAR; Recommended 
Nutrient Intakes, RNI; and Recommended Dietary Allowance, RDA. </p>

<p>were 61.45 ± 9.72 kg, 164.36 ± 8.06 cm, and 22.71 ± 2.88 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, 
respectively. There were no significant differences in BMI among 
the groups. BMI was compared by using WHO standards [17]; 
4.72% of the subjects were underweight, 37.59% were normal 
weight, 24.53% were overweight, 19.81% were obese I, and 0.94 
% were obese II. 
Dietary intakes of retinol, carotenoids, and vitamin A are 
shown in Table 2. The mean retinol intake of the subjects was 
175.92 ± 129.87 μg/day, and provitamin A carotenoid intakes 
were 472.57 ± 316.68 μg/day α-carotene, 3,828.37 ± 2,196.29 μ 
g/day β-carotene, and 412.82 ± 306.46 μg/day β-cryptoxanthin. 
The daily retinol intakes of subjects in the 50's age group were </p>

<p>significantly lower than those in their 20's and 30's. The retinol 
intakes per 1,000 kcal in the 50's age group (44.63 μg/1,000 
kcal) were also significantly lower than those in their 20's and 
30's (96.02 and 120.04 μg/1,000 kcal, respectively) (data not 
shown). However, lycopene intakes of subjects in their 50's were 
significantly higher than those in their 20's (P &lt; 0.05). Dietary 
intakes of β-carotene and lutein/zeaxanthin tended to increase 
by age. The daily vitamin A intakes were 887.77 ± 401.35 μg 
RE or 531.84 ± 226.42 μg RAE. There was no significant 
difference observed in vitamin A intakes among the age groups. 
Percentages of subjects consuming less quantities of vitamin 
A than suggested by Korean DRIs and US/Canadian DRIs are 
given in Fig. 1. Out of total subjects, 9.43% and 29.25% 
consumed less than the Korean Estimated Average Requirements 
(EAR) and RNI, respectively. However, 52.83% and 83.96% of 
subjects consumed less than EAR and Recommended Dietary 
Allowance (RDA) of US/Canadian DRIs, respectively. None of 
the subjects consumed vitamin A over the Tolerable Upper Intake 
Levels in both Korean and US/Canadian DRIs. 
Plasma concentrations of retinol and carotenoids in the subjects 
are given in Table 3. The mean plasma retinol concentration was 
1.22 ± 0.34 μmol/L. There was no significant difference in plasma 
retinol concentrations among age groups. The concentrations of 
β-carotene, lycopene, and lutein of subjects in the 50's age group 
were significantly higher than those in the 20's age group (P 
&lt; 0.05). But, there were no significant differences in α-carotene, 
β-cryptoxanthin, and zeaxanthin concentrations among any of 
the age groups. 
Fig. 2 shows the distribution of plasma retinol concentrations. 
Only one male subject (0.94%) was marginal vitamin A status </p>

<p>48 </p>

<p>Vitamin A status of Korean adults </p>

<p>Dietary intakes 
Plasma concentration </p>

<p>Retinol 
α-Carotene 
β-Carotene 
β-Cryptoxanthin 
Lutein 
Zeaxanthin 
Lycopene </p>

<p>Retinol 
0.06548 (0.5028) 
1) 0.02582 (0.7918) -0.01398 (0.8863) 
-0.04292 (0.6607) 0.03500 (0.7204) 
-0.08240 (0.3988) -0.08033 (0.4108) </p>

<p>α-Carotene 
0.04382 (0.6541) -0.11842 (0.2244) -0.11356 (0.2441) 
0.05509 (0.5731) -0.06781 (0.4877) 
0.02936 (0.7641) -0.10061 (0.3025) </p>

<p>β-Carotene 
-0.02774 (0.7767) -0.01613 (0.8690) 0.29054 (0.0024)** 
0.14912 (0.1253) 0.20640 (0.0329)* 0.16606 (0.0874) 0.18914 (0.0510) </p>

<p>β-Cryptoxanthin -0.02638 (0.7874) -0.03837 (0.6948) 0.04904 (0.6160) 
-0.04507 (0.6448) -0.01275 (0.8963) 
-0.01432 (0.8836) 0.09703 (0.3201) </p>

<p>Lutein/Zeaxanthin -0.04746 (0.6273) 0.07024 (0.4722) 0.44334 (&lt;0.0001)*** 0.19896 (0.0399)* 0.34009 (0.0003)*** 0.24412 (0.0113)* 0.27904 (0.0036)** </p>

<p>Lycopene 
-0.05128 (0.5999) -0.09344 (0.3384) 0.06837 (0.4841) 
0.04097 (0.6752) 0.01999 (0.8380) 
0.01516 (0.8768) -0.03539 (0.7174) </p>

<p>1) P-value 
* significant at P &lt; 0.05, ** significant at P &lt; 0.01, *** significant at P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Table 4. Correlations between dietary intakes and plasma concentrations of retinol and carotenoids </p>

<p>20-29 years (n = 51) 
30-39 years (n = 24) 
40-49 years (n = 21) 
50-59 years (n = 10) 
Total (n = 106) </p>

<p>Retinol (μmol/L) 
1.15 ± 0.25 
1.38 ± 0.46 
1.18 ± 0.38 
1.27 ± 0.26 
1.22 ± 0.34 </p>

<p>α-Carotene (μmol/L) 
0.10 ± 0.08 
0.14 ± 0.10 
0.11 ± 0.05 
0.09 ± 0.03 
0.11 ± 0.08 </p>

<p>β-Carotene (μmol/L) 
0.63 ± 0.47 </p>

<p>b1) </p>

<p>0.94 ± 0.62 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>0.98 ± 0.54 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>1.13 ± 0.32 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.82 ± 0.54 </p>

<p>β-Cryptoxanthin (μmol/L) 
0.10 ± 0.05 
0.09 ± 0.04 
0.13 ± 0.17 
0.10 ± 0.03 
0.10 ± 0.09 </p>

<p>Lutein (μmol/L) 
0.23 ± 0.09 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.31 ± 0.15 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.32 ± 0.15 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.42 ± 0.17 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.28 ± 0.14 </p>

<p>Zeaxanthin (μmol/L) 
0.06 ± 0.03 
0.08 ± 0.05 
0.07 ± 0.03 
0.08 ± 0.04 
0.07 ± 0.04 </p>

<p>Lycopene (μmol/L) 
0.85 ± 0.37 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.00 ± 0.39 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.97 ± 0.58 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.35 ± 0.47 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.96 ± 0.45 </p>

<p>1) Means within a row not sharing the same superscript letters differ significantly (P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Table 3. Plasma concentrations of retinol and carotenoids of 106 adults aged 20-59 years living in Seoul and the metropolitan area in Korea </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Distribution of plasma retinol concentrations of 106 adults aged 20-59 
years in living in Seoul and the metropolitan area in Korea. </p>

<p>based on plasma retinol concentration &lt; 0.70 μmol/L. Plasma 
retinol concentrations of 30% of the subjects were 0.70-&lt; 1.05 
μmol/L, which may be interpreted as a vitamin A status possibly 
responsive to greater intake of vitamin A. 
Table 4 shows the correlations between dietary intakes and 
plasma concentrations of retinol as well as carotenoids. Dietary 
intake of β-carotene was positively correlated with plasma β 
-carotene concentration (r = 0.29054, P &lt; 0.01) and also with 
plasma lutein concentration (r = 0.20640, P &lt; 0.05). Dietary 
intake of lutein/zeaxanthin was positively correlated with plasma 
concentrations of β-carotene (r = 0.44334, P &lt; 0.0001), β 
-cryptoxanthin (r = 0.19896, P &lt; 0.05), lutein (r = 0.34009, P &lt; 
0.001), zeaxanthin (r = 0.24412, P &lt; 0.05), and lycopene (r = 
0.27904, P &lt; 0.01). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study determined dietary intakes and plasma concen-
trations of retinol and carotenoids (α-carotene, β-carotene, β 
-cryptoxanthin, lutein, zeaxanthin, and lycopene), and determined 
the vitamin A status of 20-59 years old adults in Seoul and the 
metropolitan area in Korea. 
The Korean DRIs in 2010 are given as μg RE while US/ 
Canadian DRIs are expressed as μg RAE for vitamin A 
recommendations. The Korean vitamin A EARs for males and 
females (≥ 20 years) are 500 to 540 μg RE and 430 to 460 
μg RE, respectively [9]. The US/Canadian vitamin A EARs are 
625 μg RAE and 500 μg RAE for males and females (≥ 20 
years), respectively [1]. 
In this study, the mean vitamin A intake is in line with vitamin 
A intakes of Koreans aged 19 to 64 years (787.9 ± 30.1 μg 
RE/day) reported in the Korea National Health and Nutrition 
Examination Survey, 2008, (KNHANES IV-2) (n = 4,816) [24]. 
However, the mean intake was lower than that of 24 to 
67-year-old Japanese adults (1,175 ± 659 μg RE/day) (n = 53) 
[25], and was much lower than that demonstrated by the National 
Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES), 1999-
2000, for the US population (n = 4239) aged over 20 years 
(744.67 μg RAE/day) [26]. The mean retinol intake from this 
study (175.92 ± 129.87 μg/day) was relatively lower than those 
of US adults (490 μg/day) in the NHANES, 1999-2000, (n = 
4239) [26] and 19 to 64 year-old UK adults (462 μg/day) in 
the National Diet &amp; Nutrition Survey (NDNS), 2000-2001 (n 
= 1724) [27]. However, the mean daily carotenoid intakes in 
the current study were much higher than found in African-
American adults (401 μg α-carotene, 2,867 μg β-carotene, 97 </p>

<p>Sungah Kim et al. </p>



<p>μg β-cryptoxanthin, and 2,787 μg lycopene) [28] and the NDNS 
in the UK adults (331 μg α-carotene, 1,777.5 μg β-carotene, and 
67 μg β-cryptoxanthin) (n = 1,724) [27]. Several epidemiological 
studies have shown that high intakes of carotenoids are associated 
with relatively low risks of chronic diseases including cardiovascular 
disease and certain types of cancers [6-8]. Korean adults obtain 
their vitamin A mainly from plant foods [10]. Therefore, higher 
intakes of carotenoids of Korean adults may play an essential 
role in potent antioxidant concentrations and modulating the 
pathogenesis of several chronic degenerative diseases [29]. 
Both Korean [9] and the US/Canadian [1] groups have 
established the vitamin A recommendations using the EAR and 
RNI/RDA. In this study, 9.43% and 52.83% of subjects consumed 
less than vitamin A EARs for Koreans and US/Canadians, 
respectively. According to the NHANES, 2001-2002, 55 to 59 
% of US adults (n = 1988) consumed less than recommended 
by vitamin A EARs [30], which is in line with the results in 
this study. The subjects with in this study consuming lower levels 
than vitamin A RNIs for Koreans was 29.25 %, but 83.96 % 
consumed less than vitamin A RDAs of US/Canadian DRI. 
Although the values of Korean RNI and US/Canadian RDA are 
similar, the conversion factors of provitamin A carotenoids are 
different between them; therefore, there is a large difference in 
the prevalence of inadequate vitamin A intakes in the current 
study based on Korean RNI and US/Canadian RDA. 
A biochemical indicator, plasma (or serum) retinol is currently 
recommended for determining whether vitamin A deficiency is 
a public health problem [31]. In adults, appropriate cut-off levels 
are less firmly established [32], because plasma retinol concentration 
is homeostatically controlled and will not drop until body stores 
are significantly compromised [33]. However, determining the 
prevalence of plasma retinol concentrations below a defined 
cut-off point remains one of the most commonly used and widely 
accepted approach for assessing the vitamin A status of entire 
populations [34]. For assessing vitamin A status in adults, we 
set critical cut-off points for plasma retinol concentration at &lt; 
0.35 μmol/L, indicated as vitamin A deficiency, &lt; 0.70 μmol/L, 
generally accepted as indicating marginal vitamin A status, and 
0.7-&lt; 1.05 μmol/L, interpreted as possibly responsive to greater 
intake of vitamin A [35]. 
The mean plasma retinol concentration of Korean adults in 
this study was 1.22 ± 0.34 μmol/L, which was lower than the 
mean retinol concentrations of US adults (2.02 ± 0.41 μmol/L) 
(n = 307) and of Japanese 40 to 69 years-old adults (1.99 μmol/L) 
[36,37]. The mean plasma α-carotene, β-cryptoxanthin, lutein, 
zeaxanthin, and lycopene concentrations of the adults in this 
study were in line with means of a random sample of 307 
American adults [36] and 591 Dutch adults [38]. But, the mean 
plasma β-carotene concentration (0.82 ± 0.54 μmol/L) of this 
study was much higher than those of American adults (0.52 μ 
mol/L) [36] and Dutch adults (0.271 ± 0.168 μmol/L) [38], which 
may result from higher intakes of β-carotene in the current study 
than in Western countries [36,38]. In the present study, there </p>

<p>is a significant positive correlation between intakes and plasma 
concentrations of β-carotene (r = 0.29054, P &lt; 0.01). High 
intakes and plasma concentrations of β-carotene in Korean adults 
may be good for maintaining health, because β-carotene is one 
of the powerful antioxidants [39]. 
None of the subjects had a plasma retinol concentration &lt; 0.35 
μmol/L, which is indicative of vitamin A deficiency. A plasma 
retinol concentration &lt; 0.7 μmol/L is used to indicate marginal 
vitamin A status and a plasma retinol concentration 0.7-&lt; 1.05 
μmol/L is the potential to get better as a high intake of vitamin 
A [35]. In this study, only one male subject (0.94 %) had plasma 
retinol concentration &lt; 0.7 μmol/L, and 30.19 % of subjects had 
plasma retinol concentration 0.7-&lt; 1.05 μmol/L. However, 0.63 
% had plasma retinol concentration &lt; 1.05 μmol/L in non-
Hispanic adults and Mexican American adults aged &gt; 19 years 
(n = 10,403) [40], which was lower than that of subjects in this 
study. 
In conclusion, dietary intakes and status of vitamin A were 
generally adequate in Korean adults of this study, although 17 
% of the subjects had low dietary intakes (less than Korean 
EARs) and one subjects had marginal vitamin A status (plasma 
retinol concentrations &lt; 0.70 μmol/L). However, vitamin A 
intakes less than EARs for US/Canadians were indicated in 53 
% of the adults and plasma retinol concentrations of 30 % were 
0.70-&lt; 1.05 μmol/L, which is interpreted as possibly responsive 
to greater intake of vitamin A. Therefore, some individuals in 
Korea may exhibit an impairment of vitamin A function, and 
vitamin A status may improve with an increase of vitamin A 
consumption. Some adults in Korea need to be encouraged to 
consume vitamin A-rich food sources and be necessary to 
monitor their vitamin A status. </p>







</text></tei>