<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3390076" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background To investigate the effects of collateral coronary circulation on the outcome of the patients with anterior myocardial 
infarction (MI) with left anterior desending artery occlusion abruptly. Methods Data of 189 patients with acute anterior MI who had a 
primary percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) in the first 12 h from the onset of symptoms between January 2004 and December 2008 
were retrospective analyzed. Left anterior descending arteries (LAD) of all patients were occluded. LADs were reopened with primary PCI. 
According to the collateral circulation, all patients were classified to two groups: no collateral group (n = 111), patients without angiographic 
collateral filling of LAD or side branches (collateral index 0) and collateral group (n = 78), and patients with angiographic collateral filling of 
LAD or side branches (collateral index 1, 2 or 3). At one year's follow-up, the occurrence of death, reinfarction, stent thrombosis (ST), target 
vessel revascularization and readmission because of heart failure were observed. Results At one year, the mortality was lower in patients 
with collateral circulation compared with those without collateral circulation (1% vs. 8%, P = 0.049), whereas there were no differences in 
the occurrence of reinfarction, ST, target vessel revascularization and readmission because of heart failure. The occurrence of composite of 
endpoint was lower in patients with collateral circulation compared with those without collateral circulation (12% vs. 26%; P = 0.014). 
Conclusions Pre-exist collateral circulation may prefigure the satisfactory prognosis to the patients with acute anterior MI after primary 
PCI in the first 12 h of MI onset. </p>

<p>Anterior infarcts often leads to unsatisfactory prognosis 
because of impaired left ventricular function. Anterior 
infarcts are associated with a larger enzymatic infarct size 
and greater reduction in left ventricular ejection fraction 
(LVEF) compared with nonanterior infarcts. 
[1] Reperfusion </p>

<p>of the occluded coronary artery early after acute myocardial 
infarction (AMI) limits infarct size, improvers LVEF, and 
enhances survival. 
[2] In some patients, collateral circulations </p>

<p>will emerge shortly after the coronary arteries' occlusion. It 
is unknown what is the role of collateral circulation in 
prognosis of the patients with anterior AMI after percutaneous 
coronary intervention (PCI). The main purpose of the 
present study was to find the effect of collateral circulation 
on patients' outcome in the patients with anterior AMI who </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Ya-Ling Han, PhD, Department of Cardiology, Shen </p>

<p>Yang North Hospital, Liao Ning Province, China. hanyl@medmail.com.cn 
Telephone: +86-24-288511236 
Fax: +86-24-28851120 </p>

<p>Received: February 13, 2011 
Revised: March 6, 2011 </p>

<p>Accepted: March 13, 2011 
Published online: June 28, 2011 </p>

<p>had primary PCI within the first 12 h from the onset of 
symptoms. </p>

<p>2 Methods </p>

<p>2.1 Study patients </p>

<p>We selected patients who fulfilled all the following 
criteria: (1) admission to the hospital because of anterior 
wall AMI (continuous ischemic chest pain lasting &gt; 30 min 
and a minimum of 0.2 mV of ST segment elevation in two 
contiguous anterior precordial leads); (2) diagnostic 
coronary angiography showing complete occlusion of the 
left anterior descending coronary artery (LAD) (Thrombolysis 
in Myocardial Infarction [TIMI] flow grade 0 or 1); (3) 
treatment by primary PCI within the first 12 h of the onset 
of symptoms; and (4) left and right coronary angiograms 
obtained before the attempted angioplasty of sufficient 
quality to assess the filling of the LAD and side branches by 
collateral circulation. Patients with AMI secondary to acute 
or subacute coronary occlusion after PCI or coronary artery 
bypass graft surgery (CABG), patients with pulmonary 
edema, cardiac shock, patients treated by PCI after failed </p>

<p>http://www.jgc301.com; jgc@mail.sciencep.com | Journal of Geriatric Cardiology </p>



<p>Wang B et al. Primary PCI in Anterior AMI </p>

<p>thrombolysis (rescue PCI), and, patients with previous 
anterior infarction were excluded. The patients in this study 
were classified into two groups: no collateral group, patients 
without angiographic collateral filling of LAD or side 
branches (collateral index 0); collateral group, patients with 
angiographic collateral filling of LAD or side branches 
(collateral index 1, 2 or 3). </p>

<p>[3] </p>

<p>2.2 Coronary angiography and primary angioplasty </p>

<p>Patients orally received 600 mg clopidogrel and 300 mg 
aspirin as soon as possible unless there was a known allergy. 
Coronary angiography and primary PCI were performed in 
the first 12 h from the onset of symptoms of AMI. Once the 
radial or femoral artery was catheterized, 5000 IU of heparin 
was administered with additional boluses of 2000 IU if 
needed to achieve an activated clotting time of 250 s to 350 s. 
Coronary arteriograms were obtained in at least two 
projections. Flow in the LAD was determined before and 
after primary PCI and graded as described in the TIMI 
trial. 
[4] The LAD occlusion was considered proximal if it </p>

<p>was located before the origin of the first well developed 
septal branch, distal if it was located after the origin of the 
third diagonal branch and mid if located between these 
limits. 
[5] Primary PCI was performed with conventional </p>

<p>catheter balloon technique. 
[6] Stents were used routinely in </p>

<p>the target lesion. The policy was to perform angioplasty 
only to the infarct-related artery, but in exceptional cases 
additional angioplasty to another vessel was performed 
because of compromised hemodynamic status. Intraaortic 
balloon pumping was used in patients with hemodynamic 
instability or established cardiogenic shock. The primary 
PCI was considered successful when flow in the infarct-
related artery at the end of the procedure was TIMI grade 3 
and the residual stenosis was less than 30%. 
Before March 2007, most of patients were implanted 
with bare-metal stents (BMS) and since then drug-eluting 
stent (DES) was extensively used. Postinterventional 
antiplatelet therapy consisted of clopidogrel (150 mg/d for 
two weeks, continued for three months for BMS or one year 
for DES) and aspirin (300 mg/d for one month and continued 
indefinitely). </p>

<p>2.3 Coronary collateral circulation </p>

<p>Collateral circulation to the occluded LAD was assessed 
in coronary cineangiograms by two experienced coronary 
angiographers who had no knowledge of patient data. 
Collateral circulation was graded by using a semiquantitative 
scale from 0 to 3 (collateral index) depending on the degree 
of angiographic opacification of the occluded LAD in the 
best injection: 0 = no collateral circulation; 1 = collateral </p>

<p>filling of LAD side branches without visualization of any 
epicardial segment; 2 = collateral partial filling of the 
epicardial segment, and 3 = collateral filling of the complete 
epicardial segment. 
[3] In case of noncoincidence, the </p>

<p>angiographers reached a consensus. </p>

<p>2.4 Follow-up </p>

<p>All patients in the study were follow-up for one year. The 
occurrence of death, reinfarction, stent thrombosis (ST), 
target vessel revascularization and readmission because of 
heart failure were observed. The follow-up information was 
obtained by a phone call at one year. Reinfarction was 
defined as the recurrence of ischemic chest pain after 
primary PCI of ≥ 30 min duration with ST segment 
elevation of ≥ 0.1 mV over the previous ST segment in two 
contiguous leads and the MB fraction of creatine kinase 
(CK-MB) profile consistent with the diagnosis. ST was 
defined as thrombosis in stent by angiography. Target vessel 
revascularization was defined as PCI or coronary artery 
bypass graft due to restenosis or reocclusion of the target 
lesion in association with objective evidence of ischemia or 
viable myocardium. Historical angina pectoris was defined 
as typical chest pain episode(s) persisting &lt; 30 min either at 
rest or with effort before 24 h before onset of AMI. </p>

<p>2.5 Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Continuous variables followed a normal distribution is 
expressed as mean ± SD. For comparisons of continuous 
variables between both groups the Student t test for 
unpaired observations was used. We used the chi-square test 
to compare categoric variables between groups unless 
expected values were less than 5, in which case we used the 
Fisher exact test. The Cox proportional hazards model was 
used to assess the association between the composite 
endpoint and coronary collateral circulation. All results 
were analyzed by using a two-sided significance level of 
0.05. Data analyses were performed by using the statistical 
software <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">11.0</rs> from SPSS Inc. (USA). </p>

<p>3 Results </p>

<p>3.1 Baseline characteristics of patients </p>

<p>From January 2004 to December 2008, 456 patients with 
anterior wall AMI within the first 12 h of the onset of 
symptoms were treated in our center by primary PCI. For 
the present analysis, we selected 189 of these patients who 
fulfilled the above mentioned criteria. The 267 patients who 
did not fulfilled the criteria were excluded. Of the 189 
patients included, 111 (59%) did not have angiographically 
visible collateral circulation to the LAD, 78 (41%) patients, </p>

<p>Journal of Geriatric Cardiology | jgc@mail.sciencep.com; http://www.jgc301.com </p>

<p>Wang B et al. Primary PCI in Anterior AMI </p>



<p>were found some collateral circulation of the LAD (collateral 
index 1 in 60 patients, index 2 in 16 patients and index 3 in 
2 patient). 
The baseline clinical characteristics of groups are 
summarized in Table 1. There were no significant differences 
in age, gender or prevalence of the main cardiovascular risk 
factors between the two groups. </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline clinical characteristics of study groups. </p>

<p>No collateral 
(n = 111) </p>

<p>Collateral 
(n = 78) </p>

<p>P 
Value 
Age(yr), mean ± SD 
57 ± 11 
55 ± 12 
0.583 </p>

<p>Female 
21 (19%) 
11 (14%) 
0.385 </p>

<p>Hypertension 
44 (40%) 
32 (40%) 
0.989 </p>

<p>Hypercholesterolemia 
23 (21%) 
14 (18%) 
0.537 </p>

<p>Cigarette smoking 
70 (63%) 
45 (58%) 
0.698 </p>

<p>Diabetes mellitus 
16 (14%) 
11 (14%) 
0.952 </p>

<p>History of angina pectoris 
67 (60%) 
56 (72%) 
0.104 </p>

<p>3.2 PCI procedure results </p>

<p>The angiographic finding and the results of primary PCI 
in the two groups are presented in Table 2. The elapsed time 
between the onset of symptoms suggestive of AMI and the </p>

<p>angiography was 392 ± 160 min and the elapsed time 
between the onset of symptoms suggestive of AMI and the 
opening of LAD was 402 ± 160 min in no collateral group, 
which were significantly shorter as compared with that in 
collateral group (472 ± 154 min and 482 ± 154 min, P = 
0.001). </p>

<p>3.3 Follow-up </p>

<p>The follow-up results of one year were presented in 
Table 3. Nine patients in no collateral group after PCI died. 
Five of them died in hospital, one died of refractory 
ventricular fibrillation, three died of cardiogenic shock, one 
died of heart rupture. Four of them died after discharge, one 
died of refractory heart failure, one died of reinfarction, one 
died of heart rupture and one died of sudden death. One 
patient died of refractory heart failure after discharge in 
collateral group. The mortality in no collateral group was 
9/111 (8%) was significantly higher than that in collateral 
group (1/78 [1%], P = 0.049). The occurrence of reinfarc-
tion, ST, TVR and readimission because of heart failure was 
similar in the 2 groups. The composite endpoint was higher 
in no collateral group (29/111 [26%] vs. 9/78 </p>

<p>Table 2. Angiographic findings and primary PCI results. Data are presented as mean ± SD or n(%). </p>

<p>No collateral 
(n = 111) </p>

<p>Collateral 
(n = 78) 
P Value </p>

<p>Symptom to angiography time (min) 
392 ± 160 
472 ± 154 
0.001 </p>

<p>Symptom to balloon time (min) 
402 ± 160 
482 ± 154 
0.001 </p>

<p>Collateral circulation </p>

<p>0 
111 </p>

<p>1 
60 (77%) </p>

<p>2 
16 (21%) </p>

<p>3 
2 (3%) </p>

<p>Level of LAD occlusion 
0.870 </p>

<p>Distal segment 
0 
0 </p>

<p>Middle segment 
54 (46%) 
37 (50%) </p>

<p>Proximal segment 
57 (54%) 
41 (51%) </p>

<p>TIMI flow in LAD after PCI 
0.838 </p>

<p>Grade 0 
1 (1%) 
0 (0%) </p>

<p>Grade 1 
1 (1%) 
2 (3%) </p>

<p>Grade 2 
2 (2%) 
1 (1%) </p>

<p>Grade 3 
107 (96%) 
75 (96%) </p>

<p>IABP in PCI 
7 (6%) 
2 (3%) 
0.202 </p>

<p>Successful primary PCI 
109 (98%) 
75 (96%) 
0.405 </p>

<p>DES used 
56 (50%) 
40 (52%) 
0.840 </p>

<p>PCI: percutaneous coronary intervention; IABP: intra-aortic balloon pump; DES: drug eluting stent; LAD: Left anterior descending arteries. </p>

<p>http://www.jgc301.com; jgc@mail.sciencep.com | Journal of Geriatric Cardiology </p>



<p>Wang B et al. Primary PCI in Anterior AMI </p>

<p>Table 3. Results of follow-up. </p>

<p>No collateral 
(n = 111) </p>

<p>Collateral 
(n = 78) </p>

<p>P 
Value </p>

<p>Death 
9 (8%) 
1 (1%) 
0.049 </p>

<p>ST 
4 (4%) 
1 (1%) 
0.312 </p>

<p>Reinfarction 
5 (5%) 
1 (1%) 
0.210 </p>

<p>TVR 
10 (9%) 
3 (4%) 
0.137 </p>

<p>PCI 
9 
3 </p>

<p>CABG 
1 
0 
Readmission because of 
heart failure 
9 (8%) 
4 (5%) 
0.312 </p>

<p>Composite endpoint 
29 (26%) 
9 (12%) 
0.014 </p>

<p>CABG: coronary artery bypass graft surgery. </p>

<p>[12%], P = 0.014). 
The association between the composition of endpoint and 
coronary collateral circulation (with or without), the LAD 
occlusion location (proximal or non-proximal), sex, smoking, 
history of angina pectoris, diabetes mellitus, hypertension, 
hypercholesterolemia, symptom to balloon time was tested 
with the Cox proportional hazards model. The model 
indentified without collateral circulation (hazard ratio[HR] 
= 2.916, 95%CI: 1.291-6.586; P = 0.010) and the proximal 
LAD occlusion (HR = 2.196, 95%CI: 1.073-4.492; P = 
0.031) were independent predictors of one year composite 
endpoint. 
The occurrence of composite endpoint in patients with 
collateral coronary circulation was lower than that in patient 
without collateral coronary circulation in those patients 
received PCI within six hours of symptoms (0/19 [0] vs. 
16/53 [30.2%], P = 0.008), but not in those received PCI 
between 6 to 12 h after symptoms (9/59 [15.5%] vs. 13/58 
[22.4%], P = 0.353). For patients with collateral coronary 
circulation, the occurrence of composite endpoint in those 
who received PCI between 6 h and 12 h after symptom 
onset was lower than that in patients without collateral 
coronary circulation but received PCI within six hours of 
symptoms (9/59 [15.5%] vs. 16/53 [30.2%], P = 0.023). </p>

<p>4 Discussion </p>

<p>The coronary collateral circulation is an alternative 
source of blood supply to a myocardium jeopardized by 
abruptly occluded vessels, preventing myocardial death and 
favoring myocardial recovery after reperfusion therapy. 
Howerer, the functional significance of collateral circulation 
in AMI has been a matter of debate for many years. 
[7-8] It </p>

<p>has been traditionally assumed that coronary arteries are 
functional end arteries in the absence of stenoses, but it also 
was reported that there are functional collateral vessels to </p>

<p>the extent in humans with angiographically normal coronary 
arteries. 
[9] Factors that may influence the presence of </p>

<p>collaterals after the onset of AMI have been demonstrated in 
previous clinical studies. The recruitment of collateral 
circulation is affected by the presence of multivessel 
disease, 
[10] preinfarction angina, </p>

<p>[5] </p>

<p>history of angina 
pectoris, 
[11] time from onset to cardiac catheterization. 
[12] It </p>

<p>was reported that collateral circulation did not exert a 
protective effect in patients who underwent primary PCI. In 
that paper, the author didn't analyse the outcome of patients 
with anterior AMI and only chose the patients with AMI in 
the first six hours of AMI onset. 
[13] The patients with </p>

<p>LAD-related infarcts had a worse prognosis compared with 
the patients with non-LAD-related infarcts because of a 
lower residual LVEF. 
[1] So, the study for collateral </p>

<p>circulation to the LAD-related infarcts may be important. 
In the first six hours of AMI onset, 17% of patients with 
anterior AMI were found angiographic collateral circulation. </p>

<p>[13] </p>

<p>In other study, collateral circulations were visible in nearly 
40% of patient with AMI. 
[14] In the present study, collateral </p>

<p>circulation to the occluded LAD is found by angiography 
whithin the first 12 h of AMI onset in 41% of patients with 
anterior AMI. The percent of the patients with collateral 
circulation in the first six hours of AMI was 24%. The 
pressure-derived fractional collateral flow was measured in 
70 patients with AMI onset in the first 12 h. It was found 
that the left ventricular recovery after reperfused AMI was 
primarily determined by pressure-derived fractional collateral 
flow and was less dependent on time to reperfusion in 
patients with collaterals. 
[15] Time to reperfusion is important </p>

<p>for survival with thrombolytic therapy. 
[16,17] Improverment </p>

<p>in ejection fraction was substantial with reperfusion at less 
than two hours but was relatively independent of time to 
reperfusion after two hours. The mortality was independent 
of time to reperfusion. 
[18] It has been suggested that some </p>

<p>reasons why time to treatment may be less important with 
primary PCI than thrombolytic therapy might be possible. 
First, TIMI 2 to 3 flow is achieved less often with increasing 
time to treatment with thrombolytic therapy. 
[19] In contrast, </p>

<p>TIMI 3 flow was achieved in a high percentage of patients 
regardless of time to treatment with primary PCI. Second, in 
patients treated with thrombolytic therapy, mortality rates 
from myocarrdial rupture increased progressively with 
increasing time to treatment.In contrast, mortality rates due 
to myocardial rupture after primary PCI are very low. </p>

<p>[20] </p>

<p>Third, the incidence of intracranial hemorrhage after 
thrombolytic therapy increased with increasing time to 
treatment. 
[17] The occurrence of intracranial hemorrhage </p>

<p>with primary PCI is rare. 
[21] In our study, collateral circulation </p>

<p>was an dependent factor for the composite endpoint, and the </p>

<p>Journal of Geriatric Cardiology | jgc@mail.sciencep.com; http://www.jgc301.com </p>

<p>Wang B et al. Primary PCI in Anterior AMI </p>



<p>symptom to treatment time was not an dependent factor. It 
was suggested that the time to reperfusion was a crucial 
factor for the prognosis of patient with AMI in the first 
hours onset (possible two hours or six hours or other) and 
the benefit of reperfusion would decrease after the first 
hours AMI onset. The presence of collateral circulation at 
this time point may improve myocardial salvage 
[22-23] and </p>

<p>prevent ventricular remodeling, 
[24] thereby improving </p>

<p>prognosis independent of coronary reperfusion therapy. </p>

<p>[25] </p>

<p>In the present study, the patients with collateral coronary 
circulation had better prognosis than it in the patient without 
collateral coronary circulation when the patients with AMI 
accepted primary PCI in the first six hours of syndrome to 
treatment time. The patients with AMI with collateral 
coronary circulation accepted primary PCI between 6 h and 
12 h of syndrome to treatment time had a better prognosis 
tendency compared with the patients without collateral 
coronary circulation. The patients with collateral coronary 
circulation accepting primary PCI between 6 h and 12 h of 
syndrome to treatment time had better prognosis than it in 
the patients without collateral coronary circulation accepting 
primary PCI in the first 6 h of syndrome to treatment time. 
These results suggest that finding a way to gaining the 
collateral coronary circulation earlier might give a better 
prognosis to the patients with AMI. It has been found that 
basic fibroblast growth factor enhances collateral development, 
reduces infarct size and improves cardiac function. </p>

<p>[26] </p>

<p>Some potential limitations need to be addressed. First, 
the sum of sample is not a larger number. Second, some 
data, such as peak creatine kinase myocardial band and left 
ventricular ejection fraction at one year were not collected 
completely. So, the infarction area and the function of left 
ventricle were not evaluated accurately. </p>



<p>http://www.jgc301.com; jgc@mail.sciencep.com | Journal of Geriatric Cardiology </p>



<p>Wang B et al. Primary PCI in Anterior AMI </p>



<p>Journal of Geriatric Cardiology | jgc@mail.sciencep.com; http://www.jgc301.com </p>

</text></tei>